<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041102230646|7062942" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="83525" pageid="83525" ns="0" title="Matriarchy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-02T23:34:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''matriarchy''' is a tradition (and by extension a form of [[government]]) in which community power lies with the eldest [[mother]] of a community. The word matriarchy derives from the [[latin]] words ''matri'' meaning ''mother'' and ''arch'' meaning ''chief'' or prime. It refers to the ancient tradition of ''mother dominated'' societies and clans, though it is often confused as meaning ''woman dominated''. 

Matriarchy is distinct from [[matrilineality]], where children are identified in terms of their mother rather than their father, and extended families and tribal alliances form along female blood-lines. Matriarchy is sometimes extended to refer to "government by women", although this is more technically termed ''gynocracy''.

== Extremely rare ==

In the present-day world, traditional matriarchal societies are rare, if not nonexistent. Anthropologist Donald Brown's list of "human universals" (i.e. features shared by all current human societies) includes [[men]] being the "dominant element" in public political affairs (Brown 1991, p. 137). [[Feminist]] Joan Bamberger notes that the historical record contains no reliable evidence of any society in which women dominated (Bamberger 1974), though there are many known matrilineal societies. The [[Trobriand Islands]] were considered a matriarchy by anthropologist [[Bronislaw Malinowski]]; the dispute this view has engendered is discussed at that entry.  On the other hand, anthropologist [[Peggy Reeves Sanday]] favors redefining and reintroducing the word matriarchy, especially in reference to modern, matrilineal societies like the [[Minangkabau]].

=== Indonesia ===

The Islamic Minangkabau of West Sumatra number about four million and are considered the largest and most stable matrilineal society in the modern world.  Sanday argues that this society is a modern matriarchy defined not in polar opposition to patriarchy, but on in its own unique terms.

=== Japan ===

Peter N. Stearns and other historians have speculated as to whether or not agricultural [[Japan]] was a matriarchy prior to contact with patriarchal [[China]]. (Stearns 2000, p. 51).

=== Siberia ===

Matrilineal families ([[Yakut language|Yak.]] ''ye-usa'') have existed amongst [[Yakuts]] until modern time, where the female acted as the family head, living separately with her children and cattle. However, several such matrilineal units made up one patrilineal [[polygamic]] family (Yak. ''aga-usa''), thus not a pure matrilineality.

=== Nair society ===
The traditional nair community in [[South India]] is matriarchal by system. A nair matriarchal family is called as a Tarawad or Marumakkathayam family. A traditional nair Tarwad consists of a mother and her children living together with their mother's brother or maternal uncle who is called as ''Karanavan''. In a Nair family, amongst all the women at home, the eldest mother would become the head of the family. 

=== Jewish matriarchy ===

In ancient [[rabbi|rabbinical]] tradition a person has to be born of a jewish mother in order to be jewish. According to tradition, the [[jew]]ish ''nation'' is inherited through the mother while the ''tribe'' is inherited through the father. Through centuries of occidental contact, the jewish community is more patriarchal in nature, though firmly matriarchal in conception.

== Archaeological hypotheses ==

Whether matriarchal societies might have existed at some time in the distant past is controversial. The controversy began in reaction to the book by [[Johann Jakob Bachofen]] ''Mother Right: An Investigation of the Religious and Juridical Character of Matriarchy in the Ancient World'' in 1861. Several generations of ethnologists were inspired by his pseudo-evolutionary theory of archaic matriarchy. Following him and [[Jane Ellen Harrison]], several generations of scholars, arguing usually from myths or oral traditions and neolithic female cult-figures, suggested that many ancient societies were matriarchal, or even that there existed a wide-ranging matriarchal society prior to the ancient cultures of which we are aware (see for example ''[[The White Goddess]]'' by [[Robert Graves]]). 

More recent archaeologists like [[Marija Gimbutas]], arguing for a widespread matriarchal culture in pre-Indo-European Old Europe of the Neolithic, have made missteps while attempting to overcome skepticism in what has been until recently an overwhelmingly masculine field. 

== Matriarchies in mythology ==

One area where written myths are available from an early period is the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean culture-zone]], where the [[Minoan]] [[Great Goddess]] was worshipped in a society where women and men were apparently equals. Modern self-described "[[Goddess]] women" are too quick to assume that any culture that worships a [[Mother Goddess]] must be a matriarchy, but there are traces, under the insistently patriarchal Olympian mythology of classical Greece, of earlier matrilineal systems. See the entries for [[Alcimede]] or for [[Hyas]] for examples.  

Another famous legendary matriarchy (and gynarchy) on the edges of the Greek cultural horizon was [[Amazons|Amazon]] society, which took shape in the imaginations of classical Greeks, based on reports of [[Scythia]]n female status and even female warriors.  Some professional historians, however, claim that the "evidence" in the form of myths or oral traditions is too murky to conclude anything from.  About Amazons, [[Michael Grant]] notes that these female warriors were said to live at the boundaries of the world to which Greeks had travelled, making them kin to marvellous beings or [[monster]]s supposed to dwell in distant lands, like the [[Blemmyes]] or [[Cynocephali]].  Some people use this lack of solid evidence as a basis for believing that there has never been a matriarchal society.  Critics point out that this type of argument is illogical, and appeals to the fallacy of [[negative proof]].  

Regardless of actual historical fact, many cultures have myths about a time when women were dominant. Bamberger (1974) examines several of these myths from South American cultures, and concludes that, by portraying the women from this period as evil, they often serve to keep modern-day women under control.

Historian [[Ronald Hutton]] has argued that there is no necessary correlation between the worship of female [[deity|deities]] and relative levels of social or legal egalitarianism between the sexes.  He has pointed out that within European history, in [[seventeenth century]] [[Spain]] there were many religious institutions staffed exclusively by women.  A female quasi-deity was a conspicuous part of public religious [[veneration]], and [[idolatry|cult images]] of female supernatural beings were frequently encountered.  Spain can be compared to the seventeenth century [[Netherlands]], where the worship of female quasi-deities was emphatically rejected and female [[clergy]] did not exist.  Yet, the social and legal status of women was much higher in the Netherlands than in Spain during this period.  In the Netherlands, women were freer to move about unwatched, and could own businesses of their own and separate property.  In Spain, their public roles, and their rights under both law and unwritten custom, were sharply circumscribed.

== Origins of the belief ==

Belief in a matriarchy, and its replacement by "[[patriarchy]]"  can be linked to the historical "inevitabilities" which the [[nineteenth century]]'s concept of [[progress]] through [[cultural evolution]] introduced into [[anthropology]].  [[Friedrich Engels]], among others, formed the curious and rather [[racism|racist]] notion that some primitive peoples did not grasp the link between [[sexual intercourse]] and [[pregnancy]].  They therefore had no clear notion of [[paternity]], according to this hypothesis; women produced children mysteriously, without necessary links to the man or men they had sex with.  When men discovered paternity, according to the hypothesis, they acted to claim power to monopolize women and claim children as their own offspring.  The move from primitive matriarchy to patriarchy was a step forward for human knowledge.   

This belief system was the result of errors in early [[ethnography]], which in return was the result of unsophisticated methods of [[field work]].  When strangers arrive and start asking where babies come from, the urge to respond [[imagination|imaginatively]] is hard to resist, as [[Margaret Mead]] might have discovered in Samoa.  In fact, while prior to [[genetics]] there have been many different explanations of the ''mechanics'' of pregnancy and the relative contributions of either sex, no human group, however primitive, is unaware of the link between intercourse and pregnancy. The fact that each child has one unique father has come more recently, however; Greek and Roman writers thought that the seed of two men might both contribute to the character of the child.  By the time these mistakes were corrected in anthropology, however, the idea that a matriarchy had once existed had been picked up on in [[comparative religion]] and [[archaeology]], and was used as the basis of new hypotheses that were unrelated to the postulated ignorance of primitive people about paternity. 

In the late nineteenth century, belief in primitive matriarchies was also allied with [[Max Müller]]'s hypothesis that an ethnically distinct [[Aryan race]] had invaded and displaced or dominated earlier populations in prehistoric Europe.  Their conquests, according to M&amp;uuml;ller, were responsible for the spread of the [[Indo-European languages]]; they would have also replaced an earlier language and culture in the invaded areas where Indo-European languages are now spoken.  The [[Aryan invasion theory]] is no longer universally accepted in [[India]].  The corresponding hypothesis for Europe is also controversial; few scholars other than Marija Gimbutas have advocated the strongest form of the hypothesis, that of military conquest and forced cultural displacement, in recent decades.  

Matriarchy is also distinct from [[matrilocality]].

== Matriarchies in literature ==

The turn of the century mythology about a peaceful matriarchal civilisation being put to the torch by patriarchal, nomadic barbarian invaders has lived on as a powerful literary [[trope]] long after archaeologists and anthropologists concluded that it went far beyond what the evidence allowed.  The [[Nazism|Nazi]] ideology of a [[master race]] of Aryan conquerors was based in part on M&amp;uuml;ller's hypothesis about conquering Aryans being the founders of the European "race."

More recent uses of the theme share essentially the same narrative, but root for the vanquished matriarchy.  Goddess worship is one motif referred to by [[James Joyce]] in his novels such as ''[[Ulysses (novel)|Ulysses]]'' and ''[[Finnegans Wake]]''.  In addition to Robert Graves, poets such as [[T. S. Eliot]] and [[Ezra Pound]] made use of the theme; of course, when these writers were writing, the narrative of Aryan conquest commanded more scholarly respect than it did today.  

[[Mary Renault]]'s [[historical novel]]s about [[Greek mythology]] and history such as ''The King Must Die'' combine motifs of political conflict between goddess and god worshippers with ''[[The Golden Bough]]'s'' hypothesis about [[dying and reviving god]]s.  The patriarchal conquest of matriarchy motif is found in literally dozens of fantasy novels, from [[Marion Zimmer Bradley]]'s historical revisions of [[Matter of Britain|Arthurian romance]] and the [[Trojan War]]; as well as in works of pure [[fantasy]] such as [[Guy Gavriel Kay]]'s ''[[A Song for Arbonne]]''.  These literary treatments ensure that the Aryan myth lives on long after it has been rejected in science and politics.

==See also==
* [[Patriarch]]
* [[Patriarchy]]
* [[Patriarchs (Bible)]]
* [[Matriarchs (Bible)]]

== References ==
* Bamberger, Joan. (1974). '"The Myth of Matriarchy: Why Men Rule in Primitive Society," in ''Women, Culture, and Society'', edited by Michelle Zimbalist Rosaldo and Louise Lamphere, pp. 263-280. Stanford, California: Stanford University Press.
* Brown, Robert. (1991). ''Human Universals''. Philadelphia: Temple University Press
* [[Marie Antoinette Czaplicka|Czaplicka, Marie Antoinette]]. (1914).  ''Aboriginal Siberia, a study in social anthropology''.  Oxford.  Clarendon press.
*[[Cynthia Eller|Eller, Cynthia]] (2001). ''The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory: Why an Invented Past Won't Give Women a Future''.  ISBN 0807067938  
*[[Marija Gimbutas|Gimbutas, Marija]] (1991). "The Language of the Goddess".
*[[Steven Goldberg|Goldberg, Steven]] (1993) ''Why Men Rule: A Theory of Male Dominance'', rev. ed. ISBN 0812692373 
*[[Ronald Hutton|Hutton, Ronald]] (1993). ''The Pagan Religions of the Ancient British Isles'' ISBN 0631189467 
*[[Kenneth Lapatin|Lapatin, Kenneth]] (2002). ''Mysteries of the Snake Goddess: Art, Desire, and the Forging of History''.  ISBN 0306813289
* [[Peggy Reeves Sanday|Sanday, Peggy Reeves]].  (2004). ''Woman at the Center: Life in a Modern Matriarchy''.  Cornell University Press. ISBN 0801489067
* [http://culturalstudies.gmu.edu/faculty/faculty_bios/stearns.html Stearns, Peter N]. (2000). ''Gender in World History''. New York Routledge. ISBN 0415223105

== External Links ==
*[http://www.uiowa.edu/~anthro/webcourse/lost/goddess.html "The archaeology of the Goddess"]: a balanced skeptical assessment
*[http://www.newscientist.com/news/news.jsp?id=ns99994220 ''Cattle ownership makes it a man's world''] New Scientist (1. October 2003): A new study claims to demonstrate that early female-dominated societies lost their power to men when they started herding cattle.
*[http://www.debunker.com/patriarchy.html The Domain of Patriarchy]: [[Robert Sheaffer]]'s sceptical site discusses matriarchies, Goddess mythology, and claims of non-patriarchal societies.

[[de:Matriarchat]] [[pl:Matriarchat]]
[[Category:Anthropology]][[Category:Feminism]][[Category:Sociology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>