<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071110121135|170533058" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="83525" pageid="83525" ns="0" title="Matriarchy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-13T03:34:17Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Matriarchy''' is a term, which is applied  to [[:wikt:gynocentric|gynocentric]] form of [[society]], in which the leading role is with the [[female]] and especially with the [[mother]]s of a community. &lt;ref&gt;'Matriarchy', ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Some authors consider it as hypothetical form of human society.  There exist many matriarchal animal societies including [[bees]], [[elephants]], and [[killer whales]]. The word ''matriarchy'' is coined as the  opposite of ''[[Patriarchy]]'', from [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] ''{{lang|grc-Latn|[[:wikt:μήτηρ|matēr]]}}'' "mother" and ''{{lang|grc-Latn|[[:wikt:-archy|archein]]}}''  "to rule". When related to humans, the term literally meaning "wife's rule", '''''[[:wikt:gynecocracy|gynecocracy]]''''' ([[:wikt:el:γυναικοκρατία|γυναικοκρατία]]), is sometimes used synonymously.

Primarily "matriarchy" is a family rule. The main aspect of matriarchy is economical and communal property of the family. The term "matri-archy" expresses its tough tie with family rule: its root is "matri" ("mother"). The main semantic load of the term is not only "power of female" but also "power of female as a mother". Woman's power is given to a female because of her motherhood and her maternal status in community.

Though some modern anthropologists and sociologists assert that there are no known examples of human matriarchies from any point in history,&lt;ref&gt;Steven Goldberg, ''[[The Inevitability of Patriarchy]]'', (William Morrow &amp; Company, 1973).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Joan Bamberger,'The Myth of Matriarchy: Why Men Rule in Primitive Society', in M Rosaldo and L Lamphere, ''Women, Culture, and Society'', (Stanford, California: Stanford University Press, 1974), pp. 263-280.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robert Brown, ''Human Universals'', (Philadelphia: Temple University Press), 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Steven Goldberg, ''[[Why Men Rule]]'', (Chicago, Illinois: Open Court Publishing Company, 1993).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cynthia Eller, ''[[The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory]]: Why an Invented Past Won't Give Women a Future'', [http://www.amazon.com/dp/080706792X (Boston: Beacon Press, 2001).]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Marks, 'Essay 8: Primate Behavior', in ''The Un-Textbook of Biological Anthropology'', (Unpublished, 2007), p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; there is no consensus about this question. Encyclopædia Britannica, siding with the anthropologists and sociologists who made the aforementioned assertion, lists matriarchy as a "[[Hypotheticals|hypothetical]] social system&lt;ref&gt;'Matriarchy' ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;(best exemplified by present-day [[Jamaica|Jamaica]])", yet some examples of matrifocal societies are listed in "Existing matrifocal societies" section of this article. The Britannica article goes on to note, "The view of matriarchy as constituting a stage of cultural development is now generally discredited. Furthermore, the consensus among modern anthropologists and sociologists is that a strictly matriarchal society never existed."&lt;ref&gt;'Matriarchy', ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; For more information see the appendix [[Patriarchy#Appendix|Patriarchies in dispute]]. 

There is also dispute about matrifocality (see Matriarchy vs. matrifocality). Matriarchy is defined by some as distinct from [[matrilocality]], which some [[anthropologists]] use to describe societies where maternal authority is prominent in domestic relations, owing to the husband joining the wife's family, rather than the wife moving to the husband's village or tribe, such that she continues to be in possession of the family property, while the husband serves as a consort. Socially, the wife is supported by her extended family, and husbands tend to be more isolated.

Matriarchy is also distinct from [[matrilineality]]. While there are existing matrilinear and matrilocal societies, such as those of the [[Minangkabau]] or [[Mosuo]], no matriarchal societies are known, and the historical reality is a disputed topic. Strongly matrilocal societies are also known as '''matrifocal''', and there is some controversy concerning the terminological delineation of matrifocality from "actual" matriarchy.

==Matriarchal animals (non-human)==  	 
There are many animal societies that are matriarchal, these include: 	 
* [[Ants]]- The head of an ant colony is the queen. The worker ants are all female, including those that fight in war.
* [[Bees]]- The head of the bee colony is the queen.
* [[Bonobos]] 	 
* [[Elephants]] 	 
* [[Killer Whales]] 	 
* [[Spotted Hyena]]s
* [[Bison]]

== History of the concept in relation to humans ==
The notion of prehistoric matriarchy and of its replacement by [[patriarchy]]  can be linked to the historical "inevitabilities" which the [[nineteenth century]]'s concept of progress through [[cultural evolution]] introduced into [[anthropology]].  [[Friedrich Engels]], among others, formed the notion that some primitive peoples did not grasp the link between [[sexual intercourse]] and [[pregnancy]].  They therefore had no clear notion of [[paternity]], according to this [[hypothesis]]; women produced children mysteriously, without necessary links to the man or men they had sex with.  When men discovered paternity, according to the hypothesis, they acted to claim power to monopolize women and claim children as their own offspring.

This belief system was the result of errors in early [[ethnography]], which in return was the result of unsophisticated methods of [[field work]].  When strangers arrive and start asking where babies come from, the urge to respond [[imagination|imaginatively]] is hard to resist, as [[Margaret Mead]] discovered in Samoa.  In fact, while prior to the discovery of [[egg cell]]s and [[genetics]] there have been many different explanations of the ''mechanics'' of pregnancy and the relative contributions of either sex, no human group, however primitive, is unaware of the link between intercourse and pregnancy. The fact that each child has a single father has come more recently, however; Greek and Roman writers thought that the seed of two men might both contribute to the character of the child.  By the time these mistakes were corrected in anthropology, however, the idea that a matriarchy had once existed had been picked up on in [[comparative religion]] and [[archaeology]], and was used as the basis of new hypotheses that were unrelated to the postulated ignorance of primitive people about paternity. 

=== Archaeological hypotheses ===
Whether matriarchal societies might have existed at some time in the distant past is controversial. The controversy began in reaction to the book by [[Johann Jakob Bachofen]] ''Mother Right: An Investigation of the Religious and Juridical Character of Matriarchy in the Ancient World'' in 1861. Several generations of ethnologists were inspired by his pseudo-evolutionary theory of archaic matriarchy. Following him and [[Jane Ellen Harrison]], several generations of scholars, arguing usually from myths or oral traditions and Neolithic female cult-figures, suggested that many ancient societies were matriarchal, or even that there existed a wide-ranging matriarchal society prior to the ancient cultures of which we are aware (see for example ''[[The White Goddess]]'' by [[Robert Graves]]). 

[[Marija Gimbutas]] from the 1950s developed a theory of an "[[Old European culture]]" in [[neolithic Europe]] which had matriarchal traits, replaced by the patriarchal system of the [[Proto-Indo-Europeans]] with the spread of [[Indo-European languages]] from the [[Bronze Age]]. 

These ideas were taken up by [[second-wave feminism]] and, conflated with speculations of [[Margaret Murray]] and [[Robert Graves]] on "[[witchcraft]]", by the [[Goddess movement]] ([[feminist Wicca]]) from the 1970s ([[Elizabeth Gould Davis]], [[Riane Eisler]], [[Merlin Stone]]). From the 1970s also, the concept of a matriarchal "golden age" in the Neolithic has been denounced as feminist wishful thinking (''[[The Inevitability of Patriarchy]]'', ''[[Why Men Rule]]''), more recently by  Philip G. Davis (''Goddess Unmasked'', 1998) and Cynthia Eller, professor at Montclair State University (''[[The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory]]'', 2000).  According to  Eller,  Gimbutas had a large part in constructing a "myth of historical matriarchy" by examining Eastern Europe cultures that, by and large, never really bore any resemblance in character to the alleged universal matriarchality of Gimbutas and Graves. She demonstrates that in "actually documented primitive societies" paternity is never ignored and that the sacred status of feminine goddesses does not automatically increase female social status, affirming that utopian matriachy is simply an inversion of antifeminism.

While the feminist scenarios of neolithic matriarchy have been discredited, and are de-emphasized in [[third-wave feminism]], at least in their extreme manifestations in authors like Gould Davis (who could go as far as claiming "the first males were mutants, freaks produced by some damage to the genes") or Stone (who concluded that [[Levites|Hebrew priests]] must have been Indo-Europeans, not Semites, because they were so patriarchal) the original evidence recognized by Gimbutas of neolithic society being more [[egalitarian]] than the Bronze Age Indo-European and Semitic patriarchies remains valid. Del Giorgio in ''The Oldest Europeans'' (2006) insists in on a matrifocal, matrilocal, matrilineal [[Paleolithic]] society.

==Matriarchy versus matrifocality==

Due to a lack of any clear and consistent definition of the word 'matriarchy' the term 'matrifocality' has began to be preferred by several anthroplogists to refer to societies with focus on women and especially mothers though not necessarily dominated by women or mothers. &lt;ref name="smith"&gt;Smith R.T. ([[2002]]) Matrifocality, in International encyclopedia of the social and behavioral sciences (eds) Smelser &amp; Baltes, vol 14, pp 9416.&lt;/ref&gt; Anthropologist R. L. Smith (2002) refers to 'matrifocality' as the kinship structure of a social system where the mother assumes structural prominence. &lt;ref name="smith"&gt;Smith R.T. ([[2002]]) Matrifocality, in International encyclopedia of the social and behavioral sciences (eds) Smelser &amp; Baltes, vol 14, pp 9416.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Nair]] community in [[Kerala]] in [[South India]] is a prime example of matrifocality.This can be attributed to the fact that the community  being warriors by profession were bound to lose male members at a youth leading to a situation where the females took up the role of running the family.

The Wemale culture of western [[Seram]], studied by A.E. Jensen during the [[Frobenius Institute]] expedition of 1938, is often indicated as an example of matriarchy. See: [[Karl Kerenyi]] noted in passing (introduction to ''Eleusis : Archetypal Image of Mother and Daughter'' 1967, p. xxxii). On the other hand, anthropologist Donald Brown's list of "human universals" (i.e. features shared by all current human societies) includes [[men]] being the "dominant element" in public political affairs (Brown 1991, p. 137). He refers the opinion of mainstream [[anthropology]]. [[Feminist]] Joan Bamberger argues that the historical record contains no reliable evidence of any society in which women dominated (Bamberger 1974), though there are many known [[matrilineal]] societies. The [[Trobriand Islands]] were considered a matriarchy by anthropologist [[Bronisław Malinowski]], however, Malinowski defined matriarchy as the rule of a the family by the wife's male relatives, such as her brothers, rather than literal patriarchy, the rule of the family by its father; the dispute this view has engendered is discussed at that entry. Peter N. Stearns and other historians have speculated as to whether or not agricultural [[Japan]] was a matriarchy prior to contact with patriarchal [[China]]. (Stearns 2000, p. 51). On the other hand, anthropologist Peggy Reeves Sanday favors redefining and reintroducing the word matriarchy, especially in reference to modern, matrilineal societies like the [[Minangkabau]]. This group lives in [[West Sumatra]] and numbers about four million; it is considered the largest and most stable matrilineal society in the modern world. Sanday argues that this society is a modern matriarchy defined not in polar opposition to patriarchy, but on unique terms. A clear and consistent definition has been given by Heide Goettner-Abendroth, who did cross-cultural research on all of the still existing matriarchal societies of today (in her major work on matriarchy). Her viewpoint is close to that of Sanday. One of her examples are the [[Mosuo]] people of Southwestern China. Furthermore, the [[Minicoy island]]ers are also considered to be one of the living matrilineal societies today. Regardless, the existence of any true matriarchal societies (as opposed to matrilineal or matrifocal societies) remains controversial among scholars. 

Some traditional matrifocal societies have been presented by scholars and indigenous speakers  at two [http://www.hagia.de/eng/ World Congresses on Matriarchal Studies]. The first one was held in 2003 in Luxembourg, Europe; it was sponsored by the Minister for Women's Affairs of Luxembourg, [[Marie-Josée Jacobs]], and organized and guided by Heide Goettner-Abendroth. The second one took place in 2005 in San Marcos, Texas/USA, it was sponsored by Genevieve Vaughan and again led by Heide Goettner-Abendroth. 

=== Existing matrifocal societies ===
*The traditional [[Nair]] community in Kerala, [[South India]] is matrifocal by their definition of 'matrifocality'. (Nowadays this system is rarely practiced.  The members of the Nair community now live in nuclear families). A traditional Nair matrifocal family is called a Tarawad or Marumakkathayam family. A traditional Nair Tarawad consists of a mother and her children living together with their mother's surviving eldest brother or eldest surviving maternal uncle who is called ''Karanavan''. The Karnavan exercises full powers over the affairs of the family. Until recently, the main significance of this system was that the heirs to the property were the women in the family and the men folk were only allowed to enjoy the benefits during their lifetime. The naming system of the Nair community had the prefix of their mother's 'family name' and they adopted the maternal uncle’s surname. The Marumakkathayam system of Kerala was a legal right which determined inheritance through the female line. Thus if a family property was to be partitioned all female members would receive one share and all male members who were direct offspring of the family name would receive one share. Thus a brother might receive only one share while his sister and her children (and grandchildren by her daughters) would each receive a share. This right was removed by the Kerala Joint [[Hindu]] Family System (Abolition) Act, 1975.
* [[Mosuo]] people - Lugu Lake, bordering between [[Yunnan]] &amp; [[Sichuan|Sichuan province]], [[China]].
* The people of [[Western Sahara]] (the former [[Spanish Sahara]]), occupied by [[Morocco]] retain semi-matriarchal customs. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3227997.stm]. See also [[Polisario Front]].
* The people of the [[Bolama]] archipelago in [[Guinea-Bissau]][http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20070202/ap_on_re_af/guinea_bissau_ladies__choice].
* Guajiro tribes - inhabiting the [[Guajira Department]] in [[Colombia]] and the adjacent region in the [[Caribbean]] coast in [[Venezuela]], [[South America]]. Children are raised not by their father but by their mother's brother ([[avunculism]]).

== The meaning of the term in the works of classics ==

Matriarchy was discovered by J. Bachofen ("Das Mutterrecht") and was deeply investigated by [[Lewis H. Morgan|Lewis H. Morgan, LL. D]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/morgan-lewis/ancient-society/ancient-society.zip L. Morgan, "Ancient Society Or Researches in the Lines of Human Progress from Savagery through Barbarism to Civilization"]&lt;/ref&gt;. Many researchers studied the phenomenon of matriarchy afterwards, but the basis was laid by the classics of sociology. In their works Bachofen and Morgan used such terms and expressions: mother-right, female rule, gyneocracy, female authority. 
All these terms meant the same: the rule of female (mother, wife). 

The next fragments from Morgan's "Ancient Society" will explain the usage of the terms:

"In a work of vast research, Bachofen has collected and discussed the evidence of female authority (mother-right) and of female rule (gyneocracy)."

"Common lands and joint tillage would lead to joint-tenement houses and communism in living; so that gyneocracy seems to require for its creation, descent in the female line. Women thus entrenched in large households, supplied from common stores, in which their own gens so largely predominated in numbers, would produce the phenomena of mother right and gyneocracy, which Bachofen has detected and traced with the aid of fragments of history and of tradition.".

Though Bachofen and Morgan confined the "mother right" inside households, it was the basis of female influence upon the whole society. The classics never thought that gyneocracy could mean "female government" in polity. They were aware of the fact that sexual structure of government had no any relation to domestic rule and to roles of both sexes.

== Matriarchies in mythology ==
One area where written myths are available from an early period is the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean culture-zone]], where the [[Minoan civilization|Minoan]] [[Great Goddess]] was worshipped in a society where women and men were allegedly equals.
 
A famous legendary gynecocracy on the edges of the Greek cultural horizon was [[Amazons|Amazon]] society, which took shape in the imaginations of classical Greeks, based on reports of [[Scythia]]n and [[Sarmatian]] female status and even female warriors. 

Bamberger (1974) examines several matriarchal myths from South American cultures, and concludes that, by portraying the women from this period as evil, they often serve to keep women under control.

Historian [[Ronald Hutton]] has argued that there is no necessary correlation between the worship of [[goddess|female deities]] and relative levels of social or legal egalitarianism between the sexes, ostensibly in the  [[Ancient Greek religion|Greek]] and [[Ancient Roman religion|Roman]] religion, where goddesses play an important role, but Hutton  has also pointed out that in more recent European history, in [[Habsburg Spain|17th century Spain]], there were many religious institutions staffed exclusively by women.

== In popular culture ==
The idea of peaceful matriarchal civilizations being put to the torch by [[patriarchal]], nomadic barbarian invaders has lived on as a powerful literary [[Trope (literature)|trope]]. The [[Nazism|Nazi]] ideology of a [[master race]] of [[Aryan]] patriarchal conquerors was based in part on Müller's hypothesis about conquering Aryans being the founders of the European race.

More recent uses of the theme share essentially the same narrative.
[[Mary Renault]]'s [[historical novel]]s about [[Greek mythology]] and history such as ''The King Must Die'' combine motifs of political conflict between goddess and god worshippers with ''[[The Golden Bough]]'s'' hypothesis about [[dying and reviving god]]s.  The patriarchal conquest of matriarchy motif is found in literally dozens of fantasy novels, from [[Marion Zimmer Bradley]]'s historical revisions of [[Matter of Britain|Arthurian romance]] and the [[Trojan War]] to works of pure [[fantasy]] such as [[Guy Gavriel Kay]]'s ''[[A Song for Arbonne]]''. Gender roles and the conflict of patriarch vs. matriarchy is a major theme in the ''[[The Wheel of Time|Wheel of Time]]'' books by [[Robert Jordan]] (fantasy).

In the ''[[StarCraft]]'' universe, the Dark Templar Tribes of Shakuras are ruled over by Matriarch Raszagal. Near the end of [[StarCraft: Brood War]], she is killed, and names her [[Prelate]], Zeratul (a male), the new leader of the Dark Templar, thus ending the Dark Templar matriarchy.

In the expanded universe of [[Star Wars]], the women of Dathomir are portrayed as the ruling sex. Another matriarchy is the Hapan Consortium, a cluster of 63 planets, that are all ruled by the Queen Mother of Hapes.

In the fantasy world of [[Forgotten Realms]], the evil [[Drow]] race is a ''highly'' matriarchial society. The females rule drow societies—a gynocracy; males are merely servants and are regarded as pets. The same goes for the aptly-named ''gynocracy of Telchos'' in the [[Lone Wolf]] setting.

The [[webcomic]] [[Sinfest]] sometimes parodies [[The Matrix]] as "The Matriarchy."

''[[Dreamfall]]'', a game by Funcom, features a Goddessiworshipping Matriarchal people, the Azadi. Men are described as having less freedom than women, but are in no way regarded as pets. The Azadi, though very religious with a very strict code of honor, have taken to conquering other races.  Though their intentions are good, their "the cause justifies the means" attitude and their discrimination against Magicals make them responsible for many horrible crimes, as well as good deeds.

''[[The Wicker Man (2006 film)|The Wicker Man]]'', starring Nicolas Cage, takes place within a fictional matriarchy in the state of [[Washington]].  The society, Summersisle, is modeled after honeybee culture and behavior.

In the [[Warcraft Universe]], the [[Night Elves]] lived in a highly matriarchial society, due to the fact that almost all men became [[Druid (World of Warcraft)#Druid|druids]] and spent large amounts of their time in meditative slumber, leaving the women to protect them and serve their goddess. This has changed in the recent game [[World of Warcraft]], with gender roles being abolished due to a dip in population.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
* Bamberger, Joan. (1974). '"The Myth of Matriarchy: Why Men Rule in Primitive Society," in ''Women, Culture, and Society'', edited by Michelle Zimbalist Rosaldo and Louise Lamphere, pp. 263-280. Stanford, California: Stanford University Press.
* Brown, Donald. (1991). ''Human Universals''. Philadelphia: Temple University Press
* [[Marie Antoinette Czaplicka|Czaplicka, Marie Antoinette]]. (1914).  ''Aboriginal Siberia, a study in social anthropology''.  Oxford.  Clarendon press.
*Davis, Philip, ''Goddess Unmasked'', Spence Publishing, New York, 1998. ISBN 0-9653208-9-8; review: R. Sheaffer, Skeptical Inquirer (1999)[http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-54600098.html]
* del Giorgio, J.F. (2006). ''[[The Oldest Europeans]]''. A.J.Place, ISBN 978-9806898004.
*[[Cynthia Eller|Eller, Cynthia]] (2001). [[The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory|The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory: Why an Invented Past Won't Give Women a Future]].  ISBN 0-8070-6793-8  
*Finley, M.I. (1962). ''The World of Odysseus''. London. Pelican Books.
*[[Marija Gimbutas|Gimbutas, Marija]] (1991). "The Language of the Goddess".
*[[Steven Goldberg|Goldberg, Steven]] (1993) ''Why Men Rule: A Theory of Male Dominance'', rev. ed. ISBN 0-8126-9237-3 
*[[Ronald Hutton|Hutton, Ronald]] (1993). ''The Pagan Religions of the Ancient British Isles'' ISBN 0-631-18946-7 
*[[Kenneth Lapatin|Lapatin, Kenneth]] (2002). ''Mysteries of the Snake Goddess: Art, Desire, and the Forging of History''.  ISBN 0-306-81328-9
* [[Peggy Reeves Sanday|Sanday, Peggy Reeves]].  (2004). ''Woman at the Center: Life in a Modern Matriarchy''.  Cornell University Press. ISBN 0-8014-8906-7
* [http://culturalstudies.gmu.edu/faculty/faculty_bios/stearns.html Stearns, Peter N]. (2000). ''Gender in World History''. New York Routledge. ISBN 0-415-22310-5
* Smith R.T. ([[2002]]) Matrifocality, in International encyclopedia of the social and behavioral sciences (eds) Smelser &amp; Baltes, vol 14, pp 9416.
* Yoshamya, Mitjel &amp; Yoshamya, Zyelimer (2005). ''Gan-Veyan: Neo-Liburnic glossary, grammar, culture, genom.'' Old-Croatian Archidioms, Monograph I, p. 1 - 1224, Scientific society for Ethnogenesis studies, Zagreb.

==See also==
{{wiktionary}}
*[[Abrahamic religion]]
* [[Moisés Espírito Santo]]
* [[Patriarch]]
* [[Patriarchy]]
* [[Patriarchs (Bible)]]
* [[Matriarchs (Bible)]]
* [[The First Sex#Influence and criticism|The First Sex]]
* [[The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory]]
* [[Zygarchy]]

== External links ==
*[http://www.hagia.de/ www.hagia.de]
*[http://www.goettner-abendroth.de/ www.goettner-abendroth.de]
*[http://www.second-congress-matriarchal-studies.com/ www.second-congress-matriarchal-studies.com]
*[http://www.matriarchy.info Matriarchy.Info]: ancient and contemporary matriarchal societies
*[http://www.newscientist.com/news/news.jsp?id=ns99994220 ''Cattle ownership makes it a man's world''] New Scientist (1. October 2003): A new study claims to demonstrate that early female-dominated societies lost their power to men when they started herding cattle.
*[http://godmotherascending.blogspot.com/ Radical Goddess Thealogy] A blog discussing the Goddess and the ancient Matriarchy
*[http://www.mother-god.com/matriarchy.html The Myth of the Myth of Matriarchy]: Defense of the theory of historical matriarchy
*[http://www.infoshop.org/sf/index.php/Matriarchy_Planet Matriarchy Planet] (Science fiction trope on SF wiki)
*[http://usachi.narod.ru/en/zhen-en.htm/ Matriarchy in USSR] 

{{Forms of leadership}}

[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Sociology]]

&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;

[[ca:Matriarcat]]
[[cs:Matriarchát]]
[[da:Matriarkat]]
[[de:Matriarchat]]
[[es:Matriarcado]]
[[eo:Matriarkeco]]
[[fr:Matriarcat]]
[[hr:Matrijarhat]]
[[it:Matriarcato]]
[[he:מטריארכיה]]
[[lt:Matriarchatas]]
[[mk:Матријархат]]
[[nl:Matriarchaat]]
[[no:Matriarkat]]
[[oc:Matriarcat]]
[[pl:Matriarchat]]
[[pt:Matriarcado]]
[[ru:Матриархат]]
[[sk:Matriarchát]]
[[sr:Матријархат]]
[[sh:Matrijarhat]]
[[fi:Matriarkaatti]]
[[sv:Matriarkat]]
[[tr:Anaerkillik]]
[[zh:母权制社会]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>