<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091114113039|325782255" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="83525" pageid="83525" ns="0" title="Matriarchy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-14T11:37:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:''Note that in feminist literature, "matriarchy" may be used synonymously with [[matrilineality]].''
{{Forms of government}}

'''Matriarchy''' (or '''gynecocracy''') refers to a [[gynecocentric]] form of [[society]], in which the [[leadership|leading role]] is taken by the [[women]] and especially by the [[mother]]s of a community.&lt;ref&gt;'Matriarchy', ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

There are no known societies that are unambiguously matriarchal,&lt;ref&gt;Steven Goldberg, ''[[The Inevitability of Patriarchy]]'', (William Morrow &amp; Company, 1973).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Joan Bamberger,'The Myth of Matriarchy: Why Men Rule in Primitive Society', in M Rosaldo and L Lamphere, ''Women, Culture, and Society'', (Stanford, California: Stanford University Press, 1974), pp. 263-280.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Donald Brown|Donald E. Brown]], [http://www.temple.edu/tempress/titles/864_reg_print.html ''Human Universals''] (Philadelphia: Temple University Press), 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Steven Goldberg, ''[[Why Men Rule]]'', (Chicago, Illinois: Open Court Publishing Company, 1993).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cynthia Eller, ''[[The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory]]: Why an Invented Past Won't Give Women a Future'', [http://www.amazon.com/dp/080706792X (Boston: Beacon Press, 2001).]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Marks, 'Essay 8: Primate Behavior', in ''The Un-Textbook of Biological Anthropology'', (Unpublished, 2007), p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopaedia Britannica'' describes this view as "consensus", listing matriarchy as a  hypothetical social system. 'Matriarchy' ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 2007."&lt;/ref&gt; although there are a number of attested [[matrilinear]], [[matrilocal]] and [[Avunculism|avunculocal]] societies, especially among [[indigenous peoples]] of [[indigenous peoples of Asia|Asia]] and [[Indigenous peoples of Africa|Africa]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.second-congress-matriarchal-studies.com/goettnerabendroth.html Modern Matriarchal Studies Definitions, Scope and Topicality - Heide Goettner-Abendroth]&lt;/ref&gt; such as those of the [[Basques]], [[Minangkabau]], [[Mosuo]], [[Berbers]] or [[Tuareg]]. Strongly matrilocal societies sometimes are referred to as '''matrifocal''', and there is some debate concerning the terminological delineation between matrifocality and matriarchy. Note that even in patriarchical systems of [[male-preference primogeniture]] there may occasionally be [[queen regnant|queens regnant]], as in the case of [[Elizabeth I of England]] or [[Victoria of the United Kingdom]].

In 19th century scholarship, the hypothesis of matriarchy representing an early stage of human development — now mostly lost in prehistory, with the exception of some "[[Primitive culture|primitive]]" societies — enjoyed popularity. The hypothesis survived into the 20th century and was notably advanced in the context of [[feminism]] and especially [[second wave feminism]], but it is mostly discredited today.&lt;ref&gt; "The view of matriarchy as constituting a stage of cultural development now is generally discredited. Furthermore, the consensus among modern anthropologists and sociologists is that a strictly matriarchal society never existed." 'Matriarchy', ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Terminology==
The word ''matriarchy'' is coined as the  opposite of ''[[patriarchy]]'', from [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] ''{{lang|grc-Latn|[[:wikt:μήτηρ|matēr]]}}'' "mother" and ''{{lang|grc-Latn|[[:wikt:-archy|archein]]}}''  "to rule". 
According to the [[OED]], the term "matriarchy" is first attested in 1885, building on an earlier ''matriarch'', formed in analogy to [[patriarch]] already in the early 17th century. By contrast, ''[[:wikt:gynecocracy|gynæcocracy]]''  "rule of women" is in use since the 17th century, building on an actual Greek {{lang|grc|γυναικοκρατία}} found in [[Aristotle]] and [[Plutarch]].[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0058%3Aentry%3D%237148][http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3D%2323035]

The near-synonyms ''matrifocal'' and ''matricentric'' "having a mother as head of the family or household" are of more recent coinage, first used in the mid 20th century. Matriarchy can be understood as the public formation, in which woman occupies ruling position in a family (a primary cell of society). Matriarchy term is nowadays even used to analyze female power - the culture where men have traditionally been raised to protect women being sacrificed in wars and providing for women in the most risky jobs (see gendereconomy.com). 
 
Other 20th century formations are ''gynocentric'', ''gynocentrism'' (simplified by using the reduced prefix ''gyno-'' for  ''gynæco-'') is the "dominant or exclusive focus on women", as opposed to [[androcentrism]].
 
[[Marija Gimbutas]] described her notion of a "woman-centered" society surrounding [[goddess worship]] in [[Neolithic Europe]] by using the term ''matristic'' "exhibiting influence or domination by the mother figure".

A recent school of "[[Matriarchal Studies]]" led by [[Heide Göttner-Abendroth]] is calling for a more inclusive redefinition of the term: Göttner-Abendroth defines "Modern Matriarchal Studies" as the "investigation and presentation of non-patriarchal societies", effectively defining "matriarchy" as "non-patriarchy".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.second-congress-matriarchal-studies.com/goettnerabendroth.html Introduction] to the "Second World Congress on Matriarchal Studies"&lt;/ref&gt;
Similarly,  Peggy Reeves Sanday (2004) favors redefining and reintroducing the word ''matriarchy'', especially in reference to contemporary matrilineal societies such as the [[Minangkabau]]. [[Archeology]] and [[etymology]] have helped modern investigators to prove the existence of matriarchy society still in our days.

According to her, the Island of [[Sumatra]] ([[Indonesia]]) and in [[Mosuo]], the province of [[Sichuan]] (China), live within a matriarchal society.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.myrine.at/Amazons/ ''The Amazons''] &lt;/ref&gt; The prefix ''ama'' is used for Greek female warriors, the [[amazons]], in [[Africa]] and among the mosuo society, having the same meaning: ''In the language of the Moso the word ''Ama'' has the meaning ''Mother''. This is a striking analogy to the name of the warlike ''[[Amazons]]''. Well-fitting to this the Berbers in North Africa, which had been matriarchal in the past, call themselves Amazigh in their own language. Because of this we reason that the very ancient word Ama has the meaning »Mother« in its narrow sense. In the figurative sense it stands for »Matriarchal Culture''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.myrine.at/Amazons/ ''The Amazons'']&lt;/ref&gt;

== History of the concept==
===19th century===

Matriarchy was discovered by Joseph-Francois Lafitau&lt;ref&gt;[http://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/Лафито,_Жозеф-Франсуа]&lt;/ref&gt; (1681-1746), who was first who named it "ginecocratie", then was recognized by J. Bachofen ("Das Mutterrecht") and was deeply investigated by [[Lewis H. Morgan|Lewis H. Morgan, LL. D]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/morgan-lewis/ancient-society/ancient-society.zip L. Morgan, "Ancient Society Or Researches in the Lines of Human Progress from Savagery through Barbarism to Civilization"]&lt;/ref&gt; Many researchers studied the phenomenon of matriarchy afterward, but the basis was laid by the classics of sociology. In their works Bachofen and Morgan used such terms and expressions as mother-right, female rule, gyneocracy, and female authority. All these terms meant the same: the rule by females (mother or wife). 

The following excerpts from Morgan's "Ancient Society" will explain the use of the terms:

"In a work of vast research, Bachofen has collected and discussed the evidence of female authority, mother-right, and of female rule, gyneocracy."

"Common lands and joint tillage would lead to joint-tenant houses and communism in living; so that gyneocracy seems to require for its creation, descent in the female line. Women thus entrenched in large households, supplied from common stores, in which their own gens so largely predominated in numbers, would produce the phenomena of mother right and gyneocracy, which Bachofen has detected and traced with the aid of fragments of history and of tradition."

Although Bachofen and Morgan confined the "mother right" inside households, it was the basis of female influence upon the whole society. The classics never thought that gyneocracy could mean "female government" in polity. They were aware of the fact that sexual structure of government had no relation to domestic rule and to roles of both sexes.
  
[[Friedrich Engels]], among others studying historical groups, formed the notion that some contemporary primitive peoples did not grasp the link between [[sexual intercourse]] and [[pregnancy]].{{Fact|date=October 2008}} Research indicated that sexual intercourse occurred from early ages and pregnancy only occurred much later, seemingly unrelated to the sexual activity.  He proposed that these cultures had no clear notion of [[paternity]], according to this [[hypothesis]]; women produced children mysteriously, without necessary links to the man or men with whom they had sex. When realization of paternity occurred, according to the hypothesis, men acted to claim a power to monopolize women and claim their offspring as possessions and patriarchy began.

The controversy surrounding prehistoric or "primal" matriarchy began in reaction to the book by [[Johann Jakob Bachofen]] ''Mother Right: An Investigation of the Religious and Juridical Character of Matriarchy in the Ancient World'' in 1861. Several generations of ethnologists were inspired by his pseudo-evolutionary theory of archaic matriarchy. Following him and [[Jane Ellen Harrison]], several generations of scholars, usually arguing from known myths or oral traditions and examination of Neolithic female cult-figures, suggested that many ancient societies might have been matriarchal, or even, that there existed a wide-ranging matriarchal society prior to the ancient cultures of which we are aware.

===20th century===

Ethnographer [[Bronislaw Malinowski]] from London School of Economics lived among aborigines of Trobriand Islands (Western Melanesia) and studied their society in 1914-1918. In his book "Argonauts Of The Western Pacific" &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archive.org/stream/argonautsofthewe032976mbp/argonautsofthewe032976mbp_djvu.txt "Argonauts Of The Western Pacific"]&lt;/ref&gt; B. Malinowski pointed at matrilineal construction of islander's societies and at high female position:

"Their system of kinship is matrilineal, and women hold a very good position, and wield great influence." (Chapter I)

"The Trobrianders are matrilineal, that is, in tracing descent and settling inheritance, they follow the maternal line. A child belongs to the clan and village community of its mother, and wealth, as well as social position, arc inherited, not from father to son, but from maternal uncle to nephew." (Chapter II)

"As regards kinship, the main thing to be remembered is that the natives are matrilineal, and that the succession of rank, membership in all the social groups, and the inheritance of possessions descend in the maternal line."  (Chapter II)

Property was succeeded inside the mother-line: "The ownership of trees in the village grove and ownership in garden plots is ceded by the father to his son during the lifetime of the former. At his death, it often has to be returned to the man's rightful heirs, that is, his sister's children."  (Chapter II)

Man had life-long obligation to work for women and their relatives in that gyneocratic society: "They entail a life-long obligation of every man to work for his kinswomen and their families. When a boy begins to garden, he does it for his mother. When his sisters grow up and marry, he works for them. If he has neither mother nor sisters, his nearest female blood relation will claim the proceeds of his labour". (Chapter VI)

Malinowski gave confirmations of Morgan's idea that matriarchy (gyneocracy) was common feature of primitive societies at early stages, and that female rule needed matrilineality for its existence. He also confirmed that matrilineality often goes with promiscuous free-love (that was dicovered by Bachofen). 

Austrian writer [[Bertha Diener]], also known by her American pseudonym as Helen Diner, wrote ''Mothers and Amazons'' (1930) which was the first work to focus on women's cultural history. She is regarded as a classic of feminist matriarchal study.&lt;ref name="Dinner party"&gt;[http://www.brooklynmuseum.org/eascfa/dinner_party/heritage_floor/helen_diner.php Helen Diner ] Who wrote ''Mothers and Amazons'' (1930), entry at the Brooklyn Museum ''Dinner Party'' database of notable women. Accessed March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Her view is that in the past all human societies were matriarchal, then, at some point, most shifted to patriarchal and degenerated.

The controversy was reinforced further by the publication of ''[[The White Goddess]]'' by Robert Graves (1948) and his later analysis of classical Greek mythology and the vestiges of earlier myths that had been rewritten after a profound change in the religion of Greek civilization that occurred within its very early historical times. 

From the 1950s, [[Marija Gimbutas]] developed a theory of an ''[[Old European culture]]'' in [[neolithic Europe]] which had matriarchal traits, replaced by the patriarchal system of the [[Proto-Indo-Europeans]] with the spread of [[Indo-European languages]] beginning in the [[Bronze Age]]. 
 
From the 1970s these ideas were taken up by popular writers of ''[[second-wave feminism]]'' and, expanded with the speculations of [[Margaret Murray]] on ''[[witchcraft]]'', by the [[Goddess movement]], [[feminist Wicca]], as well as work by [[Elizabeth Gould Davis]], [[Riane Eisler]], and [[Merlin Stone]]. 

The concept of a matriarchal ''golden age'' in the Neolithic has been denounced as feminist wishful thinking in ''[[The Inevitability of Patriarchy]]'', ''[[Why Men Rule]]'', more recently by  Philip G. Davis ''Goddess Unmasked'', 1998, and Cynthia Eller, professor at Montclair State University ''[[The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory]]'', 2000.  According to Eller, Gimbutas had a large part in constructing a ''myth of historical matriarchy'' by examining Eastern Europe cultures that she asserts, by and large, never really bore any resemblance in character to the alleged universal matriarchal suggested by Gimbutas and Graves. She asserts that in "actually documented primitive societies" of recent (historical) times, paternity is never ignored and that the sacred status of goddesses does not automatically increase female social status, and believes that this affirms that ''utopian matriarchy'' is simply an inversion of [[antifeminism]]. The ''feminist scenarios'' of Neolithic matriarchy have been called into question and are not emphasized in [[third-wave feminism]].

The original evidence recognized by Gimbutas, however, of Neolithic societies being more [[egalitarian]] than the Bronze Age Indo-European and Semitic patriarchies remains valid. Gimbutas herself has not described these societies as "matriarchal", preferring the term "woman-centered" or "matristic". Del Giorgio in ''The Oldest Europeans'' (2006) insists on a matrifocal, matrilocal, matrilineal [[Paleolithic]] society. [[Kurt Derungs]] is a non-academic author advocating an "anthropology of landscape" based on alleged matriarchal traces in toponymy and folklore. 

Feminist authors adhering to the [[Modern Matriarchal Studies]] school of thought&lt;ref&gt;A first [http://www.hagia.de/eng/ World Congress on Matriarchal Studies] was held in 2003 in Luxembourg, Europe; it was sponsored by the Minister for Women's Affairs of Luxembourg, [[Marie-Josée Jacobs]], and was organized and guided by [[Heide Goettner-Abendroth]]. A second one took place in 2005 in San Marcos, Texas, USA; it was sponsored by Genevieve Vaughan and again led by [[Heide Goettner-Abendroth]].&lt;/ref&gt; consider any non-patriarchic form of society as falling within their field, including all examples of [[matrilineality]], [[matrilocality]] and [[avunculism]], regardless of discussions on the extent of "matrifocality".

In 1996, the [[micronation]] of the [[Other World Kingdom]] (OWK) was formed. The OWK is also a [[BDSM]] resort which rules under a system of both matriarchy and [[absolute monarchy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.owk.cz/philosophy-operation/whoweare/index.php|title=Who We Are|publisher=Other World Kingdom|accessdate=2009-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Comparison with matrifocality==
{{see|List of matrilineal or matrilocal societies}}
Due to a lack of a clear and consistent definition of the word ''matriarchy'' several anthropologists have begun to use the term ''matrifocality.''  ''Matrifocality'' refers to societies in which women, especially mothers, occupy a central position, and the term does necessarily imply domination by women or mothers.&lt;ref name = "smith"/&gt; Anthropologist R. L. Smith (2002) refers to 'matrifocality' as the kinship structure of a social system where the mothers assume structural prominence.&lt;ref name="smith"&gt;Smith R.T. (2002) Matrifocality, in International encyclopedia of the social and behavioral sciences (eds) Smelser &amp; Baltes, vol 14, pp 9416.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Nair]] community in [[Kerala]] in [[South India]] is a prime example of matrifocality. This can be attributed to the fact that the community being warriors by profession, were bound to lose male members at youth, leading to a situation where the females assumed the role of running the family. Some consider the use of the term a [[euphemism]], lacking a parallel to patriarchy, which is not redefined in the same fashion.  

While the existence of numerous [[matrilineal]] or [[avunculism|avuncular]] societies is undisputed, it has been recognized since the 1970s that there are no societies which are matriarchal in the strong sense that some societies are patriarchal. Joan Bamberger in her 1974 ''The Myth of Matriarchy'' argued that the historical record contains no reliable evidence of any society in which women dominated. Anthropologist Donald Brown's list of "[[human cultural universals]]" (i.e. features shared by all current human societies) includes [[men]] being the "dominant element" in public political affairs (Brown 1991, p. 137), which he asserts is the contemporary opinion of mainstream [[anthropology]].

== In mythology ==

A famous legendary gynecocracy related by classical Greek writers was the [[Amazons|Amazon]] society. 
[[Herodotus]] reported that the Sarmatians were descendants of Amazons and Scythians, and that their females observed their ancient maternal customs, "frequently hunting on horseback with their husbands; in war taking the field; and wearing the very same dress as the men". Moreover, said Herodotus, "No girl shall wed till she has killed a man in battle". In the story related by Herodotus, a group of Amazons was blown across the [[Sea of Azov|Maeotian Lake]] (the [[Sea of Azov]]) into [[Scythia]] near the cliff region (today's southeastern [[Crimea]]). After learning the Scythian language, they agreed to marry Scythian men, on the condition that they not be required to follow the customs of Scythian women. According to Herodotus, this band moved toward the northeast, settling beyond the [[Don River (Russia)|Tanais]] ([[Don River (Russia)|Don]]) river, and became the ancestors of the [[Sarmatians|Sauromatians]].  
 
Amazons came to play a role in [[Roman historiography]]. Caesar reminded the Senate of the conquest of large parts of Asia by [[Semiramis]] and the Amazons. Successful Amazon raids against Lycia and Cilicia contrasted with effective resistance by Lydian cavalry against the invaders.&lt;ref&gt;[[Strabo]] 5.504; [[Nicholas Damascenus]].&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Diodorus]] relates the story of Hercules defeating the Amazons at Themiscyre. [[Philostratus]] places the Amazons in the [[Taurus mountains]]. [[Ammianus]] places them east of [[Tanais]], as neighbouring the [[Alans]]. [[Procopius]] places them in the Caucasus.
Although Strabo shows scepticism as to their historicity, the Amazons in general continue to be taken as historical throughout Late Antiquity. Several Church Fathers speak of the Amazons as of a real people. [[Solinus]] embraces the account of [[Plinius]]. Under [[Aurelianus]], captured [[Goths|Gothic]] women were identified as Amazons.&lt;ref&gt;[[Claudianus]].&lt;/ref&gt; The account of [[Justinus]] was influential, and was used as a source by [[Orosius]] who continued to be read during the European Middle Ages. Medieval authors thus continue the tradition of locating the Amazons in the North, [[Adam of Bremen]] placing them at the [[Baltic Sea]] and [[Paulus Diaconus]] in the heart of Germania.&lt;ref&gt;[[F. A. Ukert]], ''Die Amazonen'', Abhandlungen der philosophisch-philologischen Classe der Königlich Bayerischen Akademie der Wissenschaften (1849), 63.&lt;/ref&gt;

Historian [[Ronald Hutton]] has argued that there is no necessary correlation between the worship of [[goddess|female deities]] and relative levels of social or legal egalitarianism, noting the late classical [[Hellenistic religion|Greek]] and [[Ancient Roman religion|Roman]] religions, where goddesses played an important role. The changes from the earlier mythology are not considered in her analysis, however, and the late classical myths were dominated by male deities.  Hutton also has pointed out that in more recent European history, in [[Habsburg Spain|17th century Spain]], there were many religious institutions staffed exclusively by women.

In classical Greek mythology,  [[Zeus]] is said to have swallowed his pregnant wife, the goddess [[Metis (mythology)|Metis]], who was carrying their daughter, [[Athene]]. The mother and child created havoc inside Zeus. He had swallowed the goddess because a prophecy had been foretold that the child of Metis would become greater than her father. After suffering great discomfort and terrible headaches, Hephaestus split Zeus's head, allowing Athene, in full battle armour, to burst forth from his forehead, thereafter being described as "being 'born' of Zeus." The prophecy was later proven true, as Athene's worship, as goddess of both wisdom and the strategic aspect of battle, surpassed that of Zeus, king of Olympus.
[[Robert Graves]] suggested that this myth displaced earlier myths in which Athene and her mother existed in established religious beliefs that had to change when a major cultural change introduced a patriarchy to replace a matriarchy, interpreting it symbolically.

Bamberger (1974) examines several matriarchal myths from South American cultures and concludes that portraying the women from this matriarchal period as evil often serves to restrain contemporary women.{{Clarifyme|date=February 2009}}

== In popular culture ==
{{see|Amazons in popular culture}}
[[Mary Renault]]'s [[historical novel]]s about [[Greek mythology]] and history such as ''The King Must Die'' combine motifs of political conflict between goddess and god worshippers with ''[[The Golden Bough]]'s'' hypothesis about [[dying and reviving god]]s.  The patriarchal conquest of matriarchy motif is found in dozens of [[fantasy]] novels, from [[Marion Zimmer Bradley]]'s historical revisions of [[Matter of Britain|Arthurian romance]] and the [[Trojan War]] to works such as [[Guy Gavriel Kay]]'s ''[[A Song for Arbonne]]''. Gender roles and the conflict of patriarch vs. matriarchy is a major theme in the ''[[The Wheel of Time|Wheel of Time]]'' books by [[Robert Jordan]].

The remake version (not the original) of ''[[The Wicker Man (2006 film)|The Wicker Man]]'', starring Nicolas Cage, takes place within a fictional matriarchy in the state of [[Washington]].  The society, Summersisle, is modeled after honeybee culture and behavior.

==See also==
{{wiktionary|matriarchy}}
{{wiktionary|gynecocracy}}
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Goddess movement]] 
* [[Feminist anthropology]]
* [[History of feminism]]
* [[Amazons]]
* [[Amazon feminism]]
* ''[[The First Sex]]''
* ''[[When God Was a Woman]]''
* ''[[The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory]]''
* [[Patriarchy]]
* [[Marianismo]]
* [[Black matriarchy]]

== Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Bamberger, Joan. (1974). '"The Myth of Matriarchy: Why Men Rule in Primitive Society," in ''Woman, Culture, and Society'', edited by Michelle Zimbalist Rosaldo and Louise Lamphere, pp. 263–280. Stanford, California: Stanford University Press.
* Brown, Donald. (1991). ''Human Universals''. Philadelphia: Temple University Press
* [[Marie Antoinette Czaplicka|Czaplicka, Marie Antoinette]]. (1914).  ''Aboriginal Siberia, a study in social anthropology''.  Oxford.  Clarendon press.
*Davis, Philip, ''Goddess Unmasked'', Spence Publishing, New York, 1998. ISBN 0-9653208-9-8; review: R. Sheaffer, Skeptical Inquirer (1999)[http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-54600098.html]
* del Giorgio, J.F. (2006). ''[[The Oldest Europeans]]''. A.J.Place, ISBN 978-9806898004.
*[[Cynthia Eller|Eller, Cynthia]] (2001). [[The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory|The Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory: Why an Invented Past Won't Give Women a Future]].  ISBN 0-8070-6793-8  
*Finley, M.I. (1962). ''The World of Odysseus''. London. Pelican Books.
*[[Marija Gimbutas|Gimbutas, Marija]] (1991). "The Language of the Goddess".
*[[Steven Goldberg|Goldberg, Steven]] (1993) ''Why Men Rule: A Theory of Male Dominance'', rev. ed. ISBN 0-8126-9237-3 
*[[Ronald Hutton|Hutton, Ronald]] (1993). ''The Pagan Religions of the Ancient British Isles'' ISBN 0-631-18946-7 
*[[Kenneth Lapatin|Lapatin, Kenneth]] (2002). ''Mysteries of the Snake Goddess: Art, Desire, and the Forging of History''.  ISBN 0-306-81328-9
* [[Peggy Reeves Sanday|Sanday, Peggy Reeves]].  (2004). ''Woman at the Center: Life in a Modern Matriarchy''.  Cornell University Press. ISBN 0-8014-8906-7
*Shorrocks, Bryan. (2007). ''The Biology of African Savannahs''. [[Oxford University Press]]. ISBN 019857066X
* [http://culturalstudies.gmu.edu/faculty/faculty_bios/stearns.html Stearns, Peter N]. (2000). ''Gender in World History''. New York Routledge. ISBN 0-415-22310-5
* Smith R.T. (2002) Matrifocality, in International encyclopedia of the social and behavioral sciences (eds) Smelser &amp; Baltes, vol 14, pp 9416.
*Sukumar Raman, (2006). "A brief review of the status, distribution and biology of wild Asian elephants Elephas maximus."  ''International Zoo Yearbook''. (40)1; 1-8.
* Yoshamya, Mitjel &amp; Yoshamya, Zyelimer (2005). ''Gan-Veyan: Neo-Liburnic glossary, grammar, culture, genom.'' Old-Croatian Archidioms, Monograph I, p. 1 - 1224, Scientific society for Ethnogenesis studies, Zagreb.

== External links ==
*[http://www.newscientist.com/news/news.jsp?id=ns99994220 ''Cattle ownership makes it a man's world''] New Scientist (1. October 2003): A   study claims to demonstrate that early female-dominated societies lost their power to men when they started herding cattle.
*[http://usachi.narod.ru/en/zhen-en.htm/ Matriarchy in USSR] 
*[http://gendereconomy.com/ Matriarchy in the Dual Gender Economy Concept]

[[Category:Prehistory]]
[[Category:Prehistoric art]]
[[Category:Matriarchy| ]]
[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Archaeology]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Feminism and society]]
[[Category:Feminism and history]]

&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;

[[az:Matriarxat]]
[[ca:Matriarcat]]
[[cs:Matriarchát]]
[[da:Matriarkat]]
[[de:Matriarchat]]
[[es:Matriarcado]]
[[eo:Matriarkeco]]
[[eu:Matriarkatu]]
[[fr:Matriarcat]]
[[hr:Matrijarhat]]
[[it:Matriarcato]]
[[he:מטריארכיה]]
[[lt:Matriarchatas]]
[[mk:Матријархат]]
[[nl:Matriarchaat]]
[[no:Matriarkat]]
[[oc:Matriarcat]]
[[pl:Matriarchat]]
[[pt:Matriarcado]]
[[ru:Матриархат]]
[[scn:Matriarcatu]]
[[sk:Matriarchát]]
[[sl:Matriarhat]]
[[sr:Матријархат]]
[[sh:Matrijarhat]]
[[fi:Matriarkaatti]]
[[sv:Matriarkat]]
[[tr:Anaerkillik]]
[[uk:Матріархат]]
[[vi:Chế độ mẫu hệ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>