<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091111031844|325177588" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29252" pageid="29252" ns="0" title="Sexual orientation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-11T19:45:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{wiktionary|sexual orientation}}
{{sexual orientation}}
'''Sexual orientation''' is a pattern of emotional, romantic, and/or [[sexual attraction]]s to men, women, [[bisexuality|both genders]], [[Asexuality|neither gender]], or [[Third gender|another gender]]. According to the [[American Psychological Association]] sexual orientation also refers to a person’s sense of "personal and [[social identity]] based on those attractions, behaviors expressing them, and membership in a community of others who share them."&lt;ref name="brief"&gt; [http://www.courtinfo.ca.gov/courts/supreme/highprofile/documents/Amer_Psychological_Assn_Amicus_Curiae_Brief.pdf APA California Amicus Brief]&lt;/ref&gt; Sexual orientation is usually classified relative to the [[gender]] of the people who are found sexually attractive. Though people may use other labels, or none at all&lt;ref name="American Psychological Association"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.apa.org/topics/sorientation.html#whatis |title=Sexuality, What is sexual orientation? |periodical=[[American Psychological Association]]: ''Sexual orientation refers to an enduring pattern of emotional, romantic, and/or sexual attractions.... Sexual orientation is usually discussed in terms of three categories: heterosexual, homosexual, bisexual...However, some people may use different labels or none at all.'' |accessdate=2008-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;, sexual orientation is usually discussed in terms of three categories: [[heterosexuality|heterosexual]], [[homosexual orientation|homosexual]], and [[bisexuality|bisexual]]. These orientations exist along a [[heterosexual-homosexual continuum|continuum]] that ranges from exclusive heterosexual to exclusive homosexual, including various forms of bisexuality in-between. The continuum between heterosexual and homosexual does not suit everyone, however, as some people identify as [[Asexuality|asexual]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asexuality.org/home/&lt;/ref&gt;  Sexologists see this linear scale as an oversimplification of a more nuanced notion of sexual identity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.plannedparenthood.org/health-topics/sexual-orientation-gender-4329.htm Planned Parent Hood: Sexual Orientation &amp; Gender, LGBTQ ... The Labels and Their Meaning]&lt;/ref&gt;

Most definitions of sexual orientation include a psychological component, such as the direction of an individual's erotic desire, or a behavioral component, which focuses on the sex of the individual's sexual partner/s. Some definitions include both components. Some people prefer simply to follow an individual's self-definition or [[Identity (social science)|identity]].

Some scholars of [[sexology]], [[anthropology]] and [[history]] have argued that social categories such as heterosexual and homosexual are not universal. Different societies may consider other criteria to be more significant than sex, including the [[Age disparity in sexual relationships|respective age of the partners]], whether partners assume an active or a passive sexual role, and their social status.

[[Sexual orientation identity|Sexual identity]] and [[sexual behavior]] are closely related to sexual orientation, but they are distinguished, with identity referring to an individual's conception of themselves, behavior referring to actual sexual acts performed by the individual, and orientation referring to "fantasies, attachments and longings."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Reiter L |title=Sexual orientation, sexual identity, and the question of choice |journal=Clinical Social Work Journal |volume=17 |pages=138–50 |year=1989}}&lt;/ref&gt; Individuals may or may not express their sexual orientation in their behaviors.&lt;ref name="apahelp"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.apahelpcenter.org/articles/article.php?id=31 |title=Sexual Orientation and Homosexuality |periodical=[[American Psychological Association|APA]]HelpCenter.org |accessdate=2007-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  People who have a homosexual sexual orientation that does not align with their sexual identity are sometimes referred to as [[closeted]].

''Sexual identity'' may also be used to describe a person's perception of his or her own ''sex'', rather than sexual orientation. The term ''sexual preference'' has a similar meaning to ''sexual orientation'', but is more commonly used outside of scientific circles by people who believe that sexual orientation is, in whole or part, a matter of choice.{{Fact|date=May 2008}}

Sexual orientation is a concept that evolved in the industrialized West and there is a controversy as to the universality of its application in other societies/ cultures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=sFHX6uu19ZEC&amp;pg=PA81&amp;lpg=PA81&amp;dq=sexual+orientation+is+a+western+concept&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Lj2ODgARED&amp;sig=6AUpbyJbsvbyqUxbjKmnXfdZX3c&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ct=result The Psychology of Sexual Orientation, Behaviour, and identity] By Louis Diamant, Richard D. McAnulty;Published by Greenwood Publishing Group, 1995; ISBN 0313285012, 9780313285011; 522 pages; Quote from page 81: Although sexual orientation is a loaded Western concept, the term is still a useful one, if we avoid imposing Western thoughts and meanings associated with our language on non-Western, noncontemporary cultures.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=zikdWhuosAgC&amp;pg=PA478&amp;lpg=PA478&amp;dq=sexual+orientation+western+concept&amp;source=web&amp;ots=afh1aodckX&amp;sig=P6TcEFjCK4Lc-OSh251ZTvt1o1o&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ct=result The Handbook of Social Work Direct Practice] By Paula Allen-Meares, Charles D. Garvin; Contributor Paula Allen-Meares, Charles D. Garvin; Published by SAGE, 2001, ISBN 0761914994, 9780761914990
733 pages; Quote from page 478: The concept of sexual orientation is a product of contemporary Western thought.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.radstats.org.uk/no083/Ross83.pdf Sexual behavior and the non-construction of sexual identity: Implications for the analysis of men who have sex with men and women who have sex with women.]
Michael W. Ross &amp; Ann K. Brooks; Quote from Page 9: Chou (2000) notes in his analysis of the lack of applicability of western concepts of sexual identity in China, just because a person has a particular taste for a specific food doesn’t mean that we label them in terms of the food that they prefer. A similar approach to sexual appetite as not conferring identity may be operating in this sample. McIntosh (1968) has previously noted that people who do not identify with the classic western, white gay/lesbian role may not necessarily identify their behavior as homosexual.&lt;/ref&gt; As Michel Foucault put it, "'Sexuality' is an invention of the modern state, the industrial revolution, and capitalism."&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=dMAtGvry_IMC&amp;pg=PA32&amp;lpg=PA32&amp;dq=china+heterosexuality+love+western&amp;source=web&amp;ots=PKv2BfyPpd&amp;sig=s43w6PzlNOgefEsjpHViwrxkM6A&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=result Chinese Femininities, Chinese Masculinities: A Reader]; By Susan Brownell, Jeffrey N. Wasserstrom; Published by University of California Press, 2002; ISBN 0520221168, 9780520221161; Quote: "The problem with Sexuality

Some scholars have argued that maleness and femaleness were not closely linked to sexuality in China. Foucault's "The History of Sexuality" (which dealt primarily with Western civilization and western Europe) began to influence some China scholars in the 1980s. Foucault's insight was to demonstrate that sexuality has a history; it is not fixed psychobiological drive that is the same for all humans according to their sex, but rather it is a cultural construct inseparable from gender constructs. After unmooring sexuality from biology, he anchored it in history, arguing that this thing we now call sexuality came into existencee in the eighteenth-century West and did not exist previously in this form. "Sexuality" is an invention of the modern state, the industrial revolution, and capitalism. Taking this insight as a starting point, scholars have slowly been compiling the history of sexuality in china. The works by Tani Barlow, discussed above, were also foundational in this trend. Barlow observes that, in the West, heterosexuality is the primary site for the production of gender: a woman truly becomes a woman only in relation to a man's heterosexual desire. By contrast, in China before the 1920s the "jia" (linage unit, family) was the priamary site for the production of gender: marriage and sexuality were to serve the lineage by producing the next generation of lineage members; personal love and pleasure were secondary to this goal. Barlow argues that this has two theoretical implications: (1) it is not possible to write a chinese history of heterosexuality, sexuality as an institution, and sexual identities in the European metaphysical sense, and (2) it is not appropriate to ground discussions of Chinese gender processes in the sexed body so central in "Western" gender processes. Here she echoes Furth's argument that, before the earlyu twentiethh century, sex-identity grounded on anatomical difference did not hold a central place in Chinese constructions of gender. And she ehoes the point illustrated in detail in Sommer's chapter on male homosexuality in the Qing legal code: a man could engage in homosexual behaviour without calling into question his manhood so long as his behaviour did not threaten the patriarchal Confucian family structure."&lt;/ref&gt; [[Non-westernized concepts of male sexuality]] differ essentially from the way sexuality is seen and classified under the system of Sexual Orientation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.allacademic.com/meta/p_mla_apa_research_citation/1/1/3/4/8/p113482_index.html Transnational Transgender: Reading Sexual Diversity in Cross-Cultural Contexts Through Film and Video]; Ryan, Joelle Ruby; American Studies Association; Quote: Many of the projects which have historically investigated sex/gender variance in non-Western contexts have been ethnographies and anthropological studies. Due to strong and lingering problems with ethnocentrism, many of these research studies have attempted to transpose a Western understanding of sex, gender and sexuality onto cultures in Asia, Latin America and Africa. Terms such as “homosexual,” “transvestite,” and “transsexual” all arose out of Western concepts of identity based on science, sexology and medicine and often bear little resemblance to sex/gender/sexuality paradigms in the varied cultures of the developing world.&lt;/ref&gt; The validity of the notion of 'sexual orientation' has also been questioned within the industrialized Western society.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psa.ac.uk/2007/pps/Waites.pdf Sexual Orientation, Human Rights and Global Politics] Matthew Waits, Department of Sociology, Anthropology and Applied Social Sciences, University of Glasgow, United Kingdom; email: m.waites@lbss.gla.ac.uk; web: http://www.gla.ac.uk/departments/sociology/staff/waites.html ; Quote from the Abstract: The paper problematises utilisation of the concept of 'sexual orientation' in moves to revise human rights conventions and discourses in the light of social constructionist and queer theory addressing sexuality, which has convincingly suggested that 'sexual orientation' is a culturally specific concept, misrepresenting many diverse forms of sexuality apparent in comparative sociological and anthropological research conducted worldwide. I will argue in particular that 'orientation' is a concept incompatible with bisexuality when interpreted within the context of dominant dualistic assumptions about sex, gender and desire in western culture (suggested by Judith Butler's concept of the 'heterosexual matrix'). I will discuss the implications of the this for interpreting contemporary struggles among competing social movements, NGO and governmental actors involved in contesting the relationship of sexuality to human rights as defined by the United Nations.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sexualorientation.info/thesis/Resisting%20Orientation%20-%20C1.pdf] McIntosh argues that the labelling process should be the focus of inquiry and that homosexuality should be seen as a social role rather than a condition. Role is more useful than condition, she argues, because roles (of heterosexual and homosexual) can be dichotomised in a way that behaviour cannot. She draws upon cross-cultural data to demonstrate that in many societies 'there may be much homosexual behaviour, but there are no "homosexuals"' (p71).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Sexual orientation, identity, behaviour ==
{{Seealso|Sexual identity|Sexual behaviour}}
{{Seealso|Situational sexual behavior}}

The [[American Psychological Association]] states that sexual orientation "describes the pattern of sexual attraction, behavior and identity e.g. [[homosexual]] (a.k.a. [[gay]]), [[lesbian]]), [[bisexual]] and [[heterosexual]] (a.k.a. straight)." "Sexual attraction, behavior and identity may be incongruent. For example, sexual attraction and/or behavior may not necessarily be consistent with identity. Some individuals may identify themselves as homosexual or bisexual without having had any sexual experience. Others have had homosexual experiences but do not consider themselves to be gay, lesbian, or bisexual. Further, sexual orientation falls along a continuum. In other words, someone does not have to be exclusively homosexual or heterosexual, but can feel varying degrees of both. Sexual orientation develops across a person's lifetime-different people realize at different points in their lives that they are heterosexual, bisexual or homosexual."&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.aapa.org/clinissues/2007C03.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest writers on sexual orientation usually understood it to be intrinsically linked to the subject's own sex. For example, it was thought that a typical female-bodied person who is attracted to female-bodied persons would have masculine attributes, and vice versa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Minton HL |title=Femininity in men and masculinity in women: American psychiatry and psychology portray homosexuality in the 1930s |journal=[[Journal of Homosexuality]] |volume=13 |issue=1 |pages=1–21 |year=1986}}&lt;br&gt;Terry, J. (1999). ''An American obsession: Science, medicine, and homosexuality in modern society.'' Chicago: University of Chicago Press&lt;/ref&gt; This understanding was shared by most of the significant theorists of sexual orientation from the mid nineteenth to early twentieth century, such as [[Karl Heinrich Ulrichs]], [[Richard von Krafft-Ebing]], [[Magnus Hirschfeld]], [[Havelock Ellis]], [[Carl Jung]] and [[Sigmund Freud]], as well as many gender variant homosexual people themselves. However, this understanding of homosexuality as sexual inversion was disputed at the time, and through the second half of the twentieth century, [[gender identity]] came to be increasingly seen as a phenomenon distinct from sexual orientation. [[Transgender]] and [[cisgender]] people may be attracted to men, women, or both, although the prevalence of different sexual orientations is quite different in these two populations (see [[sexual orientation of transwomen]]). An individual homosexual, heterosexual or bisexual person may be masculine, feminine, or [[Androgyny|androgynous]], and in addition, many members and supporters of lesbian and gay communities now see the "gender-conforming heterosexual" and the "gender-nonconforming homosexual" as negative [[stereotype]]s. However, studies by [[J. Michael Bailey|J Michael Bailey]] and KJ Zucker have found that a majority of gay men and lesbians report being gender-nonconforming during their childhood years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=[[J. Michael Bailey|Bailey JM]], Zucker KJ |title=Childhood sex-typed behavior and sexual orientation: a conceptual analysis and quantitative review |journal=Developmental Psychology |volume=31 |issue=1 |pages=43 |year=1995 |doi=10.1037/0012-1649.31.1.43}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The majority of transgender people today identify with the sexual orientation that corresponds with their gender; meaning that a transwoman who is solely attracted to women would often identify as a lesbian. Female-attracted [[Transman|transmen]] often consider themselves straight men, yet some participate in the lesbian community. 

For these reasons, the terms [[gynephilia and androphilia]] are occasionally (but increasingly) used when referring to the sexual orientation of [[transgender]] and [[intersex]] people (and occasionally, cisgender people), because rather than focusing on the sex of the subject, they only describe that of the object of their attraction. The third common term that describes sexual orientation, [[bisexuality]], makes no claim about the subject's sex or gender identity. (See also [[Pansexuality]])

Sexual orientation sees greater intricacy when non-binary understandings of both sex (male, female, or [[intersex]]) and gender (man, woman, [[transgender]], [[third gender]], or [[Gender variance|gender variant]]) are considered. Sociologist [[Paula Rodriguez Rust]] (2000) argues for a more multifaceted definition of sexual orientation:

{{quotation|...Most alternative models of sexuality...define sexual orientation in terms of dichotomous biological sex or gender.... Most theorists would not eliminate the reference to sex or gender, but instead advocate incorporating more complex nonbinary concepts of sex or gender, more complex relationships between sex, gender, and sexuality, and/or additional nongendered dimensions into models of sexuality.|&lt;ref&gt;Rodriguez Rust, Paula C. ''Bisexuality: A contemporary paradox for women'', Journal of Social Issues, Vol 56(2), Summer 2000. Special Issue: Women's sexualities: New perspectives on sexual orientation and gender. pp. 205-221. [http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0341/is_2_56/ai_66419862/pg_2 article online]&lt;br&gt;Also published in: Rodriguez Rust, Paula C. ''Bisexuality in the United States: A Social Science Reader''. Columbia University Press, 2000. ISBN 0-231-10227-5 &lt;/ref&gt;}}

==== Fluidity of sexuality ====

The [[American Psychiatric Association]] (APA) has stated "some people believe that sexual orientation is innate and fixed; however, sexual orientation develops across a person’s lifetime".&lt;ref name="Psych"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.aglp.org/pages/cfactsheets.html#Anchor-Gay-14210
|title=Gay, Lesbian and Bisexual Issues
|author=[[American Psychiatric Association]]
|publisher=Association of Gay and Lesbian Psychiatrics
|month=May | year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; The APA also says that "most people experience little or no sense of choice about their sexual orientation".&lt;ref name="answers"&gt; {{cite web
 |url=http://www.apa.org/topics/orientation.html  |title=Answers to Your Questions About Sexual Orientation and Homosexuality  |accessdate=2008-05-26
 |publisher=American Psychological Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a joint statement with other major American medical organizations, the APA says that "different people realize at different points in their lives that they are heterosexual, gay, lesbian, or bisexual".&lt;ref name="apa"&gt;
{{cite web
 |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbc/publications/justthefacts.html
 |title=Just the Facts About Sexual Orientation &amp; Youth: A Primer for Principals, Educators and School Personnel
 |accessdate=2007-08-28
 |year=1999
 |publisher=American Academy of Pediatrics, American Counseling Association, American Association of School Administrators, American Federation of Teachers, American Psychological Association, American School Health Association, The Interfaith Alliance, National Association of School Psychologists, National Association of Social Workers, National Education Association
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A report from the [[Centre for Addiction and Mental Health]] states: "For some people, sexual orientation is continuous and fixed throughout their lives. For others, sexual orientation may be fluid and change over time".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  |url=http://www.camh.net/Publications/Resources_for_Professionals/ARQ2/arq2_question_a2.html 
 |title=ARQ2: Question A2 - Sexual Orientation
 |accessdate=2007-08-28
 |publisher=Centre for Addiction and Mental Health}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gay and lesbian people can have sexual relationships with someone of the opposite sex for a variety of reasons including the desire for family with children and concerns of discrimination and religious [[ostracism]].&lt;ref name=Brokeback&gt;{{cite news
|title=Many Couples Must Negotiate Terms of 'Brokeback' Marriages
|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/07/health/07broke.html?_r=2&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin
|last=Butler
|first=Katy
|date=March 7, 2006
|publisher=[[New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=How to tell if your husband is gay
|first=Rochelle
|last=Hentges
|publisher=[[Pittsburgh Tribune-Review]]
|date=October 4, 2006
|url=http://www.pittsburghlive.com/x/pittsburghtrib/news/tribpm/s_473458.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.haworthpress.com/store/ArticleAbstract.asp?sid=3Q4EE45JK40W8L1DN0HJVF3U8WFT5DSC&amp;ID=11230 Gay Men from Heterosexual Marriages: Attitudes, Behaviors, Childhood Experiences, and Reasons for Marriage]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rickross.com/reference/mormon/mormon336.html Gay, Mormon, married]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://psychologytoday.com/articles/pto-19990301-000030.html Gay No More]&lt;/ref&gt; A [[mixed-orientation marriage]] is when one partner is [[non-heterosexual]].&lt;ref name=Buntzly93&gt;{{cite journal |author=Büntzly G |title=Gay fathers in straight marriages |journal=J Homosex |volume=24 |issue=3-4 |pages=107–14 |year=1993 |pmid=8505530 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="The Married Lesbian"&gt; [http://www.haworthpress.com/store/ArticleAbstract.asp?sid=3Q4EE45JK40W8L1DN0HJVF3U8WFT5DSC&amp;ID=82829 The Married Lesbian]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8505530?ordinalpos=86&amp;itool=EntrezSystem2.PEntrez.Pubmed.Pubmed_ResultsPanel.Pubmed_RVDocSum Gay fathers in straight marriages]&lt;/ref&gt; While some hide their orientation from their spouse, others develop a positive gay or lesbian identity while maintaining a successful marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Hays D, Samuels A |title=Heterosexual women's perceptions of their marriages to bisexual or homosexual men |journal=J Homosex |volume=18 |issue=1-2 |pages=81–100 |year=1989 |pmid=2794500 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Coleman E |title=Bisexual and gay men in heterosexual marriage: conflicts and resolutions in therapy |journal=J Homosex |volume=7 |issue=2-3 |pages=93–103 |year=1981 |pmid=7346553 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Matteson DR |title=Bisexual men in marriage: is a positive homosexual identity and stable marriage possible? |journal=J Homosex |volume=11 |issue=1-2 |pages=149–71 |year=1985 |pmid=4056386 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Coming out]] of the closet to oneself, a spouse of the opposite sex, and children can present challenges that are not faced by gay and lesbian people who are not married to people of the opposite sex or do not have children.

==== Efforts to change sexuality ====
{{main|Sexual orientation change efforts}}
Major US, UK and Australian professional and scientific organizations regard attempts to change people's sexual orientation as potentially harmful, while some groups, often motivated by religious beliefs, believe change is possible, or homosexual attraction diminished, for those who cannot accept their sexual orientation.

The [[American Psychological Association]], the [[American Psychiatric Association]], and the [[National Association of Social Workers]] state:
{{cquote|Sexual orientation has proved to be generally impervious to interventions intended to change it, which are sometimes referred to as “[[Conversion therapy|reparative therapy]].” No scientifically adequate research has shown that such interventions are effective or safe. Moreover, because homosexuality is a normal variant of human sexuality, national mental health organizations do not encourage individuals to try to change their sexual orientation from homosexual to heterosexual. Therefore, all major national mental health organizations have adopted policy statements cautioning the profession and the public about treatments that purport to change sexual orientation. The statement of the American Psychiatric Association cautions that “[t]he potential risks of ‘reparative therapy’ are great, including depression, anxiety and self-destructive behavior.”&lt;ref name=amici&gt;[http://www.courtinfo.ca.gov/courts/supreme/highprofile/documents/Amer_Psychological_Assn_Amicus_Curiae_Brief.pdf Case No. S147999 in the Supreme Court of the State of California, In re Marriage Cases Judicial Council Coordination Proceeding No. 4365, Application for leave to file brief amici curiae in support of the parties challenging the marriage exclusion, and brief amici curiae of the American Psychological Association, California Psychological Association, American Psychiatric Association, National Association of Social Workers, and National Association of Social Workers, California Chapter in support of the parties challenging the marriage exclusion]&lt;/ref&gt;}}
The [[Australian Psychological Society]] states:
{{cquote|"Homosexual orientation is not a mental illness and there is no scientific reason to attempt conversion of lesbians or gays to heterosexual orientation. The Australian Psychological Society acknowledges the lack of scientific evidence for the usefulness of conversion therapy, and notes that it can in fact be harmful for the individual. Changing the sexual orientation of a person is not simply a matter of changing the person's sexual behavior. It would require altering the emotional, romantic and sexual feelings of the person and restructuring self-concept and social identity."&lt;ref name=aps&gt;Australian Psychological Society: [http://www.psychology.org.au/publications/tip_sheets/orientation/ Sexual orientation and homosexuality]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Similarly, the [[Royal College of Psychiatrists]] states "There is no sound scientific evidence that sexual orientation can be changed."&lt;ref&gt;Royal College of Psychiatrists: [http://www.rcpsych.ac.uk/pressparliament/pressreleases2009/statement.aspx Statement from the Royal College of Psychiatrists’ Gay and Lesbian Mental Health Special Interest Group]&lt;/ref&gt; and "The best evidence for efficacy of any treatment comes from [[Randomized controlled trial|randomised clinical trials]] and no such trial has been carried out in this field."&lt;ref name=rcppalp&gt;Royal College of Psychiatrists: [http://www.rcpsych.ac.uk/college/specialinterestgroups/gaylesbian/submissiontothecofe/psychiatryandlgbpeople.aspx Psychiatry and LGB people]&lt;/ref&gt;   [[Surgeon General of the United States|United States Surgeon General]] [[David Satcher]] issued a report stating that "there is no valid scientific evidence that sexual orientation can be changed".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.surgeongeneral.gov/library/sexualhealth/call.htm#III The Surgeon General's call to Action to Promote Sexual Health and Responsible Sexual Behavior]", A Letter from the Surgeon General U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, July 9, 2001.  Retrieved March 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

American Psychological Association "encourages mental health professionals to avoid misrepresenting the efficacy of sexual orientation change efforts by promoting or promising change in sexual orientation when providing assistance to individuals distressed by their own or others’ sexual orientation and concludes that the benefits reported by participants in sexual orientation change efforts can be gained through approaches that do not attempt to change sexual orientation".&lt;ref name=apa2009&gt;American Psychological Association: [http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbc/publications/resolution-resp.html Resolution on Appropriate Affirmative Responses to Sexual Orientation Distress and Change Efforts]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Measuring sexual orientation ==
Varying definitions and strong [[sexual norm|social norms about sexuality]] can make sexual orientation difficult to quantify. Researchers may use different markers of sexual orientation, including self-labeling, sexual behaviour, sexual fantasy or a pattern of erotic arousal. A clinical measurement may use [[penile plethysmograph|penile]] or [[vaginal photoplethysmograph]]y, where genital engorgement with blood is measured in response to exposure to different erotic material.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, G. and Rahman, Q., (2005). Born Gay. London: Peter Owen Publishers, p21&lt;/ref&gt;   In 1995, two researchers argued that due to a lack of research on change over time, there is a limitation on current conceptualizations of sexual orientation. They did not abandon the concept of sexual orientation, but concluded that "given such significant measurement problems, one could conclude there is serious doubt whether sexual orientation is a valid concept at all," and warned against increasing politicization of this area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
|url=http://doi.apa.org/getuid.cfm?uid=1996-16078-001
|title=Definition and measurement of sexual orientation
|last=Gonsoriek
|first=John. C.
|coauthor=Weinrich, J. D.
|year=1995
|publisher=Suicide and Life Threatening Behavior
|volume=25
|pages=40–51}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From at least the late nineteenth century in Europe, there was speculation that the range of human sexual response looked more like a continuum than two or three discrete categories. Berlin sexologist [[Magnus Hirschfeld]] published a scheme in 1896 that measured the strength of an individual's sexual desire on two independent 10-point scales, A (homosexual) and B (heterosexual).&lt;ref&gt;[[Magnus Hirschfeld|Hirschfeld, Magnus]], 1896. ''Sappho und Socrates, Wie erklärt sich die Liebe der Männer &amp; und Frauen zu Personen des eigenen Geschlechts?'' (Sappho and Socrates, How Can One Explain the Love of Men and Women for Individuals of Their Own Sex?)&lt;/ref&gt; A heterosexual individual may be A0, B5; a homosexual individual may be A5, B0; An asexual would be A0, B0; and someone with an intense attraction to both sexes would be A9, B9.

Fifty years later, American sexologist [[Alfred Kinsey]] wrote in [[Sexual Behavior in the Human Male]] (1948):

{{quotation|Males do not represent two discrete populations, heterosexual and homosexual. The world is not to be divided into sheep and goats. It is a fundamental of taxonomy that nature rarely deals with discrete categories... The living world is a continuum in each and every one of its aspects.
While emphasizing the continuity of the gradations between exclusively heterosexual and exclusively homosexual histories, it has seemed desirable to develop some sort of classification which could be based on the relative amounts of heterosexual and homosexual experience or response in each history... An individual may be assigned a position on this scale, for each period in his life.... A seven-point scale comes nearer to showing the many gradations that actually exist.|&lt;ref&gt;A.C. Kinsey, W.B. Pomeroy, C.E. Martin, ''Sexual Behavior in the Human Male,'' (pp. 639, 656). Philadelphia, PA: W.B. Saunders, 1948). ISBN 0-253-33412-8.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The [[Kinsey scale]] measures sexual orientation from 0 (exclusively heterosexual) to 6 (exclusively homosexual), with an additional category, X, for those with no sexual attraction to either women or men. Unlike Hirschfeld's scale, the Kinsey scale is one-dimensional. [[Simon LeVay]] wrote, "it suggests (although Kinsey did not actually believe this) that every person has the same fixed endowment of sexual energy, which he or she then divides up between same-sex and opposite-sex attraction in a ratio indicative of his or her own sexual orientation."&lt;ref&gt;[[Simon LeVay|LeVay, Simon]], 1996. ''Queer Science: The Use and Abuse of Research into Homosexuality.'' Cambridge: MIT Press. ISBN 0-262-62119-3 .&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indirect detection===
{{further|[[Gaydar]]|[[Biology and sexual orientation]]}}

Scientific studies have found a number of statistical [[Biology and sexual orientation#Biological_differences_in_gay_men_and_lesbians|biological differences between gay and straight people]], which may result from the same underlying cause as orientation itself.  The attempt to detect sexual orientation in social situations is known as [[gaydar]]; some studies have found that guesses based on face photos perform better than chance. However, it is very much possible that what people notice in these situations is the femininity of the male, and since a disproportionate number of males who take up the gay identity are feminine, this may seem to work.

== Demographics of sexual orientation ==

{{Main|Demographics of sexual orientation}}

The multiple aspects of sexual orientation and the boundary-drawing problems already described create methodological challenges for the study of the demographics of sexual orientation. Determining the frequency of various sexual orientations in real-world populations is difficult and controversial.

In the oft-cited and oft-criticized [[Kinsey Reports|Sexual Behavior in the Human Male]] (1948) and [[Kinsey Reports|Sexual Behavior in the Human Female]] (1953), by [[Alfred C. Kinsey]] et al., people were asked to rate themselves on a [[Kinsey scale|scale]] from completely heterosexual to completely homosexual. Kinsey reported that when the individuals' behavior as well as their identity are analyzed, most people appeared to be at least somewhat bisexual &amp;ndash; i.e., most people have some attraction to either sex, although usually one sex is preferred. According to Kinsey, only a minority (5-10%) can be considered fully heterosexual or homosexual. Conversely, only an even smaller minority can be considered fully bisexual (with an equal attraction to both sexes).

Kinsey's methods have been criticized as flawed, particularly with regard to the randomness of his sample population, which included a large number of prison inmates. Nevertheless, [[Paul Gebhard]], subsequent director of the [[Kinsey Institute for Sex Research]], reexamined the data in the [[Kinsey Reports]] and concluded that accounting for major statistical objections barely affected the results. Most modern scientific surveys find that the majority of people report a mostly heterosexual orientation. However, the relative percentage of the population that reports a homosexual orientation varies with differing methodologies and selection criteria. Most of these statistical findings are in the range of 2.8 to 9% of males, and 1 to 5% of females for the United States&lt;ref&gt;James Alm, M. V. Lee Badgett, Leslie A. Whittington, ''Wedding Bell Blues: The Income Tax Consequences of Legalizing Same-Sex Marriage'', page 24. (1998) [http://www.colorado.edu/Economics/CEA/papers98/wp98-33.pdf PDF link]&lt;/ref&gt; — this figure can be as high as 12% for some large cities and as low as 1% percent for rural areas). In [[gay village]]s such as [[The Castro]] in [[San Francisco, California]], the concentration of self-identified homosexual people can exceed 40%.{{Fact|date=December 2007}}

Estimates for the percentage of the population that are bisexual vary widely, at least in part due to differing definitions of bisexuality. Some studies only consider a person bisexual if they are nearly equally attracted to both sexes, and others consider a person bisexual if they are ''at all'' attracted to the same sex (for otherwise mostly heterosexual persons) or to the opposite sex (for otherwise mostly homosexual persons). A small percentage of people are not sexually attracted to anyone ([[asexuality]]).

== Influences on sexual orientation ==
{{further|[[Homosexuality#Etiology|Theories on homosexuality]]}}
The [[American Academy of Pediatrics]] has stated "Sexual orientation probably is not determined by any one factor but by a combination of genetic, hormonal, and environmental influences."&lt;ref&gt;[http://aappolicy.aappublications.org/cgi/reprint/pediatrics;113/6/1827.pdf Sexual Orientation and Adolescents], [[American Academy of Pediatrics]] Clinical Report. Retrieved 2007-02-23.&lt;/ref&gt; Debate continues over what biological and/or psychological variables influence sexual orientation in humans, such as [[genes]] and the exposure of certain levels of [[Biology and sexual orientation#Fetal development|hormones]] to fetuses. Freud and other psychoanalysts maintain that sexual orientation is influenced by numerous factors including formative childhood experiences in some cases.

===Environmental factors===
{{main|Environment and sexual orientation}}
====Prenatal hormones on developing fetus====
{{main|Prenatal hormones and sexual orientation}}
The hormonal theory of sexuality holds that, just as exposure to certain hormones plays a role in fetal sex differentiation, such exposure also influences the sexual orientation that emerges later in the adult. Fetal hormones may be seen as either the primary influence upon adult sexual orientation, or as co-factor interacting with genes and/or environmental and social conditions&lt;ref&gt;G.Wilson &amp; Q.Rahman Born Gay: The Psychobiology of Human Sex Orientation, London: Peter Owen 2005&lt;/ref&gt;.

====Birth order====
{{main|Fraternal birth order and sexual orientation}}
Recent studies found an increased chance of homosexuality in men whose mothers previously carried to term many male children. This effect is nullified if the man is left-handed.&lt;ref&gt;Blanchard, R., Cantor, J. M., Bogaert, A. F., Breedlove, S. M., &amp; Ellis, L. (2006). [http://msu.edu/~breedsm/pdf/Blanchard2006IntFratHandHBFinal.pdf "Interaction of fraternal birth order and handedness in the development of male homosexuality."] ''Hormones and Behavior'', 49, 405–414.&lt;/ref&gt; No similar effect was found in women.{{Fact|date=April 2007}}

===Genetic factors===
{{main | Biology and sexual orientation}}
Research has identified several biological factors which may be related to the development of sexual orientation, including [[gene]]s, [[Prenatal hormones and sexual orientation|prenatal hormones]], and [[brain]] structure. No single controlling cause has been identified, and research is continuing in this area. At one time, [[twin studies]] appeared to point to a major genetic component, but problems in [[experimental design]] of the available studies have made their interpretation difficult, and one recent study appears to exclude genes as a major factor.&lt;ref name=Bearman&gt;This work was published in the ''American Journal of Sociology'' (Bearman, P. S. &amp; Bruckner, H. (2002) Opposite-sex twins and adolescent same-sex attraction. American Journal of Sociology 107, 1179–1205.) and is available only to subscribers. However, a final draft of the paper is available [http://www.iserp.columbia.edu/research/working_papers/downloads/2001_04.pdf here] - there are no significant differences on the points cited between the final draft and the published version.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Innate bisexuality ===
{{main|Innate bisexuality}}
[[Innate bisexuality]], or predisposition to bisexuality, is an idea introduced by [[Sigmund Freud]], based on work by his associate [[Wilhelm Fliess]]. According to this theory, all humans are born bisexual but through psychological development, which includes both external and internal factors, become monosexual while the bisexuality remains in a latent state.

===Choice===
There is disagreement among scientists about whether choice could play any role in the development of sexual orientation.

Dr. Angela Pattatucci, a clinical biologist, said "'Lifestyle' is idiotic when applied to sexual orientation &amp;ndash; would you refer to lefthandedness as an 'alternative lifestyle'? &amp;ndash; but the problem is that through misuse by the media and in political rhetoric it's become ubiquitous.... When reporters use it, it is simply intellectual laziness. But some people adore that word, and the reason is probably in many cases, I'm very sorry to say, that it is such an inaccurate description of homosexuality, implying that sexual orientation is something one chooses, something frivolous or faddish, determined by what you do, as opposed to an internal orientation that is a component of what you are." &lt;ref&gt; Burr, Chandler. ''A Separate Creation: The Search for the Biological Origins of Sexual Orientation.'' Hyperion 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Simon LeVay]], a neuroscientist, has argued against scientists, including [[Dean Hamer]], who claim that genetic research has proven that sexual orientation is not a choice. Referring to Hamer's testimony at a 1993 [[Romer v. Evans|trial]] challenging Colorado's Amendment 2, which would have rescinded anti-discrimination laws prohibiting discrimination against homosexuals, LeVay wrote, "...the pressures of the trial drove the expert witnesses to take somewhat more extreme or simplified positions than they might otherwise have done. Hamer, for example, said at one point: "Since people don't choose their genes, they couldn't possibly choose their sexual orientation. The same goes for the question about changing. People can't change their genes. So that part of sexuality that is genetically influenced, of course, cannot be easily changed." This goes beyond the data in two respects. First, it seems to deny any possibility of choice even if the genetic influence is only partial. Yet it is possible to construct a hypothesis whereby both "gay genes" ''and'' a desire to be homosexual are necessary for a person actually to become homosexual. Second, it equates genetic loading with immutability, a connection that is open to challenge." &lt;ref name="levay"&gt;LeVay, Simon (1996). ''Queer Science: The Use and Abuse of Research into Homosexuality.'' Cambridge: The MIT Press ISBN 0-262-12199-9 &lt;/ref&gt;

== Sexual orientation as a social construct ==
{{Seealso|Queer theory|Human male sexuality}}

Because sexual orientation is complex and multi-dimensional, some academics and researchers, especially in [[Queer studies]], have argued that it is a historical and social construction. In 1976 the historian [[Michel Foucault]] argued that [[homosexuality]] as an identity did not exist in the eighteenth century; that people instead spoke of "sodomy", which referred to sexual acts. Sodomy was a crime that was often ignored but sometimes punished severely (see [[sodomy law]]).

Foucault further argued that it was in the nineteenth century that homosexuality came into existence as practitioners of emerging sciences and arts sought to classify and analyze different forms of sexuality. Finally, Foucault argues that it was this emerging discourse that allowed some to claim homosexuality as a human identity.{{Fact|date=April 2007}}

Heterosexuality and homosexuality are terms often used in European and American cultures to encompass a person’s entire social identity, which includes self and personality. In Western cultures some people speak meaningfully of gay, lesbian, and bisexual identities and communities. In other cultures, homosexuality and heterosexual labels don’t emphasize an entire social identity or indicate community affiliation based on sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;Zachary Green and Michael J. Stiers. ''Multiculturalism and Group Therapy in the United States: A Social Constructionist Perspective''. Springer Netherlands 2002. Pages 233-246.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some historians and researchers argue that the emotional and affectionate activities associated with sexual-orientation terms such as gay and straight change significantly over time and across cultural boundaries. For example, in many English-speaking nations it is assumed that same-sex kissing, particularly between men, is a sign of homosexuality, whereas various types of same-sex kissing are common expressions of [[friendship]] in other nations. Also, many modern and historic cultures have formal ceremonies expressing long-term commitment between same-sex friends, even though homosexuality itself is taboo within the culture.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Brain. ''Friends and Lovers''. Granada Publishing Ltd. 1976. Chapters 3, 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Perceived sexual orientation==
One person may assume knowledge of another person's sexual orientation based upon perceived characteristics such as appearance, clothing, and tone of voice.  Perceived sexual orientation may affect how a person is treated.  For instance, in the United States, the [[FBI]] reported that 15.6% of [[hate crime]]s reported to police in 2004 were "because of a sexual-orientation bias."&lt;ref name="FBI crime"&gt;{{citation |title=Crime in the United States 2004: Hate Crime |url=http://www.fbi.gov/ucr/cius_04/offenses_reported/hate_crime/index.html |periodical=[[FBI]] |accessdate=2007-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the [[UK]] [[Employment Equality Regulations]], "workers or job applicants must not be treated less favorably because of their sexual orientation, their perceived sexual orientation or because they associate with someone of a particular sexual orientation."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acas.org.uk/CHttpHandler.ashx?id=105&amp;p=0 Sexual orientation and the workplace: Putting the Employment Equality (Sexual Orientation) Regulations 2003 into practice]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Medical associations with policy related to sexual orientation==
===Australia===
*Australian Medical Association[http://www.ama.com.au/web.nsf/doc/WEEN-5GA2YX]

===China===
*[[Chinese Society of Psychiatry]]

===United States===
*American Academy of Pediatrics [http://aappolicy.aappublications.org/cgi/content/full/pediatrics;113/6/1827]
*American Medical Association[http://www.ama-assn.org/ama/pub/category/14754.html]
*American Medical Student Association [http://www.amsa.org/lgbt/]
*American Psychological Association (for public)[http://www.apa.org/topics/orientation.html] (for educators)[http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbc/publications/justthefacts.html]
*Catholic Medical Association&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cathmed.org/publications/homosexuality.htm Catholic Medical Association&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Christian Medical and Dental Association [http://www.cmdahome.org/index.cgi?BISKIT=2302340612&amp;CONTEXT=art&amp;art=2553]

== See also ==
{{Portal|Sexuality}}
{{Portal|LGBT|Portal LGBT.svg}}
* [[Affectional orientation]]
* [[Ascribed characteristics]]
* [[Hate crime]]
* [[LGBT]] (Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender)
* [[List of anti-discrimination acts]]
* [[LGBT rights by country or territory]]
* [[Human male sexuality]], including non-western perspectives on sexual orientation
* [[Same-sex marriage]]
* [[Sexual orientation and military service]]
* [[Terminology of homosexuality]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Anders Agmo Functional and dysfunctional sexual behavior Elsevier 2007
*[[Miguel A. De La Torre|De La Torre, Miguel A.]], "Out of the Shadows, Into the Light: Christianity and Homosexuality" Chalice Press, 2009.
*Dynes, Wayne (ed.) "Encyclopedia of Homosexuality."  New York and London, Garland Publishing, 1990.
*Gil Brum, Larry McKane, and Gerry Karp. ''Biology{{ndash}} Exploring Life'', 2nd edition. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. 1994. p.&amp;nbsp;663. (About INAH-3.)
*Sell, Randall L. (December 1997). Defining and measuring sexual orientation: a review. ''Archives of Sexual Behavior'' '''26'''(6) 643-658. ([http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/assault/context/defining.html ''excerpt''])
* Serge Wunsch [http://psychobiologie.ouvaton.org/telechargement/these_comportement_reproduction.pdf PhD thesis about sexual behavior] Paris Sorbonne 2007

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
*[http://www.niquette.com/books/sophmag/h-word.htm "The H-Word"] by Paul Niquette
*[http://www.lifeofalawstudent.com/article.php?story=conlawi41 A law lecture (mp3) on sexual orientation and U.S. constitutional law]
*[http://www.apa.org/pubinfo/answers.html American Psychological Association: Answers to Your Questions About Sexual Orientation and Homosexuality]
* [http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=dn5026 Aspirin changes sexual behaviour of rats]
* [http://msu.edu/~breedsm/pdf/AmateauCommentaryFinalNatNeuro2004.pdf Brain gender: prostaglandins have their say]
*{{cite journal |author=Loraine JA, Ismail AA, Adamopoulos DA, Dove GA |title=Endocrine function in male and female homosexuals |journal=Br Med J |volume=4 |issue=5732 |pages=406–9 |year=1970 |month=November |pmid=5481520 |pmc=1819981 }}
*[http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/etiology.html Etiology] on [[glbtq.com]]
*[http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/index.htm Magnus Hirschfeld Archive of Sexology at the Humboldt University in Berlin]
* [http://www.borngayprocon.org/ Is sexual orientation determined at birth?]
*{{cite journal |author=Sanders BK |title=Sex, drugs and sports: prostaglandins, epitestosterone and sexual development |journal=Med. Hypotheses |volume=69 |issue=4 |pages=829–35 |year=2007 |pmid=17382481 |doi=10.1016/j.mehy.2006.12.058 }}
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/rcip//sbh.html Survivor bashing - bias motivated hate crimes]
*[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/03/09/60minutes/main1385230.shtml The Science Of Sexual Orientation]
*[http://www.sexedlibrary.org The SexEdLibrary]

{{Template group
|list =
{{Sex}}
{{Sexual identities}}
{{LGBT|state=collapsed|orientation=expanded}}
{{Sexual ethics}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sexual Orientation}}
[[Category:Interpersonal relationships]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation| ]]

[[ar:توجه جنسي]]
[[bn:যৌন প্রবৃত্তি]]
[[be:Сексуальная арыентацыя]]
[[br:Tuadur reizhel]]
[[bg:Сексуална ориентация]]
[[ca:Orientació sexual]]
[[cs:Sexuální orientace]]
[[cy:Cyfeiriadedd rhywiol]]
[[da:Seksuel orientering]]
[[de:Sexuelle Orientierung]]
[[et:Seksuaalne orientatsioon]]
[[es:Orientación sexual]]
[[fa:گرایش جنسی]]
[[fr:Orientation sexuelle]]
[[gl:Orientación sexual]]
[[ko:성적 지향]]
[[hr:Seksualna orijentacija]]
[[id:Orientasi seksual]]
[[it:Orientamento sessuale]]
[[he:נטייה מינית]]
[[hu:Szexuális irányultság]]
[[mk:Сексуална ориентација]]
[[mn:Бэлгийн чиг хандлага]]
[[nl:Seksuele geaardheid]]
[[ja:性的指向]]
[[no:Seksuell orientering]]
[[uz:Jinsiy moyillik]]
[[pl:Orientacja seksualna]]
[[pt:Orientação sexual]]
[[ro:Orientare sexuală]]
[[ru:Сексуальная ориентация]]
[[si:ලිංගික දිශානතිය]]
[[simple:Sexual orientation]]
[[sk:Sexuálna orientácia]]
[[sl:Spolna usmerjenost]]
[[sr:Сексуална оријентација]]
[[sh:Seksualna orijentacija]]
[[fi:Seksuaalinen suuntautuminen]]
[[sv:Sexuell läggning]]
[[tr:Cinsel yönelim]]
[[vi:Thiên hướng tình dục]]
[[yi:סעקסואלער אריענטאציע]]
[[zh:性取向]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>