<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20080820124457|233103342" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1913571" pageid="1913571" ns="0" title="Gay literature"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-10-06T09:10:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Articleissues|article=1|expert=August 2007|expand=April 2007|rewrite=August 2007}}
'''LGBT literature''' is an all encompassing term for [[literature]] produced by people who are [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]] or [[transgender]], or which involves [[fictional character|characters]], [[Plot (narrative)|plot]] lines or themes concerning this community. 

{{Cquote2|In a historical sense, literature as we understand it is a fairly new innovation, and the current concept of [[homosexuality]] is even fresher from the cultural oven. It's no great surprise, then, that gay literature ­­­­­­­­&amp;mdash; or even gay characters in literature ­­­­&amp;mdash; are so relatively new as to still be shiny. | Kilian Meloy | [http://www.afterelton.com/print/2007/9/groundbreakinggaycharacters "Influential Gay Characters in Literature" from AfterElton.com]}}

==Subgenres==
[[Lesbian literature]], [[Gay pulp fiction|gay pulp]] and [[gay science fiction]] are genres of LGBT fiction which represent some of the earliest incorporation of these "[[taboo]]" subjects in contemporary literature. Novels like ''[[La Garçonne (novel)|La Garçonne]]'' by [[Victor Margueritte]] (1922) and ''[[The Well of Loneliness]]'' by [[Radclyffe Hall]] (1928) are early examples of books with lesbian themes.

LGBT authors, characters and themes are present in all genres of literature, but the increasing amount of LGBT fiction emerging in recent years has established several (if unofficial) subgenres, including LGBT [[mystery fiction|mystery]], [[horror novel|horror]] and [[romance novel|romance]], as well as [[Gay teen fiction|gay teen]] and [[lesbian teen fiction]] and [[humor handbooks]].

==Awards==
*[[Lambda Literary Award]]
*[[Stonewall Book Award]]

==See also==
*[[Lesbian literature]]
*[[Transgender and transsexual fiction]]
*[[Homosexuality in children's literature]]
*[[Homosexuality in speculative fiction]]
*[[Singapore gay literature]]
*[[List of LGBT writers]]

==Further reading==
*''Pages passed from hand to hand : the hidden tradition of homosexual literature in English from 1748 to 1914'' edited and with an introduction by Mark Mitchell and David Leavitt, Chatto &amp; Windus 1998
*''Homosexuality in Literature, 1890-1930'' by Jeffrey Mayers, Athlone, 1977
*''A History of Gay Literature: The Male Tradition'' by Gregory Woods, Yale University Press, 1999
*''Gaiety Transfigured: Gay Self-Representation in American Literature'' edited by David Bergman, University of Wisconsin Press, 1991
*''Beyond Sex and Romance? : the politics of contemporary lesbian fiction'' edited by Elaine Hutton, Women's Press, 1998. 
*''Lesbian and Gay Writing: An Anthology of Critical Essays'' edited by Mark Lilly, Macmillan, 1990 
*''Love Between Men in English Literature'' by Paul Hammond, Macmillan, 1996
*''The Homosexual as Hero in Contemporary Fiction'' by Stephen Adams, Vision, 1980
*''The Penguin Book of Homosexual Verse'', edited by Stephen Coote, Penguin, 1983
*''Essays on Gay Literature'' edited by Stuart Kellogg, Harrington Park Press, 1983.
*''So You Want to be a Lesbian? a guide for amateurs and professionals,''by Liz Tracey and [[Sydney Pokorny]], St. Martin's/Griffin,  1996.

==External links==
*[http://www.lambdaliterary.org Lambda Literary Foundation - Publishes the Lambda Book Report and the Lambda Literary Awards]
*[http://www.blithe.com Blithe House Quarterly - online journal]
*[http://www.glbtq.com/subject/literature_a-b.html Encyclopedia of Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender and Queer Culture on Gay Literature]
*[http://www.lodestarquarterly.com Lodestar Quarterly — an Online Journal of the Finest Gay, Lesbian, and Queer Literature]
*[http://www.LesbianMysteries.com/ Lesbian Mysteries] features Lesbian Mystery Novels
*[http://www.gayauthors.org/ Gay Authors] Online LGBT Fiction Stories

{{LGBT fiction}}

[[Category:LGBT history]]
[[Category:LGBT literature|*]]
[[Category:Literature by theme|LGBT]]

[[de:Liste von literarischen Werken mit homosexuellem Inhalt]]
[[pl:Literatura gejowska i lesbijska]]
[[pt:Literatura gay]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>