<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20090919094625|314884515" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1913571" pageid="1913571" ns="0" title="Gay literature"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-13T15:09:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Hyakinthos.jpg|thumb|[[Anemoi#West wind (Zephyrus)|Zephyr]] and [[Hyacinth (mythology)|Hyakinthos]]: Greek mythology, which often features homosexuality, is a source for much modern speculative fiction and mythic figures continue to appear in fantasy stories.&lt;ref name="glbtq1-6"&gt;Marchesani, pp.1–6; Joseph Marchesani, ''GLBTQ.com — Encyclopedia of GLBTQ culture'', [http://www.glbtq.com/literature/scifi_fantasy.html "Science fiction and fantasy literature"]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
'''LGBT literature''' is a collective term for [[literature]] produced by and for [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]] and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) communities, or which involves [[fictional character|characters]], [[Plot (narrative)|plot]] lines or themes concerning LGBT communities. 

{{Cquote2|In a historical sense, literature as we understand it is a fairly new innovation, and the current concept of [[homosexuality]] is even fresher from the cultural oven. It's no great surprise, then, that gay literature ­­­­­­­­&amp;mdash; or even gay characters in literature ­­­­&amp;mdash; are so relatively new as to still be shiny. | Kilian Meloy | [http://www.afterelton.com/print/2007/9/groundbreakinggaycharacters "Influential Gay Characters in Literature" from AfterElton.com]}}

==Subgenres==
Lesbian literature, gay pulp and [[gay science fiction]] are genres of LGBT fiction which represent some of the earliest incorporation of these "[[taboo]]" subjects in contemporary literature. Novels like ''[[La Garçonne (novel)|La Garçonne]]'' by [[Victor Margueritte]] (1922) and ''[[The Well of Loneliness]]'' by [[Radclyffe Hall]] (1928) are early examples of books with lesbian themes.

LGBT authors, characters and themes are present in all genres of literature, but the increasing amount of LGBT fiction emerging in recent years has established several (if unofficial) subgenres, including LGBT [[mystery fiction|mystery]], [[horror novel|horror]] and [[romance novel|romance]], as well as [[Gay teen fiction|gay teen]] and [[lesbian teen fiction]].

==LGBT themes in mythology==
Many [[mythologies]] and religious narratives have included stories of sex or romantic affection between figures of the same sex, or feature divine actions that result in changes in gender. These myths have been interpreted as early forms of [[LGBT]] (lesbian, gay, bisexual. transgender) literature, and modern conceptions of sexuality and gender applied to them. 

The status of mythology varies by culture. Myths are generally believed to be literally true within the society that created them and deemed erroneous or fictitious elsewhere. Other cultures may regard myths as containing psychological or archetypal truths. Myths have been used to explain and validate the social institutions of a particular culture,&lt;ref name=Pequigney1&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.glbtq.com/literature/classical_myth.html|title=GLBTQ Enylcopedia, "Classical Mythology" |accessdate=2009-03-20 |last=  Pequigney|first= Joseph|coauthors= |date= 2002|page=1 |publisher=New England Publishing Associates}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as to educate the members of that culture.

==Lesbian literature==
{{main|List of lesbian literature}}
[[File:Godward-In the Days of Sappho-1904.jpg|thumb|[[Sappho]] of [[Lesbos]], depicted in an 1904 painting by [[John William Godward]] gave the term ''[[lesbian]]'' the connotation of erotic desire between women.&lt;ref name="oed"&gt;"Lesbian", [http://dictionary.oed.com/ Oxford English Dictionary], Second Edition, 1989. Retrieved on January 7, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; ]] 
Lesbian literature includes works by [[lesbian]] authors, as well as lesbian-themed works by heterosexual authors. Even works by lesbian writers that do not deal with lesbian themes are still often considered lesbian literature. Works by heterosexual writers which treat lesbian themes only in passing, on the other hand, are not often regarded as lesbian literature. 

The fundamental work of lesbian literature is the poetry of [[Sappho of Lesbos]]. From various ancient writings, historians have gathered that a group of young women were left in Sappho's charge for their instruction or cultural edification.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jeannette Howard Foster|Foster, Jeannette H.]] (1985). ''Sex Variant Women in Literature'', Naiad Press. ISBN 0-930044-65-7, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Not much of Sappho's poetry remains, but that which does demonstrates the topics she wrote about: women's daily lives, their relationships, and rituals. She focused on the beauty of women and proclaimed her love for girls.&lt;ref&gt;Aldrich, Robert, ed. (2006). ''Gay Life and Culture: A World History'', Thames &amp; Hudson, Ltd. ISBN 0-7893-1511-4, p. 47–49.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Contemporary lesbian literature is centered around several small, exclusively lesbian presses, as well as online fandoms. Certain works have established historical or artistic importance. Works of lesbian literature are sometimes difficult to identify if they are not published by small lesbian presses due to a general lack of promotion of lesbian themes by mainstream publishers. An exhaustive list of works cannot be provided here, but key works in different genres are listed.

==Gay pulp==
[[Gay pulp fiction]] or gay pulps, refers to printed works, primarily fiction, that include references to male [[homosexuality]], specifically male [[gay sex]], and that are cheaply produced, typically in [[paperback book]]s made of wood pulp paper; [[lesbian pulp fiction]] is similar work about women.  [[Michael Bronski]], the editor of an anthology of gay pulp writing, notes in his introduction, "Gay pulp is not an exact term, and it is used somewhat loosely to refer to a variety of books that had very different origins and markets"&lt;ref&gt;Bronski, Michael, ed.  ''Pulp Friction:  Uncovering the Golden Age of Gay Male Pulps''.  New York:  St. Martin's Griffin, 2003, page 2.&lt;/ref&gt;  People often use the term to refer to the "classic" gay pulps that were produced before about 1970, but it may also be used to refer to the gay erotica or pornography in paperback book or digest magazine form produced since that date.

==Science fiction==
[[Image:carmilla.jpg|thumb|Illustration by [[D. H. Friston]] that accompanied the first publication of lesbian vampire novella ''Carmilla'' by [[Sheridan Le Fanu]] in ''The Dark Blue'' magazine in 1872. ''Carmilla'' is an early work depicting gay characters as morally impure.&lt;ref&gt;Collected in ''[[In a Glass Darkly]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Eric Garber &amp; Lyn Paleo ''[[Uranian Worlds]]: A Guide to Alternative Sexuality in Science Fiction, Fantasy, and Horror'' (1983), G K Hall, ISBN 978-0816118328, "Carmilla" p. 76&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Homosexuality in speculative fiction]] refers to the incorporation of [[homosexual]] themes into [[science fiction]], [[fantasy]], [[horror fiction]] and related genres which together constitute [[speculative fiction]] (SF).{{ref label|Note1|a|a}} Such elements may include a [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]] or [[transsexual]] ([[LGBT]]) character as the protagonist or a major character, or exploration of varieties of [[human sexual behavior|sexual experience]] that deviate from the conventional.

Science fiction and fantasy have traditionally been [[puritanical]] genres aimed at a male readership, and can be more restricted than non-genre [[literature]] by their [[genre convention|conventions]] of characterisation and the effect that these conventions have on depictions of sexuality and gender. However, speculative fiction also gives authors and readers the freedom to imagine societies that are different from real-life cultures. This freedom makes speculative fiction a useful means of examining sexual bias, by forcing the reader to reconsider his or her [[heteronormative]] cultural assumptions. It has also been claimed that LGBT readers identify strongly with the [[mutants]], [[Extraterrestrials in fiction|aliens]], and other [[outsider]] characters found in speculative fiction.

==Comics==
[[LGBT themes in comics]] is a relatively new concept, as [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]] and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) themes and [[fictional character|characters]] were historically omitted intentionally from the content of [[comic book]]s and their [[comic strip]] predecessors, due to either censorship or the perception that comics were for children.&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Yellow Kid]]'', first serialized in 1895, is considered the "first newspaper comic strip," though "the mechanics of comic strips were in use well before the ''Kid''{{'s}} debut in illustrated magazines." {{citation|last=Wood|first=Mary|title=Origins of the Kid|url=http://xroads.virginia.edu/~MA04/wood/ykid/illustrated.htm|publisher=xroads.virginia.edu|date=2004-02-02|accessdate=2009-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; With any mention of [[homosexuality]] in mainstream United States comics forbidden by the [[Comics Code Authority]] (CCA) until 1989,&lt;ref name="Nyberg 1998"&gt;{{citation |last=Nyberg |first=Amy Kiste |title=Seal of Approval: The History of the Comics Code |publisher=University Press of Mississippi |date=1998 |location=Jackson |pages=143, 175–176 |isbn=087805975X}}&lt;/ref&gt; earlier attempts at exploring these issues in the US took the form of subtle hints or [[subtext]] regarding a character's sexual orientation.&lt;ref name="Applegate"&gt;{{citation|last=Applegate |first=David |title=''Coming Out in the Comic Strips''|url=http://cagle.msnbc.com/hogan/features/out/out.asp|publisher=[[MSNBC]]|accessdate=2009-03-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; LGBT themes were tackled earlier in [[underground comics]] from the early 1970s onward. Independently published one-off comic books and series, often produced by gay creators and featuring autobiographical storylines, tackled political issues of interest to LGBT readers.

[[Comic strips]] have also dealt in subtext and innuendo, their wide distribution in newspapers limiting their inclusion of controversial material. The first openly gay characters appeared in prominent strips in the late 1970s; representation of LGBT issues in these titles causes vociferous reaction, both praise and condemnation, to the present day. Comic strips aimed at LGBT audiences are also syndicated in gay- and lesbian-targeted magazines and comics have been created to educate people about LGBT-related issues and to influence real-world politics, with their format and distribution allowing them to transmit messages more subtle, complex, and positive than typical education material. Portrayal of LGBT themes in comics is recognized by several notable awards, including the [[Gaylactic Spectrum Award]] and [[GLAAD Media Awards]] for outstanding comic book and comic strip.

Since the 1990s LGBT themes have become more common in mainstream US comics, including in a number of titles in which a gay character is the star. European comics have been more inclusive from an earlier date. The lack of censorship, and greater acceptance of comics as a medium of adult entertainment led to less controversy about the representation of LGBT characters. The popular Japanese [[manga]] tradition has included genres of girls' comics that feature homosexual relationships since the 1970s, in the form of ''[[yaoi]]'' and ''[[yuri]]''. These works are often extremely romantic and include archetypal characters that often are not identified as gay. Since the Japanese "gay boom" of the 1990s, a body of manga by queer creators aimed at LGBT customers has been produced, which have more realistic and autobiographical themes. [[Hentai|Pornographic manga]] also often includes sexualised depictions of lesbians and intersex people. [[Queer theory|Queer theorist]]s have noted that LGBT characters in mainstream comic books are usually shown as assimilated into heterosexual society, whereas in alternative comics the diversity and uniqueness of LGBT culture is emphasized.

==Transgender and transsexual fiction==
[[Transgender and transsexual fiction|Transgender- and transsexual-centric fiction]] is a rare subset of LGBT literature. Most books published by and about [[transgender]] and [[transsexualism|transsexual]] people are [[non-fiction]]: [[autobiography|autobiographies]], critiques or general [[LGBT]] or [[queer studies]] texts.

==Awards==
*[[Lambda Literary Award]]
*[[Stonewall Book Award]]

==See also==
{{portal|LGBT|Portal LGBT.svg}}
{{Literature portal}}
* [[Homosexuality in children's literature]]
* [[Singapore gay literature]]
* [[List of LGBT writers]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*''Pages Passed from Hand to Hand: The Hidden Tradition of Homosexual Literature in English from 1748 to 1914'' edited and with an introduction by Mark Mitchell and David Leavitt, Chatto &amp; Windus 1998
*''Homosexuality in Literature, 1890-1930'' by Jeffrey Mayers, Athlone, 1977
*''A History of Gay Literature: The Male Tradition'' by Gregory Woods, Yale University Press, 1999
*''Gaiety Transfigured: Gay Self-Representation in American Literature'' edited by David Bergman, University of Wisconsin Press, 1991
*''Beyond Sex and Romance?: The Politics of Contemporary Lesbian Fiction'' edited by Elaine Hutton, Women's Press, 1998. 
*''Lesbian and Gay Writing: An Anthology of Critical Essays'' edited by Mark Lilly, Macmillan, 1990 
*''Love Between Men in English Literature'' by Paul Hammond, Macmillan, 1996
*''The Homosexual as Hero in Contemporary Fiction'' by Stephen Adams, Vision, 1980
*''The Penguin Book of Homosexual Verse'' edited by Stephen Coote, Penguin, 1983
*''Essays on Gay Literature'' edited by Stuart Kellogg, Harrington Park Press, 1983.

==External links==
*[http://www.lambdaliterary.org Lambda Literary Foundation - Publishes the Lambda Book Report and the Lambda Literary Awards]
*[http://www.blithe.com Blithe House Quarterly - online journal]
*[http://www.glbtq.com/subject/literature_a-b.html Encyclopedia of Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender and Queer Culture on Gay Literature]
*[http://www.lodestarquarterly.com Lodestar Quarterly — an Online Journal of the Finest Gay, Lesbian, and Queer Literature]
*[http://www.LesbianMysteries.com/ Lesbian Mysteries] features Lesbian Mystery Novels
*[http://www.gayauthors.org/ Gay Authors] Online LGBT Fiction Stories

{{LGBT fiction}}

[[Category:LGBT history]]
[[Category:LGBT literature| ]]
[[Category:Literature by theme|LGBT]]


{{LGBT-stub}}

[[de:Liste von literarischen Werken mit homosexuellem Inhalt]]
[[pl:Literatura gejowska i lesbijska]]
[[pt:Literatura gay]]
[[zh:LGBT文學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>