<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20120912084303|511980496" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1913571" pageid="1913571" ns="0" title="Gay literature"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-10-22T16:51:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Hyakinthos.jpg|thumb|[[Anemoi#West wind (Zephyrus)|Zephyr]] and [[Hyacinth (mythology)|Hyakinthos]]: Greek mythology, which often features homosexuality, is a source for much modern speculative fiction and mythic figures continue to appear in fantasy stories.&lt;ref name="glbtq1-6"&gt;Marchesani, pp.1–6; Joseph Marchesani, ''GLBTQ.com — Encyclopedia of GLBTQ culture'', [http://www.glbtq.com/literature/scifi_fantasy.html "Science fiction and fantasy literature"]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
'''Gay literature''' is a collective term for [[literature]] produced by or for the [[LGBT community]], or which involves [[fictional character|characters]], [[Plot (narrative)|plot]] lines or themes portraying male homosexual behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=A History of Gay Literature: The Male Tradition |author = Gregory Woods |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3rEJ9hpvwlcC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=Ng3lMNsFiH&amp;dq=gay%20literature&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Anthology of gay literature |author=Byrne R. S. Fone |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=HTFZTX3V7D8C&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=W_cnoqvsr2&amp;dq=gay%20literature&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |quote=This anthology offers a chronological survey of writing that represents, interprets, and constructs the experience of love, friendship, intimacy, and desire between men over time--that is, what most readers would call gay male literature.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Cquote2|In a historical sense, literature as we understand it is a fairly new innovation, and the current concept of [[homosexuality]] is even fresher from the cultural oven. It's no great surprise, then, that gay literature — or even gay characters in literature — are so relatively new as to still be shiny. | Kilian Meloy | [http://www.afterelton.com/print/2007/9/groundbreakinggaycharacters "Influential Gay Characters in Literature" from AfterElton.com]}}

==Overview and History==

Because of the frequent persecution or opposition to homosexuality in many world cultures throughout history, lgbt individuals have often turned to literature as a source of validation, understanding, and beautification of same-sex attraction. 

Themes of love between individuals of the same gender can be found in a variety of ancient texts throughout the world. The Ancient Greeks, in particular, explored the theme on a variety of different levels in such works as Plato's ''Symposium''.

=== Twentieth Century ===
The 20th century British author E.M. Forster earned a prominent reputation as a novelist while concealing his own homosexuality from the broader British public. In 1913-1914, he privately penned ''Maurice'', a bildungsroman that follows a young, upper-middle-class gentlemen through the self-discovery of his own attraction to other men, two relationships, and his interactions with an often uncomprehending or hostile society. The book is notable for its affirming tone and happy ending. "A happy ending was imperative," wrote Forster, "...I was determined that in fiction anyway, two men should fall in love and remain in it for the ever and ever that fiction allows.... Happiness is its keynote."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Forster|first=Edward Morgan|title=Maurice|year=1971|publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Company|location=500 Fifth Ave., New York, NY 10110|isbn=0-393-31032-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book was not published until 1971, after Forster's death.

By the twentieth century, discussion of homosexuality became more open and society's understanding of it evolved. A number of novels with explicitly gay themes and characters began to appear in the domain of mainstream or art literature. Notables authors include James Baldwin, Christopher Isherwood, Edmund White, Yukio Mishima, and nobel prize-winner André Gide.

==Subgenres==
Gay pulp and [[gay science fiction]] are genres of gay fiction that represent some of the earliest incorporation of this "[[taboo]]" subject in contemporary literature.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

Gay authors, characters and themes are present in all genres of literature, but the increasing amount of gay fiction emerging in recent years has established several (if unofficial) subgenres, including gay [[mystery fiction|mystery]], [[horror novel|horror]] and [[romance novel|romance]], as well as [[gay male teen fiction|gay teen]].

==Gay themes in mythology==
Many [[mythologies]] and religious narratives have included stories of sex or romantic affection between men, or feature divine actions that result in changes in gender. These myths have been interpreted as early forms of gay literature.

The status of mythology varies by culture. Myths are generally believed to be literally true within the society that created them and deemed erroneous or fictitious elsewhere. Other cultures may regard myths as containing psychological or archetypal truths. Myths have been used to explain and validate the social institutions of a particular culture,&lt;ref name=Pequigney1&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.glbtq.com/literature/classical_myth.html|title=GLBTQ Enylcopedia, "Classical Mythology" |accessdate=2009-03-20 |last=  Pequigney|first= Joseph|coauthors= |year= 2002|page=1 |publisher=New England Publishing Associates}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as to educate the members of that culture.

==Gay pulp==
[[Gay male pulp fiction|Gay pulp fiction]] or gay pulps, refers to printed works, primarily fiction, that include references to male [[homosexuality]], specifically male [[gay sex]], and that are cheaply produced, typically in [[paperback book]]s made of wood pulp paper; [[lesbian pulp fiction]] is similar work about women.  [[Michael Bronski]], the editor of an anthology of gay pulp writing, notes in his introduction, "Gay pulp is not an exact term, and it is used somewhat loosely to refer to a variety of books that had very different origins and markets"&lt;ref&gt;Bronski, Michael, ed.  ''Pulp Friction:  Uncovering the Golden Age of Gay Male Pulps''.  New York:  St. Martin's Griffin, 2003, page 2.&lt;/ref&gt;  People often use the term to refer to the "classic" gay pulps that were produced before about 1970, but it may also be used to refer to the gay erotica or pornography in [[paperback]] [[book]] or [[digest magazine]] form produced since that date.

==Science fiction==
[[File:carmilla.jpg|thumb|Illustration by [[D. H. Friston]] that accompanied the first publication of lesbian vampire novella ''Carmilla'' by [[Sheridan Le Fanu]] in ''The Dark Blue'' magazine in 1872. ''Carmilla'' is an early work depicting gay characters as morally impure.&lt;ref&gt;Collected in ''[[In a Glass Darkly]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Eric Garber &amp; Lyn Paleo ''[[Uranian Worlds]]: A Guide to Alternative Sexuality in Science Fiction, Fantasy, and Horror'' (1983), G K Hall, ISBN 978-0-8161-1832-8, "Carmilla" p. 76&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Homosexuality in speculative fiction]] refers to the incorporation of [[homosexual]] themes into [[science fiction]], [[fantasy]], [[horror fiction]] and related genres which together constitute [[speculative fiction]] (SF).{{Ref label|Note1|a|a}} Such elements may include a [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]] or [[transsexual]] ([[LGBT]]) character as the protagonist or a major character, or exploration of varieties of [[human sexual behavior|sexual experience]] that deviate from the conventional.

Science fiction and fantasy have traditionally been [[puritanical]] genres aimed at a male readership, and can be more restricted than non-genre [[literature]] by their [[genre convention|conventions]] of characterisation and the effect that these conventions have on depictions of sexuality and gender. However, speculative fiction also gives authors and readers the freedom to imagine societies that are different from real-life cultures. This freedom makes speculative fiction a useful means of examining sexual bias, by forcing the reader to reconsider his or her [[heteronormative]] cultural assumptions. It has also been claimed that LGBT readers identify strongly with the [[mutants]], [[Extraterrestrials in fiction|aliens]], and other outsider characters found in speculative fiction.{{citation needed|date=March 2011}}

==Comics==
[[LGBT themes in comics]] is a relatively new concept, as [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]] and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) themes and [[fictional character|characters]] were historically omitted intentionally from the content of [[comic book]]s and their [[comic strip]] predecessors, due to either censorship or the perception that comics were for children.&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Yellow Kid]]'', first serialized in 1895, is considered the "first newspaper comic strip," though "the mechanics of comic strips were in use well before the ''Kid''{{'s}} debut in illustrated magazines." {{citation|last=Wood|first=Mary|title=Origins of the Kid|url=http://xroads.virginia.edu/~MA04/wood/ykid/illustrated.htm|publisher=xroads.virginia.edu|date=2004-02-02|accessdate=2009-03-18|postscript=&lt;!--none--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; With any mention of [[homosexuality]] in mainstream United States comics forbidden by the [[Comics Code Authority]] (CCA) until 1989,&lt;ref name="Nyberg 1998"&gt;{{citation |last=Nyberg |first=Amy Kiste |title=Seal of Approval: The History of the Comics Code |publisher=University Press of Mississippi |year=1998 |location=Jackson |pages=143, 175–176 |isbn=0-87805-975-X |postscript=&lt;!--none--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; earlier attempts at exploring these issues in the US took the form of subtle hints or [[subtext]] regarding a character's sexual orientation.&lt;ref name="Applegate"&gt;{{citation|last=Applegate |first=David |title=''Coming Out in the Comic Strips''|url=http://cagle.msnbc.com/hogan/features/out/out.asp|publisher=[[MSNBC]]|accessdate=2009-03-29|postscript=&lt;!--none--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; LGBT themes were tackled earlier in [[underground comics]] from the early 1970s onward. Independently published one-off comic books and series, often produced by gay creators and featuring autobiographical storylines, tackled political issues of interest to LGBT readers.

[[Comic strips]] have also dealt in subtext and innuendo, their wide distribution in newspapers limiting their inclusion of controversial material. The first openly gay characters appeared in prominent strips in the late 1970s; representation of LGBT issues in these titles causes vociferous reaction, both praise and condemnation, to the present day. Comic strips aimed at LGBT audiences are also syndicated in gay- and lesbian-targeted magazines and comics have been created to educate people about LGBT-related issues and to influence real-world politics, with their format and distribution allowing them to transmit messages more subtle, complex, and positive than typical education material. Portrayal of LGBT themes in comics is recognized by several notable awards, including the [[Gaylactic Spectrum Award]] and [[GLAAD Media Awards]] for outstanding comic book and comic strip.

Since the 1990s LGBT themes have become more common in mainstream US comics, including in a number of titles in which a gay character is the star. European comics have been more inclusive from an earlier date. The lack of censorship, and greater acceptance of comics as a medium of adult entertainment led to less controversy about the representation of LGBT characters. The popular Japanese [[manga]] tradition has included genres of girls' comics that feature homosexual relationships since the 1970s, in the form of ''[[yaoi]]'' and ''[[yuri (genre)|yuri]]''. These works are often extremely romantic and include archetypal characters that often are not identified as gay. Since the Japanese "gay boom" of the 1990s, a body of manga aimed at LGBT customers has been produced, which have more realistic and autobiographical themes. [[Hentai|Pornographic manga]] also often includes sexualised depictions of lesbians and intersex people. [[Queer theory|Queer theorist]]s{{who|date=October 2011}} have noted that LGBT characters in mainstream comic books are usually shown as assimilated into heterosexual society, whereas in alternative comics the diversity and uniqueness of LGBT culture is emphasized.

==Awards==
*[[Lambda Literary Award]]
*[[Stonewall Book Award]]
*[[Dayne Ogilvie Prize]]

==See also==
{{Portal|LGBT|Literature}}
* [[Lesbian fiction]]
* [[List of books portraying sexual relations between women]]
* [[List of poetry portraying sexual relations between women]]
* [[Homosexuality in children's literature]]
* [[Singapore gay literature]]
* [[List of LGBT writers]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*''Pages Passed from Hand to Hand: The Hidden Tradition of Homosexual Literature in English from 1748 to 1914'' edited and with an introduction by Mark Mitchell and David Leavitt, Chatto &amp; Windus 1998
*''Homosexuality in Literature, 1890–1930'' by Jeffrey Mayers, Athlone, 1977
*''A History of Gay Literature: The Male Tradition'' by Gregory Woods, Yale University Press, 1999
*''Gaiety Transfigured: Gay Self-Representation in American Literature'' edited by David Bergman, University of Wisconsin Press, 1991
*''Beyond Sex and Romance?: The Politics of Contemporary Lesbian Fiction'' edited by Elaine Hutton, Women's Press, 1998.
*''Lesbian and Gay Writing: An Anthology of Critical Essays'' edited by Mark Lilly, Macmillan, 1990
*''Love Between Men in English Literature'' by Paul Hammond, Macmillan, 1996
*''The Homosexual as Hero in Contemporary Fiction'' by Stephen Adams, Vision, 1980
*''The Penguin Book of Homosexual Verse'' edited by Stephen Coote, Penguin, 1983
*''Essays on Gay Literature'' edited by Stuart Kellogg, Harrington Park Press, 1983.

==External links==
*[http://www.lambdaliterary.org Lambda Literary Foundation – Publishes the Lambda Book Report and the Lambda Literary Awards]
*[http://www.blithe.com Blithe House Quarterly – online journal]
*[http://www.glbtq.com/subject/literature_a-b.html Encyclopedia of Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender and Queer Culture on Gay Literature]
*[http://www.nuwinepress.com NuWine Press - Gay Christian Book Publisher featuring fresh perspectives on the Christian faith]
*[http://www.lodestarquarterly.com Lodestar Quarterly — an Online Journal of the Finest Gay, Lesbian, and Queer Literature]
*[http://www.LesbianMysteries.com/ Lesbian Mysteries] features Lesbian Mystery Novels
*[http://www.gayauthors.org/ Gay Authors] Online LGBT Fiction Stories
*[http://www.gaystheword.co.uk/ Gay's the Word] UK LGBTQ Specialist Bookshop

{{LGBT fiction}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lgbt Literature}}
[[Category:LGBT history]]
[[Category:LGBT literature| ]]
[[Category:Literature by theme|LGBT]]
[[Category:Gay (male) literature]]

[[de:Liste literarischer Werke mit homosexuellem Inhalt]]
[[es:Literatura homosexual]]
[[pl:Literatura gejowska i lesbijska]]
[[pt:Literatura gay]]
[[tr:Eşcinsel edebiyatı]]
[[zh:LGBT文學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>