<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20190905035630|914093883" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="146577" pageid="146577" ns="0" title="Romer v. Evans"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-09-23T23:54:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2015}}
{{Infobox SCOTUS case
  |Litigants=Romer v. Evans
  |ArgueDate=October 10
  |ArgueYear=1995
  |DecideDate=May 20
  |DecideYear=1996
  |FullName=Roy Romer, Governor of Colorado, et al. v. Richard G. Evans, et al.
  |USVol=517
  |USPage=620
  |ParallelCitations=116 S. Ct. 1620; 134 [[L. Ed. 2d]] 855; 1996 [[U.S. LEXIS]] 3245; 64 U.S.L.W. 4353; 70 Fair Empl. Prac. Cas. ([[Bloomberg BNA|BNA]]) 1180; 68 Empl. Prac. Dec. ([[CCH (company)|CCH]]) ¶ 44,013; 96 Cal. Daily Op. Service 3509; 96 Daily Journal DAR 5730; 9 Fla. L. Weekly Fed. S 607
  |Prior=Preliminary injunction granted to plaintiffs, 1993 [[Westlaw|WL]] 19678 (Colo. Dist.Ct. 1993); affirmed, 854 [[P.2d]] [https://law.justia.com/cases/colorado/supreme-court/1993/93sa17-0.html 1270] (Colo. 1993); certiorari denied, {{ussc|510|959|1993|el=no}}; injunction made permanent, 1993 WL 518586 (Colo. Dist.Ct. 1993); affirmed, 882 [[P.2d]] [https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/1297252/evans-v-romer/ 1335] (Colo. 1994); certiorari granted, {{ussc|513|1146|1995|el=no}}
  |Subsequent=None
  |Holding=An amendment to the Colorado Constitution that prevents protected status under the law for homosexuals or bisexuals was struck down because it was not rationally related to a legitimate state interest. Supreme Court of Colorado affirmed.
  |Majority=Kennedy
  |JoinMajority=Stevens, O'Connor, Souter, Ginsburg, Breyer
  |Dissent=Scalia
  |JoinDissent=Rehnquist, Thomas
  |LawsApplied=[[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|U.S. Const. amend. XIV]]; Colo. Const. art. II, § 30b
}}
'''''Romer v. Evans''''', 517 U.S. 620 (1996),&lt;ref name=opinion&gt;{{ussc|name=Romer v. Evans|volume=517|page=620|pin=|year=1996 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[List of landmark court decisions in the United States|landmark]] [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] case dealing with [[sexual orientation]] and state laws.  It was the first Supreme Court case to address [[LGBT rights in the United States|gay rights]] since ''[[Bowers v. Hardwick]]'' (1986),&lt;ref name=Bowers&gt;{{ussc|name=Bowers v. Hardwick|volume=478|page=186|pin=|year=1986}}.&lt;/ref&gt; when the Court had held that [[Sodomy laws in the United States|laws criminalizing sodomy]] were constitutional.&lt;ref name="umkc"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://law2.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/conlaw/gayrights.htm|title=Gay Rights and the Constitution|last=Linder|first=Doug|publisher=University of Missouri-Kansas City|accessdate=August 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Court ruled in a 6–3 decision that a state constitutional amendment in Colorado preventing protected status based upon homosexuality or bisexuality did not satisfy the [[Equal Protection Clause]].&lt;ref name=opinion/&gt; The majority opinion in ''Romer'' stated that the amendment lacked "a rational relationship to legitimate state interests", and the dissent stated that the majority "evidently agrees that 'rational basis'—the normal test for compliance with the Equal Protection Clause—is the governing standard".&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Wald |first1= Kenneth |last2= Calhoun-Brown |first2= Allison |last-author-amp= yes |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=Jy8EAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA347 |title= Religion and Politics in the United States |page= 347 |publisher= Rowman &amp; Littlefield |year= 2014 |via= [[Google Books]] }}.&lt;/ref&gt; The state constitutional amendment failed [[rational basis review]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Hames |first1= Joanne |last2= Ekern |first2= Yvonne |last-author-amp= yes |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=OGoxeXgx740C&amp;pg=PA215 |title= Constitutional Law: Principles and Practice |page= 215 |publisher= Cengage Learning |year= 2012 |via= Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Smith |first= Miriam |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=gnyQAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA88 |title= Political Institutions and Lesbian and Gay Rights in the United States and Canada |page= 88 |publisher= Routledge |year= 2008 |via= Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Schultz |first= David |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=f7m713xwK58C&amp;pg=PA629 |title= Encyclopedia of the United States Constitution |page= 629 |publisher= Infobase Publishing |year= 2009 |via= Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Bolick |first= Clint |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=jEGXx5XwMHUC&amp;pg=PA80 |title= David's Hammer: The Case for an Activist Judiciary |page= 80 |publisher= Cato Institute |year= 2007 |via= Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The decision in ''Romer'' set the stage for ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'' (2003),&lt;ref name=Lawrence&gt;{{ussc|name=Lawrence v. Texas|539|558|2003}}.&lt;/ref&gt; where the Court overruled its decision in ''Bowers'';&lt;ref name="umkc" /&gt; for the Supreme Court ruling striking down Section 3 of the [[Defense of Marriage Act]] in ''[[United States v. Windsor]]'' (2013); and for the Court's ruling striking down state bans on same-sex marriage in ''[[Obergefell v. Hodges]]'' (2015). Justice [[Anthony Kennedy]] authored all four opinions, and was joined by Justices [[Ruth Bader Ginsburg|Ginsburg]] and [[Stephen Breyer|Breyer]] in every one.

==Passage of Amendment 2==

In 1992, Colorado voters approved by [[initiative]] an amendment to the [[Colorado]] state constitution (Amendment 2) that would have prevented any city, town, or county in the state from taking any legislative, executive, or judicial action to recognize homosexuals or bisexuals as a [[protected class]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://lawdigitalcommons.bc.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1986&amp;context=bclr | title =Colorado's Amendment 2 and Homosexuals' Right to Equal Protection of the Law |last1= Zamansky |first= Stephen |journal= [[Boston College Law Review]] |volume= 35 |issue= 1 |pages= 221–258 |date= December 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt; The amendment stated:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Neither the State of Colorado, through any of its branches or departments, nor any of its agencies, political subdivisions, municipalities or school districts, shall enact, adopt or enforce any statute, regulation, ordinance or policy whereby homosexual, lesbian or bisexual orientation, conduct, practices or relationships shall constitute or otherwise be the basis of or entitle any person or class of persons to have or claim any minority status, quota preferences, protected status or claim of discrimination. This Section of the Constitution shall be in all respects self-executing.&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

That amendment was approved by a vote of 53% to 47%.&lt;ref name=CSM&gt;{{cite news |last= Gascoyne |first= Stephen |url= http://m.csmonitor.com/1992/1203/03031.html |title= Anti-Gay-Rights Law Leads To Colorado Boycott Calls |work= [[The Christian Science Monitor]] |date= December 3, 1992}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to public opinion surveys, Coloradans strongly opposed discrimination based upon sexual orientation, but at the same time they opposed [[affirmative action]] based upon sexual orientation, and the latter concern is what led to the adoption of Amendment 2.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Turner |first= William |url= http://hosted.law.wisc.edu/wjlgs/issues/2007-spring/turnernobanner.pdf |title= The Gay Rights State: Wisconsin's Pioneering Legislation to Prohibit Discrimination Based on Sexual Orientation |format= PDF |journal= Wisconsin Women's Law Journal |volume= 22 |pages= 91, 104 |date= 2007 |url-status= dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100611165520/http://hosted.law.wisc.edu/wjlgs/issues/2007-spring/turnernobanner.pdf |archivedate= June 11, 2010 |df= mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gerstmann&gt;{{cite book |last=Gerstmann |first=Evan |title=The Constitutional Underclass: Gays, Lesbians, and the Failure of Class-Based Equal Protection |pages=[https://archive.org/details/constitutionalun00gers_0/page/100 100–102, 135–138] |publisher=University of Chicago Press |year=1999 |isbn=0226288595 |url=https://archive.org/details/constitutionalun00gers_0/page/100 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The governor of Colorado, [[Roy Romer]], opposed the measure, but also opposed retaliatory boycotts against his state.&lt;ref name=CSM /&gt;

==Proceedings in state court==
Richard G. Evans, a gay man who worked for Denver mayor [[Wellington Webb]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Dunlap |first1=David W. |title=The Gay Rights Ruling: In Colorado;Ruling Signals More Fights To Come |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/21/us/the-gay-rights-ruling-in-colorado-ruling-signals-more-fights-to-come.html |accessdate=April 11, 2016 |work=New York Times |date=May 21, 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as other individuals and three Colorado municipalities, brought suit to enjoin the amendment. A former [[Colorado Supreme Court]] justice, [[Jean Dubofsky]], was the lead attorney. A state trial court issued a permanent injunction against the amendment, and upon appeal, the [[Colorado Supreme Court]] ruled that the amendment was subject to "[[strict scrutiny]]" under the [[Equal Protection Clause]] of the [[United States Constitution|federal Constitution]].&lt;ref name=Evans1&gt;{{cite court |litigants= Evans v. Romer |vol=854 |reporter=P.2d |opinion=1270 |pinpoint= |court=Colo. |date=1993|url=https://law.justia.com/cases/colorado/supreme-court/1993/93sa17-0.html |accessdate=2018-05-11 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://lcrm.lib.unc.edu/blog/index.php/tag/amendment-2/ |title= Archive for 'Amendment 2' On This Day: Romer v. Evans |last1= Shay |first1= Alison |publisher= [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]] |date= May 20, 2012 |url-status= dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20160424202108/https://lcrm.lib.unc.edu/blog/index.php/tag/amendment-2/ |archivedate= April 24, 2016 |df= mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The state trial court, upon [[Remand (court procedure)|remand]], concluded that the amendment could not pass strict scrutiny, which the Colorado Supreme Court agreed with upon review.&lt;ref name=Evans2&gt;{{cite court |litigants= Evans v. Romer |vol=882 |reporter=P.2d |opinion=1335 |pinpoint= |court=Colo.  |date=1994 |url=https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/1297252/evans-v-romer/ |accessdate=2018-05-11 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both times, the Colorado Supreme Court rendered 2–1 decisions.&lt;ref name=Evans1 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Evans2 /&gt;

The state supreme court held that Amendment 2 infringed on the fundamental right of gays to participate equally in the political process.  Regarding the trial court's finding that homosexuals were not a [[suspect class]], the Colorado Supreme Court said: "This ruling has not been appealed and thus, we do not address it."

The majority of the Colorado Supreme Court acknowledged that Amendment 2 would not affect Colorado law that generally protects people from discrimination:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Colorado law currently proscribes discrimination against persons who are not suspect classes. ... Of course Amendment 2 is not intended to have any effect on this legislation, but seeks only to prevent the adoption of anti-discrimination laws intended to protect gays, lesbians, and bisexuals.&lt;ref name=Evans2 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Walsh |first= Kevin |title= Throwing Stones: Rational Basis Review Triumphs over Homophobia |journal= Seton Hall Law Review |volume= 27 |page= 1064 |year= 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The dissenting justice on the Colorado Supreme Court argued that neither a suspect class nor a fundamental right was involved in the case, and thus he would have applied a rational basis test instead of strict scrutiny.&lt;ref name=Evans2 /&gt;

==U.S. Supreme Court ruling==
The case was argued on October 10, 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=nO093wNz1PoC&amp;pg=PT286&amp;lpg=PT286 |title= The Oxford Guide to United States Supreme Court Decisions |last= Hall |first= Kermit |publisher= [[Oxford University Press]] |page= 286 |isbn= 978-0195379396 |year= 2009 |via= Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; On May 20, 1996, the court ruled 6–3 that Colorado's Amendment 2 was unconstitutional, though on different reasoning from the Colorado courts. Justice [[Anthony Kennedy]] wrote the majority opinion, and was joined by [[John Paul Stevens]], [[Sandra Day O'Connor]], [[David Souter]], [[Ruth Bader Ginsburg]], and [[Stephen Breyer]]. The Court majority held that the Colorado constitutional amendment targeting homosexuals based upon animosity lacked a rational relation to any legitimate governmental purpose.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants= Romer v. Evans  |vol= 517 |reporter= U.S. |opinion= 620 |pinpoint= |court= |date= 1996 |url= |accessdate= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Regarding the state's argument that Amendment 2 blocked homosexuals merely from receiving "special rights", Kennedy wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Amendment 2's reach may not be limited to specific laws passed for the benefit of gays and lesbians. It is a fair, if not necessary, inference from the broad language of the amendment that it deprives gays and lesbians even of the protection of general laws and policies that prohibit arbitrary discrimination in governmental and private settings. ... The state court did not decide whether the amendment has this effect, however, and neither need we.&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

While leaving that question unresolved by his opinion, Kennedy concluded that the amendment imposed a special disability upon homosexuals by forbidding them to seek safeguards "without constraint".&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt; Instead of applying "[[strict scrutiny]]" to Amendment 2 (as the Colorado Supreme Court had done), Kennedy wrote that it did not even meet the much lower requirement of having a rational relationship to a legitimate government purpose:&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Its sheer breadth is so discontinuous with the reasons offered for it that the amendment seems inexplicable by anything but animus toward the class that it affects; it lacks a rational relationship to legitimate state interests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://ecf.cand.uscourts.gov/cand/09cv2292/evidence/PX0619.pdf |format= PDF |title= Chapter 14: Other Indicia of Animus Against LGBT People by State and Local Officials, 1980–Present |publisher= United States District Court for the Northern District of California |date= June 30, 2013 |url-status= dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20120305041055/https://ecf.cand.uscourts.gov/cand/09cv2292/evidence/PX0619.pdf |archivedate= March 5, 2012 |df= mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

And:

&lt;blockquote&gt;[Amendment 2] is at once too narrow and too broad. It identifies persons by a single trait and then denies them protection across the board. The resulting disqualification of a class of persons from the right to seek specific protection from the law is unprecedented in our jurisprudence.&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Kennedy did not go into depth in rejecting the claims put forward in support of the law (e.g. protecting the rights of landlords to evict gay tenants if they found homosexuality morally offensive), instead holding that the law was so unique as to "confound this normal process of judicial review" and "defies ... conventional inquiry."&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;  He elaborated:  "It is not within our constitutional tradition to enact laws of this sort."&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;

Finding that "laws of the kind now before us raise the inevitable inference that the disadvantage imposed is born of animosity toward the class of persons affected," the Court inferred that the passage of Amendment 2 was born of a "bare ... desire to harm a politically unpopular group".&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;  The Court added: "[I]f the constitutional conception of 'equal protection of the laws' means anything, it must at the very least mean that a bare ... desire to harm a politically unpopular group cannot constitute a ''legitimate'' governmental interest."(emphasis added)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants= Romer v. Evans |vol= 517 |reporter= U.S. |opinion= 620 |pinpoint= 634-635 |court= |date= 1996 |url= |accessdate= |quote=}} (citing {{cite court |litigants= Department of Agriculture v. Moreno |vol= 413 |reporter= U.S. |opinion= 528 |pinpoint= 534 |court= |date= 1973 |url= |accessdate= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority opinion in ''Romer'' neither mentioned nor overruled the Court's prior opinion in ''Bowers v. Hardwick'',&lt;ref name=Bowers/&gt; which allowed outright bans on homosexual activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Greve |first= Michael |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=x3kViV5h-O0C&amp;pg=PA100 |title= Real Federalism: Why It Matters, How It Could Happen |page= 100 |publisher= American Enterprise Institute |year= 1999 |via= Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Dissenting opinion==
Justice [[Antonin Scalia]] wrote the dissent, joined by Chief Justice [[William H. Rehnquist]] and Justice [[Clarence Thomas]]. Scalia asserted that Amendment 2 did not deprive anyone of the "protection [afforded by] general laws and policies that prohibit arbitrary discrimination in governmental and private settings", which he said was confirmed by the Colorado Supreme Court and not disputed by Justice Kennedy's opinion.&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;  Scalia's dissent said Amendment 2 merely provided that homosexuals "cannot as readily as others obtain preferential treatment under the laws".  His objections also included these:

* Regarding the Court's earlier decision in ''[[Bowers v. Hardwick]]'',&lt;ref name=Bowers/&gt; Scalia wrote:  "If it is rational to criminalize the conduct, surely it is rational to deny special favor and protection to those with a self-avowed tendency or desire to engage in the conduct."
* ''[[Davis v. Beason]]'' (1890)&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Davis v. Beason|volume=133|page=333|pin=|year=1890}}.&lt;/ref&gt; had held that laws against polygamy were not an "impermissible targeting" of polygamists, and Scalia asked: "Has the Court concluded that the perceived social harm of polygamy is a 'legitimate concern of government,' and the perceived social harm of homosexuality is not?"
* The Court, Scalia said, was engaged in [[judicial activism]]; as the Constitution says nothing on the topic, it should be decided by democratic processes.  The dissent added: "it [is] no business of the courts (as opposed to the political branches) to take sides in this culture war. But the Court today has done so, not only by inventing a novel and extravagant constitutional doctrine to take the victory away from traditional forces, but even by verbally disparaging as bigotry adherence to traditional attitudes."&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;

The dissent concluded as follows:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Today's opinion has no foundation in American constitutional law, and barely pretends to. The people of Colorado have adopted an entirely reasonable provision which does not even disfavor homosexuals in any substantive sense, but merely denies them preferential treatment. Amendment 2 is designed to prevent piecemeal deterioration of the sexual morality favored by a majority of Coloradans, and is not only an appropriate means to that legitimate end, but a means that Americans have employed before. Striking it down is an act, not of judicial judgment, but of political will.&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Scalia took the rare step of omitting the word "respectfully" when he wrote "I dissent" at the end of his opinion.&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url= http://harvardlawreview.org/2011/03/from-consensus-to-collegiality-the-origins-of-the-respectful-dissent/ |title= From Consensus to Collegiality: The Origins of the 'Respectful" Dissent' |work= [[Harvard Law Review]] |date= March 2011 |volume= 124 |number= 5 |page= 1306 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scholarly commentary==
The Court's opinion in ''Romer'' did not closely follow established equal protection doctrine (Amendment 2 "defied ... conventional inquiry" wrote Justice Kennedy), and the opinion led to much discussion by scholars and lawyers.&lt;ref name=Wexler&gt;{{cite book |last= Wexler |first= Jay |authorlink=Jay Wexler |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=G9A9bTAuFFkC&amp;pg=PT116 |title= The Odd Clauses: Understanding the Constitution Through Ten of Its Most Curious Provisions |page= 116 |publisher= Beacon Press |year= 2011 |via= Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One particular scholarly article that received widespread attention was by [[Akhil Amar]], a prominent law professor at [[Yale Law School|Yale]].&lt;ref name=Wexler /&gt; Amar wrote:&lt;ref name=Amar&gt;{{cite journal |last= Amar |first= Akhil |url= http://digitalcommons.law.yale.edu/fss_papers/936 |title= Attainder and Amendment 2: Romer's Rightness |journal= Michigan Law Review |volume= 95 |page= 203 |year= 1996 |doi=10.2307/1290134}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The Constitution does not require that "special" antidiscrimination rights, once extended, irrevocably vest via some magic and antidemocratic one-way ratchet.  And if Denver, Aspen, and Boulder can repeal these ordinances, presumably the Colorado legislature can repeal them by statute; and so too the people of Colorado can repeal them by state constitutional amendment (via initiative or referendum). To think otherwise is terminally silly.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Still, Amar asserted that Amendment 2 violated the Equal Protection Clause (although he preferred an alternative argument based on the [[Bill of attainder|Attainder Clause]]).  Regarding the Equal Protection Clause, Amar wrote:&lt;ref name=Amar /&gt;

&lt;Blockquote&gt;Under Amendment 2, heterosexuals could win local ordinances and state laws protecting themselves from being discriminated against on the basis of their sexual orientation, but nonheteros could not win symmetric ordinances and laws.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Putting aside the odds of discrimination against heterosexuals, Amar suggested that even if Amendment 2 had barred special protection for both heterosexuals and homosexuals, that still would have been unconstitutional because it would single out groups by name for harm, just like a law that says "Akhil Reed Amar shall be ineligible for a private immigration bill or a suspension of deportation".&lt;ref name=Amar /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Misleading.&lt;/sup&gt;

The "one-way ratchet" mentioned by Amar has been discussed by other authors as well.&lt;ref name=Jeffries /&gt;  For example, law professor [[John Calvin Jeffries]] has argued that the Court in ''Romer'' was actually relying upon a principle of non-retrogression, whereby "The Constitution becomes a ratchet, allowing change in one direction only."&lt;ref name=Jeffries&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Jeffries |first1= John |last2= Levinson |first2= Daryl |last-author-amp= yes |url= http://scholarship.law.berkeley.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1572&amp;context=californialawreview |title= The Non-Retrogression Principle in Constitutional Law |journal= California Law Review |volume= 86 |page= 1211 |year=1998 |doi=10.2307/3481106}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jeffries and his co-author, Daryl Levinson, conclude: "the revival of non-retrogression as a constitutional principle is symptomatic of a Supreme Court adrift in an age of judicial activism."&lt;ref name=Jeffries /&gt;

Supporters of the decision, such as law professor [[Louis Michael Seidman]], celebrated its "radical" nature, and hailed it as a revival of the [[Warren Court]]'s activism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Seidman |first= Louis |title= Romer's Radicalism: The Unexpected Revival of Warren Court Activism |volume= 1996 |journal= Supreme Court Review |pages= 67–121 |year= 1996 |doi=10.1086/scr.1996.3109727}}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to law professor Evan Gerstmann, the Court in ''Romer'' left unmentioned and unconsidered many purposes of Amendment 2 that the Colorado courts had acknowledged as legitimate.&lt;ref name=Gerstmann /&gt; The case, says Gerstmann, "has left the law of equal protection even murkier than before."&lt;ref name=Gerstmann /&gt;

==Related cases and events==
In 1993, [[Cincinnati, Ohio]], passed Ballot Issue 3, an amendment to the city charter, which forbade the city from adopting or enforcing civil rights ordinances based on sexual orientation, the only municipality in the United States to pass such a restriction. The wording of Cincinnati's amendment was almost identical to that of Colorado's. The amendment was upheld by the [[Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals]] in 1996.&lt;ref name=vacated&gt;{{cite court |litigants= Equality Foundation of Greater Cincinnati, Inc. v. City of Cincinnati ("Equality Foundation I") |vol= 54 |reporter= F.3d |opinion= 261 |pinpoint= |court= 6th Cir. |date= 1995 |url= https://caselaw.findlaw.com/us-6th-circuit/1104057.html |accessdate= |quote=}} vacated, 116 S. Ct. 2519 (1996).&lt;/ref&gt;  Later, the case was remanded by the Supreme Court for further consideration in 1997 in the wake of the ''Romer'' decision.  The Sixth Circuit upheld the amendment a second time, differentiating it from the state-level amendment on the grounds that it was a local government action of the type that Amendment 2 was designed to preempt.&lt;ref name=circuit&gt;{{cite court |litigants= Equality Foundation v. City of Cincinnati |vol= 128 |reporter= F. 3d |opinion= 289 |pinpoint= |court= |date= 1997 |url= http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=search&amp;case=/data2/circs/6th/970318p.html |accessdate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 13, 1998, the Supreme Court rejected an appeal, allowing the Sixth Circuit decision and the city amendment to stand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= Julie |last= Irwin |title= Law Denying Gay Protection Stands |date= October 14, 1998 |url= http://www.enquirer.com/editions/1998/10/14/loc_gayrights14.html |work= [[The Cincinnati Enquirer]] |access-date= January 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, Cincinnati voters overturned the amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Cincinnati Gay Rights Amendment Passes |date= March 15, 2006 |url= http://cincinnati.bizjournals.com/cincinnati/stories/2006/03/13/daily40.html |work= [[American City Business Journals|Business Courier of Cincinnati]] |access-date= January 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since ''Romer'' stood in obvious tension with the Court's earlier decision in ''Bowers v. Hardwick'',&lt;ref name=Bowers/&gt; it laid the groundwork for 2003's ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'',&lt;ref name=Lawrence/&gt; which overturned ''Bowers''; like the ''Romer'' case, Justices Kennedy and Scalia would author the majority and dissenting opinions in ''Lawrence'' with all nine justices voting almost the same way as in ''Romer'' (Justice O'Connor concurred, but with a different rationale). ''Romer'' has been narrowly cited but influential within its niche, being cited in the cases of ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'' and ''[[Hollingsworth v. Perry]]'', but the case has not had a much broader impact given the Court's assertion that it was conducting neither a "normal process of judicial review" nor a "conventional inquiry."&lt;ref name=opinion /&gt;  In the same niche, ''Romer'' was cited in the decision of [[Massachusetts Supreme Judicial Court]] case ''[[Goodridge v. Department of Public Health]]'', wherein the Department's desire to deny marriage licences to same-sex couples was explicitly likened to Amendment 2's attempt to broadly restrict from seeking benefits a narrowly defined class of citizens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Hillary Goodridge &amp; others vs. Department of Public Health &amp; another. |date= November 18, 2003 |url= http://www.boston.com/news/daily/18/sjc_gaymarriage_decision.pdf |format= PDF |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20031123132706/http://www.boston.com/news/daily/18/sjc_gaymarriage_decision.pdf |archive-date= November 23, 2003 |via= [[The Boston Globe]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, fifteen years after the referendum on Amendment 2, the Colorado legislature amended its anti-discrimination law by forbidding discrimination based on sexual orientation and gender identity, in employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://votesmart.org/bill/4143/12872/sexual-orientation-workplace-discrimination |title= SB 25: Sexual Orientation Workplace Discrimination |publisher= Project Vote Smart |access-date= August 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, Colorado further expanded its LGBT protections to include housing, public accommodation, and advertising.

Future Chief Justice [[John Roberts]] donated time [[pro bono]] to prepare oral arguments for the plaintiffs. Speaking during his nomination process, a case leader, Walter A. Smith Jr., praised his work on the case, recalling,  "He said, 'Let's do it.' And it's illustrative of his open-mindedness, his fair-mindedness. He did a brilliant job."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Roberts Donated Help to Gay Rights Case |last= Serrano |first= Richard |date= August 4, 2005 |url= http://articles.latimes.com/2005/aug/04/nation/na-roberts4 |work= [[Los Angeles Times]] |accessdate= January 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Colorado|LGBT|United States|Law}}
* [[1996 in LGBT rights]]
* [[Colorado for Family Values]]
* [[Compelling state interest]]
* [[List of United States Supreme Court cases, volume 517]]
* [[List of United States Supreme Court cases by the Rehnquist Court]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |first= William M., Jr. |last= Eskridge |chapter= The Supreme Court's Regime-Shifting Opinion in ''Romer v. Evans'' (1996) |pages= [https://archive.org/details/dishonorablepass00eskr/page/278 278–289] |title= Dishonorable Passions: Sodomy Laws in America 1861–2003 |location= New York |publisher= Viking |year= 2008 |isbn= 978-0-670-01862-8 |url= https://archive.org/details/dishonorablepass00eskr/page/278 }}
*{{cite book |first= Evan |last= Gerstmann |title= The Constitutional Underclass: Gays, Lesbians, and the Failure of Class-Based Equal Protection |year= 1999 |publisher= University of Chicago Press |location= Chicago |isbn= 0-226-28860-9 |url= https://archive.org/details/constitutionalun00gers }}
*{{cite journal |last= Hasian |first= Marouf A., Jr. |last2= Parry-Giles |first2= Trevor |last-author-amp= yes  |year= 1997 |title= 'A Stranger to Its Laws': Freedom, Civil Rights, and the Legal Ambiguity of ''Romer v. Evans'' |journal= Argumentation and Advocacy |volume= 34 |issue= |pages= 27–42 |issn= 1051-1431 |url= |accessdate= |quote= }}
*{{cite book |title= Courting Justice: Gay Men and Lesbians v. the Supreme Court |chapter= The Constitution 'Neither Knows nor Tolerates Classes among Citizens' |last= Murdoch |first= Joyce |last2= Price |first2= Deb |last-author-amp= yes |year= 2001 |publisher= Basic Books |location= New York |isbn= 0-465-01513-1 |pages=  |url= https://archive.org/details/courtingjusticeg00murd }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
*{{Wikisource-inline|Romer v. Evans|''Romer v. Evans''}}
*{{caselaw source
 | case=''Romer v. Evans'', {{ussc|517|620|1996|el=no}}
 | cornell =https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/517/620
 | courtlistener =https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/118027/romer-v-evans/
 | googlescholar = https://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=17758055891258118781
 | justia =https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/517/620/case.html
 | oyez =https://www.oyez.org/cases/1995/94-1039
 }}

{{LGBT rights in the United States}}

{{US14thAmendment}}

[[Category:1990s in LGBT history]]
[[Category:1996 in LGBT history]]
[[Category:1996 in United States case law]]
[[Category:American Civil Liberties Union litigation]]
[[Category:Anti-discrimination law in the United States]]
[[Category:Discrimination against LGBT people in the United States]]
[[Category:Legal history of Colorado]]
[[Category:LGBT in Colorado]]
[[Category:Politics of Colorado]]
[[Category:United States equal protection case law]]
[[Category:United States LGBT rights case law]]
[[Category:United States Supreme Court cases]]
[[Category:United States Supreme Court cases of the Rehnquist Court]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>