<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081104094807|249614672" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19943944" pageid="19943944" ns="0" title="Persecution of people with albinism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-04T10:34:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In some regions of [[Eastern Africa]]  certain body parts of [[albinistic]] people are believed to transmit magical powers.&lt;ref name=afp/&gt;  This [[superstition]] has been promulgated and exploited by [[witch doctor]]s and others who use such body parts as ingredients in rituals, concoctions and potions with the claim that their [[witchcraft|magic]] will bring prosperity to the user.&lt;ref name=bbc727/&gt;  As a result albinos have been persecuted, killed and dismembered, and graves of albinistics dug up and desecrated. At the same time albinos have also been ostracized and even killed because they are presumed to bring bad luck.&lt;ref name=bbc403/&gt;

==Tanzania==
In December 2007 the ''Tanzania Albino Society'' (TAS) accused the government of inactivity in the face of four albino killings over the past three months.&lt;ref  name=bbc1/&gt; While older albino women with red eyes had been at risk for being murdered sporadically in the past as [[witch]]es, this killing spree may have been the beginning of the ongoing persecution of albinos with the intent to harvest the victims' body parts.&lt;ref name=bbc1&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/7148673.stm |title=Tanzania fear over albino killing |author=BBC |date=December 17, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; With escalating killings President [[Jakaya Mrisho Kikwete|Kikwete]] publicly and repeatedly  condemned witch doctors, their helpers and middlemen, and the clients, among them members of the police force, for  these [[murder]]s. Victims include children snatched or abducted from their parents. The killers and their accomplices use hair, arms, legs, skin, eyes, genitals, and blood in rituals or for witch potions.&lt;ref name=kul/&gt;&lt;ref name=bbc727/&gt; Fishermen incorporate albino hair into their nets in their hope to catch more fish from [[Lake Victoria]] or to find gold in the belly of the fish they catch.&lt;ref name=bbc727&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/7527729.stm|title=Tanzania Albinos Targeted Again|work=[[BBC News]] (online edition)|date=July 27, 2008| author=[[BBC]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=nyt&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/06/08/world/africa/08albino.html
|title=Albinos, Long Shunned, Face Threat in Tanzania|journal=[[New York Times]]|date=[[June 8]], [[2008]]|publisher=[[New York Times Company]]|author= Jeffrey Gettleman}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of steps  were taken by the government to protect the albino population:  The president ordered a crackdown on witchdoctors in the spring of 2008,&lt;ref name=bbc403/&gt; an albino woman, Al-Shymaa Kway-Geer, was named  to become a member of the parliament – the first albino in such a position ever in Tanzania, police have been advised to generate lists of albinos and provide special protection,&lt;ref name=BBC721&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/7518049.stm | author=Karen Allen, [[BBC]] |title=Living in fear: Tanzania’s albinos. |date=July 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to foil [[graverobber]]s, graves of the albinistic were to be sealed with cement.&lt;ref name=bbc727/&gt; However, by October 2008 killings had not abated, and while some suspects had been apprehended, no convictions had taken place.&lt;ref name=kul&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.canada.com/topics/news/world/story.html?id=d9487de6-5eeb-4b6e-b21f-4863db51113c |title=Crackdown vowed after Tanzania albino girl killed, mutilated |author=John Kulekana (AFP)|date=October 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; By October 2008 it was estimated that over 50 murders had taken place since March 2007, many of them in the mining and fishing communities near Lake Victoria, especially at [[Mwanza]], [[Shinyanga]] and [[Mara, Tanzania|Mara]].&lt;ref name=kii&gt;{{cite web| url=http://allafrica.com/stories/200810200901.html |author=Orton Kiishweko |title=Tanzania: JK Orders Crackdown to Stem Murder of Albinos. |date=October 20, 2008| publisher=The Citizen (Dar es Salaam)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is estimated that over 150,000 albinos live in Tanzania; 8,000 of these are registered with the TAS. &lt;ref name=bbc403&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/low/africa/7327989.stm |author=BBC |title=Tanzania in witchdoctor crackdown |date=April 03, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of albinos have fled to the [[Dar es Salaam]] area as they feel safer in an urban setting.

==Neighboring countries==
By June 2008 killings had been reported in  neighboring [[Kenya]] and possibly the [[Democratic Republic of Congo]].&lt;ref name=nyt&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=kul/&gt;

In October 2008 [[AFP]] reported on the further expansion of killings of albinos to the  [[Ruyigi]] region  of [[Burundi]].  Body parts of the victims are then smuggled to Tanzania where they are used for witch rituals and potions. &lt;ref name=afp&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.france24.com/20081014-burundis-albinos-flee-sorcerers-organ-traders |author=Esdras Ndikumanna |title=Burundi's albinos flee sorcerers and organ traders |publisher=AFP |date=October 14, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Albinos have become  “a commercial good”, indicated  Nicodeme Gahimbare in Ruyigi who established a local safe haven in his fortified house.&lt;ref name=afp/&gt;

==International reaction==
After events had been publicized by the [[BBC]] and others, the [[European Parliament]] strongly condemned the killing of albinos in Tanzania on September 4, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-//EP//TEXT+TA+P6-TA-2008-0413+0+DOC+XML+V0//EN&amp;language=EN |title=European Parliament resolution of 4 September 2008 on the killing of albinos in Tanzania.|author=[[European Parliament]]|date=September 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}


[[Category:Tanzanian society]]
[[Category:Burundian society]]
[[Category:African witchcraft]]
[[Category:Albinism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>