<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121016220912|518202591" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="54421" pageid="54421" ns="0" title="Sex-selective abortion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-10-26T14:57:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Sex-selective abortion''' is the practice of terminating a pregnancy based upon the predicted sex of the baby. The selective [[abortion]] of female fetuses is most common in areas where cultural norms value male children over female children, especially in parts of [[People's Republic of China]], [[India]], [[Pakistan]], and the [[Caucasus]].&lt;ref name= "Goodkind"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Goodkind, Daniel |year=1999 |title=Should Prenatal Sex Selection be Restricted?: Ethical Questions and Their Implications for Research and Policy |journal=Population Studies |volume=53 |issue=1 |pages=49–61 |jstor=2584811 |doi=10.1080/00324720308069}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= "Gettis"&gt;A. Gettis, J. Getis, and J. D. Fellmann (2004). Introduction to Geography, Ninth Edition. New York: McGraw-Hill. pp. 200. ISBN 0-07-252183-X&lt;/ref&gt;

==Process of abortion==

===Prenatal sex discernment===
{{Main|Prenatal sex discernment}}
The earliest post-implantation test is to take a blood sample from the mother and test on the small amount of fetal DNA that can be found within it. A meta-analysis published in 2011 found that such tests are reliable more than 98% of the time, as long as they are taken after the seventh week of pregnancy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1001/jama.2011.1114 |journal=JAMA |year=2011 |volume=306 |issue=6 |pages=627–636 |title=Noninvasive Fetal Sex Determination Using Cell-Free Fetal DNA |author=Devaney SA, Palomaki GE, Scott JA, Bianchi DW |pmid=21828326}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-14457670 |date=10 August 2011 |title=Baby gender blood tests 'accurate' |first=Michelle |last=Roberts |newspaper=[[BBC News Online]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Obstetric ultrasonography]], either transvaginally or transabdominally, can check for the ''sagittal sign'' as a marker of fetal sex. It can be performed between 65 and 69 days from fertilization (week 12 of [[gestational age]]), where it gives a result in 90% of cases - a result that is correct in approximately ¾ of cases, according to a study from 2001.&lt;ref name=mazza&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Mazza V, Falcinelli C, Paganelli S, ''et al.'' |title=Sonographic early fetal gender assignment: a longitudinal study in pregnancies after in vitro fertilization |journal=Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol |volume=17 |issue=6 |pages=513–6 |year=2001 |month=June |pmid=11422974 |doi=10.1046/j.1469-0705.2001.00421.x |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accuracy for males is approximately 50% and for females almost 100%. When performed later, after 70 days from fertilization (at week 13 of gestational age), it gives an accurate result in almost 100% of cases.&lt;ref name=mazza/&gt;

===Surgical Abortion===
{{main|abortion}}
After the sex is determined through tests, the family decides whether to abort the child or not. Up to 15 weeks' [[gestation]], suction-aspiration or [[vacuum aspiration]] are the most common surgical methods of induced abortion.&lt;ref name="Healthwise"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://women.webmd.com/manual-and-vacuum-aspiration-for-abortion |title=Manual and Vacuum Aspiration for Abortion |publisher=[[Healthwise]] |original date= 28 October 2008. |accessdate=5 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Manual vacuum aspiration'' (MVA) consists of removing the [[fetus]] or [[embryo]], [[placenta]], and [[membranes]] by suction using a manual syringe, while ''electric vacuum aspiration'' (EVA) uses an electric pump. These techniques differ in the mechanism used to apply suction, in how early in pregnancy they can be used, and in whether [[cervical dilation]] is necessary. 
[[Unsafe abortions]] result in approximately 70 thousand maternal deaths and 5 million disabilities per year globally. An estimated 44 million abortions are performed globally each year, with slightly under half of those performed unsafely.

===Injection===
Since abortion is only possible when the fetus is three to four month old, older fetuses are aborted using chemical injection to induce the baby. In India, the injection costs well around 60000 to 70000 rupees (approximately USD $1070 to 1250 – living standard of India also must be considered) to induce [[miscarriage]]. Therefore, only well-off families have the privilege. In fact, researches have shown that as developing countries become richer, sex-selective abortion rises.

===Drugs (over-the-counter medication)===
The underprivileged who do not have the luxury to have surgical performance or chemical injection to induce abortion drug themselves with [[over-the-counter medication]] to [[miscarry]] the child. The underprivileged who cannot afford costly operations take harmful medications to poison the baby. Sadly, even if the baby fights the toxins and is born, there are no guarantees that the baby will be physically or mentally healthy – often, babies become [[deformed]] or [[disabled]].

==Geography==

===India===
{{main|Female foeticide in India}}
Sex-selective abortion has been seen as worsening the sex ratio in India, affecting gender issues related to sex compositions of Indian households.&lt;ref&gt;Sabarwal, Shwetlena. [http://i07.cgpublisher.com/proposals/226/index_html Son Preference in India: Prevelance, Trends and Agents of Change]. Retrieved March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the decennial Indian census, the sex ratio in the 0-6 age group in India went from 104.0 males per 100 females in 1981, to 105.8 in 1991, to 107.8 in 2001, to 109.4 in 2011. The ratio is significantly higher in certain [[States and territories of India|states]] such as [[Punjab (India)|Punjab]] and [[Haryana]] (126.1 and 122.0, as of 2001).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Arnold, Fred, Kishor, Sunita, &amp; Roy, T. K. |year=2002 |title=Sex-Selective Abortions in India |volume=28 |issue=4 |pages=759–785 |jstor=3092788 |journal=Population and Development Review |doi=10.1111/j.1728-4457.2002.00759.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of [[ultrasound]] and [[abortion]] for sex selection has been banned since 1994 in India and 1995 in China,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.uk/documents/post/pn198.pdf|title=Sex selection}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, there is evidence that such bans are rarely enforced,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Asia-South-Central/2010/0308/Gender-selection-In-India-abortion-of-girls-on-the-rise/%28page%29/2|title=Gender selection: In India, abortion of girls on the rise}}&lt;/ref&gt; and numerous dedicated sex selection clinics operate in many regions of those countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/world/story/2006/01/11/sex-selection060111.html|title=Sex selection in India exaggerated: doctors | work=CBC News | date=January 11, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The practice is most common among educated and wealthy residents, who are most likely to afford the procedure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0113/p01s04-wosc.html|title=India's 'girl deficit' deepest among educated}}&lt;/ref&gt; An article published in ''[[The Lancet]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Jha P, Kesler MA, Kumar R, ''et al.'' |title=Trends in selective abortion of female fetuses in India: analysis of nationally representative birth histories from 1990–2005 and census data from 1991–2011 |journal=Lancet |volume=377 |issue=9781 |pages=1921–8 |year=2011 |month=June |pmid=21612820 |doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60649-1 |pmc=3166246}}&lt;/ref&gt; analyzed Indian [[census]] data and concluded that selective abortion of female fetuses has increased in India over the past few decades due to increased [[prenatal sex discernment]] and has contributed to a widening imbalance in the child sex ratio, though the basis of the finding has been questioned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sciencedebate.com/science-blog/selective-abortion-female-fetuses-india-some-questions-lancet-article|title=Selective Abortion of Female Fetuses in India- Some Questions on the Lancet Article}}Source: ScienceDebate.com; Retrieved June 20, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

India’s prime minister acknowledges [[gendercide]] as a national shame, however, the police and judiciaries do not implement the law because they believe in the same thing. Authorities often let the unlawful parents and doctors off with light punishment. Often, when the mothers disobey the husband’s family decision to abort the female fetus and report it to the authorities, the suits are ignored or given a light sentence and the pointed finger targets the mother for bearing girls and disobeying the family’s decision to abort the child. She may even lose her job, exposed to constant death threats, and be left with unresolved cases. In addition, others who give birth to girls are prone to violence and even if she is able to give birth to the baby girls, the family is likely to not report the birth and even  [[infanticide|murder them]].&lt;ref name="Gendercide"&gt;{{cite video|url= http://abcnews.go.com/2020/video/illegal-gender-selection-ultrasound-technology-contributes-gendercide-india-2020-15126869 |title=Gendercide: Illegal Gender Selection |accessDATE=30 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

India’s secretary of health and family welfare, K. Chandramouli concedes that the law is not aggressive enough on the offender. However it will be difficult and may take years to change the cultural inclination of billions of peoples.&lt;ref name="Gendercide"/&gt;

===China===
A similar situation is going on in [[China]], too. Every year, about a million female fetuses are aborted and tens of thousands of female babies go missing. In China, a historical preference for a male child has been exacerbated by the [[one-child policy]], which was enacted in 1979. The strong cultural preference for sons is heightened by the one-child policy leading and cultural values results in serious consequences. 

Studies verify the phenomena using sex ratio at birth ([[SRB]], the ratio of boys born per 100 girls). The average SRB is supposed to lie between 104 ~ 106; however, the research has shown that in India, some areas record up to 120, and China, some provinces go well beyond 130. 

It has been argued that by having a [[one-child policy]], China has increased the rate of abortion of female fetuses, thereby accelerating a demographic decline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Hesketh T, Lu L, Xing ZW |title=The effect of China's one-child family policy after 25 years |journal=N. Engl. J. Med. |volume=353 |issue=11 |pages=1171–6 |year=2005 |month=September |pmid=16162890 |doi=10.1056/NEJMhpr051833}}&lt;/ref&gt; As most Chinese families are given incentives to have only one child, and would often prefer at least one son. Researchers have expressed concern that prenatal sex selection may reduce the number of families in the next generation.&lt;ref&gt;Das Gupta, Monica, Zhenghua, Jiang, Bobua, Li, Zbenming, Xie, Chung, Woo-in, &amp; Hwa-Ok, Bae. (December 2002). [http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/IW3P/IB/2003/02/07/000094946_03012804060286/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt Why is Son Preference so Persistent in East and South Asia?: A Cross-Country Study of China, India, and the Republic of Korea]. Retrieved March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; "Later legal concessions (including the permission to have a second child if the first one is a girl) reflect some official recognition of these problems." (Amartya Sen, 1990)

Gender bias can broadly impact a society, and it is estimated that by 2020 there could be more than 35 million young "surplus males" in [[China]] and 25 million in [[India]].&lt;ref&gt;"[http://kennedy.byu.edu/bridges/pdfs/bridgesF2000.pdf Surplus Males: The Need for Balance]." (Fall 2000). ''Bridges.'' Retrieved March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Policy makers in China are attempting to provide financial incentives to parents who have a female to help balance the sex ratio.(Ebenstein, A. (2011). Estimating a Dynamic Model of Sex Selection in China. Demography, 48(2), 783-811. doi:10.1007/s13524-011-0030-7)

===United States===
Sex-selective abortion may occur in certain Indian and Asian communities in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/gpr/15/2/gpr150218.html | title=A Problem-and-Solution Mismatch: Son Preference and Sex-Selective Abortion Bans | work=Guttmacher Policy Review | date=May 1, 2012 | accessdate=May 31, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ucsf.edu/news/2011/05/9903/pressure-bear-sons-leads-some-immigrant-indian-women-sex-selection-abortion-study | title=Pressure to Bear Sons Leads Some Immigrant Indian Women to Sex Selection, Abortion, Study Finds | work=University of California, San Francisco | date=May 20, 2012 | accessdate=May 31, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2012, [[Live Action]], a pro-life group, send actors posing as pregnant women into [[Planned Parenthood]] [[clinics]], asking a series of questions to elicit information on sex-selective abortions. These interviews were video taped and the videos were posted on the internet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/05/29/planned-parenthood-video_n_1552672.html | title=Planned Parenthood Sting Caught On Video, Released By Anti-Abortion Activists | work=The Huffington Post | date=May 29, 2012 | accessdate=May 31, 2010 | first=Laura | last=Bassett}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States Congress]] has debated legislation that would outlaw the practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.cnn.com/2012/05/30/politics/house-abortion-gender/index.html | title=House debates abortion ban for sex of fetus | work=CNN Online | date=May 31, 2012 | accessdate=May 31, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The legislation ultimately failed to pass in the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/06/01/us/politics/house-rejects-bill-to-ban-sex-selective-abortions.html?_r=1 | title=House Rejects Bill to Ban Sex-Selective Abortions | work=New York Times | date=May 31, 2012 | accessdate=May 31, 2010 | first=Jennifer | last=Steinhauer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other nations===
Abnormal sex ratios at birth, possibly explained by growing incidence of sex-selective abortion, have also been noted in some other countries outside South and East Asia. According to the 2011 CIA [[The World Factbook|World Factbook]], countries with more than 110 males per 100 females at birth also include [[Albania]] and former Soviet republics of [[Armenia]] and [[Azerbaijan]].
A 2005 study estimated that over 90 million females were "missing" from the expected population in [[Afghanistan]], [[Bangladesh]], [[China]], [[India]], [[Pakistan]], [[South Korea]] and [[Taiwan]] alone, and suggested that sex-selective abortion plays a role in this deficit.&lt;ref name= "Gettis"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wilsoncenter.org/topics/pubs/Hudson&amp;denBoer.pdf Layout 1&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; India's 2011 census shows a serious decline in the number of girls under the age of seven - activists believe eight million female [[fetus]]es may have been aborted between 2001 and 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pandey|first=Geeta|title=India's unwanted girls|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-13264301|publisher=[[BBC News]]|accessdate=23 May 2011|date=May 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Sex-selection practices also occur among some South Asian immigrants in the United States: A study of the 2000 United States Census observed definite male bias in families of Chinese, Korean and Indian immigrants, which was getting increasingly stronger in families where first one or two children were female. In those families where the first two children were girls, the sex ratio of the third child was observed to be 1.51:1 in favor of boys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/15/nyregion/15babies.html?_r=2&amp;pagewanted=1&amp;hp|title=U.S. Births Hint at Bias for Boys in Some Asians | work=The New York Times | first=Sam | last=Roberts | date=June 15, 2009 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reasons for sex-selective abortion==
Some research suggests that culture plays a larger role than economic conditions in gender preference and sex-selective abortion, because such deviations in sex ratios do not exist in [[sub-Saharan Africa]], [[Latin America]], and the [[Caribbean]].&lt;ref name= "Gettis"/&gt; Demographers argue that perceived gender imbalances may arise from the underreporting of female births, rather than sex-selective abortion or infanticide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi=10.2307/1972351 | title=The missing girls of China: a new demographic account | last=Johansson | first=Sten | last2=Nygren | jstor=1972351 | first2=Olga | year=1991 | volume=17 | issue=1 | journal = Population and Development Review | pages=35&amp;ndash;51}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title=Are births underreported in rural China? | first=M. Giovanna | last=Merli | first2=Adrian E. | last2=Raftery | journal=Demography | volume=37 | issue=1 | year=2000 | pages=109–126 |doi=10.2307/2648100 |jstor=2648100 | pmid=10748993}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cultural preference===
The reason for intensifying sex-selection abortion in China and India can be seen through history and cultural background. Generally, before the [[information era]], male babies were preferred because they provided manual labor and success the family [[lineage]]. Labor is still important in developing nations as China and India, but when it comes to family lineage, it is of great importance.
The selective abortion of female fetuses is most common in areas where cultural norms value male children over female children.&lt;ref name="Goodkind"/&gt; A son is often preferred as an "asset" since he can earn and support the family; a daughter is a "liability" since she will be married off to another family, and so will not contribute financially to her parents. The patriarchal structure of a society is the single most important factor skewing the sex ratio in favor of males, accentuated in some cultures by the burden of raising a [[dowry]] for a daughter's marriage. Openness to the very concept of sex selection is a significant factor: among societies which practice selective female abortion nowadays, many were systematically practicing [[female infanticide]] (either directly or by withholding postnatal care from children of undesirable sex) long before abortion became a viable option.&lt;ref name="Gupta_2005"&gt;Das Gupta, Monica, "Explaining Asia's Missing Women": A New Look at the Data", 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, in some cultures sons are expected to take care of their parents in their old age.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2007.01.004}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In modern East Asia, a large part of the pattern of preferences leading to this practice can be condensed simply as a desire to have a male heir. Monica Das Gupta (2005) observes that, in late 1980s to early 1990s China, there was no evidence of selective abortion of female fetuses among firstborn children, or in families with one or more existing sons (in fact, families with multiple sons were, if anything, more likely to abort a boy than a girl). But, at the same time, families with existing daughters appeared very likely to abort any further female fetuses, resulting in heavily skewed sex ratios.&lt;ref name="Gupta_2005" /&gt;

===Sexual discrimination===
The role of women in nations that are prone to sex-selection abortion is to stay home, do house chores, and raise children. She is mutely banned to work in the society, pressured by family and discouraged from the society. Lower salary, working in temporary or non-regular jobs, in lower status in working position, faced with thick harsh glass-walls and [[glass ceiling]] are all evidence that their society is not so keen towards women on top. These family usually live with their elders and the older generations considers jumping in the business sector overrated for women. In these societies, mothers are viewed to sacrifice herself into assisting her husband and raising children, sparing no time for self-development. All in all, in cultures that practice sex-selective abortion, women are prone to [[sexual discrimination]] and are viewed below status to men.

===One-child Policy===
The 1960s scare for overpopulation led governments to implement laws to control birth rate such as the ''[[one-child policy]]''. Accordingly, it led to consequence where parents highly value boys over girls; even to a point were words such as "[[infanticide]]" come into existence. Some Westerns call the situation their Eastern nations the ‘Holocaust for baby girls’. What’s more, her child will follow the husband’s surname and is restricted to visit her parents whenever she wishes. These kinds of cultural practice mixed with the government implications of one-child policy have caused one-daughter parents to become ‘’childless’’ after the marriage. As a result, these parent no longer have a financially supporting or lineage successor. Thus, for parents to insure financial dependence and hereditary successor, a boy must be born. In this regard, the pervasion of male dominant culture and one-child policy heightens the sex-selective abortion.

===Trivers–Willard hypothesis===
The [[Trivers–Willard hypothesis]] argues that available resources affect male [[reproductive success]] more than female and that consequently parents should prefer males when resources are plentiful and females when resources are scarce. This has been applied to resource differences between individuals in a society and also to resource differences between societies. Empirical evidence is mixed with higher support in better studies according to Cronk in a 2007 review. One example, in a 1997 study, of a group with a preference for females was [[Romani people|Romani]] in [[Hungary]], a low status group. They "had a female-biased sex ratio at birth, were more likely to abort a fetus after having had one or more daughters, nursed their daughters longer, and sent their daughters to school for longer."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/S1472-6483(10)60546-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Genetic===
Gender-linked genetic abnormalities, such as several forms of [[colorblindness]], are linked to [[recessive genes]] on the [[X chromosome]]. Pre-implantation genetic diagnosis can identify some life-threatening genetic abnormalities in [[embryo]]. The easiest way to select against embryos which may have a gender-linked genetic abnormality is to choose only female embryos. Embryos which are not implanted are usually discarded.

==Societal Effects==

===Demography Issues and Wifeless Men===
The strong preference on boys over girls will bring about a serious problem, millions of wifeless men. In years to come, the skewed ratio of men and women could cause men to have difficulty finding brides. There are reports of women from [[Vietnam]], [[Myanmar]], and [[North Korea]] systematically trafficked to mainland [[China]] and [[Taiwan]] and sold into forced marriages.&lt;ref name="Hvistendahl_WSJ"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702303657404576361691165631366.html?mod=googlenews_wsj|title=The War Against Girls | work=The Wall Street Journal | first=Jonathan V.|last=Last|date=June 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[South Korea]] and [[Taiwan]], high male sex ratios and declining birth rates over several decades ago have led to cross-cultural marriage between local men and foreign women from countries such as mainland China, Vietnam and the Philippines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/22/world/asia/22brides.html?pagewanted=all | work=The New York Times | first=Norimitsu | last=Onishi | title=Korean Men Use Brokers to Find Brides in Vietnam | date=February 22, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Measures being taken===
NGOs such as the [[Gendercide Watch]] and [[Population Research Institute]] have been created to address the issue of sex-selective abortion and female infanticide{{citation needed|date=August 2012}} . 
In Punjab, India, government and NGO networks have set up orphanages to shelter the unwanted girls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/india/5004051/E-cradle-saves-Indias-abandoned-babies.html | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Dean | last=Nelson | title=E-cradle saves India's abandoned babies | date=March 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
In 1994 over 180 states signed the Programme of Action of the [[International Conference on Population and Development]], agreeing to "eliminate all forms of discrimination against the girl child".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unfpa.org/webdav/site/global/shared/documents/publications/2011/Preventing_gender-biased_sex_selection.pdf|title=Preventing gender-biased sex selection|publisher=[[UNFPA]]|accessdate=1 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011 the resolution of [[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe|PACE]]'s Committee on Equal Opportunities for Women and Men condemned the practice of prenatal sex selection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://assembly.coe.int/Documents/WorkingDocs/Doc11/EDOC12715.pdf|title=Prenatal sex selection|publisher=[[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe|PACE]]|accessdate=1 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
The Manish Jha film, ''[[Matrubhoomi-A Nation Without Women]]'' (2003), depicts a [[future]] [[dystopia]] in a village in India, populated exclusively by males due to female infanticide, and which is reduced to barbarianism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/296804/Matrubhoomi/overview|title=Matrubhoomi (2003)|work=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{|width=100%
|-valign=top
|width=50%|
* [[Abortion debate]]
* [[Child abandonment]]
* [[Fetal rights]]
* [[Feticide]]
* [[Gendercide]]
* [[Missing women of Asia]]
|width=100%|
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Genetics and abortion]]
* [[Psychohistorical views on infanticide]]
* [[Selective reduction]]
* [[Sex selection]]
|}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.cicred.org/Eng/Seminars/FDA/Femaledeficit.htm ''A conference held in Singapore in December 2005 on female deficit in Asia'']
* [http://www.singstat.gov.sg/ssn/feat/1Q95/feat.html Sex Selection at Birth; ''Statistics Singapore Newsletter, Vol 17 No.3 January 1995'']
* [http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3990133/ MSNBC - No Girls Please - In parts of Asia, sexism is ingrained and gender selection often means murder]
* [http://www.alexandersanger.com/articles/2003_03_21.html Surplus Males and US/China Relations]
* [http://chronicle.com/free/v50/i34/34a01401.htm ''A Dangerous Surplus of Sons?''] - An analysis of various studies of the lopsided sex ratios in Asian countries
* [http://www.gendercide.org/case_infanticide.html Case study: Female Infanticide] in India and China
* [http://www.cid.harvard.edu/cidwp/pdf/grad_student/007.pdf Working paper by Emily Oster linking sex ratio imbalances to hepatitis B infection]
* [http://www.portlethenacademy.aberdeenshire.sch.uk/depts/mod-studs/chinarep.htm S2 China Report - China: The Effects of the One Child Policy]
* [http://www.unescap.org/esid/psis/population/database/poplaws/law%5Fchina/ch%5Frecord020.htm Notification on Addressing in a Comprehensive Way the Issue of Rising Sex Ratio at Birth] a [[UNESCAP]] document
* [http://www.cicred.org/Eng/Publications/pdf/BOOK_singapore.pdf A collection of essays on sex selection in various Asian countries by Attané and Guilmoto]
* [http://www.unfpa.org/gender/case_studies.htm Five case studies and a video on sex selection in Asia by UNFPA]
* [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5293148 ''NPR, All Things Considered, India Confronts Gender-Selective Abortion, March 21, 2006'']
* [http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702303657404576361691165631366.html ''Book Review: Unnatural Selection] - The War Against Girls / WSJ.com

{{Abortion}}
{{Social issues in India}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sex-Selective Abortion}}
[[Category:Abortion]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:Demography]]
[[Category:Infanticide]]
[[Category:Feminism and health]]
[[Category:Population]]
[[Category:Demographics]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Women and death]]
[[Category:Violence against women]]
[[Category:Social issues in India|Abortion]]

[[ar:وأد البنات]]
[[bn:লিঙ্গভিত্তিক গর্ভপাত]]
[[hi:कन्या भ्रूण हत्या]]
[[mr:भ्रूणहत्या]]
[[no:Kjønnsseleksjon ved hjelp av abort eller spedbarnsdrap]]
[[pt:Aborto seletivo]]
[[ro:Avort selectiv]]
[[ta:பால் தெரிவு கருக்கலைப்பு]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>