<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091113053307|325572922" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="54421" pageid="54421" ns="0" title="Sex-selective abortion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-13T11:37:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Original research|date=September 2007}}

'''Sex-selective abortion''' (also referred to as '''son preference''' or '''female deselection''') are methods of sex-selection which are practiced in areas where male children are valued over female children.  Sex-selective abortion refers to the targeted [[abortion]] of female [[fetus]]es; the fetus' sex may be identified by [[ultrasound]] but also rarely by [[amniocentesis]] or another procedure.

These practices arise in areas where cultural norms value male children over female children.&lt;ref name= "Goodkind"&gt;Goodkind, Daniel. (1999). [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0032-4728(199903)53%3A1%3C49%3ASPSSBR%3E2.0.CO%3B2-D Should Prenatal Sex Selection be Restricted?: Ethical Questions and Their Implications for Research and Policy]. ''Population Studies, 53 (1),'' 49-61. Retrieved March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Societies that practice sex selection in favor of males are quite common, especially in countries like the [[People's Republic of China]], [[Korea]], [[Taiwan]], and [[India]].
&lt;ref name= "Goodkind"/&gt;&lt;ref name= "Gettis"&gt;A. Gettis, J. Getis, and J. D. Fellmann (2004). Introduction to Geography, Ninth Edition. New York: McGraw-Hill. pp. 200. ISBN 0-07-252183-X&lt;/ref&gt;. In some regions of [[Indonesia]] however, people{{Who|date=September 2009}} prefer females rather than males{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}.

In 2005, 90 million women were estimated to be missing in seven Asian countries{{Which?|date=November 2009}} alone, apparently due to sex-selective abortion.&lt;ref name= "Gettis"/&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wilsoncenter.org/topics/pubs/Hudson&amp;denBoer.pdf Layout 1&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The existence of the practice appears to be determined by culture, rather than by economic conditions, because such deviations in sex ratios do not exist in sub-Saharan Africa, Latin America, and the Caribbean.&lt;ref name= "Gettis"/&gt;

Sex-selective abortion was rare before the late 20th century, because of the difficulty of determining the sex of the fetus before birth, but ultrasound has made such selection easier. However, prior to this, parents would alter family sex compositions through infanticide. It is believed to be responsible for at least part of the skewed birth statistics&lt;ref name= "Gettis"/&gt; in favor of males in [[mainland China]], [[India]], [[Taiwan]], and [[South Korea]].

==Hepatitis B theory==
Sex-selective abortion, infanticide, and abandonment may not be the only causes of sex ratio imbalances in the countries mentioned above. Research indicates that women infected with the [[hepatitis B]] virus are 1.5 times more likely to give birth to a male. The researcher, [[Emily Oster]], says that the higher rates of hepatitis B in China could account for 75% of the "missing girls."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2005/11/051109092603.htm "Hepatitis B Accounts For 40 Percent Of 'Missing' Asian Women"], [[Science Daily]], December 8, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; However, new demographic research casts doubt on the hepatitis B theory. Das Gupta found that data from a huge sample of births in China show that the only women with elevated probabilities of bearing a son are those who have already borne daughters.&lt;ref&gt;[http://econ.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/EXTDEC/EXTRESEARCH/EXTPROGRAMS/EXTPUBSERV/0,,contentMDK:21280987~pagePK:64168182~piPK:64168060~theSitePK:477916,00.html Human Development and Public Services - China’s “Missing Girls”—Son Preference or Hepatitis B Infections?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, a new study by Emily Oster and Gang Chen showed her earlier theory was incorrect.  "This ﬁnding leads me to conclude that hepatitis B cannot explain skewed sex ratios in China, and the conclusions about this in Oster (2005) were incorrect."  [http://faculty.chicagobooth.edu/emily.oster/papers/hbvnotecon.pdf]

==Societal effects of sex-selective abortion==
It is estimated that by 2020 there could be more than 35 million young "surplus males" in [[China]] and 25 million in [[India]].&lt;ref&gt;"[http://kennedy.byu.edu/bridges/pdfs/bridgesF2000.pdf Surplus Males: The Need for Balance]." (Fall 2000). ''Bridges.'' Retrieved March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sex-selective abortion has become an issue in [[South Asia|Southern]] and [[East Asia|Eastern Asia]]n countries, where sex-selective abortions have caused an increase in the imbalances between sex ratios of various Asian countries. Studies have estimated that sex-selective abortions have increased the ratio of males to females from the natural average of 105-106 males per 100 females to 113 males per 100 females in both South Korea and China, 110 males per 100 females in Taiwan and 107 males per 100 females among Chinese populations living in Singapore and parts of Malaysia.&lt;ref name="goodkind1"&gt;Goodkind, Daniel. (1995). [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0098-7921%28199603%2922%3A1%3C111%3AOSSPSI%3E2.0.CO%3B2-W On Substituting Sex Preference Strategies in East Asia: Does Prenatal Sex Selection Reduce Postnatal Discrimination?]. ''Population and Development Review, 22 (1),'' 111-125. Retrieved March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; However, a similar trend does not exist in North Korea, possibly due to limited access to prenatal sex-testing technologies.&lt;ref&gt;Goodkind, Daniel. (1999). [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0039-3665%28199909%2930%3A3%3C212%3ADPPSIN%3E2.0.CO%3B2-B Do Parents Prefer Sons in North Korea?]. ''Studies in Family Planning, 30 (3),'' 212-218. Retrieved March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1994 [[United Nations]] [[International Conference on Population and Development]] in [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]], policy objectives intended to eliminate sex-selective abortion and infanticide, along with discrimination against female children, were stated in Article 4.15 of the [http://www.unfpa.org/icpd/icpd_poa.htm Programme of Action]: "...to eliminate all forms of discrimination against the girl child and the root causes of son preference, which results in harmful and unethical practices regarding female infanticide and prenatal sex selection".&lt;ref name="goodkind1" /&gt;

Sex-selective abortion has been seen as worsening the sex ratio in India, and thus affecting gender issues related to sex compositions of Indian households.&lt;ref&gt;Sabarwal, Shwetlena. [http://i07.cgpublisher.com/proposals/226/index_html Son Preference in India: Prevelance, Trends and Agents of Change]. Retrieved March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the 2001 census, the sex-ratio in India is 107.8 males per 100 females, up from 105.8 males per 100 females in 1991. The ratio is significantly higher in certain [[States and territories of India|states]] such as [[Punjab (India)|Punjab]] (126.1) and [[Haryana]] (122.0).&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, Fred, Kishor, Sunita, &amp; Roy, T. K. (2002). [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0098-7921%28200212%2928%3A4%3C759%3ASAII%3E2.0.CO%3B2-O Sex-Selective Abortions in India]. ''Population and Development Review, 28 (4),'' 759-785. Retrieved March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

It has been argued that by having a [[one-child policy]], China has increased the rate of abortion of female fetuses, thereby accelerating a demographic decline.&lt;ref&gt;[http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/full/353/11/1171 The Effect of China's One-Child Family Policy after 25 Years],  Therese Hesketh and Zhu Wei Xing, ''[[New England Journal of Medicine]]'', 2005-09-15.&lt;/ref&gt; As most Chinese families are allowed (that is, given extreme incentives to have) only one child, and would often prefer at least one son, there are fewer daughters, thus preventing the formation of a greater number of families in the next generation.&lt;ref&gt;Das Gupta, Monica, Zhenghua, Jiang, Bobua, Li, Zbenming, Xie, Chung, Woo-in, &amp; Hwa-Ok, Bae. (December 2002). [http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/IW3P/IB/2003/02/07/000094946_03012804060286/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt Why is Son Preference so Persistent in East and South Asia?: A Cross-Country Study of China, India, and the Republic of Korea]. Retrieved March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 2005, test kits such as the [[Baby Gender Mentor]] have become available over the internet.&lt;ref name="Globe"&gt;{{cite news |title=Test reveals gender early in pregnancy |publisher=The Boston Globe |date=[[2005-06-27]] |author=Goldberg, Carey |accessdate=2007-01-16 |url=http://www.boston.com/yourlife/health/women/articles/2005/06/27/test_reveals_gender_early_in_pregnancy/}}&lt;/ref&gt; These tests have been criticized for making it easier to perform a sex-selective abortion earlier in a pregnancy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.news.com.au/dailytelegraph/story/0,22049,21715528-5001021,00.html |title=Pick-your-baby test investigated |publisher=The Daily Telegraph |date=[[May 12]], [[2007]] |author=Masters, Clare |accessdate=2007-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Concerns have also been raised about their accuracy.&lt;ref name = "Boyce1"&gt;{{cite news|author=Boyce, Nell |date=[[2005-09-29]] |url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=4867895 |title=Critics Question Accuracy of Fetus Sex Test |publisher=National Public Radio |accessdate=2007-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = "Boyce2"&gt;{{cite news|author=Boyce, Nell |date=[[2005-10-10]] |url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=4952404 |title=Questions Raised Over Accuracy of Gender Test |publisher=National Public Radio|accessdate=2007-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While sex-selective abortion is controversial, even within the pro-choice community, some commentators have championed it as a means to empower women and increase familial happiness.  For example, bioethicist [[Jacob M. Appel]] has written, "Mothers who want boys should have boys and mothers who want girls should have girls. Pre-implanting diagnosis offers the promising of increasing the number of children who are loved and wanted. I look forward to the day when every son knows that his parents wanted a son and every daughter knows that her parents wanted a daughter."&lt;ref&gt;Appel, Jacob M.  ''Want a Daughter?  Try Paying for Her'', Opposing Views, August 26, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{|width=100%
|-valign=top
|width=50%|
* [[Abortion]]
* [[Abortion debate]]
* [[Child abandonment]]
* [[Elterngeld]]
* [[Family]]
* [[Fetal rights]]
* [[Feticide]]
* [[Gendercide]]
* [[Missing women of Asia]]
|width=50%|
* ''[[Matrubhoomi]]'' &lt;!--a film based on this case--&gt;
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Genetics and abortion]]
* [[Psychohistorical views on infanticide]]
* [[Selective reduction]]
* [[Sex selection]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Sexism in India]]
|}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.cicred.org/Eng/Seminars/FDA/Femaledeficit.htm ''A conference held in Singapore in December 2005 on female deficit in Asia'']
*[http://www.singstat.gov.sg/ssn/feat/1Q95/feat.html Sex Selection at Birth; ''Statistics Singapore Newsletter, Vol 17 No.3 January 1995'']
*[http://www.webcom.com/hrin/magazine/july96/invisgrl.html The Invisible Girl]
*[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3990133/ MSNBC - No Girls Please - In parts of Asia, sexism is ingrained and gender selection often means murder]
*[http://members.tripod.com/anantmithal/Itihaas/1999/It990919IsFemaleFetocideCivilized.html Akhilesh Mithal - Itihaas - Is Female Feticide Civilized?]
*[http://morpheus.cc/myworld/issues/meiming.html It's a Girl! - Waiting to Die: The Babies Sacrificed for China's One Child Policy]
*[http://www.alexandersanger.com/articles/2003_03_21.html Surplus Males and US/China Relations]
*[http://chronicle.com/free/v50/i34/34a01401.htm ''A Dangerous Surplus of Sons?''] - An analysis of various studies of the lopsided sex ratios in Asian countries
*[http://www.gendercide.org/case_infanticide.html Case study: Female Infanticide] in India and China
*[http://www.cid.harvard.edu/cidwp/pdf/grad_student/007.pdf Working paper by Emily Oster linking sex ratio imbalances to hepatitis B infection]
*[http://www.portlethenacademy.aberdeenshire.sch.uk/depts/mod-studs/chinarep.htm S2 China Report - China: The Effects of the One Child Policy]
*[http://www.unescap.org/esid/psis/population/database/poplaws/law%5Fchina/ch%5Frecord020.htm  Notification on Addressing in a Comprehensive Way the Issue of Rising Sex Ratio at Birth] a [[UNESCAP]] document
*[http://www.cicred.org/Eng/Publications/pdf/BOOK_singapore.pdf A collection of essays on sex selection in various Asian countries by Attané and Guilmoto]
*[http://www.unfpa.org/gender/case_studies.htm Five case studies and a video on sex selection in Asia by UNFPA]
*[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5293148 ''NPR, All Things Considered, India Confronts Gender-Selective Abortion, March 21, 2006'']
*[http://www.baby-gender-online.com ''Baby Gender Selection'']
{{Abortion}}
[[Category:Abortion]]
[[Category:Adoption forms and related practices]]
[[Category:Demography]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Infanticide]]
[[Category:Feminism and health]]
[[Category:Population]]
[[Category:Demographics]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Women and death]]

[[ar:وأد البنات]]
[[no:Kjønnsseleksjon ved hjelp av abort eller spebarnsdrap]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>