<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131114045217|581584253" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="54421" pageid="54421" ns="0" title="Sex-selective abortion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-18T17:07:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Sex-selective abortion''' is the practice of terminating a pregnancy based upon the predicted sex of the baby. The selective [[abortion]] of female fetuses is most common in areas where cultural norms value male children over female children, especially in parts of [[People's Republic of China]], [[India]], [[Pakistan]], and the [[Caucasus]].&lt;ref name= "Goodkind"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Goodkind, Daniel |year=1999 |title=Should Prenatal Sex Selection be Restricted?: Ethical Questions and Their Implications for Research and Policy |journal=Population Studies |volume=53 |issue=1 |pages=49–61 |jstor=2584811 |doi=10.1080/00324720308069}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= "Gettis"&gt;A. Gettis, J. Getis, and J. D. Fellmann (2004). Introduction to Geography, Ninth Edition. New York: McGraw-Hill. pp. 200. ISBN 0-07-252183-X&lt;/ref&gt; Sex-selective abortion can affect the [[human sex ratio]]—the relative number of males to females in a given age group.&lt;ref name=coevolution&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7846643 |title=Gene-culture coevolution and sex ratios: the effects of infanticide, sex-selective abortion, sex selection, and sex-biased parental investment on the evolution of sex ratios |last1=Kumm |first1=J. |last2=Laland |first2=K. N. |last3=Feldman |first3=M. W. |PMID=7846643 |journal=Theoretical Population Biology |year=1994 |month=December |volume=43 |number=3 |pages=249–278}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://articles.philly.com/2011-06-21/news/29683905_1_gender-imbalance-fertility-institutes-boys |title= Gender imbalance tilting the world toward men |work= [[The Philadelphia Inquirer]] |last= Gammage |first= Jeff |date= June 21, 2011 |accessdate= June 27, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A marker of countries with significant sex-selective abortion is their human sex ratio. The normal range is 105-107 males to females, as more male embryos are formed than female embryos.&lt;ref&gt;Kraemer, Sebastian. "The Fragile Male." British Medical Journal (2000): n. pag. British Medical Journal. Web. 20 Oct. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; Countries with significant practices of sex-selective abortion usually have higher human sex ratios, typically 110 and above. See [[list of countries by sex ratio]].

==Prenatal sex discernment==
{{Main|Prenatal sex discernment}}
The earliest post-implantation test, [[cell free fetal DNA]] testing, involves taking a blood sample from the mother and isolating the small amount of fetal [[DNA]] that can be found within it. When performed after week seven of pregnancy, this method is about 98% accurate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1001/jama.2011.1114 |journal=JAMA |year=2011 |volume=306 |issue=6 |pages=627–636 |title=Noninvasive Fetal Sex Determination Using Cell-Free Fetal DNA |author=Devaney SA, Palomaki GE, Scott JA, Bianchi DW |pmid=21828326}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-14457670 |date=10 August 2011 |title=Baby gender blood tests 'accurate' |first=Michelle |last=Roberts |newspaper=[[BBC News Online]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Obstetric ultrasonography]], either transvaginally or transabdominally, can check for the ''sagittal sign'' as a marker of fetal sex. It can be performed between 65 and 69 days from fertilization (week 12 of [[gestational age]]), where it gives a result in 90% of cases—a result that is correct in approximately 3 out of 4 cases, according to a study from 2001.&lt;ref name=mazza&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Mazza V, Falcinelli C, Paganelli S, ''et al.'' |title=Sonographic early fetal gender assignment: a longitudinal study in pregnancies after in vitro fertilization |journal=Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol |volume=17 |issue=6 |pages=513–6 |year=2001 |month=June |pmid=11422974 |doi=10.1046/j.1469-0705.2001.00421.x |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accuracy for males is approximately 50% and for females almost 100%. When performed later, after 70 days from fertilization (at week 13 of gestational age), it gives an accurate result in almost all cases.&lt;ref name=mazza/&gt;

The most invasive measures are [[chorionic villus sampling]] (CVS) and [[amniocentesis]], which involve testing of the chorionic villus (found in the placenta) and [[amniotic fluid]], respectively. Both techniques typically test for [[Chromosome abnormality|chromosomal disorders]] but can also reveal the sex of the child and are performed early in the pregnancy. However, they are often more expensive and more dangerous than blood sampling or ultrasonography, so they are seen less frequently than other sex determination techniques.&lt;ref&gt;Alfirevic Z, von Dadelszen P (2003). "Instruments for chorionic villus sampling for prenatal diagnosis". In Alfirevic, Zarko.Cochrane Database Syst Rev (1): CD000114.doi:10.1002/14651858.CD000114&lt;/ref&gt;

==Process of abortion==
{{main|abortion}}
An induced [[abortion]] is the manual cessation of fetal development and removal of the [[fetus]] (or [[embryo]]) and related tissue. It is contrast to spontaneous abortion, which refers to the natural end of development (without outside intervention). If an induced abortion is desired, [[suction-aspiration]] and [[vacuum aspiration]] are the most common early-pregnancy (up to fifteen weeks) techniques.&lt;ref&gt;^ Healthwise (2004). "Manual and vacuum aspiration for abortion". WebMD. Archived from the original on 28 October 2008. Retrieved 2013-10-18.&lt;/ref&gt; These techniques involve the manual or electrical removal of the fetus (or embryo), [[placenta]], and [[membranes]]. From the 15th to the 26th week, more invasive techniques must be used. The most common is [[dilation and evacuation]] (D&amp;E), which involves the opening of the cervix and surgical removal of the fetus and related tissues. After week 26, induced abortions require labor induction by drugs, intact dilation and extraction, or a [[hysterectomy abortion]]. Various injections and medications are also available, dependent upon gestational age, availability, and cost. 
Due to lack of resources (monetary, physician, transportation, etc.) and emotional factors (such as fear or shame), performing unsafe abortions is a significant global issue. Of the estimated 44 million abortions per year, it is estimated that just below half are performed unsafely. These unsafe abortions lead to approximately 70,000 maternal deaths annually.&lt;ref&gt;Shah, I.; Ahman, E. (December 2009). "Unsafe abortion: global and regional incidence, trends, consequences, and challenges" (PDF). Journal of Obstetrics and Gynaecology Canada 31 (12): 1149–58. PMID 20085681.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sedgh, G.; Singh, S.; Shah, I. H.; Åhman, E.; Henshaw, S. K.; Bankole, A. (2012). "Induced abortion: Incidence and trends worldwide from 1995 to 2008". The Lancet 379 (9816): 625–632. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(11)61786-8. PMID 22264435.&lt;/ref&gt;

==India==
{{POV-section|date=November 2013}}
Abortions have been a popular medical procedure in India for quite some time, but the first law regarding abortion was not passed until 1971. This law, the [[Medical Termination of Pregnancy Act of 1971]], made abortion legal in most states, but specified “acceptable” reasons for abortion, physicians who can provide the procedure, and the facilities they can be performed.&lt;ref&gt;"Medical Termination of Pregnancy Act 1971 - Introduction." Health News RSS. Med India, n.d. Web. 20 Oct. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; (Acceptable reasons included the pregnancy posing a serious risk to the mother, serious physical or mental disability of the fetus, the pregnancy being the result of a rape, etc.) Since the act was passed, more abortions have been performed illegally than legally for a variety of reasons, including cost, availability, “incorrect” reasons for abortion, desire for secrecy, etc. In 1996, Khan, Barge, and Philip estimated that of the 5-6 million abortions performed per year in India, 90% were performed illegally.&lt;ref&gt;Khan, M􏰀 E􏰀, Sandhya Barge, and George Philip􏰀 1996􏰀 Abortion in India: An over- view􏰀 Social Change 26:208􏰃25􏰀&lt;/ref&gt; 

India’s second National Family Health Survey (NFHS-2), which compiled data from 1998-1999, found that, nationally, 2% of pregnancies ended in induced abortion, with higher rates in 25 of 26 states than found in the first survey (NFHS-1).&lt;ref&gt;International Institute for Population Sciences (IIPS)and ORCMacro. 2000. NationalFamilyHealthSurvey(NFHS-2),1998-99:India.Mumbai:IIPS.&lt;/ref&gt; However, many studies of the survey hypothesize that this number is a low estimate, as the full number of induced abortions was probably not reported (because of the number of abortions performed illegally). A sign of data inaccuracy was that the NFHS-2 showed higher rates of spontaneous abortion than NFHS-1. However, spontaneous abortions are primarily biologically and environmentally based, so they should not increase significantly over time. As a result, researchers have created higher estimates; Arnold, Kishor, and Roy believe that approximately 4.7% of Indian pregnancies ended in induced abortion in 2002.&lt;ref name=Arnold&gt;{{cite journal |author=Arnold, Fred, Kishor, Sunita, &amp; Roy, T. K. |year=2002 |title=Sex-Selective Abortions in India |volume=28 |issue=4 |pages=759–785 |jstor=3092788 |journal=Population and Development Review |doi=10.1111/j.1728-4457.2002.00759.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Techniques for determining sex prenatally first became available in the early 1970s and quickly gained popularity.&lt;ref&gt;Rutherford, R., and T. K. Roy. "Factors Affecting Sex-selective Abortion in Indian and 17 Major States." International Institute for Population Sciences and Honolulu: East-West Center (2003): n. pag. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; These techniques spread through most of the country very rapidly and today are typically available from mobile units (such as traveling ultrasound vans), although they have been banned for the purposes of sex determination since 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.uk/documents/post/pn198.pdf|title=Sex selection}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sudha and Rajan (1999) found that sex determination techniques are sometimes packaged together with abortions and are often marketed as being cheaper in the long run, saving the family from a large dowry in the future, should the fetus be female.&lt;ref&gt;Sudha, S. and S. Irudaya Rajan. 1999. "Female demographic disadvantage in India 1981- 1991: Sex selective abortions and female infanticide," Development and Change 30: 585- 618.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Indian government and various female advocacy groups have tried to prevent sex selection, it remains a significant issue nationwide. There is evidence that such bans are rarely enforced&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Asia-South-Central/2010/0308/Gender-selection-In-India-abortion-of-girls-on-the-rise/%28page%29/2|title=Gender selection: In India, abortion of girls on the rise}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that numerous dedicated sex selection clinics operate in many regions of India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/world/story/2006/01/11/sex-selection060111.html|title=Sex selection in India exaggerated: doctors | work=CBC News | date=January 11, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; India’s prime minister has stated that gendercide is a national shame and its secretary of health and family welfare has acknowledged that the country has not been aggressive enough in combating it. Women's rights activists allege that the laws are not being enforced because the police and judiciary believe in and may even practice gendercide themselves.&lt;ref name="Gendercide"&gt;{{cite web|url= http://abcnews.go.com/Health/women-pregnant-girls-pressured-abortions-india/story?id=15103950#.UWnN08oUlUb |title=Disappearing Daughters: Women Pregnant With Girls Pressured Into Abortions|accessdate= 14 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, there has been significant debate within India regarding the morality of sex selection. For example, there are arguments for sex selection which say that prenatal discrimination is more humane than postnatal discrimination,&lt;ref&gt;Kumar, Dharma. 1983. "Male utopias or nightmares?" Economic and Political Weekly 13(3):61-64.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gangoli, Geetanjali. 1998. "Reproduction, abortion and women's health," SocialScientist 26(11-12): 83-105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Goodkind, Daniel. 1996. "On substituting sex preference strategies in East Asia: Does pre- natalsexselectionreducepostnataldiscrimination?"PopulationandDevelopmenRte- view22(1): 111-125.&lt;/ref&gt; though there is little evidence that prenatal discrimination has any positive effect on postnatal discrimination; women are not necessarily held in higher regard if they are fewer in number.&lt;ref&gt;Goodkind, Daniel.1999. "Should prenatal sex selection be restricted? Ethical questions and their implications for research and policy," PopulationStudies53(1): 49-61.&lt;/ref&gt;

India’s 2001 census revealed a national sex ratio of 107.8, up from 105.8 in the 1991 census. Because this number is an average, it masks even more dramatic numbers in certain states—Punjab’s ratio was 126.1 (up from 114.3 in 1991), Haryana’s ratio was 122 (up from 113.8 in 1991), and Gujarat’s ratio was 113.9 (up from 107.8 in 1991). Arnold, Kishor, and Roy hypothesize that this rapid increase was due to increased availability of sex determination techniques.&lt;ref name=Arnold /&gt; In fact, Ganatra et al. (2000) found that ⅙ of all reported abortions followed a sex determination test.&lt;ref&gt;Ganatra,Bela, R. 2000. "Abortionresearch in India:What we know, and what we need to know," in Radhika Ramasubban and Shireen J. Jejeebhoy (eds.), Women's Reproductive Health in India. New Delhi: Rawat Publications.&lt;/ref&gt; However, this alone does not show causation between sex determination testing and high sex ratios. Researchers also analyzed sex ratios in women who had undergone an induced abortion in the pregnancy just before their most recent live birth. This revealed a sex ratio of 158.0 in Punjab, Haryana, and Gujarat, significantly higher than rates elsewhere in the country. Moreover, these states have very high ultrasonography use and women in these states with no sons are more likely to have an ultrasound than women with at least one son. In Haryana, the sex ratio for babies born from mothers who had ultrasounds performed is 186.3, pointing to widespread sex determination among this population.&lt;ref name=Arnold /&gt; This shows correlation between induced abortion and high sex ratios, probably pointing to the use of sex determination techniques.

India’s 2001 census found that the majority of southern states have a sex ratio at or approaching 105, the widely accepted “natural ratio.” In general, wealthier southern states have had sex ratios closer to 105 for quite some time. Gujarat, one of the states of interest with very high sex ratios in 2001, now has a child sex ratio around 112.8, an improvement since 2001 but not since 1991.&lt;ref&gt;Maps of India. "Gujarat Sex Ratio." India Census 2011. N.p., n.d. Web. 20 Oct. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; Punjab, another state of interest, now has a child sex ratio of approximately 118.2, a small improvement since 2001.&lt;ref&gt;Maps of India. "Punjab Sex Ratio." India Census 2011. N.p., n.d. Web. 20 Oct. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, Haryana’s 2011 child sex ratio was 120.4, reflecting little improvement since 2001.&lt;ref&gt;Maps of India. "Haryana Sex Ratio." India Census 2011. N.p., n.d. Web. 20 Oct. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

Overall, it is estimated that 6.4% of pregnancies with a female fetus are aborted, leading to a loss of approximately 106,000 female infants per year.&lt;ref name=Arnold /&gt;

==China==
{{POV-section|date=November 2013}}
When sex ratio began being studied in [[China]] in 1960, it was 106 males to 100 females, still within the normal range. However, it climbed to 111.9 by 1990 and 118 by 2010. &lt;ref name= Junhong&gt;Junhong, Chu. "Prenatal Sex Determination and Sex-Selective Abortion in Rural Central China." Population and Development Review 27.2 (2001): 259-81. JSTOR. Web. 2 Nov. 2013. &lt;http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/2695209?uid=2&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21102861301427&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Kang C, Wang Y. Sex ratio at birth. In: Theses Collection of 2001 National Family Planning and Reproductive Health Survey. Beijing: China Population Publishing House, 2003:88-98.&lt;/ref&gt;Researchers believe that the causes of this sex ratio imbalance are increased female infant mortality, underreporting of female births and sex-selective abortion. According to Zeng et al. (1993), the most prominent cause is probably sex-selective abortion, but it is difficult to prove that in a country with so little reliable data because of the hiding of “illegal” births. &lt;ref&gt;ZengYietal. 1993."Causesandimplicationosftherecentincreaseinthereportedsexratio at birthin China," Populationand DevelopmentReview19(2): 283-302.&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, there is extensive underreporting of female infants. However, they are eventually accounted for, as they must be registered for immunizations, education, etc. To avoid the issue of underreporting, many studies use the sex ratio for those age 20 and younger. 

Traditional Chinese techniques have been used to determine sex for hundreds of years, many with unknown accuracy. It was not until [[ultrasonography]] became widely available in urban and rural China that sex was determined scientifically. In 1986, the Ministry of Health posted the Notice on Forbidding Prenatal Sex Determination, but it was not widely followed. &lt;ref&gt;Ministry of Health and State Family Planning Commission.1986. "Notice on strictly forbidding prenatal sex determination," reprinted in Peng Peiyun(ed.), 1997,Family Planning Encyclopedia of China. Beijing: China Population Press,p. 939.&lt;/ref&gt; Three years later, in 1989, the Ministry of Health outlawed all sex determination techniques, except for their use in diagnosing hereditary disease. &lt;ref&gt;Ministry of Health. 1989. "Urgent notice on strictly forbidding the use of medical technology to perform prenatal sex determination," reprinted in Peng Peiyun (ed.), 1997,Family Planning Encyclopedia of China. Beijing: China Population Press, pp. 959-960.&lt;/ref&gt; However, many people still have personal connections to medical practitioners and strong [[son preference]] still dominates culture, leading to the widespread use of sex determination techniques. &lt;ref name=Junhong/&gt; According to Hardy, Gu, and Xie (2000), ultrasound has spread to all areas of China, as evidenced by the spread of the high sex ratio throughout the country. &lt;ref name=Xie&gt;Hardee,Karen,Gu Baochang,and Xie Zhenming.2000. "Holdingup morethanhalfthe sky:Fertilitycontroland women's empowermentin China,"paper presentedat the AnnualMeetingofthePopulationAssociationofAmerica,23-25 March,Los Angeles.&lt;/ref&gt; 

What’s more, Hardy, Gu, and Xie argue that if it’s available everywhere, sex-selective abortion will be more prevalent in rural China because son preference is so much stronger there. &lt;ref name=Xie/&gt; Urban areas of China, on average, are moving toward greater equality for both sexes. However, rural China tends to follow more traditional views of gender. For example, while sons are always part of the family, daughters are only temporary, going to a new family when they marry. Additionally, if a woman’s firstborn child is a son, her position in society moves up, while the same is not true of a firstborn daughter. &lt;ref name= Junhong/&gt;

In years past, when families wanted a son, many would keep having children until they did, resulting in a normal sex ratio. &lt;ref name=Junhong/&gt; However, the combination of financial concerns and the [[One-child policy]] (discussed further below) have led to an increase in gender planning and selection. Even in rural areas, most women know that ultrasonography can be used for gender discernment. For each subsequent birth, Junhong found that women are over 10% more likely to have an ultrasound (39% for firstborn, 55% for second born, 67% for third born). Additionally, he found that the sex of the firstborn child impacts whether a woman will have an ultrasound in her subsequent pregnancies: 40% of women with a firstborn son have an ultrasound for their second born child. For women with firstborn daughters, this number jumps to 70%, pointing to a strong desire to select for a son if one has not been born yet. &lt;ref name=Junhong/&gt;

Unfortunately, Junhong also found that many women don’t see a female child as a burden, but rather are pressured to produce a male son. Additionally, 85% of women would try to have two children, ideally one boy and one girl, if there were no restrictions on children. Most women will take steps to ensure their second child is a boy, if the first is a girl. However, they will not take steps to ensure their second child is a girl if the first is a boy, as it is too expensive. &lt;ref name=Junhong/&gt;

Because of the lack of data about childbirth, a number of researchers have worked to learn about abortion statistics in China. One of the earliest studies by Qui (1987) found that according to cultural belief, fetuses are not thought of as human beings until they are born, leading to a cultural preference for abortion over infanticide. &lt;ref&gt;Qiu Renzong.1987.LifeEthicsS.hanghai:ShanghaiPeople'sPress&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, [[infanticide]] and infant abandonment are rather rare in China today. &lt;ref name= Junhong/&gt; Junhong (2000) found that 27% of those surveyed had an abortion. Additionally, he found that if a family’s firstborn was a girl, 92% of known female would-be second born fetuses were aborted. &lt;ref&gt;Junhong, Chu. 2000. "Studyon thequalityofthefamilyplanningprogramin China,"paperersentedattheAnnualMeetingofthePopulationAssociationofAmerica,23-25 March,
Los Angeles.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2005 study, Zhu, Lu, and Hesketh found that the sex ratio for those ages 1-4 was highest overall, and only two provinces, Tibet and Xinjiang, had sex ratios within normal limits. Two provinces had a ratio over 140, four had ratios between 130-139, and seven had ratios between 120-129. &lt;ref name=Hesketh&gt;Zhu, W., L. Lu, and T Hesketh. "China’s Excess Males, Sex Selective Abortion, and One Child Policy: Analysis of Data from 2005 National Intercensus Survey." British Medical Journal (2009): n. pag. JSTOR. Web. 2 Nov. 2013. &lt;http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/20512658?uid=2129&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=70&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21102861713637&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; There are three types of provinces, which vary in restrictive nature of their childbearing laws. Type one is the most restrictive, where only 40% of couples are allowed a second child, and only if their firstborn is a girl. These provinces tend to be wealthier and more educated, and many parents have a pension to take care of them, eliminating the need for a son. &lt;ref name=Hesketh/&gt; Therefore, they have medium sex ratios and Winckler (2002) that traditional gender preferences are changing toward more equality. &lt;ref&gt;Winckler, Edwin A. "Chinese Reproductive Policy at the Turn of the Millennium: Dynamic Stability." Population and Development Review 28.3 (2002): 379-418. &lt;/ref&gt;In type two provinces, everyone with a firstborn daughter is allowed a second child. Additionally, parents who have a documented hardship (as determined by a local official) are allowed a second child. These provinces tend to have more traditional structure and agriculturally-based economy, causing a need for a son. Therefore, sex ratio is highest in type two provinces. &lt;ref name=Hesketh/&gt; Finally, type three provinces always allow a second child, regardless of the firstborn’s gender, and sometimes allow a third. These provinces are often poor and underpopulated and neither have a preference for sons nor believe in abortion, resulting in the lowest sex ratios. &lt;ref name=Hesketh/&gt; Based on the relationship between type of province and sex ratio, many researchers believe making type two provinces into type one or three could dramatically lower the sex ratio. &lt;ref name=Hesketh/&gt;

Families in China are aware of the critical lack of female children and it’s implication on marriage prospects in the future; many parents are beginning to work extra when their sons are young so that they will be able to pay for a bride for them. &lt;ref name=Junhong/&gt; Because of the rising awareness of the imbalance in China’s sex ratio, measures to lower it are beginning to take place. For example, in 2000, the Chinese government began the “Care for Girls” Initiative. &lt;ref&gt;"'Care For Girls' Gaining Momentum." 'Care For Girls' Gaining Momentum. China Daily, 07 Aug. 2004. Web. 03 Nov. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; The sex ratio among firstborn children in urban areas from 2000-2005 didn’t rise at all, so there is hope that this movement is taking hold across the nation. &lt;ref name=Junhong/&gt;

==United States==
Like in other countries, sex-selective abortion is difficult to track in the [[United States]] because of lack of data. However, based on the sex ratios in the United States, it is certainly rare for the population overall. Abrevaya (2009) found that among firstborn children in the U.S., the sex ratio is the normal 102-106 males per 100 females. However, he also found that among some Korean, Chinese, and Indian parents with one daughter, the sex ratio is 117 and when they have two daughters, the ratio is 151. &lt;ref&gt;Abrevaya, Jason. "Are There Missing Girls in the United States? Evidence from Birth Data." American Economic Journal: Applied Economics 1.2 (2009): 1-34.&lt;/ref&gt;

While the majority of parents in United States do not practice sex-selective abortion, there is certainly a trend toward male preference. According to a 2011 [[Gallup poll]], if they were only allowed to have one child, 49% of men and 31% of women would prefer a son. &lt;ref&gt;Newport, Frank. "Americans Prefer Boys to Girls, Just as They Did in 1941." Gallup, 23 June 2011. Web. 2 Nov. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; When told about prenatal sex selection techniques such as sperm sorting and in vitro fertilization embryo selection, 40% of Americans surveyed thought that picking embryos by sex was an acceptable manifestation of reproductive rights. &lt;ref name=Jesudason&gt;Jesudason, Sujatha, and Anat Shenker-Osorio. "The Atlantic." The Atlantic. N.p., 31 May 2012. Web. 03 Nov. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; These selecting techniques are available at about half of American fertility clinics, as of 2006. &lt;ref&gt;"Half Fertility Clinics Allow Parents to Pick Gender." Msnbc.com. Associated Press, 20 Sept. 2006. Web. 03 Nov. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of this movement toward sex preference and selection, many bans on sex-selective abortion have been proposed at the state and federal level.  In 2010 and 2011, sex-selective abortions were banned in [[Oklahoma]] and [[Arizona]], respectively. Legislators in [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], [[West Virginia]], [[Michigan]], [[Minnesota]], [[New Jersey]], and [[New York]] have also tried to pass acts banning the procedure. &lt;ref name=Jesudason/&gt;

==Other countries==
Abnormal sex ratios at birth, possibly explained by growing incidence of sex-selective abortion, have also been noted in some other countries outside South and East Asia. According to the 2011 CIA [[The World Factbook|World Factbook]], countries with more than 110 males per 100 females at birth also include [[Albania]] and former Soviet republics of [[Armenia]] and [[Azerbaijan]].
A 2005 study estimated that over 90 million females were "missing" from the expected population in [[Afghanistan]], [[Bangladesh]], [[China]], [[India]], [[Pakistan]], [[South Korea]] and [[Taiwan]] alone, and suggested that sex-selective abortion plays a role in this deficit.&lt;ref name= "Gettis"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wilsoncenter.org/topics/pubs/Hudson&amp;denBoer.pdf Layout 1&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; India's 2011 census shows a serious decline in the number of girls under the age of seven - activists believe eight million female [[fetus]]es may have been aborted between 2001 and 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pandey|first=Geeta|title=India's unwanted girls|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-13264301|publisher=[[BBC News]]|accessdate=23 May 2011|date=May 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Sex-selection practices also occur among some South Asian immigrants in the United States: A study of the 2000 United States Census observed definite male bias in families of Chinese, Korean and Indian immigrants, which was getting increasingly stronger in families where first one or two children were female. In those families where the first two children were girls, the sex ratio of the third child was observed to be 1.51:1 in favor of boys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/15/nyregion/15babies.html?_r=2&amp;pagewanted=1&amp;hp|title=U.S. Births Hint at Bias for Boys in Some Asians | work=The New York Times | first=Sam | last=Roberts | date=June 15, 2009 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reasons for sex-selective abortion==
Some research suggests that culture plays a larger role than economic conditions in gender preference and sex-selective abortion, because such deviations in sex ratios do not exist in [[sub-Saharan Africa]], [[Latin America]], and the [[Caribbean]].&lt;ref name= "Gettis"/&gt; Demographers argue that perceived gender imbalances may arise from the underreporting of female births, rather than sex-selective abortion or infanticide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi=10.2307/1972351 | title=The missing girls of China: a new demographic account | last=Johansson | first=Sten | last2=Nygren | jstor=1972351 | first2=Olga | year=1991 | volume=17 | issue=1 | journal = Population and Development Review | pages=35&amp;ndash;51}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title=Are births underreported in rural China? | first=M. Giovanna | last=Merli | first2=Adrian E. | last2=Raftery | journal=Demography | volume=37 | issue=1 | year=2000 | pages=109–126 |doi=10.2307/2648100 |jstor=2648100 | pmid=10748993}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cultural preference===
The reason for intensifying sex-selection abortion in China and India can be seen through history and cultural background. Generally, before the [[information era]], male babies were preferred because they provided manual labor and success the family [[lineage]]. Labor is still important in developing nations as China and India, but when it comes to family lineage, it is of great importance.
The selective abortion of female fetuses is most common in areas where cultural norms value male children over female children.&lt;ref name="Goodkind"/&gt; A son is often preferred as an "asset" since he can earn and support the family; a daughter is a "liability" since she will be married off to another family, and so will not contribute financially to her parents. The patriarchal structure of a society is the single most important factor skewing the sex ratio in favor of males, accentuated in some cultures by the burden of raising a [[dowry]] for a daughter's marriage. Openness to the very concept of sex selection is a significant factor: among societies which practice selective female abortion nowadays, many were systematically practicing [[female infanticide]] (either directly or by withholding postnatal care from children of undesirable sex) long before abortion became a viable option.&lt;ref name="Gupta_2005"&gt;Das Gupta, Monica, "Explaining Asia's Missing Women": A New Look at the Data", 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, in some cultures sons are expected to take care of their parents in their old age.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2007.01.004}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In modern East Asia, a large part of the pattern of preferences leading to this practice can be condensed simply as a desire to have a male heir. Monica Das Gupta (2005) observes that, in late 1980s to early 1990s China, there was no evidence of selective abortion of female fetuses among firstborn children, or in families with one or more existing sons (in fact, families with multiple sons were, if anything, more likely to abort a boy than a girl). But, at the same time, families with existing daughters appeared very likely to abort any further female fetuses, resulting in heavily skewed sex ratios.&lt;ref name="Gupta_2005" /&gt;

===Sexual discrimination===
The role of many women in nations that are prone to sex-selection abortion is to stay home, do house chores, and raise children. She is mutely banned to work in the society, pressured by family and discouraged by society. Lower salary, working in temporary or non-regular jobs, and lower status at work is often the case even for women who do work. In these societies, mothers are compelled to assist their husbands and raise their children, sparing no time for self-development. All in all, in cultures that practice sex-selective abortion, women are prone to [[sexual discrimination]] and are viewed as inferior to men.{{Citation needed|reason=Very biased, need at least some sources|date=April 2013}}

===One-child policy===
The 1960s scare for overpopulation led governments to implement laws to control birth rate such as the ''[[one-child policy]]''. Accordingly, it led to consequence where parents highly value boys over girls; even to a point were words such as "[[infanticide]]" come into existence. Infanticide has come to be known as the "Holocaust for baby girls". What’s more, her child will follow the husband’s surname and is restricted to visit her parents whenever she wishes. These kinds of cultural practice mixed with the government implications of one-child policy have caused one-daughter parents to become ‘’childless’’ after the marriage. As a result, these parent no longer have a financially supporting or lineage successor. Thus, for parents to ensure financial dependence and hereditary successor, a boy must be born. In this regard, the pervasion of male dominant culture and one-child policy heightens the sex-selective abortion.

===Trivers–Willard hypothesis===
The [[Trivers–Willard hypothesis]] argues that available resources affect male [[reproductive success]] more than female and that consequently parents should prefer males when resources are plentiful and females when resources are scarce. This has been applied to resource differences between individuals in a society and also to resource differences between societies. Empirical evidence is mixed with higher support in better studies according to Cronk in a 2007 review. One example, in a 1997 study, of a group with a preference for females was [[Romani people|Romani]] in [[Hungary]], a low status group. They "had a female-biased sex ratio at birth, were more likely to abort a fetus after having had one or more daughters, nursed their daughters longer, and sent their daughters to school for longer."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/S1472-6483(10)60546-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Genetic===
Gender-linked genetic abnormalities, such as several forms of [[colorblindness]], are linked to [[recessive genes]] on the [[X chromosome]]. Pre-implantation genetic diagnosis can identify some life-threatening genetic abnormalities in [[embryo]]. The easiest way to select against embryos which may have a gender-linked genetic abnormality is to choose only female embryos. Embryos which are not implanted are usually discarded.

==Societal effects==

===Demography issues and wifeless men===
The strong preference on boys over girls will bring about a serious problem: millions of wifeless men. In years to come, the skewed ratio of men and women could cause men to have difficulty finding brides. There are reports of women from [[Vietnam]], [[Myanmar]], and [[North Korea]] systematically trafficked to mainland [[China]] and [[Taiwan]] and sold into forced marriages.&lt;ref name="Hvistendahl_WSJ"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702303657404576361691165631366.html?mod=googlenews_wsj|title=The War Against Girls | work=The Wall Street Journal | first=Jonathan V.|last=Last|date=June 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[South Korea]] and [[Taiwan]], high male sex ratios and declining birth rates over several decades have led to cross-cultural marriage between local men and foreign women from countries such as mainland China, Vietnam and the Philippines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/22/world/asia/22brides.html?pagewanted=all | work=The New York Times | first=Norimitsu | last=Onishi | title=Korean Men Use Brokers to Find Brides in Vietnam | date=February 22, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Trafficking=== 
Some argue that sex-selective abortion will actually lead to women gaining a higher position in society. For instance, Park and Cho (1995) say that when women are in smaller supply (as will be the case in the future in nations with high sex ratios), they will be more valued. &lt;ref&gt;Park,Chai Bin and Nam-HoonCho. 1995. "Consequencesofson preferencien a low-fertil- itysociety:Imbalanceofthesex ratioatbirthin Korea,"PopulationandDevelopment Review21(1): 59-84.&lt;/ref&gt; However, most say that this is not the case-- even when there are few women, they are still trafficked. In fact, some argue that [[trafficking]] may actually get worse when there are fewer women, as men will be willing to go to more elaborate measures to get women. &lt;ref name=Junhong /&gt; 

===Measures being taken===
[[File:G106-Dajipu-to-Daye-hills-0068.jpg|thumb|A roadside slogan calls motorists to crack down on medically unnecessary antenatal sex identification and sex-selective pregnancy termination practices. ([[Daye, Hubei]], 2008)]]
NGOs such as the [[Gendercide Watch]] and [[Population Research Institute]] have been created to address the issue of sex-selective abortion and female infanticide{{citation needed|date=August 2012}}.

In Punjab, India, government and NGO networks have set up orphanages to shelter the unwanted girls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/india/5004051/E-cradle-saves-Indias-abandoned-babies.html | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Dean | last=Nelson | title=E-cradle saves India's abandoned babies | date=March 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1994 over 180 states signed the Programme of Action of the [[International Conference on Population and Development]], agreeing to "eliminate all forms of discrimination against the girl child".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unfpa.org/webdav/site/global/shared/documents/publications/2011/Preventing_gender-biased_sex_selection.pdf|title=Preventing gender-biased sex selection|publisher=[[UNFPA]]|accessdate=1 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011 the resolution of [[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe|PACE]]'s Committee on Equal Opportunities for Women and Men condemned the practice of prenatal sex selection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://assembly.coe.int/Documents/WorkingDocs/Doc11/EDOC12715.pdf|title=Prenatal sex selection|publisher=[[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe|PACE]]|accessdate=1 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Canada, a group of MPs led by [[Mark Warawa]] are working on having the [[Canadian Parliament|Parliament]] pass a resolution condemning sex-selective pregnancy termination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Jones|first=Natasha|title=MP takes aim at sex selection|url=http://www.langleytimes.com/news/172874451.html|work=The Langley Times|accessdate=October 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mark Kennedy, [http://news.nationalpost.com/2013/03/26/mp-continues-push-for-sex-selection-abortions-vote-after-motion-rejected/ MP continues push for sex-selection abortions vote after motion rejected], Postmedia News, 2013-03-26&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Congress]] has debated legislation that would outlaw the practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.cnn.com/2012/05/30/politics/house-abortion-gender/index.html | title=House debates abortion ban for sex of fetus | work=CNN Online | date=May 31, 2012 | accessdate=May 31, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The legislation ultimately failed to pass in the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/06/01/us/politics/house-rejects-bill-to-ban-sex-selective-abortions.html?_r=1 | title=House Rejects Bill to Ban Sex-Selective Abortions | work=New York Times | date=May 31, 2012 | accessdate=May 31, 2010 | first=Jennifer | last=Steinhauer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the state level, laws against sex-selective abortions have been passed in a number of US states;&lt;ref name=christie20130529&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/05/29/arizona-abortion-ban-race-sex_n_3355493.html|title=Arizona Race And Sex-Selective Abortion Ban Draws ACLU Lawsuit|first=Bob|last=Christie|date=2013-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; the law passed in [[Arizona]]  in 2011 prohibits both sex-selective and race-selective abortion.&lt;ref name=christie20130529/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.azleg.gov/legtext/50leg/1r/bills/hb2443p.pdf|title=HB 2443: An Act amending Title 13, Chapter 36, Arizona Revised Statutes, by adding section 13-3603.02; ....}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.azleg.state.az.us/FormatDocument.asp?inDoc=/ars/13/03603-02.htm&amp;Title=13&amp;DocType=ARS|title=Arizona Revised Statutes, 13-3603.02. Abortion; sex and race selection; injunctive and civil relief; failure to report; definition}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
*The Manish Jha film, ''[[Matrubhoomi-A Nation Without Women]]'' (2003), depicts a [[future]] [[dystopia]] in a village in India, populated exclusively by males due to female infanticide, and which is reduced to barbarianism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/296804/Matrubhoomi/overview|title=Matrubhoomi (2003)|work=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{|width=100%
|-valign=top
|width=50%|
* [[Abortion debate]]
* [[Child abandonment]]
* [[Fetal rights]]
* [[Feticide]]
* [[Gendercide]]
* [[Missing women of Asia]]
|width=100%|
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Genetics and abortion]]
* [[Psychohistorical views on infanticide]]
* [[Selective reduction]]
* [[Sex selection]]
|}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.cicred.org/Eng/Seminars/FDA/Femaledeficit.htm ''A conference held in Singapore in December 2005 on female deficit in Asia'']
* [http://www.singstat.gov.sg/ssn/feat/1Q95/feat.html Sex Selection at Birth; ''Statistics Singapore Newsletter, Vol 17 No.3 January 1995'']
* [http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3990133/ MSNBC - No Girls Please - In parts of Asia, sexism is ingrained and gender selection often means murder]
* [http://www.alexandersanger.com/articles/2003_03_21.html Surplus Males and US/China Relations]
* [http://chronicle.com/free/v50/i34/34a01401.htm ''A Dangerous Surplus of Sons?''] - An analysis of various studies of the lopsided sex ratios in Asian countries
* [http://www.gendercide.org/case_infanticide.html Case study: Female Infanticide] in India and China
* [http://www.cid.harvard.edu/cidwp/pdf/grad_student/007.pdf Working paper by Emily Oster linking sex ratio imbalances to hepatitis B infection]
* [http://www.portlethenacademy.aberdeenshire.sch.uk/depts/mod-studs/chinarep.htm S2 China Report - China: The Effects of the One Child Policy]
* [http://www.unescap.org/esid/psis/population/database/poplaws/law%5Fchina/ch%5Frecord020.htm Notification on Addressing in a Comprehensive Way the Issue of Rising Sex Ratio at Birth] a [[UNESCAP]] document
* [http://www.cicred.org/Eng/Publications/pdf/BOOK_singapore.pdf A collection of essays on sex selection in various Asian countries by Attané and Guilmoto]
* [http://www.unfpa.org/gender/case_studies.htm Five case studies and a video on sex selection in Asia by UNFPA]
* [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5293148 ''NPR, All Things Considered, India Confronts Gender-Selective Abortion, March 21, 2006'']
* [http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702303657404576361691165631366.html ''Book Review: Unnatural Selection] - The War Against Girls / WSJ.com

{{Abortion}}
{{Social issues in India}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sex-Selective Abortion}}
[[Category:Female foeticide and infanticide]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>