<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081111161534|251121851" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12210765" pageid="12210765" ns="0" title="Diversity (politics)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-11T21:16:52Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=October 2007}}
{{Unreferenced|date=January 2008}}
In the political arena, the term '''diversity''' (or diverse) is used to describe political entities (neighborhoods, cities, nations, student bodies, etc.) with members who have identifiable differences in their backgrounds or lifestyles.  The use of the term '''diversity''' may encompass differences in racial or [[ethnic group|ethnic classifications]], age, [[gender]], [[religion]], philosophy, [[disability|physical abilities]], [[socioeconomic]] background, [[sexual orientation]], [[gender identity]], [[intelligence]], [[mental health]], physical [[health]], [[Genetics|genetic]] attributes, [[behavior]], [[attractiveness]], place of origin, cultural values, or political view as well as other identifying features. 

Political [[creed]]s which support the idea that diversity is valuable and desirable hold that recognizing and promoting these diverse cultures may aid [[communication]] between people of different backgrounds and lifestyles, leading to greater knowledge, understanding, and peaceful coexistence.{{Fact|date=August 2007}} For example, "Respect for Diversity" is one of the six principles of the [[Global Greens Charter]], a [[manifesto]] subscribed to by [[Green party|Green parties]] from all over the world. In contrast to diversity, some political creeds promote [[cultural assimilation]] as the process to lead to these ends.

{{world}}
This use of '''diversity''' in this sense also extends to American [[academia]], wherein an attempt to create a "diverse student body" typically supports the [[recruitment]] of [[students]] from historically excluded populations, such as students of [[African-American]] or [[latino|Latina/o]] background as well as women in such historically underrepresented fields as the [[sciences]].



[[Category:Politics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>