<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241018063000|1251814021" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12210765" pageid="12210765" ns="0" title="Diversity (politics)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-10-19T20:37:28Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Concept in sociology and political studies}}
{{For|diversity outside of sociology and political science|Diversity (disambiguation){{!}}Diversity}}
{{multiple issues|
{{Cleanup|date=March 2012}}
{{one source|date=October 2013}}
{{Original research|date=August 2017}}
}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Related}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2024}}
'''Diversity''' within groups is a key concept in [[sociology]] and [[political science]] that refers to the degree of difference along socially significant identifying features among the members of a purposefully defined group, such as any group differences in [[Race (human categorization)|racial]] or [[Ethnicity|ethnic classifications]], [[Ageing|age]], [[gender]], [[religion]], [[philosophy]], [[politics]], [[cultural diversity|culture]], [[Language#Linguistic diversity|language]], [[Disability|physical abilities]], [[Socioeconomics|socioeconomic background]], [[sexual orientation]], [[gender identity]], [[intelligence]], [[Health|physical health]], [[mental health]], [[Genetics|genetic attributes]], [[personality]], [[behavior]], or [[Physical attractiveness|attractiveness]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.qcc.cuny.edu/|title=Queensborough Community College|website=www.qcc.cuny.edu|language=en|access-date=27 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When measuring human diversity, a [[diversity index]] exemplifies the likelihood that two randomly selected residents have different ethnicities. If all residents are of the same ethnic group it is zero by definition. If half are from one group and half from another, it is 50. The diversity index does not take into account the willingness of individuals to cooperate with those of other ethnicities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/diversity/neighborhood/list/ "Mapping L.A..," ''Los Angeles Times'' website]&lt;/ref&gt;

==International human rights==
{{Further|Inclusion (disability rights)}}
The [[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]] affirms to "respect difference and acceptance of persons with disabilities as human diversity and [[human nature|humanity]]" for protection of human rights of persons with disabilities.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.ohchr.org/en/instruments-mechanisms/instruments/convention-rights-persons-disabilities Article 3.d Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, UN]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ideology==
{{Main|Diversity ideologies|New Left|Multiculturalism}}
Political [[creed]]s which support the idea that diversity is valuable and desirable hold that recognizing and promoting these{{Which|date=December 2021}} diverse cultures may aid [[communication]] between people of different backgrounds and lifestyles, leading to greater knowledge, understanding, and peaceful coexistence.{{Citation needed|date=August 2007}} For example, "Respect for Diversity" is one of the six principles of the [[Global Greens Charter]], a [[manifesto]] subscribed to by [[Green party|green parties]] from all over the world. In contrast to diversity, some political creeds promote [[cultural assimilation]] as the process to lead to these ends.

==Types of diversity==
===Cultural diversity===
{{Excerpt|Cultural diversity|paragraphs=1|only=paragraphs}}
[[File:List of countries ranked by ethnic and cultural diversity level, List based on Fearon's analysis.png|thumb|right|Global ethnic and cultural diversity, orange is higher.&lt;ref name="fearon"&gt;{{cite journal |first=James |last=Fearon |year=2003 |title=Ethnic and Cultural Diversity by Country |journal=Journal of Economic Growth |volume=8 |issue=2 |pages=195–222 |doi=10.1023/A:1024419522867 |s2cid=152680631}}&lt;/ref&gt;
]]

===Functional diversity===
{{Excerpt|Functional diversity (disability)|paragraphs=1|only=paragraphs}}

===Gender diversity===
{{Excerpt|Gender diversity|paragraphs=1|only=paragraphs}}

===Gerodiversity===
{{Excerpt|Gerodiversity|paragraphs=1|only=paragraphs}}

===Neurodiversity===
{{Excerpt|Neurodiversity|paragraphs=1|only=paragraphs}}

===Sexual diversity===
{{Excerpt|Sexual diversity|paragraphs=1|only=paragraphs}}

===In Education===
This use of ''diversity'' in this sense{{Which|date=December 2021}} also extends to American [[academy]], where in an attempt to create a "diverse student body" typically supports the [[recruitment]] of [[students]] from historically excluded populations, such as students of [[African Americans|African American]] or [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Latino]] background as well as women in such historically underrepresented fields as the [[sciences]].{{citation needed|date=December 2021}}

===In workplace===
Corporations make commitments to diversity in their personnel both for reasons of brand halo and competitive advantage, but progress is slow.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/rsmdiscovery/2018/08/22/why-workplace-diversity-is-so-important-and-why-its-so-hard-to-achieve/|title=Why Workplace Diversity Is So Important, And Why It's So Hard To Achieve|last=Discovery|first=R. S. M.|website=Forbes|language=en|access-date=27 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{clarification needed|date=December 2021}}

==Gender in Politics==
Historically, women have been underrepresented in politics compared to men. Women's rights movements, such as [[feminism]], have addressed the marginalization of women in politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Celis|first=Karen|date=1 November 2013|title=Representativity in times of diversity: The political representation of women|url=https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0277539513001283|journal=Women's Studies International Forum|series=Pregnant politicians and sexy fathers? The politics of gender equality representations in Europe|language=en|volume=41|pages=179–186|doi=10.1016/j.wsif.2013.07.007|issn=0277-5395|url-access=subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite traditional doubts concerning female leadership, women have governed for at least a year in about one in four countries since 1960.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Reyes-Housholder |first=Catherine |date=September 2020 |title=A Theory of Gender's Role on Presidential Approval Ratings in Corrupt Times |url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1065912919838626 |journal=Political Research Quarterly |language=en |volume=73 |issue=3 |pages=540–555 |doi=10.1177/1065912919838626 |issn=1065-9129}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
Among the 61 Prime Ministers of the U.K. (Kingdom of Great Britain until 1801) there have been 3 women: [[Margaret Thatcher]] (1979&amp;ndash;1990), [[Theresa May]] (2016&amp;ndash;2019), [[Liz Truss]] (2022).

=== United States ===
There has been an increase in women taking on leadership roles in both the public and private sectors of many countries, including the United States.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Ferreira |first1=Fernando |last2=Gyourko |first2=Joseph |date=April 2014 |title=Does gender matter for political leadership? The case of U.S. mayors |url=https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpubeco.2014.01.006 |journal=Journal of Public Economics |volume=112 |pages=24–39 |doi=10.1016/j.jpubeco.2014.01.006 |issn=0047-2727}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, there is still a "political gap" between men and women.  Women are less likely than similarly situated men to consider running for office; less likely to run for office; less like to believe they are qualified to seek office; less likely to receive encouragement to run for office; and more likely to perceive a competitive, biased electoral environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Fox |first1=Richard L. |last2=Lawless |first2=Jennifer L. |date=August 2014 |title=Uncovering the Origins of the Gender Gap in Political Ambition |url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/american-political-science-review/article/uncovering-the-origins-of-the-gender-gap-in-political-ambition/F982DF854F45E1954AD0F5C7B9509353 |journal=American Political Science Review |language=en |volume=108 |issue=3 |pages=499–519 |doi=10.1017/S0003055414000227 |issn=0003-0554}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== White House Executive Offices ====
Administrations since [[Franklin D. Roosevelt|Franklin Roosevelt]]'s have placed aides and units charged with specific outreach to interests and constituencies in the "West Wing".&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctvrdf3zm |title=The Gendered Executive: A Comparative Analysis of Presidents, Prime Ministers, and Chief Executives |date=2016 |publisher=Temple University Press |isbn=978-1-4399-1363-5 |doi=10.2307/j.ctvrdf3zm.12|jstor=j.ctvrdf3zm }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, specific positions and units devoted to women did not appear in the [[White House Office]]s until the late 1960s under [[John F. Kennedy]]'s administration. Kennedy appointed [[Esther Peterson]] to be assistant secretary of labor and direct the department’s Women’s Bureau. Peterson worked to pass the Equal Pay Act of 1963 and was one of many to urge Kennedy to create the President’s Commission on the Status of Women. After Kennedy’s assassination, [[Lyndon B. Johnson|Johnson]] named her to an additional post for consumer affairs. Johnson’s administration's efforts to boost the representation of women revolved around highlighting consumer issues.&lt;ref name=":3"/&gt;

President [[Richard Nixon]] did not appoint a woman assistant to the President’s Task Force on Women’s Rights and Responsibilities, Nixon appointed [[Anne L. Armstrong|Anne Armstrong]] to the most senior WHO position: counselor to the president with cabinet rank. However, she was overwhelmed along with her small staff of two people and did not get to focus on representing women. Her work didn’t particularly concern women’s rights, however, scholars agree that she was an important step for the White House to have female representation in the offices, she “brought a new perspective to White House deliberations ensuring that names of women were included as candidates for vacant positions”. Armstrong was one of the first women to have direct access to the president as a White House staffer.&lt;ref name=":3"/&gt;

President [[Bill Clinton]] sought to build support among women more generally, especially following the 1990s healthcare debacle and the [[1994 United States elections|election of 1994]], which the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] faced substantial losses. In 1995, the administration created the White House Office for Women’s Initiatives and Outreach (OWIO). This was created to “better serve President Clinton’s constituents”. OWIO hosted many events and roundtable discussions and linked with many external organizations. The author states that these actions are symbolic representations. It was initially successful at connecting with women’s groups and providing their findings to the President. However, in 1996, OWIO’s activities substantially declined with the 1996 election and staff changes.&lt;ref name=":3"/&gt;

===== Mayors in the US =====
Local governments in the United States certainly have experienced an upsurge in female participation in politics. The graph depicts the increase in female participation in mayoral elections from 1950 to 2005 (see below).&lt;ref name=":1"/&gt; The graph utilizes a regression discontinuity design to mitigate the potential influence of city characteristics on the candidacy of women. The findings reveal that the gender of the mayor has no discernible effect on various policy outcomes, such as the scale of local government, the allocation of municipal resources, or crime rates. These conclusions hold true both in the short term and over extended periods. Despite this lack of policy divergence, female mayors exhibit heightened political efficacy, indicated by a notable increase in their incumbent advantage compared to male counterparts. Electing a female mayor didn't have a big impact on whether other women could win elections later on. Having a female mayor did not make it easier for other women to get elected as mayors or in local congressional races.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
[[File:Female Mayoral participation between 1950 and 2005.jpg|thumb|The proportion of elections with at least one female candidate and proportion of female wins.]]

=== Latin America ===
Associations between women and integrity appear in Latin America where 32.6 percent of citizens in 2012 said that men are more corrupt as politicians while just 4 percent said women are more corrupt.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Explanations for this “pro-women” stereotype relate to women’s historical status as outsiders as well as their traditional identities as mothers.

[[Michelle Bachelet|Michelle Bachelet's]] 2006 election marked the beginning of a string of ''presidenta'' victories in Latin America. She set records for presidential popularity in Chile during her first term, and won reelection in one of the most lopsided contests in the country’s history. However, a scandal ''(Caso Caval)'' erupted in February 2015, where her daughter-in-law and son, [[Sebastián Dávalos]], were accused of tax fraud. Dávalos was the Social-Cultural Director, a position traditionally reserved for first ladies. He resigned ten days later.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

Although Bachelet was never directly involved in the scandal, her approval ratings fell from 42 percent in the last quarter of 2014 to 36 percent in the first quarter of 2015 (the period immediately after ''Caso Caval'' erupted), 31 percent in the second quarter, and 27 percent in the third quarter. These numbers never fully bounced back, hitting 38 percent by February 2018.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==Race in politics==
===United Kingdom===
[[Rishi Sunak]] (since 2022) is the first non-white Prime Minister of the U.K.

===United States===
In American politics, white men have often been represented more compared to people of color. There has only been one black president, [[Barack Obama]]. All of the other 44 U.S. presidents have been white men. In other sections of U.S. politics, the number of people of color represented has gradually increased each year since the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last1=Uberoi|first1=Elise|last2=Burton|first2=Matthew|date=30 September 2022|title=Ethnic diversity in politics and public life|url=https://commonslibrary.parliament.uk/research-briefings/sn01156/|access-date=5 November 2022|website=The House of Commons Library}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ethnicity in politics==
===Soviet Union===
[[Korenizatsiia]] in 1920s and early 1930s Soviet Union promoted diversity by increasing the representation of non-Russian ethnic groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Liber |first1=George |title=Korenizatsiia: Restructuring Soviet nationality policy in the 1920s |journal=Ethnic and Racial Studies |date=January 1991 |volume=14 |issue=1 |page=15 |doi=10.1080/01419870.1991.9993696 |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01419870.1991.9993696 |language=en |issn=0141-9870 |quotation=In April 1923 the Russian Communist Party formalized the policy of korenizatsiia (indigenization or nativization){{nbsp}}...}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==See also==
&lt;!---♦♦♦ Please keep the list in alphabetical order ♦♦♦---&gt;&lt;!---♦♦♦ No red links in see also section ♦♦♦---&gt;{{div col}}
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Discrimination]]
* [[Diversity, equity, and inclusion]]
* [[Diversity training]]
* [[Ethnopluralism]]
* [[Heterodox Academy]] (''viewpoint'' diversity in academy)
* [[Identity politics]]
* [[Individual and group rights]]
* [[Linguistic diversity index]]
* [[Multiculturalism]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Diversity (business)|Workplace diversity]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{Citation |last1=Iwasaki |first1=M. |title=Diversity in Mind and Action: Social, Psychological, and Political Challenges |volume=4 |year=2009 |editor-last=Chin |editor-first=J.L. |chapter=Gerodiversity and social justice: Voices of minority elders |place=Westport, CT |publisher=Praeger |last2=Tazeau |first2=Y.N. |last3=Kimmel |first3=D. |last4=Baker |first4=N.L. |last5=McCallum |first5=T.J.}}&lt;!-- {{sfn|Iwasaki|Tazeau|Kimmel|Baker|2009|p=}} --&gt;

==External links==
* {{Wikiquote-inline}}

{{Discrimination}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Linguistic controversies]]
[[Category:Affirmative action]]
[[Category:Identity politics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>