<?xml version="1.0"?><api batchcomplete=""><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12210765" pageid="12210765" ns="0" title="Diversity (politics)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-08-20T17:36:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{Refimprove|date=October 2010}}
{{Cleanup|date=March 2012}}
{{one source|date=October 2013}}
}}
In [[sociology]] and [[political studies]], the term '''diversity''' (or ''diverse'') is used to describe political entities (neighborhoods, student bodies, etc.) with members who have identifiable differences in their cultural backgrounds or lifestyles.

The term describes differences in racial or [[ethnic group|ethnic classifications]], age, [[gender]], [[religion]], philosophy, [[disability|physical abilities]], [[socioeconomic]] background, [[sexual orientation]], [[gender identity]], [[intelligence]], [[mental health]], physical [[health]], [[Genetics|genetic]] attributes, [[behavior]], [[attractiveness]], or other identifying features.

In measuring human diversity, a [[diversity index]] measures the probability that any two residents, chosen at random, would be of different ethnicities. If all residents are of the same ethnic group it's zero. The diversity index does not take into account the willingness of individuals to cooperate with those of other ethnicities. If half are from one group and half from another it's .50.&lt;ref&gt;[http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/diversity/neighborhood/list/ "Mapping L.A..," ''Los Angeles Times'' website]&lt;/ref&gt;

==International human rights law==
The [[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]] affirms to "respect difference and acceptance persons with disabilities as human diversity and [[human nature|humanity]]" for protection of human rights of persons with disabilities.&lt;ref&gt;[[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]], Article 3 "General Principles", (c)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ideology==
{{Main|New Left|Multiculturalism}}
Political [[creed]]s which support the idea that diversity is valuable and desirable hold that recognizing and promoting these diverse cultures may aid [[communication]] between people of different backgrounds and lifestyles, leading to greater knowledge, understanding, and peaceful coexistence.{{Citation needed|date=August 2007}} For example, "Respect for Diversity" is one of the six principles of the [[Global Greens Charter]], a [[manifesto]] subscribed to by [[Green party|Green parties]] from all over the world. In contrast to diversity, some political creeds promote [[cultural assimilation]] as the process to lead to these ends.

===Use in American academia===
This use of ''diversity'' in this sense also extends to American [[academia]], where in an attempt to create a "diverse student body" typically supports the [[recruitment]] of [[students]] from historically excluded populations, such as students of [[African-American]] or [[Latino]] background as well as women in such historically underrepresented fields as the [[sciences]].

==See also==
{{wikiquote|Diversity}}
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Discrimination]]
* [[Gender diversity]]
* [[Identity politics]]
* [[Individual and group rights]]
* [[Multiculturalism]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Respect diversity]]
* [[Diversity (business)|Workplace diversity]]

==References==

{{Reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Political correctness]]
[[Category:Affirmative action]]
[[Category:Identity politics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>