<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091116141111|326162477" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="96908" pageid="96908" ns="0" title="Title IX"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T14:28:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972''', renamed in 2002 the '''[[Patsy T. Mink]] Equal Opportunity in Education Act''' in honor of its principal author, but more commonly known simply as '''Title IX''', is a [[United States]] law enacted on [[June 23]], [[1972]]. The law states: "No person in the United States shall, on the basis of sex, be excluded from participation in, be denied the benefits of, or be subjected to discrimination under any education program or activity receiving Federal financial assistance..."&lt;ref&gt;{{UnitedStatesCode|20|1681}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Although the most prominent aspect of Title IX is its impact on high school and [[college athletics|collegiate athletics]], the original statute made no explicit mention of athletics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Carpenter, Linda Jean|author2=Acosta, R. Vivian|year=2005|title=Title IX|location=Champaign, IL|publisher=Human Kinetics|ISBN=0-7360-4239-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:patsymink.jpg|thumb|200px|Congresswoman [[Patsy T. Mink]] (1927-2002) wrote the law as an outgrowth of adversities she faced in obtaining her undergraduate degrees at the [[University of Hawaii|University of Hawai{{okina}}i]] and [[University of Nebraska]].]]
==Applicability and compliance==
The legislation covers all educational activities, and complaints under Title IX alleging [[discrimination]] in fields such as [[science]] or [[math education]], or in other aspects of academic life such as access to [[health care]] and [[dormitory]] facilities, are not unheard of. It also applies to non-sport activities such as [[school band]] and clubs; however, [[fraternities and sororities|social fraternities and sororities]], sex-specific youth clubs such as [[Girl Scouts of the USA|Girl Scouts]] and [[Boy Scouts of America|Boy Scouts]], and [[Boys State|Girls State and Boys State]] are specifically exempt from Title IX requirements.

Title IX is administered by the Office for Civil Rights in the [[United States Department of Education|U.S. Department of Education]] (OCR).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/om/fs_po/ocr/dels.html|title=US Department of Education Principal Office Functional Statements: Office for Civil Rights|accessdate=2009-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; It applies to an entire school or institution if any part of that school receives federal funds; hence, athletic programs are subject to Title IX, even though there is very little direct federal funding of school sports.&lt;ref&gt;34 C.F.R. §106.2&lt;/ref&gt; The regulations implementing Title IX require all institutions receiving federal funds to conduct self-evaluations of whether they offer equal opportunities based on sex&lt;ref&gt;34 C.F.R. §106.3&lt;/ref&gt; and to provide written assurances to the Dept. of Education that the institution is in compliance for the period that the federally funded equipment or facilities remain in use.&lt;ref&gt;34 C.F.R. §106.4&lt;/ref&gt; 

With respect to [[college athletics|athletic]] programs, the Dept. of Education evaluates the following factors in determining whether equal treatment exists:&lt;ref&gt;34 C.F.R. §106.41(e)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(1) Whether the selection of sports and levels of competition effectively accommodate the interests and abilities of members of both sexes;

(2) The provision of equipment and supplies;

(3) Scheduling of games and practice time;

(4) Travel and per diem allowance;

(5) Opportunity to receive coaching and academic tutoring on mathematics only;

(6) Assignment and compensation of coaches and tutors;

(7) Provision of locker rooms, practice and competitive facilities;

(8) Provision of medical and training facilities and services;

(9) Provision of housing and dining facilities and services;

(10) Publicity.

Unequal aggregate expenditures for members of each sex or unequal expenditures for male and female teams if a recipient operates or sponsors separate teams will not constitute noncompliance with this section, but the Assistant Secretary [of Education for Civil Rights] may consider the failure to provide necessary funds for teams for one sex in assessing equality of opportunity for members of each sex.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On November 24, 2006, the Department of Education OCR regulations were amended to provide greater flexibility in the operation of single-sex classes or extracurricular activities at the primary or secondary school level.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ed.gov/legislation/FedRegister/finrule/2006-4/102506a.html Retrieved 2008-09-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Three-prong test of compliance===
In 1979, the U.S. [[Department of Health, Education, and Welfare]] under Jimmy Carter's administration issued a policy interpretation for Title IX, including what has become known as the "three-prong test" of an institution's compliance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/t9interp.html Title IX 1979 Policy Interpretation on Intercollegiate Athletics]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;IX:http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1568/is_10_31/ai_59580155&lt;/ref&gt;
#Prong one - Providing athletic opportunities that are substantially proportionate to the student enrollment, OR
#Prong two - Demonstrate a continual expansion of athletic opportunities for the underrepresented sex, OR
#Prong three - Full and effective accommodation of the interest and ability of underrepresented sex.

A recipient of federal funds can demonstrate compliance with Title IX by meeting any one of the three prongs.&lt;ref name=OCRletter&gt;http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/title9guidanceadditional.html Retrieved 2008-09-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 17, 2005, OCR announced a clarification of prong three of the three-part test of Title IX compliance. The guidance concerned the use web-based surveys to determine the level of interest in varsity athletics among the under-represented sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Additional Clarification of Intercollegiate Athletics Policy: Three-Part Test ― Part Three | url=http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/title9guidanceadditional.html | published= [[U.S. Department of Education]]| accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Implementation and litigation===
{{Cleanup|section|date=September 2009}}
{{Expand|section|date=October 2009}}
In 1992, the U.S. Supreme Court held in ''Franklin v Gwinnett County Public Schools''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0503_0060_ZS.html 503 U.S. 60 (1992)]&lt;/ref&gt;  that schools which failed to comply with Title IX could be sued for compensatory and punitive damages.

In one specific instance, Title IX was instrumental in a court case involving [[Louisiana State University]]. In 1996, a federal court referenced Title IX in ruling that LSU violated the civil rights of female athletes with "arrogant ignorance" of their needs. Since this ruling, LSU has made changes in its athletic programs to achieve compliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA1039F930A25752C0A960958260 |title=Sports People: College Sports;Bias Found at L.S.U. In Title IX Ruling |work=New York Times |author=Associated Press |date=January 13, 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an "unusual" case, Title IX was invoked to justify a school's decision to upgrade its [[American football|football]] program from Division I FCS (formerly I-AA) to Division I FBS (formerly I-A). The [[Western Kentucky University]] Board of Regents approved this move in November 2006, to take effect in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wku.edu/news/releases06/november/football.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080115123929/http://wku.edu/news/releases06/november/football.html|publisher=Western Kentucky University|title=WKU Regents Approve Move To Division 1-A Football|date=November 2, 2006|archivedate=2008-01-15|accessdate=2009-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the vote, WKU was purportedly out of Title IX compliance because it had a disproportionately large number of female scholarship athletes. By upgrading football, it increased the percentage of male athletes on scholarship &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kentucky.com/mld/kentucky/sports/15682246.htm|author=Bailey, Rick|title=State College Notebook: Toppers' switch to I-A probable|publisher=''[[Lexington Herald-Leader]]''|date=2006-10-05|accessdate=2006-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the following year, it eliminated its men's soccer team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mvc-sports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=36296&amp;SPID=2895&amp;DB_OEM_ID=7600&amp;ATCLID=1380502|publisher=Western Kentucky University|title=Western Kentucky Athletics Discontinues Men's Soccer|date=2008-02-13|accessdate=2009-02-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact==
{{Expand|section|date=September 2009}}
It is difficult to characterize the impact of Title IX on athletics in an unbiased way. Advocates cite increases in female athletic participation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Title IX Athletic Statistics | publisher=[[American Association of University Women]] | url=http://www.aauw.org/advocacy/laf/lafnetwork/library/athleticStatistics.cfm |accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ncwge.org/PDF/TitleIXat35.pdf |title=Title IX at 35: Beyond the Headlines|publisher=National Coalition of Women and Girls in Education | accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.titleix.info/ |title=TitleIX.info |accessdate=2009-10-13| publisher=The MARGARET Fund of NWLC  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics note that such increases might have occurred in the absence of legislation.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} 

A 2008 study of intercollegiate athletics showed that women's collegiate sports has grown to 9,101 teams, or 8.65 per school. The five most frequently offered college sports for women are, in order: (1) Basketball, 98.8% of schools have a team, (2) Volleyball, 95.7%, (3) Soccer, 92.0%, (4) Cross Country, 90.8%, and (5) Softball, 89.2%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://webpages.charter.net/womeninsport/2008%20Summary%20Final.pdf |title=Women in Intercollegiate Sport, a Longitudinal National Study |date=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
{{Expand|section|date=September 2009}}
Title IX has been a source of controversy in part due to claims that Title IX has contributed to the reduction of programs for male athletes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite article | title=Equally Bad is Not Good: Allowing Title IX "Compliance" by the Elimination of Men's Collegiate Sports  |work=University of Michigan Journal of Law Reform | first=Donald E. |last=Shelton |date=2001 |volume=34 | number=1 |accessdate=2009-10-13 |url=http://ssrn.com/abstract=1163230}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commission on Opportunity in Athletics==
On June 27, 2002, Secretary of Education [[Rod Paige]] announced the creation of the Commission on Opportunity in Athletics (COA), a blue-ribbon panel to examine ways to strengthen enforcement and expand opportunities to ensure fairness for all college athletes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Commission on Opportunity in Athletics|url=http://www.ed.gov/about/bdscomm/list/athletics/index.html|accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Co-chairs for the COA were [[Cynthia Cooper (basketball)|Cynthia Cooper]] and Ted Leland. The purpose of the Commission was to collect information, analyze issues, and obtain broad public input directed at improving the application of Federal standards for measuring equal opportunity for men and women and boys and girls to participate in athletics under Title IX. Sports scholarships between men and women must be equal.

The panel held four town hall meetings (in Atlanta, Chicago, Colorado Springs, and San Diego) to allow the general public to comment on the past, present, and future of Title IX. On February 26, 2003 the COA issued its final report.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ed.gov/about/bdscomm/list/athletics/report.html COA Report Text&lt;/ref&gt; The COA provided twenty-three recommendations to the Secretary of Education. Although many of the recommendations were unanimous, some of the more controversial recommendations passed by an 8-5 vote. These dealt with considering non-scholarship athletes in prong one of the three-part test for compliance and allowing interest surveys to determine compliance with prong three. On the same day, Secretary of Education Rod Paige announced he would only consider the unanimous recommendations, which provided that the Department of Education (1) reaffirm its strong commitment to equal opportunity for girls and boys, women and men; (2) aggressively enforce Title IX in a uniform way across the nation; (3) give equal weight to all three prongs of the test governing Title IX compliance; and (4) encourage schools to understand that the Department of Education disapproves of cutting teams in order to comply with Title IX.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ed.gov/news/pressreleases/2003/02/02262003a.html Retrieved 2008-09-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Similar U.S. state laws==
Because Title IX only addresses public and private schools that receive federal funding, several states have enacted similar laws to prohibit discrimination based on sex regardless of whether the school receives federal funding. The states are: Alaska, California, Florida, Georgia, Hawaii, Illinois, Iowa, Maine, Minnesota, Nebraska, New Jersey, New Mexico, New York, Rhode Island, South Dakota, Washington, and Wisconsin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.WomensSportsFoundation.org/Content/Articles/Issues/Title-IX/S/State-Title-IX-Laws.aspx |title=State Title IX Laws|work=Women's Sports Foundation |accessdate=2008-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Gender equality]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Title Ix}}
[[Category:1972 in law]]
[[Category:Intercollegiate athletics in the United States]]
[[Category:Sports law]]
[[Category:United States federal civil rights legislation]]
[[Category:United States federal education legislation]]

[[id:Title IX]]
[[zh:教育法修正案第九条]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>