<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061111042435|87085006" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="96908" pageid="96908" ns="0" title="Title IX"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-12T22:14:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{ActiveDiscuss}}
'''Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (United States)''', commonly known as '''Title IX''', is a 37-word law enacted on [[June 23]], [[1972]] that states: "No person in the United States shall, on the basis of sex, be excluded from participation in, be denied the benefits of, or be subjected to discrimination under any education program or activity receiving Federal financial assistance."&lt;ref&gt;20 [[United States Code|U.S.C.]] ยง 1681&lt;/ref&gt; 

Although the most prominent "public face" of Title IX is its impact on high school and collegiate athletics,&lt;ref&gt;Carpenter, Linda Jean; &amp; Acosta, R. Vivian (2005). ''Title IX.'' Champaign, IL: Human Kinetics. ISBN 0-7360-4239-3.&lt;/ref&gt; the legislation actually covers all academic activities, and complaints under Title IX alleging discrimination in fields such as science or math education, or in other aspects of academic life such as access to health care and dormitory facilities, are not unheard of.

==Three-Prong Test of Compliance==
On 1979, the U.S. [[Department of Health, Education, and Welfare]] under Jimmy Carter's administration issued a policy intepertation for Title IX, including what has become known as the "three-prong test" of and institution's compliance.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/t9interp.html&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;IX:http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1568/is_10_31/ai_59580155&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cato.org/pub_display.php?pub_id=3731&lt;/ref&gt;
#Ensure women, and men, are represented in athletics in numbers proportionate to their presence in the student body
#Demonstrate continued efforts to expand athletic opportunities for both sexes.
#Show they are fully accommodating women's and men's athletics.

[[Image:patsymink.jpg|thumb|200px|Congresswoman [[Patsy T. Mink]], wrote the law as an outgrowth of adversities she faced in obtaining her college degrees at the [[University of Hawai'i]], [[University of Nebraska]] and [[University of Chicago]].]]

==Controversy==
Since its inception, Title IX has been highly controversal in its interpretation, enforcement, and its intended purpose. 

===Purpose===
To allow both sexes equal participation and opportunities in sports and other institutions, and prevent sexism.

===Equal Participation===
Many schools feel that the requirement of equal athletic participation is unreasonable due to male students having an inherently greater athletic inclination than their female counterparts.

===Litigation===
Since the advent of Title IX, schools have been increasingly threatened with discrimination lawsuits.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cato.org/pub_display.php?pub_id=3731&lt;/ref&gt;

Title IX has recently created controversy, with some groups claiming that it has caused some schools to spend less money on men's sports programs such as [[amateur wrestling|wrestling]], [[cross country running|cross country]], [[swimming]], [[gymnastics]], and [[volleyball]].  On the other hand, supporters of Title IX point to statistics (from a [[General Accounting Office|GAO]] study&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gao.gov/docdblite/summary.php?rptno=GAO-01-297&amp;accno=164560 ''Intercollegiate Athletics: Four-Year Colleges' Experiences Adding and Discontinuing Teams'', GAO-01-291], [[March 28]], [[2001]]&lt;/ref&gt;) that indicate male collegiate sport participation has increased since the inception of Title IX, and that so-called "non-revenue" sports were being eliminated frequently even before Title IX. 

However, while the GAO study shows that male participation in sports was up 5% over the 1981 to 1998 time frame, male college enrollment during those years was up more than 27%.  The number of men's sports teams available per male student has declined 21% over that time.  Teams such as tennis, track and field, and swimming have decreased for men, while women's teams have increased. Although there are now more teams available to women than to men, the total number of participation opportunities available to men still significantly outnumber those available to women; in 1998-99 there were 232,000 males participating in college athletics and 163,000 females.

A few non-college sports leagues have opened competition to men and women in the same events, such as [[equestrianism|equestrian]] competitions, [[auto racing]], [[sailing]], a few [[golf]] tournaments, and [[inline skating]] under the so-called "[[Fabiola rule]]", named for [[Fabiola da Silva]].

==Legal Rulings==
In one specific instance, Title IX was instrumental in a court case involving [[Louisiana State University]].  In 1996, a federal court referenced Title IX in ruling that LSU violated the civil rights of female athletes with "arrogant ignorance" of their needs.  Since this ruling, LSU has made changes in its athletic programs to achieve compliance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA1039F930A25752C0A960958260 SPORTS PEOPLE: COLLEGE SPORTS;Bias Found at L.S.U. In Title IX Ruling] Associated Press [[1996]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In an unusual case, Title IX played a key role in a school's decision to upgrade its football program from Division I-AA to Division I-A. The [[Western Kentucky University]] Board of Regents approved this move in November 2006, to take effect in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wku.edu/news/releases06/november/football.html|publisher=Western Kentucky University|title=WKU Regents Approve Move To Division 1-A Football|date=2006-11-02|accessdate=2006-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the vote, WKU was out of Title IX compliance because it offered approximately 20 too few scholarships for ''men''; moving its football program to Division I-A would add 22 men's scholarships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kentucky.com/mld/kentucky/sports/15682246.htm|author=Bailey, Rick|title=State College Notebook: Toppers' switch to I-A probable|publisher=''[[Lexington Herald-Leader]]''|date=2006-10-05|accessdate=2006-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Renaming==
The law was renamed as the Patsy T. Mink Equal Opportunity in Education Act''' on [[October 29]], [[2002]], upon the death of the law's author, Congresswoman [[Patsy T. Mink]], although she was also assisted in writing this by Edith Green.

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Homosexuality in Women's Sports since Title IX]]

==External links==
* [http://www.usdoj.gov/crt/cor/coord/titleixstat.htm Text of the original Title IX]
* [http://www.titleix.info TitleIX.info], proponents of Title IX.
* [http://psg.com/~patf/TitleIX.pdf "The Case for Requiring a Proportionality Test to Assess Compliance with Title IX in High School Athletics"], ''Northern Illinois University Law Review'', vol. 23, No. 1 (fall 2002)
* [http://www.aherofordaisy.com "A Hero For Daisy"], a film about a Title IX demonstration at [[Yale University]] in 1976.
* [http://webpages.charter.net/womeninsport 29-year long longitudinal study], tracking the status of women and collegiate sport.
* [http://www.acluprocon.org/bin/procon/procon.cgi?database=5-H-Sub-2Q.db&amp;command=viewone&amp;op=t&amp;id=4&amp;rnd=179.2029913452886 Is Title IX a good law?]

[[Category:Intercollegiate athletics in the United States]]
[[Category:Sports law]]
[[Category:United States federal civil rights legislation]]
[[Category:United States federal education legislation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>