<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051109115838|27813300" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="96908" pageid="96908" ns="0" title="Title IX"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-09T12:04:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:patsymink.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Patsy T. Mink]], late Congresswoman from [[Hawaii]], wrote the law as an outgrowth of adversities she faced in obtaining her college degrees at the University of Hawai'i, University of Nebraska and University of Chicago.]]

'''Patsy T. Mink Equal Opportunity in Education Act''', formerly known as the '''Title IX Amendment of the Higher Education Act'''.  The law was renamed by President [[George W. Bush]] on [[October 29]], [[2002]] upon the death of the law's author, [[Patsy Mink|Patsy T. Mink]].  It was instituted in [[1972]] and eventually expanded to prohibit [[gender]] [[discrimination]] in any [[United States]] educational institution.  Originally, it had focused on equality in [[sport]]s opportunities and called for the increase of college scholarships of women to ensure parity with male athletes. 

Title IX has recently been under some controversy, some groups claiming that because of it, some schools are spending more money on women's traditional sports programs and less money in men's traditional sports programs such as [[amateur wrestling|Wrestling]] and other sports or, in some cases, doing away with some traditional male sports programs all together. Vivian Acosta and Linda Carpenter have conducted a longitudinal study for 29 years tracking the status of women and collegiate sport.  For more information go to : http://webpages.charter.net/womeninsport

Nonetheless, Title IX has been instrumental in the development of women sports and it can be said that it helped the public prepare for today's women's professional sports leagues such as the [[WNBA]] and [[Women's United Soccer Association|WUSA]].

==External links==

* [http://psg.com/~patf/TitleIX.pdf "The Case for Requiring a Proportionality Test to Assess Compliance with Title IX in High School Athletics," ''Northern Illinois University Law Review'', vol. 23, No. 1 (fall 2002)]

*  See also http://www.aherofordaisy.com for the award-winning film (hailed by The New York Times as a "landmark film") about the Title IX demonstration at Yale University in 1976.

[[Category:Intercollegiate athletics]]
[[Category:United States federal legislation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>