<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131101154634|579750609" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="96908" pageid="96908" ns="0" title="Title IX"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-01T16:45:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About||civil rights Title IX|Title IX of the Civil Rights Act of 1964|foreign arbitration|Title 9 of the United States Code|music business|Title 9 Productions}}

{{Infobox U.S. legislation
| name = Title IX
| fullname = &lt;!--Official title (e.g. An act to...)--&gt;
| acronym = 
| nickname = 
| enacted by = 92nd
| effective date = June 23, 1972
| public law url = 
| cite public law = 92-318
| cite statutes at large = &lt;!--{{usstat}} can be used--&gt;
| acts amended = [[Higher Education Act of 1965]]
| acts repealed =
| title amended = 
| sections created = {{usc|20|1681|1688}}
| sections amended = 
| leghisturl = 
| introducedin = Senate
| introducedbill = 
| introducedby = [[Birch Bayh]]
| introduceddate = February 28, 1972
| committees = [[United States House Education Subcommittee on Higher Education and Workforce Training|House Subcommittee on Higher Education]]
| passedbody1 = Senate
| passeddate1 = May 22, 1972
| passedvote1 = 
| passedbody2 = House of Representatives
| passedas2 = &lt;!-- used if the second body changes the name of the legislation --&gt;
| passeddate2 = June 8, 1972
| passedvote2 = 
| conferencedate = 
| passedbody3 = 
| passeddate3 = 
| passedvote3 = 
| agreedbody3 = &lt;!-- used when the other body agrees without going into committee --&gt;
| agreeddate3 = &lt;!-- used when the other body agrees without going into committee --&gt;
| agreedvote3 = &lt;!-- used when the other body agrees without going into committee --&gt;
| agreedbody4 = &lt;!-- used if agreedbody3 further amends legislation --&gt;
| agreeddate4 = &lt;!-- used if agreedbody3 further amends legislation --&gt;
| agreedvote4 = &lt;!-- used if agreedbody3 further amends legislation --&gt;
| passedbody4 = 
| passeddate4 = 
| passedvote4 = 
| signedpresident = [[Richard Nixon]]
| signeddate = June 23, 1972
| amendments = 
| SCOTUS cases = ''[[Cannon v. University of Chicago]]''&lt;br&gt;''[[Grove City College v. Bell]]''&lt;br&gt;''[[Franklin v. Gwinnett County Public Schools]]''&lt;br&gt;''[[Gebser v. Lago Vista Independent School District]]''&lt;br&gt;''[[Davis v. Monroe County Board of Education]]''&lt;br&gt;''[[Jackson v. Birmingham Board of Education]]''
}}

'''Title&amp;nbsp;IX''' is a portion of the [[Education Amendments of 1972]], Public Law No. 92‑318, 86 Stat. 235 (June 23, 1972), codified at 20 U.S.C. sections 1681 through 1688, authored and introduced by Senator [[Birch Bayh]] and named the [[Patsy Mink]] Equal Opportunity in Education Act, after its House co-author and sponsor in 2002. It states (in part) that
{{quote|text=No person in the United States shall, on the basis of sex, be excluded from participation in, be denied the benefits of, or be subjected to discrimination under any education program or activity receiving federal financial assistance...}}

==History==

===Foundation and Hearings===
Although the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] was written in order to end discrimination based on religion, race, color, or national origin, the act also energized the [[women's rights]] movement, which had somewhat slowed after [[Women's suffrage in the United States|women's suffrage in 1920]].&lt;ref name="Suggs"&gt;Suggs, Welsh. ''A Place on the Team.'' Princeton, NJ.: Princeton University Press, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; While Title&amp;nbsp;IX is best known for its impact on high school and [[college athletics|collegiate athletics]], the original statute made no explicit mention of sports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Carpenter, Linda Jean|author2=Acosta, R. Vivian|year=2005|title=Title&amp;nbsp;IX|location=Champaign, IL|publisher=Human Kinetics|ISBN=0-7360-4239-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1967 President [[Lyndon Johnson]] sent a series of executive orders in order to make some clarifications. Before these clarifications were made, the [[National Organization for Women]] (NOW) persuaded President Johnson to include women in his executive orders.&lt;ref name="Suggs"/&gt; Most notable is [[Executive Order 11375]], which required all entities receiving federal contracts to end discrimination on the basis of sex in hiring and employment.

In 1969 [[Bernice Sandler]] used the executive order to help her fight for her job at the [[University of Maryland]].&lt;ref name="Valentin"&gt;Valentin, Iram. [http://www2.edc.org/WomensEquity/pdffiles/t9digest.pdf “Title&amp;nbsp;IX: A Brief History.”] Women's Equity Resource Center. August 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; She used university statistics showing how female employment at the university had plummeted as qualified women were replaced by men.&lt;ref name="Suggs"/&gt; Sandler brought her grievance to the [[United States Department of Labor|Department of Labor]]'s [[Office of Federal Contract Compliance Programs|Office for Federal Fair Contracts Compliance]] where she was encouraged to file a formal complaint. Citing inequalities in pay, rank, admissions and much more, Sandler began to file complaints not only against the University of Maryland but numerous other colleges as well. Working in conjunction with NOW and [[Women's Equity Action League]] (WEAL), Sandler filed 269&amp;nbsp;complaints against colleges and universities.&lt;ref name="Suggs"/&gt;

In 1970 Sandler joined Representative [[Edith Green]]'s [[United States House Education Subcommittee on Higher Education and Workforce Training|Subcommittee on Higher Education]] of the [[United States House Committee on Education and the Workforce|Education and Labor Committee]] and sat in on the congressional hearings where women's rights were discussed. It was in the congressional hearings that Green and Sandler first proposed Title&amp;nbsp;IX. An early draft was authored by Representative Patsy Mink, with the assistance of Representative Green.&lt;ref name="aauw"&gt;[http://www.aauw.org/advocacy/laf/lafnetwork/library/AthleticsHistory.cfm “Title&amp;nbsp;IX: A Brief History.”] AAUW. 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In the hearing there was very little mention of athletics.&lt;ref name="Suggs"/&gt; Their focus was more specifically on the hiring and employment practices of federally financed institutions. The proposed Title&amp;nbsp;IX created much buzz and gained a lot of support.

===Introduction and Enactment===
[[File:Birch bayh.jpg|thumb|Senator [[Birch Bayh]] of Indiana]]The first person to introduce Title&amp;nbsp;IX in Congress was its author and chief Senate sponsor, Senator [[Birch Bayh]] of Indiana.

At the time, Bayh was working on numerous constitutional issues related to women's rights, including the [[Equal Rights Amendment]], to build "a powerful constitutional base from which to move forward in abolishing discriminatory differential treatment based on sex".&lt;ref name="Bayh"&gt;Cruikshank, Kate. ''[http://www.libraries.iub.edu/index.php?pageId=8621 The Art of Leadership; A Companion to an Exhibition from the Senatorial Papers of Birch Bayh]''. (Indiana University Libraries, 2007), p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt; As they were having some difficulty getting the ERA out of committee, the [[Higher Education Act of 1965]] was on the floor for reauthorization, and on February 28, 1972, Senator Bayh introduced the ERA's equal education provision as an amendment.&lt;ref name="SenateIntro"&gt;118 Cong. Record 5802-3 (1972).&lt;/ref&gt;

In his remarks on the Senate floor, Bayh said, "We are all familiar with the stereotype of women as pretty things who go to college to find a husband, go on to [[graduate school]] because they want a more interesting husband, and finally marry, have children, and never work again. The desire of many schools not to waste a 'man's place' on a woman stems from such stereotyped notions. But the facts absolutely contradict these myths about the 'weaker sex' and it is time to change our operating assumptions."&lt;ref name="SenateSpeech"&gt;118 Cong. Record 5804 (1972).&lt;/ref&gt;

"While the impact of this amendment would be far-reaching", Bayh concluded, "it is not a panacea. It is, however, an important first step in the effort to provide for the women of America something that is rightfully theirs—an equal chance to attend the schools of their choice, to develop the skills they want, and to apply those skills with the knowledge that they will have a fair chance to secure the jobs of their choice with equal pay for equal work".&lt;ref name="SenateSpeech2"&gt;118 Cong. Record 5808 (1972).&lt;/ref&gt;

Title&amp;nbsp;IX became law on June 23, 1972.&lt;ref name="now"&gt;[http://www.now.org/issues/title_ix/history.html “Legislative History of Title&amp;nbsp;IX”]  National Organization for Women. June 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  When President Nixon signed the bill, he spoke mostly about [[desegregation busing]], which was also a focus of the signed bill, but did not mention the expansion of educational access for women he had enacted.&lt;ref name="Bayh" /&gt;

===Implementation===
[[File:BirchWorkout.jpg|thumb|Senator Bayh exercises with Title&amp;nbsp;IX athletes at Purdue University, ca. 1970s.]]The wording of Title&amp;nbsp;IX is very brief, requiring specific language and clarifications to be articulated in its implementing regulations.  President Nixon directed the [[United States Department of Health and Human Services|Department of Health, Education and Welfare]] (HEW) to carry this out.&lt;ref name="Suggs"/&gt;

Concern over how Title&amp;nbsp;IX would affect men's athletics prompted some to look for ways to limit the influence of Title&amp;nbsp;IX, and Senator Bayh spent the next three years keeping watch over HEW to get regulations formulated that carried out its legislative intent of eliminating discrimination in higher education on the basis of sex.&lt;ref name="Bayh" /&gt;  When they were issued in summer 1975 they were contested, and hearings were held by the House Subcommittee on Equal Opportunities on the discrepancies between the regulations and the law. Implementation by colleges and universities also had to be monitored, although many were working to comply. One such attempt was made in 1974 by Senator [[John Tower]] who introduced the Tower Amendment, which would have exempted revenue-producing sports from Title&amp;nbsp;IX compliance.&lt;ref name="cases"&gt;[http://bailiwick.lib.uiowa.edu/ge/historyRE.html “Landmark Title&amp;nbsp;IX Cases in History”] Gender Equity in Sport. February 23, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;  Later that year the Tower Amendment was rejected and the Javits Amendment, proposed by Senator [[Jacob Javits]], stating that the HEW must include “reasonable provisions considering the nature of particular sports” was adopted in its place.&lt;ref name="Suggs"/&gt;

In June 1975, HEW published the final regulations detailing how Title&amp;nbsp;IX would be enforced.&lt;ref name="Suggs"/&gt;  The regulations were codified in the [[Federal Register]] in Volume 34, Part 106. It was not until this step was completed that many people truly understood the ramifications of Title&amp;nbsp;IX as it would apply to college athletics. Universities receiving Federal financial assistance were given three years to comply with the Title&amp;nbsp;IX regulations.&lt;ref name="now"/&gt;  The NCAA claimed that the implementation of Title&amp;nbsp;IX was illegal. A revised Tower Amendment was proposed and many debates occurred {{Vague|date=March 2012}} but Title&amp;nbsp;IX stood.&lt;ref name="Suggs"/&gt;

In 1979, HEW, under [[Presidency of Jimmy Carter|Jimmy Carter's administration]], issued further clarifications in its "Intercollegiate Athletics Policy Interpretation".&lt;ref name="Interpretation"&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/t9interp.html |title=A Policy Interpretation: Title&amp;nbsp;IX and Intercollegiate Athletics |journal=Federal Register |volume=44 |number=239 |date=December 11, 1979 |accessdate=2012-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Lynch|first=Michael W.|title=Weapons Modernization - changes to Title&amp;nbsp;IX|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1568/is_10_31/ai_59580155|newspaper=Reason|date=March 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1980, HEW was split into two separate agencies in accordance with the [[Department of Education Organization Act]] - the [[United States Department of Health and Human Services|Department of Health and Human Services (HHS)]] and the [[United States Department of Education|Department of Education (ED)]].&lt;ref name="cases"/&gt; Oversight of Title&amp;nbsp;IX enforcement and implementation was given to ED's [[Office for Civil Rights|Office for Civil Rights (OCR)]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/om/fs_po/ocr/dels.html|title=US Department of Education Principal Office Functional Statements: Office for Civil Rights|accessdate=2009-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Further legislation and regulations===
[[File:Patsymink.jpg|thumb|Representative [[Patsy Mink]] of Hawaii, Title IX co-author, for whom the law was renamed in 2002.]]The Civil Rights Restoration Act of 1988 was passed in response to the U.S. Supreme Court's 1984 ruling ''[[Grove City College v. Bell]]''&lt;ref name="oyez"&gt;[http://oyez.org/cases/1980-1989/1983/1983_82_792 ”The Oyez Project, Grove City College v. Bell”] , 465 U.S. 555 (1984)&lt;/ref&gt; in which the Court held that Title&amp;nbsp;IX applied only to those programs receiving direct federal aid.&lt;ref name="EB"&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/597287/Title-IX "Title&amp;nbsp;IX."] Encyclopædia Britannica. 2009. Encyclopædia Britannica Online. 19 Nov. 2009&lt;/ref&gt;  The case reached the Supreme Court when [[Grove City College]] disagreed with the Department of Education's assertion that it was required to comply with Title&amp;nbsp;IX. Grove City College was not a federally funded institution; however, they did accept students who were receiving [[Basic Educational Opportunity Grant]]s through a Department of Education program.&lt;ref name="oyez"/&gt; The Department of Education's stance was that, because some of its students were receiving federal grants, the school was receiving federal assistance and Title&amp;nbsp;IX applied to it. The Court decided that since Grove City College was only receiving federal funding through the grant program, only that program had to be in compliance. The ruling was a major victory for those opposed to Title&amp;nbsp;IX, as it made many institutions' sports programs outside of the rule of Title&amp;nbsp;IX and, thus, reduced the scope of Title&amp;nbsp;IX.&lt;ref name="Suggs"/&gt; The ruling, however, was short-lived. The Civil Rights Restoration Act was passed in 1988 which extended Title&amp;nbsp;IX coverage to all programs of any educational institution that receives any federal assistance, whether direct or indirect.&lt;ref name="now"/&gt;

In 1994, the Equity in Athletics Disclosure Act, sponsored by congresswoman [[Cardiss Collins]], required federally assisted higher education institutions to disclose information on roster sizes for men's and women's teams, as well as budgets for recruiting, scholarships, coaches' salaries, and other expenses, annually.&lt;ref name="cases"/&gt;

In October 2002, less than a month after the death of Rep. Patsy Mink, Congress passed a resolution to rename Title IX the "Patsy Takemoto Mink Equal Opportunity in Education Act," which President George W. Bush signed into law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bush signs resolution honoring Patsy Mink|url=http://the.honoluluadvertiser.com/article/2002/Oct/31/ln/ln41a.html|accessdate=20 May 2013|newspaper=Honolulu Advertiser|date=31 October 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 24, 2006, the Title&amp;nbsp;IX regulations were amended to provide greater flexibility in the operation of single-sex classes or extracurricular activities at the primary or secondary school level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.ed.gov/legislation/FedRegister/finrule/2006-4/102506a.html |title=Nondiscrimination on the Basis of Sex in Education Programs or Activities Receiving Federal Financial Assistance |journal=Federal Register |volume=71 |number=206 |date=October 25, 2006 |accessdate=2012-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Applicability and compliance==
The legislation covers all educational activities, and complaints under Title&amp;nbsp;IX alleging [[sex discrimination]] in fields such as [[science]] or [[math education]], or in other aspects of academic life such as access to [[health care]] and [[dormitory]] facilities, are not unheard of. It also applies to non-sport activities such as [[school band]] and clubs; however, [[fraternities and sororities|social fraternities and sororities]], sex-specific youth clubs such as [[Girl Scouts of the USA|Girl Scouts]] and [[Boy Scouts of America|Boy Scouts]], and [[Boys State|Girls State and Boys State]] are specifically exempt from Title&amp;nbsp;IX requirements.

Title&amp;nbsp;IX applies to an entire school or institution if any part of that school receives federal funds; hence, athletic programs are subject to Title&amp;nbsp;IX, even though there is very little direct federal funding of school sports.&lt;ref&gt;34 C.F.R. §106.2&lt;/ref&gt;

The regulations implementing Title&amp;nbsp;IX require all universities receiving federal funds to perform self-evaluations of whether they offer equal opportunities based on sex&lt;ref&gt;34 C.F.R. §106.3&lt;/ref&gt; and to provide written assurances to the Department of Education that the institution is in compliance for the period that the federally funded equipment or facilities remain in use.&lt;ref&gt;34 C.F.R. §106.4&lt;/ref&gt; With respect to athletic programs, the Department of Education evaluates the following factors in determining whether equal treatment exists:&lt;ref&gt;34 C.F.R. §106.41(e)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
#Whether the selection of sports and levels of competition effectively accommodate the interests and abilities of members of both sexes;
#The provision of equipment and supplies;
#Scheduling of games and practice time;
#Travel and per diem allowance;
#Opportunity to receive coaching and academic tutoring on mathematics only;
#Assignment and compensation of coaches and tutors;
#Provision of locker rooms, practice and competitive facilities;
#Provision of medical and training facilities and services;
#Provision of housing and dining facilities and services;
#Publicity.

Unequal aggregate expenditures for members of each sex or unequal expenditures for male and female teams if a recipient operates or sponsors separate teams will not constitute noncompliance with this section, but the Assistant Secretary [of Education for Civil Rights] may consider the failure to provide necessary funds for teams for one sex in assessing equality of opportunity for members of each sex.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Although the most well-known application of Title&amp;nbsp;IX regards athletics, there are several protections the law specifically delineates. Section&amp;nbsp;106.40 protects pregnant and parenting students from discrimination based on pregnant status, marital status, or parenthood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title= Nondiscrimination on the basis of sex in education programs or activities receiving federal financial assistance|url=http://www2.ed.gov/policy/rights/reg/ocr/edlite-34cfr106.html#S40| publisher= U.S. Department of Education|accessdate=27 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Their condition must be treated as any other medical condition. Students may not be excluded from any activity based on their condition of pregnancy, parenthood, or marital status. If they attend a separate facility, they must elect to do so voluntarily, and the facility must provide comparable programs.

===Three-prong test===
HEW's 1979 Policy Interpretation articulated three ways compliance with Title&amp;nbsp;IX can be achieved. This became known as the "three-part test" for compliance. A recipient of federal funds can demonstrate compliance with Title&amp;nbsp;IX by meeting any one of the three prongs.&lt;ref name=OCRletter&gt;{{cite web|title=Dear Colleague Letter|url=http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/title9guidanceadditional.html|publisher=Office of the Assistant Secretary for Civil Rights|date=April 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*"All such assistance should be available on a substantially proportional basis to the number of male and female participants in the institution's athletic program."
* "Male and female athletes should receive equivalent treatment, benefits, and opportunities" regarding facilities.
* "The athletic interests and abilities of male and female students must be equally effectively accommodated."&lt;ref name="Interpretation"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A Policy Interpretation:  Title&amp;nbsp;IX and Intercollegiate Athletics, 44 FR 71413 (Dec. 11, 1979)&lt;/ref&gt;
*"Institutions must provide both the opportunity for individuals of each sex to participate in intercollegiate competition, and for athletes of each sex to have competitive team schedules which equally reflect their abilities." Compliance can be assessed in any one of three ways:&lt;ref name=OCRletter&gt;http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/title9guidanceadditional.html Retrieved 2008-09-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

#Providing athletic participation opportunities that are substantially proportionate to the student enrollment. This prong of the test is satisfied when participation opportunities for men and women are "substantially proportionate" to their respective undergraduate enrollment.
#Demonstrating a continual expansion of athletic opportunities for the underrepresented sex. This prong of the test is satisfied when an institution has a history and continuing practice of program expansion that is responsive to the developing interests and abilities of the underrepresented sex (typically female).
#Accommodating the interest and ability of underrepresented sex. This prong of the test is satisfied when an institution is meeting the interests and abilities of its female students even where there are disproportionately fewer females than males participating in sports.

==Litigation after ''Grove City'' case==
Since Title&amp;nbsp;IX was passed into law there have been many court cases claiming non-compliance. One of the most notable cases is ''Franklin v. Gwinnett County Public Schools'', was brought to the [[U.S.&amp;nbsp;Supreme Court]] in 1992. The decision in this case required that punitive damages should be awarded to plaintiffs when Title&amp;nbsp;IX is intentionally avoided.&lt;ref name="EB"/&gt; In 1993 the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit|court of appeals]] ruled that financial difficulties is not an excuse for non-compliance in ''Favia v. [[Indiana University of Pennsylvania]]''.&lt;ref name="cases"/&gt;

In one specific instance, Title&amp;nbsp;IX was instrumental in a court case involving [[Louisiana State University]] (LSU). In 1996, a federal court referenced Title&amp;nbsp;IX in ruling that LSU violated the civil rights of female athletes by refusing to fund a trip to a women's volleyball tournament in [[Hawaii]], when earlier in the year, travel for a men's basketball tournament was funded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA1039F930A25752C0A960958260 |title=Sports People: College Sports;Bias Found at L.S.U. In Title&amp;nbsp;IX Ruling |work=New York Times |agency=Associated Press |date=January 13, 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since this ruling, LSU has made changes in its athletic programs to achieve compliance.{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}} LSU is one of only three [[NCAA]] programs that are 100% self-funded and that do not accept financial contributions from the university or government.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fas.lsu.edu/acctservices/far_b/&lt;/ref&gt;

In an "unusual" case, Title&amp;nbsp;IX was invoked to justify a school's decision to upgrade its [[American football|football]] program from Division&amp;nbsp;I FCS (formerly I‑AA) to Division&amp;nbsp;I FBS (formerly I‑A). The [[Western Kentucky University]] Board of Regents approved this move in November 2006, to take effect in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wku.edu/news/releases06/november/football.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080115123929/http://wku.edu/news/releases06/november/football.html|publisher=Western Kentucky University|title=WKU Regents Approve Move To Division 1-A Football|date=November 2, 2006|archivedate=2008-01-15|accessdate=2009-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the vote, WKU was purportedly out of Title&amp;nbsp;IX compliance because it had a disproportionately large number of female scholarship athletes. By upgrading football, it increased the percentage of male athletes on scholarship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kentucky.com/mld/kentucky/sports/15682246.htm|author=Bailey, Rick|title=State College Notebook: Toppers' switch to I-A probable|publisher=''[[Lexington Herald-Leader]]''|date=2006-10-05|accessdate=2006-10-06 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070930204126/http://www.kentucky.com/mld/kentucky/sports/15682246.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the following year, it eliminated its men's soccer team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mvc-sports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=36296&amp;SPID=2895&amp;DB_OEM_ID=7600&amp;ATCLID=1380502|publisher=Western Kentucky University|title=Western Kentucky Athletics Discontinues Men's Soccer|date=2008-02-13|accessdate=2009-02-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

More recently, the [[Associated Press]] reported in May 2011 that the Department of Education was investigating the [[University of Delaware]] (UD) for potential sex discrimination against men, following a complaint by members of the school's men's cross country and track teams. UD had announced in January 2011 that it would be eliminating both teams at the end of the current school year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=6467093 |title=Feds looking at Delaware athletics |work=[[ESPN.com]] |date=May 2, 2011 |accessdate=May 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact==
Though views differ as respects the impact of Title&amp;nbsp;IX, discussion typically focuses on whether and to what extent Title&amp;nbsp;IX has resulted in increased athletic opportunities for females, and whether and to what extent Title&amp;nbsp;IX has resulted in decreased athletic opportunities for males. In addition, the legislation had impacts on aspects other than athletes. The increased exposure of female sports led to increased dominance by males of the governance of women's athletics. For example, the male dominated NCAA, which had been content to let the women-dominated AIAW run women's championships, decided to offer women's championships, which led to the eventual demise of the AIAW.&lt;ref name="Hult 240"&gt;{{harvnb|Hult |p=240}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[2012 Summer Olympics]] in [[London]] opened new interest in the impact of Title&amp;nbsp;IX and how the growth of sports participation by women worldwide might be ascribed to the 1972 American legislation. Clearly the intense coverage by the [[NBC]]'s television system has brought a closer look to the personalities, backgrounds, and history of both men and women in sports and opens a new source for comparison with pre-Title&amp;nbsp;IX sports activity by women. That noted, there has been little reference in the popular media to possible impact by the Patsy Mink authored measure.

Advocates of Title&amp;nbsp;IX's current interpretation cite increases in female athletic participation, and attribute those increases to Title&amp;nbsp;IX.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Title&amp;nbsp;IX Athletic Statistics | publisher=[[American Association of University Women]] | url=http://www.aauw.org/advocacy/laf/lafnetwork/library/athleticStatistics.cfm |accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ncwge.org/PDF/TitleIXat35.pdf |title=Title&amp;nbsp;IX at 35: Beyond the Headlines|publisher=National Coalition of Women and Girls in Education | accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.titleix.info/ |title=TitleIX.info |accessdate=2009-10-13| publisher=The MARGARET Fund of NWLC  }}&lt;/ref&gt; One study, completed in 2006, pointed to a large increase in the number of women participating in athletics at both the high school and college level. The number of women in high school sports had increased by a factor of nine, while the number of women in college sports had increased by more than 450%.&lt;ref&gt;Linda Jean Carpenter and R. Vivian Acosta, Women in Intercollegiate Sport: A Longitudinal National Study Twenty-Nine Year Update 1977-2006 (2006)).&lt;/ref&gt; A 2008 study of intercollegiate athletics showed that women's collegiate sports has grown to 9,101 teams, or 8.65 per school. The five most frequently offered college sports for women are, in order: (1) Basketball, 98.8% of schools have a team, (2) Volleyball, 95.7%, (3) Soccer, 92.0%, (4) Cross Country, 90.8%, and (5) Softball, 89.2%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://webpages.charter.net/womeninsport/2008%20Summary%20Final.pdf |title=Women in Intercollegiate Sport, a Longitudinal National Study |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the same time, many contend that the current interpretation of Title&amp;nbsp;IX by the OCR has resulted in the dismantling of men's programs, despite strong participation in those sports.&lt;ref name="Shelton 2001"&gt;{{cite journal | title=Equally Bad is Not Good: Allowing Title&amp;nbsp;IX "Compliance" by the Elimination of Men's Collegiate Sports  |work=University of Michigan Journal of Law Reform | first=Donald E. |last=Shelton |year=2001 |volume=34 | number=1 |ssrn=1163230}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, though interest in the sport of wrestling has consistently increased at the high school level since 1990,
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=USA Wrestling response to quotes by Donna Lopiano - Women's Sports Found. |year=2000 |url=http://www.themat.com/section.php?section_id=3&amp;page=showarticle&amp;ArticleID=2523}}&lt;/ref&gt; scores of colleges have dropped their wrestling programs during that same period.&lt;ref name="collegesportsscholarships.com"&gt;{{cite news | title=Title&amp;nbsp;IX has hurt the college sport, but it is now fighting back. |year=2003 |url=http://www.collegesportsscholarships.com/title-ix-fall-college-wrestling.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="collegian.psu.edu"&gt;{{cite news | title=Wrestling programs threatened by Title&amp;nbsp;IX. |year=1997 |url=http://www.collegian.psu.edu/archive/1997/03/03-28-97tdc/03-28-97d03-017.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; The OCR's three-prong test for compliance with Title&amp;nbsp;IX often is cited as the reason for these cuts.&lt;ref name="collegian.psu.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref name="usatoday.com"&gt;{{cite news | title=Bucknell to drop wrestling for Title&amp;nbsp;IX compliance. |year=2001 |url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/2001-05-02-bucknell-title9.htm.htm}} {{Dead link|date=September 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wrestling historically was the most frequently dropped sport,&lt;ref name="usatoday.com"/&gt; but other men's sports later overtook the lead, such that according to the NCAA, the most-dropped men's sports between 1987 and 2002 were as follows:  Cross country (183), indoor track (180), golf (178), tennis (171), rowing (132), outdoor track (126), swimming (125) and wrestling (121).&lt;ref name="collegesportsscholarships.com"/&gt;

A guideline announced by Vice President [[Joe Biden]] on 4 April 2011 on sexual harassment or violence required that institutions conduct investigations and discipline on the [[preponderance of the evidence]] standard, rather than that of [[beyond reasonable doubt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Carter |first=S. Daniel |url=http://www.campussafetymagazine.com/Channel/University-Security/Articles/Print/Story/2011/04/How-to-Comply-With-the-Dept-of-Ed-s-Title-IX-s-Sexual-Violence-Guidance.aspx |title=How to Comply With the Dept. of Ed’s Title&amp;nbsp;IX Sexual Violence Guidance |publisher=Campus Safety Magazine |date=April 20, 2011 |accessdate=2012-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of such a standard by the [[University of North Dakota]] has been criticized by the [[Foundation for Individual Rights in Education]] in the case of Caleb Warner, who was suspended for three years in January 2010 on the basis of a report by a complainant who was subsequently charged with filing a false report by state police, a decision which the University has refused to reconsider.&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702303678704576440014119968294.html Yes Means Yes—Except on Campus], Wall Street Journal&lt;/ref&gt;

===Impact on sexual violence===
Title IX applies to all educational programs and all aspects of a school's educational system.  Civil rights activists and organizations such as the [[American Civil Liberties Union]] (ACLU) maintain that "when students suffer sexual assault and harassment, they are deprived of equal and free access to an education."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aclu.org/womens-rights/title-ix-and-sexual-violence-schools |title=Title IX and Sexual Violence in Schools |publisher=American Civil Liberties Union |accessdate=2013-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Further, according to an April 2011 letter issued by the [[Department of Education]]'s [[Office for Civil Rights]], "The sexual harassment of students, including sexual violence, interferes with students’ right to receive an education free from discrimination and, in the case of sexual violence, is a crime."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/letters/colleague-201104.html |title=Dear Colleague letter |publisher=Office of the Assistant Secretary, the Department of Education |accessdate=2013-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The controversial letter, known colloquially as the "Dear Colleague" letter, states that it is the responsibility of institutions of higher education "to take immediate and effective steps to end sexual harassment and sexual violence."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/letters/colleague-201104_pg2.html |title=Dear Colleague letter |publisher=Office of the Assistant Secretary, the Department of Education |accessdate=2013-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The letter illustrates multiple examples of Title IX requirements as they relate to sexual violence, and makes clear that, should an institution fail to fulfill its responsibilities under Title IX, the [[Department of Education]] can impose a fine and potentially deny further institutional access to federal funds.

On March 15, 2011, [[Yale]] undergraduate student and alleged sexual violence survivor [[Alexandra Brodsky]] filed a Title IX complaint along with fifteen fellow students alleging Yale "has a sexually hostile environment and has failed to adequately respond to sexual harassment concerns."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=John Christofferson |title=Yale Under Federal Investigation For 'Sexually Hostile Environment' |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/04/01/yale-title-ix_n_843570.html |publisher=The Huffington Post |date=2011-04-01 |accessdate=2013-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 2012, an [[Amherst College]] student, [[Angie Epifano]], wrote an explicit, personal account of her alleged sexual assault and the ensuing, "appalling treatment" she received when coming forward to seek support from the College’s administration.&lt;ref name="Epifano"&gt;{{cite news|last=Epifano|first=Angie|title=An Account of Sexual Assault at Amherst College|url=http://amherststudent.amherst.edu/?q=article/2012/10/17/account-sexual-assault-amherst-college|accessdate=June 23, 2013|newspaper=The Amherst Student|date=2012-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the narrative, Epifano alleged that she was raped by a fellow Amherst student, and how her life was completely impacted by the experience: how her perpetrator harassed her at the only dining hall, that her academics were impacted, and how, when she sought support, the administration coerced her into taking the blame for her experience, and ultimately, institutionalized her and pressured her to drop out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Richard|first=Perez-Pena|title=Student’s Account Has Rape in Spotlight|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/27/education/amherst-account-of-rape-brings-tension-to-forefront.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0|accessdate=24 June 2013|newspaper=The New York Times|date=October 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:'':" The fact that such a prestigious institution could have such a noxious interior fills me with intense remorse mixed with sour distaste. I am sickened by the Administration’s attempts to cover up survivors’ stories, cook their books to discount rapes, pretend that withdrawals never occur, quell attempts at change, and sweep sexual assaults under a rug. When politicians cover up affairs or scandals the masses often rise up in angry protestations and call for a more transparent government. What is the difference between a government and the Amherst College campus? Why can’t we know what is really happening on campus? Why should we be quiet about sexual assault?"''&lt;ref name="Epifano"/&gt;

When the Amherst case reached national attention, [[Annie E. Clark]] and [[Andrea Pino]], two women who were allegedly sexually assaulted at the [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]] connected with Amherst student, [[Dana Bolger]], and Brodsky to address the parallel concerns of hostility at their institution, filing Title IX and [[Clery Act]] complaints against the university on January 2013, both leading to investigations by the [[U.S. Department of Education]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Perez-Pena|first=Richard|title=Students Initiate Inquiry Into Harassment Reports|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/08/education/students-initiate-inquiry-into-harassment-reports.html?hpw|accessdate=24 June 2013|newspaper=The New York Times|date=March 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the national prominence of the UNC Chapel Hill case, Clark and Pino went on to coordinate with students at other schools; in 2013, complaints citing violations of Title IX were filed by [[Occidental College]] (on April 18), [[Swarthmore College]] (on May 22), [[Dartmouth College]], [[the University of California, Berkeley]] and [[the University of Southern California]] (also on May 22).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Tyler Kingkade |title=College Sexual Assault Survivors Form Underground Network To Reform Campus Policies |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/03/21/college-sexual-assault-survivors_n_2918855.html |publisher=The Huffington Post |date=2013-03-21 |accessdate=2013-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Castellanos"&gt;{{cite news |author=Dalina Castellanos |title=Complaints filed against USC, UC Berkeley over rape reporting |url=http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-0523-college-rape-20130523,0,106833.story |date=2010-05-22 |accessdate=2013-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; These complaints, the resulting campaigns against sexual violence on college campuses, and the organizing of Clark, Pino, Brodsky, Bolger and other activists led to the formation of an informal national network of activists referred to as the "IX Network."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Perez-Pena|first=Richard|title=College Groups Connect to Fight Sexual Assault|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/20/education/activists-at-colleges-network-to-fight-sexual-assault.html?pagewanted=all|accessdate=24 June 2013|newspaper=The New York Times|date=March 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Stancill|first=Jane|title=UNC-CH women wage national campaign against sexual assault|url=http://www.newsobserver.com/2013/06/01/2932161/unc-ch-women-wage-national-campaign.html|accessdate=24 June 2013|newspaper=The News &amp; Observer|date=1 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to its use within formal complaints submitted to the [[Department of Education]], Title IX has been utilized in civil litigation.  In 2006, a federal court found that there was sufficient evidence that the [[University of Colorado]] acted with "deliberate indifference" toward students Lisa Simpson and Anne Gilmore, who were sexually assaulted by student football players.  The university settled the case, promising to change its policies and pay $2.5 million in damages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aclu.org/racial-justice-womens-rights/simpson-v-university-colorado |title=Simpson v. University of Colorado |publisher=ACLU.org |accessdate=2013-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2008, [[Arizona State University]] was the subject of a lawsuit that alleged violations of rights guaranteed by Title IX:  the university expelled a football player for multiple instances of severe sexual harassment, but readmitted him; he went on to rape a fellow student in her dorm room.  Despite its claim that it bore no responsibility, the school settled the lawsuit, agreeing to revise and improve its official response to sexual misconduct and to pay the plaintiff $850,000 in damages and fees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aclu.org/womens-rights/jk-v-arizona-board-regents |title=J.K. v. Arizona Board of Regents |publisher=ACLU.org |accessdate=2013-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As of 2013, the services of women's rights attorney Gloria Allred have been retained by students at Occidental College and the University of Southern California regarding individual civil claims against their respective institutions.&lt;ref name="Castellanos" /&gt;

===Impact on male athletics===
{{Synthesis|date=August 2012}}
Some believe that the increase in athletic opportunity for girls in high school has come at the expense of boys athletics. For example, the College Sports Council has stated, “Nationwide, there are currently 1.3&amp;nbsp;million more boys participating in high school sports than girls. Using a gender quota to enforce Title&amp;nbsp;IX in high school sports would put those young athletes at risk of losing their opportunity to play.”&lt;ref name=McErlain&gt;McErlain, Eric. [http://collegesportscouncil.org "College Sports Council Urges High Schools to Fight Use of Gender Quotas to Comply with Title&amp;nbsp;IX in Athletics."], College Sports Council, 8 Feb 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; High school participation rates substantiate this claim. The [[National Federation of State High School Associations|National Federation of High School associations]] reports that in 2010-11, there were 4,494,406 boys and 3,173,549 girls participating in high school athletics.&lt;ref name=NFHS&gt;NFHS [http://www.nfhs.org/content.aspx?id=5752 "High School Sports Participation Continues Upward Climb."], National Federation of High School Associations, Aug. 23, 2011,&lt;/ref&gt;  Although Title&amp;nbsp;IX's present application to high schools has not so far barred boys from sports activities, a rigid (tit for tat) gender quota clearly would have this effect.

Some continue to challenge Title&amp;nbsp;IX's application to high school athletics, however.  The American Sports Council has sued the Department of Education seeking a declaratory judgment that its policy interpreting Title&amp;nbsp;IX's requirement for equity in participation opportunities is limited to colleges and universities.&lt;ref name=Frommer&gt;Frederick J. Frommer. [http://abcnews.go.com/Sports/wireStory?id=14125030 "Group Sues Over Title&amp;nbsp;IX High School Enforcement."], Associated Press, 21 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; American Sports Council attorney Joshua Thompson said that “The three-part test and its encouragement of quotas, has no relevance to high schools or high-school sports no federal regulation or interpretation has ever said that high schools must abide by the three-part test and the sex-based quota system it fosters".&lt;ref name=McErlain/&gt; On the other hand, the Department of Education insists that Title&amp;nbsp;IX is a "valuable tool" for ensuring a level playing field for all students" and "plays a critical role in ensuring a fundamental level of fairness in America's schools and universities".&lt;ref name=Frommer/&gt;

Regarding college athletics, it has been stated that “Between 1981 and 1999 university athletic departments cut 171 men’s [[wrestling]] teams, 84 men’s [[tennis]] teams, 56 men’s [[gymnastics]] teams, 27 men’s [[track and field|track]] teams, and 25 men’s [[swimming (sport)|swimming]] teams".&lt;ref&gt;Williams, Alison. [http://law.du.edu "Title&amp;nbsp;IX- Tipping the Scales of Equality."], [[University of Denver]] Sturm College of Law, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Yet statistics showing the elimination of men's teams do not demonstrate, as some suggest, that Title&amp;nbsp;IX has expanded women's athletic programs at the expense of men's.  While some teams—both men's and women's—have been eliminated in the Title&amp;nbsp;IX era, both sexes have seen a net increase in the number of athletic periods over a similar time period as the above quote&lt;ref name="Women's Sports Foundation"&gt;Women's Sports Foundation. [http://www.womenssportsfoundation.org/en/home/research/articles-and-reports/school-and-colleges/gender-equity-report-card "Gender Equity Report Card."], [[Women's Sports Foundation]], 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; and by studies including more recent data, though when total enrollment which had likewise increased is controlled for, only women had an increase in participation.&lt;ref name="GA0"&gt;GAO. [http://www.gao.gov/new.items/d07535.pdf "Intercollegiate Athletics: Recent Trends in Teams and Participants in National Collegiate Athletic Association Sports."], [[Government Accountability Office]], 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Moreover, the more relevant statistic for measuring equity is not the number of teams. Because teams vary widely in size, it is more appropriate to compare the number of total participation opportunities those teams afford. Such comparisons also belie the suggestion that women's gains come at the expense of men's, as the total number of college participation opportunities has increased for both sexes in the Title&amp;nbsp;IX era, though solely for women when increased enrollment is accounted for, as men's participation remained static relative to university enrollment, and men's opportunities outnumber women's by a wide margin.&lt;ref name=GAO&gt;GAO&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2007 study of athletic opportunities at NCAA institutions, Professor John Cheslock reported that over 150,000 female athletic opportunities would need to be added in order to reach participation levels proportional to the female undergraduate population.&lt;ref&gt;Cheslock, John. [http://www.epi.soe.vt.edu/perspectives/policy_news/pdf/TitleIXFR.pdf "Who's Playing College Sports."], [[Women's Sports Foundation]], 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Men's athletics also receives the lionshare of athletic department budgets for operating expenses, recruiting, scholarships, and coaches salaries.&lt;ref name="Women's Sports Foundation"&gt;Women's Sports Foundation&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
Title&amp;nbsp;IX has been a source of controversy in part due to claims that the OCR's current interpretation of Title&amp;nbsp;IX, and specifically its three-prong test of compliance, is no longer faithful to the anti-discrimination language in Title&amp;nbsp;IX's text, and instead discriminates against men and has contributed to the reduction of programs for male athletes.&lt;ref name="Shelton 2001"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Irving 2003"&gt;{{cite news | title=Wrestling With Title&amp;nbsp;IX  |work= New York Times | first=John |last=Irving |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/28/opinion/28IRVI.html?pagewanted=3 |date=2003-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Gavora 2003"&gt;{{cite news | title=Tilting the Playing Field:  Schools, Sports, Sex and Title&amp;nbsp;IX | first=Jessica |last=Gavora |year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of the three-prong test contend that it operates as a "quota" in that it places undue emphasis on the first prong (known as the "proportionality" prong), which fails to take into account any differences in the genders' respective levels of interest in participating in athletics (in spite of the third prong, which focuses on any differences in the genders' respective levels of interest in participation). Instead it requires that the genders' athletic participation be substantially proportionate to their enrollment, without regard to interest.  Prong two is viewed as only a temporary fix for universities, as universities may only point to past expansion of opportunities for female students for a limited time before compliance with another prong is necessary.  Critics say that prong three likewise fails to consider male athletic interest in spite of its gender-neutral language, as it requires that the university fully and effectively accommodate the athletic interests of the "underrepresented sex", despite the fact that ED regulations expressly require that the OCR consider whether the institution "effectively accommodate[s] the interests and abilities of members of both sexes". As such, with a focus on increasing female athletic opportunities without any counterbalance to take male athletic interest into consideration, critics maintain that the OCR's three-prong test actually operates to discriminate against men.&lt;ref name="Shelton 2001"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Gavora 2003"/&gt;

Defenders of the three-prong test counter that the genders' differing athletic interest levels is merely a product of past discrimination, and that Title&amp;nbsp;IX should be interpreted to maximize female participation in athletics regardless of any existing disparity in interest. Thus while defenders argue that the three-prong test embodies the maxim that "opportunity drives interest",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Smith professor speaks on Title&amp;nbsp;IX |work=The Smith College Sophian |year=2008 |url=http://media.www.smithsophian.com/media/storage/paper587/news/2008/12/04/Sports/Smith.Professor.Speaks.On.Title.Ix-3567623.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; critics argue that the three-prong test goes beyond Title&amp;nbsp;IX original purpose of preventing discrimination, and instead amounts to an exercise in which athletic opportunities are taken away from male students and given to female students, despite the comparatively lower interest levels of those female students.  [[Academy Award]]-winning author and self-described women's rights advocate [[John Irving]] opined in a ''[[New York Times]]'' column that on this topic, women's advocates were being "purely vindictive" in insisting that the current OCR interpretation of Title&amp;nbsp;IX be maintained.&lt;ref name="Irving 2003"/&gt;

On March 17, 2005, OCR announced a clarification of prong three of the three-part test of Title&amp;nbsp;IX compliance. The guidance concerned the use of web-based surveys to determine the level of interest in varsity athletics among the underrepresented sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Additional Clarification of Intercollegiate Athletics Policy: Three-Part Test ― Part Three | url=http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/title9guidanceadditional.html | publisher= [[U.S. Department of Education]]| accessdate= 2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Opponents of the clarification – including the NCAA Executive Committee, which issued a resolution soon afterward asking Association members not to use the survey – claimed the survey was flawed in part because of the way it counted non-responses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=OCR rescinds 2005 Title&amp;nbsp;IX clarification | url=http://www.ncaa.org/wps/portal/ncaahome?WCM_GLOBAL_CONTEXT=/ncaa/ncaa/ncaa+news/ncaa+news+online/2010/association-wide/ocr+rescinds+2005+title+ix+clarification_04_20_10_ncaa_news | publisher= [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]]| accessdate= 2010-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 20, 2010, the U.S. Department of Education's Office for Civil Rights abandoned the 2005 clarification that allowed institutions to use only Internet or e‑mail surveys to meet the interests and abilities (third prong) option of the three-part test for Title&amp;nbsp;IX compliance.

On April 20, 2010, the [[United States Commission on Civil Rights]] weighed in on the OCR's three-prong test and procedures for implementing it. On that date, the Commission on Civil Rights released several recommendations on Title&amp;nbsp;IX policy to address what it termed "unnecessary reduction of men's athletic opportunities".&lt;ref name="Brady 2010"&gt;{{cite news | title=Commission: Title&amp;nbsp;IX interpretation unnecessarily hurts men's sports |work=USA Today | first=Erik |last=Brady |url= http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/2010-04-01-title-ix_N.htm |date=2010-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Commission advocated use of surveys to measure interest, and specifically recommended that the Department of Education's regulations on interest and abilities be revised "to explicitly take into account the interest of both sexes rather than just the interest of the underrepresented sex", almost always females.&lt;ref name="Brady 2010"/&gt;

==Recognition==

There were several events praising the 40th anniversary of Title&amp;nbsp;IX in June 2012. For example, the [[White House Council on Women and Girls]] hosted a panel to discuss the life-altering nature of sports. Panelists included [[Billie Jean King]], All‑American NCAA point guard Shoni Schimmel of the University of Louisville, and [[Aimee Mullins]], the first double-amputee sprinter to compete in NCAA track and field for Georgetown University.&lt;ref name="washingtonpostix"&gt;{{cite web|last=Groer |first=Annie |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/she-the-people/post/as-title-ix-turns-40-women-pay-homage/2012/06/23/gJQArEBjxV_blog.html |title=As Title&amp;nbsp;IX turns 40, women pay homage |publisher=The Washington Post |date=June 23, 2012 |accessdate=2012-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

President [[Barack Obama]] wrote a pro-Title&amp;nbsp;IX [[op-ed|op&amp;#8209;ed]] published in ''[[Newsweek]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/06/23/us-usa-obama-sports-gender-idUSBRE85M0I720120623 |title=Obama marks 1972 law lifting education barriers to girls |publisher=Reuters |date=June 23, 2012 |accessdate=2012-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Women's Sports Foundation]] honored over 40 female athletes.&lt;ref name="washingtonpostix"/&gt;

On June 21, 2012, [[espnW]] projected a digital mosaic featuring the largest-ever collection of women and girls’ sports images (all of which were submitted by the athletes themselves) onto the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] tablet of the [[Newseum]] in Washington, D.C. The mosaic also included photos of espnW’s Top 40 Athletes of the Past 40 Years.&lt;ref name="espnmediazoneix"&gt;{{cite web|last=Margolis |first=Rachel |url=http://espnmediazone.com/us/press-releases/2012/06/espnw-to-unveil-historic-title-ix-mosaic-in-washington-june-21/ |title=espnW To Unveil Historic Title IX Mosaic in Washington June 21 |publisher=Espnmediazone.com |date=June 18, 2012 |accessdate=2012-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[ESPN The Magazine]] produced its first “Women in Sports” issue in June 2012.&lt;ref name="espnmediazoneix"/&gt;

Also in June 2012, ESPN Classic first showed the documentary ''Sporting Chance: The Lasting Legacy of Title&amp;nbsp;IX'', narrated by [[Holly Hunter]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ncaa.com/news/ncaa/article/2012-06-11/title-ix-documentary-debuts-june-23&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sportingchancetitleix.com/&lt;/ref&gt; It also showed the documentary ''On the Basis of Sex: The Battle for Title&amp;nbsp;IX in Sports'', and other programming related to women's sports.&lt;ref&gt;http://espnmediazone.com/us/press-releases/2012/06/espntitleixprogrammingday/&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013 [[ESPN Films]] will show ''[[Nine for IX]]'', a series of documentaries about women in sports.&lt;ref name="espnmediazoneix"/&gt;  ''[[Good Morning America]]'' anchor [[Robin Roberts (newscaster)|Robin Roberts]] and [[Tribeca Productions]] cofounder [[Jane Rosenthal]] are executive producers of the series.&lt;ref name="espnmediazoneix"/&gt;

==Commission on Opportunity in Athletics==
On June 27, 2002, Secretary of Education [[Rod Paige]] announced the creation of the Commission on Opportunity in Athletics (COA), a blue-ribbon panel to examine ways to strengthen enforcement and expand opportunities to ensure fairness for all college athletes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Commission on Opportunity in Athletics|url=http://www.ed.gov/about/bdscomm/list/athletics/index.html| accessdate= 2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Co-chairs for the COA were [[Cynthia Cooper (basketball)|Cynthia Cooper]] and Ted Leland. The purpose of the Commission was to collect information, analyze issues, and obtain broad public input directed at improving the application of federal standards for measuring equal opportunity for men and women and boys and girls to participate in athletics under Title&amp;nbsp;IX.

The panel held four [[town hall meeting]]s (in Atlanta, Chicago, Colorado Springs, and San Diego) to allow the general public to comment on the past, present, and future of Title&amp;nbsp;IX. On February 26, 2003, the COA issued its final report.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ed.gov/about/bdscomm/list/athletics/report.html |title=COA Report Text |publisher=Ed.gov |date= |accessdate=2012-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The COA provided twenty-three recommendations to the Secretary of Education. Although many of the recommendations were unanimous, some of the more controversial recommendations passed by an 8‑5 vote. These dealt with considering non-scholarship athletes in prong one of the three-part test for compliance and allowing interest surveys to determine compliance with prong three. On the same day, Secretary of Education [[Rod Paige]] announced he would only consider unanimous recommendations, whose effect on the Department of Education was to:
*Reaffirm its strong commitment to equal opportunity for girls and boys, women and men
*Aggressively enforce Title&amp;nbsp;IX in a uniform way across the nation
*Give equal weight to all three prongs of the test governing Title&amp;nbsp;IX compliance
*Encourage schools to understand that the Department of Education disapproves of cutting teams in order to comply with Title&amp;nbsp;IX&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ed.gov/news/pressreleases/2003/02/02262003a.html Retrieved 2008-09-05.]{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Similar U.S. state laws==
Because Title&amp;nbsp;IX only addresses public and private schools that receive federal funding, several states have enacted similar laws to prohibit discrimination based on sex regardless of whether the school receives federal funding. As of 2008,{{Update after|2012|3|16}} about a third of the states have done so, including Alaska, California, Florida, Georgia, Hawaii, Illinois, Iowa, Maine, Minnesota, Nebraska, New Jersey, New Mexico, New York, Rhode Island, South Dakota, Washington, and Wisconsin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= State Title&amp;nbsp;IX Laws |url= http://www.WomensSportsFoundation.org/Content/Articles/Issues/Title-IX/S/State-Title-IX-Laws.aspx |work=Women's Sports Foundation |accessdate=2008-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{wikisource}}
{{portal|Women's sport}}
*[[Gender equality]]
*[[Major women's sport leagues in North America]]
*[[National Collegiate Women's Ice Hockey Championship]]

==Further reading==
*Brake, Deborah L. ''Getting in the Game: Title&amp;nbsp;IX and the Women's Sports Revolution'' (New York University Press; 2010) 287 pages, scholarly history
*Blumenthal, Karen. ''Let Me Play : The story of Title&amp;nbsp;IX, the law that changed the future of girls in America'' (Atheneum Books for Young Readers; 2005) 152 pages,
*Gavora, Jessica. ''Tilting the Playing Field: Schools, Sports, Sex, and Title&amp;nbsp;IX'' (Encounter Books; 2003) 165 pages,
* Title&amp;nbsp;IX Blog, http://title-ix.blogspot.com
* The American Civil ([[ACLU]]) outlines various ways in which Title IX can be applied to combat gender discrimination (http://www.aclu.org/title-ix-gender-equity-education)
* The National Women's Law Center (NWLC) provides a fact sheet addresses harassment and bullying based on gender and gender stereotypes (http://www.nwlc.org/sites/default/files/pdfs/nwlcharassbullying_titleixfactsheet.pdf)

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
* {{cite book | last = Hult  | first = Joan S.| last2 = Trekell| first2 = Marianna| title = A Century of women's basketball : From Frailty to Final Four | publisher = National Association for Girls and Women in Sport | location = Reston, Va | year = 1991 | isbn = 9780883144909 }}

{{Major women's sport leagues in North America}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Title Ix}}
[[Category:1972 in law]]
[[Category:92nd United States Congress]]
[[Category:College sports in the United States]]
[[Category:Sports law]]
[[Category:Gender equality]]
[[Category:United States federal civil rights legislation]]
[[Category:United States federal education legislation]]
[[Category:Women's sports]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>