<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221129103639|1124566246" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21950359" pageid="21950359" ns="0" title="Corrective rape"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-29T11:46:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Type of hate crime}}
{{complex|date=September 2022}}
{{other uses|Curative (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2022}}
{{Rape sidebar}}
{{Violence against women}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
'''Corrective rape''', also called '''curative rape''',&lt;ref name="UNreport2011"/&gt; as well as '''homophobic rape''',&lt;ref name="UNAIDS"/&gt;&lt;ref name="RASmith"/&gt;&lt;ref name="MDSmith"&gt;{{Cite book|editor-last=Smith |editor-first=Merril D.  |date=2018 |title=Encyclopedia of Rape and Sexual Violence |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7SJWDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA182 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |pages=182, 187 |isbn=9781440844904 |access-date=8 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[hate crime]] in which one or more people are [[rape]]d because of their perceived [[sexual orientation]] such as homosexuality or bisexuality. The common intended consequence of the rape, as claimed by the perpetrator, is to turn the person [[heterosexuality|heterosexual]].&lt;ref name="Bartle" /&gt;&lt;ref name="academia.edu"&gt;{{cite journal |url=https://www.academia.edu/9634350|title=Corrective Rape of black lesbian women in Post-Apartheid South Africa: investigating the symbolic violence and resulting misappropriation of symbolic power that ensues within a nexus of social imaginaries.|journal=A Night of Dostoevskian Smiles and Sadean Excesses|author=Fadi Baghdadi|date=28 June 2013|via=academia.edu|access-date=12 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Encyclopedia of Diversity and Social Justice|last=Thompson|first=Sherwood|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|year=2014|isbn=978-1442216044|volume=1|location=Lanham, MD|page=475}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ''corrective rape'' was coined in South Africa after well-known cases of corrective rapes of [[lesbian]] women such as [[Eudy Simelane]] (who was also murdered in the same attack) and Zoliswa Nkonyana became public. Popularisation of the term has raised awareness and encouraged [[LGBT]]+ people in countries across the world to come forward with their own stories of being raped as punishment for or in an attempt to change their sexual orientation or gender identity.&lt;ref name="Denton"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Denton |first=Michelle |date=2017|title=Rape Culture: How Can We End It? |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nn5mDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA31 |location=New York |publisher=Greenhaven Publishing LLC |page=31 |isbn=9781534562929 |access-date=8 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although some countries have laws protecting LGBT+ people, corrective rape is often overlooked.&lt;ref name="Hawthorne" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;

== Definitions==
Corrective rape is the use of [[rape]] against people who do not conform to perceived [[Norm (social)|social norms]] regarding [[human sexuality]] or [[gender role]]s. The goal is to punish perceived abnormal behavior and reinforce societal norms.&lt;ref name="academia.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Actionaid"/&gt; The crime was first{{when|date=September 2018 |reason=Which year?}} identified in South Africa,&lt;ref name="Janoff" /&gt;{{page needed|date=September 2018}} where it is sometimes supervised by members of the woman's family or local community.&lt;ref name="Bartle" /&gt; One of the earliest known mentions of the term is by South African feminist activist Bernedette Muthien during an August 2001 interview by [[Human Rights Watch]] in [[Cape Town]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Long |first1=Scott |last2=Brown |first2=A. Widney |last3=Cooper |first3=Gail |date=2003 |title=More Than a Name: State-sponsored Homophobia and Its Consequences in Southern Africa |url=https://archive.org/details/morethannamestat00long |url-access=registration |publisher=Human Rights Watch |page=[https://archive.org/details/morethannamestat00long/page/193 193] |isbn=9781564322869 |access-date=9 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Lesbians are particularly targeted for gang rape. African lesbians are more likely to be raped as lesbians in the townships. To what extent are [[coloured]] lesbians also targeted for rape because of their sexual orientation? There are no statistics for this, and I don't know what percent of coloured lesbians are targeted for corrective rape action. Growing up, I never heard that lesbians were targeted in this way and so I want to know when that started happening. Gangsterism has always existed in the townships, so you can't attribute it to that. I don't know why black lesbians are targeted more, either. I'd like to know how many women are being raped by brothers, fathers, etc., in coloured townships. Why is no one studying this? Has it just been under-reported, not studied, or what?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The [[United Nations]] [[UNAIDS]] 2015 Terminology Guidelines suggests that the term ''corrective rape'' should no longer be used, as it gives off the perception that something needs to be fixed. The guidelines propose that the term ''[[homophobic]] rape'' should be used instead.&lt;ref name="UNAIDS"&gt;{{cite web|last1=United Nations|title=UNAIDS 2015 Terminology Guidelines |url=http://www.unaids.org/sites/default/files/media_asset/2015_terminology_guidelines_en.pdf |website=UNAIDS.org |date=2015 |access-date=21 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MDSmith"/&gt; The words "so-called 'curative' or 'corrective' rape" were mentioned in 2011 in the first UN report on discrimination and violence against [[LGBT+]] people.&lt;ref name="UNreport2011"&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrcouncil/docs/19session/A.HRC.19.41_English.pdf |title=Discriminatory laws and practices and acts of violence against individuals based on their sexual orientation and gender identity |work=Report of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights |publisher=[[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]] |date=17 November 2011 |access-date=7 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2013 global study on [[HIV/AIDS]] suggested the term ''[[lesbophobia|lesphobic]] rape'' to emphasize the fact that [[lesbians]] constitute the overwhelming majority of victims of this phenomenon.&lt;ref name="RASmith"&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last=Smith |editor-first=Raymond A.  |date=2010 |title=Global HIV/AIDS Politics, Policy, and Activism: Persistent Challenges and Emerging Issues: Persistent Challenges and Emerging Issues |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UdXYAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA49 |location=Santa Barbara |publisher=ABC-CLIO |page=49 |isbn=9780313399466 |access-date=8 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others have emphasized that gay men, [[transgender]], [[Asexuality|asexual]] and [[intersex]] people can also be victims of corrective rape for similar reasons.&lt;ref&gt;Hunter-Gault (2015), p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MDSmith178"&gt;Merrill D. Smith (2018), p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Denton"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oas.org/en/iachr/multimedia/2015/lgbti-violence/forms-lgbti-violence.html|title=IACHR: Forms and contexts of violence against LGBTI persons in the Americas|website=IACHR: Inter-American Commission on Human Rights|language=en|access-date=2019-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contributing factors and motivations==
Corrective rape is a [[hate crime]].&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; A 2000 study suggested an atmosphere supportive of hate crimes against gay men and lesbians, reactions to hate crimes by the broader community, and responses by police and justice systems contribute to corrective rape.&lt;ref name="Bartle" /&gt;

Some people believe corrective rape can "fix" people who do not conform to gender norms or who are not heterosexual. [[ActionAid]] reports that survivors remember being told that they were being taught a lesson.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.actionaid.org.uk/sites/default/files/publications/hate_crimes_the_rise_of_corrective_rape_in_south_africa_september_2009.pdf|title=ActionAid|date=2009 |publisher=ActionAid|access-date=2016-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some perpetrators of the hate crime are impelled by a sense of misogyny and chauvinism.&lt;ref&gt;Reddy, Vasu, Cheryl-Ann Potgieter, and Nonhlanhla Mkhize. "Cloud over the rainbow nation:'corrective rape'and other hate crimes against black lesbians." (2007).&lt;/ref&gt; Personal experiences have included female victims being told they were "being shown what they were missing" while male victims have related gang rape accounts "where the objective was to make the experience of being [[Top, bottom and versatile|sexually receptive]] so violent and frightening that the victim would fear potential homosexual experiences afterward".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Jay |first1=Karla |last2=Young |first2=Allen |title=The gay report: Lesbians and gay men speak out about sexual experiences and lifestyles. |date=1979 |publisher=Summit |location=New York |isbn=0-671-40013-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some sources argue that many cases of corrective rape are caused by [[is–ought problem|drawing moral conclusions]] from the [[nature–nurture debate]]. Despite the scientific community concluding that sexual orientation is the result of biology and environment,&lt;ref name="pediatrics2004"&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1542/peds.113.6.1827 |author=Frankowski BL|author2=American Academy of Pediatrics Committee on Adolescence|title=Sexual orientation and adolescents |journal=[[Pediatrics (journal)|Pediatrics]]|volume=113 |issue=6 |pages=1827–32 |date=June 2004|pmid=15173519|url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/113/6/1827.long|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Lamanna"&gt;{{cite book|authors=Mary Ann Lamanna, Agnes Riedmann, Susan D Stewart|title=Marriages, Families, and Relationships: Making Choices in a Diverse Society|publisher=[[Cengage Learning]]|isbn=978-1305176898|year=2014|page=82|access-date=11 February 2016|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fofaAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA82|quote=The reason some individuals develop a gay sexual identity has not been definitively established &amp;nbsp;– nor do we yet understand the development of heterosexuality. The American Psychological Association (APA) takes the position that a variety of factors impact a person's sexuality. The most recent literature from the APA says that sexual orientation is not a choice that can be changed at will, and that sexual orientation is most likely the result of a complex interaction of environmental, cognitive and biological factors...is shaped at an early age...[and evidence suggests] biological, including genetic or inborn hormonal factors, play a significant role in a person's sexuality (American Psychological Association 2010).}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Stuart"&gt;{{cite book|author=Gail Wiscarz Stuart|title=Principles and Practice of Psychiatric Nursing|publisher=[[Elsevier Health Sciences]]|isbn=978-0323294126|year=2014|page=502|access-date=11 February 2016|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ivALBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA502|quote=No conclusive evidence supports any one specific cause of homosexuality; however, most researchers agree that biological and social factors influence the development of sexual orientation.}}&lt;/ref&gt; many people do not believe that homosexuality (or other forms of non-heterosexuality) has a genetic basis and instead believe it is only the result of one's environment. Because of this, some of these people believe sexual orientation can be changed or, as they see it, fixed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = McCommon | first1 = B | year = 2006 | title = Antipsychiatry and the Gay Rights Movement | journal = Psychiatr Serv | volume = 57 | issue = 12| pages = 1809; author reply 1809–10 | doi = 10.1176/appi.ps.57.12.1809 | pmid = 17158503 | s2cid = 37419476 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Rissmiller | first1 = DJ | last2 = Rissmiller | first2 = J | last3 = Rissmiller | year = 2006 | title = Letter in reply | journal = Psychiatr Serv | volume = 57 | issue = 12| pages = 1809–1810 | doi = 10.1176/appi.ps.57.12.1809-a }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ladie Terry. (1994) 'ORPHANS' SPEAK OUT. San Jose Mercury News (California) Tuesday MORNING FINAL EDITION. 13 December 1994&lt;/ref&gt;

== Intersectionality ==
[[Intersectionality]] is ''intersecting'' social identities and related systems of [[oppression]], [[Dominance hierarchy|domination]], or [[discrimination]]. In South Africa, black lesbians may face homophobia, [[sexism]], [[racism]], and [[classism]]. Research in 2008 by Triangle, a gay rights group, revealed that black lesbians were twice as afraid of sexual assault as white lesbians.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Taking into account race and sexuality together is essential when examining corrective rape, as both subjects cross into each other and influence each other heavily.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|date=Feb 2013|title=Rape as a Weapon of Hate: Discursive Constructions and Material Consequences of Black Lesbianism in South Africa|journal=Women's Studies in Communication}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Intersectionality plays a major role in corrective rape cases. Sexuality and gender especially, define the social and political rank of victims. Many are ostracized, and other abusive measures are taken in order to "cure" individuals of their sexuality.

== Impact on victims ==
Corrective rape and other accompanying acts of violence can result in [[physical trauma|physical]] and [[psychological trauma]], mutilation, unwanted [[pregnancy]], and may contribute to [[suicide]].&lt;ref name="Hawthorne" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Mabuse" /&gt; Corrective rape is a major contributor to [[HIV]] infection in South African lesbians.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt; In South Africa, approximately 10% of lesbians are HIV positive, with corrective rape being the most likely cause.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; HIV in South Africa is an epidemic, and due to homophobia, there is a lack of education about sexually transmitted diseases among lesbians. Homophobic laws and discrimination in South Africa contribute to the poor quality of health care for minorities.

The psychological effects of corrective rape on victims can be detrimental. Many victims in countries such as South Africa and India where corrective rape is most prevalent suffer from a strong sense of insecurity and disempowerment due to strong homophobia in their communities. This homophobia can lead to both physical and psychological violence. There have been at least 30 lesbians who have been murdered in South Africa in the last 15 years because of their sexual orientation.{{citation needed|date=August 2018}} However, violence against the LGBTQ community in South Africa is seldom reported.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Many survivors of corrective rape suffer from triple discrimination for being women, black, and homosexual.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; This is especially true in South African townships, where corrective rape is common for lesbian women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Nduna|first=Mzikazi|date=2012|title=Disempowerment And Psychological Distress in the Lives of Young People in Eastern Cape, South Africa|journal=Journal of Child and Family Studies|volume=21|issue=6|pages=1018–1027|doi=10.1007/s10826-011-9564-y|s2cid=143486741}}&lt;/ref&gt; Corrective rape victims may suffer from [[depression (mood)|depression]], [[Anxiety disorder|anxiety]], and/or [[Posttraumatic stress disorder|post-traumatic stress disorder]].&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=du Toit|first=Louise|date=2014|title=Shifting Meanings of Postconflict Sexual Violence in South Africa|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|volume=40|issue=1|pages=101–123|doi=10.1086/676895|jstor=10.1086/676895|s2cid=143151249}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to racial and sexual discrimination in health care, victims must often deal with these issues on their own.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

Again, in countries like [[Nigeria]] where the Same-Sex Marriage (Prohibition) Act, 2013 (SSMPA) "prohibits a marriage contract or civil union entered into between persons of the same sex...",&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |date=1 April 2014 |title=Briefing on Same Sex Marriage Prohibition Act 2013 |url=https://www.humandignitytrust.org/wp-content/uploads/resources/Briefing_on_Same_Sex_Marriage_Prohibition_Act_2013_final.pd |journal=Human Dignity Trust |pages=1 }}{{Dead link|date=October 2022 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; lesbian, gay, and transgender people who are raped and targeted do not have the protection of the police and cannot report rape crimes done to them, as the police are likely to legitimize the abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2016-10-20 |title=Nigeria: Harsh Law's Severe Impact on LGBT Community |url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2016/10/20/nigeria-harsh-laws-severe-impact-lgbt-community |access-date=2022-07-02 |website=Human Rights Watch |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2019-03-27 |title=Homophobic rhetoric and Nigeria's culture of violence |url=https://guardian.ng/features/homophobic-rhetoric-and-nigerias-culture-of-violence/ |access-date=2022-07-02 |website=The Guardian Nigeria News - Nigeria and World News |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Giwa |first1=Sulaimon Abiodun Olawale |last2=Logie |first2=Carmen H. |last3=Karki |first3=Karun K. |last4=Makanjuola |first4=Olumide F. |last5=Obiagwu |first5=Chinonye Edmund |date=2020-06-30 |title=Police violence targeting LGBTIQ+ people in Nigeria: Advancing solutions for a 21st century challenge |url=https://journals.gre.ac.uk/index.php/gswr/article/view/1108 |journal=Greenwich Social Work Review |language=en |volume=1 |issue=1 |pages=36–49 |doi=10.21100/gswr.v1i1.1108 |s2cid=225731237 |issn=2633-4313}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reports of corrective rape are cloaked in "stigma" and "embarrassment" so they remain largely underreported. Apart from this being a violation of the fundamental right to protection as stated in the Violence Against Persons (Prohibition) Act 2015,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Everything You Need to Know About the Law That Could Reduce Gender-Based Violence in Nigeria |url=https://www.globalcitizen.org/en/content/everything-you-need-to-know-vapp-Nigeria/ |access-date=2022-07-02 |website=Global Citizen |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; this sexual discrimination poses a threat to the general health of homosexual people who are victims of rape as they also fear the intolerance and disregard from medical providers, leaving them susceptible to STIs and HIV.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Sekoni |first1=Adekemi O. |last2=Jolly |first2=Kate |last3=Gale |first3=Nicola K. |last4=Ifaniyi |first4=Oluwafemi A. |last5=Somefun |first5=Esther O. |last6=Agaba |first6=Emmanuel I. |last7=Fakayode |first7=Victoria A. |date=August 2016 |title=Provision of Healthcare Services to Men Who Have Sex with Men in Nigeria: Students' Attitudes Following the Passage of the Same-Sex Marriage Prohibition Law |url=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27093347/ |journal=LGBT Health |volume=3 |issue=4 |pages=300–307 |doi=10.1089/lgbt.2015.0061 |issn=2325-8306 |pmid=27093347|s2cid=46837244 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |date=1 April 2014 |title=Briefing on Same Sex Marriage Prohibition Act 2013 |url=https://www.humandignitytrust.org/wp-content/uploads/resources/Briefing_on_Same_Sex_Marriage_Prohibition_Act_2013_final.pdf |journal=Human Dignity Trust |pages=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prevalence ==
Corrective rape has been reported in countries across the world including [[Ecuador]],&lt;ref name="Caselli" /&gt; [[Haiti]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://projects.aljazeera.com/2014/haiti-lgbt/ |title=Haiti's fight for gay rights |author=Allyn Gaestel |publisher=Al Jazeera|date=8 November 2014 |access-date=7 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[India]], [[Jamaica]],&lt;ref name="Czyzselska"&gt;{{cite news |last=Czyzselska |first=Jane |title=No Woman No Cry: Lesbians in Jamaica |url=http://www.gaytimes.co.uk/HotSpots/Travel-page-3-sectionid-1-articleid-357.html |newspaper=GayTimes |access-date=3 June 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140606225837/http://www.gaytimes.co.uk/HotSpots/Travel-page-3-sectionid-1-articleid-357.html |archive-date=6 June 2014 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kenya]],&lt;ref name="KHRC"&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.khrc.or.ke/mobile-publications/equality-and-anti-discrimination/70-the-outlawed-amongst-us/file.html |title=The Outlawed Amongst Us. A study of the LGBTI community's search for equality and non-discrimination in Kenya |publisher=Kenya Human Rights Commission |date=2011 |access-date=9 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kyrgyzstan]],&lt;ref name="UNreport2011"/&gt; the [[Netherlands]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.trouw.nl/samenleving/toen-was-misbruik-nog-heel-gewoon~a9d19e2f/ |title=Toen was misbruik nog heel gewoon |author=Rianne Oosterom |work=[[Trouw]] |date=4 September 2018 |access-date=7 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nigeria]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://lens.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/09/26/gay-africans-seeking-asylum-in-brooklyn/ |title=Gay Africans Seeking Asylum in New York |author=Fayemi Shakur |work=The New York Times |date=26 September 2014 |access-date=7 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Peru]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.latintimes.com/cure-being-gay-corrective-rapes-lesbians-reported-peru-gay-conversion-therapy-minors-336432 |title=Cure For Being Gay? Corrective Rapes of Lesbians Reported in Peru As 'Gay Conversion' Therapy For Minors Banned in Illinois |author=Cedar Attanasio |work=latin Times  |date=24 August 2015 |access-date=8 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[South Africa]],&lt;ref name="Middleton" /&gt; [[Thailand]],&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt; [[Uganda]],&lt;ref name="GuarUganda"/&gt; [[Ukraine]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://nowtoronto.com/news/in-the-us-old-homophobia-is-rising-again/ |title=Old homophobia is rising again in the United States |author=Marusya Bociurkiw |work=[[Now (newspaper)|Now]] |date=15 June 2016 |access-date=7 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[United Kingdom]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-44686374 |title='Gay conversion therapy' to be banned as part of LGBT equality plan |publisher=BBC News |date=3 July 2018 |access-date=7 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[United States]],&lt;ref name="MDSmith178"/&gt; and [[Zimbabwe]].&lt;ref name="Shaw" /&gt;&lt;ref name="UN" /&gt;

=== India ===
Children in India have been speaking out about how their parents are sanctioning the child's sexuality by using "corrective rape therapy" (same as corrective rape).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/life-style/relationships/parenting/Victims-of-corrective-rape-speak-up/articleshow/47602170.cm|title=Victims of Corrective Rape Speak Up|date=June 2015|work=[[The Times of India]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Corrective rape in India typically happens in order to protect the family name, to avoid shaming from religious communities, and to prevent abnormal perception by the surrounding community. In India, there is a general discomfort with discussing homosexuality, even if an individual identifies as homosexual. This discomfort comes from the overall negative attitude towards homosexuality and the fact is that individuals in India who identify as homosexual are victimized at a higher rate. There is also a high level of negativity towards the trans community in India. Religious commitments tend to be very strong in traditional cultures and this is where much of the tension and poor perception came from. According to statistics from the Crisis Intervention Team of LGBT Collective in Telangana, India, there have been 15 reported instances of corrective rape that have been reported in the last five years.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=India's Bollywood Speaks Out Against Rape|last=MM Vetticad|first=Anna|date=10 July 2014|work=Newspaper}}&lt;/ref&gt; In general, there has been a 902 percent increase in reported rapes in India from 1971 to 2012; however, it is estimated that 90% of sex crimes in the country go unreported.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/features/2014/07/india-bollywood-speaks-out-against-rape-201471075423510320.html|title=India's Bollywood speaks out against rape|publisher=Al Jazeera|access-date=2016-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Jamaica ===
{{Further|LGBT rights in Jamaica}}

Amnesty International has received reports of violence against lesbians in [[Jamaica]], including rape and other forms of sexual violence. Lesbians reportedly have been attacked on the grounds of mannish physical appearance or other visible signs of sexuality. Some reports of abduction and rape come from inner-city communities, where local non-governmental organizations have expressed concerns about high incidences{{verify spelling|date=September 2022|reason=''incidence'' is normally used only in the singular form, perhaps ''incidence'', ''incidents'',  or ''instances'' was intended}} of violence against women.&lt;ref name="Czyzselska"/&gt;

=== Kenya ===
In Kenya, perpetrators and apologists claim that rape is a method "to straighten" LGBTI people.&lt;ref name="KHRC"/&gt;

=== Nigeria ===
In Nigeria, lesbians are the major victims of corrective rape and this has roots in [[patriarchy]]. To many Nigerians, it is incomprehensible that women may seek relationships with people other than men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last1=Committee |first1=UN Human Rights |last2=al |first2=AGHI-Access to Good Health Initiative; TIERS- The Initiative for Equal Rights in Nigeria; IAH- Initiative for the Advancement of Humanity et |date=2019-01-01 |title=Human Rights Situation for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender (LGBT) Persons and Sexual Rights in Nigeria; Report presented to the UN Human Rights Committee 126th Session; July 1 to July 26 of 2019 |url=https://www.ecoi.net/en/document/2015637.html |access-date=2022-07-02 |website=ecoi.net |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi=10.1007/s11606-012-2291-2 | title=Incorporating Lesbian and Bisexual Women into Women Veterans' Health Priorities | year=2013 | last1=Lehavot | first1=Keren | last2=Simpson | first2=Tracy L. | journal=Journal of General Internal Medicine | volume=28 | pages=609–614 | pmid=23807073 | pmc=3695269 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== South Africa ===
{{Further|LGBT rights in South Africa|Rape in South Africa}}
[[File:Justice For Sizakhele &amp; Salome (8036300204).jpg|thumb|Soweto Pride 2012 participants remember two lesbians who were raped and murdered in 2007.&lt;ref name="Ndaba"&gt;{{cite web |last=Ndaba |first=Baldwin |title='Hate crime' against lesbians slated |url=http://www.iol.co.za/news/south-africa/hate-crime-against-lesbians-slated-1.361821 |publisher=IOL News |access-date=22 December 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131224103946/http://www.iol.co.za/news/south-africa/hate-crime-against-lesbians-slated-1.361821 |archive-date=24 December 2013 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In South Africa, women have less sexual and economic power than men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Mantell|first1=Joanne|last2=Needham|first2=Sarah|last3=Smit|first3=Jennifer Ann|last4=Hoffman|first4=Susie|last5=Cebekhulu|first5=Queen|last6=Adams-Skinner|first6=Jessica|last7=Exner|first7=Theresa|last8=Mabude|first8=Zonke|last9=Beksinska|first9=Mags|last10=Stein|first10=Zena|last11=Milford|first11=Cecilia|title=Gender norms in South Africa: implications for HIV and pregnancy prevention among African and Indian women students at a South African tertiary institution|journal=Culture, Health &amp; Sexuality|date=February 2009|volume=11|issue=2|pages=139–157|doi=10.1080/13691050802521155|pmc=2782559|pmid=19247859}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the factors associated with this inequality is strict gender roles, which has led to one of the highest rates of [[violence against women]] in the world.&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt;&lt;ref name="HRW" /&gt; The South African government conducted a survey in 2009 on sexual assault. One in four men admit to engaging in sexual activity with a woman who did not consent and nearly half of these men admitted to raping more than once.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Carter|first1=Clare|title=The Brutality of "Corrective Rape" |url=https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2013/07/26/opinion/26corrective-rape.html|website=[[The New York Times]]|access-date=12 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also estimated that a woman is raped every 26 seconds in South Africa.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Corrective rape is used as a punishment for people who are gay or do not fit traditional gender roles (usually women), where often they are [[verbally abused]] before the rape. The perpetrator may claim to be teaching the women a lesson on how to be a "real woman".&lt;ref name="academia.edu"/&gt; Because women have less control over their economic situation, which creates economic vulnerability, they have less control over their own sexual activities.&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt; Poor black women who live in townships are more likely to become victims of corrective violence, and gay women are more likely to be isolated with little support, which increases their chances of being targeted.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Mabuse" /&gt;

The [[South African Constitution]] states that no person shall be discriminated against based on his or her gender, [[race (human categorization)|race]], or sexual orientation.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt;&lt;ref name="CNN" /&gt; [[Equality Act (South Africa)|The Equality Act]] of 2000 specifically bans [[hate crime]]s, crimes in which people are targeted because of one or more aspects of their identity.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Although this technically includes crimes based on sexual orientation, in practice such cases are not brought to trial.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Crimes based on sexual orientation are not expressly recognized in South Africa; corrective rape reports are not separated from general rape reports.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Mabuse" /&gt; In December 2009, there had been 31 recorded murders of lesbians in South Africa since 1998, but only one had resulted in a conviction.&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt;

The reason for this discrepancy between the law and practice is a result of [[heteronormativity]] and homophobia in South Africa. Heteronormativity can be defined as "the institutions, structures of understanding, and practical orientations that make heterosexuality not only seem coherent—that is organised as a sexuality—but also privileged".&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal |url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/1344178 |title=Sex in Public |last1=Berlant |first1=Lauren |last2=Warner |first2=Michael |journal=Critical Inquiry |volume=24 |number=2 |date=1998 |pages=547–556 |publisher=The University of Chicago Press |doi=10.1086/448884 |jstor=1344178 |s2cid=161701244 |access-date=21 April 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some historians believe the heteronormativity in South Africa can be attributed to the nation's postcolonial years of racism, and it appears that today many South Africans are recommitted to their traditional heritage.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Black South African lesbians are not included in this [[social construction]], and this leads back to the concept of [[intersectionality]]. Black lesbians in South Africa are not only excluded because of their sexual orientation but also because of their ethnicity. As displayed in the media, most homosexuality is displayed as white, leaving black lesbians in South African even more marginalized.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; In South Africa, homosexuality is regarded as "un-African" by some.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; In 2004, the [[Human Sciences Research Council (South Africa)|Human Science Research Council]] found that 78% of the respondents thought of homosexuality as unacceptable. According to [[Human Rights Watch]], in the last 20 years, attitudes toward [[homosexuality]] have become worse in South Africa.{{citation needed|date=December 2019}}

Corrective rape is on the rise in South Africa. More than 10 lesbians are raped weekly to correct their sexual preferences, as estimated by [[Luleki Sizwe]], a South African nonprofit.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Contemporary Sexuality" /&gt; It is estimated that at least 500 lesbians become victims of corrective rape every year and that 86% of black lesbians in the [[Western Cape]] live in fear of being [[sexually assaulted]], as reported by the Triangle Project in 2008.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt; Yet victims of corrective rape are less likely to report it because of the negative social view of homosexuality.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt; Under-reporting is high for sexually violent crimes, thus the number of corrective rapes are likely higher than what is reported.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;

Although it is thought to be uncommon, men also become victims of corrective rape. A study conducted by OUT [[LGBT]] Well-being and the University of South Africa Centre for Applied Psychology (UCAP) showed that "the percentage of black gay men who said they have experienced corrective rape matched that of the black lesbians who partook in the study".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Louw|first1=Angelo|title=Men are also 'corrective rape' victims |url=http://mg.co.za/article/2014-04-11-men-are-also-corrective-rape-victims|website=Mail&amp;Guardian |date=11 April 2014 |access-date=17 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, not all men admit to being victims of corrective rape.

One South African man stated, "Lesbians get raped and killed because it is accepted by our community and by our culture."&lt;ref name="Middleton" /&gt; Kekelesto explained that her experience as "where men try to turn you into a real African woman" and that she was being taught how to be a black woman.&lt;ref name="academia.edu" /&gt;

[[File:Dying For Justice (8036294736).jpg|thumb|left|Soweto Pride 2012 participants protest against violence against lesbians with a "Dying for Justice" banner and T-shirts which read "Solidarity with women who speak out".]]
Galip Asvat, a successful hair salon business owner, is a gay man born in [[Klerksdorp]]. He moved to [[Hillbrow]], which was a haven for the LGBT community, in the early 2000s.&lt;ref name="mg.co.za"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Louw|first1=Angelo|title=Men are also 'corrective rape' victims|url=http://mg.co.za/article/2014-04-11-men-are-also-corrective-rape-victims|website=Mail&amp;Guardian|date=11 April 2014 |access-date=17 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; One early morning in 2007, Asvat was ambushed and raped by three men in his apartment building. On his attack, he said, "They thought I was a woman, and when they found out I was a man, that's when they became even more violent."&lt;ref name="mg.co.za"/&gt; His beating was brutal and the gang of men nearly cut off his genitals.

Sizakele Sigasa, a lesbian activist living in [[Soweto]], and her partner Salome Masooa were raped, [[torture]]d, and murdered in July 2007. South African lesbian-[[gay rights]] organizations, including the umbrella-group Joint Working Group, said the attack was driven by lesbophobia.&lt;ref name="Ndaba"/&gt; Two other rape/murders of lesbians occurred in South Africa earlier in Summer 2007: Simangele Nhlapo, member of an [[HIV-positive]] support group was raped and murdered in June, along with her two-year-old daughter; and Madoe Mafubedu, age 16, was raped and stabbed to death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Pithouse |first=Richard |title=Only Protected on Paper |url=http://sacsis.org.za/site/article/644.1 |publisher=The South African Civil Society Information Service |access-date=22 December 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131224110129/http://sacsis.org.za/site/article/644.1 |archive-date=24 December 2013 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 April 2008, 31-year-old soccer player [[Eudy Simelane]] was abducted, gang-raped and killed in [[KwaThema]], her hometown near Johannesburg.&lt;ref name="HRW" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Kelly" /&gt; Simelane was a star of the South Africa's acclaimed [[Banyana Banyana]] national female football squad, an avid equality rights campaigner, and one of the first women to live openly as a lesbian in KwaThema.&lt;ref name="Kelly" /&gt;

On 24 April 2011, LGBT activist [[Noxolo Nogwaza]] was raped and murdered in KwaThema.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13265300 |title=South Africa killing of lesbian Nogwaza 'a hate crime' |date=3 May 2011 |publisher=BBC News |access-date=28 November 2012 |archive-date=28 January 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120128183653/http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13265300 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, two writers from South African men's magazine ''[[FHM]]'' were fired as a result of corrective rape jokes they made on Facebook. After a disciplinary hearing on Friday, 19 July 2013, ''FHM'' dismissed both men from their positions, calling their comments "entirely unacceptable".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mg.co.za/article/2013-07-19-fhm-fires-rape-comment-writers|title=FHM fires writers over rape comments|author=Staff Reporter|date=19 July 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

South Africa is a signatory of the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women (CEDAW), which obligates states to remove discriminatory barriers from the full and free exercise of rights by women. The convention's duty to modify the conduct of private citizens to ensure equality for women covers attitudes that include the inferiority of women and stereotyped gender roles, which arguably encompass the animus toward gay women that motivates many men to commit corrective rape.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt; 66% of South Africa women said they did not report their attack because they would not be taken seriously.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt; Of these, 25% said they feared exposing their sexual orientation to the police and 22% said they were afraid of being abused by the police.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt;

In August 2011, the [[Department of Justice and Constitutional Development|Department of Justice]] established a National Task Team (NTT) to address the issue of hate crimes against LGBT people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Team starts work on gay hate crimes |agency=[[South African Press Association|SAPA]]-DPA |date=10 August 2011 |url=http://www.iol.co.za/news/crime-courts/team-starts-work-on-gay-hate-crimes-1.1115051 |newspaper=[[Independent Online (South Africa)|IOL News]] |access-date=15 August 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110917113543/http://www.iol.co.za/news/crime-courts/team-starts-work-on-gay-hate-crimes-1.1115051 |archive-date=17 September 2011 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2014, then [[Minister of Justice and Constitutional Development|Minister of Justice]] [[Jeff Radebe]] launched a National Intervention Strategy for the LGBTI Sector developed by the NTT to address sex-based violence and [[gender-based violence]] against members of the community. The NTT has established a rapid response team to attend to unsolved criminal cases as a matter of urgency and produced an information pamphlet with frequently asked questions about LGBTI persons. Radebe stated that the Department of Justice acknowledged the need for a specific legal framework for hate crimes and that the matter would be subjected to public debate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=National Intervention Strategy for LGBTI Sector 2014|url=http://www.justice.gov.za/vg/lgbti/2014-LGBTI-Strategy.pdf|publisher=Department of Justice and Constitutional Development|access-date=20 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Radebe launches LGBTI violence programme |url=http://www.iol.co.za/news/crime-courts/radebe-launches-lgbti-violence-programme-1.1681563 |access-date=20 July 2014 |agency=SAPA |newspaper=IOL |date=29 April 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140626095708/http://www.iol.co.za/news/crime-courts/radebe-launches-lgbti-violence-programme-1.1681563 |archive-date=26 June 2014 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Diale|first1=Lerato|title=Plan to combat gender violence|url=http://www.thenewage.co.za/124285-1007-53-Plan_to_combat_gender_violence|access-date=20 July 2014|work=The New Age|date=30 April 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140720144529/http://www.thenewage.co.za/124285-1007-53-Plan_to_combat_gender_violence|archive-date=20 July 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2011, there was an article published that stated that there are about 10 new cases of corrective rape a week in Cape Town.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report/92198/south-africa-activism-makes-inroads-corrective-rape|title=Activism makes inroads on 'corrective rape'|date=2011-03-15|website=IRIN|access-date=2016-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cape Town|Cape Town, South Africa]], specifically has 2.5 million people and since 2011, the prevalence of corrective rape has only increased.

According to [[LGBT rights by country or territory|gay-rights]] organization Triangle, the practice of "corrective rape" is widespread in South Africa. Research released in 2008 by Triangle, revealed that 86% of black lesbians from the Western Cape said they lived in fear of sexual assault.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/mar/12/eudy-simelane-corrective-rape-south-africa |title=Raped and Killed for Being a LEsbian: South Africa Ignores "Corrective" Attacks |last=Kelly |first=Annie |date=12 March 2009 |website=The Guardian |access-date=21 April 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Uganda ===
{{Further|LGBT rights in Uganda}}

Five cases in which the victims were lesbians or transgender males were reported in [[Uganda]] between June and November 2011.&lt;ref name="GuarUganda"/&gt;

=== United States ===
In the [[United States]], [[Brandon Teena]] (1972–1993) is a well-known victim of corrective rape (and thereafter murder) for being a [[trans man]]. The book ''All She Wanted'' (1996) and the two films ''[[The Brandon Teena Story]]'' (1998) and ''[[Boys Don't Cry (1999 film)|Boys Don't Cry]]'' (1999) were about him.&lt;ref name="MDSmith178"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=McOrmond-Plummer |first1=Louise |last2=Easteal |first2=Patricia |last3=Levy-Peck |first3=Jennifer Y. |date=2014 |title=Intimate Partner Sexual Violence: A Multidisciplinary Guide to Improving Services and Support for Survivors of Rape and Abuse |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1dnDAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA266 |location=London |publisher=Jessica Kingsley Publishers |page=266 |isbn=9780857006554 |access-date=8 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Zimbabwe ===
{{Further|LGBT rights in Zimbabwe}}

A U.S. State Department report on Zimbabwe states, "In response to social pressure, some families reportedly subjected their LGBT members to corrective rape and forced marriages to encourage heterosexual conduct. Such crimes were rarely reported to police. Women, in particular, were subjected to rape by male family members."&lt;ref name="USZimbabwe2012"/&gt; 
Following the publication of an earlier report with similar wording,&lt;ref name="USZimbabwe2009"/&gt; Zimbabwean journalist [[Angus Shaw (writer)|Angus Shaw]] said that lesbian women are raped by men to make them enjoy heterosexual acts and gay men are raped by women to remove their sexual orientation tendencies.&lt;ref name="Gonda"/&gt;

==Campaigning and activism==
Child sponsorship charity [[ActionAid]] has published an article discussing corrective rape, and see ending violence against women as a pivotal part of their mission.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt; The group joined with 26 gay and women's rights and community groups, to organize a campaign focused on South Africa but also aimed at the international community, to raise awareness of the issues.  The campaign was dedicated to raising awareness about the rape and murder of two lesbian women in a Johannesburg township and called for sexual orientation to be specifically recognised as grounds for protection by police and justice systems.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt;

Ndumie Funda, a South African Social Justice Activist, started her work to end corrective rape by launching a social campaign on [[Change.org]] in hopes to have the South African Government recognize hate crimes committed due to biases against sexual orientation and provide protection for victims. This particular petition ended up gathering almost 200 thousand signatures from individuals making up over 175 countries, forcing the government to recognize this issue. The government agreed to meet Funda and in 2014 South Africa passed its first law against hate crimes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thedp.com/article/2015/02/south-africa-ndumie-funda|title=Activist takes on mission against "corrective" rape|website=thedp.com|access-date=2016-05-02|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190417160040/https://www.thedp.com/article/2015/02/south-africa-ndumie-funda|archive-date=17 April 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Causes of sexual violence]]
* [[Hate crime]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Lesbophobia]]
* [[Rape culture]]
* [[Rape statistics]]
* [[Sexual assault of LGBT persons]]
* [[Sex crimes]]
* [[Sexual violence in South Africa]]
* [[Transphobia]]
* [[Types of rape]]
* [[Violence against LGBT people]]

== References ==
{{reflist
| refs =

&lt;ref name="Bartle"&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Bartle
| first = EE
| title = Lesbians And Hate Crimes
| journal = Journal of Poverty
| volume = 4
| issue = 4
| year = 2000
| citeseerx = 10.1.1.196.9177
| pages= 23–44
| doi = 10.1300/J134v04n04_02
| s2cid = 144939243
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Hawthorne"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Hawthorne | first1 = Susan | year = 2005 | title = Ancient Hatred And Its Contemporary Manifestation: The Torture of Lesbians | url = http://journals.gonzaga.edu/index.php/johs/article/view/65 | journal = Journal of Hate Studies | volume = 4 | issue = 1| pages = 33–58 | doi = 10.33972/jhs.32 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Di"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Di Silvio | first1 = Lorenzo | year = 2011 | title = Correcting Corrective Rape: Carmichele and Developing South Africa's Affirmative Obligations To Prevent Violence Against Women | journal = Georgetown Law Journal | volume = 99 | pages = 1469–515 |ssrn=1709629}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Gonda"&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Gonda
| first = W
| url = http://www.swradioafrica.com/news080410/corrective-rape080410.htm
| title = 'Corrective Rape' against Homosexuals on the Rise in Zimbabwe
| publisher = [[SW Radio Africa]]
| date = 8 April 2010
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Actionaid"&gt;{{cite web
| last = Martin
| first = A
| author2 = Kelly A
| author3 = Turquet L
| author4 = Ross S
| url = http://www.actionaid.org.uk/doc_lib/correctiveraperep_final.pdf
| title = Hate crimes: The rise of 'corrective rape' in South Africa
| publisher = [[ActionAid]]
| year = 2009
| pages = 1–20
| access-date = 2012-04-16
| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20120508194540/http://www.actionaid.org.uk/doc_lib/correctiveraperep_final.pdf
| archive-date = 8 May 2012
| url-status = dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Janoff"&gt;
Janoff, Douglas. ''Pink Blood: Homophobic Violence in Canada.'' Toronto: University of Toronto, 2005. {{ISBN|0802085709}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Mieses"&gt;
{{Cite journal
 |title=Gender Inequality and Corrective Rape of Women Who Have Sex with Women
 |journal=GMHC Treatment Issues
 |date=December 2009
 |publisher=[[Gay Men's Health Crisis]]
 |last=Mieses
 |first=Alexa
 |url=http://www.gmhc.org/files/editor/file/ti-1209.pdf
 |access-date=20 February 2014
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Caselli"&gt;{{cite news
| last = Caselli
| first = I
| url = http://www.alaskadispatch.com/article/corrective-rape-torture-among-methods-used-cure-homosexuality-ecuador
| title = 'Corrective Rape,' Torture among Methods Used to 'cure' Homosexuality in Ecuador
| work = [[Alaska Dispatch]]
| date = 10 February 2012
| access-date = 2012-04-18
| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20120621111733/http://www.alaskadispatch.com/article/corrective-rape-torture-among-methods-used-cure-homosexuality-ecuador
| archive-date = 21 June 2012
| url-status = dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="HRW"&gt;
[http://www.asylumlaw.org/docs/sexualminorities/SoutAfrica021109.pdf "Stop the Violence&amp;nbsp;– Live Updates from South Africa."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130704115629/http://www.asylumlaw.org/docs/sexualminorities/SoutAfrica021109.pdf |date=4 July 2013 }} ''Human Rights Watch''. 11 February 2009.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Shaw"&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Shaw
| first = Angus
| date = 7 April 2010
| work = [[Salon (website)|Salon]]
| url = https://www.salon.com/2010/04/07/af_zimbabwe_gay_rights_1/
| title = US Reports Harassment and Rape of Gays in Zimbabwe
| access-date = 2012-04-18
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="UN"&gt;
{{cite web
| title = Cultural Practices in the family that are violent towards women
| publisher = [[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]]
| url = http://www.refworld.org/docid/3d6ce3cc0.html
| date = 31 January 2002
| access-date = 2012-04-18
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Middleton"&gt;
 Middleton, Lee. [https://web.archive.org/web/20110310154024/http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2057744,00.html "'Corrective Rape': Fighting a South African Scourge."] ''Time.'' Time, 8 March 2011.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="CNN"&gt;
Mabuse, Nkepile. [http://edition.cnn.com/video/?/video/international/2011/11/07/worlds-untold-stories-corrective-rape-c.cnn "'Corrective Rape' Motivated by Hate."] ''World's Untold Stories.'' CNN. London, 7 November 2011.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Mabuse"&gt;
Mabuse, Nkepile. [http://edition.cnn.com/2011/10/27/world/wus-sa-rapes/ "Horror of South Africa's 'corrective Rape.'"] ''CNN''. Cable News Network, 28 October 2011.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Contemporary Sexuality"&gt;{{cite journal | year = 2011 | title = South African lesbians at risk for 'corrective rape | journal = Contemporary Sexuality | volume = 45 | issue = 7| page = 8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Kelly"&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Kelly
| first = Annie
| url = https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/mar/12/eudy-simelane-corrective-rape-south-africa
| title = Raped and Killed for Being a Lesbian: South Africa Ignores 'corrective' Attacks
| work = [[The Guardian]]
| date = 12 March 2009
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- I have hidden this ref as I can not associate it to the correct part of the prose &lt;ref name="USSAfrica2012"&gt;
 {{Cite web
 |title=2012 Human Rights Reports: South Africa
 |url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/j/drl/rls/hrrpt/2012/af/204168.htm
 |publisher=U.S. Department of State
 |date=19 April 2013
 |access-date=20 February 2014
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; End of hide --&gt;

&lt;ref name="USZimbabwe2012"&gt;
 {{Cite web
 |title=2012 Human Rights Reports: Zimbabwe
 |url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/j/drl/rls/hrrpt/2012/af/204183.htm
 |publisher=U.S. Department of State
 |date=19 April 2013
 |access-date=20 February 2014
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="USZimbabwe2009"&gt;
 {{Cite web
 |title=2009 Human Rights Report: Zimbabwe
 |url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/j/drl/rls/hrrpt/2009/af/135984.htm
 |publisher=U.S. Department of State
 |date=19 April 2013
 |access-date=20 February 2014
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="GuarUganda"&gt;
 {{cite news
 |last=Smith
 |first=David
 |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/may/18/gay-african-refugees-violence-kenya-uganda
 |title=Gay African refugees face abduction, violence and rape in Uganda and Kenya
 |newspaper=The Guardian
 |date=18 May 2012 
 |access-date=20 February 2014
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==Further reading==
{{cite news|last1=Strudwick|first1=Patrick|title=Crisis in South Africa: The shocking practice of 'corrective rape' – aimed at 'curing' lesbians|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/africa/crisis-in-south-africa-the-shocking-practice-of-corrective-rape--aimed-at-curing-lesbians-9033224.html|access-date=23 July 2014|work=The Independent|date=4 January 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140701182154/http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/africa/crisis-in-south-africa-the-shocking-practice-of-corrective-rape--aimed-at-curing-lesbians-9033224.html|archive-date=1 July 2014|url-status=live}}

== External links ==
* [https://archive.today/20121224225931/http://triangle.org.za/home The Triangle Project]

{{LGBT in South Africa}}
{{Law enforcement in South Africa}}
{{Politics of South Africa navbox}}
{{Political history of South Africa}}
{{Lesbian feminism}}
{{Abuse}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Corrective Rape}}
[[Category:Corrective rape| ]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation change efforts]]
[[Category:Euphemisms]]
[[Category:Violence against women in South Africa]]
[[Category:Violence against LGBT people]]
[[Category:Lesbianism]]
[[Category:Lesbophobic violence]]
[[Category:LGBT rights in South Africa]]
[[Category:Rape]]
[[Category:Rape in South Africa]]
[[Category:Violence against women]]
[[Category:Sexual misconduct]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>