<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131109060804|580856634" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21950359" pageid="21950359" ns="0" title="Corrective rape"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-12T23:29:52Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2013}}
'''Corrective rape''' is a [[hate crime]] in which a person is [[rape]]d because of their perceived [[sexual orientation]] or [[gender identity]].  The common intended consequence of the rape, as seen by the perpetrator, is to "correct" their orientation, to turn them [[heterosexuality|heterosexual]], or to make them "act" more in conformity with [[gender stereotypes]].&lt;ref name="Bartle" /&gt;  The term was coined in South Africa after well-known cases of corrective rapes of lesbians like [[Eudy Simelane]] and Zoliswa Nkonyana became public.  There are many health ramifications associated with corrective rape, and although some countries have laws protecting [[LGBT]] people, corrective rape is often overlooked.&lt;ref name="Hawthorne" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;

== Definition ==
Corrective rape is the use of rape against people who do not conform to perceived [[Norm (social)|social norms]] regarding [[human sexuality]] and [[gender role]]s, often [[lesbian]]s are raped by [[heterosexual]] men and [[gay]] men are raped by women,&lt;ref name="Gonda" /&gt; with a goal of punishment of "abnormal" behavior and reinforcement of societal norms.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt;  The crime was first identified in South Africa&lt;ref name="Janoff" /&gt; where it is sometimes supervised by members of the woman's family or local community,&lt;ref name="Bartle" /&gt; and is a major contributor to [[HIV]] infection in South African [[lesbians]].&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt;  Corrective rape has also been known to occur in Thailand, Ecuador, and Zimbabwe.&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Caselli" /&gt;  Corrective rape and the accompanying violence can result in [[physical trauma|physical]] and [[psychological trauma]], mutilation, HIV infection, unwanted [[pregnancy]],  and may contribute to [[suicide]].&lt;ref name="Hawthorne" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt;

== Causes ==
A 2000 study suggested the visibility of lesbians within a community, an atmosphere supportive of [[hate crime]]s against homosexuals, isolated locations, reactions to hate crimes by the broader community, and responses by police and justice systems contribute to corrective rape.&lt;ref name="Bartle" /&gt;  Failure to conform to social norms for gendered behaviour is also thought to contribute.&lt;ref name="HRW" /&gt; Many believe that it should be recognized as a hate crime because of the misunderstanding of homosexuality and the animus toward gay people that motivate corrective rape.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;  In one article, Tina Machida, a Zimbabwean lesbian who lives in [[Harare]], writes, "They locked me in a room and brought [a man] every day to rape me so I would fall pregnant and be forced to marry him. They did this to me until I was pregnant."&lt;ref name="Hawthorne" /&gt;

Corrective rape is not limited to people under the traditional LGBT umbrella. [[Asexuality|Asexual]] activist and blogger Julie Decker has observed that corrective rape is common in the asexual community. In an interview, she recounted being sexually harassed and assaulted by a man who claimed to have her interests at heart.&lt;ref name="huff"&gt;{{cite web|title=Battling Asexual Discrimination, Sexual Violence, and Corrective Rape|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/06/20/asexual-discrimination_n_3380551.html|publisher=[[Huffington Post]]|date=June 20, 2013|last=Mosbergen|first=Dominique|accessdate=August 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prevalence ==
Corrective rape has been reported in [[Thailand]],&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt; [[Zimbabwe]],&lt;ref name="Shaw" /&gt;&lt;ref name="UN" /&gt; [[Ecuador]]&lt;ref name="Caselli" /&gt; and South Africa.&lt;ref name="Middleton" /&gt;

=== South Africa ===
Currently in South Africa, women have less sexual and economic power than men{{citation needed|date=January 2013}}.  One of the factors associated with this inequality is strict [[gender roles]], which has led to one of the highest rates of [[violence against women]] in the world.&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt;&lt;ref name="HRW" /&gt;  Corrective rape is used as a "punishment" for people who are gay or do not fit traditional gender roles (usually women), where often they are [[verbally abused]] before the rape by the perpetrator saying things, such as that they will be “teaching [the women] a lesson” on how to be a “real woman.”  Because women have less control over their [[economics]], which creates economic vulnerability, they have less control over their own sexual activities.&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt;  Poor black women who live in townships are more likely to become victims of corrective violence, and gay women are more likely to be isolated with little support, which increases their chances of being targeted.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;

Corrective rape is not recognized by the South African legal system as a [[hate crime]] despite the fact that the [[South African Constitution]] states that no person shall be discriminated against based on their [[social status]] and identity, including [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt;&lt;ref name="CNN" /&gt;  Legally, South Africa protects gay rights extensively, but the government does not do anything to prevent corrective rape, and women do not have much faith in the police and their investigations.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Mabuse" /&gt;  Crimes based on sexual orientation are not expressly recognized in South Africa; corrective rape reports are not separated from general rape reports.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;  In December 2009, there had been 31 recorded murders of lesbians in South Africa since 1998, but only one had resulted in a conviction.&lt;ref name="Mieses" /&gt;  In the last twenty years, attitudes toward [[homosexuality]] have become worse in South Africa.&lt;ref name="Hazelton" /&gt;

Corrective rape is on the rise in South Africa. More than 10 lesbians are raped or gang-raped weekly, as estimated by Luleki Sizwe, a South African nonprofit.&lt;ref name="Contemporary Sexuality" /&gt;  It is estimated that at least 500 lesbians become victims of corrective rape every year and that 86% of black lesbians in the [[Western Cape]] live in fear of being [[sexually assaulted]], as reported by the Triangle Project in 2008.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;  Yet, victims of corrective rape are less likely to report it because of the negative social view of [[homosexuality]].&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;  Under-reporting is high for sexually violent crimes, thus the number of corrective rapes are likely higher than what is reported.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt;

One South African man stated, “Lesbians get raped and killed because it is accepted by our community and by our culture.”&lt;ref name="Middleton" /&gt;

In 2013, two writers from South African men's magazine [[FHM]] were fired as a result of corrective rape "jokes" they made on Facebook. After a disciplinary hearing on Friday July 19 2013, FHM dismissed both men from their positions, calling their comments "entirely unacceptable". &lt;ref&gt;http://mg.co.za/article/2013-07-19-fhm-fires-rape-comment-writers&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legal and public policy ==

=== South Africa ===
South Africa is uniquely able to "correct" corrective rape.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt; The 1996 Constitution enshrines myriad rights on the basis of which a group may challenge the circumstances that give rise to corrective rape; the constitutional doctrine makes available several possibilities for bringing suit; and South Africa manifests an openness to international and comparative law that makes it possible to incorporate human rights approaches to preventing private rights abuses.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt; Traditionally, in South Africa and elsewhere, the legal system has allowed the public-private divide to dictate a lower level of involvement in issues of [[domestic violence]] and [[sexual assault]], including corrective rape.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt; However, "modern human rights law has largely ignored this private-public distinction."&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt; For instance, the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women (CEDAW), which obligates states to remove discriminatory barriers from the full and free exercise of rights by women, reaches any actor. The Convention's duty to modify the conduct of private citizens to ensure equality for women covers attitudes that include the inferiority of women and stereotyped gender roles, which arguably encompass the animus toward gay women that motivates many men to commit corrective rape.&lt;ref name="Di" /&gt; However, 66% of women said they did not report their attack because they would not be taken seriously.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt; Of these, 25% said they feared exposing their sexual orientation to the police and 22% said they were afraid of being abused by the police.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt;

South Africa is in the process of translating the promises of [[democracy]] into reality and in this process it is confronting a major challenge in the form of gender-based violence.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt;

== Eudy Simelane ==
{{main|Eudy Simelane}}
On 28 April 2008, 31-year-old female soccer player Eudy Simelane was abducted, gang-raped and killed in [[KwaThema]], her hometown near Johannesburg.&lt;ref name="HRW" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Kelly" /&gt;  Simelane was a star of the South Africa’s acclaimed [[Banyana Banyana]] national female football squad, an avid equality rights campaigner and one of the first women to live openly as a lesbian in KwaThema.&lt;ref name="Kelly" /&gt;

==Campaigning==
Child sponsorship charity [[ActionAid]] has published an article discussing corrective rape, and see ending violence against women as a pivotal part of their mission that would also address the issue.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt; The group joined with 26 gay and women’s rights and community groups, to organize a campaign focused on South Africa but also aimed at the international community, to raise awareness of the issues.  The campaign was dedicated to the rape and murder of two lesbian women in a Johannesburg township and called for sexual orientation to be specifically recognised as grounds for protection by police and justice systems.&lt;ref name="Actionaid" /&gt;

== See also ==
{{multicol}}
* [[Causes of sexual violence]]
* [[Discrimination]]
* [[Factors associated with being a victim of sexual violence]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Lesbophobia]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[LGBT rights in South Africa]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Rape culture]]
* [[Rape statistics]]
* [[Sexual violence in South Africa]]
* [[Types of rape]]
* [[Violence against LGBT people]]
{{multicol-end}}

== References ==
{{reflist
| colwidth = 30em
| refs =

&lt;ref name="Bartle"&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Bartle
| first = EE
| title = Lesbians And Hate Crimes
| journal = Journal of Poverty
| volume = 4
| issue = 4
| year = 2000
| format = pdf
| id = {{citeseerx|10.1.1.196.9177}}
| pages= 23–44
| doi = 10.1300/J134v04n04_02
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Hawthorne"&gt;
Hawthorne, Susan. "Ancient Hatred And Its Contemporary Manifestation: The Torture Of Lesbians." ''Journal Of Hate Studies'' 4.1 (2005): 33–58. Academic Search Complete.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Di"&gt;
Di Silvio, Lorenzo. "Correcting Corrective Rape: Carmichele and Developing South Africa’s Affirmative Obligations To Prevent Violence Against Women." ''Georgetown Law Journal'' 99 (2011): 1469–515.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Gonda"&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Gonda
| first = W
| url = http://www.swradioafrica.com/news080410/corrective-rape080410.htm
| title = ‘Corrective Rape’ against Homosexuals on the Rise in Zimbabwe
| publisher = [[SW Radio Africa]]
| date = 8 April 2010
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Actionaid"&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Martin
| first = A
| coauthors = Kelly A; Turquet L; Ross S
| url = http://www.actionaid.org.uk/doc_lib/correctiveraperep_final.pdf
| title = Hate crimes: The rise of 'corrective rape' in South Africa
| format = pdf
| publisher = [[ActionAid]]
| year = 2009
| pages = 1–20
| accessdate = 2012-04-16
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Janoff"&gt;
Janoff, Douglas. ''Pink Blood: Homophobic Violence in Canada.'' Toronto: University of Toronto, 2005.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Mieses"&gt;
Mieses, Alexa. "Gender Inequality and Corrective Rape of Women Who Have Sex with Women." ''GMHC Treatment Issues'' (2009): 1–3.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Caselli"&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Caselli
| first = I
| url = http://www.alaskadispatch.com/article/corrective-rape-torture-among-methods-used-cure-homosexuality-ecuador
| title = 'Corrective Rape,' Torture among Methods Used to 'cure' Homosexuality in Ecuador
| work = [[Alaska Dispatch]]
| date = 10 February 2012
| accessdate = 2012-04-18
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="HRW"&gt;
[http://www.asylumlaw.org/docs/sexualminorities/SoutAfrica021109.pdf "Stop the Violence&amp;nbsp;– Live Updates from South Africa."] ''Human Rights Watch.'' 11 Feb. 2009.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Shaw"&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Shaw
| first = A
| date = 7 April 2010
| work = [[Salon (website)|Salon]]
| url = http://www.salon.com/2010/04/07/af_zimbabwe_gay_rights_1/singleton
| title = US Reports Harassment and Rape of Gays in Zimbabwe
| accessdate = 2012-04-18
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="UN"&gt;
{{cite web
| title = Cultural Practices in the family that are violent towards women
| publisher = [[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]]
| url = http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/e06a5300f90fa0238025668700518ca4/42e7191fae543562c1256ba7004e963c/$FILE/G0210428.pdf
| format = pdf
| date = 31 January 2002
| accessdate = 2012-04-18
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Middleton"&gt;
 Middleton, Lee. [http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2057744,00.html "'Corrective Rape': Fighting a South African Scourge."] ''Time.'' Time, 8 Mar. 2011.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="CNN"&gt;
Mabuse, Nkepile. [http://edition.cnn.com/video/?/video/international/2011/11/07/worlds-untold-stories-corrective-rape-c.cnn "'Corrective Rape' Motivated by Hate."] ''World's Untold Stories.'' CNN. London, 7 Nov. 2011.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Mabuse"&gt;
Mabuse, Nkepile. [http://edition.cnn.com/2011/10/27/world/wus-sa-rapes/ "Horror of South Africa's 'corrective Rape.'"] ''CNN''. Cable News Network, 28 Oct. 2011.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Hazelton"&gt;
Hazelton, Liz. [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2055289/Corrective-rape-South-Africa-women-attcked-cure-lesbians.html "Raped for Being Gay: Scourge of South African Sex Attacks Which Men Claim Will 'cure' Women of Being Lesbians."] ''Mail Online.'' Daily Mail, 31 Oct. 2011.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Contemporary Sexuality"&gt;
“South African lesbians at risk for ‘corrective rape.” ''Contemporary Sexuality.'' 45.7 (2011): 8.
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Kelly"&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Kelly
| first = A
| url = http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/mar/12/eudy-simelane-corrective-rape-south-africa
| title = Raped and Killed for Being a Lesbian: South Africa Ignores 'corrective' Attacks
| work = [[The Guardian]]
| date = 12 March 2009
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

== External links ==
* [http://triangle.org.za/home The Triangle Project]
* [http://www.change.org/groups/luleki_sizwe Luleki Sizwe]

{{Law enforcement in South Africa}}
{{Politics of South Africa navbox |state=expanded}}
{{Political history of South Africa}}
{{abuse}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Corrective Rape}}
[[Category:Sexual orientation change efforts]]
[[Category:Euphemisms]]
[[Category:Violence against women]]
[[Category:Violence against women in South Africa]]
[[Category:Homophobic violence]]
[[Category:Lesbianism]]
[[Category:LGBT rights in South Africa]]
[[Category:Rape]]
[[Category:Rape in South Africa]]
[[Category:Misogyny]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>