<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221122180252|1123229009" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="148979" pageid="148979" ns="0" title="Queer theory"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-27T23:47:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Field of critical theory}}
{{LGBT sidebar}}
'''Queer theory''' is a field of [[critical theory]] {{citation needed|date=October 2022}} that emerged in the early 1990s out of [[queer studies]] (often, formerly, gay and lesbian studies) and [[women's studies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Chandler |first1=Daniel |last2=Munday |first2=Rod |title=A Dictionary of Media and Communication |date=1 January 2011 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-956875-8 |url=https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780199568758.001.0001/acref-9780199568758-e-2220 |chapter=queer theory }}&lt;/ref&gt; The term can have various meanings depending upon its usage, but has broadly been associated with the study and theorisation of gender and sexual practices that exist outside of [[heterosexuality]], and which challenge [[Heteronormativity|the notion that heterosexual desire is ‘normal’]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Warner |first1=Michael |title=Fear of a queer planet: queer politics and social theory |date=2011 |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |isbn=978-0-8166-2334-1 |oclc=934391034 }}{{page needed|date=July 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following [[Social constructivism|social constructivist]] developments in [[sociology]], queer theorists are often critical of what they consider [[Essentialism|essentialist]] views of [[Human sexuality|sexuality]] and [[gender]]. Instead, they study those concepts as social and cultural phenomena, often through an analysis of the categories, binaries, and language in which they are said to be portrayed.

==History==
{{main|Epistemology of the Closet}}
Informal use of the term "queer theory" began with [[Gloria Anzaldúa]] and other scholars in the 1990s, themselves influenced by the work of French [[post-structuralist]] philosopher [[Michel Foucault]],&lt;ref name="SAGE"/&gt; who viewed sexuality as [[Social constructionism|socially constructed]] and rejected [[identity politics]].&lt;ref name="Downing, Lisa 2008"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Downing |first1=Lisa |title=The Cambridge Introduction to Michel Foucault |date=2008 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-521-86443-5 |pages=104–117 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Teresa de Lauretis]] organized the first queer theory conference in 1990. David Halperin, an early queer theorist, writes in his article "The Normalization of Queer Theory" that de Lauretis' usage was somewhat controversial at first, as she chose to combine the word "queer" which was just starting to be used in a "gay-affirmative sense by activists, street kids, and members of the art world," and the word "theory" which was seen as very academically weighty.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Halperin |first=David M. |date=2003-09-23 |title=The Normalization of Queer Theory |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1300/J082v45n02_17 |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |language=en |volume=45 |issue=2–4 |pages=339–343 |doi=10.1300/J082v45n02_17 |pmid=14651188 |s2cid=37469852 |issn=0091-8369}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the early 1990s, the term started to become legitimized in academia.&lt;ref name="SAGE"&gt;Goldberg, Abbie E. (ed.) (2016). ''The SAGE encyclopedia of LGBTQ studies''. SAGE publications. page 915.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although it is an academic discipline that gained traction within academia, queer theory's roots can also be traced back to activism, with the reclaiming of the derogatory term "queer" as an umbrella term for those who do not identify with heteronormativity in the 1980s.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; This would continue on in the 1990s, with [[Queer Nation]]'s use of "queer" in their protest chants, such as "We're here! We're queer! Get used to it!"&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Queer Nation NY History |url=https://queernationny.org/history |access-date=2022-11-16 |website=Queer Nation NY |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Other early queer theorists include [[Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick]], [[Michael Warner]], [[Lauren Berlant]], [[Judith Butler]], and [[Adrienne Rich]].&lt;ref name="SAGE" /&gt;{{Page needed|date=December 2021}}

==Definition==
According to Jay Stewart, "Queer theory and politics necessarily celebrate transgression in the form of visible difference from norms. These 'Norms' are then exposed to be norms, not natures or inevitabilities. Gender and sexual identities are seen, in much of this work, to be demonstrably defiant definitions and configurations."&lt;ref name="BergmanBarker"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Stewart |first1=Jay |editor1-last=Richards |editor1-first=Christina |editor2-last=Bouman |editor2-first=Walter Pierre |editor3-last=Barker |editor3-first=Meg-John |title=Genderqueer and Non-Binary Genders |date=2017 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |isbn=978-1-137-51052-5 |page=62 |url=https://transreads.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/2019-03-17_5c8df4095641a_christina-richards-genderqueer-and-nonbinary-genders-11.pdf |chapter=Academic Theory |series=Critical and Applied Approaches in Sexuality, Gender and Identity |access-date=8 April 2021 |archive-date=26 September 2020 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200926010649/https://transreads.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/2019-03-17_5c8df4095641a_christina-richards-genderqueer-and-nonbinary-genders-11.pdf |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an influential essay, [[Michael Warner]] argued that [[queer]]ness is defined by what he called ‘heteronormativity'; those ideas, [[narrative]]s and [[discourse]]s which suggest that heterosexuality is the default, preferred, or normal mode of sexual orientation. Warner stated that while many thinkers had been theorising sexuality from a non-heterosexual perspective for perhaps a century, queerness represented a distinctive contribution to social theory for precisely this reason. [[Lauren Berlant]] and Warner further developed these ideas in their seminal essay, "Sex in Public".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Berlant |first1=Lauren |last2=Warner |first2=Michael |title=Sex in Public |journal=Critical Inquiry |date=1998 |volume=24 |issue=2 |pages=547–566 |doi=10.1086/448884 |jstor=1344178 |s2cid=161701244 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics such as [[Edward Carpenter]], [[Guy Hocquenghem]] and [[Jeffrey Weeks (sociologist)|Jeffrey Weeks]] had emphasised what they called the ‘necessity of thinking about sexuality as a field of power, as a historical mode of personality, and as the site of an often critical utopian aim’.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Warner |first1=Michael |title=Fear of a queer planet: queer politics and social theory |date=1993 |isbn=978-0-8166-2334-1 |oclc=28634756 }}{{page needed|date=July 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whereas the terms 'homosexual', ‘gay’ or ‘lesbian’ which they used signified particular identities with stable referents (i.e to a certain cultural form, historical context, or political agenda whose meanings can be analysed sociologically), the word ‘queer’ is instead defined in relation to a range of practices, behaviours and issues that have meaning only in their shared contrast to categories which are alleged to be 'normal'. Such a focus highlights the indebtedness of queer theory to the concept of [[Normalization (sociology)|normalisation]] found in the [[Deviance (sociology)|sociology of deviance]], particularly through the work of Michel Foucault, who studied the normalisation of heterosexuality in his work ''[[The History of Sexuality]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Epstein |first1=Steven |title=A Queer Encounter: Sociology and the Study of Sexuality |journal=Sociological Theory |date=1994 |volume=12 |issue=2 |pages=188–202 |doi=10.2307/201864 |jstor=201864 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Foucault |first1=Michel |last3=Foucault |first3=Michel |last4=Foucault |first4=Michel |last5=Foucault |first5=Michel |last6=Hurley |first6=Robert |last7=Gros |first7=Frédéric |title=The history of sexuality |date=1978 |isbn=978-0-394-41775-2 |oclc=4004090 }}{{Page needed|date=December 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In''[[The History of Sexuality]]'', Foucault argues that repressive structures in society police the discourse concerning sex and sexuality and are thus relegated in the private sphere.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; As a result, heterosexuality is normalized while homosexuality (or queerness) is stigmatized. Foucault then points out that this imposed secrecy has led to sexuality as a phenomenon that needs to be frequently confessed and examined.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Foucault's work is particularly important to queer theory in that he describes sexuality as a phenomenon that "must not be thought of as a kind of natural given which power tries to hold in check" but rather "a historical construct."&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Judith Butler extends this idea of sexuality as a social construct to gender identity in ''[[Gender Trouble|Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity]]'', where she theorizes that gender is not a biological reality but rather something that is performed through repeated actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author=Butler, Judith |url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/50506678 |title=Gender trouble : feminism and the subversion of identity |date=1999 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=0-203-90275-0 |oclc=50506678}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because this definition of queerness does not have a fixed reference point, Judith Butler has described the subject of queer theory as a site of ‘collective contestation’. They suggest that ‘queer’ as a term should never be ‘fully owned, but always and only redeployed, twisted, queered from a prior usage and in the direction of urgent and expanding political purposes’.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |doi=10.4324/9780203760505-3 |chapter=Critically Queer |title=Playing with Fire: Queer Politics, Queer Theories |year=2020 |last1=Butler |first1=Judith |pages=11–29 |isbn=978-0-203-76050-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; While proponents argue that this flexibility allows for the constant readjustment of queer theory to accommodate the experiences of people who face marginalisation and discrimination on account of their sexuality and gender,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Eng |first1=David L |last2=Halberstam |first2=Jack |last3=Muñoz |first3=José Esteban |title=What's queer about queer studies now? |date=2005 |publisher=Duke University Press |isbn=978-0-8223-6621-8 |oclc=835806226 }}&lt;/ref&gt; critics allege that such a 'subjectless critique', as it is often called,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Green |first1=Adam Isaiah |title=Queer Theory and Sociology: Locating the Subject and the Self in Sexuality Studies |journal=Sociological Theory |date=March 2007 |volume=25 |issue=1 |pages=26–45 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-9558.2007.00296.x |s2cid=144197617 }}&lt;/ref&gt; runs the risk of abstracting cultural forms from their social structure, political organization, and historical context, reducing social theory to a mere 'textual idealism'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |doi=10.1017/cbo9780511557910.008 |chapter=Identity and politics in a 'postmodern' gay culture |title=Difference Troubles |year=1997 |pages=109–138 |isbn=978-0-521-59043-3 |first1=Steven |last1=Seidman }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Analysis of same-sex partnerships==
Queer theory deals with the micro level - the identity of the individual person, the meso level - the individual in their immediate groups such as family, friends, and work, and the macro level - the larger context of society, culture, politics, policies and law. Accordingly, queer theory not only examines the communities surrounding the queer people, but also the communities they form. Same-sex living communities have a significant priority in the formation of a queer theory. The standard work of Andreas Frank, "Committed Sensations",&lt;ref name="Frank"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Frank |first1=Andreas |title=Committed Sensations - An Initiation to Homosexuality: The gay &amp; lesbian Handbook &amp; Compendium on Coming-Out &amp; same-sex Partnerships |date=2020 |publisher=BoD – Books on Demand |isbn=978-3-7519-0786-6 }}{{page needed|date=July 2022}}{{self-published inline|date=July 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; highlights comprehensively the life situation of coming-out, homosexuality and same-sex communities to the millennium.

== Queer theory and communication studies ==
As an interdisciplinary concept, queer theory is applied to different disciplines, including [[communication studies]] and research. It was introduced to the field of communication through Jeffrey Ringer's ''Queer Words, Queer Images: Communication and the Construction of Homosexuality'' in 1994, which offered a queer perspective to communication research findings.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=editor. |first=Ringer, R. Jeffrey |url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/28926454 |title=Queer words, queer images : communication and the construction of homosexuality |year=1994 |isbn=0-8147-7440-7 |oclc=28926454}}&lt;/ref&gt; Queer theory has also contributed to communication research by challenging the heternormative society's notions of what's considered deviant and taboo—what is considered normative and non-normative.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Manning |first1=Jimmie |last2=Asante |first2=Godfried |last3=Huerta Moreno |first3=Lydia |last4=Johnson |first4=Rebecca |last5=LeMaster |first5=Benny |last6=Li |first6=Yachao |last7=Rudnick |first7=Justin J. |last8=Stern |first8=Danielle M. |last9=Young |first9=Stephanie |date=2020-07-03 |title=Queering communication studies: a Journal of Applied Communication Research forum |url=https://doi.org/10.1080/00909882.2020.1789197 |journal=Journal of Applied Communication Research |volume=48 |issue=4 |pages=413–437 |doi=10.1080/00909882.2020.1789197 |s2cid=225438449 |issn=0090-9882}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Queering family communication==
Queer theory's [[interdisciplinarity]] is evident in its application in and critique of family communication. One of the criticisms regarding family communication is its focus on "mainstream" families, often focusing on heterosexual parents and children.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book |last=author. |first=Littlejohn, Stephen W. |url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/1259328675 |title=Theories of human communication |date=May 2021 |isbn=978-1-4786-4667-9 |oclc=1259328675}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although more studies on family communication have started to include nontraditional families, critical rhetorical scholar Roberta Chevrette&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Dr. Roberta Chevrette {{!}} Faculty {{!}} Middle Tennessee State University |url=https://www.mtsu.edu/faculty/roberta-chevrette/intexpert |access-date=2022-10-15 |website=www.mtsu.edu |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; argues that researchers continue to look at nontraditional families, including families with openly queer members, from a heteronormative lens.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Chevrette |first=Roberta |date=2013-03-19 |title=Outing Heteronormativity in Interpersonal and Family Communication: Feminist Applications of Queer Theory "Beyond the Sexy Streets" |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/comt.12009 |journal=Communication Theory |volume=23 |issue=2 |pages=170–190 |doi=10.1111/comt.12009 |issn=1050-3293}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; That is, when studying LGBTQ+ families, many scholars continue to compare these families to their [[Cisgender|cis]]-heterosexual counterparts' norms. As Chevrette writes, "Queering family communication requires challenging ideas frequently taken for granted and thinking about sexual identities as more than check marks."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Chevrette describes four ways that scholars can "queer" family communication: (1) revealing the biases and heteronormative assumptions in family communication; (2) challenging the treatment of sexuality and queerness as a personal and sensitive topic reserved for the private sphere rather than the public; (3) interpreting identity as a socially constructed phenomenon and sexuality as being fluid in order to expose the ways gender roles and stereotypes are reinforced by notions of identity and sexuality as being fixed; and (4) emphasizing [[intersectionality]] and the importance of studying different identity markers in connection with each other.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==Lens for power==
Queer theory is the lens used to explore and challenge how scholars, activists, artistic texts, and the media perpetrate gender- and sex-based binaries, and its goal is to undo hierarchies and fight against social inequalities.&lt;ref name="Barber"&gt;Barber, Kristen; Hidalgo, Danielle Antoinette (2017). [https://www.britannica.com/topic/queer-sexual-politics. "Queer"]. ''[[Encyclopedia Britannica]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to controversy about the definition of ''[[queer]]'', including whether the word should even be defined at all or should be left deliberately open-ended, there are many disagreements and often contradictions within queer theory.&lt;ref name="Barber" /&gt; In fact, some queer theorists, like Berlant and Warner&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Berlant |first1=Lauren |last2=Warner |first2=Michael |title=Guest Column: What Does Queer Theory Teach Us about X ? |journal=Publications of the Modern Language Association of America |date=May 1995 |volume=110 |issue=3 |pages=343–349 |doi=10.1632/S003081290005937X |s2cid=155177456 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and Butler, have warned that defining it or conceptualizing it as an academic field might only lead to its inevitable misinterpretation or destruction, since its entire purpose is to critique academia rather than become a formal academic domain itself.&lt;ref name="Jagose"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Jagose |first1=Annamarie |title=Queer Theory: An Introduction |date=1996 |publisher=NYU Press |isbn=978-0-8147-4234-1 |page=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fundamentally, queer theory does not construct or defend any particular identity, but instead, grounded in [[post-structuralism]] and [[deconstruction]], it works to actively critique [[heteronormativity]], exposing and breaking down traditional assumptions that sexual and gender identities are presumed to be [[heterosexual]] or [[cisgender]].&lt;ref name="SAGE"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Jagose"/&gt;

==Queer theory in online discourse==
One of the ways queer theory has made its way into online discourse is through the popularity of [[Adrienne Rich]]'s 1980 essay, "[[Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence]]." Rich's theory regarding [[compulsory heterosexuality]] (or comp-het)—the socio-cultural expectation that women must be attracted to men and desire a romantic heterosexual relationship&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Rich |first=Adrienne |date=1980 |title=Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence |url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/3173834 |journal=Signs |volume=5 |issue=4 |pages=631–660 |doi=10.1086/493756 |jstor=3173834 |s2cid=143604951 |issn=0097-9740}}&lt;/ref&gt;—inspired the creation of the "Lesbian Masterdoc", a 30-page [[Google Document]] originally written in 2018 by Anjeli Luz, a [[Tumblr]] user who was in the midst of questioning her own sexuality as a teenager.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Cortés |first=Michelle Santiago |date=2022-06-24 |title=Can a PDF Really Tell You If You're Queer? |url=https://www.thecut.com/2022/06/what-is-the-lesbian-masterdoc.html |access-date=2022-10-15 |website=The Cut |language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Katelyn McKenna and John Bargh’s studies of online groups consisting of marginalized groups found an interesting phenomenon called “identity demarginalization” — how participation in a group consisting of people with shared marginalized identity can lead to a higher level of self-acceptance, which could lead to eventually coming out to their friends and family.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=McKenna |first1=Katelyn |last2=Bargh |first2=John |date=1998 |title=Coming Out in the Age of the Internet: Identity "Demarginalization" Through Virtual Group Participation |url=https://wrlc-gu.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/permalink/01WRLC_GUNIV/1hdki3o/cdi_apa_psycarticles_psp_75_3_681 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=75 |issue=3 |pages=681–694 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.75.3.681 |via=Ovid PsycARTICLES}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Online groups and interactions also contribute to normalizing queerness and challenging heteronormativity by serving as a networked counterpublic. Sarah Jackson, Moya Bailey, and Brooke Foucault Welles’ discourse analysis of the [[Hashtag activism|hashtag]] #GirlsLikeUs shows how trans women have used the hashtag to build community in ways that normalize being trans and offering counter-narratives to the often stereotypical and caricatured portrayal of trans people’s lives in popular mainstream media.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Jackson |first1=Sarah J |last2=Bailey |first2=Moya |last3=Foucault Welles |first3=Brooke |date=May 2018 |title=#GirlsLikeUs: Trans advocacy and community building online |url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1461444817709276 |journal=New Media &amp; Society |language=en |volume=20 |issue=5 |pages=1868–1888 |doi=10.1177/1461444817709276 |s2cid=21663014 |issn=1461-4448}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Queer archaeology]]
*[[Queer of color critique]]
*[[Queer theology]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{Commons category-inline}}

[[Category:Queer theory| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>