<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201114015641|988586408" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="148979" pageid="148979" ns="0" title="Queer theory"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-19T10:29:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Queer studies}}
{{short description|Various theories emphasizing the sociocultural environment in which human sexuality is constructed}}
{{multiple issues|
{{original research|date=July 2011}}
{{globalize|article|Western culture|date=December 2017}}
{{technical|date=May 2019}}
{{Cleanup rewrite|date=November 2020}}
}}
{{sociology}}
{{LGBT sidebar}}

[[File:Rainbow flag and blue skies.jpg|thumb|Rainbow flag flapping in the wind with blue skies and the sun.]]
'''Queer theory''' is a field of [[critical theory]] that emerged in the early 1990s out of the fields of [[queer studies]] and [[women's studies]]. "Queer theory" can have various meanings depending upon its usage. Two common usages of queer theory include a (1) methodology for literary analysis and (2) a productive practice of theory. A literary methodology could include [[queer]] readings of texts, that is, textual interpretations which are presented from a queer perspective. While the theorization of 'queerness' works to produce ideas which relate to how queerness can be understood in various disciplinary contexts. 

Heavily influenced by the work of [[Lauren Berlant]], [[Leo Bersani]], [[Judith Butler]], [[Lee Edelman]], [[Jack Halberstam]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Halberstam|first=Jack|title=An audio overview of queer theory in English and Turkish by Jack Halberstam|url=https://archive.org/details/HalberstamQueerTheory-AnkaraTurkey|accessdate=29 May 2014|date=2014-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick]], queer theory builds both upon [[feminist]] challenges to the idea that [[gender]] is part of the [[Essentialism|essential]] self and upon [[gay]]/[[lesbian]] studies' close examination of the [[socially constructed]] nature of [[sexual acts]] and [[Sexual identity|identities]]. Whereas gay/lesbian studies focused its inquiries into natural and unnatural behavior with respect to [[Homosexuality|homosexual]] behavior, queer theory expands its focus to encompass any kind of sexual activity or identity that falls into [[Normality (behavior)|normative]] and [[deviant]] categories. [[Italian feminist]] and [[film theorist]] [[Teresa de Lauretis]] coined the term ''queer theory'' for a conference she organized at the [[University of California, Santa Cruz]] in 1990 and a special issue of ''[[Differences (journal)|Differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies]]'' she edited based on that conference.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Halperin|first=David M.|date=May 1, 2003|title=The Normalization of Queer Theory|journal=Journal of Homosexuality|volume=45|issue=2–4|pages=339–343|via=Academic Search Ultimate|doi=10.1300/j082v45n02_17|pmid=14651188|s2cid=37469852}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Through the context of heterosexuality being the origin and foundation of society's [[Heteronormativity|heteronormative]] stability, the concept of queerness focuses on, "mismatches between sex, gender and desire"&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Queerness has been associated most prominently with [[bisexual]], lesbian and gay subjects, but its [[analytic framework]] also includes such topics as [[cross-dressing]], [[intersex]] bodies and identities, [[gender ambiguity]] and [[gender-confirmation surgery]]. Queer theory holds that individual [[Human sexuality|sexuality]] is a fluid, fragmented, and dynamic collectivity of possible sexualities and it may vary at different points during one's life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Critical Theory Today: A User-friendly Guide|url=https://archive.org/details/criticaltheoryto00tyso_624|url-access=limited|last=Tyson|first=Lois|publisher=Routledge|year=2006|isbn=978-0415974097|location=New York|pages=[https://archive.org/details/criticaltheoryto00tyso_624/page/n351 335]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its criticism of stable (and correlated) sexes, genders, and sexualities develops out of the specifically lesbian and gay reworking of the post-structuralist figuring of identity as a constellation of multiple and unstable positions.

Queer theory also examines the discourses of homosexuality developed in the last century in order to place the "queer" into historical context, [[deconstructing]] contemporary arguments both for and against this latest terminology.

==Overview==
{{more citations needed section|date=March 2015}}
Queer theory is derived largely from [[post-structuralist]] [[Literary theory|theory]], and [[deconstruction]] in particular.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Encyclopedia of Law and Society: American and Global Perspectives|last=Clark|first=David|publisher=SAGE Publications|year=2007|isbn=9780761923879|location=Thousand Oaks, CA|pages=1256}}&lt;/ref&gt; Queer theory would suggest that history be a process of recognition.&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Ashgate Research Companion to Contemporary Religion and Sexuality|last1=Hunt|first1=Stephen|last2=Yip|first2=Andrew|publisher=Routledge|year=2016|isbn=9781409409496|location=Oxon|pages=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{what|date=January 2020}}  Starting in the 1970s, a range of authors brought deconstructionist critical approaches to bear on issues of sexual identity, especially [[heteronormativity]] and non-heteronormative sexuality.

The theory was also influenced by Anglo-American cultures in the HIV/AIDS activism of the 1980s and contemporary feminism in the early 1990s.&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;

Queer theory's overarching goal is to act as a lens or tool to deconstruct the existing monolithic [[social norms]] and [[Taxonomy (general)|taxonomies]] and investigate how and why they came into being.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Sexual Deviance and Society: A sociological examination|last=Worthen|first=Meredith|publisher=Routledge|year=2016|isbn=9781138819061|location=Oxon|pages=94}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The view is that these notions and norms are rigid organizing categories that do not sufficiently explain different attitudes, behaviors, or conditions of individual experiences. Authors analyze the correlation between power distribution and identification across multiple facets of [[oppression]] and [[Social privilege|privilege]]. [[Feminist theory|Feminist]] and queer theory are seen as applicable concepts that provide a framework to explore these issues rather than as an identity to those in the [[community]].  Queer is an [[umbrella term]] for those not only deemed sexually deviant, but also those who feel [[Social exclusion|marginalized]] as a result of standard [[social practices]]. (Giffney, 2004).&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite journal|doi= 10.1177/1464700104040814|title= Denormatizing Queer Theory: More Than (Simply) Lesbian and Gay Studies|journal= Feminist Theory|volume= 5|pages= 73–78|year= 2004|last1= Giffney|first1= Noreen|s2cid= 144750482}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Annamarie Jagose]] wrote ''Queer Theory: An Introduction'' in 1996.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jagose|first1=Annamarie|title=Queer theory an introduction|date=1996|publisher=New York Univ. Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0814742341|edition=Reprint.|oclc=35651102}}&lt;/ref&gt; Queer was a commonly used abusive [[slang]] word for homosexuals and is still sometimes used for [[homophobic abuse]]. Recently, the term has been used as an umbrella term for a coalition of sexual identities that are culturally marginalized, and at other times, to create discourse surrounding the budding [[theoretical model]] that primarily arose through more traditional lesbian and gay studies. According to Jagose (1996), "Queer focuses on mismatches between sex, gender and desire. For most, queer has been prominently associated with those who identify as lesbian and gay. Unknown to many, queer is in association with more than just gay and lesbian, but also cross-dressing, [[hermaphroditism]], gender ambiguity and gender-corrective surgery."

"Queer is a product of specific [[cultural]] and theoretical pressures which increasingly structured debates (both within and outside the academy) about questions of lesbian and gay identity,"&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; but now, with the evolution of language, it is important to understand that the terms ‘gay’ and ‘lesbian’ are static, [[Eurocentric]] labels that fail to be universal when looking at a transnational scale. It is merely reductive to view queer theory as a byname for Gay and Lesbian studies when the two fields have stark differences.{{quote box|align=center|width=50%|quote=Queer is by definition whatever is at odds with the normal, the legitimate, the dominant. There is nothing in particular to which it necessarily refers. It is an identity without an essence. 'Queer' then, demarcates not a positivity but a positionality vis-à-vis the normative.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|title=Saint Foucault: Towards a Gay Hagiography
|last=Halperin
|first=David
|page=62
|isbn=978-0-19-511127-9
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=o9ct-YPs66UC&amp;q=queer%20odds
|date=1997-02-06
|accessdate=2010-05-10
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|postscript=&lt;!--none--&gt;
|author-link=David Halperin
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

Queer theorist [[Michael Warner]] attempts to provide a solid definition of a concept that typically circumvents categorical definitions: "Social reflection carried out in such a manner tends to be creative, fragmentary, and defensive, and leaves us perpetually at a disadvantage. And it is easy to be misled by the [[utopian]] claims advanced in support of particular tactics. But the range and seriousness of the problems that are continually raised by queer practice indicate how much work remains to be done. Because the logic of the sexual order is so deeply embedded by now in an indescribably wide range of social institutions, and is embedded in the most standard accounts of the world, queer struggles aim not just at toleration or equal status but at challenging those institutions and accounts. Similarly, queer theorist [[Cathy J. Cohen|Cathy Cohen]] highlights the limitations of a queer politics that attempts integration into "dominant institutions and normative social relationships" in order to centralize [[LGBTQ]] identity, and rather that it is necessary to affect the [[societal values]] and legislations that result in these oppressive institutions and relationships of power.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; The dawning realization that themes of [[homophobia]] and [[heterosexism]] may be read in almost any document of our culture means that we are only beginning to have an idea of how widespread those institutions and accounts are".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor-first=Michael|editor-last=Warner|title=Fear of a queer planet queer politics and social theory|date=1997|publisher=Univ. of Minnesota Press|location=Minneapolis|isbn=978-0816623341|edition=3. pr.|oclc=28634756}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[Rosemary Hennessy]] cites calls for "a critique of heterosexuality" in the 1970s from lesbian feminists including the activist [[Charlotte Bunch]] and the theorist [[Monique Wittig]] as precursors to queer theory. However, "queer" marks both a continuity and a break with the notion of gayness emerging from [[gay liberationist]] and [[lesbian feminist]] models, such as [[Adrienne Rich]]'s ''[[Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence]]''. "Gay" vs. "queer" fueled debates (both within and outside of academia) about LGBT identity. The independence of "queer" from "gay" came from the alignment of gay ideals with assimilationism and conservatism, while queer coincided with a radical approach. Assimilationists saw nothing wrong with society; queer radicalism aspires to achieve nothing in reference to the status quo because societal acceptance is not essential because society is unacceptable.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Kemp|first1=Jonathan|title=Queer Past, Queer Present, Queer Future|journal=Graduate Journal of Social Science|date=2009|volume=6|issue=1|url=http://gjss.org/sites/default/files/issues/chapters/papers/Journal-06-01--01-Kemp.pdf|accessdate=4 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Matos|first1=Angel Daniel|title=Gay Assimilationists versus Radical Queers: The Death of Queerness?|url=http://angelmatos.net/2013/04/06/gay-assimilationists-versus-radical-queers-the-death-of-queerness/|website=The Ever and Ever That Fiction Allows|accessdate=4 June 2015|date=2013-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There has been a long history of [[Critical thinking|critical]] and [[Queer anarchism|anarchistic]] thinking about sexual and gender relations across many cultures. [[Josiah Flynt]] became one of the first [[sociologists]] to study homosexuality. Most recently, in the late 1970s and 1980s, [[social constructionists]] conceived of the sexual subject as a culturally dependent, historically specific product.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Rubin|first1=Gayle S.|title=Deviations : a Gayle Rubin reader|date=2011|publisher=Duke University Press|location=Durham, NC|isbn=978-0-8223-4971-6|oclc=777134989}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before the phrase "queer theory" was born, the term "Queer Nation" appeared on the cover of the short-lived lesbian/gay quarterly [[Outlook (LGBT magazine)|''Outlook'']] in the winter 1991 issues. Writers Allan Berube and Jeffrey Escoffier drove home the point that Queer Nation strove to embrace paradoxes in its [[political activism]], and that the activism was taking new form and revolving around the issue of identity.&lt;ref name="A genealogy of queer theory"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Turner|first1=William B.|title=A genealogy of queer theory|date=2000|publisher=Temple Univ. Press|location=Philadelphia|isbn=978-1-56639-787-2|oclc=43562107}}&lt;/ref&gt; Soon enough ''Outlook'' and ''Queer Nation'' stopped being published, however, there was a mini-gay renaissance going on during the 1980s and early 1990s. There were a number of significant outbursts of lesbian/gay political/[[LGBT culture|cultural]] activity. Out of this emerged queer theory. Their work however did not arise out of the blue. [[Teresa de Lauretis]] is credited with coining the phrase "queer theory". It was at a working conference on lesbian and gay sexualities that was held at the [[University of California]], [[Santa Cruz, California|Santa Cruz]] in February 1990 that de Lauretis first made mention of the phrase.&lt;ref&gt;David Halperin. "The Normalization of Queer Theory." ''Journal of Homosexuality'', v.45, pp. 339–343&lt;/ref&gt; She later introduced the phrase in a 1991 special issue of [[Differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies|''difference''s'': A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies'']], entitled "Queer Theory: Lesbian and Gay Sexualities." Similar to the description Berube and Escoffier used for Queer Nation, de Lauretis asserted that, "queer unsettles and questions the genderedness of sexuality."&lt;ref name=education&gt;{{Citation|last=Pinar|first=William F.|title=Queer Theory in Education|journal=Journal of Homosexuality|year=1998|volume=45|issue=2–4|publisher=Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc.|location=Mahwah|pages=357–60|doi=10.1300/J082v45n02_21|pmid=14651192|s2cid=5467245}}&lt;/ref&gt; Barely three years later, she abandoned the phrase on the grounds that it had been taken over by those mainstream forces and institutions it was coined to resist.&lt;ref&gt;Jagose, A 1996, "Queer Theory".&lt;/ref&gt; Judith Butler's ''[[Gender Trouble]]'', [[Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick]]'s ''[[Epistemology of the Closet]]'', and [[David Halperin]]'s ''[[One Hundred Years of Homosexuality]]'' inspired other works. Teresa de Lauretis, Judith Butler, and Eve Sedgwick arranged much of the conceptual base for the emerging field in the 1990s. Along with other queer theorists, these three outlined a political [[hermeneutics]], which emphasized representation. These scholars questioned whether people of varying sexual orientations had the same political goals, and whether those in the [[sexual minority]] felt that they could be represented along with others of different sexualities and orientations. "While some critics insist that queer theory is apolitical word-smithery, de Lauretis, Butler, and Sedgwick take seriously the role that signs and symbols play in shaping the meanings and possibilities of our culture at the most basic level, including politics conventionally defined."&lt;ref name="A genealogy of queer theory"/&gt;

Queer theory has increasingly been applied not just to contemporary sexualities and identities but also to practices and identities in earlier time periods. Examination of [[LGBT history#The Renaissance|Renaissance]] culture and [[Renaissance literature|literature]], for example, has generated significant scholarship in the past 20 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Traub|first1=Valerie|title=The New Unhistoricism in Queer Studies|journal=PMLA|date=2013|volume=128|issue=1|doi=10.1632/pmla.2013.128.1.21|pages=21–39|hdl=2027.42/155635|hdl-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background concepts==

Queer theory is grounded in gender and sexuality. Due to this association, a debate emerges as to whether sexual orientation is [[Nature (philosophy)|natural]] or [[Essence|essential]] to the person, as an [[Gender essentialism|essentialist]] believes, or if sexuality is a social construction and subject to change.&lt;ref&gt;Barry, P 2002, ''Lesbian/gay criticism'', in P Barry (eds), Beginning theory: an introduction to literary and cultural theory, Manchester University Press, Manchester, pp139-155.&lt;/ref&gt;

The essentialist feminists believed that genders "have an essential nature (e.g. nurturing and caring versus being aggressive and selfish), as opposed to differing by a variety of accidental or contingent features brought about by social forces".&lt;ref name="blackburn1996"&gt;Blackburn, S 1996, "essentialism", Oxford Dictionary of Philosophy, (Oxford Reference Online).&lt;/ref&gt; Due to this belief in the essential nature of a person, it is also natural to assume that a person's sexual preference would be natural and essential to a person's [[personality]].

Social constructivism is a concept that proposes the realities we produce and the meanings we create are a result of social [[interaction]]; communicating and existing in a cultural context that conveys meaning to us. Our world is a product of continuous "claims making, labelling and other constitutive definitional processes".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Biever | first1 = Joan L. |display-authors=etal  | year = 1998 | title = The Social Construction Of Gender: A Comparison Of Feminist And Postmodern Approaches | url = | journal = Counselling Psychology Quarterly | volume = 11 | issue = 2| page = 163 | doi=10.1080/09515079808254052}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Furthermore, queer theorists have offered the argument that there is no essential self at all, and that people exist not just as subjects but also as objects of the social world. In this way, an identity is not born but rather constructed through repeated [[Performativity|performative actions]] that are in turn informed by existing social constructions of gender. By thus analyzing and understanding the ways in which gender is shared and historically constituted, the production of gender can occur differently and beyond a socially constructed binary upon which heterosexuality depends.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Butler | first1 = J | year = 1988 | title = Performative acts and gender constitution: An essay in phenomenology and feminist theory | url = | journal = Theatre Journal | volume = 40 | issue = 4| pages = 519–531 | doi=10.2307/3207893| jstor = 3207893 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Identity politics==
{{Main|Identity politics#LGBT issues}}
Queer theory was originally associated with [[Political radicalism|radical]] gay politics of [[Act up|ACT UP]], [[OutRage!]] and other groups which embraced "queer" as an identity label that pointed to a [[Separatism|separatist]], [[cultural assimilation|non-assimilationist]] politics.&lt;ref name="blackburn1996"/&gt; Queer theory developed out of an examination of perceived limitations in the traditional [[identity politics]] of recognition and [[self-identity]]. In particular, queer theorists identified processes of consolidation or stabilization around some other identity labels (e.g. gay and lesbian); and construed queerness so as to resist this. Queer theory attempts to maintain a critique more than define a specific identity. These critiques are expressed through a whole range of notions in subfields such as [[ecotechnics]] within technology studies.

Acknowledging the inevitable [[Political violence|violence]] of identity politics, and having no stake in its own [[ideology]], queer is less an identity than a critique of identity. However, it is in no position to imagine itself outside the circuit of problems energized by identity politics.  Instead of defending itself against those criticisms that its operations attract, queer allows those criticisms to shape its – for now unimaginable – future directions. "The term," writes Butler, "will be revised, dispelled, rendered obsolete to the extent that it yields to the demands which resist the term precisely because of the exclusions by which it is mobilized." The mobilization of queer foregrounds the conditions of political representation, its intentions and effects, its resistance to and recovery by the existing networks of power.&lt;ref&gt;Brooker, P, ''A Concise Glossary of Cultural Theory'', 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

The studies of Fuss anticipate queer theory. Fuss analyzes queer theory while surpassing the concept of identity politics to assert the nature in how to distinguish people who were not heterosexual from people who are without asserting the positionally of the two from the lens of a binary.&lt;ref&gt;Fuss, D. 1991. "Inside/Out." Pp. 1–10 in Inside/Out. Lesbian Theories, Gay Theories, edited by D. Fuss. New York and London: Rougledge.&lt;/ref&gt;

Eng, Halberstam and Esteban Munoz offer one of its latest incarnations in the aptly titled "What is Queer about Queer studies now?".&lt;ref&gt;Eng, D. L., J. Halberstam, and J. E. Munoz. 2005. "Introduction: What’s Queer about Queer Studies Now?" Social Text 84–85:1–17.&lt;/ref&gt; Using Judith Butler's critique of sexual identity categories as a starting point, they work around a "queer epistemology" that explicitly opposes the sexual categories of Lesbian and Gay studies and lesbian and gay identity politics. They insist that the field of normalization is not limited to sexuality; social classifications such as gender, race and nationality constituted by a "governing logic" require an epistemological intervention through queer theory." &lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Green|first=Adam Isaiah|date=March 2007|title=Queer Theory and Sociology: Locating the Subject and the Self in Sexuality Studies|journal=Sociological Theory|volume=25|issue=1|pages=26–45|doi=10.1111/j.1467-9558.2007.00296.x|s2cid=144197617|issn=0735-2751}}&lt;/ref&gt; "So, the evolution of the queer begins with the problematization of sexual identity categories in Fuss (1996) and extends outward to a more general deconstruction of social [[ontology]] in contemporary queer theory." &lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

"Edelman goes from deconstruction of the subject to a deconstructive psychoanalysis of the entire social order; the modern human fear of mortality produces defensive attempts to "suture over the hole in the Symbolic Order."&lt;ref&gt;Edelman, L. 2004. No Future. Durham and London: Duke University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; According to him, constructions of "the homosexual" are pitted against constructions of "The Child" in the modern West, wherein the former symbolizes the inevitability of mortality (do not procreate) and the latter an illusory continuity of the self with the social order (survives mortality through one's offspring). The constructs are animated by futuristic fantasy designed to evade mortality." &lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

"Fuss, Eng. et al and Edelman represent a distinct moment in the development of queer theory. Whereas Fuss aims to discompose and render inert the reigning classifications of sexual identity, Eng. et al observe the extension of a deconstructive strategy to a wider field of normalization, while Edelman’s work takes not only the specter of "the homosexual", but the very notion of "society" as a manifestation of psychological distress requiring composition."&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

==Intersex and the role of biology==

Queer theorists focus on problems in classifying individuals as either [[male]] or [[female]], even on a strictly biological basis. For example, the sex [[chromosome]]s ([[X chromosome|X]] and [[Y chromosome|Y]]) may exist in atypical combinations (as in [[Klinefelter syndrome]] [XXY]). This complicates the use of [[genotype]] as a means to define exactly two distinct sexes. [[Intersex]] individuals may for various biological reasons have [[Primary sexual characteristics|sexual characteristics]] that the dominant medical discourse regards as [[disorders of sex development|disordered]].

Scientists who have written on the conceptual significance of intersex individuals include [[Anne Fausto-Sterling]], [[Katrina Karkazis]], [[Rebecca Jordan-Young]], and [[Joan Roughgarden]]. While the [[Disorders of sex development|medical literature]] focuses increasingly on genetics of intersex traits, and even their [[preimplantation genetic diagnosis#Ethical issues|deselection]], some scholars on the study of culture, such as [[Barbara Rogoff]], argue that the traditional distinction between biology and culture as independent entities is overly simplistic, pointing to the ways in which biology and culture interact with one another.&lt;ref&gt;Rogoff, Barbara. ''The Cultural Nature of Human Development''. New York: Oxford UP, USA, 2003: 63–64. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

Intersex scholars and scientists who have written on intersex include [[Morgan Holmes]], [[Georgiann Davis]], [[Iain Morland]] and [[Janik Bastien-Charlebois]], in each case focusing on more particular realities of the intersex experience. In his essay ''What Can Queer Theory Do for Intersex?'' Morland contrasts queer "hedonic activism" with an experience of post-surgical insensate intersex bodies to claim that "queerness is characterized by the sensory interrelation of pleasure and shame".&lt;ref name="after"&gt;{{Cite book |editor1-last=Morland |editor1-first=Iain |date=2009 |title=Intersex and After |url=https://www.dukeupress.edu/Intersex-and-After/ |journal=[[GLQ: A Journal of Lesbian and Gay Studies]] |volume=15 |issue=2 |isbn=978-0-8223-6705-5 |pages= |doi= |accessdate=2014-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Disability Theory and queer theory ==
In Robert McRuer's ''Crip Theory,'' he mentions the intersection between disability theory and queer theory and how they are aided by their own association with each other and what is normal; for instance, the connection between upholding an able-bodied identity and heterosexuality. He argues that an able-bodied identity functions as more of a subconscious mentality of normality than heterosexuality. McRuer argues that there is a system that is established to distinguish those who are able-bodied from those who have disabilities; that distinction that was instituted the disability concept. Following that same dynamic, the subjection of homosexuality in relation to heterosexuality founded the basis of homosexuality. McRuer emphasizes how the intersecting of queer theory and disability theory would cultivate, "critically disabled spaces overlapping with the critically queer spaces that activists and scholars have shaped during recent decades, in which we can identify and challenge the ongoing consolidation of heterosexual, able-bodied hegemony."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Crip Theory Cultural Signs of Queerness and Disability|url=https://archive.org/details/criptheorycultur00mcru|url-access=limited|last=McRuer|first=Robert|publisher=New York: New York University Press|year=2006|isbn=9780814759868|location=|pages=[https://archive.org/details/criptheorycultur00mcru/page/n17 1]–19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The creation of [[Crip (disability term)|Crip Theory]] by McRuer was not only built on neoliberism but also critically engages with the fundamentality of the term "disability" and the manner that it paradoxically operates. McRuer asserts the nature of which that queer theory and disability theory benefit each other. The functions of the concept of able-bodiedness is utilized as an additional tool to strengthen and maintain the concept of heterosexuality and heteronormativy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kafer|first=Alison|date=2009|title=What's Crip About Queer Theory Now?|url=|journal=Sex Roles|volume=60|issue=3–4|pages=291–294|doi=10.1007/s11199-008-9511-6|s2cid=141307541}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==HIV/AIDS and queer theory==

Much of queer theory developed out of a response to the [[AIDS]] crisis, which promoted a renewal of radical activism, and the growing homophobia brought about by public responses to AIDS. Queer theory became occupied in part with what effects – put into circulation around the AIDS epidemic – necessitated and nurtured new forms of political organization, education and theorizing in "queer".

To examine the effects that HIV/AIDS has on queer theory is to look at the ways in which the status of the subject or individual is treated in the biomedical discourses that construct them.&lt;ref&gt;[[Donna Haraway]], ''The Biopolitics of Postmodern Bodies'', 1989.&lt;/ref&gt;

# The shift, affected by safer [[sex education]] in emphasizing [[sexual practices]] over sexual identities&lt;ref&gt;Michael Bartos, ''Meaning of Sex Between Men'', 1993 and G.W. Dowsett, ''Men Who Have Sex With Men'', 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;
# The persistent misrecognition of HIV/AIDS as a gay disease&lt;ref&gt;Richard Meyer, ''Rock Hudson's Body'', 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;
# Homosexuality as a kind of fatality&lt;ref&gt;Ellis Hanson, ''Unread'', 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;
# The coalition politics of much HIV/AIDS activism that rethinks identity in terms of affinity rather than essence&lt;ref&gt;Catherine Saalfield, ''Shocking Pink Praxis'', 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; and therefore includes not only lesbians and gay men but also bisexuals, [[transsexuals]], [[sex workers]], [[people with AIDS]], [[health workers]], and parents and friends of gays; the pressing recognition that discourse is not a separate or second-order reality&lt;ref&gt;Jagose, A 1996, Queer Theory, [http://www.australianhumanitiesreview.org/archive/Issue-Dec-1996/jagose.html].&lt;/ref&gt;
# The constant emphasis on contestation in resisting [[Misconceptions about HIV/AIDS|dominant depictions]] of [[HIV]] and AIDS and representing them otherwise.&lt;ref&gt;Edelman, Lee 2013, ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=Tb5YAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA14#v=onepage&amp;q=%22totalizable%20identity%22&amp;f=false Homographesis: Essays in Gay Literary and Cultural Theory]'', Routledge, {{ISBN|978-1134567232}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The rethinking of traditional understandings of the workings of power in cross-hatched struggles over epidemiology, scientific research, public health and immigration policy&lt;ref&gt;David Halperin, ''Homosexuality: A Cultural Construct'', 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;

The material effects of AIDS contested many [[cultural assumptions]] about identity, justice, desire and knowledge. One scholar claimed that AIDS challenged the health and immunity of Western [[epistemology]]: "the psychic presence of AIDS signifies a collapse of identity and difference that refuses to be abjected from the systems of self-knowledge." (p.&amp;nbsp;292)&lt;ref name="Yingling"&gt;Yingling, Thomas. "[https://books.google.com/books?id=0cbuW1iQVIwC&amp;pg=PA292#v=onepage&amp;q=%22the%20psychic%20presence%20of%20AIDS%22&amp;f=false AIDS in America: Postmodern Governance, Identity, and Experience]" in Diana Fuss, ed., ''Inside/Out: Lesbian Theories, Gay Theories''. Psychology Press, 1991. pp. 291-310. {{ISBN|978-0415902373}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Thus queer theory and AIDS become interconnected because each is articulated through a postmodernist understanding of the death of the subject and both understand identity as an ambivalent site.

==Role of language==
{{for|language use as associated with sexual identity|Lavender linguistics}}

[[Rictor Norton]] suggests that queer language evolved from structures and [[Labeling theory|labels]] imposed by a [[mainstream culture]].

Early discourse of queer theory involved leading theorists: Michel Foucault, Judith Butler, Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick and others. This discourse centered on the way that knowledge of sexuality was structured through the use of language. Michel Foucault writes in "[[The History of Sexuality]]", critiquing the idea of the "repressive hypothesis" that supposes from the 17th to the mid-20th century, sex was a private matter limited within a marriage between a husband and wife, and discourses of sex have been otherwise prohibited and repressed. As a result of this repression, people sought outlets to release sexual feelings, building their own discourses of sex and thus liberating themselves from the confines of a sexually repressive society.&lt;ref&gt;Foucault, Michel. ''The History of Sexuality, volume I: La Volonté de savoir'', 1976.&lt;/ref&gt; Foucault argues that the "repressive hypothesis" is a limiting attempt to connect open discourses of sex to personal liberation. This sort of narrative which views discourses of sex as revolutionary [[Idea of progress|progress]] against a repressive system is dependent on the assumption that people of the past were [[sexually repressed]]; however, Foucault states that from the 17th to the mid-20th century the "'repressive hypothesis"' was an illusion, rather a suppression of western society's sexuality. In fact, discourse about sexuality flourished during this time period. Foucault argues,

&lt;blockquote&gt;"Western man has been drawn for three centuries to the task of telling everything concerning his sex; that since the classical age there has been a constant optimization and increasing valorization of the discourse on sex; and that this carefully analytical discourse was meant to yield multiple effects of displacement,intensification, reorientation and modification of desire itself. Not only were the boundaries of what one could say about sex enlarged, and men compelled to hear it said; but more important, discourse was connected to sex by a complex organization with varying effects, by a deployment that cannot be adequately explained merely by referring it to a law of prohibition. A censorship of sex? There was installed rather an apparatus for producing an ever greater quantity of discourse about sex, capable of functioning and taking effect in its very economy." &lt;/blockquote&gt;

Foucault says at this time there was a political, economic and technical excitement to talk about sex. Sex became a call for management procedures. It became a policing matter.

[[Heteronormativity]] was the main focus of discourse, where heterosexuality was viewed as normal and any deviations, such as homosexuality, as abnormal or "queer". Even before the founding of "queer theory" the Modern Language Association (MLA) came together for a convention in 1973 for the first formal gay-studies seminar due to the rise of lesbian and gay writers and issues of gay and lesbian textuality. The convention was entitled "Gay Literature: Teaching and Research." In 1981, the MLA established the Division of Gay Studies in Language and Literature.

== Feminism ==
{{Main|Feminist views on sexuality#Feminism and queer theory}}Queer and feminist theories, like other perspectives based on socially-based identities and gender, tend to overlap. Both of these theories are described as responses to the "essentializing" of gender and sexual identities, which lead to the oppression of those who do not conform to socially constructed gender norms.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Gender and Sexual Identity: Transcending Feminist and Queer Theory|last1=Nagoshi|first1=Julie|last2=Nagoshi|first2=Craig|last3=Brzuzy|first3=Stephanie|publisher=Springer|year=2013|isbn=9781461489658|location=New York|pages=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; This highlights their similarity in the view that gender-related identity is [[Social constructionism|socially constructed]]. There is thus an agreement that the [[oppression]] of women and sexual minority groups can be challenged by way of a self-constructive process that rejects the perceived inferiority of this group within the social order.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; While queer and feminist theories share several commonalities, this does not mean that they are easily commensurable, with some thinkers citing that they could even be an awkward pair.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Feminism Meets Queer Theory|last1=Weed|first1=Elizabeth|last2=Schor|first2=Naomi|publisher=Indiana University Press|year=1997|isbn=978-0253332783|location=Bloomington, IN|pages=viii}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One overlap of queer theory and feminist theory is through the recognition and influence of Judith Butler and Butler's cultivation of the relationship of gender and sexuality that has come to found the basis of queer theory concerns.  The analysis of society in relation to sexuality and gender, is a display of dominance that shows the way that biology is influenced by culture and society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Watson|first=Katherine|date=2005-03-01|title=Queer Theory|journal=Group Analysis|volume=38|issue=1|pages=67–81|doi=10.1177/0533316405049369|s2cid=220475449|issn=0533-3164}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A key difference between the queer and feminist theories involves their respective scope. Feminist theory is only concerned about the issues affecting women and [[Women's empowerment|women empowerment]] while the subjects of queer theory are diverse and include women, homosexuals, transsexuals, and those considered deviants. Queer theory is also distinguished from feminist theory in the sense that it asserts identity as a conceptual category, serving as "a disciplinary apparatus that pigeonholes the fluidity of the self into a politically docile normativity."&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Politics of Everybody: Feminism, Queer Theory, and Marxism at the Intersection|last=Lewis|first=Holly|publisher=Zed Books, Ltd.|year=2016|isbn=9781783602889|location=London|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The feminist position is that '[[identity politics]]' is a political error that occurs once a standpoint gets overemphasized or naturalized.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

==Criticism==
{{See also|LGBT ideology|Anti-gender movement}}
{{Essay|date=September 2018}}

Critics of queer theory often raise the concern that the approach places excessive importance on discourse, obscuring or ignoring material factors.&lt;ref name = "Edwards"&gt;{{Citation | last= Edwards | first= Tim | title= Queer Fears: Against the Cultural Turn | journal= Sexualities |volume= 1 | year= 1998 | postscript= &lt;!--none--&gt; | doi= 10.1177/136346098001004005 | issue= 4 | pages= 471–484| s2cid= 145203216 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Tim Edwards argues that, in its examination of the social, queer theory makes excessively broad claims derived exclusively from textual analysis.&lt;ref name = "Edwards"/&gt;

Adam Green's critique leans towards a sociological stance on the issue of sexuality; primarily and rather exclusively,&lt;ref name="Green1"&gt;{{Citation | doi= 10.1023/A:1020976902569 | last= Green | first= Adam | title= Gay But Not Queer: Toward a Post-Queer Study of Sexuality | journal= Theory and Society | volume= 31 | issue= 4 | pages= 521–545 | year= 2002 | s2cid= 140739910 | postscript= &lt;!--none--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; focusing on gay or lesbian subjects. Green argues that queer theory ignores the social and institutional conditions within which lesbians and gays live. For example, queer theory regards some positions as socially contingent (racialized subject positions), while not applying the same view to others (homosexual subject positions) leading to inconsistency. Reflecting on this issue, Timothy Laurie suggests that "the desire to resist norms in some contemporary queer scholarship can never be entirely reconciled with an equally important challenge, that of producing both adequate and dynamic descriptions of ordinary events".&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title= The Ethics of Nobody I Know: Gender and the Politics of Description | first= Timothy | last= Laurie | journal=Qualitative Research Journal | volume= 14 | issue= 1 | pages= 64–78 | year= 2014 | url= https://www.academia.edu/6262250 | doi=10.1108/qrj-03-2014-0011| hdl= 10453/44221 | hdl-access= free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Queer theory's commitment to deconstruction makes it nearly impossible to speak of a "lesbian" or "gay" subject, since all social categories are denaturalized and reduced to discourse.&lt;ref name = "Gamson"&gt;{{Citation |last= Gamson
|first= Josh
|title= Handbook of Qualitative Research
|year= 2000
|publisher= Sage Publications
|chapter=Sexualities, Queer Theory, and Qualitative Research
|editor1-first=N.
|editor1-last=Denzin
|editor2-last= Lincoln
|editor2-first=Y.
|edition=2nd
|pages=347–65
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, queer theory cannot be a framework for examining selves or subjectivities—including those related to race and class—but rather, must restrict its analytic focus to discourse.&lt;ref name = "Green2"/&gt; Hence, [[sociology]] and queer theory are regarded as methodologically and [[Epistemology|epistemologically]] [[Commensurability (philosophy of science)|incommensurable]] frameworks&lt;ref name = Green2&gt;{{Citation | doi= 10.1111/j.1467-9558.2007.00296.x | last= Green | first= Adam | title= Queer Theory and Sociology: Locating the Subject and the Self in Sexuality Studies | journal= Sociological Theory | volume= 25 | issue= 1 | pages= 26–45| year= 2007 | s2cid= 144197617 | postscript= &lt;!--none--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; by critics such as Adam Isaiah Green. Green writes that&lt;ref&gt;Warner, M. 1993. "Introduction." Pp. viii–xxxi in Fear of a Queer Planet. Queer Politics and Social Theory, edited by M. Warner. Minnesota: University of Minnesota Press.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michael Warner]], in an introductory section, (1990s) draws out the possibility of queer theory as a kind of critical intervention in social theory (radical deconstructionism); but alleges that despite this, he is inconsistent regarding the reification and deconstruction of sexual identity. Green argues that Warner begins the volume by invoking an ethnic identity politics that is solidified around both a specific social division and a discussion of the importance of deconstructing notions of lesbian and gay identities; but that despite this position, he constructs the queer subject or self in largely conventional terms: as lesbian and gay people bound by homophobic institutions and practices.

So, one of the leading volumes of queer theory engages the subject via conventional sociological epistemologies that conceive of subject positions constituted through systems of stratification and organized around shared experience and identity.{{clarification needed|date=January 2020}}

For Ian Barnard,&lt;ref&gt;Barnard, I. 1999. "Queer Race." Social Semiotics 9(2):199–211.&lt;/ref&gt; sexuality is inextricably linked to [[racialization]], and any considerations of sexuality must take this into account. Adam Green argues that Barnard implicitly rejects queer theory's conceptions of sexuality on the grounds that such work fails to account for the particularity of racialized sexualities. He reasons that the failure arises because queer theorists are themselves white, and therefore, operating from the particularity of a white racial standpoint, fail to take other standpoints into account. Barnard aims to integrate an analysis of race into queer theory, proposing that the deconstructionist epistemology of queer theory can be used to first decompose a white queerness, in order to then recover a racialized queerness. Thus, Adam Green argues that Barnard's attempt to bring social contingency into queer theory violates the core epistemological premise of queer theory; in fact, by proposing that queer theory capture racialized subject positions, Barnard reinstates what it means to be a person of colour. His critique of the white subject position of queer theorists is itself a testimony to the stability of the social order and the power of social categories to mark a particular kind of experience, of subjectivity and, in turn, of queer author. He backs down the road of a decidedly sociological analysis of subject position and the self.
Finally, Green observes that [[Annamarie Jagose|Jagose]]&lt;ref&gt;Jagose, A. 1996. Queer Theory: An Introduction. New York: New York University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; aims toward an analysis of social divisions, including those of race and ethnicity. Thus, while Jagose underscores the strong deconstructionist epistemological premise of the term queer and queer theory more generally, she also goes on to analyze identities and sexualities "inflected by heterosexuality, race, gender and ethnicity".
Thus Adam Green states that by advocating the incorporation of social contingency in this way, Jagose offers neither the critical edge of queer theory nor the clarity of standpoint theory. However, on the topic of race, Jagose asserted that for a black lesbian, the thing of utmost importance is her lesbianism, rather than her race. Many gays and lesbians of color attacked this approach, accusing it of re-inscribing an essentially white identity into the heart of gay or lesbian identity (Jagose, 1996).&lt;ref name=4-encylopedia&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Queer Theory and the Social Construction of Sexuality|encyclopedia=Homosexuality|publisher=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|accessdate=15 November 2011|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/homosexuality/#QueTheSocConSex}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The criticism of queer theory can be divided into three main ideas:&lt;ref&gt;Green, A. I. "Queer Theory and Sociology: Locating the Subject and the Self in Sexuality Studies". University of Toronto.&lt;/ref&gt;
* It has a failing itineration, the "subjectless critique" of queer studies
* The unsustainable analysis of this failing self
* The methodological implication that scholars of sexuality end up reiterating and consolidating social categories

Green's views  suggest gay conservation and assimilation that derive from a more traditional perspective. His concerns regarding the potential loss of a critical edge by incorporating too much discourse on nonsexual identities is valid, however, theorists like Ruth Goldman and Cathy J. Cohen, think elsewise.

In Ruth Goldman's essay "Who Is That? Exploring Norms around Sexuality, Race, and Class in Queer Theory," she examines how rhetoric works to create a "normative discourse within queer theory" (169), and how that rhetoric serves to limit our perception of queer. In stark opposition to Green's critique, Goldman argues that in order to comply with queer theories intent to challenge the normal, it must provide a framework in which to challenge other oppressive norms that intersect with sexuality (i.e. racism, misogyny, classism, etc.). By acknowledging the intersection of multiple oppressions is to dismantle a single-issue framework, and thus, creating a platform for a more intensive analysis.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3RwTCgAAQBAJ&amp;q=bell+hooks+queer+theory&amp;pg=PA169|title=Queer Studies: A Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Anthology|last1=Beemyn|first1=Brett|last2=Eliason|first2=Michele|date=1996-01-01|publisher=NYU Press|isbn=9780814712573}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Theorist Cathy J. Cohen offers a complex critique in "Punks, Bulldaggers and Welfare Queens: The Radical Potential of Queer Politics" that supports Goldman's position. Queerness, according to Cohen, provides conceptualizations of gender and sexuality that break the traditional binary visibility. Unlike single-identity-based frameworks that fail to serve those with multi-oppressed identities, queerness has the potential to unite these aspects of self to spark a more cohesive understanding of oppression. Nevertheless, Cohen expresses concerns surrounding the dichotomy between queer and heterosexual. This binary has created a misdirection of dialogue surrounding power dynamics. Thus an undercomplicated understanding of power has been sexually categorized: all heterosexuals are characterized as privileged and all queers are deemed as oppressed. As a result, queer politics have prioritized only one factor, sexuality as the primary lens through which they structure their action. Encouraging this method of thinking rejects others that are in or in-between the margins. Cohen states that to fully grasp the advantages of queer theory, ideals need to be further radicalized; as well as, push an intersectional lens when analyzing issues.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.isabelcporras.com/punks%2Bbulldaggers%2Bcohen.pdf|title=Punks, Bulldaggers and Welfare Queens: The Radical Potential of Queer Politics|last=Cohen|first=J. Cathy|date=1997|journal=GLQ|volume=3|issue=4|pages=437–465|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160804044015/http://www.isabelcporras.com/punks%2Bbulldaggers%2Bcohen.pdf|archive-date=2016-08-04|doi=10.1215/10642684-3-4-437}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Green argues that queer is itself an identity category that some self-identified "queer theorists" and "queer activists" use to consolidate a subject-position outside of the normalizing regimes of gender and sexuality.&lt;ref name="Green"&gt;{{Citation | last= Green | first= Adam Isaiah | title= Remembering Foucault: Queer Theory &amp; Disciplinary Power | journal= Sexualities | volume= 13 | issue= 3 | year= 2010 | postscript= &lt;!--none--&gt; | doi= 10.1177/1363460709364321 | pages= 316–337| s2cid= 144388064 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  These examples call into question the degree to which identity categories need be thought of as negative, in the evaluative sense of that term, as they underscore the self-determining potentials of the care of the self – an idea advanced first by Foucault in Volumes II and III of The History of Sexuality.

The role of queer theory, and specifically its replacement of historical and sociological scholarship on lesbian and gay people's lives with the theorising of lesbian and gay issues, and the displacement of gay and lesbian studies by gender and queer studies, has been criticised by activist and writer [[Larry Kramer]].&lt;ref&gt;Kaiser, Charles, [https://web.archive.org/web/20090502193413/http://www.advocate.com/exclusive_detail_ektid81256.asp Larry Kramer's Case Against "Queer"] Advocate.com, April 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2009/04/28/kramer|title=Inside Higher Ed's News|website=www.insidehighered.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.thedailybeast.com/|title=The Daily Beast|website=The Daily Beast}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kramer reports on a book by Richard Godbeer, a professor of history and gender studies at the University of Miami, called The Overflowing of Friendship. Kramer criticizes Godbeer's account of 18th century Colonial times. Kramer writes, "Godbeer is hell-bent on convincing us that two men in Colonial America could have exceedingly obsessive and passionate relationships (he called them, variously, 'sentimental,' 'loving,' 'romantic') . . . [men would] spend many a night in bed together talking their hearts out, without the issue of sex arising in any way."&lt;ref name=kramer&gt;{{Citation|last=Kramer|first=Larry|title=Queer Theory's Heist of Our History|journal=Gay &amp; Lesbian Review Worldwide|year=2011|volume=16|issue=5|url=http://www.glreview.com/article.php?articleid=166|accessdate=5 December 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111215092327/http://www.glreview.com/article.php?articleid=166|archivedate=15 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Kramer does not agree with this theory and believes that the notion the same-sex sexual relationships and experiences existed. Relatedly, educator and writer [[John D'Emilio|John D’Emilio]] argues that gay identity has not always existed and the emergence of gay men and lesbian was rather a later development associated with the spread of capitalism in the 19th century. A capitalist system of free labor propagated in society and the independent unit of the nuclear family no longer became a necessary economical unit. As the family in turn took on a new role as an emotional and affective unit and separated from the world of work and production, the idea of sexuality separated from that of procreation. Sexuality, no longer bound by the imperative of reproduction, experienced a change and allowed people to think differently about desire, thus creating conditions allowing for the expression of homosexual behavior and the construction of a gay identity.&lt;ref&gt;D’Emilio, J. (1983). Capitalism and gay identity. ''Families in the US: Kinship and domestic politics'', 131-41.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another criticism is that queer theory, in part because it typically has recourse to a very technical jargon, is written by a narrow elite for that narrow elite. It is therefore class biased and also, in practice, only really known and referenced at universities and colleges (Malinowitz, 1993).&lt;ref name=4-encylopedia /&gt; In addition, those in a position of power, have access to modes of communication where they can express their interpretation, definitions and descriptions of topics, sometimes regardless of the accuracy. This persons of power are given "privileged act of naming."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Hooks | first1 = Bell | year = 1991 | title = Theory as liberatory practice | url = | journal = Yale Journal of Law and Feminism | volume = 4 | issue = | page = 1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, this can obscure the perception of reality for those in institutionalized settings. Academia often neglects works of theory by women or men of color. This can be attributed to the fact that institutions have imposed standards of critical evaluations for what is a work of theory and what is not. These standards have led to appropriation of work that was deemed unfit and have created a stark exclusion of people who can access the material. This turns the mass public against the idea of understanding theory; an important aspect in relation to understanding practice. The institutionalization of queer theory has imposed a threat of taming and domesticating critical energy.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

An initial criticism on queer theory is that precisely "queer" does not refer to any specific sexual status or gender object choice. For example, Halperin (1995)&lt;ref name=4-encylopedia /&gt;  allows that straight persons may be "queer," which some believe, robs gays and lesbians of the distinctiveness of what causes them to be marginalized. It desexualizes identity, when the issue is precisely about a sexual identity (Jagose, 1996).&lt;ref name=4-encylopedia /&gt; On the other hand, Michael Warner argues that the objective of queer is to challenge normalness not heterosexuality. This ties back into Cohen's point about the power dichotomy. Straight persons can be oppressed for behaviors that are seen as sexually deviant as well. One example is the "welfare queen," a woman of color who is marginalized for her race, sexuality and gender—all identities which intersect to create this kind of oppression.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

The critique of queer theory is not limited to the US. Queer theory has been repeatedly criticized by the Vatican. Pope Francis spoke about "ideological colonization" by which he meant that queer theory, and more broadly critical gender studies, threatens traditional family and fertile heterosexuality. France was one of the first countries where this claim became widespread when catholic movements marched in the streets of Paris against the bill on gay marriage and adoption. [[Bruno Perreau]] in [http://www.sup.org/books/title/?id=27481 Queer Theory: The French Response] &lt;ref&gt;Queer Theory: The French Response, Stanford University Press, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; has shown that this fear has deep historical roots in France. He argues that the rejection of queer theory expresses anxieties about national identity and minority politics. Minority groups could betray the nation and prefer transnational identities. Perreau maintains that queer theory shows that being part of a group requires the ability to critique one's own belonging. This is largely unbearable to reactionary movements, Perreau argues, all the more because queer theory is ironically largely based on French theory.

==See also==
{{colbegin}}
*[[Essentialism]]
* [[Gender and Sexual Diversity]]
*[[Gender role]]
*[[Performative interval]]
*[[Performativity]]
*[[Post-feminism]]
*[[Postmodern feminism]]
*[[Social constructionism]]
*[[Third-wave feminism]]
*[[Pink capitalism]]
{{colend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite journal | last1 = Adam | first1 = B | year = 2000 | title = Love and Sex in Constructing Identity Among Men Who Have Sex With Men | url = | journal = International Journal of Sexuality and Gender Studies | volume = 5 | issue = 4| pages = 325–29 |doi=10.1023/A:1010176031080| s2cid = 141365694 }}
* {{cite book | last = Ahmed | first = Sara | title = Queer Phenomenology | year = 2006 }}
* {{cite book | last = Butler | first = Judith | author-link = Judith Butler | title = Bodies that Matter: On the Discursive Limits of 'Sex' | url = https://archive.org/details/bodiesthatmatter00butl | url-access = registration | year = 1993 }}
* {{cite book | last = Butler | first = Judith | author-link = Judith Butler | title = Gender Trouble | year = 1990 }}
* {{cite book | last = Butler | first = Judith | author-link = Judith Butler | title = Undoing Gender | year = 2004 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = de Lauretis | first = Teresa | title = Queer Theory: Lesbian and Gay Sexualities | journal = Differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies | volume = 3 | issue = 2 | page = 18 | date = Summer 1991 | isbn = 9780814742341 | ref = harv | oclc = 863428297 }}
* {{cite book | last = Edelman | first = Lee | title = No Future | year = 2004 }}
* {{cite book | last = Foucault | first = Michel | author-link = Michel Foucault | title = The History of Sexuality, volume I: La Volonté de savoir | year = 1976 }}
* {{cite book | last = Fryer | first = David | title = Thinking Queerly | year = 2010 }}
* {{citation | last = Gabilondo | first = Joseba | contribution = Ikasketa eta teoria Queer-ak | editor-last = Aizpuru | editor-first = Alaitz | title = Euskal Herriko pentsamenduaren gida | publisher = Udako Euskal Unibertsitatea [The Basque Summer University] | location = [[Bilbao|Bilbo]], Spain | year = 2012 | isbn = 978-84-8438-435-9 }}
* {{cite book | editor-last = Goldberg | editor-first = Jonathan | title = Queering the Renaissance | year = 1993 }}
* {{cite book | last = Halberstam | first = Judith | title = In a Queer Time and Place | year = 2005 }}
* {{cite book | last = Huffer | first = Lynne | title = Are the lips a grave? A queer feminist on the ethics of sex | publisher = Columbia University Press | location = New York | year = 2013 | isbn = 9780231164177 }}
:''See also'' 
:* {{cite journal | last = Huffer | first = Lynne | title = Lipwork | journal = [[Differences (journal)|differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies]] | volume = 27 | issue = 3 | pages = 93&amp;ndash;105 | doi = 10.1215/10407391-3696643 | date = December 2016 | ref = harv }}
:* {{cite journal | last = Edelman | first = Lee | author-link = Lee Edelman | title = An Ethics of Desubjectivation? | journal = [[Differences (journal)|differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies]] | volume = 27 | issue = 3 | pages = 106&amp;ndash;118 | doi = 10.1215/10407391-3696679 | date = December 2016 | ref = harv }}
:* {{cite journal | last = Lee | first = Kyoo | title = Lipthink, Anyone? On, Lips Apart, Disagreeing ''with'' You . . . For a Queer Feminist ''Rect''ification? | journal = [[Differences (journal)|differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies]] | volume = 27 | issue = 3 | pages = 119&amp;ndash;131 | doi = 10.1215/10407391-3696667 | date = December 2016 | ref = harv }}
:* {{cite journal | last = Deutscher | first = Penelope | author-link = Penelope Deutscher | title = Lynne Huffer's ''Are the Lips a Grave?'' Averting and Accentuating the Genealogical | journal = [[Differences (journal)|differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies]] | volume = 27 | issue = 3 | pages = 132&amp;ndash;144 | doi = 10.1215/10407391-3696655 | date = December 2016 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Jagose | first = Annamarie | title = Queer Theory : An Introduction | year = 1996 }}
* {{cite journal|last1=Marcus|first1=Sharon|title=Queer Theory for Everyone: A Review Essay|journal=[[Signs (journal)|Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society]]|date=2005|volume=31|issue=1|pages=191–218|doi=10.1086/432743|s2cid=145141486}}
* {{cite book | last = Marinucci | first = Mimi | title = Feminism is Queer: the intimiate connection between queer and feminist theory | year = 2010 }}
* {{cite journal|last1=Miskilci|first1=Richard|title=A Teoria Queer e a Sociologia: o desafio de uma analítica da normalização|journal=Sociologias|date=2009|volume=21|issue=21|pages=150–182|doi=10.1590/S1517-45222009000100008|trans-title=Queer Theory and Sociology: the challenging analysis of normalization|language=pt|doi-access=free}}
* {{cite book | last = Muñoz | first = José Esteban | title = Disidentifications: Queers of Color and the Performance of Politics | year = 1999 }}
* {{cite book | last = Preciado | first = Beatriz | author-link = Beatriz Preciado | title = Manifesto Contra-sexual | year = 2002 }}
* {{cite book | last = Perreau | first = Bruno | title = Queer Theory: The French Response | year = 2016 }}
* {{cite book | last = Probyn | first = Elspeth | title = Outside Belongings | year = 1996 }}
* {{cite book | last = Rayter | first = Scott | title = He Who Laughs Last: Comic Representations of AIDS | year = 2003 }}
* {{cite book | last = Sedgwick | first = Eve Kosofsky | title = Between Men | url = https://archive.org/details/betweenmenenglis00sedg | url-access = registration | year = 1985 }}
* {{cite book | last = Sedgwick | first = Eve Kosofsky | title = Epistemology of the Closet | year = 1990 }}
* {{cite book | last = Sedgwick | first = Eve Kosofsky | title = "Writing the History of Homophobia." Theory Aside | year = 2014 }}
* {{cite book | last = Turner | first = William B. | title = A Genealogy of Queer Theory | year = 2000 }}
* {{cite book | last = Wiegman | first = Robyn | title = Object Lessons | year = 2012 }}
* {{cite book | last = Wilchins | first = Riki | title = Gender Theory, Queer Theory | year = 2004 }}
* {{Cite book|title=The Ashgate Research Companion to Contemporary Religion and Sexuality|last1=Hunt|first1=Stephen|last2=Yip|first2=Andrew|publisher=Routledge|year=2016|isbn=9781409409496|location=Oxon|pages=45}}
* Godiwala, Dimple, Alternatives within the Mainstream, Queer Theatres in Post-War Britain, O'Corra, Simon et al, Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2007, ISBN 9 781847 183064

==External links==
* [http://www.trikster.net Trikster – Nordic Queer Journal]

{{LGBT |selected=academy |state=uncollapsed}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Queer theory| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>