<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161122043053|750905611" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5215866" pageid="5215866" ns="0" title="Racism in Asia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-22T04:31:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">
{{refimprove|date=August 2008}}

'''Racism in Asia''' exists for similar reasons that [[racism]] elsewhere exists. In general, racism exists in these countries due to historical events that occurred either recently or thousands of years ago.

Racist sentiments exist between citizens of [[Pakistan]] towards the citizens of [[Bangladesh]]. This conflict goes back to when India was first partitioned into [[West Pakistan]] and [[East Pakistan]] when citizens of today's Pakistan dominated the original Pakistani government. Due to political, economic, linguistic and ethnic discrimination by the Pakistani state before independence in 1971, and the atrocities against the Bengalis committed by the Pakistan Army during the Bangladesh Liberation War, some people in Bangladesh abhor everything from Pakistan. Three million Bangladeshis were killed by the Pakistani army during the 9-month-long war of independence in 1971. The Government of Bangladesh demands a formal apology for those atrocities from the Pakistani head of state, as well as putting on trial former military and political leaders who had played a role in the army action in then East Pakistan. Pakistan has continued to ignore this demand.

In [[Cambodia]], one of the biggest genocides in history occurred, with the [[Khmer Rouge]] led by [[Pol Pot]] persecuting ethnic Chinese and other foreigners living in Cambodia. This conflict stems from Chinese involvement in Cambodia before the [[Vietnam War]]. In [[Israel]], racism exists between [[Jews|Jewish]] Israelis and [[Palestinians]], both Muslim and Christian. Racism in Israel stems from the [[Israeli-Palestinian Conflict]] created with the founding of Israel.

Overall, racism exists in Asia because of ethnic conflicts that existed in the region for thousands of years.

==Bangladesh==

Disputes between East and West Pakistan soon after the partition of India were beginning to give rise to racist ideas and sentiments towards West Pakistani social groups, West Pakistanis being seen as '[[Mleccha]]' or inferior, uncivilized tribals compared to the educated Bengalis. After the 1971 [[Bangladesh Liberation War]], non-Bengalis, specifically [[Biharis]] and other Muslim refugees from India suffered from active ethnic discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://www.scientificjournals.org/journals2008/articles/1313.pdf | title=The Neglected Stateless ''Bihari'' Community in Bangladesh: Victims of Political and Diplomatic Onslaught | author=Kazi Fahmida Farzana | journal=Journal of Humanities &amp; Social Sciences | year=2008 | volume=2 | issue=1 | issn=1934-7227}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are not considered full-fledged citizens of Bangladesh and until recently were not allowed to vote.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} The Bangladesh government now allows Biharis born after 1971 to vote in elections to the legislature.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.refugeesinternational.org/content/publication/detail/7828/ Citizens of Nowhere: The Stateless Biharis of Bangladesh - Refugees International 2006 report]&lt;/ref&gt;{{dubious|date=August 2015}}
 
In 2015, ruling [[Awami League]] [[Member of Parliament]], [[Elias Mollah]], a man with little education,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Awami League MP Elias Mollah calls Africans ‘uncivilised’ after UN peacekeeping mission tour|url=http://bdnews24.com/politics/2015/08/04/awami-league-mp-elias-mollah-calls-africans-uncivilised-after-un-peacekeeping-mission-tour|accessdate=6 August 2015|agency=The Daily Star|publisher=The Daily Satr|date=4 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; commented on his recent trip to [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congo]]: "Our army has gone there (Africa) to civilise those black people. I am sure they will accomplish the task." He constantly referred  to the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congolese]] as "uncivilized black people" and added "People there are yet to become civilised. They take bath every 15 days. After applying soaps before bath, they do not even use water in a bid to retain the aroma."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Liton|first1=Shakhawat|title=Opinion: Shouldn’t AL MP Elias apologise?|url=http://www.thedailystar.net/politics/opinion-shouldn%E2%80%99t-al-mp-elias-apologise-122173|accessdate=6 August 2015|agency=The Daily Star|publisher=The Daily Star|date=5 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bhutan==
In 1991–92, [[Bhutan]] is said to have deported between 10,000 and 100,000 ethnic Nepalis ([[Lhotshampa]]). The actual number of refugees that were initially deported are debated by both sides. In March 2008, this population began a multiyear resettlement to third countries including the U.S., Canada, New Zealand, Norway, Denmark, the Netherlands and Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?ReportId=77513|title=IRIN Asia - NEPAL-BHUTAN: Bhutan questions identity of 107,000 refugees in Nepal - Nepal - Refugees/IDPs|work=IRINnews|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; At present, the [[United States]] is working towards resettling more than 60,000 of these [[refugee]]s in the US as third country settlement programme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7082586.stm | title = Bhutan refugees are 'intimidated' | author = Bhaumik, Subir | date = November 7, 2007 | work = BBC News | accessdate = 2008-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Brunei==
Brunei law provides [[positive discrimination]] in favor of [[Malays (ethnic group)|ethnic Malay]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/country_profiles/1298607.stm Country profile: Brunei], BBC NEWS&lt;/ref&gt;

==Myanmar==
[[Ne Win|Ne Win's]] rise to power in 1962 and his persecution of "resident aliens" (immigrant groups not recognised as citizens of the [[Union of Burma]]) led to an exodus of some 300,000 [[Burmese Indians]] from discriminatory policies, particularly after wholesale nationalisation of private enterprise a few years later in 1964.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Martin|last=Smith|year=1991|title=Burma - Insurgency and the Politics of Ethnicity|publisher=Zed Books|location=London,New Jersey|pages=43–44,98,56–57,176}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Burma: Asians v. Asians|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,875949,00.html|accessdate=4 October 2012|newspaper=[[Time Magazine]]|date=17 July 1964}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some Muslim refugees entered Bangladesh, but continued to suffer there as the Bangladeshi government provided no support as of 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Dummett|first=Mark|title=Burmese exiles in desperate conditions|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/7019882.stm|accessdate=4 October 2012|newspaper=BBC News|date=29 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cambodia==
The [[Khmer Rouge]] regime in [[Cambodia]] disproportionately targeted ethnic minority groups. These included ethnic [[Overseas Chinese|Chinese]], [[Vietnamese people|Vietnamese]] and [[Thai people|Thai]]. In the late 1960s, an estimated 425,000 ethnic Chinese lived in Cambodia, but by 1984, as a result of Khmer Rouge [[genocide]] and emigration, only about 61,400 Chinese remained in the country. The [[Cham (Asia)|Cham]], a Muslim minority who are the descendants of migrants from the old state of [[Champa]], were forced to adopt the [[Khmer people|Khmer]] language and customs. A Khmer Rouge order stated that henceforth "The Cham nation no longer exists on Kampuchean soil belonging to the Khmers" (U.N. Doc. A.34/569 at 9). Only about half of the Cham survived.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ppu.org.uk/genocide/g_cambodia1.html|title=GENOCIDE -  CAMBODIA|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.genocidewatch.org/aboutgenocide/stantoncambodianlaw.htm The Cambodian Genocide and International Law]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.country-studies.com/cambodia/the-chinese.html|title=Cambodia the Chinese|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==China==
{{Main|Sinocentrism|Han chauvinism|ethnic issues in China}}
{{See also|Hua–Yi distinction|Anti-Manchuism|anti-Japanese sentiment in China}}
Several clashes between [[Ethnic groups of Africa|African]] and Chinese students have occurred since the arrival of Africans to Chinese universities in the 1960s. Many African students come to China on a scholarship through the government to study at a university.  The African students were often perceived as threatening and not punctual.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1988/12/30/world/black-africa-leaves-china-in-quandary.html ''New York Times'']&lt;/ref&gt;  A well-documented [[Nanjing anti-African protests|incident in 1988]] featured Chinese students rioting against African students studying in [[Nanjing]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED8153CF933A05751C1A96E948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all ''New York Times'' article by Nicholas Kristof]&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2007, police anti-drug crackdowns in Beijing's [[Sanlitun]] district were reported to target people from [[Africa]] as suspected criminals, though police officials denied targeting any group.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beijingnewspeak.com/2007/09/28/sanlitun-saga-update-anti-drug-operation-uncovers-no-drugs Beijing Newspeak :: Sanlitun saga update: anti-drug operation uncovers no drugs&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Similar sentiment has emerged in [[Guangzhou]], where a very [[Africans in Guangzhou|large group of Africans]] have settled.

Anti-Japanese sentiment in China is an issue with old roots. Japan started off like other Western powers by annexing land from China towards the end of the Qing Dynasty. Dissatisfaction with the settlement and the Twenty-One Demands by the Japanese government led to a severe boycott of Japanese products in China. Bitterness in China persists over the atrocities of the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]], such as the [[Nanjing Massacre]] and Japan's post-war actions. Today, [[Japanese history textbook controversies|textbook revisionism and censorship]] remain contentious issues.

=== Hong Kong ===
With a population of almost 7 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.censtatd.gov.hk/press_release/press_releases_on_statistics/index.jsp?sID=1752&amp;sSUBID=7113&amp;subjectID=&amp;charsetID=&amp;displayMode=D |title = Press Release (14 Aug 2006): Mid-year Population for 2006 - Census and Statistics Department |date = 14 August 2006 |publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hong Kong]] has gained a reputation as an international city, while remaining predominantly Chinese. This multi-culturalism has raised issues of racial and gender discrimination, particularly among the 350,000 [[list of ethnic groups|ethnic]] minorities such as Nepalese, Indians, Indonesians, Pakistanis and Filipinos, who have long established minority communities since the founding days of the former colony or have come to Hong Kong recently to work as domestic workers. For example, Filipino females are sometimes addressed by the derogatory term "Bun Mui" and Filipino males "Bun Jai" (literally Filipino sister and Filipino son, respectively).{{Citation needed|reason=Also, need to qualify reference to lack of minimum wage, as certain foreign employees in Hong Kong have been eligible to be protected by minimum wage. See now the new [http://www.labour.gov.hk/eng/news/mwo.htm Minimum Wage Ordinance] which will come into force on 1 May 2011.|date=September 2011}} In 2003, the number of complaints filed with the body handling discrimination issues, the Equal Opportunities Commission&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.eoc.org.hk/eoc/GraphicsFolder/default.aspx |title = Equal Opportunities Commission |publisher = |accessdate = 17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; increased by 31 percent.

Since the transfer of sovereignty in 1997, there has been greater tension and more conflicts have risen between residents of the PRC (People's Republic of China or the "Mainland") and Hong Kong over a variety of political and [[Socioeconomics|socio-economical]] issues concerning the governance and constitutional autonomy of the territory. The issues partly involve the oppressive policy of the PRC government&lt;ref name="前香港大律師公會主席石永泰──中港爭議源自價值觀分歧"&gt;{{cite web |url = http://programme.rthk.org.hk/channel/radio/programme.php?name=radio1/hkletter&amp;d=2015-09-26&amp;p=1085&amp;e=325884&amp;m=episode |title = 前香港大律師公會主席石永泰──中港爭議源自價值觀分歧 |date=September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and also partly the behaviours of Mainland residents when they travel to Hong Kong. Mainland residents suffered considerable set-backs in the 1960s and 1970s due to catastrophes such as the [[Great Chinese Famine]] that resulted from the poor governance of the PRC. However, since the 1990s, the Mainland has had considerable economic growth and a heightened sense of its important place in the world. Lately, there have been observations that significant number of visiting Mainland residents, with a 'China is a power country now' mindset, have become overconfident, arrogant, and overbearing.&lt;ref name="前香港大律師公會主席石永泰──中港爭議源自價值觀分歧" /&gt; There also have been reports that visiting Mainland parents have taken the easy route of letting their child defecate or urinate openly in the street in busy shopping districts or in public transport, instead of locating a toilet in the unfamiliar city&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://hk.apple.nextmedia.com/news/art/20140419/18694315 |work = The Apple Daily |title = Mainland tourists let their child pee in the street and assaulted Hong Kong resident}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, when they are caught, Mainland residents and their supporters attempt to defend their behaviours by accusing others of racism.

Similarly, with the introduction of China's [[Individual Visit Scheme]] in 2003, which effectively grants Mainland residents an unlimited entry travel visa to Hong Kong, and following the [[2008 Chinese milk scandal]] and [[Food safety incidents in China|other food safety incidents in China]] an influx of Mainland residents travel regularly to Hong Kong to buy baby formula and other daily necessities. In the process, this influx caused shortages of supply for Hong Kong parents and escalated rents; it also greatly harmed the commercial diversity of Hong Kong business. Due to the great demand from mainland residents, smugglers organisations have grown rapidly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bcmagazine.net/bc/tag/real-hong-kong-news/ | title=Real Hong Kong News | work=bc magazine | accessdate=June 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; This deleterious effect on the economy, along with their poor reputation for hygiene, courtesy and flouting the norms of Hong Kong behaviour, has caused some Hong Kong residents to refer to Mainland residents as "locusts";&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.economist.com/node/21546051 |work=The Economist |title=Dogs and locusts |date=2012-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; they are seen as invaders who swarm into the city and drain its resources. Again, Mainland residents and their supporters, in response, reduce these complex political and economical issues by accusing others of racism, even though the visiting Mainlanders are largely of the same race as many Hong Kongers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://rthk.hk/rthk/news/expressnews/20150224/news_20150224_55_1079278.htm | title=回 應 反 水 貨 客 行 動  張 超 雄 認 為 屬 歧 視 不 能 接 受 | date=2015-02-24 | accessdate=June 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the other hand, a race discrimination bill has been demanded by human rights groups for the last 10 years, and the government has been accused of putting the issue on the back burner. Last 3 December 2006 was the first time a drafted bill was proposed at the Legislative Council, and was expected to be passed before the end of 2008. However, the bill was criticized for being "too conservative".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.ahrchk.net/ahrc-in-news/mainfile.php/2004ahrcinnews/222/ |title = Asian Human Rights Commission |publisher= |accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The exclusion of Mainland Chinese migrants has also been a source of controversy, with the government claiming that they are not considered to be of a different race. Another issue of the bill has been of language instruction in schools.

== India ==
{{See also|Ethnic relations in India|Aryan race#British Raj|l4=Aryanism during the British Raj}}

The earliest rejection of discrimination was made as far back as the Hindu sacred text of [[Bhagavada Gita]], which says that no person, no matter what, is barred from enlightenment.  Even early Hindu texts such as the [[Rig Veda]] discourage the abuse of outcastes.  The text reads, "[[Indra]], you lifted up the outcast who was oppressed, you glorified the blind and the lame." (Rg-Veda 2:13:12).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bharatvani.org/books/ait/ch47.htm|title=4.7. INDRA AND SHIVA|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[varna]] system was equivalent to division of labour and a [[Shudra]]'s son (the lowest varna) could become a [[Brahmin]]. But later this system became hereditary and a Shudra's son would remain a Shudra, and became to known as [[Caste system in India|caste system]].
During the [[British Raj]], racist views against Indians based on the systemic [[scientific racism]] practiced in Europe at the time were popularized. Views include dividing linguistic groups into ethnic "classes" (see [[Historical definitions of races in India]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dhbwDFfE9J8C&amp;pg=PA99 |title=Aryans and British India|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first Prime minister of India, Pandit [[Jawaharlal Nehru]], wrote
{{cquote|"We in India have known racialism in all its forms ever since the commencement of [[British Raj|British rule]]. The idea of a [[master race]] is inherent in imperialism ... India as a nation and Indians as individuals were subjected to insult, humiliation and contemptuous treatment. The English were an imperial race, we were told, with the God-given right to govern us and keep us in subjection; if we protested we were reminded of the 'tiger qualities of an imperial race'.&lt;ref name="NehruIndia"&gt;From [[Discovery of India]] by [[Jawaharlal Nehru]], reproduced from "History : Modern India" (p108) by S.N. Sen, New Age Publishers, ISBN 81-224-1774-4.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== Indonesia ==
{{See also|Jakarta Riots of May 1998|Anti-Chinese legislation in Indonesia}}

A number of discriminatory laws against [[Chinese Indonesian#Post-independence and New Order Era|Chinese Indonesians]] were enacted by the government of [[Indonesia]]. In 1959, President [[Sukarno]] approved [[PP 10/1959]] that forced Chinese Indonesians to close their businesses in rural areas and relocate into urban areas. Moreover, political pressures in the 1970s and 1980s restricted the role of the Chinese Indonesian in politics, academics, and the military. As a result, they were thereafter constrained professionally to becoming entrepreneurs and professional managers in trade, manufacturing, and banking. In the 1960s, following the failed alleged Communist coup attempt in 1965, there was a strong sentiment against the Chinese Indonesians who were accused of being Communist collaborators. In 1998, Indonesia riots over higher food prices and rumors of hoarding by merchants and shopkeepers often degenerated into anti-Chinese attacks. There were also racism against religion &amp; believe wide across the country, especially between [[Muslims]] and [[Christians]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/1998/02/24/qanda.t_2.php International Herald Tribune: Q&amp;A / Juwono Sudarsono, Defense Official : Racism in Indonesia Undercuts Unity]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Amnesty International]] has estimated more than 100,000 [[Papuan languages|Papuans]], one-sixth of the population, have died as a result of violence against [[Western New Guinea|West Papuans]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shnews.co/detile-27029-ahrc-genosida-di-papua-benar-terjadi.html|title=SHNEWS.CO:AHRC: Genosida di Papua Benar Terjadi|first=Sinar|last=Harapan|work=shnews.co|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usyd.edu.au/news/84.html?newsstoryid=651|title=News|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; while others had previously specified much higher death tolls.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news.vu/en/news/RegionalNews/050728-West-Papua-Support.shtml West Papua Support]&lt;/ref&gt; The 1990s saw Indonesia accelerate its [[Transmigration program]], under which hundreds of thousands of [[Java]]nese and [[Sumatra]]n migrants were resettled to Papua over a ten-year period, The Indonesian government saw this as the economical improvement and also population density improvement for Indonesia. Critics suspect that the Transmigration program's purpose is to tip the balance of the province's population from the heavily [[Melanesians|Melanesian]] Papuans toward western Indonesians, thus further consolidating Indonesian control.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/cline/papua/transmigration.htm|title=West Papua - Transmigration|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Iran==
As late as August 2010, [[UN]]'s anti-racism panel found The Islamic republic of [[Iran]] discriminating and practicing wide racism against [[Arabs]], [[Kurds]], [[Baloch people|Baluch]], other ethnic minorities. The [[United Nations]] panel said "Arabs, Kurds and other minorities in Iran face discrimination because of their ethnicity."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=UN anti-racism panel finds Iran discriminating against Arabs, Kurds, other minoritiesdate=August 27, 2010|work=Associated Press, Fox|url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2010/08/27/anti-racism-panel-finds-iran-discriminating-arabs-kurds-ethnic-minorities/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[U.N.]] urged [[Iran]] to tackle racism on Arab, [[Azeri]], [[Baloch people|Balochi]], [[Kurd]]ish communities and some communities of non-citizens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The U.N. urged Iran to tackle racism |work= Reuters|date= August 27, 2010|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/idUKTRE67Q2K520100827}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Israel==
{{main|Racism  and ethnic discrimination in Israel}}
Organizations such as [[Amnesty International]], the [[Association for Civil Rights in Israel]], and the United States [[Department of State]]&lt;ref name="state.gov-2004"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2004/41723.htm |title=Israel and the occupied territories |work=State.gov |date=2005-02-28 |accessdate=2010-07-22|publisher=Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor|type=Report}}&lt;/ref&gt; have published reports documenting racial discrimination in Israel.

The [[Association for Civil Rights in Israel]] (ACRI) published reports documenting racism in Israel, and the 2007 report suggested that racism in the country was increasing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Israeli anti-Arab racism 'rises'|work=BBC|date=10 December 2007|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/7136068.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One analysis of the report summarized it: "Over two-thirds Israeli teen believe Arabs to be less intelligent, uncultured and violent. Over a third of Israeli teens fear Arabs all together....The report becomes even grimmer, citing the ACRI's racism poll, taken in March 2007, in which 50% of Israelis taking part said they would not live in the same building as Arabs, will not befriend, or let their children befriend Arabs and would not let Arabs into their homes."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Synopsis of the report, from "Racism in Israel on the rise"|author=Aviram Zino|work=Ynet News|date=12 August 2007|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3480345,00.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The 2008 report from ACRI says the trend of increasing racism is continuing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Reflections on October 2000 - Eight years later, discrimination and racism against Israel's Arab citizens have only increased|type=news release|publisher=ACRI|url=http://www.acri.org.il/eng/story.aspx?id=556}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Japan ==
{{further|Ethnic issues in Japan|Uyoku dantai}}
In 2005, a [[United Nations]] report expressed concerns about racism in Japan and that government recognition of the depth of the problem was not total.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unic.or.jp/new/pr05-057-E.htm |title=Press Conference by Mr Doudou Diène, Special Rapporteur of the Commission on Human Rights |accessdate=2007-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BBC"&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4671687.stm "Japan racism 'deep and profound".] [[BBC News]] (2005-07-11). Retrieved on 2007-01-05.&lt;/ref&gt; The author of the report, [[Doudou Diène]] ([[United Nations Special Rapporteur|Special Rapporteur]] of the [[UN Commission on Human Rights]]), concluded after a nine-day investigation that racial discrimination and xenophobia in Japan primarily affects three groups: [[Ethnic issues in Japan#Japanese minorities|national minorities]], [[Dekasegi|Latin Americans of Japanese descent]], mainly [[Japanese Brazilians]], and foreigners from poor countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.imadr.org/geneva/2006/G0610396.pdf |format=PDF|title='Overcoming "Marginalization" and "Invisibility"', International Movement against all forms of Discrimination and Racism |accessdate=2007-01-05 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20061214115324/http://imadr.org/geneva/2006/G0610396.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Japan]] accepted just 16 [[refugees]] in 1999, while the [[United States]] took in 85,010 for resettlement, according to the UNHCR. [[New Zealand]], which is 30 times smaller than Japan, accepted 1,140 refugees in 1999. Just 305 persons were recognized as refugees by Japan from 1981, when Japan ratified the [[U.N.]] [[Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees]], to 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0WDQ/is_2003_Feb_24/ai_98002254|title=Japan's refugee policy|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iwanami.co.jp/jpworld/text/ClosedCountry01.html|title=Questioning Japan's 'Closed Country' Policy on Refugees|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former Prime Minister [[Taro Aso]] called Japan a "one race" nation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://search.japantimes.co.jp/member/member.html?nn20051018a7.htm Aso says Japan is nation of 'one race']&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ainu people]] are an ethnic group indigenous to [[Hokkaidō]], northern [[Honshū]], the [[Kuril Islands]], much of [[Sakhalin]], and the southernmost third of the [[Kamchatka peninsula]]. As Japanese settlement expanded, the Ainu were pushed northward, until by the [[Meiji period]] they were confined by the government to a small area in Hokkaidō, in a manner similar to the placing of American Indians on reservations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://countrystudies.us/japan/57.htm|title=Japan - Ainu|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Jordan ==
{{further|Racism in the Middle East#Jordan}}

== Korea ==
{{main|Racism in South Korea|Korean ethnic nationalism|Anti-Japanese sentiment in Korea}}
[[Koreans]] tend to equate [[nationality]] or [[citizenship]] with membership in a single, homogeneous [[ethnic group]] or "[[Race (classification of human beings)|race]]" ([[Korean ethnic nationalism|minjok]], in Korean). Discrimination and ostracism of biracial children is ubiquitous in Korean society.{{citation needed|date=August 2013}} A common language and culture also are viewed as important elements in Korean identity. Both [[North Korea]] and [[South Korea]] are among the world's most ethnically homogeneous nations.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}}

South Korean schools have been criticized for hiring only white teachers who apply to teach English, because Koreans regard fair skin color as representative of "American" or "English"-ness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=11826937|title=Ethnic Bias Seen in South Korea Teacher Hiring|date=9 July 2007|work=NPR.org|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A survey showed that 53% of adult individuals in South Korea harbor anti-Semitic beliefs, accounting for nearly 20 million people who hold such beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://global100.adl.org/#country/south-korea/2014|title=The ADL Global 100: South Korea|publisher=|accessdate=17 Feb 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

South Korea has only granted refugee status to 60 people in its entire history. In comparison, [[South Africa]] has accepted over 35,000 refugees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2007/08/20/korea-needs-open-its-doors|title=Korea needs to open its doors - Human Rights Watch|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Malaysia ==
{{main|Racism in Malaysia}}
Malaysia is a multi–ethnic country, with [[Malay (ethnic group)|Malays]] making up the majority—close to 52% of the 28 million population.  About 30% of the population are [[Chinese Malaysians]] (Malaysians of Chinese descent) and [[Indian Malaysian]]s (Malaysians of Indian descent) comprise about 10% of the population. Government policies of positive discrimination often favour the Malay majority and the Bumiputera status, particularly in areas such as housing, finance and education. Such policies has been cited in Article 153 of the Constitution of Malaysia UMNO also promotes [[Ketuanan Melayu]], which is the idea that the ethnic Malays or Bumiputeras should get special privileges in Malaysia. Basically it was written in The Federation of Malaya Agreement signed on 21 January 1948 at King House by the Malay rulers, and by Sir Edward Gent as the representative of the British government to let Malay as the leader among three races. The Malays dominate in politics at both national and state levels, the civil service, military and security forces. The Chinese have traditionally dominated in the economy and live in large numbers in urban areas of Malaysia.

The Malay-controlled government ensures that all Bumiputras of Malay origin are given preferential treatment when it comes to the number of students placed in government universities. They are also given 7% discounts for new houses they purchase, and special Malay status reserved land in most housing settlements. Burial plots in most urban areas are for the deceased Bumiputeras, while the rest have to be cremated at such locations. All key government positions are to be held by Malays, including most sporting associations. Other forms of preferential treatment include the requirement of a minimum of a 30% Malay Bumiputera equity to be held in Listed Companies, full funding for mosques and Islamic places of worship (Islam as an official religion in Malaysia), special high earning interest trust funds for Bumiputera Malays, special share allocation for new share applications for Bumiputera Malays, and making the Malay language a compulsory examination paper to pass with such high emphasis given to it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eng.fju.edu.tw/worldlit/link/malaysia_chinese.htm|title=Chinese in Malaysia|publisher=Fu Jen University Department of English Language and Literature|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even school textbooks have been criticised as racist, especially from Chinese and Indian-type schools who adopted learning methods from their countries. "[[Interlok]]" is a 1971 Malay language novel written by Malaysian national laureate Abdullah Hussain, with Chinese groups today condemning its depiction of Chinese characters as greedy, opium-smoking lechers keen to exploit Malays for profit. Some folks was said that Chinese trying to conquer Malaysia as they did to Singapore. Indian community earlier complained over the novel's use of the word "pariah". Chinese associations said the book was not only offensive to Indians but Chinese as well, as it depicted the character Kim Lock as a "miserly opium addict and callous adulterer" and his son, Cing Huat, as "cunning, greedy, unscrupulous and someone who would sell his daughters". "Interlok" written based on the ideology of Ketuanan Melayu. The groups also condemned the "major thread" in the book, which depicts the Chinese "cheating and oppressing" Malays or as "nasty and immoral" communist guerrillas.

For Ramadan 2011, television station 8TV had some advertisements featuring a Chinese woman at a Ramadan bazaar. The condescending advertisements were pulled for being racist&lt;ref name=BBC2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-pacific-14385624|title=Malaysia's 8TV pulls 'racist' Ramadan adverts|date=3 August 2011|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=20 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; following an online uproar, and the station was expected to apologise. Instead, they claimed the Ramadan advertisements were an "honest mistake" and went on to claim that the viewers misunderstood the clips.&lt;ref name=BBC/&gt; The Ramadan advertisements – released as public service announcements (PSA) – appeared to be stereotyping Chinese people, depicting a socially inept Chinese woman embarrassing others at a Ramadan bazaar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/malaysia/8679145/Racist-Ramadan-adverts-pulled-in-Malaysia.html|title='Racist' Ramadan adverts pulled in Malaysia|author=Ian MacKinnon|date=3 August 2011|work=The Daily Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some parts of the community claimed that they were "Islamophobic", especially among the Chinese in Malaysia. Quoting Austrian philosopher Karl Popper, the station said in its Facebook note: "It is impossible to speak in such a way that you cannot be misunderstood." The act clearly shows disrespectful behaviour towards the Malaysian Muslim community and the religion itself. The PSAs highlighted the clueless behaviour of a Chinese woman played by an actor in scenes to demonstrate what might embarrass Muslim Malay hawkers and bazaar patrons alike. In one instance, the Chinese woman dressed in a sleeveless singlet, proudly showed her armpits, censored by pixels, to passersby while touching a bunch of bananas. Each PSA was soon followed by a moral lesson, advising viewers on good public behaviour. Some of these messages included "Do not be greedy and eat in public".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freemalaysiatoday.com/category/nation/2011/08/02/ramadan-ads-of-armpits-and-morality/|title=Ramadan ads: Of armpits and morality|author=Patrick Lee|date=2 August 2011|work=Free Malaysia Today|accessdate=20 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pakistan==
A strong anti-[[Bengali people|Bengali]] [[Pakistan]]i regime during the [[Bangladesh Liberation War]] were strongly motivated by anti-Bengali [[racism]] within the [[The Establishment|establishment]], especially against the Bengali Hindu minority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = O'Leary | first = Brendan | authorlink = Brendan O'Leary |author2=Thomas M. Callaghy |author3=Ian S. Lustick  | title = Right-Sizing the State: The Politics of Moving Borders P179 | origyear = 2001 | edition = 1st | publisher = Oxford University Press | isbn = 0-19-924490-1 | year = 2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Discrimination in Pakistan now is mainly based on religion,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://un.op.org/node/2178|title=Item 11: Civil and Political rights: Religious intolerance (Pakistan)|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; social status&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6933876.stm|title=BBC NEWS - South Asia - Hypocrisy of Pakistan's ruling elite|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and gender.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shvoong.com/humanities/1746727-gender-discrimination-pakistan/ Gender discrimination in Pakistan]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Philippines ==
{{main|Racism in the Philippines}}
In the Philippines, preferential treatment were given to [[Spanish people|Spaniards]] and [[Filipino mestizo|Spanish Mestizos]] during the Spanish colonization of the country. After 1898, control of the islands passed on to the new American overlords, who, together with a new generation of [[Amerasian]]s, form one of the country's social elite. Up to the present-day, descendants of White colonizers of the country still obtain a positive treatment, while in the entertainment industry, actors/actresses are mostly of part-[[White people|White]] descent.

Similarly, the status of [[Chinese Filipino|Filipinos of Chinese descent]] varied throughout the colonial powers. It is accepted generally, though, that repressive treatment toward the Chinese were practised by both Filipinos and Spaniards and/or Japanese immigrants and Americans during the colonial period. After independence on 1946, the Chinese quickly assumed some of the top posts in finance and business. There were several setbacks against the Chinese, however, such as immigration policies deemed unfair toward migrants from China during President [[Ramon Magsaysay]]'s term, as well as the limiting of hours for studying Chinese subjects in Chinese schools throughout the country, as promulgated by President [[Ferdinand Marcos]]. In addition, as recent as 1992 and 1998, there were several anti-Chinese protests led by [[Armando Ducat]], a Filipino businessman, who claimed that the Chinese rose to the top economic ladder through bribery and extortion. This has not been proven, however. To this day, there are still [[Sinophobia|anti-Chinese]] sentiments among a small minority of the Philippine population, as manifested in online forums and occasional public demonstrations.

In some ways, the Philippines is a surprisingly homogeneous society considering its multiplicity of languages, ethnicities and cultures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://countrystudies.us/philippines/35.htm | title=Historical Development of Ethnic Identities | work=Country Studies | accessdate=June 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the population is of [[Austronesian]] origin with small but economically important minorities of Chinese, White American, and Spanish descent. The Philippines is also home to an increasing number of immigrants from South Korea, India, Indonesia, Australia, the United Kingdom, Japan and other countries.

== Russia ==
{{Main|Racism in Russia}}
{{further|Liberal Democratic Party of Russia|History of the Jews in the Soviet Union|History of the Jews in Russia}}
The term "[[pogrom]]" became commonly used in English after a large-scale wave of anti-Jewish riots swept through south-western [[Russian Empire|Czarist Russia]] in 1881&amp;ndash;1884. A much bloodier wave of pogroms broke out in 1903–1906, leaving an estimated 2,000 Jews dead.  By the beginning of the 20th century, most European Jews lived in the so-called [[Pale of Settlement]], the Western frontier of the [[Russian Empire]] consisting generally of the modern-day countries of Poland, Lithuania, Belarus and neighboring regions.  Many pogroms accompanied the [[Russian Revolution|Revolution of 1917]] and the ensuing [[Russian Civil War]], an estimated 70,000 to 250,000 civilian Jews were killed in the atrocities throughout the former [[Russian Empire]]; the number of Jewish orphans exceeded 300,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-215022/anti-Semitism|title=anti-Semitism|work=Encyclopedia Britannica|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hilary L Rubinstein, Daniel C Cohn-Sherbok, Abraham J Edelheit, William D Rubinstein, ''The Jews in the Modern World'', Oxford University Press, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

Racism inside Russia is quite a modern post-[[Soviet Union|USSR]] phenomenon that has been steadily growing in the past decade. In the 2000s, [[Neo-Nazism|neo-Nazi]] groups inside [[Russia]] have risen to include as many as tens of thousands of people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title=A gathering storm of Russian thugs | url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2005/08/14/MNGUSE7N2D1.DTL | work=The San Francisco Chronicle | first=Anna | last=Badkhen | date=2005-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racism against both the Russian citizens ([[peoples of the Caucasus]], [[indigenous peoples of Siberia|indigenous peoples of Siberia and Russian Far East]], etc.) and non-Russian citizens of Africans, Central Asians, East Asians (Vietnamese, Chinese, etc.) and Europeans (Ukrainians, etc.) is an ever-increasing problem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=726|title=Racist Violence, Rhetoric Plague Russia|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Pew Global opinion poll showed that 25% of Russians had an unfavorable view of Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795 | title=A Year After Iraq War: Mistrust of America in Europe Ever Higher, Muslim Anger Persists | work=Pew Global Attitudes Project | date=2004-03-16 | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061008021739/http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795 | archivedate=October 8, 2006 | deadurl=y}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racism towards Central Asians is said to be widespread.{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

== Singapore ==
Since independence, Singapore has declared itself to be a multi-cultural society, and it is successful in being so to a large extent. One common declaration of anti-racism and the embracing of all races and religions is seen in the [[Singapore National Pledge]]. [[Racial Harmony Day]] is celebrated in Singapore to mark the progress made since the [[1964 race riots in Singapore]]. However, there were still some hints of racism in this usually racially harmonious society. These issues relate to intermarriage of different ethnic groups and the social stigma attached to these practices.

A collective cultural tendency; that is a tendency to focus on group dynamics more at a societal and individual level, this in turn leads to an increased emphasis on being part of the 'in' group and not part of the 'other'.  Many have on the identity document an ethnic classification of ''Other'', although there have been recent reforms in 2011 that allows for double-barrel ethnic identification like "Indian Chinese" or "Chinese Indian" for individuals of mixed heritage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Greater Flexibility With Implementation Of Double-Barrelled Race Option From 1 January 2011|url=http://www.ica.gov.sg/news_details.aspx?nid=12443|website=Immigration and Checkpoints Authority|accessdate=25 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is still Chinese-Malay animosity that appears to pose the biggest threat in spite of general inter-racial tolerance. The potential dangers become stark under the threat of possible Jemaah Islamiah bombings in Singapore, which could result, it is feared, in some kind of a backlash against innocent Malay [[Muslims]]. The government has put in place plans involving religious and community leaders of all races to mitigate race violence in the wake of a potential terrorist attack. A [[Racial Harmony Day]] is held every year. Schools and [[Housing Development Board]] [[housing estates]] enforce ethnic quotas based on the race populations to prevent racial enclaves. The system ensures the majority Chinese live with a certain ratio of Malays and Indians and vice versa. As a result, children grow up with at least some racial mixing both at school and their residential blocks. For many years, [[community leaders]] have been organising cross-visits to celebrate each other's cultural and religious festivals.

Nonetheless, there were an insignificant number young [[bloggers]] and commentators who have been charged under the Sedition Act for making disparaging remarks about [[race (classification of humans)|race]] and [[religion]]. One of the government's approaches to handle such 'hate speech' is to deal with expressions of extreme racism, e.g. on web sites, by way of the [[Sedition Act (Malaysia)|Sedition Act]].  This, however, curtails freedom of speech in Singapore.

Anti-foreigner sentiments have recently shot up in Singapore with house-owners and landlords refusing to rent properties to people from [[India]] and [[People's Republic of China]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=No Indians Please: House Owners advertise in Singapore |url=http://news.biharprabha.com/2014/05/no-indians-please-house-owners-advertise-in-singapore/|work=IANS|publisher=news.biharprabha.com|accessdate=2 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Cheung|first1=Helier|title='No Indians No PRCs': Singapore's rental discrimination problem|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-26832115|website=BBC News|accessdate=25 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Taiwan ==
The [[Nationality Law of the Republic of China]] has been criticized&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jidanni.org/foreigner/|title=不准作台灣人 Not  allowed to be Taiwanese|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; for its methods of determining which immigrants get citizenship.

== Thailand ==
{{main|Racism in Thailand}}

== Vietnam ==
The [[Sino-Vietnamese War]] resulted in the discrimination and consequent migration of [[Vietnam]]'s [[Hoa|ethnic Chinese]]. Many of these people fled as "[[boat people]]". In 1978-79, some 450,000 ethnic Chinese left Vietnam by boat as refugees (many officially encouraged and assisted) or were expelled across the land border with China.

== See also ==
* [[Racism by country]]
* [[Antisemitism in Asia]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{Racism topics}}
{{Asia topic|Racism in}}

[[Category:Racism by region|Asia]]
[[Category:Racism in Asia| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>