<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121119175304|523877819" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1655005" pageid="1655005" ns="0" title="White privilege"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-19T19:54:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the clothing protocol in the Vatican|Privilège du blanc}}


'''White privilege''' (or '''white skin privilege''') refers to [[Privilege (social inequality)|advantages]] that [[white people]] enjoy in all societies. It sometimes connotes unspoken advantages, which white people may not realize they have.&lt;ref&gt;Neville, H., Worthington, R., Spanierman, L. (2001).Race, Power, and Multicultural Counseling Psychology: Understanding White Privilege and Color Blind Racial Attitudes. In Ponterotto, J., Casas, M, Suzuki, L, and Alexander, C.(Eds) Handbook of Multicultural Counseling, Thousand Oaks, CA: SAGE.&lt;/ref&gt; These include cultural affirmations of one's own worth, greater presumed social status, and freedom to move, buy, work, play, and speak freely.&lt;ref name="Unpacking"&gt;McIntosh, Peggy. "Unpacking the Invisible Knapsack." Race, Class, and Gender in the United States: An Integrated Study. 2001. Paula S. Rothenberg. New York: Worth Publishers, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; White privilege also implies the right to assume the universality of one's own experiences, marking others as different or exceptional while perceiving one's self as normal. It can be be compared and combined with [[male privilege]].

Academic perspectives such as [[critical race theory]] and [[whiteness studies]] use the concept of "white privilege" to analyze how [[racism]] and [[racialized society]] affect the lives of whites. The term is often used in the United States and Europe but also applies in other places with histories of racial stratification after colonialism, such as South Africa&lt;ref name=Vice&gt;{{cite journal|last=Vice|first=Samantha|title=“How Do I Live in This Strange Place?”|journal=Journal of Social Philosophy|date=7 September 2010|volume=41|issue=3|pages=323–342|doi=10.1111/j.1467-9833.2010.01496.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Martin-McDonald|first=K|coauthors=McCarthy, A|title='Marking' the white terrain in indigenous health research: literature review.|journal=Journal of advanced nursing|date=2008 Jan|volume=61|issue=2|pages=126-33|pmid=18186904}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was popularized by Peggy McIntosh through a 1987 article titled "White Privilege: Unpacking the Invisible Knapsack". McIntosh's article suggests that white people need to understand how racial inequality includes benefits to them as well as disadvantages to others.&lt;ref&gt;Jacob Bennett, "White Privilege: A History of the Concept", Masters Thesis (approved) at Georgia State University, May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of the "white privilege" concept have argued that white people do not benefit from unfair advantages and may even be victims of [[institutionalized racism]] since minority groups benefit from race-based [[affirmative action]] programs and other special advantages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Does White Privilege Exist in America? Scholars Debate Whether Society Overlooks Minorities|url=http://abcnews.go.com/2020/story?id=2629192&amp;page=1|date=2006-11-05|author=Stossel, John|authorlink=John Stossel|coauthors=Binkley, Gena|publisher=[[ABC News]] ([[20/20]])}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
Scholars within the [[law|legal]]  and sociological studies [[List of academic disciplines|field]] of [[critical race theory]], such as Cheryl Harris&lt;ref name="Harris"&gt;{{cite journal |first=Cheryl I. |last=Harris|title=Whiteness as Property |journal=Harvard Law Review |volume=106 |issue=8|pages=1709–95 |date=June 1993 |doi=10.2307/1341787 |publisher=Harvard Law Review, Vol. 106, No. 8|jstor=1341787}}&lt;/ref&gt; and George Lipsitz,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=George |last=Lipsitz |title=The Possessive Investment in Whiteness: How White People Profit from Identity Politics
|publisher=Temple University Press |year=1998 |isbn=1-56639-635-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; have argued that "whiteness" has historically been treated more as a form of [[property]] than as a racial characteristic: In other words, as an object which has intrinsic value that must be protected by social and legal institutions.  Laws and [[mores]] concerning race (from [[apartheid]] and [[Jim Crow laws|Jim Crow]] constructions that legally separate different races to social prejudices against interracial relationships or mixed communities) serve the purpose of retaining certain advantages and privileges for whites. Because of this, academic and societal ideas about race have tended to focus solely on the disadvantages suffered by [[racial minorities]], overlooking the advantageous effects that accrue to whites.&lt;ref name="Lucal"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lucal|first=Betsy|date=July 1996|title=Oppression and Privilege: Toward a Relational Conceptualization of Race|journal=Teaching Sociology|publisher=American Sociological Association|location=Washington, D.C.|volume=24|issue=3|pages=245–55|issn=0092055X|oclc=48950428|doi=10.2307/1318739|jstor=1318739}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within an educational context, Dan J. Pence and J. Arthur Fields observe resistance to the idea that white privilege of this type exists, and suggest this resistance stems from a tendency to see inequality as a black or [[Latino]] issue. One report noted that white students often react to in-class discussions about white privilege with a continuum of behaviors ranging from outright hostility to a "wall of silence."&lt;ref name="Pence"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pence|first=Dan J.|coauthors=Fields, J. Arthur|date=April 1999|title=Teaching about Race and Ethnicity: Trying to Uncover White Privilege for a White Audience|journal=Teaching Sociology|publisher=American Sociological Association|location=Washington, D.C.|volume=27|issue=2|pages=150–8|issn=0092055X|oclc=48950428|doi=10.2307/1318701|jstor=1318701}}&lt;/ref&gt; A pair of studies on a broader population by Branscombe ''et al.'' found that framing racial issues in terms of white privilege as opposed to non-white disadvantages can produce a greater degree of racially biased responses from whites who have higher levels of racial identification. Branscombe ''et al.'' demonstrate that framing racial inequality in terms of the privileges of whites increased levels of guilt among white respondents.  Those with high racial identification were more likely to give responses which concurred with modern [[racist]] attitudes than those with low racial identification.&lt;ref name="Branscombe"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Branscombe|first=Nyla R.|coauthors=Schmitt, Michael T.; Schiffhauer, Kristin|date=2006-08-25|title=Racial Attitudes in Response to Thoughts of White Privilege|journal=European Journal of Social Psychology|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.|volume=37|issue=2|pages=203–15|url=http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/112771384/abstract?CRETRY=1&amp;SRETRY=0|accessdate=2008-07-19|doi=10.1002/ejsp.348}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the studies' authors these findings suggest that representing inequality in terms of [[outgroup (sociology)|outgroup]] disadvantage allows privileged group members to avoid the negative implications of inequality.&lt;ref name="Powell"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Powell|first=Adam A.|coauthors=Branscombe, Nyla R.; Schmitt, Michael T.|year=2005|title=Inequality as Ingroup Privilege or Outgroup Disadvantage: The Impact of Group Focus on Collective Guilt and Interracial Attitudes|journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin|publisher=Society for Personality and Social Psychology, Inc.|volume=31|issue=4|pages=508–21|url=http://psp.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/31/4/508|accessdate=2008-07-19|doi=10.1177/0146167204271713|pmid=15743985}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Heidi A. Zetzer categorizes white privilege as an "institutional and individual manifestation of racism, however indirectly or unintentionally."&lt;ref&gt;Zetzer, H.A. (2005). White Out: Privilege and Its Problems. In S.K. Anderson &amp; V.A. Middleton (eds.), Explorations in Privilege, Oppression, and Diversity (pp. 5). Belmont, California: Thomson Brooks/Cole.&lt;/ref&gt; Zetzer argues the indirectness of white privilege increases its prevalence. If people are not educated about white privilege, she argues, it is unlikely that they will take note of it. Zetzer further argues that whites who are aware of privilege suffer under the stigma of benefiting from an unfair system. Zetzer asks, "How can I see myself as a just person when I willingly participate in a system that is inherently unfair?" The guilt formed by this opinion creates a spirit of inactivity in solving the problem. "White guilt," as Zetzer deems it, is an impediment to change. Zetzer argues that honest and multicultural dialogue is the first way to build alliances which can then "transform people and systems and turn intention into action."&lt;ref&gt;Zetzer, H.A. (2005). White Out: Privilege and Its Problems. In S.K. Anderson &amp; V.A. Middleton (eds.), Explorations in Privilege, Oppression, and Diversity (pp. 13). Belmont, California: Thomson Brooks/Cole.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to James Forrest and Kevin Dunn, the privileges of being white might accrue largely to certain white ethnic and cultural groups, as opposed to white people as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Forrest |first1=James |last2=Dunn |first2=Kevin |title='Core' Culture Hegemony and Multiculturalism |journal=Ethnicities |date=June 2006 |volume=6 |number=2 |doi=10.1177/1468796806063753 |url=http://www.uws.edu.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0008/29645/A23.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; Adam A. Powell, Nyla R. Branscombe, and Michael T. Schmitt argue that people in the least successful white ethnic and cultural groups are often the ones that are disadvantaged the most from any [[affirmative action]] that attempts to take into account white privilege.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Powell |first1=Adam A. |last2= Branscombe |first2=Nyla R. |last3=Schmitt |first3=Michael T. |title=Inequality as Ingroup Privilege or Outgroup Disadvantage: The Impact of Group Focus on Collective Guilt and Interracial Attitudes |journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin |date=April 2005 |volume=31 |number=4 |doi=10.1177/0146167204271713 |url=http://data.psych.udel.edu/abelcher/Shared%20Documents/6%20General%20Diversity%20Issues%20(15)/Powell.pdf |pmid=15743985}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Lawrence Blum, Professor of Philosophy writes that white privilege analysis has been too narrow in its focus.  Specifically it has failed to acknowledge important ethnic differences, especially among whites.  And it has not adequately distinguished between "spared injustice, unjust enrichment and non-injustice-related" privileges. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=EJ813198&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=EJ813198&lt;/ref&gt;

==In the United States==

=== History ===
In his 1935 ''[[Black Reconstruction|Black Reconstruction in America]]'', [[W. E. B. Du Bois]] wrote that “in black slavery and Reconstruction” could be found “the kernel and meaning of the labor movement in the United States.” &lt;ref&gt;W. E. B. Du Bois, ''Black Reconstruction in America, 1860–1880'' (New York: Free Press, 1995 reissue of 1935 original), p. 353. ISBN 0-684-85657-3.&lt;/ref&gt;  Then, in 1965, drawing from that insight, and inspired by the Civil Rights movement, [[Theodore W. Allen]] began a pioneering forty-year analysis of “white skin privilege,” “”white race” privilege, and “white” privilege in a call he drafted for a “John Brown Commemoration Committee” that urged “White Americans who want government of the people” and “by the people” to “begin by first repudiating their white skin privileges.”&lt;ref&gt;Theodore W. Allen, “A Call . . . John Brown Memorial Pilgrimage . . . December 4, 1965,” John Brown Commemoration Committee, 1965 and Jeffrey B. Perry, "The Developing Conjuncture and Some Insights from Hubert Harrison and Theodore W. Allen on the Centrality of the Fight against White Supremacy," “Cultural Logic” 2010, at http://clogic.eserver.org/2010/2010.html&lt;/ref&gt;  The groundbreaking pamphlet, "White Blindspot," authored by Allen and Noel Ignatin [Noel Ignatiev] in the late 1960s focused on the struggle against "white skin privilege” and significantly influenced Students for a Democratic Society and sectors of the “new left.”.&lt;ref&gt;See Noel Ignatin (Ignatiev) and Ted (Theodore W.) Allen, “‘White Blindspot’ &amp;“Can White Workers Radicals Be Radicalized?’” (Detroit: The Radical Education Project and New York: NYC Revolutionary Youth Movement, 1969) and Perry, "The Developing Conjuncture and Some Insights from Hubert Harrison and Theodore W. Allen. . . "&lt;/ref&gt; In 1974-1975 Allen extended his analysis to the colonial period with his ground-breaking "Class Struggle and the Origin of Racial Slavery: The Invention of the White Race" in 1974/1975,&lt;ref&gt;Theodore W. Allen, Class Struggle and the Origin of Racial Slavery: The Invention of the White Race (Hoboken: Hoboken Education Project, 1975), republished in 2006 with an “Introduction” by Jeffrey B. Perry at Center for the Study of Working Class Life, SUNY, Stony Brook, at http://clogic.eserver.org/2006/allen.html.&lt;/ref&gt; which ultimately grew into his seminal two-volume "The Invention of the White Race" in 1994 and 1997.&lt;ref&gt;Theodore W. Allen, The Invention of the White Race, Vol. I: Racial Oppression and Social Control (New York: Verso, 1994, ISBN 00086091660X {{Please check ISBN|reason=Invalid length.}}) and Vol. II: The Origin of Racial Oppression in Anglo-America (New York: Verso, 1997, ISBN 1-85984-076-0).&lt;/ref&gt; Allen’s work consistently argued that “white” privileges were not only not in the interests of direct victims of white supremacy, they were also not in the class interests of working-class European-Americans and that they should be struggled against and “repudiated” by European-Americans. 

In his 1935 ''[[Black Reconstruction|Black Reconstruction in America]]'', [[W. E. B. Du Bois]] first described the "psychological wages" of whiteness:

&lt;blockquote&gt;It must be remembered that the white group of laborers, while they received a low wage, were compensated in part by a sort of public and psychological wage. They were given public deference and titles of courtesy because they were white. They were admitted freely with all classes of white people to public functions, public parks, and the best schools. The police were drawn from their ranks, and the courts, dependent on their votes, treated them with such leniency as to encourage lawlessness. Their vote selected public officials, and while this had small effect upon the economic situation, it had great effect upon their personal treatment and the deference shown them. White schoolhouses were the best in the community, and conspicuously placed, and they cost anywhere from twice to ten times as much per capita as the colored schools. The newspapers specialized on news that flattered the poor whites and almost utterly ignored the Negro except in crime and ridicule.&lt;ref&gt;W. E. B. Du Bois, ''Black Reconstruction in America, 1860–1880'' (New York: Free Press, 1995 reissue of 1935 original), pp. 700–701. ISBN 0-684-85657-3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This concept was later taken up by David Roediger in his 1991 book, ''The Wages of Whiteness: Race and the Making of the American Working Class''.&lt;ref&gt;''
[http://www.historymatters.appstate.edu/documents/wagesofwhiteness.pdf The Wages of Whiteness: Race and the Making of the American Working Class]'' a book review.&lt;/ref&gt;  Theorists associated with the journal ''[[Race Traitor (publication)|Race Traitor]]'', such as editor [[Noel Ignatiev]], argue that whiteness (as a marker of a social status within the United States) is conferred upon people in exchange for an expectation of loyalty to an oppressive social order. This loyalty has taken a variety of forms over time: suppression of slave rebellions, support of whites-only [[trade union|union]]s, and promotion for police brutality. Like currency, the value of this privilege depends on the reliability of a white appearance as a marker for social consent. These theorists argue that with enough "counterfeit whites" resisting racism and capitalism, the privilege of whiteness will be withdrawn and prompt an era of social redefinition.{{clarify|date=December 2010}} Without such a period, they argue, progress towards social justice is impossible.

The theory of white privilege in America may be seen as having its roots in the system of legalized discrimination that existed for much of American history.{{Clarify|date=January 2010}}&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book|last=Williams |first=Linda Faye
|title=Constraint Of Race: Legacies Of White Skin Privilege In America
|publisher=Penn State
|year=2004 |isbn=0-271-02535-2}}
&lt;/ref&gt; In her book ''Privilege Revealed: How Invisible Preference Undermines America'', Stephanie M. Wildman writes that many Americans who advocate a merit-based, race-free worldview do not acknowledge the systems of privilege which have benefited them. For example, many Americans rely on a social or financial inheritance from previous generations, an inheritance unlikely to be forthcoming if one's ancestors were slaves.&lt;ref name="Wildman"&gt;{{cite book|last=Wildman|first=Stephanie M.|coauthors=Armstrong, Margalynne; Davis, Adrienne D.; Grillo, Trina;|title=Privilege Revealed: How Invisible Preference Undermines America|publisher=NYU Press|location=New York|year=1996|isbn=0-8147-9303-7|url=http://books.google.com/?id=LK-aQDstH6kC&amp;dq=Privilege+Revealed:+How+Invisible+Preference+Undermines+America&amp;printsec=frontcover|accessdate=2008-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whites were sometimes afforded opportunities and benefits that were unavailable to others. In the middle of the 20th century, the government subsidized white homeownership through the [[Federal Housing Administration]], but not homeownership by minorities.&lt;ref name="Massey"&gt;{{cite book|last=Massey|first=Douglas|coauthors=Denton, Nancy|title=American Apartheid: Segregation and the Making of the Underclass|publisher=Harvard University Press|date=1998-01-15|isbn=0-674-01821-4|accessdate=2008-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some social scientists also suggest that the historical processes of [[suburbanization]] and decentralization are instances of white privilege that have contributed to contemporary patterns of [[environmental racism]].&lt;ref name="Pulido"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pulido|first=Laura|date=March 2000|title=Rethinking Environmental Racism: White Privilege and Urban Development in Southern California|journal=Annals of the Association of American Geographers|publisher=Blackwell Publishing|volume=90|issue=1|pages=12–40|issn=0004-5608|url=http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/bpl/anna/2000/00000090/00000001/art00002;jsessionid=3rmbt81dt5utk.alice|accessdate=2008-07-19|doi=10.1111/0004-5608.00182|format= &amp;ndash; &lt;sup&gt;[http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=author%3APulido+intitle%3ARethinking+Environmental+Racism%3A+White+skin+Privilege+and+Urban+Development+in+Southern+California&amp;as_publication=Annals+of+the+Association+of+American+Geographers&amp;as_ylo=&amp;as_yhi=&amp;btnG=Search Scholar search]&lt;/sup&gt;}} {{Dead link|date=May 2009}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some historians and authors, including Noel Ignatiev and Karen Brodkin, discuss the historical trajectory from exclusion to acceptance of Irish and Jewish émigrés in the late 19th and early 20th centuries in terms of white privilege. At the end of the 20th century two sources saw a system of advantage for white people in areas such as housing, salaries, access to employment (especially to positions of power), access to education, even life expectancy.&lt;ref name="Farley"&gt;{{cite book|last=Farley|first=Reynolds|title=Race in America: The Struggle for Equality|editor=Hill, Herbert; Jones Jr, James E.|publisher=University of Wisconsin Press|location=Madison|pages=197–233|chapter=9|url=http://books.google.com/?id=cx55JM9J3RQC&amp;dq=Race+in+America:+The+Struggle+for+equality&amp;printsec=frontcover|isbn=0-299-13424-5|date=May 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Tatum"&gt;{{cite book| first=Beverly Daniel |last=Tatum |authorlink=Beverly Daniel Tatum |title=Why are all the Black Kids Sitting Together in the Cafeteria? And Other Conversations About Race |location=New York |publisher=Basic Books|date=1999-06-18 |isbn=978-0-465-09127-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sociologists in the American Mosaic Project report widespread belief in the United States that "prejudice and discrimination &lt;nowiki&gt;[in favor of whites]&lt;/nowiki&gt; create a form of white privilege." According to their 2003 poll this view was affirmed by 59% of white respondents, 83% of Blacks, and 84% of Hispanics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |work=American Mosaic Project
|publisher=University of Minnesota
|url=http://www.racialequitytools.org/resourcefiles/uminnesota.pdf
|title=The Role of Prejudice and Discrimination in Americans’ Explanations of Black Disadvantage and White Privilege
|year=2006 |accessdate=June 15, 2010| format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wealth===
According to Roderick Harrison "wealth is a measure of cumulative advantage or disadvantage" and "the fact that black and Hispanic wealth is a fraction of white wealth also reflects a history of discrimination".&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/18/national/18wealth.html Study Says White Families' Wealth Advantage Has Grown]." ''New York Times'' 18 Oct. 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Whites have historically had more opportunities to accumulate wealth.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}} Some of the institutions of wealth creation amongst American citizens were open exclusively to whites{{citation needed|date=March 2011}}. Similar differentials applied to the [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security Act]] (which excluded agricultural and domestic workers, sectors that then included most black workers),&lt;ref&gt;Ira Katznelson, ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=cfhneJPcD38C&amp;pg=PA43 When Affirmative Action Was White]'', p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; rewards to military officers, and the educational benefits offered to returning soldiers after World War II.&lt;ref&gt;Ira Katznelson, ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=cfhneJPcD38C&amp;pg=PA114 When Affirmative Action Was White]'', p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt; An analyst of the phenomenon, [[Thomas Shapiro]], professor of law and social policy at Brandeis University argues, "The wealth gap is not just a story of merit and achievement, it's also a story of the historical legacy of race in the United States."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/15704759|title=Census Report: Broad Racial Disparities Persist|date=2006-11-14|publisher=MSNBC|accessdate=2008-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the past 40 years there has been less formal discrimination in America; the inequality in wealth between racial groups however, is still extant.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}} George Lispsitz asserts that because wealthy whites were able to pass along their wealth in the form of inheritances and transformative assets (inherited wealth which lifts a family beyond their own achievements), white{{which|date=December 2010}} Americans continually accrue advantages.&lt;ref name="LispsitzInheritance"&gt;"Young whites can often rely on gifts and bequests from family members for transformative assets that help build wealth ... One in four white families receives a bequest upon the death of a relative compared with only one in twenty black families." George Lipsitz, ''The Possessive Investment in Whiteness: How White People Profit from Identity Politics'', Temple University Press, 2006, p. 107-08.&lt;/ref&gt; Pre-existing disparities in wealth are exacerbated by tax policies that reward investment over waged income, subsidize mortgages, and subsidize private sector developers.&lt;ref name="Lipsitz"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lipsitz|first=George|date=September 1995|title=The Possessive Investment in Whiteness: Racialized Social Democracy and the "White" Problem in American Studies|journal=American Quarterly|publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press|volume=47|issue=3|pages=369–87|doi=10.2307/2713291|jstor=2713291}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thomas Shapiro argues that wealth is passed along from generation to generation, giving whites a better "starting point" in life than other races. According to Shapiro many whites receive financial assistance from their parents allowing them to live beyond their income. This, in turn, enables them to buy houses and major assets which aid in the accumulation of wealth. Since houses in white neighborhoods appreciate faster, even African Americans who are able to overcome their "starting point" are unlikely to accumulate wealth as fast as whites. Shapiro asserts this is a continual cycle from which whites consistently benefit.&lt;ref name="Shapiro"&gt;{{cite book |first=Thomas M. |last=Shapiro |title=The Hidden Cost of Being African American; How Wealth Perpetuates Inequality |location=New York |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-518138-8|date=2003-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; These benefits also have effects on schooling and other life opportunities.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

[[Peggy McIntosh]], co-director of the SEED Project on Inclusive Curriculum, posits that white people in the United States can be sure that race is not a factor when they are audited by the IRS.&lt;ref name="Unpacking"&gt;McIntosh, Peggy. "Unpacking the Invisible Knapsack." Race, Class, and Gender in the United States: An Integrated Study. 2001. Paula S. Rothenberg. New York: Worth Publishers, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Justice ===
{{expand section|date=December 2010}}
A 2002 [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]] survey found that, although the likelihood of being [[Traffic stop|stopped]] by police did not differ significantly between white drivers and other races, black or Latino drivers were three times more likely to be searched than white drivers.&lt;ref&gt;Matthew R. Durose, Erica L. Schmitt and Patrick A. Langan, Contacts Between Police and the Public: Findings from the 2002 National Survey. U.S. Department of Justice, (Bureau of Justice Statistics), April 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Young white offenders are likely to receive lighter punishments than minorities in America. Black youth arrested for drug possession for the first time are incarcerated at a rate that is forty-eight times greater than the rate for white youth.&lt;ref&gt;"Young White Offenders get lighter treatment", 2000. The Tennessean. April 26: 8A.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Human Rights Watch, 2000. Punishment and Prejudice: Racial Disparities in the War on Drugs. DC: May, Volume 12, No. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; Incarceration rates are much higher among blacks and Hispanics than among whites. In 2007, the incarceration rate was 4,618 per 100,000 for black men and 1,747 per 100,000 for Hispanic men, compared to 773 per 100,000 for white men&lt;ref&gt;William J. Sabol and Heather Couture, Bureau of Justice Statistics, Prison Inmates at Midyear 2007 (Washington, DC: US Department of Justice, June 2008), NCJ221944, p. 8 
[http://bjs.ojp.usdoj.gov/content/pub/pdf/pim07.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Employment and economics ===
Racialized employment networks can benefit whites at the expense of blacks.&lt;ref name="Royster"&gt;{{cite book |first=Deirdre A. |last=Royster |title=Race and the Invisible Hand |location=Los Angeles |publisher=University of California Press |isbn=0-520-23951-2 |year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a study published in 2003, sociologist Deirdre A. Royster compared black and white males who graduated from the same school with the same skills.  In looking at their success with school-work transition and working experiences, she found that white graduates were more often employed in skilled trades, earned more, held higher status positions, received more promotions and experienced shorter periods of unemployment. Since all other factors were similar, the differences in employment experiences were attributed to race.  Royster concluded that the primary cause of these racial differences was due to [[social networking]]. The concept of "who you know" seemed just as important to these graduates as "what you know."

Since older white males predominantly control blue-collar trades, they are more likely to offer varying forms of assistance to those in their social network, often other whites.{{Citation needed|reason=unsubstantiated claim|date=July 2012}} Assistance can be anything from job vacancy information, referrals, direct job recruitment, formal and informal training, and vouching behavior and leniency in supervision.{{Citation needed|reason=speculation by author without source|date=July 2012}} Royster argues that this assistance, disproportionately available to whites, is an advantage that often puts black men at a disadvantage in the employment sector. According to Royster, "these ideologies provide a contemporary deathblow to working-class black men's chances of establishing a foothold in the traditional trades."&lt;ref name="Royster" /&gt;

This concept is similar to the theory created by [[Mark Granovetter]] which analyzes the importance of social networking and [[interpersonal ties]] with his paper ''"The Strength of Weak Ties"'' and his other economic sociology work.

Other research shows that there is a correlation between a person's name and his or her likelihood of receiving a call back for a job interview. Marianne Bertrand and Sendhil Mullainathan found in field experiment in Boston and Chicago that people with "white-sounding" names are 50% more likely to receive a call back than people with "black-sounding" names, despite equal résumé quality between the two racial groups.&lt;ref name="Bertrand"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bertrand|first=Marianne |coauthors=Mullainathan, Sendhil|date=September 2004|title=Are Emily and Greg More Employable Than Lakisha and Jamal? A Field Experiment in Labor Market Discrimination|journal=American Economic Review|volume=94|issue=4|pages=991–1013|url=http://www.aeaweb.org/articles.php?doi=10.1257/0002828042002561|doi=10.1257/0002828042002561|accessdate=2008-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; White Americans are more likely than black Americans to have their business loan applications approved, even when other factors such as credit records are comparable.&lt;ref name="Bates"&gt;{{cite book|last=Bates|first=Timothy|coauthors=Austin Turner, Margery |title=Minority Business Development: Identiﬁcation and Measurement of Discriminatory Barriers|editor=Fix, Michael E.; Austin Turner, Margery |publisher=Urban Institute|location=Washington, D.C|date=March 1998|series=A National Report Card on Discrimination in America: The Role of Testing|chapter=5|isbn=978-0-87766-696-7|url=http://www.urban.org/url.cfm?ID=308024|accessdate=2008-07-18}} at p. 104&lt;/ref&gt;

Black and Latino college graduates are less likely than white graduates to end up in a management position even when other factors such as age, experience, and academic records are similar.&lt;ref name="Williams"&gt;{{cite book|last=Williams|first=Linda Faye|title=The Constraint of Race: Legacies of White Skin Privilege in America|publisher=Pennsylvania State University Press|location=University Park, Pennsylvania|date=2004-08-30|isbn=0-271-02535-2|url=http://www.psupress.org/books/titles/0-271-02253-1.html|accessdate=2008-07-18|page=429}}fig. 7.1, p. 359&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Income Gaps Persist Among Races|last=Hartnett|first=William M.|date=2003-10-20|publisher=Palm Beach Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Mason"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Mason|first=Patrick L.|date=May–June, 1998|title=Race, Cognitive Ability, and Wage Inequality|journal=Challenge|volume=41|issue=3|pages=62–81|issn=1077193X |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1093/is_n3_v41/ai_20809842|accessdate=2008-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Housing===
&lt;!-- {{Contradict|about=statistics regarding housing opportunities|date=August 2008}} Statistics can seem as if they contradict themselves, however there doesn't appear to be a contradiction in this section. If one remains, please renew the contradiction request, or feel free to fix it. --&gt;
Discrimination in housing policies was formalized in 1934 under the Federal Housing Act which provided government credit to private lending for home buyers.  Within the Act, the Federal Housing Agency had the authority to channel all the money to white home buyers instead of minorities.  The FHA also channeled money away from inner-city neighborhoods after World War II and instead placed it in the hands of white home buyers who would move into segregated suburbs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book  |first=Paula S. |last=Rothenberg |year=2005 |title=White Privilege |location=New York |publisher=Worth Publishers |isbn=0-7167-8733-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;  These practices and others, intensified attitudes of segregation and inequality.

But "most white families have acquired their net worth from the appreciation of property that they secured under conditions of special privilege in a discriminatory housing market."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book  |first=Paula S. |last=Rothenberg |year=2005 |title=White Privilege |location=New York |publisher=Worth Publishers |page=77 |isbn=0-7167-8733-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This net worth accumulation assists in placing whites in more favorable conditions to receive low interest loans, mortgages and financial assistance in the housing market.

Chip Smith paints a quick picture of some additional ways he views whites as privileged:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Chip |last=Smith |year=2007 |title=The Cost of Privilege |location= Largo, Maryland |publisher=Linemark Printing, Inc.|isbn=0-9791828-0-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Whites are offered more choices; 60%–90% of housing units shown to whites are not brought to the attention of blacks.
*72.1% of whites own their own home opposed to 48.1% for African Americans
*46% of whites had help from their family in making down payments on homes compared to 12% for African Americans
*Whites are half as likely to be turned down for a mortgage or home improvement loan
*Whites pay on average a 8.12% interest rate on their mortgage, lower than the 8.44% African Americans pay on average
*The median home equity for whites is $58,000 compared to $40,000 for African Americans

=== Education ===
According to Wildman, education policies in the US have contributed to the construction and reinforcement of white privilege.&lt;ref&gt;Wildman, Stephanie M. "The Persistence of White Privilege." 18 Mar 2010. &lt;[https://law.wustl.edu/journal/18/p245Wildmanbookpages.pdf https://law.wustl.edu/journal/18/p245Wildmanbookpages.pdf]&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; Wildman argues that even schools that appear to be integrated often segregate students based on abilities. This can increase white students' initial educational advantage, magnifying the "unequal classroom experience of African American students" and minorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Thomas |last=Shapiro |year=2004 |title=The Hidden Cost of Being African American; How Wealth Perpetuates Inequality |location=New York |publisher=Oxford University Press |page=144 |isbn=978-0-19-518138-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is argued that the material that black and other minority children are tested on in school is  often culturally biased, not taking into consideration dialect and other differences between populations. Williams and Rivers (1972b) showed that test instructions in Standard English disadvantaged the black child and that if the language of the test is put in familiar labels without training or coaching, the child's performances on the tests increase significantly.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, R.L. and Rivers, L.W. (1972b). The use of standard and nonstandard English in testing black children. As presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Psychological Association&lt;/ref&gt; According to Cadzen a child's language development should be evaluated in terms of his progress toward the norms for his particular speech community.&lt;ref&gt;Cadzen, C.B. (1966). Subcultural Differences in Child Language: An Inter-disciplinary Review. Merrill–Palmer Quarterly, 1966, 12 pp. 185–214&lt;/ref&gt; Other studies using sentence repetition tasks found that, at both third and fifth grades, white subjects repeated Standard English sentences significantly more accurately than black subjects, while black subjects repeated nonstandard English sentences significantly more accurately than white subjects.&lt;ref name="Marwit"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Marwit|first=Samuel J.|coauthors=Walker, Elaine F.; Marwit, Karen L.|date=December 1977|title=Reliability of Standard English Differences among Black and White Children at Second, Fourth, and Seventh Grades|journal=Child Development|publisher=Blackwell Publishing on behalf of the Society for Research in Child Development|volume=48|issue=4|pages=1739–42|doi=10.2307/1128548|jstor=1128548}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Janet E. Helms traditional psychological and academic assessment is based on skills that are considered important within white, western, middle-class culture, but which may not be salient or valued within African-American culture.&lt;ref&gt;Helms, J.E. (1997) The triple quandary of race, culture, and social class in standardized cognitive ability testing. In D.P. Flanagan, J.L. Genshaft, &amp; P.L. Harrison (Eds.), contemporary intellectual assessment: theories, tests, and issues (pp.517–532). New York: Guilford Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Helms | first1 = J.E. | year = 1992 | title = Why is there no study of cultural equivalence in standardized cognitive ability testing? | url = | journal = American Psychologist | volume = 47 | issue = | pages = 1083–1101 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When tests' stimuli are more culturally pertinent to the experiences of African Americans, performance improves.&lt;ref&gt;Hayles, V.R. (1991). African American Strengths: a survey of empirical findings. In R.L. Jones (Ed.), Black Psychology (3rd ed., pp. 379–400). Berkeley, California: Cobb &amp; Henry Publishers.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Williams, R.L. and Rivers, L.W. (1972b) The use of standard and nonstandard English in testing black children. A presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Psychological Association&lt;/ref&gt; However, white privilege critics argue that the in K-12 education, students academic progress are measured on nation-wide standardized tests which reflect national standards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Common set of school standards to be proposed|first=Nick|last=Anderson|work=Washington Post|page=A1|date=March 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;But see, {{cite web|url=http://www.fairtest.org/joint%20statement%20civil%20rights%20grps%2010-21-04.html|title= Joint Organizational Statement on No Child Left Behind (NCLB) Act|date=2004-10-21|accessdate=2008-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Educational inequality is also a consequence of housing.  Since most states determine school funding based on property taxes,{{citation needed|date=December 2010}} schools in wealthier neighborhoods receive more funding per student.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}  As home values in white neighborhoods are higher than minority neighborhoods,{{citation needed|date=December 2010}} local schools receive more funding via property taxes. This will ensure better technology in predominantly white schools, smaller class sizes and better quality teachers, giving white students opportunities for a better education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Erin E. |last=Kelly |year=1995 |title=All Students Are Not Created Equal: The Inequitable Combination of Property Tax-Based School Finance Systems and Local Control |journal=Duke Law Journal |volume=45 |issue=2 |pages=397–435 |doi=10.2307/1372907 |publisher=Duke Law Journal, Vol. 45, No. 2 |jstor=1372907 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The vast majority of schools placed on academic probation as part of district accountability efforts are majority African-American and low-income.&lt;ref&gt;Diamond, John B. &amp; James P. Spillane. (2004) "High Stakes Accountability in Urban Elementary Schools: Challenging or Reproducing Inequality?" Teachers College Record, Special Issue on Testing, Teaching, and Learning. 106(6): 1140–1171.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Congress enacted the [[No Child Left Behind Act]] of 2001 to address such school performance disparities. That act provides for a large increase in federal school aid to address property tax disparities and gives parents the right to switch schools if their neighborhood school fails to progress to meet national performance standards.

Inequalities in wealth and housing allow a higher proportion of white parents the option to move to better school districts or afford to put their children in private schools if they don’t approve of the neighborhood's schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Thomas |last=Shapiro |year=2004 |title=The Hidden Cost of Being African American; How Wealth Perpetuates Inequality |location=New York |publisher=Oxford University Press |page=157 |isbn=978-0-19-518138-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Minority students are less likely to be placed in honors classes, even when justified by test scores.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, Rebecca. 1998. Education and Race. Oakland: Applied Research Center: 48–9; Fischer, Claude S. et al., 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Inequality by Design: Cracking the Bell Curve Myth. Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press: 163&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Leonard Steinhorn|Steinhorn, Leonard]] and Barabara Diggs-Brown, 1999. By the Color of Our Skin: The Illusion of Integration and the Reality of Race. NY: Dutton: 95-6.&lt;/ref&gt; Visible minority students are more likely than white students to be suspended or expelled from school, even though rates of serious school rule violations do not differ significantly by race.&lt;ref&gt;Skiba, Russell J. et al., The Color of Discipline: Sources of Racial and Gender Disproportionality in School Punishment. Indiana Education Policy Center, Policy Research Report SRS1, June 2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Youth Risk Behavior Surveillance System: Youth 2003, Online Comprehensive Results, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Adult education specialist Elaine Manglitz argues the educational system in America has deeply-entrenched biases in favor of the white majority in evaluation, curricula, and power relations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last=Manglitz |first=E |year=2003 |title=Challenging white privilege in adult education: a critical review of the literature |journal=Adult Education Quarterly |volumen=53 |issue=2 |pages=119–134 |doi=10.1177/0741713602238907 |volume=53}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In discussing unequal test scores between public school students, opinion columnist Matt Rosenberg laments the Seattle Public Schools' emphasis on "institutional racism" and "white privilege": 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The disparity is not simply a matter of color: School District data indicate income, English-language proficiency and home stability are also important correlates to achievement...By promoting the "white privilege" canard and by designing a student indoctrination plan, the Seattle School District is putting retrograde, leftist politics ahead of academics, while the perpetrators of "white privilege" are minimizing the capabilities of minorities.&lt;ref name="STRosen"&gt;Rosenberg, Matt (2007-04-11), "Putting politics ahead of kids". ''The Seattle Times'', [http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/opinion/2003661182_matt11.html].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Conservatism in the United States|Conservative]] scholar and opponent of affirmative action programs, [[Shelby Steele]] at the [[Hoover Institution]], believes that the effects of white privilege are exaggerated. Steele argues that blacks may incorrectly blame their personal failures on white oppression. He also argues that there are many "minority privileges": "If I'm a black high school student today... there are white American institutions, universities, hovering over me to offer me opportunities: Almost every institution has a [[multiculturalism|diversity]] committee... There is a hunger in this society to do right racially, to not be racist."&lt;ref name=abc&gt;{{cite news|title=Does White Privilege Exist in America? Scholars Debate Whether Society Overlooks Minorities|url=http://abcnews.go.com/2020/story?id=2629192&amp;page=1|date=2006-11-05|author=Stossel, John|authorlink=John Stossel|coauthors=Binkley, Gena|publisher=[[ABC News]] ([[20/20]])}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Self-image ===
[[Beverly Daniel Tatum]] writes that most white people do not think to [[self-image|describe themselves]] as "white" when listing descriptive terms about themselves, whereas people of color usually use racial or ethnic identity descriptors. Tatum suggests this is because the elements of one's identity that are congruent with the dominant culture are so normalized and reflected back at one that one is apt to take such traits for granted. This is not the case for identity aspects of those who are defined as "other" by the dominant culture, whether it be on the basis of race, gender, sexual orientation, religion, or other microcultural aspects.&lt;ref name="Tatum"/&gt; The true reasons behind this occurrence are unknown, but may also be due to many different unspoken psychological effects on minorities and majorities alike, whether it be pride, shame, or an environmental stimulation such as a rally. Tatum writes that dominant [[microculture]]s (in this case, white people) set the parameters in which "subordinate" microcultures operate. Subordinate groups are often labeled as substandard in significant ways: e.g., blacks have historically been characterized as less intelligent than whites.&lt;ref name="Tatum"/&gt; Subordinates are also defined as being innately incapable of being able to perform the preferred roles in society.&lt;ref name="Tatum"/&gt; 

[[Alik Shahadah]] claims that the image of Africa imposed on the world are those created and controlled by white forces and that globalization is therefore in his view not only an imposition of products but also of ideas and ideals, at the expense of the broader human diversity.&lt;ref name="The Removal of Agency from Africa"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.africanholocaust.net/news_ah/agencyandafrica.htm | title= The Removal of Agency from Africa  | publisher=[[Owen Alik Shahadah]], African Holocaust Society | accessdate=2007-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Pambazuka Online"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.pambazuka.org/en/category/features/42249 | title= Pambazuka Online | publisher=[[Pambazuka]] | African agency.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of [[skin whitening]] treatments by [[people of color]] has been linked to the benefits of white privilege. According to several theorists the relationship between white privilege and skin whitening is explained by [[colorism]] and [[colonial mentality]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Brown is Beautiful|url=http://www.americanchronicle.com/articles/viewArticle.asp?articleID=11261|author=Llewelyn Muriel Austria-del Rosario}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Mestizaje and Self-Hate|url=http://www.mexika.org/Mestizo.html|author=Victor Mejia}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=April 2008}}&lt;ref name="The Removal of Agency from Africa"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Pambazuka Online"/&gt;

== In South Africa==
[[File:Population registration certificate South Africa 1988.jpg|thumb|Registration certificate identifies a person as white]]
White privilege was legally enshrined in South Africa through [[apartheid]], which lasted formally into the 1990s. Under apartheid, racial privilege was not only socially meaningful—it became bureaucratically regulated. Laws such as the 1950 [[Population Registration Act, 1950|Population Registration Act]] established criteria to officially classify South Africans by race: White, Coloured (mixed), or Black.&lt;ref&gt;Deborah Posel, "Race as Common Sense: Racial Classification in Twentieth-Century South Africa", ''African Studies Review'' 44 (2), September 2001; accessed [http://www.jstor.org/stable/525576 via JStor].&lt;/ref&gt;

Many scholars argue that 'whiteness' still corresponds to a set of social advantages in South Africa, and conventionally refer to these advantages as "white privilege". The system of white privilege applies both to the way an individual is treated by others and to a set of behaviors, affects, and thoughts, which can be learned and reinforced. These elements of "whiteness" establish social status and guarantee advantages for some people, without directly relying on skin color or other aspects of a person's appearance.&lt;ref name=Vice/&gt; White privilege in South Africa has small-scale effects, such as preferential treatment for people who appear white in public, and large-scale effects, such as the over-fivefold difference in average per-capita income for people identified as white or black.&lt;ref&gt;Sally Matthews, "[http://mg.co.za/article/2011-09-12-inherited-or-earned-advantage Inherited or earned advantage?]", ''Mail &amp; Guardian'', 12 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; 

"Afrikaner whiteness" has also been described as a partially subordinate identity, relative to the British Empire, "disgraced" further by the end of apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;Melissa E. Steyn, "Rehabilitating a whiteness disgraced: Afrikaner white talk in post‐apartheid South Africa", ''Communication Quarterly'' 52(2); accessed [http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01463370409370187#preview via T&amp;F], DOI: 10.1080/01463370409370187.&lt;/ref&gt; Some white South Africans fear that they will suffer from "[[reverse racism]]" at the hands of the country's newly empowered majority.&lt;ref&gt;Samantha Vice, "[http://mg.co.za/article/2011-09-02-why-my-opinions-on-whiteness-touched-a-nerve/ Why my opinions on whiteness touched a nerve]", ''Mail &amp; Guardian'', 2 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==In Australia==
[[File:Ac.whiteaustralia.jpg|thumbnail|left|1906 "White Australia" badge reflects [[White Australia policy|policies]] intended to maintain white supremacy in Australia]]
White privilege in Australia parallels the pattern of dominance seen elsewhere in colonialism. [[Indigenous Australians]] were excluded from the process of creating the Australian Federation, and its early laws restricted the freedoms for people of colour. Indigenous people were governed by an "Aborigines Protection Board" as a separate class of citizens.&lt;ref name=Perera2005&gt;Suvendrini Perera, "[http://www.acrawsa.org.au/files/ejournalfiles/98SuvendriniPerera.pdf Who Will I Become? The multiple formations of Australian whiteness]", ''Australian Critical Race and Whiteness Studies Association Journal'' [http://www.acrawsa.org.au/ejournal/?id=27 1], 2005&lt;/ref&gt; [[Indigenous Australians]] report feeling discriminated against, for example by shopkeepers and real estate agents. News media are geared towards white people and their interests.&lt;ref&gt;Deirdre Howard-Wagner, "[http://sydney.edu.au/arts/sociology_social_policy/docs/TASA_Howard-Wagner_The_Performance_of_Whiteness_accounts_of_marginalisation_and_racism_in_Newcastle.pdf The performance of whiteness: accounts of Aboriginal marginalization and racism in Newcastle]"; in ''The Future of Sociology'', ed. Lockie et al., Australian Sociological Association, December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; White neighborhoods are identified as "good quality", while "ethnic" neighborhoods may become stigmatized, degraded, and neglected.&lt;ref name=Lobo&gt;Michele Lobo, "Re-Imagining Citizenship in Suburban Australia", ''ACRAWSA e-journal'' 6(1), 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; 

White people are seen presumptively as "Australian", and as prototypical citizens.&lt;ref name=Lobo/&gt;&lt;ref name=Ganley/&gt; Indeed, a major part of white Australian privilege is the ability to be in Australia itself, while excluding non-white outsiders.&lt;ref&gt;Catherine Koerner, "[http://www.acrawsa.org.au/files/ejournalfiles/3acrawsa613.pdf Whose Security? How white possession is reinforced in everyday speech about asylum seekers]", ''''ACRAWSA e-journal'' [http://www.acrawsa.org.au/ejournal/?id=1 6(1)], 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Indigenous Australians]] are welcomed to participate in a "multiculturalism" that celebrates their stories and artwork—however, they are not allowed to [[History wars|challenge the authority]] of white society, or the narrative of European colonizers as peaceful settlers. Thus, white privilege in Australia involves the ability to define the limits of what can be included in a "multicultural" society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Larbalestier|first=Jan|title=White Over Black: Discourses of Whiteness in Australian Culture|url=http://www.borderlands.net.au/vol3no2_2004/larbalestier_white.htm|work=Borderlands e-Journal|accessdate=9 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Deirdre Howard-Wagner, "'[http://sydney.edu.au/arts/sociology_social_policy/docs/Practices_of_Inclusiveness.pdf Practices of Inclusiveness' in Newcastle: protocols of whiteness, Indigenous protocols and power relations]", TASA Conference, December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Maryrose Casey, "[http://www.acrawsa.org.au/files/ejournalfiles/177CRWS201281Casey.pdf Colonisation, Notions of Authenticity and Aboriginal Australian Performance]", ''Critical Race and Whiteness Studies'' [http://www.acrawsa.org.au/ejournal/?id=54 8], 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Indigenous Studies in Australian Universities remains controlled by white people, hires many white professors, and does not always embrace political changes that benefit indigenous people or respect their sovereignty.&lt;ref&gt;Brownwyn Fredericks, "[http://www.acrawsa.org.au/files/ejournalfiles/45acrawsa518.pdf The Epistemology That Maintains White Race Privilege, Power and Control of Indigenous Studies and Indigenous Peoples' Participation in Universities]", ''ACRAWSA e-journal'' [http://www.acrawsa.org.au/ejournal/?id=8 5(1)], 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

For Australian whites, another aspect of privilege is the ability to identify with a global diaspora of other white people in the United States, Europe, and elsewhere. This privilege contrasts with the enforced separation of Indigenous Australians from other indigenous peoples in southeast Asia.&lt;ref&gt;Holly Randell-Moon, "[http://www.acrawsa.org.au/files/ejournalfiles/editorials/54CRWSRandell-Moon2012.pdf Racial Legitimations and the Unbearable Whiteness of Being]", ''Critical Race and Whiteness Studies'' [http://www.acrawsa.org.au/ejournal/?id=54 8], 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Perera2005/&gt; Global political issues such as climate change are framed in terms of white actors and effects on white countries.&lt;ref&gt;Lars Jensen, "[http://www.ub.edu/dpfilsa/jeasa22jensen9.pdf The whiteness of climate change]", ''Journal of the European Association of Studies on Australia'' 2(2), 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

White privilege varies across places and situations. Ray Minniecon, director of Crossroads Aboriginal Ministries, described the city of [[Sydney]] specifically as "the most alien and inhospitable place of all to Aboriginal culture and people."&lt;ref&gt;Ray Minniecon, "[http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2004/02/16/1076779903465.html Despair the reality for a race lost in the alien space of Redfern]", ''Sydney Morning Herald'', 17 February 2004; quoted by Suvendrini Perera, "[http://www.acrawsa.org.au/files/ejournalfiles/64SuvendriniPerera.pdf 'Aussie Luck': the Border Politics of Citizenship Post Cronulla Beach]", ''ACRAWSA e-journal'' [http://www.acrawsa.org.au/ejournal/?id=23 3(1)], 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Although people of colour live in Sidney, whites have presumptive control over urban planning—the ability to decide who lives where and when a poor neighborhood is [[gentrification|gentrified]].&lt;ref&gt;Timothy Neale, "[http://www.acrawsa.org.au/files/ejournalfiles/183CRWS201281NealeReview.pdf Book Review: Wendy Shaw. 2007. ''Cities of Whiteness'', Oxford: Blackwell Publishing.]" ''Critical Race and Whiteness Studies'' [http://www.acrawsa.org.au/ejournal/?id=54 8], 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; At the other end of the spectrum, anti-racist white Australians working with Indigenous people may experience their privilege as painful "stigma".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kowal|first=Emma|title=THE STIGMA OF WHITE PRIVILEGE|journal=Cultural Studies|date=1 May 2011|volume=25|issue=3|pages=313–333|doi=10.1080/09502386.2010.491159}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies of white privilege in Australia have increased since the late 1990s, with several books published on the history of how whiteness became a dominant identity. Aileen Moreton-Robinson's ''Talkin' Up to the White Woman'' is a critique of unexamined white privilege in the Australian feminist movement.&lt;ref name=Ganley&gt;Toby Ganley, "[http://www.polsis.uq.edu.au/dialogue/vol-1-2-4.pdf What's all this talk about whiteness?]", ''Dialogue'' 1(2), 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; The Australian Critical Race and Whiteness Studies Association formed in 2005 to study racial privilege and promote respect for Indigenous sovereignties; it publishes an online journal called ''Critical Race and Whiteness Studies''.&lt;ref&gt;"ACRAWSA: About", ''Australian Critical Race and Whiteness Studies Association'', updated 30 January 2012; accessed 19 November 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Affirmative action]]
*[[Angry white male]]
*[[Christian privilege]]
*[[Glass ceiling]]
*[[Heterosexism#Parallels and intersections|Heterosexism]]
*[[Identity politics]]
*[[Institutional racism]]
*[[Male privilege]]
*[[Media bias]]
*[[Missing white woman syndrome]]
*[[Nadir of American race relations]]
*[[Reverse discrimination]]
*[[White male]]
*[[Whiteness studies]]
*[[First world privilege]]

==References==
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
{{Further reading cleanup|date=February 2011}}
* Allen, Theodore. ''The Invention of the White Race: Racial Oppression and Social Control'' (Verso, 1994) ISBN 0-86091-660-X.
* Berger, Maurice.  "White Lies: Race and the Myths of Whiteness" (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, 1999) ISBN 0-374-52715-6
* Brown, C.S. (2002). ''Refusing Racism: White allies and the struggle of civil right.'' New York: Teachers College Press.
* DuBois, W.E.B. 1920. "The Souls of White Folk", in ''Darkwater''
* [[Richard Dyer|Dyer, Richard]]. ''White''
* [[Franz Fanon|Fanon, Franz]]. ''Black Skin, White Masks''
* Ignatiev, Noel. ''How the Irish Became White'' (Routledge, 1996). ISBN 0-415-91825-1.
* Jackson, C. 2006. ''White Anti-Racism: Living the Legacy.'' Retrieved October 31, 2006 from http://www.tolerance.org/teach/activities/activity.jsp?ar=718.
* {{cite journal | last1 = Levine-Rasky | first1 = C. | year = 2000 | title = Framing whiteness: working through the tensions in introducing whiteness to educators | url = | journal = Race Ethnicity and Education | volume = 3 | issue = 3| pages = 271–292 }}
* Lipsitz, George. ''The Possessive Investment in Whiteness: How White People Profit from Identity Politics'' (Temple University Press, 2006). ISBN 1-56639-635-2.
* [[Peggy McIntosh|McIntosh, Peggy]]. "White Privilege: Unpacking the Invisible Knapsack." (excerpt from Working Paper #189, "White Privilege and Male Privilege: A Personal Account of Coming To See Correspondence Through Work in Women's Studies" (1988), Wellesley College Center for Research on Women, Wellesley, Massachusetts.)
* Roediger, David R. ''The Wages of  Whiteness: Race and the Making of the American Working Class'' (Verso, 1991) ISBN 0860913341 9780860913344 0860915506 9780860915508.
* Roediger, D.R. 2005. ''Working toward whiteness: How America's immigrants became white. The strange journey from Ellis Island to the suburbs.'' New York: Basic Books.
* Rothenberg, Paula S., ed. ''White Privilege: Essential Readings on the Other Side of Racism'' (Worth, 2004) ISBN 0-7167-8733-4.
* {{Cite journal | doi = 10.1080/13613320500110519 | last1 = Solomona | first1 = R.P. | last2 = Portelli | first2 = J.P. | last3 = Daniel | first3 = B-J. | last4 = Campbell | first4 = A. | year = 2005 | title = The discourse of denial: how white teacher candidates construct race, racism and 'white privilege' | url = | journal = Race Ethnicity and Education | volume = 8 | issue = 2| pages = 147–169 }}
*{{cite book|title=[[White Guilt: How Blacks and Whites Together Destroyed the Promise of the Civil Rights Era]]|author=Steele, Shelby|publisher=[[HarperCollins]]|date=2006-05-02|isbn=0-06-057862-9}}
* Steyn, Melissa E., ''Whiteness Just Isn't What Is Used to Be: White Identity in a Changing South Africa'', Albany: SUNY Press, 2001, ISBN: 9780791450802.
* Updegrave, W.L. (1989). Race and money. Money, December 1989,152&amp;ndash;72.
* [[Tim Wise|Wise, Tim]]. ''White Like Me''

==External links==
*[http://www.tolerance.org/teach/activities/activity.jsp?ar=718 White anti-racism: Living the Legacy] from the Southern Poverty Law Center.

{{White people}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:White Privilege}}
[[Category:Critical race theory]]
[[Category:Definition of racism controversy]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Privilege (social inequality)]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:White supremacy]]

[[de:Weißsein]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>