<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113095816|87510856" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1655005" pageid="1655005" ns="0" title="White privilege"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T11:46:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">==Definition and Discussion==

'''White privilege''' is a term denoting purported rights, advantages, exemptions or immunities enjoyed by [[whites|white persons]] in [[Western world|Western]] countries beyond what is commonly experienced by nonwhites in those same nations. It has been described as "an invisible package of unearned assets which I [as a white person] can count on cashing in each day, but about which I was 'meant' to remain oblivious" (McIntosh, 1989).

White privilege is said to often be subtle or "invisible" to those who benefit from it. McIntosh (1989) and Jensen (1998) suggest some less obvious privileges that attach to being white in America:

* You can turn on the television or read the newspaper and expect to see members of your own race widely represented;
* You can expect your children to read books and materials in school that affirm and discuss the history of their race;
* You can swear, dress in second-hand clothes, or not answer letters, without having others attribute these behaviors to the bad morals, the poverty, or the illiteracy of your race;
* You can speak your opinion without being asked to speak for your race;
* You can do well without being called a credit to your race;
* You do not have to wonder, e.g., when being pulled over by a police officer, whether you are being singled out for your race;
* You can go shopping alone with reasonable assurance you will not be followed or harassed by store security;
* You can easily locate books, greating cards, toys, and magazines prominently featuring members of your race;
* You can take a job without having coworkers suspect you are not qualified, but rather, were hired as part of a racial quota;
* You do not look threatening to those of the dominant culture;
* You are most often evaluated by members of your own race, who see in you a reflection of themselves.

In addition to these more subtle advantages, many see a continuing, although not legalized or acknowledged, system of advantage to white people in areas such as housing, salaries, access to employment (especially to positions of power), access to education, even life expectancy (Tatum, 1997, p. 9; Farley, 1993). Manglitz (2003) argues the educational system in America has deeply entrenched biases in evaluation, curricula, and power relations toward the White majority.  Others see White privilege explaining such phenomena as white boxer Gerry Cooney receiving a very large amount of money for his 1982 fight with African American Larry Holmes despite the fact that he was an untested contender. Some historians use it to explain the historical trajectory from exclusion to acceptance of Irish and Jewish émigrés in the United States in the late 19th and early 20th centuries. Popular music, too, has been invoked to explain white privilege, including Elvis Presley (credited with popularizing "black music" with white audiences) and Eminem's popularity as a rapper. 

Parallels are often drawn between white privilege, male privilege and heterosexual privilege.

==Background== 

White privilege in America may be seen as having its roots in the system of legalized discrimination that existed for much of American history (Williams, 2003). From legalized slavery and the legalized taking of land and life from Native Americans, to Jim Crow laws, to legalized housing and job discrimination, a hierarchy of social benefits was legally and institutionally enforced for many decades in the United States. Although such active discrimination is now unconstitutional and illegal, the cultural, economic, social, and psychological effects of decades of such systematic, institutionalized racism continues to have an effect currently, according to many who have examined these issues.

It is argued that the effects of White Privilege are currently kept in place by those who benefit from systemic advantage ''passively'' accepting this advantage, often without recognizing that it exists.  It is said that White people are often willing to grant that people of color are disadvantaged, but not they they (White people) are advantaged. Whites are taught to see their lives as morally neutral, normative, and average. Most White people do not think to describe themselves as “White” when listing descriptive terms about themselves, whereas people of color usually use racial or ethnic identity descriptors. According to Tatum (1997), this is because the elements of one’s identity that are congruent with the dominant culture are so normalized and reflected back at one that one is apt to take such traits for granted.  This is not the case for identity aspects of those who are defined as “other” by the dominant culture, whether it be on the basis of race, gender, sexual orientation, religion, or other microcultural aspects.  

Tatum (1997) contends dominant microcultures (in this case, white people), set the parameters in which “subordinate” microcultures operate. This is reflected in who gets the best jobs, whose history will be taught in school, whose relationships will be validated by society, etc. Further, subordinate groups are often labeled as substandard in significant ways: e.g., Blacks have historically been characterized as less intelligent than Whites. Subordinates are also defined as being innately incapable of being able to perform the preferred roles in society. Some members of the subordinate microculture internalize these negative messages, thus being further disadvantaged by the entrenched belief that they cannot succeed to the same extent as White people. Such processes, it is contended, operate to maintain a generalized system of White advantage.

==Criticism==

As noted above, many White people do not experience themselves as being privileged or powerful. White people who are poor, who have experienced difficult developmental dynamics such as alcoholism or abuse by parents, or who have not benefitted from advanced education, often have difficulty accepting the idea that they have somehow benefitted from being White. Critics point out that Whites make up a substantial proportion of those living in poverty in the United States, and contend this is evidence against the existence of any system of advantage for Whites.

Writers such as Tatum (1997) recognize that not all Whites benefit from White privilege equally.  Other factors, such as socio-economic status, gender, age, religious affiliation, sexual orientation, and mental and physical ability or handicap also play an important role in access to privilege and power. Nevertheless, Tatum and others argue that White privilege operates even for those Whites who have experienced major disadvantages in life. 

Conservative commentator [[Steve Sailer]] argues that white privilege may be real, and that "[i]t's not 'unearned.' It was earned for you by the hard work and self-discipline of your ancestors and relatives."   Advocates of the existence of White privilege would retort that this statement is itself an example of the type of ethno-centric belief system that keeps White privilege in place, in that it implies the ancestors of non-whites failed to "earn" privilege due to their ''lack'' of “hard work and self-discipline.”

==See also==
*[[Identity politics]]
*[[Media and ethnicity]]
*[[Whiteness studies]]

== References ==
* Allen, Theodore. ''The Invention of the White Race: Racial Oppression and Social Control'' (Verso, 1994) ISBN 0-86091-660-X.
* Berger, Maurice.  "White Lies: Race and the Myths of Whiteness" (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, 1999) ISBN 0-374-52715-6 
* Farley, R (1993). The common destiny of Blacks and Whites: Observations about the social and economic status of the races. In Hill, H. &amp; Jones, J.E., Jr. (eds.) ''Race in America: The Struggle for equality.'' Madison: University of Wisconsin Press.
* Ignatiev, Noel. ''How the Irish Became White'' (Routledge, 1996). ISBN 0-415-91825-1.
* Jackson, C. (2006). ''White Anti-Racism: Living the Legacy.'' Retrieved October 31, 2006 from http://www.tolerance.org/teach/activities/activity.jsp?ar=718.
* Jensen, R. (1998). White people need to acknowledge benefits of unearned privilege. ''Baltimore Sun,'' July 19, 1998.
* Lipsitz, George. ''The Possessive Investment in Whiteness: How White People Profit from Identity Politics'' (Temple University Press, 2006). ISBN 1-56639-635-2.
* Manglitz, E.  (2003).  Challenging white privilege in adult education: a critical review of the literature.  ''Adult Education Quarterly, 53''(2), 119-134.
* McIntosh, P. (1989). White privilege: Unpacking the invisible knapsack. ''Peace and Freedom, July/August,'' 10-12.
* Roediger, David R. ''The Wages of  Whiteness: Race and the Making of the American Working Class'' (Verso, 1999) ISBN 0-86091-550-6.
* Rothenberg, Paula S., ed. ''White Privilege: Essential Readings on the Other Side of Racism'' (Worth, 2004) ISBN 0-7167-8733-4.
* Tatum, B. (1997). ''Why are all the black kids sitting together in the cafeteria? And other conversations about race.'' New York: Basic Books.
* Updegrave, W.L. (1989). Race and money. Money, December 1989,152-72.
* Williams, Linda Faye. ''Constraint Of Race: Legacies Of White Skin Privilege In America'' (Penn State, 2004) ISBN 0-271-02535-2.

==Further Reading==
* ''Black Skin, White Masks'' by [[Franz Fanon]]
* ''White Like Me'' by [[Tim Wise]]
* ''White'' by [[Richard Dyer]]
* Brown, C.S. (2002). ''Refusing Racism: White allies and the struggle of civil right.'' New York: Teachers College Press.
* Levine-Rasky, C.  (2000).  Framing whiteness: working through the tensions in introducing whiteness to educators.  ''Race Ethnicity and Education, 3''(3), 271-292.
* Roediger, D.R. (2005). ''Working toward whiteness: How America’s immigrants became white. The strange journey from Ellis Island to the suburbs.'' New York: Basic Books.
* Solomona, R.P., Portelli, J.P., Daniel, B-J. &amp; Campbell, A.  (2005).  The discourse of denial: how white teacher candidates construct race, racism and ‘white privilege’. ''Race Ethnicity and Education, 8''(2), 147-169.


==External links==
*[http://whiteprivilege.com WhitePrivilege.com, an anti-racism resource]
*[http://seamonkey.ed.asu.edu/~mcisaac/emc598ge/Unpacking.html White Privilege: Unpacking the Invisible Knapsack]
*[http://www.tolerance.org/teach/activities/activity.jsp?ar=718]
*[http://lilt.ilstu.edu/gmklass/foi/read2/unearned_privilege.htm]
*[http://wik.ed.uiuc.edu/index.php/White_privilege]

[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Philosophy of Racism]]

[[de:Weißsein]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>