<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114192351|171494607" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1655005" pageid="1655005" ns="0" title="White privilege"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T20:58:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Expert-subject|Sociology}}
{{Globalize/USA}}

'''White privilege''' is a sociological concept describing the advantages enjoyed by [[whites|white persons]] beyond what is commonly experienced by the non-white people in those same social spaces (nation, community, workplace, etc.).{{fact}} It differs from [[racism]] or [[prejudice]] by the fact that a person benefiting from white privilege need not hold overt racist beliefs themselves.{{fact}} 

== Overview ==
Scholars associated with the [[law|legal]] studies [[List of academic disciplines|field]] of [[Critical Race Theory]] have argued that whiteness or white racial status can be thought of as [[property]], something of value owned by certain members of society. This idea has been advanced in particular by Cheryl Harris&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal 
|first=Cheryl I. |last=Harris 
|title=Whiteness as Property 
|journal=Harvard Law Review 
|volume=106 |pages=1709-1795 |year=1993}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and George Lipsitz.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book |first=George |last=Lipsitz 
|title=The Possessive Investment in Whiteness: How White People Profit from Identity Politics 
|publisher=Temple University Press 
|year=1998 |isbn=1566396352}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Betsy Lucal writes that current ideas about racism are limited because of their tendency to focus only on racial "minorities" and the oppressive aspects of race. This approach, she writes, overlooks how whites are affected by race and indeed receive privileges through race.&lt;ref&gt;
''Oppression and Privilege: Toward a Relational Conceptualization of Race'' 
Betsy Lucal Teaching Sociology, 
Vol. 24, No. 3 (Jul., 1996), pp. 245-255
&lt;/ref&gt; It is particularly difficult for white people to learn about White privilege. Dan J. Pence and J. Arthur Fields suggest that resistance to acknowledging white privilege stems from the fact that whites often see inequality as a black or [[latino]] issue. Reactions range from hostility to a "wall of silence."&lt;ref&gt;
''Teaching about Race and Ethnicity: Trying to Uncover White Privilege for a White Audience'' 
Dan J. Pence, J. Arthur Fields 
Teaching Sociology, 
Vol. 27, No. 2 (Apr., 1999), pp. 150-158&lt;/ref&gt;

A study published by Branscombe et al found that thinking about the benefits gained from a privileged group membership can threaten social identity and evoke justification of the existing status difference between the ingroup and a disadvantaged group. For white Americans, racial privilege may be justified by concurring with modern [[racist]] attitudes. The study found that increased racism in response to thoughts of white privilege was limited to those who highly identified with their racial category. In contrast, when white racial identification was sufficiently low, thoughts of white privilege reliably reduced modern racism.&lt;ref&gt;
''Racial attitudes in response to thoughts of white privilege'' 
Nyla R. Branscombe, Michael T. Schmitt and Kristin Schiffhauer.
 European Journal of Social Psychology. 
Volume 37, Issue 2  , Pages 203 - 215. 25 Aug 2006
&lt;/ref&gt; Statements about racial inequality may be framed as either White privileges or Black disadvantages, when framed as White privileges a 2005 study found that the statements resulted in greater collective guilt and lower [[racism]] compared to a Black disadvantage framing. The findings suggest that representing inequality in terms of outgroup disadvantage allows privileged group members to avoid the negative psychological implications of inequality and supports prejudicial attitudes.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://psp.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/31/4/508 Inequality as Ingroup Privilege or Outgroup Disadvantage: The Impact of Group Focus on Collective Guilt and Interracial Attitudes] 
Adam A. Powell, Nyla R. Branscombe and Michael T. Schmitt. ''Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin'', 
Vol. 31, No. 4, 508-521 (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

In the widely circulated article, ''White privilege: Unpacking the invisible knapsack'', [[Peggy McIntosh]]  sought to enumerate the social, political and cultural advantages accorded to whites in American society. McIntosh claims there are parallels between white privilege, [[male privilege]] and [[Heteronormativity|heterosexual privilege]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal 
|last=McIntosh |first=P. 
|year=1989 
|title=White privilege: Unpacking the invisible knapsack 
|journal=Peace and Freedom 
|issue=July/August |pages=10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==White privilege in America==
{{seealso|Racism in the United States}}
=== History ===
In his 1935 ''[[Black Reconstruction|Black Reconstruction in America]]'', [[W. E. B. Du Bois]] first described the "psychological wages" of whiteness:

&lt;blockquote&gt;It must be remembered that the white group of [[labor (economics)|laborer]]s, while they received a low [[wage]], were compensated in part by a sort of public and psychological wage. They were given public deference and [[title]]s of courtesy because they were white. They were admitted freely with all classes of white people to public functions, public [[park]]s, and the best [[school]]s. The [[police]] were drawn from their ranks, and the [[court]]s, dependent on their [[vote]]s, treated them with such leniency as to encourage lawlessness. Their vote selected public officials, and while this had small effect upon the economic situation, it had great effect upon their personal treatment and the deference shown them. White schoolhouses were the best in the community, and conspicuously placed, and they cost anywhere from twice to ten times as much per capita as the colored schools. The [[newspaper]]s specialized on news that flattered the poor whites and almost utterly ignored the Negro except in crime and ridicule.&lt;ref&gt;W. E. B. Du Bois, ''Black Reconstruction in America, 1860-1880'' (New York: Free Press, 1995 reissue of 1935 original), pp. 700-701. ISBN 0684856573.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This concept was later taken up by David Roediger in his book, ''The Wages of Whiteness: Race and the Making of the American Working Class''&lt;ref&gt;''
[http://www.historymatters.appstate.edu/documents/wagesofwhiteness.pdf The Wages of Whiteness: Race and the Making of the American Working Class]'' a book review.
&lt;/ref&gt;  Theorists associated with the journal ''[[Race Traitor (publication)|Race Traitor]]'', such as editor [[Noel Ignatiev]], argue that whiteness (as a marker of a social status within the United States) is conferred upon people in exchange for an expectation of loyalty to what they consider an oppressive social order. This loyalty has taken a variety of forms over time: from the suppression of slave rebellions to whites-only [[union]]s to support for police brutality. Like currency, the value of this privilege (for the powerful) depends on the reliability of a white appearance as a marker for social consent. With enough "counterfeit whites" resisting racism and capitalism, the writers in this tradition argue, the privilege will be withdrawn or will splinter, prompting an era of conflict and social redefinition. Without such a period, they argue, progress towards social justice is impossible, and thus "[[treason]] to whiteness is loyalty to humanity."

The theory of White privilege in America may be seen as having its roots in the system of legalized discrimination that existed for much of American history.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book|last=Williams |first=Linda Faye 
|title=Constraint Of Race: Legacies Of White Skin Privilege In America 
|publisher=Penn State 
|year=2004 |isbn=0-271-02535-2}}
&lt;/ref&gt; In her book ''Privilege Revealed: How Invisible Preference Undermines America'' Stephanie M. Wildman writes that many Americans who advocate a merit-based, race-free worldview do not acknowledge the systems of privilege which benefit them. For example, many Americans rely on a social and sometimes even financial inheritance from previous generations. This inheritance, unlikely to be forthcoming if one's ancestors were slaves, privileges whiteness, maleness, and heterosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;
''Privilege Revealed: How Invisible Preference Undermines America'' 
By Stephanie M. Wildman. 
Published 1996 by NYU Press
&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to legal rights, whites were sometimes afforded opportunities and benefits that were unavailable to others. For example, government subsidized white homeownership in the middle of the 20th century through the [[Federal Housing Administration]], but not homeownership of other minorities. &lt;ref&gt; 
Douglas Massey and Nancy Denton, 
American Apartheid. 
Harvard University: 1993;
&lt;/ref&gt; Some social scientists suggest that the historical processes of [[suburbanization]] and decentralization are instances of white privilege that have contributed to contemporary patterns of [[environmental racism]].&lt;ref&gt;
''Rethinking Environmental Racism: White Privilege and Urban Development in Southern California'' 
Laura Pulido
Annals of the Association of American Geographers, 
Vol. 90, No. 1 (Mar., 2000), pp. 12-40&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians and authors, including Noel Ignatiev and Karen Brodkin, discuss the historical trajectory from exclusion to acceptance of Irish and Jewish émigrés in the late 19th and early [[20th centuries]] in terms of white privilege. Many see a continuing, although not legalized or acknowledged, system of advantage to white people in areas such as housing, salaries, access to employment (especially to positions of power), access to education, even life expectancy.&lt;ref&gt;
Farley, R. (1993). 
The common destiny of Blacks and Whites: Observations about the social and economic status of the races. 
In Hill, H. &amp; Jones, J.E., Jr. (eds.) 
''Race in America: The Struggle for equality.'' 
Madison: University of Wisconsin Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Tatum"&gt;{{cite book| first=Beverly Daniel |last=Tatum |authorlink=Beverly Daniel Tatum |year=1997 
|title=Why are all the black kids sitting together in the cafeteria? And other conversations about race 
|location=New York |publisher=BasicBooks |isbn=9780465091270}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sociologists in the American Mosaic Project report widespread belief in the United States that "prejudice and discrimination in favor of whites is important in explaining white advantage" or in their terms that "prejudice and discrimination create a form of white privilege." According to their 2003 poll, this view was affirmed by 59% of white respondents, 83% of Blacks, and 84% of Hispanics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |work=American Mosaic Project |url=http://www.soc.umn.edu/pdf/racialPrivledge.pdf 
|title=The Role of Prejudice and Discrimination in Americans’ Explanations of Black Disadvantage and White Privilege 
|year=2006 |accessdate=2007-09-09| format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Justice ===
Black and Latino American males are three times more likely than white males to have their vehicles stopped and searched by police. &lt;ref&gt;Matthew R. Durose, Erica L. Schmitt and Patrick A. Langan, Contacts Between Police and the Public: Findings from the 2002 National Survey. U.S. Department of Justice, (Bureau of Justice Statistics), April 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Young white offenders are likely to receive lighter punishments than minorities in America. Black youth arrested for drug possession for the first time are incarcerated at a rate that is forty-eight times greater than the rate for white youth, even when all other factors surrounding the crime are identical. &lt;ref&gt;"Young White Offenders get lighter treatment," 2000. The Tennessean. April 26: 8A.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Human Rights Watch, 2000. Punishment and Prejudice: Racial Disparities in the War on Drugs. DC: May, Volume 12, No. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Employment and economics ===
There is a correlation between a person's name and their likelihood of receiving a call back for a job interview. A field experiment in Boston and Chicago showed that people with "white-sounding" names are 50% more likely to receive a call back than people with "black-sounding" names, despite equal resumé quality between the two racial groups. &lt;ref&gt;Bertrand, Marianne and Sendhil Mullainathan, 2004. "Are Emily and Greg More Employable Than Lakisha and Jamal? A Field Experiment in Labor Market Discrimination." June 20. http://post.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/mullainathan/papers/emilygreg.pdf.&lt;/ref&gt; White Americans are more likely than African Americans to have their business loan applications approved, even when other factors such as credit records are comparable.  &lt;ref&gt; Fix, Michael and Margery Austin Turner, 1998. A National Report Card on Discrimination in America: The Role of Testing. The Urban Institute, March: 104. &lt;/ref&gt;

Black and Latino college graduates in America are less likely than white college graduates to end up in a management position. &lt;ref&gt;Linda Faye Williams, The Constraint of Race: Legacies of White Skin Privilege in America. Penn State Press: 2003, 359, Figure 7.1.&lt;/ref&gt; This is true even when other factors such as age, experience, and academic records are similar. &lt;ref&gt;William M. Hartnett, William M. "Income gaps persist among races," Palm Beach Post, October 20, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Patrick L. Mason, "Race, Cognitive Ability, and Wage Inequality," Challenge. May-June, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Education ===
Minority students are less likely to be placed in honors classes, even when justified by test scores. &lt;ref&gt;Gordon, Rebecca. 1998. Education and Race. Oakland: Applied Research Center: 48-9; Fischer, Claude S. et al., 1996. &lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Inequality by Design: Cracking the Bell Curve Myth. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press: 163&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Steinhorn, Leonard and Barabara Diggs-Brown, 1999. By the Color of Our Skin: The Illusion of Integration and the Reality of Race. NY: Dutton: 95-6.&lt;/ref&gt; Visible minority students are more likely than white students to be suspended or expelled from school, even though rates of serious school rule violations do not differ significantly by race. &lt;ref&gt;Skiba, Russell J. et al., The Color of Discipline: Sources of Racial and Gender Disproportionality in School Punishment. Indiana Education Policy Center, Policy Research Report SRS1, June 2000 &lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt; U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Youth Risk Behavior Surveillance System: Youth 2003, Online Comprehensive Results, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; E. Manglitz argues the educational system in America has deeply-entrenched biases in favor of the white majority in evaluation, curricula, and power relations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last=Manglitz |first=E |year=2003 |title=Challenging white privilege in adult education: a critical review of the literature |journal=Adult Education Quarterly |volumen=53 |issue=2 |pages=119-134}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Media ===
Television programs tend to reflect white worldviews, especially the news media which tends to feature white personalities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sunday Shutout: The Lack of Gender &amp; Ethnic Diversity on the Sunday Morning Talk Shows |first=Rob |last=Savillo |publisher=Media Matters for America |date=2007-05-14 |accessdate=2007-09-09 | url=http://mediamatters.org/items/200705140001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Self-image ===
{{Original research|date=September 2007}}

[[Beverly Daniel Tatum]] points out that most white people do not think to [[self-image|describe themselves]] as "white" when listing descriptive terms about themselves, whereas people of color usually use racial or ethnic identity descriptors. Tatum suggests this is because the elements of one’s identity that are congruent with the dominant culture are so normalized and reflected back at one that one is apt to take such traits for granted.  This is not the case for identity aspects of those who are defined as "other" by the dominant culture, whether it be on the basis of race, gender, sexual orientation, religion, or other microcultural aspects.&lt;ref name="Tatum"/&gt; The true reasons behind this occurrence are unknown, but may also be due to many different unspoken psychological effects on minorities and majorities alike, whether it be pride, shame, or an environmental stimulation such as a [[rally]].

Tatum writes that dominant microcultures (in this case, white people) set the parameters in which "subordinate" microcultures operate. 
Subordinate groups are often labeled as substandard in significant ways: e.g., blacks have historically been characterized as less intelligent than whites.&lt;ref name="Tatum"/&gt; Subordinates are also defined as being innately incapable of being able to perform the preferred roles in society.&lt;ref name="Tatum"/&gt; Some members of the subordinate microculture internalize these negative messages, thus being further disadvantaged by the entrenched belief that they cannot succeed to the same extent as white people. {{Fact|date=August 2007}}

The use of [[skin whitening]] treatments by non-whites has been linked to the benefits of white privilege. According to several theorists, the relationship between white privilege and skin whitening is explained by [[colorism]] and [[colonial mentality]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Brown is Beautiful|url=http://www.americanchronicle.com/articles/viewArticle.asp?articleID=11261|author=Llewelyn Muriel Austria-del Rosario}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Mestizaje and Self-Hate|url=http://www.mexika.org/Mestizo.html|author=Victor Mejia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
=== Non-existence of white privilege ===
Many white people do not see themselves as being privileged or powerful.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Jensen|first=R|title=White people need to acknowledge benefits of unearned privilege|publisher=[[Baltimore Sun]]|date=1998-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; White people who are poor, who have come from families affected by abuse or alcoholism, or who have not benefited from advanced education may not have benefited from being white. Critics{{Who|date=November 2007}} point out that whites make up the majority of those living in poverty in the United States,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.census.gov/prod/2003pubs/p60-222.pdf |format=PDF |title=Poverty in the United States: 2002 |year=2003 |month=September |last=Proctor |first=Bernadette D |coauthors=Dalaker, Joseph U.S. Census Bureau|publisher=U.S. Government Printing Office |work=Current Population Reports, P60-222 |location=Washington, DC}}&lt;/ref&gt; and contend this is evidence against the existence of any system of advantage for whites.

=== Justification of white privilege ===
Journalist, blogger and [[racial realism|race realist]] [[Steve Sailer]] argues that white privilege may be real, but that "it was earned for [whites] by the hard work and self-discipline of [white] ancestors and relatives ... If, say, [a white person] inherit[s] a valuable house in a nice, crime-free white neighborhood, it was earned for [them] by the law-abidingness of other whites" &lt;ref&gt; {{cite news|title=Whiteness Studies and the White Guy Gap|url=http://isteve.blogspot.com/2005/03/whiteness-studies-and-white-guy-gap.html|date=2005-03-17|author=Sailer, Steve|authorlink=Steve Sailer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Low impact of white privilege ===
Other critics such as [[Shelby Steele]] believe that the effects of white privilege are exaggerated. Steele argues that irresponsibility is a larger problem for blacks, who may incorrectly blame their personal failures on white oppression. He also argues that there are many "minority privileges": "If I'm a black high school student today... there are white American institutions, universities, hovering over me to offer me opportunities: Almost every institution has a [[multiculturalism|diversity]] committee... There is a hunger in this society to do right racially, to not be racist."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Does White Privilege Exist in America? Scholars Debate Whether Society Overlooks Minorities|url=http://abcnews.go.com/2020/story?id=2629192&amp;page=1|date=2006-11-05|author=Stossel, John|authorlink=John Stossel|coauthors=Binkley, Gena|publisher=[[ABC News]] ([[20/20]])}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

*[[Affirmative action]]
*[[Angry white male]]
*[[Colonial Mentality]]
*[[Colorism]] 
*[[Glass ceiling]]
*[[Identity politics]]
*[[Institutional racism]]
*[[Media bias]]
*[[Nadir of American race relations]]
*[[Reverse Discrimination]]
*[[Whiteness studies]]
*Privilege
**[[Male privilege]]
**[[Heterosexual privilege]]

==References==
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
{{cleanup-list}}
* Allen, Theodore. ''The Invention of the White Race: Racial Oppression and Social Control'' (Verso, 1994) ISBN 0-86091-660-X.
* Berger, Maurice.  "White Lies: Race and the Myths of Whiteness" (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, 1999) ISBN 0-374-52715-6 
* Brown, C.S. (2002). ''Refusing Racism: White allies and the struggle of civil right.'' New York: Teachers College Press.
* DuBois, W.E.B. 1920. "The Souls of White Folk," in ''Darkwater'' 
* [[Richard Dyer|Dyer, Richard]]. ''White''
* [[Franz Fanon|Fanon, Franz]]. ''Black Skin, White Masks''
* Ignatiev, Noel. ''How the Irish Became White'' (Routledge, 1996). ISBN 0-415-91825-1.
* Jackson, C. 2006. ''White Anti-Racism: Living the Legacy.'' Retrieved October 31, 2006 from http://www.tolerance.org/teach/activities/activity.jsp?ar=718.
* Levine-Rasky, C.  2000.  Framing whiteness: working through the tensions in introducing whiteness to educators.  ''Race Ethnicity and Education, 3''(3), 271-292.
* Lipsitz, George. ''The Possessive Investment in Whiteness: How White People Profit from Identity Politics'' (Temple University Press, 2006). ISBN 1-56639-635-2.
* [[Peggy McIntosh|McIntosh, Peggy]]. "White Privilege: Unpacking the Invisible Knapsack." (excerpt from Working Paper #189, "White Privilege and Male Privilege: A Personal Account of Coming To See Correspondence Through Work in Women's Studies" (1988), Wellesley College Center for Research on Women, Wellesley, MA.
* Roediger, David R. ''The Wages of  Whiteness: Race and the Making of the American Working Class'' (Verso, 1999) ISBN 0-86091-550-6.
* Roediger, D.R. 2005. ''Working toward whiteness: How America’s immigrants became white. The strange journey from Ellis Island to the suburbs.'' New York: Basic Books.
* Rothenberg, Paula S., ed. ''White Privilege: Essential Readings on the Other Side of Racism'' (Worth, 2004) ISBN 0-7167-8733-4.
* Solomona, R.P., Portelli, J.P., Daniel, B-J. &amp; Campbell, A.  (2005).  The discourse of denial: how white teacher candidates construct race, racism and ‘white privilege’. ''Race Ethnicity and Education, 8''(2), 147-169.
* Updegrave, W.L. (1989). Race and money. Money, December 1989,152-72.
* [[Tim Wise|Wise, Tim]]. ''White Like Me''

==External links==
*[http://www.tolerance.org/teach/activities/activity.jsp?ar=718 WHITE ANTI-RACISM: Living the Legacy] from the Southern Poverty Law Center.
*[http://wik.ed.uiuc.edu/index.php/White_privilege White Privilege in WikiEd] from [[UIUC]].
*[http://whiteprivilege.com/ WhitePrivilege.com]

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Philosophy of racism]]

[[de:Weißsein]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>