<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221118141627|1122611735" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="23833488" pageid="23833488" ns="0" title="Religion and LGBTQ people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-18T14:17:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Relationship between organized religions and LGBT people}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2021}}

The relationship between '''[[religion]] and [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) people''' can vary greatly across time and place, within and between different religions and sects, and regarding different forms of [[homosexuality]], [[bisexuality]], [[Non-binary gender|non-binary]], and [[transgender]] identities. More generally, the relationship between [[religion and sexuality]] ranges widely among and within them, from giving [[sex]] and [[sexuality]] a rather negative connotation to believing that sex is the highest expression of the divine.&lt;ref name="Urban 2010"&gt;{{cite book |last=Urban |first=Hugh B. |author-link=Hugh Urban |year=2010 |title=The Power of Tantra: Religion, Sexuality, and the Politics of South Asian Studies |chapter=Chapter 4 – The Sacrifice of Desire: Sexual Rites and the Secret Sacrifice |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wg6MDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA99 |location=[[London]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[I.B. Tauris]] |doi=10.5040/9780755625185.ch-004 |pages=99–124 |isbn=978-0-7556-2518-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[File:The symbols of the different big world religions on a rainbow - flag at Queer Easter.jpg|thumb|The symbols of the different big world religions on a rainbow - flag at Queer Easter]]

Some of the authoritative bodies and doctrines of the [[World religions|world's largest religions]] may view these negatively. This can range from quiet discouragement, explicitly forbidding same-sex sexual practices or sex/gender reassignment among adherents, actively opposing social acceptance of LGBT identities, to execution of people engaging in homosexual acts while tolerating sex/gender reassignment in specific cases.

Liberal and progressive voices within these religions tend to view LGBT people more positively, and some liberal [[religious denomination]]s may bless [[same-sex marriage]]s, as well as accepting and marrying people who are transgender. Historically, some cultures and religions accommodated, institutionalized, or revered same-sex love and sexuality;&lt;ref name=BOSWELL1&gt;{{Cite book | last= Boswell | first= John | publisher= University of Chicago Press | year= 2005 |title= Christianity, social tolerance, and homosexuality}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ASIA&gt;{{Cite book | last1= Dynes | first1= Wayne | last2= Donaldson |first2= Stephen | title= Asian homosexuality | publisher= Routledge | year= 1992 | isbn= 978-0-8153-0548-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; such [[LGBT themes in mythology|mythologies and traditions]] can be found in numerous religions around the world;&lt;ref name=CARPENTER1&gt;{{Cite book | last= Carpenter | first= Edward | title= Intermediate Types among Primitive Types: A Study in Social Evolution | publisher= Mitchell Kennerley | location= New York | year= 1914 | isbn= 978-0-405-07352-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; elements of religious and cultural incorporation of non-heterosexual practice can still be identified in traditions that have survived into the modern era, such as the [[Two-Spirit|Berdache]],&lt;ref name=BERDACHE&gt;{{Cite book | last= Williams | first= Walter | author-link = Walter Lee Williams| title= The Spirit and the Flesh: Sexual Diversity in American Indian Culture | publisher=Beacon House | year= 1992 | isbn= 978-0-8070-4602-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hijra (South Asia)|Hijra]],&lt;ref name=HIJRA1&gt;{{Cite book | last= Nanda | first= Serena |author-link=Serena Nanda | title= Neither Man Nor Woman | publisher= Wadsworth Publishing | year= 1998 | isbn= 978-0-534-12204-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Xanith]].&lt;ref name=XANITH1&gt;{{Cite journal | last= Wikan | first= Unni | title= The Omani Xanith: A Third Gender Role? | journal= Man |series=New Series | volume= 13 | issue= 3 | date= September 1978 | pages= 473–475 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious views of LGBT people==
According to a 2006 [[Australia]]n survey, LGBT Australians, compared to the general Australian population, were much more likely to have no religious affiliation, much less likely to be affiliated with a Christian denomination, and more likely to be affiliated with a non-Christian religion. The distribution of religions that LGBT Australians were raised in, however, was similar to that of the general population. Men, particularly bisexual men, were more likely to be Christian and more likely to have stayed in the same religion. Lesbians were more likely to have left the religion they were raised in and be currently unaffiliated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Murray|last=Couch|author2=Hunter Mulcare, Marian Pitts, Anthony Smith and Anne Mitchell|title=The religious affiliation of gay, lesbian, bisexual, transgender and intersex Australians: a report from the Private Lives survey|journal=People and Place|volume=16|issue=1|date=April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2004 survey of LGBT [[New Zealand]]ers found that 73% had no religion, 14.8% were Christian and 2.2% were Buddhist. In contrast, in 2001 census the general New Zealand population reported 59.8% Christian and 29.2% no religion. When looking at change since 1966, LGBT people are disaffiliating with Christianity at a rate 2.37 times the rate of the general population in New Zealand. In the survey 59.8% reported a belief in a spiritual force, god or gods; this differed significantly by gender, with 64.9% of women and 55.5% of men reporting such a belief.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Mark|last=Henrickson|title=Lavender Faith: Religion, Spirituality and Identity in Lesbian, Gay and Bisexual New Zealanders|journal=Journal of Religion &amp; Spirituality in Social Work|volume=26|issue=3|year=2007|url=http://lavenderislands.massey.ac.nz/downloads/Henrickson%20(2007)%20Lavender%20Faith.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111008072403/http://lavenderislands.massey.ac.nz/downloads/Henrickson%20(2007)%20Lavender%20Faith.pdf|archive-date=8 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Radical Faeries]] are a worldwide [[queer]] [[Spirituality|spiritual]] movement, founded in 1979 in the [[United States]]. Radical Faerie communities are generally inspired by aboriginal, native or traditional spiritualities, especially those that incorporate queer sensibilities.

==Religious groups and public policy==
Opposition to [[same-sex marriage]] and [[LGBT rights]] is often associated with conservative religious views. The [[American Family Association]] and other religious groups have promoted boycotts of corporations whose policies support the LGBT community.

On the other hand, the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]] supports the freedom to marry&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.uua.org/news/freedomtomarry/index.html |title=UUA News &amp; Events: Freedom to Marry for All People |access-date=2007-03-08 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060716123613/http://www.uua.org/news/freedomtomarry/index.html |archive-date=16 July 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and compares resistance to it to the resistance to abolition of [[slavery]], women's [[suffrage]], and the end of anti-[[miscegenation]] laws.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uusm.org/services/021305.php UUSM – Services &amp; Sermons&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090112081521/http://www.uusm.org/services/021305.php |date=12 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lesbians and gay men face particular problems in conservative Islamic nations where laws generally prohibit same-sex sexual behavior; where interpretation of Sharia Law on male homosexuality carries the death penalty, with this form of discrimination being viewed as a breach of human rights by international human rights [[The Yogyakarta Principles|experts]] and human rights organisations such as [[Amnesty International]].

With the signature of the US in 2009, the proposed [[UN declaration on LGBT rights]] has now been signed by 67 members of the United Nations. There was an opposing statement put forward by Muslim nations, and this has been signed by 57 member states, the majority being in Africa and Asia.  68 out of the total 192 countries have not yet signed either statement.

==Homosexuality and religion==
{{Main|Homosexuality and religion}}  There has been a long debate on whether practicing religion{{Citation needed|reason=This claim needs a reliable source.|date=October 2022}} is linked to the mistreatment of homosexual individuals. In the article, written by Whitehead,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Whitehead |first=Andrew L. |date=2018-01-02 |title=Homosexuality, Religion, and the Family: The Effects of Religion on Americans' Appraisals of the Parenting Abilities of Same-Sex Couples |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00918369.2017.1310550 |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |language=en |volume=65 |issue=1 |pages=42–65 |doi=10.1080/00918369.2017.1310550 |pmid=28332944 |s2cid=40252656 |issn=0091-8369}}&lt;/ref&gt; he explains how religion does play an important role in how people viewed same sex couples and their abilities to be functional beings in society. It has been researched that samples of American and Australian college students say that gay or lesbian parents are viewed in a more negative light compared to a heterosexual parents.It is was found that almost one third of Americans defined a same sex couple as a family without the presence of children. Recently there has been controversy on whether same sex couples should be able to able to adopt children because of some people's definition of what a family should look like and according to the Whitehead, a lot of those people who don't feel comfortable having adoption open to the homosexual population has to do with their religious views. Those associated with being religious claim that same sex individuals do not provide safe homes and considered them "confusing" and "stressful" environment. A lot of the reasoning why religion and homophobia{{Citation needed|reason=This claim needs a reliable source.|date=October 2022}} are said to correlated is with how religious individuals evaluate sacred text. Those who said to be more "traditional", and view god as a masculine entity view homosexual individuals as wrong due to reading texts like the bible as literal. Overall, much research has been done to indicate that religion is tied to more traditional and conservative views which leads to things like internalized homophobia and negative attitudes of homosexuality as a whole.

==Transgender people and religion==
{{Main|Transgender people and religion}} With the rise of transgender{{Citation needed|reason=This claim needs a reliable source.|date=October 2022}} awareness and the slow increase of acceptance. It is important to understand the role religion has on how many people view transgender individuals A lot of traditionally conservative religions such as Christianity, Catholics and Muslims often view the concept of “transgender” as wrong, and deviant considering a lot of their religious texts favor the idea of heteronormativity and intergroup pro-sociality{{Citation needed|reason=This claim needs a reliable source.|date=October 2022}}. In the study done by Campbell&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Campbell |first1=Marianne |last2=Hinton |first2=Jordan D. X. |last3=Anderson |first3=Joel R. |date=2019 |title=A systematic review of the relationship between religion and attitudes toward transgender and gender-variant people |journal=The International Journal of Transgenderism |volume=20 |issue=1 |pages=21–38 |doi=10.1080/15532739.2018.1545149 |issn=1434-4599 |pmc=6830999 |pmid=32999592}}&lt;/ref&gt; and other researchers tried to pinpoint just how religion and hatred for the transgender population comes from and their findings found that those who considered themselves religious(specifically Christian) were more associated with trans prejudice especially when correlating things like church attendance, and literal bible interpretations. These results suggest that the idea of creating an intergroup where readings like the bible are the foundation create a dislike for transgender individuals that don’t necessarily fit anywhere in sacred text, therefore associating it with the “out group”, aka, those who don’t belong.  

==Views of specific religions==
{{See also|History of human sexuality|LGBT-affirming religious groups}}

===Abrahamic religions===
[[Abrahamic religions]] (namely [[Judaism]], [[Samaritanism]], [[Christianity]], the [[Baháʼí Faith]], and [[Islam]]) have traditionally affirmed and endorsed a [[Patriarchy|patriarchal]] and [[Heteronormativity|heteronormative]] approach towards [[human sexuality]],&lt;ref name="Int J Transgend."&gt;{{cite journal |author1-last=Campbell |author1-first=Marianne |author2-last=Hinton |author2-first=Jordan D. X. |author3-last=Anderson |author3-first=Joel R. |date=February 2019 |title=A systematic review of the relationship between religion and attitudes toward transgender and gender-variant people |journal=[[International Journal of Transgenderism]] |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |volume=20 |issue=1 |pages=21–38 |doi=10.1080/15532739.2018.1545149 |doi-access=free |issn=1553-2739 |lccn=2004213389 |oclc=56795128 |pmc=6830999 |pmid=32999592 |s2cid=151069171 |quote=Many religions are based on teachings of peace, love, and tolerance, and thus, at least based on those specific teachings, these religions promote intergroup pro-sociality. However, evidence from studies of religion and social attitudes have paradoxically revealed that religion is typically a predictor of intergroup anti-sociality, or in other words religion tends to predict most forms of prejudice. When conceptualizing religion in terms of self-reported categorical religious affiliation (i.e., [[Christian]], [[Muslim]], [[Jewish]], etc.), religiously affiliated individuals tend to report more negative attitudes against a variety of social outgroups than individuals who are not religiously affiliated. [...] In addition, most [[Abrahamic religions]] (e.g., [[Judaism]], [[Christianity]], and [[Islam]]) contain dogmas in which their respective deity create mankind with individuals who are perfectly entrenched in the gender binary (e.g., [[Adam and Eve]]), and thus religions might be instilling cisgender normativity into individuals who ascribe to their doctrines.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Graham 2017"&gt;{{cite book |last=Graham |first=Philip |year=2017 |chapter=Male Sexuality and Pornography |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=X74pDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA250 |title=Men and Sex: A Sexual Script Approach |location=[[Cambridge]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |pages=250–251 |doi= 10.1017/9781316874998.013 |isbn=9781107183933 |lccn=2017004137 |quote=[[Patriarchy|Patriarchal beliefs]] assert the "natural" [[Male supremacism|superiority of men]] with a right to leadership in family and public life. Such beliefs derive particularly from [[Abrahamic religions]]. Patriarchal attitudes relating to sexual behaviour are mixed and inconsistent. They include, on one hand, the idea that as part of their natural inferiority, [[women]] are less in control of their sex drives and are therefore essentially lustful, with a constant craving for sex. This belief leads to the [[rape myth]] – even when women resist sexual advances they are using it merely as a seductive device. On the other hand, patriarchal beliefs also dictate that women, in contrast to men, are naturally submissive and have little interest in sex, so men have a "natural" right to sexual intercourse whether women want it or not.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Mbuwayesango 2016"&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Mbuwayesango |author-first=Dora R. |year=2016 |origyear=2015 |chapter=Part III: The Bible and Bodies – Sex and Sexuality in Biblical Narrative |editor-last=Fewell |editor-first=Danna N. |editor-link=Danna Nolan Fewell |title=The Oxford Handbook of Biblical Narrative |location=[[Oxford]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |pages=456–465 |doi=10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199967728.013.39 |isbn=9780199967728 |lccn=2015033360 |s2cid=146505567}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Leeming 2003"&gt;{{cite journal |author-last=Leeming |author-first=David A. |author-link=David Adams Leeming |date=June 2003 |title=Religion and Sexuality: The Perversion of a Natural Marriage |editor-last=Carey |editor-first=Lindsay B. |journal=[[Journal of Religion and Health]] |publisher=[[Springer Verlag]] |volume=42 |issue=2 |pages=101–109 |doi=10.1023/A:1023621612061 |issn=1573-6571 |jstor=27511667 |s2cid=38974409}}&lt;/ref&gt; favouring exclusively [[Heterosexual intercourse|penetrative vaginal intercourse between men and women]] within the boundaries of [[marriage]] over all other forms of [[human sexual activity]],&lt;ref name="Mbuwayesango 2016"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Leeming 2003"/&gt; including [[autoeroticism]], [[masturbation]], [[oral sex]], [[Non-penetrative sex|non-penetrative]] and [[Homosexual sexual practices|non-heterosexual]] sexual intercourse (all of which have been labeled as "[[sodomy]]" at various times),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Sauer |first=Michelle M. |year=2015 |chapter=The Unexpected Actuality: "Deviance" and Transgression |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=U8mBCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA74 |title=Gender in Medieval Culture |location=[[London]] |publisher=[[Bloomsbury Academic]] |pages=74–78 |doi=10.5040/9781474210683.ch-003 |isbn=978-1-4411-2160-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; believing and teaching that such behaviors are forbidden because they're considered [[sin]]ful,&lt;ref name="Mbuwayesango 2016"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Leeming 2003"/&gt; and further compared to or derived from the behavior of the alleged residents of [[Sodom and Gomorrah]].&lt;ref name="Mbuwayesango 2016"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Gnuse 2015"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Gnuse |first=Robert K. |date=May 2015 |title=Seven Gay Texts: Biblical Passages Used to Condemn Homosexuality |journal=[[Biblical Theology Bulletin]] |publisher=[[SAGE Publications]] on behalf of Biblical Theology Bulletin Inc. |volume=45 |issue=2 |pages=68–87 |doi=10.1177/0146107915577097 |issn=1945-7596 |s2cid=170127256}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.catholic.org/national/national_story.php?id=29699 |title=Bishop Soto tells NACDLGM: 'Homosexuality is Sinful' |last=Gilbert |first=Kathleen |date=29 September 2008 |website=Catholic Online |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080930122028/http://www.catholic.org/national/national_story.php?id=29699 |archive-date=30 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/religion/news/2010/12/08/8822/what-are-religious-texts-really-saying-about-gay-and-transgender-rights/ |title=What are Religious Texts Really Saying about Gay and Transgender Rights? |last1=Robinson |first1=Gene |last2=Krehely |first2=Jeff |last3=Steenland |first3=Sally |date=8 December 2010 |website=Center for American Progress |access-date=30 March 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.news24.com/news24/xarchive/voices/the-story-of-sodom-and-gomorrah-was-not-about-homosexuality-20180719 |title=The Story of Sodom and Gomorrah was NOT About Homosexuality |last=Modisane |first=Cameron |date=15 November 2014 |website=News24 |access-date=30 March 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the status of LGBT people in [[early Christianity]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Doerfler |author-first=Maria E. |year=2016 |origyear=2014 |chapter=Coming Apart at the Seams: Cross-dressing, Masculinity, and the Social Body in Late Antiquity |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7fsoDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA37 |editor1-last=Upson-Saia |editor1-first=Kristi |editor2-last=Daniel-Hughes |editor2-first=Carly |editor3-last=Batten |editor3-first=Alicia J. |title=Dressing Judeans and Christians in Antiquity |location=[[London]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Routledge]] |edition=1st |pages=37–51 |doi=10.4324/9781315578125-9 |isbn=9780367879334 |lccn=2014000554 |oclc=921583924 |s2cid=165559811}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Hunter |author-first=David G. |year=2015 |chapter=Celibacy Was "Queer": Rethinking Early Christianity |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VgDSBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA13 |editor1-last=Talvacchia |editor1-first=Kathleen T. |editor2-last=Pettinger |editor2-first=Michael F. |editor3-last=Larrimore |editor3-first=Mark |title=Queer Christianities: Lived Religion in Transgressive Forms |location=[[New York City|New York]] and [[London]] |publisher=[[NYU Press]] |pages=13–24 |isbn=9781479851812 |jstor=j.ctt13x0q0q.6 |lccn=2014025201 |s2cid=152944605}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Frost|first=Natasha|date=2018-03-02|title=A Modern Controversy Over Ancient Homosexuality|url=http://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/john-boswell-homosexuality-catholicism-history|access-date=2021-04-24|website=Atlas Obscura|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=McClain|first=Lisa|title=A thousand years ago, the Catholic Church paid little attention to homosexuality|url=http://theconversation.com/a-thousand-years-ago-the-catholic-church-paid-little-attention-to-homosexuality-112830|access-date=2021-04-24|website=The Conversation|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Early history of Islam|early Islam]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Geissinger |author-first=Ash |year=2021 |chapter=Applying Gender and Queer Theory to Pre-modern sources |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ABYHEAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA101 |editor-last=Howe |editor-first=Justine |title=The Routledge Handbook of Islam and Gender |location=[[London]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Routledge]] |edition=1st |pages=101–115 |doi=10.4324/9781351256568-6 |isbn=978-1-351-25656-8 |s2cid=224909490}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Schmidtke 1999"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Schmidtke |first=Sabine |author-link=Sabine Schmidtke |date=June 1999 |title=Homoeroticism and Homosexuality in Islam: A Review Article |journal=Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies (University of London) |location=Cambridge |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |volume=62 |issue=2 |pages=260–266 |doi=10.1017/S0041977X00016700 |eissn=1474-0699 |issn=0041-977X |jstor=3107489 |s2cid=170880292}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Islamic Homosexualities"&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Murray |author-first=Stephen O. |author-link=Stephen O. Murray |year=1997 |chapter=The Will Not to Know: Islamic Accommodations of Male Homosexuality |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6Zw-AAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA14 |editor1-last=Murray |editor1-first=Stephen O. |editor2-last=Roscoe |editor2-first=Will |title=[[Islamic Homosexualities|Islamic Homosexualities: Culture, History, and Literature]] |location=[[New York City|New York]] and [[London]] |publisher=[[NYU Press]] |pages=14–54 |doi=10.18574/nyu/9780814761083.003.0004 |isbn=9780814774687 |jstor=j.ctt9qfmm4 |oclc=35526232 |s2cid=141668547}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="TEOEM"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Rowson |first=Everett K. |author-link=Everett K. Rowson |title=The Effeminates of Early Medina |journal=[[Journal of the American Oriental Society]] |publisher=[[American Oriental Society]] |volume=111 |issue=4 |pages=671–693 |date=October 1991 |url=http://www.williamapercy.com/wiki/images/The_effeminates_of_early_medina.pdf |doi=10.2307/603399 |issn=0003-0279 |jstor=603399 |citeseerx=10.1.1.693.1504 |lccn=12032032 |oclc=47785421 |s2cid=163738149 |access-date=7 November 2021 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081001195534/http://www.williamapercy.com/wiki/images/The_effeminates_of_early_medina.pdf |archive-date=1 October 2008 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; is debated.

====Christianity====
{{Main|Christianity and sexual orientation|History of Christianity and homosexuality|The Bible and homosexuality}}
{{Further|Christianity and homosexuality|Christianity and transgender people|LGBT-affirming Christian denominations|LGBT clergy in Christianity}}
{{Christianity and sexual orientation|expanded=overview}}
[[File:Washington National Cathedral - DC Capital Pride - 2014-06-07 (14208630707).jpg|thumb|[[Washington National Cathedral]] ([[Episcopal Church in the United States]]) at [[Washington, D.C.|D.C.]] [[Gay Pride]] (2014)]]
[[File:St Luke's United Church of Christ Motto.jpg|thumb|[[United Church of Christ]]'s motto which expresses its support for [[LGBT rights]]]]
[[File:Scene during a church service at Glide Community Church, San Francisco.jpg|thumb|Scene during a church service at [[Glide Memorial Church]], San Francisco, a church-place that is supportive to LGBTI people]]
[[File:Mccny.jpg|thumb|[[Metropolitan Community Church of New York|Metropolitan Community Church]], a LGBT-affirming Christian church in [[New York City]]]]
[[File:UnivUnitChurchHoustonTX.JPG|thumb|The [[LGBT flag]] at the [[Unitarian Universalism|First Unitarian Universalist Church]] in [[Houston]] indicates that the church welcomes LGBT-identifying people.]]
The [[Hebrew Bible]]/[[Old Testament]] and its traditional interpretations in [[Judaism]] and [[Christianity]] have historically affirmed and endorsed a [[Patriarchy|patriarchal]] and [[Heteronormativity|heteronormative]] approach towards [[human sexuality]],&lt;ref name="Mbuwayesango 2016"&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Mbuwayesango |author-first=Dora R. |year=2016 |origyear=2015 |chapter=Part III: The Bible and Bodies – Sex and Sexuality in Biblical Narrative |editor-last=Fewell |editor-first=Danna N. |editor-link=Danna Nolan Fewell |title=The Oxford Handbook of Biblical Narrative |location=[[Oxford]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |pages=456–465 |doi=10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199967728.013.39 |isbn=9780199967728 |lccn=2015033360 |s2cid=146505567}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Leeming 2003"&gt;{{cite journal |author-last=Leeming |author-first=David A. |author-link=David Adams Leeming |date=June 2003 |title=Religion and Sexuality: The Perversion of a Natural Marriage |editor-last=Carey |editor-first=Lindsay B. |journal=[[Journal of Religion and Health]] |publisher=[[Springer Verlag]] |volume=42 |issue=2 |pages=101–109 |doi=10.1023/A:1023621612061 |issn=1573-6571 |jstor=27511667 |s2cid=38974409}}&lt;/ref&gt; favouring exclusively [[Heterosexual intercourse|penetrative vaginal intercourse between men and women]] within the boundaries of [[marriage]] over all other forms of [[human sexual activity]],&lt;ref name="Mbuwayesango 2016"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Leeming 2003"/&gt; including [[autoeroticism]], [[masturbation]], [[oral sex]], [[Non-penetrative sex|non-penetrative]] and [[Homosexual sexual practices|non-heterosexual]] sexual intercourse (all of which have been labeled as "[[sodomy]]" at various times),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Sauer |first=Michelle M. |year=2015 |chapter=The Unexpected Actuality: “Deviance” and Transgression |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=U8mBCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA74 |title=Gender in Medieval Culture |location=[[London]] |publisher=[[Bloomsbury Academic]] |pages=74–78 |doi=10.5040/9781474210683.ch-003 |isbn=978-1-4411-2160-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; believing and teaching that such behaviors are forbidden because they're considered [[sin]]ful,&lt;ref name="Mbuwayesango 2016"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Leeming 2003"/&gt; and further compared to or derived from the behavior of the alleged residents of [[Sodom and Gomorrah]].&lt;ref name="Gnuse 2015"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Mbuwayesango 2016"/&gt;

Throughout the majority of [[History of Christianity|Christian history]], most [[Christian theology|Christian theologians]] and [[Christian denominations|denominations]] have considered homosexual behavior as [[immoral]] or [[Sin in Christianity|sinful]].&lt;ref name="Gnuse 2015"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Gnuse |first=Robert K. |date=May 2015 |title=Seven Gay Texts: Biblical Passages Used to Condemn Homosexuality |journal=[[Biblical Theology Bulletin]] |publisher=[[SAGE Publications]] on behalf of Biblical Theology Bulletin Inc. |volume=45 |issue=2 |pages=68–87 |doi=10.1177/0146107915577097 |issn=1945-7596 |s2cid=170127256}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Koenig|first1=Harold G.|last2=Dykman|first2=Jackson|title=Religion and Spirituality in Psychiatry|year=2012|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge|isbn=9780521889520|pages=43|quote=the overwhelming majority of Christian churches have maintained their positions that homosexual behavior is sinful}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, [[Christian denominations]] have a variety of beliefs about LGBT people, and the moral status of same-sex sexual practices and gender variance. LGBT people may be barred from membership, accepted as [[laity]], or ordained as [[clergy]], depending on the denomination.  

The [[Roman Catholic Church]] welcomes people attracted to the same sex, while maintaining its teaching that homosexual relationships and acts are [[Christian views on sin|sinful]].&lt;ref name="CCC2357"&gt;[http://www.scborromeo.org/ccc/p3s2c2a6.htm#2357 Catechism of the Catholic Church, § 2357],[https://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/ccatheduc/documents/rc_con_ccatheduc_doc_20051104_istruzione_en.html Criteria for the Discernment of Vocation for Persons with Homosexual Tendencies]&lt;/ref&gt; The Roman Curia considers transgender individuals to be their [[Sex|biological sex]] and admits no distinction between "sex" and "gender".&lt;ref name="Norton"&gt;{{cite news|first=John|last=Norton|title=Vatican says 'sex-change' operation does not change person's gender|work=Catholic News Service|date=14 January 2003|access-date=19 July 2009|url=http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TS/CatholicTSDecision.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox Church]] holds similar stances on same-sex attraction and conjugal relations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oca.org/DOCmarriage.asp?SID=12&amp;ID=26 On Marriage, Family, Sexuality, and the Sanctity of Life]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Protestantism|Protestant]] denominations have a wide range of views. Some denominations espouse similar views to Catholicism and Orthodoxy, and teach that all sexual relations outside of traditional marriage between a man and a woman are sinful, such as the [[Reformed Church in America]],&lt;ref name="RCA - Homosexuality"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rca.org/Page.aspx?pid=501|title=Summaries of General Synod Discussions and Actions on Homosexuality and the Rights of Homosexuals|publisher=Reformed Church in America|access-date=21 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Southern Baptist Convention]],&lt;ref name="southernbaptists"&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.sbc.net/aboutus/pssexuality.asp |title=Position Statements/Sexuality |access-date=2 December 2009 |archive-date=3 October 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131003031920/http://www.sbc.net/aboutus/pssexuality.asp |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]&lt;ref&gt;[https://newsroom.churchofjesuschrist.org/ldsnewsroom/eng/public-issues/same-gender-attraction Same-Gender Attraction – LDS Newsroom]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Jehovah's Witnesses]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=February 2007|pages=28–30|journal=Awake!|url=http://wol.jw.org/en/wol/d/r1/lp-e/102007051|title=Homosexuality—How Can I Avoid It?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other Christian churches, such as the [[Church of England]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Rudgard|first1=Olivia|title=Transgender people encouraged to become priests in Church of England diversity drive|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2018/05/26/transgender-people-encouraged-become-priests-church-england/|access-date=27 May 2018|work=The Telegraph|date=26 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[United Church of Canada]], the [[United Church of Christ]], the [[Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.)]], the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in Canada]], the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.elca.org/Who-We-Are/Our-Three-Expressions/Churchwide-Organization/Communication-Services/News/Releases.aspx?a=4253| title = ELCA Assembly Opens Ministry to Partnered Gay and Lesbian Lutherans|publisher = [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]]|access-date=22 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Lutheran [[Church of Sweden]], the Lutheran [[Church of Denmark]], the Lutheran [[Church in Norway]], the Lutheran [[Church of Iceland]], the [[Protestant Church of the Netherlands]], the [[United Protestant Church in Belgium]], the [[United Protestant Church of France]], the German Lutheran, Reformed and United Churches in [[Evangelical Church in Germany]], the [[Old Catholic Church]], the [[Anglican Church in Canada]], the [[Episcopal Church (United States)|Episcopal Church in United States]], and the [[Scottish Episcopal Church]] don't consider same-sex relations immoral, and will ordain [[Ordination of LGBT Christian clergy|LGBT clergy]] and celebrate [[Blessing of same-sex marriages in Christian churches|blessings of same-sex marriages]]. Liberal Quakers, those in membership of [[Britain Yearly Meeting]] and [[Friends General Conference]] in the United States, approve of same-sex marriage and union and conduct same-sex marriage ceremonies in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name="Quakers in Britain"&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.quaker.org.uk/about-quakers/our-history/marriage-equality|title = Quakers and same sex marriage|work=Quakers in Britain |location=Friends House, London|access-date = 17 April 2017}}&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Guardian"&gt;{{cite news|url = https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/jul/31/quakers-gay-marriage| title = Quakers said same-sex couples 'miss the public recognition of their partnership in a religious ceremony'|work=The Guardian |location=London |access-date = 22 November 2009  | first=Riazat | last=Butt | date=31 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="New England Yearly Meeting of Friends"&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.neym.org/FUMworkweb/history.pdf|title = Homosexuality and Quakerism|publisher = [[New England Yearly Meeting]]|access-date = 22 November 2009|url-status=dead|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20101008224923/http://neym.org/FUMworkweb/history.pdf|archive-date = 8 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Unitarian Universalism=====
{{Main|Unitarian Universalism and LGBT people}}
[[Unitarian Universalism]] and the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]] (UUA) have a long-standing tradition of welcoming LGBT people.  The first ordained minister of any religion in the US or Canada to [[come out of the closet|come out]] was the Rev. [[James Stoll]] in 1969.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uupetaluma.org/sermons/sermon09jan05.html "My Greatly Human Hometown Minister—James Lewis Stoll, 1936–1994"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050217204501/http://www.uupetaluma.org/sermons/sermon09jan05.html |date=17 February 2005 }}, sermon by Leland Bond-Upson, delivered 9 January 2005&lt;/ref&gt; There have been UUA resolutions supporting people regardless of sexual orientation since 1970, and a popular program of becoming a "Welcoming Congregation" since 1989. The UUA has officially supported UUA clergy performing Services of Union between same-sex couples since 1984,&lt;ref&gt;[https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0DB1539F93AA15755C0A962948260 "Unitarians Endorse Homosexual Marriages"], UPI, ''The New York Times'', 29 June 1984. Retrieved 21 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and has supported [[same-sex marriage]] since 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.uua.org/obgltc/resource/history.html |title=UUA: Bisexual, Gay, Lesbian, and Transgender Community |access-date=2 December 2009 |archive-date=1 April 2007 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070401024407/http://www.uua.org/obgltc/resource/history.html |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Canadian Unitarian Council]] (CUC) similarly operates a Gender and Sexual Diversity Monitoring Group&lt;ref&gt;[http://cuc.ca/social_responsibility_monitoring_groups/gender-and-sexual-diversity/ Gender and Sexual Diversity]&lt;/ref&gt; and, like the UUA (of which it became autonomous in 2002), has Welcoming Congregations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cuc.ca/wp-content/uploads//2011/10/cucbrochures_welcomingcongregation.pdf CUC pamphlet on their Welcoming Congregation program]&lt;/ref&gt; The Canadian Unitarian Universalist congregations perform same-sex marriages and the CUC supports this work through its Lay Chaplaincy program.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://cuc.ca/wp-content/uploads//2011/10/cucbrochures_laychaplaincy.pdf |title=CUC pamphlet on their Lay Chaplaincy program |access-date=22 December 2012 |archive-date=30 October 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141030160617/http://cuc.ca/wp-content/uploads//2011/10/cucbrochures_laychaplaincy.pdf |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Judaism====
{{Main|Homosexuality and Judaism|Homosexuality in the Hebrew Bible}}
{{Further|LGBT-affirming denominations in Judaism|LGBT clergy in Judaism|Same-sex marriage and Judaism}}
[[File:Pride Minyan.jpg|thumb|A halakhic egalitarian Pride [[minyan]] in [[Tel Aviv]] on the second Shabbat of [[Hanukkah]]]]

The American branch of [[Conservative Judaism]] formally approves of same-sex marriage ceremonies.&lt;ref name="SSM"&gt;{{cite web|date=2012-06-01|title=Conservative Jews approve gay wedding guidelines|website=[[Fox News]]|url=http://www.foxnews.com/us/2012/06/01/conservative-jews-approve-gay-wedding-guidelines/|agency=Associated Press|accessdate=2013-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 1992 with the ''Report of the Reconstructionist Commission on Homosexuality'', the Reconstructionist Movement of Judaism has expressed its support for same-sex marriages as well as the inclusion of gay and lesbian people in all aspects of Jewish life. The [[Reconstructionist Judaism|Jewish Reconstructionist Federation]] leaves the choice of whether or not to perform same-sex marriages to individual rabbis but the procedure is included in the Reconstructionist ''Rabbi's Manual'' and many choose to use the traditional language and symbols of ''kiddushin''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year=2008|title=FAQ's on Reconstructionist Approaches to Jewish ideas and Practices|url=http://www.jrf.org/showres&amp;rid=487|publisher=Jewish Reconstructionist Federation|accessdate=2008-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":03"&gt;{{Cite web|title=Same-Sex Marriage|url=https://www.myjewishlearning.com/article/same-sex-marriage/|access-date=2019-02-28|website=My Jewish Learning|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reform Judaism, the largest Jewish denomination in the United States, is generally supportive of LGBT rights and marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Stances of Faiths on LGBTQ+ Issues: Reform Judaism|url=https://www.hrc.org/resources/stances-of-faiths-on-lgbt-issues-reform-judaism|access-date=2021-08-28|website=HRC|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Reform Jewish Views on LGBTQ Equality|url=https://reformjudaism.org/reform-jewish-views-lgbtq-equality|access-date=2021-08-28|website=Reform Judaism|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Islam====
{{Main|LGBT in Islam|Mukhannathun}}
{{Further|Liberalism and progressivism within Islam|Liberal and progressive Islam in Europe|Liberal and progressive Islam in North America}}
[[File:World laws pertaining to homosexual relationships and expression.svg|thumb|300px|
'''Same-sex sexual activity illegal'''
{{legend|#f9dc36|Not enforced or unclear}}
{{legend|#ec8028|Penalty}}
{{legend|#e73e21|Life in prison}}
{{legend|#cc6633|Death penalty on books but not applied}}
{{legend|#8c201f|Death penalty}}]]

Attitudes toward LGBTQ+ people and their experiences in the [[Muslim world]] have been influenced by its religious, legal, social, political, and cultural history.&lt;ref name="Schmidtke 1999"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Islamic Homosexualities"/&gt;&lt;ref name="TEOEM"/&gt;&lt;ref name="lawnet.fordham.edu"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rehman |first1=Javaid |last2=Polymenopoulou |first2=Eleni |year=2013 |title=Is Green a Part of the Rainbow? ''Sharia'', Homosexuality, and LGBT Rights in the Muslim World |url=https://ir.lawnet.fordham.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2322&amp;context=ilj |url-status=live |journal=[[Fordham International Law Journal]] |publisher=[[Fordham University School of Law]] |volume=37 |issue=1 |pages=1–53 |issn=0747-9395 |oclc=52769025 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180721220600/https://ir.lawnet.fordham.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=2322&amp;context=ilj |archive-date=21 July 2018 |access-date=30 October 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="iranica-law"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |author-last=Rowson |author-first=Everett K. |author-link=Everett K. Rowson |title=HOMOSEXUALITY ii. IN ISLAMIC LAW |url=https://iranicaonline.org/articles/homosexuality-ii |volume=XII/4 |pages=441–445 |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopædia Iranica]] |publisher=[[Columbia University]] |location=New York |date=30 December 2012 |orig-date=15 December 2004 |doi=10.1163/2330-4804_EIRO_COM_11037 |doi-access=free |issn=2330-4804 |access-date=13 April 2021 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130517035334/https://iranicaonline.org/articles/homosexuality-ii |archive-date=17 May 2013 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The religious stigma and [[Sexual taboo in the Middle East|sexual taboo]] associated with homosexuality in Islamic societies can have profound effects for those Muslims who self-identify as LGBTQ+.&lt;ref name="lawnet.fordham.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author-last=Polymenopoulou |author-first=Eleni |date=18 May 2020 |title=Forum: LGBTQ+ Issues in International Relations, Human Rights &amp; Development – Same-Sex Narratives and LGBTI Activism in the Muslim World |url=https://gjia.georgetown.edu/2020/05/18/same-sex-narratives-and-lgbti-activism-in-muslim-world/ |url-status=live |journal=[[Georgetown Journal of International Affairs]] |location=[[Washington, D.C.]] |publisher=[[Walsh School of Foreign Service]] at the [[Georgetown University]] |issn=1526-0054 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20201020121756/https://gjia.georgetown.edu/2020/05/18/same-sex-narratives-and-lgbti-activism-in-muslim-world/ |archive-date=20 October 2020 |access-date=7 December 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=19 May 2017 |title=Origins of Homophobia in the Muslim Community |url=https://sydneyqueermuslims.org.au/2017/05/19/source-homophobia-muslim-community/ |url-status=live |website=sydneyqueermuslims.org.au |location=Sydney |publisher=[[Sydney Queer Muslims]] |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180312142856/https://sydneyqueermuslims.org.au/2017/05/19/source-homophobia-muslim-community/ |archive-date=12 March 2018 |access-date=7 December 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ibrahim 2016"&gt;{{cite journal |author-last=Ibrahim |author-first=Nur Amali |date=October 2016 |title=Homophobic Muslims: Emerging Trends in Multireligious Singapore |journal=Comparative Studies in Society and History |volume=58 |issue=4 |location=[[Cambridge]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |pages=955–981 |doi=10.1017/S0010417516000499 |issn=1475-2999 |jstor=26293235 |s2cid=152039212}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, most LGBTQ-affirming Islamic organizations and individual congregations are primarily based in the [[Western world]] and [[South Asia]]n countries; they usually identify themselves with the [[Liberalism and progressivism within Islam|liberal and progressive movements within Islam]].&lt;ref name="lawnet.fordham.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Geissinger |author-first=Aisha |year=2012 |chapter=Islam and Discourses on Same-Sex Desire |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8sn9vMPUsNYC&amp;pg=PA80 |editor1-last=Boisvert |editor1-first=Donald L. |editor2-last=Johnson |editor2-first=Jay E. |title=Queer Religion: Homosexuality in Modern Religious History, Volume 1 |location=[[Santa Barbara, California]] |publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group|Praeger Publishers]] |pages=80–90 |isbn=978-0-313-35359-8 |lccn=2011043406}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Kurzman |author-first=Charles |author-link=Charles Kurzman |year=1998 |chapter=Liberal Islam and Its Islamic Context |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4n8HSe9SfXMC&amp;pg=PA1 |editor-last=Kurzman |editor-first=Charles |title=Liberal Islam: A Sourcebook |location=[[Oxford]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |pages=1–26 |isbn=9780195116229 |oclc=37368975}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Homosexual acts are [[Haram|forbidden]] in traditional [[Islamic jurisprudence]] and are liable to different punishments, including [[flagellation|flogging]], [[Stoning in Islam|stoning]], and the [[Capital punishment in Islam|death penalty]],&lt;ref name="Schmidtke 1999"/&gt;&lt;ref name="iranica-law"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Ibrahim 2016"/&gt; depending on the situation and [[Madhhab|legal school]].&lt;ref name="Ibrahim 2016"/&gt; However, homosexual relationships were generally tolerated in [[pre-modern Islamic societies]],&lt;ref name="Schmidtke 1999"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Islamic Homosexualities"/&gt;&lt;ref name="iranica-law"/&gt; and historical records suggest that these laws were invoked infrequently, mainly in cases of [[Rape in Islamic law|rape]] or other "exceptionally blatant infringement on [[Public morality|public morals]]".&lt;ref name="iranica-law"/&gt; Public attitudes toward homosexuality in the Muslim world underwent a marked negative change starting from the 19th century through the [[International propagation of Salafism and Wahhabism|global spread]] of [[Islamic fundamentalism|Islamic fundamentalist movements]] such as [[Salafi movement|Salafism]] and [[Wahhabism]],&lt;ref name="Ibrahim 2016"/&gt; and the influence of the sexual notions and restrictive norms prevalent in [[Europe]] at the time: a number of Muslim-majority countries have retained criminal penalties for homosexual acts enacted under European [[Colonialism|colonial]] rule.&lt;ref name="Ibrahim 2016"/&gt; In recent times, extreme [[prejudice]], [[Discrimination against LGBT people|discrimination]], and [[violence against LGBT people]] persists, both [[Societal attitudes toward homosexuality|socially]] and legally, in much of the Muslim world,&lt;ref name="lawnet.fordham.edu"/&gt; exacerbated by increasingly [[Social conservatism|socially conservative]] attitudes and the rise of [[Islamism|Islamist movements]] in Muslim-majority countries.&lt;ref name="Ibrahim 2016"/&gt;

Islamic views on homosexuality are also influenced by the rulings prescribed by the [[Quran]] and the teachings of the [[Islamic prophet]] [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref name="TEOEM"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Murray-Roscoe"&gt;{{cite book |editor1-last=Murray |editor1-first=Stephen O. |editor1-link=Stephen O. Murray |editor2-last=Roscoe |editor2-first=Will |year=1997 |chapter=Conclusion |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6Zw-AAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA305 |title=[[Islamic Homosexualities|Islamic Homosexualities: Culture, History, and Literature]] |location=[[New York City|New York]] and [[London]] |publisher=[[NYU Press]] |pages=305–310 |doi=10.18574/nyu/9780814761083.003.0004 |isbn=9780814774687 |jstor=j.ctt9qfmm4 |oclc=35526232 |s2cid=141668547|last1=Murray |first1=Stephen O. |last2=Roscoe |first2=Will |last3=Allyn |first3=Eric |last4=Crompton |first4=Louis |last5=Dickemann |first5=Mildred |last6=Khan |first6=Badruddin |last7=Mujtaba |first7=Hasan |last8=Naqvi |first8=Nauman |last9=Wafer |first9=Jim |last10=Westphal-Hellbusch |first10=Sigrid}}&lt;/ref&gt; The mainstream interpretation of some Quranic verses and ''[[hadith]]'' condemn sexual acts between members of the same sex, along with most forms of [[Zina|extramarital relations]].&lt;ref name="lawnet.fordham.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kilgerman|first=Nicole|title=Homosexuality in Islam: A Difficult Paradox|journal=Macalester Islam Journal|volume=2|issue=3|pages=52–64}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 1980s, Mufti [[Muhammad Sayyid Tantawy]] of [[Egypt]] issued a ''[[fatwa]]'' supporting the right for those who fit the description of ''[[mukhannathun]]'' to have [[sex reassignment surgery]]; [[Ayatollah Khomeini]] of [[Iran]] issued similar ''fatwas'' around the same time.&lt;ref name="TransgenderHealth 2020"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Zaharin |first1=Aisya Aymanee M. |last2=Pallotta-Chiarolli |first2=Maria |date=June 2020 |title=Countering Islamic conservatism on being transgender: Clarifying Tantawi's and Khomeini's fatwas from the progressive Muslim standpoint |journal=[[International Journal of Transgender Health]] |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |volume=21 |issue=3 |pages=235–241 |doi=10.1080/26895269.2020.1778238 |pmid=34993508 |pmc=8726683 |doi-access=free |issn=1553-2739 |lccn=2004213389 |oclc=56795128 |s2cid=225679841}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Transgenderism 2017"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Alipour |first=Mehrdad |year=2017 |title=Islamic shari'a law, neotraditionalist Muslim scholars and transgender sex-reassignment surgery: A case study of Ayatollah Khomeini's and Sheikh al-Tantawi's fatwas |journal=[[International Journal of Transgenderism]] |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |volume=18 |issue=1 |pages=91–103 |doi=10.1080/15532739.2016.1250239 |doi-access=free |issn=1553-2739 |lccn=2004213389 |oclc=56795128 |s2cid=152120329}}&lt;/ref&gt; Khomeini's initial ''fatwa'' concerned [[intersex]] individuals as well, but he later specified that [[sex reassignment surgery]] was also permissible in the case of transgender individuals.&lt;ref name="TransgenderHealth 2020"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Transgenderism 2017"/&gt;

[[File:21. İstanbul Onur Yürüyüşü Gay Pride (58).jpg|thumb|250px|left|[[Istanbul Pride|Istanbul LGBT Pride parade]] in 2013, [[Taksim Square]], [[Istanbul]], Turkey]]
Because [[LGBT rights in Iran|homosexuality is illegal in Iran]] but [[transgenderism]] is legal, some gay individuals have been forced to undergo sex reassignment surgery and transition into the opposite sex, regardless of their actual gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Hamedani |first=Ali |date=5 November 2014 |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-29832690 |title=The gay people pushed to change their gender |work=[[BBC Persian]] |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141106224035/https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-29832690 |archive-date=6 November 2014 |access-date=16 July 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, transgender people are generally more accepted, provided they conform to traditional gender norms post-transition; for example, the Iranian government not only allows and recognizes [[sex reassignment surgery]], but also subsidizes the procedure for transgender citizens.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/7259057.stm BBC News: Iran's 'diagnosed transsexuals']&lt;/ref&gt; In some regions of [[South Asia]] such as [[India]], [[Bangladesh]], and [[Pakistan]], the ''[[Hijra (South Asia)|hijras]]'' are officially recognized as a [[third gender]] that is neither male nor female,&lt;ref name="Cult. Health Sex."&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hossain |first=Adnan |date=April 2017 |title=The paradox of recognition: ''hijra'', third gender, and sexual rights in Bangladesh |journal=[[Culture, Health &amp; Sexuality]] |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |volume=19 |issue=12 |pages=1418–1431 |doi=10.1080/13691058.2017.1317831 |doi-access=free |pmid=28498049 |eissn=1464-5351 |issn=1369-1058 |oclc=41546256 |s2cid=5372595}}&lt;/ref&gt; a concept that some have compared to ''mukhannathun''.&lt;ref name="Murray-Roscoe"/&gt;

[[File:Al-Fatiha Muslim Gays - Gay Parade 2008 in San Francisco.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Gay Muslim activists of the [[Al-Fatiha Foundation]] holding the [[flag of Turkey]] at the [[San Francisco Pride]] (2008)]]
In [[France]] there was an Islamic same-sex marriage on 18 February 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2012-03-30|title=FRANCE – Concilier islam et homosexualité, le combat de Ludovic-Mohamed Zahed – France 24|url=http://www.france24.com/fr/20120330-france-mariage-homosexuel-musulmans-gay-religion-imam-coran-corps-livre-ludovic-mohamed-zahed|publisher=France 24}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Paris in November 2012 a room in a Buddhist prayer hall was used by gay Muslims and called a "gay-friendly mosque",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Banerji|first=Robin|date=30 November 2012|title=Gay-friendly 'mosque' opens in Paris|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-20547335|access-date=27 March 2021|publisher=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a French Islamic website&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Homosexual Muslims – HM2F|url=http://www.homosexuels-musulmans.org/gay_muslims.html|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161227151103/http://www.homosexuels-musulmans.org/gay_muslims.html|archive-date=2016-12-27|access-date=2018-01-20|work=homosexuels-musulmans.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; is supporting religious same-sex marriage. The [[Ibn Ruschd-Goethe mosque]] in Berlin is a liberal mosque open to all types of Muslims, where men and women pray together and LGBT worshippers are welcomed and supported.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sarac|first=Tugay|date=2 May 2019|title=My LGBT-friendly mosque saved me from being radicalised|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/bbcthree/article/cc70b8a4-f14f-4324-a81a-82fe347f9664|access-date=3 May 2019|publisher=BBC|series=BBC Three}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other significant LGBT-inclusive mosques or prayer groups include the El-Tawhid Juma Circle Unity Mosque in Toronto,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=juma circle|url=http://www.jumacircle.com/|access-date=2021-11-14|website=juma circle|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2016-06-03|title=Queer and going to the mosque: 'I've never felt more Muslim than I do now'|url=http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2016/jun/03/unity-mosque-queer-muslim-islam-samra-habib|access-date=2021-11-14|website=The Guardian|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Gillis|first=Wendy|date=2013-08-25|title=Islamic scholars experience diversity of Muslim practices at U of T summer program|language=en-CA|work=Toronto Star|url=https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/2013/08/25/islamic_scholars_experience_diversity_of_muslim_practices_at_u_of_t_summer_program.html|access-date=2021-11-14|issn=0319-0781}}&lt;/ref&gt; Masjid an-Nur al-Isslaah (Light of Reform Mosque) in Washington D.C.,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Meet America's first openly gay imam|url=http://america.aljazeera.com/watch/shows/america-tonight/america-tonight-blog/2013/12/20/meet-america-s-firstopenlygayimam.html|access-date=2021-11-14|publisher=Al Jazeera}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="NBC News"&gt;{{Cite web|title=Affirming mosques help gay Muslims reconcile faith, sexuality|url=https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/affirming-mosques-help-gay-muslims-reconcile-faith-sexuality-n988151|access-date=2021-11-14|publisher=NBC News|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Masjid Al-Rabia in Chicago,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=A Mosque For LGBTQ Muslims|language=en|publisher=NPR|url=https://www.npr.org/2018/04/15/602605271/a-mosque-for-lgbtq-muslims|access-date=2021-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="NBC News"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Masjid al-Rabia Home|url=https://masjidalrabia.org/|access-date=2021-11-14|website=Masjid al-Rabia|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unity Mosque in Atlanta,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Atlanta Unity Mosque|url=https://www.atlantaunitymosque.org/|access-date=2021-11-14|website=Atlanta Unity Mosque|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Stances of Faiths on LGBTQ Issues: Islam|url=https://www.hrc.org/resources/stances-of-faiths-on-lgbt-issues-islam|access-date=2021-11-14|website=HRC|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; People's Mosque in Cape Town South Africa,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2015-05-09|title=Is Cape Town's women and gay-friendly mosque a sign of new Muslim attitudes?|url=https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/cape-towns-gay-women-friendly-mosque-sign-re-interpretation-muslim-faith|access-date=2021-11-14|website=PBS NewsHour|language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Gay Mosque in Cape Town – rainbopedia.org|url=https://rainbopedia.org/wiki/gay-mosque-in-cape-town/|access-date=2021-11-14|website=rainbopedia.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Masjid Ul-Umam mosque in Cape Town,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=2019-02-05|title='Space to coexist': Inside South Africa's LGBT-friendly mosque|language=en|work=Reuters|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-safrica-lgbt-religion-idUSKCN1PU0J9|access-date=2021-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Qal'bu Maryamin in California,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2017-04-09|title=Women Building New Mosque in CA That's Open to All Genders|url=https://www.worldreligionnews.com/religion-news/women-building-new-mosque-ca-thats-open-genders|access-date=2021-11-14|website=World Religion News|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Qal'bu Maryam|url=https://qalbumaryam.weebly.com/|access-date=2021-11-14|website=Qal'bu Maryam Women's Justice Center|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Nur Ashki Jerrahi Sufi Community in New York City.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2018-06-14|title=How Queer Muslims Are Working to End Stigma This Ramadan|url=https://www.them.us/story/lgbtq-iftar|access-date=2021-11-14|website=them.|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2018-06-14|title=Queering Ramadan: Second Annual LGBTQAI+ Muslims and Allies Iftar|url=https://womensenews.org/2018/06/queering-ramadan-second-annual-lgbtqai-muslims-and-allies-iftar/|access-date=2021-11-14|website=Women's eNews|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Muslims for Progressive Values]], based in the United States and [[Malaysia]], is "a faith-based, grassroots, human rights organization that embodies and advocates for the traditional Qur'anic values of social justice and equality for all, for the 21st Century."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Who We Are|url=http://www.mpvusa.org/who-we-are|access-date=5 April 2017|work=MPVUSA.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=SEXUAL DIVERSITY|url=https://www.mpvusa.org/sexual-diversity|access-date=2021-11-14|website=Muslims for Progressive Values|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; MPV has recorded "a lecture series that seeks to dismantle the religious justification for homophobia in Muslim communities." The lectures can be viewed at MPV Lecture Series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=LGBTQI Lecture Series – YouTube|url=https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLE3saqAXcc3ahCLB4FWqyd7XAJ_Lh72IZ|access-date=5 April 2017|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Mecca Institute is an LGBT-inclusive and progressive online Islamic seminary, and serves as an online center of Islamic learning and research.&lt;ref name="NBC News"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Home|url=https://www.meccainstitute.org/|access-date=2021-11-14|website=meccainstitute.org|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Baháʼí Faith====
{{Main|Homosexuality and the Baháʼí Faith}}

The [[Baháʼí Faith]] teaches that the only acceptable form of sexual expression is within [[marriage]], and [[Baháʼí marriage]] is defined in the religion's texts as exclusively between one man and one woman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= Smith |first= Peter |author-link=Peter Smith (historian) |encyclopedia= A concise encyclopedia of the Baháʼí Faith |title= Homosexuality |year= 2002 |publisher=[[Oneworld Publications]]  |location=Oxford |isbn= 978-1-85168-184-6 |pages=184–185 |url= https://archive.org/details/conciseencyclope0000smit/page/184 |via=[[Internet Archive]] |url-access=limited }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="man and woman"&gt;"Baháʼí law restricts permissible sexual intercourse to that between a man and the woman to whom he is married." 

: (Letter from the Universal House of Justice to an individual; ''Lights of Guidance'', pp. 365, #1225) [http://bahai-library.com/hornby_lights_guidance&amp;chapter=2#n1225]&lt;/ref&gt; Baháʼís stress the importance of absolute [[chastity]] for any unmarried person,&lt;ref name="married"&gt;"...according to the Baháʼí Teachings no sexual act can be considered lawful unless performed between lawfully married persons. Outside of marital life there can be no lawful or healthy use of the sex impulse."

: (On behalf of Shoghi Effendi to an individual; ''Lights of Guidance'', pp. 364, #1220) [http://bahai-library.com/hornby_lights_guidance&amp;chapter=2#n1220]&lt;/ref&gt; and focus on personal restraint. The [[Universal House of Justice]], the elected governing body of the Baháʼí Faith, has stated that "the Faith does not recognize homosexuality as a 'natural' or permanent phenomenon."&lt;ref&gt;"…the Faith does not recognize homosexuality as a "natural" or permanent phenomenon. Rather, it sees this as an aberration subject to treatment, however intractable exclusive homosexuality may now seem to be. To the question of alteration of homosexual bents, much study must be given, and doubtless in the future clear principles of prevention and treatment will emerge. As for those now afflicted, a homosexual does not decide to be a problem human, but he does, as you rightly state, have decision in choosing his way of life, i.e. abstaining from homosexual acts.
"Your plea for understanding and of justice extended to homosexuals is well taken in many respects, and the House of Justice assures you of its concern for the large number of persons so afflicted. Your work with the homosexual community is praiseworthy, and it permits you personally to exercise the support which is necessary for these often harassed persons, support which you call for in your essay. Moreover, your interest cannot but be therapeutic, at least for the more superficial elements of the problem; however, definitive therapy of the underlying predisposition, which you consider to be innate but the Teachings do not, may have to await additional investigations. As for the responsibility of Assemblies and of individual Baháʼís, certainly all are called upon to be understanding, supportive and helpful to any individual who carries the burden of homosexuality."
:(Letter written on behalf of the Universal House of Justice to an individual, 22 March 1987)&lt;/ref&gt; The Universal House of Justice has approved of and encouraged Shoghi Effendi's idea of possible medical treatment.&lt;ref&gt;(Letter of The Universal House of Justice, 5 June 1993, ''Homosexuality'', [http://bahai-library.com/compilation_homosexuality_bwc#page7 p. 7])&lt;/ref&gt;
However, membership in the Baháʼí community is open to lesbian and gay adherents,&lt;ref&gt;"They (homosexuals) should be treated just like any other people seeking admittance to the Faith, and be accepted on the same basis. Our teachings, as outlined in "The Advent of Divine Justice" on the subject of living a chaste life, should be emphasized to them just as to every other applicant, but certainly no ruling whatsoever should be laid down in this matter. The Baháʼís have certainly not yet reached that stage of moral perfection where they are in a position to too harshly scrutinize the private lives of other souls, and each individual should be accepted on the basis of his faith, and sincere willingness to try to live up to the Divine standards" 

: (Compiled by the Universal House of Justice Research Department, ''Homosexuality'', p. 3) [http://bahai-library.com/compilation_homosexuality_bwc]&lt;/ref&gt; who are to be "advised and sympathized with".&lt;ref name="sympathized"&gt;"Amongst the many other evils afflicting society in this spiritual low water mark in history is the question of immorality, and over-emphasis of sex. Homosexuality, according to the Writings of Bahá'u'lláh, is spiritually condemned. This does not mean that people so afflicted must not be helped and advised and sympathized with."

: (On behalf of Shoghi Effendi to an individual, 21 May 1954; ''Lights of Guidance'', p. 365, #1221) [http://bahai-library.com/hornby_lights_guidance&amp;chapter=2#n1221]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="understanding"&gt;"As for the responsibility of Assemblies and of individual Baháʼís, certainly all are called upon to be understanding, supportive and helpful to any individual who carries the burden of homosexuality."

: (Compiled by Universal House of Justice Research Department, ''Homosexuality'', p. 7) [http://bahai-library.com/compilation_homosexuality_bwc]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"When an individual becomes a Baháʼí , he or she accepts the claim of Bahá'u'lláh to be the Manifestation of God bringing a divinely-inspired message from God for the benefit of mankind. Implicit in the acceptance of this claim is the commitment of the believer to embark on the lifelong process of endeavouring to implement the teachings on personal conduct. Through sincere and sustained effort, energized by faith in the validity of the Divine Message, and combined with patience with oneself and the loving support of the Baháʼí community, individuals are able to effect a change in their behaviour; as a consequence of this effort they partake of spiritual benefits which liberate them and which bestow a true happiness beyond description.
As you know, Bahá'u'lláh has clearly forbidden the expression of sexual love between individuals of the same sex. However, the doors are open for all of humanity to enter the Cause of God, irrespective of their present circumstance; this invitation applies to homosexuals as well as to any others who are engaged in practices contrary to the Baháʼí teachings. Associated with this invitation is the expectation that all believers will make a sincere and persistent effort to eradicate those aspects of their conduct which are not in conformity with Divine Law.

: (Compiled by Universal House of Justice Research Department, ''Homosexuality'', p. 11) [http://bahai-library.com/compilation_homosexuality_bwc]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dharmic religions===
[[File:Ardhanarisvara.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Ardhanarishvara]], the [[Intersex|androgynous form]] (half-male and half-female) of the [[Hindu god|Hindu deity]] [[Shiva]] combined with his consort [[Parvati]]. Tiruvenkadu, Chola, 11th century CE.]]

====Hinduism====
{{Main|Hinduism and LGBT topics}}

[[Hinduism]] has taken various positions, ranging from positive to neutral or antagonistic. Referring to the nature of [[samsara]], the ''[[Rigveda]]'', one of the four canonical [[Hindu texts|sacred texts of Hinduism]] says 'Vikruti Evam Prakriti' (perversity/diversity is what nature is all about, or, what seems un-natural is also natural), which some scholars believe recognizes homosexuality as natural, if not an approval of homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;'Expose the Hindu Taliban!' by [[Ashok Row Kavi]]&lt;/ref&gt; Sexuality is rarely discussed openly in Hindu society, and LGBT issues are largely a [[taboo]] subject&amp;nbsp;— especially among the strongly religious. A "[[third gender]]" has been acknowledged within Hinduism since [[Vedic period|Vedic times]]. Several Hindu texts, such as [[Manu Smriti]]&lt;ref&gt;Manu Smriti, 3.49&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Sushruta Samhita]], assert that some people are born with either mixed male and female natures, or sexually neuter, as a matter of natural biology. They worked as [[hairdressing|hairdressers]], flower-sellers, servants, [[massage|masseurs]] and [[prostitution|prostitutes]]. Today, many people that identify as ''[[Hijra (South Asia)|hijras]]'' are officially recognized as a [[third gender]] that is neither male nor female in India;&lt;ref name="Cult. Health Sex."/&gt; they mostly live on the margins of society, and many still work in prostitution, or make a livelihood as beggars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Nanda |author-first=Serena |year=1996 |chapter=Hijras: An Alternative Sex and Gender Role in India |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dlI91F_FHSYC |editor-last=Herdt |editor-first=Gilbert H. |title=Third sex, third gender: Beyond sexual dimorphism in culture and history |publisher=Zone Books |isbn=9780942299823}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several Hindu religious laws contain injunctions against homosexual activity, while some Hindu mythologies speaks favorably of lesbian relations and some third-gendered individuals were highly regarded by Hindu legends. Hindu groups are historically not unifyed regarding the issue of homosexuality, each one having a distinct doctrinal view.&lt;ref&gt;Lariviere. ''Naradasmriti, (Part One)''. Philadelphia, 1989.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="History1"&gt;{{harvnb|Vanita|Kidwai|2001|p=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Mahabharata]], book 5, Chapter 191-5.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Indian [[Kama Sutra]], written in the 4th century CE, contains passages describing [[eunuch]]s or "third-sex" males performing [[oral sex]] on men.&lt;ref&gt;[[Kama Sutra]], Chapter 9, "Of the Auparishtaka or Mouth Congress". [http://www.kamashastra.com/kama209.htm Text online] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100313043325/http://www.kamashastra.com/kama209.htm |date=13 March 2010 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the author was "not a fan of homosexual activities" and treated such individuals with disdain, according to historian [[Devdutt Pattanaik]].&lt;ref&gt;Pattanaik, Devdutt (2001). ''Homosexuality in Ancient India'', [[Debonair (magazine)|Debonair]] 2000 or 2001. Essay available [http://www.gaybombay.org/reading/art0001.html online] from GayBombay.org.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, some medieval Hindu temples and artifacts openly depict both male homosexuality and lesbianism within their carvings, such as the temple walls at [[Khajuraho]]. Some infer from these images that Hindu society and religion were previously more open to variations in human sexuality than they are at present.
[[File:1 Erotic Kama statues of Khajuraho Hindu Temple Kandariya Mahadeva Khajurâho India 2013.jpg|thumb|250px|upright|Erotic sculptures from [[Khajuraho Group of Monuments|Khajuraho temple complex]], [[India]]]]

In some Hindu sects (specially among the hijras), many divinities are [[androgynous]]. There are Hindu deities who are [[intersex]] (both male and female); who manifest in all three genders; who switch from male to female or from female to male; male deities with female moods and female deities with male moods; deities born from two males or from two females; deities born from a single male or single female; deities who avoid the opposite sex; deities with principal companions of the same sex, and so on.  However, this is not accepted by the majority of Hindus, and is often considered heretical in nature. Those who do accept it justify with the belief that both God and nature are unlimitedly diverse and God is difficult to comprehend.

Several Hindu priests have performed same-sex marriages, arguing that love is the result of attachments from previous births and that marriage, as a union of spirit, is transcendental to gender. It is often regarded that Hinduism does not condemn homosexuality.

====Buddhism====
{{Main|Buddhism and sexual orientation}}
{{See also|Buddhism and sexuality}}
[[File:Myoshinj shunkoin02s2000.jpg|thumb|right|[[Shunkō-in]] ({{lang-ja|春光院}}: "Temple of the Ray of Spring Light") in [[Kyoto]], [[Japan]], is a Buddhist temple that performs same-sex marriage ceremonies.]]

According to the [[Pāli Canon]] and [[Āgama (Buddhism)|Āgama]] (the [[Buddhist texts|early Buddhist scriptures]]), there is nothing saying that same or opposite gender relations have anything to do with sexual misconduct,&lt;ref name="cunda kammaraputta sutta"&gt;{{cite web|title=Cunda Kammaraputta Sutta|trans-title=To Cunda the Silversmith|others=Translated from the Pali by Thanissaro Bhikkhu|publisher=Access to Insight|year=1997|id=[[Anguttara Nikaya|AN]] 10.176|url=http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/an/an10/an10.176.than.html| access-date = 2011-03-14|quote=Abandoning sensual misconduct, he abstains from sensual misconduct. He does not get sexually involved with those who are protected by their mothers, their fathers, their brothers, their sisters, their relatives, or their Dhamma; those with husbands, those who entail punishments, or even those crowned with flowers by another man}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dhammatalks.net/suttacentral/sc/zh/ma128.html 優婆塞經] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170218064551/http://www.dhammatalks.net/suttacentral/sc/zh/ma128.html |date=18 February 2017 }}(Upāsaka Sutra from Madhyam āgama):復次，舍梨子！白衣聖弟子離邪婬、斷邪婬，彼或有父所護，或母所護，或父母所護，或兄弟所護，或姉妹所護，或婦父母所護，或親親所護，或同姓所護，或為他婦女，有鞭罰恐怖，及有名雇債至華鬘親，不犯如是女。彼於邪淫淨除其心，白衣聖弟子善護行，此第三法&lt;/ref&gt; and some [[Theravada|Theravādin]] [[Buddhist monasticism|monks]] express that same-gender relations do not violate the rule to avoid sexual misconduct, which means not having sex with someone under age (thus protected by their parents or guardians), someone betrothed or married and who have taken vows of religious celibacy.&lt;ref&gt;
* {{cite web|author1=Ajahn Punnadhammo|title=Same Sex Marriage|url=http://www.arrowriver.ca/torStar/samesex.html|quote=The lay man is told to abstain from sex with "unsuitable partners" defined as girls under age, women betrothed or married and women who have taken vows of religious celibacy. This is clear, sound advice and seems to suggest that sexual misconduct is that which would disrupt existing family or love relationships. This is consonant with the general Buddhist principle that that which causes suffering for oneself or others is unethical behaviour. ("Unskillful behaviour" would be closer to the original.) There is no good reason to assume that '''''homosexual relations which do not violate this principle''''' should be treated differently. }}
* {{cite book|author1=Somdet Phra Buddhaghosacariya|title=Uposatha Sila The Eight-Precept Observance|date=1993|url=http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/nanavara/uposatha.html}}There are '''four factors of the third precept''' (kamesu micchacara)
#agamaniya vatthu – that which should not be visited (the 20 groups of women).
#asmim sevana-cittam – the intention to have intercourse with anyone included in the above-mentioned groups. 
#sevanap-payogo – the effort at sexual intercourse. 
#maggena maggappatipatti – sexual contact through that adhivasanam effort.
* {{cite book|author1=Bhikkhu Bodhi|title=Going for Refuge &amp; Taking the Precepts (The Five Precepts)|date=1981|publisher=Buddhist Publication Society|url=http://bodhimonastery.org/going-for-refuge-taking-the-precepts.html#prec2}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Views on homosexuality and LGBT rights differ in the [[Buddhism|Buddhist tradition]]. However, many Buddhist leaders and groups have been historically supportive and continue to be supportive of LGBT people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=The Buddhist pioneers of same-sex marriage in the West: a little-known history of compassion in action by Dr Michael Vermeulen|url=http://www.ebumagazine.org/2018/06/27/the-buddhist-pioneers-of-same-sex-marriage-in-the-west-a-little-known-history-of-compassion-in-action-dr-michael-vermeulen/|access-date=2021-03-27|language=it-IT}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Michael|first=Vermeulen|date=September 2017|title=Special Rapporteur's Compilation of Articles on Freedom of religion or belief and Sexuality: The rise of Rainbow Dharma: Buddhism on sexual diversity and same-sex marriage by Michael Vermeulen|url=https://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Issues/Religion/ArticlesCompilationForbAndSexuality.pdf|url-status=live|website=The Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights (UN Human Rights)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Atwood|first=Haleigh|title=LGBTQ Buddhists: Teachings, Profiles, and Conversations – Lion's Roar|url=https://www.lionsroar.com/lgbtq-buddhism/|access-date=2021-03-27|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Jackson|first=Peter Anthony|date=December 1995|title=Thai Buddhist accounts of male homosexuality and AIDS in the 1980s|url=http://ccbs.ntu.edu.tw/FULLTEXT/JR-EPT/anth.htm|url-status=live|journal=The Australian Journal of Anthropology|volume=6|issue=3|pages=140–53|doi=10.1111/j.1835-9310.1995.tb00133.x|pmid=12291560}}&lt;/ref&gt; The renowned [[Vietnamese Thiền|Thiền Buddhist]] master, [[Thích Nhất Hạnh]], remarked that the spirit of Buddhism is inclusiveness and stated that "when you look at the ocean, you see different kinds of waves, many sizes and shapes, but all the waves have water as their foundation and substance. If you are born gay or lesbian, your ground of being in the same as mine. We are different, but we share the same ground of being."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2009-03-29|title=Thich Nhat Hanh: On Homosexuality|url=https://isanghamahal.wordpress.com/2009/03/29/thich-nhat-hanh-on-homosexuality/|access-date=2021-03-20|website=praktis isanghamahal|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Nhat.|first=Hanh, Thich|url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/730045848|title=Answers from the Heart : Practical Responses to Life's Burning Questions.|date=2009|publisher=Parallax Press|isbn=978-1-935209-00-3|oclc=730045848}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Japan]]'s [[Japanese culture|culture]] and [[Religion in Japan|major religions]] don't have a history of hostility towards homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Sam Shoushi|date=2008-03-25|title=Japan and Sexual Minorities &amp;#124; ヒューライツ大阪|url=http://www.hurights.or.jp/archives/focus/section2/2008/06/japan-and-sexual-minorities.html|access-date=2014-06-16|publisher=Hurights.or.jp}}&lt;/ref&gt; Same-sex marriages are performed at [[Shunkō-in]], a [[Rinzai Zen]] Buddhist temple in [[Kyoto]], Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kure|first=Rena|date=22 October 2015|title=Buddhist Priest Invites Same-Sex Couples To Marry at His Temple|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/shunkoin-temple-gay-marriage_us_56290990e4b0aac0b8fbeb01|access-date=5 April 2017|work=[[HuffPost]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some modern Buddhist leaders were active in the movement for same-sex marriage rights in [[Taiwan]], which legalized same-sex marriages in 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Hollingsworth |first=Julia |date=2019-05-17|title=Taiwan legalizes same-sex marriage in historic first for Asia|url=https://www.cnn.com/2019/05/17/asia/taiwan-same-sex-marriage-intl/index.html|access-date=2021-03-27|publisher=CNN|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Buddhist Nun Leads Asia's Fight for Gay Marriage|url=https://bulletin.hds.harvard.edu/buddhist-nun-leads-asias-fight-for-gay-marriage/|access-date=2021-03-27|website=Harvard Divinity Bulletin|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Taiwan to stage first same-sex Buddhist wedding|url=https://sg.news.yahoo.com/taiwan-stage-first-same-sex-buddhist-wedding-061917131.html|access-date=2021-03-27|publisher=Yahoo! News|language=en-SG}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |first=Craig |last=Lewis |title=Taiwanese Buddhist Master Ven. Shih Chao-hwei Selected for 38th Niwano Peace Prize |date=26 February 2021 |url=https://www.buddhistdoor.net/news/taiwanese-buddhist-master-ven-shih-chao-hwei-selected-for-38th-niwano-peace-prize|url-status=live|website=Buddhistdoor Global}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some adherents of the [[Navayana|Navayāna (Ambedkarite) Buddhist tradition]] are supporting LGBT rights within their larger activist activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Activism under the auspices of dhamma|url=http://www.advojka.cz/archiv/2020/23/activism-under-the-auspices-of-dhamma|access-date=2021-03-29|website=advojka.cz}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Thailand]], some leaders in the [[Theravada|Theravāda tradition]] including Phra Payom Kalayano have expressed support for LGBT rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Limited|first=Bangkok Post Public Company|title=Young monks struggle with gender issues|work=Bangkok Post|url=https://www.bangkokpost.com/thailand/special-reports/351847/gay-and-transgender-katoey-struggle-with-buddhism|access-date=2021-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Chandran|first=Rina|date=2020-08-21|title='LGBT people are also humans': Thai Buddhist monk backs equality|language=en|work=Reuters|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-thailand-lgbt-religion-interview-trfn-idUSKBN25H0RZ|access-date=2021-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Lewis|first=Craig|title=Buddhist Monk Seeks Equality, Acceptance for Thailand's LGBT+ Communities|url=https://www.buddhistdoor.net/news/buddhist-monk-seeks-equality-acceptance-for-thailandrsquos-lgbt-communities|website=Buddhistdoor Global}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997, the [[14th Dalai Lama|14th Dalai Lama Tenzin Gyatso]] declared: "From a Buddhist point of view, men-to-men and women-to-women is generally considered sexual misconduct."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sfgate.com/news/article/Dalai-Lama-Speaks-on-Gay-Sex-He-says-it-s-wrong-2836591.php |work=San Francisco Chronicle |date=1997-06-11 |title=Dalai Lama Speaks on Gay Sex / He says it's wrong for Buddhists but not for society}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this view expressed by the Dalai Lama is not based on the teachings of [[Gautama Buddha]] but derived from some later [[Abhidharma]] texts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Thubten Chodron|title=Dealing With Life's Issues|url=https://thubtenchodron.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Dealing-With-Lifes-Issues.pdf|quote=The Pali scriptures make no mention of homosexuality being unwise sexual conduct. For monastics, all sexual intercourse is a root downfall. It doesn't specify the gender of one's partner. Vasubandhu, a teacher who came several centuries after the Buddha, discouraged homosexuality. Personally speaking, I think what's most important is the motivation behind how we use our sexuality. In other words, if people use their sexuality unkindly or unwisely, it doesn't matter if it is directed to someone of their own sex or the opposite sex.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the Dalai Lama has repeatedly "voiced his support for the full recognition of human rights for all people, regardless of sexual orientation."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2006-04-23|title=Dalai Lama urges 'full human rights for all,' including gays|url=http://quietmountain.org/links/teachings/gayrites.htm|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060423234456/http://quietmountain.org/links/teachings/gayrites.htm|url-status=dead|archive-date=2006-04-23|access-date=2021-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the most recent interview with the Dalai Lama on this topic (10 March 2014), the Dalai Lama said gay marriage is "OK", provided it's not in contradiction with the values of one's chosen religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=The Dalai Lama Weighs in on Same Sex Marriage {{!}} Dalai Lama Interview {{!}} Larry King Now – Ora TV|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pJVvVSr8E2M|language=en|access-date=2021-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Dalai Lama Voices Support for Gay Marriage|url=https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/dalai-lama-voices-support-gay-marriage-n46906|access-date=2021-03-20|publisher=NBC News|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in the Tibetan tradition, the [[Nalandabodhi]] [[Sangha (Buddhism)|sangha]] has stated that they are welcoming of all sexual orientations and well-known Bhutanese lama [[Khyentse Norbu]] has expressed support for LGBT rights in [[Bhutan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=The Buddhist View on LGBTQ and Smoking|url=https://thebhutanese.bt/the-buddhist-view-on-lgbtq-and-smoking/|access-date=2021-04-13|website=The Bhutanese|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Western Buddhism|Western Buddhist denominations]], there is widescale support for LGBT rights from Buddhist groups and organizations, including the [[European Buddhist Union]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt;|date=2015-07-03|title=Rainbow Sangha|url=http://europeanbuddhism.org/activity/rainbow/|access-date=2021-03-27|website=European Buddhist Union|language=en|archive-date=20 November 2021|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20211120232630/http://europeanbuddhism.org/activity/rainbow/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Buddhist Churches of America,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Seattle Betsuin Brings New Light to LGBTQ Issues: Northwest Dharma Association|url=https://northwestdharma.org/rainbowsea/|access-date=2021-03-27|website=northwestdharma.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Wilson|first=Jeff|title="All Beings Are Equally Embraced By Amida Buddha": Jodo Shinshu Buddhism and Same-Sex Marriage in the United States|url=http://www.globalbuddhism.org/jgb/index.php/jgb/article/viewFile/125/140|url-status=dead|website=Journal of Global Buddhism Vol. 13 (2012): 31–59|access-date=20 November 2021|archive-date=13 April 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180413123019/http://www.globalbuddhism.org/jgb/index.php/jgb/article/viewFile/125/140}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Affairs|first=Berkley Center for Religion, Peace and World|title=Buddha's Big Shrug: The Non-Conflictual History of Same-Sex Marriage in the Buddhist Churches of America|url=https://berkleycenter.georgetown.edu/responses/buddha-s-big-shrug-the-non-conflictual-history-of-same-sex-marriage-in-the-buddhist-churches-of-america|access-date=2021-03-27|website=berkleycenter.georgetown.edu|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; many Shin Buddhist groups,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Seminar traces roots of Buddhists' support for LGBTQ rights » Nichi Bei|url=https://www.nichibei.org/2014/07/seminar-traces-roots-of-buddhists-support-for-lgbtq-rights/|access-date=2021-03-27|website=nichibei.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Zen leaders such as [[Thích Nhất Hạnh]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Nhất Hạnh|first=Thích|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/701109195|title=Answers from the heart : practical responses to life's burning questions|date=2009|publisher=Parallax Press|isbn=978-1-935209-00-3|location=Berkeley, Calif.|oclc=701109195}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2009-03-29|title=Thich Nhat Hanh: On Homosexuality|url=https://isanghamahal.wordpress.com/2009/03/29/thich-nhat-hanh-on-homosexuality/|access-date=2021-03-27|website=praktis isanghamahal|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Federation of Australian Buddhist Councils (FABC), representing Buddhist laypeople, and the Australian Sangha Association vocally supported [[same-sex marriage]] in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Potts|first=Andrew M.|publisher=Sydney Star|date=2012-04-19|title=Buddhists come out for equality|url=https://www.starobserver.com.au/news/buddhists-come-out-for-equality/75906|access-date=2021-03-27|website=Star Observer|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Soka Gakkai International-USA (SGI-USA) is the most diverse Buddhist community in the United States with more than 500 chapters and some 100 centers throughout the country supports LGBT rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=USA|first=Soka Gakkai International-|title=Courageous Freedom: SGI-USA's LGBTQ Community –|url=http://www.sgi-usa.org/2016/05/19/courageous-freedom-sgi-usas-lgbtq-community/|access-date=2021-03-29|website=Soka Gakkai International – USA|language=en|archive-date=20 November 2021|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20211120232629/http://www.sgi-usa.org/2016/05/19/courageous-freedom-sgi-usas-lgbtq-community/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; American [[Soka Gakkai]] Buddhists have performed same-sex union ceremonies since the 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Dart|first=John|date=1 July 1995|title=U.S. Buddhist Group Approves Marriage-Like Rights for Gays|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1995-07-01/local/me-19075_1_buddhist-groups|access-date=5 April 2017|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a PEW research poll, 88% of American Buddhists stated that homosexuality should be accepted.&lt;ref name="pewforum.org"&gt;{{Cite web|title=Religion in America: U.S. Religious Data, Demographics and Statistics|url=https://www.pewforum.org/religious-landscape-study/|access-date=2021-03-29|website=Pew Research Center's Religion &amp; Public Life Project|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was a higher level of support than any other religious group studied.&lt;ref name="pewforum.org" /&gt;

====Sikhism====
{{Main|Sikhism and sexual orientation}}
The Sikh holy book, the [[Guru Granth Sahib]], does not explicitly mention homosexuality. The Guru Granth Sahib is seen as the spiritual authority on all Sikh matters. [[File:Shik-Believers demonstrate at Pride 2011 in London for the acceptance of lgbti - people in their religion.jpg|thumb|LGBT Sikh-Believers demonstrate in London for the acceptance of lgbti - people in their religion]] [[File:Shik-Believers for lgbti - acceptance at London Pride parade.jpg|thumb|Shik-Believers for lgbti - acceptance at London Pride]]

Some modern Sikh leaders have condemned homosexuality. Giani Joginder Singh Vedanti of the temporal Sikh authority ([[Akal Takht]]), has condemned homosexuality while reminding visiting Sikh-Canadian [[Member of Parliament|Members of Parliament]] (MPs) of their religious duty to oppose [[same-sex marriage]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2005/03/28/sikhguy-050328.html World Sikh group against gay marriage bill], [[CBC Newsworld|CBC News]], Tuesday, 29 March 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; The Sikh religious body, the [[Akal Takht]], has issued an edict condemning gay marriage.&lt;ref name="Cohn"&gt;Martin Regg Cohn, ''Reject gay bill, Sikh MPs told; Warning from top religious authority says marriage backers will be shunned,'' [[Toronto Star]], Toronto, 28 March 2005, p. A.1.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other Sikhs point out that Sikhism does not condemn homosexuality or gay marriage&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.projectnaad.com/wp-content/uploads/leaflets/sikhism_yoga_and_sexuality.pdf|title=Sikhism, Yoga and Sexuality|last=Naad|first=Project|date=2010-09-02|publisher=Project Naad|page=33|access-date=2 September 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101011162907/http://www.projectnaad.com/wp-content/uploads/leaflets/sikhism_yoga_and_sexuality.pdf|archive-date=11 October 2010|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; reminding them that the Guru Granth Sahib leaves this as a matter of personal conscience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sarbat.net/2007/10/sikhism-and-same-sex-marriages/|title=Sikhism and same Sex Marriages|publisher=sarbat.net|page=1|access-date=3 September 2010|archive-date=14 September 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100914021542/http://www.sarbat.net/2007/10/sikhism-and-same-sex-marriages/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Eastern and Southeast Asian religions===

====Chinese folk religion====
{{Main|Chinese folk religion}}
{{Further|Homosexuality in China}}

[[Tu'er Shen]], also known as the Rabbit God, is a gay [[Shen (Chinese religion)|Chinese deity]]. In 2006, Lu Wei-ming founded a temple for Tu'er Shen in [[Yonghe District]] in the [[New Taipei City]] in [[Taiwan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thestar.com.my/lifestyle/people/2015/01/26/praying-for-a-soul-mate-at-rabbit-temple|title=Praying for a soul mate at Rabbit Temple|last=GOLD|first=MICHAEL|date=2015-01-26|website=The Star Online|language=en|access-date=2019-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; which has been called the world's only religious shrine for gay people.&lt;ref name="Gold 2015Reuters"/&gt; About 9,000 pilgrims visit the temple each year praying to find a suitable partner.&lt;ref name="Gold HuffPost"&gt;{{cite web | last=Gold | first=Michael | title=Taiwan's Wei-Ming 'Rabbit' Temple Draws Gay Community | website=HuffPost | date=2016-02-02 | url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/2015/01/19/taiwan-gay-temple-_n_6499210.html | access-date=2019-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Wei-ming temple also performs love ceremonies for gay couples.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.newnownext.com/taiwanese-rabbit-temple-drawing-gay-pilgrims/01/2015/|title=Thousands of Gay Pilgrims Trek To Taiwan To Pray For Love At "Rabbit" Temple|last=Alexander Stevenson 1/22/2015|website=LOGO News|access-date=2019-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the world's only religious shrine for homosexuals,&lt;ref name="Gold 2015Reuters"&gt;{{cite web | last=Gold | first=Michael | title=Taiwan's gays pray for soul mates at 'Rabbit' temple | work=Reuters| date=2015-01-19 | url=https://www.reuters.com/article/taiwan-gay-temple-idINKBN0KS0R120150119 | access-date=2019-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the temple performs love ceremonies for gay couples.&lt;ref name="Stevenson 2015"&gt;{{cite web | last=Stevenson | first=Alexander | title=Thousands of Gay Pilgrims Trek To Taiwan To Pray For Love At "Rabbit" Temple | website=LOGO News | date=2015-01-22 | url=http://www.newnownext.com/taiwanese-rabbit-temple-drawing-gay-pilgrims/01/2015/ | access-date=2019-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Confucianism====
{{Main|LGBT topics and Confucianism}}

====Shintoism====
{{Main|LGBT topics and Shinto}}

Historically, the [[Shintoism|Shinto religion]] "had no special code of morals and seems to have regarded sex as a natural phenomenon to be enjoyed with few inhibitions."&lt;ref name="Crompton 2003"&gt;{{cite book |last=Crompton |first=Louis |author-link=Louis Crompton |year=2003 |title=Homosexuality and Civilization |chapter=Pre-Meiji Japan |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TfBYd9xVaXcC&amp;pg=PA413 |location=[[Cambridge, Massachusetts]] |publisher=[[Harvard University Press]] |isbn=9780674022331 |lccn=2003245327 |page=413 |quote=[[Japanese Shintoism]] was principally concerned with propitiatory rites and ceremonies; [[Japanese mythology|its mythology]] fostered nationalism through the [[Imperial cult#Ancient and Imperial Japan|cult of divine emperors]], but it had no special code of morals and seems to have regarded sex as a natural phenomenon to be enjoyed with few inhibitions. [[Phallus|Phallic]] [[Shinto shrine|shrines]] dotted the countryside. Premarital virginity was not rigidly insisted upon, and freeborn boys did not lose status if they had adult lovers. Early law codes penalized incest and bestiality but not [[homosexual relations]]. The [[Shinto gods|gods of the Shinto pantheon]] were themselves highly sexual. In later times, some of them were seen as "guardian deities" of [[Love between men|male love]].}}&lt;/ref&gt; While [[Shinto#Beliefs|Shinto beliefs]] are diverse, Japanese Shintoism doesn't condemn homosexuality,&lt;ref name="Crompton 2003"/&gt; and the formally organized [[Konkokyo]] sect is fully affirming.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=May 2017|title=Face to Faith No.89|url=http://kic.jpn.org/jpn/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/No89.pdf|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Bernkastel|first=Olivia|date=2018-12-15|title=Throughout the years and even now, I have often been asked the view Shinto holds in regard to…|url=https://medium.com/@livingwithkami/throughout-the-years-and-even-now-i-have-often-been-asked-the-view-shinto-holds-in-regard-to-6d9eb0057997|access-date=2021-08-25|website=Medium|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Living with Kami|url=https://www.livingwithkami.com/post/171313633965/great-news-from-konkokyo-message-below-from-the|access-date=2021-08-25|website=Living with Kami|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Multiple Shinto leaders advocated in support of [[Same-sex marriage in Hawaii|gay marriage in Hawaii]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=31 October 2013|title=Testimony in support of SB1 Relating to Equal Rights|url=https://www.capitol.hawaii.gov/splsession2013b/SB1_Testimony_JUD-FIN_10-31-13_InPerson_Part1.pdf|url-status=live|website=Capitol.Hawaii.Gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Zoroastrianism====
{{Main|Zoroastrianism and sexual orientation}}

===Indigenous religions===
====African Diasporic religions====
{{Main|Haitian Vodou and sexual orientation}}

Homosexuality is religiously acceptable in [[Haitian Vodou]].&lt;ref name="Haiti's fight for gay rights"&gt;{{Cite web|title=Haiti's fight for gay rights|url=http://projects.aljazeera.com/2014/haiti-lgbt/|access-date=2021-03-27|publisher=Al Jazeera}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Homosexuality And Voodoo"&gt;{{cite web|date=20 July 2013|title=Homosexuality And Voodoo|url=http://www.haitiobserver.com/blog/homosexuality-and-voodoo.html|access-date=30 March 2021|website=Haiti Observer}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="advocate.com"&gt;{{Cite web|date=2016-10-31|title=Queer Haitians Find a Refuge in Vodou|url=http://www.advocate.com/current-issue/2016/10/31/why-queer-haitians-are-turning-vodou|access-date=2021-03-27|website=advocate.com|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The lwa or loa (spirits) Erzulie Dantor and Erzulie Freda are often associated with and viewed as protectors of queer people.&lt;ref name="Review"&gt;{{Cite web|last=Review|first=The Global Catholic|date=2018-06-06|title=Black Madonna Vodou Religion Spirit Lwa Erzulie Dantor by Kate Kingsbury|url=https://www.patheos.com/blogs/theglobalcatholicreview/2018/06/polish-black-madonna-haitian-vodou-spirit-erzulie-dantor-kate-kingsbury-africa-love-religion/|access-date=2021-03-27|website=The Global Catholic Review|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="lisantiadmin"&gt;{{Cite web|last=lisantiadmin|title=Haiti's LGBTQ-Accepting Vodou Societies|url=https://www.irenemonroe.com/haitis-lgbtq-accepting-vodou-societies/|access-date=2021-03-27|website=Rev Irene Monroe|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within [[Candomblé]], a [[Syncretism|syncretic]] religion founds primarily found in Brazil, there is widespread (though not universal) support for gay rights, many members are LGBT, and have performed gay marriages.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=CartaCapital|date=2017-09-22|title=Homossexualidade e candomblé|url=https://www.cartacapital.com.br/blogs/dialogos-da-fe/homossexualidade-e-candomble/|access-date=2021-05-01|website=CartaCapital|language=pt-BR}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Moutinho|first=Laura|year=2013|title=Homosexuality, skin color and religiosity: flirting among the "povo de santo" in Rio de Janeiro|url=http://www.clam.org.br/uploads/publicacoes/book2/32.pdf|journal=CLAM. Sexuality, Culture and Politics – A South American Reader|pages=573–592|isbn=978-85-89737-82-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GI São Paulo"&gt;{{cite web|date=27 February 2017|title=Casal gay celebra casamento umbandista em bloco no centro de São Paulo|url=https://g1.globo.com/sao-paulo/carnaval/2017/noticia/casal-celebra-casamento-em-bloco-de-carnaval-no-centro-de-sao-paulo.ghtml|work=GI São Paulo|language=pt}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Homossexualidade e candomblé"&gt;{{cite web|date=22 September 2017|title=Homossexualidade e candomblé|url=https://www.cartacapital.com.br/blogs/dialogos-da-fe/homosexualidade-e-candomble/|work=Carta Capital|language=pt}}{{Dead link|date=October 2022 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Practitioners of [[Santería]], primarily found in Cuba, generally (though not universally) welcome LGBT members and include them in religious or ritual activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Introduction ~ ¡Homofobia no! ¡Socialismo sí! Identity, culture, gender and sexuality in today's Cuba ~ Minority Stories|url=https://stories.minorityrights.org/afrocuba-lgbtqi/chapter/introduction/|access-date=2021-05-01|website=stories.minorityrights.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Vidal-Ortiz|first=Salvador|year=2006|title=Sexuality discussions in santería: A case study of religion and sexuality negotiation|url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1525/srsp.2006.3.3.52|journal=Sexuality Research and Social Policy|volume=3|issue=3|pages=52–66|doi=10.1525/srsp.2006.3.3.52|s2cid=144582747|issn=1868-9884}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also a Brazilian syncretic religion, [[Umbanda]] houses generally support LGBT rights and have performed gay marriages.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Brazil gays celebrate first mass wedding|url=https://www.pri.org/stories/2011-06-23/brazil-gays-celebrate-first-mass-wedding|access-date=2021-05-01|website=The World from PRX|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GI São Paulo"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Homossexualidade e candomblé"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Ogland|first1=Curtis P.|last2=Verona|first2=Ana Paula|year=2014|title=Religion and the rainbow struggle: does religion factor into attitudes toward homosexuality and same-sex civil unions in Brazil?|url=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24914634/|journal=Journal of Homosexuality|volume=61|issue=9|pages=1334–1349|doi=10.1080/00918369.2014.926767|issn=1540-3602|pmid=24914634|s2cid=32139660}}&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexuality is religiously acceptable in [[Haitian Vodou]].&lt;ref name="Haiti's fight for gay rights"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Homosexuality And Voodoo"/&gt;&lt;ref name="advocate.com"/&gt; The lwa or loa (spirits) [[Ezili Dantor|Erzulie Dantor]] and [[Erzulie|Erzulie Freda]] are often associated with and viewed as protectors of queer people.&lt;ref name="Review"/&gt;&lt;ref name="lisantiadmin"/&gt; The lao [[Ghede Nibo]] is sometimes depicted as an effeminate drag queen and inspires those he inhabits to lascivious sexuality of all kinds.&lt;ref name="Cassell"&gt;Randy Conner, David Hatfield Sparks &amp; Mariya Sparks (eds), Cassell's ''Encyclopedia of Queer Myth, Symbol &amp; Spirit'', p. 963, London and New York: Cassell, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Conner, p. 157, "Ghede Nibo"&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ancient Mesopotamian religion====
{{Main|Ancient Mesopotamian religion}}

Individuals who went against the traditional [[gender binary]] were heavily involved in the cult of [[Inanna]], an ancient Mesopotamian goddess.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book|last= Leick.|first= Dr. Gwendolyn|url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/1120210531|title=Sex and Eroticism in Mesopotamian Literature|isbn=978-0-203-41428-6|oclc=1120210531}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=LGBTQ+ in the Ancient World|url=https://www.worldhistory.org/article/1790/lgbtq-in-the-ancient-world/|access-date=2021-08-28|website=World History Encyclopedia|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; During Sumerian times, a set of priests known as ''[[Gala (priests)|gala]]'' worked in Inanna's temples, where they performed elegies and lamentations.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Men who became ''gala'' sometimes adopted female names and their songs were composed in the Sumerian ''[[Sumerian language#Dialects|eme-sal]]'' dialect, which, in literary texts, is normally reserved for the speech of female characters. Some Sumerian proverbs seem to suggest that ''gala'' had a reputation for engaging in [[anal sex]] with men.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Murray|first=Stephen O.|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/35526232|title=Islamic homosexualities : culture, history, and literature|date=1997|others=Will Roscoe|isbn=0-8147-7467-9|location=New York|oclc=35526232}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the Akkadian Period, ''kurgarrū'' and ''assinnu'' were servants of Ishtar who [[Cross-dressing|dressed in female clothing]] and performed war dances in Ishtar's temples.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; Several Akkadian [[proverb]]s seem to suggest that they may have also had homosexual proclivities.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; Gwendolyn Leick, an anthropologist known for her writings on Mesopotamia, has compared these individuals to the contemporary Indian ''[[Hijra (South Asia)|hijra]].''&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; In one Akkadian hymn, Ishtar is described as transforming men into women.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; Some modern pagans include Inanna in their worship.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/966491570|title=Cosmopolitanism, nationalism, and modern paganism|date=2017|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan US|others=Kathryn Rountree|isbn=978-1-137-56200-5|location=New York|oclc=966491570}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pre-colonial religions of the Americas====
{{Main|Alaska Native religion|Mesoamerican religion|Native American religion|Inuit religion}}
{{Further|Same-sex marriage in tribal nations in the United States}}
[[File:Catlin - Dance to the berdache.jpg|thumb|Drawing by [[George Catlin]] (1796–1872) while on the [[Great Plains]] among the [[Sac and Fox Nation]]. Depicting a group of male warriors dancing around a male-bodied person in a woman's dress, non-Native artist George Catlin titled the painting ''Dance to the Berdache''.]]

Among the [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas]] prior to the [[European colonization of the Americas|European colonization]], many Nations had respected ceremonial, religious, and social roles for homosexual, bisexual, and gender-nonconforming individuals in their communities and in many contemporary [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] and [[First Nations in Canada|First Nations]] communities, these roles still exist.&lt;ref name="Estrada"&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://nativeout.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Two-Spirits-Nadleeh-and-Navajo-LGBTQ2-Gaze.pdf |title=Two Spirits, Nádleeh, and LGBTQ2 Navajo Gaze |journal=American Indian Culture and Research Journal |volume=35 |issue=4 |pages=167–190 |last=Estrada |first=Gabriel S |year=2011 |doi=10.17953/aicr.35.4.x500172017344j30 |access-date=29 September 2021 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150513044527/http://nativeout.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Two-Spirits-Nadleeh-and-Navajo-LGBTQ2-Gaze.pdf |archive-date=13 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="terms"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nativeout.com/twospirit-rc/two-spirit-101/two-spirit-terms-in-tribal-languages/ |title=Two Spirit Terms in Tribal Languages |website=Native Out |access-date=29 September 2021 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150102172337/http://nativeout.com/twospirit-rc/two-spirit-101/two-spirit-terms-in-tribal-languages/ |archive-date=2 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="de Vries 2009"&gt;{{cite book|last1=de Vries|first1=Kylan Mattias|title=Encyclopedia of gender and society|date=2009|publisher=SAGE|isbn=9781412909167|editor1-last=O'Brien|editor1-first=Jodi|location=Los Angeles|page=64|chapter=Berdache (Two-Spirit)|access-date=6 March 2015|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_nyHS4WyUKEC}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kehoe"&gt;{{cite web|last=Kehoe|first=Alice B.|author-link=Alice Beck Kehoe|year=2002|title=Appropriate Terms|url=https://www.saa.org/publications/saabulletin/16-2/saa14.html|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20041105120021/https://www.saa.org/publications/saabulletin/16-2/saa14.html|archive-date=2004-11-05|access-date=2019-05-01|work=SAA Bulletin|publisher=Society for American Archaeology 16(2), [[UC-Santa Barbara]]|issn=0741-5672}}&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexual and gender-variant individuals were also common among other pre-[[Spanish colonization of the Americas|conquest]] civilizations in [[Latin America]], such as the [[Aztec]]s, [[Maya civilization|Mayans]], [[Quechuas]], [[Moche (culture)|Moches]], [[Zapotec civilization|Zapotecs]], and the [[Tupinambá people|Tupinambá]] of Brazil and were accepted in their various religions.&lt;ref name="glbtqlatinamerica"&gt;{{citation|last=Pablo|first=Ben|title=Latin America: Colonial|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/latin_america_colonial.html|periodical=[[glbtq.com]]|year=2004|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071211012339/http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/latin_america_colonial.html|access-date=2007-08-01|archive-date=2007-12-11|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="glbtqmex"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|year=2004|title=Mexico|encyclopedia=glbtq: An Encyclopedia of Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer Culture|publisher=[[glbtq.com|glbtq, Inc.]]|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/mexico.html|access-date=2007-08-01|last=Murray|first=Stephen|author-link=Stephen O. Murray|editor=Claude J. Summers|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071102132531/http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/mexico.html|archive-date=2007-11-02|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===New religious movements===
Since the beginning of the [[Sexual revolution|sexual liberation movement]] in the Western world, which coincided with [[second-wave feminism]] and the [[women's liberation movement]] initiated in the early 1960s,&lt;ref name="Urban 2007"&gt;{{cite book |last=Urban |first=Hugh B. |author-link=Hugh Urban |year=2007 |origyear=2003 |chapter=The Cult of Ecstasy: Meldings of East and West in a New Age of Tantra |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wvtLClojU_4C&amp;pg=PA203 |title=Tantra: Sex, Secrecy, Politics, and Power in the Study of Religion |location=[[Berkeley, California|Berkeley]] and [[Delhi]] |publisher=[[University of California Press]]/[[Motilal Banarsidass]] |edition=1st |pages=203–263 |doi=10.1525/california/9780520230620.003.0007 |isbn=9780520236561 |jstor=10.1525/j.ctt1pp4mm.12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Pike 2004"&gt;{{cite book |last=Pike |first=Sarah M. |author-link=Sarah M. Pike |year=2004 |chapter=Part II – “All Acts of Love and Pleasure Are My Rituals”: Sex, Gender, and the Sacred |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2DoK_bUwSR0C&amp;pg=PA115 |title=New Age and Neopagan Religions in America |location=[[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Columbia University Press]] |series=Columbia Contemporary American Religion Series |pages=115–144 |isbn=9780231508384 |jstor=10.7312/pike12402.10 |lccn=2003061844}}&lt;/ref&gt; new religious movements and alternative spiritualities such as [[Modern Paganism]] and the [[New Age]] began to grow and spread across the globe alongside their intersection with the sexual liberation movement and the [[counterculture of the 1960s]],&lt;ref name="Urban 2007"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Pike 2004"/&gt; and exhibited characteristic features, such as the embrace of [[alternative lifestyles]], unconventional dress, rejection of [[Abrahamic religions]] and their [[Social conservatism|conservative social mores]], use of [[Cannabis (drug)|cannabis]] and other [[Recreational drug use|recreational drugs]], relaxed attitude, [[Sarcasm|sarcastic humble]] or self-imposed poverty, and ''laissez-faire'' [[Human sexual activity|sexual behavior]].&lt;ref name="Urban 2007"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Pike 2004"/&gt; The sexual liberation movement was aided by feminist ideologues in their mutual struggle to challenge traditional ideas regarding [[Human female sexuality|female sexuality]], [[Human male sexuality|male sexuality]], and [[queer]] sexuality.&lt;ref name="Pike 2004"/&gt; Elimination of undue favorable bias towards men and objectification of women, as well as support for women's right to choose their sexual partners free of outside interference or societal judgment, were three of the main goals associated with sexual liberation from the feminist perspective.&lt;ref name="Pike 2004"/&gt;

====Modern Paganism====
Most [[Neopaganism|Neopagan religions]] have the theme of fertility (both physical and creative/spiritual) as central to their practices, and as such encourage what they view as a healthy sex life, consensual sex between adults, regardless of gender.

[[Heathenry (new religious movement)|Heathenry]], a [[Modern Paganism|modern Germanic Pagan movement]], includes several pro-LGBT groups. Some groups legitimize openness toward LGBT practitioners by reference to the gender-bending actions of [[Thor]] and [[Odin]] in [[Norse mythology]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/908932432|title=Contemporary pagan and native faith movements in Europe : colonialist and nationalist impulses|date=2015|others=Kathryn Rountree, European Association of Social Anthropologists|isbn=978-1-78238-647-6|location=New York|pages=64–84|oclc=908932432}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/908932432|title=Contemporary pagan and native faith movements in Europe : colonialist and nationalist impulses|date=2015|others=Kathryn Rountree, European Association of Social Anthropologists|isbn=978-1-78238-647-6|location=New York|oclc=908932432}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are, for instance, homosexual and [[transgender]] members of [[The Troth]], a prominent U.S. Heathen organisation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Rountree|first=Kathryn|year=2015|title=Contemporary Pagan and Native Faith Movements|url=https://www.stantonkeble.com/downloads/NATIVE-FAITH-MOVEMENTS.pdf|journal=Association of European Anthropologists|volume=26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many Heathen groups in Northern Europe perform [[same-sex marriage]]s,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/42330378|title=Magical religion and modern witchcraft|date=1996|publisher=State University of New York Press|others=James R. Lewis|isbn=0-585-03650-0|location=Albany, N.Y.|pages=193–236|oclc=42330378}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a group of self-described "Homo-Heathens" marched in the 2008 [[Stockholm Pride]] carrying a statue of the Norse god [[Freyr]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Schnurbein|first=Stefanie v.|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/964730476|title=Norse Revival : transformations of Germanic neopaganism|date=2017|isbn=978-1-60846-737-2|location=Chicago, IL|oclc=964730476}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research found a greater proportion of LGBT practitioners within Heathenry (21%) than wider society, although noted that the percentage was lower than in other forms of modern Paganism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Cragle|first=Joshua Marcus|date=2017-06-11|title=Contemporary Germanic/Norse Paganism and Recent Survey Data|url=https://www.equinoxpub.com/journals/index.php/POM/article/view/30714|journal=Pomegranate: The International Journal of Pagan Studies|volume=19|issue=1|pages=77–116|doi=10.1558/pome.30714|issn=1528-0268}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Wicca]], like other religions, has adherents with a broad spectrum of views, ranging from conservative to liberal. It is a largely nondogmatic religion and has no prohibitions against sexual intercourse outside of marriage or relationships between members of the same sex. The religion's ethics are largely summed up by the [[Wiccan Rede]]: "An it harm none, do as thou wilt", which is interpreted by many as allowing and endorsing responsible sexual relationships of all varieties. Specifically in the Wiccan tradition of modern witchcraft, one of the widely accepted pieces of [[Craft]] liturgy, the Charge of the Goddess instructs that "...all acts of love and pleasure are [the Goddess'] rituals",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Alternative Sexuality | publisher =Tangled Moon Coven |date=2006-08-08 | url =http://www.tangledmoon.org/sexuality.htm | access-date = 2006-12-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt; giving validity to all forms of sexual activity for Wiccan practitioners.

In the [[Gardnerian]] and [[Alexandrian Wicca|Alexandrian]] forms of Wicca, the "[[Great Rite]]" is a sex ritual much like the [[hieros gamos]], performed by a priest and priestess who are believed to embody the Wiccan God and Goddess. The Great Rite is almost always performed figuratively using the athame and chalice as symbols of the penis and vagina. The literal form of the ritual is always performed by consenting adults, by a couple who are already lovers and in private. The Great Rite is not seen as an opportunity for casual sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title =Sex, Wicca and the Great Rite | journal =The Blade &amp; Chalice | volume = Spring 1993 | issue = 3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Raëlism====
{{Main|Raëlism}}
{{Further|Raëlian beliefs and practices}}
[[File:Korea Queer Culture Festival 2014 58.JPG|thumb|230px|right|Raëlian participants attending the [[Korea Queer Culture Festival]] (2014)]]

[[Raëlism]], an international [[new religious movement]] and [[UFO religion]] which was founded in France in 1974,&lt;ref name="Palmer 2012"&gt;{{cite book |author1-last=Palmer |author1-first=Susan J. |author1-link=Susan J. Palmer |author2-last=Sentes |author2-first=Bryan |year=2012 |chapter=The International Raëlian Movement |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RM0AAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA167 |editor1-last=Hammer |editor1-first=Olav |editor1-link=Olav Hammer |editor2-last=Rothstein |editor2-first=Mikael |editor2-link=Mikael Rothstein |title=The Cambridge Companion to New Religious Movements |location=[[Cambridge]] |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |pages=167–183 |doi=10.1017/CCOL9780521196505.012 |isbn=978-0-521-19650-5 |lccn=2012015440 |s2cid=151563721}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dericquebourg 2021"&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Dericquebourg |author-first=Régis |author-link=Régis Dericquebourg |year=2021 |chapter=Rael and the Raelians |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tkswEAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA472 |editor-last=Zeller |editor-first=Ben |title=Handbook of UFO Religions |location=[[Leiden]] and [[Boston]] |publisher=[[Brill Publishers]] |series=Brill Handbooks on Contemporary Religion |volume=20 |doi=10.1163/9789004435537_024 |isbn=978-90-04-43437-0 |issn=1874-6691 |pages=472–490|s2cid=239738621}}&lt;/ref&gt; promotes a [[Sex-positive movement|positive outlook towards human sexuality]], including homosexuality.&lt;ref name="Palmer 2012"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Dericquebourg 2021"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Gregg 2014"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Gregg |first=Stephen E. |date=September 2014 |title=Queer Jesus, straight angels: Complicating 'sexuality' and 'religion' in the International Raëlian Movement |url=https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1363460714526129 |journal=[[Sexualities (journal)|Sexualities]] |publisher=[[SAGE Journals]] |volume=17 |issue=5–6 |pages=565–582 |doi=10.1177/1363460714526129 |issn=1461-7382 |hdl=2436/609871 |s2cid=147291471 |hdl-access=free |oclc=474576878}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Palmer 2014"&gt;{{cite book |last=Palmer |first=Susan J. |author-link=Susan J. Palmer |year=2014 |chapter=Raël's Angels: The First Five Years of a Secret Order |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7ZQMCgAAQBAJ |editor1-last=Bogdan |editor1-first=Henrik |editor2-last=Lewis |editor2-first=James R. |editor2-link=James R. Lewis (scholar) |title=Sexuality and New Religious Movements |location=[[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] |series=Palgrave Studies in New Religions and Alternative Spiritualities |pages=183–211 |doi=10.1057/9781137386434_9 |isbn=978-1-349-68146-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its founder [[Raël]] recognised same-sex marriage, and a Raëlian press release stated that sexual orientation is genetic and it also likened [[Homophobia|discrimination against gay people]] to [[racism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.raelpress.org/news.php?item.16.1 |title=A modern nation is a nation where gays and lesbians are free |date=25 March 2005 |website=Raelian Press Site |access-date=30 March 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Raëlian leaders have performed licensed same-sex marriages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://raelianews.org/news.php?item.524.10 |title=A Raelian official licensed to perform legal marriages for same-sex couples in Hawaii |date=18 July 2013 |website=Raelianews |access-date=30 March 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Santa Muerte====
The cult of [[Santa Muerte]] is a [[new religious movement]]&lt;ref name="Chesnut 2017"&gt;{{cite speech |last=Chesnut |first=R. Andrew |title=Santa Muerte: The Fastest Growing New Religious Movement in the Americas |url=https://www.up.edu/garaventa/archives/lectures-and-readings/2017-2018-lectures-and-readings/andrew-chesnut-lecture.html |url-status=live |event=Lecture |date=26 October 2017 |location=Portland, Oregon |publisher=[[University of Portland]] |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210207214656/https://www.up.edu/garaventa/archives/lectures-and-readings/2017-2018-lectures-and-readings/andrew-chesnut-lecture.html |archive-date=7 February 2021 |access-date=14 August 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; centered on the worship of Santa Muerte, a [[cult image]], [[female deity]], and [[folk saint]] which is popularly revered in [[Mexico|Mexican]] [[Modern Paganism|Neopaganism]] and [[folk Catholicism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Chesnut |author-first=R. Andrew |year=2016 |chapter=Healed by Death: Santa Muerte, the Curandera |editor-last=Hunt |editor-first=Stephen J. |editor-link=Stephen J. Hunt |title=Handbook of Global Contemporary Christianity: Movements, Institutions, and Allegiance |location=[[Leiden]] |publisher=[[Brill Publishers]] |series=Brill Handbooks on Contemporary Religion |volume=12 |doi=10.1163/9789004310780_017 |pages=336–353 |isbn=978-90-04-26539-4 |issn=1874-6691}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Flores Martos |author-first=Juan Antonio |year=2007 |chapter=La Santísima Muerte en Veracruz, México: Vidas Descarnadas y Práticas Encarnadas |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=F992RDiGJKEC&amp;pg=PA296 |editor1-last=Flores Martos |editor1-first=Juan Antonio |editor2-last=González |editor2-first=Luisa Abad |title=Etnografías de la muerte y las culturas en América Latina |location=[[Cuenca, Spain|Cuenca]] |publisher=[[University of Castilla–La Mancha|Ediciones de la Universidad de Castilla–La Mancha]] |language=es |pages=296–297 |isbn=978-84-8427-578-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[personification of death]], she is associated with healing, protection, and safe delivery to the [[afterlife]] by her devotees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Chesnut |first=R. Andrew |year=2018 |orig-date=2012 |title=Devoted to Death: Santa Muerte, the Skeleton Saint |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ul0vDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA6 |edition=Second |location=[[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |doi=10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199764662.001.0001 |pages=6–7 |isbn=978-0-19-063332-5 |lccn=2011009177}}&lt;/ref&gt; Santa Muerte is also revered and seen as a saint and protector of the [[LGBT in Mexico|lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer (LGBTQ+) communities in Mexico]],&lt;ref name="CIESAS 2019"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Bárcenas Barajas |first=Karina |date=September–December 2019 |title=Apropiaciones LGBT de la religiosidad popular |url=https://desacatos.ciesas.edu.mx/index.php/Desacatos/article/view/2135/1491 |journal=Desacatos: Revista de Ciencias Sociales |location=Mexico City |publisher=Centro de Investigaciones y Estudios Superiores en Antropología Social (CIESAS) |volume=61 |language=es |pages=98–113 |doi=10.29340/61.2135 |doi-broken-date=31 July 2022 |doi-access=free |issn=2448-5144 |access-date=16 June 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hemisphericinstitute.org"&gt;{{cite magazine |last=Lorentzen |first=Lois Ann |year=2016 |title=Santa Muerte: Saint of the Dispossessed, Enemy of Church and State |url=https://hemisphericinstitute.org/en/emisferica-13-1-states-of-devotion/13-1-essays/santa-muerte-saint-of-the-dispossessed-enemy-of-church-and-state.html |url-status=live |editor1-last=Pellegrini |editor1-first=Anna |editor2-last=Vaggione |editor2-first=Juan Marco |magazine=Emisférica |volume=13 |issue=1 |location=New York City |publisher=[[Hemispheric Institute of Performance and Politics]] |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190730153106/https://hemisphericinstitute.org/en/emisferica-13-1-states-of-devotion/13-1-essays/santa-muerte-saint-of-the-dispossessed-enemy-of-church-and-state.html |archive-date=30 July 2019 |access-date=14 August 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Woodman |first=Stephen |date=31 March 2017 |title=How a skeleton folk saint of death took off with Mexican transgender women |url=https://eu.usatoday.com/story/news/world/2017/03/31/santa-muerte-death-transgender-women-mexico/99867052/ |url-status=live |work=[[USA Today]] |issn=0734-7456 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20191010080701/https://eu.usatoday.com/story/news/world/2017/03/31/santa-muerte-death-transgender-women-mexico/99867052/ |archive-date=10 October 2019 |access-date=17 November 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |last=Villarreal |first=Daniel |date=6 April 2019 |title=Bishops tell Catholics to stop worshipping this unofficial LGBTQ-friendly saint of death: Even though "La Santa Muerte" is not a Church-sanctioned saint, millions of people still revere her |url=https://www.lgbtqnation.com/2019/04/bishops-asking-catholics-stop-worshipping-unofficial-lgbtq-friendly-saint-death/ |url-status=live |magazine=[[LGBTQ Nation]] |location=San Francisco |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190407080835/https://www.lgbtqnation.com/2019/04/bishops-asking-catholics-stop-worshipping-unofficial-lgbtq-friendly-saint-death/ |archive-date=7 April 2019 |access-date=16 June 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.outinthebay.com/archives.htm |title=Archives |year=2012 |website=outinthebay.com |publisher=Out in the Bay |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120424085030/http://www.outinthebay.com/archives.htm |archive-date=2012-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; since LGBTQ+ people are considered and treated as outcasts by the [[Catholic Church and homosexuality|Catholic Church]], [[Christianity and homosexuality#Evangelical churches|evangelical churches]], and Mexican society at large.&lt;ref name="CIESAS 2019"/&gt;&lt;ref name="hemisphericinstitute.org"/&gt; Many LGBTQ+ people ask her for protection from violence, hatred, disease, and to help them in their search for love. Her intercession is commonly invoked in [[Same-sex marriage in Mexico City|same-sex marriage ceremonies]] performed in Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.eluniversal.com.mx/notas/663167.html |title=Iglesia de Santa Muerte casa a gays – El Universal – Sociedad |newspaper=El Universal |date=2010-03-03 |access-date=2013-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=(MÉXICO) SOCIEDAD-SALUD &amp;gt; AREA: Asuntos sociales |url=http://www.abc.es/agencias/noticia.asp?noticia=296160 |title=La Iglesia de Santa Muerte mexicana celebró su primera boda gay y prevé 9 más – ABC.es – Noticias Agencias |work=ABC|location=Spain |access-date=2013-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Traditionalist Mexican-American Catholic Church|Iglesia Católica Tradicional México-Estados Unidos]], also known as the Church of Santa Muerte, [[recognition of same-sex unions in Mexico|recognizes]] gay marriage and performs religious wedding ceremonies for homosexual couples.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://los21.com/vision21/?p=3400 |title=La Nueva Iglesia De La Santa Muerte Permite Bodas Gay |publisher=Los21.com |date=2012-01-24 |access-date=2013-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mexicoytradicion.over-blog.org/article-la-santa-muerte-celebra-bodas-homosexuales-en-mexico-51509467.html |title=La Santa Muerte celebra 'bodas homosexuales' en México – México y Tradición |language=es |publisher=Mexicoytradicion.over-blog.org |date=2010-06-02 |access-date=2013-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tendenciagay.com/noticias/ampliar/789/culto-a-la-santa-muerte-casara-a-gays |title=Culto a la santa muerte casará a gays |publisher=Tendenciagay.com |date=2010-01-11 |access-date=2013-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.culteducation.com/reference/santa_muerta/santa_muerta7.html |title=Mexico's Holy Death Church Will Conduct Gay Weddings |publisher=Ross Institute |date=2010-01-07 |access-date=2013-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to R. Andrew Chesnut, [[Doctor of Philosophy|PhD]] in [[History of Latin America|Latin American history]] and [[professor]] of [[Religious studies]], the cult of Santa Muerte is the single fastest-growing new religious movement in the Americas.&lt;ref name="Chesnut 2017"/&gt;

====Satanism====
The [[Church of Satan]] has always accepted gays, lesbians and bisexuals since its foundation in 1966.&lt;ref name="COS FAQ"&gt;[http://www.churchofsatan.com/Pages/_FAQ10.html Church of Satan FAQ 10. SEXUALITY.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121101174746/http://www.churchofsatan.com/Pages/_FAQ10.html |date=1 November 2012 }} Church of Satan Official Website. Retrieved 28 October 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The church supports legalization of same-sex marriages.&lt;ref name = "COS FAQ"/&gt;

====Scientology====
{{Main|Scientology and sexual orientation}}

====Wicca====
{{Main|Wiccan views on LGBT people}}

==See also==
{{Portal|LGBT|Religion}}
{{columns-list|
* [[History of human sexuality]]
* [[LGBT history]]
** [[LGBT rights by country]]
** [[List of LGBT-related organizations and conferences]]
** [[Outline of transgender topics]]
** [[Timeline of LGBT history]]
* [[Religion and sexuality]]
** [[Homosexuality and religion]]
** [[LGBT-affirming religious groups]]
** [[LGBT themes in mythology]]
** [[Religious views on same-sex marriage]]
** [[Transgender people and religion]]
* [[Same-sex marriage]]
** [[History of same-sex unions]]
** [[Legal status of same-sex marriage]]
** [[Timeline of same-sex marriage]]
* [[Societal attitudes toward homosexuality]]
* [[Third gender]]
* [[Two-spirit]]
|colwidth=30em}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=note}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{cite book |last=Birdal |first=Mehmet Sinan |year=2020 |chapter=The State of Being LGBT in the Age of Reaction: Post-2011 Visibility and Repression in the Middle East and North Africa |editor1-last=Bosia |editor1-first=Michael J. |editor2-last=McEvoy |editor2-first=Sandra M. |editor3-last=Rahman |editor3-first=Momin |title=The Oxford Handbook of Global LGBT and Sexual Diversity Politics |location=[[Oxford]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |doi=10.1093/oxfordhb/9780190673741.013.16 |isbn=9780190673741}}
*[[John Boswell (historian)|John Boswell]], ''Christianity, Social Tolerance and Homosexuality: Gay People in Western Europe from the Beginning of the Christian Era to the Fourteenth Century'', University of Chicago Press, 1st ed. 1980 {{ISBN|0-226-06710-6}}, paperback Nov. 2005 {{ISBN|0-226-06711-4}}
*Dane S. Claussen, ed. ''Sex, Religion, Media,'' Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2002. {{ISBN|0-7425-1558-3}}
*Mathew Kuefler (editor), ''The Boswell Thesis: Essays on Christianity, Social Tolerance, and Homosexuality'', University of Chicago Press, Nov. 2005 {{ISBN|0-226-45741-9}}
*[[Eckhart Tolle]], ''The Power of Now: A Guide to Spiritual Enlightenment'', New World Library, 1st ed. 1999, paperback 2004 {{ISBN|1-57731-480-8}}
*Chana Etengoff. Petitioning for Change: Letters to Religious Leaders from Gay Men and their Religious Family Allies, ''Journal of Homosexuality.'' doi:[http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00918369.2016.1174022 10.1080/00918369.2016.1174022]
*Chana Etengoff &amp; Colette Daiute. (2014). [https://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/features/rel-a0035198.pdf Family Members’ Uses of Religion in Post–Coming-Out Conflicts with Their Gay Relative''.''] ''Psychology of Religion and Spirituality'', ''6''(1), 33–43. doi: 10.1037/a0035198
*{{cite book |last=Rahman |first=Momin |year=2020 |chapter=Queer Muslim Challenges to the Internationalization of LGBT Rights: Decolonizing International Relations Methodology through Intersectionality |editor1-last=Bosia |editor1-first=Michael J. |editor2-last=McEvoy |editor2-first=Sandra M. |editor3-last=Rahman |editor3-first=Momin |title=The Oxford Handbook of Global LGBT and Sexual Diversity Politics |location=[[Oxford]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |doi=10.1093/oxfordhb/9780190673741.013.27 |isbn=9780190673741}}
*Arlene Swidler: ''Homosexuality and World Religions.'' Valley Forge 1993. {{ISBN|1-56338-051-X}}
*Stephen O. Murray and Will Roscoe (eds.), "Islamic Homosexualities: culture, history, and literature" NYU Press New York 1997
*Wafer, Jim (1991) "The Taste of Blood: Spirit Possession in Brazilian Candomblé" UPP Philadelphia
*Wafer, Jim (1997) "Muhammad and Male Homosexuality" in "Islamic Homosexualities: culture, history, and literature" by Stephen O. Murray and Will Roscoe (eds.), NYU Press New York
*Wafer, Jim (1997) "The Symbolism of Male Love in Islamic Mysthical Literature" in "Islamic Homosexualities: culture, history, and literature" by Stephen O. Murray and Will Roscoe (eds.), NYU Press New York 1997

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20110927073959/http://www.changingattitude.org/home/home.asp Changing Attitude (International)]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20120226182252/http://ibcsr.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=112:religion-plays-an-important-role-in-the-lives-of-gay-americans&amp;catid=25:research-news&amp;Itemid=59 "Religion plays an important role in the lives of gay Americans"]
* [https://www.lgbtqhumanists.org LGBTQ Humanists]
* {{cite web |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |title=LGBTQI Resources |url=https://www.mpvusa.org/lgbtqi-resources |url-status=live |year=2021 |website=mpvusa.org |location=Los Angeles |publisher=[[Muslims for Progressive Values]] |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210819022452/https://www.mpvusa.org/lgbtqi-resources |archive-date=19 August 2021 |access-date=15 November 2021}}
*{{cite web |last=Eastman |first=Don |year=1990 |title=Homosexuality: Not a Sin, Not a Sickness – Part II: "What The Bible Does and Does Not Say…" |url=http://religiousinstitute.org/denom_statements/homosexuality-not-a-sin-not-a-sickness-part-ii-what-the-bible-does-and-does-not-say/ |url-status=live |website=religiousinstitute.org |location=Bridgeport, Connecticut |publisher=[[The Religious Institute on Sexual Morality, Justice, and Healing]] |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210830094927/http://religiousinstitute.org/denom_statements/homosexuality-not-a-sin-not-a-sickness-part-ii-what-the-bible-does-and-does-not-say/ |archive-date=30 August 2021 |access-date=15 November 2021}}
*{{cite magazine |last=Vines |first=Matthew |date=June 2014 |title=10 Reasons God Loves Gay Christians |url=https://time.com/2842044/gay-christians/ |url-status=live |magazine=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |location=New York City |issn=0040-781X |oclc=1311479 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210503045248/https://time.com/2842044/gay-christians/ |archive-date=3 May 2021 |access-date=15 November 2021}}
*{{cite web |last=Wilson |first=Nancy L. |date=22 May 2010 |title=Our Story Too: Reading the Bible with "New Eyes" |url=https://mccchurch.org/files/2016/08/OurStoryToo.pdf |url-status=live |website=mccchurch.org |location=Ocala, Florida |publisher=[[Metropolitan Community Church]] |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170201133244/https://mccchurch.org/files/2016/08/OurStoryToo.pdf |archive-date=7 February 2017 |access-date=15 November 2021}}

{{Religion and LGBT issues}}
{{Religion topics}}
{{Religion and topic}}
{{LGBT}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lgbt And Religion}}
[[Category:LGBT and religion| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>