<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171116195100|810680912" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="52512463" pageid="52512463" ns="0" title="White feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-20T02:11:32Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup rewrite|Info=Style needs to be fixed. Also POV etc.|date=September 2017}}{{Feminism sidebar}}
'''White feminism''' is a form of [[feminism]] that focuses on the struggles of white women while failing to address distinct forms of [[oppression]] often faced by women of colour and women lacking other [[Privilege (social inequality)|privileges]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Frankenberg|first=Ruth|date=1993-01-01|title=Growing up White: Feminism, Racism and the Social Geography of Childhood|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/1395347|journal=Feminist Review|issue=45|pages=51–84|doi=10.2307/1395347}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==
Over the past 400+ years, in predominantly white societies, issues with black women have continuously not been talked about, so the true historical struggles of black women are not widely known. African American women have always been viewed as a different "kind/type" of woman than American white women. White women in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries were not expected to work and were expected to stay at home and take care of the kids and the house. They were always seen as too delicate to go out and work a job.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Carby|first=Hazel|date=1982|title=White Women Listen!|url=|journal=The Empire Strikes Back: Race and Racism in 70s Britain|volume=|pages=212-235|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; But, black women were expected to work all day, come home and cook, then take care of the kids and the house. Society never let black women be seen as "feminine" or delicate as white women, so they always had to carry a heavier social workload. This is how black women have been perceived since the 1700s during slavery, so by the time the first wave of feminism came around, black women and their issues were not included in the feminist movement. [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] and [[Susan B. Anthony]] prioritized their suffrage over black men, so black women were not even a consideration to receive suffrage. This is all ironic due to women being excluded from the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] and the [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fifteenth Amendment]], but then the feminists excluded other marginalized groups from getting the same rights that they fought for. Now, in these third and fourth waves of feminism, it is okay to say that black women are treated the same as white women, but this is just not always the case. Within the feminist movements, white women are overall still at the forefront and still discuss issues that directly affect them. So, the issues that are specific to minority women are still being pushed to the side as they were during the first wave of feminism.

== In First-Wave Feminism ==
[[First-wave feminism]] began in the 19th century and continued into the early 20th century, and focused primarily on legal issues pertaining to women, especially [[women's suffrage]]. This wave officially started after [[Seneca Falls Convention|Seneca Falls]] and emerged out of an environment of urban industrialism and liberal, socialist politics and the goal of this wave was to open up opportunities for women, with a focus on suffrage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pacificu.edu/about-us/news-events/four-waves-feminism|title=Four Waves of Feminism {{!}} Pacific University|website=www.pacificu.edu|language=en|access-date=2017-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a movement predominantly organized and defined by middle-class, educated white women, and concentrated mostly on issues pertaining to them.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://kids.britannica.com/women/article-216012|title=Encyclopædia Britannica's Guide to Women's History|website=kids.britannica.com|access-date=2016-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.iep.utm.edu/fem-race/|title=Feminism and Race in the United States|last=Elkholy|first=Sharin N.|date=|website=Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy|publisher=|access-date=27 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some ethnic minority women were embraced in the movement, such as suffragette Princess [[Sophia Duleep Singh]] among the British first-wave feminists. However, there is little evidence that black women participated in the [[Women's suffrage in the United Kingdom|British suffragette]] effort. In 1893, [[New Zealand]] became the first nation to grant women of all races the right to vote; this was met with anger from suffragists including [[Millicent Fawcett]], who expressed displeasure that [[Māori people|Māori women]] in one of the British colonies were able to vote, while British women of society were not.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/women/womens-life/11914757/Racism-and-the-suffragettes-the-uncomfortable-truth.html|title=The uncomfortable truth about racism and the suffragettes|last=Sanghani|first=Radhika|date=6 October 2015|work=|newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|access-date=27 December 2016|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Susan B. Anthony]] (a staunch abolitionist) and [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] fought for white women to get the right to vote in the [[United States|United States of America]], prioritising this above black men getting the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.theroot.com/articles/culture/2016/04/black-feminism-white-feminism/|title=‘When and Where I Enter’: The Racist Expectations of Whites-Only Feminism|last=Savali|first=Kirsten West|date=23 April 2016|work=|newspaper=The Root|language=en-US|access-date=27 December 2016|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anthony and Stanton were wary of creating an "aristocracy of sex"; rather, they proposed universal suffrage, such that the black community and women (including black women) get enfranchised at the same time.

== In Second-Wave Feminism ==
[[Second-wave feminism]], particularly at its outset, was similarly shaped by middle-class, educated white women, and again did not tend to consider issues relevant specifically to ethnic minority women.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.progressivewomensleadership.com/a-brief-history-the-three-waves-of-feminism/|title=A Brief History: The Three Waves of Feminism|date=2015-09-22|work=Progressive Women's Leadership|access-date=2017-11-20|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the second and third-wave feminist periods, scholars from [[marginalised]] communities began to write back against the way feminist movements had been [[Essentialism|essentializing]] the experiences of women. The notable feminist scholar [[bell hooks]] brought this issue to the forefront of feminist thought, regularly writing about the struggles that black women experienced and emphasizing that the feminist movement was exclusionary towards those women by virtue of its inattention to the interactions between [[race (human categorization)|race]], gender, and class.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Feminism and 'Race'|last=hooks|first=bell|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2001|isbn=0-19-878236-5|editor-last=Bhavnani|editor-first=Kum-Kum|location=New York|pages=33–39|chapter=Black Women: Shaping Feminist Theory|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hooks argued that white women should recognise that they, like ethnic minority men, occupied a position of being both oppressed while also being oppressors.

== In Present-Day Feminism ==
Today's feminists sometimes emphasize intersectional perspectives in their work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2016/entries/feminist-power|title=Feminist Perspectives on Power|last=Allen|first=Amy|date=Fall 2016|website=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|publisher=The Metaphysics Research Lab, Stanford University|archive-url=|archive-date=|dead-url=|access-date=February 3, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, some have argued that feminist media continues to overrepresent the struggles of straight, middle class, white women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Nadeau|first=Mary-Jo|year=2009|title=Troubling Herstory: Unsettling White Multiculturalism in Canadian Feminism|url=http://search.proquest.com.library.smu.ca:2048/docview/217441442/fulltextPDF/A6D8821D66CC44DAPQ/1?accountid=13908|journal=Canadian Woman Studies|volume=27|pages=6–13|via=ProQuest}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; The position held by certain modern feminist authors that [[racism]] is not an element of society that feminism needs to be concerned with has also been cited as exemplifying white feminism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://everydayfeminism.com/2015/09/white-feminists-anti-racism/|title=When White Feminists Respond to Anti-Racism Like Men Respond to Feminism — Everyday Feminism|website=everydayfeminism.com|access-date=2016-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It has also been argued that the beliefs of some feminists that [[hijab]]s, [[burqa]]s, and [[Niqāb|niqabs]] are oppressive toward [[Muslim]] women are representative of white feminism. Notably, many [[Women in Islam|Muslim women]] have spoken out in defense of the their religious dress practices.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://this.org/2015/03/11/the-trouble-with-white-feminism/|title=THIS  →  The trouble with (white) feminism|website=this.org|access-date=2016-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

White feminism portrays a view of feminism that can be separated from issues of class, race, ability, and other oppressions. An example of white feminism in the present day can be seen in the work of Emily Shire,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bustle.com/authors/1559-emily-shire|title=Emily Shire|website=www.bustle.com|access-date=2017-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; the politics editor at Bustle and an op-ed contributor for The New York Times. Shire argues that feminism excludes some women who do not share political viewpoints when it takes positions on Israel and Palestine, efforts to raise the minimum wage, and efforts to block the construction of oil pipelines.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/07/opinion/does-feminism-have-room-for-zionists.html|title=Does Feminism Have Room for Zionists?|last=Shire|first=Emily|date=2017-03-07|work=The New York Times|access-date=2017-03-08|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shire's position contrasts with intersectional feminist activists who view pay equity, social justice, and international human rights as essential and inseparable commitments of feminism, as articulated in the Day Without a Woman platform that "[recognizes] the enormous value that women of all backgrounds add to our socio-economic system – while receiving lower wages and experiencing greater inequities, vulnerability to discrimination, sexual harassment, and job insecurity".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.womensmarch.com/womensday/|title=A Day Without a Woman|website=Women's March on Washington|language=en-US|access-date=2017-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Shire advocates for a feminism that achieves inclusivity by avoiding political positions so as to not alienate women who disagree with those positions,&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; organizers of the Women's March hold the principle that "women have intersecting identities" necessitating a movement that focuses on a "comprehensive agenda".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://static1.squarespace.com/static/584086c7be6594762f5ec56e/t/587ffb20579fb3554668c111/1484782369253/WMW+Guiding+Vision+%26+Definition+of+Principles.pdf|title=Guiding Vision and Definition of Principles|last=Women's March|first=|date=March 8, 2017|website=www.womensmarch.com|archive-url=|archive-date=|dead-url=|access-date=March 8, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Multicultural feminism]]
[[Category:White culture]]
[[Category:Women's culture]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>