<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211123163149|1056798703" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="52512463" pageid="52512463" ns="0" title="White feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-25T01:05:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{POV|date=November 2021}}

{{Short description|Form of feminism that focuses on the struggles of white women while supposedly failing to address the struggles of ethnic minority women}}
{{Feminism sidebar}} 
'''White feminism''' is a term used to describe expressions of [[feminism]] which are perceived as focusing on the struggles of white women while failing to address distinct forms of [[oppression]] faced by [[ethnic minority]] women and women lacking other [[Privilege (social inequality)|privileges]], which ultimately functions to marginalize women of color.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Frankenberg|first=Ruth|date=1993-01-01|title=Growing up White: Feminism, Racism and the Social Geography of Childhood|journal=Feminist Review|issue=45|pages=51–84|doi=10.2307/1395347|jstor=1395347}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=ABPP|first=Monnica T. Williams, Ph D.|date=2019-01-16|title=How White Feminists Oppress Black Women: When Feminism Functions as White Supremacy|url=https://chacruna.net/how-white-feminists-oppress-black-women-when-feminism-functions-as-white-supremacy/|access-date=2020-10-13|website=Chacruna|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; White feminism as a term has been used to label and criticize theories that are perceived as focusing solely on gender-based inequality, failing to acknowledge and integrate the notion of [[intersectionality]] in the struggle for equality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Coaston |first1=Jane |title=The Intersectionality Wars |url=http://www.vox.com/the-highlight/2019/5/20/18542843/intersectionality-conservatism-law-race-gender-discrimination. |website=www.vox.com |access-date=24 August 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dubious|Coaston, Jane. "The Intersectionality Wars". www.vox.com. Retrieved 24 August 2020. Does not mention White feminism|date=November 2021}} The term has also been used to refer to theories perceived to focus more specifically on the experience of white, cisgender, heterosexual, able-bodied women, and in which the experiences of women without these privileges are excluded or marginalized.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Breines|first=Wini|date=2002|title=What's Love Got to Do with It? White Women, Black Women, and Feminism in the Movement Years|journal=Signs|volume=27|issue=4|pages=1095–1133|doi=10.1086/339634|s2cid=144139580|via=JSTOR}}&lt;/ref&gt; This criticism has predominantly been leveled against the first waves of feminism which were seen as centered around the empowerment of white middle-class females in Western societies.

While the term ''white feminism'' is relatively recent, the critics of the concept it represents date back to the beginning of the feminist movement, especially in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Staples |first1=Brent |title=When the Suffrage Movement Sold Out to White Supremacy |journal=New York Times |date=2 February 2019 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2019/02/02/opinion/sunday/women-voting-19th-amendment-white-supremacy.html. |access-date=24 August 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; By theorizing the overlapping systems of oppression in society (dependent on race, ethnicity, sexuality, gender, etc.), the development of [[Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw|Crenshaw]]'s theory of intersectionality has recently galvanized critics of white feminism, described as restrictive and discriminatory. Others question the label, claiming it is used to attack white feminists, whether or not they are inclusionary of minority women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine |last=Noman |first=Natasha |date=2016-05-13 |title=Why Is 'White Feminism' Such a Dirty Phrase? A History of Feminism and Exclusion |url=https://www.mic.com/articles/143204/why-is-white-feminism-such-a-dirty-phrase-a-history-of-feminism-and-exclusion |magazine=www.mic.com |access-date=2021-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine |last=Muller |first=Marissa G. |date=2018-01-10 |title=Emma Watson Addresses Her White Privilege and ‘White Feminism’ in Letter to Her Book Club |url=https://www.wmagazine.com/story/emma-watson-white-privilege-feminism |magazine=www.wmagazine.com |access-date=2021-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Origins ==
At its origin, feminism in Western societies was represented by white educated women primarily focusing on the right to political representation and vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=ABPP|first=Monnica T. Williams, Ph D.|date=2019-01-16|title=How White Feminists Oppress Black Women: When Feminism Functions as White Supremacy|url=https://chacruna.net/how-white-feminists-oppress-black-women-when-feminism-functions-as-white-supremacy/|access-date=2020-11-12|website=Chacruna|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; An example of the criticized practices{{By whom|date=November 2021}} is found in Mary Wollstonecraft's text, ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Woman]]'' published in 1792, where Wollstonecraft advocates for moral and political equality between men and women, however only addressing members belonging to the middle-class. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Wollstonecraft |first1=Mary |title=Mary Wollstonecraft, A Vindication of the Rights of Woman |url=http://www.bl.uk/collection-items/mary-wollstonecraft-a-vindication-of-the-rights-of-woman. |website=The British Library |access-date=24 August 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, in France, Olympe de Gouges advocated for women’s rights in her [[Declaration of the Rights of Woman and of the Female Citizen]] as early as 1791.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Declaration of the Rights of Woman and of the [Female] Citizen {{!}} Definition &amp; Facts|url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/Declaration-of-the-Rights-of-Woman-and-of-the-Female-Citizen|access-date=2020-11-12|website=Encyclopedia Britannica|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In first-wave feminism ==
[[File:Feminist Suffrage Parade in New York City, 1912.jpeg|thumb|[[Women's suffrage]] parade in New York City, May 6, 1912.]]
The [[First-wave feminism|first-wave of feminism]] began in the late nineteenth century, and focused on the equality of political and economic rights. The rights women were fighting were: women's suffrage, access to education, ability to hold political office, equality in the work force, and legal rights in marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Goldstein|first=Leslie F.|date=1982|title=Early Feminist Themes in French Utopian Socialism: The St.-Simonians and Fourier|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/2709162|journal=Journal of the History of Ideas|volume=43|issue=1|pages=91–108|doi=10.2307/2709162|jstor=2709162|issn=0022-5037}}&lt;/ref&gt; This wave officially started with the 1848 [[Seneca Falls Convention]] in Seneca Falls, New York, towards the end of the [[Industrial Revolution]]. The goal of this wave was to open up opportunities for women, with a focus on suffrage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pacificu.edu/about-us/news-events/four-waves-feminism|title=Four Waves of Feminism {{!}} Pacific University|website=www.pacificu.edu|language=en|access-date=2017-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a movement predominantly organized and defined by middle-class, educated white women, and therefore concentrated mostly on issues pertaining to them.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://kids.britannica.com/women/article-216012|title=Encyclopædia Britannica's Guide to Women's History|website=kids.britannica.com|access-date=2016-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.iep.utm.edu/fem-race/|title=Feminism and Race in the United States|last=Elkholy|first=Sharin N.|website=Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy|access-date=27 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While some [[women of color]] were part of the first-wave feminist movement, such as the Indian suffragette [[Sophia Duleep Singh]], on the whole the first suffragist movements remained primarily white; for example, there has been no historical evidence pertaining to the participation of [[Black British people|Black British]] women in [[Women's suffrage in the United Kingdom|UK suffrage movement]]{{Citation needed|date=November 2021}}. In 1893, [[Colony of New Zealand|New Zealand]] became the first region in the [[British Empire]] to grant women of all ethnicities the right to vote; this was met with anger from some suffragists, including [[Millicent Fawcett]], who expressed displeasure that [[Māori people|Māori]] women in New Zealand were able to vote, while British women were not.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/women/womens-life/11914757/Racism-and-the-suffragettes-the-uncomfortable-truth.html|title=The uncomfortable truth about racism and the suffragettes|last=Sanghani|first=Radhika|date=6 October 2015|newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|access-date=27 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; American suffragettes [[Susan B. Anthony]] and [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] fought for white women to get the right to vote in the [[United States]], which led to white women gaining the right to vote before African American men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.theroot.com/articles/culture/2016/04/black-feminism-white-feminism/|title='When and Where I Enter': The Racist Expectations of Whites-Only Feminism|last=Savali|first=Kirsten West|date=23 April 2016|newspaper=The Root|language=en-US|access-date=27 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Our Documents - 19th Amendment to the U.S. Constitution: Women's Right to Vote (1920)|url=https://www.ourdocuments.gov/doc.php?flash=false&amp;doc=63|access-date=2021-11-22|website=www.ourdocuments.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Voting Rights for African Americans {{!}} The Right to Vote {{!}} Elections {{!}} Classroom Materials at the Library of Congress {{!}} Library of Congress|url=https://www.loc.gov/classroom-materials/elections/right-to-vote/voting-rights-for-african-americans/|access-date=2021-11-22|website=Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 20540 USA}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anthony and Stanton were wary of creating an "aristocracy of sex"; rather, they proposed universal suffrage, such that the Black community and women (including black women) become enfranchised at the same time.{{fact|date=October 2021}}

Nevertheless, their “[[History of Woman Suffrage]]”, is a clear example of white feminism as it widely disregards the role of black women while focusing on white figures of the movement{{Citation needed|date=November 2021}}. While 1920 is celebrated as the beginning for women's voting rights in the United States, African American women were still evicted from voting polls in the Jim Crow South. At that time, African American were excluded from the feminist movement. In fact, the black suffragist Mary Church Terrell was denied the help of white activists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Staples |first=Brent |date=2 February 2019 |title=When the Suffrage Movement Sold Out to White Supremacy |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2019/02/02/opinion/sunday/women-voting-19th-amendment-white-supremacy.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although women of color are not commonly referenced in the feminist literary space, they were still active during the origins of feminism.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Thompson|first=Becky|date=2002|title=Multiracial Feminism: Recasting the Chronology of the Second Wave Feminism|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/3178747|journal=Feminist Studies|volume=28|pages=336-360|via=JSTOR}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Grady|first=Constance|date=2018-03-20|title=The waves of feminism, and why people keep fighting over them, explained|url=https://www.vox.com/2018/3/20/16955588/feminism-waves-explained-first-second-third-fourth|access-date=2021-11-22|website=Vox|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, as early as 1851, [[Sojourner Truth]], a former slave, delivered a speech “Ain’t I a woman” in which she calls for what would be later on described as intersectionality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Gender and the Law Blog: Soujourner Truth's Ain't I a Woman Speech and Intersectional Feminism|url=https://lawprofessors.typepad.com/gender_law/2019/02/soujourner-truths-aint-i-a-woman-speech.html|access-date=2020-11-12|website=lawprofessors.typepad.com|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In second-wave feminism ==
[[Second-wave feminism]] began in the 1960s and lasted through the 1980s. This time period focused on: women in the work environment, owning sexuality, reproductive rights, domestic violence and rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Second-wave feminism|date=2020-10-20|url=https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Second-wave_feminism&amp;oldid=984463630|work=Wikipedia|language=en|access-date=2020-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;      Although second wave feminism was similarly shaped by middle-class, educated white women, it also saw the emergence of women of color into the discussion&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news|date=2015-09-22|title=A Brief History: The Three Waves of Feminism|language=en-US|work=Progressive Women's Leadership|url=https://www.progressivewomensleadership.com/a-brief-history-the-three-waves-of-feminism/|access-date=2017-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;. In 1973, African American feminists convened at the National Black Feminist Organization, discussing the same issues that the rest of the feminist movement was addressing&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite web|title=feminism - The second wave of feminism {{!}} Britannica|url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/feminism/The-second-wave-of-feminism|access-date=2021-11-23|website=www.britannica.com|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Although a separate organization, it gave both white and African American feminists alike a common ground&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;. In this way, the second wave also began to incorporate women of color, whereas the first wave focused mostly on white, cis-gender, middle class women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2015-10-25|title=Four Waves of Feminism|url=https://www.pacificu.edu/magazine/four-waves-feminism|access-date=2020-11-12|website=Pacific University|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

''The Second Sex'' by Simone de Beauvoir, stands as the one of the most striking examples of the essentialization of women in the figure of the white bourgeoise mother and hence disregard for other forms of oppressions such as race or sexuality. Nevertheless, this book has appeared as a landmark which has enabled other more complex theories to emerge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Garcia |first1=Manon |title=On Ne Naît Pas Soumise, on Le Devient |date=2019 |publisher=Climats}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=The Second Sex: Full Book Summary|url=https://www.sparknotes.com/lit/secondsex/summary/|access-date=2021-11-22|website=SparkNotes|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the second and third-wave feminist periods, women of color emerged into the feminist literary space, arguing that feminist movements were essentializing the experiences of women. Among such feminists were [[bell hooks]]. bell hooks is recognized for writing about the struggles that black women experienced as well as emphasizing that the feminist movement was exclusionary towards those women by virtue of its inattention to the interactions between [[race (human categorization)|race]], gender, and class.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Feminism and 'Race'|last=hooks|first=bell|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2001|isbn=978-0-19-878236-0|editor-last=Bhavnani|editor-first=Kum-Kum|location=New York|pages=33–39|chapter=Black Women: Shaping Feminist Theory}}&lt;/ref&gt; hooks argued that white women should recognize the fact that they, like ethnic minority men, occupied a position of being both oppressed while also being oppressors. In an attempt to shun the critiques addressed by scholars from minorities exposing second-wave feminism, the latter sought to divert attention by exposing the exclusionary practices of second-wave feminism. This has been criticized by many scholars which have labeled it under several names such as missionary, imperialist, or western feminism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Maira |first1=Susaina |title="Good" and "Bad Muslim Citizens: Feminists, Terrorists, and U. S. Orientalisms" |date=2009 |publisher=Feminist Studies |pages=631–656}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Shu-Mel|first=Shih|date=2006|title=Complicities of Western Feminism|journal=Women's Studies Quarterly|volume=34|pages=79-81|via=JSTOR}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

== In third-wave feminism ==
Led by Gen X, [[Third-wave feminism|third wave feminism]] began in the 1990s when issues surrounding sexuality, such as pornography were brought to the forefront.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite web|title=Feminism - The third wave of feminism|url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/feminism|access-date=2020-11-12|website=Encyclopedia Britannica|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the reasons for the split in the second wave was due to differences regarding how women should embrace their sexuality, leading to different views on sex work and pornography. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Snyder-Hall|first=R. Claire|date=2010|title=Third-Wave Feminism and the Defense of "Choice"|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/25698533|journal=Perspectives on Politics|volume=8|issue=1|pages=255–261|doi=10.1017/S1537592709992842|jstor=25698533|s2cid=145133253|issn=1537-5927}}&lt;/ref&gt;Third wave feminists coined the term "riot grrls" which represented strong, independent and passionate feminists in this time period. "Grrls" were typically described as angry feminists fighting against sexism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Riot Grrrls, Action Girl, Third Wave movement {{!}} Gender, Sexuality, and Women's Studies|url=http://www.gsws.pitt.edu/blogs/alm206/riot-grrrls-action-girl-third-wave-movement|access-date=2020-11-12|website=www.gsws.pitt.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; The third wave was inspired by the post-modern society, in which women worked to reclaim their own power over derogatory words men have used to shame them like, 'whore,' and 'slut.' The third wave was also created in order to address social issues the current generation was facing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Snyder|first=R. Claire|date=2008-09-01|title=What Is Third‐Wave Feminism? A New Directions Essay|url=https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/588436|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|volume=34|issue=1|pages=175–196|doi=10.1086/588436|s2cid=144068546|issn=0097-9740}}&lt;/ref&gt; This also worked to advocate for women's sexual liberation and expression of gender identity.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; This wave also included even more women of color and women from different classes than previous waves.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;When comparing the second and third wave, the third wave highlighted intersectionality. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Snyder|first=R. Claire|date=2008|title=What Is Third‐Wave Feminism? A New Directions Essay|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/588436|journal=Signs|volume=34|issue=1|pages=175–196|doi=10.1086/588436|jstor=10.1086/588436|s2cid=144068546|issn=0097-9740}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== 21st century intersectional feminism, or fourth wave ==
During [[Third-wave feminism|third wave feminism]] and at the start of fourth wave feminism after 2010, feminists sometimes emphasize intersectional perspectives in their work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2016/entries/feminist-power|title=Feminist Perspectives on Power|last=Allen|first=Amy|date=Fall 2016|website=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|publisher=The Metaphysics Research Lab, Stanford University|access-date=February 3, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, some have argued that feminist media continues to overrepresent the struggles of straight, middle class, white women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Nadeau|first=Mary-Jo|year=2009|title=Troubling Herstory: Unsettling White Multiculturalism in Canadian Feminism|journal=Canadian Woman Studies|volume=27|pages=6–13|id={{ProQuest|217441442}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; The position held by some modern feminist authors that [[racism]] is not an element of society that feminism needs to be concerned with has also been cited as exemplifying white feminism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://everydayfeminism.com/2015/09/white-feminists-anti-racism/|title=When White Feminists Respond to Anti-Racism Like Men Respond to Feminism — Everyday Feminism|website=everydayfeminism.com|access-date=2016-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, in recent years, authors like [[Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw|Kimberlé Crenshaw]] have developed the theory of intersectionality, a clear opposition to white feminism. Rather than analyzing society from a unique perspective of race or gender, she calls for a more complex analysis of systems of oppression using multiple and overlapping lenses such as race, gender, sexuality, etc.&lt;ref name=crenshaw&gt;{{cite book |last1=Crenshaw |first1=Kimberlé |author1-link=Kimberlé Crenshaw |title=On Intersectionality: the Essential Writings of Kimberlé Crenshaw |date=2018 |publisher=New Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

White feminism portrays a view of feminism that can be separated from issues of class, race, ability, and other oppressions. An example of white feminism in the present day can be seen in the work of Emily Shire,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bustle.com/authors/1559-emily-shire|title=Emily Shire|website=www.bustle.com|access-date=2017-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; politics editor at Bustle and an op-ed contributor for [[The New York Times]]. Shire argues that feminism excludes some women who do not share political viewpoints when it takes positions on Israel and Palestine, efforts to raise the minimum wage, and efforts to block the construction of oil pipelines.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/07/opinion/does-feminism-have-room-for-zionists.html|title=Does Feminism Have Room for Zionists?|last=Shire|first=Emily|date=2017-03-07|work=The New York Times|access-date=2017-03-08|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shire's position contrasts with intersectional feminist activists who view pay equity, social justice, and international human rights as essential and inseparable commitments of feminism, as articulated in the [[Day Without a Woman]] platform that "[recognizes] the enormous value that women of all backgrounds add to our socio-economic system – while receiving lower wages and experiencing greater inequities, vulnerability to discrimination, sexual harassment, and job insecurity".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.womensmarch.com/womensday/|title=A Day Without a Woman|website=Women's March on Washington|language=en-US|access-date=2017-03-08|archive-date=2019-01-30|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190130074640/https://www.womensmarch.com/womensday/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Shire advocates for a feminism that achieves inclusivity by avoiding political positions so as to not alienate women who disagree with those positions,&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; organizers of the Women's March hold the principle that "women have intersecting identities" necessitating a movement that focuses on a "comprehensive agenda".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://static1.squarespace.com/static/584086c7be6594762f5ec56e/t/587ffb20579fb3554668c111/1484782369253/WMW+Guiding+Vision+%26+Definition+of+Principles.pdf|title=Guiding Vision and Definition of Principles|last=Women's March|date=March 8, 2017|website=www.womensmarch.com|access-date=March 8, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It has also been argued that the beliefs of some feminists that [[hijab]]s, [[burqa]]s, and [[Niqāb|niqabs]] are oppressive towards [[Muslim]] women are representative of white feminism. Many [[Women in Islam|Muslim women]] have spoken out in defense of their religious dress practices.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://this.org/2015/03/11/the-trouble-with-white-feminism/|title=THIS → The trouble with (white) feminism|website=this.org|access-date=2016-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; One example of this belief is the [[Islamic scarf controversy in France]] that has argued against the Islamic veil by many French feminists claiming that Islam threatens women's autonomy and thus choosing to wear one is meaningless, when many Muslim women say that it is a choice and that denying the choice only restricts a woman's freedom. They say that some wear it as a personal commitment; others reject the notion that the veil is a religious sign.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=R. Bowen |first1=John |author-link1=Women's autonomy, Islam, and the French State. |editor1-last=B. Brettell |editor1-first=Caroline |editor2-last=F. Sargent |editor2-first=Carolyn |title=Gender in Cross-Cultural Perspective |date=2017 |publisher=Routledge |location=London; New York |isbn=978-1-138-21664-8 |pages=371–380 |chapter=26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Muslim women see the burqa as freeing, because it enabled them to be in the public sphere while still observing moral and religious requirements.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Abu-Lughod|first=Lila|title=The Muslim Woman: The Power of Images and the Danger of Pity}}&lt;/ref&gt; In her article, "Do Muslim Women Really Need Saving?" Lila Abu-Lughod states that Muslim find comfort through their burqas, as they provide "mobile homes."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Abu-Lughod|first=Lila|date=2002|title=Do Muslim Women Really Need Saving? Anthropological Reflections on Cultural Relativism and Its Others|journal=American Anthropologist|volume=104|pages=783-790|via=JSTOR}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Trans-exclusionary radical feminism]] has also been a topic of discussion. Feminism requires fighting for women's rights, but trans-exclusionary radical feminists do not see [[trans women]] as women. Many of them argue against trans women changing their sex on legal documents, say that ''lesbian'' as an identity is disappearing, that trans men are not men, and that gay children need protection when they think they are transgender.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Lewis|first=Sophie|date=2019-02-07|title=Opinion {{!}} How British Feminism Became Anti-Trans (Published 2019)|language=en-US|work=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/02/07/opinion/terf-trans-women-britain.html|access-date=2020-10-08|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics, especially within the [[LGBT]] community, have expressed their discontent with these arguments. They feel that privileged white women who make these arguments will make trans women, especially trans women of color, more at risk for discrimination and that they fail to consider many other factors that trans women have to deal with.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Tudor |first1=Alyosxa |title=Terfism is White Distraction: On BLM, Decolonising the Curriculum, Anti-Gender Attacks and Feminist Transphobia |url=https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/gender/2020/06/19/terfism-is-white-distraction-on-blm-decolonising-the-curriculum-anti-gender-attacks-and-feminist-transphobia/ |website=Engenderings |access-date=8 October 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Feminism and racism]]
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Multiracial feminist theory|Multiracial feminism]]

== References ==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{Feminism|Variants (general)}}

[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Multicultural feminism]]
[[Category:Women's culture]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>