<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211117191738|1055780319" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56812359" pageid="56812359" ns="0" title="Deplatforming"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-25T16:47:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{undue weight|date=January 2021}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2021}}
{{short description|Administrative or political action to deny access to a platform to express opinions}}
{{redirect|No-platforming|the British student organization policy|No Platform}}
'''Deplatforming''', also known as '''no-platforming''', has been defined as an "attempt to [[boycott]] a group or individual through removing the platforms (such as speaking venues or websites) used to share information or ideas,"&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.merriam-webster.com/words-at-play/the-good-the-bad-the-semantically-imprecise-08102018 The Good, The Bad, &amp; The Semantically Imprecise: The words that defined the week of August 10, 2018], ''Merriam-Webster'' (August 8, 2018).&lt;/ref&gt; or "the action or practice of preventing someone holding views regarded as unacceptable or offensive from contributing to a forum or debate, especially by blocking them on a particular website."&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.lexico.com/en/definition/deplatforming Deplatforming], ''Lexico.com'' (Dictionary.com/Oxford University Press).&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
=== Deplatforming of invited speakers ===
In the United States, the banning of speakers on University campuses dates back to the 1940s. This was carried out by policies of the universities themselves. The [[University of California]] had a policy known as the Speaker Ban, codified in university regulations under President [[Robert Gordon Sproul]] that mostly, but not exclusively, targeted [[Communism in America|communists]]. One rule stated that "the University assumed the right to prevent exploitation of its prestige by unqualified persons or by those who would use it as a platform for propaganda."  This rule was used in 1951 to block [[Max Shachtman]], a [[socialist]], from speaking at the [[University of California at Berkeley]]. In 1947, former U.S. Vice President [[Henry A. Wallace]] was banned from speaking at [[UCLA]] because of his views on U.S. [[Cold War]] policy,&lt;ref name="Freeman-2000"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Freeman|first1=Jo|author-link=Jo Freeman|year=2000|title=A Short History of the University of California Speaker Ban|url=https://www.jofreeman.com/sixtiesprotest/speakerban.htm|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20191208070157/https://www.jofreeman.com/sixtiesprotest/speakerban.htm|archive-date=2019-12-08|website=JoFreeman.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1961, [[Malcolm X]] was prohibited from speaking at Berkeley as a religious leader. 

Controversial speakers invited to appear on college campuses have faced deplatforming attempts to disinvite them or to otherwise prevent them from speaking.&lt;ref name="Young" /&gt; The British [[National Union of Students (United Kingdom)|National Union of Students]] established its [[No Platform]] policy as early as 1973.&lt;ref name="Socialist" /&gt; In the mid-1980s, visits by [[South Africa]]n ambassador [[Glenn Babb]] to Canadian college campuses faced opposition from students opposed to [[apartheid]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Bueckert |first1=Michael |title=No platform for Apartheid |url=https://africasacountry.com/2018/04/no-platform-for-apartheid |access-date=2020-11-17 |work=africasacountry.com |date=April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, recent examples include [[Charles Murray (political scientist)#Public speech and protest at Middlebury College|the March 2017 disruption]] by protestors of a public speech at [[Middlebury College]] by political scientist [[Charles Murray (political scientist)|Charles Murray]].&lt;ref name=Young/&gt; In February 2018, students at the [[University of Central Oklahoma]] rescinded a speaking invitation to creationist [[Ken Ham]], after pressure from an [[LGBT]] student group.&lt;ref name=Hinton/&gt;&lt;ref name=Causey/&gt; In March 2018, a "small group of protesters" at [[Lewis &amp; Clark Law School]] attempted to stop a speech by visiting lecturer [[Christina Hoff Sommers]].&lt;ref name=Young/&gt;  In the 2019 film ''[[No Safe Spaces]]'', [[Adam Carolla]] and [[Dennis Prager]] documented their own disinvitation along with others.&lt;ref name=NR-nss&gt;{{cite journal |title=In ''No Safe Spaces'', an Odd Couple Teams Up to Fight Free-Speech Bans |last=Fund |first=John |date=November 3, 2019  |journal=[[National Review]] |url=https://www.nationalreview.com/2019/11/documentary-no-safe-spaces-adam-carolla-dennis-prager-fight-free-speech-bans/ |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20191218052250/https://www.nationalreview.com/2019/11/documentary-no-safe-spaces-adam-carolla-dennis-prager-fight-free-speech-bans/ |archive-date=2019-12-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{As of|February 2020}}, the [[Foundation for Individual Rights in Education]], a speech advocacy group, documented 469 disinvitation or disruption attempts at American campuses since 2000,&lt;ref name=FIRE-DB/&gt; including both "unsuccessful disinvitation attempts" and "successful disinvitations"; the group defines the latter category as including three subcategories: formal disinvitation by the sponsor of the speaking engagement; the speaker's withdrawal "in the face of disinvitation demands"; and "[[heckler's veto]]es" (situations when "students or faculty persistently disrupt or entirely prevent the speakers' ability to speak").&lt;ref name=FIRE-Guide/&gt;

=== Deplatforming in social media ===
Beginning in 2015, [[Reddit]] banned several communities on the site ("[[subreddit]]s") for violating the site's anti-harassment policy.&lt;ref name=ACM/&gt; A 2017 study published in the journal ''Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction'', examining "the causal effects of the ban on both participating users and affected communities," found that "the ban served a number of useful purposes for Reddit" and that "Users participating in the banned subreddits either left the site or (for those who remained) dramatically reduced their hate speech usage. Communities that inherited the displaced activity of these users did not suffer from an increase in hate speech."&lt;ref name=ACM/&gt; In June 2020 and January 2021, Reddit also issued bans to two prominent online pro-Trump communities over violations of the website's content and harassments policies. 

On May 2, 2019, [[Facebook]] and the Facebook-owned platform [[Instagram]] announced a ban of "dangerous individuals and organizations" including [[Nation of Islam]] leader [[Louis Farrakhan]], [[Milo Yiannopoulos]], [[Alex Jones]] and his organization [[InfoWars]], [[Paul Joseph Watson]], [[Laura Loomer]], and [[Paul Nehlen]].&lt;ref name=Wells/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lorenz/&gt; In the wake of the [[2021 storming of the United States Capitol|2021 storming of the US Capitol]], Twitter banned then-president Donald Trump, as well as 70,000 other accounts linked to the event and the far-right movement [[QAnon]].

==== Donald Trump ====
{{Main|Donald Trump on social media}}
On January 6, 2021, in a [[joint session of Congress|joint session of the United States Congress]], the counting of the votes of the [[Electoral College]] was interrupted by a [[2021 storming of the United States Capitol|breach of the United States Capitol chambers]]. The rioters were supporters of President [[Donald Trump]] who hoped to delay and overturn the President's loss in the [[2020 United States presidential election|2020 election]]. The event resulted in five deaths and at least 400 people being charged with crimes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=The Capitol Siege: The Arrested And Their Stories|url=https://www.npr.org/2021/02/09/965472049/the-capitol-siege-the-arrested-and-their-stories|access-date=2021-04-18|website=NPR.org|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The certification of the electoral votes was only completed in the early morning hours of January 7, 2021. In the wake of several [[Donald Trump on social media|Tweets by President Trump]] on January 7, 2021 [[Facebook]], [[Instagram]], [[YouTube]], [[Reddit]], and [[Twitter]] all deplatformed Trump to some extent.&lt;ref name="Healey8jan2021"&gt;[https://news.yahoo.com/opinion-took-mob-riot-twitter-005826415.html John Healy (January 8, 2021) Opinion: It took a mob riot for Twitter to finally ban Trump]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Crichton9jan2021"&gt;[https://techcrunch.com/2021/01/09/the-deplatforming-of-a-president/ Danny Crichton (January 9, 2021) The deplatforming of President Trump]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Newton6jan2021"&gt;[https://www.theverge.com/2021/1/6/22217894/deplatform-trump-twitter-ban-facebook-youtube-congress-capitol-riots Casey Newton (January 6, 2021) It's time to deplatform Trump]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= youtubeOneStrike &gt;[https://www.npr.org/2021/01/13/956317191/youtube-joins-twitter-facebook-in-taking-down-trumps-account-after-capitol-siege Jaclyn Diaz (January 13, 2021) YouTube Joins Twitter, Facebook In Taking Down Trump's Account After Capitol Siege]&lt;/ref&gt; Twitter deactivated his personal account, which the company said could possibly be used to promote further violence. Trump subsequently tweeted similar messages from the President's official US Government account @POTUS, which resulted in him being permanently banned on January 8.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=January 10, 2021|title=The expulsion of Donald Trump marks a watershed for Facebook and Twitter|work=The Economist|url=https://www.economist.com/international/2021/01/10/the-expulsion-of-donald-trump-marks-a-watershed-for-facebook-and-twitter|access-date=2021-01-10|issn=0013-0613}}&lt;/ref&gt; Twitter has announced that Trump's ban from their platform will be permanent.

Trump planned to re-join on social media through the use of a new platform by May or June 2021, according to [[Jason Miller (communications strategist)|Jason Miller]] on a [[Fox News]] broadcast.&lt;ref name= pengelly &gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2021/mar/21/trump-twitter-ban-social-media-own-platform Martin Pengelly (March 21, 2021) Trump will use 'his own platform’ to return to social media after Twitter ban]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= blogShutdown&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/02/trump-blog-page-shuts-down-for-good.html |title=Trump blog page shuts down for good |date=June 2, 2021 |work=CNBC |first=Kevin |last=Breuninger}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other examples ===
==== Harassment and threats to employment ====
Deplatforming tactics have also included attempts to silence controversial speakers through various forms of personal [[harassment]], such as [[doxing]],&lt;ref name=Wilson/&gt; the making of false emergency reports for purposes of [[swatting]],&lt;ref name=Shirek/&gt; and complaints or petitions to third parties. In some cases, protesters have attempted to have speakers [[Blacklist (employment)|blacklist]]ed from projects or fired from their jobs.&lt;ref name=ReutersMishra/&gt;

In 2019, for example, students at the [[University of the Arts (Philadelphia)|University of the Arts]] in Philadelphia circulated an online petition demanding that [[Camille Paglia]] "should be removed from UArts faculty and replaced by a queer person of color."&lt;ref name=Friedersdorf/&gt; According to ''[[The Atlantic]]''{{'}}s [[Conor Friedersdorf]], "It is rare for student activists to argue that a tenured faculty member {{em|at their own institution}} should be denied a platform."&lt;ref name=Friedersdorf/&gt; Paglia, a tenured professor for over 30 years who identifies as [[transgender]], had long been unapologetically outspoken on controversial "matters of sex, gender identity, and sexual assault".&lt;ref name=Friedersdorf/&gt;

==== In print media ====
In December 2017, after learning that a French artist it had previously reviewed was a [[neo-Nazi]], the [[San Francisco]] punk magazine ''[[Maximumrocknroll|Maximum Rocknroll]]'' apologized and announced that it has "a strict no-platform policy towards any bands and artists with a Nazi ideology".&lt;ref name=MaxRock/&gt;

{{anchor|Criticism}}
== Controversy and reactions ==

=== Justifications ===
{{anchor|Defense}}{{See also|Paradox of tolerance|Defensive democracy}}
According to its defenders, deplatforming has been used as a tactic to prevent the spread of [[hate speech]] and [[disinformation]].&lt;ref name=ACM/&gt; Social media has evolved into a significant source of news reporting for its users, and support for content moderation and banning of inflammatory posters has been defended as an editorial responsibility required by news outlets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Yaraghi|first=Niam|date=January 10, 2021|title=How should social media platforms combat misinformation and hate speech?|url=https://www.brookings.edu/blog/techtank/2019/04/09/how-should-social-media-platforms-combat-misinformation-and-hate-speech/|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=|website=Brookings}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Supporters of deplatforming have justified the action on the grounds that it produces the desired effect of reducing what they characterize as "hate speech".&lt;ref name=ACM/&gt;&lt;ref name=Koebler/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wong/&gt; Angelo Carusone, president of the [[Progressivism in the United States|progressive]] organization [[Media Matters for America]] and who had run deplatforming campaigns against conservative talk hosts [[Rush Limbaugh]] [[Rush Limbaugh–Sandra Fluke controversy|in 2012]] and [[Glenn Beck]] [[Glenn Beck Program#Boycotts|in 2010]], pointed to Twitter's 2016 ban of [[Milo Yiannopoulos]], stating that "the result was that he lost a lot.... He lost his ability to be influential or at least to project a veneer of influence."&lt;ref name=Koebler/&gt;

In the United States, deprivation of rights under the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] is sometimes cited as a criticism of deplatforming, but according to Audie Cornish, host of the [[NPR]] show ''Consider This'', modern deplatforming is not a government issue. She states that "the government can't silence your ability to say almost anything you want on a public street corner. But a private company can silence your ability to say whatever you want on a platform they created."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Deplatforming: Not A First Amendment Issue, But Still A Tough Call For Big Tech : Consider This from NPR|url=https://www.npr.org/2021/01/22/959667930/deplatforming-not-a-first-amendment-issue-but-still-a-tough-call-for-big-tech|access-date=2021-04-18|website=NPR.org|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of this, proponents say, deplatforming is a legal way of dealing with controversial users online or in other digital spaces, so long as the government is not involved with causing the deplatforming.

=== Critical responses ===
According to technology journalist [[Declan McCullagh]], "[[Silicon Valley]]'s efforts to pull the plug on dissenting opinions" began around 2018 with [[Twitter]], [[Facebook]], and [[YouTube]] denying service to selected users of their platforms, "devising excuses to suspend ideologically disfavored accounts."&lt;ref name=McCullagh/&gt; In 2019, McCullagh predicted that paying customers would become targets for deplatforming as well, citing protests and open letters by employees of [[Amazon (company)|Amazon]], [[Microsoft]], [[Salesforce.com|Salesforce]], and [[Google]] who opposed policies of [[U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement]] (ICE), and who reportedly sought to influence their employers to deplatform the agency and its contractors.&lt;ref name=McCullagh/&gt;

Law professor [[Glenn Reynolds]] dubbed 2018 the "Year of Deplatforming" in an August 2018 article in ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]''. Reynolds criticized the decision of "internet giants" to "slam the gates on a number of people and ideas they don't like", naming [[Alex Jones]] and [[Gavin McInnes]]&lt;ref name=Reynolds/&gt; Reynolds cited further restrictions on "even mainstream conservative figures" such as [[Dennis Prager]], as well as [[Facebook]]'s blocking of a campaign advertisement by a Republican candidate "ostensibly because her video mentioned the [[Cambodian genocide]], which her family survived."&lt;ref name=Reynolds/&gt;

In a 2019 article, [[Conor Friedersdorf]] described what he called "standard practice" among student activists: "Activists begin with social-media callouts; they urge authority figures to impose outcomes that they favor, without regard for overall student opinion; they try to marshal [[Anti-discrimination law|antidiscrimination law]] to limit [[freedom of expression]]."&lt;ref name=Friedersdorf/&gt; Friedersdorf pointed to evidence of a [[chilling effect]] on free speech and [[academic freedom]]. Of the faculty members he had contacted for interviews, a large majority "on both sides of the controversy insisted that their comments be kept off the record or anonymous. They feared openly participating in a debate about a major event at their institution—even after their university president put out an uncompromising statement in support of free speech".&lt;ref name=Friedersdorf/&gt;

==Legislative responses==
===United Kingdom===
In May 2021, the [[government of the United Kingdom|UK government]] under [[Boris Johnson]] announced a [[Higher Education (Freedom of Speech) Bill]] that would allow speakers at universities to seek compensation for no-platforming, impose fines on universities and student unions that promote the practice, and establish a new [[ombudsman]] charged with monitoring cases of no-platforming and academic dismissals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/education-57076093|title=Universities could face fines over free speech breaches|publisher=[[BBC News]]|date=May 12, 2021|accessdate=2021-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the government published an [[Online Safety Bill]] that would prohibit social media networks from discriminating against particular political views or removing "democratically important" content, such as comments opposing or supporting political parties and policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2021/may/12/uk-to-require-social-media-to-protect-democratically-important-content|title=Online safety bill 'a recipe for censorship', say campaigners|last=Hern|first=Alex|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=May 12, 2021|accessdate=2021-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
Some critics of deplatforming have proposed that governments should treat [[social media as a public utility]] to ensure that [[constitutional right]]s of the users are protected, citing their belief that an [[Internet]] presence using social media websites is imperative in order to adequately take part in the 21st century as an individual.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Thierer |first=Adam |title=The Perils of Classifying Social Media Platforms as Public Utilities |date=March 2012 |work=Mercatus Center |type=working paper |publisher=George Mason University |url=https://www.mercatus.org/system/files/PerilsClassifyingSocialMediaPublicUtilities.pdf|accessdate=2021-09-15 |language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Boycott]]
*[[No Platform]]
*[[Freedom of speech]]
*[[Censorship]]
*[[Online shaming]]
*[[Social media as a public utility]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=ACM&gt;{{cite journal |title=You Can't Stay Here: The Efficacy of Reddit's 2015 Ban Examined Through Hate Speech |first1=Eshwar |last1=Chandrasekharan |first2=Umashanti |last2=Pavalanathan |display-authors=etal |journal=Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. |volume=1 |issue=2 |date=November 2017 |doi=10.1145/3134666 |page=Article 31 |s2cid=22713682 |url=http://comp.social.gatech.edu/papers/cscw18-chand-hate.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Causey&gt;{{cite news |last=Causey |first=Adam Kealoha |title=Creationist's speech canceled at university in Oklahoma |date=February 8, 2018 |newspaper=[[Houston Chronicle]] |agency=[[Associated Press]] |url=https://www.houstonchronicle.com/news/education/article/Creationist-s-speech-canceled-at-university-in-12563015.php |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180209020049/https://www.houstonchronicle.com/news/education/article/Creationist-s-speech-canceled-at-university-in-12563015.php |archive-date=2018-02-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=FIRE-DB&gt;{{cite web |title=Disinvitation Database |website=[[Foundation for Individual Rights in Education]] |url=https://www.thefire.org/research/disinvitation-database|access-date=2021-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=FIRE-Guide&gt;{{cite web |title=User's Guide to FIRE's Disinvitation Database |website=[[Foundation for Individual Rights in Education]] |date=June 9, 2016 |url=https://www.thefire.org/how-to-use-the-disinvitation-database/|url-status=live|access-date=2021-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Friedersdorf&gt;{{cite magazine |title=Camille Paglia Can't Say That |first=Conor |last=Friedersdorf |author-link=Conor Friedersdorf |magazine=[[The Atlantic]] |date=May 2019 |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/05/camille-paglia-uarts-left-deplatform/587125/ |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190501155608/https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/05/camille-paglia-uarts-left-deplatform/587125/ |archive-date=2019-05-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Hinton&gt;{{cite news |last=Hinton |first=Carla |title=UCO Student Group Rescinds Invitation to Christian Speaker Ken Ham |newspaper=[[The Oklahoman]] |url=http://newsok.com/uco-student-group-rescinds-invitation-to-christian-speaker-ken-ham/article/5582635 |date=February 8, 2018 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180528190603/https://newsok.com/article/5582635/uco-student-group-rescinds-invitation-to-christian-speaker-ken-ham |archive-date=2018-05-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Koebler&gt;{{cite web |last=Koebler |first=Jason |title=Deplatforming Works |website=[[Motherboard (website)|Motherboard]] |publisher=[[Vice (magazine)|Vice Media]] |date=August 10, 2018 |url=https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/bjbp9d/do-social-media-bans-work |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190319072929/https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/bjbp9d/do-social-media-bans-work |archive-date=2019-03-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Lorenz&gt;{{cite magazine |first=Taylor |last=Lorenz |title=Instagram and Facebook Ban Far-Right Extremists |date=May 2, 2019 |magazine=[[The Atlantic]] |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2019/05/instagram-and-facebook-ban-far-right-extremists/588607/ |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190503004014/https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2019/05/instagram-and-facebook-ban-far-right-extremists/588607/ |archive-date=2019-05-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=MaxRock&gt;{{cite magazine |title=Letters |type=editorial statement |magazine=[[Maximumrocknroll|Maximum Rocknroll]] |issue=415 |date=December 2017 |page=8 |url=https://archive.org/details/mrr_415/page/n7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=McCullagh&gt;{{cite magazine |title=Deplatforming Is a Dangerous Game |first=Declan |last=McCullagh |date=February 2019 |magazine=[[Reason (magazine)|Reason]] |url=https://reason.com/archives/2019/01/20/deplatforming |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190331055502/https://reason.com/archives/2019/01/20/deplatforming |archive-date=2019-03-31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=ReutersMishra&gt;{{cite news |first1=Manas |last1=Mishra |first2=Akshay |last2=Balan |agency=Reuters |title=Google to pull plug on AI ethics council |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-alphabet-google-ai/google-to-pull-plug-on-ai-ethics-council-vox-idUSKCN1RH00S |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20190405230401/https://www.reuters.com/article/us-alphabet-google-ai/google-to-pull-plug-on-ai-ethics-council-vox-idUSKCN1RH00S |archivedate=2019-04-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Reynolds&gt;{{cite news |title=When Digital Platforms Become Censors |first=Glenn Harlan |last=Reynolds |date=August 18, 2018 |newspaper=The Wall Street Journal |url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/when-digital-platforms-become-censors-1534514122?mod=rsswn |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190330045941/https://www.wsj.com/articles/when-digital-platforms-become-censors-1534514122?mod=rsswn |archive-date=2019-03-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Shirek&gt;{{cite web |last=Shirek |first=Jon |title=9-1-1 hoax snares conservative blogger |website=11Alive.com |publisher=WXIA-TV |location=Atlanta |date=June 8, 2012 |url=http://www.11alive.com/news/article/244127/3/911-Hoax-Conservative-Blogger-Erick-Erickson-target-of-SWAT-ing |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20130116004337/http://www.11alive.com/news/article/244127/3/911-Hoax-Conservative-Blogger-Erick-Erickson-target-of-SWAT-ing |archivedate=2013-01-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Socialist&gt;{{cite journal |url=https://www.marxists.org/history/etol/writers/german/1986/04/noplatform.html |title=No Platform: Free Speech for all? |first=Lindsey |last=German |author-link=Lindsey German |journal=Socialist Worker Review |issue=86 |date=April 1986 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Wells&gt;{{cite news |first=Georgia |last=Wells |title=Facebook Bans Louis Farrakhan, Alex Jones and Others as 'Dangerous' |date=May 2, 2019 |newspaper=[[The Wall Street Journal]] |url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/facebook-bans-louis-farrakhan-alex-jones-and-others-as-dangerous-11556827652?mod=rsswn |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190503043802/https://www.wsj.com/articles/facebook-bans-louis-farrakhan-alex-jones-and-others-as-dangerous-11556827652?mod=rsswn |archive-date=2019-05-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Wilson&gt;{{cite news |title=How the world has fought back against the violent far-right and started winning |first=Jason |last=Wilson |newspaper=[[The Guardian]] |date=December 18, 2018 |url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/dec/19/how-the-world-has-fought-back-against-the-violent-far-right-and-started-winning |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20190402121847/https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/dec/19/how-the-world-has-fought-back-against-the-violent-far-right-and-started-winning |archivedate=2019-04-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Wong&gt;{{cite news |title=Don't give Facebook and YouTube credit for shrinking Alex Jones' audience |first=Julia Carrie |last=Wong |location=London |newspaper=The Guardian |date=September 4, 2018 |url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/sep/04/alex-jones-infowars-social-media-ban }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Young&gt;{{cite news |title=Half of college students aren't sure protecting free speech is important. That's bad news |first=Cathy |last=Young |date=April 8, 2018 |newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]] |url=https://www.latimes.com/opinion/op-ed/la-oe-young-free-speech-on-campus-20180408-story.html |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190208031653/https://www.latimes.com/opinion/op-ed/la-oe-young-free-speech-on-campus-20180408-story.html |archive-date=2019-02-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== Further reading ==
* {{Cite journal|last=Rogers|first=Richard|date=May 6, 2020|title=Deplatforming: Following extreme Internet celebrities to Telegram and alternative social media|journal=[[European Journal of Communication]]|volume=35|issue=3|pages=213–229|doi=10.1177/0267323120922066|doi-access=free}}

== External links ==
* {{Wiktionary-inline|deplatform}}

{{Media manipulation}}
{{Conformity}}

[[Category:Internet censorship]]
[[Category:Social media]]
[[Category:Web 2.0 neologisms]]
[[Category:New media]]
[[Category:Social networks]]
[[Category:Blacklisting]]
[[Category:Censorship]]
[[Category:Political repression]]
[[Category:Ethically disputed political practices]]
[[Category:Internet manipulation and propaganda]]
[[Category:Internet-based activism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>