<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20060917223528|76305006" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2017420" pageid="2017420" ns="0" title="Feminization of poverty"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-09-17T22:37:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{linkless-date|August 2006}} 
The '''feminization of poverty''' has been observed since 1970 as female headed households accounted for a growing proportion of those below the poverty line. A large majority of these women are divorced or never-married mothers.  In 2000, 11% of all families in the United States lived in poverty, but 28% of families headed by single mothers did so.&lt;ref&gt;Dalaker. 2001. ''Poverty in the United States: 2000''. Current Population Reports Ser. P60, No. 214. Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office.&lt;/ref&gt;  The burden of supporting a family is difficult for single mothers because of low salaries relating to the lack of previous work experience and low educational attainment and is often exacerbated by meager or unavailable child supports.  The liberalisation of divorce laws, the increasing levels of parental co-habitation without marital commitment, and public and private aid programs specifically aimed to assist single parents have all played a role in this trend.  In the United States, divorce is a primary factor leading to the filing for economic bankruptcy.

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

*Richard T. Shaefer. 2004. Racial and Ethnic Groups. (9th ed). Prentice Hall Publishing. Page 410. ISBN 0-13-041869-2


{{socio-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>