<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111115111705|460761512" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1188531" pageid="1188531" ns="0" title="Medical model of disability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-15T14:05:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Disability}}
{{Refimprove|date=November 2011}}
{{info|Appropriate citations will shortly be added to this article based on sources found which are already on the Talk page. Please be patient as the various sources are integrated.}}
The '''medical model of disability''' is a sociopolitical model by which illness or [[disability]], being the result of a physical condition, and which is intrinsic to the individual (it is part of that individual’s own body), may reduce the individual's [[quality of life]], and causes clear disadvantages to the individual. 

It is today specifically referred to as the "medical model" of disability because of the high degree to which medical solutions, such as [[surgeries]], [[orthotics]] and clinical [[physical therapy]], are emphasized, and how they are intended chiefly as a way to "[[normalize]]" a disabled person's participation in society as much as possible. When referred to as the "medical model" rather than simply taken as the default model of disability (as it was at one time), the chief intent is usually to contrast it with the [[social model of disability]], an opposing model.

The medical model tends to believe that 'curing' or at least 'managing' illness or disability mostly or completely revolves around identifying the illness or disability from an in-depth clinical perspective (in the sense of the [[scientific]] understanding undertaken by trained [[Health care provider|healthcare providers]]), understanding it, and learning to 'control' and/or alter its course. By extension, the medical model also believes that a "compassionate" or [[justice|just]] society invests resources in health care and related services in an attempt to 'cure' disabilities ''medically'', to expand functionality and/or improve functioning, and to allow disabled persons a more "normal" life. The [[medical]] profession's responsibility and potential in this area is seen as central.

Among advocates of [[disability rights]], who tend to subscribe to [[social model of disability|the social model]] instead, the medical model of disability is often cited as the basis of an unintended social [[wikt:degradation|degradation]] of disabled people; further, resources are seen as excessively misdirected towards an almost-exclusively medical focus when those same resources could be used towards things like [[universal design]] and [[inclusion (disability rights)|societal inclusionary practices]]. This includes the monetary and the societal costs and benefits of various interventions, be they medical, surgical, social or occupational, from [[prosthetics]], drug-based and other "cures", and medical tests such as genetic screening or [[preimplantation genetic diagnosis]]. Often, a medical model of disability is used to justify large investment in these procedures, technologies and research, when adaptation of the disabled person's environment might ultimately be more beneficial to the society at large, as well as financially cheaper and physically more attainable.

Further, some disability rights groups see the medical model of disability as a [[civil rights]] issue, and criticise [[Charitable organization|charitable]] or medical initiatives that use it in their portrayal of disabled people, because it promotes a [[pity|pitiable]], essentially negative, largely [[disempowered]] image of people with disabilities, rather than casting disability as a political, social and environmental problem (''see also the [[political slogan]] "[[piss on pity]]"''). Various sociologists (Zola, Parsons) studied the socio-cultural aspects of "normalcy" and the pressure it exerts on individuals to conform{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}.

The recent [[World Health Organization]] ICF Classification (International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health)takes into account the social aspects of disability and does not see disability only as a 'medical' or 'biological' dysfunction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health|url=http://www.who.int/classifications/icf/en/|work=WHO|accessdate=15 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

==See also==
* [[Social model of disability]]
* [[Inclusion (disability rights)]]
* [[Biomedical model]]
* [[Medical model]]

==External Links==
*[http://www.open.ac.uk/inclusiveteaching/pages/understanding-and-awareness/medical-model.php The Open University: Making your teaching inclusive: The Medical Model]

== References ==
{{reflist}}


{{DEFAULTSORT:Medical Model Of Disability}}
[[Category:Disability]]
[[Category:Medical sociology]]
[[Category:Medical models]]
[[Category:Politics]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Sociological theories]]
[[Category:Social theories]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>