<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114180639|171477259" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="487090" pageid="487090" ns="0" title="Scientific racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T22:02:14Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{nofootnote}}
'''Scientific racism''' is a term that describes either [[obsolete scientific theories]] of the [[19th century]] or historical and contemporary racist propaganda disguised as scientific research. It may also refer to the notion, advanced by some [[Cultural relativism|relativists]] that the very root of western science is fundamentally racist.{{Facts|date=November 2007}}

Historically, scientific racism (or '''pseudo-scientifical racism''') has included the use of [[anthropology]] (especially [[physical anthropology]]), [[anthropometry]], [[craniometry]], [[phrenology]], [[physiognomy]] and other disciplines in the construction of [[typology (anthropology)|typologies]], or the classification of humans into distinct biological races. Such theories have provided [[ideology|ideological]] justifications to [[racism]], [[slavery]] and [[colonialism]] during the [[New Imperialism]] period in the second half of the 19th century. Their popularity coincide with this period of European expansion in the world. These scholarly theories sometimes worked in conjunction with [[racism]], for example in the case of the "[[human zoo]]s", during which various human beings were presented in cages during [[colonial exhibition]]s. They were strongly denounced after [[World War II]] and the [[Holocaust]], in particular by the [[UNESCO]] 1950 statement, signed by internationally known scholars, and titled ''[[The Race Question]]''.

Today, the phrase is used either as an [[accusation]] or to describe what is generally considered to be historical racist propaganda about the supposed existence of different "human races", refuted by ''The Race Question'' UNESCO statement who advocated the use of the more precise term "[[ethnic group]]". The phrase has been applied retroactively to publications on race as far back as the 18th century. Many subsequently disproven claims of scientific conclusion have been used as advocacy for racist policies.

== Overview ==

Along with [[eugenics]], invented by [[Francis Galton]] and popularized at the turn of the 20th century, such theories, which often postulated a "[[master race]]", usually "[[Nordic race|Nordic]]" and "[[Aryan]]", were a [[Nazism and race|main influence]] of the [[Nazi racial policies]] and their [[Nazi eugenics|program of eugenics]]. He developed the [[science]] of [[Eugenics]] whose primary concept was "control" and promotion of quantification and analytical measurements of "desirable traits" so as to set a guide on how to obtain the "truly proper breeding"(Higgins, 1994). However, this was not necessarily a continuous relationship, as several influential authors of [[Nazism]] were not [[anti-semitic]]. Quite to the contrary, [[Arthur de Gobineau]] (1816-82), for example, was a [[philo-semitism|philo-semite]] who placed the "[[Jew]]ish race" above all. Thus, although his racial theories largely influenced Nazi ideologies, they had to adapt him to suit their mindset. Apart from Gobineau's 1853 ''[[The Inequality of Human Races]]'',&lt;ref&gt;*Tucker, William. 2002. ''The Funding of Scientific Racism: Wickliffe Draper and the Pioneer Fund''. Urbana, IL: University of Illinois Press; *[[Leon Poliakov|Poliakov, Leon]]. 1974. ''Aryan Myth: A History of Racist and Nationalist Ideas in Europe''. New York, NY: Basic Books;* Biddiss, Michael D. 1970. ''Father of Racist Ideology: The Social and Political Thought of Count Gobineau''. New York: Weybright and Talley&lt;/ref&gt; other scientific racist works that largely influenced Nazism were [[Francis Galton]]’s 1870 ''Hereditary Genius: An Inquiry into Its Laws and Consequences'',&lt;ref&gt;(Tucker 1994)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Madison Grant]]’s 1916/1924 ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]''&lt;ref&gt;*Tucker 1994; *Mintz, Frank P. 1985. ''The Liberty Lobby and the American Right: Race, Conspiracy, and Culture.'' Westport, CT: Greenwood.)&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Lothrop T. Stoddard]]’s 1920 ''[[The Rising Tide of Color Against White World Supremacy]]''&lt;ref&gt;*Kühl, Stefan. 1994. ''The Nazi Connection: Eugenics, American Racism, and German National Socialism''. New York, NY: Oxford University Press;* Tucker 1994)&lt;/ref&gt;

Beside this first acception of the term, scientific racism is a pejorative label sometimes given to modern theories or arguments that allege that [[scientific evidence]] shows significant [[evolution]]ary differences between races or [[ethnic groups]]. 

In this sense, the term is used to criticize modern studies of [[human genetics]] or studies claiming to show a link between [[race and intelligence]], as well as hierarchically classifying races, hence asserting the superiority or inferiority of specific ones. Critics of such studies assert that both "race" and "intelligence" are [[fuzzy concept]]s.

==Earliest examples of scientific racism==
{{primarysources|section|date=October 2007}}
{{Mergeto|Racism|date=October 2007}}
{{Seealso|Race (historical definitions)}}

The ancient world, especially the Mediterranean and Hellenic, possessed certain proto-scientific racial theories, sometimes linking racial traits to climatic and environmental factors and sometimes to god-established "inborn character". ''The Invention of Racism in Classical Antiquity'' by Benjamin Isaac (Princeton University Press, 2006) provides an excellent introduction to the roots of scientific racism in Greco-Roman antiquity, discussing the role of Hippocrates, Plato, Aristotle, [[Galen]] and many other notable figures in the gradual formation of the modern scientific racist worldview. The 5th-century BC treatise ''Airs, Waters, Places'' by [[Hippocrates]] is a prime instance of early (proto)scientific racism. Therein it is asserted that Asiatics (in the ancient sense inclusive of Africa) tend to be more cowardly than tenacious, creative, enterprising and brave Europeans because the land and climate in which they reside is undemanding, moderate and nourishing in comparison with that of Europeans': 

"I think the inhabitants of Europe more courageous than those of Asia; for a climate which is always the same induces indolence, but a changeable climate, laborious exertions both of body and mind; and from rest and indolence cowardice is engendered, and from laborious exertions and pains, courage" ([http://classics.mit.edu/Hippocrates/airwatpl.23.23.html]).

Europeans thus have by nature a strong, courageous character and "endurance in body and soul" due to living in rigorous, cold, wintry climates. This theory is known nowadays in genetics, race-realist and anthropological circles as the "cold winter theory of intelligence" (see, e.g., [http://www.vdare.com/rushton/060322_iq.htm]; cf. also [[Julius Evola]]). In this text, Hippocrates also connects race and character explicitly by suggesting that archetypal warriors are bred in mountainous, rugged, wintry and other harsh environments, and are thus naturally light-featured and blond; whereas the people in morally effeminating environments, such as steamy, fertile lowlands, are generally dark-featured and base in spirit ([http://classics.mit.edu/Hippocrates/airwatpl.24.24.html]). Benjamin Isaac explains, "[According to Hippocrates], the fighters are light and blonde or ruddy, and the weak type is dark. This passage may very well be the earliest occurrence of this type of stereotype about color and character" (''The Invention of Racism in Classical Antiquity'', p. 65). For further study on Hippocrates and proto-scientific racism, see "The Well-Tempered Racism of Hippocrates" in ''Masks of Authority: Fiction and Pragmatics in Ancient Greek Poetics'' by Claude Calame, trans. Peter M. Burk (Cornell University Press, 2005), p. 135.

In his ''Republic'', [[Plato]] held to a theoretical racial model comparable to modern scientific racism, in which character traits are linked to climate and ethnicity. Plato theorized that races from the North (Germans, Celts, Scythians) were by nature more warriorly and "spirited"; races derived from the more southerly regions (Egyptians, Phoenicians, Semites) tended to be more slavish and materialistic; whereas those in the temperate middle parts, such as the Hellenes, are known for balance and learning:

"Must we not acknowledge, I said, that in each of us there are the same principles and habits which there are in the State; and that from the individual they pass into the State?--how else can they come there? Take the quality of passion or spirit; it would be ridiculous to imagine that this quality, when found in States, is not derived from the individuals who are supposed to possess it, e.g., the [[Thracians]], [[Scythians]], and in general the Northern nations; and the same may be said of the love of knowledge, which is the special characteristic of our part of the world, or of the love of money, which may, with equal truth, be attributed to the Phoenicians and Egyptians" ([http://oregonstate.edu/instruct/phl302/texts/plato/Republic-Book-IV.html]).

[[Aristotle]] believed that barbarians and Asians are more slavish by nature than
Greeks and Europeans:

"Barbarians are by nature more slavish than Greeks and those in Asia more than those in Europe" (Politics, 125a).

[[Pseudo-Aristotle]] declared that "Those who are too sunburnt or swarthy are cowardly; this applies to Egyptians and Ethiopians" (''Physiogn.'' 812a); "those whose eyes are excessively black are cowardly"; and "those with very woolly hair are cowardly; this applies to the Ethiopians" (812b). Benjamin Isaac links these suggestions of Pseudo-Aristotle to Hippocrates, "The idea that dark people are cowards and light people courageous fighters is found already in ''Airs, Waters, Places''..." (''The Invention of Racism in Classical Antiquity'', p. 356).

[[Vitruvius]] (70-25 B.C.), relying on the racial theories of [[Posidonius]], wrote "those races nearest to the southern half of the axis are of lower stature, with swarthy complexions, curly hair, black eyes and little blood on account of the sun. This poverty of blood makes them over-timid to stand up against the sword...On the other hand, men born in cold countries are indeed ready to meet the shock  of arms with great courage and without timidity" (''The Invention of Racism in Classical Antiquity'', p. 83).  

Exemplifying the upper-class Roman vantage point, [[Cicero]] argued that certain races, such as [[Jew]]s and [[Assyrian people|Syrians]], were designed by nature "to be slaves"&lt;ref&gt;servituti nati, Cicero de prov. 5.10; cf. 2004.225[http://www.uark.edu/rd_vcad/images/Demirel.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;.

In other parts of the pre-modern world, proto-scientific racist arguments persisted. In the Middle East, Islamic ethnology absorbed many of the Greek ideas on racial characteristics being attributable to the environment, climate and blood. The Muslim [[Masudi]] (d. 956) quoted the Greek physician and scientist [[Galen]] (A.D. c. 130-c. 200) in explaining the perceived deficiency of intelligence congenital to the [[Negroid]] type: 

"Galen says that merriment dominates the Black man because of his defective brain, whence also the weakness of his intelligence" (Bernard Lewis, ''Race and Slavery in the Middle East'', 1990, p. 52). 

In the South Said al-Andalusi (d. 1070) thought that the blacks, because of the hot thin air, lacked "self control and steadiness of mind and are overcome by fickleness, foolishness and ignorance" (cited in Lewis, 1990: 47-48). [[Ibn Khaldun]] (1332-1406), one of the greatest social thinkers and historians of the Middle Ages, attributed the perceived intellectual inferiority of black people to climate and not genetics (Lewis, p. 47). 

Regular publications on race and other claimed differences between people of different geographical locations began at least as early as the eighteenth century. The 17th and 18th century were marked by [[natural history]], in which the [[theory of evolution|concept of evolution]] had no sense. Early attempts at distinguishing various races had been made by [[Henri de Boulainvilliers]] (1658-1722), who divided the [[nation]] of France between two races, the [[aristocracy|aristocratic]], "French" race, descendants of the Germanic [[Franks]], and the [[Gallo-Roman]], indigenous race, which comprised the population of the [[Third Estate]]. According to Boulainvilliers, the descendants of the Franks dominated the Third Estate by a [[right of conquest]]. In the exact opposite of modern [[nationalism]], the foreigners had a legitimate right of domination on indigenous peoples. But contrary to later, scientifically-justified theories of race, Boulainvilliers did not understand the concept of race as designing an eternal and immutable essence. His account was not, however, only a mythical tale: contrary to [[hagiography|hagiographies]] and [[Epic poetry|epic]]s such as ''[[The Song of Roland]]'', Boulainvilliers sought some kind of scientific legitimity by basing his distinction between a Germanic race and a Latin race on historical events. But his theory of races was completely distinct from the biological concept of race later used by nineteenth century's theories of scientific racism.

[[Carolus Linnaeus]] (1707-78), a Swedish botanist, physician and zoologist, who laid the bases of [[binomial nomenclature]] (the method of naming species) and is known as the "father of modern [[taxonomy]]" (the science of describing, categorising and naming organisms) was also a pioneer in defining the concept of "race" as applied to humans. Within ''Homo sapiens'' he proposed four taxa of a lower (unnamed) rank. These categories are, ''Americanus'', ''Asiaticus'', ''Africanus'', and ''Europeanus''. They were based on place of origin at first, and later skin color. Each race had certain characteristics that were endemic to individuals belonging to it. Native Americans were reddish, stubborn, and angered easily. Africans were black, relaxed and negligent. Asians were yellow, avaricious, and easily distracted. Europeans were white, gentle, and inventive.&lt;ref&gt;Linnaeus, Carl. 
''Systema Naturae'' (1767), p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, in ''Amoenitates academicae'' (1763), Carolus Linnaeus defined ''Homo anthropomorpha'' as a catch-all race for a variety of human-like mythological creatures, including the [[troglodyte]], [[satyr]], [[Lernaean Hydra|hydra]], and [[phoenix (mythology)|phoenix]]. He claimed that these creatures actually existed, but were in reality inaccurate descriptions of real-world ape-like creatures.

He also defined in ''Systema Naturæ'' ''Homo ferus'' as "four-footed, mute, hairy." It included the subraces ''Juvenis lupinus hessensis'' ([[wolf child|wolf boy]]s), who he thought were raised by animals, and ''Juvenis hannoveranus'' ([[Peter of Hanover]]) and ''Puella campanica'' ([[Wild-girl of Champagne]]). He likewise defined ''Homo monstrosous'' as agile and fainthearted, and included in this race the [[Patagon|Patagonian giant]], the [[dwarf of the Alps]], and the [[monorchid]] [[Hottentot]].

[[Edward Long]], a [[The First European colonization wave (15th century - 19th century)|British colonial administrator]], created a more simple classification of race in ''History of Jamaica'' (1774). The next year, [[Johann Blumenbach]] published his thesis, ''On the Natural Varieties of Mankind'', one of the foundational work of scientific racism. Blumenbach, however, supported [[monogenism]], according to which all mankind had a common origin, against [[Samuel Thomas von Sömmering|Samuel von Sömmering]] and [[Christoph Meiners]], who supported [[polygenism]], the view that separate races originated independently.

== 19th century theories of race ==
[[Image:Races and skulls.png|200px|right|thumb|Nott's and Gliddon's ''Indigenous races of the earth'' (1857) used misleading imagery to suggest that "Negroes" ranked between whites and chimpanzees.]]

The [[scientific classification]] proposed by Linnaeus was a prerequisite of any attempts at scientifically classifying humanity according to various races. [[Unilinealism]] depicting a progression from primitive human societies to industrialised civilisation became popular amongst philosophers including [[Friedrich Hegel]], [[Immanuel Kant]] and [[Auguste Comte]], and fitted well with the Christian belief of a divine Creation following which all of humanity descended from the same Adam and Eve. In contrast, [[polygenism|polygenist]] theory alleged that there were different origins of mankind, thus making it possible to conceive of different, biological, human races, or to classify other humans as akin to animals without rights. Early scientific racist theories such as [[Arthur Gobineau]]'s ''[[An Essay on the Inequality of the Human Races]]'' (1853-1855) were mostly [[decadent]] in that they did not believe in the possibility of "improvement of the race."

[[Charles Darwin]]'s 1859 ''[[On the Origin of Species]]'' was very influential, although it made no mention of humanity and when he published his views in his ''[[The Descent of Man, and Selection in Relation to Sex|The Descent of Man]]'' of 1871  he was emphatic that there were no clear distinctive characteristics to categorise races as separate species, and that all shared very similar physical and mental characteristics indicating common ancestry.&lt;ref&gt;"It may be doubted whether any character can be named which is distinctive of a race and is constant... they graduate into each other, and.. it is hardly possible to discover clear distinctive characters between them... As it is improbable that the numerous and unimportant points of resemblance between the several races of man in bodily structure and mental faculties (I do not here refer to similar customs) should all have been independently acquired, they must have been inherited from progenitors who had these same characters.", [[Charles Darwin]], [http://darwin-online.org.uk/content/frameset?itemID=F937.1&amp;viewtype=text&amp;pageseq=238 ''The Descent of Man'' p225 onwards],&lt;br&gt;[http://www.rationalrevolution.net/articles/darwin_nazism.htm The Mis-portrayal of Darwin as a Racist]&lt;/ref&gt;  While he did not believe races to be distinct species, [[Charles Darwin]] did state, however,
&lt;blockquote&gt;
"''At some future period, not very distant as measured by centuries, the civilised races of man will almost certainly exterminate and replace throughout the world the savage races. At the same time the anthropomorphous apes, as Professor Schaaffhausen has remarked, will no doubt be exterminated. The break will then be rendered wider, for it will intervene between man in a more civilised state, as we may hope, than the Caucasian, and some ape as low as a baboon, instead of as at present between the negro or Australian and the gorilla''."&lt;ref name=Darwin&gt;
[http://darwin-online.org.uk/content/frameset?itemID=F937.1&amp;viewtype=side&amp;pageseq=1 Darwin, Charles. 1871. The Descent of Man, and selection in relation to sex. London: John Murray. Volume. 1. 1st edition. p 201]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;However with "[[Social Darwinism]]", a later name for ideas from earlier thinkers combined with concepts of [[evolution]] by [[natural selection]], scientific racist theories could postulate a racist "[[survival of the fittest]]," an expression coined by [[Herbert Spencer]] in 1864. Ideas of improving human races were popularized by [[Francis Galton]]'s "[[eugenics]]". Scientific racism theories, influenced by other [[discourse]]s and events, became extremely popular towards the end of the 19th century. 

[[Phrenology]], which attempted to describe traits of character by outward appearance, including by the shape of skulls, measured via [[craniometry]], and of skeletons, was put to use in racist ends. Thus, skulls and skeletons of Black people and other indigenous people were displayed between apes and white men. Thus, [[Ota Benga]], a [[Pygmies|Pygmy]], was displayed as the "Missing Link" in 1906 in the [[Bronx Zoo]] in New York, alongside apes and other animals. Some of the most influential theories included [[Vacher de Lapouge]] (1854-1936)'s "anthroposociology" and [[Johann Gottfried Herder|Herder]] (1744-1803), who applied "race" to [[nationalist]] theory to develop the first conception of [[ethnic nationalism]]. To the contrary, [[Ernest Renan]] famously argued in 1882 against Herder for a conception of nation based on the "will to live together," which was not founded on any ethnic or racial prerequisite. Scientific racist discourse posited the historical existence of "national races" such as German and French, branching from basal races supposed to have existed for millennia, such as the "[[Aryan]] race", and believed political boundaries should mirror these supposed racial ones.

=== Craniometry and physical anthropology ===
{{see|Craniometry |physical anthropology}}
Dutch scholar [[Pieter Camper]] (1722-89) was one of the first theorists of craniometry, the measure of skulls, which he used to justify racial differences. In 1770, he invented in one of his numerous memoirs the concept of the "facial angle", a measure meant to determine intelligence among various species. According to this technique, a "facial angle" was formed by drawing two lines: one horizontally from the nostril to the ear; and the other perpendicularly from the advancing part of the upper jawbone to the most prominent part of the forehead. Camper claimed that antique statues presented an angle of 90°, Europeans of 80°, Black people of 70° and the orangutan of 58°, thus displaying a hierarchic and racist view of mankind, based on a [[decadence|decadent]] conception of history. These scientific racist researchs were continued by [[Étienne Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire]] (1772-1844) and [[Paul Broca]] (1824-80).

[[Samuel George Morton]] (1799-1851), one of the inspirator of [[physical anthropology]], collected hundreds of human skulls from all over the world and started trying to find a way to classify them according to some logical criteria. Influenced by the common racist theories of his time, he claimed that he could judge the intellectual capacity of a race by the [[cranial capacity]] (the measure of the volume of the interior of the skull). A large skull meant a large brain and high intellectual capacity, and a small skull indicated a small brain and decreased intellectual capacity. By studying these skulls he decided at what point [[Caucasian race|Caucasians]] stopped being Caucasians, and at what point [[Negroes]] began. Morton had many skulls from ancient Egypt, and concluded that the [[ancient Egyptians]] were not [[African]], but were [[white]]. His two major monographs were the ''Crania Americana'' ([[1839]]), ''An Inquiry into the Distinctive Characteristics of the Aboriginal Race of America'' and ''Crania Aegyptiaca'' (1844). In ''Crania Americana'', he claimed that the mean cranial capacity of the skulls of Whites was 87 in³ (1,425 cm³), while that of Blacks was 78 in³ (1,278 cm³). Based on the measurement of 144 skulls of [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]], he reported a figure of 82 in³ (1,344 cm³) {{sic}}. 
[[Image:Ripley map of cephalic index in Europe.png|right|thumb|300px|[[William Z. Ripley]]'s map of the "cephalic index" in Europe, from ''[[The Races of Europe]]'' (1899).]]
[[Stephen Jay Gould]] (1941-2002), an American [[paleontologist]], evolutionary biologist and [[historian of science]], studied from a historical perspective these craniometric works in ''[[The Mismeasure of Man]]'' (1981). He showed that Samuel Morton had fudged data and "overpacked" the skulls with filler in order to justify his racist opinions.

In [[1873]], [[Paul Broca]] (1824-1880), founder of the Anthropological Society of Paris in 1859, found the same pattern described by Samuel Morton's ''Crania Americana'' by weighing brains at [[autopsy]]. Other historical studies alleging a Black-White difference in brain size include Bean (1906), Mall, (1909), Pearl, (1934) and Vint (1934).

=== Monogenism and polygenism ===
{{see|Monogenism |Polygenism}}
Morton's followers, particularly [[Josiah C. Nott]] (1804-1873) and [[George Gliddon]] (1809-57) in their monumental tribute to Morton's work, ''Types of Mankind'' (1854), carried Morton's ideas further and claimed that his findings in fact supported the notion of polygenism, which claims that humanity originates from different lineages and is the ancestor of the [[multiregional hypothesis]]. Morton himself had been reluctant to explicitly espouse polygenism because it was a major challenge to the biblical account of [[creation (theology)|creation]]. Charles Darwin opposed Nott and Glidon's polygenist &amp;mdash; and [[creationist]]s &amp;mdash; arguments  in his 1871 ''[[The Descent of Man]]'', arguing for a monogenism of the species. Darwin conceived the common origin of all humans (aka [[single-origin hypothesis]]) as essential for [[evolutionary theory]]. 

Furthermore, Josiah Nott was the translator of [[Arthur de Gobineau]]'s ''[[An Essay on the Inequality of the Human Races]]'' (1853-55), which is one of the founder of "biological racism", in contrast to [[Boulainvilliers]] (1658-1722)'s theory of races.

=== Philosophers of the Enlightenment and racial classifications ===
{{see|Unilineal evolution}}
A few years later, [[Immanuel Kant]] (1724-1804), celebrated as the symbol of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]]'s philosophy of progress and [[humanism]], wrote his essay ''On the Different Races of Man'' (1775) in which he attempted a scientific classification of human races. [[Friedrich Hegel]] (1770-1831) would also include a strongly [[unilineal evolution|evolutionist]] account of history in ''[[Lectures on the Philosophy of History]]'', describing the development of the ''Geist'' (Spirit or Reason) in history through a serie of incarnations in specific ''[[Volkgeist]]s'' (Folk Spirit). Hegel's [[philosophy of history]] was explicitly biased in favor of Europe, and, in particular, of the [[Prussia]]n state, conceived as the achievement of history (the "[[End of History]]"). In his chapter on the Geographical Foundings of Universal History, Hegel wrote that "each People represented a particular degree of the development of the Spirit," thus forming a "nation." Influenced, as many others, by [[Montesquieu]]'s theory on the influence of climate on mores and laws, which the latter had developed in ''[[The Spirit of the Laws]]'' (1748), Hegel wrote that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;''"It is true that climate has influence in that sence that neither the warm zone nor the cold zone are favourable to the liberty of man and to the apparition of historical peoples.&lt;ref&gt; [[Friedrich Hegel]], ''[[Lectures on the Philosophy of History]]'', 1828-1830, Chapter IV, Natural Conditions - The Geographical Foundings of Universal History; 1, General Definitions; A. Natural Conditioning, §5. &lt;/ref&gt;"''(i.e. of peoples that "have" a history, in contrast with "[[savage]]s" that allegedly have no history).&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Unsurprisingly, Hegel thus favored the ''Geist'' in temperate zones. Hegel finally made an account of "[[universal history]]," which started with the [[Orientalism|Oriental World]], then the [[Classical Antiquity|Greek Antiquity]], then the [[Roman Empire|Roman]] and the [[Christianism|Christian World]], and, ultimately, the Prussian World&lt;ref&gt; Hegel, ''ibid.'', Chapter V &lt;/ref&gt; It is true, however, that Hegel's philosophy, as Kant for that manner, can not be reduced to such evolutionist statements. In the same lessons, Hegel thus write that "America is the country of the future", but that "philosophy does not concerns itself with prophecies", but with history.&lt;ref&gt; Hegel, ''ibid.'', IV, 2, The [[New World]], 4 (1 is the Introduction) "North America and its Destiny," excipit &lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, as great as Hegel's philosophy may be considered to be, it has provided justifications for Europe's [[imperialism]] until [[World War I]]. In the same way, the works of Montesquieu, one of the early founder of modern [[sociology]], has provided various justifications over the age claiming to scientifically ground "Negroes' inferiority" on claims of the alleged influence of climate. Such racial and evolutionist statements would be echoed by [[Arthur Schopenhauer]] (1788-1860) who attributed civilizational primacy, on naturalistic grounds, to the "white races" who gained their sensitivity and intelligence by refinement in the rigorous North:

&lt;blockquote&gt;''"The highest civilization and culture, apart from the ancient [[Hindus]] and [[Egyptians]], are found exclusively among the white races; and even with many dark peoples, the ruling caste or race is fairer in colour than the rest and has, therefore, evidently immigrated, for example, the [[Brahmin]]s, the [[Inca Empire|Incas]], and the rulers of the [[Polynesia|South Sea Islands]]. All this is due to the fact that necessity is the mother of invention because those tribes that emigrated early to the north, and there gradually became white, had to develop all their intellectual powers and invent and perfect all the arts in their struggle with need, want and misery, which in their many forms were brought about by the climate. This they had to do in order to make up for the [[parsimony]] of nature and out of it all came their high civilization."''&lt;ref&gt; [[Schopenhauer]], ''Parerga and Paralipomena: Short Philosophical Essays'', Volume II, Section 92&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== Various typologies ===
{{see|Race (historical definitions)}}
One of the first [[typology (anthropology)|typologies]] used to classify various human races was invented by [[Georges Vacher de Lapouge]] (1854-1936), a theoretician of [[eugenics]], who published in 1899 ''L'Aryen et son rôle social'' (1899 - "The [[Aryan]] and his social role"). In this book, he classified humanity into various, hierarchized, races, spanning from the "Aryan white race, dolichocephalic", to the "brachycephalic" "mediocre and inert" race, best represented by the "[[Jew]] {{sic}}." Between these, Vacher de Lapouge identified the "''[[Nordic theory|Homo europaeus]]'' (Teutonic, Protestant, etc.), the "''[[Homo alpinus]]''" ([[Auvergne (province)|Auvergnat]], [[Turkish people|Turkish]], etc.), and finally the "''[[Homo mediterraneus]]''" ([[Naples|Neapolitan]], [[Andalusia|Andalus]], etc.) Vacher de Lapouge became one of the leading inspiration of [[Nazi]] [[anti-semitism]] and [[Nazi racial policies|Nazi racist ideology]].&lt;ref&gt; See [[Pierre-André Taguieff]], ''La couleur et le sang - Doctrines racistes à la française'' ("Colour and Blood - Racist doctrines ''à la française''"), Paris, [[Mille et une nuits]], 2002, 203 pages, and ''La Force du préjugé - Essai sur le racisme et ses doubles'', Tel [[Gallimard]], La Découverte, 1987, 644 pages &lt;/ref&gt; 

Vacher de Lapouge's classification was mirrored in [[William Z. Ripley]] in ''[[The Races of Europe]]'' (1899), a book which had a large influence on US [[white supremacism]]. Ripley even made a map of Europe according to the alleged [[cephalic index]] of its inhabitants. He was an important influence of the American eugenist [[Madison Grant]].

Furthermore, according to John Efron (Indiana Univ.), the late 19th century also witnessed "the scientizing of [[anti-Semitism|anti-Jewish prejudice]]," stigmatizing Jews with male menstruation, pathological hysteria, and [[nymphomania]] &lt;ref name=Efron&gt; John M. Efron (History and Jewish Studies, [[Indiana University]]), ''Defenders of the Race: Jewish Doctors and Race Science in Fin-De-Siecle Europe'', [[Yale University Press]], 1995, ISBN 978-0300054408 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bodek&gt; Richard Bodek. "[http://www.h-net.msu.edu/reviews/showrev.cgi?path=1716846635467 Review of John M. Efron, ''Defenders of the Race: Jewish Doctors &amp; Race Science in Fin-de-Siècle Europe''"], H-SAE, [[H-Net|H-Net Reviews]], May, 1996 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;. At the same time, several Jews, such as [[Joseph Jacobs]] or [[Samuel Weissenberg]], also endorsed the same pseudo-scientific theories, convinced that the Jews formed a distinct race &lt;ref name=Efron/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bodek/&gt;. [[Chaim Zhitlovsky]] also attempted to define ''[[Yiddishkayt]]'' (Ashkenazi Jewishness) by turning to contemporary racial theory &lt;ref name=Chaim&gt; Matthew Hoffman, [http://www.springerlink.com/content/w1945126w78284hm/ From Pintele Yid to Racenjude: Chaim Zhitlovsky and racial conceptions of Jewishness] in ''[[Jewish History]]'', Vol. 19, n°1 / January 2005 &lt;/ref&gt;.

=== Deniker, Grant and the "Nordic race" ===
[[Image:Deniker's Races de l'Europe (1899).jpg|right|thumb|250px|Deniker's "Races de l'Europe" from 1899, including ''la race nordique''.]]
One of William Ripley's main opponent was [[Joseph Deniker]] (1852-1918). While Ripley maintained, as Vacher de Lapouge, that Europe was composed of three racial stocks, Joseph Deniker held that there were ten European races (six primary races with four subsidiary or sub-races). Deniker's most lasting contribution to the field of racial theory was the designation of one of his races as ''la race nordique'' (the Northern race). While this group had no special place in Deniker's racial model, it would be elevated by [[Madison Grant]] (1865-1937) in his [[Nordic theory]] to the engine of civilization. Grant adopted Ripley's three-race model for Europeans, but disliked Ripley's use of the "Teuton" for one of the races. Grant transliterated ''la race nordique'' into "Nordic", and promoted it to the top of his racial hierarchy in his own popular racial theory of the 1910s and 1920s. 

Furthermore, Deniker proposed that the concept of "race" was too confusing, and instead proposed the use of the word "[[ethnic group]]" instead, which was later adopted prominently in the work of [[Julian Huxley]] and [[Alfred C. Haddon]]. Ripley argued that Deniker's idea of a "race" should be rather called a "type", since it was far less biologically rigid that most approaches to the question of race.

=== Scientific racism in the Svecoman movement in 19th century Finland ===
{{main|Language strife|Svecoman|Fennoman}}

A [[language strife]] developed in the [[Grand Duchy of Finland]] in the 19th century, supported by Finnish speaking nationalists, the [[Fennoman]]s, which aimed at raising the majority language, [[Finnish language]], from peasant-status it had during the Swedish reign to the position of a national language and status. These were opposed by the the Swedish speaking minority living in Finland, called [[Svecomans]] and best represented by the linguist [[Axel Olof Freudenthal]] (1836-1911), who defended the use of the [[Swedish language]] against [[Finnish language|Finnish]]. Svecomans were influenced by Herder, Gobineau, [[Johann Friedrich Blumenbach|Blumenbach]] (1752-1840) and others racialist theorists, and thus considered that Finland was separated into two discrete "races," one speaking Finnish, and the other, superior one, assimilated to the "Germanic race," spoke Swedish. The racial theory was finally disproven by genetics: the genetics of Finnish-speaking and Swedish-speaking Finns do not differ from each other.{{Fact|date=October 2007}}

=== Scientific racism and eugenics ===
{{see|Eugenics}}
[[Madison Grant]]'s ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'' (1916) was described by [[Stephen Jay Gould]] as "the most influential tract of American scientific racism." Grant's [[Nordic theory]] was embraced in Germany by the [[racial hygiene]] movement in the 1920s-30s. The term itself of ''Rassenhygiene'' was coined by [[Alfred Ploetz]] (1860-1940) in ''Racial Hygiene Basics'' (1895). Ploetz founded the [[German Society for Racial Hygiene]] in 1905. The German Racial hygiene movement advocated [[selective breeding]], [[compulsory sterilization]]s and a close alignment of [[public health]] with [[eugenics]].

Racial hygiene was historically tied to traditional notions of [[public health]], but usually with an enhanced emphasis on [[heredity]] &amp;mdash; what philosopher and historian [[Michel Foucault]] has called [[state racism]]. The use of social measures to attempt to preserve or enhance biological characteristics was first proposed by [[Francis Galton]] (1822-1911) in his early work, starting in 1869. He then coined the term "eugenics." A [[statistics|statistician]] before all, Galton had created the statistical concepts of regression and [[correlation]] and discovered [[regression toward the mean]], and was the first to apply statistical methods to the study of human differences and "[[inheritance of intelligence]]". He introduced the use of [[questionnaires]] and [[Statistical survey|survey]]s for collecting data on sets of [[population]]s, which he needed for genealogical and biographical works and for his [[anthropometrics|anthropometric]] studies. Galton also founded [[psychometrics]] (the science of measuring mental faculties) and [[differential psychology]] (the branch of psychology that concerns itself with psychological differences between people, rather than on common traits).

As scientific racism, eugenics became very popular in the early 20th century, and both were main influence of the [[Nazi racial policies]] as well as their [[Nazi eugenics|eugenics program]]. Galton, [[Karl Pearson]] (1857-1936) and [[Walter Frank Raphael Weldon|Walter F. R. Weldon]] (1860-1906) founded in 1901 the ''[[Biometrika]]'' scientific journal, which promoted the study of [[biometrics]] and the statistical analysis of [[hereditary]] phenomena. [[Charles Davenport]] (1866-1944) was involved for a short time in the review. He published in 1929 ''Race Crossing in Jamaica'', purported to give statistical evidence for biological and cultural degradation following [[miscegenation|interbreeding]] between white and black populations. Davenport had connections to [[Nazi Germany]], before and during World War II. in 1939 he wrote a contribution to the ''festschrift'' for [[Otto Reche]] (1879-1966), who became an important figure within the plan to "remove" those populations considered "inferior" in eastern Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Kuhl, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Scientific racism and popular racist ideology ===
{{see|Human zoo}}
[[Image:Baartman.jpg|thumbnail|right|240px|A caricature of [[Saartjie Baartman]], called the ''Hottentot Venus''. Born to a [[Khoisan]] family, she was displayed in London in the early 19th century that sparked the indignation of the African Association. She was examined by French anatomist [[Georges Cuvier]] and then died in 1815. Her remains were conserved until 1974 at the ''[[Musée de l'Homme]]'' and have since been returned to South Africa on [[Nelson Mandela]]'s request. ]]
[[Human zoo]]s were an important means of bolstering "popular racism", while being at the same time an object of [[anthropology]] and [[anthropometry]]; they were sometimes called "[[ethnographic]] exhibitions" or "Negro villages." Starting in the 1870s, they were common until World War II, and the concept has even survived until the 21st century. Ethnographic zoos were often predicated on [[Unilineal evolution|unilinealism]] and a version of [[Social Darwinism]]. A number of them placed [[Indigenous peoples|indigenous people]] (particularly Africans) in a continuum somewhere between the great apes and human beings of European descent.

Fundamental to any scientific racist theory and [[white supremacist]] views, [[social theory|theories]] of unilineal evolution claimed that [[Western culture]] was the contemporary pinnacle of [[social evolution]]. It was upheld by famous thinkers such as [[August Comte]] (1798-1857), [[Edward Burnett Tylor]] (1832-1917), [[Lewis Henry Morgan]] (1818-1881), and [[Herbert Spencer]] (1820-1903). [[Social evolutionism]] represented an attempt to formalize social thinking along scientific lines, later influenced by the biological [[theory of evolution]].

The display of human beings in cages, in an attempt to demonstrate scientific racist theories, became common in the second half of the 19th century. The [[Exposition Universelle (1889)|1889 World Fair]] in Paris had as major attraction a "Negro village" where 400 indigenous people were displayed. [[Carl Hagenbeck]], a German merchant in wild animals, exhibited in 1874 [[Samoans]] and [[Sami people]] described as "purely natural" populations. Two years later, he sent an emissary to [[Sudan]] to capture wild beasts for his [[circus]] attractions, along with [[Nubian]]s. Geoffroy de Saint-Hilaire, son of Edouard Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire and owner of the Parisian ''Jardin d'acclimatation'', presented Nubians and [[Inuit]] in 1877. 

In 1906, [[Madison Grant]], head of the [[Bronx Zoo|New York Zoological Society]], had [[Pygmy|Congolese pygmy]] [[Ota Benga]] put on display at the [[Bronx Zoo]] in New York City alongside [[ape]]s and other animals. At the behest of Grant, a prominent [[eugenics|eugenicist]], the zoo director placed Ota Benga in a cage with an orangutan and labeled him ''The Missing Link'', illustrating that in evolutionary terms Africans like Ota Benga were closer to apes than were Europeans.

Historian Pascal Blanchard et al. thus wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;''Human zoos, the incredible symbols of the colonial period and the transition from the nineteenth to twentieth century, have been completely suppressed in our collective history and memory. Yet they were major social events. The French, Europeans and Americans came in their tens of millions to discover the "[[Noble savage|savage]]" for the first time in zoos or "[[ethnography|ethnographic]]" and colonial fairs. These exhibitions of the exotic (the future "native") laid the foundations on which, over an almost sixty-year period, was spun the West's progressive transition from a "scientific" racism to a colonial and "mass" racism affecting millions of "visitors" from Paris to Hamburg, London to New York, Moscow to Barcelona...''&lt;ref&gt; **{{cite news | title=Le retour des zoos humains (par Pascal Blanchard et Olivier Barlet) | publisher=Africacultures |date=October 28, 2005 | url=http://www.africultures.com/index.asp?menu=affiche_article&amp;no=3920}};**{{cite news | title=From human zoos to colonial apotheoses: the era of exhibiting the Other by Pascal Blanchard, Nicolas Bancel and Sandrine Lemaire (English version) | publisher=Africacultures |date=October 28, 2005 | url=http://www.africultures.com/anglais/articles_anglais/43blanchard.htm}};**[http://www.derbraunemob.info/deutsch/index.htm Black Deutschland, von Oliver Hardt] &lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Justification of slavery in the nineteenth century===
[[Image:Morton drawing.png|left|thumb|200px|An 1839 drawing by [[Samuel George Morton]] of "a Negro head… a Caucasian skull… a Mongol head."]]

Because the [[Atlantic slave trade]] raised moral questions from its inception scientific theories were provided to justify the enslavement of Africans, in particular in the United States. According to Alexander Thomas and Samuell Sillen during this time period  the Black man was described as uniquely fitted for bondage because of what researches at the time called "his primitive psychological organization."&lt;ref&gt;[[Alexander Thomas]] and [[Samuell Sillen]] (1972).'' Racism and Psychiatry''. New York: Carol Publishing Group. &lt;/ref&gt; Hence, a well-known physician of the ante-bellum South, [[Samuel A. Cartwright]] (1793-1851) of Louisiana, had a psychiatric explanation for runaway slaves. He diagnosed their attempts to gain freedom as a treatable mental illness and coined the term "[[drapetomania]]" in 1851 to describe it. His feeling was that with "proper medical advice, strictly followed, this troublesome practice that many Negroes have of running away can be almost entirely prevented."&lt;ref&gt;Samual A. Cartwright, [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/aia/part4/4h3106t.html "Diseases and Peculiarities of the Negro Race"], ''[[DeBow's Review]]—Southern and Western States'', Volume XI, New Orleans, 1851&lt;/ref&gt; Cartwright also described ''[[dysaethesia aethiopica]]'', "called by overseers 'rascality'". By 1840 the challenge to slavery had begun in earnest. Data of an 1840 census seemed to indicate that blacks who lived in the North tended to live poorly due to mental illness at a higher pace than slaves who lived in the South. The conclusion was developed by Southerners that the Negro suffered only from "mental disorders"when seeking freedom. The census came to be used as a political weapon against the abolitionists (Higgins, 1994)

The attention focused on race leading up to, during, and after the [[American Civil War]] led to a proliferation of works looking at the physiological differences between [[Caucasian race|Caucasians]] and [[Negro]]es, with a large amount of attention paid to the question of "[[miscegenation]]."  Work by early [[anthropology|anthropologists]] such as [[Josiah Clark Nott]], [[George Robins Gliddon]], [[Robert Knox]], and [[Samuel George Morton]] attempted to prove scientifically that Negroes were not the same species as [[white people]], and alleged that the rulers of [[Ancient Egypt]] were not actually [[Africa]]ns, and that racial mixture provided infertile or weak offspring. In the years after the Civil War, Southern physicians wrote text after text outlining different scientific studies which sought to prove that the Negro was dying out as a race under the conditions of freedom, implying that the system of [[slavery]] had been beneficial.

==In the twentieth and twenty first centuries==

This sort of work continued through the early twentieth century, but soon [[intelligence testing]] became a new source for comparisons between races. Poorly designed studies appeared to justify the claim that "Negroes," as well as [[Eastern European]]s and [[Jew]]s, were physically and mentally inferior to whites from Northern Europe. In the United States, [[Eugenics|eugenicists]] such as [[Harry H. Laughlin]] and [[Madison Grant]] sought to justify policies such as [[compulsory sterilization]] and [[Immigration Act of 1924|immigration restriction]] by using scientific research to show that certain populations of people were physically or mentally inadequate. Compulsory sterilization programs were active until the 1960s and even further on. In France, [[Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine|Nobel prize]] winner [[Alexis Carrel]], who founded the ancestor of the present [[INED]] demographic institute, followed a similar discourse, in particular under the [[Vichy regime]]. However, Vichy didn't implement any eugenics programs. 

===Nazi Germany===
The Nazis and sympathizers published a great number of books dealing with scientific racism.  Many beliefs which would become associated with the Nazis, such as [[Eugenics]] and [[Anti-Semitism]], had been in circulation since the 19th century, and the Nazis seized on this body of existing work in their own publications.  Books such as ''Rassenkunde des deutschen Volkes'' (Ethnology of German People) by [[Hans F. K. Günther]] and ''Rasse und Seele'' (Race and Soul) by Dr. [[Ludwig Ferdinand Clauss]] attempt to identify and classify the differences between the [[Germans|German]], [[Nordic theory|Nordic]] or [[Aryan]] type and other, supposedly inferior, peoples using scientific and anthropological methods. These books were used as texts in German schools during the Nazi era.

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Rasse und Seele title.png|"Race and Soul" schoolbook
Image:Rasse_und_Selle_female.png|"Race and Soul" showing expressions of Nordic people
Image:Rasse_und_Seele_photos_male.png|"Race and Soul" showing characteristics of Nordic people
Image:Kleine_Rassenkunde_cover.png|"Small Ethnology of the German People"
Image:Kleine_Rassenkunde_photos.png|"Small Ethnology" showing Germanic types
Image:Kleine_Rassenkunde_dolicho.png|"Small Ethnology" showing differences in skull shape
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

===Civil rights era===
The ''[[Mankind Quarterly]]'', a journal that has been accused of publishing scientific racism, was founded in 1960, in part in response to the 1954 Supreme Court decision [[Brown v. Board of Education]] which ordered the desegregation of schools in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;''‘Scientific’ Racism Again?”:1 Reginald Gates, the Mankind Quarterly and the Question of “Race” in Science after the Second World War'' Journal of American Studies  (2007), 41: 253-278 Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="jackson"&gt;''Science for Segregation: Race, Law, and the Case Against Brown V. Board of Education. by By John P. Jackson. ISBN 0814742718 Page 148&lt;/ref&gt;  Many of those who constitute the publication's contributors, Board of Directors and publishers are connected to the academic [[hereditarianism|hereditarian]] tradition. This journal has been criticized by some as being political and frequent source of scientific racism.&lt;ref&gt;e.g., Arvidsson, Stefan (2006), Aryan Idols: Indo-European Mythology as Ideology and Science, translated by Sonia Wichmann, Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1960s [[George Lincoln Rockwell]], founder of the [[American Nazi Party]] gave an interview to [[Alex Haley]] for ''[[Playboy]]'' magazine (April 1966 issue)  In the interview, Rockwell explained why he believed black people were inferior to whites. He cited a study by G.O. Ferguson that showed that black people who were part white did better on a test than the "pure-black niggers" (Rockwell's words); Rockwell's use of these statistics is a textbook example of a [[statistical fallacy]] used to propagate scientific racism.&lt;ref&gt;The statistics used in the study and the excerpt from the Playboy article were used as an example of a "statistical fallacy" in the book ''Flaws and Fallacies in Statistical Thinking'' by Stephen K. Campbell&lt;/ref&gt;

===Criticism of IQ tests and intelligence research===
{{main|Race and intelligence}}
Much of the actual science used in certain early physical anthropological studies on race has been discredited as highly flawed, usually from [[methodology|methodological]] standpoints. The early [[IQ test]]s used during intelligence testing of soldiers during [[World War I]], for example, were found later to have measured [[acculturation]] to the USA more than they did any latent intelligence. {{Fact|date=February 2007}} Multiple-choice questions included such highly context-based questions as: "[[Crisco]] is a: patent medicine, disinfectant, toothpaste, food product" and "[[Christy Mathewson]] is famous as a: writer, artist, baseball player, comedian." Not surprisingly, recent immigrants to the USA did poorly on such questions, and the intelligence scores correlated most significantly with the number of years spent immersed in [[American culture]].  However, modern studies on [[race and intelligence]] have overcome many of these concerns, and the subject remains one of intense interest because they continue to show differences between races. Dorthy Roberts writes that the history of the eugenics movement in America was strongly tied to the older scientific racism used to justify slavery. Roberts writes that paralleling the development of eugenic theory was the acceptance of intelligence as the primary indicator of human value. Eugenicists claimed that the IQ test could quantify innate human ability in a single measurement, despite the objections of the creator of the test, [[Alfred Binet]].&lt;ref&gt;''Killing the Black Body: Race, Reproduction, and the Meaning of Liberty'' by Dorothy Roberts. Page 63. December 1998 ISBN 0679758690&lt;/ref&gt; 

Until the 1920s such work was regarded as science and faced little criticism. But soon, new work by the [[cultural anthropology|cultural anthropologist]] [[Franz Boas]] and [[Ruth Benedict]] began to slowly, point out methodological errors and to allege that political and ideological bias was affecting the conclusions more than the observations made. Through the [[1920s]] and [[1930s]], the Boasian school of [[cultural anthropology]] began to compete with and even replace the school of [[physical anthropology]], in a bitter institutional battle. Eventually the Boasians were defeated.

In the early 1930s, the government of [[Nazi Germany]] under [[Adolf Hitler]] utilized highly racialized scientific rhetoric based on [[social Darwinism]] for pushing its restrictive and discriminatory social policies. When [[World War II]] broke out, the Nazi approach to race became anathema in the United States, and Boasians such as [[Ruth Benedict]] were able to consolidate their institutional power. In the years after the war, the discovery of [[the Holocaust]] and the Nazi abuses of scientific research (such as the ethical violations of [[Josef Mengele]] and other [[war crime]]s which were revealed at the [[Nuremberg Trials]]) led to a widespread repudiation of the use of science to support racist causes within the scientific community.

In response to the German racial propaganda, many geneticists, especially [[Julian Huxley]] and [[Alfred C. Haddon]], along with certain anthropologists, published works denouncing the Nazi views on race and the studies they purported to be based on. Some of the anthropologist's works were even made into anti-racist propaganda and distributed widely in the form of pamphlets. Many began to identify Nazi Germany specifically with many racist attitudes which had previously been accepted (indeed, Nazi Germany did not develop them in a bubble, and many like-minded scientists had institutional support in the U.S. and UK as well), and after the war this had a great effect on how the public and scientists viewed research which made strong statements about the superiority or inferiority of races, even to the point that any scientific studies of racial differences, were viewed as being beyond the pale.

In the decades after the [[Civil Rights Movement]] in the United States, increased attention was paid to those who attempted to use science to justify purportedly racist viewpoints. Many scientists who had previously published works relating to racial differences moved into other fields. [[Robert Yerkes]], for example, had previously worked on the World War I Army intelligence testing, but in the years that followed moved instead into the field of [[primatology]].

Also symptomatic of this change in conditions were effort of international bodies such as [[United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization|UNESCO]] to draft resolutions that attempted to summarize the state of scientific knowledge about race and issue calls for the resolution of racial conflicts. In its [[1950]] ''The Race Question'' [http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0012/001282/128291eo.pdf] UNESCO declared that "A race, from the biological standpoint, may therefore be defined as one of the group of populations constituting the species Homo sapiens", which were broadly defined as the [[Mongoloid]], [[Negroid]], and the [[Caucasoid]] "divisions"  but stated that "It is now generally recognized that intelligence tests do not in themselves enable us to differentiate safely between what is due to innate capacity and what is the result of environmental influences, training and education." To this day, the 1950 UNESCO Statement is controversial among some scientists because of its message (some, such as [[R. A. Fisher]], vehemently disagreed with it) and its purpose (some objected to what was perceived as a political declaration about what science did or did not "say").  It clearly did not subscribe to the [[race|denial of the reality of race]] point of view.

In 1978, a similar sort of declaration ''UNESCO Declaration on Race and Racial Prejudice'' [http://portal.unesco.org/en/ev.php-URL_ID=13161&amp;URL_DO=DO_TOPIC&amp;URL_SECTION=201.html]. This  Statement proclaimed that no race was superior to any other, but in contrast to the 1950 statement, hardly mentioned science but rather relied more on "moral and ethical principles of humanity."  The corresponding [[2001]] 
statement by UNESCO, ''Universal Declaration on Cultural Diversity'' [http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0012/001271/127160m.pdf] does not mention race at all, nor does it use "science" as the underpinning justification for its views on cultural diversity.  Views, or at least the language, of racial discourse, have clearly evolved over the half-century.

==Modern usage==

The labeling of a work today as being "scientific racism" is generally meant to imply that the research has been politically motivated and is attempting to justify racist ideology through the use of a veneer of science. This labeling is often challenged by those who have conducted this research, who claim that their work was indeed objective and that the attempts to denounce it are acts of [[political correctness]] or [[censorship]]. 

Among those most prominently attacked as scientific racists in the late 20th century have been [[Arthur Jensen]] (''[[The g Factor: The Science of Mental Ability]]''), [[J. Philippe Rushton]], president of the [[Pioneer Fund]] (''[[Race, Evolution, and Behavior]]''), [[Richard Lynn]] (''[[IQ and the Wealth of Nations]]''), and [[Richard Herrnstein]] (''[[The Bell Curve]]''), among others. Many critics of these authors, such as [[Stephen Jay Gould]] and [[Richard Lewontin]], said that their refusal to renounce their work indicated racist motivations. Jensen published a rebuttal of Gould's accusations in ''The Debunking of Scientific Fossils and Straw Persons.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mugu.com/cgi-bin/Upstream/jensen-gould-fossils]&lt;/ref&gt; 

As another example, [[Edinburgh University]] psychologist [[Chris Brand]], whose work involves IQ, broke with convention in 1996 by indicating that he was a '[[Racial realism|race realist]].'  He was fired after a sixteen-month battle with his university (though later compensated financially for 'unfair dismissal')[http://www.cycad.com/cgi-bin/Brand/index.html][http://www.cycad.com/cgi-bin/Brand/racist.html].

Speaking for the modern anthropo-genetic theory, geneticist [[Spencer Wells]], in his book ''[[The Journey of Man]]'', connects differences in brain evolution and behaviorial style with the migration of human beings away from Africa and into the Northern and wintry regions:

&lt;blockquote&gt;"The Eurasian interior was a fairly brutal school for our ancestors. Advanced problem-solving skills would have been critical to their survival, which helps us to understand why it was only after the Great Leap Forward in intellectual capacity that humans were ready to colonize most of the world. During their sojourn on the steppes, modern humans developed highly specialized toolkits... The problem-solving intelligence that would have allowed Upper Paleolithic people to live in the harsh northern Eurasian steppes and hunt enormous game illustrates something that could called the 'will to kill'".&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The ''[[Mankind Quarterly]]'' is a journal dedicated to "[[physical anthropology]] and [[cultural anthropology]]." It contains articles on [[human evolution]], [[intelligence (trait)|intelligence]], [[ethnography]], languages, [[mythology]], [[archaeology]] and [[race]]. The journal seeks to publish work that they feel would otherwise be suppressed due to what they call the political domination of sciences by "liberals, communists and Jews."&lt;ref name="jackson"&gt;''Science for Segregation: Race, Law, and the Case Against Brown V. Board of Education. by By John P. Jackson. ISBN 0814742718 Page 148&lt;/ref&gt; 

During the "[[The Bell Curve|Bell Curve]] wars" of the 1990s, it received attention when opponents of ''The Bell Curve'' publicized the fact that some of the works cited by ''Bell Curve'' authors [[Richard Herrnstein|Herrnstein]] and [[Charles Murray|Murray]] had first been published in ''Mankind Quarterly''. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.press.uillinois.edu/epub/books/tucker/intro.html http://www.press.uillinois.edu/epub/books/tucker/intro.html]&lt;/ref&gt; In the New York Review of Books Charles Lane referred to The Bell Curve's "tainted sources," noting that seventeen researchers cited in the book's bibliography had contributed articles to, and ten of these seventeen had also been editors of, the Mankind Quarterly, "a notorious journal of 'racial history' founded, and funded, by men who believe in the genetic superiority of the white race."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2008 http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Albert Einstein's brain]]
* [[Craniometry]]
* [[Hamitic hypothesis]]
* [[Institute for the Study of Academic Racism]]
* [[John Hanning Speke]]
* [[Nazism and race]]
* [[Pioneer Fund]]
* [[Psychometrics]]
* [[Racialism]]
* ''[[Racists]]'', a 2006 novel by [[Kunal Basu]]
* [[Science Wars]]
* [[Alexandru Dimitrie Xenopol]] (1847-1920, authored a booklet on "[[race and intelligence]]", inspirator of the [[Iron Guard]])
* [[Drapetomania]]
* [[Eugenics]]
* [[American Renaissance (magazine)]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

== Bibliography ==
* Asseo, Henriette (1997). ''The Gypsies During the Second World War, Vol. 1: From Race Science to the Camps''. University of Hertfordshire Press. ISBN 0-900458-78-X
*Barkan, Elazar. ''The Retreat of Scientific Racism: Changing Concepts of Race in Britain and the United States between the World Wars''. New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992.
*Biddiss, Michael D. 1970. ''Father of Racist Ideology: The Social and Political Thought of Count Gobineau''. New York: Weybright and Talley.
*Efron, John M., ''Defenders of the Race: Jewish Doctors and Race Science in Fin-De-Siecle Europe'', Yale University Press, 1995, ISBN 978-0300054408
*[[Stephen Jay Gould|Gould, Stephen Jay]]. 1981. ''[[The Mismeasure of Man]]''. New York: Norton.
*[[Paul R. Gross|Gross, Paul R.]], and Levitt, Norman. ''[[Higher Superstition: The Academic Left and Its Quarrels With Science]]''.  Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1994. ISBN 0-8018-4766-4
*Mintz, Frank P. 1985. ''The Liberty Lobby and the American Right: Race, Conspiracy, and Culture.'' Westport, CT: Greenwood.
*Kühl, Stefan. 1994. ''The Nazi Connection: Eugenics, American Racism, and German National Socialism''. New York, NY: Oxford University Press.
*Lombardo, Paul A. 2002. "‘The American Breed’: Nazi Eugenics and the Origins of the [[Pioneer Fund]]." ''Albany Law Review'' 65:743–830.
*[[Charles Murray (author)|Murray, Charles]]. 2005. (co-author of ''[[The Bell Curve]]''), [http://www.commentarymagazine.com/production/files/murray0905.html The Inequality Taboo]. ''Commentary Magazine'', September.
*[[Leon Poliakov|Poliakov, Leon]]. 1974. ''Aryan Myth: A History of Racist and Nationalist Ideas in Europe''. New York, NY: Basic Books.
*[[Robert N. Proctor|Proctor, Robert N.]]. ''Racial Hygiene: Medicine under the Nazis''. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1988.
* Sapp, Jan (1987). ''Beyond the Gene: Cytoplasmic Inheritance and the Struggle for Authority in Genetics''. Oxford University Press ISBN 0-19-504206-9
*[[Pierre-André Taguieff|Taguieff, Pierre-André]]. 1987. ''La Force du préjugé. Essai sur le racisme et ses doubles'' (Tel [[Gallimard]], La Découverte) ISBN 2-07-071977-4 {{fr icon}}
*Tucker, William. 2002. ''The Funding of Scientific Racism: Wickliffe Draper and the Pioneer Fund''. Urbana, IL: University of Illinois Press.
*[[UNESCO]], ''[[The Race Question]]'', 1950.
*Rutledge, Dennis M. "Social Darwinism, scientific racism, and the metaphysics of race." The Journal of Negro Education (1995) 35. 21 Oct 2007. [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3626/is_199507/ai_n8730395]
*Higgins, A.C. "Scientific Racism: A review Of the Science and politics of Racial Research by William H. Tucker." Chicago: University of Illinois Press (1994) 1-5. 21 Oct 2007. http://www.math.buffalo.edu/mad/special/scientific-racism.html
*Detterman, Douglas K. "Intelligence." Microsoft® Student 2007 [DVD]. Redmond, WA: Microsoft Corporation, 2006.

==External links==
*[http://www.ferris.edu/HTMLS/staff/webpages/site.cfm?LinkID=259&amp;eventID=34 Institute for the Study of Academic Racism], [[Ferris State University]] (Michigan, USA) maintained by Barry Mehler
*[http://www.nizkor.org/other-sites/race-science.html Links to scholarly websites about "race science"] by [[Nizkor Project]]
*[http://www.cromohs.unifi.it/8_2003/abbamindiv.html The Problem of Human Diversity in the European Cultural Experience of the Eighteenth Century (Trieste, 14-15 February 2002)]
*[http://www.rationalrevolution.net/articles/darwin_nazism.htm The Mis-portrayal of Darwin as a Racist] - Refutes claims that Darwin was a racist or that his views inspired the Nazis
*[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fcgi?rid=neurosci.box.1833 Brain Size and Intelligence]
*[http://www.skeptic.com/eskeptic/05-02-18.html Reviews of Race: The Reality of Human Differences.]
*[http://www.racesci.org/index.html RaceSci.org: History of Race in Science]
*Gardner, Dan. [http://www.sinc.sunysb.edu/Stu/lmarfogl/project/race_gerdner.htm Race Science: When Racial Categories Make No Sense.] [[The Globe and Mail]], Oct. 27, 1995.
*[http://www.ferris.edu/htmls/OTHERSRV/ISAR Institute for the study of academic racism (ISAR)]
*[http://www.pbs.org/race/000_About/002_03_a-godeeper.htm Race, Science, and Social Policy.] From Race: The Power of an Illusion. [[PBS]].
*[http://www.arthurhu.com/INDEX/index.htm Arthur Hu's Index of Diversity]
*[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3626/is_199507/ai_n8730395]
*[http://www.math.buffalo.edu/mad/special/scientific-racism.html]

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Eugenics]]
[[Category:Race and intelligence controversy| ]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Pseudoscience]]
[[Category:Scientific racism| ]]

[[da:Racelære]]
[[fr:Racialisme]]
[[no:Rasebiologi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>