<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231117191615|1185590574" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="487090" pageid="487090" ns="0" title="Scientific racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-11-17T19:19:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Pseudoscientific justification for racism}}
{{redirect|Racial biology|the biological concept of race|Race (biology)}}
{{redirect|Race theory|the intellectual movement and framework|Critical race theory}}
{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2021}}
{{Race}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Scientific racism''', sometimes termed '''biological racism''', is the [[pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] belief that the [[Human|human species]] can be subdivided into biologically distinct [[taxa]] called "races,"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Garros |first1=Joel Z. |title=A brave old world: an analysis of scientific racism and BiDil |journal=McGill Journal of Medicine |date=9 January 2006 |volume=9 |issue=1 |pages=54–60 |pmid=19529811 |pmc=2687899 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Norton |first1=Heather L. |last2=Quillen |first2=Ellen E. |last3=Bigham |first3=Abigail W. |last4=Pearson |first4=Laurel N. |last5=Dunsworth |first5=Holly |title=Human races are not like dog breeds: refuting a racist analogy |journal=Evolution: Education and Outreach |date=9 July 2019 |volume=12 |issue=1 |pages=17 |doi=10.1186/s12052-019-0109-y |s2cid=255479613 |issn=1936-6434|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kenyon-Flatt |first1=Britanny |title=How Scientific Taxonomy Constructed the Myth of Race |url=https://www.sapiens.org/biology/race-scientific-taxonomy/ |publisher=Sapiens |date=19 March 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that [[empirical evidence]] exists to support or justify racism ([[racial discrimination]]), racial inferiority, or [[racial superiority]].&lt;ref&gt;"Ostensibly scientific": cf. Theodore M. Porter, Dorothy Ross (eds.) 2003. The Cambridge History of Science: Volume 7, The Modern Social Sciences Cambridge University Press, p. 293 "Race has long played a powerful popular role in explaining social and cultural traits, often in ostensibly scientific terms"; Adam Kuper, Jessica Kuper (eds.), ''The Social Science Encyclopedia'' (1996), "Racism", p. 716: "This [''[[sc.]] scientific''] racism entailed the use of 'scientific techniques', to sanction the belief in European and American racial Superiority"; ''Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy: Questions to Sociobiology'' (1998), "Race, theories of", p. 18: "Its exponents [''sc. of scientific racism''] tended to equate race with species and claimed that it constituted a scientific explanation of human history"; Terry Jay Ellingson, ''The myth of the noble savage'' (2001), 147ff. "In scientific racism, the racism was never very scientific; nor, it could at least be argued, was whatever met the qualifications of actual science ever very racist" (p. 151); Paul A. Erickson, Liam D. Murphy, ''A History of Anthropological Theory'' (2008), p. 152: "Scientific racism: Improper or incorrect science that actively or passively supports racism".&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SciRac_Gould"&gt;{{harvnb|Gould|1981|pp=[https://archive.org/details/mismeasureofman00goulrich/page/28 28–29]}}. "Few tragedies can be more extensive than the stunting of life, few injustices deeper than the denial of an opportunity to strive or even to hope, by a limit imposed from without, but falsely identified as lying within."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SciRac_CSI"&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.csicop.org/si/2004-09/scientific-ethics.html|title=Can the Sciences Help Us to Make Wise Ethical Judgments?|access-date=December 1, 2007|last=Kurtz|first=Paul|date=September 2004|journal=Skeptical Inquirer|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071123123232/http://www.csicop.org/si/2004-09/scientific-ethics.html|archive-date=November 23, 2007|quote=There have been abundant illustrations of pseudoscientific theories-monocausal theories of human behavior that were hailed as "scientific"-that have been applied with disastrous results. Examples: ... Many racists today point to IQ to justify a menial role for blacks in society and their opposition to affirmative action.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="EPSS"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|editor-first=Byron|editor-last=Kaldis|title=Encyclopedia of Philosophy and the Social Sciences|publisher=SAGE Publications|year=2013|pages=779|isbn=9781452276045}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before the mid-20th century, scientific racism was accepted throughout the scientific community, but it is no longer considered scientific.&lt;ref name="SciRac_Gould"/&gt;&lt;ref name="SciRac_CSI"/&gt; The division of humankind into biologically separate groups, along with the assignment of particular physical and mental characteristics to these groups through constructing and applying corresponding [[Scientific modelling|explanatory models]], is referred to as  '''racialism''', '''race realism''', or '''race science''' by those who support these ideas. Modern scientific consensus rejects this view as being irreconcilable with modern [[Genetics|genetic research]].&lt;ref name="Templeton2016"&gt;Templeton, A. (2016). EVOLUTION AND NOTIONS OF HUMAN RACE. In Losos J. &amp; Lenski R. (Eds.), ''How Evolution Shapes Our Lives: Essays on Biology and Society'' (pp. 346–361). Princeton; Oxford: Princeton University Press. {{doi|10.2307/j.ctv7h0s6j.26}}. That this view reflects the consensus among American anthropologists is stated in: {{cite journal|last2=Yu|first2=Joon-Ho|last3=Ifekwunigwe|first3=Jayne O.|last4=Harrell|first4=Tanya M.|last5=Bamshad|first5=Michael J.|last6=Royal|first6=Charmaine D.|date=February 2017|title=Anthropologists' views on race, ancestry, and genetics|journal=American Journal of Physical Anthropology|volume=162|issue=2|pages=318–327|doi=10.1002/ajpa.23120|pmid=27874171|last1=Wagner|first1=Jennifer K.|pmc=5299519}} See also: {{cite web|author=[[American Association of Physical Anthropologists]]|title=AAPA Statement on Race and Racism |website=American Association of Physical Anthropologists|access-date=June 19, 2020 |date=March 27, 2019 |url=https://physanth.org/about/position-statements/aapa-statement-race-and-racism-2019/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Scientific racism misapplies, misconstrues, or distorts [[anthropology]] (notably [[physical anthropology]]), [[craniometry]], [[evolutionary biology]], and other disciplines or pseudo-disciplines through proposing anthropological [[typology (anthropology)|typologies]] to [[Historical race concepts|classify human populations]] into physically discrete human races, some of which might be asserted to be superior or inferior to others. Scientific racism was common during the period from the 1600s to the end of [[World War II]], and was particularly prominent in European and American academic writings from the mid-19th century through the early-20th century. Since the second half of the 20th century, scientific racism has been discredited and criticized as obsolete, yet has persistently been used to support or validate racist world-views based upon belief in the existence and significance of racial categories and a hierarchy of superior and inferior races.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. Patricia Hill Collins, ''Black feminist thought: knowledge, consciousness, and the politics of empowerment'' (2nd ed., 2000), Glossary, p. 300: "Scientific racism was designed to prove the inferiority of people of color"; Simon During, ''Cultural studies: a critical introduction'' (2005), p. 163: "It [''sc. scientific racism''] became such a powerful idea because ... it helped legitimate the domination of the globe by whites"; David Brown and Clive Webb, ''Race in the American South: From Slavery to Civil Rights'' (2007), p. 75: "...the idea of a hierarchy of races was driven by an influential, secular, scientific discourse in the second half of the eighteenth century and was rapidly disseminated during the nineteenth century".&lt;/ref&gt;

After the end of World War II, scientific racism in theory and action was formally denounced, especially in [[UNESCO]]'s early [[Scientific anti-racism|antiracist]] statement, "[[The Race Question]]" (1950): "The biological fact of race and the myth of 'race' should be distinguished. For all practical social purposes, 'race' is not so much a biological phenomenon as a social myth. The myth of 'race' has created an enormous amount of human and social damage. In recent years, it has taken a heavy toll in human lives, and caused untold suffering."&lt;ref&gt;UNESCO, [http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0012/001282/128291eo.pdf The Race Question], p. 8&lt;/ref&gt; Since that time, developments in [[human evolutionary genetics]] and [[Biological anthropology|physical anthropology]] have led to a new consensus among anthropologists that [[Race (human categorization)|human races]] are a sociopolitical phenomenon rather than a biological one.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Gannon|first1=Megan|date=February 5, 2016|title=Race Is a Social Construct, Scientists Argue|url=https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/race-is-a-social-construct-scientists-argue/|journal=Scientific American|language=en|access-date=December 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Daley |first1=C. E. |title=The Cambridge Handbook of Intelligence|last2=Onwuegbuzie|first2=A. J.|publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2011 |isbn=9780521518062|editor-last=Sternberg|editor-first=R.|location=Cambridge New York |pages=293–306 |chapter=Race and Intelligence|editor-last2=Kaufman|editor-first2=S. B.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Diana Smay, George Armelagos|title=Galileo wept: A critical assessment of the use of race in forensic anthropolopy|journal=Transforming Anthropology|date=2000|volume=9|issue=2|pages=22–24|url=http://www.anthropology.emory.edu/FACULTY/ANTGA/Web%20Site/PDFs/Galileo%20Wept-%20A%20Critical%20Assessment%20of%20the%20Use%20of%20Race%20in%20Forensic%20Anthropology.pdf|access-date=July 13, 2016|doi=10.1525/tran.2000.9.2.19|archive-date=August 18, 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180818073338/http://www.anthropology.emory.edu/FACULTY/ANTGA/Web%20Site/PDFs/Galileo%20Wept-%20A%20Critical%20Assessment%20of%20the%20Use%20of%20Race%20in%20Forensic%20Anthropology.pdf|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rotimi|first=Charles N.|date=2004|title=Are medical and nonmedical uses of large-scale genomic markers conflating genetics and 'race'?|journal=Nature Genetics|volume=36|issue=11 Suppl|pages=43–47|doi=10.1038/ng1439|pmid=15508002|quote="Two facts are relevant: (i) as a result of different evolutionary forces, including natural selection, there are geographical patterns of genetic variations that correspond, for the most part, to continental origin; and (ii) observed patterns of geographical differences in genetic information do not correspond to our notion of social identities, including 'race' and 'ethnicity"|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ''scientific racism'' is generally used pejoratively when applied to more modern theories, such as those in ''[[The Bell Curve]]'' (1994). Critics argue that such works postulate racist conclusions, such as a genetic connection between [[race and intelligence]], that are unsupported by available evidence.&lt;ref name="Tucker07"&gt;{{harvnb|Tucker|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Publications such as the ''[[Mankind Quarterly]]'', founded explicitly as a "race-conscious" journal, are generally regarded as platforms of scientific racism, because they publish fringe interpretations of [[human evolution]], [[intelligence (trait)|intelligence]], [[ethnography]], [[language]], [[mythology]], [[archaeology]], and race.

==Antecedents==

===Enlightenment thinkers===
During the [[Age of Enlightenment]] (an era from the 1650s to the 1780s), concepts of [[monogenism]] and [[polygenism]] became popular, though they would only be systematized epistemologically during the 19th century. Monogenism contends that all races have a single origin, while polygenism is the idea that each race has a separate origin. Until the 18th century, the words "race" and "species" were interchangeable.&lt;ref name="Jen E. Boyle 2010 page 74"&gt;Jen E. Boyle (2010), "Anamorphosis in Early Modern Literature: Mediation and Affect", Ashgate, p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;

====François Bernier====
[[François Bernier]] (1620–1688) was a French physician and traveller. In 1684, he published a brief essay dividing humanity into what he called “races," distinguishing individuals, and particularly women, by skin color and a few other physical traits. The article was published anonymously in the ''[[Journal des Savants]]'', the earliest academic journal published in Europe, and titled "New Division of the Earth by the Different Species or 'Races' of Man that Inhabit It."&lt;ref&gt;François Bernier, [https://web.archive.org/web/20060524134126/http://www.as.ua.edu/ant/bindon/ant275/reader/bernier.PDF "A New Division of the Earth"] from ''[[Journal des Scavans]]'', 24 April 1684. Translated by T. Bendyshe in Memoirs Read Before the Anthropological Society of London, vol. 1, 1863–64, pp. 360–64.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the essay, he distinguished four different races: 1) The first race included populations from Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, India, south-east Asia, and the Americas; 2) the second race consisted of the sub-[[Sahara]]n Africans; 3) the third race consisted of the east- and northeast Asians; and, 4) the fourth race were [[Sámi people]]. A product of French Salon culture, the essay placed an emphasis on different kinds of female beauty. Bernier emphasized that his novel classification was based on his personal experience as a traveler in different parts of the world. Bernier offered a distinction between essential genetic differences and accidental ones that depended on environmental factors. He also suggested that the latter criterion might be relevant to distinguish sub-types.&lt;ref name="Rubiés"&gt;Joan-Pau Rubiés, «Race, climate and civilization in the works of François Bernier», L'inde des Lumières. Discours, histoire, savoirs (XVIIe-XIXe siècle), ''Purushartha'' 31, París, Éditions de l'EHESSS, 2013, pp. 53–78.&lt;/ref&gt; His biological classification of racial types never sought to go beyond physical traits, and he also accepted the role of climate and diet in explaining degrees of human diversity. Bernier had been the first to extend the concept of "species of man" to racially classify the entirety of humanity, but he did not establish a cultural hierarchy between the so-called 'races' that he had conceived. On the other hand, he clearly placed white Europeans as the norm from which other 'races' deviated.&lt;ref name="Stuurman"&gt;Stuurman, S. (2000), "François Bernier and the invention of racial classification", ''History Workshop Journal'', 50, pp. 1–21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Rubiés"/&gt;

The qualities which he attributed to each race were not strictly Eurocentric, because he thought that peoples of temperate Europe, the Americas, and India—although culturally very different from one another—belonged to roughly the same racial group, and he explained the differences between the civilizations of India (his main area of expertise) and Europe through climate and institutional history. By contrast, he emphasized the biological difference between Europeans and Africans, and made very negative comments towards the [[Sámi people|Sámi]] (Lapps) of the coldest climates of Northern Europe,&lt;ref name="Stuurman"/&gt; and about Africans living at the [[Cape of Good Hope]]. For example, Bernier wrote: “The 'Lappons' compose the 4th race. They are a small and short race with thick legs, wide shoulders, a short neck, and a face that I don't know how to describe, except that it's long, truly awful, and seems reminiscent of a bear’s face. I've only ever seen them twice in [[Danzig]], but according to the portraits I've seen, and from what I've heard from a number of people, they're ugly animals."&lt;ref&gt;French introduction by France Bhattacharya to an edition of ''Voyage dans les Etats du Grand Mogol'' (Paris: Fayard, 1981).&lt;/ref&gt; The significance of Bernier’s ideology for the emergence of what Joan-Pau Rubiés called the “modern racial discourse” has been debated, with Siep Stuurman considering it the beginning of modern racial thought,&lt;ref name="Stuurman"/&gt; while Joan-Pau Rubiés believes it is less significant if Bernier's entire view of humanity is taken into account.&lt;ref name="Rubiés"/&gt;

====Robert Boyle====
[[File:The Shannon Portrait of the Hon Robert Boyle.jpg|thumb|[[Robert Boyle]]]]
An early scientist who studied race was [[Robert Boyle]] (1627–1691), an Anglo-Irish [[natural philosopher]], [[chemist]], physicist, and inventor. Boyle believed in what today is called 'monogenism,' that is, that all races, no matter how diverse, came from the same source: [[Adam and Eve]]. He studied reported stories of parents' giving birth to differently coloured [[albinos]], so he concluded that Adam and Eve were originally white, and that whites could give birth to different coloured races. Theories of [[Robert Hooke]] and [[Isaac Newton]] about color and light via [[optical dispersion]] in physics were also extended by Robert Boyle into discourses of [[polygenesis (biology)|polygenesis]],&lt;ref name="Jen E. Boyle 2010 page 74"/&gt; speculating that perhaps these differences were due to "seminal impressions." However, Boyle's writings mentioned that at his time, for "European Eyes," beauty was not measured so much in colour, but in "stature, comely symmetry of the parts of the body, and good features in the face."&lt;ref&gt;Robert Boyle (1664), "Experiments and Considerations Touching Colours", Henry Herringman, London, pp. 160–61&lt;/ref&gt; Various members of the scientific community rejected his views, and described them as "disturbing" or "amusing."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Palmeri, Frank|title=Humans And Other Animals in Eighteenth-Century British Culture: Representation, Hybridity, Ethics|year=2006|pages=49–67}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Richard Bradley====
[[Richard Bradley (botanist)|Richard Bradley]] (1688–1732) was an English naturalist. In his book titled ''Philosophical Account of the Works of Nature'' (1721), Bradley claimed there to be "five sorts of men" based on their skin colour and other physical characteristics: white Europeans with beards; white men in America without beards (meaning Native Americans); men with copper-coloured skin, small eyes, and straight black hair; Blacks with straight black hair; and Blacks with curly hair. It has been speculated that Bradley’s account inspired Linnaeus' later categorisation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Staffan Müller-Wille|title=The Cultural Politics of Blood, 1500–1900|chapter=Linnaeus and the Four Corners of the World|year=2014|pages=191–209|doi=10.1057/9781137338211_10|hdl=10871/16833|isbn=978-1-349-46395-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Lord Kames ====
[[File:David Martin (1737-1797) - Henry Home (1696–1782), Lord Kames, Scottish Judge and Author - PG 822 - National Galleries of Scotland.jpg|thumb|[[Henry Home, Lord Kames]]]]
The Scottish lawyer [[Henry Home, Lord Kames]] (1696–1782) was a [[polygenist]]; he believed God had created different races on Earth in separate regions. In his 1734 book ''Sketches on the History of Man'', Home claimed that the environment, climate, or state of society could not account for racial differences, so the races must have come from distinct, separate stocks.&lt;ref name="Jackson05_39"&gt;{{harvnb|Jackson|Weidman|2005|pp=39–41}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Carl Linnaeus====
{{Unbalanced section|date=June 2020}}
[[File:Urville-Patagonians3.jpg|thumb|upright|''Homo monstrosus'', or Patagonian giants, from ''Voyage au pole sud et dans l'Océanie'' (''Voyage to the South Pole, and in Oceania''), by [[Jules Dumont d'Urville]]|alt=]]

[[Carl Linnaeus]] (1707–1778), the Swedish physician, botanist, and zoologist, modified the established [[Taxonomy (biology)|taxonomic]] bases of [[binomial nomenclature]] for fauna and flora, and also made a classification of humans into different subgroups. In the twelfth edition of ''[[Systema Naturae]]'' (1767), he labeled five&lt;ref&gt;Initially, Linnaeus had only described four categories: ''Europæus albesc[ens], Americanus rubesc[ens], Asiaticus fuscus, &amp; Africanus nigr[iculus]''(Note the color references were whitish, reddish, and blackish, in difference to later editions white, red and black). Only later editions included the "Monstrosus".&lt;/ref&gt; "[[Variety (botany)|varieties]]"&lt;ref&gt;Linnaeus did not use the term "race." He used the term ''"Homo variat"'', as can be seen in Systema naturae, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gloria Ramon (2002), [http://serendip.brynmawr.edu/biology/b103/f00/web2/ramon2.html "Race: Social Concept, Biological Idea"]&lt;/ref&gt; of human species.
Each one was described as possessing the following physiognomic characteristics "varying by culture and place":&lt;ref&gt;Linnaeus used the Latin term: ''diurnus, varians cultura, loco:'' [https://books.google.com/books?id=-eIVAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=Mammalia.+Primates.+Homo ''Systema Naturae,'' 13th edition, p. 29]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ''Americanus'': red, choleric, upright; black, straight, thick hair; nostrils flared; face freckled; beardless chin; stubborn, zealous, free; painting themself with red lines; governed by habit.&lt;ref&gt;In latin: ''rufus, cholericus, rectus. Pilis: nigris, rectis, crassis. Naribus: Patulis. Facie: ephelitica. Mento: subimberbi. Pertinax, contentus, liber. Pingit: Se lineis daedaleis rubris. Regitur Consuetudine.''&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ''[[Ethnic groups in Europe|Europeanus]]'': white, sanguine, muscular; with yellowish, long hair; blue eyes; gentle, acute, inventive; covered with close vestments; governed by customs.&lt;ref&gt;In latin: ''albus, sanguineus, torosus. Pilis flavescentibus, prolixis. Oculis caeruleis. Levis, argutus, inventor. Tegitur Vestimentis arctis. Regitur Ritibus.''&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ''Asiaticus'': yellow, melancholic, stiff; black hair, dark eyes; austere, haughty, greedy; covered with loose clothing; governed by beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;In latin: ''luridus, melancholicus, rigidus. Pilis nigricantibus. Oculis fuscis. Severus, fastuosus, avarus. Tegitur Indumentis laxis. Regitur Opinionibus.''&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ''Afer'' or ''Africanus'': black, phlegmatic, relaxed; black, frizzled hair; silky skin, flat nose, tumid lips; females with [[elongated labia]]; mammary glands give milk abundantly; sly, lazy, negligent; anoints themself with grease; governed by caprice.&lt;ref&gt;In latin: ''niger, phlegmaticus, laxus. Pilis atris, contortuplicatis. Cute holosericea. Naso simo. Labiis tumidis. Feminis sinus pudoris. Mammae lactantes prolixae. Vafer, segnis, negligens. Ungit se pingui. Regitur Arbitrio.''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Schiebinger |first=Londa |title=Taxonomy for Human Beings |url=https://wp.nyu.edu/tift/wp-content/uploads/sites/9559/2020/06/00-Week-One-Readings-2.0.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Linnaeus and Race |url=https://www.linnean.org/learning/who-was-linnaeus/linnaeus-and-race |access-date=2023-05-05 |website=The Linnean Society |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=The Geometer of Race |url=https://www.discovermagazine.com/mind/the-geometer-of-race |access-date=2023-05-05 |website=Discover Magazine |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ''Monstrosus'' were mythologic humans which did not appear in the first editions of ''Systema Naturae.'' The sub-species included: the “four-footed, mute, hairy” ''Homo feralis'' (''Feral man''); the animal-reared ''Juvenis lupinus hessensis'' (Hessian [[Feral child|wolf boy]]); the ''Juvenis hannoveranus'' ([[Peter the Wild Boy|Hannoverian boy]]); the ''Puella campanica'' ([[Marie-Angélique Memmie Le Blanc|Wild-girl of Champagne]]); the agile, but faint-hearted ''Homo monstrosus'' (''Monstrous man''); the [[Patagon]]ian giant; the Dwarf of the Alps; and the [[monorchid]] [[Khoikhoi]] (Hottentot). In ''Amoenitates academicae'' (1763), Linnaeus presented the [[mythology|mythologic]] ''Homo anthropomorpha'' (''Anthropomorphic man''), or humanoid creatures, such as the [[Troglodytae|troglodyte]], the [[satyr]], the [[Lernaean Hydra|hydra]], and the [[phoenix (mythology)|phoenix]], incorrectly identified as [[Ape|simian]] creatures.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Reid|first=Gordon McGregor|date=2009|title=Carolus Linnaeus (1707–1778): His Life, Philosophy and Science and Its Relationship to Modern Biology and Medicine|journal=Taxon|volume=58|issue=1|pages=18–31|jstor=27756820|doi=10.1002/tax.581005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are disagreements about the basis for Linnaeus' human taxa. On the one hand, his harshest critics say the classification was not only ethnocentric, but seemed to be based upon skin colour. Renato G. Mazzolini argued that classifications based on skin colour, at its core, were a white/black polarity, and that Linnaeus’ thinking became paradigmatic for later racist beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;Renato G Mazzolini – Skin Color and the Origin of Physical Anthropology. in: Reproduction, Race, and Gender in Philosophy and the Early Life Sciences. Ed. Susanne Lettow. 2014&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, Quintyn (2010) points out that some authors believed that Linnaeus’ classification was based upon geographical distribution, being cartographically-based, and not hierarchical.&lt;ref&gt;Conrad B. Quintyn (2010), "The Existence Or Non-existence of Race?, Teneo Press p.17&lt;/ref&gt; In the opinion of Kenneth A.R. Kennedy (1976), Linnaeus certainly considered his own culture as superior, but his motives for the classification of human varieties were not race-centered.&lt;ref&gt;Kenneth A.R. Kennedy (1976), "Human Variation in Space and Time". Wm. C. Brown Company, p. 25. Kennedy writes that while ''"Linnaeus was the first to use biological traits as a basis for further subdivisions of the species into varieties. It would be unfair to ascribe racist motives to this effort."''&lt;/ref&gt; Paleontologist [[Stephen Jay Gould]] (1994) argued that the taxa was "not in the ranked order favored by most Europeans in the racist tradition," and that Linnaeus' division was influenced by the medical [[Humorism|theory of humors]], which said that a person's temperament may be related to biological fluids.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gould|1981|p=67}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rachel N. Hastings (2008), "Black Eyez: Memoirs of a Revolutionary", p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1994 essay, Gould added: “I don't mean to deny that Linnaeus held conventional beliefs about the superiority of his own European variety over others... nevertheless, and despite these implications, the overt geometry of Linnaeus' model is not linear or hierarchical.”&lt;ref name="Gould 1994"&gt;{{Cite magazine |last=Gould |first=Stephen Jay |date=November 1994 |title=The Geometer of Race |url=https://www.discovermagazine.com/mind/the-geometer-of-race |magazine=Discover |pages=65–69 |issn=0274-7529}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2008 essay published by the [[Linnean Society of London]], Marie-Christine Skuncke interpreted Linnaeus' statements as reflecting a view that "Europeans' superiority resides in "culture," and that the decisive factor in Linnaeus' taxa was "culture," ''not'' race." Thus, regarding this topic, Skuncke considers Linnaeus' view as merely "[[eurocentric]]," arguing that Linnaeus never called for racist action, and did not use the word "race," which was only introduced later "by his French opponent, [[Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon|Buffon]]."&lt;ref&gt;Mary J. Morris &amp; Leonie Berwick (2008), ''[http://www.linnean.org/Resources/LinneanSociety/Documents/Publications/Other/Special%20Issue%208%20-%20The%20Linneaen%20Legacy.pdf The Linnaean Legacy: Three Centuries after his birth] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130513171426/http://www.linnean.org/Resources/LinneanSociety/Documents/Publications/Other/Special%20Issue%208%20-%20The%20Linneaen%20Legacy.pdf |date=2013-05-13 }}'', A forum for natural history. The Linnean Special Issue No. 8. [[Linnean Society of London]], Burlington House, Piccadilly, London. ''Was Linnaeus a racist?'', p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; However, the anthropologist [[Ashley Montagu]], in his book ''Man's Most Dangerous Myth: the Fallacy of Race'', points out that Buffon, indeed “the enemy of all rigid classifications,”&lt;ref name=Montagu1&gt;Montagu, A. (2001 edition) ''Man's Most Dangerous Myth: The Fallacy of Race''. New York: Columbia University Press, p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; was diametrically opposed to such broad categories, and did not use the word "race" to describe them. “It was quite clear, after reading Buffon, that he uses the word in no narrowly defined, but rather in a general sense,”&lt;ref name=Montagu1/&gt; wrote Montagu, pointing out that Buffon did employ the French word ''la race'', but as a collective term for whatever population he happened to be discussing at the time; for instance: “The Danish, Swedish, and Muscovite Laplanders, the inhabitants of Nova-Zembla, the Borandians, the Samoiedes, the Ostiacks of the old continent, the Greenlanders, and the savages to the north of the Esquimaux Indians, of the new continent, appear to be of one common race.”&lt;ref&gt;Buffon, trans. Barr, (1807) ''Natural History, General and Particular'', volume 4, p.191&lt;/ref&gt;

Scholar Stanley A. Rice agrees that Linnaeus' classification was not meant to “imply a hierarchy of humanness or superiority”;&lt;ref&gt;Stanley A. Rice (2009), "Encyclopedia of Evolution", Infobase Publishing, p. 195. Stanley states: ''"Even though the prejudice and racism of the attributes are obvious to modern scientists, Linnaeus did not apparently mean to imply a hierarchy of humanness or superiority."''&lt;/ref&gt; however, modern critics regard Linnaeus’ classification as obviously [[stereotype]]d and erroneous for having included [[anthropological]], non-biological features, such as customs or traditions.

==== John Hunter ====
[[File:John Hunter by John Jackson.jpg|thumb|''John Hunter''. Painted by John Jackson in 1813, after an original by Sir Joshua Reynolds, who exhibited his painting at the Royal Academy in 1786.]]
[[John Hunter (Surgeon)|John Hunter]] (1728–1793), a Scottish surgeon, believed that the Negroid race was originally white at birth. He thought that over time, because of the sun, the people turned dark-skinned, or "black." Hunter also stated that blisters and burns would likely turn white on a Negro, which he asserted was evidence that their ancestors were originally white.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Harris|2001|p=85}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Charles White, physician (1728–1813) (cropped).jpg|left|upright|thumb|Charles White]]

==== Charles White ====
[[Charles White (physician)|Charles White]] (1728–1813), an English physician and surgeon, believed that races occupied different stations in the "[[Great Chain of Being]]," and he tried to scientifically prove that human races had distinct origins from each other. He speculated that whites and Negroes were two different species. White was a believer in [[polygenism|polygeny]], the idea that different races had been created separately. His ''Account of the Regular Gradation in Man'' (1799) provided an empirical basis for this idea. White defended the theory of polygeny by rebutting French naturalist [[Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon]]'s interfertility argument, which said that only the same species can interbreed. White pointed to species hybrids, such as foxes, [[wolf|wolves]], and [[jackal]]s, which were separate groups that were still able to interbreed. For White, each race was a separate species, divinely created for its own geographical region.&lt;ref name=Jackson05_39/&gt;

==== Buffon and Blumenbach ====
[[File:Johann Friedrich Blumenbach.jpg|thumb|upright=0.6|left|Johann Friedrich Blumenbach|alt=]]

The French naturalist [[Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon]] (1707–1788) and the German anatomist [[Johann Blumenbach]] (1752–1840) were proponents of [[monogenism]], the concept that all races have a single origin.&lt;ref name="Harris-2001"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Harris|first=Marvin|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Ef5uAAAAQBAJ|title=The Rise of Anthropological Theory: A History of Theories of Culture|publisher=AltaMira Press|year=2001|isbn=978-0-7591-1699-3|edition=Updated|location=Walnut Creek, California|pages=84–87, 110–111|language=en|orig-date=1968}}&lt;/ref&gt; Buffon and Blumenbach believed a "degeneration theory" of the origins of racial difference.&lt;ref name="Harris-2001" /&gt; Both asserted that [[Adam and Eve]] were white, and that other races came about by degeneration owing to environmental factors, such as climate, disease, and diet.&lt;ref name="Harris-2001" /&gt; According to this model, Negroid [[pigmentation]] arose because of the heat of the tropical sun; that cold wind caused the tawny colour of the [[Eskimos]]; and that the Chinese had fairer skins than the [[Tatars|Tartars]], because the former kept mostly in towns, and were protected from environmental factors.&lt;ref name="Harris-2001" /&gt; Environmental factors, poverty, and hybridization could make races "degenerate," and differentiate them from the original white race by a process of "raciation."&lt;ref name="Harris-2001" /&gt; Interestingly, both Buffon and Blumenbach believed that the degeneration could be reversed if proper environmental control was taken, and that all contemporary forms of man could revert to the original white race.&lt;ref name="Harris-2001" /&gt;

According to Blumenbach, there are five races, all belonging to a single species: [[Caucasian race|Caucasian]], [[Mongoloid|Mongolian]], [[Negroid]], [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|American]], and the [[Malay race]]. Blumenbach stated: “I have allotted the first place to the Caucasian for the reasons given below, which make me esteem it the primeval one.”&lt;ref&gt;Emmanuel Chukwudi Eze, ''Race and the Enlightenment: A Reader,'' 1997, p. 84&lt;/ref&gt;

Before [[James Hutton]] and the emergence of scientific geology, many believed the Earth was only 6,000 years old. Buffon had conducted experiments with heated balls of iron, which he believed were a model for the Earth's core, and concluded that the Earth was 75,000 years old, but did not extend the time since [[Adam]] and the origin of humanity back more than 8,000 years—not much further than the 6,000 years of the prevailing [[Ussher chronology]] subscribed to by most of the monogenists.&lt;ref name="Harris-2001" /&gt; Opponents of monogenism believed that it would have been difficult for races to change markedly in such a short period of time.&lt;ref name="Harris-2001" /&gt;

====Benjamin Rush====
[[Benjamin Rush]] (1745–1813), a [[Founding Father of the United States]] and a physician, proposed that being black was a hereditary skin disease, which he called "negroidism," and that it could be cured. Rush believed non-whites were actually white underneath, but that they were stricken with a non-contagious form of [[leprosy]], which darkened their skin color. Rush drew the conclusion that "whites should not tyrannize over [blacks], for their disease should entitle them to a double portion of humanity. However, by the same token, whites should not intermarry with them, for this would tend to infect posterity with the 'disorder'… attempts must be made to cure the disease."&lt;ref&gt;Rush, Benjamin (1799). "Observations Intended to Favour a Supposition That the Black Color (As It Is Called) of the Negroes Is Derived from the Leprosy". Transactions of the American Philosophical Society 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Christoph Meiners====
[[File:Christoph Meiners.jpg|thumb|upright=0.6|Christoph Meiners|alt=]]

[[Christoph Meiners]] (1747–1810) was a German [[polygenist]], and believed that each race had a separate origin. Meiners studied the physical, mental, and moral characteristics of each race, and built a race hierarchy based on his findings. Meiners split mankind into two divisions, which he labelled the "beautiful [[white race]]" and the "ugly [[black race]]." In his book titled ''The Outline of History of Mankind'', Meiners argued that a main characteristic of race is either beauty or ugliness. Meiners thought only the white race to be beautiful, and considered ugly races to be inferior, immoral, and animal-like. Meiners wrote about how the dark, ugly peoples were differentiated from the white, beautiful peoples by their "sad" lack of virtue and their "terrible vices."&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Isaac|2004|p=150}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meiners hypothesized about how the Negro felt less pain than any other race, and lacked in emotions. Meiners wrote that the Negro had thick nerves, and thus, was not sensitive like the other races. He went so far as to say that the Negro possessed "no human, barely any animal, feeling." Meiners described a story where a Negro was condemned to death by being burned alive. Halfway through the burning, the Negro asked to smoke a pipe, and smoked it like nothing was happening while he continued to be burned alive. Meiners studied the [[anatomy]] of the Negro, and came to the conclusion that Negroes were all [[carnivores]], based upon his observations that Negroes had bigger teeth and jaws than any other race. Meiners claimed the skull of the Negro was larger, but the brain of the Negro was smaller than any other race. Meiners theorized that the Negro was the most unhealthy race on Earth because of its poor diet, mode of living, and lack of morals.&lt;ref name="Gupta07"&gt;{{cite book|author=Das Gupta, Tania|title=Race and Racialization: Essential Readings|year=2007|pages=25–26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meiners studied the diet of the Americans, and said they fed off any kind of "foul [[offal]]," and consumed copious amounts of alcohol. He believed their skulls were so thick that the blades of Spanish swords shattered on them. Meiners also claimed the skin of an American is thicker than that of an ox.&lt;ref name=Gupta07/&gt;

Meiners wrote that the noblest race was the [[Celts]]. This was based upon assertions that they were able to conquer various parts of the world, they were more sensitive to heat and cold, and their delicacy is shown by the way they are selective about what they eat. Meiners claimed that [[Slavs]] are an inferior race, "less sensitive and content with eating rough food." He described stories of Slavs allegedly eating poisonous fungi without coming to any harm. He claimed that their medical techniques were also counterproductive; as an example, Meiners described their practice of warming up sick people in ovens, then making them roll in the snow.&lt;ref name=Gupta07/&gt;

===Later thinkers===

====Thomas Jefferson====
[[Thomas Jefferson]] (1743–1826) was an American politician, scientist,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://allthingsliberty.com/2015/08/thomas-jefferson-scientist/|title=Thomas Jefferson, Scientist|date=August 20, 2015|website=Journal of the American Revolution|access-date=September 2, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.realclearscience.com/blog/2012/02/thomas-jefferson-citizen-scientist.html|title=Thomas Jefferson: Founding Father of Science &amp;#124; RealClearScience|website=www.realclearscience.com|access-date=September 2, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; and slave owner. His contributions to scientific racism have been noted by many historians, scientists, and scholars. According to an article published in the ''McGill Journal of Medicine'': "One of the most influential pre-Darwinian racial theorists, Jefferson's call for science to determine the obvious ‘inferiority’ of African Americans is an extremely important stage in the evolution of scientific racism."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Garrod |first1=Joel Z.|title=A Brave Old World: An Analysis of Scientific Racism and BiDil |journal=McGill Journal of Medicine |volume=9|issue=1|pages=54–60|pmc=2687899|year=2006|pmid=19529811}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writing for ''[[The New York Times]],'' historian [[Paul Finkelman]] described how as "a scientist, Jefferson nevertheless speculated that blackness might come ‘from the color of the blood,’ and concluded that blacks were ‘inferior to the whites in the endowments of body and mind’."&lt;ref&gt;Paul Finkelman (November 12, 2012). [https://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/01/opinion/the-real-thomas-jefferson.html?pagewanted=all "The Monster of Monticello"]. ''The New York Times''.&lt;/ref&gt; In his "[[Notes on the State of Virginia]]," Jefferson described black people as follows:&lt;ref&gt;[[Thomas Jefferson]], ''[[Notes on the State of Virginia]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;They seem to require less sleep. A black, after hard labor through the day, will be induced by the slightest amusements to sit up till midnight, or later, though knowing he must be out with the first dawn of the morning. They are at least as brave, and more adventuresome. But, this may perhaps proceed from a want of forethought, which prevents their seeing a danger till it be present. When present, they do not go through it with more coolness or steadiness than the whites. They are more ardent after their female: but love seems with them to be more an eager desire, than a tender delicate mixture of sentiment and sensation. Their griefs are transient. Those numberless afflictions, which render it doubtful whether heaven has given life to us in mercy or in wrath, are less felt, and sooner forgotten with them. In general, their existence appears to participate more of sensation than reflection... Comparing them by their faculties of memory, reason, and imagination, it appears to me, that in memory, they are equal to the whites; in reason, much inferior, as I think one [black] could scarcely be found capable of tracing and comprehending the investigations of Euclid; and that in imagination, they are dull, tasteless, and anomalous... I advance it, therefore, as a suspicion only, that the blacks, whether originally a distinct race, or made distinct by time and circumstances, are inferior to the whites in the endowments both of body and mind.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

However, by 1791, Jefferson had to reassess his earlier suspicions of whether blacks were capable of intelligence when he was presented with a letter and almanac from [[Benjamin Banneker]], an educated black mathematician. Delighted to have discovered scientific proof for the existence of black intelligence, Jefferson wrote to Banneker:&lt;ref&gt;(Jefferson's Letter to Benjamin Banneker, August 30, 1791. Original source: The Papers of Thomas Jefferson, vol 22, August 6, 1791 – December 31, 1791, ed. Charles T. Cullen. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1986, pp. 49–54.)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;No body wishes more than I do to see such proofs as you exhibit, that nature has given to our black brethren, talents equal to those of the other colors of men, &amp; that the appearance of a want of them is owing merely to the degraded condition of their existence both in Africa &amp; America. I can add with truth that no body wishes more ardently to see a good system commenced for raising the condition both of their body &amp; mind to what it ought to be, as fast as the imbecility of their present existence, and other circumstance which cannot be neglected, will admit. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Samuel Stanhope Smith====
[[Samuel Stanhope Smith]] (1751–1819) was an American Presbyterian minister and author of the ''Essay on the Causes of Variety of Complexion and Figure in the Human Species'' (1787). Smith claimed that Negro pigmentation was nothing more than a huge freckle that covered the whole body as a result of an oversupply of bile, which was caused by tropical climates.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Harris|2001|p=87}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Georges Cuvier====
[[File:Georges Cuvier large.jpg|thumb|upright|Georges Cuvier|alt=]]
Racial studies by [[Georges Cuvier]] (1769–1832), the French [[naturalist]] and [[zoologist]], influenced both scientific [[polygenism]] and scientific racism. Cuvier believed there were three distinct races: the [[Caucasian race|Caucasian]] (white), [[Mongoloid|Mongolian]] (yellow), and the Ethiopian (black). He rated each for the beauty or ugliness of the skull and quality of their civilizations. Cuvier wrote about Caucasians: “The white race, with oval face, straight hair and nose, to which the civilised people of Europe belong, and which appear to us the most beautiful of all, is also superior to others by its genius, courage, and activity.”&lt;ref&gt;Georges Cuvier, ''Tableau elementaire de l'histoire naturelle des animaux'' (Paris, 1798) p. 71&lt;/ref&gt;

Regarding Negroes, Cuvier wrote:&lt;ref&gt;Georges Cuvier, ''The Animal Kingdom: Arranged in Conformity with its Organization,'' Translated from the French by H.M. Murtrie, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The Negro race … is marked by black complexion, crisped or woolly hair, compressed cranium, and a flat nose. The projection of the lower parts of the face, and the thick lips, evidently approximate it to the monkey tribe: the hordes of which it consists have always remained in the most complete state of barbarism.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

He thought [[Adam and Eve]] were Caucasian, and hence, the original race of mankind. The other two races arose by survivors escaping in different directions after a major catastrophe hit the earth approximately 5,000 years ago. Cuvier theorized that the survivors lived in complete isolation from each other, and developed separately as a result.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Jackson|Weidman|2005|pp=41–42}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Colin Kidd, ''The Forging of Races: Race and Scripture in the Protestant Atlantic World, 1600–2000,'' 2006, p. 28&lt;/ref&gt;

One of Cuvier's pupils, [[Friedrich Tiedemann]], was among the first to make a scientific contestation of racism. Tiedemann asserted that based upon his documentation of craniometric and brain measurements of Europeans and black people from different parts of the world, that the then-common European belief that Negroes have smaller brains, and are thus intellectually inferior, was scientifically unfounded, and based merely on the prejudice of travellers and explorers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Tiedemann, Friedrich|title=On the Brain of the Negro, Compared with that of the European and the Orang-outang|journal=Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London |volume=126|pages=497–527|year=1836|url=http://laboratoriogene.info/Ciencia_Hoje/Tiedemann_1836.pdf|bibcode=1836RSPT..126..497T|doi=10.1098/rstl.1836.0025|s2cid=115347088|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Arthur Schopenhauer====
[[File:Arthur Schopenhauer by J Schäfer, 1859b.jpg|thumb|Arthur Schopenhauer|alt=]]
The German philosopher [[Arthur Schopenhauer]] (1788–1860) attributed civilizational primacy to the white races, who gained sensitivity and intelligence via the refinement caused by living in the rigorous Northern climate:&lt;ref&gt;[[Schopenhauer]], ''Parerga and Paralipomena: Short Philosophical Essays'', Volume II, Section 92&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; The highest civilization and culture, apart from the ancient [[Hindus]] and [[Egyptians]], are found exclusively among the white races; and even with many dark peoples, the ruling caste, or race, is fairer in colour than the rest, and has, therefore, evidently immigrated, for example, the [[Brahmin]]s, the [[Inca Empire|Inca]], and the rulers of the [[Polynesia|South Sea Islands]]. All this is due to the fact that necessity is the mother of invention, because those tribes that emigrated early to the north, and there gradually became white, had to develop all their intellectual powers, and invent and perfect all the arts in their struggle with need, want, and misery, which, in their many forms, were brought about by the climate. This they had to do to make up for the [[Occam's razor|parsimony]] of nature, and out of it all came their high civilization.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Franz Ignaz Pruner====
[[Franz Ignaz Pruner]] (1808–1882) was a German physician, ophthalmologist, and anthropologist who studied the racial structure of Negroes in Egypt. In a book Pruner wrote in 1846, he claimed that Negro blood had a negative influence on the Egyptian moral character. He published a monograph on Negroes in 1861. He claimed that the main feature of the Negro's skeleton is [[prognathism]], which he claimed was the Negro's relation to the ape. He also claimed that Negroes had brains very similar to those of apes and that Negroes have a shortened big toe, a characteristic, he said, that connected Negroes closely to apes.&lt;ref&gt;[[Gustav Jahoda]], ''Images of Savages: Ancients [sic] Roots of Modern Prejudice in Western Culture'', 1999, p. 82&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racial theories in physical anthropology (1850–1918)==
[[File:Scientific racism irish.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|A late-19th-century illustration by H. Strickland Constable shows an alleged similarity between "[[Irish Iberian]]" and "Negro" features in contrast to the higher "Anglo-Teutonic".|alt=]]

The [[scientific classification]] established by Carl Linnaeus is requisite to any human racial classification scheme. In the 19th century, [[unilineal evolution]], or classical social evolution, was a conflation of competing sociologic and anthropologic theories proposing that [[Western culture|Western European culture]] was the acme of human socio-cultural evolution. The Christian Bible was interpreted to sanction [[slavery]] and from the 1820s to the 1850s was often used in the [[History of the United States (1789–1849)|antebellum]] Southern United States, by writers such as the Rev. [[Richard Furman]] and [[Thomas R. Cobb]], to enforce the idea that Negroes had been created inferior, and thus suited to slavery.&lt;ref name=drace/&gt;

===Arthur de Gobineau===
[[File:Arthur de Gobineau.jpg|thumb|upright|Portrait of [[Arthur de Gobineau]] by the Comtesse de la Tour, 1876|alt=]]
The French aristocrat and writer [[Arthur de Gobineau]] (1816–1882), is best known for his book ''[[An Essay on the Inequality of the Human Races]]'' (1853–55) which proposed three human races (black, white and yellow) were natural barriers and claimed that [[miscegenation|race mixing]] would lead to the collapse of culture and civilization. He claimed that "The white race originally possessed the monopoly of beauty, intelligence and strength" and that any positive accomplishments or thinking of blacks and Asians were due to an admixture with whites. His works were praised by many white supremacist American pro-slavery thinkers such as [[Josiah C. Nott]] and [[Henry Hotze]].

Gobineau believed that the different races originated in different areas, the white race had originated somewhere in Siberia, the Asians in the Americas and the blacks in Africa. He believed that the white race was superior, writing:
{{blockquote|I will not wait for the friends of equality to show me such and such passages in books written by missionaries or sea captains, who declare some Wolof is a fine carpenter, some Hottentot a good servant, that a Kaffir dances and plays the violin, that some Bambara knows arithmetic… Let us leave aside these puerilities and compare together not men, but groups.&lt;ref&gt;D'Souza, Dinesh "Is Racism a Western Idea?" pp. 517–39 from The American Scholar, Vol. 64, No. 4 Autumn 1995, p.538&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Gobineau later used the term "[[Aryan race|Aryans]]" to describe the Germanic peoples (''la race germanique'').&lt;ref&gt;A. J. Woodman, 2009, ''The Cambridge Companion to Tacitus'', p. 294. (The Germanic race was also regarded by Gobineau as beautiful, honourable and destined to rule: 'cette illustre famille humaine, la plus noble'. While ''[[Aryan|arya]]'' was originally an [[endonym]] used only by [[Indo-Iranians]], "Aryan" became, partly because of the ''Essai'' a racial designation of a race, which Gobineau specified as 'la race germanique'.&lt;/ref&gt;

Gobineau's works were also influential to the [[Nazi Party]], which published his works in German. They played a key role in the [[master race]] theory of [[Nazism]].

===Carl Vogt===
[[File:Carl Vogt NYPL 1158509 (cropped).jpg|thumb|Carl Vogt in 1870]]
Another [[polygenist]] evolutionist was [[Carl Vogt]] (1817–1895) who believed that the Negro race was related to the ape. He wrote the white race was a separate species to Negroes. In Chapter VII of his ''Lectures of Man'' (1864) he compared the Negro to the white race whom he described as "two extreme human types". The difference between them, he claimed are greater than those between two species of ape; and this proves that Negroes are a separate species from the whites.&lt;ref name="GustavJahoda" /&gt;

===Charles Darwin===
[[File:Charles Darwin by Julia Margaret Cameron, c. 1868.jpg|thumb|upright|Charles Darwin in 1868]]

[[Charles Darwin]]'s views on race have been a topic of much discussion and debate. According to Jackson and Weidman, Darwin was a moderate in the 19th century debates about race. "He was not a confirmed racist — he was a staunch abolitionist, for example — but he did think that there were distinct races that could be ranked in a hierarchy."&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Jackson|Weidman|2005|p=69}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Darwin's influential 1859 book ''[[On the Origin of Species]]'' did not discuss human origins. The extended wording on the title page, which adds ''by Means of Natural Selection, or the Preservation of Favoured Races in the Struggle for Life'', uses the general terminology of [[Race (biology)|biological races]] as an alternative for "[[Variety (botany)|varieties]]" such as "the several races, for instance, of the cabbage", and does not carry the modern connotation of [[Race (classification of human beings)|human races]]. In ''[[The Descent of Man, and Selection in Relation to Sex]]'' (1871), Darwin examined the question of "Arguments in favour of, and opposed to, ranking the so-called races of man as distinct species" and reported no racial distinctions that would indicate that human races are discrete species.&lt;ref name="drace"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rationalrevolution.net/articles/darwin_nazism.htm|title=The Mis-portrayal of Darwin as a Racist|access-date=January 6, 2008|last=Price|first=R.G.|date=June 24, 2006|publisher=rationalrevolution.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"It may be doubted whether any character can be named which is distinctive of a race and is constant... they graduate into each other, and.. it is hardly possible to discover clear distinctive characters between them... As it is improbable that the numerous and unimportant points of resemblance between the several races of man in bodily structure and mental faculties (I do not here refer to similar customs) should all have been independently acquired, they must have been inherited from progenitors who had these same characters.", [[Charles Darwin]], [http://darwin-online.org.uk/content/frameset?itemID=F937.1&amp;viewtype=text&amp;pageseq=238 ''The Descent of Man'' p. 225 onwards].&lt;/ref&gt;

The historian Richard Hofstadter wrote: 
{{blockquote|Although Darwinism was not the primary source of the belligerent ideology and dogmatic racism of the late nineteenth century, it did become a new instrument in the hands of the theorists of race and struggle... The Darwinist mood sustained the belief in Anglo-Saxon racial superiority which obsessed many American thinkers in the latter half of the nineteenth century. The measure of world domination already achieved by the 'race' seemed to prove it the fittest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hofstadter|first=Richard|title=Social Darwinism in American Thought|publisher=Beacon Press|year=1992|pages=172–173|isbn=978-0807055038}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
According to the historian [[Gertrude Himmelfarb]], "The subtitle of [''The Origin of Species''] made a convenient motto for racists: 'The Preservation of Favoured Races in the Struggle for Life.' Darwin, of course, took 'races' to mean varieties or species; but it was no violation of his meaning to extend it to human races.... Darwin himself, in spite of his aversion to slavery, was not averse to the idea that some races were more fit than others."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Darwin and the Darwinian Revolution|last=Himmelfarb|first=Gertrude|year=1959|publisher=I.R. Dee |isbn=978-1566631068}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
	
On the other hand, Robert Bannister defended Darwin on the issue of race, writing that "Upon closer inspection, the case against Darwin himself quickly unravels. An ardent opponent of slavery, he consistently opposed the oppression of nonwhites... Although by modern standards ''The Descent of Man'' is frustratingly inconclusive on the critical issues of human equality, it was a model of moderation and scientific caution in the context of midcentury racism."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Bannister|first=Robert C.|title=Social Darwinism: Science and Myth in Anglo-American Social Thought|year=1979|publisher=Temple University Press|page=184|isbn=978-0877221555}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Herbert Hope Risley===
[[File:H H Risley.png|thumb|upright|Herbert Hope Risley|alt=Black-and-white photograph of a man.]]
As an exponent of "race science", colonial administrator [[Herbert Hope Risley]] (1851–1911) used the ratio of the width of a nose to its height to divide [[Indian people]] into Aryan and Dravidian races, as well as seven castes.{{sfnp|Trautmann|1997|p=203|ps=}}{{sfnp|Walsh|2011|p=171|ps=}}

===Ernst Haeckel===
[[File:ErnstHaeckel.jpg|thumb|upright|Ernst Haeckel]]

Like most of Darwin's supporters,{{Citation needed|date=September 2020}} [[Ernst Haeckel]] (1834–1919) put forward a doctrine of evolutionary [[polygenism]] based on the ideas of the linguist and polygenist [[August Schleicher]], in which several different language groups had arisen separately from speechless prehuman ''Urmenschen'' (German for "original humans"), which themselves had evolved from simian ancestors. These separate languages had completed the transition from animals to man, and, under the influence of each main branch of languages, humans had evolved as separate species, which could be subdivided into races. Haeckel divided human beings into ten races, of which the Caucasian was the highest and the primitives were doomed to extinction.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Jackson|Weidman|2005|p=87}}&lt;/ref&gt; Haeckel was also an advocate of the [[out of Asia theory]] by writing that the origin of humanity was to be found in Asia; he believed that [[Hindustan]] (South Asia) was the actual location where the first humans had evolved. Haeckel argued that humans were closely related to the primates of Southeast Asia and rejected Darwin's hypothesis of Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Palmer, Douglas|title=Prehistoric Past Revealed: The Four Billion Year History of Life on Earth|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|year=2006|page=43|isbn=978-0520248274}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Regal, Brian|title=Human Evolution: A Guide to the Debates|publisher=ABC-CLIO|location=Santa Barbara, CA|year=2004|pages=73–75|isbn=978-1851094189}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Haeckel also wrote that Negroes have stronger and more freely movable toes than any other race which is evidence that Negroes are related to apes because when apes stop climbing in trees they hold on to the trees with their toes. Haeckel compared Negroes to "four-handed" apes. Haeckel also believed Negroes were savages and that whites were the most civilised.&lt;ref name="GustavJahoda"&gt;[[Gustav Jahoda]], ''Images of Savages: Ancients [sic] Roots of Modern Prejudice in Western Culture'', 1999, p. 83&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nationalism of Lapouge and Herder===
At the 19th century's end, scientific racism conflated [[Greco-Roman]] eugenicism with [[Francis Galton]]'s concept of voluntary [[eugenics]] to produce a form of coercive, anti-immigrant government programs influenced by other socio-political [[discourse]]s and events. Such institutional racism was effected via [[phrenology]], telling character from physiognomy; [[craniometry|craniometric]] skull and skeleton studies; thus skulls and skeletons of black people and other colored ''volk'', were displayed between apes and white men.

In 1906, [[Ota Benga]], a [[Pygmies|Pygmy]], was displayed as the "Missing Link", in the [[Bronx Zoo]], New York City, alongside apes and animals. The most influential theorists included the anthropologist [[Georges Vacher de Lapouge]] (1854–1936) who proposed "anthroposociology"; and [[Johann Gottfried Herder]] (1744–1803), who applied "race" to [[nationalist]] theory, thereby developing the first conception of [[ethnic nationalism]]. In 1882, [[Ernest Renan]] contradicted Herder with a nationalism based upon the "will to live together", not founded upon ethnic or racial prerequisites (see [[Civic nationalism]]). Scientific racist discourse posited the historical existence of "national races" such as the ''[[German people|Deutsche Volk]]'' in Germany, and the "French race" being a branch of the basal "[[Aryan race]]" extant for millennia, to advocate for [[Geopolitics|geopolitical]] borders parallel to the racial ones.

===Craniometry and physical anthropology===
{{Further|Craniometry |physical anthropology}}
[[File:Petrus-Camper-(professor).jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.6|Pieter Camper]]

The Dutch scholar [[Pieter Camper]] (1722–89), an early craniometric theoretician, used "craniometry" (interior skull-volume measurement) to scientifically justify racial differences. In 1770, he conceived of the [[facial angle]] to measure intelligence among species of men. The facial angle was formed by drawing two lines: a horizontal line from nostril to ear; and a vertical line from the upper-jawbone prominence to the forehead prominence. Camper's craniometry reported that antique statues (the Greco-Roman ideal) had a 90-degree facial angle, whites an 80-degree angle, blacks a 70-degree angle, and the [[orangutan]] a 58-degree facial angle—thus he established a racist biological hierarchy for mankind, per the [[decadence|Decadent]] conception of history. Such scientific racist researches were continued by the naturalist [[Étienne Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire]] (1772–1844) and the anthropologist [[Paul Broca]] (1824–1880).

====Samuel George Morton====
[[File:Morton drawing.png|right|thumb|Racialist differences: "a Negro head ... a Caucasian skull ... a Mongol head", [[Samuel George Morton]], 1839]]

In the 19th century, an early American [[Physical anthropology|physical anthropologist]], physician and polygenist [[Samuel George Morton]] (1799–1851), collected human skulls from worldwide, and attempted a logical classification scheme. Influenced by contemporary racialist theory, Dr Morton said he could judge racial intellectual capacity by measuring the interior [[cranial capacity]], hence a large skull denoted a large brain, thus high [[Intellectualism|intellectual]] capacity. Conversely, a small skull denoted a small brain, thus low intellectual capacity; superior and inferior established. After inspecting three mummies from ancient Egyptian catacombs, Morton concluded that Caucasians and Negroes were already distinct three thousand years ago. Since interpretations of the bible indicated that [[Noah's Ark]] had washed up on [[Mount Ararat]] only a thousand years earlier, Morton claimed that Noah's sons could not possibly account for every race on earth. According to Morton's theory of polygenesis, races have been separate since the start.&lt;ref name="DavidHurst"&gt;David Hurst Thomas, ''Skull Wars: Kennewick Man, Archaeology, And The Battle For Native American Identity'', 2001, pp. 38–41&lt;/ref&gt;

In Morton's ''Crania Americana'', his claims were based on [[craniometry]] data, that the Caucasians had the biggest brains, averaging 87 cubic inches, Native Americans were in the middle with an average of 82 cubic inches and Negroes had the smallest brains with an average of 78 cubic inches.&lt;ref name="DavidHurst" /&gt; [[File:Races and skulls.png|295x295px|thumb|Illustration from ''Types of Mankind'' (1854), whose authors [[Josiah Clark Nott]] and [[George Robins Gliddon]] implied that "[[Negroes]]" were a [[Creationism|creational]] rank between "[[Greeks]]" and [[Common chimpanzee|chimpanzee]]s.|alt=|left]]In ''[[The Mismeasure of Man]]'' (1981), the [[evolutionary biology|evolutionary biologist]] and [[History of science|historian of science]] [[Stephen Jay Gould]] argued that Samuel Morton had falsified the craniometric data, perhaps inadvertently over-packing some skulls, to so produce results that would legitimize the racist presumptions he was attempting to prove. A subsequent study by the [[anthropologist]] John Michael found Morton's original data to be more accurate than Gould describes, concluding that "[c]ontrary to Gould's interpretation... Morton's research was conducted with integrity".&lt;ref name="jsmichael"&gt;{{cite journal|author=Michael, J.S.|title=A New Look at Morton's Craniological Research|journal=Current Anthropology|volume=29|issue=2|pages=349–54|year=1988|doi=10.1086/203646|s2cid=144528631}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jason Lewis and colleagues reached similar conclusions as Michael in their reanalysis of Morton's skull collection; however, they depart from Morton's racist conclusions by adding that "studies have demonstrated that modern human variation is generally continuous, rather than discrete or "racial", and that most variation in modern humans is within, rather than between, populations".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=The Mismeasure of Science: Stephen Jay Gould versus Samuel George Morton on Skulls and Bias|year=2011|journal=PLOS Biology |volume=9|issue=6|pages=e1001071+|doi=10.1371/journal.pbio.1001071|last1=Lewis|first1=Jason E.|last2=Degusta|first2=David|last3=Meyer|first3=Marc R.|last4=Monge|first4=Janet M.|last5=Mann|first5=Alan E.|last6=Holloway|first6=Ralph L.|pmid=21666803|pmc=3110184 |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1873, Paul Broca, founder of the Anthropological Society of Paris (1859), found the same pattern of measures—that ''Crania Americana'' reported—by weighing specimen brains at [[autopsy]]. Other historical studies, proposing a black race–white race, intelligence–brain size difference, include those by Bean (1906), Mall (1909), Pearl (1934), and Vint (1934).

===Nicolás Palacios===
After the [[War of the Pacific]] (1879–83) there was a rise of racial and national superiority ideas among the Chilean ruling class.&lt;ref&gt;Ericka Beckman ''Imperial Impersonations: Chilean Racism and the War of the Pacific'', University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign&lt;/ref&gt; In his 1918 book physician [[Nicolás Palacios]] argued for the existence of [[Chilean people|Chilean]] race and its superiority when compared to neighboring peoples. He thought Chileans were a mix of two [[martial race]]s: the indigenous [[Mapuche]]s and the [[Visigoth]]s of Spain, who descended ultimately from [[Götaland]] in Sweden. Palacios argued on medical grounds against immigration to Chile from southern Europe claiming that [[Mestizo]]s who are of south European stock lack "cerebral control" and are a social burden.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Palacios|first=Nicolás|author-link=Nicolás Palacios|title=Raza Chilena|publisher=Editorial Chilena|year=1918|language=es}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Monogenism and polygenism===
{{Further|Monogenism|Polygenism}}

Samuel Morton's followers, especially Dr [[Josiah C. Nott]] (1804–1873) and [[George Gliddon]] (1809–1857), extended Dr Morton's ideas in ''Types of Mankind'' (1854), claiming that Morton's findings supported the notion of [[polygenism]] (mankind has discrete genetic ancestries; the races are evolutionarily unrelated), which is a predecessor of the [[Multiregional origin of modern humans|modern human multiregional origin hypothesis]]. Moreover, Morton himself had been reluctant to espouse polygenism, because it [[Theology|theologically]] challenged the Christian [[creation myth]] espoused in the Bible.

Later, in ''[[The Descent of Man]]'' (1871), Charles Darwin proposed the [[single-origin hypothesis]], i.e., [[monogenism]]—mankind has a common genetic ancestry, the races are related, opposing everything that the polygenism of Nott and Gliddon proposed.

===Typologies===
[[File:Ripley map of cephalic index in Europe.png|right|thumb|upright=1.5|Cephalic Index. [[William Z. Ripley]]'s European cephalic index map, ''[[The Races of Europe (1899 book)|The Races of Europe]]'' (1899).]]

One of the first [[typology (anthropology)|typologies]] used to classify various human races was invented by [[Georges Vacher de Lapouge]] (1854–1936), a theoretician of [[eugenics]], who published in 1899 ''L'Aryen et son rôle social'' (1899 – "The [[Aryan]] and his social role"). In this book, he classified humanity into various, hierarchized races, spanning from the "Aryan white race, dolichocephalic", to the "brachycephalic", "mediocre and inert" race, best represented by Southern European, Catholic peasants".&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hecht|2003|p=171}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between these, Vacher de Lapouge identified the "''[[Nordic theory|Homo europaeus]]''" (Teutonic, Protestant, etc.), the "''[[Homo alpinus]]''" ([[Auvergne (province)|Auvergnat]], [[Turkish people|Turkish]], etc.), and finally the "''[[Homo mediterraneus]]''" ([[Naples|Neapolitan]], [[Andalusia|Andalus]], etc.) Jews were dolichocephalic like the Aryans, according to Lapouge, but exactly for this reason he considered them to be dangerous; they were the only group, he thought, threatening to displace the Aryan aristocracy.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hecht|2003|pp=171–72}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vacher de Lapouge became one of the leading inspirators of [[Nazi]] [[antisemitism]] and [[Nazi racial policies|Nazi racist ideology]].&lt;ref&gt;See [[Pierre-André Taguieff]], ''La couleur et le sang&amp;nbsp;– Doctrines racistes à la française'' ("Colour and Blood&amp;nbsp;– Racist doctrines ''à la française''"), Paris, [[Mille et une nuits]], 2002, 203 pages, and ''La Force du préjugé&amp;nbsp;– Essai sur le racisme et ses doubles'', Tel [[Gallimard]], La Découverte, 1987, 644 pages&lt;/ref&gt;

Vacher de Lapouge's classification was mirrored in [[William Z. Ripley]] in ''The Races of Europe'' (1899), a book which had a large influence on American [[white supremacism]]. Ripley even made a map of Europe according to the alleged [[cephalic index]] of its inhabitants. He was an important influence of the American eugenist [[Madison Grant]].

[[File:Joseph Deniker.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.6|Joseph Deniker]]

Furthermore, according to John Efron of [[Indiana University]], the late 19th century also witnessed "the scientizing of anti-Jewish prejudice", stigmatizing Jews with [[male menstruation]], [[Histrionic personality disorder|pathological hysteria]], and [[nymphomania]].&lt;ref name="Efron"&gt;{{harvnb|Efron|1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bodek"&gt;Richard Bodek. "[http://www.h-net.msu.edu/reviews/showrev.cgi?path=1716846635467 Review of John M. Efron, ''Defenders of the Race: Jewish Doctors &amp; Race Science in Fin-de-Siècle Europe''"], H-SAE, [[H-Net]] Reviews, May 1996 {{in lang|en}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, several Jews, such as [[Joseph Jacobs]] or Samuel Weissenberg, also endorsed the same pseudoscientific theories, convinced that the Jews formed a distinct race.&lt;ref name=Efron/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bodek/&gt; [[Chaim Zhitlovsky]] also attempted to define ''[[Yiddishkayt]]'' (Ashkenazi Jewishness) by turning to contemporary racial theory.&lt;ref name="Chaim"&gt;{{cite journal|author=Hoffman, Matthew|title=From Pintele Yid to Racenjude: Chaim Zhitlovsky and Racial Conceptions of Jewishness|journal=[[Jewish History]]|volume=19|issue=1|date=January 2005|doi=10.1007/s10835-005-4358-7|pages=65–78|s2cid=143976833}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Joseph Deniker]] (1852–1918) was one of [[William Z. Ripley]]'s principal opponents; whereas Ripley maintained, as did Vacher de Lapouge, that the European populace comprised three races, Joseph Deniker proposed that the European populace comprised ten races (six primary and four sub-races). Furthermore, he proposed that the concept of "race" was ambiguous, and in its stead proposed the compound word "[[ethnic group]]", which later prominently featured in the works of [[Julian Huxley]] and [[Alfred C. Haddon]]. Moreover, Ripley argued that Deniker's "race" idea should be denoted a "type", because it was less biologically rigid than most racial classifications.

==Ideological applications==
[[File:Madison Grant.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.6|Madison Grant, creator of the "Nordic race" term]]

===Nordicism===
Joseph Deniker's contribution to racist theory was ''La Race nordique'' (the [[Nordic race]]), a generic, racial-stock descriptor, which the American [[eugenics|eugenicist]] [[Madison Grant]] (1865–1937) presented as the white racial engine of world civilization. Having adopted Ripley's three-race European populace model, but disliking the "Teuton" race name, he transliterated ''la race nordique'' into "The Nordic race", the acme of the concocted racial hierarchy, based upon his racial classification theory, popular in the 1910s and 1920s.

The [[State Institute for Racial Biology]] (Swedish: ''Statens Institut för Rasbiologi'') and its director [[Herman Lundborg]] in Sweden were active in racist research. Furthermore, much of early research on [[Ural-Altaic languages]] was coloured by attempts at justifying the view that European peoples east of Sweden were Asian and thus of an inferior race, justifying colonialism, eugenics and racial hygiene.{{citation needed|date=February 2016}} The book ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'' (Or, The Racial Basis of European History) by American eugenicist, lawyer, and amateur anthropologist Madison Grant was published in 1916. Though influential, the book was largely ignored when it first appeared, and it went through several revisions and editions. Nevertheless, the book was used by people who advocated restricted immigration as justification for what became known as scientific racism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmc=2942213 | year=1917 | last1=Lindsay | first1=J. A. | title=The passing of the great race, or the racial basis of european history | journal=The Eugenics Review | volume=9 | issue=2 | pages=139–141 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Justification of slavery in the United States===
[[File:Samuelcartwright.jpg|thumb|left|Samuel Cartwright, M.D.]]

In the United States, scientific racism justified Black African slavery to assuage moral opposition to the [[Atlantic slave trade]]. Alexander Thomas and Samuell Sillen described black men as uniquely fitted for bondage, because of their "primitive psychological organization."&lt;ref&gt;Alexander Thomas and Samuell Sillen (1972). ''[https://www.jaacap.com/article/S0002-7138(09)61177-8/pdf Racism and Psychiatry]''. New York: Carol Publishing Group.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1851, in antebellum Louisiana, the physician [[Samuel A. Cartwright]] (1793–1863) wrote of slave escape attempts as "[[drapetomania]]," a treatable [[mental illness]], that "with proper medical advice, strictly followed, this troublesome practice that many Negroes have of running away can be almost entirely prevented." The term ''drapetomania'' (mania of the runaway slave) derives from the Greek δραπέτης (''drapetes'', "a runaway [slave]") and μανία (''mania'', "madness, frenzy").&lt;ref&gt;Samual A. Cartwright, [https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/aia/part4/4h3106t.html "Diseases and Peculiarities of the Negro Race"], ''[[DeBow's Review]] – Southern and Western States'', Volume XI, New Orleans, 1851&lt;/ref&gt; Cartwright also described ''[[dysaesthesia aethiopica]]'', called "rascality" by overseers. The [[1840 United States Census]] claimed that Northern, free blacks suffered mental illness at higher rates than did their Southern, enslaved counterparts. Though the census was later found to have been severely flawed by the [[American Statistical Association]], it became a political weapon against [[Abolitionism in the United States|abolitionists]]. Southern slavers concluded that escaping Negroes were suffering from "mental disorders."&lt;ref name="Higgins, 1994"&gt;Higgins, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;

At the time of the [[American Civil War]] (1861–65), the matter of [[miscegenation]] prompted studies of ostensible physiological differences between [[Caucasian race|Caucasians]] and [[Negro]]es. Early [[anthropology|anthropologists]], such as [[Josiah Clark Nott]], [[George Robins Gliddon]], [[Robert Knox]], and [[Samuel George Morton]], aimed to scientifically prove that Negroes were a human species different from the white people; that the rulers of [[Ancient Egypt]] were not African; and that mixed-race offspring (the product of miscegenation) tended to physical weakness and infertility. After the Civil War, Southern (Confederacy) physicians wrote textbooks of scientific racism based upon studies claiming that black freemen (ex-slaves) were becoming extinct, because they were inadequate to the demands of being a free man—implying that black people benefited from enslavement.

In ''Medical Apartheid'', Harriet A. Washington noted the prevalence of two different views on blacks in the 19th century: the belief that they were inferior and "riddled with imperfections from head to toe", and the idea that they did not know true pain and suffering because of their primitive nervous systems (and that slavery was therefore justifiable). Washington noted the failure of scientists to accept the inconsistency between these two viewpoints, writing that:
{{blockquote|in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, scientific racism was simply science, and it was promulgated by the very best minds at the most prestigious institutions of the nation. Other, more logical medical theories stressed the equality of Africans and laid poor black health at the feet of their abusers, but these never enjoyed the appeal of the medical philosophy that justified slavery and, along with it, our nation's profitable way of life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=apGhwRt6A7QC&amp;pg=PA42|title=Medical Apartheid: The Dark History of Medical Experimentation on Black Americans from Colonial Times to the Present|page=42|last=Washington|first=Harriet A.|publisher=Knopf Doubleday Publishing Group|date=2008|isbn=978-0767929394}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Even after the end of the Civil War, some scientists continued to justify the institution of slavery by citing the effect of topography and climate on racial development. [[Nathaniel Shaler]], a prominent geologist at [[Harvard University]] from 1869 to 1906, published the book ''Man and the Earth'' in 1905 describing the physical geography of different continents and linking these geologic settings to the intelligence and strength of human races that inhabited these spaces. Shaler argued that North American climate and geology was ideally suited for the institution of slavery.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Man and the Earth|last=Shaler|first=Nathaniel Southgate|publisher=Duffield &amp; Company|year=1905|location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===South African apartheid===
{{See also|Carnegie Commission on the Poor White Problem in South Africa}}
Scientific racism played a role in establishing [[apartheid]] in South Africa. In South Africa, white scientists, like Dudly Kidd, who published ''The essential Kafir'' in 1904, sought to "understand the African mind". They believed that the cultural differences between whites and blacks in South Africa might be caused by physiological differences in the brain. Rather than suggesting that Africans were "overgrown children", as early white explorers had, Kidd believed that Africans were "misgrown with a vengeance". He described Africans as at once "hopelessly deficient", yet "very shrewd".&lt;ref name="Dubow"&gt;{{cite book|author=Dubow, Saul|title=Scientific Racism in Modern South Africa|url=https://archive.org/details/scientificracism0000dubo|url-access=registration|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge|year=1995|isbn=978-0521479073|author-link=Saul Dubow}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Carnegie Commission on the Poor White Problem in South Africa]] played a key role in establishing apartheid in South Africa. According to one memorandum sent to Frederick Keppel, then president of the [[Carnegie Corporation]], there was "little doubt that if the natives were given full economic opportunity, the more competent among them would soon outstrip the less competent whites".&lt;ref name="swar"&gt;{{cite book|author=Füredi, Frank|title=The Silent War: Imperialism and the Changing Perception of Race|publisher=Rutgers University Press|location=New Brunswick, NJ|year=1998|pages=66–67|isbn=978-0813526126}}&lt;/ref&gt; Keppel's support for the project of creating the report was motivated by his concern with the maintenance of existing racial boundaries.&lt;ref name="swar"/&gt; The preoccupation of the Carnegie Corporation with the so-called poor white problem in South Africa was at least in part the outcome of similar misgivings about the state of poor whites in the southern United States.&lt;ref name="swar"/&gt;

The report was five volumes in length.&lt;ref name="amcentry"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Slater, David|author2=Taylor, Peter J.|title=The American Century: Consensus and Coercion in the Projection of American Power|publisher=Blackwell|location=Oxford|year=1999|page=[https://archive.org/details/americancenturyc0000unse/page/290 290]|isbn=978-0631212225|url=https://archive.org/details/americancenturyc0000unse/page/290}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around the start of the 20th century, white Americans, and whites elsewhere in the world, felt uneasy because poverty and economic depression seemed to strike people regardless of race.&lt;ref name="amcentry"/&gt;

Though the ground work for apartheid began earlier, the report provided support for this central idea of black inferiority. This was used to justify [[racial segregation]] and discrimination&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Verbeek, Jennifer|title=Racially Segregated School Libraries in KwaZulu/Natal, South Africa|journal=Journal of Librarianship and Information Science|volume=18|issue=1|pages=23–46|year=1986|doi=10.1177/096100068601800102|s2cid=62204622}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the following decades.&lt;ref name="haunted"&gt;{{cite book|author=Stoler, Ann Laura|title=Haunted by Empire: Geographies of Intimacy in North American History|publisher=Duke University Press|location=Durham, NC|year=2006|page=66|isbn=978-0822337249}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report expressed fear about the loss of white racial pride, and in particular pointed to the danger that the poor white would not be able to resist the process of "Africanisation".&lt;ref name="swar"/&gt;

Although scientific racism played a role in justifying and supporting [[institutional racism]] in South Africa, it was not as important in South Africa as it has been in Europe and the United States. This was due in part to the "poor white problem", which raised serious questions for supremacists about white racial superiority.&lt;ref name="Dubow"/&gt; Since poor whites were found to be in the same situation as natives in the African environment, the idea that intrinsic white superiority could overcome any environment did not seem to hold. As such, scientific justifications for racism were not as useful in South Africa.&lt;ref name="Dubow"/&gt;

===Eugenics===
{{Further|Eugenics}}
[[File:Francis Galton2.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Francis Galton]] in his later years]]
[[Stephen Jay Gould]] described [[Madison Grant]]'s ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'' (1916) as "the most influential tract of American scientific racism." In the 1920s–30s, the German [[racial hygiene]] movement embraced Grant's [[Nordic theory]]. [[Alfred Ploetz]] (1860–1940) coined the term ''Rassenhygiene'' in ''Racial Hygiene Basics'' (1895), and founded the [[German Society for Racial Hygiene]] in 1905. The movement advocated [[selective breeding]], [[compulsory sterilization]], and a close alignment of [[public health]] with [[eugenics]].

Racial hygiene was historically tied to traditional notions of public health, but with emphasis on [[heredity]]—what philosopher and historian [[Michel Foucault]] has called [[state racism]]. In 1869, [[Francis Galton]] (1822–1911) proposed the first social measures meant to preserve or enhance biological characteristics, and later coined the term "eugenics". Galton, a statistician, introduced [[correlation]] and [[regression analysis]] and discovered [[regression toward the mean]]. He was also the first to study human differences and [[inheritance of intelligence]] with statistical methods. He introduced the use of [[questionnaires]] and [[Statistical survey|surveys]] to collect data on population sets, which he needed for genealogical and biographical works and for [[anthropometrics|anthropometric]] studies. Galton also founded [[psychometrics]], the science of measuring mental faculties, and [[differential psychology]], a branch of psychology concerned with psychological differences between people rather than common traits.

Like scientific racism, eugenics grew popular in the early 20th century, and both ideas influenced [[Nazi racial policies]] and [[Nazi eugenics]]. In 1901, Galton, [[Karl Pearson]] (1857–1936) and [[Walter Frank Raphael Weldon|Walter F.R. Weldon]] (1860–1906) founded the ''[[Biometrika]]'' scientific journal, which promoted [[biometrics]] and statistical analysis of heredity. [[Charles Davenport]] (1866–1944) was briefly involved in the review. In ''Race Crossing in Jamaica'' (1929), he made statistical arguments that biological and cultural degradation followed white and black [[miscegenation|interbreeding]]. Davenport was connected to [[Nazi Germany]] before and during [[World War II]]. In 1939 he wrote a contribution to the ''festschrift'' for [[Otto Reche]] (1879–1966), who became an important figure within the plan to remove populations considered "inferior" from eastern Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kühl|1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Interbellum to World War II==
Scientific racism continued through the early 20th century, and soon [[intelligence testing]] became a new source for racial comparisons. Before [[World War II]] (1939–45), scientific racism remained common to [[anthropology]], and was used as justification for [[eugenics]] programs, [[compulsory sterilization]], [[anti-miscegenation laws]], and [[immigration law|immigration restrictions]] in Europe and the United States. The [[war crimes]] and [[crimes against humanity]] of [[Nazi Germany]] (1933–45) discredited scientific racism in academia,{{citation needed| date=July 2016}} but racist legislation based upon it remained in some countries until the late 1960s.

===Early intelligence testing and the Immigration Act of 1924===

Before the 1920s, social scientists agreed that whites were superior to blacks, but they needed a way to prove this to back social policy in favor of whites. They felt the best way to gauge this was through testing intelligence. By interpreting the tests to show favor to whites these test makers' research results portrayed all minority groups very negatively.&lt;ref name=Tucker07/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Richards|1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1908, [[Henry H. Goddard|Henry Goddard]] translated the Binet intelligence test from French and in 1912 began to apply the test to incoming immigrants on Ellis Island.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Shultz|Shultz|2008|pp=233,236}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some claim that in a study of immigrants Goddard reached the conclusion that 87% of Russians, 83% of Jews, 80% of Hungarians, and 79% of Italians were feeble-minded and had a mental age less than 12.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gould|1981}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some have also claimed that this information was taken as "evidence" by lawmakers and thus it affected social policy for years.&lt;ref name="Shultz08_237"&gt;{{harvnb|Shultz|Shultz|2008|p=237}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bernard Davis has pointed out that, in the first sentence of his paper, Goddard wrote that the subjects of the study were not typical members of their groups but were selected because of their suspected sub-normal intelligence. Davis has further noted that Goddard argued that the low IQs of the test subjects were more likely due to environmental rather than genetic factors, and that Goddard concluded that "we may be confident that their children will be of average intelligence and if rightly brought up will be good citizens".&lt;ref name="davis"&gt;{{cite journal|author=Davis, Bernard|title=Neo-Lysenkoism, IQ and the Press|journal=The Public Interest|volume=74|issue=2|page=45|year=1983 |pmid=11632811}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1996 the American Psychological Association's Board of Scientific Affairs stated that IQ tests were not discriminatory towards any ethnic/racial groups.&lt;ref name="APA"&gt;{{harvnb|American Psychologist|1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his book ''[[The Mismeasure of Man]]'', Stephen Jay Gould argued that intelligence testing results played a major role in the passage of the [[Immigration Act of 1924]] that restricted immigration to the United States.&lt;ref name="Gould"&gt;{{cite book|author=Gould, S.J.|title=The Mismeasure of Man|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|isbn=978-0393314250|year=1996|url=https://archive.org/details/mismeasureofman00goul_1}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Mark Snyderman and [[Richard J. Herrnstein]], after studying the [[Congressional Record]] and committee hearings related to the Immigration Act, concluded "the [intelligence] testing community did not generally view its findings as favoring restrictive immigration policies like those in the 1924 Act, and Congress took virtually no notice of intelligence testing".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Snyderman, M. |author2=Herrnstein, R.J. |title=Intelligence Tests and the Immigration Act of 1924|journal=[[American Psychologist]]|volume=38 |issue=9 |pages=986–95|year=1983|doi=10.1037/0003-066x.38.9.986 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Juan N. Franco contested the findings of Snyderman and Herrnstein. Franco stated that even though Snyderman and Herrnstein reported that the data collected from the results of the intelligence tests were in no way used to pass The Immigration Act of 1924, the IQ test results were still taken into consideration by legislators. As suggestive evidence, Franco pointed to the following fact: Following the passage of the immigration act, information from the 1890 census was used to set quotas based on percentages of immigrants coming from different countries. Based on these data, the legislature restricted the entrance of immigrants from southern and eastern Europe into the United States and allowed more immigrants from northern and Western Europe into the country. The use of the 1900, 1910 or 1920 census data sets would have resulted in larger numbers of immigrants from southern and eastern Europe being allowed into the U.S. However, Franco pointed out that using the 1890 census data allowed congress to exclude southern and eastern Europeans (who performed worse on IQ tests of the time than did western and northern Europeans) from the U.S. Franco argued that the work Snyderman and Herrnstein conducted on this matter neither proved or disproved that intelligence testing influenced immigration laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Franco, J.N.|title=Intelligence tests and social policy|journal=Journal of Counseling and Development|volume=64|issue=4|pages=278–9|year=1985|doi=10.1002/j.1556-6676.1985.tb01101.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sweden&lt;!--'Racial science' redirects here--&gt; ===
[[File:Dean's house Uppsala Sweden 001.JPG|thumb|The Swedish [[State Institute for Racial Biology]], founded in 1922, was the world's first government-funded institute performing research into racial biology. It was housed in what is now the Dean's house at [[Uppsala University|Uppsala]] and was closed down in 1958.]]

Following the creation of the first society for the promotion of racial hygiene, the [[German Society for Racial Hygiene]] in 1905—a Swedish society was founded in 1909 as "''Svenska sällskapet för rashygien''" as third in the world.&lt;ref name="FoF"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://fof.se/tidning/2012/8/en-meningslos-sortering-av-manniskor|title=En meningslös sortering av människor|newspaper=Forskning &amp; Framsteg|access-date=November 7, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Björkman|first1=Maria|last2=Widmalm|first2=Sven|date=December 20, 2010|title=Selling eugenics: the case of Sweden|journal=Notes and Records of the Royal Society|language=en|volume=64|issue=4|pages=379–400|doi=10.1098/rsnr.2010.0009|issn=0035-9149|pmid=21553636|s2cid=16786101 |doi-access=}}&lt;/ref&gt; By lobbying Swedish parliamentarians and medical institutes the society managed to pass a decree creating a government run institute in the form of the Swedish [[State Institute for Racial Biology]] in 1921.&lt;ref name="FoF" /&gt; By 1922 the institute was built and opened in [[Uppsala]].&lt;ref name="FoF" /&gt; It was the first such government-funded institute in the world performing research into "''racial biology''" and remains highly controversial to this day.&lt;ref name="FoF" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.nobelmuseum.se/sites/www.nobelmuseum.se/files/page_file/NMOP7.pdf|title=Rektor Lennmalms förslag – Om 1918–1921 års diskussioner kring ett Nobelinstitut i rasbiologi vid Karolinska institutet.|last=Ambrosiani|first=Aron|publisher=Nobel Museum Occasional Papers|year=2009|page=4|access-date=January 24, 2017|archive-date=January 16, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170116170857/http://www.nobelmuseum.se/sites/www.nobelmuseum.se/files/page_file/NMOP7.pdf|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the most prominent institution for the study of "racial science" in Sweden.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ericsson|first=Martin|date=June 30, 2020|title=What happened to 'race' in race biology? The Swedish State Institute for Race Biology, 1936–1960|journal=Scandinavian Journal of History|pages=1–24|doi=10.1080/03468755.2020.1778520|issn=0346-8755|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; The goal was to cure criminality, alcoholism and psychiatric problems through research in [[eugenics]] and racial hygiene.&lt;ref name="FoF" /&gt; As a result of the institutes work a law permitting [[compulsory sterilization]] of certain groups was enacted in Sweden in 1934.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.levandehistoria.se/fordjupning-rasbiologi/kapitel-3-rasbiologin-i-sverige|title=Kapitel 3: Rasbiologin i Sverige|newspaper=Forum för levande historia|access-date=November 7, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The second president of the institute [[Gunnar Dahlberg]] was highly critical of the validity of the science performed at the institute and reshaped the institute toward a focus on [[genetics]].&lt;ref name="Uppsala"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ub.uu.se/hitta-i-vara-samlingar/verk-och-samlingar-i-urval/rasbiologiska-institutet/|title=Rasbiologiska institutet – Uppsala universitetsbibliotek – Uppsala universitet|website=ub.uu.se|access-date=November 7, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1958 it closed down and all remaining research was moved to the Department of medical genetics at Uppsala University.&lt;ref name="Uppsala" /&gt;

===Nazi Germany===
{{Main|Racial policy of Nazi Germany}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-16748, Ausstellung "Wunder des Lebens".jpg|thumb|left|Nazi poster promoting eugenics]]

The [[Nazi Party]] and its sympathizers published many books on scientific racism, seizing on the [[eugenics|eugenicist]] and [[antisemitism|antisemitic]] ideas with which they were widely associated, although these ideas had been in circulation since the 19th century. Books such as ''[[Rassenkunde des deutschen Volkes]]'' ("Racial Science of the German People") by [[Hans F. K. Günther|Hans Günther]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title = Rassenkunde des deutschen Volkes|trans-title = Racial Science of the German People|first = Hans F. K.|last = Günther|author-link = Hans F. K. Günther|year = 1930|location = [[Munich|München]]|publisher = [[J. F. Lehmann]]|url = https://archive.org/details/rassenkundedesd00gngoog/|language = de}}&lt;/ref&gt; (first published in 1922)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first = Anne|last = Maxwell|title = Picture Imperfect: Photography and Eugenics, 1870–1940|publisher = Sussex Academic Press|year = 2010|page = 150|isbn = 9781845194154}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Rasse und Seele'' ("Race and Soul") by {{ill|Ludwig Ferdinand Clauß|de}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title = Rasse und Seele: Eine Einführung in die Gegenwart|trans-title = Race and Soul: An Introduction to the Contemporary World|publisher = [[J. F. Lehmann]]|location = [[Munich|München]]|year = 1926|first = Ludwig Ferdinand|last = Clauß}}&lt;/ref&gt; (published under different titles between 1926 and 1934)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=NWaxXRILGjYC&amp;pg=PA394|title = About Face: German Physiognomic Thought from Lavater to Auschwitz|first = Richard T.|last = Gray|publisher = [[Wayne State University Press]]|year = 2004|isbn = 9780814331798|chapter = Learning to See (Race): Ludwig Ferdinand Clauss's Racial Psychology as Applied Phenomenology|pages=273–332, 393–396|quote = ''Rasse und Seele'' has a curious publication history. The first edition appeared under this title in 1926 with the subtitle "Eine Einführung in die Gegenwart" (An Introduction to the contemporary world). A second, heavily revised edition appeared in 1929 under an entirely different title, ''Von Seele und Antlitz der Rassen und Völker'' (On the soul and face of races and nations). A third revised edition, which returned to the original title ''Rasse und Seele'', was published in 1934, this time with the subtitle of "Eine Einführung in den Sinn der leiblichen Gestalt" (An introduction to the meaning of somatic form), and this latter edition remained the basis for all subsequent printings ... [t]he content of the three books is similar, though the various editions tend to organize this material in very different ways.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|394}} attempted to scientifically identify differences between the German, [[Nordic theory|Nordic]], or [[Aryan]] people and other, supposedly inferior, groups.{{Citation needed|reason=Dubious sentence given Günther's views|date=April 2017}} German schools used these books as texts during the Nazi era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Nature, Human Nature, and Human Difference | chapter=The Nature of Science and the Nature of Philosophy | chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DtmqBwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA10 | publisher=[[Princeton University Press]] | last=Smith | first=Justin E. H.| author-link=Justin E. H. Smith | year=2015 | pages=10–15| isbn=978-1400866311}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 1930s, the Nazis used [[racialized]] scientific rhetoric based on [[social Darwinism]]{{citation needed|date=February 2011}} to push its restrictive and discriminatory social policies.

During [[World War II]], Nazi racialist beliefs became anathema in the United States, and [[Franz Boas|Boasians]] such as [[Ruth Benedict]] consolidated their institutional power. After the war, discovery of [[the Holocaust]] and Nazi abuses of scientific research (such as [[Josef Mengele]]'s ethical violations and other [[war crime]]s revealed at the [[Nuremberg Trials]]) led most of the scientific community to repudiate scientific support for racism.

Propaganda for the Nazi eugenics program began with propaganda for eugenic sterilization. Articles in ''[[Neues Volk]]'' described the appearance of the mentally ill and the importance of preventing such births.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|first = H.|last = Rodenfels|title = Frauen, die nicht Mutter werden dürfen|magazine = [[Neues Volk]]|volume = 7|year = 2007|orig-date = Published in German in May 1939|pages = 16–21|trans-title = Women Who May Not Be Allowed to become Mothers|url = https://research.calvin.edu/german-propaganda-archive/nv39-05a.htm|via = German Propaganda Archive|translator-first = Randall|translator-last = Bytwerk}}&lt;/ref&gt; Photographs of mentally incapacitated children were juxtaposed with those of healthy children.&lt;ref name="Claudia Koonz p 119"&gt;{{cite book| last = Koonz| first = Claudia| author-link = Claudia Koonz| title = The Nazi Conscience| chapter = Ethnic Revival and Racist Anxiety| year = 2003| pages = [https://archive.org/details/naziconscience00koon/page/103 103–130]| publisher = [[Harvard University Press]]| isbn = 9780674011724| chapter-url = https://archive.org/details/naziconscience00koon/page/119| url = https://archive.org/details/naziconscience00koon/page/103}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|119}} The film ''[[Das Erbe]]'' showed conflict in nature to legitimate the [[Law for the Prevention of Hereditarily Diseased Offspring]] by sterilization.

Although the child was "the most important treasure of the people", this did not apply to all children, even German ones, only to those with no hereditary weaknesses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Lynn H.|last=Nicholas|author-link=Lynn H. Nicholas|title=Cruel World: The Children of Europe in the Nazi Web|year=2006|publisher=[[Vintage Books]]|isbn=9780679776635|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nazi Germany]]'s [[Nazism and race|racially based]] social policies placed the improvement of the [[Aryan race]] through eugenics at the center of Nazis ideology. Those humans were targeted who were identified as "[[life unworthy of life]]" ({{lang-de|link=no|Lebensunwertes Leben}}), including but not limited to Jewish people, criminals, [[Social degeneration|degenerate]], [[Gleichschaltung|dissident]], feeble-minded, [[History of homosexual people in Nazi Germany and the Holocaust|homosexual]], idle, insane, and the weak, for elimination from the chain of [[heredity]].{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} Although they were still regarded as "Aryan", Nazi ideology deemed [[Slavs]] (i.e., [[Generalplan Ost|Poles, Russians, Ukrainians]], etc.) to be racially inferior to the Germanic [[master race]], suitable for expulsion, enslavement, or even extermination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ZLcDEUZfW4EC&amp;pg=PA181|title = Operation Barbarossa: Ideology and Ethics against Human Dignity|chapter = Conclusion: Anthropology and the Peculiarities of the East|first = André|last = Mineau|publisher = [[Rodopi (publisher)|Rodopi]]|year = 2004|pages = 180–182|isbn = 9789042016330}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|180}}

[[Adolf Hitler]] banned [[intelligence quotient]] (IQ) testing for being "Jewish".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title = The Structure &amp; Measurement of Intelligence|first1 = Hans Jürgen|last1 = Eysenck|author-link1 = Hans Eysenck|author-link2 = David Fulker|first2 = David W.|last2 = Fulker|publisher = [[Transaction Publishers]]|year = 1979|pages = 8–31|chapter = Intelligence: The Development of a Concept|journal = Die Naturwissenschaften|volume = 68|issue = 10|chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ka_gAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA16|location = New Brunswick|isbn = 9781412839235|pmid = 7300910|doi = 10.1007/bf00365371|s2cid = 7319985}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|16}}

===United States===
[[File:Lothrop Stoddard.JPG|upright|thumb|[[Lothrop Stoddard]] (1883–1950)]]
In the 20th century, concepts of scientific racism, which sought to prove the physical and mental inadequacy of groups deemed "inferior", was relied upon to justify [[involuntary sterilization]] programs.&lt;ref name="JacksonWeidman"&gt;{{harvnb|Jackson|Weidman|2005|p=119}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Juliet Hooker]], ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=GVy1DgAAQBAJ Theorizing Race in the Americas: Douglass, Sarmiento, Du Bois, and Vasconcelos]'' (Oxford University Press, 2017), pp. 9–10.&lt;/ref&gt; Such programs, promoted by eugenicists such as [[Harry H. Laughlin]], were upheld as constitutional by the U.S. Supreme Court in ''[[Buck v. Bell]]'' (1927). In all, between 60,000 and 90,000 Americans were subjected to involuntary sterilization.&lt;ref name="JacksonWeidman"/&gt;

Scientific racism was also used as a justification for the [[Emergency Quota Act of 1921]] and the [[Immigration Act of 1924]] (Johnson–Reed Act), which imposed racial quotas limiting Italian American immigration to the United States and immigration from other southern European and eastern European nations. Proponents of these quotas, who sought to block "undesirable" immigrants, justifying restrictions by invoking scientific racism.&lt;ref&gt;Christa Wirth, ''Memories of Belonging: Descendants of Italian Migrants to the United States, 1884–Present'' ([[Brill Publishers]], 2015), pp. 190, 198.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Lothrop Stoddard]] published many racialist books on what he saw as the peril of immigration, his most famous being ''[[The Rising Tide of Color Against White World-Supremacy]]'' in 1920. In this book he presented a view of the world situation pertaining to race focusing concern on the coming population explosion among the "colored" peoples of the world and the way in which "white world-supremacy" was being lessened in the wake of World War I and the collapse of colonialism.

Stoddard's analysis divided world politics and situations into "white", "yellow", "black", "Amerindian", and "brown" peoples and their interactions. Stoddard argued race and heredity were the guiding factors of history and civilization, and that the elimination or absorption of the "white" race by "colored" races would result in the destruction of Western civilization. Like Madison Grant, Stoddard divided the white race into three main divisions: Nordic, Alpine, and Mediterranean. He considered all three to be of good stock, and far above the quality of the colored races, but argued that the Nordic was the greatest of the three and needed to be preserved by way of eugenics. Unlike Grant, Stoddard was less concerned with which varieties of European people were superior to others (Nordic theory), but was more concerned with what he called "bi-racialism", seeing the world as being composed of simply "colored" and "white" races. In the years after the Great Migration and World War I, Grant's racial theory would fall out of favor in the U.S. in favor of a model closer to Stoddard's.{{citation needed|date=July 2016}}

An influential publication was ''[[The Races of Europe (1939 book)|The Races of Europe]]'' (1939) by [[Carleton S. Coon]], president of the [[American Association of Physical Anthropologists]] from 1930 to 1961. Coon was a proponent of [[multiregional origin of modern humans]]. He divided ''Homo sapiens'' into five main races: Caucasoid, Mongoloid (including Native Americans), Australoid, Congoid, and [[Capoid]].

Coon's school of thought was the object of increasing opposition in mainstream anthropology after World War II. [[Ashley Montagu]] was particularly vocal in denouncing Coon, especially in his ''Man's Most Dangerous Myth: The Fallacy of Race''. By the 1960s, Coon's approach had been rendered obsolete in mainstream anthropology, but his system continued to appear in publications by his student [[John Lawrence Angel]] as late as in the 1970s.

In the late 19th century, the ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' (1896) [[United States Supreme Court]] decision—which upheld the constitutional legality of [[Racial segregation in the United States|racial segregation]] under the doctrine of "[[separate but equal]]"—was intellectually rooted in the racism of the era, as was the popular support for the decision.&lt;ref name="rlac"&gt;{{cite book|author=Sarat, Austin|title=Race, Law, and Culture: Reflections on Brown v. Board of Education|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|year=1997|pages=55, 59|isbn=978-0195106220}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in the mid-20th century, the Supreme Court's ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]] of Topeka'' (1954) decision rejected [[Racism|racialist]] arguments about the "need" for racial segregation—especially in [[Public education|public schools]].

==After 1945==
By 1954, 58 years after the ''Plessy v. Ferguson'' upholding of racial segregation in the United States, American popular and scholarly opinions of scientific racism and its sociologic practice had evolved.&lt;ref name="rlac"/&gt; 

In 1960, the journal ''[[Mankind Quarterly]]'' was founded, which is commonly described as a venue for scientific racism and white supremacy,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Winston |first=Andrew S. |title=Oxford Research Encyclopedia of Psychology |date=29 May 2020 |chapter=Scientific Racism and North American Psychology |chapter-url=https://oxfordre.com/psychology/view/10.1093/acrefore/9780190236557.001.0001/acrefore-9780190236557-e-516 |website=Oxford Research Encyclopedia of Psychology|doi=10.1093/acrefore/9780190236557.013.516 |isbn=978-0-19-023655-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Measured Lies: The Bell Curve Examined |title-link=Measured Lies: The Bell Curve Examined |date=14 March 1997 |publisher=St. Martin's Press |isbn=978-0-312-17228-2 |editor1-last=Gresson |editor1-first=Aaron |edition=1st St. Martin's Griffin |page=39 |editor2-last=Kincheloe |editor2-first=Joe L. |editor2-link=Joe L. Kincheloe |editor3-last=Steinberg |editor3-first=Shirley R. |editor3-link=Shirley R. Steinberg}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;William H. Tucker, ''The funding of scientific racism: Wickliffe Draper and the Pioneer Fund'', University of Illinois Press, 2002, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; and as lacking a legitimate scholarly purpose.&lt;ref name="jackson" /&gt; The journal was founded in 1960, partly in response to the Supreme Court decision ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]'' which desegregated the American public school system.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schaffer|2007|pp=253–78}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="jackson"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jackson|first1=John|last2=McCarthy|first2=John P. Jr|title=Science for Segregation: Race, Law, and the Case against Brown v. Board of Education|publisher=New York University Press|location=New York|year=2005|page=148–|isbn=978-0814742716}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 1966, [[Alex Haley]] interviewed [[American Nazi Party]] founder [[George Lincoln Rockwell]] for ''[[Playboy]]''. Rockwell justified his belief that blacks were inferior to whites by citing a long 1916 study by G. O. Ferguson which claimed to show that the intellectual performance of black students was correlated with their percentage of white ancestry, stating "pure negroes, negroes three-fourths pure, mulattoes and quadroons have, roughly, 60, 70, 80 and 90 percent, respectively, of white intellectual efficiency".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ferguson|first=G.O.|title=The Psychology of the Negro|url=https://archive.org/stream/psychologyofnegr00ferg#page/124/mode/2up|journal= Archives of Psychology|volume=36|date=April 1916|page=125}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Playboy'' later published the interview with an editorial note claiming the study was a "discredited ... pseudoscientific rationale for racism".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Haley|first=Alex|title=Interview: George Lincoln Rockwell|magazine=[[Playboy]]|date=April 1966|url=https://archive.org/stream/1966PlayboyInterview/MicrosoftWord-Document1#page/n7/mode/2up}}&lt;/ref&gt;

International bodies such as [[United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization|UNESCO]] attempted to draft resolutions that would summarize the state of scientific knowledge about race and issued calls for the resolution of racial conflicts. In its 1950 "[[The Race Question]]", UNESCO did not reject the idea of a biological basis to racial categories,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Banton|first=Michael|chapter=Race, Unesco statements on|editor-last=Schaefer|editor-first=Richard T.|year=2008|title=Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity and Society|publisher=Sage|isbn=978-1412926942|pages=1096, 1098}}&lt;/ref&gt; but instead defined a race as: "A race, from the biological standpoint, may therefore be defined as one of the group of populations constituting the species Homo sapiens", which were broadly defined as the [[Caucasian race|Caucasian]], [[Mongoloid race|Mongoloid]], [[Negroid race|Negroid]] races but stated that "It is now generally recognized that intelligence tests do not in themselves enable us to differentiate safely between what is due to innate capacity and what is the result of environmental influences, training and education."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Race Question |date=1950 |publisher=UNESCO publication |location=France |url=https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000128291}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite scientific racism being largely dismissed by the scientific community after World War II, some researchers have continued to propose theories of racial superiority in the past few decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|date=January 31, 2014|work=Race Unmasked|publisher=Columbia University Press|isbn=978-0-231-53799-5|doi=10.7312/yude16874-011|title=9. Challenges to the Race Concept}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Sussman|first=Robert Wald|title=The Myth of Race|date=January 31, 2014|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=978-0-674-73616-0|location=Cambridge, MA and London, England|doi=10.4159/harvard.9780674736160}}&lt;/ref&gt; These authors themselves, while seeing their work as scientific, may dispute the term ''racism'' and may prefer terms such as "race realism" or "racialism".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rushton|first1=J. Philippe|last2=Jensen|first2=Arthur R.|title=Wanted: More race realism, less moralistic fallacy.|journal=[[Psychology, Public Policy, and Law]]|date=2005|volume=11|issue=2|pages=328–36|doi=10.1037/1076-8971.11.2.328|citeseerx=10.1.1.521.5570}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018, British science journalist and author [[Angela Saini]] expressed strong concern about the return of these ideas into the mainstream.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/jan/22/eugenics-racism-mainstream-science|title=Racism is creeping back into mainstream science – we have to stop it|author=Angela Saini|date=January 22, 2018|publisher=Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Saini followed up on this idea with her 2019 book ''[[Superior: The Return of Race Science]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2019/07/10/416496218/is-race-science-making-a-comeback|title=Is 'Race Science' Making A Comeback?|author=Jess Kung|date=July 10, 2019|publisher=NPR}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One such post-World War II scientific racism researcher is [[Arthur Jensen]]. His most prominent work is ''[[The g Factor: The Science of Mental Ability]]'' in which he supports the theory that black people are inherently less intelligent than whites. Jensen argues for differentiation in education based on race, stating that educators must "take full account of ''all'' the facts of [students'] nature."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Jensen|first=Arthur R.|date=1968|title=Social Class, Race, and Genetics: Implications for Education|journal=American Educational Research Journal|volume=5|issue=1|pages=1–42|doi=10.3102/00028312005001001|s2cid=38402369|issn=0002-8312}}&lt;/ref&gt; Responses to Jensen criticized his lack of emphasis on environmental factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sanday|first=Peggy R.|date=1972|title=An Alternative Interpretation of the Relationship between Heredity, Race, Environment, and IQ.|journal=The Phi Delta Kappan|volume=54|pages=250–254|via=JSTOR}}&lt;/ref&gt; Psychologist [[Sandra Scarr]] describes Jensen's work as "conjur[ing] up images of blacks doomed to failure by their own inadequacies".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Scarr|first=Sandra|date=1981|title=Implicit Messages: A Review of "Bias in Mental Testing"Bias in Mental Testing. Arthur R. Jensen|journal=American Journal of Education|volume=89|issue=3|pages=330–338|doi=10.1086/443584|s2cid=147214993|issn=0195-6744}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[J. Philippe Rushton]], president of the [[Pioneer Fund]] (''[[Race, Evolution, and Behavior]]'') and a defender of Jensen's ''The g Factor'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amazon.com/review/R3KN388AI1KTVL|website=www.amazon.com|access-date=April 29, 2020|title=Outstanding Synthesis of Current Work on IQ}}&lt;/ref&gt; also has multiple publications perpetuating scientific racism. Rushton argues "race differences in brain size likely underlie their multifarious life history outcomes."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Rushston|first=J Philippe|date=2001|title=Genes, Brains, and Culture: Returning to a Darwinian Evolutionary Psychology|journal=Behavior and philosophy|volume=29|pages=95–99}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rushton's theories are defended by other scientific racists such as [[Glayde Whitney]]. Whitney published works suggesting higher crime rates among people of African descent can be partially attributed to genetics.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Rushton|first1=J. Philippe|last2=Whitney|first2=Glayde|date=2002|title=Cross-National Variation in Violent Crime Rates: Race, r-K Theory, and Income.|journal=Population and Environment|volume=23|issue=6|pages=501–511|via=JSTOR|doi=10.1023/a:1016335501805|s2cid=16276258}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whitney draws this conclusion from data showing higher crime rates among people of African descent across different regions. Other researchers point out that proponents of a genetic crime-race link are ignoring confounding social and economic variables, drawing conclusions from correlations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Powledge|first=Tabitha M.|date=1996|title=Genetics and the Control of Crime|journal=BioScience|volume=46|issue=1|pages=7–10|doi=10.2307/1312648|jstor=1312648|issn=0006-3568|doi-access=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Chris Brand|Christopher Brand]] was a proponent of Arthur Jensen's work on racial intelligence differences.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Brand|first=Chris|date=2003|title=IQ guru talks to Skeptic magazine? Given the chance to explain how he chose to endure denunciation for 'fascism', psychologist Arthur Jensen holds his peace|journal=Heredity|language=en|volume=90|issue=5|pages=346–347|doi=10.1038/sj.hdy.6800226|issn=1365-2540|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brand's ''[[The g Factor: General Intelligence and Its Implications]]'' claims black people are intellectually inferior to whites.&lt;ref name="Brand-1996"&gt;{{cite book|last=Brand|first=Christopher|title=The g Factor: General Intelligence and Its Implications|year=1996&lt;!--|pages=Ch. 3--&gt;|chapter=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; He argues the best way to combat IQ disparities is to encourage low-IQ women to reproduce with high-IQ men.&lt;ref name="Brand-1996" /&gt; He faced intense public backlash, with his work being described as a promotion of eugenics.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Kerr|first1=Anne|last2=Cunningham-Burley|first2=Sarah|last3=Amos|first3=Amanda|date=1998|title=Eugenics and the New Genetics in Britain: Examining Contemporary Professionals' Accounts|journal=Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values|volume=23|issue=2|pages=175–198|doi=10.1177/016224399802300202|pmid=11656684|s2cid=20393035|issn=0162-2439}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brand's book was withdrawn by the publisher and he was dismissed from his position at the [[University of Edinburgh]].
[[File:Prof-Richard-Lynn-7635-2.jpg|thumb|[[Richard Lynn]] (1930–2023)]]
Psychologist [[Richard Lynn]] has published multiple papers and a book supporting theories of scientific racism. In ''[[IQ and the Wealth of Nations]],'' Lynn claims that national GDP is determined largely by national average IQ.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lynn|first=Richard|title=IQ and the wealth of nations|date=2002|publisher=Praeger|isbn=0-275-97510-X|oclc=928425551}}&lt;/ref&gt; He draws this conclusion from the correlation between average IQ and GDP and argues low intelligence in African nations is the cause of their low levels of growth. Lynn's theory has been criticized for attributing causal relationship between correlated statistics.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Volken|first=T.|date=September 1, 2003|title=IQ and the Wealth of Nations. A Critique of Richard Lynn and Tatu Vanhanen's Recent Book|journal=European Sociological Review|volume=19|issue=4|pages=411–412|doi=10.1093/esr/19.4.411|issn=0266-7215}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=MORSE|first=STEPHEN|date=2008|title=The geography of tyranny and despair: development indicators and the hypothesis of genetic inevitability of national inequality|journal=Geographical Journal|volume=174|issue=3|pages=195–206|doi=10.1111/j.1475-4959.2008.00296.x|issn=0016-7398|url=http://epubs.surrey.ac.uk/351102/1/The%20geography%20of%20tyranny%20and%20dispair%20~%20The%20Geographical%20Journal.pdf|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lynn supports scientific racism more directly in his 2002 paper "Skin Color and Intelligence in African Americans", where he proposes "the level of intelligence in African Americans is significantly determined by the proportion of Caucasian genes."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lynn|first=Richard|date=2002|title=Skin Color and Intelligence in African Americans.|journal=Population and Environment|volume=23|issue=4|pages=365–375|doi=10.1023/a:1014572602343|s2cid=145386366|issn=0199-0039}}&lt;/ref&gt; As with ''IQ and the Wealth of Nations'', Lynn's methodology is flawed, and he purports a causal relationship from what is simply correlation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hill|first=Mark E.|date=2002|title=Skin Color and Intelligence in African Americans: A Reanalysis of Lynn's Data|journal=Population and Environment|volume=24|issue=2|pages=209–214|doi=10.1023/a:1020704322510|s2cid=141143755|issn=0199-0039}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other prominent modern proponents of scientific racism include [[Charles Murray (political scientist)|Charles Murray]] and [[Richard Herrnstein]] (''[[The Bell Curve]]''); and [[Nicholas Wade]] (''[[A Troublesome Inheritance]]''). Wade's book faced strong backlash from the scientific community, with 142 geneticists and biologists signing a letter describing Wade's work as "misappropriation of research from our field to support arguments about differences among human societies."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://cehg.stanford.edu/letter-from-population-geneticists|title=Letters: "A Troublesome Inheritance" {{!}} Stanford Center for Computational, Evolutionary, and Human Genomics|website=cehg.stanford.edu|access-date=April 29, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 17, 2020, Elsevier announced it was retracting an article that [[J. Philippe Rushton]] and [[Donald Templer]] had published in 2012 in the Elsevier journal ''Personality and Individual Differences''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Personality and Individual Differences Retracts Rushton and Templer Article|url=https://www.journals.elsevier.com/personality-and-individual-differences/announcements/rushton-and-templer-article|access-date=June 19, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; The article falsely claimed that there was scientific evidence that skin color was related to aggression and sexuality in humans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Elsevier journal to retract 2012 paper widely derided as racist|date=June 17, 2020|url=https://retractionwatch.com/2020/06/17/elsevier-journal-to-retract-2012-paper-widely-derided-as-racist/|access-date=June 19, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Jena Declaration]], published by the [[German Zoological Society]], rejects the idea of human races and distances itself from the [[Scientific racism|racial theories]] of 20th century scientists. It states that [[genetic variation]] between [[World population|human populations]] is smaller than within them, demonstrating that the biological concept of "races" is invalid. The statement highlights that there are no specific [[Gene|genes]] or [[Genetic marker|genetic markers]] that match with conventional racial [[Categorization|categorizations]]. It also indicates that the idea of "races" is based on [[racism]] rather than any [[Science|scientific]] factuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Max Planck Institute of Geoanthropology |date=2019-09-10 |title=Jenaer Erklärung |url=https://www.shh.mpg.de/1464654/jenaer-erklaerung |access-date=2023-11-17 |website=www.shh.mpg.de |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Nachrichten Informationsdienst Wissenschaft |date=2019-09-10 |title=‘Human races’ do not exist |url=https://nachrichten.idw-online.de/2019/09/10/human-races-do-not-exist |access-date=2023-11-17 |website=nachrichten.idw-online.de |language=de-DE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Clarence Gravlee writes that disparities in the incidence of such medical conditions as diabetes, stroke, cancer, and low birth weight should be viewed with a societal lens. He argues that [[Social inequality|social inequalities]], not genetic differences between races, are the reason for these differences. He writes that genetic differences between different population groups are based on climate and geography, not race, and he calls for replacing incorrect biological explanations of racial disparities with an analysis of the social conditions that lead to disparate medical outcomes.&lt;ref&gt;Gravlee CC. How race becomes biology: embodiment of social inequality. Am J Phys Anthropol. 2009 May;139(1):47–57. {{doi|10.1002/ajpa.20983.}} PMID 19226645.&lt;/ref&gt; In his book ''Is Science Racist'', Jonathan Marks similarly asserts that races exist, however, they lack a natural categorization in the realm of biology. Cultural rules such as the "[[one-drop rule]]" must be devised to establish categories of race, even if they go against the natural patterns within our species. According to Marks' writing, racist ideas propagated by scientists are what make science racist.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Marks |first=Jonathan |title=Is Science Racist? |publisher=Polity |year=2017 |isbn=978-0745689227 |edition=1st}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In her book ''Medical Apartheid''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Washington|first=Harriet|title=Medical Apartheid: The Dark History of Medical Experimentation on Black Americans from Colonial Times to the Present|publisher=Doubleday|year=2007|isbn=978-0767915472}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harriet Washington describes the abuse of Black people in medical research and experimentation. Black people were tricked into participating in medical experiments through the use of unclear language on consent forms and a failure to list the risks and side effects of the treatment. Washington mentions that, because Black people were denied [[Health equity|adequate health care]], they were often desperate for medical help, and medical experimenters were able to exploit that need. Washington also emphasizes that when treatments were perfected and refined as a result of those experiments, Black people almost never benefited from the treatments.&lt;ref&gt;Mills, Malcolm. ''The Journal of African American History'', vol. 94, no. 1, [The University of Chicago Press, Association for the Study of African American Life and History], 2009, pp. 101–03, {{JSTOR|25610054}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2018 statement by the [[American Society of Human Genetics]] (ASHG) expressed alarm at the "resurgence of groups rejecting the value of genetic diversity and using discredited or distorted genetic concepts to bolster bogus claims of white supremacy." The ASHG denounced this as a "misuse of genetics to feed racist ideologies", and highlighted several factual errors upon which white supremacist claims have been based. The statement affirms that genetics "demonstrates that humans cannot be divided into biologically distinct subcategories" and that it "exposes the concept of 'racial purity’' as scientifically meaningless."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |date=1 November 2018 |title=ASHG Denounces Attempts to Link Genetics and Racial Supremacy |url=https://www.cell.com/ajhg/pdf/S0002-9297(18)30363-X.pdf |journal=The American Journal of Human Genetics |volume=103 |issue=5 |pages=636|doi=10.1016/j.ajhg.2018.10.011 |pmid=30348456 |pmc=6218810 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=28em}}
* [[Bias]]
* [[Biological determinism]]
* [[Environmental determinism]]
* [[Freak show]]
* [[History of the race and intelligence controversy]]
* [[Human zoo]]
* [[Institute for the Study of Academic Racism]]
* [[Italian Fascism and racism]]
* [[Italian racial laws]]
* [[Nazism and race]]
* [[Objectification]]
* [[Pioneer Fund]]
* [[Racial policy of Nazi Germany]]
* [[Race and genetics]]
* [[Race and health]]
* [[Race and intelligence]]
* [[Scientific imperialism]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin|35em}}
* {{cite book|last1=Asséo|first1=Henriette|last2=Fings|first2=Karola|author3=Sparing, Frank|author4=Kenrick, Donald|author5=Heuss, Herbert|title=From "race science" to the camps|publisher=University of Hertfordshire Press|location=Hatfield|year=1997|isbn=978-0900458781|series=The Gypsies During the Second World War|volume=1}}
* {{cite book|last=Barkan|first=Elazar|title=The Retreat of Scientific Racism: Changing Concepts of Race in Britain and the United States between the World Wars|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=New York|year=1992}}
* {{cite book|last=Biddiss|first=Michael D.|title=Father of Racist Ideology: The Social and Political Thought of Count Gobineau|url=https://archive.org/details/fatherofracistid00bidd|url-access=registration|publisher=Weybright and Talley|location=New York|year=1970}}
* {{cite journal|last=Dennis|first=Rutledge M.|title=Social Darwinism, scientific racism, and the metaphysics of race|journal=Journal of Negro Education|volume=64|issue=3|pages=243–52|year=1995|doi=10.2307/2967206|jstor=2967206}}
* Detterman, Douglas K. 2006. "Intelligence." ''Microsoft Student 2007'' DVD. Redmond, WA: Microsoft Corporation.
* {{cite book|last=Efron|first=John M.|title=Defenders of the race: Jewish doctors and race science in fin-de-siècle Europe|publisher=Yale University Press|location=New Haven CT|year=1994|isbn=978-0300054408|url=https://archive.org/details/defendersofracej0000efro}}
* {{cite book|last=Ehrenreich|first=Eric|title=The Nazi ancestral proof: genealogy, racial science, and the final solution|publisher=Indiana University Press|location=Bloomington|year=2007|isbn=978-0253349453|url=https://archive.org/details/naziancestralpro00ehre_0}}
* {{cite book|last1=Ewen|first1=Stuart|last2=Ewen|first2=Elizabeth|title=Typecasting: On the Arts and Sciences of Human Inequality|publisher=Seven Stories Press|location=New York|year=2007|isbn=978-1-58322-776-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Gould|first=Stephen Jay|author-link=Stephen Jay Gould|title=The Mismeasure of Man|title-link=The Mismeasure of Man|publisher=W W Norton and Co.|location=New York|year=1981|isbn=978-0-393-01489-1}}
* {{cite book|last1=Gross|first1=Paul R.|author-link1=Paul R. Gross|last2=Levitt|first2=Norman Jay|author-link2=Norman Levitt|title=Higher Superstition: The Academic Left and Its Quarrels With Science|publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press|location=Baltimore|year=1994|isbn=978-0-8018-4766-0|title-link=Higher Superstition: The Academic Left and Its Quarrels With Science}}
* {{cite book|last=Hecht|first=Jennifer Michael|title=The end of the soul: scientific modernity, atheism, and anthropology in France|publisher=Columbia University Press|year=2003|isbn=978-0231128469|location=New York|page=171|oclc=53118940}}
* Higgins, A.C. n.d. [http://www.math.buffalo.edu/mad/special/scientific-racism.html "Scientific Racism: A Review of ''The Science and Politics of Racial Research'' by William H. Tucker"]. Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1994. Accessed October 21, 2007.
* {{cite book|last=Isaac|first=Benjamin H.|title=The Invention of Racism in Classical Antiquity|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton NJ|year=2004}}
* {{cite book|last1=Jackson|first1=John P.|last2=Weidman|first2=Nadine M.|title=Race, Racism, and Science: Social Impact and Interaction|publisher=Rutgers University Press|year=2005}}
* {{cite book|last=Kühl|first=Stefan|title=The Nazi Connection: Eugenics, American Racism, and German National Socialism|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|year=1994}}
* {{cite journal|last=Lombardo|first=Paul A.|title='The American Breed': Nazi Eugenics and the Origins of the Pioneer Fund|journal=Albany Law Review|volume=65|issue=3|pages=743–830|year=2002|pmid=11998853|title-link=Pioneer Fund}}
* {{cite book|last=Mintz|first=Frank P.|title=The Liberty Lobby and the American Right: Race, Conspiracy, and Culture|publisher=Greenwood|location=Westport CT|year=1985}}
* {{cite news|last=Murray|first=Charles|author-link=Charles Murray (political scientist)|title=The Inequality Taboo|newspaper=Commentary Magazine|date=September 2005|url=http://www.commentarymagazine.com/production/files/murray0905.html|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050924130608/http://www.commentarymagazine.com/production/files/murray0905.html|archive-date=September 24, 2005}}
* {{cite book|last=Poliakov|first=Leon|author-link=Leon Poliakov|title=Aryan Myth: A History of Racist and Nationalist Ideas in Europe|publisher=Basic Books|location=New York|year=1974}}
* {{cite book|last=Proctor|first=Robert N.|author-link=Robert N. Proctor|title=Racial Hygiene: Medicine under the Nazis|url=https://archive.org/details/racialhygiene00robe|url-access=registration|publisher=Harvard University Press|location=Cambridge|year=1988}}
* {{cite book|last=Sapp|first=Jan|title=Beyond the gene: cytoplasmic inheritance and the struggle for authority in genetics|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|year=1987|isbn=978-0195042061}}
* {{cite journal|last=Schaffer|first=Gavin|title="'Scientific' Racism Again?": Reginald Gates, the ''Mankind Quarterly'' and the Question of "Race" in Science after the Second World War|journal=Journal of American Studies|volume=41|issue=2|pages=253–78|year=2007|doi=10.1017/S0021875807003477|s2cid=145322934}}
* {{cite book|last=Taguieff|first=Pierre-André|author-link=Pierre-André Taguieff|title=La Force du préjugé. Essai sur le racisme et ses doubles|publisher=[[Gallimard]], La Découverte|location=Paris|year=1987|isbn=978-2070719778|language=fr}}
* {{cite book|title=The funding of Scientific Racism: Wickliffe Draper and the Pioneer Fund|last=Tucker|first=William H.|author-link=William H. Tucker (psychologist)|publisher=[[University of Illinois Press]]|year=2007|isbn=9780252074639|url=http://www.press.uillinois.edu/books/catalog/65rwe7dm9780252074639.html}}
* {{cite book|last=Jackson|first=J.|chapter=Racially stuffed shirts and other enemies of mankind: Horace Mann Bond's parody of segregationist psychology in the 1950s|editor-last=Winston|editor-first=A.|title=Defining difference: Race and Racism in the History of Psychology|publisher=American Psychological Association|location=Washington DC|year=2004|pages=261–283|chapter-url=http://psycnet.apa.org/record/2003-06663-010}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1037/0003-066X.51.2.77|last1=Neisser|first1=U.|last2=Boodoo|first2=G.|last3=Bouchard|first3=T.J. Jr.|last4=Boykin|first4=A.W.|last5=Brody|first5=N.|last6=Ceci|first6=S.J.|title=Intelligence: Knowns and unknowns|journal=American Psychologist|volume=51|pages=77–101|year=1996|url=http://www.psych.illinois.edu/~broberts/Neisser%20et%20al,%201996,%20intelligence.pdf|issue=2|ref={{harvid|American Psychologist|1996}}|display-authors=etal|access-date=February 24, 2011|archive-date=August 16, 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100816090612/http://www.psych.illinois.edu/~broberts/Neisser%20et%20al,%201996,%20intelligence.pdf|url-status=dead}}
* {{cite book|last=Richards|first=G.|title=Race, Racism, and Psychology: Towards a Reflexive History|publisher=Routledge|location=New York|year=1997}}
* {{cite book|last1=Shultz|first1=D.P.|last2=Shultz|first2=S.E.|title=A History of Modern Psychology|publisher=Thomson Higher Education|location=Belmont CA|year=2008|edition=9th}}
* {{citation|last=Trautmann|first=Thomas R.|title=Aryans and British India|year=1997|publisher=Vistaar}}
* {{cite book|last=Tucker|first=W.H.|title=The Science and Politics of Racial Research|publisher=University of Illinois Press|location=Urbana|year=1994}}
* {{citation|last=Walsh|first=Judith E.|title=A Brief History of India|year=2011|publisher=Facts On File|isbn=978-0816081431|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/briefhistoryofin0000wals_y0v7}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* Alexander, Nathan G. (2019). ''Race in a Godless World: Atheism, Race, and Civilization, 1850–1914''. New York/Manchester: New York University Press/Manchester University Press. {{ISBN|978-1526142375}}.
* {{cite book |title=Rhetorical Engagements in the Scientist's Process of Remaking Race as Genetic |last=Condit |first=Celeste M. |publisher=[[The University of South Carolina Press]] |year=2010 |isbn=978-1299241091}}
* {{cite book |title=Racism: A Short History |last=Fredrickson |first=George M. |publisher=Princeton University Press |year=2002 |url=https://archive.org/details/racismshorthisto0000fred |isbn=978-0-691-00899-8}}
* {{cite book |title=Bone Rooms: From Scientific Racism to Human Prehistory in Museums |last=Redman |first=Samuel J. |publisher=Harvard University Press |year=2016 |isbn=978-0674660410}}
* {{Cite book|title=[[Superior: The Return of Race Science]]|last=Saini|first=Angela|publisher=[[Beacon Press]]|year=2019|isbn=978-0008341008}}
* {{cite book|title=Defending the Master Race: Conservation, Eugenics, and the Legacy of Madison Grant|last=Spiro|first=Jonathan P.|publisher=University of Vermont Press|year=2009|isbn=978-1584657156}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Scientific racism}}
* "[https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/race-evolution-and-the-science-of-human-origins/ Race, Evolution and the Science of Human Origins]" by Allison Hopper, ''[[Scientific American]]'' (July 5, 2021).
* [https://www.genome.gov/about-genomics/fact-sheets/Eugenics-and-Scientific-Racism Fact Sheet on Eugenics and Scientific Racism from the National Human Genome Research Institute]
* [https://www.encyclopedia.com/social-sciences/encyclopedias-almanacs-transcripts-and-maps/scientific-racism-history Scientific racism, history of] at [[Encyclopedia.com]] ([[Cengage]])
* [http://www.rationalrevolution.net/articles/darwin_nazism.htm The Mis-portrayal of Darwin as a Racist]&amp;nbsp;– Refutes claims that Darwin was a racist or that his views inspired the Nazis
* {{cite book|chapter=Box D. Brain Size and Intelligence|chapter-url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK11129/box/A1833/|editor1=Purves D|editor2=Augustine GJ|editor3=Fitzpatrick D|title=Neuroscience|publisher=Sinauer Associates|location=Sunderland, MA|year=2001|edition=2nd|display-editors=etal}}
* [https://www.skeptic.com/eskeptic/05-02-18/ Reviews of ''Race: The Reality of Human Differences'']
* [http://web.mit.edu/racescience/links/index.html RaceSci: History of Race in Science] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210211011719/http://web.mit.edu/racescience/links/index.html |date=February 11, 2021 }}
* Gardner, Dan. [https://web.archive.org/web/20070819221453/http://www.sinc.sunysb.edu/Stu/lmarfogl/project/race_gerdner.htm Race Science: When Racial Categories Make No Sense]. ''[[The Globe and Mail]]'', October 27, 1995.
* [https://www.ferris-pages.org/ISAR/ Institute for the study of academic racism (ISAR)] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220117143633/https://www.ferris-pages.org/ISAR/ |date=January 17, 2022 }}
* [https://www.pbs.org/race/000_About/002_03_a-godeeper.htm Race, Science, and Social Policy.] From Race: The Power of an Illusion. [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]].
* [https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/cross-check/how-can-we-curb-the-spread-of-scientific-racism/ "How Can We Curb the Spread of Scientific Racism?"] a review of ''Superior: The Return of Race Science'' by [[Angela Saini]]
* {{cite web|title=The unwelcome revival of 'race science': 20 years after the human genome was first sequenced, dangerous gene myths abound|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2021/jun/09/human-genome-genes-genetic-code|first=Philip|last=Ball|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=June 9, 2021}}
* The Asian/Pacific/American Institute at [[New York University]]'s Timeline of Scientific Racism, [https://apa.nyu.edu/hauntedfiles/about/timeline/]

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Pseudoscience}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Scientific Racism}}
[[Category:Scientific racism| ]]
[[Category:Eugenics]]
[[Category:Pseudoscience]]
[[Category:Race and intelligence controversy]]
[[Category:Social problems in medicine]]
[[Category:Pseudoarchaeology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>