<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20140926142417|627160604" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="637623" pageid="637623" ns="0" title="Glass ceiling"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-09-26T14:24:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Average earnings of workers by education and sex - 2006.png|thumb|A chart illustrating the inequality in wages between men and women of the same educational level (USA 2006)]] 
A '''glass ceiling''' is a political term used to describe "the unseen, yet unbreachable barrier that keeps minorities and women from rising to the upper rungs of the corporate ladder, regardless of their qualifications or achievements."&lt;ref name="DOL2"&gt;Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling2.pdf ''Solid Investments: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital''.] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, November 1995, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

Initially, and sometimes still today, the metaphor was applied by feminists in reference to barriers in the careers of high achieving women.&lt;ref name="DOL1"&gt;Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf ''Good for Business: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital.''] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, March 1995, p. iii.&lt;/ref&gt; In the US the concept is sometimes extended to refer to obstacles hindering the advancement of minority men, as well as women.&lt;ref name="DOL1"/&gt;

==Definition==
David Cotter and colleagues defined four distinctive characteristics that must be met to conclude that a ''glass ceiling'' exists. A glass ceiling inequality represents:
#"A gender or racial difference that is not explained by other job-relevant characteristics of the employee."
#"A gender or racial difference that is greater at higher levels of an outcome than at lower levels of an outcome."
#"A gender or racial inequality in the chances of advancement into higher levels, not merely the proportions of each gender or race currently at those higher levels."
#"A gender or racial inequality that increases over the course of a career."
Cotter and his colleagues found that glass ceilings are correlated strongly with gender. Both white and African-American women face a glass ceiling in the course of their careers. In contrast, the researchers did not find evidence of a glass ceiling for African-American men.&lt;ref&gt;Cotter, David A., Joan M. Hermsen, Seth Ovadia, and Reece Vanneman (2001). [http://www.bsos.umd.edu/socy/vanneman/papers/CotterHOV01.pdf ''The glass ceiling effect''.] '''Social Forces''', Vol. 80 No. 2, pp. 655–81.&lt;/ref&gt;

The glass ceiling metaphor has often been used to describe invisible barriers ("glass") through which women can see elite positions but cannot reach them ("ceiling").&lt;ref&gt;*Davies-Netzley, Sally A. (1998). [http://www.jstor.org/pss/190289 ''Women above the Glass Ceiling: Perceptions on Corporate Mobility and Strategies for Success''] '''Gender and Society''', Vol. 12, No. 3, p. 340, {{doi|10.1177/0891243298012003006}}.&lt;/ref&gt; These barriers prevent large numbers of women and ethnic minorities from obtaining and securing the most powerful, prestigious, and highest-grossing jobs in the workforce.&lt;ref&gt;Hesse-Biber and Carter 2005, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, this effect may make women feel they are not worthy to fill high-ranking positions or as if their bosses do not take them seriously or see them as potential candidates for advancement.&lt;ref&gt;Nevill, Ginny, Alice Pennicott, Joanna Williams, and Ann Worrall. ''Women in the Workforce: The Effect of Demographic Changes in the 1990s''. London: The Industrial Society, 1990, p. 39, ISBN 978-0-85290-655-2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=US Department of Labor|title=Good for Business: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital|url=http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.htm|publisher=Office of the Secretary|accessdate=9 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The concept of glass ceiling was originally introduced outside of print media at the National Press Club in July 1979 at a Conference of the Women's Institute for Freedom of the Press by Katherine Lawrence of Hewlett Packard. This was part of an ongoing discussion of a clash between written policy of promotion versus action opportunities for women at HP. The term was coined by Lawrence and HP manager Marianne Schreiber. 
 
The term was later used in March 1984 by Gay Bryant. She was the former editor of ''Working Woman'' magazine and was changing jobs to be the editor of ''[[Family Circle]]''. In an ''[[Adweek]]'' article by Nora Frenkel, Bryant was reported as saying, "Women have reached a certain point—I call it the glass ceiling. They're in the top of middle management and they're stopping and getting stuck. There isn't enough room for all those women at the top. Some are going into business for themselves. Others are going out and raising families."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The Up-and-Comers; Bryant Takes Aim At the Settlers-In |last=Frenkiel |first=Nora |journal=Adweek |volume=Special Report |date=March 1984 |publisher=Magazine World}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Cornell&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/research/questionofthemonth/jan05.html |title=Question of the Month: Where did the term 'glass ceiling' originate? |date=January 2005 |author=Catherwood Library reference librarians |publisher=Cornell University, ILR School |accessdate=June 30, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Success&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Y71-YCYv-48C&amp;pg=PA9&amp;lpg=PA9 |pages=9–10 |title=Women in Media Careers: Success Despite the Odds |first1=Lee |last1=Bollinger |first2=Carole |last2=O'Neill |publisher=University Press of America |year=2008 |isbn=9780761841333}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 1984, Bryant used the term in a chapter of the book ''The Working Woman Report: Succeeding in Business in the 1980s''. In the same book, Basia Hellwig used the term in another chapter.&lt;ref name=Cornell/&gt;

In a widely cited article in the ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' in March 1986 the term was used in the 
article's title: "The Glass Ceiling: Why Women Can't Seem to Break The Invisible Barrier That Blocks Them From the Top Jobs." The article was written by Carol Hymowitz and Timothy D. Schellhardt. In 1991 the [[United States Department of Labor|US Labor Department]]'s chief, [[Lynn Morley Martin]], reported the results of a research project called "The Glass Ceiling Initiative" formed to investigate the low numbers of women and minorities in executive positions. This report defined the new term as "those artificial barriers based on attitudinal or organizational bias that prevent qualified individuals from advancing upward in their organization into management-level positions."&lt;ref name=Cornell/&gt;&lt;ref name=Success/&gt;

==Gender pay gap==
{{See also|Gender pay gap|Male-female income disparity in the United States}}

The gender pay gap is the difference between male and female earnings. In 2008 the [[OECD]] found that the median earnings of female full-time workers were 17% lower than the earnings of their male counterparts and that "30% of the variation in gender wage gaps across OECD countries can be explained by discriminatory practices in the [[Labour economics|labour market]]."&lt;ref&gt;[[OECD]]. [http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/8/19/40937574.pdf ''OECD Employment Outlook - 2008 Edition Summary in English''.] OECD, Paris, 2008, p. 3-4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oecd2"&gt;[[OECD]]. [http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/36/17/43244511.pdf ''OECD Employment Outlook. Chapter 3: The Price of Prejudice: Labour Market Discrimination on the Grounds of Gender and Ethnicity''.] OECD, Paris, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[European Commission]] found that women's hourly earnings were 17.5% lower on average in the 27 [[Member state of the European Union|EU Member States]] in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[[European Commission]]. [http://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=685&amp;langId=en ''The situation in the EU''.] Retrieved on July 12, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The female-to-male earnings ratio was 0.77 in the United States in 2009.&lt;ref name="census 2009"&gt;DeNavas-Walt, Carmen, Bernadette D. Proctor, and Jessica C. Smith. [http://www.census.gov/prod/2010pubs/p60-238.pdf ''Income, Poverty, and Health Insurance Coverage in the United States: 2009.''] U.S. Census Bureau, Current Population Reports, P60-238, U.S. Government Printing Office, Washington, DC, 2010, p. 7, 50.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Columns-list|2|
* [[Celluloid ceiling]]
* [[Equal pay for women]]
* [[Female labor force in the Muslim world]]
* [[Gender equality]]
* [[Gender inequality]]
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Glass cliff]]
* [[Mommy track]]
* [[Sex differences in humans]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Stained-glass ceiling]]
* [[Superwoman (sociology)]]
* [[Time bind]]
* [[Work–life balance]]
}}

== Notes and references ==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography ==
* Federal Glass Ceiling Commission (1995a). [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf ''Good for Business: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital.''] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, March 1995.
* Fox, Mary F. and Sharlene N. Hesse-Biber. ''Women at Work''. Palo Alto, Calif.: Mayfield Publishing Company, 1984, ISBN 978-0-87484-525-9.
* [[Janet Zollinger Giele|Giele, Janet Z.]] and Leslie F. Stebbins. ''Women and Equality in the Workplace''. Santa Barbara, Calif.: ABC-CLIO, 2003, ISBN 978-1-57607-937-9.
* Hesse-Biber, Sharlene N. and Gregg L. Carter. ''Working Women in America''. New York: Oxford University Press, 2005, ISBN 978-0-19-515047-6.
* Lyness, Karen S., and Donna E. Thompson (1997). [http://psycnet.apa.org/journals/apl/82/3/359/ ''Above the Glass Ceiling?: A Comparison of Matched Samples of Female and Male Executives''.] '''Journal of Applied Psychology''', Vol 82, No. 3, pp.&amp;nbsp;359–375, {{doi|10.1037/0021-9010.82.3.359}}.
* [[Leila Schneps]] and [[Coralie Colmez]], ''Math on trial. How numbers get used and abused in the courtroom'', Basic Books, 2013. ISBN 978-0-465-03292-1. (Sixth chapter: "Math error number 6: Simpson's paradox. The Berkeley sex bias case: discrimination detection").

== External links ==
*Catalyst research report (1996). [http://www.catalyst.org/file/219/women%20in%20corporate%20leadership%20-%20progress%20and%20prospects%201996.pdf ''Women in Corporate Leadership'': Progr (2003).] [http://www.catalyst.org/file/74/women%20and%20men%20in%20u.s.%20corporate%20leadership%20same%20workplace,%20different%20realities.pdf ''Women and Men in U.S. Corporate Leadership: Same Workplace, Different Realities?'']
*Catalyst. [http://www.catalyst.org/publication/145/women-and-men-in-us-corporate-leadership-same-workplace-different-realities ''Women and Men in U.S. Corporate Leadership: Same Workplace, Different Realities?''] New York, N.Y.: Catalyst, 2004, ISBN 978-0-89584-247-3.
*Catalyst. [http://www.catalyst.org/file/420/2010_financial_post_500_women_senior_officers_and_top_earners_final.pdf ''2010 Catalyst Census: Financial Post 500 Women Senior Officers and Top Earners''.]
*Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf ''Good for Business: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital.''] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, March 1995.
*Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling2.pdf ''Solid Investments: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital''.] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, November 1995.
*Carvajal, Doreen. [http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/27/world/27iht-rules27.html ''The Codes That Need to Be Broken''.] ''The New York Times'', January 26, 2011.
*Cotter, David A., Joan M. Hermsen, Seth Ovadia, and Reece Vanneman (2001). [http://www.bsos.umd.edu/socy/vanneman/papers/CotterHOV01.pdf ''The glass ceiling effect''.] '''Social Forces''', Vol. 80 No. 2, pp.&amp;nbsp;655–81.


{{Discrimination}}
{{Portal bar|Anthropology|Sociology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Glass Ceiling}}
[[Category:Economic problems]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Feminist economics]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Employment discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>