<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061029160331|84435328" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="637623" pageid="637623" ns="0" title="Glass ceiling"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-29T16:04:17Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The term '''glass ceiling''' most commonly refers to the condition in which top-level management in businesses is dominated by men.  A "ceiling" is suggested because women are seen as limited in how far they can advance up organizational ranks; the ceiling is "glass" (transparent) because the limitation is not immediately apparent.  The "glass ceiling" is distinguished from formal barriers to advancement, such as education or experience requirements.

The term is often credited as having been originally coined by Carol Hymowitz and Timothy Schellhardt in the [[March 24]] [[1986]] edition of the &lt;cite&gt;[[Wall Street Journal]]&lt;/cite&gt;. However, the term was used prior to that e.g. in a March 1984 ''Adweek'' article by Gay Bryant.  

The term is most often used to refer to women's access to upper management. However, the glass ceiling also refers to the general tendency for women to be underrepresented at higher levels of the occupational hierarchy. Empirical evidence for this pattern in the U.S. is pervasive.&lt;ref&gt;David A. Cotter, Joan M. Hermsen, Seth Ovadia, and Reeve Vanneman. "The Glass Ceiling Effect." Social Forces Vol. 80, No. 2 (Dec., 2001), pp. 655-681.&lt;/ref&gt; The extension to other groups, such as racial or ethnic minorities, is usually made with direct or indirect reference to gender.

The term '''glass elevator''' (or '''glass escalator''') is sometimes used to describe the rapid promotion of men over women, especially into management, in female-dominated fields like [[nursing]].

The term '''glass cliff''' describes a situation wherein someone, particularly a [[woman]], has been promoted into a risky, difficult job where the chances of failure are higher.

Additional variations include the '''celluloid ceiling''', which refers to the small number of women in top positions in Hollywood, as documented by Lauzen (2002) and others.

== See also ==

* [[Stained-glass ceiling]]
* [[Equal pay for women]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Social equality|Equality]]
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Employment]]
* [[SDSDD]]
* [[Glass cliff]]

== Footnotes ==

&lt;!--See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref(erences/)&gt; tags--&gt;
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==

* [http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/catherwood/Collections/CollectionGuides/glassceiling.html Report of the Glass Ceiling Commission] ([[Portable Document Format|PDF]] format)
*[http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=pay+equity&amp;search_crit=title&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form Read Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding Pay Equity]
*[http://www.films42.com/chats/chats_lauzen.asp The Celluloid Ceiling: Behind-the-Scenes and On-Screen Employment of Women in the Top 250 Films of 2002]
*

{{fem-stub}}

[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Socioeconomics]]

[[he:תקרת הזכוכית]]
[[nl:Glazen plafond]]
[[zh:玻璃天花板]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>