<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151026181127|687617728" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="47849771" pageid="47849771" ns="0" title="Women&#039;s empowerment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-10T06:12:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Women empowerment''', referring to the [[empowerment]] of women in society, has become a significant topic of discussion in regards to development and economics. It can also point to approaches regarding other marginalized [[genders]] in a particular political or social context.

While often interchangeably used, the more comprehensive concept of [[Gender empowerment]] refers to people of any [[gender]], stressing the [[Sex and gender distinction|distinction]] between biological [[sex]] and [[Gender role|gender as a role]]. It thereby also refers to other marginalized genders in a particular political or social context.

== Methods to empower women ==
One way to deploy the empowerment of women is through [[land rights]]. Land rights offer a key way to economically empower women, giving them the confidence they need to tackle [[gender inequalities]]. Often, women in developing nations are legally restricted from their land on the sole basis of gender. Having a right to their land gives women a sort of [[bargaining power]] that they wouldn’t normally have, in turn; they gain the ability to assert themselves in various aspects of their life, both in and outside of the home.&lt;ref&gt;Agarwal, Bina. 1994. “Land Rights for Women: Making the Case,” in A Field of One’s Own: Gender and Land Rights in South Asia, pp. 1-50. Cambridge: Cambridge Univ. Press.&lt;/ref&gt;
Another way to provide women empowerment is to allocate responsibilities to them that normally belong to men. When women have [[economic empowerment]], it is a way for others to see them as equal members of society. Through this, they achieve more self-respect and confidence by their contributions to their communities. Simply including women as a part of a community can have sweeping positive effects. In a study conducted by [[Bina Agarwal]], women were given a place in a forest [[Conservation (ethic)|conservation]] group. Not only did this drive up the efficiency of the group, but the women gained incredible self-esteem while others, including men, viewed them with more respect.&lt;ref&gt;Argawal, Bina. 2010. “Gender and Green Governance: The Political Economy of Women’s Presence Within and Beyond Community Forestry.” New York, NY: Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Participation (decision making)|Participation]], which can be seen and gained in a variety of ways, has been argued to be the most beneficial form of gender empowerment. Political participation, be it the ability to [[vote]] and voice opinions, or the ability to run for office with a fair chance of being elected, plays a huge role in the empowerment of peoples.&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009"/&gt; However, participation is not limited to the realm of politics. It can include participation in the [[household]], in schools, and the ability to make [[choices]] for oneself. It can be said that these latter participations need to be achieved before one can move onto broader political participation.&lt;ref&gt;Nussbaum, Martha C. 2000. “Introduction,” in Women and Human Development: The Capabilities Approach, pp. 1–33. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; When women have the agency to do what she wants, a higher equality between men and women is established.
It is argued that [[Microcredit]] also offers a way to provide empowerment for women.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"/&gt; Governments, organizations, and individuals have caught hold of the lure of [[microfinance]]. They hope that lending money and credit allows women to function in business and society, which in turn empowers them to do more in their communities. One of the primary goals in the foundation of microfinance was women empowerment. Loans with low interest rates are given to women in developing communities in hopes that they can start a small business and provide for her family.&lt;ref&gt;Bateman, Milford. 2010. Why Doesn’t Microfinance Work?: The Destructive Rise of Local Neoliberalism, New York: Zed Books.&lt;/ref&gt; It should be said, however, that the success and efficiency of microcredit and [[microloans]] is controversial and constantly debated.&lt;ref&gt;Parmar, A. 2003. “Microcredit, Empowerment, and Agency: Re-evaluating the Discourse.” Canadian Journal of Development Studies 24 (3): 461-76.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The Internet as a tool of empowerment ===
The growing access of the web in the late 20th century, has allowed women to empower themselves by using various tools on the Internet. With the introduction of the [[World Wide Web]], women have begun to use social networking sites like Facebook and Twitter to start [[online activism]].&lt;ref name="Sutton, J. 2000"&gt;Sutton, J., &amp; Pollock, S. (2000). Online Activism for Women's Rights. Cyber Psychology &amp; Behavior, 3(5),699-706.&lt;/ref&gt; Through online activism, women are able to empower themselves by organizing campaigns and voicing their opinions for equality rights without feeling oppressed by members of society.&lt;ref&gt;Churchyard , N.(2009). The Question of Empowerment: Women’s Perspective on Their Internet Use. Gender, Technology and Development, 13(3), 341-363&lt;/ref&gt; For example, on May 29, 2013, an online campaign started by 100 female advocates forced the leading social networking website, [[Facebook]], to take down various pages that spread hatred about women.&lt;ref&gt;McVeigh.T (2013, June 6). Online Feminist activists of the digital age. Taipei Times. Retrieved from http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/editorials/archives/2013/06/06/2003564076&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, blogging has also become a powerful tool for the educational empowerment of women. According to a study done by the University of California, Los Angeles, medical patients who read and write about their disease are often in a much happier mood and more knowledgeable than those who do not.&lt;ref name="breastcancer.about.com"&gt;Stephan,P. (2013, August 13). Breast cancer patients blog their blues away. Retrieved from http://breastcancer.about.com/b/2013/08/13/blog-the-blues-away.htm&lt;/ref&gt; By reading others' experiences, patients can better educate themselves and apply strategies that their fellow bloggers suggest.&lt;ref name="breastcancer.about.com"/&gt;

With the easy accessibility and affordability of [[e-learning]] (electronic learning), women can now study from the comfort of their home anywhere, anytime.&lt;ref&gt;Radovic-Markovic, M., Nelson-Porter, B., &amp; Omolaja, M.(2012). The new alternative women's entrepreneurship education: E-learning and virtual universities. International Women Online Journal of Distance Education, 1(2), 46-54. Retrieved from http://wojde.org/FileUpload/bs295854/File/06a.markovic.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; By empowering themselves educationally through new technologies like e-learning, women are also learning new skills that will come in handy in today's advancing globalized world.

=== Barriers to the empowerment of women ===
Many of the barriers to women's empowerment and equity lie ingrained in cultural norms. Many women feel these pressures, while others have become accustomed to being treated inferior to men.&lt;ref&gt;Nussbaum, Martha C. 1995. "Introduction," in Martha C. Nussbaum and Jonathan Glover, eds. Women, Culture, and Development: A Study of Human Capabilities, pp. 1–15. Oxford: Clarendon Press&lt;/ref&gt; Even if men, [[legislators]], [[NGOs]], etc. are aware of the benefits women's empowerment and participation can have, many are scared of disrupting the status quo and continue to let [[societal norms]] get in the way of development.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"&gt;World Survey on the Role of Women In Development. 2009.  Women’s Control over Economic Resources and Access to Financial Resources, including Microfinance.  New York: United Nations&lt;/ref&gt;

Research shows that the increasing access to the internet can also result in an increased exploitation of women.&lt;ref name="Sutton, J. 2000"/&gt; Releasing personal information on websites has put some women's personal safety at risk. In 2010, Working to Halt Online Abuse stated that 73% of women were victimized through such sites.&lt;ref&gt;Debarati, H., &amp; Jaishankar, K. (2012). Cyber Crime and the Victimization of Women: Laws,Rights and Regulations. Hershey, PA: Information Science Reference&lt;/ref&gt; Types of victimization include cyber stalking, harassment, online pornography, and flaming.&lt;ref&gt;Morahan-Martin,J. (2000). Women and the Internet: Promise and Perils. Cyber Psychology &amp; Behavior, 3 (5), 683-691.&lt;/ref&gt;

Recent studies also show that women face more barriers in the workplace than do men. Gender-related barriers involve sexual harassment, unfair hiring practices, career progression, and unequal pay where women are paid less than men are for performing the same job.&lt;ref&gt;Stein, A.I. (2009). Women Lawyers Blog for Workplace Equality: Blogging as a Feminist Legal Method. Yale Journal of Law and Feminism, 20 (2), 357-408&lt;/ref&gt; Such barriers make it difficult for women to advance in their workplace or receive fair compensation for the work they provide.

== Measuring women empowerment ==
Women empowerment can be measured through the [[Gender Empowerment Measure]] (GEM), which shows women’s participation in a given nation, both politically and economically. GEM is calculated by tracking “the share of seats in [[parliament]] held by women; of female legislators, senior officials and managers; and of female profession and technical workers; and the [[gender disparity]] in earned income, reflecting economic independence.” &lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009"/&gt; It then ranks countries given this information. Other measures that take into account the importance of female participation and equality include: the [[Gender Parity Index]] and the [[Gender-related Development Index]] (GDI).&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009"/&gt;

== Role of Women empowerment for societies ==
Entire nations, businesses, communities, and groups can benefit from the implementation of programs and policies that adopt the notion of women empowerment.&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009"&gt;Deneulin, Séverine, with Lila Shahani.  2009.  An Introduction to the Human Development and Capability Approach: Freedom and Agency.  Sterling, VA: Earthscan.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Empowerment]] is one of the main procedural concerns when addressing [[human rights]] and [[International development|development]]. [[Capability Approach|The Human Development and Capabilities Approach]], [[The Millennium Development Goals]], and other credible approaches/goals point to empowerment and participation as a necessary step if a country is to overcome the obstacles associated with poverty and development.&lt;ref&gt;U.N. General Assembly, 55th Session. “United Nations Millennium Declaration.” (A/55/L.2).  8 September 2000. (Online) Available: www.un.org/millennium/declaration/ares552e.pdf (accessed January 2, 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Economic benefits of women empowerment ===
Most women across the globe rely on the [[informal sector|informal work sector]] for an income.&lt;ref&gt;United Nations Research Institute for Social Development.  2010. Combating Poverty and Inequality: Structural Change, Social Policy and Politics. Geneva: UNRISD "Gender Inequalities at Home and in the Market." Chapter 4, pp. 5–33&lt;/ref&gt; If women were empowered to do more and be more, the possibility for [[economic growth]] becomes apparent. Empowering women in developing countries is essential to reduce global poverty since women represent most of the world’s poor population.&lt;ref&gt;(2012, ). Intel . Women and the Web. Retrieved fromhttp://www.intel.com/content/dam/www/public/us/en/documents/pdf/women-and-theweb.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Eliminating a significant part of a nation’s work force on the sole basis of gender can have detrimental effects on the economy of that nation.&lt;ref&gt;UNICEF. 2007. "Equality in Employment," in The State of the World’s Children. New York: United Nations Children’s Fund.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, female participation in counsels, groups, and businesses is seen to increase efficiency.&lt;ref&gt;Argawal,uijh Bina. 2010. "Gender and Green Governance: The Political Economy of Women’s Presence Within and Beyond Community Forestry." New York, NY: Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; For a general idea on how an empowered women can impact a situation monetarily, a study found that of [[Fortune 500]] companies, "those with more women board directors had significantly higher financial returns, including 53 percent higher returns on equity, 24 percent higher returns on sales and 67 percent higher returns on invested capital (OECD, 2008)."&lt;ref&gt;World Survey on the Role of Women In Development. 2009.  Women’s Control over Economic Resources and Access to Financial Resources, including Microfinance.  New York: United Nations.&lt;/ref&gt; This study shows the impact women can have on the overall economic benefits of a company. If implemented on a global scale, the inclusion of women in the formal workforce (like a Fortune 500 company) can increase the economic output of a nation. Therefore, women can also help businesses grow and economies prosper if they have, and if they are able to use, the right knowledge and skills in their employment.

=== Empowerment in international development ===
The UK's [[Department for International Development]] are working to address constraints to the empowerment of adolescent girls in developing countries. Researchers mapped organisations that competitively seek innovative ideas from both the private and non-profit sectors potentially to reach girls, youth and/or women in developing country contexts and provides support in the forms of finance and technical assistance to bring their ideas to market.&lt;ref&gt;Mapping potential implementing organisations for girls' economic empowerment programme, Economics and Private Sector Professional Evidence and Applied Knowledge Services (EPS PEAKS) https://partnerplatform.org/?5smw2p44&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Women's rights]]
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Gender empowerment]]

== References == 
{{reflist|30em}}

[[Category:Women's studies]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]
[[Category:Human rights concepts]]
[[Category:Law and economics]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender identity-based cultures]]
[[Category:Law]]
[[Category:Egalitarianism]]
[[Category:Empowerment|*]]
[[Category:Women's empowerment|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>