<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171117013502|810725215" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="47849771" pageid="47849771" ns="0" title="Women&#039;s empowerment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-18T08:02:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{essay-like|date=July 2017}}
[[File:Shinzō Abe and Ivanka Trump (4).jpg|thumb|Advisor to [[US President]] and businesswoman [[Ivanka Trump]] (right) along with [[Japanese Prime Minister|Japanese PM]] [[Shinzo Abe]] attending the World Assembly for Women in [[Tokyo]] to speak on women's empowerment, 2017]]

'''Women's empowerment''' has become a significant topic of discussion in [[Human development (humanity)|development]] and [[economics]]. It can also point to the approaches regarding other trivialized [[gender]]s in a particular political or social context.

Women's [[economic empowerment]] refers to the ability for women to enjoy their right to control and benefit from resources, [[asset]]s, [[income]] and their own time, as well as the ability to [[Risk management|manage risk]] and improve their economic status and well being.&lt;ref name="Women's Economic Empowerment Conceptual Framework"&gt;Oxfam (Forthcoming), "Women's Economic Empowerment Conceptual Framework"&lt;/ref&gt;

While often interchangeably used, the more comprehensive concept of [[gender empowerment]] refers to people of any gender, stressing the [[Sex and gender distinction|distinction]] between biological [[sex]] and [[Gender role|gender as a role]]. It thereby also refers to other marginalized genders in a particular political or social context.

== Methods which help to empower women ==
Land rights offer a key way to economically empower women, giving them the confidence they need to tackle [[gender inequalities]]. Often, women in developing nations and underdeveloped are legally restricted from their land on the sole basis of gender. Having a right to their land gives women a sort of [[bargaining power]] that they wouldn't normally have; in turn, they gain the ability to assert themselves in various aspects of their life, both in and outside of the home.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Argawal, Bina|year=1994|chapter=Land Rights for Women: Making the Case|title=A Field of One's Own: Gender and Land Rights in South Asia|pages=1–50|location=Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge Univ. Press|isbn=9780521429269}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another way to provide women empowerment is to allocate responsibilities to them that normally belong to men. When women have [[economic empowerment]], it is a way for others to see them as equal members of society. Through this, they achieve more self-respect and confidence by their contributions to their communities. Simply including women as a part of a community can have sweeping positive effects. In a study conducted by [[Bina Agarwal]], women were given a place in a forest [[Conservation (ethic)|conservation]] group. This drove up the efficiency of the group, and the women gained self-esteem while others, including men, viewed them with more respect.&lt;ref name="Argawal 2010"&gt;{{cite book|author=Argawal, Bina|year=2010|title=Gender and Green Governance: The Political Economy of Women's Presence Within and Beyond Community Forestry|location=New York, NY|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-956968-7|url=http://www.binaagarwal.com/downloads/book9_flyer.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Participation (decision making)|Participation]], which can be seen and gained in a variety of ways, has been argued to be the most beneficial form of gender empowerment. Political participation, be it the ability to [[vote]] and voice opinions, or the ability to run for office with a fair chance of being elected, plays a huge role in the empowerment of women.&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009"/&gt; However, participation is not limited to the realm of politics. It can include participation in the [[household]], in schools, and the ability to make choices for oneself. It can be said that this latter participation need to be achieved before one can move onto broader political participation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Nussbaum, Martha C.|year=2000|chapter=Introduction|title=Women and Human Development: The Capabilities to Approach|pages=1–33|location=Cambridge, UK|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9781139459358|url=https://genderbudgeting.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/nussbaum_women_capabilityapproach2000.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; When women have the agency to do what they want, a higher equality between men and women is established.

It is argued that [[microcredit]] also offers a way to provide empowerment for women.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"/&gt; Governments, organizations, and individuals have caught hold of the lure of [[microfinance]]. They hope that lending money and credit allows women to function in business and society, which in turn empowers them to do more in their communities. One of the primary goals in the foundation of microfinance was women empowerment. Loans with low interest rates are given to women in developing communities in hopes that they can start a small business and provide for their families.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Bateman, Milford|year=2010|title=Why Doesn't Microfinance Work?: The Destructive Rise of Local Neoliberalism|location=New York|publisher=Zed Books|isbn=978-1848133327}}&lt;/ref&gt; It should be said, however, that the success and efficiency of microcredit and microloans is controversial and constantly debated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Parmar, A.|year=2003|title=Microcredit, Empowerment, and Agency: Re-evaluating the Discourse|journal=Canadian Journal of Development Studies|volume=24|issue=3|pages=461–76|doi=10.1080/02255189.2003.9668932}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The role of education ==
Improving education for women helps raise their levels of health and nutrition and reduces fertility rates.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;UNDP. 2013. Human Development Report. The Rise of the South. Human Progress in a Diverse World; New York, UNDP.&lt;/ref&gt; Education increases "people's self- confidence and enables them to find better jobs, engage in public debate and make demands on government for health care, social security and other entitlements".&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; In particular, education empowers women to make choices that improve their own and their children's health and chances of survival.&lt;ref&gt;UNESCO. 2014. EFA Global Monitoring Report 2013/2014: Teaching and Learning, Paris, UNESCO.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Education helps to prevent and contain disease, and is an essential element of efforts to reduce malnutrition. Further, education empowers women to make choices that improve their welfare, including marrying later and having fewer children. Crucially, education also increases women's awareness of their human rights their confidence and their actual ability to assert those rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0023/002343/234325E.pdf|title=Mobile phones and literacy: Empowerment in Women's Hands; A Cross-Case Analysis of Nine Experiences|last=UNESCO|first=|publisher=UNESCO|year=2015|isbn=978-92-3-100123-9|location=33|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite significant improvements in recent decades, education is not universally available and gender inequalities persist. A major concern in many countries is not only limited numbers of girls going to school, but also limited educational pathways for those that step into the classroom. This includes, more specifically, how to address the lower participation and learning achievement of [[Female education in STEM|girls in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) education]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Cracking the code: girls' and women's education in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM)|last=|first=|publisher=UNESCO|year=2017|isbn=9789231002335|location=Paris|pages=11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Internet as a tool of empowerment ==

The growing access of the web in the late 20th century has allowed women to empower themselves by using various tools on the Internet. With the introduction of the [[World Wide Web]], women have begun to use social networking sites like [[Facebook]] and [[Twitter]] for [[online activism]].&lt;ref name="Sutton, J. 2000"&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Sutton, J.|author2=Pollock, S.|lastauthoramp=y|year=2000|title=Online Activism for Women's Rights|journal=Cyber Psychology &amp; Behavior|volume=3|issue=5|pages=699–706|doi=10.1089/10949310050191700}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through online activism, women are able to empower themselves by organizing campaigns and voicing their opinions for equality rights without feeling oppressed by members of society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Churchyard, N.|year=2009|title=The Question of Empowerment: Women's Perspective on Their Internet Use|journal=Gender, Technology and Development|volume=13|issue=3|pages=341–363|doi=10.1177/097185241001300302}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, on May 29, 2013, an online campaign started by 100 female advocates forced the leading social networking website, Facebook, to take down various pages that spread hatred about women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=McVeigh, T.|date=June 6, 2013|title=Online Feminist activists of the digital age|work=Taipei Times|url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/editorials/archives/2013/06/06/2003564076}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, [[blogging]] has also become a powerful tool for the educational empowerment of women. According to a study done by the University of California, Los Angeles, medical patients who read and write about their disease are often in a much happier mood and more knowledgeable than those who do not.&lt;ref name="breastcancer.about.com"&gt;{{cite journal|author=Stephan, P.|date=August 13, 2013|title=Breast cancer patients blog their blues away|url=http://breastcancer.about.com/b/2013/08/13/blog-the-blues-away.htm|work=breastcancer.about.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; By reading others' experiences, patients can better educate themselves and apply strategies that their fellow bloggers suggest.&lt;ref name="breastcancer.about.com"/&gt;

With the easy accessibility and affordability of [[e-learning]] (electronic learning), women can now study from the comfort of their homes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Radovic-Markovic, M.|author2=Nelson-Porter, B.|author3=Omolaja, M.|lastauthoramp=y|year=2012|title=The new alternative women's entrepreneurship education: E-learning and virtual universities|journal=International Women Online Journal of Distance Education|volume=1|issue=2|pages=46–54|url=http://wojde.org/FileUpload/bs295854/File/06a.markovic.pdf|issn=2147-0367}}&lt;/ref&gt; By empowering themselves educationally through new technologies like e-learning, women are also learning new skills that will come in handy in today's advancing globalized world.

== Barriers ==

Many of the barriers to women's empowerment and equity lie ingrained in cultural norms. Many women feel these pressures, while others have become accustomed to being treated inferior to men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Nussbaum, Martha C.|year=1995|chapter=Introduction|editor1=Martha C. Nussbaum|editor2=Jonathan Glover|lastauthoramp=y|title=Women, Culture, and Development: A Study of Human Capabilities|pages=1–15|location=Oxford|publisher=Clarendon Press|isbn=9780198289647}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even if men, [[legislators]], [[NGOs]], etc. are aware of the benefits women's empowerment and participation can have, many are scared of disrupting the status quo and continue to let [[societal norms]] get in the way of development.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"&gt;{{cite report|section=World Survey on the Role of Women In Development|year=2009|title=Women's Control over Economic Resources and Access to Financial Resources, including Microfinance|location=New York|publisher=United Nations|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/public/WorldSurvey2009.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research shows that the increasing access to the internet can also result in an increased exploitation of women.&lt;ref name="Sutton, J. 2000"/&gt; Releasing personal information on websites has put some women's personal safety at risk. In 2010, Working to Halt Online Abuse stated that 73% of women were victimized through such sites. Types of victimization include [[cyber stalking]], harassment, [[online pornography]], and [[flaming (Internet)|flaming]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Morahan-Martin, J.|year=2000|title=Women and the Internet: Promise and Perils|journal=Cyber Psychology &amp; Behavior|volume=3|issue=5|pages=683–691|doi=10.1089/10949310050191683}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sexual harassment]] in particular is a large barrier for women in the workplace. It appears in almost all industries, but is most notable in the following: business, trade, banking and finance, sales and marketing, hospitality, civil service, and education, lecturing and teaching.&lt;ref name="Statistics"&gt;{{cite web|title=Statistics|work=AWARE RSS|publisher=AWARE|date=22 April 2010|accessdate=19 May 2016|url=http://www.aware.org.sg/training/wsh-site/14-statistics/}} &lt;/ref&gt; According to the International Labour Organisation (ILO), sexual harassment is a clear form of gender discrimination based on sex, a manifestation of unequal power relations between men and women. Furthermore, the UN Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women (CEDAW) is urging for increased measures of protection for women against sexual harassment and violence in the workplace. 54% (272) had experienced some form of workplace sexual harassment. 79% of the victims are women; 21% were men.&lt;ref name="Statistics"/&gt;

Recent studies also show that women face more barriers in the workplace than do men. Gender-related barriers involve sexual harassment, unfair hiring practices, career progression, and unequal pay where women are paid less than men are for performing the same job.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Stein, A.I.|year=2009|title=Women Lawyers Blog for Workplace Equality: Blogging as a Feminist Legal Method|journal=Yale Journal of Law and Feminism|volume=20|issue=2|pages=357–408|url=http://digitalcommons.law.yale.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1287&amp;context=yjlf}}&lt;/ref&gt; When taking the median earnings of men and women who worked full-time, year-round, government data from 2014 showed that women made $0.79 for every dollar a man earned. The average earnings for working mothers came out to even less—$0.71 for every dollar a father made, according to a 2014 study conducted by the National Partnership for Women and Children. While much of the public discussion of the "[[Gender pay gap|wage gap]]" has focused around women getting equal pay for the same work as their male peers, many women struggle with what is called the "pregnancy penalty". The main problem is that it is difficult to measure, but some experts say that the possibility of having a baby can be enough for employers to push women back from their line.&lt;ref name=NBC&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nbcnews.com/business/careers/motherhood-penalty-can-affect-women-who-never-even-have-child-n548511|title='Motherhood Penalty' Can Affect Women Who Never Even Have a Child|work=NBC News|date=April 11, 2016|author=Safia Samee Ali}}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, women are put in a position where they need to make the decision of whether to maintain in the workforce or have children. This problem has sparked the debate over maternity leave in the United States. 

However, despite the struggle for equal pay in the United States, the tech industry{{clarify|date=June 2017}} has made progress in helping to encourage equal pay across gender. In March 2016, tech career website Dice released a study of more than 16,000 tech professionals that found that when you compare equivalent education, experience and position, there is no pay gap—and hasn't been for the last six years.&lt;ref name=NBC/&gt; This new industry is paving a way for other companies to do the same. However, this industry also struggles to employ women in executive positions. This is partially due to the barrier of sexual harassment and pregnancy that was aforementioned. 

Such barriers make it difficult for women to advance in their workplace or receive fair compensation for the work they provide.

== Measurement ==
Women empowerment can be measured through the [[Gender Empowerment Measure]] (GEM), which shows women's participation in a given nation, both politically and economically. GEM is calculated by tracking "the share of seats in [[parliament]] held by women; of female legislators, senior officials and managers; and of female profession and technical workers; and the [[gender disparity]] in earned income, reflecting economic independence".&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009"/&gt; It then ranks countries given this information. Other measures that take into account the importance of female participation and equality include: the [[Gender Parity Index]] and the [[Gender-related Development Index]] (GDI).&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009"/&gt;

== Importance of women in societies ==
Entire nations, businesses, communities and groups can benefit from the implementation of programs and policies that adopt the notion of women empowerment.&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009"&gt;{{cite web|editor1=Deneulin, Séverine|editor2=Lila Shahani|year=2009|title=An Introduction to the Human Development and Capability Approach: Freedom and Agency|location=Sterling, VA|publisher=Earthscan|url=https://idl-bnc.idrc.ca/dspace/bitstream/10625/40248/1/IDL-40248.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Empowerment]] is one of the main procedural concerns when addressing [[human rights and development]]. [[Capability approach|The Human Development and Capabilities Approach]], the [[Millennium Development Goals]], and other credible approaches/goals point to empowerment and participation as a necessary step if a country is to overcome the obstacles associated with poverty and development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=U.N. General Assembly, 55th Session leke berrand fezer|title=United Nations Millennium Declaration|id=(A/55/L.2)|date=8 September 2000|url=https://www.un.org/millennium/declaration/ares552e.pdf|accessdate=January 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Women empowerment in Nigeria]]
* [[Women's rights]]
* [[Women in the workforce]]

== Sources ==
{{Free-content attribution
| title = Cracking the code: girls' and women's education in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM)
| author = 
| publisher = UNESCO
| page numbers = 11
| source = 
| documentURL = http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0025/002534/253479e.pdf
| license statement URL = http://www.unesco.org/ulis/cgi-bin/ulis.pl?catno=253479&amp;set=0059EF62AE_2_373&amp;gp=1&amp;lin=1&amp;ll=1
| license = 
}}{{Free-content attribution
| title = Mobile phones and literacy: Empowerment in Women's Hands; A Cross-Case Analysis of Nine Experiences
| author = UNESCO
| publisher = UNESCO
| page numbers = 33
| source = UNESCO
| documentURL = http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0023/002343/234325E.pdf
| license statement URL = http://www.unesco.org/ulis/cgi-bin/ulis.pl?catno=234325&amp;set=0058F07C09_0_256&amp;gp=1&amp;lin=1&amp;ll=1
| license = CC-BY-SA IGO 3.0
}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}
== Further reading ==
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Heldman | first1 = Caroline | last2 = Frankel | first2 = Laura Lazarus | last3 = Holmes | first3 = Jennifer |title = “Hot, black leather, whip” The (de)evolution of female protagonists in action cinema, 1960–2014 | journal = [[Sexualization, Media, and Society]] | volume = 2 | issue = 2 | publisher = [[Sage Publications|Sage]] | doi = 10.1177/2374623815627789 | date = April–June 2016 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/2374623815627789 | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [http://sme.sagepub.com/content/2/2/2374623815627789.full.pdf+html Pdf]. (Includes a section titled "The Empowerment Question").
* [https://successfullady.in/traditional-functions-role-of-women/ Traditional functions of the family and the role of women]
* [https://nbook.in/women-participation-in-real-estate-industry/ Women Participation in Real Estate Industry]


[[Category:Women's studies]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]
[[Category:Human rights concepts]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender identity-based cultures]]
[[Category:Law]]
[[Category:Egalitarianism]]
[[Category:Empowerment|*]]
[[Category:Women's empowerment|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>