<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191124045632|927694742" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="47849771" pageid="47849771" ns="0" title="Women&#039;s empowerment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-24T04:57:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{essay-like|date=July 2017}}
{{Feminism sidebar}}
[[File:MichelleObamaLetGirlsLearnCambodiaMar2015.jpg|thumb|Former First Lady [[Michelle Obama]] greets students during a Room to Read event with First Lady [[Bun Rany]] of [[Cambodia]] in support of the Let Girls Learn initiative, at Hun Sen Prasat Bakong High School in [[Siem Reap]], Cambodia, March 21, 2015.]]

'''Women's empowerment''' is the way or a social action in which women elaborate and recreate what it is to be in a circumstance that they previously were denied.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;Kabeer, Naila. "Gender equality and women's empowerment: A critical analysis o the third millennium development goal 1." ''Gender &amp; Development'' 13.1 (2005): 13-24.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":62"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Mosedale|first=Sarah|date=2005-03-01|title=Assessing women's empowerment: towards a conceptual framework|journal=Journal of International Development|language=en|volume=17|issue=2|pages=243–257|doi=10.1002/jid.1212|issn=1099-1328}}&lt;/ref&gt; Empowerment can be defined in many ways, however, when talking about women's empowerment, empowerment means accepting and allowing people (women) who are on the outside of the decision-making process into it. “This puts a strong emphasis on participation in political structures and formal decision-making and, in the economic sphere, on the ability to obtain an income that enables participation in economic decision-making.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rahman|first1=Aminur|date=2013|title=Women's Empowerment: Concept and Beyond|url=https://globaljournals.org/GJHSS_Volume13/2-Womens-Empowerment-Concept.pdf|journal=Global Journal of Human Social Science Sociology &amp; Culture|volume=13|issue=6|pages=9|accessdate=11 December 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170810094216/https://globaljournals.org/GJHSS_Volume13/2-Womens-Empowerment-Concept.pdf|archive-date=10 August 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Empowerment is the process that creates power in individuals over their own lives, society, and in their communities. People are empowered when they are able to access the opportunities available to them without limitations and restrictions such as in education, profession and lifestyle. Feeling entitled to make your own decisions creates a sense of empowerment. Empowerment includes the action of raising the status of women through education, raising awareness, literacy, and training. Women's empowerment is all about equipping and allowing women to make life-determining decisions through the different problems in society.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bayeh|first1=Endalcachew|date=January 2016|title=The role of empowering women and achieving gender equality to the sustainable development of Ethiopia|url=https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2405883116300508#!|journal=Pacific Science Review B: Humanities and Social Sciences|volume=2|issue=1|pages=38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alternatively, it is the process for women to redefine gender roles that allows for them to acquire the ability to choose between known alternatives whom have otherwise been restricted from such an ability.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; There are several principles defining women's empowerment such as, for one to be empowered, they must come from a position of disempowerment. Furthermore, one must acquire empowerment themselves rather than have it given to them by an external party. Other studies have found that empowerment definitions entail people having the capability to make important decisions in their lives while also being able to act on them. Lastly, empowerment and disempowerment is relative to other at a previous time; therefore, empowerment is a process, not a product.&lt;ref name=":62" /&gt;

Women empowerment has become a significant topic of discussion in [[Human development (humanity)|development]] and [[economics]]. It can also point to the approaches regarding other trivialized [[gender]]s in a particular political or social context.

Women's [[economic empowerment]] refers to the ability for women to enjoy their right to control and benefit from the 
resources, [[asset]]s, [[income]] and their own time, as well as the ability to [[Risk management|manage risk]] and improve their economic status and well being.&lt;ref name="Women's Economic Empowerment Conceptual Framework"&gt;Oxfam (Forthcoming), "Women's Economic Empowerment Conceptual Framework"&lt;/ref&gt;

While often interchangeably used, the more comprehensive concept of [[gender empowerment]] refers to people of any gender, stressing the [[Sex and gender distinction|distinction]] between biological  and [[Gender role|gender as a role]].

[[File:Shinzō Abe and Ivanka Trump (4).jpg|thumb|upright|Advisor to [[US President]] and businesswoman [[Ivanka Trump]] (right) and [[Japanese Prime Minister|Japanese PM]] [[Shinzo Abe]] attending the World Assembly for Women in [[Tokyo]] to speak on women's rights and empowerment, 2017]]

Entire nations, businesses, communities and groups can benefit from the implementation of programs and policies that adopt the notion of women empowerment.&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://idl-bnc.idrc.ca/dspace/bitstream/10625/40248/1/IDL-40248.pdf|title=An Introduction to the Human Development and Capability Approach: Freedom and Agency|year=2009|editor2=Lila Shahani|publisher=Earthscan|location=Sterling, VA|editor1=Deneulin, Séverine|access-date=2016-09-01|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160616162955/http://idl-bnc.idrc.ca/dspace/bitstream/10625/40248/1/IDL-40248.pdf|archive-date=2016-06-16|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Empowerment of women is a necessity for the very development of a society, since it enhances both the quality and the quantity of human resources available for development.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gupta|first=Kamla|last2=Yesudian|first2=P. Princy|date=2006|title=Evidence of women's empowerment in India: a study of socio-spatial disparities|url=|journal=GeoJournal|volume=65|issue=4|pages=365–380|doi=10.1007/s10708-006-7556-z}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Empowerment]] is one of the main procedural concerns when addressing [[human rights and development]].

Women's empowerment and achieving gender equality is essential for our society to ensure the '''[[sustainable development]]''' of the country. Many world leaders and scholars have argued that sustainable development is impossible without gender equality and women's empowerment.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Sustainable development accepts environmental protection, social and economic development,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Shah |first1=M.M |title=Sustainable Development |url=https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/earth-and-planetary-sciences/sustainable-development |website=Science Direct |publisher=Encyclopedia of Ecology }}&lt;/ref&gt; and without women's empowerment, women wouldn't feel equally important to the process of development as men. It is widely believed that, the full participation of both men and women is critical for development. Only acknowledging men's participation will not be beneficial to sustainable development. In the context of women and development, empowerment must include more choices for women to make on their own.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Mehra|first1=Rekha|date=November 1997|title=Women, Empowerment, and Economic Development|journal=The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science|volume=554|issue=1|pages=136–149|doi=10.1177/0002716297554001009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Without gender equality and empowerment, the country could not be just, and social change wouldn't occur. Therefore, scholars agree that women's empowerment plays a huge role in development and is one of the significant contributions of development. Without the equal inclusion of women in development, women would not be able to benefit or contribute to the development of the country.

== Methods ==
Scholars have identified two forms of empowerment, economic empowerment and political empowerment.&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;Kabeer, Naila. "Contextualising the Economic Pathways of Women's Empowerment: Findings from a Multi-Country Research Programme." (2011).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":10"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.undp.org/content/undp/en/home/librarypage/democratic-governance/inclusive-political-institutions/regional-organizations--gender-equality-and-the-political-empowe.html|title=Regional Organizations, Gender Equality and the Political Empowerment of Women|website=UNDP|language=en|access-date=2018-04-08|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180413044318/http://www.undp.org/content/undp/en/home/librarypage/democratic-governance/inclusive-political-institutions/regional-organizations--gender-equality-and-the-political-empowe.html|archive-date=2018-04-13|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Economic empowerment ===
Economic empowerment increases women's agency, access to formal government programs, mobility outside the home, economic independence, and purchasing power. Policy makers are suggested to support job training to aid in entrance in the formal markets.&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt; One recommendation is to provide more formal education opportunities for women that would allow for higher bargaining power in the home. They would have more access to higher wages outside the home; and as a result, make it easier for women to get a job in the market.&lt;ref name=":82"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Duflo|first=Esther|date=2012|title=Women Empowerment and Economic Development|jstor=23644911|journal=Journal of Economic Literature|volume=50|issue=4|pages=1051–1079|doi=10.1257/jel.50.4.1051|url=https://dspace.mit.edu/bitstream/1721.1/82663/2/Duflo_Women%20Empowerment.pd|hdl=1721.1/82663}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Strengthening women's access to property inheritance and land rights is another method used to economically empower women. This would allow them better means of asset accumulation, capital, and [[bargaining power]] needed to address [[gender inequalities]]. Often, women in developing and underdeveloped countries are legally restricted from their land on the sole basis of gender.&lt;ref name=":82" /&gt; Having a right to their land gives women a sort of bargaining power that they wouldn't normally have; in turn, they gain more opportunities for economic independence and formal financial institutions.

Race has a huge impact on women's empowerment in areas such as employment. Employment can help create empowerment for women. Many scholars suggest that when we discuss women's empowerment, discussing the different barriers that underprivileged women face, which makes it more difficult for them to obtain empowerment in society, is important when examining the impact of race in connection to employment. Significantly examining how opportunities are structured by gender, race, and class can transpire social change. Work opportunities and the work environment can create empowerment for women. Empowerment in the workplace can positively affect job satisfaction and performance, having equality in the work place can greatly increase the sense of empowerment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Carr |first1=Gloria |title=Empowerment: A Framework to Develop Advocacy in African American Grandmothers Providing Care for Their Grandchildren |journal=ISRN Nursing |date=February 2011 |volume=2011 |pages=531717 |pmc=3169837 |pmid=21994894 |doi=10.5402/2011/531717 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, women of color do not have the same accessibility and privileges in work settings. They(Women of color) are faced with more disadvantages in the work place. Patricia Parker argues that African American women's empowerment is their resistance to control, standing up for themselves and not conforming to societal norms and expectations. In connection to power, feminist perspectives look at empowerment as a form of resistance within systems of unequal power relations. Within the societal setting of race, gender, and class politics, African American women's empowerment in work environment “can be seen as resistance to attempts to fix meanings of appropriate identity and behavior, where such meanings are interpreted as controlling, exploitative, and other- wise oppressive to African American women.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Parker |first1=Patricia |title=Control, Resistance, and Empowerment in Raced, Gendered, and Classed Work Contexts: The Case of African American Women |journal=Annals of the International Communication Association |date=2003 |volume=27 |issue=1 |pages=257–291 |doi=10.1080/23808985.2003.11679028 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When talking about women's empowerment, many scholars suggest examining the social injustices on women in everyday organizational life that are influenced by race, class, and gender.

Another popular methodology for women's economic empowerment also includes [[microcredit]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated22"&gt;{{cite report|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/public/WorldSurvey2009.pdf|title=Women's Control over Economic Resources and Access to Financial Resources, including Microfinance|publisher=United Nations|location=New York|section=World Survey on the Role of Women In Development|year=2009|access-date=2017-06-29|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170829064329/http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/public/WorldSurvey2009.pdf|archivedate=2017-08-29|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Microfinance institutions aim to empower women in their community by giving them access to loans that have low interest rates without the requirement of collateral.&lt;ref name=":9"&gt;Geleta, Esayas Bekele. "Microfinance and the politics of empowerment: a critical cultural perspective." ''Journal of Asian and African Studies'' 49.4 (2014): 413-425.&lt;/ref&gt; More specifically, they(microfinance institutions) aim to give microcredit to women who want to be entrepreneurs.&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt; The success and efficiency of microcredit and microloans is controversial and constantly debated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Parmar, A.|year=2003|title=Microcredit, Empowerment, and Agency: Re-evaluating the Discourse|journal=Canadian Journal of Development Studies|volume=24|issue=3|pages=461–76|doi=10.1080/02255189.2003.9668932}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some critiques claim that microcredit alone doesn't guarantee women have control over the way the loan is used. Microfinance institutions don't address cultural barriers that allow men to still control household finances; as a result, microcredit may simply be transferred to the husband. Microcredit doesn't relieve women of household obligations, and even if women have credit, they don't have the time to be as active in the market as men.&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":11"&gt;Ellis, Amanda. ''Gender and economic growth in Kenya: Unleashing the power of women''. World Bank Publications, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Political empowerment ===
Political empowerment supports creating policies that would best support gender equality and agency for women in both the public and private spheres. Popular methods that have been suggested are to create affirmative action policies that have a quota for the number of women in policy making and parliament positions.&lt;ref name=":82" /&gt; As of 2017, the global average of women whom hold lower and single house parliament positions is 23.6 percent.&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt; Further recommendations have been to increase women's rights to [[vote]], voice opinions, and the ability to run for office with a fair chance of being elected.&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009" /&gt; Because women are typically associated with child care and domestic responsibilities in the home, they have less time dedicated to entering the labour market and running their business. Policies that increase their [[bargaining power]] in the household would include policies that account for cases of divorce, policies for better welfare for women, and policies that give women control over resources (such as property rights).&lt;ref name=":82" /&gt; However, participation is not limited to the realm of politics. It can include participation in the [[household]], in schools, and the ability to make choices for oneself. Some theorists believe that bargaining power and agency in the household must  be achieved before one can move onto broader political participation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Women and Human Development: The Capabilities to Approach|author=Nussbaum, Martha C.|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2000|isbn=9781139459358|location=Cambridge, UK|pages=1–33|chapter=Introduction}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Measurements And Assessment''==
Women empowerment can be measured through the [[Gender Empowerment Measure]] (GEM), which shows women's participation in a given nation, both politically and economically. GEM is calculated by tracking "the share of seats in [[parliament]] held by women; of female legislators, senior officials and managers; and of female profession and technical workers; and the [[gender disparity]] in earned income, reflecting economic independence".&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009" /&gt; It then ranks countries given this information. Other measures that take into account the importance of female participation and equality include: the [[Gender Parity Index]] or the [[Gender-related Development Index]] (GDI).&lt;ref name="Deneulin, Séverine 2009" /&gt;

Some critiques of GEM is that it is not concerned with factors regarding society, such as gender, religion, cultural context, legal context, and violations of women's rights.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;Charmes, Jacques, and Saskia Wieringa. "Measuring women's empowerment: an assessment of the gender-related development index and the gender empowerment measure." ''Journal of Human Development'' 4.3 (2003): 419-435.&lt;/ref&gt; Gender empowerment measure attempts to makes a consistent standardized approach to measure women's empowerment; in doing so, it has been critiqued that the GEM doesn't account for variation in historical factors, female autonomy, gender segregation, and women's right to vote.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Pillarisetti|first=J.|last2=McGillivray|first2=Mark|date=1998-06-01|title=Human Development and Gender Empowerment: Methodological and Measurement Issues|journal=Development Policy Review|language=en|volume=16|issue=2|pages=197–203|doi=10.1111/1467-7679.00059|issn=1467-7679}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Gender-related Development Index (GDI) is a way in which the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) measures the inequality between genders within a country. Some critique of this measurement is that, because GDI calculations rely solely on the achievement distribution between males and females of a population, GDI doesn't measure gender inequality; rather, it measures absolute levels on income, education and health.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;

A more qualitative form of assessing women's empowerment is to identify constraints to action. This allows for the identification of power relations between genders. Because this is a participatory process, it facilitates conversation on gender discrimination.&lt;ref name=":62"/&gt; Comparing constraints on women at a later time also allows for any changes or expansion to be better identified. The evaluation of the development of women's agency allows for an evaluation of actions taken. These assessments must also be based on the action taken by women, and not external groups. External groups can help facilitate women's empowerment, but cannot bestow it on them.&lt;ref name=":62" /&gt;

== Barriers ==

Many of the barriers to women's empowerment and equity lie ingrained in cultural norms. Many women feel these pressures, while others have become accustomed to being treated inferior to men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Women, Culture, and Development: A Study of Human Capabilities|author=Nussbaum, Martha C.|publisher=Clarendon Press|year=1995|isbn=9780198289647|editor1=Martha C. Nussbaum|location=Oxford|pages=1–15|chapter=Introduction|editor2=Jonathan Glover|lastauthoramp=y}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even if [[legislators]], [[NGOs]], etc. are aware of the benefits women's empowerment and participation can have, many are scared of disrupting the status of the women and continue to let [[societal norms]] get in the way of development.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"&gt;{{cite report|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/public/WorldSurvey2009.pdf|title=Women's Control over Economic Resources and Access to Financial Resources, including Microfinance|publisher=United Nations|location=New York|section=World Survey on the Role of Women In Development|year=2009|access-date=2017-06-29|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170829064329/http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/public/WorldSurvey2009.pdf|archivedate=2017-08-29|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research shows that the increasing access to the internet can also result in an increased exploitation of women.&lt;ref name="Sutton, J. 2000" /&gt; Releasing personal information on websites has put some women's personal safety at risk. In 2010, Working to Halt Online Abuse stated that 73% of women were victimized through such sites. Types of victimization include [[cyber stalking]], harassment, [[online pornography]], and [[flaming (Internet)|flaming]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Morahan-Martin, J.|year=2000|title=Women and the Internet: Promise and Perils|journal=Cyber Psychology &amp; Behavior|volume=3|issue=5|pages=683–691|doi=10.1089/10949310050191683}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sexual harassment]] in particular is a large barrier for women in the workplace. It appears in almost all industries, but is most notable in the following: business, trade, banking and finance, sales and marketing, hospitality, civil service, and education, lecturing and teaching.&lt;ref name="Statistics"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aware.org.sg/training/wsh-site/14-statistics/|title=Statistics|date=22 April 2010|work=AWARE RSS|publisher=AWARE|accessdate=19 May 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160513181143/http://www.aware.org.sg/training/wsh-site/14-statistics|archive-date=13 May 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the International Labour Organisation (ILO), sexual harassment is a clear form of gender discrimination based on sex, a manifestation of unequal power relations between men and women. Furthermore, the UN Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women (CEDAW) is urging for increased measures of protection for women against sexual harassment and violence in the workplace. 54% (272) had experienced some form of workplace sexual harassment. 79% of the victims are women; 21% were men.&lt;ref name="Statistics" /&gt;

Recent studies also show that women face more barriers in the workplace than do men. Gender-related barriers involve sexual harassment, unfair hiring practices, career progression, and unequal pay where women are paid less than men are for performing the same job.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Stein, A.I.|year=2009|title=Women Lawyers Blog for Workplace Equality: Blogging as a Feminist Legal Method|url=http://digitalcommons.law.yale.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1287&amp;context=yjlf|journal=Yale Journal of Law and Feminism|volume=20|issue=2|pages=357–408|access-date=2016-06-22|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160820031953/http://digitalcommons.law.yale.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1287&amp;context=yjlf|archive-date=2016-08-20|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; When taking the median earnings of men and women who worked full-time, year-round, government data from 2014 showed that women made $0.79 for every dollar a man earned. The average earnings for working mothers came out to even less—$0.71 for every dollar a father made, according to a 2014 study conducted by the National Partnership for Women and Children. While much of the public discussion of the "[[Gender pay gap|wage gap]]" has focused around women getting equal pay for the same work as their male peers, many women struggle with what is called the "pregnancy penalty". The main problem is that it is difficult to measure, but some experts say that the possibility of having a baby can be enough for employers to push women back from their line.&lt;ref name="NBC"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nbcnews.com/business/careers/motherhood-penalty-can-affect-women-who-never-even-have-child-n548511|title='Motherhood Penalty' Can Affect Women Who Never Even Have a Child|author=Safia Samee Ali|date=April 11, 2016|work=NBC News|access-date=June 22, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160620121244/https://www.nbcnews.com/business/careers/motherhood-penalty-can-affect-women-who-never-even-have-child-n548511|archive-date=June 20, 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, women are put in a position where they need to make the decision of whether to maintain in the workforce or have children. This problem has sparked the debate over maternity leave in the United States and many other countries in the world.

However, despite the struggle for equal pay in the Nepal, the tech industry{{clarify|date=June 2017}} has made progress in helping to encourage equal pay across gender. In March 2016, tech career website Dice released a study of more than 16,000 tech professionals that found that when you compare equivalent education, experience and position, there is no pay gap—and hasn't been for the last six years.&lt;ref name="NBC" /&gt; This new industry is paving a way for other companies to do the same. However, this industry also struggles to employ women in executive positions. This is partially due to the barrier of sexual harassment and pregnancy that was aforementioned.

Such barriers make it difficult for women to advance in their workplace or receive fair compensation for the work they provide.

== Role of education ==
It is said that education increases "people's self-confidence and also enables them to find better jobs and they can work shoulder to shoulder with men".{{fact|date=April 2019}} They engage in public debate and make demands on government for health care, social security and other entitlements".&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;UNDP. 2013. Human Development Report. The Rise of the South. Human Progress in a Diverse World; New York, UNDP.&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, education empowers women to make choices that improve their children's health, their well-being, and chances of survival.&lt;ref&gt;UNESCO. 2014. EFA Global Monitoring Report 2013/2014: Teaching and Learning, Paris, UNESCO.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Education informs others of preventing and containing the disease, and it is an essential element of efforts to reduce malnutrition. Furthermore, it empowers women to make choices that can improve their welfare, including marrying beyond childhood and having fewer children. Crucially, education can increase women's awareness of their rights, boost their self-esteem, and provide them the opportunity to assert their rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0023/002343/234325E.pdf|title=Mobile phones and literacy: Empowerment in Women's Hands; A Cross-Case Analysis of Nine Experiences|last=UNESCO|publisher=UNESCO|year=2015|isbn=978-92-3-100123-9|location=33|access-date=2017-05-10|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170517175749/http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0023/002343/234325E.pdf|archive-date=2017-05-17|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite significant improvements in recent decades, education is not universally available and gender inequalities persist. A major concern in many countries is not only the limited numbers of girls going to school but also the limited educational pathways for those that step into the classroom. More specifically, there should be more efforts to address the lower participation and learning achievement of [[Female education in STEM|girls in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) education]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Cracking the code: girls' and women's education in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM)|last=|first=|publisher=UNESCO|year=2017|isbn=9789231002335|location=Paris|pages=11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Internet use to Empower Women==

The growing access of the web in the late 20th century has allowed women to empower themselves by using various tools on the Internet. With the introduction of the [[World Wide Web]], women have begun to use social networking sites like [[Facebook]] and [[Twitter]] for [[online activism]].&lt;ref name="Sutton, J. 2000"&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Sutton, J.|author2=Pollock, S.|lastauthoramp=y|year=2000|title=Online Activism for Women's Rights|journal=Cyber Psychology &amp; Behavior|volume=3|issue=5|pages=699–706|doi=10.1089/10949310050191700}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through online activism, women are able to empower themselves by organizing campaigns and voicing their opinions for equality rights without feeling oppressed by members of society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Churchyard, N.|year=2009|title=The Question of Empowerment: Women's Perspective on Their Internet Use|journal=[[Gender, Technology and Development]]|volume=13|issue=3|pages=341–363|doi=10.1177/097185241001300302}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, on May 29, 2013, an online campaign started by 100 female advocates forced the leading social networking website, Facebook, to take down various pages that spread hatred about women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=McVeigh, T.|date=June 6, 2013|title=Online Feminist activists of the digital age|work=Taipei Times|url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/editorials/archives/2013/06/06/2003564076|access-date=September 17, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924123622/http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/editorials/archives/2013/06/06/2003564076|archive-date=September 24, 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, [[blogging]] has also become a powerful tool for the educational empowerment of women. According to a study done by the University of California, Los Angeles, medical patients who read and write about their disease are often in a much happier mood and more knowledgeable than those who do not.&lt;ref name="breastcancer.about.com"&gt;{{cite journal|author=Stephan, P.|date=August 13, 2013|title=Breast cancer patients blog their blues away|url=http://breastcancer.about.com/b/2013/08/13/blog-the-blues-away.htm|journal=Breastcancer.about.com|access-date=September 17, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130816030742/http://breastcancer.about.com/b/2013/08/13/blog-the-blues-away.htm|archive-date=August 16, 2013|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; By reading others' experiences, patients can better educate themselves and apply strategies that their fellow bloggers suggest.&lt;ref name="breastcancer.about.com"/&gt;

With the easy accessibility and affordability of [[e-learning]] (electronic learning), women can now study from the comfort of their homes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Radovic-Markovic, M.|author2=Nelson-Porter, B.|author3=Omolaja, M.|lastauthoramp=y|year=2012|title=The new alternative women's entrepreneurship education: E-learning and virtual universities|journal=International Women Online Journal of Distance Education|volume=1|issue=2|pages=46–54|url=http://wojde.org/FileUpload/bs295854/File/06a.markovic.pdf|issn=2147-0367|access-date=2015-09-17|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305002329/http://wojde.org/FileUpload/bs295854/File/06a.markovic.pdf|archive-date=2016-03-05|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; By empowering themselves educationally through new technologies like e-learning, women are also learning new skills that will come in handy in today's advancing globalized world.

Oftentimes, the internet is very useful as source of empowerment for women through its creation, dispersion, and utilization of hashtags on social media. One prime example of hashtags supporting women empowerment was in 2017 when the #AintNoCinderella hashtag came into existence. This hashtag spread like wildfire on social media after Varnika Kundu (a 29-year-old woman in India) was driving home past midnight on August 4 when she was followed and harassed by two men in a SUV.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/40872788|title=Why Indian women are no Cinderellas|last=Pandey|first=Geeta|date=2017-08-09|access-date=2019-02-15|language=en-GB|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190116211606/https://www.bbc.com/news/40872788|archive-date=2019-01-16|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kundu was blamed for being out late at night, particularly by the BJP government Vice-President Ramveer Bhatti. This led to women all across India and the world posting pictures of themselves out late at night with the hashtag "#AintNoCinderella" to show that women do not have a particular curfew to which they have to adhere to (like Cinderella did).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.thenewsminute.com/article/ain-t-no-cinderella-women-hit-out-bjp-leader-blaming-chandigarh-stalking-victim-66456|title=Ain't no Cinderella: Women hit out at BJP leader for blaming Chandigarh stalking victim|date=2017-08-08|work=The News Minute|access-date=2018-10-01|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190331073123/https://www.thenewsminute.com/article/ain-t-no-cinderella-women-hit-out-bjp-leader-blaming-chandigarh-stalking-victim-66456|archive-date=2019-03-31|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Ongoing projects ==
The UN came out with a set of goals called the Sustainable Development Goals, or SDGs, to help make the world a better place.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/sustainable-development-goals/|title=Sustainable development goals - United Nations|work=United Nations Sustainable Development|access-date=2018-03-14|language=en-US|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180313165859/http://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/sustainable-development-goals/|archive-date=2018-03-13|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 17, the fourth goal works to allow access to education for all people alike. A large effort has been made to include women in schools to better their education.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/education/|title=Education - United Nations Sustainable Development|work=United Nations Sustainable Development|access-date=2018-03-14|language=en-US|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180314214606/http://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/education/|archive-date=2018-03-14|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the fifth goal focuses on empowering women and girls to achieve gender equality through equal access to various types of opportunities (health care, education, work, etc.).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/gender-equality/|title=United Nations: Gender equality and women's empowerment|work=United Nations Sustainable Development|access-date=2018-03-14|language=en-US|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180314214620/http://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/gender-equality/|archive-date=2018-03-14|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are also some prominent non-profits that help empower women:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://thepowerofpurpose.com/10-amazing-nonprofits-empowering-women-2017/|title=10 Amazing Nonprofits Empowering Women in 2017 - The Power of Purpose|date=2017-01-26|work=The Power of Purpose|access-date=2018-03-29|language=en-US|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180425184401/https://thepowerofpurpose.com/10-amazing-nonprofits-empowering-women-2017/|archive-date=2018-04-25|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[http://www.sheshouldrun.org/ She Should Run]
*[https://www.girlsnotbrides.org/ Girls Not Brides]
*[https://www.malala.org/ The Malala Fund]
*[https://widsandiego.org/ Women in Defense]
*[https://www.womenforwomen.org/ Women for Women International]
*[https://www.everymothercounts.org/ Every Mother Counts]

=== U.S. involvement ===
[[File:First Lady Melania Trump and Under Secretary Shannon Pose for a Photo With the 2017 International Women of Courage Awardees (33338548780).jpg|thumb|[[Melania Trump]] with 2017 [[International Women of Courage Award]]ees]]
Domestically, the U.S. empowered women through passings of laws such as allowing women to vote in 1920, banning discrimination based on gender in 1964, banning discrimination against pregnant women in 1978, etc. Additionally, the inclusion of women in politics allowed for more gender equality. The first female speaker of House, the First Lady to run for president, and first women to serve on the Supreme Court were monumental events that proved socially the acceptance of "subservient" women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nwhp.org/resources/womens-rights-movement/detailed-timeline/|title=Detailed Timeline {{!}} National Women's History Project|website=www.nwhp.org|language=en-US|access-date=2018-04-28|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180428051752/http://www.nwhp.org/resources/womens-rights-movement/detailed-timeline/|archive-date=2018-04-28|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. provides foreign aid to third world countries in various forms, one of which is by providing education programs. There are currently bills in Congress that work to ensure education to girls, one of which is the Protecting Girls' Access to Education Act. These are enacted with the belief that proper education will pull them out of poverty and reduce exploitation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.congress.gov/bill/115th-congress/house-bill/2408|title=H.R.2408 - 115th Congress (2017-2018): Protecting Girls' Access to Education Act|last=Steve|first=Chabot|date=2017-10-04|website=www.congress.gov|language=en|access-date=2018-03-14|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180413082955/https://www.congress.gov/bill/115th-congress/house-bill/2408|archive-date=2018-04-13|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another action taken on by the U.S is the [[President's Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief|PEPFAR]] program, initiated by the Bush administration in 2003. The U.S. spent more than $1.4 billion in funding sub-Saharan Africa during the duration of the program. This program was taken into effect in response to the global HIV/AIDS crisis, and it promoted abstinence among young girls and women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Cohen|first=Jon|date=June 15, 2007|title=Bush Boosts AIDS Relief: Cause for Applause and Pause|jstor=20036459|journal=Science|volume=316|issue=5831|pages=1552|pmid=17569832|doi=10.1126/science.316.5831.1552}}&lt;/ref&gt; There was a partnership with DREAMS, and its main purpose with PEPFAR was to allow both girls and women to develop into Determined, Resilient, Empowered, AIDS-free, Mentored, and Safe women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pepfar.gov/partnerships/ppp/dreams/|title=Working Together for an AIDS-Free Future for Girls and Women|website=www.pepfar.gov|language=en-US|access-date=2018-05-04|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180505070203/https://www.pepfar.gov/partnerships/ppp/dreams/|archive-date=2018-05-05|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, there are criticisms that this program did not really do much to reduce HIV risk behavior, and critics such as John Dietrich worried that the context of aid enforced Western beliefs of choosing abstinence before marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bendavid|first=Eran|display-authors=etal|date=May 2016|title=Abstinence Funding Was Not Associated With Reductions In HIV Risk Behavior In Sub-Saharan Africa|url=|journal=Health Affairs|volume=35|pages=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2016/05/03/476601108/u-s-spent-1-4-billion-to-stop-hiv-by-promoting-abstinence-did-it-work|title=U.S. Spent $1.4 Billion To Stop HIV By Promoting Abstinence. Did It Work?|work=NPR.org|access-date=2018-05-04|language=en|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180502222534/https://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2016/05/03/476601108/u-s-spent-1-4-billion-to-stop-hiv-by-promoting-abstinence-did-it-work|archive-date=2018-05-02|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; There was and still is controversy regarding the effectiveness of this program in reducing HIV/AIDS through advocating abstinence and whether this would actually empower women in Africa.

== See also ==
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Women empowerment in Nigeria]]
* [[Women's rights]]
* [[Women in the workforce]]

== Source==
*{{Free-content attribution
| title = Cracking the code: girls' and women's education in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM)
| author = 
| publisher = UNESCO
| page numbers = 11
| source = 
| documentURL = http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0025/002534/253479e.pdf
| license statement URL = http://www.unesco.org/ulis/cgi-bin/ulis.pl?catno=253479&amp;set=0059EF62AE_2_373&amp;gp=1&amp;lin=1&amp;ll=1
| license = 
}}

*{{Free-content attribution
| title = Mobile phones and literacy: Empowerment in Women's Hands; A Cross-Case Analysis of Nine Experiences
| author = UNESCO
| publisher = UNESCO
| page numbers = 33
| source = UNESCO
| documentURL = http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0023/002343/234325E.pdf
| license statement URL = http://www.unesco.org/ulis/cgi-bin/ulis.pl?catno=234325&amp;set=0058F07C09_0_256&amp;gp=1&amp;lin=1&amp;ll=1
| license = CC-BY-SA IGO 3.5
}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Heldman | first1 = Caroline | last2 = Frankel | first2 = Laura Lazarus | last3 = Holmes | first3 = Jennifer |title = "Hot, black leather, whip" The (de)evolution of female protagonists in action cinema, 1960–2014 | journal = [[Sexualization, Media, and Society]] | volume = 2 | issue = 2 | pages = 237462381562778 | doi = 10.1177/2374623815627789 | date = April–June 2016 | ref = harv }} [http://sme.sagepub.com/content/2/2/2374623815627789.full.pdf+html Pdf]. (Includes a section titled "The Empowerment Question").
* [https://successfullady.in/traditional-functions-role-of-women/ Traditional functions of the family and the role of women]
* [https://medium.com/@womenzeditor/women-participation-in-real-estate-industry-9e44bd056721/ Women Participation in Real Estate Industry]
* [https://www.masalascoop.com/2018/01/girl-empowerment-quotes.html Girl Empowerment Quotes]

[[Category:Human rights concepts]]
[[Category:Women's empowerment|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>