<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171124211952|811929649" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="748253" pageid="748253" ns="0" title="Third-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-24T21:21:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve"> {{Feminism sidebar |history}}
'''Third-wave feminism'''  is generally marked as having emerged in the early 1990s in the United States&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Evans|first=Elizabeth|year=2015|title=The Politics of Third Wave Feminisms: Neoliberalism, Intersectionality, and the State in Britain and the US|location=London|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|at=22|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; and continued until the [[fourth-wave feminism|fourth wave]] began around 2011–2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Nicola|last=Rivers|title=Postfeminism(s) and the Arrival of the Fourth Wave|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|year=2017|at=8|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Cochrane|first=Kira|authorlink=Kira Cochrane|title=The Fourth Wave of Feminism: Meet the Rebel Women|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/dec/10/fourth-wave-feminism-rebel-women|newspaper=The Guardian|date=10 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Born in the 1960s and 1970s as members of [[Generation X]], and grounded in the advances of [[second-wave feminism]], third-wave feminists embraced [[individualism]] and [[Diversity (politics)|diversity]] and sought to redefine what it meant to be a feminist.{{sfn|Evans|2015|loc=22}}&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.britannica.com/topic/feminism/The-third-wave-of-feminism#ref1228639 "The Third Wave of Feminism"], ''Encyclopaedia Britannica''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards"&gt;{{cite book |title=Manifesta: Young Women, Feminism, and the Future |last1=Baumgardner |first1=Jennifer |author1-link=Jennifer Baumgardner |last2=Richards |first2=Amy |author2-link=Amy Richards |year=2000 |publisher=[[Farrar, Straus and Giroux]] |location=New York |isbn=978-0-374-52622-1 |p=77|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to feminist scholar Elizabeth Evans, "[t]he confusion surrounding what constitutes third-wave feminism is in some respects its defining feature."{{sfn|Evans|2015|loc=49}}

The start of the third wave is traced to the early 1990s with the establishment of [[Riot grrrl]], the feminist punk movement, and [[Anita Hill]]'s televised testimony in 1991—to an all-male, all-white [[Senate Judiciary Committee]]—that [[Clarence Thomas Supreme Court nomination|Clarence Thomas]], [[Clarence Thomas Supreme Court nomination|nominated for the Supreme Court]], had [[Sexual harassment|sexually harassed]] her. The term ''third wave'' is credited to [[Rebecca Walker]], who responded to Thomas's appointment to the Supreme Court, despite Hill's testimony, with an article in ''[[Ms. Magazine]]'', "Becoming the Third Wave" (1992).&lt;ref name=Walker1992&gt;{{cite journal| last1 = Walker| first1 = Rebecca | authorlink1 = Rebecca Walker| editor-last=| editor-first =| editor-link=| title = Becoming the Third Wave| journal = [[Ms. (magazine)|Ms.]]| issue = | pages = 39–41| location = | issn = 0047-8318| oclc = 194419734|date= January 1992|url=http://www.msmagazine.com/spring2002/BecomingThirdWaveRebeccaWalker.pdf|format=pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Snyder2008&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Snyder|first=R. Claire|date=1 September 2008|title=What Is Third‐Wave Feminism? A New Directions Essay|url=http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/588436|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|volume=34|issue=1|pages=(175–196), 176|doi=10.1086/588436|jstor=10.1086/588436|issn=0097-9740|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; She wrote: 

{{quote|So I write this as a plea to all women, especially women of my generation: Let Thomas’ confirmation  serve to remind you, as it did me, that the fight is far from over. Let this dismissal of a woman's experience move you to anger. Turn that outrage into political power. Do not vote for them unless they work for us. Do not have sex with them, do not break bread with them, do not nurture them if they don't prioritize our freedom to control our bodies and our lives. I am not a post-feminism feminist. I am the Third Wave.&lt;ref name="Walker1992" /&gt;}}

Walker sought to establish that third-wave feminism was not just a reaction, but a movement in itself, because women's issues were far from over. The term ''[[intersectionality]]'' had been introduced in 1989—the idea that individuals may experience "layers of oppression", caused, for example, by gender, race and class—and it was during the third wave that the concept was embraced.{{sfn|Evans|2015|loc=19}} Third-wave feminists broadened their goals, focusing on abolishing gender-role stereotypes{{sfn|Snyder|2008|loc=176–177}} and expanding feminism to include women with diverse racial and cultural identities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hewitt|first1=Nancy|title=No Permanent Waves|publisher=Rutgers University Press|isbn=978-0-8135-4724-4|pages=99}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Tong"&gt;{{cite book |last=Tong |first=Rosemarie |title=Feminist Thought: A More Comprehensive Introduction |year=2009 |edition=Third |publisher=[[Westview Press]] |location=Boulder, Colorado |isbn=978-0-8133-4375-4 |oclc=156811918 |pages=284–285, 289}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History and emergence ==
{{seealso|Second-wave feminism}}
[[File:Rebeccawalker.jpg|thumb|[[Rebecca Walker]], 2003. The term ''third wave'' is accredited to Walker's 1992 article, "I Am the Third Wave".&lt;ref name=Walker1992/&gt;]]
The rights and programs gained by feminists of the second wave served as a foundation for the third wave. The gains included [[Title IX]]; public discussion about the abuse and rape or women; access to contraception and other reproductive services (including the legalization of abortion); the creation and enforcement of sexual-harassment policies for women in the workplace; the creation of domestic-abuse shelters for women and children; child-care services; educational funding for young women; and [[women's studies]] programs.

[[Riot grrrl]], the feminist punk movement that originated in the early 1990s, was thought by some to mark the beginning of third-wave feminism. This was a movement based on hard-core punk rock that talked about issues such as rape, patriarchy, sexuality, and female empowerment. 

Feminist leaders rooted in the second wave such as [[Gloria Anzaldúa]], [[bell hooks]], [[Cherríe Moraga]], [[Audre Lorde]], [[Maxine Hong Kingston]], and other feminists of color, sought to negotiate a space within feminist thought for consideration of race.&lt;ref name="Gillis" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Heywood"&gt;{{Cite book|editor-last=Heywood|editor-first=Leslie|editor2-last=Drake|editor2-first=Jennifer|title=Third Wave Agenda: Being Feminist, Doing Feminism|year=1997|publisher=[[University of Minnesota Press]]|location=[[Minneapolis]]|isbn=978-0-8166-3005-9|oclc=36876149}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cherríe Moraga]] and [[Gloria E. Anzaldúa]] had published the anthology ''[[This Bridge Called My Back]]'' (1981), which, along with ''All the Women Are White, All the Blacks Are Men, But Some of Us Are Brave: Black Women's Studies'' (1982), critiqued second-wave feminism, which they saw as focusing primarily on the problems of white women.&lt;!--Not sure what to do with this: This focus on the intersection between race and gender remained prominent through the Hill-Thomas hearings, but was seen to shift with the Freedom Ride 1992, the first project of the Walker-led Third Wave Direct Action Corporation. This drive to register voters in poor minority communities was surrounded with rhetoric that focused on rallying young women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | last=Hayes Taylor | first=Kimberly | title=Feminism reaches the next generation – Walker underscores need for inclusion, change in 'third wave' | newspaper=[[Star Tribune]] | date = 8 March 1995 | page=1B}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

[[File:Anita Hill at Harvard Law School Sep 2014.jpg|left|thumb|upright|[[Anita Hill]], 2014]]
In 1991 [[Anita Hill]] accused [[Clarence Thomas]], an African-American judge who had been nominated to the [[United States Supreme Court]], of [[sexual harassment]]. Thomas denied the accusations, calling them a "high-tech lynching". After extensive debate, the [[United States Senate]] voted 52–48 in favor of Thomas.&lt;ref name="Walker"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Walker|first=Rebecca|title=To Be Real: Telling the Truth and Changing the Face of Feminism|year=1995|publisher=Anchor Books|location=New York|isbn=978-0-385-47262-3|oclc=32274323}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Heywood" /&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Gillis|first=Stacy|last2=Howie|first2=Gillian|last3=Munford|first3=Rebecca|title=Third Wave Feminism: A Critical Exploration|year=2004|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|isbn=978-1-4039-1821-5|oclc=54454680}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response, ''Ms. Magazine'' published an article by [[Rebecca Walker]], entitled "Becoming the Third Wave", in which she stated: "I am not a post-feminism feminist. I am the third wave." Many had argued that Thomas should be acquitted because of his plans to create opportunities for people of color. When Walker asked her partner his opinion and he said the same thing, she asked: "When will progressive black men prioritize my rights and well-being?" She wanted racial equality but without dismissing women.&lt;ref name="Walker1992"/&gt;

In 1992, dubbed the "[[Year of the Woman]]", four women enter the [[United States Senate]] to join the two already there. The following year another woman, [[Kay Bailey Hutchison]], won a special election, bringing the number to seven. The 1990s saw the first female [[Attorney General of the United States|United States Attorney General]] and [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]], as well as the second woman on the Supreme Court, [[Ruth Bader Ginsburg]], and the first US [[First Lady]], [[Hillary Clinton]], to have had an independent political, legal and activist career.

==Purpose==
The shift from second-wave feminism came about with many of the legal and institutional rights that were extended to women. In addition to these institutional gains, third-wave feminists believed there needed to be further changes in stereotypes, media portrayals, and language to define women. The purpose was to celebrate diverse identities.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://rachelyon1.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/third-wave-feminism.pdf|title=Third-wave feminism and individualism: promoting equality or reinforcing the status quo?|last=Iannello|first=Katherine P.|date=|year=1998|website=|publisher=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:JenniferBaumgardner.jpg|thumb|upright=0.8|[[Jennifer Baumgardner]], co-author of ''Manifesta'' (2000), in 2008]]
Third-wave feminists often focused on "micro-politics", and challenged the second wave's paradigm as to what was good for women.&lt;ref name="Freedman"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Freedman|first=Estelle B. |title=No Turning Back: The History of Feminism and the Future of Women|year=2002 |publisher=[[Ballantine Books]] |location=London| oclc=49193867}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Henry"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Henry|first=Astrid |title=Not My Mother's Sister: Generational Conflict and Third-Wave Feminism|year=2004|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]] |location=[[Bloomington, Indiana|Bloomington]] |oclc=53932637}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Gillis"&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last=Gillis| editor-first=Stacy|editor2-last=Howie| editor2-first=Gillian| editor3-last=Munford| editor3-first=Rebecca |title=Third Wave Feminism: A Critical Exploration|edition=Expanded Second| year=2007| publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|location=[[Basingstoke]] |isbn=978-0-230-52174-2| oclc=77795615}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Faludi"&gt;{{Cite book| last=Faludi| first=Susan| title=Backlash: The Undeclared War Against Women |year=1991 |publisher=[[Crown Publishing Group]] |location=New York| isbn=978-0-517-57698-4| oclc=23016353}}&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents of third-wave feminism said that it allowed women to define feminism for themselves. Describing third-wave feminism in ''Manifesta: Young Women, Feminism And The Future'' (2000), [[Jennifer Baumgardner]] and [[Amy Richards]] suggested that feminism could change with every generation and individual:

{{quote|The fact that feminism is no longer limited to arenas where we expect to see it—[[National Organization for Women|NOW]], ''[[Ms. (magazine)|Ms.]]'', [[women's studies]], and redsuited [[Member of Congress|congresswomen]]—perhaps means that young women today have really reaped what feminism has sown. Raised after [[Title IX]] and ''[[William's Doll|William Wants a Doll]]'' {{sic}}, young women emerged from college or high school or two years of marriage or their first job and began challenging some of the received wisdom of the past ten or twenty years of feminism. We're not doing feminism the same way that the seventies feminists did it; being liberated doesn't mean copying what came before but finding one's own way—a way that is genuine to one's own generation.&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt;}}

Third-wave ideology focused on a more [[post-structuralism|post-structuralist]] interpretation of gender and sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hardin|first=Marie|author2=Whiteside, Erin|chapter=From Second-Wave to Poststructuralist Feminism|title=The International Encyclopedia of Media Studies: Media Effects/Media Psychology|year=2013|doi=10.1002/9781444361506.wbiems991|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/9781444361506.wbiems991/pdf|publisher=Blackwell}}&lt;/ref&gt; In "Deconstructing Equality-versus-Difference: Or, the Uses of Poststructuralist Theory for Feminism" (1988), [[Joan W. Scott]] described how "poststructuralists insist that words and texts have no fixed or intrinsic meanings, that there is no transparent or self-evident relationship between them and either ideas or things, no basic or ultimate correspondence between language and the world"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Scott|first=Joan W|year=1988|title=Deconstructing Equality-versus-Difference: Or, the Uses of Poststructuralist Theory for Feminism|journal=Feminist Studies|volume=14|issue=1|pages=32–50|jstor=3177997}}&lt;/ref&gt; Post-structuralist feminists saw binaries such as male-female as an artificial construct created to maintain the power of the dominant group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Poststructural feminism in education: An overview|journal=International Journal of Qualitative Studies in Education|year=2000|volume=13|issue=5|pages=477–515|doi=10.1080/09518390050156422|author=Elizabeth Adams St. Pierre}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|In "The local is global: third wave feminism, peace, and social justice" (2009), the authors explain that third-wave feminism offered five primary focuses: (1) Responsible choice grounded in dialogue; (2) respect and appreciation for experiences and dynamic knowledge; (3) an understanding of "the personal is political" that incorporates both the idea that personal experiences have roots in structural problems and the idea that responsible, individuated personal action has social consequences; (4) use of personal narratives in both theorizing and political activism; (5) political activism as local, with global connections and consequences.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=The Local is Global: Third Wave Feminism, Peace, and Social Justice|journal=Contemporary Justice Review|volume=12|first1=Amber Lynn|last1=Zimmerman|first2=M. Joan|last2=McDermott|first3=Christina M.|last3=Gould|doi=10.1080/10282580802681766}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Third-wave feminism dealt with issues perceived to limit or oppress women through [[consciousness-raising]]—"the collective critical reconstitution of the meaning of women's social experience, as women live through it".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=MacKinnon|first=Catharine A.|year=1989|title=Toward A Feminist Theory of the State|publisher=Harvard University Press|page=83|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Baumgardner and Richards (2000) wrote:

{{quote|Consciousness among women is what caused this [change], and consciousness, one's ability to open their mind to the fact that male domination does affect the women of our generation, is what we need&amp;nbsp;... The presence of feminism in our lives is taken for granted. For our generation, feminism is like fluoride. We scarcely notice we have it—it's simply in the water.&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt;}}

[[File:Shira cropped.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.8|[[Shira Tarrant]] objected to the "wave construct".]]
Feminist scholars such as [[Shira Tarrant]] objected to the "wave construct" because it ignored important progress between the periods. Furthermore, if feminism is a global movement, she argued, the fact that the "first-, second-, and third waves time periods correspond most closely to American feminist developments" raises serious problems about how feminism fails to recognize the history of political issues around the world.&lt;ref name="Tarrant"&gt;{{cite book|last=Tarrant|first=Shira|title=When Sex Became Gender|page=222|year=2006|publisher=[[Routledge]]|location=New York|isbn=978-0-415-95347-4|oclc=62281555}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Arguably, the biggest challenge to the efforts of third-wave feminism was the decline in popular support for the relevance and importance of feminism in what some said was the "post-feminist" era. Manon Tremblay referred to this as the "antifeminist undercurrent" of the West. Here, a concern for what Amy Friedman called third-wave feminism's "radical fanaticism" is expressed.&lt;ref name="tremblay"&gt;Tremblay, Manon. "Gender and Society: Rights and Realities." ''Canada and the United States: Differences that Count''. Ed. David Thomas. Peterborough: Broadview Press, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; Essentially, the claim was that gender equality had already been achieved, via the first two waves, and further attempts to push for women's rights were either irrelevant, unnecessary, or excessively pushing the pendulum towards advantaging women over men and exaggerating the state of women in modern western society. This issue manifested itself in the heated debates over whether or not affirmative action initiatives really were creating societal gender equality, or actually disadvantaging and punishing white, middle-class, males for a biological history that they had inherited.&lt;ref&gt;Newman, Jacquetta A., and Linda A. White. ''Women, Politics, and Public Policy: The Political Struggles of Canadian Women''. Don Mills, Ont.: Oxford UP, 2012. 14–15. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Issues==
===Internet===
Third-wave feminists used the internet and modern technology to reach a larger audience. Laura Brunell wrote in 2008: "The Internet radically democratized the content of the feminist movement with respect to participants, aesthetics, and issues."&lt;ref name="Brunell, Laura 2008"&gt;Brunell, Laura. 2008. "Feminism Re-Imagined: The Third Wave." Encyclopædia Britannica Book of the Year. Chicago: Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Gender violence===
[[Violence Against Women|Gender violence]] became a central issue for third-wave feminists. Gender violence is any kind of violence which primarily affects women, such as rape, domestic violence, and sexual harassment. Organizations such as [[V-Day (movement)|V-Day]] formed with the goal of ending gender violence, and artistic expressions, such as ''[[The Vagina Monologues]],'' generated awareness and action around issues relating to women's sexuality. Third-wave feminists wanted to transform traditional notions of sexuality and embrace "an exploration of women's feelings about sexuality that included vagina-centred topics as diverse as [[orgasm]], birth, and rape".&lt;ref name="Brunell, Laura 2008" /&gt;

===Reproductive rights===
{{Main article|Reproductive rights}}
One of feminism's primary goals is to demonstrate that access to contraception and abortion are women's reproductive rights. According to Baumgardner and Richards, "It is not feminism's goal to control any woman's fertility, only to free each woman to control her own."&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards"/&gt; South Dakota's 2006 attempt to ban [[abortion]] in all cases, except when necessary to protect the mother's life,&lt;ref name="Davey"&gt;{{Cite news |last=Davey |first=Monica |title=South Dakota Bans Abortion, Setting Up a Battle | newspaper= New York Times |volume=155 |issue=53511 |pages=A1–A14 |date=7 March 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the US Supreme Court's vote to uphold the [[partial birth abortion]] ban were viewed as restrictions on women's civil and reproductive rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Ludlow | first = Jeannie | title=Sometimes, It's a Child and a Choice: Toward an Embodied Abortion Praxis | journal=[[NWSA Journal]]| volume=20 | issue= 1 | pages=26–50 | date=Spring 2008| oclc=364432908 | jstor=40071251}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1=Weitz | first1=Tracy A.| last2=Yanow | first2=Susan | title=Implications of the Federal Abortion Ban for Women's Health in the United States| journal=Reproductive Health Matters |volume=16 |issue=31 |pages=99–107 |date=May 2008 | doi=10.1016/S0968-8080(08)31374-3 | pmid=18772090 | oclc=282104847 | jstor=25475407}}&lt;/ref&gt; Restrictions on abortion in the United States, which was mostly legalized by the 1973 Supreme Court decision in ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'', were becoming more common in states around the country. Such restrictions included mandatory waiting periods,&lt;ref&gt;[[Indiana Code]] [http://www.in.gov/legislative/ic/code/title16/ar34/ch2.html#IC16-34-2-1.1 Title 16, art. XXXIV, ch. 2, § 1.1 cl. 1: Voluntary and informed consent required; viewing of fetal ultrasound] x (1993; amended 1997)&lt;/ref&gt; parental-consent laws,&lt;ref&gt;[[Government of South Dakota|South Dakota]] Code [http://legis.state.sd.us/statutes/DisplayStatute.aspx?Type=Statute&amp;Statute=34-23A-7 Title 34, ch. 23A, § 7]&lt;/ref&gt; and spousal-consent laws.&lt;ref&gt;[[South Carolina Constitution|South Carolina]] Code [http://www.scstatehouse.gov/code/t44c041.htm#44-41-10 Title 44, ch. 41, art. 1, § 10]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reclaiming derogatory terms===
English-speakers continued to use words such as ''[[spinster]]'', ''bitch'', ''[[whore]]'', and ''cunt'' to refer to women in derogatory ways. Author [[Inga Muscio]] wrote, "I posit that we're free to seize a word that was kidnapped and co-opted in a pain-filled, distant, past, with a ransom that cost our grandmothers' freedom, children, traditions, pride, and land."{{citation needed|date=November 2017}} Part of taking back the word ''bitch'' was fueled by the 1994 single, "[[All Women Are Bitches]]" by the all-woman band [[Fifth Column (band)|Fifth Column]] and later, by the book ''Bitch: In Praise of Difficult Women'' (1999) by [[Elizabeth Wurtzel]]. In her declaration of the word ''bitch'', Wurtzel introduces her philosophy: "I intend to scream, shout, race the engine, call when I feel like it, throw tantrums in Bloomingdale's if I feel like it and confess intimate details about my life to complete strangers. I intend to do what I want to do and be whom I want to be and answer only to myself: that is, quite simply, the bitch philosophy."&lt;ref name="Wurtzel 1998"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Wurtzel|first=Elizabeth|title=Bitch: In Praise of Difficult Women|page=|year=1998|publisher=[[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]]|location=New York|isbn=978-0-385-48400-8|oclc=38144418}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other issues===
Third-wave feminism regarded race, social class, transgender rights, and sexual liberation as central issues. It also paid attention to workplace matters such as the [[glass ceiling]], [[sexual harassment]], unfair [[maternity leave|maternity-leave]] policies,&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite journal 
| first = Frank | last=Munden 
| title=Female medical workers feel maternity leave unfair| journal=The Kapi'o Newspress | volume=36 | issue=28|date= 7 May 2003
|url=http://kapio.kcc.hawaii.edu/archive/v36/36_28/nurse.html| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090228075410/http://kapio.kcc.hawaii.edu/archive/v36/36_28/nurse.html
| archivedate=28 February 2009| accessdate=14 April 2011 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; motherhood support for [[single mother]]s by means of [[Welfare (financial aid)|welfare]] and [[child care]], respect for working mothers, and the rights of mothers who decide to leave their careers to raise their children full-time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://cupola.gettysburg.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1017&amp;context=poliscifac|title=Women's Leadership and Third-Wave Feminism|last=Iannello|first=Kathleen|publisher=Sage Publishing|year=2010|isbn=1412960835|location=|pages=70–77|quote=|via=The Cupola at Gettysburg College}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Global reach==
===Tahirih Justice Center===
[[Layli Miller-Muro]] founded the [[Tahirih Justice Center]] in 1997 following the [[Matter of Kasinga]], an asylum case in which she was involved as a student attorney dealing with [[female genital mutilation]].&lt;ref name="case"&gt;Fauziya Kassindja, ''Do They Hear You When You Cry.'' p. 171.&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn| The case name became ''Matter of Kasinga'' because Fauziya did not know whether she should correct the immigration official who misspelled her last name on her entry into the United States.}} Miller-Muro later co-wrote a book with the client she had aided and used her portion of the proceeds for the initial funding of the center named after [[Táhirih]]. As of 2012, the organization had assisted more than 13,000 women and children fleeing from a wide variety of abuses.&lt;ref name="services"&gt;[http://www.tahirih.org/services/ Services] ''Tahirih Justice Center'', Retrieved June 6, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The organization played a significant role in the passage of the [[International Marriage Broker Regulation Act]] (IMBRA), which was signed by [[George W. Bush|President Bush]] in early 2006 and incorporated into the [[Violence Against Women Act]] (VAWA). IMBRA gives foreign women important information about prospective American husbands.

===Third-wave feminism in Turkey===
{{further|Women in Turkey}}
One difference of the third wave compared to the first and second was the global reach of feminism.&lt;ref name="about.com"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://civilliberty.about.com/od/gendersexuality/p/third_wave.htm|title=Third-Wave Feminism|website=About.com|accessdate=2015-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Turkey, the feminist movement was separated into three separate wave classifications. The first wave dates back to the early 20th century when women faced issues with civil and political rights in 1920.&lt;ref&gt;Dubois, Ellen C. ''Woman Suffrage and Women's Rights''. New York University Press, New York. 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Şule Toktaş, "The [[Kemalist Turkish invasion of Armenia|Kemalist]] ideal of becoming a Westernized society required legal equality between all citizens irrespective of gender".&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Diner|first1=Cagla|last2=Toktaş|first2=Şule|year=2010|title=Waves of feminism in Turkey: Kemalist, Islamist and Kurdishwomen's movements in an era of globalization|journal=Journal of Balkan and Near Eastern Studies|volume=12|issue=1|pages=41–57|doi=10.1080/19448950903507388|url = http://www.academia.edu/5028615/Waves_of_Feminism_in_Turkey_Kemalist_Islamist_and_Kurdish_Women_s_Movements_in_an_Era_of_Globalization}}&lt;/ref&gt; The second wave came much later in 1980, after the military ''coup d'état''.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite web|first=Adam|last=Leake|date=August 29, 2012|title = A Brief History of the Feminist Movements in Turkey|url = http://www.e-ir.info/2012/08/29/a-brief-history-of-the-feminist-movements-in-turkey/|website = E-International Relations|accessdate = 2015-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The third wave came into effect between 1990 and 2000. The Turkish Republic called it "Kurdish nationalist feminism".&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; According to the ''Journal of Balkan and Near Eastern Studies'', "Kurdish women's groups pinpointed the dual exploitation that Kurdish women have experienced in the patriarchal tribal system dominant in Kurdish culture and the [[imperialist]] system that the centralist Turkish state has imposed on Kurdish people."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Islamic feminists soon after began condemning the United States and European countries for their affect on [[Muslim]] society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Badran|first=Margot|title=Between Secular and Islamic Feminism/s: Reﬂactions on the Middle East and Beyond|journal=Journal of Middle East Women's Studies|volume=1|issue=1|year=2005|pages=6–28|jstor=40326847}}&lt;/ref&gt; Islamic women found ways to continue to adhere to the Muslim religion and connect with feminist politics.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Throughout Turkey's feminist movement, feminists of the new era elected to battle the unequal treatment of women, especially within the Muslim community. Feminists sought to approach the gender issues from a different context by addressing the employment crisis and exploiting the reasons women receive little economic independence or are not allowed enough involvement in local or national affairs. In his article "A Brief History of the Feminist Movements in Turkey" (2012), Adam Leake wrote that "[o]vercoming these gender-stereotypes of the family-orientated mother whose job it is to look after the children is a crucial step towards achieving equal status of women in the community."&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

== Criticism ==
===Lack of cohesion===
One issue raised by critics was a lack of cohesion because of the absence of a single cause for third-wave feminism. The first wave fought for and gained the right for women to vote. The second wave fought for the right for women to have access to and equal opportunity in the workforce, as well as the end of legal sex discrimination. The third wave allegedly lacked a cohesive goal and was often seen as an extension of the second wave.&lt;ref name="Rowe-Finbeiner" /&gt; Some argued that the third wave could be dubbed the "Second Wave, Part Two" when it came to the politics of feminism and that "only young feminist culture" was "truly third wave".&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt; One argument ran that the equation of third-wave feminism with individualism prevented the movement from growing and moving towards political goals. Kathleen P. Iannello wrote:

{{quote|sign=|source=|"The conceptual and real-world "trap" of choice feminism (between work and home) has led women to challenge each other rather than the patriarchy. Individualism conceived of as "choice" does not empower women; it silences them and prevents feminism from becoming a political movement and addressing the real issues of distribution of resources."&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;}}

[[Amy Richards]] defined the feminist culture for this generation as "third wave because it's an expression of having grown up with feminism".&lt;ref name="Rowe-Finbeiner" /&gt; Second-wave feminists grew up where the politics intertwined within the culture, such as "Kennedy, the Vietnam War, civil rights, and women's rights". In contrast, the third wave sprang from a culture of "punk-rock, hip-hop, 'zines, products, consumerism and the Internet".&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt; In an essay entitled "Generations, Academic Feminists in dialogue" [[Diane Elam]] wrote:

{{quote|sign=|source=|"This problem manifests itself when senior feminists insist that junior feminists be good daughters, defending the same kind of feminism their mothers advocated. Questions and criticisms are allowed, but only if they proceed from the approved brand of feminism. Daughters are not allowed to invent new ways of thinking and doing feminism for themselves; feminists' politics should take the same shape that it has always assumed."&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt;}}

[[Rebecca Walker]], in ''To Be Real: Telling the Truth and Changing the Face of Feminism'' (1995), wrote about her fear of rejection by her mother ([[Alice Walker]]) and her godmother ([[Gloria Steinem]]) for challenging their views:

{{quote|sign=|source=|"Young Women feminists find themselves watching their speech and tone in their works so as not to upset their elder feminist mothers. There is a definite gap among feminists who consider themselves to be second-wave and those who would label themselves as third-wave. Although, the age criteria for second-wave feminists and third-wave feminists is murky, younger feminists definitely have a hard time proving themselves worthy as feminist scholars and activists."&lt;ref name="Walker" /&gt;}}

==="Girly" feminism===
Third-wave feminism was often associated, primarily by its critics, with the emergence of so-called "lipstick" or "girly" feminists and the rise of "raunch culture". This was because these new feminists advocated for "expressions of femininity and female sexuality as a challenge to objectification". Accordingly, this included the dismissal of any restriction, whether deemed patriarchal or feminist, to define or control how women or girls should dress, act, or generally express themselves.&lt;ref name="Newman &amp; White 2012 246"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Newman|first1=Jacquetta A.|last2=White|first2=Linda Ann|title=Women, Politics, and Public Policy: The Political Struggles of Canadian Women|year=2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Toronto|page=246|edition=2nd|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; These emerging positions stood in stark contrast with the [[Feminist views of pornography|anti-pornography]] strains of feminism prevalent in the 1980s. Second-wave feminism viewed pornography as encouraging violence towards women.&lt;ref name=":4"/&gt; The new feminists posited that the ability to make autonomous choices about self-expression could be an empowering act of resistance, not simply internalized oppression.

Such views were critiqued because of the subjective nature of [[empowerment]] and autonomy. Scholars were unsure whether empowerment was best measured as an "internal feeling of power and agency" or as an external "measure of power and control". Moreover they critiqued an over-investment in "a model of free will and choice" in the marketplace of identities and ideas.{{sfn|Newman|White|2012|p=247}} Regardless, the "girly" feminists attempted to be open to all different selves while maintaining a dialogue about the meaning of identity and femininity in the contemporary world.

Third-wave feminists said that these viewpoints should not be limited by the label "girly" feminism or regarded as simply advocating for "raunch culture". Rather, they sought to be inclusive of the many diverse roles women fulfill. Gender scholars [[Linda Duits]] and [[Liesbet van Zoonen]] highlighted this inclusivity by looking at the politicization of women's clothing choices and how the "controversial [[sartorial]] choices of girls" and women are constituted in public discourse as "a locus of necessary regulation".&lt;ref name="Newman &amp; White 2012 246"/&gt; Thus the "[[hijab]]" and the "[[Crop top|belly shirt]]", as dress choices, were both identified as requiring regulation but for different reasons. Both caused controversy, while appearing to be opposing forms of self-expression. Through the lens of "girly" feminists, one can view both as symbolic of "political agency and resistance to objectification". The "hijab" could be seen as an act of resistance against Western ambivalence towards Islamic identity, and the "belly shirt" an act of resistance against patriarchal society's narrow views of female sexuality. Both were regarded as valid forms of self-expression.{{sfn|Newman|White|2012|p=247}}

== Timeline ==
===1990s===
{| class="wikitable" style="font-size:95%; width: 85%; text-align:left; float:center; margin-left:10px;"
|-
! scope="col" style="width:10em;"|Date
! scope="col" style="width:70em;"|Event
! scope="col" style="width:5em;"|Sources
|-
| 1991 ||[[Riot grrrl]] movement begins in [[Olympia, Washington]] and [[Washington, D.C.]]||&lt;ref name="Rowe-Finbeiner"&gt;{{cite book |title=The F-Word |last=Rowe-Finkbeiner |first=Kristin |authorlink= |year=2004 |publisher=[[Seal Press]] |location=[[Emeryville, California|Emeryville]] |isbn=978-1-58005-114-9 |url= | oclc=55504351}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|March 1991||In ''[[R v R]]'', the British House of Lords rules that a [[marital rape]] exemption does not exist in English law.||
|-
|March 1991|| In ''[[United Automobile Workers v. Johnson Controls, Inc.]]'', the U.S. Supreme Court declares that employers cannot exclude women from jobs in which exposure to toxic substances could harm a developing fetus.||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=499&amp;invol=187 |title=FindLaw &amp;#124; Cases and Codes |publisher=Caselaw.lp.findlaw.com |date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|May 1991||The film ''[[Thelma and Louise]]'' is released: "It took all those feelings of alienation and anger—which until that point had mostly found expression in things like “Take Back the Night” rallies—and turned them into something rebellious, transgressive, iconic, punk rock and mainstream." — Carina Chocano||&lt;ref&gt;Chocano, Carina (21 April 2011). [http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/24/magazine/mag-24Riff-t.html "Thelma, Louise and All the Pretty Women"], ''The New York Times''.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|31 July 1991||The U. S. Senate votes overwhelmingly to open combat positions for women aviators.||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Eric|last=Schmitt|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1991/08/01/us/senate-votes-to-remove-ban-on-women-as-combat-pilots.html |title=Senate Votes to Remove Ban on Women as Combat Pilots|work=The New York Times |date=1991-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1991||[[Susan Faludi]] publishes ''[[Backlash: The Undeclared War Against American Women]]''.||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Emily|last=Wilson |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2005/dec/13/classics.gender |title=Backlash by Susan Faludi |work=The Guardian |date= 13 December 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|July 1991||[[Clarence Thomas Supreme Court nomination]] and the televised testimony in October of [[Anita Hill]] that he had sexually harassed her.||
|-
|October 1991||"Opportunity 2000" is launched in the UK to increase women's employment opportunities.||&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Judy (28 December 1992). [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/equality-campaign-for-women-falters-1565691.html "Equality campaign for women falters"], ''The Independent''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fenman.co.uk/traineractive/training-activity/Equal-opportunities-for-women.html |title=Equal opportunities for women Training Activity – TrainerActive, Training Activity Portal |publisher=Fenman.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1990"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/1990.shtml |title=BBC Radio 4 – Woman's Hour – Women's History Timeline: 1990–1999 |publisher=BBC |date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|January 1992||In response to the Thomas sexual-harassment case, American feminist [[Rebecca Walker]] publishes an article in [[Ms. Magazine]] entitled "Becoming the Third Wave" in which she states: "I am not a post-feminism feminist. I am the third-wave."||&lt;ref name="Walker1992" /&gt;
|-
|1992||The [[Year of the Woman]] sees four women enter the [[United States Senate]] to join the two already there.||
|-
|1992||Third Wave Direct Action Corporation (later Third Wave Foundation) founded in the US by [[Rebecca Walker]] and Shannon Liss as a multiracial, multicultural organization to support young activists||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Third Wave Foundation |url=http://thirdwavefund.org/history.html |title=History |publisher=Third Wave Foundation |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1993||[[Family and Medical Leave Act]] becomes law in the United States.||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/family_and_medical_leave_act_1993 |title=Family and Medical Leave Act (1993) &amp;#124; LII / Legal Information Institute |publisher=Law.cornell.edu |date=2012-10-12 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1993||[[Janet Reno]] nominated and confirmed as the first female U.S. Attorney General after President [[Bill Clinton]]'s previous choices, [[Zoe Baird]] and [[Kimba Wood]], fail because of [[Nannygate]].||
|-
||1993||"Take Our Daughters to Work Day" debuts in the United States to build girls' self-esteem and open their eyes to a variety of career possibilities for women. It was later called [[Take Our Daughters and Sons to Work Day]].||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100509060312/http://ms.foundation.org/about_us/our-history/take-our-daughters-and-sons-to-work |title=Ms. Foundation for Women – Take Our Daughters and Sons to Work |publisher=ms.foundation.org |date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1994||Women taking back the word ''bitch'' are helped by the single "[[All Women Are Bitches]]" by the all-woman Canadian band [[Fifth Column (band)|Fifth Column]].||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=36c |url=https://www.amazon.com/36c-Fifth-Column/dp/B000003RMV/ref=sr_1_1?s=music&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1348859218&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=fifth+column |title=36c: Music |publisher=Amazon.com |date=2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1994||[[Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994]] confirms that [[marital rape]] is illegal in the UK.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated1990"/&gt;
|-
|1994||[[Violence Against Women Act]] becomes law in the United States.||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.legalmomentum.org/history-vawa|title=History of the Violence Against Women Act|website=Legal Momentum|access-date=2016-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1995||Publication of [[Rebecca Walker]] (ed.), ''To Be Real: Telling the Truth and Changing the Face of Feminism''.||{{sfn|Snyder|2008|loc=176–177}}
|-
|1995||[[Fourth World Conference on Women]] held in China.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated1990"/&gt;
|-
|1996||[[Northern Ireland Women's Coalition]] founded.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated1990"/&gt;
|-
|1996||Feminist play ''[[The Vagina Monologues]]'', by American playwright [[Eve Ensler]], premieres in New York.||&lt;ref name="qsanantonio.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://qsanantonio.com/vday2.html |title="Vagina Monologues" performances mark S.A. V-Day |publisher=QSanAntonio |date=2012-02-25 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
||1996||In [[United States v. Virginia]], the U.S. Supreme Court rules that male-only admissions policy of state-supported Virginia Military Institute violates the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]].||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.oyez.org/cases/1990-1999/1995/1995_94_1941 |title=United States v. Virginia | publisher= The Oyez Project at IIT Chicago-Kent College of Law |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1997||Publication of Leslie Heywood and Jennifer Drake (eds.), ''Third Wave Agenda: Being Feminist, Doing Feminism''.||{{sfn|Snyder|2008|loc=176–177}}
|-
|1997||[[Layli Miller-Muro]] founds the [[Tahirih Justice Center]] in the US following [[Matter of Kasinga]], an asylum case dealing with [[female genital mutilation]].||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tahirih.org/services/|title=Services|author=Tahirih Justice Center|publisher=|accessdate=30 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1998||[[Eve Ensler]] and others, including [[Willa Shalit]], a producer of the Westside Theatre production of ''[[The Vagina Monologues]]'', launch V-Day, a global non-profit movement that raised over $75&amp;nbsp;million for women's [[sexual violence|anti-violence]] groups.||&lt;ref name="qsanantonio.com"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.womensmediacenter.com/ex/013008.html|deadurl=yes|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100104191925/http://womensmediacenter.com/ex/013008.html|archive-date=4 January 2010|title=From Superdome to SUPERLOVE—V-Day at 10|first=Marianne|last=Schnall|date=January 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1999||Publication of [[Germaine Greer]], ''The Whole Woman''||
|-
|1999||Publication of Marcelle Karp and Debbie Stoller (eds.), ''The BUST Guide to the New Girl Order''.||{{sfn|Snyder|2008|loc=176–177}}
|-
|1999||''Bitch: In Praise of Difficult Women'' by [[Elizabeth Wurtzel]] is published: "I intend to scream, shout, race the engine, call when I feel like it, throw tantrums in Bloomingdale's if I feel like it and confess intimate details about my life to complete strangers. I intend to do what I want to do and be whom I want to be and answer only to myself: that is, quite simply, the bitch philosophy."||&lt;ref name="Wurtzel 1998"/&gt;
|}

===2000s===
{| class="wikitable" style="font-size:95%; width: 85%; text-align:left; float:center; margin-left:10px;"
|-
! scope="col" style="width:10em;"|Date
! scope="col" style="width:70em;"|Event
! scope="col" style="width:5em;"|Sources
|-
|2000||CBS agrees to pay $8 million to settle a sex discrimination lawsuit on behalf of 200 women.||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-72470958.html |title=CBS to pay $8&amp;nbsp;million to settle sex discrimination lawsuit |last=Carlson|first=Scott|publisher=Knight Ridder/Tribune News Service |date=2000-10-25 |accessdate=2016-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|2001||The [[Isle of Man]] passed its first sex discrimination bill.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/2000.shtml |title=Women's History Timeline: 2000–now |publisher=''Woman's Hour'', BBC Radio 4 |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|2004||[[Condoleezza Rice]] becomes the first female US national security adviser.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2004||The [[March for Women's Lives]] is held in Washington, D.C., to support the right to abortion, access to birth control, scientifically accurate sex education, prevention and treatment of sexually transmitted infections, and to show public support for mothers and children.||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guttmacher.org/media/inthenews/2005/04/25/index.html |title=March for Women's Lives |publisher=Guttmacher.org |date=April 25, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|2004||Asylum Gender Guidelines are introduced by the UK for female asylum seekers.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2004|| Publication of Vivien Labaton and Dawn Lundy (eds.), ''The Fire This Time: Young Activists and the New Feminism''.||{{sfn|Snyder|2008|loc=176–177}}
|-
|2005||[[Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf]] in Liberia becomes Africa's first elected woman leader and the first black female president in the world.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2006||[[Angela Merkel]] becomes Germany's first woman chancellor.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2007||[[Nancy Pelosi]] becomes the first woman Speaker in the US Congress.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|1 April 2007||The Gender Equality Duty of the [[Equality Act 2006]] comes into effect in the UK. It requires public authorities "to promote equality of opportunity between women and men".||&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2008||Norway requires of all companies that at least forty percent of the people on their boards must be women.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|May 2008|| Diana Bijon's husband, Michael, takes her last name upon marriage, after their lawsuit which led to a new California state law guaranteeing the rights of both married couples and registered domestic partners to choose whichever last name they prefer.||&lt;ref name="DianaBijon"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2008/05/05/us-usa-name-idUKN0541896320080505 |title=Los Angeles man wins right to use wife's last name |publisher=Reuters |date= 2008-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|2008||[[Forced Marriage (Civil Protection) Act 2007]] comes into force in the UK.||&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2009||In the UK, [[Carol Ann Duffy]] becomes the first female [[Poet Laureate]].||&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;

|}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Baumgardner |first1=Jennifer |author1-link= Jennifer Baumgardner |last2=Richards| first2=Amy |author2-link=Amy Richards |title=Grassroots: A Field Guide for Feminist Activism |location=New York |publisher=[[Farrar, Straus, and Giroux]] |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-374-52865-2 |oclc=55109024}}
* {{Cite journal |last=DeKoven |first=Marianne |title=Jouissance, cyborgs, and companion species: Feminist experiment |journal=PMLA |volume=121 |issue=5 |pages=1690–1696 |doi=10.1632/pmla.2006.121.5.1690 |oclc=104244114 |issn=0030-8129 |jstor=25501648 |date=October 2006}}
* {{Cite book|last=Ensler |first=Eve |authorlink=Eve Ensler|title=[[The Vagina Monologues]] |publisher=[[Villard (imprint)|Villard]] |year=2001 |location=[[New York City|New York]] |isbn=978-0-375-75052-6 |oclc=37492271 }}
* {{cite journal | last = Evans | first = Elizabeth | title = What makes a (third) wave?: How and why the third-wave narrative works for contemporary feminists | journal = [[International Feminist Journal of Politics]] | volume = 18 | issue = 3 | pages = 409–428 | publisher = [[Taylor and Francis]] | doi = 10.1080/14616742.2015.1027627 | date = 2016 | url = https://dx.doi.org/10.1080/14616742.2015.1027627 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
* {{Cite book|editor-last=Findlen |editor-first=Barbara |title=Listen Up! Voices from the Next Feminist Generation |publisher=[[Seal Press]] |year=1995 |location=Seattle |isbn=978-1-878067-61-6 |oclc=31607164}}
* {{Cite book| last1 = Gillis | last2 = Howie | last3=Munford | first1=Stacy | first2=Gillian | first3=Rebecca |author2-link=Gillian Howie |title=Third Wave Feminism: A Critical Exploration |edition=Revised| publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] |year=2007 |isbn=1-4039-1821-X }}
* {{Cite journal |last=Harnois |first=Catherine |title=Re-presenting feminisms: Past, present, and future |journal=NWSA Journal | publisher=[[Johns Hopkins University Press]]|volume=20 |issue=1 |pages=120–145 |year=2008 |doi=10.1353/nwsa.0.0010 |jstor=40071255 |url=http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/nwsa_journal/summary/v020/20.1.harnois.html}}
* {{Cite book|last=Henry |first=Astrid |title=Not My Mother's Sister: Generational Conflict and Third-Wave Feminism|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]] |year=2004 |isbn=0-253-21713-X}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Hernández |first1=Daisy |last2=Reman |first2=Bushra |author1-link=Daisy Hernández |title=Colonize This! Young Women of Color and Today's Feminism |publisher=[[Seal Press]] |year=2002 |isbn=1-58005-067-0}}
*Heywood, Leslie L., ed. (2005). ''The Women's Movement Today: An Encyclopedia of Third-Wave Feminism''. 2 vols. Westport: Greenwood Press.
* {{cite journal | last = Hitchens | first = Donna | title = Feminism in the nineties: coalition strategies | journal = [[Yale Journal of Law and Feminism]] | volume = 4 | issue = 1 | pages = 57–63 | publisher = [[Yale Law School]] | date = Fall 1991 | url = http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?handle=hein.journals/yjfem4&amp;div=12&amp;id=&amp;page= | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [http://digitalcommons.law.yale.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1050&amp;context=yjlf Pdf.]
* Iannello, Kathleen. (2010) [http://cupola.gettysburg.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1017&amp;context=poliscifac "Women's Leadership and Third-Wave Feminism."] Gender and Women's Leadership: A Reference Handbook. Ed. Karen O'Connor ([[SAGE Publications|Sage Publishing]], 2010), 70–77.
* {{Cite book| last=Karaian |first=Lara |editor1-last=Rundle |editor1-first=Lisa Bryn | editor2-last=Mitchell |editor2-first=Allyson |editor2-link=Allyson Mitchell|title=Turbo Chicks: Talking Young Feminisms |location=Toronto |publisher=Sumach Press |year=2001 |isbn=978-1-894549-06-6 |oclc=46629305}}
* {{Cite journal |last=Kinser |first=Amber E. |title=Negotiating spaces for/through third-wave feminism |journal=NWSA Journal | publisher=[[University of Illinois Press]]|volume=16 |issue=3 |pages=124–153 |year=2004 |doi=10.2979/NWS.2004.16.3.124 |jstor=4317084 |url=http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/nwsa_journal/summary/v016/16.3kinser.html }}
* {{Cite book|editor1-last=Miya-Jervis |editor1-first=Lisa |editor1-link=Lisa Jervis |editor2-last=Zeisler |editor2-first=Andi |editor2-link=Andi Zeisler|title=BitchFest: 10 Years of Cultural Criticism from the Pages of Bitch Magazine |location=New York |publisher=[[Farrar, Straus, and Giroux]] |year=2006 |isbn=978-0-374-11343-8 |oclc=62895790}}
* {{Cite book|last=Muscio |first=Inga |authorlink=Inga Muscio |title=Cunt: A Declaration of Independence|location=Seattle |publisher=[[Seal Press]] |year=1998 |isbn=978-1-58005-015-9 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Springer | first = Kimberly | title = Third Wave Black Feminism? | journal = [[Signs (journal)|Signs]] | volume = 27 | issue = 4 | pages = 1059–1082 | publisher = [[University of Chicago Press]] | doi = 10.1086/339636 | jstor = 10.1086/339636 | date = Summer 2002 | ref = harv}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050130091522/http://www.rebeccawalker.com/article_2005_riding-the-third-wave.htm interview with Rebecca Walker in Satya Magazine]
* [http://www.metroactive.com/papers/cruz/11.29.00/feminism-0048.html Interview with Jennifer Baumgardner and Amy Richards]

{{Feminism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:3}}
[[Category:Third-wave feminism]]
[[Category:Feminism and history]]
[[Category:History of women in the United States]]
[[Category:History of women's rights in the United States]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]

[[de:Feminismus#Dritte Welle]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>