<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201028182326|985914767" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="748253" pageid="748253" ns="0" title="Third-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-23T13:06:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Aspect of feminism beginning in the 1990s}}
{{Feminism sidebar|expanded=history}}
[[File:Rebeccawalker.jpg|thumb|[[Rebecca Walker]] in 2003. The term ''third wave'' is credited to Walker's 1992 article, "Becoming the Third Wave".&lt;ref name=Walker1992/&gt;]]
'''Third-wave feminism''' is an iteration of the [[feminist movement]]. It began in the [[United States]]{{sfn|Evans|2015|loc=22}} in the early 1990s and continued until the rise of the [[fourth-wave feminism|fourth wave]] in the 2010s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Nicola|last=Rivers|title=Postfeminism(s) and the Arrival of the Fourth Wave|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|year=2017|at=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Cochrane|first=Kira|authorlink=Kira Cochrane|title=The Fourth Wave of Feminism: Meet the Rebel Women|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/dec/10/fourth-wave-feminism-rebel-women|newspaper=The Guardian|date=10 December 2013|access-date=2 June 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160314123922/http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/dec/10/fourth-wave-feminism-rebel-women|archive-date=14 March 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Born in the 1960s and 1970s as members of [[Generation X]] and grounded in the civil-rights advances of the [[second-wave feminism|second wave]], third-wave feminists embraced [[individualism]] and [[Diversity (politics)|diversity]] and sought to redefine what it meant to be a feminist.{{sfn|Evans|2015|loc=22}}&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.britannica.com/topic/feminism/The-third-wave-of-feminism#ref1228639 "The Third Wave of Feminism"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190528171627/https://www.britannica.com/topic/feminism/The-third-wave-of-feminism#ref1228639 |date=2019-05-28 }}, ''Encyclopaedia Britannica''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards"&gt;{{harvnb|Baumgardner|Richards|2000|p=77}}&lt;/ref&gt; The third wave saw the emergence of new feminist currents and theories, such as [[intersectionality]], [[Sex positive feminism|sex positivity]], [[vegetarian ecofeminism]], [[transfeminism]], and [[postmodern feminism]]. According to feminist scholar Elizabeth Evans, the "confusion surrounding what constitutes third-wave feminism is in some respects its defining feature."{{sfn|Evans|2015|loc=49}}

The third wave is traced to the emergence of the [[riot grrrl]] feminist [[punk subculture]] in [[Olympia, Washington]], in the early 1990s,{{efn|Steve Feliciano (New York Public Library, 2013): "The emergence of the Riot Grrrl movement began in the early 1990s, when a group of women in Olympia, Washington, held a meeting to discuss how to address sexism in the punk scene. The women decided they wanted to start a 'girl riot' against a society they felt offered no validation of women's experiences. And thus the Riot Grrrl movement was born."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Feliciano|first1=Steve|title=The Riot Grrrl Movement|url=http://www.nypl.org/blog/2013/06/19/riot-grrrl-movement|publisher=New York Public Library|date=19 June 2013|access-date=2 June 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190403081524/https://www.nypl.org/blog/2013/06/19/riot-grrrl-movement|archive-date=3 April 2019|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} and to [[Anita Hill]]'s televised testimony in 1991—to an all-male, all-white [[Senate Judiciary Committee]]—that [[Clarence Thomas Supreme Court nomination|Clarence Thomas]], nominated for and eventually confirmed to the [[Supreme Court of the United States]], had [[Sexual harassment|sexually harassed]] her. The term ''third wave'' is credited to [[Rebecca Walker]], who responded to Thomas's appointment to the Supreme Court with an article in ''[[Ms. (magazine)|Ms.]]'' magazine, "Becoming the Third Wave" (1992).&lt;ref&gt;[http://heathengrrl.blogspot.com/2007/02/becoming-third-wave-by-rebecca-walker.html "Becoming the Third Wave" by Rebecca Walker&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Walker1992&gt;{{cite journal| last1 = Walker| first1 = Rebecca| authorlink1 = Rebecca Walker| title = Becoming the Third Wave| journal = [[Ms. (magazine)|Ms.]]| pages = 39–41| issn = 0047-8318| oclc = 194419734| date = January 1992| url = http://www.msmagazine.com/spring2002/BecomingThirdWaveRebeccaWalker.pdf| access-date = 2016-10-13| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20170115202333/http://www.msmagazine.com/spring2002/BecomingThirdWaveRebeccaWalker.pdf| archive-date = 2017-01-15| url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards"/&gt; She wrote:

{{quote|So I write this as a plea to all women, especially women of my generation: Let Thomas' confirmation  serve to remind you, as it did me, that the fight is far from over. Let this dismissal of a woman's experience move you to anger. Turn that outrage into political power. Do not vote for them unless they work for us. Do not have sex with them, do not break bread with them, do not nurture them if they don't prioritize our freedom to control our bodies and our lives. I am not a post-feminism feminist. I am the Third Wave.&lt;ref&gt;[http://heathengrrl.blogspot.com/2007/02/becoming-third-wave-by-rebecca-walker.html "Becoming the Third Wave" by Rebecca Walker&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Walker1992" /&gt;}}

Walker sought to establish that third-wave feminism was not just a reaction, but a movement in itself, because the feminist cause had more work ahead. The term ''[[intersectionality]]''—to describe the idea that women experience "layers of oppression" caused, for example, by gender, race and class—had been introduced by [[Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw]] in 1989, and it was during the third wave that the concept flourished.{{sfn|Evans|2015|loc=19}} As feminists came online in the late 1990s and early 2000s and reached a global audience with blogs and e-[[zine]]s, they broadened their goals, focusing on abolishing gender-role stereotypes and expanding feminism to include women with diverse racial and cultural identities.&lt;ref name=Brunell2008/&gt;&lt;ref name=Tong&gt;{{cite book |last=Tong |first=Rosemarie |title=Feminist Thought: A More Comprehensive Introduction |year=2009 |edition=Third |publisher=Westview Press |location=Boulder, CO |isbn=978-0-8133-4375-4 |oclc=156811918 |pages=284–285, 289}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{Further|First-wave feminism|Second-wave feminism|Feminist sex wars|Fourth-wave feminism}}
The rights and programs gained by feminists of the second wave served as a foundation for the third wave. The gains included [[Title IX]] (equal access to education); public discussion about the abuse and rape of women; access to contraception and other reproductive services (including the legalization of abortion); the creation and enforcement of sexual-harassment policies for women in the workplace; the creation of domestic-abuse shelters for women and children; child-care services; educational funding for young women; and [[women's studies]] programs.

Feminist leaders rooted in the second wave such as [[Gloria Anzaldúa]], [[bell hooks]], [[Cherríe Moraga]], [[Audre Lorde]], [[Maxine Hong Kingston]], and other feminists of color, sought to negotiate a space within feminist thought for consideration of race.&lt;ref name="Gillis" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Heywood"&gt;{{Cite book|editor-last=Heywood|editor-first=Leslie|editor2-last=Drake|editor2-first=Jennifer|title=Third Wave Agenda: Being Feminist, Doing Feminism|year=1997|publisher=[[University of Minnesota Press]]|location=[[Minneapolis]]|isbn=978-0-8166-3005-9|oclc=36876149|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/thirdwaveagendab0000unse}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cherríe Moraga]] and [[Gloria E. Anzaldúa]] had published the anthology ''[[This Bridge Called My Back]]'' (1981), which, along with ''[[All the Women Are White, All the Blacks Are Men, But Some of Us Are Brave]]'' (1982), edited by [[Akasha Gloria Hull|Akasha (Gloria T.) Hull]], [[Patricia Bell-Scott]], and [[Barbara Smith]], argued that second-wave feminism had focused primarily on the problems of white women. The emphasis on the intersection between race and gender became increasingly prominent.

In the interlude of the late 1970s and early 1980s, the [[feminist sex wars]] arose as a reaction against the [[radical feminism]] of the second wave and [[Feminist views on sexuality|its views on sexuality]], therein countering with a concept of "[[Sex-positive feminism|sex-positivity]]" and heralding the third wave.&lt;ref name="end"&gt;As noted in:
*{{cite book |author1=Duggan, Lisa |author2=Hunter, Nan D. |title=Sex wars: sexual dissent and political culture |year=1995 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=978-0-415-91036-1 |pages= |url=https://archive.org/details/sexwarssexualdis0000dugg }}
*{{cite book |author=Hansen, Karen Tranberg |author2=Philipson, Ilene J. |title=Women, class, and the feminist imagination: a socialist-feminist reader |year=1990 |publisher=Temple University Press |location=Philadelphia |isbn=978-0-87722-630-7 |pages= |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/womenclassfemini0000unse }}
*{{cite book |author=Gerhard, Jane F. |title=Desiring revolution: second-wave feminism and the rewriting of American sexual thought, 1920 to 1982 |year=2001 |publisher=Columbia University Press |location=New York |isbn=978-0-231-11204-8}}
*{{cite book |author=Leidholdt, Dorchen |authorlink=Dorchen Leidholdt |author2=Raymond, Janice G |title=The Sexual liberals and the attack on feminism |year=1990 |publisher=Pergamon Press |location=New York|isbn=978-0-08-037457-4}}
*{{cite book |author=Vance, Carole S |title=Pleasure and Danger: Exploring Female Sexuality |publisher=Thorsons Publishers |isbn=978-0-04-440593-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early years==
===Riot grrrl===
{{Main|Riot grrrl}}
[[File:Kathleen Hanna live in Bikini Kill in 1991.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Kathleen Hanna]], lead singer of [[Bikini Kill]] 1991]]
The emergence of [[riot grrrl]], the feminist [[punk subculture]], in the early 1990s in [[Olympia, Washington]], marked the beginning of third-wave feminism.&lt;ref name=Piepmeier2009p45&gt;{{cite book|first=Alison|last=Piepmeier|title=Girl Zines: Making Media, Doing Feminism|location=New York|publisher=New York University Press|year=2009|p=45}}&lt;/ref&gt; The triple "r" in ''grrrl'' was intended to reclaim the word ''girl'' for women.&lt;ref name=Rowe-Finbeiner&gt;{{cite book|title=The F Word: Feminism in Jeopardy|last=Rowe-Finkbeiner|first=Kristin|authorlink=|year=2004|publisher=Seal Press|location=Emeryville, CA|p=[https://archive.org/details/fwordfeminisminj00rowe/page/85 85]|isbn=978-1-58005-114-9|url=https://archive.org/details/fwordfeminisminj00rowe/page/85}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alison Piepmeier]] writes that riot grrrl and [[Sarah Dyer]]'s ''Action Girl Newsletter'' formulated "a style, rhetoric, and iconography for grrrl [[zines]]" that came to define third-wave feminism,&lt;ref name=Piepmeier2009p45/&gt; and that focused on the viewpoint of adolescent girls.&lt;ref&gt;Starr, Chelsea (2000). "Adolescent girls and feminism", in Code, Lorraine (ed.). ''Encyclopedia of Feminist Theories''. London and New York: Routledge, p. 3. {{ISBN|0-415-30885-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Based on hard-core [[punk rock]], the movement created zines and art, talked about rape, patriarchy, sexuality, and female empowerment, started chapters, and supported and organized women in music.&lt;ref name=Schilt&gt;Schilt, Kristen (2003). "'A Little Too Ironic': The Appropriation and Packaging of Riot Grrrl Politics by Mainstream Female Musicians", in ''Popular Music and Society'', 26.&lt;/ref&gt; An undated&lt;sup&gt;but collected by 2013&lt;/sup&gt; [[Bikini Kill]] tour flier asked "What is Riot grrrl?":

{{quote|BECAUSE in every form of media I see us/myself slapped, decapitated, laughed at, objectified, raped, trivialized, pushed, ignored, stereotyped, kicked, scorned, molested, silenced, invalidated, knifed, shot, choked, and killed.&amp;nbsp;... BECAUSE a safe space needs to be created for girls where we can open our eyes and reach out to each other without being threatened by this sexist society and our day to day bullshit.&amp;nbsp;... BECAUSE we girls want to create mediums that speak to US. We are tired of boy band after boy band, boy zine after boy zine, boy punk after boy punk after boy. BECAUSE I am tired of these things happening to me; I'm not a fuck toy. I'm not a punching bag. I'm not a joke.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last = Darms|editor1-first = Lisa|title = The Riot Grrrl Collection|publisher = The Feminist Press at the City University of New York|year= 2013 |isbn = 978-1558618220|at = 168}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Riot grrrl was grounded in the [[DIY ethic|DIY philosophy]] of [[Punk ideologies#Punk ethics|punk values]], adopting an [[anti-corporate]] stance of [[self-sufficiency]] and self-reliance.&lt;ref name=Rowe-Finbeiner/&gt; Its emphasis on universal female identity and separatism often appeared more closely allied with second-wave feminism.&lt;ref name=Rosenberg_Garofalo&gt;Rosenberg, Jessica and Gitana, Garofalo (Spring 1998). "Riot Grrrl: Revolutions from within", ''Signs'', 23(3). {{jstor|3175311}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bands associated with the movement included [[Bratmobile]], [[Excuse 17]], [[Jack Off Jill]], [[Free Kitten]], [[Heavens to Betsy]], [[Huggy Bear (band)|Huggy Bear]], [[L7 (band)|L7]], [[Fifth Column (band)|Fifth Column]], and [[Team Dresch]].&lt;ref name=Schilt/&gt;

Riot grrrl culture gave people the space to enact change on a macro, meso and micro scale. As Kevin Dunn explains:&lt;blockquote&gt;Using the do-it-yourself ethos of punk to provide resources for individual empowerment, Riot Grrrl encouraged females to engage in multiple sites of resistance. At the macro-level, Riot Grrrls resist society's dominant constructions of femininity. At the meso-level, they resist stifling gender roles in punk. At the micro-level, they challenge gender constructions in their families and among their peers.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Dunn|first=Kevin C.|date=2014-04-03|title=Pussy Rioting|journal=International Feminist Journal of Politics|language=en|volume=16|issue=2|pages=317–334|doi=10.1080/14616742.2014.919103|s2cid=146989637|issn=1461-6742}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;The demise of riot grrrl is linked to commodification and misrepresentation of its message, mainly through media coverage.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Writing in ''[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]'' magazine, Jennifer Keishin Armstrong states:

{{quote|In the early 1990s, the women's movement seemed dead to the mainstream. Few pop cultural figures embraced the term "feminist." The underground punk movement known as "Riot Grrrl" scared anyone outside of it, while Alanis Morissette's breakthrough single "You Oughta Know" scared everyone else even more. Then, in the middle of the decade, the [[Spice Girls]] took all of that fear and made feminism – popularized as [[Girl Power]] – fun. Suddenly, regular girls far outside Women's Studies classrooms had at least an inkling of what would be known in wonky circles as Third Wave Feminism – led by Generation Xers pushing for sexual freedom and respect for traditionally "girly" pursuits like makeup and fashion, among many other issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Spice Girls' 'Wannabe': How 'Girl Power' Reinvigorated Mainstream Feminism in the '90s |url=https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/features/7439005/spice-girls-wannabe-girl-power-feminism |accessdate=March 21, 2019 |work=Billboard |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190323030031/https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/features/7439005/spice-girls-wannabe-girl-power-feminism |archive-date=March 23, 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

El Hunt of ''[[NME]]'' states, "Riot grrrl bands in general were very focused on making space for women at gigs. They understood the importance of giving women a platform and voice to speak out against abusers. For a lot of young women and girls, who probably weren't following the Riot grrrl scene at all, The Spice Girls brought this spirit into the mainstream and made it accessible."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Spice Girls: What happened to Girl Power? |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-48381340 |accessdate=May 25, 2019 |agency=BBC |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190525011653/https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-48381340 |archive-date=May 25, 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anita Hill===
{{main|Clarence Thomas Supreme Court nomination}}
[[File:Anita Hill at Harvard Law School Sep 2014.jpg|left|thumb|upright|[[Anita Hill]], 2014]]
In 1991, [[Anita Hill]] accused [[Clarence Thomas]], an African-American judge who had been nominated to the [[United States Supreme Court]], of [[sexual harassment]]. Thomas denied the accusations, calling them a "high-tech lynching". After extensive debate, the [[United States Senate]] voted 52–48 in favor of Thomas.&lt;ref name="Gillis" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Heywood" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Walker"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Walker|first=Rebecca|title=To Be Real: Telling the Truth and Changing the Face of Feminism|year=1995|publisher=Anchor Books|location=New York|isbn=978-0-385-47262-3|oclc=32274323|url=https://archive.org/details/toberealtelling00walk}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response, ''Ms. Magazine'' published an article by [[Rebecca Walker]], entitled "Becoming the Third Wave", in which she stated: "I am not a post-feminism feminist. I am the third wave." Many had argued that Thomas should be acquitted because of his plans to create opportunities for people of color. When Walker asked her partner his opinion and he said the same thing, she asked: "When will progressive black men prioritize my rights and well-being?" She wanted racial equality but without dismissing women.&lt;ref name="Walker1992"/&gt;

In 1992, dubbed the "[[Year of the Woman]]", four women entered the [[United States Senate]] to join the two already there. The following year, another woman, [[Kay Bailey Hutchison]], won a special election, bringing the number to seven. The 1990s saw the US's first female [[Attorney General of the United States|Attorney General]] ([[Janet Reno]]) and [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]] ([[Madeleine Albright]]), as well as the second woman on the Supreme Court, [[Ruth Bader Ginsburg]], and the first US [[First Lady]], [[Hillary Clinton]], to have had an independent political, legal and activist career.

==Purpose==
&lt;!--check and re-write: The shift from second-wave feminism came about with the legal and institutional rights that were extended to women. In addition to these institutional gains, third-wave feminists believed there needed to be further changes in stereotypes, media portrayals, and language to define women. The purpose was to celebrate diverse identities.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://rachelyon1.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/third-wave-feminism.pdf|title=Third-wave feminism and individualism: promoting equality or reinforcing the status quo?|last=Iannello|first=Katherine P.|year=1998|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161019073259/https://rachelyon1.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/third-wave-feminism.pdf|archive-date=2016-10-19|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

[[File:JenniferBaumgardner.jpg|thumb|upright=0.8|[[Jennifer Baumgardner]], co-author of ''Manifesta'' (2000), in 2008]]
Arguably the biggest challenge to third-wave feminism was that the gains of second-wave feminism were taken for granted, and the importance of feminism not understood. Baumgardner and Richards (2000) wrote: "[F]or anyone born after the early 1960s, the presence of feminism in our lives is taken for granted. For our generation, feminism is like fluoride. We scarcely notice that we have it—it's simply in the water."&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt;

Essentially the claim was that gender equality had already been achieved, via the first two waves, and further attempts to push for women's rights were irrelevant and unnecessary, or perhaps even pushed the pendulum too far in women's favor. This issue manifested itself in the heated debates about whether affirmative action was creating gender equality or punishing white, middle-class males for the biological history that they had inherited.{{sfn|Newman|White|2012|p=14–15}}&lt;!--Not clear what this refers to: Manon Tremblay referred to this as the "antifeminist undercurrent" of the West.&lt;ref name="tremblay"&gt;Tremblay, Manon (1993). "Gender and Society: Rights and Realities". In David Thomas (ed.). ''Canada and the United States: Differences that Count''. Peterborough: Broadview Press.&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;&lt;!--check the following--&gt; Third-wave feminism therefore focused on [[consciousness-raising]]—"one's ability to open their mind to the fact that male domination does affect the women of our generation, is what we need.&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=MacKinnon|first=Catharine A.|year=1989|title=Toward A Feminist Theory of the State|publisher=Harvard University Press|page=[https://archive.org/details/towardfeministth00mack/page/83 83]|url=https://archive.org/details/towardfeministth00mack|url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Third-wave feminists often engaged in "micro-politics", and challenged the second wave's paradigm as to what was good for women.&lt;ref name="Freedman"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Freedman|first=Estelle B. |title=No Turning Back: The History of Feminism and the Future of Women|url=https://archive.org/details/noturningbackhis00free|url-access=registration|year=2002 |publisher=[[Ballantine Books]] |location=London| oclc=49193867}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Henry|2004}}&lt;ref name="Gillis"&gt;{{harvnb|Gillis|Howie|Munford|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Faludi"&gt;{{Cite book| last=Faludi| first=Susan| title=Backlash: The Undeclared War Against Women | url=https://archive.org/details/backlashundeclar00falu| url-access=registration|year=1991 |publisher=[[Crown Publishing Group]] |location=New York| isbn=978-0-517-57698-4| oclc=23016353}}&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents of third-wave feminism said that it allowed women to define feminism for themselves.  Describing third-wave feminism in ''Manifesta: Young Women, Feminism And The Future'' (2000), [[Jennifer Baumgardner]] and [[Amy Richards]] suggested that feminism could change with every generation and individual:

{{quote|The fact that feminism is no longer limited to arenas where we expect to see it—[[National Organization for Women|NOW]], ''[[Ms. (magazine)|Ms.]]'', [[women's studies]], and redsuited [[Member of Congress|congresswomen]]—perhaps means that young women today have really reaped what feminism has sown. Raised after [[Title IX]] and ''[[William's Doll|William Wants a Doll]]'' {{sic}}, young women emerged from college or high school or two years of marriage or their first job and began challenging some of the received wisdom of the past ten or twenty years of feminism. We're not doing feminism the same way that the seventies feminists did it; being liberated doesn't mean copying what came before but finding one's own way—a way that is genuine to one's own generation.&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt;}}
[[File:Womensmarch austin texas img 4198 (32427292776).jpg|thumb|Protesters at a women's march in 2017]]
Third-wave feminists used personal narratives as a form of feminist theory. Expressing personal experiences gave women space to recognize that they were not alone in the oppression and discrimination they faced. Using these accounts has benefits because it records personal details that may not be available in traditional historical texts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=YU|first=SU-LIN|date=October 2011|title=Reclaiming the Personal: Personal Narratives of Third-Wave Feminists|journal=Women's Studies|language=en|volume=40|issue=7|pages=873–889|doi=10.1080/00497878.2011.603606|s2cid=144937285|issn=0049-7878}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Third-wave ideology focused on a more [[post-structuralism|post-structuralist]] interpretation of gender and sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hardin|first=Marie|author2=Whiteside, Erin|chapter=From Second-Wave to Poststructuralist Feminism|title=The International Encyclopedia of Media Studies: Media Effects/Media Psychology|year=2013|doi=10.1002/9781444361506.wbiems991|publisher=Blackwell|isbn=9781405193566}}&lt;/ref&gt; Post-structuralist feminists saw binaries such as male–female as an artificial construct created to maintain the power of the dominant group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Poststructural feminism in education: An overview|journal=International Journal of Qualitative Studies in Education|year=2000|volume=13|issue=5|pages=477–515|doi=10.1080/09518390050156422|author=Elizabeth Adams St. Pierre}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Joan W. Scott]] wrote in 1998 that "poststructuralists insist that words and texts have no fixed or intrinsic meanings, that there is no transparent or self-evident relationship between them and either ideas or things, no basic or ultimate correspondence between language and the world".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Scott|first=Joan W|year=1988|title=Deconstructing Equality-versus-Difference: Or, the Uses of Poststructuralist Theory for Feminism|journal=Feminist Studies|volume=14|issue=1|pages=32–50|jstor=3177997|doi=10.2307/3177997}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Amber Lynn Zimmerman, M. Joan McDermott, and Christina M. Gould wrote in 2009 that third-wave feminism offered five primary focuses: (1) Responsible choice grounded in dialogue; (2) respect and appreciation for experiences and dynamic knowledge; (3) an understanding of "the personal is political" that incorporates both the idea that personal experiences have roots in structural problems and the idea that responsible, individuated personal action has social consequences; (4) use of personal narratives in both theorizing and political activism; (5) political activism as local, with global connections and consequences.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=The Local is Global: Third Wave Feminism, Peace, and Social Justice|journal=Contemporary Justice Review|volume=12|pages=77–90|first1=Amber Lynn|last1=Zimmerman|first2=M. Joan|last2=McDermott|first3=Christina M.|last3=Gould|doi=10.1080/10282580802681766|year=2009|s2cid=143985823}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Relationship with second wave===
The second wave of feminism is often accused of being elitist and ignoring groups such as women of colour and transgender women, instead, focusing on white, middle class, cisgender women. Third wave feminists questioned the beliefs of their predecessors and began to apply feminist theory to a wider variety of women, who had not been previously included in feminist activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Davies |first1=Edward |title=Third Wave Feminism and Transgender: Strength Through Diversity |date=2018 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=9781315107776 |edition=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Amy Richards]] defined the feminist culture for the third wave as "third wave because it's an expression of having grown up with feminism".&lt;ref name="Rowe-Finbeiner" /&gt; Second-wave feminists grew up where the politics intertwined within the culture, such as "Kennedy, the Vietnam War, civil rights, and women's rights". In contrast, the third wave sprang from a culture of "punk-rock, hip-hop, 'zines, products, consumerism and the Internet".&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt; In an essay entitled "Generations, Academic Feminists in dialogue" [[Diane Elam]] wrote:

{{quote|sign=|source=|"This problem manifests itself when senior feminists insist that junior feminists be good daughters, defending the same kind of feminism their mothers advocated. Questions and criticisms are allowed, but only if they proceed from the approved brand of feminism. Daughters are not allowed to invent new ways of thinking and doing feminism for themselves; feminists' politics should take the same shape that it has always assumed."&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt;}}

[[Rebecca Walker]], in ''To Be Real: Telling the Truth and Changing the Face of Feminism'' (1995), wrote about her fear of rejection by her mother ([[Alice Walker]]) and her godmother ([[Gloria Steinem]]) for challenging their views:

{{quote|sign=|source=|"Young Women feminists find themselves watching their speech and tone in their works so as not to upset their elder feminist mothers. There is a definite gap among feminists who consider themselves to be second-wave and those who would label themselves as third-wave. Although, the age criteria for second-wave feminists and third-wave feminists is murky, younger feminists definitely have a hard time proving themselves worthy as feminist scholars and activists."&lt;ref name="Walker" /&gt;}}

==Issues==
===Violence against women===
[[File:Vagina Monologues Poster.jpg|thumb|upright|left|The ''[[Vagina Monologues]]'' premiered in New York in 1996.]]
[[Violence against women]], including [[rape]], [[domestic violence]], and [[sexual harassment]], became{{Citation needed|date=February 2018}}&lt;!-- Where was violence against women not a central issue of feminism? (re: lead of second-wave feminism) --&gt; a central issue. Organizations such as [[V-Day (movement)|V-Day]] formed with the goal of ending gender violence, and artistic expressions, such as ''[[The Vagina Monologues]],'' generated awareness. Third-wave feminists wanted to transform traditional notions of sexuality and embrace "an exploration of women's feelings about sexuality that included vagina-centred topics as diverse as orgasm, birth, and rape".&lt;ref name=Brunell2008&gt;Brunell, Laura (2008). [https://www.britannica.com/topic/Feminism-Reimagined-The-Third-Wave-1376924 "Feminism Re-Imagined: The Third Wave"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180922115211/https://www.britannica.com/topic/Feminism-Reimagined-The-Third-Wave-1376924 |date=2018-09-22 }}. ''Encyclopædia Britannica Book of the Year''. Chicago: Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reproductive rights===
{{Main|Reproductive rights}}
One of third-wave feminism's primary goals was to demonstrate that access to contraception and abortion are women's reproductive rights. According to Baumgardner and Richards, "It is not feminism's goal to control any woman's fertility, only to free each woman to control her own."&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards"/&gt; South Dakota's 2006 attempt to ban abortion in all cases, except when necessary to protect the mother's life,&lt;ref name="Davey"&gt;{{Cite news |last=Davey |first=Monica |title=South Dakota Bans Abortion, Setting Up a Battle | newspaper= The New York Times |volume=155 |issue=53511 |pages=A1–A14 |date=7 March 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the US Supreme Court's vote to uphold the [[partial birth abortion]] ban were viewed as restrictions on women's civil and reproductive rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Ludlow | first = Jeannie | title=Sometimes, It's a Child and a Choice: Toward an Embodied Abortion Praxis | journal=[[NWSA Journal]]| volume=20 | issue= 1 | pages=26–50 | date=Spring 2008| oclc=364432908 | jstor=40071251}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1=Weitz | first1=Tracy A.| last2=Yanow | first2=Susan | title=Implications of the Federal Abortion Ban for Women's Health in the United States| journal=Reproductive Health Matters |volume=16 |issue=31 |pages=99–107 |date=May 2008 | doi=10.1016/S0968-8080(08)31374-3 | pmid=18772090 | oclc=282104847 | jstor=25475407| s2cid=10189579}}&lt;/ref&gt; Restrictions on abortion in the US, which was mostly legalized by the 1973 Supreme Court decision in ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'', were becoming more common in states around the country. These included mandatory waiting periods,&lt;ref&gt;[[Indiana Code]] [http://www.in.gov/legislative/ic/code/title16/ar34/ch2.html#IC16-34-2-1.1 Title 16, art. XXXIV, ch. 2, § 1.1 cl. 1: Voluntary and informed consent required; viewing of fetal ultrasound] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090409200304/http://www.in.gov/legislative/ic/code/title16/ar34/ch2.html#IC16-34-2-1.1 |date=2009-04-09 }} x (1993; amended 1997)&lt;/ref&gt; parental-consent laws,&lt;ref&gt;[[Government of South Dakota|South Dakota]] Code [http://legis.state.sd.us/statutes/DisplayStatute.aspx?Type=Statute&amp;Statute=34-23A-7 Title 34, ch. 23A, § 7] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090208231736/http://legis.state.sd.us/statutes/DisplayStatute.aspx?Statute=34-23A-7&amp;Type=Statute |date=2009-02-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and spousal-consent laws.&lt;ref&gt;[[South Carolina Constitution|South Carolina]] Code [http://www.scstatehouse.gov/code/t44c041.htm#44-41-10 Title 44, ch. 41, art. 1, § 10] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110721061925/http://www.scstatehouse.gov/code/t44c041.htm#44-41-10 |date=2011-07-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reclaiming derogatory terms===
[[File:Toronto-Slutwalk.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|The first [[Slutwalk]], Toronto, 2011]]
English speakers continued to use words such as ''[[spinster]]'', ''bitch'', ''[[whore]]'', and ''[[cunt]]'' to refer to women in derogatory ways. [[Inga Muscio]] wrote, "I posit that we're free to seize a word that was kidnapped and co-opted in a pain-filled, distant past, with a ransom that cost our grandmothers' freedom, children, traditions, pride and land."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Muscio |first=Inga |authorlink=Inga Muscio |title=Cunt: A Declaration of Independence |location=Seattle |publisher=Seal Press |year=1998 |p=[https://archive.org/details/cuntdeclarationo00musc_0/page/9 9] |isbn=978-1-58005-015-9 |url=https://archive.org/details/cuntdeclarationo00musc_0/page/9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Taking back the word ''bitch'' was fueled by the single "[[All Women Are Bitches]]" (1994) by the all-woman band [[Fifth Column (band)|Fifth Column]], and by the book ''Bitch: In Praise of Difficult Women'' (1999) by [[Elizabeth Wurtzel]].&lt;ref name="Wurtzel 1998"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Wurtzel|first=Elizabeth|title=Bitch: In Praise of Difficult Women|page=|year=1998|publisher=[[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]]|location=New York|isbn=978-0-385-48400-8|oclc=38144418|url=https://archive.org/details/bitchinpraiseofd00wurt_0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The utility of the reclamation strategy became a hot topic with the introduction of [[SlutWalk]]s in 2011. The first took place in Toronto on 3 April that year in response to a Toronto police officer's remark that "women should avoid dressing like sluts in order not to be victimized."&lt;ref name="slutwalktoronto1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slutwalktoronto.com/about/why|title=SlutWalk Toronto|access-date=2011-05-28|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110522042925/http://www.slutwalktoronto.com/about/why|archive-date=2011-05-22|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additional SlutWalks sprang up internationally, including in Berlin, London, New York City, Seattle, and West Hollywood.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;{{cite web|title=Slutwalks – Do you agree with the Toronto policeman?|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p00ggb5t|work=World Have Your Say 60|publisher=BBC|access-date=2011-05-28|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110514134350/http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p00ggb5t|archive-date=2011-05-14|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several feminist bloggers criticized the campaign; reclamation of the word ''slut'' was questioned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Murphy|first=Meghan|title=We're sluts, not feminists. Wherein my relationship with Slutwalk gets rocky.|url=http://www.feminisms.org/2585/were-sluts-not-feminists-wherein-my-relationship-with-slutwalk-gets-rocky/|work=The F-Word|access-date=2011-05-28|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110610062654/http://www.feminisms.org/2585/were-sluts-not-feminists-wherein-my-relationship-with-slutwalk-gets-rocky/|archive-date=2011-06-10|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Beyerstein|first=Lindsay|title=Sluts Like Me|url=http://bigthink.com/ideas/38362|work=Big Think|access-date=2011-05-28|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110521232025/http://bigthink.com/ideas/38362|archive-date=2011-05-21|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Women: Should they have autonomy?|url=http://shakespearessister.blogspot.com/2011/05/women-should-they-have-autonomy.html|work=Women: Shakesville|access-date=2011-05-28|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110727030246/http://shakespearessister.blogspot.com/2011/05/women-should-they-have-autonomy.html|archive-date=2011-07-27|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Walia|first=Harsha|title=Slutwalk – To March or Not to March|url=http://www.racialicious.com/2011/05/19/slutwalk-–-to-march-or-not-to-march/|work=Racialicious|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120801101813/http://www.racialicious.com/2011/05/19/slutwalk-%E2%80%93-to-march-or-not-to-march/|archivedate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sexual liberation ===
Third-wave feminists expanded the second-wave feminist's definition of sexual liberation to "mean a process of first becoming conscious of the ways one's gender identity and sexuality have been shaped by society and then intentionally constructing (and becoming free to express) one's authentic gender identity".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia|url=http://www.britannica.com/topic/feminism/The-third-wave-of-feminism.|title=feminism {{!}} Definition, History, &amp; Examples|encyclopedia=Encyclopedia Britannica|access-date=2018-10-08|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since third-wave feminism relied on different personal definitions to explain feminism, there is controversy surrounding what sexual liberation really entails. Many third-wave feminists supported the idea that women should embrace their sexuality as a way to take back their power.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Harnois|first=Catherine|date=Spring 2008|title=Re-Presenting Feminisms: Past, Present, and Future|url=|journal=NWSA Journal|volume=|pages=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other issues===
Third-wave feminism regarded race, social class, and transgender rights&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Yenor|first1=Scott|title=The Rolling Revolution in Sex and Gender: A History|url=https://www.thepublicdiscourse.com/2017/07/19766/|website=Public Discourse|publisher=[[Witherspoon Institute]]|date=July 31, 2017|accessdate=21 April 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181215060405/https://www.thepublicdiscourse.com/2017/07/19766/|archive-date=15 December 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Grady|first1=Constance|title=The waves of feminism, and why people keep fighting over them, explained|url=https://www.vox.com/2018/3/20/16955588/feminism-waves-explained-first-second-third-fourth|website=[[Vox (website)|Vox]]|date=July 20, 2018|accessdate=21 April 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190405172242/https://www.vox.com/2018/3/20/16955588/feminism-waves-explained-first-second-third-fourth|archive-date=5 April 2019|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; as central issues. It also paid attention to workplace matters such as the [[glass ceiling]], unfair [[maternity leave|maternity-leave]] policies,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | first = Frank | last=Munden | title=Female medical workers feel maternity leave unfair| journal=The Kapi'o Newspress | volume=36 | issue=28|date= 7 May 2003|url=http://kapio.kcc.hawaii.edu/archive/v36/36_28/nurse.html| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090228075410/http://kapio.kcc.hawaii.edu/archive/v36/36_28/nurse.html| archivedate=28 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; motherhood support for [[single mother]]s by means of [[Welfare (financial aid)|welfare]] and [[child care]], respect for working mothers, and the rights of mothers who decide to leave their careers to raise their children full-time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|chapter-url=http://cupola.gettysburg.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1017&amp;context=poliscifac|chapter=Women's Leadership and Third-Wave Feminism|last=Iannello|first=Kathleen|editor1-first=Karen|editor1-last=O'Connor|title=Gender and Women's Leadership: A Reference Handbook|publisher=Sage Publishing|year=2010|isbn=978-1412960830|location=|pages=70–77|quote=|via=The Cupola at Gettysburg College}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism ==
===Lack of cohesion===
One issue raised by critics was a lack of cohesion because of the absence of a single cause for third-wave feminism. The first wave fought for and gained the right for women to vote. The second wave fought for the right for women to have access to an equal opportunity in the workforce, as well as the end of legal sex discrimination. The third wave allegedly lacked a cohesive goal and was often seen as an extension of the second wave.&lt;ref name="Rowe-Finbeiner" /&gt; Some argued that the third wave could be dubbed the "Second Wave, Part Two" when it came to the politics of feminism and that "only young feminist culture" was "truly third wave".&lt;ref name="Baumgardner_Richards" /&gt; One argument ran that the equation of third-wave feminism with individualism prevented the movement from growing and moving towards political goals. Kathleen P. Iannello wrote:

{{quote|sign=|source=|"The conceptual and real-world 'trap' of choice feminism (between work and home) has led women to challenge each other rather than the patriarchy. Individualism conceived of as 'choice' does not empower women; it silences them and prevents feminism from becoming a political movement and addressing the real issues of distribution of resources."&lt;ref name=Iannello2011&gt;{{Cite book|chapter-url=https://rachelyon1.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/third-wave-feminism.pdf|chapter=Third-Wave Feminism and Individualism: Promoting Equality or Reinforcing the Status Quo?|last=Iannello|first=Katherine P.|year=1998|title=Women in Politics: Outsiders or Insiders? A Collection of Readings|editor1-last=Whitaker|editor1-first=Lois Duke|location=Boston, Mass|publisher=Longman}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Objection to "wave construct"===
Feminist scholars such as [[Shira Tarrant]] objected to the "wave construct" because it ignored important progress between the periods. Furthermore, if feminism is a global movement, she argued, the fact that the "first-, second-, and third waves time periods correspond most closely to American feminist developments" raises serious problems about how feminism fails to recognize the history of political issues around the world.&lt;ref name="Tarrant"&gt;{{cite book|last=Tarrant|first=Shira|title=When Sex Became Gender|url=https://archive.org/details/whensexbecamegen00tarr|url-access=limited|page=[https://archive.org/details/whensexbecamegen00tarr/page/n14 222]|year=2006|publisher=Routledge|location=New York|isbn=978-0-415-95347-4|oclc=62281555}}&lt;/ref&gt; The "wave construct", critics argued, also focused on white women's suffrage and continued to marginalize the issues of women of color and lower-class women.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

===Relationship with women of color===
Third-wave feminists proclaim themselves as the most inclusive wave of feminism. Critics have noted that while progressive, there is still exclusion of women of color. Black feminists argue that "the women rights movements were not uniquely for the liberation of Blacks or Black Women. Rather, efforts such as women's suffrage and abolition of slavery ultimately uplifted, strengthened, and benefited White society and White women".&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Marbley|first=Aretha Faye|date=Fall 2005|title=African-American Women's Feelings of Alienation from Third-Wave Feminism: A Conversation with My Sisters|url=|journal=Western Journal of Black Studies|volume=|pages=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==="Girly" feminism===
Third-wave feminism was often associated, primarily by its critics, with the emergence of so-called "lipstick" or "girly" feminists and the rise of "raunch culture". This was because these new feminists advocated "expressions of femininity and female sexuality as a challenge to objectification". Accordingly, this included the dismissal of any restriction, whether deemed patriarchal or feminist, to define or control how women or girls should dress, act, or generally express themselves.&lt;ref name="Newman &amp; White 2012 246"&gt;{{harvnb|Newman|White|2012|p=246}}&lt;/ref&gt; These emerging positions stood in stark contrast with the [[Feminist views of pornography|anti-pornography]] strains of feminism prevalent in the 1980s. Second-wave feminism viewed pornography as encouraging violence towards women.&lt;ref name=Iannello2011/&gt; The new feminists posited that the ability to make autonomous choices about self-expression could be an empowering act of resistance, not simply [[internalized oppression]].

Such views were critiqued because of the subjective nature of [[empowerment]] and autonomy. Scholars were unsure whether empowerment was best measured as an "internal feeling of power and agency" or as an external "measure of power and control". Moreover they critiqued an over-investment in "a model of free will and choice" in the marketplace of identities and ideas.{{sfn|Newman|White|2012|p=247}} Regardless, the "girly" feminists attempted to be open to all different selves while maintaining a dialogue about the meaning of identity and femininity in the contemporary world.

Third-wave feminists said that these viewpoints should not be limited by the label "girly" feminism or regarded as simply advocating "raunch culture". Rather, they sought to be inclusive of the many diverse roles women fulfill. Gender scholars {{ill|Linda Duits|nl}} and Liesbet van Zoonen highlighted this inclusivity by looking at the politicization of women's clothing choices and how the "controversial [[sartorial]] choices of girls" and women are constituted in public discourse as "a locus of necessary regulation".&lt;ref name="Newman &amp; White 2012 246"/&gt; Thus the "[[hijab]]" and the "[[Crop top|belly shirt]]", as dress choices, were both identified as requiring regulation but for different reasons. Both caused controversy, while appearing to be opposing forms of self-expression. Through the lens of "girly" feminists, one can view both as symbolic of "political agency and resistance to objectification". The "hijab" could be seen as an act of resistance against Western ambivalence towards Islamic identity, and the "belly shirt" an act of resistance against patriarchal society's narrow views of female sexuality. Both were regarded as valid forms of self-expression.{{sfn|Newman|White|2012|p=247}}

== Timeline ==
===1990s===
{| class="wikitable" style="font-size:95%; width: 90%; text-align:left; float:center; margin-left:10px;"
|-
! scope="col" style="width:10em;"|Date
! Event
|-
|1990||Publication of [[Naomi Wolf]], ''[[The Beauty Myth]]''.
|-
| 1991 ||[[Riot grrrl]] movement begins in [[Olympia, Washington]] and [[Washington, D.C.]] in the US.&lt;ref name=Rowe-Finbeiner/&gt;
|-
|March 1991||In ''[[R v R]]'', the House of Lords in the UK rules that a [[marital rape]] exemption does not exist in English law.
|-
|March 1991|| In ''[[United Automobile Workers v. Johnson Controls, Inc.]]'', the US Supreme Court declares that employers cannot exclude women from jobs in which exposure to toxic substances could harm a developing fetus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=499&amp;invol=187 |title=FindLaw &amp;#124; Cases and Codes |publisher=Caselaw.lp.findlaw.com |access-date=2012-09-28 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121114025317/http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=499&amp;invol=187 |archive-date=2012-11-14 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|May 1991||Release of the film ''[[Thelma and Louise]]'': "It took all those feelings of alienation and anger—which until that point had mostly found expression in things like 'Take Back the Night' rallies—and turned them into something rebellious, transgressive, iconic, punk rock and mainstream." – Carina Chocano, ''New York Times''.&lt;ref&gt;Chocano, Carina (21 April 2011). [https://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/24/magazine/mag-24Riff-t.html "Thelma, Louise and All the Pretty Women"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180928213913/https://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/24/magazine/mag-24Riff-t.html |date=2018-09-28 }}, ''The New York Times''.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|31 July 1991||The US Senate votes overwhelmingly to open combat positions for women aviators.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Eric|last=Schmitt|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1991/08/01/us/senate-votes-to-remove-ban-on-women-as-combat-pilots.html|title=Senate Votes to Remove Ban on Women as Combat Pilots|work=The New York Times|date=1 August 1991|access-date=2 June 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160307015324/http://www.nytimes.com/1991/08/01/us/senate-votes-to-remove-ban-on-women-as-combat-pilots.html|archive-date=7 March 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1991||[[Susan Faludi]] publishes ''[[Backlash: The Undeclared War Against American Women]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Emily |last=Wilson |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2005/dec/13/classics.gender |title=Backlash by Susan Faludi |work=The Guardian |date=13 December 2005 |access-date=2 June 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171228042301/https://www.theguardian.com/books/2005/dec/13/classics.gender |archive-date=28 December 2017 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|July 1991||[[Clarence Thomas Supreme Court nomination]] and the televised testimony in October of [[Anita Hill]] that he had sexually harassed her.
|-
|October 1991||"Opportunity 2000" is launched in the UK to increase women's employment opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Judy (28 December 1992). [https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/equality-campaign-for-women-falters-1565691.html "Equality campaign for women falters"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181104022931/https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/equality-campaign-for-women-falters-1565691.html |date=2018-11-04 }}, ''The Independent''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fenman.co.uk/traineractive/training-activity/Equal-opportunities-for-women.html |title=Equal opportunities for women Training Activity – TrainerActive, Training Activity Portal |publisher=Fenman.co.uk |accessdate=2012-10-31 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121123003115/http://www.fenman.co.uk/traineractive/training-activity/Equal-opportunities-for-women.html |archive-date=2012-11-23 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1990"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/1990.shtml |title=BBC Radio 4 – Woman's Hour – Women's History Timeline: 1990–1999 |publisher=BBC |access-date=2012-10-31 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120319071725/http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/1990.shtml |archive-date=2012-03-19 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|January 1992||In response to the Thomas nomination, American feminist [[Rebecca Walker]] publishes "Becoming the Third Wave" in ''[[Ms. (magazine)|Ms.]]'' magazine.&lt;ref name="Walker1992" /&gt;
|-
|1992||Four women enter the [[United States Senate|US Senate]] to join the two already there, lending 1992 the label "[[Year of the Woman]]" in the US.
|-
|1992||Third Wave Direct Action Corporation (later Third Wave Foundation) founded in the US by [[Rebecca Walker]] and [[Shannon Liss-Riordan]] to support young activists&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Third Wave Foundation |url=http://thirdwavefund.org/history.html |title=History |publisher=Third Wave Foundation |accessdate=2012-10-31 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151025214042/http://thirdwavefund.org/history.html |archivedate=2015-10-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.masslive.com/news/2019/05/shannon-liss-riordan-touts-fresh-perspective-in-campaign-to-unseat-us-sen-ed-markey.html|title=Shannon Liss-Riordan touts 'fresh perspective' in campaign to unseat U.S. Sen. Ed Markey|last=Schoenberg|first=Shira|date=2019-05-22|website=masslive.com|language=en-US|access-date=2019-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1993||[[Family and Medical Leave Act]] becomes law in the US.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/family_and_medical_leave_act_1993 |title=Family and Medical Leave Act (1993) &amp;#124; LII / Legal Information Institute |publisher=Law.cornell.edu |date=2012-10-12 |accessdate=2012-10-31 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121025122953/http://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/family_and_medical_leave_act_1993 |archive-date=2012-10-25 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1993||[[Janet Reno]] nominated and confirmed as the first female US Attorney General after President [[Bill Clinton]]'s previous choices, [[Zoe Baird|Zoë Baird]] and [[Kimba Wood]], fail because of [[Nannygate]].
|-
||1993||"Take Our Daughters to Work Day" debuts in the US to build girls' self-esteem and open their eyes to a variety of career possibilities for women. It was later renamed [[Take Our Daughters and Sons to Work Day]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ms.foundation.org/about_us/our-history/take-our-daughters-and-sons-to-work |title=Ms. Foundation for Women – Take Our Daughters and Sons to Work |publisher=ms.foundation.org |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121018030645/http://ms.foundation.org/about_us/our-history/take-our-daughters-and-sons-to-work |archivedate=2012-10-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1993||First edition of ''[[Bust (magazine)|Bust]]'' magazine appears, founded by Laurie Henzel, [[Marcelle Karp]], and [[Debbie Stoller]].
|-
|1994||Women taking back the word ''bitch'' are helped by the single "[[All Women Are Bitches]]" by the all-woman Canadian band [[Fifth Column (band)|Fifth Column]].
|-
|1994||[[Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994]] confirms that [[marital rape]] is illegal in the UK.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1990"/&gt;
|-
|1994||[[Violence Against Women Act]] becomes law in the US and establishes the [[Office on Violence Against Women]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.legalmomentum.org/history-vawa|title=History of the Violence Against Women Act|website=Legal Momentum|access-date=2016-04-26|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160519144926/http://www.legalmomentum.org/history-vawa|archive-date=2016-05-19|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1995||Publication of [[Rebecca Walker]] (ed.), ''To Be Real: Telling the Truth and Changing the Face of Feminism''.&lt;ref name=Snyder2008&gt;{{harvnb|Snyder|2008|pp=176–177}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1995||[[Fourth World Conference on Women]] held in China.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1990"/&gt;
|-
|1996||[[Northern Ireland Women's Coalition]] founded.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1990"/&gt;
|-
|1996||Feminist play ''[[The Vagina Monologues]]'', by American playwright [[Eve Ensler]], premieres in New York.&lt;ref name="qsanantonio.com"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://qsanantonio.com/vday2.html |title="Vagina Monologues" performances mark S.A. V-Day |publisher=QSanAntonio |date=25 February 2012 |access-date=28 September 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120810202654/http://www.qsanantonio.com/vday2.html |archive-date=10 August 2012 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Ensler |first=Eve |authorlink=Eve Ensler|title=The Vagina Monologues |publisher=[[Villard (imprint)|Villard]] |year=2001 |location=New York |isbn=978-0-375-75052-6 |oclc=37492271 |title-link=The Vagina Monologues }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
||1996||In [[United States v. Virginia]], the US Supreme Court rules that male-only admissions policy of state-supported Virginia Military Institute violates the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.oyez.org/cases/1990-1999/1995/1995_94_1941 |title=United States v. Virginia |publisher=The Oyez Project at IIT Chicago-Kent College of Law |accessdate=2012-10-31 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121104094720/http://www.oyez.org/cases/1990-1999/1995/1995_94_1941 |archive-date=2012-11-04 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1996||First edition of the magazine ''[[Bitch (magazine)|Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture]]'' appears.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bitchmagazine.org/history|title=Bitch Magazine: Our History|work=Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture|access-date=2019-06-02|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110610080910/http://bitchmagazine.org/history|archive-date=2011-06-10|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1997||Publication of Leslie Heywood and Jennifer Drake (eds.), ''Third Wave Agenda: Being Feminist, Doing Feminism''.&lt;ref name=Snyder2008/&gt;
|-
|1997||Turkish feminist [[Şenal Sarıhan]] shared the [[Robert F. Kennedy Human Rights Award]].
|-
|1997||[[Layli Miller-Muro]] founds the [[Tahirih Justice Center]] in the US following [[Matter of Kasinga]], an asylum case dealing with [[female genital mutilation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tahirih.org/services/|title=Services|author=Tahirih Justice Center|accessdate=30 November 2014|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006095120/http://www.tahirih.org/services/|archivedate=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1998||[[Eve Ensler]] and others, including [[Willa Shalit]], a producer of the Westside Theatre production of ''[[The Vagina Monologues]]'', launch V-Day, a global non-profit movement that raises over $75&amp;nbsp;million for women's [[sexual violence|anti-violence]] groups.&lt;ref name="qsanantonio.com"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.womensmediacenter.com/ex/013008.html|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100104191925/http://womensmediacenter.com/ex/013008.html|archive-date=4 January 2010|title=From Superdome to SUPERLOVE—V-Day at 10|first=Marianne|last=Schnall|date=January 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1999||Publication of [[Germaine Greer]], ''The Whole Woman''
|-
|1999||Publication of [[Marcelle Karp]] and [[Debbie Stoller]] (eds.), ''The BUST Guide to the New Girl Order''.&lt;ref name=Snyder2008/&gt;
|-
|1999||Publication of [[Elizabeth Wurtzel]], ''Bitch: In Praise of Difficult Women''.&lt;ref name="Wurtzel 1998"/&gt;
|-
|1999||Publication of [[Carol Ann Duffy]], ''The World's Wife''
|}

===2000s===
{| class="wikitable" style="font-size:95%; width: 90%; text-align:left; float:center; margin-left:10px;"
|-
! scope="col" style="width:10em;"|Date
! Event
|-
|2000||Publication of [[Jennifer Baumgardner]] and [[Amy Richards]], ''Manifesta: Young Women, Feminism, and the Future''{{sfn|Baumgardner|Richards|2000}}
|-
|October 2000||CBS agrees to pay $8&amp;nbsp;million to settle a sex discrimination lawsuit on behalf of 200 women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-72470958.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160911033207/https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-72470958.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=2016-09-11 |title=CBS to pay $8&amp;nbsp;million to settle sex discrimination lawsuit |last=Carlson|first=Scott|publisher=Knight Ridder/Tribune News Service |date=2000-10-25 |accessdate=2016-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|2001||The [[Isle of Man]] passes its first sex-discrimination bill.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/2000.shtml |title=Women's History Timeline: 2000–now |publisher=Woman's Hour, BBC Radio 4 |accessdate=2012-10-31 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151019051316/http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/2000.shtml |archive-date=2015-10-19 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|2001||[[Condoleezza Rice]] becomes the first female US national security adviser.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2004||The [[March for Women's Lives]] is held in Washington, D.C., to support the right to abortion, access to birth control, scientifically accurate sex education, and prevention and treatment of sexually transmitted infections, and to show public support for mothers and children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guttmacher.org/media/inthenews/2005/04/25/index.html |title=March for Women's Lives |publisher=Guttmacher.org |date=April 25, 2005 |access-date=September 28, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130310100654/http://www.guttmacher.org/media/inthenews/2005/04/25/index.html |archive-date=March 10, 2013 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|2004||Asylum Gender Guidelines are introduced by the UK for female asylum seekers.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2004|| Publication of Vivien Labaton and Dawn Lundy (eds.), ''The Fire This Time: Young Activists and the New Feminism''.&lt;ref name=Snyder2008/&gt;
|-
|2004|| Start of ''[[Feministing]]'' blog by [[Jessica Valenti]] and Vanessa Valenti.
|-
|2005||[[Ellen Johnson Sirleaf]] in Liberia becomes Africa's first elected woman leader and the first black female president in the world.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2005||[[Angela Merkel]] becomes Germany's first female chancellor.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2007||[[Nancy Pelosi]] becomes the first woman Speaker in the US Congress.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|1 April 2007||The Gender Equality Duty of the [[Equality Act 2006]] comes into effect in the UK. It requires public authorities "to promote equality of opportunity between women and men".&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2007||Publication of [[Jessica Valenti]], ''Full Frontal Feminism: A Young Woman's Guide to Why Feminism Matters''.
|-
|2007
|Publication of [[Julia Serano|Julia Serrano]], ''[[Whipping Girl|Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Feminism and the Scapegoating of Femininity]]''
|-
|2008||Publication of [[Jaclyn Friedman]] and Jessica Valenti (eds.), ''[[Yes Means Yes]]''.
|-
|2008||Norway requires of all companies that at least 40 percent of their board members be women.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|May 2008|| In Los Angeles, Diana Bijon's husband, Michael, takes her last name upon marriage, after their lawsuit led to a new California state law guaranteeing the rights of married couples and registered domestic partners to choose whichever last name they prefer.&lt;ref name="DianaBijon"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2008/05/05/us-usa-name-idUKN0541896320080505 |title=Los Angeles man wins right to use wife's last name |work=Reuters |date=2008-05-05 |access-date=2012-12-03 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130506055814/http://uk.reuters.com/article/2008/05/05/us-usa-name-idUKN0541896320080505 |archive-date=2013-05-06 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|2008||[[Forced Marriage (Civil Protection) Act 2007]] comes into force in the UK.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
|2009||In the UK, [[Carol Ann Duffy]] becomes the first female [[Poet Laureate of the United Kingdom|Poet Laureate]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated2000"/&gt;
|-
| 3 April 2011 || First [[SlutWalk]] takes place in Toronto in response to Toronto police officer Michael Sanguinetti's statement that "women should avoid dressing like sluts in order not to be victimized".{{sfn|Chamberlain|2017|pp=114–115}}&lt;ref name="slutwalktoronto1"/&gt;
|-
|}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book |last1=Chamberlain |first1=Prudence |title=The feminist fourth wave : affective temporality |date=2017 |publisher=Springer |isbn=9783319536828 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8AIkDwAAQBAJ |accessdate=27 May 2019}}
*{{cite book|last=Evans|first=Elizabeth|year=2015|title=The Politics of Third Wave Feminisms: Neoliberalism, Intersectionality, and the State in Britain and the US|location=London|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=978-1-137-29527-9}}
*{{Cite book| last1 = Gillis | last2 = Howie | last3=Munford | first1=Stacy | first2=Gillian | first3=Rebecca |author2-link=Gillian Howie |title=Third Wave Feminism: A Critical Exploration |edition=Revised| publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |year=2007 |isbn=978-1-4039-1821-5}}
*{{Cite book|last=Henry|first=Astrid |title=Not My Mother's Sister: Generational Conflict and Third-Wave Feminism|year=2004|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]] |location=[[Bloomington, Indiana|Bloomington]] |oclc=53932637 |isbn=978-0-253-21713-4 }}
*{{cite book |title=Manifesta: Young Women, Feminism, and the Future |last1=Baumgardner |first1=Jennifer |author1-link=Jennifer Baumgardner |last2=Richards |first2=Amy |author2-link=Amy Richards |year=2000 |publisher=[[Farrar, Straus and Giroux]] |location=New York |isbn=978-0-374-52622-1 |url=https://archive.org/details/manifestayoungwo00baum }}
*{{cite book|last1=Newman|first1=Jacquetta A.|last2=White|first2=Linda Ann|title=Women, Politics, and Public Policy: The Political Struggles of Canadian Women|year=2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Toronto|isbn=9780195432497|edition=2nd}}
*{{Cite journal|last=Snyder|first=R. Claire|date=1 September 2008|title=What Is Third‐Wave Feminism? A New Directions Essay|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|volume=34|issue=1|pages=175–196|doi=10.1086/588436|jstor=10.1086/588436|issn=0097-9740}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Baumgardner |first1=Jennifer |author1-link= Jennifer Baumgardner |last2=Richards| first2=Amy |author2-link=Amy Richards |title=Grassroots: A Field Guide for Feminist Activism |location=New York |publisher=Farrar, Straus, and Giroux |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-374-52865-2}}
* {{cite journal | last = Evans | first = Elizabeth | title = What makes a (third) wave?| journal = International Feminist Journal of Politics | volume = 18 | issue = 3 | pages = 409–428| doi = 10.1080/14616742.2015.1027627 | date = 2016 | s2cid = 145102947 | url = https://research-information.bristol.ac.uk/en/publications/what-makes-a-third-wave(7fb16f95-5556-4a3f-b3c0-178a0cf69671).html }}
*{{cite book|first=Leela|last=Fernandes|chapter=Unsettling 'Third Wave Feminism': Feminist Waves, Intersectionality, and Identity Politics in Retrospect|editor-last1=Hewitt|editor-first1=Nancy|title=No Permanent Waves: Recasting Histories of U.S. Feminism|publisher=Rutgers University Press|isbn=978-0-8135-4724-4|year=2010}}
* {{Cite book |editor-last=Findlen |editor-first=Barbara |title=Listen Up! Voices from the Next Feminist Generation |publisher=Seal Press |year=1995 |location=Seattle |isbn=978-1-878067-61-6 |url=https://archive.org/details/listenupvoicesfr00find }}
* {{Cite journal |last=Harnois |first=Catherine |title=Re-presenting feminisms: Past, present, and future |journal=NWSA Journal|volume=20 |issue=1 |pages=120–145 |year=2008 |doi=10.1353/nwsa.0.0010 |jstor=40071255 |url=http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/nwsa_journal/summary/v020/20.1.harnois.html|doi-broken-date=2020-09-10 }}
* {{Cite book |last1=Hernández |first1=Daisy |last2=Reman |first2=Bushra |author1-link=Daisy Hernández |title=Colonize This! Young Women of Color and Today's Feminism |publisher=Seal Press |year=2002 |isbn=978-1-58005-067-8 |url=https://archive.org/details/colonizethisyoun0000hern }}
* Heywood, Leslie L., ed. (2005). ''The Women's Movement Today: An Encyclopedia of Third-Wave Feminism''. 2 vols. Westport: Greenwood Press.
* {{cite journal | last = Hitchens | first = Donna | title = Feminism in the Nineties: Coalition Strategies | journal = Yale Journal of Law and Feminism | volume = 4 | issue = 1 | pages = 57–63| date = Fall 1991 | url = http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?handle=hein.journals/yjfem4&amp;div=12&amp;id=&amp;page=}} [http://digitalcommons.law.yale.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1050&amp;context=yjlf Pdf.]
* {{Cite book |last=Karaian |first=Lara |editor1-last=Rundle |editor1-first=Lisa Bryn |editor2-last=Mitchell |editor2-first=Allyson |editor2-link=Allyson Mitchell |title=Turbo Chicks: Talking Young Feminisms |location=Toronto |publisher=Sumach Press |year=2001 |isbn=978-1-894549-06-6 |oclc=46629305 |url=https://archive.org/details/turbochickstalki0000unse }}
* {{Cite journal |last=Kinser |first=Amber E. |title=Negotiating spaces for/through third-wave feminism |journal=NWSA Journal |volume=16 |issue=3 |pages=124–153 |year=2004 |doi=10.2979/NWS.2004.16.3.124 |jstor=4317084 |s2cid=145349611 |url=http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/nwsa_journal/summary/v016/16.3kinser.html }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Springer | first = Kimberly | title = Third Wave Black Feminism? | journal = [[Signs (journal)|Signs]] | volume = 27 | issue = 4 | pages = 1059–1082 | doi = 10.1086/339636 | jstor = 10.1086/339636 | date = Summer 2002}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* [http://heathengrrl.blogspot.com/2007/02/becoming-third-wave-by-rebecca-walker.html "Becoming the Third Wave" by Rebecca Walker]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050130091522/http://www.rebeccawalker.com/article_2005_riding-the-third-wave.htm interview with Rebecca Walker in Satya Magazine]
* [http://www.metroactive.com/papers/cruz/11.29.00/feminism-0048.html Interview with Jennifer Baumgardner and Amy Richards]

{{Feminism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:3}}
[[Category:Third-wave feminism| ]]
[[Category:1990s establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Feminism and history]]
[[Category:History of women's rights in the United States]]

[[de:Feminismus#Dritte Welle]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>