<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113204751|87606845" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="748253" pageid="748253" ns="0" title="Third-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T20:48:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Third-wave feminism''' is a term identified with several diverse strains of feminist activity and study beginning in the early [[1990s]]. The movement arose as a response to perceived failures of [[second-wave feminism]]. It was also a response to the backlash against initiatives and movements created by the second-wave. 

==Overview==
''Third-wave feminism'' seeks to challenge or avoid what it deems the second wave's "[[Essentialism|''essentialist'']]" definitions of femininity, which (according to the third wave) often assumed a universal female identity and over-emphasized the experiences of upper middle class white women.  A [[Post-structuralism|post-structuralist]] interpretation of gender and sexuality is also central to much of the third wave and helps to account for its heightened emphasis on the discursive power and fundamental ambiguity inherent in all gender terms and categories. Third wave theory usually encompasses [[queer theory]], women-of-color consciousness, [[post-colonial theory]], [[critical theory]], [[transnationalism]], [[ecofeminism]], and new [[feminist theory]]. 

Third wave feminists often focus on "micropolitics," writing about forms of gender expression and representation that are less explicitly political than their predecessors. They also challenged the second wave's paradigm as to what is, or is not, good for females.

===Third wave in popular culture===
Ideals and debates associated with third-wave feminism were reflected in popular culture of the [[1990]]s and [[2000s]].  Some feminists see it as a cultural movement and trace its origin to the early 90's [[riot grrl]] movement.

:See main articles: ''[[Girl Power]]'' and ''[[Buffy studies]]''

==History==

In the fall of 1991, President [[George H. W. Bush]] nominated [[Clarence Thomas]] to the Supreme Court.  During the Senate Judiciary Committee hearings, [[Anita Hill]], an African-American law professor from Oklahoma, came forward and said that she had been sexually harassed by Thomas almost a decade earlier, while she had been employed under him.  In response to the Thomas hearings, [[Rebecca Walker]] published an article entitled “Becoming the Third Wave” in a 1992 issue of [[Ms. magazine|''Ms.'']] in which she declared, “I am not a [[Post-feminism|postfeminism]] feminist.  I am the Third Wave.”   This event is often marked as the beginning of the usage of the term third wave applied to feminism (the "wave" concept of social progress was floated by futurist [[Alvin Toffler]] in his 1980 book entitled ''[[The Third Wave (book)|The Third Wave]]'').  As Amber Kisner has argued, Walker's was "a notable expansion of feminist space for women of color."

The roots of the Third Wave began, however, in the mid 1980's. Feminist leaders rooted in the second wave like [[Gloria Anzaldua]], [[bell hooks]], [[Chela Sandoval]], [[Cherrie Moraga]], [[Audre Lorde]], [[Maxine Hong Kingston]], and many other feminists of color, called for a new subjectivity in feminist voice.  They sought to negotiate prominent space within feminist thought for consideration of race related subjectivities. This focus on the intersection between race and gender remained prominent through the Hill-Thomas hearings, but began to shift with the [[Freedom Ride 1992]].  This drive to register voters in poor communities of color was surrounded with rhetoric that focused on rallying young feminists.  For many, the rallying of the young is the emphasis that has stuck within third wave feminism.

== Dietary concerns ==

Some [[third-wave feminists]] such as [[Carol Adams]] [http://www.triroc.com/caroladams/slideshow.html] reject the consumption of meat and analogize the use and objectification of animals to the use and objectification of women in society.  This criticism focuses on societal construction of ties between [[women]] and the [[natural environment|environment]] and references the fact that a large majority of livestock animals are female.

==References==
* Jennifer Baumgardner, Amy Richards: ''Manifesta: Young Women, Feminism, and the Future'', Farrar, Straus and Giroux 2000, ISBN 0-374-52622-2
* Jennifer Baumgardner, Amy Richards, Winona LaDuke: ''Grassroots : A Field Guide for Feminist Activism'', Farrar, Straus and Giroux 2005, ISBN 0-374-52865-9
*Dekoven, Marianne. "Jouissance, Cyborgs, and Companion Species.: Feminist Experiment." ''PMLA'', Vol. 121, No.5 (October 2006):1690-1696.
*Stacy Gillis, Gillian Howie and Rebecca Munford (Editors): ''Third Wave Feminism: A Critical Exploration,'' Palgrave, 2004, ISBN 1-4039-1821-X 
* Haraway, Donna J.  ''“A Cyborg Manifesto: Science, Technology, and Socialist-Feminism in the Late Twentieth Century.”'' &lt;u&gt;Simians, Cyborgs and Women: The Reinvention of Nature&lt;/u&gt;. New York; Routledge, 1991. p.149-181.
* Hernandez, Daisy and Bushra Rehman eds. ''Colonize This! Young Women of Color and Today's Feminism'', Seal. 2002 ISBN 1-58005-067-0
* Astrid Henry: ''Not My Mother's Sister: Generational Conflict and Third-Wave Feminism,'' Indiana University Press 2004, ISBN 0-253-21713-X
* Leslie Heywood, Jennifer Drake (Editors): ''Third Wave Agenda: Being Feminist, Doing Feminism,'' University of Minnesota Press 1997, ISBN 0-8166-3005-4
* Kisner, Amber. (2004). Negotiating space for/through Third-Wave Feminism. NWSA Journal, 16(3) pp. 124-153.
* Walker, Rebecca: ''To Be Real: Telling the Truth and Changing the Face of Feminism'', Anchor. 1995, ISBN 0-385-47262-5

==Magazines==
* [[Bitch (magazine)]]
* [[Bust (magazine)]]

==External links==
* [http://www.thirdwavefoundation.org The Third Wave Foundation]
* [http://www.metroactive.com/papers/cruz/11.29.00/feminism-0048.html Interview with Jennifer Baumgardner and Amy Richards]

==See also==
* [[first-wave feminism]]
* [[second-wave feminism]]
* [[ecofeminism]]
* [[the left and feminism]]
* [[New Left]]
* [[new social movements]]

[[Category:Feminism| 3]]
[[Category:Feminists| 3]]

[[et:Kolmanda laine feminism]]
[[el:Φεμινισμός τρίτου κύματος]]
[[zh:第三波女性主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>