<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050930151713|24404919" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="748253" pageid="748253" ns="0" title="Third-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T15:14:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Third-wave feminism''' is a [[feminist]] movement that arguably began in the early [[1990]]s. Unlike [[second-wave feminism]], which largely focused on the inclusion of [[women]] in traditionally [[male]]-dominated areas, third-wave feminism seeks to challenge and expand common definitions of [[gender]] and [[sexuality]].

Traits of third-wave feminism include [[queer theory]], [[women-of-color consciousness]], [[post-colonialism]], [[critical theory]], [[transnationalism]], and new [[feminist theory]].  In particular, a [[Post-structuralism|post-structuralist]] interpretation of gender and sexuality is center to third-wave feminism. Other consequences include a lesser emphasis on addressing and overthrowing a perceived oppression by [[patriarchy]] and instead focuses on equality between the sexes.

Briefly third-wave feminist activism extends past feminist beliefs from a new point of view:
# Equality with men as targeted by [[Second-wave feminist|Second Wavers]] has not been achieved and that feminism is not "dead" until it has been.
# But, at the same time, equality doesn't mean limiting gender or sexual expression. Being female is just as valuable as being male, and equality includes reclaiming all female choices in all areas (as in [[Riot Grrrl]]).
# In fact, it is the definitions of such things as gender, sexuality, and feminism that are a major part of the problem. Defining anything, including third-wave feminism, limits it.
# Ideas, especially those enforced by common language, have essential power (c.f. [[Queer theory]]).

A comprehensive example of third-wave feminism is ''Colonize This!'', an anthology of writings by young women discussing issues like gender, [[racism]], [[nationalism]], and queer identity.

==Books==
* Jennifer Baumgardner, Amy Richards: ''Manifesta: Young Women, Feminism, and the Future'', Farrar, Straus and Giroux 2000, ISBN 0374526222
* Jennifer Baumgardner, Amy Richards, Winona LaDuke: ''Grassroots : A Field Guide for Feminist Activism'', Farrar, Straus and Giroux 2005, ISBN 0374528659
* Astrid Henry: ''Not My Mother's Sister: Generational Conflict and Third-Wave Feminism,'' Indiana University Press 2004, ISBN 025321713X
* Leslie Heywood, Jennifer Drake (Editors): ''Third Wave Agenda: Being Feminist, Doing Feminism,'' University of Minnesota Press 1997, ISBN 0816630054

==Third-wave feminists==
''See also: [[List of feminists]]''
*[[Judith Butler]]
*[[Kathleen Hanna]]
*[[Donna Haraway]]
*[[bell hooks]]
*[[Jean Kilbourne]]
*[[Inga Muscio]]
*[[Rebecca Walker]]
*[[Kaia Wilson]]
*[[Molly Yard]]


&lt;!--please remember to insert alphabetically--&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.thirdwavefoundation.org The Third Wave Foundation]
* [http://www.metroactive.com/papers/cruz/11.29.00/feminism-0048.html Interview with Jennifer Baumgardner and Amy Richards]

==See also==
* [[first-wave feminism]]
* [[second-wave feminism]]

[[el:Φεμινισμός τρίτου κύματος]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>