<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071107061112|169800651" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="748253" pageid="748253" ns="0" title="Third-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-08T20:07:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{See also|First-wave feminism|Second-wave feminism}}
{{Feminism}}
'''Third-wave feminism''' is a term identified with several diverse strains of feminist activity and study beginning in the early [[1990s]]. The movement arose as a response to perceived failures of [[second-wave feminism]]. It was also a response to the backlash against initiatives and movements created by the second-wave.

==Overview==
''Third-wave feminism'' seeks to challenge or avoid what it deems the second wave's "[[Essentialism|''essentialist'']]" definitions of [[femininity]], which (according to the third wave) often assumed a universal female identity and over-emphasized the experiences of upper middle class white women.  A [[Post-structuralism|post-structuralist]] interpretation of gender and sexuality is central to much of third wave ideology. This accounts for the heightened emphasis on the discursive power and fundamental ambiguity inherent in all gender terms and categories. Third wave theory usually encompasses [[queer theory]], colored women consciousness, [[womanism]], [[post-colonial theory]], [[critical theory]], [[transnationalism]], [[ecofeminism]], and new [[feminist theory]]. 

Third wave feminists often focus on "micropolitics," writing about forms of gender expression and representation that are less explicitly political than their predecessors. They also challenged the second wave's paradigm as to what is, or is not, good for females.

==History==
In 1991, [[Anita Hill]] accused [[Clarence Thomas]], an [[African-American]] man nominated to the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]], of sexual harassment that had allegedly occurred a decade earlier while Hill worked as his assistant at the U.S. Department of Education. Thomas denied the accusations and after extensive debate, the Senate voted 52-48 in favor of Thomas. In response to this case, Rebecca Walker published an article in a 1992 issue of ''[[Ms. magazine|Ms.]]'' titled "Becoming the Third Wave" in which she stated, "I am not a post-feminism feminist. I am the third wave." Hill and Thomas’ case brought attention to the ongoing presence of sexual harassment in the workplace and reinstated a sense of concern and awareness in many people who assumed that sexual harassment and other second wave issues had been resolved. 

The roots of the Third Wave began, however, in the mid 1980's. Feminist leaders rooted in the second wave like [[Gloria Anzaldua]], [[bell hooks]], [[Chela Sandoval]], [[Cherrie Moraga]], [[Audre Lorde]], [[Maxine Hong Kingston]], and many other feminists of color, called for a new subjectivity in feminist voice.  They sought to negotiate prominent space within feminist thought for consideration of race related subjectivities. This focus on the intersection between race and gender remained prominent through the Hill-Thomas hearings, but began to shift with the [[Freedom Ride 1992]].  This drive to register voters in poor minority communities was surrounded with rhetoric that focused on rallying young feminists.  For many, the rallying of the young is the emphasis that has stuck within third wave feminism.

The fundamental rights and programs gained by feminist activists of the second wave—the creation of domestic abuse shelters and the acknowledgment of abuse and rape on a public level, access to contraception and other reproductive services including the legalization of abortion, the creation and enforcement of sexual harassment policies for women in the workplace, child care services, equal educational and extracurricular funding for young women, women’s studies programs, and much more—have served as a foundation, and by all means a tool, for third wave feminists. 

Third wave feminists come from a variety of backgrounds. They come from many different classes and cultures, genders and sexualities. Some third-wave feminists prefer not to call themselves feminists, as the word feminist can be misinterpreted as an exclusive term or deemed man-hating or elite by critics. Third wave feminism seeks to challenge any universal definition of femininity.  

Third wave feminism deals with issues that seem to limit or oppress women. Consciousness raising activism and widespread education is often the first step that feminists take toward social change. In their book ''Manifesta: Young Women, Feminism and the Future'', [[Jennifer Baumgardner]] and [[Amy Richards]] write, "Consciousness among women is what caused this [change], and consciousness, one’s ability to open their mind to the fact that male domination does affect the women of our generation, is what we need. . . The presence of feminism in our lives is taken for granted. For our generation, feminism is like fluoride. We scarcely notice we have it—it’s simply in the water."

== Activism and the Third Wave Agenda ==
===Activism and Products of the Third-Wave===
Transformation is a product of collaboration and consciousness. Once consciousness is raised, activism is necessary to feminism and to a movement. There are an abundance of [[grassroots organization]]s and coalitions that work to transform the world that women live in; for instance, [[Dress for Success]], an organization that collects suits through donations and fundraising and then gives them to women on welfare in order to instill confidence in their appearance when interviewing for a job. Other organizations include: [[National Organization for Women]], [[La Red]], [[The Third Wave Foundation]], [[Women’s Action Alliance]], [[Voters for Choice]], [[Students Organizing Students]], [[Take Back the Night]], [[Code Pink]], [[Vox: Voices for Planned Parenthood]], [[Feminist Majority Leadership Alliance]] and more. However, third wave feminists urge that one does not have to join a preexisting organization to make important changes in their communities. Any person with strategy and intention can be an activist if they utilize their resources. 

Story-telling is a productive way in which third-wave women raise consciousness and exemplify instances of oppression. "Women often see that an experience was a result of sexism only if another woman, or group of women, [speaks] . . . Reading women’s real experiences in books and magazines can provide the same click of recognition." As a result, feminist magazines such as [[Bitch]], [[Bust]], [[Off Our Backs]], and Ms. have been successful in relaying women’s concerns and personal stories related to the feminist movement. Books such as [[The Vagina Monologues]] by Eve Ensler, [[Listen Up! Voices]] from the [[Next Feminist Generation]] edited by [[Barbara Findlen]], and [[Bitchfest]] edited by [[Lisa Jervis]] and [[Andi Zeisler]] have done the same, as well as conferences and Speak Outs where women gather and inspire one another.

===Reproductive Rights===
Reproductive rights are a third-wave feminist issue due to the fact that one of feminism’s primary concerns is a woman's life and respect for her body. South Dakota’s recent attempt to ban abortion in all cases except when necessary to save the mother's life &lt;ref name="Davey, NYT"&gt;{{Citation | last=Davey | first=Monica | title= South Dakota Bans Abortion, Setting Up a Battle. | newspaper= New York Times | volume= 155 | issue= 53511 | pages=A1-A14 | year 2006 | date= 3/7/2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;, and the US Supreme Court's recent vote to uphold the partial birth abortion ban are both viewed as restrictions on women’s civil and reproductive rights.{{Fact|date=August 2007}} Restrictions on the 1973 Supreme Court decision in ''Roe v. Wade'', which legalized abortion in the United States, are becoming more and more common in individual states around the country; such restrictions include mandatory waiting periods, parental-consent laws, and spousal-consent laws. In addition, opponents of birth control and sex education are attempting to pass laws allowing pharmacists to withhold birth control based on moral views, de-fund public family planning programs, and teach students in public schools that abstinence from sexual activity until marriage is the only correct behavior.{{Fact|date=August 2007}}  Furthermore, violence and disruption at abortion and family planning clinics continue to be obstacles to women's reproductive health care.{{Fact|date=August 2007}}&lt;ref name="9th district court"&gt;{{cite court | litigants= American Coalition for Life Activists v. Planned Parenthood of Columbia/Willamette, Inc. | court= 9th District | date=5/16/02 |URL = http://www.ce9.uscourts.gov/Web/OCELibra.nsf/eb93ae8ffb1fcb7488256394006a5c7e/b491a0f8a79345c888256bbb007d20b4?OpenDocument }}&lt;/ref&gt;. "It is not feminism’s goal to control any woman’s fertility, only to free each woman to control her own," [[Jennifer Baumgardner]] and [[Amy Richards]] wrote. {{Fact|date=May 2007}}

===Reclaiming Derogatory Terms===
Words such as "bitch," "whore," and "cunt" continue to be used in derogatory ways to demean women. Inga Muscio writes, "I posit that we’re free to seize a word that was kidnapped and co-opted in a pain-filled, distant, past, with a ransom that cost our grandmothers’ freedom, children, traditions, pride, and land." In other words, third-wave feminists generally believe that it's better (or easier) to change the meaning of a sexist word than to censor it from everyday speech.

Many of these words did not originally have their modern connotations of power. "Cunt", for example, comes from a sexually neutral [[German language|Germanic]] root meaning "female genitalia". [http://www.takeourword.com/pt.html].  The words ‘[[bitch]]’ and ‘[[Prostitution#Terminology|whore]]’ have shared a similar fate in our language

===Transnational Politics===
{{expert-subject|Gender Studies}}

Globally, women are frequent victims of violence and oppression, especially in many war-ravaged and developing countries, where women remain vehicles for shows of power by men. In such countries and in developed countries alike, women are often dehumanized and treated as property and/or as sources of pleasure for men.
  
In many countries, rape and sexual violence are used in the context of war as displays of supremacy. For example, in the early 1990s, rape camps were set up in Mogadishu, Somalia{{Fact|date=May 2007}}, and militiamen abducted and repeatedly raped women and girls of opposing factions, often inflicting severe injuries with razor blades and bayonets, frequently doing so in front of an audience of children and family members{{Fact|date=May 2007}}. Rape and sexual violence are similarly common place in the current (as of May 2007) [[ethnic cleansing]] in [[Darfur]], Sudan. 

Twenty-six of Africa's 43 countries, along with populations in the southern part of the Arabian peninsula, the Persian Gulf, Indonesia, and Malaysia, practice [[female genital cutting|female genital mutilation]], in which all or a part of the [[clitoris]] and [[labia]] is excised by knife from a woman’s body. Historically, if a girl had not undergone this procedure she was considered unclean and unmarriageable{{Fact|date=May 2007}}. This stigma is slowly fading in some areas{{Fact|date=May 2007}}. Genital mutilation makes  sex painful and renders sexual pleasure more or less impossible{{Fact|date=May 2007}}. The procedures are often done with unsanitary tools{{Fact|date=May 2007}}, so infection and other long-term consequences are common{{Fact|date=May 2007}}. 

Third-wave feminists work to educate and work with women across political borders, to give them the tools and awareness to make their own decisions. In the case of female genital mutilation, feminists from developed countries have been known to travel to countries in which genital mutilation is common in order to educate midwives on sanitation and safety.

===The Riot Grrrl Movement===
{{main|Riot Grrrl}}

The riot grrrl movement sprang out of [[Olympia]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]] in the early 1990s. It sought to give women power to control their voices and artistic expressions (Rowe-Finkbeiner 2004:85). To name their movement, riot grrrls took a growling triple r and placed it in the word girl as an effort to take back the sometimes derogatory use of the word girl instead of woman (Rowe-Finkbeiner 2004:85). It is a movement led, owned, and created by women. 

The music that came out of the riot grrrl movement was anti-corporate and focused on the importance of self-sufficiency for female artists (Rowe-Finkbeiner 2004:85). Women wrote, played, and recorded the music they produced. Women became the artist, producer and record label owner for the music that came out of the movement. Although, music was not the only artistic expression that came from the Riot Grrrl movement, there was also the emergence of zines and fanzines (Rowe-Finkbeiner 2004:85). They were written and published by their female owners. They were the predecessors to magazines such as Bitch and Bust. 

The Riot Grrrl’s links to social and political issues are where the beginning rumblings of the third-wave feminism can be seen. The music and zine writings that were produced at the time were strong examples of "cultural politics in action, with strong women giving voice to important social issues though an empowered, a female oriented community, many people link the emergence of the third-wave feminism to this time" (Rowe-Finkbeiner 2004:85). It showed young women the voice and impact they could have. The movement encouraged and made "adolescent girls’ standpoints central" allowing them to express themselves fully (Code 2000:3). It was a movement of active women making active change and from this is believed to have come inspiration for third wave feminist activists.

===Other areas of concern===
Issues of race, class and sexuality are central to third-wave feminism. Also significant are women in the workplace—the glass ceiling, sexual harassment, and unfair maternity leave policies; Sexual Assault and Rape; Motherhood—support for single mothers by means of welfare and child care, and respect for working mothers and mothers who decide to leave their careers to raise their children full-time; Women, Politics, and Intellect—respecting women as intelligent, political beings with intelligent, political minds and acknowledging the lack of diverse, positive female representatives in pop culture; The Media—unhealthy standards that women feel they need to live up to, eating disorders, the portrayal of women as sexualized objects catering solely to the man’s needs, anti-intellectualism.

==Criticism of the Third Wave==
 
===Rebels Without a Cause===
One question about the validity of the third wave is: How can it be a marker on the feminist continuum without one underlying cause? The first wave fought and gained the right for women to vote. The second wave obtained the right for women to have access and equal opportunity to the workforce and the end of legal sex discrimination (Rowe-Finkbeiner 2004:92).  The third wave of feminism has no underlying goal that can be attributed to strictly the third wave. Because of this it is often seen as an extension of the second wave (Rowe-Finkbeiner 2004:92-93). There is also no set definition of a third wave feminist that can clearly distinguish a third-wave feminist from a second-wave feminist. Some argue the third wave could be more accurately dubbed the "Second Wave, Part Two" when it comes to the politics of feminism and "only young feminist culture as truly third wave" (Richards 95). {{Fact|date=August 2007}}

===Like Mother, Like Daughter===
Another question of the emergence of feminism has to do with the overlapping generations of feminism. There was an entire generation of women that came to separate the first and second waves. The second and third waves run-over one another. The third wave has yet to break from the political and social foot prints left by the previous wave. Amy Richards, a prominent third wave writer and activist, defines "the feminist culture for this generation [as] third wave because it’s an expression of having grown up with feminism" (Rowe-Finkbeiner 2004:95). Second Wave feminists grew up where the politics were the culture, with such events as "Kennedy, the Vietnam War, civil rights, and women’s rights"; While the Third Wave sprung from a culture that included "punk-rock, hip-hop, zines, products, consumerism and the Internet (Richards 130). {{Fact|date=August 2007}} This is a major difference between second and third wave feminists. Third wave feminists grew up understanding and learning about feminist issues that came to them due to the political culture and activism that is the Second wave.
	
Although, there continues to be a tension between second wave feminists and third wave feminists. In an essay entitled "Generations, Academic Feminists in dialogue" Diane Elam writes:

"This problem manifests itself when senior feminists insist that junior feminists be good daughters, defending the same kind of feminism their mothers advocated. Questions and criticisms are allowed, but only if they proceed from the approved brand of feminism. Daughters are not allowed to invent new ways of thinking and doing feminism for themselves; feminists’ politics should take the same shape that it has always assumed" (Richards 224). {{Fact|date=August 2007}}
	
Young Women feminists find themselves watching their speech and tone in their works so as not to upset their elder feminist mothers. There is a definite gap among feminists who consider themselves to be second wave and those who would label themselves as third wave. Although, the age criteria for second wave feminists and third wave feminists is murky, younger feminist definitely have a hard time proving themselves worthy as feminist scholars and activists.{{Fact|date=August 2007}}

==References==
*{{cite book | last =Baumgardner | first = Jennifer | coauthors = Amy Richards |authorlink = Jennifer_Baumgardner| title = ManifestA: Young Women, Feminism, and the Future | location = New York | publisher = Farrar, Straus, and Giroux | year = [[2000]]}}
*{{cite book | last =Baumgardner | first = Jennifer | coauthors = Amy Richards |authorlink = Jennifer_Baumgardner| title = Grassroots: A Field Guide for Feminist Activism | location = New York | publisher = Farrar, Straus, and Giroux | year = [[2005]]}}
*{{cite book | last = Code | first = Lorraine | title = Encyclopedia of Feminist Theories | publisher = Routledge of Taylor and Francis Group | year = [[2000]] | isbn = 0-415030885-2}}
*{{cite journal | last = Dekoven | first = Marianne | title = Jouissance, Cyborgs, and Companion Species.: Feminist Experiment. | journal = PMLA | volume = 121 | issue = 5 | pages = 1690-1696 | date = October 2006}}
*{{cite book | last = Ensler | first = Eve |authorlink=Eve_Ensler| title = The Vagina Monoglogues | publisher =Virigo Press Ltd | year = [[2001]] }}
*{{cite book | last = Findlen | first = Barbara, ed | title = Listen Up! Voices From the Next Feminist Generation | publisher = Seal Press | year = [[1995]]}}
*{{Citation | last1 = Gillis | last2 = Howie | last3=Munford | first1=Stacy | first2=Gillian | first3=Rebecca | title = Third Wave Feminism: A Critical Exploration | publisher = Palgrave | year = [[2004]] | isbn = 1-4039-1821-X}}. Revised paperback edition published in 2007. 
*{{cite book | last = Henry | first = Astrid | title=Not My Mother's Sister: Generational Conflict and Third-Wave Feminism| publisher = Indiana University Press | year = [[2004]] | isbn = 0-253-21713-X}}
*{{cite book | last = Hernandez | first = Daisy | coauthors = Bushra Reman| title = Colonize This! Young Women of Color and Today's Feminism | publisher = Seal Press | year = [[2002]] | isbn = 1-58005-067-0}}
*{{cite book | last = Heywood | first = Leslie | coauthors = Jennifer Drake, ed | title = Third Wave Agenda: Being Feminist, Doing Feminism| publisher = University of Minnesota Press | year = [[1997]] | isbn = 0-8166-3005-4}}
*{{cite book | last = Jervis | first = Lisa | coauthors = Andi Zeisler, ed | title = Bitchfest | location = New York | publisher = Farrar, Straus, and Giroux | year = [[2006]]}}
*{{cite journal | last = Kinser | first = Amber | title = Negotiating space for/through Third-Wave Feminism | journal = NWSA Journal | volume = 16 | issue = 3 | pages = 124-153 | year = [[2004]]}}
*{{cite book | last=Musico | first = Inga | title = Cunt: A Declaration of Independence| location = California | publisher = Seal Press | year= [[2002]]}}
*{{Citation | last = Musse | first = Fowzia | journal =War Crimes Against Girls and Women | title = Somalia-The Untold Story: The War Through the Eyes of Somali Women | location = [[London]]| publisher = Pluto Press | year = [[2004]] | pages = 69-76}}
*{{cite book | last=Rowe-Finkbeiner | first = Kristin | title = The F-Word | publisher = Avalon Publishing Group | year = [[2004]] | isbn = 1-58005-114-6}}
*{{cite book | last = Walker | first = Rebecca | title =To Be Real: Telling the Truth and Changing the Face of Feminism| publisher= Anchor | year = [[1995]] | isbn = 0-385-47262-5}}
&lt;references/&gt;

==Magazines==
* ''[[Bitch (magazine)|Bitch]]''
* ''[[Bust (magazine)|Bust]]''
* [[Venus zine]]

==External links==
* [http://www.thirdwavefoundation.org The Third Wave Foundation]
* [http://www.metroactive.com/papers/cruz/11.29.00/feminism-0048.html Interview with Jennifer Baumgardner and Amy Richards]

==See also==
*[[Girl power]]
* [[lesbian feminism]]
* [[first-wave feminism]]
* [[second-wave feminism]]
* [[ecofeminism]]
* [[the left and feminism]]
* [[New Left]]
* [[new social movements]]

{{DEFAULTSORT: 3}}
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Feminists]]
[[Category:Third-wave Feminism|*]]

[[et:Kolmanda laine feminism]]
[[el:Φεμινισμός τρίτου κύματος]]
[[he:הגל השלישי של הפמיניזם]]
[[zh:第三波女性主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>