<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211123202830|1056831228" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="399735" pageid="399735" ns="0" title="Liberal feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-26T06:05:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Movements for gender equality through political and legal reform within liberal democracy}}
{{Distinguish|libertarian feminism|individualist feminism}}
{{Liberal feminism sidebar}}
{{Liberalism sidebar}}
'''Liberal feminism''', also called '''mainstream feminism''', is a main branch of [[feminism]] defined by its focus on achieving [[gender equality]] through [[political reform|political]] and [[legal reform]] within the framework of [[liberal democracy]]. As the oldest of the "Big Three" schools of feminist thought,&lt;ref name="Maynard" /&gt; liberal feminism has its roots in 19th century [[first-wave feminism]] that focused particularly on [[women's suffrage]] and [[Female education|access to education]], and that was associated with 19th century [[liberalism]] and [[progressivism]]. Liberal feminism "works within the structure of mainstream society to integrate women into that structure."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=West |first1=Rebecca |title=Kinds of Feminism |url=https://www.uah.edu/woolf/feminism_kinds.htm |publisher=University of Alabama in Huntsville}}&lt;/ref&gt; Liberal feminism places great emphasis on the public world, especially laws, political institutions, education and working life, and considers the denial of equal legal and political rights as the main obstacle to equality. As such liberal feminists have worked to bring women into the political mainstream. Liberal feminism is inclusive and socially progressive, while broadly supporting existing institutions of power in liberal democratic societies, and is associated with [[centrism]] and [[reformism]]. Liberal feminism "tends to be adopted by 'mainstream' (i.e., middle-class) women who do not disagree with the current social structure;"&lt;ref name=ZhangRios /&gt; Zhang and Rios found that liberal feminism with its focus on equality is viewed as the dominant and "default" form of feminism.&lt;ref name=ZhangRios /&gt; Liberal feminism actively supports men's involvement in feminism and both women and men have always been active participants in the movement; progressive men had an important role alongside women in the struggle for equal political rights since the movement was launched in the 19th century.&lt;ref name="Lønnå" /&gt;

Historically liberal feminism largely grew out of and was often associated with [[social liberalism]]; the modern liberal feminist tradition notably includes both social liberal and social democratic streams, and many often diverging schools of thought such as [[equality feminism]], [[social feminism]], [[equity feminism]], and [[difference feminism]]; some forms of modern liberal feminism have been described as [[neoliberalism|neoliberal]] feminism. In many countries, particularly in the West but also in a number of secular states in the developing world, liberal feminism is associated with the concept of [[state feminism]], and liberal feminism emphasizes constructive cooperation with the government and involvement in parliamentary and legislative processes to pursue reforms.&lt;ref name="Lønnå" /&gt; Liberal feminism is also called "mainstream feminism", "reformist feminism", "egalitarian feminism", or historically "bourgeois feminism" (or bourgeois-liberal feminism), among other names.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Lindsey |first=Linda L. |date=2015 |title=Gender Roles: A Sociological Perspective |publisher= Routledge |page=17 |isbn=9781317348085}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Voet" /&gt; As one of the "Big Three" schools of feminist thought,&lt;ref name="Maynard"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Maynard |first1=Mary |title=Beyond the ‘big three’: the development of feminist theory into the 1990s |journal=Women's History Review |date=1995|volume=4|issue=3|pages=259–281}}&lt;/ref&gt; liberal feminism is often contrasted with [[Socialist feminism|socialist]]/[[Marxist feminism]] and [[radical feminism]], but in contrast to them, liberal feminism seeks gradual social progress and equality on the basis of liberal democracy rather than a revolution or radical reordering of society.&lt;ref name="Maynard" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Voet" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Murphy | first = Meghan | title = The divide isn't between 'sex negative' and 'sex positive' feminists — it's between liberal and radical feminism | url = http://www.feministcurrent.com/2014/04/11/the-divide-isnt-between-sex-negative-and-sex-positive-feminists-its-between-liberals-and-radicals/ | work = Feminist Current | date = April 11, 2014 | access-date = December 24, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Appignanesi | first1 = Richard | last2 = Garratt | first2 = Ghris | title = Postmodernism for beginners | url = https://archive.org/details/postmodernismfor0000appi | url-access = registration | pages = [https://archive.org/details/postmodernismfor0000appi/page/100 100–101] | publisher = Icon | location = Trumpington | year = 1995 | isbn = 9781874166214 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MacKinnon"&gt;{{cite book|last=MacKinnon|first=Catharine A. | author-link = Catharine MacKinnon |chapter=Sexuality | editor-last1 = Kolmar | editor-first1 = Wendy K. |editor-last2= Barkowski |editor-first2= Frances | title = Feminist theory: a reader | publisher = McGraw-Hill Higher Education | location = New York | year = 2013 | edition = 4th | isbn = 9780073512358 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite AV media | people= [[Gail Dines]] | date= 29 June 2011 |access-date= 24 December 2017 | title= Gail Dines on radical feminism | medium= Video | publisher= Wheeler Centre, Sydney Writers' Festival, Melbourne via [[YouTube]] | url = https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B9LVVxvuomU&amp;t=0m20s}}&lt;/ref&gt; Liberal feminism and mainstream feminism are very broad terms, frequently taken to encompass all feminism that is not radical or revolutionary socialist/Marxist, and that instead pursues equality through political, legal and social reform within a liberal democratic framework; as such liberal feminists may subscribe to a range of different feminist beliefs and political ideologies within the democratic spectrum from the [[centre-left]] to the [[centre-right]]. 

Inherently [[Pragmatism|pragmatic]] in orientation, liberal feminists have emphasized building far-reaching support for feminist causes among both women and men, and among the political centre, the government and legislatures. In the 21st century liberal feminists have increasingly embraced an [[Intersectionality|intersectional]] understanding of gender equality. Liberal feminists typically support laws and regulations that promote gender equality and ban practices that are discriminatory towards women; mainstream liberal feminists, particularly those of a social democratic bent, often support social measures to reduce material inequality within a liberal democratic framework. While rooted in first-wave feminism and traditionally focused on political and legal reform, the broader liberal feminist tradition may include parts of subsequent waves of feminism, especially [[third-wave feminism]] and [[fourth-wave feminism]]. The [[sunflower]] and the color gold, taken to represent enlightenment, became widely used symbols of mainstream liberal feminism and [[women's suffrage]] from the 1860s, originally in the United States and later also in parts of Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Cheris Kramarae &amp; Paula A. Treichler (eds.), ''Amazons, Bluestockings and Crones: A Feminist Dictionary'', Pandora Press, 1992&lt;/ref&gt;

==Terminology==
The specific term "liberal feminism" is fairly modern, but its political tradition is much older. "[[Feminism#Terminology|Feminism]]" became the dominant term in English for the struggle for women's rights in the late 20th century, around a century after the organized liberal women's rights movement came into existence, but most western feminist historians contend that all movements working to obtain women's rights should be considered feminist movements, even when they did not (or do not) apply the term to themselves.&lt;ref&gt;Walters, Margaret (2005). ''Feminism: A very short introduction''. Oxford University. pp. 1–176. ISBN 978-0-19-280510-2.&lt;/ref&gt; Many liberal feminists embraced the term "feminism" in the 1970s or 1980s, although some initially expressed scepticism towards the term; for example the liberal feminist [[Norwegian Association for Women's Rights]] expressed scepticism towards the term "feminism" as late as 1980 because it could foster "unnecessary antagonism towards men",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Adresseavisen |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digavis_adresseavisen_null_null_19800308_214_58_1?page=11 |access-date=27 July 2021 |date=8 March 1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; but accepted the term some years later as it increasingly became the mainstream general term for the women's rights struggle in the western world.&lt;ref name="Lønnå" /&gt;

==Philosophy==
[[File:Portrett av Gina Krog (6276081582) - Restoration.jpg|thumb|[[Gina Krog]], a Norwegian liberal feminist who became the leader of the first wave feminist movement in Norway and who founded the [[Norwegian Association for Women's Rights]] and the journal ''[[Nylænde]]'']]
According to [[Anthony Giddens]], liberal feminist theory "believes gender inequality is produced by reduced access for women and girls to civil rights and allocation of social resources such as education and employment."&lt;ref&gt;[[Anthony Giddens]] (2001). ''Sociology'' (p. 692). Polity Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Catherine Rottenberg notes that the [[wikt:raison d'être|raison d'être]] of classic liberal feminism was "to pose an immanent critique of liberalism, revealing the gendered exclusions within liberal democracy’s proclamation of universal equality, particularly with respect to the law, institutional access, and the full incorporation of women into the public sphere." Rottenberg contrasts classic liberal feminism with modern neoliberal feminism which "seems perfectly in sync with the evolving neoliberal order."&lt;ref name=Rottenberg /&gt;

At its core liberal feminism believes in pragmatic "reforms against gender discrimination through the promotion of equal rights by engaging and formulating laws and policies that will ensure equality."&lt;ref&gt;Ledwaba S, Nkomo TS. An Exploration of Motivations for Women Mine Workers to Work Underground. SAGE Open. July 2021. doi:10.1177/21582440211032157&lt;/ref&gt; Liberal feminists argue that society holds the false belief that women are, by nature, less intellectually and physically capable than men; thus it tends to discriminate against women in the academy, the forum, and the marketplace. Liberal feminists believe that "female subordination is rooted in a set of customary and legal constraints that blocks women's entrance to and success in the so-called public world", and strive for gender equality via political and legal reform.&lt;ref name="Tong, Rosemarie 1989"&gt;{{cite book | last = Tong | first = Rosemarie | chapter = Liberal feminism | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=cv5EAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT17 | title = Feminist thought: a comprehensive introduction | publisher = Routledge | location = London | year = 1992 | isbn = 9780415078740 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Inherently [[pragmatism|pragmatic]], liberal feminism does not have a clearly defined set of philosophies. Liberal feminists tend to focus on practical reforms of laws and policies in order to achieve [[Social equality|equality]]; liberal feminism has a more individualistic approach to justice than left-wing branches of feminism such as socialist or radical feminism.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wendell|first=Susan|date=June 1987|title=A (Qualified) Defense of Liberal Feminism|journal=Hypatia|volume=2|issue=2|pages=65–93|doi=10.1111/j.1527-2001.1987.tb01066.x|issn=0887-5367}}&lt;/ref&gt; Susan Wendell argues that "liberal feminism is an historical tradition that grew out of liberalism, as can be seen very clearly in the work of such feminists as Mary Wollstonecraft and John Stuart Mill, but feminists who took principles from that tradition have developed analyses and goals that go far beyond those of 18th and 19th century liberal feminists, and many feminists who have goals and strategies identified as liberal feminist ... reject major components of liberalism" in a modern or party-political sense; she highlights "equality of opportunity" as a defining feature of liberal feminism.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

[[Liberalism|Political liberalism]] gave feminism a familiar platform for convincing others that their reforms "could and should be incorporated into existing law".&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Musgrave|first=L. Ryan|date=2003-11-01|title=Liberal Feminism, from Law to Art: The Impact of Feminist Jurisprudence on Feminist Aesthetics|journal=Hypatia|volume=18|issue=4|pages=214–235|doi=10.1111/j.1527-2001.2003.tb01419.x|issn=1527-2001|citeseerx=10.1.1.582.4459|s2cid=22580016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Liberal feminists argued that women, like men, be regarded as autonomous individuals, and likewise be accorded the rights of such.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

==History==
Liberal feminism ultimately has historical roots in [[classical liberalism]] and was often associated with [[social liberalism]] from the late 19th century. The goal for liberal feminists beginning in the late 18th century was to gain suffrage for women with the idea that this would allow them to gain individual liberty. They were concerned with gaining freedom through equality, diminishing men's cruelty to women, and gaining opportunities to become full persons.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite book | last = Marilley | first = Suzanne M. | chapter = The feminism of equal rights | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=SQ7PP7qSkRsC&amp;pg=PA16 | title = Woman suffrage and the origins of liberal feminism in the United States, 1820-1920 | pages = 1–10 | publisher = Harvard University Press | location = Cambridge, Massachusetts | year = 1996 | isbn = 9780674954656 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They believed that no government or custom should prohibit the due exercise of personal freedom. Early liberal feminists had to counter the assumption that only white men deserved to be full citizens. Pioneers such as [[Mary Wollstonecraft]], [[Judith Sargent Murray]], and [[Frances Wright]] advocated for women's full political inclusion.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; In 1920, after nearly 50 years of intense activism, women were finally granted the right to vote and the right to hold public office in the United States, and in much of the [[Western world]] within a few decades before or a few decades after this time.

Liberal feminism was largely quiet in the United States for four decades after winning the vote. In the 1960s during the civil rights movement, liberal feminists drew parallels between systemic race discrimination and sex discrimination.&lt;ref name="Tong, Rosemarie 1989"/&gt; Groups such as the [[National Organization for Women]], the [[National Women's Political Caucus]], and the [[Women's Equity Action League]] were all created at that time to further women's rights. In the U.S., these groups have worked, thus far unsuccessfully, for the ratification of the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] or "Constitutional Equity Amendment", in the hopes it will ensure that men and women are treated as equals under the law. Specific issues important to liberal feminists include but are not limited to reproductive rights and abortion access, sexual harassment, voting, education, fair compensation for work, affordable childcare, affordable health care, and bringing to light the frequency of sexual and domestic violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;hooks, bell. "Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center" Cambridge, MA: South End Press 1984&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, liberal feminism, also called "bourgeois feminism", was mainly contrasted with the working-class or "proletarian" women's movements, that eventually developed into called [[Socialist feminism|socialist]] and [[Marxist feminism]]. Since the 1960s both liberal feminism and the "proletarian" or socialist/Marxist women's movements are also contrasted with [[radical feminism]]. Liberal feminism is usually included as one of the two, three or four main traditions in the history of feminism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Artwińska |first1=Anna |title=Gender, Generations, and Communism in Central and Eastern Europe and Beyond |date=2020 |publisher=Routledge}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Voet"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Voet |first1=Rian |title=Feminism and Citizenship |date=1998 |publisher=SAGE |isbn=1446228045 |page=25|chapter=Categorizations of feminism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Liberal feminism as a broad school of thought and main tradition in feminism includes many different varieties, such as [[equality feminism]], [[social feminism]], [[equity feminism]], and [[difference feminism]]. [[State feminism]] is often linked to liberal feminism, particularly in Western countries. Some forms of modern liberal feminism have been described as [[neoliberalism|neoliberal]] feminism.&lt;ref name=Rottenberg&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rottenberg |first1=Catherine |title=The Rise of Neoliberal Feminism |journal=Cultural Studies |date=2014 |volume=28 |issue=3 |doi=10.1080/09502386.2013.857361}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Individualist or [[libertarian feminism]] is sometimes grouped as one of many branches of feminism with historical roots in liberal feminism, but tends to diverge significantly from mainstream liberal feminism on many issues. For example, "libertarian feminism does not require social measures to reduce material inequality; in fact, it opposes such measures ... in contrast, liberal feminism may support such requirements and egalitarian versions of feminism insist on them."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Mahowald |first1=Mary Briody |title=Genes, Women, Equality |date=1999 |publisher=Oxford University Press |page=145}}&lt;/ref&gt; Libertarian feminists tend to focus more on sexual politics, a topic traditionally of less concern to liberal feminists. Unlike many libertarian feminists, mainstream liberal feminists today tend to oppose [[prostitution]]; for example the mainstream liberal [[Norwegian Association for Women's Rights]] supports the ban on buying sexual services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Behold sexkjøpsloven |url=https://kvinnesak.no/2014/02/behold-sexkjopsloven-ny-tid-14-02/ |publisher=[[Norwegian Association for Women's Rights]] |access-date=18 November 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Liberal feminist organizations such as the [[International Alliance of Women]] tend to be supportive of liberal democratic states' foreign and security policy, and maintained a clear pro-[[Western Bloc|Western]] stance throughout the [[Cold War]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Francisca de Haan]], ''Rosa Manus (1881–1942)'', p. 17, BRILL, 2016, ISBN 9789004333185&lt;/ref&gt; From the second half of the 20th century [[women in development]] has increasingly become an important topic for liberal feminist organizations.

[[Hillary Clinton]] is often considered a liberal feminist, and has defined "feminist" in accordance with the liberal feminist definition as "someone who believes in equal rights."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Feminisms of Hillary Clinton and Carly Fiorina |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/09/the-feminisms-of-hillary-clinton-and-carly-fiorina/455790/ |access-date=24 October 2021 |work=The Atlantic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Zhang and Rios, "liberal feminism tends to be adopted by 'mainstream' (i.e., middle-class) women who do not disagree with the current social structure." They found that liberal feminist beliefs were viewed as the dominant and "default" form of feminism.&lt;ref name=ZhangRios&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Zhang |first1=Y. |last2=Rios |first2=K. |title=Understanding Perceptions of Radical and Liberal Feminists: The Nuanced Roles of Warmth and Competence |journal=[[Sex Roles (journal)|Sex Roles]]|date=2021 |doi=10.1007/s11199-021-01257-y}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Symbolism===
[[File:Jus suffragii - earthenware plate - International Woman Suffrage Alliance - Atria, Institute on Gender Equality and Women's History , Amsterdam.jpg|thumb|Plate with the symbol and motto of the [[International Alliance of Women|International Woman Suffrage Alliance]], featuring a sun and the color gold, with the motto "Jus Suffragii" (the right to vote) and [[Lady Justice]] holding a balance in her right hand.]]
The [[sunflower]] (and sometimes by analogy the [[Sun]]) and the color yellow/gold ([[Or (heraldry)|Or]] in heraldry), taken to represent enlightenment, became widely used symbols of the mainstream liberal women's rights movement and women's suffrage from the 1860s, originally in the United States and later also in parts of Europe. The suffragists and liberal feminists [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] and [[Susan B. Anthony]] encouraged the use of the sunflower by wearing sunflower pins when campaigning for the right to vote in 1867 in Kansas. Hence the colors yellow and white became the main colors of the international liberal (also called mainstream or bourgeois) suffrage movement around the turn of the century, notably used by the [[International Alliance of Women|International Woman Suffrage Alliance]]. Historians Cheris Kramarae and Paula A. Treichler noted that

{{quote|Colors were important in the iconography of the suffrage movement. The use of the color gold began with Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony’s campaign in Kansas in 1867 and derived from the color of the sunflower, the Kansas state symbol. Suffragists used gold pins, ribbons, sashes, and yellow roses to symbolize their cause. In 1876, during the U.S. Centennial, women wore yellow ribbons and sang the song “The Yellow Ribbon.” In 1916, suffragists staged “The Golden Lane” at the national Democratic convention; to reach the convention hall, all delegates had to walk through a line of women stretching several blocks long, dressed in white with gold sashes, carrying yellow umbrellas, and accompanied by hundreds of yards of draped gold bunting. Gold also signified enlightenment, the professed goal of the mainstream U.S. suffrage movement.|Cheris Kramarae &amp; Paula A. Treichler&lt;ref&gt;Cheris Kramarae &amp; Paula A. Treichler (eds.), Amazons, Bluestockings and Crones: A Feminist Dictionary, Pandora Press, 1992&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The sunflower and/or the color yellow/gold remain in use among the older liberal (bourgeois) feminist organizations such as the [[Norwegian Association for Women's Rights]] and the [[International Alliance of Women]] that were founded during the struggle for women's suffrage.

The color yellow is also widely used as a symbol of liberalism in general.&lt;ref&gt;Adams, Sean; Morioka, Noreen; Stone, Terry Lee (2006). ''Color Design Workbook: A Real World Guide to Using Color in Graphic Design''. Gloucester, Mass.: Rockport Publishers. pp. 86. ISBN 159253192X. OCLC 60393965.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Writers==
Feminist writers associated with this theory include [[Mary Wollstonecraft]], [[John Stuart Mill]], [[Helen Taylor (feminist)|Helen Taylor]], [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]], and [[Gina Krog]]; [[Second wave feminism|Second Wave]] feminists [[Betty Friedan]], [[Gloria Steinem]], [[Simone de Beauvoir]]; and [[Third-wave feminism|Third Wave]] feminist [[Rebecca Walker]].

[[File:Mary Wollstonecraft by John Opie (c. 1797).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Mary Wollstonecraft]]]]
;Mary Wollstonecraft
[[Mary Wollstonecraft]] (1759–1797) has been very influential in her writings as ''A Vindication of the Rights of Woman'' commented on society's view of women and encouraged women to use their voices in making decisions separate from decisions previously made for them. Wollstonecraft "denied that women are, by nature, more pleasure seeking and pleasure giving than men. She reasoned that if they were confined to the same cages that trap women, men would develop the same flawed characters. What Wollstonecraft most wanted for women was personhood."&lt;ref name="Tong, Rosemarie 1989"/&gt; She argued that patriarchal oppression is a form of slavery that could no longer be ignored {{Citation needed|date=February 2019}}. Wollstonecraft argued that the inequality between men and women existed due to the disparity between their educations. Along with Judith Sargent Murray and Frances Wright, Wollstonecraft was one of the first major advocates for women's full inclusion in politics.

{{break}}

;Elizabeth Cady Stanton
[[File:Elizabeth Stanton.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]]]]
[[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] (1815–1902) was one of the most influential women in [[First-wave feminism|first wave feminism]]. An American social activist, she was instrumental in orchestrating the [[Seneca Falls Convention]], the first [[women's rights]] convention, which was held in Seneca Falls, New York. Not only was the suffragist movement important to Stanton, she also was involved in women's parental and custody rights, divorce laws, birth control, employment and financial rights, among other issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Baker | first = Jean H. | title = Sisters: the lives of America's suffragists | publisher = Hill and Wang | location = New York | year = 2005 | isbn = 9780809095285 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Her partner in this movement was the equally influential [[Susan B. Anthony]].  Together, they fought for a linguistic shift in the [[Reconstruction Amendments|Fourteenth and Fifteenth Amendments]] to include "female".&lt;ref name="Evans, Sara M 1997"&gt;{{cite book | last = Evans | first = Sara M. | title = Born for liberty: a history of women in America | publisher = Free Press Paperbacks | location = New York, New York | year = 1997 | isbn = 9780684834986 | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/bornforliberty00sara }}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, in 1890 she founded the [[National American Woman Suffrage Association]] and presided as president until 1892.&lt;ref name="Evans, Sara M 1997"/&gt; She produced many speeches, resolutions, letters, calls, and petitions that fed the first wave and kept the spirit alive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Stanton | first = Elizabeth Cady | author-link = Elizabeth Cady Stanton | chapter = Address to the New York State Legislature, 1854 | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=2V6YAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA143 | editor-last = Schneir | editor-first = Miriam | title = Feminism: the essential historical writings | publisher = Vintage Books | location = New York | year = 1994 | page = 110 | isbn = 9780679753810 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, by gathering a large number of signatures, she aided the passage of the Married Women's Property Act of 1848 which considered women legally independent of their husbands and granted them property of their own. Together these women formed what was known as the NWSA (National Women Suffrage Association), which focused on working legislatures and the courts to gain suffrage.

{{break}}

;John Stuart Mill
[[File:PSM V03 D380 John Stuart Mill.jpg|thumb|upright|[[John Stuart Mill]]]]
[[John Stuart Mill]] (20 May 1806 – 7 May 1873) believed that both sexes should have equal rights under the law and that "until conditions of equality exist, no one can possibly assess the natural differences between women and men, distorted as they have been. What is natural to the two sexes can only be found out by allowing both to develop and use their faculties freely."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Mill | first = John Stuart | author-link = John Stuart Mill | title = The Subjection of Women (A Feminist Literature Classic) | publisher = e-artnow Editions | location = Cork | orig-year = 1869 | year = 2013 | isbn = 9788074843150 | title-link = The Subjection of Women }}&lt;/ref&gt; Mill frequently spoke of this imbalance and wondered if women were able to feel the same "genuine unselfishness" that men did in providing for their families. This unselfishness Mill advocated is the one "that motivates people to take into account the good of society as well as the good of the individual person or small family unit".&lt;ref name="Tong, Rosemarie 1989"/&gt; Similar to Mary Wollstonecraft, Mill compared sexual inequality to slavery, arguing that their husbands are often just as abusive as masters, and that a human being controls nearly every aspect of life for another human being. In his book ''The Subjection of Women'', Mill argues that three major parts of women's lives are hindering them: society and gender construction, education, and marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Brink | first = David | chapter = Mill's Moral and Political Philosophy | chapter-url = https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/mill-moral-political/ | title = Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy |date=9 October 2007|publisher=Stanford University}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also argues that sex inequality is greatly inhibiting the progress of humanity.

==Notable liberal feminists==
{{expand section|date= October 2020}}
{{cols|colwidth=21em}}
* 18th century
**[[Mary Wollstonecraft]]
**[[Judith Sargent Murray]]
**[[Frances Wright]]
*19th century
**[[John Stuart Mill]]
**[[Harriet Taylor Mill|Harriet Taylor]]
**[[Harriet Tubman]]
**[[Susan B. Anthony]]
**[[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]]
**[[Gina Krog]]
*20th century
**[[Margarete Bonnevie]]
**[[Eva Kolstad]]
**[[Nadine Strossen]]&lt;ref&gt;[[n:ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush|Interview with Nadine Strossen]], [[Wikinews]], Retrieved 12 June 2020&lt;/ref&gt; 
**[[Ellen Willis]]
**[[Naomi Wolf]]
**[[Betty Friedan]]
**[[Rebecca Walker]]
**[[Martha Nussbaum]]
**[[Karin M. Bruzelius]]
{{colend}}

==Organizations==

===National Organization for Women===
The [[National Organization for Women]] (NOW) is the largest liberal feminist organization in the United States. It supports the [[Equal Rights Amendment]], [[reproductive rights]] including freer access to abortion, as well as lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender rights ([[LGBT Rights|LGBT rights]]), and [[economic justice]]. It opposes violence against women and racism. 

Various other issues the National Organization for Women also deals with are: 
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
*Affirmative action
*Disability rights
*EcoFeminism
*Family
*Opposing right-wing causes contrary to NOW's interests
*Global feminism
*Women's health
*Immigration
*Promotion of nominating judges with feminist viewpoints
*Legislation
*Legal recognition of same-sex marriages
{{Col-2}}
*Media activism
*Mothers' economic Rights
*Working for peace; opposition to conflicts such as the Iraq War
*Social Security
*Supreme Court
*Title IX/Education
*Welfare
*Workplace discrimination
*Women in the Military
*Young feminist programs
{{Col-end}}

===National Women's Political Caucus===
The [[National Women's Political Caucus]] (NWPC), founded in 1971, is the only national organization in the U.S. dedicated exclusively to increasing women's participation in all areas of political and public life as elected and appointed officials, as delegates to national party conventions, as judges in the state and federal courts, and as lobbyists, voters and campaign organizers.&lt;ref name="nwpc.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nwpc.org/history |title=Archived copy |access-date=2014-12-14 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029053715/http://www.nwpc.org/history |archive-date=2013-10-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Founders of NWPC include such prominent women as [[Gloria Steinem]], author, lecturer and founding editor of [[Ms. Magazine]]; former Congresswoman [[Shirley Chisholm]]; former Congresswoman [[Bella Abzug]]; [[Dorothy Height]], former president of the [[National Council of Negro Women]]; [[Jill Ruckelshaus]], former U.S. Civil Rights Commissioner; [[Ann Lewis]], former Political Director of the [[Democratic National Committee]]; [[Elly Peterson]], former vice-chair of the [[Republican National Committee]]; [[LaDonna Harris]], Indian rights leader; [[Liz Carpenter]], author, lecturer and former press secretary to [[Lady Bird Johnson]]; and [[Eleanor Holmes Norton]], [[Non-voting members of the United States House of Representatives|Delegate]] to the [[U.S. House of Representatives]] and former chair of the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]].

These women were spurred by Congress' failure to pass the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] in 1970. They believed legal, economic and social equity would come about only when women were equally represented among the nation's political decision-makers. Their faith that women's interests would best be served by women lawmakers has been confirmed time and time again, as women in Congress, state legislatures and city halls across the country have introduced, fought for and won legislation to eliminate sex discrimination and meet women's changing needs.&lt;ref name="nwpc.org"/&gt;

===Women's Equity Action League===
The [[Women's Equity Action League]] (WEAL) was a national membership organization, with state chapters and divisions, founded in 1968 and dedicated to improving the status and lives of women primarily through education, litigation, and legislation. It was a more conservative organization than [[National Organization for Women|NOW]] and was formed largely by former members of that organization who did not share NOW's assertive stance on socio-sexual issues, particularly on [[abortion rights]]. WEAL spawned a sister organization, the Women's Equity Action League Fund, which was incorporated in 1972 "to help secure legal rights for women and to carry on educational and research projects on sex discrimination". The two organizations merged in 1981 following changes in the tax code.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oasis.lib.harvard.edu/oasis/deliver/~sch00323|title=Women's Equity Action League. Records of the Women's Equity Action League, 1966-1979: A Finding Aid|website=oasis.lib.harvard.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; WEAL dissolved in 1989.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kraft |first1=Katherine Gray |last2=Stickney |first2=Zephorene L. |title=Women's Equity Action League. Records of the Women's Equity Action League, 1966-1979: A Finding Aid |url=http://oasis.lib.harvard.edu/oasis/deliver/~sch00323 |website=Oasis |publisher=[[Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study]], Harvard University |access-date=18 October 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The stated purposes of WEAL were:
*to promote greater economic progress on the part of American women;
*to press for full enforcement of existing anti-discriminatory laws on behalf of women;
*to seek correction of de facto discrimination against women;
*to gather and disseminate information and educational material;
*to investigate instances of, and seek solutions to, economic, educational, tax, and employment problems affecting women;
*to urge that girls be prepared to enter more advanced career fields;
*to seek reappraisal of federal, state and local laws and practices limiting women's employment opportunities;
*to combat by all lawful means, job discrimination against women in the pay, promotional or advancement policies of governmental or private employers;
*to seek the cooperation and coordination of all American women, individually or as organizations *to attain these objectives, whether through legislation, litigation, or other means, and by doing any and all things necessary or incident thereto.

===Norwegian Association for Women's Rights===
[[File:Margarete Bonnevie, President of the Norwegian Association for Women's Rights.jpg|thumb|[[Margarete Bonnevie]], President (1936–1946) of the [[Norwegian Association for Women's Rights]] (NKF), said that NKF will work for solutions that are in the best interest of all women and society, "be the captain who keeps a steady course" in the struggle for equality and "set out the main policy objectives and seek to get the government, parliament and local government bodies to implement the reforms that are required"&lt;ref name=Morgenbladet1946&gt;{{cite news |title=Morgenbladet |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digavis_morgenbladet_null_null_19460325_128_71_1?page=9 |date=25 March 1946}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dagbladet1946&gt;{{cite news |title=Dagbladet |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digavis_dagbladet_null_null_19460325_77_71_2 |date=25 March 1946}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Norway]] has had a tradition of government-supported liberal feminism since 1884, when the [[Norwegian Association for Women's Rights]] (NKF) was founded with the support of the progressive establishment within the then-dominant governing [[Liberal Party (Norway)|Liberal Party]] (which received 63.4% of the votes in the election the following year). The association's founders included five Norwegian prime ministers, and several of its early leaders were married to prime ministers. Rooted in first-wave liberal feminism, it works "to promote [[gender equality]] and women's and girls' [[human rights]] within the framework of [[liberal democracy]] and through [[political reform|political]] and [[legal reform]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=About us |url=http://kvinnesak.no/english/ |website=Norwegian Association for Women's Rights |access-date=2020-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; NKF members had key roles in developing the government apparatus and legislation related to gender equality in Norway since 1884; with the professionalization of gender equality advocacy from 1970s, the "Norwegian government adopted NKF's [equality] ideology as its own"&lt;ref name="Lønnå" /&gt; and adopted laws and established government institutions such as the [[Gender Equality and Anti-Discrimination Ombud|Gender Equality Ombud]] based on NKF's proposals; the new government institutions to promote gender equality were also largely built and led by prominent NKF members such as [[Eva Kolstad]], NKF's former president and the first Gender Equality Ombud. NKF's feminist tradition has often been described as Norway's [[state feminism]]. The term state feminism itself was coined by NKF member [[Helga Hernes]].&lt;ref name="Lønnå"&gt;Elisabeth Lønnå: ''Stolthet og kvinnekamp: Norsk kvinnesaksforenings historie fra 1913'', [[Gyldendal Norsk Forlag]], 1996, p. 273, passim, {{ISBN|8205244952}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although it grew out of 19th century progressive liberalism, Norwegian liberal feminism is not limited to liberalism in a modern party-political sense, and NKF is broadly representative of the democratic political spectrum from the centre-left to the centre-right, including the social democratic [[Labour Party (Norway)|Labour Party]]. Norwegian supreme court justice and former NKF President [[Karin Maria Bruzelius]] has described NKF's liberal feminism as "a realistic, sober, practical feminism".&lt;ref name=nkfom&gt;{{cite web |title=Hvem vi er |url=http://kvinnesak.no/om/ |publisher=Norwegian Association for Women's Rights|access-date=2020-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other organizations===
*[[Feminist Majority Foundation]]
*[[Ms. Magazine|''Ms.'' Magazine]]
*[[EMILY's List]]

==The Equal Rights Amendment==
{{main| Equal Rights Amendment}}
A fair number of American liberal feminists believe that equality in pay, job opportunities, political structure, social security, and education for women especially needs to be guaranteed by the [[U.S. Constitution]].

Three years after women won the right to vote, the [[Equal Rights Amendment|Equal Right Amendment]] (ERA) was introduced in Congress by Senator [[Charles Curtis]] Curtis and Representative [[Daniel Read Anthony Jr.]], both [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]]. This amendment stated that civil rights cannot be denied on the basis of one's sex. It was authored by [[Alice Paul]], head of the [[National Women's Party]], who led the [[suffrage]] campaign. Through the efforts of Alice Paul, the Amendment was introduced into each session of the [[United States Congress]], but it was buried in committee in both Houses of Congress. In 1946, it was narrowly defeated by the full [[United States Senate|Senate]], 38–35. In February 1970, twenty NOW leaders disrupted the hearings of the U.S. Senate Subcommittee on Constitutional Amendments, demanding the ERA be heard by the full Congress. In May of that year, the Senate Subcommittee began hearings on the ERA under Senator [[Birch Bayh]]. In June, the ERA finally left the House Judiciary Committee due to a discharge petition filed by Representative [[Martha Griffiths]]. In March 1972, the ERA was approved by the full Senate without changes, 84–8. Senator [[Sam Ervin]] and Representative [[Emanuel Celler]] succeeded in setting a time limit of seven years for ratification. The ERA then went to the individual states for approval but failed to win in enough of them (38) to become law. In 1978, Congress passed a disputed (less than [[supermajority]]) three year extension on the original seven year ratification limit, but the ERA could not gain approval by the needed number of states.&lt;ref&gt;[https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/R42979.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

The state legislatures that were most hostile to the ERA were Utah, Florida, Illinois, North Carolina, and Oklahoma. The NOW holds that the single most obvious problem in passing the ERA was the gender and racial imbalance in the legislatures. More than 2/3 of the women and all of the African Americans in state legislatures voted for the ERA, but less than 50% of the white men in the targeted legislatures cast pro-ERA votes in 1982.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.now.org/issues/economic/cea/history.html |title=Archived copy |access-date=2007-07-31 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070807035643/http://www.now.org/issues/economic/cea/history.html |archive-date=2007-08-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Equity feminism ==
{{main|Equity feminism}}
[[Equity feminism]] is a form of liberal feminism discussed since the 1980s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Black | first = Naomi | title = Social feminism | publisher = Cornell University Press | location = Ithaca |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=kDYqAAAAYAAJ | year = 1989 | isbn = 9780801422614 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Halfmann&gt;{{cite book | last = Halfmann | first = Jost | chapter = Social change and political mobilization in West Germany | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Q83kxhOsgxYC&amp;pg=PA79 | editor-last = Katzenstein | editor-first = Peter | title = Industry and politics in West Germany: toward the Third Republic |page=79 | publisher = Cornell University Press | location = Ithaca, N.Y | year = 1989 | isbn = 9780801495953 |quote=Quote: ''Equity-feminism differs from equality-feminism in the depth and scope of its strategic goals. A feminist revolution would pursue three goals, according to Herrad Schenk:'' }}
* ''Citing'':
:* {{cite book | last = Schenk | first = Herrad | title = Die feministische Herausforderung: 150 Jahre Frauenbewegung in Deutschland | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=wb62AAAAIAAJ | publisher = Beck | location = München | year = 1980 | isbn = 9783406060137 |quote=English translation: ''...the abolition of the gender-specific division of work in the family, the dissolution of the psychic foundations of different gender roles, and the feminization of the societal system of norms and values.'' }}&lt;/ref&gt; specifically a kind of [[classical liberalism|classically liberal]] or [[libertarianism|libertarian]] feminism, emphasizing equality under law, equal freedoms, and rights, rather than profound social transformations.&lt;ref name=Stanford&gt;{{cite web |url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-liberal/#EquFem |title=Liberal Feminism |publisher=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy |date=18 October 2007 |access-date=24 February 2016}} (Revised 30 September 2013.)&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]'' refers to [[Wendy McElroy]], [[Joan Kennedy Taylor]], [[Cathy Young]], Rita Simon, [[Katie Roiphe]], [[Diana Furchtgott-Roth]], Christine Stolba, and [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] as equity feminists.&lt;ref name="Stanford" /&gt; [[Steven Pinker]], an [[evolutionary psychologist]], identifies himself as an equity feminist, which he defines as "a moral doctrine about equal treatment that makes no commitments regarding open empirical issues in psychology or biology".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Pinker | first = Steven | author-link = Steven Pinker | chapter = Gender | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=G3_UAeo8Dh0C&amp;pg=PA510 | title = The blank slate: the modern denial of human nature | page = 341 | publisher = Viking | location = New York | year = 2002 | isbn = 9780142003343 | title-link = The Blank Slate }}&lt;/ref&gt; Barry Kuhle asserts that equity feminism is compatible with [[evolutionary psychology]], in contrast to [[Who Stole Feminism?|gender feminism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Kuhle | first = Barry X. | title = Evolutionary psychology is compatible with equity feminism, but not with gender feminism: A reply to Eagly and Wood | journal = [[Evolutionary Psychology (journal)|Evolutionary Psychology]] | volume = 10 | issue = 1 | pages = 39&amp;ndash;43 | doi = 10.1177/147470491201000104 | pmid = 22833845 | date = January 2012 | doi-access = free }}
* ''See also'':
:* {{cite journal | last1 = Eagly | first1 = Alice H. | last2 = Wood | first2 = Wendy | title = Feminism and the evolution of sex differences and similarities | journal = [[Sex Roles (journal)|Sex Roles]] | volume = 64 | issue = 9&amp;ndash;10 | pages = 758&amp;ndash;767 | doi = 10.1007/s11199-011-9949-9 | date = May 2011 | s2cid = 144177655 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Critics ==

=== Main critiques ===
Critics of liberal feminism argue that its individualist assumptions make it difficult to see the ways in which underlying social structures and values disadvantage women. They argue that even if women are not dependent upon individual men, they are still dependent upon a [[Patriarchy|patriarchal]] state. These critics believe that institutional changes, like the introduction of [[women's suffrage]], are insufficient to emancipate women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Bryson | first = Valerie | title = Feminist debates: issues of theory and political practice | pages = 14–15 | publisher = New York University Press | location = New York | year = 1999 | isbn = 9780814713488 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the more prevalent critiques of liberal feminism is that it, as a study, allows too much of its focus to fall on a "metamorphosis" of women into men, and in doing so, it disregards the significance of the traditional role of women.&lt;ref name="Tong, Rosemarie 1989"/&gt; One of the leading scholars who have critiqued liberal feminism is [[radical feminist]] [[Catherine A. MacKinnon]], an American lawyer, writer, and social activist. Specializing in issues regarding sex equality, she has been intimately involved in the cases regarding the definition of sexual harassment and sex discrimination.&lt;ref name="MacKinnon"/&gt; She, among other radical feminist scholars, views liberalism and feminism as incompatible, because liberalism offers women a "piece of the pie as currently and poisonously baked".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Morgan | first = Robin | author-link = Robin Morgan | chapter = Light bulbs, radishes and the politics of the 21st century | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=K22CrjaKYsYC&amp;pg=PA5 | editor-last1 = Bell | editor-first1 = Diane | editor-last2 = Klein | editor-first2 = Renate | title = Radically speaking: feminism reclaimed | pages = 5–8 | publisher = Spinifex Press | location = Chicago | year = 1996 | isbn = 9781742193649 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[bell hooks]]' main criticism of the philosophies of liberal feminism is that they focus too much on equality with men in their own class.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://zaknafein81.wordpress.com/2012/06/18/bell-hooks-feminist-theory-from-margin-to-center-chapter-2/|title=bell hooks' "Feminist Theory: From Margin To Center": Chapter 2.|date=2012-06-18|website=Loftier Musings|access-date=2018-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; She maintains that the "cultural basis of group oppression" is the biggest challenge, in that liberal feminists tend to ignore it.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

=== White woman's burden ===
Another important critique of liberal feminism posits the existence of a "white woman's burden" or [[white savior]] complex. The phrase "white woman's burden" derives from "[[The White Man's Burden]]". Critics such as [[Black feminism|Black feminists]] and [[Postcolonial feminism|postcolonial feminists]] assert that mainstream liberal feminism reflects only the values of middle-class, heterosexual, white women and fails to appreciate the position of women of different races, cultures, or classes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mills|first=Sara|title=Contemporary feminist theories|publisher=Edinburgh University Press|year=1998|isbn=9780748606894|editor-last1=Jackson|editor-first1=Stevi|editor-link1=Stevi Jackson|location=Edinburgh|pages=98–112|chapter=Postcolonial feminist theory|editor-last2=Jones|editor-first2=Jackie|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mg4CnbiN_rMC}}&lt;/ref&gt; With this, white liberal feminists reflect the issues that underlie the white savior complex. They do not understand women that are outside the dominant society but try to "save" or "help" them by pushing them to assimilate to their ideals of feminism. According to such critics liberal feminism fails to recognize the power dynamics that are in play with women of color and transnational women which involve [[intersectionality|multiple sources of oppression]].

== Literature ==
*Johnson, Pauline. "Normative tensions of Contemporary Feminism"&lt;ref&gt;https://files.zotero.net/16332415126/Johnson%20-%202010%20-%20Normative%20Tensions%20of%20Contemporary%20Feminism.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;''Thesis Eleven Journal''May, 2010.
*Kensinger, Loretta. "In Quest of Liberal Feminism"&lt;ref name="InQuest of Liberal Feminism"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Kensinger|first1=Loretta|year=1997|title=(In)Quest of Liberal Feminism|journal=Hypatia|volume=12|issue=4|pages=178–197|jstor=3810738|doi=10.1111/j.1527-2001.1997.tb00303.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Hypatia'' 1997.
*McCloskey, Deirdre. "Free-Market Feminism 101"&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |jstor = 40326003|title = Free-Market Feminism 101|journal = Eastern Economic Journal|volume = 26|issue = 3|pages = 363–365|last1 = McCloskey|first1 = Deirdre N.|year = 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Eastern Economic Journal''2000.
*Code, Lorraine. "Encyclopedia Of Feminist Theories" ''Taylor and Francis Group''2014.
*Dundes, Lauren. "Concerned, Meet Terrified: Intersectional Feminism and the Women's March" ''Women's Studies International Forum'' July 2018.

==References==
{{Wikibooks|Feminism/Liberal Feminism}}
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

{{Liberal feminism}}
{{Liberalism}}

[[Category:Liberal feminism| ]]
[[Category:Liberalism|Feminism]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Feminism and history]]
[[Category:Feminist movements and ideologies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>