<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101031105729|393954642" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2811532" pageid="2811532" ns="0" title="Employment discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-10-31T12:53:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=July 2008}}

'''Employment discrimination''' (or '''workplace discrimination''') is [[discrimination]] in hiring, promotion, job assignment, termination, and compensation.  It includes various types of [[harassment]].

Many jurisdictions prohibit some types of employment discrimination, often by forbidding discrimination based on certain traits ("protected categories").  In other cases, the law may require discrimination against certain groups.

In places where it is illegal, discrimination often takes subtler forms, such as [[wage discrimination]] and requirements with [[disparate impact]] on certain groups.  In addition, employees sometimes suffer retaliation for opposing workplace discrimination or for reporting violations to the authorities.

Like most discrimination, employment discrimination may occur intentionally or unintentionally, because of [[prejudice]] or [[ignorance]].

{{Discrimination sidebar}}

==Protected categories==
Laws often prohibit discrimination on the basis of:
* [[Race (classification of human beings)|Race]] or [[color]]
* [[Ethnicity]] or [[Nationality|national]] origin
* [[Sex]] or [[gender]]
* [[Pregnancy]]
* [[Religion]] or [[creed]]
* Political affiliation
* [[Language]] abilities
* [[Citizenship]]
* [[Disability]] or [[medical condition]]
* [[ageing|Age]]
* [[Sexual orientation]]
* [[Gender identity]]
* [[Marital status]]
* [[Military]] [[veteran]] status
* Military discharge status or anticipated military deployment
* [[Smoker Protection Laws|Use of Tobacco Products]]

Some jurisdictions prohibit employment discrimination against other social groups that have legal protections. They include discrimination or harassment based on [[socioeconomic]] [[Social class|class]], [[height]] or [[weight]] if not relevant to employment, and [[Province|provincial]]/[[regional]] origin.

==Effects of discrimination in the workplace==
Discrimination in the workplace negatively affects businesses in that discriminatory policies can hurt a company's reputation. A business self-limits itself when it restricts advancement to certain groups or types of employees.  Speaking negatively about a former employee can be damaging for a potential client. There is also a direct correlation between loyalty, retention, and discrimination. Employees are more likely to be looking for new jobs when they feel they have been wronged. According to a report on discrimination at the workplace by the [[International Labour Organization]], “workplace discrimination remains a persistent global problem, with new, more subtle forms emerging.”&lt;ref name="ILO"&gt;[http://www.ilo.org/global/About_the_ILO/Media_and_public_information/Feature_stories/lang--en/WCMS_075613/index.htm ILO: Workplace discrimination, a picture of hope and concern]&lt;/ref&gt; Sending wrong signals to potential clients can also cause conflict because customers can sense when employees aren't enthusiastic or don't believe in their company. This is one reason that it is important for a job applicant to observe the attitudes of people they wish to work with.  Sending positive signals to employees attracts future potential employees.

Inequalities suffered by discriminated groups spreads. Due to [[affirmative action]] policies, a new middle class has been created that consists of formerly discriminated people in some countries but in others, people who are from discriminated groups are frequently involved in the worst jobs, denied benefits, capital, land, social protection, training, or credit. Discrimination at a workplace can lead to poverty. “Discrimination creates a web of poverty, forced and child labor and social exclusion, (seeking to eliminate discrimination is indispensable to any strategy for poverty reduction and sustainable economic development).”&lt;ref name="ILO"/&gt;

In December 2005, a [[Gallup poll]] showed that job satisfaction was lowest when employees experienced discrimination.

==Gender discrimination and the workplace==
Even though there are regulations that are used to promote equality within the workplace, discrimination is still rampant. Women still do not measure up to men when it comes to income, employment rates and occupational range. Women’s average salary is 72 to 88 percent of men’s, even when variables such as education, age, position level and job tenure are considered. In most countries, the [[glass ceiling]] is ever present for women and the wage differences are significant compared to men. Based on a report by Catalyst in 2005, only “one in eight woman were CEO’s in the Fortune 500; an additional nine were CEO’s in Fortune 501-1000 companies.” Women are also more likely to be stuck in low-paid and insecure jobs. They face higher unemployment rates. “Discrimination can occur at every stage of employment, from recruitment to education and remuneration, occupational segregation, and at time of layoffs.”&lt;ref name="ILO"/&gt;

==Unintentional discrimination==
Unintentional discrimination (often termed "[[Statistical_discrimination_(economics)|statistical discrimination]]") occurs when neutral selection practices produce a substantial disparity of outcomes between one group and another. Such practices include the use of standardized tests (which may disadvantage certain groups) or height (which may disadvantage women and some ethnic groups) in the hiring process. If the requirements are job-related and a "business necessity", the disparity is irrelevant.

Some laws prohibit unintentional as well as intentional discrimination, but may have different standards for deciding what is acceptable.  Substantial disparities in outcome are not necessarily illegal, if the practices that produce them are necessary.

==Legal protection from employment discrimination==
Many countries have laws prohibiting employment discrimination.  Sometimes these are part of broader [[anti-discrimination law]]s.

* [[Employment discrimination law in the United States]]
* [[Employment discrimination law in the United Kingdom]]
* [[Employment discrimination law in the European Union]]

==See also==
* [[Equal Remuneration Convention, 1951]]
* [[Discrimination (Employment and Occupation) Convention, 1958]]
* [[Economic discrimination]]
* [[Labour and employment law]]
* [[Marriage bars]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |author=Pager, Devah |title=Marked: Race, Crime, and Finding Work in an Era of Mass Incarceration |publisher=University of Chicago Press |year=2009 |pages= |isbn=9780226644844}}
*{{cite book|title=Organizational Communication: Perspectives and Trends|last=Papa|first=Michael J.|coauthors=Tom D. Daniels, Barry K. Spiker|edition=5|publisher=SAGE|year=2007|isbn=1412916844}}
*{{cite journal |last=Trentham |first=Susan |coauthors=Laurie Larwood |year=1998 |title=Gender Discrimination and the Workplace: An Examination of Rational Bias Theory |journal=Sex Roles |volume=38 |issue=112 |pages=1–28 |doi=10.1023/A:1018782226876 |accessdate=2009-08-29}}
*{{cite news |first=Vivek |last=Wadhwa |title=The True Cost of Discrimination |newspaper=BusinessWeek Online |date=6 June 2006 |accessdate=29 August 2009 |url=http://www.businessweek.com/smallbiz/content/jun2006/sb20060606_087038.htm }}

{{Employment}}
{{Workplace}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Employment|Discrimination]]

[[he:אפליה בשוק העבודה]]
[[fi:Työsyrjintä]]
[[fr:Discrimination à l'embauche]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>