<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20240812213420|1239989521" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="912421" pageid="912421" ns="0" title="Forced assimilation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-10-31T15:42:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Involuntary cultural assimilation of minority groups}}
{{Refimprove|date=March 2009}}
{{multiple image
 | align = right
 | direction = vertical
 | total_width = 300px
 | image1 = Saami Family 1900.jpg
 | alt1 = Photograph of a Sami family in the year 1900
 | caption1 = 
 | image2 = Blomsterbarn og Kongen (10308485073).jpg
 | alt2 = Photograph of the king of Norway speaking to and receiving a bouquet of flowers from a young girl dressed in a traditional Sami gaeptie
 | caption2 = The [[Sámi people|Sámi]] people have been victim to forced assimilation tactics by the governments of Norway, Sweden, Finland, and Russia during the 19th and first half of the 20th century. Today, their culture and languages are instead promoted, legally protected, and taught in schools.
}}

'''Forced assimilation''' is the involuntary [[cultural assimilation]] of religious or [[ethnic]] [[minority group]]s, during which they are forced by a government to adopt the [[language]], [[national identity]], [[Social norm|norms]], [[mores]], [[Convention (norm)|customs]], [[tradition]]s, [[Value (ethics)|values]], [[mentality]], [[perception]]s, [[Lifestyle (sociology)|way of life]], and often the [[Forced conversion|religion]] and [[ideology]] of an established and generally larger [[community]] belonging to a [[dominant culture]]. 

The enforced use of a dominant language in legislation, [[education]], literature, and worship also counts as forced assimilation. Unlike [[ethnic cleansing]], the local population is not outright [[Genocide|destroyed]] and may or may not be forced to leave a certain area. Instead, the assimilation of the population is made mandatory. This is also called ''mandatory assimilation'' by scholars who study [[genocide]] and [[nationalism]]. 

Mandatory assimilation has sometimes been made a policy of new or contested nations, often during or in the aftermath of a war. Some examples are both the German and French forced assimilation in the provinces [[Alsace]] and (at least a part of) [[Lorraine (region)|Lorraine]], and some decades after the Swedish conquests of the Danish provinces [[Scania]], [[Blekinge]] and [[Halland]] the local population was submitted to forced assimilation, or even the forced assimilation of [[Thai Chinese|ethnic Teochew]]s in [[Bangkok]] by the [[Thailand|Siam government]] during [[World War I|World War&amp;nbsp;I]] until the [[1973 Thai popular uprising|1973 uprising]].

== Overview ==
Forced assimilation is a mode of [[Cultural assimilation|assimilation]] that occurs by force, when one society conquers another society. It may manifest through the establishment of different types of colonies and tends to take place during the process of colonization. Forced assimilation may persist into the postcolonial era.{{sfn|Danver|2015|p=708}}

Numerous societies have undergone forced assimilation following the establishment of plantation, occupation, or settler colonies. This process often intersects with broader historical events such as enslavement, forced immigration, or foreign conquest. Forced assimilation occurs when a society is deprived of the ability to preserve its cultural or societal institutions and customs, potentially resulting in either full or partial assimilation.{{sfn|Danver|2015|p=709}}

Full forced assimilation entails the complete adoption of another society's [[language]], [[religion]], and social practices, accompanied by full integration into the dominant society. Conversely, partial forced assimilation may involve the adoption of aspects of another society's language, religion, and social norms, yet without the acquisition of equivalent privileges enjoyed by the dominant society. Such incomplete assimilation is marked by the perpetuation of hierarchical relationships between the dominant and subordinate societies.{{sfn|Danver|2015|p=709}}

==Ethnic==
{{see also|Ethnic group|Ethnic conflict}}
If a [[State (polity)|state]] puts extreme emphasis on a homogeneous [[national identity]], it may resort, especially in the case of minorities originating from historical foes, to harsh, even extreme measures to 'exterminate' the minority culture, sometimes to the point of considering the only alternative its physical elimination ([[Population transfer|expulsion]] or even [[genocide]]).

States, mostly based on the idea of nation, perceived the presence of ethnic or linguistic minorities as a danger for their own [[territorial integrity]]. In fact minorities could claim their own independence, or to be rejoined with their own motherland. The consequence was the weakening or disappearing of several ethnic minorities.

The latter half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century saw the rise of Euro-Christian [[nationalism]], which asserts the [[right to homeland]] for each nation with a common heritage through [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], religion, and language. Previously, a country consisted largely of whatever peoples lived on the land that was under the dominion of a particular ruler. Thus, as principalities and kingdoms grew through conquest and marriage, a ruler could wind up with peoples of many different ethnicities under his dominion. This also reflected the long history of migrations of different tribes and peoples throughout Europe. Much of [[European history]] in the latter half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century can be understood as efforts to realign national boundaries with this concept of "one people, one nation".

===East Asia===
In [[Japan]] and [[Korea]], as each country stated themselves as a single-nation country, ethnic minorities had to hide their national identity for centuries, and many resulted in assimilation, migrants of [[Peninsular Japonic]] and [[Tungusic peoples]] in Korea.

[[Ainu people|Ainu]] and [[Ryukyuan people]] in Japan were subject to forced assimilation.{{sfn|Danver|2015|pp=189, 230}}{{sfn|Embrick|Rodríguez|Sáenz|2015|p=226}}

[[Thailand]] sought to assimilate its many [[Thai Chinese|Chinese immigrants]] by only granting Thai citizenship if they renounced all loyalty to China, learned to speak Thai, changed their names, and sent their children to Thai schools.&lt;ref&gt;Baker, Chris and Pasuk Phongpaichit. ''A History of Thailand: Third Edition'', Cambridge UP, 2014, p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Cambodian genocide]], [[Cham Muslims]] [[Cambodian genocide#Cham Muslims|were persecuted]] by the [[Khmer Rouge]] regime, first through forced assimilation, but later through direct violence (mass killing, raiding and destroying their villages).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bartrop |first=Paul R. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=unhXEAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA25 |title=Cambodian Genocide: The Essential Reference Guide |date=2022 |publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]] |isbn=978-1-4408-7653-0 |page=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====China====
{{further information|Human rights in China|Affirmative action in China}}

At least one million members of [[Islam in China|China's Muslim]] [[Uyghurs|Uyghur]] minority have been detained in [[Xinjiang re-education camps|mass detention camps]] in [[Xinjiang]], termed "[[Re-education through labor|reeducation camps]]", aimed at changing the political thinking of detainees, their identities, and their religious beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Cronin-Furman |first=Kate |title=China Has Chosen Cultural Genocide in Xinjiang—For Now |url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2018/09/19/china-has-chosen-cultural-genocide-in-xinjiang-for-now/ |access-date=2018-09-20 |website=Foreign Policy |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately one million Tibetan minority children are experiencing the impacts of Chinese government policies designed to assimilate Tibetan people culturally, religiously, and linguistically, primarily through a residential school system.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2023-02-06 |title=China: Tibetan children forced to assimilate, independent rights experts fear {{!}} UN News |url=https://news.un.org/en/story/2023/02/1133212 |access-date=2023-10-03 |website=news.un.org |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Europe ===
==== Azerbaijan ====
{{main|Forced assimilation in Azerbaijan}}

Ethnic minorities in [[Azerbaijan]], including [[Talysh people|Talyshis]] (see [[Talysh assimilation]]), [[Lezgins in Azerbaijan|Lezghins]], [[Kurds in Azerbaijan|Kurds]], [[Tat people (Caucasus)|Tats]] and [[Ingiloy people|Georgian-Ingilois]], are subjected to forced assimilation into [[Azerbaijanis|Azerbaijani Turkic identity]] and ethnic discrimination by the Azerbaijani government since the Soviet era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=UNPO: Talysh |url=https://unpo.org/members/17338 |access-date=4 May 2023 |website=unpo.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=UNPO: Lezghin |url=https://unpo.org/members/15284 |website=unpo.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Goff, Krista A. |url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/nationalities-papers/article/abs/nested-nationalism-making-and-unmaking-nations-in-the-soviet-caucasus-by-krista-a-goff-ithaca-new-york-cornell-university-press-2021-336-pp-4995-hardcover-isbn-9781501753275-3299-ebook-isbn-9781501753299/1E6B52CA25F7F6B18E1762880D66B35B |title=Nested Nationalism: Making and Unmaking Nations in the Soviet Caucasus |publisher=[[Cornell University Press]] |year=2021 |isbn=9781501753299 |place=[[Ithaca, New York]] |pages=132–179 |ref=Goff}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Angelova, Milena |year=2022 |title=Ethnography, Demography and Assimilation – How Talysh Community was Made to Disappear in Soviet Azerbaijan |url=https://www.academia.edu/91430327 |journal=Balkanistic Forum |language=bg |pages=162–166 |number=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Talysh (or the Talishi) |url=http://www.eki.ee/books/redbook/talysh.shtml |website=www.eki.ee |publisher=[[The Red Book of the Peoples of the Russian Empire]] |quote=During recent decades, Talysh were put under considerable pressure by the administration of the Azerbaijan SSR, whose aim it was to unite all minorities in the republic into one unified Azerbaijani people. This policy was relatively easy to act on with peoples of the Islamic faith, as they were simply proclaimed to be an ethnic group of the Azerbaijani people. This is borne out by the census policy which simply left several minorities of different languages unregistered. Therefore, the 1959 and following censuses do not mention the Talysh.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Tats |url=http://www.eki.ee/books/redbook/tats.shtml |website=www.eki.ee |publisher=[[The Red Book of the Peoples of the Russian Empire]] |quote=The assimilation of the Tats by the Azerbaijani has been an on-going process for centuries. It is greatly assisted by the common Islamic religion. The process was accelerated in recent years, however, when the covert but purposeful assimilation of all minorities living on the territory of the republic became the aim and policy of the Azerbaijani SSR. This is illustrated, for example, by the constant stressing of a common history and closeness of culture (even in academic publications).}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Kurds |url=http://www.eki.ee/books/redbook/kurds.shtml |website=www.eki.ee |publisher=[[The Red Book of the Peoples of the Russian Empire]] |quote=Kurdish identity is most endangered in Azerbaijan. In recent decades the Azerbaijani authorities have been attempting to assimilate all ethnic minorities. In the absence of religious differences they have succeeded. The Kurdish language is not officially used and during censuses the Kurds have been recorded as Azerbaijanis.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=March 2018 |title=World Directory of Minorities and Indigenous Peoples - Azerbaijan : Lezgins |url=https://www.refworld.org/docid/49749d5a2d.html |access-date=28 May 2023 |website=refworld.org |publisher=[[Minority Rights Group International]] |quote=In general, Lezgins enjoyed better rights in Dagestan under the jurisdiction of the Russian Federation than in Azerbaijan itself, where they have been subjected to assimilation policies. This could in part explain the variance in official statistics and unofficial estimates in the numbers of Lezgins in Azerbaijan.&lt;br&gt;[…]&lt;br&gt;Lezgins traditionally suffered from unemployment and a shortage of land. Resentments were fuelled in 1992 by the resettlement of 105,000 Azeri refugees from the Nagorno-Karabakh conflict on Lezgin lands and by the forced conscription of Lezgins to fight in the conflict. This contributed to an increase in tensions between the Lezgin community and the Azeri government over issues of land, employment, language and the absence of internal autonomy…}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== France ====
{{main|Vergonha}}

[[France]] practiced forced assimilation of [[Occitans]] and other [[Languages of France|ethnic minorities]] whose native language was not [[French language|French]], such as [[Alsatians (people)|Alsatians]], [[French Basque Country|Basques]] and [[Northern Catalonia|Catalans]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Joubert |first=Aurélie |date=2010 |title=A Comparative Study of the Evolution of Prestige Formations and of Speakers' Attitudes in Occitan and Catalan |url=https://www.research.manchester.ac.uk/portal/files/54504513/FULL_TEXT.PDF |website=www.research.manchester.ac.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt; This process extended during the 19th and 20th centuries and was known as [[Vergonha]]. It included "being made to reject and feel ashamed of one's (or one's parents') mother tongue through official exclusion, humiliation at school and rejection from the media" and was endorsed by French political leaders from [[Henri Grégoire]] onward.&lt;ref name="French National Convention"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Grégoire |first1=Henri |date=1790 |title=Report on the necessity and means to annihilate the patois and to universalise the use of the French language |url=https://fr.wikisource.org/wiki/Rapport_sur_la_n%C3%A9cessit%C3%A9_et_les_moyens_d%E2%80%99an%C3%A9antir_les_patois_et_d%E2%80%99universaliser_l%E2%80%99usage_de_la_langue_fran%C3%A7aise |access-date=16 January 2020 |website=Wikisource |publisher=French National Convention |language=fr |location=Paris}}&lt;/ref&gt; The number of [[Occitan language|Occitan]] speakers in France was reduced from 39% of the French population in 1860 to 7% in 1993.&lt;ref&gt;Louis de Baecker, ''Grammaire comparée des langues de la France'', 1860, p. 52: ''parlée dans le Midi de la France par quatorze millions d'habitants'' ("spoken in the South of France by fourteen million inhabitants"). [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k5846989r.f61.pagination.langEN.hl] + [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k5846989r.f63.langEN]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Barbour &amp; Cathie Carmichael, ''Language and nationalism in Europe'', 2000, p. 62: Occitan is spoken in 31 ''départements'', but even the [[European Bureau for Lesser-Used Languages|EBLUL]] (1993: 15–16) is wary of statistics: 'There are no official data on the number of speakers. Of some 12 to 13 million inhabitants in the area, it is estimated that 48 per cent understand Occitan, 28 per cent can speak it, about 9 per cent of the population use it on a daily basis, 13 per cent can read and 6 per cent can write the language.'&lt;/ref&gt;

To this day, France has also continuously refused to ratify the [[European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages]], and native non-French languages in France continue to be denied official recognition, with [[Occitania|Occitans]], [[Basques]], [[Corsicans]], [[Catalan people|Catalans]], [[French Flanders|Flemings]], [[Bretons]], [[Alsace|Alsatians]], and [[Savoyard dialect|Savoyards]] still having no explicit legal right to conduct public affairs in their regional languages within their home lands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Roger |first1=Geoffrey |date=2019 |title=The langues de France and the European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages: Keeping Ratification at Bay Through Disinformation: 2014–2015 |url=https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-95939-9_14 |journal=French Language Policies and the Revitalisation of Regional Languages in the 21st Century |pages=309–333 |doi=10.1007/978-3-319-95939-9_14 |isbn=978-3-319-95938-2 |s2cid=158474654 |access-date=29 July 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Russia ====
As part of the ongoing [[Russian invasion of Ukraine]] the Russian government forcibly relocated thousands of Ukrainian children to [[Russia]] and adopted them out to Russian families,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2022-10-13 |title=How Moscow grabs Ukrainian kids and makes them Russians |url=https://apnews.com/article/ukrainian-children-russia-7493cb22c9086c6293c1ac7986d85ef6 |access-date=2023-03-17 |website=AP NEWS |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; a process that is in violation of the forced assimilation prohibition of the [[Genocide Convention]]. On March 17, 2023, the [[International Criminal Court]] issued arrest warrants for Russian President [[Vladimir Putin]] and Russian Children's Rights Commissioner [[Maria Alekseyevna Lvova-Belova]] for their roles in this alleged war crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last1=Borger |first1=Julian |last2=Sauer |first2=Pjotr |date=2023-03-17 |title=ICC judges issue arrest warrant for Vladimir Putin over alleged war crimes |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2023/mar/17/vladimir-putin-arrest-warrant-ukraine-war-crimes |access-date=2023-03-17 |work=The Guardian |language=en-GB |issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Middle East ===
==== Turkey ====
{{Main|Denial of Kurds by Turkey}}
&lt;!-- This article is on forced assimilation, not genocide. This section only covers forced assimilation, not the late Ottoman genocides. --&gt;

The denial of Kurds was the official state policy of Turkey for several decades, which denied that [[Kurds]] constituted an ethnic group and instead alleged that they are a subgroup of [[Turkish people|Turks]]. The words 'Kurd' and 'Kurdistan' were omitted by state institutions, and during the 20th century, Kurds were referred to as Mountain Turks ({{Langx|tr|Dağ Türkleri}}). To this day, Turkey does not recognize Kurds as an ethnic group, though the [[Kurdish languages]] are now permitted to be used.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Hassanpour |first=Amir |author-link=Amir Hassanpour |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fP9jAAAAMAAJ |title=Nationalism and Language in Kurdistan, 1918-1985 |date=1992 |publisher=Mellen Research University Press |isbn=978-0-7734-9816-7 |location= |pages=132–133 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=12 June 2012 |title=Turkey to allow Kurdish lessons in schools |url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/europe/2012/06/2012612133656956705.html |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130313145427/http://www.aljazeera.com/news/europe/2012/06/2012612133656956705.html |archive-date=13 March 2013 |access-date=12 June 2013 |newspaper=Aljazeera}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was denied that a Kurdish nation had ever existed; according to the [[Turkish History Thesis]], the Kurds migrated from [[Turan]]ic Central Asia in the past.&lt;ref name=":12"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Poulton |first=Hugh |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=f4dpAAAAMAAJ |title=Top Hat, Grey Wolf, and Crescent: Turkish Nationalism and the Turkish Republic |date=1997 |publisher=[[C. Hurst &amp; Co.]] |isbn=0-81476648-X |pages=121 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; During the 1920s and 1930s, merchants were fined separately for every word of Kurdish they used.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; In school, students were punished if they were caught speaking Kurdish and during the 1960s Turkish language boarding schools were established in order to separate the students from their Kurdish relatives&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;Hassanpour, Amir (1992). p.133&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Turkification|Turkify]] the Kurdish population.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite web |last=webteam |date=11 December 2014 |title=SEÇBİR Konuşmaları-41: Bir Asimilasyon Projesi: Türkiye'de Yatılı İlköğretim Bölge Okulları {{!}} Haberler / Duyurular Arşivi {{!}} İstanbul Bilgi Üniversitesi |url=https://www.bilgi.edu.tr/tr/etkinlik/6298/secbir-konusmalari-41-bir-asimilasyon-projesi-turkiyede-yatili-ilkogretim-bolge-okullari/ |access-date=2021-01-28 |website=www.bilgi.edu.tr |language=tr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== North America ===
[[Atlantic slave trade|Enslaved Africans]] in the 16th to 19th centuries throughout North America,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2019-08-23 |title=How slavery flourished in the United States in charts and maps |url=https://www.nationalgeographic.com/culture/article/how-slavery-flourished-united-states-chart-maps |access-date=2024-06-19 |website=Culture |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Pargas |first=Damian Alan |url=https://archive.org/details/slaveryforcedmig0000parg |title=Slavery and forced migration in the antebellum South |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2014 |pages=133-135 |chapter=Part II Assimilation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Jackson |first=Brandon |title=From Chains to Freedom: The evolution of slavery in the Yucatan |url=https://historicalmx.org/items/show/211 |access-date=2024-06-19 |website=HistoricalMX |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; South America,&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Davis |first=Darién J. |url=https://archive.org/details/beyondslaverymul0000unse/page/n1/mode/1up |title=Beyond Slavery: The Multilayered Legacy of Africans in Latin America and the Caribbean |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |year=2007 |location=Lanham, Maryland, U.S.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Caribbean&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; were forced to abandon their native languages, religions, and cultural practices. [[African diaspora|Many communities]] descending from these groups formed traditions and linguistic dialects&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=African Diaspora Culture {{!}} Slavery and Remembrance |url=https://slaveryandremembrance.org/articles/article/?id=A0057 |access-date=2024-06-19 |website=slaveryandremembrance.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Price |first=Richard |title=Maroon Societies: Rebel Slave Communities in the Americas |publisher=Anchor Press |year=1973 |isbn=0385065086 |location=Garden City, New York |pages=25 |oclc=805137}}&lt;/ref&gt; that still face discrimination&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=King |first=Sharese |last2=Kinzler |first2=Katherine D. |date=2020-07-14 |title=Op-Ed: Bias against African American English speakers is a pillar of systemic racism |url=https://www.latimes.com/opinion/story/2020-07-14/african-american-english-racism-discrimination-speech |access-date=2024-06-19 |website=Los Angeles Times |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; and attempts at forced assimilation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Smith |first=Ernie |title=The real Ebonics debate: Power, language, and the education of African-American children |work= |publisher=Beacon |year=1998 |isbn=0-8070-3145-3 |editor-last=Lisa |editor-first=Delpit |location=Boston |chapter=What is Black English? What is Ebonics? |editor-last2=Perry |editor-first2=Theresa}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Griner |first=Allison |title=The Gullah Geechee’s fight against ‘cultural genocide’ |url=https://www.aljazeera.com/features/2015/9/4/the-gullah-geechees-fight-against-cultural-genocide |access-date=2024-06-19 |website=Al Jazeera |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== United States and Canada ====
{{further information|Cultural assimilation of Native Americans}}
In the United States and Canada, forced assimilation had been practiced against indigenous peoples through the [[American Indian boarding schools]] and [[Canadian Indian residential school system]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Little |first1=Becky |title=How Boarding Schools Tried to 'Kill the Indian' Through Assimilation |url=https://www.history.com/news/how-boarding-schools-tried-to-kill-the-indian-through-assimilation |website=History |access-date=11 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Carpenter |first1=Mary |title=Lost Generations |url=https://www.canadashistory.ca/explore/first-nations-inuit-metis/lost-generations |website=Canada's History |access-date=11 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same assimilation was also faced by French and Spanish speaking peoples populating the U.S. and Canada, through language bans, violence, and extreme prejudice by anglophones into and throughout the 20th century.{{Citation needed|date=April 2024}}

During [[World War I]] and [[World War II]], people of Japanese, German, and Italian descent faced societal and political pressure to stop speaking their native languages and abandon their cultural practices in the United States and Canada, even being interred in concentration camps (See [[Internment of Japanese Americans|Japanese American internment]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Be Good Americans: The Message of The Japanese-American Courier - Great Depression Project |url=https://depts.washington.edu/depress/japanese_american_courier_americanism.shtml |access-date=2024-06-19 |website=depts.washington.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Internment of Japanese Canadians|Japanese Canadian internment]], [[Internment of German Americans|German American internment]],&lt;ref&gt;When German Immigrants Were America’s Undesirables. (2019). Retrieved 10 October 2020, from https://www.history.com/news/anti-german-sentiment-wwi&lt;/ref&gt; [[List of concentration and internment camps#German Canadian internment|German Canadian internment]],  [[Internment of Italian Americans|Italian American internment]], [[Italian Canadian internment]]). 

=== Oceania ===

==== Australia ====
{{Main article|Stolen Generations}}
As a part of its [[genocide of Indigenous Australians]], the Australian government enacted policies of forced assimilation that included removing [[Aboriginal Australians|Australian Aboriginal]] and [[Torres Strait Islanders|Torres Strait Islander]] children from their families throughout the twentieth century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Nieves |first=Evelyn |date=2017-05-24 |title=Australia's 'Stolen Generations' Tell Their Stories |url=https://archive.nytimes.com/lens.blogs.nytimes.com/2017/05/24/australias-aboriginal-stolen-generation-tells-its-stories/ |access-date=2024-08-08 |website=Lens Blog |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious==
{{further information|Forced conversion}}

Assimilation also includes the (often forced) [[religious conversion|conversion]] or [[secularization]]{{citation needed|date=December 2022}} of religious members of a minority group.

Throughout the Middle Ages and until the mid-19th century, most Jews in Europe were forced to live in small towns ([[shtetl]]s) and were restricted from entering universities or high-level professions.

In the [[Kingdom of Hungary]], most ethnic Romanians, Croatians, Czechs, and other non-Hungarians were forcibly converted to [[Catholic Church|Catholicism]], and those who resisted conversion were usually arrested.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Lupaș |first=Ioan |author-link=Ioan Lupaș |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_0ppAAAAMAAJ |title=The Hungarian Policy of Magyarization |publisher=Romanian Cultural Foundation |year=1992}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Cultural genocide]]
* [[Cultural imperialism]]
* [[Diaspora politics]]
* [[Ethnic interest group]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Linguistic discrimination]]
* [[Language shift]]
* [[Language death]]
* [[Stolen Generations]]
* [[Outline of genocide studies]]
* ''[[Umvolkung]]''
* [[Anglicisation]]
* [[Francization]]
* [[Russification]]
* [[Slavicisation]]
* [[Sinicization]]
* [[Germanisation]]
* [[Magyarization]]
* [[Persianization]]
* [[Turkification]]
* [[Arabization]]
* [[Kurdification]]
* [[Romanization]]
* [[Sovietization]]
* [[Europeanisation]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Sources ==
* {{cite book|editor-last = Danver|editor-first = Steven L.|editor-link = Steven L. Danver|title = Native Peoples of the World: An Encyclopedia of Groups, Cultures and Contemporary Issues|date = 2015|publisher = [[Routledge]]|isbn = 9780765682222}}
* {{cite book|editor-last1 = Embrick|editor-first1 = David G.|editor-last2 = Rodríguez|editor-first2 = Néstor P.|editor-last3 = Sáenz|editor-first3 = Rogelio|editor-link3 = Rogelio Sáenz|title = The International Handbook of the Demography of Race and Ethnicity|date = 2015|publisher = Springer Netherlands|isbn = 9789048188918}}

== Further reading ==
* [[Bibliography of genocide studies]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Forced Assimilation}}
[[Category:Cultural assimilation]]
[[Category:Cultural genocide]]
[[Category:Political and cultural purges]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>