<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231030014309|1182561453" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="912421" pageid="912421" ns="0" title="Forced assimilation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-10-30T13:49:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Involuntary cultural assimilation of minority groups}}
{{Refimprove|date=March 2009}}
{{multiple image
 | align = right
 | direction = vertical
 | total_width = 300px
 | image1 = Saami Family 1900.jpg
 | alt1 = Photograph of a Sami family in the year 1900
 | caption1 = 
 | image2 = Blomsterbarn og Kongen (10308485073).jpg
 | alt2 = Photograph of the king of Norway speaking to and receiving a bouquet of flowers from a young girl dressed in a traditional Sami gaeptie
 | caption2 = The [[Sámi]] people have been victim to forced assimilation tactics by the governments of Norway, Sweden, Finland, and Russia during the 19th and first half of the 20th century. Today, their culture and languages are instead promoted, legally protected, and taught in schools.
}}

'''Forced assimilation''' is the involuntary [[cultural assimilation]] of religious or [[ethnic]] [[minority group]]s, during which they are forced by a government to adopt the [[language]], [[national identity]], [[Social norm|norms]], [[mores]], [[Convention (norm)|customs]], [[tradition]]s, [[Value (ethics)|values]], [[mentality]], [[perception]]s, [[Lifestyle (sociology)|way of life]], and often the [[Forced conversion|religion]] and [[ideology]] of an established and generally larger [[community]] belonging to a [[dominant culture]]. The enforced use of a dominant language in legislation, [[education]], literature, and worship also counts as forced assimilation. Unlike [[ethnic cleansing]], the local population is not outright [[Genocide|destroyed]] and may or may not be forced to leave a certain area. Instead, the assimilation of the population is made mandatory. This is also called ''mandatory assimilation'' by scholars who study [[genocide]] and [[nationalism]]. Mandatory assimilation has sometimes been made a policy of new or contested nations, often during or in the aftermath of a war. Some examples are both the German and French forced assimilation in the provinces [[Alsace]] and (at least a part of) [[Lorraine (region)|Lorraine]], and some decades after the Swedish conquests of the Danish provinces [[Scania]], [[Blekinge]] and [[Halland]] the local population was submitted to forced assimilation, or even the forced assimilation of [[Thai Chinese|ethnic Teochew]]s in [[Bangkok]] by the [[Thailand|Siam government]] during [[World War I]] until the [[1973 Thai popular uprising|1973 uprising]].

==Ethnic==
{{see also|Ethnic group|Ethnic conflict}}
If a [[State (polity)|state]] puts extreme emphasis on a homogeneous [[national identity]], it may resort, especially in the case of minorities originating from historical foes, to harsh, even extreme measures to 'exterminate' the minority culture, sometimes to the point of considering the only alternative its physical elimination ([[Population transfer|expulsion]] or even [[genocide]]).

States, mostly based on the idea of nation, perceived the presence of ethnic or linguistic minorities as a danger for their own [[territorial integrity]]. In fact minorities could claim their own independence, or to be rejoined with their own motherland. The consequence was the weakening or disappearing of several ethnic minorities.

The latter half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century saw the rise of [[nationalism]], which asserts the [[right to homeland]] for each nation with a common heritage through [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[religion]], [[language]] and [[culture]]. Previously, a country consisted largely of whatever peoples lived on the land that was under the dominion of a particular ruler. Thus, as principalities and kingdoms grew through conquest and marriage, a ruler could wind up with peoples of many different ethnicities under his dominion. This also reflected the long history of migrations of different tribes and peoples throughout Europe. Much of [[European history]] in the latter half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century can be understood as efforts to realign national boundaries with this concept of "one people, one nation".

Much conflict would arise when one nation asserted territorial rights to land outside its borders on the basis of a common bond with the people living on that land. (Example: organized territorial rights by [[Russia]] for [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]'s breakaway province of South [[Ossetia]] to North Ossetia) Another source of conflict arose when a group of people who constituted a minority in one nation would seek to secede from the nation either to form an independent nation or join another nation with whom they felt stronger ties. Yet another source of conflict was the desire of some nations to expel people from territory within its borders on the ground that those people did not share a common bond with the majority of people living in that nation.{{specify|date=July 2014}}{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

It is useful to contrast the mass migrations and forced expulsion of [[ethnic Germans]] out of [[Eastern Europe]] with other massive [[population transfer]]s, such as [[population exchange between Greece and Turkey]], and population exchanges that occurred after the [[Partition of India]]. In all cases those expelled suffered greatly.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} [[Forced migration]]s took place after each of the two [[world wars]].

===East Asia===
In [[Japan]] and [[Korea]], as each country stated themselves as a single-nation country, ethnic minorities had to hide their national identity for centuries, and many resulted in assimilation, such as [[Ainu people|Ainu]] and [[Ryukyuan people]] in Japan, migrants of [[Goguryeo]], [[Balhae]] and [[Tungusic peoples]] in Korea.

[[Thailand]] sought to assimilate its many Chinese immigrants by only granting Thai citizenship if they renounced all loyalty to China, learned to speak Thai, changed their names, and sent their children to Thai schools.&lt;ref&gt;Baker, Chris and Pasuk Phongpaichit. ''A History of Thailand: Third Edition'', Cambridge UP, 2014, p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt;

====China====
{{further information|Human rights in China|Affirmative action in China}}

At least one million members of [[Islam in China|China's Muslim]] [[Uyghurs|Uyghur]] minority have been detained in [[Xinjiang re-education camps|mass detention camps]] in [[Xinjiang]], termed "[[Re-education through labor|reeducation camps]]", aimed at changing the political thinking of detainees, their identities, and their religious beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2018/09/19/china-has-chosen-cultural-genocide-in-xinjiang-for-now/|title=China Has Chosen Cultural Genocide in Xinjiang—For Now|last=Cronin-Furman|first=Kate|website=Foreign Policy|language=en|access-date=2018-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately one million Tibetan minority children are experiencing the impacts of Chinese government policies designed to assimilate Tibetan people culturally, religiously, and linguistically, primarily through a residential school system.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2023-02-06 |title=China: Tibetan children forced to assimilate, independent rights experts fear {{!}} UN News |url=https://news.un.org/en/story/2023/02/1133212 |access-date=2023-10-03 |website=news.un.org |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== North America ===
{{further information|Cultural assimilation of Native Americans|Mexicans in Omaha, Nebraska}}
In the United States and Canada, forced assimilation had been practiced against indigenous peoples through the [[Canadian Indian residential school system]] and [[American Indian boarding schools]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Little |first1=Becky |title=How Boarding Schools Tried to 'Kill the Indian' Through Assimilation |url=https://www.history.com/news/how-boarding-schools-tried-to-kill-the-indian-through-assimilation |website=History |access-date=11 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Carpenter |first1=Mary |title=Lost Generations |url=https://www.canadashistory.ca/explore/first-nations-inuit-metis/lost-generations |website=Canada's History |access-date=11 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same assimilation was also faced by French and Spanish speaking peoples populating the US and Canada, through language bans, violence, and extreme prejudice by anglophones into and throughout the 20th century.

In the United States, during World War I, the American government burned most German books, banned the use of German in public places and renamed many places that previously had German names with more English-sounding words; the forced assimilation was highly successful. Before that, the German American community at large had refused assimilation, and retained their German traditions, such as having beers on Sundays. [[Plautdietsch language#Speaker population and language maintenance|German]] also was the major language in many parts of the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://macaulay.cuny.edu/seminars/drabik09/articles/g/e/r/German_Immigrants_and_Assimilation_0e32.html|title = German Immigrants and Assimilation - the Peopling of New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;When German Immigrants Were America’s Undesirables. (2019). Retrieved 10 October 2020, from https://www.history.com/news/anti-german-sentiment-wwi&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Europe ===
==== Azerbaijan ====
Ethnic minorities in [[Azerbaijan]], including, [[Talysh people|Talyshis]] (see [[Talysh assimilation]]), [[Lezgins in Azerbaijan|Lezghins]], [[Kurds in Azerbaijan|Kurds]], [[Tat people (Caucasus)|Tats]] and [[Ingiloy people|Georgian-Ingilois]], are subjected to forced assimilation into [[Azerbaijanis|Azerbaijani Turkic identity]] and ethnic discrimination by the Azerbaijani government since the Soviet era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://unpo.org/members/17338|title = UNPO: Talysh|website = unpo.org|access-date = 4 May 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://unpo.org/members/15284|title = UNPO: Lezghin|website = unpo.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|ref = Goff|author = Goff, Krista A.|url = https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/nationalities-papers/article/abs/nested-nationalism-making-and-unmaking-nations-in-the-soviet-caucasus-by-krista-a-goff-ithaca-new-york-cornell-university-press-2021-336-pp-4995-hardcover-isbn-9781501753275-3299-ebook-isbn-9781501753299/1E6B52CA25F7F6B18E1762880D66B35B|title = Nested Nationalism: Making and Unmaking Nations in the Soviet Caucasus|place = [[Ithaca, New York]]|year = 2021|publisher = [[Cornell University Press]]|pages = 132–179|isbn = 9781501753299}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author = Angelova, Milena|title = Ethnography, Demography and Assimilation – How Talysh Community was Made to Disappear in Soviet Azerbaijan|url = https://www.academia.edu/91430327|language = bg|year = 2022|journal = Balkanistic Forum|number = 2|pages = 162–166}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = The Talysh (or the Talishi)|url = http://www.eki.ee/books/redbook/talysh.shtml|website = www.eki.ee|publisher = [[The Red Book of the Peoples of the Russian Empire]]|quote = During recent decades, Talysh were put under considerable pressure by the administration of the Azerbaijan SSR, whose aim it was to unite all minorities in the republic into one unified Azerbaijani people. This policy was relatively easy to act on with peoples of the Islamic faith, as they were simply proclaimed to be an ethnic group of the Azerbaijani people. This is borne out by the census policy which simply left several minorities of different languages unregistered. Therefore, the 1959 and following censuses do not mention the Talysh.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = The Tats|url = http://www.eki.ee/books/redbook/tats.shtml|website = www.eki.ee|publisher = [[The Red Book of the Peoples of the Russian Empire]]|quote = The assimilation of the Tats by the Azerbaijani has been an on-going process for centuries. It is greatly assisted by the common Islamic religion. The process was accelerated in recent years, however, when the covert but purposeful assimilation of all minorities living on the territory of the republic became the aim and policy of the Azerbaijani SSR. This is illustrated, for example, by the constant stressing of a common history and closeness of culture (even in academic publications).}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Kurds|url = http://www.eki.ee/books/redbook/kurds.shtml|website = www.eki.ee|publisher = [[The Red Book of the Peoples of the Russian Empire]]|quote = Kurdish identity is most endangered in Azerbaijan. In recent decades the Azerbaijani authorities have been attempting to assimilate all ethnic minorities. In the absence of religious differences they have succeeded. The Kurdish language is not officially used and during censuses the Kurds have been recorded as Azerbaijanis.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://www.refworld.org/docid/49749d5a2d.html|title = World Directory of Minorities and Indigenous Peoples - Azerbaijan : Lezgins
|website = refworld.org|access-date = 28 May 2023|publisher = [[Minority Rights Group International]]|date = March 2018|quote = In general, Lezgins enjoyed better rights in Dagestan under the jurisdiction of the Russian Federation than in Azerbaijan itself, where they have been subjected to assimilation policies. This could in part explain the variance in official statistics and unofficial estimates in the numbers of Lezgins in Azerbaijan.&lt;br&gt;[…]&lt;br&gt;Lezgins traditionally suffered from unemployment and a shortage of land. Resentments were fuelled in 1992 by the resettlement of 105,000 Azeri refugees from the Nagorno-Karabakh conflict on Lezgin lands and by the forced conscription of Lezgins to fight in the conflict. This contributed to an increase in tensions between the Lezgin community and the Azeri government over issues of land, employment, language and the absence of internal autonomy…}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Russia ====
As part of the ongoing [[Russian invasion of Ukraine]] the Russian government forcibly relocated thousands of Ukrainian children to [[Russia]] and adopted them out to Russian families,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2022-10-13 |title=How Moscow grabs Ukrainian kids and makes them Russians |url=https://apnews.com/article/ukrainian-children-russia-7493cb22c9086c6293c1ac7986d85ef6 |access-date=2023-03-17 |website=AP NEWS |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; a process that is in violation of the forced assimilation prohibition of the [[Genocide Convention]]. On March 17, 2023 the [[International Criminal Court]] issued arrest warrants for Russian President [[Vladimir Putin]] and Russian Children's Rights Commissioner [[Maria Alekseyevna Lvova-Belova]] for their roles in this alleged war crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last1=Borger |first1=Julian |last2=Sauer |first2=Pjotr |date=2023-03-17 |title=ICC judges issue arrest warrant for Vladimir Putin over alleged war crimes |language=en-GB |work=The Guardian |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2023/mar/17/vladimir-putin-arrest-warrant-ukraine-war-crimes |access-date=2023-03-17 |issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== France ====

[[France]] practiced forced assimilation of [[Occitans]] and other [[Languages of France|ethnic minorities]] whose native language was not [[French language|French]], such as [[Alsatians (people)|Alsatians]], [[French Basque Country|Basques]] and [[Northern Catalonia|Catalans]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.research.manchester.ac.uk/portal/files/54504513/FULL_TEXT.PDF|title=A Comparative Study of the Evolution of Prestige Formations and of Speakers' Attitudes in Occitan and Catalan|last=Joubert|first=Aurélie|date=2010|website=www.research.manchester.ac.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt; This process extended during the 19th and 20th centuries and was known as [[Vergonha]]. It included "being made to reject and feel ashamed of one's (or one's parents') mother tongue through official exclusion, humiliation at school and rejection from the media" and was endorsed by French political leaders from [[Henri Grégoire]] onward.&lt;ref name="French National Convention"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Grégoire |first1=Henri |title=Report on the necessity and means to annihilate the patois and to universalise the use of the French language |url=https://fr.wikisource.org/wiki/Rapport_sur_la_n%C3%A9cessit%C3%A9_et_les_moyens_d%E2%80%99an%C3%A9antir_les_patois_et_d%E2%80%99universaliser_l%E2%80%99usage_de_la_langue_fran%C3%A7aise |website=Wikisource |publisher=French National Convention |location=Paris |language=fr |date=1790 |access-date=16 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; The number of [[Occitan language|Occitan]] speakers in France was reduced from 39% of the French population in 1860 to 7% in 1993.&lt;ref&gt;Louis de Baecker, ''Grammaire comparée des langues de la France'', 1860, p. 52: ''parlée dans le Midi de la France par quatorze millions d'habitants'' ("spoken in the South of France by fourteen million inhabitants"). [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k5846989r.f61.pagination.langEN.hl] + [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k5846989r.f63.langEN]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Barbour &amp; Cathie Carmichael, ''Language and nationalism in Europe'', 2000, p. 62: Occitan is spoken in 31 ''départements'', but even the [[European Bureau for Lesser-Used Languages|EBLUL]] (1993: 15–16) is wary of statistics: 'There are no official data on the number of speakers. Of some 12 to 13 million inhabitants in the area, it is estimated  that 48 per cent understand Occitan, 28 per cent can speak it, about 9 per cent of the population use it on a daily basis, 13 per cent can read and 6 per cent can write the language.'&lt;/ref&gt;

To this day, France has also continuously refused to ratify the [[European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages]], and native non-French languages in France continue to be denied official recognition, with [[Occitania|Occitans]], [[Basques]], [[Corsicans]], [[Catalan people|Catalans]], [[French Flanders|Flemings]], [[Bretons]], [[Alsace|Alsatians]], and [[Savoyard dialect|Savoyards]] still having no explicit legal right to conduct public affairs in their regional languages within their home lands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Roger |first1=Geoffrey |title=The langues de France and the European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages: Keeping Ratification at Bay Through Disinformation: 2014–2015 |journal=French Language Policies and the Revitalisation of Regional Languages in the 21st Century |date=2019 |pages=309–333 |doi=10.1007/978-3-319-95939-9_14 |isbn=978-3-319-95938-2 |s2cid=158474654 |url=https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-95939-9_14 |access-date=29 July 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious==
{{further information|Forced conversion}}

Assimilation also includes the (often forced) [[religious conversion|conversion]] or [[secularization]]{{citation needed|date=December 2022}} of religious members of a minority group.

Throughout the Middle Ages and until the mid-19th century, most Jews in Europe were forced to live in small towns ([[shtetl]]s) and were restricted from entering universities or high-level professions.

During the [[Cambodian Genocide]], [[Cham Muslims]] [[Cambodian genocide#Cham Muslims|were persecuted]] by the [[Khmer Rouge]] regime, first through forced assimilation, but later through direct violence (mass killing, raiding and destroying their villages).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bartrop |first=Paul R. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=unhXEAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA25 |title=Cambodian Genocide: The Essential Reference Guide |publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]] |date=2022 |isbn=978-1-4408-7653-0 |page=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==National==
{{further information|Nationalism|Patriotism}}
When new [[immigrant]]s enter a country, there is a tension as they adapt to new people and surroundings to fit in, while holding on to their original culture. Here, studies show that native inhabitants often expect assimilation especially from negatively viewed immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Montreuil | first1 = Annie | last2 = Richard | first2 = Y. Bourhis Majority Acculturation Orientations Toward | year = 2001 | title = Valued" and "Devalued" Immigrants | journal = Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology | volume = 32 | issue = 6| pages = 698–719 | doi = 10.1177/0022022101032006004 | s2cid = 145706948 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Montreuil | first1 = Annie | last2 = Bourhis | first2 = Richard Y. | year = 2004 | title = Acculturation orientations of competing host communities toward valued and devalued immigrants | doi = 10.1016/j.ijintrel.2005.01.002 | journal = International Journal of Intercultural Relations | volume = 28 | issue = 6| pages = 507–532 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, [[Individualism|assimilation pressure]] seems to be particularly pronounced toward [[Immigrant generations#Second generation|second generation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi=10.1016/j.ijintrel.2013.10.007 | volume=39 | title="It's on Time That They Assimilate" – Differential acculturation expectations towards first and second generation immigrants | journal=International Journal of Intercultural Relations | pages=188–195| year=2014 | last1=Kunst | first1=Jonas R. | last2=Sam | first2=David L. | url=https://zenodo.org/record/812238 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Acculturation]]
* [[Cultural genocide]]
* [[Cultural imperialism]]
* [[Diaspora politics]]
* [[Ethnic interest group]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Hegemony]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[Linguistic discrimination]]
* [[Language shift]]
* [[Language death]]
* "[[More Irish than the Irish themselves]]"
* [[Stolen Generations]]
*[[Outline of Genocide studies]]
* ''[[Umvolkung]]''
*[[Francization]]
*[[Russification]]
*[[Slavicisation]]
*[[Germanisation]]
*[[Kurdification]]
*[[Kurdification of Yazidis]]
*[[Turkification]]
*[[Arabization]]
*[[Romanization]]
*[[Sovietization]]
*[[Europeanisation]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [[Bibliography of Genocide studies]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Forced Assimilation}}
[[Category:Cultural assimilation]]
[[Category:Cultural genocide]]
[[Category:Political and cultural purges]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>