<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20090523231114|291901156" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="912421" pageid="912421" ns="0" title="Forced assimilation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-05-25T23:21:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=March 2009}}
{{POV|date=March 2009}}

'''Forced assimilation''' is a process of forced [[cultural assimilation]] of religious or ethnic [[minority group]]s, into an established and generally larger community. This presumes a loss of many characteristics which make the minority different.

== Ethnic assimilation ==
If a state or a government puts extreme emphasis on a homogeneous national identity, it may resort, especially in the case of minorities originating from historical foes, to harsh, even extreme measures to 'exterminate' the minority culture, sometimes to the point of considering the only alternative its physical elimination ([[expulsion]] or even [[genocide]]).

In Europe during the time of [[Nationalism]]. Europeans states, mostly based on the idea of nation, perceived the  presence of ethnic or linguistic minorities as a danger for their own [[territorial integrity]]. In fact minorities could claim their own independence, or to be rejoined with their own motherland. For this reason, in the 19th and 20th century, most European states conducted politics of forced assimilation against their ethnic and linguistic minorities.{{Fact|date=March 2009}} The consequence was the weakening or disappearing of several ethnic minorities.  [[Forced migration]]s took place after each of the two [[world wars]].

The latter half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century saw the rise of nationalism in Europe. Previously, a country consisted largely of whatever peoples lived on the land that was under the dominion of a particular ruler. Thus, as principalities and kingdoms grew through conquest and marriage, a ruler could wind up with peoples of many different ethnicities under his dominion.  This also reflected the long history of migrations of different tribes and peoples through Europe.

The concept of nationalism was based on the idea of a "people" who shared a common bond through race, religion, language and culture. Furthermore, nationalism asserted that each "people" had a right to its own nation. Thus, much of European history in the latter half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century can be understood as efforts to realign national boundaries with this concept of "one people, one nation".

Much conflict would arise when one nation asserted territorial rights to land outside its borders on the basis of a common bond with the people living on that land. (Example?)  Another source of conflict arose when a group of people who constituted a minority in one nation would seek to secede from the nation either to form an independent nation or join another nation with whom they felt stronger ties. Yet another source of conflict was the desire of some nations to expel people from territory within its borders on the ground that those people did not share a common bond with the majority of people living in that nation.(Specifics?)  {{Fact|date=March 2009}}

It is useful to contrast the mass migrations and forced expulsion of ethnic Germans out of Eastern Europe with other massive transfers of populations, such as exchange of populations between Greece and Turkey, and population exchanges that occurred after the Partition of India. In all cases those expelled suffered greatly.{{Fact|date=March 2009}}

See also [[Assimilation (linguistics)]].

==Religious assimilation==
Assimilation also includes the (often forced) conversion or secularization of religious members of a minority group, such as [[Judaism]]. 

Throughout the Middle Ages and until the mid-19th century, most Jews in Europe were forced to live in small towns (shtetls) and were restricted from entering universities or high-level professions. 

{{main|Jewish Assimilation}}

== Massive immigration and colonization ==
When new immigrants enter a country, there is a tension as they adapt to new people and surroundings to fit in, while holding on to their original culture. Some rules and expectations they have to follow.  Sooner or later the majority culture will no longer view the immigrants (or perhaps their children) as immigrants; they will seem to be similar to everyone else because of assimilation. 

Sometimes the immigrants instead assimilate the original inhabitants, depending on numbers involved.
This can occur during a [[colonisation]] process.

==See also==
* [[Acculturation]]
* [[Americanization (of Native Americans)]]
* [[Cultural imperialism]]
* [[Cultural appropriation]]
* [[Diaspora politics]]
* [[Ethnic interest group]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* Forced assimilation
* [[Forced conversion]]
* [[Hegemony]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[Language shift]]
* [[Linguicide]]
* [[Mexicans in Omaha, Nebraska]]
* "[[More Irish than the Irish themselves]]"
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Patriotism]]
* [[Political correctness]]
* [[Racial integration|Integration]]
* [[Racial segregation|segregation]]
* [[Stolen generation]]
* [[White American]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Forced Assimilation}}
[[Category:Cultural assimilation]]

[[de:Ethnizität]]
[[fr:Rayonnement culturel#L.27assimilation_forc.C3.A9e]]
[[it:Assimilazione forzata]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>