<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151015083622|685837844" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="912421" pageid="912421" ns="0" title="Forced assimilation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-01T08:11:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=March 2009}}
'''Forced assimilation''' is a process of forced [[cultural assimilation]] of religious or ethnic [[minority group]]s, into an established and generally larger [[community]]. Also enforcement of a new language in legislation, education, literature, worshiping counts as forced assimilation. Forced assimilation can, and has been, used both by minorities against majority as well as the opposite. &lt;u&gt;Unlike&lt;/u&gt; [[Ethnic cleansing]] isn't the local population forced to leave a certain area. Instead the population becomes assimilated by force. It has often been used after an area has changed nationality, often in the aftermath of war. Some examples are both the German and French forced assimilation in the provinces [[Alsace]] and (at least a part of) [[Lorraine (region)|Lorraine]], and some decades after the Swedish conquests of the Danish provinces [[Scania]], [[Blekinge]] and [[Halland]] the local population was submitted to forced assimilation.

==Ethnic assimilation==
If a [[country|state]] puts extreme emphasis on a homogeneous [[national identity]], it may resort, especially in the case of minorities originating from historical foes, to harsh, even extreme measures to 'exterminate' the minority culture, sometimes to the point of considering the only alternative its physical elimination ([[Population transfer|expulsion]] or even [[genocide]]).

States, mostly based on the idea of nation, perceived the presence of ethnic or linguistic minorities as a danger for their own [[territorial integrity]]. In fact minorities could claim their own independence, or to be rejoined with their own motherland. The consequence was the weakening or disappearing of several ethnic minorities.  [[Forced migration]]s took place after each of the two [[world wars]].

The latter half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century saw the rise of [[nationalism]]. Previously, a country consisted largely of whatever peoples lived on the land that was under the dominion of a particular ruler. Thus, as principalities and kingdoms grew through conquest and marriage, a ruler could wind up with peoples of many different ethnicities under his dominion.  This also reflected the long history of migrations of different tribes and peoples through Europe.

The concept of nationalism was based on the idea of a "people" who shared a common bond through [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[religion]], [[language]] and [[culture]]. Furthermore, nationalism asserted that each "people" had a right to its own nation. Much of [[European history]] in the latter half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century can be understood as efforts to realign national boundaries with this concept of "one people, one nation". Such scenes also happened in [[Japan]] and [[Korea]], as the two countries stated themselves as a single-nation country, ethnic minorities had to hide their national identity for centuries, and many resulted in assimilation, such as [[Ainu people|Ainu]] and [[Ryukyuan people]] in Japan, migrants of [[Goguryeo]], [[Balhae]] and [[Tungusic peoples]] in Korea. Much conflict would arise when one nation asserted territorial rights to land outside its borders on the basis of a common bond with the people living on that land. (Example: organized territorial rights by [[Russia]] for [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]'s breakaway province of South [[Ossetia]] to North Ossetia)  Another source of conflict arose when a group of people who constituted a minority in one nation would seek to secede from the nation either to form an independent nation or join another nation with whom they felt stronger ties. Yet another source of conflict was the desire of some nations to expel people from territory within its borders on the ground that those people did not share a common bond with the majority of people living in that nation.{{specify|date=July 2014}}{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

It is useful to contrast the mass migrations and forced expulsion of ethnic [[Ethnic Germans|Germans]] out of [[Eastern Europe]] with other massive transfers of populations, such as exchange of populations between [[Greece]] and [[Turkey]], and population exchanges that occurred after the [[Partition of India]]. In all cases those expelled suffered greatly.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

==Religious assimilation==
{{main|Jewish Assimilation}}

Assimilation also includes the (often [[forced conversion|forced]]) [[religious conversion|conversion]] or [[secularization]] of religious members of a minority group.

Throughout the Middle Ages and until the mid-19th century, most Jews in Europe were forced to live in small towns ([[shtetl]]s) and were restricted from entering universities or high-level professions. See also [[Christianity in Pakistan]] for contemporary issues.

==Immigration==
When new [[immigrant]]s enter a country, there is a tension as they adapt to new people and surroundings to fit in, while holding on to their original culture. Here, studies show that native inhabitants often expect assimilation especially from negatively viewed immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;Annie Montreuil and Richard Y. Bourhis Majority Acculturation Orientations Toward "Valued" and "Devalued" Immigrants Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology November 2001 32: 698-719, {{DOI|10.1177/0022022101032006004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Annie Montreuil, Richard Y. Bourhis Acculturation orientations of competing host communities toward valued and devalued immigrants, International Journal of Intercultural Relations, Volume 28, Issue 6, November 2004, Pages 507–532 http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijintrel.2005.01.002&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, assimilation pressure seems to be particularly pronounced toward the second generation of these immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;"It's on Time That They Assimilate" – Differential acculturation expectations towards first and second generation immigrants, International Journal of Intercultural Relations 2013, Jonas R. Kunst, David L. Sam, http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0147176713001223 https://www.academia.edu/5282613/_Its_on_Time_That_They_Assimilate_-_Differential_acculturation_expectations_towards_first_and_second_generation_immigrants&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|3}}
* [[Acculturation]]
* [[Affirmative action in China]]
* [[Americanization (of Native Americans)]]
* [[Assimilation (linguistics)]]
* [[Cultural appropriation]]
* [[Cultural imperialism]]
* [[Diaspora politics]]
* [[Ethnic interest group]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Forced conversion]]
* [[Hegemony]]
* [[Human rights in China]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[Language shift]]
* [[Linguicide]]
* [[Mexicans in Omaha, Nebraska]]
* "[[More Irish than the Irish themselves]]"
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Patriotism]]
* [[Political correctness]]
* [[Racial integration]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Stolen generation]]
* [[White American]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Forced Assimilation}}
[[Category:Cultural assimilation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>