<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221111011201|1121199300" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="912421" pageid="912421" ns="0" title="Forced assimilation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-22T13:13:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Involuntary cultural assimilation of minority groups}}
{{Refimprove|date=March 2009}}
'''Forced assimilation''' is an involuntary process of [[cultural assimilation]] of religious or [[ethnic]] [[minority group]]s during which they are forced to adopt [[language]], [[Identity (social science)|identity]], [[Social norm|norms]], [[mores]], [[Convention (norm)|customs]], [[tradition]]s, [[Value (ethics)|values]], [[mentality]], [[perception]]s, [[Lifestyle (sociology)|way of life]], and often [[Forced conversion|religion]] and [[ideology]] of established and generally larger [[community]] belonging to [[dominant culture]] by government. Also enforcement of a new language in legislation, [[education]], literature, worshiping counts as forced assimilation. Unlike [[ethnic cleansing]], the local population is not outright [[Genocide|destroyed]] and may or may not be forced to leave a certain area. Instead the population becomes assimilated by force. It has often been used after an area has changed nationality, often in the aftermath of war. Some examples are both the German and French forced assimilation in the provinces [[Alsace]] and (at least a part of) [[Lorraine (region)|Lorraine]], and some decades after the Swedish conquests of the Danish provinces [[Scania]], [[Blekinge]] and [[Halland]] the local population was submitted to forced assimilation, or even the forced assimilation of [[Thai Chinese|ethnic Teochew]]s in [[Bangkok]] by the [[Thailand|Siam government]] during [[World War I]] until the [[1973 Thai popular uprising|1973 uprising]].

==Ethnic==
{{see also|Ethnic group|Ethnic conflict}}
If a [[State (polity)|state]] puts extreme emphasis on a homogeneous [[national identity]], it may resort, especially in the case of minorities originating from historical foes, to harsh, even extreme measures to 'exterminate' the minority culture, sometimes to the point of considering the only alternative its physical elimination ([[Population transfer|expulsion]] or even [[genocide]]).

States, mostly based on the idea of nation, perceived the presence of ethnic or linguistic minorities as a danger for their own [[territorial integrity]]. In fact minorities could claim their own independence, or to be rejoined with their own motherland. The consequence was the weakening or disappearing of several ethnic minorities.

The latter half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century saw the rise of [[nationalism]], which asserts the [[right to homeland]] for each nation with a common heritage through [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[religion]], [[language]] and [[culture]]. Previously, a country consisted largely of whatever peoples lived on the land that was under the dominion of a particular ruler. Thus, as principalities and kingdoms grew through conquest and marriage, a ruler could wind up with peoples of many different ethnicities under his dominion. This also reflected the long history of migrations of different tribes and peoples throughout Europe. Much of [[European history]] in the latter half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century can be understood as efforts to realign national boundaries with this concept of "one people, one nation".

Much conflict would arise when one nation asserted territorial rights to land outside its borders on the basis of a common bond with the people living on that land. (Example: organized territorial rights by [[Russia]] for [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]'s breakaway province of South [[Ossetia]] to North Ossetia) Another source of conflict arose when a group of people who constituted a minority in one nation would seek to secede from the nation either to form an independent nation or join another nation with whom they felt stronger ties. Yet another source of conflict was the desire of some nations to expel people from territory within its borders on the ground that those people did not share a common bond with the majority of people living in that nation.{{specify|date=July 2014}}{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

It is useful to contrast the mass migrations and forced expulsion of [[ethnic Germans]] out of [[Eastern Europe]] with other massive [[population transfer]]s, such as [[population exchange between Greece and Turkey]], and population exchanges that occurred after the [[Partition of India]]. In all cases those expelled suffered greatly.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} [[Forced migration]]s took place after each of the two [[world wars]].

===East Asia===
In [[Japan]] and [[Korea]], as each country stated themselves as a single-nation country, ethnic minorities had to hide their national identity for centuries, and many resulted in assimilation, such as [[Ainu people|Ainu]] and [[Ryukyuan people]] in Japan, migrants of [[Goguryeo]], [[Balhae]] and [[Tungusic peoples]] in Korea.

[[Thailand]] sought to assimilate its many Chinese immigrants by only granting Thai citizenship if they renounced all loyalty to China, learned to speak Thai, changed their names, and sent their children to Thai schools.&lt;ref&gt;Baker, Chris and Pasuk Phongpaichit. ''A History of Thailand: Third Edition'', Cambridge UP, 2014, p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== North America ===
{{further information|Cultural assimilation of Native Americans|Mexicans in Omaha, Nebraska}}
In the United States and Canada, forced assimilation had been practiced against indigenous peoples through the [[Canadian Indian residential school system]] and [[American Indian boarding schools]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Little |first1=Becky |title=How Boarding Schools Tried to 'Kill the Indian' Through Assimilation |url=https://www.history.com/news/how-boarding-schools-tried-to-kill-the-indian-through-assimilation |website=History |access-date=11 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Carpenter |first1=Mary |title=Lost Generations |url=https://www.canadashistory.ca/explore/first-nations-inuit-metis/lost-generations |website=Canada's History |access-date=11 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same assimilation was also faced by French and Spanish speaking peoples populating the US and Canada, through language bans, violence, and extreme prejudice by anglophones into and throughout the 20th century.

In the United States, during World War I, the American government burned most German books, banned the use of German in public places and renamed many places that previously had German names with more English-sounding words; the forced assimilation was highly successful. Before that, the German American community at large had refused assimilation, and retained their German traditions, such as having beers on Sundays. [[Plautdietsch language#Speaker population and language maintenance|German]] also was the major language in many parts of the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://macaulay.cuny.edu/seminars/drabik09/articles/g/e/r/German_Immigrants_and_Assimilation_0e32.html|title = German Immigrants and Assimilation - the Peopling of New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;When German Immigrants Were America’s Undesirables. (2019). Retrieved 10 October 2020, from https://www.history.com/news/anti-german-sentiment-wwi&lt;/ref&gt;

=== China ===
{{further information|Human rights in China|Affirmative action in China|Sinicization}}
At least one million members of [[Islam in China|China's Muslim]] [[Uyghurs|Uyghur]] minority have been detained in [[Xinjiang re-education camps|mass detention camps]] in [[Xinjiang]], termed "[[Re-education through labor|reeducation camps]]", aimed at changing the political thinking of detainees, their identities, and their religious beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2018/09/19/china-has-chosen-cultural-genocide-in-xinjiang-for-now/|title=China Has Chosen Cultural Genocide in Xinjiang—For Now|last=Cronin-Furman|first=Kate|website=Foreign Policy|language=en|access-date=2018-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ukraine ===
In December 2017, [[Reuters]] reported that "[[Ukraine]]'s neighbors have a right to criticize a [[Education in Ukraine#2017 law "On Education"|new Ukrainian law]] banning schools from teaching in minority languages beyond primary school level, a leading European rights watchdog said".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Criticism of Ukraine's language law justified: rights body |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-ukraine-language/criticism-of-ukraines-language-law-justified-rights-body-idUSKBN1E227K |publisher=Reuters |date=December 8, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Latvia ===
Beginning in 2019, instruction in [[Russian language]] will be gradually discontinued in private colleges and [[private university|universities]] in [[Latvia]], as well as general instruction in Latvian public [[high school]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baltic-course.com/eng/education/?doc=141256|title=Latvian president promulgates bill banning teaching in Russian at private universities|date=April 7, 2018|publisher=The Baltic Course|access-date=August 11, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://eng.lsm.lv/article/society/education/government-okays-transition-to-latvian-as-sole-language-at-schools-in-2019.a265290/|title=Government okays transition to Latvian as sole language at schools in 2019|date=January 23, 2018|publisher=[[Public Broadcasting of Latvia]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Permanent Representative of the [[Russian Federation]] to the [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]] Alexander Lukashevich has denounced the reform as a "discriminatory policy with the goal of forced assimilation of [[Russians in Latvia|the Russian-speaking population]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.euractiv.com/section/languages-culture/news/in-latvia-school-language-reform-irks-russian-minority/|title=Latvia's school language reform irks Russian minority|date=June 25, 2018|publisher=[[EURACTIV]]|access-date=August 11, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious==
{{further information|Forced conversion|Jewish assimilation|Christianity in Pakistan}}
Assimilation also includes the (often forced) [[religious conversion|conversion]] or [[secularization]] of religious members of a minority group.

Throughout the Middle Ages and until the mid-19th century, most Jews in Europe were forced to live in small towns ([[shtetl]]s) and were restricted from entering universities or high-level professions.

During the [[Cambodian Genocide]], [[Cambodian genocide#Cham Muslims|Cham Muslims were persecuted]] by the Khmer Rouge regime, first through assimilation tactics, later through direct violence.

==National==
{{further information|Nationalism|Patriotism}}
When new [[immigrant]]s enter a country, there is a tension as they adapt to new people and surroundings to fit in, while holding on to their original culture. Here, studies show that native inhabitants often expect assimilation especially from negatively viewed immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Montreuil | first1 = Annie | last2 = Richard | first2 = Y. Bourhis Majority Acculturation Orientations Toward | year = 2001 | title = Valued" and "Devalued" Immigrants | journal = Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology | volume = 32 | issue = 6| pages = 698–719 | doi = 10.1177/0022022101032006004 | s2cid = 145706948 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Montreuil | first1 = Annie | last2 = Bourhis | first2 = Richard Y. | year = 2004 | title = Acculturation orientations of competing host communities toward valued and devalued immigrants | doi = 10.1016/j.ijintrel.2005.01.002 | journal = International Journal of Intercultural Relations | volume = 28 | issue = 6| pages = 507–532 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, [[Individualism|assimilation pressure]] seems to be particularly pronounced toward [[Immigrant generations#Second generation|second generation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi=10.1016/j.ijintrel.2013.10.007 | volume=39 | title="It's on Time That They Assimilate" – Differential acculturation expectations towards first and second generation immigrants | journal=International Journal of Intercultural Relations | pages=188–195| year=2014 | last1=Kunst | first1=Jonas R. | last2=Sam | first2=David L. | url=https://zenodo.org/record/812238 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Acculturation]]
* [[Cultural genocide]]
* [[Cultural imperialism]]
* [[Diaspora politics]]
* [[Ethnic interest group]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Hegemony]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[Linguistic discrimination]]
* [[Language shift]]
* [[Language death]]
* "[[More Irish than the Irish themselves]]"
* [[Stolen Generations]]
* ''[[Umvolkung]]''
*[[Arabization]]
*[[Russification]]
*[[Slavicisation]]
*[[Germanisation]]
*[[Kurdification]]
*[[Kurdification of Yazidis]]
*[[Turkification]]
*[[Romanization]]
*[[Sovietization]]
*[[Europeanisation]]
*[[Islamization]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Forced Assimilation}}
[[Category:Cultural assimilation]]
[[Category:Cultural genocide]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>