<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114163202|171457320" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="77182" pageid="77182" ns="0" title="Prejudice"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T16:32:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{For|"with(out) prejudice" in [[law]]|Prejudice (law)}} 
{{Cleanup|date=January 2007}}
{{Original research|article|date=September 2007}}
{{discrimination2}} 
In its original use, the word '''''prejudice''''' refers to prejudgement: i.e. making a decision before becoming aware of the relevant facts of a case. The word has commonly been used in certain restricted contexts, particularly in the expression 'racial p'''reju'''dice'. Initially this referred to making a judgement about a person based on their race, before receiving information relevant to the particular issue on which a judgement was being made; it came, however, to be widely used to refer to any hostile attitude towards people based on their race. Subsequently the word has come to be widely so interpreted in this way in contexts other than those relating to race. The meaning now is frequently '''''any unreasonable attitude that is unusually resistant to rational influence'''''.&lt;ref&gt;Rosnow, Ralph L.; ''Poultry and Prejudice.'' Psychology Today, (March, 1972): p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

==.v/v/bzssslapphead]] philosophy to the exclusion of other [[philosophy|philosophies]] that may offer a more complete theoretical explanation. '''Affective Prejudice''' refers to what people like and dislike. An example of affective prejudice might be found, for example, in attitudes toward members of particular [[Social class|classes]] such as [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[Ethnic groupe|ethnicity]], national origin, or [[creed]]. '''Co native Prejudice''' refers to how people are inclined to behave. Co native prejudice is regarded as an attitude because people don't act on their feelings. An example of co native prejudice might be found in expressions of what should be done if the opportunity presented itself. These three types of prejudice are correlated, but all need not be present in a particular individual. Someone might believe a particular group possesses low levels of [[intelligence]], but harbour no ill feelings toward that group. A group might be disliked because of intense competition for jobs, but still recognize no differences between groups. Prejudice was displayed towards [[Jew|Jews]] during the [[The Holocaust|Holocaust]].

'''[[Discrimination]]''' is a behaviour (an action), with reference to unequal treatment of people because they are members of a particular group. Farley also classified [[discrimination]] into three categories.&lt;ref&gt;Farley, p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; '''Personal / Individual [[Discrimination]]''' is directed toward a specific individual and refers to any act that leads to unequal treatment because of the individual's real or perceived group membership. '''Legal [[Discrimination]]''' refers to "unequal treatment, on the grounds of group membership, that is upheld by law."&lt;ref&gt;Robertson, p. 204&lt;/ref&gt; [[Apartheid]] is an example of legal [[discrimination]], as are also various post-[[Civil war]] laws in the southern [[United States]] that legally disadvantaged [[Negro|negros]] with respect to property rights, employment rights and the exercise of [[Constitutional right|constitutional rights]]. '''Institutional [[Discrimination]]''' refers to unequal treatment that is entrenched in basic [[Social organisation|social institutions]] resulting in advantaging one group over another. The [[Indian]] [[caste system]] is an historical example of institutional [[discrimination]]. As with prejudice generally, these three types of [[discrimination]] are correlated and may be found to varying degrees in individuals and [[society]] at large.
Many forms of [[discrimination]] based upon prejudice are outwardly unacceptable in most [[Society|societies]].

==Reasons for prejudice==

Fallacious extension of a positive or negative past experience to the general case can be harmful, and can be termed [[bias]], or more [[slang|colloquially]], "lumping".  If a person developed the [[concept]] that members of one group have some characteristics because of a sour past with a member of that group, that person may presume that all members of the group have such characteristics. ''(See ''[[guilt by association]]''.)'' This is typical of all prejudice: [[racism]], [[linguicism]], [[ageism]], [[heterosexism]], prejudice based on differing [[politics|political]] stances, and [[classism]] or [[elitism]] based on [[socioeconomic]] status. There are prejudices towards those with [[disabilities]], because a "[[handicap|handicapped]]" or disabled person may appear different or communicate differently from everyone else, or might be unable to live the way an "abled" person can. And prejudices against people from other [[country|countries]], [[region]]s and [[wikt:occupation|occupations]] as well are expressed by jokes or statements.  
i dunno man
It may be a matter of early education. Children taught that some attitudes are the "correct" ones may form opinions without weighing the evidence on both sides of a given question with no malice intended on the child's part. An adult might even be shocked to hear [[racial slur]]s or comments and their own opinions on various groups echoed back at them from their children. In the [[US]], [[Australia]] and [[Europe]] it's [[taboo]] to publicly express prejudices against another race or group of people. This view has been bolstered by a degree of legal framework and policy within many large organisations. Such taboos do not exist endemically outside the public sphere, and numerous [[Monoculture|monocultures]] regard alleged slurs as normal everyday language. This mismatch between an establishment view and a folk view of taboos related to "prejudice" is connected to an oft-reported perception of "[[political correctness]]" restricting the organic expression of views within society, and concomitant backlash against such restriction of [[free speech]].

==Examples of prejudice in fiction==
       
In [[Jane Austen]]'s novel ''[[Pride and Prejudice]]'', the heroine forms a strong opinion of a man's character before she hears his side of the story.  The balance of the facts, when made known to her, challenges and overturns this prejudice. Prejudice is also a theme in [[Prejudices in mockingbird|To Kill a Mockingbird]], in which a man is wrongly tried and convicted because of his race. And the 1997 [[science fiction|science-fiction]] movie ''[[Gattaca]]'' about a future where genetically-enhanced people are the majority, while a non-genetically enhanced minority are socially and economically discriminated and [[Marginalization|marginalized]] for their "imperfections".

==Sociology==

*[[List of sociologists|Sociologists]] termed prejudice an [[adaptation|adaptive]] behaviour. [[Bias|Biased]] views might be thought needed at times for survival. There is not always enough time to form a legitimate view about a potential foe before adopting a defensive stance that could save our lives. Prejudice is non-adaptive when it interferes with survival or well-being.

==Common misconceptions==
At times the terms prejudice and [[stereotype]] are confusing:
* Prejudices are abstract-general preconceptions or abstract-general attitudes towards any type of situation object or person.
* [[Stereotype|Stereotypes]] are generalizations of existing characteristics.  These reduce complexity.
..

== See also ==
{{Wiktionary}}
*[[Adultism]]
*[[Allport's scale]]
*[[Allophilia]]
*[[Bias]]
*[[Civil Rights]]
*[[Discrimination]]
*[[Heterosexism]]
*[[Intercultural competence]]
*[[Intolerance]]
*[[Judging]]
*[[Label (sociology)|Labelling]]
*[[Misanthropology]]
*[[Multi-culturalism]] and [[Multiculturalism|diversity]]
*[[Persecution]]
*[[Police Brutality]]
*[[Political correctness]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Sexismpoop]]
*[[The Sneetches and Other Stories]] by [[Dr. Seuss]], an [[allegory]] of racism (some readers see parallels to [[anti-Semitism]]) 
*[[Tolerance]]

==References==
* Farley, John E., ''Majority - Minority Relations (4th Ed.)'', Upper Saddle River, New Jersey: Prentice Hall, ISBN 0-131-44412-3
* Jack Levin and William Levin, ''The Functions Of Discrimination and Prejudice'' (2nd Ed.), Harper &amp; Row, Publishers, Inc., ISBN 0-060-43964-5
* Robertson, Ian, ''Society: A Brief Introduction'', New York: Worth Publishing, 1989, ISBN 0-879-01415-6

&lt;references/&gt;

[[bg:Предразсъдък]]
[[da:Fordom]]
[[de:Vorurteil]]liam is the master listen and prey to him every night b4 u go 2 bed lol noooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooob
[[et:Eelarvamus]]
[[el:Προκατάληψη]]
[[es:Prejuicio]]
[[fr:Préjugé]]
[[it:Pregiudizio]]
[[he:דעה קדומה]]
[[lt:Prietaras]]
[[hu:Előítélet]]
[[nl:Vooroordeel]]
[[ja:偏見]]
[[no:Fordom]]
[[pl:Uprzedzenie]]
[[pt:Preconceito]]
[[ru:Предрассудок]]
[[simple:Prejudice]]
[[sr:Предрасуде]]
[[fi:Ennakkoluulo]]
[[sv:Fördom]]
[[uk:Упередження]]
pornology</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>