<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121113235314|522908218" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="77182" pageid="77182" ns="0" title="Prejudice"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-16T03:28:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|a discrimination concept|legal procedure|Prejudice (legal procedure)}}
{{discrimination sidebar}}

The word '''prejudice''' (or '''[[wikt:foredeem|foredeeming]]''') is most often used to refer to preconceived, usually unfavorable, judgments toward people or a person because of [[gender]], [[social class]], [[Ageing|age]], [[disability]], [[religion]], [[sexual orientation|sexuality]], [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]]/[[ethnicity]], [[language]], [[nationality]] or other personal characteristics. It can also refer to unfounded beliefs&lt;ref&gt;[[William James]] wrote, "A great many people think they are thinking when they are merely rearranging their prejudices."[http://www.freemaninstitute.com/quotes.htm Quotable Quotes – Courtesy of The Freeman Institute]&lt;/ref&gt; and may include "any unreasonable attitude that is unusually resistant to rational influence."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rosnow |first1=Ralph L. |title=Poultry and Prejudice |journal=Psychologist Today |month=March |year=1972 |volume=5 |issue=10 |pages=53–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gordon Allport]] defined prejudice as a "feeling, favorable or unfavorable, toward a person or thing, prior to, or not based on, actual experience."{{citation needed|date=April 2012}}

==Historical approaches==
The first [[psychological research]] conducted on prejudice occurred in the 1920s. This research was done to attempt to prove [[white supremacy]]. One article from 1925 reviewing 73 studies on race concluded that the “studies take all together seem to indicate the mental superiority of the white race”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/h0075064 |title=A review of race psychology |year=1930 |last1=Garth |first1=T. R. |journal=Psychological Bulletin |volume=27 |issue=5 |pages=329–56}}&lt;/ref&gt; This research among others led many psychologists to view prejudice as a natural response to inferior races.

In the 1930s and 1940s, this perspective began to change due to the increasing concern about [[anti-Semitism]]. Theorists of this time viewed prejudice as pathological and looked for personality syndromes linked with racism. Theorist [[Theodor Adorno]] believed prejudice stemmed from an authoritarian personality. Adorno described authoritarians as “rigid thinkers who obeyed authority, saw the world as black and white, and enforced strict adherence to social rules and hierarchies”.&lt;ref name="Plous, S 2011"&gt;Plous, S. "The Psychology of Prejudice." Understanding Prejudice.org. Web. 07 Apr. 2011.{{vs|where's the URL?|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adorno believed people with authoritarian personalities were the most likely to be prejudiced against groups of lower status. 

In 1954, [[Gordon Allport]] linked prejudice and categorical thinking. Allport claims prejudice is in part a normal process for humans. According to him, "The human mind must think with the aid of categories… Once formed, categories are the basis for normal prejudgment. We cannot possibly avoid this process. Orderly living depends upon it."&lt;ref&gt;Allport, G. W. (1954). ''The nature of prejudice.'' Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley.{{pn|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the 1970s, research began to show that much of prejudice is based not on negative feelings towards other groups but favoritism towards one’s own groups. According to [[Marilyn Brewer]], prejudice "may develop not because outgroups are hated, but because positive emotions such as admiration, sympathy, and trust are reserved for the ingroup."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/0022-4537.00126 |title=The Psychology of Prejudice: Ingroup Love and Outgroup Hate? |year=1999 |last1=Brewer |first1=Marilynn B. |journal=Journal of Social Issues |volume=55 |issue=3 |pages=429–44}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1979, [[Thomas Pettigrew]] described the [[ultimate attribution error]] and its role in prejudice. The ultimate attribution error occurs when ingroup members "(1) attribute negative outgroup behavior to dispositional causes (more than they would for identical ingroup behavior), and (2) attribute positive outgroup behavior  to one or more of the following causes: (a) a fluke or exceptional case, (b) luck or special advantage, (c) high motivation and effort, and (d) situational factors."&lt;ref name="Plous, S 2011"/&gt;

==Contemporary theories and empirical findings==

[[Social psychology|Social psychologist]] [[Henri Tajfel]] and colleagues found that ingroup favouritism can occur even in groups with no prior social meaning. In the [[minimal group paradigm|minimal group]] experiments it was found that when voluntary study participants were assigned into groups based on something trivial such as a coin toss those participants exhibited [[In-group–out-group bias|in-group favouritism]], giving preferential treatment to in-group members.&lt;ref&gt;Tajfel, H. (1982). Social identity and intergroup relations. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.{{pn|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[out-group homogeneity]] effect is the perception that members of an out-group are more similar (homogenous) than members of the in-group. Social psychologists Quattrone and Jones conducted a study demonstrating this with students from the rival schools Princeton and Rutgers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.38.1.141 |title=The perception of variability within in-groups and out-groups: Implications for the law of small numbers |year=1980 |last1=Quattrone |first1=George A. |last2=Jones |first2=Edward E. |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=38 |pages=141–52}}&lt;/ref&gt; Students at each school were shown videos of other students from each school choosing a type of music to listen to for an auditory perception study. Then the participants were asked to guess what percentage of the videotaped students’ classmates would choose the same. Participants predicted a much greater similarity between out-group members (the rival school) than between members of their in-group

The justification-suppression model of prejudice was created by Christian Crandall and Amy Eshleman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.129.3.414 |title=A justification-suppression model of the expression and experience of prejudice |year=2003 |last1=Crandall |first1=Christian S. |last2=Eshleman |first2=Amy |journal=Psychological Bulletin |volume=129 |issue=3 |pages=414–46 |pmid=12784937}}&lt;/ref&gt; This model explains that people face a conflict between the desire to express prejudice and the desire to maintain a positive [[self-concept]]. This conflict causes people to search for justification for disliking an out-group, and to use that justification to avoid negative feelings ([[cognitive dissonance]]) about themselves when they act on their dislike of the out-group.

The [[realistic conflict theory]] states that competition between limited resources leads to increased negative prejudices and discrimination. This can be seen even when the resource is insignificant. In the Robber’s Cave experiment,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Muzafer |last1=Sherif |first2=O. J. |last2=Harvey |first3=B. Jack |last3=White |first4=William R. |last4=Hood |first5=Carolyn W. |last5=Sherif |year=1988 |title=The Robbers Cave Experiment: Intergroup Conflict and Cooperation |location=Middletown, Connecticut |publisher=Wesleyan University Press |isbn=978-0-8195-6194-7}}{{pn|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; negative prejudice and hostility was created between two summer camps after sports competitions for small prizes. The hostility was lessened after the two competing camps were forced to cooperate on tasks to achieve a common goal.

Another contemporary theory is Integrated Threat Theory (ITT) developed by Walter G Stephan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/j.1471-6402.2000.tb01022.x |title=Women's Attitudes Toward Men: an Integrated Threat Theory Approach |year=2000 |last1=Stephan |first1=Cookie White |last2=Stephan |first2=Walter C. |last3=Demitrakis |first3=Katherine M. |last4=Yamada |first4=Ann Marie |last5=Clason |first5=Dennis L. |journal=Psychology of Women Quarterly |volume=24 |pages=63–73}}&lt;/ref&gt; It draws from and builds upon several other psychological explanations of prejudice and ingroup/outgroup behaviour, such as Realistic Group Conflict Threat and [[symbolic racism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1207/s15327957pspr1004_4 |title=Intergroup Threat and Outgroup Attitudes: A Meta-Analytic Review |year=2006 |last1=Riek |first1=Blake M. |last2=Mania |first2=Eric W. |last3=Gaertner |first3=Samuel L. |journal=Personality and Social Psychology Review |volume=10 |issue=4 |pages=336–53 |pmid=17201592}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It also uses the Social Identity Theory perspective as the basis for its validity, that is, it assumes that individuals operate in a group-based context where group memberships form a part of individual identity. ITT  posits that outgroup prejudice and discrimination is caused when individuals perceive an outgroup to be threatening in some way. ITT defines four threats: 
* Realistic threats
* Symbolic threats
* Intergroup anxiety
* Negative stereotypes

''Realistic threats'' are tangible, such as competition for a natural resource or a threat to income.  ''Symbolic threats'' arise from a perceived difference in cultural values between groups or a perceived imbalance of power—for example, an ingroup perceiving an outgroup’s religion as incompatible with theirs. ''Intergroup anxiety'' is a feeling of uneasiness experienced in the presence of an outgroup or outgroup member, which constitutes a threat because interactions with other groups cause negative feelings (e.g., a threat to comfortable interactions). ''Negative stereotypes'' are similarly threats, in that individuals anticipate negative behaviour from outgroup members in line with the perceived stereotype, for example, that the outgroup is violent. Often these stereotypes are associated with emotions such as fear and anger. ITT differs from other threat theories by including intergroup anxiety and negative stereotypes as threat types.

Additionally, [[Social Dominance Theory]] states that society can be viewed as group-based hierarchies. In competition for scarce resources such as housing or employment, dominant groups create prejudiced "legitimizing myths" to provide moral and intellectual justification for their dominant position over other groups and validate their claim over the limited resources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.70.3.476 |title=Racism, conservatism, Affirmative Action, and intellectual sophistication: A matter of principled conservatism or group dominance? |year=1996 |last1=Sidanius |first1=Jim |last2=Pratto |first2=Felicia |last3=Bobo |first3=Lawrence |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=70 |issue=3 |pages=476–90}}&lt;/ref&gt; Legitimizing myths, such as discriminatory hiring practices or biased merit norms, work to maintain these prejudiced hierarchies.

Prejudice can be a central contributing factor to depression.&lt;ref name="Cox et al. (2012)"&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1177/1745691612455204 |title=Stereotypes, Prejudice, and Depression: The Integrated Perspective |year=2012 |last1=Cox |first1=William T. L. |last2=Abramson |first2=Lyn Y. |last3=Devine |first3=Patricia G. |last4=Hollon |first4=Steven D. |journal=Perspectives on Psychological Science |volume=7 |issue=5 |pages=427–49}}&lt;/ref&gt; This can occur in someone who is a prejudice victim, being the target of someone's else's prejudice, or when people have prejudice against themselves that causes their own depression.

==Controversies and prominent topics==
One can be prejudiced against, or have a preconceived notion about someone due to any characteristic they find to be unusual or undesirable. A few commonplace examples of prejudice are those based on someone’s race, gender, nationality, social status, sexual orientation or religious affiliation, and controversies may arise from any given topic.

===Sexism===
{{Main|Sexism}}
The term sexism is generally linked to negative female sentiments that derive from the belief that females are worth less or less capable than males.&lt;ref name="Dovidio"&gt;Dovidio, John, Peter Glick, and Laurie Rudman. On the Nature of Prejudice. Malden: Blackwell Publishing, 2005. 108. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; The discussion of such sentiments, and actual gender differences and stereotypes continue to be controversial topics. Throughout history, women have been thought of as being subordinate to men, often being ignored in areas like the academic arena or belittled altogether. Traditionally, men were thought of as being more capable than women, mentally and physically.&lt;ref name="Dovidio" /&gt; In the field of Social Psychology, prejudice studies like the “Who Likes Competent Women” study led the way for gender-based research on prejudice &lt;ref name="Dovidio" /&gt; This resulted in two broad themes or focuses in the field: the first being a focus on attitudes toward [[gender equality]], and the second focusing on people’s beliefs about men and women &lt;ref name="Dovidio" /&gt; Today studies based on sexism continue in the field of psychology as researchers try to understand how people’s thoughts, feelings, and behaviors influence and are influenced by others.

===Nationalism===
{{Main|Nationalism}}
Nationalism is a sentiment based on common cultural characteristics that binds a population and often produces a policy of national independence or separatism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/nationalism  World English Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; It suggests a “shared identity” amongst a nation's people that minimizes differences withing the group and emphasizes perceived boundaries between the group and non-members.&lt;ref name="Blackwell, Judith 2003 p31-2"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Blackwell |first1=Judith |first2=Murray |last2=Smith |first3=John |last3=Sorenson |title=Culture of Prejudice: Arguments in Critical Social Science |location=Toronto |publisher=Broadview Press |year=2003 |page=31–2}}&lt;/ref&gt; This leads to the assumption that members of the nation have more in common than they actually do, that they are “culturally unified,” even if injustices within the nation based on differences like status and race exist.&lt;ref name="Blackwell, Judith 2003 p31-2"/&gt; Nationalism, during times of conflict between one nation and another, is controversial since it may function as a buffer for criticism when it comes to the nation’s own problems since it makes the nation’s own hierarchies and internal conflicts appear to be natural.&lt;ref name="Blackwell, Judith 2003 p31-2"/&gt; It may also serve a way of rallying the people of the nation in support of a particular political goal.&lt;ref name="Blackwell, Judith 2003 p31-2"/&gt; Nationalism usually involves a push for conformity, obedience, and solidarity amongst the nation’s people and can result, not only in feelings of public responsibility, but also a narrow sense of community due to the exclusion of those who are considered outsiders.&lt;ref name="Blackwell, Judith 2003 p31-2"/&gt; Since the identity of nationalists is linked to their allegiance to the state, the presence of strangers who do not share this allegiance may result in hostility.&lt;ref name="Blackwell, Judith 2003 p31-2"/&gt;

===Classism===
{{Main|Classism}}
Classism is defined by the World English Dictionary as, “...a biased or discriminatory attitude on distinctions made between social or economic classes.”&lt;ref&gt;World English Dictionary, [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/classism] “Classism”]&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of separating people based on class is controversial in itself.  Some argue that [[economic inequality]] is an unavoidable aspect of society, so there will always be a ruling class.&lt;ref&gt;Blackwell, Judith, Murray Smith, and John Sorenson. Culture of Prejudice: Arguments in Critical Social Science. Toronto: Broadview Press, 2003. 145. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Some also argue that even within the most egalitarian societies in history, some form of ranking based on social status takes place. Therefore, one may believe the existence of social classes is a natural feature of society.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;Blackwell, Judith, Murray Smith, and John Sorenson. Culture of Prejudice: Arguments in Critical Social Science. Toronto: Broadview Press, 2003. 146. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Others argue the contrary. According to anthropological evidence, for the majority of the time the human species has been in existence, we have lived in a manner in which the land and resources were not privately owned.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; Also, when social ranking did occur, it was not antagonistic or hostile like the current class system.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; This evidence has been used to support the idea that the existence of a social class system is unnecessary. Overall, society has yet to come to a consensus over the necessity of the class system, nor has society been able to deal with the hostility and prejudice that occurs because of the class system.

===Sexual discrimination===
{{Main|Homophobia}}
One’s sexual orientation is a “predilection for homosexuality, heterosexuality, or bisexuality”.&lt;ref&gt;World English Dictionary, [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/sexual+orientation] “Sexual Orientation]&lt;/ref&gt; Like most minority groups, homosexuals and bisexuals are not immune to prejudice or stereotypes from the majority group. They may experience hatred from others because of their sexual preferences; a term for such intense hatred based upon one’s sexual orientation is [[homophobia]]. Due to what social psychologists call the vividness effect, a tendency to notice only certain distinctive characteristics, the majority population tends to draw conclusions like gays flaunt their sexuality.&lt;ref name="Anderson, Kristin 2010"&gt;Anderson, Kristin. “Benign Bigotry: The Psychology of Subtle Prejudice.” Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2010. 198. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Such images may be easily recalled to mind due to their vividness, making it harder appraise the entire situation.&lt;ref name="Anderson, Kristin 2010"/&gt; The majority population may not only think that homosexuals flaunt their sexuality or are “too gay,” but may also erroneously believe that homosexuals are easy to identify and label as being gay or lesbian when compared to others who are not homosexual.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Kristin. “Benign Bigotry: The Psychology of Subtle Prejudice.” Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2010. 200. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of heterosexual privilege seems to flourish in society. Research and questionnaires are formulated to fit the majority—heterosexuals.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Kristin. “Benign Bigotry: The Psychology of Subtle Prejudice.” Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2010. 204. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; This discussion of whether heterosexuals are the privileged group and whether homosexuals are a minimized group is controversial.

===Racism===
{{Main|Racism}}
Racism is defined as “the belief that races exist, that physical characteristics determine cultural traits, and that racial characteristics make some groups superior.&lt;ref name="Blackwell37"&gt;Blackwell, Judith, Murray Smith, and John Sorenson. Culture of Prejudice: Arguments in Critical Social Science. Toronto: Broadview Press, 2003. 37-38. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; By separating people into hierarchies based upon their race, it has been argued that unequal treatment among the different groups of people is just and fair due to their genetic differences.&lt;ref name="Blackwell37" /&gt; Racism can occur amongst any group that can be identified based upon physical features or even characteristics of their culture.&lt;ref name="Blackwell37" /&gt; Though people may be lumped together and called a specific race, everyone does not fit neatly into such categories, making it hard to define and describe a race accurately.&lt;ref name="Blackwell37" /&gt;

Scientific racism began to flourish in the eighteenth century and was greatly influenced by [[Charles Darwin]]’s evolutionary studies, as well as ideas taken from the writings of philosophers like [[Aristotle]]; for example, Aristotle believed in the concept of “natural slaves”.&lt;ref name="Blackwell37" /&gt; This concept focuses on the necessity of hierarchies and how some people are bound to be on the bottom of the pyramid. Though racism has been a prominent topic in history, there is still debate over whether race actually exists{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}}, making the discussion of race a controversial topic. Even though the concept of race is still being debated, the effects of racism are apparent. Racism and other forms of prejudice can affect a person’s behavior, thoughts and feelings, and social psychologists strive to study exactly that.

===Religious discrimination===
While various religions teach its members to be tolerant of those who are different and to have compassion, throughout history there have also been instances where religion has been used to promote hate.&lt;ref&gt;On the Nature of Prejudice. Malden: Blackwell Publishing, 2005. 413. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers have done various studies explore the relationship between religion and prejudice; thus far, they have received mixed results. A study done with US college students found that those who reported religion to be very influential in their lives seem to have a higher rate of prejudice than those who reported not being religious.&lt;ref name="Dovidio, John 2005"&gt;Dovidio, John, Peter Glick, and Laurie Rudman. On the Nature of Prejudice. Malden: Blackwell Publishing, 2005. 413. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Other studies found that religion has a positive affect on people as far as prejudice is concerned.&lt;ref name="Dovidio, John 2005"/&gt; This difference in results may be attributed to the differences in religious practices or religious interpretations amongst the individuals. Those who practice “institutionalized religion,” which focuses more on social and political aspects of religious events, are more likely to have an increase in prejudice.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;Dovidio, John, Peter Glick, and Laurie Rudman. On the Nature of Prejudice. Malden: Blackwell Publishing, 2005. 414. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Those who practice “interiorized religion,” in which believers devote themselves to their beliefs, are most likely to have a decrease in prejudice.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt;

===Linguistic discrimination===

{{Main|Linguistic discrimination}}

Individuals or groups may be treated unfairly treatment based solely on their use of language. This use of language may include the individual's native language or other characteristics of the person's speech, such as an accent, the size of vocabulary (whether the person uses complex and varied words), and syntax. It may also involve a person's ability or inability to use one language instead of another.
In the mid-1980s, [[linguistics|Linguist]] Tove Skutnabb-Kangas, captured this idea of discrimination based on language as the concept of linguicism. Kangas defined linguicism as the ideologies and structures used to, "...legitimate, effectuate, and reproduce unequal division of power and resources (both material and non-material) between groups which are defined on the basis of language."&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Skutnabb-Kangas, Tove, and Phillipson, Robert, "'Mother Tongue': The Theoretical and Sociopolitical Construction of a Concept." In Ammon, Ulrich (ed.) (1989). ''Status and Function of Languages and Language Varieties'', p. 455. Berlin, New York: Walter de Gruyter &amp; Co. ISBN 3-11-011299-X.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Multiculturalism==
Humans have an evolved propensity to think categorically about social groups, manifested in cognitive processes with broad implications for public and political endorsement of multicultural policy, according to Crisp and Meleady.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1126/science.1219009 |title=Adapting to a Multicultural Future |year=2012 |last1=Crisp |first1=Richard J. |last2=Meleady |first2=Rose |journal=Science |volume=336 |issue=6083 |pages=853–5 |pmid=22605761}}&lt;/ref&gt; They postulated a cognitive-evolutionary account of human adaptation to social diversity that explains general resistance to multiculturalism, and offer a reorienting call for scholars and policy-makers who seek intervention-based solutions to the problem of prejudice.

==Reducing prejudice==
Academics Thomas Pettigrew and Linda Tropp conducted a [[meta-analysis]] of 515 studies involving a quarter of a million participants in 38 nations to examine how intergroup contact reduces prejudice. They found that three [[Mediation (statistics)|mediators]] are of particular importance: Intergroup contact reduces prejudice by (1) enhancing knowledge about the [[Ingroups and outgroups|outgroup]], (2) reducing anxiety about intergroup contact, and (3) increasing [[empathy]] and perspective taking. While all three of these mediators had mediational effects, the mediational value of increased knowledge was less strong than anxiety reduction and empathy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Pettigrew |first1= Thomas F. |last2= Tropp |first2= Linda R. |year= 2008 |title= How does intergroup contact reduce prejudice? Meta-analytic tests of three mediators |journal= European Journal of Social Psychology |volume= 38 |issue= 6 |pages= 922–934 |publisher= |doi= 10.1002/ejsp.504 |url= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Ambivalent prejudice]]
*[[Benevolent prejudice]]
*[[Symbolic prejudice]]
*[[Hostile prejudice]]
*[[Idée fixe (psychology)]]
*[[In-group–out-group bias]]
*[[Multiculturalism]]
*[[Stigma management]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Adorno, Th. W., Frenkel-Brunswik, E., Levinson, D. J. and Sanford, R. N. (1950). ''The authoritatian personality''. New York: Harper.
*Dorschel, A., ''Rethinking prejudice''. Aldershot, Hampshire – Burlington, Vermont – Singapore – Sydney: Ashgate, 2000 (New Critical Thinking in Philosophy, ed. Ernest Sosa, Alan H. Goldman, Alan Musgrave et alii) ISBN 0-7546-1387-9
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1348/000712601162059 |title=Social cognition: Categorical person perception |year=2001 |last1=MacRae |first1=C. Neil |last2=Bodenhausen |first2=Galen V. |journal=British Journal of Psychology |volume=92 |pages=239–55}}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.75.3.589 |title=Stereotype efficiency reconsidered: Encoding flexibility under cognitive load |year=1998 |last1=Sherman |first1=Jeffrey W. |last2=Lee |first2=Angela Y. |last3=Bessenoff |first3=Gayle R. |last4=Frost |first4=Leigh A. |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=75 |issue=3 |pages=589–606 |pmid=9781404}}
*{{cite book |first1=Donald R. |last1=Kinder |first2=Lynn M. |last2=Sanders |year=1997 |chapter=Subtle Prejudice for Modern Times |chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=QluVfkhpKpsC&amp;pg=PA92 |pages=92–160 |title=Divided by Color: Racial Politics and Democratic Ideals |series=American Politics and Political Economy |location=Chicago |publisher=University of Chicago Press |isbn=978-0-226-43574-9}}

== External links ==
{{wiktionary|prejudice|prejudgment}}

{{abuse}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Prejudices| ]]

[[ar:تحامل]]
[[bg:Предразсъдък]]
[[ca:Prejudici]]
[[cs:Předsudek]]
[[co:Preghjudiziu]]
[[cy:Rhagfarn]]
[[da:Fordom]]
[[de:Vorurteil]]
[[et:Eelarvamus]]
[[el:Προκατάληψη]]
[[es:Prejuicio]]
[[eo:Antaŭjuĝo]]
[[eu:Aurreiritzi]]
[[fa:تعصب]]
[[fr:Préjugé]]
[[hr:Predrasuda]]
[[id:Prasangka]]
[[is:Fordómur]]
[[it:Pregiudizio]]
[[he:דעה קדומה]]
[[ky:Көмүскө эс]]
[[la:Praeiudicium]]
[[lv:Aizspriedums]]
[[lt:Išankstinis nusistatymas]]
[[hu:Előítélet]]
[[nl:Vooroordeel]]
[[ja:偏見]]
[[no:Fordom]]
[[pl:Uprzedzenie]]
[[pt:Preconceito]]
[[ro:Prejudecată]]
[[ru:Предрассудок]]
[[simple:Prejudice]]
[[sl:Predsodek]]
[[sr:Предрасуде]]
[[fi:Ennakkoluulo]]
[[sv:Fördom]]
[[tl:Prehuwisyo]]
[[ta:முன்முடிவு]]
[[th:อคติ]]
[[tr:Ön yargı]]
[[uk:Упередження]]
[[vec:Pregiudisio]]
[[zh:偏見]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>