<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020828135405|179534" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="77182" pageid="77182" ns="0" title="Prejudice"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-08-28T13:59:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Prejudice''' is, as the name implies, the process of "pre-judging" something.  In general, it implies coming to a judgement on the subject before learning where the preponderance of the evidence actually lies.  

Thus, for example, in [[Jane Austen]]'s novel ''[[Pride and Prejudice]]'', the heroine forms a strong opinion of a man's character before she has the chance to hear his side of the story.  When the balance of the facts are finally made known to her, they challenge and ultimately overturn this prejudice.

Sometimes this is a matter of fallaciously extending one's own experience to the general case. In other cases, it may be a matter of early education; those taught that certain attitudes are the "correct" ones may form opinions without weighing the evidence on both sides of a given question.

When applied to social groups, prejudice generally refers to existing biases toward the members of such groups, often based on [[social stereotype]]s.  For example, a person who has had a series of bad relationships with those of the opposite sex may develop a prejudice against that sex, and thus assume that the factors souring the relationships are always present in members of that sex, and adopt the set of prejudices known as [[sexism]].   Or, if a person has grown up with the concept that members of group "X" have certain characteristics, they may apply this prejudice by assuming that all members of the group fit that stereotype, as in [[racism]] or [[homophobia]].</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>