<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061103221855|85556502" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56101" pageid="56101" ns="0" title="Ethnic conflict"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-03T22:27:42Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">An '''ethnic war''' is a war between [[ethnic group]]s often as a result of [[ethnic nationalism]].  They are of interest because of the apparent prevalence in the aftermath of the [[Cold War]] and because they frequently result in [[war crime]]s such as [[genocide]].

Two controversial questions about ethnic wars is whether they have become more or less prevalent in the post-Cold War period and whether they are really about ethnicity at all. Actual research shows that the fall of [[Communism]] and the increase in the number of democratic states were accompanied by a sudden and dramatic decline in total warfare, interstate wars, [[ethnic]] wars, [[revolutionary]] wars, and the number of [[refugees]] and [[displaced person]]s [http://members.aol.com/CSPmgm/conflict.htm].  

The post-Cold War period has seen ethnically-informed [[secessionist movements]], predominantly within the former communist states such as the [[Croats]], [[Serbs]], [[Bosniak]]s and [[Albanians]] in [[Yugoslavia]], [[Transnistria]] in [[Moldova]], [[Armenians]] in [[Azerbaijan]], [[Abkhaz people|Abkhaz]] in [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] and the [[Chechens]] in the [[Soviet Union]] (see O'Leary, Lustick, and Callaghy source below). 

There are a number of political scientists who refer to the concept of ethnic wars as a myth because they argue that the root causes of ethnic conflict do not involve ethnicity but rather institutional, political, and economic factors.  These political scientists argue that the concept of ethnic war is misleading because it leads to the conclusion that certain groups are doomed to fight each other when in fact the wars between them are the result of political decisions. Opposing groups may substitute ethnicity for the underlying factors to simplify identification of friend and foe.

A classic example of the reformulation of economic differences as ethnic differences is found in [[Rwanda]].  In a 1930s census, all people owning ten or more head of cattle were classified as Tutsi; everyone else was classified as Hutu.

==See also==
* [[Identity politics]]

==Further reading==

===Books===
* ''Ethnic Groups in Conflict'' by [[Donald L. Horowitz]], ISBN 0-520-22706-9
* [http://www.paradisepoisoned.com ''Paradise Poisoned: Learning About Conflict, Development and Terrorism from Sri Lanka's Civil Wars''] by [[John Richardson (professor and author)|John Richardson]], ISBN 955-580-094-4.
* ''Right-Sizing the State'' by [[Brendan O'Leary]], [[Ian S. Lustick]] and [[Thomas Callaghy]], ISBN 0-19-924490-1
* Monica Duffy Toft, ''The Geography of Ethnic Violence: Identity, Interests, and the Indivisibility of Territory'' (Princeton NJ: Princeton University Press, 2003). ISBN 0-691-12383-7.

===Journals===
* ''Ethnopolitics'' (http://www.tandf.co.uk/journals/titles/17449057.asp)

==External links==
* ''Ethnopolitics'' (http://www.ethnopolitics.org)
* ''European Centre for Minority Issues'' (http://www.ecmi.de)
* ''Genocide of Tamils in Sri Lanka'' (http://www.genocide.org.uk)

[[Category:Wars by type]]
[[Category:Ethnicity]]

[[de:Stammeskrieg]]
[[ja:民族紛争]]
[[pl:konflikt etniczny]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>