<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20130919021622|573583994" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56101" pageid="56101" ns="0" title="Ethnic conflict"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-10-06T06:52:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{see|ethnic violence|ethnic hatred|race war}}
[[File:Evstafiev-chechnya-prayer3.jpg|thumb|A [[Chechen people|Chechen]] man praying during the [[Battle of Grozny (1994–95)|battle of Grozny]] in 1995 (photograph by [[Mikhail Evstafiev]])]]
[[File:Rwandan refugee camp in east Zaire.jpg|thumb|right|A [[refugee camp]] for displaced [[Tutsi]] in [[Zaire]] following the [[Rwandan Genocide]] of 1994.]]

An '''ethnic conflict''' or '''ethnic war''' is an armed conflict between [[ethnic group]]s.
It contrasts with [[civil war]] on one hand (where a single nation or ethnic group is fighting among itself) and regular [[warfare]] on the other, where two or more sovereign states (which may or may not be [[nation state]]s) are in conflict.

Examples of ethnic wars since the 1990s were typically caused by [[secessionist]] movements leading to the breakup of [[multi-ethnic state]]s along ethnic lines: the [[Yugoslav Wars]], the [[First Chechen War]], the [[Nagorno-Karabakh War]], the [[Rwandan Civil War]] and the [[War in Darfur]], among others

Academic explanations of ethnic conflict generally fall into one of three schools of thought: [[primordialism|primordialist]], [[instrumentalism|instrumentalist]] or [[social constructivism|constructivist]]. Intellectual debate has also focused around the issue of whether ethnic conflict has become more prevalent since the end of the [[Cold War]], and on devising ways of managing conflicts, through instruments such as [[consociationalism]] and [[Federalism|federalisation]].

==Theories of ethnic conflict==
The causes of ethnic conflict are debated by [[political scientists]] and [[sociologists]] who generally fall into one of three schools of thought: primordialist, instrumentalist, and constructivist. More recent{{year needed|date=August 2013}}{{who|date=August 2013}} scholarship draws on all three schools.

===Primordialist accounts===
Proponents of primordialist accounts of ethnic conflict argue that “[e]thnic groups and nationalities exist because there are traditions of belief and action towards primordial objects such as biological features and especially territorial location”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Steven |last=Grosby |year=1994 |title=The verdict of history: The inexpungeable tie of primordiality&amp;nbsp;– a response to Eller and Coughlan |journal=[[Ethnic and Racial Studies]] |volume=17 |issue=1 |pages=164–171 [p. 168] |doi=10.1080/01419870.1994.9993817 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The primordialist account relies on a concept of kinship between members of an ethnic group. [[Donald L. Horowitz]] argues that this kinship “makes it possible for ethnic groups to think in terms of family resemblances”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Donald L. |last=Horowitz |year=1985 |title=Ethnic Groups in Conflict |location=Berkeley, CA |publisher=University of California Press |page=57 |isbn=0520053850 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are a number of political scientists who refer to the concept of ethnic wars as a myth because they argue that the root causes of ethnic conflict do not involve ethnicity but rather institutional, political, and economic factors.  These political scientists argue that the concept of ethnic war is misleading because it leads to an [[essentialism|essentialist]] conclusion that certain groups are doomed to fight each other when in fact the wars between them are the result of political decisions. Opposing groups may substitute ethnicity for the underlying factors to simplify identification of friend and foe.

===Instrumentalist accounts===
[[Anthony D. Smith|Anthony Smith]] notes that the instrumentalist account “came to prominence in the 1960s and 1970s in the United States, in the debate about (white) ethnic persistence in what was supposed to have been an effective melting pot”.&lt;ref name="Smith"&gt;{{cite journal |first=Anthony |last=Smith |year=2001 |title=Nationalism: Theory, Ideology, History |location=Cambridge |publisher=Polity |pages=54–55 |isbn=0745626580 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This new theory sought to explain such persistence as the result of the actions of community leaders, “who used their cultural groups as sites of mass mobilization and as constituencies in their competition for power and resources, because they found them more effective than social classes”.&lt;ref name="Smith"/&gt; In this account of ethnic identification, “[e]thnicity and race are viewed as instrumental identities, organized as means to particular ends”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Stephen |last=Cornell |first2=Douglas |last2=Hartmann |year=1998 |title=Ethnicity and Race: Making Identities in a Changing World |location=Thousand Oaks, CA |publisher=Pine Forge |page=59 |isbn=0761985018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Whether ethnicity is a fixed perception is not crucial in the instrumentalist accounts. Moreover, the scholars of this school do generally not oppose neither that ethnic difference is a part of many conflicts nor that a lot of belligerent human beings believe that they are fighting over such difference. Instrumentalists simply claim that ethnic difference is not sufficient to explain conflicts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Schlichting |first=Ursel |year=1997 |chapter=Conflict Between Different Nationalities: Chances for and Limits to Their Settlement |editor1-first=Andreas |editor1-last=Klinke |editor2-first=Ortwin |editor2-last=Renn |editor3-link=Jean Paul Lehners |editor3-first=Jean Paul |editor3-last=Lehners |title=Ethnic Conflicts and Civil Society |location=Aldershot |publisher=Ashgate |year=1997 |isbn=1840144556 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://www.berghof-handbook.net/uploads/download/smith_handbook.pdf |last=Smith |first=Dan |year=2003 |chapter=Trends and Causes of Armed Conflicts |editor1-first=Alexander |editor1-last=Austin |editor2-first=Martina |editor2-last=Fischer |editor3-first=Norbert |editor3-last=Ropers |title=Berghof Handbook for Conflict Transformation |location=Berlin |publisher=Berghof Research Centre for Constructive Conflict Management |isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Constructivist accounts===
Formalization of the theory of constructivism is generally attributed to [[Jean Piaget]], who articulated mechanisms by which knowledge is internalized by learners. He suggested that through processes of ''accommodation'' and ''assimilation'', individuals construct new knowledge from their experiences. When individuals assimilate, they incorporate the new experience into an already existing framework without changing that framework. This may occur when individuals' experiences are aligned with their internal representations of the world, but may also occur as a failure to change a faulty understanding; for example, they may not notice events, may misunderstand input from others, or may decide that an event is a fluke and is therefore unimportant as information about the world. In contrast, when individuals' experiences contradict their internal representations, they may change their perceptions of the experiences to fit their internal representations. According to the theory, accommodation is the process of reframing one's mental representation of the external world to fit new experiences. Accommodation can be understood as the mechanism by which failure leads to learning: when we act on the expectation that the world operates in one way and it violates our expectations, we often fail, but by accommodating this new experience and reframing our model of the way the world works, we learn from the experience of failure, or others' failure.

It is important to note that constructivism is not a particular [[pedagogy]]. In fact, constructivism is a theory describing how learning happens, regardless of whether learners are using their experiences to understand a lecture or following the instructions for building a model airplane. In both cases, the theory of constructivism suggests that learners construct knowledge out of their experiences. However, Constructivism is often associated with pedagogic approaches that promote [[active learning]], or learning.

A third, constructivist, set of accounts stress the importance of the socially constructed nature of ethnic groups, drawing on [[Benedict Anderson]]'s concept of the [[imagined community]]. Proponents of this account point to [[Rwanda]] as an example since the [[Tutsi]]/[[Hutu]] distinction was codified by the [[Belgian colonial empire|Belgian colonial power]] in the 1930s on the basis of cattle ownership, physical measurements and church records. Identity cards were issued on this basis, and these documents played a key role in the [[Rwandan genocide|genocide]] of 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Mahmood |last=Mamdani |year=2001 |title=When Victims Become Killers: Colonialism, Nativism, and the Genocide in Rwanda |location=Princeton, NJ |publisher=Princeton University Press |isbn=0691058210 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Scholars of ethnic conflict and [[civil war]]s have introduced theories that draw insights from all three traditional schools of thought. In ''The Geography of Ethnic Violence'', for example, Monica Duffy Toft shows how ethnic group settlement patterns, socially constructed identities, charismatic leaders, issue indivisibility, and state concern with precedent setting can lead rational actors to escalate a dispute to violence, even when doing so is likely to leave contending groups much worse off.&lt;ref name="Toft"&gt;{{cite book |first=Monica Duffy |last=Toft |year=2003 |title=The Geography of Ethnic Violence: Identity, Interests, and the Indivisibility of Territory |location=Princeton, NJ |publisher=Princeton University Press |isbn=0691113548 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Such research addresses empirical puzzles that are difficult to explain using primordialist, instrumentalist, or constructivist approaches alone.

==Ethnic conflict in the post–Cold War world==
The term "ethnicity" as it is used today arose in the mid 20th century, replacing the terminology of "races" or "nations" used for the concept in the 19th century. Regular [[warfare]] was formerly conceived as conflicts between [[nation]]s, and only with the rise of [[multiethnic society|multi-ethnic societies]] and the shift to [[asymmetric warfare]] did the concept of "ethnic conflict" arise as separate from generic "war".
This has been the case especially since the  [[Dissolution of the Soviet Union|collapse of the Soviet Union]] and [[Breakup of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] in the 1990s, both of which were followed by ethnic conflicts that escalated to violence and civil war.

The end of the Cold War thus sparked interest in two important questions about ethnic conflict: was ethnic conflict on the rise; and given that some ethnic conflicts had escalated into serious violence, what, if anything, could scholars of large-scale violence (security studies, strategic studies, interstate politics) offer by way of explanation?

One of the most debated issues relating to ethnic conflict is whether it has become more or less prevalent in the post–Cold War period. At the end of the Cold War, academics including [[Samuel P. Huntington]] and [[Robert D. Kaplan]] predicted a proliferation of conflicts fuelled by [[Clash of Civilizations|civilisational clashes]], [[tribalism]], [[Natural resource|resource]] [[scarcity]] and [[overpopulation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Samuel P. |last=Huntington |year=1993 |url=http://www.foreignaffairs.org/19930601faessay5188/samuel-p-huntington/the-clash-of-civilizations.html |title=The clash of civilizations? |journal=[[Foreign Affairs]] |volume=72 |issue=3 |pages=22–49 |doi= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Robert D. |last=Kaplan |year=1994 |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/ideastour/archive/kaplan.mhtml |title=The coming anarchy |journal=[[The Atlantic Monthly]] |volume=273 |issue=2 |pages=44–76 |doi= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The post–Cold War period has witnessed a number of ethnically-informed [[secessionist movements]], predominantly within the former communist states. Conflicts have involved secessionist movements in the [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|former Yugoslavia]], [[Transnistria]] in [[Moldova]], [[Armenians]] in [[Azerbaijan]], [[Abkhaz people|Abkhaz]] and [[Ossetians]] in [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]].

&lt;!-- Unsourced image removed: [[File:Omarska.jpg|thumb|right|Starved detainees at the [[Trnopolje camp]] in [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia]], filmed by [[ITN]]]] --&gt;
However, some theorists contend that this does not represent a rise in the incidence of ethnic conflict, since many of the [[proxy wars]] fought during the Cold War were in fact ethnic conflicts masked as hot spots of the Cold War. Research shows that the fall of [[Communism]] and the increase in the number of capitalist states were accompanied by a decline in total warfare, interstate wars, [[ethnic]] wars, [[revolutionary]] wars, and the number of [[refugees]] and [[displaced person]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Peter |last=Wallensteen |first2=Margareta |last2=Sollenberg |year=1995 |doi=10.1177/0022343395032003007 |title=After the Cold War: Emerging patterns of armed conflict 1989–94 |journal=Journal of Peace Research |volume=32 |issue=3 |pages=345–360 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Lotta |last=Harbom |first2=Peter |last2=Wallensteen |year=2005 |url=http://info.uu.se/press.nsf/166B1EC86A3FAF93C125706D0037D2E3/$File/JPRarticle.pdf |title=Armed conflict and its international dimensions, 1946–2004 |journal=Journal of Peace Research |volume=42 |issue=5 |pages=623–635 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://members.aol.com/CSPmgm/conflict.htm |title=Measuring systemic peace |publisher=Center for Systemic Peace |date=30 October 2006 |accessdate=18 February 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, some scholars have questioned whether the concept of ethnic conflict is useful at all.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Bruce |last=Gilley |year=2004 |doi=10.1080/0143659042000256959 |title=Against the concept of ethnic conflict |journal=Third World Quarterly |volume=25 |issue=6 |pages=1155–1166 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Others have attempted to test the clash of civilisations thesis, finding it to be difficult to operationalise and that civilisational conflicts have not risen in intensity in relation to other ethnic conflicts since the end of the Cold War.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Jonathan |last=Fox |year=2002 |doi=10.1017/S0007123402000170 |title=Ethnic minorities and the Clash of Civilizations: A quantitative analysis of Huntington's thesis |journal=British Journal of Political Science |volume=32 |issue=3 |pages=415–434 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Giacomo |last=Chiozza |year=2002 |jstor=1555255 |title=Is there a Clash of Civilizations? Evidence from patterns of international conflict involvement, 1946–97 |journal=Journal of Peace Research |volume=39 |issue=6 |pages=711–734 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the question of whether scholars deeply invested in theories of interstate violence could adapt their theories to explain or predict large-scale ethnic violence, a key issue proved to be whether ethnic groups could be considered "rational" actors.&lt;ref name="Kalyvas"&gt;{{cite book |first=Stathis N. |last=Kalyvas |year=2006 |title=The Logic of Violence in Civil War |location=New York |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=0521854091 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the end of the Cold War, the consensus among students of large-scale violence was that ethnic groups should be considered irrational actors, or semi-rational at best. If true, general explanations of ethnic violence would be impossible. In the years since, however, scholarly consensus has shifted to consider that ethnic groups may in fact be counted as rational actors, and the puzzle of their apparently irrational actions (for example, fighting over territory of little or no intrinsic worth) must therefore be explained some other way.&lt;ref name="Toft"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Kalyvas"/&gt; As a result, the possibility of a general explanation of ethnic violence has grown, and collaboration between comparativist and international relations subfields has resulted in increasingly useful theories of ethnic conflict.

The book ''[[World on Fire]]'' by [[Amy Chua]] argues that democratization may give political power to an ethnic majority that is poor compared to an ethnic minority that more economically successful. This which may cause conflict, persecution, and even genocide of the minority.

The war between the Sinhalese and Tamils in Sri Lanka is one of the prominent ethnic war that had happened after 1950's.

==Ethnic conflict regulation==
A number of scholars have attempted to synthesize the methods available for the [[conflict resolution|resolution]], [[conflict management|management]] or [[conflict transformation|transformation]] their ethnic conflict. [[John Coakley]], for example, has developed a [[wiktionary:Typology|typology]] of the methods of conflict resolution that have been employed by states, which he lists as: [[indigenization]], accommodation, [[Cultural assimilation|assimilation]], [[acculturation]], [[population transfer]], boundary alteration, [[genocide]] and ethnic suicide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=John |last=Coakley |year=1992 |doi=10.1177/019251219201300401 |title=The resolution of ethnic conflict: Towards a typology |journal=[[International Political Science Review]] |volume=13 |issue=4 |pages=343–358 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Greg Meyjes suggests that the degree to which ethnic tensions stem from inter-group disparity, dominance, discrimination, and repression has been critically unaccounted -- and proposes a [[cultural rights]] approach to understanding and managing ethnic conflicts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Meyjes |first=Gregory Paul P. |year=2012 |chapter=Multi-Ethnic Conflicts in U.S. Military Theatres Overseas: Intercultural Imperatives |editor1-first=Volker |editor1-last=Franke |editor2-first=Robert H. |editor2-last=Dorff |title=Conflict Management and ‘Whole of Government’: Useful Tools for U.S. National Security Strategy |location=Carlisle, PA |publisher=Strategic Studies Institute, U.S. Army War College |pages=381–438 |isbn=1584875240 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper |last=Meyjes |first=Gregory Paul P. |year=2007 |title='Plan "C" is for Culture: out of Iraq&amp;nbsp;– Opportunity' |work=Landpower Essay 07-4 |month=May |year=2007 |location=Arlington, VA |publisher=Association of the United States Army }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John McGarry]] and [[Brendan O'Leary]] have developed a [[Taxonomy (general)|taxonomy]] of eight macro-political ethnic conflict regulation methods, which they note are often employed by states in combination with each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=John |last=McGarry |first2=Brendan |last2=O’Leary |year=1993 |chapter=Introduction: The macro-political regulation of ethnic conflict |title=The Politics of Ethnic Conflict Regulation: Case Studies of Protracted Ethnic Conflicts |location=London |publisher=Routledge |pages=1–40 |isbn=041507522X }}&lt;/ref&gt; They include a number of methods that they note is clearly morally unacceptable.

*Methods for eliminating differences:
**[[Genocide]]
**Forced [[Population transfer|mass-population transfers]]
**[[Partition (politics)|Partition]] and/or [[separatism|secession]] ([[self-determination]])
**[[Racial integration|Integration]] and/or [[Cultural assimilation|assimilation]]

*Methods for managing differences:
**[[Hegemony|Hegemonic control]]
**[[Arbitration]] ([[Humanitarian intervention|third-party intervention]])
**[[Canton (country subdivision)|Cantonisation]] and/or [[Federalism|federalisation]]
**[[Consociationalism]] or power-sharing

==See also==
* [[Ethnic nepotism]]
* [[Ethnic hatred]]
* [[Ethnic violence]]
* [[Ethnic nationalism]]
* [[Diaspora politics]]
* [[Genocide]]
* [[List of ongoing military conflicts]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ecmi.de European Centre for Minority Issues]
* [http://www.incore.ulst.ac.uk/ INCORE International Conflict Research]
* [[Political Studies Association]] [http://www.ethnopolitics.org Specialist Group on Ethnopolitics]
* [http://www.minorityrights.org Minority Rights Group International]

{{Ethnicity}}
[[Category:Wars by type]]

&lt;!--for some reason we have a category called "Ethnic conflict" and another called"Ethnic conflicts". The reason is presumably the polysemy of the term "conflict", the former is indending the wider sense of 'conflict' as any clash of interests, the second is using it in the sense of "armed, open conflict". This should be fixed, the categories should be named more clearly --&gt;
[[Category:Ethnic conflict|*]]
[[Category:Ethnic conflicts|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>