<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20060908155603|74543150" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="374004" pageid="374004" ns="0" title="Diversity training"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-25T14:36:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Diversity training''' is training provided by an organization, usually with the stated purpose of treating [[diversity]] as an opportunity and promoting the ability of students and workers from a great variety of backgrounds to cooperate productively and make as great a contribution as possible to organizational goals. 

Although it is a big business with a profound effect on business, government and education, observers characterize diversity training in very different ways. Its proponents consider it morally right, because it [[respect diversity|respects diversity]]. They also view it as economically sound, because it enables organizations to draw on multiplicities of talents and strengths. Its opponents consider it an oppressive [[ideology|ideological]] [[re-education]] tactic, that actually injures the ability of organizations to attain their goals. It has been suggested that diversity training reinforces differences between individuals instead of concentrating on their commonalities, thus helping to further racialize the workplace and creating situations where people "tiptoe" around issues such as how to relate to people of different cultures as opposed to people learning to communicate with and truly understand each other.

==Examples of corporate diversity groups==
*[http://www.intelglbt.org/ Intel's Gay &amp; Lesbian Group]
*[http://www.ibcn.org/ Intel's Christian Group]
*[http://www.christathp.com/ HP's Christian Employee Group]
*[http://www.btkaleidoscope.co.uk BT's Gay &amp; Lesbian Group]

==External links==
*[http://www.intel.com/jobs/diversity/index.htm Diversity at Intel]
*[http://www.hitechchristians.org/index.htm Hitech Christian Leadership Network]
*[http://www.coastal.com/diversity-training/diversity-training.html Coastal Training Technologies Corp.'s Diversity Training ]
*[http://www.tmcorp.com/channel.aspx?channel_id=tmcnews&amp;page_id=TN160 What is Diversity and Inclusion really about? By Joerg Schmitz]
*[http://www.diverse-ct.co.uk/index.htm Equality and Diversity Training Specialists (UK)]

[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>