<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20150927174331|683031611" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="374004" pageid="374004" ns="0" title="Diversity training"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-10-04T21:06:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Diversity training''' is a course of instruction aimed at increasing the participants' cultural awareness, knowledge, and skills in order to benefit an organization by protecting against [[civil rights]] violations, by increasing the inclusion of different [[identity group]]s, and by promoting better teamwork.
&lt;ref&gt;Vaughn, B. "[http://diversityofficermagazine.com/diversity-inclusion/the-history-of-diversity-training-its-pioneers/ The history of diversity training and its pioneers]", ''Strategic Diversity &amp; Inclusion Management,'' pp. 11-16, Spring 2007. DTUI.com Publications Division: San Francisco.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversial issues==
Diversity training has been a controversial issue, raising questions about moral considerations and counter-productivity.

Observers characterize diversity training in very different ways. Its proponents consider it morally right, because it respects diversity, recognizing the value and contributions of every human being. They also view it as economically sound, because it enables organizations to draw on multiplicities of talents and strengths.&lt;ref&gt;
Orlando Richard, "Diversity at the Top May Boost the Bottom Line," September, 2010.[http://www.utdallas.edu/news/2010/9/10-5431_Diversity-at-the-Top-May-Boost-the-Bottom-Line_article.html#sharer]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Hans Bader, its opponents consider it an oppressive, ideology reeducation tactic that actually reduces the ability of organizations to attain their goals. It has been suggested that diversity training reinforces differences between individuals instead of fostering their commonalities, thus helping to further racialize the workplace, creating situations where people "tiptoe" around issues such as how to relate to people of different cultures as opposed to people learning to communicate with and truly understand each other.&lt;ref&gt;Hans Bader: [http://www.openmarket.org/2007/12/26/diversity-training-backfires/ Diversity Training Backfires] OpenMarket.org. December 26, 2007. Accessed April 15, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; It may also, according to law professor Gail Heriot, amount to a "rather blatant form of racial and sexual harassment".&lt;ref&gt;Gail Heriot: [http://rightcoast.typepad.com/rightcoast/2007/12/white-guys-have.html White Guys Have No Rights. And They’d Better Shut Up If Think They Have (Part 1)] December 23, 2007. Accessed April 15, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

These opinions have been confirmed by the [[Tenth Circuit Court of Appeals]] which, in ''Fitzgerald v. Mountain States Tel &amp; Tel. Co.'' (1995), noted that "diversity training sessions generate conflict and emotion" and that "diversity training is perhaps a tyranny of virtue."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.leagle.com/decision/1995132568F3d1257_11129  ''Fitzgerald v. Mountain States Tel &amp; Tel. Co.'']&lt;/ref&gt;

In a paper published in the ''[[American Sociological Review]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | last=Alexandra Kalev, Frank Dobbin and Erin Kelley
  | title=[http://scholar.harvard.edu/files/dobbin/files/2006_asr_kalev.pdf Best Practices or Best Guesses? Assessing the Efficacy of Corporate Affirmative Action and Diversity Policies]
  | newspaper=[[American Sociological Review]]
  | volume=71
  | pages=589–617
  | year=2006}}
&lt;/ref&gt; the authors concluded that efforts to mitigate managerial [[bias]] ultimately fail to achieve the organization's aim of increasing diversity in the management and leadership ranks. In contrast, programs which established specific responsibility for diversity, such as [[equal opportunity]] staff positions or diversity task forces, have proven most effective in general. However, the results also indicate that [[White people|White]] females benefit significantly more from diversity training.  The benefits for [[African American]] females and males were appreciably lower than European American females. [[Social network|Networking]] and [[mentor]]ing, which were considered bias mitigating approaches, served African American females the most. African American males were the least likely to benefit from any of the methods.

The news media have used the study results to question the merits of financing the sizable diversity training industry. In January 2008, the ''Washington Post'' used quotes from “longtime diversity trainer” Dr. Billy E. Vaughn (Diversity Training University International) and others to make the point that Kalev’s research &lt;ref&gt;Shankar Vedantam: [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/01/19/AR2008011901899_pf.html Most Diversity Training Ineffective, Study Finds] ''The Washington Post,'' p. A03, January 20, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; suggests other strategies may be more effective than diversity training for mobilizing people of color and women into management roles.

Dr. Billy Vaughn wrote the article “The Short-Sighted Washington Post Article About Diversity Training” in response to the article. The Washington Post news article relied on research data that suggests that mandating sensitivity training for managers does not lead to increased management level positions for non-white males. In his response, Dr. Vaughn points out that the research is based on the assumption that one course or training can change behaviors that have taken a lifetime to develop. Dr. Vaughn wrote “most organizations engaged in a serious diversity effort today focus on building an inclusive organization, for which diversity training is one of several programs in a larger diversity education initiative.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Vaughn|first1=Billy|title=The Short-Sighted Washington Post Article About Diversity Training|url=http://dtui.com/diversityblog/14/|website=DTUI.com Diversity Blog|publisher=DTUI.com|accessdate=January 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The results of the study cited in the Washington Post article confirm what diversity professionals and human resource officers have known for a long time. "It takes a long-term effort to promote an inclusive organizational culture", states Dr. Vaughn in the article.

According to supporters of diversity training, the goal is to reach people's sense of empathy and morality. It seeks to address a sense of apathy that many people have because they do not think the problem affects them or they do not believe that they act in a racist manner.&lt;ref&gt;PBS, "Class Divided - FRONTLINE". Last modified January 2003. Accessed April 17, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jane Elliott]] says racism is not inherent: "You are not born a racist. You have to carefully be taught to be one."&lt;ref name="McPhee"&gt;{{cite news |first= Nicole |last= McPhee |authorlink= |title= Doing diversity right: Renowned Iowa schoolteacher and discrimination educator get to the heart of the matter |url= http://gauntlet.ucalgary.ca/a/story/2741 |work= |publisher= Gauntlet News |date= 2001-08-09 |accessdate= 2008-05-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the manner in which these training sessions are conducted and Elliott's role as a trainer have drawn criticism.&lt;ref name="Mirza"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Mirza  | first = Munira | authorlink = Munira Mirza | title = Ticking all the boxes  | journal = BBC News Magazine | volume = | issue = | pages = | id = | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/4521244.stm | accessdate = 2008-05-30 | quote =  | date=2005-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kors"/&gt;&lt;ref name="NPLC"&gt;[http://nlpc.org/sites/default/files/CorDiv_SR_0.pdf NLPC Special Report The Authoritarian Roots of Corporate Diversity Training] by the [[National Legal and Policy Center]] by Dr. Carl F. Horowitz&lt;/ref&gt;

Elliott has also been accused of not recognizing the social and political changes that have occurred since the era in which she originally developed her version of the diversity training-exercise. [[Alan Charles Kors]]—a professor of history at [[University of Pennsylvania]]—noted, in his defense of students accused of shouting racial slurs in the [[water buffalo incident]] of 1993, that Elliott's exercise teaches "blood-guilt and self-contempt to whites," adding that "in her view, nothing has changed in America since the collapse of [[Reconstruction Era|Reconstruction]]."&lt;ref name="Kors"&gt;[http://reason.com/archives/2000/03/01/thought-reform-101/3 ''Thought Reform 101'']; ''The Orwellian implications of today's college orientation'' by [[Alan Charles Kors]], [[Reason (magazine)|Reason]]; March 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

Mercedes Martin and Dr. Billy Vaughn argue that most diversity training is based on a limited view of what it means to be culturally competent. In their article ''Cultural Competence: The Nuts and Bolts of Diversity &amp; Inclusion'', they point out the limitations of the view that diversity training is all about sensitivity and awareness raising. They state that diversity training based on a [[cultural competence]] perspective includes awareness, attitude, knowledge and skill building.  From this perspective, focusing on sensitivity and awareness limits the effectiveness of diversity training because it is not based on an understanding of the range of potential other training content that may be needed to improve results.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Martin|first1=Mercedes|last2=Vaughn|first2=Billy|title=CULTURAL COMPETENCE: The Nuts &amp; Bolts of Diversity &amp; Inclusion|url=http://diversityofficermagazine.com/cultural-competence/cultural-competence-the-nuts-bolts-of-diversity-inclusion/|website=Diversity Officer Magazine|publisher=DTUI.com Publications|accessdate=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Sensitivity training]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.tmcorp.com/channel.aspx?page_id=P0107 What Diversity &amp; Inclusion is ''Really'' about - by Joerg Schmitz]
*[http://www.dtui.com/qapg1.html What is the "diversity training" profession?- by Diversity Training University International]
{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Diversity Training}}
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Education]]
[[Category:Political correctness]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Sociological terminology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>