<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20070924183957|160073757" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="374004" pageid="374004" ns="0" title="Diversity training"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-09-24T18:40:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{citations needed|date=May 2007}}

'''Diversity training''' is [[training]], provided to members of an organization (often [[student]]s, [[employee]]s or [[volunteer]]s), usually with the stated purpose of treating [[Multiculturalism|diversity]] as an opportunity and promoting the ability of members from a great variety of backgrounds to cooperate productively and make as great a contribution as possible to organizational [[diversity (business)|goals]]. 

==Leading Diverse Teams==
According to Bird (2007)[http://professormbird.com/page7.html], many project managers may feel that they are treading new territory as they lead project [[team]]s made of individuals from different cultures, heterogeneous mixes, and differing [[demographic]]s.  This signals a lack understanding of the techniques required to manage diverse teams which can lead to project managers being less efficient and effective.  This in turn can cause the team member motivation, satisfaction levels and productivity to drop due to the lack of knowledge and skills needed to lead diverse teams.  Bird further states that the project manager will need to refine and improve management techniques and should complete a post project evaluation to measure the overall results of managing the diverse teams. 

Based on Bird’s research, the following positive approaches can be adopted by the project managers leading such heterogeneous teams in order to seek positive effects of managing diversity in project teams effectively:

* Recognize that diversity will bring a greater skills base when managed properly
* Improve the overall climate on diverse project teams in order to improve satisfaction, reduce conflicts, and improve team member retention
* Encourage creativity, flexibility, and innovation among the team members which will allow the injection of new ideas and challenge the normal organizational mindsets

Bird further concludes in his article that managing diversity provides greater opportunities for project teams with better performance, and greater strategic awareness, which enables them to be more innovative and responsive. 

==References==

1. Bird, Professor (2007). Improving Project Productivity with Diverse Membership. Professor of Devry University of South Florida.  Retrieved on July 25, 2007 from http://professormbird.com/page7.html.

==External links==

*[http://www.tmcorp.com/channel.aspx?page_id=P0107 What Diversity &amp; Inclusion is ''Really'' about - by Joerg Schmitz]
*[http://www.workforcediversitynetwork.com/docs/article_creatinginclusion12-02.pdf Creating Inclusion is More than Meets the Eye! - by Dr. William A. Guillory Ph. D.]
*[http://workforcediversitynetwork.com/docs/Diversity-AManagersToolbox.pdf ''Diversity-The Competitive Advantage "A Manager's Toolbox"'' - by Dr. William A. Guillory Ph. D.]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>