<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20190810132126|910212435" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="374004" pageid="374004" ns="0" title="Diversity training"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-10-18T15:04:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Diversity training''' is any program designed to facilitate positive intergroup interaction, reduce [[prejudice]] and [[discrimination]], and generally teach individuals who are different from others how to work together effectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Lindsey |first=Alex |last2=King |first2=Eden |last3=Hebl |first3=Michelle |last4=Levine |first4=Noah |date=September 2015|title=The Impact of Method, Motivation, and Empathy on Diversity Training Effectiveness|journal=[[Journal of Business and Psychology]]|volume=30|issue=3|pages=605–617|doi=10.1007/s10869-014-9384-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; "From the broad corporate perspective, diversity training is defined as raising personal awareness about individual differences in the workplace and how those differences inhibit or enhance the way people work together and get work done. In the narrowest sense, it is education about compliance  – [[Affirmative Action]] (AA), [[Equal Employment Opportunity]] (EEO), and [[sexual harassment]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Wheeler|first1=M.L.|title=Diversity Training|journal=The Conference Board|date=1994|volume=Research Report 1083-94RR|url=http://ncrve.berkeley.edu/abstracts/MDS-934/MDS-934-REFERENC.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; A competency based definition refers to diversity training as any solution designed to increase cultural diversity awareness, attitude, knowledge, and skills.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Vaughn | first = Billy E. | title = The history of diversity training &amp; its pioneers | url = http://diversityofficermagazine.com/diversity-inclusion/the-history-of-diversity-training-its-pioneers/ | work = Diversity Officer Magazine Newsletter | date = August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Diversity training is thought to be more needed because of the growing ethnic and racial diversity in the workplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Cocchiara | first1 = Faye K. | last2 = Connerley | first2 = Mary L. | last3 = Bell | first3 = Myrtle P. | title = "A GEM" for increasing the effectiveness of diversity training | journal = Human Resource Management | volume = 49 | issue = 6 | pages = 1089&amp;ndash;1106 | doi = 10.1002/hrm.20396 | date = November–December 2010 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; While major corporations believe that diversity training and active diversity hiring will assist them in remaining competitive in a global economy, other large organizations (universities and colleges) have been slow to embrace diversity training.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Utz | first = Richard | title = The Diversity Question in Administrative-Job Interviews | url =http://www.chronicle.com/article/The-Diversity-Questionthe/238914 | work = [[The Chronicle of Higher Education]] | date = January 18, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Diversity training is often aimed to meet objectives such as attracting and [[Customer retention|retaining customers]] and productive workers; maintaining high [[employee morale]]; and/or fostering understanding and harmony between workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Chavez | first1 = Carolyn I. | last2 = Weisinger | first2 = Judith Y. | title = Beyond diversity training: a social infusion for cultural inclusion | journal = Human Resource Management| volume = 47 | issue = 2 | pages = 331&amp;ndash;350 | doi = 10.1002/hrm.20215 | date = Summer 2008 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite purported and intended benefits, systematic studies have not shown benefits to diversity training and instead show that they backfire and lead to reductions in diversity and to discrimination complaints being taken less seriously.&lt;ref name="ethics.harvard.edu"&gt;{{Cite web | last1 = Dobbin | first1 = Frank | last2 = Kalev | first2 = Alexandra | url = http://ethics.harvard.edu/blog/why-diversity-management-backfires-and-how-firms-can-make-it-work|title=Why Diversity Management Backfires (And How Firms Can Make it Work)|website=ethics.harvard.edu | publisher = [[Edmond J. Safra Center for Ethics]], Harvard University |access-date=2016-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="washingtonpost.com"&gt;{{Cite news | last = McGregor | first = Jena|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/on-leadership/wp/2016/07/01/to-improve-diversity-dont-make-people-go-to-diversity-training-really-2/|title=To improve diversity, don't make people go to diversity training. Really.|work=Washington Post | date = July 1, 2016|access-date=15 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

==Controversial issues==
According to Hans Bader, its opponents consider it an oppressive [[ideology]] and reeducation tactic that actually reduces the ability of organizations to attain their goals. It has been suggested that diversity training reinforces differences between individuals instead of fostering their commonalities, thus helping to further racialize the workplace, creating situations where people "tiptoe" around issues such as how to relate to people of different cultures as opposed to people learning to [[communicate]] with and truly understand each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | last = Bader | first = Hans | url = https://cei.org/blog/diversity-training-backfires | title = Diversity training backfires | publisher = [[Competitive Enterprise Institute]] | website = cei.org| date = 26 December 2007 | access-date = 13 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Programs which established specific responsibility for diversity, such as [[equal opportunity]] staff positions or diversity task forces, have proven most effective in general. However, the results also indicate that [[White people|white]] females benefit significantly more from diversity training. The benefits for [[African American|black]] females and males were appreciably lower than white  females. [[Social network|Networking]] and [[mentor]]ing, which were considered bias mitigating approaches, served black females the most. Black males were the least likely to benefit from any of the methods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Kalev | first1 = Alexandra | last2 = Dobbin | first2 = Frank | last3 = Kelly | first3 = Erin | title = Best practices or best guesses? Assessing the efficacy of corporate affirmative action and diversity policies | journal = [[American Sociological Review]] | volume = 71 | issue = 4 | pages = 589&amp;ndash;617 | doi = 10.1177/000312240607100404 | date = August 2006 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sue Steiner and collaborators have advocated that controversy be used as a cooperative learning style. They argue that attempting to see both sides of a controversial issue builds empathy and allows working environments to function better.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Steiner | first1 = Sue | last2 = Brzuzy | first2 = Stephanie | last3 = Gerdes | first3 = Karen | last4 = Hurdle | first4 = Donna | title = Using structured controversy to teach diversity content and cultural competence | journal = Journal of Teaching in Social Work | volume = 23 | issue = 1&amp;ndash;2 | pages = 55&amp;ndash;71 | doi = 10.1300/J067v23n01_05 | date = 2003 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alexandra Kalev conducted a comprehensive review of cultural diversity training conducted in 830 midsize to large U.S. workplaces over a thirty one year period.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/01/19/AR2008011901899.html|title=Most Diversity Training Ineffective, Study Finds|journal=The Washington Post and Times-Herald|last=Vedantam|first=Shankar|date=2008-01-20|access-date=2018-04-29|language=en-US|issn=0190-8286}}&lt;/ref&gt; The results showed that diversity training was followed by a decrease of anywhere from 7.5-10% in the number of women in management. The percentage of black men in top positions fell by 12 percent. Similar effects were shown for Latinos and Asians. The study did not find that all diversity training is ineffective. Mandatory training programs offered to protect against discrimination lawsuits were called into question. Voluntary diversity training participation to advance organization’s business goals was associated with increased diversity at the management level.

== Purported benefits ==
An analysis of data from over 800 firms over 30 years shows that diversity training and grievance procedures backfires and leads to reductions in the diversity of the firms workforce.&lt;ref name="ethics.harvard.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref name="washingtonpost.com"/&gt; Other research shows that people "were less likely to take discrimination complaints seriously against companies who had diversity programs".&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite news| last = McElroy | first = Molly | url = http://www.washington.edu/news/2013/04/03/diversity-programs-give-illusion-of-corporate-fairness-study-shows/ | title = Diversity programs give illusion of corporate fairness, study shows | work = UW Today | publisher = [[University of Washington]] | date = 3 April 2013 |access-date=15 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As organizations and communities are becoming more [[Globalization|globalized]], there is a need for an expansion in relation to communication among individuals from all over the world, operating within a diverse environment.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/240550|title=The Myriad Benefits of Diversity in the Workplace|last=Abreu|first=Kim|work=[[Entrepreneur (magazine)|Entrepreneur]]|access-date= 13 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some scholars believe it is beneficial for companies to train a diverse staff, as a reflection of the market in which you wish to serve.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Armache | first = Jalal | title = Diversity in the workplace: benefits and challenges | journal = Journal of International Diversity | volume = 2012 | issue = 1 | pages = 59&amp;ndash;75 | date = March 2012 | url = http://connection.ebscohost.com/c/articles/75172682/diversity-workplace-benefits-challenges | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Jalai Armache, in a heterogeneous workplace environment filled with people knowledgeable of those with different backgrounds and nationalities, there is ability to easily expand an organization.  There is an ability to create inventive solutions to issues being faced in the world market.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==See also==
* [[Diversity (business)]]
* [[Multiculturalism]]
* [[Neurodiversity]]
* [[Respect diversity]]
* [[Sensitivity training]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite journal | last = Beddoes | first = Kacey | title = Institutional influences that promote studying down in engineering diversity research | journal = [[Frontiers: A Journal of Women Studies]] | volume = 38 | issue = 1 | pages = 88&amp;ndash;99 | jstor = 10.5250/fronjwomestud.38.1.0088 | date = 2017 |url = http://muse.jhu.edu/article/653261 | ref = harv | doi = 10.5250/fronjwomestud.38.1.0088 }}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Diversity Training}}
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Education by subject]]
[[Category:Linguistic controversies]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Sociological terminology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>