<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20240930141854|1248608908" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="4941" pageid="4941" ns="0" title="Blood libel"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-10-12T19:20:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{Short description|False claim that Jews killed Christians to use blood in ceremonies}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2022}}
[[File:Trento-statue of Simon of Trent in via Simonino.jpg|thumb|Statue of [[Simon of Trent]], an Italian child whose disappearance and death was blamed on the leaders of the city's Jewish community]]
{{Antisemitism sidebar|Canards}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Manifestations}}
'''Blood libel''' or '''ritual murder libel''' (also '''blood accusation''')&lt;ref name=JewishEncyclopedia&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last1=Gottheil |first1=Richard |last2=Strack |first2=Hermann L. |last3=Jacobs |first3=Joseph |encyclopedia=Jewish Encyclopedia |title=Blood Accusation |url=http://jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/3408-blood-accusation |year=1901–1906 |location=New York |publisher=Funk &amp; Wagnalls }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dundes&gt;{{Cite book |editor1-last = Dundes |editor1-first = Alan |year = 1991 |title = The Blood Libel Legend: A Casebook in Anti-Semitic Folklore |publisher = University of Wisconsin Press |isbn = 978-0-299-13114-2 |url-access = registration |url = https://archive.org/details/bloodlibellegend00alan }}&lt;/ref&gt; is an [[antisemitic canard]]&lt;ref name=Turvey2008p3&gt;Turvey, Brent E. ''Criminal Profiling: An Introduction to Behavioral Evidence Analysis'', Academic Press, 2008, p. 3. "Blood libel: An accusation of ritual murder made against one or more persons, typically of the Jewish faith".&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Chanes2004pp34-35&gt;Chanes, Jerome A. ''Antisemitism: A Reference Handbook'', ABC-CLIO, 2004, pp. 34–45. "Among the most serious of these [anti-Jewish] manifestations, which reverberate to the present day, were those of the libels: the leveling of charges against Jews, particularly the blood libel and the libel of desecrating the host."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Goldish2008p8&gt;Goldish, Matt. ''Jewish Questions: Responsa on Sephardic Life in the Early Modern Period'', Princeton University Press, 2008, p. 8. "In the period from the twelfth to the twentieth centuries, Jews were regularly charged with blood libel or ritual murder{{snd}} that Jews kidnapped and murdered non-Jews as part of a Jewish religious ritual."&lt;/ref&gt; which falsely accuses Jews of murdering Christians in order to use their blood in the performance of [[religious ritual]]s.&lt;ref name=JewishEncyclopedia /&gt;&lt;ref name=dundes /&gt;&lt;ref name=zeitlin&gt;Zeitlin, S [https://www.jstor.org/pss/1453766 "The Blood Accusation"] ''Vigiliae Christianae'', Vol. 50, No. 2 (1996), pp. 117–124&lt;/ref&gt; Echoing very old myths of secret [[Child sacrifice|cultic practices]] in many [[Prehistory|prehistoric]] societies, the claim, as it is leveled against Jews, was rarely attested to in [[Ancient history|antiquity]]. According to [[Tertullian]], it originally emerged in late antiquity as an accusation made against [[Early Christianity|members of the early Christian community]] of the [[Roman Empire]].&lt;ref name="D'Antonio"&gt;Emanuele D'Antonio, [https://www.quest-cdecjournal.it/jewish-self-defense-against-the-blood-libel-in-mid-nineteenth-century-italy-the-badia-affair-and-proceedings-of-the-castilliero-trial-1855-56/ ''Jewish Self-Defense against the Blood Libel in Mid-Nineteenth Century Italy: the Badia Affair and Proceedings of the Castilliero Trial (1855-56),'']  [[:it:Quest. Issues in Contemporary Jewish History|Quest. Issues in Contemporary Jewish History]] volume 14, 1 pp. 23–47&lt;/ref&gt; Once this accusation had been dismissed, it was revived a millennium later as a Christian slander against Jews in the [[Middle Ages|medieval period]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Norman Cohn]], ''[[Europe's Inner Demons]],'' (1975) Paladin Books 1976 pp.1-8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Albert Ehrman, 'The Origins of the Ritual Murder Accusation and Blood Libel,' [[Tradition (journal)|Tradition]] vol.14, No.4 Spring 1976 p.83&lt;/ref&gt; The first examples of medieval blood libel emerged in England in the mid 1100s before spreading into other parts of Europe, especially France and Germany. This libel, alongside those of [[well poisoning]] and [[host desecration]], became a major theme of the [[History of the Jews in Europe|persecution of Jews in Europe]] from that period down to modern times.&lt;ref name=Chanes2004pp34-35/&gt;

Blood libels often claim that Jews require human blood for the baking of [[Matzah|matzos]], an unleavened flatbread which is eaten during [[Passover]]. Earlier versions of the blood libel accused Jews of ritually re-enacting the [[Crucifixion of Jesus|crucifixion]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://archive.org/details/lifemiraclesofst00thomuoft/page/14/mode/2up?view=theater | title=The life and miracles of St. William of Norwich | year=1896 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The accusations often assert that the blood of Christian children is especially coveted, and historically, blood libel claims have been made in order to account for the otherwise unexplained deaths of children. In some cases, the alleged victims of [[human sacrifice]] have become venerated as [[Christian martyr]]s. Many of these{{snd}} most prominently [[William of Norwich]] (1144), [[Little Saint Hugh of Lincoln]] (1255), and [[Simon of Trent]] (1475){{snd}} became objects of local [[Cult (religious practice)|cult]]s and veneration; the cult of Hugh of Lincoln gained the support of [[Henry III of England|Henry III]] and his son [[Edward I of England|Edward I]], giving it official credibility and helping it to be particularly well remembered. Although he was never canonized, the veneration of Simon was added to the [[General Roman Calendar]]. One child who was allegedly murdered by Jews, [[Gabriel of Białystok]], was canonized by the [[Russian Orthodox Church]].

In [[Jewish mythology|Jewish lore]], blood libels served as the impetus for the creation of the [[Golem of Prague]] by [[Rabbi]] [[Judah Loew ben Bezalel]] in the 16th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~dash/golem.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110418003740/http://www.pitt.edu/~dash/golem.html|url-status=dead|title=Angelo S. Rappoport ''The Folklore of the Jews'' (London: Soncino Press, 1937), pp. 195–203|archivedate=18 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term 'blood libel' has also been used in reference to any unpleasant or damaging false accusation, and as a result, it has acquired a broader metaphoric meaning. However, this wider usage of the term remains controversial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-12176503|title=What does 'blood libel' mean?|date=12 January 2011|access-date=16 April 2018|publisher=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://www.nationalreview.com/the-campaign-spot/term-blood-libel-more-common-you-might-think-jim-geraghty/|title=The Term 'Blood Libel': More Common Than You Might Think|author=Jim Geraghty|date=12 January 2011|magazine=National Review|access-date=16 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424052748703583404576079823067585318|title=Sarah Palin Is Right About 'Blood Libel'|first=Shmuley|last=Boteach|date=14 January 2011|website=The Wall Street Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The earliest versions of the accusations involving Jews supposedly crucifying Christian children on [[Easter]]/Passover is said to be because of a prophecy.{{Clarify|reason=|date=September 2023}} There is no reference to the use of blood in unleavened matzo bread at this time yet, which develops later as a major motivation for the crime.&lt;ref&gt;Paul R. Bartrop, Samuel Totten, ''Dictionary of Genocide'', ABC-CLIO, 2007, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Possible precursors===
The earliest known antecedent is tenth century, from Damocritus (not [[Democritus]] the philosopher) mentioned in the [[Suda]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/3408-blood-accusation#3489 Blood Accusation] in ''Jewish Encyclopedia''. (Richard Gottheil, Hermann L. Strack, Joseph Jacobs). Accessed 31 October 2018. Note that the version of the Jewish Encyclopedia here quoted misspells the name ''Damocritus'' as ''Democritus'', the name of an unrelated philosopher.&lt;/ref&gt; who alleged that "every seven years the Jews captured a stranger, brought him to the temple in [[Jerusalem]], and sacrificed him, cutting his flesh into bits."&lt;ref name="Patterson2015"&gt;{{cite book|author=David Patterson|title=Anti-Semitism and Its Metaphysical Origins|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=F_1DBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA1|year=2015|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-1-107-04074-8|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Greco-Egyptian author [[Apion]] claimed that the Jews sacrificed Greek victims in [[Second Temple|their temple]]. Here, the writer states that when [[Antiochus IV Epiphanes|Antiochus Epiphanes]] entered the temple in Jerusalem, he discovered a Greek captive, who told him that he was being fattened for sacrifice. Every year, Apion claimed, the Jews would sacrifice a Greek and consume his flesh, at the same time swearing eternal hatred towards the Greeks.&lt;ref&gt;Louis H. Feldman, ''Jew and Gentile in the Ancient World: Attitudes and Interactions from Alexander to Justinian'', Princeton University Press, Princeton, New Jersey, 1993. pp. 126–27.&lt;/ref&gt; Apion's claim likely reflects already circulating attitudes towards Jews as similar claims are made by [[Posidonius]] and [[Apollonius Molon]] in the 1st century BCE.&lt;ref name=Feldmanp1996p293&gt;Feldman, Louis H. ''Studies in Hellenistic Judaism'', Brill, 1996, p. 293.&lt;/ref&gt; This idea is exampled later in history, when [[Socrates Scholasticus]] ({{floruit}} 5th century) reported that in a drunken frolic, a group of Jews bound a Christian child to a cross in mockery of the death of Christ and scourged him until he died.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/History/syriabloodlibel.html |title=Blood libel in Syria |publisher=Jewishvirtuallibrary.org |access-date=2010-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Medieval context===
The blood libels emerged at a time when the church and particularly the Crusades were driving increasingly anti-Judaic discourses. These were later reinforced through the Church council [[Lateran IV]] which mandated the segregation of Christian and Jewish society, and built an apparatus of enforcement across Europe.{{cn|date=March 2024}} At a local context, many of the English examples may have included an element of church competition for saintly cults, with the income that veneration produced.{{cn|date=March 2024}}

[[Israel Yuval]] proposed that the blood libel may have originated in the 12th century due to Christian views on Jewish behavior during the [[First Crusade]]. Some Jews committed suicide and killed their own children rather than exposing them to [[forced conversion]] to Christianity. Yuval wrote that Christians may have argued that if Jews could kill their own children, they could also kill Christian children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/827036.html |title=And if it's not good for the Jews? |author=Lily Galili |work=Haaretz |date=18 February 2007 |access-date=2007-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;''Two Nations in Your Womb: Perceptions of Jews and Christians in Late Antiquity and the Middle Ages'' by Israel J. Yuval; translated by Barbara Harshav and Jonathan Chipman, University of California Press, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===Origins in England===
[[File:Death of William of Norwich.jpg|thumb|left|upright|The crucifixion of William of Norwich depicted on a [[rood screen]] in Holy Trinity church, [[Loddon, Norfolk|Loddon]], Norfolk ]]
{{Main|Harold of Gloucester|Little Saint Hugh of Lincoln|Robert of Bury|William of Norwich}}

In England in 1144, the Jews of [[Norwich]] were falsely accused of [[Human sacrifice|ritual murder]] after a boy, [[William of Norwich]], was found dead in the woods with stab wounds. William's hagiographer, [[Thomas of Monmouth]], falsely claimed that every year there is an international council of Jews at which they choose the country in which a child will be killed during Easter, because of a Jewish prophecy that states that the killing of a Christian child each year will ensure that the Jews will be restored to the Holy Land. According to Monmouth, England was chosen in 1144, and the leaders of the Jewish community delegated the Jews of Norwich to perform the killing, after which they abducted and crucified William.&lt;ref name="soc"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Langham |first1=Raphael |title=William of Norwich |url=http://www.jhse.org/node/44?page=0%2C0 |website=The [[Jewish Historical Society of England]] |access-date=1 July 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110718203040/http://www.jhse.org/node/44?page=0%2C0 |archive-date=18 July 2011 |date=10 March 2008}};{{br}} Langmuir, Gavin I (1996), ''Toward a Definition of Antisemitism'', University of California Press, pp. 216ff.&lt;/ref&gt; The legend was turned into a cult, with William acquiring the status of a martyr and pilgrims bringing offerings to the local church.&lt;ref&gt;{{Catholic Encyclopedia |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/15635a.htm |title=St. William of Norwich}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This was followed by similar accusations in [[Harold of Gloucester|Gloucester (1168)]], [[Robert of Bury|Bury St Edmunds (1181)]] and Bristol (1183). In 1189, the Jewish deputation attending the coronation of [[Richard I of England|Richard the Lionheart]] was attacked by the crowd. [[History of the Jews in England#Massacres at London and York (1189–90)|Massacres of Jews at London and York]] soon followed. In 1190 on 16 March 150 Jews were attacked in York and then massacred when they took refuge in the royal castle, where Clifford's Tower now stands, with some committing suicide rather than being taken by the mob.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyofyork.org.uk/themes/norman/the-1190-massacre|title=The 1190 Massacre: History of York|first=SUMO|last=Design|website=historyofyork.org.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt; The remains of 17 bodies thrown in a well in Norwich between the 12th and 13th century (five that were shown by DNA testing to likely be members of a single Jewish family) were very possibly killed as part of one of these [[pogroms]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-13855238 | publisher=BBC News | title=Jewish bodies found in medieval well in Norwich | date=23 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the death of [[Little Saint Hugh of Lincoln]], there were trials and executions of Jews.&lt;ref&gt;"The Knight's Tale of Young Hugh of Lincoln", Gavin I. Langmuir, Speculum, Vol. 47, No. 3 (July 1972), pp. 459–482.&lt;/ref&gt; The case was described by [[Matthew Paris]] and later by [[Chaucer]], and formed the basis of the ''[[Sir Hugh]]'' ballads which have circulated to the present day. Its notoriety sprang from the intervention of the Crown, the first time an accusation of ritual killing had been given royal credibility. 

The eight-year-old Hugh disappeared at [[Lincoln, Lincolnshire|Lincoln]] on 31 July 1255. His body was probably discovered on 29 August, in a well. A Jew named Copin or Koppin confessed to involvement. He confessed to [[John Lexington|John of Lexington]], a servant of the crown, and relative of the Bishop of Lincoln. He confessed that the boy had been crucified by the Jews, who had assembled at Lincoln for that purpose. [[Henry III of England|King Henry III]], who had reached Lincoln at the beginning of October, had Copin executed and 91 of the Jews of Lincoln seized and sent up to London, where 18 of them were executed. The rest were pardoned at the intercession of the Franciscans or Dominicans.&lt;ref&gt;See Langmuir (1972), p479; Jacobs, ''Jewish Ideals'', pp.&amp;nbsp;192–224&lt;/ref&gt; 

Within a few decades, Jews would be [[Edict of Expulsion|expelled from all of England]] in 1290 and not allowed to return until 1657, although it is likely that some Jews lived there during this period and kept their religion secret.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/education/resources/jews-in-england-1290/#:~:text=It%20was%20not%20until%201656,while%20keeping%20their%20religion%20secret.|title= Jews in England 1290 |website= National Archives|access-date= 3 July 2024}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the expulsion, [[Edward I of England|Edward I]] renovated "Little Saint Hugh's" shrine and decorated it with his Royal insignia, as part of his efforts to justify his actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb| David Stocker|1986}}&lt;/ref&gt; As Stacey notes: "A more explicit identification of the crown with the ritual crucifixion charge can hardly be imagined."&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Stacey|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Continental Europe===
[[File:Ritualmord-Legende.jpg|thumb|left|[[Simon of Trent]] blood libel. Illustration in Hartmann Schedel's Weltchronik, 1493]]

Much like the blood libel of England, the history of blood libel in continental Europe consists of unsubstantiated claims made about the corpses of Christian children. There were frequently associated supernatural events speculated about these discoveries and corpses, events which were often attributed by contemporaries to miracles. Also, just as in England, these accusations in continental Europe typically resulted in the execution of numerous Jews – sometimes even all, or close to all, the Jews in one town. These accusations and their effects also, in some cases, led to royal interference on behalf of the Jews.

Thomas of Monmouth's story of the annual Jewish meeting to decide which local community would kill a Christian child also quickly spread to the continent. An early version appears in ''Bonum Universale de Apibus'' ii. 29, § 23, by [[Thomas of Cantimpré]] (a monastery near Cambray). Thomas wrote, in around 1260, "It is quite certain that the Jews of every province annually decide by lot which congregation or city is to send Christian blood to the other congregations." Thomas of Cantimpré also believed that since the time when the Jews called out to [[Pontius Pilate]], "His blood be on us, and on our children" ({{bibleverse||Matthew|27:25|NIV}}), they have been afflicted with hemorrhages, a condition equated with male menstruation:&lt;ref&gt;Albert Ehrman, "The Origins of the Ritual Murder Accusation and Blood Libel," Tradition: A Journal of Orthodox Jewish Thought, Vol. 15, No. 4 (Spring 1976): 86&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;A very learned Jew, who in our day has been converted to the (Christian) faith, informs us that one enjoying the reputation of a prophet among them, toward the close of his life, made the following prediction: 'Be assured that relief from this secret ailment, to which you are exposed, can only be obtained through Christian blood ("''solo sanguine Christiano''").' This suggestion was followed by the ever-blind and impious Jews, who instituted the custom of annually shedding Christian blood in every province, in order that they might recover from their malady.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Thomas added that the Jews had misunderstood the words of their prophet, who by his expression "''solo sanguine Christiano''" had meant not the blood of any Christian, but that of Jesus{{snd}} the only true remedy for all physical and spiritual suffering. Thomas did not mention the name of the "very learned" proselyte, but it may have been [[Nicholas Donin]] of [[La Rochelle]], who, in 1240, had a disputation on the [[Talmud]] with [[Yechiel of Paris]], and who in 1242 caused the burning of numerous Talmudic manuscripts in Paris. It is known that Thomas was personally acquainted with Nicholas. Nicholas Donin and another Jewish convert, Theobald of Cambridge, are greatly credited with the adoption and the belief of the blood libel myth in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Albert Ehrman, "The Origins of the Ritual Murder Accusation and Blood Libel," Tradition: A Journal of Orthodox Jewish Thought, Vol. 15, No. 4 (Spring 1976): 88.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first known case outside England was in [[Blois]], France, in 1171. This was the site of a blood libel accusation against the town's entire Jewish community that led to around 31–33 Jews (with 17 women making up this total&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt;)&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;Susan L. Einbinder "Pucellina of Blois: Romantic Myths and Narrative Conventions," ''Jewish History'', Vol. 12, No. 1 (Spring 1998): 29&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Heritage: Civilization and the Jews: Source Reader |editor1-last=Hallo |editor1-first=William W. |editor1-link=William W. Hallo |editor2-last=Ruderman |editor2-first=David B. |editor2-link=David B. Ruderman |editor3-last=Stanislawski |editor3-first=Michael |editor3-link=Michael Stanislawski |publisher=Praeger Special Studies |year=1984 |isbn=978-0275916084 |location=Santa Barbara, California |page=134 }}&lt;/ref&gt; being burned to death&lt;ref name=trachtenberg&gt;{{Cite book |editor1-last = Trachtenberg |editor1-first = Joshua |year = 1943 |title = The Devil and the Jews, The Medieval Conception of the Jew and its Relation to Modern Anti-Semitism |publisher = Yale University Press |isbn = 0-8276-0227-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; on 29 May of that year, or the 20th of Sivan of 4931.&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt; The blood libel revolved around R. Isaac, a Jew whom a Christian servant reported had deposited a murdered Christian in the [[Loire]].&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;Susan L. Einbinder "Pucellina of Blois: Romantic Myths and Narrative Conventions," ''Jewish History'', Vol. 12, No. 1 (Spring 1998): 30-31.&lt;/ref&gt; The child's body was never found. The count had about 40 adult Blois Jews arrested and they were eventually to be burned. The surviving members of the Blois Jewish community, as well as surviving holy texts, were ransomed. As a result of this case, the Jews garnered new promises from the king. The burned bodies of the sentenced Jews were supposedly maintained unblemished through the burning, a claim which is a well-known miracle, martyr myth for both Jews and Christians.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt; There is significant primary source material from this case including a letter revealing moves for Jewish protection with [[King Louis VII]].&lt;ref&gt;Susan L. Einbinder "Pucellina of Blois: Romantic Myths and Narrative Conventions," ''Jewish History'', Vol. 12, No. 1 (Spring 1998): 31.&lt;/ref&gt; Responding to the mass execution, the [[Twentieth of Sivan]] was declared a fast day by [[Rabbenu Tam]].&lt;ref name="auto1"&gt;Albert Ehrman, "The Origins of the Ritual Murder Accusation and Blood Libel," ''Tradition: A Journal of Orthodox Jewish Thought'', Vol. 15, No. 4 (Spring 1976): 85.&lt;/ref&gt; In this case in Blois, there was not yet the myth proclaimed that Jews needed the blood of Christians.&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt;

[[File:Werner-vom-Oberwesel.jpg|thumb|upright|Painting of Werner of Oberwesel as a martyr]]
In 1235, after the dead bodies of five boys were found on Christmas day in [[Fulda]], the inhabitants of the town claimed the Jews had killed them to consume their blood, and burned 34 Jews to death with the help of Crusaders assembled at the time. Even though emperor [[Frederick II, Holy Roman Emperor|Frederick II]] cleared the Jews of any wrongdoing after an investigation, blood libel accusations persisted in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.haaretz.com/jewish/.premium-1235-34-jews-burned-to-death-1.5352841 |title=1235: 34 Jews Burned to Death in First 'Blood Cannibalism' Case |publisher=Haaretz |date=2014-12-28 |access-date=2020-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |others=Middle Ages section of [[Encyclopaedia Judaica]] article |title=Blood Libel |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/religion/encyclopedias-almanacs-transcripts-and-maps/blood-libel |access-date=25 February 2023 |website=[[Encyclopedia.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; At [[Pforzheim]], [[Baden]], in 1267, a woman supposedly sold a girl to Jews who, according to the myth, then cut her open and dumped her in the [[Enz]] River, where boatmen found her; the girl cried for vengeance, and then died. The body was said to have bled as the Jews were brought to it. The woman and the Jews allegedly confessed and were subsequently killed.&lt;ref&gt;Steven K. Baum, "When Fairy Tales Kill," ''Journal for the Study of Antisemitism'', Vol. 1, No. 2 (2009): 190-191.&lt;/ref&gt; That a judicial execution was summarily committed in consequence of the accusation is evident from the manner in which the [[Nuremberg]] "Memorbuch" and the synagogal poems refer to the incident.&lt;ref&gt;[[Siegmund Salfeld]], ''Das Martyrologium des Nürnberger Memorbuches'' (1898), pp.&amp;nbsp;15, 128–130&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1270, at [[Wissembourg|Weissenburg]], of [[Alsace]],&lt;ref name="auto2"&gt;"Blood Libel," Zionism and Israel –  Encyclopedic Dictionary, n.d. http://www.zionism-israel.com/dic/blood_libel.htm.&lt;/ref&gt; a supposed miracle alone decided the charge against the Jews. A child's body had shown up in the [[Lauter (Rhine)|Lauter]] River; it was claimed that Jews had cut into the child to acquire his blood, and that the child continued bleeding for five days.&lt;ref name="auto2"/&gt;

At Oberwesel, near Easter of 1287,&lt;ref&gt;Jörg R. Müller, "Ereẓ gezerah—'Land of Persecution': Pogroms against the Jews in the regnum Teutonicum from c. 1280 to 1350," The Jews of Europe in the Middle Ages (Tenth to Fifteenth Centuries): Proceedings of the International Symposium, ed. Christoph Cluse (20–25 October 2002): 249.&lt;/ref&gt; alleged miracles again constituted the only evidence against the Jews. In this case, it was claimed that the corpse of the 16-year-old [[Werner of Oberwesel]] (also referred to as "Good Werner") landed at [[Bacharach]] and the body performed miracles, particularly medicinal miracles.&lt;ref name="auto3"&gt;Ariel Toaff, Blood Passover, trans. Gian Marco Lucchese and Pietro Gianetti (AAARG, 2007): 64.&lt;/ref&gt; Light was also said to have been emitted by the body.&lt;ref&gt;Jörg R. Müller, "Ereẓ gezerah—'Land of Persecution': Pogroms against the Jews in the regnum Teutonicum from c. 1280 to 1350," The Jews of Europe in the Middle Ages (Tenth to Fifteenth Centuries): Proceedings of the International Symposium, ed. Christoph Cluse (20–25 October 2002): 249-250.&lt;/ref&gt; Reportedly, the child was hung upside down, forced to throw up the host and was cut open.&lt;ref name="auto3"/&gt; In consequence, the Jews of Oberwesel and many other adjacent localities were severely persecuted during the years 1286-89. The Jews of Oberwesel were particularly targeted because there were no Jews remaining in Bacharach following a 1283 pogrom. Additionally, there were pogroms following this case as well at and around Oberwesel.&lt;ref name="Miller 2002 p.250"&gt;Jörg R. Müller, "Ereẓ gezerah—'Land of Persecution': Pogroms against the Jews in the regnum Teutonicum from c. 1280 to 1350," The Jews of Europe in the Middle Ages (Tenth to Fifteenth Centuries): Proceedings of the International Symposium, ed. Christoph Cluse (20–25 October 2002): 250.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rudolph I of Germany|Rudolph of Habsburg]], to whom the Jews had appealed for protection, in order to manage the miracle story, had the archbishop of Mainz declare great wrong had been done to the Jew. This apparent declaration was very limited in effectiveness.&lt;ref name="Miller 2002 p.250"/&gt;

A statement was made, in the ''Chronicle'' of [[Konrad Justinger]] of 1423, that at [[Bern]] in 1293&lt;ref name="auto4"&gt;Albert Winkler, "The Approach of the Black Death in Switzerland and the Persecution of Jews, 1348–1349," Swiss American Historical Society Review, Vol. 43, No. 3 (2007): 14.&lt;/ref&gt; or 1294 the Jews tortured and murdered a boy called Rudolph (sometimes also referred to as Ruff, or Ruof). The body was reportedly found by the house of Jöly, a Jew. The Jewish community was then implicated. The penalties imposed upon the Jews included torture, execution, expulsion, and steep financial fines. Justinger argued Jews were out to harm Christianity.&lt;ref name="auto4"/&gt; The historical impossibility{{clarify|date=October 2019}} of this widely credited story was demonstrated by Jakob Stammler, pastor of Bern, in 1888.&lt;ref&gt;"Katholische Schweizer-Blätter", Lucerne, 1888.&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been several explanations put forth as to why these blood libel accusations were made and perpetuated. For example, it has been argued Thomas of Monmouth's account and other similar false accusations, as well as their perpetuation, largely had to do with the economic and political interests of leaders perpetuating these myths.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffrey Cohen, Review of The Murder of William of Norwich: The Origins of the Blood Libel in Medieval Europe, by E.M. Rose Journal of Interdisciplinary History, Vol. 47, No. 3 (Winter 2017): 410.&lt;/ref&gt; The use of blood and other human products for medicinal or magical purposes was an established concept in medieval Europe.&lt;ref name="JT141-3"&gt;Joshua Trachtenberg, The Devil and the Jews: The Medieval Conception of the Jew and its Relation to Modern Anti-Semitism.  (Vardo Books, 2001): 141-143.&lt;/ref&gt;  As such illegal ways of accessing these item were ascribed (in 1507) by Franciscans to Dominicans, by others to sorcerers and devil worshippers as well as Jews.&lt;ref name="JT141-3"/&gt;

===Renaissance and Baroque===
[[File:Judensau Frankfurt.jpg|thumb|upright|From an 18th-century etching from Brückenturm. ''Above'': The murdered body of Simon of Trent. ''Below'': The "[[Judensau]]"]]

* Simon of Trent, aged two, disappeared in 1475, and his father alleged that he had been kidnapped and murdered by the local Jewish community. Fifteen local Jews were sentenced to death and burned. Simon was regarded locally as a saint, although he was never canonised by the church of Rome. He was removed from the Roman Martyrology in 1965 by [[Pope Paul VI]].
* Christopher of Toledo, also known as Christopher of La Guardia or "the [[Holy Child of La Guardia]]", was a four-year-old Christian boy supposedly murdered in 1490 by two Jews and three [[converso]]s (converts to Christianity). In total, eight men were executed. It is now believed&lt;ref&gt;Reston, James: "Dogs of God: Columbus, the Inquisition, and the defeat of the Moors", p. 207. Doubleday, 2005. {{ISBN|0-385-50848-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; that this case was constructed by the [[Spanish Inquisition]] to facilitate the [[Alhambra decree|expulsion of Jews from Spain]].
* In a case at Tyrnau (Nagyszombat, today [[Trnava]], Slovakia), the absurdity, even the impossibility, of the statements forced by torture from women and children shows that the accused preferred death as a means of escape from the torture, and admitted everything that was asked of them. They even said that Jewish men menstruated and that the latter therefore practiced the drinking of Christian blood as a remedy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://doi.org/10.7916/D8H420D6|doi=10.7916/D89Z9CT6|date=November 2009|author1=Dentler, Jonathan|title=Sexing The Jewish Body: Male Menstruation Libel and the Making of Modern Gender }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* At Bösing (Bazin, today [[Pezinok]], Slovakia), it was charged that a nine-year-old boy had been bled to death, suffering cruel torture; thirty Jews confessed to the crime and were publicly burned. The true facts of the case were disclosed later when the child was found alive in Vienna. He had been taken there by the accuser, Count Wolf of Bazin, as a means of ridding himself of his Jewish creditors at Bazin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Harvey|first=Richard S.|date=2015-05-27|title=27 May 1529 Blood Libel and Burning to Death of 30 Jews in Bazin, Hungary #otdimjh|url=https://jewinthepew.org/2015/05/27/27-may-1529-blood-libel-and-burning-to-death-of-30-jews-in-bazin-hungary-otdimjh/|access-date=2020-09-29|website=On This Day in Messianic Jewish History|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Jelinek |first=Yeshayahu |author-link=Yeshayahu Jelínek |year=2007 |orig-date= |others=[[Encyclopaedia Judaica]] article |title=Pezinok |url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/religion/encyclopedias-almanacs-transcripts-and-maps/pezinok |access-date=25 February 2023 |website=[[Encyclopedia.com]] |edition=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Rinn]], near [[Innsbruck]], a boy named [[Andreas Oxner]] (also known as Anderl von Rinn) was said to have been bought by Jewish merchants and cruelly murdered by them in a forest near the city, his blood being carefully collected in vessels. The accusation of drawing off the blood (without murder) was not made until the beginning of the 17th century when the cult was founded. The older inscription in the church of Rinn, dating from 1575, is distorted by fabulous embellishments{{snd}} for example, that the money paid for the boy to his godfather turned into leaves, and that a lily blossomed upon his grave. The cult continued until officially prohibited in 1994, by the Bishop of Innsbruck.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/rinn.html Medieval Sourcebook: A Blood Libel Cult: Anderl von Rinn, d. 1462] www.fordham.edu.&lt;/ref&gt;
* On 17 January 1670, [[Raphael Levy]], a member of the Jewish community of [[Metz]], was executed on charges of the ritual murder of a peasant child who had gone missing in the woods outside the village of [[Glatigny, Moselle|Glatigny]] on 25 September 1669, the eve of [[Rosh Hashanah]].&lt;ref&gt;Edmund Levin, [https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424052702303973704579357000706882812 The Exoneration of Raphael Levy], ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'', 2 February 2014. Accessed 10 October 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Sandomierz]], a city in [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth|Poland]], has been the venue of a number of blood libel cases, leading to the torture and execution of several people.&lt;ref name=Sand&gt;{{cite web |author= Daniel Tilles |title= The "compelling need for truth": reflections on Sandomierz's blood-libel plaque |date= 25 February 201 |website= Notes from Poland |url= https://notesfrompoland.com/2015/02/25/the-compelling-need-for-truth-reflections-on-sandomierzs-blood-libel-plaque/ |access-date= 5 December 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; One such case from 1698 involved Małgorzata, a dead two-year-old Christian girl whose corpse was deposited in a church mortuary by her mother, and the Jew she accused under torture, Aleksander Berek.&lt;ref name=Sand/&gt; Both the mother and Berek were executed.&lt;ref name=Sand/&gt; Other cases are known from earlier dates, and in 1710 another one followed: the body of a boy, Jerzy Krasnowski, was found, a local rabbi was accused of killing him, with the result that the rabbi along with several other Jews died in prison during the proceeding, and three more Jews were sentenced and executed.&lt;ref name=Sand/&gt;
[[File:Antisemitic-church-fresco.jpg|thumb|[[Fresco]] in St Paul's Church in [[Sandomierz]], Poland, depicting blood libel]]

===19th century===
One of the child-saints in the Russian Orthodox Church is the six-year-old boy Gavriil Belostoksky from the village [[Zwierki|Zverki]]. According to the legend supported by the church, the boy was kidnapped from his home during the holiday of [[Passover]] while his parents were away. Shutko, who was a Jew from [[Białystok]], was accused of bringing the boy to Białystok, piercing him with sharp objects and draining his blood for nine days, then bringing the body back to Zverki and dumping it at a local field. A cult developed, and the boy was canonized in 1820. His relics are still the object of pilgrimage. On [[All Saints Day]], 27 July 1997, the Belarusian state TV showed a film alleging the story is true.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vestnik.com/issues/97/0902/win/stonov.htm Is the New in the Post-Soviet Space Only the Forgotten Old?] by Leonid Stonov, International Director of Bureau for the Human Rights and Law-Observance in the Former Soviet Union, the President of the American Association of Jews from the former USSR&lt;/ref&gt; The revival of the cult in [[Belarus]] was cited as a dangerous expression of antisemitism in international reports on human rights and religious freedoms&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.4humanrights.org/by/eng/reports/relig2003.shtml Belarus. International Religious Freedom Report 2003] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070907160230/http://www.4humanrights.org/by/eng/reports/relig2003.shtml |date=7 September 2007 }} Released by the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2004/37195.htm Belarus. International Religious Freedom Report 2004] Released by the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2005/51542.htm Belarus. International Religious Freedom Report 2005] Released by the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2006/71370.htm Belarus. International Religious Freedom Report 2006] Released by the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://www.foreignaffairs.house.gov/archives/108/91075d.pdf |publisher=[[U.S. Department of State]] |title=Annual Report on International Religious Freedom for 2004 |chapter=Belarus |page=281 |access-date=2010-01-23 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100106153449/http://foreignaffairs.house.gov/archives/108/91075d.pdf |archive-date=6 January 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; which were passed to the [[UNHCR]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unhcr.org/home/RSDCOI/450fb0b128.html |title=U.S. Department of State Annual Report on International Religious Freedom for 2006 – Belarus |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070907060158/http://www.unhcr.org/home/RSDCOI/450fb0b128.html |archive-date=7 September 2007 |website=UNHCR  |access-date=10 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1823–35 [[Velizh]] blood libel: After a Christian child was found murdered outside of this small Russian town in 1823, accusations by a drunk prostitute led to the imprisonment of many local Jews. Some were not released until 1835.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Avrutin |first=Eugene |date=2017 |title=The Velizh Affair: Blood Libel in a Russian Town|location=Oxford |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=9780190640521}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1840 [[Damascus affair]]: In February, at Damascus, a Catholic monk named Father Thomas and his servant disappeared. The accusation of ritual murder was brought against members of the Jewish community of Damascus. 
* 1840 [[Rhodes blood libel]]: The Jews of [[Rhodes]], under the [[Ottoman Empire]], were accused of murdering a [[Greeks|Greek]] Christian boy. The libel was supported by the local governor and the European consuls posted to Rhodes. Several Jews were arrested and tortured, and the entire Jewish quarter was blockaded for twelve days. An investigation carried out by the central Ottoman government found the Jews to be innocent.
* In 1844 [[David Paul Drach]], the son of the Head Rabbi of [[Paris]] and a convert to Christianity, wrote in his book ''De L'harmonie Entre L'eglise et la Synagogue'', that a Catholic priest in Damascus had been ritually killed and the murder covered up by powerful Jews in Europe; referring to the 1840 Damascus affair [See above]
* In 1851-53, a case of blood libel took place in [[Surami]], [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] (then part of the Russian Empire): seven Jewish men, all versed in religious matters, were falsely accused of the murder of a Christian (Georgian) boy for ritual purposes. Local investigators pressed the case for three years before the [[Governing Senate]] in St Petersburg, the Russian Empire's highest judicial organ, convicted and exiled the accused to remote provinces.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Ben-Oren |first=Gershon |title=Montefiori ve-yehudei gruzia [Montefiore and the Jews of Georgia] |url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/23423315 |journal=Pe'amim: Studies in Oriental Jewry |publication-date=1984 |volume=20 |pages=69–76 |jstor=23423315 |via=JSTOR}}&lt;/ref&gt; Soviet, Israeli and Georgian scholars agree that the Russian imperial state, especially [[Caucasus Viceroyalty (1801–1917)|Viceroy]] Mikhail Vorontsov, was heavily involved, even manipulated the case to ensure a conviction.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Shukian |first=M.P. |year=1940 |title=Pravovoe polozhenie evreev Gruzii v XIX stoletii |journal=Trudy Istoriko-etnograficheskogo Muzeia Evreev Gruzii |volume=1 |pages=73–74}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Mamistvalishvili |first=El'dar |title=Gruzinskie evrei (s epokhi antichnosti do 1921g.) |year=2014 |location=Tbilisi |pages=210–215 |trans-title=Georgian Jews: from antiquity to the year 1921}}&lt;/ref&gt; This conviction greatly influenced the Kutaisi case (1878-80, see below).&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;
* In the [[Kingdom of Lombardy–Venetia|Lombardo-Venetian Kingdom]] in [[Badia Polesine|Badia]], in the [[Province of Rovigo]] on June 25, 1855, a 21-year-old peasant woman from [[Masi, Veneto|Masi]], Giuditta Castilliero, returned after eight days missing and claimed she escaped from a ritual murder. She showed wounds on her arms as evidence of bloodletting, giving evidence to her story of blood libel. She testified that a fellow townsman, Caliman Ravenna, was one of the parties responsible. Ravenna was a wealthy merchant, entrepreneur, district tax collector, moneylender and member of the elite in Badia. He was taken into custody on a charge of public violence, and rumours concerning the matter spread throughout the region. The case was moved to the Court of Rovigo. There, the magistrate and other criminal authorities rapidly reviewed the case and immediately arrested the alleged perpetrator. On July 9, Giuditta Castilliero was arrested for a theft in [[Legnago]] that took place during the days she had been reportedly missing. This contradicted her testimony, and Caliman Ravenna was released on July 14 and welcomed back into his community. Castilliero was charged with slander, a more serious crime than theft, and was sentenced to six years of hard labour. It was believed she had been put up to make the accusation by a criminal network, personal enemies of Ravella.&lt;ref name="D'Antonio" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Emanuele D’Antonio, ''Il sangue di Giuditta:Antisemitismo e voci ebraiche nell’Italia di metà Ottocento,'' [[:it:Carocci Editore|Carocci]] 2020 {{isbn|978-8-829-00329-7}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In March 1879, nine Jewish men from the village of [[Sachkhere]] were brought to [[Kutaisi]], [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] to stand trial for the alleged kidnapping and murder of a Christian girl.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Kirmse |first=Stefan B. |date=9 February 2024 |title=Russian imperial borderlands, Georgian Jews, and the struggle for 'justice' and 'legality': blood libel in Kutaisi, 1878–80 |journal=[[Central Asian Survey]] |volume=43 |issue=2 |pages=171–195 |doi=10.1080/02634937.2024.2302581|doi-access=free |pmid=38903059 |pmc=11188619 }}{{Creative Commons text attribution notice|cc=by4|from this source=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case attracted a great deal of attention in the Russian Empire (of which Georgia was then a part): "While periodicals as diverse in tendency as ''[[Vestnik Evropy|Herald of Europe]]'' and ''[[Sankt-Peterburgskie Vedomosti|Saint Petersburg Notices]]'' expressed their amazement that medieval prejudice should have found a place in the modern judiciary of a civilized state, ''[[Novoye Vremya (newspaper)|New Times]]'' hinted darkly of strange Jewish sects with unknown practices."&lt;ref&gt;Effie Ambler, ''Russian Journalism and Politics: The Career of Aleksei S. Suvorin, 1861–1881'' (Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 1972: {{ISBN|0-8143-1461-9}}), p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt; The trial ended in acquittal, and the orientalist [[Daniel Chwolson]] published a refutation of the blood libel.
* 1882 [[Tiszaeszlár affair|Tiszaeszlár blood libel]]: The Jews of the village of [[Tiszaeszlár]], Hungary were accused of the ritual murder of a fourteen-year-old Christian girl, Eszter Solymosi. The case was one of the main causes of the rise of antisemitism in the country. The accused persons were eventually acquitted.
* In 1899 [[Hilsner Affair]]: Leopold Hilsner, a [[Czech Jewish]] vagabond, was accused of murdering a nineteen-year-old Christian woman, Anežka Hrůzová, with a slash to the throat. Despite the absurdity of the charge and the relatively progressive nature of society in [[Austria-Hungary]], Hilsner was convicted and sentenced to death. He was later convicted of an additional unsolved murder, also involving a Christian woman. In 1901, the sentence was commuted to life imprisonment. [[Tomáš Masaryk]], a prominent Austro-Czech philosophy professor and future president of [[Czechoslovakia]], spearheaded Hilsner's defense. He was later blamed by Czech media because of this. In March 1918, Hilsner was pardoned by Austrian emperor [[Karl of Austria|Charles I]]. He was never exonerated, and the true guilty parties were never found.

===20th and 21st centuries===
{{Further|Religious antisemitism|Antisemitism in Christianity|Antisemitism in Islam|Antisemitism in Europe|Antisemitism in Russia|Antisemitism in the Arab world|Antisemitism in the United States}}

* The 1903 [[Kishinev pogrom]], an anti-Jewish revolt, started when an anti-Semitic newspaper wrote that a Christian Russian boy, Mikhail Rybachenko, was found murdered in the town of [[Dubăsari|Dubossary]], alleging that the Jews killed him in order to use the blood in preparation of matzo. Around 49 Jews were killed and hundreds were wounded, with over 700 houses being looted and destroyed.
* In the [[1910 Shiraz blood libel]], the Jews of [[Shiraz]], [[Qajar Iran|Iran]], were falsely accused of murdering a Muslim girl. The entire Jewish quarter was pillaged; the pogrom left 12 Jews dead and about 50 injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=[[David Littman (historian)|Littman, David]]|year=1979|title=Jews Under Muslim Rule: The Case of Persia|url=http://www.dhimmitude.org/archive/littman_jews_under_muslims_case_of_persia.pdf |archive-url=https://ghostarchive.org/archive/20221009/http://www.dhimmitude.org/archive/littman_jews_under_muslims_case_of_persia.pdf |archive-date=2022-10-09 |url-status=live|publisher=Institute of Contemporary History|page=14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:1910s antisemitic flier Andrei Yushchinsky.jpg|thumb|Antisemitic flier in [[Kyiv]] in the 1910s with a picture of the dead Yushchinskyi, issued some time during the trial of Beilis, that read: "Christians, take care of your children!!! It will be the Jews' Passover on 17 March."]]

* In [[Kyiv]], a Jewish factory manager, [[Menahem Mendel Beilis]], was accused of murdering 13-year-old Andriy Yushchinskyi, a Christian child, and using his blood to make matzos. He was acquitted by an all-Christian jury after a sensational trial in 1913.&lt;ref name=malamud&gt;{{Cite book |editor1-last = Malamud |editor1-first = Bernard |year = 1966 |title = The Fixer |publisher = POCKET BOOKS, a Simon &amp; Schuster division of GULF &amp; WESTERN CORPORATION |isbn = 0-671-82568-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1928, the Jews of [[Massena (village), New York|Massena]], [[New York (state)|New York]] were falsely accused of kidnapping and killing a Christian girl in the [[Massena blood libel]].
* Jews were frequently accused of the ritual murder of Christians for their blood in ''[[Der Stürmer]]'', an antisemitic newspaper which was published in [[Nazi Germany]]. The infamous May 1934 issue of the paper was later banned by the Nazi authorities, because it went so far as to compare alleged Jewish ritual murder with the Christian [[Sacrament|rite]] of [[Eucharist|communion]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://research.calvin.edu/german-propaganda-archive/sturmer.htm German propaganda archive{{snd}} Caricatures from Der Stürmer], [[Calvin College]] website.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1938 the British fascist politician and veterinarian [[Arnold Leese]] published an antisemitic booklet in defense of the Blood Libel which he titled ''My Irrelevant Defence: Meditations inside Gaol and Out on Jewish Ritual Murder''.
* The [[Anti-Jewish violence in Poland, 1944–46#Number of victims|1944–1946 Anti-Jewish violence in Poland]], which according to some estimates killed as many as 1000–2000 Jews (237 documented cases),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Jews are Coming Back: The Return of the Jews to Their Countries of Origin After WW II|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=UFVFmxjpqLgC|publisher = Berghahn Books|date = 2005-01-01|isbn = 9781571815279|first = David|last = Bankier}}{{page needed|date=November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; involved, among other elements, accusations of blood libel, especially in the case of the [[Kielce pogrom|1946 Kielce pogrom]].
* [[Faisal of Saudi Arabia|King Faisal]] of [[Saudi Arabia]] (r. 1964–1975) made accusations against Parisian Jews that took the form of a blood libel.&lt;ref name = "Berger"&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Gerber | first = Gane S.
 | editor-last =Berger |editor-first =David
 | title = History and hate: the dimensions of anti-Semitism
 | year = 1986
 | publisher = [[Jewish Publication Society of America|Jewish Publication Society]]
 | location = Philadelphia
 | isbn = 0-8276-0267-7
 | oclc = 13327957
 | chapter = Anti-Semitism and the Muslim World
 | page = 88
 | lccn = 86002995
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

* ''The Matzah of Zion'' was written by the [[Syrian Ministry of Defense|Syrian Defense Minister]], [[Mustafa Tlass]] in 1986. The book concentrates on two issues: renewed ritual murder accusations against the Jews in the [[Damascus affair]] of 1840, and ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Frankel, Jonathan. ''The Damascus Affair: "Ritual Murder", Politics, and the Jews in 1840'', pp. 418, 421. Cambridge University Press, 1997. {{ISBN|978-0-521-48396-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book was cited at a [[United Nations]] conference in 1991 by a Syrian delegate. On 21 October 2002, the London-based Arabic paper ''[[Al-Hayat]]'' reported that the book ''The Matzah of Zion'' was undergoing its eighth reprinting and it was also being translated into English, French and Italian.{{citation needed|date=September 2011}} Egyptian filmmaker Munir Radhi has announced plans to adapt the book into a film.&lt;ref name="Goldberg2008"&gt;{{cite book|author=Jeffrey Goldberg|title=Prisoners: A Story of Friendship and Terror|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NQABTDuvi68C&amp;pg=PA250|year=2008|publisher=Vintage Books|isbn=978-0-375-72670-5|page=250}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2003, a private Syrian film company created a 29-part television series ''[[Ash-Shatat]]'' ("The Diaspora"). This series originally aired in [[Lebanon]] in late 2003 and it was subsequently broadcast by ''[[Al-Manar]]'', a satellite television network owned by [[Hezbollah]]. This TV series, based on the antisemitic forgery ''The Protocols of the Learned Elders of Zion'', shows the Jewish people engaging in a conspiracy to rule the world, and it also presents Jews as people who murder the children of Christians, drain their blood and use it to bake [[matzah]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=January 9, 2004 |title=Satellite Network Recycles The Protocols Of The Elders of Zion |url=http://www.adl.org/special_reports/protocols/protocols_recycled.asp |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130115091803/http://www.adl.org/special_reports/protocols/protocols_recycled.asp |archive-date=January 15, 2013 |website=[[Anti-Defamation League]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In early January 2005, some 20 members of the Russian [[State Duma]] publicly made a blood libel accusation against the Jewish people. They approached the Prosecutor General's Office and demanded that Russia "ban all Jewish organizations." They accused all Jewish groups of being extremist, "anti-Christian and inhumane, and even accused them of practices that include ritual murders." Alluding to previous antisemitic Russian court decrees that accused the Jews of ritual murder, they wrote that "Many facts of such religious extremism were proven in courts." The accusation included traditional [[antisemitic canards]], such as the claim that "the whole democratic world today is under the financial and political control of international Jewry. And we do not want our Russia to be among such unfree countries". This demand was published as an open letter to the prosecutor general, in ''Rus Pravoslavnaya'' ({{lang|ru|Русь православная}}, "Orthodox Russia"), a national-conservative newspaper. This group consisted of members of the ultra-nationalist [[Liberal Democratic Party of Russia|Liberal Democrats]], the [[Communist Party of the Russian Federation|Communist faction]], and the nationalist [[Motherland (Russia)|Motherland party]], with some 500 supporters. The mentioned document is known as "[[Letter of 5000|The Letter of Five Hundred]]" ("Письмо пятисот").&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://xeno.sova-center.ru/45A29F2/5295297?pub_copy=on |title=Письмо пятисот. Вторая серия. Лучше не стало |publisher=Xeno.sova-center.ru |access-date=2010-01-23 |archive-date=23 May 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130523024740/http://www.sova-center.ru/racism-xenophobia/news/racism-nationalism/2005/03/d4029 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rusk.ru/tema.php?idaid=14 |title=Русская линия / Актуальные темы / "Письмо пятисот": Обращение в Генеральную прокуратуру представителей русской общественности с призывом запретить в России экстремистские еврейские организации |publisher=Rusk.ru |access-date=2010-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their supporters included editors of nationalist newspapers as well as journalists. By the end of the month, this group was strongly criticized, and it retracted its demand in response.
* At the end of April 2005, five boys, ages 9 to 12, in [[Krasnoyarsk]] (Russia) disappeared. In May 2005, their burnt bodies were found in the city sewage. The crime was not disclosed, and in August 2007 the investigation was extended until 18 November 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://regnum.ru/news/872810.html |title=The investigation of the murder of five schoolboys in Krasnoyarsk was extended again (Regnum, 20 August 2007) |publisher=Regnum.ru |date=2007-08-20 |access-date=2010-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Russian nationalist groups claimed that the children were murdered by a Jewish sect with a ritual purpose.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://regnum.ru/news/454284.html |title="Jewish people were accused with murder of children in Krasnoyarsk" ("Regnum", 12 May 2005) |publisher=Regnum.ru |date=2005-05-16 |access-date=2010-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rusidea.org/index.php?a=2001 |title=Russian nationalistic publishers "Russian Idea", the article about the antisemitic movement "Living Without the Fear of the Jews.", June 2007: "...the murder of five children in Krasnoyarsk, which bodies were bloodless. Our layer V. A. Solomatov said that there is undoubtedly a ritual murder..." |publisher=Rusidea.org |access-date=2010-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nationalist M. Nazarov, one of the authors of "The Letter of Five Hundred" alleges "the existence of a '[[Hasidic Judaism|Hasidic sect]]', whose members kill children before Passover to collect their blood", using the Beilis case mentioned above as evidence. M.Nazarov also alleges that "the ritual murder requires throwing the body away rather than its concealing". "The Union of the Russian People" demanded officials thoroughly investigate the Jews, not stopping at the search in synagogues, [[Matzah]] bakeries and their offices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://regnum.ru/news/454284.html|title=В убийстве красноярских детей обвинили евреев и вспомнили дело Бейлиса|date=16 May 2005|website=regnum.ru|trans-title= Hasids were accused in Krasnoyarsk children murder, the [[Menahem Mendel Beilis|Beilis Affair]] was reanimated}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* During a speech in 2007, [[Raed Salah]], the leader of the northern branch of the [[Islamic Movement in Israel]], referred to Jews in Europe having in the past used children's blood to bake holy bread. "We have never allowed ourselves to knead [the dough for] the bread that breaks the fast in the holy month of [[Ramadan]] with children's blood", he said. "Whoever wants a more thorough explanation, let him ask what used to happen to some children in Europe, whose blood was mixed in with the dough of the [Jewish] holy bread."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/news/islamic-movement-head-charged-with-incitement-to-racism-violence-1.238209 "Islamic Movement head charged with incitement to racism, violence"], ''[[Haaretz]]'', 29 January 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the 2000s, a team of Polish anthropologists and sociologists investigated the currency of the blood libel myth in [[Sandomierz]] where a painting depicting the blood libel adorns the Cathedral, and Orthodox faithful in villages near [[Bialystok]], and they discovered that these beliefs persist among some Catholic and Orthodox Christians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.booksandideas.net/spip.php?page=print&amp;id_article=1054&amp;lang=fr| title = ''Joanna Tokarska-Bakir, Legendy o krwi, antropologia przesądu'' (Anthropology of Prejudice: Blood Libel Myths) Warsaw, WAB, 2008, 796 pp, 89 złotys, reviewed here by Jean-Yves Potel}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lubimyczytac.pl/ksiazka/23894/legendy-o-krwi-antropologia-przesadu|title=Legendy o krwi. Antropologia przesądu|website=Lubimyczytać.pl|language=pl|access-date=2019-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.miesiecznik.znak.com.pl/6592010krzysztof-jaskulowskilegendy-o-krwi/|title=Legendy o krwi|last=Jaskułowski|first=Krzysztof|date=2010-04-21|website=Miesięcznik Znak|language=pl|access-date=2019-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fact that local Jews were saved by orders from the bishop, who saw them hide in the very same cathedral during the [[Holocaust]], gave rise to hopes of transforming Sandomierz into a symbol of hope for the checkered historical [[History of the Jews in Poland|Polish-Jewish relations]].&lt;ref name=Sand/&gt; 
[[File:Sandomierz katedra - mord rytualny.jpg|Blood libel, 18th-century painting by Karol de Prevot in Sandomierz Cathedral|thumb]]

* In an address that aired on ''[[Al-Aqsa TV]]'', a [[Hamas]] run TV station in [[Gaza City|Gaza]], on 31 March 2010, Salah Eldeen Sultan (Arabic: صلاح الدين سلطان), founder of the American Center for Islamic Research in [[Columbus, Ohio]], the [[Islamic American University]] in [[Southfield, Michigan]], and the Sultan Publishing Co.&lt;ref&gt;"Egyptian extremists an ill wind in Arab Spring" by Harry Sterling, Calgary Herald, 2 September 2011. p. A13&lt;/ref&gt; and described in 2005 as "one of America's most noted Muslim scholars", alleged that Jews kidnap Christians and others in order to slaughter them and use their blood for making matzos. Sultan, who is currently a lecturer on Muslim jurisprudence at [[Cairo University]] stated that: "The Zionists kidnap several non-Muslims{{sic}}{{snd}} Christians and others... this happened in a Jewish neighborhood in Damascus. They killed the French doctor, Toma, who used to treat the Jews and others for free, in order to spread Christianity. Even though he was their friend and they benefited from him the most, they took him on one of these holidays and slaughtered him, along with the nurse. Then they kneaded the matzos with the blood of Dr. Toma and his nurse. They do this every year. The world must know these facts about the Zionist entity and its terrible corrupt creed. The world should know this." (Translation by the [[Middle East Media Research Institute]])&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memri.org/report/en/print4099.htm Blood Libel on Hamas' Al-Aqsa TV – American Center for Islamic Research President Dr. Sallah Sultan: Jews Murder Non-Jews and Use Their Blood for Passover Matzos], MEMRI, Special Dispatch No. 2907, 14 April 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memritv.org/clip_transcript/en/2443.htm Blood Libel on Hamas TV – President of the American Center for Islamic Research Dr. Sallah Sultan: Jews Murder Non-Jews and Use Their Blood to Knead Passover Matzos], MEMRITV, clip no. 2443{{snd}} Transcript, 31 March 2010 ([http://www.memritv.org/clip/en/2443.htm video clip available here]).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.se/32806/20110325/ Islamic group invited anti-Semitic speaker] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110816220334/http://www.thelocal.se/32806/20110325/ |date=16 August 2011 }}, The Local (Sweden's News in English), 25 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/147288 Egypt: More Calls to Murder Israelis] by Maayana Miskin, Arutz Sheva 7 (Isranelnationalnews.com), 28 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://antisemitism.org.il/article/64564/why-muslim-association-doesn%E2%80%99t-expresses-reservations-towards-antisemitism Why the Muslim Association doesn’t express reservations towards Antisemitism] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120419071200/http://antisemitism.org.il/article/64564/why-muslim-association-doesn%E2%80%99t-expresses-reservations-towards-antisemitism |date=19 April 2012 }} by Willie Silberstein, Coordination Forum for Countering Antisemitism (CFCA), 17 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* During an interview which aired on ''[[Rotana (television)|Rotana Khalijiya TV]]'' on 13 August 2012, Saudi Cleric Salman Al-Odeh stated (as translated by [[MEMRI]]) that "It is well known that the Jews celebrate several holidays, one of which is the Passover, or the Matzos Holiday. I read once about a doctor who was working in a laboratory. This doctor lived with a Jewish family. One day, they said to him: 'We want blood. Get us some human blood.' He was confused. He didn't know what this was all about. Of course, he couldn't betray his work ethics in such a way, but he began inquiring, and he found that they were making matzos with human blood." Al-Odeh also stated that "[Jews] eat it, believing that this brings them close to their false god, [[Yahweh]]" and that "They would lure a child in order to sacrifice him in the religious rite that they perform during that holiday."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memritv.org/clip_transcript/en/3536.htm Saudi Cleric Salman Al-Odeh: Jews Use Human Blood for Passover Matzos], MEMRITV, Clip No. 3536, (transcript), 13 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofisrael.com/saudi-cleric-accuses-jewish-people-of-genocide-drinking-human-blood/ Saudi cleric accuses Jewish people of genocide, drinking human blood] by Ilan Ben Zion, ''[[The Times of Israel]]'', 16 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In April 2013, the Palestinian non-profit organization MIFTAH, founded by [[Hanan Ashrawi]] apologized for publishing an article which criticized US President [[Barack Obama]] for holding a [[Passover Seder]] in the [[White House]] by saying "Does Obama, in fact, know the relationship, for example, between 'Passover' and 'Christian blood'...?! Or 'Passover' and 'Jewish blood rituals?!' Much of the chatter and gossip about historical Jewish blood rituals in Europe is real and not fake as they claim; the Jews used the blood of Christians in the Jewish Passover." MIFTAH's apology expressed its "sincerest regret".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.jta.org/news/article/2013/04/02/3123361/palestinian-non-profit-belatedly-apologizes-for-blood-libel-article|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130406011957/http://www.jta.org/news/article/2013/04/02/3123361/palestinian-non-profit-belatedly-apologizes-for-blood-libel-article|url-status=dead|title=Palestinian non-profit belatedly apologizes for blood libel article|archivedate=6 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In an interview which aired on [[Al-Hafez|Al-Hafez TV]] on 12 May 2013, Khaled Al-Zaafrani of the Egyptian Justice and Progress Party, stated (as translated by [[MEMRI]]): "It's well known that during the Passover, they [the Jews] make matzos called the 'Blood of Zion.' They take a Christian child, slit his throat and slaughter him. Then they take his blood and make their [matzos]. This is a very important rite for the Jews, which they never forgo... They slice it and fight over who gets to eat Christian blood." In the same interview, Al-Zaafrani stated that "The French kings and the Russian czars discovered this in the Jewish quarters. All the massacring of Jews that occurred in those countries were because they discovered that the Jews had kidnapped and slaughtered children, in order to make the Passover matzos."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memritv.org/clip_transcript/en/3873.htm Egyptian Politician Khaled Zaafrani: Jews Use Human Blood for Passover Matzos], MEMRITV, Clip No. 3873 (transcript), 24 May 2013 (see also: [http://www.memritv.org/clip/en/0/0/0/0/0/0/3873.htm Video Clip]).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/169004#.Ub6MqHFza-8 Egyptian Politician: Jews Use Human Blood for Passover Matzos] by Elad Benari, ''[[Arutz Sheva]]'', 17 June 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofisrael.com/egyptian-politician-revives-passover-blood-libel/ Egyptian politician revives Passover blood libel] by Gavriel Fiske, ''[[Times of Israel]]'', 19 June 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
*In an interview which aired on the [[Al-Quds TV]] channel on 28 July 2014 (as translated by [[MEMRI]]), [[Osama Hamdan]], the top representative of [[Hamas]] in [[Lebanon]], stated that "we all remember how the Jews used to slaughter Christians, in order to mix their blood in their holy matzos. This is not a figment of imagination or something taken from a film. It is a fact, acknowledged by their own books and by historical evidence."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memritv.org/clip_transcript/en/4384.htm Top Hamas Official Osama Hamdan: Jews Use Blood for Passover Matzos], MEMRITV, Clip No. 4384 (transcript), 28 July 2014. (video clip [http://www.memritv.org/clip/en/0/0/0/0/0/0/4384.htm available here])&lt;/ref&gt; In a subsequent interview with CNN's [[Wolf Blitzer]], Hamdan defended his comments, stating that he "has Jewish friends".&lt;ref&gt;[http://religion.blogs.cnn.com/2014/08/06/blood-libel-the-short-history-of-a-dangerous-myth/ Blood libel: the myth that fuels anti-Semitism] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140812024809/http://religion.blogs.cnn.com/2014/08/06/blood-libel-the-short-history-of-a-dangerous-myth/ |date=12 August 2014 }} by [[Candida Moss]] and Joel Baden, special to [[CNN]], 6 August 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In a sermon broadcast on the official [[Jordan Radio and Television Corporation|Jordanian TV channel]] on 22 August 2014, Sheik Bassam Ammoush, a former Minister of Administrative Development who was appointed to Jordan's [[Parliament of Jordan|House of Senate ("Majlis al-Aayan")]] in 2011, stated (as translated by [[MEMRI]]): "In [the [[Gaza Strip]]] we are dealing with the enemies of [[Allah]], who believe that the matzos that they bake on their holidays must be kneaded with blood. When the Jews were in the [[Jewish diaspora|diaspora]], they would murder children in England, in Europe, and in America. They would slaughter them and use their blood to make their matzos... They believe that they are [[Jews as the chosen people|God's chosen people]]. They believe that the killing of any human being is a form of worship and a means to draw near their god."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memritv.org/clip_transcript/en/4454.htm Friday Sermon by Former Jordanian Minister: Jews Use Children's Blood for Their Holiday Matzos], [[MEMRI]] Clip No. 4454 (transcript), 22 August 2014. (video clip [http://www.memritv.org/clip/en/0/0/0/0/0/0/4454.htm available here]).&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Palestinian genocide accusation|Allegations of genocide against Palestinians by Israel]] have been described as a form of blood libel by some critics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Nelson |first1=Cary |title=Israel Denial: Anti-Zionism, Anti-Semitism, &amp; The Faculty Campaign Against the Jewish State |date=7 June 2009 |publisher=[[Indiana University Press]] |isbn=978-0253045089}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Fandos |first=Nicholas |date=11 November 2023 |title=Two Young Democratic Stars Collide Over Israel and Their Party's Future |language=en-US |work=[[The New York Times]] |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/11/nyregion/aoc-torres-israel-gaza.html |access-date=11 November 2023 |issn=0362-4331 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20231118155151/https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/11/nyregion/aoc-torres-israel-gaza.html |archive-date=18 November 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In March 2020, Italian painter [[Giovanni Gasparro]] unveiled a painting of the martyrdom of [[Simon of Trent]], titled "''Martirio di San Simonino da Trento (Simone Unverdorben), per omicidio rituale ebraico'' (The Martyrdom of St. Simon of Trento in accordance with Jewish ritual murder)". The painting was condemned by the Italian Jewish community and the [[Simon Wiesenthal Center]], among others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.jpost.com/Diaspora/Antisemitism/Italian-artist-accused-of-antisemitism-for-new-painting-of-blood-libel-622578|title=Italian artist accused of antisemitism for new painting of blood libel|date=2020-03-27|access-date=2020-04-12|website=The Jerusalem Post|last=Reich|first=Aaron}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/277933|title=Italian painter unveils depiction of 1475 blood libel|date=2020-03-28|access-date=2020-04-12|website=Israel National News|last=Liphshiz|first=Cnaan}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[QAnon]] conspiracy theory has been accused of advancing blood libel tropes through its belief that Hollywood elites [[Adrenochrome#In popular culture|are harvesting adrenochrome from children]] through [[Satanic ritual abuse]] in order to become [[immortality|immortal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Rothschild |first1=Mike |title=The Storm Is Upon Us: How QAnon Became a Movement, Cult, and Conspiracy Theory of Everything |date=22 June 2021 |publisher=Octopus |isbn=978-1-80096-046-6 |pages=58{{endash}}61 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bicYEAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT58}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2022, a sculpture of Simon of Trent depicting the blood libel was used to promote the adrenochrome-harvesting conspiracy theory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Lee |first1=Ella |title=Fact check: Sculpture is evidence of antisemitic 'blood libel,' not false QAnon theory |url=https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/factcheck/2022/02/03/fact-check-qanons-adrenochrome-conspiracy-theory-baseless/9268681002/ |access-date=6 February 2022 |work=USA Today |date=3 February 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Views of the Catholic Church==
The attitude of the [[Catholic Church]] towards these accusations and the cults venerating children supposedly killed by Jews has varied over time. The [[Pope|Papacy]] generally opposed them, although it had problems in enforcing its opposition.

In 1911, the ''[[Dictionnaire apologétique de la foi catholique]]'', an important French Catholic encyclopedia, published an analysis of the blood libel accusations.&lt;ref&gt;English translation here [http://counterenlightenment.blogspot.com/2011/04/blood-libel-view-from-1911.html].&lt;/ref&gt; This may be taken as being broadly representative of educated Catholic opinion in continental Europe at that time. The article noted that the popes had generally refrained from endorsing the blood libel, and it concluded that the accusations were unproven in a general sense, but it left open the possibility that some Jews had committed ritual murders of Christians. Other contemporary Catholic sources (notably the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]] periodical ''[[La Civiltà Cattolica]]'') promoted the blood libel as truth.&lt;ref&gt;As shown by David Kertzer in ''The Popes Against the Jews'' (New York, 2001), pp. 161–63.&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, the accusations are rarer in Catholic circles. While [[Simon of Trent]]'s local status as a saint was removed in 1965, several towns in Spain still commemorate the blood libel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2022-08-11 |title=Spanish Catholic church to investigate antisemitic rituals |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2022/aug/11/spanish-catholic-church-to-investigate-antisemitic-rituals |access-date=2022-08-28 |website=The Guardian |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Papal pronouncements===
* [[Pope Innocent IV]] took action against the blood libel: "5 July 1247 Mandate to the prelates of Germany and France to annul all measures adopted against the Jews on account of the ritual murder libel, and to prevent the accusation of Arabs on similar charges" (The Apostolic See and the Jews, Documents: 492–1404; Simonsohn, Shlomo, pp.&amp;nbsp;188–189, 193–195, 208). In 1247, he wrote also that "Certain of the clergy, and princes, nobles and great lords of your cities and dioceses have falsely devised certain godless plans against the Jews, unjustly depriving them by force of their property, and appropriating it themselves;... they falsely charge them with dividing up among themselves on the Passover the heart of a murdered boy...In their malice, they ascribe every murder, wherever it chance to occur, to the Jews. And on the ground of these and other fabrications, they are filled with rage against them, rob them of their possessions without any formal accusation, without confession, and without legal trial and conviction, contrary to the privileges granted to them by the Apostolic See... Since it is our pleasure that they shall not be disturbed,... we ordain that ye behave towards them in a friendly and kind manner. Whenever any unjust attacks upon them come under your notice, redress their injuries, and do not suffer them to be visited in the future by similar tribulations."&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08017a.htm Pope Innocent IV], ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' (1910), Vol. 8, pp.&amp;nbsp;393–394&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Pope Gregory X]] (1271–1276) issued a letter which criticized the practice of blood libels and forbade arrests and persecution of Jews based on a blood libel, ''... unless which we do not believe they be caught in the commission of the crime.''&lt;ref name="gregx"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/g10-jews.html | title=Medieval Sourcebook: Gregory X: Letter on Jews, (1271-76) – Against the Blood Libel | author=[[Pope Gregory X]] | access-date=2007-05-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Pope Benedict XIV]] wrote the bull ''Beatus Andreas'' (22 February 1755) in response to an application for the formal [[canonization]] of the 15th-century [[Andreas Oxner]], a [[folk saint]] alleged to have been murdered by Jews "out of hatred for the Christian faith". Benedict did not dispute the claim that Jews murdered Christian children, and in anticipating that further cases on this basis would be brought appears to have accepted it as accurate, but decreed that in such cases beatification or canonization would be inappropriate.&lt;ref&gt;Marina Caffiero, ''Forced Baptisms: Histories of Jews, Christians, and Converts in Papal Rome'', translated by [[Lydia G. Cochrane]] (University of California Press, 2012), pp. 34-36.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Blood libels in Muslim lands ==
In late 1553 or 1554, [[Suleiman the Magnificent]], the reigning [[sultan of the Ottoman Empire]], issued a [[firman (decree)|firman]] (royal decree) which formally denounced blood libels against the Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Mansel |first=Philip |author-link=Philip Mansel|title=[[Constantinople: City of the World's Desire, 1453–1924]]|year= 1998|publisher= St. Martin's Griffin |location= New York |isbn= 978-0-312-18708-8 |page= 124}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1840, following the Western outrage arising from the [[Damascus affair]], British politician and leader of the British Jewish community, Sir [[Moses Montefiore]], backed by other influential westerners including Britain's [[Henry Temple, 3rd Viscount Palmerston|Lord Palmerston]] and Damascus consul [[Charles Henry Churchill]],&lt;ref name= Lewis/&gt; the French lawyer [[Isaac Moïse Crémieux|Adolphe Crémieux]], Austrian consul Giovanni Gasparo Merlato, Danish missionary [[John Nicolayson]],&lt;ref name= Lewis&gt;{{cite book |last= Lewis |first= Donald |title= The Origins of Christian Zionism: Lord Shaftesbury And Evangelical Support for a Jewish Homeland |publisher= Cambridge University Press |date= 2 January 2014 |location= Cambridge |page= 380 |isbn= 9781107631960}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Solomon Munk, persuaded Sultan [[Abdulmejid I]] in [[Constantinople]], to issue a firman on 6 November 1840 intended to halt the spread of blood libel accusations in the Ottoman Empire. The edict declared that blood libel accusations were a [[slander]] against Jews and they would be prohibited throughout the Ottoman Empire, and read in part:

&lt;blockquote&gt;... and for the love we bear to our subjects, we cannot permit the Jewish nation, whose innocence for the crime alleged against them is evident, to be worried and tormented as a consequence of accusations which have not the least foundation in truth...&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the remainder of the 19th century and into the 20th century, there were many instances of the blood libel in Ottoman lands,&lt;ref name=LewisJews&gt;{{cite book |author=[[Bernard Lewis|Lewis, Bernard]] |title= The Jews of Islam |publisher= Princeton University Press |year= 1984 |pages= 158–159}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as the 1881 [[Fornaraki affair]]. However the libel almost always came from the Christian community, sometimes with the connivance of Greek or French diplomats.&lt;ref name=LewisJews/&gt; The Jews could usually count on the goodwill of the Ottoman authorities and increasingly on the support of British, [[Prussia]]n and Austrian representatives.&lt;ref name=LewisJews/&gt;

In the [[1910 Shiraz blood libel]], the Jews of [[Shiraz]], [[Qajar Iran|Iran]], were falsely accused of murdering a Muslim girl. The entire Jewish quarter was pillaged, with the pogrom leaving 12 Jews dead and about 50 injured.

In 1983, [[Mustafa Tlass]], the [[Ministry of Defense (Syria)|Syrian Minister of Defense]], wrote and published ''[[The Matzah of Zion]]'', which is a treatment of the Damascus affair of 1840 that repeats the ancient "blood libel", that [[Jew]]s use the blood of murdered non-Jews in religious rituals such as baking Matza bread.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1986/07/15/world/an-anti-jewish-book-linked-to-syrian-aide.html An Anti-Jewish Book Linked to Syrian Aide], ''[[The New York Times]]'', 15 July 1986.&lt;/ref&gt; In this book, he argues that the true religious beliefs of Jews are "black hatred against all humans and religions", and no Arab country should ever sign a peace treaty with [[Israel]].&lt;ref name=adl&gt;{{cite web |title= Literature Based on Mixed Sources – Classic Blood Libel: Mustafa Tlas' Matzah of Zion |publisher=[[Anti-Defamation League|ADL]] |url= http://www.adl.org/css/mix_blood_libel.asp|url-status= dead |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20110413063812/http://www.adl.org/css/mix_blood_libel.asp |archive-date= 13 April 2011 |access-date= 5 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tlass re-printed the book several times. Following the book's publication, Tlass told ''[[Der Spiegel]]'', that this accusation against Jews was valid and he also claimed that his book is "an historical study ... based on documents from France, Vienna and the [[American University in Beirut]]."&lt;ref name=adl/&gt;&lt;ref name=HNNblood&gt;[http://hnn.us/articles/664.html Blood Libel]  Judith Apter Klinghoffer, ''[[History News Network]]'', 19 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, the Egyptian newspaper ''[[Al-Ahram]]'' published a series of articles by [[Osama El-Baz]], a senior advisor to the then Egyptian President [[Hosni Mubarak]]. Among other things, Osama El-Baz explained the origins of the blood libel against the Jews. He said that [[Arabs]] and [[Muslim]]s have never been antisemitic, as a group, but he accepted the fact that a few Arab writers and media figures attack Jews "on the basis of the [[Racism|racist]] fallacies and myths that originated in [[Europe]]". He urged people not to succumb to "myths" such as the blood libel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author= Osama El-Baz |title= Al-Ahram Weekly Online, 2–8 January 2003 (Issue No. 619) |publisher= Weekly.ahram.org.eg |url= http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2003/619/focus.htm |access-date= 2010-01-23 |archive-date= 19 September 2009 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090919022746/http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2003/619/focus.htm |url-status= dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, on many occasions in modern times, blood libel stories have appeared in the state-sponsored media of a number of Arab and Muslim nations, as well as on their television shows and websites, and books which allege instances of Jewish blood libels are not uncommon there.&lt;ref&gt;Antisemitic blood libel in the modern world:
*In 1986, the Defense Minister of [[Syria]] [[Mustafa Tlass]] authored the book ''The Matzah of Zion''. The book renews the anti-Jewish ritual murder accusations of 1840 [[Damascus affair]] and alleges that ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]'' is a factual document. (Frankel, Jonathan. ''The Damascus Affair: "Ritual Murder", Politics, and the Jews in 1840'', pp. 418, 421. Cambridge University Press, 1997. {{ISBN|978-0-521-48396-4}})
* In 2001 an [[Egypt]]ian film company produced and aired a film titled ''Horseman Without a Horse'', partly based on Tlass's book.
* The Syrian TV series ''[[Ash-Shatat]]'' ("The Diaspora") depicts Jews engaging in a conspiracy to rule the world, murder Christian children, and use their blood to bake [[matzah]].
* [http://www.memri.org/report/en/0/0/0/0/0/177/1561.htm Iranian TV Blood Libel] 22 December 2005
*[[Faisal of Saudi Arabia|King Faisal]] of [[Saudi Arabia]] accused Jews of a blood libel in Paris. Gane S. Gerber (1986): ''History and hate: the dimensions of anti-Semitism''. [[Jewish Publication Society of America]]{{ISBN|0827602677}} p. 88
&lt;/ref&gt;
The blood libel was featured in a scene in the Syrian [[Syrian television series|TV series]] ''[[Ash-Shatat]]'', shown in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.adl.org/special_reports/protocols/protocols_recycled.html#.VhNkrPlVgoI Anti-Semitic Series airs on Arab Television] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150630002519/http://archive.adl.org/special_reports/protocols/protocols_recycled.html#.VhNkrPlVgoI |date=30 June 2015 }}, [[Anti Defamation League]], 9 January 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KHqXt_JNSt8 Clip] from ''[[Ash-Shatat]]'', [[MEMRI]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, Lebanese poet Marwan Chamoun, in an interview aired on [[Télé Liban]], referred to the "... slaughter of the priest Tomaso de Camangiano ... in 1840... in the presence of two rabbis in the heart of Damascus, in the home of a close friend of this priest, Daud Al-Harari, the head of the Jewish community of [[Damascus]]. After he was slaughtered, his blood was collected, and the two rabbis took it."&lt;ref&gt;[http://memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Page=archives&amp;Area=sd&amp;ID=SP145307 Lebanese Poet Marwan Chamoun: Jews Slaughtered Christian Priest in Damascus in 1840 and Used His Blood for Matzos] ([[Middle East Media Research Institute|MEMRI]] ''Special Dispatch Series – No. 1453'') 6 February 2007&lt;/ref&gt; A novel, ''[[Death of a Monk]]'', based on the Damascus affair, was published in 2004.

==See also==
* [[Blood atonement]]
* [[Blood curse]]
* [[Blood ritual]]
* [[Cake of Light]]
* [[Conspiracy theory]]
* [[Human cannibalism]]
* [[Kiddush#History of using white wine]]
* [[Moral panic]]
* [[OpIndia#Bihar human sacrifice claims]]
* [[QAnon#Child sex trafficking and satanic sacrifice]]
* [[Salem witch trials]]
* [[Satanic ritual abuse]]
* [[Sefer HaRazim]]
* [[Statute of Kalisz]], 13th-century Polish ducal decree offering Jews protection against blood libel, among others

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |last1=Bemporad |first1=Elissa |title=Legacy of Blood: Jews, Pogroms, and Ritual Murder in the Lands of the Soviets |date=2019 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-046647-3 |language=en}}
*{{Cite book|last = Dundes |first = Alan|year = 1991 |title = The Blood Libel Legend: A Casebook in Anti-Semitic Folklore |publisher = University of Wisconsin Press |isbn = 978-0-299-13114-2|url-access = registration|url = https://archive.org/details/bloodlibellegend00alan}}
* Hsia, R. Po-chia (1998) ''The Myth of Ritual Murder: Jews and Magic in Reformation Germany''. New Haven: Yale University Press. {{ISBN|0-300-04120-9}}
*{{cite book |last1=Kieval |first1=Hillel J.|authorlink=Hillel J. Kieval|title=Blood Inscriptions: Science, Modernity, and Ritual Murder at Europe's Fin de Siecle |date=2022 |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press |isbn=978-0-8122-9838-3 |language=en}}
* O'Brien, Darren (2011) ''The Pinnacle of Hatred: The Blood Libel and the Jews''. Jerusalem: Vidal Sassoon International Center for the Study of Antisemitism, Hebrew University Magnes Press. {{isbn|978-9654934770}}
*[[E. M. Rose|Rose, E. M.]] (2015) ''The Murder of William of Norwich: The Origins of the Blood Libel in Medieval Europe''. Oxford University Press {{ISBN|9780190219628}}
* {{cite book |first1=Robert |last1=Stacey |editor1-last=Maddicott |editor1-first=J. R. |editor2-last=Pallister |editor2-first=D. M. |title=The Medieval State: Essays Presented to James Campbell |date=2001 |location=London|publisher=The Hambledon Press |pages=163–77 |chapter=Anti-Semitism and the Medieval English State}}
* {{cite book |author1=David Stocker |title=Medieval Art and Architecture at Lincoln Cathedral |date=1986 |isbn=978-0-907307-14-3 |pages=109–117 |chapter=The Shrine of Little St Hugh|publisher=British Archaeological Association }}
*{{cite book |last1=Teter |first1=Magda |title=Blood Libel: On the Trail of an Antisemitic Myth |date=2020 |publisher=Harvard University Press |isbn=978-0-674-24355-2 |language=en}}
* [[Israel Yuval|Yuval, Israel Jacob]] (2006) ''Two Nations in Your Womb: Perceptions of Jews and Christians in Late Antiquity and the Middle Ages''. Berkeley: University of California Press. pp.&amp;nbsp;135–204

==External links==
{{wiktionary}}
{{commons category|Blood libel}}

{{Blood libel}}
{{Antisemitism topics}}{{Racism}}{{Discrimination}}{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Blood libel| ]]
[[Category:Anti-Judaism]]
[[Category:Antisemitic tropes]]
[[Category:Christianity and antisemitism]]
[[Category:Islam and antisemitism]]
[[Category:Christianity-related controversies]]
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Conspiracy theories involving Jews]]
[[Category:Propaganda legends]]
[[Category:Haematophagy|*]]
[[Category:Human sacrifice in folklore and mythology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>