<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020904130043|199717" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="4941" pageid="4941" ns="0" title="Blood libel"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-09-06T16:53:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The term &lt;b&gt;blood libel&lt;/b&gt; refers to allegations that Jews killed Christian children or infants and used their blood to make [[Passover]] [[matzoh]]s. These allegations first surfaced in the mediaeval period. All serious historians believe that there is no substance to the allegations. Although in past centuries they were widely held to be true, few people today in the West believe them (the exception being small groups of anti-Semites and Neo-Nazis). Zionist advocates have asserted that similar allegations of Jewish atrocities to children still widely circulate today in the Muslim and Arab world.

Although Jews have been the primary target of these sort of accusations in recent history, similar accusations have been made against a large variety of different groups throughout history.

In many cases, the blood libel served as a religious cult, the alleged victim being venerated as a Christian martyr. The first recorded blood libel cult was that of Saint William of Norwich, which originated in 1144. Another example of a blood libel cult was the cult of Anderl von Rinn, who was allegedly murdered by Jews in the year 1462, in the town of Rinn, Tyrol. Stories of his death, however, do not emerge until the 17th century, when the cult of Anderl was founded. The cult continued until it was officially prohibited in 1994 by the Bishop of Innsbruck. (source [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/rinn.html]).

The attitude of the Catholic church towards blood libel cults varied. The church sometimes opposed the blood libel cults, but it generally did little to stop the cults, and in some cases gave them clear approval. [[Pope Benedict XIV]] permitted the continuation of the cult of Anderl von Rinn as a local cult, but refused to canonize him as a saint. [[Pope Sixtus V]] cannonized one Simon of Trent, who was allegedly murdered by Jews in 1475. On the other hand, [[Pope Gregory X]] issued a letter rejecting the blood libel accusations (source [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/g10-jews.html]).

=== Modern day blood libels ===
The blood libel still exists today. The blood libel was resurrected in 1840s Syria.
[http://www.us-israel.org/jsource/anti-semitism/reaction.html Blood libel in 1840 Syria]

The blood libel exploded onto the international scene with the 1913 Beilis case in Russia.

Syrian Minister of Defense, Mustafa Tlass, authored a book entitled "The Matza of Zion", which states that in the 1800s at least some Syrian Jews ate babies, and did so as part of their religion. Zionist advocates have also alleged that in 1984 the Saudi Arabian delegate to the UN Human Rights Commission conference on religious tolerance, Marouf al-Dawalibi, publicly told the UN that "The Talmud says that if a Jew does not drink every year the blood of a non-Jewish man, he will be damned for eternity.

The Anti Defamation League has asserted that Egyptian Government newspapers regularly run newspaper articles presenting blood libel cases as facts, inciting hatred against Jews.

[http://www.adl.org/presrele/islme%5F62/3790%5F62.asp Anti-Defamation League condemns Egyptian blood libel]

Some have also reported that a modern form of the blood libel is widely spread on college campuses in the United States by Louis Farrakhan's [[Nation of Islam]] and the Khalid Muhammed's spin-off group, known as "The New Black Panthers". They allege that members of these group publicly teach that Jewish doctors are part of an international conspiracy to infect African-Americans with HIV, the virus that causes AIDS.

Others allege that many Palestinians have adopted this form of the blood libel, and that it is now widely taught amnong Palestinians that Jews are in a conspiracy to inject Arab children with the HIV virus. One example is the statement by by Ambassador Nabil Ramlawi, Permanent Observer of Palestine to the UN Commission on Human Rights, who allegedly testified in 1997 to the UN in Geneva that "the Israelis authorities have infected by injection 300 Palestinian children with the HIV virus during the years of the Intifadah."

See [[antisemitism]], [[Judaism]], [[Christianity]], [[Holocaust]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>