<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091102000453|323375428" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="4941" pageid="4941" ns="0" title="Blood libel"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-14T15:43:14Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Blood libels''' are false and sensationalized allegations that a person or group engages in [[human sacrifice]], often accompanied by the claim that the [[blood]] of the victims is used in various [[ritual]]s and/or acts of [[cannibalism]]. The alleged victims are often [[child sacrifice|children]].

Some of the best documented cases of blood libel focus upon accusations against [[Jew]]s, but many other groups have been accused throughout history, including [[Christianity|Christians]], [[Cathar]]s, [[Carthage|Carthaginian]]s, [[Knights Templar]], [[witches]], [[Wicca]]ns, Christian [[Christian heresy|heretics]], [[Romani people]], [[Mormons]], [[neopagan]]s, [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]], Africans, [[atheists]] and [[Communism|communists]]. {{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}

==Against Jews==
[[Image:Antisemitic-church-fresco.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Fresco]] in St Paul's Church in [[Sandomierz]], Poland, depicting blood libel]]
{{Main|Blood libel against Jews}}
The first recorded instance of a blood libel against the Jews was in the writings of [[Apion]], who claimed that certain Jews sacrificed Greek victims in the [[Temple of Jerusalem]]. After this, there are no known records of the blood libel brought against Jews until the 12th century legend surrounding [[William of Norwich]], first recorded in the [[Peterborough Chronicle]]. The accusation became more common afterward . In some subsequent cases, antisemitic blood libels served as the basis for a ''blood libel cult'', in which the alleged victim of human sacrifice was venerated as a Christian martyr. Many Jews have been killed as a result of blood libels, which continue up to the present day, with the [[Menahem Mendel Beilis|Beilis Trial]] in Russia and the [[Kielce pogrom]] in post-[[World War II]] Poland. Probably the most recent high profile claim is that from December 1984, when the [[Saudi Arabian]] delegate and President of the [[World Muslim Congress]] Dr. Ma'ruf al-Dawalibi, speaking before the UN [[Human Rights Commission]] conference on religious tolerance, stated 

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Jews have indeed been the victims of discriminations throughout the centuries. But why? Let them answer this question themselves. The [[Talmud]] says that any Jew who does not drink every year the blood of a non-Jew will be damned forever.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=i8gdMNJmpvUC&amp;pg=PA170&amp;dq=%22raphael+israeli%22+dawalibi&amp;ei=FeorSpWSIYPuzQSp87CmBw Israeli, p. 170]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=PoqeaUWscB0C&amp;pg=PA326&amp;dq=%22dan+cohn-sherbok%22+dawalibi&amp;ei=6OkrSrj0EojCyQTC9cSXBw Cohn-Sherbok, p. 326]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A thorough exploration of these various claims was carried out by a group of scholars and distinguished Jewish converts to [[Christianity]] from all parts of Europe convened by German emperor, [[Frederick II, Holy Roman Emperor|Frederick II]] which replied to the claims by stating:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Neither the Old nor the New Testament states that the Jews lust for human blood: on the contrary, it is expressly stated in the [[Bible]], in the [[laws of Moses]], and in the Jewish ordinances designated in Hebrew as the '[[Talmud]],' that they should not defile themselves with blood.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=1173&amp;letter=B&amp;search=TALMUD%20blood Blood Accusations by Richard Gottheil]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Against Christians==
During the first and second centuries, some [[Roman Empire|Roman]] commentators had various interpretations of the ritual of the [[Eucharist]] and related teachings. {{Citation needed|date=November 2008}} While celebrating the Eucharist, Christians drink red wine in response to the words "This is the blood of Christ". [[Propaganda]] arguing that the Christians literally drank blood based on their belief in [[transubstantiation]] was written and used to [[persecution of Christians|persecute Christians]]{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}. The Romans were highly suspicious of Christian [[adoption]]s of abandoned Roman babies and this was suggested as a possible source of the blood.{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}} 

In the [[Mandaeanism|Mandaean]] scripture, the [[Ginza Rba]], a supposed Christian group called the "Minunei" are accused of a blood libel against Jewish children: "They kill a Jewish child, they take his blood, they cook it in bread and they proffer it to them as food."&lt;ref&gt;Ginza Rba 9.1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Blood libels in the modern world==
Accusations of ritual murder have gradually disappeared from mainstream Christianity, and some child [[martyr]]s have been removed from the official Catholic [[calendar of saints]]. In the modern world, only radical groups and individuals advance accusations of ritual murder and blood libels.

One claim states that physicians in the [[People's Republic of China]] who perform abortions consider the fetus a delicacy and eat it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Fetus Feast |publisher=[[Snopes|Snopes.com]] |url=http://www.snopes.com/horrors/cannibal/fetus.asp |date=2007-02-03 |accessdate=2007-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The story, reported from [[Hong Kong]] by [[Bruce Gilley]], was investigated by Senator [[Jesse Helms]], and gruesome artwork reminiscent of traditional depictions of blood libel was featured in several [[pro-life]] campaigns.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jesus21.com/poppydixon/sex/chinese_eating_fetuses.html Chinese Eating Fetuses: Christian Pornography&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The only use for "human fetal tissue"  is in the medical research field, particularly [[stem cell research]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www1.od.nih.gov/oir/sourcebook/oversight/human-tissue-use.htm |title=Human-tissue-use |date=2000-09-20 |publisher=Office of Human Subjects Research, United States National Institute of Health |accessdate=2007-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nesu.mphy.lu.se/nectar/eth.1.html |title=ETHICAL GUIDELINES FOR THE USE OF HUMAN EMBRYONIC OR FETAL TISSUE FOR EXPERIMENTAL AND CLINICAL NEUROTRANSPLANTATION AND RESEARCH |publisher=Network of European CNS Transplantation and Restoration |date=1996-02-21 |accessdate=2007-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:GoyaBrownComparison.png|left|300px|thumb|Comparison of Brown's cartoon (right) and Goya's painting (left).]]
Many Jewish groups were shocked in 2003 by the British newspaper ''[[The Independent]]'''s publication of a cartoon depicting Ariel Sharon eating a baby.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.somethingjewish.co.uk/articles/627__grotesque__cartoon_.htm |title="Grotesque" cartoon award |first=Leslie |last=Bunder |publisher=Something Jewish |accessdate=2007-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Israeli government complained to the [[Press Complaints Commission]] that the cartoon alluded to the blood libel of Jews eating the children of Christians; [[Dave Brown (UK cartoonist)|Dave Brown]], the author, responded by saying that the cartoon was in fact inspired by [[Francisco de Goya]]'s painting ''[[Saturn Devouring His Son]]'' and was not anti-Semitic in intent. The PCC accepted Brown's argument, stating "There is nothing inherently anti-semitic about the Goya image or about the myth of Saturn devouring his children, which has been used previously to satirise other politicians accused of sacrificing their own 'children' for political purposes".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Independent cartoon cleared of anti-semitism |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/israel/Story/0,2763,961357,00.html |publisher=[[Guardian Unlimited]] |first=Ciar |last=Bryne |date=2003-05-22 |accessdate=2007-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The cartoon ultimately earned Brown the British [[Political Cartoon Society]]'s Political Cartoon of the Year award.

Italian Prime Minister [[Silvio Berlusconi]], during his March 2006 failed bid for re-election, said that communists had a history of boiling babies.&lt;ref name = Berlusconi&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/world/berlusconis-communist-claims/2006/03/27/1143330959861.html |title=Berlusconi's communist claims |publisher=[[Sydney Morning Herald]] |date=2006-03-27 |accessdate=2007-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  "I have been accused many times of saying that communists eat babies," said Berlusconi at a rally of his ''[[Forza Italia]]'' party.&lt;ref name = Berlusconi/&gt; "Go and read the [[The Black Book of Communism|Black Book on Communism]] and you'll find that in Mao's China they didn't eat babies but they boiled them to fertilise the fields."&lt;ref name = Berlusconi/&gt;  Despite Berlusconi's 2006 denial that he has ever said that 'communists eat babies,' in the 2001 campaign, Berlusconi said "I can organise a conference in which I will prove that communists have really eaten babies and done even worse things."&lt;ref name = Berlusconi/&gt;

In July 2007, American [[Michael Yon]] reported that Lieutenant [[David Wallach]], an Arabic translator, had told him about an Iraqi official's allegations that [[Al-Qaeda in Iraq]] has baked a young boy and served the boy's body to his family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.michaelyon-online.com/wp/baqubah-update-05-july-2007.htm |publisher=[[Michael Yon]] |title=Baqubah Update: 05 July 2007 |date=2007-07-05 |accessdate=2007-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These claims were later repeated in articles by the conservative American website ''[[World Net Daily]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=[[World Net Daily]] |url=http://www.worldnetdaily.com/news/article.asp?ARTICLE_ID=56723 |title=More cases of terrorists 'baking' children cited |date=2007-07-19 |accessdate=2007-10-20 |first=Bob |last=Unruh}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wnd.com/news/article.asp?ARTICLE_ID=56643 |title=Report: Al-Qaida bakes little boys |publisher=[[World Net Daily]] |date=2007-07-13 |accessdate=2007-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Antisemitic accusations of ritual murder can still be found in [[Islamism|Islamist]] propaganda and in state-sponsored media published in a number of Muslim nations.&lt;ref&gt;Examples of these antisemitic accusations in the modern Muslim world include:
*In 1986, Defense Minister of [[Syria]] [[Mustafa Tlass]] authored the book ''The Matzah Of Zion''. The book renews the anti-Jewish ritual murder accusations of 1840 [[Damascus affair]] and alleges that ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]'' is a factual document. (Frankel, Jonathan. ''The Damascus Affair: "Ritual Murder," Politics, and the Jews in 1840'', pp. 418, 421. Cambridge University Press, 1997. ISBN 978-0-521-48396-4) 
* In 2001 an [[Egypt]]ian film company produced and aired a film called ''Horseman Without a Horse'', partly based on Tlass's book. 
* The TV series ''Ash-Shatat'' ("The Diaspora"), sponsored by the Syrian government, depicts Jews engaging in a conspiracy to rule the world, murder Christian children, and use their blood to bake [[matzah]]. ([http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/rsd/rsddocview.html?tbl=RSDCOI&amp;id=4226d98c19&amp;count=1 U.S. Department of State Country Report on Human Rights Practices 2004 - Syria] February 2005, [http://domino.un.org/unispal.nsf/85255db800470aa485255d8b004e349a/3911b1e58df0bb7485256e4d0057a10c!OpenDocument Written statement submitted by the Association for World Education, a non-governmental organization on the Roster] Racism, Racial Discrimination, Xenophobia and All Forms of Discrimination. Question of Violation of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms in Any Part of the World. Promotion and Protection of Human Rights. UN Commission on Human Rights. 60th session. E/CN.4/2004/NGO/5. 10 February 2004)
* [http://memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Page=archives&amp;Area=sd&amp;ID=SP105305 Iranian TV Blood Libel] December 20, 2005
*[[Faisal of Saudi Arabia|King Faisal]] of [[Saudi Arabia]] accused Jews of a blood libel in Paris. (Gane S. Gerber (1986): ''History and hate: the dimensions of anti-Semitism''. [[Jewish Publication Society of America]]ISBN 0827602677 p. 88
* [http://www.cnsnews.com/ViewForeignBureaus.asp?Page=\ForeignBureaus\archive\200412\FOR20041223c.html Israel Is 'Stealing Palestinian Children's Eyes,' Iranian TV Series Says] by Susan Jones (CNSNews) December 23, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1990s, a number of publications by the [[Russian Orthodox Church]], as well as radio and TV broadcasts in [[Belarus]] revived the cult of child saint [[Gavriil Belostoksky]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fsumonitor.com/stories/091697aa.shtml "Blood Libel" Documentary Broadcast in Belarus] - The Union of Councils for Soviet Jews (UCSJ) Action Alert - campaign against antisemitic programming on state TV. September 16, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; The revival of the cult was cited as a dangerous expression of antisemitism in international reports on human rights and religious freedoms&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.4humanrights.org/by/eng/reports/relig2003.shtml Belarus. International Religious Freedom Report 2003] Released by the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2006/71370.htm Belarus. International Religious Freedom Report 2006] Released by the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foreignaffairs.house.gov/archives/108/91075d.pdf Annual Report on International Religious Freedom 2004]&lt;/ref&gt; and were passed to the [[UNHCR]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/home/RSDCOI/450fb0b128.html UNHCR - U.S. Department of State Annual Report on International Religious Freedom for 2006 - Belarus&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/rsd/rsddocview.html?tbl=RSDCOI&amp;id=450fb0b128&amp;count=1 UNHCR - Refworld Redirect&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{See|Aftonbladet-Israel controversy}}

In August 2009, ''[[Aftonbladet]]'', a leading Swedish tabloid, published an op-ed by [[Donald Boström]] called "They plunder the organs of our sons", implying that Israeli soldiers are abducting Palestinians to steal their organs at the [[Abu Kabir Forensic Institute]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aftonbladet.se/kultur/article5691805.ab]&lt;/ref&gt; The article prompted furious condemnation and accusations of an anti-Semitic blood libel from the Foreign Ministry of Israel, evolving to a diplomatic controversy between Israel and Sweden when the latter declined to officially condemn the article with reference to freedom of the press.

==See also==
*[[Vampirism]]
*[[Witch-hunt]]
*[[Host desecration]]
*[[Satanic ritual abuse]]
*[[Aftonbladet-Israel controversy]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
===General===
*Susanna Buttaroni, Stanislaw Musial: ''Ritualmord.'' Böhlau Verlag 2002, ISBN 3-205-77028-5 (German)
*Rainer Erb: ''Die Legende vom Ritualmord.'' Metropol 1993, ISBN 3-926893-15-X (German)
*Hannelore Fieg: ''Ritualmord und Satanskultbeschuldigungen in Spätantike, Mittelalter und früher Neuzeit. Christen und Juden, Ketzer und Hexen'', Diploma thesis Universität Innsbruck 2000 (German)
*Gerhard Muller (Hrsg.): Theologische Realenzyklopädie Band 29, ''Religionspsychologie - Samaritaner''. Walter de Gruyter, 1998, ISBN 3-11-016127-3 (entry ''Ritualmord'', pg. 253–265) (German)

===Jews===
*[[Alan Dundes]]: ''The Blood Libel Legend: A Casebook in Anti-Semitic Folklore.'' The University of Wisconsin Press, 1992, ISBN 0-299-13110-6
*[[Jules Isaac]], ''Die Genesis des Antisemitismus'', Wien: Europa Verlag, 1969 (German)
*Stefan Rohrbacher, Michael Schmidt: ''Judenbilder. Kulturgeschichte antijüdischer Mythen und antisemitischer Vorurteile.'' Rowohlt, Reinbek 1991, ISBN 3-499-55498-4 (pg. 269–291: ''Ritualmord und Hostienfrevel''; pg. 304–368: ''Die Barbarei längst verflossener Jahrhunderte'')
*Johannes T. Groß: ''Ritualmordbeschuldigungen gegen Juden im Deutschen Kaiserreich (1871–1914)'' Berlin: Metropol, 2002. ISBN 3-932482-84-0
*Alexander Baron: ''Jewish Ritual Murder: Anti-semitic Fabrication or Urban Legend? Anglo-Hebrew Publishing.'' 1994, ISBN 1898318360 
*John M. McCulloh: ''Jewish Ritual Murder: William of Norwich, Thomas of Monmouth, and the Early Dissemination of the Myth'' In: Speculum, Vol. 72, No. 3 (Juli 1997), S. 698–740
*Ronnie Po-Chia Hsia: ''The Myth of Ritual Murder: Jews and Magic in Reformation Germany.'' Yale University Press, 1990, ISBN 0-300-04746-0 (English)

===Case studies===
*Schmoger, Karl (1974) ''The Life of Anna Katherina Emmerich'': Rockford, Illinois: Tan Books and Publishing: 1974: Volume 1: ISBN 0-89555-059-8

==External links==
* [http://www.dinur.org/resources/resourceCategoryDisplay.aspx?categoryid=455&amp;rsid=478 Resources &gt; Medieval Jewish History &gt; Blood Libels] 
* [http://www.adl.org/presrele/islme%5F62/3790%5F62.asp Anti-Defamation League condemns Egyptian blood libel]
* [http://www.us-israel.org/jsource/anti-semitism/reaction.html Blood libel in 1840 Syria]
* [http://www.religioustolerance.org/jud_blib1.htm Blood Libel, Host Desecration, and other Myths]
* [http://www.independent.co.uk/story.jsp?story=350273 The Independent] – info on ''Horseman Without a Horse''
* [http://www.snopes.com/religion/blood.htm Blood Feast] Snopes.com Info page
* [http://www.engageonline.org.uk/journal/index.php?journal_id=12&amp;article_id=42  Anthony Julius: 'On Blood Libels' on the Engage website]
*Stevenson, Mark (2006) [http://www.livescience.com/history/human_sacrifice_050123.html "Evidence May Back Human Sacrifice Claims"], Associated Press news story, accessed September 18, 2006. {{Dead link|date=March 2009}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Blood Libel}}
[[Category:Blood libel| ]]
[[Category:Religion and violence]]
[[Category:Crimes involving Satanism or the occult]]
[[Category:Antisemitic attacks and incidents]]

{{Link FA|de}}
[[bg:Кръвна обида]]
[[de:Ritualmordlegende]]
[[es:Libelo de sangre contra los judíos]]
[[fr:Légende des crimes rituels]]
[[it:Accusa del sangue]]
[[lt:Kruvinų ritualų mitai]]
[[pt:Libelo de sangue]]
[[ru:Кровавый навет]]
[[uk:Кривавий наклеп]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>