<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112214356|87406960" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="4941" pageid="4941" ns="0" title="Blood libel"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-12T21:44:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Blood libels''' are unfounded allegations that a particular group kills people as a form of [[human sacrifice]], and uses their [[blood]] in various [[ritual]]s. The alleged victims are often [[child sacrifice|children]].

[[Jew]]s are the most common target of blood libels, but many other groups have been accused, including [[Christianity|Christian]]s, [[Cathar]]s, [[Carthage|Carthaginian]]s, [[Knights Templar]], [[Witches]], Christian [[heresy|heretics]], [[Roma (people)|Roma]], [[Wiccan]]s, [[Druidry|Druid]]s, [[neopagan]]s, [[satanic ritual abuse|Satanists]], and [[Evangelicalism|evangelical]] [[Protestant]] [[missionaries]].

== Blood libel against followers of Ancient Greek religion ==
When the [[Christianization]] of Greece occurred, there was an attempt to portray all sacrifices as blood sacrifices, but contrary to popular Christian myth sacrifices to the Greek gods were typically in the forms of wealth. Human blood sacrifices were exceedingly rare, and in most Greek cities, they were illegal. Early Christians spread myths about Christian children being abducted and having their esophaguses slit in various temples. Such myths are similar to the blood libel accusations against Jews. Virtuvian blood sacrifices were seen by the Greek people as barbaric and laws against them were believed to be part of what separated the Greeks from those they considered barbarians, even after Romanization occurred.

== Blood libel against Jews ==
{{main|Blood libel against Jews}}

Blood libels against the Jews were a common form of [[anti-Semitism]] during the Middle Ages, though there is no ritual involving human blood in Jewish law or custom.  Though the first recorded instance was in the writings of [[Apion]], who claimed that the Jews sacrificed Greek victims in the Temple, there are no existent records of the blood libel against the Jews from that period until the legend surrounding [[William of Norwich]] in the 12th century, but the libel afterward became an increasingly common accusation.  In many cases, anti-Semitic blood libels served as the basis for a ''blood libel cult'', in which the alleged victim of human sacrifice was worshipped as a Christian martyr, but the claim has pre-Christian origins. Many Jews were killed as a result of false blood libels, which continued into the 20th century, with the [[Menahem Mendel Beilis|Beilis Trial]] in Russia and the [[Kielce pogrom]] in Poland, and the persistence of blood libel stories in the Arab world.

The blood libel resurfaced in the work of [[Anne Catherine Emmerich]] (1774–1824), a German Catholic nun and alleged visionary, when she commented (pp 547–8) in her biography that an elderly Jewish woman had told her that the blood libel was "true" and that Jews "did" steal Christian children for use in ritual sacrifices.

== Blood libel against Christians ==
During the [[1st century|first]] and [[2nd century|second]] centuries, some [[Roman Empire|Roman]] commentators had various interpretations of the ritual of the [[Eucharist]] and related teachings. While celebrating the Eucharist, Christians drink red wine in response to the words "This is the blood of Christ". [[Propaganda]] arguing that the Christians literally drank blood based on their belief in [[transubstantiation]] was written and used to [[persecution of Christians|persecute Christians]]. Romans were highly suspicious of Christian [[adoption]]s of abandoned Roman babies and this was suggested as a possible source of the blood.

In the [[Mandaeanism|Mandaean]] scripture, the [[Ginza Rba]], a purportedly Christian group called the "Minunei" are accused of it against the Jews: "They kill a Jewish child, they take his blood, they cook it in bread and they proffer it to them as food." (Ginza Rba 9.1).

==Contemporary blood libel myths in the West==
Accusations of ritual murder are being advanced by different groups to this day. In the United States, this is especially noticeable in certain branches of the anti-[[abortion]] movement, which has produced numerous charges against doctors performing the procedure.[http://poisonevercure.150m.com/Witchcraft/AbortionISWitchcraft.htm]

One claim stated that physicians in the [[People's Republic of China]] who perform abortions consider the fetus a delicacy and eat it.  The story, reported from [[Hong Kong]] by [[Bruce Gilley]], was investigated by Senator [[Jesse Helms]], and gruesome artwork reminiscent of traditional depictions of blood libel was featured in several anti-abortion campaigns.[http://www.jesus21.com/poppydixon/sex/chinese_eating_fetuses.html] The only use for "human fetal tissue"  is in the medical research field, particularly [[stem cell research]].[http://www1.od.nih.gov/oir/sourcebook/oversight/human-tissue-use.htm][http://www.nesu.mphy.lu.se/nectar/eth.1.html]

Another contemporary blood libel in the United States alleges, falsely, that both neopagans and Satanists use human blood, sexual abuse, or ritual murder, especially of children, in their rituals. Often [[Satanism]], all of the diverse [[neopagan]] religions, the role playing game [[Dungeons &amp; Dragons]], and sometimes Roman Catholicism and liberal or non-fundamentalist Christian denominations, are portrayed as expressions of one monolithic and ancient global conspiracy of Satan-worshippers. [[Mike Warnke]] (''The Satan Seller''), [[Bill Schnoebelen]] (''Wicca: Satan's Little White Lie''), [[Lawrence Pazder]] and [[Michelle Smith (author)|Michelle Smith]] (''[[Michelle Remembers]]''), [[Jon Watkins]][http://www.exposingsatanism.org/witchcraft.htm], [[Bill Pricer]], and [[Ken Wooden]] (''Child Lures'') are some of the voices of these libels.

Many Jewish groups were shocked by the publication in 2003 by the British newspaper [[The Independent]] of a cartoon depicting Ariel Sharon eating a baby.[http://www.somethingjewish.co.uk/articles/627__grotesque__cartoon_.htm] The Israeli government complained to the [[Press Complaints Commission]] that the cartoon alluded to the blood libel of Jews eating Christian children; Dave Brown, the author, responded that the cartoon was in fact inspired by [[Francisco de Goya]]'s painting ''[[Saturn Devouring his Son]]''[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Image:Goya_-_Saturno_devorando_a_su_hijo.jpg] and was not anti-Semitic in intent. The PCC accepted Brown's argument, stating "There is nothing inherently anti-semitic about the Goya image or about the myth of Saturn devouring his children, which has been used previously to satirise other politicians accused of sacrificing their own 'children' for political purposes".[http://www.guardian.co.uk/israel/Story/0,2763,961357,00.html] The cartoon ultimately earned Brown the British [[Political Cartoon Society]]'s Political Cartoon of the Year award.

Italian Prime Minister [[Silvio Berlusconi]], in his failed bid for re-election in March 2006, said communists have a history of boiling babies. "I have been accused many times of saying communists eat babies," said Berlusconi at a rally of his ''[[Forza Italia]]'' party. "Go and read the black book on communism and you'll find that under Mao's China they didn't eat babies but they boiled them to fertilise the fields." Despite Berlusconi's 2006 denial that he has ever said that 'communists eat babies,' in the 2001 campaign, Berlusconi said "I can organise a conference in which I will prove communists have really eaten babies and done even worse things."[http://www.smh.com.au/news/world/berlusconis-communist-claims/2006/03/27/1143330959861.html]

== The decline of belief in ritual murder ==

Belief in ritual murder has gradually disappeared from mainstream Christianity, and child-martyrs have been purged from the official Catholic calendar of saints.  Nevertheless, similar accusations are still being made by some Muslim groups against the Jews, and the same accusations were defended by [[Nazism]] and related movements in the twentieth century.

== See also ==

*[[Vampirism]]
*[[Witch hunt]]
*[[Host desecration]]
*[[Child cannibalism]]

==Bibliography==
&lt;references/&gt;
*Schmoger, Karl (1974) ''The Life of Anna Katherina Emmerich'': Rockford, Illinois: Tan Books and Publishing: 1974: Volume 1: ISBN 0-89555-059-8
*Stevenson, Mark (2006) [http://www.livescience.com/history/human_sacrifice_050123.html "Evidence May Back Human Sacrifice Claims"], Associated Press news story, accessed September 18, 2006.

== External links ==
*[http://www.dinur.org/resources/resourceCategoryDisplay.aspx?categoryid=455&amp;rsid=478 Resources &gt; Medieval Jewish History &gt; Blood Libels] 
* [http://www.adl.org/presrele/islme%5F62/3790%5F62.asp Anti-Defamation League condemns Egyptian blood libel]
* [http://www.us-israel.org/jsource/anti-semitism/reaction.html Blood libel in 1840 Syria]
* [http://www.religioustolerance.org/jud_blib1.htm Blood Libel, Host Desecration, and other Myths] (on religioustolerance.org)
* [http://www.independent.co.uk/story.jsp?story=350273 The Independent] – info on ''Horseman Without a Horse''
* [http://www.snopes.com/religion/blood.htm Blood Feast] Snopes.com Info page
* [http://memri.org/bin/media.cgi?ID=114704 Updated Blood Libel in Mideast Media]
* [http://www.discord.org/~lippard/jetrep.html The JET report on murerous and cannabalistic Satanist allegations in the Broxtowe child abuse case.]
* [http://www.engageonline.org.uk/journal/index.php?journal_id=12&amp;article_id=42  Anthony Julius: 'On Blood Libels' on the Engage website]

[[Category:Moral panics]]
[[Category:Hoaxes]]
[[Category:Blood libel| ]]

{{Link FA|he}}

[[es:Libelo de sangre contra los judíos]]
[[it:Accusa del sangue]]
[[he:עלילת דם]]
[[lt:Kruvinų ritualų mitai]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>