<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051111160037|28033128" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="398489" pageid="398489" ns="0" title="Sectarianism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-12T01:40:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup-date|September 2005}}

'''Sectarianism''' refers (usually [[pejorative]]ly) to a rigid adherence to a particular [[sect]] or party or denomination. It often implies discrimination, denunciation, or violence against those outside the sect. The term is most often used to refer to religious sectarianism, involving conflict between members of different religions or denominations of the same religion. It is also frequently used to refer to political sectarianism, generally on the part of a tight-knit political faction or party.

Sectarianism may, in the abstract, be characterized by dogmatism and inflexibility; sentimental or axiomatic adherence to an idea, belief or tradition; and idealism that provides a sense of continuity, orientation, and certainty. As a pejorative term, accusations of sectarianism may sometimes be used to demonize an opposing group and thus serve as a convenient ploy to evade taking what somebody says or does seriously. 

The ideological underpinnings of attitudes and behaviours labelled as sectarian are extraordinarily varied. Members of a religious group may feel that their own salvation requires aggressively seeking converts from other groups; adherents of a given faction may believe that for the achievement of their own political or religious project their opponents must be purged. Sometimes a group feeling itself to be under economic or political pressure will attack members of another group thought to be responsible for its own decline. At other times, sectarianism may be the expression of a group's [[nationalist]]ic or cultural ambitions, or cynically exploited to serve an individual demagogue's ambition. 

In all cases, there is a real or felt opposition between 'Us' and 'Them', between insiders and outsiders. Sectarianism may take the form of hatred and fear of an outside sect or group. In such cases, sectarianism does not require a strong sense of religious belief, as much as a sense of group belonging.

A sectarian conflict usually refers to conflict along religious and political lines such as the conflicts between between [[Shia]] and [[Sunni]] [[Muslim]]s, or between [[Catholics]] and [[Protestants]] in [[Ulster]] and western [[Scotland]]. A sectarian conflict may also refer to general philosophical or political conflict between different schools of thought.  Non-sectarians espouse that free association and tolerance of different beliefs are the cornerstone to successful peaceful human interaction.

==Religious sectarianism==

Religious sectarianism may be found, in varying forms and degrees, wherever religious sects (or their members) are in competition. In many regions, [[Roman Catholic]]s and [[Protestant]]s have been in fierce conflict &amp;ndash; one contemporary example of this is in [[Ireland]] and its [[Irish diaspora|diaspora]]. Within [[Islam]], there has been conflict at various periods between Sunnis and Shias; contrary to the majority Muslim opinion, certain Sunni sects inspired by [[Wahhabism]] and other ideologies have declared Shias (and sometimes mainstream Sunnis) to be [[heresy|heretics]] and/or [[apostasy|apostates]].

===Ireland===
:''See also: [[Troubles|the Troubles]], [[Demographics and politics of Northern Ireland]]''

Since the [[17th century]], there has been sectarian conflict of varying intensity in [[Ireland]]. Since the [[Irish Free State]] became independent in [[1922]], this has been particularly intense in [[Northern Ireland]]. Irish emigration has taken this conflict to other lands, including western [[Scotland]] (see [[religious rivalry in Glasgow]]), [[Newfoundland]], [[Canada]]'s [[Maritime provinces]], [[New York State]], [[Ontario]], [[Liverpool]], and elsewhere. See also [[Know-Nothings]] for anti-Catholic sentiment in the [[United States]].

===Persecution of Protestants by Catholics===
In Catholic countries, Protestants have historically been persecuted as [[heresy|heretics]]. For example, the substantial Protestant population of [[France]] (the [[Huguenot]]s) was expelled from the kingdom in the [[1680s]] following the [[revocation of the Edict of Nantes]]. In [[Spain]], the [[Spanish Inquisition|Inquisition]] sought to root out not only Protestantism but also [[crypto-Jews]] and crypto-Muslims (''[[morisco]]s''); elsewhere the [[Inquisition|Papal Inquisition]] held similar goals.

===Persecution of Catholics by Protestants===
In places where Protestantism is the majority or 'official' religion, there have been examples of Catholics being persecuted.  In countries where The [[Reformation]] was successful, this often lay in the perception that Catholics retained allegience to a 'foreign' power ([[the Papacy]]), causing them to be regarded with suspicion. Sometimes this mistrust manifested itself in Catholics being subjected to restrictions and discrimination, which itself led to further conflict. For example, before [[Catholic Emancipation]] in 1829, Catholics were forbidden from voting, running for office or buying land in Ireland. 

Nowadays, bigotry and discrimination in employment usually only remains in a few places where 'strong' forms of Protestantism (such as [[Calvinism]] or [[Presbyterianism]]) are the norm, or in poor areas with a long history of sectarian violence and tension, such as [[Northern Ireland]].  In places where more 'moderate' forms (such as [[Anglicanism]] / [[Episcopalianism]]) prevail, the two traditions do not become polarized against each other, and usually co-exist peacefully. However, in western [[Scotland]], where many people have some Irish ancestry, sectarianism can frequently be found between Catholics and Protestants.

===South Asian communalism===
:''Main article: [[Communalism (South Asia)]]''

In [[India]], sectarianism is known as '''[[communalism (South Asia)|communalism]]''', which refers particularly to conflict between the [[Hindu]] and [[Islam in India|Muslim]] communities. It can also refer to Hindu/[[Sikh]] conflict and Hindu/[[Christianity in India|Christian]] conflicts.

Violence in [[Sri Lanka]] between the [[Tamil]], [[Sinhalese]], and [[Islam in Sri Lanka|Muslim]] communities often has heavy sectarian overtones.

In [[Pakistan]], there have been many sectarian attacks between [[Sunni]]s and [[Shia]]s, and between Sunnis and [[Ahmadiyya|Ahmadis]].

===Sectarianism in Iraq===
:''Main article: [[Sectarian violence in Iraq]]''

Iraq's Shia population was persecuted during the presidency of [[Saddam Hussein]], and certain elements of the [[Iraqi insurgency]] have made a point of targeting Shias in sectarian attacks.

===Ethnic conflict in the Balkans===
:''See also: [[History of Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[Yugoslavia#Breakup]]''

The civil wars in the Balkans which followed the [[breakup of Yugoslavia]] have been heavily tinged with sectarianism. [[Croats]] and [[Slovenes]] have traditionally been Catholic, [[Serbs]] and [[Macedonian Slavs|Macedonians]] [[Eastern Orthodox]], and [[Bosniaks]] and (for the most part) [[Albanians]] Muslim. Religious affiliation served as a marker of group identity in this conflict, despite relatively low rates of religious practice and belief among these various groups after decades of [[communism]].

===Christian/Muslim conflict in West Africa===
In certain [[West Africa]]n countries, particularly [[Nigeria]], competition between Muslims and Christians has exploded into severe violence.

===Sectarianism within Judaism===
Sectarianism also exists between orthodox and reform Jews, with orthodox Jews often characterising reform Jews as being non-religious, disobeying the Torah, rarely attending shul and adopting semi-Christian styles of worship. Reform Jews, on the other hand, often view the orthodox as being intolerant of them and other religions, placing legalistic rules such as the observance of the Sabbath above ethical obligations, being cult-like and hostile to change.

===Anti-Semitism===
:''Main article: [[Anti-Semitism]]''

Anti-Semitism has traditionally been the most widespread variety of sectarianism in Europe. However, this form of prejudice is not wholly religious in nature, as can be seen by the racial policies of the Nazis, who could be said to be more concerned with the "contamination" of Aryan blood than with the Jewish religion itself, and the experiences of Marranos who were treated with suspicion several generations after their families had converted to Christianity. 

==Political sectarianism==
Political sectarianism differs from religious sectarianism in that political affinity is usually more likely to be elective, as opposed to hereditary, than is religious affinity. In the political realm, the term sectarian is generally used to refer to the tendency of political movements to splinter into mutually antagonistic factions. Various [[Trotskyist]] formations, for example, may accuse each other of sectarianism and/or be perceived by outsiders to be sectarian. The same phenomenon may be observed across the political spectrum, to varying degrees, wherever a strong priority is placed on party loyalty and [[party discipline]].

Political sectarianism among [[Zealot|Judaean nationalists]] was parodied by [[Monty Python]] in ''[[The Life of Brian]]''.

==See also==
*[[Sectarian violence]]
*[[Cult]]
*[[sect]]

[[Category:Religious faiths, traditions, and movements]]
[[fr:Méthode des sectes]]
{{reli-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>