<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181105202112|867452053" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="398489" pageid="398489" ns="0" title="Sectarianism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-25T19:31:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Sekumname1525 Chaldiran battle.jpg|210px|thumb|Sectarian battle between the [[Sunni]] [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] and [[Shia]] [[Safavid]] empire at the [[Battle of Chaldiran]], 1514.]]
{{about|sectarianism as conflict between groups|sectarianism as a characteristic of sects|sect}}
'''Sectarianism''' is a form of [[bigotry]], [[discrimination]], or [[hatred]] arising from attaching relations of inferiority and superiority to differences between subdivisions within a group. Common examples are [[Religious denomination|denomination]]s of a [[religion]], [[ethnic identity]], [[Social class|class]], or [[region]] for citizens of a state and [[Political faction|faction]]s of a [[political movement]].

The [[ideological]] underpinnings of attitudes and behaviours labelled as sectarian are extraordinarily varied. Members of a religious, national or political group may believe that their own salvation, or the success of their particular objectives, requires aggressively seeking converts from other groups; adherents of a given faction may believe that for the achievement of their own political or religious project their internal opponents must be converted or purged.

Sometimes a group that is under economic or political pressure will kill or attack members of another group which it regards as responsible for its own decline. It may also more rigidly define the definition of orthodox belief within its particular group or organization, and expel or excommunicate those who do not support this new found clarified definition of political or religious [[orthodoxy]]. In other cases, dissenters from this orthodoxy will secede from the orthodox organisation and proclaim themselves as practitioners of a reformed belief system, or holders of a perceived former orthodoxy. At other times, sectarianism may be the expression of a group's [[nationalist]]ic or cultural ambitions, or exploited by [[demagogue]]s. 

The phrase "sectarian conflict" usually refers to violent conflict along religious or political lines such as the conflicts between [[Irish Nationalism|Nationalists]] and [[Unionism in Ireland|Unionists]] in [[Northern Ireland]] (religious and class-divisions may play major roles as well). It may also refer to general philosophical, political disparity between different schools of thought such as that between [[Shia Islam|Shia]] and [[Sunni Islam|Sunni]] [[Muslim]]s. Non-sectarians espouse that free association and tolerance of different beliefs are the cornerstone to successful peaceful human interaction. They espouse political and religious [[Pluralism (political philosophy)|pluralism]].

While sectarianism is often labelled as 'religious' and/ or 'political', the reality of a sectarian situation is usually much more complex.  In its most basic form sectarianism has been defined as, 'the existence, within a locality, of two or more divided and actively competing communal identities, resulting in a strong sense of dualism which unremittingly transcends commonality, and is both culturally and physically manifest.'&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Liverpool Sectarianism: The Rise and Demise|last=Roberts|first=Keith Daniel|publisher=Liverpool University Press|year=2017|isbn=978-1-78694-010-0|location=Liverpool|pages=19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious sectarianism==
[[File:Orange Riot 1871 crop.jpg|thumb|right|250px|In 1871, New York's [[Orange Riots]] were incited by Irish Protestants. 63 citizens, mostly Irish Catholics, were massacred in the resulting police-action.]]
Wherever people of different religions live in close proximity to each other, religious sectarianism can often be found in varying forms and degrees. In some areas, religious sectarians (for example Protestant and Catholic [[Christians]]) {{as of | 2010 | alt = now}} exist peacefully side-by-side for the most part, although these differences have resulted in violence, death, and outright warfare as recently as the 1990s. Probably the best-known example in recent times were [[The Troubles]].

Catholic-Protestant sectarianism has also been a factor in U.S. presidential campaigns. Prior to [[John F. Kennedy]], only one Catholic ([[Al Smith]]) had ever been a major party presidential nominee, and he had been solidly defeated largely because of claims based on his Catholicism. JFK chose to tackle the sectarian issue head-on during the West Virginia primary, but that only sufficed to win him barely enough Protestant votes to eventually win the presidency by one of the narrowest margins ever.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jfklibrary.org/JFK/JFK-in-History/JFK-and-Religion.aspx|title=John F. Kennedy and Religion|publisher=|accessdate=29 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within [[Islam]], there has been conflict at various periods between [[Sunni Islam|Sunnis]] and [[Shia Islam|Shias]];  Shi'ites consider Sunnis to be damned, due to their refusal to accept the first Caliph as [[Ali]] and accept all following descendants of him as infallible and divinely guided. Many Sunni religious leaders, including those inspired by [[Wahhabism]] and other ideologies have declared Shias to be [[Heresy|heretics]] or [[Apostasy|apostates]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/7181042.stm | work=BBC News | title=Lahore bomb raises sectarian questions | date=January 10, 2008 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
{{See also|The Troubles|Balkanization}}
{{Original research|section|date=July 2016}}
[[File:La masacre de San Bartolomé, por François Dubois.jpg|thumb|Painting of the [[St. Bartholomew's Day Massacre]], an event in the [[French Wars of Religion]]]]
Long before the Reformation, dating back to the 12th century, there has been sectarian conflict of varying intensity in Ireland. This sectarianism is connected to a degree with [[nationalism]]. This has been particularly intense in Northern Ireland since the early 17th century [[plantation of Ulster]] under James I, with its religious and denominational sectarian tensions lasting to the present day in some forms. This has translated to parts of [[Great Britain]], most notably [[Liverpool]], and the [[West of Scotland (Scottish Parliament region)|West of Scotland]], the latter being very close geographically to Northern Ireland, and where some fans of the two best-known football clubs, [[Celtic F.C.|Celtic]] (long been affiliated with Catholics) and [[Rangers F.C.|Rangers]] (long affiliated with Protestants), indulge in provocative and sectarian behaviour. 

Historically, some Catholic countries once persecuted Protestants as heretics. For example, the substantial Protestant population of France (the [[Huguenot]]s) was expelled from the kingdom in the 1680s following the [[revocation of the Edict of Nantes]]. In Spain, the [[Spanish Inquisition|Inquisition]] sought to root out [[Marrano|crypto-Jews]] but also [[Morisco|crypto-Muslims]] (''[[expulsion of the Moriscos|moriscos]]''); elsewhere the [[Inquisition|Papal Inquisition]] held similar goals.

In most places where Protestantism is the majority or "official" religion, there have been examples of Catholics being persecuted.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} In countries where the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]] was successful, this often lay in the perception that Catholics retained allegiance to a 'foreign' power ([[the Papacy]] or [[Holy See|the Vatican]]), causing them to be regarded with suspicion. Sometimes this mistrust manifested itself in Catholics being subjected to restrictions and discrimination, which itself led to further conflict. For example, before [[Catholic Emancipation]] was introduced with the [[Roman Catholic Relief Act 1829]], Catholics were forbidden from voting, becoming MP's or buying land in Ireland.

Ireland was deeply scarred by religious sectarianism following the [[Protestant Reformation]] as tensions between the native Catholic Irish and Protestant settlers from Britain led to massacres and attempts at ethnic cleaning by both sides during the [[Irish Rebellion of 1641]], [[Cromwellian conquest of Ireland]], [[Irish Rebellion of 1798]] and the [[Home Rule Crisis]] of 1912. The invasion of Ireland by English parliamentarian forces under [[Oliver Cromwell]] in 1659 was notoriously brutal and witnessed the widespread [[ethnic cleansing]] of the native Irish. The failure of the [[Irish Rebellion of 1798|Rebellion of 1798]], which sought to unite Protestants and Catholics for an independent Ireland, helped cause more sectarian violence in the island, most infamously the [[Scullabogue Barn massacre]], in which Protestants were burned alive in [[County Wexford]]. The British response, which included the public executions of dozens of suspected rebels in [[Dunlavin Green executions|Dunlavin]] and [[Carnew executions|Carnew]], along with other violence perpetrated by all sides, ended the hope that Protestants and Catholics could work together for Ireland.

After the [[Partition of Ireland]] in 1922, [[Northern Ireland]] witnessed decades of intensified conflict, tension, and sporadic violence between the dominant Protestant majority and the Catholic minority, which in 1969 finally erupted into 25 years of violence known as “[[The Troubles]]” between [[Irish Republicans]] whose goal is a [[United Ireland]] and Ulster loyalists who wish for Northern Ireland to remain a part of the United Kingdom. The conflict was primarily fought over the existence of the Northern Irish state rather than religion, though sectarian relations within Northern Ireland fueled the conflict. However, religion is commonly used as a marker to differentiate the two sides of the community. The Catholic minority primarily favour the nationalist, and to some degree, republican, goal of unity with the [[Republic of Ireland]], while the Protestant majority favour Northern Ireland continuing the union with Great Britain.

[[File:Sack of Magdeburg 1631.jpg|thumb|The [[sack of Magdeburg]] by Catholic army in 1631. Of the 30,000 Protestant citizens, only 5,000 survived.]]

Northern Ireland has introduced a Private Day of Reflection,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dayofreflection.com/|title=HTR - Day of Reflection - Home|publisher=|accessdate=29 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; since 2007, to mark the transition to a post-[sectarian] conflict society, an initiative of the cross-community Healing through Remembering&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.healingthroughremembering.org/|title=Healing Through Remembering|publisher=|accessdate=29 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; organisation and research project.

The civil wars in the [[Balkans]] which followed the [[breakup of Yugoslavia]] in the 1990s have been heavily tinged with sectarianism. [[Croats]] and [[Slovenes]] have traditionally been Catholic, [[Serbs]] and [[Macedonian Slavs|Macedonians]] [[Eastern Orthodox]], and [[Bosniaks]] and most [[Albanians]] Muslim. Religious affiliation served as a marker of group identity in this conflict, despite relatively low rates of religious practice and belief among these various groups after decades of [[communism]].

===Africa===
Over 1,000 Muslims and Christians were killed in the [[Central African Republic conflict (2012–present)|sectarian violence]] in the [[Central African Republic]] in 2013–2014.&lt;ref&gt;"[https://www.amnesty.org/en/news/central-african-republic-ethnic-cleansing-sectarian-violence-2014-02-12 Central African Republic: Ethnic cleansing and sectarian killings]". Amnesty International. February 12, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; Nearly 1 million people, a quarter of the population, were displaced.&lt;ref&gt;"[https://www.reuters.com/article/2014/01/26/us-centralafrican-idUSBREA0P0O220140126 Eight dead in Central African Republic capital, rebel leaders flee city]". [[Reuters]]. January 26, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia===
{{Main article|Sectarianism in Australia}}
Sectarianism in Australia was a historical legacy from the 18th, 19th and 20th centuries, between Catholics of mainly Celtic heritage and Protestants of mainly English descent. It has largely disappeared in the 21st century. In the late 20th and early 21st centuries, religious tensions are more centered on Muslim immigrants amid the backdrop of Salafist or Islamist terrorism.{{cn|date=February 2018}}

===Asia===
[[File:Basawan. Battle of rival ascetics. Akbarnama, ca. 1590, V&amp;A Museum.jpg|thumb|180px|[[Battle of Thanesar|Battle]] of rival ascetics in 1567. [[Muslim conquests of the Indian subcontinent|Hindu-Muslim conflicts]] provoked the creation of a military order of [[Sannyasa|Hindu ascetics]] in India.]]
====Japan====
For the violent conflict between Buddhist sects in Japan, see [[Japanese Buddhism]].

====Pakistan====
{{Main article|Sectarian violence in Pakistan}}
Pakistan, one of the largest Muslim countries the world, has seen serious [[Shia Islam|Shia]]-[[Sunni]] [[sectarian violence]]. Almost 80 - 85 
of Pakistan's Muslim population is [[Sunni]], and another 10 - 20% are [[Shia]].&lt;ref name="State"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2008/108505.htm |title=Pakistan - International Religious Freedom Report 2008 |quote= |work=[[United States Department of State]] |publisher= |accessdate=2013-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Oxford"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t125/e1809?_hi=1&amp;_pos=1 |title=Pakistan, Islam in |accessdate=2013-04-19 |work=[[Oxford Centre for Islamic Studies]] |quote=''Approximately 97 percent of Pakistanis are Muslim. The majority are Sunnis following the [[Hanafi]] school of Islamic law. Between 10 and 15 percent are Shiis, mostly Twelvers.'' |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this Shia minority forms the second largest Shia population of any country, larger than the Shia majority in Iraq.

In the last two decades, as many as 4,000 people are estimated to have died in sectarian fighting in Pakistan, 300 in 2006.&lt;ref name="csmonitor.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0202/p01s02-wosc.html|title=Shiite-Sunni conflict rises in Pakistan|author=The Christian Science Monitor|work=The Christian Science Monitor|accessdate=29 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the culprits blamed for the killing are [[Al Qaeda]] working "with local sectarian groups" to kill what they perceive as Shi'a apostates.&lt;ref name="csmonitor.com"/&gt;

====Sri Lanka====
Most Muslims in Sri Lanka are Sunnis. There are a few Shia Muslims too from the relatively small trading community of Bohras. Divisiveness is not a new phenomenon to Beruwala. Sunni Muslims in the Kalutara district are split in two different sub groups. One group, known as the Alaviya sect, historically holds its annual feast at the Ketchimalai mosque located on the palm fringed promontory adjoining the fisheries harbour in Beruwala.

It is a microcosm of the Muslim identity in many ways. The Galle Road that hugs the coast from Colombo veers inland just ahead of the town and forms the divide. On the left of the road lies China Fort, the area where some of the wealthiest among Sri Lankans Muslims live. The palatial houses with all modern conveniences could outdo if not equal those in the Colombo 7 sector. Most of the wealthy Muslims, gem dealers, even have a home in the capital, not to mention property.

Strict Wahabis believe that all those who do not practise their form of religion are heathens and enemies. There are others who say Wahabism's rigidity has led it to misinterpret and distort Islam, pointing to the Taliban as well as Osama bin Laden. What has caused concern in intelligence and security circles is the manifestation of this new phenomenon in Beruwala. It had earlier seen its emergence in the east.

===Middle East===
{{main article|Sectarian violence among Muslims}}
[[File:Al-Askari Mosque 2006.jpg|250px|thumb|The [[Al-Askari Mosque]], one of the holiest sites in Shia Islam, after [[2006 al-Askari Mosque bombing|the first attack]] by [[Wahhabi movement|Wahhabi]] affiliated [[Al-Qaeda in Iraq]] in 2006]]

====Ottoman Empire====
Sultan [[Selim I|Selim the Grim]], regarding the Shia [[Qizilbash]] as heretics, reportedly proclaimed that "the killing of one Shiite had as much otherworldly reward as killing 70 Christians."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jalāl Āl Aḥmad|title=Plagued by the West|year=1982|publisher=Center for Iranian Studies, Columbia University|isbn=978-0-88206-047-7|others=Translated by Paul Sprachman}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1511, a pro-Shia revolt known as [[Şahkulu Rebellion]] was brutally suppressed by the Ottomans: 40,000 were massacred on the order of the sultan.&lt;ref&gt;H.A.R. Gibb &amp; H. Bowen, "Islamic society and the West", i/2, Oxford, 1957, p. 189&lt;/ref&gt;

====Iraq====
{{See also|Civil war in Iraq (2006-07)}}
Sunni  [[Iraqi insurgency (Iraq War)|Iraqi insurgency]] and foreign Sunni terrorist organizations who came to Iraq after the fall of Saddam have targeted Shia civilians in sectarian attacks. Following the civil war, the Sunnis have complained of supposed discrimination by Iraq's Shia majority government, which is bolstered by the news that Sunni detainees were allegedly discovered to have been [[torture]]d in a compound used by government forces on November 15, 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Iraqi Sunnis demand abuse inquiry
  | work =
  | publisher = BBC News
  | date =November 16, 2005
  | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4441568.stm
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2007-05-12  }}&lt;/ref&gt; This sectarianism has fueled a giant level of emigration and internal displacement.

However, the Shia majority oppression by the Sunni minority has a long history in Iraq, after the fall of the Ottoman Empire, the British imposed upon Iraq a rule of Sunni Hashemite monarchy that suppressed various uprisings against its rule by the Christian Assyrians, Kurds, Yazidis and Shi'ites. After the monarchy's overthrow, Iraq was ruled by the de jure secular Baathist Party, while de facto a minority Sunni absolute rule that heavily persecuted the Shia majority. Since 2003, Shi'ite majority first time since ever gained any say in the government, however at the price of being a constant terrorist target by the Sunni minority that can't accept multireligious, plural and democratic state.

====Syria====
{{See also|Sectarianism and minorities in the Syrian civil war}}
[[File:Wounded civilians arrive at hospital Aleppo.jpg|thumb|Wounded civilians arrive at a hospital in Aleppo]]
Sectarianism has been described as a characteristic feature of the [[Syrian civil war]]. The sharpest split is between the ruling minority [[Alawite]] sect, a Shiite Muslim offshoot, and the country's Sunni Muslim majority.

====Saudi Arabia====
The Saudi government has often been viewed as an active oppressor of Shia Muslims because of the funding of the [[Wahabbism|Wahabbi]] ideology which denounces the Shia faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=syedjaffar|title=The Persecution of Shia Muslims in Saudi Arabia|url=http://ireport.cnn.com/docs/DOC-1015700|work=August 4, 2013|publisher=CNN Report|accessdate=1 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prince [[Bandar bin Sultan]], Saudi ambassador to the United States, stated: "The time is not far off in the Middle East when it will be literally 'God help the Shia'. More than a billion Sunnis have simply had enough of them."&lt;ref&gt;"[https://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/iraq-crisis-how-saudi-arabia-helped-isis-take-over-the-north-of-the-country-9602312.html Iraq crisis: How Saudi Arabia helped Isis take over the north of the country]," ''[[The Independent]],'' 13 July 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to ''The New York Times'', "The documents from Saudi Arabia’s Foreign Ministry illustrate a near obsession with Iran, with diplomats in Africa, Asia and Europe monitoring Iranian activities in minute detail and top government agencies plotting moves to limit the spread of Shiite Islam."&lt;ref&gt;"[https://www.nytimes.com/2015/07/17/world/middleeast/wikileaks-saudi-arabia-iran.html WikiLeaks Shows a Saudi Obsession With Iran]". ''The New York Times''. 16 July 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 25, 2015, Saudi Arabia, spearheading a coalition of [[Sunni Islam|Sunni Muslim]] states,&lt;ref&gt;"[https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2015-03-26/yemeni-bombing-led-by-saudis-is-backed-by-u-s-logistics-spying U.S. Backs Saudi-Led Yemeni Bombing With Logistics, Spying]". [[Bloomberg News|Bloomberg]]. 26 March 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; started a [[Saudi Arabian-led intervention in Yemen|military intervention in Yemen]] against the [[Shia Islam|Shia]] [[Houthis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/jul/07/jihadis-likely-winners-of-saudi-arabias-futile-war-on-yemens-houthi-rebels |title=Jihadis likely winners of Saudi Arabia's futile war on Yemen's Houthi rebels |date=7 July 2015|work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{as of|2015}}, Saudi Arabia is openly supporting the [[Army of Conquest]],&lt;ref&gt;"[https://news.yahoo.com/army-conquest-rebel-alliance-pressures-syria-regime-090529121.html 'Army of Conquest' rebel alliance pressures Syria regime]". Yahoo News. 28 April 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/News/12392/21/Gulf-allies-and-%E2%80%98Army-of-Conquest%E2%80%99.aspx Gulf allies and ‘Army of Conquest’]". ''[[Al-Ahram Weekly]]''. 28 May 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; an umbrella group of anti-government forces fighting in the [[Syrian Civil War]] that reportedly includes an [[al-Qaeda]] linked [[al-Nusra Front]] and another [[Salafi jihadism|Salafi]] coalition known as [[Ahrar al-Sham]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/syria-crisis-turkey-and-saudi-arabia-shock-western-countries-by-supporting-antiassad-jihadists-10242747.html |title=Turkey and Saudi Arabia alarm the West by backing Islamist extremists the Americans had bombed in Syria  |author=Kim Sengupta |newspaper=The Independent |date=12 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2016, Saudi Arabia executed the prominent [[Shia Islam in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Shia]] cleric [[Nimr al-Nimr]].&lt;ref name="nimr"&gt;{{cite web | title=Saudi execution of Shia cleric sparks outrage in Middle East |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/02/saudi-execution-of-shia-cleric-sparks-outrage-in-middle-east |work=[[The Guardian]]| date=2 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Lebanon====

=====Overview=====
Sectarianism in Lebanon has been formalized and legalized within state and non-state institutions and is inscribed in its constitution. The foundations of sectarianism in Lebanon date back to the mid-19th century during Ottoman rule. It was subsequently reinforced with the creation of the Republic of Lebanon in 1920 and its 1926 constitution, and in the National Pact of 1943. In 1990, with the Taif Agreement, the constitution was revised but did not structurally change aspects relating to political sectarianism.&lt;ref name=Bahout&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bahout|first=Joseph|title=Sectarianism in Lebanon and Syria: The Dynamics of Mutual Spill-Over|journal=United States Institute of Peace|date=18 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dynamic nature of sectarianism in Lebanon has prompted some historians and authors to refer to it as "the sectarian state ''par excellence''" because it is an amalgam of religious communities and their myriad sub-divisions, with a constitutional and political order to match.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hirst|first=David|title=Beware of Small States: Lebanon, Battleground of the Middle East|year=2011|publisher=Nation Books|page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Historical background=====
According to various historians, sectarianism in Lebanon is not simply an inherent phenomena between the various religious communities there. Rather, historians have argued that the origins of sectarianism lay at the "intersection of nineteenth-century European colonialism and Ottoman modernization".&lt;ref name=Makdisi&gt;{{cite book|last=Makdisi|first=Ussama|title=The Culture of Sectarianism: Community, History, and Violence in Nineteenth-Century Ottoman Lebanon|year=2000|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|page=xi}}&lt;/ref&gt; The symbiosis of Ottoman modernization (through a variety of reforms) and indigenous traditions and practices became paramount in reshaping the political self-definition of each community along religious lines. The Ottoman reform movement launched in 1839 and the growing European presence in the Middle East subsequently led to the disintegration of the traditional Lebanese social order based on a hierarchy that bridged religious differences. Nineteenth-century Mount Lebanon was host to [[1860 Mount Lebanon civil war|competing armies and ideologies]] and for "totally contradictory interpretations of the meaning of reform" (i.e. Ottoman or European).&lt;ref name=Makdisi-a&gt;{{cite book|last=Makdisi|first=Ussama|title=The Culture of Sectarianism: Community, History, and Violence in Nineteenth-Century Ottoman Lebanon|year=2000|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8F5f1kjEVOEC|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|page=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; This fluidity over reform created the necessary conditions for sectarianism to rise as a "reflection of fractured identities" pulled between enticements and coercions of Ottoman and European power.&lt;ref name=Makdisi/&gt;  As such, the Lebanese encounter with European colonization altered the meaning of religion in the multi-confessional society because it "emphasized sectarian identity as the only viable marker of political reform and the only authentic basis for political claims."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Makdisi|first=Ussama|title=The Culture of Sectarianism: Community, History, and Violence in Nineteenth-Century Ottoman Lebanon|year=2000|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, during both Ottoman rule and later during the [[French Mandate for Syria and the Lebanon|French Mandate]], religious identities were deliberately mobilized for political and social reasons.

=====The Lebanese political system=====
Lebanon gained independence on 22 November 1943. Shortly thereafter, the National Pact was agreed upon and established the political foundations of modern Lebanon and laid the foundations of a sectarian power-sharing system (also known as confessionalism) based on the 1932 census.&lt;ref name=Salamey/&gt; The 1932 census is the only official census conducted in Lebanon: with a total population of 1,046,164 persons, Maronites made up 33.57%, Sunnis made up 18.57% and Shiites made up 15.92% (with several other denominations making up the remainder). The National Pact served to reinforce the sectarian system that had begun under the French Mandate, by formalizing the confessional distribution of the highest public offices and top administrative ranks according to the proportional distribution of the dominant sects within the population.&lt;ref name=Rogan&gt;{{cite book|last=Rogan|first=Eugene|title=The Arabs: A History|date=2009|publisher=Basic Books|location=New York|page=242}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Because the census showed a slight Christian dominance over Muslims, seats in the Chamber of Deputies (parliament) were distributed by a six-to-five ratio favoring Christians over Muslims. This ratio was to be applied to all highest-level public and administrative offices, such as ministers and directors. Furthermore, it was agreed that the President of the Republic would be a Maronite Christian; the Premier of the Council of Ministers would be a Sunni Muslim; the President of the National Assembly would be a Shiite Muslim; and the Deputy Speaker of Parliament a Greek Orthodox Christian.&lt;ref name=Salamey/&gt;

=====The Lebanese Civil War, 1975–1990=====
{{main article|Lebanese Civil War}}
During the three decades following independence from the French Mandate, "various internal tensions inherent to the Lebanese system and multiple regional developments collectively contributed to the breakdown of governmental authority and the outbreak of civil strife in 1975”.&lt;ref name=Salamey/&gt; According to Makdisi, sectarianism reached its peak during the civil war that lasted from 1975–1990.&lt;ref name=Makdisi-b&gt;{{cite journal|last=Makdisi|first=Ussama|title=Reconstructing the Nation-State: The Modernity of Sectarianism in Lebanon|journal=Middle East Report|year=1996|volume=200|page=23|doi=10.2307/3013264}}&lt;/ref&gt; The militia politics that gripped Lebanon during the civil war represents another form of popular mobilization along sectarian lines against the elite-dominated Lebanese state.&lt;ref name=Makdisi/&gt;

Christians began setting up armed militias what they “saw as an attempt by the Palestinian Liberation Organization (PLO) to seize Lebanon – those militias would be united under the Lebanese Forces umbrella in 1976”.&lt;ref name=Lebanon&gt;{{cite journal|title=Lebanon: The Persistence of Sectarian Conflict|journal=Berkley Center for Religion, Peace, and World Affairs|year=2013|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lebanese Sunni groups splintered into armed factions as well, competing against one another and against the Christian militias. The beginning of the Lebanese Civil War dates to 1975, when a Maronite militia opened fire on a bus full of civilians in response to an assassination attempt of a Maronite leader by PLO-affiliated Muslims.&lt;ref name=Lebanon/&gt; On May 31, seven weeks after fighting began between militias, Beirut witnessed its first sectarian massacre in which "unarmed civilians were killed simply on the grounds of their religion."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rogan|first=Eugene|title=The Arabs: A History|date=2009|publisher=Basic Books|location=New York|page=382}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Syria entered the conflict in June 1976, in order to avoid a PLO takeover of Lebanon – Syria’s entry into the war resulted in a de facto division of the country into zones controlled by Syria, the PLO, and Maronite militias.&lt;ref name=Lebanon/&gt; Shi’a militias were also created, including the formation of Amal in the late 1970s and later when some Amal militants decided to create a more religious Shi’a militia known as Hezbollah (Party of God). [[Hezbollah|See Wikipedia page on Hezbollah]].

The Lebanese Civil War became a regional dilemma when Israel invaded in 1982 with two avowed aims: destroy the PLO military infrastructure and secure its northern frontier. In March 1989, Prime Minister (and Acting President) General Michel Aoun launched a “liberation war” against the Syrian army with the backing of the PLO and Iraqi president Saddam Hussein. In doing so, General Aoun internationalized the Lebanese crisis by “emphasized the destructive role of the Syrian army in the country”.&lt;ref name=Lebanon/&gt;  His decision resulted in multilateral negotiations as well as efforts to strengthen the role of the UN. By 1983, what had begun as an internal war between Lebanese factions had become a regional conflict that drew in Syria, Israel, Iran, Europe and the United States directly - with Iraq, Libya, Saudi Arabia, and the Soviet Union involved indirectly by providing financial support and weaponry to different militias.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rogan|first=Eugene|title=The Arabs: A History|date=2009|publisher=Basic Books|location=New York|page=411}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After fifteen years of war, at least 100,000 Lebanese were dead, tens of thousands had emigrated abroad, and an estimated 900,000 civilians were internally displaced.&lt;ref name=Lebanon/&gt;

=====The Taif Agreement=====
{{main article|Taif Agreement}}
After twenty-two days of discussions and negotiations, the surviving members of the 1972 parliament reached an agreement to end the Civil War on October 22, 1989. The Taif Agreement reconfigured the political power-sharing formula that formed that basis of government in Lebanon under the National Pact of 1943.&lt;ref name=Saseen&gt;{{cite book|last=Saseen|first=Sandra|title=The Taif Accord and Lebanon's Struggle to Regain its Sovereignty|year=1990|publisher=American University International Law Review|page=67}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
As noted by Eugene Rogan, "the terms of Lebanon's political re-construction, enshrined in the Taif [Agreement], preserved many of the elements of the confessional system set up in the National Pact but modified the structure to reflect the demographic realities of modern Lebanon."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rogan|first=Eugene|title=The Arabs: A History|date=2009|publisher=Basic Books|location=New York|page=460}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As such, several key provisions of the National Pact were changed including: it relocated most presidential powers in favor of Parliament and the Council of Ministers and, as such, the Maronite Christian President lost most of his executive powers and only retained symbolic roles; it redistributed important public offices, including those of Parliament, Council of Ministers, general directors, and grade-one posts evenly between Muslims and Christians thereby upsetting the traditional ratio of six to five that favored Christians under the National Pact; it “recognized the chronic instability of confessionalism and called for devising a national strategy for its political demise. It required the formation of a national committee to examine ways to achieve deconfessionalization and the formation of a non-confessional Parliament," which has not yet been implemented to date&lt;ref name=Salamey&gt;{{cite book|last=Salamey|first=Imad|title=The Government and Politics of Lebanon|year=2014|publisher=Routledge|location=London|page=57}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it required the disarmament of all Lebanese militias; however, Hezbollah was allowed to retain its militant wing as a  “resistance force” in recognition of its fight against Israel in the South.&lt;ref name=Salamey/&gt;

=====Spillover from the Syrian conflict=====
{{main article|Syrian Civil War}}
The Syrian conflict which began in 2011 when clashes began between the Assad government and opposition forces has had a profound effect on sectarian dynamics within Lebanon. In November 2013, the United States Institute of Peace published a Peace Brief in which Joseph Bahout assesses how the Syrian crisis has influenced Lebanon’s sectarian and political dynamics. Bahout argues that the Syrian turmoil is intensifying Sunni-Shia tensions on two levels: “symbolic and identity-based on the one hand, and geopolitical or interest based, on the other hand." Syria’s conflict has profoundly changed mechanisms of inter-sectarian mobilization in Lebanon: interest-based and “political” modes of mobilization are being transformed into identity-based and “religious” modes. Bahout notes that this shift is likely due to how these communities are increasingly perceiving themselves as defending not only their share of resources and power, but also their very survival. As the conflict grows more intense, the more the sectarian competition is internalized and viewed as a zero-sum game. Perceptions of existential threat exist among both the Shiite and Sunni communities throughout Lebanon: the continuation of the Syrian conflict will likely increase these perceptions over time and cause [[terrorism]].&lt;ref name=Bahout/&gt;

There are notable divisions within the Lebanese community along sectarian lines regarding the Syrian Civil War. The Shi'ite militant and political organization Hezbollah and its supporters back the Assad government, while many of the country's Sunni communities back the opposition forces. These tensions have played out in clashes between Sunnis and Shi'ites within Lebanon, resulting in clashes and deaths. For instance, clashes in the northern city of Tripoli, Lebanon left three dead when fighting broke out between Assad supporters and opponents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Holmes|first=Oliver|title=Three dead in north Lebanon in spillover from Syria war|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2014/03/21/uk-syria-crisis-lebanon-clashes-idUKBREA2K0J320140321|accessdate=8 April 2014|newspaper=Reuters|date=21 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The largest concentration of Syrian refugees, close to one million people as of April 2014, can be found in Lebanon and has resulted in a population increase by about a quarter. According to the United Nations, the massive influx of refugees threatens to upset the “already fragile demographic balance between Shi’ites, Sunnis, Druze, and Christians.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ryan|first=Missy|title=Syria refugee crisis poses major threat to Lebanese stability: U.N.|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2014/03/28/us-lebanon-usa-idUSBREA2R02E20140328|accessdate=6 April 2014|newspaper=Reuters|date=27 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Lebanese government faces major challenges for handling the refugee influx, which has strained public infrastructure as Syrians seek housing, food, and healthcare at a time of economic slowdown in Lebanon.

For background on Syria-Lebanon relations, see [[Lebanon-Syria relations]].

==Political sectarianism==
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2015}}
In the political realm, to describe a group as "sectarian" (or as practising "sectarianism") is to accuse them of prioritizing differences and rivalries with politically close groups. An example might be a [[capitalist]] group who are accused of devoting an excessive amount of time and energy to denouncing other capitalist groups rather than their common foes.

==See also==
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
* [[Collective narcissism]]
* [[Communalism (South Asia)]]
* [[Cybersectarianism]]
* [[Ethnic cleansing]]
* [[Exclusivism]]
* [[Group conflict]]
* [[Identity politics]]
* [[Identitarianism]]
* [[Ingroups and outgroups]]
* [[Jingoism]]
* [[Narcissism of small differences]]
* [[Partisanship]]
* [[Religious segregation]]
* [[Sect]]
* [[Supremacism]]
* [[Tribalism]]
* [[Xenophobia]]
}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160401130757/http://tda-sy.org/english-sectarianism-in-syria-survey-study/?lang=en Sectarianism in Syria (Survey Study), The Day After, 2016.]
* [http://www.yourmiddleeast.com/culture/middle-east-sectarianism-explained-the-narcissism-of-small-differences_31307 Middle East sectarianism explained: the narcissism of small differences] Victor Argo 13 Apr 2015 ''Your Middle East''

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|sectarian}}
* [http://causeofallcauses.com/NonsectarianReligion.htm Non-Sectarian Religion] by [[Bhaktivinoda Thakura]] 1880

[[Category:Sectarianism| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>