<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061027020711|83971010" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="398489" pageid="398489" ns="0" title="Sectarianism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-12T19:54:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Merge|Sectarian violence|date=September 2006}} 
{{cleanup-date|September 2005}}

'''Sectarianism''' refers (usually [[pejorative]]ly) to a rigid adherence to a particular [[sect]] or party or denomination. It often implies discrimination, denunciation, or violence against those outside the sect. The term is most often used to refer to religious sectarianism, involving conflict between members of different religions or denominations of the same religion. It is also frequently used to refer to political sectarianism, generally on the part of a tight-knit political faction or party.

Sectarianism may, in the abstract, be characterized by dogmatism and inflexibility; sentimental or axiomatic adherence to an idea, belief or tradition; and idealism that provides a sense of continuity, orientation, and certainty. As a pejorative term, accusations of sectarianism may sometimes be used to demonize an opposing group.

The ideological underpinnings of attitudes and behaviours labelled as sectarian are extraordinarily varied. Members of a religious group may feel that their own salvation requires aggressively seeking converts from other groups; adherents of a given faction may believe that for the achievement of their own political or religious project their opponents must be purged. Sometimes a group feeling itself to be under economic or political pressure will attack members of another group thought to be responsible for its own decline. At other times, sectarianism may be the expression of a group's [[nationalist]]ic or cultural ambitions, or cynically exploited to serve an individual demagogue's ambition. 

In all cases, there is a real or felt opposition between 'Us' and 'Them', between insiders and outsiders. Sectarianism may take the form of hatred and fear of an outside sect or group. In such cases, sectarianism does not require a strong sense of religious belief, as much as a sense of group belonging.

A sectarian conflict usually refers to violent conflict along religious and political lines such as the conflicts between [[Catholics]] and [[Protestants]] in [[Northern Ireland]]. It may also refer to general philosophical or political conflict between different schools of thought such as that between [[Shia]] and [[Sunni]] [[Muslim]]s.  Non-sectarians espouse that free association and tolerance of different beliefs are the cornerstone to successful peaceful human interaction.

==Religious sectarianism==
Wherever religious sectarians compete, religious sectarianism is found in varying forms and degrees.
In some areas, religious sectarians (for example Protestant and Roman Catholic [[Christians]] in the [[United States]]) now exist peacefully side-by-side. In others, [[Roman Catholic]]s and [[Protestant]]s have been in fierce conflict &amp;ndash; one contemporary example of this is in [[Ireland]] and its [[Irish diaspora|diaspora]]. Within [[Islam]], there has been conflict at various periods between Sunnis and Shias; contrary to the majority Muslim opinion, certain Sunni sects inspired by [[Wahhabism]] and other ideologies have declared Shias (and sometimes mainstream Sunnis) to be [[heresy|heretics]] and/or [[apostasy|apostates]].

===United States===
Despite a history of conflict and violence, Protestants and Roman Catholics in the United States mostly get along.

===Ireland===
:''See also: [[Troubles|the Troubles]], [[Demographics and politics of Northern Ireland]]''

Since the [[17th century]], there has been sectarian conflict of varying intensity in [[Ireland]]. This religious sectarianism is bound up with [[nationalism]]. Since the [[Irish Free State]] became independent in [[1922]], this has been particularly intense in [[Northern Ireland]]. Irish emigration has taken this conflict to other lands, including western [[Scotland]] (see: ''[[Sectarianism in Glasgow]]''), [[Newfoundland]], [[Canada]]'s [[Maritime provinces]], [[New York State]], [[Ontario]], [[Liverpool]], and elsewhere. See also [[Know-Nothings]] for anti-Catholic sentiment in the [[United States]].

===Persecution of Protestants by Catholics===
In Catholic countries, Protestants have historically been persecuted as [[heresy|heretics]]. For example, the substantial Protestant population of [[France]] (the [[Huguenot]]s) was expelled from the kingdom in the [[1680s]] following the [[revocation of the Edict of Nantes]]. In [[Spain]], the [[Spanish Inquisition|Inquisition]] sought to root out not only Protestantism but also [[crypto-Jews]] and crypto-Muslims (''[[morisco]]s''); elsewhere the [[Inquisition|Papal Inquisition]] held similar goals.

===Persecution of Catholics by Protestants===
In places where Protestantism is the majority or 'official' religion, there have been examples of Catholics being persecuted.  In countries where The [[Reformation]] was successful, this often lay in the perception that Catholics retained allegiance to a 'foreign' power ([[the Papacy]]), causing them to be regarded with suspicion. Sometimes this mistrust manifested itself in Catholics being subjected to restrictions and discrimination, which itself led to further conflict. For example, before [[Catholic Emancipation]] in 1829, Catholics were forbidden from voting, running for office or buying land in Ireland. 

Nowadays, bigotry and discrimination in employment usually only remains in a few places where extreme forms of Protestantism are the norm, or in poor areas with a long history of sectarian violence and tension, such as [[Northern Ireland]].  In places where more 'moderate' forms (such as [[Anglicanism]] / [[Episcopalianism]]) prevail, the two traditions do not become polarized against each other, and usually co-exist peacefully. However, in western [[Scotland]], where many people have some Irish ancestry, sectarianism can frequently be found between Catholics and Protestants.

===South Asian communalism===
:''Main article: [[Communalism (South Asia)]]''

In [[India]], sectarianism is known as '''[[communalism (South Asia)|communalism]]''', which refers particularly to conflict between the [[Hindu]] and [[Islam in India|Muslim]] communities. It can also refer to Hindu/[[Sikh]] conflict and Hindu/[[Christianity in India|Christian]] conflicts. While [[communalism]] ususally implies economic communalism, in this sense it refers to the sectarians' "community."

Violence in [[Sri Lanka]] between the [[Tamil people|Tamil]], [[Sinhalese]], and [[Islam in Sri Lanka|Muslim]] communities often has heavy sectarian overtones.

===Sectarianism in Pakistan ===

In [[Pakistan]], there has been a brutal history of sectarian violence and unrest since the 1970s.  In early years, the [[Sunni]] focus was [[Qadianism|Ahmadis]].  Today, though the majority of violence exists between [[Sunnis]] and [[Shias]], there has also been example of ethnic violence that has played a major role in the development of the 60 year old nation.    

Under the rule of [[Zia-ul-Haq|Muhammad Zia-ul-Haq]], sectarianism in Pakistan, especially in [[Karachi]] came to an explosive point.  This sparked a whole new era of sectarian violence whose legacy came to a near end when a [[Sunni]] suicide bombing of a [[Shia]] mosque in 2003 took place.  Many have attributed this to Zia's practice of [[Wahhabism]], which gained notoriety in mainstream [[Sunni]] after the destruction of the [[Shia]] holy shrine of [[Imam Hussein]] in [[Karbala]], [[Iraq]] in [[1800]].  The plan for [[Islamization]] of Pakistan led to further violence between the two main sects.  

In the early part of the new millennium, [[Shia]] doctors and lawyers were put on anonymously paid for newspaper ads that published assassination hitlists.  Then, those people were systematically assassinated by extremist [[Salafist]] and [[Deobandi]] groups as part of an effort to ethnically cleanse the nation of its [[Shia]] notables.

===Sectarianism in Iraq===
:''Main article: [[Sectarian violence in Iraq]]''

Iraq's Shia population was persecuted during the presidency of [[Saddam Hussein]], and certain elements of the [[Iraqi insurgency]] have made a point of targeting Shias in sectarian attacks. In turn, the Sunnis have complained of discrimination and human rights abuses by Iraq's Shia majority government, which is bolstered by the fact that Sunni detainees were allegedly discovered to have been tortured in a compound used by government forces on [[November 15]]. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4441568.stm]

===Ethnic conflict in the Balkans===
:''See also: [[History of Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[Yugoslavia#Breakup]]''

The civil wars in the Balkans which followed the [[breakup of Yugoslavia]] have been heavily tinged with sectarianism. [[Croats]] and [[Slovenes]] have traditionally been Catholic, [[Serbs]] and [[Macedonian Slavs|Macedonians]] [[Eastern Orthodox]], and [[Bosniaks]] and (for the most part) [[Albanians]] Muslim. Religious affiliation served as a marker of group identity in this conflict, despite relatively low rates of religious practice and belief among these various groups after decades of [[communism]].

===Christian/Muslim conflict in West Africa===
In certain [[West Africa]]n countries, particularly [[Nigeria]], competition between Muslims and Christians has exploded into severe violence.

===Sectarianism within Judaism===
Sectarianism also exists between [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] and [[Reform Judaism|Reform]] Jews, with orthodox Jews often characterising reform Jews as being non-religious, disobeying the Torah, rarely attending shul and adopting semi-Christian styles of worship. Reform Jews, on the other hand, often view the orthodox as being intolerant of them and other religions, placing legalistic rules such as the observance of the Sabbath above ethical obligations, being cult-like and hostile to change.

===Anti-Semitism===
:''Main article: [[Anti-Semitism]]''

Anti-Semitism has traditionally been the most widespread variety of sectarianism in Europe. However, this form of prejudice is not wholly religious in nature, as can be seen by the racial policies of the Nazis, who could be said to be more concerned with the "contamination" of Aryan blood than with the Jewish religion itself, and the experiences of Marranos who were treated with suspicion several generations after their families had converted to Christianity.

==Political sectarianism==
Political sectarianism differs from religious sectarianism in that political affinity is usually more likely to be elective, as opposed to hereditary, than is religious affinity. In the political realm, the term sectarian is generally used to refer to the tendency of political movements to splinter into mutually antagonistic factions. Various [[Trotskyist]] formations, for example, may accuse each other of sectarianism and/or be perceived by outsiders to be sectarian. The same phenomenon may be observed across the political spectrum, to varying degrees, wherever a strong priority is placed on party loyalty and [[party discipline]].

Political sectarianism among [[Zealot|Judaean nationalists]] was parodied by [[Monty Python]] in ''[[The Life of Brian]]''.

==Sectarianism in football==

Most notable is the case of [[Rangers FC]] and [[Celtic FC]] from [[Glasgow]], [[Scotland]]. Rangers are seen as the [[Protestant]] team and Celtic the [[Catholic]] team. The two clubs are the most successful in Scotland, and every week attract thousands of Protestants and Catholics from Northern Ireland[http://66.249.93.104/search?q=cache:ukyBkHM2KLkJ:www.math.nus.edu.sg/aslaksen/celtic/Sanders.doc+rangers+sectarian+song&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=uk&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=30].

==See also==
{{wiktionary|sectarian}}
*[[Sectarian violence]]
*[[Cult]]
*[[Sect]]
*[[Fundamentalism]]

[[Category:Religious faiths, traditions, and movements]]

[[el:Σεκταρισμός]]
[[fr:Méthode des sectes]]
[[pt:Sectarismo]]

Solving the sectarian problem

The killings at Hangu, and the ominous presence of security personnel everywhere during Ashura, have once more proved that sectarianism remains deeply entrenched. Quite aside from the terrible murders and the mayhem created by them, the sense of fear and of discrimination that lives on in the country is deeply damaging. More and more Shias have complained of intolerance, which is causing new rift lines to emerge within an already fractured society. The real question is how the sectarian issue can be resolved over the coming years. It is obvious that the existing policies have had only limited impact, and militant elements continue to wreak havoc at periodic intervals. The fact of the matter is that a problem which has taken root over two decades or so may take at least as long to eradicate. After all, numerous studies have shown that prejudice of all kinds is an insidious social phenomenon, which can take generations to wipe out. It is, however, essential that the effort to tackle sectarianism begin immediately. This effort must be underpinned with far greater commitment and a longer-term strategy than has so far been the case. Mere cosmetic measures, revolving around policing militancy by locking up dozens in jails for weeks, or deploying security forces in an effort to keep vigilance over every street corner, is neither feasible nor wise. It must, in the first place, be accepted that the dozens of young militants who today form small bands, and unleash on society the violence that they have been trained in for many years, need to be dealt with. They also need to be considered as victims, not merely criminals. Rather than simply locking them into jail cells, there must also be an attempt to rehabilitate them as useful members of society. In this, the state needs to face up to its responsibilities. After all, previous governments played a major role in the training of militants and in the setting up of the seminaries where they received their education in the cruel rules of hatred. The result of those policies are now evident in the form of bomb blasts, the targeted shootings and the suicide blasts that have in recent years shaken cities and towns across the country. The government of today must then find ways of reversing the trends so deliberately created. Simply mowing the grass is not enough. Roots too need to be dug out. To attain this, those spreading militancy need to be stopped. While anyone guilty of criminal acts must of course face penalties under the law, there is also a need for the re-training and re-education of the many members of these armies. As with any cult, extremist forces operate essentially by cutting off young victims -- in this case often children or teenagers -- from other social contact, and brainwashing them into abiding by a particular set of beliefs. Examples from around the world suggest that these tactics can be so powerful that average citizens have been willing to kill, maim or commit suicide at the command of leaders. The same holds true for those inculcated into specific schools of thought by extremist forces. The extent to which the power of persuasion can work in changing individuals is readily visible today in society -- with celebrity figures, including pop singers, cricketers and other sportsmen, quite obviously a focus for preachers. For the task of rehabilitating those won over to extremist causes, and convinced that violence is a legitimate means to achieve their ends, it may be useful to study the methods used to undertake similar exercises in the US, UK, Japan and other countries, where large cults have from time to time taken command of the minds of individuals. Specialists in rehabilitating victims of such cults now exist in many countries. Having mental health specialists talk to members of extremist forces, for instance when they are in jail, may prove a useful exercise rather than simply holding them for a few weeks and then once more letting them loose on the streets. But it is also worth keeping in mind the fact that given the existing social order, simply providing people a means of survival in economic terms can motivate them to change the pattern of their own lives. Many of the militants have no training -- except in how to use a gun. Due to their lack of skills, many are unemployable and as such able to pursue only the kind of militancy that formed their lone lesson in life. A scheme for training young members of militant groups and offering them work could very well prove a means to limit the number of persons ready to gun down other citizens on the basis of belief or allow themselves to be used as suicide bombers in a game of destruction that has already shattered hundreds of lives. There are also longer-term strategies that need to be followed. In the first place, discrimination against persons on the basis of belief by the state must end. After all, extremism in the country was given a big boost when, three decades ago, the state took it upon itself to determine who was Muslim and who was not. Since then, more and more bars, social, legal and economic, have gone up which prevent non-Muslim citizens from holding the equal status guaranteed to them by the constitution. An example of this comes in the battle being staged by a young Christian girl denied a place at the King Edwards Medical College in Lahore. The girl, who comes from a low-income background, qualified on merit for a seat but was denied a spot because a Muslim student, tied with her in terms of marks, obtained 20 additional points as a 'Hafiz-e-Quran" -- another means of discrimination that has become institutionalised in the country. Similar rules, regarding remissions for prisoners who memorise the Holy Quran, reflect the same in-built bias. To push aside the prejudices that have invaded society, several steps are essential. Seminary schools must be replaced by public-sector institutions which can offer a meaningful education. The money being wasted on reforming seminaries must instead be poured into rebuilding a viable public-school network. After all, parents have turned to seminaries in response to the failings of government schools. Even if curriculums at seminaries are widened, and computers provided, a core learning which weaves hatred into it, inculcates deep biases on the basis of religion or gender and encourages an extremely narrow understanding of religion will inevitably remain in place at these institutions. It is also true, as has been pointed out many times, that it is the economic desperation of people, the frustration of jobless young men, that most often drives them into the waiting arms of extremist groups. These forces specialise in picking out the vulnerable -- and luring them into an expanding fold. For these reasons, policies that can create jobs, and that can offer socio-economic relief to people, are essential if the sectarian crisis in the country is to be resolved. If such strategies are not put in place, if ways are not found to pull back young zealots from the fringes of society to where they have been pushed by extremist waves, violence will continue to grow. There is as such an urgent need to end the culture of the gun, before more lives are lost and more fault-lines carved out across a country that is today locked in a desperate struggle to retain harmony and integrity within its boundaries.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>