<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131003143530|575585222" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="398489" pageid="398489" ns="0" title="Sectarianism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-10T20:11:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:''This article concentrates on sectarianism as conflict between groups. For sectarianism as a characteristic of sects, see [[sect]].''
[[File:Brooklyn Museum - Battle of Karbala - Abbas Al-Musavi - overall.jpg|thumb|300px|Sectarian battle between [[Sunni]]s and [[Shia]]s at the [[Battle of Karbala]], 680 AD]]
'''Sectarianism''', according to one definition, is [[bigotry]], [[discrimination]], or [[hatred]] arising from attaching importance to perceived differences between subdivisions within a group, such as between different [[Religious denomination|denomination]]s of a [[religion]], [[Social class|class]], [[regional]] or [[Political faction|faction]]s of a [[political movement]].

The [[ideological]] underpinnings of attitudes and behaviours labelled as sectarian are extraordinarily varied. Members of a religious or political group may believe that their own salvation, or the success of their particular objectives, requires aggressively seeking converts from other groups; adherents of a given faction may believe that for the achievement of their own political or religious project their internal opponents must be converted or purged. 

Sometimes a group that is under economic or political pressure will kill or attack members of another group which it regards as responsible for its own decline. It may also more rigidly define the definition of "orthodox" belief within its particular group or organisation, and expel or excommunicate those who do not support this newfound clarified definition of political or religious 'orthodoxy'. In other cases, dissenters from this orthodoxy will secede from the orthodox organisation and proclaim themselves as practitioners of a reformed belief system, or holders of a perceived former orthodoxy. At other times, sectarianism may be the expression of a group's [[nationalist]]ic or cultural ambitions, or exploited by [[demagogue]]s.

The phrase "sectarian conflict" usually refers to violent conflict along religious or political lines such as the conflicts between [[Irish Nationalism|Nationalists]] and [[Unionism in Ireland|Unionists]] in [[Northern Ireland]] (religious and class-divisions may play major roles as well). It may also refer to general philosophical, political disparity between different schools of thought such as that between [[Shia Islam|Shia]] and [[Sunni Islam|Sunni]] [[Muslim]]s. Non-sectarians espouse that free association and tolerance of different beliefs are the cornerstone to successful peaceful human interaction. They espouse political and religious [[Pluralism (political philosophy)|pluralism]].

==Religious sectarianism==
[[File:Orange Riot 1871 crop.jpg|thumb|right|250px|In 1871, New York's [[Orange Riots]] were incited by Irish Protestants. 63 citizens, mostly Irish Catholics, were massacred in the resulting police-action.]]
{{main|Sectarian violence among Muslims}}
Sectarianism is present throughout the world. Wherever people of different religions live in close proximity to each other, religious sectarianism can often be found in varying forms and degrees. In some areas, religious sectarians (for example Protestant and Catholic [[Christians]]) {{as of | 2010 | alt = now}} exist peacefully side-by-side for the most part. Within [[Islam]] however, there has been conflict at various periods between [[Sunni Islam|Sunnis]] and [[Shia Islam|Shias]];  Shi'ites consider Sunnis to be damned, due to their refusal to accept the first Caliph as [[Ali]] and accept all following descendants of him as infallible and divinely guided. Many Sunni religious leaders, including those inspired by [[Wahhabism]] and other ideologies have declared Shias to be [[Heresy|heretics]] and/or [[Apostasy|apostates]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/7181042.stm | work=BBC News | title=Lahore bomb raises sectarian questions | date=January 10, 2008 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The historical usage of the term ''sect'' in [[Christendom]] has had [[pejorative]] connotations, referring to a group or movement with [[Christian heresy|heretical]] beliefs or practices that deviate from those of groups considered orthodox.&lt;ref&gt;[[Bryan Wilson|Wilson, Bryan]] ''Religion in Sociological Perspective'' 1982, ISBN 0-19-826664-2 [[Oxford University Press]] page 89&lt;br&gt;"In English, it is a term that designates a religiously separated group, but in its historical usage in Christendom it carried a distinctly pejorative connotation. A sect was a movement committed to heretical beliefs and often to ritual acts and practices like isolation that departed from orthodox religious procedures."&lt;/ref&gt;

==Europe==
{{Original research|section|date=July 2010}}
:''See also: [[The Troubles]], [[demographics and politics of Northern Ireland]]''
[[File:Francois Dubois 001.jpg|thumb|Painting of the [[St. Bartholomew's Day Massacre]], an event in the [[French Wars of Religion]]]]
Since the 12th century there has been sectarian conflict of varying intensity in [[Ireland]]. This religious sectarianism is connected to a degree with [[nationalism]]. This has been particularly intense in Northern Ireland since the early 17th century [[plantation of Ulster]] under James I. Sectarian tensions can be found in other regions of the British Isles to this day, including [[Scotland]] (with some fans of football clubs such as [[Celtic F.C.|Celtic]] and [[Rangers F.C.|Rangers]] indulging in sectarian chants) (see: ''[[Sectarianism in Glasgow]]''), [[Liverpool]], [[Birmingham]] and elsewhere. 

Historically, some Catholic countries once persecuted Protestants as heretics. For example, the substantial Protestant population of [[France]] (the [[Huguenot]]s) was expelled from the kingdom in the 1680s following the [[revocation of the Edict of Nantes]]. In [[Spain]], the [[Spanish Inquisition|Inquisition]] sought to root out [[Marrano|crypto-Jews]] but also [[Morisco|crypto-Muslims]] (''[[expulsion of the Moriscos|moriscos]]''); elsewhere the [[Inquisition|Papal Inquisition]] held similar goals.

In most places where Protestantism is the majority or "official" religion, there have been examples of Catholics being persecuted.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} In countries where the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]] was successful, this often lay in the perception that Catholics retained allegiance to a 'foreign' power ([[the Papacy]]), causing them to be regarded with suspicion. Sometimes this mistrust manifested itself in Catholics being subjected to restrictions and discrimination, which itself led to further conflict. For example, before [[Catholic Emancipation]] was introduced with the [[Catholic Relief Act]] of 1829, Catholics were forbidden from voting, becoming MP's or buying land in Ireland.

{{As of | 2010}}, bigotry and discrimination in employment are usually restricted to a few places where extreme forms of religion are the norm, or in areas with a long history of sectarian violence and tension, such as Northern Ireland, especially in terms of employment; however, this is dying out in this jurisdiction, due to strictly-enforced legislation. [[Reverse discrimination]] now takes place in terms of employment quotas which are now applied. In places where more "moderate" forms of Protestantism (such as [[Anglicanism]]/Episcopalianism) prevail, the two traditions do not become polarized against each other, and usually co-exist peacefully. Especially in England, sectarianism is nowadays almost unheard of. However in [[West of Scotland|Western Scotland]] (where [[Calvinism]] and [[Presbyterianism]] are the norm) sectarian divisions can still sometimes arise between Catholics and Protestants.  Indeed, in the early years following the [[Scottish Reformation]] there was actually internal sectarian tension between [[Church of Scotland]] Presbyterians and '[[High Church]]' Anglicans, whom they regarded as having retained too many attitudes and practices from the pre-Reformation Catholic era. Northern Ireland has introduced a Private Day of Reflection,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dayofreflection.com/ Private Day of Reflection : Ireland]&lt;/ref&gt; since 2007, to mark the transition to a post-[sectarian] conflict society, an initiative of the cross-community Healing through Remembering&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.healingthroughremembering.org/ Healing through Remembering : Ireland]&lt;/ref&gt; organisation and research project.

The civil wars in the [[Balkans]] which followed the [[breakup of Yugoslavia]] in the 1990s have been heavily tinged with sectarianism. [[Croats]] and [[Slovenes]] have traditionally been Catholic, [[Serbs]] and [[Macedonian Slavs|Macedonians]] [[Eastern Orthodox]], and [[Bosniaks]] and most [[Albanians]] Muslim. Religious affiliation served as a marker of group identity in this conflict, despite relatively low rates of religious practice and belief among these various groups after decades of [[communism]].

==Australia==
{{Main|Sectarianism in Australia}}
Sectarianism in Australia is a historical legacy from the 18th, 19th and 20th centuries, between Catholics of mainly Celtic heritage and Protestants of mainly English descent.

==Middle East and Asia==
===Ottoman Empire===
Sultan [[Selim I|Selim the Grim]], regarding the Shia [[Qizilbash]] as heretics, reportedly proclaimed that "the killing of one Shiite had as much otherworldly reward as killing 70 Christians."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jalāl Āl Aḥmad|title=Plagued by the West|year=1982|publisher=Center for Iranian Studies, Columbia University|isbn=978-0-88206-047-7|others=Translated by Paul Sprachman}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1511, a pro-Shia revolt known as [[Şahkulu Rebellion]] was brutally suppressed by the Ottomans: 40,000 were massacred on the order of the sultan.&lt;ref&gt;H.A.R. Gibb &amp; H. Bowen, "Islamic society and the West", i/2, Oxford, 1957, p. 189&lt;/ref&gt;

===Iraq===
{{See also|Civil war in Iraq}}
Iraqi society was largely not sectarian during the rule of [[Saddam Hussein]]. Certain elements of the [[Iraqi insurgency]] and foreign terrorist organizations who came to Iraq during the American invasion have targeted Shias in sectarian attacks. In turn, this caused a full sectarian civil war in Iraq mostly due to instigation by American forces. Following the civil war, the Sunnis have complained of discrimination by Iraq's Shia majority government, which is bolstered by the fact that Sunni detainees were allegedly discovered to have been [[torture]]d in a compound used by government forces on November 15, 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Iraqi Sunnis demand abuse inquiry
  | work =
  | publisher = BBC News
  | date =November 16, 2005
  | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4441568.stm
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2007-05-12  }}&lt;/ref&gt; This sectarianism has fueled a giant level of emigration and internal displacement.

Some people advocate an independent nation for the Sunnis of Iraq. One possible scenario envisages splitting Iraq into three: [[Kurdistan]] in the north, Iraq in the center and [[Basra]] in the south.  The thinking is that if each community is busy [[nation-building]], they would not be attacking each other as they would be within a single country where the communities may be striving for political dominance at expense of other communities instead of working together.   British India  split into Hindu-dominant India and Muslim-dominant Pakistan in 1947.  After a two-year trial, [[Malaysia]] split into [[Malays (ethnic group)|Malay]]-dominant Malaysia and [[Chinese people|Chinese]]-dominant [[Singapore]] in 1965.

===Syria===
{{See also|Sectarianism and minorities in the Syrian civil war}}
[[File:Wounded civilians arrive at hospital Aleppo.jpg|thumb|Wounded civilians arrive at a hospital in Aleppo]]
Sectarianism has been described as a characteristic feature of the [[Syrian civil war]]. The sharpest split is between the ruling minority [[Alawite]] sect, a Shiite Muslim offshoot, and the country's Sunni Muslim majority, mostly aligned with the opposition. 

===Lebanon===
{{See also|Lebanese civil war}}

Lebanon's [[religion|religious]] divisions are extremely complicated, with Lebanese society made of  a multitude of [[Demographics of Lebanon|religious groupings]]. Sectarianism in [[Lebanon]] was chosen to enable the political sharing of power.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} The 1943 National Pact gave the [[Maronite Christians]], the then majority, more power than the other groups. Although the [[Taif agreement]] (1989) ended the [[Lebanese Civil War]] (1975–1990), power remains divided among different groups.

The political system makes both intersectarian marriages and civil non-religious unions difficult.

===Pakistan===
{{Main|Sectarian violence in Pakistan}}

[[Pakistan]], one of the largest Muslim countries the world, has seen serious [[Shia Islam|Shia]]-[[Sunni]] '''[[sectarian violence]]'''. Almost 80 - 90% of [[Pakistan]]'s Muslim population is [[Sunni]], and another 10 - 20% are [[Shia]]. &lt;ref name="State"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2008/108505.htm |title=Pakistan - International Religious Freedom Report 2008 |quote= |work=[[United States Department of State]] |publisher= |accessdate=2013-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Oxford"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t125/e1809?_hi=1&amp;_pos=1 |title=Pakistan, Islam in |accessdate=2013-04-19 |work=[[Oxford Centre for Islamic Studies]] |quote=''Approximately 97 percent of Pakistanis are Muslim. The majority are Sunnis following the [[Hanafi]] school of Islamic law. Between 10 and 15 percent are Shiis, mostly Twelvers.'' |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this Shia minority forms the second largest Shia population of any country, larger than the Shia majority in Iraq. 

In the last two decades, as many as 4,000 people are estimated to have died in sectarian fighting in Pakistan, 300 in 2006.&lt;ref name="csmonitor.com"&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0202/p01s02-wosc.html "Shiite-Sunni conflict rises in Pakistan," by David Montero, February 02, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; Among the culprits blamed for the killing are [[Al Qaeda]] working "with local sectarian groups" to kill what they perceive as Shi'a apostates, and "foreign powers ... trying to sow discord."&lt;ref name="csmonitor.com"/&gt;

===Sri Lanka===
{{See also|Sri Lankan civil war}}
The BBC reported that "Sri Lanka’s [[Islam in Sri Lanka|Muslim]] minority is being targeted by [[Bodu Bala Sena|hardline Buddhists]]. ... There have also been assaults on churches and Christian pastors but it is the Muslims who are the most concerned."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-21840600| title =The hardline Buddhists targeting Sri Lanka's Muslims | publisher =[[BBC]] | date = March 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Political sectarianism==
In the political realm, to describe a group as "sectarian" (or as practicising "sectarianism"), is to accuse them of prioritizing differences and rivalries with politically close groups. An example might be a [[communist]] group who are accused of devoting an excessive amount of time and energy to denouncing other communist groups rather than their common foes. However, separatist [[fundamentalist]] Protestant political parties have proliferated (and regularly denounce one another{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}})in [[New Zealand]], as can be seen from the entries on [[United Future New Zealand]] and [[Future New Zealand]]. [[Libertarianism]] is similarly susceptible to fissiparous tendencies of its own. The [[Boston Tea Party (political party)|Boston Tea Party]] splintered off from the [[Libertarian Party (United States)|Libertarian Party]], due to the former being completely opposed to all government. Also, geo-libertarians are often disliked by other libertarians.

The [[Monty Python]] film ''[[The Life of Brian]]'' has a well-known joke in which various [[Judea]]n groups, indistinguishable to an outsider, are more concerned with [[in-fighting]] than with their nominal aim of opposing Roman rule.

==Memorials to victims of sectarian violence==
* [[The Linen Memorial]] : Northern Ireland

==See also==
{{Wiktionary|sectarian}}
* [[Communalism (South Asia)]]
* [[Ethnic cleansing]]
* [[Religious segregation]]
* [[Sectarian violence]]
* [[Sect]]
* [[Cybersectarianism]]

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

[[Category:Sectarianism| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>