<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071107065433|169807934" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1597743" pageid="1597743" ns="0" title="Ephebiphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-11T17:58:49Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination2}}
The psychological and social '''fear of [[youth]]''' is called ephebiphobia.

==Etymology and usage==
===Coinage===
The word '''ephebiphobia''' is formed from Greek '[[ephebos]]' έφηβος = teenager, underage adolescent and '[[fobos]]' φόβος = fear, phobia. 

Coinage is attributed to a 1994 article by Kirk Astroth published in ''[[Phi Delta Kappan]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Gough, P. (2000) "Detoxifying Schools." ''Phi Delta Kappan''. March 1, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Today, common usage occurs internationally by sociologists, government agencies, and youth advocacy organizations that define ephebiphobia as an abnormal or irrational and persistent [[fear]] and/or loathing of teenagers or [[adolescence]].&lt;ref&gt;Astroth, K. (1994) Beyond ephebiphobia: problem adults or problem youths? (fear of adolescents). ''Phi Delta Kappan''. January 1, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- &lt;ref&gt;Grønnestad-Damur, W. &amp; Pratch, L. (n.d.) [http://72.14.209.104/search?q=cache:mvQsUXWY2nwJ:albertalibraryconference.com/2005/presentations/C4_ephibiphobia2.pdf+site:albertalibraryconference.com&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=2 ''No Ephebiphobia Here!''] Edmonton: Edmonton Public Library.&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clark, C. (2004) ''Hurt: Inside the World of Today's Teenagers (Youth, Family, and Culture).'' Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Book House.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Similar terms===
The term '''paedophobia''' has gained popular acceptance in Europe to describe the aforementioned "fear of youth".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ippr.org/pressreleases/archive.asp?id=2388&amp;fID=173 Childhood is changing, but "paedophobia" makes things worse] Institute for Public Policy Research. 22 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Waiton, S. (2006) [http://www.spiked-online.com/index.php?/site/article/2032/ ''The Roots of Paedophobia'']. Online. &lt;/ref&gt;  [[Pediaphobia]] is the fear of infants and children. Using this term to categorize fear of youth may dismiss the unique social position that youth occupy. Hebephobia (from Greek 'hebe' (ήβη) = youth) has also been proposed; however, no verifiable evidence is available to support that claim. Similar terms include [[adultism]], which is a predisposition towards adults that is biased against children and youth, and [[ageism]], which describes discrimination against any person because of their age.

==Impacts==

The effects of ephebiphobia appear to cause damage throughout society. At least one major economist has proposed that the fear of youth can have grave effects on the economic health of nations.&lt;ref&gt;Gray, D. (1999) [http://www.cnn.com/TECH/computing/9909/15/euro.risks.idg/ ''Negroponte: Europe's Net development held back by fear of youth, risk taking''] CNN. September 15, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; A growing number of researchers report that the fear of youth affects the health of [[democracy]], reporting that the consequential vilification of youth has in the past, and continues to presently undermine public,&lt;ref&gt;Jones, P., Shoemaker, S. Chelton, M. (2001) ''Do It Right! Best Practices for Serving Young Adults in School and Public Libraries'' New York: Neal-Schuman Publishers.&lt;/ref&gt; social, political,&lt;ref&gt;[[Lawrence Grossberg]], (2005) ''Caught In The Crossfire: Kids, Politics, And America's Future (Cultural Politics &amp; the Promise of Democracy)'' New York: Paradigm Publishers&lt;/ref&gt; and cultural&lt;ref&gt;Giroux, H. (2004) ''Take Back High Education: Race, Youth, and the Crisis of Democracy in the post-Civil Rights Era'' New York: Palgrave&lt;/ref&gt; participation among current and future generations.

Many social programs and social critics view ephebiphobia as a condemning force against youth throughout society, particularly when coupled with [[racism]] as it affects urban [[law enforcement]],&lt;ref&gt;Males, M. (2002) [http://home.earthlink.net/~mmales/epheb.htm "The New Demons: Ordinary teens"]. ''Los Angeles Times''. April 21, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Youth Media Council. (2005) [http://www.youthmediacouncil.org/pdfs/YMC-ReclaimMeaning.pdf Reclaiming Meaning, Echoing Justice]. Oakland, CA: Author.&lt;/ref&gt; schooling,&lt;ref&gt;Kozol, J. (2005) ''The Shame of a Nation: The Restoration of Apartheid Schooling in America''. New York: Three Rivers Press.&lt;/ref&gt; and media around the world&lt;ref&gt;Collins, J. (2002). [http://www.uts.edu.au/new/releases/2002/September/23.html ''Gangs, Crime and Community Safety: Perceptions and Experiences in Multicultural Sydney''] Sydney: University of Technology.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scottish Executive (2006) [http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2005/03/31141334/13366 Measurement of the Extent of Youth Crime in Scotland.]&lt;/ref&gt; The effects of [[sexism]] are similarly reported to be amplified by ephebiphobia.&lt;ref&gt;Bromwich, R.J. (2002) ''[http://www.owjn.org/issues/equality/girls.htm#_ftn1 Beyond Villains and Victims: Some Thoughts on Youth and Violence in Canada]'' Toronto, ON: Women's Justice Network.&lt;/ref&gt; 

As it effects young people themselves, ephebiphobia has been recognized as a barrier towards successful academic achievement,&lt;ref&gt;Butts, P.M. (2000) ''Beyond Ephebiphobia: Overcoming the Fear of Middle &amp; High School Students; A Program for Public Librarians.'' Macatawa, MI: Macatawa Public Library.&lt;/ref&gt; a barrier to successful social intervention programs,&lt;ref&gt;Astroth, K. (1994) Beyond ephebiphobia: problem adults or problem youths? (fear of adolescents). ''Phi Delta Kappan''. January 1, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; and as an indicator of the ineptitude of many adults to be successful parents.&lt;ref&gt;Coontz, S. (1999) ''The Way We Really Are: Coming to Terms With America's Changing Families.'' New York: Basic Books.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Academics acknowledge the force of ephebiphobia in the commercial&lt;ref&gt;Palladino, G. (1997) ''Teenagers: An American History.'' New York: Basic Books.&lt;/ref&gt; and governmental&lt;ref&gt;Giroux, H. (2003) ''The Abandoned Generation: Democracy beyond the culture of fear.'' New York: Palgrave.&lt;/ref&gt; sectors of society, where this fear of youth has been extensively exploited for financial gain. This is elaborated on by social critics who claim that popular media exacerbated society's fear of youth.&lt;ref&gt;"Studios caught in teen-age dilemmas Multiplex issues," Worcester Telegram &amp; Gazette (MA), July 20, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shary, T. (2002). ''Generation Multiplex: The Image of Youth in Contemporary American Cinema.'' Austin: University of Texas Press. p.4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Giroux, H. (1999) ''The Mouse that Roared: Disney and the End of Innocence''. New York: Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers.&lt;/ref&gt; That notion is supported by newspaper reports of the fear of youth as a driver of social policy.&lt;ref&gt;Parrish, G. (1999). [http://www.seattleweekly.com/news/9908/impolitics-parrish.php "Fear of Youth"], ''Seattle Weekly.'' February 29, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Street-Porter, J. (2005) "[http://comment.independent.co.uk/columnists_m_z/janet_street_porter/article613.ece The Politicians Fear of Youth Culture]", ''The Independent'' April 7, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; A number of observers have indicated the deliberate perpetuation of mass social ephebiphobia in order to elicit particular public and social responses.&lt;ref&gt;Males, M. (2001) [http://www.nospank.net/males2.htm "Lies, Damn Lies, and 'Youth Risk' Surveys"] ''Youth Today''. April 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- ==Political examples==

In an example that illustrates the relationship between [[adultcentrism]], [[gerontocracy]] and ephebiphobia, [[Iran]] recently raised its [[voting age]] from 15 to 18&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iranfocus.com/modules/news/article.php?storyid=9841&lt;/ref&gt;. The moved stemmed from the growing discontent among Iranian youth with their conservative and aging leadership. President [[Mahmoud Ahmadinejad]]'s [[hardline]] policies were humiliatingly defeated in local elections, stemming from the [[youth vote]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2007-01-13-iran-voting-age_x.htm&lt;/ref&gt;. It was rumored that polling of Iran's youth may have prompted the move by the [[Majlis]] and the quick approval by the Guardian's Council. Over 26% of Iran's population is 15 or under, and since the youth vote posed a threat to the ruling regime, the government demonstrated ephebiphobia when they postponed [[suffrage|youth suffrage]]. The Executive half-heartedly opposed the measure because they hope to make the youth "pillars of the revolution"&lt;ref&gt;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/1025045.cms&lt;/ref&gt;.

Other examples of this may include recent elections in the [[Philippines]]{{Fact|date=April 2007}}.
 --&gt;

==Examples of the fear of youth in popular culture==

*''A Tribe Apart: A Journey into the Heart of American Adolescence'' by Patricia Hersch
*[[Rosemary's Baby (film)|Rosemary's Baby]] (film)
*[[The Exorcist]] (film) and its first sequel, [[Exorcist II: The Heretic]]
*[[Carrie]] movie [[duology]]
*[[Children of the Corn]] (film)
*[[Chitty Chitty Bang Bang]]
*[[The Parent Trap]] (film)
*[[Battle Royale (film)|Battle Royale]] (film)
*[[List of movies about school|Many movies about school life]]
*[[List of songs about school|Many songs about school life]]
*[[The Bad Seed]] (film)
*[[The Omen]] and its first sequel, [[Damien: Omen II]]

==See also==
*[[Fear of children]]
*[[Adultism]]
*[[Ageism]] 
*[[Adultcentrism]]
*[[Youth rights]] 
*[[Jack Thompson (attorney)|Jack Thompson]]
*[[National Youth Rights Association]]
*[[ASFAR|Americans for a Society Free from Age Restrictions]]
*[[Moral panic]]
*[[Mean world syndrome]]
*[[Mass hysteria]]
*[[Herding instinct]]
*[[Social control]]
*[[Youth culture]]
*[[Youth voice]]
*[[List of youth subcultures]]
*[[Generation gap]]
*[[In loco parentis]]
*Holt, J. (1964) ''[[How Children Fail]].'' New York: Delta.
*Llewellyn, G. (n.d.) ''[[The Teenage Liberation Handbook|The Teenage Liberation Handbook: how to quit school and get a real life and education.]]

==External links==
*[http://freechild.org/SNAYR/Ephebiphobia.htm The Freechild Project webpage on Ephebiphobia.]

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==Related publications==
*(n.d.) [http://www.zmag.org/0009.htm Youth Liberation], ''Z'' magazine online.
*[http://www.youthrights.org/threetypes.php Three Types of Youth Liberation] - by Sven Bonnichsen
*[http://www.geocities.com/hatredsucks/upagainst.html Pro-Youth] - A firm text against ageism towards teenagers, presenting a case of ageism committed by a jury.
*[http://hrsbstaff.ednet.ns.ca/engramja/projects&amp;evals/sem2_mag1/chantellemag/chanceessay.htm Everyone deserves to be given a chance] - An essay against ageism towards teenagers, written by a Canadian adolescent.
*[http://research.unc.edu/endeavors/fall2005/grossberg.php "Are We Down On Our Kids?"] - A Review of ''Caught in the Crossfire: Kids, Politics, and America’s Future'' by [[Lawrence Grossberg]] in ''Endeavours'' magazine that diagnoses cultural ephebiphobia in the U.S.
*Ayotte, W. (1986) ''As Soon as You're Born They Make You Feel Small: Self Determination for Children.''
*Chicago Anarchist Youth Federation (n.d.) ''Schoolstoppers Textbook.''
*Cullen, S. (1991) ''Children in Society: a libertarian critique.'' London: Freedom Press.
*Goodman, P. (1964) ''Compulsory Mis-education and The Community of Scholars.'' New York: Vintage Books.
*Illich, I. (1970) ''Deschooling Society.'' New York: Harrow Books.
*Holt, J. (1972) ''Freedom and Beyond.'' New York: E.P. Dutton &amp; Co.
*Miller, A. (1990) ''For Your Own Good: Hidden cruelty in child-rearing and the roots of violence.'' 3rd edition. New York: Noonday Press.
 
{{Youth Empowerment}}
{{phobias}}

[[Category:Psychological conditions]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination]]
[[Category:Youth]]
[[Category:Aging]]
[[Category:Ageism]]
[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:Bias]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>