<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20230712231829|1165093365" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1597743" pageid="1597743" ns="0" title="Ephebiphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-07-12T23:24:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Fear of youth}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expand-social=yes}}
{{Youth rights sidebar}}
[[File:North Star staff and teens.jpg|thumb|A group of teens]]
'''Ephebiphobia''' is the fear of youth.  First coined as the "fear or loathing of teenagers",&lt;ref name="Astroth, K. 1994"&gt;Astroth, K. (1994) Beyond ephebiphobia: problem adults or problem youths? (fear of adolescents). ''Phi Delta Kappan''. January 1, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; today the [[phenomenon]] is recognized as the "inaccurate, exaggerated and sensational characterization of young people" in a range of settings around the world.&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, A.M. and Summers, R.W. (2001) ''Teen Violence: A Global View.'' Greenwood Press. p 2.&lt;/ref&gt; Studies of the fear of youth occur in [[sociology]] and [[youth studies]]. It is distinguished from [[Fear of children|pedophobia]] by being more focused on [[Adolescence|adolescents]] than [[Child|prepubescent children]].

==Lexicology==
===Coinage===
The word ''ephebiphobia'' is formed from the [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|ἔφηβος}} ''[[ephebos|éphēbos]]'', meaning "[[youth]]" or "[[adolescent]]" and {{lang|el|φόβος}} ''phóbos'', meaning "fear" or "[[phobia]]". The coinage of this term is attributed to a 1994 article by Kirk Astroth published in ''[[Phi Delta Kappan]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Gough, P. (2000) "Detoxifying Schools." ''Phi Delta Kappan''. March 1, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Today, common usage occurs internationally by sociologists, government agencies,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stop-discrimination.info/6423.0.html?&amp;no_cache=1&amp;mc_glossary%5Bcategories%5D=1 European Union's Stop Discrimination website - Glossary on age] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071017120531/http://stop-discrimination.info/6423.0.html?&amp;no_cache=1&amp;mc_glossary%5Bcategories%5D=1 |date=October 17, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and youth advocacy organizations that define ephebiphobia as an abnormal or irrational and persistent [[fear]] or loathing of teenagers or [[adolescence]].&lt;ref&gt;Grønnestad-Damur, W. &amp; Pratch, L. (n.d.) [https://web.archive.org/web/20060323044035/http://albertalibraryconference.com/2005/presentations/C4_ephibiphobia2.pdf ''No Ephebiphobia Here!''] Edmonton: Edmonton Public Library.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clark, C. (2004) ''Hurt: Inside the World of Today's Teenagers (Youth, Family, and Culture).'' Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Book House.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Similar terms===
====Analogous labels====
{{expand section|date=March 2020}}
The term ''paedophobia'' has gained popular acceptance in Europe to describe the aforementioned "fear of youth".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ippr.org/pressreleases/archive.asp?id=2388&amp;fID=173 Childhood is changing, but "paedophobia" makes things worse] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070904052625/http://www.ippr.org/pressreleases/archive.asp?id=2388&amp;fID=173 |date=2007-09-04 }} Institute for Public Policy Research. 22 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Waiton, S. (2006) [http://www.spiked-online.com/index.php?/site/article/2032/ ''The Roots of Paedophobia'']. Online.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Pediaphobia]]'' is the fear of infants and children. ''Hebephobia'' (from the Greek {{lang|grc|ἥβη}}, ''hḗbē'', "youth, puberty") has also been proposed{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}. Similar terms include ''[[adultism]]'', which is a predisposition towards adults that is biased against children and youth, and ''[[ageism]]'', which describes discrimination against any person because of their age.

====Juvenoia====
In the context of the 21st century, the [[neologism]] ''juvenoia'' has been used by publications such as ''[[The Christian Science Monitor]]'' to describe distaste and/or fear of the social culture associated with young people. The psychological distancing is prominently tied to advancements in technology and the exposure it facilitates to material that violates traditional values.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=https://www.csmonitor.com/The-Culture/Family/Modern-Parenthood/2013/0723/Juvenoia-The-kids-are-all-right-even-on-the-Internet|title = Juvenoia: The kids are all right, even on the Internet|journal = Christian Science Monitor|date = 23 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The fear of youth, along with fear of [[urban culture|street culture]] and the [[fear of crime]], is said to have been in [[Western culture]] for "time immemorial".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Pearson |first=G. |year=1983 |title=Hooligan: A History of Respectable Fears |location=London |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |page=236 |isbn=0-333-23399-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Machiavelli]] is said to have realized that a fear of youth is what kept the city of [[Florence]] from keeping a standing army.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Trexler |first=R. C. |year=1980 |title=Public Life in Renaissance Florence |location=Ithaca |publisher=Cornell University Press |page=390 |isbn=0-8014-2694-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ancient [[Venice]] and [[ancient Greece]] are also said to have had floundering public policy because of their fear of youth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Garland |first=Robert |year=1993 |title=Review of ''Ancient Youth: The Ambiguity of Youth and the Absence of Adolescence in Greco-Roman Society'' by M. Kleijwegt |journal=[[Journal of Hellenic Studies]] |volume=113 |pages=204–205 |doi=10.2307/632438 |jstor=632438 |s2cid=163442168 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Strauss |first=B. |year=1993 |title=Fathers and Sons in Athens: Ideology and Society in the Era of the Peloponnesian War |location=London |publisher=Routledge |page=16 |isbn=0-415-04146-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early American [[Puritan]]ism has been seen as reliant on a fear of youth, who were seen as embodying [[adventure]] and enlightenment, and therefore were viewed as susceptible to "decadent [[morality]]".&lt;ref&gt;Meily, C. (1911) ''Puritanism.'' C. H. Kerr &amp; Company. p 118.&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Industrial Revolution]],  [[Western Europe]]an and [[North America]]n popular media was particularly driven to propagate the [[Pedophobia (social phenomena)|fear of children]] and youth in order to further the [[industrialization]] of schooling,&lt;ref&gt;[[John Taylor Gatto|Gatto, J.T.]], (2001) ''The Underground History of American Education.'' Oxford Village Press.&lt;/ref&gt; and eventually to remove young people from the workplace when their [[child labor|labor]] became unnecessary due to [[mechanization]] and the influx of new labor.&lt;ref&gt;Savage, J. (2007) ''Teenage: The Creation of Youth Culture.'' Viking Adult.&lt;/ref&gt;

Post-[[World War II]] [[France]] was said to have been stricken by concern for ''mal de jeunesse'' when they created policies that reflected their fear of youth. "Send them to summer camps, place others in reformatories, the rest should have some fresh air, build some athletic fields..." were the intentions of youth policies in that era.&lt;ref&gt;Jobs, R.I. (2007) ''Riding the New Wave: Youth and the Rejuvenation of France After the Second World War''. Stanford University Press. p 230&lt;/ref&gt; Following World War II the United States military identified the growing number of youth in the [[Deep South]] as a problematic scenario for [[national security]]. Analysts have suggested the upswing in the popular culture's fear of youth may be attributed to defense policies created in response to that threat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-link=Angela Davis |first=Angela |last=Davis |chapter=The 'Youth Bulge' in the South |editor-last=Silliman |editor-first=J. |editor2-last=Bhattacharjee |editor2-first=A. |editor3-last=Davis |editor3-first=A. J. |year=2002 |title=Policing the National Body: Sex, Race, and Criminalization |location=Cambridge |publisher=[[South End Press]] |page=235 |isbn=0-89608-661-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

"In the 1990s public fear of adolescents mounted", caused by the "increased youth access to [[handgun]]s, the [[Syndicate|syndicatization]] of territorial youth [[gang]]s into illegal [[drug cartel]]s, racist [[stereotype|stereotyping]] of urban youth, academic and political pandering, media frenzy, and a spate of high-profile [[school shooting]]s of students by their fellow students".&lt;ref&gt;Rosenheim, M.K., Zimring, F.E. and Tanenhaus, D.S. (2002) ''A Century of Juvenile Justice.'' University of Chicago Press. p 282.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Seattle Weekly]]'' specifically cited the fear of youth as the driving factor behind [[Seattle, Washington]]'s now-defunct [[Teen Dance Ordinance]].&lt;ref&gt;Parrish, G. (1999). [http://www.seattleweekly.com/news/9908/impolitics-parrish.php "Fear of Youth"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130515082519/http://www.seattleweekly.com/news/9908/impolitics-parrish.php |date=2013-05-15 }}, ''Seattle Weekly.'' February 29, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; The government of Prime Minister [[Tony Blair]] introduced the [[Anti-Social Behaviour Order]] in 1998, which has also been attributed directly to a fear of youth.&lt;ref&gt;Street-Porter, J. (2005) "[http://comment.independent.co.uk/columnists_m_z/janet_street_porter/article613.ece The Politicians Fear of Youth Culture] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070930155733/http://comment.independent.co.uk/columnists_m_z/janet_street_porter/article613.ece |date=2007-09-30 }}", ''The Independent'' April 7, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Causes==
{{See also|Mid-Life Crisis#Characteristics|Baby Boom Generation#Aging and end-of-life issues}}

[[Mass media|Media]], marketers, politicians, [[youth work]]ers and researchers have been implicated in perpetuating the fear of youth.&lt;ref&gt;Fletcher, A. (2006) ''[http://www.commonaction.org/WYVH.pdf Washington Youth Voice Handbook] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080414023902/http://www.commonaction.org/WYVH.pdf |date=2008-04-14 }}''. CommonAction. p 11. Retrieved 6/3/08.&lt;/ref&gt; Since young people in [[developed country|developed countries]] are expected to stay out of the workforce, any role for them outside that of [[consumer]] is potentially threatening to adults.&lt;ref&gt;Sternheimer, K. (2006) ''Kids These Days: Facts and Fictions about Today's Youth''. Rowman &amp; Littlefield. p 140.&lt;/ref&gt; Selling safety to parents and teachers has also been a driving force, as home security systems, cellphones, and [[computer surveillance]] usage is marketed to parents; and [[X-ray]] machines, [[metal detector]]s and [[closed-circuit television]] are increasingly sold to schools on the premise that young people are not to be trusted. These steps are in spite of the fact that experience consistently shows that monitoring youth does little to prevent violence or tragedy: the [[Columbine High School massacre]] occurred in a building with video surveillance and in-building police.&lt;ref&gt;Sternheimer, K. (2006) p 146.&lt;/ref&gt;

The very creation of the terms [[youth]], [[adolescence]] and [[teenager]] have all been attributed to the fear of youth.&lt;ref&gt;Savage, J. (2007) ''Teenage: The Creation of Youth 1875-1945.'' Chatto &amp; Windus.&lt;/ref&gt; As the [[western world]] became more industrialized, young people were increasingly driven from the [[workforce]], including [[child labor|involuntary]] and voluntary positions, and into increasingly [[total institution]]s where they lost personal autonomy in favor of [[social control]].&lt;ref&gt;[[John Taylor Gatto|Gatto, J.T.]] (2001) ''The Underground History of American Education.'' Oxford Village Press. p 306.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Breeding, J. (2002) ''True nature and great misunderstandings: On How We Care for Our Children.'' Virtualbookworm Publishing. p 10.&lt;/ref&gt; Government policies outside of schools have been implicated as well, as over the last forty years [[curfew]]s, anti-[[loitering]] and anti-[[cruising (driving)|cruising]] laws, and other legislation apparently targeted at teenagers have taken hold across the country. Courts have increasingly ruled against [[youth rights]], as well.&lt;ref&gt;Lauter, P. and Howe, P. (1971) ''The conspiracy of the young.'' Meridian. p 304.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Epstein, R. (2007) ''The case against adolescence''. Quill Driver Books. p 323.&lt;/ref&gt; Before the 1940s "teenagers" were not listed in newspaper headlines, because as a group they did not exist. The impact of youth since [[World War II]] on western society has been immense, largely driven by marketing that proponents them as the "[[Other (philosophy)|Other]]". In turn, youth are caused to behave in ways that appear different from adults. This has led to the phenomenon of youth, and in turn has created a perpetuated fear of them.&lt;ref&gt;Palladino, G. (1996) ''Teenagers: An American perspective.'' BasicBooks. p 247.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effects==
The fear of youth is thought to exist throughout the entire [[Western world]].&lt;ref&gt;Konopka, G. (1983) ''Social Group Work: A Helping Process.'' Prentice Hall. p 40.&lt;/ref&gt; Sociologist [[Ray Oldenburg]] has attributed the [[generation gap]] and the "increasing segregation of youth from adults in [[American society]]" to "adult estrangement and fear of youth".&lt;ref&gt;Oldenburg, R. (1999) ''The Great Good Place: Cafés, Coffee Shops, Bookstores, Bars, Hair Salons.'' Marlowe &amp; Company. p xx.&lt;/ref&gt;

At least one major economist has proposed that the fear of youth can have grave effects on the economic health of nations.&lt;ref&gt;Gray, D. (1999) [http://www.cnn.com/TECH/computing/9909/15/euro.risks.idg/ ''Negroponte: Europe's Net development held back by fear of youth, risk taking''] CNN. September 15, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; A growing number of researchers report that the fear of youth affects the health of [[democracy]], reporting that the consequential vilification of youth has in the past, and continues to presently undermine public,&lt;ref&gt;Jones, P., Shoemaker, S. Chelton, M. (2001) ''Do It Right! Best Practices for Serving Young Adults in School and Public Libraries'' New York: Neal-Schuman Publishers.&lt;/ref&gt; social, political,&lt;ref&gt;[[Lawrence Grossberg]], (2005) ''Caught In The Crossfire: Kids, Politics, And America's Future (Cultural Politics &amp; the Promise of Democracy)'' New York: Paradigm Publishers&lt;/ref&gt; religious,&lt;ref&gt;Rice, W. (1998) ''Junior High Ministry: A Guide to Early Adolescence for Youth Workers.'' Zondervan Publishing. p 15.&lt;/ref&gt; and cultural&lt;ref&gt;Giroux, H. (2004) ''Take Back High Education: Race, Youth, and the Crisis of Democracy in the post-Civil Rights Era'' New York: Palgrave&lt;/ref&gt; participation among current and future generations.

As it affects young people themselves, ephebiphobia has been recognized as a barrier towards successful academic achievement,&lt;ref&gt;Butts, P.M. (2000) ''Beyond Ephebiphobia: Overcoming the Fear of Middle &amp; High School Students; A Program for Public Librarians.'' Macatawa, MI: Macatawa Public Library.&lt;/ref&gt; a barrier to successful social intervention programs,&lt;ref name="Astroth, K. 1994"/&gt; and as an indicator of the ineptitude of many adults to be successful parents.&lt;ref&gt;Coontz, S. (1999) ''The Way We Really Are: Coming to Terms With America's Changing Families.'' New York: Basic Books.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social discrimination===
"Today citizens as a whole as well as people who work with children live in fear of youth in our homes and schools and on our streets".&lt;ref&gt;Bender, S.J., Neutens, J., Skonie-Hardin, S., et al. (1997) ''Teaching health science: Elementary and middle school.'' Jones &amp; Bartlett Publishers. p 7.&lt;/ref&gt; While "society loves their attractive bodies, [[youth]]fulness and commercial firepower", we also "vilify adolescents as a noncontributing drain on the economy and our democracy". In the mainstream media, young people are most often portrayed as self-absorbed and [[Apathy|apathetic]], uninterested in the common good or in advancing social goals.&lt;ref&gt;Jee, K. and Sherman, R. (2006) [http://www.ncl.org/publications/ncr/95-1/fulltext1.pdf "Youth as important civic actors: From the margins to the center"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080515151632/http://www.ncl.org/publications/ncr/95-1/fulltext1.pdf |date=2008-05-15 }}, ''National Civic Review. 95'';1.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many social programs and social critics view the fear of youth as a condemning force against youth throughout society, particularly when coupled with [[racism]].&lt;ref&gt;Delgado, M. (2001) ''Where are All the Young Men and Women of Color?'' Columbia University Press. p 231.&lt;/ref&gt; Poet [[Gwendolyn Brooks]] was applauded for her consciousness-raising work around the fear of youth, particularly young African-Americans.&lt;ref&gt;Levingston, K. (2001) [http://www.brennancenter.org/content/resource/new_statistics_puncture_myth_of_violent_kids/ "New Statistics Puncture Myth of Violent Kids"], ''Philadelphia Inquirer.'' January 6, 2001. Retrieved 5/9/08.&lt;/ref&gt; Popular contemporary beliefs about adolescents are different from historical narratives; in the past youth were portrayed as "the future" and the "leaders of tomorrow"; today they are seen as "a source of worry, not potential," contributing to a fear of adolescents, especially racial and ethnic minorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Zeldin |first=S. |year=2002 |title=Sense of community and positive adult beliefs toward adolescents and youth policy in urban neighborhoods and small cities |journal=Journal of Youth and Adolescence |volume=31 |issue=5 |pages=331–342 |doi=10.1023/A:1015624507644 |s2cid=141934241 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In turn this [[racism|racist]] and [[adultism|adultist]] perspective informs urban law enforcement,&lt;ref&gt;Males, M. (2002) [http://home.earthlink.net/~mmales/epheb.htm "The New Demons: Ordinary teens"]. ''Los Angeles Times''. April 21, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Youth Media Council]]. (2005) [http://www.youthmediacouncil.org/pdfs/YMC-ReclaimMeaning.pdf Reclaiming Meaning, Echoing Justice] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061010002716/http://www.youthmediacouncil.org/pdfs/YMC-ReclaimMeaning.pdf |date=2006-10-10 }}. Oakland, CA: Author.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Collins, J. (2002). [http://www.uts.edu.au/new/releases/2002/September/23.html ''Gangs, Crime and Community Safety: Perceptions and Experiences in Multicultural Sydney''] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061231054711/http://www.uts.edu.au/new/releases/2002/September/23.html |date=2006-12-31 }} Sydney: University of Technology.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scottish Executive (2006) [http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Publications/2005/03/31141334/13366 Measurement of the Extent of Youth Crime in Scotland.]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Public school (government funded)|public schools]],&lt;ref&gt;Kozol, J. (2005) ''The Shame of a Nation: The Restoration of Apartheid Schooling in America''. New York: Three Rivers Press.&lt;/ref&gt; and social services.&lt;ref&gt;Abram, S. (2007) "Ephebiphobia," p 130 in Abram, S. ''Out Front with Stephen Abram: A Guide for Information Leaders.'' ALA Editions.&lt;/ref&gt; Sociologists have suggested that much of the current spread of the fear of youth is due to "adult anxiety over the shifting racial mix in the general population".&lt;ref&gt;Rapping, E. (2003) ''Law and Justice as Seen on TV.'' NYU Press. p 208.&lt;/ref&gt; The effects of [[sexism]] are similarly reported to be amplified by ephebiphobia.&lt;ref&gt;Bromwich, R.J. (2002) ''[http://www.owjn.org/issues/equality/girls.htm#_ftn1 Beyond Villains and Victims: Some Thoughts on Youth and Violence in Canada] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070214062437/http://www.owjn.org/issues/equality/girls.htm#_ftn1 |date=2007-02-14 }}.'' Toronto, ON: Women's Justice Network.&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[New York University]] professor Pedro Noguera has suggested that the fear of youth extends beyond color boundaries, as "[[skateboard]]ers, [[punk subculture|punks]], even straight-laced [[suburb]]an teenagers can evoke anxiety among adults by congregating in large numbers in places deemed off-limits to youth".&lt;ref&gt;Noguera, P. (2003) ''City Schools and the American Dream: Reclaiming the Promise of Public Education.'' Teachers College Press. p 127.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ability of youth to [[youth participation|participate]] throughout society is seen as compromised because of the fear of youth, and is often disguised as a [[paternalism]] or protectionism among adults.&lt;ref&gt;Fredman, S. and Spencer, S. (2003) ''Age as an Equality Issue.'' Hart Publishing. p 34.&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, scholar [[Henry Jenkins]], "links criticism of new media with fear of adolescents, who are the most eager adopters. [[Youth subculture|Teen culture]] seems meaningless and dangerous without an appreciation of its context".&lt;ref&gt;Tushnet, R. ([http://www.law.virginia.edu/pdf/workshops/0708/tushnet.pdf "Volunteers from the Audience: Audience Interests and the First Amendment,"] Georgetown University Law Center. p 3., footnote 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Commercial gain===
Academics specifically acknowledge the force of ephebiphobia in the [[commerce|commercial sector]], where this fear of youth has been extensively exploited for financial gain.&lt;ref&gt;Palladino, G. (1997) ''Teenagers: An American History.'' New York: Basic Books.&lt;/ref&gt; This is elaborated on by researchers and social critics who claim that popular media, including cinema and television, specifically exacerbated society's fear of youth for financial gain,&lt;ref&gt;"Studios caught in teen-age dilemmas Multiplex issues," Worcester Telegram &amp; Gazette (MA), July 20, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shary, T. (2002). ''Generation Multiplex: The Image of Youth in Contemporary American Cinema.'' Austin: University of Texas Press. p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Giroux, H. (1999) ''The Mouse that Roared: Disney and the End of Innocence''. New York: Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers.&lt;/ref&gt; as one study reports, "Extreme fear of youth is an established [[media panic]]".&lt;ref&gt;Hope, A. and Oliver, P. (2005) ''Risk, education and culture.'' Ashgate Publishing, Ltd. p 79.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pulp novel]]s in the 1950s were mass-produced to specifically cash in on the growing fear of youth that was spreading throughout society.&lt;ref&gt;Shary, T. (2005) ''Teen Movies: American Youth on Screen.'' Wallflower Press. p 20.&lt;/ref&gt; Ironically, it has also been said that popular media's effects on young people are not as powerful as the fear of youth, which drives the fear of technology and in turn perpetuates the fear of youth.&lt;ref&gt;Sternhiemer, S. (2003) ''It's Not the Media: The Truth about Pop Culture's Influence on Children.'' Westview Press. p 115.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Governmental policy===
Decision-making by government agencies, including [[Public school (government funded)|public schools]], [[police|policing]] and [[court]]s, have been found to be driven by the fear of youth.&lt;ref&gt;Giroux, H. (2003) ''The Abandoned Generation: Democracy beyond the culture of fear.'' New York: Palgrave.&lt;/ref&gt; The fear of adolescents has been said to cause a disjunction between what is said about the value of young people and what is done to them in education and social services, and causes them to be seen, "primarily as threats—to persons, to institutions, to [[status quo]]".&lt;ref&gt;Beker, J. and Magnuson, D. (1996) ''Residential Education as an Option for At-Risk Youth.'' Haworth Press. p 60.&lt;/ref&gt; A number of observers have indicated the deliberate perpetuation of mass social ephebiphobia in order to elicit particular public and social responses. [[United States|American]] sociologist [[Mike Males]] has identified trends among politicians and policy-makers of stoking the fear of youth among society in order to make headway in [[political campaign]]s and build popular support or otherwise "generate media sensation and public fear".&lt;ref&gt;Males, M. (2001) [http://www.nospank.net/males2.htm "Lies, Damn Lies, and 'Youth Risk' Surveys"] ''Youth Today''. April 2001&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the fear of youth has been identified as the driving factor behind many governmental programs designed to combat so-called "youth violence," in which the actions of few youth are attributed to the population of youth in general.&lt;ref&gt;Barak, G. (2003) ''Violence and Nonviolence: Pathways to Understanding''. Sage Publications Inc. p 132.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Collins, J., Noble, G., and Poynting, B. (2000) ''Kebabs, Kids, Cops and Crime: Youth, Ethnicity and Crime.'' Pluto Press Australia. p 122.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Walgrave, L. and Bazemore, B. (1999) ''Restorative Juvenile Justice: Repairing the Harm of Youth Crime.'' Criminal Justice Press. p 192.&lt;/ref&gt; In a specific instance, "In [[Dallas]], fear of youth led to accelerated surveillance and policing, particularly in its poorest area, [[Gaston Park|Gaston]]".&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, D. (2005) ''Inventing Black-on-Black Violence: Discourse, Space, and Representation.'' Syracuse University Press. p 144.&lt;/ref&gt; The fear of adolescents is also said to have caused many governments to lower their [[age of criminal responsibility]] and escalate the detention of young people from childhood through [[adult]]hood.&lt;ref&gt;Susskind, A. (1987) "Issues in Institutional Child Sexual Abuse The Abused, the Abuser, and the System," '' Residential Treatment for Children &amp; Youth. 4'';2. p 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Education===
Examining the [[Black Power]] movement of the 1970s, one researcher wrote, "The common adult dislike and fear of youth is compounded by the teacher's fear—fear of losing control in the classroom, fear of losing one's authority".&lt;ref&gt;Ornstein, A.C. (1972) ''Urban Education: Student Unrest, Teacher Behaviors, and Black Power.'' Charles E. Merrill Publishing Co. p 73.&lt;/ref&gt; A specific increase in the fear of youth in schools following the [[Columbine High School massacre]] of 1999 is seen as a particular cause in evidence suggesting an overall decrease in [[student engagement]] throughout [[high school]]s today.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, N. (2004) ''American Youth Cultures.'' Routledge. p 19.&lt;/ref&gt; Fear of youth has led to the development of [[zero tolerance]] policies in many schools,&lt;ref&gt;Lyons, W. and Drew, J. (2006) ''Punishing Schools: Fear And Citizenship In American Public Education.'' University of Michigan Press. p 4.&lt;/ref&gt; which in turn is attributed as the cause of the increase in arrests for [[Juvenile delinquency|juvenile crime]] on school campuses, which has promoted the fear of youth and led school administrators to call police for infractions once dealt with internally.&lt;ref&gt;Acland, C.R. (1995) ''Youth, Murder, Spectacle: The Cultural Politics of "youth in crisis".'' Westview Press. p 144.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Combating ephebiphobia==
The [[American Library Association]] has developed a resource collection for [[library|librarians]] specifically to combat the ephebiphobia by promoting [[customer service]] skills specific to youth.&lt;ref&gt;ALA President's Program. (1994) "Beyond Ephebiphobia: A tool chest for customer service to young adults". American Library Association.&lt;/ref&gt; However, sociologist Mike Males has suggested that ephebiphobia does not analyze the problem deep enough, as the fear of adult [[stereotype]] of [[adolescence]], or kourophobia, is the core challenge facing young people today.&lt;ref&gt;Males, M. (1999) ''Framing Youth: 10 myths about the next generation.'' Common Courage Press. p 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|colwidth=22em|
* [[Adultcentrism]]
* Americans for a Society Free from Age Restrictions
* [[Fear of children]]
* [[Herding instinct]]
* [[In loco parentis]]
* [[List of phobias]]
* [[List of youth subcultures]]
* [[Mass hysteria]]
* [[Moral panic]]
* [[Mosquito alarm]], an 'anti-loitering device' which plays high-frequency soundwaves specifically targeted towards children and teens
* [[National Youth Rights Association]]
* [[Social control]]
* "[[Help, My Teenager Hates Me!]]", an episode of the animated television series ''South Park'' dealing with the stereotypes of teenagers
* "[[Teenagers (song)|Teenagers]]", a My Chemical Romance song about the singer's fear of teenagers
* [[Youth culture]]
* [[Youth voice]]
* Holt, J. (1964) ''[[How Children Fail]].'' New York: Delta.
* Llewellyn, G. (n.d.) ''[[The Teenage Liberation Handbook|The Teenage Liberation Handbook: how to quit school and get a real life and education.]]''
}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* Lesko, N. (2001) ''Act Your Age!: A Cultural Construction of Adolescence.'' Routledge. {{ISBN|0-415-92833-8}}.
* (n.d.) [https://web.archive.org/web/20070213202808/http://www.zmag.org/0009.htm "Youth liberation"], ''Z'' magazine online.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110201231951/http://www.youthrights.org/threetypes.php Three Types of Youth Liberation] - by Sven Bonnichsen
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050216123535/http://www.geocities.com/hatredsucks/upagainst.html Pro-Youth] - A firm text against ageism towards teenagers, presenting a case of ageism committed by a jury.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20180418210246/http://hrsbstaff.ednet.ns.ca/engramja/projects%26evals/sem2_mag1/chantellemag/chanceessay.htm Everyone deserves to be given a chance] - An essay against ageism towards teenagers, written by a Canadian adolescent.
* [http://research.unc.edu/endeavors/fall2005/grossberg.php "Are We Down On Our Kids?"] - A Review of ''Caught in the Crossfire: Kids, Politics, and America's Future'' by [[Lawrence Grossberg]] in ''Endeavours'' magazine that diagnoses cultural ephebiphobia in the U.S.
* Ayotte, W. (1986) ''As Soon as You're Born They Make You Feel Small: Self Determination for Children.''
* Chicago Anarchist Youth Federation (n.d.) ''Schoolstoppers Textbook.''
* Cullen, S. (1991) ''Children in Society: a libertarian critique.'' London: Freedom Press.
* [[Paul Goodman|Goodman, P.]] (1964) ''[[Compulsory Miseducation]] and [[The Community of Scholars]].'' New York: Vintage Books.
* Illich, I. (1970) ''Deschooling Society.'' New York: [[Harper &amp; Row|Harrow Books]].
* Holt, J. (1972) ''Freedom and Beyond.'' New York: E.P. Dutton &amp; Co.
* Miller, A. (1990) ''For Your Own Good: Hidden cruelty in child-rearing and the roots of violence.'' 3rd edition. New York: Noonday Press.
* Sternheimer, K. (2006) ''Kids These Days: Facts and Fictions about Today's Youth.'' Rowman and Littlefield.

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|ephebiphobia}}
{{Wiktionary|hebephobia}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070708132109/http://freechild.org/SNAYR/Ephebiphobia.htm "Ephebiphobia,"] The Freechild Project.

{{Youth empowerment}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Youth]]
[[Category:Ageism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>