<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050901022753|22297370" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1597743" pageid="1597743" ns="0" title="Ephebiphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-09-01T02:28:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Ephebiphobia''' (from Greek '[[ephebos]]' &amp;#941;&amp;#966;&amp;#951;&amp;#946;&amp;#959;&amp;#962; = teenager, underage adolescent and 'fobos' &amp;#966;&amp;#972;&amp;#946;&amp;#959;&amp;#962; = fear, phobia), also known as '''hebephobia ('''from Greek 'hebe' (ήβη) = youth), denotes both the irrational [[fear]] of teenagers or of [[adolescence]], and the [[prejudice]] against teenagers or underage adolescents. It is essentially a social [[phobia]] comparable to [[xenophobia]] or [[homophobia]].

==Definitions==

'''Ephebiphobia''' can manifest in the following main categories :

* the irrational [[fear]] of being near, among or in the company of [[teenagers]];
* the [[prejudice]] on the grounds of [[age]] ([[ageism]]) towards [[teenagers]] or underage adolescents, or the [[discrimination]] derived from this prejudice;
* the [[fear]], [[prejudice]], [[hatred]], [[intolerance]] or [[discrimination]] referring to love relationships between adults and adolescents, either when it is the manifestation of [[ephebophilia]], of ephebosexuality, or when it is none of them; 
* the irrational [[fear]], [[panic]] or [[hysteria]], usually through the [[mass media]] (see [[culture of fear]]), relating to anything concerning the behavioral or social [[emancipation]] of underage adolescents (based on the belief that the adolescent's behavior is more appropriate for adults). 

The concept encompasses the irrational fear of a wide variety of issues, ranging from teenage sexuality, [[teenage pregnancy]], preteen pregnancy, and teen motherhood, to proposals to change the law and assure more [[youth rights]], like reducing the [[voting age]], the [[age of majority]], the [[drinking age]], the [[marriageable age]], the [[age of consent]], the [[age of candidacy]], eliminating [[curfew]] laws or assuring more students rights.

==Ageism against teenagers==

'''Ageism''' is [[discrimination]] against a person or group on the grounds of age. Although theoretically the word can refer to the [[discrimination]] against any age group, ageism usually comes in one of two forms: discrimination against [[youth]], and discrimination against the [[elderly]]. Ageism against youth is also known as "[[Adultism]]".

Some underage teenagers consider themselves victims of ageism and believe they should be treated more respectfully by adults and not as second-class citizens. Some complain that social [[stratification]] in age groups causes outsiders to incorrectly [[stereotype]] and generalize the group, to claim for instance that all adolescents are equally immature, violent or rebellious. Some have organized groups against ageism.

A growing number of sociologists address the issues of discrimination against youth, Adultism, and ephebiphobia as a digressive continuum for situating the conditions of adolescents throughout society.

==Pathological forms of ephebiphobia==

In extreme cases, pathological forms of ephebiphobia may be observed, especially when associated with violent acts (often but not always resulting in criminal acts).

Possible pathological behaviors include, among others, the following :

* incarcerating teenagers or underage adolescents at home for a long period of time, or through the use of handcuffs (in any period of time), usually to prevent them from going out to parties, to the mall, to the movie theatre or to any  place where they could potentially develop a social or a love relationship; 

* vigorously humiliating an underage adolescent in public; 

* compulsively or obsessively hiding a pregnant teen or preteen from public observation (as if she had a contagious disease), especially when moving or traveling to another place (neighborhood, city, region or country) solely with the purpose of hiding the pregnancy; 

* forcefully inducing or coercing an underage adolescent to have an abortion, by the means of violence, use of terror or threats of any kind (as if the baby were property of the perpetrator or threatener). 

==Sources==

* Shelley Wu, PhD, psychologist and professor at the University of Pennsylvania - in ''[http://psychology.about.com/cs/glossaries/g/Ephebiphobia.htm About.com Psychology Glossary]'' 

* Mike Males - ''"The New Demons: Ordinary Teens" - Los Angeles Times, April 21, 2002'' (see "External Links")

* Wendy Grønnestad-Damur and Lindy Pratch - presenters of the [http://albertalibraryconference.com/schedule1.html Alberta, Canada, Library Conference] ''"No Ephebiphobia Here! Ephebiphobia: an abnormal and persistent fear of teenagers"'' (April 30, 2005).

* Thimothy Shary, visitant assistant professor of screen studies at Department of Visual and Performing Arts at Clark University - source used for the news article ''Studios caught in teen-age dilemmas Multiplex issues'' (Worcester Telegram &amp; Gazette (MA) - July 20, 2001) (see [http://www.newslibrary.com/ Newslibrary.com])

* '''Ephebiphobia''' is listed in the National Youth Rights Association's [http://www.youthrights.net/index.php?title=Youth_Rights_Glossary Glossary]. The NYRA website is affiliated to the Wikipedian system.

==External links==

* http://www.youthrights.org/ - National Youth Rights Association, "the last civil rights movement".
* '''[http://www.youthrights.net/ YouthRights.net]''' - the National Youth Rights Association's website '''affiliated to the Wikipedian system'''.
* [http://www.asfar.org/ ASFAR.org] - an organization dedicated to protecting and advancing the legal civil rights of youth. ASFAR fights for eliminating age discrimination (ageism) and reducing the voting age, curfew laws, age of majority, age of consent, emancipation (see also marriageable age), freedom of speech and other laws that limit the freedom of young people .

* [http://www.youthrights.net/index.php?title=Three_Types_of_Youth_Liberation%28article%29 Three Types of Youth Liberation] - by Sven Bonnichsen
* [http://www.geocities.com/hatredsucks/upagainst.html Pro-Youth] - A firm text against ageism towards teenagers, presenting a case of ageism committed by a jury.

* [http://hrsbstaff.ednet.ns.ca/engramja/projects&amp;evals/sem2_mag1/chantellemag/chanceessay.htm Everyone deserves to be given a chance] - An essay against ageism towards teenagers, written by a Canadian adolescent. 

* [http://home.earthlink.net/~mmales/epheb.htm The new demons : ordinary teens] - by Mike Males. Published in the Los Angeles Times (Apr 21, 2002).

* [http://www.freechild.org/SNAYR/Ephebiphobia.htm The FreeChild Project's page on Ephebiphobia] - FreeChild Project : promoting young people and social change.

* [http://www.changingworldviews.com/GuestCommentaries/DebraRaearticle6.htm Changing worldviews] - by Debra Rae, author of ''"ABCs of Globalism"''.

* [http://www.joe.org/joe/1993fall/a6.html Are Youth at Risk ?] - by Kirk A. Astroth. Article published in the ''Journal of Extension'' (Fall 1993) of the Montana State University.

* [http://home.comcast.net/~egallaway/professional/govdum.htm Now That They've Come, How Do We Make Them Behave?], by Beth Gallaway (Sept. 2003). Workshop at Governor Dummer Academy, YA Librarian Haverhill Public Library Haverhill MA.

==Some additional newspaper articles covering ephebiphobia==

* Articles listed in the [http://www.newslibrary.com/ Newslibrary.com] databank.

* ''"BOXED IN - No longer kids, not yet adults: Teens struggle for rights in a wary society"'', published in the Dallas Morning News (TX) - Dec. 15, 2002.

* ''"Studios caught in teen-age dilemmas Multiplex issues"'' - Worcester Telegram &amp; Gazette (MA) - July 20, 2001 

* ''"Kids these days,  Good works win Alaska teens Spirit of Youth awards"'', published in the Anchorage Daily News (AK) - Jan. 24, 2005.

==See also==

*[[ephebophilia]] 
*[[phobia]] 
*[[adultism]]
*[[ageism]] 
*[[discrimination]] 
*[[Youth Rights]] 
*[[National Youth Rights Association]]
*[[ASFAR]] - Americans for a Society Free from Age Restrictions</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>