<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113160838|87555863" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11185" pageid="11185" ns="0" title="Feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T16:09:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism}}

{{weasel words}}


'''Feminism''' is a diverse collection of [[social theory|social theories]], [[political movement]]s and [[ethics|moral philosophies]], largely motivated by or concerned with the experiences of women. Most feminists are especially concerned with social, political and economic inequality between men and women (in the context of it being to the disadvantage of women); some have argued that gendered and sexed identities, such as "man" and "woman", are [[Social construction|socially constructed]]. Feminists differ over the sources of inequality, how to attain equality, and the extent to which gender and gender-based identities should be questioned and critiqued. In simple terms, feminism is the belief in social, political and economic equality of the sexes, and the movement organised around the belief that gender should not be the pre-determinant factor shaping a person's social identity, or socio-political or economic rights.

Most modern feminist political [[activism|activists]] commonly campaign on issues such as [[reproductive rights]] (including the right to safe, legal [[abortion]], access to [[Birth control|contraception]] and quality [[prenatal care]]), [[domestic violence|violence]] within a [[domestic partnership]], [[parental leave|maternity leave]], [[equal pay for women|equal pay]], [[sexual harassment]], [[street harassment]], [[discrimination]] and [[rape]]. Many feminists today argue that feminism is a [[Grassroots democracy|grass-roots]] movement that seeks to cross boundaries based on social class, race, [[culture]] and [[religion]]. They also argue that an effective feminist movement should be culturally specific and address issues relevant to the women of the [[society]] in question such as [[female genital cutting]], or "clitorectomies", in [[Africa]] and the [[Middle East]] and the "[[glass ceiling]]" issue in developed economies. They also debate the extent to which certain issues such as [[rape]], [[incest]] and [[Mother|mothering]] are universal. Themes explored in feminism include [[patriarchy]], [[Stereotype|stereotyping]], [[objectification]], [[sexual objectification]] and [[oppression]].

==Origins==
{{main|History of feminism}}
How long feminism has been around is a different question to when history has marked feminism as beginning. Modern feminism as a [[philosophy]] and movement is often dated to [[Age of Enlightenment|The Enlightenment]] with such thinkers as [[Lady Mary Wortley Montagu]] and the [[Marquis de Condorcet]] championing women's education. The first [[scientific society]] for women was founded in [[Middelburg]], a city in the south of the [[Dutch Republic]] in [[1785]]. Journals for women which focused on issues like science became popular during this period as well. [[Mary Wollstonecraft]]'s ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Woman]]'' ([[1792]]) is one of the first works that can unambiguously be called feminist.

[[Image:Early_feminists.jpg|thumb|250px|First International Convention of Women in [[Washington D.C.]] [[Susan B. Anthony]] is third from the left, front row.]]

Feminism became an organized movement in the [[19th century]] as people increasingly came to believe that women were being treated unfairly. The feminist movement was rooted in the progressive movement and especially in the [[reform movement]] of the [[19th century]]. The [[Utopian socialism|utopian socialist]] [[Charles Fourier]] coined the word ''féminisme'' in [[1837]], and had argued that the extension of [[women's rights]] underpinned all social progress as early as [[1808]]. The organized movement was dated from the first women's rights convention at [[Seneca Falls convention|Seneca Falls]], New York in [[1848]]. In 1869, [[John Stuart Mill]] published [[The Subjection of Women]] to demonstrate that "the legal subordination of one sex to the other is wrong...and...one of the chief hindrances to human improvement."

Many countries began to grant women the [[suffrage|vote]] in the late [[19th century]] and early [[20th century]] ([[New Zealand]] being first in 1893, with the help of suffragist [[Kate Sheppard]]), especially in the final years of the [[World War I|First World War]] onwards. The reasons varied, but they included a desire to recognize the contributions of women during the war, and were also influenced by rhetoric used by both sides at the time to justify their war efforts. For example, since [[Woodrow Wilson]]'s [[Fourteen Points]] recognized self-determination as vital to society, the hypocrisy of denying half the population of modern nations the vote became difficult to ignore.

==Feminism in many forms==
Some feminist theories question basic assumptions about gender, gender difference and sexuality, including the category of "woman" itself as a [[holism|holistic]] concept, other theories question the male/female dichotomy completely (offering instead a multiplicity of genders). Still other feminist theories take for granted the concept of "woman" and provide specific analyses and critiques of [[gender]] [[inequality]], and most feminist social movements promote women's [[right]]s, interests and issues. Several subtypes of feminist ideology have developed over the years. Early feminists and primary feminist movements are often called the [[first-wave feminism|first-wave feminists]], and feminists after about [[1960]] the [[second-wave feminism|second-wave feminists]]. More recently, some younger feminists have identified themselves as  [[third-wave feminism|third-wave feminists]] while the second-wave feminists are still active.

In her book ''A Fearful Freedom: Women's Flight from Equality'', [[Wendy Kaminer]] identifies another conflict between forms of feminism: the
conflict between what she calls "egalitarian" and "protectionist" feminism. She sees egalitarian feminism as promoting equality between women and men through the granting of equal [[rights]]. Protectionist feminists prefer to focus on legal protections for women, such as [[labor law|employment laws]] and [[divorce]] laws that protect women, sometimes advocating restricting men's rights, such as [[free speech]] (specifically, the right to produce and consume pornography). Though the book predates third-wave feminism, Kaminer identifies both protectionist and egalitarian currents within first-wave feminism and second-wave feminism.

Some radical feminists, such as [[Mary Daly]], [[Charlotte Bunch]] and [[Marilyn Frye]], have advocated [[separatism]]&amp;mdash;a complete separation of male and female in society and culture&amp;mdash;while others question not only the relationship between men and women, but the very meaning of "man" and "woman" as well (see [[Queer theory]]). Some argue that [[gender role]]s, [[gender identity]] and sexuality are themselves [[social constructionism|social constructs]] (see also [[heteronormativity]]). For these feminists, feminism is a primary means to human liberation (i.e., the liberation of men as well as women.)

Many&amp;mdash; certainly not all&amp;mdash; feminists are women. There are exclusively
male organisations sympathetic to the feminist view who believe the dominant model of manhood or masculinity is oppressive to women and
limiting for men.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.menstuff.org/resources/resourcefiles/femenist.html Feminist/Pro-Feminist links], The National Men's Resource Center&lt;/ref&gt;

There is debate ''about'' feminism concerning which types should exclusively be labeled or considered. There are also overlapping beliefs such as in oppression by patriarchy and/or capitalism, and the belief they are synonymous.

===Subtypes of feminism===
{{Political ideology entry points}}
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
{| style="background-color: transparent; width: {{{width|80%}}}"
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
| width="{{{width|}}}" align="{{{align|left}}}" valign="{{{valign|top}}}" |
*[[African feminism]]
*[[Amazon feminism]]
*[[Anarcha-Feminism]]
*[[Anti-racist feminism]]
*[[Black Feminism]]
*[[Chicana feminism|Chicana Feminism]]
*[[cultural feminism]]
*[[Difference feminism]]
*[[ecofeminism]]
*[[existentialist feminism]]
*[[feminism in Japan]]
*[[feminism in Poland]]
*[[French feminism]]
*[[individualist feminism]] (also known as libertarian feminism)
*[[Islamic feminism]]
*[[lesbian feminism]]
*[[liberal feminism]]
*male feminism or [[Pro-feminist men]]

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
| width="{{{width|}}}" align="{{{align|left}}}" valign="{{{valign|top}}}" |

*[[Marxist feminism]] (related to socialist feminism)
*[[material feminism]]
*[[New feminism]]
*[[pop feminism]]
*[[Postcolonial feminism|post-colonial feminism]]
*[[postmodern feminism]] which includes [[queer theory]]
*[[pro-sex feminism]] (also known as sexually liberal feminism, sex-positive feminism, do me feminism)
*[[psychoanalytical feminism|psychoanalytic feminism]]
*[[radical feminism]]
*[[separatist feminism]]
*[[socialist feminism]]
*[[spiritual feminism]]
*[[standpoint feminism]]
*[[third-world feminism]]
*[[transnational feminism]]
*[[transfeminism]]
*[[womanism]]
*Certain actions, approaches and people can also be described as [[proto-feminism|proto-feminist]] or [[post-feminism|post-feminist]].
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
|}

==Relationship to other movements==
Some feminists take a holistic approach to politics, believing the saying of [[Martin Luther King Jr.]], "A threat to justice anywhere is a threat to justice everywhere". In that belief, some self-identified feminists support other movements such as the [[civil rights]] movement and the [[gay rights movement]]. At the same time, many black feminists such as [[bell hooks]] criticize the movement for being dominated by white women. Feminist claims about the alleged disadvantages women face in Western society are often less relevant to the lives of black women. This idea is the key in [[postcolonial feminism]]. Many black feminist women prefer the term [[womanism]] for their views.

Feminism is often linked with gay, [[lesbian]] and transgender studies and [[Psychoanalytic feminism]] places focus on [[psychosexual]] development. Some feminists are wary of the [[transgender]] movement because they view it as challenging the distinction between men and women. Transgender and [[transsexual]] individuals who identify as female are excluded from some "[[Women-only spaces|women-only]]" gatherings and events and are rejected by some feminists, who say that no one who was assigned as male at birth can fully understand the oppression that women face. This exclusion is criticized as "[[transphobic]]" by other feminists and transgender people alike, who assert that their political and social struggles are linked to those of feminists, and that discrimination against gender-variant people is a facet of the [[patriarchy]]. (See [[transfeminism]] and [[gender studies]].)

In the 1800s the women's rights movement in the United States splintered over questions concerning the passage of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth]] and [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fifteenth]] Amendments to the United States Consititution granting African American men the right to vote. [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] and [[Susan B. Anthony]], among others, contended that black men should not be franchised unless similar rights were granted to ''all'' women. From 1868 to 1870, when the [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|15th Amendment]] was passed, this created division in the broader U.S. civil rights movement and, in 1869, caused a schism the women's suffrage movement, leading to the creation of the separate [[National Woman's Suffrage Association]] (NWSA) and the [[National American Suffrage Association|American Woman's Suffrage Association]] (AWSA) in the United States.

== Modern feminism ==
Most feminists believe discrimination against women still exists worldwide. But there is disagreement within the movement regarding the severity of current problems, what the problems are, and how to confront them.{{fact}}

Extremes on the one hand include some radical feminists such as [[Gloria Allred]] and [[Mary Daly]] who argue that human society would be better off with dramatically fewer men. There are also dissidents, such as [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] or [[Camille Paglia]], who identify themselves as feminist but who accuse the movement of anti-male prejudice. 	 
	 
Many feminists question the use of the term ''feminist'' to groups or people who fail to recognize a fundamental equality between the sexes. Some feminists, like [[Katha Pollitt]] (see her book ''[[Reasonable Creatures]]'') or [[Nadine Strossen]] (President of the [[ACLU]] and author of ''Defending Pornography'' [a treatise on freedom of speech]), consider feminism to be simply that "women are people." Views that separate the sexes rather than unite them are considered by these people to be ''sexist'' rather than ''feminist''. 	 
	 
There are also debates between [[difference feminism|difference feminists]] such as [[Carol Gilligan]] on the one hand, who believe that there are important differences between the sexes (which may or may not be inherent, but which cannot be ignored), and those who believe that there are no essential differences between the sexes, and that the roles observed in society are due to conditioning. 	 
	 
In Marilyn French's seminal works analyzing [[patriarchy]] and its effects on the world at large, she defines patriarchy as a system that values power over life, control over pleasure and dominance over happiness. According to French, "it is not enough either to devise a morality that will allow the human race simply to survive. Survival is an evil when it entails existing in a state of wretchedness. Intrinsic to survival and continuation is felicity/pleasure. Pleasure has been much maligned, diminished by philosophers and conquerors as a value for the timid, the small-minded and the self-indulgent. "Virtue" too often involves the renunciation of pleasure in the name of some higher purpose, a purpose that involves power (for men) or sacrifice (for women). Pleasure is described as shallow and frivolous in a world of high-minded, serious purpose. But pleasure does not exclude serious pursuits or intentions, indeed, it is found in them, and it is the only real reason for staying alive.".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=French |first=Marilyn |date=1985 |url=http://www.fragmentsweb.org/stuff/10french.html |title=Beyond Power}}&lt;/ref&gt; This philosophy is what Marilyn French offers as a replacement to the current structure where power has the highest value. 	 
	 
[[Carol Tavris]], author of ''Anger: the Misunderstood Emotion'' and ''The Mismeasure of Woman: Why Women Are Not the Better Sex, the Inferior Sex, or the Opposite Sex'', maintains that as long as men's experiences are considered to be the default human experiences, women will always face discrimination in North America or elsewhere. She holds that too much emphasis is placed on innate differences between men and woman, and that it has been used to justify the restriction of women's rights.

==Effects of feminism in the West==
While a number of feminists argue that there are many battles for equity to be waged, others disagree and observe that many challenges have been overcome. For example, in developed nations, women now outnumber men in both high school graduation rates [http://www.manhattan-institute.org/html/cr_48.htm] and university enrollment [http://www.statcan.ca/Daily/English/051011/d051011b.htm]. Women are admitted to professional schools at rates equal to or greater than males, the only notable exception being dentistry.  {{fact}}

===Effects on civil rights===
[[Image:Opposed to suffrage.jpg|right|frame|Securing women's suffrage has been a defining issue for the feminist movement.]]
Feminism has effected many changes in Western society, including [[women's suffrage]], broad employment for women at more equitable wages, the right to initiate [[divorce]] proceedings and the introduction of [[No fault divorce|"no fault" divorce]], the right to obtain contraception and safe abortions, and the right to [[university]] education.

===Effect on language===
Many [[English language|English]]-speaking feminists are often proponents of what they consider to be [[non-sexist language]], using "[[Ms.]]" to refer to both married and unmarried women or "he or she" (or other [[gender-neutral pronouns]]) in place of "he" where the gender is unknown.
Feminists are also often proponents of using ''gender-inclusive'' language, such as "humanity" instead of "mankind".
Feminists in most cases advance their desired use of language either to promote what they claim is an equal and respectful treatment of women or to affect the tone of political discourse. This can be seen as a move to change language which has been viewed by some feminists as imbued with sexism, providing for example the case in the [[English language]] in which the word for the general pronoun is "he" or "his" (''The child should have his paper and pencils''), which is the same as the masculine pronoun (''The boy and his truck''). These feminists argue that language then directly affects perception of reality (compare [[Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis]]).

In postcolonial feminism the issue of language is often less emphasized as many non-[[Indo-European languages]] do not have grammatical gender.

A different tendency can be seen in feminism inspired changes to the [[French language]]. Grammatical gender is much more pervasive in French than in English, making it virtually impossible to create inclusive language. Instead, nouns that originally had only a masculine form have had feminine counterparts created for them. "''Professeur''" ("teacher"), once always masculine regardless of the teacher's sex, now has a parallel feminine form "''Professeure''". In cases where separate masculine and feminine forms have always existed, it was once standard practice for a group containing both men and women to be referred to using the masculine plural. Nowadays, forms such as "''Tous les Canadiens et Canadiennes''" ("all Canadians", or literally "all the male Canadians and female Canadians") are becoming more common. Such phrasing is common in [[Canada]] and in France, where President Jacques Chirac routinely uses "Françaises et Français" (French women and French men) in political speeches, but is practically unknown in other French-speaking countries.

An equivalent tendency in [[Germany]] where male and female terms are both required in the plural is to use the male term, followed by the female plural ending.  An example of this is instead of the bulky phrase ''sehr geehrte Kollegen und Kolleginnen'', meaning ''dear male colleagues and female colleagues'', is the use of ''sehr geehrte KollegInnen'', which expresses the plurality of both genders.

===Effect on heterosexual relationships===

The entry of women into the workplace and the demands of child-rearing has modified gender roles.
Some men argue that the de-emphasis on their being a primary provider harms their ability to attract mates. Furthermore, while many women have the choice to try to "have it all," they argue that societal expectations placed upon men preclude them from devoting themselves fully to domestic activities and child-rearing. Several studies support this belief, and point out the fact that although men are derided for not devoting enough time to childrearing and domestic tasks, few women seem attracted to men who engage in these activities to the detriment of their careers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/klu/aseb/1997/00000026/00000003/00423348 "The Perception of Sexual Attractiveness: Sex Differences in Variability"] by Townsend J.M.; Wasserman T., Archives of Sexual Behavior, Volume 26, Number 3, June 1997, pp. 243-268(26) McGraw, Kevin J. (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/servlet/useragent?func=synergy&amp;synergyAction=showAbstract&amp;doi=10.1046/j.1439-0310.2002.00757.x "Environmental Predictors of Geographic Variation in Human Mating Preferences."] Ethology 108 (4), 303-317.
''In Defense of Working Fathers'' [http://www.hisside.com/7_10_05.htm Sacks, Glenn]. &lt;/ref&gt;
Some argue that men devote less time to household chores because they devote more time to work outside the home. According to the International Labor Organization, "the average American father works 51 hours a week, whereas those mothers of young children who do work full time (themselves in the minority) work a 41-hour week.".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sacks  |first=Glenn | date= [[2006-05-17]] |url=http://www.glennsacks.com/is_pay_a.htm |title=Is Pay a Function of Gender Bias? |accessyear=2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been argued that women often hold the power in a relationship because they direct the majority of purchases made by a household, whereas men direct the few large purchases.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reparateme.com ReparateMe.com], "[http://www.reparateme.com/story51.html Stop Polarizing the Sexes]"&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sociologist]] [[Arlie Russell Hochschild]] attempted to counter these arguments with her books ''The Second Shift'' and ''The Time Bind.'' These books present some evidence that married men might contribute more time to their wives than to child care and housework. However, Hochschild's statistical evidence did not apply to two-career couples. According to the studies she cites, in two-career couples, men and women on the average spend about equal amounts of time working, but women still spend more time on housework. Feminist critiques of men's contributions to child care and domestic labor are typically centered around the idea that it is unfair for women to be expected to perform more than half of a household's domestic work and child care when both members of the relationship also work outside the home. Several studies provide statistical evidence that married men may contribute a smaller share of housework, regardless of whether or not they earn more than their wives.&lt;ref&gt;Scott J. South and Glenna Spitze, "Housework in Marital and Nonmarital Households," ''American Sociological Review'' 59, no. 3 (1994):327-348&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Fenstermaker Berk and Anthony Shih, "Contributions to Household Labor: Comparing Wives' and Husbands' Reports,", in Berk, ed., ''Women and Household Labor''&lt;/ref&gt; However, in general, in couples where one or both partners do not work outside the home, gender-based [[division of labor]] is less of a point of contention for feminists.

It should be noted that the preceding arguments mainly apply to [[middle-class]] women.

In her 1996 book ''Dubious Conceptions'', [[Kristin Luker]] discusses the effect of feminism on teenage women's choices to bear a child, both in and out of wedlock. She argues that as childbearing without being married has become more socially acceptable for women, young women, while not bearing children at a higher rate than in the 1950s, now see less reason to get married before having a child, especially in the case of poor young women. To explain this, she argues that the economic prospects for poor men are slim, and so poor women have a low chance of finding a husband who will be able to provide reliable financial support.

There have also been changes in attitudes towards sexual morality and behavior with the onset of second wave feminism and "[[Oral contraceptive|the Pill]]." Women are more in control of their bodies, and are freer to experience sex with fewer repercussions. This [[sexual revolution]] was seen as positive (especially by [[Sexually liberal feminism|sex-positive feminists]]) as it enabled women and men to experience sex in a free and equal manner.

[[Evangelical Feminism|Evangelical (Christian) feminists]] sometimes argue that life-long monogamy ideally promotes [[egalitarianism]] in sex, especially when viewed in light of some other alternatives to monogamy (e.g., [[polygyny|polygamy]], [[swinging]], [[open marriage]]s, or [[infidelity]]). However, some feminists endorse [[polyamory]], [[open marriage]], [[cohabitation]] and [[swinging]] as egalitarian lifestyles (see [[sex-positive feminism]]).

[[Friedrich Engels]], in his essay ''[[The Origin of the Family, Private Property, and the State]]'' expresses his belief that monogamy was originally conceived as a way for men to control women. However, scientific evidence strongly suggests that monogamy evolved as a way to ensure the survival of human infants, who are born relatively vulnerable in comparison to other animal species, and need care from both men and women in their early development.

===Effect on religion===
{{main|God and gender}}
Feminism has had a great effect on many aspects of [[religion]]. In liberal branches of [[Protestant Christianity]] (and, notably, in some theologically conservative dominations, such as [[Assemblies of God]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| date=[[1990-08-14]] |url=http://ag.org/top/beliefs/position_papers/pp_downloads/pp_4191_women_ministry.pdf |title=The Role of Women in Ministry |format=[[PDF]] |pages=7 |publisher=The General Council of the Assemblies of God}}&lt;/ref&gt;) women are ordained as [[clergy]]{{fact}}, and in [[Reform Judaism|Reform]], [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] and [[Reconstructionist Judaism|Reconstructionist]] [[Judaism]], women are ordained as [[rabbi]]s and [[Hazzan|cantor]]s{{fact}}. Within these [[Christianity|Christian]] and [[Judaism|Jewish]] groups, women have gradually become more equal to men by obtaining positions of power; their perspectives are now sought out in developing new statements of belief{{fact}}.

The leadership of women in religious matters has also been resisted within [[Roman Catholicism]]. Roman Catholicism has historically excluded women from entering the priesthood and other clerical positions, limiting women to the roles of nuns or laypeople.

Feminism also has had an important role in embracing new forms of religion. [[Neopagan]] religions especially tend to emphasize the importance of [[Goddess]] spirituality, and question what they regard as traditional religion's hostility to women and the sacred feminine. In particular, [[Dianic Wicca]]'s origins lie within [[radical feminism]]. Among traditional religions, feminism has led to self examination, with reclaimed positive Christian and Islamic views and ideals of [[Mary, mother of Jesus|Mary]], Islamic views of [[Fatima Zahra]], and especially the Catholic belief in the [[Coredemptrix]], as counterexamples.

==Worldwide statistics==

 {| cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" border="1" valign="top" align=right
|+ '''Female share of seats in elected national chambers in November 2004 (percent)'''
|[[Rwanda]]||49.0 || ||[[Iceland]]||30.2
|-
|[[Sweden]]||45.3 || ||[[New Zealand]]||28.3
|-
|[[South Africa]]||42.0 || ||[[Austria]]||27.5
|-
|[[Namibia]]||42.0 || ||[[Pakistan]]||21.3&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rizvi |first=Muddassir | date=[[2002-10-15]] |url=http://www.ipsnews.net/interna.asp?idnews=12918 |title=Women Win Record Seats, But Not Activists' Hearts |publisher=[[Inter Press Service]] |accessdate=2006-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[Denmark]]||38.0 || ||[[Canada]]||21.1
|-
|[[Finland]]||37.5 || ||[[People's Republic of China|China]]||20.2
|-
|[[Norway]]||36.4 || ||[[United Kingdom|UK]](Commons)||17.8
|-
|[[Spain]]||36.0 || ||[[Mauritius]]||17.0
|-
|[[Netherlands]]||35.0 || ||[[United States]]||15.0
|-
|[[Germany]]||32.8 || ||[[Japan]]||7.1
|-
|}
The following is a sampling of statistics related to the relative status of women worldwide.

*According to studies cited by the [[United Nations]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2004 |url=http://hdr.undp.org/reports/global/2004/pdf/hdr04_HDI.pdf |title=Section 28, Gender, Work Burden, and Time Allocation |format=[[PDF]] |work=United Nations Human Development Report 2004: Section 28 |publisher=[[United Nations]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; on average, women work more than men, when both paid employment and unpaid household tasks are accounted for. In rural areas of selected developing countries, women performed an average of 20% more work than men, or an additional 102 minutes per day. In the OECD countries surveyed, on average women performed 5% more work than men, or 20 minutes per day.
*By population, women are underrepresented in all of the world's major legislative bodies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/world.htm Women in National Parliaments, November 2004]&lt;/ref&gt; In [[1985]], [[Finland]] had the largest percentage of women in national legislature at approximately 32 percent (P. Norris, Women&lt;nowiki&gt;'s&lt;/nowiki&gt; Legislative Participation in Western Europe, ''West European Politics''). Currently, [[Rwanda]] has the highest number of women at 49 percent. The [[United States]] has 14 percent. The world average is 9 percent. In contrast, half of the members of the recently established [[Welsh Assembly Government]] are women.{{fact}} and 40% of members of the [[Scottish Parliament]] are female. [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Members_of_the_Scottish_Parliament%2C_2003-2007]

*In the US in 2003, for every $1 males earn, women earn 76 cents on average.{{fact}}

==Contemporary criticisms of feminism==
Criticism of feminism as a ''whole'' ideology, criticism of specific ''types'' of feminism, and criticism of ''specific'' feminist ideas have come from feminists themselves, non-feminists, [[masculism|masculists]], social conservatives, and social progressives.

[[Postcolonial feminism|Postcolonial feminists]] criticize certain ideas of Western forms of feminism, notably [[radical feminism]] and its most basic assumption, universalization of the female experience. They argue that this assumption cannot so easily be applied to women for whom gender oppression comes second to, for example, racial or class oppression.{{fact}}

From the perspective of some strands of feminism, as well as the [[men's movement]] and [[queer theory]], inequalities and stereotypes based on gender are detrimental to both men and women and both sexes suffer from the expectations of traditional gender roles.

Many who support [[masculism]] argue that because of both traditional gender roles and sexism infused into society by feminists, males are and have been oppressed. [[Marriage Rights]] advocates oppose feminist aspirations to replace the traditional family, as illustrated by statements made by a variety of feminist leaders such as [[Shelia Cronan]]'s view that marriage constitutes slavery for women, and the women's movement must concentrate on attacking this institution and that freedom for women cannot be won without the abolition of marriage. Dr. Mary Jo Bane, associate director of Wellesley College's Center for Research on Woman suggested that to raise children with equality, they should be taken from families and communally raised. Men and Family rights groups oppose feminists such as Robin Morgan, the openly [[lesbian]] editor of Ms. Magazine, who advocated 'man-hating' as an honorable and viable political act and concludes the inequities between men and women cannot be resolved until  marriage is destroyed. Family and [[Men's Rights]] groups are also critical of [[Feminist]] encouragment of [[Lesbian]] agendas which undermine the traditional role of men in the family, such as  Sheila Cronan's National NOW Times January 1988 interview statements declaring every woman must be willing to be identified as a lesbian to be fully feminist{{fact}}. Many critics of feminism are alarmed by the prevalence of lesbians such as Patricia Ireland, the head of NOW, in feminist leadership roles.  [[Men's Rights]] advocates view much of contemporary feminist issues "extremist" due to their perception that feminist demands such as [[equal rights]] has been achieved.{{fact}} Issues such as the [[Violence Against Women Act]] are viewed as discriminatory of men. [[Father's Rights]] advocates are critical of feminist efforts to block shared parenting, or joint custody, after divorce. 

[[Ann Widdecombe]], a British [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] politician and former leadership candidate, claimed that feminism slowly evolved into its antithesis[http://politics.guardian.co.uk/interviews/story/0,,1076316,00.html].  She argues that 1970s rhetoric emphasized equal rights and self-sufficiency, whereas 1990s rhetoric demanded special assistance for women and implied that women could not look after themselves.  She identifies with the former variant, and describes the latter as "absolute tosh".

==Academic research about feminist issues==
Some natural and social scientists have used science in order to question theories of innate social or cognitive differences between men and women; some examples follow:

* [[Anne Fausto-Sterling]]'s book ''Myths of Gender'' explores the assumptions embodied in scientific research that purports to support a biologically [[essentialist]] view of gender.

* [[Carol Tavris]], in ''The Mismeasure of Woman'', uses psychology and sociology to voice the failure to identify innate differences between males and females and to ''pin down'' how these differences dictate, and account for, perceived differences between men and women. She argues there is a reliance on ever-changing hypothesizes (and the hysteria they create instead of evidence) to justify inequality. She further argues a tendency to punish women for not conducting themselves on traditional male terms, which provides a counter-argument for [[Warren Farrell]]'s wage-gap ideas.

* [[Evelyn Fox Keller]] has argued that the rhetoric of science reflects a masculine perspective, and questions the idea of [[scientific objectivity]]. Many anthropologists (Haviland, Prins, Walrather, McBride) noted that a non-masculine perspective is relatively new in studies of human evolution and culture. [[Primatologist]] [[Sarah Blaffer Hrdy]] (''Infanticide: Comparative and Evolutionary Perspectives'', ''Mother Nature: A History of Mothers, Infants and Natural Selection'') notes the prevalence of masculine-coined stereotypes and theories, such as the non-sexual female, despite "''the accumulation of abundant openly available evidence contradicting it''" (Hrdy, 1988, p.120).

* Other researchers who have exposed flaws in social and scientific theories cited by some anti-feminist authors include [[Barbara Ehrenreich]], [[Kristin Luker]], and [[Stephanie Coontz]]. {{citationneeded}} &lt;!-- Note:  the citation is needed ''both'' for the claim that flaws have been exposed, as well as the claim that Ehrenreich et. al. are anti-feminist.  The article on Ehrenreich herself puts her in category:feminists.  -Kasreyn --&gt;

==Famous feminists==
''See [[list of feminists]].''

==References==
&lt;div class='references-2column'&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
*Sweeney, Brian (ed.) 2000, 'OPTIMISTS: Kate Sheppard - Suffragist'. Accessed May  23rd, 2006, from http://www.nzedge.com/heroes/sheppard.html.
&lt;/div&gt;

==See also==
{{wiktionary}}
&lt;div class='references-2column'&gt;
*[[Suffragettes]]
*[[Equal Rights Amendment]] (ERA)
*[[Anarcha-feminism]]
*[[Domestic violence]]
*[[Equal pay for women]]
*[[Feminazi]]
*[[Feminist history in the United States]]
*[[Feminist history in the United Kingdom]]
*[[Feminism in Poland|Feminist history in Poland]]
*[[Feminist history in Latin America]]
*[[Feminist theology]]
*[[Gender studies]]
*[[Gender-neutral language]]
*[[History of feminism]]
*[[Islamic feminism]]
*[[Lesbian feminism]]
*[[List of feminism topics]]
*[[List of notable feminists]]
*[[Radical feminism]]
*[[Role of women in Judaism]]
*[[Women's cinema]]
*[[Women's Environment &amp; Development Organization]]
*[[Women's music]]
*[[Sex/gender distinction]]
*[[Circle K (Kiwanis)#Controversy|Circle K International Member Pledge Controversy]]
&lt;/div&gt;

==Books==
&lt;div class='small'&gt;
*Antrobus, Peggy. "The global women's movement - Origins, issues and strategies", London, Zed Books 2004
*Berk, Sarah Fenstermaker, ed. "Women and Household Labor", Sage 1980.
*[[Judith Butler|Butler, Judith]] (1994). "Feminism in Any Other Name", ''differences'' 6:2-3: 44-45.
*[[Kate Chopin|Chopin, Kate]]. "The Awakening". 1899.
*Code, Lorraine, ed., "Encyclopedia of feminist theories", Routledge 2000
*Patricia Hill Collins, "Black Feminist Thought. Knowledge, Consciousness and the Politics of Empowerment", Second Edition, Routledge  2000
*Echols, Alice. "Daring to Be Bad: Radical Feminism in America, 1967-1975", University of Minnesota Press 1990
*Faludi, Susan. "Backlash: The Undeclared War Against American Women". 1992 (ISBN 0-385-42507-4)
*Friedan, Betty. "The Feminine Mystique" 1963
*French, Marilyn. "Beyond Power"; "War Against Women"; "From Eve to Dawn", a 3-volume history of women
*J.F. del Giorgio. ''[[The Oldest Europeans]]'':''Who are we? Where do we come from? What made European women different?''.A.J.Place 2006 (ISBN 980-6898-00-1)
*Gossett, Hattie. "presenting sister noblues" 1989
*Gossett, Hattie. "this bridge called my back: writings by radical women of color", 1981
*Hochschild, Arlie Russell. "The Second Shift" 1990 (ISBN 0-380-71157-5)
*Hochschild, Arlie Russell. "The Time Bind: When Work Becomes Home and Home Becomes Work" 1997 (ISBN 0-8050-4470-1)
*hooks, bell. (1984). "Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center". ISBN 0-89608-614-3
*Jacobson, Joyce P. "The Economics of Gender" 1998. (ISBN 0-631-20726-0)
*Kaminer, Wendy. "A Fearful Freedom: Women's Flight from Equality", Addison Wesley 1990 (ISBN 0-201-09234-4)
*Kipnes, Laura, "The Female Thing: Dirt, Sex, Envy, Vulnerability", ISBN 0-375-42417-2
*[[Gerda Lerner|Lerner, Gerda]]. "The Creation of Feminist Consciousness: From the Middle Ages to Eighteen-Seventy", Oxford University Press 1994
*Luker, Kristin. "Dubious Conceptions: The Politics of the Teenage Pregnancy Crisis". (Harvard University Press, 1996) (ISBN 0-674-21703-9)
*Schneir, Miriam. "Feminism : The Essential Historical Writings", New York: Vintage 1994
*Sommers, Christina Hoff. "Who Stole Feminism? - How women have betrayed women" (1996) (ISBN 0-684-80156-6)
*Tavris, Carol. "The Mismeasure of Woman: Why Women Are Not the Better Sex, the Opposite Sex, or the Inferior Sex". Simon and Schuster, 1992. ISBN 0-671-66274-0
*Wertheim, Margaret. "Pythagoras' Trousers - God, Physics, and the Gender Wars", W.W. Norton &amp; Co. (1995, 1997)
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
{| style="background-color: transparent; width: {{{width|100%}}}"
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
| width="{{{width|}}}" align="{{{align|left}}}" valign="{{{valign|top}}}" |
===Feminist organizations===
*[http://www.ansarburney.org/ Ansar Burney Trust]
*[http://www.awpsych.org/ Association for Women in Psychology]
*[http://www.ALF.org The Association of Libertarian Feminists]
*[http://www.AdvanceWomen.org/ Center for the Advancement of Women]
*[http://www.cawinfo.org/ Committee for Asian Women]
*[http://www.feministinitiative.bc.ca/ FemINist INitiative of BC]
*[http://feminist.org Feminist Majority]
*[http://now.org NOW] - National Organization for Women in the United States.
*[http://www.wluml.org/english/ Women living under muslim laws]
*[http://www.ffeusa.org Feminists for Free Expression]
*[http://www.feministsforlife.org/ Feminists for Life]
*[http://www.ifeminists.net/index.php ifeminists: the home for individualist feminism on the net]
*[http://www.lilithgallery.com/feminist/index.html 1001 Feminist Links] - The Lilith Gallery of Toronto.
*[http://www.iwf.org/ Independent Women's Forum]
*[http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Topic:Women%27s_Studies The Women's Studies Department at Wikiversity]

===Supportive of feminism===
*[http://www.fnsa.org/ Feminism &amp; Nonviolence Studies]
*[http://www.susanbrownmiller.com Susan Brownmiller.com: Where Feminism Lives]
*[http://www.egs.edu/faculty/judithbutler.html Judith Butler - Bibliography]
*[http://www.synaptic.bc.ca/ejournal/wolf.html Naomi Wolf - Resources]
*[http://www.fembio.org/default.shtml FemBio - Notable Women International]
*[http://www.synaptic.bc.ca/ejournal/faludi.html Susan Faludi - Resources]
*[http://www.lilithgallery.com/feminist/hattiegossett-biography.html Hattie Gossett - Biography]
*[http://feminism.eserver.org/ EServer Feminism and Women's Studies]
*[http://www.ericdigests.org/2002-1/women.html The Seneca Falls Convention: Teaching about the Rights of Women and the Heritage of the Declaration of Independence]
* [http://www.womensfreedom.org Women's Freedom Network]

===Critical of feminism, or specific types of feminism===

*[http://www.mensnewsdaily.com/ MensNewsDaily]
*[http://www.mediaradar.org/ RADAR]
*[http://Mensactivism.org/ Men's Activism News Network]
*[http://www.equityfeminism.com Equity feminism]
*[http://www.eagleforum.org/topics/Feminism/index.shtml Eagle Forum]
*[http://www.ukmm.org.uk/issues/masc.htm The Masculist Perspective: Response to Feminist Claims]
*[http://www.cwfa.org Concerned Women for America]
*[http://www.heritage.org/Research/Family/bg1662.cfm Why Congress Should Ignore Radical Feminist Opposition to Marriage]
*[http://organizenow.net/cco/right/antifem.html Female Anti-Feminism for Fame and Profit], by [[Jennifer Pozner]] criticizes so-called "dissident" feminists such as [[Christina Hoff-Sommers]]

===Feminism and religion===
*[http://www.irfi.org/articles/articles_101_150/religious_conservatism.htm Riffat Hasan on ''Religious conservatism: Feminist theology as a means of combating injustice towards women in muslim communities/culture'']
*[http://www.jwa.org/feminism Jewish Women and the Feminist Revolution] from the Jewish Women's Archive
*[http://www.liberalislam.net/women.html Islam from Patriarch]

[[Category:Feminism| ]]
[[Category:Sociological paradigms]]

{{Link FA|el}}

[[ar:أنثوية]]
[[bs:Feminizam]]
[[bg:Феминизъм]]
[[ca:Feminisme]]
[[cs:Feminismus]]
[[da:Feminisme]]
[[de:Feminismus]]
[[et:Feminism]]
[[el:Φεμινισμός]]
[[es:Feminismo]]
[[eo:Feminismo]]
[[eu:Feminismo]]
[[fa:فمینیسم]]
[[fr:Féminisme]]
[[gd:Beanalachd]]
[[gl:Feminismo]]
[[ko:페미니즘]]
[[hi:नारीवाद]]
[[hr:Feminizam]]
[[ia:Feminismo]]
[[it:Femminismo]]
[[he:פמיניזם]]
[[lt:Feminizmas]]
[[mk:Феминизам]]
[[nl:Feminisme]]
[[ja:フェミニズム]]
[[no:Feminisme]]
[[nn:Feminisme]]
[[pl:Feminizm]]
[[pt:Feminismo]]
[[ro:Feminism]]
[[ru:Феминизм]]
[[scn:Fimminismu]]
[[simple:Feminism]]
[[sk:Feminizmus (hnutie)]]
[[sl:Feminizem]]
[[sr:феминизам]]
[[sh:Feminizam]]
[[fi:Feminismi]]
[[sv:Feminism]]
[[tr:Feminizm]]
[[uk:Фемінізм]]
[[zh:女性主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>