<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111114183443|460646425" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11185" pageid="11185" ns="0" title="Feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-16T20:37:42Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Feminists}}
{{See also|feminist movement|feminism in the United States}}
{{pp-semi|small=yes}}{{pp-move-indef}}
[[Image:8marchrallydhaka (55).JPG|thumb|300px|[[International Women's Day]] rally in Dhaka, Bangladesh, organized by the National Women Workers Trade Union Centre on March 8, 2005.]]

'''Feminism''' is a collection of [[feminist movement|movements]] aimed at defining, establishing, and defending [[feminism and equality|equal]] political, economic, and social rights and equal opportunities for women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/feminism |title=Feminism – Definition and More from the Free Merriam-Webster Dictionary |publisher=www.merriam-webster.com |accessdate=12 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/british/feminism |title=Definition of feminism noun from Cambridge Dictionary Online: Free English Dictionary and Thesaurus |publisher=dictionary.cambridge.org |accessdate=12 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://encarta.msn.com/encnet/features/dictionary/DictionaryResults.aspx?refid=1861610952 |title=feminism definition – Dictionary – MSN Encarta |publisher=encarta.msn.com |accessdate=12 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its concepts overlap with those of [[women's rights]]. Feminism is mainly focused on women's issues, but because feminism seeks gender equality, some feminists argue that men's liberation is therefore a necessary part of feminism, and that men are also harmed by sexism and gender roles. '''Feminists''' are "person[s] whose beliefs and behavior[s] are based on feminism."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | title = ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'', 4th edition
  | publisher = [[Houghton Mifflin]]
  | year = 2006
  | doi = 
  | isbn = 9780618701728
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Feminist theory]] exists in a variety of disciplines, emerging from these feminist movements&lt;ref name="Chodorow1989"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Chodorow, Nancy |title=Feminism and Psychoanalytic Theory |year=1989 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven, Conn. |isbn=978-0-300-05116-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gilligan1977"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Gilligan |first=Carol |year=1977 |title='In a Different Voice: Women's Conceptions of Self and Morality'|journal=Harvard Educational Review|volume=47|issue=4 |pages=481–517|url=http://eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/custom/portlets/recordDetails/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=EJ174986&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=EJ174986 |doi=|oclc = |accessdate=2008-06-08 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; and including general theories{{Specify|date=July 2011}} and theories about the origins of inequality, and, in some cases, about the social construction of sex and gender. Feminist activists have campaigned for women's rights—such as in contract, property, and [[women's suffrage|voting]] — while also promoting women's rights to bodily integrity and autonomy and [[reproductive rights]]. They have opposed [[domestic violence]], [[sexual harassment]], and [[sexual assault]]. In economics, they have advocated for workplace rights, including [[equal pay for women|equal pay]] and opportunities for careers and to start businesses.{{cn|date=November 2011}}

Some of the earlier forms of feminism have been [[feminism#Civil rights movement and anti-racism|criticized]] for being geared towards white, middle-class, educated perspectives.  This led to the creation of ethnically-specific or multiculturalist forms of feminism.&lt;ref name=Weedon/&gt;

== History ==
[[Image:8marta.jpg|thumb|150px|A 1932 Soviet poster for [[International Women's Day]].]]
{{main|History of feminism}}
Depending on time, culture and country, feminists around the world have sometimes had different causes and goals. Most western feminist historians assert that all movements that work to obtain [[women's rights]] should be considered feminist movements, even when they did not (or do not) apply the term to themselves.&lt;ref name="spender"&gt;Spender, Dale. There's always been a women's movement. Pandora Press, London 1983&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lerner, Gerda. The Creation of Feminist Consciousness From the Middle Ages to Eighteen-seventy, Oxford University Press, 1993&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="walters"&gt;Walters, Margaret. "Feminism: A very short introduction". Oxford University 2005 (ISBN 0-19-280510-X)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="kinnaird"&gt;Kinnaird, Joan.Mary Astell: Inspired by ideas (1668-1731) in Spender, op. cit. at 29&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-femhist/index.html Witt, Charlotte. Feminist History of Philosophy 2006(Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="taylor"&gt;[http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/ahr/104.4/ah001085.html Allen, Ann Taylor. Feminism, Social Science, and the Meanings of Modernity: The Debate on the Origin of the Family in Europe and the United States, 1860–1914. The American Historical Review 1999 October 104(4)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="woolf"&gt;[[Virginia Woolf|Woolf, Virginia]] A room of one's own. 1928&lt;/ref&gt; Other historians assert that the term should be limited to the modern feminist movement and its descendants.  Those historians use the label "[[protofeminist]]" to describe earlier movements.&lt;ref name="botting-houser"&gt;Botting, Eileen H, Houser, Sarah L., '"Drawing the Line of Equality": Hannah Mather Crocker on Women's Rights' in ''American Political Science Review'' (2006), 100: 265-278&lt;/ref&gt;

The history of the modern western feminist movements is divided into three "waves".&lt;ref name="Humm"&gt;Humm, Maggie. 1995. The Dictionary of Feminist Theory. Columbus: Ohio State University Press, p. 251&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Walker1992"&gt;Walker, Rebecca, 'Becoming the Third Wave' in ''Ms.'' (January/February, 1992) pp. 39-41&lt;/ref&gt; Each is described as dealing with different aspects of the same feminist issues. The [[First-wave feminism|first wave]] refers mainly to [[women's suffrage]] movements of the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries (mainly concerned with women's right to vote). The [[Second-wave feminism|second wave]] refers to the ideas and actions associated with the women's liberation movement beginning in the 1960s (which campaigned for legal and social equality for women). The [[Third-wave feminism|third wave]] refers to a continuation of, and a reaction to, the perceived failures of second-wave feminism, beginning in the 1990s.&lt;ref name="Suffragettes to Grrls"&gt;{{cite book|last=Krolokke|first=Charlotte|coauthors=Anne Scott Sorensen|title=Gender Communication Theories and Analyses:From Silence to Performance|year=2005|publisher=Sage|isbn=0761929185|page=24|chapter=Three Waves of Feminism: From Suffragettes to Grrls}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{see also|Protofeminist}}

=== Nineteenth and early twentieth centuries ===
[[First-wave feminism]] was a period of activity during the nineteenth century and early twentieth century. In the [[U.K.]] and [[U.S.]], it focused on the promotion of equal contract, marriage, parenting, and property rights for women. However, by the end of the nineteenth century, activism focused primarily on gaining political power, particularly the right of women's [[suffrage]], though some feminists were active in campaigning for women's sexual, [[reproductive rights|reproductive]], and economic rights at this time.&lt;ref name=Freedman&gt;{{cite book |author=Freedman, Estelle B. |title=No Turning Back : The History of Feminism and the Future of Women |year=2003 |publisher=Ballantine Books |location= |isbn=0-345-45053-1 |page=464}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Louise Weiss.jpg|thumb|250px|left|[[Louise Weiss]] along with other [[Paris]]ian suffragettes in 1935. The newspaper headline reads ''"THE FRENCHWOMAN MUST VOTE."'']]
[[Women's suffrage]] was achieved in Britain's [[Australasian]] colonies at the close of the 19th century with the self-governing colonies of [[New Zealand]] and [[South Australia]] granting women the [[right to vote]] in 1893 and 1895 respectively, and followed by Australia permitting women to stand for parliamentary office and granting women's' right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elections.org.nz/study/education-centre/history/votes-for-women.html Votes for Women | Elections New Zealand]. Elections.org.nz (2005-04-13). Retrieved on 2011-06-12.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://aec.gov.au/Elections/Australian_Electoral_History/milestone.htm Electoral Milestones for Women – Australian Electoral Commission]. Aec.gov.au (2008-12-17). Retrieved on 2011-06-12.&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|Britain]] the [[Suffragette]]s and the [[National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies|Suffragists]] campaigned for the women's vote, and in 1918 the [[Representation of the People Act 1918|Representation of the People Act]] was passed granting the vote to women over the age of 30 who owned houses. In 1928 this was extended to all women over twenty-one.&lt;ref name=Phillips&gt;{{cite book |author=Phillips, Melanie |title=The ascent of woman: a history of the suffragette movement and the ideas behind it |year=2004 |publisher=Abacus |location=London |isbn=978-0-349-11660-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the U.S., notable leaders of this movement included [[Lucretia Mott]], [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]], and [[Susan B. Anthony]], who each campaigned for the abolition of slavery prior to championing women's right to vote and were strongly influenced by [[Quaker]] thought. In the United States, first-wave feminism is considered to have ended with the passage of the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] (1919), granting women the right to vote in all states. The term ''first wave'', was coined retrospectively to categorize these western movements after the term ''[[second-wave feminism]]'' began to be used to describe a newer feminist movement that focused as much on fighting social and cultural inequalities as political inequalities.&lt;ref name=Freedman&gt;{{cite book |author=Freedman, Estelle B. |title=No Turning Back : The History of Feminism and the Future of Women |publisher=Ballantine Books |isbn=0-345-45053-1 |page=464}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= DuBois&gt;{{cite book |author=DuBois, Ellen Carol |title=Harriot Stanton Blatch and the winning of woman suffrage |year=1997 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven, Conn. |isbn=978-0-300-06562-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Flexner&gt;Flexner, Eleanor, ''Century of Struggle: The Woman's Rights Movement in the United States'' (The Belknap Press, 1996), ISBN 9780674106539&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= Wheeler&gt;{{cite book |author=Wheeler, Marjorie W. |title=One woman, one vote: rediscovering the woman suffrage movement |year=1995 |publisher=NewSage Press |location=Troutdale, OR |isbn=978-0-939165-26-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Stevens&gt;{{cite book |author=Stevens, Doris |authorlink= |coauthors=O'Hare, Carol |title=Jailed for freedom: American women win the vote |year=1995 |publisher=NewSage Press |location=Troutdale, OR |isbn=978-0-939165-25-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the late [[Qing Dynasty|Qing period]] and reform movements such as the [[Hundred Days' Reform]], Chinese feminists called for women's liberation from traditional roles and [[Neo-Confucian]] gender segregation.&lt;ref&gt;Ko, Dorothy, JaHyun Kim Haboush, Joan R. Piggott ''Women and Confucian cultures in premodern China, Korea, and Japan''. University of California Press, 2003, ISBN 0520231384&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ma, Yuxin ''Women journalists and feminism in China, 1898–1937'' Cambria Press, 2010, ISBN 1604976608&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Farris, Catherine S., Anru Lee, Murray A. Rubinstein, ''Women in the new Taiwan: gender roles and gender consciousness in a changing society '' M.E. Sharpe, 2004, ISBN 0765608146&lt;/ref&gt; Later, the [[Chinese Communist Party]] created projects aimed at integrating women into the workforce, and claimed that the revolution had successfully achieved women's liberation.&lt;ref name="Dooling"&gt;Dooling, Amy D. ''Women's literary feminism in twentieth-century China'', Macmillan, 2005, ISBN 1403967334&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1899, [[Qasim Amin]], considered the "father" of [[Arab feminism]], wrote ''[[The Liberation of Women]]'', which argued for legal and social reforms for women.&lt;ref&gt;Stange, Mary Zeiss, Carol K. Oyster, Jane E. Sloan, ''Encyclopedia of Women in Today's World'', SAGE, 2011, ISBN 1412976855&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hoda Shaarawi]] founded the [[Egyptian Feminist Union]] in 1923, and became its president and a symbol of the Arab women's rights movement. Arab feminism was closely connected with [[Arab nationalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Golley, Nawar Al-Hassan, ''Reading Arab women's autobiographies: Shahrazad tells her story'', University of Texas Press, 2003, ISBN 029270545X&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Iranian Constitutional Revolution]] in 1905 triggered the [[Iranian women's movement]], which aimed to achieve women's equality in education, marriage, careers, and legal rights.&lt;ref&gt;Ettehadieh, Mansoureh (2004). The Origins and Development of the Women's Movement in Iran, 1906–41 in Women in Iran from 1800 to the Islamic Republic By Lois Beck and Guity Nashat. University of Illinois Press. ISBN 978-0252071898.&lt;/ref&gt; However, during the [[Iranian revolution]] of 1979, many of the rights that women had gained from the women's movement were systematically abolished, such as the [[Iran's Family Protection Law|Family Protection Law]].&lt;ref&gt;Chronology of Events Regarding Women in Iran since the Revolution of 1979, Elham Gheytanchi, Social Research via FindArticles, Summer 2000; accessed September 21, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Mid-twentieth century ===
[[Second-wave feminism]] is a feminist movement beginning in the early 1960s&lt;ref name=Whelehan&gt;{{cite book |author=Whelehan, Imelda |title=Modern feminist thought: from the second wave to "post-feminism" |year=1995 |publisher=Edinburgh University Press |location=Edinburgh |isbn=978-0-7486-0621-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; and continuing to the present, and it coexists with [[third-wave feminism]]. Second wave feminism is largely concerned with issues of equality other than suffrage, such as ending discrimination.&lt;ref name=Freedman/&gt;

Second-wave feminists see women's cultural and political inequalities as inextricably linked and encourage women to understand aspects of their personal lives as deeply politicized and as reflecting [[sexism|sexist]] power structures. The feminist activist and author [[Carol Hanisch]] coined the slogan "The Personal is Political", which became synonymous with the second wave.&lt;ref name=Echols/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hanisch&gt;{{cite web |url=http://scholar.alexanderstreet.com/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=2259 |title=Hanisch, New Intro to "The Personal is Political"&amp;nbsp;– Second Wave and Beyond |accessdate=2008-06-08 |last=Hanisch |first=Carol |date=2006-01-01 |work=The Personal Is Political}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Second and third-wave feminism in China{{Clarify|date=July 2011}} has been characterized by a re-examination of women's roles during the communist revolution and other reform movements, and new discussions about whether women's equality has actually been fully achieved.&lt;ref name="Dooling" /&gt;

In 1956, President [[Nasser]] of Egypt initiated as part of his government "[[state feminism]]", which outlawed discrimination based on gender and granted women's suffrage, but also blocked political activism by feminist leaders.&lt;ref&gt;Badran, Margot, ''Feminists, Islam, and nation: gender and the making of modern Egypt'', Princeton University Press, 1996, ISBN 069102605X&lt;/ref&gt;  During [[Sadat]]'s presidency, his wife, [[Jehan Sadat]], publicly advocated for further women's rights, though Egyptian policy and society began to move away from women's equality with the new [[Islamist]] movement and growing conservatism.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Bonnie G., ''Global feminisms since 1945'', Psychology Press, 2000, ISBN 0415184916&lt;/ref&gt; However, some activists proposed a new feminist movement, [[Islamic feminism]], which argues for women's equality within an Islamic framework.&lt;ref&gt;[http://feminismeislamic.org/home/ ''International Congress on Islamic Feminism''], as accessed Jun. 12, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Late twentieth and early twenty-first centuries ===
The term [[post-feminism]] is used to describe a range of viewpoints reacting to feminism since the 1980s. While not being "anti-feminist", post-feminists believe that women have achieved second wave goals while being critical of third wave feminist goals. The term was first used to describe a backlash against [[second-wave feminism]], but it is now a label for a wide range of theories that take critical approaches to previous feminist discourses and includes challenges to the second wave's ideas.&lt;ref name=Wright2000&gt;{{cite book |author=Wright, Elizabeth |title=Lacan and Postfeminism (Postmodern Encounters) |year=2000 |publisher=Totem Books |location= |isbn=978-1-84046-182-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other post-feminists say that feminism is no longer relevant to today's society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Modleski, Tania |title=Feminism without women: culture and criticism in a "postfeminist" age |year=1991 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=0-415-90416-1 |page=188}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amelia Jones has written that the post-feminist texts which emerged in the 1980s and 1990s portrayed second-wave feminism as a monolithic entity and criticized it using generalizations.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Amelia. “Postfeminism, Feminist Pleasures, and Embodied Theories of Art,” in ''New Feminist Criticism: Art, Identity, Action'', ed. by Joana Frueh, Cassandra L. Langer and Arlene Raven. New York: HarperCollins, 1994. 16–41, 20.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1990s in the USA, [[third-wave feminism]] began as a response to perceived failures of the second wave and to the backlash against initiatives and movements created by the second wave. Third-wave feminism seeks to challenge or avoid what it deems the second wave's [[Essentialism|essentialist]] definitions of [[femininity]], which, they argue, over-emphasize the experiences of upper middle-class white women. Third-wave feminists often focus on "micro-politics" and challenge the second wave's paradigm as to what is, or is not, good for women, and tend to use a [[post-structuralism|post-structuralist]] interpretation of gender and sexuality.&lt;ref name=Freedman/&gt;&lt;ref name=Henry&gt;{{cite book |author=Henry, Astrid |title=Not my mother's sister: generational conflict and third-wave feminism |year=2004 |publisher=Indiana University Press |location=Bloomington |isbn=978-0-253-21713-4}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gillis&gt;{{cite book |author=Gillis, Stacy |coauthors=Howie, Gillian; Munford, Rebecca |title=Third wave feminism: a critical exploration |year=2007 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |location=Basingstoke |isbn=978-0-230-52174-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Faludi&gt;{{cite book |author=Faludi, Susan |authorlink=Susan Faludi |title=Backlash: the undeclared war against women |year=1992 |publisher=Vintage |location=London |isbn=978-0-09-922271-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Feminist leaders rooted in the second wave, such as [[Gloria Anzaldua]], [[bell hooks]], Chela Sandoval, [[Cherrie Moraga]], [[Audre Lorde]], [[Maxine Hong Kingston]], and many other black feminists, sought to negotiate a space within feminist thought for consideration of race-related subjectivities.&lt;ref name=Gillis/&gt;&lt;ref name=Walker/&gt;&lt;ref name=Heywood&gt;{{cite book |author=Leslie, Heywood; Drake, Jennifer |title=Third wave agenda: being feminist, doing feminism |year=1997 |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |location=Minneapolis |isbn=978-0-8166-3005-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Third-wave feminism also contains internal debates between [[difference feminism|difference feminists]], who believe that there are important differences between the sexes, and those who believe that there are no inherent differences between the sexes and contend that gender roles are due to [[social conditioning]].&lt;ref name=Gilligan&gt;{{cite book |author=Gilligan, Carol |authorlink=Carol Gilligan |title=In a different voice: psychological theory and women's development |year=1993 |publisher=Harvard University Press |location=Cambridge, Mass. |isbn=0-674-44544-9 |page=184}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theoretical schools ==
{{main|Feminist theory}}
[[Feminist theory]] is an extension of feminism into theoretical or philosophical fields. It encompasses work in a variety of disciplines, including [[feminist anthropology|anthropology]], [[feminist sociology|sociology]], [[feminist economics|economics]], [[women's studies]], [[feminist literary criticism|literary criticism]],&lt;ref name=Zajko&gt;{{cite book |author=Zajko, Vanda |coauthors=Leonard, Miriam |title=Laughing with Medusa: classical myth and feminist thought |year=2006 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0-19-927438-X |page=445}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Howe&gt;{{cite book |author=Howe, Mica; Aguiar, Sarah Appleton |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=He said, she says: an RSVP to the male text |year=2001 |publisher=Fairleigh Dickinson University Press |location=Madison [[N.J.]] |isbn=0-8386-3915-1 |page=292}}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Art history#Psychoanalytic art history|art history]],&lt;ref&gt;Griselda Pollock, ''Encounters in the Virtual Feminist Museum: Time, Space and the Archive''. Routledge, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Feminist theory#Feminist psychoanalysis|psychoanalysis]]&lt;ref name=matrixial_borderspace&gt;{{cite book |author=Ettinger, Bracha |authorlink=Bracha Ettinger |coauthors=Judith Butler, Brian Massumi, Griselda Pollock |title=The matrixial borderspace |year=2006 |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |location=Minneapolis |isbn=0-8166-3587-0 |page=245}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and [[feminist philosophy|philosophy]].&lt;ref&gt;Brabeck, M. and Brown, L. (With Christian, L., Espin, O., Hare-Mustin, R., Kaplan, A., Kaschak, E., Miller, D., Phillips, E., Ferns, T., and Van Ormer, A.). (1997). Feminist theory and psychological practice. In J. Worell and N. Johnson (Eds.) Shaping the future of feminist psychology: Education, research, and practice) (pp.15–35). Washington, D.C.: American Psychological Association.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Florence&gt;{{cite book |author=Florence, Penny |coauthors=Foster, Nicola |title=Differential aesthetics: art practices, philosophy and feminist understandings |year=2001 |publisher=Ashgate |location=Aldershot, Hants, England |isbn=0-7546-1493-X |page=360}}&lt;/ref&gt; Feminist theory aims to understand [[gender inequality]] and focuses on gender politics, power relations, and sexuality. While providing a critique of these social and political relations, much of feminist theory also focuses on the promotion of women's rights and interests. Themes explored in feminist theory include [[discrimination]], [[stereotyping]], [[objectification]] (especially [[sexual objectification]]), [[oppression]], and [[patriarchy]].&lt;ref name=Chodorow1989&gt;{{cite book |author=Chodorow, Nancy |title=Feminism and psychoanalytic theory |year=1989 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven, Conn. |isbn=978-0-300-05116-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=gilligan1977&gt;
{{Cite journal
 |last=Gilligan
 |first=Carol
 |date=1977-00-00
 |title='In a Different Voice: Women's Conceptions of Self and Morality'
|journal=Harvard Educational Review
|volume=47
|issue=4
 |pages=481–517
|url=http://eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/custom/portlets/recordDetails/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=EJ174986&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=EJ174986
|doi=
|oclc =
 |accessdate=2008-06-08
 |postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to "." for the cite to end in a ".", as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}
}} (1977)&lt;/ref&gt;

The American literary critic and feminist [[Elaine Showalter]] describes the phased development of feminist theory. The first she calls "feminist critique", in which the feminist reader examines the ideologies behind literary phenomena. The second Showalter calls "[[gynocriticism]]", in which the "woman is producer of textual meaning" including "the psychodynamics of female creativity; linguistics and the problem of a female language; the trajectory of the individual or collective female literary career and literary history". The last phase she calls "gender theory", in which the "ideological inscription and the literary effects of the sex/gender system" are explored".&lt;ref name=showalter1979&gt;{{cite book |author=Showalter, Elaine |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=The New feminist criticism: essays on women, literature, and theory |year=1985 |publisher=Pantheon |location=New York |isbn=978-0-394-72647-2 |pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; This model has been criticized by the scholar [[Toril Moi]] who sees it as an [[essentialism|essentialist]] and [[determinism|deterministic]] model for female subjectivity and for failing to account for the situation of women outside the West.&lt;ref name=Moi&gt;{{cite book |author=Moi, Toril |title=Sexual/textual politics: feminist literary theory |year=2002 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=978-0-415-28012-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Movements and ideologies ==
{{Main|Feminist movements and ideologies}}
Several overlapping movements of feminist ideologies have developed over the years.

[[File:Sojourner truth c1870.jpg|thumb|250px|right|[[Sojourner Truth]], a famous [[black feminism|black feminist]], delivered the speech ''[[Ain't I a Woman?]]'' arguing for black women's equality in 1851]][[Liberal feminism]] seeks individualistic equality of men and women through political and legal reform without altering the structure of society. [[Radical feminism]] considers the male-controlled [[capitalism|capitalist]] hierarchy as the defining feature of women's oppression and the total uprooting and reconstruction of society as necessary.&lt;ref name="Echols" /&gt; [[Socialist feminism]] connects oppression of women to exploitation, oppression, and labor. [[Marxist]] feminists feel that overcoming class oppression overcomes gender oppression;&lt;ref name="Marx"&gt;Marx, Karl, trans. B. Fowkes, ''Capital'' (Penguin Classics, 1990 (ISBN 978-0-14-044568-8)).&lt;/ref&gt; some socialist feminists disagree.&lt;ref name="round-table_discussion"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Connolly |first=Clara | number = 23 |coauthors=Lynne Segal, Michele Barrett, Beatrix Campbell, Anne Phillips, Angela Weir, Elizabeth Wilson |title=Feminism and Class Politics: A Round-Table Discussion |journal=Feminist Review |issue=Socialist–Feminism: Out of the Blue |page=17 |month=Summer |year=1986 |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and has branched into such as [[anti-pornography feminism]], opposed by [[sex-positive feminism]]. [[Anarcha-feminism|Anarcha-feminist]]s believe that [[class struggle]] and [[anarchism|anarchy]] against the [[State (polity)|state]]&lt;ref name="farrow"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Dunbar-Ortiz, Roxanne |title=Quiet Rumours |publisher=AK Press |isbn=978-1-902593-40-1 |year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; require struggling against [[patriarchy]], which comes from involuntary hierarchy. [[Separatist feminism]] does not support [[heterosexual]] relationships. Lesbian feminism is thus closely related. Other feminists criticize separatist feminism as sexist.&lt;ref name="hooks"&gt;bell hooks (2000), Feminism is for Everybody: Passionate Politics. Cited in Austin, Hannah (2004) "Separatism: Are We Limiting Ourselves?", EM 4:2&lt;/ref&gt;

[[List of conservative feminisms|Conservative feminism]] is conservative relative to the society in which it resides. [[Individualist feminism|Libertarian feminism]] conceives of people as self-owners and therefore as entitled to freedom from coercive interference.&lt;ref name="Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy"&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-liberal/#ClasCri ''Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy''].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Individualist feminism]] or ifeminism, opposing so-called [[gender feminism]], draws on [[anarcho-capitalism]].&lt;ref name="McElroy0"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wendymcelroy.com/xxx |title=XXX: A Woman's Right to Pornography|accessdate=2008-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Eco-feminist|Ecofeminist]]s see men's control of land as responsible for the oppression of women and destruction of the [[ecology|natural environment]], but a criticism is that [[ecofeminism]] focuses too much on a mystical connection between women and nature.&lt;ref name="Biehl"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Biehl, Janet |authorlink=Janet Biehl |title=Rethinking Eco-Feminist Politics |year=1991 |publisher=South End Press |location=Boston, Massachusetts |isbn=978-0-89608-392-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Cultural feminism]] attempts to revalidate undervalued "female nature" or [[essentialist|"female essence"]];&lt;ref name="Alcoff_1998"&gt;{{Cite journal |author=Alcoff, Linda |journal=Signs |volume=13 | number= 3 |month=Spring |year=1998 |page=32 |title=Cultural Feminism Versus Post-Structuralism: the Identity Crisis in Feminist Theory |publisher=The University of Chicago Press |issue=3 |doi=10.1086/494426 |jstor=3174166 |unused_data=DUPLICATE DATA: year=1988}}&lt;/ref&gt; its critics assert that it has led feminists to retreat from politics to lifestyle.&lt;ref name="Verta"&gt;{{Cite journal |author=Taylor, Verta |journal=Signs |volume=19 | number= 1 |month=Autumn |year=1993 |page=30 |publisher=The University of Chicago Press |title=# Women's Culture and Lesbian Feminist Activism: A Reconsideration of Cultural Feminism |issue=1 |doi=10.1086/494861 | coauthor=Rupp, Leila J. |jstor=3174744 |unused_data=DUPLICATE DATA: month=November}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During much of its [[history of feminism|history]], feminist movements and [[Feminism#Theoretical schools|theoretical developments]] were led predominantly by middle-class white women from Western Europe and North America.&lt;ref name="Walker"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Walker, Alice |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=[[In Search of Our Mothers' Gardens: Womanist Prose]] |year=1983 |publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich |location=San Diego |isbn=0-15-144525-7 |page=397}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BFT"&gt;Hill Collins, P., ''Black Feminist Thought: Knowledge, Consciousness, and the Politics of Empowerment'' (New York: Routledge, 2000).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Narayan"/&gt; However, at least since [[Sojourner Truth]]'s 1851 speech to American feminists, women of other races have proposed alternative feminisms.&lt;ref name="BFT" /&gt; This trend accelerated in the 1960s with the civil rights movement in the United States and the collapse of European colonialism in Africa, the Caribbean, parts of Latin America, and Southeast Asia. Since that time, women in [[Third World|developing nations]] and [[postcolonialism|former colonies]] and who are of colour or various ethnicities or living in poverty have proposed additional feminisms.&lt;ref name="Narayan" /&gt;

[[Womanism]]&lt;ref name="Ogunyemi"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Ogunyemi |first=C. O. |title=Womanism: The Dynamics of the Black Female Novel in English |journal=Signs |year=1985 |volume=1 |page=17 | issue = 1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kolawole"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Kolawole, Mary Ebun Modupe |title=Womanism and African Consciousness |year=1997 |publisher=Africa World Press |location=Trenton, N.J. |isbn=0-86543-540-5 |page=216}}&lt;/ref&gt; emerged after early feminist movements were largely white and middle-class.&lt;ref name="Walker" /&gt; Black feminism argues that [[sexism]], [[Social class|class]] oppression, and [[racism]] are inextricably bound together.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/modern/Defining-Black-Feminist-Thought.html |title=Defining Black Feminist Thought|accessdate=May 31, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Angela Davis|Davis, Angela]], ''Women, Race, and Class''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/blackwomen.html |title=List of Books written by Black Feminists|accessdate=May 31, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chicana feminism]] focuses on Mexican American, Chicana, and Hispanic women in the United States. Multiracial or "women of colour" feminism is related.&lt;ref name="Baca_Zinn"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Baca Zinn, Maxine|coauthor = Bonnie Thornton Dill |editor=Carole R. McCann &amp; Seung-Kyung Kim |title=Feminist Theory Reader: Local and Global Perspectives|year=2002 |chapter=Theorizing Difference from Multiracial Feminism.|place = New York |publisher=Routledge|isbn=0415931525}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Standpoint feminism|Standpoint feminist]]s argue that feminism should examine how women's experience of inequality relates to that of [[racism]], [[homophobia]], [[classism]], and [[colonization]].&lt;ref name="BFT" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Harding2003"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Harding, Sandra |title=The Feminist Standpoint Theory Reader: Intellectual and Political Controversies |year=2004 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=978-0-415-94501-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Postcolonial feminism|Postcolonial feminist]]s argue that [[colonialism|colonial]] oppression and Western feminism marginalized postcolonial women but did not turn them passive or voiceless.&lt;ref name=Weedon&gt;Weedon, C: "Key Issues in Postcolonial Feminism: A Western Perspective," 2002&lt;/ref&gt; [[Third-world feminism]] is closely related to postcolonial feminism.&lt;ref name="Narayan"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Narayan, Uma |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Dislocating Cultures: Identities, Traditions, and Third-World Feminism |year=1997 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=0-415-91418-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; These ideas also correspond with ideas in African feminism, motherism,&lt;ref name="Acholonu"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Obianuju Acholonu, Catherine |title=Motherism: The Afrocentric Alternative to Feminism |year=1995 |publisher=Afa Publ. |isbn=9783199714 |page=144}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stiwanism,&lt;ref name="Ogundipe-Leslie"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Ogundipe-Leslie, Molara |title=Re-creating Ourselves: African Women &amp; Critical Transformations |year=1994 |publisher=Africa World Press |isbn=0865434123 |page=262}}&lt;/ref&gt; negofeminism,&lt;ref name="Nnaemeka"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Nnaemeka |first=O. |title=Feminism, Rebellious Women, and Cultural Boundaries |journal=Research in African Literatures |year=1970}}&lt;/ref&gt; femalism, [[transnational feminism]], and [[Africana womanism]].&lt;ref name="Hudson-Weems"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Hudson-Weems, Clenora |title=Africana Womanism: Reclaiming Ourselves |year=1994 |publisher=Bedford Publishers |location=Troy, Mich. |isbn=0-911557-11-3 |page=158}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Postmodern feminism|Postmodern feminist]]s argue that sex and gender are [[social construction|socially constructed]],&lt;ref name="Butler"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Butler, Judith |title=Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity |year=1999 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=9780415924993}}&lt;/ref&gt; that it is impossible to generalize women's experiences across cultures and histories,&lt;ref name="Benhabib"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Benhabib |first=Seyla |title=From Identity Politics to Social Feminism: A Plea for the Nineties |journal=Philosophy of Education |volume=1 |issue=2 |page=14 |year=1995 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that [[dualisms]] and traditional gender, feminism, and politics are too limiting.&lt;ref name="Harraway"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Harraway, Donna |title=Simians, Cyborgs and Women: The Reinvention of Nature |chapter=Cyborg Manifesto: Science, Technology, and Socialist-Feminism in the Late Twentieth Century |year=1991 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=1853431389 |page=32 |url=http://www.stanford.edu/dept/HPS/Haraway/CyborgManifesto.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Post-structural feminism]] uses various intellectual currents for feminist concerns.&lt;ref name="Johnson"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Barbara Johnson |title=The Feminist Difference: Literature, Psychoanalysis, Race and Gender |year=2002 |publisher=Harvard University Press |page=224 |isbn=0674001915}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many post-structural feminists maintain that difference is one of the most powerful tools that women possess.&lt;ref name="Johnson" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |editor=Price, Janet |others=Shildrick, Margrit |author=Irigaray, Luce |chapter=When Our Lips Speak Together |coauthors= |title=Feminist Theory and the Body: A Reader |year=1999 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=0-415-92566-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Riot grrrl]] (or riot grrl) is an underground feminist [[Punk rock|punk]] movement that started in the 1990s and is often associated with [[third-wave feminism]] (it is sometimes seen as its starting point). It was grounded in the [[DIY ethic|DIY philosophy]] of [[Punk ideologies#Punk ethics|punk values]]. Riot grrls took an [[anti-corporate]] stance of [[self-sufficiency]] and [[self-reliance]].&lt;ref name=Rowe-Finbeiner&gt;{{cite book |author=Rowe-Finkbeiner, Kristin |coauthors= |title=The F-Word: Feminism In Jeopardy—Women, Politics and the Future |year=2004 |publisher=Seal Press |isbn=1-58005-114-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Riot grrrl's emphasis on universal female identity and separatism often appears more closely allied with second-wave feminism than with the third wave.&lt;ref name=Rosenberg_Garofalo&gt;{{cite journal  |author=Rosenberg, Jessica | coauthor= Gitana Garofalo |title=Riot Grrrl: Revolutions from within |journal=Signs |volume=23  | number = 3 |date=Spring 1998 |issue=Feminisms and Youth Cultures  |doi=10.1086/495289  |page=809}}&lt;/ref&gt; The movement encouraged and made "adolescent girls’ standpoints central," allowing them to express themselves fully.&lt;ref name=Code&gt;{{cite book |author=Code, Lorraine |title=Encyclopedia of Feminist Theories |year=2004 |publisher=Routledge |place=London |isbn=10415308852 |page=560 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

[[Lipstick feminism]] is a cultural feminist movement that attempts to respond to the backlash of second-wave radical feminism of the 1960s and 1970s by reclaiming symbols of "feminine" identity such as make-up, suggestive clothing and having a sexual allure as valid and empowering personal choices.&lt;ref&gt;Scanlon, Jennifer, ''Bad girls go everywhere: the life of Helen Gurley Brown'', Oxford University Press US, 2009, ISBN 0195342054&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Joanne Hollows; Rachel Moseley (17 February 2006). [http://books.google.com/books?id=0RuRknkzxe4C&amp;pg=PA84 Feminism in popular culture]. Berg Publishers. p. 84. ISBN 9781845202231. Retrieved 18 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Societal impact ==
{{Main|Feminist effects on society}}
By 1970 in the U.S.A, four out of five adults had read or heard of women's liberation, although not all agreed with it.&lt;ref&gt;Siegel, Deborah, ''Sisterhood, Interrupted: From Radical Women to Grrls Gone Wild'' (N.Y.: Palgrave Macmillan, 2007 (ISBN 978-1-4039-8204-9)), p. 54 &amp; n. 14 (author Ph.D. &amp; fellow, Woodhull Institute for Ethical Leadership), citing a CBS News poll (Sep. 4–5, 1970) and Rosen, Ruth, ''The World Split Open: How the Modern Women's Movement Changed America'' (N.Y.: Viking, 2000), pp. 92–93.&lt;/ref&gt;

The feminist movement has effected change in Western society, including [[women's suffrage]]; in education; in [[gender neutrality in English]]; [[Equal pay for women|job pay more nearly equal to men's]]; the right to initiate divorce proceedings; the [[reproductive rights]] of women to make individual decisions on pregnancy (including access to [[contraceptive]]s and [[abortion]]); and the right to enter into contracts and own property.&lt;ref name="Butler2" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Messer-Davidow" /&gt; Feminists have struggled to protect women and girls from [[domestic violence]], [[sexual harassment]], and [[sexual assault]],&lt;ref name="Echols"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Echols, Alice |authorlink=Alice Echols |title=Daring to Be Bad: Radical Feminism in America, 1967–1975 |year=1989 |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |location=Minneapolis |isbn=0-8166-1787-2 |page=416}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Cornell" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amnesty.org/en/campaigns/stop-violence-against-women/issues/implementation-existing-laws ''Campaign: Stop Violence against Women''].&lt;/ref&gt; emphasizing the grounds as women's rights, rather than as men's traditional interests in families' safety for reproductive purposes. On economic matters, feminists have advocated for workplace rights, including [[maternity leave]], and against other forms of [[gender equality|gender-specific discrimination against women]].&lt;ref name="Butler2"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Butler |first=Judith |title=Feminism in Any Other Name |journal=Differences |volume=6 |page=30 |month=March |year=1992 |doi= | issue= 2–3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Messer-Davidow"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Messer-Davidow, Ellen |title=Disciplining Feminism: From Social Activism to Academic Discourse |year=2002 |publisher=Duke University Press |location=Durham, [[North Carolina|N.C.]] |isbn=978-0-8223-2843-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="shildrick"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Price, Janet |coauthors=Shildrick, Margrit |title=Feminist Theory and the Body: A Reader |year=1999 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=0-415-92566-5 |page=487}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have achieved some protections and societal changes through [[consciousness raising|sharing experiences]], developing [[Feminism#Theoretical schools|theory]], and campaigning for rights.&lt;ref name=Humm&gt;{{Cite book |author=Humm, Maggie |title=The Dictionary of Feminist Theory |year=1990 |publisher=Ohio State University Press |location=Columbus |isbn=0-8142-0506-2 |page=278}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Cornell"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Cornell, Drucilla |authorlink=Drucilla Cornell|title=At the Heart of Freedom: Feminism, Sex, and Equality |year=1998 |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton, N.J. |isbn=978-0-691-02896-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Humm2"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Humm, Maggie |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Modern Feminisms: Political, Literary, Cultural |year=1992 |publisher=Columbia University Press |location=New York |isbn=0-231-08072-7 |pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author= |title=Collins Dictionary and Thesaurus |year=2006 |publisher=Collins |location=London |isbn=0-00-722405-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author=Agnes, Michael |title=Webster's New World College Dictionary |year=2007 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |location= |isbn=0-7645-7125-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Civil rights ===
[[Image:CEDAW Participation.svg|thumb|Participation in the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women. {{Col-begin}}{{Col-2}}{{legend|#00aa00|Signed and ratified}}{{legend|#008000|Acceded or succeeded}}{{legend|#008080|Unrecognized state, abiding by treaty}}{{Col-2}}{{legend|#eeee00|Only signed}}{{legend|#ff1111|Non-signatory}}{{Col-end}}]]
From the 1960s on, the campaign for [[women's rights]]&lt;ref name="quarterly"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Lockwood, Bert B. |title=Women's Rights: A Human Rights Quarterly Reader |year=2006 |publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press |isbn=978-0-8018-8374-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; was met with mixed results&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jofreeman.com/feminism/suffrage.htm |title=FROM SUFFRAGE TO WOMEN'S LIBERATION: FEMINISM IN TWENTIETH CENTURY AMERICA by Jo Freeman}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the U.S. and the U.K. Other countries of the [[European Economic Community|EEC]] agreed to ensure that discriminatory laws would be phased out across the European Community.

In the U.S., the [[National Organization for Women]] ([[National Organization for Women|NOW]]) began in 1966 to seek women's equality, including through the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] ([[Equal Rights Amendment|ERA]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.now.org/history/purpos66.html|title=The National Organization for Women's 1966 Statement of Purpose}}&lt;/ref&gt; which did not pass, although [[Equal Rights Amendment#State constitutions|some states enacted their own]]. [[Reproductive rights]] in the U.S. centered on the court decision in [[Roe v. Wade|''Roe'' v. ''Wade'']] enunciating a woman's right to choose whether to carry a pregnancy to term. Western women gained more reliable [[birth control]], allowing family planning and careers. The movement started in the 1910s in the U.S. under [[Margaret Sanger]] and elsewhere under [[Marie Stopes]] and grew in the late 20th century.

The [[division of labor]] within [[household]]s was affected by the increased entry of women into workplaces in the 20th century. Sociologist [[Arlie Russell Hochschild]] found that, in two-career couples, men and women, on average, spend about equal amounts of time working, but women still spend more time on housework,&lt;ref name="Hochschild1"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Hochschild, Arlie Russell |coauthors=Machung, Anne |title=The Second Shift |year=2003 |publisher=Penguin Books |location=New York  |isbn=978-0-14-200292-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Hochschild2"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Hochschild, Arlie Russell |title=The Time Bind: When Work Becomes Home and Home Becomes Work |year=2001 |publisher=Henry Holt &amp; Co. |location=New York  |isbn=978-0-8050-6643-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; although [[Cathy Young]] responded by arguing that women may prevent equal participation by men in housework and parenting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dir.salon.com/story/mwt/feature/2000/06/12/gatekeeping/index.html |title=The Mama Lion at the Gate |accessdate=2008-07-08 |publisher=Salon.com |author=Young, Cathy |authorlink=Cathy Young}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In international law, the ''[[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]]'' (CEDAW) is an international convention adopted by the [[United Nations]] [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] and described as an international [[bill of rights]] for women. It came into force in those nations ratifying it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/cedaw.htm |title=Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women New York, 18 December 1979 |publisher=Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights|accessdate=2009-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the final three decades of the 20th century, Western women knew a new freedom through [[birth control]], which enabled women to plan their adult lives, often making way for both career and family. The movement had been started in the 1910s by US pioneering social reformer [[Margaret Sanger]] and in the UK and internationally by [[Marie Stopes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.u-s-history.com/pages/h1676.html|title=Margaret Sanger}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Language ===
{{details|Gender-neutral language in English}}
Gender-neutral language is a description of [[Word usage|language usages]] which are aimed at minimizing assumptions regarding the biological [[sex]] of human [[reference|referents]]. The advocacy of gender-neutral language reflects, at least, two different agendas: one aims to clarify the ''inclusion'' of both sexes or genders (gender-inclusive language); the other proposes that gender, as a category, is rarely worth marking in language (gender-neutral language). Gender-neutral language is sometimes described as ''non-sexist language'' by advocates and ''politically-correct language'' by opponents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usask.ca/policies/2_03.htm|title="Gender Neutral Language." University of Saskatchewan Policies 2001 |accessdate=2007-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Theology ===
{{see also|Feminist theology|God and gender}}
[[File:US Navy 080123-N-3385W-028 Cmdr. Adrienne Simmons, medical provider for Provincial Reconstruction Team Khost and only woman on the team, speaks at the groundbreaking ceremony for a women's mosque and park in downtown Khost City.jpg|thumb|Cmdr. Adrienne Simmons speaking at the 2008 ceremony for the first and only women's mosque in Khost City, a symbol of progress for growing women's rights in the Pashtun belt.]]
[[Feminist theology]] is a movement that reconsiders the traditions, practices, scriptures, and theologies of religions from a feminist perspective. Some of the goals of feminist theology include increasing the role of women among the clergy and religious authorities, reinterpreting male-dominated imagery and language about God, determining women's place in relation to career and motherhood, and studying images of women in the religion's sacred texts.&lt;ref name=Bundesen&gt;{{cite book |author=Bundesen, Lynne |title=The Feminine Spirit: Recapturing the Heart of Scripture |publisher=Jossey-Bass |isbn=978-0-7879-8495-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Christian feminism]] is a branch of feminist theology which seeks to interpret and understand [[Christianity]] in light of the equality of women and men, and that this interpretation is necessary for a complete understanding of Christianity. While there is no standard set of beliefs among Christian feminists, most agree that God does not discriminate on the basis of biologically-determined characteristics such as sex, and are involved in issues such as the [[ordination of women]], male dominance and the balance of parenting in Christian marriage, claims of moral deficiency and inferiority of abilities of women compared to men, and the overall treatment of women in the church.&lt;ref name=Haddad&gt;{{cite journal |author=Haddad, Mimi |title=Egalitarian Pioneers: Betty Friedan or Catherine Booth? |journal=Priscilla Papers |year=2007 |volume=20 |date=Autumn 2006 | issue = 4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=andeson&gt;{{cite book |author=Anderson, Pamela Sue |coauthors=Clack, Beverley |title=Feminist philosophy of religion: critical readings |year=2004 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=0-415-25749-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Islamic feminism]] is concerned with the role of [[Women and Islam|women in Islam]] and aims for the full equality of all [[Muslims]], regardless of gender, in public and private life. Islamic feminists advocate [[women's rights]], [[gender equality]], and social justice grounded in an Islamic framework. Although rooted in Islam, the movement's pioneers have also utilized secular and Western feminist discourses and recognize the role of Islamic feminism as part of an integrated global feminist movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.feminismeislamic.org/eng/index.htm|publisher=feminismeislamic.org |author=Catalonian Islamic Board |title=II International Congress on Islamic Feminism|accessdate=2008-07-09 |date=24–27 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advocates of the movement seek to highlight the deeply rooted teachings of equality in the [[Quran]] and encourage a questioning of the patriarchal interpretation of Islamic teaching through the Quran, ''[[hadith]]'' (sayings of [[Muhammad]]), and ''[[sharia]]'' (law) towards the creation of a more equal and just society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2002/569/cu1.htm|title=Al-Ahram Weekly: Islamic feminism: what's in a name? |author=Badran, Margot |accessdate=2008-07-09 |date=17–23 January 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jewish feminism]] is a movement that seeks to improve the religious, legal, and social status of women within [[Judaism]] and to open up new opportunities for religious experience and leadership for Jewish women. Feminist movements, with varying approaches and successes, have opened up within all major branches of Judaism. The main issues for early Jewish feminists in these movements were the exclusion from the all-male prayer group or ''[[minyan]]'', the exemption from positive time-bound ''[[Mitzvah|mitzvot]]'', and women's inability to function as witnesses and to initiate [[Jewish view of marriage#Divorce|divorce]].&lt;ref name=Plaskow1997&gt;{{cite book |author=Plaskow, Judith |editor=Frank, Daniel H. |others=Leaman, Oliver |title=History of Jewish philosophy |year=2003 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=0-415-32469-6 |chapter=Jewish Feminist Thought}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Dianic Wicca]] or Wiccan feminism is a female focused, Goddess-centered Wiccan sect; also known as a feminist religion that teaches witchcraft as every woman’s right. It is also one sect of many practiced in [[Wicca]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Raphael, Melissa |title=Introducing Thealogy: Discourse on the Goddess |year=1999 |publisher=Routledge |chapter=Chapter ^: Feminist Witchcraft|isbn=1850759758}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Secular or [[atheist feminism|atheist feminists]] have engaged in feminist criticism of religion, arguing that many religions have oppressive rules towards women and [[misogynistic]] themes and elements in religious texts.&lt;ref&gt;Gaylor, Annie Laurie, ''Woe To The Women: The Bible Tells Me So'', Freedom From Religion Foundation, Inc. (July 1, 1981) ISBN 1877733024&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ali, Ayaan Hirsi  ''The Caged Virgin: A Muslim Woman's Cry for Reason'', Free Press 2004, ISBN 9780743288330&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Miles, Rosalind, ''Who cooked the Last Supper?'',Random House Digital, Inc., 2001, ISBN 0609806955&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Patriarchy ===
{{main|Patriarchy}}
Patriarchy is a social system in which the role of the male as the primary authority figure is central to social organization, and where fathers hold authority over women, children, and property. It implies the institutions of male rule and privilege, and is dependent on female subordination.&lt;ref&gt;''MacMillan Encyclopedia of Sex and Gender'' p. 1104.&lt;/ref&gt;  Most forms of feminism characterize patriarchy as an unjust social system that is [[oppression|oppressive]] to women. As the feminist and political theorist [[Carole Pateman]] writes: "The patriarchal construction of the difference between masculinity and femininity is the political difference between freedom and subjection."&lt;ref&gt;Pateman, Carole (1988). ''The Sexual Contract'', Stanford: Stanford University Press, p. 207.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[feminist theory]] the concept of patriarchy often includes all the social mechanisms that reproduce and exert male dominance over women. Feminist theory typically characterizes patriarchy as a social construction, which can be overcome by revealing and critically analyzing its manifestations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Tickner, Ann J.|chapter=Patriarchy|title=Routledge Encyclopedia of International Political Economy: Entries P-Z|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2001|isbn=9780415243520|pages=1197–1198|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=lSmU3aXWIAYC&amp;pg=PA1197}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some [[radical feminism|radical feminists]] have proposed that because patriarchy is too deeply rooted in society, [[Separatist feminism|separatism]] is the only viable solution.&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Hoagland, Lesbian Ethics: toward new value&lt;/ref&gt; Other feminists have criticized these radical feminist views as being anti-men, though some radical feminists reject this portrayal of their views.&lt;ref&gt;Friedan, Betty. The Second Stage: With a New Introduction. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard Univ. Press, © 1981 1986 1991 1998, 1st Harvard Univ. Press pbk. ed. (ISBN 0-674-79655-1) 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bullough, Vern L. Human sexuality: an encyclopedia, Taylor &amp; Francis, 1994, ISBN 0824079728&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Echols, Alice, ''Daring to Be Bad'', ''op. cit.'', p. 78 &amp; n. 124 ("124. Interview with Cindy Cisler.") and see p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt; Societal tension caused by second-wave feminism gave rise to backlash in the form of anti-feminist men's movements, such as [[Masculism]], though today some see masculism as a complementary movement that does not oppose feminism.&lt;ref name="Gardiner" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Honderich, Ted, ''The Oxford companion to philosophy',' Oxford University Press, 1995, ISBN 0198661320&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Men and masculinity ===
{{main|Men and feminism}}
Feminist theory has explored the social construction of masculinity and its implications for the goal of gender equality. The social construct of masculinity{{Clarify|date=July 2011}} is seen by feminism as problematic because it associates males with aggression and competition, and reinforces [[patriarchy|patriarchal]] and unequal gender relations.&lt;ref name="Faludi" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tong, Rosemarie Putnam, Feminist Thought: A More Comprehensive Introduction (Boulder, Colo.: Westview Press, 2d ed. 1998 (ISBN 0-8133-3295-8)), p. 70&lt;/ref&gt; The patriarchal concept of masculinity is also seen as harmful to men by narrowing their life choices, limiting their sexuality, and blocking full emotional connections with women and other men.&lt;ref name="Gardiner"&gt;Gardiner, Judith Kegan, ''Masculinity studies and feminist theory'', Columbia University Press, 2002, ISBN 0231122780&lt;/ref&gt; Some feminists are engaged with men's issues activism, such as bringing attention to male rape and spousal battery and addressing negative social expectations for men.&lt;ref&gt;Harv. Women's L.J. 107 (1978) Fathers' Rights and Feminism: The Maternal Presumption Revisited; Uviller, Rena K.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Unwed Fathers' Rights, Adoption, and Sex Equality: Gender-Neutrality and the Perpetuation of Patriarchy&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Feminism for Men: Legal Ideology and the Construction of Maleness, N Levit – UCLA L. Rev., 1995 – works.bepress.com&lt;/ref&gt;

Male participation in feminism is encouraged by feminists and is seen as an important strategy for achieving full societal commitment to gender equality.&lt;ref name="hooks" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Digby, Tom (1998). Men Doing Feminism. New York: Routledge. ISBN 978-0-415-91625-7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Phillips, Layli, ''The Womanist reader'', CRC Press, 2006, ISBN 0415954118&lt;/ref&gt; Many male feminists and pro-feminists are active in both women's rights activism, feminist theory, and masculinity studies. However, some argue that while male engagement with feminism is necessary, it is problematic due to the ingrained social influences of patriarchy in gender relations.&lt;ref&gt;Jardine, Alice, Paul Smith, ''Men in feminism '', ISBN 0415902517&lt;/ref&gt; The consensus today in feminist and masculinity theories is that both genders can and should cooperate to achieve the larger goals of feminism.&lt;ref name="Gardiner" /&gt;

== Culture ==
{{Main|Feminism in culture}}
According to the [[Tate Collection]], feminist art can "be defined as art by women artists made consciously in the light of developments in feminist art theory since about 1970."&lt;ref name=tate&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tate.org.uk/collections/glossary/definition.jsp?entryId=103 |title=Tae | Glossary | Feminist art |accessdate=14 November 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Architecture ===
Gender-based inquiries into and conceptualization of architecture have also come about, leading to [[Feminism and modern architecture|feminism in modern architecture]]. Piyush Mathur coined the term "archigenderic". Claiming that "architectural planning has an inextricable link with the defining and regulation of gender roles, responsibilities, rights, and limitations", Mathur came up with that term "to explore...the meaning of 'architecture' in terms of gender" and "to explore the meaning of 'gender' in terms of architecture".&lt;ref&gt;Mathur, Piyush, in ''Women's Writing'', p.&amp;nbsp;71 (1998) (British journal) (article).&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Literature ===
[[File:Butler signing.jpg|thumb|[[Octavia Butler]], award winning feminist science fiction author.]]
{{details|Women's writing in English|Women's literature written in English}}
The feminist movement produced both feminist fiction and non-fiction, and created new interest in women's writing. It also prompted a general reevaluation of women's [[Women's history|historical]] and academic contributions in response to the belief that women's lives and contributions have been underrepresented as areas of scholarly interest.&lt;ref name=Blain&gt;{{cite book |author=Blain, Virginia |coauthors=Clements, Patricia; Grundy, Isobel |title=The feminist companion to literature in English: women writers from the Middle Ages to the present |year=1990 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven |isbn=0-300-04854-8 |page=1231}}&lt;/ref&gt; Much of the early period of feminist literary scholarship was given over to the rediscovery and reclamation of texts written by women. Commensurate with this growth in scholarly interest, various presses such as [[Virago Press]] and Pandora Press began reissuing long-out-of-print texts.&lt;ref&gt;Sandra M. Gilbert, "[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DD1E3AF937A35756C0A960948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=1 Paperbacks: From Our Mothers' Libraries: women who created the novel]." ''New York Times'', May 4, 1986.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mary Wollstonecraft]] wrote one of the first works of feminist philosophy, [[A Vindication of the Rights of Woman]] which called for equal education for women in 1792 and her daughter, [[Mary Shelley]] became an accomplished author best known for her 1818 novel [[Frankenstein]]. [[The Female Eunuch]], by Australian feminist [[Germaine Greer]], was first published in 1970, and became an international bestseller and an important text in the feminist movement.

Beginning in the 1960s, authors used the genre of [[Feminist science fiction|science fiction]] to explore feminist themes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Clute, John |coauthors=Nicholls, Peter |title=The Encyclopedia of science fiction |year=1995 |publisher=St. Martin's Griffin |location=New York |isbn=0-312-13486-X |page=1386}}&lt;/ref&gt; Notable books in this genre include [[Ursula K. Le Guin|Ursula K. Le Guin's]] ''[[The Left Hand of Darkness]]'' (1969), [[Joanna Russ]]' ''[[The Female Man]]'' (1970).  [[Octavia Butler]]'s ''[[Kindred (novel)|Kindred]]'', and [[Margaret Atwood]]'s''[[The Handmaid's Tale]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Sturgis, Susanna. Octavia E. Butler: June 22, 1947 – February 24, 2006: ''The Women's Review of Books'', 23(3): 19 May 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Elyce Rae Helford, in Westfahl, Gary. The Greenwood Encyclopedia of Science Fiction and Fantasy: Greenwood Press, 2005: 290.&lt;/ref&gt;  Russ, Le Guin, and other authors also engaged in feminist criticism of science fiction in the 1960s and 70s.&lt;ref&gt;The Language of the Night (Le Guin, 1979)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Music ===
{{main| Women's music}}

[[Women's music]] (or womyn's music or wimmin's music) is the music by women, for women, and about women.&lt;ref name="NoSmPvtPty"&gt;Lont, Cynthia, ''Women's Music: No Longer a Small Private Party'', in Reebee Garofalo, ed., ''Rockin' the Boat: Mass Music &amp; Mass Movements'' (Cambridge, MA: South End Press, 1992 (ISBN 0-89608-427-2), p. 242).&lt;/ref&gt; The genre emerged as a musical expression of the [[second-wave feminist]] movement&lt;ref&gt;Peraino, Judith, ''Girls with Guitars and Other Strange Stories'', in ''Journal of the American Musicological Society'', vol. 54, no. 3 (2001), p. 693.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[labour (economics)|labor]], [[civil rights]], and [[peace movement]]s.&lt;ref name="RadHarmonies"&gt;Mosbacher, Dee, ''Radical Harmonies'', ''Woman Vision'' (2002 (OCLC 53071762)). See also [http://www.woman-vision.org/radicalharmonies/index.htm].&lt;/ref&gt; The movement was started by lesbians such as [[Cris Williamson]], [[Meg Christian]], and [[Margie Adam]], African-American women activists such as [[Bernice Johnson Reagon]] and her group [[Sweet Honey in the Rock]], and peace activist [[Holly Near]].&lt;ref name="RadHarmonies" /&gt; Women's music also refers to the wider industry of women's music that goes beyond the performing artists to include [[studio musicians]], [[record producer|producers]], [[sound engineer]]s, [[technician]]s, cover artists, [[distributors]], [[promoter (entertainment)|promoter]]s, and festival organizers who are also women.&lt;ref name="NoSmPvtPty" /&gt;

Feminsim became a principal concern of musicologists in the 1980s.&lt;ref name=mus&gt;Beard, David; Gload, Kenneth. 2005. Musicology : The Key Concepts. London and New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to this, in the 1970s, musicologists were beginning to discover women composers and performers, and had begun to review concepts of canon, genius, genre and periodization from a feminist perspective. In other words, the question of how women musicians fit into the traditional music history realm was now being asked.&lt;ref name=mus/&gt;

Through the 1980s and 1990s musicologists such as Susan McClary, Marcia Citron and Ruth Solie began to consider the cultural reasons for the marginalizing of women from the received body of work. Concepts such as music as gendered discourse; professionalism; reception of women's music; examination of the sites of music production; relative wealth and education of women; popular music studies in relation to women's identity; patriarchal ideas in music analysis; and notions of gender and difference are among the themes examined during this time.&lt;ref name=mus/&gt;

== Sexuality ==
[[Lesbian]]ism and [[bisexuality]] were accepted as part of feminism by a significant proportion of feminists, while others considered sexuality irrelevant to the attainment of other goals. Sexuality, sexual representation, [[sadomasochism]], the role of [[transwomen]] in the lesbian community, and other sexual issues arose within acrimonious feminist debates known as the [[feminist sex wars]].

Opinions on the [[sex industry]] are diverse. They are generally either critical of it (seeing it as exploitative, a result of patriarchal social structures and reinforcing sexual and cultural attitudes that are complicit in [[rape]] and [[sexual harassment]]) or supportive of at least parts of it (arguing that some forms of it can be a medium of feminist expression and a means of women taking control of their sexuality).

=== Distinction between sex and gender ===
The [[Sex and gender distinction|distinction between ''sex'' and ''gender'']] is generally that ''sex'' is biological (''e.g.'', chromosomal or morphological) while ''gender'' is social or cultural (''e.g.'', how societies structure relationships.)&lt;ref&gt;[[Shira Tarrant|Tarrant, Shira]], ''When Sex Became Gender'' (Routledge, 2006),&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Pornography ===
{{details|Feminist sex wars}}
{{see also|Anti-pornography#Feminist objections|Sex-positive feminism}}
The "Feminist Sex Wars" is a term for the acrimonious debates within the feminist movement in the late 1970s through the 1980s around the issues of feminism, sexuality, sexual representation, [[pornography]], [[sadomasochism]], the role of [[transwomen]] in the lesbian community, and other sexual issues. The debate pitted [[Anti-pornography movement|anti-pornography feminism]] against [[sex-positive feminism]], and parts of the feminist movement were deeply divided by these debates.&lt;ref name=Duggan&gt;{{cite book |author=Duggan, Lisa; Hunter, Nan D. |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Sex wars: sexual dissent and political culture |year=1995 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=0-415-91036-6 |pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hansen&gt;{{cite book |author=Hansen, Karen Tranberg; |coauthors=Philipson, Ilene J. |title=Women, class, and the feminist imagination: a socialist-feminist reader |year=1990 |publisher=Temple University Press |location=Philadelphia |isbn=0-87722-630-X |pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gerhard&gt;{{cite book |author=Gerhard, Jane F. |title=Desiring revolution: second-wave feminism and the rewriting of American sexual thought, 1920 to 1982 |year=2001 |publisher=Columbia University Press |location=New York |isbn=0-231-11204-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Leidholdt&gt;{{cite book |author=Leidholdt, Dorchen; |authorlink=Dorchen Leidholdt |coauthors=Raymond, Janice G |title=The Sexual liberals and the attack on feminism |year=1990 |publisher=Pergamon Press |location=New York |isbn=0-08-037457-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Vance&gt;{{cite book |author=Vance, Carole S. |title=Pleasure and Danger: Exploring Female Sexuality |publisher=Thorsons Publishers|isbn=0-04-440593-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Prostitution and trafficking ===
{{Main|Feminist views on prostitution}}
Feminists' views on prostitution vary, but many of these perspectives can be loosely arranged into an overarching standpoint that is generally either critical or supportive  of prostitution and [[sex work]].&lt;ref&gt;O’Neill, Maggie (2001) ''Prostitution and Feminism''. Polity Press: Cambridge pp. 14–16&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-prostitution feminists are strongly opposed to prostitution, as they see the practice as a form of violence against and exploitation of women, and a sign of male dominance over women. Feminists who hold such views on prostitution include Kathleen Barry, [[Melissa Farley]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prostitutionresearch.com/faq/000008.html Prostitution: Factsheet on Human Rights Violations]. Prostitution Research &amp; Education. Retrieved on 2009-09-03.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prostitutionresearch.com/FarleyProstitution%26InvisibleHarm2003.pdf Farley, Mellisa, ''Prostitution and the Invisibility of Harm'', cited to ''Women &amp; Therapy'', vol. 26, no. 3/4 (2003) 247–280, hosted by Prostitution Research &amp; Education], as accessed Mar. 6, 2011. For a non-.pdf and shorter version, see [http://www.prostitutionresearch.com/how_prostitution_works/000176.html excerpt (same author, title, and ''Women &amp; Therapy'' citation)], as accessed Mar. 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Julie Bindel]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2006/jan/18/ukcrime.prisonsandprobation |title=Eradicate the oldest oppression |author=Julie Bindel |date=18 January 2006 |publisher=The Guardian |accessdate=8 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2007/sep/10/endingatradeinmisery Ending a trade in misery] (10 September 2007). The Guardian. Retrieved on 2009-09-03.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sheila Jeffreys]], [[Catharine MacKinnon]]&lt;ref&gt;Catharine A. MacKinnon (1993) "[http://www.prostitutionresearch.com/mackinnon1.html Prostitution And Civil Rights]" Michigan Journal of Gender &amp; Law, 1993, Volume 1: 13–31. Retrieved on 2009-09-03.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Laura Lederer]];&lt;ref&gt;Lederer Laura J. [http://www.globalcenturion.org/Articles/Demand.aspx Addressing Demand: Examining New Practices]. Global Centurion. Retrieved on 2009-09-03.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[European Women's Lobby]] has also condemned prostitution as "an intolerable form of male violence".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.womenslobby.eu/spip.php?article472&amp;lang=en European Women's Lobby Européen des femmes : Prostitution in Europe: 60 Years of Reluctance]. Womenslobby.eu. Retrieved on 2011-06-12.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other feminists hold that prostitution and other forms of [[sex work]] can be valid choices for women and men who choose to engage in it. In this view, prostitution must be differentiated from forced prostitution, and feminists should support [[sex workers' rights|sex worker activism]] against abuses by both the sex industry and the legal system. The disagreement between these two feminist stances has proven particularly contentious, and may be comparable to the [[feminist sex wars]] of the late twentieth century.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, Priscilla (1997) ''Feminism, Sex Workers and Human Rights'' in Nagle, Jill (ed.) Whores and Other Feminists. Routledge: New York: pp. 83–90.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Relationship to political movements ==
In the U.S., feminism, when politically active, formerly aligned largely with the [[right-wing politics|political right]], e.g., through the [[National Woman's Party]], from the 1910s to the 1960s, and presently aligns largely with the [[left-wing politics|left]], e.g., through the [[National Organization for Women]], of the 1960s to the present, although in neither case has the alignment been consistent.

=== Socialism ===
{{main|Left-wing politics#Social progressivism and counterculture|l1=Left-Wing Politics (section Social Progressivism and Counterculture (on feminism))}}
Since the early twentieth century some feminists have allied with [[socialism]]. In 1907 there was an International Conference of Socialist Women in [[Stuttgart]] where suffrage was described as a tool of class struggle. [[Clara Zetkin]] of the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany]] called for women's suffrage to build a "''socialist order, the only one that allows for a radical solution to the women's question''".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marxismo.net/idm/idm5/idm5.htm|title=Rossi, Elisabetta. L'emancipazione femminile in Russia prima e dopo la rivoluzione In difesa del marxismo Nr. 5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marxist.com/emancipation-women-russia.htm|title=The Emancipation of Women in Russia before and after the Russian Revolution In Defence of Marxism}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Badia, Gilbert |title=Zetkin. Femminista senza frontiere |year=1994 |publisher=University of Michigan. |isbn=8885378536 |page=320}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hww5"/&gt;

In Britain, the women's movement was allied with the [[Labour party (UK)|Labour party]]. In the U.S., [[Betty Friedan]] emerged from a radical background to take leadership. [[Radical Women]] is the oldest socialist feminist organization in the U.S. and is still active.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author= |coauthors= |title=The Radical Women Manifesto: Socialist Feminist Theory, Program and Organizational Structure |year=2001 |publisher=Red Letter Press |location=Seattle, WA |isbn=0-932323-11-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Spanish Civil War]], [[Dolores Ibárruri]] (''La Pasionaria'') led the [[Communist Party of Spain (main)|Communist Party of Spain]]. Although she supported equal rights for women, she opposed women fighting on the front and clashed with the [[Anarcha-Feminism|anarcha-feminist]] [[Mujeres Libres]].&lt;ref name="Ib"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Ibárruri, Dolores |title=Speeches &amp; Articles, 1936–1938 |year=1938 |publisher=University of Michigan |page=263}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Latin America, revolutions brought changes in women's status in countries such as [[Role of women in Nicaraguan Revolution|Nicaragua]], where [[feminist ideology during the Sandinista Revolution]] aided women's quality of life but fell short of achieving a social and ideological change.&lt;ref name="parpart"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Parpart, Jane L. |coauthors=Connelly, M. Patricia; Connelly, Patricia; Barriteau, V. Eudine; Barriteau, Eudine |title=Theoretical Perspectives on Gender and Development |date= |publisher=Ottawa, Canada : International Development Research Centre 2000. |isbn=0-88936-910-0 |page=215}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Fascism ===
Scholars have argued that [[Nazi Germany]] and the other [[fascist]] states of the 1930s and 1940s illustrates the disastrous consequences for society of a state ideology that, in glorifying women, becomes anti-feminist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Bridenthal, Renate |coauthors=Grossmann, Atina; Kaplan, Marion A. |title=When biology became destiny: women in Weimar and Nazi Germany |year=1984 |publisher=Monthly Review Press |location=New York |isbn=0-85345-642-9 |page=364}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Germany after the rise of [[Nazism]] in 1933, there was a rapid dissolution of the political rights and economic opportunities that feminists had fought for during the prewar period and to some extent during the 1920s. In Franco's Spain, the right wing Catholic conservatives undid the work of feminists during the Republic. Fascist society was hierarchical with an emphasis and idealization of virility, with women maintaining a largely subordinate position to men.&lt;ref name=hww5&gt;{{cite book |author=Duby, Georges |coauthors=Perrot, Michelle; Pantel, Pauline, Schmitt |title=A history of women in the West |year=1994 |publisher=Belknap Press of Harvard University Press |location=Cambridge, Mass. |isbn=0-674-40369-X |page=600}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Civil rights movement and anti-racism ===
The [[civil rights movement]] has influenced and informed the feminist movement and vice versa. Many Western feminists adapted the language and theories of black equality activism and drew parallels between women's rights and the rights of non-white people.&lt;ref name="Levy"&gt;Levy, Peter B. ''The civil rights movement '',  Greenwood Publishing Group, 1998, ISBN 0313298548&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the connections between the women's and civil rights movements, some tension arose during the late 1960s and early 1970s as non-white women argued that feminism was predominantly white and middle class, and did not understand and was not concerned with race issues.&lt;ref&gt;Code, Lorraine, ''Encyclopedia of feminist theories'', "civil rights" entry, Taylor &amp; Francis, 2000, ISBN 0415132746&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, some women argued that the civil rights movement had sexist elements and did not adequately address minority women's concerns.&lt;ref name="Levy" /&gt; These criticisms created new feminist social theories about the intersections of [[racism]], [[classism]], and sexism, and new feminisms, such as black feminism and Chicana feminism.&lt;ref&gt;Roth, Benita, ''Separate roads to feminism: Black, Chicana, and White feminist movements in America's second wave'', Cambridge University Press, 2004, ISBN 0521529727&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently, many feminist organizations worldwide participate in [[anti-racism]] activism, in diverse areas such as [[immigration law]] in Europe, [[Caste system in India|caste discrimination]] in India, and the discrimination of formerly [[slavery|enslaved African ethnic groups]] in Africa and the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;Winddance Twine, France, and Kathleen M. Blee, ''Feminism and antiracism: international struggles for justice'', NYU Press, 2001, ISBN 0814798551&lt;/ref&gt;

== Science ==
Some feminists, such as [[Evelyn Fox Keller]], criticize traditional [[rhetoric of science|scientific discourse]] as historically biased towards a masculine perspective,&lt;ref name="shildrick" /&gt; including the idea of [[scientific objectivity]]. [[Primatologist]] [[Sarah Blaffer Hrdy]] notes the prevalence of masculinely coined stereotypes and theories, such as of the non-sexual female, despite "the accumulation of abundant openly available evidence contradicting it".&lt;ref name="Hrdy"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Blaffer Hrdy |first=Sarah |title=Infanticide: Comparative and Evolutionary Perspectives: Mother Nature: A History of Mothers, Infants and Natural Selection |publisher=Pantheon, 1999 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many feminist scholars rely on qualitative scientific research methods that emphasize women's subjective and individual experiences, including treating research participants as authorities equal to the researcher. Objectivity is eschewed in favor of open self-reflexivity and the agenda of helping women. Also, part of the feminist research agenda is the uncovering of ways in which power inequities are created and/or reinforced in society and in scientific and academic institutions. A feminist approach to research often involves nontraditional forms of presentation.&lt;ref name="QCommRsrch"&gt;Lindlof, Thomas R., &amp; Taylor, Bryan C., ''Qualitative Communication Research Methods'' (Thousand Oaks: Sage Publications, 2002 (978-0-7619-2493-7)), p. 357 (authors communication scholars).&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Biology of gender ===
{{main|Biology of gender}}
Modern feminist science challenges the biological [[Gender essentialism|essentialist]] view of [[gender]].&lt;ref&gt;Code, Lorraine, ''Encyclopedia of feminist theories'', Taylor &amp; Francis, 2000, ISBN 0415132746 p. 89&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bern, Sandra L., ''The lenses of gender: transforming the debate on sexual inequality'', Yale University Press, 1993, ISBN 0300056761, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is increasingly interested in the study of [[sexual differentiation|biological sex differences]] and their effect on [[human behavior]]. For example, [[Anne Fausto-Sterling]]'s book, ''Myths of Gender'', explores the assumptions embodied in scientific research that purports to support a biologically [[essentialist]] view of gender.&lt;ref name="Fausto-Sterling"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Fausto-Sterling, Anne |title=Myths of Gender: Biological Theories About Women and Men |year=1992 |publisher=BasicBooks |location=New York, New York  |isbn=0-465-04792-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;  For example, in ''[[Delusions of Gender]]'' [[Cordelia Fine]] argues that there is currently no scientific evidence for innate biological differences between men and women's minds, and that cultural and societal beliefs contribute to commonly perceived sex differences.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Fine |first=Cordelia |title=Delusions of Gender: How Our Minds, Society, and Neurosexism Create Difference |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Evolutionary biology ===
Sarah Kember—drawing from numerous areas such as [[evolutionary biology]], [[sociobiology]], [[artificial intelligence]], and [[cybernetics]] in development with a new evolutionism—discusses the biologization of technology. She notes how feminists and sociologists have become suspicious of [[evolutionary psychology]], particularly in as much as sociobiology is subjected to [[complexity]] in order to strengthen sexual difference as [[wiktionary:immutable|immutable]] through pre-existing cultural value judgments about [[human nature]] and [[natural selection]].&lt;ref name="Kember"&gt;{{Cite journal  |author=Kember, Sarah |title=Resisting the New Evolutionism |journal=Women: a Cultural Review |year=2001 |volume=12 |month=Spring |page=8  |doi=10.1080/09574040110034075  | issue = 1  |unused_data=DUPLICATE DATA: year=1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; Where feminist theory is criticized for its "false beliefs about human nature", Kember then argues in conclusion that "feminism is in the interesting position of needing to do more biology and evolutionary theory in order not to simply oppose their renewed hegemony, but in order to understand the conditions that make this possible, and to have a say in the construction of new ideas and artefacts."&lt;ref name="Kember" /&gt;

== Reactions ==
Different groups of people have responded to feminism, and both men and women have been among its supporters and critics. Among American university students, for both men and women, support for feminist ideas is more common than self-identification as a feminist.&lt;ref&gt;Zucker, A. N. (2004), DISAVOWING SOCIAL IDENTITIES: WHAT IT MEANS WHEN WOMEN SAY, “I'M NOT A FEMINIST, BUT …”. Psychology of Women Quarterly, 28: 423–435. [http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-6402.2004.00159.x DOI].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shawn Meghan Burn, Roger Aboud and Carey Moyles, "The Relationship Between Gender Social Identity and Support for Feminism", ''Sex Roles'', Volume 42, Numbers 11–12, 1081–1089, [http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1007044802798 DOI].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Claire M. Renzetti, "New wave or second stage? Attitudes of college women toward feminism ", ''Sex Roles'', Volume 16, Numbers 5–6, 265–277, [http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00289954 DOI].&lt;/ref&gt; The US media tends to portray feminism negatively and feminists "are less often associated with day-to-day work/leisure activities of regular women."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Lind | first1 = R. A. | last2 = Salo | first2 = C. | year = 2002 | title = The Framing of Feminists and Feminism in News and Public Affairs Programs in U.S. Electronic Media | url = | journal = Journal of Communication | volume = 52 | issue = | pages = 211–228 | doi = 10.1111/j.1460-2466.2002.tb02540.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Roy, R. E., Weibust, K. S. and Miller, C. T. (2007), EFFECTS OF STEREOTYPES ABOUT FEMINISTS ON FEMINIST SELF-IDENTIFICATION. Psychology of Women Quarterly, 31: 146–156. doi: 10.1111/j.1471-6402.2007.00348.x&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Pro-feminism ===
{{main|Pro-feminism}}
[[Pro-feminism]] is the support of feminism without implying that the supporter is a member of the feminist movement. The term is most often used in reference to men who are actively supportive of feminism. The activities of pro-feminist men's groups include anti-violence work with boys and young men in schools, offering [[sexual harassment]] workshops in workplaces, running community education campaigns, and counseling male perpetrators of violence. Pro-feminist men also are involved in men's health, activism against pornography including anti-pornography legislation, [[men's studies]], and the development of [[gender equality|gender equity]] curricula in schools. This work is sometimes in collaboration with feminists and women's services, such as domestic violence and rape crisis centers. Some activists of both genders will not refer to men as "feminists" at all and will refer to all men who support feminism as "pro-feminists".&lt;ref name="Lingard-isbnX-p192"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Lingard, Bob |coauthors=Douglas, Peter |title=Men Engaging Feminisms: Pro-Feminism, Backlashes and Schooling |year=1999 |publisher=Open University Press |location=Buckingham, England |isbn=0-335-19818-X |page=192}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kimmel-Tide"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Kimmel, Michael S. |authorlink=Michael Kimmel |coauthors=Mosmiller, Thomas E. |title=Against the Tide: Pro-Feminist Men in the United States, 1776–1990: A Documentary History |year=1992 |publisher=Beacon Press |location=Boston |isbn=978-0-8070-6767-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Anti-feminism ===
{{main|Anti-feminism}}
Anti-feminism is opposition to feminism in some or all of its forms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.oed.com/cgi/entry/50009621/50009621se1|title="Anti-feminist." ''The Oxford English Dictionary''. 2nd ed. 1989}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the nineteenth century, anti-feminism was mainly focused on opposition to women's suffrage. Later, opponents of women's entry into institutions of higher learning argued that education was too great a physical burden on women. Other anti-feminists opposed women's entry into the labor force, or their right to join unions, to sit on juries, or to obtain birth control and control of their sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;Kimmel, Michael (2004). "Antifeminism". In Kimmel, Michael. Men and Masculinities: A Social, Cultural, and Historical Encyclopedia. Santa Barbara: ABC-CLIO. pp. 35–7&lt;/ref&gt;

Some people have opposed feminism on the grounds that they believe it is contrary to traditional values or religious beliefs. These anti-feminists argue, for example, that social acceptance of divorce and non-married women is wrong and harmful, and that men and women are fundamentally different and thus their different traditional roles in society should be maintained.&lt;ref&gt;Carrie L. Lukas, The politically incorrect guide to women, sex, and feminism, Regnery Publishing, 2006, ISBN 1596980036&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mary A. Kassian, The feminist mistake: the radical impact of feminism on church and culture, Crossway, 2005, ISBN 1581345704&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schlafly, Phyllis (1977). The Power of the Positive Woman. New York: Arlington House Publishers&lt;/ref&gt; Other anti-feminists oppose women's entry into the workforce, political office, and the voting process, as well as the lessening of male authority in families.&lt;ref&gt;Gottfried, Paul (2001). "The Trouble With Feminism". LewRockwell.com. http://www.lewrockwell.com/gottfried/gottfried9.html. Retrieved 2006-09-30.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Calvert, John ''Islamism: a documentary and reference'' Greenwood Publishing Group, 2008, 0313338566&lt;/ref&gt;

Writers such as [[Camille Paglia]], [[Christina Hoff Sommers]], [[Jean Bethke Elshtain]], [[Elizabeth Fox-Genovese]] and [[Daphne Patai]] oppose some forms of feminism, though they identify as feminists. They argue, for example, that feminism  often promotes misandry and the elevation of women's interests above men's, and criticize radical feminist positions as harmful to both men and women.&lt;ref name="Hoff_Sommers"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Sommers, Christina Hoff |authorlink=Christina Hoff Sommers |title=Who Stole Feminism?: How Women Have Betrayed Women |year=1995 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0-684-80156-6 |page=320}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Daphne Patai]] and Noretta Koertge argue that the term "anti-feminist" is used to silence academic debate about feminism.&lt;ref name=Patai_Koertge&gt;{{cite book |last=Patai |first=Daphne |coauthors=Noretta Koertge |title=Professing Feminism: Education and Indoctrination in Women's Studies |isbn=0739104551 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Feminism}}
* [[Index of feminism articles]]
* [[American Association of University Women]]
* [[European Women's Lobby]]
* [[Feminist art movement]]
* [[Feminist Majority Foundation]]
* [[Feminist therapy]]
* [[Gender equality]]
* [[History of feminism]]
* [[Ms. (magazine)]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
* {{Cite book |author=DuBois, Ellen Carol |title=Harriot Stanton Blatch and the Winning of Woman Suffrage |year=1997 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven, Conn. |isbn=978-0-300-06562-0}}
* Flexner, Eleanor, ''Century of Struggle: The Woman's Rights Movement in the United States'' (The Belknap Press, 1996 (ISBN 9780674106539)).
*[[Robin Truth Goodman|Goodman, Robin Truth]]. ''Feminist Theory in Pursuit of the Public: Women and the "Re-Privatization" of Labor''. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2010.
*{{cite journal|date=March 2004|title='In labor alone is happiness': women's work, social work, and feminist reform endeavors in Wilhelmine Germany—a transatlantic perspective|journal=Journal of Women's History|volume=16|issue=1|publisher=Indiana University Press|issn=1042-7961}}
* Mathur, Piyush, The Archigenderic Territories: ''Mansfield Park'' and ''A Handful of Dust,'' in ''Women's Writing'' 5:1,71–81 ([http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09699089800200034]).
* Stansell, Christine, ''The Feminist Promise: 1792 to the Present'' (2010 (ISBN 978-0-679-64314-2528)), pages.
* {{Cite book |author=Stevens, Doris |authorlink= |coauthors=O'Hare, Carol |title=Jailed for Freedom: American Women Win the Vote |year=1995 |publisher=NewSage Press |location=Troutdale, OR |isbn=978-0-939165-25-2 }}
* {{Cite book |author=Wheeler, Marjorie W. |title=One Woman, One Vote: Rediscovering the Woman Suffrage Movement |year=1995 |publisher=NewSage Press |location=Troutdale, OR |isbn=978-0-939165-26-0 }}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary|feminism|feminist}}
{{wikiversity|Women's Studies}}
{{commons|Feminism}}
* {{In Our Time|Feminism|p00545b0|Feminism}}
* [http://www.britishpathe.com/record.php?id=78523 ''Early Video on the Emancipation of Women''], documentary filmed ca. 1930, which includes footage from the 1890s
* [http://www.feminist.com/resources/links/ Feminist.com directory]
* [http://www.womensforumaustralia.org/ Women's Forum Australia]
* [http://scriptorium.lib.duke.edu/wlm/ Documents from the Women's Liberation Movement], Special Collections Library, Duke University
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-topics/ ''Topics in Feminism''], at the [[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]
* {{Cite Collier's|Feminism|year=1921}}

{{Feminism}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Political ideologies}}

[[Category:Feminism| ]]
[[Category:Civil rights and liberties]]
[[Category:Sociological paradigms]]
[[Category:Sociological theories]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Gender and education]]

{{Link GA|sv}}
{{Link GA|lv}}

[[af:Feminisme]]
[[ar:أنثوية]]
[[an:Feminismo]]
[[ast:Feminismu]]
[[az:Feminizm]]
[[bn:নারীবাদ]]
[[be:Фемінізм]]
[[be-x-old:Фэмінізм]]
[[bs:Feminizam]]
[[br:Gwregelouriezh]]
[[bg:Феминизъм]]
[[ca:Feminisme]]
[[cs:Feminismus]]
[[cy:Ffeministiaeth]]
[[da:Feminisme]]
[[de:Feminismus]]
[[et:Feminism]]
[[el:Φεμινισμός]]
[[es:Feminismo]]
[[eo:Feminismo]]
[[eu:Feminismo]]
[[fa:فمینیسم]]
[[hif:Feminism]]
[[fr:Féminisme]]
[[fy:Feminisme]]
[[gd:Boireann-dhligheachas]]
[[gl:Feminismo]]
[[ko:여성주의]]
[[hy:Ֆեմինիզմ]]
[[hi:नारीवाद]]
[[hr:Feminizam]]
[[id:Feminisme]]
[[ia:Feminismo]]
[[ie:Feminisme]]
[[is:Femínismi]]
[[it:Femminismo]]
[[he:פמיניזם]]
[[ka:ფემინიზმი]]
[[kk:Феминизм]]
[[ku:Femînîzm]]
[[la:Feminismus]]
[[lv:Feminisms]]
[[lt:Feminizmas]]
[[hu:Feminizmus]]
[[mk:Феминизам]]
[[ml:സ്ത്രീവാദം]]
[[mr:स्त्रीवाद]]
[[ms:Feminisme]]
[[mwl:Femenismo]]
[[nl:Feminisme]]
[[new:मिसावाद]]
[[ja:フェミニズム]]
[[no:Feminisme]]
[[nn:Feminisme]]
[[nov:Feminisme]]
[[oc:Feminisme]]
[[pnb:فیمینزم]]
[[pl:Feminizm]]
[[pt:Feminismo]]
[[ro:Feminism]]
[[rue:Фемінізм]]
[[ru:Феминизм]]
[[sah:Феминизм]]
[[scn:Fimminismu]]
[[simple:Feminism]]
[[sk:Feminizmus (hnutie)]]
[[sl:Feminizem]]
[[sr:Феминизам]]
[[sh:Feminizam]]
[[fi:Feminismi]]
[[sv:Feminism]]
[[tl:Peminismo]]
[[ta:பெண்ணியம்]]
[[te:స్త్రీవాదం]]
[[th:สตรีนิยม]]
[[tr:Feminizm]]
[[uk:Фемінізм]]
[[ug:فېمىنىزم]]
[[vi:Nữ quyền]]
[[fiu-vro:Feminism]]
[[wa:Feminisse]]
[[war:Peminismo]]
[[wuu:女权主义]]
[[yi:פעמיניזם]]
[[bat-smg:Femėnėzmos]]
[[zh:女權主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>