<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20040930160202|6847684" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25998" pageid="25998" ns="0" title="Radical feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-25T08:04:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Radical [[feminism]]''' views women's oppression as a fundamental element in human society and seeks to challenge that standard by broadly rejecting standard gender roles. The traditional Radical feminist standpoint may be expressed as viewing ''the division in all societies as that between men and women'' and stating ''that men are the oppressors of women''[http://pers-www.wlv.ac.uk/~le1810/femin.htm]. These concepts were first developed in the late sixties as a significant part of [[Second-wave feminism]]. 

Many radical feminists believe that society forces an oppressive [[patriarchy]] on women (some [[masculism|masculists]] claim that patriarchy, amongst other things, oppresses men also) and seek to abolish this patriarchal influence, with some strands advocating replacing it with its opposite. Because of this, some observers believe that radical feminism focuses on the gender oppression of patriarchy as the first and foremost fundamental oppression that women face. However, critiques of the above view have resulted in a different perspective on radical feminism held by some which acknowledges the  simultaneity or intersectionality of different types of oppression which may include, but are not limited to the following: [[gender identity|gender]], [[race]], [[social class|class]], [[sexuality]], [[ability]], whilst still affirming the recognition of [[patriarchy]]. 

Some strains of radical feminism have been compared to [[Marxism]] in that they describe a "great struggle of history" between two opposed polar forces; the struggle between the [[proletariat]] and [[bourgeoisie]] [[social class|classes]] is said to be similar to that of "women" and "men". 



''See also'':  [[bell hooks]], [[Mary Daly]], [[Andrea Dworkin]], [[Womyn]], [[List of feminism topics]]

==External links==
*[http://www.capital.demon.co.uk/LA/pamphlets/rad-fem.htm Liberal feminist view on radical feminism]
*[http://pers-www.wlv.ac.uk/~le1810/femin.htm Academic definition]
*[http://pers-www.wlv.ac.uk/~le1810/ws.htm Women's Studies]

*[http://www.nostatusquo.com NoStatusQuo.com Radical feminist commentary]

Women Against Pornography

Men Against Pornography [http://the-vu.com/men_against_pornography.htm Article about Men Against Pornography]

*[http://www.catwinternational.org International Coalition Against Trafficking in Women]

*[http://www.sigi.org Sisterhood Is Global Institute]

Feminist International Network of Resistance to Reproductive and Genetic Engineering (FINRRAGE) [http://www.geocities.com/Wellesley/Garden/3971/journals.html FINRRAGE journal listed]

*[http://web2.airmail.net/ktrig246/out_of_cave/martian.html This link names the groups above as radical]

[[Category:Feminism]]

[[sv:Radikalfeminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>