<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131120224119|582592214" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="32492747" pageid="32492747" ns="0" title="Cyberbullying"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-20T22:42:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect-distinguish|Cyberbully|Cyberbully (film)}}
:''For the Wikipedia guidance essay, see [[Wikipedia:Cyberbullying]].''
{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2012}}
{{pp-move-indef}}{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{Original research|date=April 2011}}{{Synthesis|date=April 2011}}

[[File:Targeted Individuals.png|thumb|[[Awareness ribbon|Indigo awareness ribbon]]]]
'''Cyberbullying''' is the use of [[Information Technology]] to harm or harass other people in a deliberate, repeated, and hostile manner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=What is Cyberbullying|url=http://www.stopbullying.gov/cyberbullying/what-is-it/| publisher=U.S. Department of Health &amp; Human Services}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to U.S. Legal Definitions, ''Cyber-bullying could be limited to posting rumors or gossips about a person in the internet bringing about hatred in other’s minds; or it may go to the extent of personally identifying victims and publishing materials severely defaming and humiliating them.''&lt;ref&gt;{{ccite web\title=Cyber Bullying Law and Legal Definition|url=http://definitions.uslegal.com/c/cyber-bullying/|publisher=U.S. Legal Definitions}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the increase in use of these technologies Cyberbullying has become increasingly common, especially among teenagers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cyberbullying: its nature and impact in secondary school pupils|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1469-7610.2007.01846.x/full|publisher=The Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry}}&lt;/ref&gt; Awareness has also risen, due in part to high profile cases like the [[Suicide of Tyler Clementi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Legal Debate Swirls Over Charges in a Student's Suicide|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/02/nyregion/02suicide.html?_r=0|publisher=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Definition ==
===Legal definition===
Cyberbullying is defined in legal glossaries as 
* actions that use information and communication technologies to support deliberate, repeated, and hostile behavior by an individual or group, that is intended to harm another or others.
* use of communication technologies for the intention of harming another person
* use of internet service and mobile technologies such as web pages and discussion groups as well as instant messaging or [[SMS]] text messaging  with the intention of harming another person.

Examples of what constitutes cyberbullying include communications that seek to [[intimidate]], control, [[Psychological manipulation|manipulate]], put down, [[False accusation|falsely discredit]], or [[humiliate]] the recipient. The actions are deliberate, repeated, and hostile behavior intended to harm another. Cyberbullying has been defined by [[The National Crime Prevention Council]]: “When the Internet, cell phones or other devices are used to send or post text or images intended to hurt or embarrass another person."&lt;ref name="definitions.uslegal.com"&gt;[http://definitions.uslegal.com/c/cyber-bullying/ Cyberbullying - Law and Legal Definitions] US Legal&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://legaldefinitions.co/cyber-bullying.html Cyber-bullying Definition] Legal Definitions&lt;/ref&gt;

A cyberbully may be a person whom the target knows or an online stranger. A cyberbully may be anonymous and may solicit involvement of other people online who do not even know the target. This is known as a 'digital pile-on.'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cyberslammed|url=http://www.cyberslammed.com/where-to-start.html|accessdate=22 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cyberbullying vs. Cyberstalking===
{{further|Cyberstalking}}
The practice of cyberbullying is not limited to children and, while the behavior is identified by the same definition when practiced by adults, the distinction in age groups sometimes refers to the abuse as [[cyberstalking]] or [[cyberharassment]] when perpetrated by adults toward adults.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Cyber stalking|url=http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2011-06-06/personal-tech/29722217_1_cyber-stalking-stalkers-chat|newspaper=THE TIMES OF INDIA|date=Jun 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Common tactics used by cyberstalkers are performed in public forums, social media or online information sites and are intended to threaten a victim's earnings, employment, reputation, or safety. Behaviors may include encouraging others to harass the victim and trying to affect a victim's online participation. Many cyberstalkers try to damage the reputation of their victim and turn other people against them.

Cyberstalking may include false accusations, monitoring, making threats, identity theft, damage to data or equipment, the solicitation of minors for sex, or gathering information in order to harass.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Stalking and Cyber Stalking|url=http://www.uh.edu/wrc/StalkingandCyber-Stalking.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A repeated pattern of such actions and [[harassment]] against a target by an adult constitutes cyberstalking. Cyberstalking often features linked patterns of online and offline behavior. There are consequences of law in offline stalking and online stalking, and cyber-stalkers can be put in jail.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/headlines/2012/01/ucf-cyber-stalkers-sentence-not-harsh-enough-victim-says/ |title=UCF Cyber Stalker’s Sentence Not Harsh Enough, Victim Says|publisher=ABC News|date=January 23, 2012|accessdate=2012-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cyberstalking is a form of cyberbullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=DIFFERENT FORMS OF  CYBER BULLYING|url=http://www.headspace.org.au/media/41514/ed%202.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comparison to Traditional Bullying===
Certain characteristics inherent in online technologies increase the likelihood that they will be exploited for deviant purposes.&lt;ref name="patchin"/&gt; Unlike physical bullying, electronic bullies can remain virtually anonymous using temporary email accounts, pseudonyms in chat rooms, instant messaging programs, cell-phone text messaging, and other Internet venues to mask their identity; this perhaps frees them from normative and social constraints on their behavior.

Additionally, electronic forums often lack supervision. While chat hosts regularly observe the dialog in some chat rooms in an effort to police conversations and evict offensive individuals, personal messages sent between users (such as electronic mail or text messages) are viewable only by the sender and the recipient, thereby outside the regulatory reach of such authorities. In addition, when teenagers know more about computers and cellular phones than their parents or guardians, they are therefore able to operate the technologies without concern that a parent will discover their experience with bullying (whether as a victim or offender).

Another factor is the inseparability of a cellular phone from its owner, making that person a perpetual target for [[victimization]]. Users often need to keep their phone turned on for legitimate purposes, which provides the opportunity for those with malicious intentions to engage in persistent unwelcome behavior such as harassing telephone calls or threatening and insulting statements via the cellular phone’s text messaging capabilities. Cyberbullying thus penetrates the walls of a home, traditionally a place where victims could seek refuge from other forms of bullying. Compounding this infiltration into the home life of the cyberbully victim is the unique way in which the internet can "create simultaneous sensations of exposure (the whole world is watching) and alienation (no one understands)."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Puar|first=Jasbir|title=Ecologies of Sex, Sensation, and Slow Death|url=http://www.socialtextjournal.org/periscope/2010/11/ecologies-of-sex-sensation-and-slow-death.php|work=Periscope|publisher=Social Text|accessdate=December 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; For youth who experience shame or self-hatred, this effect is dangerous because it can lead to extreme self isolation.

One possible advantage for victims of cyberbullying over traditional bullying is that they may sometimes be able to avoid it simply by avoiding the site/chat room in question. Email addresses and phone numbers can be changed; in addition, most e-mail accounts now offer services that will automatically filter out messages from certain senders before they even reach the inbox, and phones offer similar caller ID functions.

However, this does not protect against all forms of cyberbullying; publishing of defamatory material about a person on the internet is extremely difficult to prevent and once it is posted, many people or archiving services can potentially download and copy it, at which point it is almost impossible to remove from the Internet. Some perpetrators may post victims' photos, or victims' edited photos like defaming captions or pasting victims' faces on nude bodies. Examples of famous forums for disclosing personal data or photos to "punish" the "enemies" include the [[Hong Kong Golden Forum]], [[Live Journal]], and more recently [[JuicyCampus]]. Despite policies that describe cyberbullying as a violation of the terms of service, many social networking Web sites have been used to that end.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.informationweek.com/news/internet/showArticle.jhtml;jsessionid=4X0TWRLMFJITYQSNDLRSKHSCJUNN2JVN?articleID=200001167&amp;cid=tab_art_sec#community Cyberbullying Common, More So At Facebook And MySpace] by Thomas Claburn, Information week; June 27, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Methods Used==
Manuals to educate the public, teachers and parents summarize, "Cyberbullying is being cruel to others by sending or posting harmful material using a cell phone or the internet." Research, legislation and education in the field are ongoing. Basic definitions and guidelines to help recognize and cope with what is regarded as abuse of electronic communications have been identified. 
* Cyberbullying involves repeated behavior with intent to harm and repeated nature
* Cyberbullying is perpetrated through [[Harassment]], [[Cyberstalking]], Denigration (sending or posting cruel rumors and falsehoods to damage reputation and friendships), [[Impersonation]], Exclusion (intentionally and cruelly excluding someone from an online group)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csriu.org/cyberbully/docs/cbcteducator.pdf ''An Educators Guide to Cyberbullying''] Brown Senate.gov&lt;/ref&gt;

Cyberbullying can be as simple as continuing to send e-mails or text messages harassing someone who has said they want no further contact with the sender.  It may also include public actions such as repeated [[threat]]s, sexual remarks, pejorative labels (i.e., [[hate speech]]) or defamatory false accusations), ganging up on a victim by making the person the subject of ridicule in online forums, hacking into or vandalizing sites about a person, and posting false statements as fact aimed a discrediting or humiliating a targeted person.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Defining a Cyberbully|url=http://www.nsf.gov/discoveries/disc_summ.jsp?cntn_id=121847|publisher=The National Science Foundation|accessdate=November 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Cyberbullying could be limited to posting rumors about a person on the internet with the intention of bringing about hatred in others' minds or convincing others to dislike or participate in online denigration of a target. It may go to the extent of personally identifying victims of crime and publishing materials severely defaming or humiliating them.&lt;ref name="definitions.uslegal.com"/&gt;  

Cyberbullies may disclose victims' personal data (e.g. real name, home address, or workplace/schools) at websites or forums or may use [[impersonation]], creating fake accounts, comments or sites posing as their target for the purpose of publishing material in their name that defames, discredits or ridicules them. This can leave the cyberbully anonymous which can make it difficult for the offender to be caught or punished for their behavior.  Though, not all cyberbullies use anonymity. Text or instant messages and emails between friends can also be cyberbullying if what is said or displayed is hurtful to the participants.   

Some cyberbullies may also send threatening and harassing emails, instant messages or texts to the victims. Others post rumors or gossip and instigate others to dislike and gang up on the target.

[[File:Email final.jpg|thumb|Cyberbullying by [[email]] from a fictional friend@hotmail.com]]

The recent use of mobile applications and rise of smartphones have yielded to a more accessible form of cyberbullying. It is expected that cyberbullying via these platforms will be associated with bullying via mobile phones to a greater extent than exclusively through other more stationary internet platforms. In addition, the combination of cameras and Internet access and the instant availability of these modern smartphone technologies yield themselves to specific types of cyberbullying not found in other platforms. It is likely that those cyberbullied via mobile devices will experience a wider range of cyberbullying types than those exclusively bullied elsewhere. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Görzig|first=Anke|coauthors=Lara A. Frumkin|title=Cyberbullying experiences on-the-go: When social media can become distressing|journal=Cyberpsychology: Journal of Psychosocial Research on Cyberspace|year=2013|url=http://www.cyberpsychology.eu/view.php?cisloclanku=2013022801&amp;article=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In Gaming===
[[Sexual harassment]] as a form of Cyberbullying is common in [[Video game culture]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Effects of exposure to sex-stereotyped video game characters on tolerance of sexual harassment |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022103108001005|publisher=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study by the Journal of Experimental Social Psychology suggests that this harassment is due in part to the portrayal of women in video games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Effects of exposure to sex-stereotyped video game characters on tolerance of sexual harassment |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022103108001005|publisher=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology}}&lt;/ref&gt; This harassment generally involves slurs directed towards women, sex role stereotyping, and overaggressive language.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Gender Stereotypes, Aggression, and Computer Games: An Online Survey of Women|url=http://online.liebertpub.com/doi/pdf/10.1089/cpb.2004.7.714|publisher=CyberPsychology &amp; Behavior}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In one case, in which [[Capcom]] sponsored an internet streamed reality show pitting fighting game experts against each other for a prize of $25,000, one female gamer forfeited a match due to intense harassment.&lt;ref&gt;{{web|title=Sexual harassment as ethical imperative: how Capcom’s fighting game reality show turned ugly|url=http://penny-arcade.com/report/article/sexual-harassment-as-ethical-imperative-the-ugly-side-of-fighting-games|publisher=The Penny Arcade Report}}&lt;/ref&gt; The coach of the opposing team, Aris Bakhtanians, stated, "The sexual harassment is part of the culture. If you remove that from the fighting game community, it’s not the fighting game community… it doesn’t make sense to have that attitude. These things have been established for years."&lt;ref&gt;{{web|title=Sexual harassment as ethical imperative: how Capcom’s fighting game reality show turned ugly|url=http://penny-arcade.com/report/article/sexual-harassment-as-ethical-imperative-the-ugly-side-of-fighting-games|publisher=The Penny Arcade Report}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A study from National Sun Yat-sen University observed that children who enjoyed violent video games were far more likely to both experience and perpetrate cyberbullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Paths to Bullying in Online Gaming: The Effects of Gender, Preference for Playing Violent Games, Hostility, and Aggressive Behavior on Bullying|url=http://web.ebscohost.com/ehost/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?sid=9d53046e-ce89-455f-9bfd-67df5a285840%40sessionmgr111&amp;vid=2&amp;hid=123|publisher=National Sun Yat-sen University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Law Enforcement: Cyberbullying, Cyberstalking and Electronic Harassment==
A majority of states have laws that explicitly include electronic forms of communication within stalking or harassment laws.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncsl.org/issues-research/educ/cyberbullying.aspx  Cyberstalking, cyberharassment and cyberbullying] NCSL National Conference of State Legislatures&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://apps.leg.wa.gov/rcw/default.aspx?cite=9.61.260 Cyberstalking] Washington State Legislature&lt;/ref&gt;

Most law enforcement agencies have cyber-crime units and often Internet stalking is treated with more seriousness than reports of physical stalking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=What Is Cyberstalking?|url=http://www.cla.purdue.edu/people/engl/blackmon/101cresources/cyberstalking.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Help and resources can be searched by State or area.

===Schools===
The safety of schools is increasingly becoming a focus of state legislative action. There was an increase in cyberbullying enacted legislation between 2006-2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncsl.org/issues-research/educ/cyberbullying.aspx Cyberbullying Enacted Legislation: 2006-2010] Legislation by State, NCSL&lt;/ref&gt; Initiatives and curriclulum requirements also exist in the UK (the Ofsted eSafety guidance) and Australia (Overarching Learning Outcome 13).
In 2012, a group of teens in New Haven, Connecticut developed an app to help fight bullying. Called "Back Off Bully" (BOB), the web app is an anonymous resource for computer, smart phone or iPad. When someone witnesses or is the victim of bullying, they can immediately report the incident. The app asks questions about time, location and how the bullying is happening. As well as providing positive action and empowerment over an incident, the reported information helps by going to a data base where administrators study it. Common threads are spotted so others can intervene and break the bully's pattern.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.whdh.com/news/articles/local/south/12007792580056/ct-teens-develop-bullying-app-to-protect-peers/ CT teens develop bullying app to protect peers] 7 News; June 2012&lt;/ref&gt; BOB, the brainchild of fourteen teens in a  design class, is being considered as standard operating procedure at schools across the state.

===Protection for Victims of Any Age===
There are laws that only address online harassment of children or focus on child predators as well as laws that protect adult cyberstalking victims, or victims of any age. Currently, there are 45 cyberstalking (and related) laws on the books.  

While some sites specialize in laws that protect victims age 18 and under, Working to Halt Online Abuse is a help resource containing a list of current and pending cyberstalking-related United States federal and state laws.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haltabuse.org/resources/laws/index.shtml  Current and pending cyberstalking-related United States federal and state laws] WHOA&lt;/ref&gt; It also lists those states that do not have laws yet and related laws from other countries. The Global Cyber Law Database (GCLD) aims to become the most comprehensive and authoritative source of cyber laws for all countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cyberlawdb.com/main/ The Global Cyber Law Database] GCLD&lt;/ref&gt;

===Children and Adolescents===
Kids report being mean to each other online beginning as young as 2nd grade. According to research, boys initiate mean online activity earlier than girls do. However, by middle school, girls are more likely to engage in cyberbullying than boys.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfaxtimes.com/cms/story.php?id=2078 Cyberbullying defies traditional stereotype: Girls are more likely than boys to engage in this new trend, research suggests] September 1, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Whether the bully is male or female, his or her purpose is to intentionally embarrass others, harass, intimidate, or make threats online to one another. This bullying occurs via email, text messaging, posts to blogs, and web sites.

The National Crime Prevention Association lists tactics often used by teen cyberbullies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncpc.org/cyberbullying Cyberbullying among Teens] The National Crime Prevention Association&lt;/ref&gt;
* Pretend they are other people online to trick others
* Spread lies and rumors about victims
* Trick people into revealing personal information
* Send or forward mean text messages
* Post pictures of victims without their consent

Studies in the psychosocial effects of cyberspace have begun to monitor the impacts cyberbullying may have on the victims, and the consequences it may lead to. Consequences of cyberbullying are multi-faceted, and affect online and offline behavior.  Research on adolescents reported that changes in the victims' behavior as a result of cyberbullying could be positive. Victims "created a cognitive pattern of bullies, which consequently helped them to recognize aggressive people."&lt;ref name="cyberpsychology.eu"&gt;[http://www.cyberpsychology.eu/view.php?cisloclanku=2011121901&amp;article=4 Cyberbullying in Adolescent Victims: Perception and Coping] Journal of Psychosocial Research on Cyberspace&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Journal of Psychosocial Research on Cyberspace abstract reports critical impacts in almost all of the respondents’, taking the form of lower self-esteem, loneliness, disillusionment, and distrust of people. The more extreme impacts were self-harm. Children have killed each other and committed suicide after having been involved in a cyberbullying incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stopcyberbullying.org/what_is_cyberbullying_exactly.html |title=Stop Cyberbullying |publisher=Stop Cyberbullying |date=2005-06-27 |accessdate=2013-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The most current research in the field defines cyberbullying as "an aggressive, intentional act or behaviour that is carried out by a group or an individual repeatedly and over time against a victim who cannot easily defend him or herself" (Smith &amp; Slonje, 2007, p.&amp;nbsp;249).&lt;ref name="cyberpsychology.eu"/&gt; Though the use of sexual remarks and threats are sometimes present in cyberbullying, it is not the same as sexual harassment, typically occurs among peers, and does not necessarily involve [[sexual predators]].

Some cases of digital [[self-harm]] have been reported, where an individual engages in cyberbullying against themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Topping|first=Alexandra|title=Cyberbullying on social networks spawning form of self-harm|url=http://www.theguardian.com/society/2013/aug/06/cyberbullying-social-networks-self-harm|publisher=Guardian News and Media Limited|accessdate=Tuesday 6 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Englander|first=Elizabeth|title=Digital Self-Harm: Frequency, Type, Motivations, and Outcomes|journal=MARC Research Reports|year=2012|month=June|volume=5|url=http://vc.bridgew.edu/marc_reports/5|publisher=Massachusetts Agression Reduction Center, Bridgewater State University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Adults===
Stalking online has criminal consequences just as physical stalking. A target's understanding of why cyberstalking is happening is helpful to remedy and take protective action to restore remedy. Cyberstalking is an extension of physical stalking.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/criminal_mind/psychology/cyberstalking/1.html Cyberstalking - Introduction] Crime Library, Criminal Minds and Methods&lt;/ref&gt; Among factors that motivate stalkers are: [[envy]], pathological obsession (professional or sexual), unemployment or failure with own job or life; intention to intimidate and cause others to feel inferior; the stalker is [[delusional]] and believes he/she "knows" the target; the stalker wants to instill fear in a person to justify his/her status; belief they can get away with it (anonymity).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/criminal_mind/psychology/cyberstalking/3.html Cyber-Stalking: Obsessional Pursuit and the Digital Criminal], by Wayne Petherick - Stalking Typologies and Pathologies&lt;/ref&gt; UK National Workplace Bullying Advice Line theorizes that bullies harass victims in order to make up for inadequacies in their own lives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hcib.ch/topic/bullying.pdf UK National Workplace Bullying Advice Line] Bullying&lt;/ref&gt; 

The US federal cyberstalking law is designed to prosecute people for using electronic means to repeatedly harass or threaten someone online. There are resources dedicated to assisting adult victims deal with cyberbullies legally and effectively. One of the steps recommended is to record everything and contact police.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wiredsafety.org/subjects/cyberbullying.php Cyberbullying] Stalking and Harassment&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://voices.yahoo.com/what-cyberbullies-adults-11081994.html What to Do About Cyberbullies: For Adults], by Rena Sherwood; YAHOO Contributor network&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research==

===Australia===
The nation-wide Australian Covert Bullying Prevalence Survey (Cross et al., 2009)&lt;ref name="ACBPS"&gt;[http://www.deewr.gov.au/Schooling/NationalSafeSchools/Pages/research.aspx Cross, D., Shaw, T., Hearn, L., Epstein, M., Monks, H., Lester, L., &amp; Thomas, L. 2009. Australian Covert Bullying Prevalence Study (ACBPS). Child Health Promotion Research Centre, Edith Cowan University, Perth]. Deewr.gov.au. Retrieved on July 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; assessed cyber-bullying experiences among 7,418 students. Rates of cyber-bullying increased with age, with 4.9% of students in Year 4 reporting cyberbullying compared to 7.9% in year nine. Cross et al., (2009) reported that rates of bullying and harassing others were lower, but also increased with age. Only 1.2% of Year 4 students reported cyber-bullying others compared to 5.6% of Year 9 students.

===Canada===
Similarly, a Canadian study found:
* 23% of middle-schoolers surveyed had been bullied by e-mail
* 35% in chat rooms
* 41% by text messages on their cell phones
* Fully 41% did not know the identity of the perpetrators.

===European Union===
Reporting on the results from a meta analysis from European Union countries, Hasebrink et al. (2009)&lt;ref name="Hasebrink"&gt;Hasebrink, U., Livingstone, S., Haddon, L. and Ólafsson, K.(2009) Comparing children’s online opportunities and risks across Europe: Cross-national comparisons for EU Kids Online. LSE, London: EU Kids Online (Deliverable D3.2, 2nd edition), ISBN 978-0-85328-406-2 [http://www.lse.ac.uk/collections/EUKidsOnline/Reports/D3.2,secondedition.pdf lse.ac.uk]&lt;/ref&gt; estimated (via median results) that approximately 18% of European young people had been "bullied/harassed/stalked" via the internet and mobile phones. Cyber-harassment rates for young people across the EU member states ranged from 10% to 52%.

===Finland===
In addition to the current research, Sourander et al. (2010) conducted a population-based cross-sectional study that took place in Finland. The authors of this study took the self-reports of 2215 Finish adolescents between the ages of 13 to 16 years old about cyberbullying and cybervictimization during the past 6 months. It was found that, amongst the total sample, 4.8% were cybervictims only, 7.4% were cyberbullies only, and 5.4% were cyberbully-victims. Cybervictim-only status was associated with a variety of factors, including emotional and peer problems, sleeping difficulties, and feeling unsafe in school. Cyberbully-only status was associated with factors such as hyperactivity and low prosocial behavior, as well as conduct problems. Cyberbully-victim status was associated with all of the risk factors that were associated with both cybervictim-only status and cyberbully-only status. The authors of this study were able to conclude that cyberbullying as well as cybervictimization is associated not only with psychiatric issues, but psychosomatic issues. Many adolescents in the study reported headaches or difficulty sleeping. The authors believe that their results indicate a greater need for new ideas on how to prevent cyberbullying and what to do when it occurs. It is clearly a world-wide problem that needs to be taken seriously.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Sourander, A., Klomek, A.B., Ikonen, M., Lindroos, J., Luntamo, T., Koskeiainen, M., … 
Helenius, H.|title=Psychosocial risk factors associated with cyberbullying among adolescents: A population-based study.|year=2010|work=Archives of General Psychiatry|volume=67|number=7|pages=720–728|url=http://archpsyc.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/67/7/720}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===

====2000====
A survey by the Crimes Against Children Research Center at the [[University of New Hampshire]] in 2000 found that 6% of the young people in the survey had experienced some form of harassment including threats and negative rumours and 2% had suffered distressing harassment.&lt;ref name=ccrc&gt;Finkelhor, D., Mitchell, K.J., &amp; Wolak, J. (2000). Online victimization: A report on the nation’s youth. Alexandria, VA: National Center for Missing and Exploited Children.&lt;/ref&gt;

====2004====
In September 2006, [[ABC News]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com ABCnews.co.com]. Abcnews.go.com. Retrieved on July 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; reported on a 2004 survey of 1,500 students between grades 4–8 which found:
* 42% of kids have been bullied while online. One in four have had it happen more than once.
* 35% of kids have been threatened online. Nearly one in five had had it happen more than once.
* 21% of kids have received mean or threatening e-mails or other messages.
* 58% of kids admit someone has said mean or hurtful things to them online. More than four out of ten say it has happened more than once.
* 58% have not told their parents or an adult about something mean or hurtful that happened to them online.

====2005====
The Youth Internet Safety Survey-2, conducted by the Crimes Against Children Research Center at the [[University of New Hampshire]] in 2005, found that 9% of the young people in the survey had experienced some form of harassment.&lt;ref name=ccrc&gt;Wolak, J., Mitchell, K.J., &amp; Finkelhor, D. (2006). Online Victimization of Youth: Five Years Later. Alexandria, VA: National Center for Missing and Exploited Children.&lt;/ref&gt; The survey was a nationally representative telephone survey of 1,500 youth 10–17 years old. One third reported feeling distressed by the incident, with distress being more likely for younger respondents and those who were the victims of aggressive harassment (including being telephoned, sent gifts, or visited at home by the harasser).&lt;ref name=ybarra&gt;Ybarra, M.L., Mitchell, K.J., Wolak, J., &amp; Finkelhor, D. Examining characteristics and associated distress related to Internet harassment: findings from the Second Youth Internet Safety Survey. Pediatrics. 2006 Oct;118(4):e1169-77&lt;/ref&gt; Compared to youth not harassed online, victims are more likely to have social problems. On the other hand, youth who harass others are more likely to have problems with rule breaking and aggression.&lt;ref name=ybarra2&gt;Ybarra, M.L. &amp; Mitchell, K.J. Prevalence and frequency of Internet harassment instigation: implications for adolescent health. J Adolesc Health. 2007 Aug;41(2):189-95&lt;/ref&gt; Significant overlap is seen&amp;nbsp;— youth who are harassed are significantly more likely to also harass others.

Hinduja and Patchin completed a study in the summer of 2005 of approximately 1,500 Internet-using adolescents and found that over one-third of youth reported being victimized online, and over 16% of respondents admitted to cyber-bullying others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Statistics on Bullying|url=http://district.seattleschools.org/modules/groups/homepagefiles/cms/1583136/File/Departmental%20Content/cyber%20bullying/lesson%202/cbms_2_tr1.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;  While most of the instances of cyber-bullying involved relatively minor behavior (41% were disrespected, 19% were called names), over 12% were physically threatened and about 5% were scared for their safety. Notably, fewer than 15% of victims told an adult about the incident.&lt;ref name="patchin1"/&gt;

Additional research by Hinduja and Patchin in 2007&lt;ref name=patchin2&gt;Hinduja, S. &amp; Patchin, J. W. (2007). [http://www.haworthpress.com/store/ArticleAbstract.asp?ID=101357 Offline Consequences of Online Victimization: School Violence and Delinquency.] Journal of School Violence, 6(3), 89–112.&lt;/ref&gt; found that youth who report being victims of cyber-bullying also experience stress or strain that is related to offline problem behaviors such as running away from home, cheating on a school test, skipping school, or using alcohol or marijuana. The authors acknowledge that both of these studies provide only preliminary information about the nature and consequences of online bullying, due to the methodological challenges associated with an online survey.

According to a 2005 survey by the [[Action for Children|National Children's Home]] charity and [[Tesco Mobile]]&lt;ref name=survey&gt;National Children's Home. (2005).[http://www.nch.org.uk/uploads/documents/Mobile_bullying_%20report.pdf Putting U in the picture. Mobile Bullying Survey 2005.](pdf)&lt;/ref&gt; of 770 youth between the ages of 11 and 19, 20% of respondents revealed that they had been bullied via electronic means. Almost three-quarters (73%) stated that they knew the bully, while 26% stated that the offender was a stranger. 10% of responders indicated that another person has taken a picture and/or video of them via a [[camera phone|cellular phone camera]], consequently making them feel uncomfortable, embarrassed, or threatened. Many youths are not comfortable telling an authority figure about their cyber-bullying [[victimization]] for fear their access to technology will be taken from them; while 24% and 14% told a parent or teacher respectively, 28% did not tell anyone while 41% told a friend.&lt;ref name=survey/&gt;

====2007====
In 2007, Debbie Heimowitz, a [[Stanford University]] master's student, created [[Adina's Deck]], a film based on Stanford accredited research. She worked in focus groups for ten weeks in three schools to learn about the problem of cyber-bullying in Northern California. The findings determined that over 60% of students had been cyber-bullied and were victims of cyber-bullying. The film is now being used in classrooms nationwide as it was designed around learning goals pertaining to problems that students had understanding the topic. The middle school of [[Suicide of Megan Meier|Megan Meier]] is reportedly using the film as a solution to the crisis in their town.

====2008====
In the summer of 2008, researchers Sameer Hinduja ([[Florida Atlantic University]]) and Justin Patchin ([[University of Wisconsin-Eau Claire]]) published a book on cyber-bullying that summarized the current state of cyber-bullying research. (''Bullying Beyond the Schoolyard: Preventing and Responding to Cyberbullying'').&lt;ref name=patchin3&gt;{{cite book | last= Hinduja | first = S. | coauthors = Patchin, J. W. | title = Bullying beyond the schoolyard: Preventing and responding to cyberbullying | publisher=Corwin Press | year = 2009| location = Thousand Oaks, CA | isbn = 1412966892}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their research documents that cyber-bullying instances have been increasing over the last several years. They also report findings from the most recent study of cyber-bullying among middle-school students. Using a random sample of approximately 2000 middle-school students from a large school district in the southern United States, about 10% of respondents had been cyber-bullied in the previous 30 days while over 17% reported being cyber-bullied at least once in their lifetime.&lt;ref name="patchin3"/&gt; While these rates are slightly lower than some of the findings from their previous research, Hinduja and Patchin point out that the earlier studies were predominantly conducted among older adolescents and Internet samples. That is, older youth use the Internet more frequently and are more likely to experience cyber-bullying than younger children.&lt;ref name="patchin"/&gt;&lt;ref name=patchin1&gt;Hinduja, S. &amp; Patchin, J. W. (2008). Cyberbullying: An Exploratory Analysis of Factors Related to Offending and Victimization. Deviant Behavior, 29(2), 129–156.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=patchin2&gt;Hinduja, S. &amp; Patchin, J. W. (2007). [http://www.haworthpress.com/store/ArticleAbstract.asp?ID=101357 Offline Consequences of Online Victimization: School Violence and Delinquency.] Journal of School Violence, 6(3), 89–112&lt;/ref&gt;

====2011====
[[File:Youth and Electronic aggression.gif|thumb|Distribution of cyberbullying venues used by young people in the US, according to the [[Centers for Disease Control]]]]
The National Crime Prevention Council reported in 2011 that cyber-bullying is a problem that affects almost half of all American teens.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncpc.org/cyberbullying NCPC.org]. NCPC.org. Retrieved on July 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legislation Against cyberbullying==
{{Main|Cyberstalking legislation}}

===United States===
Legislation geared at penalizing cyberbullying has been introduced in a number of U.S. states including New York, Missouri, Rhode Island and Maryland. At least forty five states passed laws against digital harassment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=PÉREZ-PEÑA|first=RICHARD|title=Christie Signs Tougher Law on Bullying in Schools|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/07/nyregion/07bully.html?_r=0|publisher=NewYork Times|accessdate=January 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Dardenne Prairie of Springfield, Missouri, passed a city ordinance making online harassment a misdemeanor. The city of St. Charles, Missouri has passed a similar ordinance. Missouri is among other states where lawmakers are pursuing state legislation, with a task forces expected to have “cyberbullying” laws drafted and implemented.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pantagraph.com/articles/2007/12/20/news/doc476b40995b5d1039247289.txt Bill targets adults who cyberbully] Pantagraph, by Kevin Mcdermott, December 20, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; In June, 2008, Rep. Linda Sanchez (D-Calif.) and Rep. Kenny Hulshof (R-Mo.) proposed a federal law that would criminalize acts of cyberbullying.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-10784_3-9962375-7.html A rallying cry against cyberbullying]. CNET News, by Stefanie Olsen, June 7, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Lawmakers are seeking to address cyberbullying with new legislation because there's currently no specific law on the books that deals with it. A fairly new federal cyberstalking law might address such acts, according to [[Parry Aftab]], but no one has been prosecuted under it yet. The proposed federal law would make it illegal to use electronic means to "coerce, intimidate, harass or cause other substantial emotional distress."

In August 2008, the California state legislature passed one of the first laws in the country to deal directly with cyberbullying. The legislation, [http://info.sen.ca.gov/pub/07-08/bill/asm/ab_0051-0100/ab_86_cfa_20080115_125502_asm_comm.html Assembly Bill 86 2008], gives school administrators the authority to discipline students for bullying others offline or online.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/teachers/learning.now/2008/08/ca_legislation_criminalizes_ca.html PBS Teachers]. Pbs.org. Retrieved on July 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; This law took effect, January 1, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/12/31/AR2008123103067.html|title=States Passing Laws to Combat Cyber-Bullying&amp;nbsp;— washingtonpost.com|work=The Washington Post |accessdate=January 2, 2009|last=Surdin|first=Ashley | date=January 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A recent ruling first seen in the UK determined that it is possible for an [[Internet Service Provider]] (ISP) to be liable for the content of sites which it hosts, setting a precedent that any ISP should treat a notice of complaint seriously and investigate it immediately.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.out-law.com/page-5624 International IT and e-commerce legal info]. Out-law.com. Retrieved on July 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{uscsub|18|875|c}} criminalizes the making of threats via Internet.

===Research on Preventative Legislation===

Researchers suggest that programs be put in place for prevention of cyberbullying. These programs would be incorporated into school curricula and would include online safety and instruction on how to use the Internet properly.&lt;ref name= von&gt;Von Marees, N., &amp; Petermann, F. (2012). Cyberbullying: An increasing challenge for schools. School Psychology International, 33(5), 476.&lt;/ref&gt; This could teach the victim proper methods of potentially avoiding the cyberbully, such as blocking messages or increasing the security on their computer.&lt;ref name= von/&gt;

Within this suggested school prevention model, even in a perfect world, not one crime can be stopped fully. That is why it is suggested that within this prevention method, effective coping strategies should be introduced and adopted. As with any crime, people learn to cope with what has happened, and the same goes for cyberbullying. People can adopt coping strategies to combat future cyberbullying events. An example of a coping strategy would be a social support group composed of various victims of cyberbullying.&lt;ref name= von/&gt; That could come together and share experiences, with a formal speaker leading the discussion. Something like a support group can allow students to share their stories, and allows that feeling of them being alone to be removed.

Teachers should be involved in all prevention educational models, as they are essentially the "police" of the classroom. Most cyberbullying often goes unreported as the victim feels nothing can be done to help in their current situation.&lt;ref name= von/&gt; However, if given the proper tools with preventative measures and more power in the classroom, teachers can be of assistance to the problem of cyber-bullying. If the parent, teacher, and victim can work together, a possible solution or remedy can be found.&lt;ref name= von/&gt;

There have been many legislative attempts to facilitate the control of bullying and cyberbullying. The problem is due to the fact that some existing legislation is incorrectly thought to be tied to bullying and cyberbullying (terms such as libel and slander). The problem is they do not directly apply to it nor define it as its own criminal behavior.&lt;ref&gt;Smyth, S. M. (2010). Cybercrime in canadian criminal law. (pp. 105-122). Toronto, ON: Carswell.&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-cyberbullying advocates even expressed concern about the broad scope of applicability of some of the bills attempted to be passed.&lt;ref name= walt&gt;Walther, B. (2012). Cyberbullying: Holding grownups liable for negligent entrustment. Houston Law Review, 49(2), 531-562.&lt;/ref&gt;
	
In the United States, attempts were made to pass legislation against cyberbullying. Few states attempted to pass broad sanctions in an effort to prohibit cyberbullying. Problem include how to define cyberbullying and cyberstalking, and if charges are pressed, whether it violates the bully's freedom of speech.&lt;ref name= walt/&gt; B. Walther has said that "Illinois is the only state to criminalize 'electronic communication(s) sent for the purpose of harassing another person' when the activity takes place outside a public school setting." Again this came under fire for infringement on freedom of speech.&lt;ref name= walt/&gt;

==Harmful Effects==
Research had demonstrated a number of serious consequences of cyberbullying victimization.&lt;ref name="patchin"/&gt;&lt;ref name="patchin1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="patchin2"/&gt;&lt;ref name=patchin3&gt;Hinduja, S. &amp; Patchin, J. W. (2009). ''Bullying beyond the schoolyard: Preventing and responding to cyberbullying''&lt;/ref&gt; For example, victims have lower self-esteem, increased suicidal ideation, and a variety of emotional responses, retaliating, being scared, frustrated, angry, and depressed.&lt;ref name="patchin3"/&gt;

One of the most damaging effects is that a victim begins to avoid friends and activities, often the very intention of the cyberbully.

Cyberbullying campaigns are sometimes so damaging that victims have committed suicide. There are at least four examples in the United States where cyberbullying has been linked to the suicide of a teenager.&lt;ref name="patchin3"/&gt; The [[suicide of Megan Meier]] is a recent example that led to the conviction of the adult perpetrator of the attacks.

According to Lucie Russell, director of campaigns, policy and participation at youth mental health charity Young Minds, young people who suffer from [[mental disorder]] are vulnerable to cyberbullying as they are sometimes unable to shrug it off:&lt;blockquote&gt;When someone says nasty things healthy people can filter that out, they're able to put a block between that and their self-esteem. But mentally unwell people don't have the strength and the self-esteem to do that, to separate it, and so it gets compiled with everything else. To them, it becomes the absolute truth – there's no filter, there's no block. That person will take that on, take it as fact.&lt;ref name=Guardian8813&gt;{{cite news|title=Cyberbullying websites should be boycotted, says Cameron: Prime minister calls for website operators to 'step up to the plate', following death of 14-year-old Hannah Smith    ,|url=http://www.theguardian.com/society/2013/aug/08/cyberbullying-websites-boycotted-david-cameron|accessdate=8 August 2013|newspaper=The Guardian|date=8 August 2013|author=Alexandra Topping|author2=Ellen Coyne and agencies}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Intimidation, Emotional Damage, Suicide===
According to the Cyberbullying Research Center, "there have been several high‐profile cases involving teenagers taking their own lives in part because of being harassed and mistreated over the Internet, a phenomenon we have termed cyberbullicide – suicide indirectly or directly influenced by experiences with online aggression."

Cyberbullying is an intense form of psychological abuse, whose victims are more than twice as likely to suffer from mental disorders compared to traditional bullying.&lt;ref name="cyberthreat"&gt;{{cite magazine | magazine=[[Ideas and Discoveries (magazine)|Ideas and Discoveries]] |title=Cyberthreat: How to protect yourself from online bullying | publisher=Ideas and Discoveries | year=2011 | pages=76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The reluctance youth have in telling an authority figure about instances of cyberbullying has led to fatal outcomes. At least three children between the ages of 12 and 13 have committed suicide due to depression brought on by cyberbullying, according to reports by USA Today and the Baltimore Examiner. These would include the [[suicide of Ryan Halligan]] and the [[suicide of Megan Meier]], the latter of which resulted in [[United States v. Lori Drew]].

More recently, teenage suicides tied to cyberbullying have become more prevalent. The latest victim of cyberbullying through the use of mobile applications was Rebecca Ann Sedwick, who committed suicide after being terrorized through mobile applications such as [[Ask.fm|Ask.fm]], [[Kik|Kik Messenger]] and [[Voxer]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Alvarez|first=Lizette|title=Girl’s Suicide Points to Rise in Apps Used by Cyberbullies|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/09/14/us/suicide-of-girl-after-bullying-raises-worries-on-web-sites.html?_r=0|publisher=The New York Times|accessdate=20 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adults and the Workplace==
Cyberbullying is not limited to personal attacks or children. Cyberharassment, referred to as cyberstalking when involving adults, takes place in the workplace or on company web sites, blogs or product reviews.

Cyberbullying can occur in product reviews along with other consumer-generated data are being more closely monitored and flagged for content that is deemed malicious and biased as these sites have become tools to cyberbully by way of malicious requests for deletion of articles, [[vandalism]], abuse of administrative positions, and ganging up on products to post "false" reviews and vote products down.

Cyberstalkers use posts, forums, journals and other online means to present a victim in a false and unflattering light. The question of liability for harassment and character assassination is particularly salient to legislative protection since the original authors of the offending material are, more often than not, not only anonymous, but untraceable. Nevertheless, abuse should be consistently brought to company staffers' attention.

===Recognition of Adult and Workplace Cyberbullying Tactics===
Common tactics used by cyberstalkers is to vandalize a search engine or encyclopedia, to threaten a victim's earnings, employment, reputation, or safety. Various companies provide cases of cyber-stalking (involving adults) follow the pattern of repeated actions against a target. While motives vary, whether romantic, a business conflict of interest, or personal dislike, the target is commonly someone whose life the stalker sees or senses elements lacking in his or her own life. Web-based products or services leveraged against cyberstalkers in the harassment or defamation of their victims.

The source of the defamation seems to come from four types of online information purveyors: Weblogs, industry forums or boards, and commercial Web sites. Studies reveal that while some motives are personal dislike, there is often direct economic motivation by the cyberstalker, including conflict of interest, and investigations reveal the responsible party is an affiliate or supplier of a competitor, or the competitor itself.

==Awareness==

===Campaigns===
'''Spain'''

There are multiple non-profit organizations that fight cyberbullying and cyberstalking. They advise victims, provide awareness campaigns, and report offenses to the police. These NGOs include the ''Protégeles'', ''PantallasAmigas'', ''[[Foundation Alia2]]'', the non-profit initiative ''Actúa Contra el Ciberacoso'', the National Communications Technology Institute (INTECO), the Agency of Internet quality, the ''Agencia Española de Protección de Datos'', the ''Oficina de Seguridad del Internauta'', the Spanish Internet users' Association, the Internauts' Association, and the Spanish Association of Mothers and Parents Internauts. The Government of [[Castile and León]] has also created a ''Plan de Prevención del Ciberacoso y Promoción de la Navegación Segura en Centro Escolares'', and the Government of the [[Canary Islands]] has created a portal on the phenomenon called ''Viveinternet''.

'''United States'''

In March 2007, the Advertising Council in the United States, in partnership with the National Crime Prevention Council, U.S. Department of Justice, and Crime Prevention Coalition of America, joined to announce the launch of a new [[public service advertising]] campaign designed to educate preteens and teens about how they can play a role in ending cyber-bullying.

A Pew Internet and American Life survey found that 33% of teens were subject to some sort of cyber-bullying.

January 20, 2008 – the [[Boy Scouts of America]]'s 2008 edition of ''[[Boy Scout Handbook|The Boy Scout Handbook]]'' addresses how to deal with online bullying. A new [[Ranks in the Boy Scouts of America#First Class|First Class]] rank requirements adds: "Describe the three things you should avoid doing related to use of the Internet. Describe a cyberbully and how you should respond to one."
&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.usscouts.org/advance/boyscout/changes/bsrank4-08.asp
|publisher=US Scout Service Project
|title=First Class Rank Requirements
|accessdate=August 5, 2008}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/news/localnews/stories/012009dnmetscoutbullies.24d01f1.html
|publisher=Dallas Morning News|title=Boy Scout Handbook adds advice for dealing with bullies|accessdate=August 5, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

January 31, 2008 – [[KTTV]] Fox 11 News based in Los Angeles put out a report about organized cyber-bullying on sites like [[Stickam]] by people who call themselves "[[Anonymous (group)|/b/rothas]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myfoxla.com/myfox/pages/ContentDetail?contentId=5647826|publisher=Fox Television Stations, Inc.|title=FOX 11 Investigates: Cyber Bullies|accessdate=February 5, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The site had put out report on July 26, 2007, about a subject that partly featured cyberbullying titled "hackers on steroids".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myfoxla.com/myfox/pages/ContentDetail?contentId=3894628|publisher=Fox Television Stations, Inc.|title=FOX 11 Investigates: 'Anonymous'|accessdate=August 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

June 2, 2008 – Parents, teens, teachers, and Internet executives came together at Wired Safety's International Stop Cyberbullying Conference, a two-day gathering in White Plains, New York and New York City. Executives from Facebook, [[Verizon]], MySpace, [[Microsoft]], and many others talked with hundreds about how to better protect themselves, personal reputations, kids and businesses online from harassment. Sponsors of the conference included [[McAfee]], [[AOL]], [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]], [[Procter &amp; Gamble]], [[Girl Scouts of the USA]], WiredTrust, Children’s Safety Research and Innovation Centre, KidZui.com and others. This conference was being delivered in conjunction and with the support of Pace University. Topics addressed included cyberbullying and the law, with discussions about laws governing cyberbullying and how to distinguish between rudeness and criminal harassment. Additional forums addressed parents’ legal responsibilities, the need for more laws, how to handle violent postings of videos be handled, as well as the differentiation between free speech and hate speech. Cyberharassment vs. cyberbullying was a forefront topic, where age makes a difference and abusive internet behavior by adults with repeated clear intent to harm, ridicule or damage a person or business was classified as [[stalking]] harassment vs. bullying by teens and young adults.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wiredsafety.org/conference/progams.html Stop Cyberbullying&amp;nbsp;— An International Conference to Address Cyberbullying, Solutions and Industry Best Practices] Wired Safety, Pace University Program, June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

August 2012 - A new organized movement to make revenge porn illegal began in  August 2012.  It is known as End Revenge Porn [http://www.endrevengeporn.org/].  Currently revenge porn is only illegal in two states, but the demand for its criminalization is on the rise as digital technology has increased in the past few generations.  The organization seeks to provide support for victims, educate the public, and gain activist support to bring new legislation before the United States Government. &lt;ref&gt; End Revenge Porn http://www.endrevengeporn.org/ &lt;/ref&gt;

===Growing Awareness===

Cyberbullying has subsequently been defined as "when the Internet, cell phones or other devices are used to send or post text or images intended to hurt or embarrass another person".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncpc.org/cyberbullying National Crime Prevention Council]. Ncpc.org. Retrieved on July 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Other researchers use similar language to describe the phenomenon.&lt;ref&gt;''Bullying Beyond the Schoolyard: Preventing and Responding to Cyberbullying'', by J.W. Patchin and S. Hinuja; Sage Publications, (Corwin Press, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=patchin&gt;Patchin, J. W. &amp; Hinduja, S. (2006). [http://yvj.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/4/2/148 Bullies move beyond the schoolyard: A preliminary look at cyberbullying] [[Youth Violence and Juvenile Justice]], 4(2), 148–169.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Community Support===
A number organizations are in coalition to provide awareness, protection and recourse for the escalating problem. Some aim to inform and provide measures to avoid as well as effectively terminate cyberbullying and cyberharassment. Anti-bullying charity [[Act Against Bullying]] launched the CyberKind campaign in August 2009 to promote positive internet usage.

In 2007, YouTube introduced the first Anti-Bullying Channel for youth, (BeatBullying) engaging the assistance of celebrities to tackle the problem.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/education/7098978.stm YouTube tackles bullying online] BBC News, November 19, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2010, a 17-year old girl named Alexis Skye Pilkington was found dead in her room by her parents. Her parents claimed that after repeated cyberbullying, she was driven to suicide. Shortly after her death, attacks resumed. Members of [[eBaums World]] began to [[Troll (Internet)|troll]] teens' memorial pages on [[Facebook]], with the comments including expressions of pleasure over the death, with pictures of what seemed to be a banana as their profile pictures. Family and friends of the deceased teen responded by creating Facebook groups denouncing cyberbullying and trolling, with logos of bananas behind a red circle with a diagonal line through it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Salazar|first=Cristian|title=Alexis Pilkington Facebook Horror: Cyber Bullies Harass Teen Even After Suicide|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/03/24/alexis-pilkington-faceboo_n_512482.html|accessdate=22 October 2012|newspaper=Huffington Post|date=2010-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response and partnership to the 2011 film ''[[Bully]]'', a grassroots effort to stop cyberbullying called The Bully Project was created. Their goal is “sparked a national movement to stop bullying that is transforming kids’ lives and changing a culture of bullying into one of empathy and action.” &lt;ref&gt; The Bully Project http://www.thebullyproject.com/ &lt;/ref&gt;

==In Media and Pop Culture==
* ''[[Adina's Deck]]''— a film about three 8th-graders who help their friend who's been cyberbullied.
* ''Let's Fight It Together''— a film produced by [[Childnet|Childnet International]] to be used in schools to support discussion and awareness-raising around cyberbullying.
* ''[[Odd Girl Out]]''— a film about a girl who is bullied at school and online.
* ''At a Distance''— a short film produced by [[netsafe|NetSafe]] for the 8-12-year-old audience. It highlights forms and effects of cyberbullying and the importance of bystanders.
* ''[[Cyberbully (film)|Cyberbully]]''— a TV movie broadcast July 17, 2011 on [[ABC Family]]. Similar to ''Odd Girl Out'', it too depicts a girl who is bullied at school and online.
*''[[The Casual Vacancy]]'' - a young girl is subjected to harassing images repeatedly posted on her Facebook page.
*''[[The Truth about Truman School]]'', a 2008 children's book about a middle school girl who is cyberbullied by one of her classmates

==See also==
{{columns-list|3|
* [[Cyber defamation law]]
* [[Cyberstalking]]
* [[Defamation]]
* [[Digital safety]]
* [[Internet Troll]]
* [[Mobbing]]
* [[Sexting]]
* [[Suicide of Amanda Todd]]
* [[Suicide of Megan Meier]]
* [[Suicide of Ryan Halligan]]
* [[Suicide of Tyler Clementi]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Berson, I. R., Berson, M. J., &amp; Ferron, J. M.(2002).Emerging risks of violence in the digital age: Lessons for educators from an online study of adolescent girls in the United States.''Journal of School Violence'', 1(2), 51–71.
* Burgess-Proctor, A., Patchin, J. W., &amp; Hinduja, S. (2009). Cyberbullying and online harassment: Reconceptualizing the victimization of adolescent girls. In V. Garcia and J. Clifford [Eds.]. ''Female crime victims: Reality reconsidered''. Upper Saddle River, NJ: Prentice Hall. In Print.
* Keith, S. &amp; Martin, M. E. (2005). ''Cyber-bullying: Creating a Culture of Respect in a Cyber World.Reclaiming Children &amp; Youth'', 13(4), 224–228.
* Hinduja, S. &amp; Patchin, J. W. (2007). Offline Consequences of Online Victimization: School Violence and Delinquency. ''Journal of School Violence'', 6(3), 89–112.
* Hinduja, S. &amp; Patchin, J. W. (2008). Cyberbullying: An Exploratory Analysis of Factors Related to Offending and Victimization. ''Deviant Behavior'', 29(2), 129–156.
* Hinduja, S. &amp; Patchin, J. W. (2009). ''Bullying beyond the Schoolyard: Preventing and Responding to Cyberbullying''. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publications.
* Patchin, J. &amp; Hinduja, S. (2006). Bullies Move beyond the Schoolyard: A Preliminary Look at Cyberbullying. ''Youth Violence and Juvenile Justice', 4(2), 148–169.
* Tettegah, S. Y., Betout, D., &amp; Taylor, K. R. (2006). Cyber-bullying and schools in an electronic era. In S. Tettegah &amp; R. Hunter (Eds.) Technology and Education: Issues in administration, policy and applications in k12 school. PP. 17–28. London: Elsevier.
* Wolak, J. Mitchell, K.J., &amp; Finkelhor, D. (2006). ''Online victimization of youth: 5 years later''. Alexandria, VA: National Center for Missing &amp; Exploited Children. Available at [http://www.unh.edu/ccrc unh.edu]
* Ybarra, M. L. &amp; Mitchell, J. K. (2004). Online aggressor/targets, aggressors and targets: A comparison of associated youth characteristics. ''Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry'', 45, 1308–1316.
* Ybarra ML (2004). Linkages between depressive symptomatology and Internet harassment among young regular Internet users. ''Cyberpsychol and Behavior''. Apr;7(2):247-57.
* Ybarra ML, Mitchell KJ (2004). Youth engaging in online harassment: associations with caregiver-child relationships, Internet use, and personal characteristics. ''Journal of Adolescence''. Jun;27(3):319-36.
* Frederick S. Lane, (Chicago: NTI Upstream, 2011)

==External links==
{{wiktionary|cyberbully}}
{{commonscat}}
* [http://www.cyberbullying.us Cyberbullying Research Center]
* [http://www.stopbullying.gov/topics/cyberbullying/ Cyberbullying] at Stopbullying.gov
* [http://site.ebrary.com/lib/cyberbullying/home.action Cyberbullying Searchable Information Center], [[ebrary]]
* [http://www.cyberbullying.org.nz/ Cyberbullying.org.nz] – Cyberbullying information, support, and teaching resources from the New Zealand non-profit [[netsafe|NetSafe]], including the short film [http://www.cyberbullying.org.nz/at-a-distance-film/ At a Distance]
* [http://raisingchildren.net.au/articles/cyberbullying_teenagers.html Cyberbullying in Australia] Australian Cyberbullying resource for teenagers

{{Bullying}}
{{abuse}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cyber-Bullying}}
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Bullying]]
[[Category:Computer crimes]]
[[Category:Cyber-bullying| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>