<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20170917172258|801099655" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="35714069" pageid="35714069" ns="0" title="Net bias"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-10-31T16:47:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Network neutrality}}
{{Merge from|Data discrimination|date=November 2016}}

'''Net bias''' (or network bias) is the counter-principle to [[net neutrality]], which indicates differentiation or discrimination of price and the quality of content or applications on the Internet by [[Internet service provider|ISP]]s.

Net bias, the term, was first coined by [[Rob Frieden]], a professor at [[Penn State University]]. Similar terms include [[data discrimination]] and [[network management]]. Net bias occurs when an ISP drops packets or denies access based on artificially induced conditions such as simulating congestion or blocking packets, despite the fact that ample capacity exists to carry traffic. Examples (models) of net bias include [[tiered service]] (specialized service), metering, [[bandwidth throttling]], and [[Block (Internet)|port blocking]]. These forms of net bias are achieved by technical advancements of the [[Internet Protocol]]. 

The idea of net bias can arise from [[politics|political]] and [[economy|economic]] motivations and backgrounds, which create some concerns regarding [[discrimination issues]] from political and economic perspectives.

== Models of net bias ==
=== Tiered service (specialized service, bandwidth partitioning) ===
[[Tiered service]] is one of the strategies employed to change Internet [[pricing]] and involves an intent to have flexibility in [[quality of service]] (QoS) on the Internet. Tiered service allows ISPs to create and manage speed-related subscriber tiers.&lt;ref name=autogenerated7&gt;{{cite web|title=The problem: Managing and Profiting from the Growth of Data Traffic|url=http://servicetiers.openet.com/the-problem.html|publisher=OPENET|accessdate=22 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, this model partitions bandwidth and provides different levels of peering requirements and offers transit clients different amounts of [[throughput]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite journal|last=Frieden|first=Robert|title=Network Neutrality or Bias?--Handicapping the Odds for a Tiered and Branded Internet|journal=bepress Legal Series|year=2006|series=Working Paper 1755|url=http://law.bepress.com/expresso/eps/1755}}&lt;/ref&gt; This model stems from the perception of technical and economic limitations in the [[broadband]] industry. As technology develops, the demand for faster and higher performance of [[communication network]]s and the customer demand for bandwidth-intensive services, such as [[streaming video]]s, have increased.&lt;ref name=autogenerated13&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lee|first=R. S.|author2=Wu, T.|title=Subsidizing Creativity through Network Design: Zero-Pricing and Net Neutrality|journal=Journal of Economic Perspectives|year=2009|volume=23|issue=3|pages=61–67|doi=10.1257/jep.23.3.61}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated11&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lee|first=G. H.|title=Network Neutrality Regulation in the Broadband Market in Korea|journal=Korea Information Society Development Institute|year=2007|volume=14|pages=41–66}}&lt;/ref&gt; These situations result in [[network congestion]] that is mainly driven by a small number of heavy users.&lt;ref name=autogenerated7 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated10&gt;{{cite journal|last=Krämer|first=J.|author2=Wiewiorra, L.|title=Network Neutrality and Congestion Sensitive Content providers: Implications for Service Innovation, Broadband Investment and Regulation|year=2010|series=SSRN Working Paper 1444423|ssrn=1444423}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite journal|last=Yoo|first=Christopher S.|title=Network Neutrality and the Economics of Congestion|journal=Georgetown Law Journal|date=August 2006|volume=94|issue=6|pages=18–47}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, ISPs argue that existing [[Flat rate|flat-rate]] plans do not enable them to cover the additional cost required to manage heavier network traffic.&lt;ref name=autogenerated7 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;{{cite journal|last=Choi|first=J.|author2=Kim, B.|title=Net Neutrality and Investment Incentives|year=2008|series=NET Institute Working Paper 08-03|ssrn=1285639}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, this model may allow ISPs to reach different market segments with different data plans, targeting the different types of needs based on speed tiers, volume [[data cap]]s, and other customizable conditions.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6&gt;{{cite web|title=The Solution: Flexibly package and sell data plans, and better match revenues with network utilization|url=http://servicetiers.openet.com/the-solution.html|publisher=OPENET|accessdate=22 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Metering ===
Metered service (also called pay-per-use) is another strategy utilized to change Internet pricing other than tiered service. This model represents a usage-based pricing scheme that charges users based on their [[Packet (information technology)|packet]] usages.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hwang|first=J.|author2=Lee, D. |author3=Lee, K. |title=Internet Pricing and Network Neutrality: How Internet  Pricing Schemes Affect the Incentives of Internet Service Providers|journal=International Telecommunications Policy Review|year=2010|volume=18|issue=1|pages=17–44}}&lt;/ref&gt; Metered service contrasts with the model of paying a [[Flat rate|flat fee]] on a recurring basis to have unlimited access to a given good or service.{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} This metering scheme not only satisfies ISPs in terms of recovering cost, but also enables users to rethink their usage patterns with a price signal.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt; This pricing plan can benefit low-volume users because metered service might create new and possibly lower price points for those users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=metered services (pay-per-use)|url=http://searchcio.techtarget.com/definition/metered-services|publisher=SearchCIO|accessdate=22 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, research shows that price is the most important factor for users, among other factors such as Internet speed, which indicates that broadband users are price-sensitive. Price-sensitivity explains why few consumers like having to think about how much they are using the Internet.&lt;ref name=autogenerated9&gt;{{cite journal|last=Nam|first=C.|author2=Lee, H. |author3=Kim, S. |author4=Kim, T. |title=Network Neutrality Debate: an End User’s Perspective|journal=International Telecommunications Policy Review|year=2011|volume=18|issue=1|pages=1–15}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, from the users’ perspective, one study suggested that consumers might have far less tolerance for unsolicited advertising, [[Spam (e-mail)|spam emails]], [[banner advertising]], and third party users of throughput when they are required to consider the cost for the amount of traffic.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; However, from the ISPs’ perspective, one study indicates that a usage-based pricing scheme does not cause ISPs’ discrimination incentives against [[content provider]]s because ISPs are able to gain sufficient profits for the network investment to meet market needs.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt;

===Bandwidth throttling===
[[Bandwidth throttling]] is a tactic that allows information and telecommunication companies to regulate network traffic and control [[network congestion]]. This type of measure is viewed as a limitation on users’ upload and download speeds (rates) of content.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kellex|title=As of Yesterday Verizon Started Throttling its Top 5% Data Hogs, Doesn’t Affect 4G LTE or Tiered Data Customers|url=http://www.droid-life.com/2011/09/16/as-of-yesterday-verizon-started-throttling-its-top-5-data-hogs-doesnt-affect-4g-lte-or-tiered-data-customers/|accessdate=22 April 2012|newspaper=DroidLife|date=Sep 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Comcast]], one of the major ISPs, conducted bandwidth throttling on 49% of its customers who were using bandwidth for [[P2P file sharing]]. After Comcast’s actions were exposed, the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) ordered the company to stop throttling on a large scale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Walters|first=Ray|title=BitTorrent throttlilng report reveals Comcast is keeping its word|url=http://www.geek.com/articles/news/bittorrent-throttling-report-reveals-comcast-is-keeping-its-word-20111021/|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=Geek.com|date=Oct 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, this form of net bias frequently targets heavy mobile users who consume large amounts of content (packets), like unlimited data plans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bonnington|first=Christina|title=AT&amp;T Adjusts Data-Throttling Policy in Response to Customer Complaints|url=https://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2012/03/att-throttling-adjustment/|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=wired.com|date=Mar 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mobile companies such as [[AT&amp;T]] and [[Verizon Communications|Verizon]] have their own throttling policy because they are sometimes required to limit users’ traffic to maintain the quality of the entire network. Recently, however, throttling has become a controversial issue because some companies infringe upon this policy. For example, AT&amp;T had to pay US$850 to one customer to compensate for slowing down data speeds because they violated the terms of unlimited [[smartphone]] data contracts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Skelton|first=Alissa|title=AT&amp;T Loses Throttling Case, Pays $935 to Customer|url=http://mashable.com/2012/03/17/att-loses-throttling-suit/|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=Mashable Tech|date=Mar 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Fitchard|first=Kevin|title=AT&amp;T vs. the consumer: The throttling controversy grows|url=http://gigaom.com/mobile/att-vs-the-consumer-the-throttling-controversy-grows/|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=gigaom|date=Mar 14, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to these complaints from smartphone subscribers, AT&amp;T announced that they would change their policy for unlimited data users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Svensson|first=Peter|title=AT&amp;T Data Throttling: Carrier Clarifies Policy Of Slowing Speeds For 'Unlimited' Subscribers|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/03/01/att-data-throttling-unlimited_n_1314046.html|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=HUFFPOST Tech|date=Mar 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Blocking (port blocking) ===
[[Block (Internet)|Port blocking]] includes the deliberate decision by ISPs to deny onward transmission of traffic, or delivery of traffic, to an intended recipient. ISPs do not have a legitimate reason to deny onward packet transmission to specific customers of other ISPs. The ISPs have contractually committed to carry any and all packets from the former ISP without regard for the identity and marketplace success of that ISP’s customers (on a first-come, first-served basis).&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated9 /&gt; However, an ISP is more likely to have higher incentives for port blocking when the ISP is vertically and horizontally integrated because those integrated companies attempt to enhance the marketplace attractiveness of [[Affiliated company|corporate affiliates]]. For example, AT&amp;T blocked [[Voice over Internet Protocol]] (VoIP) because the company was concerned that the VoIP service might threaten its wireless and wired [[Telephone company|telephony service]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bradley|first=Tony|title=AT&amp;T and Apple Admit Deal to Block VoIP on iPhone|url=https://www.pcworld.com/article/170661/atandt_and_apple_admit_deal_to_block_voip_on_iphone.html|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=PCworld|date=Aug 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Vahey|first=Moira|title=FCC Actions Pushed AT&amp;T to Stop VoIP Blocking|url=http://www.freepress.net/node/73305|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=FreePress|date=Oct 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, an ISP can engage in port blocking for VoIP traffic when giving preference to an affiliated telephone company.

== Technical component for net bias ==
Technological advancements allowed these types of net bias to function, while the technology was not fully matured enough to apply new pricing or QoS schemes in the past.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;{{cite news|last=Krim|first=Jonathan|title=Executive Wants to Charge for Web Speed|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/11/30/AR2005113002109.html|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=The Washington Post|date=Dec 1, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, as network technologies develop, ISPs implemented technological innovations that can prioritize packets and meter them when faced with increasing bandwidth requirements, using systems to distinguish properties of data packets. [[Packet analyzer|Packet analysis]] enables ISPs to monitor the [[Internet traffic]], and can be performed by a computer program or hardware component that intercepts and logs traffic passing over a digital network.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Connolly|first=Kevin|title=Law of Internet Security and Privacy|year=2003|publisher=Aspen Publishers|isbn=978-0-7355-4273-0|pages=131}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are many technologies for network management such as [[SNMP]] or [[NETCONF]].

== Motivations==
The idea of network flexibility in pricing, service provisioning, and QoS tends to be based on economic and political considerations. These considerations show that net bias (network flexibility) makes economic sense and may not violate a reasonable expectation of [[net neutrality]].

=== Economic motivations ===
ISPs have been increasingly investing in the infrastructure necessary to transport the bits and packets that correspond to commercially successful content and services.&lt;ref name=autogenerated9 /&gt; As the [[Internet]] becomes more capable of covering most converged services, and those services require wide bandwidth, high QoS guarantees, and time-sensitivity, ISPs must make substantial investments to the network.&lt;ref name=autogenerated11 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Madden|first=Mary|title=The Audience for Online Video-Sharing Sites Shoots Up.|url=http://www.pewinternet.org/Reports/2009/13--The-Audience-for-Online-VideoSharing-Sites-Shoots-Up/3-Mobile-and-TV-Viewing/Americans-who-have-cut-back-on-expenses-are-more-likely-to-watch-online-video-on-their-televisions.aspx|publisher=Pew  Internet &amp; American Life Project|accessdate=23 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, at the early stage of the Internet’s appearance, ISPs were able to concentrate on “connectivity” over “cost” because the government supported the development of the Internet. However, as this support has been removed and ISPs have sought to recoup their investment, cost recovery has become substantially more important to ISPs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Leiner|first=Barry|title=Brief History of the Internet|url=http://www.internetsociety.org/internet/internet-51/history-internet/brief-history-internet|publisher=Internet society 20 years|accessdate=23 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, [[incumbent carrier]]s like AT&amp;T, whose business involves both the Internet and telephony service, needed the new powerful source of revenue because traditional telephony became less profitable and its market share declined.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; In this situation, the incumbent carriers recognize that the significant profits accrued by Internet content and application providers such as [[Google]] can bring carriers the new revenue streams they are seeking. Accordingly, some of the major ISPs believe that the best way to achieve their goals is through the partitioning of network bandwidth and the prioritizing of bitstreams by offering different QoS.&lt;ref name=autogenerated10 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt; Likewise, some researchers argue that these strategies could work, emphasizing that ISPs should have unregulated pricing freedom, which may lead to promoted innovation, risk tasking, and diverse services and features.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Hazlett|first=Thomas|title=Neutering the net|url=http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/2/392ad708-b837-11da-bfc5-0000779e2340.html#axzz1sov6yyRz|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=Financial Times|date=Mar 20, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Yoo pointed out that ISPs could offer undropped packets and timely packet delivery even under truly congested conditions when they have the option of offering a premium peak service.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Professor Lawrence Lessig also indicates that consumer-tiering, which provides end users with different throughput speeds or permissible volume of traffic, could recoup infrastructure investments and create the necessary incentives for increased investment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lessig|first=Lawrence|title=TESTIMONY OF LAWRENCE LESSIG C. WENDELL AND EDITH M. CARLSMITH PROFESSOR OF LAW STANFORD LAW SCHOOL. HEARING ON "NETWORK NEUTRALITY"|url=http://commerce.senate.gov/pdf/lessig-020706.pdf|publisher=SENATE COMMITTEE ON COMMERCE, SCIENCE AND TRANSPORTATION|accessdate=23 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Political motivations ===
As the FCC has perceived the need to create more incentives for incumbent carriers to invest in broadband, the commission has taken apart the access requirements and pricing model that force incumbent carriers to offer services at a low rate through the [[Telecommunications Act of 1996]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; In addition, the FCC has removed the traditional regulatory burdens for common carriers that provide Internet access and services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Appropriate Framework for Broadband Access to the Internet over Wireline Facilities|url=http://hraunfoss.fcc.gov/edocs_public/attachmatch/FCC-05-150A1.doc|publisher=FCC|accessdate=23 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; These deregulatory initiatives have freed the carriers of having to share and interconnect facilities providing information services. Some proponents of net bias argue that ISPs do not have legal obligation to operate as [[common carrier]]s and that the network’s interconnection arrangements result from commercial necessity.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt; Moreover, in terms of establishing the network’s interconnection, ISPs argue that they used their resources to maintain and upgrade the network for customers, and so far popular websites have received a “free ride” from these resources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bandyopadhyay|first=S.|author2=Guo, H. |author3=Cheng, H. |title=Subsidizing Creativity through Network Design: Zero-Pricing and Net Neutrality|journal=Journal of Economic Perspectives|year=2009|volume=23|issue=3|pages=61–67|ssrn=1422061|doi=10.1257/jep.23.3.61}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Waldmeir|first=Patti|title=The Net Neutrality Dogfight that is Shaking Up Cyberspace|url=http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/76d85cb6-ba11-11da-9d02-0000779e2340,Authorised=false.html?_i_location=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.ft.com%2Fcms%2Fs%2F0%2F76d85cb6-ba11-11da-9d02-0000779e2340.html&amp;_i_referer=#axzz1sov6yyRz|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=Financial Times|date=Mar 23, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advocates of net bias also propose lawful [[pricing]]. Network flexibility for pricing, interconnection, and QoS characterize the initiatives as lawful [[price discrimination]] that can provide consumers with greater flexibility and potentially lower bills for low-volume users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sidak|first=Gregory|title=Testimony of J. Gregory Sidak Visiting Professor of Law Georgetown University Law Center|url=http://commerce.senate.gov/pdf/sidak-020706.pdf|publisher=Testimony of [[J. Gregory Sidak]] Visiting Professor of Law Georgetown University Law Center|accessdate=23 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advocates of net bias also argue that combining simple routing with superior service offers options that are no different from the multiple classes of service provided by most airlines or the qualitative difference between free and toll highways.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; Consequently, some experts contend that the option of offering network flexibility provides a means for consumers and carriers to utilize premium services.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;

== Concerns regarding discrimination ==
The Internet has been historically regarded as an open and “best effort” network. Internet routers must forward packets on a first-come, first-served basis without regard for the analysis of data or content inside the packet.&lt;ref name=autogenerated11 /&gt; This aspect of the Internet has increased its value, contributing not only to the quality of our lives, but also to economic growth around the globe.&lt;ref name=autogenerated10 /&gt; Based on these notions, forms of net bias have created some concerns regarding discrimination from economic and political perspectives.&lt;ref name=autogenerated13 /&gt; In other words, unreasonable net bias occurs when an ISP conducts a discrimination strategy against a specific type of packet without a reasonable and fair financial or operational justification.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;

=== Concerns about economic discrimination ===
Users enjoy the high level of value when they are able to access the Internet on an unmetered and [[Flat rate|flat-rate]] basis.&lt;ref name=autogenerated10 /&gt; Users can also obtain attractive content subsidized by advertisers who employ the flat-rate subscription option by adding to the downloaded packet payload.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; This value proposition provides users with the benefits of the Internet, emphasizing connectivity with less regard for cost-related concerns. Likewise, the positive [[network effect]] — which refers to the process whereby more and more people adopt a service or buy a good, and as a result users receive enjoyable benefits and additional users are attracted to the Internet — created by the spread of the Internet is substantially beneficial.&lt;ref name=autogenerated12&gt;{{cite book|last=Crandall|first=R.|title=Broadband communications|year=2005|publisher=Handbook of Telecommunications Economics|pages=156–190}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Internet, interlinking hundreds and thousands of networks reduces [[transaction cost]]s and brings a flood of free information to subscribers.&lt;ref name=autogenerated12 /&gt; However, if major ISPs can freely block and degrade specific traffic streams, there would be societal losses as the Internet becomes more expensive and less productive. Proponents of net bias contend that market-based Internet access achieves efficient outcomes, such as creating innovation incentives for ISPs to invest in building and expanding networks. Nevertheless, opponents of net bias claim that allowing price and service discrimination may ruin the value of the Internet and enable ISPs to shut out competitors or other stakeholders who are unwilling or unable to pay surcharges.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; In other words, when large or powerful ISPs place a disproportionate financial burden on small and less financially sound ISPs and their subscribers by using forms of net bias like [[Block (Internet)|port blocking]] or [[tiered service]]s, they may exacerbate the [[digital divide]] that separates people with easy and robust Internet service access opportunities from those without.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=REGULATORY REFORM AS A TOOL FOR BRIDGING THE DIGITAL DIVIDE|url=http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/40/11/34487084.pdf|publisher=OECD|accessdate=22 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; One consumer group, [[Free Press (organization)|Free Press]], calls attention to a number of disadvantages that specialized services ([[tiered service]]s) may produce. This organization argues that any form of prioritization on the open Internet would bring enormous disadvantages in terms of innovation, competition, investment, consumer choice, and [[free speech]] because this permission may enable ISPs to choose specific content/applications with respect to their own interests and thereby destroy the nature and value of the today’s open Internet. Free Press cautions that specialized services will result in unbalanced and unparalleled economic growth, which is utterly against the public interest.&lt;ref name=autogenerated8&gt;{{cite web|last=Free Press|title=Comments of Free Press Regarding Further Inquiry|url=http://apps.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/view?id=7020916539|publisher=FCC|accessdate=22 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Concerns about political discrimination ===
In 2005, the FCC issued a Broadband Policy Statement (also known as the Internet Policy Statement) that offered guidance and insight into its approach to the Internet and broadband consistent with Congress’ direction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Policy Statement|url=http://hraunfoss.fcc.gov/edocs_public/attachmatch/FCC-05-151A1.pdf|publisher=FCC|accessdate=22 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  (FCC) The four principles of this statement are as follows:

:*To encourage broadband deployment and preserve and promote the open and interconnected nature of the public Internet, consumers are entitled to access the lawful Internet content of their choice.

:*To encourage broadband deployment and preserve and promote the open and interconnected nature of the public Internet, consumers are entitled to run applications and use services of their choice, subject to the needs of law enforcement.

:*To encourage broadband deployment and preserve and promote the open and interconnected nature of the public Internet, consumers are entitled to connect their choice of legal devices that do not harm the network.

:*To encourage broadband deployment and preserve and promote the open and interconnected nature of the public Internet, consumers are entitled to competition among network providers, application and service providers, and content providers.

At first glance, these principles appear noncontroversial in terms of standards regarding the freedom of the network. However, these principles do not address regulations with respect to the issues of differentiations in pricing, interconnection, and QoS.&lt;ref name=autogenerated11 /&gt; Further, the unregulated forms of net bias have the potential to create false congestion by the ISPs.&lt;ref name=autogenerated9 /&gt; More specifically, advanced Internet protocol technology can allow ISPs to fabricate congestion and drop packets when no real congestion takes place. In addition, existing peering and transit agreements between stakeholders such as small and large ISPs may lack a specific prohibition of deliberate packet loss.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;

Many ISPs contend that major content providers such as [[Google]] or [[Yahoo!]] enjoy a [[Free rider problem|free ride]]. [[AT&amp;T]], one of the major ISPs, stated that the current standard procedure for Internet pricing and interconnection has left the company burdened with having to create, maintain, and frequently upgrade an expensive bit transport infrastructure whereas content providers do not have to do the same.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=At SBC, It's All About "Scale and Scope"|url=http://www.freepress.net/news/14959|publisher=Free Press|accessdate=23 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Rob Frieden points out that the ISPs’ practices of net bias, as they are based on a “free rider” consideration, may violate the principles of network freedom or even the peering and transit agreement between ISPs. Based on existing peering and transit agreements made by AT&amp;T, Google is allowed to have its traffic delivered to AT&amp;T subscribers free of charge, and AT&amp;T is compensated for the traffic from other ISPs by the agreements.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated13 /&gt; Moreover, if AT&amp;T penalizes Google’s traffic from the various forms of net bias, it would jeopardize the principles of network freedom as well as violate its contractual commitment to its peers and transit customers who have paid for best efforts access to AT&amp;T’s networks.

Technical and market convergence as well as deregulation by the [[Telecommunications Act of 1996]] provided incentives for companies to integrate vertically and horizontally. As a result, those integrated companies have discrimination incentives such that they may try port blocking or unfair throttling to enhance the marketplace attractiveness of corporate affiliates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Guo|first=H.|author2=Bandyopadhyay, S. |author3=Cheng, H.K. |author4=Yang, Y. |title=Net Neutrality and Vertical Integration of Content and Broadband Services|year=2009|series=Warrington College of Business Administration Working Paper Series}}&lt;/ref&gt; From this perspective, Free Press emphasized through its comments to the FCC Notice of Inquiry that specialized services should be provided with fairness, particularly in the vertically integrated environments of the information and telecommunication industry (e.g., Comcast, which has both content and broadband services).&lt;ref name=autogenerated8 /&gt; Consequently, concerns regarding discrimination raised the need of network neutrality regulations to preserve the open Internet and public interest and enable the Internet industry to survive and succeed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Shrimali|first=G.|title=Surplus extraction by network providers: Implications for net neutrality and innovation|journal=Telecommunications Policy|year=2008|volume=32|issue=8|pages=545–558|doi=10.1016/j.telpol.2008.06.005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Knieps|first=G.|title=Market Driven Network Neutrality and the Fallacies of Internet Traffic Quality Regulation|journal= International Telecommunications Policy Review|year=2011|volume=18|issue=3|pages=1–22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Biases}}

[[Category:Net neutrality]]
[[Category:Media bias]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>