<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20220626021614|1095044993" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="35714069" pageid="35714069" ns="0" title="Net bias"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-07-20T22:34:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Network neutrality}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
'''Net bias''' (or '''network bias''') is the counter-principle to [[net neutrality]], which indicates differentiation or discrimination of price and the quality of content or applications on the Internet by [[Internet service provider|ISP]]s. Similar terms include '''data discrimination,''' [[digital redlining]], and [[network management]].

Net bias occurs when an ISP drops packets or denies access based on artificially induced conditions such as simulating congestion or blocking packets, despite the fact that ample capacity exists to carry traffic. Examples (models) of net bias include [[tiered service]] (specialized service), metering, [[bandwidth throttling]], and [[Block (Internet)|port blocking]]. These forms of net bias are achieved by technical advancements of the [[Internet Protocol]].

The idea of net bias can arise from [[politics|political]] and [[economy|economic]] motivations and backgrounds, which create some concerns regarding [[data discrimination]] arising from political and economic interests. Non-discrimination means that one class of Internet customers may not be favored over another. According to this view, the  Internet should continue "to operate in a nondiscriminatory manner, both in terms of how subscribers access and receive Internet transmitted services and how content and other service providers reach subscribers."&lt;ref name=Frieden /&gt; Every internet user should have equal upload and download capabilities on every network.&lt;ref name=Frieden /&gt;&lt;ref name=Bagwell&gt;{{cite web|last=Bagwell|first=Dana|title=A First Amendment Case For Internet Broadband Network Neutrality|publisher=University of Washington|access-date=8 Feb 2011|url=http://gradworks.umi.com/cgi-bin/redirect?url=http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl%3furl_ver=Z39.88-2004%26res_dat=xri:pqdiss%26rft_val_fmt=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:dissertation%26rft_dat=xri:pqdiss:3421533}}{{Dead link|date=April 2020 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Net neutrality==
{{main|Net neutrality}}
The principle of equal treatment of traffic, called "Net Neutrality" by proponents, is not enshrined in law in the United States but is supported by some regulations. Most of the debate around the issue has centered on tentative plans, now postponed, by large Internet carriers to offer preferential treatment of traffic from certain content providers for a fee.&lt;ref name=ComcastBlocks&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/10/19/AR2007101900842.html |title=Comcast Blocks Some Internet Traffic |date=2010-10-19 |newspaper=The Washington Post | access-date=2011-08-02 |first=Peter |last=Svensson}}&lt;/ref&gt; Network neutrality is a set of rules that forbid network owners from discriminating against independent applications (instead of against competing ISPs, as with open access).&lt;ref name=Bagwell/&gt;

== Models of net bias ==
=== Tiered service (specialized service, bandwidth partitioning) ===
[[Tiered service]] is one of the strategies employed to change Internet [[pricing]] and involves an intent to have flexibility in [[quality of service]] (QoS) on the Internet. Tiered service allows ISPs to create and manage speed-related subscriber tiers.&lt;ref name=autogenerated7&gt;{{cite web|title=The problem: Managing and Profiting from the Growth of Data Traffic|url=http://servicetiers.openet.com/the-problem.html|publisher=OPENET|access-date=22 April 2012|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://archive.today/20130131025902/http://servicetiers.openet.com/the-problem.html|archive-date=31 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, this model partitions bandwidth and provides different levels of peering requirements and offers transit clients different amounts of [[throughput]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite journal|last=Frieden|first=Robert|title=Network Neutrality or Bias?--Handicapping the Odds for a Tiered and Branded Internet|journal=Bepress Legal Series|year=2006|series=Working Paper 1755|url=http://law.bepress.com/expresso/eps/1755}}&lt;/ref&gt; This model stems from the perception of technical and economic limitations in the [[broadband]] industry. As technology develops, the demand for faster and higher performance of [[communication network]]s and the customer demand for bandwidth-intensive services, such as [[streaming video]]s, have increased.&lt;ref name=autogenerated13&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lee|first=R. S.|author2=Wu, T.|title=Subsidizing Creativity through Network Design: Zero-Pricing and Net Neutrality|journal=Journal of Economic Perspectives|year=2009|volume=23|issue=3|pages=61–67|doi=10.1257/jep.23.3.61|url=https://scholarship.law.columbia.edu/faculty_scholarship/1601}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated11&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lee|first=G. H.|title=Network Neutrality Regulation in the Broadband Market in Korea|journal=Korea Information Society Development Institute|year=2007|volume=14|pages=41–66}}&lt;/ref&gt; These situations result in [[network congestion]] that is mainly driven by a small number of heavy users.&lt;ref name=autogenerated7 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated10&gt;{{cite journal|last=Krämer|first=J.|author2=Wiewiorra, L.|title=Network Neutrality and Congestion Sensitive Content providers: Implications for Service Innovation, Broadband Investment and Regulation|year=2010|series=SSRN Working Paper 1444423|ssrn=1444423}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite journal|last=Yoo|first=Christopher S.|title=Network Neutrality and the Economics of Congestion|journal=Georgetown Law Journal|date=August 2006|volume=94|issue=6|pages=18–47}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, ISPs argue that existing [[Flat rate|flat-rate]] plans do not enable them to cover the additional cost required to manage heavier network traffic.&lt;ref name=autogenerated7 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;{{cite journal|last=Choi|first=J.|author2=Kim, B.|title=Net Neutrality and Investment Incentives|year=2008|series=NET Institute Working Paper 08-03|ssrn=1285639}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, this model may allow ISPs to reach different market segments with different data plans, targeting the different types of needs based on speed tiers, volume [[data cap]]s, and other customizable conditions.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6&gt;{{cite web|title=The Solution: Flexibly package and sell data plans, and better match revenues with network utilization|url=http://servicetiers.openet.com/the-solution.html|publisher=OPENET|access-date=22 April 2012|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://archive.today/20130130201901/http://servicetiers.openet.com/the-solution.html|archive-date=30 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Metering ===
Metered service (also called pay-per-use) is another strategy utilized to change Internet pricing other than tiered service. This model represents a usage-based pricing scheme that charges users based on their [[Packet (information technology)|packet]] usages.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hwang|first=J.|author2=Lee, D. |author3=Lee, K. |title=Internet Pricing and Network Neutrality: How Internet Pricing Schemes Affect the Incentives of Internet Service Providers|journal=International Telecommunications Policy Review|year=2010|volume=18|issue=1|pages=17–44}}&lt;/ref&gt; Metered service contrasts with the model of paying a [[Flat rate|flat fee]] on a recurring basis to have unlimited access to a given good or service.{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} This metering scheme not only satisfies ISPs in terms of recovering cost, but also enables users to rethink their usage patterns with a price signal.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt; This pricing plan can benefit low-volume users because metered service might create new and possibly lower price points for those users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=metered services (pay-per-use)|url=http://searchcio.techtarget.com/definition/metered-services|publisher=SearchCIO|access-date=22 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, research shows that price is the most important factor for users, among other factors such as Internet speed, which indicates that broadband users are price-sensitive. Price-sensitivity explains why few consumers like having to think about how much they are using the Internet.&lt;ref name=autogenerated9&gt;{{cite journal|last=Nam|first=C.|author2=Lee, H. |author3=Kim, S. |author4=Kim, T. |title=Network Neutrality Debate: an End User's Perspective|journal=International Telecommunications Policy Review|year=2011|volume=18|issue=1|pages=1–15}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, from the users’ perspective, one study suggested that consumers might have far less tolerance for [[unsolicited advertisement|unsolicited advertising]], [[Spam (e-mail)|spam emails]], [[banner advertising]], and third party users of throughput when they are required to consider the cost for the amount of traffic.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; However, from the ISPs’ perspective, one study indicates that a usage-based pricing scheme does not cause ISPs’ discrimination incentives against [[content provider]]s because ISPs are able to gain sufficient profits for the network investment to meet market needs.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt;

===Bandwidth throttling===
[[Bandwidth throttling]] is a tactic that allows information and telecommunication companies to regulate network traffic and control [[network congestion]]. This type of measure is viewed as a limitation on users’ upload and download speeds (rates) of content.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kellex|title=As of Yesterday Verizon Started Throttling its Top 5% Data Hogs, Doesn't Affect 4G LTE or Tiered Data Customers|url=http://www.droid-life.com/2011/09/16/as-of-yesterday-verizon-started-throttling-its-top-5-data-hogs-doesnt-affect-4g-lte-or-tiered-data-customers/|access-date=22 April 2012|newspaper=DroidLife|date=Sep 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Comcast]], one of the major ISPs, conducted bandwidth throttling on 49% of its customers who were using bandwidth for [[P2P file sharing]]. After Comcast's actions were exposed, the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) ordered the company to stop throttling on a large scale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Walters|first=Ray|title=BitTorrent throttlilng report reveals Comcast is keeping its word|url=http://www.geek.com/articles/news/bittorrent-throttling-report-reveals-comcast-is-keeping-its-word-20111021/|access-date=23 April 2012|newspaper=Geek.com|date=Oct 21, 2011|archive-date=28 April 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120428184048/http://www.geek.com/articles/news/bittorrent-throttling-report-reveals-comcast-is-keeping-its-word-20111021|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, this form of net bias frequently targets heavy mobile users who consume large amounts of content (packets), like unlimited data plans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bonnington|first=Christina|title=AT&amp;T Adjusts Data-Throttling Policy in Response to Customer Complaints|url=https://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2012/03/att-throttling-adjustment/|access-date=23 April 2012|newspaper=wired.com|date=Mar 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mobile companies such as [[AT&amp;T]] and [[Verizon Communications|Verizon]] have their own throttling policy because they are sometimes required to limit users’ traffic to maintain the quality of the entire network. Recently, however, throttling has become a controversial issue because some companies infringe upon this policy. For example, AT&amp;T had to pay US$850 to one customer to compensate for slowing down data speeds because they violated the terms of unlimited [[smartphone]] data contracts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Skelton|first=Alissa|title=AT&amp;T Loses Throttling Case, Pays $935 to Customer|url=http://mashable.com/2012/03/17/att-loses-throttling-suit/|access-date=23 April 2012|newspaper=Mashable Tech|date=Mar 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Fitchard|first=Kevin|title=AT&amp;T vs. the consumer: The throttling controversy grows|url=http://gigaom.com/mobile/att-vs-the-consumer-the-throttling-controversy-grows/|access-date=23 April 2012|newspaper=gigaom|date=Mar 14, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to these complaints from smartphone subscribers, AT&amp;T announced that they would change their policy for unlimited data users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Svensson|first=Peter|title=AT&amp;T Data Throttling: Carrier Clarifies Policy Of Slowing Speeds For 'Unlimited' Subscribers|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/03/01/att-data-throttling-unlimited_n_1314046.html|access-date=23 April 2012|newspaper=HUFFPOST Tech|date=Mar 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Blocking (port blocking) ===
[[Block (Internet)|Port blocking]] includes the deliberate decision by ISPs to deny onward transmission of traffic, or delivery of traffic, to an intended recipient. ISPs do not have a legitimate reason to deny onward packet transmission to specific customers of other ISPs. The ISPs have contractually committed to carry any and all packets from the former ISP without regard for the identity and marketplace success of that ISP's customers (on a first-come, first-served basis).&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated9 /&gt; However, an ISP is more likely to have higher incentives for port blocking when the ISP is vertically and horizontally integrated because those integrated companies attempt to enhance the marketplace attractiveness of [[Affiliated company|corporate affiliates]]. For example, AT&amp;T blocked [[Voice over Internet Protocol]] (VoIP) because the company was concerned that the VoIP service might threaten its wireless and wired [[Telephone company|telephony service]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bradley|first=Tony|title=AT&amp;T and Apple Admit Deal to Block VoIP on iPhone|url=https://www.pcworld.com/article/170661/atandt_and_apple_admit_deal_to_block_voip_on_iphone.html|access-date=23 April 2012|newspaper=PCworld|date=Aug 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Vahey|first=Moira|title=FCC Actions Pushed AT&amp;T to Stop VoIP Blocking|url=http://www.freepress.net/node/73305|access-date=23 April 2012|newspaper=FreePress|date=Oct 7, 2009|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131219235555/http://www.freepress.net/node/73305|archive-date=19 December 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, an ISP can engage in port blocking for VoIP traffic when giving preference to an affiliated telephone company.

== Technical component for net bias ==
Technological advancements allowed these types of net bias to function, while the technology was not fully matured enough to apply new pricing or QoS schemes in the past.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;{{cite news|last=Krim|first=Jonathan|title=Executive Wants to Charge for Web Speed|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/11/30/AR2005113002109.html|access-date=23 April 2012|newspaper=The Washington Post|date=Dec 1, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, as network technologies develop, ISPs implemented technological innovations that can prioritize packets and meter them when faced with increasing bandwidth requirements, using systems to distinguish properties of data packets. [[Packet analyzer|Packet analysis]] enables ISPs to monitor the [[Internet traffic]], and can be performed by a computer program or hardware component that intercepts and logs traffic passing over a digital network.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Connolly|first=Kevin|title=Law of Internet Security and Privacy|year=2003|publisher=Aspen Publishers|isbn=978-0-7355-4273-0|pages=131}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are many technologies for network management such as [[SNMP]] or [[NETCONF]].

== Motivations==
The idea of network flexibility in pricing, service provisioning, and QoS tends to be based on economic and political considerations. These considerations show that net bias (network flexibility) makes economic sense and may not violate a reasonable expectation of [[net neutrality]].

=== Economic motivations ===
ISPs have been increasingly investing in the infrastructure necessary to transport the bits and packets that correspond to commercially successful content and services.&lt;ref name=autogenerated9 /&gt; As the [[Internet]] becomes more capable of covering most converged services, and those services require wide bandwidth, high QoS guarantees, and time-sensitivity, ISPs must make substantial investments to the network.&lt;ref name=autogenerated11 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Madden|first=Mary|title=The Audience for Online Video-Sharing Sites Shoots Up.|url=http://www.pewinternet.org/Reports/2009/13--The-Audience-for-Online-VideoSharing-Sites-Shoots-Up/3-Mobile-and-TV-Viewing/Americans-who-have-cut-back-on-expenses-are-more-likely-to-watch-online-video-on-their-televisions.aspx|publisher=Pew Internet &amp; American Life Project|access-date=23 April 2012|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120713060708/http://www.pewinternet.org/Reports/2009/13--The-Audience-for-Online-VideoSharing-Sites-Shoots-Up/3-Mobile-and-TV-Viewing/Americans-who-have-cut-back-on-expenses-are-more-likely-to-watch-online-video-on-their-televisions.aspx|archive-date=13 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, at the early stage of the Internet's appearance, ISPs were able to concentrate on “connectivity” over “cost” because the government supported the development of the Internet. However, as this support has been removed and ISPs have sought to recoup their investment, cost recovery has become substantially more important to ISPs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Leiner|first=Barry|title=Brief History of the Internet|url=http://www.internetsociety.org/internet/internet-51/history-internet/brief-history-internet|publisher=Internet society 20 years|access-date=23 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, [[incumbent carrier]]s like AT&amp;T, whose business involves both the Internet and telephony service, needed the new powerful source of revenue because traditional telephony became less profitable and its market share declined.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; In this situation, the incumbent carriers recognize that the significant profits accrued by Internet content and application providers such as [[Google]] can bring carriers the new revenue streams they are seeking. Accordingly, some of the major ISPs believe that the best way to achieve their goals is through the partitioning of network bandwidth and the prioritizing of bitstreams by offering different QoS.&lt;ref name=autogenerated10 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt; Likewise, some researchers argue that these strategies could work, emphasizing that ISPs should have unregulated pricing freedom, which may lead to promoted innovation, risk tasking, and diverse services and features.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Hazlett|first=Thomas|title=Neutering the net|url=http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/2/392ad708-b837-11da-bfc5-0000779e2340.html#axzz1sov6yyRz|access-date=23 April 2012|newspaper=Financial Times|date=Mar 20, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Yoo pointed out that ISPs could offer undropped packets and timely packet delivery even under truly congested conditions when they have the option of offering a premium peak service.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Professor Lawrence Lessig also indicates that consumer-tiering, which provides end users with different throughput speeds or permissible volume of traffic, could recoup infrastructure investments and create the necessary incentives for increased investment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lessig|first=Lawrence|title=TESTIMONY OF LAWRENCE LESSIG C. WENDELL AND EDITH M. CARLSMITH PROFESSOR OF LAW STANFORD LAW SCHOOL. HEARING ON "NETWORK NEUTRALITY"|url=http://commerce.senate.gov/pdf/lessig-020706.pdf|publisher=SENATE COMMITTEE ON COMMERCE, SCIENCE AND TRANSPORTATION|access-date=23 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Political motivations ===
As the FCC has perceived the need to create more incentives for incumbent carriers to invest in broadband, the commission has taken apart the access requirements and pricing model that force incumbent carriers to offer services at a low rate through the [[Telecommunications Act of 1996]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; In addition, the FCC has removed the traditional regulatory burdens for common carriers that provide Internet access and services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Appropriate Framework for Broadband Access to the Internet over Wireline Facilities|url=http://hraunfoss.fcc.gov/edocs_public/attachmatch/FCC-05-150A1.doc|publisher=FCC|access-date=23 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; These deregulatory initiatives have freed the carriers of having to share and interconnect facilities providing information services. Some proponents of net bias argue that ISPs do not have legal obligation to operate as [[common carrier]]s and that the network's interconnection arrangements result from commercial necessity.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt; Moreover, in terms of establishing the network's interconnection, ISPs argue that they used their resources to maintain and upgrade the network for customers, and so far popular websites have received a “free ride” from these resources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bandyopadhyay|first=S.|author2=Guo, H. |author3=Cheng, H. |title=Subsidizing Creativity through Network Design: Zero-Pricing and Net Neutrality|journal=Journal of Economic Perspectives|year=2009|volume=23|issue=3|pages=61–67|ssrn=1422061|doi=10.1257/jep.23.3.61}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Waldmeir|first=Patti|title=The Net Neutrality Dogfight that is Shaking Up Cyberspace|url=http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/76d85cb6-ba11-11da-9d02-0000779e2340,Authorised=false.html?_i_location=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.ft.com%2Fcms%2Fs%2F0%2F76d85cb6-ba11-11da-9d02-0000779e2340.html&amp;_i_referer=#axzz1sov6yyRz|access-date=23 April 2012|newspaper=Financial Times|date=Mar 23, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advocates of net bias also propose lawful [[pricing]]. Network flexibility for pricing, interconnection, and QoS characterize the initiatives as lawful [[price discrimination]] that can provide consumers with greater flexibility and potentially lower bills for low-volume users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sidak|first=Gregory|title=Testimony of J. Gregory Sidak Visiting Professor of Law Georgetown University Law Center|url=http://commerce.senate.gov/pdf/sidak-020706.pdf|publisher=Testimony of [[J. Gregory Sidak]] Visiting Professor of Law Georgetown University Law Center|access-date=23 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advocates of net bias also argue that combining simple routing with superior service offers options that are no different from the multiple classes of service provided by most airlines or the qualitative difference between free and toll highways.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; Consequently, some experts contend that the option of offering network flexibility provides a means for consumers and carriers to utilize premium services.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;

===Internet censorship===
{{main|Internet censorship}}
The concept of [[freedom of information]] has emerged in response to state sponsored monitoring, surveillance, and censorship of the [[Internet]]. Internet censorship includes the control or suppression of publishing or accessing information on the [[Internet]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}} Data discrimination may also occur on a national level to [[Censorship|censor]] political, 'immoral' or religious Internet content.{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}}

For example, [[Internet censorship in the People's Republic of China|China]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opennetinitiative.net/studies/china/ONI_China_Country_Study.pdf] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080227034922/http://www.opennetinitiative.net/studies/china/ONI_China_Country_Study.pdf|date=February 27, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Saudi Arabia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opennetinitiative.net/studies/saudi/ONI_Saudi_Arabia_Country_Study.pdf] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080228013402/http://www.opennetinitiative.net/studies/saudi/ONI_Saudi_Arabia_Country_Study.pdf|date=February 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; both filter content on the Internet, preventing access to certain types of websites. [[Singapore]] has network blocks on more than 100 sites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.opennetinitiative.net/studies/singapore/#toc2a |title=Internet Filtering in Singapore in 2004-2005: A Country Study |date=August 2005 |publisher=OpenNet Initiative |access-date=2018-07-28 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150318053014/http://www.opennetinitiative.net/studies/singapore/#toc2a |archive-date=2015-03-18 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[UK|Britain]], telecommunication companies block access to websites that depict  [[child pornography|sexually explicit images of children]]. In the [[United Arab Emirates]] {{as of|2006|lc=y}}, [[Skype]] was being blocked. &lt;!-- is it still? ---&gt; In [[Norway]], some ISPs use a voluntary filter to censor websites that the police (Kripos) believe to contain images of abuse of children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.openrightsgroup.org/2006/10/26/uknof5-richard-clayton-content-filtering/ |title=UKNOF5: Richard Clayton - Content Filtering |last=Charman |first=Suw |date=2006-10-26 |publisher=Open Rights Group |access-date=2018-07-28 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080516041904/http://www.openrightsgroup.org/2006/10/26/uknof5-richard-clayton-content-filtering/ |archive-date=2008-05-16 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Germany]] also blocks foreign sites for copyright and other reasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Internet Censorship in Germany |url=http://odem.org/informationsfreiheit/en/presse.html |publisher=Online-Demonstrations-Plattform |date=April 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the U.S., public institutions (e.g. libraries and schools), by law, block material that is related to the exploitation of children, and 'obscene and pornographic' material, unless they do not receive funding. The network filters also block sites and material relating to women's health, gay and lesbian rights groups, and sexual
education for teenagers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://deibert.citizenlab.org/Circ_guide.pdf |title=EVERYONE'S GUIDE TO BY-PASSING INTERNET CENSORSHIP FOR CITIZENS WORLDWIDE |access-date=November 28, 2008 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081029085950/http://deibert.citizenlab.org/Circ_guide.pdf |archive-date=October 29, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ifea.net/cipa.pdf {{Bare URL PDF|date=March 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Concerns regarding discrimination ==
The Internet has been historically regarded as an open and “best effort” network. Internet routers must forward packets on a first-come, first-served basis without regard for the analysis of data or content inside the packet.&lt;ref name=autogenerated11 /&gt; This aspect of the Internet has increased its value, contributing not only to the quality of our lives, but also to economic growth around the globe.&lt;ref name=autogenerated10 /&gt; Based on these notions, forms of net bias have created some concerns regarding discrimination from economic and political perspectives.&lt;ref name=autogenerated13 /&gt; In other words, unreasonable net bias occurs when an ISP conducts a discrimination strategy against a specific type of packet without a reasonable and fair financial or operational justification.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;

=== Concerns about economic discrimination ===
Users enjoy the high level of value when they are able to access the Internet on an unmetered and [[Flat rate|flat-rate]] basis.&lt;ref name=autogenerated10 /&gt; Users can also obtain attractive content subsidized by advertisers who employ the flat-rate subscription option by adding to the downloaded packet payload.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; This value proposition provides users with the benefits of the Internet, emphasizing connectivity with less regard for cost-related concerns. Likewise, the positive [[network effect]] — which refers to the process whereby more and more people adopt a service or buy a good, and as a result users receive enjoyable benefits and additional users are attracted to the Internet — created by the spread of the Internet is substantially beneficial.&lt;ref name=autogenerated12&gt;{{cite book|last=Crandall|first=R.|title=Broadband communications|year=2005|publisher=Handbook of Telecommunications Economics|pages=156–190}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Internet, interlinking hundreds and thousands of networks reduces [[transaction cost]]s and brings a flood of free information to subscribers.&lt;ref name=autogenerated12 /&gt; However, if major ISPs can freely block and degrade specific traffic streams, there would be societal losses as the Internet becomes more expensive and less productive. Proponents of net bias contend that market-based Internet access achieves efficient outcomes, such as creating innovation incentives for ISPs to invest in building and expanding networks. Nevertheless, opponents of net bias claim that allowing price and service discrimination may ruin the value of the Internet and enable ISPs to shut out competitors or other stakeholders who are unwilling or unable to pay surcharges.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; In other words, when large or powerful ISPs place a disproportionate financial burden on small and less financially sound ISPs and their subscribers by using forms of net bias like [[Block (Internet)|port blocking]] or [[tiered service]]s, they may exacerbate the [[digital divide]] that separates people with easy and robust Internet service access opportunities from those without.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=REGULATORY REFORM AS A TOOL FOR BRIDGING THE DIGITAL DIVIDE|url=http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/40/11/34487084.pdf|publisher=OECD|access-date=22 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; One consumer group, [[Free Press (organization)|Free Press]], calls attention to a number of disadvantages that specialized services ([[tiered service]]s) may produce. This organization argues that any form of prioritization on the open Internet would bring enormous disadvantages in terms of innovation, competition, investment, consumer choice, and [[free speech]] because this permission may enable ISPs to choose specific content/applications with respect to their own interests and thereby destroy the nature and value of the today's open Internet. Free Press cautions that specialized services will result in unbalanced and unparalleled economic growth, which is utterly against the public interest.&lt;ref name=autogenerated8&gt;{{cite web|last=Free Press|title=Comments of Free Press Regarding Further Inquiry|url=http://apps.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/view?id=7020916539|publisher=FCC|access-date=22 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Viewpoint of Pro-discrimination advocates====
While a broad presumption pertaining to data discrimination is perceived censorship, those in favor of this practice claim that there are benefits.  The ISPs are a business, and as such, “…correctly state that external, non-market driven constraints on their ability to price discriminate can adversely impact their incentive to invest in broadband infrastructure and their ability to recoup that investment.”&lt;ref name="Frieden"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Frieden|first=R|title=A Primer on Network Neutrality|journal=[[Intereconomics]]|volume=43|year=2008|issue=43|pages=4–15|doi=10.1007/s10272-008-0237-z|hdl=10419/42030|s2cid=189843638|hdl-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;  There are times when it could make sense, in the eyes of the ISPs, to give preference to one type of content over another.  For example, loading a plain text and image website is not nearly as strenuous as loading sites such as Hulu and YouTube.  Frieden states that “Some Internet Service Providers (ISPs) seek to diversify the Internet by prioritizing bitstreams and by offering different quality of service guarantees. To some observers, this strategy constitutes harmful discrimination that violates a tradition of network neutrality in the switching, routing, and transmission of Internet traffic.”&lt;ref name="Frieden" /&gt; While the QoS argument is that network neutrality rules make allowances for network owners to practice some types of discrimination to protect the functioning of the network.&lt;ref name="Bagwell" /&gt;

====Argument Against Data Discrimination====
Those  who oppose data discrimination say that it hurts the growth of the Internet, as well as the economy that is rooted in the depths of the Internet model.  “Instead of promoting competition, such picking of winners and losers will stifle the investment needed to perpetuate the Internet's phenomenal growth, hurting the economy.“&lt;ref name="Transcript" /&gt;
If, for example, telecommunication network operators blocked data 
packets of Voice-over-IP services that might substitute their own telephone services, this would not only discriminate against specific firms but also reduce competition and economic welfare. Technically, this would not be a problem. Although data packets are homogeneous with respect to switching and transmission treatment, type, source, and destination can be revealed and data packets be handled differently if a network operator prefers to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kruse|first=Jorn|title=Network Neutrality and Quality of Service|journal=Intereconomics|volume=43|date=Jan–Feb 2008|pages=25–30|id={{ProQuest|211594195}}|doi=10.1007/s10272-008-0242-2|hdl=10419/42050|s2cid=153571925|hdl-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Another problem is that the type of data that is given preferential treatment is up to the discretion of the ISP.  This allows them to move data as they see fit, whether it be through a political, moral, any other such kind of "lens".  This goes against the first amendment, the freedom of speech because by stopping certain kinds of information from reaching the end user, they are censoring content.  It is not the place of the ISP to censor content from the people.

The real threat to an open Internet is at the local network (the ends), where network owners can block information coming in from the inter-network, but it also is at the local network where the most harm can occur. Because of this, network neutrality rules allow some discrimination by the local network to protect itself, though it may not be based on content or type of application. For example, network owners want to protect their networks from being damaged. So, some discrimination is allowed to "prevent physical harm to the local Broadband Network caused by any network attachment or network usage." This means that local network operators may not control which types of applications users choose to employ, what type of devices users use to access the network, or which type of legal content users choose to convey or consume. The only allowable restrictions are on applications that cause harm to the local network.&lt;ref name="Bagwell" /&gt;

Proponents of network neutrality concede that network security is crucial enough to warrant making an exception to a network neutrality rule. Allowing network providers to deviate from neutrality only to the extent necessary to protect network trustworthiness is rooted in judicial and regulatory decisions and administrative rules that helped establish the principle of nondiscrimination as the core of network neutrality.&lt;ref name="Burstein"&gt;{{cite book|last=Burstein|first=Aaron|title=Trustworthiness as a Limitation on Network Neutrality|year=2009|publisher=Federal Communications Law Journal|pages=591–623|id={{ProQuest|213153514}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Sen. Al Franken has spoken out on FCC rulings “calling net neutrality the 'free speech issue of our time,'” Franken (D-MN) expressed his displeasure with the FCC's recent net neutrality rules. ‘These rules are not strong enough,' he said, pointing out that paid prioritization was not banned and that wireless networks are allowed to discriminate at will. The rules mark the ‘first time the FCC has ever allowed discrimination on the Internet’ and they ‘will create essentially two Internets.’&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Anderson|first=Nate|title=Comcast Is Trying To Whack Netflix: Sen Al Franken.|url=https://www.wired.com/epicenter/2011/01/comcast-is-trying-to-whack-netflix-sen-al-franken/|magazine=Wired|access-date=8 Feb 2011|date=2011-01-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another important concept for marketers to understand is that of disparate impact. If a discrimination case is brought against your company, the plaintiff would have to show evidence of disparate impact.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.madmarketer.com/topics/digital/articles/419740-data-discrimination-dark-side-big-data.htm|title=Data Discrimination: The Dark Side of Big Data|website=www.madmarketer.com|language=en|access-date=2017-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Concerns about political discrimination ===
In 2005, the FCC issued a Broadband Policy Statement (also known as the Internet Policy Statement) that offered guidance and insight into its approach to the Internet and broadband consistent with Congress’ direction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Policy Statement|url=http://hraunfoss.fcc.gov/edocs_public/attachmatch/FCC-05-151A1.pdf|publisher=FCC|access-date=22 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  (FCC) The four principles of this statement are as follows:

:*To encourage broadband deployment and preserve and promote the open and interconnected nature of the public Internet, consumers are entitled to access the lawful Internet content of their choice.

:*To encourage broadband deployment and preserve and promote the open and interconnected nature of the public Internet, consumers are entitled to run applications and use services of their choice, subject to the needs of law enforcement.

:*To encourage broadband deployment and preserve and promote the open and interconnected nature of the public Internet, consumers are entitled to connect their choice of legal devices that do not harm the network.

:*To encourage broadband deployment and preserve and promote the open and interconnected nature of the public Internet, consumers are entitled to competition among network providers, application and service providers, and content providers.

At first glance, these principles appear noncontroversial in terms of standards regarding the freedom of the network. However, these principles do not address regulations with respect to the issues of differentiations in pricing, interconnection, and QoS.&lt;ref name=autogenerated11 /&gt; Further, the unregulated forms of net bias have the potential to create false congestion by the ISPs.&lt;ref name=autogenerated9 /&gt; More specifically, advanced Internet protocol technology can allow ISPs to fabricate congestion and drop packets when no real congestion takes place. In addition, existing peering and transit agreements between stakeholders such as small and large ISPs may lack a specific prohibition of deliberate packet loss.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;

Many ISPs contend that major content providers such as [[Google]] or [[Yahoo!]] enjoy a [[Free rider problem|free ride]]. [[AT&amp;T]], one of the major ISPs, stated that the current standard procedure for Internet pricing and interconnection has left the company burdened with having to create, maintain, and frequently upgrade an expensive bit transport infrastructure whereas content providers do not have to do the same.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=At SBC, It's All About "Scale and Scope"|url=http://www.freepress.net/news/14959|publisher=Free Press|access-date=23 April 2012|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120314003726/http://www.freepress.net/news/14959|archive-date=14 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Rob Frieden points out that the ISPs’ practices of net bias, as they are based on a “free rider” consideration, may violate the principles of network freedom or even the peering and transit agreement between ISPs. Based on existing peering and transit agreements made by AT&amp;T, Google is allowed to have its traffic delivered to AT&amp;T subscribers free of charge, and AT&amp;T is compensated for the traffic from other ISPs by the agreements.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated13 /&gt; Moreover, if AT&amp;T penalizes Google's traffic from the various forms of net bias, it would jeopardize the principles of network freedom as well as violate its contractual commitment to its peers and transit customers who have paid for best efforts access to AT&amp;T's networks.

Technical and market convergence as well as deregulation by the [[Telecommunications Act of 1996]] provided incentives for companies to integrate vertically and horizontally. As a result, those integrated companies have discrimination incentives such that they may try port blocking or unfair throttling to enhance the marketplace attractiveness of corporate affiliates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Guo|first=H.|author2=Bandyopadhyay, S. |author3=Cheng, H.K. |author4=Yang, Y. |title=Net Neutrality and Vertical Integration of Content and Broadband Services|year=2009|series=Warrington College of Business Administration Working Paper Series}}&lt;/ref&gt; From this perspective, Free Press emphasized through its comments to the FCC Notice of Inquiry that specialized services should be provided with fairness, particularly in the vertically integrated environments of the information and telecommunication industry (e.g., Comcast, which has both content and broadband services).&lt;ref name=autogenerated8 /&gt; Consequently, concerns regarding discrimination raised the need of network neutrality regulations to preserve the open Internet and public interest and enable the Internet industry to survive and succeed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Shrimali|first=G.|title=Surplus extraction by network providers: Implications for net neutrality and innovation|journal=Telecommunications Policy|year=2008|volume=32|issue=8|pages=545–558|doi=10.1016/j.telpol.2008.06.005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Knieps|first=G.|title=Market Driven Network Neutrality and the Fallacies of Internet Traffic Quality Regulation|journal= International Telecommunications Policy Review|year=2011|volume=18|issue=3|pages=1–22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The FCC and Data Discrimination==
In the United States, the [[Federal Communications Commission]] does not permit data discrimination except for "reasonable traffic management."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nbcnews.com/id/22560491|title=FCC to probe Comcast data discrimination|first=Peter |last=Svensson|date=Jan 2008|publisher=NBC News|access-date=2008-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Federal Communication Commission defines reasonable traffic management as follows:
&lt;blockquote&gt;A network management practice is reasonable if it is appropriate and tailored to achieving a legitimate network management purpose, taking into account the particular network architecture and technology of the broadband Internet access service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.fcc.gov/Daily_Releases/Daily_Business/2010/db1223/FCC-10-201A1.pdf|title=In the Matter of Preserving the Open Internet Broadband Industry Practices|page=48|author=Federal Communications Commission|date=December 23, 2010|access-date=2011-03-02|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110218175730/http://www.fcc.gov/Daily_Releases/Daily_Business/2010/db1223/FCC-10-201A1.pdf|archive-date=February 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

It is considered unreasonable for internet service providers to manage traffic by blocking applications or assigning quality of service based on source, destination, or unreasonable application provider payment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.ics.uci.edu/~sjordan/papers/tprc09.pdf |title=How to determine whether a traffic management practice is reasonable |first=Jordan |last=Scott |date=September 2009 |publisher=TPRC |access-date=2011-02-27 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120128013929/http://www.ics.uci.edu/~sjordan/papers/tprc09.pdf |archive-date=2012-01-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Regardless, there are currently no laws prohibiting internet service providers from offering different service plans that may restrict consumers' access to selected material.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.scribd.com/doc/29489974/Full-Text-Comcast-vs-FCC-Federal-Court-Ruling|title=Full Text Comcast vs FCC Federal Court Ruling|date=April 2010|access-date=2011-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2007 the [[Federal Trade Commission]] (FTC) published ''Broadband Connectivity Competition Policy'' which suggested that it may be beneficial to consumers if [[broadband]] providers would pursue a variety of business arrangements, including data prioritization, exclusive deals, and vertical integration into online content and applications. The report also suggests that government should move cautiously in implementing any changes to current regulations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Plunkett's Telecommunications Industry Almanac 2009 |last= Plunkett|first=Jack W. |year=2008 |publisher= Plunkett Research|isbn=978-1-59392-141-5 |page=208|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6PUiN5cE7-QC&amp;q=%22data+prioritization%22+network+neutrality}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===FCC Appeals===
* Verizon Communications filed an appeal against the FCC in the United States Court of Appeals for the DC Circuit on January 20, 2011. The FCC's rules aim to prevent Internet service providers from blocking certain websites or applications. Verizon's appeal claims that the FCC has overstepped its authority and that the rules violate the company's constitutional rights. The company says that the net neutrality rules modify the terms of existing licenses held by Verizon. Rather than launching a lawsuit that directly challenges the regulations, the company is appealing the rules as an illegal change to their existing licenses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tpmdc.talkingpointsmemo.com/2011/01/verizons-net-neutrality-challenge-claims-it-violates-their-licenses.php |title=Verizon's Net Neutrality Challenge Claims It Violates Their Licenses |date=2011-01-21 |publisher=TalkingPointsMemo.com | access-date=2011-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
**“It has been a very long and drawn out fight, and it has certainly distracted the FCC for the last year. It has distracted the carriers as well, who have spent a lot of time, effort and money in terms of publicly fighting about it and privately fighting about it," says Larry Downes an industry consultant and author..."It is very, very unlikely that AT&amp;T will file suit," said Downes. "They've said publicly and repeatedly that they are comfortable with the net neutrality order and I take that as a pretty strong indication that they are not going to litigate it."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Marcus|first=Stephanie|title=AT&amp;T, Sprint, T-Mobile Unlikely To Challenge Net Neutrality.|url=http://tpmdc.talkingpointsmemo.com/2011/01/att-sprint-t-mobile-unlikely-to-challenge-net-neutrality.php|publisher=TalkingPointsMemo.com|access-date=9 Feb 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Evidence of Anti-competitiveness===
During a hearing held by Rep. Greg Walden, one of the speakers put forth a question that needs to be addressed by the FCC, as well as other groups that are in support of Net Neutrality.  The speaker said, "If the mere threat of Internet discrimination is such a concern and if the FCC has done no analysis to demonstrate why one company has more market power than another, why would discrimination by companies like Google or Skype be any more acceptable than discrimination by companies like AT&amp;T and Comcast?"&lt;ref name="Transcript"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Walden|first=Greg|title=REP. GREG WALDEN HOLDS A HEARING ON NETWORK NEUTRALITY/INTERNET REGULATION.|journal=Political Transcript Wire|date=February 2011|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  During the same hearing, a different member spoke up and quoted Section 230 of the Communications Act saying, "...preserve the vibrant and competitive free market that presently exists for the Internet and other interactive computer services, unfettered by federal or state regulations." essentially saying that there should be laws in place so that the government knows how to handle its authority over the FCC and ISPs.  He did not say that these laws are not laws meant for regulating what the FCC does, but how the FCC ''should'' act.&lt;ref name="Transcript" /&gt;

In 2005, a small North Carolina telecom company, Madison River Communications, blocked their [[DSL]] customers from using the Vonage VoIP service. Service was restored after the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) intervened and entered into a consent decree that had Madison River pay a fine of $15,000.&lt;ref&gt;http://hraunfoss.fcc.gov/edocs_public/attachmatch/DA-05-543A2.pdf {{Bare URL PDF|date=March 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this case, the FCC investigated allegations that Madison River violated nondiscriminatory obligations contained in the Communications Act, but the redefinition of broadband as an information service dramatically reduces the authority of regulators to deter this kind of competitive misconduct.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Network neutrality: Competition, innovation, and nondiscriminatory access : hearing before the Task Force on Telecom and Antitrust on of the Committee on the Judiciary, House of Representatives, One Hundred Ninth Congress, second session|year=2006|publisher=Washington: U.S. G.P.O.|url=http://commdocs.house.gov/committees/judiciary/hju27225.000/hju27225_0.HTM}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As Anti-Piracy
* “Network-level filtering means your Internet service provider – Comcast, AT&amp;T, EarthLink, or whoever you send that monthly check to – could soon start sniffing your digital packets, looking for material that infringes on someone’s copyright. “What we are already doing to address piracy hasn’t been working. There’s no secret there...""&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Stone|first=Brad|title=att-and-other-isps-may-be-getting-ready-to-filter|url=http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/01/08/att-and-other-isps-may-be-getting-ready-to-filter|work=New York Times|date=2008-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This may be one of the major reasons that ISPs want to be able to discriminate against certain data types.  Ever since the dawn of peer-to-peer file sharing, both the MPAA and the RIAA have been hounding ISPs to divulge any and all information relating to file sharing.  With the implementation of data discrimination, that file sharing data can be, and will be, thrown to the bottom of the pecking order.  This will render any kind of sharing, even the kind that isn't deemed illegal, useless because the transfer speeds will be unusably slow.
* Center of Digital Democracy (CDD) conducts a study which finds out several internet service providers (ISP) offer advertising companies specific packages for users personal information.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.truth-out.org/news/item/38721-digital-redlining-how-internet-service-providers-promote-poverty|title=Digital Redlining: How Internet Service Providers Promote Poverty|last=Tveten|first=Julianne|website=Truthout|language=en-us|access-date=2018-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples==
Worldwide, the [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]] application is widely given reduced bandwidth or even in some cases blocked entirely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Adam |last=Livingstone |title=BitTorrent: Shedding no tiers |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/newsnight/5017542.stm |work=Newsnight |publisher=BBC |date=2006-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Worldwide, under heavy attack from [[spam e-mail]], many e-mail servers no longer accept connections except from [[Whitelist|white-listed]] hosts. While few care about the rights of spammers, this means that legitimate hosts not on the list are often blocked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Paul |last=Elosegui |title=Email Delivery Neutrality Gone Forever |url=http://blog.eucap.com/network-neutrality/email_neutrality_gone_forever.html |publisher=EUCAP |date=2006-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Save The Internet]], an advocacy organization led by [[Free Press (organization)|Free Press]], is documenting situations in which ISPs have engaged in data discrimination.
* In 2005, Canadian telephone giant [[Telus]] blocked access to voices-for-change.ca, a website supporting the company's labour union during a labour dispute, as well as over 600 other websites, for about sixteen hours after pictures were posted on the website of employees crossing the picket line.&lt;ref name="CBC News"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2005/07/24/telus-sites050724.html?print|title=Telus cuts subscriber access to pro-union website|date=2005-07-24|publisher=CBC News|access-date=2006-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In April 2006, [[Time Warner]]'s AOL ([[America On Line]]) blocked all e-mails that mentioned &lt;nowiki&gt;www.dearaol.com&lt;/nowiki&gt;, an advocacy campaign opposing the company's pay-to-send e-mail scheme. An AOL spokesman called the issue an unintentional glitch.&lt;ref name="ZDNet News"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.zdnet.com/2100-9595_22-6061089.html |title=AOL charged with blocking opponents' e-mail |date=2006-04-13 |publisher=ZDNet News |access-date=2006-07-10 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060617200037/http://news.zdnet.com/2100-9595_22-6061089.html |archive-date=2006-06-17 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In February 2006, some of [[Cox Cable]]'s customers were unable to access [[Craigslist]] because of a confluence of a software bug in the Authentium personal firewall distributed by Cox Cable to improve customers' security and the way that Craigslist had their servers misconfigured. Save the Internet said this was an intentional act on the part of Cox Cable to protect classified ad services offered by its partners. The issue was resolved by correction of the software as well as a change in the network configuration used by Craig's List. Craig's List founder [[Craig Newmark]] stated that he believed the blocking was unintentional.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Silicon Valley Watcher|url=http://www.siliconvalleywatcher.com/mt/archives/2006/06/craigslist_is_b.php}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In August 2007, [[Comcast]] was found to be preventing or at least severely delaying uploads on [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]].&lt;ref&gt;TorrentFreak. [http://torrentfreak.com/comcast-throttles-bittorrent-traffic-seeding-impossible/ Comcast Throttles BitTorrent Traffic, Seeding Impossible] August 17, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; These claims were verified in October by the EFF&lt;ref&gt;EFF,[https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2007/10/eff-tests-agree-ap-comcast-forging-packets-to-interfere|EFF tests agree with AP: Comcast is forging packets to interfere with user traffic], OCTOBER 19TH, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; and Associated Press.&lt;ref&gt;Svensson, Peter, and AP T. Writer. "Comcast Blocks some Subscriber Internet Traffic, AP Testing shows." The Associated Press October 20, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In September 2007, Verizon Wireless prevented a pro-choice organization from sending text messages to its members coordinating a public demonstration, despite the fact that the intended recipients had explicitly signed up to receive such messages.&lt;ref name="NYT September"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4D7133EF934A1575AC0A9619C8B63|title=Verizon Rejects Text Messages For Abortion Rights Group|date=2007-09-27|work=New York Times | first=Adam | last=Liptak | access-date=2010-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On February 4, 2010, [[Verizon Wireless]] blocked [[4chan]], an English language imageboard from being accessed by its customers. A few days later, on February 7, 2010, Verizon Wireless confirmed that 4chan had been "explicitly blocked", offering no explanation. The block was lifted a few days later.&lt;ref name="Wireless Federation"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://wirelessfederation.com/news/21888-verizon-wireless-restores-4chan-traffic-2/|title=Verizon Wireless restores 4chan traffic|date=2010-02-04|publisher=Wireless Federation | access-date=2010-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--This sounds like an essay --&gt;
*In a March 2009 Freedom House report on Internet and digital media censorship worldwide, Egypt scored a 45 (out of 100), slightly worse than Turkey but better than Russia. Cuba scored a 90, making it more Net-censored than even Iran, China and Tunisia. Cellphone service is too expensive for most Cubans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=O'Grady|first=Mary|title=Will Cuba Be the Next Egypt?|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424052748704709304576124591746057376|newspaper=The Wall Street Journal|access-date=9 Feb 2011|date=2011-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Comcast Corp. actively interferes with attempts by some of its high-speed Internet subscribers to share files online, a move that runs counter to the tradition of treating all types of Net traffic equally. The interference, which The Associated Press confirmed through nationwide tests, is the most drastic example yet of data discrimination by a U.S. Internet service provider. It involves company computers masquerading as those of its users. Comcast's interference appears to be an aggressive way of managing its network to keep file-sharing traffic from swallowing too much bandwidth and affecting the Internet speeds of other subscribers.&lt;ref name=ComcastBlocks/&gt;
**If widely applied by other ISPs, the technology Comcast is using would be a crippling blow to the BitTorrent, eDonkey and Gnutella file-sharing networks. While these are mainly known as sources of copyright music, software and movies, BitTorrent in particular is emerging as a legitimate tool for quickly disseminating legal content.&lt;ref name=ComcastBlocks/&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}
{{Biases}}

[[Category:Net neutrality]]
[[Category:Media bias]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>