<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20060906012720|74050650" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1840508" pageid="1840508" ns="0" title="Prisoner abuse"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-09-29T13:26:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{CriminTheo}}{{abuse}}

{{POV-check}}

'''Prisoner abuse''' is the mistreatment of persons while they are under arrest or incarcerated.
Abuse falling into this category includes:
* Physical abuse: Needless beating, hitting, or other [[Corporal punishment]].
* Psychological abuse: Taunting, sleep depravation, or other forms of [[Psychological abuse]].
* Sexual abuse: Forced intercourse, genital mutilation, or other forms of [[Sexual abuse]].
* Other abuse: Refusal of essential medication, humiliation, etc.
* [[Torture]]: any act by which severe pain, whether physical or [[Psychology|psychological]], is intentionally inflicted

==Allegations of prisoner abuse by the U.S. military==

Abuse of prisoners is considered a crime in the [[United States]] [[Uniform Code of Military Justice]].

Allegations have been made that U.S. or [[Multinational force in Iraq|Coalition]] guards routinely abused prisoners at the [[Abu Ghraib prison]] - even [[torture]]d them.

Regarding prisoners held at the [[Guantanamo Bay detainment camp|Guantanamo Bay]], Rep. Duncan Hunter, chairman of the House Armed Services Committee, has shown food that is similar to what is served there, "purchased for them by American taxpayers" - in order to dispel allegations that the prisoners had been abused or tortured.

According to Hunter, "They've never eaten better. They've never been treated better. We don't beat them. We don't touch them. We've been treating people well." [http://ap.washingtontimes.com/dynamic/stories/C/CONGRESS_GUANTANAMO?SITE=DCTMS&amp;SECTION=HOME]

== External links ==
* [http://tortureprotest.org/atrocities/guantanamo_bay Details of prisoner abuse] at [[Guantanamo Bay detainment camp|Guantanamo Bay]]
* [http://tortureprotest.org/blog/?permalink=18 United States Military Redefines Torture]

[[Category:Penology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>