<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191107054625|924999101" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1840508" pageid="1840508" ns="0" title="Prisoner abuse"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-14T11:58:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=July 2012}}
{{Criminology and penology |penology}}

'''Prisoner abuse''' is the mistreatment of persons while they are under arrest or incarcerated, therefore deprived of the [[right of self-defense]] against acting authorities and generally defenseless in actual fact.

Abuse falling into this category includes:
* [[Physical abuse]]: Illicit beating and hitting, unlawful [[corporal punishment]], [[stress position]]s, excessive or prolonged [[physical restraints|physical restraining]], etc.
* [[Psychological abuse]]: [[Verbal abuse]], [[sleep deprivation]], [[white noise]], pointless/absurd or [[humiliation|humiliating]] instructions, recurrent exhaustive [[inspection]]s and [[Police raid|shakedowns]], arbitrary [[strip search]]es, denuding actions, exposure, etc.
* [[Sexual abuse]]: excessive [[body cavity search|vaginal or rectal contraband searches]] or other not indicated internal checks, [[prison rape|forced sexual intercourse]], forced insertion of objects into vagina or rectum, arbitrary [[strip search]]es and other forms of forced denudation (sexual abuse is thematically widely overlapping with psychological and physical abuse.) 
** [[Strip search]]es: The experience of a forced strip search can be experienced as a traumatic event similarly to that of [[rape]] especially by female prisoners. The prevalence of [[CCTV]] in prisons and the generally indiscreet nature of strip searches, with often a number of guards observing, can add to the experienced humiliation. Strip searches are often arbitrarily used under various pretences, when the actual ambition is to assert control or to intimidate the subjected prison inmates&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.aclu.org/blog/smart-justice/mass-incarceration/standing-against-sexual-assault-state|title=Standing Up Against Sexual Assault By the State|website=American Civil Liberties Union|language=en|access-date=2019-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;.
** [[Enema]]s: Forced enemas are commonly acknowledged as being uncomfortable and degrading for the receiving person. Such a treatment can also be registered as a form of [[physical abuse]] as well as [[sexual abuse]], if practiced against the will of the prisoner. This is usually done in order to demonstrate predominance and assert "total control" over detainees. As a consequence of this practice, [[anal fissure]]s, chronic [[Hemorrhoid|hemorrhoids]] and [[rectal prolapse]] can occur when administered excessively. Forced enemas have evidentially been used for example at the [[Guantanamo Bay detention camp]] by the United States. In certain cases it was administered under the pretence to counter a prisoner's [[dehydration]]. Forms of medical justification were employed whenever enemas were in fact used as a coercive tool. Despite the pretext of medical need, it was later admitted in certain cases, that this was in fact untrue. The [[CIA]] administered enemas to [[Khalid Sheik Mohammed]], [[Mustafa al-Hawsawi]] and [[Mohammed al-Qahtani]] among others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/01/us/fresh-details-emerge-on-harsh-methods-at-guantanamo.html?_r=0 |title=Fresh Details Emerge on Harsh Methods at Guantánamo |author=Neil A. Lewis |date=2005-01-01 |work=Archives &amp;ndash; 2005 |publisher=The [[New York Times]] |accessdate=2019-07-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title = Rectal rehydration and waterboarding: the CIA torture report's grisliest findings |url = https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2014/dec/09/cia-torture-report-worst-findings-waterboard-rectal |accessdate = 13 March 2015 |agency = [[The Guardian]] |date = 7 July 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Torture]]: any act, whether physical or psychological, which is deliberately done to inflict excruciating and agonizing pain upon a person under the actor's custody or physical control for any reason such as extracting information or punishment.
**[[Enhanced interrogation]]: a euphemism for U.S. torture methods implemented in the [[War on Terror]] purportedly needed to extract information from detainees. Examples include use of [[Stress position|stress positions]], [[sleep deprivation]], [[starvation]], [[thirst]], and [[Sexual abuse|sexual humiliation]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2014/dec/09/cia-torture-methods-waterboarding-sleep-deprivation|title=How the CIA tortured its detainees|last=Laughland|first=Oliver|date=2015-05-20|work=The Guardian|access-date=2019-10-13|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;.
* Other abuse: Refusal of essential medication, etc.&lt;ref&gt;Prisoner Abuse Law &amp; Legal Definition. ''USLegal''. Retrieved from http://definitions.uslegal.com/p/prisoner-abuse/&lt;/ref&gt;

== Psychological abuse ==
===White noise===
The endless playing of random static (similar to that of unused TV frequencies) with no pattern; this can cause extreme discomfort and disorientation.

===Verbal abuse===
Prisoners may be subject to taunting, heckling, profanity, and malicious lies by prison authorities.  Guards and other authorities may use verbal abuse as a means of frightening or demoralizing prisoners to make them more compliant, or simply out of sadism.

===Enablement of sexual violence===
Prisoners are sometimes intentionally housed with inmates known to have raped other prisoners, or protection from known rapists may be purposely withheld from the prisoners. These practices create a very high incidence of [[prison rape in the United States|rape in US prisons]], which was the topic of the 2001 report No Escape from Human Rights Watch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/reports/2001/prison/|title=No Escape: Male Rape in U.S. Prisons|author=|date=|website=www.hrw.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Plenary 2 -- Redefining Gender Violence -- Transcripts from Converge! Reimagining the Movement to End Gender Violence|ssrn = 2628984|publisher = Social Science Research Network|date = 2015-07-09|location = Rochester, NY|first = Leigh|last = Goodmark|first2 = Juanita|last2 = Flores|first3 = Julie|last3 = Goldscheid|first4 = Andrea|last4 = Ritchie|last5 = SpearIt}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Abu Ghraib torture and prisoner abuse]]
*[[Prisoner abuse in the United States]]
*[[Iraq prison abuse scandals]]
*[[Prison overcrowding]]
*[[Extermination through labor]]
*[[Penal harm]]
*[[Police misconduct]]
*[[Death in custody]]
*[[Stun belt]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*Gates, Madison L. and Robert K. Bradford. "[https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4381682/ The Impact of Incarceration on Obesity: Are Prisoners with Chronic Diseases Becoming Overweight and Obese during Their Confinement?]" ''[[Journal of Obesity]]''. 2015; 2015: 532468. Published online 2015 Mar 18. doi: [https://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2015/532468 10.1155/2015/532468].
{{abuse}}
{{Psychological manipulation}}
{{Incarceration}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Prisoner Abuse}}
[[Category:Penology]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Prison-related crime]]
[[Category:Prisoner abuse| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>