<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20240613074022|1228799258" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1840508" pageid="1840508" ns="0" title="Prisoner abuse"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-08-11T03:22:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Mistreatment of imprisoned people by authorities}}
{{more citations needed|date=July 2012}}
{{Criminology and penology |penology}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Related}}

'''Prisoner abuse''' is the mistreatment of persons while they are under [[arrest]] or [[incarcerated]]. Prisoner abuse can include [[physical abuse]], [[psychological abuse]], [[sexual abuse]], [[torture]], or other acts such as refusal of essential medication, and it can be perpetuated by either fellow inmates or prison faculty.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Prisoner Abuse Law and Legal Definition {{!}} USLegal, Inc. |url=https://definitions.uslegal.com/p/prisoner-abuse/ |access-date=2024-06-13 |website=definitions.uslegal.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Physical abuse ==

Physical abuse of prisoners includes illicit beating and hitting of prisoners, unlawful [[corporal punishment]], [[stress position]]s, and excessive or prolonged [[physical restraints|physical restraining]].
[[File:Abu Ghraib 91.jpg|right|thumb|US Military Police officer restraining and sedating prisoner, while a soldier holds him down]]
According to the ''New York Times'', along with physical abuse, prisoners are being thrown into jail for mental illnesses that they obtain and not being treated for them. This causes their issues to get worse and in some cases never get better. Also, relating to physical abuse the mentally ill can be thrown into restrained areas for a long amount of time because of their mental condition, this means that these mentally ill people do not have the resources to get better in the jail.

This is also caused by overpopulation in jails. Penal Reform International claims, that overcrowding in the main source of poor jail conditions globally. This caused overcrowding and understaffing: one of the reasons why there can sometimes be 2–3 people in the same jail cell for a long period of time. This causes a lack of privacy and because the jails are so overcrowded some minor cases are cut from the justice system altogether.

According to the Marshall Plan, there are also many gangs that are formed in different prisons which cause chaos and force the jail to go through many lockdowns which are a vulnerable time for the prison guards especially when they are understaffed. It also says that the prisoners and the prison guards have to be safe, which caused the guards to be defensive and sometimes abusive.

== Psychological abuse ==
Psychological abuse of prisoners can include [[verbal abuse]], [[sleep deprivation]], [[white noise]], pointless/absurd or [[humiliation|humiliating]] instructions, recurrent exhaustive [[inspection]]s and [[Police raid|shakedowns]], arbitrary [[strip search]]es, and denuding actions.

According to Reflexions, prison can alter people's bodily dimensions, their emotional wellbeing, and possibly change their perception for an extended amount of time. It also claims that not only does the prison environment make mental disorders worse, but it also may cause them. The type of prison environment can be cruel and if the prisoner does not have the mental, emotional, and physical willpower they will struggle very greatly.

===White noise===
The endless playing of random static (similar to that of unused TV frequencies) with no pattern; this can cause extreme discomfort and disorientation.

===Verbal abuse===
Prisoners may be subject to taunting, heckling, profanity, and malicious lies by prison authorities. Guards and other authorities may use verbal abuse as a means of frightening or demoralizing prisoners to make them more compliant, or simply out of sadism.

===Enablement of sexual violence===
Prisoners are sometimes intentionally housed with inmates known to have raped other prisoners, or protection from known rapists may be purposely withheld from the prisoners. These practices create a very high incidence of [[prison rape in the United States|rape in US prisons]], which was the topic of the 2001 report No Escape from [[Human Rights Watch]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/reports/2001/prison/|title=No Escape: Male Rape in U.S. Prisons|website=www.hrw.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Plenary 2 -- Redefining Gender Violence -- Transcripts from Converge! Reimagining the Movement to End Gender Violence|ssrn = 2628984|publisher = Social Science Research Network|date = 2015-07-09|location = Rochester, NY|first1 = Leigh|last1 = Goodmark|first2 = Juanita|last2 = Flores|first3 = Julie|last3 = Goldscheid|first4 = Andrea|last4 = Ritchie|last5 = SpearIt}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sexual abuse==
Sexual abuse is known to occur in facilities for both genders, however it is especially predominant with female prisoners. Common acts can include arbitrary and extensive [[strip search]]es as well as other forms of forced denudation beyond general necessity, excessive [[body cavity search|vaginal or rectal contraband searches]] or other internal checks including the oral cavity of a prisoner. In extreme cases even forced insertion of objects into the inmate's vagina or rectum and also [[prison rape|forced sexual intercourse]] is known to occur mostly on female detainees.

===Strip searches===
The experience of forced [[strip search]]es can be experienced as a traumatic event similarly to that of [[rape]] especially by female prisoners, especially when combined with habitual [[body cavity search]]es. The prevalence of [[CCTV]] in modern correctional facilities and the generally indiscreet nature of strip searches, often with a number of [[prison guard]]s observing, usually adds to the experienced humiliation. Strip searches are often arbitrarily used under various pretences, when the actual ambition is to assert control and predominance as well as to intimidate the subjected prison inmates.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.aclu.org/blog/smart-justice/mass-incarceration/standing-against-sexual-assault-state|title=Standing Up Against Sexual Assault By the State|website=American Civil Liberties Union|date=12 April 2012 |language=en|access-date=2019-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Torture==
Torture of prisoners includes any act, whether physical or psychological, which is deliberately done to inflict sensations of pain upon a person under the actor's custody or physical control. This form of prisoner abuse is usually exerted to extract information, but also as means of intimidation, attrition or punishment.

===Enhanced interrogation===
"Enhanced interrogation" is a euphemism for U.S. torture methods implemented in the [[War on Terror]] purportedly needed to extract information from detainees. Examples include use of [[stress position]]s, [[sleep deprivation]], [[starvation]], [[thirst]], and [[Sexual abuse|sexual humiliation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2014/dec/09/cia-torture-methods-waterboarding-sleep-deprivation|title=How the CIA tortured its detainees|last=Laughland|first=Oliver|date=2015-05-20|work=The Guardian|access-date=2019-10-13|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Right to health==
According to international laws, a State is liable to ensure prisoners' [[Right to health|right to receive health care]]. Prison authorities are fully responsible to provide proper medical treatment to the detainees and ensure their well-being.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.lrwc.org/prisoners-the-right-to-medical-treatment-international-law-provisions-report/|title=Prisoners: The Right to Medical Treatment – International Law Provisions-Report|access-date=28 March 2019|website=Lawyers’ Rights Watch Canada}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===COVID-19 pandemic===
During the [[COVID-19 pandemic]], the overcrowded Jaw prison of Bahrain witnessed a major [[COVID-19]] outbreak. Several prisoners were confirmed to be infected with the virus, while the authorities failed to facilitate them with proper preventive medical supplies, including face masks or hand sanitizers, and conducting regular screening tests. The authorities fell short of ensuring prisoners' rights to health and following the rules of treating prisoners. One of the main concerns had been the extensive population of the prison, which made [[social distancing]] impossible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2021/04/bahraini-authorities-flouting-prisoners-rights-to-health-amid-rise-in-covid-19-cases-at-jaw-prison/|title=Bahraini authorities flouting prisoners' rights to health amid rise in COVID-19 cases at Jaw prison|access-date=12 April 2021|website=Amnesty International|date=9 April 2021 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 June 2021, an inmate of Jaw prison, Husain Barakat, died due to COVID-19 complications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2021/06/bahrain-death-of-prisoner-a-warning-for-covid-19-failings-in-jaw-prison/|title=Bahrain: Death of prisoner a warning for Covid-19 failings in Jaw Prison|access-date=14 June 2022|website=Amnesty International|date=14 June 2021 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Even after the pandemic, Bahrain's Jaw prison remained controversial, where prisoners' rights of health continued to be violated. In June 2022, [[Amnesty International]] reported that Bahraini authorities failed to respond to the inmates suffering with [[tuberculosis]]. Prison authorities constantly disregarded the prisoners with symptoms and did not allow them to get tested for the airborne disease. Some of the prisoners were called back to the prison after they were confirmed of being infected in the hospital. One of the prisoners, Ahmed Jaber, was not sent to the hospital until he was semi-paralysed after being sick for 11 months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2022/06/bahrain-prison-officials-inadequate-response-to-tuberculosis-cases-in-jaw-prison-puts-prisoners-health-at-serious-risk/|title=Bahrain: Prison Officials' Inadequate Response To Tuberculosis Cases In Jaw Prison Puts Prisoners' Health At Serious Risk|access-date=9 June 2022|website=Amnesty International|date=9 June 2022 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Abu Ghraib torture and prisoner abuse]]
*[[Prisoner abuse in the United States]]
*[[Prison overcrowding]]
*[[Extermination through labor]]
*[[Penal harm]]
*[[Police misconduct]]
*[[Prisoners' rights]]
*[[Death in custody]]
*[[Stun belt]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*Gates, Madison L. and Robert K. Bradford. "[https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4381682/ The Impact of Incarceration on Obesity: Are Prisoners with Chronic Diseases Becoming Overweight and Obese during Their Confinement?]" ''[[Journal of Obesity]]''. 2015; 2015: 532468. Published online 2015 Mar 18. [[doi:10.1155/2015/532468]].

{{World topic|prefix=Prisoner abuse in|noredlinks=yes|title=Prisoner abuse by country}}
{{abuse}}
{{Psychological manipulation}}
{{Incarceration}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Prisoner abuse| ]]
[[Category:Prisoners and detainees|abuse]]
[[Category:Prison violence|abuse]]
[[Category:Torture]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>