<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091101183716|323316394" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2649767" pageid="2649767" ns="0" title="Social stigma"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-03T10:32:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Social stigma''' is severe social disapproval of personal characteristics or [[beliefs]] that are perceived to be against [[Norm (sociology)|cultural norms]]. Stigma is often based on [[ignorance]], [[irrational]] or unfounded fears, [[mass hysteria]], lack of education, or a lack of information pertaining to a particular person or group. Social stigma often leads to [[marginalization]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

Examples of existing or historical social stigmas include [[mental illness]], [[physical disabilities]] and diseases such as [[leprosy]]&lt;ref&gt;Jopling WH.  leprosy stigma.  Lepr Rev 62,1-12,1991 &lt;/ref&gt;, as well as [[illegitimacy]], skin tone or affiliation with a specific [[nationality]], [[religion]] (or lack of religion&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20070331.ATHEIST31/TPStory/TPNational/Ontario/ globeandmail.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://atheism.about.com/b/a/258950.htm Atheists Attacked in Hate Crime?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;) or being deemed to be or proclaiming oneself to be of a certain [[ethnicity]], in any of a myriad of geopolitical and corresponding sociopolitical contexts in various parts of the world. 

The perception or attribution, rightly or wrongly, of [[Crime|criminality]] carries a strong social stigma.

Stigma comes in three forms:&lt;ref&gt;Erving Goffman, ''Stigma: Notes on the Management of Spoiled Identity'', Prentice-Hall, 1963, ISBN 0-671-62244-7.&lt;/ref&gt; Firstly, overt or external deformations, such as [[scar]]s, physical manifestations of [[anorexia nervosa]], [[leprosy]] ([[leprosy stigma]]), or of a [[physical disability]] or social disability, such as [[obesity]]. Secondly, deviations in personal traits, including mental illness, [[drug addict]]ion, [[alcoholic|alcoholism]], and [[Criminal|criminal backgrounds]] are stigmatized in this way.  Thirdly, "tribal stigmas" are traits, imagined or real, of [[ethnic groups]], [[nationalities]], or religions that are deemed to constitute a deviation from what is perceived to be the prevailing normative ethnicity, nationality or religion. Stigma is generally based on [[stereotype|stereotypical]] and uninformed impressions or characterizations of a given subject. 
Although the specific social categories that become stigmatized can vary across times and places, the three basic forms of stigma (physical deformity, poor personal traits, and tribal outgroup status) are found in most cultures and time periods, leading some psychologists{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} to hypothesize that the tendency to stigmatize may have evolutionary roots.

== Link and Phelan stigmatization Model ==

Bruce Link and Jo Phelan &lt;ref&gt;Bruce G. Link and Jo C. Phelan , "Conceptualizing Stigma", Annual Review of Sociology, 2001, p.363&lt;/ref&gt; propose that stigma exists when four specific components converge.  (1) Individuals differentiate and [[Labelling|label]] human variations. (2) Prevailing cultural beliefs tie those labeled to adverse attributes. (3) Labeled individuals are placed in distinguished groups that serve to establish a sense of disconnection between “us” and “them.” (4) Labeled individuals experience “status loss and [[discrimination]]” that leads to unequal circumstances. In this model stigmatization is also contingent on “access to [[Power (sociology)|social]], [[Economic power|economic]], and [[political power]] that allows the identification of differences, construction of [[stereotype]]s, the separation of labeled persons into distinct groups, and the full execution of disapproval, [[Social rejection|rejection]], exclusion, and [[discrimination]].”  Subsequently, in this model the term stigma is applied when labeling, stereotyping, disconnection, status loss, and discrimination all exist within a power situation that facilitates stigma to occur. 

===Differentiation and labeling===

Identifying which human differences are salient, and therefore worthy of labeling, is a social process.  There are two primary factors to examine when considering the extent to which this process is a social one.  The first issue is the fact that significant oversimplification is needed to create [[Group (sociology)|groups]].  The broad groups of [[Black people|black]] and [[White people|white]], [[Homosexuality|homosexual]] and [[Heterosexuality|heterosexual]], the [[Sanity|sane]] and the [[mentally ill]]; and [[Youth|young]] and [[Old age|old]] are all examples of this.  Secondly, the differences that are socially judged to be relevant differ vastly according to time and place.  An example of this is the emphasis that was put on the size of forehead and faces of individuals in the late nineteenth century – which was believed to be an indication of a person’s degree of criminal nature.

===Linking to stereotypes===

The second component of this model centers on the linking of labeled differences with [[stereotype]]s.  [[Erving Goffman|Goffman’s]] 1963 work made this aspect of stigma prominent and it has remained so ever since.  This process of applying certain stereotypes to differentiated groups of individuals has garnered a large amount of attention and [[research]] in recent decades as it helps to understand the [[Psychology|psychological]] nature of the thought process taking place as this linkage occurs.

===Us and them===

The linking of negative attributes to differentiated groups of individuals described above facilitates a sense of separation between the proverbial “us” and “them.” This sense that the individuals of the labeled group are fundamentally different causes stereotyping to take place with little hesitation.  The "us" and "them" component of the stigmatization process implies that the labeled group is slightly less [[human]] in nature, and at the extreme not human at all.  It is at this extreme that the most horrific events occur.

===Disadvantage===

The fourth component of stigmatization in this model includes the “status loss and [[discrimination]]” that is experienced.  Many definitions of stigma do not include this aspect, however it is the belief of these authors that this loss occurs inherently as individuals are “labeled, set apart, and linked to undesirable characteristics.”  The members of the labeled groups are subsequently disadvantaged in the most common group of [[life chances]] including [[income]], [[education]], [[Mental health|mental well-being]], housing status, [[health]], and [[Health care|medical treatment]].  However, the authors are quick to point out that even though some groups are able to escape some of the [[disadvantage]]s listed, the [[principle]] is sound when broadly applied. 

===Necessity of power===

The authors also emphasize the necessity of power ([[Power (sociology)|social]], [[Economic power|economic]], and [[political power]]) to stigmatize.  While the role of power is clear in some situations, in others it can become masked as the power differences are so stark.  An extreme example of a situation in which the power role was explicitly clear was the treatment of [[Jewish]] people by the [[Nazi Germany|Nazis]].  On the other hand, an example of a situation in which individuals of a stigmatized group have “stigma-related processes” occurring would be the inmates of a [[prison]].  It is very imaginable that each of the steps described above would take place regarding the inmates’ thoughts about the [[Corrections officer|guards]].  However, this situation cannot involve true stigmatization according to this model because the prisoners do not have the economic, political, or social power to act on these thoughts with any serious discriminatory consequences.

==Further reading==
* [[Erving Goffman]], ''Stigma: Notes on the Management of Spoiled Identity'', Prentice-Hall, 1963, ISBN 0-671-62244-7.
* Heatherton, T. F., Kleck, R. E., Hebl, M. R., &amp; Hull, J. G. (Eds.), ''The Social Psychology of Stigma'', Guilford Press, 2000, ISBN 1-572-30573-8.
* Kurzban, R., &amp; Leary, M. R. (2001). Evolutionary Origins of Stigmatization: The Functions of Social Exclusion. ''[[Psychological Bulletin]]'' '''127''': 187-208.

''This article incorporates text translated from [http://de.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Stigmatisierung&amp;oldid=8257586 the corresponding German Wikipedia article].''

==See also==
*[[National Mental Health Anti-Stigma Campaign]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Social Stigma}}
[[Category:Bipolar disorder]]
[[Category:Identity politics]]
[[Category:Mental health]]

[[de:Stigmatisierung]]
[[id:Stigma sosial]]
[[it:Stigmatizzazione (scienze sociali)]]
[[he:סטיגמה]]
[[lt:Stigmatizacijos teorija]]
[[no:Sosial stigma]]
[[pl:Stygmatyzacja]]
[[pt:Estigma social]]
[[ru:Социальная стигматизация]]
[[sr:Стигматизација]]
[[sv:Socialt stigma]]
[[tr:Tepecik (bitki)]]
[[uk:Стигматизація]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>