<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181107164720|867728835" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2649767" pageid="2649767" ns="0" title="Social stigma"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-16T20:44:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Inadequate lead|date=April 2018}}{{discrimination sidebar|expanded=Related}}
'''Social stigma''' is the disapproval of, or [[discrimination]] against, a person based on perceivable social characteristics that serve to distinguish them from other members of a society. Social stigmas are commonly related to [[culture]], [[gender]], [[race (classification of human beings)|race]], and health.

==Description==
Stigma is a Greek word that in its origins referred to a type of marking or [[tattoo]] that was cut or burned into the skin of criminals, slaves, or traitors in order to visibly identify them as blemished or morally polluted persons. These individuals were to be avoided particularly in public places.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Goffman |first=Erving |title=Stigma: Notes on the Management of Spoiled Identity |date=2009 |publisher=Simon and Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0-671-62244-7 |page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Social stigmas can occur in many different forms. The most common deal with [[culture]], [[gender]], [[race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[illness]] and [[disease]]. Individuals who are stigmatized usually feel different and devalued by others.

Stigma may also be described as a label that associates a person to a set of unwanted characteristics that form a stereotype. It is also affixed.&lt;ref name="Jacoby-2005"&gt;{{citation |vauthors=Jacoby A, Snape D, Baker GA |year=2005 |title=Epilepsy and Social Identity: the Stigma of a Chronic Neurological Disorder |journal=Lancet Neurology |volume=4 |issue=3 |pages=171–8 |pmid=15721827 |doi=10.1016/s1474-4422(05)70020-x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once people identify and label your differences others will assume that is just how things are and the person will remain stigmatized until the stigmatizing attribute is undetectable. A considerable amount of generalization is required to create groups, meaning that you put someone in a general group regardless of how well they actually fit into that group. However, the attributes that society selects differ according to time and place. What is considered out of place in one society could be the norm in another. When society categorizes individuals into certain groups the labeled person is subjected to status loss and [[discrimination]].&lt;ref name="Jacoby-2005"/&gt; Society will start to form expectations about those groups once the cultural stereotype is secured.

Stigma may affect the [[behavior]] of those who are stigmatized. Those who are [[stereotype]]d often start to act in ways that their stigmatizers expect of them. It not only changes their behavior, but it also shapes their [[emotion]]s and [[belief]]s.&lt;ref name="Major-O'Brien-2005"/&gt;  Members of stigmatized social groups often face prejudice that causes depression (i.e. deprejudice).&lt;ref name="Cox et al. (2012)"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Cox |first1=William T. L. |last2=Abramson |first2=Lyn Y. |last3=Devine |first3=Patricia G. |last4=Hollon |first4=Steven D. |year=2012 |title=Stereotypes, Prejudice, and Depression: The Integrated Perspective |journal=[[Perspectives on Psychological Science]] |volume=7 |issue=5 |pages=427–49 |publisher= |doi=10.1177/1745691612455204 |pmid=26168502}}&lt;/ref&gt;  These stigmas put a person's [[social identity]] in threatening situations, like [[low self-esteem]]. Because of this, identity theories have become highly researched. Identity threat theories can go hand-in-hand with [[labeling theory]].

Members of stigmatized groups start to become aware that they aren't being treated the same way and know they are probably being discriminated against. Studies have shown that "by 10 years of age, most children are aware of cultural stereotypes of different groups in society, and children who are members of stigmatized groups are aware of cultural types at an even younger age."&lt;ref name="Major-O'Brien-2005"&gt;{{cite journal |author1=[[Brenda Major]] |author2=Laurie T. O'Brien |title=The Social Psychology of Stigma |journal=Annual Review of Psychology |year=2005 |volume=56 |issue=1 |pages=393–421 |doi=10.1146/annurev.psych.56.091103.070137}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Main theories and contributions==

===Émile Durkheim===
French sociologist [[Émile Durkheim]] was the first to explore stigma as a social phenomenon in 1895. He wrote:

''Imagine a society of saints, a perfect cloister of exemplary individuals. Crimes or deviance, properly so-called, will there be unknown; but faults, which appear venial to the layman, will there create the same scandal that the ordinary offense does in ordinary consciousnesses. If then, this society has the power to judge and punish, it will define these acts as criminal (or deviant) and will treat them as such.''&lt;ref&gt;[[Émile Durkheim]] (1982). ''Rules of Sociological Method'' (1895) The Free Press&lt;/ref&gt;

===Erving Goffman===
[[Erving Goffman]] was one of the most influential sociologists of the twentieth century. He described stigma as a phenomenon whereby an individual with an attribute which is deeply discredited by his/her society is rejected as a result of the attribute. Goffman saw stigma as a process by which the reaction of others spoils normal identity.&lt;ref name="Goffman-1963"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Stigma: Notes on the Management of Spoiled Identity|last=Goffman|first=Erving|publisher=[[Prentice Hall]]|year=1963|isbn=0-671-62244-7|location=|pages=|quote=|author-link=Erving Goffman|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

More specifically, he explained that what constituted this attribute would change over time.  "It should be seen that a language of relationships, not attributes, is really needed.  An attribute that stigmatizes one type of possessor can confirm the usualness of another, and therefore is neither creditable nor discreditable as a thing in itself."&lt;ref name="Goffman-1963" /&gt;

In Goffman's theory of social stigma, a stigma is an attribute, behavior, or reputation which is socially discrediting in a particular way: it causes an individual to be mentally classified by others in an undesirable, rejected [[stereotype]] rather than in an accepted, normal one. Goffman, a noted [[sociologist]], defined stigma as a special kind of gap between ''virtual social identity'' and ''actual social identity'':

{{quote|Society establishes the means of categorizing persons and the complement of attributes felt to be ordinary and natural for members of each of these categories. [...] When a stranger comes into our presence, then, first appearances are likely to enable us to anticipate his category and attributes, his "social identity" [...] We lean on these anticipations that we have, transforming them into normative expectations, into righteously presented demands. [...] It is [when an active question arises as to whether these demands will be filled] that we are likely to realize that all along we had been making certain assumptions as to what the individual before us ought to be. [These assumed demands and the character we impute to the individual will be called] ''virtual social identity''. The category and attributes he could in fact be proved to possess will be called his ''actual social identity''. (Goffman 1963:2).

While a stranger is present before us, evidence can arise of his possessing an attribute that makes him different from others in the category of persons available for him to be, and of a less desirable kind--in the extreme, a person who is quite thoroughly bad, or dangerous, or weak. He is thus reduced in our minds from a whole and usual person to a tainted, discounted one. Such an attribute is a '''stigma''', especially when its discrediting effect is very extensive [...] It constitutes a special discrepancy between virtual and actual social identity. Note that there are other types of [such] discrepancy [...] for example the kind that causes us to reclassify an individual from one socially anticipated category to a different but equally well-anticipated one, and the kind that causes us to alter our estimation of the individual upward. (Goffman 1963:3). }}

====The stigmatized, the normal, and the wise====
Goffman divides the individual's relation to a stigma into three categories:
# the stigmatized are those who bear the stigma;
# the normals are those who do not bear the stigma; and
# the wise are those among the normals who are accepted by the stigmatized as "wise" to their condition (borrowing the term from the homosexual community).

The wise normals are not merely those who are in some sense accepting of the stigma; they are, rather, "those whose special situation has made them intimately privy to the secret life of the stigmatized individual and sympathetic with it, and who find themselves accorded a measure of acceptance, a measure of courtesy membership in the clan." That is, they are accepted ''by'' the stigmatized as "honorary members" of the stigmatized group. "Wise persons are the marginal men before whom the individual with a fault need feel no shame nor exert self-control, knowing that in spite of his failing he will be seen as an ordinary other." Goffman notes that the wise may in certain social situations also bear the stigma with respect to other normals: that is, they may also be stigmatized for being wise. An example is a parent of a homosexual; another is a white woman who is seen socializing with a black man. (Limiting ourselves, of course, to social milieus in which homosexuals and blacks are stigmatized).

Until recently, this typology has been used without being empirically tested. A 2012 study&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Smith, R. |title=Segmenting an Audience into the Own, the Wise, and Normals: A Latent Class Analysis of Stigma-Related Categories |journal=Communication Research Reports |edition=29 |pages=257–65 |year=2012 |doi=10.1080/08824096.2012.704599 |volume=29|issue=4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; showed empirical support for the existence of the own, the wise, and normals as separate groups; but, the wise appeared in two forms: active wise and passive wise. Active wise encouraged challenging stigmatization and educating stigmatizers, but passive wise did not.

====Ethical considerations====
Goffman emphasizes that the stigma relationship is one between an individual and a social setting with a given set of expectations; thus, everyone at different times will play both roles of stigmatized and stigmatizer (or, as he puts it, "normal"). Goffman gives the example that "some jobs in America cause holders without the expected college education to conceal this fact; other jobs, however, can lead to the few of their holders who have a higher education to keep this a secret, lest they be marked as failures and outsiders. Similarly, a middle class boy may feel no compunction in being seen going to the library; a professional criminal, however, writes [about keeping his library visits secret]." He also gives the example of blacks being stigmatized among whites, and whites being stigmatized among blacks.

Individuals actively cope with stigma in ways that vary across stigmatized groups, across individuals within stigmatized groups, and within individuals across time and situations.&lt;ref name="Levin &amp; van Laar, 2004"&gt;{{citation |author1=Shana Levin |author2=Colette van Laar |year=2004 |title=Stigma and Group Inequality: Social Psychological Perspectives |publisher=Lawrence Erlbaum Associates |isbn=978-0805844153}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====The stigmatized=====
The stigmatized are ostracized, [[devalued]]
,  scorned, shunned and ignored. They experience [[discrimination]] in the realms of employment and housing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bordieri | first1 = J. E. | last2 = Drehmer | first2 = D. E. | year = 1986 | title = Hiring Decisions for Disabled Workers: Looking at the Cause | url = | journal = Journal of Applied Social Psychology | volume = 16 | issue = 3| pages = 197–208 | doi = 10.1111/j.1559-1816.1986.tb01135.x }}&lt;/ref&gt; Perceived prejudice and discrimination is also associated with negative physical and mental health outcomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Williams | first1 = D. R. | last2 = Neighbors | first2 = H. W. | last3 = Jackson | first3 = J. S. | year = 2003 | title = Racial/ethnic discrimination and health: findings from community studies | url = | journal = American Journal of Public Health | volume = 93 | issue = 2| pages = 200–208 | doi=10.2105/ajph.93.2.200| pmc = 2518588 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Young people who experience stigma associated with mental health difficulties may face negative reactions from their peer group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Dolphin|first=Louise|last2=Hennessy|first2=Eilis|date=2014-08-30|title=Adolescents׳ perceptions of peers with depression: An attributional analysis|url=http://www.psy-journal.com/article/S0165-1781(14)00365-5/abstract#|journal=Psychiatry Research|language=English|volume=218|issue=3|pages=295–302|doi=10.1016/j.psychres.2014.04.051|issn=0165-1781}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |url=http://psycnet.apa.org/buy/2016-07227-001|title=Depression stigma among adolescents in Ireland. |publisher =American Psychological Association |last1 = Dolphin|first1 = L. |last2 = Hennessy |first2 = E.| date = 2016|journal = Stigma and Health|language=en|access-date=|doi = 10.1037/sah0000025}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Dolphin|first=Louise|last2=Hennessy|first2=Eilis|date=2017-06-24|title=Labelling effects and adolescent responses to peers with depression: an experimental investigation|journal=BMC Psychiatry|volume=17|doi=10.1186/s12888-017-1389-9|pmc=5483288|pmid=28646873}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=O'Driscoll|first=Claire|last2=Heary|first2=Caroline|last3=Hennessy|first3=Eilis|last4=McKeague|first4=Lynn|date=October 2012|title=Explicit and implicit stigma towards peers with mental health problems in childhood and adolescence|journal=Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, and Allied Disciplines|volume=53|issue=10|pages=1054–1062|doi=10.1111/j.1469-7610.2012.02580.x|issn=1469-7610|pmid=22823158}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those who perceive themselves to be members of a stigmatized group, whether it is obvious to those around them or not, often experience psychological distress and many view themselves contemptuously.&lt;ref name="Heatherton-2000"&gt;Heatherton, T. F.; Kleck, R. E.; Hebl, M. R.; Hull, J. G. (2000). ''The Social Psychology of Stigma''. Guilford Press. {{ISBN|1-57230-573-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the experience of being stigmatized may take a toll on self-esteem, academic achievement, and other outcomes, many people with stigmatized attributes have high self-esteem, perform at high levels, are happy and appear to be quite resilient to their negative experiences.&lt;ref name="Heatherton-2000"/&gt;

There are also "positive stigma": it is possible to be too rich, or too smart. This is noted by Goffman (1963:141) in his discussion of leaders, who are subsequently given license to deviate from some behavioral norms, because they have contributed far above the expectations of the group. This can result in social stigma.

=====The stigmatizer=====
From the perspective of the stigmatizer, stigmatization involves, threat, aversion{{clarify|date=January 2012}} and sometimes the depersonalization of others into stereotypic caricatures. Stigmatizing others can serve several functions for an individual, including [[self-esteem]] enhancement, control enhancement, and anxiety buffering, through ''downward-comparison''—comparing oneself to less fortunate others can increase one's own subjective sense of [[subjective well-being|well-being]] and therefore boost one's self-esteem.&lt;ref name="Heatherton-2000"/&gt;

21st century social psychologists consider stigmatizing and stereotyping to be a normal consequence of people's cognitive abilities and limitations, and of the social information and experiences to which they are exposed.&lt;ref name="Heatherton-2000"/&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Current views of stigma, from the perspectives of both the stigmatizer and the stigmatized person, consider the process of stigma to be highly situationally specific, dynamic, complex and nonpathological.&lt;ref name="Heatherton-2000"/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Gerhard Falk===
German born sociologist and historian [[Gerhard Falk]] wrote:&lt;ref name="Falk-2001"&gt;Gerhard Falk (2001). [https://web.archive.org/web/20060501220023/http://www.buffalostate.edu/sociology/falkg.xml?username=falkg ''STIGMA: How We Treat Outsiders''], Prometheus Books.&lt;/ref&gt;

''All societies will always stigmatize some conditions and some behaviors because doing so provides for group solidarity by delineating "outsiders" from "insiders"''.

Falk&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jbuff.com/gfal.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; describes stigma based on two categories, ''existential stigma'' and ''achieved stigma''. He defines existential stigma as "stigma deriving from a condition which the target of the stigma either did not cause or over which he has little control." He defines ''Achieved Stigma'' as "stigma that is earned because of conduct and/or because they contributed heavily to attaining the stigma in question."&lt;ref name="Falk-2001"/&gt;

Falk concludes that "we and all societies will always stigmatize some condition and some behavior because doing so provides for group solidarity by delineating 'outsiders' from 'insiders'".&lt;ref name="Falk-2001"/&gt; Stigmatization, at its essence is a challenge to one's humanity- for both the ''stigmatized'' person and the ''stigmatizer''. The majority of stigma researchers have found the process of stigmatization has a long history and is cross-culturally ubiquitous.&lt;ref name="Heatherton-2000"/&gt;

===Link and Phelan stigmatization model===
Bruce Link and Jo Phelan propose that stigma exists when four specific components converge:&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author1=Link, Bruce G. |author2=Phelan, Jo C. |year=2001 |title=Conceptualizing Stigma |journal=Annual Review of Sociology |volume=27 |pages=363–85 |doi=10.1146/annurev.soc.27.1.363}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Individuals differentiate and [[labelling|label]] human variations.
# Prevailing cultural beliefs tie those labeled to adverse attributes.
# Labeled individuals are placed in distinguished groups that serve to establish a sense of disconnection between "us" and "them".
# Labeled individuals experience "status loss and [[discrimination]]" that leads to unequal circumstances.

In this model stigmatization is also contingent on "access to [[power (sociology)|social]], [[economic power|economic]], and [[political power]] that allows the identification of differences, construction of [[stereotype]]s, the separation of labeled persons into distinct groups, and the full execution of disapproval, [[social rejection|rejection]], exclusion, and [[discrimination]]." Subsequently, in this model the term stigma is applied when labeling, stereotyping, disconnection, status loss, and discrimination all exist within a power situation that facilitates stigma to occur.

====Differentiation and labeling====
Identifying which human differences are salient, and therefore worthy of labeling, is a social process. There are two primary factors to examine when considering the extent to which this process is a social one. The first issue is that significant oversimplification is needed to create [[group (sociology)|groups]]. The broad groups of [[black people|black]] and [[white people|white]], [[homosexuality|homosexual]] and [[heterosexuality|heterosexual]], the [[sanity|sane]] and the [[mentally ill]]; and [[youth|young]] and [[old age|old]] are all examples of this. Secondly, the differences that are socially judged to be relevant differ vastly according to time and place. An example of this is the emphasis that was put on the size of forehead and faces of individuals in the late 19th century—which was believed to be a measure of a person's criminal nature.{{Citation needed|date=November 2017}}

====Linking to stereotypes====
The second component of this model centers on the linking of labeled differences with [[stereotype]]s. [[Erving Goffman|Goffman's]] 1963 work made this aspect of stigma prominent and it has remained so ever since. This process of applying certain stereotypes to differentiated groups of individuals has attracted a large amount of attention and [[research]] in recent decades.

====Us and them====
Thirdly, linking negative attributes to groups facilitates separation into "us" and "them". Seeing the labeled group as fundamentally different causes stereotyping with little hesitation. "Us" and "them" implies that the labeled group is slightly less [[human]] in nature, and at the extreme not human at all. At this extreme, the most horrific events occur.{{Citation needed|date=November 2017}}

====Disadvantage====
The fourth component of stigmatization in this model includes "status loss and [[discrimination]]". Many definitions of stigma do not include this aspect, however these authors believe that this loss occurs inherently as individuals are "labeled, set apart, and linked to undesirable characteristics." The members of the labeled groups are subsequently disadvantaged in the most common group of [[life chances]] including [[income]], [[education]], [[mental health|mental well-being]], housing status, [[health]], and [[health care|medical treatment]].
Thus, stigmatization by the majorities, the powerful, or the "superior" leads to the [[Othering]] of the minorities, the powerless, and the "inferior".  Where by the stigmatized individuals become disadvantaged due to the ideology created by "the self," which is the opposing force to "the Other."  As a result, the others become socially excluded and those in power reason the exclusion based on the original characteristics that led to the stigma.&lt;ref&gt;Frosh, Stephen. "The Other." American Imago 59.4 (2002): 389-407. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Necessity of power====
The authors also emphasize{{Citation needed|date=November 2017}}  the role of power ([[power (sociology)|social]], [[economic power|economic]], and [[political power]]) in stigmatization. While the use of power is clear in some situations, in others it can become masked as the power differences are less stark. An extreme example of a situation in which the power role was explicitly clear was the treatment of [[Jewish]] people by the [[Nazi Germany|Nazis]]. On the other hand, an example of a situation in which individuals of a stigmatized group have "stigma-related processes"{{Clarify|date=January 2012}} occurring would be the inmates of a [[prison]]. It is imaginable that each of the steps described above would occur regarding the inmates' thoughts about the [[corrections officer|guards]]. However, this situation cannot involve true stigmatization, according to this model, because the prisoners do not have the economic, political, or social power to act on these thoughts with any serious discriminatory consequences.

==='Stigma allure' and authenticity===
Sociologist Matthew W. Hughey explains that prior research on stigma has emphasized individual and group attempts to reduce stigma by 'passing as normal', by shunning the stigmatized, or through selective disclosure of stigmatized attributes.  Yet, some actors may embrace particular markings of stigma (e.g.: social markings like dishonor or select physical dysfunctions and abnormalities) as signs of moral commitment and/or cultural and political authenticity.  Hence, Hughey argues that some actors do not simply desire to 'pass into normal' but may actively pursue a stigmatized identity formation process in order to experience themselves as causal agents in their social environment. Hughey calls this phenomenon 'stigma allure'.&lt;ref&gt;Hughey, Matthew W. (2012) 'Stigma Allure and White Antiracist Identity Management.' Social Psychology Quarterly. p. 1-23.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Six Dimensions of Stigma===
While often ''incorrectly'' attributed to Goffman the "Six Dimensions of Stigma" were '''not''' his invention. They were developed to augment Goffman's two levels – the discredited and the discreditable. Goffman considered individuals whose stigmatizing attributes are not immediately evident. In that case, the individual can encounter two distinct social atmospheres. In the first, he is ''discreditable''—his stigma has yet to be revealed, but may be revealed either intentionally by him (in which case he will have some control over how) or by some factor he cannot control. Of course, it also might be successfully concealed; Goffman called this ''passing''. In this situation, the analysis of stigma is concerned only with the behaviors adopted by the stigmatized individual to manage his identity: the concealing and revealing of information.
In the second atmosphere, he is ''discredited''—his stigma has been revealed and thus it affects not only his behavior but the behavior of others. Jones et al. (1984) added the "six dimensions" and correlate them to Goffman's two types of stigma, discredited and discreditable.

There are six dimensions that match these two types of stigma:&lt;ref name="Jones-1984"&gt;{{citation |vauthors=Jones E, Farina A, Hastorf A, Markus H, Miller D, Scott R |year=1984 |title=Social stigma: The psychology of marked relationships. |place=New York |publisher=Freeman |isbn=978-0716715924}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Concealable – extent to which others can see the stigma
# Course of the mark – whether the stigma's prominence increases, decreases, or terminated
# Disruptiveness – the degree to which the stigma and/or others' reaction to it impede social interactions
# [[Aesthetics]] – the subset of others' reactions to the stigma comprising reactions that are positive/approving or negative/disapproving but represent estimations of qualities other than the stigmatized person's inherent worth or dignity
# Origin – whether others think the stigma is present at birth, accidental, or deliberate
# Peril – the danger that others perceive (whether accurately or inaccurately) the stigma to pose to them

===Types===
In ''Unraveling the contexts of stigma'', authors Campbell and Deacon describe Goffman's universal and historical forms of Stigma as the following.
* '''Overt or external deformities''' - such as [[leprosy]], [[clubfoot]], [[cleft lip]] or palate and [[muscular dystrophy]].
* '''Known deviations in personal traits''' - being perceived rightly or wrongly, as weak willed, domineering or having unnatural passions, treacherous or rigid beliefs, and being dishonest, e.g., mental disorders, imprisonment, addiction, homosexuality, unemployment, suicidal attempts and radical political behavior.
* '''Tribal stigma''' - affiliation with a specific [[nationality]], [[religion]], or [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]] that constitute a deviation from the normative, i.e. being [[African American]], or being of [[Arab]] descent in the [[United States]] after the [[9/11]] attacks.&lt;ref name="Campbell-Deacon-2006"&gt;{{citation |author1=Catherine Campbell |author2=Harriet Deacon |title=Unraveling the Contexts of Stigma: From Internalisation to Resistance to Change |journal=Journal of Community &amp; Applied Social Psychology |date=Sep 2006 |volume=16 |issue=6 |pages=411–17 |issn=1052-9284 |doi=10.1002/casp.901}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Deviance====
Stigma occurs when an individual is identified as [[deviant]], linked with negative [[stereotype]]s that engender [[prejudice]]d attitudes, which are acted upon in [[discriminatory]] behavior. Goffman illuminated how stigmatized people manage their "Spoiled identity" (meaning the stigma disqualifies the stigmatized individual from full social acceptance) before audiences of normals. He focused on stigma, not as a fixed or inherent attribute of a person, but rather as the experience and meaning of difference.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author=Linda Shaw |date=Oct 1991 |title=Stigma and the Moral Careers of Ex-Mental Patients Living in Board and Care |journal=Journal of Contemporary Ethnography |volume=20 |issue=3 |pages=285–305 |doi=10.1177/089124191020003003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gerhard Falk expounds upon Goffman's work by redefining ''deviant'' as "others who deviate from the expectations of a group" ''and'' by categorizing deviance into two types:
* '''Societal deviance''' refers to a condition widely perceived, in advance and in general, as being deviant and hence stigma and stigmatized. "Homosexuality is therefore an example of societal deviance because there is such a high degree of consensus to the effect that homosexuality is different, and a violation of norms or social expectation".&lt;ref name="Falk-2001"/&gt;
* '''Situational deviance''' refers to a deviant act that is labeled as deviant in a specific situation, and may not be labeled deviant by society. Similarly, a socially deviant action might not be considered deviant in specific situations. "A robber or other street criminal is an excellent example. It is the crime which leads to the stigma and stigmatization of the person so affected."
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The physically disabled, mentally ill, homosexuals, and a host of others who are labeled ''[[deviant]]'' because they deviate from the expectations of a group, are subject to ''stigmatization-'' the [[social rejection]] of numerous individuals, and often entire groups of people who have been labeled deviant.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Stigma communication===
Communication is involved in creating, maintaining, and diffusing stigmas, and enacting stigmatization.&lt;ref name="Smith-2001"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Smith, R. |title=Stigma, Communication, and Health |publisher=Routledge Handbook of Health Communication |edition=2 |pages=455–68 |year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The model of stigma communication explains how and why particular content choices (marks, labels, peril, and responsibility) can create stigmas and encourage their diffusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Smith, R. |title=Language of the lost: An explication of stigma communication |journal=Communication Theory |volume=17 |issue=4 |pages=462–85 |year=2007 |doi=10.1111/j.1468-2885.2007.00307.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; A recent experiment using health alerts tested the model of stigma communication, finding that content choices indeed predicted stigma beliefs, intentions to further diffuse these messages, and agreement with regulating infected persons' behaviors.&lt;ref name="Smith-2001"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Smith, R. |title=An Experimental Test of Stigma Communication Content with a Hypothetical Infectious Disease Alert |journal=Communication Monographs |year=2012 |volume=79 |issue=4 |doi=10.1080/03637751.2012.723811 |pages=522–538}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Challenging===
Stigma, though powerful and enduring, is not inevitable, and can be challenged. There are two important aspects to challenging stigma: challenging the stigmatisation on the part of stigmatizers, and challenging the internalized stigma of the stigmatized. To challenge stigmatization, Campbell et al. 2005&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author1=Catherine Campbell |author2=Carol Ann Foulis |author3=Sbongile Maimane |author4=Zweni Sibiya |year=2005 |title=I have an evil child at my house: stigma and HIV/AIDS management in a South African community |journal=American Journal of Public Health |volume=95 |issue=5 |pages=808–15 |doi=10.2105/AJPH.2003.037499|pmid=15855456 |pmc=1449259}}&lt;/ref&gt; summarise three main approaches.
# There are efforts to educate individuals about the non-stigmatising facts and why they should not stigmatise.
# There are efforts to legislate against [[discrimination]].
# There are efforts to mobilize the participation of [[community]] members in anti-stigma efforts, to maximize the likelihood that the anti-stigma messages have relevance and effectiveness, according to local contexts.
#
In relation to challenging the internalized stigma of the stigmatized, [[Paulo Freire]]'s theory of [[critical consciousness]] is particularly suitable. Cornish provides an example of how sex workers in [[Sonagachi]], a red light district in India, have effectively challenged internalized stigma by establishing that they are respectable women, who admirably take care of their families, and who deserve rights like any other worker.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author=Cornish, F |year=2006 |title=Challenging the stigma of sex work in India: Material context and symbolic change |journal=Journal of Community and Applied Social Psychology |volume=16 |issue=6 |pages=462–71 |doi=10.1002/casp.894 |url=https://gcal.academia.edu/FloraCornish/Papers/85187/Challenging-the-stigma-of-sex-work-in-India--Material-context-and-symbolic-change}}&lt;/ref&gt; This study argues that it is not only the force of rational argument that makes the challenge to the stigma successful, but concrete evidence that sex workers can achieve valued aims, and are respected by others.

Stigmatized groups often harbor cultural tools to respond to stigma and to create a positive self-perception among their members. For example, advertising professionals have been shown to suffer from negative portrayal and low approval rates. However, the advertising industry collectively maintains narratives describing how advertisement is a positive and socially valuable endeavor, and advertising professionals draw on these narratives to respond to stigma.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Cohen|first1=Andrew C.|last2=Dromi|first2=Shai M.|title=Advertising morality: maintaining moral worth in a stigmatized profession|journal=Theory &amp; Society|volume=47|issue=2|pages=175–206|doi=10.1007/s11186-018-9309-7|url=https://link.springer.com/epdf/10.1007/s11186-018-9309-7?author_access_token=7NqWYsAc_xBowppAv-q8mve4RwlQNchNByi7wbcMAY6AEWVv2PLqubmhfuYTCeD-V3SRQ6CfZmxJResEGYJBsoZEDraaO2K-ltnWj2TVPmZ7jDY7bNZ5z2Kbuu8SoXhAHCzJkdSEdHAdS5s0BzfR6w%3D%3D|accessdate=21 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current research==

Research undertaken to determine effects of social stigma primarily focuses on disease-associated stigmas. Disabilities, psychiatric disorders, and sexually transmitted diseases are among the diseases currently scrutinized by researchers. In studies involving such diseases, both positive and negative effects of social stigma have been discovered.{{clarify|date=August 2015}}

===Research on self-esteem===
{{Main|Self-esteem}}
Members of stigmatized groups may have lower [[self-esteem]] than those of nonstigmatized groups. A test could not be taken on the overall self-esteem of different races. Researchers would have to take into account whether these people are optimistic or pessimistic, whether they are male or female and what kind of place they grew up in.
Over the last two decades, many studies have reported that African Americans show higher global self-esteem than whites even though, as a group, African Americans tend to receive poorer outcomes in many areas of life and experience significant discrimination and stigma.{{Citation needed|date=November 2017}}

===People with mental disorders===
{{further|Mental disorder#Stigma}}
[[Empirical research]] on stigma associated with mental disorders, pointed to a surprising attitude of the general public. Those who were told that mental disorders had a genetic basis were more prone to increase their [[social distance]] from the mentally ill, and also to assume that the ill were dangerous individuals, in contrast with those members of the general public who were told that the illnesses could be explained by social and environment factors. Furthermore, those informed of the genetic basis were also more likely to stigmatize the entire family of the ill.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ben Goldacre]], ''[http://www.badscience.net/2010/10/pride-and-prejudice/ The stigma gene]'', reproduced on his blog from his column in [[The Guardian]], 9 October 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Although the specific social categories that become stigmatized can vary over time and place, the three basic forms of stigma (physical deformity, poor personal traits, and tribal outgroup status) are found in most cultures and eras, leading some researchers to hypothesize that the tendency to stigmatize may have evolutionary roots.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FRszpOfV5o0C&amp;pg=PA113|title=Weight Bias|last=|first=|publisher=|year=2005|isbn=9781593851996|location=|pages=|quote=|via=|author1=Brownell|first1=Kelly D}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |vauthors=Kurzban R, Leary MR |year=2001 |title=Evolutionary Origins of Stigmatization: The Functions of Social Exclusion |journal=[[Psychological Bulletin]] |volume=127 |issue=2 |pages=187–208 |pmid=11316010 |url=http://www2.uni-jena.de/svw/igc/studies/ss04/Kurzban_Leary_2001_PB.pdf |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110716085409/http://www2.uni-jena.de/svw/igc/studies/ss04/Kurzban_Leary_2001_PB.pdf |dead-url=yes |archive-date=2011-07-16 |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.127.2.187}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently, several researchers believe that mental disorders are caused by a [[Chemical imbalance|chemical imbalance in the brain.]] Therefore, this biological rationale suggests that individuals struggling with a mental illness do not have control over the origin of the disorder. Much like [[cancer]] or another type of physical disorder, persons suffering from mental disorders should be supported and encouraged to seek help. Unlike [[Physical disorder|physical disabilities]], there is a negative social stigma surrounding mental illness, with those suffering being perceived to have control of their disabilities and being responsible for causing them. "Furthermore, research respondents are less likely to pity persons with mental illness, instead reacting to psychiatric disability with anger and believing that help is not deserved." &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Understanding the impact of stigma on people with mental illness|journal = World Psychiatry|date = 2002-02-01|issn = 1723-8617|pmc = 1489832|pmid = 16946807|pages = 16–20|volume = 1|issue = 1|first = PATRICK W|last = CORRIGAN|first2 = AMY C|last2 = WATSON}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although there are effective mental health interventions available across the globe, many persons with mental illnesses do not seek out the help that they need. Only 59.6% of individuals with a mental illness, including conditions such as depression, anxiety, schizophrenia, and bipolar disorder, reported receiving treatment in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.psychologicalscience.org/index.php/publications/mental-illness-stigma.html&lt;/ref&gt; Reducing the negative stigma surrounding mental disorders may increase the probability of afflicted individuals seeking professional help from a [[psychiatrist]] or a non-psychiatric [[physician]].  How particular mental disorders are represented in the media can vary, as well as the stigma associated with each.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Fennell|first=Dana|last2=Boyd|first2=Michael|date=2014|title=Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder in the Media|url=|journal=Deviant Behavior|volume=|pages=|via=|doi=10.1080/01639625.2013.872526}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the music industry, specifically in the genre of hip-hop or rap, those who speak out on mental illness are heavily criticized. However, according to a [[The Huffington Post]] article, there's a significant increase in rappers who are breaking their silence on depression and anxiety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/5-influential-rappers-that-broke-the-mental-health_us_57896a66e4b0e7c873500ec7 |title=5 Influential Rappers That Broke The Mental Health Stigma |last=Florez |first=Jose |date=2016-07-27 |publisher=The Huffington Post }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Addiction and substance use disorders ===
Throughout history, addiction has largely been seen as a moral failing or character flaw, as opposed to an issue of public health.&lt;ref name="barry1269"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Barry|first=Colleen L.|last2=McGinty|first2=Emma E.|last3=Pescosolido|first3=Bernice A.|last4=Goldman|first4=Howard H.|date=2014-10-01|title=Stigma, discrimination, treatment effectiveness, and policy: public views about drug addiction and mental illness|journal=Psychiatric Services (Washington, D.C.)|volume=65|issue=10|pages=1269–1272|doi=10.1176/appi.ps.201400140|issn=1557-9700|pmc=4285770|pmid=25270497}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.whitehouse.gov/ondcp/changing-the-language-draft|title=DRAFT: Changing the Language of Addiction|website=The White House|access-date=2016-12-12|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220103114/https://www.whitehouse.gov/ondcp/changing-the-language-draft|archivedate=20 December 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.drugabuse.gov/news-events/nida-in-the-news/ending-stigma-addiction|title=Ending the stigma of addiction|last=Abuse|first=National Institute on Drug|date=2012-07-03|language=en-US|access-date=2016-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Substance use has been found to be more stigmatized than smoking, obesity, and mental illness.&lt;ref name="barry1269"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Phillips|first=Lindsay A.|last2=Shaw|first2=Autherine|date=2013-08-01|title=Substance use more stigmatized than smoking and obesity|url=https://dx.doi.org/10.3109/14659891.2012.661516|journal=Journal of Substance Use|volume=18|issue=4|pages=247–253|doi=10.3109/14659891.2012.661516|issn=1465-9891}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.recoveryanswers.org/pressrelease/substance-use-is-more-stigmatized-than-both-smoking-and-obesity/|title=Substance use is more stigmatized than both smoking and obesity {{!}} Recovery Research Institute|website=www.recoveryanswers.org|access-date=2016-12-12|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220130557/http://www.recoveryanswers.org/pressrelease/substance-use-is-more-stigmatized-than-both-smoking-and-obesity/|archivedate=20 December 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.recoveryanswers.org/pressrelease/recoveryanswers-org-october-november-highlighted-article-public-attitudes-about-persons-with-drug-addiction-and-mental-illness/|title=Drug addiction is substantially more stigmatized than mental illness {{!}} Recovery Research Institute|website=www.recoveryanswers.org|access-date=2016-12-12|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220130604/http://www.recoveryanswers.org/pressrelease/recoveryanswers-org-october-november-highlighted-article-public-attitudes-about-persons-with-drug-addiction-and-mental-illness/|archivedate=20 December 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research has shown stigma to be a barrier to treatment-seeking behaviors among individuals with addiction, creating a "treatment gap".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://addiction.surgeongeneral.gov/executive-summary|title=Executive Summary|last=admin|date=2016-10-16|website=addiction.surgeongeneral.gov|access-date=2016-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Cunningham|first=John A.|last2=Sobell|first2=Linda C.|last3=Sobell|first3=Mark B.|last4=Agrawal|first4=Sangeeta|last5=Toneatto|first5=Tony|date=1993-05-01|title=Barriers to treatment: Why alcohol and drug abusers delay or never seek treatment|url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0306460393900369|journal=Addictive Behaviors|volume=18|issue=3|pages=347–353|doi=10.1016/0306-4603(93)90036-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://blog.samhsa.gov/2016/05/16/words-matter/#.WE7uZ9IrJpg|title=Words Matter|publisher =Substance Abuse and Mental Health Administration|first=Marla|last = Hendriksson |date=2016-05-16|website=SAMSHA blog |access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research shows that the words used to talk about addiction can contribute to stigmatization, and that the commonly used terms of "abuse" &amp; "abuser" actually increase stigma.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kelly|first=John F.|last2=Westerhoff|first2=Cassandra M.|date=2010-05-01|title=Does it matter how we refer to individuals with substance-related conditions? A randomized study of two commonly used terms|url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0955395909001546|journal=International Journal of Drug Policy|volume=21|issue=3|pages=202–207|doi=10.1016/j.drugpo.2009.10.010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kelly|first=John F.|last2=Dow|first2=Sarah J.|last3=Westerhoff|first3=Cara|date=2010-10-01|title=Does Our Choice of Substance-Related Terms Influence Perceptions of Treatment Need? An Empirical Investigation with Two Commonly Used Terms|url=http://jod.sagepub.com/content/40/4/805|journal=Journal of Drug Issues|language=en|volume=40|issue=4|pages=805–818|doi=10.1177/002204261004000403|issn=0022-0426}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apa.org/monitor/2014/03/words-matter.aspx|title=Words matter|website=http://www.apa.org|access-date=2016-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Botticelli|first=Michael P.|last2=Koh|first2=Howard K.|date=2016-10-04|title=Changing the Language of Addiction|url=http://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2565298|journal=JAMA|volume=316|issue=13|doi=10.1001/jama.2016.11874|issn=0098-7484|page=1361}}&lt;/ref&gt; Behavioral addictions (i.e. gambling, sex, etc.) are found to be more likely to be attributed to character flaws than substance-use addictions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Konkolÿ Thege|first=Barna|last2=Colman|first2=Ian|last3=el-Guebaly|first3=Nady|last4=Hodgins|first4=David C.|last5=Patten|first5=Scott B.|last6=Schopflocher|first6=Don|last7=Wolfe|first7=Jody|last8=Wild|first8=T. Cameron|date=2015-03-01|title=Social judgments of behavioral versus substance-related addictions: a population-based study|journal=Addictive Behaviors|volume=42|pages=24–31|doi=10.1016/j.addbeh.2014.10.025|url=https://zenodo.org/record/938494|issn=1873-6327|pmid=25462650}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stigma is reduced when Substance Use Disorders are portrayed as treatable conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McGinty|first=Emma E.|last2=Goldman|first2=Howard H.|last3=Pescosolido|first3=Bernice|last4=Barry|first4=Colleen L.|date=2015-02-01|title=Portraying mental illness and drug addiction as treatable health conditions: effects of a randomized experiment on stigma and discrimination|journal=Social Science &amp; Medicine|volume=126|pages=73–85|doi=10.1016/j.socscimed.2014.12.010|issn=1873-5347|pmid=25528557}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.recoveryanswers.org/pressrelease/breaking-the-stigma-portraying-opioid-use-disorder-as-a-treatable-health-condition/|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160521035040/http://www.recoveryanswers.org/pressrelease/breaking-the-stigma-portraying-opioid-use-disorder-as-a-treatable-health-condition/|dead-url=yes|archive-date=2016-05-21|title=Breaking the stigma: portraying opioid use disorder as a treatable health condition {{!}} Recovery Research Institute|website=www.recoveryanswers.org|access-date=2016-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Acceptance and Commitment Therapy has been used effectively to help people to reduce shame associated with cultural stigma around substance use treatment.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=The effectiveness of interventions for reducing stigma related to substance use disorders: a systematic review|year=2012|author1=James D Livingston|author2=Teresa Milne|author3=Mei Lan Fang|author4=Erica Amari|journal=Addiction|volume=107|issue=1|pages=39–50|doi=10.1111/j.1360-0443.2011.03601.x|pmc=3272222|pmid=21815959}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lee|first=Eric B.|last2=An|first2=Woolee|last3=Levin|first3=Michael E.|last4=Twohig|first4=Michael P.|date=2015-10-01|title=An initial meta-analysis of Acceptance and Commitment Therapy for treating substance use disorders|journal=Drug and Alcohol Dependence|volume=155|pages=1–7|doi=10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2015.08.004|issn=1879-0046|pmid=26298552}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.recoveryanswers.org/pressrelease/introducing-acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-a-preliminary-evaluation-of-its-effectiveness-in-addiction-treatment/|title=Introducing Acceptance and Commitment Therapy: A preliminary evaluation of its effectiveness in addiction treatment {{!}} Recovery Research Institute|website=www.recoveryanswers.org|access-date=2016-12-12|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220130601/http://www.recoveryanswers.org/pressrelease/introducing-acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-a-preliminary-evaluation-of-its-effectiveness-in-addiction-treatment/|archivedate=20 December 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mental illness, Taiwan===
In [[Taiwan]], strengthening the psychiatric rehabilitation system has been one of the primary goals of the Department of Health since 1985. Unfortunately, this endeavor has not been successful and it is believed that one of the barriers is social stigma towards the mentally ill.&lt;ref name="Song-Chang-Shih-Lin-Yang-2005"&gt;{{citation |vauthors=Song LY, Chang LY, Shih CY, Lin CY, Yang MJ |year=2005 |title=Community Attitudes Towards the Mentally Ill: The Results of a National Survey of the Taiwanese Population |journal=International Journal of Social Psychiatry |volume=51 |issue=2 |pages=162–76 |pmid=16048245 |doi=10.1177/0020764005056765}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, a study was conducted to explore the attitudes of the general population towards patients with mental disorders. A survey method was utilized on 1,203 subjects nationally. The results revealed that the general population held high levels of benevolence, tolerance on rehabilitation in the community, and nonsocial restrictiveness.&lt;ref name="Song-Chang-Shih-Lin-Yang-2005"/&gt; Essentially, benevolent attitudes were favoring the acceptance of rehabilitation in the community. It could then be inferred that the belief (held by the residents of Taiwan) in treating the mentally ill with high regard, somewhat eliminated the stigma.&lt;ref name="Song-Chang-Shih-Lin-Yang-2005"/&gt;

===Epilepsy, Hong Kong===
[[Epilepsy]], a common [[neurological disorder]] characterised by recurring [[seizure]]s, is associated with various social stigmas. Chung-yan Gardian Fong and Anchor Hung conducted a study in Hong Kong which documented public attitudes towards individuals with epilepsy. Of the 1,128 subjects interviewed, only 72.5% of them considered epilepsy to be acceptable;{{clarify|date=February 2012}} 11.2% would not let their children play with others with epilepsy; 32.2% would not allow their children to marry persons with epilepsy; additionally, employers (22.5% of them) would terminate an employment contract after an epileptic seizure occurred in an employee with unreported epilepsy.&lt;ref name="Fong-Hung-2002"&gt;{{citation |author1=Fong, C. |author2=Hung, A. |year=2002 |title=Public Awareness, Attituse, and Underdstanding of Epilepsy in Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, China |journal=Epilepsia |volume=43 |issue=3 |pages=311–16 |doi=10.1046/j.1528-1157.2002.31901.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Suggestions were made that more effort be made to improve public awareness of, attitude toward, and understanding of epilepsy through school education and epilepsy-related organizations.&lt;ref name="Fong-Hung-2002"/&gt;

===In the media===

In the early 21st century, technology has  a large impact on the lives of people in multiple countries and has become a social norm. Many people own a television, computer, and a smart phone. The media can be helpful with keeping people up to date on news and world issues and it is very influential on people. Because it is so influential sometimes the portrayal of minority groups affects attitudes of other groups toward them. Much media coverage has to do with other parts of the world. A lot of this coverage has to do with war and conflict, which people may relate to any person belonging from that country. There is a tendency to focus more in the positive behaviour of one's own group and the negative behaviours of other groups. This promotes negative thoughts of people belonging to those other groups, reinforcing stereotypical beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author=Geschke, D., Sassenberg, K., Ruhrmann, G., Sommer, D. |year=2010 |title=Effects of linguistic abstractness in the mass media: How newspaper articles shape readers' attitudes toward migrants |journal=Journal of Media Psychology: Theories, Methods, and Applications |volume=22 |issue=3 |pages=99–104 |doi=10.1027/1864-1105/a000014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

"Viewers seem to react to violence with emotions such as anger and contempt.  They are concerned for the integrity of the social order and show disapproval of others. Emotions such as sadness and fear are shown much more rarely." (Unz, Schwab &amp; Winterhoff-Spurk, 2008, p.&amp;nbsp;141)&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author=Unz, D., Schwab, F., Winterhoff-Spurk, P. |year=2008 |title=TV news–the daily horror?: Emotional effects of violent television news |journal=Journal of Media Psychology: Theories, Methods, and Applications |volume=20 |issue=4 |pages=141–55 |doi=10.1027/1864-1105.20.4.141}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a study testing the effects of stereotypical advertisements on students, 75 high school students viewed magazine advertisements with stereotypical female images such as a woman working on a holiday dinner, while 50 others viewed non stereotypical images such as a woman working in a law office.  These groups then responded to statements about women in a "neutral" photograph.  In this photo a woman was shown in a casual outfit not doing any obvious task.  The students that saw the stereotypical images tended to answer the questionnaires with more stereotypical responses in 6 of the 12 questionnaire statements.  This suggests that even brief exposure to stereotypical ads reinforces stereotypes.(Lafky, Duffy, Steinmaus &amp; Berkowitz, 1996)&lt;ref&gt;Lafky et al. "Looking through Gendered Lenses: Female Stereotyping in Advertisements and Gender Role Expectations" in ''Journalism and Mass Communication Quarterly'', v73 n2 p379-88 Sum 1996. http://virtualworker.pbworks.com/f/Looking%20through....pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Effects of education, culture===
The aforementioned stigmas (associated with their respective diseases) propose effects that these stereotypes have on individuals. Whether effects be negative or positive in nature, 'labeling' people causes a significant change in individual perception (of persons with disease). Perhaps a mutual understanding of stigma, achieved through education, could eliminate social stigma entirely.

Laurence J. Coleman first adapted [[Erving Goffman]]'s (1963) social stigma theory to gifted children, providing a rationale for why children may hide their abilities and present alternate identities to their peers.&lt;ref name="Coleman, Laurence J. 1985"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Coleman, Laurence J. |year=1985 |title=Schooling the Gifted |publisher=Addison-Wesley Publishing Company}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Coleman, L. J. &amp; Cross, T. L. 2001"&gt;{{Cite book |author1=Coleman, L. J.  |author2=Cross, T. L.  |lastauthoramp=yes |year=2001 |title=Being Gifted in School |publisher=Prufrock Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Cross |first1=T.L. |last2=Coleman |first2=L.J. |title= The social cognition of gifted adolescents: An exploration of the stigma of giftedness paradigm|journal= Roeper Review |volume=16 |issue=1 |year=1993 |pages=37–47 |doi=10.1080/02783199309553532}}&lt;/ref&gt; The stigma of giftedness theory was further elaborated by Laurence J. Coleman and [[Tracy L. Cross]] in their book entitled, ''Being Gifted In School'', which is a widely cited reference in the field of gifted education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=being+gifted+in+school+&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C47 |title=Google Scholar Search |accessdate=May 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the chapter on Coping with Giftedness, the authors expanded on the theory first presented in a 1988 article.&lt;ref name="Is being gifted a social handicap"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Coleman |first1=L.J. |last2=Cross |first2=T. L. |title=Is being gifted a social handicap? |journal=Journal for the Education of the Gifted |volume=11 |issue=4 |year=1988 |pages=41–56}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Google Scholar, this article has been cited at least 110 times in the academic literature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=is+being+gifted+a+social+handicap&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C47 |title=Google Scholar Search |accessdate=May 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Coleman and [[Tracy L. Cross|Cross]] were the first to identify intellectual giftedness as a stigmatizing condition and they created a model based on Goffman's (1963) work, research with gifted students,&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; and a book that was written and edited by 20 teenage, gifted individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=The American Association of Gifted Children |year=1978 |title=On Being Gifted |publisher=Walker and Company}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Being gifted sets students apart from their peers and this difference interferes with full social acceptance. Varying expectations that exist in the different social contexts which children must navigate, and the value judgments that may be assigned to the child result in the child's use of social coping strategies to manage his or her identity. Unlike other stigmatizing conditions, giftedness is a unique because it can lead to praise or ridicule depending on the audience and circumstances.

Gifted children learn when it is safe to display their giftedness and when they should hide it to better fit in with a group. These observations led to the development of the Information Management Model that describes the process by which children decide to employ coping strategies to manage their identities. In situations where the child feels different, she or he may decide to manage the information that others know about him or her. Coping strategies include: disidentification with giftedness, attempting to maintain a low visibility, or creating a high-visibility identity (playing a stereotypical role associated with giftedness). These ranges of strategies are called the Continuum of Visibility.{{Citation needed|date=November 2017}}

===Stigmatising attitude of narcissists to psychiatric illness===
Arikan found that a [[stigmatization of mental illness|stigmatising attitude to psychiatric patients]] is associated with [[narcissistic]] personality traits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Arikan, K. |title=A stigmatizating attitude towards psychiatric illnesses is associated with narcissistic personality traits |journal=Isr J Psychiatry Relat Sci |volume=42 |issue=4 |pages=248–50 |year=2005 |format=PDF |url=http://www.kemalarikan.com/wp-content/uploads/pdf/arikan_stigma_narsisizm.pdf |pmid=16618057}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Abortion===
While abortion medicine is very common in western society, women rarely disclose their use of such services, and providers are also subject to stigma.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Harris|first1=Lisa|title=Second Trimester Abortion Provision: Breaking the Silence and Changing the Discourse|journal=Reproductive Health Matters|date=2008|volume=16|issue=31|pages=74–81|doi=10.1016/S0968-8080(08)31396-2|url=http://lib.tcu.edu/staff/bellinger/abortion/Harris.pdf|accessdate=29 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=O'Donnell, Jenny|author2=Weitz, Tracy|author3=Freedman, Lori|title=Resistance and vulnerability to stigmatization in abortion work|journal=Social Science and Medicine|date=November 2011|volume=73|issue=9|pages=1357–1364|doi=10.1016/j.socscimed.2011.08.019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stigmatization of Prejudice===
Cultural norms can prevent displays of prejudice as such views are stigmatized and thus people will express non-prejudiced views even if they believe otherwise ([[preference falsification]]). However, if the stigma against such views is lessened, people will be more willing to express prejudicial sentiments.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2017-05-26/yes-trump-is-making-xenophobia-more-acceptable "Yes, Trump is Making Xenophobia More Acceptable"], Bloomberg News, 26/05/17, retrieved 25/11/17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.vox.com/science-and-health/2017/8/14/16143582/charlottesville-prejudice-psychology "The scientific case that America is becoming more prejudiced"] Vox, 14/08/17, retrieved 25/11/17&lt;/ref&gt; For example, following the 2008 economic crisis, anti-immigration sentiment seemingly increased amongst the US population when in reality the level of sentiment remained the same and instead it simply became more acceptable to openly express opposition to immigration.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Creighton|first=Matthew|last2=Jamal|first2=Amaney|last3=Malancu|first3=Natalia|date=3 May 2014|title=Has Opposition to Immigration Increased in the United States after the Economic Crisis? An experimental Approach|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/imre.12091/full|journal=International Migration Review|volume=49|issue=3|pages=727–756|doi=10.1111/imre.12091}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Psychology|Sociology}}
{{div col}}

* [[Badge of shame]]
* [[Collateral consequences of criminal charges]]
* [[Discrimination]]
* [[Guilt by association]]
* [[Identity (social science)|Identity]]
* [[Label (sociology)]]
* [[Labelling]]
* [[Labeling theory]]
* [[Leprosy stigma]]
* [[Passing (sociology)|Passing]]
* [[Post-assault treatment of sexual assault victims|Post-assault mistreatment of sexual assault victims]]
* [[Prejudice]]
* [[Scapegoat]]
* [[Self-Schema]]
* [[Self-esteem]]
* [[Self-Concealment]]
* [[Stereotype]]
* [[Stereotype threat]]
* [[Stig-9|Stig-9 perceived mental illness stigma questionnaire]]
* [[Social alienation]]
* [[Social exclusion]]
* [[Stigma management]]
* [[Taboo]]
* [[Weight Stigma]]

{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}
''This article incorporates text translated from [http://de.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Stigmatisierung&amp;oldid=8257586 the corresponding German Wikipedia article].''

==References==
* [[George Ritzer]] (2006). ''Contemporary Social Theory and its Classical Roots: The Basics (Second Edition)''. McGraw-Hill.
* Blaine, B. (2007). ''Understanding The Psychology of Diversity''. SAGE Publications Ltd.
* Smith, R. A. (2009). Stigma communication. In S. Littlejohn &amp; K. Foss (Eds.), Encyclopedia of communication theory (pp 931–34). Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage.
* Healthline Networks, Inc. [https://web.archive.org/web/20081004215407/http://www.healthline.com/galecontent/stigma] Retrieved: February 2007
* Anna Scheyett, ''The Mark of Madness: Stigma, Serious Mental Illnesses, and Social Work'', [http://ssw.unc.edu/rti/presentation/PDFs/stigma&amp;SMI.pdf] Retrieved: February 2007
* Osborne, Jason W. (November 1993) Niagara county community college. "Academics, Self-Esteem, and Race: A look at the Underlying Assumptions of the Dissidentification Hypothesis"
* Carol T. Miller, Ester D. Rothblum, Linda Barbour, Pamela A. Brand and Diane Felicio (September 1989). University of Vermont. "Social Interactions of Obese and Nonobese Women"
* [[Kenneth Plummer]] (1975). ''Sexual stigma: an interactionist account''. Routledge. {{ISBN|0-7100-8060-3}}.

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.stigmaj.org/ Stigma Research and Action] a peer reviewed open access journal in the stigma field

{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}

{{Social class}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Social Stigma}}
[[Category:Identity politics]]
[[Category:Labeling theory]]
[[Category:Social rejection]]
[[Category:Social stigma| ]]
[[Category:Sociological terminology]]
[[Category:Stereotypes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>