<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101113092912|396476868" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="24035321" pageid="24035321" ns="0" title="Oikophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-13T10:23:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Oikophobia''' is a term used in the nineteenth century to describe a desire (particularly by the English) to leave home and travel,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Southey|first=Robert|title=Letters from England, Volume 1|year=1808|publisher=David Longworth|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=cr4sAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA157&amp;dq=Oikophobia&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=XEfeTP28OMbMhAfdrpm7DQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CEIQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Oikophobia&amp;f=false|authorlink=Robert Southey|page=311}}&lt;/ref&gt; or, in clinical contexts, an aversion to home surroundings ("fear of household appliances, equipment, bathtubs, household chemicals, and other common objects in the home").&lt;ref&gt;Ronald Manual Doctor, Ada P. Kahn, Christine A. Adamec. ''The encyclopedia of phobias, fears, and anxieties.'' Third edition. Infobase Publishing, 2008. Page 281.&lt;/ref&gt; More recently it was used by the British philosopher [[Roger Scruton]] to mean "the repudiation of inheritance and home,"&lt;ref&gt;Roger Scruton, ''England and the Need for Nations'', (London: Civitas, 2004), pp.33-38 and for the excerpt of Scruton's definition [http://www.civitas.org.uk/pdf/cs49-8.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; as "a stage through which the adolescent mind normally passes."&lt;ref&gt;Roger Scruton, ''A Political Philosophy'', p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Scruton's usage ==
In his book, ''Roger Scruton: Philosopher on Dover Beach'', Mark Dooley describes oikophobia  as centered within the Western academic establishment on "both the common culture of the West, and the old educational curriculum that sought to transmit its humane values." This disposition has grown out of, for example, the writings of [[Jacques Derrida]] and of [[Michel Foucault]]'s "assault on '[[bourgeois]]' society result[ing] in an 'anti-culture' that took direct aim at holy and sacred things, condemning and repudiating them as oppressive and power-ridden."&lt;ref&gt;Dooley, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
Derrida is a classic oikophobe in so far as he repudiates the longing for home that the Western theological, legal, and literary traditions satisfy.   . . .  Derrida's deconstruction seeks to block the path to this 'core experience' of membership, preferring instead a rootless existence founded 'upon nothing.'&lt;ref&gt;Dooley, p. 83&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
An extreme aversion to the sacred and the thwarting of the connection of the sacred to the culture of the West is described as the underlying motif of oikophobia; and not the substitution of Judeo-Christianity by another coherent system of belief. The paradox of the oikophobe seems to be that any opposition directed at the theological and cultural [[tradition]] of the West is to be encouraged even if it is "significantly more parochial, exclusivist, patriarchal, and ethnocentric."&lt;ref&gt;Mark Dooley, Roger Scruton: Philosopher on Dover Beach (Continuum 2009), p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of phobias]]
*''[[Wanderlust]]''
*[[Allophilia]]
*[[Xenophily]]
*[[Xenocentrism]]

== References ==
*Roger Scruton, ''A Political Philosophy'', pp.23-25:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Scruton |first=Roger |url=http://www.continuumbooks.com/authors/details.aspx?AuthorId=145104&amp;BookId=126311 |title=Continuum - Political Philosophy &gt; Roger Scruton |publisher=Continuumbooks.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{reflist}}

[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Culture]]

[[cs:Oikofobie]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>