<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114034257|171359310" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5348421" pageid="5348421" ns="0" title="Racism by country"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T03:43:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{articleissues
|OR=February 2007
|cleanup=January 2007
|POV= February 2007
|disputed= February 2007
}}

The article describes the state of '''[[race relations]] and [[racism]] in a number of countries'''.  Racism of various forms are found in every country on Earth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://web.amnesty.org/library/index/engACT400202001|publisher = Amnesty International|title = Racism and the administration of justice}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Racism is widely condemned throughout the world, with 170 states signatories of the [[International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]] by [[August 8]] [[2006]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/(Symbol)/208ba1d9617d31d1c1257259003eed53?Opendocument|title = Report of the Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination 68th and 69th session|publisher = United Nations Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In different countries, the forms that racism takes may be different for historic, cultural, economic or demographic reasons.

== Australia ==
Prior to the establishment of a national federal government in 1901, the territory of Australia was occupied from 1788 by various British Colonies (which have since become Australia's States) that had commenced the dispossession of about 300 Aboriginal nations which had come to exist on the continent during the previous 40,000 years. The first Act of the new Australian government was the ''[[White Australia Policy]]'' that aimed to purify the new nation by denying citizenship rights to non-Europeans already resident and allowing only Europeans to immigrate. Australia's Aboriginal people were not included in the constituency of the new nation and it was not until the 1960s that they were included in the census and given the right to vote in national elections. 

By the 1930s the White Australia Policy had succeeded in reducing the non-European component of Australia's population such that the nation was about 98% European. Following World War II, interest in migrating to Australia from traditional British sources declined (due to reconstruction efforts in Europe and the relative desirability and proximity of Canada and the USA). The post-war nation-building imperative of 'populate or perish' thereby required a slight broadening of the White Australia Policy to include Southern Europeans, particularly Greeks and Italians, large numbers of whom have since made Australia home. Further relaxations followed, allowing an increasingly diverse migrant intake from all parts of the world. 

Australia officially became a multicultural country in 1973 when the Australian government adopted policies of [[multiculturalism]]. However, like most contemporary settler societies, such policies have never had universal acceptance within the community and there have been some high-profile issues of race-based violence (for example the [[2005 Cronulla riots]]) as well as upsurges of popular race-based discourse since the 1996 election of the Liberal-National Coalition Government led by Prime Minister [[John Howard]], who was criticised in some quarters for allowing the views of [[Pauline Hanson]] to circulate without censure. In her maiden parliamentary speech, Hanson said that "a multicultural country can never be a strong country" and supported this assertion with a number of widely publicised remarks about Asians not assimilating and living in ghettos. 

Following her meteoric rise to prominence on the national political scene, Hanson formed the [[One Nation (Australia)|One Nation Party]], which attracted significant support for a few years. Many of Hanson's policy proposals about restricting the entry of asylum seekers and refugees have since become official Howard government policy while her One Nation Party's political stocks have dramatically declined, though her views continue to exert influence on the Howard Government's approach to immigration. Her public criticsm of African refugees in Australia in October 2007 were soon followed by the Minister for Immigration, [[Kevin Andrews]], revisions to justifications for reducing the humanitarian intake from Africa from a policy based on changed political circumstances in source countries to problems with integration within Australia.

==Austria==
Austria has sometimes been criticised of trying to sweep its [[Consequences of German Nazism|Nazi]] past under the carpet, typified by the widely pronounced myth that Austria was a victim of Nazi aggression rather than a willing participant. This has its origins as an Allied propaganda tactic. This complacency was severely tested in the [[1986]] presidential race when it emerged that [[Kurt Waldheim]] (a former [[UN secretary general]]) had concealed (or forgotten) certain facts about his war-time military service with the [[Wehrmacht]]. The revelations caused much controversy in Austria as well as in the outside world. Nevertheless Waldheim was elected President. Controversy again erupted in [[2000]] when [[Jörg Haider]]'s centre-right [[Freedom Party]] entered into coalition with the conservative [[People's Party]] having gained 27% of the vote.

However much progress has been made with settling the disputes and compensation for Jews and others whose property and assets were seized during the Nazi era, with a deal completed in [[2001]]. Elections in [[2002]] saw a significant drop in support for the Freedom Party, with the party subsequently splitting into opposing factions. [[Jörg Haider]] now leads the "[[Alliance for the Future of Austria]]".

==Botswana==
Since the mid-1990s the central government of [[Botswana]] has been trying to move [[Bushmen]] out of the [[Central Kalahari Game Reserve]] even though the national constitution guarantees the Bushmen the right to live there in perpetuity. As of October 2005, the government has resumed its policy of forcing all Bushmen off their lands in the Game Reserve, using armed police and threats of violence or death.&lt;ref name="Daily Telegraph"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2005/10/29/wbot29.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2005/10/29/ixworld.html
|title=Bushmen forced out of desert after living off land for thousands of years |publisher=The Daily Telegraph |accessdate=2005-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the involuntarily displaced Bushmen live in squalid resettlement camps and some have resorted to [[prostitution]] and [[alcoholism]], while about 250 others remain or have surreptitiously returned to the [[Kalahari]] to resume their independent lifestyle.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2004/09/0914_040914_labushmen_2.html African Bushmen Tour U.S. to Fund Fight for Land]&lt;/ref&gt;

“How can you have a [[Stone Age]] creatures continue to exist in the age of computers?“ asked Botswana’s president [[Festus Mogae]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.motherjones.com/news/dispatch/2005/01/01_800.html Exiles of the Kalahari]&lt;/ref&gt;  A report released by the [[United Nations]] Committee on the Elimination of
Racial Discrimination condemns Botswana's treatment of the 'Bushmen' as racist.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.survival-international.org/news/tribes/bushmen/2002 News by tribe | Survival International]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.survival-international.org/news/1454 UN condemns Botswana government over Bushman evictions]&lt;/ref&gt;  

==Brazil==
{{main|Racial democracy}}

Race relations in Brazil have long been characterized by a belief in [[racial democracy]], i.e. an ideology stating that racial prejudice is not a significant factor in Brazilian society, and that racism is not an obstacle to employment, education, and social mobility the way some believe it is in other countries.  This theory has come under fire in recent years by researchers who say that racism is very much a factor in the country's social life.

In a sign that some Brazilian universities have come to see racism as an obstacle to higher education, several of them have created [[affirmative action]] programs aimed at increasing the admission of ([[Afro-Brazilian|Afro-Brazilians]] and members of the native population).&lt;ref&gt;Plummer, Robert. "Black Brazil Seeks a Better Future." &lt;u&gt;BBC News, São Paulo&lt;/u&gt; [[25 September]] [[2006]]. [[16 November]] [[2006]] &lt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/5357842.stm&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bulgaria==
Racism in Bulgaria has been geared towards the [[Romani people]] who are perceived to be of different racial and ethnic background. However, not all Bulgarians are racist towards the Roma, and it really depends on the individual's upbringing, education, area where they lived, and other factors.
Bulgarian nationalists are also wary of the country's large [[Turkish people|Turkish]] minority because of their perceived ambitions for greater power in Bulgaria and potential separatism in areas where Turks predominantly live. The forced assimilation campaign of the late 80s and early 90s directed against ethnic Turks resulted in the permanent emigration of some 300,000 Bulgarian Turks to Turkey. During this period, Turks were forced to change their names to Slavic Bulgarian ones and Turkish culture was heavily suppressed. [[Muslim Bulgarians]] (ethnic Bulgarians practicing Islam) were also targeted as Islam was seen as a "foreign "Turkish element" that stood against Bulgarian interests.
The [[National Union Attack]] or Ataka, a party widely considered fanatically xenophobic, surprisingly won 10% of the popular vote at the recent [[2005]] elections.

==Canada==
[[Canada|Canadian]] society is often depicted as being a very progressive, tolerant, diverse, and [[multicultural]].  Accusing a person of racism in Canada is usually considered a serious slur.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last = Fontaine|first = Phil|author-link = Phil Fontaine|url = http://www.hrsdc.gc.ca/asp/gateway.asp?hr=/en/lp/lo/lswe/we/special_projects/RacismFreeInitiative/speeches/Fontaine.shtml&amp;hs=|title = Modern Racism in Canada by Phil Fontaine|place = Queen's University|date = Friday, April 24, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] legally assures equal treatments, rights and freedoms without discrimination based on race (among other criteria).   Nevertheless, racism is still present in Canada, and continues to affect the lives of all people who live in Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = PART I - SETTING THE CONTEXT: UNDERSTANDING RACE, RACISM AND RACIAL DISCRIMINATION|publisher = Ontario Human Rights Commission|url = http://www.ohrc.on.ca/english/publications/racism-and-racial-discrimination-policy_1.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Canada's treatment of [[Aboriginal peoples in Canada|Aboriginal]]s is governed by the [[Indian Act]], which provides special treatment for [[First Nations|Indians]], [[Inuit]] and [[Metis]]. In [[1999]], the Canadian government created an autonomous territory, [[Nunavut]] for the [[Inuit]] living in the Arctic and Northernmost parts of the country.  Inuit composed 85% of the population of [[Nunavut]], which represents a new level of [[self-determination]] for the indigenous people of Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.un.org/WCAR/e-kit/indigenous.htm|title = Press kit: Issues - Racism against Indigenous peoples - World Conference Against Racism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are notable records of [[slavery in Canada]] in the [[1600s]].  More than half of all Canadian slaves were [[First Nations|aboriginal]], and the [[United Empire Loyalists]] brought their slaves with them after leaving what became the [[United States]]. In [[1793]], the [[Lieutenant Governor (Canada)|Lieutenant Governor]] of [[Upper Canada]], [[John Graves Simcoe]], passed a bill called the [[Act Against Slavery]] making it illegal to bring a person into the colony for the purposes of enslavement, and mandating the gradual emancipation of all slaves&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Freedom from Slavery|publisher = Government of Ontario, Ministry of Government Services|url = http://www.archives.gov.on.ca/English/exhibits/humnrits/slavery.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; in Upper Canada. Slavery was fully outlawed across all of Canada in [[1834]]. Most of the emancipated slaves of African descent were then sent to settle [[Freetown]] in [[Sierra Leone]] and those that remained primarily ended up in segregated communities such as [[Africville]] outside [[Halifax Urban Area|Halifax]], [[Nova Scotia]].

Starting in 1858, [[China|Chinese]] "[[coolies]]" were brought to Canada to work in the mines and on the [[Canadian Pacific Railway]]. However, they were denied by law the rights of citizenship, including the right to vote, and in the [[1880s]], "[[Head Tax|head taxes]]" were implemented to curtail immigration from China. In [[1907]], a riot in [[Vancouver, British Columbia|Vancouver]] targeted Chinese and Japanese-owned businesses. In [[1923]], the federal government passed the ''[[Chinese Immigration Act of 1923|Chinese Immigration Act]]'', commonly known as the ''Exclusion Act'', prohibiting further Chinese immigration except under "special circumstances". [[Japanese Canadian]]s were also subject to anti-Asian racism, particularly during [[World War II]] when many Canadians of Japanese heritage &amp;mdash; even those who were born in Canada &amp;mdash; were forcibly moved to internment camps. The government of Canada officially apologised and made restitution for the treatment of Japanese Canadians in 1988.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://history.cbc.ca/histoire/?MIval=EpisContent.html&amp;series_id=1&amp;episode_id=14&amp;chapter_id=3&amp;page_id=3&amp;lang=E|title = Japanese Internment|publisher = Canadian Broadcasting Corporation}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Exclusion Act was repealed in 1947, the same year in which [[Chinese Canadian]]s were finally given the right to vote.  Restrictions would continue to exist on immigration from Asia until 1967, when all racial restrictions on [[immigration to Canada]] were repealed, and Canada adopted the current points based immigration system.

In [[Northwest Territories]] in the Canadian north, Aboriginals are given preference for jobs and education and are considered to have P1 status. Non-aboriginal people who were born in the NWT or have resided half of their life there are considered a P2, as well as women and disabled peoples. White males receive the lowest priority, P3. &lt;ref&gt;GNWT - Human Resources - Affirmative Action &lt;http://www.hr.gov.nt.ca/employment/affirmativeaction/&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chile==
{{Cleanup|date=October 2007}}
{{Unreferencedsection|date=December 2006}}
Located in [[South America]], Chile is a country that viewed itself with a high degree of both [[European ethnic groups|European]] and/or [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Amerindian]] blood, but demography and national politics has argued over whether or not Chileans are more of a white people, a ''[[mestizo]]'' majority, or descendants from a multiplicity of [[ethnic group]]s, since Chile had attracted waves of European immigrants in the late 19th/early 20th centuries. 

If the Chilean people feel they have Amerindian, [[Spanish people|Spanish]] or in many cases: British (English/Irish), French or Swiss, German or Austrian, Italian, Portuguese, Yugoslavian (Serbian/Croatian) and Arab (Lebanese/Syrian) ancestry, it won't explain the problematic issues faced by most Latin American countries is [[poverty]]  affects a large segment of Chilean society the same way the [[middle-class]]es are 40 percent of the population, one of Latin America's largest groups of affluent or financially secure peoples. Disputed but asymmetrical statistics shown that between 20 to 50 percent of the Chilean population, are poor and in the [[low income]] strata, mainly consists of ''mestizos'' and Amerindians. 

The national cultural profile of Chile appears more of a [[White people|white]] country located in the [[southern hemisphere]] surrounded by more Amerindian or ''mestizo'' majority [[Latin America]], might indicated the political and cultural ethos of the Chilean government under an [[elite]] not typically identified as mestizos, since its' independence in [[1818]] from Spanish rule. 

The Chilean government like most Latin American nations, used policies and public messages in attempt to encourage their people to take pride of their ''mestizo'' background, but like its mostly [[White people|white]] neighbor [[Argentina]], insisted it has a more European cultural integrity. Chile passed several laws and changed their 1925 constitution to prohibit racial [[discrimination]] in public or private [[employment]], and despite its [[Catholic]] majority, the country allowed [[freedom of religion]] for its small [[Protestant]], [[Eastern Orthodox]], [[Judaism|Jewish]], [[Mormonism|Mormon]] and other religious communities.   

Chile had a history of high levels of [[socio-economic]] inequality despite its' tradition of ensured economic prosperity and social protection laws enacted in the early 20th century. But the country's small wealthy elite is predominantly of Spanish and other European descent, whom might been allowed to take [[Mapuche]], [[Aymara]] or [[Inca]]n wives in order to procreate children to inherit the land. 

The [[Roman Catholic Church]] promoted the white Spanish settlers and later European [[immigration|immigrants]] to intermarry the indigenous or ''mestizo'' majority, with disregard to their racial origin or skin color, in order to procreate a new colony. From the first census in 1821 to the 1901 census report, Chile had grown from 500,000 to near 3 million people, but still today much of the country is sparsely populated.

However, Chile has experienced many levels of racial conflict between its' indigenous peoples (esp. between the [[Mapuche]]s) and [[Spanish people|Spanish]] [[conquistadors]] who from 1541, had a 350-year conflict ending in defeat and oppression of the Mapuche by chileanos. 

The Mapuches were expert warriors and knew how to have battles with little casualties or defeats with the first Spanish, then Chilean armies, but the Mapuches' fighting skills declined in efficiency and they surrendered to the Chileans in the 1880s, to increase their level of racial malignment and economic status in the next century, as they joined the ranks of lower-class Chileans (esp. mestizos not considered "white" or not from land inheritance families) into the status of underpaid or overworked farmers and miners in the early 20th century. 

When it comes to a history being a land of untapped natural sources abound in its' thin (its widest point is 100 miles) but 3,000 mile long shape, Chile should highly profited from its' major byproducts: copper, nitrates and sulfates exported to the global market, esp. in high demand in World Wars I and II, provided a high source of financial revenue for the "white" political and business elite. 

The Mapuche only made up 3 percent of the country's population, but continued to encounter open and subliminal forms of racial [[prejudice]], and the majority of Mapuche migrated to the cities in search of work and opportunity find themselves in the bottom of the country's defined class system. In [[Santiago de Chile|Santiago]], the country's capital and largest city, the endless influx of rural tenants now represent over half the city population, neighborhoods of dirt floor slums, rackety shacks and substandard housing, and these areas are avoided by local upper middle classes don't want to witness or get near the poverty and racial tension of Amerindians under "white" rule. 

Similarly [[Polynesian]] [[Rapanui]]s of [[Easter Island]], located 2,000 miles (1.400 km.) west of Chile, has been under Chilean rule since 1888. But until 1966 the Rap Nui were not granted full Chilean citizenship, and for most of that time they were confined to the town of [[Hanga Roa]] and its environs and not allowed to visit their ancestral homes. When Chile annexed the island only 111 [[Rapa Nui]] survived after two centuries of slave raiding, European diseases, famine and civil war, numbers have now recovered somewhat but tensions remain. 

The Rapanui recently demanded more political autonomy and cultural preservation after introduction of culture and technology from the outside world, in the same time the Rapanui had very high rates of poverty than Chileans on the mainland, and until the late 1980s the Chilean government restricted the Rapanui language, cultural practices and although mostly Catholic, their animist religious elements to preserve their traditional integrity as a South Pacific people. In the late 1990s, autonomous rule was granted to the Rapanui of Easter Island.   

Chileans had a strong emotional pull on issues relating to poverty, racism and class distinction, although the Chileans are discovering how deep the impact of racial and class divisions had on the country in the 1940s and 1950s, along with a growing concern in leftist circles to produce a small opposition to promote liberal reforms. The country had a large political presence of [[left]]-wing activists and an active [[Communism|Communist]] party from the 1930s (the first in Latin America, but was banned under law in [[1956]] and permanently in [[1973]]) whom opposed what they felt the country's economic system was oppressive, a highly unequal distribution of wealth, and lack of opportunities that most rural ''mestizos'' and Amerindians encountered. 

The leftists called the system as an anathema of a developing country, once in the late [[1960s]] had a billion-dollar surplus in its' treasury accumulated by mining profits, could been used to fund one of the world's oldest social [[welfare state]] programs. After leftist parties were elected to majority status in Chilean congress, they created farm work programs and subdivided large estates into collective farms, but was small land plots for rural ''mestizo'' peasants. 

In 1970, [[Salvador Allende]], the first [[Marxism|Marxist]] president elected in the [[western hemisphere]] tried to decrease the country's huge class disparities through changes in [[banking]], the national [[treasury]], [[land ownership]] and [[nationalization]] of private [[industry]]. Allende promised to boost the buying power and financial security of the poorest and working-class Chileans (especially ''mestizos'' and Amerindians) he got the most popularity from, but this came with a price by high opposition of the upper-class and businessmen got the Chilean army to take care of an ailing economy, and protect their wealth and business interests from damage by the Allende regime. 

In the [[Chilean Coup of 1973|bloody coup]] in 1973, Allende was found dead (or allegedly killed), might put an end to his [[socialism|socialist]] reforms to decrease racial and class disparity, as Chile fell under a military dictatorship by general [[Augusto Pinochet]] from evident assistance from the [[US]]-[[CIA]], as Chilean leftists and worldwide left-wing activists claimed, meant to preserve the "status quo" of the rich "white" Spanish elite whom supported Pinochet to take power, over the Amerindians, ''mestizos'' and the working poor. 

From 1973 to his retirement in 1990, Pinochet had a "laissez-faire" approach to business, and promised to restructure the social, political and economic functions of Chile left damaged or neglected by previous governments and when civilian rule returned in [[1989]], the Chilean congress began to focus again on racial and ethnic issues once scorned by Pinochet in order to avoid being labeled as "socialist agitation". Pinochet wanted to preserve the status quo of business elite interests, emphasized a more nationalistic ideology of conservative and patriotic values on what he viewed the Chilean people, and took little consideration on poverty and racism faced by large numbers of lower-class mestizos. 

In the 1990s and early 2000s, Chile enjoyed unprecedented economic growth and more middle-class Chileans began to have a higher standard of living by a mixed socialist/capitalist free market. The Chilean government with restored [[democracy|democratic]] rule began to discuss on including every Chilean not of upper-class or mostly European ancestry to not only share, but invest in financial gains after authoritarian rule ended. 

Chilean poverty rates were cut in half from 45% in 1989 to 18% in 2005. However, its small Mapuche minority whom lived apart and encountered racial insults by non-Amerindian or "white" Chileans struggle to keep their autonomy and livelihood, a byproduct of over four centuries of their servitude and inferior status in a Hispanic country. 

Recent waves of immigration from East or South Asia, Eastern Europe and other Latin American countries came to Chile in a fast pace, but most Chileans hold little prejudices on the basis of race or ethnicity but Chileans complained they wanted these immigrants to assimilate and contribute to the country, the homogeneous "[[melting pot]]" concept known as ''Chileanadad'' at large.

But, Chile was also a site of pro-[[Nazism|Nazi]] political activity to nearly claimed electoral victories in the 1930s and early 1940s, but Chile was a wartime ally against Nazi Germany. In recent years (early 2000s) Chile got into news reports as active in [[far-right]] and "skinhead" gangs had racial and anti-Semitic views, and the country has an image of low percentages of black Africans (less than 1 percent, lower than numbers of east Asians or Japanese-Chileans), but this came from a low need for [[slavery]] in colonial Chile has explained the ethnographic trend. 

The country had an emotionally charged argument for so long whether or not to admit a ''mestizanaje'' side in a Hispanic culture modeled on that of Northern/western Europeans, and the country's small black minority does not feel regularly threatened for their race, since Chilean law has traditionally avoided racial segregation, but nonetheless experienced the plight of its' "non white" mestizo, black, Asian, Amerindian and Rapanui populations.

==China==
{{main|Racism in the People's Republic of China}}
For decades African students in [[China]] have been treated with hostility and prejudice.  Their complaints regarding their treatment were largely ignored until 1988-9, when "[[Nanjing anti-African protests|students rose up]] in protest against what they called 'Chinese apartheid'". African officials, who had until then ignored the problem, took notice of the issue. The [[Organization of African Unity]] issued an official protest, and the organization's chairman, [[Mali]]'s president [[Moussa Traoré]], went on a fact-finding mission to China. The issue was so severe that, according to a ''[[The Guardian|Guardian]]'' 1989 Third World Report titled "'Chinese apartheid' threatens links with Africa", "'Chinese apartheid', as the African students call it, could threaten Peking's entire relationship with the continent."

{{Further|[[Anti-Japanese sentiment in China]]}}
Anti-Japanese sentiment in China is an issue with old roots. Japan started off like other Western powers by annexing land from China towards the end of the Qing Dynasty. Dissatisfaction with the settlement and the Twenty-One Demands by the Japanese government led to a severe boycott of Japanese products in China. Bitterness in China persists over the atrocities of the Second Sino-Japanese War and Japan's post-war actions. Today, textbook revisionism and censorship remain contentious issues.

==Fiji==
Relationships between ethnic [[Fijians]] and [[Indians in Fiji|Indo-Fijians]] have often been strained, and the tension between the two communities has dominated politics in the islands for the past generation. The level of tension varies between different regions of the country. [http://web.amnesty.org/report2004/fji-summary-eng] [http://www.cdnn.info/special-report/fiji_coup/fijitimeline.html]

==France==
The French have a long history of ethnic and racial conflicts. [[Anti-Semitism]], a common trend in European history, is also highlighted in French history by events such as the [[Dreyfus Affair]] at the turn of the nineteenth century, and France's treatment of its Jewish population during the [[Vichy regime]]. Likewise, the treatment of North Africans and other former colonials during the colonial era, the atrocities committed in Algeria during the [[Algerian War of Independence|War of Independence]] (1954-1962) and also the [[Paris massacre of 1961]] are also signs of intolerance. The fact that Algerians formed the bulk of late-twentieth century immigration has raised delicate issues, which are exacerbated by the degradation of the general social situation. In the 1970s [[Jean Raspail]] wrote ''[[The Camp of the Saints]]'' which some felt implied African immigrants should be drowned or shot to prevent them from entering France.

In [[1998]] the Council of Europe's European Commission Against Racism and Intolerance (ECRI) made a report stating concern about racist activities in France and accused the French authorities of not doing enough to combat this. The report and other groups have expressed concern about organizations like [[Front National (France)]]. In a recent [[Pew Research Center|Pew Survey]], 47% of the French deem immigration from Eastern Europe to be a bad thing. A small minority shows signs of Anti-Semitism. Roughly 11% had an unfavorable view of Jews [http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795] and 8% felt that US policy was most influenced by the Jews [http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=803]. In the colonial age some French also displayed negative sentiments toward black Africans.

Nevertheless these judgments should be balanced by the following: Canadians had roughly the same percentage linking US policy to Jews as France did. Furthermore, France had been ruled by Jewish leaders during the twentieth century (most notably [[Léon Blum]] and [[Pierre Mendès-France]], who were both highly popular). Indeed, France has a long history of support for universalism dating back to the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] : the unenforced constitution of 1794 gave the right to vote to all "foreigners" (independently of any racial consideration) living in France for more than one year. The French also generally have a greater interest in African culture and aid to the region.

The Palestine question is widely known to have "imported" Jews vs Arabs' mutual hatred into the French society as a whole. When in October and November of 2005, [[2005 Paris riots|violent riots]] erupted in north-east Paris, and later other cities around France, after two presumably innocent youths of North African origin were accidentally electrocuted after they were chased by the police, some German and French media [http://www.alterinfo.net/Emeutes-de-novembre-en-France-une-operation-des-services-secrets_a4684.html accused] Israeli's secret services, the [[Mossad]], of covert operations behind the general troubles.

[[France]] is home to Europe’s largest population of [[Muslims]] — about 6 million — as well as the continent’s largest community of Jews, about 600,000. Over the last several years, anti-Jewish violence, property destruction, and racist language has been wildly increasing and French-Jews are worried more every month that it will spiral even higher. Jewish leaders perceive an intensifying anti-Semitism in France, mainly among Muslims of [[Arab]] or [[African]] heritage, but also growing among [[Caribbean]] islanders from former colonies.[http://www.boston.com/news/world/europe/articles/2006/03/13/anti_semitism_seen_rising_among_frances_muslims/]

In May 2005, there have been explosive riots between North Africans and Romas in [[Perpignan]] after young Arab man was shot dead and another Arab man was lynched by a group of [[Romani people|Roma]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title='Race killing' sparks French riot |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4594019.stm |publisher=[[BBC]] |date=[[2005-05-30]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Megan |last=Rowling |title=French riots borne of mutual exclusion |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/English/archive/archive?ArchiveId=12707 |publisher=[[Al Jazeera]] |date=[[2005-06-06]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It must be added here, as a conclusion to this chapter about racism and anti-semitism in France, that in the 2007 presidential elections, the French have elected [[Nicolas Sarkozy]], the son of an immigrant Hungarian, who, together with his wife Cecilia, are both of Jewish descent. Nicolas Sarkozy, who is right wing, has nominated many personalities also of Jewish descent, although left wing, to head important ministries in his government, most noticeably Foreign Minister [[Bernard Kouchner]]. Recently, in September 2007, Kouchner very suddenly raised the question of a [http://www.guardian.co.uk/france/story/0,,2170890,00.html threat of "war" with Iran] provoking general controversy and criticisms about the new government seemingly open bias, now representing a clear rupture with France's usual and traditionally more balanced foreign policy.

==Germany==
{{further|[[Nazism]] and [[Christian antisemitism]]}}
[[Image:Nazi poster Der ewige Jude.jpg|thumb|left|''[[The Eternal Jew (film)|The Eternal Jew]]'' (German: Der ewige Jude): 1937 German poster advertising an antisemitic [[Nazism|Nazi]] movie, exhibits drawn Jewish caricatures are examples of negative ethnic stereotypes perpetuated by "racial" [[Nazi Germany|Nazi]] propaganda.]]
The history of [[Germany]] has included many acts and policies of racism. If one includes pre-19th century acts of [[anti-Semitism]] as racism, the history stretches back to at least the eleventh century, when [[Henry II, Holy Roman Emperor]] expelled Jews from [[Mainz]] in 1012. Other acts of anti-Semitism included numerous bloody attacks on Jews living in the area in the thirteenth and fourteenth centuries, most notably the massacres of Jews in the 1340s after they were blamed for spreading the [[Black Death]].

In the nineteenth century, Germany became one of the major centers of nationalist thought, with the ''[[Völkisch movement]]'', and also a major area for development of racial theories, many of them virulently racist ''[[Racism#From "racial theory" to "racism"|See above]]''. Anti-semitic campaigns in this period took on a definitely "racial" valence, as definitely distinct from a purely religious one.

The period after [[World War I]] led to an increased use of anti-Semitism and other racism in political discourse, for example among [[Erich Ludendorff|General Ludendorff]]'s followers, which was capped by the ascent of [[Adolf Hitler]] and his [[Nazi Party]] in 1933. [[Nazi racial policy]] and the [[Nazi Nuremberg Laws]] represented some of the most explicit racist policies in Europe in the twentieth century, and culminated in [[the Holocaust]], a systematic murdering of millions of [[Jews]], [[Slavs]], [[Porrajmos|Gypsies]], disabled people and other "undesirables".

In the post-[[World War II]] era, German reconciliation with its anti-Semitic past has been a protracted experience. Recent concerns about racism have centered around immigrants (''Ausländer''), who encounter prejudice when seeking jobs and apartments, or can even experience direct violent attacks by some right-wing groups. This pattern is similar to what is happening in some other European countries.

The immigrants came in two waves, the first in the 1950s, the so called ''Gastarbeiter'' (Guest Workers) and their families. These people came from countries such as [[Turkey]] and [[Yugoslavia]] in [[West Germany]], and [[Vietnam]] and [[Angola]] in [[East Germany]]. The ''Gastarbeiter'' were expected to remain on limited contracts, and then leave. Many did not. Starting from the 1980s, the second wave were the ''Asylbewerber'' (Asylum Seekers) from countries such as [[Sri Lanka]] and [[Lebanon]]. This second group were considered by some locals to not be genuine cases, but so called ''Wirtschaftsflüchtlinge'' (Economic Migrants).

==Guyana==
There has been racial tension between the [[Indo-Caribbean]] people and the [[African Caribbean|African-Caribbeans]]. This is evident during elections where major riots by the blacks occur when an Indian is president.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/caribbean/news/story/2005/09/050920_guyana_race.shtml Guyana turns attention to racism]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guyana.org/features/conflicts_indiansandblacks.html Conflict between East Indians and Blacks]&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Hong Kong==
[[Image:Hk anti-discrimination poster.jpg|thumb|right|200px|An [[racism|anti-discrimination]] poster in a Hong Kong [[MTR|subway]] station. Circa. 2005]]
In a population of almost 7 million [http://www.censtatd.gov.hk/press_release/press_releases_on_statistics/index.jsp?sID=1752&amp;sSUBID=7113&amp;subjectID=&amp;charsetID=&amp;displayMode=D] [[Hong Kong]] has gained a reputation as international city, while remaining predominantly Chinese. This multi-culturalism has raised issues of racial and sex discrimination, particularly among the 350,000 [[list of ethnic groups|ethnic]] minorities such as Nepalese, Indians, Indonesians, Pakistanis and Filipinos, who have long established minority communities since the founding days of the former colony or have come to Hong Kong recently to work as domestic workers. There are also around 380,000 immigrants from [[mainland China]] who have also suffered discrimination [http://www.amrc.org.hk/5301.htm], as evidenced by cases of high unemployment rates, poor working conditions, psychological and physical violence, lack of minimum wage. In 2003, the number of complaints filed with the body handling discrimination issues, the Equal Opportunities Commission [http://www.eoc.org.hk/eoc/GraphicsFolder/default.aspx] was up by 31 percent. 

A race discrimination bill has been demanded by human rights groups for the last 10 years, and the government has been accused of putting the issue on the back burner. 

Last December 3, 2006 was the first time a drafted bill was released onto the Legislative Council, and is expected to be passed before the end of 2008. However, the bill is criticized to be "too conservative" [http://www.ahrchk.net/ahrc-in-news/mainfile.php/2004ahrcinnews/222/]. The exclusion of mainland Chinese immigrants has also been a source of controversy, with the government claiming that they are not considered to be of a different race. Another issue of the bill has been of language instruction in schools. Low-income ethinic minority parents who cannot afford to send their children to English-instruction schools have to send them to Chinese-instruction schools, where they fall behind in classes or make little progress.

==India==

It is claimed by some activists [http://www.wcc-coe.org/wcc/what/jpc/echoes/echoes-17-04.html] that [[casteism]] practised in India is a form of racism, but this is debated by those who believe that casteism has nothing to do with physical attributes, unlike racism. At the UN world conference on racism (August 31 - September 7 2001) the Indian Government opposed the discussion of caste in the conference, saying that "the caste issue is not the same as racism" [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/1495052.stm].

Such allegations have also been rejected by many sociologists such as [[Andre Béteille]], who writes that treating caste as a form of racism is "politically mischievous" and worse, "scientifically nonsense" since there is no discernable difference in the racial characteristics between [[Brahmins]] and [[Scheduled Castes]]. He writes that "Every social group cannot be regarded as a race simply because we want to protect it against prejudice and discrimination".&lt;ref&gt;[http://wcar.alrc.net/mainfile2.php/For+the+negative/14/] Andre Beteille, Race and Caste,''The Hindu'', 10 March 2001&lt;/ref&gt;
In addition, the view of the caste system as "static and unchanging" (which would indicate a form of racial discrimination) has been disputed by many scholars. Sociologists describe how the perception of the caste system as a static and textual stratification has given way to the perception of the caste system as a more processual, empirical and contextual stratification. Others have applied theoretical models to explain mobility and flexibility in the caste system in India.&lt;ref name="Silverberg Paper"&gt;{{cite journal
|author = James Silverberg
|date=  November 1969
|year = 1969
|month = Nov
|title = Social Mobility in the Caste System in India: An Interdisciplinary Symposium
|journal = The American Journal of Sociology
|volume = 75
|issue = 3
|pages = 443-444
}}&lt;/ref&gt;. According to these scholars, groups of lower-caste individuals could seek to elevate the status of their caste by attempting to emulate the practices of higher castes.

Sociologist [[M. N. Srinivas]] has also debated the question of rigidity in Caste.&lt;ref&gt;Srinivas, M.N, Religion and Society among the Coorgs of South India by MN Srinivas, Page 32 (Oxford, 1952)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Caste in Modern India; And other essays: Page 48. (Media Promoters &amp; Publishers Pvt. Ltd, Bombay; First Published: 1962, 11th Reprint: 1994)&lt;/ref&gt; For details see [[sanskritization]]. 

[[Pakistan]]i-American sociologist [[Ayesha Jalal]] also rejects these allegations. In her book, "Democracy and Authoritarianism in [[South Asia]]", she writes that "As for [[Hinduism]], the hierarchical principles of the Brahmanical social order have always been contested from within Hindu society, suggesting that equality has been and continues to be both valued and practiced."&lt;ref&gt;A. Jalal,Democracy and Authoritarianism in [[South Asia]]: A Comparative and Historical Perspective (Contemporary South Asia), Cambridge University Press (May 26, 1995), ISBN 0521478626&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, many [[Hindu reform movements]] have actively combated casteism and the practice of untouchability (segregation of the lower castes). In order to curb the practice of caste-based discrimination, numerous laws, including [[Constitution of India|constitutional laws]], have been passed in India outlawing casteist discrimination. &lt;ref&gt;Bayly, Susan (July 1999). Caste, Society and Politics in India from the Eighteenth Century to the Modern Age. Cambridge University Press. DOI:10.2277/0521264340. ISBN-13: 9780521264341&lt;/ref&gt;[[Reservation in India|Special quotas]] are provided to the lower castes in access to schools and jobs. Lower caste political parties have achieved increasing prominence in the Indian political landscape since India's independence. The public practice of casteism has diminished significantly among the large urban and cosmopolitan classes in India. Nonetheless, the fight to end casteism is an uphill struggle, especially in rural areas where education and modernity are scarce, and numerous hate crimes have taken place in India that have been attributed to Casteism.

[[India]]'s treatment of its lower-class [[Dalit (outcaste)|Dalit]]s has been described by [[UNESCO]] as "India's hidden apartheid".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unesco.org/courier/2001_09/uk/doss22.htm&lt;/ref&gt; According to Rajeev Dhavan, of India's leading English-language newspaper ''[[The Hindu]]'', "''casteism'' is India's apartheid which will continue in its most vicious and persistent forms for decades to come."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hinduonnet.com/2001/08/24/stories/05242523.htm&lt;/ref&gt; [[Eric Margolis]] has claimed that India "frantically tr[ied] to prevent its caste system, which is often called ‘hidden apartheid" from being put on the agenda of the 2001 [[World Conference against Racism]] in [[Durban]].

They were not allowed draw water from the same wells as those with caste, and they usually lived in segregated neighborhoods outside the main village. The majority of rural Dalits still live in [[segregation]] and experience [[atrocities]] to the scale of 110,000 registered cases a year according to 2005 statistics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/world/story/2007/03/02/india-dalits.html UN report slams India for caste discrimination]&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, [[Anti-Brahmanism|Anti-Brahmanist]] racial sentiments have been expressed by extremist fringe groups among Dalit Nationalists.

However, such allegations of apartheid are regarded by academic sociologists as a [[political epithet]], since apartheid implies state sponsored discrimination, and no such thing exists in India. Anti-dalit prejudice and discrimination is a social malaise that exists primarily in rural areas, where small societies can track the caste lineage of individuals and discriminate accordingly. Sociologists Kevin Reilly, Stephen Kaufman, Angela Bodino, while being critical of casteism, conclude that modern India does not practice any "apartheid" since there is no state sanctioned discrimination.&lt;ref name="Reilley et al"&gt;Kevin Reilly, Stephen Kaufman, Angela Bodino, Racism: A Global Reader P21, M.E. Sharpe, 2003 ISBN 0765610604.&lt;/ref&gt; They write that [[Caste]]ism in India is presently "not apartheid. In fact, untouchables, as well as tribal people and members of the lowest castes in India benefit from broad [[Reservation in India|affirmative action programmes]] and are enjoying greater political power."&lt;ref name="Reilley et al"/&gt;

In the [[India]]n [[Indian caste system|caste system]], a [[Dalit]], often called an [[untouchable]]is a person who lay outside the [[Indian Caste System]]. Historically,  Hindu Dalits were forbidden to worship in temples and Muslim Dalits forbidden in mosques [http://www.indianexpress.com/story/12109.html]. Dalits who converted to Christianity are frequently discriminated against by upper-caste Catholic priests and nuns.&lt;ref&gt;Kerala Christians and the Caste System C. J. Fuller Man, New Series, Vol. 11, No. 1. (Mar., 1976), pp. 53-70.&lt;/ref&gt;[http://indianhope.free.fr/site_eng/article_5.php3]
They were not allowed draw water from the same wells as those with caste, and they usually lived in segregated neighborhoods outside the main village. Additionally, [[Anti-Brahmanism|Anti-Brahmanist]] racial sentiments have been expressed by extremist fringe groups among Dalit Nationalists.
Caste Discrimination, while still being present in private life and in politics, has all but disappeared from urban public life.

==Indonesia==
See [[Jakarta Riots of May 1998]] and [[Anti-Chinese legislation in Indonesia]].

A number of discriminatory laws against [[Chinese Indonesian#Post-independence and New Order Era|Chinese Indonesians]] were enacted by the government of [[Indonesia]]. In 1959, President [[Sukarno|Soekarno]] approved [[PP 10/1959]] that forced Chinese Indonesians to close their businesses in rural areas and relocate into urban areas. Moreover, political pressures in the [[1970]]s and [[1980]]s restricted the role of the Chinese Indonesian in politics, academics, and the military. As a result, they were thereafter constrained professionally to becoming entrepreneurs and professional managers in trade, manufacturing, and banking. In the [[1960]]s, following the failed alleged Communist coup attempt in 1965, there was a strong sentiment against the Chinese Indonesians who were accused of being Communist collaborators. In 1998, Indonesia riots over higher food prices and rumors of hoarding by merchants and shopkeepers often degenerated into anti-Chinese attacks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/1998/02/24/qanda.t_2.php International Herald Tribune: Q&amp;A / Juwono Sudarsono, Defense Official : Racism in Indonesia Undercuts Unity]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Amnesty International]] has estimated more than 100,000 [[Papuan languages|Papuans]], one-sixth of the population, have died as a result of government-sponsored violence against [[Western New Guinea|West Papuans]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usyd.edu.au/news/84.html?newsstoryid=651 Report claims secret genocide in Indonesia - University of Sydney]&lt;/ref&gt; while others had previously specified much higher death tolls.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news.vu/en/news/RegionalNews/050728-West-Papua-Support.shtml West Papua Support]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[1990s]] saw Indonesia accelerate its [[Transmigration program]], under which hundreds of thousands of [[Javanese]] and [[Sumatra]]n migrants were resettled to Papua over a ten-year period. Prior to Indonesian rule, the Asian population was estimated at 16,600. Critics suspect that the Transmigration program's purpose is to tip the balance of the province's population from the heavily [[Melanesians|Melanesian]] Papuans toward western Indonesians, thus further consolidating Indonesian control.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/cline/papua/transmigration.htm West Papua - Transmigration]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Iraq==

During [[World War II]], [[Rashid Ali al-Kaylani]] blamed British hostility toward his pro-Nazi stance on the [[History of the Jews in Iraq|Iraqi Jewish community]].  In 1941, Iraqi nationalists murdered 200 Jews in Baghdad in a [[pogrom]].&lt;ref name="RubinIraq"&gt;[[Michael Rubin|Rubin, Michael]].  "Iraq." ''The Continuum Political Encyclopedia of the Middle East''. Ed. [[Avraham Sela]]. New York: Continuum, 2002. pp. 410-419.&lt;/ref&gt; 
{{see|Farhud}} 

After the [[1948 Arab-Israeli War]], Iraqi Jews faced persecution so great that by 1951, approximately 100,000 of them left the country while the Iraqi rulers confiscated their property and financial assets.&lt;ref name="RubinIraq" /&gt; 

During 1987-1988, Iraqi forces infamously carried out a genocide against the Iraqi [[Kurds]] that claimed the lives of hundreds of thousands of people.
{{see|Al-Anfal Campaign}}

The UN reports that although [[Christians]] comprise less than 5% of Iraq's population, they make up nearly 40% of the refugees fleeing Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/iraq/2007-03-22-christians-iraq_N.htm Christians, targeted and suffering, flee Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/08/26/AR2007082601004.html Iraq's Endangered Minorities]&lt;/ref&gt; More than 50% of [[Iraqi Christians]] have already left the country since 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mysanantonio.com/news/metro/stories/MYSA052707.01A.chaldean_christians.3555f3e.html Out of Iraq, a flight of Chaldeans]&lt;/ref&gt; Iraq's Christian community numbered 1.4 million in the early 1980s at the start of [[Iran-Iraq War]]. But as the [[2003 invasion of Iraq|2003 invasion]] has radicalized Islamic sensibilities, Christians' total numbers slumped to about 500,000, of whom 250,000 live in [[Baghdad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/pope/story/0,,1961207,00.html|title='We're staying and we will resist'}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asianews.it/index.php?l=en&amp;art=7410|title=Terror campaign targets Chaldean church in Iraq}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Furthermore, the [[Mandaeans|Mandaean]] and [[Yazidi]] communities are at the risk of elimination due to [[ethnic cleansing]] by [[Islamism|Islamic]] extremists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm|title=Iraq's Mandaeans 'face extinction'}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/meast/08/15/iraq.main/index.html?iref=topnews Iraqi officials: Truck bombings killed at least 500]&lt;/ref&gt;

A May 25, 2007 article notes that in the past seven months only 69 people from Iraq have been granted [[Immigration to the United States#Asylum for refugees|refugee status]] in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;Ann McFeatters: [http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/opinion/317322_mcfeatters27.html Iraq refugees find no refuge in America]. ''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'' May 25, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
{{section stub}}

==Ireland==

For most of the last eight centuries of [[Irish history]] discrimination in Ireland has been experienced in terms of oppression against the indigenous Irish people by a succession of English rulers beginning with the English supported [[Norman invasion of Ireland|Norman invasion of Ireland in 1169]]. This persecution was felt in terms of laws forbidding land ownership (the [[Penal Laws]]), restrictions on freedom of religion (persecution of the Roman Catholic faith, following the Protestant reformation in England), denial of the right to vote or hold office and inaction during the [[The Great Famine]] leading to approximately 1 million deaths.&lt;ref&gt;Demography (official journal of the Population Association of America), Vol. 23, No. 4 (Nov., 1986), pp. 543-562. Fertility Trends, Excess Mortality, and the Great Irish Famine - 
Phelim P. Boyle, Cormac O Grada.
This paper estimates mortality and fertility rates prevailing in Ireland during the 25-year period before the Great Irish Famine of 1845-1849. A technique is developed to estimate the age-specific mortality level during the Famine and the number of Famine-related deaths. The paper concludes that fertility rates were declining during the period 1821-1845 and that the effects of the Famine were especially severe on the very young and the very old. Ignoring deaths among emigrants, it is estimated that one million individuals perished as a result of the Famine. The analysis permits year-by-year reconstruction of the Irish population age structure for the period 1821-1851.
&lt;/ref&gt; In cases of wars and rebellions, such as the [[Cromwellian conquest of Ireland]], [[Irish Rebellion of 1798]] and the [[Irish War of Independence]] of [[1919]]-[[1921]] [[war crimes]], massacres and atrocities where committed by British forces or British supported paramilitaries. The [[Shelta]] or [[Irish Travellers]], a traditionally nomadic ethnic group once speaking their own language have also experienced persecution in past and modern times from both previous British authorities and also from the Irish people.

Following independence in [[1921]] there was traditionally  very little [[immigration]] by non-whites to the Republic of Ireland due to historic [[poverty]], though in recent times growing prosperity in the country (see: [[Celtic Tiger]]) has attracted increasing numbers of [[immigrants]], mainly from Africa, China, and Eastern Europe. Also the absence of any colonialist baggage has meant that foreign people are not drawn to Ireland by "[[mother country]]" factors that have affected other European countries. Descendants of [[Irish people]] who emigrated in the past have also started moving to the country. Most immigrants have settled in [[Dublin]] and the other cities. Though these developments have been accepted or tolerated by most, there has been a rise in racist attitudes among some sections of society. Much of this racism takes the form of verbal and other abuses. However, in 2002, a Chinese man Zhao liu Tao (29) was murdered in Dublin in what was described as the Republic of Ireland's first racially motivated murder. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1813880.stm] Later that year Leong Ly Min, another Chinese man who had lived in Dublin since 1979, was beaten to death by a gang who had been racially abusing him. [http://republican-news.org/archive/2002/August29/29anti.html]

Several issues relating to immigration have gained publicity in recent years. After [[1997]] and prior to [[2005]] any baby born in the Republic was entitled to Irish citizenship due to stipulations in the [[Good Friday agreement]]. This led to claims that many pregnant women from Africa (overwhelmingly from Nigeria),  having discarded their identification documentation, were travelling to Ireland expressly to give birth and thus allow their child to gain Irish citizenship. This became known as [[citizenship tourism]]. Following these alleged abuses of the loophole in the Irish Constitution a referendum on the issue was held. The referendum was duly carried and the loophole was closed.

In [[2005]] Nigerian student Olukunle Elukanlo was deported after his asylum application was rejected. Following an outcry by various left-wing activist groups at the decision he was allowed to return to complete his [[Leaving Cert]]. He was later deported. It is understood that one factor in the decision was Mr Elukanlo's recent plea of guilty in court to charges of driving without insurance or tax, along with the fact that he already has a previous conviction for a road traffic offence. The issue highlighted the growing numbers of failed asylum seekers being deported, an issue which is highly controversial to some (despite that fact that very few failed applicants are actually deported). This has been highlighted in recent television and radio programmes focused on exposing the extreme high cost to the Irish taxpayer of processing false asylum claims in addition to the cost of returning bogus asylum-seekers to their country of origin. 

The large majority of Irish people support their country's membership of the European Union, but increasingly large numbers resent migrants from outside the Union coming to Ireland expressly for the purpose of claiming asylum, without having applied for asylum in other countries along their route as is required by international law. There are several "anti-racism" groups active in the Republic, as well as those seeking tighter immigration laws such as the [[Immigration Control Platform]].

==Israel==
On 22 February 2007, the [http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cerd/ United Nations Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination] will consider the report submitted by Israel under Article 9 of the [[International Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Racial Discrimination]]. The report states that  “Racial discrimination is prohibited in Israel. The State of Israel condemns all forms of racial discrimination, and its government has maintained a consistent policy prohibiting such discrimination”. [http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cerd/docs/CERD_C_471_Add2_En.doc]
 
However, this report was challenged by several reports submitted to the Committee by other bodies. The [[Association for Civil Rights in Israel]] alleges “Israel's discriminatory planning practices”, the “discriminatory permit regime” and “egregious and systemic discrimination against Palestinians based solely on their national origin . . . reminiscent of policies characteristic of an Apartheid regime.” [http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cerd/docs/ngos/acri-ShadowReport.pdf] [[Adalah: The Legal Center for Arab Minority Rights in Israel]] alleges that “the State of Israel pursues discriminatory land and housing policies against Palestinian citizens of Israel” and that “the needs of  Palestinian citizens of Israel are systematically disregarded” [http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cerd/docs/ngos/ADALAH%E2%80%99S-Feb07.pdf] A joint report submitted by 19 Israeli, Palestinian and international NGOs alleges “State laws and institutions that dispossess the indigenous Palestinian and Syrian populations”. [http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cerd/docs/ngos/coverletter.pdf]

Also see [[Israeli Arab#Discrimination|Israeli Arab discrimination]], [[Anti-arabism#Anti-Arabism in Israel|Anti-Arabism in Israel]] and [[Racism in Israel]]. See: [http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/830750.html Haaretz:UN panel to hear Israel respond to charges of bias against Arabs]

==Italy==
''See [[Lega Nord|Northern League (Italy)]]''
{{section stub}}

==Ivory Coast==
In the past recent years the Ivory Coast has seen a resurgence in ethnic tribal hatred and religious intolerance.  In addition to the many victims among the various tribes of the northern and southern regions of the country that have perished in the ongoing conflict, foreigners residing or visiting the Ivory Coast have also been subjected to violent attacks. According to a report by Human Rights Watch, the Ivory Coast government is guilty of fanning ethnic hatred for its own political ends.&lt;ref&gt;
[news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/Africa/1932930.stm Ivory Coast "fanning ethnic hatred"]&lt;/ref&gt;  

In 2004, the [[Congrès Panafricaine des Jeunes Patriotes|Young Patriots]] of Abidjan, strongly [[nationalist]] organisation, rallied by the State media, plundered possessions of foreign nationals in [[Abidjan]]. Calls for violence against whites and non-Ivorians were broadcast on national radio and TV after the Young Patriots seized control of its offices. Rapes, beatings, and murders of white expatriates and local [[Arab diaspora|Lebanese]] followed. Thousands of expatriates and Lebanese fled. The attacks drew international condemnation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/11/19/wapp19.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2004/11/19/ixnewstop.html The night westerners were hunted for being white - Telegraph]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/newsitems/200411/s1242699.htm Europeans flee Ivory Coast violence. 13/11/2004. ABC News Online]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Japan==
{{Further|[[Ethnic issues in Japan]]}}
Japanese society, with its ideology of homogenity, has traditionally been [[Arudou Debito#Otaru onsen lawsuit|intolerant]] of ethnic and other differences.  It is safe to say that there has been a growing sense of [[xenophobia]] since it has opened borders to foreigners.  For example, the [[Dutch people|Dutch]] sailors landed on the Japanese shore were characterized by their "butter-like" [[body odor]], hairiness, and unsophisticated behavior.  Those who were identified as different might be considered "polluted" —- the category applied historically to the [[Castes|outcasts]] of Japan, particularly the hisabetsu buraku, "discriminated communities," often called [[burakumin]], a term some find offensive —- and thus not suitable as marriage partners or employees. Men or women of [[multiracial|mixed ancestry]], those with family histories of certain diseases, and [[Demography of Japan|foreigners]], and members of [[minority groups]] faced [[discrimination]] in a variety of forms. In 2005, a [[United Nations]] report expressed concerns about racism in Japan and that government recognition of the depth of the problem was not total.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unic.or.jp/new/pr05-057-E.htm |title=Press Conference by Mr Doudou Diène, Special Rapporteur of the Commission on Human Rights |accessdate=2007-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BBC"&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4671687.stm "Japan racism 'deep and profound".] [[BBC News]] ([[2005-07-11]]). Retrieved on [[2007-01-05]].&lt;/ref&gt; The author of the report, [[Doudou Diène]] ([[United Nations Special Rapporteur|Special Rapporteur]] of the [[UN Commission on Human Rights]]), concluded after a nine-day investigation that racial discrimination and xenophobia in Japan primarily affects three groups: [[Ethnic issues in Japan#Japanese minorities|national minorities]], [[Dekasegi|Latin Americans of Japanese descent]], mainly [[Japanese Brazilians]], and foreigners from "poor" countries.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite web |url=http://www.imadr.org/geneva/2006/G0610396.pdf |title='Overcoming "Marginalization" and "Invisibility"', International Movement against all forms of Discrimination and Racism |accessdate=2007-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

[[Japan]] accepted just 16 [[refugees]] in 1999, while the [[United States]] took in 85,010 for resettlement, according to the UNHCR. [[New Zealand]], which is smaller than Japan, accepted 1,140 refugees in 1999. Just 305 persons were recognized as refugees by Japan from 1981, when Japan ratified the [[U.N.]] [[Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees]], to 2002. &lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0WDQ/is_2003_Feb_24/ai_98002254 Japan's refugee policy]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iwanami.co.jp/jpworld/text/ClosedCountry01.html Questioning Japan's 'Closed Country' Policy on Refugees]&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese Minister [[Taro Aso]] has called Japan a “one race” nation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://search.japantimes.co.jp/member/member.html?nn20051018a7.htm Aso says Japan is nation of 'one race']&lt;/ref&gt;The Japanese government must endeavour to educate its citizens to eschew racism and xehophobia and I know Japanese to be very peaceful and friendly.  Racism is a canker and it can destroy people.

==South Korea==
Like their Japanese neighbors, [[Koreans]] tend to equate [[nationality]] or [[citizenship]] with membership in a single, homogeneous [[ethnic group]] or "[[race]]" (minjok, in Korean).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amren.com/mtnews/archives/2005/05/biracial_people.php Biracial People Face Discrimination in Korea]&lt;/ref&gt; A common language and culture also are viewed as important elements in Korean identity. The idea of multiracial or multiethnic nations, like [[Canada]] or the [[United States]], strikes many Koreans as odd or even contradictory. Both [[Japan]] and [[South Korea]] are among the world's most ethnically homogeneous nations. It has been criticized that South Korean schools often hire only white Americans who apply to teach English, because Koreans regard fair skin color as representative of "American" or "English"-ness. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=11826937 NPR : Ethnic Bias Seen in South Korea Teacher Hiring]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blogtoplist.com/rss/racism.html Racism]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Madagascar==
Ethnic tensions in Madagascar often produce violent conflict between the highlanders and coastal peoples. The Merina people in particular are often the targets of violence especially during political campaigns to elect a new president.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/1987383.stm Ethnic strife rocks Madagascar]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Malaysia==
Malaysia is multi–ethnic country, with [[Malay (ethnic group)|Malay]]s making up the majority—close to 52% of the population. About 30% of the population are [[Chinese Malaysian]]s—Malaysians of Chinese descent)—and [[Indian Malaysian]]s—Malaysians of Indian descent—comprise about 8% of the population.{{Facts|date=November 2007}} 

Economic policies designed to favour [[Bumiputra]]s (ethnic Malays), including affirmative action in public education, were implemented in the 1970s in order to defuse inter-ethnic tensions following the [[May 13 Incident]] in [[1969]]. However, these policies have not been fully effective in eradicating poverty among rural Bumiputras and have further caused a backlash especially from Chinese and Indian minorities. The policies are enshrined in the [[Article 153 of the Constitution of Malaysia|Malaysian constitution]] and questioning them is technically illegal.{{Facts|date=November 2007}}

Both major ethnic groups have their own control and power. UMNO, the ruling political party, depends on the majority Malay population for votes by using laws that give Malays priority over other races in areas such as employment.{{Facts|date=November 2007}} However, Chinese Malaysians control about 90 percent of the non-government sector, and they rarely employ Malays.{{Facts|date=November 2007}}

==Mauritania==
{{Further|[[Slavery in Modern Africa]]}}
[[Slavery in Mauritania]] persists despite its abolition in 1980 and affects the descendants of black Africans abducted into [[slavery]] before generations, who live now in [[Mauritania]] as "black [[Moors]]" or ''[[haratin]]'' and who partially still serve the "white Moors", or ''bidhan'', as slaves. The practice of slavery in Mauritania is most dominant within the traditional upper class of the Moors. For centuries, the so-called Haratin lower class, mostly poor black Africans living in rural areas, have been considered natural slaves by these Moors. Social attitudes have changed among most urban Moors, but in rural areas, the ancient divide is still very alive.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L18334379.htm Reuters AlertNet - Slavery still exists in Mauritania]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The ruling bidanes (the name means literally white-skinned people) are descendants of the [[Sanhaja]] [[Berbers]] and [[Beni Hassan]] Arab tribes who emigrated  to northwest [[Africa]] and present-day [[Western Sahara]] and [[Mauritania]] during the [[Middle Ages]]. Many descendants of the Beni Hassan tribes today still adhere to the [[supremacist]] ideology of their ancestors. This ideology has led to oppression, discrimination and even enslavement of other groups in the Mauritania.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?ReportId=70522 Fair elections haunted by racial imbalance]&lt;/ref&gt;  

According to some estimates, as many to 600,000 black Mauritanians, or 20% of the population, are still enslaved, many of them used as [[bonded labour]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/specials/1458_abolition/page4.shtml The Abolition season on BBC World Service]&lt;/ref&gt; Slavery in Mauritania was finally criminalized in August 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6938032.stm Mauritanian MPs pass slavery law]&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Netherlands==

In 2006 the [[Dutch Equal Treatment Commission]] got 694 requests to judge if a treatment legislation law had been broken. By far the most cases concerned [[Ageism|age discrimination]] (219), [[Racism|race discrimination]] followed (105). THE CGB brought out 261 judgements; 46 per cent of the cases where declared discrimination&lt;ref&gt;http://www.discriminatie.nl/?nieuws=171&lt;/ref&gt;.

In the early twenty-first century, Dutch politician [[Pim Fortuyn]] and film maker [[Theo van Gogh (film director)|Theo van Gogh]] both aired highly controversial views on immigration, particularly North African immigration. Adding further controversy were their subsequent murders. 

[[Pim Fortuyn]] was murdered by [[Volkert van der Graaf]], an animal rights activist, while [[Theo van Gogh (film director)|Theo van Gogh]] was murdered by [[Mohammed Bouyeri]], who was, in fact, of Moroccan descent.
{{section stub}}

==New Zealand==
Although New Zealand did not have an official policy along the lines of the [[White Australia Policy]], it did impose a poll tax on Chinese immigrants during the [[19th Century|19th]] and early [[20th Century|20th centuries]]. The poll tax was effectively lifted in the [[1930s]] following the invasion of China by Japan, and was finally repealed in [[1944]]. An official apology to the Chinese community of New Zealand was afforded by Prime Minister [[Helen Clark]] in 2004.

After World War II, immigration policy remained largely pro-British Isles until the mid-[[1980s]], although war refugees, non-Anglo-Celtic migrants, and foreign students studying under the [[Colombo Plan]] were allowed into the country in varying numbers. In the 1960s and 70s, large numbers of British [[immigrants]] and their proliferation in the trade union movement gave rise to popular Anglophobia in the media and on the streets. This was typified by talkback radio host Tim Bickerstaff's promotion of his "punch a Pom a day" campaign.

In the [[1975]] election campaign, opposition leader [[Robert Muldoon]] ran a scare campaign directed against [[Pacific Islands]] migrant workers, which was followed by a series of dawn raids on suspected overstayers. In response, a Pacific Islands group known as the [[Polynesian Panthers]] came to prominence. Indigenous land issues came to a head in the late [[1970s]] with Maori protesters occupying the Raglan Golf Course and Bastion Point, with land claims on both being settled by the following decade.

In [[1986]], country-of-origin rules were abolished, leading to major inflows of immigration for the first time in years, in particular large groups of skilled and business migrants. However, anti-immigration rhetoric directed mainly towards Asians from the populist [[Maori]] politician [[Winston Peters]] has since forced immigration rules to be tightened. A [http://www.hrc.co.nz/home/hrc/newsandissues/discriminationstillaconcernonracerelationsday.php 2003 study by the Human Rights Commission] showed 70% of New Zealanders think that Asians face significant discrimination. Many non-Polynesian ethnic minorities perceive official policy to be indifferent towards them in the context of the Maori-Pakeha bi-culturalism issue.

Individuals of [[Māori]] or other [[Polynesia]]n descent are often afforded preferential access to university courses, and scholarships.&lt;ref name="cre"&gt;UK [[Commission for Racial Equality]] website "Affirmative action around the world" http://www.cre.gov.uk/Default.aspx.LocID-0hgnew0l0.RefLocID-0hg01b001006009.Lang-EN.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Niger==
In October 2006, [[Niger]] announced that it would deport the [[Arabs]] living in the Diffa region of eastern Niger to Chad.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6087048.stm BBC NEWS | Africa | Niger starts mass Arab expulsions]&lt;/ref&gt; This population numbered about 150,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L25138454.htm Reuters AlertNet - Niger's Arabs say expulsions will fuel race hate]&lt;/ref&gt; While the government was rounding Arabs in preparation for the deportation, two girls died, reportedly after fleeing government forces, and three women suffered miscarriages. Niger's government had eventually suspended a controversial decision to deport Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6081416.stm BBC NEWS | Africa | Niger's Arabs to fight expulsion]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/refworld/rwmain?docid=469638881e UNHCR | Refworld - The Leader in Refugee Decision Support]&lt;/ref&gt;

In Niger, where the practice of [[slavery]] was outlawed in 2003, a study has found that more than 800,000 people are still slaves, almost 8% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/International/Story?id=813618&amp;page=1 The Shackles of Slavery in Niger]&lt;/ref&gt; .&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/4250709.stm Born to be a slave in Niger] By Hilary Andersson, BBC Africa Correspondent, Niger&lt;/ref&gt; Slavery dates back for centuries in Niger and was finally criminalised in 2003, after five years of lobbying by [[Anti-Slavery International]] and Nigerian human-rights group, Timidria.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0310/p07s01-woaf.html On the way to freedom, Niger's slaves stuck in limbo]&lt;/ref&gt;

Descent-based slavery, where generations of the same family are born into [[debt bondage|bondage]], is traditionally practiced by at least four of Niger’s eight ethnic groups. The slave masters are mostly from the lighter-skinned [[nomadic]] tribes — the [[Tuareg]], [[Fulani]], [[Toubou]] and [[Arabs]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smithsonianmagazine.com/issues/2005/september/bondage.php?page=3 Born into Bondage]&lt;/ref&gt; It is especially rife among the warlike [[Tuareg]], in the wild deserts of north and west Niger, who roam near the borders with Mali and Algeria. In the region of Say on the right bank of the river Niger, it is estimated that three-quarters of the population around 1904-1905 was composed of slaves.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.antislavery.org/homepage/resources/PDF/Full%20English%20Slavery%20in%20Niger.pdf Slavery in Niger]&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, the Tuareg swelled the ranks of their black slaves during war raids into other peoples’ lands. War was then the main source of supply of slaves, although many were bought at slave markets, run mostly by indigenous peoples.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=53497 NIGER: Slavery - an unbroken chain]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/International/Story?id=813618&amp;page=1 The Shackles of Slavery in Niger]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pakistan==
{{main|1971 Bangladesh atrocities}}
Prior to the independence of [[Bangladesh]] through the [[Bangladesh Liberation War]], the eastern region of [[Bengal]], populated by ethnic [[Bengali people]] was under [[Pakistan]]i occupation and called [[East Pakistan]]. The Pakistani ruling elite practiced systemic racial discrimination against the Bengali people&lt;ref name="Gendercide"&gt;[http://www.gendercide.org/case_bangladesh.html Case Study: Genocide in Bangladesh, 1971],'''gendercide.org'''&lt;/ref&gt;.The [[genocide]] and gendercidal atrocities perpetrated by the [[Muslim]]-majority [[Pakistan]]i regime during the liberation war of Bangladesh were strongly motivated by anti-Bengali [[racism]], especially against the Bengali Hindu minority. Bengalis were often compared with monkeys and chickens. The military commander during the Bangladesh war, general [[Amir Abdullah Khan Niazi]], referred to Bengalis as a 'low lying people.' The attitudes exhibited by the Pakistani ruling class against the ethnic Bengalis stands compared to the [[antisemitism]] of [[Nazi Germany]]&lt;ref name="Gendercide"/&gt;. Bengalis were called "scum" and "vermin" that were to be exterminated. Bengali Muslims were subjected as much to stereotyping and scapegoating as were Bengali Hindus.The journalist Dan Coggin quoted one Punjabi captain as telling him, 'We can kill anyone for anything. We are accountable to no one.' This is the arrogance of Power." &lt;ref&gt;Rummel, Death By Government, p. 335.&lt;/ref&gt; Bengalis were scapegoated, accused of [[dual loyalty]] with India, and discriminated against on the basis of what Pakistani authorities called "security concerns". This situation degenerated into outright anti-Bengali racism under the rule of General [[Ayub Khan]]&lt;ref&gt; {{cite book
 | last = O'Leary
 | first = Brendan
 | authorlink = Brendan O'Leary
 | coauthors = Thomas M. Callaghy, Ian S. Lustick
 | title = Right-Sizing the State: The Politics of Moving Borders P179
 | origyear = 2001
 | accessyear = 2007
 | edition = 1st
 | publisher = Oxford University Press
 | language = English
 | isbn = 0199244901
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The minorities of Bangladesh, especially the [[Hindus]], were specific targets of the Pakistan army.&lt;ref name="usconsulate_cable_march31"&gt;U.S. Consulate (Dacca) Cable, Sitrep: [http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB79/BEBB6.pdf Army Terror Campaign Continues in Dacca; Evidence Military Faces Some Difficulties Elsewhere], March 31, 1971, Confidential, 3 pp&lt;/ref&gt; There was widespread killing of Hindu males, and rapes of women. More than 60% of the Bengali refugees that had fled to India were Hindus.&lt;ref name="usstatedept_south_asia_crisis"&gt;US State Department, "Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969-1976", Volume XI, South Asia Crisis, 1971", Page 165&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="kennedy"&gt;Kennedy, Senator Edward, "Crisis in South Asia - A report to the Subcommittee investigating the Problem of Refugees and Their Settlement, Submitted to U.S. Senate Judiciary Committee", November 1, 1971, U.S. Govt. Press, page 66. Sen. Kennedy wrote, "Field reports to the U.S. Government, countless eye-witness journalistic accounts, reports of International agencies such as World Bank and additional information available to the subcommittee document the reign of terror which grips East Bengal (East Pakistan). Hardest hit have been members of the Hindu community who have been robbed of their lands and shops, systematically slaughtered, and in some places, painted with yellow patches marked 'H'. All of this has been officially sanctioned, ordered and implemented under martial law from Islamabad."&lt;/ref&gt; This widespread violence against Hindus was motivated by a policy to purge East Pakistan of what was seen as Hindu and Indian influences. The West Pakistani rulers identified the Bengali culture with Hindu and Indian culture, and thought that the eradication of Hindus would remove such influences from the majority Muslims in East Pakistan.&lt;ref name="sundaytimes6_13_71"&gt;The Sunday Times, London, June 13, 1971, ""The Government's policy for East Bengal was spelled out to me in the Eastern Command headquarters at Dacca. It has three elements: 1. The Bengalis have proved themselves unreliable and must be ruled by West Pakistanis; 2. The Bengalis will have to be re-educated along proper Islamic lines. The - Islamization of the masses - this is the official jargon - is intended to eliminate secessionist tendencies and provide a strong religious bond with West Pakistan; 3. When the Hindus have been eliminated by death and fight, their property will be used as a golden carrot to win over the under privileged Muslim middle-class. This will provide the base for erecting administrative and political structures in the future."&lt;/ref&gt;

It should be pointed out however that three ethnic Bengalis (Bogra, Suhawardy and Chundigarh) held the office of Prime Minister of Pakistan.

Historian Christoffe Jaffrelot argues in his landmark work "Pakistan. Nationalism without a Nation" that contemporary Pakistan is essentially little more than a [[Punjabi people|Punjabi]] racial [[ethnocracy]].He refers to the phenomenon as the "Punjabization of Pakistan"&lt;ref name="Jaffrelot"&gt; Christophe Jaffrelot, Pakistan: Nationalism Without A Nation, Zed Books (May 17, 2002),ISBN 1842771175&lt;/ref&gt;He observes systemic ethnic and cultural [[irredentism]] in Pakistan that intentionally minimizes and disparages non-Punjabis (such as the [[Sindhi people|Sindhi]],[[Baluch]] or [[Pukhtun]] ethnic minoroties). The Pakistani government machinery is heavily dominated by Punjabis, and systemic discrimination, as well as underrepresentation, against non-Punjabis in the country is the norm.&lt;ref name="Jaffrelot"/&gt; Endemic and systematic discrimination against the [[Baluch]] has given rise to Baluch militants such as [[Nawab Akbar Bugti]] and the [[Balochistan Liberation Army]], which seeks to build an independent Baluch country. Again, this is not the complete story, ethnic Baloch have achieved high political positions within Pakistan, such as  former President Leghari or former Prime Minister Jamali, whilist Pakhtuns are actually overrepresented in the army, and civil servie (and three, Ayub Khan, Yayha Khan and Ishaq Khan have been President) Other ethnic and sectarian strife in Pakistan that has it's roots in racism, or perceptions of race, are the [[Muhajir Urdu]] movement, and [[Pashtun people|Pashtun]] nationalism. Also 

==Russia and other post-Soviet states==
{{further|[[Racism in modern Russia]], [[Liberal Democratic Party of Russia]], and [[History of the Jews in Russia and the Soviet Union]]}}
Racism inside Russia is quite a modern post-[[USSR]] phenomenon that has been steadily growing in the past decade. In the 2000s, [[neo-Nazi]] groups inside [[Russia]] have risen to include as many as tens of thousands of people. [http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2005/08/14/MNGUSE7N2D1.DTL] Racism against the [[peoples of the Caucasus]], Africans, Central Asians and East Asians (Vietnamese, Chinese, etc.) is an ever-increasing problem. [http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=726]

A Pew Survey showed that of those who believed some religions are more violent than others; 10% of Russians named Judaism as the most violent. [http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=811]  This was the highest percentage outside the Muslim world. Furthermore, a previous poll showed that 25% of Russians had an unfavorable view of Jews. [http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795] Racism towards central Asians is said to be even more widespread.

==Slovenia==
[[Roma people]] are the main target of Slovenian racists, although situation is gradually improving and problems arise mostly from personal issues, while legislation is more or less egalitarian. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.humaniteinenglish.com/article441.html Slovenia: Chasing out the Roma&lt;/ref&gt;

==Spain==
{{further|[[Pureza de sangre]], [[Bartolomé de Las Casas]], and [[Eduardo Galeano]]}}
At the end of the ''[[Reconquista]]'', [[Spanish Inquisition]] imposed ''[[pureza de sangre]]'' ("[[racial purity]]") against Jews and Muslims.
Discovery of the [[New World]] also led to the famous [[Valladolid Controversy]], in which [[Bartolomé de Las Casas]] opposed [[Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda|Sepúlveda]]'s denegation of the existence of "Indian souls". ''See [[Eduardo Galeano]]'s ''The Veins of South America'' ''.

Racist abuse aimed at black footballers has been reported at Spanish football league matches in recent years. This has led to protests and UEFA fines against clubs whose supporters continue the abuse. Several players in the Spanish league including Barcelona player [[Samuel Eto'o]] have spoken out against the abuse. In 2006, Real Zaragoza player [[Ewerthon]] stated : "the Spanish Federation have to start taking proper measures and we as black players also have to act.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/football/europe/4751876.stm Eto'o makes anti-racism protest] BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sudan==
In the Sudan, [[black people|black]] African captives in the civil war were often [[slavery in modern Africa|enslaved]], and female prisoners were often used sexually, with their [[Arab]] captors claiming that Islamic law grants them permission.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.brandeis.edu/projects/fse/Pages/islamandslavery.html&lt;/ref&gt;  According to [[CBS News|CBS news]], slaves have been sold for US$50 apiece.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/1999/01/25/world/main29927.shtml Curse Of Slavery Haunts Sudan] CBS News. [[January 25]], [[1998]]&lt;/ref&gt; In September, 2000, the [[U.S. State Department]] alleged that "the Sudanese government's support of [[slavery]] and its continued military action which has resulted in numerous deaths are due in part to the victims' religious beliefs."&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2000/US/09/05/state.dept.religion/index.html U.S. State Department report says 'religious intolerance remains far too common' around world. September 6, 2000] CNN US News&lt;/ref&gt; Jok Madut Jok, professor of History at [[Loyola Marymount University]], states that the abduction of women and children of the south by north is [[slavery]] by any definition. The government of Sudan insists that the whole matter is no more than the traditional tribal [[feuding]] over resources.&lt;ref&gt; Jok Madut Jok (2001), p.3&lt;/ref&gt; 

It is estimated that as many as 200,000 people had been taken into slavery during the [[Second Sudanese Civil War]]. The slaves are mostly [[Dinka]] people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iabolish.org/slavery_today/in_depth/sudan-genocide.html War and Genocide in Sudan]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://journalism.nyu.edu/pubzone/livewire/archived/the_lost_children_of_sudan/ The Lost Children of Sudan]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sweden==
According to the report ''Racism and Xenophobia in Sweden'' by the Board of Integration Muslims are exposed to the most racial harassment in Sweden. Almost 40% of the interviewed said they had witnessed verbal abuse directed at Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.se/article.php?ID=2363&amp;date=20051025 The Local: Muslims face most racism in Sweden]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Taiwan==
The [[Nationality Law of the Republic of China]] has been criticized&lt;ref&gt;[http://jidanni.org/foreigner/ Not allowed to be Taiwanese]&lt;/ref&gt; for its methods of determining which immigrants get citizenship.

==Trinidad==
Trinidad is a melting pot of cultures and has been also a place of great ethnic tensions between the politically and economically empowered African-Caribbean and  Indo-Caribbean people.
Trinidad and Tobago is home to 1.3 million people, wheras 95% live on Trinidad and 5% live on Tobago. Around 39% of Trinidadians are of African decent and 43% is of Indian decent. Racism exists on every level of society although both ethnic groups mix fairly well in everyday life. 
Africans usually live in the urban areas, notably the East West corridor while Indians usually live in rural areas surrounding the sugar cane planations. &lt;br /&gt;
Tension existed between the two ethnic groups from the day African slaves achieved emancipation and Indians from India came to work on the farms. Africans accused the Indians from stealing their jobs because Indians worked for cheap wages. 
Most Africans then migrated to the urban areas, notably Port of Spain and to other villages around the industrial areas. Indians usually remained in the areas surrounding the sugar cane plantations to continue agriculture.
There has been long calls of discrimination between the two ethnic groups, and also with religion. Whites and Christians were usually accepted into high school while if you were from an Indian family, Hindu or Muslim your chances were slim.
Racism exists in Trinidad for many reasons. The biggest issue is politics. The two major political parties are marginalized between race. Politically, the Africans are in power. Afro-Trinidadians are accused of discriminating against East Indians in the government sector such as jobs, housing, health and scholarships. Housing and media licensing is a  huge issue where as Africans are preferred receiving these privileges. Indians continuously protest against crime which usually target those of Indian decent. Rural Indians are long neglected where their consituencies are usually flooded out and underdeveloped. Whereas the agriculture sector is domininatly Indian, their have been complaints about the blatant neglect of this sector by the government. 
Indians usually accuse the government for trying to "Africanize" the country. 
Although Africans hold the government and the economy (which is huge from today's high oil prices), Indian-Trinidadians are predominant in the professional field such as businessmen, doctors, teachers, lawyers..etc. Thus, the majority of the middle class are Indians. Africans usually accuse Indians of having a better life and thus justified in having preference in the government.
Although 18% of the country is mixed, intermarriage between Africans and Indians remain a controversial issue especially with Indians. Indians accuse Africans for discriminating during boom years, crime, nepotism. Indians are usually discriminated because of their names. &lt;br /&gt;
Indians usually think of Africans as violent, uneducated, ugly, inconsiderate, involved in gangs and lives in ghettos. Africans usually think of Indians as cliquish, conceited, unsociable and intolerant. 
In modern times, tension is getting worse. 
There have been discrimination on the religious area. Christians usually are classified superior to non Cristian religions. Hindus and Muslims have long complained about discrimination; such an issue is the issuing a radio license to a prominent Hindu group and the persecution of a well known Muslim activist when he protested against crime under anti-terrorism laws. 
 
==Turkey==
{{further| [[Pan-Turkism]], [[Pan-Turanism]] and [[Greco-Turkish relations]]}}
The [[Istanbul Pogrom]] directed against Turkey's Greek minority resulted in the deaths of 16 Greeks and 1 Armenian.
The supporters of [[Nationalist Movement Party|MHP]] (Nationalist Movement Party) (also known as [[Grey Wolves]]) advocate the supremacy of Turkish race and promote hatred against [[Armenians]], [[Greeks]] and "separatist" [[Kurds]] in Turkey. Smaller [[right-wing]] groups like "National Socialist Turkish Movement" [http://www.nsth.cjb.net] and followers of Turkish racist [[Nihal Atsiz]] [http://www.nihalatsiz.org] also promote [[hate speech]] and [[violence]] against [[Kurds]], [[Africans]], and [[Jews]]. None of these activities are prosecuted by Turkish authorities. Recently, in the course of [[Accession of Turkey to the European Union|Turkey's accession to the EU]], fringe nationalist groups (often with racist tones) are reported to gain considerable support among Turkish youth.

==Uganda==
In the 1970s [[Uganda]] and other East African nations implemented racist policies that targeted the Asian population of the region. Uganda under [[Idi Amin]]'s leadership was particularly most virulent in its anti-Asian policies. In August 1972, Idi Amin declared what he called an "economic war", a set of policies that included the expropriation of properties owned by Asians and Europeans. Uganda's 80,000 Asians were mostly [[India]]ns born in the country, whose ancestors had come to Uganda when the country was still a British colony. [http://www.ugandamission.net/aboutug/articles/amin.html] [http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/august/7/newsid_2492000/2492333.stm]

The forced expulsion of Uganda's entire Asian population attests to the persecution of Asian peoples residing in the country at the time. Today, Asian/Indian residents of Uganda continue to face marginalization being given an inferior status.

==United Kingdom==
[[Image:AS 1900s postcard 01.jpg|thumb|300px|This [[postcard]] from the [[1900s]] depicts an Englishman calling "BOY!" to a Chinese man to bring him a drink. The caption reads "The Call of the East."]]
There were [[race riot]]s across the [[United Kingdom]] in [[1919]]: [[South Shields]], [[Glasgow]], London's [[East End; London|East End]], [[Liverpool]], [[Cardiff]], [[Barry, Wales|Barry]], and [[Newport]]. There were further riots by immigrant and minority populations in East London during the [[1930s]] and [[Notting Hill]] in the [[1950s]].

In the 1980s, perceived societal racism, discrimination and [[poverty]] - alongside further perceptions of powerlessness and oppressive policing - sparked a series of riots in areas with substantial [[British African-Caribbean community|African-Caribbean]] populations.&lt;ref name="scarman"&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/bbc_parliament/3631579.stm Q&amp;A: The Scarman Report 27] BBC Online. April 2004. Accessed ''[[6 October]] [[2006]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; These "uprisings" (as they were described by some in the community) took place in [[St Pauls, Bristol|St Pauls]] in 1980, [[Brixton riot (1981)|Brixton]], [[Toxteth riots|Toxteth]] and [[Moss Side]] in 1981, St Pauls again in 1982, [[Notting Hill Gate]] in 1982, Toxteth in 1982, and [[Handsworth riots|Handsworth]], [[Brixton riot (1985)|Brixton]] and [[Broadwater Farm riot|Tottenham]] in 1985.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.warwick.ac.uk/CRER/differentreality/timeline.html A Different Reality: minority struggle in British cities] [[University of Warwick]]. Centre for Research in Ethnic Relations. Accessed ''[[6 October]] [[2006]]''&lt;br&gt; ° [http://www.eco.utexas.edu/~hmcleave/357Limpossibleintro.pdf#search=%22riots%20uprisings%20brixton%22 The 1981 Brixton Uprisings] "The Riot not to work collective". "''...What has changed since last year's uprisings''". London 1982. Accessed ''[[6 October]] [[2006]]''&lt;/ref&gt; 

The report identified both "racial discrimination" and a "racial disadvantage" in Britain, concluding that urgent action was needed to prevent these issues becoming an "endemic, ineradicable disease threatening the very survival of our society".&lt;ref name="scarman"/&gt; The era saw an increase in attacks on Black people by white people. The ''Joint Campaign Against Racism'' committee reported that there had been more than 20,000 attacks on non-indigenous Britons including [[British Asian|Britons of Asian origin]] during 1985.&lt;ref&gt;Law and Order, moral order: The changing rhetoric of the Thatcher government. [http://socialistregister.com/socialistregister.com/files/SR_1987_Taylor.pdf online]. Ian Taylor. ''Accessed [[6 October]] [[2006]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

More recently in [[2001]], there have been both the [[Bradford Riot|Bradford riots]] and the [[Oldham Riots]]. These riots have followed cases of perceived racism - either the public displays of racist sentiment (including crimes against members of ethnic minorities which were subsequently ignored by the authorities), or, as in the [[Brixton Riots]], [[racial profiling]] and alleged harassment by the [[police]] force. In [[2005]], there have been [[2005 Birmingham riots|Birmingham riots]] between the [[Black British]] and [[British Asian]] communities, with the spark for the riot being an alleged gang rape of a teenage black girl by a group of Asian men. 

The [[British Crime Survey]] reveals that in 2004, 87,000 people from black or minority ethnic communities said they had been a victim of a racially motivated crime. They had suffered 49,000 violent attacks, with 4,000 being wounded. At the same time 92,000 white people said they had also fallen victim of a racially motivated crime. The number of violent attacks against whites reached 77,000, while the number of white people who reported being wounded was five times the number of black and minority ethnic victims at 20,000. Most of the offenders (57%) in the racially motivated crimes identified in the British Crime Survey are not white. White victims said 82% of offenders were not white.&lt;ref&gt;[http://card.wordpress.com/2006/11/12/the-hidden-white-victims-of-racism/ The hidden white victims of racism]&lt;/ref&gt;

Racism in one form or another was widespread in Britain before the [[twentieth century]], and during the [[1900s]] particularly towards Jewish groups and immigrants from Eastern Europe. The British establishment even considered [[Irish people]] a separate and degenerate race until well into the [[19th Century]]. 

Since [[World War I]], public expressions of white supremacism have been limited to [[far-right]] political parties such as the [[British Union of Fascists]] in the [[1930s]] and the [[British National Front]] in the [[1970s]], whilst most mainstream politicians have publicly condemned all forms of racism. However, anecdotal evidence suggests that racism remains widespread, and some politicians and public figures have been accused of excusing or pandering to racist attitudes in the media, particularly with regard to [[immigration]]. There have been growing concerns in recent years about [[institutional racism]] in public and private bodies, and the tacit support this gives to crimes resulting from racism, such as the murder of [[Stephen Lawrence]], Gavin Hopely and Ross Parker.

The [[Race Relations Act 1965]] outlawed public discrimination, and established the [[Race Relations Board]]. Further Acts in [[1968]] and [[1976]] outlawed discrimination in employment, housing and social services, and replaced the Race Relations Board with [[Commission for Racial Equality]]. The [[Human Rights Act 1999]] made organizations in Britain, including public authorities, subject to the [[European Convention on Human Rights]]. The [[Race Relations Act 2000]] extends existing legislation for the public sector to the police force, and requires public authorities to promote equality.

There have been tensions over [[immigration]] since at least the early [[1900s]]. These were originally engendered by hostility towards Jews and immigrants from [[Russia]] and [[Eastern Europe]]. Britain first began restricting immigration in [[1905]] and has also had very strong limits on immigration since the early [[1960s]]. Legislation was particularly targeted at members of the [[Commonwealth of Nations]], who had previously been able to migrate to the UK under the [[British Nationality Act 1948]]. Virtually all legal immigration, except for those claiming refugee status, ended with the [[Immigration Act 1971]]; however, free movement for citizens of the [[European Union]] was later established by the [[Immigration Act 1988]]. Legislation in [[1993]], [[1996]] and [[1999]] gradually decreased the rights and benefits given to those claiming refugee statues ("asylum seekers"). 582,000 people came to live in the UK from elsewhere in the world in 2004 according to the office of National Statistics.

Some commentators believe that a huge amount of racism, from within all communities, has been undocumented within the UK, adducing the many British cities whose populations have a clear racial divide. While these commentators believe that race relations have improved immensely over the last thirty years, they still believe that [[racial segregation]] remains an important but largely unaddressed problem, although research [http://www.london.gov.uk/gla/publications/factsandfigures/dmag-briefing-2005-38.pdf] has shown that ethnic segregation has reduced within England and Wales between the [[United Kingdom Census 1991|1991 Census]] and [[United Kingdom Census 2001|2001 Census]].

The [[United Kingdom]] has been accused of "sleepwalking toward apartheid" by [[Trevor Phillips]], chair of that country's [[Commission for Racial Equality]]. Philips has said that Britain is fragmenting into isolated racial communities: "literal black holes into which no one goes without fear and trepidation and nobody escapes undamaged". Philips believes that racial segregation in Britain is approaching that of the United States. "You can get to the point as they have in the U.S. where things are so divided that there is no turning back." &lt;ref name=Freeman&gt;Freeman, Simon. [http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2-1792559,00.html "Britain urged to wake up to race crisis"], The Times, September 22, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

The BBC has reported that the latest crime statistics appear to support Phillips' concerns. They show that race-hate crimes increased by almost 600 per cent in [[London]] in the month after the [[7/7|July 7 bomb attacks]], with 269 more offenses allegedly "motivated by religious hatred" reported to the [[Scotland Yard|Metropolitan Police]], compared to the same period last year. &lt;ref name=Freeman/&gt;

In 2007 racist remarks made by contestants on the [[Big Brother (UK)|Celebrity Big Brother]] TV series against Bollywood actress [[Shilpa Shetty]] caused widespread outrage, not least in the [[UK]] with the British public phoning in to make Shetty the series winner and the other ethnic minority contestant [[Jermaine Jackson]] the runner up. Demonstrators in [[Banglore]] burned effigies of the TV Channel's directors.&lt;ref name="BLINK"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blink.org.uk/pdescription.asp?key=13808&amp;grp=1&amp;cat=197|publisher="[[BLINK]]"|title="Channel 4 should have licence withdrawn, says Ken "|}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scotland===
It has been reported that racial minorities are underrepresented in the police force [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/4684429.stm]. Philomena de Lima noted that Scots sometimes feel there is "no problem here" because ethnic minorities are regarded as small in number, "invisible", and "silent." However, she found that in most schools, at least 4% of students were ethnic minorities. In the urban areas tensions between Whites and Pakistanis occasionally flare up. In the past [[football (soccer)|football]] (soccer in US English) has at times divided on racial lines with "Asian teams" versus "Scottish teams" causing conflict. Though not yet on the same scale as the longstanding Scottish sectarianism between Catholic and Protestant. There is however a deep seated racism towards foreigners in Scotland, especially those from Pakistan. Several items regarding this type of racism in Scotland are reported here. [http://news.scotsman.com/topics.cfm?tid=562].

In 2005-6, 1,543 victims of racist crime in Scotland were of Pakistani origin, while more than 1,000 victims were classed as being "white British".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.scotsman.com/scotland.cfm?id=479212007 Scotsman.com News - Almost 20 race-hate crimes a day in Scotland]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kriss Donald]] was a [[Scotland|Scottish]] fifteen-year-old who was kidnapped and murdered in [[Glasgow]] in [[2004]].Five [[British Asian]] men were later found guilty of racially-motivated violence; those convicted of murder were all sentenced to life imprisonment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/glasgow_and_west/5409734.stm BBC NEWS | Scotland | Glasgow and West | Kriss attacked 'for being white']&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[BBC]], in [[2002]], has [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/2277959.stm reported] on poll conducted by [[System Three]] which "suggested
that one in four Scots admitted to being strongly or slightly racist" and that "almost 50% said they did not believe it was racist to use terms such as 'Chinky' or 'Paki' in relation to food or shops. (Although it should be noted that "Paki's" can often be used as a word meaning convenience store, regardless of the nationality of the store or the people working in it.) 

However, there are indications that the Scottish authorities and people are well aware of the problem and are trying to tackle it. Among the Scottish under 15 years old there is the positive sign that, "younger white pupils rarely drew on racist discourses." [http://www.scotland.gov.uk/library5/education/mepess-05.asp]

There is also a strong current of anti-English prejudice in Scotland; see [[Anglophobia]].

===Northern Ireland===
Racism in the United Kingdom is particularly acute in [[Northern Ireland]], which has prompted ''[[The Guardian]]'' newspaper to label it the "race hate capital of Europe" [http://www.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,11374,1120113,00.html]. Despite having the smallest numbers of non-whites in the UK it has the highest levels of racist violence in the country (racially motivated attacks are at 16.4% per 1000 of the minority population, whilst in [[England]] and [[Wales]] the figure is 12.6%).

More recently non-white people, especially Chinese, have started to live in Northern Ireland, primarily in the capital [[Belfast]]. Northern Ireland is the only region of the United Kingdom to have a Chinese assembly member in its devolved government, Anna Lo of Chinese origin and belonging to the Alliance Party. Discrimination takes many forms such as the spraying of racist graffiti, intimidation, assaults, general harassment, protection racketing, vandalism and house burning. Attempts to build a mosque in Portadown were met by much opposition; the plan was eventually dropped. However recently the Police Service of Northern Ireland in liaison with local politicians have managed to improve community relations between migrants and local communities, leading to a noticeable decrease in racism in general.

==Tanzania==
The [[Zanzibar Revolution]] of January 12, 1964 put an end to the local Arab dynasty. As many as 17,000 Arabs were massacred by the descendants of black African [[Arab slave trade|slaves]], according to reports, and thousands of others were detained and their property either confiscated or destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://channel4.empireschildren.co.uk/category/chapters/index.php?chapter=472&amp;cat=3 Country Histories - Empire's Children]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  |url=http://whosfaultisit.blogspot.com/2006/09/homemade-genocide-arab-world-is.html |title=A Homemade Genocide  |last=Heartman |first=Adam |authorlink= |coauthors= |date=[[2006-09-26]] |publisher=Who's Fault Is It?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==United States of America==
{{main|Racism in the United States}}
[[Image:1900sc Mammy Card Interracial.jpg|thumb|right|250px|This racist item from the [[1900s]] shows a denigratiing depiction of black women.]]

Many historians have argued that racism has been an integral part of the [[United States of America]] since it was first colonized by [[Europe]]ans. Historically, the country has been dominated by a [[settler|settler society]] of religiously and ethnically diverse [[European Americans]]. Major racially structured institutions include slavery, settlement, Indian reservations, segregation, residential schools (for American Indians), and internment camps. Racial stratification has occurred in employment, housing, education and government. Although racial discrimination was largely criminalized in the mid-20th century, major inequalities persist. 

The heaviest burdens of [[racism]] in the country have fallen upon [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]], [[Asian Americans|Asian]]s, [[African American]]s, [[Latin Americans]] and some other [[Immigration to the United States|immigrant groups]] and their descendants. Racist attitudes, or [[prejudice]], are still held by substantial portions of the population. Members of every American ethnic group have perceived racism in their dealings with other groups.

===Slavery===

The history of '''slavery in the United States''' (1619-1863) began soon after the [[British colonization of the Americas|English colonists]] first settled in [[Colony of Virginia|Virginia]] and lasted until the passage of the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th Amendment to the U.S. Constitution]]. In the very early decades of the institution, there was ''[[indentured servitude]]'', which typically lasted a period of four to seven years for [[white people|white]] and [[black people|black]] alike; by 1662 the American incarnation of [[slavery]] was established by court ruling. By the end of the [[17th century]] slavery was far more common in the [[Southern Colonies|Southern colonies]] than in the [[Thirteen Colonies|North]].

From about the 1640s until 1865, people of [[Africa]]n descent were legally enslaved within the boundaries of the present [[United States]], mostly by [[European American|whites]], but also by a number of [[Native Americans in the United States|American Indians]] and free blacks. The vast majority of this slaveholding was in the [[southern United States]]; approximately one Southern family in four held slaves prior to war&lt;!--which war? Based on the following sentence, I'd guess the revolution.--&gt;. According to the [[United States Census, 1860|1860 U.S. census]], fewer than 385,000 individuals (i.e. 1.4% of [[White American]]s in the country, or 4.8% of southern whites) owned one or more slaves.&lt;ref&gt;Grooms, R.M.[http://americancivilwar.com/authors/black_slaveowners.htm "Dixie's censored subject - Black slaveholders"], ''The Barnes Review'' via americancivilwar.com, 1997. Retrieved October 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Olsen, O.H. [http://www.southernhistory.net/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=9406&amp;mode=thread&amp;order=0&amp;thold=0 " Historians and the extent of slave ownership in the Southern United States."], ''Civil War History'' via southernhistory.net, December 2004. Retrieved October 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 95% of blacks lived in the South, comprising one-third of the population there as opposed to 1% of the population of the [[Northern United States|North]].&lt;ref&gt;James McPherson, Drawn with the Sword, page 15&lt;/ref&gt;

The wealth of the U.S. in the first half of the 19th century was greatly enhanced by this exploitation of [[negro]] race slaves.&lt;ref&gt;Horton and Horton pg. 7. The Hortons write, "The slave trade and the products created by slaves' labor, particularly [[cotton]], provided the basis for America's wealth as a nation, underwriting the country's [[Industrial Revolution|industrial revolution]] and enabling it to project its power into the rest of the world."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.digitalhistory.uh.edu/historyonline/con_economic.cfm "Was slavery the engine of economic growth?"], ''Digital History''. Retrieved October 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; But with the [[Union (American Civil War)|Northern]] victory in the [[American Civil War|Civil War]], the slave-labor system was abolished in the south and the large southern [[cotton]] plantations became much less profitable. Northern [[Technological and industrial history of the United States|industry]], which had expanded rapidly before and during the war, surged even further ahead of the South's [[Agriculture in the United States|agricultural]] economy. Industrialists came to dominate many aspects of the nation's life, including social and [[Politics of the United States|political affairs]]. The planter [[aristocracy]] of the South disappeared. The rapid economic development following the Civil War laid the groundwork for the modern [[Economy of the United States|U.S. industrial economy]].

Approximately 12 million Black Africans were shipped to the [[Americas]] from the 17th to the 19th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;Ronald Segal, ''The Black Diaspora: Five Centuries of the Black Experience Outside Africa'' (New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 1995), ISBN 0-374-11396-3, page 4. "It is now estimated that 11,863,000 slaves were shipped across the Atlantic. [Note in original: Paul E. Lovejoy, "The Impact of the Atlantic Slave Trade on Africa: A Review of the Literature," in ''Journal of African History'' 30 (1989), p. 368.] ... It is widely conceded that further revisions are more likely to be upward than downward."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/6445941.stm Quick guide: The slave trade], BBC, March 15, 2007. Retrieved October 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Of these, 5.4% (645,000) were brought to what is now the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen D. Behrendt, David Richardson, and David Eltis, [[W. E. B. Du Bois Institute|W. E. B. Du Bois Institute for African and African-American Research]], [[Harvard University]]. Based on "records for 27,233 voyages that set out to obtain slaves for the Americas". Stephen Behrendt, "Transatlantic Slave Trade", ''Africana: The Encyclopedia of the African and African American Experience'' (New York: Basic Civitas Books, 1999), ISBN 0-465-00071-1.&lt;/ref&gt; The slave population in the U.S. had grown to 4 million by the 1860 Census.

===Treatment of slaves===
Historian [[Kenneth M. Stampp]] describes the role of coercion in slavery, “Without the power to punish, which the state conferred upon the master, [[Unfree labour|bondage]] could not have existed. By comparison, all other techniques of control were of secondary importance.” Stampp further notes that while rewards sometimes led slaves to perform adequately, most agreed with an [[Arkansas]] slaveholder, who wrote:

{{quote|Now, I speak what I know, when I say it is like ‘casting pearls before swine' to try to persuade a negro to work.  He must be made to work, and should always be given to understand that if he fails to perform his duty he will be punished for it.&lt;ref&gt;Stampp, The Peculiar Institution  pg. 171&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to both the Pulitzer Prize-winning historian [[David Brion Davis]] and the [[Marxism|Marxist]] historian [[Eugene Genovese]], treatment of slaves was both harsh and inhumane. Whether laboring or walking about in public, people living as slaves were regulated by legally authorized violence. Davis makes the point that, while some aspects of slavery took on a "welfare capitalist" look,:

{{quote|Yet we must never forget that these same "welfare capitalist" plantations in the Deep South were essentially ruled by terror.  Even the most kindly and humane masters knew that only the threat of violence could force gangs of field hands to work from dawn to dusk "with the discipline," as one contemporary observer put it, "of a regular trained army."  Frequent public floggings reminded every slave of the penalty for inefficient labor, disorderly conduct, or refusal to accept the authority of a superior.&lt;ref&gt;Davis pg. 196&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On large [[Plantation#Slavery, para-slavery and plantations|plantations]], slave overseers were authorized to [[bullwhip|whip]] and brutalize non-compliant slaves. [[Slave codes]] authorized, [[indemnity|indemnified]] or even required the use of violence, and were denounced by [[abolitionism|abolitionists]] for their brutality. Both slaves and free blacks were regulated by the [[Black Codes in the USA|Black Codes]], and had their movements monitored by [[slave patrol]]s conscripted from the white population which were allowed to use summary punishment against escapees, sometimes maiming or killing them. In addition to physical abuse and murder, slaves were at constant risk of losing members of their families if their owners decided to trade them for profit, punishment, or to pay debts. A few slaves retaliated by murdering owners and overseers, burning barns, killing horses, or staging work slowdowns. &lt;ref&gt;Genovese (1967)&lt;/ref&gt; Stampp, without contesting Genovese's assertions concerning the violence and [[sexual slavery|sexual exploitation]] faced by slaves, does question the appropriateness of a Marxian approach in analyzing the master-slave relationship.&lt;ref&gt;Stampp, Kenneth M. "Interpreting the Slaveholders' World: a Review."  Stampp writes, "Genovese writes with verve, and certainly he is never dull. But, in my opinion,his attempt to demonstrate the superiority of the Marxian interpretation of history must be adjudged a failure. Some may explain this by arguing that the book's point of view is not in fact very Marxian. My own explanation is that the antebellum South, with its essentially racial defense of slavery, and with its emphasis on caste rather than class, is just about as unpromising a place for the application of a Marxian interpretation of history as one can imagine."&lt;/ref&gt;

Genovese claims that because the slaves were the legal property of their owners, it was not unusual for enslaved black women to be raped by their owners, members of their owner's families, or their owner's friends. Children who resulted from such rapes were slaves as well, as they took the status of their mothers, unless freed by the slaveholder. Nell Irwin Painter and other historians have also documented that Southern history went "across the color line". Contemporary accounts by  [[Mary Chesnut]] and [[Fanny Kemble]], both married in the planter class, as well as accounts by former slaves gathered under the [[Works Progress Administration]] (WPA), all attested to the abuse of women slaves by white men of the owning and overseer class.

According to Genovese, slaves were fed, clothed, housed and provided medical care in the most minimal manner. It was common to pay small bonuses during the [[Christmas]] season, and some slave owners permitted their slaves to keep earnings and gambling profits. (One slave, [[Denmark Vesey]], is known to have won a lottery and bought his freedom.) In many households, treatment of slaves varied with the slave's skin color. Darker-skinned slaves worked in the fields, while lighter-skinned house servants had comparatively better clothing, food and housing.&lt;ref&gt; Genovese (1967)&lt;/ref&gt;

As in President [[Thomas Jefferson]]'s famous household, it wasn't just an abstract issue of skin color. Sometimes planters used light-skinned slaves as house servants because they were relatives. Several of Jefferson's household slaves were children of his father-in-law and an enslaved woman, who were brought to the marriage by Jefferson's wife. [[Sally Hemings]], the young enslaved woman with whom Thomas Jefferson had a sexual relationship and children after his wife died, was half-sister to his wife.

However, Fogel argues that the material conditions of the lives of slaves compared favorably with those of free industrial workers. They were not good by modern standards, but this fact emphasizes the hard lot of all workers, free or slave, during the first half of the 19th century. Over the course of his lifetime, the typical slave field hand received about 90 percent of the income he produced.&lt;ref name="weiss"/&gt;

In a survey, 58 percent of historians and 42 percent of economists disagreed with the proposition that the material condition of slaves compared favorably with those of free industrial workers.&lt;ref name="weiss"/&gt;

Slaves were considered legal non-persons except if they committed crimes. An Alabama court asserted that slaves "are rational beings, they are capable of committing crimes; and in reference to acts which are crimes, are regarded as persons. Because they are slaves, they are incapable of performing civil acts, and, in reference to all such, they are things, not persons.&lt;ref&gt;Catterall, Helen T., Ed. 1926. Judicial Cases Concerning Slavery and the Negro. Washington, D.C.: Carnegie Institute, p. 247&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Cicatrices de flagellation sur un esclave.jpg|thumb|right|222px|Peter, a slave from [[Baton Rouge, Louisiana]], 1863. The scars are a result of a whipping by his overseer, who was subsequently discharged. It took two months to recover from the beating.]]

Influential leaders of the '''abolition movement''' (1810-60) included:
*[[William Lloyd Garrison]] - published ''[[The Liberator]]'' newspaper
*[[Harriet Beecher Stowe]] - author of ''[[Uncle Tom's Cabin]]''
*[[Frederick Douglass]] - nation's most powerful anti-slavery speaker, a former slave. Most famous for his book ''Narrative in the Life of Frederick Douglass''.
*[[Harriet Tubman]] - helped 350 slaves escape from the South, became known as a "conductor" on the [[Underground Railroad]].

===Apologies===
On [[February 24]] [[2007]] the [[Virginia General Assembly]] passed House Joint Resolution Number 728 acknowledging "with profound regret the involuntary servitude of Africans and the exploitation of Native Americans, and call for reconciliation among all Virginians."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/02/25/AR2007022500470.html |title= Virginia Apologizes for Role in Slavery |publisher= The Washington Post |first= Larry |last= O'Dell |date= [[2007-02-25]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the passing of this resolution, Virginia becomes the first of the 50 United States to acknowledge through the state's governing body their state's negative involvement in slavery. The passing of this resolution came on the heels of the 400th anniversary celebration of the city of [[Jamestown, Virginia]], which was one of the first slave ports of the American colonies.

===Arguments used to justify slavery===
In the 19th century, proponents of slavery often defended the institution as a "necessary evil". It was feared that emancipation would have more harmful social and economic consequences than the continuation of slavery. In 1820, [[Thomas Jefferson]] wrote in a letter that with slavery: 
{{quote|We have the wolf by the ear, and we can neither hold him, nor safely let him go. Justice is in one scale, and self-preservation in the other.&lt;ref&gt;Jefferson, Thomas. [http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/jefferson/159.html "Like a fire bell in the night"] Letter to [[John Holmes (U.S. politician)|John Holmes]], April 22, 1820. ''Library of Congress''. Retrieved October 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;|}}

[[Robert E. Lee]] wrote in 1856:
{{quote|There are few, I believe, in this enlightened age, who will not acknowledge that slavery as an institution is a moral and political evil. It is idle to expatiate on its disadvantages. I think it is a greater evil to the white than to the colored race. While my feelings are strongly enlisted in behalf of the latter, my sympathies are more deeply engaged for the former. The blacks are immeasurably better off here than in Africa, morally, physically, and socially. The painful discipline they are undergoing is necessary for their further instruction as a race, and will prepare them, I hope, for better things. How long their servitude may be necessary is known and ordered by a merciful Providence.&lt;ref&gt;Lee, R.E. [http://www.civilwarhome.com/leepierce.htm "Robert E. Lee's opinion regarding slavery]", letter to president [[Franklin Pierce]], December 27, 1856. ''civilwarhome.com''. Retrieved October 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;|}}

Some people believe that slavery was not as widespread as some say, and that African Americans also owned slaves. According to 1860 census, there were about 385,000 individuals who owned slaves. Even if all slaveholders had been white, that would amount to only 1.4 percent of [[European American]] in the country (or 4.8 percent of southern European Americans owning one or more slaves). However, in New Orleans over 3,000 free [[African American]] owned slaves, or 28 percent of the free African American in that city. [http://americancivilwar.com/authors/black_slaveowners.htm] [http://www.uwec.edu/Geography/Ivogeler/w188/south/charles/charles3.htm]

===Enslavement of Native Americans===
During the 17th century, [[Indian slavery]], the enslavement of Native Americans by [[European colonization of the Americas|European colonists]], was common. Many of these Native slaves were exported to off-shore colonies, especially the "sugar islands" of the [[Caribbean]]. Historian Alan Gallay estimates that from 1670-1715, British slave traders sold between 24,000 and 51,000 Native Americans from what is now the southern part of the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;Gallay, Alan. (2002) ''The Indian Slave Trade: The Rise of the English Empire in the American South 1670-171''. Yale University Press: New York. ISBN 0-300-10193-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

Slavery of Native Americans was organized in [[Las Californias|colonial]] and [[Alta California|Mexican California]] through [[Franciscan]] missions, theoretically entitled to ten years of Native labor, but in practice maintaining them in perpetual servitude, until their charge was revoked in the mid-1830s. Following the 1847-1848 [[Mexican-American War|invasion by U.S. troops]], Native Californians were enslaved in the new state from statehood in 1850 to 1867.&lt;ref&gt;Castillo, E.D. 1998. ''[http://www.ceres.ca.gov/nahc/califindian.html "Short Overview of California Indian History"], ''California Native American Heritage Commission'', 1998. Retrieved October 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Slavery required the posting of a bond by the slave holder and enslavement occurred through raids and a four-month servitude imposed as a punishment for Indian "[[vagrancy (people)|vagrancy]]".&lt;ref&gt;[[Delilah L. Beasley|Beasley, Delilah L.]] (1918). "Slavery in California," ''The Journal of Negro History'', Vol. 3, No. 1. (Jan.), pp. 33-44.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Slavery among Native Americans===
The [[Haida]] and [[Tlingit]] Indians who lived along the Southeast [[Alaska]]'s coast were traditionally known as fierce warriors and slave-traders, raiding as far as [[California]]. Slavery was hereditary, the slaves being [[prisoner of war|prisoners of war]]. Among some [[Pacific Northwest]] tribes, about a quarter of the population were slaves.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.digitalhistory.uh.edu/black_voices/voices_display.cfm?id=2 Digital "African American Voices"], ''Digital History''. Retrieved October 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.civilization.ca/aborig/haida/havwa01e.html "Haida Warfare"], ''civilization.ca''. Retrieved October 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Other slave-owning tribes of North America were, for example, [[Comanche]] of Texas, [[Creek people|Creek]] of Georgia, the fishing societies, such as the [[Yurok]], that lived along the coast from what is now Alaska to California, the [[Pawnee]], and [[Klamath]].&lt;ref name="britannica"/&gt;

===Post-slavery racism===
The [[Emancipation Proclamation]], issued on [[January 1]], [[1863]] by President [[Abraham Lincoln]], freed all [[slaves]] in the Southern states that had made up the Confederacy except slaveholding border states which had not seceded from the [[Union (American Civil War)|Union]], and those states already under Union control. Slavery ended in the whole country with the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th Amendment]] which was declared ratified on [[December 18]], [[1865]]. Despite this, discrimination continued in the United States with the existence of [[Jim Crow laws]], educational disparities, widespread criminal acts perpetrated by local and vigilante groups, and vigorous action by trade unions and their allies to enact [[Minimum wages]], which had the effect of pricing the typically unskilled and untrained black and immigrant laborers out of the labor market.

In the 1950s and 1960s a mass-based movement of predominantly African Americans capitalizing on the gains made by the New Deal engaged in a series of local movements, national lobbying and legal attacks on segregation and discrimination. These groups included the [[Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee]], the [[Congress of Racial Equality]], the [[NAACP Legal Defense Fund]], and a variety of local groups and labor unions. This movement culminated in the passage of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] and the [[Voting Rights Act]].

:"I have a dream that my four little children will one day live in a nation where they will not be judged by the color of their skin but by the content of their character" &amp;mdash; [[Martin Luther King, Jr.|Martin Luther King]], ''[[I Have a Dream|"I Have a Dream"]]'' speech at the Lincoln Memorial, Washington D.C. ([[28 August]], [[1963]]).

While attention to race relations in the United States has been focused largely on that between European Americans and African Americans, the changing racial makeup of the American population (when Asian Americans, Latinos, Arab Americans, Native Hawaiians and non-[[English people|English]] European Americans), began to advance higher in political representation and slowly but surely climbed the socioeconomic ladder) at the beginning of the twenty first century has caused many voices to call for the inclusion of other races in the equation.  It is estimated that by 2050, European Americans will comprise less than 50% of the total population (Latinos, for example, will acount for 25% of the U.S. population).  Thinking about race relations in the United States is therefore broadening to include Latinos (the fastest growing ethnic group) and Asian Americans.  At this writing, at least four states, California, Texas, Hawaii, and New Mexico (and the District of Columbia) are deemed "majority minority" states, where European Americans are a minority of the population.  [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] dealt with similar issues on color-based racism, greater demands for tribal autonomy, fought social discrimination and economic disparities for a people whom encountered hardship and oppression for centuries after the first Europeans entered the land to become the United States.
  
===Discussion of "[[Reverse Racism]]"===
In order to combat long standing inequalities in the United States, a plan was devised to attempt more equaility in hiring practices and in advancement opportunities.  [[Affirmative action in the United States]] occurs in school admissions, job hiring, and government and corporate contracts.  Its intended beneficiaries are typically ethnic minorities (approximately 33% of the population, though women and those who may suffer from disabilities can also benefit.  Some claim that this type of action is racist, and in fact makes the European American male as the most disadvantaged group. Therefore, affirmative action has been the subject of numerous court cases, and has been contested on [[United States Constitution|constitutional]] grounds.  [[California]], [[Michigan]], and [[Washington]] have banned various forms of affirmative action by government organizations. According to U.S. Office of Personnel Management's annual report  ''"Federal Equal Opportunity Recruitment Program",'' a total of 48,033 new minority employees have been hired by the feds from FY 2001 to FY 2006.  During the same period there has been a net decrease of 3,960 [[European American]] male employees in federal jobs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://adversity.net/fed_stats/OPM2007/default.htm Feds Continue to Overhire Minorities in 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;
With 9 346 victims of hate crime violence between 1995 and 2002, [[European Americans]] are the second most targeted group for the racial &amp; ethnic categories combined, with African Americans being the first. There are more hate crimes against European Americans than against Hispanics, Asians, American Indians and Multiple race groups. European Americans are also the racial &amp; ethnic group the most frequently targeted for inter-racial crimes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.racismeantiblanc.bizland.com/005/06.htm Statistics on Anti-white racism &amp; hate-crime in the USA &amp; Canada]&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[US Department of Justice]] survey stated that more than 6.6 million violent crimes (murder, rape, assault and robbery) are committed in the [[United States]] each year, of which about 20%, are inter-racial crimes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.nbc15online.com/forums/thread/1695280.aspx The Sydney Morning Herald]&lt;/ref&gt; According to research done by [[Larry Elder]], a radio host and [[New York Times]] best-selling author, of the approximately 1,700,000 interracial crimes of violence each year, nearly 1,200,000 involved black-white crime, and 90% of these 1.2 million cases are committed by [[African Americans]] against [[European Americans]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.townhall.com/columnists/LarryElder/2000/10/26/the_color_of_racism The color of racism:: By Larry Elder]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=3722 Inter-Racial Crime: The Dirty Little Secret by John Perazzo]&lt;/ref&gt; African Americans are more than 50 times more likely to commit violent crimes against European Americans than vice versa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cornellsun.com/node/22263 Out of Control | The Cornell Daily Sun]&lt;/ref&gt;  

According to [[United States Department of Justice]] document Criminal Victimization in the United States, in the United States in 2005, 37,460 European American females were sexually assaulted or raped by a African American man, while between zero and ten African American females were sexually assaulted or raped by a European American man. There were overall 111,590 European American victims of rape/sexual assault in 2005. In those 111,590 cases the offender was European American in 44.5 percent of the cases and African American in 33.6 percent of the cases.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/abstract/cvusst.htm United States Department of Justice document]&lt;/ref&gt;

Double standard when it comes to interracial crime is significant. Somme people claim that the overwheliming majority of interracial crime involves European American victims and African or Hispanic American suspects, yet very few of these crimes are classified as "hate crimes." The opposite is assumed when a crime features a European American suspect and a minority victim. On Saturday, [[January 6]] [[2007]], [[Channon Christian]], 21, and [[Christopher Newsom]], 23, of Knoxville, Tennessee, went on a date from which they would never return. On their way to the home of another couple, they were carjacked and kidnapped. Over the next 24 hours they were beaten, gang-raped, tortured, and murdered. Some commentators complained that the murders highlighted a double standard in American journalism: that if Channon Christian and Christopher Newsom had been African American and their killers European American, their story would have received more attention.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jacksonville.com/apnews/stories/051707/D8P6ED601.shtml Critics say news media ignoring Knoxville couple slaying]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[2006 Duke University lacrosse case]] attracted widespread media attention almost from the moment it became public. The apparent circumstances—three European American males from privileged backgrounds at an elite university apparently taking advantage of a student and single mother from a crosstown historically African American college, trying to make ends meet by working as a stripper—seemed tailor-made for wall-to-wall coverage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsobserver.com/1185/story/563248.html newsobserver.com | Duke lacrosse players 'innocent']&lt;/ref&gt;

==="Interracial" Crime===
Minority racism is sometimes considered controversial because of theories of [[power (sociology)|power]] in society. Racist thinking among and between minority groups does occur, for example conflicts between African Americans and [[Korean Americans]] (notably in the [[1992 Los Angeles Riots]]) or between African Americans and Jews (such as the [[Crown Heights Riot|riots in Crown Heights]] in 1991 [http://www.recomnetwork.org/articles/01/08/16/0254240.shtml]) in various urban environments, new immigrant groups (such as [[Hispanics in the United States|Latinos]] [http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?pid=902]) or towards European Americans. [http://www.michnews.com/artman/publish/article_12516.shtml] [http://www.nola.com/news/t-p/frontpage/index.ssf?/base/news-4/1137481512176100.xml] 

There has been a long running racial tension between [[African Americans]] and [[Mexican Americans]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/world/na/displaystory.cfm?story_id=9587776 Race relations | Where black and brown collide | Economist.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/opinion/la-op-hernandez7jan07,1,414328.story?coll=la-news-comment&amp;ctrack=2&amp;cset=true Roots of Latino/black anger]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/10/14/national/main2089618.shtml Riot Breaks Out At Calif. High School, Melee Involving 500 People Erupts At Southern California School]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://.www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5192595&amp;ft=1&amp;f=1001]&lt;/ref&gt; There have been several significant riots in [[California]] prisons where Mexican American and African Americans inmates have targeted each other particularly, based on racial reasons.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jurist.law.pitt.edu/paperchase/2006/12/race-riot-put-down-at-california-state.php JURIST - Paper Chase: Race riot put down at California state prison]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsmine.org/archive/security/incarceration/racial-segregation-continues-in-california-prisons.txt Racial segregation continues in California prisons]&lt;/ref&gt; There have been reports of racially motivated attacks against African Americans who have moved into neighborhoods occupied mostly by Mexican Americans, and vice versa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/world/story/0,,2036580,00.html A bloody conflict between Hispanic and African American gangs is spreading across Los Angeles]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackamericaweb.com/site.aspx/bawnews/stateof/hutchinson105 The Hutchinson Report: Thanks to Latino Gangs, There’s a Zone in L.A. Wher���S���P�}m'��E���t�@�@���EQ�FB��d���P&gt;1X����&lt;��C��������
�AY�$p�emag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=9600]&lt;/ref&gt; There had also been cases in the late 1920s [[California]] in which [[Filipino American|Filipino]] [[immigrants]] have been victimized for moving into a predominantly European American neighbourhood, or for working in an overwhelmingly European American workplace.&lt;ref&gt;[http://opmanong.ssc.hawaii.edu/filipino/cali.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Recently there has also been an increase in racial violence between [[European American]] and Hispanic immigrants,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gjsentinel.com/news/content/news/stories/2007/07/25/7_25_07_ethnic_intimidation.html Late-night snack soured by racially motivated violence]&lt;/ref&gt; between European Americans and [[Native Hawaiians]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2007-03-06-hawaii-cover_N.htm?csp=34 Racial tensions are simmering in Hawaii's melting pot]&lt;/ref&gt; between [[Asian American|Asians]] and Hispanics&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2006/07/11/BAGO8JT0GL1.DTL 6 Asian boys arrested in beating of Latino]&lt;/ref&gt; and between [[Africans in the United States|African]] immigrants and African Americans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/06044/654613.stm African immigrants face bias from blacks]&lt;/ref&gt;  

The [[Aztlan]] movement has been described as racist.  The movement's goal involves the pursuit of repossessing the American southwest.  It has also been called the Mexican "reconquista"(re-conquest) whose name was inspired by the [[Reconquista|Spanish "reconquista"]] which led to the expulsion of the [[Moors]] from Spain. [http://www.aztlan.net]

According to gang experts and law enforcement agents, a longstanding race war between the [[Mexican Mafia]] and the Black Guerilla family, a rival [[African American]] [[prison gang]], has generated such intense racial hatred among Mexican Mafia leaders, or shot callers, that they have issued a "green light" on all African Americans.  A sort of gang-life fatwah, this amounts to a standing authorization for Latino gang members to prove their mettle by terrorizing or even murdering any African American sighted in a neighborhood claimed by a gang loyal to the Mexican Mafia. [http://www.blackamericaweb.com/site.aspx/bawnews/stateof/hutchinson105]

With 9 346 victims of hate crime violence between 1995 and 2002, [[European Americans]] are the second most targeted group for the racial &amp; ethnic categories combined, with African Americans being the first. There are more hate crimes against European Americans than against Hispanics, Asians, American Indians and Multiple race groups. European Americans are also the racial &amp; ethnic group the most frequently targeted for inter-racial crimes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.racismeantiblanc.bizland.com/005/06.htm Statistics on Anti-white racism &amp; hate-crime in the USA &amp; Canada]&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[US Department of Justice]] survey stated that more than 6.6 million violent crimes (murder, rape, assault and robbery) are committed in the [[United States]] each year, of which about 20%, are inter-racial crimes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.nbc15online.com/forums/thread/1695280.aspx The Sydney Morning Herald]&lt;/ref&gt; According to research done by [[Larry Elder]], a radio host and [[New York Times]] best-selling author, of the approximately 1,700,000 interracial crimes of violence each year, nearly 1,200,000 involved black-white crime, and 90% of these 1.2 million cases are committed by [[African Americans]] against [[European Americans]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.townhall.com/columnists/LarryElder/2000/10/26/the_color_of_racism The color of racism:: By Larry Elder]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=3722 Inter-Racial Crime: The Dirty Little Secret by John Perazzo]&lt;/ref&gt; African Americans are more than 50 times more likely to commit violent crimes against European Americans than vice versa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cornellsun.com/node/22263 Out of Control | The Cornell Daily Sun]&lt;/ref&gt;  

According to [[United States Department of Justice]] document Criminal Victimization in the United States, in the United States in 2005, 37,460 European American females were sexually assaulted or raped by a African American man, while between zero and ten African American females were sexually assaulted or raped by a European American man. There were overall 111,590 European American victims of rape/sexual assault in 2005. In those 111,590 cases the offender was European American in 44.5 percent of the cases and African American in 33.6 percent of the cases.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/abstract/cvusst.htm United States Department of Justice document]&lt;/ref&gt;

Double standard when it comes to interracial crime is significant. The overwheliming majority of interracial crime involves European American victims and African or Hispanic American suspects, yet very few of these crimes are classified as "hate crimes." The opposite is assumed when a crime features a European American suspect and a minority victim. On Saturday, [[January 6]] [[2007]], [[Channon Christian]], 21, and [[Christopher Newsom]], 23, of Knoxville, Tennessee, went on a date from which they would never return. On their way to the home of another couple, they were carjacked and kidnapped. Over the next 24 hours they were beaten, gang-raped, tortured, and murdered. Some commentators complained that the murders highlighted a double standard in American journalism: that if Channon Christian and Christopher Newsom had been African American and their killers European American, their story would have received more attention.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jacksonville.com/apnews/stories/051707/D8P6ED601.shtml Critics say news media ignoring Knoxville couple slaying]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[2006 Duke University lacrosse case]] attracted widespread media attention almost from the moment it became public. The apparent circumstances—three European American males from privileged backgrounds at an elite university apparently taking advantage of a student and single mother from a crosstown historically African American college, trying to make ends meet by working as a stripper—seemed tailor-made for wall-to-wall coverage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsobserver.com/1185/story/563248.html newsobserver.com | Duke lacrosse players 'innocent']&lt;/ref&gt;

== South Africa ==
See [[History of South Africa in the apartheid era]].
{{section stub}}

Government’s employment legislation reserves 80% of new jobs for [[black people]] and favours black owned companies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/magazine/story/0,,1691343,00.html Simon Wood meets the people who lost most when Mandela won in South Africa]&lt;/ref&gt; 

== Zimbabwe/Rhodesia ==
Until majority rule in [[1980]], the minority white government of [[Rhodesia]] (as [[Zimbabwe]] was then called) practised institutionalised racism similar in most respects to the [[apartheid]] system in [[South Africa]].  White Rhodesians "''lived in the best houses, owned most of the best land, enjoyed a high standard of living and controlled the executive, the legislature, the judiciary and the means of coercion."'' (Godwin, P. &amp; Hancock, I., 1993.  ''Rhodesians never Die'', Baobab Books, Harare, Zimbabwe.)

The laws enforcing [[racial segregation]], however, were not always welcomed by the local white community.  They were viewed as not only being racist, but expensive and unnecessary.  This was highlighted in an incident, called "[[Reps Theatre#"The Battle of the Toilets"|The Battle of the Toilets]]" in [[1960]], involving a new [[Reps Theatre|theatre]] that would be open to all races.

Twenty years after [[Zimbabwe#Independence|Independence]], whites in Zimbabwe remained a [[Market dominant minorities|market dominant minority]] through their continued ownership of the vast majority of [[arable]] land, the most valuable resource in a country like Zimbabwe where agriculture is the leading industry.  In [[2000]], the government, arguing that the country's landownership patters were the result of longtime failure to address the legacies of colonialism and racism in Zimbabwean society, began a controversial [[Land reform in Zimbabwe|land reform]] process directed at confiscating the land of the white resident farmers and redistributing it to the poor black majority.  Mugabe, however, has come under heavy criticism and accusations of having apportioned land to supporters, doing so in a disorganized and anarchical manner.  This was coupled with renewed criticisms (originally directed decades ago) that a comprehensive land reform has been long overdue. (Astrow, A., 1983, ''Zimbabwe: A revolution that lost its way?'', Zed Books, London)

== Footnotes ==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Racism by country or region|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>