<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061109223145|86812876" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5348421" pageid="5348421" ns="0" title="Racism by country"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-10T12:57:56Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In nineteenth century Europe and America, some scientists developed various theories about biological differences among [[race]]s, and these theories were in turn used to legitimize racist beliefs and practices. As did [[Michel Foucault]] show in ''Society Must Be Defended'' (1978-79), the old notion of "race" was biologized by racist scholars and [[eugenicists]], paving the way to twentieth century "[[state racism]]" (''[[Racism#From "racial theory" to "racism"|See above]]''). This work has since been rejected by the scientific community as flawed and even as [[pseudoscience]].

Today there are some scientists, mostly anthropologists who claim that "race", in the general sense in which the term is used, is a [[social construct]]: the way in which individuals are classified into racial groups varies from person to person, and from place to place, and from time to time. These scientists say that superficial characteristics which are associated with racial groupings are poor predictors of genetic variability. There can be more genetic variation within a racial grouping than between two racial groupings. They also point to the lack of well-defined boundaries to racial classifications; for example characteristics such as skin colour and facial appearance can be shown to vary as a continuum from place to place. Other scientists counter that "sex" and "species" are likewise seen by some as socially constructed. After all, humans and chimpanzees (or males and females) are far more genetically alike than different. According to this view, categories need not be absolute in order to have scientific utility. Other scientists, mostly biologists, who claim that race, sex and species are biologically significant concepts, and that despite their opposition to racism, deplore the misuse of scientifically significant language for political purposes.

====Argentina====
While [[Argentina]] has considered itself a crisol de razas or melting pot, it has only recently begun to recognize itself as a multicultural, multiracial society. The government of Argentina has taken significant formal steps toward the elimination of racial discrimination over the last decade. However, the measures provided by legal and institutional changes are still in the initial stages of implementation and have been substantially hindered by a lack of funds, the logistical and political complications associated with the transfer of power from one party to another in 1999, and Argentina's history of racism.

Most sources report Argentina's population as 97 per cent white (mostly of Italian and Spanish descent) and three percent mestizo (Amerindian' and European), Amerindian, or other nonwhite groups. 

The nineteenth century founders of the nation aimed to make Argentina a white nation through various policies aimed at eliminating ethnic minority populations, while simultaneously encouraging European immigration. The 1853 Constitution is still largely in force today, and the preference for European immigration remains explicit. Racial discrimination persists against indigenous peoples, immigrants, Afro-Argentines, mestizo Argentines, Jews and Arabs.
Argentina's indigenous peoples face struggles concerning fundamental issues of survival, maintenance of cultural and linguistic integrity, land rights and bilingual education. Furthermore, the small, impoverished, socially maligned population must fight for mere recognition. The indigenous population in Argentina according to the 2005 Complementary Survey of Indigenous Peoples, stands at approximately 318,700 people (0.8 percent of the total population)[http://www.indec.mecon.ar/webcenso/ECPI/index_ecpi.asp].

Immigration from other South American nations rose in the second half of the 20th century. [[Korean]] immigrants also began to arrive in significant numbers in the 1970s (totaling approximately 30,000 by 1998). The delayed 2000 census and the large number of undocumented immigrants makes an accurate assessment of recent immigration difficult, but the 1991 census counted close to five per cent of the total population as foreign born.

Politicians have used rising crime rates in the metropolitan Buenos Aires area to fuel xenophobia and to argue for further restrictions on immigrants. They blame immigrants for the rise in crime, despite the government's own statistics demonstrating that immigrants were not responsible for the majority of crimes. News reports on the proposed legislation referred to foreign workers as an "invasion' and also blamed them for lower wages and high unemployment.
Discrimination against Korean immigrants significantly worsened after a series of news reports in 1993 on a case of Korean grocers exploiting undocumented [[Bolivian]] immigrant workers and stealing electricity from the State appeared in the press. A previous popular image of Koreans as industrious changed to an image of Koreans as poorly integrated, exclusive, and not willing to learn Spanish. Their presence in good schools and neighbourhoods has been described as an invasion.

The [[Jewish]] population in Argentina is estimated at two per cent (the largest in Latin America and fifth worldwide). The most recent manifestations of Argentina's history of anti-Semitism include the terrorist bombings of the Israeli embassy (1992) and the Argentine Jewish Mutual Aid Association (1994), the desecration of Jewish cemeteries and the prevalence of swastikas and anti-Semitic slogans among the graffiti on buildings (including government buildings) in Buenos Aires. Anti- Semitic attitudes are widespread among the populace, and many do not consider Jewish people to be truly Argentine. Anti-Semitism within security forces also remains a significant problem. For example, until popular agitation forced a change in 2000, a police manual contained racist and anti-Semitic expressions.

Former President [[Carlos Menem]], while his Syrian ancestry did not prevent him from being elected -- an important indicator of the lack of discrimination -- he was required to convert to Catholicism when he ran in 1989 (this prerequisite has since been abolished), and informal criticisms of him during his tenure were sometimes radicalized.

On 24 August 1994, the Argentine Constitution was amended in several ways that are relevant to the elimination of racial discrimination. In correspondence with international human rights instruments, new amendments prohibit discrimination, provide equal civil rights to nationals and foreigners, and recognize indigenous communities as previously-extant legal entities entitled to participation in relevant development issues. Under the auspices of the Instituto Nacional de Asuntos Indigenas (National Institute of Indigenous Affairs, INAT), various programmes have been established for furthering land re-distribution, bilingual education, health programmes, and rural economic development. Other articles allow for equal access to education, with protections for cultural identities and diversity, and give international human rights treaties, including the Convention on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination, equal standing with the Constitution.

==Austria==
Austria has sometimes been criticised of trying to sweep its Nazi past under the carpet, typified by the widely pronounced myth that Austria was a victim of Nazi aggression rather than a willing participant. This has its origins as an Allied propaganda tactic. This complacency was severely tested in the [[1986]] presidential race when it emerged that [[Kurt Waldheim]] (a former [[UN secretary general]]) had concealed (or forgotten) certain facts about his war-time military service with the [[Wehrmacht]]. The revelations caused much controversy in Austria as well as in the outside world. Nevertheless Waldheim was elected President. Controversy again erupted in [[2000]] when [[Jörg Haider]]'s centre-right [[Freedom Party]] entered into coalition with the conservative [[People's Party]] having gained 27% of the vote.

However much progress has been made with settling the disputes and compensation for Jews and others whose property and assets were seized during the Nazi era, with a deal completed in [[2001]]. Elections in [[2002]] saw a significant drop in support for the Freedom Party, with the party subsequently splitting into opposing factions. [[Jörg Haider]] now leads the "[[Alliance for the Future of Austria]]".

==Bulgaria==
Racism in Bulgaria has been geared towards the [[Roma people|gypsies]] who are perceived to be of different racial and ethnic background. However, not all Bulgarians are racist towards gypsies, and it really depends on the individual's upbringing, education, area where they lived, and other factors.
Bulgarian nationalists are also wary of the country's large [[Turkish people|Turkish]] minority because of their perceived ambitions for greater power in Bulgaria and potential separatism in areas where Turks predominantly live. The forced assimilation campaign of the late 80s and early 90s directed against ethnic Turks resulted in the permanent emigration of some 300,000 Bulgarian Turks to Turkey. During this period, Turks were forced to change their names to Slavic Bulgarian ones and Turkish culture was heavily suppressed. [[Muslim Bulgarians]] (ethnic Bulgarians practicing Islam) were also targeted as Islam was seen as a "foreign "Turkish element" that stood against Bulgarian interests.
The [[National Union Attack]] or Ataka, a party widely considered fanatically xenophobic, surprisingly won 10% of the popular vote at the recent [[2005]] elections.

==Canada==
{{POV-check-section|Canada Section}}

[[Canada]] often depicts its society as being a very progressive, tolerant, diverse, and [[multicultural]] nation. However, like every other country, Canada also has its own history of racism. Although the historical records are not very clear at the very beginnings of the country's history, one can argue that the first instance of racism in Canada occurred during the first trip of [[Jacques Cartier]] in [[1534]], when he brought two [[Iroquois]] more or less against their will back to [[France]], which greatly amused the [[List of French monarchs|French royal court]]. Later, although still not very clearly recognised in the mainstream culture (where it is more seen as territorial wars), much racism occurred between the French and the [[First Nations]] people, between First Nations tribes themselves (fuelled by alliances of certain tribes with the French, and others with the English), between the English and the First Nations, and between the English and the French. Although the country's history was influenced greatly by these wars, the relationships between all those ethnicities has changed a lot since the beginning of European settlement in Canada.

Moreover, there are notable records of [[slavery in Canada]] in the [[1700s]]. More than half of all Canadian slaves were [[First Nations|aboriginal]], and the [[United Empire Loyalists]] brought their slaves with them after leaving what became the [[United States]]. In [[1793]], [[Upper Canada]] governor [[John Graves Simcoe]] passed a bill making it illegal to bring a person into the colony for the purposes of enslavement, and slavery was fully outlawed in [[1834]]. Most of the emancipated slaves of African descent were then sent to settle [[Freetown]] in [[Sierra Leone]] and those that remained primarily ended up in segregated communities such as [[Africville]] outside [[Halifax, Nova Scotia|Halifax]], [[Nova Scotia]]. (Today there are four remaining slave [[cemetery|cemeteries]] in Canada: in [[Brome-Missisquoi Regional County Municipality, Quebec|St.-Armand]], [[Quebec]], [[Shelburne, Nova Scotia]] and [[Princeville, Ontario|Princeville]] and [[Chatham-Kent, Ontario|Dresden]] in [[Ontario]].)

Starting in [[1858]], [[China|Chinese]] "[[coolies]]" were brought to Canada to work in the mines and on the [[Canadian Pacific Railway]]. However, they were denied by law the rights of citizenship, including the right to vote, and in the [[1880s]], "[[Head Tax|head taxes]]" were implemented to curtail immigration from China. In [[1907]], a riot in [[Vancouver, British Columbia|Vancouver]] targeted Chinese and Japanese-owned businesses. In [[1923]], the federal government passed the ''[[Chinese Immigration Act of 1923|Chinese Immigration Act]]'', commonly known as the ''Exclusion Act'', prohibiting further Chinese immigration except under "special circumstances". The Exclusion Act was repealed in [[1947]], the same year in which [[Chinese Canadian]]s were finally given the right to vote.

Restrictions still existed on immigration from Asia. In [[1967]], these restrictions were repealed and Asian immigrants were given the same rights as any other group. In [[1999]], [[Adrienne Clarkson]], the child of Chinese immigrants who moved to Canada in [[1942]] under the "special circumstances" clause, became [[Governor General of Canada]]. [[Japanese Canadian]]s were also subject to anti-Asian racism, particularly during [[World War II]] when many Canadians of Japanese heritage &amp;mdash; even those who were born in Canada &amp;mdash; were forcibly moved to internment camps. The government of Canada officially made restitution for the treatment of Japanese Canadians in [[1988]].

Notable organizations in Canadian history have included the ''[[Parti national social chrétien]]'', and the ''[[Heritage Front]]''. Other notable individuals in this context include [[Adrien Arcand]], [[Ernst Zündel]], [[Doug Christie (lawyer)|Doug Christie]], [[Wolfgang Droege]] and [[Don Andrews]].

In 1982 [[The Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] was signed, legally assuring equal treatments, rights and freedoms without discrimination.

===More recently in Canada===

However, racism in Canada has not only been connected to immigration. French Canadians, including [[Acadian]]s, [[Québécois]] and [[Franco-Ontarien]]s, [[First Nations|aboriginals]] and Western Canadians have purportedly also been subject to discriminatory treatment in Canada. While having French recognised as an official language was seen as a step towards multiculturalism for Francophones, there has been nothing similar that can be described as culturally validating for Aboriginal Canadians. In fact, Canada's treatment of Aboriginal-Canadians is still governed by a document frequently described as racist, the [[Indian Act]].

==Finland==
[[Sami people]] were traditionally feared for being wizards and Russians for being criminals, but the fear was more cultural. In the nineteenth century, the ruling Swedish-speaking minority considered Finnish-speaking people to be a separate race and inferior to the Germanic race. The discrimination since transformed into mainly linguistic.

==France==
The French have a long history of ethnic and racial conflicts. [[Anti-Semitism]], a common trend in European history, is also highlighted in French history by events such as the [[Dreyfus Affair]] at the turn of the nineteenth century, and France's treatment of its Jewish population during the [[Vichy regime]]. Likewise, the treatment of North Africans and other former colonials during the colonial era, the atrocities committed in Algeria during the [[Algerian War of Independence|War of Independence]] (1954-1962) and also the [[Paris massacre of 1961]] are also signs of intolerance. The fact that Algerians formed the bulk of late-twentieth century immigration has raised delicate issues, which are exacerbated by the degradation of the general social situation. In the 1970s [[Jean Raspail]] wrote ''[[The Camp of the Saints]]'' which some felt implied African immigrants should be drowned or shot to prevent them from entering France.

In [[1998]] the Council of Europe's European Commission Against Racism and Intolerance (ECRI) made a report stating concern about racist activities in France and accused the French authorities of not doing enough to combat this. The report and other groups have expressed concern about organizations like [[Front National (France)]]. In a recent [[Pew Research Center|Pew Survey]], 47% of the French deem immigration from Eastern Europe to be a bad thing. A small minority shows signs of Anti-Semitism. Roughly 11% had an unfavorable view of Jews [http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795] and 8% felt that US policy was most influenced by the Jews [http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=803]. In the colonial age some French also displayed negative sentiments toward black Africans.

Nevertheless these judgments should be balanced by the following: Canadians had roughly the same percentage linking US policy to Jews as France did. Furthermore, France had been ruled by Jewish leaders during the twentieth century (most notably [[Léon Blum]] and [[Pierre Mendès-France]], who were both highly popular). Indeed, France has a long history of support for universalism dating back to the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] : the unenforced constitution of 1794 gave the right to vote to all "foreigners" (independently of any racial consideration) living in France for more than one year. The French also generally have a greater interest in African culture and aid to the region.

In late October of 2005, [[2005 Paris riots|violent riots]] erupted in north-east Paris, and later other cities around France, after two youths of North African origin were accidentally electrocuted after supposedly fleeing police.

==Germany==
{{main|Christian antisemitism|Anti-Judaism}}

The history of [[Germany]] has included many acts and policies of racism. If one includes pre-19th century acts of [[anti-Semitism]] as racism, the history stretches back to at least the eleventh century, when [[Henry II, Holy Roman Emperor]] expelled Jews from [[Mainz]] in 1012. Other acts of anti-Semitism included numerous bloody attacks on Jews living in the area in the thirteenth and fourteenth centuries, most notably the massacres of Jews in the 1340s after they were blamed for spreading the [[Black Death]].

{{further|[[Nazism]]}}
In the nineteenth century, Germany became one of the major centers of nationalist thought, with the ''[[Völkisch movement]]'', and also a major area for development of racial theories, many of them virulently racist ''[[Racism#From "racial theory" to "racism"|See above]]''. Anti-semitic campaigns in this period took on a definitely "racial" valence, as definitely distinct from a purely religious one.

The period after [[World War I]] led to an increased use of anti-Semitism and other racism in political discourse, for example among [[Erich Ludendorff|General Ludendorff]]'s followers, which was capped by the ascent of [[Adolf Hitler]] and his [[Nazi Party]] in 1933. [[Nazi racial policy]] and the [[Nazi Nuremberg Laws]] represented some of the most explicit racist policies in Europe in the twentieth century, and culminated in [[the Holocaust]], a systematic murdering of millions of Jews, [[Porrajmos|Gypsies]], disabled people and others "undesirables".

In the post-[[World War II]] era, German reconciliation with its anti-Semitic past has been a protracted experience.

Recent concerns about racism have centered around immigrants (''Ausländer''), who encounter prejudice when seeking jobs and apartments, or can even experience direct violent attacks by some right-wing groups. This pattern is similar to what is happening in some other European countries.

The immigrants came in two waves, the first in the 1950s, the so called ''Gastarbeiter'' (Guest Workers) and their families. These people came from countries such as [[Turkey]] and [[Yugoslavia]] in [[West Germany]], and [[Vietnam]] and [[Angola]] in [[East Germany]]. The ''Gastarbeiter'' were expected to remain on limited contracts, and then leave. Many did not.

Starting from the 1980s, the second wave were the ''Asylbewerber'' (Asylum Seekers) from countries such as [[Sri Lanka]] and [[Lebanon]]. This second group were considered by some locals to not be genuine cases, but so called ''Wirtschaftsflüchtlinge'' (Economic Migrants).



==India==
It is claimed by some activists[http://www.wcc-coe.org/wcc/what/jpc/echoes/echoes-17-04.html] that [[casteism]] practised in India is a form of racism, but this is debated by those who believe that casteism has nothing to do with physical attributes, unlike racism. At the UN world conference on racism (August 31 - September 7 2001) the Indian Government opposed the discussion of caste in the conference, saying that "the caste issue is not the same as racism"[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/1495052.stm]

==Indonesia==
See [[Jakarta Riots of May 1998]].

==Ireland==
Traditionally there has been very little immigration by non-whites to the Republic of Ireland due to historic poverty, though in recent times growing prosperity in the country (see: [[Celtic Tiger]]) has attracted increasing numbers of immigrants, mainly from Africa, China, and Eastern Europe. Also the absence of any colonialist baggage has meant that foreign people are not drawn to Ireland by "[[mother country]]" factors that have affected other European countries. Descendants of Irish people who emigrated in the past have also started moving to the country. Most immigrants have settled in [[Dublin]] and the other cities. Though these developments have been accepted or tolerated by most, there has been a rise in racist attitudes among some sections of society. Much of this racism takes the form of verbal and other abuses. However, in 2002, a Chinese man Zhao liu Tao (29) was murdered in Dublin in what was described as the Republic of Ireland's first racially motivated murder.[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1813880.stm] Later that year Leong Ly Min, another Chinese man who had lived in Dublin since 1979, was beaten to death by a gang who had been racially abusing him. [http://republican-news.org/archive/2002/August29/29anti.html]

Several issues relating to immigration have gained publicity in recent years. After [[1997]] and prior to [[2005]] any baby born in the Republic was entitled to Irish citizenship due to stipulations in the [[Good Friday agreement]]. This led to claims that many pregnant women (overwhelmingly from Nigeria) from Africa, having discarded their identification documentation were travelling directly to Ireland expressly to give birth and thus allow their child to gain Irish citizenship. This became known as [[citizenship tourism]]. Following these alleged abuses of the loophole in the Irish Constitution a referendum on the issue was held. The referendum was duly carried and the loophole was closed.

In [[2005]] Nigerian student Olukunle Elukanlo was deported after his asylum application was rejected. Following an outcry by various left-wing activist groups at the decision he was allowed to return to complete his [[leaving cert]]. The issue highlighted the growing numbers of failed asylum seekers been deported, an issue which is highly controversial to some (despite that fact that very few failed applicants are actually deported). This has been highlighted in recent television and radio programmes focused on exposing the extreme high cost to the Irish taxpayer of processing false asylum claims in addition to the cost of returning bogus asylum-seekers to their country of origin.

Many Irish people are very proud of being in the European Union, but increasingly large numbers resent migrants from outside the Union coming to Ireland expressly for the purpose of claiming asylum, without having applied for asylum in other countries along their route as is required by international law. There are several "anti-racism" groups active in the Republic, as well as those seeking tighter immigration laws such as the [[Immigration Control Platform]].

==Italy==
''See [[Northern League (Italy)]]''

==Japan==
''See [[Ethnic issues in Japan]]''

==Malaysia==
Economic policies designed to favour Bumiputras (including affirmative action in public education) were implemented in the 1970s in order to defuse inter-ethnic tensions following the [[May 13 Incident]] in 1969, but these have not been fully effective in eradicating poverty among rural bumiputras and have further caused a backlash of resentment on the part of non-bumi ethnic groups.


[[Malays]] are also facing 'silent' discrimination when the word 'Islam' is stated on the national identity card or known as MyKad. This limits the freedom of religion practice in Malaysia and clearly it is against the so-called freedom of religion practice as stated in the [[Constitution of Malaysia]] and are tied to Shalia laws as well as Civil law.

==Netherlands==
In the early twenty first century, Dutch politician [[Pim Fortuyn]] and film maker [[Theo Van Gogh (film director)]] both aired highly controversial views on immigration, particularly North African immigration. Adding further controversy were their subsequent murders.

==New Zealand==
Although New Zealand did not have an official policy along the lines of the [[White Australia Policy]], it did impose a poll tax on Chinese immigrants during the [[19th Century|19th]] and early [[20th Century|20th centuries]]. The poll tax was effectively lifted in the [[1930s]] following the invasion of China by Japan, and was finally repealed in [[1944]]. An official apology to the Chinese community of New Zealand was afforded by Prime Minister [[Helen Clark]] in 2004.

After World War II, immigration policy remained largely pro-British Isles until the mid-[[1980s]], although war refugees, non-Anglo-Celtic migrants, and foreign students studying under the [[Colombo Plan]] were allowed into the country in varying numbers. In the 1960s and 70s, large numbers of British immigrants and their proliferation in the trade union movement gave rise to popular anglophobia in the media and on the streets. In the [[1975]] election campaign, opposition leader [[Robert Muldoon]] ran a scare campaign directed against [[Pacific Islands]] migrant workers, which was followed by a series of dawn raids on suspected overstayers. In response, a Pacific Islands group known as the [[Polynesian Panthers]] came to prominence. Indigenous land issues came to a head in the late [[1970s]] with Maori protesters occupying the Raglan Golf Course and Bastion Point, with land claims on both being settled by the following decade.

In [[1986]], country-of-origin rules were abolished, leading to major inflows of immigration for the first time in years, in particular large groups of skilled and business migrants. However, anti-immigration rhetoric directed mainly towards Asians from the populist Maori politician [[Winston Peters]] has since forced immigration rules to be tightened. A [http://www.hrc.co.nz/home/hrc/newsandissues/discriminationstillaconcernonracerelationsday.php 2003 study by the Human Rights Commission] showed 70% of New Zealanders think that Asians face significant discrimination. Many non-Polynesian ethnic minorities perceive official policy to be indifferent towards them in the context of the Maori-Pakeha bi-culturalism issue.

==Northern Ireland==
Racism in the United Kingdom is particularly acute in [[Northern Ireland]], which has prompted ''[[The Guardian]]'' newspaper to label it the "race hate capital of Europe"[http://www.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,11374,1120113,00.html]. Despite having the smallest numbers of non-whites in the UK it has the highest levels of racist violence in the country (racially motivated attacks are at 16.4% per 1000 of the minority population, whilst in [[England]] and [[Wales]] the figure is 12.6%).

Traditionally there has been segregration, hatred and violence between Northern Ireland's two main communities: the Unionists/Loyalists, mostly Protestant, who want to remain within the UK and Nationalists/Republicans, mostly Catholic, who want a united Ireland. Following the partition of Ireland and the creation of Northern Ireland the government of the province was controlled by and for Protestants, with a policy of systematic discrimination against Catholics, who formed roughly 1/3 of the population. Tensions eventually erupted in 'the Troubles' in [[1968]], which saw a renewed campaign of [[PIRA|IRA]] activity and corresponding Loyalist paramilitary violence, the presence of British soldiers and extreme sectarianism fostered by frequent riots and violence.

More recently non-white people, especially Chinese, have started to live in Northern Ireland, primarily in the capital [[Belfast]]. The population of Northern Ireland is 99% white. Discrimination takes many forms such as the spraying of racist graffiti, intimidation, assaults, general harassment, protection racketing, vandalism and house burning. Attempts to build a mosque in Portadown were met by much opposition &amp;mdash; the plan was eventually dropped.

===Racism in Russia===
{{Main|Anti-national sentiment in Russia}}
Racism inside Russia is quite a modern post-[[USSR]] phenomenon that has been steadily growing in the past decade. In the 2000s, [[neo-Nazi]] groups inside [[Russia]] have risen to include as many as tens of thousands of people. [http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2005/08/14/MNGUSE7N2D1.DTL] Racism against the [[Caucasian peoples]], Africans and [[Central Asia]]ns is an ever increasing problem.

==Scotland==
It has been reported that racial minorities are underrepresented in the police force [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/4684429.stm]. Philomena de Lima noted that Scots sometimes feel there is "no problem here" because ethnic minorities are regarded as small in number, "invisible", and "silent." However, she found that in most schools, at least 4% of students were minorities. In the urban areas tensions between Whites and Pakistanis occasionally flare up. In the past [[football (soccer)|football]] (soccer in US English) has at times divided on racial lines with "Asian teams" versus "Scottish teams" causing conflict. There is however a more sinister and deep seated racism towards foreigners in Scotland, especially those from Pakistan. Several items regarding this type of racism in Scotland are reported here. [http://news.scotsman.com/topics.cfm?tid=562].

The [[BBC]], in [[2002]], has [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/2277959.stm reported] on poll conducted by [[System Three]] which "suggested
that one in four Scots admitted to being strongly or slightly racist" and that "almost 50% said they did not believe it was racist to use terms such as 'Chinky' or 'Paki' in relation to food or shops.

However, there are indications that the Scottish authorities and people are well aware of the problem and are trying to tackle it. Among the Scottish under 15 years old there is the positive sign that, "younger white pupils rarely drew on racist discourses." [http://www.scotland.gov.uk/library5/education/mepess-05.asp]

There is also a strong current of Anti-English Racism in Scotland see [[Anglophobia]]

==Spain==
{{further|[[Pureza de sangre]], [[Bartolomé de Las Casas]], and [[Eduardo Galeano]]}}

At the end of the ''[[Reconquista]]'', [[Spanish Inquisition]] imposed ''[[pureza de sangre]]'' ("[[racial purity]]") against Jews and Muslims.
Discovery of the [[New World]] also led to the famous [[Valladolid Controversy]], in which [[Bartolomé de Las Casas]] opposed [[Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda|Sepúlveda]]'s denegation of the existence of "Indian souls". ''See [[Eduardo Galeano]]'s ''The Veins of South America'' ''.

Spanish football fans have been known to make monkey noises at black players laeding to FA fines. Samuel Etoo has spoken out against this and so have the English national team who played there for a friendly.

==Soviet Union, Russia and other post-Soviet states==
{{further|[[Racism in Russia]], [[Liberal Democratic Party of Russia]], and [[History of the Jews in Russia and the Soviet Union]]}}.

The subject of racism in Russia is at present controversial and heated. However a Pew Survey showed that of those who believed some religions are more violent than others 10% of Russians named Judaism[http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=811] as the most violent. This was the highest percentage outside the Muslim world. Further a previous poll showed that 25% of Russians had an unfavorable view of Jews.[http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795] Racism towards Central Asians is said to be even more widespread.

==Turkey==
{{further| [[Pan-Turkism]], [[Pan-Turanism]] and [[Greco-Turkish relations]]}}

The [[Istanbul Pogrom]] directed against Turkey's Greek minority resulted in the deaths of 16 Greeks and 1 Armenian.
The supporters of [[Nationalist Movement Party|MHP]] (Nationalist Movement Party) (also known as [[Grey Wolves]]) advocate the supremacy of Turkish race and promote hatred against [[Armenians]], [[Greeks]] and "separatist" [[Kurds]] in Turkey. Smaller [[right-wing]] groups like "National Socialist Turkish Movement" [http://www.nsth.cjb.net] and followers of Turkish racist [[Nihal Atsiz]] [http://www.nihalatsiz.org] also promote [[hate speech]] and [[violence]] against [[Kurds]], [[Africans]], and [[Jews]]. None of these activities are prosecuted by Turkish authorities. Recently, in the course of [[Accession of Turkey to the European Union|Turkey's accession to the EU]], fringe nationalist groups (often with racist tones) are reported to gain considerable support among Turkish youth.

==United Kingdom==
[[Image:AS 1900s postcard 01.jpg|thumb|300px|This [[postcard]] from the [[1900s]] depicts an Englishman calling "BOY!" to a Chinese man to bring him a drink. The caption reads "The Call of the East."]]
There were [[race riot]]s across the [[United Kingdom]] in [[1919]]: [[South Shields]], [[Glasgow]], London's [[East End; London|East End]], [[Liverpool]], [[Cardiff]], [[Barry, Wales|Barry]], and [[Newport]]. There were further riots by immigrant and minority populations in East London during the [[1930s]], [[Notting Hill]] in the [[1950s]], and [[Brixton]], and [[Blackbird Leys]], [[Oxford]] in the [[1980s]]. More recently in [[2001]], there have been both the [[Bradford Riot|Bradford riots]] and the [[Oldham Riots|Oldham riots]]. These riots have followed cases of perceived racism - either the public displays of racist sentiment (including crimes against members of ethnic minorities which were subsequently ignored by the authorities), or, as in the [[Brixton Riots|Brixton]] riots, [[racial profiling]] and alleged harassment by the [[police]] force.

Racism in one form or another was widespread in Britain before the [[twentieth century]], and during the [[1900s]] particularly towards Jewish groups and immigrants from Eastern Europe. The British establishment even considered the [[Irish people|Irish]] a separate and degenerate race until well into the [[19th Century]]. 

Since [[World War I]], public expressions of white supremacism have been limited to [[far-right]] political parties such as the [[British Union of Fascists]] in the [[1930s]] and the [[British National Front]] in the [[1970s]], whilst most mainstream politicians have publicly condemned all forms of racism. However, anecdotal evidence suggests that racism remains widespread, and some politicians and public figures have been accused of excusing or pandering to racist attitudes in the media, particularly with regard to [[immigration]]. There have been growing concerns in recent years about [[institutional racism]] in public and private bodies, and the tacit support this gives to crimes resulting from racism, such as the murder of [[Stephen Lawrence]], Gavin Hopely and Ross Parker.

The [[Race Relations Act 1965]] outlawed public discrimination, and established the [[Race Relations Board]]. Further Acts in [[1968]] and [[1976]] outlawed discrimination in employment, housing and social services, and replaced the Race Relations Board with [[Commission for Racial Equality]]. The [[Human Rights Act 1999]] made organizations in Britain, including public authorities, subject to the [[European Convention on Human Rights]]. The [[Race Relations Act 2000]] extends existing legislation for the public sector to the police force, and requires public authorities to promote equality.

There have been tensions over [[immigration]] since at least the early [[1900s]]. These were originally engendered by hostility towards Jews and immigrants from [[Russia]] and [[Eastern Europe]]. Britain first began restricting immigration in [[1905]] and has also had very strong limits on immigration since the early [[1960s]]. Legislation was particularly targeted at members of the [[Commonwealth of Nations]], who had previously been able to migrate to the UK under the [[British Nationality Act 1948]]. Virtually all legal immigration, except for those claiming refugee status, ended with the [[Immigration Act 1971]]; however, free movement for citizens of the [[European Union]] was later established by the [[Immigration Act 1988]]. Legislation in [[1993]], [[1996]] and [[1999]] gradually decreased the rights and benefits given to those claiming refugee statues ("asylum seekers"). 582,000 people came to live in the UK from elsewhere in the world in 2004 according to the office of National Statistics.

Some commentators believe that a huge amount of racism, from within all communities, has been undocumented within the UK, adducing the many British cities whose populations have a clear racial divide. While these commentators believe that race relations have improved immensely over the last thirty years, they still believe that [[racial segregation]] remains an important but largely unaddressed problem, although research [http://www.london.gov.uk/gla/publications/factsandfigures/dmag-briefing-2005-38.pdf] has shown that ethnic segregation has reduced within England and Wales between the [[United Kingdom Census 1991|1991 Census]] and [[United Kingdom Census 2001|2001 Census]].

In England today there is in general an attitude of tolerance, but perhaps some resentment towards the perceived flood of immigrants (both legal and illegal), especially the 'Polish plumbers' that have seemingly flooded the country since the EU expanded in 2004 to incorporate 12 countries, many of them former Eastern-bloc.

==United States of America==
{{main|Racism in the United States}}
[[Image:1900sc Mammy Card Interracial.jpg|thumb|right|250px|This racist item from the [[1900s]] shows a denigratiing depiction of black women.]]

Many historians have argued that racism has been an integral part of the [[United States of America]] since it was first colonized by [[Europe]]ans. In general, the question of race and the practices of racism have been major issues in American politics and daily life since before the country became independent in the late eighteenth century, and continue to have a major role in political and social life today. Racism exists among members of every ethnic group and demographic. Specifically among those of African American, Caucasian, Jewish, Native American and Latin Heritages. All of these ethnic groups have racists within, and likewise all of these ethnic groups have members within that have been a victim of racism.

===Slavery===
In colonial America, before colonial slavery became completely based on racial lines, thousands of [[African]] slaves served [[European]], alongside other [[Europeans]] serving a term of [[indentured servitude]]. In some cases for African slaves, a term of service meant freedom and a land grant afterward, but these were rarely awarded, and few Africans became landowners this way. In [[1676]], [[Nathaniel Bacon]] led a [[Bacon's Rebellion|revolt]] against the Governor of [[Virginia]] and the system of exploitation he represented: exploitation of poorer colonists by the increasingly wealthy landowners. However, Bacon died, probably of [[dysentery]], and the revolt lost steam.

The central cause of concern to landowners was the unity of Bacon's populist movement. It raised the question to the landowners of how to divide the population politically in ways that would keep the poorer colnists divided enough to rule. To the Governor, the most threatening, and unexpected, aspect of Bacon's rebellion was its multi-racial aspect. So from that time on, the wealthy landowners determined that only Africans would be used as slaves &amp;mdash; and European colonists were promised whatever benefits would have gone to Africans had they continued to be indentured servants. The fuel of the racism was due to the fear of sex among Africans and Europeans. This relationship was specifically afraid of African, Native American, Asian, and Latin men with European women. The thousands of lynchings were testimony to this. This legacy is still seen in the antimiscegenation laws which were repealed only within the past few years. This change began the infamously long period of the American slave society, in which slaves were primarily used for [[agriculture|agricultural]] labor, notably in the production of [[cotton]] and [[tobacco]]. African slavery in the Northeast was less common, usually confined to [[involuntary domestic servitude]]. The social rift along color lines soon became engrained in every aspect of colonial American culture.

===Post-slavery racism===
The [[Emancipation Proclamation]], issued on [[January 1]], [[1863]] by President [[Abraham Lincoln]], freed all [[slaves]] in the Southern states that had made up the Confederacy except slaveholding border states which had not seceded from the [[Union (American Civil War)|Union]], and those states already under Union control. Slavery ended in the whole country with the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th Amendment]] which was declared ratified on [[December 18]], [[1865]]. Despite this, discrimination continued in the United States with the existence of [[Jim Crow laws]], educational disparities, widespread criminal acts perpetrated by local and vigilante groups, and vigorous action by trade unions and their allies to enact [[Minimum wages]], which had the effect of pricing the typically unskilled and untrained black and immigrant laborers out of the labor market.

In the 1950's and 1960's a mass based movement of predominantly African-Americans capitalizing on the gains made by the New Deal engaged in a series of local movements, national lobbying and legal attacks on segregation and discrimination. These groups included the [[Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee]], the [[Congress of Racial Equality]], the [[NAACP Legal Defense Fund]], and a variety of local groups and labor unions. This movement culminated in the passage of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] and the [[Voting Rights Act]].

:"I have a dream that my four little children will one day live in a nation where they will not be judged by the color of their skin but by the content of their character" &amp;mdash; [[Martin Luther King, Jr.|Martin Luther King]], ''[[I Have a Dream|"I Have a Dream"]]'' speech at the Lincoln Memorial, Washington D.C. ([[28 August]], [[1963]]).

While attention to race relations in the United States has been focused largely on that between European-Americans and African-Americans, the changing racial makeup of the American population at the beginning of the twenty first century has caused many voices to call for the inclusion of other races in the equation. It is estimated that by 2050, European-Americans in America will comprise less than 50% of the total population (Latinos, for example will acount for 25% of the US population). Thinking about race relations in the United States is therefore broadening to include Latin-Americans (the fastest growing ethnic group) and Asian-Americans. At this writing, at least 4 states, California, Texas, Hawaii, and New Mexico (and the District of Columbia) are deemed "majority minority" states, where whites are not the majority of the population.

==South Africa==
See [[History of South Africa in the apartheid era]].

==Switzerland==
[[Switzerland|The Swiss Confederation]] or ''Confederatio Helvetica'' is a nation composed of four subcultural groups: German-speaking (63.7%), French-speaking (20.4%), Italian-speaking (6.5%) and [[Romansch]]-speaking (0.5%) (Source: [http://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/portal/en/index/themen/bevoelkerung/sprachen__religionen/blank/kennzahlen0/sprachen.html Federal Population Census 2000]). With this diversity and its history of [[Neutral country|neutrality]], Switzerland has been seen as a safe refuge for those genuinely fleeing from persecution, and this is backed up by statistics. Switzerland has seen an increase in refugees in recent years, (particularly from Africa), who have claimed asylum directly in Switzerland. In 1992, the federal refugee office registered some 7,000 black Africans requesting asylum. In the first nine months of 2002 the number was 17,000.

The vast majority of asylum seekers are believed by many Swiss politicians to be economic immigrants rather than genuine asylum seekers. Furthermore, the SVP or [[Swiss People's Party]] has significantly increased its share of the vote in recent years on a perceived "anti-immigrant" platform. It is best known for opposing Swiss membership in international organisations such as the EU and [[United Nations]] and for its campaigning against perceived flaws in the immigration, asylum and penal laws.

Swiss "Confederation Commission Against Racism" which is part of the Swiss "Federal Department of Home Affairs"[http://www.edi.admin.ch/]published a 2004 report, ''Black People in Switzerland'': ''A Life between [[Racial integration|Integration]] and [[Discrimination]]'' [http://www.edi.admin.ch/ekr/dokumentation/shop/00019/00142/index.html?lang=de] (published in German, French, and Italian only). According to this report, discrimination based on skin colour in Switzerland is not exceptional, and affects immigrants decades after their immigration.

==Zimbabwe/Rhodesia==
Until majority rule in [[1980]], the minority white government of [[Rhodesia]] (as [[Zimbabwe]] was then called) practised institutionalised racism similar in most respects to the [[apartheid]] system in [[South Africa]]. White Rhodesians "''lived in the best houses, owned most of the best land, enjoyed a high standard of living and controlled the executive, the legislature, the judiciary and the means of coercion."'' (Godwin, P. &amp; Hancock, I., 1993. ''Rhodesians never Die'', Baobab Books, Harare, Zimbabwe.)

The laws enforcing [[racial segregation]], however, were not always welcomed by the local white community. They were viewed as not only being racist, but expensive and unnecessary. This was highlighted in an incident, called "[[Reps Theatre#"The Battle of the Toilets"|The Battle of the Toilets]]" in [[1960]], involving a new [[Reps Theatre|theatre]] that would be open to all races.

Twenty years after [[Zimbabwe#Independence|Independence]], whites in Zimbabwe remained a [[Market dominant minorities|market dominant minority]] through their continued ownership of the vast majority of [[arable]] land, the most valuable resource in a country like Zimbabwe where agriculture is the leading industry. In [[2000]], the government, arguing that the country's landownership patters were the result of longtime failure to address the legacies of colonialism and racism in Zimbabwean society, began a controversial [[Land reform in Zimbabwe|land reform]] process directed at confiscating the land of the white resident farmers and redistributing it to the poor black majority. Mugabe, however, had come under heavy criticism and accusations of having apportioned land to supporters, doing so in a disorganized and anarchical manner. This was coupled with renewed criticisms (originally directed decades ago) that a comprehensive land reform has been long overdue. (Astrow, A., 1983, ''Zimbabwe: A revolution that lost its way?'', Zed Books, London)</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>