<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20130606235904|558682674" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3523938" pageid="3523938" ns="0" title="World Conference on Women, 1995"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-10-07T06:07:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2012}}
{{refimprove|date=January 2011}}
The United Nations convened the '''Fourth World Conference on Women: Action for Equality, Development and Peace''' on 4–15 September 1995 in Beijing, China. Delegates had prepared a Declaration and Platform for Action aimed at achieving greater equality and opportunity for women. 

In fallout from pre-conference meetings, the [[Holy See]] publicly disagreed with positions outlined by the [[United States]] and other nations concerning [[abortion]], [[reproductive rights]], and other sensitive issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/1994/08/09/world/vatican-attacks-population-stand-supported-by-us.html |newspaper=[[New York Times]] |title=Vatican Attacks U.S.-Backed Draft for Women's Conference | author=Tagliabue, John | date=August 26, 1995 |accessdate=2012-4-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aung San Suu Kyi]] delivered the keynote address at the conference.&lt;ref name=nobelprize.org&gt;{{cite web|title=nobelprize.org|url=http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/1991/kyi-bio.html|accessdate=12 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

==Beijing Declaration of Indigenous Women==

A major result of the conference was the Beijing Declaration of Indigenous Women, signed at the NGO Forum in the Indigenous Women's Tent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Beijing Declaration of Indigenous Women|url=http://www.ipcb.org/resolutions/htmls/dec_beijing.html|publisher=Indigenous Peoples Council on Biocolonialism}}&lt;/ref&gt; This document seeks, in part, to reconcile the tension felt by Aboriginal women activists between (primarily white) feminism and Aboriginal movements dominated by men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Green|first=Joyce|title=Balancing Strategies: Aboriginal Women and Constitutional Rights in Canada|journal=Making Space for Indigenous Feminism|year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 50-point declaration provides rationale and a clear call to action for governments navigating Aboriginal issues across the globe. The demands in the document are "that all governments and international non-governmental and governmental organizations recognize the right of Indigenous peoples to self-determination, and enshrine the historical, political, social, cultural, economic, and religious rights of the Indigenous peoples in their constitutions and legal systems."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Beijing Declaration of Indigenous Women|url=http://www.ipcb.org/resolutions/htmls/dec_beijing.html|publisher=Indigenous Peoples Council on Biocolonialism}}&lt;/ref&gt; From that premise, the declaration goes on to specify areas for action including self-determination; development, education and health; human rights violations and violence against Indigenous women; intellectual and cultural heritage; and political participation.

The document addresses the unique problems Aboriginal women suffer in addition to those suffered by Aboriginal men, which include erosion of culture (and gender roles therein), loss of traditional land, and compromised identity and status in the spaces they inhabit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sayers|first=Judith F.|coauthors=Kelly A. MacDonald|title=A Strong and Meaningful Role for First Nations Women in Governance|journal=First Nations Women, Governance and the Indian Act: A Collection of Policy Research Reports|year=2001|page=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

As its bases, the declaration cites the "UN Declaration of the International Decade of the World's Indigenous peoples, the Draft Declaration of the Rights of the Indigenous peoples, the [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]], the Nairobi Forward Looking Strategies for the Advancement of Women, [[Agenda 21]] and the [[Rio Declaration on Environment and Development]], the [[Cairo Declaration]], and the Copenhagen Social Summit Declaration."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Beijing Declaration of Indigenous Women|url=http://twnside.org.sg/title/dec-ch.htm|publisher=Third World Network}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{official|http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/fwcwn.html}}

{{UN-stub}}

[[Category:Women's rights]]
[[Category:Reproductive rights]]
[[Category:United Nations conferences]]
[[Category:Diplomatic conferences in China]]
[[Category:20th-century diplomatic conferences]]
[[Category:1995 in international relations]]
[[Category:1995 conferences]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>