<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20240722192525|1236075233" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3523938" pageid="3523938" ns="0" title="World Conference on Women, 1995"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-07-22T19:27:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|United Nations conference}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2017}}
[[File:Fourth United Nations Conference on Women.svg|thumb|upright=.5|Conference logo]]
[[File:Hillary Rodham Clinton Addresses the Fourth United Nations Conference on Women at the Beijing International Conference Center in Bejiing, China - NARA - 131493880.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|[[Hillary Clinton]] gives a speech during the conference]]
{{Feminism sidebar |expanded=By country}}
The '''Fourth World Conference on Women: Action for Equality, Development and Peace''' was the name given for a conference convened by the United Nations during 4–15 September 1995 in [[Beijing]], China.&lt;ref name=UKcommis&gt;{{cite web|title=The Fourth United Nation's Conference on Women in Beijing 1995|url=http://wnc.equalities.gov.uk/work-of-the-wnc/international-articles/beijing-platform/162-beijing-platform-for-action.html|publisher=Women's National Commission (UK)|access-date=24 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At this conference, governments from around the world agreed on a comprehensive plan to achieve global [[equality before the law|legal equality]], known as the Beijing Platform for Action.

== Background ==
[[File:UN charter logo.png|thumb|alt=|UN charter logo]]
The [[United Nations Charter|founding United Nations charter (1945)]] included a provision for equality between men and women ([[Chapter III of the United Nations Charter#Article 8|chapter III, article 8]]). Subsequently, from 1945 to 1975 various female officials within the United Nations and leaders of women's movements on the global stage attempted to turn these principles into action. The [[United Nations General Assembly]] passed a resolution ([[United Nations General Assembly Resolution 3010|resolution 3010]]) that 1975 should be [[International Women's Year]]. In December 1975, the UN General Assembly passed a further resolution ([[United Nations General Assembly Resolution 31/136|resolution 31/136]]) that 1976–1985 should be the "Decade of Women".&lt;ref name="O'Barr"&gt;{{Citation | last = O'Barr | first = Jean F. | contribution = United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women, Beijing, China (1995) – "Global Framework" of the Platform for Action | editor1-last = DeLamotte | editor1-first = Eugenia | editor2-last = Meeker | editor2-first = Natania | editor3-last = O'Barr | editor3-first = Jean F. | pages = [https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780415915311/page/502 502–510] | title = Women imagine change: a global anthology of women's resistance from 600 B.C.E. to present | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 1997 | isbn = 9780415915311 | url = https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780415915311/page/502 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== First World Conference on Women, Mexico City, 1975 ===

{{Main article| World Conference on Women, 1975}}
In conjunction with [[International Women's Year]], the first world conference on women was held in Mexico City in 1975.&lt;ref name=UKcommis /&gt; It resulted in the [[Declaration of Mexico on the Equality of Women and Their Contribution to Development and Peace]].&lt;ref name=MexicoDec&gt;{{cite web|title=World Conference of the International Women's Year|url=http://www.un-documents.net/mex-dec.htm |publisher=United Nations|access-date=25 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Second World Conference on Women, Copenhagen, 1980 ===
{{Main article| World Conference on Women, 1980}}
The second world conference on women was held in Copenhagen in 1980.&lt;ref name=UKcommis /&gt; The conference agreed that the 1979 [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]] was an important milestone. The Copenhagen conference also acknowledged the gap between rights being secured for women and women's ability to exercise those rights. It was also agreed that it was action on the three areas of: equal access to education; employment opportunities; and adequate health care services are essential to achieve the goals set out in Mexico.&lt;ref name=Copenhagen&gt;{{cite web|title=1980 World Conference on Women|url=http://www.5wwc.org/conference_background/1980_WCW.html|publisher=5th Women's World Conference|access-date=25 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Third World Conference on Women, Nairobi, 1985 ===
{{Main article| World Conference on Women, 1985}}
The third world conference on women was held in Nairobi in 1985.&lt;ref name=UKcommis /&gt; The Nairobi conference set out areas by which progress in women's equality could be measured: constitutional and legal measures; equality in social participation; equality in political participation; and decision-making. The conference also acknowledged that women need to participate in all areas of human activity, not just those areas that relate to gender.&lt;ref name=Nairobi&gt;{{cite web|title=1985 World Conference on Women|url=http://www.5wwc.org/conference_background/1985_WCW.html|publisher=5th Women's World Conference|access-date=25 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Preceding the Fourth World Conference on Women, Beijing, 1995 ===

Delegates had prepared the UNDP Beijing Express Declaration aimed at achieving greater equality and opportunity for women.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite news |last=Siggins |first=Lorna |date=16 July 1996 |title=Ireland still falling behind on gender and equality issues |url=https://www.irishtimes.com/news/ireland-still-falling-behind-on-gender-and-equality-issues-1.67420 |access-date=2023-02-20 |newspaper=The Irish Times |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Human Development Under Transition: Europe &amp; CIS.. (1997). United States: UNDP, Regional Bureau for Europe and the CIS. p14&lt;/ref&gt;

== Attendees  ==
[[File:Políticas chilenas en Beijing.jpg|250px|thumb|[[Chile]]an politicians attending the conference.]]
[[File:Beijing International Convention Center (20200810181819).jpg|thumb|[[Beijing International Convention Center]], where the conference was held]]
The conference was attended by representatives of 189 governments, UN agencies,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/unastatements.html|title=Fourth World Conference on Women, Beijing 1995|website=www.un.org|access-date=2020-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; intergovernmental organizations such as the [[European Union]] and [[Arab League|League of Arab States]], as well as activists and organizations from across the world. There were 17,000 participants, with a further 30,000 activists attending a parallel Forum.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://beijing20.unwomen.org/en/about|title=The Beijing Platform for Action: inspiration then and&amp;nbsp;now|website=UN Women {{!}} The Beijing Platform for ActionTurns 20|language=en|access-date=2020-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gertrude Mongella]] of Tanzania was the secretary-general of the conference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Fourth World Conference on Women|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/sun10.htm|date=10 September 1995|access-date=5 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aung San Suu Kyi]] delivered the [[keynote]] address at the conference.&lt;ref name="nobelprize.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/1991/kyi-bio.html|title=nobelprize.org|access-date=12 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A full list of the statements made by attendees [https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/fwcwn.html can be found on the UN website].

== Speeches ==
[[File:First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton's Remarks to the Fourth Women's Conference in Beijing, China.webm|thumb|thumbtime=187|Hillary Rodham Clinton giving [[Women's rights are human rights|a speech]] during the conference.]]
[[Hillary Clinton]], at the time the [[First Lady of the United States]], gave the speech ''[[Women's Rights Are Human Rights]]'' at the conference on 5 September 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Fester|first=Gertrude|title=Women's Rights Are Human Rights|journal=Agenda: Empowering Women for Gender Equity |year=1994|volume=20|issue=20|pages=76–79|doi=10.2307/4065874 |jstor=4065874}}&lt;/ref&gt; That speech is considered to be influential in the women's rights movement, and in 2013 Clinton led a review of how women's rights have changed since her 1995 speech.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rucker|first=Philip|title=Hillary Clinton to lead review of progress for women since 1995 Beijing conference|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/post-politics/wp/2013/09/25/hillary-clinton-to-lead-review-of-progress-for-women-since-1995-beijing-conference/|newspaper=[[The Washington Post]]|date=25 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1995 speech was listed as No. 35 in American Rhetoric's Top 100 Speeches of the 20th Century (listed by rank).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Michael E. Eidenmuller |url=http://www.americanrhetoric.com/top100speechesall.html |title=Top 100 Speeches of the 20th Century by Rank |publisher=American Rhetoric |date=13 February 2009 |access-date=27 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;"If there is one message that echoes forth from this conference, it is that human rights are women's rights.... And women's rights are human rights.

Let us not forget that among those rights are the right to speak freely. And the right to be heard.

Women must enjoy the right to participate fully in the social and political lives of their countries if we want freedom and democracy to thrive and endure."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.un.org/esa/gopher-data/conf/fwcw/conf/gov/950905175653.txt|title=UN - Fourth World Conference on Women - Statements By Governments|website=UN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

--Hillary Rodham Clinton&lt;/blockquote&gt;[[Beverley Palesa Ditsie]] became the first African lesbian woman to address the [[United Nations]] about [[LGBT]] rights when she made her speech on 13 September 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.sahistory.org.za/dated-event/beverly-palesa-ditsie-first-out-lesbian-woman-address-united-nations-about-lgbt-rights|title=Beverly&amp;#91;sic&amp;#93; Palesa Ditsie is the first out lesbian woman to address the United Nations about LGBT rights|last=Nolundi|date=2017-04-10|work=South African History Online|access-date=2017-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;"No woman can determine the direction of her own life without the ability to determine her sexuality.&amp;nbsp; Sexuality is an integral, deeply ingrained part of every human being's life and should not be subject to debate or coercion.&amp;nbsp; Anyone who is truly committed to women's human rights must recognize that every woman has the right to determine her sexuality free of discrimination and oppression.

I urge you to make this a conference for all women, regardless of their sexual orientation, and to recognize in the Platform for Action that lesbian rights are women's rights and that women's rights are universal, inalienable, and indivisible human rights."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.un.org/esa/gopher-data/conf/fwcw/conf/ngo/13123944.txt|title=UN Fourth World Conference on Women - Statements by NGOs|website=UN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

--Beverley Palesa Ditsie &lt;/blockquote&gt;Many other speeches were also given at the conference, on behalf of governments, the United Nations and inter-governmental organizations, and non-governmental organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/fwcwn.html |title=Fourth World Conference on Women, Beijing 1995 |publisher=United Nations |date=31 December 2003 |access-date=27 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/govstatements.html |title=Fourth World Conference on Women, Beijing 1995 [Governments] |publisher=United Nations |access-date=27 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/unastatements.html |title=Fourth World Conference on Women, Beijing 1995 [The United Nations and inter-governmental organizations] |publisher=United Nations |access-date=27 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/ngostatements.html |title=Fourth World Conference on Women, Beijing 1995 [NGOs] |publisher=United Nations |access-date=27 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Beijing Platform for Action ==
{{Main article|Beijing Declaration}}
The Beijing Declaration and Platform for Action is widely known as the most progressive blueprint for advancing [[women's rights]].

The framework covers 12 areas of concern:

# [[Women and the environment]]
# [[Women in government|Women in power and decision making]]
# [[Girl|The girl child]] 
# [[Women in the workforce|Women and the economy]]
# [[Feminization of poverty|Women and poverty]]
# [[Violence against women]] 
# [[Women's rights|Human rights of women]] 
# [[Female education|Education and training of women]] 
# Institutional mechanisms for the advancement of women 
# [[Women and Health|Women and health]] 
# Women and the media 
# [[Women in war|Women and armed conflict]]

=== Beijing Declaration of Indigenous Women ===
A major result of the conference was the Beijing Declaration of Indigenous Women, signed at the NGO Forum in the Indigenous Women's Tent.&lt;ref name="ipcb.org"&gt;{{cite web|title=Beijing Declaration of Indigenous Women|url=http://www.ipcb.org/resolutions/htmls/dec_beijing.html|publisher=Indigenous Peoples Council on Biocolonialism}}&lt;/ref&gt; This document seeks, in part, to reconcile the tension felt by Indigenous women activists and Indigenous movements dominated by men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Green|first=Joyce|title=Balancing Strategies: Aboriginal Women and Constitutional Rights in Canada|journal=Making Space for Indigenous Feminism|year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a significant step forward towards Indigenous women's rights and a significant victory for [[Indigenous feminism]] practice.

The 50-point declaration provides the rationale and a clear call to action for governments navigating Indigenous issues across the globe. The demands in the document are "that all governments and international non-governmental and governmental organizations recognize the right of Indigenous peoples to self-determination, and enshrine the historical, political, social, cultural, economic, and religious rights of the Indigenous peoples in their constitutions and legal systems."&lt;ref name="ipcb.org"/&gt; From that premise, the declaration goes on to specify areas for action including self-determination; development, education and health; human rights violations and violence against Indigenous women; intellectual and cultural heritage; and political participation.

The document addresses the unique problems Indigenous women suffer in addition to those suffered by Indigenous men, which include erosion of culture (and gender roles therein), loss of traditional land, and compromised identity and status in the spaces they inhabit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sayers|first=Judith F.|author2=Kelly A. MacDonald|title=A Strong and Meaningful Role for First Nations Women in Governance|journal=First Nations Women, Governance and the Indian Act: A Collection of Policy Research Reports|year=2001|page=11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As its bases, the declaration cites the "UN Declaration of the International Decade of the World's Indigenous Peoples, the Draft Declaration of the Rights of the Indigenous peoples, the [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]], the Nairobi Forward-Looking Strategies for the Advancement of Women, [[Agenda 21]] and the [[Rio Declaration on Environment and Development]], the [[Cairo Declaration on Human Rights in Islam]], and the Copenhagen Social Summit Declaration."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Beijing Declaration of Indigenous Women|url=http://twnside.org.sg/title/dec-ch.htm|publisher=Third World Network}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Global Focus: Women in Art and Culture ==
''Global Focus: Women in Art and Culture'' was a project founded by artist and project director [[Nancy Cusick]] and gave women artists the opportunity to participate in the dialogue at the World Conference of Women. Women artists from around the world used their chosen media as a vehicle to produce work that evoked the universal issues paramount to women, their lives, and their position within the framework of society. Co-sponsored by the [[National Museum of Women in the Arts]] (NMWA), Global Focus presented an art exhibition, a video festival, slide presentations, performance pieces, and workshops that showed the artistic accomplishments and creativity of women. Most of the 880 artworks, produced by women artists from 27 countries, were displayed at the World Trade Center in [[Beijing, China]]. A smaller group of works were also exhibited in [[Huairou]], China. These artworks formed a visual landscape of powerful images that immortalized the women's issues and themes which encompassed the conference—Equality, Development, and Peace.

Following the exhibition of the Global Focus artworks in Beijing, China, the corpus of works traveled to various international locations. Immediately after the close of the Beijing exhibit, a selection of 53 American paintings were displayed at the Elite Gallery in [[Moscow]] from October to November 1995. Subsequently, in November 1995, a selection of 200 works adorned the walls of the art gallery at the United States Department of Health and Human Services in [[Washington, D.C.|Washington D.C.]] Simultaneously, another group of artworks from the collection were exhibited at the United States Information Agency also in Washington D.C. On March 20, 1996, the first public showing of the collection in the United States opened at NMWA in Washington D.C., with a day-long celebration revisiting and reflecting upon the experiences in Beijing. This exhibition, titled "Look at the World Through Women’s Eyes", was on display through April 21, 1996. On September 28, 1996, the collection was exhibited at [[George Washington University]] in Washington D.C., during the National Women's Satellite Conference hosted by First Lady [[Hillary Clinton|Hillary Rodham Clinton]]. From April to June 1997, a selection of 300 works from the collection were exhibited at the Peace Museum in Detroit. The last public display of the Global Focus exhibit was shown during the 20th Anniversary Celebration of the 1977 Spirit of Houston Conference in Washington D.C. After this final showing, the large group of artworks ended its journey, and the entire collection was presented by the project co-directors Nancy Cusick and Mal Johnson to the archives of the National Museum of Women in the Arts.

==Commemoration==
[[File:Fourth World Conference on Women Commemorative Park (20200810153232).jpg|thumb|Fourth World Conference on Women Commemorative Park in [[Huairou District]], Beijing]]
On 28 September 2004, the Fourth World Conference on Women Commemorative Park was officially opened in [[Huairou District]], where the NGO forum was held.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.sohu.com/20040929/n222295858.shtml|title=世妇会纪念公园在北京落成 28日投入使用|publisher=[[Xinhua News Agency]]|date=29 September 2004|access-date=10 August 2020|language=zh}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014 [[UN Women]] began its commemoration of the 20th anniversary of the Fourth World Conference on Women with the ''Empowering Women, Empowering Humanity: Picture It!'' campaign, also called the Beijing+20 campaign.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.looktothestars.org/news/12227-gloria-steinem-helps-un-women-unveil-beijing-20-campaign |title=Gloria Steinem Helps UN Women Unveil Beijing+20 Campaign |date=July 2014 |publisher=Look to the Stars |access-date=27 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mediaforfreedom.com/readarticle.php?AID=18455] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714202335/http://www.mediaforfreedom.com/readarticle.php?AID=18455|date=14 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2019, [[UN Women]] launched the Generation Equality Campaign and Generation Equality Forum to "tackle the unfinished business of empowering women through a new groundbreaking, multi-generational campaign, ''Generation Equality: Realizing women’s rights for an equal future''."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.unwomen.org/-/media/headquarters/attachments/sections/library/publications/2019/generation-equality-realizing-womens-rights-for-an-equal-future-en.pdf?la=en&amp;vs=4330|title=Celebrating 25 years of championing women's rights|last=UN Women}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also called Beijing +25, the campaign and forum are being organized in collaboration with members of civil society, and are meant to serve as the planning events, along with the 64th Session of the UN's [[United Nations Commission on the Status of Women|Commission on the Status of Women]] (CSW), in the lead up to a [[United Nations General Assembly|UN General Assembly]] high-level meeting in New York on September 23, 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://ngocsw.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/GenerationEquality-Civil-Society-Deck.pdf|title=Generation Equality|website=NGOCSW}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2019, at the 73rd session of the UN General Assembly, governments agreed to present their commitments and planned activities to bring about gender equality by 2030 at a one-day session during the 74th session in 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://undocs.org/en/A/RES/73/340|title=A/RES/73/340 - E - A/RES/73/340|website=undocs.org|access-date=2019-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The demands of the Generation Equality Campaign include "equal pay, equal sharing of unpaid care and domestic work, an end to sexual harassment and all forms of violence against women and girls, health-care services that respond to their needs, and their equal participation in political life and decision-making in all areas of life."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.unwomen.org/en/get-involved/beijing-plus-25/about|title=About Generation Equality {{!}} Get involved: Generation Equality: Realizing women's rights for an equal future|website=UN Women|language=en|access-date=2019-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Generation Equality Forum is being convened by UN Women, and co-chaired by Mexico and France. The Forum will begin in Mexico City, May 7–8, 2020 and will conclude in Paris, France from 7-10 of July, 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.unwomen.org/en/get-involved/beijing-plus-25/generation-equality-forum|title=Generation Equality Forum Get involved: Generation Equality: Realizing women's rights for an equal future|website=UN Women|language=en|access-date=2019-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Discussions and reviews of progress on the [[Beijing Platform for Action]] and the [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]] (CEDAW) will also take place at the 64th session of the Commission on the Status of Women, in New York, on March 9–20, 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.unwomen.org/en/csw/csw64-2020|title=CSW64 / Beijing+25 (2020) {{!}} Commission on the Status of Women|website=UN Women|language=en|access-date=2019-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 October 2020, the High-Level Meeting on the 25th Anniversary of the Fourth World Conference on Women was held, where China proposed another Global Leaders' Meeting on Gender Equality and Women's Empowerment in 2025.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.usnews.com/news/world/articles/2020-10-01/25-years-after-un-womens-meeting-equality-remains-distant|title=25 Years After UN Women's Meeting, Equality Remains Distant|publisher=US News|date=1 October 2020|access-date=2 October 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Documentary==
In 2015 a documentary called "MAKERS: Once And For All", about the Fourth World Conference on Women, premiered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=MAKERS Team |url=http://www.makers.com/blog/premiere-once-and-for-all |title=Go Behind the Scenes of the World Premiere of "MAKERS: Once And For All" |publisher=MAKERS |date=20 November 2015 |access-date=20 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.makers.com/once-and-for-all |title=Once and for All |publisher=MAKERS |date=15 September 2015 |access-date=20 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Women's Peace Train#Helsinki, Finland to Beijing, China (1995)|Women's Peace Train]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* {{official website|http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/fwcwn.html}}
* The [https://nmwa.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Beijing-Finding-Aid-2020.pdf Global Focus Collection] at the [[National Museum of Women in the Arts]]

{{United Nations}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Diplomatic conferences in China]]
[[Category:Women's conferences]]
[[Category:United Nations conferences]]
[[Category:1995 in women's history]]
[[Category:1995 conferences]]
[[Category:1995 in international relations]]
[[Category:1995 in Beijing]]
[[Category:20th-century diplomatic conferences]]
[[Category:Reproductive rights]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]
[[Category:Women's rights in China]]
[[Category:China and the United Nations]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Women in Beijing]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>