<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181115211047|869011405" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1527351" pageid="1527351" ns="0" title="LGBTQ rights opposition"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-25T02:15:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{LGBT rights}}
'''LGBT rights opposition''' is the opposition to [[legal rights]], proposed or enacted, for [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], and [[transgender]] people.

Organizations influential in [[LGBT rights]] opposition frequently oppose the enactment of laws making [[same-sex marriage]] legal, the passage of anti-discrimination laws aimed at curtailing [[Discrimination against LGBT people|anti-LGBT discrimination]], including in employment and housing, the passage of anti-bullying laws to protect LGBT minors, laws decriminalizing same-gender relationships, and other LGBT rights related laws. These groups are often religious or [[social conservatism|socially conservative]] in nature.

Such opposition can be motivated by [[religion]], [[morality|moral beliefs]], [[homophobia]], [[transphobia]], [[bigotry]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vexen.co.uk/religion/homosexuality.html#Islam |title=Homosexuality and Religion|quote=Lillian Ladele contined {{sic}} to fight, and the case eventually went to the European Court of Human Rights, where, on the 15th of Jan 2013, they also found that anti-gay bigotry was not excused in the public sector, not even by domineering Christians.}}&lt;/ref&gt; animosity,&lt;ref name=opinion&gt;{{cite court |litigants= Romer v. Evans |vol=517 |reporter=U.S.  |opinion=620  |pinpoint= |court= |date= 1996 |url= http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=000&amp;invol=U10179 |accessdate= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[political ideologies]], or other reasons.

Laws that LGBT rights opponents may be opposed to include [[civil unions|civil unions or partnerships]], [[LGBT parenting]] and [[LGBT adoption|adoption]], [[Sexual orientation and military service|military service]], access to [[assisted reproductive technology]], and access to [[sex reassignment surgery]] and [[hormone replacement therapy (transgender)|hormone replacement therapy]] for [[transgender]] individuals.

== History ==
[[File:Bucherverbrennung-book-burning-Nazi-1933-Institute.jpg|left|thumb|Students organised by the [[Nazi]] party parade in front of the [[Institut für Sexualwissenschaft|Institute for Sexual Research]] in Berlin on 6 May 1933, before pillaging it and confiscating its books and photos for burning.]]

The first organized [[gay rights movement]] arose in the late nineteenth century in Germany.&lt;ref name=chron&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/CHR06.HTM|title=Archive for Sexology|work=hu-berlin.de|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080709054341/http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/CHR06.HTM|archivedate=2008-07-09|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1920s and into the early 1930s, there were LGBT communities in cities like Berlin; German-Jewish sexologist [[Magnus Hirschfeld]] was one of the most notable spokespeople for LGBT rights at this time. When the Nazi party came to power in 1933, one of the party's first acts was to burn down Hirschfeld's ''[[Institut für Sexualwissenschaft]]'', where many prominent Nazis had been treated for perceived sexual problems.&lt;ref name="Lenz"&gt;"not ten percent of those men who, in 1933, took the fate of Germany into their hands, were sexually normal" LUDWIG L. LENZ, The Memoirs of a Sexologist (New York: 1954) pp. 429, cited by Erwin Haeberle in "Swastika, Pink Triangle, and Yellow Star – The Destruction of Sexology and the Persecution of Homosexuals in Nazi Germany" The Journal of Sex Research, vol. 17, no. 3 (August 1981), pp. 270–287, http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/SWAST.HTM#A7 {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100416025939/http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/SWAST.HTM |date=2010-04-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially tolerant to the homosexuality of [[Ernst Röhm]] and his followers, many [[gay men]] were purged from the Nazi Party following the [[Night of the Long Knives]] and the [[Paragraph 175|Section 175 Laws]] began to be enforced again, with gay men interned in [[concentration camp]]s by 1938.&lt;ref group=note&gt;See [[Persecution of homosexuals in Nazi Germany and the Holocaust]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Under Nazi rule in Germany, the dismantling of rights for LGBT individuals was approached in two ways. By strengthening and re-enforcing existing laws that had fallen into disuse, male homosexuality was effectively re-criminalised; homosexuality was treated as a medical disorder, but at a social level rather than individual level intended to reduce the incidence of homosexuality. The treatment was a program of [[Nazi eugenics|eugenics]], starting with [[Sterilization (medicine)|sterilisation]], then a system of working people to death in forced labour camps, and eventually refined by medical scientists to include [[euthanasia]]. The driving force was the elimination of perceived [[Racial hygiene|degeneracy]] at various levels – genetic, social, identity and practice, and the elimination of such genetic material in society. Lifton wrote about this in his book ''The Nazi Doctors'':&lt;ref name="LIFTON"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Lifton | first = Robert | title = The Nazi Doctors: Medical Killing and the Psychology of Genocide | publisher = Basic Books | year = 1986}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[...] sexology and defense of homosexuality [...] were aspects of "sexual degeneration, a breakdown of the family and loss of all that is decent," and ultimately the destruction of the German Volk. [...] medicine was to join in the great national healing mission, and the advance image of what Nazi doctors were actually to become: the healer turned killer. [...] Sterilization policies were always associated with the therapeutic and regenerative principles of the biomedical vision: with the "purification of the national body" and the "eradication of morbid hereditary dispositions." Sterilization was considered part of "negative eugenics" [...]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.holocaust-history.org/lifton/LiftonT042.shtml|title=Lifton' Nazi Doctors p.42|work=holocaust-history.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

It is argued that the numbers of gay people who perished in the Holocaust was quite low in comparison to other [[Holocaust victims]], and confined to Germany itself, based on estimates that of 50,000 gay people who came before the courts, between 5,000 and 15,000&lt;ref name=ushm&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ushmm.org/information/exhibitions/traveling-exhibitions/nazi-persecution-of-homosexuals |title=Nazi Persecution of Homosexuals 1933-1945 |publisher=Ushmm.org |accessdate=21 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.holocaust-trc.org/homosx.htm |title=Homosexuals - Holocaust Teacher Resource Center |publisher=Holocaust-trc.org |accessdate=21 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.holocaustforgotten.com/fivmil.htm |title=Non-Jewish Victims of the Holocaust: 5 Million Often Forgotten |publisher=holocaustforgotten.com |date=1 September 1939 |accessdate=21 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ended up in concentration camps. However, many of those who came before the courts were directed (or volunteered) to undergo sterilisation/castration; they would be included with others who, in line with the historic shift in German society (that started with [[Carl Friedrich Otto Westphal|Westphal]], and developed through [[Krafft-Ebing]] to [[Magnus Hirschfeld]], of homosexuality being seen as having a neurological, endocrinological or genetic basis), were treated for homosexuality as a medical rather than criminal matter. Those treated by psychiatrists and thereby included in the T4 project to eliminate people with alleged [[medical disorder]]s would not be reflected in the rates of those dealt with as criminals.

After the [[Second World War]], the [[United States]] became more intolerant of homosexuality,&lt;ref&gt;Michael Klarman: ''From the Closet to the Altar: Courts, Backlash, and the Struggle for Same-Sex Marriage''.  Oxford University Press, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; but many gay men and lesbians decided to reveal their gay identities after meeting others in the military.&lt;ref name=infoplease&gt;{{cite web|title=Milestones in the Gay Rights Movement|url=http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0194028.html|website=infoplease.com|publisher=Houghton Miffin Company|accessdate=14 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many gay bars and villages were created, and a whole gay [[subculture]] was created.&lt;ref name=infoplease/&gt; Campaigns for gay rights began to develop, initially in the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1957: Homosexuality 'should not be a crime'|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/september/4/newsid_3007000/3007686.stm|website=news.bbc.co.uk|publisher=BBC|accessdate=14 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Towards the end of the 1960s homosexuality began to be decriminalised and de-medicalised in areas such as the UK, New Zealand, Australia, North America and Europe, in the context of the [[sexual revolution]] and [[anti-psychiatry]] movements. Organized opposition to gay and lesbian rights began in the 1970s.&lt;ref name=Himmelstein&gt;Jerome Himmelstein, p. 97; Spiritual Warfare: The Politics of the Religious Right, p.49–50, Sara Diamond, [[South End Press]], Boston, MA&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public opinion==
{{Main|Societal attitudes toward homosexuality}}
Societal attitudes towards homosexuality vary greatly in different cultures and different historical periods, as do attitudes toward sexual desire, activity and relationships in general. All cultures have their own [[Sexual norm|norms regarding appropriate and inappropriate sexuality]]; some sanction same-sex love and sexuality, while others disapprove of such activities.&lt;ref&gt;Murray, Stephen O., ''Homosexualities'', University of Chicago 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

According to The 2007 Pew Global Attitudes Project, "Throughout Western Europe and much of the Americas, there is widespread tolerance towards homosexuality. However, the United States, Japan, South Korea, and Israel stand apart from other wealthy nations on this issue; in each of these countries, fewer than half of those surveyed say homosexuality should be accepted by society. Meanwhile, in most of Africa, Asia and the Middle East, there is less tolerance toward homosexuality."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=WORLD PUBLICS WELCOME GLOBAL TRADE – BUT NOT IMMIGRATION|url=http://pewglobal.org/files/pdf/258.pdf|website=pewglobal.org|publisher=The Pew Global Attitudes Project|accessdate=14 February 2015|format=PDF|date=4 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, a 2012 [[CNN]] poll showed that a majority number of Americans are in favor of gay rights, such as same-sex marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com/2012/06/06/cnn-poll-americans-attitudes-toward-gay-community-changing/ |title=CNN Poll: Americans' attitudes toward gay community changing |publisher=politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com |date=6 June 2012 |accessdate=21 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In late 2015, a poll of Japanese people also found that a majority supported same-sex marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2015/11/29/new-poll-shows-majority-of-japanese-support-marriage-equality/|title=New poll shows majority of Japanese support marriage equality|date=29 November 2015|accessdate=22 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious reasons for opposition==
{{Essay-like|section|date=July 2015}}
{{Main|Religion and homosexuality}}
{{see also|Human sexuality#Religious sexual morality}}
Many forms of religions, including the Eastern faiths and Abrahamic faiths, do not support homosexual sex. [[Evangelicalism|Evangelical Christianity]],&lt;ref&gt;Strauss, Lehman, Litt.D., F.R.G.S. [http://www.bible.org/page.asp?page_id=1302 "Homosexuality: The Christian Perspective"].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Catholicism]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_rom.htm "Roman Catholics and Homosexuality"], Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mormonism]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lds.org/hf/library/0,16866,4266-1,00.html?LibraryURL=/lds/hf/display "Teaching about Procreation and Chastity: Homosexuality"], The Church of Jesus-Christ of Latter-day Saints. Home &amp; Family.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Orthodox Judaism]],&lt;ref&gt;Shafran, Rabbi Avi. [http://www.jlaw.com/Commentary/maritalprob.html "Jewish Law: Marital Problems"]. Jewish Law Commentary: Examining Halacha, Jewish Issues, and Secular Law.&lt;/ref&gt;
and [[Islam]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_isla1.htm "Islam and Homosexuality"], Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance (2005).&lt;/ref&gt; hold the view that homosexual sex is a [[sin]] and that its practice and acceptance in society weakens moral standards.

=== Christian opposition ===
{{Expand section|a sub-subsection sketching the position of the Catholic Church on the issue, with a "see also" to [[Homosexuality and the Catholic Church]]; Catholic arguments extend far beyond Leviticus and Romans and entail discussion of the paradigms of [[Marriage in the Catholic Church|marriage]] and family|talksection=talk|date=May 2016|small=no}}{{Main|Christianity and homosexuality|List of Christian denominational positions on homosexuality|The Bible and homosexuality}}

Passages in the [[Old Testament]] that prohibit man "lie with mankind as with womankind"&lt;ref group=note&gt;[http://biblehub.com/kjv/leviticus/18.htm Leviticus 18:22] and [http://biblehub.com/kjv/leviticus/20.htm Leviticus 20:13] (KJV).&lt;/ref&gt; and the story of [[Sodom and Gomorrah]] have historically been interpreted as condemning [[sodomy]]. Several [[Paul the Apostle|Pauline]] passages have also been cited against male and female homosexuality.&lt;ref group=note&gt;[http://biblehub.com/kjv/romans/1.htm Romans 1:25-28] - these are often considered the only explicit references in the Bible discussing female homosexuality.&lt;/ref&gt; Christians who take a conservative position on homosexuality endorse this reading of these passages in the belief that God is against same-sex sexual activity, while Christians who take a liberal position believe that these same passages refer to more specific situations, such as rape or abuse, and not homosexuality.&lt;ref name=TolerancerefA&gt;{{cite web|title=What the Bible says and means about homosexuality|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/homglance.htm|website=religioustolerance.org|accessdate=14 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest Christian body, the [[Catholic Church]], condemns homosexual acts as "gravely sinful" and "intrinsically disordered". The second-largest Christian body, the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], also condemns homosexual behaviour, as do most denominations of [[Protestantism]].

=== Islamic opposition ===
{{Further|Islam and sexual orientation}}
[[Sodomy]] is regarded as criminal and forbidden in most [[Islamic countries]], according to [[Sharia law|''Sharia'' law]], and officially carries the [[death penalty]] in [[Saudi Arabia]], [[United Arab Emirates]], [[Iran]], [[Mauritania]], [[Nigeria]], [[Sudan]] and [[Yemen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=WORLD DAY AGAINST DEATH PENALTY|url=http://www.ilga.org/news_results.asp?LanguageID=1&amp;FileCategory=50&amp;ZoneID=7&amp;FileID=1111|website=ilga.org|publisher=ILGA Files|accessdate=4 July 2015|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091029185853/http://www.ilga.org/news_results.asp?LanguageID=1&amp;FileCategory=50&amp;ZoneID=7&amp;FileID=1111|archivedate=29 October 2009|date=10 October 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Homosexuality and Islam|url=http://www.religionfacts.com/homosexuality/islam.htm|website=religionfacts.com|accessdate=4 July 2015|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150415225546/http://www.religionfacts.com/homosexuality/islam.htm|archivedate=15 April 2015|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It formerly carried the death penalty in [[Afghanistan]] under the [[Taliban]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Reid |first1=Tim |title=Kandahar Comes Out of the Closet |url=http://glapn.org/sodomylaws/world/afghanistan/afnews007.htm |website=sodomylaws.org |accessdate=14 February 2015 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040911230539/http://www.sodomylaws.org/world/afghanistan/afnews007.htm |date=12 January 2002 |archivedate=11 September 2004 |deadurl=no |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Egypt]], openly gay men have been prosecuted under general public morality laws.&lt;ref group=note&gt;See: [[Cairo 52]].&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, homosexuality has been legal in Turkey since 1858.&lt;ref name="History"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-25927595 |title=Where is it illegal to be gay? |accessdate=11 February 2014 |work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Saudi Arabia, the maximum punishment for homosexuality is public execution, but the government will use other punishments – e.g., fines, jail time, and [[flagellation]] – as alternatives, unless it feels that LGBT individuals are challenging state authority by engaging in [[LGBT social movements]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Dahir |first1=Mubarak |title=Is Beheading Really the Punishment for Homosexuality in Saudi Arabia? |url=http://glapn.org/sodomylaws/world/saudi_arabia/saudinews19.htm |website=sodomylaws.org |accessdate=6 July 2015 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20030106001332/http://www.sodomylaws.org/world/saudi_arabia/saudinews19.htm |archivedate= 6 January 2003 |date=December 2002 |deadurl=no |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Iran is perhaps the nation to execute the largest number of its citizens for homosexuality. Since the 1979 [[Iranian Revolution|Islamic revolution]] in Iran, the Iranian government has executed more than 4,000 people charged with homosexual acts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vexen.co.uk/religion/homosexuality.html#Islam |title=Homosexuality and Religion}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even though homosexuality is widespread amongst the [[Pashtun ethnic group]] in southern Afghanistan,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Farmer|first1=Ben|title=Paedophilia 'culturally accepted in south Afghanistan'|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/8257943/Paedophilia-culturally-accepted-in-south-Afghanistan.html|accessdate=6 July 2015|work=telegraph.co.uk|publisher=The Daily Telegraph|date=13 January 2011|location=Kabul|quote=American social scientists employed to help troops understand the local culture reported that homosexual sex was widespread among the Pashtun ethnic group in southern Afghanistan. Strict separation of men and women, coupled with poverty and the significant expense of getting married, contributed to young men turning to each other for sexual companionship.}}&lt;/ref&gt; after the fall of the Taliban, homosexuality went from a capital crime to one that is punished with fines, prison sentences, and [[vigilante]] violence.{{citation needed|date=July 2015}}

Most international human rights organizations, such as [[Human Rights Watch]] and [[Amnesty International]], condemn laws that make homosexual relations between consenting adults a crime. Muslim nations insist that such laws are necessary to preserve Islamic morality and virtue. Of the nations with a majority of Muslim inhabitants, only Lebanon and Tunisia have  organizations which are trying to get homosexuality legalized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.helem.net/|title=Helem English - !EXIST|work=helem.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Indian and East Asian religious opposition ===
{{Further|Homosexuality and Hinduism|Buddhism and sexual orientation|Homosexuality and Taoism|Homosexuality in China}}
Among the [[Indian religions|religions that originated in India]], including [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]], [[Jainism]] and [[Sikhism]], teachings regarding homosexuality are less clear than among the Abrahamic traditions. Unlike in western religions, homosexuality is rarely discussed. [[Vasubandhu]] included homosexuality among sexual practices that were forbidden because of their association with foreigners,&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=hqgRb_Thd_QC&amp;pg=PA199 Wise Teacher, Wise Student: Tibetan Approaches to a Healthy Relationship], Alexander Berzin&lt;/ref&gt; and the Dalai Lama has stated that male-female relationships are intended by nature, though without condemning same-sex relationships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tibet.ca/en/wtnarchive/1993/7/1_7.html|title=A Lesson on Life, Happiness; Anyone Can Achieve It, Says Dalai Lama to Seattle Crowd|author=Canada Tibet Committee|date=1 July 1993|work=World Tibet Network News|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040804014757/http://www.tibet.ca/en/wtnarchive/1993/7/1_7.html|archivedate=4 August 2004|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexuality is considered to be against the Sikh code of conduct, because it is not mentioned in Sikh scripture and because Sikhs are encouraged to marry, although this matter is not considered very important.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sikhism: beliefs about love and sex|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/schools/gcsebitesize/rs/relationships/sikhloveandsexrev2.shtml|website=BBC.co.uk|publisher=BBC GCSE Bitesize|accessdate=4 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, the Head Cleric of the Akal Takht condemned same-sex marriages,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Homosexuality and Sikhism|url=http://www.gaylaxymag.com/articles/queer-voices/homosexuality-and-sikhism/|website=gaylaxymag.com|publisher=GayLaxy|accessdate=4 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/world-sikh-group-against-gay-marriage-bill-1.536239 World Sikh group against gay marriage bill], [[CBC Newsworld|CBC News]], Tuesday, 29 March 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Hinduism is diverse, with no supreme governing body, but the majority of [[swami]]s opposed the idea of religious same-sex marriage in a 2004 survey, and a minority supported them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Discussions on Dharma|url=http://www.faithandthecity.org/issues/social/articles/Discussions_on_Dharma%20.shtml|publisher=Hinduism Today|accessdate=4 July 2015|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110929021150/http://www.faithandthecity.org/issues/social/articles/Discussions_on_Dharma%20.shtml|archivedate=29 September 2011|date=October 2004|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is no mention of homosexuality in the Hindu scriptures and it is sometimes a taboo subject, but as Hinduism considers it a religious duty to marry and have children, heterosexual relationships are considered the norm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hinduism: beliefs about love and sex|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/schools/gcsebitesize/rs/relationships/hiloveandsexrev1.shtml|website=BBC.co.uk|publisher=BBC GCSE Bitesize|accessdate=4 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Scientologist opposition ===
{{Main|Scientology and sexual orientation}}
Scientologist founder [[L. Ron Hubbard]] classified homosexuality as a mental illness and [[paraphilia]] (then known as "sexual perversion"), citing contemporary psychiatric and psychological textbooks to support his view.&lt;ref&gt;"The sexual pervert (and by this term Dianetics, to be brief, includes any and all forms of deviation in Dynamic II [i.e. sexuality] such as homosexuality, lesbianism, sexual sadism, etc., and all down the catalog of [[Havelock Ellis|Ellis]] and [[Richard Freiherr von Krafft-Ebing|Krafft-Ebing]]) is actually quite ill physically...he is very far from culpable for his condition, but he is also far from normal and extremely dangerous to society..." {{cite book | last=Hubbard | title=Dianetics: The Modern Science of Mental Health | pages=122–123 | publisher=Church of Scientology of California | year=1978 | isbn=0-88404-000-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gay people are designated a 1.1. on Hubbard's [[emotional tone scale]], and Hubbard urged society to tackle the issue of "sexual perversion" (including homosexuality), calling it "of vital importance, if one wishes to stop immorality, and the abuse of children." In ''Science of Survival'', he called for drastic action to be taken, saying that: "Such people should be taken from the society as rapidly as possible and uniformly institutionalized; for here is the level of the contagion of immorality, and the destruction of ethics; here is the fodder which secret police organizations use for their filthy operations."&lt;ref name="sos1"&gt;{{cite book | last=Hubbard | title=Science of Survival | pages=88–90 | publisher=Church of Scientology of California | year=1975 | isbn=0-88404-001-1}} "Such people should be taken from the society as rapidly as possible and uniformly institutionalized; for here is the level of the contagion of immorality, and the destruction of ethics; here is the fodder which secret police organizations use for their filthy operations. One of the most effective measures of security that a nation threatened by war could take would be rounding up and placing in a [[cantonment]], away from society, any 1.1 individual who might be connected with government, the military, or essential industry; since here are people who, regardless of any record of their family's loyalty, are potential traitors, the very mode of operation of their insanity being betrayal. In this level is the slime of society, the sex criminals, the political subversives, the people whose apparently rational activities are yet but the devious writhings of secret hate."&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2004 article in the ''[[St. Petersburg Times]]'' reported that the Church defines marriage as the union between a man and a woman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=About Scientology |url=http://www.sptimes.com/2004/07/18/Tampabay/About_Scientology.shtml |work=[[St. Petersburg Times]] |date=2004-07-18 &lt;!-- |accessdate=2006-09-02 --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; One year later, in response to a query about the Church's position on homosexuality, the Church of Scientology in 2005 stated: "The Church of Scientology does not dictate sexual preferences. Scientology is a practical method of improving conditions in life and works to increase a person's abilities, give higher [[IQ]] and better reaction time, greater ability to solve his problems in life – things of this nature."&lt;ref name=Wilcox&gt;Gallagher, Eugene V.; Ashcraft, Michael (2006). ''Introduction to New and Alternative Religions in America'', [[Greenwood Press]], Westport, CT/London, UK, Vol. 1, pp. 263–264&lt;/ref&gt;

== Health ==
{{See also|LGBT issues in medicine}}

A systematic review of research in the UK indicates that there appears to be limited evidence available from which to draw general conclusions about lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender health because epidemiological studies have not incorporated sexuality as a factor in data collection.&lt;ref name = WMID&gt;{{Cite journal | last1= Meads | first1= C
 | last2= Pennant | first2= M
 | last3= McManus | first3= J
 | last4= Bayliss | first4= S
 | title=  A systematic review of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender health in the West Midlands region of the UK compared to published UK research
 | publisher=  Unit of Public Health, Epidemiology &amp; Biostatistics, West Midlands Health Technology Assessment Group
 | year= 2009 | postscript= &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The review found that from the research there is in the UK, there are no differences in terms of major health problems between LGBT people and the general population, although LGBT people's general health appears poorer, but with no specific information on common and major diseases, cancers or long-term health.&lt;ref name = WMID/&gt;  Research points to issues encountered from an early age, such as LGBT people being targeted for bullying, assault, and discrimination, as contributing significantly to depression, suicide and other mental health issues in adulthood.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bjp.rcpsych.org/cgi/content/abstract/185/6/479 Rates and predictors of mental illness in gay men, lesbians and bisexual men and women], [[British Journal of Psychiatry]], (2004) 185: 479–485&lt;/ref&gt;  One researcher looked at the long-term consequences of bullying at schools,&lt;ref name = RIVERS1&gt;{{Cite journal | last1= Rivers | first1= I
 | title=  The bullying of sexual minorities at school: Its nature and long-term correlates.
 | journal=  Educational and Child Psychology
 | pages = 32–46
 | year= 2001
 | issue = 18(1) | postscript= &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = RIVERS2&gt;{{Cite journal | last1= Rivers | first1= I
 | title=  Recollections of Bullying at School and Their Long-Term Implications for Lesbians, Gay Men, and Bisexuals
 | journal=  Crisis
 | pages = 169–175
 | year= 2004
 | issue = 25(4) | postscript= &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a social researcher has focused on the way LGBT people can experience discriminatory practices in accessing healthcare, and its effects.&lt;ref name = WILT1&gt;{{Cite journal
 | last = Wilton
 | first = Tamsin
 | title = Sexualities in health and social care: a textbook
 | publisher = Open University Press
 | year = 2000
 | isbn = 0-335-20026-5
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some LGBT activists argue that the experience of growing up LGBT contributes to mental health issues in adulthood, and the barriers to accessing appropriate healthcare as adults contribute towards poorer health; they argue that protection of LGBT rights is necessary to minimise the potential development of health problems and ensure access to healthcare resources. In 2009 Canadian LGBT activists filed a complaint alleging that the health issues of LGB Canadians are being neglected by the government, equating it to a violation of the human rights of LGBT people. In the complaint, the activists highlight a life expectancy 20 years less than average for LGB people, with more cases of cancer and HIV and increased rates of suicide, alcoholism and drug use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.xtra.ca/BinaryContent/pdf/human%20rights%20complaint.pdf|title=Daily Xtra|work=xtra.ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opposition in different countries==
{{Essay-like|section|date=July 2015}}

=== Belarus ===
{{see also|LGBT rights in Belarus}}
A 2014 report prepared by the [[United Kingdom]], under the Conservative and Liberal Democrat coalition government of 2010–2015, raised concerns about LGBT treatment in [[Belarus]]:
{{quote|The LGBT community suffered increased harassment from the [Belarusian] regime in 2013. The Ministry of Justice denied registration to LGBT groups, and members of the LGBT community were regularly targeted by the security forces and brought in for questioning. The authorities threatened to stigmatise them by informing their colleagues, families, or friends of their sexual orientation. Gay clubs in Minsk and Vitebsk were raided, and those present were filmed and had their details collected. The clubs were then closed down.

Gay Pride week in Minsk was disrupted by the authorities who forced owners of venues, where events were due to be held, to withdraw at the last minute. Those events that did take place were raided by the police, and a request for a march through the city was turned down by the authorities.|title="LGBT rights", ''Corporate Report: Belarus – Country of Concern''|source=(UK [[Foreign and Commonwealth Office]], October 2014)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Corporate Report: Belarus - Country of Concern |url= https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/belarus-country-of-concern/belarus-country-of-concerndate=16| date =  October 2014 |website=Gov.uk |publisher=[[Foreign and Commonwealth Office]] |accessdate=28 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

=== Malaysia ===
Hong-Kong's Gazette of Record reported that Malaysian LGBT's are also facing high-tech clampdowns.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.scmp.com/news/asia/southeast-asia/article/2160781/mahathirs-malaysia-accused-state-sponsored-homophobia-after&lt;/ref&gt;

=== India ===
{{see also|Section 377 of the Indian Penal Code}}
On October 6, 1860, sodomy was legally forbidden in [[India]] according to Section 377 of the Indian Penal Code.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.faithology.com/topics/homosexuality-in-hinduism|title=Homosexuality in Hinduism|author=|date=|work=Faithology|accessdate=7 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was ruled unconstitutional in 2009 by the Delhi High Court, but reaffirmed on 11 December 2013 by a Supreme Court ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=India's Supreme Court turns the clock back with gay sex ban|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2013/12/11/us-india-rights-gay-idUSBRE9BA05620131211|newspaper=[[Reuters]]|date=11 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
It was again legalised by Supreme Court 6 September 2018.

=== Russia ===
{{see also|LGBT rights in Russia}}
[[File:Moscow opposition rally 2 March 2013, LGBT activists.JPG|thumb|190px|LGBT activists in Moscow, 2 March 2013]]
Opposition to the LGBT rights movement is very prevalent in [[Russia]], including within the [[Kremlin]]. President [[Vladimir Putin]] enacted laws in 2012 which criminalised education about LGBT issues, calling it "[[gay propaganda]]". It banned telling minors that homosexuality was normal or natural.&lt;ref name=Vice&gt;{{cite web|title=Young and Gay in Putin's Russia - Full Length|url=https://www.vice.com/video/young-and-gay-in-putins-russia-full-length-vice|website=VICE.com|publisher=VICE News}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was opposed by some Western nations with many members of the public in the U.S. and Western Europe calling for a [[boycott]] of the [[2014 Winter Olympics]] in [[Sochi]]. However President Putin assured that all athletes would be respected, regardless of their sexuality&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Brydum|first1=Sunnivie|title=Putin Promises Gay Olympians Will Be "Comfortable" in Sochi|url=http://www.advocate.com/news/world-news/2013/10/28/putin-promises-gay-olympians-will-be-comfortable-sochi|accessdate=6 April 2015|publisher=The Advocate|date=28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the event, no boycott occurred.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Caldwell|first1=Christopher|title=Why the west has not boycotted the Sochi Olympics|url=http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/ac73f5c6-69ac-11e3-aba3-00144feabdc0.html#axzz3WXeP80vV|website=FT.com|publisher=The Financial Times|accessdate=6 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The law passed has been described as taking Russia's LGBT community "from being a stigmatized fringe group to full-blown [[Enemy of the people#Soviet Union|enemies of the state]]", and has been described as a major contributor to a wave of anti-gay violence by several [[neo-Nazi]] organisations (such as ''[[Occupy Paedophilia]]''), which target gay teens online and meet up with them, posting on YouTube their acts of assault against the LGB teens, which have even resulted in the death of several LGB teens in Russia, which are rarely investigated by the authorities, defining them as "civil movements fighting the sins of society".&lt;ref name=Vice/&gt;

=== United Kingdom ===
{{see also|LGBT rights in the United Kingdom|LGBT rights in Scotland}}
In 1988, the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]], who were [[Premiership of Margaret Thatcher|in government at the time]], enacted [[Section 28]] which stated that [[Local government in the United Kingdom|local authorities]] must not "intentionally promote homosexuality or publish material with the intention of promoting homosexuality"  and that [[maintained school]]s should not "promote the teaching [...] of the acceptability of homosexuality", describing families with gay parents as being in a "pretended family relationship".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts1988/Ukpga_19880009_en_5.htm Local Government Act 1988 (c. 9)] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051122112358/http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts1988/Ukpga_19880009_en_5.htm |date=2005-11-22 }}, section 28. Accessed 18 January 2015 on opsi.gov.uk.&lt;/ref&gt; Research on the effect of suppressing information about sexuality awareness in schools showed a correspondence with increases in the level of homophobic bullying by peers, as well as increased incidence in depression and suicide amongst LGBT people trying to come to terms with their sexuality.&lt;ref name = EPSTEIN&gt;{{Cite journal |last1 = Epstein | first1 = Debbie | last2 = O'Flynn |first2 = Sarah |last3 = Telford |first3 = David |title = Silenced Sexualities in Schools and Universities |publisher = Trentham Books |year = 2003 |postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1987, Thatcher also declared that "hard left education authorities and extremist teachers" were indoctrinating the nation by teaching the younger generation "political slogans", "anti-racist mathematics" and telling their pupils that they have an "inalienable right to be gay", rather than "taught to respect traditional moral values".&lt;ref name=MTFoundation/&gt; She then went on to say that "all of those children are being cheated of a sound start in life—yes cheated!"&lt;ref name=MTFoundation&gt;{{cite web|title=Speech to Conservative Party Conference, 1987 Oct 9  |url=http://www.margaretthatcher.org/document/106941 |website=margaretthatcher.org |publisher=Margaret Thatcher Foundation|accessdate=18 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, despite opposition from the Conservatives such as [[David Cameron]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.channel4.com/news/articles/dispatches/cameron+toff+at+the+top/328047|title=Channel 4 - News - Dispatches - Cameron: Toff At The Top|work=channel4.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Section 28 was eventually repealed in 2003 by the [[Blair ministry|Labour government]] under [[Tony Blair]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Roberts|first1=Scott|title=Ian McKellen: 'Margaret Thatcher misjudged the future with Section 28' |url=http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2013/04/16/ian-mckellen-margaret-thatcher-misjudged-the-future-with-section-28/ |website=pinknews.co.uk|publisher=[[Pink News]]|accessdate=18 January 2015|quote=Section 28 was later removed from the statute book by Tony Blair's Labour government in 2003.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2009, David Cameron, whilst campaigning to be the next Prime Minister, formally apologised for his party introducing the law, stating that it was a mistake and had been offensive to gay people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/politics/cameron-sorry-for-section-28-1728003.html|title=Cameron sorry for Section 28|work=The Independent}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Pierce|first1=Andrew|title=David Cameron says sorry over Section 28 gay law|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/politics/david-cameron/5710650/David-Cameron-says-sorry-over-Section-28-gay-law.html|website=Telegraph.co.uk|publisher=The Telegraph|accessdate=14 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, [[Marriage (Same Sex Couples) Act 2013|same-sex marriage]] was legalised under Cameron's leadership,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://publications.parliament.uk/pa/bills/cbill/2012-2013/0126/cbill_2012-20130126_en_1.htm|title=Marriage (Same Sex Couples) Bill|publisher=House of Commons|date=25 January 2013|accessdate=28 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; which Cameron described as "an important step forward" and said that he thought that "it is right that gay people should be able to get married too".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Gay marriage an important step forward, says PM|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-21325702|website=bbc.co.uk|publisher=BBC|accessdate=14 February 2015|date=5 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The largest voice against LGBT equality in the UK currently comes from the [[Church of England]] over the issue of gay marriage. Labour passed into law in 2005 the ability for same-sex couples to enter civil-partnerships, but they could not take place in a church or be called a "marriage". The Church of England was opposed to the then coalition Government's plans (this government came to an end in May 2015) to extend this to "full marriage rights."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/religion/8221964/Coalition-ministers-consider-gay-marriage-plans.html |location=London |work=The Daily Telegraph |first=Tim |last=Ross |title=Coalition ministers consider gay marriage plans |date=24 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[British National Party]] has shifted its platform from recriminalization to an extension of [[section 28]]-style legislation, i.e. making it illegal to portray homosexuality positively in the media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://observer.guardian.co.uk/magazine/story/0,11913,783675,00.html|title=Andrew Anthony meets Nick Griffin - From the Observer - The Observer|author=Andrew Anthony|work=the Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1999, the [[Admiral Duncan pub]], a gay bar in London's Soho, was targeted up as part of a terrorist campaign by a former [[National Socialist Movement (United Kingdom)|National Socialist Movement]] and [[British National Party]] (BNP) member, [[David Copeland]]; three people were killed, and 70 maimed or injured by a nail bomb detonated in the pub.&lt;ref name = DUNCAN&gt;{{cite news |url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/april/30/newsid_2499000/2499249.stm |work=BBC News |title= 1999: Dozens injured in Soho nail bomb |date=30 April 1999 |accessdate=7 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following this bombing, [[Nick Griffin]] (former leader of the BNP) said: "The TV footage of dozens of 'gay' demonstrators flaunting their perversion in front of the world's journalists showed just why so many ordinary people find these creatures so repulsive."&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title = Factbox: British National Party |url = https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1399666/Factbox-British-National-Party.html |work=The Daily Telegraph |date = 10 January 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===

==== History ====
{{see also|Stonewall riots#Background}}
In the 1950s in the [[United States]], open homosexuality was taboo. Legislatures in every state had passed laws against homosexual behavior well before this, most notably [[Sodomy laws in the United States|anti-sodomy laws]]. During the [[Cold War]] politicians frequently described homosexuals as "subversives" who undermined national security and patriotism, and described them as [[Fellow traveller|Communist sympathisers]] or a Communist [[Fifth column]]. During the [[Lavender Scare]], [[Joseph McCarthy]] used accusations of homosexuality as a [[smear tactic]].&lt;ref&gt;Cuordileone, K. A. "'Politics in an Age of Anxiety': Cold War Political Culture and the Crisis in American Masculinity, 1949–1960" ''The Journal of American History'' 87 (2) (2000): 515–545&lt;/ref&gt; Senator [[Kenneth S. Wherry|Kenneth Wherry]] publicized fears that [[Joseph Stalin]] had obtained a list of closeted homosexuals in positions of power from [[Adolf Hitler]], which he believed Stalin intended to use to blackmail these men into working against the U.S. for the Soviet regime.&lt;ref&gt;Von Hoffman, Nicholas, ''Citizen Cohn'' Doubleday, 1988, pp 130&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Hoey Report|1950 report]] produced by a Senate subcommittee titled "Employment of Homosexuals and Other Sex Perverts in Government" said that "the pervert is easy prey to the blackmailer.... It is an accepted fact among intelligence agencies that espionage organizations the world over consider sex perverts who are in possession of or have access to confidential material to be prime targets where pressure can be exerted." Along with that security-based concern, the report found homosexuals unsuitable for government employment because "those who engage in overt acts of perversion lack the emotional stability of normal persons. In addition there is an abundance of evidence to sustain the conclusion that indulgence in acts of sex perversion weakens the moral fiber of an individual to a degree that he is not suitable for a position of responsibility."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/assault/context/employment.html|title=Who's Gay? What's Straight? - Employment Of Homosexuals And Other Sex Perverts In Government (1950) - Assault On Gay America - FRONTLINE - PBS|work=pbs.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; McCarthy and [[Roy Cohn]] more often used the secrets of closeted gay American politicians as tools for blackmail than did foreign powers.&lt;ref&gt;Von Hoffman, Nicholas, ''Citizen Cohn'' Doubleday, 1988&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anita Bryant]] organized [[Save Our Children]], a widespread campaign to oppose legislation prohibiting discrimination on the basis of [[sexual orientation]] in [[Miami-Dade County, Florida]]. The group argued that gay people were "[[Homosexual recruitment|recruiting]]" or "molesting children" in order to make them gay. Bryant infamously claimed that "As a mother, I know that homosexuals cannot biologically reproduce children; therefore, they must recruit our children," and also claimed that "If gays are granted rights, next we'll have to give rights to prostitutes and to people who sleep with St. Bernards and to nail biters."&lt;ref name="At Any Cost"&gt;{{cite book|title= At Any Cost|last= Bryant|first=Anita |author2=Green, Bob |year= 1978|publisher= Fleming H. Revell |location= Grand Rapids, Michigan, US|asin= B004V8W7OO}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bryant campaign achieved success in repealing some city anti-discrimination laws, and proposed other citizen initiatives such as a [[Briggs Initiative|failed California ballot question]] designed to ban gay people or those who supported gay rights from holding public teaching jobs.

From the late 1970s onwards, some [[Christian right|Conservative Christian]] organizations such as the [[Christian Broadcasting Network]], [[Focus on the Family]], [[Concerned Women for America]], the [[American Family Association]] and the [[Christian Coalition of America|Christian Coalition]], among right-wing Christian hate groups such as the [[Westboro Baptist Church]], have been outspoken against LGBT rights.

Some [[neo-Nazi]] organizations, such as the American [[National Socialist Movement (United States)|National Socialist Movement]], oppose LGBT rights and may advocate [[capital punishment]] for people engaging in [[sodomy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=25 POINTS OF AMERICAN NATIONAL SOCIALISM |url=http://www.nsm88.org/25points/25pointsengl.html |publisher=National Socialist Movement |accessdate=3 September 2014 |quote=Only members of the nation may be citizens of the state. Only those of pure White blood, whatever their creed, may be members of the nation. Non-citizens may live in America only as guests and must be subject to laws for aliens. Accordingly, no Jew or homosexual may be a member of the nation. |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130404235316/http://www.nsm88.org/25points/25pointsengl.html |archivedate= 4 April 2013 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== U.S. public opinion ====
{{see also|Public opinion of same-sex marriage in the United States}}
Public opinion has shifted towards increased acceptance of homosexuality and equal rights for gays and lesbians since the late 1970s.  According to the Gallup poll, the percentage of Americans who think that same-sex relations between consenting adults should be legal increased from 43% in 1977 to 59% in 2007.&lt;ref name="gallup07"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/27694/Tolerance-Gay-Rights-HighWater-Mark.aspx|title=Tolerance for Gay Rights at High-Water Mark|author=Gallup, Inc.|work=Gallup.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1977, 56% of Americans thought that gay people should have equal rights in terms of job opportunities.  {{as of|2007}}, that number has risen to 89%.&lt;ref name=gallup07 /&gt;  In 1982, 34% thought that homosexuality should be considered "an acceptable alternative lifestyle".  {{as of|2007}}, that number is 54%.&lt;ref name="gallup07" /&gt;  In 1997, 27% of Americans thought that [[same-sex marriage]]s should be legally valid.  That number is 46% {{as of|2007|lc=y}}.  In 1977, 13% of Americans thought that sexual orientation is "something a person is born with"; {{as of|2007|lc=y}}, that percentage increased to 42%.&lt;ref name=gallup07 /&gt; A poll conducted in 2013 showed a record high of 58% of the Americans supporting legal recognition for same-sex marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Kludt, Tom|url=http://livewire.talkingpointsmemo.com/entry/poll-new-high-of-58-percent-support-same?|title=Poll:New High Of 58 Percent Support Same-Sex Marriage|publisher=livewire.talkingpointsmemo.com|date=18 March 2013|accessdate=11 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-fix/wp/2013/03/18/gay-marriage-support-hits-new-high-in-post-abc-poll/|title=Gay marriage support hits new high in Post-ABC poll|publisher=washingtonpost.com|date=18 March 2013|accessdate=11 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2015, a Washington Post-ABC News poll showed that 61% of Americans supported same-sex marriage and a similar share were against state-by-state legalization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/courts_law/poll-gay-marriage-support-at-record-high/2015/04/22/f6548332-e92a-11e4-aae1-d642717d8afa_story.html|title=Poll: Gay-marriage support at record high|publisher=washingtonpost.com|date=23 April 2015|accessdate=24 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous studies have investigated the prevalence of acceptance and disapproval of homosexuality and have consistently found correlations with various demographic, psychological, and social variables. For example, studies (mainly conducted in the United States) have found that heterosexuals with positive attitudes towards homosexuality are more likely to be non-religious, politically liberal or moderate, young, female and have close personal contact with [[coming out|openly]] gay men and lesbians.&lt;ref&gt;Studies finding that heterosexual men usually exhibit more hostile attitudes toward gay men and lesbians than heterosexual women:
*Herek, G. M. (1994). ''Assessing heterosexuals' attitudes toward lesbians and gay men.'' In "B. Greene and G.M. Herek (Eds.) Psychological perspectives on lesbian and gay issues: Vol. 1 Lesbian and gay psychology: Theory, research, and clinical applications." Thousands Oaks, Ca: Sage.
*Kite, M.E. (1984). ''Sex differences in attitudes toward homosexuals: A meta-analytic review.'' Journal of Homosexuality, 10 (1–2), 69–81.
*Morin, S., &amp; Garfinkle, E. (1978). ''Male homophobia.'' Journal of Social Issues, 34 (1), 29–47.
*Thompson, E., Grisanti, C., &amp; Pleck, J. (1985). ''Attitudes toward the male role and their correlates.'' Sex Roles, 13 (7/8), 413–427.
For other correlates, see:
*Larson et al. (1980) ''Heterosexuals' Attitudes Toward Homosexuality'', The Journal of Sex Research, 16, 245–257
*Herek, G. (1988), ''Heterosexuals' Attitudes Toward Lesbians and Gay Men'', ''[[Journal of Sex Research]]'', 25, 451–477
*Kite, M.E., &amp; Deaux, K., 1986. ''Attitudes toward homosexuality: Assessment and behavioral consequences. Basic and Applied Social Psychology,'' 7, 137–162
*Haddock, G., Zanna, M. P., &amp; Esses, V. M. (1993). ''Assessing the structure of prejudicial attitudes: The case of attitudes toward homosexuals.'' Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 65, 1105–1118.
See also: Lewis, Gregory B., ''Black-White Differences in Attitudes toward Homosexuality and Gay Rights,'' Public Opinion Quarterly, Volume 67, Number 1, Pp. 59–78&lt;/ref&gt; They are also more likely to have positive attitudes towards other minority groups&lt;ref&gt;Herek, G.M. (1991). ''Stigma, prejudice, and violence against lesbians and gay men.'' In: J. Gonsiorek &amp; J. Weinrich (Eds.), "Homosexuality: Research implications for public policy" (pp. 60–80). Newbury Park, CA: Sage.&lt;/ref&gt; and are less likely to support traditional gender roles.&lt;ref&gt;Kyes, K.B. &amp; Tumbelaka, L. (1994). ''Comparison of Indonesian and American college students' attitudes toward homosexuality.'' Psychological Reports, 74, 227–237.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== United States Armed Forces ====
{{Main|Don't ask, don't tell}}

Until its repeal in December 2010 by President [[Barack Obama]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Study: Military gays don't undermine unit|url=http://www.nbcnews.com/id/25575198/|accessdate=5 July 2015|work=NBC News|publisher=Associated Press|date=7 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; the United States Armed Forces' "[[Don't ask, don't tell]]" policy required gay men and lesbian women to be discharged from the armed forces if they [[coming out|came out]], but did not allow the military to question people about their sexual orientation.
Even before [[Don't ask, don't tell#History|it was established]], there were advocates for allowing gay people to [[Sexual orientation and military service|serve openly in the military]].  Critics of the policy pointed out that neither [[unit cohesion]] nor morale were affected when the [[United Kingdom|UK]] admitted gay people into the military. A similar comparison has been made to the lack of negative consequences when African-Americans and women were admitted into the military.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/out_in_force.html|title=Out In Force|work=ucdavis.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Boy Scouts of America ====
{{details|Boy Scouts of America membership controversies#Position on homosexuality}}

The [[Boy Scouts of America]] excludes gay and bisexual people from its organizations, an exclusion enforced commonly for Scoutmasters but also for scouts in leadership positions. Their rationale is that homosexuality is immoral, and that Scouts are expected to have certain [[moral]] standards and values, as the [[Scout Oath]] and [[Scout Law]] requires boys to be "morally straight".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scouting.org/BoyScouts.aspx |title=Boy Scouts |publisher=Scouting.org |accessdate=21 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Boy Scout organization does not view their policy as unjustly [[discriminatory]], but instead defends their policy saying that, "Tolerance for diversity of values does not require abdication of one's own values".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scouting.org/media/positions/unitedway.html|title=Position statements: United Way|author=The Boy Scouts of America|date=|work=scouting.org|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20021016025135/http://www.scouting.org/media/positions/unitedway.html|archivedate=16 October 2002|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000 the [[United States Supreme Court]] ruled in [[Boy Scouts of America v. Dale]] that the Boy Scouts of America is a [[Club (organization)|private organization]], and as such can decide its own membership rules.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archives.cnn.com/2000/LAW/06/28/scotus.gay.boyscouts|title=Breaking News, U.S., World, Weather, Entertainment &amp; Video News - CNN.com|work=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is still a movement to try to persuade the organization to change its policy or allow local chapters to decide for themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scoutingforall.org/data/layer02/mission.html|title=Scouting for All: Committed to Scouting, Open to Diversity.  Working to end discrimination against gays, atheists, agnostics, other non-theists, and all other groups in the Boy Scouts of America.|work=scoutingforall.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, the [[U.S. Congress]] passed the [[Support Our Scouts Act]] of 2005 to exempt the BSA from anti-discrimination laws, to require the [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]] to support scouting [[National Scout jamboree (Boy Scouts of America)|Jamboree]]s (thus rendering ineffective a Federal Court injunction prohibiting this as an [[unconstitutional]] [[establishment of religion]] in violation of the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]]) and to require [[U.S. state|state]] or local governments that receive Community Development Block Grant money from the [[United States Department of Housing and Urban Development|Department of Housing and Urban Development]] to allow BSA to have meetings in their facilities or on their property.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bsalegal.org/support-our-scouts-act-of-2005-261.asp |title=Support our scouts act of 2005 |publisher=BSALegal.org |date=30 December 2005 |accessdate=21 August 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20130112130516/http://www.bsalegal.org/support-our-scouts-act-of-2005-261.asp |archivedate=12 January 2013 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The BSA receives much of its funding and support from religious groups noted for their opposition to the [[gay rights movement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Two-year anniversary of Supreme Court case|url=http://www.religionlink.org/tip_020624b.php|website=religionlink.org|accessdate=4 July 2015|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090416213806/http://www.religionlink.org/tip_020624b.php|archivedate=16 April 2009|date=24 June 2002|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some BSA local councils found that [[United Way of America|United Way]]'s, municipalities', school districts' and businesses' support and funding was reduced because of their adherence to the BSA's policy on sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ffrf.org/timely/bsa.php|title=Boy Scouts Of America Practices Discrimination|publisher=Freedom From Religion Foundation|accessdate=9 October 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050207120637/http://ffrf.org/timely/bsa.php|archivedate=7 February 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to continue receiving funding, local councils like New Jersey signed nondiscrimination agreements contrary to BSA National Council policy.&lt;ref name="jersey"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bsa-discrimination.org/html/njcouncil.html|title=United Way to Continue Aid to Central Jersey Scouts|work=NY Times|date=31 August 2001|accessdate=3 November 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lambdalegal.org/cgi-bin/iowa/news/fact.html?record=1325|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060626123129/http://www.lambdalegal.org/cgi-bin/iowa/news/fact.html?record=1325|title=: The Impact of the Boy Scouts of America's Anti-Gay Discrimination|archivedate=26 June 2006|work=lambdalegal.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other outdoor-focused, youth-based organizations such as the [[4-H]] club and [[Girl Scouts of the USA]] do not discriminate on the basis of sexual orientation.

In most countries where Boy Scouts organizations exist homosexuality is not regarded as incompatible with scout values, and gay members are not excluded from activities;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scoutingforall.org/data/layer02/international.html|title=Scouting for All: Committed to Scouting, Open to Diversity.  Working to end discrimination against gays, atheists, agnostics, other non-theists, and all other groups in the Boy Scouts of America.|work=scoutingforall.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; this includes the [[United Kingdom]], where scouting was founded by [[Baden-Powell]].

In July 2015, the Boy Scouts' executive board voted to end the ban on adult leaders who are openly gay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2015/07/27/us/boy-scouts-gay-leaders-feat/|title=Boy Scouts change policy on gay leaders|author=Todd Leopold, CNN|date=27 July 2015|work=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|LGBT|Human rights|Politics}}
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Antifeminism]]
* [[Culture war]]
* [[Gay agenda]]
* [[Hate crimes]]
* [[Heteronormativity]]
* [[Homophile]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Homophobic propaganda]]
* [[Homosexual recruitment]]
* [[Lesbophobia]]
* [[LGBT social movements]]
* [[LGBT retirement issues]]
* [[List of organizations designated by the Southern Poverty Law Center as anti-LGBT hate groups]]
* [[List of U.S. ballot initiatives to repeal LGBT anti-discrimination laws]]
* [[Straight pride]]
* [[Violence against LGBT people]]
{{div col end}}

== Notes ==
{{reflist|group=note|colwidth=30em}}

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{LGBT|social=expanded|rights=expanded}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lgbt Rights Opposition}}
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]
[[Category:LGBT rights|Opposition]]
[[Category:Persecution of LGBT people]]
[[Category:Discrimination against LGBT people]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>