<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121025164844|519788138" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1527351" pageid="1527351" ns="0" title="LGBTQ rights opposition"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-10-25T21:53:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2007}}
{{Globalize|date=December 2010}}
{{LGBT rights}}
'''LGBT rights opposition''' refers to active opposition to lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender civil rights. Organizations influential in [[LGBT rights]] opposition frequently challenge judicial rulings, and legislative initiatives, and dispute findings that [[sexual orientation]] is an immutable characteristic. These groups are often affiliated with [[right-wing]] religious and [[social conservatism|socially conservative]] political organizations.

Such opposition can be motivated by religious belief, political ideology, [[homophobia]], or other factors.

The rights and privileges that opponents reject may include the right to free enjoyment of interpersonal and sexual relationships, government recognition of gay rights and anti-discrimination laws, [[same-sex marriage]], [[civil unions|civil unions or partnerships]], [[adoption]] by same-sex couples, access to [[assisted reproductive technology]], and access to [[sex reassignment surgery]].

== History ==
[[File:Bucherverbrennung-book-burning-Nazi-1933-Institute.jpg|left|thumb|Students organised by the [[Nazi]] party parade in front of the [[Institut für Sexualwissenschaft|Institute for Sexual Research]] in Berlin on May 6, 1933, before pillaging it and confiscating its books and photos for burning.]]
{{Expand section|date=July 2011}}
The first organized [[gay rights movement]] arose in the late nineteenth century in Germany.&lt;ref name=chron&gt;[http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/CHR06.HTM Archive for Sexology]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1920s and into the early 1930s, there were gay communities in cities like Berlin; sexologist [[Magnus Hirschfeld]] was one of the most notable spokespeople for gay rights at this time. When the Nazi party came to power in 1933, one of the party's first acts was to burn down Hirschfeld's [[Institut für Sexualwissenschaft]], where many prominent Nazis had been treated for sexual problems.&lt;ref name="Lenz"&gt;"not ten percent of those men who, in 1933, took the fate of Germany into their hands, were sexually normal" LUDWIG L. LENZ, The Memoirs of a Sexologist (New York: 1954) pp. 429, cited by Erwin Haeberle in "Swastika, Pink Triangle, and Yellow Star – The Destruction of Sexology and the Persecution of Homosexuals in Nazi Germany" The Journal of Sex Research, vol. 17, no. 3 (August 1981), pp. 270–287, http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/SWAST.HTM#A7&lt;/ref&gt; Initially tolerant to the homosexuality of [[Ernst Rohm]] and his followers, homosexuals were purged from the Nazi Party following the [[Night of the Long Knives]] and the [[Paragraph 175|Section 175 Laws]] began to be enforced again, with [[homosexuals]] interned in concentration camps by 1938 (see [[Persecution of homosexuals in Nazi Germany and the Holocaust]]).

Under National Socialism in Germany, the dismantling of homosexual rights was approached in two ways. By strengthening and re-enforcing existing laws that had fallen into disuse, it was effectively re-criminalised; homosexuality was treated as a medical disorder, but at a social level rather than individual level intended to reduce the incidence of homosexuality. The treatment was a program of negative eugenics, starting with sterilisation, then a system of working people to death in forced labour camps, and eventually refined by medical scientists to include euthanasia. The driving force was the elimination of degeneracy at various levels – genetic, social, identity and practice, and the elimination of such genetic material in society. Lifton wrote about this in his book ''The Nazi Doctors'':&lt;ref name="LIFTON"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Lifton | first = Robert | title = The Nazi Doctors: Medical Killing and the Psychology of Genocide | publisher = Basic Books | year = 1986}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[...] sexology and defense of homosexuality [...] were aspects of “sexual degeneration, a breakdown of the family and loss of all that is decent,” and ultimately the destruction of the German Volk. [...] medicine was to join in the great national healing mission, and the advance image of what Nazi doctors were actually to become: the healer turned killer. [...] Sterilization policies were always associated with the therapeutic and regenerative principles of the biomedical vision: with the “purification of the national body” and the "eradication of morbid hereditary dispositions.” Sterilization was considered part of “negative eugenics” [...]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.holocaust-history.org/lifton/LiftonT042.shtml Lifton' Nazi Doctors p.42]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

It is argued that the numbers of homosexuals eliminated was quite low, and confined to Germany itself, based on estimates that of 50,000 homosexuals who came before the courts, between 5,000 and 15,000&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/hsx/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.holocaust-trc.org/homosx.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.holocaustforgotten.com/fivmil.htm&lt;/ref&gt; ended up in concentration camps. However, many of those who came before the courts were directed (or volunteered) to undergo sterilisation/castration; they would be included with others who, in line with the historic shift in German society (that started with [[Westphal]], and developed through [[Krafft-Ebing]] to [[Magnus Hirschfeld]], of homosexuality being seen as having a neurological, endocrinological and/or genetic basis), were treated for homosexuality as a medical rather than criminal matter. Those treated by psychiatrists and thereby included in the T4 project to eliminate people with medical disorders would not be reflected in the rates of those dealt with as criminals.

After the [[Second World War]], campaigns for gay rights began to develop{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}, initially in the UK, Europe and North America. Towards the end of the 1960s homosexuality began to be decriminalised and demedicalised in countries such as the UK, New Zealand, Australia, North America and Western Europe, in the context of the [[sexual revolution]] and [[anti-psychiatry]] movements. Organized opposition to gay and lesbian rights began in the 1970s,{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}, primarily amongst Christian groups, following the liberalization of attitudes and laws relating to homosexuality in many English-speaking countries and Western Europe.

==Public opinion==
{{Main|Societal attitudes toward homosexuality}}
Societal attitudes towards homosexuality vary greatly in different cultures and different historical periods, as do attitudes toward sexual desire, activity and relationships in general. All cultures have their own [[Sexual norm|values regarding appropriate and inappropriate sexuality]]; some sanction same-sex love and sexuality, while others disapprove of such activities.&lt;ref&gt;Murray, Stephen O., ''Homosexualities'', University of Chicago 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

According to The 2007 Pew Global Attitudes Project, "Throughout [[Western Europe]] and much of the [[Americas]], there is widespread tolerance towards homosexuality. However, the [[United States]], [[Japan]], [[South Korea]], and [[Israel]] stand apart from other wealthy nations on this issue; in each of these countries, fewer than half of those surveyed say homosexuality should be accepted by society. Meanwhile, in most of [[Africa]], [[Asia]] and the [[Middle East]], there is less tolerance toward homosexuality."&lt;ref&gt;http://pewglobal.org/reports/pdf/258.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious reasons for opposition==
{{Main|Religion and homosexuality}}
Many forms of religions, including the Eastern faiths and Abrahamic faiths, do not support gay sex. [[Evangelicalism|Evangelical Christianity]],&lt;ref&gt;Strauss, Lehman, Litt.D., F.R.G.S. [http://www.bible.org/page.asp?page_id=1302 "Homosexuality: The Christian Perspective"].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Catholicism]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_rom.htm "Roman Catholics and Homosexuality"], Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|Mormonism]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lds.org/hf/library/0,16866,4266-1,00.html?LibraryURL=/lds/hf/display "Teaching about Procreation and Chastity: Homosexuality"], The Church of Jesus-Christ of Latter-day Saints. Home &amp; Family.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Orthodox Judaism]],&lt;ref&gt;Shafran, Rabbi Avi. [http://www.jlaw.com/Commentary/maritalprob.html "Jewish Law: Marital Problems"]. Jewish Law Commentary: Examining Halacha, Jewish Issues, and Secular Law.&lt;/ref&gt;
and [[Islam]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_isla1.htm "Islam and Homosexuality"], Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance (2005).&lt;/ref&gt; hold the view that gay sex is a [[sin]] and that its practice and acceptance in society weakens moral standards and undermines the family.

=== Christian views and opposition to homosexuality ===
{{Main|Homosexuality and Christianity|List of Christian denominational positions on homosexuality|The Bible and homosexuality}}

==== Christian mainstream opposition ====
Orthodox, Roman Catholic and conservative Evangelicals within the Anglican and Baptist churches are opposed to people of the same sex having sex together, having committed partnerships, raising children, etc.; they oppose people changing sex as well.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

=== Islamic opposition ===
{{See|Islam and sexual orientation}}
[[Homosexuality|Homosexual acts]] are regarded as criminal and forbidden in most [[Islam]]ic countries according to [[Sharia law]]. Same-sex intercourse officially carries the [[death penalty]] in [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Iran]], [[Mauritania]], [[Nigeria]], [[Sudan]] and [[Yemen]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ilga.org/news_results.asp?LanguageID=1&amp;FileID=1111&amp;ZoneID=7&amp;FileCategory=50 ILGA:7 countries still put people to death for same-sex acts]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religionfacts.com/homosexuality/islam.htm Homosexuality and Islam – ReligionFacts] Retrieved 2 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
It formerly carried the death penalty in [[Afghanistan]] under the [[Taliban]]. The legal situation in the [[United Arab Emirates]] is unclear. In other nations, such as [[Bahrain]], [[Qatar]], [[Algeria]] and the [[Maldives]], homosexuality is punished with jail time, fines, or corporal punishment. In some Muslim-majority nations, such as [[Turkey]], [[Jordan]], [[Indonesia]] or [[Mali]], same-sex intercourse is not specifically forbidden by law. In [[Egypt]], openly gay men have been prosecuted under general public morality laws. ''See: [[Cairo 52]].''

On the other hand, homosexuality has been legal in Turkey for decades. In Oman, the [[Khanith|Xanith]] are men who occupy a role in society which allows them to have sex with men provided they act in the 'female role' and [[Top, bottom and versatile#Bottom|receive the phallus]].&lt;ref name = XANITH&gt;{{Cite journal
 | last = Nanda
 | first = Serena
 | title = Neither Man Nor Woman: The Hijras of India
 | publisher = Wadsworth Publishing
 | year = 1998
 | pages = 130–131
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Saudi Arabia, the maximum punishment for homosexuality is public execution, but the government will use other punishments – e.g., fines, jail time, and [[Flagellation|whipping]] – as alternatives, unless it feels that homosexuals are challenging state authority by engaging in [[LGBT social movements]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sodomylaws.org/world/saudi_arabia/saudinews19.htm Is Beheading Really the Punishment for Homosexuality in Saudi Arabia?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Iran is perhaps the nation to execute the largest number of its citizens for homosexuality. Since the 1979 [[Iranian Revolution|Islamic revolution]] in Iran, the Iranian government has executed more than 4,000 people charged with homosexual acts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vexen.co.uk/religion/homosexuality.html#Islam |title=Homosexuality and Religion}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Afghanistan after the fall of the Taliban, homosexuality went from a capital crime to one that is punished with fines and prison sentence.

Most international human rights organizations, such as [[Human Rights Watch]] and [[Amnesty International]], condemn laws that make homosexual relations between consenting adults a crime. Muslim nations insist that such laws are necessary to preserve Islamic morality and virtue. Of the nations with a majority of Muslim inhabitants, only Lebanon has an organization which is trying to get homosexuality legalized.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.helem.net/ Helem&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{See also|Mahmoud Asgari and Ayaz Marhoni}}

=== Indian and East Asian opposition ===
{{See|Homosexuality and Hinduism|Homosexuality and Buddhism|Homosexuality and Taoism}}
Among the [[Indian religions|religions that originated in India]], including [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]], [[Jainism]] and [[Sikhism]], teachings regarding homosexuality are less clear than among the Abrahamic traditions. Unlike in western religions, homosexuality is rarely discussed. However, a few contemporary religious authorities in the various dharmic traditions view homosexuality negatively, and when it is discussed, it is discouraged or actively forbidden.&lt;ref&gt;See [[Homosexuality and Buddhism]] for pronouncements from Thai, Tibetan and Chinese Buddhist leaders.&lt;br /&gt;The supreme body of Sikhism condemned homosexuality in 2005: [http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2005/03/28/sikhguy-050328.html World Sikh group against gay marriage bill], [[CBC Newsworld|CBC News]], Tuesday, 29 March 2005.&lt;br /&gt;Hinduism is diverse, with no supreme governing body, but the majority of [[swami]]s opposed same-sex relationships in a 2004 survey, and a minority supported them. See: [http://www.faithandthecity.org/issues/social/articles/Discussions_on_Dharma%20.shtml Discussions on Dharma], by Rajiv Malik, in Hinduism Today. October/November/December 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; (see [[Homosexuality in China]].)

== Health ==
{{See also|LGBT issues in medicine}}

A systematic review of research in the UK indicates that there appears to be limited evidence available from which to draw general conclusions about lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender health because epidemiological studies have not incorporated sexuality as a factor in data collection.&lt;ref name = WMID&gt;{{Cite journal | last1= Meads | first1= C
 | last2= Pennant | first2= M
 | last3= McManus | first3= J
 | last4= Bayliss | first4= S
 | title=  A systematic review of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender health in the West Midlands region of the UK compared to published UK research
 | publisher=  Unit of Public Health, Epidemiology &amp; Biostatistics, West Midlands Health Technology Assessment Group
 | year= 2009 | postscript= &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The review found that from the research there is in the UK, there are no differences in terms of major health problems between LGBT people and the general population, although LGBT people's general health appears poorer, but with no specific information on common and major diseases, cancers or long-term health.&lt;ref name = WMID/&gt;  Research points to issues encountered from an early age, such as LGBT people being targeted for bullying, assault, and discrimination, as contributing significantly to depression, suicide and other mental health issues in adulthood.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bjp.rcpsych.org/cgi/content/abstract/185/6/479 Rates and predictors of mental illness in gay men, lesbians and bisexual men and women], [[British Journal of Psychiatry]], (2004) 185: 479–485&lt;/ref&gt;  One researcher looked at the long-term consequences of bullying at schools,&lt;ref name = RIVERS1&gt;{{Cite journal | last1= Rivers | first1= I
 | title=  The bullying of sexual minorities at school: Its nature and long-term correlates.
 | journal=  Educational and Child Psychology
 | pages = 32–46
 | year= 2001
 | issue = 18(1) | postscript= &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = RIVERS2&gt;{{Cite journal | last1= Rivers | first1= I
 | title=  Recollections of Bullying at School and Their Long-Term Implications for Lesbians, Gay Men, and Bisexuals
 | journal=  Crisis
 | pages = 169–175
 | year= 2004
 | issue = 25(4) | postscript= &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a social researcher has focused on the way LGBT people can experience discriminatory practices in accessing healthcare, and its effects.&lt;ref name = WILT1&gt;{{Cite journal
 | last = Wilton
 | first = Tamsin
 | title = Sexualities in health and social care: a textbook
 | publisher = Open University Press
 | year = 2000
 | isbn = 0-335-20026-5
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some LGBT activists argue that the experience of growing up LGBT contributes to mental health issues in adulthood, and the barriers to accessing appropriate healthcare as adults contribute towards poorer health; they argue that protection of LGBT rights is necessary to minimise the potential development of health problems and ensure access to healthcare resources. In 2009 Canadian LGBT activists filed a complaint alleging that the health issues of GLB Canadians are being neglected by the government, equating it to a violation of the human rights of LGBT people. In the complaint, the activists highlight a life expectancy 20 years less than average for LGB people, with more cases of cancer and HIV and increased rates of suicide, alcoholism and drug use.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xtra.ca/BinaryContent/pdf/human%20rights%20complaint.pdf Human Rights complaint against the Canadian government by LGBT activists]&lt;/ref&gt;  Pundits such as writer and editor Terry O'Neill reject the idea that homophobia caused all the additional GLB health problems in Canada, and derides what he calls "the victim-group mentality, the lack of personal responsibility and the all-too-predictable blaming of others for one's problems".&lt;ref&gt;[http://network.nationalpost.com/np/blogs/fullcomment/archive/2009/05/04/terry-o-neill-a-new-wing-for-canada-s-human-rights-neverland.aspx Terry O'Neill: A new wing for Canada's human rights Neverland], [[National Post]], 4 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opposition in different countries==
===United States===
==== History ====
[[Anita Bryant]] organized [[Save Our Children]], a major campaign to oppose gay rights in the United States. The group used various slogans that played on the fear that gay people were interested in [[Homosexual recruitment|recruiting]] or molesting children into a lifestyle. A common slogan of the campaign was "Homosexuals cannot reproduce — so they must recruit." The Bryant campaign was successful in repealing many of the city anti-discrimination laws, and in proposing other citizen initiatives, such as a [[Briggs Initiative|failed California ballot question]] designed to ban homosexuals or anyone who endorsed gay rights from being a public school teacher.

From the late 1970s onwards, [[Christian right|Conservative Christian]] organizations such as the [[Christian Broadcasting Network]], [[Focus on the Family]], [[Concerned Women for America]], the [[American Family Association]] and the [[Christian Coalition of America|Christian Coalition]] built strong lobbying and fundraising organizations to oppose the gay rights movement's goals.

Some [[neo-Nazism|Neo-Nazi]] organizations oppose gay rights and may advocate [[capital punishment]] for people engaging in homosexual activity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mediamouse.org/resources/right.php?orgId=3 The Michigan-based '''National Socialist Movement']&lt;/ref&gt;

==== US public opinion ====
Public opinion has shifted towards increased acceptance of homosexuality and equal rights for gays and lesbians since the late 1970s.  According to the Gallup poll, the percentage of Americans who think that same-sex relations between consenting adults should be legal increased from 43% in 1977 to 59% in 2007.&lt;ref name="gallup07"&gt;[http://www.gallup.com/poll/27694/Tolerance-Gay-Rights-HighWater-Mark.aspx The Gallup Poll | Tolerance for Gay Rights at High-Water Mark | May 27, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1977, 56% of Americans thought that gay people should have equal rights in terms of job opportunities.  As of 2007, that number has risen to 89%.&lt;ref name=gallup07 /&gt;  In 1982, 34% thought that homosexuality should be considered an acceptable lifestyle.  As of 2007, that number is 54%.&lt;ref name="gallup07" /&gt;  In 1997, 27% of Americans thought that [[same-sex marriage]]s should be legally valid.  That number is 46% as of 2007.  In 1977, 13% of Americans thought that sexual orientation is "something a person is born with"; as of 2007, that percentage increased to 42%.&lt;ref name=gallup07 /&gt;

Numerous studies have investigated the prevalence of acceptance and disapproval of homosexuality and have consistently found correlations with various demographic, psychological, and social variables. For example, studies (mainly conducted in the United States) have found that heterosexuals with positive attitudes towards homosexuality are more likely to be female, young, non-religious, politically liberal or moderate, and have close personal contact with [[coming out|openly]] gay men and lesbians.&lt;ref&gt;Studies finding that heterosexual men usually exhibit more hostile attitudes toward gay men and lesbians than heterosexual women:
*Herek, G. M. (1994). ''Assessing heterosexuals’ attitudes toward lesbians and gay men.'' In "B. Greene and G.M. Herek (Eds.) Psychological perspectives on lesbian and gay issues: Vol. 1 Lesbian and gay psychology: Theory, research, and clinical applications." Thousands Oaks, Ca: Sage.
*Kite, M.E. (1984). ''Sex differences in attitudes toward homosexuals: A meta-analytic review.'' Journal of Homosexuality, 10 (1–2), 69–81.
*Morin, S., &amp; Garfinkle, E. (1978). ''Male homophobia.'' Journal of Social Issues, 34 (1), 29–47.
*Thompson, E., Grisanti, C., &amp; Pleck, J. (1985). ''Attitudes toward the male role and their correlates.'' Sex Roles, 13 (7/8), 413–427.
For other correlates, see:
*Larson et al. (1980) ''Heterosexuals' Attitudes Toward Homosexuality'', The Journal of Sex Research, 16, 245–257
*Herek, G. (1988), ''Heterosexuals' Attitudes Toward Lesbians and Gay Men'', ''[[Journal of Sex Research]]'', 25, 451–477
*Kite, M.E., &amp; Deaux, K., 1986. ''Attitudes toward homosexuality: Assessment and behavioral consequences. Basic and Applied Social Psychology,'' 7, 137–162
*Haddock, G., Zanna, M. P., &amp; Esses, V. M. (1993). ''Assessing the structure of prejudicial attitudes: The case of attitudes toward homosexuals.'' Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 65, 1105–1118.
See also: Lewis, Gregory B., ''Black-White Differences in Attitudes toward Homosexuality and Gay Rights,'' Public Opinion Quarterly, Volume 67, Number 1, Pp. 59–78&lt;/ref&gt; They are also more likely to have positive attitudes towards other minority groups&lt;ref&gt;Herek, G.M. (1991). ''Stigma, prejudice, and violence against lesbians and gay men.'' In: J. Gonsiorek &amp; J. Weinrich (Eds.), "Homosexuality: Research implications for public policy" (pp. 60–80). Newbury Park, CA: Sage.&lt;/ref&gt; and are less likely to support traditional gender roles.&lt;ref&gt;Kyes, K.B. &amp; Tumbelaka, L. (1994). ''Comparison of Indonesian and American college students' attitudes toward homosexuality.'' Psychological Reports, 74, 227–237.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== United States Armed Forces ====
{{Main|Don't ask, don't tell}}

Until its repeal by President [[Barack Obama]] in December 2010,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/25575198/%3Cbr%20%3E%3C Study: Military gays don't undermine unit]&lt;/ref&gt; the United States Armed Forces' "[[Don't ask, don't tell]]" policy required gay men and lesbian women to be discharged from the armed forces if they [[coming out|came out]], but did not allow the military to question people about their sexual orientation.
Even before [[Don't ask, don't tell#History|it was established]], there were advocates for allowing gay people to [[Sexual orientation and military service|serve openly in the military]].  Critics of the current policy point out that neither [[unit cohesion]] nor morale were affected when the United Kingdom admitted gay people. A similar comparison has been made to the lack of negative consequences when African-Americans and women were admitted into the military.&lt;ref&gt;[http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/out_in_force.html Out In Force | Sexual Orientation and the Military]&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Boy Scouts of America ====
===== Policy and rationale =====
{{details|Boy Scouts of America membership controversies#Position on homosexuals}}

The [[Boy Scouts of America]] excludes gay and bisexual people from its organizations, an exclusion enforced commonly for Scoutmasters but also for scouts in leadership positions. Their rationale is that homosexuality is immoral, and that scouts are expected to have certain [[moral]] standards and values, as the [[Scout Oath]] and [[Scout Law]] requires boys to be "morally straight".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.scouting.org/BoyScouts.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; The Boy Scout organization does not view their policy as unjustly [[Discrimination|discriminatory]], but instead defends their policy saying that, "Tolerance for diversity of values does not require abdication of one's own values".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scouting.org/media/positions/unitedway.html Position Statement: United Way&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000 the [[United States Supreme Court]] ruled in [[Boy Scouts of America v. Dale]] that the Boy Scouts of America is a [[club|private organization]], and as such can decide its own membership rules.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2000/LAW/06/28/scotus.gay.boyscouts CNN.com – Supreme Court says Boy Scouts can bar gay troop leaders – June 28, 2000&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; There is still a movement to try to persuade the organization to change its policy or allow local chapters to decide for themselves.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scoutingforall.org/data/layer02/mission.html Scouting For All – Mission Statement]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, the [[U.S. Congress]] passed the "[[Support Our Scouts Act|Support Our Scouts Act of 2005]]" to exempt the BSA from anti-discrimination laws, to require the [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]] to support scouting [[National Scout jamboree (Boy Scouts of America)|Jamboree]]s (thus rendering ineffective a Federal Court injunction prohibiting this as an [[unconstitutional]] [[establishment of religion]] in violation of the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]]) and to require [[U.S. state|state]] or local governments that receive Community Development Block Grant money from the [[United States Department of Housing and Urban Development|Department of Housing and Urban Development]] to allow BSA to have meetings in their facilities or on their property.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bsalegal.org/support-our-scouts-act-of-2005-261.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

The BSA receives much of its funding and support from religious groups noted for their opposition to the [[gay rights movement]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religionlink.org/tip_020624b.php ReligionLink – Boy Scouts: Two-year anniversary of Supreme Court case]&lt;/ref&gt; Some BSA local councils found that [[United Way of America|United Way]]s, municipalities, school districts and businesses support and funding was reduced because of their adherence to the BSA's policy on sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thewaytocare.org/html/about_bsqa.html|title=Boy Scout Q &amp; A|publisher=United Way of Eastern Fairfield County|accessdate=2007-10-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ffrf.org/timely/bsa.php|title=Boy Scouts Of America Practices Discrimination|publisher=Freedom From Religion Foundation|accessdate=2007-10-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to continue receiving funding, local councils like New Jersey signed nondiscrimination agreements contrary to BSA National Council policy.&lt;ref name="jersey"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bsa-discrimination.org/html/njcouncil.html|title=United Way to Continue Aid to Central Jersey Scouts|work=NY Times|date=2001-08-31|accessdate=2006-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20060626123129/http://www.lambdalegal.org/cgi-bin/iowa/news/fact.html?record=1325 The Impact of the Boy Scouts of America’s Anti-Gay Discrimination]&lt;/ref&gt;  Other outdoor-focused, youth-based organizations such as the [[4-H]] club and [[Girl Scouts of the USA]] do not discriminate against homosexuals.

In most countries where Boy Scouts organizations exist gay people are not regarded as incompatible with scout values, and are not discriminated against;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scoutingforall.org/data/layer02/international.html Scouting for All: International]&lt;/ref&gt; this includes the [[United Kingdom]], where scouting was founded by [[Baden-Powell]].

=== United Kingdom ===

In 1988, the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]], who were in government at the time, enacted [[Section 28]] which banned local authorities (including state schools) from promoting homosexuality or endorsing same-sex marriages. Research on the effect of suppressing information about sexuality awareness in schools showed a correspondence with increases in the level of homophobic bullying by peers, as well as increased incidence in depression and suicide amongst people trying to come to terms with their sexuality.&lt;ref name = EPSTEIN&gt;{{Cite journal
 | last1 = Epstein
 | first1 = Debbie
 | last2 = O'Flynn
 | first2 = Sarah
 | last3 = Telford
 | first3 = David
 | title = Silenced Sexualities in Schools and Universities
 | publisher = Trentham Books
 | year = 2003
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The law was repealed in 2003 by the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour government]].

In June 2009, Cameron—then leader of the Conservative Party whilst campaigning to be the next Prime Minister—formally apologised for his party introducing the law, stating that it was a mistake and had been offensive to gay people,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/politics/cameron-sorry-for-section-28-1728003.html The Independent - David Cameron apologises for Section 28]&lt;/ref&gt; and has since proposed a number of LGBT equality measures.

The largest voice against LGBT right in the UK currently comes from the Church of England over the issue of gay marriage. Labour passed into law in 2005 the ability for same-sex couples to enter civil-partnerships, but they could not take place in a church or be called a "Marriage". The [[Church of England]] has taken up opposition to the current Conservative/Liberal Democrat Government's plans to extend this to full marriage rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/religion/8221964/Coalition-ministers-consider-gay-marriage-plans.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Tim | last=Ross | title=Coalition ministers consider gay marriage plans | date=December 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[British National Party]] has shifted its platform from recriminalization to an extension of [[section 28]]-style legislation, i.e. making it illegal to portray homosexuality positively in the media.&lt;ref&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/magazine/story/0,11913,783675,00.html ''The Observer'']&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1999, the [[Admiral Duncan pub]], a gay bar in London's Soho, was targeted up as part of a terrorist campaign by a [[National Socialist Movement (United Kingdom)|National Socialist Movement]] member, [[David Copeland]]; three people were killed, and 70 maimed or injured by a nail bomb detonated in the pub.&lt;ref name = DUNCAN&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/april/30/newsid_2499000/2499249.stm | work=BBC News | title=1999: Dozens injured in Soho nail bomb | date=April 30, 1999 | accessdate=May 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{multicol}}
* [[Culture war]]
* [[Gay agenda]]
* [[Heteronormativity]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobic propaganda]]
* [[Homosexual recruitment]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[LGBT social movements]]
* [[LGBT retirement issues]]
* [[List of organizations designated by the Southern Poverty Law Center as hate groups]]
* [[List of US ballot initiatives to repeal LGBT anti-discrimination laws]]
* [[Straight pride]]
* [[Opponents of same-sex marriage in the United States]]
* [[Violence against LGBT people]]
* [[Westboro Baptist Church]]
{{multicol-break}}{{Portal box|LGBT|Human rights|Politics}}
{{multicol-end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|3}}

{{LGBT|social=expanded|rights=expanded}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lgbt Rights Opposition}}
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]
[[Category:LGBT rights|Opposition]]

[[bg:Антихомосексуално движение]]
[[he:התנגדות לזכויות להט"ב]]
[[ru:Антигомосексуальное движение]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>