<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071105152539|169389291" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1527351" pageid="1527351" ns="0" title="LGBTQ rights opposition"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-11T05:41:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2007}}
{{Globalize/US}}
{{Gay rights}}

'''LGBT rights opposition''' refers to various movements or attitudes which oppose the extension of certain [[LGBT social movements|rights]] to [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], and [[transgender]] people.  The specific rights that are opposed may include rights to [[social equality]], [[same-sex marriage|marriage]] or [[civil unions]], [[adoption by same-sex couples|adoption]], and freedom from [[discrimination]] on the basis of [[sexual orientation]] or [[gender identity]].

== History ==

[[Image:Bucherverbrennung-book-burning-Nazi-1933-Institute.jpg|right|250px|thumb|Students organized by the [[Nazi]] party parade in front of the [[Institute for Sexual Research]] in Berlin on [[May 6]], [[1933]] prior to pillaging it and confiscating its books and photos for burning.]]

The first organized [[gay rights movement]] arose in the late nineteenth century in Germany.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} When the German Nazi party came to power in [[1933]], one of the party's first acts was to burn down the [[Institut für Sexualwissenschaft]].  Subsequently, the Nazis also began sending [[homosexuals]] to concentration camps (see [[History of gays in Nazi Germany and the Holocaust]]). The organized gay rights movement would not rise again until after the [[Second World War]].

From the late 1940s to the early 1960s gay rights movements began to form in America and Western Europe, but it was not until the [[sexual revolution]] of the 1960s and 1970s that an organized movement arose to oppose gay rights.

In the [[1980s]] the rise of [[AIDS]] contributed to a public backlash against LGBT rights issues.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

== Conservative opposition to LGBT rights in the US==

In the late [[1970s]] gay rights organizations were forming self-supporting communities in large urban centers in America such as [[San Francisco]], [[New York City]], and [[Minneapolis]].  Several states reformed their criminal code to decriminalize same-sex sexual relations between consenting adults, and some cities passed local anti-discrimination laws that included protection based on [[sexual orientation]].{{Fact|date=August 2007}}

[[Anita Bryant]] organized the first major opposition movement to gay rights in America, based on [[fundamentalist Christian]] values.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} The group used various slogans that played off the fear that gay people were interested in "recruiting" or molesting children into a "life-style." A common slogan of the campaign was "Homosexuals cannot reproduce — so they must recruit."  The Bryant campaign was successful in repealing many of the city anti-discrimination laws, and in proposing other citizen initiatives, such as a failed California ballot question designed to ban homosexuals or anyone who endorsed gay rights from being a public school teacher.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}  The name of this group was "Save Our Children," and its most successful campaign resulted in the repealing of [[Dade County|Dade County's]] [[Civil Rights Ordinance]] by an overwhelming margin of 69 to 31.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} Soon after, legislation was passed outlawing adoption by non-heterosexual persons in Florida.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} In [[1998]], Dade County passed an anti-discrimination law that included the protection of people from discrimination based on [[sexual orientation]], but the ban on homosexuals adopting children remains on the books.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} The success of the Bryant campaign encouraged the development of other organizations which opposed gay rights legislation.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

From the late [[1970s]] onwards, [[Conservative Christianity|Conservative Christian]] organizations such as the [[700 Club]], [[Focus on the Family]], [[Concerned Women For America]], and the [[Christian Coalition of America|Christian Coalition]] built strong lobbying and fundraising organizations to oppose the gay rights movement's goals.  These organizations tend to align themselves with the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]].

Conservative Christian organizations behaved similarly in other nations.{{Fact|date=August 2007}}  In the [[1980s]] organizations opposed to gay rights successfully persuaded the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] to enact [[Section 28]], which banned public schools from "promoting homosexuality" or endorsing same-sex marriages.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

== American Public opinion ==

Public opinion has shifted towards increased acceptance of homosexuality and equal rights for gays and lesbians over the past 30 years.  According to the Gallup poll, the percentage of Americans who think that same-sex relations between consenting adults should be legal has increased from 32% to 57% since 1986.&lt;ref name="oldgallup"&gt;[http://www.sodomylaws.org/usa/usnews32.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gallup06"&gt;[http://www.seniorjournal.com/NEWS/SeniorStats/6-05-31-SeniorCitizensAtOdds.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1977, 56% of Americans thought that gay people should have equal rights in terms of job opportunities.  Today, that number has risen to 89%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sodomylaws.org/lawrence/lwnews179.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gallup06" /&gt;  In 1992, 38% thought that homosexuality should be considered an acceptable lifestyle.  Today, that number is 54%.&lt;ref name="oldgallup" /&gt;&lt;ref name="gallup06" /&gt;  In 1997, 27% of Americans thought that gay marriages should be legally valid.  That number is now 39%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_poll5.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gallup06" /&gt; In 1977, 13% of Americans thought that sexual orientation was genetically determined; now, 42%{{Fact|date=February 2007}} think it is.

Numerous studies have investigated the prevalence of acceptance and disapproval of homosexuality, and have consistently found correlates with various demographic, psychological, and social variables. For example, studies (mainly conducted in the United States) have found that heterosexuals with positive attitudes towards homosexuality are more likely to be female, young, non-religious, well-educated, politically liberal or moderate, and have close personal contact with [[coming out|openly]] gay men and lesbians.&lt;ref&gt;Studies finding that heterosexual men usually exhibit more hostile attitudes toward gay men and lesbians than do heterosexual women:&lt;br&gt;:*Herek, G. M. (1994). ''Assessing heterosexuals’ attitudes toward lesbians and gay men.'' In "B. Greene and G.M. Herek (Eds.) Psychological perspectives on lesbian and gay issues: Vol. 1 Lesbian and gay psychology: Theory, research, and clinical applications." Thousands Oaks, Ca: Sage.&lt;br&gt;:*Kite, M.E. (1984). ''Sex differences in attitudes toward homosexuals: A meta-analytic review.'' Journal of Homosexuality, 10 (1-2), 69-81.&lt;br&gt;:*Morin, S., &amp; Garfinkle, E. (1978). ''Male homophobia.'' Journal of Social Issues, 34 (1), 29-47.&lt;br&gt;:*Thompson, E., Grisanti, C., &amp; Pleck, J. (1985). ''Attitudes toward the male role and their correlates.'' Sex Roles, 13 (7/8), 413-427.&lt;br&gt;For other correlates, see:&lt;br&gt;:*Larson et al. (1980) ''Heterosexuals' Attitudes Toward Homosexuality'', The Journal of Sex Research, 16, 245-257&lt;br&gt;:*Herek, G. (1988), ''Heterosexuals' Attitudes Toward Lesbians and Gay Men'', ''[[Journal of Sex Research]]'', 25, 451-477&lt;br&gt;:*Kite, M.E., &amp; Deaux, K., 1986. ''Attitudes toward homosexuality: Assessment and behavioral consequences. Basic and Applied Social Psychology,'' 7, 137-162&lt;br&gt;:*Haddock, G., Zanna, M. P., &amp; Esses, V. M. (1993). ''Assessing the structure of prejudicial attitudes: The case of attitudes toward homosexuals.'' Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 65, 1105-1118.&lt;br&gt;:See also: Lewis, Gregory B., ''Black-White Differences in Attitudes toward Homosexuality and Gay Rights,'' Public Opinion Quarterly, Volume 67, Number 1, Pp. 59-78&lt;/ref&gt; They are also more likely to have positive attitudes towards other minority groups&lt;ref&gt;Herek, G.M. (1991). ''Stigma, prejudice, and violence against lesbians and gay men.'' In: J. Gonsiorek &amp; J. Weinrich (Eds.), "Homosexuality: Research implications for public policy" (pp. 60-80). Newbury Park, CA: Sage.&lt;/ref&gt; and are less likely to support traditional gender roles.&lt;ref&gt; Kyes, K.B. &amp; Tumbelaka, L. (1994). ''Comparison of Indonesian and American college students' attitudes toward homosexuality.'' Psychological Reports, 74, 227-237.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Boy Scouts of America ==
=== Policy and rationale ===
{{details|Boy Scouts of America membership controversies#Position on homosexuals}}

The [[Boy Scouts of America]] exclude gay and bisexual people from its organizations, generally for Scoutmasters but also for scouts in leadership positions. Their rationale is that homosexuality is immoral, and that scouts are expected to have certain [[moral]] standards and values, as the [[Scout Oath]] and [[Scout Law]] requires boys to be "morally straight."{{Fact|date=August 2007}}  The Boy Scout organization does not view their policy as unjustly [[Discrimination|discriminatory]], but instead defends their policy saying that, "Tolerance for diversity of values does not require abdication of one's own values" &lt;ref&gt;http://www.scouting.org/media/positions/unitedway.html&lt;/ref&gt;.

In [[2000]] the [[United States Supreme Court]] ruled in [[Boy Scouts of America v. Dale]] that the Boy Scouts of America is a [[club|private organization]], and as such can decide its own membership rules.&lt;ref&gt;http://archives.cnn.com/2000/LAW/06/28/scotus.gay.boyscouts&lt;/ref&gt;  There is still a movement to try and persuade the organization to change its policy or allow local chapters to decide for themselves.

In [[2005]], the [[U.S. Congress]] passed the "[[Support Our Scouts Act|Support Our Scouts Act of 2005]]" to exempt the BSA from anti-discrimination laws, to require the [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]] to support scouting [[National Scout jamboree (Boy Scouts of America)|Jamboree]]s (thus rendering ineffective a Federal Court injunction prohibiting this as an [[unconstitutional]] [[establishment of religion]] in violation of the [[First Amendment]]) and to require [[U.S. state|state]] or local governments that receive Community Development Block Grant money from the [[United States Department of Housing and Urban Development|Department of Housing and Urban Development]] to allow BSA to have meetings in their facilities or on their property.{{Fact|date=August 2007}}

Critics claim that gay people are not incompatible with scout values and are allowed to be members in most countries in the world [http://www.scoutingforall.org/international.shtml], including the [[United Kingdom]], where scouting was founded. Some [[United Way of America|United Way]]s, municipalities, school districts and businesses have stopped supporting the BSA for those reasons. &lt;ref&gt;http://lambdalegal.org/cgi-bin/iowa/news/fact.html?record=1325&lt;/ref&gt;

Other outdoor-focused, youth-based organizations such as the [[4-H]] club and [[Girl Scouts of the USA]] do not have similar policies.  The BSA, however, receives a high level of support from religious groups, many of which are noted for their opposition to the [[gay rights movement]]. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.religionlink.org/tip_020624b.php&lt;/ref&gt;

== United States Armed Forces ==

The United States Armed Forces' "[[Don't Ask, Don't Tell]]" policy requires gay men and lesbians to be discharged from the armed forces if they [[coming out|come out]], but does not allow the military to specifically question people about their sexual orientation.

Even when it was put in place, there have been advocates for allowing gay people to [[Sexual orientation and military service|serve openly in the military]].  Critics of the current policy often argue that when the United Kingdom admitted gay people, no such unit cohesion or morale was lost.{{Fact|date=August 2007}}  The same comparison is made to no negative consequences when African-Americans and women were admitted into the military.

== Fascist and far-right opposition == 
[[Image:National Front at gay pride 2007.jpg|180px|thumb|BNP protesting "Homosexual Marriage" at London Gay Pride 2007]]
[[Fascist]] political parties have been universal in their violent opposition to gay rights. Today, [[Neo Nazi]] organizations and oppose gay rights, and may advocate life sentences in prison or concentration camps for homosexuals, or even the [[death penalty]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mediamouse.org/resources/right.php?orgId=3 The Michigan-based '''National Socialist Movement']&lt;/ref&gt; (which was instituted by the original [[Nazi]]s instituted in 1942&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?sid=328 Southern Poverty Law Center]&lt;/ref&gt;). The [[Ku Klux Klan]] hold that homosexual behaviour should be illegal, and [[HIV]] positive people should be forcibly hospitalized.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kkk.bz/program.htm The Knight's Party Platform]&lt;/ref&gt;. The [[British National Party]] has shifted its platform from recriminalisation to an extension of [[clause 28]]-style legislation, ie. making it illegal to portray homosexuality positively in the media.&lt;ref&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/magazine/story/0,11913,783675,00.html ''The Observer'']&lt;/ref&gt;

== Libertarian opposition ==
{{details|Libertarian perspectives on gay rights#Libertarian opposition to certain goals of major gay rights organizations|Libertarian perspectives on gay rights}}

[[Libertarianism]] runs contrary to the mainstream gay rights movement on some, but not all, gay rights issues. While a libertarian perspective on gay rights endorses some gay rights positions, it also opposes gay rights when they involve anti-discrimination laws that impose government regulations on the private sector, religious organizations or private clubs. The [[Gays and Lesbians For Individual Liberty]] filed a Supreme Court brief in support of the right of the [[Boy Scouts of America]] to refuse to admit gays into its ranks (noting that if the BSA were forced by government to admit gay members, gay organizations might also be forced to admit anti-gay members).  [[Outright Libertarians]], favor an approach that does not require government coercion and seek to limit government action to the implementation of equal rights -- rather than "special rights" such as legally-required preferential treatment on the basis of sexual orientation in employment, housing or education that are often demanded by other gay organizations.

The libertarian position on gay rights underscores the divide between liberal groups (who favor ENDA and hate crimes laws as a primary vehicle for gay rights) and libertarians (who generally view gay rights as equal treatment in areas such as marriage equality and other positions that are broadly opposed by both Democrats and Republicans).

== Anarchist &amp; other opposition ==

Some self-entitled anarchists, such as [[L. Susan Brown]], oppose all marriage, and therefore gay marriage, due to its connection to the state. Some anarchists also see marriage as an inherently oppressive institution.
(See [[Anarchism and society#Anarchist opposition to sexuality|Anarchist criticisms to sexuality]])

== Psychological ==
{{Cleanup|date=August 2007}}

Most LGBT groups see homosexuality as natural and not a choice. A resolution adopted by the [[American Psychological Association]] in [[August 1997]] states that "homosexuality is not a mental disorder".&lt;ref&gt;American Psychological Association Council of Representatives (1997). [http://www.apa.org/pi/sexual.html "Resolution on Appropriate Therapeutic Responses to Sexual Orientation"]. (Adopted August 14, 1997)&lt;/ref&gt;

Some groups, many of which are funded by religious organizations, promote an idea called ''[[reparative therapy]]'', which considers homosexuality to be a behavior that can be modified, rather than a permanent orientation, with the goal of creating [[ex-gay]]s.&lt;ref&gt; Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance (2006). [http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_exod.htm "ReligiousTolerance.org: REPARATIVE &amp; SIMILAR THERAPIES"]. Retrieved June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Ironically the desire to change ones sexuality is considered a disorder by the [[American Psychological Association]]{{Fact|date=November 2007}}.

== Religious and philosophical ==

Christian,&lt;ref&gt;Strauss, Lehman, Litt.D., F.R.G.S. [http://www.bible.org/page.asp?page_id=1302 "Homosexuality: The Christian Perspective"].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_rom.htm "Roman Catholics and Homosexuality"], Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lds.org/hf/library/0,16866,4266-1,00.html?LibraryURL=/lds/hf/display "Teaching about Procreation and Chastity: Homosexuality"], The Church of Jesus-Christ of Latter-day Saints. Home &amp; Family.&lt;/ref&gt; 
Jewish,&lt;ref&gt;Shafran, Rabbi Avi. [http://www.jlaw.com/Commentary/maritalprob.html "Jewish Law: Marital Problems"]. Jewish Law Commentary: Examining Halacha, Jewish Issues, and Secular Law. &lt;/ref&gt; 
and Islamic&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_isla1.htm "Islam and Homosexuality"], Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance (2005).&lt;/ref&gt; 
social conservatives view homosexuality as a [[sin]], and its practice and acceptance in society as a weakening of moral standards. The [[Unification Church]] concurs with this view, although it permits homosexuals to be members and attend worship services. This is a primary reason why many religious social conservatives oppose the gay rights movement.

By contrast, some [[liberal Christianity|Liberal Christian]] churches are supportive of gay rights, such as the leadership and many congregations within the [[United Church of Christ]] have supported the right for homosexuals to marry.&lt;ref&gt; {{PDFlink| [http://www.ucc.org/synod/resolutions/gsrev25-7.pdf In Support of Equal Marriage Rights for All]|34.2&amp;nbsp;[[Kibibyte|KiB]]&lt;!-- application/pdf, 35074 bytes --&gt;}}, United Church of Christ (2005). Resolution by General Synod 25 in Atlanta.&lt;/ref&gt;  Currently the [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopal Church]] and [[Presbyterian Church (USA)]] bless civil unions but do not 'marry' their congregants.

Also, in Europe some [[Lutheran]], [[Reformed]] and [[United]] churches in [[Germany]] ([[EKD]]), [[Switzerland]], [[Netherland]]s, [[Belgium]], [[Denmark]] and [[Sweden]] are supportive of gay rights. In recent years, support has also come from some Anglican churches ([[Canada]], [[England]]).

Some also cite [[natural law]], sometimes called God's law or nature's law, when opposing the gay rights movement.&lt;ref&gt;Pickett, Brent (2002). [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/homosexuality/#Natural "Homosexuality: Natural Law"]. The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Fall 2002 Edition). Edward N. Zalta (ed.). Retrieved May 12, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vitagliano, Ed (2003). [http://www.afajournal.org/2003/April/4.03_morality_dw.html "Morality: hanging by a thread"]. American Family Association Journal (April 2003). Retrieved June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Flynn, Eileen P (2000). [http://www.americamagazine.org/gettext.cfm?textID=2202&amp;articleTypeID=1&amp;issueID=382 "Responding to the ‘Gay Agenda’"]. America: The National Catholic Weekly (Vol. 183 No. 9, September 30, 2000). Retrieved June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Culture war]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[LGBT social movements]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Homophobia]]

[[bg:Антихомосексуално движение]]
[[ru:Антигомосексуальное движение]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>