<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081025023524|247517574" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1527351" pageid="1527351" ns="0" title="LGBTQ rights opposition"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-10-26T02:35:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2007}}
{{Globalize/US}}
{{LGBT rights}}
'''LGBT rights opposition''' refers to various movements or attitudes which oppose the extension of certain [[LGBT social movements|rights]] to [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], and [[transgender]] people.  The specific rights that are opposed may include rights to [[social equality]], [[same-sex marriage]] or [[civil unions]], [[adoption by same-sex couples|adoption]], and freedom from [[discrimination]] on the basis of [[sexual orientation]] or [[gender identity]].

==United States==
=== Conservative opposition to LGBT rights in the US===
In the late 1970s gay rights organizations were forming self-supporting communities in large urban centers in America such as [[San Francisco]], [[New York City]], and [[Minneapolis]].  Several states reformed their criminal code to decriminalize same-sex sexual relations between consenting adults, and some cities passed local anti-discrimination laws that included protection based on [[sexual orientation]].{{Fact|date=August 2007}}

[[Anita Bryant]] organized the first major opposition movement to gay rights in America, based on [[fundamentalist Christian]] values.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} The group used various slogans that played off the fear that gay people were interested in "recruiting" or molesting children into a "life-style." A common slogan of the campaign was "Homosexuals cannot reproduce — so they must recruit."  The Bryant campaign was successful in repealing many of the city anti-discrimination laws, and in proposing other citizen initiatives, such as a failed California ballot question designed to ban homosexuals or anyone who endorsed gay rights from being a public school teacher.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}  The name of this group was "Save Our Children," and its most successful campaign resulted in the repealing of [[Dade County|Dade County's]] [[Civil Rights Ordinance]] by an overwhelming margin of 69 to 31.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} Soon after, legislation was passed outlawing adoption by non-heterosexual persons in Florida.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} In 1998, Dade County passed an anti-discrimination law that included the protection of people from discrimination based on [[sexual orientation]], but the ban on homosexuals adopting children remains on the books.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} The success of the Bryant campaign encouraged the development of other organizations which opposed gay rights legislation.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

From the late 1970s onwards, [[Conservative Christianity|Conservative Christian]] organizations such as the [[700 Club]], [[Focus on the Family]], [[Concerned Women For America]], and the [[Christian Coalition of America|Christian Coalition]] built strong lobbying and fundraising organizations to oppose the gay rights movement's goals.  These organizations tend to align themselves with the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]].

Conservative Christian organizations behaved similarly in other nations.{{Fact|date=August 2007}}  In the 1980s organizations opposed to gay rights successfully persuaded the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] to enact [[Section 28]], which banned public schools from "promoting homosexuality" or endorsing same-sex marriages.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

=== US public opinion ===
Public opinion has shifted towards increased acceptance of homosexuality and equal rights for gays and lesbians over the past 30 years.  According to the Gallup poll, the percentage of Americans who think that same-sex relations between consenting adults should be legal has increased from 32% to 57% since 1986.&lt;ref name="oldgallup"&gt;[http://www.sodomylaws.org/usa/usnews32.htm American Attitudes Toward Homosexuality Continue to Become More Tolerant&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gallup06"&gt;[http://www.seniorjournal.com/NEWS/SeniorStats/6-05-31-SeniorCitizensAtOdds.htm Senior Citizens at Odds with Young Americans over Gay Rights&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1977, 56% of Americans thought that gay people should have equal rights in terms of job opportunities.  Today, that number has risen to 89%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sodomylaws.org/lawrence/lwnews179.htm Six out of 10 Americans Say Homosexual Relations Should Be Recognized as Legal&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gallup06" /&gt;  In 1992, 38% thought that homosexuality should be considered an acceptable lifestyle.  Today, that number is 54%.&lt;ref name="oldgallup" /&gt;&lt;ref name="gallup06" /&gt;  In 1997, 27% of Americans thought that [[same-sex marriage]]s should be legally valid.  That number is now 39%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_poll5.htm U.S. public opinion polls on same-sex marriage&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gallup06" /&gt; In 1977, 13% of Americans thought that sexual orientation was genetically determined; now, 42%{{Fact|date=February 2007}} think it is.

Numerous studies have investigated the prevalence of acceptance and disapproval of homosexuality, and have consistently found correlations with various demographic, psychological, and social variables. For example, studies (mainly conducted in the United States) have found that heterosexuals with positive attitudes towards homosexuality are more likely to be female, young, non-religious, politically liberal or moderate, and have close personal contact with [[coming out|openly]] gay men and lesbians.&lt;ref&gt;Studies finding that heterosexual men usually exhibit more hostile attitudes toward gay men and lesbians than do heterosexual women:
*Herek, G. M. (1994). ''Assessing heterosexuals’ attitudes toward lesbians and gay men.'' In "B. Greene and G.M. Herek (Eds.) Psychological perspectives on lesbian and gay issues: Vol. 1 Lesbian and gay psychology: Theory, research, and clinical applications." Thousands Oaks, Ca: Sage.
*Kite, M.E. (1984). ''Sex differences in attitudes toward homosexuals: A meta-analytic review.'' Journal of Homosexuality, 10 (1-2), 69-81.
*Morin, S., &amp; Garfinkle, E. (1978). ''Male homophobia.'' Journal of Social Issues, 34 (1), 29-47.
*Thompson, E., Grisanti, C., &amp; Pleck, J. (1985). ''Attitudes toward the male role and their correlates.'' Sex Roles, 13 (7/8), 413-427.
For other correlates, see:
*Larson et al. (1980) ''Heterosexuals' Attitudes Toward Homosexuality'', The Journal of Sex Research, 16, 245-257
*Herek, G. (1988), ''Heterosexuals' Attitudes Toward Lesbians and Gay Men'', ''[[Journal of Sex Research]]'', 25, 451-477
*Kite, M.E., &amp; Deaux, K., 1986. ''Attitudes toward homosexuality: Assessment and behavioral consequences. Basic and Applied Social Psychology,'' 7, 137-162
*Haddock, G., Zanna, M. P., &amp; Esses, V. M. (1993). ''Assessing the structure of prejudicial attitudes: The case of attitudes toward homosexuals.'' Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 65, 1105-1118.
See also: Lewis, Gregory B., ''Black-White Differences in Attitudes toward Homosexuality and Gay Rights,'' Public Opinion Quarterly, Volume 67, Number 1, Pp. 59-78&lt;/ref&gt; They are also more likely to have positive attitudes towards other minority groups&lt;ref&gt;Herek, G.M. (1991). ''Stigma, prejudice, and violence against lesbians and gay men.'' In: J. Gonsiorek &amp; J. Weinrich (Eds.), "Homosexuality: Research implications for public policy" (pp. 60-80). Newbury Park, CA: Sage.&lt;/ref&gt; and are less likely to support traditional gender roles.&lt;ref&gt; Kyes, K.B. &amp; Tumbelaka, L. (1994). ''Comparison of Indonesian and American college students' attitudes toward homosexuality.'' Psychological Reports, 74, 227-237.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Boy Scouts of America ===
==== Policy and rationale ====
{{details|Boy Scouts of America membership controversies#Position on homosexuals}}

The [[Boy Scouts of America]] exclude gay and bisexual people from its organizations, generally for Scoutmasters but also for scouts in leadership positions. Their rationale is that homosexuality is immoral, and that scouts are expected to have certain [[moral]] standards and values, as the [[Scout Oath]] and [[Scout Law]] requires boys to be "morally straight."{{Fact|date=August 2007}}  The Boy Scout organization does not view their policy as unjustly [[Discrimination|discriminatory]], but instead defends their policy saying that, "Tolerance for diversity of values does not require abdication of one's own values".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scouting.org/media/positions/unitedway.html Position Statement: United Way&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000 the [[United States Supreme Court]] ruled in [[Boy Scouts of America v. Dale]] that the Boy Scouts of America is a [[club|private organization]], and as such can decide its own membership rules.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2000/LAW/06/28/scotus.gay.boyscouts CNN.com - Supreme Court says Boy Scouts can bar gay troop leaders - June 28, 2000&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  There is still a movement to try and persuade the organization to change its policy or allow local chapters to decide for themselves.

In 2005, the [[U.S. Congress]] passed the "[[Support Our Scouts Act|Support Our Scouts Act of 2005]]" to exempt the BSA from anti-discrimination laws, to require the [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]] to support scouting [[National Scout jamboree (Boy Scouts of America)|Jamboree]]s (thus rendering ineffective a Federal Court injunction prohibiting this as an [[unconstitutional]] [[establishment of religion]] in violation of the [[First Amendment]]) and to require [[U.S. state|state]] or local governments that receive Community Development Block Grant money from the [[United States Department of Housing and Urban Development|Department of Housing and Urban Development]] to allow BSA to have meetings in their facilities or on their property.{{Fact|date=August 2007}}

Critics claim that gay people are not incompatible with scout values and are allowed to be members in most countries in the world,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scoutingforall.org/international.shtml]{{Dead link|date=March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the [[United Kingdom]], where scouting was founded. Some [[United Way of America|United Way]]s, municipalities, school districts and businesses have stopped supporting the BSA for those reasons.&lt;ref&gt;http://lambdalegal.org/cgi-bin/iowa/news/fact.html?record=1325&lt;/ref&gt;

Other outdoor-focused, youth-based organizations such as the [[4-H]] club and [[Girl Scouts of the USA]] do not have similar policies.  The BSA, however, receives a high level of support from religious groups, many of which are noted for their opposition to the [[gay rights movement]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religionlink.org/tip_020624b.php ReligionLink - Boy Scouts: Two-year anniversary of Supreme Court case&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United States Armed Forces ===
The United States Armed Forces' "[[Don't Ask, Don't Tell]]" policy requires gay men and lesbians to be discharged from the armed forces if they [[coming out|come out]], but does not allow the military to question people about their sexual orientation.

Even when it was put in place, there have been advocates for allowing gay people to [[Sexual orientation and military service|serve openly in the military]].  Critics of the current policy often argue that when the United Kingdom admitted gay people, no such unit cohesion or morale was lost.{{Fact|date=August 2007}}  The same comparison is made to no negative consequences when African-Americans and women were admitted into the military.

== Fascist and far-right opposition ==
[[Image:National Front at gay pride 2007.jpg|180px|thumb|National Front protesting "Homosexual Marriage" at London Gay Pride 2007]]
[[Fascist]] political parties have been universal in their violent opposition to gay rights. Today, [[Neo Nazi]] organizations oppose gay rights, and may advocate life sentences in prison or concentration camps for homosexuals, or even the [[death penalty]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mediamouse.org/resources/right.php?orgId=3 The Michigan-based '''National Socialist Movement']&lt;/ref&gt; (which was instituted by the original [[Nazi]]s in 1942&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?sid=328 Southern Poverty Law Center]&lt;/ref&gt;). The [[British National Party]] has shifted its platform from recriminalisation to an extension of [[clause 28]]-style legislation, ie. making it illegal to portray homosexuality positively in the media.&lt;ref&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/magazine/story/0,11913,783675,00.html ''The Observer'']&lt;/ref&gt;

In Israel, both mainstream ultra-Orthodox religious groups and Jewish right-wing movements such as the Samson Blinded oppose LGBT rights which are claimed to run contrary to the [[Torah]].{{Facts|date=January 2008}}

== Psychological ==
{{Cleanup|date=August 2007}}

Most LGBT groups see [[homosexual orientation]] as natural and not a choice. A resolution adopted by the [[American Psychological Association]] in August 1997 states that "homosexuality is not a mental disorder".&lt;ref&gt;American Psychological Association Council of Representatives (1997). [http://www.apa.org/pi/sexual.html "Resolution on Appropriate Therapeutic Responses to Sexual Orientation"]. (Adopted August 14, 1997)&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Ego-dystonic sexual orientation]] is listed in the [[ICD-10]] by the [[World Health Organization]].({{ICD10|F|66|1|f|60}})

Some LGBT groups do not see [[sexual behavior]] as a choice.  [[Orson Scott Card]] commented "In my opinion, all homosexuals should be enraged at the notion that of all human beings, only homosexuals cannot control their sexual behavior by conscious choices."&lt;ref name="choice"&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.mormontimes.com/ME_blogs.php?id=1702
|title=Science on gays falls short
|publisher=[[Deseret Morning News]]
|date=Aug. 7, 2008
|last=Card
|first=Orson Scott}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some groups, many of which are funded by religious organizations, promote [[conversion therapy]], which is designed to reduce homosexual attractions and behaviors and for some people increase heterosexual attractions.  [[Sexual Identity Therapy]] is another alternative where clients can choose the direction based on their personal values, whether it be gay relationships, celibacy, or heterosexual relationships.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite journal
|url=http://www.apa.org/monitor/jun07/programming.html
|publisher=Monitor on Psychology
|date=June 2007
|title=Programming highlights for San Francisco
|volume=38
|number=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=framework&gt;[http://wthrockmorton.com/wp-content/uploads/2007/04/sexualidentitytherapyframeworkfinal.pdf Sexual Identity Therapy Framework]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="New Ground"&gt;{{cite news
 |url=http://wthrockmorton.com/2007/06/18/la-times-article-features-ex-gay-debate-and-sexual-identity-therapy
 |title=New ground in debate on 'curing' gays
 |last=Simon
 |first=Stephanie
 |publisher=[[Los Angeles Times]]
 |date=2007-06-18
 |accessdate=2007-10-29
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid46515.asp
|title=Christian conservatives, gay leaders work together to transform "ex-gay" therapy
|date=June 20, 2007
|publisher=[[The Advocate]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

== Health ==
Some opponents of gay rights argue that promoting gay rights leads to an increase in health risks coming from [[men who have sex with men]], such as STDs and anal cancer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholiceducation.org/articles/homosexuality/ho0075.html The Health Risks of Gay Sex]&lt;/ref&gt;  Critics charge that political correctness has led to the association of sex between males and HIV being downplayed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.netassets.co.za/medical/medical.asp?websiteContentItemID=67274
|first=James
|last=Chin
|title=The risks in hiding the HIV/AIDS truth
|publisher=Business Day
|date=March 12, 2007
|volume=9
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-347665/The-people-punish-Mr-Blair.html
|title=The people punish Mr Blair
|publisher=Daily Mail (UK)
|date=May 6, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some also associate gay sex with higher levels of promiscuity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholiceducation.org/articles/homosexuality/ho0075.html The Health Risks of Gay Sex]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Traditional Marriage Movement ==
{{main|traditional marriage movement}}
People in the traditional marriage movement believe only unions between one man and one woman should be legally defined as marriages.  They believe that children should be reared in homes with both a father and mother.&lt;ref name = DMD&gt;
{{cite web
  |last=Brownback
  |first=Sam
  |title=Defining Marriage Down - We need to protect marriage.
  |publisher=[[National Review]]
  |date=July 09, 2004
  |url=http://www.nationalreview.com/comment/brownback200407090921.asp }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://lds.org/ldsorg/v/index.jsp?vgnextoid=e1fa5f74db46c010VgnVCM1000004d82620aRCRD&amp;locale=0&amp;sourceId=1aba862384d20110VgnVCM100000176f620a____&amp;hideNav=1&amp;contentLocale=0 ''The Family: A Proclamation to the World''&lt;/ref&gt;  They have said same-sex relationships are not marriages,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.savemarriageny.org/The%20Case%20Against%20Same-Sex%20Marriage%20and%20Civil%20Unions.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; that legalization of same-sex marriage will open the door for the legalization of polygamy,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nationformarriage.org/atf/cf/%7B39D8B5C1-F9FE-48C0-ABE6-1029BA77854C%7D/CatholicEnglish.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;   that it is unnatural&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DE1731F937A35753C1A964958260 |title=Anti-Gay Backlashes Are on 3 States' Ballots |date=1992-10-04 |accessdate=2008-06-06 |publisher=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that it encourages unhealthy behavior.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.balancedpolitics.org/same_sex_marriages.htm BalancedPolitics.org - Same Sex Marriages (Pros &amp; Cons, Arguments For and Against)&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.apacny.net/The%20Christian%20Case%20Against%20Same-Sex%20Marriage.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; 

== Religious ==
Christian,&lt;ref&gt;Strauss, Lehman, Litt.D., F.R.G.S. [http://www.bible.org/page.asp?page_id=1302 "Homosexuality: The Christian Perspective"].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_rom.htm "Roman Catholics and Homosexuality"], Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lds.org/hf/library/0,16866,4266-1,00.html?LibraryURL=/lds/hf/display "Teaching about Procreation and Chastity: Homosexuality"], The Church of Jesus-Christ of Latter-day Saints. Home &amp; Family.&lt;/ref&gt;
Jewish,&lt;ref&gt;Shafran, Rabbi Avi. [http://www.jlaw.com/Commentary/maritalprob.html "Jewish Law: Marital Problems"]. Jewish Law Commentary: Examining Halacha, Jewish Issues, and Secular Law. &lt;/ref&gt;
and Islamic&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_isla1.htm "Islam and Homosexuality"], Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;
social conservatives view gay sex as a [[sin]], and its practice and acceptance in society as a weakening of moral standards. For example, [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] has stated "The powers of procreation are to be exercised only between a man and a woman lawfully wedded as husband and wife.  Any other sexual relations, including those between persons of the same gender, undermine the divinely created institution of the family. The Church accordingly favors measures that define marriage as the union of a man and a woman and that do not confer legal status on any other sexual relationship."&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsroom.lds.org/ldsnewsroom/v/index.jsp?vgnextoid=a1312e636369f010VgnVCM100000176f620aRCRD First Presidency Message on Same-Gender Marriage]&lt;/ref&gt;  However, it does permit people in homosexual relations to attend worship services,&lt;ref&gt;{{lds|3 Nephi|3_ne|18|22-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; and does not object to rights regarding hospitalization and medical care, fair housing and employment rights, or probate rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsroom.lds.org/ldsnewsroom/eng/commentary/the-divine-institution-of-marriage The Divine Institution of Marriage]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Unification Church]] concurs with this view. This is a primary reason why many religious social conservatives oppose the gay rights movement.

By contrast, some [[liberal Christianity|Liberal Christian]] churches are supportive of gay rights. The leadership and many congregations within the [[United Church of Christ]] have supported the right for same-sex couples to marry.&lt;ref&gt; {{PDFlink| [http://www.ucc.org/synod/resolutions/gsrev25-7.pdf In Support of Equal Marriage Rights for All]|34.2&amp;nbsp;[[Kibibyte|KiB]]&lt;!-- application/pdf, 35074 bytes --&gt;}}, United Church of Christ (2005). Resolution by General Synod 25 in Atlanta.&lt;/ref&gt;  Currently the [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopal Church]] and [[Presbyterian Church (USA)]] bless civil unions but do not 'marry' their congregants.

Also, in Europe some [[Lutheran]], [[Reformed]] and [[United]] churches in [[Germany]] ([[EKD]]), [[Switzerland]], [[Netherland]]s, [[Belgium]], [[Denmark]] and [[Sweden]] are supportive of gay rights. In recent years, support has also come from some Anglican churches ([[Canada]], [[England]]).

Some also cite [[natural law]], sometimes called God's law or nature's law, when opposing the gay rights movement.&lt;ref&gt;Pickett, Brent (2002). [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/homosexuality/#Natural "Homosexuality: Natural Law"]. The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Fall 2002 Edition). Edward N. Zalta (ed.). Retrieved May 12, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vitagliano, Ed (2003). [http://www.afajournal.org/2003/April/4.03_morality_dw.html "Morality: hanging by a thread"]. American Family Association Journal (April 2003). Retrieved June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Flynn, Eileen P (2000). [http://www.americamagazine.org/gettext.cfm?textID=2202&amp;articleTypeID=1&amp;issueID=382 "Responding to the ‘Gay Agenda’"]. America: The National Catholic Weekly (Vol. 183 No. 9, September 30, 2000). Retrieved June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Conflict with other rights ==
{{seealso|Homosexuality and Christianity#Conflicts}}

Religious leaders in England have expressed concerns that gay hate-crime legislation infringe on freedom of speech and commented that "People holding firm opinions on sexuality will generally be reluctant to risk the emotional and financial costs of being challenged by a neighbour or colleague and being investigated by the police."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=496871&amp;in_page_id=1770
|title=Gay hate law 'threat to Christian free speech'
|date=28th November 2007
|first=Steve
|last=Doughty
|publisher=Daily Mail}}&lt;/ref&gt;  They cite examples of [[Harry Hammond]], [[Stephen Green (Christian Voice)|Stephen Green]], and other Christians who have been arrested for expressing opposition to homosexual relationships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=403815&amp;in_page_id=1770
|title=Christian faces court over 'offensive' gay festival leaflets
|first=Steve
|last=Doughty
|date=6th September 2006
|publisher=Daily Mail}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/columnists/michael_gove/article805241.ece
|publisher=The Times
|title=I'd like to say this, but it might land me in prison
|date=December 24, 2002
|first=Michael
|last=Gove}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Concerned Christians Canada expressed similar concerns over investigation over comments made by [[Craig Chandler]] against homosexual relationships, calling such investigation a "[[witch hunt]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/calgary/story/2007/11/28/chandler-meeting.html
|title=Christian group likens Tory candidate review to witch hunt
|date=November 28, 2007
|publisher=CBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Also in Canada [[Chris Kempling]] was suspended from his job from writing in a newspaper against homosexual relationships.&lt;ref name=supreme&gt;"Supreme Court rejects teacher's appeal over homosexuality issue", Calgary Herald, 29 January 2006, B5 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.nationalpost.com/opinion/story.html?id=431535&amp;p=2
|title=Conduct unbecoming a free society
|date=April 09, 2008
|last=Kempling
|first=Chris
|publisher=National Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Leaders of adoption agencies complained of discrimination of Roman Catholics after new gay right laws shut down an adoption agency in England.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/2080669/Catholic-adoption-service-stops-over-gay-rights.html
|title=Catholic adoption service stops over gay rights
|date=June 5 ,2008
|publisher=Telegraph
|first=Martin
|last=Beckford}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Earlier, when Catholic adoption agencies in Boston chose to close their doors rather than comply with non-discrimination laws, [[Mitt Romney]] commented "It's a mistake for our laws to put the rights of adults over the needs of children... I find the current state of the law deeply disturbing and a threat to religious freedom."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/massachusetts/articles/2006/03/10/catholic_charities_to_halt_adoptions_over_issue_involving_gays/
|title=Catholic Charities to halt adoptions over issue involving gays
|date=March 10, 2006
|last=LeBlanc
|first=Steve
|publisher=[[Boston Globe]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gay rights have also brought up conflicts with religious rights in the workplace,&lt;ref&gt; {{cite news
|url=http://www.law.com/jsp/ihc/PubArticleIHC.jsp?id=1193735028038
|title=Employer's Dilemma: When Religious Expression and Gay Rights Cross
|first=Judith
|last=Moldover
|publisher=New York Law Journal
|date=October 31, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1374/is_1_68/ai_n24944645
|title=Collision of religious and gay rights in the workplace
|publisher=Humanist
|date=Jan-Feb, 2008
|first=Bob
|last=Ritter}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a government-subsidized Christian organization in Canada was ordered to abolish a conduct policy which prohibited employees from viewing or engaging in various sexual acts, including gay and lesbian relationships. The Human Rights Tribunal of Ontario wrote that "the effect of the policy was to make (the employee) a pariah within the organization."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://news.therecord.com/News/CanadaWorld/article/341201
|date=April 24, 2008
|first=Greg
|last=Mercer
|publisher=The Record
|title=Christian Horizons rebuked: Employer ordered to compensate fired gay worker, abolish code of conduct
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and churches are forced to hire people in sexual relationships outside of marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/wales/6904057.stm
|title=Bishop loses gay employment case
|date=18 July 2007
|publisher=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;  An Ocean Grove church group is suing New Jersey, saying that the state is pressuring it to allow a civil union ceremony for a lesbian couple at its oceanfront pavilion, thereby violating the group’s First Amendment rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/14/nyregion/14civil.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin
|date=August 14, 2007
|title=Church Group Complains of Civil Union Pressure
|first=Jill
|last=Capuzzo
|publisher=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The pavilion lost its exemption from property taxes, as its exempt status was dependent on being open to all members of the public, and a state official ruled that the church's prohibition of civil union ceremonies constituted a violation of this requirement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/18/nyregion/18grove.html
|title=Group Loses Tax Break Over Gay Union Issue
|first=Jill
|last=Capuzzo
|publisher=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[ex-gay]]s have felt oppressed by the gay rights movement.  [[PFOX]] sued and won a case where they said the Arlington school district discriminated against them because they allowed gay rights group to pass out fliers to a school and not ex-gay groups.  Randy Thomas has said "As a former homosexual, when I was involved in the 1980s promoting the gay agenda, our only focus was to seek tolerance, whereas today's political activism has moved from true tolerance into political domination and power. It's an amazing thing to watch a group that said they were oppressed become oppressors."&lt;ref name="bluely"&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.cnsnews.com/ViewCulture.asp?Page=/Culture/archive/200406/CUL20040621a.html
|title=Documents Reveal San Francisco Mayor's Ties to Homosexual Activists
|last=Bluely
|first=Robert
|date=2004-07-21
|accessdate=2007-11-01
|publisher=[[Cybercast News Service]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Culture war]]
* [[Gay agenda]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Homosexuality and religion]]
* [[Homosexual recruitment]]
* [[LGBT social movements]]
* [[LGBT retirement issues]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Homophobia]]

[[bg:Антихомосексуално движение]]
[[ru:Антигомосексуальное движение]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>