<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101101183417|394216216" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="67918" pageid="67918" ns="0" title="Genital modification and mutilation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-07T22:43:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The terms '''genital modification''' and '''genital mutilation''' can refer to permanent or temporary changes to [[human]] [[sex organ]]s. Some forms of genital alteration are performed at the behest of an adult, with their informed consent. Others are performed on infants or children. Any of these procedures may be considered modifications or mutilations by different groups of people.

==Body modification==
{{main|Body modification}}
[[Image:Fourchette foto.jpg|thumb|right| Female genital piercing: a [[Fourchette piercing]]]][[Image:Prince Albert piercing.jpg|thumb|right| Male circumcision and genital piercing: a [[Prince Albert piercing]]]]
Many types of genital modification are performed at the behest of the individual, for personal, sexual, aesthetic or cultural reasons. [[Penile subincision]], or splitting of the underside of the penis, is widespread in the traditional cultures of [[Indigenous Australian]]s.  This procedure has taken root in [[Western culture|Western]] [[body modification]] culture. [[Meatotomy]] is a form that involves splitting of the [[glans penis]] alone, while [[genital bisection]] is a more extreme form that splits the penis entirely in half.  

Genital piercings and [[genital tattooing]] may be performed for aesthetic reasons, but piercings have the benefit of increasing [[sexual pleasure]] for the pierced individual or their [[sex partner]]s.&lt;ref name="expressmilwaukee"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.expressmilwaukee.com/article-7386-penises-piercings-and-pleasure.html |title=Penises, Piercings and Pleasure |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[Pearling (body modification)|Pearling]] involves surgical insertion of small, inert spheres under the skin along the shaft of the penis for the purpose of providing sexual stimulation to the walls of the vagina.

[[Clitoris enlargement]] may be achieved temporarily through the use of a [[clitoral pump]], or it may be achieved permanently through application of [[testosterone]] cream to the clitoris, or through injectable testosterone.  [[Penis enlargement]] is a term for various techniques used to attempt to increase the size of the penis, though the safety and efficacy of these techniques are debated.

==Voluntary sex reassignment==
{{main|Sex reassignment surgery}}
Some [[transgender]] people choose to undergo [[sex reassignment surgery]] as part of their [[gender transition]].  Male to female transgenders, mtfs, or [[transwomen]] may undergo [[castration]], with or without [[vaginoplasty]], while female to male, ftms, or [[transmen]] transgenders may undergo [[phalloplasty]] or [[metoidioplasty]], with or without [[oophorectomy]] or [[hysterectomy]]. Transgender people who wish to make this surgical transition are referred to as [[transsexual]]s.

==Involuntary sex assignment==
{{Main|Sex assignment}}
If a [[baby]] is born with ambiguous genitalia due to an [[intersex]] condition, it may not be clear whether the child is female or male. In certain cases, the child's chromosomal makeup is neither female nor male, but a combination.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}  In these cases, the baby is usually given a sex assignment, and in many cases, the child's genitals are surgically altered to conform to those of the assigned sex.  This practice is met with strong dissent from advocates for [[genital integrity]].  As cosmetic surgery is not medically necessary for health, they argue that the individual should be free to make the choice whether to pursue cosmetic surgery upon their genitals.  Advocates state that the surgery can damage the individual's ability to experience sexual arousal and can render the individual incapable of orgasm.  Another concern is that sex assignment holds a significant element of guesswork, and that an individual's sex assignment may turn out to be incorrect.  If, for instance, an individual is assigned female, their phallus is usually surgically reduced in size, and the shape of a vulva may be created.  If, upon maturing, the individual identifies as male; their phallus is still gone, and the individual may require further surgery to try to reverse the erroneous sex assignment.  Those who oppose medically unnecessary genital surgery, and genital surgery coerced or performed without consent comprise the [[genital integrity]] movement.  The case of [[David Reimer]], the victim of a botched [[circumcision]] who was raised as a girl alongside his twin brother, bears many parallels to this issue.

==In disease or medical necessity==
If the genitals become diseased, as in the case of [[cancer]], sometimes the diseased areas are surgically removed.  Biological females may undergo [[vaginectomy]], while males may undergo [[penectomy]].  [[Reconstructive surgery]] may be performed to restore what was lost, often with techniques similar to those used in [[sex reassignment surgery]].  

Similarly, during [[childbirth]], [[episiotomy]] is sometimes performed to increase the amount of space through which the baby may emerge.  Advocates of [[natural childbirth]] and [[unassisted birth]] state that this intervention is often performed without medical necessity, with significant damage to the person giving birth. 

[[Hymenotomy]] is the surgical perforation of an [[imperforate hymen]].  It may be performed to allow [[menstruation]] to occur.  An adult individual may opt for increasing the size of her hymenal opening, or removal of the hymen altogether, to facilitate [[sexual penetration]] of her vagina.

==Female genitals==

Cosmetic surgery of female genitalia, known as '''elective genitoplasty''', has become pejoratively known as '''designer vagina'''. In May 2007, an article published in the British Medical Journal blasted the "designer vagina" craze, citing its popularity being rooted in commercial and media influences.&lt;ref name="bb"&gt;{{cite news | last=Bourke |first=Emily | title = Designer vagina craze worries doctors| publisher = Australian Broadcasting Corporation| date = 2009-11-12| url = http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2009/11/12/2741446.htm?site=local| accessdate = 2007-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bmj"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Liao | first = Lih Mei| coauthors = Sarah M Creighton| title = Requests for cosmetic genitoplasty: how should healthcare providers respond?| journal = BMJ| volume = 334| issue = 7603 | pages = 1090–1092| publisher = [[British Medical Journal]]| date = 2007-05-26| url = http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/extract/334/7603/1090| doi = 10.1136/bmj.39206.422269.BE| accessdate = 2007-05-29| pmid = 17525451 | pmc = 1877941}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Similar concerns have been expressed in Australia.&lt;ref name="bb"/&gt;

===Female genital cutting===
{{Main|Female genital cutting}}
[[Female genital cutting]] (FGC), also known as female genital mutilation or female circumcision, refers to "all procedures involving partial or total removal of the external [[female genitalia]] or other injury to the female [[sex organ|genital organs]] whether for [[culture|cultural]], [[religion|religious]] or other non-therapeutic reasons."&lt;ref&gt;Definition of the [[World Health Organization]]&lt;/ref&gt;  It is not the same as the procedures used in [[Sex reassignment surgery|gender reassignment surgery]] or the [[genital modification]] of [[intersexual]]s. FGC is practiced throughout the world, but the practice is concentrated more heavily in [[Africa]], [[Indonesia]], and the [[Middle East]]. There is much controversy surrounding [[infibulation]] procedures, due to concerns regarding the safety and consequences of the procedure.  In the past several decades, efforts have been made by global health organizations, such as the WHO, to end the practice of FGC. However, because of its importance in [[tradition]]al and religious life, FGC continues to be practised in many societies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=nthWORD Magazine |url=http://www.nthword.com/issue5/Interview_Liz_Canner_Orgasm_Inc.php |title=nthWORD Magazine Interview with Liz Canner, filmmaker of Orgasm, Inc |publisher=Nthword.com |date= |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hymenorrhaphy===
[[Hymenorrhaphy]] refers to the practice of thickening the hymen, or, in some cases, implanting a capsule of red liquid within the newly-created vaginal tissue.  The newly-created hymen is created to cause physical resistance, blood, or the appearance of blood, at the time that the individual's new husband inserts his penis into her vagina.  This is done in cultures where a high value is placed on female [[virginity]] at the time of marriage. In these cultures, a woman may be punished, perhaps violently, if the community leaders deem that she was not virginal at the time of [[consummate|consummation]] of her marriage.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}} Individuals who are victims of [[rape]], who were virginal at the time of their rape, may elect for hymenorrhaphy.

===Vaginoplasty and labiaplasty===
Some women undergo [[vaginoplasty]] or [[labiaplasty]] procedures to alter the shape of their [[vulva]]s to meet personal [[aesthetic]] standards. The surgery itself is controversial, and critics refer to the procedures as "designer vagina".&lt;ref&gt;Green, Fiona: "From clitoridectomies to 'designer vaginas': The medical construction of heteronormative female bodies and sexuality through female genital cutting." ''Sexualities, Evolution &amp; Gender'' 7(2):153-187, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Essen, B &amp; Johnsdotter, S: "Female Genital Mutilation in the West: Traditional Circumcision versus Genital Cosmetic Surgery". ''Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand'',(83):611-613, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Braun, Virginia: "In search of (better) sexual pleasure: female genital ‘cosmetic’ surgery". ''Sexualities'' 8(4):407-424, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Labia pulling===
See [[labia stretching]] and [[elongated labia]].

==Male genitals==
===Male circumcision===
{{Main|Circumcision}}[[Image:Circumcised highres closeup.jpg|thumb|A circumcised penis in flaccid state]]

Male circumcision involves the removal of the [[foreskin]]. It may also involve [[frenectomy]], the removal of the [[frenulum]].  A related procedure is [[preputioplasty]], which is used as a treatment for [[phimosis]].  This procedure is most often performed upon infant boys.  It has religious significance in the [[Jewish]] religion and in [[Islam]].  It spread into Western culture, and peaked in the early 80s.  The [[bioethics of neonatal circumcision]] are a subject of intense debate, with [[circumcision advocacy|circumcision advocates]] promoting it as beneficial, and supporters of genital integrity opposing it as harmful and/or a violation of the individual's human rights.  Some adults who were circumcised as infants engage in [[foreskin restoration]], a method of stretching the penile skin in order to partially recreate the foreskin.

===Penile subincision===
{{Expand-section|date=January 2009}}
{{Main|Penile subincision}}
'''Penile subincision''' is a form of body modification consisting of a urethrotomy, in which the underside of the [[penis]] is incised and the [[urethra]] slit open lengthwise, from the urethral opening ([[urinary meatus|meatus]]) toward the base. The slit can be of varying lengths.

===Infibulation===
{{Main|Infibulation}}
Infibulation refers to suturing of the foreskin.  In ancient Greece, performers infibulated themselves by using a clasp or string to foreskin and draw the penis over to one side.

==See also==
*[[Skoptic syndrome]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

{{Sexual abuse}}
{{Genital procedures}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Genital Modification And Mutilation}}
[[Category:Genital modification]]

[[fr:Mutilation génitale]]
[[pt:Mutilação sexual]]
[[fi:Naisten sukupuolielinten silpominen]]
[[sv:Könsstympning]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>