<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051027234412|26661145" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="67918" pageid="67918" ns="0" title="Genital modification and mutilation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-08T00:08:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Genital modification''' and '''genital mutilation''' both can refer to permanent or temporary changes to the [[human]] [[genitals]].

When genital alterations are used for punishment, typically for [[rape]], [[adultery]] or other socially forbidden sexual practices, such mutilations have included [[castration]] (actual or chemical) or [[penectomy]]. 

==Circumcision==

Issues surrounding [[female circumcision]], also known as female genital mutilation or FGM, became prominent in the [[English language|English]]-speaking world in the latter quarter of the [[20th century]].  Opponents of the practice became aware of female circumcision existing in some [[Africa]]n countries. It is also practiced by some groups in the Arabian peninsula.

In most cases, female circumcision is a social practice, not a [[religion|religious]] one.  [[Male circumcision]] is performed for religious or social reasons or as medical treatment (for [[phimosis]], for example).  Some cultures initiate both boys and girls around the age of puberty.  In the United States, circumcision is performed on a majority of male infants, according to the wishes of the parents.

Opposition to the routine, non-medical circumcision of infant males has grown over several decades.  The [[World Health Organization]], a [[United Nations]] agency, currently campaigns against FGM (female genital mutilation) but not against male circumcision.

In 1996 the United States passed a federal law criminalizing circumcision of female minors unless there is a legitimate medical reason.

==Elective genital alteration==

In some cases, people elect to have their genitals [[Genital piercing|pierced]], [[Genital tattooing|tattooed]] or otherwise altered for aesthetic or other reasons.

Such modifications run the gamut from single to multiple piercings, small decorative marks to complete tattooing, [[urethral relocation]], and, in males, [[subincision]] or even complete [[penile bisection|bisection]].

==Types of genital alteration==

The alterations listed below may be undertaken voluntarily by some individuals; they may also be performed for medical reasons or performed on infants or adults against their will.  Any of these changes may be considered modifications or mutilations.

===Removal of tissue===

Male 
*[[Circumcision]]
**[[Posthectomy]]
**[[Frenectomy]]
*[[Castration]]
**[[Orchidectomy]]
*[[Penectomy]]

Female
*[[Female circumcision|circumcision]]
**[[Clitoridotomy]]
**[[Clitoridectomy]]
**[[Infibulation]]
*[[Labiaplasty]]

Sex Reassignment
*[[Penile inversion]]

===Alteration of tissue===

Male 
*Dorsal slit [http://www.male-initiation.net/library/anatomy/dorsal.html]
*Preputial infibulation
*Preputioplasty [http://www.rcsed.ac.uk/journal/vol44_5/4450008.htm]
*[[Genital piercing]]
*[[Genital bisection]]
*[[Subincision]]
*[[Meatotomy]]
*Autocircumcision [http://www.male-initiation.net/library/surround/bob2.html]
*[[Foreskin restoration|Surgical foreskin restoration]]

Female
*[[Genital piercing]]
*[[Episiotomy]]

Sex Reassignment
*[[Colovaginoplasty]]
*[[Metoidioplasty]]

===Addition to tissue===
Male
*[[Foreskin restoration]]
*[[Pearling (body modification)|Pearling]]
*[[Genital tattooing]]
*[[Silicone]] injection (between the skin of the penis shaft and the tissues that engorge with blood when getting hard)

Female
*[[Genital tattooing]]
*Labia elongation [http://www.labiastretching.com/en/index.shtml]

Sex Reassignment
*[[Phalloplasty]]

==See also==
* [[Bioethics of neonatal circumcision]]
* [[Sterilization (surgical procedure)|sterilization]]
* [[Docking]]
* [[Designer vagina]]

== External links ==
* [http://collegian.ksu.edu/issues/v100/sp/n145/opn-circumcision-samiller.html "US also practices genital mutilation"] - editorial by opponent of male circumcision
* [http://dmoz.org/Health/Women%27s_Health/Genital_Mutilation/ Genital Mutilation] - from the "Women's health" section of [[dmoz]].
* [http://www.fathermag.com/health/circ/gmas/ "Genital Mutilation American Style"] - opinion article by opponent of male circumcision. 
* [http://www.changesurfer.com/Hlth/episiotomy.html Episiotomy: Ritual Genital Mutilation in Western Obstetrics] - Information on routine episiotomies
* [http://www.bmezine.com/ On Line Body Modification Magazine/Site.] Photos, details, history, everything. WARNING - adults only. Very graphic.

&lt;!-- Categorization --&gt;
[[Category:Body modification]]
[[Category:Circumcision debate]]
[[Category:Genital modification]]
[[Category:Circumcision]]

&lt;!-- Localization --&gt;
[[pt:Mutilação sexual]]
[[sv:Könsstympning]]
[[fi:Naisten sukupuolielinten silpominen]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>