<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041111221544|7360777" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="67918" pageid="67918" ns="0" title="Genital modification and mutilation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-11T23:24:49Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">Both '''genital modification''' and '''genital mutilation''' are controversial terms.  Both can refer to permanent or temporary changes to the [[human]] [[genitals]], but they are used differently by different people and to different ends; there is little consensus on their correct use.  

For example, some consider any form of permanent or temporary change to the [[genitals]] mutilation.  For some, any procedure that alters the genitals, from  [[body piercing|decorative piercing]] or [[genital tattooing|tattooing]] to genital reassignment surgery as part of a [[sex change operation]], is mutilation.

For others consent or medical necessity are the deciding factors.  Some people might consider involuntary circumcision as mutilation, but voluntary [[subincision]] as modification. Dictionaries, however, do not refer to consent in definitions of "mutilation".

The choice of one word over another can reflect a person's political, religious, cultural or other beliefs.  "Modification" (as in the term [[body modification]]) is a more neutral or positive term than "mutilation," which suggests permanent or violent damage.  Thus, the term "genital modification" is generally preferred by those who view such procedures as an individual choice.  The term "genital mutilation" is generally preferred by those who see certain procedures, typically those involving forced alteration, as a violation of individual [[human rights|rights]]. The term "genital mutilation" may also be used by those who have religious, cultural or personal aversions to certain types of body decoration. For others, alterations such as piercings, or male circumcision are "modifications,".

Sometimes alleged "genital mutilation" is used as punishment, typically for [[rape]], [[adultery]] or other socially forbidden sexual practices. Some societies have historically engaged in castration or penectomy, although this is rare in the modern world (see [[penis removal]]). 

==Circumcision==

Issues surrounding [[female genital mutilation]] or FGM, became prominent in the [[English language|English]]-speaking world in the latter quarter of the [[20th century]], when opponents became aware of the practice of female circumcision in [[Africa]]n and [[Muslim]] countries. 

In most cases, female circumcision is a social practice, not a [[religion|religious]] one.  Male circumcision might be performed for religious, social or medical reasons; in the United States, circumcision was once routine for male infants and is still common.   

Opposition to the routine, non-medical circumcision of infant males has grown but remains a minority position in the United States, as more than half of infant males are circumcised. The [[World Health Organization]], a [[United Nations]] agency, campaigns against FGM (female genital mutilation) but not against male circumcision.

==Elective genital alteration==

In some cases, people elect to have their genitals [[Genital piercing|pierced]], [[Genital tattooing|tattooed]] or otherwise altered for aesthetic or other reasons.

Such modifications run the gamut from single to multiple piercings, small decorative marks to complete tattooing, to urethral relocation, and, in males, [[subincision]] or even complete bisection.


==Types of genital alteration==

The alterations listed below may be undertaken voluntarily by some individuals; they may also be performed for medical reasons or performed on infants or adults against their will.  Whether they are considered modifications or mutilations will vary.

===Removal of tissue===

Male 
*[[Circumcision]]
**[[Posthectomy]]
**[[Frenectomy]]
*[[Castration]]
**[[Orchidectomy]]
*[[Penectomy]]

Female
*[[Female circumcision|circumcision]]
**Clitoridotomy
**Clitoridectomy
**[[Infibulation]]
*Labia reduction

Sex Reassigment
*[[Penile inversion]]


===Alteration of tissue===

Male 
*Dorsal slit [http://www.male-initiation.net/library/anatomy/dorsal.html]
*Preputial infibulation
*Preputioplasty [http://www.rcsed.ac.uk/journal/vol44_5/4450008.htm]
*[[Genital piercing]]
*[[Genital bisection]]
*[[Subincision]]
*[[Meatotomy]]
*Autocircumcision [http://www.male-initiation.net/library/surround/bob2.html]
*[[Foreskin restoration|Surgical foreskin restoration]]

Female
*[[Genital piercing]]
*[[Episiotomy]]

Sex Reassignment
*[[Colovaginoplasty]]
*[[Metoidioplasty]]

===Addition to tissue===
Male
*[[Foreskin restoration]]
*[[Pearling]]
*[[Gential tatooing]]

Female
*[[Gential tatooing]]
*Labia elongation [http://www.labiastretching.com/en/index.shtml]

Sex Reassignment
*[[Phalloplasty]]


== See Also ==
* [[Sterilization]]

== External links ==
* [http://collegian.ksu.edu/issues/v100/sp/n145/opn-circumcision-samiller.html "US also practices genital mutilation"] - editorial by opponent of male circumcision
* [http://dmoz.org/Health/Women%27s_Health/Genital_Mutilation/ Genital Mutilation] - from the "Women's health" section of [[dmoz]].
* [http://www.fathermag.com/health/circ/gmas/ "Genital Mutilation American Style"] - opinion article by witness of male circumcision. Contains statistics and a description of circumcision.
* [http://www.changesurfer.com/Hlth/episiotomy.html Episiotomy: Ritual Genital Mutilation in Western Obstetrics] - Information on routine episiotomies

 [[sv:Könsstympning]]

[[Category:Body modification]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>