<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20200831181052|976014323" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="631216" pageid="631216" ns="0" title="Second-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-10-20T06:37:52Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2020}}
{{short description|Period of feminist activity and thought that began in the early 1960s in the United States}}
{{Globalize|article|USA|2name=the United States|date=January 2018|talk=Talk:Second-wave feminism#Globalize}}
{{Feminism sidebar |history}}

'''Second-wave feminism''' was a period of [[Feminism|feminist]] activity and thought that began in the United States in the early 1960s and lasted roughly two decades. It quickly spread across the [[Western world]], with an aim to increase equality for women by gaining more than just [[Suffrage|enfranchisement]].

Whereas [[first-wave feminism]] focused mainly on [[Women's suffrage|suffrage]] and overturning legal obstacles to [[gender equality]] (''e.g.'', [[Women's suffrage in the United States|voting rights]] and [[property rights]]), second-wave feminism broadened the debate to include a wider range of issues: sexuality, family, the workplace, [[reproductive rights]], ''de facto'' inequalities, and official legal inequalities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/647122/womens-movement |title=women's movement (political and social movement) |website=Britannica Online Encyclopedia |accessdate=July 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a movement that was focused on critiquing the patriarchal, or male-dominated, institutions, and cultural practices throughout society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Pierceson, Jason, 1972-|title=Sexual minorities and politics : an introduction|isbn=978-1-4422-2768-2|location=Lanham, Maryland|oclc=913610005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Second-wave feminism also drew attention to the issues of [[domestic violence]] and [[marital rape]], engendered [[Rape crisis center|rape-crisis centers]] and [[women's shelter]]s, and brought about changes in custody laws and divorce law. Feminist-owned [[Feminist bookstore|bookstores]], credit unions, and restaurants were among the key meeting spaces and economic engines of the movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UjEtDwAAQBAJ&amp;q=head+shops&amp;pg=PT146|title=From Head Shops to Whole Foods: The Rise and Fall of Activist Entrepreneurs|last=Davis|first=Joshua Clark|date=August 8, 2017|publisher=Columbia University Press|isbn=9780231543088|location=|pages=129–175}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term "second-wave feminism" itself was brought into common parlance by journalist Martha Lear in a ''[[New York Times Magazine]]'' article in March 1968 titled "The Second Feminist Wave: What do These Women Want?"&lt;ref name=lear&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://nyti.ms/2h6kh3X|title=The Second Feminist Wave: What do these women want?|last=Lear|first=Martha Weinman|date=March 10, 1968|work=The New York Times|access-date=2020-06-25|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; She wrote, "Proponents call it the Second Feminist Wave, the first having ebbed after the glorious victory of [[Women's suffrage in the United States|suffrage]] and disappeared, finally, into the great sandbar of Togetherness."&lt;ref name=lear /&gt;{{rp|323}} 

Many historians view the second-wave feminist era in America as ending in the early 1980s with the intra-feminism disputes of the [[feminist sex wars]] over issues such as [[Feminist views on sexuality|sexuality]] and [[Feminist views on pornography|pornography]], which ushered in the era of [[third-wave feminism]] in the early 1990s.&lt;ref name="end"&gt;As noted in:
*{{cite book |author1=Duggan, Lisa |author2=Hunter, Nan D. |title=Sex wars: sexual dissent and political culture |year=1995 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=978-0-415-91036-1 |pages= |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/sexwarssexualdis0000dugg }}
*{{cite book |author=Hansen, Karen Tranberg |author2=Philipson, Ilene J. |title=Women, class, and the feminist imagination: a socialist-feminist reader |year=1990 |publisher=Temple University Press |location=Philadelphia |isbn=978-0-87722-630-7 |pages= |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/womenclassfemini0000unse }}
*{{cite book |author=Gerhard, Jane F. |title=Desiring revolution: second-wave feminism and the rewriting of American sexual thought, 1920 to 1982 |year=2001 |publisher=Columbia University Press |location=New York |isbn=978-0-231-11204-8}}
*{{cite book |author=Leidholdt, Dorchen |authorlink=Dorchen Leidholdt |author2=Raymond, Janice G |title=The Sexual liberals and the attack on feminism |year=1990 |publisher=Pergamon Press |location=New York|isbn=978-0-08-037457-4}}
*{{cite book |author=Vance, Carole S |title=Pleasure and Danger: Exploring Female Sexuality |publisher=Thorsons Publishers |isbn=978-0-04-440593-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview in the United States==
The second wave of feminism in the United States came as a delayed reaction against the renewed domesticity of women after [[World War II]]: the late 1940s [[Post–World War II economic expansion|post-war boom]], which was an era characterized by an unprecedented economic growth, a [[baby boom]], a move to family-oriented suburbs and the ideal of companionate marriages. During this time, women did not tend to seek employment due to their engagement with domestic and household duties, which was seen as their primary duty but often left them isolated within the home and estranged from politics, economics, and law making. This life was clearly illustrated by the media of the time; for example television shows such as ''[[Father Knows Best]]'' and ''[[Leave It to Beaver]]'' idealized domesticity.&lt;ref&gt;Murray Knuttila, ''Introducing Sociology: A Critical Approach'' (4th ed. 2008 Oxford University Press)&lt;/ref&gt;

Some important events laid the groundwork for the second wave. French writer [[Simone de Beauvoir]] had in the 1940s examined the notion of women being perceived as "other" in the patriarchal society. She went on to conclude in her 1949 treatise ''[[The Second Sex]]'' that male-centered ideology was being accepted as a norm and enforced by the ongoing development of myths, and that the fact that women are capable of getting pregnant, lactating, and menstruating is in no way a valid cause or explanation to place them as the "second sex".&lt;ref&gt;Simone de Beauvoir, ''[[The Second Sex]]'', 1949.&lt;/ref&gt; This book was translated from French to English (with some of its text excised) and published in America in 1953.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Moi |first=Toril |title=While we wait: The English translation of The Second Sex |journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society |volume=27 |number=4 |year=2002 |pages=1005–1035 |doi=10.1086/339635 |jstor=10.1086/339635}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1960, the [[Food and Drug Administration (United States)|Food and Drug Administration]] approved the [[combined oral contraceptive pill]], which was made available in 1961.&lt;ref&gt;Tone, Andrea (2001). Devices &amp; Desires: A History of Contraceptives in America. New York: Hill and Wang.&lt;/ref&gt; This made it easier for women to have careers without having to leave due to unexpectedly becoming pregnant. It also meant young couples would not be routinely forced into unwanted marriages due to accidental pregnancies.

Though it is widely accepted that the movement lasted from the 1960s into the early 1980s, the exact years of the movement are more difficult to pinpoint and are often disputed. The movement is usually believed to have begun in 1963, when [[Betty Friedan]] published ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]'', and President [[John F. Kennedy]]'s [[Presidential Commission on the Status of Women]] released its report on gender inequality.

{{external media | width = 210px | float = right | headerimage=[[File:Eleanor Roosevelt and John F. Kennedy (President's Commission on the Status of Women) - NARA cropped.jpg|210px]] | video1 = [http://openvault.wgbh.org/catalog/V_285B9C3362534FFF8494B95922E3240B Prospects of Mankind with Eleanor Roosevelt; What Status For Women?], 59:07, 1962.&lt;br&gt;[[Eleanor Roosevelt]], chair of the Presidential Commission on the Status of Women, interviews President [[John F. Kennedy]], Secretary of Labor [[Arthur Goldberg]] and others, [[WGBH Educational Foundation|Open Vault from WGBH]]&lt;ref name="wgbhov"&gt;{{cite web | title =Prospects of Mankind with Eleanor Roosevelt; What Status For Women? | work = [[National Educational Television]] | publisher =[[WGBH Educational Foundation|Open Vault at WGBH]] | date =1962 | url =http://openvault.wgbh.org/catalog/V_285B9C3362534FFF8494B95922E3240B | accessdate =September 19, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; }}
The administration of [[John F. Kennedy|President Kennedy]] made women's rights a key issue of the [[New Frontier]], and named women (such as [[Esther Peterson]]) to many high-ranking posts in his administration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aflcio.org/aboutus/history/history/peterson.cfm |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927032402/http://www.aflcio.org/aboutus/history/history/peterson.cfm |archive-date=September 27, 2011 |title=Esther Eggertsen Peterson (1906–1997) |website=AFL-CIO}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kennedy also established a [[Presidential Commission on the Status of Women]], chaired by [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] and comprising cabinet officials (including Peterson and [[United States Attorney General|Attorney General]] [[Robert F. Kennedy]]), senators, representatives, businesspeople, psychologists, sociologists, professors, activists, and public servants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://womenshistory.about.com/od/laws/a/status_women.htm |title=President's Commission on the Status of Women 1961–1963 |publisher=Womenshistory.about.com |date=December 14, 1961 |accessdate=July 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report recommended changing this inequality by providing paid maternity leave, greater access to education, and help with child care to women.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

There were other actions by women in wider society, presaging their wider engagement in politics which would come with the second wave. In 1961, 50,000 women in 60 cities, mobilized by [[Women Strike for Peace]], protested above ground testing of nuclear bombs and tainted milk.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.latimes.com/news/obituaries/la-me-dagmar-wilson-20110130,0,5499397.story | work=Los Angeles Times | first=Elaine | last=Woo | title=Dagmar Wilson dies at 94; organizer of women's disarmament protesters | date=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Laurie Ouellette |title=Inventing the Cosmo Girl: class identity and girl-style American dreams |journal=Media, Culture &amp; Society |volume=21 |issue=3 |pages=359–383 |publisher=Mcs.sagepub.com |date=May 1, 1999 |doi=10.1177/016344399021003004 |s2cid=143024139 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:American Association of University Women members with President John F. Kennedy as he signs the Equal Pay Act into law.jpg|thumb|[[American Association of University Women]] members with President [[John F. Kennedy]] as he signs the [[Equal Pay Act of 1963|Equal Pay Act]] into law in 1963]]

In 1963, [[Betty Friedan]], influenced by [[Simone de Beauvoir]]'s ground-breaking, feminist  ''[[The Second Sex]]'', wrote the bestselling book ''The Feminine Mystique''. Discussing primarily white women, she explicitly objected to how women were depicted in the mainstream media, and how placing them at home (as 'housewives') limited their possibilities and wasted potential. She had helped conduct a very important survey using her old classmates from [[Smith College]]. This survey revealed that the women who played a role at home and the workforce were more satisfied with their life compared to the women who stayed home. The women who stayed home showed feelings of agitation and sadness. She concluded that many of these unhappy women had immersed themselves in the idea that they should not have any ambitions outside their home.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite book |title=The World Transformed: 1945 to the Present |last=Hunt |first=Michael |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2014 |isbn=978-0-19-937102-0 |location=New York |pages=220, 221}}&lt;/ref&gt; Friedan described this as "The Problem That Has No Name".&lt;ref&gt;DuBois and Dumenil. ''Through Women's Eyes: An American History Since 1865''. (Bedford; St Martin's, New York)&lt;/ref&gt; The perfect [[nuclear family]] image depicted and strongly marketed at the time, she wrote, did not reflect happiness and was rather degrading for women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Epstein |first=Cynthia Fuchs |date=1988 |title=Deceptive Distinctions: Sex, Gender, and the Social Order |location=New Haven |publisher=Yale University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; This book is widely credited with having begun second-wave feminism in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/obituaries/betty-friedan-465800.html |location=London |work=The Independent |first=Corinne |last=Sweet |title=Betty Friedan |date=February 7, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The report from the Presidential Commission on the Status of Women, along with Friedan's book, spoke to the discontent of many women (especially [[homemaker|housewives]]) and led to the formation of local, state, and federal government women's groups along with many independent feminist organizations. Friedan was referencing a "movement" as early as 1964.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CBCtv |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iDZh3nY9clY |title=Betty Friedan: Women |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=July 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The movement grew with legal victories such as the [[Equal Pay Act of 1963]], [[Civil Rights Act of 1964|Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964]], and the ''[[Griswold v. Connecticut]]'' [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] ruling of 1965. In 1966 Friedan joined other women and men to found the [[National Organization for Women]] (NOW); Friedan would be named as the organization's first president.&lt;ref name=fredianfap&gt;{{cite book|title=The Sixties Chronicle|first=David|last=Farber|publisher=Legacy Publishing|page=256|year=2004|isbn=978-1412710091}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the early successes NOW achieved under Friedan's leadership, her decision to pressure the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] (EEOC) to use Title VII of the 1964 Civil Rights Act to enforce more job opportunities among American women met with fierce opposition within the organization.&lt;ref name="fredianfap"/&gt; Siding with arguments among several of the group's African-American members,&lt;ref name="fredianfap"/&gt; many of NOW's leaders were convinced that the vast number of male African-Americans who lived below the poverty line were in need of more job opportunities than women within the middle and upper class.{{sfnp|Farber|2004|p=257}} Friedan stepped down as president in 1969.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.now.org/press/02-06/02-04.html NOW statement on Friedan's death] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131208133536/http://www.now.org/press/02-06/02-04.html |date=December 8, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1963, freelance journalist [[Gloria Steinem]] gained widespread popularity among feminists after a diary she authored while working undercover as a [[Playboy Bunny]] waitress at the [[Playboy Club]] was published as a two-part feature in the May and June issues of ''[[Show (magazine)|Show]]''.{{sfnp|Farber|2004|p=150}}  In her diary, Steinem alleged the club was mistreating its waitresses in order to gain male customers and exploited the Playboy Bunnies as symbols of male chauvinism, noting that the club's manual instructed the Bunnies that "there are many pleasing ways they can employ to stimulate the club's liquor volume".{{sfnp|Farber|2004|p=150}}  By 1968, Steinem had become arguably the most influential figure in the movement and support for legalized [[abortion]] and federally funded day-cares had become the two leading objectives for feminists.{{sfnp|Farber|2004|p=377}}

Among the most significant legal victories of the movement after the formation of NOW were a 1967 Executive Order extending full [[affirmative action]] rights to women, a 1968 EEOC decision ruling illegal sex-segregated help wanted ads, [[Title IX]] and the [[Women's Educational Equity Act]] (1972 and 1974, respectively, educational equality), [[Title X]] (1970, health and family planning), the [[Equal Credit Opportunity Act]] (1974), the [[Pregnancy Discrimination Act of 1978]], the outlawing of [[spousal rape|marital rape]] (although not outlawed in all states until 1993&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.refugehouse.com/resources_marital_rape.html|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061110033706/http://www.refugehouse.com/resources_marital_rape.html|archive-date=November 10, 2006|website=Refuge House|title=Resources – Marital Rape}}&lt;/ref&gt;), and the legalization of [[no-fault divorce]] (although not legalized in all states until 2010&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.newsday.com/news/region-state/ny-becomes-50th-state-with-no-fault-divorce-1.2212018|title=NY becomes 50th state with no-fault divorce|work=Newsday|agency=AP|date=August 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;), a 1975 law requiring the U.S. Military Academies to admit women, and many Supreme Court cases such as ''[[Reed v. Reed]]'' of 1971 and ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'' of 1973. However, the changing of social attitudes towards women is usually considered the greatest success of the women's movement. In January 2013, US Secretary of Defense [[Leon Panetta]] announced that the longtime ban on women serving in US military combat roles had been lifted.&lt;ref name=ppippav /&gt; The [[United States Department of Defense|US Department of Defense]] (DoD) plans to integrate women into all combat positions by 2016.&lt;ref name=ppippav&gt;[http://www.infoplease.com/us/military/women-history.html A History of Women in the U.S. Military]. ''Infoplease.com''. Accessed December 28, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

Second-wave feminism also affected other movements, such as the [[civil rights movement]] and the [[Student_activism#United_States|student's rights movement]], as women sought equality within them. In 1965 in "Sex and Caste," a reworking of a memo they had written as staffers in civil-rights organizations [[Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee|SNCC]], [[Casey Hayden]] and [[Mary King (political scientist)|Mary King]] proposed that "assumptions of male superiority are as widespread and deep rooted and every much as crippling to the woman as the assumptions of white supremacy are to the Negro," and that in the movement, as in society, women can find themselves "caught up in a common-law caste system."&lt;ref name="Sex and Caste"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carolsim.com/cwluherstory/CWLUArchive/memo.html|title=Sex and Caste: A Kind of Memo|website=The CWLU Herstory Website|accessdate=March 30, 2017|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170331205231/http://www.carolsim.com/cwluherstory/CWLUArchive/memo.html|archivedate=March 31, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dear Sisters"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2uMwEGfAMSQC&amp;pg=PA21|title=Dear Sisters: Dispatches From The Women's Liberation Movement|editor1-first=Rosalyn|editor1-last=Baxandall|editor2-first=Linda|editor2-last=Gordon|year=2000|publisher=Basic Books|isbn=978-0-465-01707-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1967, [[Jo Freeman]] attended a "free school" course on women at the University of Chicago led by [[Heather Booth]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/feminism/_html/JWA004.htm|title=Feminism |website=Jewish Women's Archive}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Naomi Weisstein]]. She invited them to organize a woman's workshop at the then-forthcoming [[National Conference of New Politics]] (NCNP), to be held over [[Labor Day]] weekend 1967 in [[Chicago]]. At that conference, a woman's caucus was formed, and it (led by Freeman and [[Shulamith Firestone]]) tried to present its own demands to the plenary session.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jhmQvhJMUagC&amp;pg=PA61 |title=American Patriotism, American Protest: Social Movements Since the Sixties |first=Simon |last=Hall |year=2011 |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press |page=61 |isbn=978-0-8122-4295-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the women were told their resolution was not important enough for a floor discussion, and when through threatening to tie up the convention with procedural motions they succeeded in having their statement tacked to the end of the agenda, it was never discussed.&lt;ref name="jofreeman.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jofreeman.com/socialmovements/origins.htm|title=On the Origins of Social Movements|first=Jo|last=Freeman|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the National Conference for New Politics (NCNP) Director William F. Pepper refused to recognize any of the women waiting to speak and instead called on someone to speak about [[Native Americans in the United States|American Indians]], five women, including Firestone, rushed the podium to demand to know why.&lt;ref name="jofreeman.com"/&gt; But Willam F. Pepper patted Firestone on the head and said, "Move on little girl; we have more important issues to talk about here than [[women's liberation]]", or possibly, "Cool down, little girl. We have more important things to talk about than women's problems."&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="jofreeman.com"/&gt; Freeman and Firestone called a meeting of the women who had been at the "free school" course and the women's workshop at the conference; this became the first Chicago [[Women's liberation movement|women's liberation]] group. It was known as the Westside group because it met weekly in Freeman's apartment on Chicago's west side. After a few months, Freeman started a newsletter which she called ''Voice of the women's liberation movement.'' It circulated all over the country (and in a few foreign countries), giving the new movement of [[women's liberation movement|women's liberation]] its name. Many of the women in the Westside group went on to start other feminist organizations, including the [[Chicago Women's Liberation Union]].

In 1968, an [[Students for a Democratic Society|SDS]] organizer at the [[University of Washington]] told a meeting about white college men working with poor white men, and "[h]e noted that sometimes after analyzing societal ills, the men shared leisure time by 'balling a chick together.' He pointed out that such activities did much to enhance the political consciousness of poor white youth. A woman in the audience asked, 'And what did it do for the consciousness of the chick?'" (Hole, Judith, and Ellen Levine, ''Rebirth of Feminism'', 1971, pg. 120).&lt;ref name="jofreeman.com"/&gt; After the meeting, a handful of women formed [[Seattle]]'s first women's liberation group.&lt;ref name="jofreeman.com"/&gt;

Some black feminists who were active in the early second-wave feminism include civil rights lawyer and author [[Florynce Kennedy]], who co-authored one of the first books on abortion, 1971's ''Abortion Rap''; Cellestine Ware, of New York's [[Stanton-Anthony Brigade]]; and Patricia Robinson. These women "tried to show the connections between racism and male dominance" in society.

The second wave of the feminist movement also marks the emergence of [[women's studies]] as a legitimate field of study. In 1970, [[San Diego State University]] was the first university in the United States to offer a selection of women's studies courses.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Women's voices, feminist visions : classic and contemporary readings|others=Shaw, Susan M. (Susan Maxine), 1960–, Lee, Janet, 1954–|isbn=9780078027000|edition=Sixth|location=New York, NY|oclc=862041473|last1 = Shaw|first1 = Susan|last2 = Lee|first2 = Janet|date = April 23, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[1977 National Women's Conference]] in [[Houston]], [[Texas]] presented an opportunity for women's liberation groups to address a multitude of women's issues. At the conference, delegates from around the country gathered to create a [[1977 National Women's Conference#National Plan of Action|National Plan of Action]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite conference|last=|first=|date=1977|title=National Plan of Action|url=https://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/1996_007/item/1364/show/1328|conference=1977 National Women's Conference|publisher=National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year|volume=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; which offered 26 planks on matters such as women's health, women's employment, and child care.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Divided we stand: the battle over women's rights and family values that polarized American politics|last=Spruill|first=Marjorie J.|isbn=9781632863140|location=New York|oclc=972965013|date=February 28, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Alice paul.jpg|thumb|right|upright|alt=Alice Paul stands before the Woman Suffrage Amendment's ratification banner.|[[Alice Paul]] wrote the [[Equal Rights Amendment]], whose passage became an unachieved goal of the feminist movement in the 1970s]] By the early 1980s, it was largely perceived that women had met their goals and succeeded in changing social attitudes towards gender roles, repealing oppressive laws that were based on sex, integrating the "boys' clubs" such as [[military academy|military academies]], the [[United States armed forces]], [[NASA]], single-sex colleges, men's clubs, and the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]], and making gender discrimination illegal. However, in 1982, adding the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] to the [[United States Constitution]] failed, having been ratified by only 35 states, leaving it three states short of ratification.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url=http://content.time.com:80/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,2088114_2087975_2087972,00.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180311044029/http://content.time.com:80/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,2088114_2087975_2087972,00.html |archive-date=March 11, 2018 |url-status=live |date=August 12, 2011 |author=Megan Gibson |title=The Equal Rights Amendment Marches |magazine=A Brief History of Women's Protests |publisher=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |accessdate=December 28, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Second-wave feminism was largely successful, with the failure of the ratification of the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] and [[Richard Nixon|Nixon]]'s veto of the [[Comprehensive Child Development Bill of 1972]] (which would have provided a multibillion-dollar national day care system) the only major legislative defeats. Efforts to ratify the Equal Rights Amendment have continued. Ten states have adopted constitutions or constitutional amendments providing that equal rights under the law shall not be denied because of sex, and most of these provisions mirror the broad language of the Equal Rights Amendment. Furthermore, many women's groups are still active and are major political forces. {{As of | 2011}}, more women earn [[bachelor's degree]]s than men,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mibn.org/site.php/snew/read/demographics_of_working_moms/ |title=Demographics of Working Moms |publisher=Mibn.org |accessdate=July 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; half of the [[Ivy League]] presidents are women, the numbers of women in government and traditionally male-dominated fields have dramatically increased, and in 2009 the percentage of women in the American workforce temporarily surpassed that of men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/06/business/06women.html?_r=1&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=women%20workforce&amp;st=cse | work=The New York Times | title=As Layoffs Surge, Women May Pass Men in Job Force | first=Catherine | last=Rampell | date=February 6, 2009 | accessdate=April 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The salary of the average American woman has also increased over time, although as of 2008 it is only 77% of the average man's salary, a phenomenon often referred to as the [[gender pay gap]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1983185,00.html | work=Time | first=Laura | last=Fitzpatrick | title=Why Do Women Still Earn Less Than Men? | date=April 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whether this is due to discrimination is very hotly disputed, however economists and sociologists have provided evidence to that effect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Rosabeth Moss |last=Kanter |title=Men and Women of the Corporation |url=https://archive.org/details/menwomenofcorpor00kant |url-access=registration |publisher=Basic Books |year=1977 |isbn=978-0-465-04452-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://clinton4.nara.gov/WH/EOP/CEA/html/gendergap.html#disc |title=Office of the White House, Council of Economic Advisors, 1998, IV. Discrimination |publisher=Clinton4.nara.gov |accessdate=July 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.policyalmanac.org/economic/archive/pay_equity.pdf |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051018181503/http://policyalmanac.org/economic/archive/pay_equity.pdf |url-status=dead |archive-date=October 18, 2005 |title=The Gender Wage Gap and Pay Equity: Is Comparable Worth the Next Step? |first=Linda |last=Levine |date=April 21, 2003 |publisher=Congressional Research Service, The Library of Congress |accessdate=July 20, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Second-wave feminism ended in the early 1980s with the [[feminist sex wars]]&lt;ref name=Douglas&gt;{{cite book|title=Love and Politics : Radical Feminist and Lesbian Theories|author=Douglas, Carol Anne|publisher=ISM PRESS|date=July 1990|location=San Francisco, CA, USA|isbn=9780910383172}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was succeeded by [[third-wave feminism]] in the early 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gilmore|first=Stephanie|date=2004|title=No Turning Back: The History of Feminism and the Future of Women, and: Tidal Wave: How Women Changed America at Century's End, and: Feminism in the Heartland (review)|journal=NWSA Journal|volume=16|issue=2|pages=190–196|doi=10.1353/nwsa.2004.0054|s2cid=144734371|issn=1527-1889}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview outside the United States ==
In 1967, at the [[International Alliance of Women]] Congress held in London, delegates were made aware of an initiative by the [[UN Commission on the Status of Women]] to study and evaluate the situation of women in their countries. Many organizations and NGOs like the Association of Business and Professional Women, [[Soroptimists|Soroptimists Club]]s, as well as teaching and nursing associations developed committees in response to the initiative to prepare evaluations on the conditions of women and urge their governments to establish National Commissions on the Status of Women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite thesis|ref=harv|last1=Connolly|first1=Linda Mary|type=PhD|title=From Revolution to Devolution: A Social Movements Analysis of the Contemporary Women's Movement in Ireland|url=http://eprints.maynoothuniversity.ie/5117/1/Linda_Mary_Connolly_20140624131840.pdf|date=September 1997|publisher=[[National University of Ireland Maynooth]]|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180428201554/http://eprints.maynoothuniversity.ie/5117/1/Linda_Mary_Connolly_20140624131840.pdf|archivedate=April 28, 2018|location=Maynooth, County Kildare, Ireland|pages=156–157}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Turkey]]&lt;ref&gt;Badran, Margot, ''Feminism in Islam: Secular and Religious Convergences'' (Oxford, Eng.: Oneworld, 2009) p. 227.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Diner |first1=Cagla |title=Waves of feminism in Turkey: Kemalist, Islamist and Kurdish women's movements in an era of globalization |journal=Journal of Balkan and Near Eastern Studies |date=18 Feb 2010 |volume=12 |issue=1 |pages=41–57 |doi=10.1080/19448950903507388 |s2cid=144926463 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Israel]],&lt;ref&gt;Freedman, Marcia, "Theorizing Israeli Feminism, 1970–2000", in Misra, Kalpana, &amp; Melanie S. Rich, ''Jewish Feminism in Israel: Some Contemporary Perspectives'' (Hanover, N.H.: Univ. Press of New England (Brandeis Univ. Press) 2003) pp. 9–10.&lt;/ref&gt; second-wave feminism began in the 1980s.

=== Spain ===
The 1960s in Spain saw a generational shift in Spanish feminist in response to other changes in Spanish society.  This included increased emigration and tourism (resulting in the spread of ideas from the rest of the world), greater opportunities in education and employment for women and major economic reforms.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;Nielfa Cristóbal, Gloria. ''Movimientos femeninos'', en ''Enciclopedia Madrid S.XX''&lt;/ref&gt; Feminism in the late Franco period and early transition period was not unified.  It had many different political dimensions, however, they all shared a belief in the need for greater equality for women in Spain and a desire to defend the rights of women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.elmundo.es/la-aventura-de-la-historia/2015/03/08/54faf788e2704ea15e8b4576.html|title=Y nos hicimos visibles|date=March 8, 2015|website=ELMUNDO|language=es|access-date=March 27, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Feminism moved from being about the individual to being about the collective.&lt;ref name=":19"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.vocesvisibles.com/historia-del-feminismo/historia-del-feminismo-en-espana|title=Historia del Feminismo en España|last=Seara|first=Marita|date=November 29, 2015|website=Voces Visibles|access-date=March 30, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was during this period that second-wave feminism arrived in Spain.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":32"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KoHC6Oi-SGkC|title=Spanish Women's Writing 1849-1996|last=Davies|first=Catherine|date=January 1, 1998|publisher=A&amp;C Black|isbn=9780485910063}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Second-wave Spanish feminism was about the struggle for the rights of women in the context of the dictatorship.  PCE would start in 1965 to promote this movement with MDM, creating a feminist political orientation around building solidarity for women and assisting imprisoned political figures. MDM launched its movement in Madrid by establishing associations among the housewives of the [[Tetuán (Madrid)|Tetuán]] and [[Getafe]] in 1969. In 1972, Asociación Castellana de Amas de Casa y Consumidora was created to widen the group's ability to attract members.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

Second-wave feminism entered the Spanish comic community by the early 1970s.  It was manifested in Spanish comics in two ways.  The first was that it increased the number of women involved in comics production as writers and artists.  The second was it transformed how female characters were portrayed, making women less passive and less likely to be purely sexual beings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Almerini|first=Katia|date=March 1, 2017|title=La irrupción del feminismo en el cómic español de los setenta / The Emergence of Feminism in the 1970s Spanish Comic|journal=Anuario del Departamento de Historia y Teoría del Arte|language=es|volume=27|issue=2015|doi=10.15366/anuario2015.009|issn=2530-3562|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sweden===
:''See also [[Feminism in Sweden]]''
In Sweden, the Second-wave feminism is foremost associated with [[Group 8 (Sweden)|Group 8]], a feminist organization which was founded by eight women in Stockholm in 1968.&lt;ref&gt;Matthis, Iréne; Dick Urban Vestbro. Kvinnokamp: för en revolutionär kvinnorörelse. Solna: Gidlund.&lt;/ref&gt;

The organization took up various feminist issues such as demands for expansions of kindergartens, 6-hour working day, equal pay for equal work and opposition to pornography. Initially based in Stockholm, local groups were founded throughout the country. The influence of Group 8 on feminism in Sweden is still prevalent.

===The Netherlands===
In 1967, "The Discontent of Women", by [[Joke Smit|Joke Kool-Smits]], was published;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.emancipatie.nl/_documenten/js/werk/hetonbehagenbijdevrouw/hetonbehagenbijdevrouw.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; the publication of this essay is often regarded as the start of second-wave feminism in the Netherlands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://isgeschiedenis.nl/nieuws/joke-smit-feministe-en-journaliste|title=Joke Smit: feministe en journaliste|date=October 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this essay, Smit describes the frustration of married women, saying they are fed up being solely mothers and housewives.

==Beginning and consciousness raising==
The beginnings of second-wave feminism can be studied by looking at the two branches that the movement formed in: the [[liberal feminists]] and the [[Radical feminism|radical feminists.]] The liberal feminists, led by figures such as Betty Friedan and Gloria Steinem advocated for federal legislation to be passed that would promote and enhance the personal and professional lives of women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Takin' it to the Streets|date=2015|publisher=Oxford University Press|editor1-last=Bloom|editor1-first=Alexander|location=New York|page=81|ref=harv|editor2-last=Brines|editor2-first=Wini}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, radical feminists, such as Casey Hayden and Mary King, adopted the skills and lessons that they had learned from their work with civil rights organizations such as the [[Students for a Democratic Society]] and [[Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee]] and created a platform to speak on the violent and sexist issues women faced while working with the larger [[Civil Rights Movement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The World Split Open: How the Modern Women's Movement Changed America|last=Rosen|first=Ruth|date=2000|publisher=The Penguin Group|location=New York|page=100|ref=harv|authorlink=Ruth Rosen|title-link=The World Split Open}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The liberal feminist movement===
{{Main|Liberal feminism}}
After being removed from the workforce, by either personal or social pressures, many women in the post-war America returned to the home or were placed into female only jobs in the service sector.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Grand Expectations: The United States, 1945–1974|last1=Patterson|first1=James T.|date=2000|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|page=33}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the publication of Friedan's ''The Feminine Mystique'' in 1963, many women connected to the feeling of isolation and dissatisfaction that the book detailed. The book itself, however, was not a call to action, but rather a plea for self-realization and [[consciousness raising]] among middle-class women throughout America.{{sfnp|Rosen|2000|p=8}} Many of these women organized to form the [[National Organization for Women]] in 1966, whose "Statement of Purpose" declared that the right women had to equality was one small part of the nationwide civil rights revolution that was happening during the 1960s.{{sfnp|Rosen|2000|p=78}}

===The radical feminist movement===
{{Main|Radical feminism}}
Women who favoured radical feminism collectively spoke of being forced to remain silent and obedient to male leaders in [[New Left]] organizations. They spoke out about how they were not only told to do clerical work such as stuffing envelopes and typing speeches, but there was also an expectation for them to sleep with the male activists that they worked with.&lt;ref name="Shulman"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Shulman|first1=Alix Kates|date=1980|title=Sex and Power: Sexual Bases of Radical Feminism|journal=Signs|volume=5|issue=4, ''Women: Sex and Sexuality''|page=592|doi=10.1086/493754|jstor=3173832}}&lt;/ref&gt; While these acts of sexual harassment took place, the young women were neglected their right to have their own needs and desires recognized by their male cohorts.&lt;ref name="Shulman" /&gt; Many radical feminists had learned from these organizations how to think radically about their self-worth and importance, and applied these lessons in the relationships they had with each other.{{sfnp|Bloom|Brines|2015|p=44}}

== Businesses ==
Feminist activists have established a range of [[feminist businesses]], including [[Feminist bookstore|women's bookstores]], feminist credit unions, feminist presses, feminist mail-order catalogs, feminist restaurants, and feminist record labels. These businesses flourished as part of the second and third waves of feminism in the 1970s, 1980s, and 1990s.&lt;ref name="Echols"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Daring to be Bad: Radical Feminism in America, 1967–1975|last=Echols|first=Alice|publisher=University of Minnesota Press|year=1989|pages=269–278|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Feminist Bookstore Movement: Lesbian Antiracism and Feminist Accountability|last=Hogan|first=Kristen|publisher=Duke University Press|year=2016|location=Durham, North Carolina}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In West Berlin sixteen projects emerged within three years (1974–76)&lt;ref&gt;Cristina Perincioli, "Berlin wird feministisch"(2015) p.137 translated in English [https://feministberlin1968ff.de/womens-center/womens-projects-berlin1972-74/]&lt;/ref&gt; all without state funding (except the women's shelter). Many of those new concepts the social economy picked up later, some are still run autonomously today.&lt;ref&gt;Ilse Lenz (Ed.): Die Neue Frauenbewegung in Deutschland – Abschied von kleinen Unterschied. Eine Quellensammlung (2010) p.281-324, {{ISBN|978-3-531-17436-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Annette Gröschner: Berolinas zornige Töchter – 50 Jahre Berliner Frauenbewegung (2018) p. 78-103, {{ISBN|978-3-9819561-1-5}} Published by the Feminist Archive of Berlin (FFBIZ)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music and popular culture==

Second-wave feminists viewed popular culture as sexist, and created pop culture of their own to counteract this. "One project of second wave feminism was to create 'positive' images of women, to act as a counterweight to the dominant images circulating in popular culture and to raise women's consciousness of their oppressions."&lt;ref name="Arrow2007" /&gt;

==="I Am Woman"===
{{Main|I Am Woman}}

Australian artist [[Helen Reddy]]'s song "[[I Am Woman]]" played a large role in popular culture and became a feminist anthem; Reddy came to be known as a "feminist [[poster child|poster girl]]" or a "feminist icon".&lt;ref name="Arrow2007"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Arrow |first=Michelle |year=2007 |title='It Has Become My Personal Anthem': 'I Am Woman', Popular Culture and 1970s Feminism |journal=Australian Feminist Studies |volume=22 |issue=53 |pages=213–230 |doi=10.1080/08164640701361774|s2cid=143230741 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Reddy told interviewers that the song was a "song of pride about being a woman".&lt;ref name="Gourley"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ms. and the Material Girls: Perceptions of Women from the 1970s through the 1990s|last=Gourley|first=Catherine|publisher=Twenty-First Century|year=2008|isbn=|location=Minneapolis, MN|pages=26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The song was released in 1972. A few weeks after "I Am Woman" entered the charts, radio stations refused to play it. Some music critics and radio stations believed the song represented "all that is silly in the Women's Lib Movement".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=She's a Rebel: The History of Women in Rock &amp; Roll|last=Gaar|first=Gillian|publisher=Seal Press|year=1992|isbn=|location=Seattle|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Helen Reddy then began performing the song on numerous television variety shows. As the song gained popularity, women began calling radio stations and requesting to hear "I Am Woman" played. The song re-entered the charts and reached number one in December 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.gilderlehrman.org/history-by-era/seventies/essays/women-and-music-industry-1970s|first=Elizabeth L.|last=Wollman|title=Women and the Music Industry in the 1970s|website=The Gilder Lehrman Institute of American History|date=July 3, 2012 |url-access=subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Arrow2007" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Aso.gov.au"&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://aso.gov.au/titles/music/i-am-woman/ |title=Overview I Am Woman (1972) |website=ASO – Australia's audio and visual heritage online  |accessdate=July 20, 2012}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated2003"&gt;
"The Anthem and the Angst", Sunday Magazine, Melbourne Sunday Herald Sun/Sydney Sunday Telegraph, June 15, 2003, Page 16.
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated257"&gt;
Betty Friedan, "It Changed My Life" (1976), pp. 257
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1981"&gt;
"Reddy to sing for the rent", Sunday Telegraph (Sydney), November 13, 1981
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"&gt;
"Helen still believes, it's just that she has to pay the rent too", by John Burns of the Daily Express, reprinted in ''Melbourne Herald'', December 16, 1981
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="suntimes1"&gt;
{{cite news| url=http://southtownstar.suntimes.com/southtown/columns/vickroy/x07-dvy2.htm | archive-url=https://archive.today/20110721221948/http://southtownstar.suntimes.com/southtown/columns/vickroy/x07-dvy2.htm | url-status=dead | archive-date=July 21, 2011 | work=Chicago Sun-Times}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.gilderlehrman.org/history-by-era/seventies/essays/women-and-music-industry-1970s|title=Women and the Music Industry in the 1970s|last=Wollman|first=Elizabeth|date=|website=History Now|access-date=|url-access=subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ms. and the Material Girls: Perceptions of Women from the 1970s to 1990s|last=Gourley|first=Catherine|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=26|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; "I Am Woman" also became a protest song that women sang at feminist rallies and protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://0-hnpl.bigchalk.com.catalog.toledolibrary.org/hnweb/hnpl/do/document?set=searchalleras&amp;start=151&amp;rendition=x-article-image&amp;inmylist=false&amp;urn=urn%3Aproquest%3AUS%3BPQDOC%3BHNP%3BPQD%3BHNP%3BPROD%3Bx-article-image%3B603643512&amp;mylisturn=urn%3Aproquest%3AUS%3BPQDOC%3BHNP%3BPQD%3BHNP%3BPROD%3Bx-citation%3B603643512|title=Radical Chic: How Protest Became Saleable|last=Harvey|first=Steve|date=January 28, 1973|work=Los Angeles Times|access-date=April 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Olivia Records===
{{Main|Olivia Records}}
In 1973, a group of five feminists created the first women's owned-and-operated record label, called [[Olivia Records]].&lt;ref name="Wollman"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.gilderlehrman.org/history-by-era/seventies/essays/women-and-music-industry-1970s|title=Women and the Music Industry in the 1970s|last=Wollman|first=Elizabeth|date=|website=The Gilder Lehrman Institute of American History|access-date=March 9, 2017|url-access=subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt; They created the record label because they were frustrated that major labels were slow to add female artists to their rosters. One of Olivia's founders, Judy Dlugacz, said that, "It was a chance to create opportunities for women artists within an industry which at that time had few."&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://0-hnpl.bigchalk.com.catalog.toledolibrary.org/hnweb/hnpl/do/document?set=searchalleras&amp;start=26&amp;rendition=x-article-image&amp;inmylist=false&amp;urn=urn%3Aproquest%3AUS%3BPQDOC%3BHNP%3BPQD%3BHNP%3BPROD%3Bx-article-image%3B2166468282&amp;mylisturn=urn%3Aproquest%3AUS%3BPQDOC%3BHNP%3BPQD%3BHNP%3BPROD%3Bx-citation%3B2166468282|title=Olivia Records: A Healthy Gain in 15 Years|last=Liveton|first=Sharon|date=May 14, 1988|work=Los Angeles Times|access-date=April 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, they had a budget of $4,000, and relied on donations to keep Olivia Records alive. With these donations, Olivia Records created their first LP, an album of feminist songs entitled ''I Know You Know.''&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://0-hnpl.bigchalk.com.catalog.toledolibrary.org/hnweb/hnpl/do/document?set=searchalleras&amp;start=1&amp;rendition=x-article-image&amp;inmylist=false&amp;urn=urn%3Aproquest%3AUS%3BPQDOC%3BHNP%3BPQD%3BHNP%3BPROD%3Bx-article-image%3B650283422&amp;mylisturn=urn%3Aproquest%3AUS%3BPQDOC%3BHNP%3BPQD%3BHNP%3BPROD%3Bx-citation%3B650283422|title=Feminist Record Company: Women Who Love the Spin They're In|last=McKenna|first=Kristine|date=December 11, 1977|work=Los Angeles Times|access-date=April 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The record label originally relied on volunteers and feminist bookstores to distribute their records, but after a few years their records began to be sold in mainstream record stores.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

Olivia Records was so successful that the company relocated from Washington D.C. to Los Angeles in 1975.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Olivia Records released several records and albums, and their popularity grew.&lt;ref name="Wollman" /&gt; As their popularity grew, an alternative, specialized music industry grew around it. This type of music was initially referred to as "lesbian music" but came to be known as "women's music".&lt;ref name="Wollman" /&gt; However, although Olivia Records was initially meant for women, in the 1980s it tried to move away from that stereotype and encouraged men to listen to their music as well.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

===Women's music===
{{Main|Women's music}}
Women's music consisted of female musicians combined music with politics to express feminist ideals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://womensliberationmusicarchive.co.uk|title=The Women's Liberation Music Archive|last=|first=|date=|website=The Women's Liberation Music Archive|access-date=March 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cities throughout the United States began to hold Women's Music Festivals, all consisting of female artists singing their own songs about personal experiences.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://0-hnpl.bigchalk.com.catalog.toledolibrary.org/hnweb/hnpl/do/document?set=searchalleras&amp;start=1&amp;rendition=x-article-image&amp;inmylist=false&amp;urn=urn%3Aproquest%3AUS%3BPQDOC%3BHNP%3BPQD%3BHNP%3BPROD%3Bx-article-image%3B658294452&amp;mylisturn=urn%3Aproquest%3AUS%3BPQDOC%3BHNP%3BPQD%3BHNP%3BPROD%3Bx-citation%3B658294452|title=Women's Music Festival: Alternative in Yosemite|last=Japenga|first=Ann|date=September 21, 1980|work=Los Angeles Times|access-date=April 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first Women's Music Festival was held in 1974 at the University of Illinois.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; In 1979, the [[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]] attracted 10,000 women from across America.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; These festivals encouraged already-famous female singers, such as [[Laura Nyro]] and [[Ellen McIlwaine|Ellen McIllwaine]], to begin writing and producing their own songs instead of going through a major record label.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; Many women began performing hard rock music, a traditionally male-dominated genre. One of the most successful examples included the sisters Ann and Nancy Wilson, who formed the famous hard rock band [[Heart (band)|Heart]].&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

=== Film ===

==== German speaking Europe ====
The [[:de:Deutsche Film- und Fernsehakademie Berlin|Deutsche Film- und Fernsehakademie Berlin]] gave women a chance: from 1968 on one third of the students were female. Some of them - pioneers of women's movement - produced feminist feature films: [[Helke Sander]] 1971 "Eine Prämie für Irene" [A Reward for Irene], and [[Cristina Perincioli]] 1971 "Für Frauen – 1.Kap" [For Women – 1st Chapter].
In West Germany [[Helma Sanders-Brahms]] and [[Claudia von Alemann]] produced feminist documentaries from 1970 on. 
1973 Claudia von Alemann and Helke Sander organized the 1. Internationale Frauen-Filmseminar in Berlin. 
In 1974 Helke Sander founded the journal [[:de:Frauen und Film|Frauen und Film]] – a first feminist filmjournal, which she edited until 1981.

In the 1970s in West Germany, women directors produced a whole series of [[:de:Frauenfilm|Frauenfilm]] - films focusing on women's personal emancipation. In 1980s the [[Goethe Institute]] brought a collection of German women's films in every corner of the world.
“…here the term ‘feminist filmmaking’ does function to point to a filmmaking practice defining itself outside the masculine mirror. German feminism is one of the most active women's movements in Europe. It has gained access to television; engendered a spectrum of journals, a publishing house and a summer women's university in Berlin; inspired a whole group of filmmakers; ...” writes Marc Silberman in [[Jump Cut (journal)]].&lt;ref&gt;Jump Cut, no. 27, July 1982, pp. 41-42.&lt;/ref&gt; But most of the women filmmakers did not see themselves as feminists, except [[Helke Sander]]&lt;ref&gt;Film and feminism in Germany, Jump Cut, no. 29, February 1984, pp. 60-62.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Cristina Perincioli]]. Perincioli stated in an interview: “Fight first … before making beautiful art”.&lt;ref&gt;Jump Cut, 29, February 1984, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; There, she explains how she develops and shoots the film together with the women concerned: saleswomen, battered wives - and why she prefers to work with an all female team. Camera women were still so rare in the 1970 that she had to find them in Denmark and France. Working with an all women film crew Perincioli encouraged women to learn these then male dominated professions.

==== Association of women filmworkers ====
In 1979, German women filmworkers formed the Association of women filmworkers&lt;ref&gt;Petra Haffter in Jump Cut, no. 30, March 1985, p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt; which was active for a few years. In 2014, a new attempt with Proquote Film (then as [[:de:|Proquote Regie]][https://proquote-film.de] turned out to be successful and effective.
A study by the University of Rostock shows that 42% of the graduates of film schools are female, but only 22% of the German feature films are staged by a woman director and are usually financially worse equipped. Similarly, women are disadvantaged in the other male-dominated film trades, where men even without education are preferred to the female graduates.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imf.uni-rostock.de/fileadmin/PHF_IMD/Bilder/News/Gender-Report-Deutscher_Kinofilm_2015.pdf ''Wer dreht deutsche Kinofilme? Gender Report: 2009–2013'', Studie des Instituts für Medienforschung der Universität Rostock, Februar 2015 (pdf)]&lt;/ref&gt;
The initiative points out that the introduction of a quota system in Sweden has brought the proportion of women in key positions in film production around the same as the population share.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfi.se/en-GB/Statistics/Gender-equality/ ''Gender equality in Swedish Film'', Swedish Film Institute], abgerufen am 12. Februar 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, the Swedish initiative calls also for a parity of film funding bodies and the implementation of a gradual women's quota for the allocation of film and television directing jobs in order to achieve a gender-equitable distribution. This should reflect the plurality of a modern society, because diversity can not be guaranteed if more than 80% of all films are produced by men.
ProQuote Film is the third initiative with which women with a high share in their industry are fighting for more female executives and financial resources (see [[:de:|Pro Quote]] Medien (2012) and Quote Medizin).

==== USA ====
In the USA, both the creation and subjects of motion pictures began to reflect second-wave feminist ideals,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite thesis|last=Smith|first=Allison A.|date=May 2010|title=Leading Ladies?: Feminism and the Hollywood New Wave|url=https://digitalcommons.salve.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1053&amp;context=pell_theses|series=Pell Scholars and Senior Theses|publisher=Salve Regina University|volume=Paper 53}}&lt;/ref&gt; leading to the development of [[feminist film theory]]. In the late 1970s and early 1980s, female filmmakers that were involved in part of the new wave of feminist film included [[Joan Micklin Silver]] (''[[Between the Lines (1977 film)|Between the Lines]]''), [[Claudia Weill]] (''[[Girlfriends (1978 film)|Girlfriends]]''), [[Stephanie Rothman]], and [[Susan Seidelman]] (''[[Smithereens (film)|Smithereens]]'', ''[[Desperately Seeking Susan]]'').&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.bfi.org.uk/news-opinion/news-bfi/lists/10-great-feminist-films|title=10 great feminist films|work=British Film Institute|access-date=May 19, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Women Who Write the Movies: From Frances Marion to Nora Ephron|last=Marcia|first=McCreadie|publisher=Carol Publishing Group|year=1994|isbn=|location=|pages=3–67}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other notable films that explored feminist subject matters that were made at this time include the film adaptation of [[Lois Gould]]'s novel ''[[Such Good Friends]]'' and ''[[Rosemary's Baby (film)|Rosemary's Baby]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ward |first=Sarah |title=All of them witches: Individuality, conformity and the occult on screen |journal=Screen Education |issue=83 |year=2016 |pages=34–41 |url=http://go.galegroup.com/ps/i.do?p=AONE&amp;sw=w&amp;v=2.1&amp;id=GALE%7CA467335921&amp;it=r&amp;asid=23711336d4c3b97545d608fe155564c9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The documentary ''[[She's Beautiful When She's Angry]]'' was the first [[documentary film]] to cover feminism's second wave.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.newsweek.com/ride-feminisms-second-wave-new-documentary-shes-beautiful-when-shes-angry-289945|title=Ride Feminism's Second Wave in New Documentary 'She's Beautiful When She's Angry'|date=December 7, 2014|work=Newsweek|access-date=May 19, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Social changes ==
===Use of birth control===
Finding a need to talk about the advantage of the [[Food and Drug Administration]] passing their approval for the use of [[birth control]] in 1960, liberal feminists took action in creating panels and workshops with the goal to promote conscious raising among sexually active women. These workshops also brought attention to issues such as venereal diseases and safe abortion.{{sfnp|Rosen|2000|p=176}} Radical feminists also joined this push to raise awareness among sexually active women. While supporting the "Free Love Movement" of the late 1960s and early 1970s, young women on college campuses distributed pamphlets on birth control, sexual diseases, abortion, and cohabitation.{{sfnp|Bloom|Brines|2015|p=66}}

While white women were concerned with obtaining birth control for all, women of color were at risk of sterilization because of these same medical and social advances: "Native American, African American, and Latina groups documented and publicized sterilization abuses in their communities in the 1960s and 70s, showing that women had been sterilized without their knowledge or consent... In the 1970s, a group of women... founded the Committee to End Sterilization Abuse (CESA) to stop this racist population control policy begun by the federal government in the 1940s – a policy that had resulted in the sterilization of over one-third of all women of child-bearing age in Puerto Rico."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Shaw|first1=Susan|last2=Lee|first2=Janet|title=Women's Voices, Feminist Visions|date=September 2008|publisher=McGraw Hill|isbn=978-0073512280|page=342|edition=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of forced sterilization disproportionately affected women of color and women from lower socioeconomic statuses. Sterilization was often done under the ideology of [[eugenics]]. Thirty states within the United States authorized legal sterilizations under eugenic sciences.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Schoen|first=Johanna|date=2001|title=Between Choice and Coercion: Women and the Politics of Sterilization in North Carolina, 1929–1975|journal=Journal of Women's History|volume=13|issue=1|pages=132–156|doi=10.1353/jowh.2001.0034|s2cid=143129170}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Domestic violence and sexual harassment===
The second-wave feminist movement also took a strong stance against physical violence and sexual assault in both the home and the workplace. In 1968, [[National Organization for Women|NOW]] successfully lobbied the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] to pass an amendment to Title VII of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], which prevented discrimination based on sex in the workplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Patterson|first1=James T.|title=Grand Expectations: The United States, 1945–1974|url=https://archive.org/details/grandexpectation00patt|url-access=registration|date=1996|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|page=[https://archive.org/details/grandexpectation00patt/page/646 646]}}&lt;/ref&gt; This attention to women's rights in the workplace also prompted the EEOC to add sexual harassment to its "Guidelines on Discrimination", therefore giving women the right to report their bosses and coworkers for acts of sexual assault.

Domestic violence, such as battery and rape, were rampant in post-war America. Women were often abused as a result of daily frustration in their husband's lives, and as late as 1975 domestic battery and rape were both socially acceptable and legal as women were seen to be the possessions of their husbands.{{sfnp|Rosen|2000|pp=186, 183}} Because of activists in the second-wave feminist movement, and the local law enforcement agencies that they worked with, by 1982 three hundred shelters and forty-eight state coalitions had been established to provide protection and services for women who had been abused by male figures in their lives.{{sfnp|Rosen|2000|p=186}}

==Education==

===Title IX===
{{Main|Title IX}}

===Coeducation===
One debate which developed in the [[United States]] during this time period revolved around the question of [[coeducation]]. Most [[men's colleges in the United States]] adopted coeducation, often by merging with [[Women's colleges in the United States|women's colleges]]. In addition, some women's colleges adopted coeducation, while others maintained a single-sex student body.

====Seven Sisters Colleges====
Two of the [[Seven Sisters (colleges)|Seven Sister colleges]] made transitions during and after the 1960s. The first, [[Radcliffe College]], merged with [[Harvard University]]. Beginning in 1963, students at Radcliffe received Harvard diplomas signed by the presidents of Radcliffe and Harvard and joint commencement exercises began in 1970. The same year, several Harvard and Radcliffe dormitories began swapping students experimentally and in 1972 full co-residence was instituted. The departments of [[College athletics|athletics]] of both schools merged shortly thereafter. In 1977, Harvard and Radcliffe signed an agreement which put undergraduate women entirely in Harvard College. In 1999, Radcliffe College was dissolved and Harvard University assumed full responsibility over the affairs of female undergraduates. Radcliffe is now the Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study in [[Women's Studies]] at Harvard University.

The second, [[Vassar College]], declined an offer to merge with [[Yale University]] and instead became coeducational in 1969.

The remaining Seven Sisters decided against coeducation. [[Mount Holyoke College]] engaged in a lengthy debate under the presidency of [[David Truman]] over the issue of coeducation. On November 6, 1971, "after reviewing an exhaustive study on coeducation, the board of trustees decided unanimously that Mount Holyoke should remain a women's college, and a group of faculty was charged with recommending curricular changes that would support the decision."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.mtholyoke.edu/cic/about/detailed.shtml|title=Mount Holyoke:A Detailed History|publisher=mtholyoke.edu|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Smith College]] also made a similar decision in 1971.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.smith.edu/collegerelations/presidents.php |title=Smith Tradition |publisher=smith.edu |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070101215838/http://www.smith.edu/collegerelations/presidents.php |archivedate=January 1, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1969, [[Bryn Mawr College]] and [[Haverford College]] (then all male) developed a system of sharing residential colleges. When Haverford became coeducational in 1980, Bryn Mawr discussed the possibly of coeducation as well, but decided against it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.brynmawr.edu/visit/history.shtml|title=A Brief history of Bryn Mawr College|publisher=brynmawr.edu|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080120065225/http://www.brynmawr.edu/visit/history.shtml|archivedate=January 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1983, [[Columbia University]] began admitting women after a decade of failed negotiations with [[Barnard College]] for a merger along the lines of Harvard and Radcliffe (Barnard has been affiliated with Columbia since 1900, but it continues to be independently governed). [[Wellesley College]] also decided against coeducation during this time.

====Mississippi University for Women====
In 1982, in a 5–4 decision, the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] ruled in ''[[Mississippi University for Women v. Hogan]]'' that the [[Mississippi University for Women]] would be in violation of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]]'s [[Equal Protection Clause]] if it denied admission to its nursing program on the basis of gender. Mississippi University for Women, the first [[Public university|public or government institution]] [[Women's colleges in the United States|for women in the United States]], changed its admissions policies and became coeducational after the ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mississippi.edu/universities/ |title=Mississippi Public Universities – Mississippi's University System |publisher=Mississippi.edu |date=September 15, 1925 |accessdate=July 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In what was her first opinion written for the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]], [[Sandra Day O'Connor|Justice Sandra Day O'Connor]] stated, "In limited circumstances, a gender-based classification favoring one sex can be justified if it intentionally and directly assists members of the sex that is disproportionately burdened."  She went on to point out that there are a disproportionate number of women who are nurses, and that denying admission to men "lends credibility to the old view that women, not men, should become nurses, and makes the assumption that nursing is a field for women a [[self-fulfilling prophecy]]".&lt;ref&gt;''[[Mississippi University for Women v. Hogan]]'', 458 U.S. 718 (1982)&lt;/ref&gt;

In the dissenting opinions, Justices [[Harry A. Blackmun]], [[Warren E. Burger]], [[Lewis F. Powell, Jr.]], and [[William H. Rehnquist]] suggested that the result of this ruling would be the elimination of publicly supported single-sex educational opportunities. This suggestion has proven to be accurate as there are no public women's colleges in the United States today and, as a result of ''[[United States v. Virginia]]'', the last all-male public university in the United States, [[Virginia Military Institute]], was required to admit women. The ruling did not require the university to change its name to reflect its [[Mixed-sex education|coeducational status]] and it continues a tradition of academic and leadership development for women by providing [[liberal arts]] and professional education to women and men.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muw.edu/pie/vision.html MUW – Planning and Institutional Effectiveness] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101017083159/http://www.muw.edu/pie/vision.html |date=October 17, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Mills College====
On May 3, 1990, the Trustees of [[Mills College]] announced that they had voted to admit male students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F30610F73C540C778CDDAC0894D8494D81 |title=Venerable School for Women Is Going Co-ed |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=May 4, 1990|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; This decision led to a two-week student and staff [[Strike action|strike]], accompanied by numerous displays of [[Nonviolence|nonviolent]] protests by the students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DE1738F936A35756C0A966958260 |title=Mills Students Protesting Admission of Men |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=May 5, 1990|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F30616FC355E0C758CDDAC0894D8494D81 |title=Disbelieving and Defiant, Students Vow: No Men |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=May 6, 1990| first=Katherine | last=Bishop | accessdate=April 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; At one point, nearly 300 students blockaded the administrative offices and boycotted classes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DE133EF93BA35756C0A966958260|title=Protest Continues at College Over Decision to Admit Men |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=May 8, 1990|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; On May 18, the Trustees met again to reconsider the decision,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DA1130F931A25756C0A966958260 |title=College to Reconsider Decision to Admit Men |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=May 12, 1990|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; leading finally to a reversal of the vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F30616F63C550C7A8DDDAC0894D8494D81 |title=Women's College Rescinds Its Decision to Admit Men |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=May 19, 1990| first=Katherine | last=Bishop | accessdate=April 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other colleges====
[[Sarah Lawrence College]] declined an offer to merge with [[Princeton University]], becoming coeducational in 1969.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://etcweb.princeton.edu/CampusWWW/Studentdocs/Coed.html|title=Chicks and Bricks|website=etcweb.princeton.edu|access-date=April 30, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Connecticut College]] also adopted coeducation during the late 1960s.
[[Wells College]], previously with a student body of women only, became co-educational in 2005. Douglass College, part of [[Rutgers University]], was the last publicly funded women's only college until 2007 when it became coed.

==Criticism==
Some black and/or working class and poor women felt alienated by the main planks of the second-wave feminist movement, which largely advocated women's right to work outside the home and expansion of reproductive rights. Women of color and poor white women in the US had been working outside of the home in blue-collar and service jobs for generations. Additionally, [[Angela Davis]] wrote that while Afro-American women and white women were subjected to multiple unwilled pregnancies and had to clandestinely [[Abortion|abort]], Afro-American women were also suffering from [[compulsory sterilization]] programs that were not widely included in dialogue about reproductive justice.

Beginning in the late 20th century, numerous feminist scholars such as [[Audre Lorde]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lewis|first=Gail|date=July 2005|title=Audre Lorde: vignettes and mental conversations|journal=Feminist Review|volume=80|issue=1|pages=130–145|doi=10.1057/palgrave.fr.9400222|s2cid=189905287|issn=0141-7789}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Winona LaDuke]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Jenks|first=Tom|date=February 2001|title=From the Conferences|journal=The San Francisco Jung Institute Library Journal|volume=19|issue=4|pages=53–66|doi=10.1525/jung.1.2001.19.4.53|issn=0270-6210}}&lt;/ref&gt; critiqued the second wave in the United States as reducing feminist activity into a homogenized and whitewashed chronology of [[feminist history]] that ignores the voices and contributions of many [[women of color]], working-class women, and LGBT women.&lt;ref name="Blackwell"&gt;{{Cite book|title = ¡Chicana Power!: Contested Histories of Feminism in the Chicano Movement|last = Blackwell|first = Maylei|publisher = University of Texas Press|year = 2011|isbn = 9780292726901|location = Austin|pages = 11, 14|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Rethinking Women's and Gender Studies|last = Henry|first = Astrid|publisher = Routledge|year = 2012|isbn = 978-0415808316|location = New York|pages = 2071|editor-last = Orr|editor-first = Catherine M.|editor-last2 = Braithwaite|editor-first2 = Ann|editor-last3 = Lichtenstein|editor-first3 = Diane|chapter = Chapter 6: Waves|type = Kindle}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second-wave feminist movement in the United States has been criticized for failing to acknowledge the struggles of women of color, and their voices were often silenced or ignored by white feminists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://rewire.news/article/2013/07/28/women-of-color-and-feminism-a-history-lesson-and-way-forward/|title=Women of Color and Feminism: A History Lesson and Way Forward|website=Rewire.News|access-date=April 30, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Blackwell"/&gt; It has been suggested that the [[Dominant narrative|dominant historical narratives]] of the feminist movement focuses on white, East Coast, and predominantly middle-class women and women's [[Consciousness raising|consciousness-raising]] groups, excluding the experiences and contributions of lesbians, women of color, and working-class and lower-class women.&lt;ref name=Douglas /&gt; [[Chela Sandoval]] called the dominant narratives of the women's liberation movement "[[Hegemony|hegemonic]] feminism" because it [[Essentialism|essentializes]] the feminist historiography to an exclusive population of women, which assumes that all women experience the same oppressions as the white, East Coast, and predominantly middle-class women.{{sfnp|Blackwell|2011|p=16}} This restricting view purportedly ignored the oppressions women face determined by their race, class, and sexuality, and gave rise to women-of-color feminisms that separated from the [[women's liberation movement]], such as [[Black feminism]], [[Womanism|Africana womanism]], and the Hijas de Cuauhtémoc that emerged at California State University, Long Beach, which was founded by [[Anna Nieto-Gómez]], due to the [[Chicano Movement]]'s [[sexism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Thompson|first=Becky|date=22/2002|title=Multiracial Feminism: Recasting the Chronology of Second Wave Feminism|journal=Feminist Studies|volume=28|issue=2|pages=337–360|doi=10.2307/3178747|jstor=3178747|s2cid=152165042|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/7e742ad93c990615a97d8c857597206b6ebaf54b}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=ARRASTÍA|first1=LISA|last2=WATSON|first2=CATHRYN MERLA|last3=NAGAR|first3=RICHA|date=December 7, 2007|title=Black, Brown, Yellow and Left: Radical Activism in Los Angeles by Laura Pulido|journal=Antipode|volume=39|issue=5|pages=943–947|doi=10.1111/j.1467-8330.2007.00564.x|issn=0066-4812}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Dicochea|first=Perlita R.|date=2004|title=Chicana Critical Rhetoric: Recrafting La Causa in Chicana Movement Discourse, 1970-1979|journal=Frontiers: A Journal of Women Studies|volume=25|issue=1|pages=77–92|doi=10.1353/fro.2004.0032|s2cid=143518721|issn=1536-0334}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw|Kimberlé Crenshaw]] coined the term "[[intersectionality]]" in 1989 in response to the white, middle-class views that dominated second-wave feminism. Intersectionality describes the way systems of oppression (i.e. sexism, racism) have multiplicative, not additive, effects, on those who are multiply marginalized. It has become a core tenet of [[third-wave feminism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Crenshaw|first=Kimberlé|date=1989|title="Demarginalizing the intersection of race and sex: a Black feminist critique of antidiscrimination doctrine, feminist theory and antiracist politics".|url=https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1052&amp;context=uclf|journal=University of Chicago Legal Forum|volume=1989|pages=139–168|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many feminist scholars see the generational division of the second wave as problematic.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Babb|first=Florence E.|date=2012|title=Feminist, Queer, and Indigenous: The Anthropologies of Elizabeth Lapovsky Kennedy—A Personal Reflection|journal=Feminist Formations|volume=24|issue=3|pages=69–78|doi=10.1353/ff.2012.0035|s2cid=144409984|issn=2151-7371}}&lt;/ref&gt; Second wavers are typically essentialized as the [[Baby boomers|Baby Boomer]] generation, when in actuality many feminist leaders of the second wave were born before World War II ended. This generational essentialism homogenizes the group that belongs to the wave and asserts that every person part of a certain demographic generation shared the same ideologies, because ideological differences were considered to be generational differences.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Rethinking Women's and Gender Studies|last = Henry|first = Astrid|publisher = Routledge|year = 2012|isbn = 978-0415808316|location = New York|pages = 2134 &amp; 2180|editor-last = Orr|editor-first = Catherine M.|editor-last2 = Braithwaite|editor-first2 = Ann|editor-last3 = Lichtenstein|editor-first3 = Diane|chapter = Chapter 6: Waves|type = Kindle}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Feminist scholars, particularly those from the late 20th and early 21st centuries to the present day, have revisited diverse writings,&lt;ref name=Douglas /&gt; oral histories, artwork, and artifacts of women of color, working-class women, and lesbians during the early 1960s to the early 1980s to decenter what they view as the dominant historical narratives of the second wave of the women's liberation movement, allowing the scope of the historical understanding of feminist consciousness to expand and transform. By recovering histories that they believe have been erased and overlooked, these scholars purport to establish what Maylei Blackwell termed "[[Retrofitting|retrofitted]] memory".{{sfnp|Blackwell|2011|pp=2–3}} Blackwell describes this as a form of "countermemory" that creates a transformative and fluid "alternative archive" and space for women's feminist consciousness within "hegemonic narratives".{{sfnp|Blackwell|2011|pp=2–3}} For Blackwell, looking within the gaps and crevices of the second wave allows fragments of historical knowledge and memory to be discovered, and new historical feminist subjects as well as new perspectives about the past to emerge, forcing existing dominant histories that claim to represent a [[Universality (philosophy)|universal]] experience to be decentered and refocused.{{sfnp|Blackwell|2011|p=101}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Feminism}}
{{columns-list|*[[American philosophy]]
*[[Black Feminism]]
*[[Civil rights movements]]
*[[Counterculture of the 1960s]]
*[[Feminism in 1950s Britain]]
*[[First-wave feminism]]
*[[History of feminism]]
*[[List of feminists]]
*[[List of women's rights activists]]
*[[Pro-life feminism]]
*[[Radical Feminism]]
*[[Sexual revolution]]
*[[Third-wave feminism]]
*[[Timeline of reproductive rights legislation]]
*[[Timeline of second-wave feminism]]
*[[Timeline of women's legal rights (other than voting)]]
*[[Timeline of women's suffrage]]|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Boxer, Marilyn J. and Jean H. Quataert, eds. ''Connecting Spheres: European Women in a Globalizing World, 1500 to the Present'' (2000)
*[[Nancy F. Cott|Cott, Nancy]]. ''No Small Courage: A History of Women in the United States'' (2004)
*[[Estelle Freedman|Freedman, Estelle B]]. ''No Turning Back: The History of Feminism and the Future of Women'' (2003)
* {{Cite journal |last=Harnois |first=Catherine |title=Re-presenting feminisms: Past, present, and future |journal=NWSA Journal | publisher=[[Johns Hopkins University Press]]|volume=20 |issue=1 |pages=120–145 |year=2008 |jstor=40071255 |url=http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/nwsa_journal/summary/v020/20.1.harnois.html }}
* MacLean, Nancy. ''The American Women's Movement, 1945–2000: A Brief History with Documents'' (2008)
* Offen, Karen; Pierson, Ruth Roach; and Rendall, Jane, eds. ''Writing Women's History: International Perspectives'' (1991)
* Prentice, Alison and [[Susan Mann (Canadian historian)|Trofimenkoff, Susan Mann]], eds. ''The Neglected Majority: Essays in Canadian Women's History'' (2 vol 1985)
*[[Barbara N. Ramusack|Ramusack, Barbara N.]], and Sharon Sievers, eds. ''Women in Asia: Restoring Women to History'' (1999)
*[[Ruth Rosen|Rosen, Ruth]]. ''[[The World Split Open|The World Split Open: How the Modern Women's Movement Changed America]]'' (2nd ed. 2006)
* Roth, Benita. ''Separate Roads to Feminism: Black, Chicana, and White Feminist Movements in America's Second Wave.'' Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press (2004)
* Stansell, Christine. ''The Feminist Promise: 1792 to the Present'' (2010)
*{{cite journal |last=Thébaud |first=Françoise |title=Writing women's and gender history in France: A national narrative? |journal=Journal of Women's History |date=Spring 2007 |volume=19 |issue=1 |pages=167–172 |doi=10.1353/jowh.2007.0026|s2cid=145711786 }}
* Zophy, Angela Howard, ed. ''Handbook of American Women's History'' (2nd ed. 2000)

==External links==
*{{Commons category-inline}}

{{Second-wave feminism}}
{{Feminism}}
{{Counterculture of the 1960s}}
{{United States topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Second Wave Feminism}}
[[Category:Second-wave feminism| ]]
[[Category:Counterculture of the 1960s]]

[[de:Feminismus#Zweite Welle des Feminismus]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>