<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061024021047|83338641" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="631216" pageid="631216" ns="0" title="Second-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-26T20:21:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''''Second-wave feminism''''' refers to a period of [[feminist]] activity which began during the early [[1960s]]  and lasted through the late [[1980s]]. 
==Overview==
Second Wave Feminism is generally identified with a period beginning in the early nineteen sixties and extending through the late nineteen eighties. Whereas [[first-wave feminism]] focused largely on [[de jure]] (officially mandated) inequalities, second wave feminism saw [[de jure]] and [[de facto]] (unofficial) inequalities as inextricably linked issues that had to be addressed in tandem. 

The movement encouraged women to understand aspects of their own personal lives as deeply politicized, and reflective of a sexist structure of power. If [[first-wave feminism]] focused upon absolute rights such as [[Women's suffrage|suffrage]], second-wave feminism was largely concerned with other [[issues]] of equality ranging from the economic to the reproductive. This latter reproduction issue came probably out with the marketing of [[The_pill#Social_and_cultural_impact |the pill]] since 1960.

==Major moments==
Among the major events that marked the time known as second wave feminism, were:

*''The Commission on the Status of Women'' was created in the USA by the [[Kennedy administration]], with [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] as its chair. The report issued by that commission in 1963 that documented discrimination against women in virtually every area of American life. 

*That same year, [[Betty Friedan]]'s, ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]'', appeared on bookshelves. The book was composed of interview materials with women that buttressed the facts reported by the Commission report. It became an immediate bestseller.

*Due to a combined effort from many different sorts of activists, ''Title VII'' of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] of the USA was passed. Title VII illegalized employment discrimination on the basis of sex as well as race, religion, and national origin. Historians note that the category "sex" was actually included in an eleventh hour attempt to kill the bill. 

*Frustrated by what they saw as a blatant disregard for spirit of the law, The [[National Organization for Women]] (NOW) was formed in the USA in 1966. Its mission was to function as a legal "watchdog" for women, along the lines of the NAACP for Black Americans. This was soon followed by other organizations addressing the needs of specific groups of women, including Blacks, Latinas, Asians-Americans, lesbians, welfare recipients, business owners, aspiring politicians, and professional women of every sort. 

*The rise of [[radical feminism]] during the 1970s.

*Eight years after Title VII, [[Title IX]] in the [[Education Amendments of 1972 (United States)]] was passed, which forbade discrimination in the field of education. Many people see Title IX is extremely important to young women today, contributing to equal provisions for women's sports in school and feminist campus activism, among other things. However, it became clear early that many existing anti-discrimination laws were not enforced. For instance, within the commission's first five years, it received 50,000 sex discrimination complaints, but did little to investigate them.

*Inspired in part by the legal victories of the 1960s and 1970s, but still worried about ''de facto'' discrimination, many feminists supported and worked to ratify the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] into the United States Constitution. The Amendment, proposed in 1972, said:

:''Equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any state on account of sex.'' 

Opponents, such as [[Phyllis Schlafly]], charged that passage of the ERA of the USA would lead to men abandoning their families, unisex toilets, gay marriages, and women being drafted. Despite polls consistently showing a large majority of the population supporting an Equal Rights Amendment, when the deadline for ratification came in 1982, the ERA was still three states short of the 38 needed to write it into the U.S. constitution.

*On January 22, 1973, [[Roe vs. Wade]] was decided by the [[U.S. Supreme Court]]. The decision legalized abortion in all 50 states, by stating that the right to decisions regarding one's reproductive system was consistent with a right to privacy under the 14th Amendment to the Constitution.

*The [[Feminist Sex Wars]] of the late 1970s and 1980s between [[Anti-pornography movement|anti-pornography feminism]] and [[sex-positive feminism]]. The "Sex Wars" led to deep divisions within the feminist movement and also laid the groundwork for many issues that were important in [[third-wave feminism]].

==Education==
One debate which developed in the [[United States]] during this time period revolved around the question of [[Women's colleges in the United States|women's colleges]] and [[coeducation]].  

===Adopt coeducation===
During this time, many of the most prominent American [[men's college]]s, including multiple [[Ivy League]] institutions, became co-ed.  Some [[Women's colleges in the United States|women's colleges]] also responded by becoming coeducational, such as the Seven Sister [[Radcliffe College]], which followed [[Tulane University]] and [[H. Sophie Newcomb Memorial College]]'s example (mentioned above) and merged with [[Harvard University]]. In addition, another Seven Sister college, [[Vassar College]], declined an offer to merge with [[Yale University]] and instead became coeducational in 1969. [[Sarah Lawrence College]] declined an offer to merge with [[Princeton University]] and became coeducational in 1969. [[Connecticut College]] also became co-ed during the late [[1960s]].

===Remain women's college===
Other schools responded to the tenets of second-wave feminism by maintaining their single-sex status. 

Since 1900, the seven sister college, [[Barnard College]] has been affiliated with [[Columbia University]], but it continues to be independently governed. In 1983, Columbia College began admitting women after a decade of failed negotiations with Barnard for a merger along the lines of Harvard and Radcliffe. Of the original ''Seven Sisters,'' [[Mount Holyoke College]], [[Smith College]], [[Barnard College]], [[Bryn Mawr College]], and [[Wellesley College]] are still women's colleges.

In 1990, [[Mills College]]'s tentative decision to become co-ed was met with so much resistance from students and alumnae that the proposal was dropped.

==Journalism==
''[[Ms. magazine]]'', founded in 1972 by [[Gloria Steinem]], contains articles centered around issues related to the second wave.

==Legislation==
Important works of legislation which developed in the [[United States]] as a result of the second wave include ''[[Title IX]]''  (1972), which enforced the involvement of girls in sports and athletics in school. The ''[[Equal Rights Amendment]]'' (ERA), which sought to guarantee [[equal rights]] under the [[law]] for [[United States|Americans]] regardless of [[sex]], also developed during this time. The amendment was not ratified, due in part to the extreme difficulty of passing constitutional amendments of any kind. The amendment was of a general nature and did not focus on specific rights. Instead it sought to provide a strong legal precedent for other changes and function and a general symbol of feminist empowerment.

==Organizations==
Individuals involved in the development of these and related issues were often a part of NOW or the ''[[National Organization for Women]]'(USA)''.  [[Betty Friedan]] was one of the founders.

==The rise of intentional communities==
One interesting and underdocumented aspect of the second-wave was the rise of  women's cooperative living communities. An example of one such intentional community was the [[Chatanika River Women's Colony]].

==Second wave in popular culture==
Ideals and debates associated with second-wave feminism were reflected in popular culture of the [[1970s]] and [[1980s]] (see references below).  These figures would be revisted during the late [[1990]]s and early [[2000]]s period of ''[[Girl Power]]''.

===[[Blaxploitation]] films and characters===
*[[Tamara Dobson]] in (and as) ''[[Cleopatra Jones]]'' 
*[[Teresa Graves]] as ''Christie Love'' in ''[[Get Christie Love!]]''
*[[Pam Grier]] in (and as) ''[[Coffy]]'' and ''[[Foxy Brown (1974 film)|Foxy Brown]]''
*[[Gloria Hendry]] as ''Rosie Carver''  in ''[[Live and Let Die (film)]]'' and as ''Sydney'' in ''[[Black Belt Jones]]''

===Other characters===
* [[Barbara Bain]] as ''Cinnamon Carter'' in ''[[Mission: Impossible]]''
*[[Lynda Carter]]  in (and as) ''[[Wonder Woman (television series)|Wonder Woman]]''
*''[[Charlie's Angels]]''
* [[Carrie Fisher]] as  [[Princess Leia Organa]] in '' [[Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope]]''
* [[Sharon Gless]] as Det. Sgt. Christine Cagney and [[Tyne Daly]] as Det. Mary Beth Lacey in  ''[[Cagney &amp; Lacey]]''
* [[Linda Hamilton]] as  [[Sarah Connor (fictional character)|Sarah Connor]] in ''[[The Terminator]]'' films
*[[Anya Major]] as the nameless heroine of [[Ridley Scott]]'s [[1984 (television commercial)|1984 Apple commercial]] which introduced the [[Apple Macintosh]] computer
*[[Julie Newmar]] as [[Catwoman]] in the television show, ''[[Batman (TV series)|Batman]]''
*[[Diana Rigg]] as [[Emma Peel]] of ''[[The Avengers (TV series)|The Avengers]]''
*[[Lindsay Wagner]] as Jaime Sommers in ''[[The Bionic Woman]]''
* [[Sigourney Weaver]] as [[Ellen Ripley]] in the ''[[Alien (film)|Alien ]]'' films

===General films, plays, and television===
* ''[[All in the Family]]'' (1971-9)
* ''[[An Unmarried Woman]]'' (1978)
* ''[[The Cosby Show]] (1984-1992)
* ''[[A Different World]] (1987-1993)
* ''[[Educating Rita]]'' (1980}
* ''[[The Heidi Chronicles]]'' (1989)
* ''[[Kramer vs. Kramer]]'' (1979)
* ''[[Maude (TV series)|Maude]]'' (1972-1978)
* ''[[Nine to Five]]'' (1980)
* ''[[One Day at a Time]] (1975-1984)
* ''[[Private Benjamin]]'' (1980)
* ''[[The Stepford Wives]]'' (1975)
* ''[[Thirtysomething]]'' (1987-1991)
* ''[[Tootsie]]'' (1982)
* ''[[Uncommon Women and Others]]'' (1979)
* ''[[Murphy Brown]]'' (1988-1998)

==See also==
* [[first-wave feminism]]
* [[third-wave feminism]]
* [[Going Dutch]]
* [[Girl Power]]
* [[List of feminists#Second-wave feminists|List of feminists]]

==References==
*Heide, Margaret J. ''[http://www.upenn.edu/pennpress/book/834.html Television Culture and Women's Lives: "Thirtysomething" and the Contradictions of Gender]'' 
*Inness, Sherrie A. (ed.) '''Tough Girls : Women Warriors and Wonder Women in Popular Culture''. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1999.
*Osgerby, Bill, Anna Gough-Yates, and Marianne Wells. ''Action TV : Tough-Guys, Smooth Operators and Foxy Chicks.''  London: Routledge, 2001. 
*Press, Andrea L. ''Women Watching Television: Gender, Class, and Generation in the American Television Experience''. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1991.
*——— and Tery Strathman. "Work, Family, and Social Class in Television Images of Women: Prime-Time Television and the Construction of Postfeminism." ''Women and Language'', 1993 Fall, 16:2, 7-15.
*Roth, Benita. ''Separate Roads to Feminism: Black, Chicana, and White Feminist Movements in America's Second Wave.'' Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2004.
*Tasker, Yvonne. ''Working Girls: Gender and Sexuality in Popular Culture''. London: Routledge 1998
*———.''Spectacular Bodies : Gender, Genre, and the Action Cinema''. London and New York: Routledge, 1993.

[[Category:Feminism| 2]]
[[Category:Feminists| 2]]

[[et:Teise laine feminism]]
[[el:Φεμινισμός δεύτερου κύματος]]
[[he:הגל השני]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>