<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141118040705|634327318" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="631216" pageid="631216" ns="0" title="Second-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-18T04:10:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism sidebar |History}}

'''Second-wave feminism''' is a period of [[feminism|feminist]] activity that first began in the early 1960s in the United States, and eventually spread throughout the Western world and beyond. In the United States the movement lasted through the early 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Gamble, ed. ''The Routledge companion to feminism and postfeminism'' (2001) p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; It later became a worldwide movement that was strong in Europe and parts of Asia, such as [[Turkey]]&lt;ref&gt;Badran, Margot, ''Feminism in Islam: Secular and Religious Convergences'' (Oxford, Eng.: Oneworld, 2009 p. 227 (&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Israel]], where it began in the 1980s, and it began at other times in other countries.&lt;ref&gt;Freedman, Marcia, ''Theorizing Israeli Feminism, 1970–2000'', in Misra, Kalpana, &amp; Melanie S. Rich, ''Jewish Feminism in Israel: Some Contemporary Perspectives'' (Hanover, N.H.: Univ. Press of New England (Brandeis Univ. Press) 2003 pp. 9–10&lt;/ref&gt;

Whereas [[first-wave feminism]] focused mainly on [[Women's suffrage|suffrage]] and overturning legal obstacles to gender [[Gender equality|equality]] (''i.e.'', [[Women's suffrage in the United States|voting rights]], [[property rights]]), second-wave feminism broadened the debate to a wide range of issues: sexuality, family, the workplace, [[reproductive rights]], de facto inequalities, and official legal inequalities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/647122/womens-movement |title=women's movement (political and social movement) - Britannica Online Encyclopedia |publisher=Britannica.com |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; At a time when mainstream women were making job gains in the professions, the military, the media, and sports in large part because of second-wave feminist advocacy, second-wave feminism also drew attention to [[domestic violence]] and [[marital rape]] issues, establishment of rape crisis and battered women's shelters, and changes in custody and divorce law. Its major effort was the attempted passage of the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] (ERA) to the [[United States Constitution]], in which they were defeated by anti-feminists led by [[Phyllis Schlafly]], who argued as an anti-ERA view that the ERA meant women would be [[conscription|drafted]] into the [[United States Armed Forces|military]].

Many historians view the second-wave feminist era in America as ending in the early 1980s with the intra-feminism disputes of the [[feminist sex wars]] over issues such as sexuality and pornography, which ushered in the era of [[third-wave feminism]] in the early 1990s.&lt;ref name=Duggan&gt;{{Cite book|author=Duggan, Lisa; Hunter, Nan D.|authorlink= |title=Sex wars: sexual dissent and political culture|year=1995|publisher=Routledge|location=New York|isbn=0-415-91036-6|pages= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hansen&gt;{{Cite book|author=Hansen, Karen Tranberg|author2=Philipson, Ilene J. |title=Women, class, and the feminist imagination: a socialist-feminist reader|year=1990|publisher=Temple University Press|location=Philadelphia|isbn=0-87722-630-X |pages= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gerhard&gt;{{Cite book|author=Gerhard, Jane F.|title=Desiring revolution: second-wave feminism and the rewriting of American sexual thought, 1920 to 1982|year=2001|publisher=Columbia University Press|location=New York|isbn=0-231-11204-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Leidholdt&gt;{{Cite book|author=Leidholdt, Dorchen|authorlink=Dorchen Leidholdt|author2=Raymond, Janice G |title=The Sexual liberals and the attack on feminism|year=1990|publisher=Pergamon Press|location=New York|isbn=0-08-037457-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Vance&gt;{{Cite book|author=Vance, Carole S|title=Pleasure and Danger: Exploring Female Sexuality|publisher=Thorsons Publishers|isbn=0-04-440593-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
The second wave of feminism in North America came as a delayed reaction against the renewed domesticity of women after World War II: the late 1940s post-war boom, which was an era characterized by an unprecedented economic growth, a [[baby boom]], a move to family-oriented suburbs, and the ideal of companionate marriages. This life was clearly illustrated by the media of the time; for example television shows such as ''[[Father Knows Best]]'' and ''[[Leave It to Beaver]]'' idealized domesticity.&lt;ref&gt;Murray Knuttila, ''Introducing Sociology: A Critical Approach'' (4th ed. 2008 Oxford University Press)&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the second wave there were some important events which laid the groundwork for it. French writer [[Simone de Beauvoir]] had in the 1940s examined the notion of women being perceived as "other" in the patriarchal society. She went on to conclude that male-centered ideology was being accepted as a norm and enforced by the ongoing development of myths, and that the fact that women are capable of getting pregnant, lactating, and menstruating is in no way a valid cause or explanation to place them as the "second sex".&lt;ref&gt;Simone de Beauvoir, ''[[The Second Sex]]'', 1949.&lt;/ref&gt;
This book was translated from French to English (with some of its text excised) and published in America in 1953.&lt;ref&gt;Moi, Toril, 'While we wait: The English translation of The Second Sex' in Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society vol. 27, no 4 (2002), pp. 1005–1035&lt;/ref&gt; In 1960 the [[Food and Drug Administration (United States)|Food and Drug Administration]] approved the [[combined oral contraceptive pill]], which was made available in 1961.&lt;ref&gt;Tone, Andrea (2001). Devices &amp; Desires: A History of Contraceptives in America. New York: Hill and Wang.&lt;/ref&gt; This made it easier for women to have careers without having to leave due to unexpectedly becoming pregnant. The administration of [[John F. Kennedy|President Kennedy]] made women's rights a key issue of the [[New Frontier]], and named women (such as [[Esther Peterson]]) to many high-ranking posts in his administration.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aflcio.org/aboutus/history/history/peterson.cfm ]{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kennedy also established a [[Presidential Commission on the Status of Women]], chaired by [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] and comprising cabinet officials (including Peterson and [[United States Attorney General|Attorney General]] [[Robert F. Kennedy]]), senators, representatives, businesspeople, psychologists, sociologists, professors, activists, and public servants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://womenshistory.about.com/od/laws/a/status_women.htm |title=President's Commission on the Status of Women 1961–1963 |publisher=Womenshistory.about.com |date=1961-12-14 |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were also notable actions by women in wider society, presaging their wider engagement in politics which would come with the second wave. In 1961, 50,000 women in 60 cities, mobilized by [[Women Strike for Peace]], protested above ground testing of nuclear bombs and tainted milk.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.latimes.com/news/obituaries/la-me-dagmar-wilson-20110130,0,5499397.story | work=Los Angeles Times | first=Elaine | last=Woo | title=Dagmar Wilson dies at 94; organizer of women's disarmament protesters | date=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Laurie Ouellette |url=http://mcs.sagepub.com/content/21/3/359.abstract |title=Inventing the Cosmo Girl: class identity and girl-style American dreams |publisher=Mcs.sagepub.com |date=1999-05-01 |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1963 [[Betty Friedan]], influenced by ''[[The Second Sex]]'', wrote the bestselling book ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]'' in which she explicitly objected to the mainstream media image of women, stating that placing women at home limited their possibilities, and wasted talent and potential. The perfect [[nuclear family]] image depicted and strongly marketed at the time, she wrote, did not reflect happiness and was rather degrading for women.&lt;ref&gt;Epstein, Cynthia Fuchs. 1988. ''Deceptive Distinctions: Sex, Gender, and the Social Order''. New Haven: Yale University Press&lt;/ref&gt; This book is widely credited with having begun second-wave feminism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/obituaries/betty-friedan-465800.html | location=London | work=The Independent | first=Corinne | last=Sweet | title=Betty Friedan | date=February 7, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though it is widely accepted that the movement lasted from the 1960s into the early 1980s, the exact years of the movement are more difficult to pinpoint and are often disputed. The movement is usually believed to have begun in 1963, when "Mother of the Movement" [[Betty Friedan]] published [[The Feminine Mystique]], and President [[John F. Kennedy]]'s [[Presidential Commission on the Status of Women]] released its report on gender inequality. The report, which revealed great discrimination against women in American life, along with Friedan's book, which spoke to the discontent of many women (especially [[homemaker|housewives]]), led to the formation of many local, state, and federal government women's groups as well as many independent feminist organizations. Friedan was referencing a "movement" as early as 1964.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CBCtv |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iDZh3nY9clY |title=Betty Friedan: Women |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The movement grew with legal victories such as the [[Equal Pay Act of 1963]], [[Civil Rights Act of 1964|Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964]], and the ''[[Griswold v. Connecticut]]'' [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] ruling of 1965. In 1966 Friedan joined other women and men to found the [[National Organization for Women]] (NOW);  Friedan would be named as the organization's first president.&lt;ref name=fredianfap&gt;{{cite book|title=The Sixties Chronicle|author=David Farber|publisher=Legacy Publishing|page=256|year=2004|isbn=141271009X|accessdate=September 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the early successes NOW achieved under Friedan's leadership, her decision to pressure the Equal Employment Opportunity to use Title VII of the 1964 Civil Rights Act to enforce more job opportunities among American women met with fierce opposition within the organization.&lt;ref name="fredianfap"/&gt; Siding with arguments among several of the group's African-American members,&lt;ref name="fredianfap"/&gt; many of NOW's leaders were convinced that the vast number of male African-Americans who lived below the poverty line were in need of more job opportunities than women within the middle and upper class.&lt;ref name=fredianfap245&gt;{{cite book|title=The Sixties Chronicle|author=David Farber|publisher=Legacy Publishing|page=257|year=2004|isbn=141271009X|accessdate=September 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Friedan stepped down as president in 1969.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.now.org/press/02-06/02-04.html NOW statement on Friedan's death]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1963, freelance journalist [[Gloria Steinem]] gained widespread popularity among feminists after a diary she authored while working undercover as a [[Playboy Bunny]] waitress at the [[Playboy Club]] was published as a two-part feature in the May and June issues of ''[[Show (magazine)|Show]]''.&lt;ref name=steinfem&gt;{{cite book|title=The Sixties Chronicle|author=David Farber|publisher=Legacy Publishing|page=150|year=2004|isbn=141271009X|accessdate=July 31, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In her diary, Steinem alleged the club was mistreating its waitresses in order to gain male customers and exploited the Playboy Bunnies as symbols of male chauvinism, noting that the club's manual instructed the Bunnies that "there are many pleasing ways they can employ to stimulate the club's liquor volume."&lt;ref name=steinfem /&gt;  By 1968, Steinem had become arguably the most influential figure in the movement and support for legalized abortion and federally funded day-cares had become the two leading objectives for feminists.&lt;ref name=steinfem2&gt;{{cite book|title=The Sixties Chronicle|author=David Farber|publisher=Legacy Publishing|page=377|year=2004|isbn=141271009X|accessdate=July 31, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Amongst the most significant legal victories of the movement after the formation of NOW were a 1967 Executive Order extending full [[Affirmative Action]] rights to women, a 1968 EEOC decision ruling illegal sex-segregated help wanted ads, [[Title IX]] and the [[Women's Educational Equity Act]] (1972 and 1974, respectively, educational equality), [[Title X]] (1970, health and family planning), the [[Equal Credit Opportunity Act]] (1974), the [[Pregnancy Discrimination Act of 1978]], the illegalization of [[spousal rape|marital rape]] (although not illegalized in all states until 1993 &lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20061110033706/http://www.refugehouse.com/resources_marital_rape.html Refuge House Resources - Marital Rape&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;), and the legalization of [[no-fault divorce]] (although not legalized in all states until 2010 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsday.com/news/region-state/ny-becomes-50th-state-with-no-fault-divorce-1.2212018 NY becomes 50th state with no-fault divorce - Newsday&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;).  A 1975 law requiring the U.S. Military Academies to admit women, and many Supreme Court cases, perhaps most notably ''[[Reed v. Reed]]'' of 1971 and ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'' of 1973. However, the changing of social attitudes towards women is usually considered the greatest success of the women's movement.  In January 2013, US Secretary of Defense Leon Panetta announced that the longtime ban on women serving in US military combat roles had been lifted.&lt;ref name=ppippav /&gt; The US Department of Defense plans to integrate women into all combat positions by 2016.&lt;ref name=ppippav&gt;[http://www.infoplease.com/us/military/women-history.html A History of Women in the U.S. Military] Accessed December 28, 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

Second-wave feminism also affected other movements, such as the civil rights movement and the student's rights movement, as women sought equality within them. In 1965 [[Casey Hayden]] and [[Mary King (political scientist)|Mary King]] published "Sex and Caste: A Kind of Memo"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uic.edu/orgs/cwluherstory/CWLUArchive/memo.html|title=Sex and Caste: A Kind of Memo|publisher=|accessdate=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; detailing women's inequality within the civil rights organization [[SNCC]].&lt;ref name="books.google.com"&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=2uMwEGfAMSQC&amp;pg=PA21&amp;dq=sex+and+caste+a+kind+of+memo&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=tuN-UomdDtHh4APvxoDwCA&amp;ved=0CDAQ6wEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22sex%20and%20caste%22&amp;f=false Dear Sisters: Dispatches From The Women's Liberation Movement - Rosalyn Fraad Baxandall, Rosalyn Baxandall, Linda Gordon - Google Books&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1967 [[Jo Freeman]] attended a “free school’” course on women at the University of Chicago led by [[Heather Booth]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://jwa.org/feminism/_html/JWA004.htm Heather Booth | Jewish Women's Archive&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Naomi Weisstein]]. She invited them to organize a woman’s workshop at the then-forthcoming [[National Conference of New Politics]] (NCNP), to be held over Labor Day weekend 1967 in Chicago. At that conference a woman's caucus was formed, and it (led by Freeman and [[Shulamith Firestone]]) tried to present its own demands to the plenary session.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=jhmQvhJMUagC&amp;pg=PA61&amp;lpg=PA61&amp;dq=%22move+on+little+girl%22+%22women's+liberation%22+sds&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=MuCF5NzJYv&amp;sig=h6F7rS_FjBQOcyB_Q-Gn4kvj_Kc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=FlV-UrehEte84AOY_YGwBA&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAQ American Patriotism, American Protest: Social Movements Since the Sixties - Simon Hall - Google Books&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; However, the women were told their resolution was not important enough for a floor discussion, and when through threatening to tie up the convention with procedural motions they succeeded in having their statement tacked to the end of the agenda, it was never discussed.&lt;ref name="jofreeman.com"&gt;[http://www.jofreeman.com/socialmovements/origins.htm On the Origins of Social Movements&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; When the National Conference for New Politics Director Willam F. Pepper refused to recognize any of the women waiting to speak and instead called on someone to speak about the American Indian, five women, including Firestone, rushed the podium to demand to know why.&lt;ref name="jofreeman.com"/&gt; But Willam F. Pepper patted Firestone on the head and said, "Move on little girl; we have more important issues to talk about here than [[women's liberation]]", or possibly, "Cool down, little girl. We have more important things to talk about than women's problems."&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="jofreeman.com"/&gt; Freeman and Firestone called a meeting of the women who had been at the “free school” course and the women’s workshop at the conference; this became the first Chicago women’s liberation group. It was known as the Westside group because it met weekly in Freeman’s apartment on Chicago’s west side. After a few months Freeman started a newsletter which she called ''Voice of the women’s liberation movement.'' It circulated all over the country (and in a few foreign countries), giving the new movement of [[women's liberation movement|women's liberation]] its name. Many of the women in the Westside group went on to start other feminist organizations, including the [[Chicago Women's Liberation Union]].

In 1968, an SDS organizer at the University of Washington told a meeting about white college men working with poor white men, and "[h]e noted that sometimes after analyzing societal ills, the men shared leisure time by 'balling a chick together.' He pointed out that such activities did much to enhance the political consciousness of poor white youth. A woman in the audience asked, 'And what did it do for the consciousness of the chick?'" (Hole, Judith, and Ellen Levine, ''Rebirth of Feminism'', 1971, pg. 120).&lt;ref name="jofreeman.com"/&gt; After the meeting, a handful of women formed Seattle's first women's liberation group.&lt;ref name="jofreeman.com"/&gt;

By the early 1980s, it was largely perceived that women had met their goals and succeeded in changing social attitudes towards gender roles, repealing oppressive laws that were based on sex, integrating the "boys' clubs" such as [[military academy|Military academies]], the [[United States armed forces]], [[NASA]], single-sex colleges, men's clubs, and the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]], and illegalizing gender discrimination. However, in 1982 adding the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] to the [[United States Constitution]] failed, three states short of ratification.

Second-wave feminism was largely successful, with the failure of the ratification of the ERA the only major legislative defeat. Efforts to ratify it have continued, and twenty-one states now have ERAs in their state constitutions. Furthermore, many women's groups are still active and are major political forces. {{As of | 2011}}, more women earn [[bachelor's degree]]s than men,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mibn.org/site.php/snew/read/demographics_of_working_moms/ |title=Demographics of Working Moms |publisher=Mibn.org |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; half of the [[Ivy League]] presidents are women, the numbers of women in government and traditionally male-dominated fields have dramatically increased, and in 2009 the percentage of women in the American workforce temporarily surpassed that of men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/06/business/06women.html?_r=1&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=women%20workforce&amp;st=cse | work=The New York Times | title=As Layoffs Surge, Women May Pass Men in Job Force | first=Catherine | last=Rampell | date=February 6, 2009 | accessdate=April 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The salary of the average American woman has also increased over time, although as of 2008 it is only 77% of the average man's salary, a phenomenon often referred to as the [[Gender pay gap|Gender Pay Gap]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1983185,00.html | work=Time | first=Laura | last=Fitzpatrick | title=Why Do Women Still Earn Less Than Men? | date=April 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whether this is due to discrimination is very hotly disputed, however economists and sociologists have provided evidence to that effect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Men and Women of the Corporation: New Edition |url=http://www.amazon.com/Women-Corporation-Rosabeth-Moss-Kanter/dp/0465044549 |title=Kanter, '&amp;#39;Men and Women of the Corporation'&amp;#39;, Basic Books, 1977 |publisher=Amazon.com |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://clinton4.nara.gov/WH/EOP/CEA/html/gendergap.html#disc |title=Office of the White House, Council of Economic Advisors, 1998, IV. Discrimination |publisher=Clinton4.nara.gov |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.policyalmanac.org/economic/archive/pay_equity.pdf |title=Levine, Report for Congress, "The Gender Gap and Pay Equity: Is Comparable Worth the Next Step?", Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress, 2003 |format=PDF |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Second-wave feminism in the U.S. coincided in the early 1980s with the feminist sex wars and was overlapped by [[third wave feminism]] in the early 1990s.

==View on popular culture==

Second-wave feminists viewed popular culture as sexist, and created pop culture of their own to counteract this. Australian artist [[Helen Reddy]]’s song "[[I Am Woman]]" played a large role in popular culture and became a feminist anthem; Reddy came to be known as a "feminist [[poster child|poster girl]]" or a "feminist icon".&lt;ref name="autogenerated2007"&gt;
Arrow. Michelle. 2007. "It Has Become My Personal Anthem": “I Am Woman”, Popular Culture and 1970s Feminism. Australian Feminist Studies 22: 213-230.
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Aso.gov.au"&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://aso.gov.au/titles/music/i-am-woman/ |title=Overview I Am Woman (1972) on ASO - Australia's audio and visual heritage online |publisher=Aso.gov.au |accessdate=2012-07-20}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated2003"&gt;
"The Anthem and the Angst", Sunday Magazine, Melbourne Sunday Herald Sun/Sydney Sunday Telegraph, June 15, 2003, Page 16.
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated257"&gt;
Betty Friedan, "It Changed My Life" (1976), pp. 257
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1981"&gt;
"Reddy to sing for the rent", Sunday Telegraph (Sydney), November 13, 1981
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"&gt;
Helen still believes, it's just that she has to pay the rent too", by John Burns of the Daily Express, reprinted in ''Melbourne Herald'', December 16, 1981
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="suntimes1"&gt;
{{cite news| url=http://southtownstar.suntimes.com/southtown/columns/vickroy/x07-dvy2.htm | deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=April 2012|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
"One project of second wave feminism was to create 'positive' images of women, to act as a counterweight to the dominant images circulating in popular culture and to raise women's consciousness of their oppressions."&lt;ref&gt;Arrow, Michelle. 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Timeline of second-wave feminism worldwide==

===1961===

* The report of the [American] [[Presidential Commission on the Status of Women]] found discrimination against women in every aspect of American life and outlined plans to achieve equality. Specific recommendations for women in the workplace included fair hiring practices, paid [[maternity leave]], and affordable [[childcare]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://learningtogive.org/papers/paper200.html |title=National Organization for Women (Informational Paper) |publisher=Learningtogive.org |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="uic.edu"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uic.edu/orgs/cwluherstory/CWLUAbout/timeline.html |title=CWLU Chronology: A timeline for Second Wave Feminism |publisher=Uic.edu |date=1968-04-04 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1963===
* Twenty years after it was first proposed, the [[Equal Pay Act of 1963|Equal Pay Act]] became law in the U.S., and it established equality of pay for men and women performing equal work. However, it did not originally cover executives, administrators, outside salespeople, or professionals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.eeoc.gov/epa/anniversary/epa-40.html]{{dead link|date=October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1972, Congress enacted the Educational Amendments of 1972, which (among other things) amended the [[Fair Labor Standards Act]] to expand the coverage of the Equal Pay Act to these employees, by excluding the Equal Pay Act from the professional workers exemption of the Fair Labor Standards Act.{{Citation needed|date=November 2012}}
* [[Betty Friedan]]'s ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]'' was published, became a best-seller, and laid the groundwork for the second-wave feminist movement in the U.S.&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Addison, Heather; Goodwin-Kelly, Mary Kate; Roth, Elaine (2009). Motherhood misconceived: representing the maternal in U.S. film. SUNY Press. p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Alice S. Rossi]] presented "Equality Between the Sexes: An Immodest Proposal" at the [[American Academy of Arts and Sciences]] conference.&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=National Organization for Women |url=http://www.now.org/history/founders.html |title=Honoring NOW's Founders and Pioneers |publisher=Now.org |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1964===

* [[Title VII]] of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] became law in the U.S., and it barred employment discrimination on account of sex, race, etc. by private employers, employment agencies, and unions.
* The [U.S.] [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] was established; in its first five years, 50,000 complaints of gender discrimination were received.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iq-tests.eu/iq-test-Use-of-IQ-in-the-United-States-legal-system-910.html |title=IQ - Use of IQ in the United States legal system |publisher=Iq-tests.eu |date=2002-06-20 |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Haven House, the first "modern" women's shelter in the world, opened in [[California]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jfsla.org/havenhouse/domestic_violence/shelter/prevention_education/C61#contentPrimary |title=jfsla.org |publisher=Jewish Family Service of Los Angeles |date=2012-05-29 |accessdate=2012-06-05}}{{Failed verification|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1965===

* Casey Hayden and [[Mary King (political scientist)|Mary King]] published "Sex and Caste: A Kind of Memo",&lt;ref&gt;[http://uic.edu/orgs/cwluherstory/CWLUArchive/memo.html Sex and Caste: A Kind of Memo]"&lt;/ref&gt; detailing women's inequality within the civil rights organization [[SNCC]].&lt;ref name="books.google.com"/&gt;
* The U.S. Supreme Court case ''[[Griswold v. Connecticut]]'' struck down the only remaining state law banning the use of [[contraceptive]]s by married couples.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www4.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0381_0479_ZO.html |title=Griswold v. Connecticut |publisher=.law.cornell.edu |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The case ''Weeks v. Southern Bell'' marked a major triumph in the fight against restrictive labor laws and company regulations on the hours and conditions of women’s work in the U.S., opening many previously male-only jobs to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.library.gsu.edu/spcoll/pages/pages.asp?ldID=105&amp;guideID=534&amp;ID=3512 |title=Special Collections &amp; Archives — University Library — Georgia State University |publisher=Library.gsu.edu |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The "Woman Question" was raised for the first time at a [[Students for a Democratic Society (1960 organization)|Students for a Democratic Society]] (SDS) conference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marxists.org/subject/women/subject.htm#question |title=Women and Marxism: Marxists Internet Archive |publisher=Marxists.org |date=1940-08-20 |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[EEOC]] commissioners were appointed to enforce the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964|Civil Rights Act]]. Among them there was only one woman, [[Aileen Hernandez]], a future president of the [[National Organization for Women]].&lt;ref&gt;Wright, Susan (2005), The Civil Rights Act of 1964: Landmark Antidiscrimination Legislation, The Rosen Publishing Group&lt;/ref&gt;
* According to [[Fred R. Shapiro]], in ''American Speech'' (Vol. 60, No. 1, Spring 1985), the term "sexism" was most likely coined on November 18, 1965, by [[Pauline M. Leet]] during the "Student-Faculty Forum" at [[Franklin and Marshall College]].&lt;ref name="wordpress2007"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://finallyfeminism101.wordpress.com/2007/10/19/feminism-friday-the-origins-of-the-word-sexism/ |title=Feminism Friday: The origins of the word "sexism" |work=Finallyfeminism101.wordpress.com |date=October 19, 2007 |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term appears in Leet's forum contribution titled "Women and the Undergraduate", in which she defines it by comparing it to racism, saying in part, "When you argue…that since fewer women write good poetry this justifies their total exclusion, you are taking a position analogous to that of the racist—I might call you in this case a 'sexist'… Both the racist and the sexist are acting as if all that has happened had never happened, and both of them are making decisions and coming to conclusions about someone’s value by referring to factors which are in both cases irrelevant."&lt;ref name="wordpress2007"/&gt;

===1966===

* Twenty-eight women, among them [[Betty Friedan]], founded the [[National Organization for Women]] (NOW) to function as a [[civil rights organization]] for women. Betty Friedan became its first [[List of Presidents of the National Organization for Women|president]]. The group is now one of the largest women's groups in the U.S. and pursues its goals through extensive legislative lobbying, litigation, and public demonstrations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.now.org/organization/info.html |title=Information about NOW |publisher=Now.org |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Barbara Jordan was elected to the Texas Senate. She was the first African-American woman in the Texas legislature.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;TEXT_Allen, Ashley&lt;/ref&gt;

* Flight attendants filed Title VII complaints about being forced to quit when they married, got pregnant or reached age 35.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

===1967===

* Due to a new law, abortion in Britain was made legal under certain criteria and with medical supervision.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/1960.shtml |title=BBC Radio 4 - Woman's Hour - Women's History Timeline: 1960–1969 |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* American feminist [[Valerie Solanas]] wrote and published "[[SCUM Manifesto]]".&lt;ref&gt;Winkiel, Laura, The "Sweet Assassin" and the Performative Politics of SCUM Manifesto, in Smith, Patricia Juliana, ed., ''The Queer Sixties'' (N.Y.: Routledge, 1999 (ISBN 0-415-92169-4)), p. [62] (author, PhD from English department, University of Notre Dame, was research fellow, Center for the Humanities, Wesleyan University).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Castro, Ginette, trans. Elizabeth Loverde-Bagwell, American Feminism: A Contemporary History (N.Y.: N.Y. Univ. Press, 1990 (ISBN 0-8147-1448-X)), p. 264 (Chronology) (trans. from Radioscopie du féminisme américain (Paris, France: Presses de la Fondation Nationale des Sciences Politiques, 1984) (French)) (author prof. Eng. lang. &amp; culture, Univ. of Bordeaux III, France).&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Executive order (United States)|Executive Order]] 11375 expanded [[Lyndon B. Johnson|President Johnson]]'s 1965 [[affirmative action]] policy to cover discrimination based on sex, resulting in federal agencies and contractors taking active measures to ensure that all women as well as minorities have access to educational and employment opportunities equal to white males.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.archives.gov/federal-register/executive-orders/1967.html#11375 |title=Executive Orders Disposition Tables |publisher=Archives.gov |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Women’s liberation groups sprang up all over America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jofreeman.com/feminism/liberationmov.htm |title=The Women's Liberation Movement |publisher=Jofreeman.com |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[The pill]] makes the cover of ''[[Time (magazine)|TIME]]'' magazine&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/covers/0,16641,1101670407,00.html |title=TIME Magazine Cover: The Pill |publisher=Time.com |date=April 7, 1967 |accessdate=2010-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* NOW began petitioning the EEOC to end sex-segregated want ads and adopted a [[Bill of Rights]] for Women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.h-net.org/~hst203/documents/nowrights.html]{{dead link|date=October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Senator [[Eugene McCarthy]] introduced the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] in the U.S. Senate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.msu.edu/~harrow/ucad/Feminist-theory.htm |title=Feminist Theory |publisher=Msu.edu |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[New York Radical Women]] was formed by [[Shulamith Firestone]] and [[Chude Pam Allen|Pam Allen]].&lt;ref&gt;Maren Lockwood Carden, The New Feminist Movement (1974, Russell Sage Foundation)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Echols, Alice. Daring to be Bad: Radical Feminism in America&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://library.duke.edu/digitalcollections/wlmpc_wlmms01037/ |title=Notes from the First Year - Documents from the Women's Liberation Movement |publisher=Library.duke.edu |accessdate=2014-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Anne Koedt]] organized American "[[consciousness raising]]" groups.&lt;ref&gt;Feminist Revolution, p. 147–148&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [American] [[National Welfare Rights Organization]] was formed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackpast.org/?q=aah/national-welfare-rights-organization-1966-1975 |title=National Welfare Rights Organization (1966–1975) &amp;#124; The Black Past: Remembered and Reclaimed |publisher=The Black Past |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1968===

* [[Robin Morgan]] led members of [[New York Radical Women]] to [[No More Miss America|protest]] the [[Miss America|Miss America Pageant]] of 1968, which they decried as sexist and [[racism|racist]].&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jofreeman.com/photos/MissAm1968.html ]{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first American national gathering of women's liberation activists was held in [[Lake Villa, Illinois|Lake Villa]], a suburb of [[Chicago, Illinois]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kesselman |first=Amy |url=http://www.uic.edu/orgs/cwluherstory/CWLUMemoir/Kesselman.html |title=Our Gang of Four |publisher=Uic.edu |date=1973-01-01 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Coretta Scott King]] assumed leadership of the [[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1955–1968)|African-American Civil Rights Movement]] following the death of [[Martin Luther King, Jr.|her husband]], and expanded the movement's platform to include women's rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gale.cengage.com/free_resources/whm/bio/king_c_s.htm |title=Gale - Free Resources - Women's History - Biographies - Coretta Scott King |publisher=Gale.cengage.com |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The EEOC issued revised guidelines on sex discrimination, making it clear that the widespread practice of publishing "help wanted" advertisements that use "male" and "female" column headings violates Title VII.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eeoc.gov/eeoc/history/35th/milestones/1968.html |title=Milestones in the History of the U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission: 1968 |publisher=Eeoc.gov |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* New York feminists buried a dummy of "Traditional Womanhood" at the all-women's [[Jeannette Rankin]] Brigade demonstration against the [[Vietnam War]] in Washington, D.C.&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;
* For the first time, feminists used the slogan "Sisterhood is Powerful."&lt;ref name="about1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://womenshistory.about.com/od/feminism/a/sisterhood_is_powerful.htm |title=Sisterhood Is Powerful - The Influential Feminist Anthology Sisterhood Is Powerful |publisher=Womenshistory.about.com |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first public speakout against [[abortion]] laws was held in [[New York City]].&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;
* ''Notes from the First Year'', a women's liberation theoretical journal, was published by New York Radical Women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://library.duke.edu/digitalcollections/wlmpc_wlmms01037/|title=Notes from the First Year - Documents from the Women's Liberation Movement |publisher=Library.duke.edu |accessdate=2014-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* NOW celebrated [[Mother's Day]] with the slogan ''"Rights, Not Roses"''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.pl/books/about/Rights_not_roses.html?id=AJmwUNPU1McC&amp;redir_esc=y |title=Rights, Not Roses: Unions and the Rise of Working-Class Feminism, 1945-80 - Dennis Arthur Deslippe - Google Książki |publisher=Books.google.pl |date=1975-05-09 |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Mary Daly]], professor of theology at [[Boston College]], published a scathing criticism of the [[Catholic Church]]'s view and treatment of women entitled "The Church and the Second Sex."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/07/education/07daly.html?hpw | work=The New York Times | first=Margalit | last=Fox | title=Mary Daly, a Leader in Feminist Theology, Dies at 81 | date=January 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Germaine Greer|Greer, Germaine]], ''[[The Female Eunuch]]'' (N.Y.: McGraw-Hill, 1st ed. in U.S. 1971, © 1970 &amp; 1971), p. 306 ("The summer ... was ... momentous for the women's movement ... [partly] because Valerie Solanas shot Andy Warhol.... S.C.U.M. ... was big news, battling ... for the front page.").&lt;/ref&gt;
* 850 sewing machinists at [[Ford]] in [[Dagenham]], which is in Britain, went on [[1968 Ford sewing machinists strike|strike]] for equal pay and against sex discrimination. This ultimately led to the passing of the [[Equal Pay Act 1970]], the first legislation in the United Kingdom aimed at ending pay discrimination between men and women.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* According to [[Fred R. Shapiro]], the first time the term "sexism" appeared in print was in Caroline Bird's speech "On Being Born Female", which was published on November 15, 1968, in ''Vital Speeches of the Day'' (p.&amp;nbsp;6).&lt;ref name="wordpress2007"/&gt; In this speech she said in part, "There is recognition abroad that we are in many ways a sexist country. Sexism is judging people by their sex when sex doesn’t matter. Sexism is intended to rhyme with racism. Both have used to keep the powers that be in power."&lt;ref name="wordpress2007"/&gt;

===1969===

* The American [[Radical feminism|radical]] organization [[Redstockings]] organized.&lt;ref&gt;Willis, "Radical Feminism and Feminist Radicalism", p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Members of Redstockings disrupted a hearing on abortion laws of the New York Legislature when the panel of witnesses turned out to be 14 men and a nun. The group demanded repeal, not reform, of laws restricting abortion.&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;
* [[NARAL Pro-Choice America]], then called The National Association for the Repeal of Abortion Laws (NARAL), was founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oasis.lib.harvard.edu/oasis/deliver/~sch00781 |title=National Abortion Rights Action League. Records, 1968–1976: A Finding Aid |publisher=Oasis.lib.harvard.edu |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[California]] adopted a [[No-fault divorce|"no fault" divorce law]], allowing couples to divorce by mutual consent. It was the first state to do so; by 2010 every state had adopted a similar law. Legislation was also passed regarding equal division of common property.&lt;ref name="about1"/&gt;

[[File:Leffler - WomensLib1970 WashingtonDC.jpg|thumb|A Women's Liberation march in Washington, D.C., 1970]]

===1970===

* American feminist [[Kate Millett]] published her book, ''[[Sexual Politics]]''.&lt;ref&gt;P. T. Clough (1994)The Sociological Quarterly, vol 35 no 3, page 473 The Hybrid Criticism of Patriarchy: Rereading Kate Millett's "Sexual Politics"&lt;/ref&gt;
* Australian feminist [[Germaine Greer]] published her book, ''[[The Female Eunuch]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Wilde, W H; Hooton, Joy and Andrews, Barry (1994) [1985]. The Oxford companion to Australian Literature (2nd ed.). Melbourne: Oxford University Press. p. 271. ISBN 0-19-553381-X. "... the book became almost a sacred text for the international women's liberation movement of the 1970s, notwithstanding sporadic criticism of aspects of its ideology from some feminists."&lt;/ref&gt;
* In ''[[Schultz v. Wheaton Glass Co.]]'', a U.S. Court of Appeals ruled jobs held by men and women must be "substantially equal" but not "identical" to fall under the protection of the Equal Pay Act, and that it is therefore illegal for employers to change the job titles of women workers in order to pay them less than men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=14302099308500970559&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=2&amp;as_vis=1&amp;oi=scholarr |title=Schultz v. Wheaton Glass Co. |publisher=Scholar.google.com |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Sisterhood Is Powerful, An Anthology of Writings from the Women's Liberation Movement]]'' edited by the American feminist [[Robin Morgan]], is published.&lt;ref name="about1"/&gt;
* The American women's health book ''[[Our Bodies, Ourselves|Our Bodies]]'' was first published as a newsprint booklet for 35 cents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/17/books/review/17JACOBSL.html?adxnnl=1&amp;adxnnlx=1121694259-hrAJtKlnrchHW0dafaeuXw | work=The New York Times | first=Alexandra | last=Jacobs | title=A Feminist Classic Gets a Makeover | date=July 17, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A ''[[Ladies' Home Journal]]'' sit-in protested "[[List of women's magazines|women's magazines]]" as sexist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scripophily.stores.yahoo.net/curpubcom.html |title=Curtis Publishing Company (Saturday Evening Post &amp; Ladies Home Journal) |publisher=Scripophily.stores.yahoo.net |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[North American Indian Women's Association]] was founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.pl/books?id=jFY3CxmHk4cC&amp;pg=PA319&amp;dq=%22north+american+indian+women%27s+association%22+founded&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=18LwTrCaGobn0gGU55CqAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=book-thumbnail&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=%22north%20american%20indian%20women's%20association%22%20founded&amp;f=false |title=Chronology of Women's History - Kirstin Olsen - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.pl |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Chicana]] feminists founded [[Comisión Femenil Mexicana Nacional]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.library.ucsb.edu/speccoll/collections/cema/cfmn.html ]{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Italy]], [[Rivolta Femminile]] ("Women's Revolt") formed and published a manifesto.&lt;ref name="BondanellaBondanella2001"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Peter Bondanella|author2=Julia Conway Bondanella|author3=Jody Robin Shiffman|title=Cassell Dictionary of Italian Literature|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=_q9BAwI-11YC&amp;pg=PA207|date=1 January 2001|publisher=A&amp;C Black|isbn=978-0-304-70464-4|page=207}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* American feminist [[Toni Cade Bambara]] published ''The Black Woman''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=The Black Woman: An Anthology |url=http://www.amazon.com/Black-Woman-Toni-Cade-Bambara/dp/0743476972 |title=The Black Woman: An Anthology (9780743476973): Toni Cade Bambara, Eleanor W Traylor: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On August 26, 1970, the 50th anniversary of woman suffrage in the U.S., tens of thousands of women across the nation participated in the [[Women's Strike for Equality]], organized by Betty Friedan and thought up by [[Betty Jameson Armistead]] to demand equal rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/1093465/Womens-Strike-for-Equality |title=Women's Strike for Equality (American history) - Britannica Online Encyclopedia |publisher=Britannica.com |date=1970-08-26 |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=kpNarH7t9CkC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q=armistead&amp;f=false Feminists who Changed America, 1963-1975 - Google Books&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Feminist leader [[Bella Abzug]] was elected to the U.S. Congress, famously declaring "A woman's place is in the [[United States House of Representatives|House]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.pl/books?id=oIro7MtiFuYC&amp;pg=PA374&amp;redir_esc=y |title=Encyclopedia of Women's History in America - Kathryn Cullen-DuPont - Google Książki |publisher=Books.google.pl |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Richard Nixon|President Richard Nixon]] vetoed the [[Comprehensive Child Development Bill of 1972|Comprehensive Child Development Act]], which would have established federally funded [[childcare]] centers throughout the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenberg, Rosalind. Divided Lives: American Women in the Twentieth Century. New York: Hill and Wang, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[AFL-CIO]] met to discuss the status of women in unions. It endorsed the ERA and opposed state protective legislation.&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;
* The [[Lutheran Church]] in America and the [[American Lutheran Church]] allowed women to be ordained.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://floridaindependent.com/35887/national-right-to-life-conference-kicks-off-in-jacksonville |title=National Right to Life Convention kicks off in Jacksonville |publisher=Florida Independent |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The U.S. Congress enacted [[Title X]] of the Public Health Service Act, the only American federal program—then and now—devoted solely to the provision of family planning services nationwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/tgr/04/1/gr040105.html |title=Title X: Three Decades of Accomplishment |publisher=Guttmacher.org |date=2001-02-01 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first national meeting of the women's liberation movement in Britain took place at [[Ruskin College]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* The [[Equal Pay Act 1970]] became law in the United Kingdom, although it did not take effect until 1975.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* The [[Miss World]] contest in London was disrupted by feminist protesters armed with flour bombs, stink bombs, and water pistols.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;

===1971===

* Switzerland allowed women to vote in national elections. However, some cantons did not allow women to vote in local elections until 1994.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* The first women's liberation march in London occurred.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* In the U.S. Supreme Court Case [[Reed v Reed]], for the first time since the Fourteenth Amendment went into effect in 1868, the Court struck down a state law on the ground that it discriminated against women in violation of the Equal Protection Clause of that amendment. The law in question—enacted in Idaho in 1864—required that when the father and mother of a deceased person both sought appointment as administrator of the estate, the man had to be preferred over the woman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.supremecourthistory.org/learning-center/womens-rights/breaking-new-ground/ |title=The Supreme Court Historical Society - Learning Center - Women's Rights |publisher=Supremecourthistory.org |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Westbeth Playwrights Feminist Collective]] was founded in New York. It was one of the first feminist theater groups  formed to write and produce plays about women's issues and to provide work experience in theatrical professions which had been dominated by men.&lt;ref&gt;Rea, Charlotte, Women's Theatre Groups in The Drama Review, vol. 16, no 2, June 1972, pg 87.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lowell, Sondra, “New Feminist Theater,” Ms. Magazine, Aug. 1972. p. 17-21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnston, Laurie, “Sexism in Theater Can Be a Boon: At the Drama Desk Luncheon,” Theater Section, New York Times, February 8, 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The song "[[I Am Woman]]" was published. It was a popular song performed by Australian singer Helen Reddy, which became an enduring anthem for the women’s liberation movement.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2007"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Aso.gov.au"/&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated2003"/&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated257"/&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1981"/&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt;&lt;ref name="suntimes1"/&gt;
* [[Women's Equality Day]] has been August 26 in America since 1971.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nwhp.org/resourcecenter/equalityday.php |title=National Women's History Project |publisher=Nwhp.org |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; This resolution was passed in 1971 designating August 26 of each year as Women's Equality Day:

:The full text of the resolution reads:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;poem&gt;'''Joint Resolution of Congress, 1971 Designating August 26 of each year as Women's Equality Day

WHEREAS, the women of the United States have been treated as [[second-class citizen]]s and have not been entitled the full rights and privileges, public or private, legal or institutional, which are available to male citizens of the United States; and

WHEREAS, the women of the United States have united to assure that these rights and privileges are available to all citizens equally regardless of sex; and

WHEREAS, the women of the United States have designated August 26, the anniversary date of the passage of the Nineteenth Amendment, as symbol of the continued fight for equal rights: and

WHEREAS, the women of United States are to be commended and supported in their organizations and activities,

NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED, the Senate and House of Representatives of the United States of America in Congress assembled, that August 26 of each year is designated as "Women's Equality Day," and the President is authorized and requested to issue a proclamation annually in commemoration of that day in 1920, on which the women of America were first given the right to vote, and that day in 1970, on which a nationwide demonstration for women's rights took place.''' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.public.navy.mil/BUPERS-NPC/ORGANIZATION/BUPERS/WOMENSPOLICY/Pages/WomensEqualityDay.aspx |title=Women's Equality Day |publisher=Public.navy.mil |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/poem&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===1972===

* Britain's first feminist magazine, ''[[Spare Rib]]'', was launched by [[Marsha Rowe]] and [[Rosie Boycott]].
* Egyptian feminist [[Nawal El-Saadawi]] published her book ''[[Women and Sex]]''.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* Five formerly all-male colleges at [[Oxford University]] opened to women.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* American feminists [[Gloria Steinem]] and [[Letty Cottin Pogrebin]] co-founded [[Ms. (magazine)|Ms. magazine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msmagazine.com/about.asp |title=Ms magazine website |work=About Ms.|accessdate=August 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Steinem|first=Gloria|title=Who is Gloria?|url=http://www.gloriasteinem.com/who-is-gloria/|work=Gloria Steinem Official Website|accessdate=August 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Equal Rights Amendment]] was sent to the U.S. states for ratification. The amendment reads: "Equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of sex." &lt;ref name="equalrightsamendment.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/era.htm |title=History |publisher=Equalrightsamendment.org |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In ''[[Eisenstadt v. Baird]]'' the U.S. Supreme Court ruled that unmarried couples have a right to use contraception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oyez.org/cases/1970-1979/1971/1971_70_17 |title=Eisenstadt v. Baird &amp;#124; The Oyez Project at IIT Chicago-Kent College of Law |publisher=Oyez.org |date=1972-03-22 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Title IX]] of the [[Education Amendments of 1972]], became law. It is a comprehensive federal law that prohibits discrimination on the basis of sex in any federally funded education program or activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.justice.gov/crt/about/cor/coord/titleix.php |title=Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 |publisher=Justice.gov |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Educational Amendments of 1972 also amended the [[Fair Labor Standards Act]] to expand the coverage of the Equal Pay Act to executives, administrators, outside salespeople and professionals, by excluding the Equal Pay Act from the professional workers exemption of the Fair Labor Standards Act.{{Citation needed|date=November 2012}}
* The [American] [[National Women's Political Caucus]] was founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nwpc.org/history |title=History &amp;#124; National Women's Political Caucus |publisher=Nwpc.org |date=2012-09-02 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Gloria Steinem delivered her ''[[Address to the Women of America]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.com/speeches/gloria-steinem-addresses-the-nwpc#gloria-steinem-addresses-the-nwpc |title=Gloria Steinem Addresses the Women of America — History.com Audio |publisher=History.com |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[New York Radical Feminists]] held a series of speakouts and a conference on rape and women's treatment by the criminal justice system.&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;
* The Feminist Women's Health Center was founded in [[Los Angeles]] by [[Carol Downer]] and [[Lorraine Rothman]].&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;
* In [[San Francisco, California]], [[Margo St. James]] organized [[COYOTE|Call Off Your Old Tired Ethics]] (COYOTE) to improve the working conditions of prostitutes.&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;

===1973===

* Women are allowed on the floor of the [[London Stock Exchange]] for the first time.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* American tennis player [[Billie Jean King]] defeated [[Bobby Riggs]] in the "Battle of the Sexes" tennis match in 1973.  This match is remembered for its effect on society and its contribution to the women’s movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wtt.com/page.aspx?article_id=1252 |title=&gt; news |publisher=WTT |date=1943-11-22 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:STOP ERA.gif|thumb|Symbol used for signs and buttons by ERA opponents]]
* The [[Supreme Court of the United States]] ruled in ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'' that laws prohibiting abortion are unconstitutional.  States are constitutionally allowed to place regulations on abortion which fall short of prohibition after the first trimester.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0410_0113_ZS.html |title=Roe v. Wade |publisher=Law.cornell.edu |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The U.S. Supreme Court held that sex-segregated help wanted ads are illegal in [[Pittsburgh Press Co. v. Pittsburgh Commission on Human Relations]], 413 U.S. 376.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wearewoman.us/p/us-womens-rights-history.html |title=We Are Woman: Women's History |publisher=Wearewoman.us |date=2012-08-18 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* AT&amp;T agreed to end discrimination in women's salaries and to pay retroactive compensation to women employees.&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;
* The [American] National Black Feminist Organization was formed.&lt;ref name="uic.edu"/&gt;
* The term ''[[sexual harassment]]'' was used in 1973 in ''"Saturn's Rings"'', a report authored by Mary Rowe to the then President and Chancellor of MIT about various forms of gender issues.&lt;ref&gt;Rowe, Mary, "Saturn's Rings," a study of the minutiae of sexism which maintain discrimination and inhibit affirmative action results in corporations and non-profit institutions; published in Graduate and Professional Education of Women, American Association of University Women, 1974, pp.&amp;nbsp;1–9. "Saturn's Rings II" is a 1975 updating of the original, with racist and sexist incidents from 1974 and 1975. Revised and republished as "The Minutiae of Discrimination: The Need for Support," in Forisha, Barbara and Barbara Goldman, Outsiders on the Inside, Women in Organizations, Prentice-Hall, Inc., New Jersey, 1981, Ch. 11, pp.&amp;nbsp;155–171. ISBN 978-0-13-645382-6.&lt;/ref&gt; Rowe has stated that she believes she was not the first to use the term, since sexual harassment was being discussed in women's groups in Massachusetts in the early 1970s, but that MIT may have been the first or one of the first large organizations to discuss the topic (in the MIT Academic Council), and to develop relevant policies and procedures. MIT at the time also recognized the injuries caused by racial harassment and the harassment of women of color which may be both racial and sexual.

===1974===

* Contraception became free for women in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* ''[[Virago Press]]'', a British feminist press, was set up by the publisher [[Carmen Callil]]. Its first title, ''Life As We Have Known It'', was published in 1975.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* The [[Women's Aid Federation]] was set up to unite battered women's shelters in Britain.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* The [[Equal Credit Opportunity Act]] became law in the U.S. It prohibits discrimination in consumer credit practices on the basis of sex, race, marital status, religion, national origin, age, or receipt of public assistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://civilrights.uslegal.com/equal-credit-opportunity-act/ |title=Equal Credit Opportunity Act - Civil Rights |publisher=Civilrights.uslegal.com |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In ''[[Corning Glass Works v. Brennan]]'', the U.S. Supreme Court ruled that employers cannot justify paying women lower wages because that is what they traditionally received under the "going market rate." A wage differential occurring "simply because men would not work at the low rates paid women" is unacceptable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=case&amp;court=us&amp;vol=417&amp;invol=188 |title=FindLaw &amp;#124; Cases and Codes |publisher=Caselaw.lp.findlaw.com |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The U.S. First Lady [[Betty Ford]] was pro-choice.&lt;ref name="voices.yahoo.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://voices.yahoo.com/top-five-unique-interesting-facts-betty-8773121.html?cat=37 |title=Top Five Unique and Interesting Facts About Betty Ford - Yahoo! Voices |publisher=voices.yahoo.com |date=2006-07-14 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; A moderate [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]], Ford lobbied to ratify the ERA, earning the ire of [[conservative]]s, who dub her "No Lady".&lt;ref name="voices.yahoo.com"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Eleanor Smeal|url=http://articles.cnn.com/2011-07-09/opinion/smeal.betty.ford_1_betty-ford-equal-rights-amendment-era-vote?_s=PM:OPINION |title=Betty Ford, champion of women's rights - CNN |publisher=Articles.cnn.com |date=2011-07-09 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Mexican-American Women's National Association]] was founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nwhm.org/online-exhibits/coalition/11.htm |title=NWHM National Coalition Exhibit |publisher=Nwhm.org |date=2004-01-01 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The American Coalition of Labor Union Women was founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ufcw.org/womens_history_month/timeline/index.cfm |title=Timeline Index |publisher=UFCW |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Women's Educational Equity Act]] (WEEA) of 1974 was enacted in 1974 to promote educational equity for American girls and women, including those who suffer multiple discrimination based on gender and on race, ethnicity, national origin, disability, or age, and to provide funds to help education agencies and institutions meet the requirements of Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ed.gov/pubs/Biennial/125.html |title=Archived: Women's Educational Equity |publisher=.ed.gov |date=1999-09-30 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Dell Williams]] founded the first feminist [[sex toy]] business in the United States, [[Eve's Garden]], in [[New York City]] in 1974.)&lt;ref name="amazon1"&gt;{{cite web|author=Revolution in the Garden |url=http://www.amazon.com/Revolution-Garden-Dell-Williams/dp/1596370386 |title=Revolution in the Garden (9781596370388): Dell Williams, Lynn Vannucci: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |accessdate=2012-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="google1"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tOVlvvrMJhUC&amp;pg=PA117&amp;lpg=PA117&amp;dq=%22dell+williams%22+first+woman-oriented&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=tl3ozGah16&amp;sig=ZB3l2aAcam3hAXR7p7ostgGxqOI&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=2iOxUIzRO4yn0AH5m4CwAg&amp;ved=0CF4Q6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22dell%20williams%22%20first%20woman-oriented&amp;f=false |title=Hd Feminism 2ed(52) - Janet K. Boles, Janet K. Boles Diane Long Hoeveler - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |accessdate=2012-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="google1"/&gt; [[Eve's Garden]] was also the first woman-owned and woman-operated [[sex toy]] business in America.&lt;ref name="amazon1"/&gt;

===1975===

* The [[Equal Pay Act 1970]] took effect in the UK.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* The [[Sex Discrimination Act 1975]] became law in the UK, making it illegal to discriminate against women in education, recruitment, and advertising.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* The [[Employment Protection Act 1975]] became law in the UK, introducing statutory maternity provision and making it illegal to fire a woman because she is pregnant.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* In ''[[Taylor v. Louisiana]]'', the U.S. Supreme Court held that women could not be excluded from a ''venire'', or [[Jury duty|jury pool]], on the basis of having to register for jury duty, thus overturning ''[[Hoyt v. Florida]]'', the 1961 case that had allowed such a practice.&lt;ref name="www-rohan.sdsu.edu"&gt;[http://www-rohan.sdsu.edu/dept/wsweb/timeline.htm ]{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[United Nations|U.N.]] sponsored the First International Conference on Women in [[Mexico City]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Dz4wU64f_JYC&amp;pg=PA225&amp;lpg=PA225&amp;dq=%22%5BUnited+Nations%7CU.N.%5D%5D+sponsored+the+First+International+Conference+on+Women+in+%5B%5BMexico+City%5D%5D.%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=mGU8MoEM94&amp;sig=24TCK2-n9adV52XdO98uewMqbks&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=B0JmUIG6MbTI0AH9noGYDg&amp;ved=0CB0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22%5BUnited%20Nations%7CU.N.%5D%5D%20sponsored%20the%20First%20International%20Conference%20on%20Women%20in%20%5B%5BMexico%20City%5D%5D.%22&amp;f=false |title=The Concise Encyclopedia of Sociology - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* U.S. federal employees' salaries could be garnished for child support and alimony.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=467&amp;invol=822 |title=FindLaw &amp;#124; Cases and Codes |publisher=Caselaw.lp.findlaw.com |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tish Sommers]], chairwoman of NOW's Older Women Task Force, coined the phrase "displaced homemaker".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://feminist.org/research/chronicles/fc1975.html |title=The Feminist Chronicles, 1953–1993 – 1975 - Feminist Majority Foundation |publisher=Feminist.org |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* American feminist [[Susan Brownmiller]] published the landmark book ''[[Against Our Will]]'', about rape.&lt;ref name="susanbrownmiller.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.susanbrownmiller.com/susanbrownmiller/html/against_our_will.html |title=Against Our Will |publisher=Susanbrownmiller.com |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; She later became one of ''[[Time (magazine)|TIME]]'''s "Women of the Year" (see below).&lt;ref name="susanbrownmiller.com"/&gt;&lt;ref name="time.com"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,947597,00.html | work=Time | title=WOMEN OF THE YEAR: Great Changes, New Chances, Tough Choices | date=January 5, 1976 | accessdate=April 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* NOW sponsored "Alice Doesn't" Day, asking women across the country to go on strike for one day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.civilrights.uga.edu/cities/macon/now_strikes2.htm |title=Freedom On Film :: Civil Rights In Georgia |publisher=Civilrights.uga.edu |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Joan Little]], who was raped by a guard while in [[jail]], was [[acquittal|acquitted]] of murdering her offender. The case established a precedent in America for killing as [[self-defense]] against rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://testaae.greenwood.com/doc_print.aspx?fileID=C8337&amp;chapterID=C8337-1097&amp;path=books/greenwood |title=The African American Experience |publisher=Testaae.greenwood.com |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[New York City]], the first women's bank opened.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=ERIC PACEPublished: October 24, 2003 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/24/business/judy-h-mello-is-dead-at-60-executive-of-women-s-bank.html |title=Judy H. Mello Is Dead at 60; Executive of Women's Bank - New York Times |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=2003-10-24 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[United States armed forces]] opened its military academies to women.&lt;ref name="www-rohan.sdsu.edu"/&gt;
* ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' declared: "[F]eminism has transcended the feminist movement. In 1975 the women's drive penetrated every layer of society, matured beyond ideology to a new status of general—and sometimes unconscious—acceptance." The [[Time Person of the Year]] award goes to American Women, celebrating the successes of the feminist movement.&lt;ref name="time.com"/&gt;
* The [[Equal Opportunities Commission]] came into effect in the UK (besides Northern Ireland, where it came into effect in 1976) to oversee the Sex Discrimination and Equal Pay Acts.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;&lt;ref name="encyclo1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.encyclo.co.uk/define/Equal%20Opportunities%20Commission |title=Equal Opportunities Commission (Meaning of) |publisher=Encyclo.co.uk |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first "[[Take Back the Night]]" march was held.&lt;ref name="themaneater.com"&gt;[http://www.themaneater.com/stories/2010/9/22/students-take-back-night/ Students 'Take Back the Night' on Columbia streets – The Maneater&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="themaneater.com"/&gt; It was held in [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]] in October 1975, after the murder of a microbiologist, Susan Alexander Speeth, who was stabbed to death while walking home alone.&lt;ref name="themaneater.com"/&gt;&lt;ref name="themaneater.com"/&gt;

===1976===

* The [[Equal Opportunities Commission]] came into effect in Northern Ireland to oversee the Sex Discrimination and Equal Pay Acts.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;&lt;ref name="encyclo1"/&gt;
* The Domestic Violence Act became law in Britain, enabling women to obtain a court order against their violent husband or partner.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* The first marital rape law was enacted in [[Nebraska]], making it illegal for a husband to rape his wife.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trustblackwomen.org/2011-05-10-03-28-12/publications-a-articles/african-americans-and-abortion-articles/28-historical-timeline-of-reproductive-rights-in-the-united-states |title=Historical Timeline of Reproductive Rights in the United States |publisher=Trustblackwomen.org |date=2011-05-10 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Congresswoman [[Barbara Jordan|Barbara Charline Jordan]] of [[Texas]], the first African-American congresswoman to come from the Deep South and the first woman ever elected to the Texas Senate, who had received widespread recognition as a key member of the [[United States House Committee on the Judiciary|House Judiciary Committee]] during [[Richard Nixon|President Nixon]]'s impeachment, delivered the [[keynote|keynote address]] to the [[Democratic National Convention]].&lt;ref name="biography.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.biography.com/people/barbara-jordan-9357991 |title=Barbara Jordan Biography - Facts, Birthday, Life Story |publisher=Biography.com |date=1936-02-21 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="avoiceonline.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.avoiceonline.org/cbcwomen/jordan.html |title=Women of the CBC &gt; Barbara Jordan Biography |publisher=Avoiceonline.org |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was the first black person and first woman to address the convention as a keynote speaker, declaring that "My presence here . . . is one additional bit of evidence that the American dream need not forever be deferred." &lt;ref name="biography.com"/&gt;&lt;ref name="avoiceonline.org"/&gt;
* The [[Organization of Pan Asian American Women]] was formed for women of [[Asia]]n and [[Pacific Islander|Pacific American Islander]] descent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/440596/Organization-of-Pan-Asian-American-Women |title=Organization of Pan Asian American Women (American organization) - Britannica Online Encyclopedia |publisher=Britannica.com |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A "[[Reclaim the Night|Take Back the Night]]" march was held in Belgium in March 1976 by the women attending the [[International Tribunal on Crimes against Women]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.everything2.com/index.pl?node_id=720761|title=The International Tribunal on Crimes Against Women|publisher=everything2.com|accessdate=2013-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the state of [[Wisconsin]], [[Susan B. Anthony Day]] is an established state holiday, which was enacted into law April 15, 1976, from the 1975 Laws of Wisconsin, Chapter 307, section 20.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dpi.wi.gov/eis/observe.html|title=Wisconsin Public School Observance Days|publisher=|accessdate=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also a state holiday in West Virginia and Florida.

===1977===

* The [[Canadian Human Rights Act]] was passed, prohibiting discrimination based on characteristics including sex and sexual orientation, and requiring "equal pay for work of equal value." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/h-6/ |title=Canadian Human Rights Act |publisher=Laws-lois.justice.gc.ca |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the U.S., the first [[National Women's Conference]] in a century was held in [[Houston, Texas]]. Women from all over the country, 20,000 in all, gathered to pass a National Plan of Action.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/pwngq |title=NATIONAL WOMEN'S CONFERENCE, 1977 &amp;#124; The Handbook of Texas Online&amp;#124; Texas State Historical Association (TSHA) |publisher=Tshaonline.org |date=1977-11-27 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The National Association of Cuban-American Women was established.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nacaw-us.org/ |title=NACAW.ORG - Home Page |publisher=Nacaw-us.org |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first women pilots of the [[United States Air Force]] graduated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.afhso.af.mil/topics/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=15244 |title=Factsheets : Women's Airforce Service Pilots (WASP) |publisher=Afhso.af.mil |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[International Women's Day]] was formalized as an annual event by the U.N. General Assembly.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* The first Rape Crisis Centre opened in London.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;
* In a landmark ruling, the Washington Supreme Court, sitting [[en banc]], declared that [[Yvonne Wanrow]] was entitled to have a jury consider her actions in the light of her “perceptions of the situation, including those perceptions which were the product of our nation’s long and unfortunate history of sex discrimination.” &lt;ref name="ccrjustice.org"&gt;[http://ccrjustice.org/ourcases/past-cases/state-washington-v.-wanrow State of Washington v. Wanrow | Center for Constitutional Rights&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The ruling was the first in America recognizing the particular legal problems of women who defend themselves or their children from male attackers, and was again affirmed by the Washington Supreme Court in denying the prosecutor’s petition for rehearing in 1979.&lt;ref name="ccrjustice.org"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://faculty.law.miami.edu/zfenton/documents/Wanrow2.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Before the Wanrow decision, standard jury instructions asked what a "reasonably prudent man" would have done, even if the accused was a woman; the Wanrow decision set a precedent that when a woman is tried in a criminal trial the juries should ask "what a reasonably prudent woman similarly situated would have done." &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1314&amp;dat=19790428&amp;id=h_ZLAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Ce4DAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7221,6494620 The Spokesman-Review - Google News Archive Search&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===1978===

*The ''[[Oregon v. Rideout]]'' decision, in which Rideout was acquitted of raping his wife, led to many American states allowing prosecution for marital and cohabitation rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.enotes.com/american-court-cases/oregon-v-rideout |title=Oregon v. Rideout |publisher=eNotes.com |date=1978-12-27 |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Pregnancy Discrimination Act]] banned employment discrimination against pregnant women in the U.S., stating a woman cannot be fired or denied a job or a promotion because she is or may become pregnant, nor can she be forced to take a pregnancy leave if she is willing and able to work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eeoc.gov/laws/statutes/pregnancy.cfm |title=The Pregnancy Discrimination Act |publisher=Eeoc.gov |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Equal Rights Amendment's deadline arrived with the ERA still three states short of ratification; there was a successful bill to extend the ERA's deadline to 1982, but it was still not ratified by then.&lt;ref name="equalrightsamendment.org"/&gt;

===1979===

* [[Margaret Thatcher]] became the first female Prime Minister of the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/people/margaret_thatcher |title=BBC History - Margaret Thatcher |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The feminist art piece ''[[The Dinner Party]]'', by American feminist artist [[Judy Chicago]], was first put on display at the [[San Francisco Museum of Modern Art]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1960"/&gt;

===The 1980s===
* In the U.S., the early 1980s were marked by the end of the second wave and the beginning of the [[feminist sex wars]]. Many historians view the second-wave feminist era in America as ending in the early 1980s with the intra-feminism disputes of the feminist sex wars over issues such as sexuality and pornography, which ushered in the era of [[third-wave feminism]] in the early 1990s.&lt;ref name="Duggan"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Hansen"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Gerhard"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Leidholdt"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Vance"/&gt;
* The second wave began in the 1980s in [[Turkey]]&lt;ref&gt;Badran, Margot, ''Feminism in Islam: Secular and Religious Convergences'' (Oxford, Eng.: Oneworld, 2009 (ISBN 978-1-85168-556-1)), p. 227 (author sr. fellow, Ctr. for Muslim Christian Understanding, Georgetown Univ., U.S., &amp; fellow, Woodrow Wilson International Ctr. for Scholars, Washington, D.C.).&lt;/ref&gt; and in [[Israel]].&lt;ref&gt;Freedman, Marcia, ''Theorizing Israeli Feminism, 1970–2000'', in Misra, Kalpana, &amp; Melanie S. Rich, ''Jewish Feminism in Israel: Some Contemporary Perspectives'' (Hanover, N.H.: Univ. Press of New England (Brandeis Univ. Press) (Brandeis Ser. on Jewish Women), 1st ed. 2003 (ISBN 1-58465-325-6)), pp. 9–10 (author taught philosophy, Haifa Univ., &amp; women's studies, Oranim Teacher's Seminary, 2d-wave feminist leader, &amp; cofounder Women's Party, editor Kalpana Misra assoc. prof. pol. sci., Univ. of Tulsa, &amp; editor Melanie S. Rich psychologist &amp; chair, Partnership 2000 Women's Forum).&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] was enacted by the [[Canada Act]] of 1982, and it declares (among other things), "15. (1) Every individual is equal before and under the law and has the right to the equal protection and equal benefit of the law without discrimination and, in particular, without discrimination based on race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, sex, age or mental or physical disability. (2) Subsection (1) does not preclude any law, program or activity that has as its object the amelioration of conditions of disadvantaged individuals or groups including those that are disadvantaged because of race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, sex, age or mental or physical disability....28. Notwithstanding anything in this Charter, the rights and freedoms referred to in it are guaranteed equally to male and female persons." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.efc.ca/pages/law/charter/charter.text.html |title=Canadian Charter Of Rights And Freedoms |publisher=Efc.ca |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1983, the women's minister of France, [[Yvette Roudy]], passed a law obliging all companies with more than 50 employees to carry out a comparative salary survey between men and women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Jon Henley in Paris |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2005/may/11/gender.france |title=France tries again to give women equal pay &amp;#124; World news |publisher=The Guardian |date= 2005-05-11|accessdate=2012-10-31 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Japanese Equal Employment Opportunity Law of 1985, effective in April 1986, prohibits gender discrimination with respect to recruitment, hiring, promotion, training, and job assignment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/2523634?uid=3739256&amp;uid=2129&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=70&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21101217225471|title=Equal Employment Opportunities in Japan: A View From The West|author=Linda N. Edwards|publisher=Jstor.org|accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==

===Title IX===
{{Main|Title IX}}

===Coeducation===
One debate which developed in the [[United States]] during this time period revolved around the question of [[coeducation]]. Most [[men's colleges in the United States]] adopted coeducation, often by merging with [[Women's colleges in the United States|women's colleges]]. In addition, some women's colleges adopted coeducation, while others maintained a single-sex student body.

====Seven Sisters Colleges====
Two of the [[Seven Sisters (colleges)|Seven Sister colleges]] made transitions during and after the 1960s. The first, [[Radcliffe College]], merged with [[Harvard University]]. Beginning in 1963, students at Radcliffe received Harvard diplomas signed by the presidents of Radcliffe and Harvard and joint commencement exercises began in 1970. The same year, several Harvard and Radcliffe dormitories began swapping students experimentally and in 1972 full co-residence was instituted. The departments of [[College athletics|athletics]] of both schools merged shortly thereafter. In 1977, Harvard and Radcliffe signed an agreement which put undergraduate women entirely in Harvard College. In 1999 Radcliffe College was dissolved and Harvard University assumed full responsibility over the affairs of female undergraduates. Radcliffe is now the ''Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study'' in [[women's studies|Women's Studies]] at Harvard University.

The second, [[Vassar College]], declined an offer to merge with [[Yale University]] and instead became coeducational in 1969.

The remaining Seven Sisters decided against coeducation. [[Mount Holyoke College]] engaged in a lengthy debate under the presidency of [[David Truman]] over the issue of coeducation. On November 6, 1971, "after reviewing an exhaustive study on coeducation, the board of trustees decided unanimously that Mount Holyoke should remain a women's college, and a group of faculty was charged with recommending curricular changes that would support the decision."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.mtholyoke.edu/cic/about/detailed.shtml|title=Mount Holyoke:A Detailed History|publisher=mtholyoke.edu|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Smith College]] also made a similar decision in 1971.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.smith.edu/collegerelations/presidents.php|title=Smith Tradition|publisher=smith.edu|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1969, [[Bryn Mawr College]] and [[Haverford College]] (then all male) developed a system of sharing residential colleges. When Haverford became coeducational in 1980, Bryn Mawr discussed the possibly of coeducation as well, but decided against it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.brynmawr.edu/visit/history.shtml|title=A Brief history of Bryn Mawr College|publisher=brynmawr.edu|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1983, [[Columbia University]] began admitting women after a decade of failed negotiations with [[Barnard College]] for a merger along the lines of Harvard and Radcliffe (Barnard has been affiliated with Columbia since 1900, but it continues to be independently governed). [[Wellesley College]] also decided against coeducation during this time.

====Mississippi University for Women====
In 1982, in a 5–4 decision, the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] ruled in ''[[Mississippi University for Women v. Hogan]]'' that the [[Mississippi University for Women]] would be in violation of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]]'s [[Equal Protection Clause]] if it denied admission to its nursing program on the basis of gender. Mississippi University for Women, the first [[Public university|public or government institution]] [[Women's colleges in the United States|for women in the United States]], changed its admissions policies and became coeducational after the ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mississippi.edu/universities/ |title=Mississippi Public Universities - Mississippi's University System |publisher=Mississippi.edu |date=1925-09-15 |accessdate=2012-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In what was her first opinion written for the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]], [[Sandra Day O'Connor|Justice Sandra Day O'Connor]] stated, "In limited circumstances, a gender-based classification favoring one sex can be justified if it intentionally and directly assists members of the sex that is disproportionately burdened."  She went on to point out that there are a disproportionate number of women who are nurses, and that denying admission to men "lends credibility to the old view that women, not men, should become nurses, and makes the assumption that nursing is a field for women a [[self-fulfilling prophecy]]".&lt;ref&gt;"[[Mississippi University for Women v. Hogan]]", 458 U.S. 718 (1982)&lt;/ref&gt;

In the dissenting opinions, Justices [[Harry A. Blackmun]], [[Warren E. Burger]], [[Lewis F. Powell, Jr.]], and [[William H. Rehnquist]] suggested that the result of this ruling would be the elimination of publicly supported single-sex educational opportunities. This suggestion has proven to be accurate as there are no public women's colleges in the United States today and, as a result of ''[[United States v. Virginia]]'', the last all-male public university in the United States, [[Virginia Military Institute]], was required to admit women. The ruling did not require the university to change its name to reflect its [[Mixed-sex education|coeducational status]] and it continues a tradition of academic and leadership development for women by providing [[liberal arts]] and professional education to women and men.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muw.edu/pie/vision.html MUW - Planning and Institutional Effectiveness]{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Mills College====
On May 3, 1990, the Trustees of [[Mills College]] announced that they had voted to admit male students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F30610F73C540C778CDDAC0894D8494D81 |title=Venerable School for Women Is Going Co-ed |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=1990-05-04|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; This decision led to a two-week student and staff [[Strike action|strike]], accompanied by numerous displays of [[Nonviolence|non-violent]] protests by the students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DE1738F936A35756C0A966958260 |title=Mills Students Protesting Admission of Men |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=1990-05-05|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F30616FC355E0C758CDDAC0894D8494D81 |title=Disbelieving and Defiant, Students Vow: No Men |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=1990-05-06| first=Katherine | last=Bishop | accessdate=April 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; At one point, nearly 300 students blockaded the administrative offices and boycotted classes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DE133EF93BA35756C0A966958260|title=Protest Continues at College Over Decision to Admit Men |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=1990-05-08|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; On May 18, the Trustees met again to reconsider the decision,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DA1130F931A25756C0A966958260 |title=College to Reconsider Decision to Admit Men |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=1990-05-12|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; leading finally to a reversal of the vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F30616F63C550C7A8DDDAC0894D8494D81 |title=Women's College Rescinds Its Decision to Admit Men |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=1990-05-19| first=Katherine | last=Bishop | accessdate=April 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other colleges====
[[Pembroke College (Brown University)|Pembroke College]] merged with [[Brown University]]. [[Sarah Lawrence College]] declined an offer to merge with [[Princeton University]], becoming coeducational in 1969.{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}} [[Connecticut College]] also adopted coeducation during the late 1960s.
[[Wells College]], previously with a student body of women only, became co-educational in 2005. Douglass College, part of [[Rutgers University]], was the last publicly funded women's only college until 2007 when it became coed.

===''Feminists Who Changed America 1963-1975''===
In 1996 [[Barbara Love]] began a project to write biographies of 2,200 second-wave feminists and record the important events from that period, which was published in the book ''Feminists Who Changed America 1963-1975.'' It was published in 2006 by University of Illinois Press.&lt;ref name="VFA"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.vfa.us/BARBARA%20LOVE.htm | title=Barbara Love, Feminist of the Month - October 2009 | publisher=Veteran Feminists of American | date=October 2009 | accessdate=September 6, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=[[Barbara Love]]|title=Feminists who Changed America, 1963-1975|year=2006|publisher=University of Illinois Press|isbn=978-0-252-03189-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Love is collecting information about feminists that were not included in the book for a supplement or next edition.&lt;ref name="VFA" /&gt;

==See also==
*[[American philosophy]]
*[[Feminism in 1950s Britain]]
*[[First-wave feminism]]
*[[History of feminism]]
*[[PaVEM]]
*[[Pro-life feminism]]
*[[Third-wave feminism]]
*[[Timeline of women's rights (other than voting)]]
*[[Timeline of women's suffrage]]
*[[List of feminists]]
*[[List of women's rights activists]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Boxer, Marilyn J. Jean H. Quataert, and Joan W. Scott, eds. ''Connecting Spheres: European Women in a Globalizing World, 1500 to the Present'' (2000),
* [[Nancy F. Cott|Cott, Nancy]]. ''No Small Courage: A History of Women in the United States''  (2004)
* Freedman,  Estelle B. ''No Turning Back: The History of Feminism and the Future of Women'' (2003)
* MacLean, Nancy. ''The American Women's Movement, 1945–2000: A Brief History with Documents'' (2008)
* Offen, Karen; Pierson, Ruth Roach; and Rendall, Jane, eds. ''Writing Women's History: International Perspectives'' (1991)
* Prentice, Alison and Trofimenkoff, Susan Mann, eds. ''The Neglected Majority: Essays in Canadian Women's History'' (2 vol 1985)
* Ramusack, Barbara N., and Sharon Sievers, eds. ''Women in Asia: Restoring Women to History'' (1999)
* Rosen, Ruth. ''The World Split Open: How the Modern Women's Movement Changed America'' (2nd ed. 2006)
* Roth, Benita. ''Separate Roads to Feminism: Black, Chicana, and White Feminist Movements in America's Second Wave.'' Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2004.
* Stansell, Christine. ''The Feminist Promise: 1792 to the Present'' (2010)
* Thébaud, Françoise. "Writing Women's and Gender History in France: A National Narrative?" ''Journal of Women's History,'' Spring 2007, Vol. 19 Issue 1, pp 167–172.
* Zophy, Angela Howard, ed. ''Handbook of American Women's History'' (2nd ed. 2000)

{{Second-wave feminism}}
{{Feminism}}
{{United States topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Feminist Movement In The United States}}
[[Category:Counterculture of the 1960s]]
[[Category:Feminism and history]]
[[Category:Women in history]]
[[Category:Feminist movements and ideologies]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1964–80)]]
[[Category:History of women in the United States]]
[[Category:History of women's rights in the United States]]
[[Category:Second-wave feminism| ]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]

[[de:Feminismus#Zweite Welle des Feminismus]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>