<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050922004259|23715284" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="631216" pageid="631216" ns="0" title="Second-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-23T18:23:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''''Second-wave feminism''''' refers to a period of [[feminist]] thought that originated around the [[1960s]] and was mainly concerned with independence and greater political action to improve women's rights.

The second-wave [[feminist movement]] was most concerned with items such as economic equality between the genders and addressing the rights of female minorities rather than absolute rights such as suffrage, as first wave feminism had. One phenomenon included the recognition of [[lesbian]] women within the movement. Lesbians had an ambiguous relationship with other, generally heterosexual-oriented feminist groups. Many feminists did not want to be associated with lesbians because of the stereotypes of "mannish" lesbians that predominated at the time. As a result many feminist groups felt betrayed and rejected by straight women, claiming that heterosexual sexual relationships automatically subordinated women, and that the only true independence could come in lesbian relationships ("[[lesbian separatism]]").

The second wave is most commonly linked with the [[radical feminism|radical feminist]] theory. 

==The rise of intentional communities==

One interesting and underdocumented aspect of the second-wave was the rise of  women's cooperative living communities. An example of one such intentional community was the [[Chatanika River Women's Colony]].

==Second-wave feminists==

*[[Bella Abzug]]
*[[Gloria E. Anzaldúa]]
*[[Simone de Beauvoir]]
*[[Lorraine Bethel]]
*[[Susan Brownmiller]]
*[[Charlotte Bunch]]
*[[Thérèse Casgrain]]
*[[Mary Daly]]
*[[Angela Davis]]
*[[Heather Dean]]
*[[Andrea Dworkin]]
*[[Susan Faludi]]
*[[Shulamith Firestone]]
*[[Jo Freeman]]
*[[Marilyn French]]
*[[Betty Friedan]]
*[[Carol Gilligan]]
*[[Germaine Greer]]
*[[Carol Hanisch]]
*[[Donna Haraway]]
*[[Nancy Hartsock]]
*[[Dorothy Hewett]]
*[[bell hooks]]
*[[Bonnie Kreps]]
*[[Jacqueline Livingston]]
*[[Catharine MacKinnon]]
*[[Kate Millett]]
*[[Cherrie Moraga]]
*[[Robin Morgan]]
*[[Bernice Johnson Reagon]]
*[[Erin Pizzey]]
*[[Sheila Rowbotham]]
*[[Margaret Sanger]]
*[[Kathie Sarachild]]
*[[Alice Schwarzer]]
*[[Gloria Steinem]]
*[[Betsy Warrior]]
&lt;!--please remember to insert alphabetically--&gt;

See also [[list of feminists]].

==See also==

* [[first-wave feminism]]
* [[third-wave feminism]]

[[Category:Feminism]]

[[el:Φεμινισμός δεύτερου κύματος]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>