<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171120013628|811185642" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="4663436" pageid="4663436" ns="0" title="Lavender Scare"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-20T03:28:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:McCarthy Cohn.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|[[Joseph McCarthy]] and [[Roy Cohn]] during the [[Army-McCarthy hearings]]]]
The '''lavender scare''' refers to a [[moral panic|witch hunt]] and the mass firings of homosexual people in the 1950s from the United States government. It paralleled the [[Anti-communism|anti-communist]] campaign known as [[McCarthyism]] and the [[McCarthyism|Second Red Scare]]. Gay men and lesbians were said to be security risks and communist sympathizers, which led to the call to remove them from state employment.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Lavender Scare|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=Chicago University Press|year=2004|isbn=9780226401904|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Former U.S. Senator [[Alan K. Simpson]] has written: "The so-called 'Red Scare' has been the main focus of most historians of that period of time. A lesser-known element ... and one that harmed far more people was the witch-hunt McCarthy and others conducted against homosexuals."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Simpson|first=Alan K. |chapter=Prologue |title=Dying for Joe McCarthy's Sins: The Suicide of Wyoming Senator Lester Hunt |first2=Rodger |last2=McDaniel |publisher=WordsWorth Press |year=2013|page=x |isbn= 978-0983027591}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
The term for this persecution was popularized by David K. Johnson's 2004 book which studied this anti-homosexual campaign, ''The Lavender Scare.'' The book drew its title from the term "[[lavender (color)|lavender]] lads", used repeatedly by Senator [[Everett Dirksen]] as a synonym for homosexual males. In 1952, Dirksen said that a [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] victory in the November elections would mean the removal of "the lavender lads" from the [[State Department]].&lt;ref&gt;Stephen J. Whitfield, ''The Culture of the Cold War'', 2nd ed. (Johns Hopkins University Press, 1996), p. 44; Byron C. Hulsey, ''Everett Dirksen and his Presidents: How a Senate Giant Shaped American Politics'' (University Press of Kansas, 2000), 48–9&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase was also used by ''[[Confidential (magazine)|Confidential]]'' magazine, a periodical known for gossiping about the sexuality of politicians and prominent Hollywood stars.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Bernstein, "Lavender Lads Bartone Babes", ''[[The Advocate]]'', February 27, 2007. On the association of a variety colors with homosexuality, see Venetia Newall, "Folklore and Male Homosexuality", ''Folklore'', vol. 97, no. 2, 1986, 126&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
In 1950, the same year that Senator [[Joseph McCarthy]] claimed 205 communists were working in the [[United States Department of State|State Department]], [[Undersecretary]] of State [[John Peurifoy]] said that the State Department had allowed 91 homosexuals to resign.&lt;ref&gt;Representative [[Arthur L. Miller|Miller]] ([[Nebraska|NE]]). [http://www.writing.upenn.edu/~afilreis/50s/gays-in-govt.html "Homosexuals in Government."] ''Congressional Record'' 96:4 (March 29, 1950), H4527&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |title=THAILAND: Smiling Jack |url=http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,807544,00.html |date=August 22, 1955}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 19, 1950, the Republican National Chairman [[Guy George Gabrielson]] said that "sexual perverts who have infiltrated our Government in recent years" were "perhaps as dangerous as the actual Communists".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9D01E7DD153DE03BBC4152DFB266838B649EDE|title=Perverts Called Government peril|date=April 19, 1950}}&lt;/ref&gt; The danger was not solely because they were gay though. The homosexuals were considered to be more susceptible to blackmail and thus were labeled as security risks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.dailykos.com/story/2012/2/28/1069129/-Today-in-history-State-Department-reveals-purge-of-91-homosexuals|title=Today in history: State Department reveals purge of 91 homosexuals|website=Daily Kos|access-date=2016-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; McCarthy hired [[Roy Cohn]]{{Em dash}}who died of [[AIDS]] and was accused of being a [[closeted]] homosexual&lt;ref&gt;[http://partners.nytimes.com/library/national/science/aids/080386sci-aids.html The New York Times]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.maryellenmark.com/text/magazines/life/905W-000-035.html|title=Life Magazine - The Snarling Death of Roy M. Cohn - 905w-000-035|author=Nicholas von Hoffman|date=March 1988|work=maryellenmark.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Em dash}}as chief counsel of his Congressional subcommittee. Together, McCarthy and Cohn{{Em dash}}with the enthusiastic support of the head of the [[FBI]], [[J. Edgar Hoover]]{{Em dash}}were responsible for the firing of scores of gay men and women from government employment and strong-armed many opponents into silence using rumors of their homosexuality.&lt;ref name="johnson"&gt;{{cite book|title=The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=2004|at=22|ISBN=0-226-40190-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rodger McDaniel, ''Dying for Joe McCarthy's Sins: The Suicide of Wyoming Senator Lester Hunt'' (WordsWorth, 2013), {{ISBN|978-0983027591}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=May 20, 1950|accessdate= December 29, 2014|url=https://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive/pdf?res=9A03E5D91338E532A25753C2A9639C946192D6CF |title=Inquiry by Senate on Perverts Asked|work=New York Times|first=William S.|last=White}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1953, during the final months of the Truman administration, the State Department reported that it had fired 425 employees for allegations of homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://williamsinstitute.law.ucla.edu/wp-content/uploads/5_History.pdf|title=The Legacy of Discriminatory State Laws, Policies, and Practices, 1945-Present |publisher=Williams Institute, UCLA}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=126 Perverts Discharged |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=980CE7D8123BE23BBC4E51DFB5668389649EDEE |date=March 26, 1952|work=New York Times|accessdate=December 29, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1418&amp;context=uhm Berard, Lauren B., "Something Changed: The Social and Legal Status of Homosexuality in America as Reported by ''The New York Times''" (2014). Honors Theses. Paper 357.]&lt;/ref&gt;

McCarthy often used accusations of homosexuality as a [[smear tactic]] in his anti-communist crusade, often combining the [[Second Red Scare]] with the Lavender Scare.  On one occasion, he went so far as to announce to reporters, "If you want to be against McCarthy, boys, you've got to be either a Communist or a cocksucker."&lt;ref&gt;Cuordileone, K.A.  "'Politics in an Age of Anxiety': Cold War Political Culture and the Crisis in American Masculinity, 1949-1960"  ''The Journal of American History'' 87 (2) (2000): 515-545&lt;/ref&gt; At least one recent history has argued that, in linking communism and homosexuality and psychological imbalance, McCarthy was employing guilt-by-association if evidence for communist activity was lacking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first1=Joy |last1=Damousi|first2=Mariano Ben |last2=Plotkin|title=Psychoanalysis and Politics: Histories of Psychoanalysis Under Conditions of Restricted Political Freedom|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RhhpAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA221|date=5 January 2012|publisher=Oxford University Press, USA|isbn=978-0-19-992316-8|page=221}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Executive Order 10450 ===
In 1953 [[Dwight D. Eisenhower|President Dwight D. Eisenhower]] signed [[Executive Order 10450]], which set security standards for federal employment and barred homosexuals from working in the federal government. The restrictions set in place were cause for hundreds of homosexuals to be exposed as gay and fired from the State Department. The executive order was also the cause for the firing of approximately 5,000 homosexuals from federal employment; this included private contractors and military personnel. Not only did the victims lose their jobs, but also they were forced out of the closet and thrust into the public eye as homosexuals. Executive Order 10450 stayed on paper and in effect until 1995 when [[Bill Clinton|President Bill Clinton]] rescinded the order and put in place the "[[Don't ask, don't tell]]" policy for admittance of gays into the military.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://thinkprogress.org/lgbt/2011/08/05/288942/clinton-issued-order-letting-gays-get-security-clearances-16-years-ago-today/|title=Clinton Issued Order Letting Gays Get Security Clearances 16 Years Ago Today|website=ThinkProgress|access-date=2016-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Association of communism with "subversives" ===
Both homosexuals and Communist Party members were seen as subversive elements in American society who all shared the same ideals of [[antitheism]], rejection of [[Bourgeoisie#Bourgeois culture|bourgeois culture]] and middle-class morality, lack of conformity; they were scheming and manipulative and, most importantly, would put their own agendas above others in the eyes of the general population.&lt;ref name="glbtq.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtqarchive.com/ssh/mccarthyism_S.pdf|title=McCarthyism|last=Prono|first=Luca|date=|website=|publisher=[[glbtq.com]]|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; McCarthy also associated homosexuality and communism as "threats to the 'American way of life'."&lt;ref&gt;Carlson, Dennis. "Gayness, multicultural education, and community." [https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=K2_VMQyk-ZMC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA233 Beyond black and white: New faces and voices in the U.S. Schools] (1997): 233-256.&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexuality was directly linked to security concerns, and more government employees were dismissed because of their homosexual [[sexual orientation]] than because they were left-leaning or communist. George Chauncey noted that, "The specter of the invisible homosexual, like that of the invisible communist, haunted Cold War America," and homosexuality (and by implication homosexuals themselves) were constantly referred to not only as a disease, but also as an invasion, like the perceived danger of communism and subversives.&lt;ref&gt;Field, Douglas, ed. [https://books.google.com/books?id=DztQtydwimMC American cold war culture]. Edinburgh University Press, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Senator [[Kenneth S. Wherry|Kenneth Wherry]] similarly attempted to invoke a connection between homosexuality and [[anti-nationalism]]. He said in an interview with [[Max Lerner]] that "You can't hardly separate homosexuals from subversives."  Later in that same interview, he drew the line between patriotic Americans and gay men: "But look Lerner, we're both Americans, aren't we?  I say, let's get these fellows [closeted gay men in government positions] out of the government."&lt;ref&gt;Lerner, Max, ''The Unfinished Country: A Book of American Symbols'' Simon and Schuster, 1959 pp 313-316&lt;/ref&gt;

Connections between gay rights groups and so-called subversive elements were not entirely baseless. The [[Mattachine Society]], one of the earliest gay rights groups in the United States, was founded by [[Harry Hay]], a former member of the [[Communist Party USA]], who resigned when the membership condemned his politics as a threat to the organization he had founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Lillian Faderman|author2=Stuart Timmons|title=Gay L.A.: A History of Sexual Outlaws, Power Politics, and Lipstick Lesbians |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=I5SVsJmVxDUC&amp;pg=PA113|year=2006|publisher=Basic Books |isbn=978-0-465-02288-5 |page=113 |accessdate=May 8, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Subcommittee on Investigations ===
The Subcommittee on Investigations was a subcommittee of the [[U.S. Senate Committee on Expenditures in Executive Departments|Committee on Expenditures in Executive Departments]]. This subcommittee led by Senator [[Clyde R. Hoey]] from 1949-1952  investigated "the employment of homosexuals in the Federal workforce."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://catalog.archives.gov/id/28748701|title=Executive Session Hearing of the Subcommittee on Investigations|last=|first=|date=1950|website=National Archives and Record Administration|publisher=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A related report, known as the Hoey Report, stated that all of the government's intelligence agencies "are in complete agreement that sex perverts in Government constitute security risks."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=University of Chicago|year=2004|isbn=0-226-40481-1|location=Chicago|pages=114–5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Contemporary views of homosexuality ===
Washington D.C. had a fairly large and active gay community before McCarthy launched his witch hunt campaign against homosexuals, but as time went on and the climate of the Cold War spread, so too did the negative views of homosexuals.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Because social attitudes toward homosexuality were overwhelmingly negative and the psychiatric community regarded homosexuality as a [[mental disorder]], [[gay]] men and [[lesbian]]s were considered susceptible to [[blackmail]], thus constituting a security risk. U.S. government officials assumed that [[Communism|communists]] would blackmail homosexual employees of the federal government to provide them classified information rather than risk exposure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |work=Gay Today |url=http://gaytoday.com/interview/010104in.asp |title=Historian David K. Johnson: Exposes the U.S. Government's Anti-Gay Crusades |first=Raj |last=Ayyar |accessdate=May 8, 2015|date=January 1, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1957 [[Crittenden Report]] of the [[United States Navy]] [[Public inquiry|Board of Inquiry]] concluded that there was "no sound basis for the belief that homosexuals posed a security risk" and criticized the prior Hoey Report: "No intelligence agency, as far as can be learned, adduced any factual data before that committee with which to support these opinions" and said that "the concept that homosexuals necessarily pose a security risk is unsupported by adequate factual data."&lt;ref&gt;Bérubé, 282. The Report is dated December 21, 1956, to March 15, 1957.&lt;/ref&gt; The Crittenden Report remained secret until 1976. Navy officials claimed they had no record of studies of homosexuality, but attorneys learned of its existence and obtained it through a [[Freedom of Information Act (United States)|Freedom of Information Act]] request.&lt;ref&gt;Gibson, 356-67; Bérubé, 278&lt;/ref&gt; As of September 1981, the Navy claimed it was still unable to fulfill a request for the Report's supporting documentation.&lt;ref&gt;Bérubé, 283; Haggerty, 45n38&lt;/ref&gt;

According to John Loughery, author of a study of gay identity in the 20th century, "few events indicate how psychologically wracked America was becoming in the 1950s ... than the presumed overlap of the Communist and the homosexual menace."&lt;ref name=glbtq.com/&gt;

The research of [[Evelyn Hooker]], presented in 1956, and the first conducted without a polluted sample (gay men who had been treated for mental illness) dispelled the [[illusory correlation]] between homosexuality and mental illness that prior research, conducted with polluted sampling, had established. Hooker presented a team of three expert evaluators with 60 unmarked psychological profiles from her year of research. She chose to leave the interpretation of her results to others, to avoid potential bias. The evaluators concluded that in terms of adjustment, there were no differences between the members of each group. Her demonstration that it is not an illness led the way to the eventual removal of homosexuality from the [[American Psychiatric Association]]'s [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]].&lt;ref name="ucd"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/hooker2.html#biography | title=Evelyn Hooker, Ph.D.: September 2, 1907 – November 18, 1996 | publisher=UC Davis | accessdate=April 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Resistance ==
One of the first and most influential members of the gay rights movements, [[Frank Kameny]], was thrust into unemployment because of his sexual orientation in 1957. He was working as an astronomer for the United States Army Map Service, but was fired as a result of the Lavender Scare and could never find another job in the United States federal government again. This led to Kameny devoting his life to the [[LGBT social movements|gay rights movement]], which in some ways he began. In 1965, 4 years before the [[Stonewall riots|Stonewall Riots]], Kameny picketed the White House on the grounds of gay rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://notevenpast.org/lavender-scare-cold-war-persecution-gays-and-lesbians-federal-government-2006/|title=The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government by David K. Johnson (2006)|website=notevenpast.org|access-date=2016-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Lillian Faderman, the [[LGBT community]] formed a [[subculture]] of its own in this era, constituting "not only a choice of sexual orientation, but of social orientation as well." The [[Mattachine Society]] and the [[Daughters of Bilitis]], which formed the [[homophile]] movements of the U.S., were in many ways defined by McCarthyism and the lavender scare.{{Citation needed|date=November 2016}} They were underground organizations that maintained the anonymity of their members.&lt;ref name="glbtq.com" /&gt;

== Legacy ==
Though the main vein of McCarthyism ended in the mid-1950s when the 1956 ''Cole v Young'' ruling severely weakened the ability to fire people from the federal government for discriminatory reasons,&lt;ref&gt;https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/351/536/&lt;/ref&gt; the movement that was born from it, the Lavender Scare, lived on. One such way was that Executive Order 10450, which was not rescinded until 1995, continued to bar gays from entering the military.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Another form of the Lavender Scare that persisted was the [[Florida Legislative Investigation Committee]], also referred to as the FLIC and the Johns Committee. The FLIC was founded in 1956 and was not disbanded until 1964. The purpose of the committee was to operate within Florida continuing the work of the Lavender Scare by investigating and firing public school teachers that were gay. During its active years the FLIC was responsible for more than 200 firings of alleged gay teachers. The FLIC was disbanded following the release of the [[Homosexuality and Citizenship in Florida|Purple Pamphlet]] due to public outrage over its explicit and pornographic nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://riches.cah.ucf.edu/committee/history.php|title=The Committee Documentary|website=riches.cah.ucf.edu|access-date=2016-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2017, the State Department formally apologized.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/state-department-apologizes-lavender-scare-180961746/ "State Department Apologizes for the "Lavender Scare"], Jason Daley. Smithsonian. January 10, 2017. Retrieved 5 feb 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

==Documentary==
''The Lavender Scare,'' directed by Josh Howard, is a documentary film that recounts the events of the Lavender Scare. David K. Johnson is part of the project as the movie is based on his book.  To help with funding, Josh Howard created a Kickstarter that met its goal in donations. The film was completed in 2016 and began screenings in film festivals around the country. The schedule is available at www.thelavenderscare.com.

==See also==
{{div col|col width=30em}}
* ''[[Advise and Consent]]''
* [[Joseph Alsop]]
* [[Blue discharge]]
* [[Boise homosexuality scandal]]
* [[Civil Service Reform Act of 1978]]
* [[Executive Order 10450]]
* [[Executive Order 11478]]
* [[Executive Order 13087]]
* [[Florida Legislative Investigation Committee]]
* [[Fruit machine (homosexuality test)]]
* [[Gays and Lesbians in Foreign Affairs Agencies]]
* ''[[Homosexuality and Citizenship in Florida]]''
* [[Frank Kameny]]
* [[Martin and Mitchell Defection]]
* [[R. W. Scott McLeod]]
* [[Carmel Offie]]
* [[Samuel Reber]]
* ''[[Seduction of the Innocent]]''
* [[Sexual orientation and the United States military]]
* [[Charles W. Thayer]]
* [[Arthur H. Vandenberg, Jr.]]
* [[Walter Jenkins]]
* [[Wright Commission on Government Security]]
* [[Communism and homosexuality#Association of communism with homosexuality by anti-communists|Association of Communism with homosexuality by anti-Communists]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Adkins, Judith, “‘These People Are Frightened to Death’: Congressional Investigations and the Lavender Scare,” ''Prologue'', 48 (Summer 2016), 6–20. 
*Bérubé, Allan. ''Coming out under fire: the history of gay men and women in World War Two'' (NY: Free Press, 1990)
* Dean, Robert D. ''Imperial Brotherhood: Gender and the Making of Cold War Foreign Policy'' (University of Massachusetts Press, 2003), {{ISBN|978-1-55849-414-5}}
* Gibson, 'E. Lawrence. 'Get Off my Ship : Ensign Berg vs. the U.S. Navy'' (NY: Avon, 1978)
* Haggerty, Timothy. "History Repeating Itself: A Historical Overview of Gay Men and Lesbians in the Military before 'Don't Ask, Don't Tell'," in Aaron Belkin and Geoffrey Bateman, eds., ''Don't Ask, Don't Tell: Debating the Gay Ban in the Military'' (Boulder, CO: Lynne Rienner, 2003)
* McDaniel, Rodger. ''Dying for Joe McCarthy's Sins: The Suicide of Wyoming Senator Lester Hunt''. (WordsWorth, 2013), {{ISBN|978-0983027591}}
* [[Michael S. Sherry]], ''Gay Artists in Modern American Culture An Imagined Conspiracy'' ([http://www.sfgate.com/books/article/They-re-here-queer-and-art-pioneers-in-Sherry-s-3300516.php book review])

==External links==
* [http://bulk.resource.org/courts.gov/c/F2/229/229.F2d.27.12568.html Longernecker v. Higley, December 22, 1955]
* [http://www.thelavenderscare.com/ ''The Lavender Scare''], official website for documentary film
* An [http://press.uchicago.edu/Misc/Chicago/404811in.html Interview with David K. Johnson], author of ''The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government''
* [https://news.yahoo.com/uniquely-nasty--the-u-s--governments-war-on-gays-191808993.html ''Uniquely Nasty: The U.S. Government's War on Gays''], Yahoo News documentary film (2015)

{{LGBT |rights=yes}}

[[Category:Aftermath of World War II in the United States]]
[[Category:Political history of the United States]]
[[Category:Anti-communism in the United States]]
[[Category:McCarthyism]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:LGBT history in the United States]]
[[Category:1950s in LGBT history]]
[[Category:History of LGBT civil rights in the United States]]
[[Category:Scares]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>