<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20200916233913|978791126" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="4663436" pageid="4663436" ns="0" title="Lavender Scare"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-10-07T14:22:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{for|the lavender scare in the state of Florida|Florida Legislative Investigation Committee}}
[[File:McCarthy Cohn.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|[[Joseph McCarthy]] and [[Roy Cohn]] during the [[Army–McCarthy hearings]]]]
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
The "'''Lavender Scare'''" was a [[moral panic]] during the mid-20th century about [[Homosexuality|homosexual]] people in the United States government and their mass dismissal from government service. It contributed to and paralleled the [[Anti-communism|anti-communist]] campaign known as [[McCarthyism]] and the [[Red Scare#Second Red Scare|Second Red Scare]].&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite web|title=An interview with David K. Johnson author of The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government|url=http://www.press.uchicago.edu/Misc/Chicago/404811in.html|website=press.uchicago.edu|publisher=The University of Chicago|date=2004|quote=The Lavender Scare helped fan the flames of the Red Scare. In popular discourse, communists and homosexuals were often conflated. Both groups were perceived as hidden subcultures with their own meeting places, literature, cultural codes, and bonds of loyalty. Both groups were thought to recruit to their ranks the psychologically weak or disturbed. And both groups were considered immoral and godless. Many people believed that the two groups were working together to undermine the government.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gay men and lesbians were said to be national security risks and communist sympathizers, which led to the call to remove them from state employment.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Lavender Scare|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=Chicago University Press|year=2004|isbn=9780226401904|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was thought that gay people were more susceptible to being manipulated, which could pose a threat to the country.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Shibusawa|first1=Naoko|date=September 2012|title=The Lavender Scare and Empire: Rethinking Cold War Antigay Politics|journal=Diplomatic History|volume=36|issue=4|pages=723–752|doi=10.1111/j.1467-7709.2012.01052.x|jstor=44376170}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Lavender Scare – the federal government's official response to both a visible lesbian and gay community and a perceived homosexual menace – normalized persecution of homosexuals through bureaucratic institutionalization of homophobic discrimination policy. Former U.S. Senator [[Alan K. Simpson]] has written: "The so-called '[[Red Scare]]' has been the main focus of most historians of that period of time. A lesser-known element ... and one that harmed far more people was the witch-hunt McCarthy and others conducted against homosexuals."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Simpson|first=Alan K. |chapter=Prologue |title=Dying for Joe McCarthy's Sins: The Suicide of Wyoming Senator Lester Hunt |first2=Rodger |last2=McDaniel |publisher=WordsWorth Press |year=2013|page=x |isbn= 978-0983027591}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
The term for this persecution was popularized by [[David K. Johnson]]'s 2004 book which studied this anti-homosexual campaign, ''The Lavender Scare.'' The book drew its title from the term "[[lavender (color)|lavender]] lads", used repeatedly by Senator [[Everett Dirksen]] as a synonym for homosexual males. In 1952, Dirksen said that a [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] victory in the November elections would mean the removal of "the lavender lads" from the [[State Department]].&lt;ref&gt;Stephen J. Whitfield, ''The Culture of the Cold War'', 2nd ed. (Johns Hopkins University Press, 1996), p. 44; Byron C. Hulsey, ''Everett Dirksen and his Presidents: How a Senate Giant Shaped American Politics'' (University Press of Kansas, 2000), 48–9&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase was also used by ''[[Confidential (magazine)|Confidential]]'' magazine, a periodical known for gossiping about the sexuality of politicians and prominent Hollywood stars.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Bernstein, "Lavender Lads Bartone Babes", ''[[The Advocate (LGBT magazine)|The Advocate]]'', February 27, 2007. On the association of a variety colors with homosexuality, see Venetia Newall, "Folklore and Male Homosexuality", ''Folklore'', vol. 97, no. 2, 1986, 126&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
Well before the congressional investigations of 1950, U.S. institutions had already developed an intricate and effective system of regulations, tactics, and personnel to uncover homosexuals that would become enforcement mechanisms during the Lavender Scare.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Lavender Scare|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|year=2004|location=Chicago, IL|page=63}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was related to a general expansion of the bureaucratic state during the late nineteenth century, with institutions that increasingly systematically categorized people as unfit or fit, including homosexuals in the unfit category along with people who were designated as “criminally insane” or “morally depraved”, even though they did not consistently take regulatory action on this until later.'''&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;'''

In 1947, at the very beginning of the [[Cold War]] and the heightened concern about internal security, the State Department began campaigns to rid the department of communists and homosexuals, and they established a set of “security principles” that would go on to inspire the creation of a dual loyalty-security test which became the model for other government agencies, as well as the basis for a government-wide security program under President Dwight D. Eisenhower's administration.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Lavender Scare|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|year=2004|location=Chicago, IL|page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under the criteria of the State Department's security principles, “disloyal” persons included communists, their associates, and those guilty of espionage, along with persons known for “habitual drunkenness, sexual perversion, moral turpitude, financial irresponsibility or criminal record,” and were to be denied federal employment.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; With the inclusion of “sexual perversion” among those considered unsuitable for federal employment, discrimination against homosexuals was implicitly built into State Department policy, and it would be grandfathered into federal governmental protocol and procedure.

Even before the 1947 establishment of State Department security principles, the United States military had developed discriminatory policies targeting gay men and lesbians. In 1940, President Roosevelt and his Selective Service advisers were convinced by psychiatrists of the need to implement screening programs to determine the mental health of potential soldiers as to reduce the cost of psychiatric rehabilitation for returning veterans.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Coming Out Under Fire: The History of Gay Men and Women in World War II|last=Berube|first=Allan|publisher=The University of North Carolina Press|year=1990|location=Chapel Hill, NC|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the initial plan for psychiatric screenings of military recruits included no direct references to homosexuality, within a year, direct references were added – this development in military bureaucratic processes contributed towards the momentum of the military's preoccupation with homosexuality during World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Coming Out Under Fire: The History of Gay Men and Women in World War II|last=Berube|first=Allan|publisher=The University of North Carolina Press|year=1990|location=Chapel Hill, NC|page=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new psychiatric screening directives and procedures introduced to the military the idea that homosexuals were unfit to serve in the armed forces because they were mentally ill: a change from the military's traditional way of approaching homosexuality as a crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Coming Out Under Fire: The History of Gay Men and Women in World War II|last=Berube|first=Allan|publisher=The University of North Carolina Press|year=1990|location=Chapel Hill, NC|page=33}}&lt;/ref&gt; During World War I, punishment of homosexual soldiers was first codified in American military law, and during World War II, final regulations were declared and homosexuals were banned from all branches of the military in 1943.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Conduct Unbecoming: Gays and Lesbians in the U.S. Military|last=Shilts|first=Randy|publisher=Fawcett Columbine Books|year=1994|location=New York, NY|pages=15–17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite all of the regulations, the need for troops allowed for loopholes regarding the accepting/rejection of homosexuals to fight in war. Around 4,000–5,000 out of 18 million men that had been in consideration were turned away.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; Those serving in the military were ordered to report homosexual acts from other soldiers that were serving. Between two thousand and five thousand soldiers were suspected to be homosexuals in the military, where women were discharged at a higher rate when compared to men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=The Air Force expelled her in 1955 for being a lesbian. Now, at 90, she's getting an honorable discharge.|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/morning-mix/wp/2018/01/11/in-1955-she-was-kicked-out-of-the-air-force-for-being-a-lesbian-now-at-90-she-is-fighting-back/|last=Swenson|first=Kyle|date=January 11, 2018|work=[[The Washington Post]]|id={{proquest|1988830718}}|access-date=2019-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

If the influx of people into Washington D.C. during the New Deal created the urban and professional environments that allowed a gay and lesbian subculture to flourish, then World War II accelerated the process: for many lesbians and gay men, the war was a national coming out experience.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Lavender Scare|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|year=2004|location=Chicago, IL|page=51}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mobilization for World War II and the war experience gave birth to a new addition to the American social urban landscape – the lesbian and gay community. To many Americans, this visible homosexual subculture seemed to prove their suspicions that the war had loosened puritanical moral codes, broadened sexual mores and certainly represented a viable threat to ideals of puritanical gender roles, heterosexuality, and the nuclear family. After the war, as families were united and as Americans struggled to put their lives back together, a national narrative rigorously promoted and propagated idealized versions of the nuclear family, heterosexuality, and traditional gender roles in the home and the workplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Coming Out Under Fire: The History of Gay Men and Women in World War II|last=Berube|first=Allan|publisher=The University of North Carolina Press|year=1990|location=Chapel Hill, NC|page=258}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1950, the same year that Senator [[Joseph McCarthy]] claimed 205 communists were working in the [[United States Department of State|State Department]], [[Undersecretary]] of State [[John Peurifoy]] said that the State Department had allowed 91 homosexuals to resign.&lt;ref&gt;Representative [[Arthur L. Miller|Miller]] ([[Nebraska|NE]]). [http://www.writing.upenn.edu/~afilreis/50s/gays-in-govt.html "Homosexuals in Government."] ''Congressional Record'' 96:4 (March 29, 1950), H4527&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|magazine=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |title=Thailand: Smiling Jack |url=http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,807544,00.html |date=August 22, 1955}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 19, 1950, the Republican National Chairman [[Guy George Gabrielson]] said that "sexual perverts who have infiltrated our Government in recent years" were "perhaps as dangerous as the actual Communists".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9D01E7DD153DE03BBC4152DFB266838B649EDE|title=Perverts Called Government peril|date=April 19, 1950|newspaper=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; The danger was not solely because they were gay, however. Homosexuals were considered to be more susceptible to blackmail and thus were labeled as security risks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.dailykos.com/story/2012/2/28/1069129/-Today-in-history-State-Department-reveals-purge-of-91-homosexuals|title=Today in history: State Department reveals purge of 91 homosexuals|website=Daily Kos|access-date=2016-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; McCarthy hired [[Roy Cohn]]{{snd}}who would later die of [[AIDS]] and was accused of being a [[closeted]] homosexual&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://partners.nytimes.com/library/national/science/aids/080386sci-aids.html|title=Roy Cohn, Aide to McCarthy and Fiery Lawyer, Dies at 59|author=|date=|website=partners.nytimes.com|accessdate=21 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.maryellenmark.com/text/magazines/life/905W-000-035.html|title=Life Magazine – The Snarling Death of Roy M. Cohn |author=Nicholas von Hoffman|date=March 1988|work=maryellenmark.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{snd}}as chief counsel of his Congressional subcommittee. Together, McCarthy and Cohn{{snd}}with the enthusiastic support of the head of the [[FBI]], [[J. Edgar Hoover]]{{snd}}were responsible for the firing of scores of gay men and women from government employment and strong-armed many opponents into silence using rumors of their homosexuality.&lt;ref name="johnson"&gt;{{cite book|title=The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=2004|at=22|isbn=0-226-40190-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rodger McDaniel, ''Dying for Joe McCarthy's Sins: The Suicide of Wyoming Senator Lester Hunt'' (WordsWorth, 2013), {{ISBN|978-0983027591}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=May 20, 1950|accessdate= December 29, 2014|url=https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1950/05/20/113156266.pdf |title=Inquiry by Senate on Perverts Asked|work=New York Times|first=William S.|last=White}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1953, during the final months of the Truman administration, the State Department reported that it had fired 425 employees for allegations of homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://williamsinstitute.law.ucla.edu/wp-content/uploads/5_History.pdf|title=The Legacy of Discriminatory State Laws, Policies, and Practices, 1945–Present |publisher=Williams Institute, UCLA}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=126 Perverts Discharged |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=980CE7D8123BE23BBC4E51DFB5668389649EDEE |date=March 26, 1952|work=New York Times|accessdate=December 29, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1418&amp;context=uhm Berard, Lauren B., "Something Changed: The Social and Legal Status of Homosexuality in America as Reported by ''The New York Times''" (2014). Honors Theses. Paper 357.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140914040222/http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1418&amp;context=uhm |date=2014-09-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

McCarthy often used accusations of homosexuality as a [[smear tactic]] in his anti-communist crusade, often combining the [[Second Red Scare]] with the Lavender Scare.  On one occasion, he went so far as to announce to reporters, "If you want to be against McCarthy, boys, you've got to be either a Communist or a cocksucker."&lt;ref&gt;Cuordileone, K.A.  "'Politics in an Age of Anxiety': Cold War Political Culture and the Crisis in American Masculinity, 1949–1960"  ''The Journal of American History'' 87 (2) (2000): 515–545&lt;/ref&gt; At least one recent history has argued that, in linking communism and homosexuality and psychological imbalance, McCarthy was employing guilt-by-association if evidence for communist activity was lacking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first1=Joy |last1=Damousi|first2=Mariano Ben |last2=Plotkin|title=Psychoanalysis and Politics: Histories of Psychoanalysis Under Conditions of Restricted Political Freedom|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RhhpAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA221|date=2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-992316-8|page=221}}&lt;/ref&gt; Political rhetoric at the time often linked communists and homosexuals, and common beliefs among the public were similar, including that both were "morally weak" or “psychologically disturbed”, along with being godless and undermining traditional families.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.archives.gov/publications/prologue/2016/summer/lavender.html|title="These People Are Frightened to Death": Congressional Investigations and the Lavender Scare|date=2016-08-15|website=National Archives|language=en|access-date=2019-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For example, McCarthy spoke on the Senate floor about two individual people, "Case 14" and "Case 62", as Communists who were "unsafe risks", and he directly linked that to their homosexuality.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; He said a top intelligence official had told him “every active Communist is twisted mentally or physically”, and he implied that these people were vulnerable to recruitment by Communists because of their “peculiar mental twists” of homosexuality.&lt;ref name=":6"/&gt;

=== Executive Order 10450 ===
In 1953 [[Dwight D. Eisenhower|President Dwight D. Eisenhower]] signed [[Executive Order 10450]], which set security standards for federal employment and barred homosexuals from working in the federal government. The restrictions set in place were cause for hundreds of gay people to be forcibly outed and fired from the [[United States Department of State|State Department]]. With a stroke of a pen, President Eisenhower expanded the federal government's anti-homosexual policies and procedures to include every department and agency and every private corporation with a government contract – affecting the job security of more than six million workers and armed forces personnel.&lt;ref name="Berube 1990 269"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Coming Out Under Fire: The History of Gay Men and Women in World War II|last=Berube|first=Allan|publisher=The University of North Carolina Press|year=1990|location=Chapel Hill, NC|page=269}}&lt;/ref&gt; The executive order was also the cause for the firing of approximately 5,000 gay people from federal employment; this included private contractors and military personnel. Not only did the victims lose their jobs, but also they were forced out of the closet and thrust into the public eye as lesbian or gay.

Specifically, Truman's loyalty program had been extended through this executive order: “sexual perversion” was added to a list of behaviors that would keep a person from holding a position in government. There were many new regulations and policies put into place to detect and remove gay, lesbian, and bisexual people. The new procedures to search out homosexuals were frequently to interview and look for signs of sexual orientation. They also looked at places these individuals frequently visited, such as gay bars, and they even found people guilty by association. If their friends or family showed signs of being homosexual, they might also be suspected.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://outhistory.org/items/show/1425|title=The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government |website=outhistory.org • It's About Time|access-date=2019-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the mid-1950s, similar repressive and oppressive policies had gone into effect in state and local governments which extended the prohibitions on the employment of lesbians and gay men to cover twelve million workers – more than twenty percent of the United States labor force – who now had to sign oaths attesting to their moral purity to get or to keep their jobs.&lt;ref name="Berube 1990 269"/&gt;

In 1973, a federal judge ruled a person's sexual orientation could not be the sole reason for termination from federal employment, and in 1975 the [[United States Civil Service Commission]] announced that they would consider applications by gays and lesbians on a case by case basis. Executive Order 10450 stayed partly in effect until 1995 when [[Bill Clinton|President Bill Clinton]] rescinded the order and put in place the "[[Don't ask, don't tell]]" policy for admittance of gays into the military.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://thinkprogress.org/lgbt/2011/08/05/288942/clinton-issued-order-letting-gays-get-security-clearances-16-years-ago-today/|title=Clinton Issued Order Letting Gays Get Security Clearances 16 Years Ago Today|website=ThinkProgress|access-date=2016-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Association of communism with "subversives" ===
Both homosexuals and [[Communist Party USA|Communist Party]] members were seen as subversive elements in American society who all shared the same ideals of [[antitheism]], rejection of [[Bourgeoisie#Bourgeois culture|bourgeois culture]] and middle-class morality, and lack of conformity. They were also seen as scheming and manipulative and, most importantly, would put their own agendas above others in the eyes of the general population.&lt;ref name="glbtq.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtqarchive.com/ssh/mccarthyism_S.pdf|title=McCarthyism|last=Prono|first=Luca|date=|website=|publisher=[[glbtq.com]]|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; McCarthy also associated homosexuality and communism as "threats to the 'American way of life'."&lt;ref&gt;Carlson, Dennis. "Gayness, multicultural education, and community." [https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=K2_VMQyk-ZMC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA233 Beyond black and white: New faces and voices in the U.S. Schools] (1997): 233–256.&lt;/ref&gt; [Homosexuals and communists] were perceived as hidden subcultures with their own meeting places, literature, cultural codes, and bonds of loyalty. [They] were thought to recruit the psychologically weak or disturbed [and] many believed the two were working together to undermine the government.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; David K. Johnson notes that without an idealized traditional American moral fiber, any citizen could succumb to immoral temptations such as homosexuality; and they could ultimately be seduced by communism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Lavender Scare|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago, IL|page=95}}&lt;/ref&gt; The association of homosexuality with communism proved to be a convenient political tool to develop and implement homophobic discriminatory policy throughout the federal government. It was easy to convince a Congress dictated by a communist containment policy to respond to the perceived homosexual menace because they were already viewed to be not only subversive social elements of American culture, but subversive political elements. Homosexuality was directly linked to security concerns, and more government employees were dismissed because of their homosexual [[sexual orientation]] than because they were left-leaning or communist. George Chauncey noted that: "The specter of the invisible homosexual, like that of the invisible communist, haunted Cold War America," and homosexuality (and by implication homosexuals themselves) were constantly referred to not only as a disease, but also as an invasion, like the perceived danger of communism and subversives.&lt;ref&gt;Field, Douglas, ed. [https://books.google.com/books?id=DztQtydwimMC American cold war culture]. Edinburgh University Press, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Senator [[Kenneth S. Wherry|Kenneth Wherry]] similarly attempted to invoke a connection between homosexuality and anti-nationalism. He said in an interview with [[Max Lerner]] that: "You can't hardly separate homosexuals from subversives." Later in that same interview, he drew the line between patriotic Americans and gay men: "But look, Lerner, we're both Americans, aren't we? I say, let's get these fellows [closeted gay men in government positions] out of the government."&lt;ref&gt;Lerner, Max, ''The Unfinished Country: A Book of American Symbols'' Simon and Schuster, 1959 pp. 313–316&lt;/ref&gt;

The term “Homintern” was coined in the 1930s, possibly by Cyril Connolly, W.H. Auden, or Harold Norse, as a [[Camp (style)|camp]] term playing off of "Comintern" ([[Communist International]]). It was first used to describe an imagined group of gay men who controlled the art world, and later used in reference to “a fantastical gay international that sought to control the world”. In 1952, an article written by [[R. G. Waldeck|R. G Waldeck]] argued that this conspiracy was a real and important reason to expel homosexual people from the State Department, even more important than the possibility of blackmail, and this article was read into the [[Congressional Record]] and cited by others.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

While the [[Mattachine Society]] was founded by [[Harry Hay]], a former member of the [[Communist Party USA]], Hay resigned from the society when the membership condemned his politics as a threat to the organization he had founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Lillian Faderman|author2=Stuart Timmons|title=Gay L.A.: A History of Sexual Outlaws, Power Politics, and Lipstick Lesbians |url=https://archive.org/details/gaylahistoryofse00lill|url-access=registration|year=2006|publisher=Basic Books |isbn=978-0-465-02288-5 |page=[https://archive.org/details/gaylahistoryofse00lill/page/113 113] |accessdate=May 8, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Subcommittee on Investigations ===
The Subcommittee on Investigations was a subcommittee of the [[U.S. Senate Committee on Expenditures in Executive Departments|Committee on Expenditures in Executive Departments]]. This subcommittee led by Senator [[Clyde R. Hoey]] from 1949–1952  investigated "the employment of homosexuals in the Federal workforce."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://catalog.archives.gov/id/28748701|title=Executive Session Hearing of the Subcommittee on Investigations|last=|first=|date=1950|website=National Archives and Record Administration|publisher=|access-date=|series=Series: Committee Papers, 1789–2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A related report, known as the Hoey Report, stated that all of the government's intelligence agencies "are in complete agreement that sex perverts in Government constitute security risks."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=University of Chicago|year=2004|isbn=0-226-40481-1|location=Chicago|pages=[https://archive.org/details/lavenderscarecol00john_0/page/114 114–115]|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/lavenderscarecol00john_0/page/114}}&lt;/ref&gt; The congressional Wherry-Hill and Hoey Committee investigation hearings were held between March and May, and July and September 1950 respectively. Republican Senator Kenneth Wherry and Democratic Senator Lester Hill formed a subcommittee to make preliminary investigations into the “Infiltration of Subversives and Moral Perverts into the Executive Branch of the United States Government.”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Coming Out Under Fire: The History of Gay Men and Women in World War II|last=Berube|first=Allan|publisher=The University of North Carolina Press|year=1990|location=Chapel Hill, NC|page=264}}&lt;/ref&gt; No records of the Wherry-Hill investigation survive beyond press coverage and two published reports.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite news|title=Congressional Investigation and the Lavender Scare.|last=Adkins|first=Judith|date=2016|work=Prologue Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; One such report contained the statements of the head of the DC Metropolitan Police Department vice squad, Lieutenant Roy Blick, who testified that 5,000 homosexuals lived in Washington D.C. and that around 3,700 were federal employees.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Lt. Blick's comments, which were speculative at best, further fueled the media storm surrounding the gays-in-government controversy; the Wherry-Hill preliminary investigation convinced the Senate to launch a full-scale congressional exploration.

The recommended investigation was assigned to the Committee on Expenditures in Executive Departments, led by Democrat senator Clyde Hoey, and the full Senate unanimously authorized the investigation into sexual perversion in the federal workforce; with outrage mounting to astronomical heights, no Democrat dared speak out against it lest they risk their political career.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Lavender Scare|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|year=2004|location=Chicago, IL|page=99}}&lt;/ref&gt; Investigating the “Employment of Homosexuals and Other Sex Perverts in Government,” the subcommittee came to be known as the Hoey Committee and while the White House under President Truman was heavily involved in managing its methodology and processes, the driving force behind the congressional investigation of homosexuals was its chief counsel, former FBI agent Francis Flanagan.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=David K. Johnson. The Lavender Scare, 103|last=Johnson|first=David K.|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|year=2004|location=Chicago, IL|page=103}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Hoey Committee consulted with and heard testimony from law enforcement, judicial authorities, military and governmental security officers, and medical experts. Rather than uncovering any evidence of any federal employee being blackmailed into revealing state secrets on account of their homosexuality, the investigation uncovered considerable differences of opinion, even within the government, over federal policy of homosexual exclusion and over whether foreign government agents had ever attempted to blackmail homosexuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Lavender Scare|last=Johnson|first=David K|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|year=2004|location=Chicago, IL|page=114}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Hoey Committee's conclusive report, released in mid-December that year, ignored the ambiguities of testimony and deemed authoritatively that there was “no place in the United States Government for persons who violate the laws or the accepted standards of morality,” especially those who “bring disrepute to the Federal service by infamous or scandalous conduct,” stating that lesbians and gay men were “unsuitable” for federal employment because they were “security risks” as well as people engaged in illegal and immoral activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Hoover's War on Gays: Exposing the FBI's "Sex Deviants" Program|last=Charles|first=Douglas M.|publisher=The University Press of Kansas|year=2015|location=Lawrence, KS|page=94}}&lt;/ref&gt; The committee recommended that the military's policy and procedure should be used as the model; in the areas of explicit policies, standardized procedures, uniform enforcement, constant vigilance, and coordination with law enforcement agencies regarding homosexuals, the armed services set the precedent. Further, the Hoey Committee report stated that in the past, the federal government “failed to take a realistic view of the problem of sex perversion,” and that to adequately protect the “public interest,” the federal government must “adopt and maintain a realistic and vigilant attitude toward the problem of sex perverts in the Government.” &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Hoover's War on Gays: Exposing the FBI's 'Sex Deviants' Program|last=Charles|first=Douglas M.|publisher=The University Press of Kansas|year=2015|location=Lawrence, KS|page=95}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The authoritative findings of the Wherry-Hill and Hoey Committee congressional investigations directly helped the Lavender Scare move beyond a strictly Republican rhetoric towards bipartisan appeal, and purging lesbians and gay men from federal employment quickly became part of standard, government-wide policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Hoover's War on Gays: Exposing the FBI's 'Sex Deviants' Program|last=Charles|first=Douglas M.|publisher=The University Press of Kansas|year=2015|isbn=|location=Lawrence, KS|page=95}}&lt;/ref&gt; The major purpose and achievement of the Wherry-Hill and Hoey Committees was the construction and promotion of the belief that homosexuals in the military and federal government constituted security risks who, as individuals or working in conspiracy with members of the Communist Party, threatened the safety of the nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Coming Out Under Fire: The History of Gay Men and Women in World War II|last=Berube|first=Allan|publisher=The University of North Carolina Press|year=1990|location=Chapel Hill, NC|page=267}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexuality===
When Cohn brought on [[G. David Schine]] as chief consultant to the McCarthy staff, speculation arose that Schine and Cohn had a sexual relationship.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Shooting Star: The Brief Arc of Joe McCarthy|last=Wicker|first=Tom|publisher=Harcourt|year=2006|isbn=015101082X|edition=1|location=Orlando|oclc=61204327|author-link=Tom Wicker|url=https://archive.org/details/shootingstarbrie00wick}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="miller" /&gt; Although some historians have concluded the Schine–Cohn friendship was [[platonic love|platonic]],&lt;ref name=miller&gt;{{cite book |last=Miller |first=Neil |title=Out of the Past: Gay and Lesbian History from 1869 to the Present |publisher=Advocate Books |location=Los Angeles, California|year=2005 |chapter=Chapter 18 |url=http://www2.english.uiuc.edu/finnegan/English%20256/Miller.htm |isbn=978-1-55583-870-6 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090902224218/http://www2.english.uiuc.edu/finnegan/English%20256/Miller.htm |archivedate=September 2, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Wolfe |first=Tom |authorlink=Tom Wolfe |title=Dangerous Obsessions |work=[[The New York Times]] |location=New York City|date=April 3, 1988 |quote=But so far as Mr. Schine is concerned, there has never been the slightest evidence that he was anything but a good-looking kid who was having a helluva good time in a helluva good cause. In any event, the rumors were sizzling away ... |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D9163BF930A35757C0A96E948260&amp;sec=&amp;pagewanted=print}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/cohn_r.html|title=An Encyclopedia of Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer Culture|last=Baxter|first=Randolph|date=November 13, 2006|publisher=glbtq, Inc|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120129105211/http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/cohn_r.html|archive-date=January 29, 2012|url-status=dead|access-date=December 26, 2018|quote=Tall, rich, and suave, the Harvard-educated (and heterosexual) Schine contrasted starkly with the short, physically undistinguished, and caustic Cohn.}}&lt;/ref&gt; others state, based on the testimony of friends, that Cohn was gay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.salon.com/2012/06/23/lgbts_worst_foe_the_closet_monster/slide_show/1|title=Roy Cohn|last=Lauerman|first=Kerry|website=[[Salon (website)|Salon]]|location=San Francisco, California|date=June 23, 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170114194952/http://www.salon.com/2012/06/23/lgbts_worst_foe_the_closet_monster/slide_show/1|archive-date=January 14, 2017|url-status=dead|accessdate=December 26, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|first=Nicholas|last=von Hoffman|title=The Snarling Death of Roy M. Cohn|magazine=[[Life (magazine)|Life]]|publisher=[[Time, Inc.]]|location=New York City|date=March 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the Army–McCarthy hearings, Cohn denied having any "special interest" in Schine or being bound to him "closer than to the ordinary friend."&lt;ref name=miller/&gt; [[Joseph Welch]], the Army's attorney in the hearings, made an apparent reference to Cohn's homosexuality. After asking a witness, at McCarthy's request, if a photo entered as evidence "came from a pixie", he defined "pixie" as "a close relative of a fairy".&lt;ref name="miller" /&gt; Though "pixie" was a camera-model name at the time, the comparison to "fairy," a derogatory term for a homosexual man, had clear implications. The people at the hearing recognized the slur and found it amusing; Cohn later called the remark "malicious," "wicked," and "indecent."&lt;ref name=miller/&gt;

Speculation about Cohn's sexuality intensified following his death from AIDS in 1986.&lt;ref name="NYTObit"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://partners.nytimes.com/library/national/science/aids/080386sci-aids.html|title=Roy Cohn, Aide to McCarthy and Fiery Lawyer, Dies at 59|last=Krebs|first=Albin|date=August 3, 1986|work=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=December 26, 2018|quote=Roy M. Cohn, the flamboyant, controversial defense lawyer who was chief counsel to Joseph R. McCarthy's Senate investigations in the 1950s into Communist influence in American life, died yesterday at the age of 59.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2008 article published in ''[[The New Yorker]]'', [[Jeffrey Toobin]] quotes [[Roger Stone]]: "Roy was not gay. He was a man who liked having sex with men. Gays were weak, effeminate. He always seemed to have these young blond boys around. It just wasn't discussed. He was interested in power and access."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Stone worked with Cohn beginning with the Reagan campaign during the [[Republican Party presidential primaries, 1976|1976 Republican Party presidential primaries]].

=== Contemporary views of homosexuality ===
Washington D.C. had a fairly large and active gay community before McCarthy launched his witch hunt campaign against homosexuals, but as time went on and the climate of the Cold War spread, so too did negative views of homosexuals.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Because social attitudes toward homosexuality were overwhelmingly negative and the psychiatric community regarded homosexuality as a [[mental disorder]], [[gay]] men and [[lesbian]]s were considered susceptible to [[blackmail]], thus constituting a security risk. U.S. government officials assumed that [[Communism|communists]] would blackmail homosexual employees of the federal government to provide them classified information rather than risk exposure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |work=Gay Today |url=http://gaytoday.com/interview/010104in.asp |title=Historian David K. Johnson: Exposes the U.S. Government's Anti-Gay Crusades |first=Raj |last=Ayyar |accessdate=May 8, 2015|date=January 1, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1957 [[Crittenden Report]] of the [[United States Navy]] [[Public inquiry|Board of Inquiry]] concluded that there was "no sound basis for the belief that homosexuals posed a security risk" and criticized the prior Hoey Report: "No intelligence agency, as far as can be learned, adduced any factual data before that committee with which to support these opinions" and said that "the concept that homosexuals necessarily pose a security risk is unsupported by adequate factual data."&lt;ref&gt;Bérubé, 282. The Report is dated December 21, 1956, to March 15, 1957.&lt;/ref&gt; The Crittenden Report remained secret until 1976. Navy officials claimed they had no record of studies of homosexuality, but attorneys learned of its existence and obtained it through a [[Freedom of Information Act (United States)|Freedom of Information Act]] request.&lt;ref&gt;Gibson, 356–367; Bérubé, 278&lt;/ref&gt; As of September 1981, the Navy claimed it was still unable to fulfill a request for the Report's supporting documentation.&lt;ref&gt;Bérubé, 283; Haggerty, 45n38&lt;/ref&gt;

According to John Loughery, author of a study of gay identity in the 20th century, "few events indicate how psychologically wracked America was becoming in the 1950s ... than the presumed overlap of the Communist and the homosexual menace."&lt;ref name=glbtq.com/&gt;

The research of [[Evelyn Hooker]], presented in 1956, and the first conducted without a polluted sample (gay men who had been treated for mental illness) dispelled the [[illusory correlation]] between homosexuality and mental illness that prior research, conducted with polluted sampling, had established. Hooker presented a team of three expert evaluators with 60 unmarked psychological profiles from her year of research. She chose to leave the interpretation of her results to others, to avoid potential bias. The evaluators concluded that in terms of adjustment, there were no differences between the members of each group. Her demonstration that it is not an illness led the way to the eventual removal of homosexuality from the [[American Psychiatric Association]]'s [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]].&lt;ref name="ucd"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/hooker2.html#biography | title=Evelyn Hooker, Ph.D.: September 2, 1907 – November 18, 1996 | publisher=UC Davis | accessdate=April 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Resistance ==
One of the first and most influential members of the gay rights movements, [[Frank Kameny]], was thrust into unemployment because of his sexual orientation in 1957. He was working as an astronomer for the United States Army Map Service, but was fired as a result of the Lavender Scare and could never find another job in the United States federal government again. This led to Kameny devoting his life to the [[LGBT social movements|gay rights movement]], which in some ways he began. In 1965, four years before the [[Stonewall riots|Stonewall Riots]], Kameny picketed the White House on the grounds of gay rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://notevenpast.org/lavender-scare-cold-war-persecution-gays-and-lesbians-federal-government-2006/|title=The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government by David K. Johnson (2006)|website=notevenpast.org|access-date=2016-03-21|date=2012-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Lillian Faderman, the [[LGBT community]] formed a [[subculture]] of its own in this era, constituting "not only a choice of sexual orientation, but of social orientation as well." The [[Mattachine Society]] and the [[Daughters of Bilitis]], which formed the [[homophile]] movements of the U.S., were in many ways defined by McCarthyism and the lavender scare.{{Citation needed|date=November 2016}} They were underground organizations that maintained the anonymity of their members.&lt;ref name="glbtq.com" /&gt;

== Legacy ==
Though the main vein of McCarthyism ended in the mid-1950s when the 1956 ''Cole v Young'' ruling severely weakened the ability to fire people from the federal government for discriminatory reasons,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/351/536/|title=Cole v. Young, 351 U.S. 536 (1956)|author=|date=|website=justia.com|accessdate=21 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; the movement that was born from it, the Lavender Scare, lived on. One such way was that Executive Order 10450, which was not rescinded until 1995, continued to bar gays from entering the military.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Another form of the Lavender Scare that persisted was the [[Florida Legislative Investigation Committee]], also referred to as the FLIC and the Johns Committee. The FLIC was founded in 1956 and was not disbanded until 1964. The purpose of the committee was to operate within Florida continuing the work of the Lavender Scare by investigating and firing public school teachers who were gay. During its active years the FLIC was responsible for more than 200 firings of alleged gay teachers. The FLIC was disbanded following the release of the [[Homosexuality and Citizenship in Florida|Purple Pamphlet]] due to public outrage over its explicit and pornographic nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://riches.cah.ucf.edu/committee/history.php|title=The Committee Documentary|website=riches.cah.ucf.edu|access-date=2016-03-21|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160329110959/http://riches.cah.ucf.edu/committee/history.php|archivedate=2016-03-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2017, the State Department formally apologized following suggestion by Senator [[Ben Cardin]]. Cardin also noted that investigations by the state department into homosexuality of federal employees continued as late as the 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/state-department-apologizes-lavender-scare-180961746/ "State Department Apologizes for the "Lavender Scare"], Jason Daley. Smithsonian. January 10, 2017. Retrieved 5 feb 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

==Documentary==
''The Lavender Scare,'' directed by Josh Howard and narrated by [[Glenn Close]], is a documentary film that recounts the events of the Lavender Scare. David K. Johnson is part of the project, as the film is based on his book. To help with funding, Josh Howard created a [[Kickstarter]] that met its goal in donations. The film was completed, screened at more than 70 film festivals around the world, and opened at theaters in New York City and Los Angeles in 2019. [[PBS]] televised the film on June 18, 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/about/blogs/news/the-lavender-scare-premieres-tuesday-june-18-on-pbs/|title=THE LAVENDER SCARE Premieres Tuesday, June 18 on PBS|publisher=PBS.org|date=May 14, 2019|accessdate=June 21, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* ''[[Advise and Consent]]''
* [[Joseph Alsop]]
* [[Newton Arvin]]
* [[Blue discharge]]
* [[Boise homosexuality scandal]]
* [[Civil Service Reform Act of 1978]]
* [[Executive Order 10450]]
* [[Executive Order 11478]]
* [[Executive Order 13087]]
* [[Florida Legislative Investigation Committee]]
* [[Fruit machine (homosexuality test)]]
* [[Gays and Lesbians in Foreign Affairs Agencies]]
* ''[[Homosexuality and Citizenship in Florida]]''
* [[Frank Kameny]]
* [[Martin and Mitchell Defection]]
* [[R. W. Scott McLeod]]
* [[Helen G. James]]
* [[Carmel Offie]]
* [[Samuel Reber]]
* ''[[Seduction of the Innocent]]''
* [[Sexual orientation and the United States military]]
* [[Charles W. Thayer]]
* [[Arthur H. Vandenberg, Jr.]]
* [[Walter Jenkins]]
* [[Wright Commission on Government Security]]
* [[Communism and homosexuality#Association of communism with homosexuality by anti-communists|Association of Communism with homosexuality by anti-Communists]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Adkins, Judith, "'These People Are Frightened to Death': Congressional Investigations and the Lavender Scare," ''Prologue'', 48 (Summer 2016), 6–20. 
*Bérubé, Allan. ''Coming out under fire: the history of gay men and women in World War Two'' (NY: Free Press, 1990)
* Dean, Robert D. ''Imperial Brotherhood: Gender and the Making of Cold War Foreign Policy'' (University of Massachusetts Press, 2003), {{ISBN|978-1-55849-414-5}}
* Gibson, 'E. Lawrence. 'Get Off my Ship : Ensign Berg vs. the U.S. Navy'' (NY: Avon, 1978)
* Haggerty, Timothy. "History Repeating Itself: A Historical Overview of Gay Men and Lesbians in the Military before 'Don't Ask, Don't Tell'," in Aaron Belkin and Geoffrey Bateman, eds., ''Don't Ask, Don't Tell: Debating the Gay Ban in the Military'' (Boulder, CO: Lynne Rienner, 2003)
* McDaniel, Rodger. ''Dying for Joe McCarthy's Sins: The Suicide of Wyoming Senator Lester Hunt''. (WordsWorth, 2013), {{ISBN|978-0983027591}}
* [[Michael S. Sherry]], ''Gay Artists in Modern American Culture An Imagined Conspiracy'' ([http://www.sfgate.com/books/article/They-re-here-queer-and-art-pioneers-in-Sherry-s-3300516.php book review])

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090703175422/http://bulk.resource.org/courts.gov/c/F2/229/229.F2d.27.12568.html Longernecker v. Higley, December 22, 1955]
* [http://www.thelavenderscare.com/ ''The Lavender Scare''], official website for documentary film
* An [http://press.uchicago.edu/Misc/Chicago/404811in.html Interview with David K. Johnson], author of ''The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government''
* [https://news.yahoo.com/uniquely-nasty--the-u-s--governments-war-on-gays-191808993.html ''Uniquely Nasty: The U.S. Government's War on Gays''], Yahoo News documentary film (2015)

{{LGBT |rights=yes}}
{{LGBT rights in the United States}}

[[Category:Aftermath of World War II in the United States]]
[[Category:Political history of the United States]]
[[Category:Anti-communism in the United States]]
[[Category:Discrimination against LGBT people in the United States]]
[[Category:McCarthyism]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:LGBT history in the United States]]
[[Category:1950s in LGBT history]]
[[Category:History of LGBT civil rights in the United States]]
[[Category:Scares]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>