<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113222637|87627368" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19481110" pageid="19481110" ns="0" title="Jim Crow laws"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T22:29:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{AfricanAmerican|bottom}}
'''Jim Crow Laws''' were state and local laws enacted in the Southern and border states of the [[United States]] and in force between 1876 and 1967 that required racial segregation, especially of [[black]], in all public facilities. It also affected Asians and many other races.  "Jim Crow period" or the "Jim Crow era" refers to the time during which this practice occurred.  The most important laws required that public schools and most public places (including trains and buses) have separate facilities for whites and blacks.  (These ''Jim Crow Laws'' were separate from the 1800-1866 [[Black Codes in the USA|Black Codes]], which had restricted the civil rights and civil liberties of African Americans.)  State-sponsored school segregation was declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court in 1954 in [[Brown v. Board of Education]]. All the other Jim Crow laws were repealed by the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]].

During the [[Reconstruction]] period of 1865-1876, federal law provided civil rights protection in the South for [[Freedmen]]&amp;mdash;the African-Americans who had formerly been slaves. Reconstruction ended at different dates (the latest 1877), and was followed in each Southern state by [[Redeemers|Redeemer]] governments that passed the Jim Crow laws to separate the races.  In the [[Progressive Era]] the restrictions were formalized, and segregation was extended to the federal government by President [[Woodrow Wilson]] in 1913.  

After 1945, the [[Civil Rights movement]] gained momentum and used federal courts to attack Jim Crow.  The [[Supreme Court]] declared legal, or ''[[de jure]]'', public school segregation unconstitutional in 1954, and it ended in practice in the 1970s. The Court ruling did not stop ''[[de facto]]'' or informal school segregation, which continues in large cities. President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]], building a coalition of northern Democrats and Republicans, pushed Congress to pass the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] which immediately annulled all Jim Crow laws.  Restaurants, hotels and theatres (with rare exceptions) immediately dropped racial segregation.

==Origins of the Jim Crow laws==
In the first stage of [[Presidential Reconstruction]], all-white Southern legislatures, overwhelmingly dominated by ex-Confederates, abolished laws regarding slavery but passed the [[black codes]], which gave new rights to the freed men but fewer than whites possessed. The North reacted against those codes, which never went into effect in any state. Instead, the [[Radical Republicans]] passed the [[Civil Rights Act of 1866]] which gave freed men legal rights (but not the right to vote). The country, by 1870, passed the  [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th]] and [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|15th]] Amendments to the [[United States Constitution]], guaranteeing civil rights and the right to vote. The southern states came under Republican control--a party comprising the [[Freedmen]], white Southerners ("[[Scalawags]]") and migrants from the North ("[[Carpetbaggers]]"). The [[Ku Klux Klan]] and related groups reacted violently, but they were suppressed by President [[Ulysses S. Grant]] using the federal courts and troops. By 1877, the conservatives and Democrats, forming a [[Redeemer]] coalition, ousted all the Republican governments. From 1877 down to the 1970s, the Southern Democrats controlled every Southern state nearly all the time. 

After 1877, the [[Redeemers]] reversed many of the civil rights gains that black Americans had made during Reconstruction, passing laws that mandated discrimination by both local governments and by private citizens. Since "Jim Crow law" is a blanket term for any of this type of legislation, the exact date of inception for the laws varies by state. The most important laws came in the 1890s and the adoption of legislation segregating railroad cars in New Orleans as the first genuine Jim Crow law. By 1915, every Southern state had effectively destroyed the gains in civil rights and liberties that blacks had enjoyed due to the Reconstructionist efforts.

It is thought that the term 'Jim Crow laws' originated from the [[1828]] popular song [[Jump Jim Crow]], a [[blackface]] song which made derogatory references to the character of colored people. As a result of this song, the term 'Jim Crow' became a pejorative or mocking term for colored people, used in the [[Deep South]].

Between 1890 and 1920, many state governments prevented most blacks from voting by various techniques, such as [[poll tax]]es and [[literacy test]]s. (These could be waived for whites  due to [[grandfather clause]]s.) It is estimated that of 181,000  African-American males of voting age in [[Alabama]] in 1900, only 3,000 were registered to vote. 

Many of the discriminatory Jim Crow laws were enacted to support [[racial segregation]] in everyday life. They required black and white people to use separate water fountains, public schools, public bath houses, restaurants, public libraries, buses and rail cars -- although, even without legal segregation, the desire of the white majority to use the frequently inferior facilities set aside for black use was admittedly limited.

==Examples of Jim Crow laws in various states==

The following examples of segregation (Jim Crow laws) are excerpts from examples of Jim Crow laws shown on a (U.S.) National Park Service web site. [http://www.nps.gov/malu/documents/jim_crow_laws.htm]

Note that the examples here include anti-[[miscegenation]] laws; though sometimes counted among the "Jim Crow laws" of the South, those laws had also existed outside the South for many years.  Anti-miscegenation laws were not repealed by the Civil Rights Act of 1964, but were declared unconstitutional in the 1967 Supreme Court case ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]''.

[[Image:ColoredDrinking.jpg|thumb|250px|An [[African American]] drinks out of a segregated water cooler designated for "colored" patrons in 1939 at a streetcar terminal in Oklahoma City]]

===Alabama===
* "Nurses. No person or corporation shall require any white female nurse to work in &lt;nowiki&gt;wards&lt;/nowiki&gt; or rooms in hospitals, either public or private, in which Negro men are placed. 

* "Buses. All passenger stations in this state operated by any motor transportation company shall have separate waiting rooms or space and separate ticket windows for the white and colored races." 

* "Railroads. The conductor of each passenger train is authorized and required to assign each passenger to the car or the division of the car, when it is divided by a partition, designated for the race to which such passenger belongs." 

* "Restaurants. It shall be unlawful to conduct a restaurant or other place for the serving of food in the city, at which white and colored people are served in the same room, unless such white and colored persons are effectually separated by a solid partition extending from the floor upward to a distance of seven feet or higher, and unless a separate entrance from the street is provided for each compartment."

===Florida===
* Intermarriage. All marriages between a white person and a Negro, or between a white person and a person of Negro descent to the fourth generation inclusive, are hereby forever prohibited. 

* Cohabitation. Any Negro man and white woman, or any white man and Negro woman, who are not married to each other, who shall habitually live in and occupy in the nighttime the same room shall each be punished by imprisonment not exceeding twelve (12) months, or by fine not exceeding five hundred ($500.00) dollars. 

* Education. The schools for white children and the schools for Negro children shall be conducted separately.  

*The following is a list of legislation and penalties dealing with racial relations in Florida, some in effect until 1967:
**1865: Railroad [Statute] &amp;mdash; Negroes or mulattoes who intruded into any railroad car reserved for white persons would be found guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, sentenced to stand in the [[pillory]] for one hour, or to be whipped, not exceeding 39 stripes, or both, at the discretion of the jury." Whites faced the same penalty for entering a car reserved for persons of color.
**1873: Barred public accommodation segregation [Statute] &amp;mdash; Prohibited discrimination on account of race in the full and equal enjoyment of public accommodations such as inns, public transportation, theaters, schools, cemeteries and places of public amusement. Did not include private schools or cemeteries established exclusively for white or colored persons.
**1881: Miscegenation [Statute] &amp;mdash; Unlawful for any white person to intermarry with any Negro person. Penalty: Performing such a ceremony punishable by a fine of $1,000, "of which one-half shall be paid to the informer."
**1885: Education [Constitution] &amp;mdash; White and colored children shall not be taught in the same school.
**1885: Miscegenation [Constitution] &amp;mdash; "Forever" prohibited marriages between whites and blacks, or between a "white person and a person of Negro descent to the fourth generation inclusive."
**1887: Railroads [Statute] &amp;mdash; "All respectable Negro persons" to be sold first-class tickets at the same rates as white passengers and shall be provided a separate car "equally as good and provided with the same facilities for comfort as for white persons." Penalty: Conductors and railroad companies violating the provisions of the law faced a fine up to $500.
**1887: Education [Constitution] &amp;mdash; White and colored children prohibited from being taught in the same schools.
** 1895: Education [Statute] &amp;mdash; Penal offense for any persons to conduct any school, any grade, either public or private where whites and blacks are instructed or boarded in the same building, or taught in the same class by the same teachers. Penalty: Between $150 and $500 fine, or imprisonment in the county jail between three and six months.
** 1903: Miscegenation [Statute] &amp;mdash; Intermarriage with a Negro, mulatto, or any person with one-eighth Negro blood shall be punished. Penalty: Imprisonment up to ten years or a fine not more than $1,000.
** 1905: Streetcars [Statute] &amp;mdash; Separation of races required on all streetcars. Gave Caucasian mistresses the right to have their children attended in the white section of the car by an African nurse, but withheld from an African woman the equal right to have her child attended in the African section by its Caucasian nurse.
** 1907: Railroads [Statute] &amp;mdash; Separate waiting rooms for each race to be provided at railroad depots along with separate ticket windows. Also called for separation of the races on streetcars. Signs in plain letters to be marked "For White" and "For Colored" to be displayed. Penalties: Railroad companies that refused to comply with the provision could be fined up to $5,000.
** 1909: Railroads [Statute] &amp;mdash; Separate accommodations required by race. Penalty: Passengers who failed to comply with law would be fined up to $500.
** 1913: Education [Statute] &amp;mdash; Unlawful for white teachers to teach Negroes in Negro schools, and for Negro teachers to teach in white schools. Penalty: Violators subject to fines up to $500, or imprisonment up to six months.
** 1927: Education [Statute] &amp;mdash; Criminal offense for teachers of one race to instruct pupils of the other in public schools.
** 1927: Race classification [Statute] &amp;mdash; Defined the words "Negro" or "colored person" to include persons who have one eighth or more Negro blood.
** 1941: Voting rights protected [Statute] &amp;mdash; Poll tax repealed.
** 1944: Miscegenation [Statute] &amp;mdash; Illegal for whites and Negroes to live in adultery. Penalty: up to $500, or up to two years imprisonment.
** 1945: Antidefamation [Statute] &amp;mdash; Unlawful to print, publish, distribute by any means, any publications, handbills, booklets, etc. which tends to expose any individual or any religious group to hatred, contempt, ridicule, or abuse unless the name and address of those doing so is clearly printed on the written material.
** 1958: Education [Statute] &amp;mdash; County boards of education may adopt regulation for closing schools during emergencies. Schools to close automatically when federal troops used to prevent violence.
** 1958: Public Carrier [Statute] &amp;mdash; Races to be segregated on public carriers.
** 1967: Public accommodations [City Ordinance] &amp;mdash; [[Sarasota]] passed a city ordinance stating that "Whenever members of two or more…races shall…be upon any public…bathing beach within the corporate limits of the City of Sarasota, it shall be the duty of the Chief of police or other officer…in charge of the public forces of the City...with the assistance of such police forces, to clear the area involved of all members of all races present."

===Georgia===
* Restaurants. All persons licensed to conduct a restaurant, shall serve either white people exclusively or colored people exclusively and shall not sell to the two races within the same room or serve the two races anywhere under the same license. 

* Amateur Baseball. It shall be unlawful for any amateur white baseball team to play baseball on any vacant lot or baseball diamond within two blocks of a playground devoted to the Negro race, and it shall be unlawful for any amateur colored baseball team to play baseball in any vacant lot or baseball diamond within two blocks of any playground devoted to the white race. Colored people usually didn't get served.

===Louisiana===
* Housing. Any person...who shall rent any part of any such building to a Negro person or a Negro family when such building is already in whole or in part in occupancy by a white person or white family, or vice versa when the building is in occupancy by a Negro person or Negro family, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and on conviction thereof shall be punished by a fine of not less than twenty-five ($25.00) nor more than one hundred ($100.00) dollars or be imprisoned not less than 10, or more than 60 days, or both such fine and imprisonment in the discretion of the court. 

===Mississippi===
* Promotion of Equality. Any person...who shall be guilty of printing, publishing or circulating printed, typewritten or written matter urging or presenting for public acceptance or general information, arguments or suggestions in favor of social equality or of intermarriage between whites and Negroes, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and subject to fine or not exceeding five hundred (500.00) dollars or imprisonment not exceeding six (6) months or both. 

===North Carolina===
* Textbooks. Books shall not be interchangeable between the white and colored schools, but shall continue to be used by the race first using them. 

* Libraries. The state librarian is directed to fit up and maintain a separate place for the use of the colored people who may come to the library for the purpose of reading books or periodicals. 

===Virginia===
* Theaters. Every person...operating...any public hall, theatre, opera house, motion picture show or any place of public entertainment or public assemblage which is attended by both white and colored persons, shall separate the white race and the colored race and shall set apart and designate...certain seats therein to be occupied by white persons and a portion thereof , or certain seats therein, to be occupied by colored persons. 

* Railroads. The conductors or managers on all such railroads shall have power, and are hereby required, to assign to each white or colored passenger his or her respective car, coach or compartment. If the passenger fails to disclose his race, the conductor and managers, acting in good faith, shall be the sole judges of his race.

===Wyoming===
* Intermarriage. "All marriages of white persons with Negroes, Mulattos, Mongolians, or Malaya hereafter contracted in the State of Wyoming are and shall be illegal and void."  The term 'Mongolian' probably included Aboriginal Americans as well as Asians.

===Other states===
* Alabama, Arizona, Florida, Georgia and Kentucky [http://afroamhistory.about.com/cs/jimcrowlaws/a/jimcrowlaws.htm]

* Louisiana, Maryland, Mississippi, Missouri, New Mexico, and North Carolina [http://afroamhistory.about.com/cs/jimcrowlaws/a/jimcrowlaws_2.htm]

* Oklahoma, South Carolina, Texas, Virginia, and Wyoming [http://afroamhistory.about.com/cs/jimcrowlaws/a/jimcrowlaws_3.htm]

==Attempts at dismantling Jim Crow==
Congress passed the [[Civil Rights Act of 1875]], legislation introduced by [[Charles Sumner]] and [[Benjamin F. Butler]] in 1870, and passed March 1, 1875. It guaranteed that everyone, regardless of race, color, or previous condition of servitude, was entitled to the same treatment in "public accommodations" (i.e. inns, public conveyances on land or water, theaters, and other places of public amusement).

The Supreme Court, in 1883, restricted the Civil Rights Act of 1875 to actions by state and local government. It ruled Congress could not control private persons or corporations; (see [[Civil Rights Cases]]). After Congress passed the Civil Rights Act of 1875, it did not pass another civil rights law until 1957.

In 1890, the State of Louisiana passed a law requiring separate accommodations for colored and white passengers on railroads. Louisiana law distinguished between "white," "black" and "colored" - that is, people of mixed white and black ancestry; the law already had provided that blacks could not ride with white people, but colored people could ride with whites prior to 1890. A group of concerned black, colored and white citizens in New Orleans formed an association dedicated to the repeal of the law. They persuaded [[Homer Plessy]], who was only one-eighth "Negro" and fair-complected, to test it. In 1892, Plessy purchased a first-class ticket from New Orleans on the [[East Louisiana Railway]]. Once he had boarded the train, he informed the train conductor of his racial lineage, and took a seat in the whites-only car. He was directed to leave that car and sit instead in the "coloreds only" car. Plessy refused and was immediately arrested. The Citizens Committee of New Orleans fought the case all the way to the [[Supreme Court of the United States]].  They lost in 1896, and ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' resulted in 58 more years of legal discrimination against black and colored people in the United States. 

When black soldiers returning from World War II refused to put up with the second class citizenship of segregation, the movement for [[Civil Rights]] was renewed. The NAACP Legal Defense Committee (a group independent of the [[NAACP]])--and its lawyer [[Thurgood Marshall]]-- brought the landmark case ''[[Brown v. Board of Education|Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka]]'', {{ussc|347|483|1954}} before the Supreme Court. In 1954, the Court unanimously overturned the 1896 Plessy decision in its ruling; Thurgood Marshall would later become the first black Supreme Court Justice.

Jim Crow laws were a product of the [[Solid South|solidly Democratic South]]. As the party which supported the Confederacy, the Democrats quickly dominated all aspects of local, state, and federal political life in the post-Civil War South, right up through the 1970s. Even as late as 1956, a resolution called [[Southern Manifesto]], condemning the Supreme Court's ruling in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]'', was read into the Congressional Record, and supported by 96 southern congressman and senators, each one a Democrat.

While African-American entertainers, musicians, and literary figures had broken into the white world of American art and culture after 1890, African-American athletes found obstacles confronting them at every turn. By 1900, white opposition to African-American boxers, baseball players, track athletes, and basketball players kept them segregated and limited in what they could do. But their prowess and abilities in all-African-American teams and sporting events could not be denied, and one by one the barriers to African-American participation in all the major sports began to crumble in the 1950s and 1960s.

==The legacy of Jim Crow==
The [[Supreme Court of the United States]] held in the ''[[Civil Rights Cases]]'' 109 US 3 (1883) that the Fourteenth Amendment did not give the federal government the power to outlaw private discrimination, and then held in ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' 163 US 537 (1896) that Jim Crow laws were constitutional as long as they allowed for "[[separate but equal]]" facilities. In the years that followed, the Court made this "separate but equal" requirement a hollow phrase, by approving discrimination even in the face of evidence of profound inequalities in practice.

In 1902, Reverend [[Thomas Dixon (minister)|Thomas Dixon]], a white, Southern anti-Reconstructionist, published the novel ''[[The Leopard's Spots]]'', which intentionally fanned racial animosity.[http://docsouth.unc.edu/dixonclan/bio.html]

Jim Crow laws were a product of the [[Solid South|solidly Democratic South]]. As the party which supported the Confederacy, the Democrats quickly dominated all aspects of local, state, and federal political life in the post-Civil War South, right up through the 1970s. Even as late as 1956, a resolution called [[Southern Manifesto]], condemning the Supreme Court's ruling in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]'', was read into the Congressional Record, and supported by 96 southern congressman and senators, each one a Democrat.

While African-American entertainers, musicians, and literary figures had broken into the white world of American art and culture after 1890, African-American athletes found obstacles confronting them at every turn. By 1900, white opposition to African-American boxers, baseball players, track athletes, and basketball players kept them segregated and limited in what they could do. But their prowess and abilities in all-African-American teams and sporting events could not be denied, and one by one the barriers to African-American participation in all the major sports began to crumble in the 1950s and 1960s.

==Twentieth century==
{{Progressivism}}
In the 20th century, the Supreme Court began to overturn Jim Crow laws on constitutional grounds. The Court held in ''[[Guinn v. United States]]'' 238 US 347 (1915) that an [[Oklahoma]] law that denied the right to vote to non-white citizens was unconstitutional. (Nonetheless, the majority of African-Americans were unable to vote in most states in the [[Deep South]] of the U.S. until the 1950s or 1960s.) In ''[[Buchanan v. Warley]]'' 245 US 60 (1917), the Court held that a [[Kentucky]] law could not require residential segregation. The Supreme Court outlawed the white [[primary election]] in ''[[Smith v. Allwright]]'' 321 US 649 (1944), and, in 1946, in ''[[Irene Morgan|Irene Morgan v. Virginia]]'' ruled segregation in interstate transportation to be unconstitutional, though its reasoning stemmed from the [[commerce clause]] of the Constitution rather than any moral objection to the practice. It was not until 1954 in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education|Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka]]'' 347 US 483 that the Court held that separate facilities were inherently unequal in the area of public schools, effectively overturning ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'', and outlawing Jim Crow in other areas of society as well. This landmark case consisted of complaints filed in the states of Delaware-[[Gebhart v. Belton]]; South Carolina-[[Briggs v. Elliot]]; Virginia – [[Davis v. County School Board of Prince Edward County]]; and Washington, DC – [[Bolling v. C. Melvin Sharpe]].These decisions, along with other cases such as ''[[McLaurin v. Oklahoma State Board of Regents]]'' 339 US 637 (1950), ''[[NAACP v. Alabama]]'' 357 US 449 (1958), and ''[[Boynton v. Virginia]]'' 364 US 454 (1960), slowly dismantled the state-sponsored segregation imposed by Jim Crow laws. 

In addition to Jim Crow laws, in which the state compelled segregation of the races, businesses, political parties, unions and other private parties created their own Jim Crow arrangements, barring blacks from buying homes in certain neighborhoods, from shopping or working in certain stores, from working at certain trades, etc. The Supreme Court outlawed some forms of private discrimination in ''[[Shelley v. Kraemer]]'' 334 US 1 (1948), in which it held that "restrictive covenants" that barred sale of homes to blacks or Jews or Asians were unconstitutional, on the grounds that they represented state-sponsored discrimination, in that they were only effective if the courts enforced them. 

The Supreme Court was unwilling, however, to attack other forms of private discrimination; it reasoned that private parties did not violate the [[Equal Protection]] clause of the Constitution when they discriminated, because they were not "state actors" covered by that clause. 

After [[World War II]], as attitudes in the Federal courts turned against segregation, the segregationist white governments of many of the states of the Southeast countered with even more numerous and strict segregation laws on the local level until the start of the 1960s. The modern [[American Civil Rights Movement|Civil Rights movement]] is often considered to have been sparked by an act of [[civil disobedience]] against Jim Crow laws when [[Rosa Parks]], an African-American woman, refused to give up her seat on a bus to a white man, after being ordered to do so by the bus driver. Her action, and the demonstrations that it spawned, led to a series of legislation and court decisions in which Jim Crow laws were repealed or annulled.

However, the [[Montgomery Bus Boycott]] led by Reverend [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]] which followed Rosa Parks' action, did not come in a vacuum. Numerous boycotts and demonstrations against segregation had occurred throughout the 1930s and 1940s. These early demonstrations achieved positive results and helped spark political activism. For instance, [[K. Leroy Irvis]] of Pittsburgh's Urban League led a demonstration against employment discrimination by Pittsburgh's department stores in 1947, and later became the first 20th century African-American to serve as a state Speaker of the House.

In 1964, the [[Congress of the United States|U.S. Congress]] attacked the parallel system of private Jim Crow practices. It invoked the [[commerce clause]] to pass the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], which outlawed discrimination in public accommodations, i.e., privately owned restaurants, hotels, and stores, and in private schools and workplaces. This use of the commerce clause was upheld in ''[[Heart of Atlanta Motel v. United States]]'' 379 US 241 (1964).

===End of ''de jure'' segregation===

In January, 1964, President Johnson met with civil rights leaders. On January 8, during his first State of the Union address, Johnson asked Congress to "let this session of Congress be known as the session which did more for civil rights than the last hundred sessions combined." On June 21, civil rights workers [[Michael Schwerner]], [[Andrew Goodman]], and [[James Chaney]], disappeared in Neshoba County, Mississippi. The three were volunteers traveling to Mississippi to aid in the registration of African-American voters as part of the Mississippi Summer Project. The FBI recovered their bodies, which had been buried in an earthen dam, 44 days later. The Neshoba County deputy sheriff and 16 others, all Ku Klux Klan members, were indicted for the crimes; seven were convicted. On July 2, President Johnson signed the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] [http://www.lbjlib.utexas.edu/johnson/lbjforkids/civil_timeline.shtm]

According to the United States Department of Justice, "By 1965 concerted efforts to break the grip of state disfranchisement had been under way for some time, but had achieved only modest success overall and in some areas had proved almost entirely ineffectual. The murder of voting-rights activists in Philadelphia, Mississippi, gained national attention, along with numerous other acts of violence and terrorism. Finally, the unprovoked attack on March 7, 1965, by state troopers on peaceful marchers crossing the Edmund Pettus Bridge in [[Selma, Alabama|Selma]], [[Alabama]], en route to the state capitol in Montgomery, persuaded the President and Congress to overcome Southern legislators' resistance to effective voting rights legislation. President Johnson issued a call for a strong voting rights law and hearings began soon thereafter on the bill that would become the Voting Rights Act." [http://www.usdoj.gov/crt/voting/intro/intro_b.htm]

==The name==
[[Image:jimcrow.jpg|right|frame|A depiction of [[Thomas D. Rice]]'s "Jim Crow"]]
The term ''Jim Crow'' comes from the [[minstrel show]] song "[[Jump Jim Crow]]" written in [[1828]] and performed by Thomas Dartmouth "Daddy" Rice, a white English migrant to the U.S. and the first popularizer of [[blackface]] performance. The song and blackface itself were an immediate hit. A caricature of a shabbily dressed rural black, "Jim Crow" became a standard character in minstrel shows. He was often paired with "Zip Coon," a flamboyantly dressed urban black who associated more with [[White (people)|white]] culture. By 1837, ''Jim Crow'' was being used to refer to racial segregation.

==Further reading==
* Ayers, Edward L. ''The Promise of the New South'' Oxford University Press, 1992, a general history of the South in the late 19th century
* Barnes, Catherine A. ''Journey from Jim Crow: The Desegregation of Southern Transit'' Columbia University Press, 1983. 
* Bartley, Numan V. ''The Rise of Massive Resistance: Race and Politics in the South during the 1950s'' Louisiana State University Press, 1969.
* Bond, Horace Mann. “The Extent and Character of Separate Schools in the United States.” ''Journal of Negro Education'' 4(July 1935):321–27. online via JSTOR
* Jane Dailey, Glenda Elizabeth Gilmore, and Bryant Simon, eds. ''Jumpin' Jim Crow: Southern Politics from Civil War to Civil Rights'' (2000), essays by scholars on impact of Jum Crow on black communities
* Fairclough, Adam. “‘Being in the Field of Education and Also Being a Negro…Seems…Tragic’: Black Teachers in the Jim Crow South.” ''Journal of American History'' 87 (June 2000): 65–91. online via JSTOR 
* Feldman, Glenn. ''Politics, Society, and the Klan in Alabama, 1915–1949''. University of Alabama Press, 1999.
* Harvey Fireside,  ''Separate and Unequal: Homer Plessy and the Supreme Court Decision That Legalized Racism'',  2004. ISBN 0-7867-1293-7
* Eric Foner ''Reconstruction, America's Unfinished Revolution, 1863-1877: America's Unfinished Revolution, 1863-1877'' (Harpercollins, 1988), ISBN 0-06-015851-4, standard history of Reconstruction from [[neoabolitionist]] school
* Gaines, Kevin. ''Uplifting the Race: Black Leadership, Politics, and Culture in the Twentieth Century'' University of North Carolina Press, 1996. 
* Gaston, Paul M. ''The New South Creed: A Study in Southern Mythmaking'' Alfred A. Knopf, 1970. 
* Glenda Elizabeth Gilmore; ''Gender and Jim Crow Women and the Politics of White Supremacy in North Carolina, 1896-1920'' (1996)
* [[John Howard Griffin]] ''[[Black Like Me]]'' by (Signet, 1996) ISBN 0-451-19203-6. Author leaves privileged life as Southern white man and darkens his skin to experience segregation in the Deep South in 1959.
* Haws, Robert, ed. ''The Age of Segregation: Race Relations in the South, 1890– 1945'' University Press of Mississippi, 1978. 
* Sheldon Hackney, ''Populism to Progressivism in Alabama'' (1969) 
* Johnson, Charles S. ''Patterns of Negro Segregation'' Harper and Brothers, 1943. 
* Michael J. Klarman; ''From Jim Crow to Civil Rights: The Supreme Court and the Struggle for Racial Equality'' Oxford University Press, 2004 
* Leon F. Litwack, ''Trouble in Mind: Black Southerners in the Age of Jim Crow'' (Alfred A. Knopf: 1998) "This is the most complete and moving account we have had of what the victims of the Jim Crow South suffered and somehow endured" — C. Vann Woodward
* Stephen Kantrowitz. ''Ben Tillman &amp; the Reconstruction of White Supremacy'' (2000) 
* McMillen, Neil R. ''Dark Journey: Black Mississippians in the Age of Jim Crow. '' University of Illinois Press, 1989. 
* Keith Weldon Medley, ''We As Freemen: Plessy v. Ferguson'' by  Pelican Publishing Company, March, 2003. ISBN 1-58980-120-2. Popular story of Homer Plessy, who lost his case before the Supreme Court; the case legalized segregation in the U.S. for the next 58 years.
* Myrdal, Gunnar. ''An American Dilemma: The Negro Problem and Modern Democracy'' Harper and Row, 1944. the most detailed analysis of the Jim Crow system in operation.
* Percy, William Alexander. ''Lanterns on the Levee: Recollections of a Planter's Son.'' 1941. Reprint, Louisiana State University Press, 1993. by conservative white planter
* Rabinowitz, Howard N. ''Race Relations in the Urban South, 1856–1890'' (1978)
* J. Douglas Smith; ''Managing White Supremacy: Race, Politics, and Citizenship in Jim Crow Virginia'' University of North Carolina Press, 2002 
* Smith, J. Douglas. “The Campaign for Racial Purity and the Erosion of Paternalism in Virginia, 1922–1930: “Nominally White, Biologically Mixed, and Legally Negro.’” ''Journal of Southern History'' 68 (February 2002): 65–106. 
* Smith, J. Douglas. “Patrolling the Boundaries of Race: Motion Picture Censorship and Jim Crow in Virginia, 1922–1932.” ''Historical Journal of Film, Radio, and Television'' 21 (August 2001): 273–91. 
* Sterner, Richard.   ''The Negro's Share'' (1943) detailed statistics 
* C. Vann Woodward. ''The Strange Career of Jim Crow'' (1955) the classic history by Pulitzer prize winner. 
* C. Vann Woodward. ''The Origins of the New South: 1877-1913'' (1951).

==See also==
* [[Apartheid]]
* [[Israeli West Bank barrier]]
* [[Bantustan]]
* [[Black Codes in Northern USA]]
* [[Carpetbagger]]
* [[Dunning School]]
* [[Freedman]]
* [[Freedmen's Bureau]]
* [[Ghetto]]
* [[Group Areas Act]]
* [[Neoabolitionist]]
* [[Pass Law]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Radical Republican]]
* [[Redeemers]]
* [[Redemption (U.S. history)]]
* [[Scalawag]]
* [[Second-class citizen]]
* [[Separate but equal]]

==External links==
* [http://www.jimcrowhistory.org/resources/lessonplans/hs_es_etiquette.htm Racial Etiquette: The Racial Customs and Rules of Racial Behavior in Jim Crow America] - A detailed article outlining the basics of Jim Crow etiquette.
* [http://www.ferris.edu/jimcrow/ Jim Crow Museum of Racist Memorabilia]
* [http://www.ferris.edu/news/jimcrow/newforms/ An article on "New Racist Forms: Jim Crow in the 21st Century"]
* [http://www.robinwashington.com/jimcrow/1_home.html "You Don't Have to Ride Jim Crow!"] PBS documentary on first Freedom Ride, in 1947
* [http://www.jimcrowhistory.org/scripts/jimcrow/courtcases.cgi?casetype=Segregation The History of Jim Crow]
* [http://californiaccw.org/files/sf-chronicle-article.htm A 1923 article in the SF Chronicle] lauding California's Jim Crow handgun law, which is still in force today

[[Category:History of racial segregation in the United States]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Reconstruction]]
[[Category:Legal history of the United States]]
[[Category:African-American history]]

[[de:Jim Crow]]
[[fr:Lois Jim Crow]]
[[nl:Jim Crow-wetten]]
[[ja:ジム・クロウ法]]
[[ru:Законы Джима Кроу]]
[[sv:Jim Crow]]
[[de:Jim Crow]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>