<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20030929175213|1658181" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19481110" pageid="19481110" ns="0" title="Jim Crow laws"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-01T16:00:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In the [[United States]], the so-called '''Jim Crow laws''' (or '''Black Codes''') were made to enforce [[racial segregation]], and included laws that would prevent [[African-American]]s from doing things that a "white" person could do. For instance, Jim Crow laws regulated separate use of water fountains and separate seating sections on public transport. Jim Crow laws varied between communities and states

The first Jim Crow law was passed in [[1723]], when blacks in the state of [[Virginia]] were stripped of the right to vote and own property. The later passage of Black Codes, which attempted to return freed slave to bondage in fact, rather than name, by Southern legislatures immediately after the [[American Civil War]] led to the policy of [[Reconstruction]], in which the federal government intervened to protect the rights conferred on black Americans by the [[Thirteenth Amendment|13th]], [[Fourteenth Amendment|14th]], and [[Fifteenth Amendment|15th]] Amendments to the [[Constitution of the United States]] and the [[Civil Rights Act]]s of [[1866]] and [[1875]].

Reconstruction ended, however, in [[1877]]. In its aftermath the resurgent white elites, who referred to themselves as [[redeemers]], undid many of the civil rights gains that black Americans had made during Reconstruction, passing laws that mandated discrimination by both local governments and by private citizens. The [[Supreme Court of the United States]] ruled in the ''[[Civil Rights Cases]]'' 109 US 3 ([[1883]]) that the Fourteenth Amendment did not give the federal government the power to outlaw private discrimination, then held in ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' 163 US 537 ([[1896]]) that Jim Crow laws were constitutional as long as they allowed for [[separate but equal]] facilities. In the years that followed, the Court made this “separate but equal” requirement a hollow phrase by approving discrimination even in the face of evidence of profound inequalities in practice.

The Supreme Court began to overturn Jim Crow laws on constitutional grounds in the 20th century. The Supreme Court ruled in ''[[Guinn v. United States]]'' 238 US 347 ([[1915]]) that an [[Oklahoma]] law that denied the right to vote to some citizens was unconstitutional. (Nonetheless, the majority of African Americans were unable to vote in most states in the [[Deep South]] of the USA until the [[1950s]] or [[1960s]].) In ''[[Buchanan v. Warley]]'' 245 US 60 ([[1917]]), the Court held that a [[Kentucky]] law could not require residential segregation. The court outlawed the white primary in ''[[Smith v. Allwright]]'' 321 US 649 ([[1944]]), and in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]] of [[Topeka]]'' 347 US 483 ([[1954]]) the Court ruled that separate facilities were inherently unequal in the area of public schools. These decisions, along with other cases such as ''[[McLaurin v. Oklahoma State Board of Regents]]'' 339 US 637 ([[1950]]), ''[[NAACP v. Alabama]]'' 357 US 449 ([[1958]]), and ''[[Boynton v. Virginia]]'' 364 US 454 ([[1960]]), slowly dismantled the state-sponsored segregation imposed by Jim Crow laws. 

In addition to Jim Crow laws, in which the state compelled segregation of the races, businesses, political parties, unions and other private parties created their own Jim Crow arrangements, barring blacks from buying homes in certain neighborhoods, from shopping or working in certain stores, from working at certain trades, etc. The Supreme Court outlawed some forms of private discrimination in ''[[Shelley v. Kraemer]]'' 334 US 1 ([[1948]]), in which it held that "restrictive covenants" that barred sale of homes to blacks or Jews or Asians were unconstitutional, on the ground that they represented state-sponsored discrimination in that they were only effective if the courts enforced them. 

The Supreme Court was unwilling, however, to attack other forms of private discrimination; it reasoned that private parties did not violate the [[Equal Protection]] clause of the Constitution when they discriminated because they were not "state actors" covered by that clause. It was only in [[1964]] that [[Congress]] finally attacked private discrimination by passing the [[Civil Rights Act]] of [[1964]], which outlawed discrimination in public accommodations, i.e., privately owned restaurants, hotels and stores, and in private schools and workplaces, that Congress attacked the parallel system of private Jim Crow practices. The Supreme Court ultimately upheld that statute in ''Heart of Atlanta Motel v. US'' 379 US 241 ([[1964]]) on the theory that Congress could prohibit private discrimination under the authority given it by the [[Commerce Clause]] of the Constitution.

As attitudes turned against segregation in the Federal courts after [[World War II]], the segregationist white governments of many of the states of the South East countered with even more numerous and strict segregation laws on the local level until the start of the 1960s. The modern [[civil rights movement]] is often considered to have been sparked by an act of [[civil disobedience]] against Jim Crow laws when [[Rosa Parks]], an African-American woman, refused to give up her seat on a bus to a white man. This led to a series of legislation and court decisions in which Jim Crow laws were repealed or annulled.

The term ''Jim Crow'' comes from the [[minstrel show]] song "[[Jump Jim Crow]]" written in [[1828]] by [[Thomas D. Rice]], a white man, the originator of [[blackface]] performance. The song and blackface itself were an immediate hit. "Jim Crow" became a standard character in Minstrel shows, being a caricature of a shabbily dressed rural black; "Jim Crow" was often paired with the character "Zip Coon", a flamboyantly dressed urban black. By 1837, ''Jim Crow'' was being used to refer to racial segregation. 

In conjunction with the laws there was also [[Jim Crow etiquette]]: a set of unwritten rules governing how blacks and whites should interact. Breaking of this code could result in a [[lynching]] ([[1878]]-[[1898]] saw 10,000 lynchings) or other forms of sadistic murder. The murders of [[Sam Hose]] and [[Emmet Till]], more than fifty years apart, serve as examples.

See also [[apartheid]].</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>