<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114233959|171546823" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19481110" pageid="19481110" ns="0" title="Jim Crow laws"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T23:40:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{AfricanAmerican|bottom}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Segregation}}
The '''Jim Crow laws''' were state and local laws enacted in the [[Southern United States|Southern]] and [[Border States (Civil War)|border states]] of the [[United States]] and enforced between 1876 and 1965. They mandated "[[separate but equal]]" status for black Americans. In reality, this led to treatment and accommodations that were almost always inferior to those provided to [[white American]]s.  The '''Jim Crow period''' or the '''Jim Crow era''' refers to the time during which this practice occurred. The most important laws required that public schools, public places and public transportation, like trains and buses, have separate facilities for whites and blacks.  (These Jim Crow Laws were separate from the 1800-66 [[Black Codes in the USA|Black Codes]], which had restricted the [[civil rights]] and civil liberties of African Americans.)  State-sponsored school segregation was declared unconstitutional by the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] in 1954 in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]''. Generally, the remaining Jim Crow laws were overruled by the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] and the [[Voting Rights Act]]; none were in effect at the end of the 1960s.

During the [[Reconstruction]] period of 1865-76, federal law provided civil rights protection in the South for [[freedmen]]&amp;mdash;the African-Americans who had formerly been slaves. Reconstruction ended at different dates (the latest 1877), and was followed in each Southern state by [[Redeemers|Redeemer]] governments that passed the Jim Crow laws to separate the races.  In the [[Progressive Era]] the restrictions were formalized, and segregation was extended to the federal government by President [[Woodrow Wilson]] in 1913.  

After 1945, the [[American Civil Rights Movement (1896-1954)|Civil Rights movement]] gained momentum and used federal courts to attack Jim Crow.  The Supreme Court declared legal, or ''[[de jure]]'', public school segregation unconstitutional in 1954, and it ended in practice in the 1970s. The court ruling did not stop ''[[de facto]]'' or informal school segregation, which continued in large cities. President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]], building a coalition of northern Democrats and Republicans, pushed [[United States Congress|Congress]] to pass the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] which immediately annulled Jim Crow laws that segregated restaurants, hotels and theatres; these facilities (with rare exceptions) immediately dropped racial segregation. The [[Voting Rights Act]] ended discrimination in voting for all federal, state and local elections.

==Origins==
[[Presidential Reconstruction]], all white Southern legislatures overwhelmingly dominated by ex-[[Confederate States of America|Confederates]], abolished laws regarding slavery but passed the black codes, which gave new rights to the freedmen but fewer than whites possessed. The [[Northern United States|North]] reacted against those codes, which never went into effect in any state. Instead, the [[Radical Republicans]] passed the [[Civil Rights Act of 1866]] which gave freedmen legal rights (but not the right to vote). The country, by 1870, passed the  [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th]] and [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|15th]] Amendments to the [[United States Constitution]], guaranteeing civil rights and the right to vote. The southern states came under Republican control&amp;mdash; a party comprising the Freedmen, white Southerners ("[[Scalawags]]") and migrants from the North ("[[Carpetbaggers]]"). The [[Klan]] and related groups reacted violently, but they were suppressed by President [[Ulysses S. Grant]] using the federal courts and troops. By 1877, the conservatives and Democrats, forming a Redeemer coalition, ousted all the Republican governments. From 1877 until the 1970s, the Southern Democrats largely controlled every Southern state.

After 1877, the Redeemers reversed many of the civil rights gains that African Americans had made during Reconstruction, passing laws that mandated discrimination by both local governments and by private citizens. Since "Jim Crow law" is a blanket term for any of this type of legislation, the date of inception for the laws varies by state. The most important laws came in the 1890s with the adoption of legislation segregating railroad cars in [[New Orleans]] as the first genuine Jim Crow law. By 1915, every Southern state had effectively destroyed the gains in civil rights and liberties that flap jacks had enjoyed from the Reconstructionist efforts.
The term ''Jim Crow'' comes from the [[minstrel show]] song "[[Jump Jim Crow]]" written in [[1828]] and performed by [[Thomas_D._Rice|Thomas Dartmouth "Daddy" Rice]], a white New Yorker and the first popularizer of [[blackface]] performance. The song and blackface itself were an immediate hit. A caricature of a shabbily dressed rural black, "Jim Crow" became a standard character in minstrel shows. He was often paired with "[[Zip Coon]]," a flamboyantly dressed urban black who associated more with [[White (people)|white]] culture. By 1837, ''Jim Crow'' was being used to refer to racial segregation in Vermont.

Many of the discriminatory Jim Crow laws were enacted to support [[racial segregation]] in everyday life. They required black and white people to use separate water fountains, public schools, public bath houses, restaurants, public libraries, buses and rail cars&amp;mdash;although, even without legal segregation, the desire of the white majority to use the frequently inferior facilities set aside for black use was limited.

===Voting disfranchisement===
{{main|Disfranchisement after the Civil War}}
Between 1890 and 1920, many state governments prevented most blacks from voting by various techniques, such as [[poll tax]]es and [[literacy test]]s. (These could be waived for whites by [[grandfather clause]]s, until this was found to be unconstitutional in [[1915]].) It is estimated that of 181,000 African-American males of voting age in [[Alabama]] in 1900, only 3,000 were registered to vote.

==Examples==
The following examples of segregation are excerpts from examples of Jim Crow laws shown on the [[National Park Service]] [http://www.nps.gov/malu/documents/jim_crow_laws.htm website].

The examples include [[anti-miscegenation laws]]; though sometimes counted among the "Jim Crow laws" of the South, those laws had also existed outside the South for many years.  Anti-miscegenation laws were not repealed by the Civil Rights Act of 1964 but were declared unconstitutional in the 1967 Supreme Court case ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]''.

===Alabama===
* "All passenger stations in this state operated by any motor transportation company shall have separate waiting rooms or space and separate ticket windows for the white and colored races."

===Arkansas===
* Various laws from 1884 to 1947 prohibited marriage or        relations between whites and blacks or [[mulatto]]es, providing for specific fines and imprisonment of up to three years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jimcrowhistory.org/scripts/jimcrow/insidesouth.cgi?state=Arkansas The History of Jim Crow&amp;mdash;Inside the South]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Various laws from 1891 to 1959 segregated rail travel, streetcars, buses, all public carriers, race tracks, gaming establishments, polling places, washrooms in mines, tuberculosis hospitals, public schools and teachers' colleges.  

* A [[poll tax]] was first imposed in the 1890s.

===Florida===
* "All marriages between a white person and a Negro, or between a white person and a person of Negro descent to the fourth generation inclusive, are hereby forever prohibited."

* "Any Negro man and white woman, or any white man and Negro woman, who are not married to each other, who shall habitually live in and occupy in the nighttime the same room shall each be punished by imprisonment not exceeding twelve (12) months, or by fine not exceeding five hundred ($500.00) dollars."

* "The schools for white children and the schools for Negro children shall be conducted separately."  
&lt;!--See no need to list so many. Not meant to be all-inclusive; that's what the website reference is for...*The following is a list of legislation and penalties dealing with racial relations in Florida, some of which were in effect until 1967:
**1865: Railroad statute &amp;mdash; "Negroes or mulattoes who intruded into any railroad car reserved for white persons would be found guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, sentenced to stand in the [[pillory]] for one hour, or to be whipped, not exceeding 39 stripes, or both, at the discretion of the jury." Whites faced the same penalty for entering a car reserved for persons of color.
**1873: Barred public accommodation segregation statute &amp;mdash; prohibited discrimination on account of race in the full and equal enjoyment of public accommodations such as inns, public transportation, theaters, schools, cemeteries and places of public amusement. This did not include private schools or cemeteries established exclusively for white or colored persons.
**1881: Miscegenation statute &amp;mdash; it was unlawful for any white person to intermarry with any Negro person. The offense was punishable by a fine of $1,000, "of which one-half shall be paid to the informer."
**1885: Education (constitution) &amp;mdash; "White and colored children shall not be taught in the same school."
**1885: Miscegenation (constitution) &amp;mdash; "Forever" prohibited marriages between whites and blacks, or between a "white person and a person of Negro descent to the fourth generation inclusive."
**1887: Railroads statute &amp;mdash; "All respectable Negro persons" to be sold first-class tickets at the same rates as white passengers and shall be provided a separate car "equally as good and provided with the same facilities for comfort as for white persons." Conductors and railroad companies violating the provisions of the law faced a fine up to $500.
**1887: Education (constitution) &amp;mdash; white and colored children were prohibited from being taught in the same schools.
** 1895: Education [Statute] &amp;mdash; Penal offense for any persons to conduct any school, any grade, either public or private where whites and blacks are instructed or boarded in the same building, or taught in the same class by the same teachers. Penalty: Between $150 and $500 fine, or imprisonment in the county jail between three and six months.
** 1903: Miscegenation [Statute] &amp;mdash; Intermarriage with a Negro, mulatto, or any person with one-eighth Negro blood shall be punished. Penalty: Imprisonment up to ten years or a fine not more than $1,000.
** 1905: Streetcars [Statute] &amp;mdash; Separation of races required on all streetcars. Gave Caucasian mistresses the right to have their children attended in the white section of the car by an African nurse, but withheld from an African woman the equal right to have her child attended in the African section by its Caucasian nurse.
** 1907: Railroads [Statute] &amp;mdash; Separate waiting rooms for each race to be provided at railroad depots along with separate ticket windows. Also called for separation of the races on streetcars. Signs in plain letters to be marked "For White" and "For Colored" to be displayed. Penalties: Railroad companies that refused to comply with the provision could be fined up to $5,000.
** 1909: Railroads [Statute] &amp;mdash; Separate accommodations required by race. Penalty: Passengers who failed to comply with law would be fined up to $500.
** 1913: Education [Statute] &amp;mdash; Unlawful for white teachers to teach Negroes in Negro schools, and for Negro teachers to teach in white schools. Penalty: Violators subject to fines up to $500, or imprisonment up to six months.
** 1927: Education [Statute] &amp;mdash; Criminal offense for teachers of one race to instruct pupils of the other in public schools.
** 1927: Race classification [Statute] &amp;mdash; Defined the words "Negro" or "colored person" to include persons who have one eighth or more Negro blood.
** 1941: Voting rights protected [Statute] &amp;mdash; Poll tax repealed.
** 1944: Miscegenation [Statute] &amp;mdash; Illegal for whites and Negroes to live in adultery. Penalty: up to $500, or up to two years imprisonment.
** 1945: Antidefamation [Statute] &amp;mdash; Unlawful to print, publish, distribute by any means, any publications, handbills, booklets, etc. which tends to expose any individual or any religious group to hatred, contempt, ridicule, or abuse unless the name and address of those doing so is clearly printed on the written material.
** 1958: Education [Statute] &amp;mdash; County boards of education may adopt regulation for closing schools during emergencies. Schools to close automatically when federal troops used to prevent violence.
** 1958: Public Carrier [Statute] &amp;mdash; Races to be segregated on public carriers.
** 1967: Public accommodations [City Ordinance] &amp;mdash; [[Sarasota]] passed a city ordinance stating that "Whenever members of two or more…races shall…be upon any public…bathing beach within the corporate limits of the City of Sarasota, it shall be the duty of the Chief of police or other officer…in charge of the public forces of the City...with the assistance of such police forces, to clear the area involved of all members of all races present."--&gt;

===Georgia===
* "All persons licensed to conduct a restaurant, shall serve either white people exclusively or colored people exclusively and shall not sell to the two races within the same room or serve the two races anywhere under the same license."

* "It shall be unlawful for any amateur white baseball team to play baseball on any vacant lot or baseball diamond within two blocks of a playground devoted to the Negro race, and it shall be unlawful for any amateur colored baseball team to play baseball in any vacant lot or baseball diamond within two blocks of any playground devoted to the white race."

===Louisiana===
* "Any person who shall rent any part of any such building to a Negro person or a Negro family when such building is already in whole or in part in occupancy by a white person or white family, or vice versa when the building is in occupancy by a Negro person or Negro family, shall be guilty of a [[misdemeanor]] and on conviction thereof shall be punished by a fine of not less than twenty-five ($25.00) nor more than one hundred ($100.00) dollars or be imprisoned not less than 10, or more than 60 days, or both such fine and imprisonment in the discretion of the court."

===Mississippi===
* "Any person...who shall be guilty of printing, publishing or circulating printed, typewritten or written matter urging or presenting for public acceptance or general information, arguments or suggestions in favor of social equality or of intermarriage between whites and Negroes, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and subject to fine or not exceeding five hundred (500.00) dollars or imprisonment not exceeding six (6) months or both."

===North Carolina===
* "Books shall not be interchangeable between the white and colored schools, but shall continue to be used by the race first using them. "

* "The state librarian is directed to fit up and maintain a separate place for the use of the colored people who may come to the library for the purpose of reading books or periodicals."

===Oklahoma===
* "The [Conservation] Commission shall have the right to make segregation of the white and colored races as to the exercise of rights of fishing, boating and bathing."

* "The baths and lockers for the negroes shall be separate from the white race, but may be in the same building."

* "The Corporation Commission is hereby vested with power and authority to require telephone companies...to maintain separate booths for white and colored patrons when there is a demand for such separate booths. That the Corporation Commission shall determine the necessity for said separate booths only upon complaint of the people in the town and vicinity to be served after due hearing as now provided by law in other complaints filed with the Corporation Commission."

===South Carolina===
* "No persons, firms, or corporations, who or which furnish meals to passengers at station restaurants or station eating houses, in times limited by common carriers of said passengers, shall furnish said meals to white and colored passengers in the same room, or at the same table, or at the same counter."

* "It shall be unlawful for any parent, relative, or other white person in this State, having the control or custody of any white child, by right of [[guardianship]], natural or acquired, or otherwise, to dispose of, give or surrender such white child permanently into the custody, control, maintenance, or support, of a negro."

===Texas===
Twenty-seven Jim Crow laws were passed in the Lone Star state from 1866 to 1958.  Some examples include:

* 1925: Required racially segregated schools.

* 1950: Separate facilities required for white and black citizens in state parks

* 1953: Public carriers to be segregated

* 1958: No child compelled to attend schools that are racially mixed. No desegregation unless approved by election. Governor may close schools where troops used on federal authority.

[[Image:ColoredDrinking.jpg|thumb|250px|An [[African American]] drinks out of a segregated water cooler designated for "colored" patrons in 1939 at a streetcar terminal in Oklahoma City]]

===Virginia===
* "Every person...operating...any public hall, theater, opera house, motion picture show or any place of public entertainment or public assemblage which is attended by both white and colored persons, shall separate the white race and the colored race and shall set apart and designate...certain seats therein to be occupied by white persons and a portion thereof, or certain seats therein, to be occupied by colored persons." 

* "The conductors or managers on all such railroads shall have power, and are hereby required, to assign to each white or colored passenger his or her respective car, coach or compartment. If the passenger fails to disclose his race, the conductor and managers, acting in good faith, shall be the sole judges of his race."

==Attempts at dismantling the laws==
Congress passed the [[Civil Rights Act of 1875]], legislation introduced by [[Charles Sumner]] and [[Benjamin F. Butler]] in 1870, and passed [[March 1]], [[1875]]. It guaranteed that everyone, regardless of race, color, or previous condition of servitude, was entitled to the same treatment in "public accommodations" (inns, public conveyances on land or water, theaters, and other places of public amusement).

In 1883, the Supreme Court restricted the Civil Rights Act of 1875 to actions by state and local government. It [[Civil Rights Cases|ruled]] Congress could not control private persons or corporations. After Congress passed the Civil Rights Act of 1875, it did not pass another civil rights law until 1957.

In 1890, Louisiana passed a law requiring separate accommodations for colored and white passengers on railroads. Louisiana law distinguished between "white," "black" and "colored" (that is, people of mixed white and black ancestry). The law already had provided that blacks could not ride with white people, but colored people could ride with whites prior to 1890. A group of concerned black, colored and white citizens in New Orleans formed an association dedicated to the repeal of the law. They persuaded [[Homer Plessy]], who was only one-eighth "Negro" and of fair complexion, to test it. In 1892, Plessy purchased a first-class ticket from New Orleans on the [[East Louisiana Railway]]. Once he had boarded the train, he informed the train conductor of his racial lineage and took a seat in the whites-only car. He was directed to leave that car and sit instead in the "coloreds only" car. Plessy refused and was immediately arrested. The Citizens Committee of New Orleans fought the case all the way to the Supreme Court of the United States.  They lost in 1896, and ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' resulted in 58 more years of legal discrimination against black and colored people in the United States. 

When black soldiers returning from [[World War II]] refused to put up with the second class citizenship of segregation, the movement for [[Civil Rights]] was renewed. The [[NAACP]] Legal Defense Committee (a group independent of the NAACP)&amp;mdash;and its lawyer [[Thurgood Marshall]]&amp;mdash;brought the landmark case ''[[Brown v. Board of Education|Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka]]'', {{ussc|347|483|1954}} before the Supreme Court. In 1954, the court unanimously overturned the 1896 Plessy decision in its ruling; Thurgood Marshall later became the first black [[List of Justices of the Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court Justice]].

==Legacy==
The Supreme Court of the United States held in the ''[[Civil Rights Cases]]'' 109 US 3 (1883) that the Fourteenth Amendment did not give the federal government the power to outlaw private discrimination, and then held in ''Plessy v. Ferguson'' 163 US 537 (1896) that Jim Crow laws were constitutional as long as they allowed for "separate but equal" facilities. In the years that followed, the court made this "separate but equal" requirement a hollow phrase by approving discrimination even in the face of evidence of profound inequalities in practice.

In 1902, Reverend [[Thomas Dixon, Jr.|Thomas Dixon]], a white Southern anti-Reconstructionist, published the novel ''[[The Leopard's Spots]]'', which intentionally fanned racial animosity. &lt;ref&gt;http://docsouth.unc.edu/dixonclan/bio.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Jim Crow laws were a product of the [[Solid South|solidly Democratic South]]. As the party which supported the Confederacy, the Democrats quickly dominated all aspects of local, state, and federal political life in the post-Civil War South, right up through the 1970s. As late as 1956, a resolution called [[Southern Manifesto]], condemning the Supreme Court's ruling in ''Brown v. Board of Education'', was read into the Congressional Record and supported by 96 southern congressmen and senators, each one a Democrat.

The Jim Crow laws were a major factor in [[Great Migration (African American)|the Great Migration]] during the early part of the 20th century, because opportunities were so limited in the South that African Americans moved in great numbers to northern cities to seek a better life.

While African-American entertainers, musicians, and literary figures had broken into the white world of American art and culture after 1890, African-American athletes found obstacles confronting them at every turn. By 1900, white opposition to African-American boxers, baseball players, track athletes, and basketball players kept them segregated and limited in what they could do. But their prowess and abilities in all-African-American teams and sporting events could not be denied, and the barriers to African-American participation in all the major sports began to crumble in the 1950s and 1960s.

==Twentieth century==
{{Progressivism}}
In the 20th century, the Supreme Court began to overturn Jim Crow laws on constitutional grounds. In ''[[Buchanan v. Warley]]'' 245 US 60 (1917), the court held that a [[Kentucky]] law could not require residential segregation. The Supreme Court in 1946, in ''[[Irene Morgan|Irene Morgan v. Virginia]]'' ruled segregation in interstate transportation to be unconstitutional, though its reasoning stemmed from the [[commerce clause]] of the Constitution rather than any moral objection to the practice. It was not until 1954 in ''Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka'' 347 US 483 that the court held that separate facilities were inherently unequal in the area of public schools, effectively overturning ''Plessy v. Ferguson'', and outlawing Jim Crow in other areas of society as well. This landmark case consisted of complaints filed in the states of Delaware (''[[Gebhart v. Belton]]''); South Carolina (''[[Briggs v. Elliott]]''); Virginia (''[[Davis v. County School Board of Prince Edward County]]''); and [[Washington, D.C.]] (''[[Bolling v. Sharpe|Spottswode Bolling v. C. Melvin Sharpe]]''). These decisions, along with other cases such as ''[[McLaurin v. Oklahoma State Board of Regents]]'' 339 US 637 (1950), ''[[NAACP v. Alabama]]'' 357 US 449 (1958), and ''[[Boynton v. Virginia]]'' 364 US 454 (1960), slowly dismantled the state-sponsored segregation imposed by Jim Crow laws. 

In addition to Jim Crow laws, in which the state compelled segregation of the races, businesses, political parties, unions and other private parties created their own Jim Crow arrangements, barring blacks from buying homes in certain neighborhoods, from shopping or working in certain stores, from working at certain trades, etc. The Supreme Court outlawed some forms of private discrimination in ''[[Shelley v. Kraemer]]'' 334 US 1 (1948), in which it held that "restrictive covenants" that barred sale of homes to blacks or [[Jew]]s or [[Asian people|Asian]]s were unconstitutional, on the grounds that they represented state-sponsored discrimination, in that they were only effective if the courts enforced them. 

The Supreme Court was unwilling, however, to attack other forms of private discrimination; it reasoned that private parties did not violate the [[Equal Protection]] clause of the Constitution when they discriminated, because they were not "state actors" covered by that clause. 

After World War II, as attitudes in the Federal courts turned against segregation, the segregationist white governments of many of the states of the Southeast countered with even more numerous and strict segregation laws on the local level until the start of the 1960s. The modern [[American Civil Rights Movement|Civil Rights movement]] is often considered{{Fact|date=June 2007}} to have been sparked by an act of [[civil disobedience]] against Jim Crow laws when [[Rosa Parks]], an African-American woman, refused to give up her seat on a bus to a white man after being ordered to do so by the bus driver. Her action, and the demonstrations that it spawned, led to a series of legislation and court decisions in which Jim Crow laws were repealed or annulled.

However, the [[Montgomery Bus Boycott]] led by Reverend [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]] which followed Rosa Parks' action, was not an isolated case. Numerous boycotts and demonstrations against segregation had occurred throughout the 1930s and 1940s. These early demonstrations achieved positive results and helped spark political activism. For instance, [[K. Leroy Irvis]] of [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania|Pittsburgh's]] Urban League led a demonstration against employment discrimination by Pittsburgh's department stores in 1947, and he became the first 20th century African-American to serve as a state Speaker of the House.

In 1964, the U.S. Congress attacked the parallel system of private Jim Crow practices. It invoked the [[commerce clause]] to pass the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], which outlawed discrimination in public accommodations (privately owned restaurants, hotels, and stores, and in private schools and workplaces). This use of the commerce clause was upheld in ''[[Heart of Atlanta Motel v. United States]]'' 379 US 241 (1964).

In 1971, the Supreme Court, in [[Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of Education]], upheld [[desegregation busing]] of students to achieve integration.

===End of ''de jure'' segregation===
[[Image:jimcrow.jpg|right|frame|A depiction of [[Thomas D. Rice]]'s "Jim Crow"]]

In January, 1964, President [[Lyndon Johnson]] met with civil rights leaders. On [[January 8]], during his first [[State of the Union (USA)|State of the Union address]], Johnson asked Congress to "let this session of Congress be known as the session which did more for civil rights than the last hundred sessions combined." On [[June 21]], civil rights workers [[Michael Schwerner]], [[Andrew Goodman]], and [[James Chaney]], disappeared in [[Neshoba County, Mississippi]]. The three were volunteers traveling to Mississippi to aid in the registration of African-American voters as part of the Mississippi Summer Project. The [[FBI]] recovered their bodies, which had been buried in an earthen dam, 44 days later. The Neshoba County deputy sheriff, [[Cecil Price]] and 16 others, all [[            ]] members, were indicted for the crimes; seven were convicted. On [[July 2]], President Johnson signed the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lbjlib.utexas.edu/johnson/lbjforkids/civil_timeline.shtm LBJ for Kids] CIVIL RIGHTS DURING THE JOHNSON ADMINISTRATION&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[United States Department of Justice]], "By 1965 concerted efforts to break the grip of state disfranchisement had been under way for some time, but had achieved only modest success overall and in some areas had proved almost entirely ineffectual. The murder of voting-rights activists in [[Philadelphia, Mississippi]], gained national attention, along with numerous other acts of violence and terrorism. Finally, the [[Selma_to_Montgomery_marches#First_march|unprovoked attack on March 7, 1965]], by state troopers on peaceful marchers crossing the [[Edmund Pettus Bridge]] in [[Selma, Alabama|Selma]], [[Alabama]], en route to the state capitol in [[Montgomery, Alabama|Montgomery]], persuaded the President and Congress to overcome Southern legislators' resistance to effective voting rights legislation. President Johnson issued a call for a strong voting rights law and hearings began soon thereafter on the bill that would become the Voting Rights Act."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usdoj.gov/crt/voting/intro/intro_b.htm United States Department of Justice] Introduction To Federal Voting Rights Laws&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{col-begin}}{{col-2}}
* [[Anti-miscegenation laws]]
* [[Black Codes in the USA]]
* [[Racial segregation in the United States]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Apartheid]]
* [[Carpetbagger]]
* [[Disfranchisement after the Civil War]]
* [[Dunning School]]
* [[Freedman]]
* [[Freedmen's Bureau]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Ghetto]]
* [[Group Areas Act]]
* [[Neoabolitionist]]
* [[Nuremberg laws]]
* [[Radical Republican]]
* [[Redeemers]]
* [[Redemption (U.S. history)]]
* [[Scalawag]]
* [[Second-class citizen]]
* [[Timeline of the African-American Civil Rights Movement]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Ayers, Edward L. ''The Promise of the New South'' Oxford University Press, 1992, a general history of the South in the late 19th century
* Barnes, Catherine A. ''Journey from Jim Crow: The Desegregation of Southern Transit'' [[Columbia University Press]], 1983. 
* Bartley, Numan V. ''The Rise of Massive Resistance: Race and Politics in the South during the 1950s'' [[Louisiana State University Press]], 1969.
* Bond, Horace Mann. “The Extent and Character of Separate Schools in the United States.” ''Journal of Negro Education'' 4(July 1935):321–27. online via JSTOR
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=283998&amp;high=%20Gabriel%20CHin Gabriel Chin &amp; Hrishi Karthikeyan, Preserving Racial Identity: Population Patterns and the Application of Anti-Miscegenation Statutes to Asians, 1910 to 1950, 9 Asian L.J. (2002)]
* Campbell, Nedra.  "More Justice, More Peace: The Black Person's Guide to the American Legal System" Lawrence Hill Books; Chicago Review Press], 2003, which includes in its chapter "Free at Last" a chronology of laws during the Jim Crow era. ISBN 1-55652-468-4
* Jane Dailey, Glenda Elizabeth Gilmore, and Bryant Simon, eds. ''Jumpin' Jim Crow: Southern Politics from Civil War to Civil Rights'' (2000), essays by scholars on impact of Jum Crow on black communities
* Fairclough, Adam. “‘Being in the Field of Education and Also Being a Negro…Seems…Tragic’: Black Teachers in the Jim Crow South.” ''Journal of American History'' 87 (June 2000): 65–91. online via JSTOR 
* Feldman, Glenn. ''Politics, Society, and the Klan in Alabama, 1915–1949''. [[University of Alabama Press]], 1999.
* Harvey Fireside,  ''Separate and Unequal: Homer Plessy and the Supreme Court Decision That Legalized Racism'',  2004. ISBN 0-7867-1293-7
* Eric Foner ''Reconstruction, America's Unfinished Revolution, 1863-1877: America's Unfinished Revolution, 1863-1877'' (Harpercollins, 1988), ISBN 0-06-015851-4, standard history of Reconstruction from [[neoabolitionist]] school
* Gaines, Kevin. ''Uplifting the Race: Black Leadership, Politics, and Culture in the Twentieth Century'' University of North Carolina Press, 1996. 
* Gaston, Paul M. ''The New South Creed: A Study in Southern Mythmaking'' Alfred A. Knopf, 1970. 
* Glenda Elizabeth Gilmore; ''Gender and Jim Crow Women and the Politics of                 in North Carolina, 1896-1920'' (1996)
* [[John Howard Griffin]] ''[[Black Like Me]]'' by (Signet, 1996) ISBN 0-451-19203-6. Author leaves privileged life as Southern white man and darkens his skin to experience segregation in the Deep South in 1959.
* Haws, Robert, ed. ''The Age of Segregation: Race Relations in the South, 1890– 1945'' [[University Press of Mississippi]], 1978. 
* Sheldon Hackney, ''Populism to Progressivism in Alabama'' (1969) 
* Johnson, Charles S. ''Patterns of Negro Segregation'' Harper and Brothers, 1943. 
* Michael J. Klarman; ''From Jim Crow to Civil Rights: The Supreme Court and the Struggle for Racial Equality'' [[Oxford University Press]], 2004 
* Leon F. Litwack, ''Trouble in Mind: Black Southerners in the Age of Jim Crow'' (Alfred A. Knopf: 1998) "This is the most complete and moving account we have had of what the victims of the Jim Crow South suffered and somehow endured" — C. Vann Woodward
* Stephen Kantrowitz. ''Ben Tillman &amp; the Reconstruction of                '' (2000) 
* McMillen, Neil R. ''Dark Journey: Black Mississippians in the Age of Jim Crow. '' [[University of Illinois Press]], 1989. 
* Keith Weldon Medley, ''We As Freemen: Plessy v. Ferguson'' by  Pelican Publishing Company, March, 2003. ISBN 1-58980-120-2. Popular story of Homer Plessy, who lost his case before the Supreme Court; the case legalized segregation in the U.S. for the next 58 years.
* Myrdal, Gunnar. ''An American Dilemma: The Negro Problem and Modern Democracy'' Harper and Row, 1944. the most detailed analysis of the Jim Crow system in operation.
* Percy, William Alexander. ''Lanterns on the Levee: Recollections of a Planter's Son.'' 1941. Reprint, [[Louisiana State University Press]], 1993. by conservative white planter
* Rabinowitz, Howard N. ''Race Relations in the Urban South, 1856–1890'' (1978)
* J. Douglas Smith; ''Managing                : Race, Politics, and Citizenship in Jim Crow Virginia'' [[University of North Carolina Press]], 2002 
* Smith, J. Douglas. “The Campaign for Racial Purity and the Erosion of Paternalism in Virginia, 1922–1930: “Nominally White, Biologically Mixed, and Legally Negro.’” ''Journal of Southern History'' 68 (February 2002): 65–106. 
* Smith, J. Douglas. “Patrolling the Boundaries of Race: Motion Picture Censorship and Jim Crow in Virginia, 1922–1932.” ''Historical Journal of Film, Radio, and Television'' 21 (August 2001): 273–91. 
* Sterner, Richard.   ''The Negro's Share'' (1943) detailed statistics 
* C. Vann Woodward. ''The Strange Career of Jim Crow'' (1955) the classic history by Pulitzer prize winner. 
* C. Vann Woodward. ''The Origins of the New South: 1877-1913'' (1951).

==External links==
* [http://www.jimcrowhistory.org/resources/lessonplans/hs_es_etiquette.htm Racial Etiquette: The Racial Customs and Rules of Racial Behavior in Jim Crow America] - A detailed article outlining the basics of Jim Crow etiquette.
* [http://www.ferris.edu/jimcrow/ Jim Crow Museum of Racist Memorabilia]
* [http://www.ferris.edu/news/jimcrow/newforms/ An article on "New Racist Forms: Jim Crow in the 21st Century"]
* [http://www.robinwashington.com/jimcrow/1_home.html "You Don't Have to Ride Jim Crow!"] PBS documentary on first Freedom Ride, in 1947
* [http://www.jimcrowhistory.org/scripts/jimcrow/courtcases.cgi?casetype=Segregation The History of Jim Crow]
* [http://californiaccw.org/files/sf-chronicle-article.htm A 1923 article in the SF Chronicle] lauding California's Jim Crow handgun law, which is still in force today
* [http://afroamhistory.about.com/cs/jimcrowlaws/a/jimcrowlaws.htm List of laws enacted in various states]
*[http://www.newsreel.org/nav/title.asp?tc=CN0147&amp;s=Jim%20Crow Video: The Rise and Fall of Jim Crow]
*[http://www.newsreel.org/nav/title.asp?tc=CN0088&amp;s=Jim%20Crow Video: The Strange Demise of Jim Crow]
*[http://www.ferris.edu/news/jimcrow/what.htm Ferris University page] about Jim Crow
*[http://www.pbs.org/wnet/jimcrow/index.html PBS] page about a relevant program
**[http://www.pbs.org/wnet/jimcrow/themap/map.html Interactive map of Jim Crow laws by state]
{{Aafooter}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}} 
{{Types of Segregation|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jim Crow}}
[[Category:History of racial segregation in the United States]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Reconstruction]]
[[Category:Discrimination in the United States]]
[[Category:Legal history of the United States]]
[[Category:African-American history]]
[[Category:American political terms]]
[[Category:Race legislation in the United States]]
[[Category:United States repealed legislation]]
[[Category:Race-related legal issues]]

[[de:Jim Crow]]
[[fr:Lois Jim Crow]]
[[id:Jim Crow]]
[[it:Jim Crow]]
[[nl:Jim Crow-wetten]]
[[ja:ジム・クロウ法]]
[[pl:Prawa Jim Crow]]
[[pt:Leis de Jim Crow]]
[[ru:Законы Джима Кроу]]
[[fi:Jim Crow -lait]]
[[sv:Jim Crow-lagar]]
[[tr:Jim Crow]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>