<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051109134305|27819688" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19481110" pageid="19481110" ns="0" title="Jim Crow laws"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-09T13:57:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In the [[United States]], the '''Jim Crow laws''' were made to enforce [[racial segregation]], and included laws that would prevent [[Black (people)|black]] people from doing things that a [[White (people)|white]] person could do. For instance, Jim Crow laws regulated separate use of water fountains, public bath houses, and separate seating sections on [[public transportation|public transport]]. Jim Crow laws varied among communities and states.  The term is not applied to all racist laws, but only to those passed post-[[Reconstruction]] starting in about [[1890]], the start of a period of worsening race relations in the United States. Similar laws passed immediately after the civil war were called the [[Black Codes]]. These were the codes that transformed into the Jim Crow laws of the twentieth century. The name comes from the character in a negro minstrel song written by [[Thomas D. Rice]].

==Early history== 
The conclusion of the [[American Civil War]] in [[1865]] led to the policy of [[Reconstruction]], in which the Federal government intervened to protect the rights conferred on black Americans by the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th]], [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th]], and [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|15th]] Amendments to the [[United States Constitution]], as well as (upon their introductions) the [[Civil Rights Act of 1866]] and the [[Civil Rights Act of 1875]]. In almost-immediate response Southern legislatures passed the [[black codes]], which attempted to return freed [[slavery|slaves]] to bondage in legal fact, rather than official terminology.

This government-controlled Reconstruction ended by [[1877]]. In its aftermath the resurgent white elites, who referred to themselves as [[Redeemers]], reversed many of the civil rights gains that black Americans had made during Reconstruction, passing laws that mandated discrimination by both local governments and by private citizens. These became known as the '''Jim Crow laws''', a reference to the character Jim Crow (popular in [[antebellum]] [[minstrel]] entertainment) that was a racist stage depiction of a poor and uneducated rural black. Since '''Jim Crow law''' is a blanket term for any of this type of legislation following the end of Reconstruction, the exact date of inception for the laws is difficult to isolate; common consensus points to the [[1890s]] and the adoption of segregational railroad legislation in New Orleans as the first genuine "Jim Crow" law. By [[1915]] every Southern state had effectively destroyed any gains in civil liberties that blacks had enjoyed due to the Reconstructionist efforts.

As an example, many state governments prevented blacks from voting by requiring [[poll tax]]es and [[literacy test]]s, both of which were not enforced on whites of British descent due to [[grandfather clause]]s.  One common "literacy test" was to require the black would-be voter to recite the entire [[United States Constitution|U.S. Constitution]] and [[United States Declaration of Independence|Declaration of Independence]] from memory.  

The [[Supreme Court of the United States]] held in the ''[[Civil Rights Cases]]'' 109 US 3 ([[1883]]) that the Fourteenth Amendment did not give the federal government the power to outlaw private discrimination, then held in ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' 163 US 537 ([[1896]]) that Jim Crow laws were constitutional as long as they allowed for [[separate but equal]] facilities. In the years that followed, the Court made this "separate but equal" requirement a hollow phrase by approving discrimination even in the face of evidence of profound inequalities in practice.

It is estimated that of 181,471 African-American males of voting age in [[Alabama]] in [[1900]], only 3,000 were registered. 

In [[1902]], Reverend [[Thomas Dixon]] published the novel ''[[The Leopard's Spots]]'', which intentionally fanned racial animosity.

==Twentieth century== 
[[Image:ColoredDrinking.jpg|thumb|250px|An "[[African American]]" drinks out of a segregated water cooler designated for "colored" patrons in 1939 at a streetcar terminal in Oklahoma City.]]

The Supreme Court began to overturn Jim Crow laws on constitutional grounds in the 20th century. The Supreme Court held in ''[[Guinn v. United States]]'' 238 US 347 ([[1915]]) that an [[Oklahoma]] law that denied the right to vote to some citizens was unconstitutional. (Nonetheless, the majority of African Americans were unable to vote in most states in the [[Deep South]] of the USA until the [[1950s]] or [[1960s]].) In ''[[Buchanan v. Warley]]'' 245 US 60 ([[1917]]), the Court held that a [[Kentucky]] law could not require residential segregation. The court outlawed the [[white primary]] in ''[[Smith v. Allwright]]'' 321 US 649 ([[1944]]), and in [[1946]] in ''[[Irene Morgan]] v. Virginia'' ruled segregation in interstate transportation to be unconstitutional, though its reasoning stemmed from the [[commerce clause]] of the Constitution rather than any moral objection to the practice. It wasn't until [[1954]] in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]] of [[Topeka]]'' 347 US 483 that the Court held that separate facilities were inherently unequal in the area of public schools, effectively overturning [[Plessy v. Ferguson]] to outlaw Jim Crow in other areas of society as well. These decisions, along with other cases such as ''[[McLaurin v. Oklahoma State Board of Regents]]'' 339 US 637 ([[1950]]), ''[[NAACP v. Alabama]]'' 357 US 449 ([[1958]]), and ''[[Boynton v. Virginia]]'' 364 US 454 ([[1960]]), slowly dismantled the state-sponsored segregation imposed by Jim Crow laws. 

In addition to Jim Crow laws, in which the state compelled segregation of the races, businesses, political parties, unions and other private parties created their own Jim Crow arrangements, barring blacks from buying homes in certain neighborhoods, from shopping or working in certain stores, from working at certain trades, etc. The Supreme Court outlawed some forms of private discrimination in ''[[Shelley v. Kraemer]]'' 334 US 1 ([[1948]]), in which it held that "restrictive covenants" that barred sale of homes to blacks or Jews or Asians were unconstitutional, on the ground that they represented state-sponsored discrimination in that they were only effective if the courts enforced them. 

The Supreme Court was unwilling, however, to attack other forms of private discrimination; it reasoned that private parties did not violate the [[Equal Protection]] clause of the Constitution when they discriminated because they were not "state actors" covered by that clause. 

As attitudes turned against segregation in the Federal courts after [[World War II]], the segregationist white governments of many of the states of the South East countered with even more numerous and strict segregation laws on the local level until the start of the 1960s. The modern [[American Civil Rights Movement|civil rights movement]] is often considered to have been sparked by an act of [[civil disobedience]] against Jim Crow laws when [[Rosa Parks]], an African-American woman, refused to give up her seat on a bus to a white man. This led to a series of legislation and court decisions in which Jim Crow laws were repealed or annulled.

However, the [[Montgomery Bus Boycott]] led by Rev. Martin Luther King, Jr., which followed Rosa Parks' unplanned decision not to give up her seat, did not come in a vacuum.  Numerous boycotts and demonstrations against segregation had occurred throughout the 1930's and 1940's. These early demonstrations achieved positive results and helped spark political activism.  For instance, K. Leroy Irvis of Pittsburgh's Urban League led a demonstration against employment discrimination by Pittsburgh's department stores in 1947, and later became the first 20th Century African American to serve as a state Speaker of the House.

In [[1964]] the [[Congress of the United States|U.S. Congress]] invoked the [[commerce clause]] to pass the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], which outlawed discrimination in public accommodations, i.e., privately owned restaurants, hotels and stores, and in private schools and workplaces, that Congress attacked the parallel system of private Jim Crow practices. This use of the Commerce clause was upheld in ''[[Heart of Atlanta Motel v. United States]]'' 379 US 241 ([[1964]]).

==The Name== 
[[Image:jimcrow.jpg|right|frame|A depiction of [[Thomas D. Rice]]'s "Jim Crow"]]
The term ''Jim Crow'' comes from the [[minstrel show]] song "[[Jump Jim Crow]]" written in [[1828]] and performed by Thomas Dartmouth "Daddy" Rice, a white English migrant to the U.S., the originator of [[blackface]] performance. The song and blackface itself were an immediate hit. "Jim Crow" became a standard character in Minstrel shows, being a caricature of a shabbily dressed rural black; "Jim Crow" was often paired with the character "Zip Coon," a flamboyantly dressed urban black who associated more into [[White (people)|white]] culture. By [[1837]], ''Jim Crow'' was being used to refer to racial segregation.



==References==
* [[John Howard Griffin]].  ''[[Black Like Me]]''.  Signet,  [[1996]]. ISBN 0451192036

==External links==
* [http://www.jimcrowhistory.org/resources/lessonplans/hs_es_etiquette.htm Racial Etiquette: The Racial Customs and Rules of Racial Behavior in Jim Crow America] - A detailed article outlining the basics of Jim Crow etiquette.
* [http://www.ferris.edu/news/jimcrow/what.htm What Was Jim Crow?]
*[http://www.ferris.edu/news/jimcrow/newforms/ An article on "New Racist Forms: Jim Crow in the 21st Century"]
*[http://www.robinwashington.com/jimcrow/1_home.html "You Don't Have to Ride Jim Crow!"] PBS documentary on first Freedom Ride, in 1947
*[http://www.jimcrowhistory.org/scripts/jimcrow/courtcases.cgi?casetype=Segregation The History of Jim Crow]

[[Category:U.S. civil rights history]]
[[Category:Reconstruction]]
[[Category:United States legal history]]
[[Category:African-American history]]

[[de:Jim Crow]]
[[nl:Jim Crow-wetten]]
[[ru:Законы Джима Кроу]]
[[sv:Jim Crow]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>