<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050928163252|24242585" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="191537" pageid="191537" ns="0" title="Internment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-09T16:28:52Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{dablink|Internment coming from the same root of "confinement" could also refer to [[burial]].}}
The word '''internment''' is generally used to refer to the imprisonment or confinement of people, generally in [[prison camp]]s or [[prison]]s, without due process of law and a trial.  It also refers to the practice of [[neutral country|neutral countries]] in time of [[war]] to hold belligerent [[armed forces]] and equipment which enter their territory, under the [[Second Hague Convention]].

==United States==
In reaction to the bombing of [[Pearl Harbor]] by [[Japan]] in [[1941]], [[United States]] [[Executive Order 9066]] on [[February 19]], [[1942]] allowed military commanders to designate areas "from which any or all persons may be excluded."  Under this order all Japanese and [[Japanese American|Americans of Japanese ancestry]] were removed from Western coastal regions to guarded camps in [[Arkansas]], [[Oregon]], [[Washington]], [[Wyoming]], [[Colorado]] and [[Arizona]]; [[Germany|German]] and [[Italy|Italian]] citizens, permanent residents, and American citizens of those respective ancestories (and American citizen family members) were removed from (among other places) the West and [[East Coast of the United States|East Coast]] and relocated or interned, and roughly one-third of the US was declared an exclusionary zone.

Almost 120,000 Japanese Americans and resident Japanese aliens would eventually be removed from their homes as part of the single largest forced relocation in U.S. history.

:''See: [[Japanese internment in the United States]]''

Following the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]] at least 2 US citizens, [[José Padilla]] and another, have been detained without charge, trial or [[prisoner of war]] status by order of the [[President]] as "enemy combatants", without [[Congress]] passing a [[statute]] allowing internment. 

Hundreds of detainees are also imprisoned at US [[Camp Delta]] at [[Guantanamo Bay]] on the island of Cuba. They have all been denied prisoner of war status and most have yet to be charged with a crime. [[Human Rights Watch]] says they must legally be treated as prisoners of war since an independent tribunal has not ruled that any of them are unlawful combatants on an individual basis. Those who have been charged face Military Commissions (rather than [[courts-martial]] or [[civilian]] federal courts) and this has been condemned by many as unfair.

The majority of the detainees are suspected [[Afghanistan|Afghan]] soldiers and [[Al Qaeda]] militants captured by US troops in [[Afghanistan]]. However, several were [[kidnap]]ped or illicitly transferred from other countries with which the US is not at war. A British national was captured by the [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]] in [[Pakistan]], apparently with the collusion of security forces. His transfer was a violation of Pakistani law because he was not [[extradite]]d. Several men were allegedly abducted by the CIA in Bosnia after a Human Rights Court (which had been set up with US help in the aftermath of ethnic cleansing and war) ruled that the Americans must release them.

==Britain==
During [[World War II]], about 8,000 people were interned in [[United Kingdom|Britain]], many on the [[Isle of Man]].  They included [[enemy alien]]s, refugees who had fled from [[Germany]], and suspected British [[Nazi]] sympathisers, such as [[British Union of Fascists]] leader [[Oswald Mosley]]. British nationals were detained under [[Defence Regulation 18B]]. Initially they were shipped overseas, but that was halted when a German [[U boat]] sank the SS ''[[Arandora Star]]'' in July [[1940]] with the loss of 800 internees, though this was not the first loss that had occurred.  The last internees were released late in [[1945]], though many were released in [[1942]].  In Britain, internees were housed in camps and prisons.  Some camps had tents rather than buildings with internees sleeping directly on the ground.  Men and women were separated and most contact with the outside world was denied.  A number of prominent Britons including writer [[H. G. Wells]] campaigned against the internment of refugees.

Initially the British government rounded up 74,000 German and [[Austria]]n aliens, but within 6 months the 112 alien tribunals had individually summoned and examined 64,000 aliens, designated them as "friendly aliens" and freed them from internment with no special restrictions, eventually only 2,000 of the remainder were interned.

Overseas, British citizens were also interned by the [[Axis Powers]].

During [[The Troubles]] suspected members of paramilitary groups were imprisoned without trial from August 9, 1971 following [[Operation Demetrius]]. Many were held at [[Maze (HM Prison)|HM Prison Maze]].

Following the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]], the [[Anti-Terrorism, Crime and Security Act 2001]] was passed allowing the indefinite detention without charge, trial or [[prisoner of war]] status, of foreigners designated "suspected international terrorists" by the [[Home Secretary]], but cannot be deported under existing immigration powers because they may face [[human rights abuses]]. In order to pass this statute, the British government declared a [[state of emergency]] and opted out of part of the [[European Convention on Human Rights]] referring to the right to liberty. The internees can choose to leave Britain voluntarily, if any other country lets them in. The legislation was judged to be illegal by the British courts and so [[HMG]] has initiated house arrest under temporay legislation.

==Northern Ireland==
One of most famous example of modern ''internment''&amp;mdash;and one which made world headlines&amp;mdash;occurred in [[Northern Ireland]] in [[1971]], when hundreds of [[Irish nationalism|nationalists]] and [[Irish republicanism|republicans]] were arrested by the [[British Army]] and the [[Royal Ulster Constabulary]] on the orders of the then [[Prime Minister of Northern Ireland]], [[Brian Faulkner]], with the backing of the [[British government]]. Historians generally view that period of internment as inflaming [[sectarian]] tensions in Northern Ireland while failing in its stated aim of arresting members of the paramilitary [[Provisional IRA]], because many of the people arrested were completely unconnected with that organisation but had had their names appear on the list of those to be interned through bungling and incompetence, and over 100 [[IRA]] men escaped arrest. The backlash against internment and its bungled application contributed to the decision of the British government under Prime Minister [[Edward Heath]] to suspend the [[Stormont government]]al system in Northern Ireland and replace it with ''direct rule'' from London, under the authority of a British [[Secretary of State for Northern Ireland]].

From 1971 internment began, beginning with the arrest of 342 suspected republican guerrillas and paramilitary members on August 9. They were held at [[Her Majesty's Prison Service|HM Prison]] [[Maze (HM Prison)|Maze]]. By 1972, 924 men were interned. Serious rioting ensued, and 23 people died in three days. The [[British government]] attempted to show some balance by arresting some [[loyalist]] paramilitaries later, but out of the 1,981 men interned, only 107 were loyalists. Internment was ended in 1975, but had resulted in increased support for the IRA and created political tensions which culminated in the [[1981 Irish Hunger Strike]] and the death of [[Bobby Sands]] MP. The imprisonment of people under anti-terrorism laws specific to Northern Ireland continued until the [[Good Friday Agreement]] of 1998, but these laws required the right to a fair trial be respected. However non-jury [[Diplock court]]s tried paramilitary-related trials, to prevent jury intimidation.

Many of those interned were held in a prison called Long Kesh, later known as the [[Maze (HM Prison)|Maze Prison]] outside [[Belfast]]. 

The republican song ''[[The Men Behind the Wire]]'' was composed in response to the internment.

Internment had previously been used as a means of repressing the [[Irish Republican Army]]. It was used between 1939 - 1945 and 1956 - 1962.  On all these occasions, internment has had a somewhat limited success.

==Republic of Ireland==

Internment has also been used as a means of suppressing the [[Irish Republican Army]] in the [[Republic of Ireland]]. It was used during and after the [[Irish Civil War]] (June 1922–April 1923), between 1939 and 1945 to safeguard the state's neutrality during [[WWII]] (''[[the Emergency]]''), and between 1956 and 1962 during the IRA's [[Border Campaign (IRA)|Border Campaign]].

== Canada ==
This nation has had numerous internments during times of war.  Property confiscation was common and there have been numerous movements for compensation with varying levels of success. 

In [[World War I]], 8,579 male "aliens of enemy nationality" were interned, including 5,954 [[Austro-Hungarian]]s, most of whom were probably ethnic [[Ukrainians]].  Many of these internees were used for [[forced labor]] in internment camps, including the creation of [[Banff National Park]].  See [[Ukrainian Canadian internment]].

In [[World War II]], some [[Germans]] and [[Italians]] were interned. [[Japan|Japanese]] and [[Japanese Canadians]] were singled out, and thousands of Canadian families had their belongings confiscated, were separated and interned.  See [[Japanese Canadian internment]].

=== External links ===
* [http://www.infoukes.com/history/internment/ Internment of Ukrainians in Canada 1914-1920] at InfoUkes
* [http://www.infoukes.com/history/internment/booklet02/doc-042.html Re: internment of Ukrainian Canadians] by Orest Martynowych, Ukrainian Weekly

==See also==
*[[Concentration camp]]
*[[Defence Regulation 18B]]
*[[Enemy alien]]
*[[Habeas corpus]]
*[[House arrest]]

[[Category:Imprisonment and detention]]
[[Category:Internments| ]]
[[de:Internierung]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>