<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101115101242|396880511" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="191537" pageid="191537" ns="0" title="Internment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-15T10:16:28Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Merge|administrative detention|date=September 2010}}
{{Distinguish|interment|internship}}
{{Dablink|This article is about the usage and history of the terms concentration camp, internment camp and internment. For a listing of individual camps, see [[List of concentration and internment camps]]. For German concentration camps during World War II, see [[Nazi concentration camps]]. For the period of detention without trial in Northern Ireland in the 1970s, see [[Operation Demetrius]]. For the internment of Japanese living in North America during World War II, see [[Japanese American internment]] and [[Japanese Canadian internment]].}}
&lt;!-- {{otheruses}} Disambig page exists, but nothing is there. If more is added, feel free to uncomment. --&gt;
[[Image:Japanese internment camp in British Columbia.jpg|thumb|[[Japanese Canadian internment|Internment]] camp for [[Japanese-Canadian]]s in [[British Columbia]] during [[World War II]].]]

'''Internment''' is the imprisonment or confinement&lt;ref&gt;per Oxford Universal Dictionary, 1st edition 1933.&lt;/ref&gt; of people, commonly in large groups, without trial. The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' (1989) gives the meaning as: "The action of 'interning'; confinement within the limits of a country or place." Most modern usage is about individuals, and there is a distinction between '''internment''', which is being confined usually for preventive or political reasons, and imprisonment, which is being closely confined as a punishment for crime.

''Internment'' also refers to the practice of [[neutral country|neutral countries]] in time of war in detaining belligerent armed forces and equipment in their territories under the [[Hague Conventions (1899 and 1907)#Hague Convention of 1907|Second Hague Convention]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/lawofwar/hague05.htm The Second Hague Convention, 1907]&lt;/ref&gt;.

Early civilizations such as [[Assyria]] used [[forced resettlement]] of populations as a means of controlling territory,&lt;ref&gt;[http://eawc.evansville.edu/anthology/hammurabi.htm Laws of Hammurabi]&lt;/ref&gt; but it was not until much later in the late 19th and the 20th centuries that records exist of groups of civilian non-combatants being concentrated into large prison camps.

The [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] strictly prohibits internment. Article 9 states that "No one shall be subjected to [[Arbitrary arrest and detention|arbitrary arrest]], [[detention (imprisonment)|detention]] or exile."

==Internment camps==
An internment camp  is a large [[Detention (Imprisonment)|detention]] center created for political opponents, [[enemy aliens]], people with [[mental illness]], members of specific ethnic or religious groups, civilian inhabitants of a critical war-zone, or other groups of people, usually during a war. The term is used for facilities where the inmates were selected by some generalized criteria, rather than detained as individuals after [[due process of law]] fairly applied by a [[judiciary]].

As a result of the mistreatment of civilians interned during recent conflicts, the [[Fourth Geneva Convention]] was established in 1949 to provide for the protection of civilians during times of war "in the hands" of an enemy and under any occupation by a foreign power.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icrc.org/ihl.nsf/FULL/380?OpenDocument Full text of 4th Geneva Convention]&lt;/ref&gt; It was ratified by 194 nations. [[Prisoner-of-war camp]]s are  internment camps intended specifically for holding members of an enemy's armed forces as defined in the [[Third Geneva Convention]], and the treatment of whom is specified in that Convention.

==Concentration camps==
[[Image:Boercamp1.jpg|thumb|left|[[Boer]] women and children in a [[United Kingdom|British]]-run concentration camp in South Africa (1900-1902)]]
The [[Random House Dictionary]] defines the term "concentration camp" as: "a guarded compound for the detention or imprisonment of aliens, members of ethnic minorities, political opponents, etc.", and, the [[American Heritage Dictionary]] defines it as: "A camp where civilians, enemy aliens, political prisoners, and sometimes prisoners of war are detained and confined, typically under harsh conditions."

=== US and Spanish Camps and first usage of the word re-concentration camp===
The earliest of these camps may have been those set up in the [[United States]] for [[Cherokee removal|Cherokee]] and other [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]]s in the 1830s; however, the term originated in the ''reconcentrados'' (reconcentration camps) set up by the [[Spain under the Restoration|Spanish military]] in [[Cuba]] during the [[Ten Years' War]] (1868–1878) and by the [[United States]] during the [[Philippine–American War]] (1899–1902).&lt;ref name = "columbia"&gt;Concentration Camp. The Columbia Encyclopedia, Sixth Edition, 2008.Columbia University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;.

===British Camps and the Boer War===
The [[English language|English]] term "concentration camp" grew in prominence during the [[Second Boer War]] (1899–1902), when they were operated by the British in South Africa.&lt;ref name = "columbia"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-sul.stanford.edu/africa/boers.html Documents re camps in Boer War]&lt;/ref&gt;

There were a total of 45 tented camps built for Boer internees and 64 for black Africans. Of the 28,000 Boer men captured as prisoners of war, 25,630 were sent overseas. The vast majority of Boers remaining in the local camps were women and children. Over 26,000 women and children were to perish in these concentration camps.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

===Russian Camps in Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth===
Polish historian Władysław Konopczyński has suggested the first concentration camps were created in [[Poland]] in the 18th century, during the [[Bar Confederation]] rebellion, when the [[Russian Empire]] established three concentration camps for Polish rebel captives awaiting deportation to [[Siberia]].&lt;ref&gt;Konopczyński, Władysław. (1991) '' Konfederacja barska, t. II'', pp. 733-734.&lt;/ref&gt;

Use of the word ''concentration'' comes from the idea of ''concentrating'' a group of people who are in some way undesirable in one place, where they can be watched by those who incarcerated them. For example, in a time of insurgency, potential supporters of the insurgents may be placed where they cannot provide supplies or information.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

===Nazi German camps===
{{Main|Nazi concentration camps}}
{{citations missing|section|date=November 2010}}
[[Image:Buchenwald Slave Laborers Liberation.jpg|thumb|Jewish slave laborers in the [[Buchenwald concentration camp]] near Jena, 16 April 1945.]]
During the 20th century, the arbitrary internment of civilians by the state reached a climax with [[Nazi concentration camps]] (1933–1945). As a result, the term "concentration camp" carries many of the connotations of "death camp" or "extermination camp", and is sometimes used synonymously.

However, even Nazi concentration camps were not necessarily death camps. For example, some camps were sources of [[slavery|slave labor]]: the inmates were exploited rather than killed, although many were worked to death or killed for refusing to work.

Because of these negative connotations, the term "concentration camp", originally itself a euphemism, has been replaced by newer euphemisms such as ''internment camp'', ''resettlement camp'', and ''detention facility'', regardless of the actual circumstances of these camps, which vary a great deal.

==Northern Ireland==
[[Operation Demetrius]] (or '''internment''' as it is more commonly known) began in [[Northern Ireland]] on the morning of Monday 9 August 1971. Operation Demetrius was launched by the [[British Army]] and [[Royal Ulster Constabulary]] and involved arresting and [[internment|interning]] (without [[Trial (law)|trial]]) people accused of being [[paramilitary]] members. During the operation, the British Army killed 10 civilians&lt;ref&gt;[http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/events/intern/chron.htm Internment - A Chronology of the Main Events]&lt;/ref&gt; and detained 342 people, leading to widespread protests and rioting.

==List of camps==
{{Main|List of concentration and internment camps}}

==See also==
*[[Civilian Internee]]
*[[List of concentration and internment camps]]
*[[Prisoner-of-war camp]]
*[[Extermination camp]]
*[[Labor camp]]s
*[[Quasi-criminal]]
*[[Extrajudicial detention]]

==References==
{{Reflist|1}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

[[Category:Internments| ]]

[[af:Konsentrasiekamp]]
[[ar:معسكر اعتقال]]
[[bs:Koncentracioni logor]]
[[br:Kampoù-bac'h]]
[[bg:Концентрационен лагер]]
[[ca:Camp de concentració]]
[[cs:Koncentrační tábor]]
[[cy:Gwersyll crynhoi]]
[[da:Koncentrationslejr]]
[[de:Konzentrationslager (historischer Begriff)]]
[[es:Campo de concentración]]
[[eo:Koncentrejo]]
[[eu:Kontzentrazio-esparru]]
[[fr:Camp de concentration]]
[[gl:Campo de concentración]]
[[hr:Sabirni logor]]
[[io:Koncentreso-kampeyo]]
[[id:Kamp konsentrasi]]
[[it:Campo di concentramento]]
[[he:מחנה ריכוז]]
[[sw:Makambi ya KZ]]
[[la:Castra carceralia]]
[[lv:Koncentrācijas nometne]]
[[lt:Koncentracijos stovykla]]
[[hu:Koncentrációs tábor]]
[[mk:Концентрационен логор]]
[[nl:Concentratiekamp]]
[[ja:強制収容所]]
[[no:Konsentrasjonsleir]]
[[nn:Konsentrasjonsleir]]
[[pl:Obóz koncentracyjny]]
[[pt:Campo de concentração]]
[[ro:Lagăr de concentrare]]
[[ru:Концентрационный лагерь]]
[[simple:Concentration camp]]
[[sk:Koncentračný tábor]]
[[sl:Koncentracijsko taborišče]]
[[sr:Концентрациони логор]]
[[fi:Keskitysleiri]]
[[sv:Koncentrationsläger]]
[[uk:Концентраційний табір]]
[[ur:بیگار کیمپ]]
[[vi:Trại tập trung]]
[[yi:קאנצענטראציע לאגער]]
[[zh:集中营]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>