<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071105203148|169446946" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="191537" pageid="191537" ns="0" title="Internment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-12T22:43:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{dablink|This article is about the usage and history of the terms concentration camp, internment camp and internment. For a listing of individual camps, see [[List of concentration and internment camps]].  For German concentration camps during World War II, see [[Nazi concentration camps]]}}
&lt;!-- {{otheruses}}Disambig page exists, but nothing there- if more is added, feel free to uncomment. --&gt; 
[[Image:Japanese internment camp in British Columbia.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Japanese Canadian internment|Internment]] camp for Japanese in Canada during [[World War II]]]]
'''Internment''' is the imprisonment or confinement&lt;ref&gt;per Oxford Universal Dictionary, 1st edition 1933.&lt;/ref&gt; of people, commonly in large groups, without trial.  The ''Oxford English Dictionary'' (1989) gives the meaning as "The action of ‘interning’; confinement within the limits of a country or place". Most modern usage is about individuals, and there is a distinction between '''internment''', which is being confined usually for preventative or political reasons, and imprisonment, which is being closely confined as a punishment for crime. "Internment" also refers to the practice of [[neutral country|neutral countries]] in time of [[war]] in detaining belligerent [[armed forces]] and equipment in their territories under the [[Hague Conventions (1899 and 1907)#Hague Convention of 1907|Second Hague Convention]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/lawofwar/hague05.htm The Second Hague Convention, 1907]&lt;/ref&gt;.

Early civilizations such as the [[Assyria]]ns used forced resettlement of populations as a means of controlling territory&lt;ref&gt;[http://eawc.evansville.edu/anthology/hammurabi.htm Laws of Hammurabi]&lt;/ref&gt;, but it was not until much later in the late 19th and the 20th centuries that records exist of groups of civilian non-combatants being concentrated into large prison camps.

==Internment camps==
An internment camp  is a large [[Detention (Imprisonment)|detention]] center created for [[political dissent|political opponents]], [[enemy aliens]], people with [[mental illness]], specific [[ethnic group|ethnic]] or [[religion|religious groups]], [[civilian]]s of a critical [[war]]-zone, or other groups of people, usually during a war. The term is used for facilities where inmates are selected according to some specific criteria, rather than individuals who are [[incarcerated]] after [[due process of law]] fairly applied by a [[judiciary]].

As a result of mistreatment of [[civilians]] interned during recent conflicts, the [[Fourth Geneva Convention]] was established in 1949 to provide for the protection of civilians during times of war "in the hands" of an enemy and under any occupation by a foreign power&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icrc.org/ihl.nsf/FULL/380?OpenDocument  Full text of 4th Geneva Convention]&lt;/ref&gt;. It was ratified by 194 nations. [[Prisoner-of-war camp]]s are  internment camps intended specifically for holding members of an enemy's [[armed forces]] as defined in the [[Third Geneva Convention]], and the treatment of whom is specified in that Convention. 

=== Concentration camp ===
[[Image:Boercamp1.jpg|thumb|250px|left|[[Boer]] women and children in a South African concentration camp]]
The [[Oxford English Dictionary]], 2nd ed. defines ''concentration camp'' as: ''a camp where non-combatants of a district are accommodated, such as those instituted by [[Horatio Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener|Lord Kitchener]] during the [[South African War|South African war]] of 1899-1902; one for the internment of political prisoners, foreign nationals, etc., esp. as organized by the Nazi regime in Germany before and during the war of 1939-45''.

The term "concentration camp" was coined at this time to signify the "concentration" of a large number of people in one place and comes from the Spanish "re-concentration"&lt;ref&gt;War and genocide in Cuba, 1895-1898, John Lawrence Tone&lt;/ref&gt;. It was used to describe both the camps established by the Spanish to support an anti-insurgency campaign in [[Cuba]] (circa 1895-1898 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spanamwar.com/proctorspeech.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;), although at least some Spanish sources disagree with the comparison&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.loc.gov/rr/hispanic/1898/weyler.html]&lt;/ref&gt;, and soon after in [[South Africa]] (1899-1902), during the [[Second Boer War]]. During the war to retain [[Cuba]] (1895-98), the general [[Valeriano Weyler y Nicolau]] (nicknamed the "butcher") created a system of "re-concentration", in which all inhabitants were given eight days to move to camps. If the inhabitants refused and stayed outside, they were considered enemies and killed&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historyofcuba.com/history/scaw/scaw1a.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;. Although, Spain lost this war, the British army translated the Spanish term, "re-concentration", and the concept during the Second Boer War.

The English term "concentration camp" was first used to describe camps operated by the [[United Kingdom|British]] in South Africa during the 1899-1902 Second Boer War&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-sul.stanford.edu/africa/boers.html  Documents re camps in Boer War]&lt;/ref&gt;. Allegedly conceived as a form of humanitarian aid to the families whose farms had been destroyed in the fighting, the camps were used to confine and control large numbers of civilians as part of a [[Scorched Earth]] tactic. 

Use of the word ''concentration'' comes from the idea of ''concentrating'' a group of people who are in some way undesirable in one place, where they can be watched by those who incarcerated them. For example, in a time of [[insurgency]], potential supporters of the insurgents are placed where they cannot provide them with supplies or information.

[[Image:Buchenwald Slave Laborers Liberation.jpg|thumb|Buchenwald concentration camp]]The term ''concentration camp'' lost some of its original meaning after [[Nazi concentration camps]] were discovered, and has ever since been understood to refer to a place of mistreatment, starvation, forced labour, and murder. The expression since then has only been used in this extremely pejorative sense; no government or organization has used it to describe its own facilities, using instead terms such as ''internment camp'', ''resettlement camp'', ''detention facility'', etc, regardless of the actual circumstances of the camp, which can vary a great deal.

In the 20th century the arbitrary internment of civilians by the state became more common and reached a climax with Nazi concentration camps and the practice of [[genocide]] in [[Nazi extermination camp]]s, and with the [[Gulag]] system of [[Labor camp|forced labor camp]]s of the [[Soviet Union]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/archives/gula.html  documents relative to ''Gulags'']&lt;/ref&gt;. As a result of this trend, the term "concentration camp" carries many of the connotations of "extermination camp" and is sometimes used synonymously. A concentration camp, however, is not by definition a death-camp. For example, many of the slave [[labor camp]]s were used as cheap or free sources of factory labor for the manufacture of war materials and other goods.

Indeed, in terming their camps "concentration camps," the Nazis were using a mundane term to mask something far more horrific than the word had previously meant, similar to their usage of the term '[[Ghetto]].' Previously, ghettos had been separate, usually walled-in [[Jewish Quarter (diaspora)|Jewish Quarter]]s designed to segregate Jews from outside society and "protect" them from their neighbors. The [[Ghettos in occupied Europe 1939-1944|Ghettos in occupied Europe]] were far more brutal, however. 

Although the term "concentration camp" has become virtually indistinguishable from "death camp" in the popular mind, the two are not identical. The British continued to use the term concentration camp in its original meaning long after the collapse of the Third Reich, with quite possibly the last being the forced but relatively peaceful relocation of hundreds of thousands of ethnic [[Malaysian Chinese|Chinese]] squatters from the edge of the Malayan Jungle to "[[New Village]]s" during the [[Malayan Emergency]] to choke supply and support off for the [[Malayan Communist Party]].{{Fact|date=July 2007}}

==References==
{{reflist|1}}

==See also== 
*[[List of concentration and internment camps]]
*[[Prisoner-of-war camp]]
*[[Extermination camp]]
*[[Labor camp]]s

[[Category:Internments| ]]

[[af:Konsentrasiekamp]]
[[ar:معسكر اعتقال]]
[[bg:Концентрационен лагер]]
[[bs:Koncentracioni logor]]
[[br:Konzentrationslager]]
[[ca:Camp de concentració]]
[[cs:Koncentrační tábor]]
[[da:Koncentrationslejr]]
[[de:Internierungslager]]
[[es:Campo de concentración]]
[[eu:Kontzentrazio-zelai]]
[[fr:Camp de concentration]]
[[gl:Campo de concentración]]
[[hr:Sabirni logor]]
[[he:מחנה ריכוז]]
[[io:Koncentreso-kampeyo]]
[[id:Kamp konsentrasi]]
[[it:Campo di concentramento]]
[[mk:Концентрационен логор]]
[[nl:Concentratiekamp]]
[[ja:強制収容所]]
[[no:Konsentrasjonsleir]]
[[nn:Konsentrasjonsleir]]
[[pl:Obóz koncentracyjny]]
[[pt:Campo de concentração]]
[[ro:Lagăr de concentrare]]
[[ru:Концентрационный лагерь]]
[[simple:Concentration camp]]
[[sk:Koncentračný tábor]]
[[sl:Koncentracijsko taborišče]]
[[sr:Концентрациони логор]]
[[fi:Keskitysleiri]]
[[sv:Koncentrationsläger]]
[[vi:Trại tập trung]]
[[uk:Концентраційний табір]]
[[ur:بیگار کیمپ]]
[[yi:קאנצענטראציע לאגער]]
[[zh:集中营]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>