<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131111174034|581209270" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="191537" pageid="191537" ns="0" title="Internment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-17T21:32:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Distinguish|Interment|Internship}}
{{about|the usage and history of the terms concentration camp, internment camp and internment|a listing of individual camps|List of concentration and internment camps|The Walking Dead episode|Internment (The Walking Dead)}}

[[Image:Japanese internment camp in British Columbia.jpg|thumb|[[Japanese Canadian internment|Internment]] camp for [[Japanese Canadian]]s in [[British Columbia]] during [[World War II]].]]

'''Internment''' is the imprisonment or confinement&lt;ref&gt;per Oxford Universal Dictionary, 1st edition 1933.&lt;/ref&gt; of people, commonly in large groups, without trial. The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' (1989) gives the meaning as: "The action of 'interning'; confinement within the limits of a country or place."

Most modern usage is about individuals, and there is a distinction between '''internment''', which is being confined usually for preventive or political reasons, and imprisonment, which is being closely confined as a punishment for crime.{{Attribution needed|date=February 2013}}

''Internment'' also refers to the practice of [[neutral country|neutral countries]] in time of war in detaining belligerent armed forces and equipment in their territories under the [[Second Hague Convention]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/lawofwar/hague05.htm |title=The Second Hague Convention, 1907 |publisher=Yale.edu |date= |accessdate=1 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early civilizations such as [[Assyria]] used [[forced resettlement]] of populations as a means of controlling territory,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eawc.evansville.edu/anthology/hammurabi.htm |title=Laws of Hammurabi |publisher=Eawc.evansville.edu |date= |accessdate=1 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; but it was not until much later in the late 19th and 20th centuries that records exist of groups of civilian non-combatants being concentrated into large prison camps.

The [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] restricts the use of internment. Article 9 states that "No one shall be subjected to [[Arbitrary arrest and detention|arbitrary arrest]], [[detention (imprisonment)|detention]] or exile."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/en/documents/udhr/index.shtml#a9 Universal Declaration of Human Rights, Article 9], United Nations&lt;/ref&gt;

==Internment camp==
An '''internment camp''' is a large [[Detention (imprisonment)|detention]] centre created for political opponents, [[enemy alien]]s, people with [[mental illness]], members of specific ethnic or religious groups, civilian inhabitants of a critical war-zone, or other groups of people, usually during a war. The term is used for facilities where the inmates were selected by some generalized criteria, rather than detained as individuals after [[due process of law]] fairly applied by a [[judiciary]].{{Attribution needed|date=February 2013}}

As a result of the mistreatment of civilians interned during World War II, the [[Fourth Geneva Convention]] was established in 1949 to provide for the protection of civilians during times of war "in the hands" of the enemy and under any occupation by a foreign power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icrc.org/ihl.nsf/FULL/380?OpenDocument |title=Full text of 4th Geneva Convention |publisher=Icrc.org |date= |accessdate=1 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was ratified by 194 nations. [[Prisoner-of-war camp]]s are internment camps intended specifically for holding members of enemy armed forces as defined in the [[Third Geneva Convention]], and condition of their treatment is specified in that Convention.{{citation needed|date=February 2013}}

[[File:Internment-Resettlement-Facility-for-Dislocated-Civilians.png|thumb|A layout for an internment/resettlement facility for dislocated civilians]]

==Concentration camp==
[[File:Boercamp1.jpg|thumb|[[Boer]] women and children in a British-run concentration camp in South Africa (1900-1902)]]
[[File:El Agheila Concentration Camp.jpg|thumb|right|[[Bedouins]] at the Italian [[El Agheila concentration camp]] during the [[Pacification of Libya]]. Photo taken between 1930-1933.]]
The ''[[Random House Dictionary]]'' defines the term "concentration camp" as: "a guarded compound for the detention or imprisonment of aliens, members of ethnic minorities, political opponents, etc.",{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} whilst the ''[[American Heritage Dictionary]]'' defines it as: "A camp where civilians, enemy aliens, political prisoners, and sometimes prisoners of war are detained and confined, typically under harsh conditions."{{citation needed|date=February 2013}}

=== Earliest usage and origins of the term===
The Polish historian Władysław Konopczyński has suggested the first concentration camps were created in Poland in the 18th century, during the [[Bar Confederation]] rebellion, when the [[Russian Empire]] established three concentration camps for Polish rebel captives awaiting deportation to [[Siberia]].&lt;ref&gt;Konopczyński, Władysław. (1991) '' Konfederacja barska, t. II'', pp. 733–734.&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest of these camps may have been those set up in the United States for [[Cherokee removal|Cherokee]] and other [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]]s in the 1830s;{{Attribution needed|date=February 2013}} however, the term originated in the ''reconcentrados'' (reconcentration camps) set up by the [[Spain under the Restoration|Spanish military]] in [[Cuba]] during the [[Ten Years' War]] (1868–1878) and by the United States during the [[Philippine–American War]] (1899–1902).&lt;ref name="columbia"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |title=Concentration Camp |work=The Columbia Encyclopedia |edition= Sixth Edition |year=2008 |publisher=Columbia University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The English term "concentration camp" was used more widely during the [[Second Boer War]] (1899–1902), when the British operated such camps in South Africa for interning Boers.&lt;ref name="columbia"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www-sul.stanford.edu/africa/boers.html |title=Documents re camps in Boer War |publisher=sul.stanford.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; They built a total of 45 tented camps for Boer internees and 64 for black Africans. Of the 28,000 Boer men captured as prisoners of war, the British sent 25,630 overseas. The vast majority of Boers remaining in the local camps were women and children.{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} Between 1904 and 1908, the [[Imperial German Army]] operated both concentration camps and the [[Shark Island Extermination Camp]] in [[German South-West Africa]] (now [[Namibia]]) as part of their [[Herero and Namaqua genocide|genocide of the Herero and Namaqua peoples]].

===Shift in meaning===
{{Main|Nazi concentration camps}}
[[Image:Buchenwald Slave Laborers Liberation.jpg|thumb|Jewish slave laborers in the [[Buchenwald concentration camp]] near Jena, 16 April 1945. Second row, seventh from left is [[Elie Wiesel]].]]

During the 20th century, the arbitrary internment of civilians by the state reached a climax with [[Nazi concentration camps]] (1933–1945). As a result, the term "concentration camp" today carries many of the connotations of [[extermination camp|"extermination camp" (or "death camp")]], and is sometimes used synonymously with these terms by people who are unaware of the original usage pre-1933. Not all Nazi concentration camps were "extermination camps" however. Many were used primarily to house [[forced labor]]. The inmates in these camps were held there for the purpose of exploitation, rather than extermination. However, for the many inmates of these "[[Arbeitslager]]" or "[[Forced labour under German rule during World War II|Forced Labor Camps]]", the result was often the same as many did not survive them, dying from malnutrition, disease or simply as a result of the inhuman conditions under which they were kept; effectively [[extermination through labor]].

==List of camps==
{{Main|List of concentration and internment camps}}

==See also==
*[[Civilian Internee]]
*[[Extrajudicial detention]]
*[[Gulag]]
*[[Labor camp]]s
*[[Prisoner-of-war camp]]
*[[Prison overcrowding]]
*[[Quasi-criminal]]
*[[Remand (detention)|Remand]]
*[[Strategic Hamlet Program]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Internment}}

{{Incarceration}}
{{Segregation by type}}

[[Category:Internments| ]]
[[Category:Total institutions]]
[[Category:Segregation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>