<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071112210657|171039734" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="706186" pageid="706186" ns="0" title="Reproductive rights"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-12T21:36:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{AbortionDebate}}
'''Reproductive rights''' are a subset of [[human rights]] relating to [[sexual reproduction]] and [[reproductive health]]. Advocates of reproductive rights support the right to control one's reproductive functions, such as the rights to reproduce (as in opposition to [[compulsory sterilization]] and forced contraception), as well as rights to not reproduce (including support for access to [[birth control]] and [[abortion]]), the rights to privacy, medical coverage, contraception, family planning and protection from discrimination, harassment and gender-oriented harm.

While the term is often associated with the [[pro-choice]] position, which states that abortion should be a legal option for any pregnant woman, reproductive rights encompass more than just abortion. Reproductive rights first became an internationally-recognized subset of human rights at the United Nation's 1968 International Conference on Human Rights. The sixteenth article of the Proclamation of Tehran states that "[p]arents have a basic human right to determine freely and responsibly the number and the spacing of their children".  Reproductive rights advocates work to secure affordable access to abortion, contraception, as well as education about contraception and [[Sexually transmitted disease|sexually transmitted infections]], and freedom from coerced sterilization and contraception, for both men and women. In addition, reproductive rights advocates endeavor to protect all women from harmful gender-based practices. Examples include cultural practices such as [[female genital cutting]], or FGC, as well as state, customary and religious laws that contribute to women's political and economic disenfranchisment. 

==Reproductive rights as a women's issue==
Organizations such as the Center for Reproductive Rights, the [[United Nations Population Fund]], the [[World Health Organization]] and the [[National Organization for Women]] pursue reproductive rights with a primary emphasis on women's rights.  While much attention has been paid to abortion rights as one aspect of reproductive rights, groups focus on a range of issues from access to family planning services, sex education, the reduction of [[obstetric fistula]], and menopause, to the relationship between reproductive health and economic status.  

There has also been an attempt to look at micro and macro conditions that affect a woman's access to reproductive health care. The term ''reproductive justice'' has been used to describe these broader social and economic issues.  Proponents of reproductive justice argue that while the right to legalized abortion and contraception applies to everyone, these choices are only meaningful to those with resources, and that there is a growing gap between access and affordability (Kirk, Okazawa-Rey 2004).

==Reproductive rights in the United States==

In the United States, the public debate surrounding reproduction rights is often about abortion rights. Reproductive rights advocates often support a woman's right to abortion and contraception from within the context of the [[right to privacy]], or freedom from governmental interference, supporting legalized contraception and abortion. 

In the [[United States Constitution]], the right to privacy has been interpreted to include reproductive rights, as seen in numerous [[United States Supreme Court|Supreme Court]] cases. Three important cases are ''[[Griswold v. Connecticut]]'' ([[1965]]), ''[[Eisenstadt v. Baird]]'' ([[1972]]), and ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'' ([[1973]]). In ''Griswold v. Connecticut'', the Supreme court overturned a state law prohibiting the use of contraceptives, which establishd a constitutional right to privacy and legalized contraception for married people. ''Eisenstadt v. Baird'' extended the right to use contraceptives to unmarried people. ''Roe v. Wade'' legalized abortion on a federal level. 

The term ''procreative liberty'' was coined by [[John A. Robertson]], a professor of [[law]] and [[bioethics]] at the [[University of Texas School of Law]].

==References==
* {{cite web
  | title = Proclamation of Tehran
  | publisher = International Conference on Human Rights
  | date = 1968
  | url = http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/b_tehern.htm
  | accessdate = 2007-11-08 }}
* Freedman, Lynn P. &amp; Stephen L. Isaacs (Jan. - Feb., 1993). "Human Rights and Reproductive Choice". ''Studies in Family Planning'' '''24''' (1), 18&amp;ndash;30.
* {{cite web
  | title = About Us
  | publisher = Center for Reproductive Rights
  | url = http://www.reproductiverights.org/about.html#mission
  | accessdate = 2007-11-08 }}
 
==See also==
* [[Bioethics]]
* [[Parental leave]]
* [[Procreative beneficence]] 
* [[Reprogenetics]]

==External links==
* [http://www.reproductiverights.org Center for Reproductive Rights]
* [http://www.now.org The National Organization for Women]
* [http://www.ipas.org Ipas]
* [http://www.lwv.org/AM/Template.cfm?Section=Reproductive_Choice&amp;Template=/TaggedPage/TaggedPageDisplay.cfm&amp;TPLID=23&amp;ContentID=991 The League of Women Voters on Reproductive Choice]
* [http://www.unfpa.org/rh/index.htm UNFPA Population Issues: Reproductive Rights]
* [http://www.naral.org NARAL Pro-Choice America]
* [http://www.plannedparenthood.org Planned Parenthood]
* [http://www.aclu.org/reproductiverights American Civil Liberties Union]

[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:Pro-choice movement]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>