<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051022161644|26193597" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="706186" pageid="706186" ns="0" title="Reproductive rights"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-06T03:36:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Reproductive rights''' is a [[controversy|controversial]] political term to refer to "[[women's rights]]" in areas of sexual [[reproduction]], including the rights ''to'' reproduce (such as [[forced sterilization]]) as well as rights ''not'' to reproduce, (such as [[birth control]], [[abortion]]). 

Uncontroversially, the term represents the political [[framing]] of contraception and abortion as rights, particular to women, as women, exclusively, are the biological vessels of human reproduction.
In this context, "reproductive rights" is largely synonymous with "[[pro-choice]]," meaning a position that a woman ought to be the decision maker in whether to bring her pregnancy to term. Many "[[pro-life]]" advocates claim that the term is simply mincing words &amp;mdash;claiming there to be no practical (hence ''meaningful'') difference between the two statements. 
However, supporters of reproductive rights may consider it misleading to say, in the context of reproduction politics, that a political figure "supports abortion", when instead that person may simply support a "woman's right to choose abortion among other alternatives."
Supporters claim that such principle falls within the context of [[right to privacy]], and freedom from "governmental interference" &amp;mdash;supporting the "legalization of abortion" rather than "supporting abortion" itself.  Still other reproductive rights advocates favor the term because they embrace a basic [[human rights]] moral justification for their position rather then the right to privacy logic of United States Constitutional interpretation. 

{{poli-stub}}
[[Category:Human rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>