<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101018185757|391492085" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3330631" pageid="3330631" ns="0" title="Gendercide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-10-21T20:14:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{homicide}}
'''Gendercide''' is a [[neologism]] that refers to the systematic killing of members of a specific sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Mary Anne|last=Warren|title=Gendercide: The Implications of Sex Selection|isbn=0847673308}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gendercide==

Gendercide is gender-selective mass killing. The term was first used by [[Mary Anne Warren]] in her 1985 book, ''Gendercide: The Implications of Sex Selection''. Warren drew "an analogy between the concept of [[genocide]]" and what she called "gendercide." Citing the Oxford English Dictionary definition of genocide as "the deliberate [[genocide|extermination]] of a race of people," Warren wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;By analogy, gendercide would be the deliberate extermination of persons of a particular sex (or gender). Other terms, such as "gynocide" and "femicide," have been used to refer to the wrongful killing of girls and women. But "gendercide" is a sex-neutral term, in that the victims may be either male or female. There is a need for such a sex-neutral term, since sexually discriminatory killing is just as wrong when the victims happen to be male. The term also calls attention to the fact that gender roles have often had lethal consequences, and that these are in important respects analogous to the lethal consequences of racial, religious, and class prejudice.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Warren explored the deliberate extermination of women through analysis of such subjects as female [[infanticide]], [[maternal death]], [[witch-hunts]] in early modern Europe, and other atrocities and abuses against women.

==Femicide==

Femicide is defined as the systematic killing of women for various reasons, usually cultural. The word is attested from the 1820s.&lt;ref&gt;2006 Random House Unabridged Dictionary&lt;/ref&gt;

The most widespread form of femicide is in the form of [[sex-selective infanticide]] in cultures with strong preferences for male offspring.

There have been reports of femicide in [[Guatemala City]], [[Guatemala]], and in [[Ciudad Juárez]], [[Chihuahua (state)|Chihuahua]], [[Mexico]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/international/Gender-Violence-in-Mexico.html Femicide and Gender Violence in Mexico], retrieved on May 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Female homicides in Ciudad Juárez|murders in Juarez]], also known as '''las muertas de Juárez''' ("The dead women of Juárez"), and Guatemala were reportedly not investigated by the [[police|local authorities]]. Most of the women were [[rape]]d before being murdered and some were [[mutilation|mutilated]], [[torture]]d, and [[dismember]]ed. In Guatemala City, about 20% of the over 500 women murdered in 2004 and 2005 were killed in pairs, due to a ([[lesbian]]) "intimate relationship", according to [[Claudia Acevedo]] of [[Lesbiradas]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2007}}

==Viricide==
Viricide is the systematic killing of men for various reasons, usually cultural. Viricide may happen during war to reduce an enemy's potential pool of soldiers.

Viricide as a common practice continued in ancient times. Mythological accounts of the Greek takeover of [[Miletus]] in circa 9th century BCE have the legendary son of Poseidon leading a massacre of the men of [[Miletus]] and settling the city in the Milesian men's stead.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/Miletus 1911 Encyclopedia Britannica]&lt;/ref&gt;

Biblical viricides include the [[Massacre of the Innocents]] recounted in the [[Book of Matthew]]  although many modern scholars consider that this may be apocryphal.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Eisenman, ''James The Brother of Jesus'', 1997, I.3 "Romans, Herodians and Jewish sects" discusses Mariamne, the last representative of the Maccabean line, by whom Herod had two sons, whom he put to death. "Here Herod really did kill all the Jewish children who sought to replace him, as Matthew 2:17 would have it, but these were rather his own children with Maccabean blood!" (p. 49); see also E. P. Sanders, The Historical Figure of Jesus, 87-88&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pakistan]] targeted male intellectuals for extermination in the erstwhile province of [[East Pakistan]] (present day [[Bangladesh]]) during the [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities]].&lt;ref&gt;Rounaq Jahan, "Genocide in Bangladesh", in Samuel Totten et al., eds., Century of Genocide, p298. R.J. Rummel writes: "By November [1971], the rebel guerrillas ... had wrested from the army control over 25 percent of East Pakistan, a success that led the Pakistan army to seek out those especially likely to join the resistance -- young boys. Sweeps were conducted of young men who were never seen again. Bodies of youths would be found in fields, floating down rivers, or near army camps. As can be imagined, this terrorized all young men and their families within reach of the army. Most between the ages of fifteen and twenty-five began to flee from one village to another and toward India. Many of those reluctant to leave their homes were forced to flee by mothers and sisters concerned for their safety." Rummel, Death By Government (New Brunswick, USA: Transaction Publishers, 1994), p329.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pol Pot]] executed many men in [[Cambodia]], resulting in a large percentage of Cambodia's population afterwards being women.&lt;ref name="Jones"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Jones |first= Adam |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2000 |month=June |title = Gendercide and Genocide |journal= Journal of Genocide Research |volume=2 |issue=2 |pages= 185–211 |id= |url= |accessdate= 2008-11-09 |quote= |doi=10.1080/713677599 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
During the [[1984 Anti-Sikh riots]] men were targeted overwhelmingly on account of them being breadwinners of the family.&lt;ref name="Jones"/&gt;
More recent examples include the [[1988 Anfal campaign]] against [[Kurds|Kurdish]] men and boys&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/frontlineworld/stories/iraq501/events_anfal.html The Crimes of Saddam Hussein]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/reports/1992/iraqkor/KOREME2.htm Koreme Before The Anfal Campaign&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Iraq]] and the [[Srebrenica massacre]] of [[Bosniaks|Bosniak]] men and boys on July 12, 1995.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2005/07/ba90ec7e-1d42-43de-88f3-3724c21c2756.html Srebrenica Timeline]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=4737583 Serbians Still Divided Over Srebrenica Massacre]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Genocide}}
* [[Genocide]]
* [[Ritual murder]]
* [[SCUM Manifesto]]
* [[Missing women of Asia]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Books==

*{{cite book |last=Warren |first=Mary Anne |title=Gendercide: The Implications of Sex Selection |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1985 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Allanheld |location= |isbn=0847673308 |pages= }}
*{{cite book |last=Russell |first=Diana E.H., ed. |title=Femicide in Global Perspective |authorlink= |coauthors=Roberta A. Harmes |year=2001 |publisher=Teachers College Press |location= |isbn=0807740470 |pages= }}
*{{cite book |last=Sanford |first=Victoria |title=Guatemala : Del Genocidio Al Feminicidio/From Genocide to Femicide |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2008 |publisher=F&amp;G Editores |location= |isbn=9992261889 |pages= }}

==External links==
* [http://www.guernicamag.com/features/299/the_price_of_life_1/ Femicide in Guatemala--Guernica Magazine (guernicamag.com)]
* [[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights]], '' [http://www.cidh.org/annualrep/2002eng/chap.vi.juarez.htm Situation of the Rights of Women in Ciudad Juárez]'' (2002) — Report by [[Organization of American States|OAS]] human rights agency.
* Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Graduate Research " [http://www.elnorteproductions.com/ Juarez Mothers Fight Femicide Documentary]" (March 2005)
*  [http://www.economist.com/World/africa/displayStory.cfm?story_id=5220396 ''The Economist'' - No place for your daughters] (November 24, 2005)
*  [http://www.lourdesportillo.com/senoritaextraviada/index.html Lourdes Portillo Video], Señorita Extraviada ISDN 0807861731  2001

[[Category:Feminism and health]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Genocide]]
[[Category:Hate crime]]
[[Category:Homicide]]
[[Category:Murder]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]
[[Category:Population]]
[[Category:Violence against women]]

[[ca:Feminicidi]]
[[da:Femicide]]
[[de:Gendercide]]
[[es:Femicidio]]
[[eu:Feminizidio]]
[[fr:Gynécide]]
[[ko:젠더사이드]]
[[zh:性别灭绝]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>