<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061105031535|85778066" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3330631" pageid="3330631" ns="0" title="Gendercide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-10T11:34:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup-date|September 2006}}
{{unreferenced}}
{{npov}}
{{Merge|sex selection|date=October 2006}}

'''Gendercide''' is a term that refers to the systematic killing of members of a specific [[sex]], either [[male]]s or [[female]]s, coined by [[Mary Anne Warren]] in her 1985 book ''Gendercide: The Implications of Sex Selection'' [http://www.gendercide.org/what_is_gendercide.html]. 

==Male victims==
The systematic killing of men viricide happens sometimes during war to reduce an enemy's potential pool of soldiers; this happened for example in the [[1988 Anfal campaign]] against [[Kurds|Kurdish]] men in [[Iraq]] and in the 1995 [[Srebrenica massacre]] of [[Bosniak]] men and boys.

Gendercide against men is rumored to be a common fantasy among particularly [[misandry|misandrous]] adherents of [[radical feminism]] and [[separatist feminism]].{{fact}}

==Femicide==
The term '''femicide''' or '''feminicidio''' (femicidio in [[Spanish language|Spanish]]) is a term referring to the systematic [[kill]]ing of [[woman|women]] because they are women. Femicide is seen as a [[gender crime]]. It is attested from the [[1820s]] (2006 Random House Unabridged Dictionary).

There have been reports of femicide in [[Guatemala City]], [[Guatemala]] and in [[Ciudad Juarez]], [[Chihuahua]], [[Mexico]]. The [[Deaths in Ciudad Juarez|murders in Juarez]] and Guatemala were reportedly not investigated by the [[police|local authorities]]. Most of the women were [[rape]]d before being [[murder]]ed and some were [[mutilation|mutilated]], [[torture]]d and even [[dismembered]]. In Guatemala City about 20% of the over 500 women murdered in 2004 and 2005 were killed in pairs, due to an [[lesbian|"intimate relationship"]] according to [[Claudia Acevedo]] of [[Lesbiradas]].

There is also concern that femicide of [[Aboriginal peoples in Canada|Aboriginal]] women is taking place in [[Canada]].  Five hundred Aboriginal women have been reported missing or murdered since 1980, a disproportionate proportion compared to non-Aboriginal women.  According to [[socioecology|sociological studies]] these women are seen as easy targets because their [[race]] places them at the bottom of the social and economic hierarchy.  Many of the missing women have been dismissed as [[prostitutes]] and their disappearances have gone uninvestigated.  A major factor in bringing international attention to Canadian women was the murder of [[Helen Betty Osborne]] in 1971.

According to the [[Geneva Centre for the Democratic Control of the Armed Forces]] between 113 and 200 million women are missing.

The most widespread form of femicide is in the form of [[Sex-selective infanticide]] in cultures with strong preferences for male offspring, notably in [[People's Republic of China|China]], [[India]], and [[South Korea]]. These practices result in demographic imbalance with an excess of males. The [[Demographics of mainland China]] for example shows 1.13 males/female under 15 years, as opposed to a 'natural' average of 1.05.
Sex selection in favour of females appears to be rare or non-existent.

==External links==

* [http://www.gendercide.org Gendercide Watch] Website devoted to this subject, with links to publications and related resources
*[http://www.gendercide.org/case_infanticide.html Gendercide watch - Female Infanticide]
*[[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights]], ''[http://www.cidh.org/annualrep/2002eng/chap.vi.juarez.htm Situation of the Rights of Women in Ciudad Juárez]'' (2002) &amp;mdash;&lt;br&gt; Report by [[Organization of American States|OAS]] human rights agency.
*Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Graduate Research "[http://www.elnorteproductions.com/ Juarez Mothers Fight Femicide Documentary]" (March 2005)
*[http://www.economist.com/World/africa/displayStory.cfm?story_id=5220396 The Economist - No place for your daughters] (Nov 24th 2005)
*[http://www.ibiblio.org/rcip//sbh.html Rape Survivor Bashing as a bias crime or hate crime]
*[http://www.lourdesportillo.com/senoritaextraviada/index.html Lourdes Portillo Video], Señorita Extraviada ISDN 0807861731  2001

==References==
*AJIC, Aboriginal Justice Implementation Commission. “The Death of Helen Betty Osborne.” &lt;http://www.ajic.mb.ca/volumell/toc.html&gt;
*Andersen, Margaret L., 1983, Thinking About Women, Macmillan Publishing Co., Nueva York.
*Bellhouse, Mary L., 1999, “Crimes and Pardons: Bourgeois Justice, Gendered Virtue, and the Criminalized Other in Eighteenth-century France”, Signs, vol. 24, núm. 4, verano, pp. 959-1010. 
*Britton, Dana M., 2000, “Feminism in Criminology: Engendering the Outlaw”, Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, vol. 571, Thousand Oaks, CA, septiembre, pp. 57-76.  
*Bunster-Bunalto, Ximena, 1993, “Surviving Beyond Fear: Women and Torture in Latin America”, en Feminist Frameworks, McGraw-Hill, pp. 252-261. 
*Burgess, Ann, W. et. al., 1995, Sexual Homicide: Patterns and Motives, Free Press, Nueva York. 
*Antonio Mendoza, ''Killers on the Loose: Unsolved Cases of Serial Murder'', (Virgin Books 2002), [ISBN 0-7535-0681-5] &amp;mdash; Study of unsolved serial killing around the world, including Ciudad Juárez.
*Cameron, Deborah y Elizabeth Frazer, 1987, The Lust To Kill, Nueva York University Press, Nueva York. 
*"Canada: Stolen Sisters: A Human Rights Response to Discrimination and Violence against Indigenous Women in Canada." Amnesty International of Canada, 4 Oct. 2004, 30 Oct. 2005  [http://www.amnesty.ca/campaigns/resources/amr2000304.pdf]*Caputi, Jane, 1987, The Age of Sex Crime, Bowling Green State University Popular Press, Ohio. 
*Caputi, Jane, 1989, “The Sexual Politics of Murder”, Gender &amp; Society, vol. 3, núm. 4, diciembre, pp. 437-456. 
*Caputi, Jane, 1990, “The New Founding Fathers: The Lore and Lure of the Serial Killer in Contemporary Culture”, Journal of American Culture, vol. 13, núm. 3, pp. 1-12. 
*Culhane, Dara. “Their Spirits Live within Us: Aboriginal Women in Downtown Eastside Vancouver Emerging into Visibility.” American Indian Quarterly 27 (2003): 593-606.
*Daly, Mary, 1990, Gyn/Ecology The Methaetics of Radical Feminism, Beacon Press, Boston. 
*Devalle, Susana B.C., 2000, “Violencia: estigma de nuestro siglo”, en Devalle Susana B.C. (comp.), Poder y cultura de la violencia, El Colegio de México, México, pp. 15-31. 
*Dobash, Rebeca E., y Dobash, Russell P., 1998, “Violent Men and Violent Contexts”, en Dobash y Dobash (comps.), Rethinking Violence Against Women, Sage Publications, Thousand Oaks, CA, pp. 141-168. 
*Domingo, Chris, 1992, “What the White Man Won’t Tell Us: Report from the Berkeley Clearinghouse on Femicide”, en Femicide: The Politics of Woman Killing, Twayne Publishers, Nueva York, pp. 195-202. 
*Dworkin, Andrea, 1997, Life and Death, Free Press, Nueva York. 
*Fisas, Vicenç, 1998, “Introducción”, El sexo de la violencia: Género y cultura de la violencia, Icaria, Barcelona, pp.7-18. 
*Foucault, Michel, 1998, Vigilar y castigar, trad. de Aurelio Garzón del Camino, Siglo XXI editores, México. 
*Fuentes, Noé, Brugues, Alejandro y Cortez, Willy, 1998, “Inseguridad en la Frontera Norte”, Ciudades, núm. 40, Red Nacional de Investigación Urbana, octubre-diciembre, pp. 18-24. 
*Gibson, Lisa. “Innocence and purity vs. deviance and immorality: the spaces of prostitution in Nepal and Canada” Institute of Development Studies, University of Sussex, Brighton. MA Thesis. September 2003
*Grupos de estudios de género de la UACJ/Comité Independiente de Chihuahua de los Derechos Humanos / Grupo Ocho de marzo de Ciudad Juárez, Mujeres asesinadas 1983-1998, Ciudad Juárez, Chihuahua. 
*Gunder Frank, Andre, 1999, “A testimonial contribution to the 25th Anniversary Issue of Social Justice”, Social Justice, verano, vol. 26, núm. 2, pp.1-15. 
*Izquierdo, María Jesús, 1998, “Los órdenes de la violencia: especie, sexo y género”, en Vicenç Fisas (ed.), El sexo de la violencia: género y cultura de la violencia, Icaria, Barcelona, pp.61-91. 
*Jenkins, Phillip, 1994, Using Murder: The Social Construction of Serial Homicide, Aldine de Gruyter, Nueva York. 
*Kelly, Liz y Jill Radford, 1998, “Sexual Violence Against Women and Girls: An Approach to an International Overview”, en Dobash y Dobash (comps.), Rethinking Violence Against Women, Sage Publications, Thousand Oaks, CA, pp. 53-76. 
*Lagarde, Marcela, 1997, Identidades de género y derechos humanos. La construcción de las humanas, VII curso de verano. “Educación, democracia y nueva ciudadanía”, Universidad Autónoma de Aguascalientes, 7 y 8 de agosto. 
*Lagarde, Marcela, 1999, Una mirada feminista en el umbral del milenio, Instituto de Estudios de la Mujer/Facultad de Filosofía y Letras/Universidad Nacional, Costa Rica. 
*Leyton, Elliot. ''Hunting Humans: The Rise of the Modern Multiple Murderer.'' 1995, McClelland &amp; Stewart, Canadá. 
*Manieri, Rosaria, 1978, Mujer y capital, trad. de Benito Gómez ,Tribuna Feminista, Madrid. 
*Marx, K., y Engels, F., 1980, Obras escogidas I y III, Editorial Progreso, Moscú. 
*McWilliams, Monica, 1998, “Violence Against Women in Societies Under Stress”, en Dobash y Dobash (comps.), Rethinking Violence Against Women, Sage Publications, Thousand Oaks, CA, pp. 111-140. 
*Monárrez, Julia E., 2000, “La cultura del feminicidio en Ciudad Juárez, 1993-1999”, en Frontera Norte, núm. 23, vol. 12, enero-junio, pp. 87-117. 
*Pally, Marcia, 1997, “Pornography Does Not Cause Sexual Violence”, en Mary E. Williams y Tamara L. 
*Roleff (eds.), Sexual Violence: Opposing Viewpoints, Greenhaven Press, San Diego, pp. 24-28. 
*Poulantzas, Nicos, 1977, “Las clases sociales”, en Raúl Benítez Zenteno et. al., Las clases sociales en América Latina, Siglo XXI, México, pp. 96-126. 
*Procuraduría General de Justicia del Estado/Subprocuraduría Zona Norte, Homicidios cometidos en perjuicio de mujeres en Ciudad Juárez, Chihuahua en el periodo de 1993-1998, Averiguaciones previas. 
*Whitechapel, Simon. ''Crossing to Kill: The True Story of the Serial-Killer Playground.'' Virgin Books 2002, ISBN 0-7535-0686-6 &amp;mdash; Updated edition of the first detailed study of the Juárez murders.

==See also==
*[[Uxoricide]]
*[[Sororicide]]
*[[Matricide]]
*[[Patricide]]
*[[Fratricide]]
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Hate crime]]
[[Category:Murder]]
[[Category:Genocide]]

[[ca:Feminicidi]]
[[es:Femicidio]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>