<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081115184226|251999947" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3330631" pageid="3330631" ns="0" title="Gendercide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T18:42:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Portal|Genocide|GenocidePortalLogo(ESR)2.JPG}}
{{homicide}}
'''Gendercide''' is a [[neologism]] that refers to the systematic killing of members of a specific [[sex]], either [[male]]s or [[female]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Coined by Mary Anne Warren in her 1985 book ''Gendercide: The Implications of Sex Selection''[http://www.gendercide.org/what_is_gendercide.html]&lt;/ref&gt; The term is intended to be sex-neutral, but in mainstream [[feminism]] it is mostly used to refer to female victims ('''feminicide''' or '''femicide''').{{Fact|date=October 2008}}

==Femicide==
Femicide is the systematic [[kill]]ing of [[woman|women]] for various reasons, usually cultural. Femicide is seen as a [[gender crime]]. The word is attested from the 1820s.&lt;ref&gt;2006 Random House Unabridged Dictionary&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been reports of femicide in [[Guatemala City]], [[Guatemala]], and in [[Ciudad Juarez]], [[Chihuahua]], [[Mexico]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/international/Gender-Violence-in-Mexico.html Femicide and Gender Violence in Mexico], retrieved on May 28th 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;. The [[Deaths in Ciudad Juarez|murders in Juarez]], also known as '''las muertas de Juárez''' ("The dead women of Juárez"), and Guatemala were reportedly not investigated by the [[police|local authorities]]. Most of the women were [[rape]]d before being [[murder]]ed and some were [[mutilation|mutilated]], [[torture]]d and [[dismember]]ed. In Guatemala City about 20% of the over 500 women murdered in 2004 and 2005 were killed in pairs, due to an ([[lesbian]]) "intimate relationship," according to [[Claudia Acevedo]] of [[Lesbiradas]].{{Fact|date=March 2007}}

The most widespread form of femicide is in the form of [[sex-selective infanticide]] in cultures with strong preferences for male offspring, notably in the [[mainland China|mainland]] of the [[People's Republic of China]], [[India]], and [[South Korea]]. These practices may result in [[gender imbalance|demographic imbalance]] with an excess of males.{{Fact|date=July 2008}} &lt;!-- No doubt this is true, but numbers and sources will make the point better than bald assertions. --&gt;

==Viricide==
Viricide is the systematic [[kill]]ing of [[man|men]] for various reasons, usually cultural. Viricide is seen as a [[gender crime]]. Viricide may happen during war to reduce an enemy's potential pool of soldiers.

Perhaps one of the earliest examples of viricide in recorded history occurred some time during the 600s [[BCE]] when Ionian pirates massacred the men of [[Miletus]], forced the Milesian women into marriage with them, and settled the city of Miletus in the Milesian men's stead.&lt;REF&gt;[http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/Miletus 1911 Encyclopedia Brittanica]&lt;/ref&gt;  It has been written that forever afterward the Milesian women would neither eat with their husbands nor address them by name.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=OvoLAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA197&amp;lpg=PA197&amp;dq=Miletus+massacre+husbands&amp;source=web&amp;ots=V5fwDBhiCr&amp;sig=toN-KgVTC0PVmC2uV33hcfurDBM&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ct=result ''A History of Greece''] by Connop Thirlwall, footnote at page 197.  Accessed November 12, 2008 via Google Books.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Cartoon History of the Universe by Larry Gonick Pg. 238&lt;!-- IS THIS A SERIOUS REFERENCE?&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

The most famed example of viricide in Western literature is recounted in the [[Book of Matthew]] in the [[New Testament]] of the [[Bible]].  If modern scholars are correct in establishing the birth of Jesus as around the year 3 [[BCE]], the slaughter would have taken shortly thereafter.  Matthew 2:16 states that [[Herod]] ordered what is known as the [[Massacre of the Innocents]], which modern scholars note may be apocryphal&lt;ref&gt;Robert Eisenman, ''James The Brother of Jesus'', 1997, I.3 "Romans, Herodians and Jewish sects" discusses Mariamne, the last representative of the Maccabean line, by whom Herod had two sons, whom he put to death. "Here Herod really did kill all the Jewish children who sought to replace him, as Matthew 2:17 would have it, but these were rather his own children with Maccabean blood!" (p. 49); see also E. P. Sanders, The Historical Figure of Jesus, 87-88&lt;/ref&gt; rather than an actual historical event:


{{cquote|Then when Herod saw that he had been tricked by the [[Biblical Magi|magi]], he became very enraged, and sent and slew all the male children who were in Bethlehem and all its vicinity, from two years old and under, according to the time which he had determined from the magi.|30px|30px|Matthew 2:16|New American Standard Bible}}

In 627 [[Common Era|CE]], the men and boys of the [[Qurayza]] were beheaded by Muhammad&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url = http://www.americanthinker.com/2006/02/muhammad_and_massacre_of_the_q.html
|title = Muhammad and Massacre of the Qurayza Jews
|accessdate = 2008-10-26}}
&lt;/ref&gt; after the tribe surrendered. They condition of the surrender were they would be tried and passed judgement by Sa'd ibn Mu'adh, a chief of their allied tribe of Aws. After asking what the punishment for treason was in Jewish law, all the males were decapitated.

A case of viricide can be found in [[World War II]] with the [[Nazi crimes against Soviet POWs|Nazi killing of Soviet POWs]].  Over a period of about 8 months as part of [[Operation Barbarossa]], between June 1941 and February 1942, the Nazis captured approximately 3.5 million Soviet POWs (almost entirely male) and subjected them to starvation, exposure, disease, and summary execution.  Nearly 2.4 million of these prisoners died.  These deaths were a premeditated part of [[the Holocaust]] (see [[Goering's Green Folder]]).

[[Pakistan]] targeted male intellectuals for extermination in the erstwhile province of [[East Pakistan]] (present day [[Bangladesh]]) during the [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities]]&lt;ref&gt;Rounaq Jahan, "Genocide in Bangladesh," in Samuel Totten et al., eds., Century of Genocide, p298. R.J. Rummel writes: "By November [1971], the rebel guerrillas ... had wrested from the army control over 25 percent of East Pakistan, a success that led the Pakistan army to seek out those especially likely to join the resistance -- young boys. Sweeps were conducted of young men who were never seen again. Bodies of youths would be found in fields, floating down rivers, or near army camps. As can be imagined, this terrorized all young men and their families within reach of the army. Most between the ages of fifteen and twenty-five began to flee from one village to another and toward India. Many of those reluctant to leave their homes were forced to flee by mothers and sisters concerned for their safety." Rummel, Death By Government (New Brunswick, USA: Transaction Publishers, 1994), p329. &lt;/ref&gt; Male Gendercide was also carried out by [[Pol pot]] in [[Cambodia]], thanks to which a large percentage of Cambodia's present population are women.&lt;ref name="Jones"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Jones |first= Adam |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2000 |month=June |title = Gendercide and Genocide |journal= Journal of Genocide Research |volume=2 |issue=2 |pages= 185 - 211 |id= |url= |accessdate= 2008-11-09 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
During the [[1984 Anti-Sikh riots]] men were targeted overwhelmingly on account of them being breadwinners of the family.&lt;ref name="Jones"/&gt;
More recents examples include the [[1988 Anfal campaign]] against [[Kurds|Kurdish]] men and boys&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/frontlineworld/stories/iraq501/events_anfal.html The Crimes of Saddam Hussein]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/reports/1992/iraqkor/KOREME2.htm Koreme Before The Anfal Campaign&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gendercide.org/case_anfal.html Gendercide Watch: The Anfal Campaign (Iraqi Kurdistan), 1988&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Iraq]] and the [[Srebrenica massacre]] of [[Bosniaks|Bosniak]] men and [[boy]]s on [[12 July]] [[1995]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2005/07/ba90ec7e-1d42-43de-88f3-3724c21c2756.html Srebrenica Timeline]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=4737583 Serbians Still Divided Over Srebrenica Massacre]&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Draft dodgers===
Men who refused [[conscription]] in the military have been the target of [[forced labor]], [[mutilation]], and [[Wiktionary:massacre|massacre]] in the nations of Angola, Ethiopia and Iraq&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gendercide.org/case_conscription.html Case Study:  Military conscription/ Impressment]&lt;/ref&gt;.

==See also==
* [[Ritual murder]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==

*[http://www.guernicamag.com/features/299/the_price_of_life_1/ Femicide in Guatemala--Guernica Magazine (guernicamag.com)]
*[[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights]], ''[http://www.cidh.org/annualrep/2002eng/chap.vi.juarez.htm Situation of the Rights of Women in Ciudad Juárez]'' (2002) — Report by [[Organization of American States|OAS]] human rights agency.
*Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Graduate Research "[http://www.elnorteproductions.com/ Juarez Mothers Fight Femicide Documentary]" (March 2005)
*[http://www.economist.com/World/africa/displayStory.cfm?story_id=5220396 The Economist - No place for your daughters] (Nov 24th 2005)
*[http://www.lourdesportillo.com/senoritaextraviada/index.html Lourdes Portillo Video], Señorita Extraviada ISDN 0807861731  2001

[[Category:Genocide]]
[[Category:Hate crime]]
[[Category:Homicide]]
[[Category:Murder]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]
[[Category:Violence against women]]
[[Category:Feminism and health]]
[[Category:Population]]
[[Category:Gender]]

[[ca:Feminicidi]]
[[da:Femicide]]
[[de:Gendercide]]
[[es:Femicidio]]
[[fr:Gynécide]]
[[ko:젠더사이드]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>