<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241120005456|1258488851" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3330631" pageid="3330631" ns="0" title="Gendercide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-20T00:57:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Systematic killing of members of a specific gender}}
{{Not to be confused with||Genericide}}
{{recentism|date=October 2018}}
{{homicide}}{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
'''Gendercide''' is the systematic killing of members of a specific [[gender]].&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{Cite book |first=Mary Anne |last=Warren |title=Gendercide: The Implications of Sex Selection |isbn=978-0-8476-7330-8 |date=1985-01-01 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Allanheld |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/gendercideimplic0000warr}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term is related to the general concepts of [[assault]] and [[murder]] against victims due to their gender, with [[violence against men]] and [[Violence against women|women]] being problems dealt with by [[human rights]] efforts. Gendercide shares similarities with the term '[[genocide]]' in inflicting mass murders; however, gendercide targets solely one gender, being men or women. Politico-military frameworks have historically inflicted militant-governed divisions between femicide and androcide; gender-selective policies increase violence on gendered populations due to their socioeconomic significance. Certain cultural and religious sentiments have also contributed to multiple instances of gendercide across the globe.

== Etymology ==
The term gendercide was first coined by American feminist [[Mary Anne Warren]] in her 1985 book, ''Gendercide: The Implications of Sex Selection''. It refers to gender-selective mass killing.&lt;ref name="auto1"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Jones |first1=Adam |author-link=Adam Jones (Canadian scholar) |title=Gendercide and Genocide |journal=[[Journal of Genocide Research]] |date=2000 |volume=2 |issue=2 |pages=185–211 |doi=10.1080/713677599 |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/713677599 |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |s2cid=143867857 |access-date=2023-08-27 |archive-date=2023-08-27 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20230827010220/https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/713677599 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Warren drew "an analogy between the concept of genocide" and what she called "gendercide". In her book, Warren wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
By analogy, gendercide would be the deliberate extermination of persons of a particular sex (or gender). Other terms, such as "gynocide" and "femicide," have been used to refer to the wrongful killing of girls and women. Nevertheless, "gendercide" is a sex-neutral term in that the victims may be either male or female. There is a need for such a sex-neutral term since sexually discriminatory killing is just as wrong when the victims happen to be male. The term also calls attention to the fact that gender roles have often had lethal consequences and that these are in important respects analogous to the lethal consequences of racial, religious, and class prejudice.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Femicide ==
{{main|Femicide}}
{{see also|Violence against women|Missing women|Female infanticide}} 
[[File:Gedenktafel Stadtrandstr 562 (FalFe) Nuriye Bekir.jpg|thumb|Memorial plaque in Berlin for Nuriye Bekir, who was murdered in an "honor" killing]] [[File:Gedenktafel Oberlandgarten 1 (Temp) Hatun Sürücü.JPG|thumb|200 px|Memorial plaque for [[Hatun Sürücü]] in Berlin. The Kurdish woman from Turkey was murdered at the age of 23 by her brothers in an "honor" killing.]]
{{Violence against women}}
[[Femicide]] is defined as the systematic killing of women for various reasons, usually cultural. The word is attested from the 1820s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.dictionary.com/browse/femicide 'femicide' at dictionary.com |title=Origin of femicide: First recorded in 1820–30 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190509063104/https://www.dictionary.com/browse/femicide |archive-date=2019-05-09 |website=www.dictionary.com |access-date=8 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The most widespread form of femicide is in the form of gender-selective [[infanticide]] in cultures with strong preferences for males such as [[China]] and [[India]]. According to the United Nations, male-to-female ratios have experienced radical changes from the normal range.&lt;ref name="auto2"&gt;[http://www.unfpa.org/webdav/site/global/shared/documents/publications/2011/Preventing_gender-biased_sex_selection.pdf United Nations Population Fund 2011.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111011095023/https://www.unfpa.org/webdav/site/global/shared/documents/publications/2011/Preventing_gender-biased_sex_selection.pdf |date=2011-10-11 }} ''www.unfpa.org'' accessed 8 September 2019&lt;/ref&gt; Gendercide of girls is reported to be a rising problem in several countries. Census statistics report that in countries such as China, the male to female ratio is as high as 120 men for every 100 women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.economist.com/node/15606229 |work=[[The Economist]] |title=The War on Baby Girls: Gendercide |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180614064837/https://www.economist.com/node/15606229 |archive-date=2018-06-14 |date=4 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many experts attribute such a ratio to institutions such as [[One-child policy|China's one-child policy]]. Female heirs were considered less desirable than male heirs, and subsequently abandoned and eliminated in mass.&lt;ref name="auto4"&gt;{{Cite web |last=Soken-Huberty |first=Emmaline |date=2020-04-18 |title=What is Gendercide? |url=https://www.humanrightscareers.com/issues/what-is-gendercide/ |access-date=2022-12-01 |website=Human Rights Careers |language=en-US |archive-date=2022-11-10 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20221110173425/https://www.humanrightscareers.com/issues/what-is-gendercide/ |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gendercide also takes the forms of infanticide and lethal violence against a particular gender at any stage of life. The World Bank describes violence against girls and women as a "global pandemic". One in three women experiences gender-based violence in their lifetime. In research released in 2019, 38% of murdered women were killed by an intimate partner.&lt;ref name="auto4"/&gt;

Sex ratios at birth over time in China:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.allgirlsallowed.org/category/topics/gendercide |title=Gendercide in China Statistics Statistics About Gendercide in China |website=All Girls Allowed |access-date=2012-03-22 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190327101345/http://www.allgirlsallowed.org/category/topics/gendercide |archive-date=2019-03-27 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 106:100 in 1979 (106 boys for every 100 girls, close to the upper limit of the 'normal' range)
* 111:100 in 1988
* 117:100 in 2001
* 120:100 in 2005

In India, parents may prefer male children because they desire heirs who will care for them in their old age. Other instances of female infanticide are carried out in belief that the female children are better off not being alive, so as to not "[suffer]".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |title=Girls killed at birth in some poor parts of India |url=https://www.baltimoresun.com/news/bs-xpm-1994-02-22-1994053187-story.html |access-date=2022-11-29 |work=[[Baltimore Sun]] |date=22 February 1994 |archive-date=2022-11-29 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20221129173250/https://www.baltimoresun.com/news/bs-xpm-1994-02-22-1994053187-story.html |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, the cost of a [[dowry]] – the family's price for their daughter to be married off – is very high in India, making a female child undesirable, while a male heir would bring a dowry to the family by way of marriage. According to the [[Britain (place name)|British]] publication, ''[[The Independent]]'', the 2011 [[census]] revealed 7.1 million fewer girls than boys aged under the age of seven, up from 6 million in 2001 and from 4.2 million in 1991. The sex ratio in the age group is now 915 girls to 1,000 boys (109 boys for every 100 girls), the lowest since records began in 1961.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/the-full-extent-of-indias-gendercide-2288585.html |last=Laurence |first=Jeremy |title=The full extent of India's 'gendercide' |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171201043825/https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/the-full-extent-of-indias-gendercide-2288585.html |archive-date=2017-12-01 |work=[[The Independent]] |access-date=8 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been reports of [[Female homicides in Ciudad Juárez|femicide in Ciudad Juárez]], [[Chihuahua, Chihuahua|Chihuahua, Mexico]],&lt;ref name=Amnesty&gt;{{cite web |title=Mexico: Justice fails in Ciudad Juárez and the city of Chihuahua |url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/node/55339 |website=[[Amnesty International]] |access-date=19 March 2012 |date= 28 February 2005 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120303095740/http://www.amnestyusa.org/node/55339 |archive-date=3 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; where 411 assassinations of women were qualified as serial and/or of sexual characteristic, by domestic violence, intimate femicides and hatred against women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Feminicidio |language=es |trans-title=Femicide |url=http://www.inegi.org.mx/inegi/contenidos/espanol/eventos/vigenero/dia29/feminicidios.asp?c=1420 |website=INEGI |publisher=Encuentro Internacional de Estadística de Género |access-date=19 September 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100328115112/http://www.inegi.org.mx/inegi/contenidos/espanol/eventos/vigenero/dia29/feminicidios.asp?c=1420 |archive-date=28 March 2010 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The response to these murders has included the criminalisation of feminicide in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Garita Vílchez |first=Ana Isabel |title=La regulación del delito de feminicidio/feminicio en América Latina y El Caribe |trans-title=The regulation of the crime of femicide/femicide in Latin America and the Caribbean |chapter-url=http://www.un.org/es/women/endviolence/pdf/reg_del_femicicidio.pdf|access-date=19 September 2017 |isbn=978-1-936291-74-8 |location=Ciudad de Panamá, Panamá |page=48 |language=es |chapter=Cuadro No.6. Elementos del tipo penal. Chile. Código Penal |trans-chapter=Table No. 6. Elements of the criminal type. Chile. Criminal Code |archive-date=27 July 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180727124901/http://www.un.org/es/women/endviolence/pdf/reg_del_femicicidio.pdf |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Contemporary mechanisms of gendercide lie within sexualized violence against women; the females of "sub-Saharan Africa (Sierra Leone, the Democratic Republic of Congo, Angola) in areas that are also at the heart of the "AIDS belt",&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt; are not only at-risk due to living in places where there are "current cases of large-scale rape",&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt; but are also susceptible to contracting HIV. Less popularized tactics of gendercide against women include the systemic withholding of critical medical, and nutritional care, predominantly occurring "across the belt of "deep patriarchy" extending from East through West Asia and into Northern Africa";&lt;ref name="auto3"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Jones |first1=Adam |author-link=Adam Jones (Canadian scholar) |title=Gendercide: Examining gender-based crimes against women and men |journal=Clinics in Dermatology |date=March 2013 |volume=31 |issue=2 |pages=226–229 |doi=10.1016/j.clindermatol.2011.09.001 |pmid=23438385}}&lt;/ref&gt; here. Adam Jones, a co-founder of Gendercide Watch, an online research platform created to spread awareness, estimates that the denial of healthcare for women equates to approximately the same toll as that of the 1994 Rwandan Genocide per year.&lt;ref name="auto3"/&gt;

Over 200,000 die from bleeding, with many giving birth in buses or bullock carts. Lack of health education restricts commonplace medical knowledge; thus, bystanders are unable to offer assistance. In addition, the casualty rate from self-administered abortions is roughly 75,000. [[Eclampsia]], a condition possible pre-, during, and post-childbirth, is characterized by seizures due to high blood pressure, and its effects kill another 75,000 through damage to the brain and kidneys. Moreover, 100,000 die from sepsis, contracted through untreated infections of the uterus and remaining fragments of the placenta that poison the bloodstream. Also, female casualties due to labor obstructions stagger around the 400,000 range.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

[[Female genital mutilation]] also proves itself a form of gendercide, with at least 200 million girls and women having been cut in 31 different countries, most prominently in [[MENA]] countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Female Genital Mutilation (FGM) Statistics |url=https://data.unicef.org/topic/child-protection/female-genital-mutilation/ |access-date=2022-11-29 |website=[[UNICEF]] |language=en-US |archive-date=2019-05-26 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190526211316/https://data.unicef.org/topic/child-protection/female-genital-mutilation/ |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The practice has shown to have both fatal immediate and long-term complications. Immediate complications include infection, bleeding, urinary problems, and long-term complications include vaginal and menstrual problems, decreased sexual satisfaction, and complications with childbirth, including the increased risk of newborn deaths.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Female genital mutilation |url=https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/female-genital-mutilation |access-date=2022-11-29 |website=[[World Health Organization]] |language=en |archive-date=2021-01-29 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210129023511/https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/female-genital-mutilation |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, women have historically been the victims of sexual violence, and rape has been repeatedly used as both a weapon of war, and a form of genocide. For example, "between the months of January and August of 1945," there were over "1.4 million" reported "rape cases". Subsequently, some "200,000 girls and women" died because of sexually transmitted diseases.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2018-03-11 |title=IN PICTURES: How German women suffered largest mass rape in history by Soviets |url=https://english.alarabiya.net/features/2018/03/11/PICTURES-The-largest-mass-rape-in-history |access-date=2022-12-01 |website=[[Al Arabiya English]] |language=en |archive-date=2022-12-01 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20221201005145/https://english.alarabiya.net/features/2018/03/11/PICTURES-The-largest-mass-rape-in-history |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=rape - Rape as a weapon of war {{!}} Britannica |url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/rape-crime/Rape-as-a-weapon-of-war |access-date=2022-12-01 |website=www.britannica.com |language=en |archive-date=2022-12-01 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20221201005143/https://www.britannica.com/topic/rape-crime/Rape-as-a-weapon-of-war |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Adam Jones drafted possible solutions to aid the crisis in Africa. He concluded treatment "would mean training some 850,000 health workers, according to UNICEF and World Health Organization reports, as well as [funding] the necessary drugs and equipment. The total cost would be US $200 million, about the price of half a dozen jet fighters".&lt;ref name="auto3"/&gt;

== Androcide ==
{{main|Androcide}}
{{see also|Violence against men|Male expendability}}[[File:Tissot Pharaoh and the Midwives.jpg|thumb|Pharaoh and the Midwives, [[James Tissot]] c. 1900. In [[:s:Bible (King James)/Exodus#Chapter 1|Exodus 1:15-21]], [[Puah]] and [[Shiphrah]] were commanded by Pharaoh to kill all of the newborn baby boys, but they disobeyed.]]
{{Violence against men}}

Androcide is the systematic killing of men or boys for various reasons, usually cultural.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Liao |first1=Fang-Lian |last2=Green |first2=Tamara M. |date=1991 |title=The Greek and Latin Roots of English |journal=TESOL Quarterly |volume=25 |issue=4 |pages=724 |doi=10.2307/3587092 |issn=0039-8322 |jstor=3587092}}&lt;/ref&gt; Androcide may happen during war to reduce an enemy's potential pool of soldiers. According to the Global Justice Center, perpetrators of genocide often target men and boys first or give them greater priority, and they may also suffer "other acts of violence ... such as torture, rape, and enslavement" that tend to be obscured by a focus on the killings themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |page=12 |last1=Ashraph |first1=Sareta |last2=Radhakrishnan |first2=Akila |title=BEYOND KILLING: Gender, Genocide, &amp; Obligations Under International Law |url=https://globaljusticecenter.net/files/Gender-and-Genocide-Whitepaper-FINAL.pdf |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210227175649/https://globaljusticecenter.net/files/Gender-and-Genocide-Whitepaper-FINAL.pdf |archive-date=2021-02-27 |website=[[Global Justice Centre]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples include the 1988 [[Al-Anfal Campaign|Anfal campaign]] against Kurdish males that were considered "battle-aged" (or approximately ages 15–50)&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.hrw.org/reports/1991/IRAQ913.htm Whatever Happened To The Iraqi Kurds? Human Rights Watch Report, 1991] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171023161026/https://www.hrw.org/reports/1991/IRAQ913.htm |date=2017-10-23 }} ''www.hrw.org'', accessed 8 September 2019&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.pbs.org/frontlineworld/stories/iraq501/events_faylee.html Dave Johns: The Crimes of Saddam Hussein, 1980 The Fayli Kurds] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210416142017/https://www.pbs.org/frontlineworld/stories/iraq501/events_faylee.html |date=2021-04-16 }} ''www.pbs.org'', accessed 8 September 2019&lt;/ref&gt; in Iraqi [[Kurdistan]]. While many of these deaths took place after the Kurdish men were captured and processed at a concentration camp, the worst instances of the gendercide happened at the end of the campaign (August 25 – September 6, 1988).&lt;ref name=":055"&gt;{{Cite book |title=Gendered Experiences of Genocide: Anfal Survivors in Kurdistan-Iraq |last=Hardi |first=Choman |publisher=Ahgate |year=2011 |isbn=978-0754677154 |pages=21–22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another incident of androcide was the [[Srebrenica massacre]] of approximately 8,000 Bosniak men and boys on July 12, 1995, ruled as an act of genocide by the International Court of Justice.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.rferl.org/a/1059660.html Srebrenica Timeline] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190710210815/https://www.rferl.org/a/1059660.html |date=2019-07-10 }} ''www.rferl.org'', accessed 8 September 2019&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=4737583&amp;t=1567976226887 Serbians Still Divided Over Srebrenica Massacre] ''www.npr.org'', accessed 8 September 2019&lt;/ref&gt; From the morning of July 12, Serb forces began gathering men and boys from the refugee population in Potočari and holding them in separate locations, and as the refugees began boarding the buses headed north towards Bosniak-held territory, Serb soldiers separated men of military age who were trying to clamber aboard. Occasionally, younger and older men were stopped (some as young as 14 or 15).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icty.org/x/cases/krstic/trans/en/000726ed.htm "Separation of boys, ICTY Potocari"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20230219152951/https://www.icty.org/x/cases/krstic/trans/en/000726ed.htm |date=2023-02-19 }} 26 July 2000, ''Icty.org'' accessed 8 September 2019&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icty.org/x/cases/popovic/trans/en/070206ED.htm "Separation, ICTY Sandici"]''Icty.org'' {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190317090440/http://www.icty.org/x/cases/popovic/trans/en/070206ED.htm |date=2019-03-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icty.org/x/cases/krstic/trans/en/000411ed.htm "Separation, ICTY"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20230219153008/https://www.icty.org/x/cases/krstic/trans/en/000411ed.htm |date=2023-02-19 }} 11 July 1995 ''Icty.org'' accessed 8 September 2019&lt;/ref&gt;

Individual men also fall victim to honor killings. Male honor killings are often carried out by family members to prevent dishonor from falling onto families; reasons for male honor killings range from sexuality to gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |title=Gay Iranian man dead in alleged 'honor killing,' rights group says |url=https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/gay-iranian-man-dead-alleged-honor-killing-rights-group-says-n1266995 |access-date=2022-11-29 |work=[[NBC News]] |date=11 May 2021 |language=en |archive-date=2021-05-12 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210512005039/https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/gay-iranian-man-dead-alleged-honor-killing-rights-group-says-n1266995 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=A Dark History: Honor Killings of Iran's LGBTQ Citizens |url=https://iranwire.com/en/features/67398/ |access-date=2022-11-29 |website=iranwire.com |language=en |archive-date=2022-11-29 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20221129174808/https://iranwire.com/en/features/67398/ |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to genocide scholar Adam Jones, "non-combatant men have been and continue to be the most frequent targets of mass killing and genocidal slaughter, as well as a host of lesser atrocities and abuses."&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt;

== Third gender ==
{{Main article|Transgender genocide}}
Gendercide against [[third gender]] people is the systemic killing of people who do not fit within the [[gender binary]]. [[Deborah A. Miranda|Deborah Miranda]] uses the term gendercide to identify the Spanish colonial practice of systemically targeting ''joyas'' (the Spanish term for third gender people) in an attempt to exterminate them.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Miranda |first=Deborah |date=2010 |title=Extermination of the Joyas: Gendercide in Spanish California |url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/372454/pdf |journal=GLQ: A Journal of Lesbian and Gay Studies |volume=16 |issue=1–2 |pages=255–260 |doi=10.1215/10642684-2009-022 |s2cid=145480469 |via=Project MUSE |access-date=2021-12-31 |archive-date=2021-05-17 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210517043746/https://muse.jhu.edu/article/372454/pdf |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Qwo-Li Driskill writes how this violence was waged against people now understood as [[two-spirit]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Qwo-Li |first=Driskill |title=Asegi Stories: Cherokee Queer and Two-Spirit Memory |publisher=[[University of Arizona Press]] |year=2016 |isbn=9780816533640 |pages=54}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1513 at Santa Clara, Darien (present day [[ Panama]]), Spanish explorer [[Vasco Núñez de Balboa|Vasco Nuñez de Balboa]] encountered about forty [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Indigenous]] men dressed as women. He commanded his soldiers to execute them through making them prey for their [[war dogs]], which were specially bred [[mastiff]]s or [[greyhound]]s. They were dismembered and eaten alive by the dogs. Third gender people from around the area were rounded up in service of Spanish authority. Miranda writes that "the Spanish had made it clear that to tolerate, harbor, or associate with the third gender meant death."&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt;

In his 1775 memoir, [[Spanish Empire|Spanish]] soldier [[Pedro Fages]] wrote that about two or three ''joyas'' could be identified in each [[Indigenous Californian]] village and were "held in great esteem" in their communities. Fages sought to initiate a swift reduction of the ''joyas'', writing "we place our trust in God and expect that these accursed people will disappear with the growth of the [[Spanish missions in California|missions]]. The abominable vice will be eliminated to the extent that the [[Catholic faith]] and all the other virtues are firmly implanted there, for the glory of God and the benefit of those poor ignorants."&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt;

== By region ==

=== Europe ===
In Europe, there are many different types of gendercide.

Most recent instances of mass gendercide in Europe have resulted from sociopolitical motions, as "military strategies". For example, during the 1999 war in Kosovo, "battle age" ethnic-Albanian men were detained and killed in mass as a part of a "Serb military strategy".&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt;

Historically, from the 15th to the 18th century, girls, women, and some men fell victim to the frenzied cultural phenomena of witch-hunts. It is estimated that upwards of 100,000 trials took place, and from those trials, 60,000 individuals were executed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Gendercide Watch: European Witch-Hunts |url=https://www.faculty.umb.edu/gary_zabel/Courses/Phil%20281b/Philosophy%20of%20Magic/Arcana/Witchcraft%20and%20Grimoires/case_witchhunts.html |access-date=2022-12-01 |website=www.faculty.umb.edu |archive-date=2022-10-24 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20221024193301/http://www.faculty.umb.edu/gary_zabel/Courses/Phil%20281b/Philosophy%20of%20Magic/Arcana/Witchcraft%20and%20Grimoires/case_witchhunts.html |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Individual instances of gendercide also continue to permeate European society, ranging to individual murders, honor killings, to war-related deaths.

=== Asia ===
When compared to Europe, Asia has a staggeringly different sex-ratio. In Qatar, a middle-eastern country, there are a reported 299 males for every 100 females. The ratio is primarily due to large immigrant populations of largely male temporary workers&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Global population skews male, but UN projects parity between sexes by 2050 |url=https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2022/08/31/global-population-skews-male-but-un-projects-parity-between-sexes-by-2050/#:~:text=Sex%20ratios%20vary%20widely&amp;text=In%20several%20Persian%20Gulf%20countries,population%2C%2083%25%20were%20male |access-date=2023-03-23 |website=[[Pew Research]] |date=31 August 2022 |archive-date=2023-03-27 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20230327084852/https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2022/08/31/global-population-skews-male-but-un-projects-parity-between-sexes-by-2050/#:~:text=Sex%20ratios%20vary%20widely&amp;text=In%20several%20Persian%20Gulf%20countries,population%2C%2083%25%20were%20male |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; or the pervading cultural sentiment of males being more desirable than females.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Countries by Sex Ratio 2022 |url=https://worldpopulationreview.com/country-rankings/countries-by-sex-ratio |access-date=2022-12-01 |website=worldpopulationreview.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Men are seen as more useful, and women as costly burdens. Such sentiments have led to increased rates of female infanticide across the continent, especially in countries such as India.&lt;ref name="auto4"/&gt;

And though honor killings occur everywhere, they occur most commonly in Asian countries like India, Pakistan and Bangladesh.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Honour Killings By Region |url=http://hbv-awareness.com/regions/ |access-date=2022-12-01 |language=en-US |archive-date=2013-12-08 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131208172508/http://hbv-awareness.com/regions/ |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Experts explain that such murders are performed in order to protect the cultural concept of familial honor; things dishonorable enough to warrant such actions can range from sexuality, divorce, to gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Janjua |first=Haroon |date=2022-03-15 |title=The horror of honor killings |url=https://adnchronicles.org/2022/03/15/the-horror-of-honor-killings/ |access-date=2022-12-01 |website=Asia Democracy Chronicles |language=en-US |archive-date=2022-12-01 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20221201005144/https://adnchronicles.org/2022/03/15/the-horror-of-honor-killings/ |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Africa ===
Gendercide across Africa is as ranged as any other continent. Gendercide through systematic governmental efforts have been carried out across African countries over the centuries. For example, there exists the Rwandan genocide in which 800,000 were killed, and 250,000 girls and women were systematically raped by individuals infected with HIV/AIDs virus, resulting in even more death, and a continued issue with the disease even to this day.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |date=2019-04-06 |title=Factbox: Rwanda remembers the 800,000 killed on 25th anniversary of genocide |language=en |work=[[Reuters]] |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-rwanda-genocide-anniversary-factbox-idUSKCN1RI0FV |access-date=2022-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gendercide also exists in Africa through the form of female genital mutilation–a procedure performed on both infants and girls that can result in numerous immediate and longterm complications and even death.

Similarly to Europe, witch-hunts prove a form of gendercide across Africa. It is reported that both men and women fall victim to witch-hunts, but women are more heavily targeted.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Witch-hunts in contemporary sub-Saharan Africa |url=https://www.gendercide.org/witch-hunts-in-contemporary-sub-saharan-africa/ |access-date=2022-12-01 |website=Gendercide |language=en-GB |archive-date=2022-12-01 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20221201040723/https://www.gendercide.org/witch-hunts-in-contemporary-sub-saharan-africa/ |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Main|Outline of genocide studies}}
{{Portal|Genocide}}
* [[Male expendability]]
* [[Female foeticide in India]]
* [[Female infanticide in China]]
* [[Gender disappointment]]
* [[Genocide]]
* [[Honor killing]]
* [[Missing women]]
* [[Witch-hunt]]
* [[Chick culling]]
* [[Girl power]]
* [[Women's rights]]
* [[Women's empowerment]]
* [[Male infanticide]]
* [[Daughter preference]]
* [[Single-gender world]]
* ''[[Matrubhoomi: A Nation Without Women]]''
* ''[[Y: The Last Man]]'' 
* [[Men's rights movement]] 
* [[Son preference]] 

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
{{Main|Bibliography of Genocide studies}}
* A [http://www.taliacarner.com/gendercide.pdf comprehensive analysis of gendercide in China] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220709185918/https://www.taliacarner.com/gendercide.pdf |date=2022-07-09 }} was delivered by author Talia Carner at the 2007 U.N. Commission on the Status of Women.
*{{cite book |last=Warren |first=Mary Anne |title=Gendercide: The Implications of Sex Selection |year=1985 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Allanheld |isbn=978-0-8476-7330-8 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/gendercideimplic0000warr }}
*{{cite book |last=Russell |first=Diana E.H. |title=Femicide in Global Perspective |author2=Roberta A. Harmes |year=2001 |publisher=Teachers College Press |isbn=978-0-8077-4047-7 }}
*{{cite book |last=Sanford |first=Victoria |title=Guatemala : Del Genocidio Al Feminicidio/From Genocide to Femicide |year=2008 |publisher=F&amp;G Editores |isbn=978-99922-61-88-0 }}
*Shahrzad Mojab. (2003). Kurdish Women in the Zone of Genocide and Gendercide. Al-Raida 21(103): 20–25.

== External links ==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070806225912/http://www.guernicamag.com/features/299/the_price_of_life_1/ Femicide in Guatemala—Guernica Magazine (guernicamag.com)]
* [[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights]], '' [http://www.cidh.org/annualrep/2002eng/chap.vi.juarez.htm Situation of the Rights of Women in Ciudad Juárez]'' (2002) — Report by [[Organization of American States|OAS]] human rights agency.
* [https://www.economist.com/middle-east-and-africa/2005/11/24/no-place-for-your-daughters ''The Economist'' – No place for your daughters] (November 24, 2005)

{{Sexual identities}}
{{Sexual abuse}}
{{Genocide topics}}{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Gendercide| ]]
[[Category:Gender-related violence]]
[[Category:Killings by type]]
[[Category:Genocide]]
[[Category:Hate crime]]
[[Category:Murder]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Human sex ratio]]
[[Category:1985 neologisms]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>