<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051011060114|25257094" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="54944" pageid="54944" ns="0" title="Religious intolerance"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-06T22:34:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Religious persecution}}
'''Religious intolerance'''  is either [[intolerance]] motivated by one's own [[Religion|religious]] beliefs or intolerance against another's religious beliefs or practices. 

The opposite of intolerance is [[tolerance]].

Religious intolerance and [[religious persecution|persecution]] have been common throughout history, and most faiths have been subject to it at one time or another.

In its 2000 annual report on international religious freedom, the U.S. State Department cited China, Myanmar, Iran, Iraq and Sudan for persecuting people for their religious faith and practices.  The report, which covers July 1999 through June 2000, details U.S. policy toward countries where religious freedom is violated in view of the U.S. State Department.  The 1998 International Religious Freedom Act,  created the State Department's Office of International Religious Freedom mandates an integrates U.S. policy on religious freedom into overall U.S. international policy.[http://www.uscirf.gov/mediaroom/press/2000.html]

==Notable historical cases==
* [[Jean Calas]]
* [[Jean-François de la Barre]]
* [[Dreyfus Affair]]

==See also==

*[[Anti-Catholicism]]
*[[Anti-Protestantism]]
*[[Anti-Mormonism]]
*[[Anti-Semitism]]
*[[Apostasy]]
*[[Christianophobia]]
*[[Freedom of religion]]
*[[Inquisition]]
*[[Islamophobia]]
*[[Opposition to cults and new religious movements]]
*[[Religiocentrism]]
*[[Religious persecution]]
*[[Religious pluralism]]
*[[Religious terrorism]]
*[[Religious toleration]]
*[[Tolerance]]
*[[Witch hunt]]

{{religion-stub}}

[[Category:Religion and society]]

[[pl:Dyskryminacja religijna]]
[[he: אפליה דתית]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>