<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20180212214421|825345661" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="54944" pageid="54944" ns="0" title="Religious intolerance"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-04-14T11:25:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{about|intolerance by or between religious communities or by communities of specific practices|intolerance of religion itself|Antireligion|and|Irreligion|and|Antitheism}}
{{overcoverage|date=January 2018}}
{{Refimprove|date=June 2015}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Religious intolerance''' is [[Toleration|intolerance]] against another's religious beliefs or practices or lack thereof.

==Definition==
The mere statement on the part of a religion that its own beliefs and practices are correct and any contrary beliefs are incorrect does not in itself constitute intolerance (i.e., ideological intolerance).

Religious intolerance, rather, is when a group (e.g., a society, religious group, non-religious group) specifically refuses to tolerate practices, persons or beliefs  on religious grounds.

==Historical perspectives==
The modern concept of intolerance developed out of the religious controversies between Protestants and Catholics in 17th- and 18th-century England. The doctrine of 'religious toleration' at this time, sought to eradicate religious sentiments and dogmas from the political demesne.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hobolt|first=Sara B.|authorlink=Sara Hobolt|last2=Brug|first2=Wouter Van der|last3=Vreese|first3=Claes H. De|last4=Boomgaarden|first4=Hajo G.|last5=Hinrichsen|first5=Malte C.|date=2011-09-01|title=Religious intolerance and Euroscepticism|url=http://eup.sagepub.com/content/12/3/359|journal=European Union Politics|language=en|volume=12|issue=3|pages=359–79|doi=10.1177/1465116511404620|issn=1465-1165}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the 19th century British historian [[Arnold Toynbee]], for a religious establishment to persecute another religion for being "wrong" ironically puts the persecuting religion in the wrong, undermining its own legitimacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Toynbee|first=Arnold|title=A Study of History: Abridgment of Volumes I–VI|year=1947|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York, NY|isbn=0-19-505081-9|editor=Dorothea Grace Somervell|page=300|chapter=Failure of Self-Determination}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contemporary attitude and practice==
[[File:Taller Buddha of Bamiyan before and after destruction.jpg|thumb|A statue of the [[Buddha]] at [[Buddhas of Bamiyan|Bamiyan]] before and after its March 2001 destruction by [[Taliban]] forces.]]

The [[constitution]]s of some countries contain provisions expressly forbidding the state from engaging in certain acts of religious intolerance or preference within its own borders, examples of such include the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] of the [[United States]] [[United States Constitution|Constitution]], the Article 4 of the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany|Basic Law]] of [[Germany]], Article 44.2.1 of the [[Constitution of Ireland|Constitution]] of [[The Republic of Ireland]], Article 40 of the [[Estonia]]n Constitution,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/en00000_.html ''"Estonia - Constitution"''], ICL Document 28 June 1992, retrieved 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Article 24 of the [[Constitution of Turkey|Constitution]] of [[Turkey]], Article 36 of the [[Constitution of the People's Republic of China|Constitution]] of the [[People's Republic of China]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://en.people.cn/constitution/constitution.html|title=Constitution of the People's Republic of China|website=en.people.cn|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Article 3 Section 5 of the [[1987 Constitution|Constitution of the Philippines]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thecorpusjuris.com/laws/constitutions/8-philippineconstitutions/70-1987-constitution.html 1987 Constitution of the Republic of the Philippines], [http://thecorpusjuris.com CorpusJuris], retrieved 24 September 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Other states, whilst not containing constitutional provisions directly related to religion, nonetheless contain provisions forbidding discrimination on religious grounds (see, for example, Article 1 of the [[France|French]] [[Constitution of France|Constitution]], article 15 of Canada's [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] and article 40 of the [[Constitution of Egypt|Constitution]] of Egypt). These constitutional provisions do not necessarily guarantee that all elements of the state remain free from religious intolerance at all times, and practice can vary widely from country to country.

Other countries, meanwhile, may allow for religious preference, for instance through the establishment of one or more [[state religion]]s, but not for religious intolerance. [[Finland]], for example, has the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]] and [[Finnish Orthodox Church]] as its official state religions, yet upholds the right of free expression of religion in article 11 of its [[Constitution of Finland|constitution]].

Some countries retain laws forbidding [[defamation]] of religious belief. Some retain laws forbidding all forms of [[blasphemy]] (e.g., [[Germany]] where, in 2006, [[Manfred van H.]] was convicted of blasphemy against [[Islam]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.expatica.com/de/news/Suspended-prison-for-German-who-insulted-Koran_135903.html|title=Suspended prison for German who insulted Koran|website=www.expatica.com|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is seen by some as official endorsement of religious intolerance, amounting to the criminalization of religious views. The connection between intolerance and blasphemy laws is closest when the laws apply to only one religion. In [[Pakistan]] blasphemy directed against either the tenets of the [[Qur'an]] or the Prophet [[Mohammed]] is punishable by either life imprisonment or death. [[Apostasy]], the rejection of one's old religion, is also criminalized in a number of countries, notably [[Afghanistan]] with [[Abdul Rahman (convert)|Abdul Rahman]] being the first to face the [[Capital punishment|death penalty]] for converting to [[Christianity]].

The [[United Nations]] upholds the right to free expression of religious belief in articles and 18 and 19 of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] while article 2 forbids [[discrimination]] on the basis of religion. Article 18 also allows for the freedom to change religion. The Declaration is not legally binding, however the United States chose in 1998 to pass the International Religious Freedom Act, creating the [[United States Commission on International Religious Freedom|Commission on International Religious Freedom]], and mandating that the United States government take action against any country found to violate the religious freedoms outlined in the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://usinfo.state.gov/usa/infousa/laws/majorlaw/intlrel.htm "International Religious Freedom Act of 1998"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070608190937/http://usinfo.state.gov/usa/infousa/laws/majorlaw/intlrel.htm |date=2007-06-08 }}, 27 January 1998, retrieved 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Human Rights Council in 2011 adopted Resolution 16/18 on "Combating intolerance, negative stereotyping and stigmatization of, and discrimination, incitement to violence and violence against, persons based on religion or belief"&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrcouncil/docs/16session/A.HRC.RES.16.18_en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; which was hailed by stakeholders from all regions and faiths as a turning point in international efforts to confront religious intolerance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = URG Policy Report: Combatting global religious intolerance|url = http://www.universal-rights.org/urg-policy-reports/combatting-global-religious-intolerance-the-implementation-of-human-rights-council-resolution-1618/|website = Universal Rights Group|access-date = 2016-02-10|language = en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[European Convention on Human Rights]], which is legally binding on all [[European Union]] states (following the passage of the [[Human Rights Act 1998]] in the [[United Kingdom]]), makes restricting the rights of an individual to practice or change their religion illegal in article 9, and discrimination on the basis of religion illegal in article 14.

In its 2000 annual report on international religious freedom, the U.S. [[State Department]] cited China, [[Myanmar]], Iran, Iraq and [[Sudan]] for persecuting people for their religious faith and practices.  The report, which covers July 1999 through June 2000, details U.S. policy toward countries where religious freedom is violated in the view of the U.S. State Department.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uscirf.gov/mediaroom/press/2000.html "United States Commission on International Freedom of Religion"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051103150009/http://uscirf.gov/mediaroom/press/2000.html |date=2005-11-03 }}, Press Releases 2000, retrieved 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[advocacy group]] [[Freedom House]] produced a report entitled "Religious Freedom in the World" in 2000 which ranked countries according to their religious freedom. The countries receiving a score of 7, indicating those where religious freedom was least respected, were [[Turkmenistan]], Iran, Saudi Arabia, [[Sudan]], [[Myanmar]] and [[North Korea]]. China was given a score of 6 overall, however [[Tibet]] was listed separately in the 7 category. Those countries receiving a score of 1, indicating the highest level of religious freedom, were [[Estonia]], [[Finland]], [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], the [[Netherlands]], [[Norway]] and the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://freedomhouse.org/report/freedom-world/freedom-world-2000|title=Freedom in the World 2000 {{!}} Freedom House|website=freedomhouse.org|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within those countries that openly advocate religious tolerance there remain debates as to the limits of tolerance. Some individuals and religious groups, for example, retain beliefs or practices which involve acts contrary to established law, such as the use of [[Cannabis (drug)|cannabis]] by members of the [[Rastafari movement]], the religious use of eagle feathers by non-[[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] (contrary to the [[eagle feather law]], 50 CFR 22), or the practice of [[polygamy]] amongst the [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|LDS Church]] in the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://scriptures.lds.org/en/od/1 "Official Declaration"], Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, 6 October 1890, retrieved 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

== In Australia ==
Religious freedom has developed partly due to the agreeable relationship between religious groups in its society. Several non-governmental organizations promoted tolerance and better understanding among religions in the country, both indigenous and non-indigenous. These groups included the Columbian Centre for Christian-Muslim Relations, the National Council of Churches in Australia and its affiliated Aboriginal and Islander Commission, and the Australian Council of Christians and Jews. In Victoria, Australia the Racial and Religious Tolerance Act 2001 makes illegal "conduct that incites hatred against, serious contempt for, or revulsion or severe ridicule of, that other person or class of persons" on the grounds of religious belief.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/legis/vic/consol_act/rarta2001265/|title=Racial and Religious Tolerance Act 2001|website=www.austlii.edu.au|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2003, in response to an increase in anti-Islamic sentiment, the HREOC undertook a project involving national consultations on eliminating prejudice against Arab and Muslim citizens. As part of the consultations, the commission considered whether Muslim citizens shared an ethnic origin or race, as well as a religion, which would entitle them to comprehensive protection under the Federal Race Discrimination Act. The commission's report, made public in June 2004, contained no findings on the racial status of Arab and Muslim citizens. In January 2005 the leader of the neo-Nazi Australian Nationalist Movement was connected to incidents in 2004 in which several Asian-owned businesses and a synagogue in Perth were firebombed or sprayed with racist graffiti. On December 11, 2005, there was a riot in the Sydney suburb of Cronulla, that erupted because a group of Lebanese-Australian youths had assaulted two lifeguards.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.acma.gov.au/webwr/_assets/main/lib101068/2gb%2520-%2520report%25201485.pdf|title=Error {{!}} ACMA|website=www.acma.gov.au|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Demonstrators against the assault displayed anti-Arab and anti-Muslim slogans. When the gathering turned violent, bystanders perceived to be of Middle Eastern origin or Muslim were attacked. The following day, retaliatory vandalism and other assaults were reported around Sydney.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.state.gov/j/drl/rls/irf/2006/71333.htm|title=Australia|website=U.S. Department of State|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Religion|Human rights}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Antireligion]]
*[[Antitheism]]
*[[Demonization]]
*[[Fundamentalism]]
*[[Heterosexism]]
*[[Homophobia]]
*[[Religious controversies]]
*[[Religious discrimination]]
*[[Religious freedom]]
*[[Religious paranoia]]
*[[Religious tolerance]]
*[[Religious violence]]
*[[Religious war]]
*[[Toleration]]
*[[Violence against LGBT people]]
{{div col end}}

;Specific religions:
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Anti-Catholicism]]
*[[Anti-cult movement]]
*[[Anti-Hinduism]]
*[[Anti-Judaism]]
*[[Anti-Mormonism]]
*[[Anti-Semitism]]
*[[Anti-Christian sentiment]]
*[[Buddhas of Bamiyan]]
*[[Christian countercult movement]]
*[[Demolition of the Babri Masjid]]
*[[Destruction of cultural heritage by ISIL]]
*[[Islamophobia]]
*[[Persecution of Baha'is]]
*[[Persecution of Buddhists]]
*[[Persecution of Hindus]]
*[[Persecution of Muslims]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;

==Further reading==
* Garth Blake, "Promoting Religious Tolerance in a Multifaith Society: Religious Vilification Legislation in Australia and the UK." ''The Australian Law Journal'', 81 (2007): 386–405.
* Chopra, R.M., "A Study of Religions", 2015, Anuradha Prakashan, New Delhi, {{ISBN|978-93-82339-94-6}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Religious persecution}}
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/4075442.stm "New Effort to Ban Religious Hate", BBC News, 11 June 2005] retrieved 25 May 2007

{{Religious persecution}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Religious Intolerance}}
[[Category:Religious discrimination]]
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Religion and society]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>