<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061103153635|85484184" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="54944" pageid="54944" ns="0" title="Religious intolerance"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-03T15:37:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Religious persecution}}
{{Cleanup-date|October 2006}}
{{Mergeto|Freedom of religion|date=October 2006}}
'''Religious intolerance'''  is either [[intolerance]] motivated by one's own [[Religion|religious]] beliefs or intolerance against another's religious beliefs or practices. 

Religious intolerance and [[religious persecution|persecution]] have been common throughout history, and most faiths have been subject to it at one time or another.

==Contemporary attitudes and practice==
A number of countries worldwide contain provisions within their [[constitution]]s expressly forbidding the state from engaging in certain acts of religious intolerance or preference within its own borders. Examples include The [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] of the [[United States]] [[United States Constitution|Constitution]], Article 4 of the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany|Basic Law]] of [[Germany]], Article 44.2.1 of the [[Constitution of Ireland|Constitution]] of [[The Republic of Ireland]], Article 40 of the [[Estonian]] Constitution[http://www.oefre.unibe.ch/law/icl/en00000_.html] and Article 24 of the [[Constitution of Turkey|Constitution]] of [[Turkey]]. Many other states, whilst not containing constitutional provisions directly related to religion, nonetheless contain provisions forbidding discrimination on religious grounds (see, for example, Article 1 of the [[France|French]] [[Constitution of France|Constitution]], article 15 of the [[Canada|Canadian]] [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms|Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] and article 40 of the [[Constitution of Egypt|Constitution]] of [[Egypt]]). It should be noted that these constitutional provisions do not necessarily guarantee that all elements of the state remain free from religious intolerance at all times, and practice can vary widely from country to country.

Other countries, meanwhile, may allow for religious preference, for instance through the establishment of one or more [[state religion]]s, but not for religious intolerance. [[Finland]], for example, has the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]] and [[Finnish Orthodox Church]] as its official state religions, yet upholds the right of free expression of religion in article 11 of its [[Constitution of Finland|constitution]]. 

Some countries retain [[blasphemy]] laws, forbidding [[defamation]] of religious belief, which are sometimes seen as a way of condoning religious intolerance. Whilst some countries retain laws forbidding all forms of blasphemy (such as [[Germany]] where in [[2006]] [[Manfred van H.]] was convicted of blasphemy against [[Islam]]), the connection between intolerance and blasphemy laws  is most closely connected if the laws apply to only one religion. In the [[United Kingdom]], for instance, it is illegal to make blasphemous remarks only if the remarks are directed against the beliefs of the [[Church of England]], though there have been no convictions since [[1922]] (see [[Blasphemy law in the United Kingdom]]). In [[Pakistan]] blasphemy directed against either the tenets of the [[Qur'an]] or the Prophet [[Mohammed]] is punishable by either life imprisonment or death. [[Apostasy]], the rejection of one's old religion, is also criminalised in a number of countries, notably [[Afghanistan]] with [[Abdul Rahman (convert)|Abdul Rahman]] being the first to face the death penalty for converting to Christianity.

The [[United Nations]] upholds the right to free expression of religious belief in article 18 of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] while article 2 forbids discrimination on the basis of religion. Article 18 also allows for the freedom to change religion. The Declaration is not legally binding, however the [[United States]] chose in [[1998]] to pass the International Religious Freedom Act, creating the [[United States Commission on International Religious Freedom|Commission on International Religious Freedom]], and mandating that the United States government take acation against any country found to violate the religious freedoms outlined in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.[http://usinfo.state.gov/usa/infousa/laws/majorlaw/intlrel.htm] The [[European Convention on Human Rights]], which is legally binding on all [[European Union]] states (following the passage of the [[Human Rights Act 1998]] in the [[United Kingdom]]), makes restricting the rights of an individual to practice or change their religion illegal in article 9, and discrimination on the basis of religion illegal in article 14. 

In its 2000 annual report on international religious freedom, the U.S. [[State Department]] cited [[China]], [[Myanmar]], [[Iran]], [[Iraq]] and [[Sudan]] for persecuting people for their religious faith and practices.  The report, which covers July 1999 through June 2000, details U.S. policy toward countries where religious freedom is violated in the view of the U.S. State Department.[http://www.uscirf.gov/mediaroom/press/2000.html]  The [[advocacy group]] [[Freedom House]] produced a report entitled "Religious Freedom in the World" in 2000 which ranked countries according to their religious freedom. The countries receiving a score of 7, indicating those where religious freedom was least respected, were [[Turkmenistan]], [[Iran]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Sudan]], [[Myanmar]] and [[North Korea]]. [[China]] was given a score of 6 overall, however [[Tibet]] was listed separately in the 7 category. Those countries receiving a score of 1, indicating the highest level of religious freedom, were [[Estonia]], [[Finland]], [[Ireland]], [[The Netherlands]], [[Norway]] and the [[United States]]. [http://freedomhouse.org/religion/publications/rfiw/fig1.htm]

Within those countries that openly advocate religious tolerance there remain debates as to the limits of tolerance. Some individuals and religious groups, for example, retain beliefs or practices which involve acts contrary to established law, such as the use of [[marijuana]] by [[Rastafarians]], the religious use of [[eagle]] [[feathers]] by non-[[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] (contrary to the [[eagle feather law]], 50 CFR 22), or the practice of [[polygamy]] amongst [[Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|Mormons]] in the 19th century. The precise definition of "religion", and to which groups it applies, can also cause controversy, for example the case of [[Scientologists]] who regard the refusal by the German government to recognise their religious status as an example of religious intolerance whereas the government regards it as a matter of regulation involving a commercial organisation. Attempts to legislate against acts of religious intolerance amongst citizens frequently come up against issues regarding the [[freedom of speech]]; whilst in [[France]] being convicted of incitement to religious hatred can carry a maximum of 18 months in prison an attempt to pass a similar law by [[Tony Blair]]'s [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour]] government in the [[United Kingdom]] had to be dropped in April, [[2006]] after criticism that it restricted free speech. In [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]], [[Australia]] the [[Racial and Religious Tolerance Act 2001]] makes illegal "conduct that incites hatred against, serious contempt for, or revulsion or severe ridicule of, that other person or class of persons" on the grounds of religious belief.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>