<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20240928081818|1248215529" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="54944" pageid="54944" ns="0" title="Religious intolerance"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-10-21T11:55:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Intolerance of another's religious beliefs or practices}}
{{About|intolerance by and between religious communities or by communities of specific practices|intolerance of religion itself|Antireligion|and|Irreligion|and|Antitheism}}{{See also|Religious tolerance}}{{Multiple issues|
{{update|date=April 2019}}
{{missing information|Ancient, Medieval and Early Modern history of religious intolerance and persecution and trends on religious intolerance in the 2010s|date=April 2019}}
{{Globalize|date=January 2018}}
{{More citations needed|date=June 2015}}
}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expanded=Related}}
[[File:Somnath temple ruins (1869).jpg|thumb|257x257px|The [[Somnath temple|Somnath Hindu Temple]] was first attacked by Muslim Turkic invader [[Mahmud of Ghazni]] and repeatedly rebuilt after being demolished by more Invaders.]]
''' Religious intolerance''' is [[Toleration|intolerance]] of another's religious beliefs, practices, faith or lack thereof. 

Statements which are contrary to one's religious beliefs do not constitute intolerance. Religious intolerance, rather, occurs when a person or group (e.g., a society, a religious group, a non-religious group) specifically refuses to tolerate the religious convictions and practices of a religious group or individual.

==Historical perspectives==
The intolerance, and even the active persecution of religious minorities (sometimes religious majorities as in modern [[Bahrain]] or the Pre-Dutch Indonesian kingdoms), has a long history. Almost all religions have historically faced and perpetrated persecution of other viewpoints.

The modern concept of [[religious tolerance]] developed out of the [[European wars of religion]], more specifically out of the [[Peace of Westphalia]] which ended the [[30 Years' War]] (1618–1648), during the [[Protestant Reformation]] and the ensuing conflicts between [[Protestantism|Protestants]] and [[Catholic Church|Catholics]] in the 16th, 17th and 18th centuries. The doctrine of 'religious toleration' was established as a result of the 30 Years' War between the Catholic [[Hapsburgs]] and newly Protestant nations like [[Sweden]] under [[Gustavus Adolphus]]. At this time, rulers sought to eradicate religious sentiments and dogmas from their political [[demesne]]s. The 1648 Treaty gave nations the right of sovereignty and it also allowed minority Christian denominations to exist within the [[Holy Roman Empire]].&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Hobolt|first1=Sara B.|author-link=Sara Hobolt|last2=Brug|first2=Wouter Van der|last3=Vreese|first3=Claes H. De|last4=Boomgaarden|first4=Hajo G.|last5=Hinrichsen|first5=Malte C.|date=2011-09-01|title=Religious intolerance and Euroscepticism|journal=European Union Politics|language=en|volume=12|issue=3|pages=359–79|doi=10.1177/1465116511404620|s2cid=93065237|issn=1465-1165}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contemporary attitude and practice==
[[File:Taller Buddha of Bamiyan before and after destruction.jpg|thumb|A [[Buddhas of Bamiyan|statue of the Buddha at Bamiyan]] before and after its March 2001 destruction by [[Taliban]] forces]]

The [[constitution]]s of some countries contain provisions which expressly forbid the state from engaging in certain acts of religious intolerance and these same provisions also forbid the state from showing a preference for a particular religion within its own borders, examples of such provisions include the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution]], the Article 4 of the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany]], Article 44.2.1 of the [[Constitution of Ireland]], Article 40 of the [[Constitution of Estonia|Estonian Constitution]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|first= Axel 
| last = Tschentscher|title=Estonia &gt; Constitution
| translator= Martin Scheinin
| orig-date = 28 July 1992
| publisher=International Constitutional Law Project | year = 1995
|url=http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/en00000_.html|access-date=2023-01-02|website=www.servat.unibe.ch|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 24 of the [[Constitution of Turkey]], Article 36 of the [[Constitution of the People's Republic of China]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://en.people.cn/constitution/constitution.html|title=Constitution of the People's Republic of China|website=en.people.cn|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Article 3 Section 5 of the [[1987 Constitution|Constitution of the Philippines]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The 1987 Constitution of the Republic of the Philippines – Article III |url=http://www.officialgazette.gov.ph/constitutions/the-1987-constitution-of-the-republic-of-the-philippines/the-1987-constitution-of-the-republic-of-the-philippines-article-iii |website=[[Official Gazette of the Republic of the Philippines]] |access-date=22 August 2023 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170903150355/http://www.officialgazette.gov.ph/constitutions/the-1987-constitution-of-the-republic-of-the-philippines/the-1987-constitution-of-the-republic-of-the-philippines-article-iii |archive-date=September 3, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other states, whilst not containing constitutional provisions which are directly related to religion, nonetheless contain provisions which forbid [[Religious discrimination|discrimination on religious grounds]] (see, for example, Article 1 of the [[Constitution of France]], article 15 of the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] and article 40 of the [[Constitution of Egypt]]). These constitutional provisions do not necessarily guarantee that all elements of the state remain free from religious intolerance at all times, and practice can vary widely from country to country.
[[File:Desecrated Jain idols on the stone cliffs, Gopachal Parvat, Gwalior Fort, Madhya Pradesh.jpg|thumb|Mughal Emperor [[Babur]] demolished [[Gopachal rock cut Jain monuments|Gopalchal rock cut Jain Monuments]].]]
Other countries, meanwhile, may allow for religious preference, for instance through the establishment of one or more [[state religion]]s, but not for religious intolerance. [[Finland]], for example, has the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]] and [[Finnish Orthodox Church]] as its official state religions, yet upholds the right of free expression of religion in article 11 of [[Constitution of Finland|its constitution]].

In [[Nazi Germany]], smaller religious minorities such as the [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] and the [[Baháʼí Faith in Germany|Baháʼí Faith]] were banned in Germany, while the eradication of [[Judaism]] was attempted along with the [[The Holocaust|genocide]] of its adherents.

Hundreds of religious riots have been recorded, in every decade of independent India. In these riots, the victims have included many Muslims, Hindus, Sikhs, Jains, Christians and Buddhists. The US Commission on International Religious Freedom classified India as Tier-2 in persecuting religious minorities, the same as that of Iraq and Egypt. In a 2018 report, [[United States Commission on International Religious Freedom|USCIRF]] charged [[Hindu nationalism|Hindu nationalist]] groups for their campaign to "[[Saffronisation|Saffronize]]" India through violence, intimidation, and harassment against non-Hindus.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{cite report |url=https://www.uscirf.gov/sites/default/files/USCIRF2018AnnualReport_abb_wlinks.pdf |title=Annual Report of the U.S. Commission on International Religious Freedom |date=April 2018 |publisher=[[United States Commission on International Religious Freedom|U.S. Commission on International Religious Freedom]] |page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately one-third of state governments enforced anti-conversion and/or anti-cow slaughter&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=States Where Cow Slaughter is Banned So Far, and States Where it Isn't |date=26 May 2017 |url=https://www.news18.com/news/india/states-where-cow-slaughter-is-banned-so-far-and-states-where-it-isnt-1413425.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; laws against non-Hindus, and mobs engaged in violence against Muslims whose families have been engaged in the dairy, leather, or beef trades for generations, and against Christians for proselytizing. "Cow protection" lynch mobs killed at least 10 victims in 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |title=Tracking mob lynching in two charts |url=https://www.thehindu.com/data/tracking-mob-violence-in-two-charts/article24321028.ece |website=[[The Hindu]]|date=3 July 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=India's Got Beef With Beef: What You Need To Know About The Country's Controversial 'Beef Ban' |url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/leezamangaldas/2017/06/05/indias-got-beef-with-beef-what-you-need-to-know-about-the-countrys-controversial-beef-ban/#9e5a0c053c25 |website=[[Forbes]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some countries retain laws which forbid the [[defamation]] of religious beliefs. Some constitutions retain laws which forbid all forms of [[blasphemy]] (e.g., [[Germany]] where, in 2006, [[Manfred van H.]] was convicted of blasphemy against [[Islam]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.expatica.com/de/news/Suspended-prison-for-German-who-insulted-Koran_135903.html|title=Suspended prison for German who insulted Koran|website=www.expatica.com|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The connection between intolerance and blasphemy laws is closest when the laws apply to only one religion. In [[Pakistan]] blasphemy directed against either the tenets of the [[Qur'an]] or the Prophet [[Mohammed]] is punishable by either life imprisonment or death. [[Apostasy]], the rejection of one's old religion, is also criminalized in a number of countries, notably [[Afghanistan]] with [[Abdul Rahman (convert)|Abdul Rahman]] being the first to face the [[Capital punishment|death penalty]] for converting to [[Christianity]]. Though, he was later released.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.inq7.net/world/index.php?index=1&amp;story_id=70608 Afghan convert likely to be freed after Karzai intervention] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160115061705/http://news.inq7.net/world/index.php?index=1&amp;story_id=70608|date=January 15, 2016}}, by Sardar Ahmad, ''mq7.net'', 26 March 2006, retrieved 28 March 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Hate Hurts Wales - Portrayal of Religious Hate Crime.webm|thumb|[[Welsh Government]] advisory video: religious hate crime; 2021]]

The [[United Nations]] upholds the right to freely express one's religious beliefs, as listed in the [[Charter of the United Nations|UN's charter]], and additionally in articles 2 and 18 of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]]. Article 2 forbids discrimination based on religious grounds. Article 18 protects the freedom to change one's religion. 
As a [[treaty]], not a [[wikt:declaration|declaration]], is legally binding, the signing of the human rights declaration is a public pledge of commitment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Declaration on the Elimination of All Forms of Intolerance and of Discrimination Based on Religion or Belief |url=https://www.ohchr.org/en/instruments-mechanisms/instruments/declaration-elimination-all-forms-intolerance-and-discrimination |website=OHCHR.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{clarify|date=December 2019}}&lt;!--So, is or is not the UDHR legally binding?--&gt; Out of a desire to avoid subservience to an international court, the United States chose in 1998 to pass the [[International Religious Freedom Act]], creating the [[United States Commission on International Religious Freedom|Commission on International Religious Freedom]], and mandating that the United States government take action against any country found to violate the religious freedoms outlined in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://usinfo.state.gov/usa/infousa/laws/majorlaw/intlrel.htm "International Religious Freedom Act of 1998"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070608190937/http://usinfo.state.gov/usa/infousa/laws/majorlaw/intlrel.htm |date=2007-06-08 }}, 27 January 1998, retrieved 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Human Rights Council]] in 2011 adopted Resolution 16/18 on "Combating intolerance, negative stereotyping and stigmatization of, and discrimination, incitement to violence and violence against, persons based on religion or belief"&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrcouncil/docs/16session/A.HRC.RES.16.18_en.pdf|title=Combating intolerance, negative stereotyping and stigmatization of, and discrimination, incitement to violence and violence against, persons based on religion or belief|access-date=2019-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was hailed by stakeholders from all regions and faiths as a turning point in international efforts to confront religious intolerance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = URG Policy Report: Combatting global religious intolerance|url = http://www.universal-rights.org/urg-policy-reports/combatting-global-religious-intolerance-the-implementation-of-human-rights-council-resolution-1618/|website = Universal Rights Group|access-date = 2016-02-10|language = en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[European Convention on Human Rights]], which is legally binding on all [[European Union states]] (following the passage of the [[Human Rights Act 1998]] in the [[United Kingdom]]), makes restricting the rights of an individual to practice or change their religion illegal in article 9, and discrimination on the basis of religion illegal in article 14.

In North Korea, The regime reportedly continues to repress the religious activities of unauthorized religious groups. North Korea is considered an [[atheist state]],&lt;ref name="State Atheism"&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YG2AFyFppJQC&amp;pg=PA933 |title=World and Its Peoples: Eastern and Southern Asia |date=September 2007 |publisher=[[Marshall Cavendish]] |isbn=9780761476313 |quote=North Korea is officially an atheist state in which almost the entire population is nonreligious. |access-date=2011-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Atheist State"&gt;{{cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/stateofreligiona00obri |title=The State of Religion Atlas |publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]] |year=1993 |isbn=9780671793760 |quote=Atheism continues to be the official position of the governments of China, North Korea and Cuba. |access-date=2011-03-05 |url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt; where refugees, defectors and [[non-governmental organization]]s (NGOs) continued to allege that they witnessed the arrests and [[execution]] of members of underground [[Christianity|Christian]] churches by the regime in prior years. Due to the country's inaccessibility and the inability to gain timely information, this activity remains difficult to verify.&lt;ref name="USGov"&gt;{{Source-attribution|United States Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor. [https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90140.htm North Korea: International Religious Freedom Report 2007].|sentence=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Aid to the Church in Need {{!}} North Korea |url=http://acnuk.org/north-korea/ |access-date=2019-07-03 |website=Aid to the Church in Need |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In its 2000 annual report on international religious freedom, the [[U.S. State Department]] cited China, [[Myanmar]], Iran, Iraq and [[Sudan]] for persecuting people for their religious faith and practices.  The report, which covers July 1999 through June 2000, details U.S. policy toward countries where religious freedom is violated in the view of the State Department.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uscirf.gov/mediaroom/press/2000.html "United States Commission on International Freedom of Religion"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051103150009/http://uscirf.gov/mediaroom/press/2000.html |date=2005-11-03 }}, Press Releases 2000, retrieved 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[advocacy group]] [[Freedom House]] produced a report entitled "Religious Freedom in the World" in 2000 which ranked countries according to their religious freedom. The countries receiving a score of 7, indicating those where religious freedom was least respected, were [[Turkmenistan]], Iran, Saudi Arabia, [[Sudan]], [[Myanmar]] and [[North Korea]]. China was given a score of 6 overall, however [[Tibet]] was listed separately in the 7 category. Those countries receiving a score of 1, indicating the highest level of religious freedom, were [[Estonia]], [[Finland]], [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], the [[Netherlands]], [[Norway]] and the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://freedomhouse.org/report/freedom-world/freedom-world-2000|title=Freedom in the World 2000 {{!}} Freedom House|website=freedomhouse.org|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within those countries that openly advocate religious tolerance there remain debates as to the limits of tolerance. Some individuals and religious groups, for example, retain beliefs or practices which involve acts contrary to established law, such as the use of [[Cannabis (drug)|cannabis]] by members of the [[Rastafari movement]], the religious use of eagle feathers by non-[[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] (contrary to the [[eagle feather law]], 50 CFR 22), or the [[Mormonism and polygamy|practice of polygamy amongst the LDS Church]] in the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Official Declaration 1|url=https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/eng/scriptures/dc-testament/od/1|access-date=2023-01-02|website=www.churchofjesuschrist.org|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In Australia ==
Religious freedom has developed partly due to the agreeable relationship between religious groups in its society. Several non-governmental organizations promoted tolerance and better understanding among religions in the country, both indigenous and non-indigenous. These groups included the Columbian Centre for Christian-Muslim Relations, the [[National Council of Churches in Australia]] and its affiliated Aboriginal and Islander Commission, and the [[Australian Council of Christians and Jews]]. In Victoria, Australia the [[Racial and Religious Tolerance Act 2001]] makes illegal "conduct that incites hatred against, serious contempt for, or revulsion or severe ridicule of, that other person or class of persons" on the grounds of religious belief.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/legis/vic/consol_act/rarta2001265/|title=Racial and Religious Tolerance Act 2001|website=www.austlii.edu.au|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, in response to an increase in [[Islamophobia in Australia|anti-Islamic sentiment]], the [[HREOC]] undertook a project involving national consultations on eliminating prejudice against Arab and Muslim citizens. As part of the consultations, the commission considered whether Muslim citizens shared an ethnic origin or race, as well as a religion, which would entitle them to comprehensive protection under the Federal Race Discrimination Act. The commission's report, made public in June 2004, contained no findings on the racial status of Arab and Muslim citizens. In January 2005 the leader of the neo-Nazi [[Australian Nationalist Movement]] was connected to incidents in 2004 in which several Asian-owned businesses and a synagogue in Perth were firebombed or sprayed with racist graffiti. On December 11, 2005, there was a riot in the Sydney suburb of Cronulla, that erupted because a group of Lebanese-Australian youths had assaulted two lifeguards.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.acma.gov.au/webwr/_assets/main/lib101068/2gb%2520-%2520report%25201485.pdf|title=Error {{!}} ACMA|website=www.acma.gov.au|access-date=2016-05-17|archive-date=2016-07-02|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160702141545/http://www.acma.gov.au/webwr/_assets/main/lib101068/2gb%20-%20report%201485.pdf|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Demonstrators against the assault displayed anti-Arab and anti-Muslim slogans. When the gathering turned violent, bystanders perceived to be of Middle Eastern origin or Muslim were attacked. The following day, retaliatory vandalism and other assaults were reported around Sydney.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/j/drl/rls/irf/2006/71333.htm|title=Australia|website=U.S. Department of State|access-date=2016-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Religion}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Antireligion]]
*[[Antitheism]]
*[[Demonization]]
*[[Forced conversion]]
*[[Fundamentalism]]
*[[Religious discrimination]]
*[[Freedom of religion|Religious freedom]]
*[[Religious persecution]]
*[[Toleration|Religious tolerance]]
*[[Religious violence]]
*[[Supremacism#Religious|Religious supremacism]]
*[[Religious terrorism]]
*[[Religious war]]
*[[Sectarian violence]]
*[[State atheism]]
*[[State religion]]
*[[Toleration]]
*[[Violence against LGBT people#Religious texts]]
{{div col end}}

{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
;Specific religions:
*[[Anti-cult movement]]
*[[Christian countercult movement]]
*[[Discrimination against atheists]]
*[[Persecution of Baháʼís]]
*[[Persecution of Buddhists]]
*[[Persecution of Christians]]
**[[Anti-Mormonism]]
**[[Anti-Protestantism]]
**[[Persecution of Eastern Orthodox Christians]]
**[[Anti-Catholicism]]
**[[Anti-Christian sentiment]]
*[[Persecution of Hindus]]
**[[Anti-Hinduism]]
*[[Persecution of Jews]]
**[[Anti-Judaism]]
**[[Antisemitism]]
*[[Persecution of Muslims]]
**[[Islamophobia]]

;[[Religious nationalism]]:
** [[Christian nationalism]]
** [[Islam and nationalism]]
** [[Hindutva]]
** [[Religious Zionism]]

;Specific examples:
*[[2012 Ramu violence]]
*[[Aranthalawa massacre]]
*[[Bodh Gaya bombings]]
*[[Buddhas of Bamiyan]]
*[[Buddhist crisis]]
*[[Demolition of the Babri Masjid]]
*[[Destruction of cultural heritage by ISIL]]
*[[Conversion of non-Islamic places of worship into mosques]]

{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Chopra, R.M., "A Study of Religions", Anuradha Prakashan, New Delhi, 2015 {{ISBN|978-93-82339-94-6}}
* Garth Blake, "Promoting Religious Tolerance in a Multifaith Society: Religious Vilification Legislation in Australia and the UK." ''The Australian Law Journal'', 81 (2007): 386–405.

==External links==
{{commons category|Religious persecution}}
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/4075442.stm "New Effort to Ban Religious Hate", BBC News, 11 June 2005] retrieved 25 May 2007

{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
{{Religious persecution}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Religion and society]]
[[Category:Religious discrimination]]
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Toleration]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>