<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071016190234|165010207" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3244031" pageid="3244031" ns="0" title="Black feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-13T13:29:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Expand|date=January 2007}}
{{Feminism}}

'''Black feminism''' essentially argues that [[sexism]] and [[racism]] are inextricable from one another&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/modern/Defining-Black-Feminist-Thought.html Defining Black Feminist Thought], retrieved on May 31st 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;. Forms of [[feminism]] that strive to overcome [[sexism]] and [[Social class|class]] oppression but ignore or minimize race can perpetuate [[racism]] and thereby contribute to the oppression of many people, including women. Black feminists argue that the liberation of black women entails [[Freedom (political)|freedom]] for all people, since it would require the end of racism, sexism, and class oppression&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/modern/Black-Feminist-Statement.html A Black Feminist Statement - 1974], retrieved on May 31st 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;. Black women in this category often refer to themselves as [[Womanism|womanist]].
[[Kathleen Watkins]] adds that contrary to "[[Urban legend|urban lore]]", black feminists and womanists are loving and gentle wives who respect their male companions.{{fact|date=September 2007}}

== Current Black Feminism ==

The current incarnation of '''Black Feminism''' is a political/social movement that grew out of a sense of feelings of discontent with both the [[Civil Rights|Civil Rights Movement]] and the [[Feminism|Feminist Movement]] of the 1970s.  Not only did the Civil Rights Movement primarily focus only on the oppression of black men, but many black women faced severe sexism within Civil Rights groups such as the [[Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee]].  The Feminist Movement focused on the problems faced by white women.  For instance, earning the power to work outside of the home was not an accomplishment for black feminists; they had been working all along.  Neither movement confronted the issues that concerned black women specifically.  Because of their [[intersectionality|intersectional position]], black women were being systematically disappeared by both movements.  Black women began creating theory and developing a new movement which spoke to the combination of problems, sexism, racism, classism, etc., that they had been battling.

== Alice Walker's Black Feminism ==

One of the theories that evolved out of this movement was [[Alice Walker|Alice Walker's]] [[Womanism]].  [[Angela Davis]] was one of the first people who formed an argument centered on intersectionality; she did this in her book, "Women, Race, and Class."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/blackwomen.html List of Books written by Black Feminists], retrieved on May 31st 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Kimberle Crenshaw]], prominent feminist law theorist, gave the idea a name while discussing [[Identity Politics]] in her essay, "Mapping the Margins: Intersectionality, Identity Politics and Violence Against Women of Color."  Another Feminist theorist is [[Patricia Hill Collins]]; much of her work concerns the politics of black feminist thought and oppression.  While many of these theorists were beginning their writing, Black Feminist groups were forming.  One of these groups is [[The Combahee River Collective]], founded by [[Barbara Smith]]; this group's primary goal was "the development of integrated analysis and practice based upon the fact that the major systems of oppression are interlocking."

== Pat Parker ==
[[Pat Parker]]'s (1944-1989) involvement in the black feminist movement was reflected in her writings as a poet. Her work inspired other black feminist poets like [[Hattie Gossett]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/hattiegossett-biography.html Biography of Hattie Gossett], retrieved on May 31st 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Some of her works include:
*Child of Myself (1971)
*Pit Stop (1974)
*Womanslaughter (1978)
*Movement in Black (1978)
*Jonestown &amp; Other Madness (1985)

==References==
*Crenshaw, K. 1991. Mapping the margins: Intersectionality, identity politics, and violence against women of color. Stanford Law Review 43(6) 1241-99.
*Combahee River Collective. 1977. A Black Feminist Statement. in Capitalist Patriarchy and the Case For Social Feminism. Zillah Eisenstein, ed.
*Roth, Benita. 2004. Separate Roads to Feminism: Black, Chicana, and White Feminist Movements in America's Second Wave, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
*In Memoriam: Pat Parker (1944-1989) Black American Literature Forum, Vol. 23, No. 3, Poetry Issue (Autumn, 1989), p. 538.

==Notes==
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]

[[hr:Crni feminizam]]
[[sh:Crni feminizam]]
[[sv:Black feminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>