<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051026225956|26568535" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20903342" pageid="20903342" ns="0" title="Sodomy law"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-27T19:47:28Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''sodomy law''' is a law which makes certain [[sexual acts]] into [[sex crime]]s. The term [[sodomy]] has in the past been used to refer to any deviant sexual act, often deemed so because such does not lead to [[procreation]]. That inclusive interpretation includes [[oral sex]], and [[bestiality]], but the predominant understanding of sodomy relates it to [[anal sex]].

It is believed that sodomy laws originated from cultural and religious beliefs as a result of the health complications associated with it. The tissue lining the [[rectum]] is the most absorbent of all the body's tissues, therefore an increased risk of [[sexually transmitted diseases]] exists.

While many other parts of the world have, or had, laws against sodomy or other sexual practices, the term ''sodomy law'' has mainly been used when discussing the sodomy laws of the [[United States]] which were struck down by the [[United States Supreme Court|U.S. Supreme Court]] in [[2003]]. 

Following Sir [[William Blackstone]]'s ''[[Commentaries on the Laws of England]]'' [http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/blackstone/bk4ch15.htm], the crime of sodomy has often been defined in the past only as the ''abominable and detestable crime against nature'', or some variation of the phrase.  This language led to widely varying rulings about what specific acts were encompassed by its prohibition.  

== Impact on homosexuals ==

A common misunderstanding is that sodomy laws are anti-homosexual. Most sodomy laws target both [[heterosexuality|heterosexual]] and [[homosexuality|homosexual]] acts, including [[oral sex]] and [[anal sex]]. Although these acts are not exclusively homosexual, the laws against them are selectively enforced primarily against homosexuals. 

Frequently, [[Religion and homosexuality|religious beliefs]] are responsible, if not cited for the existence of sodomy laws. Some sodomy laws include all homosexual or all ''non-coital'' sex, including [[oral sex]], [[Frottage (sexology)|frottage]], [[tribadism]], and [[masturbation]]. Historically, heterosexuals have not been prosecuted for acts covered under sodomy laws. In [[England]], [[Henry VIII]] introduced the first legislation against homosexuals with the [[Buggery Act]] of [[1533]], making [[buggery]] punishable by [[hanging]], a penalty not lifted until [[1861]]. 

After the publishing of the [[Wolfenden report]] in the [[United Kingdom|UK]], many western governments, including the [[United States]], have repealed laws specifically against homosexual acts while retaining sodomy laws. In June 2003, the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] ruled in ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'' that [[U.S. state|state]] laws criminalizing private, non-commercial sexual activity (including homosexual activity) between consenting adults are unconstitutional.  

This trend among Western nations has not been followed in all other regions of the world, where sodomy often remains a serious crime. Homosexual acts remain punishable by death in [[Afghanistan]], [[Mauritania]], [[Iran]], [[Nigeria]], [[Pakistan]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Sudan]], [[United Arab Emirates]], and [[Yemen]], and by life in prison in [[Bangladesh]], [[Bhutan]], [[Guyana]], [[India]], [[Maldives]], [[Nepal]], [[Singapore]], and [[Uganda]].

Along with alleged [[communist]]s, homosexuals were investigated by the notorious Senator [[Joseph McCarthy]] in the U.S., who chaired a committee that produced a report entitled "Employment of Homosexuals and Other Sex [[Perversion|Perverts]] in Government".

=== United Kingdom ===

The [[United Kingdom|UK]] has historically had similar laws, but the offence is known as '''[[buggery]]''', not sodomy, and is usually interpreted as referring to anal intercourse between two males or a male and a female.  Buggery was made a [[felony]] by the [[Buggery Act]] in [[1533]], during the reign of [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]].  In [[1885]], Parliament enacted the [[Labouchere Amendment]] [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/pwh/englaw.html], which prohibited ''gross indecency'' between males, a broad term that was understood to encompass most or all male homosexual acts.  It was under this law that [[Oscar Wilde]] was convicted and imprisoned.  Subsequent to the [[Wolfenden report]], sexual acts between two adult males, with no other people present, were made legal in [[England]], [[Wales]] in [[1967]], in [[Scotland]] in [[1980]] and [[Northern Ireland]] in [[1982]]. 

During 1994, attempts were made to reduce the age of consent for homosexuals to 16 (from 21), this was rejected by MPs, and a compromise age of 18 introduced. The passage of the [[Human Rights Act 1998]] has resulted in further broadening of the legality of homosexual acts, culminating, in [[2001]], under the [[Sexual Offences (Amendment) Act 2000]], with the homosexual age of consent reduced to 16 in England, Scotland, and Wales. The age of consent for both heterosexuals and homosexuals remains at 17 in Northern Ireland.

=== Canada ===

[[Canada|Canadian]] law now permits anal sex by consenting parties above the age of 18, provided no more than two people are present. Its sodomy laws were repealed in the [[1960s]] by [[Pierre Trudeau]] who famously stated that "the government has no place in the bedrooms of the nation". In the [[1995]] [[Ontario Court of Appeal]] case ''R. v. M. (C.)'', the judges ruled that the relevant section (section 159) of the [[Canadian Criminal Code|Criminal Code]] violated [[Section Fifteen of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms|section 15]] of the [[Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] when one or both of the partners are 14 to 18 years of age; this has not been tried in court again.

A similar decision was made by the [[Quebec Court of Appeal]] in the [[1998]] case ''R. v. Roy''.

=== Australia ===

[[Australia]] inherited the [[United Kingdom]]'s sodomy laws on colonisation in [[1788]].  These were retained in the criminal codes passed by the various colonial [[parliament]]s during the 19th century, and by the state parliaments after [[Federation]].

Following the [[Wolfenden report]], the [[Don Dunstan|Dunstan]] government introduced a ''consenting adults in private'' type defence in [[South Australia]] in [[1972]]. This defence was initiated as a bill by Murray Hill, father of [[Defence Minister]] [[Robert Hill]], and repealed the state's sodomy law in [[1975]].  The [[Campaign Against Moral Persecution]] during the 1970s raised the profile and acceptance of Australia's gay and lesbian communities, and other states and territories repealed their laws between 1976 and 1990.  The exception was [[Tasmania]], which retained its laws until the [[Government of Australia|Federal Government]] and the [[United Nations]] [[Human Rights Committee]] forced their repeal in 1997.  The details are given in the book ''Living out Loud: A History of Gay and Lesbian Activism in Australia''.

Since 1997, the states and territories that retained different ages of consent or other vestiges of sodomy laws have tended to repeal them.  [[New South Wales]] and the [[Northern Territory]] did so in 2003.  In 2004, [[Queensland]] is the only Australian jurisdiction that enforces a sodomy law, with the [[age of consent]] for anal sex being 18 as compared to 16.

=== China ===
Sodomy laws have been abolished since the early [[1990s]] in the [[People's Republic of China]]. Yet there is no clear statute towards consenting parties above the age of 18. If someone under 18 is involved, the adult partner will be prosecuted. In a notable case in [[2002]], a man who had anal intercourse with a teenager was sentenced to three and a half years in prison.

===France===
Since the [[French Revolution]], [[France]] has not had laws punishing homosexual conduct ''per se'' between over-age consenting adults in private. However, other qualifications such as "offense to good mores" were occasionally retained in the 19th century ''(see [[Jean Jacques Régis de Cambacérès]])''. Furthermore, the [[age of consent]] for homosexual sex was kept to the age of the [[legal majority]] (18 then 21), above the age for heterosexual sex (15), until [[1981]].

In [[1960]], a parliamentary amendment by [[Paul Mirguet]] added homosexuality to a list of "[[social scourge]]s", along with [[alcoholism]] and [[prostitution]]. This prompted the government to increase the penalties for public display of a sex act when the act was homosexual. [[Transvestite]]s or homosexuals caught [[cruising]] were also the target of police repression.

In [[1982]], under president [[François Mitterrand]], the last measures against homosexuality were repealed: one, dating from [[1942]] ([[Vichy France]]), making the age of consent for homosexual sex higher than for heterosexual sex, the other, dating from the [[1960s]], making homosexuality an aggravating circumstance for public indecency.

=== Germany ===
[[Paragraph 175]], which punished "[[fornication]] between men", was eased to an [[age of consent]] of 21 in [[East Germany]] in [[1957]] and in [[West Germany]] in [[1969]].  This age was lowered to 18 in the East in [[1968]] and the West in [[1973]], and all legal distinctions between [[heterosexual]] and [[homosexuality|homosexual]] acts were abolished in the East in [[1988]], with this change being extended to all of Germany in [[1994]] as part of the process of [[German Reunification]]. 

In modern [[German language|German]], the term ''Sodomie'' has a meaning different from the  [[English language|English]] word "[[sodomy]]": it does not refer to [[anal sex]] at all, but solely to acts of [[bestiality]].

=== Hungary ===

[[Homosexuality]] in [[Hungary]] was decriminalized in [[1962]], [[Paragraph 199 of the Hungarian Penal Code]] from then on threatened "only" adults over 18 who engaged themselves in a consensual same-sex relationship with an underaged person between 14 and 18. In [[1995]] a kind of [[domestic partners]]hip was introduced for same sex couples, on [[September 3]], [[2002]] the ruling of the [[Hungarian Constitutional Court]] abrogated Paragraph 199, since then the [[age of consent]] for both sexes and both for heterosexuals and homosexuals, is 14 years.

=== United States ===

[[Sodomy laws in the United States]], laws primarily intended to outlaw [[gay sex]], were largely a matter of state rather than federal jurisdiction.  By the last quarter of the [[20th century]], 46 out of 50 states had repealed any specifically anti-homosexual-conduct laws, and 36 had repealed all sodomy laws. The remaining anti-homosexual laws have been invalidated by the 2003 U.S. Supreme Court decision ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'' (see above).

Prior to 2003 invalidation: 

* '''Alabama  -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (1 year/$2,000)'''
* Alaska (repealed through legislative action 1980)
* Arizona (repealed through legislative action 2001)
* Arkansas  -- struck down by Jegley v. Picado, 80 S.W.3d 332 (Ark. 2001)
* California (repealed through legislative action 1976)
* Colorado (repealed through legislative action 1972)
* Connecticut (repealed through legislative action 1971)
* Delaware (repealed through legislative action 1973)
* '''Florida  -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (60 days/$500)'''
* Georgia -- struck down by Powell v. State, 510 S.E.2d 18 (1998) 
* District of Columbia (repealed through legislative action 1993)
* Hawaii (repealed through legislative action 1973)
* '''Idaho  -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (5 years to life)'''
* Illinois (repealed through legislative action 1962)
* Indiana (repealed through legislative action 1977)
* Iowa (repealed through legislative action 1978)
* '''Kansas  -- Same-Sex sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (6 months/$1,000)'''
* Kentucky -- struck down by Commonwealth v. Wasson, 842 S.W.2d 487 (Ky. 1992) 
* '''Louisiana  -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (5 years/$2,000)*'''
* Maine (repealed through legislative action 1976)
* Maryland  -- struck down by Williams v. State, 1998 Extra LEXIS 260, Baltimore City Circuit Court, January 14, 1999 
* Massachusetts -- struck down by GLAD v. Attorney General, SJC-08539 (Mass. Supreme Judicial Ct. 2002)
* '''Michigan -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty =(15 years) '''
* Minnesota -- struck down by Doe v. Ventura, No. MC 01-489, 2001 WL 543734 (Minn. Dist. Ct 2001)
* '''Mississippi  -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (10 years)'''
* '''Missouri -- Same-Sex sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (1 year/$1,000)'''
* Montana -- struck down by Gryczan v. Montana, 942 P.2d 112 (1997) 
* Nebraska (repealed through legislative action 1978)
* Nevada (repealed through legislative action 1993) 
* New Hampshire (repealed through legislative action 1975)
* New Jersey (repealed through legislative action 1979)
* New Mexico (repealed through legislative action 1975)
* New York -- struck down by People v. Onofre, 415 N.E.2d 936 (N.Y. 1980) 
* '''North Carolina  -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (10 years/discretionary fine)'''
* North Dakota (repealed through legislative action 1973)
* Ohio (repealed through legislative action 1974)
* '''Oklahoma -- Same-Sex sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (10 years)'''
* Oregon (repealed through legislative action 1972)
* Pennsylvania -- struck down by Commonwealth v. Bonadio, 415 A.2d 47 (Pa. 1980) and repealed by the legislature in 1995.) 
* Rhode Island (repealed through legislative action 1998)
* '''South Carolina  -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (5 years/$500)'''
* South Dakota (repealed through legislative action 1977)
* Tennessee -- Campbell v. Sundquist, 926 S.W.2d 250 (1996) 
* '''Texas --Same-Sex sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = ($500)'''
* '''Utah  -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (6 months/$1,000)'''
* Vermont (repealed through legislative action 1977)
* '''Virginia  -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (1-5 years)*'''
* Washington (repealed through legislative action 1976)
* West Virginia (repealed through legislative action 1976)
* Wisconsin (repealed through legislative action 1983)
* Wyoming (repealed through legislative action 1977)
'''Puerto Rico  -- All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (10 years)*'''

Source: [http://www.aclu.org/LesbianGayRights/LesbianGayRights.cfm?ID=5028&amp;c=41 ACLU website June 9, 2003]

===Singapore===

See [[Section 377 of the Singapore Penal Code]]

==See also== 
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Gay rights]]
* [[Societal attitudes towards homosexuality]]
* [[Homosexuality laws of the world]]

== References ==
* Graham Willett, ''Living out Loud: A History of Gay and Lesbian Activism in Australia'', [[2000]].  ISBN 1864489499.
* Peter McWilliams, [[Ain't Nobody's Business If You Do]], [[1998]].  ISBN 0931580587.

== External links ==
* [http://www.sodomylaws.org SodomyLaws.Org]
* [http://www.sodomylaws.org/usa/florida/flnews002.htm  Going Down Down South: Fighting Absurd Sex Laws]
* [http://www.sodomylaws.org/world/united_kingdom/uknews24.htm  The Accidental Legacy of a Homophobic Humanitarian] &amp;mdash; [[The Times]], [[October 2]], [[2000]]

[[Category:LGBT-related legislation]]
[[Category:Sex crimes]]
[[Category:Legal history]]
[[zh:&amp;#40481;&amp;#22904;&amp;#27861;]]
[[de:Gesetze gegen Homosexualität]]
[[nl:Sodomiewetgeving]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>