<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071102113528|168707661" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20903342" pageid="20903342" ns="0" title="Sodomy law"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-11T18:03:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''sodomy law''' is a [[law]] that defines certain [[sexual acts]] as [[sex crime]]s. The precise sexual acts meant by the term [[sodomy]] are rarely spelled out in the law, but is typically understood by courts to include any sexual act which does not lead to [[procreation]]. Furthermore, ''Sodomy'' has many [[synonym]]s: [[buggery]], [[crime against nature]], [[unnatural act]], [[deviant sexual intercourse]]. It also has a range of similar [[euphemism]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Weeks | first = Jeff | title =Sex, Politics and Society: The Regulation of Sexuality Since 1800 | publisher = Longman Publishing Group |date=January 1981 | location = London | id = ISBN 0-582-48334-4  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

While in theory this may include heterosexual [[oral sex]], [[anal sex]], [[masturbation]], and [[bestiality]], in practice such laws are primarily enforced against sex between men (particularly anal sex).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Sullivan | first = Andrew | title =  We're all sodomists now. | publisher = The New Republic Online |date=2003-04-03 | url = http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20030324&amp;s=sullivan032403 | accessdate = 2006-12-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians dispute the reason for the emergence of such laws, but they have roots in antiquity, and are linked to religious proscriptions against certain sex acts. Contemporary supporters of sodomy laws argue that there are additional reasons for retaining them. They include public health concerns about anal sex, or concerns that legalisation of homosexuality will lead to a declining population.

Sodomy laws can be found around the world. Today, consensual homosexual acts between adults are illegal in about 70 out of the 195 countries of the world;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fco.gov.uk/servlet/Front?pagename=OpenMarket/Xcelerate/ShowPage&amp;c=Page&amp;cid=1007029391647&amp;a=KArticle&amp;aid=1152525661291]&lt;/ref&gt; in 40 of these, only male-male sex is outlawed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ilga.info/Information/Legal_survey/summary_information_by_subject.htm ILGA World Legal Survey] (Last updated: 31 July 2000, accessed 19 April 2006); updates from [[Homosexuality laws of the world]].&lt;/ref&gt; This number has been declining since the second half of the 20th century.

== History ==

The Middle Assyrian Law Codes (1075 BCE) state: If a man have intercourse with his brother-in-arms, they shall turn him into a eunuch. This is the earliest known law condemning the act of [[sodomy]], 
The '''Lex Scantia''' was written by the [[Ancient Rome|Romans]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infopt.demon.co.uk/homopho2.htm Rictor Norton, "A History of Homophobia", 2 The Destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah].&lt;/ref&gt;

Most anti-sodomy laws in Western countries originated from a Christian world-view established from the bible.  The Biblical book [[Leviticus]] defines sex between men as a crime that warrants [[capital punishment]]. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Leviticus%2018:22;Leviticus%2020:13;&amp;version=31;49;45;9;50; Leviticus 18:22 &amp; 20:13]&lt;/ref&gt;The New Testament also condemns Sodomy. The biblical book of Romans calls Sodomy "unnatural", "degrading passions", "indecent acts"(Romans 1:24-27)"Therefore God gave them over in the lusts of their hearts to impurity, so that their bodies would be dishonored among them. 25 For they exchanged the truth of God for a lie, and worshiped and served the creature rather than the Creator, who is blessed forever.  Amen 26 for this reason God gave them over to degrading passions; for their women exchanged the natural function for that which is unnatural, and in the same way also the men abandoned the natural function of the women and burned in their desire toward one another, men with men committing indecent acts and receiving in their own persons the due penalty of their error." 1 Cor 6:9 says, "Do you not know that the unrighteous will not inherit the kingdom of God?  Do not be deceived; neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor homosexuals, nor thieves, nor the covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor swindlers, will inherit the kingdom of God." 1 Timothy (1:9-10) calls Sodomy an act that ungodly and sinners do.

In [[England]], [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]] introduced the first legislation under English criminal law against homosexuals with the [[Buggery Act of 1533]], making [[buggery]] punishable by [[hanging]], a penalty not lifted until [[1861]].

Following Sir [[William Blackstone]]'s ''[[Commentaries on the Laws of England]]'' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/blackstone/bk4ch15.htm|work=Blackstone's Commentaries on the Laws of England|title=Book the Fourth - Chapter the Fifteenth: Of Offences Against the Persons of Individuals|accessdate=2006-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;, the crime of sodomy has often been defined only as the ''abominable and detestable crime against nature'', or some variation of the phrase.  This language led to widely varying rulings about what specific acts were encompassed by its prohibition.

After the publishing of the [[Wolfenden report]] in the [[United Kingdom|UK]], which asserted that "homosexual behaviour between consenting adults in private should no longer be a criminal offence", many western governments, including the [[United States]], have repealed laws specifically against homosexual acts while retaining sodomy laws. In June 2003, the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] ruled in ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'' that [[U.S. state|state]] laws criminalizing private, non-commercial sexual activity (including homosexual activity) between consenting adults on the grounds of morality are unconstitutional since there is insufficient justification for state interest in such conduct.

In [[Europe]] and [[Latin America]] (except [[Belize]], [[Nicaragua]] and [[Guyana]]) there are no longer anti-sodomy laws. This trend among Western nations has not been followed in all other regions of the world (Africa, some parts of Asia, Oceania and the Caribbean Islands), where sodomy often remains a serious crime. Homosexual acts remain punishable by death in [[Iran]], [[Mauritania]], [[Saudi-Arabia]], [[Sudan]], [[United Arab Emirates]], [[Yemen]], some parts of [[Nigeria]] and [[Somalia]]. Prison for life in; [[Barbados]] (Not enforced for in private - Under review) [[Bangladesh]], [[Guyana]], [[India]], [[Maldives]], [[Myanmar]]/[[Burma]], [[Pakistan]], [[Qatar]], [[Sierra Leone]], [[Tanzania]] and [[Uganda]].

Sources:

* [http://www.planetout.com/news/history/archive/06071999.html David Bianco, First Sodomy Laws in the American Colonies]
* [http://www.ilga.org/statehomophobia/With_the_government_in_our_bedrooms_November_2006.pdf Daniel Ottosson, International Lesbian and Gay Association, "With the Government in Our Bedrooms: A Survey on the Laws Over the World Prohibiting Consenting Adult Sexual Same-Sex Acts (Nov. 2006)]
* [http://www.ilga.org/statehomophobia/World_legal_wrap_up_survey_November2006.pdf International Lesbian and Gay Association, "World Legal Wrap-Up" (Nov. 2006)]
* [http://www.actwin.com/eatonohio/gay/world.htm Homosexual Rights Around the World]

== Sodomy laws by country ==
=== Australia ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Australia}}

[[Australia]] inherited the [[United Kingdom]]'s sodomy laws on colonisation in [[1788]].  These were retained in the criminal codes passed by the various colonial [[parliament]]s during the 19th century, and by the state parliaments after [[Federation]]. {{Fact|date=February 2007}}

Following the [[Wolfenden report]], the [[Don Dunstan|Dunstan]] [[Australian Labor Party|Labor]] government introduced a ''consenting adults in private'' type defence in [[South Australia]] in [[1972]]. This defence was initiated as a bill by Murray Hill, father of former [[Defence Minister]] [[Robert Hill (Australian politician)|Robert Hill]], and repealed the state's sodomy law in [[1975]].  The [[Campaign Against Moral Persecution]] during the 1970s raised the profile and acceptance of Australia's gay and lesbian communities, and other states and territories repealed their laws between 1976 and 1990. The exception was [[Tasmania]], which retained its laws until the [[Government of Australia|Federal Government]] and the [[United Nations]] [[Human Rights Committee]] forced their repeal in 1997.  The details are given in the book ''Living out Loud: A History of Gay and Lesbian Activism in Australia''. {{Fact|date=February 2007}}

When male homosexuality was decriminalised in the [[Australian Capital Territory]] in 1976, then [[Norfolk Island]] in 1993, following [[South Australia]] in 1975 and [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] in 1981 - At the time of legalization (for the above), the age of consent, rape, defences, etc were all set [[gender-neutral]] and [[equal]] {{Fact|date=March 2007}}. [[Western Australia]] legalised male homosexuality in 1989, as did [[New South Wales]] and the [[Northern Territory]] in 1984 with unequal ages of consent of 18 for [[New South Wales]] and the [[Northern Territory]] and 21 for [[Western Australia]]. Then since 1997, the states and territories that retained different ages of consent or other vestiges of sodomy laws have tended to repeal them later; [[Western Australia]] did so in 2002, and [[New South Wales]] and the [[Northern Territory]] did so in 2003. Today only [[Tasmania]] and [[Queensland]] are the only Australian jurisdictions that still enforces a sodomy law - with the [[age of consent]] for [[anal sex]] being set at 18 (as compared to 16 for vaginal and [[oral sex]] in [[Queensland]]) &lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawstuff.org.au/Page.asp?PageID=168&amp;Section=Topics&amp;State=qld&lt;/ref&gt; and in [[Tasmania]], certain exceptions which constitute a defence do not apply if [[anal sex]] is involved with a person or persons under 17. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawstuff.org.au/Page.asp?PageID=163&amp;Section=Topics&amp;State=tas.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Brazil ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Brazil}}
Brazilian criminal law does not punish any sexual act performed by consenting adults, but allows for prosecution, under statutory rape laws and the children's protection act, when one of the participants is under 14 year of age and the other an adult, as per Articles 214, 223, 224 and 225 of the Brazilian Penal Code and Articles 240 and 244-A of the Estatuto da Criança e do Adolescente - Law 8.069.
Article 235 of the Brazilian Military Criminal Code - DL 1.001/69-, however, does incriminate any  contact deemed to be libidinous,  be it of a homosexual nature or not, made in any location subject to military administration. Since the article is entitled ''Of pederasty or other libidinous acts'', gay rights advocates claim that, since the Brazilian armed forces are comprised almost exclusively by males,  the article allows for  witch-hunts against homosexuals in the military service.

=== Canada ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Canada}}
Before 1859, Canada relied on British law to prosecute sodomy.  In 1859, Canada repatriated its buggery law in the Consolidated Statutes of Canada as an offense punishable by death.  Buggery remained punishable by death until 1869.  A broader law targeting all homosexual male sexual activity ("gross indecency") was passed in 1890.  Changes to the criminal code in 1948 and 1961 were used to brand gay men as "criminal sexual psychopaths" and "dangerous sexual offenders."  These labels provided for indeterminate prison sentences.  Most famously, [[George Klippert]], a homosexual, was labelled a dangerous sexual offender and sentenced to life in prison, a sentence confirmed by the Supreme Court of Canada.  He was released in 1971.

[[Canada|Canadian]] law now permits anal sex by consenting parties above the age of 18, provided no more than two people are present. The bill repealing Canada's sodomy laws achieved royal assent on [[June 27]] [[1969]].  The bill had been introduced in the House of Commons by [[Pierre Trudeau]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite Journals of the ''House of Commons'', vol. CXV (1968-69)}}&lt;/ref&gt;, who famously stated that "there's no place for the state in the bedrooms of the nation" &lt;ref&gt;{{cite http://archives.cbc.ca/IDC-1-73-538-2671/politics_economy/omnibus/clip1}}&lt;/ref&gt;. In the [[1995]] [[Ontario Court of Appeal]] case ''R. v. M. (C.)'', the judges ruled that the relevant section (section 159) of the [[Canadian Criminal Code|Criminal Code]] violated [[Section Fifteen of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms|section 15]] of the [[Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] when one or both of the partners are 16 to 18 years of age; this has not been tried in court again.

A similar decision was made by the [[Quebec Court of Appeal]] in the [[1998]] case ''R. v. Roy''.

=== China ===
{{main|LGBT rights in China}}
Sodomy laws have been abolished since the early [[1990s]] in the [[People's Republic of China]]. Yet there is no clear statute towards consenting parties above the age of 18. {{Fact|date=February 2007}} If someone under 18 is involved, the adult partner will be prosecuted. In a notable case in [[2002]], a man who had anal intercourse with a teenager was sentenced to three and a half years in prison. {{Fact|date=February 2007}}

=== Denmark ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Denmark}}
Denmark was the first country to fully legalize homosexuality, in 1934. {{Fact|date=February 2007}} The age of consent is '''15''' the same for all people since 1977.

=== France ===
{{main|LGBT rights in France}}
Since the [[French Revolution]], [[France]] has not had laws punishing homosexual conduct ''per se'' between over-age consenting adults in private. However, other qualifications such as "offense to good mores" were occasionally retained in the 19th century ''(see [[Jean Jacques Régis de Cambacérès]])''. Furthermore, the [[age of consent]] for homosexual sex was kept to the age of the [[legal majority]] (21 then 18), above the age for heterosexual sex (15), until [[1981]].

In [[1960]], a parliamentary amendment by [[Paul Mirguet]] added homosexuality to a list of "[[social scourge]]s", along with [[alcoholism]] and [[prostitution]]. This prompted the government to increase the penalties for public display of a sex act when the act was homosexual. [[transvestism|Transvestites]] or homosexuals caught [[Cruising for sex|cruising]] were also the target of police repression.

In [[1980]], the 1960 law making homosexuality an aggravating circumstance for public indecency was repealed.  Then in [[1982]], under president [[François Mitterrand]], the law from [[1942]] ([[Vichy France]]) making the age of consent for homosexual sex higher than for heterosexual sex was also repealed.

=== Germany ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Germany}}
[[Paragraph 175]], which punished "[[fornication]] between men", was eased to an [[age of consent]] of 21 in [[East Germany]] in [[1957]] and in [[West Germany]] in [[1969]].  This age was lowered to 18 in the East in [[1968]] and the West in [[1973]], and all legal distinctions between [[heterosexual]] and [[homosexuality|homosexual]] acts were abolished in the East in [[1988]], with this change being extended to all of Germany in [[1994]] as part of the process of [[German Reunification]].

In modern [[German language|German]], the term ''Sodomie'' has a meaning different from the  [[English language|English]] word "[[sodomy]]": it does not refer to [[anal sex]] at all, but acts of [[Zoophilia]].

=== Hungary ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Hungary}}
[[Homosexuality]] in [[Hungary]] was decriminalized in [[1962]], [[Paragraph 199 of the Hungarian Penal Code]] from then on threatened "only" adults over 18 who engaged themselves in a consensual same-sex relationship with an underaged person between 14 and 18. In [[1995]] a kind of [[domestic partners]]hip was introduced for same sex couples, on [[September 3]], [[2002]] the ruling of the [[Hungarian Constitutional Court]] abrogated Paragraph 199; since then the [[age of consent]] for both sexes and both for heterosexuals and homosexuals, is 14 years.

=== Iceland ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Iceland}}
Homosexuality has been legal in [[Iceland]] since 1940, but equal age of consent was not approved until 1992. [[Civil union]] was legalised by [[Alþingi]] in [[1996]] with 44 votes pro, 1 con, 1 neutral and 17 not present. Those laws were changed to allow adoption and [[artificial insemination]] for [[lesbians]] 27th of June 2006 among other things. Civil Union of Lesbians and Gays is now equal to marriage of heterosexual people, except it cannot be performed by religious foundations, only the State.

=== India ===
{{main|LGBT rights in India}}
India also inherited the anti-sodomy laws in its criminal code from the [[British raj]], which were not present in its history of codified or customary legal system before. Section 377 of the ''[[Indian Penal Code]]'' calls for a maximum punishment of life imprisonment for all ''sexual acts against human nature'' (primarily interpreted to be homosexuality, especially sodomy, including between consenting adults). This law has rarely been executed, if at all, in case of consenting adults, although sometimes comes in the news when a homosexual rape has been conducted and the rapist is arrested. Police repression in alleged or real gay bars is common, and is often highlighted by the contemporary media. Section 377 is currently facing constitutional challenge in the Delhi High Court in a petition filed by Naz Foundation.&lt;ref&gt;[[Homosexuality in India]]&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexual marriages are ''de facto'' banned.

=== Israel ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Israel}}
The [[Israel|State of Israel]] inherited its sodomy ("buggery") law from the [[British Mandate of Palestine]] but there is no record that it was ever enforced against homosexual acts that took place between consenting adults in private.  In the late [[1960s]] the [[Supreme Court of Israel]] ruled that these laws could not be enforced and they were formally repealed by the national legislative assembly in [[1988]].  The [[age of consent]] for both heterosexuals and homosexuals is sixteen years of age.

=== Japan ===

''Main Article'': [[LGBT rights in Japan]]

Extra-marital heterosexual anal sex is not considered an act of infidelity in Japanese law.{{Fact|date=October 2007}}

=== New Zealand ===
{{main|LGBT rights in New Zealand}}
Homosexual sex was legalised in New Zealand as a result of the passage of the [[Homosexual_Law_Reform_Act|Homosexual Law Reform Act 1986]]. The age of consent was set at 16 years, the same as for heterosexual sex.

=== Singapore ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Singapore}}
[[Section 377A of the Singapore Penal Code]] criminalizes ("outrages on decency") additionally punishes commission, solicitation, or attempted male same-sex "gross indecency", with imprisonment up to two years [http://www.gaywired.com/article.cfm?id=17034&amp;section=67].  Prior to October 2007 Singaporean Section 377 was added by the British colonial administration in 1858, replacing Hindu law at the time  which had not criminalized consensual same-sex sexuality. In October 2007, [[Singapore]] has "repealed section 377 in the New Penal Code it will reduce the maximum sentence for male-male sex to just a maximum term of 2 years in prison under "maintained" section 377A.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.generationq.net/articles/Singapore-gay-sex-ban-to-remain-straight-ban-abolished-00001.html&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sweden ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Sweden}}
[[Sweden]] legalized homosexuality in 1944.  The age of consent is 15 regardless of sexuality, since equalization in 1978. The Swedish Crime Law (SFS 1962:700), chapter six ('About Sexual Crimes')), does not distinguish between heterosexual and homosexual sexual acts. The only sexual act specifically mentioned in the law is intended indecent exposure.

=== Russia ===
{{main|LGBT rights in Russia}}
In [[Russia]] sexual activity between males was criminalized by state law on March 4, 1934. Sexual activity between females was not mentioned in the law. On [[May 27]], [[1993]], homosexual acts between consenting males were decriminalized.

=== United Kingdom ===
{{main|LGBT rights in the United Kingdom}}
The [[United Kingdom|UK]] has historically had similar laws, but the offence is known in England and Wales as '''[[buggery]]''', not sodomy, and is usually interpreted as referring to anal intercourse between two males or a male and a female. In England and Wales Buggery was made a [[felony]] by the [[Buggery Act]] in [[1533]], during the reign of [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]]. The punishment for those convicted was the death penalty right up until [[1861]]. A lesser offence of "attempted buggery" was punished by 2 years of jail and some time on the [[pillory]]. In [[1885]], Parliament enacted the [[Labouchere Amendment]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/pwh/englaw.html|title=The Law in England, 1290-1885|accessdate=2006-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;, which prohibited ''gross indecency'' between males, a broad term that was understood to encompass most or all male homosexual acts. Following the [[Wolfenden report]], sexual acts between two adult males, with no other people present, were made legal in [[England and Wales]] in [[1967]], in [[Scotland]] in [[1980]] and [[Northern Ireland]] in [[1982]].

In the [[1980s]] and [[1990s]], attempts were made by [[LGBT rights in the United Kingdom|gay rights]] organizations to equalize the age of consent for heterosexuals and homosexuals, as the age of consent for homosexuals was set at 21, while the age of consent for heterosexuals was 16. Efforts were also made to modify the "no other person present" clause so that it dealt only with minors. In 1994, Conservative MP [[Edwina Currie]] introduced an amendment to Criminal Justice and Public Order Bill which would have lowered the age of consent to 16. The amendment failed, but a compromise amendment which lowered the age of consent to 18 was accepted. Therefore the age of consent disparity remained, albeit reduced. However, the July 1, 1997 decision in the case ''[[Sutherland v. United Kingdom]]'' resulted in the [[Sexual Offences (Amendment) Act 2000]] which further reduced it to 16, and the "no other person present" clause was modified to "no minor persons present". Today, the universal age of consent is 16 in England, Scotland, and Wales. The age of consent for both heterosexuals and homosexuals remains at 17 in Northern Ireland.

=== United States ===

''Main Article'': [[LGBT rights in the United States]]

[[Image:US-sodomy-laws.png|right|thumb|400px|US [[sodomy laws]] by the year when they were repealed or struck down.  Lighter is earlier; darker is later. ]]

[[Sodomy laws in the United States]] were largely a matter of state rather than federal jurisdiction.  By the last quarter of the [[20th century]], 47 out of 50 states had repealed any specifically [[Anti-homosexualism|anti-homosexual-conduct]] laws, and 37 had repealed all sodomy laws. The remaining [[Anti-homosexualism|anti-homosexual]] sodomy laws have been invalidated by the 2003 U.S. Supreme Court decision ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'' (see above).  It is not clear whether or how sodomy laws that apply to both homosexual and heterosexual sex are affected by Lawrence.  The United States Supreme Court also implied that the [[age of consent]] must be the same for heterosexuals and homosexuals when it ordered the Kansas courts to review the constitutionality of the state's Romeo and Juliet Law.

However, under the [[Uniform Code of Military Justice]], sodomy is illegal for all members of the United States armed forces.

The term "crime against nature" was first used in law in [[1828]].

==== State laws at time of 2003 Supreme Court decision ====

U.S. Supreme Court decision ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'' (2003) invalidated [[anti-homosexualism|anti-homosexual]] sodomy laws in the fifty states, the District of Columbia, and Puerto Rico. At that time, the laws stood as follows:

* '''Alabama — All sodomy acts illegal - affects only unmarried couples. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.actwin.com/eatonohio/gay/sodomy.html&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.sodomylaws.org/usa/alabama/alabama.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Penalty = (1 year/$2,000)'''
* Alaska (repealed through legislative action 1980)
* Arizona (repealed through legislative action 2001)
* Arkansas — struck down by [[Jegley v. Picado]], 80 S.W.3d 332 (Ark. 2001)
* California (repealed through legislative action 1976)
* Colorado (repealed through legislative action 1972)
* Connecticut (repealed through legislative action 1971)
* Delaware (repealed through legislative action 1973)
* '''Florida — All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (60 days/$500)'''
* Georgia — struck down by [[Powell v. Georgia]], 510 S.E.2d 18 (1998)
* Hawaii (repealed through legislative action 1973)
* '''Idaho — All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (5 years to life)'''
* Illinois (repealed through legislative action 1962)
* Indiana (repealed through legislative action 1977)
* Iowa (repealed through legislative action 1978)
* '''Kansas — Same-Sex sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (6 months/$1,000)'''
* Kentucky — struck down by [[Commonwealth v. Wasson]], 842 S.W.2d 487 (Ky. 1992)
* '''Louisiana — All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (5 years/$2,000)''' &lt;ref&gt;http://www.nola.com/printer/printer.ssf?/base/news-9/111466958966450.xml&lt;/ref&gt;
* Maine (repealed through legislative action 1976)
* Maryland — struck down by [[Williams v. State]], 1998 Extra LEXIS 260, Baltimore City Circuit Court, January 14, 1999
* Massachusetts — struck down by [[GLAD v. Attorney General]], SJC-08539 (Mass. Supreme Judicial Ct. 2002)
* '''Michigan - In Michigan Organization for [[Human Rights v. Kelley]] 1990, a trial court ruled Michigan’s sodomy law unconstitutional under the state constitution. This ruling is believed to apply to all state prosecutors; however, due to the fact that the judge's decision has not yet been appealed, the current status of the law is unclear. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.gaytimes.co.uk/gt/listings.asp?action=ShowRegion&amp;RID=23&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.actwin.com/eatonohio/gay/sodomy.html&lt;/ref&gt; (all sexes; felony punishable by up to 15 years imprisonment, repeat offenders get life)'''
* Minnesota — struck down by [[Doe v. Ventura]], No. MC 01-489, 2001 WL 543734 (Minn. Dist. Ct 2001)
* '''Mississippi — All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (10 years)'''
* '''Missouri — Same-Sex sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (1 year/$1,000), then repealed through legislative action in 2006 &lt;ref&gt;http://www.365gay.com/Newscon06/06/060506missouri.htm&lt;/ref&gt;'''
* Montana — struck down by [[Gryczan v. Montana]], 942 P.2d 112 (1997)
* Nebraska (repealed through legislative action 1978)
* Nevada (repealed through legislative action 1993)
* New Hampshire (repealed through legislative action 1975)
* New Jersey (repealed through legislative action 1979)
* New Mexico (repealed through legislative action 1975)
* New York — struck down by [[People v. Onofre]], 415 N.E.2d 936 (N.Y. 1980) and repealed by the legislature in 2000.
* '''North Carolina — All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (10 years/discretionary fine)'''
* North Dakota (repealed through legislative action 1973)
* Ohio (repealed through legislative action 1974)
* '''Oklahoma — Same-Sex sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (10 years)'''
* Oregon (repealed through legislative action 1972)
* Pennsylvania — struck down by [[Commonwealth v. Bonadio]], 415 A.2d 47 (Pa. 1980) and repealed by the legislature in 1995.
* Rhode Island (repealed through legislative action 1998)
* '''South Carolina — All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (5 years/$500)'''
* South Dakota (repealed through legislative action 1977)
* Tennessee — Struck down in [[Campbell v. Sundquist]], 926 S.W.2d 250 (1996)
* '''Texas — Same-Sex sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = ($500)'''
* '''Utah — All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (6 months/$1,000)''' &lt;ref&gt;http://www.365gay.com/Newscon07/03/030507sodomy.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* Vermont (repealed through legislative action 1977)
* '''Virginia — All sodomy acts illegal. Penalty = (1-5 years)'''
* Washington (repealed through legislative action 1976)
* West Virginia (repealed through legislative action 1976)
* Wisconsin (repealed through legislative action 1983)
* Wyoming (repealed through legislative action 1977)
* District of Columbia (City Council repealed law in 1995; Congress did not veto repeal as it did the first time in 1981) &lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrc.org/Template.cfm?Section=Home&amp;CONTENTID=30422&amp;TEMPLATE=/ContentManagement/ContentDisplay.cfm&lt;/ref&gt;
* Puerto Rico (repealed through legislative action 2005) &lt;ref&gt;http://www.ilga.org/statehomophobia/Legal%20Wrap%20Up%20Survey%20July%202006.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

"repealed" - means abolished from the law books (statutes)
"law invalidated" (by Lawrence vs Texas) - means still in the law books, but not enforced (statutes)

Source:
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.actwin.com/eatonohio/gay/sodomy.html&lt;/ref&gt; and &lt;ref&gt;http://www.actwin.com/eatonohio/gay/GAY.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Updated on 6-9-06

== See also ==

* [[Homophobia]]
* [[LGBT rights by country]]
* [[Societal attitudes towards homosexuality]]
* [[Homosexuality laws of the world]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== References ==

* Graham Willett, ''Living out Loud: A History of Gay and Lesbian Activism in Australia'', [[2000]].  ISBN 1-86448-949-9.
* Peter McWilliams, [[Ain't Nobody's Business If You Do]], [[1998]].  ISBN 0-931580-58-7.

== External links ==

* [http://www.ilga.info/Information/Legal_survey/ilga_world_legal_survey%20introduction.htm International Lesbian and Gay Association World Legal Survey] (2000)
* [http://www.sodomylaws.org/ Sodomy Laws Around the World]
* [http://www.iglhrc.org/site/iglhrc/content.php?type=1&amp;id=77 Where Having Sex is a Crime: Criminalization and Decriminalization of Homosexual Acts], IGLHRC (2003)
* [http://www.sodomylaws.org/world/united_kingdom/uknews24.htm  The Accidental Legacy of a Homophobic Humanitarian] — [[The Times]], [[October 2]], [[2000]]

[[Category:LGBT-related legislation]]
[[Category:Sex crimes]]
[[Category:Legal history]]
[[Category:LGBT history]]

[[de:Gesetze gegen Homosexualität]]
[[es:Ley de sodomía]]
[[nl:Sodomiewetgeving]]
[[zh:鸡奸法]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>