<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031015231901|1572938" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20903342" pageid="20903342" ns="0" title="Sodomy law"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-16T07:14:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[zh:&amp;#40481;&amp;#22904;&amp;#27861;]]

A '''sodomy law''' is a law which makes certain [[sexual acts]] into [[sex crime]]s, most commonly [[anal intercourse]].  Sometimes the definition of [[sodomy]] has been broader and included [[oral sex]] and [[bestiality]] as well.  Following Sir [[William Blackstone]]'s ''[[Commentaries on the Laws of England]]'' [http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/blackstone/bk4ch15.htm], the crime of sodomy has often been defined in the past only as the ''abominable and detestable crime against nature'', or some variation of the phrase.  This language led to widely varying rulings about what specific acts were encompassed by its prohibition.  

While many other parts of the world have, or had, laws against homosexuality or other sexual practices, the term ''sodomy law'' has mainly used when discussing the law of the [[United States]].

Even though many of these laws target both [[heterosexuality|heterosexual]] and [[homosexuality|homosexual]] acts, they are sometimes selectively enforced only against homosexuals; in some [[U.S. state|states of the US]], this practice was codified and the laws prohibited only homosexual acts, not heterosexual ones. In the [[United States]], most sodomy laws were broad enough to apply to [[lesbian|female homosexuality]], but were more commonly enforced against [[gay|male homosexuality]].  It is a common misunderstanding that sodomy laws are laws against homosexuality, when many of them prohibit some heterosexual acts as well.

== United Kingdom ==

The [[United Kingdom]] has historically had similar laws, but the offence was usually called there '''[[buggery]]''', not sodomy, and was usually intepreted as referring to anal intercourse between two males or a male and a female.  Buggery was made a [[felony]] by [[statute]] in [[1533]], during the reign of [[Henry VIII]].  (See [[Buggery Act]].)  In [[1885]], Parliament enacted the so-called [[Labouchere Amendment]] [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/pwh/englaw.html], which prohibited "gross indecency" between males, a broad term that was understood to encompass most or all male homosexual acts.  It was under this law that [[Oscar Wilde]] suffered his well-known conviction and imprisonment.  Sexual acts between two adult males, with no other people present, were made legal in [[England]] in [[1967]], and in [[Scotland]] and [[Northern Ireland]] somewhat later.

== Canada ==

[[Canada|Canadian]] law now permits anal sex by consenting parties above the age of 18, provided no more than two people are present.  Its sodomy laws were repealed in the 1960s by [[Pierre Trudeau]] who famously stated that "the government has no place in the bedrooms of the nation."

== China ==
Sodomy laws have been abolished since the early [[1990s]] in the [[People's Republic of China]]. Yet, there is no clear statute towards consenting parties above the age 18. If person under 18 involed, criminal action suit will be applied. In a notable case in [[2002]], the person who had sodomy with a teenager was sentenced 3 and a half years in prison.

==Penalties and Enforcement in US==

In June [[2003]], the [[US Supreme Court]] in a 6-3 decision struck down the [[Texas]] same-sex sodomy law, ruling that this private sexual conduct is protected by the liberty rights implicit in the [[Due process|due process clause]] of the [[United States Constitution]].  (See ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]''.)  This decision invalidated all [[U.S. state|state]] sodomy laws insofar as they applied to noncommercial conduct in private between consenting adults, and overruled an earlier ruling from [[1986]] in which [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]]'s sodomy law had been upheld. (''[[Bowers v. Hardwick]]''.)

Before that 2003 ruling, 27 states, the [[District of Columbia]] and 4 [[U.S. territory|territories]] had repealed their sodomy laws by [[legislation|legislative action]], 9 states had had them overturned or invalidated by [[state court]] action, 4 states still had same-sex laws, and 10 states, [[Puerto Rico]] and the [[U.S. military]] had laws applying to all regardless of gender. 

Prior to [[1962]], sodomy was a felony in every state, punishable by a lengthy term of [[imprisonment]].  Over the years, many of the states that did not repeal their sodomy laws had enacted legislation reducing the penalty.  Immediately prior to the ''Lawrence'' decision in 2003, the penalty for violating a sodomy law varied very widely from jurisdiction to jurisdiction among those states retaining their sodomy laws. The most harsh penalties were in the state of [[Idaho]], where sodomy could theoretically earn a life sentence. [[Michigan]] followed, with a maximum penalty of 15 years' imprisonment.

In most US states the laws were no longer enforced, or were very selectively enforced.  The continued presence of these rarely enforced laws on the statute books, however, was often cited as justification for [[discrimination]] against [[homosexuality|gay men and lesbians]].

=== State Laws prior to 2003 invalidation ===

Sodomy laws and penalties in US states and territories, immediately prior to their invalidation in 2003, according to information provided by the [[Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund]] [http://www.lambdalegal.org/cgi-bin/iowa/documents/record?record=275] and the [[American Civil Liberties Union]] [http://www.aclu.org/issues/gay/sodomy.html], were as follows:

* [[Alabama]] (all sexes; misdemeanor punishable by up to 1 year imprisonment and $2000 fine)
* [[Alaska]] (repealed, 1980)
* [[American Samoa]] (repealed, 1979)
* [[Arizona]] (repealed, 2001)
* [[Arkansas]] (invalidated by courts, [http://www.lambdalegal.org/binary-data/LAMBDA_PDF/pdf/149.pdf ''Jegley v. Picado''], 2002)
* [[California]] (repealed, 1976)
* [[Colorado]] (repealed, 1972)
* [[Connecticut]] (repealed, 1971)
* [[Delaware]] (repealed, 1973)
* [[District of Columbia]] (repealed, 1993)
* [[Florida]] (all sexes; misdemeanor punishable by up to 60 days imprisonment and $500 fine)
* [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] (invalidated by courts, ''Powell v. State'', 510 S.E.2d 18, 1998)
* [[Guam]] (repealed, 1976)
* [[Hawaii]] (repealed, 1973)
* [[Idaho]] (all sexes; felony punishable by imprisonment for 5 years to life)
* [[Illinois]] (repealed, 1962)
* [[Indiana]] (repealed, 1977)
* [[Iowa]] (repealed, 1978)
* [[Kansas]] (same sex only; misdemeanor punishable by up to 6 months imprisonment and $1000 fine)
* [[Kentucky]] (invalidated by courts, ''Commonwealth v. Wasson'', 842 S.W.2d 487, 1992)
* [[Louisiana]] (all sexes; felony punishable by up to 5 years imprisonment and $2000 fine)
* [[Maine]] (repealed, 1976)
* [[Maryland]] (invalidated by courts, ''Williams v. Glendening'', 1998 Extra LEXIS 260, Baltimore City Circuit Court, 1998)
* [[Massachusetts]] (interpreted by courts not to apply to private acts, [http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=ma&amp;vol=sjcslip/8539&amp;invol=1 ''GLAD v. Attorney General''], 2002)
* [[Michigan]] (felony punishable by up to 15 years imprisonment; statute was struck down by Wayne County judge but status was unclear)
* [[Minnesota]] (invalidated by courts, 2001)
* [[Mississippi]] (all sexes; felony punishable by up to 10 years imprisonment)
* [[Missouri]] (same sex only; misdemeanor punishable by up to 1 year imprisonment and $1000 fine; one appellate court interpreted the law not to apply to consensual acts, but other appellate court reached opposite conclusion)
* [[Montana]] (invalidated by courts, ''Gryczan v. Montana'', 1997)
* [[Nebraska]] (repealed, 1978)
* [[Nevada]] (repealed, 1993) 
* [[New Hampshire]] (repealed, 1975)
* [[New Jersey]] (repealed, 1979)
* [[New Mexico]] (repealed, 1975)
* [[New York]] (invalidated by courts, ''People v. Onofre'', 415 N.E.2d 936, 1980; and later repealed, 2000)
* [[North Carolina]] (all sexes; felony punishable by up to 10 years imprisonment and discretionary fine)
* [[Northern Mariana Islands]] (repealed, 1983)
* [[North Dakota]] (repealed, 1973)
* [[Ohio]] (repealed, 1974)
* [[Oklahoma]] (same sex only; felony punishable by up to 10 years imprisonment)
* [[Oregon]] (repealed, 1972)
* [[Pennsylvania]] (invalidated by courts, ''Commonwealth v. Bonadio'', 415 A.2d 47, 1980; and later repealed, 1995)
* [[Puerto Rico]] (all sexes; felony punishable by up to 10 years imprisonment)
* [[Rhode Island]] (repealed, 1998)
* [[South Carolina]] (all sexes; felony punishable by up to 5 years imprisonment and $500 fine)
* [[South Dakota]] (repealed, 1977)
* [[Tennessee]] (invalidated by courts, ''Campbell v. Sundquist'', 926 S.W.2d 250, 1996)
* [[Texas]] (same sex only; misdemeanor punishable by up to $500 fine)
* [[Utah]] (all sexes; misdemeanor punishable by up to 6 months imprisonment and $1000 fine)
* [[Vermont]] (repealed 1977)
* [[U.S. Virgin Islands|Virgin Islands]] (repealed, 1984)
* [[Virginia]] (all sexes; felony punishable by 1-5 years imprisonment)
* [[Washington]] (repealed, 1976)
* [[West Virginia]] (repealed, 1976)
* [[Wisconsin]] (repealed, 1983)
* [[Wyoming]] (repealed, 1977)

See also: [[homophobia]], [[gay rights]]

== External links ==
* [http://www.sodomylaws.org SodomyLaws.Org]
* [http://www.sodomylaws.org/usa/florida/flnews02.htm  Going Down Down South: Fighting Absurd Sex Laws]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>