<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031104033056|1670209" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="49392" pageid="49392" ns="0" title="Affirmative action"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-04T05:03:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Affirmative action''' is action affording, to groups considered victims of social [[discrimination]], "preferential" or "equal" (depending on one's point of view) access to an environment or benefits, such as [[education]], [[employment]], [[health care]] or [[social welfare]].

This can involve "[[equal opportunity]]" hiring and other practices, required demographically-representative (or over/under-representative) [[diversity]] in an environment, or other practices that actively prefer members of [[minority]] groups. The latter may include [[racial quota]]s and lowered performance requirements for applicants belonging to particular racial group(s). 

==Basis in US Law==
In the [[United States Constitution|US Constitution]], the ''[[equal protection]]'' clause of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] mandates that no governmental entity burden a person or deny them benefits because they are members of a racial minority (see Constitutional Law, Nowak and Rotunda). The Oxford Desk dictionary defines a racial minority as a smaller number of persons within a political party or structure. 

The [[Lyndon Johnson|Johnson]] administration embraced affirmative action in [[1965]], by issuing United States Executive Order 11246, later amended by Executive Order 11375. The order, as amended, aims "to correct the effects of past and present [[discrimination]]".  It prohibits federal contractors and subcontractors from discriminating against any employee or applicant for [[employment]] because of [[race]], skin [[color]], [[religion]], [[gender]], or [[national origin]]. The Order requires that contractors take affirmative action to ensure that "protected class, underutilized applicants" are employed, and that employees are treated without discriminatory regard to their protected class status.

The Order specifically requires certain organizations accepting federal funds to take affirmative action to increase employment opportunities for members of racial minorities and women. Any [[organization]] with fifty or more employees and an aggregate revenue exceeding $50,000 from [[Government of the United States|federal]] contracts during a twelve month period must have a written affirmative action plan. This plan must include goals and timetables for achieving full utilization of women and members of racial minorities, in [[racial quota|quota]]s based on an analysis of the current workforce compared to the availability in the general labor pool of women and members of racial minorities.

The order is enforced by the Office of Federal Contract Compliance Programs of the Employment Standards Administration of the U.S. Department of Labor.

Section 717 of Title VII of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] and Section 501 of the [[Rehabilitation Act of 1973]] require all United States Federal Agencies to implement affirmative employment opportunity programs for all federal employees. [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission|EEOC]] [http://www.eeoc.gov/federal/eeomd715.html Equal Employment Opportunity Management Directive 715 (MD 715)] provides guidance as to how such programs are to be implemented.

In the beginning, racial classifications that only discriminated against racial minorities were inherently suspect and subject to strict scrutiny.  These classifications would only be upheld if necessary to promote a compelling governmental interest.  Later the [[United States Supreme Court|US Supreme Court]] decided that racial classifications that benefited underrepresented minorities were to only be upheld if necessary and promoted a compelling governmental purpose.  (See Richmond v. JA Croson Co.)

Individual US States [http://www.moga.state.mo.us/statutes/chapters/chap213.htm e.g. Missouri] also have orders that prohibit discrimination and outline affirmative action requirements with regard to race, creed, color, religion, national origin, gender, age, and disability status.

==Implementation in Universities==
When underrepresented minorities are actively sought or preferred, the reason given is usually that this is necessary to compensate for advantages to groups such as [[male]]s or those of [[Europe]]an descent from [[racism]], [[sexism]], results of historical circumstances, and [[institutional racism]]. 

Some dissenters claim that racial preferences have in-effect caused a [[reverse discrimination]] against a historically-dominant group (white males in Europe and North America), and liken such preferences to [[apartheid]].

In the US, the most common form of affirmative action centres around access to education, in particular entrance to [[university]] and other forms of tertiary instruction. Typically, individuals will have the difficulty of their entrance and/or exam requirements or numerical-maximum/minimum number of student-entries set in relation to what group(s) they belong to, such as their [[race]], [[ethnicity]], [[native language]], [[social class|class]], [[geography|geographic]] origin or [[gender role|gender]]. Individuals can also be awarded [[scholarship]]s and have fees paid on the basis of the hitherto-listed criteria.

In the [[United States]], affirmative action programs at universities usually benefit only black [[African Americans]], [[Hispanic Americans]], and [[Native Americans]]. [[Asian Americans]], although a racial minority, do not benefit at most colleges because their makeup in the student body exceeds their makeup in the general US population. [[Whites|White-skinned people]] do not benefit in universities where their makeup in the student body is less than their makeup in the general US population because they are not members of a racial minority.
==Consultations==
Another more abstract form of affirmative action is in ''consultations'', whereby institutions such as [[school]]s or health-care facilities are declared to be [[ethnocentric]] around the majority culture, and therefore consultation with other ethnic groups, especially [[indigenous people|indigenous]] groups, are specified as a remedy. This can cause accusations of double-standards, as often in practice representatives of all ethnic groups ''except the majority group'' receive consultation on institutional workings. Proponants discount this as being irrelevant, as they claim consultation with the majority group is pointless, as the institution's management is centric around them anyway.
==Outside the United States==
In those countries outside the US which have laws on racial equality, such as the [[United Kingdom]], affirmative action would be illegal because of a requirement to treat all races equally. This approach of equal treatment is sometimes described as being [[race-blind]]. It tends to act against both [[discrimination]] and [[reverse discrimination]].

In those countries, the focus tends to be on ensuring equal opportunity and, for example, advertising campaigns to encourage ethnic minority candidates to join the police force.
==Opposing Views of Affirmative Action==
A particular minority group may be under-represented in some areas (for example, in the [[UK]] there are fewer Asian people in the police than might be expected given the proportion of Asians in the population in general), perhaps due to past discrimination against members of the group.  When this occurs, there is a school of thought that unless this group is given specific help to progress in this area (whether in recruitment to a specific job, college or other place or status) it will never gain the critical mass and acceptance in that role, even if discrimination against the group is eradicated.  For this reason, it is suggested, more effort must be made to recuit persons from that background, train them, and if necessary, lower the pass mark in any final exam.  

Opponents of affirmative action argue that the effect of such policies is to discriminate against the majority (by giving a benefit to a specific minority) and therefore constitutes reverse discrimination.  They argue that it is just as unfair to discriminate against the majority as to discriminate against the minority. For example, with lower university entrance standards for minority members, those from the minority who do get in may be less able to complete the course, leading to a higher drop out rate and a greater public perception that they are not up to it, defeating the stated aim.

Proponents of affirmative action argue that affirmative action is the best way to correct a history of discrimination against a minority group. With a wide and long term perspective, affirmative action may be seen as redressing an otherwise unfair balance of historical wrongs and institutionalised disadvantages.
==Important [[Supreme Court of the United States|US Supreme Court]] cases==

Investigated and outlined in Harvard researcher Shaheen Lakhan's article under the section ''History and Legal Contex of Affirmative Action'' of [http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6920/3/6 '''Diversification of U.S. Medical Schools via Affirmative Action Implementation''' - ''BMC Medical Education'' 2003 3:6]

*''[[Regents of the University of California v. Bakke]]'', 1978
:The Supreme Court held that the [[University of California, Davis|UC Davis]] medical school admissions program violated the equal protection clause with the institution of quotas for underrepresented minorities. However, the court ruled that race could be ''one'' of the factors in university admissions.

*''[[Grutter v. Bollinger]]'', 2003
:The Supreme Court ruled that race could be used as a criterion in school admissions and that it would not be in violation of the equal protection clause of the 14th Amendment.  The Court found that the University of Michigan Law School's narrowly-tailored policy was constitutional and appropriate "to further a compelling interest in obtaining the educational benefits that flow from a diverse student body."

*''[[Gratz v. Bollinger]]'', 2003
:The Supreme Court ruled that the University of Michigan's point-based undergraduate admissions policy that took race into account numerically was too mechanical and unconstitutional.
==See Also==
*[[Bakke case]]
*[[Equal Opportunity Employment Commission|Equal Opportunity Employment Commission (US)]]
*[[Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity|Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity  (US)]]
==External Link==
*[http://www.dol.gov/esa/regs/compliance/ofccp/fs11246.htm Executive Order 11246]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>