<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161122072103|750922418" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="49392" pageid="49392" ns="0" title="Affirmative action"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-23T17:15:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2015}}
{{POV|talk=Mathematical Modeling|date=March 2016}}{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Affirmative action''' (known as '''employment equity''' in [[Canada]], '''[[Reservation in India|reservation]]''' in [[India]] and [[Nepal]], and '''positive discrimination''' in the [[UK]]) is the policy of favoring members of a disadvantaged group who suffer or have suffered from [[discrimination]] within a [[culture]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=positive discrimination|url=http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/positive-discrimination?q=positive+discrimination|work=Oxford Dictionaries|publisher=Oxford University Press|accessdate=13 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=affirmative action|url=http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/affirmative-action?q=affirmative+action|work=Oxford Dictionaries|publisher=Oxford University Press|accessdate=13 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="The Federal Register"&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = The Federal Register
| title = Executive Order 11246—Equal employment opportunity
| url = http://www.archives.gov/federal-register/codification/executive-order/11246.html
| accessdate =5 February 2010| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100330083544/http://www.archives.gov/federal-register/codification/executive-order/11246.html| archivedate= 30 March 2010 | deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy"&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = Stanford University
| title = Affirmative Action
| url = http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/affirmative-action/
| accessdate =4 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Often, these people are disadvantaged for historical reasons, such as oppression or slavery.&lt;ref name="Christophe Jaffrelot pg. 321"&gt;Christophe Jaffrelot, India's Silent Revolution: The rise of lower castes in northern India, pg. 321 2003&lt;/ref&gt; Historically and internationally, support for affirmative action has sought to achieve goals such as bridging inequalities in employment and pay, increasing access to education, promoting diversity, and redressing apparent past wrongs, harms, or hindrances. The nature of affirmative action policies varies from region to region. Some countries, [[Reservation in India|such as India]], use a quota system, whereby a certain percentage of government jobs, political positions, and school vacancies must be reserved for members of a certain group. In some other regions where quotas are not used, minority group members are given preference or special consideration in selection processes.

In 1989, the International [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]] stipulated (in Article 2.2) that affirmative action programs may be required of countries that ratified the convention, in order to rectify systematic discrimination. It also states that such programs "shall in no case entail as a consequence the maintenance of unequal or separate rights for different racial groups after the objectives for which they were taken have been achieved."&lt;ref name="unhchr.ch"&gt;United Nations Committee on Human Rights, [http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/(Symbol)/3888b0541f8501c9c12563ed004b8d0e?Opendocument General Comment 18 on Non-discrimination, Paragraph 10]&lt;/ref&gt;

Several countries, such as India, [[Reserved political positions|reserve political, vocational and educational positions]] for members of disadvantaged groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Sakrikar|first1=Dinkar|title=The Mandal Commission Report (August 1994)|url=http://www.pucl.org/from-archives/Dalit-tribal/mandal-2.htm|website=www.pucl.org|publisher=PUCL - Peoples Union for Civil Liberties|accessdate=2 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In India, this varies between 30% (nationwide) to up to 70% (in [[Tamil Nadu]]&lt;ref name="pucl2"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Singh|first1=Aruna|title=A comment on the application of the mandal commission report -  (August 1984)|url=http://www.pucl.org/from-archives/Dalit-tribal/mandal-2.htm|website=www.pucl.org|publisher=PUCL - People's Union for Civil Linerties|accessdate=2 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;). In the United States, affirmative action in employment and education has been the subject of legal and political controversy, and in 2003, a pair of US Supreme Court decisions (''[[Grutter v. Bollinger]]'' and ''[[Gratz v. Bollinger]]'') permitted educational institutions to consider race as a factor when admitting students while prohibiting the use of quotas.&lt;ref name="Supct.law.cornell.edu"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://supct.law.cornell.edu/supct/03highlts.html#2 |title=Highlights of the 2002–2003 Supreme Court Term |publisher=Supct.law.cornell.edu |date= |accessdate=1 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In other countries, such as the UK,&lt;ref name="cre"/&gt;&lt;ref name=govuk&gt;{{cite web|title=Types of discrimination`|url=https://www.gov.uk/discrimination-your-rights/types-of-discrimination|work=Discrimination: your rights|publisher=GOV.UK|accessdate=7 April 2013|author=GOV.UK|authorlink=Gov.uk|date=4 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="personneltoday.com"&gt;Personneltoday.com [http://www.personneltoday.com/Articles/2006/01/17/33430/is-there-a-case-for-positive-discrimination.html "Is there a case for positive discrimination?"] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080105095039/http://www.personneltoday.com/Articles/2006/01/17/33430/is-there-a-case-for-positive-discrimination.html |date=5 January 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; affirmative action is rendered illegal because it does not treat all races equally. This approach to equal treatment is described as being "[[Color blindness (race)|color blind]]." In such countries, the focus tends to be on ensuring equal opportunity and, for example, targeted advertising campaigns to encourage ethnic minority candidates to join the police force. This is sometimes described as "[[positive action]]."

Opponents of affirmative action such as [[George Sher]] believe that affirmative action devalues the accomplishments of people who are chosen based on the social group to which they belong rather than their qualifications, thus rendering affirmative action counterproductive.&lt;ref name="Sher, George 1983, p.40"&gt;Sher, George, "Preferential Hiring", in Tom Regan (ed.), Just Business: New Introductory Essays In Business Ethics, Philadelphia, Temple University Press, 1983, p.40.&lt;/ref&gt; Opponents,&lt;ref name="American Civil Rights Institute"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.acri.org/ |title=American Civil Rights Institute |publisher=Acri.org |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; who sometimes say that affirmative action is [[reverse discrimination]], further claim that affirmative action has undesirable side-effects in addition to failing to achieve its goals.&lt;ref name="Cultural Whiplash 2006"&gt;''Cultural Whiplash: Unforeseen Consequences of America's Crusade Against Racial Discrimination'' / Patrick Garry (2006) ISBN 1-58182-569-2&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the idea of "mismatching" suggests that affirmative action might place students into colleges that are too difficult for them, increasing their chances of dropping out.&lt;ref name="latimes.com"&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/opinion/la-oe-sander26sep26,0,3998908.story?coll=la-opinion-center Does affirmative action hurt minorities?], ''Los Angeles Times'', 26 September 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Quotas on trial"&gt;[http://www.jewishworldreview.com/cols/sowell010803.asp Quotas on trial], by Thomas Sowell, 8 January 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==
The term "affirmative action" was first used in the United States in "[[Executive Order 10925|Executive Order No. 10925]]",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://shfg.org/shfg/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/4-MacLaury-design4-new_Layout-1.pdf | title=President Kennedy’s E.O.10925: Seedbed of Affirmative Action | publisher=Society for History in the Federal Government | accessdate=27 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; signed by President [[John F. Kennedy]] on 6 March 1961, which included a provision that [[government contractor]]s "take ''affirmative action'' to ensure that applicants are employed, and employees are treated during employment, without regard to their race, creed, color, or national origin."&lt;ref name="oeod.uci.edu"&gt;[http://www.oeod.uci.edu/aa.html A Brief History of Affirmative Action], University of California, Irvine (access date 16 May 2015)&lt;/ref&gt; It was used to promote actions that achieve non-discrimination. In 1965, President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]] issued [[Executive Order 11246]] which required government employers to take "affirmative action" to "hire without regard to race, religion and national origin". This prevented employers from discriminating against members of disadvantaged groups.
In 1967, gender was added to the anti-discrimination list.&lt;ref name="clinton2.nara.gov"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://clinton2.nara.gov/WH/EOP/OP/html/aa/aa02.html|title=Affirmative Action: History and Rationale|date=19 July 1995|publisher=Clinton Administration's Affirmative Action Review: Report to the President}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Affirmative action is intended to promote the opportunities of defined minority groups within a society to give them equal access to that of the majority population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Affirmative Action |url=http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/sharamkohan1/affirmative-action/ |website=Harvard Blogs |publisher=Harvard Law School |accessdate=30 April 2015 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150518061955/http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/sharamkohan1/affirmative-action/ |archivedate=18 May 2015 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is often instituted for government and educational settings to ensure that certain designated "[[minority group]]s" within a society are able to participate in all provided opportunities including promotional, educational, and training opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Equal Opportunity &amp; Affirmative Action Policy Statement|url=http://www.chatham.edu/about/legal_nondiscrimination.cfm|website=chatham.edu|accessdate=30 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The stated justification for affirmative action by its proponents is that it helps to compensate for past discrimination, persecution or [[Exploitation of labour|exploitation]] by the ruling class of a culture,&lt;ref&gt;Sowell, Thomas (2004). Affirmative Action Around the World: An Empirical Study, Yale University Press, ISBN 0-300-10199-6&lt;/ref&gt; and to address existing discrimination.&lt;ref name="Affirmative Action"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/affirmative-action/|title=Affirmative Action|publisher=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|date=1 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Women==
{{See also|Women in government#Quotas|label 1=Women in government (quotas)}}
Several different studies investigated the effect of affirmative action on women. Kurtulus (2012) in her review of affirmative action and the occupational advancement of minorities and women during 1973-2003 showed that the effect of affirmative action on advancing black, Hispanic, and white women into management, professional, and technical occupations occurred primarily during the 1970s and early 1980s. During this period, contractors grew their shares of these groups more rapidly than noncontractors because of the implementation of affirmative action. But the positive effect of affirmative action vanished entirely in the late 1980s, which Kurtulus says may be due to the slowdown into advanced occupation for women and minorities because of the political shift of affirmative action that started by President Reagan. Becoming a federal contractor increased white women's share of professional occupations by 0.183 percentage points, or 7.3 percent, on average during these three decades, and increased black women's share by 0.052 percentage points (or by 3.9 percent). Becoming a federal contractor also increased Hispanic women's and black men's share of technical occupations on average by 0.058 percent and 0.109 percentage points respectively (or by 7.7 and 4.2 percent). These represent a substantial contribution of affirmative action to overall trends in the occupational advancement of women and minorities over the three decades under the study.&lt;ref&gt;Fidan Ana Kurtulus, "Affirmative Action and the Occupational Advancement of Minorities and Women During 1973–2003," ''Industrial Relations: A Journal of Economy and Society'' (2012) 51#2 pp 213-246. [http://economics.lafayette.edu/files/2011/04/kurtulus.pdf online]{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; A further study by Kim and Kim (2014) considered the impact of four primary factors on support for affirmative action programs for women: gender; political factors; psychological factors; and social structure. They found that, "Affirmative action both corrects existing unfair treatment and gives women equal opportunity in the future."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Kim | first1 = Sunhee | last2 = Kim | first2 = Seoyong | title = Exploring the effect of four factors on affirmative action programs for women | journal = [[Asian Journal of Women's Studies]] | volume = 20 | issue = 1 | pages = 30–69 | publisher = [[Ewha Womans University Press]] | date = March 2014 | url = http://itlboard.ewha.ac.kr/ys_board/view.htm?oid=26&amp;mcode=56&amp;page=2&amp;serial=96605 | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [http://ajou.ac.kr/~seoyong/paper/2014-Exploring%20the%20Effect%20of%20Four%20Factors Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Quotas==
Law regarding quotas and affirmative action varies widely from nation to nation. Caste-based quotas are used in India for [[Reservation in India|reservation]]. However, they are illegal in the United States, where no employer, university, or other entity may create a set number required for each race.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://labor-employment-law.lawyers.com/employment-discrimination/Affirmative-Action.html |title=Affirmative Action |publisher=Labor-employment-law.lawyers.com |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, the [[European Union]] Commission approved a plan for women to constitute 40% of non-executive board directorships in large listed companies in Europe by 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The EU's Boardroom Quota Battle Is Over, But Women Cannot Yet Rest |url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/insead/2012/11/19/the-eus-boardroom-quota-battle-is-over-but-women-cannot-yet-rest/ |publisher=Forbes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Sweden, the Supreme Court has ruled that "affirmative action" ethnic quotas in universities are discrimination and hence unlawful. It said that the requirements for the intake should be the same for all. The justice minister said that the decision left no room for uncertainty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thelocal.se/20061221/5871 |title=Uppsala discriminated against Swedes |publisher= The Local |date= 21 December 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==National approaches==
{{See also|Reserved political positions}}

In some countries that have laws on racial equality, affirmative action is rendered illegal because it does not treat all races equally. This approach of equal treatment is sometimes described as being "[[Color blindness (race)|color blind]]", in hopes that it is effective against discrimination without engaging in [[reverse discrimination]].

In such countries, the focus tends to be on ensuring equal opportunity and, for example, targeted advertising campaigns to encourage ethnic minority candidates to join the police force. This is sometimes described as "positive action."

=== Africa ===

====South Africa====
{{see also|Black Economic Empowerment}}

=====Apartheid=====
The [[Apartheid]] government, as a matter of state policy, favoured white-owned, especially [[Afrikaner]]-owned companies. The aforementioned policies achieved the desired results, but in the process they marginalised and excluded black people. Skilled jobs were also reserved for white people, and blacks were largely used as unskilled labour, enforced by legislation including the [[Mines and Works Act]], the [[Job Reservations Act]], the [[Native Building Workers Act]], the [[Apprenticeship Act]] and the [[Bantu Education Act]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southendmuseum.co.za/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=19&amp;Itemid=20 |title=Job Reservations Act |publisher=South End Museum |accessdate=31 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; creating and extending the "colour bar" in South African labour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sahistory.org.za/luli-35 |title=White Workers and the Colour Bar |publisher=Sahistory.org.za |accessdate=31 May 2015 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140319002102/http://www.sahistory.org.za/luli-35 |archivedate=19 March 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in early 20th century South Africa mine owners preferred hiring black workers because they were cheaper.&lt;ref name=enc&gt;[http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/Discrimination.html Discrimination], The Concise Encyclopedia of Economics, Library of Economics&lt;/ref&gt; Then the whites successfully persuaded the government to enact laws that highly restricted the blacks' employment opportunities.&lt;ref name=enc/&gt;

Since the 1960s the Apartheid laws had been weakened. Consequently, from 1975 to 1990 the real wages of black manufacturing workers rose by 50%, that of whites by 1%.&lt;ref name=africa&gt;[http://www.economist.com/node/244570 Race, law and poverty in the new South Africa], The Economist, 30 September 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

The economic and politically structured society during the apartheid ultimately caused disparities in employment, occupation and income within labour markets, which provided advantages to certain groups and characteristics of people. This in due course was the motivation to introduce affirmative action in South Africa, following the end of Apartheid.&lt;ref name=prob&gt;{{cite web |last=Stokes|first= G. |date=15 March 2010 |title=The problem with affirmative action |url=http://www.fanews.co.za/article.asp?Front_Page_Features~25,Stokes_Stage~1145,The_problem_with_affirmative_action~7618 |publisher=Fanews.co.za}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Post-apartheid - the Employment Equity Act=====
Following the transition to democracy in 1994, the [[African National Congress]]-led government chose to implement affirmative action legislation to correct previous imbalances (a policy known as employment equity). As such, all employers were compelled by law to employ previously disenfranchised groups (blacks, [[Indian South Africans|Indians]], [[Chinese people|Chinese]] and [[Coloureds]]). A related, but distinct concept is [[Black Economic Empowerment]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ecsecc.org/files/publications/120307130010.pdf ] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140318215653/http://www.ecsecc.org/files/publications/120307130010.pdf |date=18 March 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Employment Equity Act]] and the [[Broad Based Black Economic Empowerment]] Act aim to promote and achieve equality in the workplace (in South Africa termed "equity"), by advancing people from designated groups. The designated groups who are to be advanced include all people of colour, women (including white women) and [[people with disabilities]] (including whites). Employment Equity legislation requires companies employing more than 50 people to design and implement plans to improve the representativity of workforce demographics, and report them to the [[Department of Labour (South Africa)|Department of Labour]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southafrica.info/services/rights/employmentequity.htm |title=Employment Equity FAQ |publisher=Southafrica.info |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Employment Equity also forms part of a company's [[Black Economic Empowerment]] scorecard: in a relatively complex scoring system, which allows for some flexibility in the manner in which each company meets its legal commitments, each company is required to meet minimum requirements in terms of representation by previously disadvantaged groups. The matters covered include equity ownership, representation at employee and management level (up to board of director level), procurement from black-owned businesses and social investment programs, amongst others.

The policies of Employment Equity and, particularly, Black Economic empowerment have been criticised both by those who view them as discriminatory against white people, and by those who view them as ineffectual.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mg.co.za/article/2010-02-03-bees-glass-slipper |title=BEE's Glass Slipper |publisher=Mg.co.za |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.moneyweb.co.za/mw/view/mw/en/page292679?oid=346519&amp;sn=2009+Detail+no+image&amp;pid=295799 |title=BEE: A man made disaster |publisher=Moneyweb.co.za |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="fin24.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fin24.com/articles/default/display_article.aspx?ArticleId=1518-24_2564628 |title='SAB deal to enrich black elite': Fin24: Companies |publisher=Fin24 |accessdate=29 July 2010 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111003093857/http://www.fin24.com/articles/default/display_article.aspx?ArticleId=1518-24_2564628 |archivedate=3 October 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.busrep.co.za/index.php?fArticleId=5340048 |title=Business Report – Home – Motlanthe warns BEE council has failed |publisher=Busrep.co.za |date=9 February 2010 |accessdate=29 July 2010 }}{{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mg.co.za/article/2009-11-20-manyi-vows-to-get-tough-over-bee |title=Manyi vows to get tough over BEE – Mail &amp; Guardian Online: The smart news source |publisher=Mg.co.za |accessdate=29 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

These laws cause disproportionally high costs for small companies and reduce economic growth and employment.&lt;ref name=africa/&gt; The laws may give the black middle-class some advantage but can make the worse-off blacks even poorer.&lt;ref name=africa/&gt; Moreover, the [[Supreme Court of Appeal of South Africa|Supreme Court]] has ruled that in principle blacks may be favored, but in practice this should not lead to unfair discrimination against the others.&lt;ref name=africa/&gt; Yet it is impossible to favor somebody without discriminating against others.&lt;ref name=africa/&gt;

=====Affirmative Action Purpose=====
As mentioned previously affirmative action was introduced through the Employment Equality Act, 55 in 1998, 4 years after the end of Apartheid. This act was passed to promote the constitutional right of equality and exercise true democracy. This idea was to eliminate unfair discrimination in employment, to ensure the implementation of employment equity to redress the effects of discrimination, to achieve a diverse workforce broadly representative of our people, to promote economic development and efficiency in the workforce and to give effects to the obligations of the Republic as a member of the International Labour Organisation.&lt;ref name=prob/&gt;&lt;ref name=aff&gt;{{cite web |last=Bergmann |first=B. |year=1999 |title=The continuing need for affirmative action. The Quarterly Review of Economics and Finance, 39(5), 757-768 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1062976999000277}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many embraced the Act; however some concluded that the act contradicted itself. The act eliminates unfair discrimination in certain sectors of the national labour market by imposing similar constraints on another.&lt;ref name=prob/&gt;

With the introduction of Affirmative Action, Black Economic Empowerment (BEE) rose additionally in South Africa. The BEE was not a moral initiative to redress the wrongs of the past but to promote growth and strategies that aim to realize a country's full potential. The idea was targeting the weakest link in economics, which was inequality and which would help develop the economy. This is evident in the statement by the Department of Trade and Industry, "As such, this strategy stresses a BEE process that is associated with growth, development and enterprise development, and not merely the redistribution of existing wealth".&lt;ref name=info&gt;{{cite web |title=Black economic empowerment. (n.d.) |url= http://www.southafrica.info/business/trends/empowerment/bee.htm |publisher=Southafrica.info}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Franchi|first= V. |year=2003 |title=The racialization of affirmative action in organizational discourses: A case study of symbolic racism in post-apartheid south africa |work= International Journal of Intercultural Relations, 27(2), 157-187 |url= http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0147176702000913}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarities between the BEE and affirmative action are apparent; however there is a difference. BEE focuses more on employment equality rather than taking wealth away from the skilled white labourers.&lt;ref name=info/&gt;

The main goal of Affirmative Action is for a country to reach its full potential. This occurrence would result in a completely diverse workforce in economic and social sectors. Thus broadening the economic base and therefore stimulating economic growth.&lt;ref name=dem&gt;Edigheji, O. (2006). Affirmative action and state capacity in a democratic South Africa. Policy: issues &amp; actors,20(4), Retrieved from http://cps.org.za/cps%20pdf/pia20_4.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Outcomes=====
Once applied within the country, many different outcomes arose, some positive and some negative. This depended on the approach to and the view of The Employment Equality Act and affirmative action.

'''Positive:'''
Pre-Democracy, the apartheid governments discriminated against non-white races, so with affirmative action, the country started to redress past discriminations. Affirmative action also focused on combating structural racism and racial inequality, hoping to maximize diversity in all levels of society and sectors.&lt;ref name=culture&gt;Goga, F. (n.d.). ''A critique of affirmative action: The concept''. Retrieved from {{cite web|url=http://ccms.ukzn.ac.za/index.php |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-11-05 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120622114513/http://ccms.ukzn.ac.za:80/index.php |archivedate=22 June 2012 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; Achieving this would elevate the status of the perpetual underclass and to restore equal access to the benefits of society.&lt;ref name=prob/&gt;

'''Negative:'''
Though affirmative action had its positives, negatives arose. A quota system was implemented, which aimed to achieve targets of diversity in a work force. This target affected the hiring and level of skill in the work force, ultimately affecting the free market.&lt;ref name=dem/&gt;&lt;ref name=culture/&gt; Affirmative action created marginalization for coloured and Indian races in South Africa, as well as developing and aiding the middle and elite classes, leaving the lower class behind. This created a bigger gap between the lower and middle class, which led to class struggles and a greater segregation.&lt;ref name=aff/&gt;&lt;ref name=culture/&gt; Entitlement began to arise with the growth of the middle and elite classes, as well as race entitlement. Many believe that affirmative action is discrimination in reverse. With all these negatives, much talent started to leave the country.&lt;ref name=prob/&gt; Many negative consequences of affirmative action, specifically the quota system, drive skilled labour away, resulting in bad economic growth. This is due to very few international companies wanting to invest in South Africa.&lt;ref name=culture/&gt;

With these negative and positive outcomes of affirmative action, it is evident that the concept of affirmative action is continually evolving.&lt;ref name=culture/&gt;

===Asia===

====China====
{{main article|Affirmative action in China}}
There is affirmative action in education for minority nationalities. This may equate to lowering minimum requirements for the National University Entrance Examination, which is a mandatory exam for all students to enter university.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.moe.gov.cn/edoas/website18/30/info26630.htm Graduate Student Admission Ordainment – Ministry of Education, PRC]  {{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mzzjw.gd.gov.cn/mzjy/ShowArticle.asp?ArticleID=541 |title=Ethnic and Religious Affairs Commission of Guangdong Province |publisher=Mzzjw.gd.gov.cn |date=15 October 2007 |accessdate=11 April 2012 }}{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some universities set quotas for minority (non-Han) student intake.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Hasmath|first1=Reza|title=The education of ethnic minorities in Beijing|journal=[[Ethnic and Racial Studies]]|date=November 2011|volume=34|issue=11|pages=1835–1854|doi=10.1080/01419870.2011.553238}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further, minority students enrolled in ethnic minority-oriented specialties (e.g. language and literature programs) are provided with scholarships and/or pay no tuition, and are granted a monthly stipend.

====Israel====
A class-based affirmative action policy was incorporated into the admission practices of the four most selective universities in [[Israel]] during the early to mid-2000s. In evaluating the eligibility of applicants, neither their financial status nor their national or ethnic origins are considered. The emphasis, rather, is on structural disadvantages, especially neighborhood socioeconomic status and high school rigor, although several individual hardships are also weighed. This policy made the four institutions, especially the echelons at the most selective departments, more diverse than they otherwise would have been. The rise in geographic, economic and demographic diversity of a student population suggests that the plan's focus on structural determinants of disadvantage yields broad diversity dividends.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Alon, Sigal |year= 2011 |title=The Diversity Dividends of a Need-blind and Color-blind Affirmative Action Policy |work= Social Science Research, 40(6):1494-1505. |url= http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0049089X11001037}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Israeli citizens who are; Women, Arabs, Blacks or people with disabilities are entitled to Affirmative Action in the civil service employment.&lt;ref name="moital.gov.il"&gt;http://www.moital.gov.il/NR/exeres/8C492E47-135C-4B82-84D7-C62254B8BFEF.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Also Israeli citizens who are Arabs, Blacks or people with disabilities are entitled for Affirmative Actions are entitled for full University tuition scholarships by the state.&lt;ref name="che.org.il"&gt;http://che.org.il/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/%D7%94%D7%97%D7%9C%D7%98%D7%AA-%D7%95%D7%AA%D7%AA-%D7%9E%D7%A1-1-%D7%AA%D7%A9%D7%A2%D7%93.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Izraeli in her study of gender Politics in Israel showed that the paradox of affirmative action for women directors is that the legitimation for legislating their inclusion on boards also resulted in the exclusion of women's interested as a legitimate issue on the boards' agendas. "The new culture of the men's club is seductive token women are under the pressure to become "social males" and prove that their competence as directors, meaning that they are not significantly different from men. In the negotiation for status as worthy peers, emphasizing gender signals that a woman is an "imposter," someone who does not rightfully belong in the position she is claiming to fill." And once affirmative action for women is fulfilled, and then affirmative action shares the element, as Izareli put it, the "group equality discourse," making it easier for other groups to claim for a fairer distribution of resources. This suggests that affirmative action can have applications for different groups in Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Gender politics in israel: the case of affirmative action for women directors|url=http://0-www.sciencedirect.com.catalog.sewanee.edu/science/article/pii/S0277539503000438|work=Scandinavian Journal of Management|accessdate=23 October 2013|author=Dafna Izraeli}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====India====
{{Main article|Reservation in India}}

Reservation in India is a form of affirmative action designed to improve the well-being of [[Backward class|backward]] and under-represented communities [[Caste system in India|defined primarily by their caste]].

==== Malaysia ====
{{Main article|Ketuanan Melayu}}

The [[Malaysian New Economic Policy]] or NEP serves as a form of affirmative action. Malaysia provides affirmative action to the majority because in general, the Malays have lower income than the Chinese who have traditionally been involved in businesses and industries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationsencyclopedia.com/economies/Asia-and-the-Pacific/Malaysia-POVERTY-AND-WEALTH.html |title=Encyclopedia of the Nations, "Malaysia Poverty and Wealth" |publisher=Nationsencyclopedia.com |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Malaysia is a multi-ethnic country, with [[Malay (ethnic group)|Malay]]s making up the majority of close to 52% of the population. About 23% of the population are [[Chinese Malaysian|Malaysians of Chinese descent]], while [[Indian Malaysian|Malaysians of Indian descent]] comprise about 7% of the population. During more than 100 years of British colonization, the Malays were discriminated against employment because the British preferred to bring in influx of migrant workers from China and India.

(''See also [[Bumiputra]]'') The mean income for Malays, Chinese and Indians in 1957/58 were 134, 288 and 228 respectively. In 1967/68 it was 154, 329 and 245, and in 1970 it was 170, 390 and 300. Mean income disparity ratio for Chinese/Malays rose from 2.1 in 1957/58 to 2.3 in 1970, whereas for Indians/Malays the disparity ratio also rose from 1.7 to 1.8 in the same period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Perumal |first=M. |year=1989 |title=Economic Growth and Income Inequality in Malaysia, 1957–1984 |journal=Singapore Economic Review |volume=34 |issue=2 |pages=33–46 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Malays viewed Independence as restoring their proper place in their own country's socioeconomic order while the non-Malays were opposing government efforts to advance Malay political primacy and economic welfare.

==== Sri Lanka ====
In 1971 the [[Policy of standardisation|Standardization policy]] of [[Sri Lanka]]n universities was introduced as an affirmative action program for students from areas which had lower rates of education than other areas due to missionary activity in the north and east, which essentially were the Tamil areas. Successive governments cultivated a historical myth after the colonial powers had left that the British had practised [[communal]] favouritism towards Christians and the minority [[Tamil people|Tamil community]] for the entire 200 years they had controlled [[Sri Lanka]]. However, the Sinhalese in fact benefitted from trade and plantation cultivations over the rest of the other groups and their language and culture as well as the religion of Buddhism was fostered and made into mediums for schools over the Tamil language, which did not have the same treatment and Tamils learned English instead as there was no medium for Tamil until near independence. Tamils' knowledge of English and education came from the very American missionary activity by overseas Christians that the British were concerned will anger the Sinhalese and destroy their trading relationships, so they sent them to the Tamil areas instead to teach, thinking it would have no consequences and due to their small numbers. The British sending the missionaries to the north and east was for the protection of the Sinhalese and in fact showed favouritism to the majority group instead of the minorities to maintain trading relationships and benefits from them. The Tamils, out of this random benefit from learning English and basic education excelled and flourished and were able to take many civil service jobs to the chagrin of the Sinhalese. The myth of Divide and Rule is untrue. The 'policy of standardisation' was typical of affirmative action policies, in that it required drastically lower standards for Sinhalese students than for the more academic Tamils who had to get about ten more marks to enter into universities. The policy, were it not implemented would have prevented the civil wars ahead as the policies had no basis and in fact is an example of discrimination against the Tamil ethnic group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sangam.org/british-divide-rule-ceylon/ |title=Did the British Divide &amp; Rule Ceylon? &amp;#124; Ilankai Tamil Sangam |publisher=Sangam.org |date= |accessdate=1 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Taiwan====
A 2004 legislation requires that, for a firm with 100 employees or more wishing to compete for government contracts, at least 1 per cent of its employees must be [[Taiwanese aborigines]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://minorityrights.org/minorities/indigenous-peoples-7/ Taiwan - Indigenous peoples]&lt;/ref&gt; Ministry of Education and [[Council of Indigenous Peoples|Council of Aboriginal Affairs]] announced in 2002 that Taiwanese Aboriginal students would have their high-school or undergraduate entrance exams boosted by 33% for demonstrating some knowledge of their tribal language and culture.&lt;ref name="HolsingerJacob2009"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Donald B. Holsinger|author2=W. James Jacob|title=Inequality in Education: Comparative and International Perspectives|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-lIGaO2-aq4C&amp;pg=PA295|date=29 May 2009|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|isbn=978-90-481-2652-1|pages=295}}&lt;/ref&gt; The percentage of boost have been revised several times, and the latest percentage is 35% in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://law.moj.gov.tw/LawClass/LawOldVer.aspx?Pcode=H0020031&amp;LNNDATE=20130819&amp;LSER=001 | title=原住民學生升學保障及原住民公費留學辦法(民國 102 年08月19 日 )| trans_title=Aboriginal Students Enrollment Guarantee and Public Funding for Aboriginal Study Abroad Act | publisher=[[Ministry of Justice (Taiwan)]] | language=zh}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===

==== Finland ====
In certain university education programs, including legal and medical education, there are quotas for persons who reach a certain standard of skills in the [[Swedish language]]; for students admitted in these quotas, the education is partially arranged in Swedish.&lt;ref name="Helsinki med"&gt;{{cite web|title=Hakuopas 2011. Lääketieteen ja hammaslääketieteen opiskelijavalinnat |url=http://www.med.helsinki.fi/peruskoulutus/docs/opiskelijaksi/hakuopas_2011.pdf |publisher=Faculty of Medicine, University of Helsinki |accessdate=4 June 2011 |language=Finnish |format=PDF |year=2011 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111002143806/http://www.med.helsinki.fi/peruskoulutus/docs/opiskelijaksi/hakuopas_2011.pdf |archivedate=2 October 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Helsinki law"&gt;{{cite web|title=Oikeustieteellinen tiedekunta. Hakuopas 2011|url=http://www.helsinki.fi/oikeustiede/opiskelijaksi/valintakokeet/2011/hakuopas_2011.pdf|publisher=Faculty of Law, University of Helsinki|accessdate=4 June 2011|page=3|language=Finnish|format=PDF|year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The purpose of the quotas is to guarantee that a sufficient number of professionals with skills in Swedish are educated for nationwide needs.&lt;ref name="Helsinki med" /&gt; The quota system has met with criticism from the Finnish speaking majority, some of whom consider the system unfair. In addition to these linguistic quotas, women may get preferential treatment in recruitment for certain public sector jobs if there is a gender imbalance in the field.

==== France ====
No distinctions based on race, religion or sex are allowed under the 1958 [[French Constitution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jonathan D. Mott, Ph.D. |url=http://thisnation.com/library/france.html |title=The French Constitution of 1958 and its Amendments |publisher=Thisnation.com |date=7 February 1992 |accessdate=28 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the 1980s, a French version of affirmative action based on neighborhood is in place for primary and secondary education. Some schools, in neighborhoods labeled "Priority Education Zones", are granted more funds than the others. Students from these schools also benefit from special policies in certain institutions (such as [[Sciences Po]]).&lt;ref&gt;Ghorbal, Karim., "[http://dx.doi.org/10.3989/chdj.2015.016 Essence coloniale d’une politique contemporaine: pour une approche fanonienne de la discrimination positive en France]". ''Culture &amp; History Digital Journal'' 4.2 (2015). Web.&lt;/ref&gt;

The French Ministry of Defence tried in 1990 to make it easier for young French soldiers of North-African descent to be promoted in rank and obtain driving licenses. After a strong protest by a young French lieutenant&lt;ref&gt;Jean-Pierre Steinhofer, "Beur ou ordinaire", ''Armée d'ajourd'hui'', 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; in the Ministry of Defence newspaper (''Armées d'aujourd'hui''), the driving license and rank plan was cancelled. After the Sarkozy election, a new attempt in favour of Arab-French students was made, but Sarkozy did not gain enough political support to change the French constitution. However, ivy league French schools do implement affirmative action in that they are obligated to take a certain number of students from impoverished families.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lemonde.fr/politique/article/2008/12/17/le-plan-sarkozy-pour-favoriser-l-egalite-reelle-des-chances_1132074_823448.html#ens_id=1128487° |title=Le Plan Sarkozy |work=Le Monde  |date=17 December 2008 |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br&gt; Additionally, following the Norwegian example, after 27 January 2014, women must represent at least 20% of board members in all stock exchange listed or state owned companies. After 27 January 2017, the proportion will increase to 40%. All appointments of males as directors will be invalid as long as the quota is not met, and monetary penalties may apply for other directors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vie-publique.fr/actualite/panorama/texte-discussion/proposition-loi-relative-representation-equilibree-femmes-hommes-au-sein-conseils-administration-surveillance-egalite-professionnelle.html |title=Vie Publique |publisher=Vie-publique.fr |date=25 June 2002 |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Germany ====
Article 3 of the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany|German Basic Law]] provides for equal rights of all people regardless of sex, race or social background. There are programs stating that if men and women have equal qualifications, women have to be preferred for a job; moreover, the disabled should be preferred to non-disabled people. This is typical for all positions in state and university service {{as of|2007|lc=y}}, typically using the phrase "We try to increase diversity in this line of work". In recent years, there has been a long public debate about whether to issue programs that would grant women a privileged access to jobs in order to fight discrimination. Germany's ''[[The Left (Germany)|Left Party]]'' brought up the discussion about affirmative action in [[Education in Germany|Germany's school system]]. According to [[Stefan Zillich]], quotas should be "a possibility" to help working class children who did not do well in school gain access to a ''[[Gymnasium (Germany)|Gymnasium]]'' (University-preparatory school).&lt;ref&gt;Susanne Vieth-Entus (29. December 2008): "Sozialquote: Berliner Gymnasien sollen mehr Schüler aus armen Familien aufnehmen". Der Tagesspiegel&lt;/ref&gt; Headmasters of ''Gymnasien'' have objected, saying that this type of policy would "be a disservice" to poor children.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Klesmann (23 February 2009). "'Kinder aus Neukölln würden sich nicht integrieren lassen' – Ein Politiker und ein Schulleiter streiten über Sozialquoten an Gymnasien". Berliner Zeitung&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Norway ====
In all [[Allmennaksjeselskap|public stock companies (ASA)]] boards, either gender should be represented by at least 40%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lovdata.no/all/tl-19970613-045-032.html#6-3 |title=LOV-1997-06-13-45 Lov om allmennaksjeselskaper (allmennaksjeloven) |publisher=Lovdata.no |accessdate=29 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This affects roughly 400 companies of over 300,000 in total.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nettavisen.no/nyheter/27-000-flere-bedrifter-i-norge/1874337.html |title=27.000 flere bedrifter i Norge |publisher=nettavisen.no |accessdate=31 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Seierstad &amp; Opsahl in their study of the effects of affirmative action on presence, prominence, and social capital of women directors in Norway found that there are few boards chaired by a woman, from the beginning of the implementation of affirmative action policy period to August 2009, the proportion of boards led by a woman has increased from 3.4% to 4.3%. This suggests that the law has had a marginal effect on the sex of the chair and the boards remain internally segregated. Although at the beginning of our observation period, only 7 of 91 prominent directors were women. The gender balance among prominent directors has changed considerable through the period, and at the end of the period, 107 women and 117 men were prominent directors. Interestingly, by applying more restrictive definitions of prominence, the proportion of directors who are women generally increases. If only considering directors with at least three directorships, 61.4% of them are women. When considering directors with seven or more directorships, all of them are women. Thus, affirmative action increase the female population in the director position.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Seierstad|first1=Cathrine|last2=Opsahl|first2=Tore|title=For the few not the many? The effects of affirmative action on presence, prominence, and social capital of women directors in Norway|journal=Scandinavian Journal of Management|date=March 2011|volume=27|issue=1|pages=44–54|doi=10.1016/j.scaman.2010.10.002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Romania ====
[[Romani people]] are allocated quotas for access to public schools and state universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mmuncii.ro/old/ro/domenii-politici-familiale-incluziune-si-asistenta-sociala-romii---progrese-inregistrate-in-romania-in-perioada-2007---2008-540-view.html |title=Romii - PROGRESE ÎNREGISTRATE ÎN ROMÂNIA ÎN PERIOADA 2007 - 2008 |accessdate=30 January 2013 }}{{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is evidence that some ethnic Romanians exploit the system so they can be themselves admitted to universities, which has drawn criticism from Roma representatives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.studentie.ro/campus/admiterea_in_facultati_pe_locuri_pentru_rromi_un_fenomen_ce_trebuie_s/c-70-a-149985 | title=Admiterea in facultati pe locuri pentru rromi, un fenomen ce trebuie stopat | accessdate=30 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Russia ====
Quota systems existed in the [[USSR]] for various social groups including [[ethnic minorities]] (as a compensation of their "[[cultural backwardness]]"), women and factory workers.

Quotas for access to university education, offices in the Soviet system and the Communist Party existed: for example, the position of First Secretary of a Soviet Republic's (or Autonomous Republic's) Party Committee was always filled by a representative of this republic's "[[titular ethnicity]]".

Modern Russia retains this system partially. Quotas are abolished, however, preferences for some ethnic minorities and inhabitants of certain territories &lt;ref&gt;http://sakhapress.ru/archives/207211&lt;/ref&gt; remain.

==== Slovakia ====
The [[Constitutional Court of Slovakia|Constitutional Court]] declared in October 2005 that affirmative action i.e. "providing advantages for people of an ethnic or racial minority group" as being against its [[Constitution of Slovakia|Constitution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Goldirova |first=Renata |url=http://euobserver.com/9/20123 |title=Slovakia bans positive discrimination |publisher=Euobserver.com |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== United Kingdom ====
In the UK, any discrimination, quotas or favouritism due to sex, race and ethnicity among other "protected characteristics" is generally illegal for any reason in education, employment, during commercial transactions, in a private club or association, and while using public services.&lt;ref name="cre"/&gt;&lt;ref name=govuk&gt;{{cite web|title=Types of discrimination`|url=https://www.gov.uk/discrimination-your-rights/types-of-discrimination|work=Discrimination: your rights|publisher=GOV.UK|accessdate=7 April 2013|author=GOV.UK|authorlink=Gov.uk|date=4 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="personneltoday.com"/&gt; The [[Equality Act 2010]] established the principles of equality and their implementation in the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15 |title=Equality Act 2010 |publisher=Legislation.gov.uk |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Specific exemptions include:

* Part of the [[Northern Ireland Peace Process]], the [[Good Friday Agreement]] and the resulting [[Patten report]] required the [[Police Service of Northern Ireland]] to recruit 50% of numbers from the [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] community and 50% from the [[Protestantism|Protestant]] and [[Ethnic minorities in Northern Ireland|other communities]], in order to reduce any possible bias towards Protestants. This was later referred to as the '50:50' measure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/1540861.stm |title=UK &amp;#124; N Ireland &amp;#124; Police recruitment 'will be 50:50' |publisher=BBC News |date=12 September 2001 |accessdate=1 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; (See also [[Independent Commission on Policing for Northern Ireland]].)
* The [[Sex Discrimination (Election Candidates) Act 2002]] allowed the use of [[all-women shortlists]] to select more women as election candidates.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.parliament.uk/documents/commons/lib/research/briefings/snpc-05057.pdf|title=All-women shortlists|publisher=House of Commons Library|id=SN/PC/05057|date=29 April 2009|author=Richard Kelly and Isobel White|accessdate=23 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== North America ===

==== Canada ====
{{Further information|Employment equity (Canada)|Federal Contractors' Program}}
The equality section of the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] explicitly permits affirmative action type legislation, although the Charter does not ''require'' legislation that gives preferential treatment. Subsection 2 of [[Section Fifteen of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms|Section 15]] states that the equality provisions do "not preclude any law, program or activity that has as its object the amelioration of conditions of disadvantaged individuals or groups including those that are disadvantaged because of race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, sex, age or mental or physical disability."

The [[Canadian Employment Equity Act]] requires employers in federally-regulated industries to give preferential treatment to four designated groups: Women, people with disabilities, aboriginal people, and [[visible minorities]]. Less than one-third of Canadian Universities offer alternative admission requirements for students of aboriginal descent. Some provinces and territories also have affirmative action-type policies. For example, in [[Northwest Territories]] in the Canadian north, aboriginal people are given preference for jobs and education and are considered to have P1 status. Non-aboriginal people who were born in the NWT or have resided half of their life there are considered a P2, as well as women and people with disabilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hr.gov.nt.ca/employment/affirmativeaction/ |title=GNWT – Human Resources – Affirmative Action |publisher=Hr.gov.nt.ca |date=3 April 2012 |accessdate=11 April 2012}}{{dead link|date=February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United States====
{{Main article|Affirmative action in the United States}}
The concept of affirmative action was introduced in the early 1960s in the United States, as a way to combat [[racial discrimination]] in the hiring process, with the concept later expanded to address gender discrimination.&lt;ref name="clinton2.nara.gov" /&gt; Affirmative action was first created from [[Executive Order 10925]], which was signed by President [[John F. Kennedy]] on 6 March 1961 and required that government employers "not discriminate against any employee or applicant for employment because of race, creed, color, or national origin" and "take affirmative action to ensure that applicants are employed, and that employees are treated during employment, without regard to their race, creed, color, or national origin".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://shfg.org/shfg/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/4-MacLaury-design4-new_Layout-1.pdf|title=President Kennedy’s E.O.10925: Seedbed of Affirmative Action|publisher=Society for History in the Federal Government|accessdate=27 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission
| title = Executive Order 10925 – Establishing The President's Committee On Equal Employment Opportunity
| url = http://www.eeoc.gov/eeoc/history/35th/thelaw/eo-10925.html
| accessdate =5 February 2010| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100527213307/http://www.eeoc.gov/eeoc/history/35th/thelaw/eo-10925.html| archivedate= 27 May 2010 | deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 September 1965, President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]] signed [[Executive Order 11246]], thereby replacing [[Executive Order 10925]] and affirming Federal Government's commitment "to promote the full realization of equal employment opportunity through a positive, continuing program in each executive department and agency".&lt;ref name="The Federal Register"/&gt; Affirmative action was extended to women by [[Executive Order 11375]] which amended Executive Order 11246 on 13 October 1967, by adding "sex" to the list of protected categories. In the U.S. affirmative action's original purpose was to pressure institutions into compliance with the nondiscrimination mandate of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]].&lt;ref name="Affirmative Action"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://lcrm.lib.unc.edu/blog/index.php/2012/09/24/executive-order-11246-and-affirmative-action/ Alison Shay "Publishing the Long Civil Rights Movement-Executive Order 11246 and Affirmative Action" Carolina Digital Library and Archive (University of North Carolina)]&lt;/ref&gt; The Civil Rights Acts do not cover veterans, people with disabilities, or people over 40. These groups are protected from discrimination under different laws.&lt;ref name="EmployeeIssues.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://employeeissues.com/discrimination_laws.htm|title=Federal Employment Discrimination Laws|publisher=EmployeeIssues.com|accessdate=18 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Affirmative action has been the subject of numerous court cases,&lt;ref name="indystar.com"&gt;[http://www.indystar.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080205/LOCAL/80205048 Indy fire-fighters sue city, charge bias; also see] [[Norma M. Riccucci]]&lt;span&gt;. Managing Diversity in Public Sector Workforces. Boulder, CO: Westview Press, 2002&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; and has been questioned upon its [[United States Constitution|constitutional]] legitimacy. In 2003, a Supreme Court decision regarding affirmative action in higher education (''[[Grutter v. Bollinger]]'', 539 US 244 – Supreme Court 2003) permitted educational institutions to consider race as a factor when admitting students.&lt;ref name="Supct.law.cornell.edu"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://supct.law.cornell.edu/supct/03highlts.html#2 |title=Highlights of the 2002–2003 Supreme Court Term |publisher=Supct.law.cornell.edu |date= |accessdate=1 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Alternatively, some colleges use financial criteria to attract racial groups that have typically been under-represented and typically have lower living conditions. Some states such as California ([[California Civil Rights Initiative]]), Michigan ([[Michigan Civil Rights Initiative]]), and Washington ([[Initiative 200]]) have passed constitutional amendments banning public institutions, including public schools,  from practicing affirmative action within their respective states. Conservative activists have alleged that colleges quietly use illegal quotas to increase the number of minorities and have launched numerous lawsuits to stop them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Steven M. Teles|title=The Rise of the Conservative Legal Movement: The Battle for Control of the Law|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MTps-NK20jAC&amp;pg=PA235|year=2010|publisher=Princeton University Press|pages=235–7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Oceania ===

==== New Zealand ====
Individuals of [[Māori people|Māori]] or other [[Polynesia]]n descent are often afforded improved access to university courses, or have scholarships earmarked specifically for them.&lt;ref name=cre&gt;{{cite web|title=Affirmative action around the world|url=http://www.catalystmagazine.org/Default.aspx.LocID-0hgnew0l0.RefLocID-0hg01b001006009.Lang-EN.htm|work=Catalyst|publisher=Commission for Racial Equality|author=Commission for Racial Equality |authorlink=Commission for Racial Equality |archiveurl=http://www.juliushonnor.com/catalyst/Default.aspx.LocID-0hgnew0l0.RefLocID-0hg01b001006009.Lang-EN.htm|archivedate=24 September 2007|date=29 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Affirmative action is provided for under section 73 of the Human Rights Act 1993&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legislation.govt.nz/act/public/1993/0082/latest/DLM304672.html |title=Human Rights Act 1993 No 82 (as at 1 July 2013), Public Act 73 Measures to ensure equality – New Zealand Legislation |publisher=Legislation.govt.nz |date=1 July 2013 |accessdate=1 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and section 19(2) of the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act 1990.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legislation.govt.nz/act/public/1990/0109/latest/DLM225519.html |title=New Zealand Bill of Rights Act 1990 No 109 (as at 1 July 2013), Public Act 19 Freedom from discrimination – New Zealand Legislation |publisher=Legislation.govt.nz |date=1 July 2013 |accessdate=1 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== South America ===

====Brazil====
{{Further information|Vestibular}}

Some Brazilian Universities (State and Federal) have created systems of preferred admissions (quotas) for racial minorities (blacks and native Brazilians), the poor and people with disabilities. There are also quotas of up to 20% of vacancies reserved for people with disabilities in the civil public services.&lt;ref&gt;Plummer, Robert. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/5357842.stm "Black Brazil Seeks a Better Future."] BBC News São Paulo, 25 September 2006. 16 November 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Democrats (Brazil)|Democrats]] party, accusing the board of directors of the [[University of Brasília]] of "Nazism", appealed to the [[Supreme Federal Court]] against the [[constitutionality]] of the quotas the University reserves for minorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Por Rodrigo Haidar e Filipe Coutinho |url=http://www.conjur.com.br/2009-jul-20/dem-unb-ressuscitou-ideais-nazistas-suspensao-matriculas |title=DEM entra com ADPF contra cotas raciais |language=pt |publisher=Conjur.com.br |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Supreme Court unanimously approved their constitutionality on 26 April 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Débora Santos |url =http://g1.globo.com/vestibular-e-educacao/noticia/2012/04/stf-decide-por-unanimidade-pela-constitucionalidade-das-cotas-raciais.html | title=Supremo decide pro unanimidade pela constiucionalidade das cotas |language=pt| publisher=g1.globo.com | accessdate=3 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== International organizations ==

=== United Nations ===
The International [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]] stipulates (in Article 2.2) that affirmative action programs may be required of countries that ratified the convention, in order to rectify systematic discrimination. It states, however, that such programs "shall in no case entail as a consequence the maintenance of unequal or separate rights for different racial groups after the objectives for which they were taken have been achieved."&lt;ref name="unhchr.ch"&gt;United Nations Committee on Human Rights, [http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/(Symbol)/3888b0541f8501c9c12563ed004b8d0e?Opendocument General Comment 18 on Non-discrimination, Paragraph 10]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Nations Human Rights Committee]] states that "the principle of equality sometimes requires States parties to take affirmative action in order to diminish or eliminate conditions which cause or help to perpetuate discrimination prohibited by the Covenant. For example, in a State where the general conditions of a certain part of the population prevent or impair their enjoyment of human rights, the State should take specific action to correct those conditions. Such action may involve granting for a time to the part of the population concerned certain preferential treatment in specific matters as compared with the rest of the population. However, as long as such action is needed to correct discrimination, in fact, it is a case of legitimate differentiation under the Covenant."&lt;ref name="unhchr.ch"/&gt;

==Support==
The principle of affirmative action is to promote societal equality through the preferential treatment of socioeconomically disadvantaged people. Often, these people are disadvantaged for historical reasons, such as oppression or slavery.&lt;ref name="Christophe Jaffrelot pg. 321"/&gt;
Historically and internationally, support for affirmative action has sought to achieve a range of goals: bridging inequalities in employment and pay; increasing access to education; enriching state, institutional, and professional leadership with the full spectrum of society; redressing apparent past wrongs, harms, or hindrances, in particular addressing the apparent social imbalance left in the wake of slavery and slave laws.

===Polls===
{{Globalize/US|section|date=May 2010}}
According to a poll taken by ''[[USA Today]]'' in 2005, majority of Americans support affirmative action for women, while views on [[minority group]]s were more split.&lt;ref name="usatoday.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/polls/tables/live/0623.htm |title=Usatoday.Com |publisher=Usatoday.Com |date=20 May 2005 |accessdate=28 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Men are only slightly more likely to support affirmative action for women; though a majority of both do.&lt;ref name="usatoday.com"/&gt; However, a slight majority of Americans do believe that affirmative action goes beyond ensuring access and goes into the realm of preferential treatment.&lt;ref name="usatoday.com"/&gt; More recently, a Quinnipiac poll from June 2009 finds that 55% of Americans feel that affirmative action in general should be discontinued, though 55% support it for people with disabilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Quinnipiac University – Office of Public Affairs |url=http://www.quinnipiac.edu/x1295.xml?ReleaseID=1307 |title=National (US) Poll * June 3, 2009 * U.S. Voters Disagree 3-1 With – Quinnipiac University – Hamden, Connecticut |publisher=Quinnipiac.edu |date=3 June 2009 |accessdate=11 April 2012}}{{dead link|date=February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[The Gallup Organization|Gallup]] poll from 2005 showed that 72% of black Americans and 44% of white Americans supported racial affirmative action (with 21% and 49% opposing), with support and opposition among Hispanics falling between those of blacks and whites. Support among blacks, unlike among whites, had almost no correlation with political affiliation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Race, Ideology, and Support for Affirmative Action|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/18091/race-ideology-support-affirmative-action.aspx|publisher=[[The Gallup Organization|Gallup]]|date=23 August 2005|last=Jones|first=Jeffrey M.|accessdate=11 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2009 [[Quinnipiac University Polling Institute]] survey found 65% of American voters opposed the application of affirmative action to gay people, with 27% indicating they supported it.&lt;ref name=qui&gt;[http://www.quinnipiac.edu/institutes-and-centers/polling-institute/national/release-detail?ReleaseID=1307 U.S. Voters Disagree 3-1 With Sotomayor On Key Case]. [[Quinnipiac University]]. Published 3 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

A Leger poll taken in 2010 found 59% of Canadians opposed considering race, gender, or ethnicity when hiring for government jobs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[David Akin]], QMI Agency Parliamentary Bureau Chief |url=http://www.torontosun.com/news/canada/2010/08/12/14998311.html |title=Canadians against job hiring quotas |work=Toronto Sun |date=12 August 2010 |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism ==
Opponents of affirmative action such as [[George Sher]] believe that affirmative action devalues the accomplishments of people who are chosen based on the social group to which they belong rather than their qualifications, thus rendering affirmative action counterproductive.&lt;ref name="Sher, George 1983, p.40"&gt;Sher, George, "Preferential Hiring", in Tom Regan (ed.), Just Business: New Introductory Essays In Business Ethics, Philadelphia, Temple University Press, 1983, p.40.&lt;/ref&gt; Opponents,&lt;ref name="American Civil Rights Institute"/&gt; who sometimes say that affirmative action is [[reverse discrimination]], further claim that affirmative action has undesirable side-effects in addition to failing to achieve its goals. They argue that it hinders reconciliation, replaces old wrongs with new wrongs, undermines the achievements of minorities, and encourages individuals to identify themselves as disadvantaged, even if they are not. It may increase racial tension and benefit the more privileged people within [[minority group]]s at the expense of the least fortunate within majority groups (such as lower-class white people).&lt;ref name="Cultural Whiplash 2006"/&gt;

Opponents claim that cases such as ''[[Fisher v. University of Texas (2013)|Fisher v. University of Texas]]'' are few of the many examples that show how reverse discrimination can take place. In 2008, Abigail Fisher, who is a native to Texas, sued the [[University of Texas at Austin]], claiming that she was denied admission to the university because she was "white". The students that are of top 10% in the applicants of the University of Texas are admitted and there are students that compete to barely make it in on the threshold, such as Abigail Fisher. In such cases, race becomes an important factor in deciding who gets admitted to the university, and Fisher argued that discriminating and accepting students according to their race is a violation of the [[Equal Protection Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]], which ensures equal protection of the law and the citizen's privilege as a citizen of United States. The constitutionality of affirmative action in college admissions is now back before the Supreme Court in the case ''[[Fisher v. University of Texas (2016)]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Toobin |first=Jeffrey |url=http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/comment/2012/05/the-other-big-supreme-court-case.html |title=Fisher v. University of Texas and the End of Affirmative Action |work=The New Yorker |date=1 May 2012 |accessdate=1 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

American economist, social and political commentator, Dr. [[Thomas Sowell]] identified some negative results of race-based affirmative action in his book, ''[[Affirmative Action Around the World|Affirmative Action Around the World: An Empirical Study]]''.&lt;ref&gt;ISBN 0-300-10199-6, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;  Sowell writes that affirmative action policies encourage non-preferred groups to designate themselves as members of preferred groups (i.e., primary beneficiaries of affirmative action) to take advantage of group preference policies; that they tend to benefit primarily the most fortunate among the preferred group (e.g., upper and middle class blacks), often to the detriment of the least fortunate among the non-preferred groups (e.g., poor whites or Asians); that they reduce the incentives of both the preferred and non-preferred to perform at their best – the former because doing so is unnecessary and the latter because it can prove futile – thereby resulting in net losses for society as a whole; and that they increase animosity toward preferred groups.

=== Mismatching ===
Mismatching is the term given to the negative effect that affirmative action has when it places a student into a college that is too difficult for him or her. For example, according to the theory, in the absence of affirmative action, a student will be admitted to a college that matches his or her academic ability and have a good chance of graduating. However, according to the mismatching theory, affirmative action often places a student into a college that is too difficult, and this increases the student's chance of dropping out. Thus, according to the theory, affirmative action hurts its intended beneficiaries, because it increases their dropout rate.&lt;ref name="latimes.com"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Quotas on trial"/&gt;

Evidence in support of the mismatching theory was presented by Gail Heriot, a professor of law at the [[University of San Diego]] and a member of the [[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]], in a 24 August 2007 article published in the ''[[Wall Street Journal]]''. The article reported on a 2004 study that was conducted by [[UCLA]] law professor [[Richard Sander]] and published in the ''[[Stanford Law Review]]''. The study concluded that there were 7.9% fewer black attorneys than there would have been if there had been no affirmative action. The study was titled, "A Systemic Analysis of Affirmative Action in American Law Schools."&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB118792252575507571.html?mod=opinion_main_commentaries Affirmative Action Backfires], by Gail Heriot, ''Wall Street Journal'', 24 August 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The article also states that because of mismatching, blacks are more likely to drop out of law school and fail bar exams.&lt;ref name=Sander&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sander|first=Richard|title=A SYSTEMIC ANALYSIS OF AFFIRMATIVE ACTION IN AMERICAN LAW SCHOOLS|journal=Stanford Law Review|year=2004|pages=367–483|url=http://www2.law.ucla.edu/sander/Systemic/final/SanderFINAL.pdf|accessdate=13 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sander's paper on mismatching has been criticized by several law professors, including [[Ian Ayres]] and Richard Brooks from Yale who argue that eliminating affirmative action would actually reduce the number of black lawyers by 12.7%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Fisman |first=Ray |url=http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/jurisprudence/2005/04/sanding_down_sander.html |title=Slate.com |publisher=Slate.com |accessdate=11 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2008 study by [[Jesse Rothstein]] and Albert H. Yoon confirmed Sander's mismatch findings, but also found that eliminating affirmative action would "lead to a 63 percent decline in black matriculants at all law schools and a 90 percent decline at elite law schools."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2008/09/03/affirm | title=Attacking the 'Mismatch' Critique of Affirmative Action | work=Inside Higher Education | date=3 September 2008 | accessdate=27 January 2016 | author=Jaschik, Scott}}&lt;/ref&gt; These high numbers predictions were doubted in a review of previous studies by Peter Arcidiacono and Michael Lovenheim. Their 2016 article found a strong indication that affirmative action results in a mismatch effect. They argued that the attendance by some African-American students to less-selective schools would significantly improve the low first attempt rate at passing the [[State bar association|state bar]], but they cautioned that such improvements could be outweighed by decreases in law school attendance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1=Peter |last1=Arcidiacono |first2=Michael |last2=Lovenheim |date=March 2016 |title=Affirmative Action and the Quality-Fit Tradeoff |url=https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/jeclit/v54y2016i1p3-51.html |journal=[[Journal of Economic Literature]] |pages=30, 31 and 69 |volume=54 |number=1 |doi=10.1257/jel.54.1.3 |accessdate=May 25, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2011 study proposed that mismatch can only occur when a selective school possesses private information that, had this information been disclosed, would have changed the student's choice of school. The study found that this is in fact the case for [[Duke University]], and that this information predicts the student's academic performance after beginning college.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Arcidiacono|first1=Peter|last2=Aucejo|first2=Esteban M.|last3=Fang|first3=Hanming|last4=Spenner|first4=Kenneth I.|title=Does affirmative action lead to mismatch? A new test and evidence|journal=Quantitative Economics|date=November 2011|volume=2|issue=3|pages=303–333|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/store/10.3982/QE83/asset/QE83.pdf?v=1&amp;t=ime7f83m&amp;s=b2bc907adca860d18314bee2a1ea9b9c2e27e2e1|doi=10.3982/QE83}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2016 study on affirmative action in India fails to find evidence for the mismatching hypothesis.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Surendrakumar|first=Bagde,|last2=Dennis|first2=Epple,|last3=Lowell|first3=Taylor,|date=2016-06-01|title=Does Affirmative Action Work? Caste, Gender, College Quality, and Academic Success in India|url=https://www.aeaweb.org/atypon.php?return_path=/doi/pdfplus/10.1257/aer.20140783&amp;etoc=1|journal=American Economic Review|volume=106|issue=6|doi=10.1257/aer.20140783|issn=0002-8282}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Achievement gap]]
* [[Affirmative action bake sale]]
* [[Angry white male]]
* [[Civil and political rights]]
* [[Diversity (business)]]
* [[Diversity training]]
* [[Economic discrimination]]
* [[Equality of opportunity]]
* [[Ethnic Penalty]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Harrison Bergeron]]
* [[Jewish quota]]
* [[Legacy preferences]]
* [[Minority rights]]
* [[Multiculturalism]]
* [[Numerus clausus]]
* [[Political correctness]]
* [[Positive liberty]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Principle-policy puzzle]]
* [[Progressive stack]]
* [[Reasonable accommodation]]
*[[Special Measures for Gender Equality in The United Nations(UN)]]
* [[Strong-basis-in-evidence standard]]
* [[Teaching for social justice]]
* [[White Guilt]]
* [[Women's rights]]
* [[Quotaism]]
{{col-end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book | last = Anderson | first = Terry H. | author-link = Terry H. Anderson | title = The pursuit of fairness: a history of affirmative action | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford New York | year = 2004 | isbn = 9780195157642 }}
* {{cite book | editor-last1 = Featherman | editor-first1 = David L. | editor-last2 = Hall | editor-first2 = Martin | editor-last3 = Krislov | editor-first3 = Marvin | title = The next twenty-five years: affirmative action in higher education in the United States and South Africa | publisher = University of Michigan Press | location = Ann Arbor | year = 2010 | isbn = 9780472033775 }} Forewords by: Mary Sue Coleman, President of the University of Michigan and Njabulo Ndebele, Former Vice-Chancellor and Principal of the University of Cape Town. [http://www.press.umich.edu/titleDetailDesc.do?id=229720 Details.]
* {{cite thesis | degree = Ph.D. | last = Golland | first = David Hamilton | date = 2008 | title = Constructing affirmative action: federal contract compliance and the building construction trades, 1956-1973 |publisher= [[City University of New York]] | oclc = 279305174 }} Order No. DA3325474.
* {{cite book | last = Vieth-Entus | first = Susanne | title = Sozialquote: Berliner Gymnasien sollen mehr Schüler aus armen Familien aufnehmen | date = 29 December 2008 }} Der Tagesspiegel
* {{cite web | last = Bossuyt | first = Marc | author-link = Marc Bossuyt | title = United Nations Sub-Commission on the Promotion and Protection of Human Rights | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151016080556/http://www.unhchr.ch/Huridocda/Huridoca.nsf/TestFrame/0aaa7775daf0bcebc1256c0c0031c5bd?Opendocument | archive-date = 16 October 2015 | url = http://www.unhchr.ch/Huridocda/Huridoca.nsf/TestFrame/0aaa7775daf0bcebc1256c0c0031c5bd?Opendocument | publisher = [[United Nations Economic and Social Council|UN Economic and Social Council]] | date = 17 June 2002 }} E/CN.4/Sub.2/2002/21 [https://web.archive.org/web/20140319035719/http://www.unhchr.ch/Huridocda/Huridoca.nsf/0/0aaa7775daf0bcebc1256c0c0031c5bd/$FILE/G0214014.pdf Pdf.]
* {{cite book | last = Riccucci | first = Norma M. | author-link = Norma M. Riccucci | title = Managing diversity in public sector workforces | publisher = Westview Press | location = Boulder, Colorado | year = 2002 | series = Essentials of Public Policy and Administration Series | isbn = 9780813398389 }}

== Further reading ==
* {{Cite journal | last = Anderson | first = Elizabeth S. | author-link = Elizabeth S. Anderson | title = Integration, affirmative action, and strict scrutiny | journal = [[New York University Law Review|NYU Law Review]] | volume = 77 | pages = 1195–1271 | publisher = [[New York University School of Law|New York University - Law]] | year = 2002 | url = http://www.nyulawreview.org/issues/volume-77-number-5/integration-affirmative-action-and-strict-scrutiny | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [http://www.nyulawreview.org/sites/default/files/pdf/NYULawReview-77-5-Anderson.pdf Pdf.]
* {{cite encyclopedia |last=Bolick |first=Clint |authorlink= Clint Bolick |editor-first=Ronald |editor-last=Hamowy |editor-link=Ronald Hamowy |encyclopedia=The Encyclopedia of Libertarianism |title= Affirmative Action|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=yxNgXs3TkJYC  |accessdate= |edition= |year=2008 |publisher= [[SAGE Publications|Sage]]; [[Cato Institute]] |location= Thousand Oaks, California |id= |isbn= 978-1-4129-6580-4 |oclc=750831024| lccn = 2008009151 |pages=6–8 |quote= |ref= }}
* {{citation | last1 = Boxill | first1 = Bernard | last2 = Boxill | first2 = Jan | contribution = Affirmative action | editor-last1 = Frey | editor-first1 = R.G. | editor-last2 = Heath Wellman | editor-first2 = Christopher | title = A companion to applied ethics | pages = 89–101 | publisher = Blackwell Publishing | series = Blackwell Companions to Philosophy | location = Oxford, UK Malden, Massachusetts | year = 2005 | doi = 10.1002/9780470996621.ch9 | isbn = 9781405133456 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Condit | first1 = Deirdre M. | last2 = Condit | first2 = Celeste M. | last3 = Achter | first3 = Paul J. | author-link1 = Deirdre M. Condit | title = Human equality, affirmative action, and genetic models of human variation | journal = Rhetoric &amp; Public Affairs | volume = 4 | issue = 1 | pages = 85–108 | publisher = [[Michigan State University Press]] via [[JSTOR]] | doi = 10.1353/rap.2001.0003 | jstor = 41939651 | date = Spring 2001 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1353/rap.2001.0003 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Ghorbal | first1 = Karim | title = Essence coloniale d’une politique contemporaine: pour une approche fanonienne de la discrimination positive en France | journal = Culture &amp; History Digital Journal | volume = 4 | issue = 2 | publisher = [[Spanish National Research Council|CSIC]] | doi = 10.3989/chdj.2015.016 | date = 2015 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.3989/chdj.2015.016| ref = harv | postscript = .}}
* {{Cite journal | last = Harpalani | first = Vinay | title = Diversity within racial groups and the constitutionality of race-conscious admissions | journal = [[University of Pennsylvania Journal of Constitutional Law]] | volume = 15 | issue = 2 | pages = 463–537 | publisher = [[University of Pennsylvania Law School]] | date = November 2012 | url = http://scholarship.law.upenn.edu/jcl/vol15/iss2/3/ | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [http://scholarship.law.upenn.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1009&amp;context=jcl Pdf.] 
::Cited in Society of American Law Teachers (S.A.L.T.) amicus brief to U.S. Supreme Court in Fisher v. University of Texas, No. 11-345 (argued 10 October 2012). Also available at the [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2087731 Social Science Research Network (SSRN).]
* {{Cite journal | last = Harpalani | first = Vinay | title = Fisher's fishing expedition | journal = [[University of Pennsylvania Journal of Constitutional Law]] | volume = 15 | issue = 1 | pages = 57–74 | publisher = [[University of Pennsylvania Law School]] | date = February 2013 | url = http://scholarship.law.upenn.edu/jcl_online/vol15/iss1/5/ | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [https://www.law.upenn.edu/live/files/1687-harpalani15upajconstlheightscrutiny572013pdf Pdf.]
::Invited commentary on oral arguments in Fisher v. University of Texas, No. 11-345 (argued 10 October 2012). Also available at the [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2185453 Social Science Research Network (SSRN).]
* {{cite book | last = Hasmath | first = Reza | title = Managing ethnic diversity: meanings and practices from an international perspective | publisher = Ashgate | location = Farnham Burlington, Vermont | year = 2011 | isbn = 9781409411215 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Pollak | first = Oliver B. | title = Antisemitism, the Harvard Plan, and the roots of reverse discrimination | journal = Jewish Social Studies | volume = 45 | issue = 2 | pages = 113–122 | publisher = [[Indiana University Press]] via JSTOR | date = 1983 | jstor = 4467214 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}

==External links==
*{{cite SEP |url-id=affirmative-action |title=Affirmative Action}}
*{{NYTtopic|subjects/a/affirmative_action}}
*{{WSJ topic}}
* [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/politics/special/affirm/affirm.htm Affirmative Action] collected news and commentary at ''[[The Washington Post]]''
* [http://www.pbs.org/now/shows/434/index.html Does the success of Barack Obama mean we no longer need affirmative action?] NOW on PBS investigates
*[http://cle.ens-lsh.fr/29902590/0/fiche___pagelibre/&amp;RH=CDL_ANG020000 An interview with Professor Randall Kennedy about the presidency of Barack Obama and affirmative action] Clifford Armion for La Clé des langues.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070615173751/http://www.minorityrights.org/admin/Download/pdf/MRG_RomaBriefing2006.pdf Substantive Equality, Positive Action and Roma Rights in the European Union], Report by Minority Rights Group International
* [[Intelligence Squared]] debate: [http://intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/past-debates/item/1054-affirmative-action-on-campus-does-more-harm-than-good Affirmative Action on Campus Does More Harm than Good]

{{Employment}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Affirmative Action}}
[[Category:Education issues]]
[[Category:History of education]]
[[Category:Education policy]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Social inequality]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination]]
[[Category:Race and law]]
[[Category:Affirmative action| ]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>