<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113215557|87620910" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="49392" pageid="49392" ns="0" title="Affirmative action"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T22:07:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup-date|July 2006}}
{{Unreferenced}}
'''Affirmative action''' is a policy or a program which gives preference to a minority, or protected group of people with the stated goal of countering past or ongoing discrimination against them. It can take many forms including priority acceptance for government contracts, education, or employment and/or language training or vocational training.

==Purpose==
Affirmative action began as a corrective measure&lt;ref&gt;The history of "affirmative" or "positive" remedies command the wrongdoer to do something. In contrast, "negative" remedies command the wrongdoer not to do something or to stop doing something.&lt;/ref&gt; for governmental and social injustices against demographic groups that have been said to be subjected to discrimination in areas such as employment and education. The stated goal of Affirmative Action is to sufficiently counter past discrimination such that a strategy will no longer be necessary: the power elite will reflect the demographics of society at large.

Some groups who are targetted for affirmative action are characterized by [[race]], [[Gender role|gender]], [[ethnicity]], [[sexual orientation]], or [[handicap]].  In India, the focus has mostly been on undoing [[caste]] discrimination.  In [[South Africa]], the focus has been primarily race-based and, to a lesser extent, sex-based discrimination.  When members of targeted groups are actively sought or preferred, the reason given is usually that this is necessary to compensate for advantages that other groups are said to have had (such as through [[institutional racism]] or [[institutional sexism]] or historical circumstances).

The theory is that a simple adoption of [[meritocracy|meritocratic]] principles along the lines of [[race-blind]]ness or [[gender-blind|gender-blindness]] will not suffice to change the situation for several reasons:

*Discrimination practices of the past preclude the acquisition of 'merit' by limiting access to educational opportunities and job experiences.
*Ostensible measures of 'merit' may well be biased toward the same groups who are already empowered.
*Regardless of overt principles, people already in positions of power are likely to hire people they already know, and/or people from similar backgrounds.

==Controversy==

Proponents of affirmative action generally advocate it either as a means to address past discrimination or to enhance racial, ethnic, gender, or other diversity. &lt;ref name=Richardson-1998&gt;L. Anita Richardson, [http://www.abanet.org/publiced/focus/spr98const.html What Is the Constitutional Status of Affirmative Action?: Reading Tea Leaves], in ''ABA Focus on Law Studies'', Spring 1998, Volume XIII Number 2, [[American Bar Association]]; part of article series "Affirmative Action: A Dialogue on Race, Gender, Equality and Law in America". Accessed online September 7, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; They may argue that the end result — a more diversified student body, police-force or other group — justifies the means. 

Many claim that it has unintended and undesireable side-effects and that it fails to achieve its goals. They argue that it can act as a form of discrimination, perpetrate new wrongs to counter old ones, and instill a sense of victimhood in the majority. It may increase racial tension and benefit the more privileged people within [[minority groups]] (such as middle to upper class blacks) at the expense of the disenfranchised within majority groups (such as poor whites). In the British 2001 Summer Of Violence Riots in [[Oldham]], [[Bradford]], [[Leeds]] and [[Burnley]], one of the major complaints voiced in poor white areas was alleged discrimination in council funding which favoured minority areas.
&lt;!-- Such complaints may result from media portrayal of affirmative action programmes, which may be biased or erroneous. On the other hand, bodies such as local councils that initiate such programmes have a duty to explain them fully and transparently to all of their constituents, be aware of the tensions that may arise, and avoid discriminating actively against majority groups.--&gt;

There are also claims that the practice is itself [[racism|racist]] and/or [[sexism|sexist]]. Finally critics and supporters disagree on the [[economics|economic]] effects of affirmative action {{fact}}.

==Affirmative action in international human rights law==

The International [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]] stipulates (in Article 2.2) that affirmative action programs may be required of states that have ratified the convention, in order to rectify systematic discrimination. It states however that such programs "shall in no case entail as a consequence the maintenance of unequal or separate rights for different racial groups after the objectives for which they were taken have been achieved". Positive discrimination, on the other hand, even if intended to improve the lot of disadvantaged groups, is considered illegal in [[international human rights law]], as is any kind of discrimination.

An in-depth examination of the legal status of affirmative action, and the different kinds of programs that exist and their pros and cons, can be found in a paper written for the United Nations [[Sub-Commission on the Promotion and Protection of Human Rights]] by one of its members, Marc Bossuyt&lt;ref&gt;"The concept and practice of affirmative action" http://www.unhchr.ch/Huridocda/Huridoca.nsf/TestFrame/0aaa7775daf0bcebc1256c0c0031c5bd?Opendocument&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Implementation worldwide==

In some countries which have laws on racial equality, affirmative action is rendered illegal by a requirement to treat all races equally. This approach of equal treatment is sometimes described as being "[[race-blind]]", in hopes that it is effective against discrimination without engaging in [[reverse discrimination]].

In such countries, the focus tends to be on ensuring equal opportunity and, for example, targeted advertising campaigns to encourage ethnic minority candidates to join the police force. This is sometimes described as "positive action", as opposed to "positive discrimination".

===United States===
''Main article: [[Affirmative action in the United States]]''

In the [[United States]], affirmative action occurs in school admissions, job hiring, and government and corporate contracts.  Its intended beneficiaries are ethnic minorities (such as blacks and Hispanics), women, people with disabilities, and veterans.  Affirmative action has been the subject of numerous court cases, and has been contested on [[United States Constitution|constitutional]] grounds. 

===India===

''Main article: [[Reservation in India]]

Affirmative action has historically been implemented in [[India]] in the form of [[Reservation in India|reservation]] or quotas in government positions, employment and education for lower [[caste]]s and minorities. The first records of these policies are seen in the late 19th century in the princely states of [[Kingdom of Mysore|Mysore]] in [[South India]] and [[Baroda]] and [[Kolhapur]] in western India. Reservations in government jobs were introduced in 1918 in Mysore in favour of a number of castes and communities that had little share in the administration. In another instance, upon petition from the Muslim community, the British government at facilities. In the communal award of 1935, legislative seats were reserved for members of the Muslim, Sikh, Maratha, Parsi, Christian, European and Anglo-Indian communities. In addition seats were reserved for depressed classes within the Hindu community. The scheduled castes were given 8.5 reservation in central services and other facilities in 1942. In independent India, provision for reservation in legislature was made in the constitution until 1960, recently extended until 2010. Provision for public services was made at the same time with no time limit. More recently in 1990, the implementation of the [[Mandal commission]]s' recommendations have been in the social and political limelight. Despite widespread agitation (mostly among students), reservation for the backward classes were upheld to the extent of 27 per cent (this was in addition to the 22.5% already reserved for scheduled castes and tribes, bringing the total of 'open' seats to only 50%). [http://www.ambedkar.org/research/Bhagwandas.pdf]

There have been recent attempts to introduce it into the private job sector and for Muslims.
Many people disagree with affirmative action which has led to a lot of controversy.


===Other countries===
*[[Belgium]]. The [[Flanders|Flemish]] government proposed in January 2006 a measure that will make some job opportunities available exclusively to immigrants, disabled and elderly people for the first three weeks. [http://www.hln.be/hln/cch/det/art_159838.html]
*[[Bosnia-Herzegovina]]. Women must represent at least 29% of all politicians.
*[[Brazil]]. Some Brazilian Universities (State or Federal) have created systems of preferred admissions (quotas) for racial minorities (blacks and native Brazilians), the poor and the handicapped. There are also quotas for the disabled in the civil public services.
*[[Brunei]]. The [[Bumiputera]]s of Brunei are accorded special benefits through a variety of affirmative action programs. For instance, the [[Royal Brunei Armed Forces]] enlist only Bumiputeras.
*[[China]]. The People's Republic allows non-Han ethnic groups (around 9% of the population) to be exempt from the [[One-child policy]], and there is a quota for minority representatives in the [[National Assembly]] in Beijing, as well as other realms of government.
*[[France]]. The French Ministry of Defense tried in 1990 to give more easily higher ranks and driving licenses to young French soldiers with Arabian origins. After a strong protest by a young French lieutenant in the Ministry of Defense newspaper ("Armées d'aujourd'hui"), this driving license and rank project was cancelled. (article: [[Jean-Pierre Steinhofer]]: "Beur ou ordinaire").
*[[Germany]]. Article 3 of the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany|German constitution]] provides for equal rights of all people regardless of sex or race. In recent years there has been a long public debate about whether to issue programs that would grant women a privileged access to jobs in order to fight discrimination. There were programs stating that if men and women had equal qualifications, women had to be preferred for a job. The Government agreed on the details of an anti-discrimination law (Antidiskriminierungsgesetz; ADG) in May 2006, that aims at improving the protection of minorities. The draft follows EU-standards and has passed the [[Bundestag|German Parliament]] in August 2006.
*[[Greece]]. has quotas setting a lower limit for women participating in election lists of political parties for most of the election processes.
*[[Japan]]. Spot for universities as well as all the government position (including teachers) are determined by the entrance exam, which is extremely competitive at the top level. It is illegal to include sex, ethnicity or other social background (but not nationality) in criteria. However, there are informal policies to provide employment and long term welfare (which is usually not available to general public) to [[Burakumin]] at municipality level.
*[[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]]. Minorities, most notably Albanians, are allocated quotas for access to state universities, as well as in civil public services.
*[[Malaysia]]. The [[bumiputra]] laws are a form of affirmative action meant to provide more opportunity for the majority ethnic [[Malay people|Malay]] population versus the historical financial dominance of the [[Chinese Malaysian|Chinese]] and [[Indian Malaysian|Indian]] populations.
*[[New Zealand]]. Individuals of [[Māori]] or other [[Polynesia]]n descent are often afforded preferential access to university courses, and scholarships.
*[[Norway]]: All [[public company]] (ASA) boards with more than five members, must have at least 40 % women (can not be made up of more than 60% of one sex). This affects roughly 400 companies.
*[[Philippines]]. State universities implement a modified version of Affirmative Action. Secondary schools, both private and public schools, are each assigned a quota on how many students from that high school are accepted for admission, in addition to each student's score during the entrance examination. This was done to address the situation wherein a majority of the university school population was composed mostly of students who came from well-off families and private schools.
*[[Slovakia]]. The Constitutional Court declared in October 2005 that affirmative action i.e. 'providing advantages for people of an ethnic or racial minority group' as being against its Constitution. [http://euobserver.com/9/20123] This is seen as an anti-[[Roma people|gipsy]] decision immediately following [[roma people|Roma]] hunger riots, which protested curtailing of social aids in Slovakia.
*[[South Africa]]. The Employment Equity Act and the Broad Based Black Economic Empowerment Act aim to promote and achieve equality in the workplace (in South Africa termed "equity"), by not only advancing people from designated groups but also specifically disadvancing the others.  By legal definition, the designated groups include all non-whites, females, people with disabilities, and people from rural areas.  The term "black economic empowerment" is somewhat of a misnomer, therefore, because it covers empowerment of any member of the designated groups, regardless of race.  It is quota-based, with specific required outcomes. By a relatively complex scoring system, which allows for some flexibility in the manner in which each company meets its legal commitments, each company is required to meet minimum requirements in terms of representation by previously disadvantaged groups. The matters covered include equity ownership, representation at employee and management level (up to board of director level), procurement from black-owned businesses and social investment programs, amongst others.
*[[Southeast Asia]]. In countries such as [[Indonesia]], affirmative action programs give natives preference over [[Han Chinese]] who have immigrated into the country.
*[[United Kingdom]]. Positive Discrimination is unlawful in the UK and quotas/selective systems are not permitted.  A singular exception to this is a provision made under the [[1998]] [[Good Friday Agreement]] which requires that the [[Police Service of Northern Ireland]] recruit equal numbers of [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]]s and non Catholics.


==="Consultations"===
Another, more indirect form of affirmative action works through "consultations", whereby institutions such as [[school]]s or health-care facilities are viewed as centred on the majority culture, and therefore consultation with other ethnic groups are specified as a remedy. This can cause accusations of double-standards, as in practice representatives of all ethnic groups ''except the majority group'' receive consultation on institutional workings. Proponents discount this as being irrelevant, as they claim consultation with the majority group is pointless, as the institution's management is centered on their culture anyway..


===See also===
* [[Race and intelligence]]
* [[Equality of opportunity vs equality of results]]
* [[Jewish quota]] (historically restricting number of Jews)
* [[Malaysian New Economic Policy]]
* [[Legacy preferences]]
* [[Reservation in India]]
* [[minority groups]]
* [[minority rights]]
* [[women's rights]]

==Notes==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/affirmative-action/ Affirmative Action] at the [http://plato.stanford.edu/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]
* [http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/meta/long_68184.htm US Census Bureau: Definition of Race]

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Social inequality]]
[[Category:Social justice]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination]]
[[Category:Anti-racism]]

[[af:Regstellende aksie]]
[[de:Quotenregelung]]
[[es:Acción afirmativa]]
[[fr:Discrimination positive]]
[[he:העדפה מתקנת]]
[[hu:Pozitív diszkrimináció]]
[[nl:Rechtstellende actie]]
[[ja:積極的差別是正措置]]
[[pt:Ação afirmativa]]
[[sr:Афирмативна акција]]
[[fi:Positiivinen syrjintä]]
[[sv:Kvotering]]
[[ta:சீர்திருத்த செயலாக்கம்]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>