<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20170617202214|786182350" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="27139763" pageid="27139763" ns="0" title="Disability hate crime"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-09-11T06:31:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{essay-like|date=April 2010}}
{{cleanup-rewrite|date=September 2013}}
}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{Disability}}
'''Disability hate crime''' is a form of [[hate crime]] arising from the hostility of the perpetrator towards the [[disability]], or perceived disability, of the victim, or because of their perceived connection to disability. It is often viewed politically as a logical extreme of [[ableism]] (sometimes known in the UK by the disputed word "disablism"), carried through into criminal acts against the person. This phenomenon can take many forms, from [[verbal abuse]] and [[intimidation|intimidatory behaviour]] to [[vandalism]], [[assault]], or even [[murder]]. Disability hate crimes may take the form of one-off incidents, or may represent systematic abuse which continues over periods of weeks, months or even years.

Disability hate crime may occur between strangers who have never met, between acquaintances or within the family. The two key requirements for an act to be called a "disability hate crime" are that it is motivated in part or whole by prejudice against someone because of disability; and second, that the act is actually a crime.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Sherry (2010) "Disability Hate Crimes: Does Anyone Really Hate Disabled People?" Ashgate, London&lt;/ref&gt;

== Recognition==
[[Ken Macdonald|Sir Ken Macdonald, QC]], the then [[Director of Public Prosecutions (England and Wales)|Director of Public Prosecutions for England and Wales]] stated in a speech to the [[Bar Council]] in October 2008 that "I am on record as saying that it is my sense that disability hate crime is very widespread. I have said that it is my view that at the lower end of the spectrum there is a vast amount not being picked up. I have also expressed the view that the more serious disability hate crimes are not always being prosecuted as they should be. This is a scar on the conscience of criminal justice. And all bodies and all institutions involved in the delivery of justice, including my own, share the responsibility." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cps.gov.uk/legal/d_to_g/disability_hate_crime_/#a16|title=Error 404 (page not found): The Crown Prosecution Service|publisher=|accessdate=29 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legal status==
In the [[United States of America|United States]], the ''[[Matthew Shepard and James Byrd Jr. Hate Crimes Prevention Act]]'' of 2009 expanded the [[Hate crimes in the United States#Federal prosecution of hate crimes|1969 United States federal hate-crime law]] to include crimes motivated by a victim's actual or perceived disability.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/10/28/obama-signs-billion-defense-policy/ Obama Signs Defense Policy Bill That Includes 'Hate Crime' Legislation] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091030123045/http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/10/28/obama-signs-billion-defense-policy/ |date=2009-10-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[United Kingdom|UK]], disability hate crime is regarded as an aggravating factor under Section 146 of the [[Criminal Justice Act 2003]], allowing a heavier tariff to be used in sentencing than the crime might draw without the hate elements. Section 146 states that the sentencing provisions apply if:
:(a) that, at the time of committing the offence, or immediately before or after doing so, the offender demonstrated towards the victim of the offence hostility based on—
::(i) the sexual orientation (or presumed sexual orientation) of the victim, or
::(ii) a disability (or presumed disability) of the victim, or
:(b) that the offence is motivated (wholly or partly)—
::(i) by hostility towards persons who are of a particular sexual orientation, or
::(ii) by hostility towards persons who have a disability or a particular disability.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/ukpga_20030044_en_14#pt12-ch1-pb1-l1g145 Sections 145 and 146 of the Criminal Justice Act 2003].&lt;/ref&gt;

The test in Section 146 is deliberately one for evidence of 'hostility' rather than 'hatred' as the seriousness of the offence was considered to justify the application of a less-strict test.

== Crime recording ==
The historical failure of police forces, prosecutors and some social care organizations to treat disability hate crime as a serious issue, an echo of previous failures over other forms of hate crime, particularly racial and [[Violence against LGBT  people|LGBT-focused hate crimes]], has led to chronic under-reporting. This under-reporting is both pre-emptive, through a widespread belief within the disabled community that they will not be treated seriously by law enforcement, and post-facto, where police forces investigate the crime as non hate-based and record it as such.

The UK [[Crown Prosecution Service]]'s Annual Hate Crime Report,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cps.gov.uk/publications/prosecution/disability.html|title=The CPS : Disability hate crime|publisher=|accessdate=29 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; shows that 11,624 cases of racial or religious hate crime were prosecuted in England and Wales in 2009 with 10,690 leading to successful convictions. By contrast only 363 prosecutions and 299 convictions were for disability hate crimes.

The UK charity [[Scope (charity)|Scope]] has conducted research into the prevalence and experience of disability hate crime, summarizing their findings and those of other disability groups in the report ''Getting Away With Murder'' &lt;ref&gt;http://www.scope.org.uk/About-Us/Research-and-Policy/Publication-directory/Getting-away-with-murder&lt;/ref&gt;  Katharine Quarmby, who wrote the report and was the first British journalist to investigate disability hate crime, has also written a book on the matter.&lt;ref name=Quarmby&gt;Quarmby, Katharine. "Scapegoat: Why we are failing disabled people." ''Portobello'', 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Perceived vulnerability ==
The treatment of disability hate crimes has been affected by the perception of disabled people as inherently [[vulnerability|vulnerable]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2014-09-16/young-victim-blaming-at-its-very-worst/5745346|title=Disability and murder: victim blaming at its very worst|work=ABC News|accessdate=29 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is a multi-faceted issue. Unfounded application of the 'vulnerable' label to a disabled person is considered a form of infantilization, a type of ableism in which disabled people are regarded as childlike, rather than as functioning adults.{{Citation needed|date=December 2013}} The use of this label also frequently represents a failure to distinguish between the victim of the crime and the situation they found themselves facing. {{clarify|date=February 2015}}

Perceptions of [[social vulnerability|vulnerability]] can also lead to the perception that the victim is partially or entirely responsible for the crime. For example, a disabled person may be perceived as having been at fault due to being alone after dark, i.e. engaged in risky behaviour. This pattern of [[victim blaming]] has also appeared in the prosecution of rape and other sexual crimes.

On the other hand, it has been suggested that the vulnerability of victims is a key factor in all crimes. It has been applied to wide variety of scenarios, including people working at night or handling large amounts of money.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Sherry (2010) Disability Hate Crimes: Does anyone really hate disabled people? Ashgate, London&lt;/ref&gt; This implies that the issue of vulnerability is more complex than some advocates {{who|date=February 2015}} have argued. If it is a factor in all crimes, it then becomes necessary to adopt a contextual perspective without regarding disability as intrinsically vulnerable. {{citation needed|date=September 2013}}

The Crown Prosecution Service has issued guidance to its prosecutors reminding them that 'vulnerable' should only be used as a description of a person within the precise legal meaning of the term - for instance, as defined in section 16 of the Youth Justice and Criminal Evidence Act 1999.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cps.gov.uk/legal/d_to_g/disability_hate_crime_ Guidance on the distinction between vulnerability and hostility in the context of crimes committed against disabled people&lt;/ref&gt;

{{incomplete|date=September 2013}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Disability|Discrimination|Criminal justice}}
*[[Ableism]]
*[[Disability abuse]]
*[[Mate crime]]
*[[Sagamihara stabbings]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{abuse}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hate Crime}}
[[Category:Hate crime]]
[[Category:Disability in law]]
[[Category:Crime by type]]
[[Category:Abuse]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>