<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20110903141404|448228030" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="27139763" pageid="27139763" ns="0" title="Disability hate crime"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-09-22T08:45:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|essay-like=April 2010|intromissing=April 2010|original research=April 2010}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{Disability}}
'''Disability hate crime''' is [[hate crime]] arising from the hostility of the perpetrator towards the [[disability]], or perceived disability, of the victim, or because of their perceived connection to disability. It represents [[Disablism]] carried through into criminal acts against the person.

== Forms of Disability Hate Crime ==

'''Disability hate crime''' can take many forms, from verbal abuse and intimidatory behaviour to [[vandalism]], [[assault]], or even [[murder]]. Disability hate crimes may be one-off incidents, or systematic abuse that may continue over periods of weeks, months or even years. Disability hate crime may occur between strangers who have never met, between acquaintances or within the family.

== Recognition of Disability Hate Crime ==

Disability hate crime is currently one of the least recognised forms of hate crime. [[Ken Macdonald|Sir Ken Macdonald, QC]], the then [[Director of Public Prosecutions (England and Wales)|Director of Public Prosecutions for England and Wales]] stated in a speech to the [[Bar Council]] in October 2008 that "I am on record as saying that it is my sense that disability hate crime is very widespread. I have said that it is my view that at the lower end of the spectrum there is a vast amount not being picked up. I have also expressed the view that the more serious disability hate crimes are not always being prosecuted as they should be. This is a scar on the conscience of criminal justice. And all bodies and all institutions involved in the delivery of justice, including my own, share the responsibility." &lt;ref&gt;http://www.cps.gov.uk/legal/d_to_g/disability_hate_crime_/#a16&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legal Status of Disability Hate Crime ==

In the [[United States of America|United States]], the ''[[Matthew Shepard Act]]'', expanded the [[Hate crimes in the United States#Federal prosecution of hate crimes|1969 United States federal hate-crime law]] to include crimes motivated by a victim's actual or perceived disability.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/10/28/obama-signs-billion-defense-policy/ Obama Signs Defense Policy Bill That Includes 'Hate Crime' Legislation]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[United Kingdom|UK]], disability hate crime is regarded as an aggravating factor under Section 146 of the [[Criminal Justice Act 2003]], allowing a heavier tariff to be used in sentencing than the crime might draw without the hate elements. Section 146 states that the sentencing provisions apply if:
:(a) that, at the time of committing the offence, or immediately before or after doing so, the offender demonstrated towards the victim of the offence hostility based on—
::(i) the sexual orientation (or presumed sexual orientation) of the victim, or
::(ii) a disability (or presumed disability) of the victim, or
:(b) that the offence is motivated (wholly or partly)—
::(i) by hostility towards persons who are of a particular sexual orientation, or
::(ii) by hostility towards persons who have a disability or a particular disability.^ Sections 145 and 146 of the Criminal Justice Act 2003&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/ukpga_20030044_en_14#pt12-ch1-pb1-l1g145 Sections 145 and 146 of the Criminal Justice Act 2003].&lt;/ref&gt;

The test in Section 146 is deliberately one for evidence of 'hostility' rather than 'hatred' as the seriousness of the offence was considered to justify the application of a less-strict test.

== Disability Hate Crime and Crime Recording ==

The historical failure of police forces, prosecutors and some social care organizations to treat Disability Hate Crime as a serious issue, an echo of previous failures over other forms of hate crime, particularly racial and LGBT-focused hate crimes, has led to chronic under-reporting. This under-reporting is both pre-emptive, through a widespread belief within the disabled community that they will not be treated seriously by law enforcement, and post-facto, where police forces investigate the crime as non hate-based and record it as such.

The UK Crown Prosecution Service's Annual Hate Crime Report&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cps.gov.uk/publications/prosecution/disability.html&lt;/ref&gt;, shows that 11,624 cases of racial or religious hate crime were prosecuted in England and Wales in 2009 with 10,690 leading to successful convictions. By contrast only 363 prosecutions and 299 convictions were for Disability Hate Crimes.

The UK charity [[Scope (charity)|Scope]] has conducted research into the prevalence and experience of Disability hate crime, summarizing their findings and those of other disability groups in the report ''Getting Away With Murder'' &lt;ref&gt;http://www.scope.org.uk/sites/default/files/pdfs/Campaigns_policy/Scope_Hate_Crime_Report.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  Katharine Quarmby, who wrote the report and was the first British journalist to investigate disability hate crime, has also written a book on the matter.&lt;ref name=Quarmby&gt;Quarmby, Katharine. "Scapegoat: Why we are failing disabled people." ''Portobello'', 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

== 'Vulnerability' ==

Prosecution of disability hate crimes has faced problems caused by the predominant perception of disabled people as inherently 'vulnerable'. This is a multi-faceted issue. Unthinking application of the 'vulnerable' label to a disabled person is itself a form of infantilization, a widely recognised form of disablism in which disabled people are regarded, or disregarded, as child-like rather than as functioning adults with their own opinions. Secondly the use of the 'vulnerable' label frequently represents a failure to distinguish between the victim of the crime and the situation they found themselves facing. The CPS has found it necessary to issue guidance to its prosecutors reminding them that 'vulnerable' should only be used as a description of a person within the precise legal meaning of, for instance, section 16 of the Youth Justice and Criminal Evidence Act 1999&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cps.gov.uk/legal/d_to_g/disability_hate_crime_ Guidance on the distinction between vulnerability and hostility in the context of crimes committed against disabled people&lt;/ref&gt; Further to this, perceptions of 'vulnerability' can also lead to the perception that the victim is responsible for the crime, through reckless behaviour, rather than the perpetrator. For example a disabled person may be perceived as being engaged in risky behaviour by being out alone after dark. The parallels between this pattern of blame-shifting onto the victim and earlier manifestations of similar behaviour in the prosecution of rape and other sexual crimes are readily apparent.

==References==
{{Portalbox|Disability|Discrimination|Criminal justice}}
{{Reflist|2}}

{{abuse}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hate Crime}}
[[Category:Hate crime]]
[[Category:Disability]]
[[Category:Crime by type]]
[[Category:Abuse]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>