<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041104143229|7097824" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1073739" pageid="1073739" ns="0" title="Neurodiversity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-04T14:32:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">Neurodiversity is a concept that atypical neurological wiring is a normal human difference that is to be tolerated and respected as any other human difference. The concept of neurodiversity was created by autistic individuals who believe that autism is not a disorder but a part of who they are and that curing them would be the same as killing them and replacing them with different people.

==Response to Prejudice==

The term neurodiversity is usually used as a statement against prejudice and bigotry towards autism. This could include any of the following:
* Intolerant attitudes toward autistic behavior that may be perceived as odd or unusual.
* Intolerance toward difficulties autistic people often have.
* Discrimination against people for being autistic or because of autistic traits or behaviors.
* Lack of accommodations for difficulties associated with autism.
* Attitude that autistics are inferior to [[Neurotypical]] people; or that there is something wrong with being autistic; or that autism is a disease that needs to be cured.
* Institutions designed without consideration of autistics (for example: schools with heavy demand on social skills that may be hard for autistics).
* Barriers to participation in society due to difficulties associated with autism that could have been accommodated (for example, a technically competent autistic person may lose a job because of social awkwardness or may never get past the interview stage).
* Lack of protection for autistics in equal employment opportunity legislation.

==Who are the proponents?==

Most supporters of neurodiversity are anti-cure autistics who are engaged in civil rights advocacy. Many parents of autistic children also support neurodiversity and the view that autism is a unique way of being, rather than a disease to be cured. Such parents value their children's individuality and want to allow their children to develop naturally.

==Neurodiversity Art==

[http://www.autistics.org/pride/card.html autistics.org virtual greeting cards] celebrate neurodiversity.

==Opposing Views==

Most opponents of neurodiversity are pro-cure groups that include some parents of autistic children. Such groups view autism as a disease and argue that accepting a child's autism as an intrinsic part of the child's personality would be similar to accepting a child with cancer without a desire to cure cancer. They believe that it is unfair to characterize the desire to cure autism as bigotry.

==See Also==

* [[Controversies in autism]]
* [[Autism]]
* [[Autistic culture]]
* [[Asperger_syndrome]]
* [[Neurotypical]]

==External Links==

[http://www.neurodiversity.com/ www.neurodiversity.com]

[http://www.neurodiversitynow.net/ www.neurodiversitynow.net/]

{{stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>