<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051111161735|28034426" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1073739" pageid="1073739" ns="0" title="Neurodiversity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T16:20:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Neurodiversity''' is a concept that atypical neurological wiring ([[neurodivergent]]) is a normal human difference that is to be tolerated and respected as any other human difference. The concept of neurodiversity was created by some autistic individuals and people with [[Autistic spectrum|related conditions]], who believe that [[autism]] is not a disorder, but a part of who they are, and that curing autistic people would be the same as destroying their original personalities and replacing them with different people. However, others have adopted other terms, such as dyslexic, dyspraxic and hyperactive. &lt;!--Huh? Last sentence does not make sense and needs to be cleaned up/explained --&gt;

==Views on prejudice==

The term neurodiversity is usually used as a statement against perceived [[prejudice]] and [[bigotry]] towards autism, which has been claimed to be the following by neurodiversity proponents:
* Intolerant attitudes toward autistic behavior that may be perceived as odd or unusual.
* Intolerance toward difficulties autistic people often have. 
* [[Discrimination]] against people for being autistic or because of autistic traits or behaviors.
* Lack of accommodations for difficulties associated with autism.
* Attitude that autistics are inferior to [[Neurotypical]] people.
* Belief that autism is a disease that needs to be cured or that there is something wrong with being autistic.
* Institutions designed without consideration of autistics (for example: schools with heavy demand on social skills that may be hard for autistics).
* Barriers to participation in society due to difficulties associated with autism that could have been accommodated (for example, a technically competent autistic person may lose a job because of social awkwardness or may never get past the interview stage).
* Lack of protection for autistics in [[equal opportunity|equal employment opportunity]] legislation.

==Proponents==

Most supporters of neurodiversity are anti-cure autistics, who are engaged in advocacy. In addition, some parents of autistic children also support neurodiversity and the view that autism is a unique way of being, rather than a disease to be cured. Such parents say they value their children's individuality and want to allow their children to develop naturally. According to proponents, autistics may need therapies only to cure [[comorbid]] conditions, or to develop some inadequate skills. Forcing autistics to act as desired, or trying get rid of autistic neurological wiring is condemned. The proponents think that if autistics face more difficulties in life, the source are the society's institutions and habits, not autism itself.

==Opposing views==

Because autistic people usually have some challenges in life, there are some people who think finding a cure for autism would be in the best interest of autistics. People who are interested in a cure for autism are predominantly neurotypical individuals; including physicians, therapists and parents of autistic children, who believe the "benefits" of the unique, and arguably, rewarding subjectivity experienced by the autistic is not worth the social and functional strains entailed. These people believe a cure for autism is the best way to solve the problems of autistics, and see it as unfair to characterize the desire to cure autism as bigotry. [http://www.asatonline.org/resources/library/moms_perspective.html] [http://wampum.wabanaki.net/archives/001574.html] [http://www.sarnet.org/ltr/weintraub1-05.htm]

==History of the term ==

The first citation of the term "neurodiversity" is generally held to have occurred in an essay by [[Judy Singer]]: 

Judy Singer, "'Why can't you be normal for once in your life?'" in Disability Discourse, Mairian Corker ed., Open University Press, [[February 1]], [[1999]]) where it is used to describe a post modernist critique and addition to the social cleavages of class, gender, race and so on. 

However, Judy Singer actually first used this term in her Honours Thesis, written in 1996-7 and presented in 1998. 

Singer, J (1998) "''Odd People In: The Birth of Community Amongst People on the Autistic Spectrum: A personal exploration of a New Social Movement based on Neurological Diversity''" Faculty of Humanities and Social Science University of Technology, Sydney, 1998.

Judy Singer wrote: 
''For me, the significance of the Autistic Spectrum lies in its call for and anticipation of a Politics of Neurodiversity. The Neurologically Different represent a new addition to the familiar political categories of  class / gender / race  and will augment the insights of the Social Model of Disability.''
''The rise of Neurodiversity takes postmodern fragmentation one step further. Just as the postmodern era sees every once too solid belief melt into air, even our most taken-for granted assumptions: that we all more or less see, feel, touch, hear, smell, and sort information, in more or less the same way, (unless visibly disabled) are being dissolved.
'' (pp 12-13)

Judy Singer believes she coined the term, as she had done extensive literature and internet searches, and  had not come up with the term anywhere. Nor was it mentioned in any of the Autistic egroups ANI, InLv, Autinet that she was a member of. 

Since the idea was meant to bring together the insights of socio-biology/evolutionary psychology and sociology/ disability studies in a positive synthesis, it's unlikely that anyone else would have thought of it since sociologists and disability activists abhor sociobiology. Judy Singer talked about the politics and sociology of neurodiversity on the InLv forum for Autistics at the time,  and it may have spread from there. Judy Singer knows that Jane Meyerding asked her for (and she gave) permission to use the term on her website  [http://mjane.zolaweb.com/diff.html#F8]. 

A print citation is given for the Coventry Evening Telegraph (U.K.) ([[January 14|Jan. 14th]] [[2004]] )with reference to the Coventry and Warwickshire Neurodiversity Group who define the term thus:

"Neurodiversity is a word that has been around since autistic people started putting sites on the internet. It has since been expanded to include not just people who are known as "autistics and cousins", but to express the idea that a diversity of ways of human thinking is a good thing, and [[dyslexia|dyslexic]], autistic, [[ADHD]], [[dyspraxia|dyspraxic]] and [[Tourette syndrome|tourettes people]] to name but a few all have some element in common not being neurotypical in the way our brains work."

http://www.geocities.com/CapitolHill/7138/rights/neurodiversity.htm

Whilst the term most appears to have originated within the online [[autistic community]], its usage has spread outside to a more general meaning sometimes hotly disputed between its proponents as to whether it is inclusive of people with conditions like Cerebral Palsy, Parkinsons Disease, Multiple Sclerosis etc. Whilst others prefer to confine it to the invisible conditions such as those outlined by the Developmental Adult Neurodiversity Association in the UK 

http://www.danda.org.uk/

Certainly the term has been eagerly sought amongst top level domain name registrations, with [http://www.neurodiversity.com neurodiversity.com] and [http://www.neurodiversity.info neurodiversity.info] being examples, and there is no doubt that the term has seen a boost with the New York Times article by [[Amy Harmon]] 

Amy Harmon, "The Disability Movement Turns to Brains," The New York Times, [[May 9]], 2004

==See also==

*'''Topics related to neurodiversity'''
** [[Autistic community]]
** [[Autism rights movement]]
** [[Linguicism]]
** [[Neurotypical]]
** [[Autistic culture]]
*'''Topics in autism in general'''
** [[Asperger's syndrome]]
** [[Controversies in autism]]

==External links==
*'''Supporting Views'''
** [http://neurodiversity.com Neurodiversity.com] 'honoring the variety of human wiring'
** [http://www.aspies.co.uk Aspies.co.uk] site about AS - 'I don't believe aspies should be "cured" or forced to be "normal"'
** [http://www.celebrateautismtoday.org Celebrate Autism Today] "Autism is a difference, not a disease."
** [http://www.wordspy.com/words/neurodiversity.asp Word Spy on Neurodiversity] The Word Spy discusses the emerging concept of neurodiversity
** [http://www.neurodiversitynow.net Neurodiversity Now] Essays and a link to a livejournal discussion
*'''Opposing Views'''
** [http://www.asatonline.org ASAT] The Association for Science in Autism Treatment 
** [http://www.feat.org FEAT] Families for Early Autism Treatment, a parent run pro cure site.
** [http://www.cureautismnow.org Cure Autism Now] The Cure Autism Now Foundation
[[Category:Autism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>