<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181121010059|869887499" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1073739" pageid="1073739" ns="0" title="Neurodiversity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-21T01:07:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Neurodiversity''' is an approach to [[learning]] and [[mental health]] that argues various [[neurological condition]]s are the result of normal [[Human genome#Genomic variation in humans|variations in the human genome]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.diva-portal.org/smash/get/diva2:457919/FULLTEXT01.pdf|title=Autism as a Natural Human Variation: Reflections on the Claims of the Neurodiversity Movement|publisher=Linköping University|accessdate=November 5, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; "Neurodiversity" is a [[portmanteau]] of "neurological" and "diversity" that originated in the late 1990s as a challenge to prevailing views of certain neurological conditions as being inherently [[pathological]], instead asserting that neurological differences should be recognized and respected as a social category on par with [[gender]], [[ethnicity]], [[sexual orientation]], or disability status.

The neurodiversity movement describes itself as an international [[civil rights movements|civil rights movement]], of which the [[autism rights movement]] is its most influential submovement. Citing the classic legal maxim, "[[Nothing About Us Without Us]]", the movement promotes self-advocacy of its members. Neurodiversity advocates promote support systems (such as inclusion-focused services, accommodations, communication and assistive technologies, occupational training, and independent living support)&lt;ref name="ASAN"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://autisticadvocacy.org/policy-advocacy/position-statements/|title=Position Statements|publisher=Autistic Self Advocacy Network|accessdate=April 21, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; that allow those who are "non-neurotypical" to live their lives as they are, rather than being coerced or forced to adopt what neurodiversity proponents see as uncritically accepted ideas of normality, or to conform to a clinical ideal.&lt;ref name="Syracuse"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://neurodiversitysymposium.wordpress.com/what-is-neurodiversity/|title=What is Neurodiversity?|publisher=National Symposium on Neurodiversity at Syracuse University|year=2011|accessdate=October 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Neurodiversity frames [[autism spectrum|autism]], dyslexia, and other neurological conditions as natural human variations rather than pathologies or disorders, and rejects the idea that neurological differences need to be (or can be) [[cure]]d, instead believing them to be authentic forms of human [[diversity (politics)|diversity]], self-expression, and being.

==Terminology==
According to the 2011 National Symposium on Neurodiversity held at [[Syracuse University]], neurodiversity is:

{{quote|... a concept where neurological differences are to be recognized and respected as any other human variation. These differences can include those labeled with Dyspraxia, Dyslexia, Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, Dyscalculia, Autistic Spectrum, Tourette Syndrome, and others.&lt;ref name="Syracuse"/&gt;}}

==Autism rights movement==
{{further|Autism rights movement}}
The [[autism rights movement]] (ARM) is a [[social movement]] within the neurodiversity movement that encourages autistic people, their caregivers and society to adopt a position of neurodiversity, accepting autism as a variation in functioning rather than a [[mental disorder]] to be cured.&lt;ref name="Solomon"&gt;{{cite news |work=New York |title=The autism rights movement |last=Solomon |first=Andrew |date=2008-05-25 |accessdate=2008-05-27 |url=http://nymag.com/news/features/47225/| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080527025140/http://nymag.com/news/features/47225/| archivedate= 27 May 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The ARM advocates a variety of goals including a greater acceptance of autistic behaviors;&lt;ref name=AAP&gt;[http://www.taaproject.com/about-us/mission-statement/ Mission Statement.] Autism Acceptance Project. Retrieved on 2008-11-24.&lt;/ref&gt; therapies that teach autistic individuals coping skills rather than therapies focused on imitating behaviors of [[neurotypical]] peers;&lt;ref name=AFF&gt;[http://www.aspiesforfreedom.com/ Mission Statement.] Aspies for Freedom. Retrieved on 2008-11-24.&lt;/ref&gt; the creation of social networks and events that allow autistic people to socialize on their own terms;&lt;ref name=Autreat&gt;[http://ani.autistics.org/autreat.html Autism Network International presents Autreat.] (2008-05-23) AIN.&lt;/ref&gt; and the recognition of the Autistic community as a minority group.&lt;ref name=UN&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.prweb.com/releases/2004/11/prweb179444.htm |title=Declaration From the Autism Community That They Are a Minority Group |date =2004-11-18|publisher=PRWeb, Press Release Newswire |accessdate=2007-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Autism rights or neurodiversity advocates believe that the autism spectrum is genetic and should be accepted as a natural expression of the human genome. This perspective is distinct from two other views: the mainstream perspective that autism is caused by a genetic defect and should be addressed by targeting the genes that cause autism; and the perspective that autism is caused by environmental factors and could be cured by addressing environmental causes.&lt;ref name="Solomon"/&gt;

Many autistic supporters of autism rights describe themselves through words that emphasize the condition as an intrinsic part of their identity, such as "autistic", or "aspie" for those with [[Asperger syndrome]].&lt;ref name="Ortega2009"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Ortega|first1=Francisco|title=The Cerebral Subject and the Challenge of Neurodiversity|journal=BioSocieties|date=December 2009|volume=4|issue=4|pages=425–445|doi=10.1017/S1745855209990287|url=http://www.palgrave-journals.com/biosoc/journal/v4/n4/full/biosoc200938a.html|language=en|issn=1745-8552}}&lt;/ref&gt; This contrasts to a general recommendation by [[United States|US]] disability advocacy organizations{{who|date=July 2018}} for the use of [[person-first language]] when referring to a person with a medical or mental condition or disability, which emphasizes the ''person'' with the condition, who has, rather than is defined by it.&lt;ref&gt;[[BusinessWeek]] (letter to the editor), Issues 3059–3062, 1988 [https://books.google.com/books?id=tGA1AAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22people-first+language%22&amp;dq=%22people-first+language%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=SaLOTKWwAYeBOoS1jOcB&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwBA];
''Supportive housing needs of elderly and disabled persons: hearing before the Subcommittee on Housing and Urban Affairs of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, United States Senate, One Hundred First Congress, first session on S. 566 ... the National Affordable Housing Act, June 2, 1989, Volumes 22–23'': "All references to 'handicapped individuals' in the Act must be changed to 'people with disabilities{{'"}} – We join with many of our fellow advocacy organizations in emphasizing the importance of using 'people first' language throughout the Act."&lt;/ref&gt; There are accepted general arguments for the use of 'disabled person' similarly based on the [[social model of disability]] that are recognised in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] and elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/3708576.stm|author=Damon Rose |title=Don't call me handicapped!|date=4 October 2004|work=[[BBC]]|accessdate=30 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.disabilityartsonline.org.uk/why-we-are-disabled-people-not-people-with-disabilities|author=Colin Cameron|title=Why we are disabled people, not people with disabilities|date=2 July 2015|accessdate=30 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Acceptance perspective===
Members of the various autism rights organizations view autism as a way of life rather than as a disease and thus advocate acceptance over a search for a cure.&lt;ref name=Harmon&gt;Harmon, Amy. [https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?sec=health&amp;res=9C07E0D9143CF93AA35756C0A9629C8B63 Neurodiversity Forever; The Disability Movement Turns to Brains.] ''The New York Times'', May 9, 2004.  Retrieved on 2007-11-08.&lt;/ref&gt; Some advocates believe that common therapies for the behavioral and language differences associated with autism, like [[applied behavior analysis]], are not only misguided but also unethical.&lt;ref&gt;[[Michelle Dawson|Dawson, Michelle]]. [http://www.sentex.net/~nexus23/naa_aba.html The Misbehaviour of Behaviourists.] (2004-01-18). Retrieved on 2007-01-23.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''"acceptance perspective"'' endorsed by the movement is a view that [[autism spectrum|autism]] is not a disorder, but a normal occurrence—an alternate variation in brain wiring or a less common expression of the human genome.&lt;ref name="Harmon"/&gt; Advocates of this perspective believe that autism is a unique way of being that should be validated, supported and appreciated rather than shunned, discriminated against or eliminated.&lt;ref name="Harmon"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Gal&gt;{{cite news |author=Gal L |title=Who says autism's a disease? |work=Haaretz |date=2007-06-28 |url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/876283.html |accessdate=2007-07-16| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070701201936/http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/876283.html| archivedate= 1 July 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; They believe quirks and uniqueness of autistic individuals should be tolerated as the differences of any minority group should be tolerated and that efforts to eliminate autism should not be compared, for example, to curing cancer but instead to the antiquated notion of curing [[left-handedness]].&lt;ref name="Harmon"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Dawson&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.autistics.org/library/dawson.html|title=In Support of Michelle Dawson and Her Work|publisher=Autistics.org|accessdate=2012-03-21|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120215181832/http://archive.autistics.org/library/dawson.html|archivedate=2012-02-15|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ARM is a part of the larger disability rights movement, and as such adheres to the social model of disability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Waltz, M |title=Autism: A Social and Medical History |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |location=London |year=2013 |isbn=0-230-52750-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within this model, struggles faced by autistic people are viewed as discrimination rather than deficiencies.

===Advocacy===
According to Andrew Fenton and Tim Krahn, proponents of neurodiversity strive to reconceptualize autism and related conditions in society by the following measures: acknowledging that neurodiversity does not require a cure; changing the language from the current "condition, disease, disorder, or illness"-based nomenclature and "broaden[ing] the understanding of healthy or independent living"; acknowledging new types of autonomy; and giving non-neurotypical individuals more control over their treatment, including the type, timing, and whether there should be treatment at all.&lt;ref name="article"&gt;Fenton, Andrew, and Tim Krahn. [http://www.jemh.ca/issues/v2n2/documents/JEMH_V2N2_Theme_Article2_Neurodiversity_Autism.pdf "Autism, Neurodiversity and Equality Beyond the Normal" (PDF).] Journal of Ethics in Mental Health 2.2 (2007): 1-6. 10  November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2009 study&lt;ref name=Griffin&gt;{{cite journal|last=Griffin|first=Edward|author2=Pollak, David|title=Student experiences of neurodiversity in higher education: Insights from the BRAINHE project.|journal=Dyslexia|date=January 2009|volume=15|issue=1|pages=23–41|pmid=19140120|doi=10.1002/dys.383}}&lt;/ref&gt; by Edward Griffin and David Pollak separated 27 students (with autism, dyslexia, developmental coordination disorder, ADHD, and stroke), into two categories of self-view: "a 'difference' view—where neurodiversity was seen as a difference incorporating a set of strengths and weaknesses, or a 'medical/deficit' view—where neurodiversity was seen as a disadvantageous medical condition". They found that although all of the students reported uniformly difficult schooling careers involving exclusion, abuse, and bullying, those who viewed themselves from a difference view (41% of the study cohort) "indicated higher academic self-esteem and confidence in their abilities and many (73%) expressed considerable career ambitions with positive and clear goals".&lt;ref name=Griffin/&gt; Many of these students reported gaining this view of themselves through contact with neurodiversity advocates in online support groups.&lt;ref name=Griffin/&gt;

A 2013 online survey said this: "Such a deficit-as-difference conception of autism suggests the importance of harnessing autistic traits in developmentally beneficial ways, transcending a false dichotomy between celebrating differences and ameliorating deficit".&lt;ref name="Kapp"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kapp|first=Steven K.|date=January 2013|title=Deficit, difference, or both? Autism and neurodiversity.|journal=Developmental Psychology|volume=49|issue=1|pages=59–71|doi=10.1037/a0028353|pmid=22545843|author2=Gillespie-Lynch, Kristen|author3=Sherman, Lauren E.|author4=Hutman, Ted}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, German computer software giant SAP, seeking innovation that "comes from the edges", launched a recruitment drive for software testers specifically seeking autistic people. [[Freddie Mac]], the U.S. home financing firm, aimed its hiring campaign's second round of paid internships at autistic students.&lt;ref name=thinkingdifferently4june2013&gt;{{cite news |title=Thinking differently: Autism finds space in the workplace |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2013/06/04/us-autism-recruitment-idUSBRE9530KA20130604 |publisher=Reuters |date=4 June 2013 |first=Kate |last=Kelland |location=London, UK |accessdate=4 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==


The neurodiversity paradigm was initially embraced by individuals on the [[autism spectrum]],&lt;ref name=Jaarsma&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Jaarsma P, Welin S |title=Autism as a Natural Human Variation: Reflections on the Claims of the Neurodiversity Movement |journal=Health Care Anal |date=February 2011 |pmid=21311979 |doi=10.1007/s10728-011-0169-9 |url=http://www.imh.liu.se/avd_halsa_samhalle/filarkiv1/1.264263/JaarsmaWelin2011Autismasanaturalvariation.pdf |format=PDF |volume=20 |issue=1 |pages=20–30 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131101015957/http://www.imh.liu.se/avd_halsa_samhalle/filarkiv1/1.264263/JaarsmaWelin2011Autismasanaturalvariation.pdf |archivedate=2013-11-01 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; but subsequent groups have applied the concept to other developmental conditions such as [[attention deficit hyperactivity disorder|ADHD]],&lt;ref name="Woodford"&gt;Woodford, Gillian. [http://www.nationalreviewofmedicine.com/issue/2006/04_30/3_patients_practice05_8.html 'We Don't Need to be Cured' Autistics Say] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303202254/http://www.nationalreviewofmedicine.com/issue/2006/04_30/3_patients_practice05_8.html|date=2016-03-03}}. National Review of Medicine. Volume 3. No. 8. April 30, 2006. Retrieved February 23, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Speech disorder|developmental speech disorders]], dyslexia, [[developmental coordination disorder|dyspraxia]], [[dyscalculia]], [[Anomic aphasia|dysnomia]] and [[intellectual disability]]; mental health conditions such as [[bipolar disorder|bipolarity]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bphope.com/blog/on-neurodiversity/|title=On Neurodiversity|access-date=14 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = An Exploration Of The Neurodiversity Movement|url = http://radicalpsychology.org/vol7-1/boundy.html|website = radicalpsychology.org|accessdate = 2015-08-11|quote = Conducting a poll of what she calls her 'online tribe', other bipolar people participating in specialized listservs and chatrooms, Antonetta discovered that, like her, most responders like their minds and the gifts their bipolarity brings them.  One man she quotes says: "I choose not to look at bipolarity as an illness at all. In fact, I couldn't imagine myself as not being bipolar, nor would I want to be. The bipolar is a strong component of who I am, and I do not wish to be anyone else but me" (p. 89).  Another respondent wrote, "I feel, and cause others to feel ... Touched, the life of the imagination is the real life" (Antonetta, 2005, p.90).|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150601091803/http://radicalpsychology.org/vol7-1/boundy.html|archive-date = 2015-06-01|dead-url = yes|df = }}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[schizophrenia]],&lt;ref&gt;Morrice, Polly (January 29, 2006) [https://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/29/books/review/29morrice.html "Otherwise Minded"] ''The New York Times'', review of ''A Mind Apart: Travels in a Neurodiverse World''&lt;/ref&gt; [[schizoaffective disorder]], [[psychopathy|sociopathy]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = The Virtue of Sociopaths: how to appreciate the neurodiversity of sociopathy without becoming a victim|url = https://www.academia.edu/2034622/The_Virtue_of_Sociopaths_how_to_appreciate_the_neurodiversity_of_sociopathy_without_becoming_a_victim|accessdate = 2015-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[obsessive–compulsive disorder]], and [[Tourette syndrome]];&lt;ref name=Woodford/&gt;&lt;ref name='Mackenzie 2011-01-31'&gt;{{cite journal | title = Is our legal, health care and social support infrastructure neurodiverse enough? How far are the aims of the neurodiversity movement fulfilled for those diagnosed with cognitive disability and learning disability? | journal = Tizard Learning Disability Review | date = 2011-01-31 | first = Robin | last = Mackenzie |author2=John Watts | volume = 16 | issue = 1 | pages = 30–37| id =  | publisher= Pier Professional | quote = We recommend, therefore, that the term neurodiverse include the conditions ASD, ADHD, OCD, language disorders, developmental coordination disorder, dyslexia and Tourette's syndrome. | doi=10.5042/tldr.2011.0005}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the medical condition [[Parkinson's disease]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://journalofethics.ama-assn.org/2015/04/msoc1-1504.html|title=The Myth of the Normal Brain: Embracing Neurodiversity, Apr 15 - AMA Journal of Ethics (formerly Virtual Mentor)|website=journalofethics.ama-assn.org|accessdate=2015-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term neurodiversity represents a move away from the "mother-blaming"  [[refrigerator mother]] theories of the 20th century.&lt;ref name="genetics"&gt;Bumiller, Kristen. "The Geneticization of Autism: From New Reproductive Technologies to the Conception of Genetic Normalcy." Signs 34.4 (2009): 875-99. ''Chicago Journals''. University of Chicago Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term is attributed to Judy Singer, an Australian social scientist on the autism spectrum,&lt;ref name=Jaarsma/&gt; and it first appeared in print in an article by journalist Harvey Blume (which did not credit Singer)&lt;ref name=Solomon/&gt; in ''[[The Atlantic]]'' on September 30, 1998:&lt;ref name=BlumeAtlantic&gt;{{Cite news |author= Blume, Harvey |url= https://www.theatlantic.com/doc/199809u/neurodiversity |archive-url= https://archive.is/20130105003900/http://www.theatlantic.com/doc/199809u/neurodiversity |dead-url= yes |archive-date= January 5, 2013 |title= Neurodiversity |work= The Atlantic |date= September 30, 1998 |accessdate= November 7, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|Neurodiversity may be every bit as crucial for the human race as biodiversity is for life in general. Who can say what form of wiring will prove best at any given moment? Cybernetics and computer culture, for example, may favor a somewhat autistic cast of mind.&lt;ref name=BlumeAtlantic/&gt;}}

In a ''[[New York Times]]'' piece on June 30, 1997, Blume did not use the term "neurodiversity", but he did describe the foundation of the idea in the phrase "neurological pluralism":&lt;ref name=BlumeNYT&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7DC1F31F933A05755C0A961958260|author=Blume, Harvey|title=Autistics, freed from face-to-face encounters, are communicating in cyberspace|work=The New York Times|date=June 30, 1997|accessdate=November 8, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|"Yet, in trying to come to terms with an NT [&lt;nowiki/&gt;[[neurotypical]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;]-dominated world, autistics are neither willing nor able to give up their own customs. Instead, they are proposing a new social compact, one emphasizing neurological pluralism. ... The consensus emerging from the Internet forums and Web sites where autistics congregate [...] is that NT is only one of many neurological configurations -- the dominant one certainly, but not necessarily the best."&lt;ref name=BlumeNYT/&gt;}}

Blume was an early advocate who predicted the role the Internet would play in fostering the international neurodiversity movement, writing:&lt;ref name=BlumeMIT&gt;{{Cite web|author=Blume, Harvey|url=http://web.mit.edu/m-i-t/articles/index_blume.html|title="Autism &amp; The Internet" or "It's The Wiring, Stupid"|date=July 1, 1997|publisher=Media In Transition, Massachusetts Institute of Technology|accessdate=November 8, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|There is a political dimension to this bond with the Internet. A project called CyberSpace 2000 is devoted to getting as many people as possible in the autistic spectrum hooked up by the year 2000, reason being that "the Internet is an essential means for autistic people to improve their lives, because it is often the only way they can communicate effectively. ... The challenge we will all be increasingly confronted with, on-line and off, is, to look at ourselves differently than we have before, that is, to accept neurological diversity.&lt;ref name=BlumeMIT/&gt;}}

Some authors&lt;ref name=Solomon/&gt;&lt;ref name="article"/&gt; also credit the earlier work of autistic advocate [[Jim Sinclair (activist)|Jim Sinclair]], who was a principal early organizer of the international online autism community. Sinclair's 1993 speech, "Don't Mourn For Us",&lt;ref name=Sinclair&gt;Sinclair, Jim. [http://www.autreat.com/dont_mourn.html Don't Mourn For Us.] Autism Network International, n.d..  Retrieved on 2013-05-07.&lt;/ref&gt; mentioned that some parents considered their child's autism diagnosis as "the most traumatic thing that ever happened to them". Sinclair (who did not speak until the age of 12) addressed the communal grief parents felt by asking them to try to take the perspectives of autistic people themselves:
{{quote|Non-autistic people see autism as a great tragedy, and parents experience continuing disappointment and grief at all stages of the child's and family's life cycle. But this grief does not stem from the child's autism in itself. It is grief over the loss of the normal child the parents had hoped and expected to have ... There's no normal child hidden behind the autism. Autism is a way of being. It is pervasive; it colors every experience, every sensation, perception, thought, emotion, and encounter, every aspect of existence. It is not possible to separate the autism from the person—and if it were possible, the person you'd have left would not be the same person you started with. This is important, so take a moment to consider it: Autism is a way of being. It is not possible to separate the person from the autism.&lt;ref name=Sinclair/&gt;}}

The term "neurodiversity" has since been applied to other conditions and has taken on a more general meaning; for example, the [[Developmental Adult Neurodiversity Association]] (DANDA) in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] encompasses [[developmental coordination disorder]], [[attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder|ADHD]], [[Asperger's syndrome]] and related conditions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.danda.org.uk/ danda.org.uk]  DANDA website.  Retrieved on 6 January 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism ==
The concept of neurodiversity is controversial.&lt;ref name=Jaarsma /&gt; Those supporting the [[medical model of disability]] identify the mental differences associated with these conditions as disorders, deficits, and dysfunctions, intrinsic differences in functioning which cause impairments in many areas of life. From this point of view, the mental states that are encompassed by neurodiversity are medical conditions that can and should be treated.&lt;ref name="Pollak"&gt;Pollak, David. 2009. "Neurodiversity in Higher Education." John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.&lt;/ref&gt;

Author David Pollak sees neurodiversity as an inclusive term for the equality of all possible mental states. Still others reject the word because they think it sounds too medical.&lt;ref name="Pollak" /&gt;

The concept of neurodiversity as applied to [[autism]] is criticized for being skewed towards the "high-functioning" individuals of the autistic spectrum or those with milder forms of the condition. Those with "low-functioning" autism are often significantly impaired in their everyday functioning, and may not be able to function effectively with even the extensive use of advanced [[Assistive technology|assistive technologies]]. Because many of these low-functioning individuals are unable to communicate effectively to express their opinions and wishes, controversy surrounds the issue of who represents them and what represents their interests.&lt;ref name="MichaelFitzpatrick"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Fitzpatrick|first1=Michael|title=Why we should be cautious about celebrating autism|url=http://www.spiked-online.com/review_of_books/article/why-we-shouldnt-celebrate-autism/17468#.VxzY_nBWY7k|website=www.spiked-online.com|accessdate=24 April 2016|date=September 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sue Rubin]], an autistic woman and author who was the subject of the documentary ''[[Autism is a World]]'', favors a cure for the condition and asserts that while those with high-functioning autism tend to support the neurodiversity anti-cure position, those who have low-functioning autism generally hold the opposite opinion.&lt;ref name="Ortega2009" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Rubin|first1=Sue|title=Acceptance versus cure|url=http://www-cgi.cnn.com/CNN/Programs/presents/shows/autism.world/notebooks/sue/notebook.html|website=www-cgi.cnn.com|publisher=Cable News Network|accessdate=25 April 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130926031713/http://www-cgi.cnn.com/CNN/Programs/presents/shows/autism.world/notebooks/sue/notebook.html|archive-date=26 September 2013|dead-url=yes|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jaarsma and Welin wrote in 2011 that the "broad version of the neurodiversity claim, covering low-functioning as well as high-functioning autism, is problematic. Only a narrow conception of neurodiversity, referring exclusively to high-functioning autists, is reasonable."&lt;ref name=Jaarsma /&gt; They say that "higher functioning" individuals with autism may "not [be] benefited with such a psychiatric defect-based diagnosis ... some of them are being harmed by it, because of the disrespect the diagnosis displays for their natural way of being", but "think that it is still reasonable to include other categories of autism in the psychiatric diagnostics. The narrow conception of the neurodiversity claim should be accepted but the broader claim should not."&lt;ref name=Jaarsma /&gt;

Criticism has been levied against the "acceptance" position of neurodiversity advocates, with it being noted that even though the biomedical therapies that target the clinical features of, for example, autism and the conditions that may co-occur with it, do not amount to a complete cure, such treatments can still potentially significantly improve the everyday functioning and quality of life of those with these conditions. While such treatments require substantial investment and development and would not be available for application in the immediate future, they may provide greater benefit in the future and in the long-term.&lt;ref name="MichaelFitzpatrick" /&gt; Many of those who view autism as a disabling developmental disease consider that the acceptance perspective of neurodiversity insults the suffering of its patients and their families.&lt;ref name="Ortega2009" /&gt;  Biology professor [[Jerry Coyne]] says that in its extreme, neurodiversity wishes to deny medical treatment for any person with a mental condition, particularly autism, even if the person wants a medical treatment.&lt;ref name="Coyne"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Coyne |first1=Jerry |title=What do we do about “neurodiversity”? |url=https://whyevolutionistrue.wordpress.com/2015/06/23/what-do-we-do-about-neurodiversity/ |website=Why Evolution Is True |accessdate=1 October 2018 |date=23 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jonathan Mitchell (writer)|Jonathan Mitchell]], an [[autistic]] author and blogger who is a vocal opponent of the neurodiversity movement and an advocate for research for a cure for autism, criticizes the concept of neurodiversity for providing "simplistic solutions to hard problems" and trivializing the disabling aspects of autism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=White|first1=Mark|title=A different way of thinking|url=http://www.sbs.com.au/news/feature/different-way-thinking|website=News|accessdate=25 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; He considers his condition to have negatively affected his life, describing autism as having "prevented me from making a living or ever having a girlfriend. It's given me bad fine motor coordination problems where I can hardly write. I have an impaired ability to relate to people. I can't concentrate or get things done."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Hamilton|first1=Jon|title=Shortage of Brain Tissue Hinders Autism Research|url=https://www.npr.org/blogs/health/2013/02/04/170835708/shortage-of-brain-tissue-sets-autism-research-back|website=NPR|accessdate=10 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He describes neurodiversity as a "tempting escape valve" for many of the people who are on the autism spectrum; and commenting on the supposition of a general acceptance of neurodiversity by those on the spectrum, he says that "most persons with an autism-spectrum disorder have never expressed their opinions on someone's blog and never will". He states that neurodiversity has no solution for low-functioning autistics.&lt;ref name=Solomon /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Mitchell|first1=Jonathan|title=Neurodiversity: Just Say No - An Article by Jonathan Mitchell|url=http://www.jonathans-stories.com/non-fiction/neurodiv.html|website=www.jonathans-stories.com|accessdate=24 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also criticizes [[Temple Grandin]] for making generalizations about the condition and the experiences of those with it, saying that her generalizations trivialize his suffering.&lt;ref name=Osborne&gt;{{cite book|last1=Osborne|first1=Lawrence|title=American Normal : The Hidden World of Asperger Syndrome|date=2002|publisher=Copernicus|location=New York|isbn=978-0-387-95307-6|pages=114–115, 155, 158–159}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Due to these positions, Mitchell is one of the most controversial voices in the autistic blogosphere, and has been highly criticized by many members of the neurodiversity movement.&lt;ref name=Hayasaki2015&gt;{{cite web|last1=Hayasaki|first1=Erika|title=The Debate Over an Autism Cure Turns Hostile|url=http://www.newsweek.com/2015/02/27/one-activists-search-cure-his-autism-drawing-violent-backlash-306998.html|website=Newsweek|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Autistic Pride Day]]
* [[Disability rights movement]]
* [[Diversity training]]
* [[Mad Pride|Mad pride movement]]
* [[Psychiatric survivors movement]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|last=Armstrong|first=Thomas|title=Neurodiversity: Discovering the Extraordinary Gifts of Autism, ADHD, Dyslexia, and Other Brain Differences|year=2010|publisher=Da Capo Lifelong|location=Boston |isbn=978-0738213545|pages=288}}
* {{cite book|last=Armstrong|first=Thomas|title=Neurodiversity in the Classroom: Strength-Based Strategies to Help Students with Special Needs Succeed in School and Life|year=2012|publisher=Association for Supervision &amp; Curriculum Development|location=Alexandria, VA|isbn=978-1416614838|pages=188}}
* {{cite web|last=Silberman|first=Steve|title=Neurodiversity Rewires Conventional Thinking About Brains|url=https://www.wired.com/magazine/2013/04/neurodiversity/ |publisher=Wired|accessdate=7 May 2013}}
* {{cite book|last=Reitman|first=Harold|title=Aspertools: The Practical Guide for Understanding and Embracing Asperger's, Autism Spectrum Disorders, and Neurodiversity|year=2015|publisher=HCI Books|location=Deerfield Beach, FL|isbn=9780757318542|pages=240}}

== External links ==
* {{Wiktionary-inline|neurodiversity}}
* {{Wikiversity-inline|The Neurodiversity Movement}}

{{Pervasive developmental disorders}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Neurodiversity| ]]
[[Category:Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder]]
[[Category:Autism rights movement]]
[[Category:Bioethics]]
[[Category:Bipolar disorder]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Dyslexia]]
[[Category:Identity politics]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Medical sociology]]
[[Category:Obsessive–compulsive disorder]]
[[Category:Schizophrenia]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Sociological terminology]]
[[Category:Tourette syndrome]]
[[Category:Words and phrases introduced in 1998]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1990s]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>