<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051111092456|28011693" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8900" pageid="8900" ns="0" title="Discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T12:27:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">To '''discriminate''' is to make a distinction. There are several meanings of the word, including [[statistical discrimination]], or the actions of a [[circuit]] called a `discriminator`. This article addresses the most common colloquial sense of the word, ''invidious'' discrimination. That is, irrational social, [[race|racial]], [[religion|religious]], [[sex|sexual]], [[disability]], [[ethnicity|ethnic]] and [[ageism|age-related]] discrimination of people.

==Government sanctioned discrimination==
By virtue of establishing [[nationalism]] (as opposed to [[globalization| globalism]]) every government has formalized and supported discrimination. 

Examples of discrimination within countries include: [[apartheid]] in [[South Africa]]; institutionalized [[Racial segregation|racial segregation]] in the USA from the [[United States Civil War|Civil War]] through the [[1960s]]; the "Jewish problem" in [[Nazi Germany]]; and re-education camps in some [[communist]] countries. 

Many governments have attempted to control discrimination through [[civil rights]] legislation, [[equal opportunity]] laws and institutionalised policies of [[affirmative action]] (called [[reverse discrimination]] by its opponents).

Even in western, secular countries, governments practice discrimination. For example, governments may provide better treatment to citizens than to non-citizens. Unemployed citizens may receive welfare benefits funded by taxpayers, while unemployed non-citizens may be denied such benefits. Governments often have the power to forcefully expel non-citizens but cannot expel citizens. Discrimination based on citizenship status is not generally considered illegal.

==Religious discrimination==
[[Religious intolerance]] often manifests itself in discriminatory behaviours. During the [[Middle Ages]], in the [[Crusade]]s, [[Pope]]s, kings, and emperors tried to draw on Christian unity to defend their lands from some followers of [[Islam]], which was spreading along Europe's southern and eastern borders. Some [[Roman Catholic]] countries have historically persecuted dissenters, for example with the [[Spanish Inquisition]]. Some rulers of [[Protestant]] countries sponsored discrimination against [[Roman Catholic]]s. During [[Tudor dynasty|Tudor]] and [[House of Stuart|Stuart]] times, rulers of the [[United Kingdom]] persecuted both Catholics and non-Catholics at intervals for political reasons.

However, today, Muslims are widely faced job related discrimination in the West, particularly in the United Sates, following the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001.  This is termed "Sophisticated discrimination" where the act of discrimination is performed in a way that it cannot be proven easly. According to the [[EEOC]], since September 11, 2001, it has received more than 800 charge filings nationwide, alleging backlash discrimination by individuals who are or who are perceived to be Muslim, Arabic, Middle Eastern, South Asian or Sikh. The two most common issues alleged are harassment and discharge.

Another out of the ordinary example of discrimination against [[Muslim|Muslims]] is occurring in an extremely large context on very different platform.  The [[European Union]] leaders are openly declaring that [[Turkey]] is unqualified to be a full member of the institution despite meeting all of the requirements because of its "religious and ethnic differences". This has been stated by the leaders of France, Austria, Germany and the Vatican. To some, this is conceived to be a case of a largest religious discrimination against a nation of seventy million by a major international governmental organization.

Currently, Non-Muslims too are discriminated against under remaining few Islamic [[theocratic]] states. Jews and Christians have historically had fewer rights than Muslim citizens under Muslim states; non-Muslim [[monotheism|monotheists]] have been consigned to the status of [[dhimmi]]s in some cases. [[Marxism|Marxist]] states have discriminated against all religions at some time or another. This continues in [[North Korea]], [[China]] and [[Vietnam]], and many former [[Soviet]] republics. 

The Kingdom of [[Jordan]] forbids Jews from becoming citizens, although peoples of any other group are allowed to do so (law No. 6, sect. 3, of April 3, 1954; restated in law no. 7, sect. 2, of April 1, 1963). [[Saudi Arabia]] forbids non-Muslims from practising their religion in public, and clergy may not enter the country to lead ceremonies of other faiths. Christians asking Muslims to convert to Christianity have been persecuted and arrested; Muslims who have converted to Christianity have been executed as [[apostate]]s.  Fictional tales of Jews committing diabolic crimes are published by the state.  The article on [[discrimination against non-Muslims in Saudi Arabia]] discusses this subject in more depth.

According to reports from the U.S. Department of State, non-Muslims also suffer discrimination in many non-Arab [[Muslim]] nations. Separate articles discuss discrimination against non-Muslims in [[Status of religious freedom in Afghanistan|Afghanistan]], [[Status of religious freedom in Iran|Iran]], [[Status of religious freedom in Malaysia|Malaysia]], [[Status of religious freedom in Mauritania|Mauritania]], [[Status of religious freedom in Pakistan|Pakistan]] and [[Status of religious freedom in Sudan|Sudan]].

The State of [[Israel]] is often accused of discrimination against [[Palestinian]]s; this topic is discussed in the article on the [[Arab-Israeli conflict]].

Some [[New religious movement]]s often claim that they are discriminated for their non-conformist beliefs. They claim [[apostates]] of these movements are the ones carrying the discrimination.

Some others claim that non-religious people (atheists, agnostics, etc.) are subject to the most widespread religious discrimination.  During his 1988 Presidential campaign, [[George H.W. Bush]] stated that atheists should not be considered patriots or citizens.

Christians students are discriminated in schools publicly and privately. Names of clubs have been changed because the school systems claim that some part of the name or the symbolism it represents may offend other students, parents, or teachers. Students who are Muslim may be approached by another student who says, "Stupid Muslim. Go back to where to you came from and stop killing us" (meaning, the Americans).

==Ageism==

[[Ageism]] is discrimination against a person or group on the grounds of age. Although theoretically the word can refer to the discrimination against any age group, ageism usually comes in one of two forms: discrimination against [[youth]], and discrimination against the [[elderly]].

In many countries, companies refuse more or less openly to hire people above a
certain age despite the increasing lifespans and average age of the populace. The reasons for this range from vague feelings that younger people are more "dynamic" and create a positive image for the company, to more concrete concerns about regulations granting older employees higher salaries or other benefits without these expenses being fully justified by such employees' greater experience.

Some underage [[teenagers]] consider that they're victims of ageism—prejudice on the grounds of age—and that they should be treated more respectfully by adults and not as second-class citizens. Some complain that social [[stratification]] in age groups causes outsiders to incorrectly [[stereotype]] and generalize the group, for instance that all adolescents are equally immature, violent or rebellious, listen to rock or rap music and do [[drug]]s. Some have organized groups against ageism.

==The paradox of discrimination==
Many people assume that when there is discrimination, one group of people is given more favorable treatment than others.  This is not always the case. It is possible to have cases where it is not at all clear which group is given the more favorable treatment.

*Example: A country is under attack during wartime. The war is so ferocious that 80% of the combatants are killed. A law has been passed to forcefully conscript males between 18-24 years of age into the frontline, but females are forbidden to participate. 
*Question: Who is suffering unfair discrimination?

There are four possible answers:
#Males are suffering unfair discrimination.  They are forced to participate in the effort which will result in a high probability of death.
#Females are suffering unfair discrimination. They are prevented from participation in the war effort to protect their homeland.
#Both males and females are suffering unfair discrimination.
#No one suffers unfair discrimination. The ruling was made because of valid intrinsic reasons suiting men and women to different activities.  (This is not to assert anything about the relative suitability of men and women for conflict.) 

There may however be other examples of a situation some might regard as discriminatory, but in which there was no discrimination because of the decision was based on the intrinsic suitedness of the two groups to the roles being apportioned. An example might be symphony orchestras made up of all-white musicians selected by blind auditions. In a blind audition, the musician plays behind a curtain. The reviewer can't see the player, so there is no possibility of skin or race influencing the choice. 

Even here, the situation is complicated by possible indirect or ''institutionalized'' discrimination. Suppose black people are just as capable of being musicians but have not had access to training. For example, in [[1989]], the [[Detroit Symphony Orchestra]] was threatened with losing a $1.3m subsidy from the state of [[Michigan]] unless it hired a second black musician. It side-stepped the blind audition and hired a black man, who noted nonetheless that he would've preferred to be hired normally. This affirmative action hiring was clearly in the narrowest sense discriminatory, yet a chain of events followed leading to the Detroit Symphony African-American Fellowship Program in which young black musicians join the orchestra in rehearsals and performances. They receive coaching and audition preparation tips from orchestra members. Seven [[Detroit]] fellows have won seats in major American orchestras.

The key to the paradox is the subjectively interpreted phrase "more favorable treatment". Different people have different ideas about what constitutes "favorable treatment". To a male who does not want to die, favorable treatment means not being forced to go to the frontline. To a female who wants to defend her homeland, favorable treatment means being allowed to defend her homeland.

Different groups of people will have different perceptions of a situation. Four people who witness a car accident will have four different perceptions of what happened and how it happened.

Therefore it is possible to have a situation where two groups of people vehemently oppose each other, both objecting to the same piece of legislation on the grounds that it "gives more favorable treatment" to the other group.


== '''Gender Discrimination''' ==

Any action that specifically denies opportunities, privileges, or rewards to a person or a group because of their sex.

Internationally, the [[United Nations]] concludes that women are facing a global glass ceiling and that in no society do women enjoy the same opportunities as men. In the most developed country, the [[USA]], the Glass Ceiling Commission states that between 95 and 97 per cent of senior managers in the country's biggest corporations are men (...)The term 'glass ceiling' describes the process by which women are barred from promotion by means of an invisible barrier.

Traditionally, sexual differences have been used to justify male-dominated societies in which women have been given inferior and secondary roles in their working lives. There are differences between men and women, other than the physical, but there is little agreement as to what they are.

Generally, legislation to promote gender equality is complex and varied, with a wide divergence in different countries. In the UK, the principal legislation is found in the Equal Pay Act of 1970, providing for equal pay for comparable work; and the Sex Discrimination Act of 1975, which makes discrimination against women or men (including discrimination on the grounds of marital status) illegal in the working situation.

==See also==
*[[Ableism]] / [[Disablism]]
*[[Affirmative action]]
*[[Ageism]]
*[[Anti-semitism]]
*[[Apartheid]]
*[[Black Economic Empowerment]]
*[[Caucasophobia]]
*[[Civil rights movement]]
*[[Collectivism]]
*[[Equal opportunity]]
*[[Health disparities]]
*[[Heightism|Height discrimination]]
*[[List of anti-discrimination acts]]
*[[Prejudice]]
*[[Price discrimination]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Social equality|Equality]]
*[[Statistical discrimination]]
*[[Special rights]]
*[[White supremacy]]

==References==
{{unsourced}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]

[[bg:Дискриминация]]
[[de:Diskriminierung]]
[[es:Discriminación]]
[[fr:Discrimination]]
[[he:אפליה]]
[[hu:Hátrányos megkülönböztetés]]
[[nl:Discriminatie]]
[[ja:差別]]
[[pl:Dyskryminacja (psychologia społeczna)]]
[[pt:Discriminação]]
[[sl:Diskriminacija]]
[[sv:Diskriminering]]
[[zh:歧視]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>