<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020812091332|317567" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8900" pageid="8900" ns="0" title="Discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-09-27T04:31:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Discrimination''' is a general term used to refer to treating one group of people differently from another on such grounds as their [[race]] ([[racism]]), sex ([[sexism]]), [[religion]] ([[Religious discrimination|religious discrimination]]), ethnic background, [[disability]], [[sexual orientation]], [[sexual preference|preference]], or [[sexual behavior|behavior]], or political views. Use of the term implies that the factors on which the discrimination is based are or should be considered irrelevant. Generally, the aggrieved group is considered by the discriminator as inferior to others.

Discrimination on the basis of such grounds as subcultural preference ([[Punks]], [[Hippies]], [[Mods]] vs. [[Rockers]]) is also common.

Discrimination spans the spectrum from mild, such as slow or unhelpful retail service, through racial and ethnic slurs, denial of jobs or housing, to [[hate crime]]s and [[genocide]]. 

Many governments have attempted to control discrimination through [[civil rights]] legislation, while in other regimes discrimination has been formalized and government-supported. Examples of the latter include [[apartheid]] in [[South Africa]], institutionalized [[Racial segregation|racial segregation]] in the USA from the [[United States Civil War|Civil War]] through the [[1960s]], the "Jewish problem" in [[Nazi Germany]], or re-education camps in some [[communist]] countries. 


See also: [[anti-semitism]], [[apartheid]], [[civil rights movement]], [[collectivism]], [[hate crime]], [[homophobia]], [[race]], [[race riot]], [[speciesism]], [[statistical discrimination]], [[white supremacy]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>