<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091115135554|325977778" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8900" pageid="8900" ns="0" title="Discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-15T23:03:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Dablink|This article focuses on discrimination in sociology, not [[statistical discrimination]]. For other uses of the term, see [http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/discrimination Wiktionary] }}

{{Article issues|globalize=May 2008|POV=December 2007|refimprove =August 2008}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Discrimination''' is a [[sociological term]] referring to the treatment taken toward or against a person of a certain group that is taken in consideration based on class or category. The [[United Nations]] explains: "Discriminatory behaviors take many forms, but they all involve some form of exclusion or rejection." &lt;ref&gt;[http://cyberschoolbus.un.org/discrim/id_8_ud_print.asp United Nations CyberSchoolBus: What is discrimination?] {{PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Discriminatory laws such as [[redlining]] have existed in many countries. In some countries, controversial attempts such as [[racial quotas]] have been used to redress negative effects of discrimination.

==Race discrimination==
Racial discrimination differentiates between individuals on the basis of real and perceived racial differences, and has been official government policy in several countries, such as [[South Africa]] in the [[apartheid]] era, and the USA.  However, it does not appear to be entirely dead, yet, as evidenced by a rather recent news article on a website called NowPublic.com concerning alleged YMCA discrimination and a Federal Court Case in Texas. (See http://www.nowpublic.com/world/blacks-men-are-racial-gender-discrimination-not-dead-yet.)
[[Image:Segregation 1938b.jpg|left|thumb|250px|An [[African-American]] child at a segregated drinking fountain on a courthouse lawn, [[North Carolina]], 1938.]]
In the [[United States]], [[racial profiling]] of minorities by law enforcement officials has been called racial discrimination.&lt;ref&gt; 
{{cite news 
 |first=Gene 
 |last=Callahan
 |coauthors=Anderson, William
 |title=The Roots of Racial Profiling 
 |work=Reason Online  
 |publisher=Reason Foundation 
 |date =2001 August-September
 |accessdate=2006-07-27 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; As early as 1865, the [http://www.finduslaw.com/civil_rights_act_of_1866_civil_rights_act_of_1871_cra_42_u_s_code_21_1981_1981a_1983_1988 Civil Rights Act] provided a remedy for intentional race discrimination in employment by private employers and state and local public employers. The [http://www.finduslaw.com/civil_rights_act_of_1866_civil_rights_act_of_1871_cra_42_u_s_code_21_1981_1981a_1983_1988 Civil Rights Act of 1871] applies to public employment or employment involving state action prohibiting deprivation of rights secured by the federal constitution or federal laws through action under color of law.  Title VII is the principal federal statute with regard to employment discrimination prohibiting unlawful employment discrimination by public and private employers, labor organizations, training programs and employment agencies based on race or color, religion, gender, and national origin. 

Title VII also prohibits retaliation against any person for opposing any practice forbidden by statute, or for making a charge, testifying, assisting, or participating in a proceeding under the statute. The [http://www.finduslaw.com/civil_rights_act_of_1964_cra_title_vii_equal_employment_opportunities_42_us_code_chapter_21 Civil Rights Act of 1991] expanded the damages available in Title VII cases and granted Title VII plaintiffs the right to a jury trial.  Title VII also provides that [http://deskinlawfirm.com/race_color_ancestry_and_ethnicity_discrimination race and color discrimination] against every race and color is prohibited.

In the UK the inquiry following the murder of [[Stephen Lawrence]] accused the police of [[institutional racism]].
* [http://www.legalferret.net Weaver v NATFHE (now part of the UCU)] Race/sex discrimination case. An Industrial (Employment) Tribunal in the UK in 1987 decided that a trade union was justified in not assisting a Black woman member, complaining of racist/sexist harassment, regardless of the merits of the case, because the accused male would lose his job. The Employment Appeal Tribunal upheld the decision, which still stands today as the definitive [[legal precedent]] in this field. Also known as the [[Bournville College]] Racial Harassment issue.
* [[Red hair#Gingerism (prejudice/discrimination towards redheads)|Gingerism]] is a form of discrimination which is sometimes considered to be racism.

Within the criminal justice system in some Western countries, minorities are convicted and imprisoned disproportionately when compared with whites.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.publiceye.org/defendingjustice/pdfs/factsheets/10-Fact%20Sheet%20-%20System%20as%20Racist.pdf How is the Criminal Justice System Racist?]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2008/06/05/us-prison-numbers-hit-new-high Blacks Hardest Hit by Incarceration Policy]. Human Rights Watch. June 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1998, nearly one out of three black men between the ages of 20-29 were in prison or jail, on probation or parole on any given day in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eji.org/race%20crim%20just.pdf Race and the Criminal Justice System]&lt;/ref&gt; [[First Nations]] make up about 2% of [[Canada]]'s population, but account for 18% of the federal prison population as of 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite_web| url=http://www.csc-scc.gc.ca/text/rsrch/reports/r144/r144_e.shtml| title=A Profile of Visible Minority Offenders in the Federal Canadian Correctional System| author=Trevethan, Shelley| coauthors=Rastin, Christopher J.| publisher=Research Branch, Correctional Service of Canada| month=June| year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the Australian government's June 2006 publication of prison statistics, indigenous peoples make up 24% of the overall prison population in [[Australia]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite_web| url=http://www.abs.gov.au/AUSSTATS/abs@.nsf/Lookup/4517.0Main+Features12006?OpenDocument| title=Prisoners in Australia, 2006| publisher=Australian Bureau of Statistics| date=2006-12-14| accessdate=2007-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; ("Indigenous" meaning those identifying themselves as being of [[Indigenous Australians|Aboriginal]] or [[Torres Strait Islanders|Torres Strait Islander]] origin&lt;ref&gt;{{cite_web| url=http://www.abs.gov.au/AUSSTATS/abs@.nsf/Lookup/4517.0Explanatory%20Notes12006?OpenDocument| title=Prisoners in Australia, 2006: Explanatory Notes| publisher=Australian Bureau of Statistics| date=2006-12-14| accessdate=2007-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;) In 2004, [[Maori]] made up just 15% of the total population of [[New Zealand]] but 49.5% of prisoners. Maori were entering prison at 8 times the rate of non-Maori.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2004/41654.htm New Zealand's Prison Population]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Age discrimination==
[[Ageism|Age discrimination]] is discrimination on the grounds of age. Although theoretically the word can refer to the discrimination against any age group, age discrimination usually comes in one of three forms: discrimination against [[youth]] (also called [[adultism]]), discrimination against those 40 years old or older [http://www.finduslaw.com/age_discrimination_in_employment_act_of_1967_adea_29_u_s_code_chapter_14], and discrimination against elderly people.

In the United States, the [[Age Discrimination in Employment Act]] prohibits employment discrimination nationwide based on age with respect to employees 40 years of age or older. The [http://www.finduslaw.com/age_discrimination_in_employment_act_of_1967_adea_29_u_s_code_chapter_14 Age Discrimination in Employment Act] also addresses the difficulty older workers face in obtaining new employment after being displaced from their jobs, arbitrary age limits.

In many countries, companies more or less openly refuse to hire people above a certain age despite the increasing lifespans and average age of the population. The reasons for this range from vague feelings younger people are more "dynamic" and create a positive image for the company, to more concrete concerns about regulations granting older employees higher salaries or other benefits without these expenses being fully justified by an older employees' greater experience.

Some people consider that [[teenagers]] and [[youth]] (around 15–25 years old) are victims of [[adultism]], age discrimination framed as a paternalistic form of protection. In seeking social justice, they feel that it is necessary to remove the use of a false moral agenda in order to achieve agency and empowerment. 

This perspective is based on the grounds that youth should be treated more respectfully by adults and not as second-class citizens. Some suggest that social [[stratification]] in age groups causes outsiders to incorrectly [[stereotype]] and generalize the group, for instance that all adolescents are equally immature, violent or rebellious, listen to rock tunes, and do [[hard and soft drugs|drug]]s. Some have organized groups against age discrimination.

Ageism is the causal effect of a continuum of fears related to age.{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}} This continuum includes:
*[[Ephebiphobia]]: the fear of youth.
*[[Gerontophobia]]: the fear of elderly people.
*[[Pediaphobia]]: the fear of infants or small children.

Related terms include:

*[[Adultism]]: Also called adultarchy, adult privilege, and adultcentrism/adultocentrism, this is the wielding of authority over young people and the preference of adults before children and youth.
*[[Jeunism]]: Also called "youthism" is the holding of beliefs or actions taken that preference 'younger' people before adults.

== Gender discrimination ==
{{See also|Sexism}}
Though gender discrimination and sexism refers to beliefs and [[Attitude (psychology)|attitudes]] in relation to the [[gender]] of a person, such beliefs and attitudes are of a social nature and do not, normally, carry any legal consequences. '''Sex discrimination''', on the other hand, may have legal consequences. 

Though what constitutes sex discrimination varies between countries, the essence is that it is an adverse action taken by one person against another person that would not have occurred had the person been of another sex. Discrimination of that nature in certain enumerated circumstances is illegal in many countries.

Currently, discrimination based on sex is defined as adverse action against another person, that would not have occurred had the person been of another sex. This is considered a form of [[prejudice]] and is illegal in certain enumerated circumstances in most countries. 

Sexual discrimination can arise in different contexts. For instance an employee may be discriminated against by being asked discriminatory questions during a job interview, or because an [[employer]] did not hire, promote or wrongfully terminated an employee based on his or her gender, or employers pay unequally based on gender. 

In an educational setting there could be claims that a student was excluded from an educational institution, program, opportunity, loan, student group, or scholarship due to his or her gender. In the housing setting there could be claims that a person was refused negotiations on seeking a house, contracting/leasing a house or getting a loan based on his or her gender. Another setting where there have been claims of gender discrimination is banking; for example if one is refused credit or is offered unequal loan terms based on one’s gender.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, F. (2003) Organizational Behaviour and Gender (2nd Edition), Aldershot: Ashgate.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another setting where there is usually gender discrimination is when one is refused to extend his or her credit, refused approval of credit/loan process, and if there is a burden of unequal loan terms based on one’s gender. 

Socially, sexual differences have been used to justify different roles for men and women, in some cases giving rise to claims of primary and secondary roles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://digitalcommons.shu.ac.uk/ciod_papers/54/ Ridley-Duff, R. J. (2008) "Gendering, Courtship and Pay Equity: Developing Attraction Theory to Understand Work-Life Balance and Entrepreneurial Behaviour", paper to the ''31st ISBE Conference'', 5th-7th November, Belfast]&lt;/ref&gt; 

While there are alleged non-physical differences between men and women, major reviews of the academic literature on gender difference find only a tiny minority of characteristics where there are consistent psychological differences between men and women, and these relate directly to experiences grounded in biological difference.&lt;ref&gt;Hyde, J. S. (2005) “The Gender Similarities Hypothesis”, ''American Psychologist'', 60(6): 581 592.&lt;/ref&gt; However, there are also some psychological differences in regard to how problems are dealt with and emotional perceptions and reactions which may relate to hormones and the successful characteristics of each gender during longstanding roles in past primitive lifestyles.

Unfair discrimination usually follows the [[sexism|gender stereotyping]] held by a society.

The [[United Nations]] had concluded that women often experience a "[[glass ceiling]]" and that there are no societies in which women enjoy the same opportunities as men. The term "glass ceiling" is used to describe a perceived barrier to advancement in employment based on discrimination, especially sex discrimination. 

In the [[United States]], the Glass Ceiling Commission, a government-funded group, stated: "Over half of all Master’s degrees are now awarded to women, yet 95% of senior-level managers, of the top Fortune 1000 industrial and 500 service companies are men. Of them, 97% are white." In its report, it recommended [[affirmative action]], which is the consideration of an employee's gender and race in hiring and promotion decisions, as a means to end this form of discrimination.&lt;ref name="Glass Ceiling Commission"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://digitalcommons.ilr.cornell.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1117&amp;context=key_workplace
|title=A Solid Investment: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital
|date=1995-11
|accessdate=2008-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Transgender]] individuals, both male to female and female to male, often experience problems which often lead to dismissals, underachievement, difficulty in finding a job, social isolation, and, occasionally, violent attacks against them. Nevertheless, the problem of gender discrimination does not stop at trandgender individuals nor with women.  Men are often the victim in certain areas of employment as the traditional "male" job-field opens to women, the influx of millions of illegal aliens take many jobs in construction, highway work, etc., and men begin to seek work in office and childcare settings traditionally perceived as "women's jobs".  One such situation seems to be evident in a recent news article, mentioned above,  on a website called NowPublic.com concerning alleged YMCA discrimination and a Federal Court Case in Texas. (See http://www.nowpublic.com/world/blacks-men-are-racial-gender-discrimination-not-dead-yet.) The case actually involves alleged discrimination against both men and blacks in childcare, even when they pass the same strict background tests and other standards of employment.  It is currently being contended in federal court, as of fall 2009, and sheds light on how a workplace dominated by a majority (- women in this case) sometimes will seemingly "justify" whatever they wish to do, regardless of the Law.  This may be done as an effort at self-protection, to uphold traditional societal roles, or some other faulty, unethical or illegal prejudicial reasoning.  

===Legislation===
;{{flagicon|Australia}} [[Australia]]
* [http://scaleplus.law.gov.au/html/pasteact/0/171/top.htm Sex Discrimination Act 1984]
;{{flagicon|Canada}} [[Canada]]
* {{flagicon|Ontario}} [[Ontario Human Rights Code]] 1962
* [[Canadian Human Rights Act]] 1977
;{{flagicon|Hong Kong}} [[Hong Kong]]
* Sex Discrimination Ordinance (1996) [[Image:Flag of Hong Kong 1959.svg|22px|Flag of Hong Kong (before 1997)]]
;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom]]
* [[Equal Pay Act 1970]] - provides for equal pay for comparable work
* [[Sex Discrimination Act 1975]] - makes discrimination against women or men, including discrimination on the grounds of marital status, illegal in the workplace except when it pertains to a "white man" and a "black woman."
* [[Human Rights Act 1998]] - provides more scope for redressing all forms of discriminatory imbalances
;{{flagicon|United States}} [[United States]]
* [[Equal Pay Act of 1963]][http://www.finduslaw.com/equal_pay_act_of_1963_epa_29_u_s_code_chapter_8_206_d] - (part of the [[Fair Labor Standards Act]]) - prohibits wage discrimination by employers and labor organizations based on sex
* [[Title VII]] of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]][http://www.finduslaw.com/civil_rights_act_of_1964_cra_title_vii_equal_employment_opportunities_42_us_code_chapter_21] - broadly prohibits discrimination in the workplace including hiring, firing, workforce reduction, benefits, and sexually harassing conduct
* [[Pregnancy Discrimination Act]], which amended Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 - covers discrimination based upon pregnancy in the workplace&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |last=
  |first=
  |authorlink=omg
  |coauthors=
  |title=Pregnancy Discrimination Act
  |work=
  |publisher=
  |date=
  |url=http://employment.findlaw.com/employment/employment-employee-discrimination-harassment/employment-employee-pregnancy-discrimination-top/pregnancy-discrimination-act.html
  |doi=
  |accessdate=2008-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Caste discrimination==
{{see also|Caste system in India}}
According to [[UNICEF]] and [[Human Rights Watch]], [[caste]] discrimination affects an estimated 250 million people worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unicef.org/protection/index_discrimination.html Discrimination], [[UNICEF]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/english/docs/2001/08/29/global1815.htm Global Caste Discrimination]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newint.org/issue380/facts.htm Caste - The Facts]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Hindu]] population of [[South Asia]] comprises about 2,000 [[caste]]s.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/285248/India/46404/Caste India – Caste]". Encyclopædia Britannica.&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently, there are an estimated 160 million [[Dalit]]s or "untouchables" in India.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.npr.org/programs/specials/racism/010828.caste.html The Caste System]". NPR: National Public Radio.&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of Dalits live in [[segregation]] and experience violence, [[murder]], [[rape]] and [[persecution of Dalits|other atrocities]] to the scale of 110,000 registered cases a year, according to 2005 statistics.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.cbc.ca/world/story/2007/03/02/india-dalits.html UN report slams India for caste discrimination]". CBC News.  March 2, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; An estimated 40 million people in [[India]], most of them Dalits, are [[Debt bondage|bonded]] workers, many working to pay off debts that were incurred generations ago.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.cbc.ca/ideas/features/untouchables/index.html The Untouchables]". CBC Radio.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Indian government statistics, an estimated one million Dalits or "untouchables" are manual scavengers, cleaning latrines and sewers by hand and clearing away dead animals.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/country,,HRW,,IND,4562d8cf2,3ae6a83f0,0.html Broken People: Caste Violence Against India's "Untouchables"]". UNHCR | Refworld.&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of human scavengers suffer from respiratory diseases, with 23% suffering [[trachoma]], leading to blindness.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.hrw.org/en/reports/2007/02/12/hidden-apartheid?print Caste Discrimination against India's "Untouchables"]". Human Rights Watch.&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Employment discrimination==
{{Main|Employment discrimination}}
The American federal laws that protect against:
* race, color and national origin discrimination include the [http://www.finduslaw.com/civil_rights_act_of_1964_cra_title_vii_equal_employment_opportunities_42_us_code_chapter_21 Civil Rights Act of 1964], [http://www.finduslaw.com/executive_order_number_11478_equal_employment_opportunity_in_the_federal_government Executive Order Number 11478] among other numerous laws that protect people from [http://www.finduslaw.com/employment_discrimination/race_national_origin race, color and national origin discrimination]. 
* [http://www.finduslaw.com/federal_employment_law/employment_discrimination/harassment_gender_sex_pregnancy sex and gender discrimination] include the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] and [http://www.finduslaw.com/equal_pay_act_of_1963_epa_29_u_s_code_chapter_8_206_d Equal Pay Act of 1963].
* [http://www.finduslaw.com/employment_discrimination/age age discrimination] include the [http://www.finduslaw.com/age_discrimination_in_employment_act_of_1967_adea_29_u_s_code_chapter_14 Age Discrimination in Employment Act of 1967].
* [http://www.finduslaw.com/employment_discrimination/disability physical and mental disability discrimination] include the [http://www.finduslaw.com/americans_with_disabilities_act_of_1990_ada_42_u_s_code_chapter_126 Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]
* [http://www.finduslaw.com/employment_discrimination/religion religious discrimination]include the [http://www.finduslaw.com/civil_rights_act_of_1964_cra_title_vii_equal_employment_opportunities_42_us_code_chapter_21 Civil Rights Act of 1964].
* [http://www.finduslaw.com/employment_discrimination/military_status military status discrimination] include the [http://www.finduslaw.com/vietnam_era_veterans_readjustment_assistance_act_of_1974_vevraa_38_us_code_chapter_42_4211_4215 Vietnam Era Veterans Readjustment Assistance Act of 1974]

Most other western nations have similar laws protecting these groups.

==Discrimination against lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender and gender variant people==
''See:'' [[Heterosexism]], [[Heteronormativity]], and [[Homophobia]]
{{Expand section|examples and additional citations|date=August 2009}}

==Language discrimination==
Diversity of language is protected and respected by most nations who value cultural diversity. However, people are sometimes subjected to different treatment because their preferred [[language]] is associated with a particular group, class or category. Commonly, the preferred language is just another [[attribute]] of separate [[ethnic group]]s. Discrimination exists if there is prejudicial treatment against a person or a group of people who speak a particular language or dialect.
Language discrimination is suggested to be labeled [[Linguacism]] or [[logocism]]. Anti-discriminatory and inclusive efforts to accomodate persons who speak different languages or cannot have fluency in the country's predominant or "official" lanugage, is [[bilingualism]] such as official documents in two languages, and [[multiculturalism]] in more than two languages.

==Reverse discrimination==
{{Main|Reverse discrimination}}

Some attempts at antidiscrimination have been criticized as '''reverse discrimination'''. In particular, minority quotas (e.g. [[affirmative action]]) can be said to discriminate against members of a dominant or majority group. In its opposition to race preferences, the American Civil Rights Institute's [[Ward Connerly]] stated, "There is nothing positive, affirmative, or equal about 'affirmative action' programs that give preference to some groups based on race." &lt;ref&gt;http://www.acri.org/pr_7_25_07.html&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, it is argued that critics of antidiscriminatory steps often rely on misconceptions, that policy should take into account the negative effects of discrimination on minorities to reduce existing inequalities. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.understandingprejudice.org/readroom/articles/affirm.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Disability discrimination==
{{Main|Disability discrimination}}
 
People with [[disabilities]] face discrimination in all levels of society.  The attitude that disabled individuals are inferior to non-disabled individuals is called [[ableism]] or [[disablism]]. Historically, the disabled have been shunned for their problems. These views are reinforced in modern times in media, books, films, comics, art and language.

[[Chronic pain]] is a debilitating condition which is often neglected in modern society. According to the [[American Chiropractic Association]], over 50% of all working US citizens complain of back pain each year. An estimated 80% of the population will experience back pain at some point in their life. Many times pain can become chronic and debilitating. 

[[Ergonomic]] seating and work environments are not only be a reasonable accommodation for those who suffer, they are also a preventative measure to counteract the soaring cost of medical treatment for pain conditions. Ergonomic seating in all public institutions would be a positive step to providing access to public services for all those who need it. 

In the United States, the [[Americans with Disabilities Act]] provides guidelines for providing wheelchair access for public institutions.

==Theories==
===Discrimination===
[[Social theories]] such as [[Egalitarianism]] claim that [[social equality]] should prevail. In some societies, including most developed countries, each individual's civil rights include the right to be free from government sponsored social discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.weblocator.com/attorney/mn/law/concivrig.html#30 |title=Civil rights |accessdate=2006 }}bbb;
&lt;/ref&gt;
Taking into account the capacity to perceive pain and/or suffering that all animals have, '[[abolitionist]]' or '[[vegan]]' egalitarianism maintains that every individual, regardless their species, should have at least the basic right not to be an object.{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}} See also [[speciesism]].

===Conservative and Anarcho-Capitalist===
In contrast, [[conservatism|conservative]] writer and law professor [[Matthias Storme]] has claimed that the freedom of discrimination in human societies is a fundamental human right, or more precisely, the basis of all fundamental freedoms and therefore the most fundamental freedom. Author [[Hans-Hermann Hoppe]], in an essay&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lewrockwell.com/hoppe/hoppe4.html]{{cite web |last=Hoppe |first=Hans-Hermann |year=2001 |url=http://www.lewrockwell.com/hoppe/hoppe4.html |title=Democracy: The God That Failed |accessdate=2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; about his book [[Democracy: The God That Failed]], asserts that a natural social order is characterized by increased discrimination.

=== Labeling theory ===
Discrimination, in [[labeling theory]], takes form as mental categorisation of minorities and the use of [[stereotype]]. This theory describes difference as deviance from the norm, which results in internal devaluation and social stigma&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last=Slattery| first=M. | year=2002 | title=Key Ideas in Sociology | publisher=Nelson Thornes| isbn=978-0748765652 | p=134-137}}&lt;/ref&gt; that may be seen as discrimination. It is started by describing a 'natural' social order. It is distinguished between the fundamental principle of fascism and social democracy. Both the [[Nazis]] in 1930's-era Germany, the pre-1990 [[Apartheid]] government of South Africa and other countries in the present day used racial discriminatory agendas for their political means.

==See also==
{{top}}
* [[Ableism]]
* [[Adultism]]
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Allport's scale]]
* [[Anti-discrimination law]]
* [[Apartheid]]
* [[Colorism]]
* [[Crimes against humanity]]
* [[Egalitarianism]]
* [[Equal opportunity]]
* [[Equal rights]]
* [[Genetic discrimination]]
* [[Genderism]]
* [[Genocide]]
* [[Hate crime]]
* [[Heightism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Institutionalized discrimination]]
* [[Master race]]
* [[Persecution]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Reverse discrimination]]
* [[Second-class citizen]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[State racism]]
{{bottom}}

==References==
&lt;!--See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref(erences/)&gt; tags--&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;!--See Richey, Warren. "Affirmative Action's Evolution." The CS Monitor. Staff Writer of the Christian Science Montior, 2003. [[3 May]] [[2007]] &lt;http://www.csmonitor.com/2003/0328/p01s01-usju.html&gt;. --&gt;

==External links==
* Legal definitions
** [http://www.hreoc.gov.au/legal/index.html Australia]
** [http://www.chrc-ccdp.ca/legislation_policies/human_rights_act-en.asp Canada]
** [http://www.departments.bucknell.edu/russian/const/ch2.html Russia]
** [http://www.eeoc.gov/facts/qanda.html US]
* [http://www.finduslaw.com/taxonomy_menu/12/23 Employment Discrimination Laws in the United States]
* [http://eur-lex.europa.eu/en/dossier/dossier_23.htm Discrimination Laws in Europe ]

[[Category:Discrimination| ]]

[[ar:تمييز]]
[[bg:Дискриминация]]
[[ca:Discriminació]]
[[cs:Diskriminace]]
[[da:Diskrimination]]
[[de:Diskriminierung]]
[[es:Discriminación]]
[[eo:Diskriminacio]]
[[fa:تبعیض]]
[[fr:Discrimination]]
[[ko:차별]]
[[hr:Diskriminacija]]
[[id:Diskriminasi]]
[[it:Discriminazione]]
[[he:אפליה]]
[[ka:დისკრიმინაცია]]
[[lv:Diskriminācija]]
[[lt:Diskriminacija]]
[[hu:Diszkrimináció]]
[[mk:Дискриминација]]
[[ms:Diskriminasi]]
[[nl:Discriminatie]]
[[ja:差別]]
[[pl:Dyskryminacja (psychologia społeczna)]]
[[pt:Discriminação]]
[[rmy:Diskriminaciya]]
[[ru:Дискриминация]]
[[simple:Discrimination]]
[[sk:Diskriminácia (znevýhodňovanie)]]
[[sl:Diskriminacija]]
[[sr:Дискриминација]]
[[fi:Syrjintä]]
[[sv:Diskriminering]]
[[tr:Ayrımcılık]]
[[uk:Дискримінація]]
[[ur:امتیاز]]
[[vls:Discriminoatie]]
[[yi:דיסקרימינאציע]]
[[zh:歧視]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>