<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031104062035|1670488" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8900" pageid="8900" ns="0" title="Discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-04T06:29:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Diskriminierung]]
[[ja:&amp;#24046;&amp;#21029;]]
[[nl:Discriminatie]]
[[pl:Dyskryminacja]]

To '''discriminate''' means to make a distinction. There are several meanings of the word, including [[statistical discrimination]], or the actions of a circuit called a  [[discriminator]]. This article addresses the most common meaning of the word, social, racial, religious, sexual and ethnic discrimination.
==Definition==
'''Discrimination''' involves formally or informally classifying people into different groups and according the members of each group distinct, and typically unequal, treatments, rights and obiligations. The criteria delineating the groups, such as gender, race, or class, determine the kind of discrimination.

Discrimination generally refers to treating one group of people less well than another on such grounds as their [[race]] ([[racism]]), [[gender]] ([[sexism]]), [[religion]] ([[Religious discrimination|religious discrimination]]), ethnic background, national origin, [[disability]], [[sexual orientation]], [[sexual preference|preference]] or [[sexual behavior|behavior]], or political views. Discrimination on the basis of such grounds as subcultural preference ([[Punk]]s, [[hippy|Hippies]], [[Mods (youth movement)|Mods]] vs. [[Rockers]]) is also common.

The effects of discrimination span the spectrum from mild, such as slow or unhelpful [[retail]] service, through racial and ethnic slurs, denial of [[employment]] or housing, to [[hate crime]]s and [[genocide]]. 

Use of the term carries the implication that the factors on which the discrimination is based are intrinsically irrelevant to the decision being influenced. Generally, the aggrieved group is considered by the discriminator as inferior to others. 
==Institutionalized Discrimination and Responses==
Many governments have attempted to control discrimination through [[civil rights]] legislation, [[equal opportunity]] laws and institutionalised policies of [[affirmative action]] (or [[reverse discrimination]]).

Some governments have formalized and supported discrimination. Examples include [[apartheid]] in [[South Africa]], institutionalized [[Racial segregation|racial segregation]] in the USA from the [[United States Civil War|Civil War]] through the [[1960s]], the "Jewish problem" in [[Nazi Germany]], or re-education camps in some [[communist]] countries. 
==Religious Discrimination==
[[Religious intolerance]] often manifests itself in discriminatory behaviours. During the [[Middle Ages]], in the [[Crusade]]s, [[Pope]]s, kings, and emperors tried to draw on Christian unity to defend their lands from some followers of [[Islam]], which was spreading along Europe's southern and eastern borders. [[Roman Catholic]] countries have historically persecuted dissenters, for example with the [[Spanish Inquisition]]. Rulers of [[Protestant]] countries sponsored discrimination against members of the [[Roman Catholic]] faith. During [[Tudor]] and [[Stuart]] times, rulers of the [[UK]] persecuted both Catholics and non-Catholics at intervals for political reasons. Non-Muslims are discriminated against in many [[Arab]] nations. Jews and Christians have historically had fewer rights than Muslim citizens in all Muslim nations; all non-Muslim [[monotheism|monotheists]] have been consigned to the status of [[dhimmi]]s. Communist countries have discriminated against members of all theistic faiths.

For example, the Kingdom of [[Jordan]] forbids Jews from becoming citizens, although peoples of any other group are allowed to do so. (Law No. 6, sect. 3, of April 3, 1954; restated in law no. 7, sect. 2, of April 1, 1963.) [[Saudi Arabia]] forbids non-Muslims from practising their religion in public. Christians who ask Muslims to convert to Christianity have been persecuted and arrested; Muslims who have converted to Christianity have been executed. Jews are forbidden from practising their faith. The article on [[discrimination against non-Muslims in Saudi Arabia]] discuses this subject in more depth. 
According to reports from the U.S. Department of State, non-Muslims also suffer discrimination in many non-Arab [[Muslim]] nations. Separate articles discuss discrimination against non-Muslims in [[Discrimination against non-Muslims in Afghanistan|Afghanistan]], [[Discrimination against non-Muslims in Iran|Iran]], [[Discrimination against non-Muslims in Malaysia|Malaysia]], [[Discrimination against non-Muslims in Mauritania|Mauritania]], [[Discrimination against non-Muslims in Pakistan|Pakistan]] and 
[[Discrimination against non-Muslims in Sudan|Sudan]].

The [[State of Israel]] is often accused of discrimination against [[Palestinians|Palestinian Arabs]]; this topic is discussed in the article on [[apartheid]].

==The Paradox of Discrimination==
Many people assume that when there is discrimination, one group of people is given more favorable treatment than others.  This is not always the case. It is possible to have cases where it is not at all clear which group is given the more favorable treatment.

*Example: Your country is under attack during wartime. The war is so ferocious that 80% of the combatants are killed. A law has been passed to forcefully conscript males between 18-24 years of age into the frontline, furthermore females are forbidden to participate. 
*Question: Who is being discriminated against?

There are four possible answers.

#Males are being discriminated against.  They are forced to participate in the effort which will result in a high probability of death.
#Females are being discriminated against. They are prevented from participation in the war effort to protect their homeland.
#Both males and females are being discriminated against.
#Nobody is being discriminated against. The ruling was made because of valid intrinsic reasons suiting men and women to different activities.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; 

The key to the paradox is the subjectively interpreted phrase "more favorable treatment". Different people have different ideas about what constitutes "favorable treatment". To a male who does not want to die, favorable treatment means not being forced to go to the frontline. To a female who wants to defend her homeland, favorable treatment means being allowed to defend her homeland.

Different groups of people will have different perceptions of a situation. Four people who witness a car accident will have four different perceptions of what happened and how it happened.

Therefore it is possible to have a situation where two groups of people vehemently oppose each other, both objecting to the same piece of legislation on the grounds that it "gives more favorable treatment" to the other group.

==See Also==
*[[Affirmative action]]
*[[Anti-semitism]]
*[[Apartheid]]
*[[Civil rights movement]]
*[[Collectivism]]
*[[Equal opportunity]]
*[[Equality]]
*[[Hate crime]]
*[[Homophobia]]
*[[Race riot]]  
*[[Racism]]
*[[White supremacy]]
==Footnote==
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; This is not to assert anything about the relative suitability of men and women for conflict. There may however be other examples of a situation some might regard as discriminatory, but in which there was no discrimination because of the decision was based on the intrinsic suitedness of the two groups to the roles being apportioned. An example might be symphony orchestras made up of all-white musicians selected by blind auditions. In a blind audition, you play behind a curtain. They can't see you, so there is no possibility of skin or race influencing the choice. 

Even here, the situation is complicated by possible indirect or ''institutionalized'' discrimination. Suppose black people are just as capable of being musicians but have not had access to training. For example, in 1989, the Detroit Symphony Orchestra was threatened with losing a $1.3 state subsidy unless it hired a second black musician. It side-stepped the blind audition and hired an African-American. This affirmative action was clearly in the narrowest sense discriminatory, yet a chain of events followed leading to the Detroit Symphony African-American Fellowship Program in which young black musicians join the orchestra in rehearsals and performances. They receive coaching and audition preparation tips from orchestra members. Seven Detroit fellows have won seats in major American orchestras.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>