<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20021012154805|403115" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="14233" pageid="14233" ns="0" title="Hate speech"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-11-04T03:51:49Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[nl:Hate speech]] [[pl:Hate speech]]
'''Hate speech''' is a controversial term used to describe spoken or printed expressions deemed to arise from, or to incite, hatred or contempt towards some group of people, such as an ethnic or religious group or sexual minority. It is not a legal or statutory term (as is, for instance, "[[obscenity]]"), though it has been written into the bylaws of some governmental institutions such as public universities (see below).

Those who use the term "hate speech" do so in protest against ideas or expressions they believe are destructive to the public good or to the good of a group deserving protection. They draw a link between hateful or prejudiced speech and discriminatory conduct, or the creation of a biased or harassing environment. Those who object to the term hold it to be inextricably connected with calls for the censorship of unpopular viewpoints, and also to be irrationally dismissory, in that to label an expression "hate speech" is to call for it to be dismissed out of hand without being evaluated further.

In the [[United States]], the disagreement over the term is often stereotyped as rancor between "liberals" and "conservatives" -- with liberals seeking protection for oppressed groups, and conservatives holding out for an absolute form of freedom of speech. This is a simplistic view, however, as many self-described liberals oppose the restriction of speech in the name of nondiscrimination, and many conservatives have called for the restriction of speech against particular (usually religious) groups. The traditional [[political spectrum]] is a poor model for this issue, as with many others.

====Hate speech codes in academia====

Some American universities have speech codes that prohibit hate speech. These rules are intended to ensure an atmosphere free from harassment and intimidation, conducive to a learning environment. Many speakers have opposed such speech codes, claiming they constitute a new orthodoxy of [[political correctness]] and represent an erosion of the [[freedom of speech]] guaranteed in the [[United_States_Constitution/Amendment_One|First Amendment]] to the [[United States Constitution]], which strictly speaking only prohibits government censorship.  Freedom of speech, however, is a widely held value beyond the governmental sphere and many universities are government institutions and almost all accept government funds.

Some observers believe that the accusation of hate speech is often made to suppress points of view which are unfavorable to certain "protected groups", which represents a significant infringement of the tradition of academic freedom and gives members of these groups an unfair advantage in the marketplace of ideas.

For example, for a college professor to say, "[[Lesbian]]s should not be schoolteachers", could be considered hate speech. The professor could be denied tenure, even if he were expressing his religious belief that people who engage in lesbian behavior should not be put in positions where they can influence young people. The defense that he doesn't hate lesbians and didn't intend to hurt anyone's feelings would be dismissed on the grounds that to object to certain behavior or have one's livelihood threatened is harmful on its face.  

See also [[profanity]], [[taboo]], [[hate crime]].</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>