<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071113202032|171273970" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="105004" pageid="105004" ns="0" title="Ethnicity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T20:56:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">''The term "Ethnicity" redirects here.  For the album of the same name by [[Yanni]], see [[Ethnicity (Yanni album)]]''
&lt;br /&gt;

An '''ethnic group''' or '''ethnicity''' is a [[population]] of [[human|human being]]s whose members identify with each other, usually on the basis of a presumed common [[genealogy]] or [[ancestry]].&lt;ref name=Smith&gt;Smith 1987&lt;/ref&gt; Ethnicity is also defined from the recognition by others as a distinct group&lt;ref name=EB&gt;"Anthropology. The study of ethnicity, minority groups, and identity," ''Encyclopaedia Britannica, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and by common [[culture|cultural]], [[linguistic]], [[religion|religious]], [[human behaviour|behavioural]] or [[Race|biological]] traits.&lt;ref name=Smith/&gt;&lt;ref name="statcan"&gt;[http://www.statcan.ca/english/concepts/definitions/ethnicity.htm Statistics Canada Definition of Ethnicity] &lt;/ref&gt; 

According to some, "Ethnicity is a fundamental factor in human life: it is a phenomenon inherent in human experience."&lt;ref name="statcan"/&gt;  According to others, however, ethnic identities only arise under specific conditions.&lt;ref&gt;Frederick Barth ed. 1969 ''Ethnic Groups and Boundaries: The Social Organization of Cultural Difference; Eric Wolf 1982 ''Europe and the People Without History'' p. 381&lt;/ref&gt;
Processes that result in the emergence of such identification are summarized as [[ethnogenesis]]. Members of an ethnic group, on the whole, claim cultural continuities over time, although [[historian]]s and [[Cultural anthropology|cultural anthropologist]]s have documented that many of the values, practices, and norms that imply continuity with the past are of relatively recent invention.&lt;ref&gt;Friedlander 1975 ''Being Indian in Hueyapan'', Hobsbawm and Ranger 1983 ''The Invention of Tradition'', Sider 1993 ''Lumbee Indian Histories''.&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Defining ethnicity==
The sociologist Max Weber once remarked that "The whole conception of ethnic groups is so complex and so vague that it might be good to abandon it altogether."&lt;ref name="weber"&gt;Max Weber [1922]1978 ''Economy and Society'' eds. Guenther Roth and Claus Wittich, trans. Ephraim Fischof, vol. 2 Berkeley: University of California Press, 389&lt;/ref&gt;  

In any case, Weber proposed a definition of ethnic group that became accepted by many social scientists: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;[T]hose human groups that entertain a subjective belief in their common descent because of similarities of physical type or of customs or both, or because of memories of colonization and migration; this belief must be important for group formation; furthermore it does not matter whether an objective blood relationship exists.&lt;ref name="weber"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Anthropologist Ronald Cohen, in a review of anthropological and sociological studies of ethnic groups since Weber, claimed that while many ethnic groups subjectively claimed common descent and cultural continuity, objectively there was often evidence that countered such claims.&lt;ref name="cohen"&gt;Ronald Cohen 1978 "Ethnicity: Problem and Focus in Anthropology" in ''Annual Review of Anthropology'' 7: 385 Palo Alto: Stanford University Press&lt;/ref&gt;  Harold Isaacs has identified other ''diacritics'' (distinguishing markers) of ethnicity, among them physical appearance, name, language, history, and religion;&lt;ref&gt;Isaacs, H. 1975 ''Idols of the Tribe: Group Identity and Political Change''  New York: Harper''&lt;/ref&gt; this definition has entered some dictionaries.&lt;ref&gt;2006 ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, Fourth Edition'' Boston:Houghton Mifflin&lt;/ref&gt; Social scientists have thus focused on how, when, and why different markers of ethnic identity become salient. Thus, anthropologist Joan Vincent observed that ethnic boundaries often have a mercurial character.&lt;ref&gt;Joan Vincent 1974 "The Structure of Ethnicity" in ''Human Organization 33(4): 375-379&lt;/ref&gt; Ronald Cohen concluded that ethnicity is "a series of nesting dichotomizations of inclusiveness and exclusiveness".&lt;ref name="cohen"/&gt;  He agrees with Joan Vincent's observation that (in Cohen's paraphrase) "Ethnicity ... can be narrowed or broadened in boundary terms in relation to the specific needs of political mobilization.&lt;ref name="cohen"/&gt;  This may be why descent is sometimes a marker of ethnicity, and sometimes not:  which diacritic of ethnicity is salient depends on whether people are scaling ethnic boundaries up or down, and whether they are scaling them up or down depends generally on the political situation.

==Ethnicity and race==
Ethnicity and race are related concepts in that both are usually defined in terms of shared [[genealogy]].&lt;ref&gt;Abizadeh 2001&lt;/ref&gt; Often, ethnicity also connotes shared cultural, linguistic, behavioural or religious traits. Race, by contrast, refers to "some concentrations, as relative to frequency and distribution, of hereditary particles (genes) and physical characters, which appear, fluctuate, and often disappear in the course of time by reason of geographic and or cultural isolation."  In [[1950]], the [[UNESCO]] statement ''[[The Race Question]]'', signed by some of the internationally renowned scholars of the time (including [[Ashley Montagu]], [[Claude Lévi-Strauss]], [[Gunnar Myrdal]], [[Julian Huxley]], etc.), suggested that: "National, religious, geographic, linguistic and cultural groups do not necessarily coincide with racial groups: and the cultural traits of such groups have no demonstrated genetic connection with racial traits. Because serious errors of this kind are habitually committed when the term “ race ” is used in popular parlance, it would be better when speaking of human races to drop the term ” race ” altogether and speak of 'ethnic groups'." &lt;ref&gt;A. Metraux (1950) "United nations Economic and Security Council Statement by Experts on Problems of Race" in ''American Anthropologist 53(1): 142-145)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ethnicity and nation==
In some cases, especially involving transnational migration, or colonial expansion, ethnicity is linked to nationality.  Many anthropologists and historians, following the work of Ernest Gellner&lt;ref&gt;Gellner 2006 ''Nations and Nationalism'' Blackwell Publishing&lt;/ref&gt; and Benedict Anderson&lt;ref&gt;Anderson 2006 ''Imagined Communities'' Verson&lt;/ref&gt; see nations and nationalism as developing with the rise of the modern state system in the seventeenth century, culminating in the rise of "nation-states" in which the presumptive boundaries of the nation coincided (or ideally coincided) with state boundaries.
Thus, in the West, the notion of ethnicity, like [[race]] and [[nation]], developed in the context of European colonial expansion, when [[mercantilism]] and [[capitalism]] were promoting global movements of populations at the same time that [[state]] boundaries were being more clearly and rigidly defined.  In the nineteenth century, modern states generally sought legitimacy through their claim to represent "nations."  [[Nation-state]]s, however, invariably include populations that have been excluded from national life for one reason or another.  Members of excluded groups, consequently, will either demand inclusion on the basis of equality, or seek autonomy, sometimes even to the extent of complete political separation in their own nation-state.&lt;ref&gt;Walter Pohl, "[http://www.kroraina.com/bulgar/pohl_etnicity.html Conceptions of Ethnicity in Early Medieval Studies]" ''Debating the Middle Ages: Issues and Readings'', ed. Lester K. Little and Barbara H. Rosenwein, (Blackwell), 1998, pp 13-24, notes that historians have projected the nineteenth-century conceptions of the nation-state backwards in time, employing biological metaphors of birth and growth: "that the peoples in the [[Migration Period]] had little to do with those heroic (or sometimes brutish) clichés is now generally accepted among historians," he remarked. Early medieval peoples were far less homogeneous than often thought, and Pohl follows Reinhard Wenskus,''Stammesbildung und Verfassung''. (Cologne and Graz) 1961, whose researches into the "ethnogenesis" of the [[Germanic people|German]] peoples convinced him that the idea of common origin, as expressed by [[Isidore of Seville]] ''Gens est multitude ab uno principle orta'' ("a people is a multitude stemming from one origin") which continues in the original ''Etymologiae'' IX.2.i) ''"sive ab alia natione secundum propriam collectionem distincta'' ("or distinguished from another people by its proper ties") was a myth.&lt;/ref&gt;  Under these conditions - when people moved from one state to another,&lt;ref&gt;Aihway Ong 1996 "Cultural Citizenship in the Making" in ''Current Anthropology'' 37(5)&lt;/ref&gt; or one state conquored or colonized peoples beyond its national boundaries - ethnic groups formed by people who identified with one nation, but who lived in another state.

==Ethno-national conflict==
Sometimes ethnic groups are subject to prejudicial attitudes and actions by the state or its constituents. In the twentieth century, people began to argue that conflicts among ethnic groups or between members of an ethnic group and the state can and should be resolved in one of two ways.  Some, like [[Jürgen Habermas]] and [[Bruce Barry]], have argued that the legitimacy of modern states must be based on a notion of political rights of autonomous individual subjects.  According to this view the state should not acknowledge ethnic, national or racial identity but rather instead enforce political and legal equality of all individuals.  Others, like [[Charles Taylor (philosopher)|Charles Taylor]] and [[Will Kymlicka]] argue that the notion of the autonomous individual is itself a cultural construct.  According to this view, states must recognize ethnic identity and develop processes through which the particular needs of ethnic groups can be accommodated within the boundaries of the nation-state.

The nineteenth century saw the development of the political ideology of [[ethnic nationalism]], when the concept of [[race]] was tied to [[nationalism]], first by German theorists including [[Johann Gottfried von Herder]]. Instances of societies focusing on ethnic ties arguably to the exclusion of history or historical context have resulted in the justification of nationalist goals. Two periods frequently cited as examples of this are the nineteenth century consolidation and expansion of the [[German Empire]] and the [[Third Reich|Third (Greater German) Reich]], each promoted on the pan-ethnic idea that these governments were only acquiring lands that had always been ethnically German. The history of late-comers to the nation-state model, such as those arising in the Near East and south-eastern Europe out of the dissolution of the Ottoman and Austro-Hungarian Empires, as well as those arising out of the former USSR, is marked by [[ethnic war|inter-ethnic conflicts]] that usually occurs within multi-ethnic states, as opposed to between them, in other regions of the world; thus, those other conflicts are often misleadingly labelled and characterized as "civil war."

In last decades of the twentieth century, mass migrations have occurred in most countries of the Northern hemisphere. The legal system as well as the official ideology emphasized race equality, and prohibited ethnic-based discrimination.

==Ethnicity in specific countries==

In the United States of America, collectives of related ethnic groups are typically denoted as "ethnic". Most prominently in the [[U.S.]], the various [[Latin American#Population|Latin American]] ethnic groups plus a racial mix of the [[Spanish people|Spanish]] or [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] are typically collectivized as, depending on the part of the country you are in, either "[[Hispanics]]" or "[[Latinos]]". The many previously designated '[[Oriental]]' ethnic groups are designated as [[Asia]]n ethnic groups and similarly lumped together as "Asians". The terms "[[Black people|Black]]" and "[[African-American]]," while different, usually describe the descendants whose ancestors, usually in predominant part, were indigenous to [[Africa]]. Even the racial term "[[White American]]s" are generally peoples originally from [[Europe]], who now live in [[North America]]. "[[Middle East]]erners" are peoples from the Middle-East, i.e. [[Southwest Asia]] and [[North Africa]]. These countries include [[Iran]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Egypt]], et cetera. (For a list of official ethnic categories according to the [[U.S. Census Bureau]], see [[Ethnicity (United States Census)]]).

In the United Kingdom, the classification of ethnic groups has attracted controversy in the past: particularly at the time of the 2001 Census where the existence and nature of such a classification, which appeared on the Census form, became more widely known than general. Different classifications, both formal and informal, are used in the UK. Perhaps the most accepted is the National Statistics classification, identical to that used in the 2001 Census in England and Wales (for list, see [[Ethnicity (United Kingdom)]]). In terms of use as opposed to official policy there is one main difference, the use of the term [[Oriental]] is widespread and without negative connotation in the UK and Europe while in the UK Asian is generally reserved for people from the Indian subcontinent (see [[Oriental]] and [[British Asian]] for more details).

[[People's Republic of China|China]] officially recognizes 56 ethnic groups of which the most numerous are the [[Han Chinese]]. Many of the ethnic minorities maintain their own individual culture and language, although many are also becoming more like the Han Chinese. Some of these groups suffered during the [[Cultural Revolution]]. Han Chinese dominate the whole of China with the exception of [[Tibet]] and [[Xinjiang]] where the Han are still in the minority. Sometimes people are given the choice of which ethnic group they wish to belong to, but 'mixed-race' is not an option. All ID cards in China state which ethnic group the holder belongs to. (For more details, see [[List of ethnic groups in China]] and [[Ethnic minorities in China]].)

Currently, the world's most ethnically diverse city is [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]], [[Canada]].{{Fact|date=August 2007}}

== See also ==
{{Wiktionary|ethnicity}}
*[[Clan]]
*[[Diaspora]]
*[[Ethnic autonomous regions]]
*[[Ethnic cleansing]]
*[[Ethnic minority]]
*[[Ethnic nationalism]]
*[[Ethnicity and health]]
*[[Ethnogenesis]]
*[[Ethnocentrism]]
*[[Genealogy]]
*[[Genetic genealogy]]
*[[German American]]
*[[Human Genome Diversity Project]] ([[HGDP]])
*[[Identity politics]]
*[[Kinship and Descent]]
*[[List of ethnic groups]]
*[[List of indigenous peoples]]
*[[List of stateless ethnic groups]]
*[[Meta-ethnicity]]
*[[Multiculturalism]]
*[[Nation]]
*[[National minority]]
*[[National symbol]]
*[[Non-exclusive ethnic group]]
*[[Passing (ethnic group)]]
*[[Population genetics]]
*[[Race]]
*[[Stateless nation]]
*[[Tribe]]

==Notes==
&lt;!--This article uses the Cite.php citation mechanism. If you would like more information on how to add references to this article, please see http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Cite/Cite.php --&gt;
{{reflist|2}}

==References==


* Abizadeh, Arash, [http://www.profs-polisci.mcgill.ca/abizadeh/Ethnicity.htm "Ethnicity, Race, and a Possible Humanity"] ''World Order'', 33.1 (2001): 23-34. (Article that explores the social construction of ethnicity and race.)
* Billinger, Michael S. (2007), [http://coa.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/27/1/5 "Another Look at Ethnicity as a Biological Concept: Moving Anthropology Beyond the Race Concept"] ''Critique of Anthropology'' '''27''',1:5–35.
* Dunnhaupt, Gerhard, "The Bewildering German Boundaries", in: ''Festschrift for P. M. Mitchell'' (Heidelberg: Winter 1989).
* Eysenck, H.J., ''Race, Education and Intelligence'' (London: Temple Smith, 1971) (ISBN 0-8511-7009-9)
* Friedlander, Judith, ''Being Indian in [[Hueyapan]]: A Study of Forced Identity in Contemporary Mexico'' (New York: Saint Martin's Press, 1975).
* [[Eric Hobsbawm|Hobsbawm, Eric]], and Terence Ranger, editors, ''The Invention of Tradition''.  (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1983).
* Morales-Díaz, Enrique; Gabriel Aquino; &amp; Michael Sletcher, "Ethnicity", in Michael Sletcher, ed., ''New England'', (Westport, CT, 2004).
* Sider, Gerald, ''Lumbee Indian Histories'' (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1993).
* {{citation|last=Smith|first= Anthony D.|year= 1987|title=The Ethnic Origins of Nations|publisher= Blackwell}}
* {{note|census}} [[U.S. Census Bureau]] [http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/meta/long_68178.htm State &amp; County QuickFacts: Race].
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- Please cite sources to help with the encyclopedia's general verifiability concerns. 

Tips for referencing:

For websites, use the formatting below (date/year are when you accessed the web page):
{{Web reference | title=Title of page | work=Title of Complete Work | url=http://www.example.com | date=Month Day | year=Year}}


For Books, use:
{{Book reference | Author=Lincoln, Abraham; Grant, U. S.; &amp; Davis, Jefferson | Title=Resolving Family Differences Peacefully | Publisher=Gettysburg: Printing Press | Year=1861 | Editor=Stephen A. Douglas | ID=ISBN 0-12-345678-9}}


For other sources, see: [[WP:CITET]]. Thanks!
--&gt;

[[Category:Ethnic groups| ]]
[[Category:Ethnicity| ]]
[[Category:Multiracial affairs]]

[[bs:Etnička grupa]]
[[bg:Етническа група]]
[[cs:Etnikum]]
[[cy:Grŵp ethnig]]
[[da:Etnicitet]]
[[de:Ethnie]]
[[et:Etnos]]
[[es:Etnia]]
[[eo:Etno]]
[[eu:Etnia]]
[[fr:Groupe ethnique]]
[[gl:Etnia]]
[[ko:민족]]
[[it:Etnia]]
[[he:אתניות]]
[[hu:Nemzetiség]]
[[ms:Etnik]]
[[nl:Etniciteit]]
[[ja:民族]]
[[no:Etnisitet]]
[[nn:Etnisitet]]
[[pl:Grupa etniczna]]
[[pt:Grupo étnico]]
[[ru:Этнос]]
[[simple:Ethnic group]]
[[sr:Етничка група]]
[[fi:Etninen ryhmä]]
[[sv:Etnicitet]]
[[uk:Етнос]]
[[zh:族群]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>