<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051112010013|28074943" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="105004" pageid="105004" ns="0" title="Ethnicity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-12T01:00:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">An '''ethnic group''' is a [[culture]] or [[subculture]] whose members are readily distinguishable by outsiders based on traits originating from a common [[racial]], [[nation]]al, [[linguistic]], or [[religious]] source. Members of an ethnic group are often presumed to be culturally or [[genetically]] similar, although this is not in fact necessarily the case.

Ethnic groups share a common origin, and exhibit a continuity in time, that is, a [[history]] and a future as a people.  This is achieved through the intergenerational transmission of common [[language]], [[institution]]s, [[Value_system|values]] and [[tradition]]s.  It is important to consider this characteristic of ethnic groups if we are to distinguish them from a group of individuals who share a common characteristic, such as ancestry, in a specific point in time.  On the political front, an ethnic group is distinguished from a [[nation-state]] by the former's lack of [[sovereignty]].

==In the West==
In the United States, the collectivity of immigrants from a region of the world and their descendants are called "ethnic groups" despite their lack of internal cohesion and common institutions and their inability to transmit language to the next generation.  Immigrants are socialized into identifying as a member of one of the list of "ethnic groups" provided by the [[US Census Bureau]] and with various "traditions" which, although often of recent invention, appeal to some notion of the past.  Thus Mexican nationals, upon crossing the border, become [[Hispanic]] ethnics. 

In the West, the notion of ethnicity, like [[race]] and [[nation]], developed in the context of European colonial expansion, when [[mercantilism]] and [[capitalism]] were promoting global movements of populations at the same time that [[state]] boundaries were being more clearly and rigidly defined.  In the nineteenth century, modern states generally sought legitimacy through their claim to represent "nations."  Nation-states, however, invariably include indigenous populations that were excluded from the nation-building project and such people typically constitute ethnic groups.  Members of ethnic groups, consequently, often understand their own identity in terms of something outside of the history of the nation-state -- either an alternate history, or in ahistorical terms, or in terms of a connection to another nation-state.  

The Spaniards called the different indigeneous communities of Mexico ''pueblos'' or ''naciones'' (communities or nations) depending on their size and importance.  In contemporary Mexico, "ethnic group" refers to the surviving indigenous territorial communities that maintain their distinct language and political, economic and social systems.  The [[Zapatista]] movement, which demands legal status for ethnic groups and their right to a common future as such, can only be understood with a definition of ethnic group as a territorial and social organization.  

Sometimes ethnic groups are subject to prejudicial attitudes and actions by the state or its constituents. In the twentieth century, people began to argue that conflicts among ethnic groups or between members of an ethnic group and the state can and should be resolved in one of two ways.  Some, like [[Jürgen Habermas]] and [[Bruce Barry]], have argued that the legitimacy of modern states must be based on a notion of political rights of autonomous individual subjects.  According to this view the state ought not to acknowledge ethnic, national or racial identity and should instead enforce political and legal equality of all individuals.  Others, like [[Charles Taylor (philosopher)|Charles Taylor]] and [[Will Kymlicka]] argue that the notion of the autonomous individual is itself a cultural construct, and that it is neither possible nor right to treat people as autonomous individuals.  According to this view, states must recognize ethnic identity and develop processes through which the particular needs of ethnic groups can be accommodated within the boundaries of the nation-state.

==Ethnicity==
While ethnicity and race are related concepts, the concept of ethnicity is rooted in the idea of societal groups, marked especially by shared [[nationality]], [[tribe|tribal]] affiliation, [[religion|religious]] faith, shared [[language]], or cultural and traditional origins and backgrounds, whereas race is rooted in the idea of [[biology|biological]] classification of [[Homo sapiens]] to [[subspecies]] according to arbitrarily chosen [[genotypic]] and/or [[phenotypic]] traits.

It is a term also used to justify real or imagined historic ties as well.  In [[English language|English]], ''Ethnicity'' goes far beyond the modern ties of a person to a particular [[nation]] (e.g., citizenship), and focuses more upon the connection to a perceived shared past and culture. See also [[Romanticism]], [[folklore]]. In other languages, the corresponding terms for ethnicity and [[nation]]hood can be closer to each other.

The [[19th century]] saw the development of the political ideology of [[ethnic nationalism]], when the vague concept of [[race]] was tied to [[nationalism]], first by German theorists including [[Johann Gottfried von Herder]]. Instances of societies focusing on ethnic ties to the exclusion of history or historical context arguably have resulted in almost fanatical self-justifying nationalist and/or imperialist goals. Two periods frequently cited as examples of this are the [[19th-century]] consolidation and expansion of the [[German Empire]], and the [[Third Reich]], each promoted on the theory that these governments were only re-possessing lands that had "always" been ethnically German. The history of late-comers to the nation state model, such as those arising in Near East and southeast Europe out of the dissolution of the Ottoman and Austro-Hungarian Empires, as well as those arising out of the former USSR, is particularly plagued with [[ethnic war|inter-ethnic conflicts]].

The term "ethnicity" may also be used to refer to a particular [[ethnic group]]: "People of various ethnicities."

Historically, the word "ethnic" signified "gentile," coming from the Greek adjective "ethnikos."  The adjective is derived from the noun ethnos, which meant foreign people or nations.  The noun "ethnic" ceased to be related to "heathen" in the early 18th century.  The use of the term ethnic in the modern sense began in the mid-20th century.

== See also ==
*[[List of ethnic groups]]
*[[Ethnic nationalism]]
*[[Ethnogenesis]]
*[[Ethnic origin]]
*[[Nation]]
*[[Identity politics]]
*[[List of stateless ethnic groups]]
*[[Stateless nation]]
*[[Ethnic minority]]
*[[National minority]]


[[Category:Ethnicity|*]]

[[cs:Etnie]]
[[de:Ethnie]]
[[da:Etnicitet]]
[[eo:Etno]]
[[fi:Etninen ryhmä]]
[[fr:Ethnie]]
[[he:אתניות]]
[[ja:民族]]
[[ms:Etnik]]
[[nl:Etniciteit]]
[[nn:Folkegrupper]]
[[pl:Grupa etniczna]]
[[simple:Ethnic group]]
[[sv:Etnicitet]]
[[tr:Budun]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>