<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114192912|171495775" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20971" pageid="20971" ns="0" title="Meritocracy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T19:30:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Articleissues|OR=August 2007|disputed=August 2007|refimprove=June 2006|article=y}}
{{Forms of government}}
'''Meritocracy''' is a [[-cracy|system of a government]] or another organization wherein appointments are made and responsibilities are given based on demonstrated [[ability]] ([[merit]]) and talent rather than by [[wealth]] ([[plutocracy]]), family connections ([[nepotism]]), [[social class|class]] privilege, [[cronyism]], popularity (as in [[democracy]]) or other historical determinants of [[social position]] and political power.  

The word "meritocracy" is now also often used to describe a type of [[society]] where wealth, position, and [[social status]] are in part assigned through [[competition]] or demonstrated talent and competence, on the premise that positions of trust, responsibility and social prestige should be earned, not inherited or assigned on arbitrary quotas.  Meritocracy is used{{Fact|date=February 2007}} both to describe or even criticize competitive societies, that could accept large [[social inequality|inequalities]] of income, wealth and status amongst the population as a function of perceived talent{{Fact|date=February 2007}}, merit, competence, motivation and effort.

==Origin of term==
The term 'meritocracy' was first used, in a pejorative sense, in [[Michael Young]]'s [[1958]] book ''[[Rise of the Meritocracy]]'', which is set in a [[dystopia]]n future in which one's social place is determined by [[Intelligence quotient|IQ]] plus effort. In the book, this social system ultimately leads to a social revolution in which the masses overthrow the elite, who have become arrogant and disconnected from the feelings of the public.

Despite the negative origin of the word, there are many who believe that a meritocratic system is a good thing for society. Proponents of meritocracy argue that a meritocratic system is more [[justice|just]] and more productive than other systems, and that it allows for an end to distinctions based on such arbitrary things as sex, race or social connections. Detractors of meritocracy, on the other hand, argue that the central [[dystopia]]n aspect of Young's conception -- the existence of a meritocratic class that monopolises access to merit and the symbols and markers of merit, and thereby perpetuates its own power, social status, and privilege -- has rapidly appeared in many if not all societies that have embraced meritocracy.

In writing the United States "Declaration of Independence" Thomas Jefferson relied heavily on Chapter Five of [[John Locke]]'s '''Second Treatise on Government''', which conceives of a society where the foundation of all property is solely the labour exerted by men. Locke argued that the acquisition of property was not morally wrong, if it were acquired through the exertion of labour ''and'' if it were in order to meet one's own immediate needs. So, he said, society is necessarily stratified, but by merit, not by birth. This doctrine of industry and merit as opposed to idleness and inheritance as the determining factor in a just society argued strongly against kings and governments of nobles and their lackeys, in favor of representative republicanism.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sheilaomalley.com/archives/001033.html&lt;/ref&gt; 

Often, opponents of the concept of meritocracy argue that characteristics such as intelligence or effort are simply impossible to measure accurately. Therefore, in their view, any implementation of meritocracy necessarily involves a high degree of guesswork and is inherently flawed.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} Those who support free markets, on the other hand, believe that the free market can and should determine both merit and reward. {{Fact|date=February 2007}}

==Social Darwinism==
{{Main|Social Darwinism}}
[[Social Darwinism]] is a [[social theory]] which holds that [[Charles Darwin|Darwin]]'s theory of [[evolution]] by [[natural selection]] is a model for the development of biological traits in a population and is sometimes incorrectly applied to human [[social institution]]s. Social Darwinism was at its most popular from the late [[19th century]] to the end of [[World War II]]. Proponents of Social Darwinism sometimes used the theory to justify [[social inequality]] as being meritocratic.

==Individual proponents==
===Confucius===
''"In teaching there should be no distinction of classes."''
''- [[Analects]] XV. 39. tr. Legge''
Many western admirers of [[Confucius]], like [[Voltaire]] or [[H. G. Creel]], have pointed out an innovative and revolutionary idea of Confucius': he replaced the nobility of blood with one of virtue. Jūnzǐ (君子), which had meant "superior person," coming from the contemporary meaning of the literal translation "son of the ruler," slowly took on a new meaning close to the English "[[gentleman]]."  A virtuous plebeian who cultivates his qualities could be a "gentleman", whilst a shameless son of a King was only a "small man." That he allowed any kind of student to be his disciple (his teachings were intended to train future rulers) is a clear indication that he didn't wholly support [[feudalism|feudal]] structures in Chinese society.

===Han Feizi===
In addition to Confucius, another ancient Chinese philosopher of the same period (the [[Warring States]]) advocated a meritocratic system of government and society. This was [[Han Feizi]] who was famous as being the foremost proponent of the School of Law (otherwise known as the philosophy of [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalism]]). The central tenet of his argument was the absolute rule of law, but there were also numerous meritocratic elements to be found {{Fact|date=February 2007}}. Another Legalist, [[Shang Yang]] implemented Legalist and meritocratic reforms in the state of [[Qin (state)|Qin]] by abolishing the aristocracy and promoting individuals based on skill, intelligence, and initiative. This led to the armies of the Qin having a critical edge over the other nations that adhered to old aristocratic systems of government. Legalism, along with its anti-aristocratic, pro-meritocratic ideals, remained a key part Chinese philosophy and politics for another two millennia, although after the Qin Dynasty it was heavily diluted.

===Genghis Khan===
Meritocracy was the primary basis for selection of chiefs and generals in the [[Mongol Empire]]. [[Genghis Khan]] chose whomever was talented and fit for his military chain of command. He even trusted generals and soldiers from opponents' armies if they showed loyalty to their leaders. For example, Genghis Khan's general [[Jebe]] had been an enemy soldier who had shot Genghis's horse in battle before he became Great [[Khan]].

===Napoleon===
[[Napoleon]]ic (Revolutionary) [[French Republic|France]] is also sometimes considered to have been meritocratic. After the [[French Revolution|revolution]] of [[1792]] hardly a member of the [[ancien regime|former elite]] remained. When Napoleon rose to power, there was no ancient base from which to draw his staff, and he had to choose the people he thought best for the job, including officers from his army, revolutionaries who had been in the peoples' assembly, and even some former aristocrats such as [[prime minister]] [[Talleyrand]]. This policy was summed up in Bonaparte's often-quoted phrase "''La carriere ouverte aux talents''", careers open to the talented, or as more freely translated by [[Thomas Carlyle]], "the tools to him that can handle them".  
A clear example is the order of the [[Légion d'honneur]], the first [[order of merit]], admitting all kind of men (cases of women have been found) not on ancestry or wealth, but on military, scientific or artistic prowess.

A later non-meritocratic practice, however, was the appointment of [[Bonaparte|family members]] and Corsican friends to important positions (specifically regional leadership); loyalty may have been a more important factor than sheer merit in performance, a common case in political situations.

===Thomas Jefferson===

[[Thomas Jefferson]] was a strong advocate of meritocratic types of government, believing they are superior to all other known forms of government; in more general terms, he believed a noble "natural aristocracy" would arise to look after the common good. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.sparknotes.com/biography/jefferson/section6.rhtml&lt;/ref&gt;

==Meritocratic states==
===Singapore===
Among modern nation-states, the Republic of [[Singapore]] claims to be a pure meritocracy, placing a great emphasis on identifying and grooming bright young citizens for positions of leadership{{Who|date=September 2007}}{{Fact|date=September 2007}}.  The Singaporean interpretation places overwhelming emphasis on academic credentials as objective measures of merit.{{Fact|date=September 2007}}

Meritocracy is a central political concept in Singapore, due in part to the circumstances surrounding the city-state's rise to independence{{Or|date=September 2007}}. Singapore was expelled from neighboring [[Malaysia]] in 1965 as a result of the unwillingness of the majority of its population, mostly ethnic Chinese, to accept a "special position" for the self-proclaimed bumiputera (Malay for "inheritors of the earth") Malays{{Fact|date=September 2007}}.  The federal Malaysian government had argued for a system which would give special privileges to the Malays as part of their "birthright" as an "indigenous" people. Political leaders in Singapore vehemently protested against this system, arguing instead for the equality of all citizens of Malaysia, with places in universities, government contracts, political appointments, etc., going to the most deserving candidate, rather than to one chosen on the basis of connections or ethnic background.  The ensuing animosity between State and Federal governments eventually proved irreconcilable.  Singapore was expelled, and became an independent city-state.  To this day, Singapore continues to hold up meritocracy as one of its official guiding principles for domestic public policy formulation.{{Fact|date=September 2007}} 

There is criticism from within that the increasing stratification of Singaporean society and the creation of an elite class based on a narrow segment of the population as a result of this system has some serious disadvantages.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.littlespeck.com/content/politics/CTrendsPolitics-061028.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Commentators have also criticized the city-state for not applying this principle uniformly, citing for example the disproportionate influence and presence of the family of the founding prime minister [[Lee Kuan Yew]] in both political and business circles.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} Although most Singaporeans still agreed that the city-state's tremendous economic success was due in part to its strong emphasis on developing and promoting talented leaders,&lt;ref&gt;http://app.amed.sg/internet/amed/read_content.asp?View,176,&lt;/ref&gt; there are [[Wee Shu Min elitism scandal|increasing signs]] that an increasing number of Singaporeans believe that Singapore is becoming an [[elitist]] society instead.&lt;ref&gt;http://tomorrow.sg/archives/2006/10/19/please_get_out_of_my_elite_uncar_1.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Grand Duchy of Finland===

Another example is the [[19th century]] [[Grand Duchy of Finland|Finland]], which was formally ruled by an [[autocrat]], though in practice governing was exercised by the educated class. Although ancestry and inherited wealth influenced one's educational opportunities, education and not ancestry was the principal requirement for admittance to, and promotion within, the civil service and government. Well into the mid-[[20th century]], academic degrees remained important factors for politicians asking for the electorate's confidence. Likewise, one's military rank in reserves has been a decisive factor on selecting leaders and managers both in public and private sector. Even today, most Finnish managers are amongst those who have attained are either NCO or reserve officer rank during their [[conscription|conscript]] tour of duty.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

===Venetian Republic===

{{sectstub}}
Lasting 1,112 years, the [[Republic of Venice]] at times used a system based on meritocracy to decide the membership of its ruling council. Each year, citizens were assessed based on the number of merit points earned through their successes — in [[academia]], for works or art, for business ventures, and so on — and the top names were appointed to the council. The council had a role encompassing legislative, judicial and executive functions. They elected a [[Doge of Venice|Doge]], on the understanding that any councillor who voted to appoint a Doge who took Venice to war ''and lost'' would, with that Doge, be put to death.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

==Meritocracy Online==

Although formal meritocracies are uncommon online, informal ones are much more prevalent. They often occur in online games such as [[MMORPG]]s where the best players are more likely to become [[Clan (computer gaming)|guild]] leaders or be otherwise influential.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A671500&lt;/ref&gt;, although the ability to invest large amounts of time and/or money is also important.

==Open Source==

There is a general tendency among open source projects for meritocracies: The more able a programmer seems to be, the higher his position (albeit informal) will be. The Apache Software Foundation is an example of an (open source) organization which officially is explicitly a meritocracy&lt;ref&gt;http://www.apache.org/foundation/how-it-works.html#meritocracy&lt;/ref&gt;.

==See also==
{{wiktionary|meritocracy}}
*[[Confucianism#Meritocracy|Meritocracy in China]]
*[[Participatory economics]]
*[[Participatory democracy]]
*[[Aristocracy]]
*[[Functionalism (sociology)]]
*[[Consensus democracy]]
*[[Majoritarianism]]
*[[Nepotism]]
*[[Racialism]]
*[[Militarism]]
*[[Geniocracy]]
*[[Technocracy (bureaucratic)|Technocracy]], the ruling by technicians that claim to apply rational principles rather than ideology.
*[[Differential Education Achievement]]

{{Forms of leadership}}

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.worldwidewords.org/topicalwords/tw-mer1.htm World Wide Words] &amp;mdash; Michael Quinion writes about the changing use of the term
*[http://www.reference.com/browse/wiki/Meritocracy Reference.com]
*[http://www.rouncefield.homestead.com/files/as_soc_ed_14.htm Discussion of Meritocracy including an Introduction and arguements on both sides of the issue]

[[Category:Forms of government]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]

[[bg:Меритокрация]]
[[ca:Meritocràcia]]
[[cs:Meritokracie]]
[[da:Meritokrati]]
[[de:Meritokratie]]
[[et:Meritokraatia]]
[[es:Meritocracia]]
[[eo:Meritokratio]]
[[eu:Meritokrazia]]
[[fa:شایسته‌سالاری]]
[[fr:Méritocratie]]
[[gl:Meritocracia]]
[[id:Meritokrasi]]
[[it:Meritocrazia]]
[[nl:Meritocratie]]
[[no:Meritokrati]]
[[pl:Merytokracja]]
[[pt:Meritocracia]]
[[ru:Меритократия]]
[[sr:Меритократија]]
[[sh:Meritokracija]]
[[fi:Meritokratia]]
[[sv:Meritokrati]]
[[uk:Меритократія]]
[[zh:精英政治]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>