<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041026234754|7290949" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20971" pageid="20971" ns="0" title="Meritocracy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-10T09:49:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Meritocracy''' is a system of [[government]] based on rule by ability rather than by wealth or social position. Ironically, the term was first used in a pejorative sense in [[Michael Young|Michael Young's]] [[1958]] book ''Rise of the Meritocracy'', which was written from the standpoint of a future in which one's social place is determined by [[IQ]] plus effort. In the book, this social system ultimately leads to a social revolution in which the masses overthrow the elite, who have become arrogant and disconnected from the feelings of the public.

Despite the negative origin of the word, there are many who believe that a meritocratic system is a good thing for society. Proponents of meritocracy argue that a meritocratic system is more [[justice|just]] and more productive than other systems, and allows for an end to distinctions based on [[social class]] or [[race]].  

There have been other criticisms of the notion of meritocracy in addition to Young's original criticism that a system in which social position is determined by objective characteristics would still be unegalitarian and unstable. Proponents of [[critical theory]] often argue that '''merit''' is defined by the power elite simply to legitimize a system in which social status is actually determined by class, birth, and wealth.

Most governmental systems contain some elements of meritocracy. For instance, in most [[representative democracy|representative democracies]], parties and voters use the performance of candidates in campaigning or in office to determine who should be re-elected and what senior positions they may hold. Elected officers usually also hire expert advisers to help formulate policies. However, pure meritocracies are virtually unknown. 

Among modern nation-states, perhaps the Republic of [[Singapore]] comes closest, with its relentless emphasis on identifying and grooming bright young citizens for positions of leadership. There is also a tremendous emphasis on the achievement of academic credentials, as these are seen as 'objective' and hence meritocratic measures of both intelligence and effort. Meritocracy is also an ingrained political concept in Singapore, and is located at the core of its ''founding myth''. Specifically, Singapore is seen to have been 'expelled' from neighbouring Malaysia in 1965 as a result of the unwillingness of its majority immigrant groups (especially the ethnic Chinese) to accept the special position of the indigenous communities (especially the Malays). The (federal) Malaysian government argued for a system which would give special privileges to the Malays as part of their birthright as indigenous people. In time, the federal government came to implement an affirmative action policy that favoured the numerically preponderant but economically backward indigenous groups. The Singapore government argued for the equality of all citizens of Malaysia, with places in universities, government contracts, political appointments &amp; etc going to the most deserving candidate, rather than one chosen on the basis of connections or ethnic background. In the ensuing conflict between State and Federal governments, Singapore was expelled in 1965 and became an independent city-state. Ever since, meritocracy has remained one of its core founding values, together with multi-racialism and, to a lesser extent, democracy and social justice. 

''Meritocracy'' is also the term often chosen to describe the condition of a government or other body that stresses formal education and competence more than other features, such as [[likeability]] or ancestry. An example is 19th century [[Grand Duchy of Finland|Finland]], that formally was ruled by an [[autocrat]] though the government in practice was left to the educated class. Although ancestry and inherited wealth influenced one's opportunities to get an education, education and not ancestry was the principal requirement for admittance to, and promotion within, the civil service and government. Well into the mid-20th century, academic degrees remained important features for politicians asking for the electorate's confidence.

Some would suggest that the [[military rank]]ing system is perhaps the closest system to pure meritocracy which can easily be found. People also suggest that the [[Internet]] and (other) [[open source]] / [[free software]] projects are run as a form of meritocracy as well. This might apply in particular to the [[Wikipedia]], considering its [[Wikipedia:Power structure|power structure]].

''Contrast with'': [[nepotism]]

==See also==
*[[Aristocracy]]
*[[Consensus democracy]]
*[[Majoritarianism]]
*[[Seniomeritocracy]]

[[de:Meritokratie]]
[[nl:Meritocratie]]

[[Category:Forms of government]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>