<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101117093545|397275239" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20971" pageid="20971" ns="0" title="Meritocracy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-17T21:12:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Sociology}}
{{Forms of government}}
'''Meritocracy''' is a system of government or another organization wherein [[appointment]]s are made and responsibilities assigned to individuals based upon demonstrated intelligence and ability ([[merit]]).

Meritocracy itself is not a form of government, but rather an [[ideology]]. Meritocracy itself is frequently confused as being a type of government, rather than correctly as a methodology or factor used in or for, the appointment of individuals to government. Individuals appointed to a meritocracy are judged based upon certain merits which could range from intelligence to morality to general aptitude to specific knowledge. A criticism of this methodology is that &lt;ref&gt;Arrow, Bowles and Durlauf&amp;nbsp;— Meritocracy and Economic Inequality, (Princeton, 1999)&lt;/ref&gt; "merit" itself is a highly subjective, vague term potentially lacking clarity allowing for potential misuse.

Meritocracy can also refer to a general act of judgment upon the basis of people's various demonstrated merits; such acts are frequently described in [[Sociology]] and [[Psychology]]. In [[Rhetoric]], the demonstration of one's merit regarding mastery of a particular subject is an essential task most directly related to the Aristotelian term ''[[Ethos]]''. The equivalent Aristotelian conception of meritocracy is based upon [[aristocracy|aristocratic]] or [[oligarchy|oligarchical]] structures rather than in the context of the modern [[nation state]].&lt;ref&gt;Aristot. Pol. 2.1261b&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aristotle, (351 BCE) ''Politics''. Book Three Part IV. (Jowett, B., Trans)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin of term==
The term itself was defined by [[United Kingdom|British]] politician and [[sociology|sociologist]], [[Michael Young (politician)|Michael Young]] in his 1958 [[satire|satirical]] [[essay]],&lt;ref name="riseofmeri"&gt;{{Citation | last = Young | first = Michael | authorlink = Michael Young (politician) | title = Rise of the Meritocracy | year = 1958 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = 
Down with meritocracy: The man who coined the word four decades ago wishes Tony Blair would stop using it | last = Young | first = Michael | authorlink = Michael Young (politician) | date = 29 June 2001 | journal = [[The Guardian]] | url = http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2001/jun/29/comment }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ford, Boris. 1992 ''The Cambridge cultural history of Britain.'' Cambridge University Press. p.34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kamolnick, Paul. 2005. ''The just meritocracy: IQ, class mobility, and American social policy.'' Greenwood Publishing Group. p.87.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Best, Shaun. 2005. ''Understand Social Divisions.'' SAGE. p.32.&lt;/ref&gt; "[[The Rise of the Meritocracy]]", which pictured the United Kingdom under the rule of a government favouring intelligence and aptitude (merit) above all. The essay is written in the first-person by a fictional historical narrator in 2032, and interweaves history from the politics of pre and post-war Britain with those of fictional future events in the short (1960 onwards) and long term (2020 onwards).&lt;ref name="young_p11"&gt;Young, Michael. (1958), p11&lt;/ref&gt;

The essay itself was based upon the tendency of the then-current governments in their striving towards intelligence to ignore  shortcomings and upon the failure of education systems to correctly utilize gifted and talented members within their civilizations.&lt;ref name="young_p13"&gt;Young, Michael. (1958), p13&lt;/ref&gt;

Young's fictional narrator describes that on one hand, the "stolid mass" or majority is not the greatest contributor to society, but the "creative minority" or "restless elite".&lt;ref name="young_p15"&gt;Young, Michael. (1958), p15&lt;/ref&gt; Yet on the other hand, describes that there are casualties of progress whose influence is underestimated and that from such stolid adherence to natural science and intelligence, arises arrogance and complacency.&lt;ref name="young_p15" /&gt; The casualties of this progress described by the phrase "Every selection of one is a rejection of many".&lt;ref name="young_p15" /&gt;

==Social Darwinism==
{{Main|Social Darwinism}}
[[Social Darwinism]] is a [[social theory]] which holds that [[Charles Darwin|Darwin]]'s theory of [[evolution]] by [[natural selection]] is a model, not only for the development of biological traits in a population, but also as an application for human [[social institution]]s&amp;nbsp;— the existing social institutions being implicitly declared as [[normative]]. Social Darwinism was at its most popular from the late 19th century to the end of [[World War II]]. Proponents of Social Darwinism argue that the theory justifies [[social inequality]] as being meritocratic. Darwin himself only ventured to propound his theories in a biological sense, and it is other thinkers and theorists who have applied Darwin's model to unequal endowments of human ambition.

==Historical examples==
===Han Feizi===
In addition to [[Confucius]], another ancient Chinese philosopher of the same period (that of the [[Warring States]]) advocated a meritocratic system of government and society. This was [[Han Feizi]] who was famous as the foremost proponent of the School of Law, otherwise known as the philosophy of [[Legalism]]. This had, as its central tenet, the absolute rule of law, but also contained numerous meritocratic elements. Another Legalist, [[Shang Yang]] implemented Legalist and meritocratic reforms in the state of [[Qin Dynasty|Qin]] by abolishing the aristocracy and promoting individuals based on their skill, intelligence, and initiative.

This led to the armies of the Qin gaining a critical edge over the other nations that adhered to old aristocratic systems of government. Legalism, along with its pro-meritocratic ideals, remained a key part of [[Chinese philosophy]] and politics for another two millennia, although after the Qin Dynasty it was heavily diluted. But meritocratic governance within the bureaucracy remains a key stone of Chinese government all the way to the present. This can be most clearly seen in the use of standardized "imperial examinations" to determine entry into the official class, which began in the [[Sui Dynasty]].

===Genghis Khan===
Meritocracy was the primary basis for selection of chiefs and generals in the Mongol Empire. Genghis Khan chose whomever was talented and fit for his military chain of command. He even trusted generals and soldiers from opponents' armies if they showed loyalty to their leaders. For example, Genghis Khan's general Jebe had been an enemy soldier who had shot Genghis in battle before he became Great Khan.

===Napoleon===
Napoleonic (Revolutionary) France is considered to have been meritocratic. After the revolution of 1792 hardly a member of the former elite remained. When Napoleon rose to power, there was no ancient base from which to draw his staff, and he had to choose the people he thought best for the job, including officers from his army, revolutionaries who had been in the peoples' assembly, and even some former aristocrats such as prime minister Talleyrand. This policy was summed up in Bonaparte's often-quoted phrase "La carrière ouverte aux talents", careers open to the talented, or as more freely translated by Thomas Carlyle, "the tools to him that can handle them". A clear example is the order of the Légion d'honneur, the first order of merit, admitting men of any class. They were judged not by ancestry or wealth but by military, scientific or artistic prowess.

==Meritocratic states==
===Singapore===
Among modern nation-states, the Republic of [[Singapore]] claims to be meritocratic, {{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} placing a great emphasis on identifying and grooming bright young citizens for positions of leadership (e.g., [[Lee Kuan Yew]]).{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}  The Singaporean interpretation places overwhelming emphasis on academic credentials as objective measures of merit.{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}} Meritocracy is one of the two pillars supporting all Singapore education policies since 1959, the other being social and religious harmony.

Meritocracy is a central political concept in Singapore, due in part to the circumstances surrounding the city-state's rise to independence.{{Or|date=September 2007}} Singapore was expelled from neighboring [[Malaysia]] in 1965 as a result of the unwillingness of the majority of its population, mostly ethnic Chinese, to accept a "special position" for the self-proclaimed [[Bumiputra]] (Malay for "inheritors of the earth"), the Malays.{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}  The federal Malaysian government had argued for a system which would give special privileges to the Malays as part of their "birthright" as an "indigenous" people. Political leaders in Singapore vehemently protested against this system, arguing instead for the equality of all citizens of Malaysia, with places in universities, government contracts, political appointments, etc., going to the most deserving candidates, rather than to those chosen on the basis of connections or ethnic background.  The ensuing animosity between State and Federal governments eventually proved irreconcilable;  Singapore was expelled and became an independent city-state.  To this day, Singapore continues to hold up meritocracy as one of its official guiding principles for domestic public policy formulation.&lt;ref&gt;http://app.mfa.gov.sg/data/paris/statements/REMARKS_FOR_MEDEF_28_Aug_08.html SPEECH BY SINGAPORE AMBASSADOR TO FRANCE, HIS EXCELLENCY BURHAN GAFOOR AT MEDEF UNVERSITE DEBATE AT L'ECOLE POLYTECHNIQUE, 28 AUGUST 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

There is criticism backed by evidence that this system has some serious disadvantages: for one, Singaporean society is being increasingly stratified; and, for another, an elite class is being created from just a narrow segment of the population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.littlespeck.com/content/politics/CTrendsPolitics-061028.htm Singapore's elites&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Commentators have also criticized the city-state for not applying the meritocracy principle uniformly; they cite, for example, the disproportionate influence and presence of the family of the founding prime minister [[Lee Kuan Yew]] in both political and business circles.&lt;ref&gt;[[Lee Kuan Yew]]&lt;/ref&gt; Although most Singaporeans still agree that the city-state's tremendous economic success has been due in part to its strong emphasis on developing and promoting talented leaders,&lt;ref&gt;http://app.amed.sg/internet/amed/read_content.asp?View,176&lt;/ref&gt; there are [[Wee Shu Min elitism scandal|more and more signs]] that an increasing number of Singaporeans believe Singapore is instead becoming an [[elitist]] society.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tomorrow.sg/archives/2006/10/19/please_get_out_of_my_elite_uncar_1.html Please, get out of my elite uncaring face&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Defendants claim the ancient Chinese proverb that 'Wealth does not pass three generations', suggesting that elitists will eventually be, and often are, replaced by those lower down the hierarchy. Indeed, many top political leaders in Singapore come from peasant backgrounds, while modern peasants boast about their great ancestry.

===Venetian Republic===
{{Expand section|date=May 2008}}
Lasting 1,112 years, the [[Republic of Venice]] at times used a system based on meritocracy to decide the membership of its ruling council. Each year, citizens were assessed based on the number of merit points earned through their successes&amp;nbsp;— in [[academia]], with works or art, in business ventures, and so on&amp;nbsp;— and the top names were appointed to the council. The council's role was legislative, judicial and executive, and it elected a [[Doge of Venice|Doge]], on the understanding that any councillor who voted to appoint a Doge who later took Venice to war ''and lost'' would, along with that Doge, be put to death.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} In practice, however, a relatively small number of influential families usually provided the bulk of the council nominees year after year.

==Computing==
===Meritocracy Online===
{{cquote|The great thing about the internet is it is a meritocracy and it's free.
|4=[[Damian Kulash]], [[OK Go]]
|5=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbc.ca/arts/music/story/2010/04/26/ok-go-video.html | work=CBC News | title=Behind OK Go's viral video | date=26 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Although formal meritocracies are uncommon online, informal ones are quite prevalent. They often occur in online games such as [[MMORPG]]s where the best players are more likely to become [[Clan (computer gaming)|guild]] leaders or be otherwise influential,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A671500 BBC - h2g2 - The Politics of Internet Discussion&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; although the ability to invest large amounts of time and/or money is also important. This is also the case for many discussion forums, since the most knowledgeable users often have better chances of becoming moderators.

Further, due to the nature of online interaction, where identity and anonymity are more readily managed than in direct interaction, the effects of social inequity can often be discounted in online communities.  Intelligence, effort, education, and personality may be readily conveyed in an online interaction but a person's gender, race, religion, and social standing can be easily obfuscated or left entirely unsaid.

===Open Source===
There is a tendency, in the structure of [[open source]] projects, for a meritocracy to arise. Technically, the more proficient the developer is in contributing towards the project; developing new features, or maintaining existing code, the more they are required or the more the project necessitates their contribution, and thus the more senior their informal position becomes. Those who contribute more code, and have more of an effect on the direction or status of the project, will tend to have more seniority and influence. The [[Apache Software Foundation]] is an example of an (open source) organization which officially claims to be a meritocracy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apache.org/foundation/how-it-works.html#meritocracy How the ASF works - The Apache Software Foundation&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wikimedia===
Meritocracy could consist in having [[responsibilities]] assigned to {{formatnum:4000}} individuals who produced more than {{formatnum:80}}% of [[english Wikipedia]]'s content.&lt;ref&gt;[http://stats.wikimedia.org/EN/ChartsWikipediaEN.htm Less than 5203 Wikipedians contribute presently 100 times or more a month]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
Meritocracy has been criticized as a myth which merely serves to justify the status quo; merit can always be defined as whatever results in success.

==See also==
* [[Equality of opportunity]] vs [[Equality of outcome]]
* [[Equality before the law]]
* [[Confucianism#Meritocracy|Meritocracy in China]]
* [[Jedem das Seine]]

'''Criticism:'''
* [[Functionalism (sociology)]]
* [[Differential Education Achievement]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|meritocracy}}
*[http://www.worldwidewords.org/topicalwords/tw-mer1.htm World Wide Words] &amp;mdash; Michael Quinion writes about the changing use of the term

[[Category:Political philosophy]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Forms of government]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]
[[Category:Affirmative action]]

[[ar:حكم بالاستحقاق]]
[[bg:Меритокрация]]
[[ca:Meritocràcia]]
[[ckb:مێریتۆکراسی]]
[[cs:Meritokracie]]
[[da:Meritokrati]]
[[de:Meritokratie]]
[[et:Meritokraatia]]
[[es:Meritocracia]]
[[eo:Meritokratio]]
[[eu:Meritokrazia]]
[[fa:شایسته‌سالاری]]
[[fr:Méritocratie]]
[[gl:Meritocracia]]
[[hr:Meritokracija]]
[[id:Meritokrasi]]
[[is:Verðleikaræði]]
[[it:Meritocrazia]]
[[he:מריטוקרטיה]]
[[ka:მერიტოკრატია]]
[[ms:Meritokrasi]]
[[nl:Meritocratie]]
[[ja:メリトクラシー]]
[[no:Meritokrati]]
[[pl:Merytokracja]]
[[pt:Meritocracia]]
[[ro:Meritocrație]]
[[ru:Меритократия]]
[[simple:Meritocracy]]
[[sk:Meritokracia]]
[[sr:Меритократија]]
[[sh:Meritokracija]]
[[fi:Meritokratia]]
[[sv:Meritokrati]]
[[th:คุณธรรมนิยม]]
[[tr:Meritokrasi]]
[[uk:Меритократія]]
[[zh:精英政治]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>