<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241123080516|1259086767" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="74892878" pageid="74892878" ns="0" title="Cosmetics policy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-23T08:05:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Regulation or law about the wearing of cosmetics}}
[[File:GCR TEAM.jpg|thumb|200px|Female warehouse workers in Russia wearing makeup, December 2021.]]
A '''cosmetics policy''' is a policy concerning the wearing of [[cosmetics]], which may be required or forbidden in different places and circumstances. A cosmetics policy that applies to only one sex, such as a policy requiring women to wear lipstick or a policy forbidding men to wear nail polish, is considered a form of sex discrimination by some critics. Sex-specific cosmetics policies may place burdens on women workers and may also present difficulties for [[Transphobia|transgender]] and [[Discrimination against non-binary people|non-binary people]]. Sex-specific cosmetics policies are legal in many jurisdictions.

==About==
While many companies have mandatory cosmetics policies for women workers, the expectation that women wear cosmetics at work is often "unspoken". A gendered "grooming gap" in the workplace may have negative consequences for women workers, who may have to spend more money and time on cosmetics than men. Women workers may be disciplined, fired, or paid less if they do not wear cosmetics in the workplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://inthesetimes.com/article/grooming-gap-women-economics-wage-gender-sexism-make-up-styling-dress-code |title=The Grooming Gap: What "Looking the Part" Costs Women |publisher=[[In These Times (publication)|In These Times]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Companies with formal policies requiring that women wear makeup or that men cannot wear makeup have historically been permitted to have these gendered policies by federal courts in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://witi.com/articles/1657/Sexism-and-Fashion-in-the-Workplace:-What-You-Should-Know/ |title=Sexism and Fashion in the Workplace: What You Should Know |publisher=[[Women in Technology International]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.shrm.org/resourcesandtools/hr-topics/employee-relations/pages/gender-discrimination-in-dress-codes.aspx |title=When Do Dress Codes That Perpetuate Gender Stereotypes Cross the Line? |publisher=[[Society for Human Resource Management]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==By jurisdiction==
===Japan===
Mandatory cosmetics policies for women workers are commonplace in [[Japan]]. Women workers in the beauty industry have been prohibited from wearing eyeglasses by some companies because the eyeglasses may prevent customers from clearly seeing the makeup worn by a worker. Japanese women have protested eyeglass bans and requirements for makeup and high heels on social media, but the policies remain legal in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/lisettevoytko/2019/11/08/dont-tell-us-what-to-wear-japanese-women-protest-workplace-glasses-ban/?sh=48f01aaf2e0d |title=‘Don’t Tell Us What To Wear’: Japanese Women Protest Workplace Glasses Ban |publisher=[[Forbes Magazine]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
In 2019, [[Virgin Atlantic]] airlines announced that they would no longer have a policy requiring women workers to wear makeup.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/business/2019/mar/04/virgin-atlantic-drops-mandatory-makeup-for-female-cabin-crew |title=Virgin Atlantic drops mandatory makeup for female cabin crew |publisher=[[The Guardian]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2022, [[British Airways]] changed their uniform policy to be gender neutral. Makeup is now optional for women workers and male workers are now allowed to wear makeup and nail polish.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cnn.com/travel/article/british-airways-males-staff-makeup-piercings-gbr-intl-scli/index.html |title=British Airways will let male staff wear makeup and piercings |publisher=[[CNN]] |accessdate=2023-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
====20th century====
[[File:Aircraft-worker-vega-aircraft-corporation-burbank-california.jpg|thumb|200px|Female aircraft worker of the Vega Aircraft Corporation at Burbank, California, checking the electro-installation, July 1942. The worker is wearing red lipstick.]]
In 1941, and for the duration of [[World War II]], the wearing of red lipstick became mandatory for women who joined the [[United States Army]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cnn.com/style/article/red-lipstick-history-beauty/index.html |title=Empowering, alluring, degenerate? The evolution of red lipstick |publisher=[[CNN]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====21st century====
In 2005, a worker alleged that she was dismissed from [[Harrah's Entertainment]] after she objected to the company's policy that women workers wear makeup. Her case, ''[[Jespersen v. Harrah's Operating Co.]]'', was considered by the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://money.cnn.com/2005/05/17/news/funny/lipstick/ |title=Woman fired for not wearing lipstick |publisher=[[CNN]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The court decided that she was "justly fired" for refusing to wear makeup.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2004-dec-29-na-harrahs29-story.html |title=Court Rules Bartender Was Justly Fired for Refusing to Wear Makeup |publisher=[[Los Angeles Times]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, a transgender teenager was instructed to remove her makeup before she could have her photograph taken for her drivers' license. A lawsuit against the South Carolina Department of Motor Vehicles resulted in a settlement allowing her to wear makeup in her photograph.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ibtimes.com/transgender-teen-chase-culpepper-wins-right-wear-makeup-dmv-photo-lgbt-lawsuit-1892092 |title=Transgender Teen Chase Culpepper Wins Right To Wear Makeup In DMV Photo; LGBT Lawsuit Settled |publisher=[[International Business Times]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017, a lawsuit in [[New Jersey]] alleged that a [[Cooper University Hospital]] worker was fired for wearing makeup to work. The worker claimed that a supervisor told him that "men should not wear make-up" in the workplace. The worker, a gay man, alleged discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation and [[gender non-conformity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nj.com/camden/2017/12/hospital_fired_gay_man_for_wearing_make-up_lawsuit.html |title=Hospital fired gay man for wearing makeup, lawsuit claims |publisher=[[NJ.com]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2018, a male student at [[Shadow Creek High School]] in [[Pearland, Texas]], was disciplined after wearing makeup to school. Following controversy, the school district reevaluated its dress code which stipulated that "Boys may not wear make-up".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.teenvogue.com/story/a-texas-school-district-is-reevaluating-its-dress-code-after-a-male-student-was-suspended-for-wearing-makeup |title=A Texas School District Is Reevaluating Its Dress Code After a Male Student Was Suspended for Wearing Makeup |publisher=[[Teen Vogue]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Soldier's Blue Book, issued by the [[United States Army Training and Doctrine Command]], states that men in the army are prohibited from wearing cosmetics unless medically necessary, but that women are permitted to wear cosmetics with any uniform as long as the cosmetics are applied "modestly and conservatively". Women in the army who wear cosmetics must apply cosmetics that "complement both the Soldier’s complexion and the uniform" and leadership are expected to "exercise good judgement" in enforcing the cosmetics policy. Women may not wear lipstick that "distinctly" differs from the shade of their lips and any cosmetics styles that are "Eccentric, exaggerated, or faddish" in their appearance are prohibited. Permanent cosmetics, including eyeliner and eyebrow makeup, may be permitted as long as it otherwise complies with the cosmetics guidelines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://usacimt.tradoc.army.mil/ltb/imtls/Reg/Soldier%27s%20Blue%20Book.pdf |title=The Soldier’s Blue Book |publisher=[[United States Army Center for Initial Military Training]] |accessdate=2023-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
[[Sheila Jeffreys]], a political science professor at the [[University of Melbourne]], has criticized policies mandating makeup, claiming that the wearing of makeup by women is often "not simply a matter of choice in the workplace, but the result of a system of power relations." She has compared compulsory makeup policies to compulsory [[burqa]] policies that exist in some Muslim-majority countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.smh.com.au/business/small-business/makeup-is-compulsory-20150709-gi88cn.html |title=Makeup is compulsory |publisher=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |accessdate=2023-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Gender-based dress codes]]
*[[High heel policy]]
*[[Trousers as women's clothing]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[https://www.nbcnews.com/leftfield/video/is-having-to-wear-makeup-sexist-1366295107910 Is having to wear makeup sexist?], [[NBC News]]
*[https://www.allure.com/story/should-makeup-be-required-in-the-workplace Should Makeup Be Required in the Workplace?], [[Allure (magazine)|Allure]]
*[https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/may/21/women-heels-makeup-guidance-sexist-dress-codes Opinion: Vague guidance won’t stop women being forced to wear heels and makeup], [[The Guardian]]
*[https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-wales-58086061 Sexism: Can my employer make me wear make-up and heels?], [[BBC]]

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Cosmetics law]]
[[Category:Discrimination against LGBTQ people]]
[[Category:Dress codes (legal)]]
[[Category:Labour law]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Transgender rights]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]
[[Category:Working conditions]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>