<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20220807220653|1102984759" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1021495" pageid="1021495" ns="0" title="Ethnocide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-10-19T10:44:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Extermination of a culture.}}
{{Genocide}}
'''Ethnocide''' is the [[cultural genocide|extermination of cultures]].&lt;ref name="Shaw2007"/&gt;&lt;ref name="AutoC2-1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="DelantyKumar2006"/&gt;

Reviewing the legal and the academic history of the usage of the terms genocide and ethnocide, [[Bartolomé Clavero]] differentiates them by stating that "Genocide kills people while ethnocide kills social cultures through the killing of individual souls".&lt;ref name="Clavero2008"/&gt; Ethnocide or [[cultural genocide]] is possible without a genocide.&lt;ref name="Shaw2007"&gt;{{cite book|author=Martin Shaw|title=What is Genocide|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sVnl-HgG4QEC&amp;pg=PA66|access-date=28 February 2013|date=20 March 2007|publisher=Polity|isbn=978-0-7456-3182-0|pages=66–67|quote= So the idea that ethnocide or 'cultural genocide' is distinct from physically violent genocide is misleading, since cultural genocide can only be the cultural dimension ''of'' genocide, something which is integral to every genocidal attack. ... It is better to refer to cultural suppression as the pre-genocidal denial of culture, because the cultural dimension of genocide or cultural suppression is part of a broader genocidal process, and it is different from unintentional group destruction or destruction which occurs when groups are destroyed by [[disease]]s and [[famine]]s which were originally unintended.|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200513203246/https://books.google.com/books?id=sVnl-HgG4QEC&amp;pg=PA65|archive-date=13 May 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because concepts such as cultural genocide and ethnocide have been used in different contexts, the anthropology of genocide examines their inclusion and exclusion in law and policies.&lt;ref name="BloxhamMoses2010"/&gt;

==Origin of the word==
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
[[Raphael Lemkin]], the linguist and lawyer who coined ''genocide'' in 1943 as the union of "the Greek word ''genos'' (race, tribe) and the Latin ''cide'' (killing)", also suggested ''ethnocide'' as an alternative form representing the same concept, using the Greek ''ethnos'' (nation) in place of ''genos''.&lt;ref name="AutoC2-1"/&gt; However, the term genocide has received much wider adoption than ethnocide.&lt;ref name="Shaw2007"/&gt;

==Usage==
As early as 1933, the lawyer [[Raphael Lemkin]] proposed that genocide had a cultural component, a component which he called "cultural genocide."&lt;ref name="AutoC2-2"/&gt; The term has since acquired rhetorical value as a phrase that is used to protest against the destruction of cultural heritage.

===Proposed usage===
{{wikisource|Draft United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples}}
{{wikisource|Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples}}
The drafters of the 1948 [[Genocide Convention]] considered the use of the term, but dropped it from their consideration.&lt;ref name="AutoC2-3"/&gt; The legal definition of [[genocide]] is left unspecific about the exact nature in which genocide is done only that it is destruction with [[genocidal intent|intent to destroy]] a racial, religious, ethnic or national group as such.&lt;ref name="AutoC2-4"/&gt;

Article 7 of a 1994 draft of the [[United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples]] uses the word "ethnocide" as well as the phrase "cultural genocide" but it does not define what they mean.&lt;ref name="AutoC2-5"/&gt; The complete article reads as follows:
:Indigenous peoples have the collective and individual right not to be subjected to ethnocide and [[cultural genocide]], including prevention of and redress for:
::(a) Any action which has the aim or effect of depriving them of their integrity as distinct peoples, or of their cultural values or ethnic identities;
::(b) Any action which has the aim or effect of dispossessing them of their lands, territories or resources;
::(c) Any form of [[population transfer]] which has the aim or effect of violating or undermining any of their rights;
::(d) Any form of [[acculturation|assimilation or integration]] by other cultures or ways of life imposed on them by legislative, administrative or other measures;
::(e) Any form of propaganda directed against them.

The [[United Nations]] Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples was adopted by the [[United Nations General Assembly]] during its 62nd session at [[UN Headquarters]] in [[New York City]] on 13 September 2007, but only mentions "genocide", not "cultural genocide", although the article is otherwise unchanged.

==Notions of ethnocide==

===UNESCO===
In [[UNESCO]]'s "Declaration of San Jose":&lt;ref name="Schabas2000"/&gt;

The Declaration of San Jose commits the United States and the nations of Central America to engage in a more in-depth discussion about a broad range of issues. These issues include: strengthening [[democracy]] and regional security, building trade and investment, combating [[crime]], drugs and [[corruption]], promoting dialogue on [[immigration]], and achieving more equitable and sustainable development.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/sanjose.htm#:~:targetText=The%20Declaration%20of%20San%20Jose,more%20equitable%20and%20sustainable%20development.|title=THE SAN JOSE DECLARATION|website=www.mtholyoke.edu|access-date=2019-11-29|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151022214211/https://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/sanjose.htm#:~:targetText=The%20Declaration%20of%20San%20Jose,more%20equitable%20and%20sustainable%20development.|archive-date=2015-10-22|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Declaration of San José, UNESCO also addresses and works to define ethnocide. UNESCO defines the term as follows:

{{blockquote|Ethnocide means that an ethnic group is denied the right to enjoy, develop and transmit its own [[culture]] and its own [[language]], whether collectively or individually. This involves an extreme form of massive violation of [[human rights]] and, in particular, the right of ethnic groups to respect for their cultural identity.}}

===Robert Jaulin===
{{main|Robert Jaulin#The concept of ethnocide}}
The French ethnologist [[Robert Jaulin]] (1928-1996) proposed a redefinition of the concept of ethnocide in 1970, to refer not  the ''means'' but the ''ends'' that define ethnocide.&lt;ref name="AutoC2-6"/&gt; Accordingly, the ethnocide would be the systematic destruction of the thought and the way of life of people different from those who carry out this enterprise of destruction. Whereas the genocide assassinates the people in their body, the ethnocide kills them in their spirit.

=== Pierre Clastres ===
In Chapter 4 of ''The Archeology of Violence'' by Pierre Clastres

Ethnocide, unlike genocide, is not based on the destruction of the physical person, but rather on the destruction of a person's culture. Ethnocide exterminates ways of thinking, living, and being from various cultures. It aims to destroy cultural differences, especially focused on the idea of "wrong" differences, that are present in a minority group by transforming the group's population into the culture norm of a certain place. This measuring of differences according to one's own culture is called ethnocentrism. The ethnocentric mind is based on the assumption that there is a hierarchy of superior and inferior cultures. Therefore, ethnocide hopes to raise inferior cultures to the status of superior cultures by any means necessary.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Archeology of Violence|last=Clastres|first=Pierre|publisher=Éditions du Seuil|year=1980|isbn=9781584350934|location=France|pages=Chapter 4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Barry Sautman ===
Barry Victor Sautman is a professor with the Division of Social Science at the [[Hong Kong University of Science and Technology]].&lt;blockquote&gt;The "intent that underlies ethnocide is not the same intent as the intent of cultural genocide, for the same reason that it is not tied to physical or biological destruction of a group. The intent is therefore typically aimed at forced assimilation and not on population decimation. Thus the intent that underlies ethnocide is an intentional act resulting in cultural death" &lt;ref&gt;Barry Sautman, ‘Cultural genocide and Asian state peripheries. Cultural genocide in international context’ New York: Palgrave Macmillan , 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=23em}}
* [[Cultural genocide]]
* [[Ethnic cleansing]]
* [[Forced assimilation]]
* [[Language death]]
* [[Linguistic discrimination]] (includes Linguicide)
* [[Policide]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist|2| refs=

&lt;ref name="AutoC2-1"&gt;Lemkin, Raphael. [http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/AxisRule1944-1.htm Acts Constituting a General (Transnational) Danger Considered as Offences Against the Law of Nations] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070526221818/http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/AxisRule1944-1.htm |date=2007-05-26 }}. Published 14 October 1933. Accessed 21 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="DelantyKumar2006"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Gerard Delanty|author2=Krishan Kumar|title=The SAGE Handbook of Nations and Nationalism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3Y3zK_jyagQC&amp;pg=PA326|access-date=28 February 2013|date=29 June 2006|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-1-4129-0101-7|pages=326|quote=The term 'ethnocide' has in the past been used as a replacement for cultural genocide (Palmer 1992; Smith 1991:30-3), with the obvious risk of confusing ethnicity and culture.|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140630200126/http://books.google.com/books?id=3Y3zK_jyagQC&amp;pg=PA326|archive-date=30 June 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Clavero2008"&gt;{{cite book|author=Bartolomé Clavero|title=Genocide Or Ethnocide, 1933-2007: How to Make, Unmake, and Remake Law with Words|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=f_-_0d8JMtEC&amp;pg=PA101|access-date=28 February 2013|year=2008|publisher=Giuffrè Editore|isbn=978-88-14-14277-2|pages=101|quote=Genocide kills people while ethnocide kills social cultures through the killing of individual souls.|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140630195703/http://books.google.com/books?id=f_-_0d8JMtEC&amp;pg=PA101|archive-date=30 June 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="BloxhamMoses2010"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Donald Bloxham|author2=A. Dirk Moses|title=The Oxford Handbook of Genocide Studies|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xCHMFHQRNtYC&amp;pg=PR2-IA92|access-date=28 February 2013|date=15 April 2010|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-161361-6|pages=2–|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140630192728/http://books.google.com/books?id=xCHMFHQRNtYC&amp;pg=PR2-IA92|archive-date=30 June 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoC2-2"&gt;[http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/madrid1933-english.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Acts Constituting a General (Transnational) Danger Considered as Offences Against the Law of Nations'' (J. Fussell trans., 2000) (1933)] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120716204853/http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/madrid1933-english.htm |date=2012-07-16 }}; [http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/AxisRule1944-3.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Axis Rule in Occupied Europe'', p. 91 (1944)] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120206214811/http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/AxisRule1944-3.htm |date=2012-02-06 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoC2-3"&gt;See [https://www.un.org/icty/krstic/TrialC1/judgement/krs-tj010802e-3.htm#IIIG2bi Prosecutor v. Krstic, Case No. IT-98-33-T (Int'l Crim. Trib. Yugo. Trial Chamber 2001), at para. 576] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081218125016/http://www.un.org/icty/krstic/TrialC1/judgement/krs-tj010802e-3.htm#IIIG2bi |date=2008-12-18 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoC2-4"&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm Convention on Prevention and Punishment of Genocide, art. 2, Dec. 9, 1948, 78 U.N.T.S. 277.] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20000408162107/http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm |date=April 8, 2000 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoC2-5"&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/E.CN.4.SUB.2.RES.1994.45.En?OpenDocument Draft United Nations declaration on the rights of indigenous peoples] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070804163536/http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/E.CN.4.SUB.2.RES.1994.45.En?OpenDocument |date=2007-08-04 }} drafted by The Sub-Commission on Prevention of Discrimination and Protection of Minorities Recalling  resolutions 1985/22 of 29 August 1985, 1991/30 of 29 August 1991, 1992/33 of 27 August 1992, 1993/46 of 26 August 1993, presented to the Commission on Human Rights and the Economic and Social Council at 36th meeting 26 August 1994 and adopted without a vote.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Schabas2000"&gt;{{cite book|author=William Schabas|title=Genocide in International Law: The Crime of Crimes|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pYptuRHDQPgC&amp;pg=PA189|access-date=3 March 2013|year=2000|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-78790-1|pages=189–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoC2-6"&gt;''La Paix blanche, Introduction à l'ethnocide'', Paris, Éditions du Seuil (Combats), 1970&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==External links==
{{wiktionary|ethnocide}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20120707083552/http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/genocide/ethnocide.htm Stein, Stuart D, ''Ethnocide'']{{Unreliable source?|date=April 2015|reason=Source says it is to be published and it's now offline except as archived; I don't have the encyclopedia that should have it.}}
*[http://www.massviolence.org/ethnocide Ethnocide by Barbara Lukunka in the encyclopedia of mass violence ]

{{Genocide topics}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Genocide]]
[[Category:Ethnic conflict]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>