<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20100830155910|381898496" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="804964" pageid="804964" ns="0" title="Dehumanization"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-04T13:03:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the Crucifix album|Dehumanization (album)}}
{{Unreferenced|date=January 2007}}{{Expert-subject|Psychology|date=July 2010}}

'''Dehumanization''' is the process by which members of a group of people assert the "inferiority" of another group through subtle or overt acts or statements.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} Dehumanization may be directed by an organization (such as a state) or may be the composite of individual sentiments and actions, as with some types of ''de facto'' [[racism]]. State-organized dehumanization has been directed against perceived racial or [[ethnic groups]], nationalities (or "foreigners" in general), [[religious group]]s, genders, minorities of various sexual orientations (e.g., [[homosexuals]]), [[disabled]] people as a class, economic (e.g., the [[homeless people|homeless]]) and [[social class]]es, and many other groups.

The concept of dehumanization has received empirical attention in the psychological literature (Deci &amp; Moller, 2010; Haslam et al., 2008). See: http://www.psychwiki.com/wiki/Dehumanization

==Nations and governments==
[[File:Alaskadeathtrapa.jpg|thumb|150px|A [[U.S. government]] poster from [[World War II]] depicting a [[Japan]]ese soldier as a rat.]]

[[Sociologist]]s and [[historian]]s often view dehumanization as central to some or all types of [[war]]s. Governments sometimes present "enemy" civilians or soldiers as less than human so that voters will be more likely to support a war they may otherwise consider mass murder. [[Dictatorship]]s use the same process to prevent opposition by citizens. Such efforts often depend on preexisting [[racist]], [[sectarianism|sectarian]] or otherwise biased beliefs, which governments play upon through various types of [[mass media|media]], presenting "enemies" as barbaric, undeserving of rights, and a threat to the nation. Alternately, states sometimes present the enemy ''government'' or way of life as barbaric and its citizens as childlike and incapable of managing their own affairs. Such arguments have been used as a pretext for [[colonialism]].

[[The Holocaust]] during [[World War II]] and the [[Rwandan Genocide]] have both been cited as atrocities predicated upon government-organized campaigns of dehumanization, while crimes like [[lynching]] (especially in the [[United States]]) are often thought of as the result of popular bigotry and government apathy. The main cause behind the [[American mutilation of Japanese war dead]] has been stated to be dehumanization.

[[Anthropologist]]s [[Ashley Montagu]] and [[Floyd Matson]] famously wrote that dehumanization might well be considered "the fifth horseman of the apocalypse" because of the inestimable damage it has dealt to society. When people become things, the logic follows, they become dispensable - and any atrocity can be justified.

Dehumanization can be seen outside of overtly violent conflicts, as in [[political debate]]s where opponents are presented as collectively stupid or inherently evil. Such "good-versus-evil" claims help end substantive debate (see also [[thought-terminating cliché]]).

==Themes: scapegoating, ethnic stereotypes, and racism==
A common theme is that of [[scapegoating]], where dehumanizing the target provides a release from [[guilt]] for the person that scapegoats them, who typically begins to see themselves as a victim of the dehumanized person, rather than as a potential oppressor.  
 
In war, the enemy is generally [[demonization|demonized]], with [[ethnic slur]]s being used to dehumanize them to the point where killing them becomes morally acceptable. The U.S. Army for example has a long history of dehumanizing names for its enemies. For example the Vietnamese were referred to as [[gook]], Somalis as "skinnys", and now Arabs as "hajis".

Furthermore, sub-minorities of  the [[Caucasian race|Caucasian]] population can be the subjects of dehumanization by the "accepted" majority. One such sub-minority are people with [[red hair]] and [[fair skin]] which have been the subject of dehumanization in both public and private arenas.

==Other topics==
The empirically-supported [[propaganda model]] of [[Edward S. Herman]] and [[Noam Chomsky]] shows how [[corporate media]] are able to carry out large-scale, successful dehumanization campaigns when that promotes the goals ([[Profit (economics)|profit]]-making) that the [[corporation]]s are contractually obliged to maximise.  [[State media]], in either [[democracies]] or [[dictatorship]]s, are also capable of carrying out dehumanization campaigns, to the extent with which the population is unable to counteract the dehumanizing [[meme]]s. {{Citation needed|date=November 2007}}

The dissections of human cadavers, was seen as dehumanizing in the [[Dark Ages]] (see [[History of anatomy#Medieval anatomy|Medieval anatomy]]), but now the importance of dissections as a training aid is more widely accepted.

==See also==
{{columns-list|2|
*[[Ethnic stereotype]]
*[[Life unworthy of life]]
*[[Nonperson]]
*[[Objectification]]
*[[Propaganda]]
*[[Race (classification of human beings)|Race]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Second-class citizen]]
*[[Sectarianism]]
*[[Social defeat]]
*[[Victimisation]]
}}

==References==

Moller, A. C., &amp; Deci, E. L. (2010). Interpersonal control, dehumanization, and violence: A self-determination theory perspective. Group Processes and Intergroup Relations, 13, 41-53. 

Haslam, N., Kashima, Y., Loughnan, S., Shi, J., &amp; Suitner, C. (2008). Subhuman, inhuman, and superhuman: Contrasting humans with nonhumans in three cultures. Social Cognition, 26(2), 248-258. doi:10.1521/soco.2008.26.2.248. 

{{abuse}}

[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Sociology]]

[[es:Deshumanización]]
[[sv:Avhumanisering]]
[[uk:Дегуманізація]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>