<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20220811000312|1103769648" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="60185328" pageid="60185328" ns="0" title="List of incidents of xenophobia during the Venezuelan refugee crisis"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-28T07:05:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|None}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expand-ethnic=yes}}
{{Lead too short|date=March 2022}}
Acts and displays of [[prejudice]], [[xenophobia]], [[discrimination]], [[Ethnic violence|violence]], and [[racism]] against Venezuelan migrants have intensified in the 2010s due to the [[Venezuelan refugee crisis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=SENTIMIENTO ANTI VENEZOLANO – La Nación|url=https://lanacion.com.ec/sentimiento-anti-venezolano/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==
=== Independence period ===
[[File:Flag of Ecuador (1845–1860).svg|thumb|right|250px|Flag of Ecuador between 1845 and 1861 ([[Época Marcista]]), used in place of the Bolivarian tricolor that was then associated with the dictatorship of Venezuelan general [[Juan José Flores]].]]

After the [[Spanish American wars of independence]], Venezuelans came to hold key positions in the administration of the nascent republics. This unleashed the resentment of the local populations, who held revolts to expel the foreigners. In September 1828 in [[Bogotá]], the [[Septembrina Conspiracy]] was carried out; this was an attempt to assassinate the leader [[Simón Bolívar]], who was supported by the Venezuelan military and in opposition to the generals and Nueva-Granadian lawyers led by [[Francisco de Paula Santander]]. These events would lead to the dissolution of the Bolivarian projects of [[Gran Colombia]] and [[Republic of New Granada|New Granada]] (today [[Colombia]] and [[Panama]]) three years later, with [[Ecuador]] and [[Venezuela]] achieving total independence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Melo|first=Jorge Orlando|title=Bolivar en Colombia: conservador y revolucionario|url=https://www.academia.edu/4035604|journal=Boletín de la Academia Nacional de la Historia, Caracas|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For his part, Bolívar also imposed an authoritarian regime in [[Peru]], where Venezuelan troops committed various abuses. The unpopular [[Bolivarian Constitution]] was repealed in 1827 and Peru went to war with Gran Colombia the following year, shortly after intervening in [[Bolivia]] in support of the rebels who wished to overthrow the regime of the Venezuelan [[Antonio José de Sucre]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://elcomercio.pe/eldominical/articulos-historicos/simon-bolivar-heroe-villano-noticia-516116|title=Simón Bolívar: ¿Héroe o villano?|last=Laos|first=Jorge Paredes|date=2018-05-01|website=El Comercio|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.abc.es/historia/abci-traiciones-y-dictadura-autentico-simon-bolivar-millonario-espanol-hizo-revolucionario-201806280113_noticia.html|title=Traiciones y dictadura del auténtico Simón Bolívar: el millonario "español" que se hizo revolucionario|date=2018-06-27|website=abc|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://educared.fundaciontelefonica.com.pe/sites/independencia-peru/independencia_2c.htm|title=La independencia - La Independecia del Perú - Educared Perú - Estudiantes|website=educared.fundaciontelefonica.com.pe}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://latam.historyplay.tv/hoy-en-la-historia/peru-invade-territorio-boliviano-para-expulsar-las-tropas-bolivarianas|title=Perú invade territorio boliviano para expulsar a las tropas bolivarianas|last=superuser|date=2014-02-03|website=History Channel|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Ecuador, the Venezuelan [[Juan José Flores]] continued to rule as a dictator until 1845, the year in which the Marcista Revolution or Nationalist Revolution occurred, an uprising that had among its objectives the expulsion foreign troops that still remained in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.eltelegrafo.com.ec/noticias/columnistas/1/la-revolucion-marcista|title=La Revolución Marcista|date=2014-03-06|website=El Telégrafo - Noticias del Ecuador y del mundo|language=es-es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.eluniverso.com/2006/03/06/0001/18/9B0BB0F6789B4945BEED8CB66BB7A730.html|title=La revolución nacionalista del 6 de Marzo de 1845 - MAR. 06, 2006 - El Gran Guayaquil - Historicos - EL UNIVERSO|website=www.eluniverso.com|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Petroleum boom ===
With the advent of the oil boom in the 1970s, the Venezuelan economy experienced unprecedented growth. This caused Venezuelans to be stereotyped as opulent, arrogant or "''[[wikt:agringar#Spanish|agringados]]''", partly due to the xenophobia they committed against the population of border regions and against the increased numbers of migrants who moved to the country.&lt;ref name=Inmigrantes&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2018-03-05/venezuelans-go-home-xenophobia-spreads-as-refugees-flee-crisis|title=Venezuelans, Go Home: Xenophobia Haunts Refugees|date=March 5, 2018|via=www.bloomberg.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.las2orillas.co/ahora-los-venezolanos-los-mojados/|title=Ahora los venezolanos son "los mojados"|date=2017-07-14|website=Las2orillas|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Chavismo and crisis ===
{{Crisis in Bolivarian Venezuela short}}
When [[Hugo Chávez]] came to power relations with several countries deteriorated, to the point that the Colombian government denounced the existence of a project of Venezuelan imperialism over the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.semana.com/on-line/articulo/palabras-del-presidente-alvaro-uribe-respuesta-su-homologo-venezolano-hugo-chavez/89744-3/|title=Palabras del presidente Álvaro Uribe en respuesta a su homólogo venezolano Hugo Chávez|date=November 25, 2007|website=Semana.com Últimas Noticias de Colombia y el Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to various sources, the Venezuelan government was interfering in the governments of [[Argentina]], Bolivia, and several Caribbean islands, as well as outwardly supporting the [[Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.abc.com.py/edicion-impresa/economia/preocupa-en-bolivia-injerencia-venezolana-918171.html|title=Preocupa en Bolivia injerencia venezolana - Economía - ABC Color|website=www.abc.com.py|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://elpais.com/internacional/2008/09/24/actualidad/1222207211_850215.html|title=El testigo clave del 'caso del maletín' dice que Chávez envió 5 millones de dólares a Cristina Fernández|date=2008-09-24|work=El País|access-date=2019-09-19|language=es|issn=1134-6582}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/mundo/noticias/2015/01/150127_eeuu_venezuela_petrocaribe_tsb|title=¿Quiere EE.UU. destronar a Petrocaribe?|last=Sparrow|first=Thomas|website=BBC News Mundo|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.eltiempo.com/archivo/documento/MAM-3823809|title=Chávez apoya a las Farc, dice reporte de inteligencia de E.U.|date=2010-02-04|website=El Tiempo|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ideological rejection of [[Chavismo]] and [[Madurismo]] gained a growing xenophobia following the daily departure of thousands of Venezuelans due to the [[Crisis in Venezuela|economic crisis that the country has been going through since 2013]]. According to the [[United Nations|UN]], by the beginning of 2019 the number of refugees from Venezuela in other countries reached about 3.5 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.infobae.com/america/venezuela/2019/02/22/onu-ya-son-casi-tres-millones-y-medio-de-venezolanos-los-que-huyeron-de-la-crisis/|title=ONU: ya son casi tres millones y medio de venezolanos los que huyeron de la crisis|website=Infobae|language=es-ES|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the fact that regional governments have welcomed migrants in solidarity, Venezuelans have been accused of influencing higher unemployment and crime rates, and have become victims of harassment, insults and even violence by citizens of different countries.&lt;ref name="Inmigrantes" /&gt;

== By country ==

=== Bolivia ===
In March 2019, a group of 14 [[Venezuelans]] were arrested by immigration authorities for protesting in front of [[Cuba]]'s embassy in [[La Paz]]. Six of them were expelled from the country, since according to the government:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.la-razon.com/nacional/bolivia-venezolanos-expulsion-ciudadanos-conspiracion_0_3113088673.html|title=Bolivia expulsa a 6 venezolanos por actividades conspirativas - La Razón|website=www.la-razon.com|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Once the immigration interviews were completed, it was identified that these citizens do not have legal trade or legal reason for their stay in the country. They confessed to being involved in conspiratorial activities, and participating in political activities that affect public order, in exchange for money.|sign=|source=}}

However, the action was condemned by organizations such as [[Amnesty International]], which felt that the expulsion was arbitrary and done as part of systematic persecution against Venezuelan migrants due to the close relationship of the government of [[Evo Morales]] with the regime of [[Nicolás Maduro]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.france24.com/es/20190330-venezolanos-bolivia-solidaridad-derechos|title=Venezolanos en Bolivia: entre la solidaridad y la violación de sus derechos|date=2019-03-29|website=France 24|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Brazil ===
[[File:Conflictos sociales en Paracaima.jpg|300px|An attack on a Venezuelan migrant population in [[Pacaraima]], [[Brazil]], in August 2018.|alt=|thumb]]In August 2018, the government of the border state of [[Roraima]] requested a temporary closure of the border, claiming that its administration was unable to control the large number of Venezuelans who entered the country daily. Initially, Judge Helder Girão Barreto ordered the suspension of land entry of Venezuelans, but later the measure was revoked by the [[Supreme Court of Brazil|Supreme Court]], which considered that the prohibition was contrary to the Constitution and international pacts signed by Brazil.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.rcnradio.com/internacional/supremo-de-brasil-rechaza-cerrar-frontera-con-venezuela-tras-orden-de-juez|title=Supremo de Brasil rechaza cerrar frontera con Venezuela, tras orden de juez|date=2018-08-07|website=RCN Radio|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Days later, a Venezuelan refugee camp was attacked in the municipality of Pacaraima. A mob armed with provincial weapons set fire to tents and other belongings of the immigrants, forcing more than 1,200 back over the border. The events occurred in retaliation for the alleged attack on a Brazilian merchant by four Venezuelans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Ataque a venezolanos en Brasil: disturbios en Pacaraima contra campamento de inmigrantes|url=https://www.bbc.com/mundo/noticias-america-latina-45240028|access-date=27 January 2019|date=20 August 2018|publisher=BBC Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Then-presidential candidate [[Jair Bolsonaro]] said the government should not turn its back on popular sentiment in Roraima, and proposed the creation of refugee camps with the help of the UN.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://elcomercio.pe/mundo/latinoamerica/brasil-jair-bolsonaro-sugiere-crear-campos-refugiados-venezolanos-venezuela-noticia-550369|title=Bolsonaro sugiere crear campos de refugiados para venezolanos|date=2018-08-24|website=El Comercio|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once he became president, Bolsonaro said he would adopt more rigorous criteria for the entry of foreigners to Brazil, but ruled that he would not return Venezuelan immigrants to their country.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://elcomercio.pe/mundo/latinoamerica/brasil-jair-bolsonaro-devolvera-venezolanos-roraima-anuncia-control-migratorio-noticia-580848|title=Jair Bolsonaro no devolverá a venezolanos en Roraima pero anuncia control migratorio|date=2018-11-24|website=El Comercio|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Chile ===
{{see also|Tarapacá migrant crisis}}
In May 2017, Venezuelan protesters were confronted by a group of Chileans who showed their support for the government of Nicolás Maduro in the vicinity of the Venezuelan embassy in [[Santiago]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cnnchile.com/pais/chilenos-se-enfrentan-manifestantes-venezolanos-en-santiago_20170520/|title=Chilenos se enfrentan a manifestantes venezolanos en Santiago|first=C. N. N.|last=Chile|website=CNN Chile}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some months later, Venezuelans protesting in the same place were beaten and robbed by Chilean communists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.el-nacional.com/noticias/mundo/comunistas-chile-golpearon-robaron-manifestantes-venezolanos_196529 |title=Comunistas en Chile golpearon y robaron a manifestantes venezolanos |access-date=2019-09-19 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190424021753/http://www.el-nacional.com/noticias/mundo/comunistas-chile-golpearon-robaron-manifestantes-venezolanos_196529 |archive-date=2019-04-24 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2018, a disabled woman attacked an immigrant woman in Santiago with a cane, while calling her a communist and saying she voted for [[Sebastián Piñera]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.elnacional.com/sociedad/chilena-protagonizo-ataque-xenofobo-hacia-una-venezolana_67898/|title=Chilena protagonizó ataque xenófobo hacia una venezolana|date=2018-01-15|website=EL NACIONAL|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same month, a driver from [[Valparaíso]] shouted "Venezuelan piece of shit" at an immigrant who was working in a gas station, before attacking him with a broom.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.adnradio.cl/noticias/nacional/mujer-trata-de-venezolano-de-mierda-a-trabajador-de-bencinera-en-valparaiso/20180115/nota/3689721.aspx|title=Mujer trata de 'venezolano de mierda' a trabajador de bencinera en Valparaíso|date=2018-01-15|website=www.adnradio.cl|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2019, during a match between the U-20 teams of Chile and Venezuela, Chilean soccer player [[Nicolás Díaz Huincales]] called the Venezuelan player [[Pablo Bonilla]] "starving to death". Subsequently, the Chilean player offered public apologies through a letter.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.infobae.com/america/deportes/2019/01/20/muerto-de-hambre-la-agresion-de-un-futbolista-chileno-a-su-colega-de-venezuela-que-genera-indignacion/|title="Muerto de hambre": la agresión de un futbolista chileno a su colega de Venezuela que genera indignación|website=Infobae|language=es-ES|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Chilean woman also referred to an immigrant she worked with "starving to death" in [[Cartagena, Chile|Cartagena]] later in the month.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://thetimes.cl/noticia/436/instagram-ardiente-nicki-minaj-en-una-comprometedora-pose-y-un-bodysuit-diminuto|title=Instagram ardiente: Nicki Minaj en una comprometedora pose y un bodysuit diminuto|date=2019-08-12|website=THE TIMES CHILE|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February of the same year, following the publication of a video where a group of Chileans and Venezuelans offended the victims of [[Augusto Pinochet]], left-wing citizens launched a virtual campaign calling on people not to help immigrants and asking for expulsion of the ''venecos'' and ''venezorranas'', both offensive slurs against Venezuelans specifically.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.latercera.com/opinion/noticia/campana-xenofoba-venezolanos/546138/|title=Campaña xenófoba contra venezolanos|date=2019-02-27|website=La Tercera|language=es-CL|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to statements by the Dominican consul in [[Arica]], the Chilean border police deny entry to any immigrant who is black or Venezuelan and does not carry prepaid documents and tickets detailing where they will stay and when they will return.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ismorbo.com/inmigracion-en-chile-no-entras-si-eres-negro-o-venezolano/|title=Inmigración en Chile: "No entras si eres negro o venezolano"|date=2017-06-29|website=MOR.BO|language=es-CL|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 25, 2021, residents of [[Iquique]] organised a protest against recent immigrants, most of whom are Venezuelans.&lt;ref name=France24-sept26&gt;{{Cite news|title=Fiscalía chilena abre investigación por violenta protesta contra venezolanos en Iquique|url=https://www.france24.com/es/minuto-a-minuto/20210926-fiscal%C3%ADa-chilena-abre-investigaci%C3%B3n-por-violenta-protesta-contra-venezolanos-en-iquique|date=2021-09-26|access-date=2021-09-27|work=[[France 24]]|language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the protests an incident occurred in which a group of protesters sat the belongings of migrants afire.&lt;ref name=Adn25sept&gt;{{Cite news|title=Manifestantes en Iquique quemaron carpas y pertenencias de inmigrantes que se encontraban en avenida Aeropuerto|url=https://www.adnradio.cl/nacional/2021/09/25/manifestantes-en-iquique-quemaron-carpas-y-pertenencias-de-inmigrantes-que-se-encontraban-en-avenida-aeropuerto.html|date=2021-09-25|access-date=2021-09-26|work=[[ADN Radio Chile|ADN Radio]]|language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chilean [[Parquet (legal)|Public Ministry]] ordered an investigation to identify and prosecute the responsibles for the arson.&lt;ref name=France24-sept26/&gt;

=== Colombia ===
{{see also|Venezuela–Colombia migrant crisis}}
In January 2017, while delivering houses built by the Ministry of Housing to displaced people in the border town of [[Tibú]], then-Vice President [[Germán Vargas Lleras]] said:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://noticias.canalrcn.com/nacional-pais/vargas-lleras-casas-gratis-no-vayan-dejar-meter-los-venecos-no-venecos|title=Vargas Lleras sobre casas gratis: "no vayan a dejar meter a los 'venecos', esto no es para 'venecos'"|website=Vargas Lleras sobre casas gratis: "no vayan a dejar meter a los 'venecos', esto no es para 'venecos'"|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|They are for displaced population, but those in Tibú, they are not going to let the "venecos" get there, for all in the world, they are not for the "venecos".|sign=|source=}}

Although Vargas Lleras later said that his use of "veneco" was only as a demonym, the Venezuelan president Nicolás Maduro said it was a xenophobic aggression and demanded an apology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.lafm.com.co/colombia/german-vargas-lleras-termino-veneco-no-nada-despectivo|title=Germán Vargas Lleras: el término 'veneco' "no es para nada despectivo"|date=2017-01-27|website=www.lafm.com.co|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.semana.com/nacion/multimedia/maduro-acusa-a-vargas-lleras-de-xenofobo/513793/|title=Maduro acusa a Vargas Lleras de xenófobo|date=January 29, 2017|website=Semana.com Últimas Noticias de Colombia y el Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2017, Rodolfo Hernández, mayor of [[Bucaramanga]], said that from Venezuela it was the beggars, prostitutes and unemployed who had arrived, and that it was not possible to throw them out, but the city was unable to respond to the crisis.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.rcnradio.com/colombia/santanderes/se-vinieron-los-limosneros-desocupados-venezuela-aca-alcalde-bucaramanga|title=Se vinieron los limosneros y desocupados de Venezuela para acá: Alcalde de Bucaramanga|website=RCN Radio|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2017, there was a confrontation between Colombian and Venezuelan street vendors for the control of the spaces within the [[TransMilenio]] system, which left one person dead.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://noticias.caracoltv.com/bogota/pelea-de-vendedores-ambulantes-colombianos-y-venezolanos-en-bogota-habria-causado-un-muerto|title=Pelea de vendedores ambulantes colombianos y venezolanos en Bogotá habría causado un muerto|date=2017-09-15|website=Noticias Caracol|language=ES|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the end of 2017, threatening pamphlets against Venezuelans began circulating in the border cities of [[Cúcuta]] and [[Arauca, Arauca|Arauca]]. Among the groups involved in delivering these threats were the ELN, the Clan del Golfo, and the Arauca Social Cleansing Group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.semana.com/nacion/articulo/xenofobia-en-colombia-contra-los-venezolanos/569808/|title=Alerta por xenofobia en contra de los venezolanos en Colombia|date=June 2, 2018|website=Semana.com Últimas Noticias de Colombia y el Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2018, a group of young people launched incendiary bombs at 900 Venezuelans who were in a refuge in a sports center in Cúcuta.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.elespectador.com/noticias/nacional/atacan-con-bombas-incendiarias-venezolanos-en-cucuta-articulo-734891|title=Atacan con bombas incendiarias a venezolanos en Cúcuta|date=2018-01-23|website=ELESPECTADOR.COM|language=ES|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2018, an audio clip began circulating in which military threats were made against immigrants who did not leave the municipality of [[Subachoque]] within two weeks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://conexioncapital.co/xenofobia-contra-venezolanos-en-subachoque-alerta-a-la-poblacion/|title=Xenofobia contra venezolanos en Subachoque alerta a la población|last=Bermúdez|first=Jessica|date=2018-05-22|website=Conexión Capital|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2018, a Venezuelan was lynched in [[Ciudad Bolívar, Bogotá|Ciudad Bolívar]], after being connected to the kidnapping of children through fake [[WhatsApp]] chains. At least 200 citizens participated in the lynching using stones, sticks and machetes. After this, two Venezuelans were about to be lynched in the same place and two other migrants were beaten in Transmilenio.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://hsbnoticias.com/noticias/bogota/xenofobia-tras-linchamiento-venezolanos-denuncian-persecucio-474577|title=¿Xenofobia? Tras linchamiento, venezolanos denuncian persecución y bomba social [VIDEOS]|date=October 28, 2018|website=hsbnoticias.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.eltiempo.com/justicia/investigacion/la-historia-detras-del-hombre-que-fue-linchado-en-bogota-por-una-falsa-noticia-289508|title=La verdadera historia del hombre linchado por falsa noticia en redes|date=2018-11-03|website=El Tiempo|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2019, threatening pamphlets appeared against Venezuelans residing in [[Ipiales]], near the border with Ecuador. The authorities consider that the phenomenon occurred due to the return of a Venezuelan population from Ecuador, where there were attacks against immigrants in the previous weeks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://diariodelsur.com.co/noticias/local/en-narino-priorizan-combatir-actos-de-xenofobia-contra-ciuda-495280|title=En Nariño priorizan combatir actos de xenofobia contra ciudadanos venezolanos|date=January 26, 2019|website=diariodelsur.com.co}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2019, mayor Rodolfo Hernández said Venezuelans were "factories for making poor ''[[wikt:chino#Spanish#Etymology 3|chinitos]]''".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.elespectador.com/noticias/nacional/alcalde-de-bucaramanga-afirmo-que-venezolanas-son-fabricas-de-hacer-chinitos-pobres-articulo-838724|title=Alcalde de Bucaramanga afirmó que venezolanas son "fábricas de hacer chinitos pobres"|date=2019-02-08|website=ELESPECTADOR.COM|language=ES|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Five months later, journalist Claudia Palacios wrote a column in the newspaper ''[[El Tiempo (Colombia)|El Tiempo]]'' urging Venezuelans to stop giving birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.eltiempo.com/opinion/columnistas/claudia-palacios/paren-de-parir-columna-de-claudia-isabel-palacios-giraldo-374742|title=Paren de parir|date=2019-06-12|website=El Tiempo|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2019, five quartered bodies were found in Bogotá, three of them belonging to Venezuelan citizens.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.publimetro.co/co/bogota/2019/07/25/tres-de-los-cuerpos-desmembrados.html|title=Tres de los cuerpos desmembrados hallados en Bogotá son de venezolanos|last=Rincón|first=Ginna|website=Publimetro Colombia|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August of the same year, threatening pamphlets appeared in Bucaramanga, demanding that the city's merchants replace their Venezuelan workers within 48 hours.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.elespectador.com/noticias/nacional/santander/denuncian-panfletos-amenazantes-contra-venezolanos-en-bucaramanga-articulo-873862|title=Denuncian panfletos amenazantes contra venezolanos en Bucaramanga|date=2019-08-01|website=ELESPECTADOR.COM|language=ES|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the increase in the number of Venezuelan immigrants seeking housing in Bogotá, there are reports that in several places it is common to find advertisements saying "For rent: no Venezuelans."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sumarium.es/2018/11/30/bogotanos-se-niegan-a-alquilar-viviendas-a-los-venezolanos/|title=Bogotanos se niegan a alquilar viviendas a los venezolanos – Sumarium}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the campaign for the 2018 presidential elections, a common accusation among the candidates was that their competition wanted to make Colombia a second Venezuela.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.portafolio.co/economia/gobierno/posibilidad-que-colombia-se-convierta-en-una-venezuela-515262|title=¿Qué posibilidad real hay de que Petro convierta a Colombia en una Venezuela?|first=Casa Editorial El|last=Tiempo|website=Portafolio.co}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pulzo.com/elecciones-2018/venezolanizacion-colombia-vendra-manos-uribismo-PP463290|title=Si Colombia se 'venezolaniza' no será a manos de Petro, sino de Duque (Uribe)|website=pulzo.com|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the conservative candidate Alejandro Ordóñez said that in the face of massive migration of Venezuelans, businessmen should prioritize the right to work of Colombians.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://caracol.com.co/programa/2018/03/06/6am_hoy_por_hoy/1520344363_005604.html|title=Priorizar el derecho al trabajo de los colombianos pide Alejandro Ordóñez|date=2018-03-06|website=Caracol Radio|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ordóñez was subsequently appointed Colombian ambassador to the [[Organization of American States]], a position from which he said that Venezuelan migration was part of an agenda to radiate socialism throughout Latin America.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.wradio.com.co/noticias/actualidad/ordonez-afirma-que-migracion-venezolana-es-estrategia-para-diseminar-el-socialismo/20190503/nota/3898041.aspx|title=Ordóñez afirma que migración venezolana es estrategia para 'diseminar el socialismo'|date=2019-05-03|website=www.wradio.com.co|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a survey published by ''Semana'' magazine in March 2019, 41% of migrants had suffered some type of rejection or discrimination. However, 81% of respondents said they had not been the victim of any crime because of their nationality, and most of them described Colombians as kind and friendly people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.semana.com/nacion/articulo/la-primera-encuesta-para-conocer-que-piensan-y-como-viven-los-venezolanos-q/604701/|title=Los migrantes venezolanos tienen la palabra|date=March 9, 2019|website=Semana.com Últimas Noticias de Colombia y el Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Curaçao ===
In 2017, 1,203 Venezuelans were deported from [[Curaçao]]. Many of them were even forced to pay their return ticket.

Through a fierce removal strategy, Venezuelans without stability are deported before they can apply for refugee status. Despite the claims of organizations such as [[Amnesty International]]. In November 2018, the [[Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations]] of the [[Netherlands]] (the country to which the island belongs) stated that the government would not investigate the matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/nov/13/venezuelan-migrants-caribbean-islands|title=Venezuelan migrants seek refuge in Caribbean islands|work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ecuador ===
In August 2018, the Ecuadorian government issued a decree requiring Venezuelans who would like to enter the country to present valid passports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Ecuador exigirá a extranjeros presentación de pasaporte para ingresar al país
|url=https://www.eluniverso.com/noticias/2018/08/16/nota/6908318/ecuador-exigira-venezolanos-presentacion-pasaporte-ingresar-pais |website=El Universo|access-date=27 January 2019|date=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, a judge suspended the application of the decree, arguing that it contradicted the international agreements signed by Ecuador.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Jueza amplía plazo para ingreso de ciudadanos venezolanos sin pasaporte|url=https://www.elcomercio.com/actualidad/medidas-cautelares-efecto-pasaporte-venezolanos.html |website=El Comercio|date=24 August 2018 |access-date=27 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October of the same year, a march by Venezuelans in [[Quito]] was confronted by a group of citizens who threatened to burn immigrants alive, while calling on the government for greater immigration controls. One of the group participants stated:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://larepublica.pe/mundo/1331452-youtube-ecuatorianos-amenazan-quemar-vivos-venezolanos-marcha-video-yt-crisis-nicolas-maduro-lenin-moreno/|title=YouTube: ecuatorianos amenazan con quemar vivos a venezolanos [VIDEO]|date=2019-05-28|website=larepublica.pe|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|We are tired that Venezuelans in addition to their conceit, their arrogance, that they come to steal, to kill, all against us. I don't know what they demand, nor do I know who would organize that march, but we want to avoid confrontation.|sign=|source=}}

In January 2019, after the brutal murder of an Ecuadorian woman at the hands of a Venezuelan in [[Ibarra, Ecuador|Ibarra]], there were a series of attacks against migrants, including forced evictions and burning of property. A few hours after the murder, President [[Lenín Moreno|Lenin Moreno]] had declared:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://caracol.com.co/radio/2019/01/21/internacional/1548068682_107721.html|title=Brotes de xenofobia por caso de feminicidio en Ecuador|last=AFP|date=2019-01-21|website=Caracol Radio|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Ecuador is and will be a country of peace. I will not let any antisocial people take it away from us. The integrity of our mothers, daughters and friends is my priority.

I have arranged for the immediate formation of brigades to monitor the legal situation of Venezuelan immigrants in the streets, in the workplace and on the border.

We have opened the doors, but we will not sacrifice anyone's safety.|sign=|source=}}

Moreno received harsh criticism for these statements, as some groups felt that his words prompted xenophobia.{{Citation needed|date=November 2020}} Venezuelan president Nicolás Maduro called Moreno a "nazi", "fascist" and a traitor.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ecuavisa.com/articulo/noticias/internacionales/451686-maduro-califica-moreno-nazi-traidor|title=Maduro califica a Moreno de "nazi" y "traidor"|date=2019-01-23|website=Ecuavisa|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Days later, Ecuador began to demand that Venezuelans entering the country show their criminal records, while some 250 migrants returned to Venezuela as part of a humanitarian corridor created by the Venezuelan government itself because of increased anti-Venezuelan sentiment after the event.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.elcomercio.com/actualidad/certificado-antecedentes-penales-frontera-colombia.html|title=La exigencia del certificado de antecedentes penales sorprendió a venezolanos en Rumichaca|website=El Comercio|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ecuavisa.com/articulo/noticias/politica/451461-venezolanos-dejan-ecuador-tras-incidentes-ibarra|title=Venezolanos dejan Ecuador tras incidentes en Ibarra|date=2019-01-23|website=Ecuavisa|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Hungary ===
Despite its anti-immigration rhetoric following the [[European migrant crisis]], the government of [[Viktor Orbán]] has welcomed hundreds of Venezuelan migrants who have proven to have at least one Hungarian ancestor. However, the reception has not been as positive, with several citizens complaining to the police about the presence of black Venezuelans in the surroundings of the spa of [[Balatonőszöd|Balatonoszod]], where immigrants were initially housed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/mundo/noticias-america-latina-47441135|title=Por qué el gobierno antiinmigrante de Hungría recibe en silencio a cientos de venezolanos|newspaper=BBC News Mundo }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Iran ===
During the [[2017 Iranian presidential election|2017 presidential elections]], the reformist press used the word ''venezueloi'' ("Venezuelanization"), to criticize the government for taking a course similar to that of the [[Nicolás Maduro]] regime and to warn of the possibility of an economic crisis similar to that of Venezuela.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/mundo/noticias-america-latina-47170209|title=Rusia, Turquía, India, Zimbabue... : por qué lo que sucede en Venezuela interesa tanto fuera del continente|last=Gozzer|first=Stefania|date=2019-02-21|access-date=2019-09-19|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Relevance inline|date=September 2019}}

=== Panama ===
In November 2016, the National Front of the Panamanian People called a protest under the slogan "no more [[arepa]]s, no more [[tequeño]]s" (in reference to two typical dishes of Venezuela). The organizers of the march argued that Venezuelan migrants harmed the country's economy, displacing local workers and increasing crime. The march generated alarm among some groups, but in the end it only gathered a few dozen people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.diariolasamericas.com/america-latina/marcha-panama-contra-inmigrantes-venezolanos-genera-alarma-n4108217|title=Marcha en Panamá contra inmigrantes venezolanos genera alarma|website=diariolasamericas.com|language=es-ES|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.elimpulso.com/2016/11/20/fotos-asi-fue-la-marcha-en-contra-de-los-venezolanos-en-panama-20nov/|title=FOTOS: Así fue "la marcha" en contra de los venezolanos en Panamá #20Nov|last=Vidal|first=Brian|date=2016-11-20|website=El Impulso|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2017, president [[Juan Carlos Varela]] announced that a visa would be required for Venezuelans traveling to Panama, citing economic and security reasons:

{{quote|In the face of the [[Crisis in Venezuela|rupture of the democratic order in Venezuela]], a situation that puts our security, our economy and the sources of employment of Panamanians at risk, and after thorough consideration, I have made the decision to demand a visa from Venezuelan citizens who want to travel to Panama|sign=|source=}}

The Venezuelan government considered the measure anti-integrationist and said they would act with reciprocity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.eltiempo.com/mundo/venezuela/venezuela-responde-a-panama-sobre-exigencia-de-visa-a-ciudadanos-122558|title=Venezuela rechaza exigencia de visa a ciudadanos por parte de Panamá|date=2017-08-23|website=El Tiempo|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly thereafter, advertisements appeared in which Panamanian bars offered discounts to those who beat Venezuelan immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://tn.com.ar/internacional/xenofobia-en-panama-premian-con-descuentos-en-bares-al-que-golpee-un-venezolano_816604|title=Xenofobia en Panamá: "premian" con descuentos en bares al que golpee a un venezolano - TN.com.ar|date=2017-08-29|website=Todo Noticias|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Peru ===
[[File:Los_venezolanos_buenos_en_Perú_somos_más.jpg|alt=|thumb|Campaign slogan saying "We the good Venezuelans in Peru are more"]]
It is reported that many Venezuelan criminals have arrived in Peru and continued to commit crimes, which causes the increase in xenophobia. In March 2018, an anti-Venezuelan campaign was spread on social networks, during which banners with the slogan "Peru without Venezuelans" were seen on several bridges in [[Lima]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://es.panampost.com/sabrina-martin/2018/03/06/exiliados-venezolanos-xenofobia/|title=Rechazo masivo en Perú a campaña xenófoba contra exiliados venezolanos|date=2018-03-06|website=PanAm Post|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2018, a person was injured after clashes between Peruvians and Venezuelans in the Lima district of [[San Martín de Porres District|San Martín de Porres]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.americatv.com.pe/noticias/actualidad/persona-resulto-herida-durante-pelea-entre-peruanos-y-venezolanos-n326562|title=Una persona resultó herida durante pelea entre peruanos y venezolanos|website=América Noticias|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2018, marches were called to reject the presence of Venezuelan immigrants in Peru.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://800noticias.com/xenofobia-asi-fue-una-protesta-en-el-peru-por-la-llegada-de-miles-de-venezolanos|title=¡Xenofobia! Así fue una protesta en el Perú por la llegada de miles de venezolanos {{!}} 800Noticias|website=800noticias.com|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2018, the Peruvian government introduced a passport requirement from those Venezuelans who intended to enter the country, but the measure was suspended in October, when the courts ruled that this requirement was against with the commitments Peru must follow as part of [[Mercosur]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://elcomercio.pe/peru/venezolanos-podran-ingresar-peru-pasaporte-noticia-564940|title=Venezolanos podrán ingresar a Perú sin pasaporte|date=2018-10-05|website=El Comercio|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same month, 89 Venezuelans returned to their country sponsored by their own government. Nicolás Maduro said that his countrymen had been victims of a hate campaign, and that in Peru they had only found racism, contempt, economic persecution and slavery.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.americatv.com.pe/noticias/internacionales/nicolas-maduro-denuncia-campana-desprecio-contra-venezolanos-peru-n336346|title=Nicolás Maduro denuncia campaña de odio contra venezolanos en Perú|website=América Noticias|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2019, a Venezuelan was killed after fights between Venezuelans and Peruvians in the district of Chao (La Libertad).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://diariocorreo.pe/edicion/la-libertad/fiesta-de-aniversario-en-distrito-liberteno-termina-en-gresca-con-balacera-video-863293/|title=Venezolano pierde la vida tras balacera en fiesta de aniversario de distrito liberteño (VIDEO)|date=2019-01-07|website=Diario Correo|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same month there were clashes between Venezuelans protesting in front of their country's embassy in Lima and Peruvian citizens who demanded that their government close the borders.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://peru21.pe/lima/enfrentamientos-protesta-venezolanos-lima-nuevo-mandato-nicolas-maduro-nndc-452429-noticia/|title=Enfrentamientos durante protesta de venezolanos en Lima contra Nicolás Maduro|date=2019-01-11|website=Peru21|language=es|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[International Organization for Migration]], 35% of Venezuelans living in Peru have suffered acts of xenophobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.france24.com/es/20180819-venezuela-xenofobia-racismo-discriminacion|title=Trabas burocráticas y ataques xenófobos contra venezolanos en América Latina|date=2018-08-19|website=France 24|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2019, news was given of the discovery of two mutilated bodies whose remains had been distributed in different parts of Lima. After some investigations, the police reported that the bodies belonged to a citizen of Venezuelan origin and a Peruvian, apparently killed due to deals with a foreign criminal organization. In videos obtained from the security cameras of a hotel in San Martín de Porres, where both victims were killed, it was discovered that those involved in the crime were five Venezuelan nationals, three men and two women, one of whom already had a criminal record for homicide, who are seen moving the remains to a vehicle. This news spurred a wave of hatred and panic towards Venezuelan immigrants in social networks. The border security was also criticized, with the government of [[Martín Vizcarra]] facing condemnation for allowing the entry of the criminals.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

=== Trinidad and Tobago ===
In April 2018, 82 Venezuelan asylum seekers were deported from Trinidad and Tobago, which violated international laws on the matter. Given the criticism issued by [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|UNHCR]], Prime Minister [[Keith Rowley]] said he would not allow the UN or any other agency to "turn his country into a refugee camp". Venezuelan migrants in Trinidad and Tobago are victims of widespread discrimination, since unlike other countries, no refugee reception plan has been implemented on the islands so it is hard to find legal work without being sent back.&lt;ref name="Islas"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/nov/13/venezuelan-migrants-caribbean-islands|title=Venezuelan migrants live in shadows on Caribbean's sunshine islands|first=Bram|last=Ebus|date=November 13, 2018|via=www.theguardian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Internet ==
With the [[hyperinflation in Venezuela]] and the devalued [[Venezuelan bolívar]], many Venezuelans have turned to virtual [[gold farming]] in [[massively multiplayer online role-playing game]]s (MMORPG) like [[Tibia (video game)|Tibia]] and [[RuneScape]]. In [[Reddit]], a user published a racially abusive guide on how to kill Venezuelans in the “[[Player versus player|player-v-player]]” places where the gold farming takes place; the guide was followed by intemperate comments. The moderators removed the post and the comments afterwards.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2019/11/21/venezuelas-paper-currency-is-worthless-so-its-people-seek-virtual-gold|title=Venezuela's paper currency is worthless, so its people seek virtual gold|date=21 November 2019|newspaper=The Economist|access-date=2019-11-26|issn=0013-0613}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Anti-Chilean sentiment]]
* [[Anti-Mexican sentiment]]
* [[Venezuelan refugee crisis]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Anti-national sentiment|Venezuelan]]
[[Category:Foreign relations of Venezuela]]
[[Category:Hispanophobia|Venezuelan]]
[[Category:Venezuelan refugee crisis]]
[[Category:Venezuela-related lists|xenophobia]]
[[Category:Xenophobia|Venezuelan]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>