<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20060701175717|61567022" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1586266" pageid="1586266" ns="0" title="Blood quantum laws"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-08-13T05:40:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Blood Quantum Laws''' is an umbrella term that describes  legislation enacted to define membership in [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] groups. "Blood quantum" refers to attempts to calculate the degree of racial inheritance for a given individual.

The [[Dawes Act]], also known as the General Allotment Act, was part of a federal initiative to "civilize" the Indians by forcing them into Western cultural and legal practices. The strategy of this Act was to take lands held in common by tribes as reservations and break them up into individually-owned parcels. Parcels of land were given to individuals who could prove that they were members of the tribe who owned the land, and the remainder was often opened for white settlement. Tribes set their own membership requirements, and many used blood quantum as part of the necessary qualification. 

Many Indian tribes continue to employ blood quantum in their own current tribal laws to determine who is eligible for membership in the tribe. These often require a minimum degree of blood relationship and often an ancestor listed in a specific tribal [[census]] from the late 1800s or early 1900s. The [[Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians]] of [[North Carolina]], for example, require an ancestor listed in the 1924 Baker census and a minimum of 1/32 Cherokee blood inherited from their ancestor(s) on that roll. Meanwhile the Western Cherokee require applicants to descend from an ancestor in the 1906 Dawes roll (direct lineal ancestry), but impose no minimum blood quantum requirement. The [[Ute Tribe|Ute]] require a 5/8 blood quantum, the highest requirement of any U.S. tribe, while the [[Miccosukee]] of [[Florida]], the [[Mississippi]] [[Choctaw]] and the [[St. Croix Band of Chippewa Indians|St. Croix]] [[Chippewa]] of [[Wisconsin]] all require 1/2 "tribal blood quantum". At the other end of the scale, the [[Mashantucket Pequots|Mashantucket]] [[Pequot]] of [[Connecticut]] and the [[Sac and Fox]] of [[Oklahoma]] both require 1/16, whereas the [[Confederated Tribes of the Grand Ronde Community of Oregon]] require a combined minimum of 1/16 from any of a list of several [[Oregon]] indigenous peoples. A 1/4 blood requirement is by far the most common, along with requirements of "Lineal descendency" which do not specify any minimum tribal ancestry.

Critics of the laws say they have been used to discriminate against Blacks and Native Americans and deny them their [[civil rights]] as well as pre-empt the right of tribes to determine themselves who is and who is not a member. Contemporary defenders point out that U.S. tribes set their own rules to determine tribal membership, and that they can decide on their own whether or not to employ blood quantum. Groups such as the [[Cherokee Freedman]] and others claim they are denied tribal rights based on the blood quantum laws. The base rolls recorded blacks simply as blacks despite the fact that they had been made members of the tribe and even when they may have had some degree of Indian blood.

Federal blood quantum laws continue to affect benefits that some individuals of Indian descent receive from the Federal government, independent of tribal law. For example, in [[1985]], the [[US Congress]] passed the ''Quarter Blood Amendment Act'' to determine which Indian students were eligible for Indian education programs and tuition-free attendance at the [[U.S. Bureau of Indian Affairs|Bureau of Indian Affairs]] or contract schools. This must be verified by obtaining a [[Certificate of Degree of Indian Blood]] which is sometimes also used for tribal determinations.

== External links ==
* [http://www.weyanoke.org/jdf-BloodQuantum.html Blood Quantum: A Relic Of Racism And Termination]

[[Category:Native American law]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>