<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151110072304|689929698" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1586266" pageid="1586266" ns="0" title="Blood quantum laws"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-10T07:26:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Indian Blood|ethnic Indians of the Indian subcontinent of South Asia|ethnic Indian|ethnic aboriginals of the Americas|Indigenous peoples of the Americas|the play by A. R. Gurney|Indian Blood (play)}}
{{redirect|blood quantum|the CSI novel|CSI: Blood Quantum|other topics|blood purity (disambiguation)}}
{{about|laws concerning establishing if a person is an aboriginal of the Americas|laws establishing if a person is of Black African ancestry|One-drop rule|Nazi Germany laws concerning German-ness, Jewish-ness and otherness|Racial policy of Nazi Germany}}
[[Image:Creeks in Oklahoma.png|300px|right|thumb|Members of the [[Muscogee (Creek) Nation]] in [[Oklahoma]] around 1877, including some with European and African ancestry&lt;ref&gt;Charles Hudson, ''The Southeastern Indians'', 1976, pg. 479&lt;/ref&gt;]]
'''Blood quantum laws''' or '''Indian blood laws''' are legislation enacted in the United States to define membership in [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] tribes or nations. A person's blood quantum (aka BQ) is the percentage of their ancestors, out of their total ancestors, who are documented as full-blood Native Americans. For instance, a person who has one parent who is a full-blood Native American, and one who has no Native ancestry, has a blood quantum of 1/2.  Tribes that use blood quantum as part of their enrollment criteria may set different requirements. For instance, the [[Omaha people]] require a blood quantum of 1/4 for enrollment. 

Its use started in 1705 when [[Virginia]] adopted laws that limited colonial civil rights of Native Americans and persons of half or more Native American ancestry.&lt;ref name="ucd"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nas.ucdavis.edu/Forbes/Blood_Quantum_II.html|title=THE BLOOD GROWS THINNER :BLOOD QUANTUM, PART 2|author=Professor Jack D. Forbes |accessdate=2009-08-07 |year=2008 |publisher=[[University of California|University of California-Davis]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; The concept of blood quantum was not widely applied until the [[Indian Reorganization Act]] of 1934. The [[United States government|government]] used it to establish the individuals who could be recognized as Native American and be eligible for financial and other benefits under treaties that were made or sales of land.&lt;ref name="nar"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=955032|title= A Legal History of Blood Quantum in Federal Indian Law to 1935 |author=Paul Spruhan |accessdate=2009-08-07 |year=2001 |publisher=Social Science Electronic Publishing, Inc }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since that time, however, Native American nations have established their own rules for tribal membership, which vary among them. In some cases, individuals may qualify as tribal members, but not as American Indian for the purposes of certain federal benefits, which are still related to blood quantum. In the early 21st century some tribes have tightened their membership rules and excluded people who had previously been considered members, such as in the case of the [[Cherokee Freedmen]].

==Origin of blood quantum law==
The blood quantum law or "Indian Blood law" was passed by European Americans to regulate who would be classified as Native American. The first such law was passed in 1705 in Virginia, to define Native Americans and to restrict the rights of people who were half or more Native American.&lt;ref name="ucd"/&gt; In the 19th and 20th centuries, the US government believed definition of tribal members was required, as it made treaties with the nations and paid tribal members benefits or annuities for land cessions.&lt;ref name="naaa"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=5355&amp;page=103|title=Tribal Membership Requirements and the Demography of "Old" and "New" Native Americans
|author=Russell Thornton|accessdate=2009-09-02 |year=2008 |publisher=The National Academies Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Native American tribes did not use blood quantum law until the [[United States government|government]] introduced the [[Indian Reorganization Act of 1934]]. Some tribes, such as the [[Navajo Nation]], did not adopt the type constitution suggested in that law until the 1950s.&lt;ref name="unm"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tlj.unm.edu/volumes/vol8/8TLJ1LSPRUHAN.pdf|title=THE ORIGINS, CURRENT STATUS, AND FUTURE PROSPECTS OF BLOOD QUANTUM AS THE DEFINITION OF MEMBERSHIP IN THE NAVAJO NATION|author=Paul Spruhan|accessdate=2009-08-15 |year=2008 |publisher=Tribal Law Journal }}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics contend that, because the federal blood quantum laws required individuals to identify as belonging to only one tribe, despite ancestry that may include ancestors from more than one tribe, some lost legitimate membership in more than one tribe. Overall numbers of registered members of many Native American tribes have been reduced.

"The U.S. census decennial enumerations indicate a Native American population growth for the United States that has been nearly continuous since 1900 (except for an [[1918 flu pandemic|influenza epidemic]] in 1918 that caused serious losses), to 1.42 million by 1980 and to over 1.9 million by 1990."&lt;ref name="naaa"/&gt; In the 2000 census, there were 2.5 million American Indians. Since 1960, people may self-identify their ancestry on the US Census.&lt;ref name="naaa"/&gt;

For decades, tribes have established their own requirements for membership. In some cases, they have excluded members who had long been part of the tribe. An example of a tribal membership requirement is one based on documented lineal descent from a Native American member listed on the [[Dawes Rolls]], or an early 20th-century [[census]]. Unlike the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act, many tribes allow members to claim ancestry in more than one tribe.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

Each federally recognized tribe has established its own criteria for membership.&lt;ref name="naaa"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=5355&amp;page=103|title=Tribal Membership Requirements and the Demography of "Old" and "New" Native Americans
|author=Russell Thornton|accessdate=2009-09-02 |year=2008 |publisher=[[The National Academic Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Given the new revenues that many tribes are realizing from gambling casinos and other economic development, or from settlement of 19th-century [[land claims]], some have established more restrictive rules to limit membership.

Such actions have led to charges of racial injustice and controversies such as that of the [[Cherokee Nation]]'s 2007 vote to exclude those [[Cherokee Freedmen]] with no Indian ancestors on the Cherokee-by-blood Dawes rolls, although the Cherokee Supreme Court ruled in 2005 that they were legitimate members of the tribe in 2005. Similarly, in 2000, the [[Seminole Nation of Oklahoma]] attempted to exclude two bands of Seminole Freedmen from membership to avoid including them in settlement of land claims in Florida, where Seminole Freedmen had also owned land taken by the US government.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, Ben. [http://www.indiancountrytoday.com/home/content/44590087.html "Dems ask DoJ to probe treatment of Indian freedmen."]{{dead link|date=November 2015}} ''Indian Country Today.'' 8 May 2009 (retrieved 20 April 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="cr"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ccrjustice.org/newsroom/press-releases/ccr-files-amicus-brief-behalf-black-seminoles|title=CCR Files Amicus Brief on Behalf of Black Seminoles|author=Jeff Fogel, Barbara Olshansky, and Shayana Kadidal|accessdate=2009-08-15 |year=2008 |publisher=Center for Constitutional Rights}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1942, the [[Seminole]] have at times tried to exclude [[Black Seminoles]] from the tribe. The freedmen were listed separately on the [[Dawes Rolls]] and suffered [[Racial segregation in the United States|segregation]] in [[Oklahoma]]. More recently, the Seminole refused to share with them the revenues of 20th-century US government settlements of land claims. The [[Center for Constitutional Rights]] has filed an ''amicus'' brief, taking up the legal case of the Black Seminoles and criticizing some officials of the [[Bureau of Indian Affairs]] for collaborating in this discrimination by supporting tribal autonomy in lawsuits. By treaty, after the [[American Civil War]], the Seminole were required to emancipate slaves and provide Black Seminoles with all the rights of full-blood Indian members.&lt;ref name="cr" /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;"American Indian tribes located on reservations tend to have higher blood quantum requirements for membership than those located off reservation....[reference to table] [O]ver 85 percent of tribes requiring more than a one-quarter blood quantum for membership are reservation based, as compared with less than 64 percent of those having no minimum requirement. Tribes on reservations have seemingly been able to maintain exclusive membership by setting higher blood quanta, since the reservation location has generally served to isolate the tribe from non-Indians and intermarriage with them.&lt;ref name="naaa"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Issues related to blood quantum laws==
Many Native Americans have become used to the idea of "blood quantum".&lt;ref name="ucd"/&gt; The blood quantum laws have caused problems in Native American families whose members were inaccurately recorded as having differing full or partial descent from particular tribes.&lt;ref name="ucd"/&gt;&lt;ref name="unm"/&gt;&lt;ref name="che"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allthingscherokee.com/articles_gene_040101.html|title=Blood Quantum - Why It Matters, and Why It Shouldn't|author=Christina Berry|accessdate=2009-09-07 |year=2008 |publisher=All Things Cherokee, personal website}}{{dead link|date=November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, family members or entire families have been excluded from being enrolled as members of their tribe even when they have no non-Native American ancestors.&lt;ref name="unm"/&gt;

At certain times, some state governments classified persons with [[African American]] and Native American admixture solely as African American, largely because of racial discrimination related to slavery history. This was prevalent in the South after [[Reconstruction Era of the United States|Reconstruction]], when white-dominated legislatures imposed legal [[Racial segregation in the United States|segregation]], which classified the entire population only as white or colored (Native Americans, some of whom were of mixed race, were included in the latter designation). It related to the racial caste system of slavery before the [[American Civil War]]. Until 1870 there was no separate classification on the census for Indian.

The [[Lumbee]], a group that appeared to organize from a variety of [[free people of color]] on the [[North Carolina]] frontier in the 19th century, achieved state recognition as [[Croatan]] Indian in 1885 after Reconstruction.&lt;ref name="lb"&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=lLbAgZBy3_8C&amp;pg=PA25&amp;lpg=PA25&amp;dq=problems+with+indian+blood+and+black+indian&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=oHEV8ZnYnJ&amp;sig=PD4JeX-D8jYMrPwQX6jgVYuBPgg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=uF16SoLWBpCCNo36_PIC&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|title=The Lumbee problem: the making of an American Indian people |author= Karen I. Blu|accessdate=2009-08-15 |year=1980 |publisher=[[University of Nebraska]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="mtb"/&gt; This separate status allowed them to establish a school system for their children distinct from that for [[freedmen]]'s children.&lt;ref name="lb" /&gt;

The question of identity is complex. Award-winning researcher Paul Heinegg and Dr. [[Virginia DeMarce]] found that ancestors of 80 percent of free people of color (including individuals on the census later claimed as Lumbee ancestors) in the 1790 and 1810 censuses on the North Carolina frontier were descended from families of white women and [[Native ethnic groups of Africa|African]] men, and were free in colonial Virginia because of the mother's status. Many mixed-race people in frontier areas identified as Indian, [[Portugal|Portuguese]] or [[Arab]] to escape racial strictures.&lt;ref&gt;DeMarce, pp.24-45&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="freeafricanamericans.com"&gt;[http://www.freeafricanamericans.com/ Paul Heinegg, ''Free African Americans of Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Maryland and Delaware''], accessed 9 Mar 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1952 the Croatan Indians voted to adopt the name of Lumbee. (They were settled near the [[Lumber River]], also called the Lumbee.) They achieved limited federal recognition in 1956 as an [[ethnic]] Indian nation by a special act of the US Congress, and accepted at the time that it was without benefits. Since then, they have tried to appeal to Congress for legislation to gain full federal recognition. Their effort has been opposed by several federally recognized tribes.&lt;ref name="lb"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Houghton, p.750.&lt;/ref&gt;

In other cases, because mixed-race children were often raised in the mother's Native American culture, United States society considered them to be Native American, despite European ancestry. (As the trappers, traders and soldiers on the frontiers were mostly men, for some time most European-Native American unions were between European men and Native women.)&lt;ref name="lb"/&gt;

In 1924 Virginia passed the [[Racial Integrity Act]], which required that every individual be classified as either white or black. (Some other states adopted similar laws.) In application, the law was enforced to the standard of the "[[one drop rule]]": individuals with any known African ancestry were classified as black. As a result, in the censuses of the 1930s and the 1940s, particularly in the South's segregated society, many people of African American and Native American descent who were either biracial or multiracial were largely classified as black, even though they identified culturally as Native American.&lt;ref name="mtb"&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=9tP7_3j3WrkC&amp;pg=PA72&amp;lpg=PA72&amp;dq=native+americans+with+african+ancestry&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=-X76NOyNdj&amp;sig=-f0v6_rn56IZ6ksa1mDHuxHwuuk&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=LJSHSpCADIaeMfCk1fsO&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10#v=onepage&amp;q=native%20americans%20with%20african%20ancestry&amp;f=false|title=More than Black?: multiracial identity and the new racial order|author=G. Reginald Daniel|accessdate=2009-09-01 |year=2002 |publisher=[[Temple University Press]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; The result negatively affected many individuals with mixed African American and Native American descent. Because there are few reservations in the South, such individuals needed to provide evidence of ancestry to be enrolled in a tribe. The changes in historic records erased their documentation of continuity of identity as Indian.&lt;ref name="mtb"/&gt; During the early years of slavery, some Native Americans and Africans intermarried because they were enslaved at the same time and shared a common experience of enslavement. Others made unions before slavery became institutionalized, as they worked together.&lt;ref name="afrna"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nps.gov/history/ethnography/aah/aaheritage/lowCountry_furthRdg1.htm|title=Park Ethnography: Work, Marriage, Christianity|author=National Park Service| date=2009-05-30|publisher=National Park Service}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, the proposed regulations for children adopted into Native families are that they are unable to be federally recognized members unless they have a biological parent who is enrolled in a tribe.&lt;ref name="ucd"/&gt; Such cases of adoption are probably less frequent than in the past. Historically, especially recorded during the [[colonial history of the United States|colonial]] years and the 19th century in the [[American West]], many tribes adopted young captives taken in war or raids to replace members who had died. Whether European or of another Native American tribe, the captives generally were fully assimilated into the tribal culture and were considered full members of the tribe. Generally, they remained with the tribe, marrying other members and rearing their children within the cultural tradition.

In some cases, census rolls for tribes such as the [[Cherokee]] were incomplete due to intermarriage, immigration, treaties, or because the members were not living within the boundaries of the nation, and thus would not be recorded on the census.&lt;ref name="chro"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allthingscherokee.com/faq_proving.html|title=I Know I'm Cherokee, But How Do I Prove It?|author=Christina Berry|accessdate=2009-09-07 |year=2008 |publisher=All Things Cherokee, personal website}}{{dead link|date=November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; As noted above, however, many people have identified as Native American on the [[US Census]] but are not eligible for tribal enrollment.

Some critics argue that blood quantum laws helped create racism among tribal members. The historian Tony Seybert contends that was why some members of the so-called [[Five Civilized tribes]] were slaveholders. The majority of slave owners were of mixed-European ancestry. Some believed they were of higher status than full-blood Indians and people of African ancestry.&lt;ref name="amslav"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slaveryinamerica.org/history/hs_es_indians_slavery.htm|title=Slavery and Native Americans in British North America and the United States: 1600 to 1865|author= Tony Seybert|accessdate=2009-06-20 |year=2009 |publisher=New York Life}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="cat"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.williamlkatz.com/Essays/History/AfricansIndians.php|title=Africans and Indians: Only in America|author=William Loren Katz |accessdate=2008-09-20 |year=2008 |publisher=William Loren Katz }}{{dead link|date=November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other historians contend that the Cherokee and other tribes held slaves because it was in their economic interest and part of the general southeastern culture. Cherokee and other tribes had also traditionally taken captives in warfare to use as slaves, although their institution differed from that which developed in the southern colonies.

===Issues with DNA ancestry testing===
No [[federally recognized tribes|federally recognized tribe]] enrolls members solely based on DNA testing, as it generally cannot distinguish among tribes. Many researchers have published articles that caution that genetic ancestry DNA testing has limitations and should not be depended on by individuals to answer all their questions about heritage.&lt;ref name="true2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2007/10/071018145955.htm|title=Genetic Ancestral Testing Cannot Deliver On Its Promise, Study Warns|author=ScienceDaily|accessdate=2008-10-02 |year=2008 |publisher=ScienceDaily}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hr"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.geneticsandsociety.org/article.php?id=3908|title=Deep Roots and Tangled Branches|author=Troy Duster|accessdate=2008-10-02 |year=2008 |publisher=Chronicle of Higher Education}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is widely believed that many African Americans have Native American ancestry, and historians such as Sherrel Wheeler Stewart says that most African Americans have Native American ancestry.&lt;ref name="dstu2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rlnn.com/ArtOct06/MoreBlacksAfricanAmerNativeAmerConnection.html|title=More Blacks are Exploring the African-American/Native American Connection|author=Sherrel Wheeler Stewart |accessdate=2008-08-06 |year=2008 |publisher=BlackAmericaWeb.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; But, in the [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] series led by historian [[Henry Louis Gates, Jr.]], called ''[[African American Lives]]'', geneticists argued that African-Native American admixture is relatively rare.&lt;ref name="African American Lives"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://racerelations.about.com/od/ahistoricalviewofrace/a/dnaandrace.htm|title=DNA Testing: review, ''African American Lives'', About.com}}{{dead link|date=November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="African American Lives"&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://racerelations.about.com/od/ahistoricalviewofrace/a/dnaandrace.htm
|title=DNA Testing: review, ''African American Lives'', About.com}}{{dead link|date=November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="African American Lives PBS"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/wnet/aalives/dna/index.html
|title=African American Lives 2}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his associated book, Gates summarized the information: &lt;blockquote&gt;Only 5 percent of African Americans have at least one-eighth Native American ancestry (equivalent to one great-grandparent). On the other hand, nearly 78 percent of African Americans have at least one-eighth European ancestry (the equivalent to a great-grandparent), and nearly 20 percent have at least one-quarter European ancestry (the equivalent to a grandparent.)&lt;ref&gt;Henry Louis Gates, Jr., ''In Search of Our Roots: How 19 Extraordinary African Americans Reclaimed Their Past'', New York: Crown Publishing, 2009, pp. 20-21&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Direct Y-chromosome and [[mitochondrial DNA|mtDNA]] (mitochondrial DNA) testing looks only at "direct" line male and female ancestors, and thus can fail to pick up many ancestors' heritage.&lt;ref name="genej"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipcb.org/publications/briefing_papers/files/identity.html|title=Genetic Markers Not a Valid Test of Native Identity|author=Brett Lee Shelton, J.D. and Jonathan Marks, Ph.D.
|accessdate=2008-10-02 |year=2008 |publisher=Counsel for Responsible Genetics}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some critics thought the PBS series did not sufficiently explain the limitations of DNA testing for assessment of heritage.&lt;ref name="hr"/&gt; More significantly, current DNA testing cannot distinguish among separate Native American tribes.&lt;ref name="genej"/&gt; Newer DNA tests can survey all the DNA that can be inherited from either parent of an individual, but at a cost of precision.&lt;ref name="jh"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slate.com/id/2138059|title=How African Are You? What genealogical testing can't tell you.|author=John Hawks|accessdate=2010-06-26 |year=2008 |publisher=Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; DNA tests that survey the full DNA strand focus on "single nucleotide polymorphisms" or SNPs, but SNP might be found in Africans, Asians, and people from every other part of the world.&lt;ref name="jh"/&gt; Full survey of DNA testing can not accurately determine an individual's full ancestry.&lt;ref name="jh"/&gt;

==Implementation==
Many Native American tribes continue to employ blood quantum in current tribal laws to determine who is eligible for membership or citizenship in the tribe or Native American nation. These often require a minimum degree of blood relationship and often an ancestor listed in a specific tribal [[census]] from the late 19th century or early 20th century. The [[Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians]] of [[North Carolina]], for example, require an ancestor listed in the 1924 Baker census and a minimum of 1/16 Cherokee blood inherited from their ancestor(s) on that roll. Meanwhile, the [[Cherokee Nation]] requires applicants to descend from an ancestor in the 1906 [[Dawes Rolls|Dawes roll]] (direct lineal ancestry), but does not impose minimum blood quantum requirement. The [[United Keetoowah Band]] requires a minimum 1/4 blood quantum.

The [[Ute Tribe|Ute]] require a 5/8 blood quantum, the highest requirement of any US tribe. The [[Miccosukee]] of [[Florida]], the [[Mississippi]] [[Choctaw]] and the [[St. Croix Band of Chippewa Indians|St. Croix]] [[Chippewa]] of [[Wisconsin]] all require one-half "tribal blood quantum", also a high percentage.

At the other end of the scale, the [[Caddo Nation]] of [[Oklahoma]] requires only 1/16 documented heritage. The [[Confederated Tribes of the Grand Ronde Community of Oregon]] require a combined minimum of 1/16 from any of a list of several [[Oregon]] indigenous peoples.

Some tribes, such as [[Alabama-Quassarte Tribal Town]] and the [[Wyandotte Nation]],&lt;ref name=oia/&gt; require an unspecified amount of Indian ancestry (known as "[[lineal descendancy]]") documented by descent from a recognized member. Others require a specified degree of Indian ancestry but an unspecified share of ancestry from the ancestral tribe or tribes from which the modern tribal entity is derived, such as the [[Grand Traverse Band of Ottawa and Chippewa Indians]] and the [[Poarch Band of Creek Indians]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.narf.org/nill/Constitutions/poarchconstitution/poarchconst.htm "Constitution of the Poarch Band of Creek Indians."]{{dead link|date=November 2015}} ''[[Native American Rights Fund]].'' 1 June 1985 (retrieved 25 Nov 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; Many modern tribes are confederations of original tribal peoples joined into a single political entity.

Other tribes require a minimum blood degree only for tribal members born "off" ( outside) the nominal [[Indian reservation|reservation]]. This is a concept comparable to the legal principles of ''[[Jus soli]]'' and ''[[Jus sanguinis]]'' in the [[nationality law]]s of modern sovereign states. Below are listings of blood quantum requirements of [[federally recognized tribes]].

===Tribes requiring 1/2 degree blood quantum for membership===
(equivalent to one parent)
*[[Chippewa Cree]], Montana&lt;ref name="Chippewa Cree Constitution"&gt;{{cite web|title=CONSTITUTION AND BYLAWS OF THE  CHIPPEWA CREE INDIANS OF THE  ROCKY BOY'S RESERVATION  MONTANA|url=http://thorpe.ou.edu/IRA/creecons.html|website=thorpe.ou.edu|accessdate=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Kialegee Tribal Town]]&lt;ref name=oia&gt;[http://www.ok.gov/oiac/Publications/ "Pocket Pictorial."]{{dead link|date=November 2015}} ''Oklahoma Indian Affairs Commission.'' 2010. (retrieved 10 June 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Miccosukee Tribe of Indians of Florida]]
*[[Mississippi Band of Choctaw Indians, Mississippi]]
*[[St. Croix Chippewa Indians of Wisconsin]]
*[[Pueblo of Isleta, New Mexico]]
*[[White Mountain Apache Tribe]], Arizona
*[[Yomba Shoshone Tribe]], Nevada&lt;ref&gt;[http://thorpe.ou.edu/IRA/yomba.html "Constitution and By-Laws of the Yomba Shoshone Tribe of the Yomba Reservation, Nevada."] ''Native American Constitution and Law Digitization Project.'' (retrieved 5 May 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tribes requiring 1/4 degree blood quantum for membership===
(equivalent to one grandparent)
* [[Absentee-Shawnee Tribe of Indians]], Oklahoma&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
* [[Ak-Chin Indian Community]], Arizona&lt;ref name="Ak-Chin Constitution"&gt;{{cite web|title=CONSTITUTION AND BY-LAWS OF AK-CHIN (PAPAGO) INDIAN COMMUNITY|url=http://www.nptao.arizona.edu/ProtocolPDFs/CONSTITUTION%20AND%20BYLAWS%20of%20the%20AK%20CHIN.pdf|website=nptao.arizona.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Blackfeet Tribe of the Blackfeet Indian Reservation of Montana]]&lt;ref name="Blackfeet Constitution"&gt;{{cite web|title=Constitution and By-Laws For the Blackfeet Tribe Of The Blackfeet Indian Reservation of Montana|url=http://thorpe.ou.edu/constitution/blackfeet/bfcontTOC.html|website=thrope.ou.edu|accessdate=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Cheyenne and Arapaho Tribes]], Oklahoma&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
* [[Confederated Tribes and Bands of the Yakama Nation]], Washington
* [[Confederated Tribes of the Chehalis Reservation]], Washington&lt;ref name="Chehalis Constitution"&gt;{{cite book|title=Confederated Tribes of the Chehalis Reservation, Human and Natural Resources|publisher=United States Bureau of Indian Affairs|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=P3TjAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA111&amp;lpg=PA111&amp;dq=chehalis+constitution&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ZKNg9jl6mC&amp;sig=2ooAtwtF6FbnnSEx62uPE08IPJQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Rk8OVcbHJoabyASDyICwBQ&amp;ved=0CFEQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=chehalis%20constitution&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ho-Chunk Nation of Wisconsin]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.narf.org/nill/Codes/hochunkcode/2HCC07_Enrollment.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Wisconsin
* [[Hopi Tribe of Arizona]]
* [[Kickapoo Traditional Tribe of Texas]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://thorpe.ou.edu/constitution/kickapoo/ "Constitution of the Kickapoo Traditional Tribe of Texas."] ''Native American Constitution and Law Digitization Project.'' Retrieved 13 Sept 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Kickapoo Tribe of Oklahoma]], Oklahoma&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
* [[Kiowa Tribe of Oklahoma]], Oklahoma&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
* [[Fort McDowell Yavapai Nation]], Arizona
* [[Fort Peck Indian Reservation|Fort Peck Assiniboine and Sioux Tribes]], Montana
* [[Navajo Nation]], Arizona, Utah and New Mexico
* [[Oneida Tribe of Indians]], Wisconsin
* [[Pascua Yaqui Tribe]], Arizona
* [[Penobscot Nation]], Maine
* [[Prairie Band Potawatomi Nation]], Kansas&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbpindiantribe.com/member-services.aspx "Member Services."]{{dead link|date=November 2015}} ''Prairie Band Potawatomi Nation.'' (retrieved 2 Feb 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Seminole Tribe of Florida]], Florida
* [[Shoshone Tribe of the Wind River Reservation]], Wyoming&lt;ref&gt;Ahtone, Tristan. [http://www.npr.org/2011/03/31/134421470/native-american-intermarriage-puts-benefits-at-risk "Native American Intermarriage Puts Benefits At Risk."] ''NPR: Around the Nation.'' 31 March 2011 (retrieved 31 March 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Standing Rock Sioux Tribe]], North and South Dakota
* [[United Keetoowah Band of Cherokee Indians]], Oklahoma&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
* [[Utu Utu Gwaitu Paiute Tribe]], California&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bentonpaiutereservation.com/EnrollmentOrdinance.pdf "Enrollment Ordiance."]{{dead link|date=November 2015}} ''Utu Utu Gawitu Paiute Tribe.'' (retrieved 5 May 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Yavapai-Prescott Tribe]], Arizona
*Zuni Pueblo (Ashiwi), New Mexico&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ashiwi.org/constitution.aspx The Pueblo of Zuni&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tribes requiring 1/8 degree blood quantum for membership===
(equivalent to one great-grandparent)
*[[Agua Caliente Band of Cahuilla Indians]], California&lt;ref name="Agua Caliente Constitution"&gt;{{cite web|title=Constitution and By-Laws of the Agua Caliente Band of Cahuilla Indians|url=http://thorpe.ou.edu/IRA/aguacalcons.html|website=thorpe. ou.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Apache Tribe of Oklahoma]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Comanche Nation]], Oklahoma&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Delaware Nation]], Oklahoma&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Confederated Tribes of the Siletz Reservation]], Oregon
*[[Fort Sill Apache Tribe of Oklahoma]]
*[[Hooopa Valley Tribe of California]]
*[[Karuk Tribe of California]]
*[[Klamath Tribes]], Oregon&lt;ref name="Enrollment Notice"&gt;{{cite web|title=Enrollment Notice|url=http://klamathtribes.org/administration/enrollment-notice/|website=klamathtribes.org|accessdate=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Muckleshoot Indian Tribe of the Muckleshoot Reservation]], Washington
*[[Northwestern Band of Shoshoni Nation of Utah (Washakie)]]
*[[Otoe-Missouria Tribe of Indians]], Oklahoma&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.omtribe.org/index.php?enrollment "Enrollment Department."] ''Otoe-Missouria Tribe.'' 2010 (retrieved 22 July 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Pawnee people|Pawnee Nation of Oklahoma]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Ponca Nation]], Oklahoma&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Sac and Fox Nation]], Oklahoma&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Sac &amp; Fox Nation of Missouri in Kansas and Nebraska]]
*[[Squaxin Island Tribe of the Squaxin Island Reservation, Washington]]
*[[Suquamish Indian Tribe of the Port Madison Reservation, Washington]]
*[[Mandan, Hidatsa, and Arikara Nation|Three Affiliated Tribes of the Fort Berthold Reservation]]
*[[Upper Skagit Indian Tribe of Washington]]
*[[Yurok people|Yurok Tribe of California]]
*[[Wichita and Affiliated Tribes (Wichita, Keechi, Waco and Tawakonie)]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;

===Tribes requiring 1/16 degree blood quantum for membership===
(equivalent to one great-great-grandparent)
*[[Caddo Nation]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Confederated Tribes of the Grand Ronde Community of Oregon]]
*[[Confederated Tribes of Siletz Indians]]
*[[Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians]], North Carolina
*[[Fort Independence Indian Community of Paiute Indians of the Fort Independence Reservation]], California&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.narf.org/nill/Constitutions/fortindpconst/fi.htm "Fort Independence Articles of Association."]{{dead link|date=November 2015}} ''National Indian Law Library''. Retrieved 2 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Fort Sill Apache Tribe]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Iowa Tribe of Oklahoma]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;

===Tribes requiring 1/32 degree blood quantum for membership===
(equivalent to one great-great-great-grandparent)
*[[Kaw Nation]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://kawnation.com/?page_id=3312 "Constitution of the Kaw Nation."] ''Kaw Nation.'' 2011. Retrieved 30 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tribes determining membership by lineal descent===
These tribes do not have a minimum blood quantum requirement, but members must be able to document descent from original enrollees of tribal rolls.
{{colbegin|2}}
*[[Alabama-Coushatta Tribe of Texas]]&lt;ref name="Alabama-Coushatta Constitution"&gt;{{cite web|title=CONSTITUTION AND BY-LAWS * " OF THE ALABAMA AND COUSHATTA TRIBES OF TEXAS|url=http://thorpe.ou.edu/IRA/consalacous.pdf|website=thorpe.ou.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Alabama-Quassarte Tribal Town]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Aroostook Band of Micmac]], Maine&lt;ref name="Aroostook Band of Micmac Membership"&gt;{{cite web|title=Membership|url=http://www.micmac-nsn.gov/html/membership.html|website=micmacs-nsn.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Cherokee Nation]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Chickasaw Nation]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Choctaw Nation of Oklahoma|Choctaw Nation]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Citizen Potawatomi Nation]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Delaware Tribe of Indians]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Eastern Shawnee Tribe]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Mashantucket Pequot Tribe of Connecticut]]&lt;ref name="indiangaming.org"&gt;[http://www.indiangaming.org/library/articles/novel-attack.shtml]{{dead link|date=November 2015}} Professor Laurence M. Hauptman. "A Review" of Jeff Benedict’s ''Without Reservation: The Making of America’s Most Powerful Indian Tribe and Foxwoods, the World’s Largest Casino''], ''Indian Gaming,'' 17 March 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mashpee Wampanoag Tribe of Massachusetts]]
*[[Miami Tribe of Oklahoma]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
* [[Minnesota Chippewa Tribe, White Earth Band]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Gunderson|first1=Dan|title=White Earth Band votes to end 'blood quantum' for tribal membership|url=http://www.mprnews.org/story/2013/11/20/politics/white-earth-band-votes-to-end-blood-quantum-for-tribal-membership--|website=MPR News|publisher=Minnesota Public Radio|accessdate=22 April 2015|date=Nov 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mohegan Tribe of Connecticut]]
*[[Modoc Tribe]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Muscogee Creek Nation]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Narragansett Indian Tribe of Rhode Island]]
*[[Osage Nation]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Ottawa Tribe of Oklahoma]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Peoria Tribe of Indians]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Quapaw Tribe of Oklahoma]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Sault Ste. Marie Tribe of Chippewa Indians of Michigan]]
*[[Seminole Nation]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Seneca-Cayuga Tribe of Oklahoma]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Shawnee Tribe]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Thlopthlocco Tribal Town]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Tonkawa Tribe]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
*[[Wyandotte Nation]]&lt;ref name=oia/&gt;
{{colend}}

===Tribes determining membership by both blood quantum ''and'' lineal descent===
These tribes require both a specified blood quantum and lineal descent from an individual on a designated tribal roll.
* [[Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation]] – Since 1993, have required 1/4 descent from any federally recognized Native American tribe, plus being the biological child or grandchild of an already-enrolled member.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ctuir.org/system/files/EnrollmentCode.pdf |title=Chapter 2, Section 2.01: Enrollment Criteria |work=Enrollment Code of the Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation |date=July 7, 2014 |accessdate=May 15, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Future==
Native American populations increased considerably during the 20th century. Increasing urbanization and intermarriage may affect their futures as distinct peoples tied to geographic areas. Nations with high blood quantum requirements may have to change their rules for tribal membership or see their numbers decrease. Each tribe will deal with the issue in its own way, and with reference to whether it has a large reservation, urbanized population, cultural revival, etc.

==See also==
* [[Disenrollment]]
* [[Kamehameha Schools#Admission|Kamehameha Schools Admission Policy]]
* [[One-drop rule]]
* [[Indian Register]] - the list of First Nations Canadians who are eligible for treaty benefits

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=955032 A Legal History of Blood Quantum in Federal Indian Law to 1935]
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1138302 The Origins, Current Status, and Future Prospects of Blood Quantum as the Definition of Membership in the Navajo Nation]
* [http://www.charkoosta.com/2007_12_13/tribal_enrollment.html Indian by identity: a look inside tribal enrollment]{{dead link|date=November 2015}}, by Alyssa Kelly
* [http://www.yvwiiusdinvnohii.net/Articles2000/JDForbes001126Blood.htm Blood Quantum: A Relic Of Racism And Termination], by Jack Forbes
* [http://www.allthingscherokee.com/articles_gene_040101.html Blood Quantum — Why It Matters, and Why It Shouldn't]{{dead link|date=November 2015}}, by Christina Berry

{{DEFAULTSORT:Blood Quantum Laws}}
[[Category:African-American history]]
[[Category:Native American history]]
[[Category:Native American law]]
[[Category:Race legislation in the United States]]
[[Category:History of racism in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>