<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201101134010|986536377" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="38466074" pageid="38466074" ns="0" title="Ethnic penalty"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-01T14:08:17Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar|Related}}

'''Ethnic penalty''' in [[sociology]] is defined as the economic and non-economic disadvantages that [[minority group|ethnic minorities]] experience in the [[Labour economics|labour market]] compared to other ethnic groups. As an area of study among [[behavioral economics|behavioral economists]], psychologists, and sociologists, it ranges beyond discrimination to take non-cognitive factors into consideration for explaining unwarranted differences between individuals of similar abilities but differing ethnicities.

==Overview==
The concept of the ethnic penalty was first discussed by Oxford sociologist Anthony Heath. Heath originally looked at the ethnic penalty by making comparisons between two groups in Britain, [[White British|whites]] and [[Black British|blacks]], noting that unemployment of black African men was twice as high as unemployment of white men.&lt;ref&gt;Heath, A.F. and J. Ridge (1983) “Social Mobility of Ethnic Minorities”, ''Journal of Biosocial Science'', Supplement No. 8: 169-184.&lt;/ref&gt; Using 2001 UK census data, Johnston et al. suggests that all ethno-religious groups in the UK experienced ethnic penalties in the labour market, with the exception of White British ethno-religious groups.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston, R. et al. (2010) "Ethno-Religious Categories and Measuring Occupational Attainment in Relation to Education in England and Wales: A Multilevel Analysis’, Environment and Planning A 42(3): 578-591.&lt;/ref&gt; Carmichael and Woods additionally show that "the penalties paid vary considerably between the minority groups" studied, in the case of black, Indian, Pakistani, and Bangladeshi workers in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name="carmichael &amp; woods, 2000"&gt;{{cite journal | title=Ethnic Penalties in Unemployment and Occupational Attainment: Evidence for Britain |author1=Carmichael, F.  |author2=Woods, R. | journal=International Review of Applied Economics | year=2000 | volume=14 | issue=1 | pages=71–98 | doi=10.1080/026921700101498}}&lt;/ref&gt; Simpson, Purdam, Tajar, et al. also found that this differs between UK-born members of an ethnic minority and those of the same ethnicity born abroad – UK-born males are more likely to be unemployed than males from overseas, while UK-born women "tend to do better in the labour market than their overseas-born counterparts".&lt;ref&gt;Simpson et al. (2006) "Ethnic Minority Populations and the Labour Market: An Analysis of the 1991 and 2001 Census", Department for Work and Pensions.&lt;/ref&gt; Beyond this, Simpson et al. confirmed that this disadvantage is not tied to "concentration of ethnic minorities in deprived areas"; those of an "ethnic minority were still twice as likely to be unemployed than their White counterparts... even in areas that are predominantly White". 

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Ethnicity}}
{{Discrimination|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Minorities]]
[[Category:Ethnic minorities]]
[[Category:Unemployment]]
[[Category:Social justice]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]
[[Category:Human rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>