<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20230901181719|1173323763" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="38466074" pageid="38466074" ns="0" title="Ethnic penalty"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-09-06T20:43:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Economic and non-economic disadvantage}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Related}}

In [[sociology]], the term '''ethnic penalty''' is used in reference to the economic and non-economic disadvantages that [[minority group|ethnic minorities]] experience in the [[Labour economics|labour market]] compared to other ethnic groups. As an area of study among [[behavioral economics|behavioral economists]], psychologists, and sociologists, it ranges beyond discrimination so non-cognitive factors can also be taken into consideration in order to explain why unwarranted differences exist between individuals with similar abilities because they are members of different [[Ethnic group|ethnicities]].

==Overview==
The concept of the ethnic penalty was first discussed by Oxford sociologist Anthony Heath. Heath originally looked at the ethnic penalty by making comparisons between two groups in Britain, [[White British|whites]] and [[Black British|blacks]], noting that unemployment of black African men was twice as high as unemployment of white men.&lt;ref&gt;Heath, A.F. and J. Ridge (1983) “Social Mobility of Ethnic Minorities”, ''Journal of Biosocial Science'', Supplement No. 8: 169-184.&lt;/ref&gt; Using 2001 UK census data, Johnston et al. suggests that all ethno-religious groups in the UK experienced ethnic penalties in the labour market, with the exception of White British ethno-religious groups.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston, R. et al. (2010) "Ethno-Religious Categories and Measuring Occupational Attainment in Relation to Education in England and Wales: A Multilevel Analysis’, Environment and Planning A 42(3): 578-591.&lt;/ref&gt; Carmichael and Woods additionally show that "the penalties paid vary considerably between the minority groups" studied, in the case of black, Indian, Pakistani, and Bangladeshi workers in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name="carmichael &amp; woods, 2000"&gt;{{cite journal | title=Ethnic Penalties in Unemployment and Occupational Attainment: Evidence for Britain |author1=Carmichael, F.  |author2=Woods, R. | journal=International Review of Applied Economics | year=2000 | volume=14 | issue=1 | pages=71–98 | doi=10.1080/026921700101498|s2cid=154020583 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Simpson, Purdam, Tajar, et al. also found that this differs between UK-born members of an ethnic minority and those of the same ethnicity born abroad – UK-born males are more likely to be unemployed than males from overseas, while UK-born women "tend to do better in the labour market than their overseas-born counterparts".&lt;ref&gt;Simpson et al. (2006) "Ethnic Minority Populations and the Labour Market: An Analysis of the 1991 and 2001 Census", Department for Work and Pensions.&lt;/ref&gt; Beyond this, Simpson et al. confirmed that this disadvantage is not tied to "concentration of ethnic minorities in deprived areas"; those of an "ethnic minority were still twice as likely to be unemployed than their White counterparts... even in areas that are predominantly White".

Ethnic penalties are usually measured as differences in labour market outcomes between minorities and the majority that remain after controlling for human capital and social background characteristics in a statistical model. The ethnic penalty can be related to unemployment,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=International Migration Outlook 2016 |url=https://www.oecd-ilibrary.org/social-issues-migration-health/international-migration-outlook-2016_migr_outlook-2016-en |access-date=2022-09-11 |via=www.oecd-ilibrary.org |year=2016 |language=en |doi=10.1787/migr_outlook-2016-en|isbn=9789264258440 }}&lt;/ref&gt; occupational status &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Ubalde |first1=Josep |last2=Alarcón |first2=Amado |date=2020-10-19 |title=Immigrant disadvantage in the labour market: the role of attitudinal context |url=https://doi.org/10.1080/14616696.2020.1719180 |journal=European Societies |volume=22 |issue=5 |pages=636–658 |doi=10.1080/14616696.2020.1719180 |s2cid=213923819 |issn=1461-6696}}&lt;/ref&gt; or over-qualification&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Prokic-Breuer |first1=Tijana |last2=McManus |first2=Patricia A. |date=June 2016 |title=Immigrant Educational Mismatch in Western Europe, Apparent or Real? |url=https://academic.oup.com/esr/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/esr/jcw005 |journal=European Sociological Review |language=en |volume=32 |issue=3 |pages=411–438 |doi=10.1093/esr/jcw005 |issn=0266-7215}}&lt;/ref&gt; differences. Ethnic penalties in the labour market are explained by a diversity of factors, such as individual characteristics, country characteristics, the social environment in the host country, and the policy environment in the host country and tested them separately.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kislev|first=Elyakim|date=2016-09-19|title=Deciphering the 'Ethnic Penalty' of Immigrants in Western Europe: A Cross-Classified Multilevel Analysis|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/308032232|journal=Social Indicators Research|volume=134|issue=2|pages=725–745|doi=10.1007/s11205-016-1451-x|s2cid=255005352 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, ethnic penalties are usually attributed employer discriminatory behaviour against minorities.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Ethnicity}}
{{Discrimination|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Employment discrimination]]
[[Category:Minorities]]
[[Category:Ethnic minorities]]
[[Category:Unemployment]]
[[Category:Social justice]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]
[[Category:Human rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>