<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241115005112|1257463356" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="219177" pageid="219177" ns="0" title="Social conservatism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-18T19:00:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Political ideology advocating traditional values and power structures}}
{{distinguish|Paternalistic conservatism}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2022}}
{{conservatism sidebar|variants}}

'''Social conservatism''' is a [[political philosophy]] and a variety of [[conservatism]] which places emphasis on [[Tradition#In political and religious discourse|traditional]] social structures over [[Cultural pluralism|social pluralism]].&lt;ref name="Wiener 1973"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wiener|first=Jonathan|author-link=Jon Wiener|date=Spring 1973|title=Review: ''The Politics of Unreason: Right-Wing Extremism in America, 1790-1970''|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/202704|journal=The Journal of Interdisciplinary History|publisher=[[MIT Press]]|volume=3|issue=4|pages=791{{ndash}}793|doi=10.2307/202704|jstor=202704}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Cooper|first=Melinda|title=Family Values: Between Neoliberalism and the New Social Conservatism|publisher=Zone Books|year=2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Social conservatives [[Political campaign|organize]] in favor of [[duty]], [[traditional values]] and [[Institution|social institutions]], such as traditional [[Familialism|family structures]], [[Gender roles#Political ideologies|gender role]]s, [[sexual relations]], [[Patriotism#Cultural aspects|national patriotism]], and [[Religion#Impact|religious traditions]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-first=Robert B. |author-last=Smith |title=Social Conservatism, Distractors, and Authoritarianism: Axiological versus instrumental rationality |editor=Harry F. Dahms|date=2014|publisher=Emerald Group Publishing|isbn=9781784412227|page=101|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=C5V1BQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA101|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web |title=Social Conservatism |url=https://www.populismstudies.org/Vocabulary/social-conservatism/ |access-date=2022-08-17 |website=Populism Studies |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Social conservatism is usually skeptical of social change, instead tending to support the [[status quo]] concerning social issues.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Social conservatives also value the rights of religious institutions to participate in the public sphere, thus often supporting [[accommodationism|government-religious endorsement]] and opposing [[state atheism]], and in some cases opposing [[secularism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Dean|first=John W.|title=Conservatives Without Conscience|date=11 July 2006|publisher=Penguin Publishing Group|language=en|isbn=9781101201374|page=77}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Wald|first1=Kenneth D.|last2=Calhoun-Brown|first2=Allison|title=Religion and Politics in the United States|year=2007|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|language=en|isbn=9780742540415|page=240}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Booten |first1=Matthew |title=19 different types of conservatives |url=https://www.politic-ed.com/2020/05/11/19-different-types-of-conservatives/ |website=Politic-Ed |date=11 May 2020 |quote=Social conservatism often opposes state-atheism, however not necessarily atheism itself. They believe that if we allow states to stop believing in God, that societal order will simply break down as a result.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Social conservatism, as a movement, is largely an outgrowth of [[traditionalist conservatism]]. The key difference is that traditional conservatism is broader and includes philosophical considerations, whereas social conservatism is largely focused on just [[moralism]].

== Social conservatism and other ideological views ==
There is overlap between social conservatism and [[paleoconservatism]], in that they both support and value traditional social forms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Rowland|first1=Howard S.|title=Things to Think About|date=2010|publisher=Xlibris Corporation|isbn=9781453571286|page=171|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NFi3g3qSfsAC&amp;pg=PA171|language=en}}{{self-published source|date=December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Social conservatism is not to be confused with [[Economic interventionism|economically interventionist]] conservatism, where conservative ideas are combined with [[Keynesian]] economics and a [[welfare state]] as practised by some European conservatives (e.g. [[one-nation conservatism|one-nation conservatives]] in the [[United Kingdom]], [[Gaullism|Gaullists]] in [[France]]). Some social conservatives support [[free trade]] and [[Laissez faire|laissez faire market]] approaches to economic and fiscal issues, but social conservatives may also support economic intervention where the intervention serves moral or cultural aims. Historian [[Jon Wiener]] has described social conservatism as historically the result of an appeal from "[[Elite|elitist preservationists]]" to lower-class workers to 'protect' wealth from immigration.&lt;ref name="Wiener 1973" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=West|first=Ed|title=Small Men on the Wrong Side of History: The Decline, Fall and Unlikely Return of Conservatism|year=2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many social conservatives support a balance between [[protectionism]] and a [[free market]]. This concern for material welfare, like advocacy of traditional [[mores]], will often have a basis in religion. Examples include the [[Christian Social Union of Bavaria]], the [[Family First Party]] and [[Katter's Australian Party]], and the [[Communitarianism|communitarian]] movement in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Robin|first=Corey|title=The Reactionary Mind: Conservatism from Edmund Burke to Donald Trump|publisher=Oxford University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Social conservatism by country ==
{{More citations needed section|date=January 2013}}

=== Australia ===
{{Further information|Conservatism in Australia}}
Mainstream conservatism in Australia generally incorporates [[liberalism]], hence [[liberal conservatism]] being the primary ideology of the major centre-right coalition in Australia, the [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal]]-[[National Party of Australia|National]] [[Coalition (Australia)|Coalition]]. Therefore, the Coalition, while having members with some socially conservative views, is not considered socially conservative. However, both social conservatism and [[right-wing populism]] are present among [[right-wing]] minor parties, such as [[Pauline Hanson's One Nation]], the [[United Australia Party (2013)|United Australia Party]] (UAP) and [[Katter's Australian Party]] (KAP) amongst others.

Nevertheless, the [[National Right (Liberal Party of Australia)|National Right]] (also known as the "Conservative" faction or the "Right" faction) serves as the party's social conservative faction, although the party is still considered a [[broad church]] conservative party and factions do collaborate with each other; for example, the [[New South Wales Liberal Party]] often chooses a leadership team consisting of both a member of the more centrist [[Moderates (Liberal Party of Australia)|Moderate]] faction and a member of the Right.

Social conservatives in Australia often need to take a broad church stance while governing. For example, former [[New South Wales Liberal Party]] leader and state premier, [[Dominic Perrottet]], a conservative [[Catholicism in Australia|Catholic]], despite having voted against legalising [[same-sex marriage in Australia|same-sex marriage]] in 2018 and opposing [[abortion]], followed Labor leader [[Chris Minns]]' in supporting a 2023 state-wide ban on gay [[conversion therapy]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://amp.9news.com.au/article/655d8171-eca1-4929-a694-af25ef48ea9b | title=NSW Premier Dominic Perrottet agrees to gay conversion therapy ban }}&lt;/ref&gt; whilst also vowing to protect [[religious freedom]] and [[preaching]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://amp.smh.com.au/politics/nsw/we-won-t-ban-preaching-perrottet-puts-caveats-on-gay-conversion-law-20230222-p5cmtc.html | title=NSW election 2023: Perrottet puts caveats on gay conversion law | date=22 February 2023 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Australian Marriage Law Postal Survey]] of 2018, which successfully sought to legalise same-sex marriage in Australia, the Coalition government led by [[Prime Minister of Australia|Prime Minister]] [[Malcolm Turnbull]] allowed its members a [[conscience vote]] on the issue. While many (including Turnbull) were in favour, some were opposed, but supported holding a [[plebiscite]] on the matter. Federal Coalition MPs who opposed same-sex marriage during the debate included former Prime Minister [[Tony Abbott]], [[Peter Dutton]], [[Scott Morrison]] and many others. However, when the plebiscite was successful (with 61.6% in favour), a vote needed to be held in both chambers of [[Australian Parliament|Parliament]]. The ''[[Marriage Amendment (Definition and Religious Freedoms) Act 2017]]'' was tabled in the [[Australian Senate|Senate]] and was subsequently passed in the [[Australian House of Representatives|House of Representatives]], with just three votes against (excluding the members who abstained). Due to their respective electorates delivering a majority "yes" vote (as well as the entire country), members such as Dutton (who voted "no" in the plebiscite) voted in favour of the bill after his seat of [[Division of Dickson|Dickson]] voted 65.16% in favour.

=== Canada ===
{{Main|Social conservatism in Canada}}

In Canada, social conservatism, though widespread, is not as prominent in the public sphere as [[social conservatism in the United States|in the United States]]. It is prevalent in all areas of the country but is seen as being more prominent in [[rural]] areas. It is also a significant influence on the ideological and political culture of the western provinces of [[Manitoba]], [[Saskatchewan]], [[Alberta]], and [[British Columbia]].{{citation needed|date=October 2020}}

Compared to [[social conservatism in the United States]], social conservatism has not been as influential in Canada. The main reason is that the [[neoconservative]] style of politics as promoted by leaders such as former Prime Ministers such as [[Paul Martin]] and [[Stephen Harper]] have focused on [[fiscal conservatism]], with little or no emphasis on moral or social conservatism.&lt;ref&gt;John Middlemist Herrick and Paul H. Stuart, eds. ''Encyclopedia of social welfare history in North America'' (2005) p. 143&lt;/ref&gt; Without a specific, large political party behind them, social conservatives have divided their votes and can be found in all political parties.&lt;ref&gt;David M. Haskell, ''Through a lens darkly: how the news media perceive and portray evangelicals'' (2009) p 57&lt;/ref&gt;

Social conservatives often felt that they were being sidelined by officials in the [[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada]] and its leadership of so-called "[[Red Tories]]" for the last half of the twentieth century and therefore many eventually made their political home with parties such as the [[Social Credit Party of Canada]] and the [[Reform Party of Canada]]. Despite the Reform Party being dominated by social conservatives, leader [[Preston Manning]], seeking greater national support for the party, was reluctant for the party to wholly embrace socially conservative values. This led to his deposition as leader of the party (now called [[Canadian Alliance]]) in favor of social conservative [[Stockwell Day]].&lt;ref&gt;Murray Dobbin, ''Preston Manning and the Reform Party'' (1991)&lt;/ref&gt; The party's successor, the [[Conservative Party of Canada]], despite having a number of socially conservative members and cabinet ministers, has chosen so far not to focus on socially conservative issues in its platform. This was most recently exemplified on two occasions in 2012 when the current [[Conservative Party of Canada]] declared they had no intention to repeal [[same-sex marriage]] or [[abortion]] laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.nationalpost.com/2012/01/13/same-sex-marriages-declared-legal-and-valid-by-justice-minister-rob-nicholson/|title=Same-sex marriages declared legal and valid by federal justice minister Rob Nicholson|date=13 January 2012|work=National Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== China ===
[[Chiang Kai-shek]], a former [[President of the Republic of China|president]] of [[Republic of China (1912–1949)|Republic of China]], could be seen as a social conservative who was critical of [[Liberalism in China|liberal values]] and defended the union of [[Confucian]] traditions and [[modernism]]. Under his rule, the [[Kuomintang]] led the [[New Life Movement]].

After the [[Chinese Communist Revolution]], social conservatism in China increased due to the rise of [[New Confucianism]] and others after the 1970s to 1980s during the [[Chinese economic reform]].

[[General Secretary of the Chinese Communist Party|CCP general secretary]] [[Xi Jinping]] has adopted a more conservative social view since he began his [[20th National Congress of the Chinese Communist Party|third leadership]] in 2022. He reflects traditional and patriarchal views of women in speeches and policies. This is related to China's low birth rate problem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url=https://time.com/6330091/china-population-xi-childbirth-culture/ |title=Facing Population Decline, China's Xi Promotes 'Childbirth Culture' for Women |date=31 October 2023 |magazine=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic world===
{{Further|Sharia|Conservatism in Islam}}
Most Muslim countries are somewhat more socially conservative (such as [[Tajikistan]] and [[Malaysia]]) than neighbouring countries that are not Muslim. However, due to their interpretation of Islamic law also known as Shariah, they have some differences from social conservatism as understood in the nations of West Europe, North America and Oceania.{{cn|date=September 2023}}

==== Arab world ====
{{Further|Arab world|Islam|Censorship}}
The Arab world has recently{{when|date=October 2021}} been more conservative in social and moral issues due to the [[Arab Spring|Arab spring]].{{citation needed|date=October 2020}}

===India===
==== Hindu social conservatism ====
{{Further|Shiv Sena|Bharatiya Janata Party|Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh|Hindu nationalism|Hindutva}}
Hindu social conservatism in India in the twenty first century has developed into an influential movement, represented in the political arena by the [[Right-wing politics|right-wing]] [[Bharatiya Janata Party]]. Hindu social conservatism, also known as the [[Hindutva]] movement, is spearheaded by the voluntary non-governmental organization [[Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh]]. The core philosophy of this ideology is [[nativism (politics)|nativism]], and it sees [[Hinduism]] as a national identity, rather than a religious one. Due to an inclination towards [[nativism (politics)|nativism]], much of its platform is based on the belief that Islamic and Christian denominations in India are the result of occupations, and, therefore, these groups should be uprooted from the [[Indian subcontinent]] by converting their members back to [[Hinduism]].

In terms of political positions, Hindu social conservatives in India seek to institutionalize a [[Uniform civil code of India|Uniform Civil Code]] (which is also a directive under Article 44 of the [[Constitution of India]]) for members of all religions,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Press Trust of India |url=http://www.expressindia.com/news/fullstory.php?newsid=23591 |title=Muslim leaders oppose uniform civil code |publisher=Express India |date=2 August 2003 |access-date=18 August 2014 |archive-date=25 September 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120925185807/http://www.expressindia.com/news/fullstory.php?newsid=23591 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; over the current scheme of different personal laws for different religions. For instance, [[polygamy]] is legal for Muslims in India, but not Hindus.

==== Muslim social conservatism ====
{{Further|Lakshar-e-Taiba}}
There are several socially conservative Muslim organisations in India, ranging from groups such as the [[Indian Union Muslim League]] which aim to promote the preservation of Indian Muslim culture as a part of the nation's identity and history.{{citation needed|date=January 2019}}

=== South Africa ===

Social conservatism had an important place in [[Apartheid]] South Africa ruled by the [[National Party (South Africa)|National Party]].  Pornography,&lt;ref&gt;JCW Van Rooyen, Censorship in South Africa (Cape Town: Juta and Co., 1987),&lt;/ref&gt; gambling&lt;ref&gt;Bet and board in the new South Africa. (legalisation of gambling could lead to growth of casinos, lotteries)(Brief Article)''The Economist'' (US) | 5 August 1995&lt;/ref&gt; and other activities that were deemed undesirable were severely restricted. The majority of businesses were forbidden from doing [[Sunday shopping|business on Sunday]].&lt;ref&gt;Apartheid mythology and symbolism.
desegregated and re-invented in the service of nation building in the new South Africa: the covenant and the battle of Blood/Ncome River&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United States ===
{{Main|Social conservatism in the United States}}

Social conservatism in the [[United States]] is a [[right-wing politics|right-wing]] political ideology that opposes [[progressivism|social progressivism]]. It is centered on the preservation of what adherents often call 'traditional' or '[[family values]]', though the accepted aims of the movement often vary amongst the organisations it comprises, making it hard to generalise about ideological preferences. There are, however, a number of general principles to which at least a majority of social conservatives adhere, such as [[Anti-abortion movements|opposition to abortion]] and opposition to [[same-sex marriage]].&lt;ref name="Wiener 1973" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Riley|first1=Jim|title=Liberalism &amp; Conservatism|url=http://academic.regis.edu/jriley/libcons.htm|website=academic.regis.edu|access-date=4 July 2017|archive-date=14 November 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171114163741/http://academic.regis.edu/jriley/libcons.htm|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Farney|first1=James Harold|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=odcZbJnUN3cC&amp;pg=PA13|title=Social Conservatives and Party Politics in Canada and the United States|date=2012|publisher=University of Toronto Press|isbn=9781442612600|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Cramer|first=Clayton E.|title=Social Conservatism in An Age of Revolution: Legislating Christian Morality in Revolutionary America|year=2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sociologist [[Harry F. Dahms]] suggests that Christian doctrinal conservatives (anti-abortion, anti-same-sex marriage) and gun-use conservatives (such as supporters and members of the [[National Rifle Association of America]] (NRA)) form two domains of ideology within American social conservatism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-first=Robert B. |author-last=Smith |title=Social Conservatism, Distractors, and Authoritarianism: Axiological versus instrumental rationality |editor=Harry F. Dahms |date=2014|publisher=Emerald Group Publishing|isbn=9781784412227|page=101|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=C5V1BQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA101|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]] is the largest United States political party with socially conservative ideals incorporated into its platform. Other socially conservative parties include the [[American Solidarity Party]], the [[Constitution Party (United States)|Constitution Party]] and the [[Prohibition Party]].

Social conservatives are strongest in the South, where they are a mainstream political force with aspirations to translate those ideals using the party platform nationally. Supporters of social conservatism played a major role in the political coalitions of [[Ronald Reagan]] and [[George W. Bush]].&lt;ref&gt;Darren Dochuk, ''From Bible Belt to Sun Belt: Plain-Folk Religion, Grassroots Politics, and the Rise of Evangelical Conservatism'' (W.W. Norton &amp; Company; 2010) shows how migrants to Southern California from Oklahoma, Texas, and Arkansas provided evangelical support for social conservatism.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other areas===
There are also social conservative movements in many other parts of the world, such as [[Latin America]], [[Eastern Europe]], the [[Balkans]], the [[Caucasus]], [[Central Europe]], [[List of Mediterranean countries|Mediterranean countries]], [[Southeast Asia]], and [[Oceania]].

== Examples of social conservative political parties ==
{{more citations needed section|date=August 2017}}

===Armenia===
* [[Conservative Party (Armenia)|Conservative Party]]
* [[Constitutional Rights Union]]
* [[For Social Justice (Armenia)|For Social Justice]]
* [[National Christian Party (Armenia)|National Christian Party]]
* [[Pan-Armenian National Agreement]]
* [[Prosperous Armenia]]
* [[Republican Party of Armenia]]

=== Australia ===
* [[Liberal Party of Australia]] (factions)
* [[National Party of Australia]] (factions)
* [[Family First Party (2021)|Family First Party]]
* [[Democratic Labour Party (Australia, 1978)|Democratic Labour Party]]
* [[Katter's Australian Party]]
* [[Pauline Hanson's One Nation]]
* [[Shooters, Fishers and Farmers Party]]
* [[United Australia Party (2013)|United Australia Party]]

===Austria===
* [[Freedom Party of Austria]]
* [[Austrian People's Party]]
* [[Christian Party of Austria]]

===Belgium===
* [[New-Flemish Alliance]]
* [[Vlaams Belang]]

===Bosnia and Herzegovina===
* [[Alliance of Independent Social Democrats]]

===Brazil===
* [[Brazilian Labour Renewal Party]]
* [[Brazilian Woman's Party]]
* [[Christian Democracy (Brazil)|Christian Democracy]]
* [[Liberal Party (Brazil, 2006)|Liberal Party]]
* [[Republicans (Brazil)|Republicans]]

=== Bulgaria ===
* [[GERB]]
* [[IMRO – Bulgarian National Movement]]
* [[Bulgarian Socialist Party]] (factions)

===Cambodia===
* [[Cambodian People's Party]]

===Canada===
* [[Conservative Party of Canada]] (factions)
* [[Christian Heritage Party of Canada]]
* [[People's Party of Canada]] (factions)

=== Chile ===
* [[Christian Social Party (Chile)|Christian Social Party]] (PDC)
* [[Republican Party (Chile, 2019)|Chilean Republican Party]] (PLR)
* [[Independent Democratic Union]] (UDI)

===Czech Republic===
* [[Freedom and Direct Democracy]]
* [[KDU-ČSL]]

===Denmark===
* [[Danish People's Party]]

===El Salvador===
* [[Nuevas Ideas]]
* [[Nationalist Republican Alliance]]

===Estonia===
* [[Conservative People's Party of Estonia|Conservative People's Party]]
* [[Isamaa]]

===Faroe Islands===
* [[Centre Party (Faroe Islands)|Centre Party]]

===Fiji===
* [[Social Democratic Liberal Party]]

===Finland===
* [[Finns Party]]
* [[Christian Democrats (Finland)|Christian Democrats]]

===France===
* [[Movement for France]]
* [[National Rally]]
* [[VIA, the Way of the People]]

=== Germany ===
* [[Christian Democratic Union of Germany]]
* [[Alternative for Germany]]
* [[Family Party of Germany]]
* [[Alliance C – Christians for Germany]]
* [[Bündnis Sahra Wagenknecht]]

===Georgia===
* [[Alliance of Patriots of Georgia]]

=== Greece ===
* [[New Democracy (Greece)|New Democracy]] (factions)
* [[Greek Solution]]
* [[Independent Greeks]]

===Hungary===
* [[Fidesz]]
* [[Christian Democratic People's Party (Hungary)|Christian Democratic People's Party]]
* [[Our Homeland Movement]]
* [[Jobbik]]

===India===
* [[Bharatiya Janata Party]]
* [[All India Majlis-e-Ittehadul Muslimeen]]
* [[Shiv Sena (1966–2022)|Shiv Sena]]
* [[Maharashtra Navnirman Sena]]
* [[National People's Party (India)|National People's Party]]

===Ireland===
* [[Aontú]]
* [[Renua]]

===Israel===
* [[Shas]]
* [[Agudat Yisrael]]
* [[Degel HaTorah]]
* [[National Religious Party–Religious Zionism]]
* [[Noam (political party)|Noam]]
* [[Otzma Yehudit]]

===Italy===
* [[The People of Family]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intelligonews.it/articoli/24-marzo-2016/38867/il-programma-del-popolo-della-famiglia-di-mario-adinolfi-c-e-x-come-xenofilia-e-y-come-y-chromosome Il programma del Popolo della Famiglia di Mario Adinolfi] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170118032608/http://www.intelligonews.it/articoli/24-marzo-2016/38867/il-programma-del-popolo-della-famiglia-di-mario-adinolfi-c-e-x-come-xenofilia-e-y-come-y-chromosome |date=18 January 2017 }} (intelligonews)&lt;/ref&gt;  (''Il Popolo della Famiglia'')
* [[Christian Italy]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.italiacristiana.it/il-programma-2/ Programma] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170307052641/http://www.italiacristiana.it/il-programma-2/ |date=7 March 2017 }} (Italia Cristiana)&lt;/ref&gt;  (''Italia Cristiana'')
* [[Union of the Centre (2002)|Union of the Centre]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://parties-and-elections.eu/italy.html Parties and Elections in Europe] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120615231622/http://parties-and-elections.eu/italy.html |date=15 June 2012 }}. Parties-and-elections.eu. Retrieved on 24 August 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ignazi2008"&gt;{{cite book|author=Piero Ignazi|title=Partiti politici in Italia |year=2008|publisher=Il Mulino, Bologna|page=58}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===
* [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic Party]]&lt;ref name="blogs.wsj.com"&gt;Inada, Miho; Dvorak, Phred. [https://blogs.wsj.com/japanrealtime/2013/09/20/same-sex-marriage-in-japan-a-long-way-away/ "Same-Sex Marriage in Japan: A Long Way Away?"] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160616022229/https://blogs.wsj.com/japanrealtime/2013/09/20/same-sex-marriage-in-japan-a-long-way-away/ |date=16 June 2016 }}. ''The Wall Street Journal''. 20 September 2013. Retrieved 31 March 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Lockhart |first=Charles |year=2010 |title=Protecting the Elderly: How Culture Shapes Social Policy |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZcO7LGc5CogC&amp;pg=PA84 |publisher=Penn State Press |page=84 |isbn=978-0-271-02289-5 |access-date=22 November 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor1-last=Magara |editor1-first=Hideko |editor2-last=Sacchi |editor2-first=Stefano |year=2013 |title=The Politics of Structural Reforms: Social and Industrial Policy Change in Italy and Japan |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=beLDAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA95 |publisher=Edward Elgar Publishing |page=95 |isbn=978-0-85793-292-1 |access-date=22 November 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor1-last=Pekkanen |editor1-first=Robert J. |editor2-last=Scheiner |editor2-first=Ethan |editor3-last=Reed |editor3-first=Steven R. |year=2016 |title=Japan decides 2014: the Japanese general election |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6m_eCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA104 |publisher=Springer |pages=104, 106 |doi=10.1057/9781137552006 |isbn=978-1-349-56437-8 |access-date=22 November 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Komeito]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor=Lucien Ellington |title=Japan |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Fox9YR80V7sC&amp;q=social+conservative+Komeito&amp;pg=PA168 |quote= ... Because of this political strength, the Liberal Democratic Party has in recent years included the moderate to socially conservative Komeito Party in coalition governments. |date=2009 |page=168 |publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]]|isbn=9781598841626 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Kazakhstan ===
* [[Amanat (political party)|Amanat]]

===Latvia===
* [[National Alliance (Latvia)|National Alliance]]
* [[The Conservatives (Latvia)|The Conservatives]]

===Liechtenstein===
* [[Patriotic Union (Liechtenstein)|Patriotic Union]]
* [[Progressive Citizens' Party]]

===Lithuania===
* [[Order and Justice]]

===Luxembourg===
* [[Alternative Democratic Reform Party]]
* [[Déi Konservativ]]

===Malaysia===
* [[United Malays National Organization]] (UMNO)
* [[Malaysian United Indigenous Party]] (BERSATU)
* [[Homeland Fighters' Party]] (PEJUANG)

=== Mexico ===
* [[National Action Party (Mexico)|National Action Party]]
* [[Institutional Revolutionary Party]]
* [[Social Encounter Party]]

===Moldova===
* [[Party of Socialists of the Republic of Moldova]]
* [[Victory (political bloc)|Victory]]
* [[Party of Communists of the Republic of Moldova]]

===Netherlands===
* [[Christian Union (Netherlands)|Christian Union]] (CU){{cn|date=August 2024}}
* [[Reformed Political Party]] (SGP)

===New Zealand===
* [[New Zealand National Party|National Party]] (factions)
* [[New Conservative Party (New Zealand)|New Conservative Party]]
* [[New Zealand First]]

===Norway===
* [[Christian Democratic Party (Norway)|Christian Democratic Party]]
* [[Conservative (Norwegian political party)|Conservative]]

===Philippines===
* [[Nationalist People's Coalition]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |chapter=Philippines |title=World Encyclopedia of Political Systems and Parties |publisher=Facts On File |year=1999 |pages=887}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |first=Louis |last=Perron |title=Election Campaigns in the Philippines |publisher=Routledge |year=2009 |page=361}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Poland===
* [[Law and Justice]]
* [[United Poland]]
* [[The Republicans (Poland)|The Republicans]]
* [[Polish People's Party]]
* [[Confederation Liberty and Independence]]

=== Portugal ===
* [[Social Democratic Party (Portugal)|Social Democratic Party]]
* [[CDS – People's Party]]
* [[Chega (political party)|Chega]]

===Romania===
* [[Social Democratic Party (Romania)|Social Democratic Party]]
* [[National Liberal Party (Romania)|National Liberal Party]]
* [[People's Movement Party]]
* [[Alliance for the Union of Romanians]]
* [[Ecologist Party of Romania]]
* [[Democratic Alliance of Hungarians in Romania]]

===Russia===
* [[United Russia]]
* [[CPRF]]
* [[LDPR]]
* [[A Just Russia]]

===Slovakia===
* [[Christian Democratic Movement]]
* [[Direction – Social Democracy]]
* [[Slovak National Party]]
* [[We Are Family (Slovakia)|We Are Family]]
* [[People's Party Our Slovakia]]
* [[Republic (Slovakia)|Republic]]
* [[Christian Union (Slovakia)|Christian Union]]

=== Spain ===
* [[Spanish Alternative]]
* [[People's Party (Spain)|People's Party]]
* [[Vox (Spanish political party)|Vox]]

===Serbia===
* [[Serbian Radical Party]]
* [[Dveri]]
* [[Healthy Serbia]]
* [[Better Serbia]]
* [[Democratic Party of Serbia]]
* [[People's Freedom Movement (Serbia)|People's Freedom Movement]]
* [[Serbian Party Oathkeepers]]
* [[Serbian Right]]

=== Sweden ===
* [[Sweden Democrats]]
* [[Christian Democrats (Sweden)|Christian Democrats]]
* [[Alternative for Sweden]]

===Switzerland===
* [[Swiss People's Party]]
* [[Federal Democratic Union of Switzerland]]
* [[Evangelical People's Party of Switzerland]]

===Turkey===
* [[Justice and Development Party (Turkey)|Justice and Development Party]]
* [[Nationalist Movement Party]]
* [[Felicity Party]]
* [[Great Unity Party]]

===Ukraine===
* [[European Solidarity]]
* [[Batkivshchyna]]

===United Kingdom===
* [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] (factions)
* [[Heritage Party (UK)|Heritage Party]]
* [[UK Independence Party]]
* [[Social Democratic Party (UK, 1990–present)]]
* [[Workers Party of Britain]]
* [[Scottish Family Party]]

====Northern Ireland====
* [[Democratic Unionist Party]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/2015/04/27/gay-marriage-once-again-blocked-in-northern-ireland-by-socially-conservative-democratic-unionist-party_n_7152810.html |title=Gay Marriage Bill In Northern Ireland Blocked Again By Socially Conservative Democratic Unionist Party |work=Huffingtonpost.co.uk |date=27 April 2015 |access-date=9 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Traditional Unionist Voice]]
* [[Aontú]]

===United States===
* [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]] (factions)
* [[Constitution Party (United States)|Constitution Party]]
* [[Prohibition Party]]
* [[American Solidarity Party]]
* [[Christian Liberty Party]]
* [[Alaskan Independence Party]]
* [[American Independent Party]]

==Social conservative factions of political parties==
* [[Blue Labour]] ([[Labour Party (UK)]])
* [[Cornerstone Group]] ([[Conservative Party (UK)]])
* [[House Freedom Caucus]] ([[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party (USA)]])
* [[National Right (Liberal Party of Australia)|National Right]] ([[Liberal Party of Australia]])
* [[Republican Study Committee]] ([[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party (USA)]])

==See also==
{{Portal|Conservatism}}
* [[Christian right]]
* [[Social inertia]]: the prevention of social change
* [[Social liberalism]]
* [[Victorian morality]]
* [[High Tory]]
* [[Paleoconservatism]]
* [[Traditionalist conservatism]]
* [[Social conservatism in Canada]]
* [[Social conservatism in the United States]]
* [[Anti-abortion movement]]
* [[Family values]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book|last=Heywood|first=Andrew|year=2017|title=Political Ideologies: An Introduction|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=978-1-137-60604-4}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin|40em}}
* [[Allan C. Carlson|Carlson, Allan]], ''The Family in America: Searching for Social Harmony in the Industrial Age'' (2003) {{ISBN|0-7658-0536-7}}
* [[Allan C. Carlson|Carlson, Allan]], ''Family Questions: Reflections on the American Social Crisis'' (1991) {{ISBN|1-56000-555-6}}
* Fleming, Thomas, ''The Politics of Human Nature,'' (1988) {{ISBN|1-56000-693-5}}
* Gallagher, Maggie, ''The Abolition of Marriage: How We Destroy Lasting Love'' (1996) {{ISBN|0-89526-464-1}}
* Himmelfarb, Gertrude, ''The De-moralization Of Society'' (1996) {{ISBN|0-679-76490-9}}
* Hitchens, Peter, ''[[The Abolition of Britain]]''. (1999) {{ISBN|0-7043-8117-6}}
* Jones, E. Michael, ''Degenerate Moderns: Modernity As Rationalized Sexual Misbehavior''. (1993) {{ISBN|0-89870-447-2}}
* Kirk, Russell, ''The Conservative Mind,'' 7th Ed. (2001) {{ISBN|0-89526-171-5}}
* Magnet, Myron, ''Modern Sex: Liberation and Its Discontents'' (2001) {{ISBN|1-56663-384-2}}
* Medved, Diane and Dan Quayle, ''The American Family: Discovering the Values That Make Us Strong'' (1997) {{ISBN|0-06-092810-7}}
* Sobran, Joseph, ''Single Issues: Essays on the Crucial Social Questions'' (1983) {{ISBN|1-199-24333-7}}.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* {{Commons category-inline}}

{{Social philosophy}}
{{Christian Democracy}}
{{Conservatism navbox}}
{{American Social Conservatism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Social Conservatism}}
[[Category:Social conservatism| ]]
[[Category:Conservatism]]
[[Category:Right-wing ideologies]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Social policy]]
[[Category:Political science terminology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>