<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071102022947|168649100" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="219177" pageid="219177" ns="0" title="Social conservatism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-02T12:47:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Articleissues|POV=August 2007|unreferenced=March 2007|globalize=August 2007}}
{{conservatism}}

'''Social [[conservatism]]''' generally refers to a political ideology or personal belief system that advocates the conservation or resurrection of what one, or one's community, considers to be [[traditional]] [[morality]] and social structure. However, the accepted meaning of traditional morality often differs from group to group within social conservatism. Thus, there are really no policies or positions that could be considered universal among social conservatives. There are, however, a number of principles to which at least a majority of social conservatives adhere.

A second meaning of the term has developed in the [[Nordic countries]]. Here it refers to pro-welfare [[liberal conservatism|liberal conservatives]].

== Definition and Core Principles ==
{{Original research|date=September 2007}}
There are two main principles which drive Social Conservatism:

'''Limit the definition of family.''' Social Conservatism opposes divorce except for infidelity, sex outside of marriage, commercialization of sex, sequential monogamy, domestic partnerships, and same-sex marriage. However this is a generalization, since not all social conservatives agree with each other on these principles: for instance, Roman Catholic social conservatives do not believe in divorce for any reason, while other social conservatives accept divorce for any number of reasons. Roman Catholic social conservatives would also add "opposes contraception in any form" and "opposes in vitro fertilization" to the above list.  Many social conservatives &amp;mdash; for instance [[Richard Cheney|Dick]] and [[Lynne Cheney]] &amp;mdash; accept and actively support [[Mary Cheney|family members]] who enter into domestic partnerships or who are part of [[gay]] families.  Groups who consider themselves social conservatives hold a wide range of views on issues related to the family.

'''Sanctity of human life.''' Social Conservatism is often believed to generally reject abortion, euthanasia, and embryonic stem cell research.  Socially conservative [[Quakers]], [[Mennonites]], and [[Amish]] maintain that their respect for the sanctity of human life requires of them a [[pacifist]] view of war.  But social conservatism, like [[social progressivism]], also embraces human rights and the dignity of the individual in societies where these values have a long history of popular support.  (In societies with no standing tradition of respecting human rights or individual liberties, these values are considered liberal or even radical.)  As with matters related to the family, social conservatives do not generally agree among themselves about even these issues.  Many social conservatives reach the conclusion that their respect for traditional notions of individual autonomy, limited governmental power, and privacy require them to support a pro-choice policy on abortion.  Prominent social conservatives such as [[Nancy Reagan]] are vocal supporters of stem cell medical research.  Social conservatives who oppose the death penalty are a distinct minority, as most social conservatives support the death penalty because it is either a retributive or traditional form of punishment.

Social Conservatives believe that their personal views are inalienable and ought to be protected by other laws and policies developed by governments, and taught in school, or the view points at least discussed in schools.

The opposite of Social Conservatism is [[Social Progressivism]].

Social Conservatism is almost universal among the [[Christian Right]]. The basic principles are believed to derive from [[Natural Law]] &amp;mdash; that is, the system of social norms that may appear to arise naturally in human societies through time and across cultures &amp;mdash; rather than being a construct specific to one culture or time.

Therefore, the way Social Conservatism plays out in practice varies between locations, depending on the social, religious and national traditions of a particular place. However, they all have in common the idea of protecting or enhancing their respective understanding of what constitutes "family" in relation to that of the State.

== Social vs. Other Conservatisms ==
There is no necessary link between Social and Economic or [[fiscal conservative|Fiscal Conservatism]]. In fact, some Social Conservatives are otherwise apolitical or even left-wing on fiscal issues. For example, Social Conservatives may also support a degree of government intervention in economic life for what they feel is to the benefit of the community, and as such will tend to support the concept of a [[social market]] economy to further this aim. This concern for material welfare, like advocacy of traditional mores, will often have a basis in the religion of the Social Conservatives in question. Examples of such Social Conservatives include the [[Christian Social Union of Bavaria]], the [[Family First]] and [[Democratic Labor Party]] of Australia,the so-called [[red tory]] movement in Canada, and possibly the [[Communitarian]] movement in the United States.

There is more overlap between Social Conservatism and [[Paleoconservative|Paleoconservatism]] in that they both have respect for traditional social forms. However, [[Paleoconservative|Paleoconservatism]] has a strong [[cultural conservatism|Cultural Conservative]] strain which Social Conservatism, in and of itself, is not necessarily allied with. For example, [[John Burger]], writing in [[Crisis Magazine]] in 2005 said:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
"''The presence of a significant population of culturally Catholic immigrants offers hope that their culture will permeate a decadent American society and contribute to the re-evangelization of native-born Catholics. . . Abortion is still illegal in most Latin American countries. And in most areas, it’s not even part of a person’s consciousness''." [http://www.crisismagazine.com/julaug2005/burger.htm]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Social Conservative Political Parties ==
A few examples only. Many [[Christian Democracy|Christian Democratic Parties]] around the world are Socially Conservative.

'''Canada'''
* [http://familycoalitionparty.com/ Family Coalition Party of Ontario]
* [http://www.chp.ca/ Christian Heritage Party of Canada]
* A large number of [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative Party]] members in Canada are considered socially conservative also.  An example being the [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative Party]] was the only mainstream party that opposed same-sex marriage in Canada.  Although the party has no stance on abortion, many of its member are for fetal rights, and its the defacto party for Pro Life Canadians. 

'''Australia'''
* [[Democratic Labor Party]]
* [[Family First]]
* [[Christian Democratic Party (Australia)|Christian Democratic Party]]
* A large number of [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal Party]] and [[National Party of Australia|National Party]] members in Australia are considered socially conservative also, as are those members of the [[Australian Labor Party]] associated with the [[Shop, Distributive and Allied Employees Association|Shop Stewards]] union. 

'''Germany'''
* [[Christian Social Union of Bavaria]]
* [[Partei Bibeltreuer Christen]]

'''United States'''
* [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]]              
'''Ireland'''
* [[Muintir na hÉireann]]
'''Nigeria'''
* [[People's Democratic Party (Nigeria)|People's Democratic Party (PDP)]]
* [[All Nigeria Peoples Party|All Nigeria Peoples Party (ANPP)]]

'''Sweden'''
* [[Sweden Democrats]]

'''Japan'''
* [[New Komeito Party]]

'''United Kingdom'''
* [[Democratic Unionist Party]]

== Resources ==
'''Books'''
* [[Allan C. Carlson|Carlson, Alan]], ''The Family in America: Searching for Social Harmony in the Industrial Age'' (2003) ISBN 0-7658-0536-7
* [[Allan C. Carlson|Carlson, Alan]], ''Family Questions: Reflections on the American Social Crisis'' (1991) ISBN 1-56000-555-6
* Fleming, Thomas, ''The Politics of Human Nature,'' (1988) ISBN 1-56000-693-5
* Gallagher, Maggie, ''The Abolition of Marriage: How We Destroy Lasting Love'' (1996) ISBN 0-89526-46 4-1
* Himmelfarb, Gertrude, ''The De-moralization Of Society'' (1996) ISBN 0-679-76490-9
* Hitchens, Peter, ''[[The Abolition of Britain]]''. (1999) ISBN 0-7043-8117-6
* Jones, E. Michael, ''Degenerate Moderns: Modernity As Rationalized Sexual Misbehavior''. (1993) ISBN 0-89870-447-2
* Kirk, Russell, ''The Conservative Mind,'' 7th Ed. (2001) ISBN 0-89526-171-5
* Magnet, Myron, ''Modern Sex: Liberation and Its Discontents'' (2001) ISBN 1-56663-384-2
* Medved, Diane and Dan Quayle, ''The American Family: Discovering the Values That Make Us Strong'' (1997) ISBN 0-06-092810-7
* Sobran, Joseph, ''Single Issues: Essays on the Crucial Social Questions'' (1983) ISBN 1-199-24333-7.

'''Social Conservative Groups in Canada'''
* [http://www.socon.ca/ Socons United ]
* [http://www.equite-famille.ca/ Équité-Famille] (French language)
* [http://www.realwomenca.com/ REAL Women of Canada ]
* [http://www.preservemarriage.ca/ Preserve Marriage - Protect Children's Rights] (French and English)

'''Social Conservative Groups in USA'''
* [http://www.family.org/ Focus on the Family ]

'''Social Conservative News Services'''
* [http://www.theinterim.com/ The Interim]

== See also ==
* [[Christian Democracy]]
* [[Conservatism]]
* [[Paleoconservatism]]
* [[Pro-life]]
* [[Communitarian]]
* [[Social conservatism (Canada)]]
* [[Distributism]]
* [[Social progressivism]]

[[Category:Conservatism]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Political science terms]]

[[da:Socialkonservatisme]]
[[es:Conservadurismo social]]
[[fr:Conservatisme social]]
[[nl:Sociaal conservatisme]]
[[sr:Пермисивност]]
[[sv:Socialkonservatism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>