<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051019200232|25944224" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="219177" pageid="219177" ns="0" title="Social conservatism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-05T00:06:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{conservatism}}
'''Social [[conservatism]]''' is a belief in traditional or [[natural law]]-based [[morality]] and social [[mores]] and the desire to preserve these in present day society, often through civil law or regulation. Social change is generally regarded as suspect, while social values based on tradition are generally regarded as tried, tested and true. Its opponents commonly associate it with conservative [[religious]] groups, [[militarism]] and [[nationalism]].

Opponents of social conservatism argue that tradition is not necessarily a source of [[wisdom]]. Many views and values, for instance, which were at one time viewed as "traditional" are now viewed as outdated or unacceptable. Proponents of social conservatism counter that many "modern" values are also vapid and corrupt, often pointing to the deterioration of the traditional nuclear family over the past century as a result of increased social acceptance of [[divorce]], [[promiscuity]], and [[homosexuality]].

The meaning of social conservatism may vary between locations, depending on the social, religious and nationalistic traditions of a particular locale. It may be, for instance, socially conservative to promote "traditional" marriage in a [[Protestantism|Protestant]], [[Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|mainstream Mormon]], or [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]] community, but socially conservative to promote [[polygamy]] in a devoutly [[Muslim]] or [[Mormon fundamentalism|fundamentalist Mormon]] community. What is considered to be socially conservative is therefore very much dependent on what is considered traditional.  Though most common in [[American Conservatism]]—indeed, international observers often wrongly believe it to be the whole of the US Conservative movement—it does have its counterparts outside the United States—in the UK, it is evinced in the work of writers like [[Peter Hitchens]] and [[Alexander Deane]], and in publications like the [[Salisbury Review]].

== See also ==

* [[Conservatism]]
* [[Social conservatism (Canada)]]

[[Category:Conservatism]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>