<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041105203646|7278018" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="219177" pageid="219177" ns="0" title="Social conservatism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-09T23:45:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Social conservatism''' is a belief in traditional [[morality]] and social [[mores]] and the desire to preserve these in present day society, often through civil law or regulation. Social change is generally regarded as suspect, while social values based on tradition are generally regarded as tried, tested and true. It is a view commonly associated with conservative [[religious]] groups, [[militarism]] and [[nationalism]].

Opponents of social conservatism argue that tradition is not necessarily a source of [[wisdom]]. Many views and values, for instance, which were at one time viewed as "traditional" are now viewed as outdated or even barbaric, such as [[slavery]], the excessive use of [[corporal punishment]], and in many Western countries (but not the US), [[capital punishment]]. Proponents of social conservatism counter that many "modern" values are also vapid and corrupt, often pointing to the perceived deterioration of the family over the past century as a result of increased social acceptance of [[divorce]] and [[promiscuity]].

The meaning of social conservatism may vary between locations, depending on the social, religious and nationalistic traditions of a particular locale. It may be, for instance, socially conservative to promote "traditional" marriage in a [[Protestant]], [[Mormon]], or [[Catholic]] community, but socially conservative to promote [[polygamy]] in a devoutly [[Muslim]] community. What is considered to be socially conservative is therefore very much dependent on what is considered traditional.

== See also ==

* [[Conservatism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>