<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061029144922|84425145" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="13547" pageid="13547" ns="0" title="Hate crime"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-04T22:13:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Hate crimes''' (also known as '''bias crimes''') are [[violent crime]]s, [[hate speech]] or [[vandalism]], motivated by feelings of [[enmity]] against an identifiable [[social group]]. If systematic, rather than spontaneous, participants in such crimes are members of [[hate groups]].

==Arguments for hate crime legislation==
When it enacted the Hate Crimes Act of 2000, the New York State Legislature included legislative findings that offer a survey of the various arguments for hate crime legislation. The legislature specifically found that:

"Hate crimes do more than threaten the safety and welfare of all citizens. They inflict on victims incalculable physical and emotional damage and tear at the very fabric of free society. Crimes motivated by invidious hatred toward particular groups not only harm individual victims but send a powerful message of intolerance and discrimination to all members of the group to which the victim belongs. Hate crimes can and do intimidate and disrupt entire communities and vitiate the civility that is essential to healthy democratic processes. In a democratic society, citizens cannot be required to approve of the beliefs and practices of others, but must never commit criminal acts on account of them. Current law does not adequately recognize the harm to public order and individual safety that hate crimes cause. Therefore, our laws must be strengthened to provide clear recognition of the gravity of hate crimes and the compelling importance of preventing their recurrence.  Accordingly, the legislature finds and declares that hate crimes should be prosecuted and punished with appropriate severity."{{citation needed}}

The legislature adopted a retributivist position when it argued that crimes motivated by animosity toward another’s protected status deserve more severe punishment.  The basic tenet of a retributivist outlook is that punishment should be commensurate with moral and social culpability.  Proponents point out that it is not unusual to make thoughts or states of mind ([[mens rea]]) elements of a crime. For example, the distinction between [[first-degree murder]], [[second-degree murder]], and [[manslaughter]] depends on the degree to which the killing was deliberate or premeditated. The definition of [[fraud]] requires [[scienter]] -- that the perpetrator knowingly defraud the victim.  Supporters also claim that all laws are subjective, and that if society can determine that one crime deserves more punishment than another (e.g. [[murder]] vs. [[involuntary manslaughter]]) then it can also determine what motivations deserve harsher [[punishments]].{{citation needed}}

The legislature applied a utilitarian approach when it argued that hate crimes impede the democratic process and should be prosecuted in order to protect the "public order."  The utilitarian perspective tends to view punishment as a means to maintain or enhance a social system that promotes the greatest overall good to the whole public.  This can be done through deterrence, rehabilitation, and/or incapacitation.  Here, the New York State Legislature employs more severe sentences in an effort to deter future crime and achieve the public policy goals put forth in the legislative findings.  Many support hate crime laws, stating that their harsher sentences give individuals greater discouragement from committing hate crimes.  Some supporters reason that one who can be moved to violence by hatred of a class of people presents a greater danger to society than one who merely hates an individual. Their position states that if normal punishments are inadequate deterrents, then additional punishments may deter crimes motivated by hate.

==Arguments against hate crimes legislation==
One basic argument against the concept of hate crimes is that it criminalizes thought by increasing the penalty for crimes based solely on motive. Some argue that the deliberation or premeditation that distinguishes degrees of murder and manslaughter are part of the act itself. Motives, whether they are hate, jealousy, greed, or passion, are not part of the crime in the same way. People sitting in a room discussing their hatred of a social group are not committing [[conspiracy (civil)|conspiracy]]. On the other hand, people plotting to rob a bank are guilty.

In weighing an offense under a utilitarian philosophy, the argument questions whether individual deterrence can be achieved over such an entrenched social conscience. Further, there is concern that general deterrence may not be achieved, and in fact may have the opposite effect of enraging individuals pscyhologically susceptible to developing anger and hatred towards others amidst a domination complex.{{citation needed}}

From a retributivist standpoint, there are also arguments that because the crime should be weighed from the standpoint of the harm to the victim, if a particular crime was equally harmful, then the mental state of the defendant should not require additional punishment.{{citation needed}}

The issue arises when a statute imposes additional sentencing criteria for a pre-existing offense for a guilty mind (mens rea). However, not every state form of statute is susceptible to this argument. In the Pennsylvania Code, a separate offense exists entitled "ethnic intimidation." The ethnic intimidation offense is a particular offense which requires both a specific form of criminal conduct and a particular state of mind (mens rea) at the time. There are offenses in criminal law, within both common law and civil law systems which do not require a separate mens rea including most public welfare (regulatory) offenses and homicide statutes based upon common law doctrinal Felony-Murder and Misdemeanor-Manslaughter rules. {{citation needed}}

==See also==
*[[Hate crimes in the United States]]
*[[Cognitive liberty]]
*[[Freedom of thought]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Thoughtcrime]]

==External links==
*[http://www.tolerance.org  Tolerance.org] , a web project sponsored by the [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] - [http://www.SPLCenter.org] 
*[http://www.asian-nation.org/racism.shtml Asian-Nation: Anti-Asian Racism &amp; Hate Crimes] by C.N. Le, Ph.D.
*[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_hat1.htm Definitions, laws, legislative efforts]
*[http://www.ibiblio.org/rcip//sbh.html Survivor bashing - bias motivated hate crimes]
*[http://www.hatecrime.net Hate Crimes Research Network]
* [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3724/is_199807/ai_n8811038 ''Identity parade''] - newspaper article from ''[[The Spectator]]'' by [[Mark Steyn]] on "hate crimes"

==News reports on recent alleged hate-crimes==
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/in_pictures/4913170.stm Egypt clashes between Coptic Christians and Muslims]
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4886298.stm Student murder in Russia 'racist']
*[http://timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,13509-2123721,00.html Swastika vigilantes kill foreign students to keep their city 'clean']
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/merseyside/4486956.stm Racist graffiti at murder scene]
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4486910.stm Learning lessons of Lawrence case]
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/merseyside/4475862.stm Murder 'proves racism exists']
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/merseyside/4477156.stm Youth guilty of racist axe murder]
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/merseyside/4639642.stm Walker family bid to fight racism]
*[http://news.scotsman.com/uk.cfm?id=2285652005 Asian gang guilty of racist killing]
*[http://www.thisislocallondon.co.uk/news/topstories/display.var.545802.0.0.php Three charged with campus murder]
*[http://news.yahoo.com/s/nm/20060611/music_nm/crime_assault_dc Four charged in hate crime attack on gay singer]
*[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/10/21/BAGMTLTGM51.DTL Religious hate seen as motive in killing Fremont slaying:]

[[Category:Hate crime| ]]
[[Category:Crimes]]
[[Category:Criminology topics]]

[[da:Hate crime]]
[[de:Hate crime]]
[[ja:ヘイトクライム]]
[[ru:Преступления на почве ненависти]]
[[simple:Hate crime]]
[[sv:Hatbrott]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>