<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081112122157|251325440" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="13547" pageid="13547" ns="0" title="Hate crime"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-13T03:44:17Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Hate crimes''' (also known as '''bias motivated crimes''') occur when a perpetrator targets a victim because of his or her membership in a certain [[social group]], usually defined by [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial group]], [[religion]], [[sexual orientation]], [[disability]], [[ethnicity]], [[nationality]], [[Ageing|age]], [[gender]], [[gender identity]], or [[political affiliation]].&lt;ref name="williams"&gt;Stotzer, R.: [https://www.law.ucla.edu/williamsinstitute/publications/Comparison%20of%20Hate%20Crime%20Formatted.pdf Comparison of Hate Crime Rates Across Protected and Unprotected Groups], [[The Williams Institute]], 2007-06. Retrieved on 2007-08-09.&lt;/ref&gt;

Hate crime can take many forms. Incidents may involve physical assault, damage to property, bullying, harassment, verbal abuse or insults, or offensive graffiti or letters.&lt;ref name = "ovrbwx"&gt;[http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/crime-victims/reducing-crime/hate-crime/ Home Office | Hate crime&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
Concern about hate crimes has become increasingly prominent among policymakers in many nations and at all levels of [[government]] in recent years, but the phenomenon is not new. Examples from the past include [[Roman Empire|Roman]] [[persecution]] of [[Christianity|Christians]], the [[Ottoman empire|Ottoman]] [[Armenian genocide|genocide]] of [[Armenians]], and the [[Nazi]] "[[final solution]]" for the [[Jew]]s, and more recently, the [[ethnic cleansing]] in [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia]] and [[genocide]] in [[Rwanda]]. Hate crimes have shaped and sometimes defined world history. In the [[United States]], racial and religious biases have inspired most hate crimes. As [[European ethnic groups|Europeans]] began to [[colonialism|colonize]] the New World in the 16th and 17th centuries, [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] increasingly became the targets of bias-motivated [[intimidation]] and [[violence]]. During the past two centuries, some of the more typical examples of hate crimes in the US include [[lynchings]] of [[African Americans]], [[cross burnings]] to drive black families from predominantly white neighborhoods, [[assault]]s on [[gay]], [[lesbian]] and [[transgender]] people, and the painting of [[swastika]]s on Jewish [[synagogue]]s.&lt;ref name = "tvccce"&gt;[http://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/bja/162304.pdf A Policymaker's Guide to Hate Crimes&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Hate crime victims ==

In the United States, anti-Black bias was the most frequently reported hate crime motivation. (African-Americans constitute the second-largest minority group; Hispanics are the largest).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2005/table1.htm Table 1 - Hate Crime Statistics 2005&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Of the nearly 8,000 hate crimes reported to the FBI in 1995, almost 3,000 of them were motivated by bias against African Americans.&lt;ref name="fbi"&gt;[http://www.fbi.gov/ucr/hatecm.htm#bias FBI - Uniform Crime Reports - Hate Crime Statistics 1995&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Other frequently reported bias motivations were anti-white, anti-Jewish, anti-gay, and anti-Hispanic.&lt;ref name="fbi" /&gt; A slight reduction in hate-crime occurrence has been recorded in more recent years.{{Fact|date=October 2008}}

== Hate crime laws ==
Hate crime laws generally fall into one of several categories: (1) laws defining specific bias-motivated acts as distinct crimes; (2) criminal penalty-enhancement laws; (3) laws creating a distinct civil cause of action for hate crimes; and (4) laws requiring administrative agencies to collect hate crime statistics.&lt;ref name="human"&gt;[http://www.humanrightsfirst.org/discrimination/pdf/everyday-fears-080805.pdf Microsoft Word - Everyday Fears FINAL for web.doc&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Sometimes (as in [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]), the laws focus on [[war crimes]], [[genocide]], and [[crimes against humanity]] with the prohibition against discriminatory action limited to public officials.

=== Eurasia ===
==== Andorra ====

Discriminatory acts constituting harassment or infringement of a person's dignity on the basis of origin, citizenship, race, religion, or sex (Penal Code Article 313). Courts have cited bias-based motivation in delivering sentences, but there is no explicit penalty enhancement provision in the Criminal Code. The government does not track hate crime statistics, although they are relatively rare.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Armenia ====

[[Armenia]] has a penalty-enhancement statute for crimes with ethnic, racial, or religious motives (Criminal Code Article 63).&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Austria ====

[[Austria]] has a penalty-enhancement statute for crimes with racist or xenophobic motivation (Penal Code section 33(5)).&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Azerbaijan ====

[[Azerbaijan]] has a penalty-enhancement statute for crimes motivated by racial, national, or religious hatred (Criminal Code Article 61). Murder and infliction of serious bodily injury motivated by racial, religious, national, or ethnic intolerance are distinct crimes (Article 111).&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Belarus ====

[[Belarus]] has a penalty-enhancement statute for crimes motivated by racial, national, and religious hatred and discord.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pravo.by/webnpa/text.asp?RN=HK9900275 Criminal Code of the Republic of Belarus, § 64 (1), para. 9 (translated from the Russian)], [[June 9]], 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Belgium ====

[[Belgium]]'s Act of [[25 February]] [[2003]] ("aimed at combating discrimination and modifying the Act of [[15 February]] [[1993]] which establishes the Centre for Equal Opportunities and the Fight against Racism") establishes a penalty-enhancement for crimes involving discrimination on the basis of sex, supposed race, color, descent, national or ethnic origin, sexual orientation, civil status, birth, fortune, age, religious or philosophical beliefs, current or future state of health and handicap or physical features. The Act also "provides for a civil remedy to address discrimination."&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;  The Act, along with the Act of [[20 January]] [[2003]] ("on strengthening legislation against racism"), requires the Centre to collect and publish statistical data on racism and discriminatory crimes.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Bosnia and Herzegovina ====

The Criminal Code of [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]] (enacted 2003) "contains provisions prohibiting discrimination by public officials on grounds, inter alia, of race, skin colour, national or ethnic background, religion and language and prohibiting the restriction by public officials of the language rights of the citizens in their relations with the authorities (Article 145/1 and 145/2)."&lt;ref&gt;Office of the High Representative, [http://www.ohr.int/decisions/judicialrdec/doc/HiRep-dec-101-law-crim-code-bih.doc Criminal Code of Bosnia and Herzegovina], January 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Bulgaria ====

[[Bulgaria]]n criminal law prohibits certain crimes motivated by racism and xenophobia, but a 1999 report by the [[European Commission against Racism and Intolerance]] found that it does not appear that those provisions "have ever resulted in convictions before the courts in Bulgaria."&lt;ref&gt;ECRI, Second Report on Bulgaria, adopted on [[June 18]], 1999, and made public on [[March 21]], [[2000]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Croatia ====

[[Croatia]]n law allows for consideration of any extenuating or aggravating circumstances in sentencing, but no explicit provision is made for bias-based motivations.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Czech Republic ====

"The [[Czech Republic|Czech]] Criminal Code defines racist motivation as a specific aggravating circumstance that judges are required to take into account in sentencing, as well as defining specific racist acts as crimes. Section 196 punishes 'violence against a group of inhabitants and against individuals on the basis of race, nationality, political conviction or religion.'"&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Denmark ====

Although [[Denmark]] law does not include explicit hate crime provisions, "section 80(1) of the Criminal Code instructs courts to take into account the gravity of the offence and the offenders motive when meting out penalty, and therefore to attach importance to the racist motive of crimes in determining sentence."&lt;ref&gt;ECRI, Second Report on Denmark, adopted on June 16, 2000, and made public on April 3, 2001, para. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;  In recent years judges have used this provision to increase sentences on the basis of racist motives.&lt;ref&gt;Chahrokh, Klug, and Bilger, Migrants, Minorities, and Legislation.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

Since 1992, the Danish Civil Security Service (PET) has released statistics on crimes with apparent racist motivation.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== England and Wales ====

In [[England and Wales]] criminal actions are considered hate crimes if they are perceived by the victim or any other person  as being motivated by prejudice and hatred. Hate crimes may be physical attack, [[verbal]] attack, [[Intimidation|threats]] or [[insults]] and will be considered a hate crime if they are motivated by the victims race, colour, ethnic origin, nationality or national origins, religion, gender or gender identity, sexual orientation or disability.&lt;ref name = "ovrbwx"/&gt;

==== Finland ====

[[Finland|Finnish]] Penal Code 515/2003 (enacted [[January 31]], [[2003]]) makes "committing a crime against a person,
because of his national, racial, ethnical or equivalent group" an aggravating circumstance in sentencing.&lt;ref&gt;EUMC, Racism and xenophobia in the E.U., p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="human" /&gt; In addition, ethnic agitation ({{lang-fi|kiihotus kansanryhmää vastaan}}) is criminalized and carries a fine or a prison sentence of not more than two years. The prosecution need not prove that an actual danger to an ethnic group is caused but only that malicious message is emissioned. A more aggravated hate crime, [[warmongering]] ({{lang-fi|sotaan yllyttäminen}}), carries a prison sentence of one to ten years. However, in case of warmongering, the prosecution must prove an overt act that evidently increases the risk that Finland is involved in a war or becomes a target for a military operation. The act in question may consist of 
#illegal violence directed against foreign country or her citizens, 
#systematic dissemination of false information on Finnish foreign policy or defence
#public influence on the public opinion towards a pro-war viewpoint or 
#public suggestion that a foreign country or Finland should engage in an aggressive act.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.finlex.fi/en/laki/kaannokset/1889/en18890039.pdf Penal Code (39/1889)] as of 1006/2004. §§ 6:5.1.4 (ethnic hatred as an aggravating factor), 11:8 (ethnic agitation) and 12:2 (warmongering). The points cited remain in force on the day of retrieval, checked from the Finnish version: [http://www.finlex.fi/fi/laki/ajantasa/1889/18890039001 Rikoslaki]. The Government proposal [http://217.71.145.20/TRIPviewer/show.asp?tunniste=HE+55/2007&amp;base=erhe&amp;palvelin=www.eduskunta.fi&amp;f=WORD HE 55/2007] will move the § 11:8 to §11:10 without changing the content, if the proposal is passed by the [[Parliament of Finland]]. Retrieved 11-23-2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==== France ====

In 2003, France enacted penalty-enhancement hate crime laws for crimes motivated by bias against the victim's actual or perceived ethnicity, nation, race, religion, or sexual orientation. The penalties for murder were raised from 30 years (for non-hate crimes) to life imprisonment (for hate crimes), and the penalties for violent attacks leading to permanent disability were raised from 10 years (for non-hate crimes) to 15 years (for hate crimes).&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Georgia ====

"There is no general provision in Georgian law for racist motivation to be considered an aggravating circumstance in prosecutions of ordinary offenses. Certain crimes involving racist motivation are, however, defined as specific offenses in the Georgian Criminal Code of 1999, including murder motivated by racial, religious, national or ethnic intolerance (article 109); infliction of serious
injuries motivated by racial, religious, national or ethnic intolerance (article 117); and torture motivated by racial, religious, national or ethnic intolerance (article 126). ECRI reported no knowledge of cases in which this law has been enforced. There is no systematic monitoring or data collection on discrimination in Georgia."&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Germany ====

The [[German Criminal Code]] permits the motives and aims of the criminal, including racist motives, to be taken into account in sentencing.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

§130 of the German penal code prohibits 

1) Incitement of violence, incitment of arbitrary discrimination
as well as &lt;br/&gt;
2) Violating people's human dignity by swearing at, denegrading or slandering 

groups of people defined by nationality, race, religion or ethnicity

==== Greece ====

Article Law 927/1979 "Section 1,1 penalises incitement to discrimination, hatred or violence towards individuals or groups because of
their racial, national or religious origin, through public written or oral expressions; Section 1,2 prohibits the
establishment of, and membership in, organisations which organise propaganda and activities aimed at racial
discrimination; Section 2 punishes public expression of offensive ideas; Section 3 penalises the act of refusing,
in the exercise of one’s occupation, to sell a commodity or to supply a service on racial grounds."&lt;ref&gt;ECRI, Second Report on Greece, adopted on 1999-12-10, and made public on 2000-06-27.&lt;/ref&gt; Public prosecutors may press charges even if the victim does not file a complaint. However, as of 2003, no convictions had been attained under the law.&lt;ref&gt;Sitaropoulos, N.: [http://europa.eu.int/comm/employment_social/fundamental_rights/pdf/legisln/msracequality/greece.pdf Executive Summary on Race Equality Directive, State of Play in Greece], section 5, 2003-10-12. Retrieved on 2007-08-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Hungary ====

Violent action, cruelty, and coercion by threat made on the basis of the victim's actual or perceived national, ethnic, or religious status are punishable under article 174/B of the [[Hungary|Hungarian]] Criminal Code.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Iceland ====
Section 233 of the Icelandic Penal Code states  "Anyone who in a ridiculing, slanderous, insulting, threatening or any other manner publicly assaults a person or a group of people on the basis of their nationality, skin colour, race, religion or sexual orientation, shall be fined or jailed for up to 2 years." (The word "assault" in this context does not refer to physical violence, only to expressions of hatred.)

[http://www.althingi.is/lagas/135a/1940019.html Icelandic Penal Code (in Icelandic)]

==== Iran ====

Iranian constitution's article 19 sates: All people of Iran, whatever the ethnic group or tribe to which they belong, enjoy equal rights; color, race, language, and the like, do not bestow any privilege.

Iranian constitution's article 20 sates: All citizens of the country, both men and women, equally enjoy the protection of the law and enjoy all human, political, economic, social, and cultural rights, in conformity with Islamic criteria.

Iranian constitution's article 14 prohibits the maltreatment of the non-islamic recognized minorities: In accordance with the sacred verse "God does not forbid you to deal kindly and justly with those who have not fought against you because of your religion and who have not expelled you from your homes" [60:8], the government of the Islamic Republic of Iran and all Muslims are duty-bound to treat non-Muslims in conformity with ethical norms and the principles of Islamic justice and equity, and to respect their human rights. This principle applies to all who refrain from engaging in conspiracy or activity against Islam and the Islamic Republic of Iran.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.servat.unibe.ch/law/icl/ir00000_.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Ireland ====

"The [[Prohibition of Incitement to Hatred Act 1989]] makes it an offense to incite hatred against any group of persons on account of their race, color, nationality, religion, ethnic or national origins, or membership of the Traveller community, an indigenous minority group."&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

[[Ireland]] does not systematically collect hate crime data.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Italy ====

Italian criminal law, at Section 3 of Law No. 205/1993, contains a penalty-enhancement provision for all crimes motived by racial, ethnic, national, or religious bias.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Kazakhstan ====

In [[Kazakhstan]], there are constitutional provisions prohibiting propaganda promoting racial or ethnic superiority.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Kyrgyzstan ====

In [[Kyrgyzstan]], "the Constitution of the State party prohibits any kind of discrimination on grounds of origin, sex, race, nationality, language, faith, political or religious convictions or any other personal or social trait or circumstance, and that the prohibition against racial discrimination is also included in other legislation, such as the Civil, Penal and Labour Codes."&lt;ref&gt;[http://wwjaiw.unhchr.ch/tbs/DOC.NSF/8e9c603f486cdf83802566f8003870e7/1b14be971da31f368025686a00522889?OpenDocument#A%2F54%2F18E CERD, Consideration of Reports Submitted by States Parties under Article 9 of the Convention; Concluding Observations: Kyrgyzstan], 1999. Retrieved on 2007-08-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

Article 299 of the Criminal Code defines incitement to national, racist, or religious hatred as a specific offense. This article has been used in political trials of suspected members of the banned organization [[Hizb-ut-Tahrir]].&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ihfhr.org/documents/doc_summary.php?sec_id=3&amp;d_id=3860 Human Rights in the OSCE Region: Europe, Central Asia and North America, Report 2004 (Events of 2003)], [[International Helsinki Federation]], 2004-06-23. Retrieved on 2007-08-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Scotland ====

In [[Scotland|Scottish]] [[Common law]] the courts can take any aggravating factor into account when sentencing someone found guilty of an offence. There is specific legislation dealing with the offences of incitement of racial hatred, racially-aggravated harassment and offences aggravated by religious prejudice. A [[Scottish Executive]] working party examined the issue of hate crime and ways of combating crime motivated by social prejudice, reporting in 2004.&lt;ref&gt; http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Topics/Justice/criminal/17543/8978 &lt;/ref&gt; Its main recommendations were not implemented, but in their manifestos for the [[Scottish Parliament election, 2007]] several political parties included commitments to legislate in this area, including the [[Scottish National Party]] who now form the Scottish Government.  The Offences (Aggravation by Prejudice) (Scotland) Bill was introduced on 19 May 2008 by [[Patrick Harvie]] MSP &lt;ref&gt; [http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/s3/bills/09-AggPrej/index.htm Offences (Aggravation by Prejudice) (Scotland) Bill] &lt;/ref&gt;, having been prepared with support from the Scottish Government.

==== Spain ====

Article 22(4) of the [[Spanish Penal Code]] includes a penalty-enhancement provision for crimes motivated by bias against the victim's ideology, beliefs, religion, ethnicity, race, nationality, gender, sexual orientation, illness, or disability.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Sweden ====

Article 29 of the [[Swedish Penal Code]] includes a penalty-enhancement provision for crimes motivated by bias against the victim's race, color, nationality, ethnicity, religion, or "other circumstance" of the victim.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== Eurasian countries with no hate crime laws ====

[[Albania]], [[Cyprus]], [[Estonia]], [[San Marino]], and [[Slovenia]] have no hate crime laws.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

=== North America ===
==== Canada ====

Since 1966 the [[Canada|Canadian]] Criminal Code has included a penalty-enhancement provision for crimes "motivated by bias, prejudice or hate based on racial group, national or ethnic origin, language, colour, religion, sex, age, mental or physical disability, sexual orientation, or any other similar factor."&lt;ref&gt;Canadian Criminal Code, Subparagraph 718.2(a)(i)&lt;/ref&gt; The Code also "punishes
anyone who advocates or promotes genocide, with genocide defined to require that acts be committed with the intent to destroy in whole or in part any identifiable group. Identifiable group, in turn, is defined to mean any section of the public distinguished by skin color, racial group, religion, ethnic origin or sexual orientation. Section 319, adopting the same definition of identifiable group, punishes the incitement or expression of hatred against such a group."&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;  Civil remedies are also available in Canada for discriminatory acts.&lt;ref name="human" /&gt;

==== United States ====
{{Main|Hate crime laws in the United States}}

As defined in the 1999 [[National Crime Victim Survey]], "A hate crime is a criminal offense committed against a person or property motivated, in whole or in part, by the offender's bias against a racial group, religion, ethnicity, gender, sexual preference, or disability. The offense is considered a hate crime whether or not the offender's perception of the victim as a member or supporter of a protected group is correct."&lt;ref&gt;http://66.102.1.104/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=cache:vynjDEZksWEJ:https://www.amstat.org/sections/srms/Proceedings/papers/1999_181.pdf+kkk+cross+burning+gang+signs&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[United States]] federal prosecution is possible for hate crimes committed on the basis of a person's race, color, religion, or nation origin when engaging in a federally protected activity. Measures to [[Matthew Shepard Act|add]] perceived [[gender]], [[gender identity]], [[sexual orientation]], and [[disability]] to the list have been proposed, but failed due to conservative opposition.

Forty-five states and the [[District of Columbia]] have statutes criminalizing various types of hate crimes. Thirty-one states and the District of Columbia have statutes creating a [[liability|civil cause of action]] in addition to the criminal penalty for similar acts. Twenty-seven states and the District of Columbia have statutes requiring the state to collect hate crime statistics&lt;ref name="adl"&gt;[http://www.adl.org/99hatecrime/state_hate_crime_laws.pdf State Hate Crime Laws], [[Anti-Defamation League]], June 2006. Retrieved 2007-05-04.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the FBI Hate Crime Statistics report for 2006, hate crimes increased nearly 8 percent nationwide, with a total of 7,722 incidents and 9,080 offenses reported by participating law enforcement agencies.  Of the 5,449 crimes against persons, 46 percent were classified as intimidation and 31.9 percent as simple assaults.  81 percent of the 3,593 crimes against property were acts of vandalism or destruction.  58.6 percent of the 7,330 known offenders were white and 20.6 black.   More than half, 52 percent, of  the 9,652 victims identified were targeted because of racial group.&lt;ref&gt;Hate Crime Statistics, 2006[http://www.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2006/index.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Arguments for hate crime laws ==

Justifications for harsher punishments for hate crimes focus on the notion that hate crimes cause greater individual and societal harm. In [[Wisconsin v. Mitchell]], the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] unanimously found that "bias-motivated crimes are more likely to provoke retaliatory crimes, inflict distinct emotional harms on their victims, and incite community unrest.... The State's desire to redress these perceived harms provides an adequate explanation for its penalty-enhancement provision over and above mere disagreement with offenders' beliefs or biases. As [[William Blackstone|Blackstone]] said long ago, 'it is but reasonable that, among crimes of different natures, those should be most severely punished which are the most destructive of the public safety and happiness.'"&lt;ref name="mitchell"&gt;[[Wisconsin v. Mitchell]], 508 U.S. 476 (1993).&lt;/ref&gt;  It is said that, when the core of a person’s identity is attacked, the degradation and [[dehumanization]] is especially severe, and additional emotional and physiological problems are likely to result. Society then, in turn, can suffer from the [[empowerment|disempowerment]] of a group of people. Furthermore, it is asserted that the chances for retaliatory crimes are greater when a hate crime has been committed. The [[riots]] in [[Los Angeles]], California, that followed the beating of Rodney King, a Black motorist, by a group of [[white people|White]] police officers are cited as support for this argument.&lt;ref name = "tvccce"/&gt;

The U.S. Supreme Court unanimously found that penalty-enhancement hate crime statutes do not conflict with [[free speech]] rights because they do not punish an individual for exercising [[freedom of expression]]; rather, they allow courts to consider motive when sentencing a criminal for conduct which is not protected by the First Amendment.&lt;ref name="mitchell" /&gt;

When it enacted the Hate Crimes Act of 2000, the [[New York State]] Legislature found that:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Hate crimes do more than threaten the safety and welfare of all citizens. They inflict on victims incalculable physical and emotional damage and tear at the very fabric of free society. Crimes motivated by invidious hatred toward particular groups not only harm individual victims but send a powerful message of [[intolerance]] and [[discrimination]] to all members of the group to which the victim belongs. Hate crimes can and do intimidate and disrupt entire communities and vitiate the civility that is essential to healthy [[democracy|democratic]] processes. In a democratic society, citizens cannot be required to approve of the beliefs and practices of others, but must never commit criminal acts on account of them. Current law does not adequately recognize the harm to public order and individual [[safety]] that hate crimes cause. Therefore, our laws must be strengthened to provide clear recognition of the gravity of hate crimes and the compelling importance of preventing their recurrence. Accordingly, the legislature finds and declares that hate crimes should be prosecuted and punished with appropriate severity."&lt;ref&gt;[http://criminaljustice.state.ny.us/legalservices/ch107_hate_crimes_2000.htm Hate Crimes Act - Ch 107, 2000&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Arguments in opposition to hate crime laws ==
{{Expand-section|date=May 2008}}

The U.S. Supreme Court unanimously found that hate crime statutes which criminalize bias-motivated speech or symbolic speech conflict with free speech rights because they isolated certain words based on their content or viewpoint .&lt;ref&gt;[[R. A. V. v. City of St. Paul]], 505 U.S. 377 (1992).&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have argued hate crime laws bring the law into disrepute and further divides society, as groups apply to have their critics silenced.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aei.org/publications/pubID.17122,filter.all/pub_detail.asp AEI - Short Publications&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Some have argued that if it is true that all violent crimes are the result of the perpetrator's contempt for the victim, then all crimes are hate crimes. Thus if there is no alternate rationale for prosecuting some people more harshly for the same crime based on who the victim is, then different defendants treated unequally under the law, which violates the [[United States Constitution]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/99hatecrime/constitutionality.asp Constitutional Challenges to Hate Crimes Statutes&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

[[Hate speech]]

[[Fighting Discrimination]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.fbi.gov/ucr/ucr.htm#hate ''Hate Crime Statistics''], annual [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]]/[[United States Department of Justice|U.S. Department of Justice]] report on the prevalence of hate crimes in the United States. Required by the [[Hate Crime Statistics Act]].
*[http://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/bja/162304.pdf A Policymaker's Guide to Hate Crimes], a publication by the [[National Criminal Justice Reference Service]], part of the [[United States Department of Justice|U.S. Department of Justice]]. Many parts of this article have been adapted from this document.
*[http://www.tolerance.org Tolerance.org], a web project sponsored by the [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] 
* Peabody, Michael "[http://www.libertymagazine.org/article/articleview/710/1/105/ Thought &amp; Crime]," Liberty Magazine, March/April 2008, review of recently proposed hate crime legislation and criminal intent issues. 
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TEumNAGVxhc], a video focusing on the [[hate crimes]] incited by KABC 790 AM [[shock jock]] [[Doug McIntyre]] against a Los Angeles charter school, [[Academia Semillas del Pueblo]], in 2006. 

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Hate crime| ]]
[[Category:Crimes]]
[[Category:Crime by type]]

[[cs:Trestné činy z nenávisti]]
[[da:Hate crime]]
[[de:Hate crime]]
[[es:Delito de odio]]
[[fr:Crime haineux]]
[[he:פשע שנאה]]
[[hu:Gyűlölet-bűncselekmény]]
[[ja:ヘイトクライム]]
[[pl:Zbrodnia nienawiści]]
[[ru:Преступление на почве ненависти]]
[[simple:Hate crime]]
[[fi:Viharikos]]
[[sv:Hatbrott]]
[[tr:Nefret suçu]]
[[zh-yue:仇恨罪行]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>