<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181022000311|865134723" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="30533724" pageid="30533724" ns="0" title="Bias against left-handed people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-18T01:10:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{more citations needed|date=November 2014}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Bias based on handedness''' is bias or design that is usually unfavorable against people who are [[Handedness|left-handed]]. Part of this is due to design in the world which is often right-hand biased. Handwriting is one of the biggest sources of actual disadvantage for left-handed people, other than for those forced to work with certain machinery. About ten percent of the world's population is left-handed,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|vauthors=Hardyck C, Petrinovich LF |title=Left-handedness |journal=Psychol Bull |volume=84 |issue=3 |pages=385–404 |year=1977 |pmid=859955|doi=10.1037/0033-2909.84.3.385}}&lt;/ref&gt; yet many common articles are designed for efficient use by right-handed people, and may be inconvenient, painful, or even dangerous for left-handed people to use.  These may include school desks, kitchen implements, and tools ranging from simple [[scissors]] to hazardous machinery such as [[Saw#Mechanically powered saws|power saws]].&lt;ref name="tools" /&gt;

Beyond being inherently disadvantaged by a right-handed bias in the design of tools, left-handed people have been subjected to deliberate discrimination and discouragement.  In certain societies, they may be considered unlucky or even malicious by the right-handed majority. Many languages still contain references to left-handedness to convey awkwardness, dishonesty, stupidity, or other undesirable qualities.  Even in relatively advanced societies, left-handed people were historically (and in some cases still are) forced as children to use their right hands for tasks which they would naturally perform with the left, such as eating or writing.&lt;ref name="Susumu" /&gt;

==Favorable perceptions==
[[File:Inca lloque yupanqui.jpg|thumb|right|120px|[[Lloque Yupanqui]], the third [[Sapa Inca]], whose name means "the glorified lefthander"]]
Among [[Inca civilization|Incas]] left-handers were called (and now are called among the indigenous peoples of the [[Andes]]) ''lloq'e'' ({{lang-qu|lluq'i}}) which has positive value. Peoples of the Andes consider left-handers to possess special spiritual abilities, including [[magic (paranormal)|magic]] and [[healing]].

The Third [[Sapa Inca]]—[[Lloque Yupanqui]]—was left-handed. His name, when translated from [[Quechua languages|Quechua]], means "the glorified lefthander."

In the Chinese language, the character for "left", {{lang|zh|{{linktext|左}}}},  depicts a left hand attending to its work. In contrast, the character for "right", {{lang|zh|{{linktext|右}}}} (''yòu''), depicts a right hand in relation to the mouth, suggesting the act of eating.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

In tantra [[Buddhism]], the left hand represents wisdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Beer|first=Robert|title=The Encyclopedia of Tibetan Symbols and Motifs|year=2004|isbn=1-93247-610-5|page=150}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early Roman times, the left side retained a positive connotation, as the [[Augures]] proceeded from the eastern side.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etimo.it/?term=sinistro|title=Sinistro|language=Italian}}&lt;/ref&gt; The negative meaning was subsequently borrowed into Latin from Greek, and ever since in all Roman languages.

In Russian, "levsha" (lefty, lefthander) became a common noun for skilled craftsman, after the title character from "[[The Tale of Cross-eyed Lefty from Tula and the Steel Flea]]" written in 1881 by [[Nikolai Leskov]].

==Unfavorable perceptions==
The unfavorable associations and connotations of the use of the left hand among cultures are varied. In some areas, in order to preserve cleanliness where sanitation was an issue, the right hand, as the dominant hand of most individuals, was used for eating, handling food, and social interactions. The left hand would then be used for personal hygiene, specifically after urination and defecation. These rules were imposed on all, no matter their dominant hand. Through these practices, the left hand became known as the "unclean" hand.&lt;ref name="Coren"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ROYoKoUn1jUC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA195|title=Left-handedness: behavioral implications and anomalies|first=Stanley|last=Coren|publisher=Elsevier Science Publishers B.V|year=1990|isbn=0-444-88438-6|location=Amsterdam}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, amongst Muslims and in some societies including [[Nepal]] and India it is still customary to use the left hand for cleaning oneself with water after defecating. The right hand is commonly known in contradistinction from the left, as the hand used for eating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Muhammad Saed Abdul-Rahman|year=2007|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZfMjhRAkn_kC|title=Islam: Questions and Answers – Manners (Part 1)|publisher=MSA Publication Ltd|location=London|oclc=58477120|isbn=1-86179-336-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the film [[Lawrence of Arabia (film)|''Lawrence of Arabia'']] there is no insult taken when the guide offers his food to Lawrence and he takes it to his mouth with his left hand.&lt;ref&gt;The scene on the first day of travel to Feisal's camp.&lt;/ref&gt;

In many religions, including Christianity, the [[right hand of God]] is the favored hand. For example, Jesus sits at God's right side. God's left hand, however, is the hand of [[Divine judgment|judgement]]. The [[Archangel Gabriel]] is sometimes called "God's left hand", sits at God's left side, and is one of six [[Destroying angel (Bible)|angels of death]]. Those who fall from favor with God are sent to left, as described in Matthew 25: 32–33, in which sheep represent the righteous and goats represent the fallen: "And he shall separate them one from another, as a shepherd divideth his sheep from the goats. And he shall set the sheep on his right, but the goats on his left." In 19th-century Europe, homosexuals were referred to as "left-handed".&lt;ref name="Evans"&gt;{{cite book|last=Evans|first=Dave|year=2007|title=The History of British Magick after Crowley|publisher=Hidden Publishing}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Protestant-majority parts of the United Kingdom, Catholics were called "left-footers", and vice versa in Catholic-majority parts of Ireland and [[Irish American|Irish America]].&lt;ref name="Dolan2004"&gt;{{cite book|last=Dolan|first=T. P.|title=A Dictionary of Hiberno-English: The Irish Use of English|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uPo0oB19gDUC&amp;pg=PA139|accessdate=7 December 2016|year=2004|publisher=Gill &amp; Macmillan Ltd|isbn=9780717135356|page=139|chapter=left-footer}}; {{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/notesandqueries/query/0,5753,-5016,00.html|title=Notes and Queries: Where does the phrase 'left footer' come from?|work=[[The Guardian]]|accessdate=7 December 2016}}; {{cite book|last=Mencken|first=Henry Louis|title=The American language |year=1962|publisher=A. A.Knopf|page=745}}; {{cite book|last=Partridge|first=Eric|title=A Dictionary of Slang and Unconventional English|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IAjyQdFwh4UC&amp;pg=PA674|accessdate=7 December 2016|date=2006-05-02|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9781134963652|page=674|chapter=left-footer}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Black magic]] is sometimes referred to as the "[[left-hand path]]", which is strongly associated with [[Satanism]].{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}

Various innocuous activities and experiences become rude or even signs of bad luck when the left hand becomes involved. In some parts of [[Scotland]], it is considered bad luck to meet a left-handed person at the start of a journey.&lt;ref name="Wilson"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LEkLAQAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover|title=The right hand: left-handedness|first=Sir Daniel|last=Wilson|publisher=MacMillan and Co|year=1891|location=London|isbn=0-665-25982-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Ghana]], pointing, gesturing, giving or receiving items with the left hand is considered taboo or rude. A person giving directions will put their left hand behind them and even physically strain to point with their right hand if necessary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1075/gest.1.1.06kit|url=http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/jbp/gest/2001/00000001/00000001/art00005|title=Pointing left in Ghana: How a taboo on the use of the left hand influences gestural practice|journal=Gesture|volume=1|issue=1|author1=Kita, S. |author2=Essegbey, J. |pages=73–95|year=2001|publisher=John Benjamins Publishing Company}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some Asian countries, holding eating utensils in the left hand is considered impolite.&lt;ref name="Binns" /&gt;
{{further|Etiquette in Asia}}

===Forced use of the right hand===
Due to cultural and social pressures, many left-handed children were encouraged or forced to write and perform other activities with their right hands. This conversion can cause multiple problems in the developing left-handed child, including [[learning disorders]], [[dyslexia]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Orton|first=S.T|year=1937|title=Reading, writing, and speech problems in children|location=London|publisher=Chapman and Hall|isbn=0-89079-179-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[stuttering]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmc=1591462|title=THE PSYCHOLOGICAL APPROACH TO THE PRESCHOOL STUTTERER|first=Ruth|last=Lewis|publisher=Canad. M.A.J|date=May 1949|pmid=18125462|volume=60|issue=5|journal=Can Med Assoc J|pages=497–500}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://jhered.oxfordjournals.org/content/24/10/387.full.pdf|title=LEFT-HANDEDNESS AND STUTTERING|first1=Bryng|last1=Bryngelson|first2=Thomas B.|last2=Clark|journal=The Journal of Heredity|publisher=American Genetic Association|year=1933|volume=24|issue=10|pages=387–390|accessdate=January 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Johnson, W.  |author2=L. Duke |lastauthoramp=yes |year=1935|title=Changes in handedness associated with onset or disappearance of stuttering; sixteen cases|journal=Journal of Experimental Education|volume=4|pages=112–132}}&lt;/ref&gt; and other [[speech disorders]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ballard|first=PB|year=1912|title=Sinistrality and speech|journal=Journal of Experimental Pediatrics|volume=1|pages=298–310}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shifts from left- to right-handed are more likely to be successful than right to left, though neither have a high success rate to begin with. Successful shifters are more likely to become ambihanded than unsuccessful ones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Porac |first1=C |last2=Buller |first2=T |title=Overt attempts to change hand preference: a study of group and individual characteristics. |journal=Canadian Journal of Psychology |volume=44 |issue=4 |pages=512–21 |year=1990 |pmid=2292088 |doi=10.1037/h0084268}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conversions can be successful with consistent daily practice in a variety of manual activities, but though activity in the non-dominant left-hemisphere of the brain will increase during tasks, so too will activity in the dominant right-hemisphere. Consistent left-handers have no higher activity in these task centers than converted left-handers, so it may be inferred that "attempts to switch handedness by educational training far from weakening the functional expression of lefthandedness in higher-order motor areas of the (dominant) right hemisphere in fact enhance it."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kloppel |first1=S. |last2=Vongerichten |first2=A. |last3=Eimeren |first3=T. v. |last4=Frackowiak |first4=R. S. J. |last5=Siebner |first5=H. R. |title=Can Left-Handedness be Switched? Insights from an Early Switch of Handwriting |journal=Journal of Neuroscience |volume=27 |issue=29 |pages=7847–53 |year=2007 |pmid=17634378 |doi=10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1299-07.2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Asian countries encourage or force their children to become right-handed due to cultural perceptions of bad luck associated with the left hand. In India and Indonesia, it is considered rude to eat with the left hand.&lt;ref name="Binns" /&gt; In a 2007 study in [[Taiwan]], about 59.3% of children studied had been forced to convert from left-handedness to right-handedness. The study took into account economic status of the children's families and found that children whose parents had less education were more likely to be forced to convert. Even among children whose parents had higher levels of education, the conversion rate was 45.7%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Meng |first1=LF |title=The rate of handedness conversion and related factors in left-handed children. |journal=Laterality |volume=12 |issue=2 |pages=131–8 |year=2007 |pmid=17365629 |doi=10.1080/13576500601005727}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among naturally left-handed Japanese senior high school students, only 0.7% and 1.7% of individuals used their left hand for writing and eating, respectively,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Shimizu A, Endo M|lastauthoramp=yes |year=1983|title=Handedness and familial sinistrality in a Japanese student population|journal=Cortex|volume=19|issue=2|pages=265–272|pmid=6884043|doi=10.1016/s0010-9452(83)80020-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; though young Japanese are more likely to convert to using chopsticks right-handed than forks or spoons (29.3% to 4.6%). The proportion of females subjected to forced conversion is significantly higher compared to males (95.1% to 81.0%).&lt;ref name="Susumu"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Sato |first1=Susumu |last2=Demura |first2=Shinichi |last3=Sugano |first3=Noriaki |last4=Mikami |first4=Hajime |last5=Ohuchi |first5=Tetsuhiko |title=Characteristics of Handedness in Japanese Adults: Influence of Left-handed Relatives and Forced Conversion |journal=International Journal of Sport and Health Science |volume=6 |pages=113–9 |year=2008 |doi=10.5432/ijshs.IJSHS20070298}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Western countries{{which|date=December 2014}} have also attempted to convert left-handed children due to cultural, social and religious biases. Schools{{where?|date=December 2014}} tend to urge children to use their right hands, sometimes against the wishes of the child's parents. In America{{when|date=December 2014}} some students have been [[school corporal punishment|physically punished]] for writing with their left hands (though nowadays left-handedness is more widely accepted):&lt;ref name="Binns"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.livescience.com/health/060321_left_hand.html|title=What Makes a Lefty: Myths and Mysteries Persist|first=Corey|last=Binns|publisher=Live Science|date=March 21, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; "I was educated in the USA in Catholic school in the 60s. My left hand was beaten until it was swollen, so I would use my right right [sic] hand" ... "I had a teacher who would smack my left hand with a yardstick every time she caught me writing with my left hand" ... "My fourth grade teacher [...] would force me to use my right hand to perform all of my school work. If she caught me using my left hand, I was hit in the head with a dictionary. It turned out that she believed left handers were connected with Satan."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indiana.edu/~primate/lspeak2.html#educators|title=Educators|publisher=gauche! Left-Handers in Society|accessdate=January 5, 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101212091224/http://www.indiana.edu/~primate/lspeak2.html| archivedate= December 12, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Malawi]]ans cite their views that "the left hand is less skilled and less powerful than the right one" as main reasons for forcing left-handers to convert. Among students, teachers and parents, 75% said the left hand should not be used to perform habitual activities, and 87.6% of these believed left-handers should be forced to switch dominant hands. Parents and close relatives are most responsible for impressing these beliefs upon their children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Zverev |first1=YP |title=Cultural and environmental pressure against left-hand preference in urban and semi-urban Malawi. |journal=Brain and cognition |volume=60 |issue=3 |pages=295–303 |year=2006 |pmid=16481084 |doi=10.1016/j.bandc.2005.07.008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rise in acceptance of left-handedness===

On March 8, 1971, ''The Florence Times—Tri-Cities Daily'' reported that left-handed people "are becoming increasingly accepted and enabled to find their right (or left) place in the world."&lt;ref name=Dawns&gt;{{cite newspaper |title=New Day Dawns For Southpaws |work=[[TimesDaily|The Florence Times—Tri-Cities Daily]] |date=March 8, 1971 |accessdate=June 22, 2018 |page=4 |url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1842&amp;dat=19710308&amp;id=-gAsAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=3McEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=739,1203077}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Florence Times—Tri-Cities Daily'' also wrote "we still have a long way to go before the last vestiges of discrimination against left-handedness are uprooted, however."&lt;ref name=Dawns /&gt; The frequency of left-handed writing in the United States, which was only 2.1 percent in 1932, had risen to over 11 percent by 1972.&lt;ref name=Restak /&gt; According to an article by ''[[The Washington Post]]'' from August 13, 1979, a psychologist from University of Chicago named Jerre Levy said: "In 1939, 2 percent of the population wrote with the left hand. By 1946, it was up to 7 1/2 percent. In 1968, 9 percent. By 1972, 12 percent. It's leveling off, and I expect the real number of left-handers will turn out to be about 14 percent."&lt;ref name=OtherHand&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/lifestyle/1979/08/13/on-the-other-hand-consider-whos-left/6c2c854c-42eb-44fa-b4c8-f2a04a740049/ |title=On the Other Hand, Consider Who's Left |work=[[The Washington Post]] |last=Tracy |first=Lisa |date=August 13, 1979 |accessdate=June 22, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the article by ''The Washington Post'' from August 13, 1979, "a University of Michigan study points out that left-handers may not be taking over the world but...7 percent of the men and 6 percent of the women over 40 who were interviewed were lefties, but the percentages jumped to well above 10 percent in the 18-to-39 age group."&lt;ref name=OtherHand /&gt; According to the article by ''The Washington Post'' from August 13, 1979, Dr. Bernard McKenna of the National Education Association said: "There was recognition by medical authorities that left-handedness was normal and that tying the hand up in a child often caused stuttering."&lt;ref name=OtherHand /&gt; In Japan, Tokyo psychiatrist Soicki Hakozaki coped with such deep-seated discrimination against left-handed people that he wrote ''The World of Left-Handers''. Hakozaki reported finding situations in which women were afraid their husbands would divorce them for being left-handed.&lt;ref name=OtherHand /&gt; According to the article by ''The Washington Post'' from August 13, 1979, an official at the Japanese Embassy said: "Before the war, there was discrimination against left-handers," said the official at the Japanese Embassy. "Children were not trained to use their left hand while eating or writing. I used to throw a baseball left-handed, but my grandparents wanted me to throw right-handed. I can throw either way. Today, in some local areas, discrimination may still remain, but on the whole, it seems to be over. There are many left-handers in Japan."&lt;ref name=OtherHand /&gt; In an article by ''The Washington Post'' from December 11, 1988, Richard M. Restak wrote that left-handedness became more accepted and people decided to leave southpaws alone and decided to quit working against left-handedness.&lt;ref name=Restak&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/opinions/1988/12/11/do-we-want-a-left-handed-president/1a6c49dc-0e40-4ea3-ab4b-e3956dc04208/ |title=Do We Want a Left-Handed President? |work=[[The Washington Post]] |last=Restak |first=Richard M. |date=December 11, 1988 |accessdate=June 22, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an article by ''[[The Gadsden Times]]'' from October 3, 1993, the newspaper mentioned a 5-year-old named Daniel, writing: "the advantage that little Daniel does have of going to school in the '90s is that he will be allowed to be left-hander. That wasn't always the case in years past."&lt;ref name=Gadsden&gt;{{cite newspaper |title=Southpaws tough it out in a right-handed world |work=[[The Gadsden Times]] |last=Pritchett |first=Leigh Bailey |date=October 3, 1993 |accessdate=June 22, 2018 |pages=D8}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1998 survey, 24 percent of younger-generation left-handed people reported some attempts to switch their handedness.&lt;ref name=Roth&gt;{{cite book |title=The Left Stuff: How the Left-Handed Have Survived and Thrived in a Right-Handed World |publisher=Government Institutes |last=Roth |first=Melissa |date=July 25, 2005 |isbn=9781590771518 |page=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Equipment==
[[File:2scissors-clean.jpg|thumb|Left-handed (left) and right-handed scissors]]
[[File:Japanese knife blade types.png|thumb|Kitchen knives: (1) symmetrical, (2) right-handed, (3) left-handed. Cross sections seen from the handle.]]
Because the vast majority of the world population is right-handed, most everyday items are mass-produced for ease of use with the right hand. Tools, game equipment, musical instruments and other items must be specially ordered for left-handed use, if they are even produced and are usually more expensive than their right-handed counterparts.

===Household items===
Right-handed tools can be difficult, uncomfortable, or dangerous for left-handed people to use.

====Scissors====
For example [[Scissors#'Handed' scissors|(right-handed) scissors]] are arranged so that, in the right hand, fingers and thumb push the blades together laterally, creating the shearing action essential to scissors' utility. In the left hand, however, fingers and thumb tend to force right-handed blades apart, so that, rather than being sheared, the work-material is merely hacked, as by a knife, or slips between the blades uncut.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xqbrm_left-handed-scissors-and-cutting_school|title=Lefthanded scissors explained|publisher=dailymotion.com (video)}}&lt;/ref&gt; Left-handers using right-handed scissors will often try to compensate by forcing the handles apart laterally, causing discomfort or injury to the first knuckle of the thumb.&lt;ref name=howscissors&gt;{{cite web|title=How Scissors are Left-Handed|url=http://www.anythinglefthanded.co.uk/acatalog/scissors-how-left-handed.html|archive-url=https://archive.is/20131030185511/http://www.anythinglefthanded.co.uk/acatalog/scissors-how-left-handed.html|dead-url=yes|archive-date=30 October 2013|work=Anything Left-Handed|publisher=Anything Left-Handed Ltd.|accessdate=30 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, a right-handed person using right-handed scissors can easily see the cutting line, but for a left-handed user the upper blade obscures the view.&lt;ref name=Lefthandersday&gt;{{cite web|title=Left-Handed Products|url=http://www.lefthandersday.com/tour10.html|publisher=Lefthandersday.com|accessdate=30 October 2013|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131031013722/http://www.lefthandersday.com/tour10.html|archivedate=October 31, 2013|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many scissors are offered as "ambidextrous" or "suitable for right- or left-handed use."  Typically, these are merely right-handed scissors with modified handles to permit use in the left hand with less discomfort, but because the blades are still arranged for right-handed use, they will not perform well in the left hand.&lt;ref name=Lefthandersday /&gt;

====Computer input devices====
Input devices for computers can present obstacles to left-handed operation if intended for right-handed use. Some computer set-ups have the [[Mouse (computing)|mouse]] placed on the right side of the keyboard and unable to be repositioned to the left. The mouse itself is also sometimes shaped to fit the right hand better. The functions of mouse buttons, even on mice shaped to fit both hands, default to right-hand use. On two-button mice, the left button —under the index finger of a right-handed person— is the primary button, while the right button performs secondary functions. The on-screen pointers themselves are also configured for right-handed people. Most desktop operating systems allow a user to reverse the functionality of mouse buttons to accommodate left-handed use, but left-handed cursors sometimes need to be specially downloaded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.howtogeek.com/howto/15833/make-your-mouse-pointers-left-hand-friendly/|title=Make Your Mouse Pointers Left-hand Friendly|publisher=How-To Geek|date=April 30, 2010|accessdate=January 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Trackball]]s and [[trackpad]]s are often shaped for right-handed use. Even with the ability to change the functionality of buttons, these devices may be difficult for left-handed use. For a left handed person there are computer mice designed for left handed use, but they are a much smaller segment of the marketplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ergonomicallyspeaking.net/best-left-handed-mouse/|title=Best Left Handed Mouse Rankings|publisher=Ergonomically Speaking}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Video game controllers often have the action buttons on the right with the directional controls on the left. In first-person shooters, many games default to the right pointer-finger being used to fire, simulating a right-handed person pulling the trigger of the weapon. Certain systems' layouts, such as Nintendo's Wii U and 3DS, have games in which right-handed stylus use is assumed and can cause difficulty for left-handed players.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://kotaku.com/shigeru-miyamoto-hears-this-left-handed-gamers-pain-1592285438/ | title=Shigeru Miyamoto Hears this Left-Handed Gamer's Pain |publisher=Kotaku}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Trackman marble wheel.JPG|thumb|A right-handed trackball is difficult to use with the left hand.]]

====Knives====
While European-style [[kitchen knife|kitchen knives]] are usually symmetrical, [[Japanese kitchen knives]] have the cutting edge ground asymmetrically, having the cutting edge closer to the user's body{{citation needed|date=February 2012}} with ratios{{clarify|reason=The ratio between what?|date=February 2012}} ranging from 70–30 for the average chef's knife, to 90–10 for professional [[sushi]] chef knives; left-handed models are rare, and usually must be specially ordered or custom made.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/23/business/23pursuits.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin|title=How to Succeed at Knife-Sharpening Without Losing a Thumb|work=New York Times|date=September 23, 2006|accessdate=September 23, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On the other hand, the majority of "flat ground" general-purpose knives typically have the cutting edge on the right, as with a left-handed knife, for aesthetic reasons rather than practical.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

====Cameras====
One of the few cameras ever produced for left-handers was the half-frame [[Yashica]] Samurai. Cameras predominantly have the hand grip, shutter release, film wind lever and commonly used selection buttons, switches and dials controlled by the right hand. Lens controls (where present) tend to be accessible by either hand. When an unskilled left-handed person uses a right-handed camera the hand control can be less steady and hence produce camera shake leading to poorer pictures at low shutter speeds.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

===Musical instruments===
Left-handed adaptations have even bridged the world of music. Left-handed [[string instrument]]s are produced, including [[guitar]]s and [[violin]]s. Inverted [[trumpet]]s are made, too. Although the trumpet's valves are normally designed to be operated with the right hand, the prevailing belief is that left-handed trumpeters are not at a significant disadvantage. The [[French horn]], for example, is played with the left hand, yet most horn players are right-handed. Left handed [[drum]]mers also set up drum kits the exact opposite to conventional right-handed setup (i.e. [[Hi-hat (instrument)|hi-hat]] on the right, bass pedal under left foot, [[ride cymbal]] to the drummer's left, etc.).

===Sports===
A left-handed individual may be known as a southpaw, particularly in a sports context. It is widely accepted that the term originated in the United States, in the game of [[baseball]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fightbeat.com/article_detail.php?AT=57|title=Southpaws: Doing It Right the Wrong Way|publisher=fightbeat.com|accessdate=August 2006|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070324215110/http://www.fightbeat.com/article_detail.php?AT=57|archivedate=March 24, 2007|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ballpark]]s are often designed so that batters are facing east, so that the afternoon or evening sun does not shine in their eyes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/downloads/y2008/official_rules/01_objectives_of_the_game.pdf|title=Rules of Major League Baseball, Section 1.04|publisher=MLB.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; This means that left-handed [[pitchers]] are throwing with their south-side arm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Olmert|first=Michael|year=1996|title=Milton's Teeth and Ovid's Umbrella: Curiouser &amp; Curiouser Adventures in History|page=108|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster|location=New York|isbn=0-684-80164-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' lists a non-baseball citation for "south paw", meaning a punch with the left hand, as early as 1848,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Morris|first=Evan|year=1995|url=http://www.word-detective.com/093098.html|title=Word detective research|accessdate=June 2006| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20060628213442/http://www.word-detective.com/093098.html| archivedate= June 28, 2006 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; just three years after the first organized baseball game, with the note "(orig. U.S., in Baseball)."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Definition for "southpaw"|publisher=Oxford English Dictionary Online}}&lt;/ref&gt; A left-handed advantage in sports can be significant and even decisive, but this advantage usually results from a left-handed competitor's unshared familiarity with opposite-handed opponents. Baseball is an exception since batters, pitchers, and fielders in certain scenarios are physically advantaged or disadvantaged by their handedness.

In baseball, due to the direction in which [[curveball]]s and [[slider]]s break, it is generally accepted that the pitcher has an advantage when his handedness is the same as the batter's, and the batter has an advantage when they are opposite. For this reason, many baseball teams include a [[left-handed specialist]] pitcher, who is brought into the game specifically to pitch to dangerous left-handed batters in crucial situations. A left-handed first baseman uses a more fluid motion to tag out a baserunner returning to first base during a pickoff attempt by the pitcher and has less difficulty avoiding baserunners while presenting their mitt as a target for other fielders to throw to. It is very uncommon to see a left-handed player playing any infield position other than pitcher or first basemen due to the counterclockwise flow of the game when throwing the ball around the bases. A fielder's handedness is either a physical advantage or hindrance for similar reasons throughout the infield positions, and left-handedness is not always the more desirable dexterousness.

Left-handed [[Bowler (ten-pin)|bowlers]] are usually at an advantage during [[ten-pin bowling]] competition when hooking the ball into the pins from the left side of the lane. As there are fewer left-handed players, the lane's left side is not used as much, and thus the applied oil pattern does not change as quickly as it does for right-handed bowlers.

In [[boxing]], someone who boxes left-handed is frequently referred to as southpaw. The term is also used to refer to a stance in which the boxer places the right foot in front of the left, so it is possible for a right-handed boxer to box with a [[southpaw stance]]. Most boxers, southpaw or otherwise, tend to train with sparring partners who adopt an orthodox stance which gives southpaws an advantage. [[Manny Pacquiao]] is an example of a southpaw (although he writes with his right hand). In the popular boxing film series ''[[Rocky]]'', the main character [[Rocky Balboa]] is a southpaw. Southpaw is also a term in professional wrestling, often giving them the advantage.

Fencing weapons feature left- and right-handed grips, and a left-handed fencer's stance is opposite that of a right-handed opponent. Although commonly asserted that left-handed fencers have an advantage over right-handed opponents because the line of defence favors their sword arm, this assertion describes both fencers in a mixed-handed duel, so neither competitor has a unique physical advantage. Thus the left-hander's advantage in fencing stems mostly from a right-hander's unfamiliarity with a left-handed stance.

The game of golf is most commonly played right-handed, and left-handed players typically must provide their own special [[golf club (equipment)|golf club]]s.&lt;ref name="Wilson" /&gt; The game can be played with both hands, provided the player has both left- and right-handed clubs, giving an advantage over one-handed players. Professional golfer [[Phil Mickelson]] plays left-handed though he is naturally right-handed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pgatour.com/players/r/?/00/18/10/media|title=Personal section of PGA Tour official media guide|publisher=PGA Tour|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110629092928/http://www.pgatour.com/players/r/?%2F00%2F18%2F10%2Fmedia|archivedate=June 29, 2011|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In tennis, southpaws hold the racket in their left hand. Because of this, their grip of the handle is supposedly adjusted in a slightly different style from right-handed players. Some world champion left-handed tennis players include [[Jimmy Connors]], [[Guillermo Vilas]], [[John McEnroe]], [[Martina Navratilova]], [[Marcelo Ríos]], [[Goran Ivanišević]]  and [[Rafael Nadal]].

Often the [[Playing card|playing cards]] have their [[Pip (counting)|pips]] printed only in the upper left corner assuming holding them with right hand. Such design may be uncomfortable for left-handed people who may prefer all four corners of the card to be used.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.leftyslefthanded.com/Lefty_s_Left_Handed_Playing_Cards_p/607414.htm|title=Lefty's "Always right" double deck of playing cards|last=|first=|date=|website=|archive-url=|archive-date=|dead-url=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/craigertiger/sinister-deck-the-left-handed-card-deck-with-famou|title=Sinister Deck: The Left-Handed Card Deck With Famous Lefties|last=|first=|date=|website=|archive-url=|archive-date=|dead-url=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Weapons===
[[File:US Navy 071019-N-6552M-190 SEAL trainees scan the room for possible threats as part of a SEAL qualification training exercise.jpg|thumb|right|A [[United States Navy SEALs|US Navy SEALs]] left-handed shooter]]
The vast majority of [[firearm]]s are designed for right-handed shooters, with the operating handle, magazine release, or safety mechanisms set up for manipulation by the right hand, and fired cartridge cases ejected to the right. Also, scopes and sights may be mounted in such a way as to require the shooter to place the rifle against the right shoulder. A left-handed shooter must either purchase a left-handed or ambidextrous firearm (which are manufactured in smaller numbers and are generally more expensive and/or harder to obtain), shoot a right-handed gun left-handed (which presents certain difficulties, such as the controls being improperly located for the left hand or hot shell cases being ejected towards the shooter's body, especially the eyes or down the collar or right sleeve), or learn to shoot right-handed (which may be less comfortable or "natural"). A related issue is [[ocular dominance]], due to which left-handed people may wish to shoot right-handed, and vice versa. Ocular dominance plays more of a rule in shooting accuracy than does left versus right handiness. Therefore, ocular dominance will cause a preference on how a shooter chooses to hold a gun.

Some modern firearms are ambidextrous (e.g. the [[FN P90]] and [[Heckler &amp; Koch P7]]), or can be converted between right- and left-handed operation (e.g. the [[Heckler &amp; Koch G36]] and [[Steyr AUG]]). [[Bullpup]] rifles are particularly problematic for left-handers unless they can be reconfigured, since empty shells would be ejected straight into the shooter's face and cheek potentially causing injury, or otherwise designed from the ground up for ambidextrous use, often by way of complex ejection systems as seen on the [[FN F2000]] and the [[Kel-Tec RFB]]. The British [[SA80|L85 Assault Rifle]] must be fired right-handed, placing left-handed soldiers at a disadvantage. In contrast, the [[Steyr AUG]] is of a modular design and the ejection port and extractor can be switched/replaced to suit the handedness of the soldier operating it. The [[M16 rifle|M-16]] and its variants have a fixed ejection port, but being a conventional (i.e. not bullpup) design the ejection port is forward of the operator and hence able to be fired either-handed. Circa 1985, with the introduction of the M16A2 version, a case deflector was incorporated adjacent to the ejector port to direct discarded shells in a more forward direction, making the rifle even more left hand operator friendly. The deflector is not always effective, however, as the ejected shell still stands a chance of hitting the left-handed shooter's cheek, especially in windy conditions.

[[Lever action]] and [[pump action]] firearms present fewer difficulties for left-handers than [[bolt action]] weapons do. Many weapons with adjustable sights allow for left-handed use, but for a right eye dominant shooter it is necessary to adjust. In fact, most weapons adjust well enough that a weapon will not eject shells into a left-hander's eye.

===Machinery===
[[Power tools]], machinery and other potentially dangerous equipment is typically manufactured with the right-handed user in mind. Common problems faced by left-handed operators include the inability to keep materials steady, and difficulty reaching the on/off switch, especially in emergency situations.&lt;ref name="tools"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greathomeimprovements.com/Mar07_niche_theme/power-tools/finding-power-tools-for-left-handed-people.php|title=Finding Power Tools for Left Handed People|publisher=Great Home Improvements|accessdate=January 14, 2011|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110711123652/http://www.greathomeimprovements.com/Mar07_niche_theme/power-tools/finding-power-tools-for-left-handed-people.php|archivedate=July 11, 2011|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Table saw]]s, whose blades protrude from the top of a table and pose the risk of losing fingers or hands, have their cutting area on the right side. This makes it difficult for a left-handed operator to guide the material being cut, as it must be pushed to the right side to align with the fence to avoid kickback. On [[bandsaw]]s, the blade teeth are on the left side of the blade, necessitating the material being cut to be pushed from the left side of the machine. However, at this angle, the casing of the machine containing the rest of the blade is on the operator's left side, making it extremely difficult to guide the wood with their left hand.

Handheld [[circular saw]]s are made almost exclusively for right-handers, with the motor and grip on the right side. If held in the left hand, it is impossible for the operator to see what they are cutting. Tool manufacturer [[Porter-Cable]] produces a left-handed circular saw that can be purchased relatively inexpensively.&lt;ref name="tools" /&gt;

{{Gallery
 |height=150|width=150|lines=4
|File:Rem700 action lefthand standard right.jpg|Left-handed [[Remington 700]] rifle action—note that the bolt handle is not visible from this side
|File:Sega circolare.jpg|A [[table saw]]. Notice how the cutting surface, fence, etc. are on the right side
}}

==Language==
Historically, the left side, and subsequently left-handedness, was considered negative. The word "left" itself derives from the [[Anglo-Saxon]] word ''lyft'', "weak".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emedia.leeward.hawaii.edu/hurley/Ling102web/mod5_Llearning/mod5docs/handedness.pdf|archive-url=http://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20111025105045/http://emedia.leeward.hawaii.edu/hurley/ling102web/mod5_Llearning/mod5docs/handedness.pdf|dead-url=yes|archive-date=2011-10-25|title=Encyclopedia of Childhood and Adolescence|first=Zoran|last=Minderovic|publisher=Gale Research|year=1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Ancient Greek]] both words meaning "left" were [[euphemism]]s: the word [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Da%29ristero%2Fs ἀριστερός], ''aristerós'' (the standard word in [[Modern Greek]] as well) is derived from ἂριστος, ''áristos'', "best", and the word [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/morph?l=eu%29w%2Fnumos&amp;la=greek&amp;can=eu%29w%2Fnumos0&amp;prior=a%29/ristos&amp;d=Perseus:text:1999.04.0057:entry=a%29ristero/s&amp;i=1#lexicon εὺώνυμος], ''euōnymos'', "of good name", is another [[euphemism]] used in lieu of "ill-named".  The [[Latin language|Latin]] adjective ''sinister/sinistra/sinistrum'' originally meant "left" but took on meanings of "evil" or "unlucky" by the [[Classical Latin]] era, and this double meaning survives in [[Romance languages|European derivatives of Latin]], and in the English word "sinister". Alternatively, ''sinister'' comes from the Latin word ''sinus'' meaning "pocket": a traditional Roman [[toga]] had only one pocket, located on the left side. The right hand has historically been associated with skill: the Latin word for right-handed is ''dexter'', as in "dexterity", meaning manual skill. Even the word "[[ambidexterity]]" reflects the [[bias]]. Its intended meaning is "skillful on both sides". However, since it keeps the Latin root ''dexter'', which means "right", it ends up conveying the idea of being "right-handed on both sides". This bias is also apparent in the lesser-known [[antonym]] "ambisinistrous", which means "left-handed [''i.e.'', clumsy] on both sides".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yourdictionary.com/wotd/wotd.pl?word=ambisinistrous|title=Ambisinistrous|publisher=YourDictionary.com|accessdate=November 28, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; In more technical contexts, "sinistral" may be used in place of "left-handed" and "sinistrality" in place of "left-handedness".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yourdictionary.com/wotd/wotd.pl?word=sinistral|title=Sinistral|publisher=YourDictionary.com|accessdate=June 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In both [[Ancient Greek religion|Ancient Greek]] and [[Religion in ancient Rome|Roman religion]], [[auspice]]s (usually the flight paths of birds, as observed by a bird-diviner, or ''[[augur]]'') were thought to be unfavorable if appearing on the diviner's left-hand side and favorable if on the right: an ancient custom mentioned in [[Homer]]'s [[Iliad]] and of apparently Middle Eastern origin (as attested in the [[Amarna correspondence]], in which a king of [[Alashiya]], i.e. [[Cyprus]], requests an eagle-diviner from the [[Pharaoh]] of Egypt).

Meanings gradually developed from use of these terms in the ancient languages. In many modern European languages, including English, the word for the direction "right" also means "correct" or "proper", and also stands for authority and justice.

In Sanskrit, the word "वाम" (waama)
stands for both "left" and "wicked."
 
In most [[Slavic language]]s the root ''prav'' (right) is used in words carrying meanings of correctness or justice. In colloquial Russian the word ''левый (levyĭ)'' "left" means unofficial, counterfeit, strange. In Polish, the word ''prawo'' means "right" as well as "law", ''prawy'' means: lawful; the word ''lewy'' means "left" (opposite of right), and colloquially "illegal" (opposite of legal).

In French, ''droit(e)'' ([[cognate]] to English ''direct'') means both "right" and "straight", as well as "law" and the legal sense of "right", while ''gauche'' means "left" and is also a synonym of ''maladroit'', literally "not right", meaning "clumsy". Spanish, Italian, Portuguese and German have similar constructs. The Spanish term ''diestro'' and the Italian term ''destro'' mean both "right-handed" and "skillful". The contemporary Italian word ''sinistra'' has both meanings of sinister and left (the masculine adjective for sinister being ''sinistro''), and ''maldestro'' means "clumsy". The Spanish ''siniestra'' has both, too, although the "left" meaning is less common and is usually expressed by ''izquierda'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://etimologias.dechile.net/?izquierda|title=Etimología de izquierda|publisher=deChile.com|accessdate=June 2006|language=Spanish| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20060619201838/http://etimologias.dechile.net/?izquierda| archivedate= June 19, 2006 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; a Basque word that made its way into Portuguese as well. In some Spanish-speaking countries, to do something ''por izquierda'' means to engage in corrupt conduct or employ illegitimate means, whereas ''por derecha'' or ''a derechas'' means to do it the right (legitimate) way.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://forum.wordreference.com/showthread.php?t=1295427|title=Word Reference}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, in Spanish, to tell someone "Eres tan zurdo" means that they are being clumsy, though the literal meaning is "You're so lefty." In Portuguese, the most common word for left-handed person, ''canhoto'', was once used to identify [[the devil]], and ''canhestro'', a related word, means "clumsy".

In Romanian ''drept/dreaptă'' (coming from Latin ''directus'') means both "right" and "straight". The word for "left" is ''stâng/stângă'' coming from Latin ''stancus'' (= ''stanticus'') meaning "tired".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://dexonline.ro/definitie/stanga|title=stanga - definiție - dexonline}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In German, ''recht'' means "right" in both the adjectival sense (correct) and the nominal (legal entitlement). The word for "left" is ''links'', and is closely related to both ''link'' (underhand, questionable), and ''linkisch'' (clumsy).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|authorlink1=link|editor1-last=Clark|editor1-first=M.|title=Oxford German Dictionary|date=2008|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|isbn=978-0-19-954568-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Die Deutsche Sprache'', "link" (Berlin: Duden 2013).&lt;/ref&gt;

The Dutch words for "left" (''links, linker'') and "right" (''recht, rechts, rechter'') have much the same meanings and connotations as in English.  The adjective ''link'' means "cunning, shifty" or "risky". A ''linkerd'' is a "crafty devil".  To look at someone over the left shoulder (''iemand over de linkerschouder aanzien'') is to regard him or her as insignificant.&lt;ref&gt;W. Martin and G. A. J. Tops, eds., ''Van Dale groot woordenboek Nederlands-Engels'', 2d ed. (Utrecht, Antwerp: Van Dale, 1991).&lt;/ref&gt;

In Irish, ''deas'' means "right side" and "nice". ''Ciotóg'' is the left hand and is related to ''ciotach'' meaning "awkward";&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archives.tcm.ie/thekingdom/2003/07/24/story10018.asp|title=My Left Foot|publisher=The Kingdom|date=July 24, 2003|accessdate=June 2006|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070523133146/http://archives.tcm.ie/thekingdom/2003/07/24/story10018.asp|archivedate=May 23, 2007|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''ciotógach'' (kyut-OH-goch) is the term for left-handed. In Welsh, the word ''chwith'' means "left", but can also mean "strange", "awkward", or "wrong". The Scots term for left-handedness is ''corrie fistit''. The term can be used to convey clumsiness.

In Finnish, the word ''oikea'' means both "right" (okay, correct) and "right" (the opposite of left).

In Swedish, ''att göra något med vänsterhanden'' (literally "to do something with your left hand") means "to do something badly". In Swedish, ''vänster'' means "left". The term ''vänsterprassel'' means "infidelity", "adultery" and "cheating". From this term the verb ''vänstra'' is derived.

In Hungarian, the word for right is ''jobb'', which also means "better". The word for left is ''bal'', which also means "bad". In Estonian, the word ''pahem'' stands for both "left" and "worse" and the word ''parem'' stands for both "right" and "better".

In Turkish, the word for right is ''sağ'', which means "alive". The word for left is ''sol'', which means "discolor", "die", "ill".

In Chinese culture, the adjective "left" ([[Chinese character]]: {{lang|zh|{{linktext|左}}}}, [[Mandarin Chinese|Mandarin]]: ''zuǒ'') sometimes means "improper" or "out of accord". For instance, the phrase "left path" ({{lang|zh|{{linktext|左|道}}}}, ''zuǒdào'') stands for unorthodox or immoral means.

In Korean, the word for right is ''oreun'' (오른), to be compared to the word meaning morally proper, ''orheun'' (옳은) which shares the same pronunciation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=YBM, Korea|year=2002|title=Si-sa Elite Korean-English Dictionary|isbn=978-89-17-07460-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Hebrew, as well as in other ancient [[Semitic language|Semitic]] and [[Mesopotamian]] languages, the term "left" was a symbol of power or custody.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Jeffries|last=Hamilton|title=Social Justice and Deuteronomy: the Case of Deuteronomy 15|location=Atlanta|publisher=Scholar's Press|year=1992|page=145|isbn=1-55540-748-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were also examples of left-handed assassins in the Old Testament (Ehud killing the Moabite king). The left hand symbolized the power to shame society, and was used as a metaphor for misfortune, [[natural evil]], or punishment from the gods. This metaphor survived ancient culture and was integrated into mainstream Christianity by early Catholic [[theologians]], such as [[Ambrose of Milan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Ambrose of Milan: political letters and speeches / translated with an introduction and notes by J.H.W.G. Liebeschuetz|location=Liverpool, England|publisher=Liverpool University Press|year=2005|isbn=0-85323-829-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; to modern Protestant theologians, such as [[Karl Barth]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Rosemary Radford|last=Ruether|title=The Left Hand of God in the Theology of Karl Barth—Karl Barth as a Mythopoeic Theologian|work=The Journal of Religious Thought|year=1968–69}}&lt;/ref&gt; to attribute [[natural evil]] to God in explaining God's [[omnipotence]] over the universe.

===Expressions and colloquialisms===
{{refimprove section|date=August 2014}}
The left side is often associated with awkwardness and clumsiness. The Spanish expression "''tener dos pies izquierdos''", in English, the expression "to have two left feet", refers to clumsiness in the domains of football or dancing. A "left-handed compliment" is considered one that is unflattering or dismissive in meaning. The Polish expression "''mieć dwie lewe ręce''", Dutch "''twee linkerhanden hebben''", German "''zwei linke Hände haben''", the Bulgarian expression "''dve levi ratse''", French "''avoir deux mains gauches''", Hungarian ''kétbalkezes'' and Czech "''Mít obě ruce levé''" all mean "to have two left hands"—that one is clumsy or is a very poor handyman; the English equivalent is "to be all thumbs". Moreover, the German idiom "''mit dem linken Fuß aufgestanden sein''", the Spanish expression "''levantarse con el pie izquierdo''", the French expression "''s'être levé du pied gauche''" and the Hungarian expression "''bal lábbal kelt fel''" (literally, to get up with the left foot) mean to have a bad day and do everything wrong or unsuccessfully, related to the English expression "to get up on the wrong side of the bed". The Welsh phrase "''tu chwith allan''" (left side out) refers to an object being inside-out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aber.ac.uk/~gpcwww/pdf/GPC0018-03.pdf |title=Geiriadur Prifysgol Cymru |page=1735 |accessdate=2008-07-28|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Russian, the use of the term ''nalyevo'' means "on the left", but can also connote taking bribes or "sneaky" behavior. ''Balszerencse'' (lit. "left luck") is Hungarian for "bad luck".

There are many [[colloquial]] terms used to refer to a left-handed person, e.g. "southpaw" (USA).  Some are just slang or jargon words, while other references may be offensive or demeaning, either in context or in origin. In some parts of the English-speaking world, "cack-handed" is slang for left-handed, and is also used to mean clumsy. The origin of this term is disputed, but some suggest it is derived from the Latin ''cacare'', in reference to the habit of performing [[Washing|ablutions]] with the left hand, leaving the right hand "clean".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldwidewords.org/qa/qa-cac1.htm|title=Cack-handed|publisher=world wide words}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/cack-handed|title=Definition of "cack-handed"|publisher=The Free Dictionary}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, other sources suggest that it is derived from the Old Norse word ''keikr'', meaning "bent backwards".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/cack%20handed|title=Cack-handed|publisher=Merriam Webster Dictionary}}&lt;/ref&gt; Australians frequently use "cacky-handed". A less common Australian slang word for a left-handed individual is the term ''Molly-Dooker'', whose origins cannot be determined with certainty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Quinion|first=Michael|year=2003|url=http://www.worldwidewords.org/qa/qa-mol2.htm|publisher=World Wide Words|title=Mollydooker|accessdate=October 31, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Handwriting===
Left-handed people who speak [[Arabic]], [[Persian language|Persian]], [[Urdu]], [[Hebrew]] or any other right-to-left script do not have the same difficulties with writing. The right-to-left nature of these languages prevents left-handers from running their hand on the ink as happens with left-to-right languages. Because writing when moving one's hand away from its side of the body can cause smudging if the outward side of the hand is allowed to drag across the writing, it is considered easier to write the [[Latin alphabet]] with the right hand than with the left. Furthermore, it is considered more difficult to write legible [[Chinese language|Chinese characters]] with the left hand than it is to write Latin letters, though difficulty is subjective and depends on the person in question.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.china.org.cn/english/LivinginChina/243637.htm|title=A question of the left being right – and normal|work=China Daily|date=February 22, 2008|accessdate=2011-01-19| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110124025533/http://china.org.cn/english/LivinginChina/243637.htm| archivedate= January 24, 2011 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Left-to-right alphabets can be written smudge-free and in proper "forward slant" with the left hand if the paper is turned 1/4 turn clockwise (90 degrees to the right), and the left hand is drawn toward the body on forward strokes, and left to right on upward strokes (as expressed in directionality of the text). It is also possible to do [[calligraphy]] in this posture with the left hand, but using right-handed pen nibs. Otherwise, left-handed pen nibs are required in order to get the thick-to-thin stroke shapes correct for most type faces, and the left-handed calligrapher is very likely to smudge the text. Left-handed pen nibs are not generally easy to find, and strokes may have to be done backwards from traditional right-handed calligraphic work rules to avoid nib jamming and splatter. Left-handed people have an advantage in learning 19th-century [[copperplate script|copperplate]] hands, which control line-width by pressure on the point.

==Civic life==

===Schooling===
As the majority of students in [[Public school (government funded)|public school]]s are right-handed, most commonly used implements are designed for the right-handed, from [[pencil sharpener]]s to scissors to [[school desk|desks]]. The consequences to left-handed students can vary from decreased academic performance or physical ailments to nothing at all.&lt;ref name="flower"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogcritics.org/culture/article/left-over-left-out-left-behind/|title=Left Over, Left Out, Left Behind: The Daily Discrimination against Left-Handed Students|first=Mei|last=Flower|publisher=blog critics|date=July 28, 2005|accessdate=January 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In many classrooms and [[lecture hall]]s, desks are designed so that the writing surface is attached to the chair instead of separate from it. In this design, the desk is attached on the right side, offering an armrest for right-handed people to use while writing. In some of these desks, the writing surface does not extend fully to the left, necessitating a left-handed user to turn their body in order to write properly, sometimes causing back, neck and shoulder problems.&lt;ref name="flower" /&gt;&lt;ref name="gaucheschool"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indiana.edu/~primate/lspeak2.html#let'sfixit|title=Common school problems|publisher=gauche! Left-Handers in Society|accessdate=2011-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; This contorted posture may also cause the student to be accused of [[Academic dishonesty#Cheating|cheating]].&lt;ref name="gauchedesks"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indiana.edu/~primate/lspeak2.html#desks|title=School desk plague|publisher=gauche! Left-Handers in Society|accessdate=2011-01-19| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101212091224/http://www.indiana.edu/~primate/lspeak2.html| archivedate= December 12, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, however, large lecture halls will use left-handed desks on the left-most column of each section so that left-handed people can comfortably write without bumping against a neighbor.

This right-handed bias is reflected in [[standardized test]]s as well. [[Multiple-choice]] tests tend to put the question on the left side of the page and the answers on the right side. If the answers must be filled in&lt;!--not a mistake--&gt; in a separate booklet, it can be awkward and uncomfortable for a left-handed student to line up the booklet with the answers. The time it takes to find a comfortable, convenient position cuts into test-taking time, resulting in rushed answers and unchecked work.&lt;ref name="flower" /&gt;&lt;ref name="gaucheschool" /&gt;

In [[Vietnam]], schools officially require students to write with their right hands, and some teachers of Grade 1 (when writing is taught) would implement that rule by deducting points from tests written by the left hand. The Civic Education textbook for grade 6 mentions a student thanking her old teacher for helping her write with her right hand, and stopping her from using her left hand to write.

===Employment===
In research done on the relations of handedness and employment, researchers may start their experiments believing left-handers earn lower wages than their right-handed counterparts, due to effects like difficulty using right-handed tools and increased rate of illness among left-handed people.&lt;ref name="slate"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slate.com/id/2147842|title=Sinister and Rich: The evidence that lefties earn more|first=Joel|last=Waldfogel|publisher=Slate|date=August 16, 2006|accessdate=2010-01-19| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100112084036/http://www.slate.com/id/2147842| archivedate= January 12, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=April 2013}} However, their findings are more complex. In studies in the United States and United Kingdom, it was found that left-handed men earn more than right-handed men; about 5% more in the UK. Conversely, left-handed women earn about 7.5% less than right-handed women.&lt;ref name="slate" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucd.ie/economics/research/papers/2004/WP04.22.pdf|title=The Economic Consequences of being Left-handed: Some Sinister Results|first1=Kevin|last1=Denny|first2=Vincent|last2=O’Sullivan|publisher=University College Dublin|date=July 2, 2004|accessdate=January 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Cross-dominance]]
* [[Footedness]]
* [[Laterality]]
* [[Ocular dominance]] (eyedness)
* [[Edinburgh Handedness Inventory]]
* [[Geschwind–Galaburda hypothesis]]
* [[Handedness and mathematical ability]]
* [[List of musicians who play left-handed|Musicians who play left-handed]]
* [[Situs inversus]]
* [[Southpaw stance]] (boxing)
* [[Handedness and sexual orientation]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://wikiexplain.blogspot.com/2017/04/right-handedness.html Why most People are Right-Handed], WikiExplain
* [https://www.buzzfeed.com/daves4/lefties-unite 23 Soul-Crushing Problems Only Left-Handed People Understand]
* [http://www.anythinglefthanded.co.uk/ Left Handers Club]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pbrVSeavxJ8 Left-Handed Problems]
* [http://handedness.org/ Handedness Research Institute]

{{Handedness}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Handedness]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>