<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20060822041615|71103828" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="6357156" pageid="6357156" ns="0" title="Gerontophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-19T02:59:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{expert}}
{{wiktionarypar|gerontophobia}}

"'''Gerontophobia''' is defined as the fear of growing old or a hatred of old people. The definition is curiously double-edged. It encompasses both the fears and self-doubt of individuals as they age; even more importantly it describes asense of hostility that sometimes appears directed at an older generation, by a new and upcoming order". [http://www.ias.ac.in/currsci/nov102004/1163.pdf  Current Science: ''Gerontophobia, Ageing and Retirement''-10 November 2004]


Ken Dychtwald identifies seven markers that can make up this phobia in chapter two of ''Age Wave: How the Most Important Trend of Our Time Will Change Your Future'':
 
* If young is good, then old is bad
* If the young have it all, the old are losing it
* If the young are creative, the old are dull
* If the young are beautiful then the old are unattractive 
* If the young are stimulating, then the old are boring
* If the young are full of passion, then the old are beyond caring
* If the children are tomorrow, the old represent yesterday

==Ageist Language:==

* "old bags," 
* "old hags," 
* "old biddies," 
* "old birds," 
* "old fogies," 
* "old fangled," 
* "old fashioned," 
* "old geezers," 
* "old and decrepit," 
* "old timers,"
* "over the hill," 
* "blue hairs," 
* "golden oldies," 
* "vulnerable," 
* "frail," 
* "declining," 
* "dowdy," 
* "doddering," 
* "fuddy duddies," 
* "out of touch," 
* "not getting any younger'"
* "responsible for a mountain of debt that will become an intolerable burden on society."

==See also==
* [[Ageism]]
* [[Phobia]]

==External links==

* [http://www.mariahburtonnelson.com/Articles/AgingArticles/AgeismAgingUpQandA.htm/ ''AGEISM AND AGING UP: A Q and A with Mariah'']
* [http://www.medfriendly.com/gerontophobia.html/ MedFriendly]
* [http://www.agewave.com/ Age Wave]
* [http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/055334806X Buy ''Age Wave: How the Most Important Trend of Our Time Will Change Your Future'' on Amazon.com] 

[[Category:Aging|Gerontophobia]]
[[Category:Phobias|Gerontophobia]]
[[Category:Old age|Gerontophobia]]
[[Category:Articles with sections needing expansion|Gerontophobia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>