<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071101143035|168511595" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="181322" pageid="181322" ns="0" title="Culture war"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-03T18:08:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''culture war''' (or '''culture wars''') in American usage is a metaphor used to claim that political conflict is based on sets of conflicting values.  The term frequently implies a conflict between values considered [[traditional]] or [[conservative]] and those considered [[Progressivism|progressive]] or [[liberal]].  The "culture war" is sometimes traced to the [[1960s]] and has taken various forms since then. 

==James Davison Hunter==
The expression gained wide use with the 1991 publication of ''Culture Wars: The Struggle to Define America'' by [[James Davison Hunter]]. In that book, Hunter described what he saw as a dramatic re-alignment and polarization that had transformed [[politics of the United States|American politics]] and [[American culture|culture]]. 

He argued that on an increasing number of "hot-button" defining issues &amp;mdash; [[abortion]], [[gun politics]], [[separation of church and state]], [[privacy]], [[homosexuality]], [[censorship]] issues&amp;mdash; there had come to be two definable polarities. Furthermore, it was not just that there were a number of divisive issues, but that society had divided along essentially the same lines on each of these issues, so as to constitute two warring groups, defined primarily not by nominal religion, ethnicity, social class, or even political affiliation, but rather by ideological [[world view]]s. 

Hunter characterised this polarity as stemming from opposite impulses, toward what he refers to as ''Progressivism'' and ''Orthodoxy''. The dichotomy has been adopted with varying labels, including, for example, by commentator [[Bill O'Reilly (commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]] who emphasizes differences between "Secular-Progressives" and "Traditionalists".

In 1990 [[paleoconservatism|paleoconservative]] commentator [[Pat Buchanan]] mounted a campaign for the [[United States Republican Party|Republican]] nomination for [[president of the United States]] against incumbent [[George H.W. Bush]] in 1992. After doing surprisingly well in the [[New Hampshire Primary]], where he drew 37% of the vote, his campaign faded. He received a prime time speech slot on the opening night of the [[Republican National Convention]]. His keynote is sometimes dubbed the "'''&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;'culture war' speech'''".&lt;ref&gt;
''"Not since Pat Buchanan's famous "culture war" speech in 1992 has a major speaker at a national political convention spoken so hatefully, at such length, about the opposition."''&lt;br/&gt;
{{cite web
 | title =  Dogs of War
 | url = http://www.newdonkey.com/2004/09/dogs-of-war.html
 | publisher = New
 | date = 2004-09-02
 | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050308043424/http://www.newdonkey.com/2004/09/dogs-of-war.html
 | archivedate = 2005-03-08
 | accessdate = 2006-08-29
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

During his speech, he said:  "There is a religious war going on in our country for the soul of America. It is a cultural war, as critical to the kind of nation we will one day be as was the Cold War itself." [http://www.buchanan.org/pa-92-0817-rnc.html]  In addition to criticizing "environmental extremists" and "radical feminism," he said [[public morality]] was a [[defining issue]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The agenda [Bill] Clinton and [Hillary] Clinton would impose on America--abortion on demand, a litmus test for the Supreme Court, homosexual rights, discrimination against religious schools, women in combat--that's change, all right. But it is not the kind of change America wants. It is not the kind of change America needs. And it is not the kind of change we can tolerate in a nation that we still call God's country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |authorlink = Patrick Buchanan| first=Patrick | last=Buchanan  | title=1992 Republican National Convention Speech | date=1992-08-17 | publisher= | url =http://www.buchanan.org/pa-92-0817-rnc.html |  accessdate = 2007-11-03 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A month later, Buchanan elaborated that this conflict was about power over society's definition of right and wrong.  He named abortion, sexual orientation and popular culture as major fronts – and mentioned other controversies,  including clashes over the [[Confederate Flag]], Christmas and taxpayer-funded art.  He also said that the negative attention his talk of a culture war received was itself evidence of America’s polarization.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buchanan.org/pa-92-0914.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

When Buchanan ran for president in 1996, he promised to fight for the conservative side of the culture war:
&lt;blockquote&gt;I will use the [[bully pulpit]] of the Presidency of the United States, to the full extent of my power and ability, to defend American traditions and the values of faith, family, and country, from any and all directions. And, together, we will chase the purveyors of sex and violence back beneath the rocks whence they came.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.4president.org/speeches/buchanan1996announcement.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In a 2004 column, Buchanan said the culture war had reignited and that Americans no longer inhabited the same moral universe.  He gave such examples as gay civil unions, the "crudity of the MTV crowd," and the controversy surrounding [[Mel Gibson|Mel Gibson's]] film, [[Passion of the Christ]].   He wrote,
&lt;blockquote&gt;Who is in your face here? Who started this? Who is on the offensive? Who is pushing the envelope? The answer is obvious. A radical Left aided by a cultural elite that detests Christianity and finds Christian moral tenets reactionary and repressive is hell-bent on pushing its amoral values and imposing its ideology on our nation.
The unwisdom of what the Hollywood and the Left are about should be transparent to all.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theamericancause.org/patculturewars.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Campus culture wars==
{{Original research|date=September 2007}}
From the point of view of American [[academia]], the "culture wars" and their alignments were nothing new &amp;mdash; rather, they were perceived as an extrapolation of some conflicts that had been simmering in university life since the [[1960s]]. Positions had been taken up on a number of issues: alleged [[ethnocentricity]] of traditional studies such as philosophy and literature; [[feminism]]; [[postmodernism]]; and [[queer studies|homosexuality]] as a topic in the [[humanities]]. Cruder debates in more emotive terms were expected on the [[curriculum]], [[popular culture]], [[political correctness]], [[affirmative action]] as it applies to admissions, and allegations that teaching was too centered on so called "[[dead white males]]." 

The campus culture wars reflected a change in the demographics of the student population, as well as social change in society at large. [[Public intellectual]]s have sometimes blurred the distinction between "culture war" in this sense, and in national politics.{{Fact|date=July 2007}}

The 1992 book ''Beyond the Culture Wars: How Teaching the Conflicts Can Revitalize American Education'' by [[Gerald Graff]] took a positive line on the campus culture wars.{{Specify|date=July 2007}}

==In Australia==

The concept of a "culture war" is also current in [[Australia]], particularly in the area of [[History of Australia|Australian historiography]]. The so-called [[history wars]] concern how to interpret the country's history, especially regarding [[Indigenous Australians|Aborigines]].&lt;ref name=Australian-debate-on-genocide&gt;[http://www.hyperhistory.org/index.php?option=displaypage&amp;Itemid=364&amp;op=page#arti Debates on Genocide - Part One Debates on 'Genocide' in Australian History], Australian Government Department of Education Science and Traning&lt;/ref&gt;

==Further reading==

* Buchanan, Patrick J.,  ''State of Emergency: The Third World Invasion and Conquest of America'' (August 22, 2006) ISBN 0-312-36003-7
* Buchanan, Patrick J., ''The Death of the West: How Dying Populations and Immigrant Invasions Imperil Our Country and Civilization'', New York: St. Martin's Griffin, 2002 ISBN 0-312-30259-2
* [[Morris P. Fiorina|Fiorina, Morris P.]], with [[Samuel J. Abrams]] and Jeremy C. Pope, ''Culture War?: The Myth of a Polarized America'', London: Longman, 2004 ISBN 0-321-27640-X
*  Gerald Graff. ''Beyond the Culture Wars: How Teaching the Conflicts Can Revitalize American Education'' (1992)
* Hunter, James Davison, ''Culture Wars: The Struggle to Define America'', New York: Basic Books, 1992 ISBN 0-465-01534-4
* Jay, Gregory S., ''American Literature and the Culture Wars'', Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1997 ISBN 0-8014-3393-2 ISBN-13: 978-0801433931
* Jensen, Richard. "The Culture Wars, 1965-1995: A Historian's Map" ''Journal of Social History'' 29 (Oct 1995) 17-37. [http://members.aol.com/dann01/cwar.html online version] 
* Jones, E. Michael, ''Degenerate Moderns: Modernity As Rationalized Sexual Misbehavior'', Ft. Collins, CO: Ignatius Press, 1993 ISBN 0-89870-447-2
* Strauss, William &amp; Howe, Neil , ''The Fourth Turning, An American Prophecy: What the Cycles of History Tell Us About America's Next Rendezvous With Destiny'', 1998, Broadway Books, New York
* Webb, Adam K., ''Beyond the Global Culture War'', Routledge, Jan 2006 ISBN 0-415-95313-8
* Zimmerman, Jonathan, ''Whose America? Culture Wars in the Public Schools'', Harvard University Press, 2002 ISBN 0-674-01860-5

==See also==
*[[Bill O'Reilly (commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]]
*[[Paleoconservatism]]
*[[Pat Buchanan]]
*[[Red state vs. blue state divide]]
*[[Adultism]]
*[[Ageism]]
*[[Mean world syndrome]]
*[[Culture of fear]]
*[[Culture Warrior]]

===Battleground issues in the "culture wars"===
*[[Abortion]]
*[[Adolescent sexuality in the United States|Adolescent sexuality]]
*[[Affirmative action]]
*[[Creation-evolution controversy]] including [[Intelligent Design movement|Intelligent Design]]
*[[Censorship]], [[Video game controversy]]
*[[Capital punishment in the United States|Capital punishment]]
*[[Prohibition (drugs)|Drug Prohibition]]
*[[English-only movement]]
*[[Family values]]
*[[Feminism]], [[Reproductive rights]] and the [[Feminist movement]]
*[[Free speech zones]]
*[[Homosexuality]], [[Lesbian and gay rights]] and [[Gay marriage]]
*[[Identity politics]]
*[[Iraq War]]
**[[Abu Ghraib torture and prisoner abuse]]
*[[Illegal Immigration]]
**[[Opposition to immigration]]
*[[Math wars]], see also [[Traditional mathematics]]
*[[Media bias in the United States|Media bias in the U.S.]]
*[[Moral absolutism]] vs. [[Moral relativism]]
*[[Patriot Act]]
**[[Invasion of privacy]]
**[[Right to privacy]]
*[[Permissive society]]
*[[Political correctness]]
*[[Race]], [[Racism]], [[Race war]] and [[Xenophobia]]
*[[Race and intelligence]]
*[[Right to die|Right to die movement]], [[euthanasia]], and [[Terri Schiavo]]
*[[Secularism]] and [[Secularization]]
*[[Separation of church and state in the United States|Separation of church and state]], public displays of the [[Ten Commandments]], and [[freedom of religion]]
**addition of the phrase "under God" to the [[Pledge of Allegiance]]
**state sanctioned [[school prayer|prayer in public schools]]
*[[Sexual revolution]]
**[[Sexual education]] and [[abstinence|abstinence only]]
*[[Stem-cell research]]
*[[Terrorist surveillance program]]
*[[Transgender]] rights
*[[Transhumanism]]
*[[Women in combat]]
*[[War on drugs]]

===Australia===
*[[History wars]]
**[[Black armband view of history]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
===United States===
*Pat Buchanan, [http://www.buchanan.org/pa-92-0817-rnc.html 1992 Republican National Convention keynote], speech dated August 17, 1992.
*Pat Buchanan, [http://www.buchanan.org/pa-92-0914.html The Cultural War for the Soul of America], speech dated September 14, 1992.
*Pat Buchanan, [http://www.theamericancause.org/patculturewars.htm The Aggressors in the Culture Wars], column dated March 8, 2004.
*[http://www.culturewire.net CultureWire] Daily news.
*[http://defineculture.com/articles.php?subaction=showfull&amp;id=1175831263&amp;archive=&amp;start_from=&amp;ucat=&amp; Culture War]
*[http://www.citizenlink.org/FOSI/abstinence/A000002139.CFM A Look at the Sexual Revolution in the United States]

===Australia===
*[http://www.pm.gov.au/news/speeches/speech1754.html The Hon John Howard MP, Prime Minister of Australia, Speech: ''A sense of balance: The Australian Achievement in 2006''], Address to the National Press Club, 25 January 2006

[[Category:Politics of the United States]]

[[fi:Kulttuurisodankäynti]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>