<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051110182238|27942910" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="181322" pageid="181322" ns="0" title="Culture war"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-10T18:27:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The term '''''Culture Wars''''' has been used to describe ideologically-driven and often strident confrontations typical of [[United States|American]] public culture and politics since the 1960s, but especially beginning in the 1980s. The term evokes the 19th-century German ''[[Kulturkampf]]''.

==''Culture Wars: The Struggle to Define America'' (1991)==

The expression gained wide use with the 1991 publication of ''Culture Wars: The Struggle to Define America'' by [[James Davison Hunter]]. In that book, Hunter described what he saw as a dramatic re-alignment and [[polarity|polarization]] that had transformed [[politics of the United States|American politics]] and [[American culture|culture]]. 

He argued that on an increasing number of "hot-button" defining issues&amp;mdash;[[abortion]], [[gun control]], [[separation of church and state]], [[privacy]], [[homosexuality]], [[censorship]]&amp;mdash;there had come to be two definable polarities. Furthermore it was not just that there were a number of divisive issues, but that society had divided along essentially the same lines on each of these issues, so as to constitute two warring groups, primarily defined not by nominal [[religion]], [[ethnicity]], [[social class]] or even [[political affiliation]], but rather by [[ideology|ideological]] [[world view]]s. 

Hunter characterised this polarity as stemming from opposite impulses, toward what he refers to as ''[[Progressivism]]'' and ''[[Orthodoxy]]''.

==Buchanan's 1992 speech==
''See also [[culture war speech]]''

During the same period, [[paleoconservatism|paleoconservative]] commentator [[Patrick J. Buchanan|Patrick J. "Pat" Buchanan]] mounted a campaign for the [[United States Republican Party|Republican]] nomination for [[president of the United States]] against incumbent [[George H. Bush]] in 1992, based mostly on Bush's decision to raise [[taxes]] after having famously pledged, "[[Read my lips, no new taxes]]". After doing surprisingly well in the first [[primary election]] in [[New Hampshire]], where he drew in 37% of the vote, his campaign faded. However, he received a consolation prize, the [[keynote speech]] at the 1992 [[Republican National Convention]]. 

The speech played well with hard-line Republicans, but some consider that it may have cost the party [[swing vote]]s and alienated [[moderate]]s, ultimately costing them the election. That is, it was adjudged to have been polarizing. Buchanan said, "There is a religious war going on in our country for the soul of America. It is a cultural war, as critical to the kind of nation we will one day be as was the Cold War itself." In short, in the Culture Wars, [[public morality]] was to be a [[defining issue]].
 
[[Independent (politican)|Independent]] [[Ross Perot]] emerged that year as a major figure in politics. Perot received 19% of the vote; some of his relative success is attributed to Buchanan's campaign.

==''Fourth Turning'' (1996)==

The term '''''Culture Wars''''' was adopted by [[William Strauss]] and [[Neil Howe]] in ''Fourth Turning'' (1996), to describe the historical period from [[1984]] to approximately [[2005]]. The preceding era they termed the [[Consciousness Revolution]]; the succeeding era in Strauss and Howe's system is the predicted upcoming [[Crisis of 2020]].

The period opened with triumphant "Morning in America" [[individualism]] and drifted toward [[pessimism]] as time wore on. Personal confidence remained high and in the [[1990s]] few national problems demanded immediate action. But, the public reflected darkly on growing violence and [[incivility]], widening inequality, pervasive distrust of institutions and leaders, and what some saw as a debased popular culture. People began fearing that the national consensus was splitting into competing "values" camps. [http://jkalb.freeshell.org/web/culture_wars.html]

==Campus culture wars==

From the point of view of American [[academia]], the 'culture wars' and their alignments were nothing new &amp;mdash; rather they were perceived as an extrapolation of some conflicts that had been simmering in university life since the [[1960s]]. Positions had been taken up on a number of issues: [[feminism]], [[homosexuality]] as a topic in the [[humanities]], [[postmodernism]] being some of those attracting attention in the arts faculties. Cruder debates in more emotive terms were expected on the [[curriculum]], [[popular culture]], supposed enforcement of [[political correctness]], [[affirmative action]] as it applies to admissions, and allegations that teaching was too centred on [[DWEM]]s and [[WASP]] interpretations. 

The campus culture wars reflected a change in the [[demographics]] of the student population, as well as social change in society at large. [[Public intellectual]]s have sometimes been content to blur the distinction between 'culture war' in this sense, and in national politics.

==After 9/11==

The national mood post-[[9/11]] had been compared by some to the time of the start of the [[Great Depression]]. Others disputed that, arguing that the 9/11 attacks were "a new [[Pearl Harbor]]" that heralded the beginning of a ''culture shift.'' Some right-wing and some left-wing intellectuals saw a post-9/11 United States as being more assertive, more [[militaristic]], more [[unilateral]], and more [[jingoistic]]. The perceived change was both applauded and criticized. 

Fewer questioned at the time that public opinion was more unified than before the attacks. The idea that the events of 9-11 might have ended the culture wars, however, became a less tenable position after the 2004 presidential election. Current debates and controversy over "hot button" culture wars issues of the 1980s and 1990s seem more polarized than ever. The red state/blue state electoral divide seems to show the country very evenly split. Some have argued that the destruction of the World Trade Center produced only a temporary, sobering reaction on the American populace. 

Commentators and others were surprised by the outcome of the [[exit poll]]s on November 2nd, 2004, in which many voters responded that their primary concern in the election was "moral values." Others have pointed out that this is misleading, as the [[Iraq War]] and [[terrorism]] were separate items on the list of concerns, while many Americans saw those issues as one in the same, or at least very closely related.

==See also==

===Battleground issues in the "culture wars"===

*[[abortion]]
*[[affirmative action]]
*[[creation-evolution controversy]] including [[Intelligent Design movement|Intelligent Design]]
*[[censorship]] and [[nipplegate]]
*[[Capital punishment in the United States|capital punishment]]
*[[English-only movement]]
*[[environmentalism]]
*[[family values]]
*[[feminism]]
*[[homosexuality]], [[Don't Ask, Don't Tell]] and [[gay marriage]]
*mention of [[God]] in the [[Pledge of Allegiance]]
*support or opposition to the [[Iraq War]]
*[[Judicial activism]]
*[[Patriot Act]]
*[[Right to die|Right to die movement]], [[euthanasia]], and [[Terry Shiavo]]
*[[Separation of church and state in the United States|Separation of church and state]], public displays of the [[Ten Commandments]], and [[religious freedom]]
*[[school prayer]]
*[[sexual education]] and [[abstinence|abstinence only]]
*[[stem-cell research]]
*[[welfare reform]]
*[[women in combat]]

==External links==

*Patrick Buchanan's Speech to 1992 GOP Convention [http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Patrick_Buchanan's_Speech_to_1992_GOP_Convention]

* [http://www.culturewarbriefing.com/ Culture War Briefing - weekday news guide] - A Christian site that actively embraces the term "culture war"

[[Category:Politics of the United States]]
[[Category:Issue in the Culture Wars| ]]

[[fi:Kulttuurisodankäynti]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>