<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041030100105|6987888" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="181322" pageid="181322" ns="0" title="Culture war"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-30T18:47:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The term '''''Culture Wars''''' has been used to describe ideologically-driven and often strident confrontations typical of [[U.S.A.|American]] public culture and politics since the 1980s. 

The expression gained wide use with the publication in 1991 of ''Culture Wars: The Struggle to Define America'' by [[James Davison Hunter]]. In that book, he described the dramatic polarized re-alignment that had transformed American politics. The observation is that on an increasing number of "hot-button" defining issues &amp;mdash; [[abortion]], [[gun control]], [[separation of church and state]], [[privacy]], [[homosexuality]], [[censorship]] &amp;mdash; there are two definable polarities in [[American culture]]. These are not defined by their nominal [[religion]] or even by their [[political affiliation]], but rather by an ideological [[world view]]. Hunter characterised this [[polarity]] as stemming from the impulses toward [[Progressivism]] and toward [[Orthodoxy]]. 

During the same period, [[paleoconservative]] commentator [[Patrick J. Buchanan]] mounted a campaign for the [[United States Republican Party|Republican]] nomination for [[President of the United States]] against incumbent [[George H. Bush]] in 1992, mostly based on Bush's decision to raise [[taxes]] after the latter's famous pledge, "[[Read my lips, no new taxes]]". After doing surprisingly well in the first [[Primary election|Primary]] in [[New Hampshire]], drawing 37% of the vote, his campaign faded. However, he received a consolation prize, the [[keynote speech]] at the 1992 [[Republican National Convention]]. The speech played well amongst the hard-line Republicans, but some consider that its effect may have cost the party [[swing vote]]s and alienated [[moderate]]s. That is, it was adjudged to have been polarizing. Buchanan said, "There is a religious war going on in our country for the soul of America. It is a cultural war, as critical to the kind of nation we will one day be as was the Cold War itself." Buchanan's campaign is credited to some extent with allowing [[Independent#Politics|Independent]] [[Ross Perot]] to emerge as a major figure in politics; Perot received 19% of the vote that year.

The term '''''Culture Wars''''' was adopted by [[William Strauss]] and [[Neil Howe]] in ''Fourth Turning'' (1996), to describe the historical period from [[1984]] to approximately [[2005]]. The preceding era they termed the [[Consciousness Revolution]]; the succeeding era in Strauss and Howe's system is the predicted upcoming [[Crisis of 2020]].

In the Culture Wars, [[public morality]] was a [[defining issue]].

The period opened with triumphant "Morning in America" [[individualism]] and drifted toward [[pessimism]] as time wore on. Personal confidence remained high and in the [[1990s]] few national problems demanded immediate action. But, the public reflected darkly on growing violence and [[incivility]], widening inequality, pervasive distrust of institutions and leaders, and a debased popular culture. People began fearing that the national consensus was [http://jkalb.freeshell.org/web/culture_wars.html splitting] into competing "values" camps.

==Suggested causes of the split==

Though society had been turning away from tradition and the [[transcendent]] for centuries, [[technology]] had by this time enabled the decoupling of many biological functions from their respective social functions &amp;mdash; sex from its social function of producing the next generation, etc.

==The various camps==

The [[baby boomer|Boom Generation]], who had control of the culture at the beginning of the era, came under attack from their next juniors, [[Generation X]], who had a distinctive anti-Boom crossculture. These two generations are like oil and water: the early generation was defined by their neo-hedonism, while their disillusioned children, having lived through the rise of the [[AIDS]] epidemic and their own parents' broken marriages, craved restored boundaries on behavior and a return to traditional morality.

==Age location in history==

*The [[Silent Generation]] was entering elderhood.
*The [[Baby boomer]]s were entering midlife.
*[[Generation X]] was entering rising adulthood, looking at a Boom-built culture in need of the one thing missing at [[Woodstock Festival|Woodstock]]: ice-water realism.
*[[Generation Y]] was entering childhood.

==Campus culture wars==

From the point of view of American [[academia]], the 'culture wars' and their alignments were nothing new &amp;mdash; rather they were perceived as an extrapolation of some conflicts that had been simmering in university life since the 1960s. Positions had been taken up on a number of issues: [[feminism]], [[homosexuality]] as a topic in the [[humanities]], [[postmodernism]] being some of those attracting attention in the arts faculties. Cruder debates in more emotive terms were expected on the [[curriculum]], [[popular culture]], supposed enforcement of [[political correctness]], [[affirmative action]] as it applies to admissions, and allegations that teaching was too centred on [[DWEM]]s and [[WASP]] interpretations. The campus culture wars reflect a change in the demographics of the student population, as well as social change in society at large. [[Public intellectual]]s have sometimes been content to blur the distinction between 'culture war' in this sense, and in national politics.

==Did the [[September 11 Terrorist Attacks]] herald the end of the Culture Wars era?==

Some argue that the destruction of the World Trade Center produced only a temporary sobering reaction from the American populace. If the Culture Wars era had ended then, the national mood would have been akin to the mood at the time of the start of the [[Great Depression]]. The American military took over [[Afghanistan]] and [[Iraq]], but that has not had the same feeling among the populace as, say, [[VE Day]].

Other critics dispute this.  Instead of comparing September 11 to the end of the Second World War, they see it as similar to the beginning.  Many argue that the 9/11 Attacks were "a new [[Pearl Harbor]]" that heralded the beginning of a ''culture shift.''  Some right-wing and left-wing intellectuals see a post-9/11 United States as being more assertive, more [[militaristic]], more [[unilateral]], and more patriotic.  This perceived change has been both applauded and criticized.

==External links==

[http://sources.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Buchanan%27s_Speech_to_1992_GOP_Convention Text of Culture Wars speech via Wikisource]

[[Category:Politics of the U.S.]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>