<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101029131550|393602998" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="181322" pageid="181322" ns="0" title="Culture war"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-05T00:28:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''culture war''' (or '''culture wars''') in [[United States|American]] usage is a metaphor used to claim that political conflict is based on sets of conflicting cultural values. The term frequently implies a conflict between those values considered traditional or [[Conservativism in the United States|conservative]] and those considered [[Progressivism in the United States|progressive]] or [[Modern liberalism in the United States|liberal]].  The "culture war" is sometimes traced to the 1960s and has taken various forms since then.

==Origins==
The concept of a "culture war" has been in use in English since at least its adoption as a [[calque]] (loan translation) to refer to the German ''[[Kulturkampf]]'' ("cultural struggle" or "struggle between cultures"; literally, "battle of cultures"), the campaign from 1871 to 1878 under [[Chancellor of Germany (German Reich)|Chancellor]] [[Otto von Bismarck]] of the [[German Empire]] against the influence of the [[Roman Catholic Church]].&lt;ref&gt;Martin Spahn, "[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08703b.htm Kulturkampf]", ''[[The Catholic Encyclopedia]]'', volume 8, [[Robert Appleton Company]], 1910.&lt;/ref&gt;
"Culture war" is a [[calque]] generalizing the idea of these kinds of struggle.

Italian [[Marxist]] [[Antonio Gramsci]] presented in the 1920s a theory of [[cultural hegemony]] to explain the slower advance, compared to many Marxists' expectations, of [[proletarian revolution]] in Europe. This stated that a culturally diverse society can be dominated by one class that has a monopoly over the mass media and popular culture, and Gramsci argued for a "culture war" in which [[anti-capitalist]] elements seek to gain a dominant voice in [[mass media]], education, and other mass institutions.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}

As an American phenomenon, its origin was in the 1920s when urban and rural American values came into clear conflict.  This followed several decades of immigration to the cities by elements considered alien by the earlier immigrants and was a result of the cultural shifts and modernizing trends of the [[Roaring 20s]], culminating in the presidential campaign of [[Al Smith]].&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.assumption.edu/users/McClymer/his394/ Seminar on the Culture Wars of the 1920s]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.realclearpolitics.com/articles/2008/03/reclaiming_faith_and_politics.html "Culture Wars: How 2004" Article by [[E.J. Dionne]]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==American 1980s culture wars==
The American 1980s culture wars were characterized by the conservative climate during the [[Presidency of Ronald Reagan]].&lt;ref name="Cengage96"&gt;''[http://www.enotes.com/1980-arts-american-decades/culture-wars Culture Wars]'', 1980's The Arts. Gale Cengage, 1996. eNotes.com. 2006. 2 Mar, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the [[religious right]] often [[Anti-intellectualism|criticized academics and artists]], and their works, in a fight against what they considered indecent, [[Subversion|subversive]], and [[Blasphemy|blasphemous]].&lt;ref name="Cengage96"/&gt; They often accused their political opponents of undermining [[Traditionalist conservatism|tradition]], [[Western civilization]]&lt;ref name="NationObituaries"&gt;Ross Benjamin ''[http://www.thenation.com/doc/20041213/benjamin Hostile Obituary for Derrida]'', [[The Nation]], November 24, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; and [[family values]].

==1990s==
[[File:Patrickjbuchanan.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Patrick Buchanan, pictured in 2008.]]

The expression was introduced again by the 1991 publication of ''Culture Wars: The Struggle to Define America'' by James Davison Hunter, a [[sociologist]] at the [[University of Virginia]]. In it, Hunter described what he saw as a dramatic realignment and polarization that had transformed [[politics of the United States|American politics]] and [[American culture|culture]].

He argued that on an increasing number of "hot-button" defining issues &amp;mdash; [[abortion]], [[gun politics]], [[separation of church and state]], [[privacy]], [[recreational drug use]], [[homosexuality]], [[censorship]] issues &amp;mdash; there had come to be two definable polarities. Furthermore, it was not just that there were a number of divisive issues, but that society had divided along essentially the same lines on each of these issues, so as to constitute two warring groups, defined primarily not by nominal religion, ethnicity, social class, or even political affiliation, but rather by ideological [[world view]]s.

Hunter characterised this polarity as stemming from opposite impulses, toward what he refers to as ''Progressivism'' and ''Orthodoxy''. The dichotomy has been adopted with varying labels, including, for example, by [[Fox News]] commentator [[Bill O'Reilly (commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]] who emphasizes differences between "Secular-Progressives" and "Traditionalists".

In 1990 commentator [[Pat Buchanan]] mounted a campaign for the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] nomination for [[President of the United States]] against incumbent [[George H. W. Bush]] in [[United States presidential election, 1992|1992]].  He received a prime time speech slot at the [[1992 Republican National Convention]], which is sometimes dubbed the "'''&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;'culture war' speech'''".&lt;ref&gt;
''"Not since Pat Buchanan's famous "culture war" speech in 1992 has a major speaker at a national political convention spoken so hatefully, at such length, about the opposition."''&lt;br/&gt;
{{Cite web
 | title =  Dogs of War
 | url = http://www.newdonkey.com/2004/09/dogs-of-war.html
 | publisher = New
 | date = 2004-09-02
 | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050308043424/http://www.newdonkey.com/2004/09/dogs-of-war.html
 | archivedate = 2005-03-08
 | accessdate = 2006-08-29
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

During his speech, he said:  "There is a religious war going on in our country for the soul of America. It is a cultural war, as critical to the kind of nation we will one day be as was the Cold War itself." [http://www.buchanan.org/pa-92-0817-rnc.html]  In addition to criticizing "environmental extremists" and "radical feminism," he said [[public morality]] was a [[defining issue]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The agenda [Bill] Clinton and [Hillary] Clinton would impose on America &amp;mdash; abortion on demand, a litmus test for the Supreme Court, homosexual rights, discrimination against religious schools, women in combat &amp;mdash; that's change, all right. But it is not the kind of change America wants. It is not the kind of change America needs. And it is not the kind of change we can tolerate in a nation that we still call God's country.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|authorlink = Patrick Buchanan| first=Patrick | last=Buchanan  | title=1992 Republican National Convention Speech | date=1992-08-17 | publisher= | url =http://www.buchanan.org/pa-92-0817-rnc.html |  accessdate = 2007-11-03 | language = |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071018035401/http://www.buchanan.org/pa-92-0817-rnc.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A month later, Buchanan elaborated that this conflict was about power over society's definition of right and wrong.  He named abortion, sexual orientation and popular culture as major fronts – and mentioned other controversies,  including clashes over the [[Confederate Flag]], Christmas and taxpayer-funded art.  He also said that the negative attention his talk of a culture war received was itself evidence of America’s polarization.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buchanan.org/pa-92-0914.html The Cultural War for the Soul of America - by Pat Buchanan - Articles, Essays and Speeches - T H E I N T E R N E T B R I G A D E - Official Web Site&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

When Buchanan ran for President in 1996, he promised to fight for the conservative side of the culture war:
&lt;blockquote&gt;I will use the [[bully pulpit]] of the Presidency of the United States, to the full extent of my power and ability, to defend American traditions and the values of faith, family, and country, from any and all directions. And, together, we will chase the purveyors of sex and violence back beneath the rocks whence they came.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.4president.org/speeches/buchanan1996announcement.htm Announcement Speech by Patrick J&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==2000s==
In a 2004 column, [[Pat Buchanan]] said the culture war had reignited and that Americans no longer inhabited the same moral universe. He gave such examples as homosexual [[civil union]]s, the "crudity of the MTV crowd," and the controversy surrounding [[Mel Gibson|Mel Gibson's]] film ''[[The Passion of the Christ]]''. He wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Who is in your face here? Who started this? Who is on the offensive? Who is pushing the envelope? The answer is obvious. A radical Left aided by a cultural elite that detests Christianity and finds Christian moral tenets reactionary and repressive is hell-bent on pushing its amoral values and imposing its ideology on our nation.
The unwisdom of what the Hollywood and the Left are about should be transparent to all.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.theamericancause.org/patculturewars.htm|title=The Aggressors in the Culture Wars|date=March 8, 2004|accessdate=January 26, 2009|author=[[Pat Buchanan]]|publisher=[http://www.theamericancause.org/ theamericancause.org]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:US President Barack Obama taking his Oath of Office - 2009Jan20.jpg|thumb|right|275px|[[Barack Obama]] takes the [[Oath of office of the President of the United States|oath of office]] to begin his [[Presidency of Barack Obama|Presidency]].]]

[[Peter Beinart]], best known as a senior fellow of the [[Council on Foreign Relations]], argued in a January 2009 column for ''[[The Daily Beast]]'' that the new [[United States presidential election, 2008|election of Barack Obama as President]] could be the beginning of the end for American culture war. He wrote:
{{quote|When it comes to culture, Obama doesn’t have a public agenda; he has a public anti-agenda. He wants to remove culture from the political debate. He wants to cut our three-sided political game back down to two... Barack Obama was more successful than John Kerry in reaching out to moderate white evangelicals in part because he struck them as more authentically Christian. That’s the foundation on which Obama now seeks to build. He seems to think there are large numbers of conservative white Protestants and Catholics who will look beyond culture when they enter the voting booth as long as he and other Democrats don’t ram cultural liberalism down their throats.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2009-01-26/the-end-of-the-culture-wars/|author=[[Peter Beinart]]|publisher=''[[The Daily Beast]]''|accessdate=January 5, 2010|title=The End of the Culture Wars|date=January 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;}}

In response, author and writer [[Rod Dreher]] stated in a [[RealClearPolitics]] column that the rhetoric of a culture war disguises the fact that American society truly is deeply divided on some moral issues, which is not an artificial creation of political parties seeking to drum up support. He wrote that the economic positions of the Democratic Party are generally popular enough that, if it chose to drop polarizing social issues, it would become a majority party in ongoing control. He describes the culture war as "inevitable".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.realclearpolitics.com/articles/2009/02/obama_wont_end_the_culture_war.html|publisher=[[RealClearPolitics]]|author=[[Rod Dreher]]|date=February 16, 2009|title=Obama Won't End the Culture Wars|accessdate=January 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Columnist [[Ross Douthat]], then with ''[[The Atlantic]]'', wrote that he had "a lot to agree with" [[Peter Beinart|Beinart]], but he stated that what Obama and his supporters seem to be doing is "winning" the culture wars for their side rather than coming to some kind of compromise.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|publisher=''[[The Atlantic]]''|author=[[Ross Douthat]]|date=January 28, 2009|title=Ending or Winning?|url=http://rossdouthat.theatlantic.com/archives/2009/01/ending_or_winning.php|accessdate=January 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a February 2009 column in ''[[The New York Times]]'', [[William Saletan]] stated that a holistic mix of left-wing and right-wing would come out of the culture wars. He wrote, "morality has to be practical, and that practicality requires morals." He concluded that conservatives should embrace [[family planning]] as a way to reduce abortion and [[government assistance]] while liberals should embrace personal responsibility, which means that unprotected sex is criticized "bluntly". He also advocated same sex marriage as a way to lead LGBT Americans to an "ethic of mutual support and sacrifice" involving stricter personal responsibility.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|publisher=''[[The New York Times]]''|date=February 21, 2009|accessdate=January 5, 2010|author=[[William Saletan]]|title=This Is the Way the Culture Wars End|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/22/opinion/22saletan.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Regional culture wars==
The '''culture war''' (or '''culture wars''') in [[Canada|Canadian]] usage is a metaphor used to describe the current polarization between the different values of Canadians. This can be framed to describe [[Western Canada|West]] versus [[Quebec|East]], [[Rural Canada|rural]] versus [[List of the 100 largest urban areas in Canada by population|urban]] or [[Conservatism in Canada|traditional values]] versus [[Progressivism in Canada|progressive secularism]]. The "culture war" is a relatively new phrase to enter within Canadian political commentary. However it can still be used to describe historical events within Canada, such as the [[Rebellions of 1837]], [[Western Alienation]], [[Front de libération du Québec|Quebec separatism]], and any [[:Category:Aboriginal conflicts in Canada|Aboriginal conflicts in Canada]]. The term is more so relevant to current events such as the [[Grand River land dispute|Caledonia conflict with Natives]] and the increasing amount of hostility between [[Conservative]] Canadians and [[Liberal Party of Canada|Liberal]] Canadians. The '''culture war''' expression is relatively new to Canadian political commentary, but its usage has sparked considerably in the recent year due to prorogation rallies, abortion and the gun registry.

==See also==
*[[Paleoconservatism]]
*[[Neoconservatism]]
*[[Bill O'Reilly (political commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]]
*[[Glenn Beck]]
*[[Pat Buchanan]]
*[[The War on Christmas]]
*[[Red state vs. blue state divide]]
*[[History wars]] in [[Australia]]
*[[Christofascism]]

===Battleground issues in the "culture wars"===
{{col-begin}}
{{col-3}}
*[[Abortion]] / [[Reproductive rights]]
*[[Age of consent]]
*[[Animal Rights]]
*[[Creation-evolution controversy]]
*[[Legal drinking age]]
*[[Family values]]
** [[Corporal punishment]]
** [[Child discipline]], most notably [[spanking]]
*[[Feminism]]
*[[Gun politics]]
*[[Homosexuality]], [[Lesbian and gay rights|Gay rights]], and [[Gay marriage]]
** [[California Proposition 8 (2008)]]
*[[Identity politics]]
{{Col-3}}
*[[Law and order (politics)|Law and order]]
*[[Media bias in the United States|Media bias in the U.S.]]
*[[Moral absolutism]] vs. [[Moral relativism]]
*[[Multiculturalism]]
*[[Permissive society]]
*[[Political correctness]]
*[[Race (classification of human beings)|Race]], [[Racism]], and [[Xenophobia]]
{{Col-3}}
*[[Right to die|Right to die movement]] and [[euthanasia]]
*[[Secularism]] and [[Secularization]]
*[[Separation of church and state in the United States|Separation of church and state]]
*[[Sexual revolution]]
**[[Sexual education]] and [[Sexual abstinence|abstinence only]]
*[[Stem-cell research]]
*[[Transhumanism]]
{{Col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Buchanan, Patrick J., ''The Death of the West: How Dying Populations and Immigrant Invasions Imperil Our Country and Civilization'', New York: St. Martin's Griffin, 2002 ISBN 0-312-30259-2
* [[Morris P. Fiorina|Fiorina, Morris P.]], with [[Samuel J. Abrams]] and Jeremy C. Pope, ''Culture War?: The Myth of a Polarized America'', London: Longman, 2004 ISBN 0-321-27640-X
*  Gerald Graff. ''Beyond the Culture Wars: How Teaching the Conflicts Can Revitalize American Education'' (1992)
* Hunter, James Davison, ''Culture Wars: The Struggle to Define America'', New York: Basic Books, 1992 ISBN 0-465-01534-4
* Jay, Gregory S., ''American Literature and the Culture Wars'', Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1997 ISBN 0-8014-3393-2 ISBN 978-0801433931
* Jensen, Richard. "The Culture Wars, 1965-1995: A Historian's Map" ''Journal of Social History'' 29 (Oct 1995) 17-37.
* Jones, E. Michael, ''Degenerate Moderns: Modernity As Rationalized Sexual Misbehavior'', Ft. Collins, CO: Ignatius Press, 1993 ISBN 0-89870-447-2
* Strauss, William &amp; Howe, Neil , ''The Fourth Turning, An American Prophecy: What the Cycles of History Tell Us About America's Next Rendezvous With Destiny'', 1998, Broadway Books, New York
* Thomson, Irene Tavis.,  [http://www.press.umich.edu/titleDetailDesc.do?id=1571326 ''Culture Wars and Enduring American Dilemmas''] , Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press, 2010 ISBN 978-0-472-07088-6
* Webb, Adam K., ''Beyond the Global Culture War'', Routledge, Jan 2006 ISBN 0-415-95313-8
* Zimmerman, Jonathan, ''Whose America? Culture Wars in the Public Schools'', Harvard University Press, 2002 ISBN 0-674-01860-5

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}

===United States===
*Pat Buchanan, [http://buchanan.org/blog/1992-republican-national-convention-speech-148 1992 Republican National Convention keynote], speech dated August 17, 1992.
*Pat Buchanan, [http://www.buchanan.org/pa-92-0914.html The Cultural War for the Soul of America], speech dated September 14, 1992.
*Pat Buchanan, [http://www.theamericancause.org/patculturewars.htm The Aggressors in the Culture Wars], column dated March 8, 2004.
*Focus on the Family, [http://www.citizenlink.org/FOSI/abstinence/A000002139.CFM A Look at the Sexual Revolution in the United States]

===Australia===
*[http://australianpolitics.com/news/2006/01/06-01-25_howard.shtml The Hon John Howard MP, Prime Minister of Australia, Speech: ''A sense of balance: The Australian Achievement in 2006''], Address to the National Press Club, 25 January 2006

{{DEFAULTSORT:Culture War}}
[[Category:American political terms]]
[[Category:American culture]]
[[Category:Christian fundamentalism]]

[[is:Menningarstríðin (Bandaríkin)]]
[[fi:Kulttuurisodankäynti]]
[[zh:文化战争]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>