<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031028100214|1669866" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="181322" pageid="181322" ns="0" title="Culture war"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-04T03:25:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Culture Wars''' is the term used by [[William Strauss]] and [[Neil Howe]] in their book ''Fourth Turning'' to describe the historical period from [[1984]] to approximately [[2005]]. The preceding era is the [[Consciousness Revolution]]; the succeeding era in Strauss and Howe's system is the predicted upcoming [[Crisis of 2020]].

The period opened with triumphant "Morning in America" individualism and drifted toward pessimism as time wore on. Personal confidence remained high and in the [[1990s]] few national problems demanded immediate action. But, the public reflected darkly on growing violence and incivility, widening inequality, pervasive distrust of institutions and leaders, and a debased popular culture. People began fearing that the national consensus was [http://jkalb.freeshell.org/web/culture_wars.html splitting] into competing "values" camps.

==Causes of the Split==
Though society had been turning away from tradition and the [[transcendent]] for centuries, technology had by this time enabled the decoupling of many biological functions from their respective social functions - sex from its social function of producing the next generation, etc.

==The Various Camps==
The [[baby boomer|Boom Generation]], who had control of the culture at the beginning of the era, came under attack from their next juniors, [[Generation X]], who had a distinctive anti-Boom crossculture. These two generations are like oil and water: aggressive moralizers on one side, neo-hedonists on the other.

----

'''Age Location in History:'''
*The [[Silent Generation]] was entering elderhood.
*The [[Baby boomer]]s were entering midlife, now fully transformed from [[hippie]] to [[yuppie]] and beyond to a bunch of parents firmly intent on denying the young the same mind-expanding drugs the Boom had in its youth in a pitiless, Scrooge-like, moralistic campaign.
*[[Generation X]] was entering rising adulthood, looking at a Boom-built culture in need of the one thing missing at Woodstock: ice-water realism.
*[[Generation Y]] was entering childhood.

'''Did the acts of September 11, 2001 herald the end of the Culture Wars era?'''
The destruction of the World Trade Center produced only temporarily a sobering reaction from the American populace. If the Culture Wars era had ended then, the national mood would have been akin to the mood at the time of the start of the [[Great Depression]]. The American military took over Afghanistan and Iraq, but that has not had the same feeling among the populace as, say, V-E Day. President [[George W. Bush]] is trying to take up the mantle of the warrior-priest waging righteous wars against less godly opponents such as [[Saddam Hussein]] and [[Osama bin Laden]], but his political opponents are launching a full-scale attack to discredit him. Ultimately, Bush and his mainstream detractors seem unlikely to herald in any new thought or behavior in terms of political culture.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>