<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051030040624|26849202" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="66936" pageid="66936" ns="0" title="LGBTQ"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-03T19:45:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:'' LGBTQ, LGBTA, LGBTT, LGBTI, LGBTIQ, LGBU, GLB, and FABGLITTER redirect to this page, because they are variants of the term LGBT. See the [[#Variants|variants section]] for the meanings of these initialisms. ''

'''LGBT''' (or '''GLBT''') is an [[initialism]] used as a collective term to refer to [[lesbian|'''L'''esbian]], [[gay|'''G'''ay]], [[bisexuality|'''B'''isexual]], and [[transgender|'''T'''ransgender]] people. It is considered less controversial than the terms ''[[queer]]'' or ''lesbigay'' and is more comprehensive than ''[[homosexual]]'' or simply ''[[gay]]''. The initialism '''GLBT''' is commonly used in the United States, but to a lesser extent elsewhere.

Many variants exist, however the most commonly used involve adding an '''''I''''' for ''[[intersex]]''.

==Meaning of each term==

Each term in the initialism is used to refer to members of the specific group and to the ''community'' that surrounds them. This can include family and friends, rights advocates, artists, authors, etc.

===Lesbian===
{{see details|lesbian}}

In this context, lesbian refers to women with a [[sexual orientation]] towards women; and the general lesbian (and to some extent, parts of the lesbian-supportive [[feminist]]) community.

===Gay===
{{see details|gay}}

In this context, ''gay'' refers specifically to men with a sexual orientation towards men; and the gay male community, though the term can be used without respect to the gender of the person in question in wider contexts.

===Bisexual===
{{see details|bisexuality}}

Bisexual refers to persons who are attracted to both men and women. Bisexuality can fall anywhere between the sexual orientations of homosexuality and heterosexuality.

===Transgender===
{{see details|transgender}}

Transgender is generally used as a catch-all umbrella term for a variety of individuals, behaviors, and groups centered around the full or partial reversal of gender roles as well as physical sexual reassignment therapies (which can be just hormonal or involve various degrees of surgical alteration). A common definition is "People who feel that the gender they were assigned (usually at birth) is a false or incomplete description of themselves". Included in this definition are a number of well known sub-categories such as [[transsexual]] and [[transvestism|transvestite]] (see also [[cross-dressing]]).

===Intersex===
{{see details|intersex}}

This term (represented by the letter "''I''" in the ''LGBTI'' and ''GLBTI'' initialisms) may or may not be included, and some intersex communities are not inclusive of non-intersex LGBT persons (while some are).

Intersex refers to ambiguous or mismatching [[sexual characteristics]] (including levels of [[sex hormone]]s) and those people who have them. This is distinct from the older term [[hermaphrodite]], which is generally not accurate when referring to [[vertebrates]] (including humans). In many cases, the line between intersex and transgender is complex, and some individuals fit into both classifications.

==History==

''This section is about the term "LGBT".  For a history of the gay rights movement, see [[Gay rights]] and [[LGBT history]].''

Up until the [[sexual revolution]] of the [[1960s]] there were no widely known terms for describing the people in these groups other than the derogatory terms used by the [[heterosexual|straight]] community; [[third gender]], in use before the second world war, fell out of use after it.  As people began organizing for their sexual rights they needed a term that would say who they were in a positive way. (Compare [[heteronormativity]])  

The first term used, [[Homosexual]], carried too much negative baggage and was replaced by "Gay".  As Lesbians forged their own identity, the term "Gay and Lesbian" became more common.

''LGBT'' became increasingly common from the mid [[1990s]] and [[as of 2005]], ''LGBT'' has become so mainstream that it has been adopted by the majority of [[List of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender community centers|lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender community centers]] and the [[gay press]] in most [[English language|English]]-speaking countries. In [[October]] [[2004]], media company PlanetOut Inc., which owns the PlanetOut.com and Gay.com domains, chose ''LGBT'' as its ticker symbol when it listed on the [[NASDAQ]] exchange after a successful [[IPO]].  To date it has remained mostly a text-based, rather than a conversational, term.

==Variants==

Many variants exist, including variations which merely change the order of the letters; but ''LGBT'' is the most common acronym and the one most accepted in current usage. When not inclusive of transgender people it is shortened to '''LGB'''. It may also include two additional ''Q''s for ''[[queer|queer]]'' and ''questioning'' (sometimes abbreviated with a question mark) ('''LGBTQ''', '''LGBTQQ'''); a variant being '''LGBU''', where ''U'' stands for "unsure", an ''I'' for [[intersex]] ('''LGBTI'''), another ''T'' for ''[[transsexual]]'' ('''LGBTT'''), another ''T'' (or ''TS'' or the numeral 2) for [[Two-Spirit|two-spirited]] people, and an ''A'' for [[straight ally|straight allies]] ('''LGBTA'''). At its fullest, then, it is some permutation of '''LGBTTTIQQA''', though this is extremely rare.  The magazine ''[[Anything That Moves]]'' coined the acronym '''FABGLITTER''' (from [[Sexual_fetishism|Fetish]], Allies, Bisexual, Gay, Lesbian, Intersexed, Transgender, Transsexual [[Gender|Engendering]] [[Revolution]]).  This term has not made its way into common usage.

The terms transsexual and intersex are regarded by some people as falling under the umbrella term ''transgender'', though many transsexual and intersex people object to this (both for different reasons). [[Gay-Straight Alliance]] (GSA) organizations often use ''LGBTQA'' for ''LGBT'' &amp;mdash; questioning and allies.

Some variants are local alterations that are used to the exclusion of others by virtue of being commonplace in a region.  For example, in [[Minnesota]] the term GLBT is more prominent.

==Controversy==

''LGBT'' is not uncontroversial. For example, some transgender and transsexual people do not like the term because they do not believe their cause is the same as that of LGB people; they may also object when an organization adds a ''T'' to their acronym when the level of service they actually offer to trans people is questionable. There are also LGB people who don't like the ''T'' for the same or similar reasons. 

Many people also believe that a sharp distinction should be drawn between [[sexual orientation]] and [[gender identity]]. ''GLB'' concerns the former; ''TTI'' concerns the latter.

Similarly, some intersex people want to be included into LGBT groups and would prefer ''LGBTI''; others insist that they are not a part of the LGBT community and would rather not be included in the acronym.

Many people have looked for a generic term to replace acronyms. Words like "[[queer]]" and "rainbow" have been tried but most have not been widely adopted.  "Queer" has many negative connotations to older people who remember the word as a taunt and insult, a usage of the term which has continued. Many younger people also understand "queer" to be more politically charged than "LGBT".  "Rainbow" has connotations that recall the [[hippies]], [[New Age]] movements and politics ([[Jesse Jackson]]'s [[Rainbow Coalition]].)  

==See also==
*[[Gay]]
*[[Gay community]]
*[[Gender]]
*[[Homosexuality]]
*[[Lesbian]]
*[[List of gay-related topics]]
*[[List of transgender-related topics]]
*[[List of LGBT organizations]]
*[[List of LGBT publications]]
*[[Queer]]
*[[Queer theory]]
*[[Queer Theology]]
*[[Transgender]]

==External links==
* [http://www.planetoutinc.com/ PlanetOut Inc.]
* [http://www.aboutgaymovies.info/ About Gay Movies]: Compendium of [[LGBT]]-themed movies and television series. With reviews, pictures, wallpapers, forum, glbt filmfestivals, gay movie history, sweepstakes and more
*[http://gayinfo.tripod.com/ Extensive set of short LGBT biographies]

[[Category:LGBT]]
[[Category:LGBT history]]

[[bg:ЛГБТ]]
[[de:LGBT]]
[[fr:LGBT]]
[[it:LGBT]]
[[he:להט"ב]]
[[nl:LGBT]]
[[pl:LGBT]]
[[pt:LGBT]]
[[simple:LGBT]]
[[sv:HBT]]
[[zh:LGBT]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>