<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20170923203521|802072119" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2159778" pageid="2159778" ns="0" title="Sexual and reproductive health"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-10T19:12:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Sexual health|the journal|International Journal of Sexual Health}}

{{Feminism sidebar}}

Within the framework of the [[World Health Organization]]'s (WHO) definition of [[health]] as a state of complete physical, mental and social well-being, and not merely the absence of disease or infirmity, '''reproductive health''', or '''sexual health'''/'''hygiene''', addresses the reproductive processes, functions and system at all stages of life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/topics/reproductive_health/en/|title=WHO: Reproductive health|accessdate=2008-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Reproductive health implies that people are able to have a responsible, satisfying and [[Safer sex|safer sex life]] and that they have the capability to reproduce and the [[Family planning|freedom to decide]] if, when and how often to do so. One interpretation of this implies that men and women ought to be [[sex education|informed]] of and to have access to safe, effective, affordable and acceptable methods of [[birth control]]; also access to appropriate [[reproductive medicine|health care services]] of [[sexual medicine|sexual]], [[reproductive medicine]] and implementation of health education programs to stress the importance of [[maternal health|women to go safely]] through [[pregnancy]] and [[childbirth]] could provide couples with the best chance of having a healthy infant.

Individuals do face inequalities in reproductive health services. Inequalities vary based on socioeconomic status, education level, age, ethnicity, religion, and resources available in their environment. It is possible for example, that low income individuals lack the resources for appropriate health services and the knowledge to know what is appropriate for maintaining reproductive health.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Hall KS, Moreau C, Trussell J |title=Determinants Of And Disparities In Reproductive Health Service Use Among Adolescent And Young Adult Women In The United States, 2002-2008 |journal=American Journal of Public Health |volume=102|issue=2 |date=2012 |pages=359–367|via=Academic Search Premier |doi=10.2105/ajph.2011.300380 |pmid=22390451 |pmc=3483992}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The WHO assessed in 2008 that "Reproductive and sexual ill-health accounts for 20% of the global burden of ill-health for women, and 14% for men."&lt;ref name=WHOstrat&gt;{{cite web| title = Reproductive Health Strategy |publisher=World Health Organization | url = http://www.who.int/reproductive-health/strategy.htm | accessdate = 2008-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reproductive health is a part of [[sexual and reproductive health and rights]].

According to the [[United Nations Population Fund]] (UNFPA), unmet needs for sexual and reproductive health deprive women of the right to make "crucial choices about their own bodies and futures", affecting family welfare. Women bear and usually nurture children, so their reproductive health is inseparable from gender equality. Denial of such rights also worsens poverty.&lt;ref name=SRH&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unfpa.org/sexual-reproductive-health |publisher=UN Population Fund |title=Sexual reproductive health }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reproductive health should be looked at through a lifecycle approach as it affects both men and women from infancy to old age. According to UNFPA, reproductive health at any age profoundly affects health later in life.&lt;ref name=SRH/&gt; The lifecycle approach incorporates the challenges people face at different times in their lives such as family planning, services to prevent sexually transmitted diseases and early diagnosis and treatment of reproductive health illnesses. As such, services such as health and education systems need to be strengthened and availability of essential health supplies such as contraceptives and medicines must be supported.

== Sexual health ==
A WHO working definition for sexual health is that it "is a state of physical, emotional, mental and social well-being in relation to sexuality; it is not merely the absence of disease, dysfunction or infirmity. Sexual health requires a positive and respectful approach to sexuality and sexual relationships, as well as the possibility of having pleasurable and safe sexual experiences, free of coercion, discrimination and violence. For sexual health to be attained and maintained, the sexual rights of all persons must be respected, protected and fulfilled."&lt;ref name=WHOGenderRights&gt;{{cite web |title=Gender and human rights |publisher=WHO |url=http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/topics/gender_rights/sexual_health/en/ | accessdate = 4 September 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, while used by WHO as well as other organizations, this is not an official WHO position, and should not be used or quoted as a WHO definition.&lt;ref name=WHOGenderRights /&gt;

The programme of action (PoA) of the [[International Conference on Population and Development]] (ICPD) in Cairo in 1994 was the first among international development frameworks to address issues related to sexuality, sexual and reproductive health, and reproductive rights. The PoA defined sexual health as, dealing “with the enhancement of life and personal relations, not merely counseling and care related to reproduction and sexually transmitted diseases.19 It refers to the integration of the somatic, emotional, intellectual and social aspects of sexual being in ways that are positively enriching and that enhance personality, communication and love.” &lt;ref name="Reproductive rights"&gt;{{cite web|title=Reproductive rights are human rights |url=http://www.unfpa.org/sites/default/files/pub-pdf/NHRIHandbook.pdf|publisher=[[United Nations Population Fund|UNFPA]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Emerging research in the field of sexual and reproductive health (SRH) identifies a series of factors that enhance the translation of research into policy and practice.&lt;ref name="Theobold 2011 S2"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Theobold S, etal |title=Strengthening the research to policy and practice interface: exploring strategies used by research organisations working on sexual and reproductive health and HIV/AIDS |journal=Health Research Policy and Systems|year=2011|volume=9|issue=1|pages=S2|url=http://www.futurehealthsystems.org/publications/creating-a-public-space-and-dialogue-on-sexuality-and-rights.html|accessdate=24 May 2012|doi=10.1186/1478-4505-9-s1-s2}}&lt;/ref&gt; These include discursive changes (creating spaces for public debate); content changes (to laws and practices); procedural changes (influencing how data on SRH are collected) and behavioural changes (through partnerships with civil society, advocacy groups and policy makers).&lt;ref name="Theobold 2011 S2"/&gt;

== Childbearing and health ==
{{see also | Maternal health|Family planning}}

Early childbearing and other behaviours can have health risks for women and their infants. Waiting until a woman is at least 18 years old before trying to have children improves maternal and child health.&lt;ref name=USAIDHTSP&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.esdproj.org/site/PageServer?pagename=Themes_Spacing_KeyMessages | title = Healthy timing and spacing of pregnancy: HTSP Messages | publisher = USAID |accessdate=2008-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Brown |first=H. L. |last2=Fan |first2=Y. D. |last3=Gonsoulin |first3=W. J. |title=Obstetric complications in young teenagers |journal=South Medical Journal |year=1991 |volume=84 |issue= |pages=46–48 |pmid=1986428 |doi=10.1097/00007611-199101000-00012}}&lt;/ref&gt; If an additional child is to be conceived, it is considered healthier for the mother, as well as for the succeeding child, to wait at least 2 years after the previous birth before attempting to concep
tion.&lt;ref name=USAIDHTSP/&gt;  After a fetal fatality, it is healthier to wait at least 6 months.&lt;ref name=USAIDHTSP/&gt;

The WHO estimates that each year, 358 000 women die due to complications related to pregnancy and childbirth; 99% of these deaths occur within the most disadvantaged population groups living in the poorest countries of the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/topics/maternal_perinatal/en/index.html |publisher=World Health Organization |title=Maternal and perinatal health |accessdate=3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Most of these deaths can be avoided with improving women's access to quality care from a [[birth attendant|skilled birth attendant]] before, during and after pregnancy and childbirth.

== Availability of modern contraception ==

Modern contraception is often unavailable in certain parts of the world. According to the WHO, about 222 million women worldwide have an unmet need for modern contraception, and the lack of access to modern contraception is highest among the most disadvantaged population: the poor, those living in rural areas and urban slums, those living with HIV, and those who are internally displaced.&lt;ref name="apps.who.int"&gt;http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/102539/1/9789241506748_eng.pdf?ua=1&lt;/ref&gt; In developing parts of the world, the lack of access to contraception is a main cause of [[unintended pregnancy]], which is associated with poorer reproductive outcomes.&lt;ref name="apps.who.int"/&gt; According to [[UNFPA]], access to contraceptive services for all women could prevent about one in three deaths related to pregnancy and childbirth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unfpa.org/public/home/mothers/pid/4382|title=Family planning&amp;nbsp;— UNFPA&amp;nbsp;— United Nations Population Fund|publisher=|accessdate=13 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Female genital mutilation ==

[[File:FGM prevalence UNICEF 2013.svg|right|thumb|250px|Prevalence of FGM by country, according to a 2013 UNICEF report&lt;ref name=childinfo&gt;{{cite web|title=Prevalence of FGM/C |url=http://data.unicef.org/child-protection/fgmc |publisher=UNICEF |accessdate=18 August 2014 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150715233215/http://data.unicef.org/child-protection/fgmc |archivedate=15 July 2015 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

{{Main|Female genital mutilation}}

Female genital mutilation (FGM), also known as female genital cutting or female circumcision, "comprises all procedures that involve partial or total removal of the external female genitalia, or other injury to the female genital organs for non-medical reasons".&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs241/en/ |publisher=WHO |title=Female genital mutilation |date=February 2014 |accessdate=14 May 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=UNFPAFGM&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unfpa.org/female-genital-mutilation |title=Female genital mutilation |publisher=UNFPA }}&lt;/ref&gt; The practice is concentrated in 29 countries in Africa and the Middle East; and more than 125 million girls and women today are estimated to have been subjected to FGM.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; FGM also takes place in immigrant communities in Western countries, such as the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nhs.uk/conditions/female-genital-mutilation/pages/introduction.aspx |publisher=UK National Health Service |title=Female genital mutilation }}&lt;/ref&gt;

FGM does not have any health benefits, and has negative effects on reproductive and sexual health, including severe pain, shock, hemorrhage, tetanus or sepsis (bacterial infection), urine retention, open sores in the genital region and injury to nearby genital tissue, recurrent bladder and urinary tract infections, cysts, increased risk of infertility, childbirth complications and newborn deaths. FGM procedures that seal or narrow a vaginal opening (known as type 3) lead to a need for future surgeries of cutting open in order to allow for sexual intercourse and childbirth.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;

According to UNFPA, “FGM violates human rights principles and standards&amp;nbsp;– including the principles of equality and non-discrimination on the basis of sex, the right to freedom from torture or cruel, inhuman or degrading punishment, the right to the highest attainable standard of health, the rights of the child, and the right to physical and mental integrity, and even the right to life, among others.&lt;ref name=UNFPAFGM /&gt;

== Sexually transmitted infections ==

[[File:AIDS and HIV prevalence.svg|thumb|upright=1.2|alt= A map of the world where most of the land is colored green or yellow except for sub Saharan Africa which is colored red|Estimated [[prevalence]] in % of HIV among young adults (15–49) per country as of 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=AIDSinfo |url=http://www.unaids.org/en/dataanalysis/datatools/aidsinfo/ |work=UNAIDS |accessdate=4 March 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break}}

{{legend|#787878|&lt;small&gt;No data&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{legend|#94bf8b|&lt;small&gt;&lt;0.10&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{legend|#f4e2ba|&lt;small&gt;0.10–0.5&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{legend|#eaca83|&lt;small&gt;0.5–1&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{Col-break}}

{{legend|#f07568|&lt;small&gt;1–5&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{legend|#ff4800|&lt;small&gt;5–15&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{legend|#b00000|&lt;small&gt;15–50&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{col-end}}]]

{{Main|Sexually transmitted infection}}

A [[sexually transmitted infection]] (STI)—formerly called ''sexually transmitted disease'' (STD) or ''venereal disease'' (VD)—is an infection that has a significant likelihood of transmission between humans by means of [[sexual activity]]. Common STIs include [[Chlamydia infection|chlamydia]], [[gonorrhea]], [[herpes]], [[HIV]], [[hepatitis B]], [[human papillomavirus]] (HPV), [[syphilis]], and [[trichomoniasis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cdc.gov/STD/ |publisher=US Centers for Disease Control |title=Sexually transmitted diseases }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nhs.uk/conditions/Sexually-transmitted-infections/Pages/Introduction.aspx  |publisher=UK National Health Service |title=Sexually transmitted diseases }}&lt;/&lt;/ref&gt;

Sexually transmitted infections affect reproductive and sexual health, having a profound negative impact worldwide.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs110/en/|title=Sexually transmitted infections (STIs)|publisher=|accessdate=13 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Programs aimed at preventing STIs include comprehensive [[sex education]], STI and HIV pre- and post-test counseling, safer sex/risk-reduction counseling, condom promotion, and interventions targeted at key and vulnerable populations.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; Having access to effective medical treatment for STIs is very important.

== Adolescent health ==

[[File:Teenage birth rate per 1000 women 15–19, 2000-09.svg|thumb|300px|Teenage birth rate per 1,000 females aged 15–19, 2000–2009&lt;ref name=ustats-births&gt;[http://unstats.un.org/unsd/demographic/products/dyb/dyb2009-2010/Table10.pdf Live births by age of mother and sex of child, general and age-specific fertility rates: latest available year, 2000–2009]&amp;nbsp;— United Nations Statistics Division&amp;nbsp;– Demographic and Social Statistics&lt;/ref&gt;]]

{{Further|Teenage pregnancy|Adolescent sexuality}}

Issues affecting adolescent reproductive and sexual health are similar to those of adults, but may include additional concerns about [[teenage pregnancy]] and lack of adequate access to information and health services. Worldwide, around 16 million adolescent girls give birth every year, mostly in low- and middle-income countries.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs364/en/|title=Adolescent pregnancy|publisher=|accessdate=13 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The causes of teenage pregnancy are diverse. In developing countries girls are often under pressure to marry young and bear children early (see [[child marriage]]). Some adolescent girls do not know how to avoid becoming pregnant, are unable to obtain contraceptives, or are coerced into sexual activity.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC"/&gt; Adolescent pregnancy, especially in developing countries, carries increased health risks, and contributes to maintaining the [[cycle of poverty]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/adolescence/9789241502214/en/|title=Preventing early pregnancy and poor reproductive outcomes among adolescents in developing countries |publisher=World Health Organization|access-date=September 23, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The availability and type of [[sex education]] for teenagers varies in different parts of the world. LGBT teens may suffer additional problems if they live in places where homosexual activity is socially disapproved and/or illegal; in extreme cases there can be depression, social isolation and even [[suicide among LGBT youth]].

[[UNFPA]] recommends “Comprehensive sexuality education” (CSE) as it enables young people to make informed decisions about their sexuality.&lt;ref name="Education"&gt;{{cite web |title=UNFPA Operational Guidance for Comprehensive Sexuality Education: A Focus on Human Rights and Gender|url=http://www.unfpa.org/sites/default/files/pub-pdf/UNFPA_OperationalGuidance_WEB3.pdf |publisher=[[United Nations Population Fund|UNFPA]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the UNFPA, CSE should be taught by introducing content which is age-appropriate to the capacities of young people over a span of several years. The curriculum includes  scientifically accurate information on physical development, anatomy,  pregnancy, contraception and sexually transmitted infections (STIs), including HIV. It should encourage confidence and skills for communication topics include social issues around sexuality and reproduction.&lt;ref name="Education" /&gt;

== International Conference on Population and Development, 1994 ==

The [[International Conference on Population and Development]] (ICPD) was held in [[Cairo]], Egypt, from 5 to 13 September 1994. Delegations from 179 States took part in negotiations to finalize a Programme of Action on population and development for the next 20 years. Some 20,000 delegates from various governments, [[UN]] agencies, [[NGOs]], and the [[Mass media|media]] gathered for a discussion of a variety of population issues, including [[immigration]], [[infant mortality]], [[birth control]], [[family planning]], and the education of women.

In the [https://www.un.org/ecosocdev/geninfo/populatin/icpd.htm#intro ICPD Program of Action], 'Reproductive health' is defined as:

&lt;blockquote&gt;a state of complete physical, mental and social well-being and...not merely the absence of disease or infirmity, in all matters relating to the reproductive system and its functions and processes. Reproductive health therefore implies that people are able to have a satisfying and safe sex life and that they have the capability to reproduce and the freedom to decide if, when and how often to do so. Implicit in this last condition are the right of men and women to be informed [about] and to have access to safe, effective, affordable and acceptable methods of family planning of their choice, as well as other methods of birth control which are not against the law, and the right of access to appropriate health-care services that will enable women to go safely through pregnancy and childbirth and provide couples with the best chance of having a healthy infant.&lt;ref&gt;ICPD Programme of Action, paragraph 7.2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This definition of the term is also echoed in the [https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/platform/health.htm United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women], or the so-called Beijing Declaration of 1995.&lt;ref&gt;The United Nations
Fourth World Conference on Women&lt;/ref&gt; However, the ICPD Program of Action, even though it received the support of a large majority of UN Member States, does not enjoy the status of an international legal instrument; it is therefore not legally binding.

The Program of Action endorses a new strategy which emphasizes the numerous linkages between population and development and focuses on meeting the needs of individual women and men rather than on achieving [[demographic targets]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=https://www.un.org/ecosocdev/geninfo/populatin/icpd.htm#intro |author=ICPD| title=ICPD Program of Action | accessdate=2009-02-04| authorlink=International Conference on Population and Development}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[International Conference on Population and Development|ICPD]]  achieved consensus on four qualitative and quantitative goals for the international community, the final two of which have particular relevance for reproductive health:

* '''Reduction of maternal mortality''': A reduction of [[maternal mortality]] rates and a narrowing of disparities in maternal mortality within countries and between geographical regions, socio-economic and ethnic groups.
* '''Access to reproductive and sexual health services including family planning''': [[Family planning]] counseling, pre-natal care, safe delivery and post-natal care, prevention and appropriate treatment of [[infertility]], prevention of [[abortion]] and the management of the consequences of abortion, treatment of reproductive tract infections, [[sexually transmitted diseases]] and other reproductive health conditions; and education, counseling, as appropriate, on human sexuality, reproductive health and responsible parenthood. Services regarding [[HIV]]/[[AIDS]], [[breast cancer]], infertility, delivery, [[hormone therapy]], [[sex reassignment therapy]], and abortion should be made available. Active discouragement of [[female genital cutting|female genital mutilation (FGM)]].

The keys to this new approach are empowering women, providing them with more choices through expanded access to education and health services, and promoting skill development and employment. The programme advocates making family planning universally available by 2015 or sooner, as part of a broadened approach to reproductive health and rights, provides estimates of the levels of national resources and international assistance that will be required, and calls on governments to make these resources available.

== Millennium Development Goals ==

Achieving universal access to reproductive health by 2015 is one of the two targets of ''Goal 5'' - ''Improving Maternal Health'' - of the eight [[Millennium Development Goals]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.mdgmonitor.org/goal5.cfm |author=UN| title=Tracking the Millennium Development Goals| accessdate=2008-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; To monitor global progress towards the achievement of this target, the [[United Nations]] has agreed on the following indicators:

* 5.3: contraceptive prevalence rate
* 5.4: adolescent birth rate
* 5.5: antenatal care coverage
* 5.6: unmet need for family planning

According to the MDG Progress Report, regional statistics on all four indicators have either improved or remained stable between the years 2000 and 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/millenniumgoals/pdf/The%20Millennium%20Development%20Goals%20Report%202008.pdf |author=UN |title=2008 MDG Progress Report |pages=28–29 |accessdate=2009-02-04 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090203222613/http://www.un.org/millenniumgoals/pdf/The%20Millennium%20Development%20Goals%20Report%202008.pdf |archivedate=2009-02-03 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, progress has been slow in most [[developing countries]], particularly in [[Sub-saharan Africa]], which remains the region with the poorest indicators for reproductive health.&lt;ref name=progressMDG5&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.who.int/making_pregnancy_safer/topics/mdg/en/index.html |author=WHO| title=What progress has been made on MDG 5? | accessdate=2009-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[WHO]] in 2005 an estimated 55% of women do not have sufficient antenatal care and 24% have no access to family planning services.&lt;ref name=progressMDG5 /&gt;

== Reproductive health and abortion ==

An article from the World Health Organization calls safe, legal abortion a "[[fundamental right]] of women, irrespective of where they live" and [[unsafe abortion]] a "silent [[pandemic]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/unsafe_abortion/ua_paper/en/index.html |title=WHO: Unsafe Abortion&amp;nbsp;— The Preventable Pandemic |accessdate=2010-01-16 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100113104553/http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/unsafe_abortion/ua_paper/en/index.html |archivedate=2010-01-13 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The article states "ending the silent pandemic of unsafe abortion is an urgent [[public health|public-health]] and [[human-rights]] imperative." It also states "access to safe abortion improves [[women’s health]], and vice versa, as documented in [[Romania]] during the regime of President [[Nicolae Ceaușescu]]" and "legalisation of abortion on request is a necessary but insufficient step toward improving women’s health" citing that in some countries, such as India where abortion has been legal for decades, access to competent care remains restricted because of other barriers. WHO’s Global Strategy on Reproductive Health, adopted by the World Health Assembly in May 2004, noted: “As a preventable cause of maternal mortality and morbidity, unsafe abortion must be dealt with as part of the MDG on improving maternal health and other international development goals and targets." &lt;ref name="who.int"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/topics/unsafe_abortion/hrpwork/en/index.html|title=WHO&amp;nbsp;— Preventing unsafe abortion|publisher=|accessdate=13 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The WHO's Development and Research Training in Human Reproduction (HRP), whose research concerns people's sexual and reproductive health and lives,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/hrp/en/|title=World Health Organization|publisher=|accessdate=13 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; has an overall strategy to combat unsafe abortion that comprises four inter-related activities:&lt;ref name="who.int"/&gt;

* to collate, synthesize and generate scientifically sound evidence on unsafe abortion prevalence and practices;
* to develop improved technologies and implement interventions to make abortion safer;
* to translate evidence into norms, tools and guidelines;
* and to assist in the development of programmes and policies that reduce unsafe abortion and improve access to safe abortion and high quality post-abortion care

During and after the ICPD, some interested parties attempted to interpret the term ‘reproductive health’ in the sense that it implies abortion as a means of family planning or, indeed, a right to abortion. These interpretations, however, do not reflect the consensus reached at the Conference.
For the European Union, where legislation on abortion is certainly less restrictive than elsewhere, the Council Presidency has clearly stated that the Council’s commitment to promote ‘reproductive health’ did not include the promotion of abortion.&lt;ref&gt;European Parliament, 4 December 2003: Oral Question (H-0794/03) for Question Time at the part-session in December 2003 pursuant to Rule 43 of the Rules of Procedure by Dana Scallon to the Council. In the written record of that session, one reads: Posselt (PPE-DE): "Does the term ‘reproductive health’ include the promotion of abortion, yes or no?" - Antonione, Council: "No."&lt;/ref&gt;  Likewise, the European Commission, in response to a question from a member of the European Parliament, clarified:

{{quotation|The term ‘reproductive health’ was defined by the United Nations (UN) in 1994 at the Cairo International Conference on Population and Development. All Member States of the Union endorsed the Programme of Action adopted at Cairo. The Union has never adopted an alternative definition of ‘reproductive health’ to that given in the Programme of Action, which makes no reference to abortion.&lt;ref&gt;European Parliament, 24 October 2002: Question no 86 by Dana Scallon (H-0670/02)&lt;/ref&gt;}}

With regard to the US, only a few days prior to the Cairo Conference, the head of the US delegation, Vice President Al Gore, had stated for the record: {{quotation|Let us get a false issue off the table: the US does not seek to establish a new international right to abortion, and we do not believe that abortion should be encouraged as a method of family planning.&lt;ref&gt;Jyoti Shankar Singh, Creating a New Consensus on Population (London: Earthscan, 1998), 60&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Some years later, the position of the US administration in this debate was reconfirmed by US Ambassador to the UN, Ellen Sauerbrey, when she stated at a meeting of the UN Commission on the Status of Women that: {{quotation|Nongovernmental organizations are attempting to assert that Beijing  in some way creates or contributes to the creation of an internationally recognized fundamental right to abortion.&lt;ref&gt;Lederer, AP/San Francisco Chronicle, 1 March 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;There is no fundamental right to abortion. And yet it keeps coming up largely driven by NGOs trying to hijack the term and trying to make it into a definition.&lt;ref&gt;Leopold, Reuters, 28 February 2005&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== See also ==

* [[Sexual intercourse#Health effects]]
* [[Abortion debate]]
* [[Demography]]
* [[List of bacterial vaginosis microbiota]]
* ICPD: [[International Conference on Population and Development]]
* [[POPLINE]]: World's largest reproductive health database
** [[The INFO Project]]
* [[Reproductive justice]]
* [[Obstetric transition]]
* [[Comprehensive sex education]] (CSE)
* Organizations:
** [[Association of Reproductive Health Professionals]]
** [[Centre for Development and Population Activities]]
** [[EngenderHealth]]
** [[Guttmacher Institute]]
** [[German Foundation for World Population]]
** [[International Planned Parenthood Federation]]
** [[Marie Stopes International]]
** [[Reproductive Health Supplies Coalition]]
** [[United Nations Population Fund]]

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commonscat|Sexual health}}
* [https://www.cdc.gov/reproductivehealth/DRH/ CDC Division of Reproductive Health]
* [http://www.emro.who.int/entity/rhrn/ WHO Reproductive health and research]

{{reproductive health}}

{{Human sexuality}}

{{Particular human rights}}

{{Public health}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Reproductive Health}}
[[Category:Population]]
[[Category:Sexual health| ]]
[[Category:Midwifery]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>