<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181122132154|870111738" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2159778" pageid="2159778" ns="0" title="Sexual and reproductive health"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-22T20:25:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Sexual health|the journal|International Journal of Sexual Health}}
[[File:Angolan community members at HIV AIDS outreach event (5686747785).jpg|thumb|300px|right|[[Public health]] education with regard to prevention of [[HIV/AIDS]] in an educational outreach session in [[Angola]].]]
Within the framework of the [[World Health Organization]]'s (WHO) definition of [[health]] as a state of complete physical, mental and social well-being, and not merely the absence of disease or infirmity, '''reproductive health''', or '''sexual health'''/'''hygiene''', addresses the reproductive processes, functions and system at all stages of life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/topics/reproductive_health/en/|title=WHO: Reproductive health|access-date=2008-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;  UN agencies claim, sexual and reproductive health includes physical, as well as psychological well-being vis-a-vis sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url = http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0026/002607/260770e.pdf | title = International technical guidance on sexuality education: an evidence-informed approach | publisher = UNESCO | year = 2018 | isbn = 978-92-3-100259-5 | location = Paris | pages = 22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reproductive health implies that people are able to have a responsible, satisfying and [[Safer sex|safer sex life]] and that they have the capability to reproduce and the [[Family planning|freedom to decide]] if, when and how often to do so. One interpretation of this implies that men and women ought to be [[sex education|informed]] of and to have access to safe, effective, affordable and acceptable methods of [[birth control]]; also access to appropriate [[reproductive medicine|health care services]] of [[sexual medicine|sexual]], [[reproductive medicine]] and implementation of health education programs to stress the importance of [[maternal health|women to go safely]] through [[pregnancy]] and [[childbirth]] could provide couples with the best chance of having a healthy infant.

Individuals do face inequalities in reproductive health services. Inequalities vary based on socioeconomic status, education level, age, ethnicity, religion, and resources available in their environment. It is possible for example, that low income individuals lack the resources for appropriate health services and the knowledge to know what is appropriate for maintaining reproductive health.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hall KS, Moreau C, Trussell J | title = Determinants of and disparities in reproductive health service use among adolescent and young adult women in the United States, 2002-2008 | journal = American Journal of Public Health | volume = 102 | issue = 2 | pages = 359–67 | date = February 2012 | pmid = 22390451 | pmc = 3483992 | doi = 10.2105/ajph.2011.300380 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reproductive health ==
The WHO assessed in 2008 that "Reproductive and sexual ill-health accounts for 20% of the global burden of ill-health for women, and 14% for men."&lt;ref name="WHOstrat2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/reproductive-health/strategy.htm|title=Reproductive Health Strategy|last=|first=|date=|website=|publisher=World Health Organization|archive-url=|archive-date=|dead-url=|access-date=2008-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reproductive health is a part of [[sexual and reproductive health and rights]]. According to the [[United Nations Population Fund]] (UNFPA), unmet needs for sexual and reproductive health deprive women of the right to make "crucial choices about their own bodies and futures", affecting family welfare. Women bear and usually nurture children, so their reproductive health is inseparable from gender equality. Denial of such rights also worsens poverty.&lt;ref name="SRH2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unfpa.org/sexual-reproductive-health|title=Sexual reproductive health|publisher=UN Population Fund}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Adolescent health ==
[[File:Teenage birth rate per 1000 women 15–19, 2000-09.svg|thumb|300px|Teenage birth rate per 1,000 females aged 15–19, 2000–2009&lt;ref name="ustats-births"&gt;[http://unstats.un.org/unsd/demographic/products/dyb/dyb2009-2010/Table10.pdf Live births by age of mother and sex of child, general and age-specific fertility rates: latest available year, 2000–2009]&amp;nbsp;— United Nations Statistics Division&amp;nbsp;– Demographic and Social Statistics&lt;/ref&gt;]]

{{Further|Teenage pregnancy|Adolescent sexuality}}
[[Adolescent health]] creates a major global burden and has a great deal of additional and diverse complications compared to adult reproductive health such as early pregnancy and parenting issues, difficulties accessing contraception and safe abortions, lack of healthcare access, and high rates of HIV and sexually transmitted infections, and mental health issues. Each of those can be affected by outside political, economic and socio-cultural influences.&lt;ref name="pmid26433504"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Morris JL, Rushwan H | title = Adolescent sexual and reproductive health: The global challenges | journal = International Journal of Gynaecology and Obstetrics | volume = 131 Suppl 1 | issue = | pages = S40–2 | date = October 2015 | pmid = 26433504 | doi = 10.1016/j.ijgo.2015.02.006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For most adolescent females, they have yet to complete their body growth trajectories, therefore adding a pregnancy exposes them to a predisposition to complications. These complications range from anemia, malaria, HIV and other STI's, postpartum bleeding and other postpartum complications, mental health disorders such as depression and suicidal thoughts or attempts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Maternal, newborn, child and adolescent health | url = http://www.who.int/maternal_child_adolescent/topics/maternal/adolescent_pregnancy/en/ | publisher = World Health Organization }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, adolescent birth rates between the ages of 15-19 was 44 per 1000, 1 in 3 experienced sexual violence, and there more than 1.2 million deaths. The top three leading causes of death in females between the ages of 15-19 are maternal conditions 10.1%, self-harm 9.6%, and road conditions 6.1%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Global Strategy for Women's, Children's and Adolescents' Health (2016-2030) Key Statistics | url = http://www.who.int/life-course/partners/global-strategy/global-strategy-key-statistics-03-11-2017.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The causes for teenage pregnancy are vast and diverse. In developing countries, young women are pressured to marry for different reasons. One reason is to bear children to help with work, another on a [[dowry system]] to increase the families income, another is due to prearranged marriages. These reasons tie back to financial needs of girls' family, cultural norms, religious beliefs and external conflicts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | chapter = Girl Child Marriage: A Persistent Global Women’s Health and Human Rights Violation | title = Global Perspectives on Women's Sexual and Reproductive Health Across the Lifecourse | last = Raj | first  = A nita | last2 = Jackson | first2 = Emma | last3 = Dunham | first3 = Serena | name-list-format = vanc | date = 2018| publisher = Springer, Cham | isbn = 9783319604169 | pages = 3–19 | doi=10.1007/978-3-319-60417-6_1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Adolescent pregnancy, especially in developing countries, carries increased health risks, and contributes to maintaining the [[cycle of poverty]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/adolescence/9789241502214/en/|title=Preventing early pregnancy and poor reproductive outcomes among adolescents in developing countries |publisher=World Health Organization|access-date=September 23, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The availability and type of [[sex education]]&lt;nowiki/&gt; for teenagers varies in different parts of the world. LGBT teens may suffer additional problems if they live in places where homosexual activity is socially disapproved and/or illegal; in extreme cases there can be depression, social isolation and even [[suicide among LGBT youth]].

== Maternal health ==
[[File:Maternal mortality rate worldwide.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Maternal Mortality Rate]] worldwide, as defined by the number of maternal deaths per 100,000 live births from any cause related to or aggravated by pregnancy or its management, excluding accidental or incidental causes.&lt;ref name=CIA2010&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/rankorder/2223rank.html?countryName=Australia&amp;countryCode=as&amp;regionCode=aus&amp;rank=156#as Country Comparison: Maternal Mortality Rate] in [[:en:The World Factbook|The CIA World Factbook]]. Date of Information: 2010&lt;/ref&gt;]]
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Projections of MMR and maternal deaths for 2030.gif|link=https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Projections_of_MMR_and_maternal_deaths_for_2030.gif|thumb|Projections of maternal deaths for 2030.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/adolescence/9789241502214/en/ | publisher = WHO | title = Preventing early pregnancy and poor reproductive outcomes among adolescents in developing countries |access-date=2018-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[maternal health]]]] --&gt;
Ninety nine percent of maternal deaths occur in developing countries and in 25 years, maternal mortality globally dropped to 44%.&lt;ref name="WHO_Maternal_mortality"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.who.int/en/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/maternal-mortality|title=Maternal mortality|website=World Health Organization |access-date=2018-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Statistically, a woman’s chance of survival during childbirth is closely tied to her social economic status, access to healthcare, where she lives geographically, and cultural norms.&lt;ref name="Alkema_2016"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Alkema L, Chou D, Hogan D, Zhang S, Moller AB, Gemmill A, Fat DM, Boerma T, Temmerman M, Mathers C, Say L | title = Global, regional, and national levels and trends in maternal mortality between 1990 and 2015, with scenario-based projections to 2030: a systematic analysis by the UN Maternal Mortality Estimation Inter-Agency Group | journal = Lancet | volume = 387 | issue = 10017 | pages = 462–74 | date = January 2016 | pmid = 26584737 | pmc = 5515236 | doi = 10.1016/S0140-6736(15)00838-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; To compare, a woman dies of complications from childbirth every minute in developing countries versus a total of 1% of total maternal mortality deaths in developed countries. Women in developing countries have little access to family planning services, different cultural practices, have lack of information, birthing attendants, prenatal care, birth control, postnatal care, lack of access to health care and are typically in poverty. In 2015, those in low-income countries had access to antenatal care visits averaged to 40% and were preventable.&lt;ref name="WHO_Maternal_mortality" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Alkema_2016" /&gt; All these reasons lead to an increase in the [[Maternal Mortality Ratio|Maternal Mortality Ratio (MMR)]].

One of the international [[Sustainable Development Goals]] developed by [[The UN|United Nation]]s is to improve maternal health by a targeted 70 deaths per 100,000 live births by 2030.&lt;ref name="Alkema_2016" /&gt; Most models of maternal health encompass family planning, preconception, prenatal, and postnatal care. All care after childbirth recovery is typically excluded, which includes [[Premenopause|pre-menopause]] and aging into old age.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.unfpa.org/maternal-health|title=Maternal health|website=www.unfpa.org|language=en|access-date=2018-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;  During childbirth, women typically die from severe bleeding, infections, high blood pressure during pregnancy, delivery complications, or an unsafe abortion. Other reasons can be regional such as complications related to diseases such as malaria and AIDS during pregnancy.  The younger the women is when she gives birth, the more at risk her and her baby is for complications and possibly mortality.&lt;ref name="WHO_Maternal_mortality" /&gt;

== Contraception ==
[[File:Pilule_contraceptive.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Combined oral contraceptive pill]]]]

Access to reproductive health services is very poor in many countries. Women are often unable to access [[maternal health]] services due to lack of knowledge about the existence of such services or lack of [[freedom of movement]]. Some women are subjected to [[forced pregnancy]] and banned from leaving the home. In many countries, women are not allowed to leave home without a male relative or husband, and therefore their ability to access medical services is limited. Therefore, increasing women's autonomy is needed in order to improve reproductive health, however doing may require a cultural shift. According to the WHO, "All women need access to antenatal care in pregnancy, skilled care during childbirth, and care and support in the weeks after childbirth".

The fact that the law allows certain reproductive health services, it does not necessary ensure that such services are ''de facto'' available to people. The availability of contraception, sterilization and abortion is dependent on laws, as well as social, cultural and religious norms. Some countries have liberal laws regarding these issues, but in practice it is very difficult to access such services due to doctors, pharmacists and other social and medical workers being [[conscientious objector]]s.

In developing regions of the world, there are about 214 million women who want to avoid pregnancy but are unable to use safe and effective [[family planning]] methods.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.unfpa.org/family-planning | title=Family planning}}&lt;/ref&gt; When taken correctly, the [[combined oral contraceptive pill]] is over 99% effective at preventing pregnancy. However, it does not protect from [[sexually transmitted infection]]s (STIs). Some methods, such as using [[condom]]s, achieve both protection from STIs and unwanted pregnancies. There are also [[natural family planning]] methods, which may be preferred by religious people, but some very conservative religious groups, such as the [[Quiverfull]] movement, oppose these methods too, because they advocate the maximization of procreation. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | url=https://www.thenation.com/article/arrows-war/ | title=Arrows for the War| journal=The Nation| date=2006-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.lifesitenews.com/news/protestant-group-advocates-leaving-fertility-in-gods-hands-no-birth-control | title=Protestant Group Advocates Leaving Fertility in God's Hands - No Birth Control Artificial or Natural}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the oldest ways to reduce unwanted  pregnancy  is [[coitus interruptus]] - still widely used in the developing world.

There are many types of contraceptives. One type of contraceptive includes barrier methods.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nichd.nih.gov/health/topics/contraception/conditioninfo/types|title=What are the different types of contraception?|website=http://www.nichd.nih.gov/|language=en|access-date=2018-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; One barrier method includes condoms for males and females.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nichd.nih.gov/health/topics/contraception/conditioninfo/types|title=What are the different types of contraception?|website=http://www.nichd.nih.gov/|language=en|access-date=2018-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both types stop sperm from entering the woman’s uterus, thereby preventing pregnancy from occurring.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nichd.nih.gov/health/topics/contraception/conditioninfo/types|title=What are the different types of contraception?|website=http://www.nichd.nih.gov/|language=en|access-date=2018-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another type of contraception is the birth control pill, which stops ovulation from occurring by combining the chemicals progestin and estrogen.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nichd.nih.gov/health/topics/contraception/conditioninfo/types|title=What are the different types of contraception?|website=http://www.nichd.nih.gov/|language=en|access-date=2018-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many women use this method of contraception, however they discontinue using it equally as much as they use it.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stevens|first=Lindsay|date=September 2018|title='We Have to Be Mythbusters': Clinician Attitudes about the Legitimacy of Patient Concerns and Dissatisfaction with Contraception.|url=|journal=Social Science &amp; Medicine|volume=212|pages=145–152|via=EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt; One reason for this is because of the side effects that occur from using the pill. Some side effects that result from birth control pill usage include minor side effects such as increased BMI and frequent headaches, and major side effects like dangerous blood pressure levels.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stevens|first=Lindsay|date=September 2018|title='We Have to Be Mythbusters': Clinician Attitudes about the Legitimacy of Patient Concerns and Dissatisfaction with Contraception.|url=|journal=Social Science &amp; Medicine|volume=212|pages=145–152|via=EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another reason stems from health care providers not taking women’s concerns about negative side effects seriously.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stevens|first=Lindsay|date=September 2018|title='We Have to Be Mythbusters': Clinician Attitudes about the Legitimacy of Patient Concerns and Dissatisfaction with Contraception.|url=|journal=Social Science &amp; Medicine|volume=212|pages=145–152|via=EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt; When women report negative side effects to their physicians, they are told to continue using the pill.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stevens|first=Lindsay|date=September 2018|title='We Have to Be Mythbusters': Clinician Attitudes about the Legitimacy of Patient Concerns and Dissatisfaction with Contraception.|url=|journal=Social Science &amp; Medicine|volume=212|pages=145–152|via=EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt; This causes women to dedicate more thought towards which side effects can be accepted rather than how to stop side effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stevens|first=Lindsay|date=September 2018|title='We Have to Be Mythbusters': Clinician Attitudes about the Legitimacy of Patient Concerns and Dissatisfaction with Contraception.|url=|journal=Social Science &amp; Medicine|volume=212|pages=145–152|via=EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are many objections to the use of birth control. One argument against birth control usage states there is no need for birth control to begin with.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McAndrews|first=Lawrence|date=Winter 2015|title=Before Roe: Catholics, Nixon, and the Changing Politics of Birth Control.|url=|journal=Fides et Historia|volume=47|pages=24–43|via=EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt; This argument was levied in 1968 when Richard Nixon was elected president, and the argument stated that since birth rates were at their lowest point since World War II ended, birth control was not necessary.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McAndrews|first=Lawrence|date=Winter 2015|title=Before Roe: Catholics, Nixon, and the Changing Politics of Birth Control.|url=|journal=Fides et Historia|volume=47|pages=24–43|via=EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another argument states that women should use natural methods of contraception in place of artificial ones, such as having sexual intercourse when one is infertile.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McAndrews|first=Lawrence|date=Winter 2015|title=Before Roe: Catholics, Nixon, and the Changing Politics of Birth Control.|url=|journal=Fides et Historia|volume=47|pages=24–43|via=EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another natural method encouraged by the Catholic Church is abstinence from sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McAndrews|first=Lawrence|date=Winter 2015|title=Before Roe: Catholics, Nixon, and the Changing Politics of Birth Control.|url=|journal=Fides et Historia|volume=47|pages=24–43|via=EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt; This argument was written out in ''Humanae Vitae'', a papal encyclical released in 1968.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McAndrews|first=Lawrence|date=Winter 2015|title=Before Roe: Catholics, Nixon, and the Changing Politics of Birth Control.|url=|journal=Fides et Historia|volume=47|pages=24–43|via=EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Catholic Church bases its argument against birth control pills on the basis that birth control pills undermine the natural law of God.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Reiterman|first=Carl|date=1965|title=Birth Control and Catholics.|journal=Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion|volume=4|pages=213–233|jstor=1384139}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Catholic Church also argues against birth control on the basis of family size, with Cardinal Mercier of Belgium arguing,  "...the duties of conscience are above worldly considerations, and besides, it is the large families who are the best" (Reiterman, 216).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Reiterman|first=Carl|date=1965|title=Birth Control and Catholics.|journal=Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion|volume=4|pages=213–233|jstor=1384139}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, another argument against birth control stems from fear in the African-American community that Caucasians plan to significantly reduce their population.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Caron|first=Simone|date=22 March 1998|title=Birth Control and the Black Community in the 1960s: Genocide or Power Politics?|url=|journal=Journal of Social History|volume=31|pages=545–569|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; This fear reached a high point in the 1960s, as birth control clinics were constructed in mainly African-American areas.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Caron|first=Simone|date=22 March 1998|title=Birth Control and the Black Community in the 1960s: Genocide or Power Politics?|url=|journal=Journal of Social History|volume=31|pages=545–569|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fear of decimated African-American communities is a result of slavery and the disproportionate castration of African-Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Caron|first=Simone|date=22 March 1998|title=Birth Control and the Black Community in the 1960s: Genocide or Power Politics?|url=|journal=Journal of Social History|volume=31|pages=545–569|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Sexually transmitted infection ==
[[File:AIDS and HIV prevalence 2008.svg|thumb|upright=1.2|alt= A map of the world where most of the land is colored green or yellow except for sub Saharan Africa which is colored red|Estimated [[prevalence]] in % of HIV among young adults (15–49) per country as of 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=AIDSinfo |url=http://www.unaids.org/en/dataanalysis/datatools/aidsinfo/ |work=UNAIDS |access-date=4 March 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break}}

{{legend|#787878|&lt;small&gt;No data&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{legend|#94bf8b|&lt;small&gt;&lt;0.10&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{legend|#f4e2ba|&lt;small&gt;0.10–0.5&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{legend|#eaca83|&lt;small&gt;0.5–1&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{Col-break}}

{{legend|#f07568|&lt;small&gt;1–5&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{legend|#ff4800|&lt;small&gt;5–15&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{legend|#b00000|&lt;small&gt;15–50&lt;/small&gt;}}

{{col-end}}]]
[[File:Syphilis_world_map-Deaths_per_million_persons-WHO2012.svg|thumb|200px|left|Deaths from [[syphilis]] in 2012 per million persons]]
[[File:Kondom.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Condom]]s offer effective protection from STIs]]
{{Main|Sexually transmitted infection}}

A [[Sexually transmitted infection]] (STI) --previously known as a ''sexually transmitted disease (STD)'' or ''venereal disease (VD)--'' is an infection that has a significant likelihood of transmission between humans by means of [[sexual activity]]. The CDC analyses the eight most common STI's: [[Chlamydia trachomatis|chlamydia]], [[gonorrhea]], [[Hepatitis B virus|hepatitis B viru]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s (HBV), [[herpes simplex virus]] type 2 ([[Hsv 2|HSV-2]]), human immunodeficiency virus ([[HIV/AIDS|HIV]]), [[Human papillomavirus HPV|human papillomavirus (HPV)]], [[syphilis]], and [[trichomoniasis]].&lt;ref name="CDC_2013"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cdc.gov/std/stats/sti-estimates-fact-sheet-Feb-2013.pdf | title= Incidence, Prevalence, and Cost of Sexually Transmitted Infections in the United States | date = February 2013 | work = CDC STI Fact Sheet | publisher = United States Centers for Disease Control (CDC) }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are more than 600 million cases of STI's worldwide and more than 20 million new cases within the United States.&lt;ref name="CDC_2013" /&gt; Numbers of such high magnitude weigh a heavy burden on the local and global economy. A study&lt;ref name="Shah_2016"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Shah M, Risher K, Berry SA, Dowdy DW | title = The Epidemiologic and Economic Impact of Improving HIV Testing, Linkage, and Retention in Care in the United States | journal = Clinical Infectious Diseases | volume = 62 | issue = 2 | pages = 220–229 | date = January 2016 | pmid = 26362321 | pmc = 4690480 | doi = 10.1093/cid/civ801 | url = https://doi.org/10.1093/cid/civ801 }}&lt;/ref&gt; conducted at Oxford University in 2015 concluded that despite giving participants early antiviral medications [[Antiretroviral therapy|(ART)]], they still cost an estimated $256 billion over 2 decades. HIV testing done at modest rates could reduce HIV infections by 21%, HIV retention by 54% and HIV mortality rates by 64%, with a cost-effectiveness ration of $45,300 per [[Quality-adjusted life year]]. However, the study concluded that the United States has led to an excess in infections, treatment costs, and deaths, even when interventions do not improve over all survival rates.&lt;ref name="Shah_2016" /&gt;

There is a profound reduction on STI rates once those who are sexually active are educated about transmissions, condom promotion, interventions targeted at key and vulnerable populations through a comprehensive [[Sex education]] courses or programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.who.int/en/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/sexually-transmitted-infections-(stis)|title=Sexually transmitted infections (STIs)|website=World Health Organization |access-date=2018-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Africa’s policy addresses the needs of women at risk for HIV and who are HIV positive as well as their partners and children. The policy also promotes screening activities related to sexual health such as HIV counseling and testing as well as testing for other STIs, tuberculosis, cervical cancer, and breast cancer.&lt;ref name = "RSA_2014"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Department of Health, Republic of South Africa | year = 2014 | title = Bookshelf: National Contraception and Fertility Planning Policy and Service Delivery Guidelines | journal = Reproductive Health Matters | volume = 22 | issue = 43 | pages = 200–203 | doi = 10.1016/S0968-8080(14)43764-9 | jstor = 43288351 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Young African American women are at a higher risk for STI's, including HIV.&lt;ref name="Painter_2012"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Painter JE, Wingood GM, DiClemente RJ, Depadilla LM, Simpson-Robinson L | title = College graduation reduces vulnerability to STIs/HIV among African-American young adult women | journal = Women's Health Issues | volume = 22 | issue = 3 | pages = e303–10 | date = 2012-05-01 | pmid = 22555218 | pmc = 3349441 | doi = 10.1016/j.whi.2012.03.001 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A recent study published outside of Atlanta, Georgia collected data (demographic, psychological, and behavioral measures) with a vaginal swab to confirm the presence of STIs. They found a profound difference that those women who had graduated from college were far less likely to have STIs, potentially be benefiting from a reduction in vulnerability to acquiring STIs/HIV as they gain in education status and potentially move up in demographic areas and/or status.&lt;ref name="Painter_2012" /&gt;

== Abortion ==
Globally, an estimated 25 million [[unsafe abortion]]s occur each year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.who.int/news-room/detail/28-09-2017-worldwide-an-estimated-25-million-unsafe-abortions-occur-each-year | title=Worldwide, an estimated 25 million unsafe abortions occur each year}}&lt;/ref&gt; The vast majority of such unsafe abortions occur in developing countries in Africa, Asia and Latin America.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.who.int/news-room/detail/28-09-2017-worldwide-an-estimated-25-million-unsafe-abortions-occur-each-year | title=Worldwide, an estimated 25 million unsafe abortions occur each year}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[abortion debate]] is the ongoing controversy surrounding the moral, legal, and religious status of induced [[abortion]].&lt;ref&gt;Groome, Thomas.  [https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/27/opinion/to-win-again-democrats-must-stop-being-the-abortion-party.html “To Win Again, Democrats Must Stop Being the Abortion Party.”] ''The New York Times''. March 27, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; The sides involved in the debate are the self-described “[[Abortion-rights movements|pro-choice]]” and “[[Anti-abortion movements|pro-life]]” movements. “Pro-choice” emphasizes the right of women to decide whether to terminate a pregnancy. “Pro-life” emphasizes the right of the embryo or fetus to gestate to term and be born. Both terms are considered [[loaded word|loaded]] in mainstream media, where terms such as “abortion rights” or “anti-abortion” are generally preferred.&lt;ref&gt;For example: {{cite news|title=Wall Street Journal style guide: Vol. 23, No. 1|url=https://blogs.wsj.com/styleandsubstance/2010/01/31/vol-23-no-1/|publisher=Wall Street Journal|accessdate=4 November 2011|date=January 31, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each movement has, with varying results, sought to influence public opinion and to attain legal support for its position, with small numbers of anti-abortion advocates using [[anti-abortion violence|violence]], such as murder and arson.

Articles from the World Health Organization call legal [[abortion]] a [[Fundamental rights|fundamental right]] of women regardless of where they live, and argue that [[unsafe abortion]] is a silent [[pandemic]]. In 2005, it was estimated that 19-20 million abortions had complications, some complications are permanent, while another estimated 68,000 women died from unsafe abortions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/unsafe_abortion/ua_paper/en/index.html |title=WHO: Unsafe Abortion&amp;nbsp;— The Preventable Pandemic |access-date=2010-01-16 |deadurl=yes |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100113104553/http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/unsafe_abortion/ua_paper/en/index.html |archive-date=2010-01-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Having access to safe abortion can have positive impacts on women's health and life, and vice versa. "Legislation of abortion on request is necessary but an insufficient step towards improving women's health.&lt;ref name="who.int"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/topics/unsafe_abortion/hrpwork/en/index.html | title = Preventing unsafe abortion | publisher = World Health Organization |access-date=13 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some countries where it abortion is legal, and has been for decades, there has been no improvement in access to adequate services making abortion unsafe due to lack of healthcare services. It is hard to get an abortion due to legal and policy barriers, social and cultural barriers (gender discrimination, poverty, religious restrictions, lack of support etc., health system barriers (lack of facilities or trained personnel), however safe abortions with trained personnel, good social support, and access to facilities, can improve maternal health and increase reproductive health later in life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Finer L, Fine JB | title = Abortion law around the world: progress and pushback | journal = American Journal of Public Health | volume = 103 | issue = 4 | pages = 585–9 | date = April 2013 | pmid = 23409915 | pmc = 3673257 | doi = 10.2105/AJPH.2012.301197 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Maputo Protocol]], which was adopted by the [[African Union]] in the form of a protocol to the [[African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights]], states at  Article 14 (Health and Reproductive Rights) that: "(2). States Parties shall take all appropriate measures to: [...] c) protect the reproductive rights of women by authorising medical abortion in cases of sexual assault, rape, incest, and where the continued pregnancy endangers the mental and physical health of the mother or the life of the mother or the foetus." &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.achpr.org/instruments/women-protocol/#14 | title=Protocol to the African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights on the Rights of Women in Africa / Legal Instruments / ACHPR}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Maputo Protocol is the first international treaty to recognize abortion, under certain conditions, as a woman's human right.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.achpr.org/instruments/general-comment-two-rights-women/ | title=General Comment No. 2 on Article 14.1 (a), (b), (c) and (f) and Article 14. 2 (a) and (c) of the Protocol to the African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights on the Rights of Women in Africa / Legal Instruments / ACHPR}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The  ''General comment No. 36 (2018) on article 6 of the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]], on the right to life'', adopted by the [[Human Rights Committee]] in 2018, defines, for the first time ever, a human right to abortion - in certain circumstances (however these UN general comments are considered [[soft law]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/un-human-rights-treaty-bodies/general-comments-of-the-human-rights-committee-and-their-legitimacy/EF8328BB5B2B3EC932E44C45E192EB9B | title=General Comments of the Human Rights Committee and their legitimacy| date=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, as such, not legally binding).

&lt;blockquote&gt;"Although   States   parties   may  adopt measures designed to regulate voluntary terminations of pregnancy, such measures must not result in violation of the right to life of a pregnant woman or girl, or her other rights under the Covenant. Thus, restrictions on the ability of women or girls to seek abortion must not, inter alia, jeopardize their lives, subject them  to  physical  or  mental  pain  or  suffering  which violates  article  7,  discriminate  against them  or  arbitrarily  interfere  with  their  privacy.  ''States  parties  must  provide  safe,  legal  and effective  access  to  abortion where  the  life  and  health  of  the  pregnant  woman  or girl  is  at risk,  and  where  carrying a pregnancy to term  would cause  the  pregnant  woman  or  girl substantial  pain  or  suffering,  most  notably  where  the  pregnancy  is  the  result  of  rape  or incest or is not viable.'' [8] In addition, States parties may not regulate pregnancy or abortion in all other cases in a manner that runs contrary to their duty to ensure that women and girls do  not  have  to  undertake  unsafe  abortions,  and  they should  revise  their  abortion  laws accordingly.  [9]  For  example,  they  should  not  take measures  such  as  criminalizing pregnancies  by  unmarried  women  or  apply  criminal  sanctions  against  women  and  girls undergoing  abortion  [10]  or  against  medical  service providers  assisting  them  in  doing  so, since  taking  such  measures  compel  women  and  girls  to  resort  to  unsafe  abortion.  States parties should not introduce new barriers and should remove existing barriers [11] that deny effective  access  by  women  and  girls  to  safe  and  legal  abortion  [12],  including  barriers caused  as  a  result  of  the  exercise  of  conscientious objection  by  individual  medical providers. [13]"&lt;ref&gt;https://tbinternet.ohchr.org/Treaties/CCPR/Shared%20Documents/1_Global/CCPR_C_GC_36_8785_E.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

When negotiating the Cairo Programme of Action at the 1994 [[International Conference on Population and Development]] (ICPD), the issue was so contentious that delegates eventually decided to omit any recommendation to legalize abortion, instead advising governments to provide proper post-abortion care and to invest in programs that will decrease the number of unwanted pregnancies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Reproductive Rights in a Global Context |last= Knudsen |first=Lara |authorlink= |year=2006 |publisher= Vanderbilt University Press |location= |isbn=978-0-8265-1528-5 |page=6 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=b3thCcdyScsC&amp;dq=reproductive+rights }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women]] considers the criminalization of abortion a "violations of women’s sexual and reproductive health and rights" and a form of "gender based violence"; paragraph 18 of its ''General recommendation No. 35 on gender based violence against women, updating general recommendation No. 19'' states that: "Violations of women’s sexual and reproductive health and rights, such as forced sterilizations, forced abortion, forced pregnancy, criminalisation of abortion, denial or delay of  safe  abortion  and  post abortion  care,  forced  continuation  of pregnancy,  abuse  and mistreatment  of  women  and  girls  seeking  sexual  and  reproductive  health  information, goods and services, are forms of [[violence against women|gender based violence]] that, depending on   the circumstances, may amount to torture or cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment."&lt;ref name="tbinternet.ohchr.org"&gt;http://tbinternet.ohchr.org/Treaties/CEDAW/Shared%20Documents/1_Global/CEDAW_C_GC_35_8267_E.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The same ''General Recommendation'' also urges countries at paragraph 31 to [...] In particular, repeal:
a) Provisions  that  allow,  tolerate  or  condone  forms  of  gender based  violence against women, including [...] legislation  that  criminalises  abortion".&lt;ref name="tbinternet.ohchr.org"/&gt;

In 2008, the [[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe]], a group comprising members from 47 European countries, has adopted a resolution calling for the decriminalization of abortion within reasonable gestational limits and guaranteed access to safe abortion procedures. The nonbinding resolution was passed on April 16 by a vote of 102 to 69.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.guttmacher.org/article/2008/04/council-europe-urges-member-states-decriminalize-abortion | title=Council of Europe Urges Member States to Decriminalize Abortion| date=2008-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Accesses to abortion is not only a question of legality, but also an issue of overcoming de ''facto barriers'', such as [[conscientious objection]]s from medical stuff, high prices, lack of knowledge about the law, lack of access to medical care (especially in [[rural areas]]). The ''de facto'' inability of women to access abortion even in countries where it is legal is highly controversial because it results in a situation where women have rights only on paper not in practice; the UN in its 2017 resolution on ''Intensification of efforts to prevent and eliminate all forms of violence against women and girls: domestic violence'' urged states to guarantee access to "safe abortion where such services are permitted by national law".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.un.org/en/ga/search/view_doc.asp?symbol=A/RES/71/170 | title=United Nations Official Document}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At a global level, the region with the strictest abortion laws is considered to be [[Latin America]] (see [[Reproductive rights in Latin America]]), a region strongly influenced by the [[Catholic Church in Latin America]].

== Female genital mutilation ==
{{Main|Female genital mutilation}}
[[File:FGM prevalence UNICEF 2013.svg|right|thumb|250px|Prevalence of FGM by country, according to a 2013 UNICEF report&lt;ref name=childinfo&gt;{{cite web|title=Prevalence of FGM/C | url = http://data.unicef.org/child-protection/fgmc | publisher = UNICEF | access-date = 18 August 2014 | dead-url = yes | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150715233215/http://data.unicef.org/child-protection/fgmc | archive-date = 15 July 2015 | date = 2014-07-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:FGM road sign, Bakau, Gambia, 2005.jpg|thumb|250 px|left|Anti-FGM road sign, Bakau, Gambia, 2005]]

Female genital mutilation (FGM) or female genital circumcision or cutting is most commonly known as the complete or partial removal of the external female genitalia or other injury to female genital organs for a non-medical reason. This is mostly practiced in around 30 countries and affecting around 160 million women and girls, globally, and between 500,000 and 515,000 in the United States. The most severe form of FGM, [[infibulation]], is practiced mostly in the north-eastern region of Africa in Djibouti, Eritrea, Ethiopia, Somalia, and Sudan.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/topics/fgm/prevalence/en/ | title=WHO &amp;#124; Female genital mutilation (FGM)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are four types:

*[[Clitoridectomy|Cliteridectomy]]:  partial or total removal of the clitoris (a small, sensitive and erectile part of the female genitals) and/or in very rare cases only, the prepuce (the fold of skin surrounding the clitoris).
*Excision: partial or total removal of the clitoris and the labia minora, with or without excision of the labia majora (the labia are the ‘lips’ that surround the vagina).
*Infibulation:  narrowing of the vaginal opening through the creation of a covering seal. The seal is formed by cutting and re-positioning the inner, or outer, labia, with or without removal of the clitoris.
*Other: all other harmful procedures to the female genitalia for non-medical purposes (piercing, scraping, cauterizing of the genital area)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/77428/WHO_RHR_12.41_eng.pdf?sequence=1|title=Female Genital Mutilation|last=Staff|date=|website=WHO|archive-url=|archive-date=|dead-url=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are no health benefits of FGM, as it interferes with the natural functions of a woman's and girls' bodies, such as causing severe pain, shock, hemorrhage, tetanus or sepsis (bacterial infection), urine retention, open sores in the genital region and injury to nearby genital tissue, recurrent bladder and urinary tract infections, cysts, increased risk of infertility, childbirth complications and newborn deaths. Sexual problems are 1.5 more likely to occur in women who have undergone FGM, they may experience painful intercourse, have less sexual satisfaction, and be two times more likely to report lack of sexual desire. In addition, the maternal and fetal death rate is significantly higher due to childbirth complications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Martin|first=Caroline | name-list-format = vanc | title = The psychological impact of Female Genital Mutilation/Cutting (FGM/C) on girls/women's mental health: a narrative literature review | journal = Journal of Reproductive and Infant Psychology | date = 19 September 2014 | volume = 32 | issue = 5 | pages = 469–485 | doi = 10.1080/02646838.2014.949641 |url=http://researchrepository.napier.ac.uk/id/eprint/8928 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The psychological effects of FGM  can cause severe trauma throughout women's lives. These psychological problems include depression, anxiety, post-traumatic stress disorder, low self-esteem.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/female-genital-mutilation | title=Female genital mutilation}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other women identified with socio-cultural differences in the meaning of "consequences".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=How to Avoid Stretch Marks After Weight Loss|year=2018|publisher=Health4sure|location=Cardiff, United Kingdom|url=https://www.boredpanda.com/how-to-avoid-stretch-marks-after-weight-loss/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence|Istanbul Convention]] prohibits FGM (Article 38).&lt;ref&gt;https://rm.coe.int/168046031c&lt;/ref&gt;

==Child and forced marriage==
{{Main|Child marriage|Forced marriage}}
[[File:Girl_Summit_-_22nd_July_in_London_(14498368279).jpg|thumb|250px|Poster against child and forced marriage]]
The practice of forcing young girls into early marriage, common in many parts of the world, is threatening their reproductive health. According to the World Health Organization:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/Life-stages/sexual-and-reproductive-health/news/news/2012/12/child-marriage-a-threat-to-health | title=Child marriage – a threat to health| date=2012-12-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;"The sexual and reproductive health of the female in a child marriage is likely to be jeopardized, as these young girls are often forced into sexual intercourse with an older male spouse with more sexual experience. The female spouse often lacks the status and the knowledge to negotiate for safe sex and contraceptive practices, increasing the risk of acquiring HIV or other sexually transmitted infections, as well as the probability of pregnancy at an early age." &lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Niger]] has the highest prevalence of child marriage under 18 in the world, while [[Bangladesh]]  has the highest rate of marriage of girls under age 15.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.unicef.org/media/files/Child_Marriage_Report_7_17_LR..pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Practices such as [[bride price]] and [[dowry]] can contribute to child and forced marriages.

== International Conference on Population and Development, 1994 ==
The [[International Conference on Population and Development]] (ICPD) was held in [[Cairo]], Egypt, from 5 to 13 September 1994. Delegations from 179 States took part in negotiations to finalize a Programme of Action on population and development for the next 20 years. Some 20,000 delegates from various governments, [[UN]] agencies, [[NGOs]], and the [[Mass media|media]] gathered for a discussion of a variety of population issues, including [[immigration]], [[infant mortality]], [[birth control]], [[family planning]], and the education of women.

In the ICPD Program of Action,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.un.org/ecosocdev/geninfo/populatin/icpd.htm#intro ICPD Program of Action]&lt;/ref&gt; 'reproductive health' is defined as:

&lt;blockquote&gt;a state of complete physical, mental and social well-being and...not merely the absence of disease or infirmity, in all matters relating to the reproductive system and its functions and processes. Reproductive health therefore implies that people are able to have a satisfying and safe sex life and that they have the capability to reproduce and the freedom to decide if, when and how often to do so. Implicit in this last condition are the right of men and women to be informed [about] and to have access to safe, effective, affordable and acceptable methods of family planning of their choice, as well as other methods of birth control which are not against the law, and the right of access to appropriate health-care services that will enable women to go safely through pregnancy and childbirth and provide couples with the best chance of having a healthy infant.&lt;ref&gt;ICPD Programme of Action, paragraph 7.2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This definition of the term is also echoed in the United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/platform/health.htm United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women]&lt;/ref&gt; or the so-called Beijing Declaration of 1995.&lt;ref&gt;The United Nations
Fourth World Conference on Women&lt;/ref&gt; However, the ICPD Program of Action, even though it received the support of a large majority of UN Member States, does not enjoy the status of an international legal instrument; it is therefore not legally binding.

The Program of Action endorses a new strategy which emphasizes the numerous linkages between population and development and focuses on meeting the needs of individual women and men rather than on achieving [[demographic targets]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=https://www.un.org/ecosocdev/geninfo/populatin/icpd.htm#intro |author=ICPD| title=ICPD Program of Action | access-date=2009-02-04| authorlink=International Conference on Population and Development}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[International Conference on Population and Development|ICPD]]  achieved consensus on four qualitative and quantitative goals for the international community, the final two of which have particular relevance for reproductive health:

* '''Reduction of maternal mortality''': A reduction of [[maternal mortality]] rates and a narrowing of disparities in maternal mortality within countries and between geographical regions, socio-economic and ethnic groups.
* '''Access to reproductive and sexual health services including family planning''': [[Family planning]] counseling, pre-natal care, safe delivery and post-natal care, prevention and appropriate treatment of [[infertility]], prevention of [[abortion]] and the management of the consequences of abortion, treatment of reproductive tract infections, [[sexually transmitted diseases]] and other reproductive health conditions; and education, counseling, as appropriate, on human sexuality, reproductive health and responsible parenthood. Services regarding [[HIV]]/[[AIDS]], [[breast cancer]], infertility, delivery, [[hormone therapy]], [[sex reassignment therapy]], and abortion should be made available. Active discouragement of [[female genital cutting|female genital mutilation (FGM)]].

The keys to this new approach are empowering women, providing them with more choices through expanded access to education and health services, and promoting skill development and employment. The programme advocates making family planning universally available by 2015 or sooner, as part of a broadened approach to reproductive health and rights, provides estimates of the levels of national resources and international assistance that will be required, and calls on governments to make these resources available.

== Sustainable Development Goals ==
Half of the development goals put on by the United Nations started in 2000 to 2015 with the [[Millennium Development Goals]] (MDGs). Reproductive health was Goal 5 out of 8. To monitor the progress, the UN agreed to four indicators:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/millenniumgoals/pdf/The%20Millennium%20Development%20Goals%20Report%202008.pdf|title=2008 MDG Progress Report|author=UN|pages=28–29|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090203222613/http://www.un.org/millenniumgoals/pdf/The%20Millennium%20Development%20Goals%20Report%202008.pdf|archive-date=2009-02-03|deadurl=yes|access-date=2009-02-04|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Contraceptive prevalence rates
*Adolescent birth rate
*Antenatal care coverage
*Unmet need for family planning

Progress was slow, and according to the [[WHO]] in 2005, about 55% of women did not have sufficient antenatal care and 24% had no access to family planning services.&lt;ref name="progressMDG52"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/making_pregnancy_safer/topics/mdg/en/index.html|title=What progress has been made on MDG 5?|author=WHO|access-date=2009-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; The MDGs expired in 2015 and were replaced with a more comprehensive set of goals to cover a span of 2016-2030 with a total of 17 goals, called the [[Sustainable Development Goals]]. All 17 goals are comprehensive in nature and build off one another, but goal 3 is "To ensure health lives and promote wellbeing for all at all ages". Specific goals are to reduce global maternal mortality ratio to less than 70 per 100,000 live births, end preventable deaths of newborns and children, reduce the number by 50% of accidental deaths globally, strengthen the treatment and prevention programs of substance abuse and alcohol.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.who.int/topics/sustainable-development-goals/targets/en/|title=Sustainable Development Goal 3: Health|website=World Health Organization|language=en-GB|access-date=2018-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==By region==
===Africa===
{{See|HIV/AIDS in Africa}}
[[File:Kenya2006- worldaidsday- contesto- COSV (3).jpg|thumb|200px|right|[[World AIDS Day]] 2006 event in [[Kenya]].]]
HIV/AIDS in Africa is a major public health problem. Sub-Saharan Africa is the worst affected world region for prevalence of HIV, especially among young women. 90% of the children in the world living with HIV are in sub-Saharan Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = HIV/AIDS | url = http://www.afro.who.int/health-topics/hivaids | publisher = World Health Organization Africa }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In most African countries, the total fertility rate is very high,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | chapter-url = https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/rankorder/2127rank.html | chapter = Country Comparison: Total Fertility Rate | title = The World Factbook | publisher = United States Central Intelligence Agency | year = 2017 | title-link = The World Factbook }}&lt;/ref&gt; often due to lack of access to contraception and family planning, and practices such as forced and child marriage. Niger, Angola, Mali, Burundi	and Somalia have very high fertility rates.

The updated contraceptive guidelines in [[South Africa]] attempt to improve access by providing special service delivery and access considerations for sex workers, lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender and intersex individuals, migrants, men, adolescents, women who are perimenopausal, have a disability, or chronic condition. They also aim to increase access to long acting contraceptive methods, particularly the copper IUD, and the introductions of single rod progestogen implant and combined oestrogen and progestogen injectables. The copper IUD has been provided significantly less frequently than other contraceptive methods but signs of an increase in most provinces were reported. The most frequently provided method was injectable progesterone, which the article acknowledged was not ideal and emphasised condom use with this method because it can can increase the risk of HIV: The product made up 49% of South Africa’s contraceptive use and up to 90% in some provinces.&lt;ref name="RSA_2014" /&gt;

[[Tanzania]]n provider perspectives address the obstacles to consistent contraceptive use in their communities. It was found that the capability of dispensaries to service patients was determined by inconsistent reproductive goals, low educational attainment, misconceptions about the side effects of contraceptives, and social factors such as gender dynamics, spousal dynamics, economic conditions, religious norms, cultural norms, and constraints in supply chains. A provider referenced and example of propaganda spread about the side effects of contraception: "There are influential people, for example elders and religious leaders. They normally convince people that condoms contain some microorganisms and contraceptive pills cause cancer". Another said that women often had pressure from their spouse or family that caused them to use birth control secretly or to discontinue use, and that women frequently preferred undetectable methods for this reason.  Access was also hindered as a result of a lack in properly trained medical personnel: "Shortage of the medical attendant...is a challenge, we are not able to attend to a big number of clients, also we do not have enough education which makes us unable to provide women with the methods they want". The majority of medical centers were staffed by people without medical training and few doctors and nurses, despite federal regulations, due to lack of resources. One center had only one person who was able to insert and remove implants, and without her they were unable to service people who wanted an implant inserted or removed. Another dispensary that carried two methods of birth control shared that they sometimes run out of both materials at the same time. Constraints in supply chains sometimes cause dispensaries to run out of contraceptive materials. Providers also claimed that more male involvement and education would be helpful.&lt;ref name="pmid27337850"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Baraka J, Rusibamayila A, Kalolella A, Baynes C | title = Challenges Addressing Unmet Need for Contraception: Voices of Family Planning Service Providers in Rural Tanzania | journal = African Journal of Reproductive Health | volume = 19 | issue = 4 | pages = 23–30 | date = December 2015 | pmid = 27337850 | doi =  | url = https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/7e2f/02d167efbda5c739175dc076ee82d56692a3.pdf | jstor = 24877606 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Public health officials, researchers, and programs can gain a more comprehensive picture of the barriers they face, and the efficacy of current approaches to family planning, by tracking specific, standardized family planning and reproductive health indicators.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.measureevaluation.org/prh/rh_indicators|title=Family Planning and Reproductive Health Indicators Database — MEASURE Evaluation|website=www.measureevaluation.org|language=en-us|access-date=2018-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{col div|colwidth=30em}}

* [[Sexual intercourse#Health effects]]
* [[Abortion debate]]
* [[Demography]]
* [[List of bacterial vaginosis microbiota]]
* ICPD: [[International Conference on Population and Development]]
* [[POPLINE]]: world's largest reproductive health database
** [[The INFO Project]]
* [[Reproductive justice]]
* [[Obstetric transition]]
* [[Comprehensive sex education]] (CSE)
* Organizations:
** [[Association of Reproductive Health Professionals]]
** [[EngenderHealth]]
** [[Guttmacher Institute]]
** [[German Foundation for World Population]]
** [[International Planned Parenthood Federation]]
** [[Marie Stopes International]]
** [[Reproductive Health Supplies Coalition]]
** [[United Nations Population Fund]]
** [[MEASURE Evaluation]]{{colend}}

== References ==
{{reflist|32em}}

== External links ==
{{Commonscat|Sexual health}}
* [https://www.cdc.gov/reproductivehealth/DRH/ CDC Division of Reproductive Health]
* [http://www.emro.who.int/entity/rhrn/ WHO Reproductive health and research]
*[https://www.measureevaluation.org/prh/rh_indicators MEASURE Evaluation Family Planning and Reproductive Health Indicators Database]

{{reproductive health}}
{{Sex}}
{{Particular human rights}}
{{Public health}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Reproductive Health}}
[[Category:Population]]
[[Category:Sexual health| ]]
[[Category:Midwifery]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>