<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131115020901|581711069" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="39498321" pageid="39498321" ns="0" title="Anti–Middle Eastern sentiment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-15T02:09:46Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Anti Middle Eastern sentiment''' is feelings and expression of hostility, hatred, [[discrimination]], or [[prejudice]] towards [[Middle East]] and its culture,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://academiccommons.columbia.edu/catalog/ac:124582 |title=Middle Eastern Americans and the First Amendment - Academic Commons |publisher=Academiccommons.columbia.edu |date= |accessdate=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; and towards persons based on their association with Middle East and Middle Eastern culture.

==America==
In 1993, the [[American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee]] confronted [[The Walt Disney Company]] about [[Anti-Arabism|anti-Arab]] [[Racism|racist]] content in its animated film ''[[Aladdin (1992 Disney film)|Aladdin]]''. At first Disney denied any problems but eventually relented and changed two lines in the opening song.&lt;ref name="adc"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adc.org/index.php?id=283|title=Arab Stereotypes and American Educators|publisher=[[American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee]]|accessdate=2007-03-16| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20070405005650/http://www.adc.org/index.php?id=283| archivedate= April 05 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Members of the ADC were still unhappy with the portrayal of Arabic characters and the referral to the Middle East as "[[Barbarian|barbaric]]".&lt;ref name="adc" /&gt; 

Hate crimes against people of [[Middle Eastern]] origin or descent increased from 354 attacks in 2000, to 1,501 attacks in 2001. Among the victims of the backlash was a Middle Eastern man in [[Houston]], [[Texas]] who was shot and wounded after an assailant accused him of "blowing up the [[country]]", and four immigrants shot and killed by a man named Larme Price, who confessed to killing them as revenge for the September 11 attacks. Mr. Price said he was motivated by a desire to kill people of Middle Eastern descent after the terror attacks of Sept.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"&gt;{{cite news|author= |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/31/nyregion/police-arrest-brooklyn-man-in-slayings-of-4-shopkeepers.html |title=Police Arrest Brooklyn Man In Slayings of 4 Shopkeepers - New York Times |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=2003-03-31 |accessdate=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Price described his victims as Arabs, only one was from an [[Arab country]]. This appears to be a trend; because of stereotypes of Arabs, several non-Arab, non-Muslim groups were subjected to attacks in the wake of 9/11, including several Sikh men attacked for wearing their religiously-mandated [[turban]].

One widely publicized incident was the murder of [[Balbir Singh Sodhi]]. The term Towelhead is a pejorative reference to Middle Eastern and Arab headdresses including turbans. It is mainly used to refer to both Arabs and Middle Eastern terrorists. Middle Eastern, Central Asian, South Asian, and Sikh turban wearers usually wind their turban anew for each wearing, using long strips of cloth. The cloth is usually five meters or less. However, some elaborate South Asian turbans may be permanently formed and sewn to a foundation. Turbans can be very large or quite modest dependent upon region, culture, and religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.middleeastexplorer.com/Turkey/Turban |title=Turban profile. Information about Turban. Asia culture and attractions |publisher=Middleeastexplorer.com |date= |accessdate=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mr. Price's mother, Leatha Price, said that her son's anger at Middle Easterners was a matter of mental illness, not ethnic hatred.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"/&gt;

America rebuilt and Americans came together after 9/11. In doing so, however, Islamophobia and anti-Middle Eastern sentiment imbedded itself into the American [[Bias#Other aspects|Psyche]]. Furthermore, America was put on high-alert. We had been attacked and we felt as though we may be attacked again at any moment. To this day, no one can sit in an airport, on a bus or subway, walk in a mall or be in any other public space without constantly being told to keep an eye out for “unattended bags” and “if we see something suspicious, report it.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thesuflyer.com/2013/04/23/boston-bombings-give-opportunity-to-reflect-on-american-ideals/ ]{{dead link|date=November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[US Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] brought charges against [[NCL America Inc.]], alleging that the company discriminated against seven crew members with Middle East backgrounds. The suit, filed on behalf of the employees, stated that the discrimination led to the plaintiffs losing their jobs aboard the cruise ship Pride of Aloha. The 2006 lawsuit had the company deny the allegations, refusing to accept that it had acted improperly in firing the seven Middle Eastern crew members. Sources stated that the two sides reached a settlement agreement, in which [[NCL America Inc.]] has agreed to pay $485,000 to resolve allegations. Additionally, the company also agreed to revise its policies to ensure a workplace that promotes equal employment opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lawyersandsettlements.com/settlements/11837/ncl-america-middle-eastern-discrimination.html |title=Cruise lines to pay $485,000 settlement in employment lawsuit |publisher=Lawyersandsettlements.com |date= |accessdate=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Saucedo Mercer]] interview with a conservative website quotes her as saying the primary goal of Middle Easterners “is to cause harm to the United States. So why do we want them here, either legally or illegally?”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.azpm.org/p/yv2012-us/2012/8/29/15220-candidate-criticized-for-anti-muslim-remarks/ |title=Candidate Criticized for Anti-Middle Eastern Remarks - Arizona Public Media |publisher=Azpm.org |date=2012-08-29 |accessdate=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview with a conservative website, [[Saucedo Mercer]] talked in depth about her views on [[immigration]]. A Mexican immigrant herself who became a U.S. citizen, she said the issue was important because people from places other than Mexico were among those coming across the border illegally. “That includes Chinese, Middle Easterners,” she said. “If you know Middle Easterners, a lot of them, they look [[Mexican people|Mexican]] or they look, you know, like a lot of people in South America, [[dark skin]], dark hair, [[brown eyes]]. And they mix. They mix in. “And those people, their only goal in life is to, to cause harm to the United States. So why do we want them here, either [[legally]] or illegally? When they come across the border, besides the [[Waste|trash]] that they leave behind, the [[drug smuggling]], the killings, the beheadings. I mean, you are seeing stuff. It’s a war out there.”&lt;ref name="tpmmuckraker.talkingpointsmemo.com"&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://tpmmuckraker.talkingpointsmemo.com/2012/08/gabriela_saucedo_mercer_middle_easterners.php |title=Gabriela Saucedo Mercer: We don’t want Middle Easterners in U.S. &amp;#124; TPMMuckraker |publisher=Tpmmuckraker.talkingpointsmemo.com |date=2012-08-28 |accessdate=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; “Maybe she should have said [[terrorist]]-oriented Middle Easterners.” Saucedo Mercer’s husband, Ted Mercer said.&lt;ref name="tpmmuckraker.talkingpointsmemo.com"/&gt;

After [[Boston Bombing]],  Before the suspects were named in the twin blasts, several young men, mostly South Asian or Middle Eastern, were convicted in the court of public opinion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Berrett |first=Dan |url=http://chronicle.com/article/After-Boston-Bombing-Fears-of/138713/ |title=After Boston Bombing, Fears of Backlash Against Muslim Students - Students - The Chronicle of Higher Education |publisher=Chronicle.com |date=2013-04-20 |accessdate=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Australia==
{{See also|2005 Cronulla riots}}
Attacks in Spain, London and [[Agam Regency|agam]] Bali have increasingly associated people of 'Middle Eastern appearance' with terrorism.&lt;ref name = "epress"&gt;http://epress.lib.uts.edu.au/research/bitstream/handle/10453/8089/2009001804.pdf?sequence=1&lt;/ref&gt; A clearer picture of the impact of these events on Sydney's Muslim, Arabic and Middle Eastern population emerged from data collected from a hotline between September 12, 2001 and November 11, 2001 by the ''Community Relations Commission for a Multicultural'' NSW, during which time 248 incidents were logged. There were seven categories of attack: physical assault; verbal assault; sexual assault; threat; racial discrimination or harassment, damage to property; and media attack. Half of all victims were female; seven out of ten were adults. Not surprisingly the largest language groups to use the hotline were Arabic - 52.4% of calls. 47.2%of all incidents occurred in public spaces.&lt;ref name="epress" /&gt;

On 11 December 2005, a violent mob of about five thousand young ‘white’ Australians gathered on the beach at Cronulla, [[New South Wales]]. Waving Australian flags, singing Waltzing Matilda and Australia’s national anthem, the mob verbally abused and physically assaulted anyone of ‘Middle Eastern appearance’.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.turkishweekly.net/article/261/&lt;/ref&gt; Five thousand people reportedly gathered at the site, encouraged by the week’s events and fueled by sun and alcohol, the crowd marched through the streets of [[Cronulla]], attacking anyone who they identified as “Middle Eastern”&lt;ref name="sgo.sagepub.com"&gt;{{cite web|author=Jayde Cahir1 |url=http://sgo.sagepub.com/content/3/2/2158244013484733.full |title=Balancing Trust and Anxiety in a Culture of Fear |publisher=Sgo.sagepub.com |date=2013-04-14 |accessdate=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One victim recalled how the violence erupted when a man deemed to be “of Middle Eastern appearance” was walking along the beachfront with his girlfriend and “two girls turned around and screamed . . . ‘get off our f__king beaches’ [and then] the whole street turned on them”&lt;ref name="sgo.sagepub.com"/&gt; The riots put the spotlight on two segments of Sydney's population -the White,Anglo-Celtic majority	and a Middle Eastern minority- and two parts of the city, the Sutherland Shire Local Government Area(LGA)in Sydney's southern suburbs where	[[Cronulla Beach]]is located(known as 'the Shire'), and the Canterbury and Bankstown  LGAs, located in south-western Sydney, where most of the city's Lebanese and Middle Eastern immigrants live.&lt;ref name="epress" /&gt; Middle Eastern males were tagged as criminal and un-Australian by the media brush of ethnic crime.&lt;ref name="epress" /&gt;

Two  [[Bangladeshis|Bangladeshi]]  students, unlikely  bearers  of  'Middle  Eastern  appearance'  but probably  suspected of  being [[Muslim]]s, were chased up the street by the violent melee, and managed to escape in their car, though it was attacked and pelted with bottles. 'Where's those Muslims? I'm going to  kill  them?', shouted  a  man  hefting  a  carton  of  beer  on  his  shoulder  while  running towards the railway station, where, the rumour had  circulated, a trainload of 'Lebs' was to arrive. Two young men of 'Middle Eastern appearance', on their way for a swim, were mobbed  on  one  invaded  train  carriage,  and  savagely  bashed,  with  both  the  rescuing police  and  a  witnessing  press  photographer  fearing  there  would  indeed  be  a  killing&lt;ref&gt;http://www.crsi.mq.edu.au/public/download.jsp?id=10589&lt;/ref&gt;

The latest incident occurred in 2011, when Criminal lawyer of Middle Eastern background, Adam Houda,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Tineka Everaardt |url=http://au.news.yahoo.com/today-tonight/lifestyle/article/-/16406193/targeted-through-racial-profiling/ |title=Targeted through racial profiling - Today Tonight |publisher=Au.news.yahoo.com |date=2013-03-20 |accessdate=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; was arrested for refusing a frisk search and resisting arrest after having been approached by police suspecting him of involvement in a recent robbery. These charges were thrown out of court by Judge John Connell who stated "At the end of the day, here were three men of Middle Eastern [[Human physical appearance|appearance]] walking along a suburban street, for all the police knew, minding their own business at an unexceptional time of day, in unexceptional clothing, except two of the men had hooded jumpers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Mercer |first=Neil |url=http://www.bordermail.com.au/story/939697/suing-police-again-the-lawyer-of-middle-eastern-appearance/ |title=Suing police again, the lawyer of Middle Eastern appearance |publisher=The Border Mail |date=2011-11-12 |accessdate=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The place they were in could not have raised a reasonable suspicion they were involved in the robberies"

==See also==
* [[Anti-Arabism]]
* [[Anti-Iranian sentiment]]
* [[Anti-Semetism]]
* [[Anti-Turkism]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Anti-cultural sentiment}}
[[Category:Anti-national sentiment]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Middle Eastern culture]]
[[Category:Middle Eastern studies]]
[[Category:Middle Eastern diaspora]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>