<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231002210256|1178308349" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="39498321" pageid="39498321" ns="0" title="Anti–Middle Eastern sentiment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-10-02T21:08:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Against Mideast}}
{{Distinguish|Islamophobia}}
{{use dmy dates |date=May 2023}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expand-ethnic=yes}}{{Lead too short|date=March 2022}}

'''Anti–Middle Eastern sentiment''' is feelings and expression of hostility, hatred, [[discrimination]], or [[prejudice]] towards the [[Middle East]] and its culture,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://academiccommons.columbia.edu/catalog/ac:124582 |title=Middle Eastern Americans and the First Amendment|journal=Columbia University Academic Commons|year=2009 |access-date=2013-09-14|doi=10.7916/D8D224BB|last1=Mistele|first1=Ashley}}&lt;/ref&gt; and towards persons based on their association with the Middle East and Middle Eastern culture. This is different from Islamophobia; prejudice and hatred towards Muslims in general.

==United States==
In 1993, the [[American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee]] confronted [[The Walt Disney Company]] about [[Anti-Arabism|anti-Arab]] [[Racism|racist]] content in its animated film ''[[Aladdin (1992 Disney film)|Aladdin]]''. At first, Disney denied any problems but eventually relented and changed two lines in the opening song.&lt;ref name="adc"&gt;{{cite web |date=March 1995 |url=https://adc.org/arab-stereotypes-and-american-educators/ |title=Arab Stereotypes and American Educators |first1=Marvin |last1=Wingfield |first2=Bushra |last2=Karaman |work=[[American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee]] |access-date=2007-03-16| archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070405005650/http://www.adc.org/index.php?id=283| archive-date= April 5, 2007 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the ADC were still unhappy with the portrayal of Arabic characters and the referral to the Middle East as "[[Barbarian|barbaric]]".&lt;ref name="adc" /&gt;

Since 9/11, anti–Middle Eastern racism has risen dramatically. A man in [[Houston]], [[Texas]], was shot and wounded after an assailant accused him of "blowing up the country", and four immigrants were shot and killed by a man named [[Larme Price]], who confessed to killing them as revenge for the [[September 11 attacks]]. Price said he was motivated by a desire to kill people of Arab descent after the attacks.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/31/nyregion/police-arrest-brooklyn-man-in-slayings-of-4-shopkeepers.html |first=Robert F. |last=Worth |title=Police Arrest Brooklyn Man In Slayings of 4 Shopkeepers |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=2003-03-31 |access-date=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Price described his victims as Arabs, only one was from an [[Arab country]]. This appears to be a trend; because of stereotypes of Arabs, several non-Arab, non-Muslim groups were subjected to attacks in the wake of 9/11, including several Sikh men attacked for wearing their religiously mandated [[turban]]. Price's mother, Leatha Price, said that her son's anger at Arabs was a matter of mental illness, not ethnic hatred.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"/&gt; The [[murder of Balbir Singh Sodhi]] is another example of a Sikh man who was targeted in an [[Islamophobia|Islamophobic]] hate crime, despite being neither Muslim nor Middle Eastern.

The [[US Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] brought charges against [[NCL America Inc.]], alleging that the company discriminated against seven crew members with Middle East backgrounds. The suit filed on behalf of the employees, stated that the discrimination led to the plaintiffs losing their jobs aboard the cruise ship ''Pride of Aloha''. The 2006 lawsuit had the company deny the allegations, refusing to accept that it had acted improperly in firing the seven Middle Eastern crew members. Sources stated that the two sides reached a settlement agreement, in which [[NCL America Inc.]] has agreed to pay $485,000 to resolve allegations. Additionally, the company also agreed to revise its policies to ensure a workplace that promotes equal employment opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lawyersandsettlements.com/settlements/11837/ncl-america-middle-eastern-discrimination.html |title=Cruise lines to pay $485,000 settlement in employment lawsuit |date=19 May 2008 |publisher=Lawyersandsettlements.com |access-date=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an interview with a conservative website, [[Saucedo Mercer]], a Mexican immigrant who became a U.S. citizen, talked in depth about her views on [[immigration]]. She stated the issue was important because people from places other than Mexico were among those coming across the border illegally.

&lt;blockquote&gt;"That includes Chinese, Middle Easterners. If you know Middle Easterners, a lot of them, they look [[Mexican people|Mexican]] or they look, you know, like a lot of people in South America, [[dark skin]], dark hair, [[brown eyes]]. And they mix. They mix in. And those people, their only goal in life is to cause harm to the United States. So why do we want them here, either [[legally]] or illegally? When they come across the border, besides the [[Waste|trash]] that they leave behind, the [[drug smuggling]], the killings, the beheadings. I mean, you are seeing stuff. It’s a war out there."&lt;ref name="tpmmuckraker.talkingpointsmemo.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tpmmuckraker.talkingpointsmemo.com/2012/08/gabriela_saucedo_mercer_middle_easterners.php |title=Arizona GOP Favorite Doesn't Want Middle Easterners In U.S. 'Legally Or Illegally'|publisher=Talking Points Memo |date=2012-08-28 |access-date=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.azpm.org/p/yv2012-us/2012/8/29/15220-candidate-criticized-for-anti-muslim-remarks/ |title=Candidate Criticized for Anti-Middle Eastern Remarks - Arizona Public Media |publisher=Azpm.org |date=2012-08-29 |access-date=2013-09-14 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402162419/https://www.azpm.org/p/yv2012-us/2012/8/29/15220-candidate-criticized-for-anti-muslim-remarks/ |archive-date=2015-04-02 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

After the [[Boston Marathon bombing]], before the perpetrators [[Dzhokhar Tsarnaev|Dzhokhar]] and [[Tamerlan Tsarnaev]] were identified, several young men, mostly South Asian or Middle Eastern, were convicted in the court of public opinion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Berrett |first=Dan |url=http://chronicle.com/article/After-Boston-Bombing-Fears-of/138713/ |title=After Boston Bombing, Fears of Backlash Against Muslim Students - Students - The Chronicle of Higher Education |publisher=Chronicle.com |date=2013-04-20 |access-date=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Australia==
{{See also|2005 Cronulla riots}}
Attacks in Spain, London, and Bali have increasingly associated people of "Middle Eastern appearance" with terrorism.&lt;ref name = "epress"&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://opus.lib.uts.edu.au/handle/10453/8089 |isbn=9780975196786 |first=Jock |last=Collins |editor-first=Greg |editor-last=Noble |hdl=10453/8089 |publisher=Institute of Criminology Press |title=Lines in the Sand: The Cronulla Riots, Multiculturalism and National Belonging |year=2009 |edition=1st |page=27-43 |chapter=Sydney's Cronulla riots: The context and implications |access-date=2013-06-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A clearer picture of the impact of these events on Sydney's Muslim, Arabic, and Middle Eastern population emerged from data collected from a hotline between September 12, 2001, and November 11, 2001, by the Community Relations Commission for a Multicultural NSW, during which time 248 incidents were logged. There were seven categories of attack: physical assault; verbal assault; sexual assault; threat; racial discrimination or harassment, damage to property; and media attack. Half of all victims were female; seven out of ten were adults. The largest language groups to use the hotline were Arabic, consisting 52.4% of calls. 47.2% of the incidents occurred in public spaces.&lt;ref name="epress" /&gt;

On 11 December 2005, a violent mob of about five thousand young white Australians gathered on the beach at Cronulla, [[New South Wales]]. Waving Australian flags, and singing [[Waltzing Matilda]] and Australia's national anthem, the mob verbally abused and physically assaulted anyone of Middle Eastern appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.turkishweekly.net/article/261/ |title=New Racism and Fear: The Cronulla Riots and Racial Violence in Australia |access-date=May 31, 2013 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130917011835/http://www.turkishweekly.net/article/261 |archive-date=September 17, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Five thousand people reportedly gathered at the site and marched through the streets of [[Cronulla]], attacking anyone who they identified as Middle Eastern.&lt;ref name="sgo.sagepub.com"&gt;{{cite journal|first=Jayde |last=Cahir1 |url=http://sgo.sagepub.com/content/3/2/2158244013484733.full |title=Balancing Trust and Anxiety in a Culture of Fear |journal=SAGE Open |publisher=Sgo.sagepub.com |date=2013-04-14 |volume=3 |issue=2 |doi=10.1177/2158244013484733 |s2cid=55882624 |access-date=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One victim recalled how the violence erupted when a man deemed to be "of Middle Eastern appearance" was walking along the beachfront with his girlfriend and "two girls turned around and screamed ... 'get off our f__king beaches' [and then] the whole street turned on them"&lt;ref name="sgo.sagepub.com"/&gt; The riots put the spotlight on two segments of Sydney's population (the white, Anglo-Celtic majority and a Middle Eastern minority) and two parts of the city: the Sutherland Shire Local Government Area (LGA), located in Sydney's southern suburbs where [[Cronulla Beach]] is located (known as the Shire); and the Canterbury and Bankstown LGAs, located in south-western Sydney, where most of the city's Lebanese and other Middle Eastern immigrants live.&lt;ref name="epress" /&gt; Middle Eastern males were tagged as criminal and un-Australian by the media brush of ethnic crime.&lt;ref name="epress" /&gt;

In one incident, two young men of Middle Eastern appearance, on their way for a swim, were mobbed and beaten on a train carriage, with both responding police officers and a nearby press photographer fearing there would be a killing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://www.crsi.mq.edu.au/public/download.jsp?id%3D10589 |title=Multiculturalism at the end of the Line |first=Scott |last=Poynting |date=2007 |access-date=June 1, 2013 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130423212859/http://www.crsi.mq.edu.au/public/download.jsp?id=10589 |isbn=978-0-9803403-0-3 |archive-date=April 23, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The latest incident occurred in 2011, when the criminal lawyer of Middle Eastern background, Adam Houda,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Tineka |last=Everaardt |url=http://au.news.yahoo.com/today-tonight/lifestyle/article/-/16406193/targeted-through-racial-profiling/ |title=Targeted through racial profiling - Today Tonight |publisher=Au.news.yahoo.com |date=2013-03-20 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130323024234/http://au.news.yahoo.com/today-tonight/lifestyle/article/-/16406193/targeted-through-racial-profiling/ |access-date=2013-09-14|archive-date=23 March 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; was arrested for refusing a frisk search and resisting arrest after having been approached by police, who suspected him of involvement in a recent robbery. These charges were thrown out of court by Judge John Connell, who stated, "At the end of the day, there were three men of Middle Eastern [[Human physical appearance|appearance]] walking along a suburban street, for all the police knew, minding their own business at an unexceptional time of day, in unexceptional clothing, except two of the men had hooded jumpers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Mercer |first=Neil |url=http://www.bordermail.com.au/story/939697/suing-police-again-the-lawyer-of-middle-eastern-appearance/ |title=Suing police again, the lawyer of Middle Eastern appearance |publisher=The Border Mail |date=2011-11-12 |access-date=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The place they were in could not have raised a reasonable suspicion they were involved in the robberies."

== Turkey ==
Negative sentiments towards Middle Eastern individuals, Middle Eastern history, and peoples are also observed in Turkey. This sentiment reached its peak during incidents such as the genocide of Anatolian Greeks, Armenians, and Lebanese populations. Furthermore, the Turkish government consistently expresses a desire to join Europe and disassociate itself from being perceived as part of the Middle East. Such rhetoric is commonly encountered in Turkish politics, as being associated with the Middle East is generally viewed unfavorably within the secular parts of Turkey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.kocaeligazetesi.com.tr/makale/12149701/mesut-akbulut/turkiye-avrupa-mi-ortadogu-ulkesi-mi | title=Türkiye, Avrupa mı Ortadoğu ülkesi mi? }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.haaretz.com/world-news/.premium-palestinians-were-spared-turkey-s-rising-anti-arab-hate-until-now-1.7491287 | title=Palestinians Were Spared Turkey's Rising anti-Arab Hate. Until Now | newspaper=Haaretz }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00263206.2010.504553 | doi=10.1080/00263206.2010.504553 | title=Arabs in Kemalist Turkish Historiography | year=2010 | last1=Akturk | first1=Ahmet Serdar | journal=Middle Eastern Studies | volume=46 | issue=5 | pages=633–653 | s2cid=145675272 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ümit Özdağ]], the former deputy Chairman of the [[Good Party]], warned that Turkey risked becoming "a Middle Eastern country" because of the influx of refugees.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/syrian-refugees-who-fled-turkey-face-backlash-n978831|title=Syrian refugees who were welcomed in Turkey now face backlash|website=NBC News|language=en|access-date=2019-08-27|archive-date=2021-05-09|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210509001620/https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/syrian-refugees-who-fled-turkey-face-backlash-n978831|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Anti-Arabism|Anti-Arab sentiment]]
* [[Anti-Palestinianism|Anti-Palestinian sentiment]]
* [[Anti-Armenian sentiment]]
* [[Anti-Assyrian sentiment]]
* [[Anti-Iranian sentiment]]
* [[Anti-Zionism|Anti-Israeli sentiment]]
* [[Antisemitism|Anti-Jewish sentiment]]
* [[Anti-Kurdish sentiment]]
* [[Islamophobia|Anti-Muslim sentiment]]
* [[Anti-Turkism|Anti-Turkish sentiment]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book|last=Maghbouleh|first=Neda|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TdHdnQAACAAJ|title=The Limits of Whiteness: Iranian Americans and the Everyday Politics of Race|publisher=Stanford University Press|year=2017|isbn=9781503603370|author-link=Neda Maghbouleh}}

{{Racism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anti-Middle Eastern sentiment}}
[[Category:Anti–Middle Eastern sentiment| ]]
[[Category:Anti-Asian sentiment|Middle Eastern]]
[[Category:Anti-national sentiment|Middle Eastern]]
[[Category:Racism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>