<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161121205122|750787923" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33178" pageid="33178" ns="0" title="White supremacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-21T20:52:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''White supremacy''' or '''white supremacism''' is a [[racism|racist ideology]] centered upon the belief, and promotion of the belief, that [[white people]] are superior in certain characteristics, traits, and attributes to people of other [[race (human classification)|racial backgrounds]] and that therefore white people should politically, economically and socially rule non-white people.

The term is also typically used to describe a [[political ideology]] that perpetuates and maintains the [[society|social]], [[politics|political]], [[historical revisionism|historical]] and/or [[institutional racism|industrial]] domination by white people (as evidenced by historical and contemporary sociopolitical structures such as the [[Atlantic slave trade]], [[Jim Crow laws]] in the United States, and ''[[apartheid]]'' in South Africa).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Privilege Revealed: How Invisible Preference Undermines America |last=Wildman |first=Stephanie M. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1996 |publisher=NYU Press |location= |isbn=0-8147-9303-7 |page=87}}&lt;/ref&gt; Different forms of white supremacism put forth different conceptions of who is considered white, and different white supremacists identify various racial and cultural groups as their primary enemy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Spaces of Hate: Geographies of Discrimination and Intolerance in the U.S.A. |last=Flint |first=Colin |year=2004 |publisher=Routledge |location= |isbn=0-415-93586-5 |page=53 |quote=Although white racist activists must adopt a political identity of whiteness, the flimsy definition of whiteness in modern culture poses special challenges for them. In both mainstream and white supremacist discourse, to be white is to be distinct from those marked as non-white, yet the placement of the distinguishing line has varied significantly in different times and places.}}&lt;/ref&gt; White supremacist groups have typically opposed [[Person of color|people of color]] and [[Antisemitism|Jews]].

In academic usage, particularly in usage drawing on [[critical race theory]], the term "white supremacy" can also refer to a political or socio-economic system where white people enjoy a structural advantage ([[Privilege (social inequality)|privilege]]) over other ethnic groups, both at a collective and an individual level.

==History of white supremacy==
White supremacy has ideological foundations that at least date back to 17th-century [[scientific racism]], the predominant paradigm of human variation that helped shape international and intra-national relations from the latter part of the [[Age of Enlightenment]] (in European history) through the late 20th century (marked by the abolition of [[apartheid]] in [[South Africa]] in 1991, followed by that country's [[South African general election, 1994|first multiracial elections in 1994]]).

===United States===
{{maincat|White supremacy in the United States}}
White supremacy was dominant in the [[United States]] even after the [[American Civil War]] and also decades after the [[Reconstruction Era]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Fredrickson | first = George | title = White Supremacy | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford Oxfordshire | year = 1981 | isbn = 0-19-503042-7 |page=162}}&lt;/ref&gt; In large areas of the U.S. this included the holding of non-whites (specifically [[African Americans]]) in [[slavery in the United States|chattel slavery]] with four million denied freedom from bondage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=How the end of slavery led to starvation and death for millions of black Americans|url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/jun/16/slavery-starvation-civil-war|publisher=The Guardian|date=September 3, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The outbreak of the Civil War saw the desire to uphold white supremacy cited as a cause for state secession&lt;ref&gt;[http://avalon.law.yale.edu/19th_century/csa_texsec.asp A Declaration of the Causes which Impel the State of Texas to Secede from the Federal Union]: "We hold as undeniable truths that the governments of the various States, and of the confederacy itself, were established exclusively by the white race, for themselves and their posterity; that the African race had no agency in their establishment; that they were rightfully held and regarded as an inferior and dependent race, and in that condition only could their existence in this country be rendered beneficial or tolerable. That in this free government all white men are and of right ought to be entitled to equal civil and political rights; that the servitude of the African race, as existing in these States, is mutually beneficial to both bond and free, and is abundantly authorized and justified by the experience of mankind, and the revealed will of the Almighty Creator, as recognized by all Christian nations; while the destruction of the existing relations between the two races, as advocated by our sectional enemies, would bring inevitable calamities upon both and desolation upon the fifteen slave-holding states."&lt;/ref&gt; and the formation of the [[Confederate States of America]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://teachingamericanhistory.org/library/index.asp?documentprint=76 The "Cornerstone Speech", Alexander H. Stephens (Vice President of the Confederate States), March 21, 1861, Savannah, Georgia]: "Our new government is founded upon exactly the opposite idea; its foundations are laid, its cornerstone rests, upon the great truth that the negro is not equal to the white man; that slavery--subordination to the superior race--is his natural and normal condition."&lt;/ref&gt; In an editorial about [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] in 1890, author [[L. Frank Baum]] wrote: "The Whites, by law of conquest, by justice of civilization, are masters of the American continent, and the best safety of the frontier settlements will be secured by the total annihilation of the few remaining Indians."&lt;ref&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071209193251/http://www.northern.edu/hastingw/baumedts.htm |date=December 9, 2007 |title="L. Frank Baum's Editorials on the Sioux Nation" }} Full text of both, with commentary by professor A. Waller Hastings&lt;/ref&gt;

In some parts of the United States, many people who were considered non-white were [[disfranchisement|disenfranchised]], barred from government office, and prevented from holding most government jobs well into the second half of the 20th century. Since the founding of the United States, when the right to vote was restricted to white men of property, professor Leland T. Saito of [[University of Southern California|USC]] writes: "Throughout the history of the United States race has been used by whites for legitimizing and creating difference and social, economic and political exclusion."&lt;ref&gt;Leland T. Saito (1998). "Race and Politics: Asian Americans, Latinos, and Whites in a Los Angeles Suburb". p. 154. University of Illinois Press&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Naturalization Act of 1790]] limited U.S. citizenship to whites only.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Schultz|first=Jeffrey D.|title=Encyclopedia of Minorities in American Politics: African Americans and Asian Americans|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WDV40aK1T-sC&amp;pg=PA284&amp;dq=African+Americans+discriminated+by+Naturalization+Act+of+1790&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|page=284|year=2002|accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The denial of social and political freedom continued into the mid-20th century resulting in the [[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1954–68)|Civil Rights Movement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.archives.gov/kansas-city/press/2013/13-29.html |title=50th Anniversary of the 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom Panel Discussion at the Black Archives of Mid-America|accessdate=October 3, 2015 |format=press release |publisher=The U.S. National Archives and Records Administration|date=August 7, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On the U.S. immigration laws prior to 1965, sociologist Stephen Klineberg cited the law as clearly declaring "that [[Northern European]]s are a superior subspecies of the white race."&lt;ref name="Immigration law"/&gt; The [[Immigration and Nationality Act of 1965]] dramatically opened entry to the U.S. to immigrants other than traditional Northern European and [[Germanic peoples|Germanic groups]], and as a result would significantly alter the demographic mix in the U.S.&lt;ref name="Immigration law"&gt;{{cite web |title= 1965 immigration law changed face of America |author=Jennifer Ludden |url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5391395 |publisher=NPR}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[U.S. state]]s banned [[interracial marriage]] through [[anti-miscegenation laws]] until 1967, when these laws were invalidated by the [[Supreme Court of the United States]]' decision in ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]''. Additionally, white leaders often viewed Native Americans as obstacles to economic and political [[progress (history)|progress]] with respect to the natives' claims to land and rights.

===Germany===
[[Nazism]] promoted the idea of a superior  [[Germanic people]] or [[Aryan race]] in Germany during the early 20th century. Notions of white supremacy and Aryan racial superiority were combined in the 19th century, with white supremacists maintaining that white people were members of an Aryan "master race" which is superior to other races, particularly the [[Jews]] who were described as the "Semitic race", [[Slavs]] and [[Names of the Romani people|Gypsies]], which they associated with "cultural sterility". [[Arthur de Gobineau]], a French racial theorist and aristocrat, blamed the fall of the [[Ancien Régime|ancient ''régime'']] in France on racial degeneracy caused by racial intermixing, which he argued had destroyed the purity of the Nordic or Germanic race. Gobineau's theories, which attracted a strong following in Germany, emphasized the existence of an irreconcilable polarity between Aryan or Germanic peoples and Jewish cultures.&lt;ref&gt;Blamires, Cyprian; Jackson, Paul. "World Fascism: A Historical Encyclopedia": Volume 1. Santa Barbara, California, USA: ABC-CLIO, Inc, 2006. p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to preserve the Aryan race or [[Nordic race]], the Nazis introduced the [[Nuremberg Laws|Nuremberg racial laws]] in 1935, which forbade sexual relations and marriages between Germans and Jews, and later between Germans and [[Romani people|Romani]] and [[Slavs]].

The Nazis used the [[Mendelian inheritance]] theory to argue that social traits were innate, claiming that there was a racial nature associated with certain general traits such as inventiveness or criminal behavior.&lt;ref&gt;Henry Friedlander. The Origins of Nazi Genocide: From Euthanasia to the Final Solution. Chapel Hill, North Carolina, USA: University of North Carolina Press, 1995. p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many modern-day white supremacist groups around the world reuse [[Nazi symbolism]], including the [[swastika]], to represent their beliefs.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}}

According to the 2012 annual report of Germany's interior intelligence service, the [[Federal Office for the Protection of the Constitution]], at the time there were 26,000 right-wing extremists living in Germany, including 6000 [[Neo-Nazism|Neo-Nazis]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.verfassungsschutz.de/de/oeffentlichkeitsarbeit/publikationen/verfassungsschutzberichte/vsbericht-2012&lt;/ref&gt;

===Southern Africa===
A number of [[Southern Africa]]n nations experienced severe racial tension and conflict during global [[decolonization]], particularly as [[white Africans of European ancestry]] fought to protect their preferential social and political status. Racial segregation in South Africa began in colonial times under the Dutch Empire, and continued when the British took over the [[Cape of Good Hope]] in 1795. [[Apartheid]] as an officially structured policy was introduced by the [[Afrikaners|Afrikaner]]-dominated [[National Party (South Africa)|National Party]] after the [[South African general election, 1948|general election of 1948]]. Legislation divided inhabitants into four racial groups—"black", "white", "coloured", and "Indian", the last two of which were divided into several sub-classifications.&lt;ref&gt;Baldwin-Ragaven, Laurel; London, Lesley; du Gruchy, Jeanelle (1999). ''An ambulance of the wrong colour: health professionals, human rights and ethics in South Africa.'' Juta and Company Limited. p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; In 1970, the Afrikaner-run government [[Separate Representation of Voters Amendment Act, 1968|abolished non-white political representation]], and starting that year black people were deprived of South African citizenship.&lt;ref&gt;John Pilger (2011). "Freedom Next Time". p. 266. Random House&lt;/ref&gt; South Africa abolished apartheid in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title = abolition of the White Australia Policy |url = http://www.immi.gov.au/media/fact-sheets/08abolition.htm | publisher = Australian Government | date= November 2010 | accessdate =October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url =http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/555568/South-Africa/259494/The-apartheid-years | title = Encyclopaedia Britannia, South Africa the Apartheid Years | publisher = Encyclopaedia Britannia | accessdate = October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Rhodesia]], a predominantly white government issued its own [[unilateral declaration of independence]] from the United Kingdom during an unsuccessful attempt to avoid immediate majority rule.&lt;ref name="africapolitics"&gt;{{cite book|last=Gann|first=L.H.|title=Politics and Government in African States 1960-1985|pages=162–202}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the [[Rhodesian Bush War]] which was fought by [[African nationalism|African nationalists]], Rhodesian prime minister [[Ian Smith]] acceded to biracial political representation in 1978 and the state achieved recognition from the United Kingdom as [[Zimbabwe]] in 1980.&lt;ref name="zimstudy"&gt;{{cite book|last=Nelson|first=Harold|title=Zimbabwe: A Country Study|pages=1–317}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ukraine and Russia===
[[Neo-Nazism|Neo-Nazi]] organisations embracing white-supremacist ideology are present in many countries in the world. It has been claimed in 2007, that Russian Neo-Nazis accounted for "half of the world's total".&lt;ref&gt;"[http://abcnews.go.com/Nightline/story?id=3718255&amp;page=1#.UCDbiaA4SuI Violence 'in the Name of the Nation']." ''[[ABC News]]''. October 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academic use of the term==
The term ''white supremacy'' is used in academic studies of racial power to denote a system of structural or [[societal racism]] which privileges white people over others, regardless of the presence or absence of racial hatred. White racial advantages occur both at a collective and an individual level (''[[ceteris paribus]]'', {{Nowrap|i. e.}}, when individuals are compared that do not relevantly differ except in ethnicity). Legal scholar Frances Lee Ansley explains this definition as follows:
{{quote|By "white supremacy" I do not mean to allude only to the self-conscious racism of white supremacist [[hate group]]s. I refer instead to a political, economic and cultural system in which whites overwhelmingly control power and material resources, conscious and unconscious ideas of white superiority and entitlement are widespread, and relations of white dominance and non-white subordination are daily reenacted across a broad array of institutions and social settings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ansley|first=Frances Lee|title=Stirring the Ashes: Race, Class and the Future of Civil Rights Scholarship|journal=Cornell Law Review|year=1989|volume=74|pages=993ff}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Temple University Press | isbn = 978-1-56639-532-8 | editors = Richard Delgado and Jean Stefancic (eds.) | last = Ansley | first = Frances Lee | title = Critical white studies: Looking behind the mirror | chapter = White supremacy (and what we should do about it) | date = 1997-06-29 | page = 592}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

This and similar definitions are adopted or proposed by Charles Mills,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | pages = 35–48 | last = Mills | first = C.W. | title = White supremacy as sociopolitical system: A philosophical perspective | journal = White out: The continuing significance of racism | year = 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[bell hooks]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Pluto Press | isbn = 978-0-7453-1663-5 | last = Hooks | first = Bell | title = Feminist theory: From margin to center | date = 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; David Gillborn,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1177/1468796806068323 | issn = 1468-7968 | volume = 6 | issue = 3 | pages = 318–340 | last = Gillborn | first = David | title = Rethinking White Supremacy Who Counts in 'WhiteWorld' | journal = Ethnicities | accessdate = 2012-03-14 | date = 2006-09-01 | url = http://etn.sagepub.com/content/6/3/318}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Neely Fuller Jr,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = SAGE | asin = B0007BLCWC | last = Fuller | first = Neely | title = The united-independent compensatory code/system/concept: A textbook/workbook for thought, speech, and/or action, for victims of racism (white supremacy) | year = 1984 | page = 334}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are widely used in [[critical race theory]] and [[Intersectionality|intersectional]] feminism. Some [[anti-racism|anti-racist]] educators, such as Betita Martinez and the Challenging White Supremacy workshop, also use the term in this way. The term expresses historic continuities between a pre-[[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1954–68)|African-American Civil Rights Movement]] era (1954–68) of open white supremacism and the current racial power structure of the United States. It also expresses the visceral impact of structural racism through "provocative and brutal" language that characterizes racism as "nefarious, global, systemic, and constant."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis US | isbn = 978-0-415-98980-0 | editors = Jeanette Davidson and George Yancy (eds.) | last = Davidson | first = Tim | title = Critical perspectives on Bell Hooks | chapter = bell hooks, white supremacy, and the academy | date = 2009-02-23 | page = 68}}&lt;/ref&gt; Academic users of the term sometimes prefer it to ''racism'' because it allows for a disconnection between racist feelings and white racial advantage or [[white privilege|privilege]].&lt;ref&gt;"Why is it so difficult for many white folks to understand that racism is oppressive not because white folks have prejudicial feelings about blacks (they could have such feelings and leave us alone) but because it is a system that promotes domination and subjugation?" {{Cite book | publisher = Turnaround Publisher Services Limited | isbn = 978-1-873262-02-3 | last = hooks | first = bell | title = Black Looks: Race and Representation | date = 2009-02-04 | page = 12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Grillo and Wildman cite hooks to argue for the term ''racism/white supremacy'': "hooks writes that liberal whites do not see themselves as prejudiced or interested in domination through coercion, and do not acknowledge the ways they the ways they contribute to and benefit from the system of white privilege." {{Cite book | publisher = Temple University Press | isbn = 978-1-56639-532-8 | editors = Richard Delgado and Jean Stefancic (eds.) | last1 = Grillo | first1 = Trina |author2= Stephanie M. Wildman | title = Critical white studies: Looking behind the mirror | chapter = The implications of making comparisons between racism and sexism (or other isms) | date = 1997-06-29 | page = 620}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ideologies and movements==
Supporters of [[Nordic race#Nordicism|Nordicism]] consider the "Nordic peoples" to be a superior race.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nordicism|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/nordicism|website=Merriam Webster}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the early 19th century, white supremacy was attached to emerging theories of racial hierarchy. The German philosopher [[Arthur Schopenhauer]] attributed civilisational primacy to the white race:
{{quote|The highest civilization and culture, apart from the ancient Hindus and Egyptians, are found exclusively among the white races; and even with many dark peoples, the ruling caste or race is fairer in colour than the rest and has, therefore, evidently immigrated, for example, the Brahmans, the Incas, and the rulers of the South Sea Islands. All this is due to the fact that necessity is the mother of invention because those tribes that emigrated early to the north, and there gradually became white, had to develop all their intellectual powers and invent and perfect all the arts in their struggle with need, want and misery, which in their many forms were brought about by the climate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Schopenhauer | first = Arthur | authorlink = Arthur Schopenhauer | title = ''[[Parerga and Paralipomena]]'' | year = 1851 | pages = Vol. 2, Section 92}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[File:Klan-in-gainesville.jpg|thumb|left|Members of the second [[Ku Klux Klan]] at a rally in 1923.]]

[[File:Flag of the NSDAP (1920–1945).svg|thumb|right|A [[swastika]], the symbol of the [[Nazi party]] (NSDAP) led by [[Adolf Hitler]].]]

The [[eugenics|eugenicist]] [[Madison Grant]] argued in his 1916 book, ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'', that the Nordic race had been responsible for most of humanity's great achievements, and that admixture was "race suicide".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Grant | first = Madison | title = The Passing of the Great Race | publisher = C. Scribner's sons | year = 1921 | edition = 4 | page = xxxi | url = https://archive.org/stream/passingofgreatra00granuoft/passingofgreatra00granuoft_djvu.txt}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this book, Europeans who are not of Germanic origin but have Nordic characteristics such as blonde/red hair and blue/green/gray eyes, were considered to be a Nordic admixture and suitable for [[Aryanization (Nazism)|Aryanization]].&lt;ref name="Grant1916"&gt;[[Madison Grant|Grant, Madison]] (1916). ''The Passing of the Great Race''. Charles Scribner's Sons, New York.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, the [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK) is the group most associated with the white supremacist movement. Many white supremacist groups are based on the concept of preserving genetic purity, and they do not focus solely on [[discrimination]] based on skin color.&lt;ref name="law.jrank.org"&gt;http://law.jrank.org/pages/11302/White-Supremacy-Groups.html White Supremacy Groups&lt;/ref&gt; The KKK's reasons for supporting [[racial segregation]] are not primarily based on religious ideals, but some Klan groups are openly [[Protestantism|Protestant]]. The KKK and other white supremacist groups like [[Aryan Nations]], [[The Order (white supremacist group)|The Order]] and the [[White Patriot Party]] are considered [[Antisemitism in the United States|antisemitic]].&lt;ref name="law.jrank.org"/&gt;
[[File:Good Citizen Pillar of Fire Church July 1926.jpg|right|thumb|''[[The Good Citizen]]'' 1926, published by [[Pillar of Fire International|Pillar of Fire Church]]]]

[[Nazi Germany]] promulgated white supremacy based on the belief that the [[Aryan race]], or the Germans, were the ''[[master race]]''. It was combined with a [[Nazi eugenics|eugenics programme]] that aimed for [[racial hygiene]] through compulsory sterilization of sick individuals and extermination of [[Untermensch]]en ("subhumans"): [[Anti-Slavic sentiment|Slavs]], Jews and [[antiziganism|Romani]], which eventually culminated in [[the Holocaust]].&lt;ref&gt;Gumkowski, Janusz; Leszczynski, Kazimierz; Robert, Edward (translator) (1961). Hitler's Plans for Eastern Europe (PAPERBACK). Poland Under Nazi Occupation (First ed.) (Polonia Pub. House). p. 219. ASIN B0006BXJZ6. Retrieved March 12, 2014. at Wayback machine.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Peter Longerich]] (15 April 2010). Holocaust: The Nazi Persecution and Murder of the Jews. Oxford University Press. p. 30. ISBN 978-0-19-280436-5.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="USHMM"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://digitalassets.ushmm.org/photoarchives/detail.aspx?id=10049&amp;search=EUTHANASIA+%28PATIENTS%2FVICTIMS%29&amp;index=25 | title=Close-up of Richard Jenne, the last child killed by the head nurse at the Kaufbeuren-Irsee euthanasia facility. | publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum | accessdate=July 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ian Kershaw]], ''Hitler: A Profile in Power'', Chapter VI, first section (London, 1991, rev. 2001)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Snyder, S. &amp; D. Mitchell. Cultural Locations of Disability. University of Michigan Press. 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Christian Identity]] is another movement closely tied to white supremacy. Some white supremacists identify themselves as [[Heathenry (new religious movement)|Odinists]], although many Odinists reject white supremacy. Some white supremacist groups, such as the [[South Africa]]n [[Boeremag]], conflate elements of [[Christianity]] and Odinism. [[Creativity (religion)|Creativity]] (formerly known as "The World Church of the Creator") is [[atheism|atheistic]] and denounces Christianity and other theistic religions.&lt;ref name="Atheistic"&gt;{{cite book|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=HB1wyFPRGm4C&amp;pg=PA23&amp;dq=atheism+white+supremacy#v=onepage&amp;q=atheistic&amp;f=false|title =The new white nationalism in America: its challenge to integration|publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]]|quote=For instance, Ben Klassen, founder of the atheistic Church of the Creator and author of ''The White Man's Bible'', discusses Christianity extensively in his writings and denounces it as a religion that has brought untold horror into the world and has divided the white race.|accessdate = 2011-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Atheism"&gt;{{cite book|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=rBgn3xB75ZcC&amp;pg=PA493&amp;dq=competing+atheistic+white+racist+movement#v=onepage&amp;q=competing%20atheistic%20white%20racist%20movement&amp;f=false|title =The World's Religions: Continuities and Transformations|publisher = [[Taylor &amp; Francis]]|quote=A competing atheistic or panthestic white racist movement also appeared, which included the Church of the Creator/ Creativity (Gardell 2003: 129–134).|accessdate = 2011-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aside from this, its ideology is similar to many Christian Identity groups because it believes in an [[List of conspiracy theories#Antisemitic conspiracy theories|antisemitic conspiracy theory]] that there is a "Jewish conspiracy" in control of governments, the banking industry and the media. [[Matthew F. Hale]], founder of the World Church of the Creator, has published articles stating that all races other than white are "mud races," which is what the group's religion teaches.&lt;ref name="law.jrank.org"/&gt;

The white supremacist ideology has become associated with a racist faction of the [[skinhead]] [[subculture]], despite the fact that when the skinhead culture first developed in the [[United Kingdom]] in the late 1960s, it was heavily influenced by [[black]] fashions and music, especially [[Jamaica]]n [[reggae]] and [[ska]], and African American [[soul music]].&lt;ref&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20010219175613/ska.about.com/musicperform/ska/library/1999/aa081699a.htm |date=February 19, 2001 |title=Smiling Smash: An Interview with Cathal Smyth, a.k.a. Chas Smash, of Madness }}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reggaereggaereggae.com/Special%20Articles.htm Special Articles&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="skinheads"&gt;{{cite book |last=Old Skool Jim |first= |title=Trojan Skinhead Reggae Box Set liner notes |publisher=Trojan Records |date= |location=London |id=TJETD169}}&lt;/ref&gt;

White supremacist recruitment activities are conducted primarily at a [[grassroots]] level and on the Internet. Widespread access to the Internet has led to a dramatic increase in white supremacist websites.&lt;ref name="Adversity"&gt;{{cite web |last=1Adams |first1=Josh |first2=Vincent J. |last2=Roscigno |title=White Supremacists, Oppositional Culture and the World Wide Web |work=University on North Carolina Press 84 (2005): 759-788 |date=20 November 2009 |jstor=3598477}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Internet provides a venue to openly express white supremacist ideas at little [[social cost]], because people who post the information are able to remain anonymous.

==Relationships with black separatist groups==

In February 1962 [[George Lincoln Rockwell]], the leader of the [[American Nazi Party]], spoke at a [[Nation of Islam]] rally in Chicago, where he was applauded by [[Elijah Muhammad]] as he pronounced: "I am proud to stand here before black men. I believe Elijah Muhammed is the Adolf Hitler of the black man!"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=George Thayer|title=The Farther Shore of Politics: The American Political Fringe Today|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3EEGAAAAMAAJ|year=1967|publisher=Allen Lane|pages=25–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rockwell had attended, but did not speak at, an earlier NOI rally in June 1961 in Washington, D.C.&lt;ref name=gardell&gt;{{cite book|author=Mattias Gardell|title=In the Name of Elijah Muhammad: Louis Farrakhan and The Nation of Islam|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Z9ufS6aXctQC&amp;pg=PA273|date=7 October 1996|publisher=Duke University Press|isbn=0-8223-1845-8|pages=273–4}}&lt;/ref&gt; and even once donated $20 to the NOI.&lt;ref name=voice&gt;{{cite news|title=White Supremacists Voice Support of Farrakhan|author=Wayne King|work=New York Times|date=October 12, 1985|page=12}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1965, after breaking with the Nation of Islam and denouncing its separatist doctrine, [[Malcolm X]] told his followers that the Nation of Islam under Elijah Muhammad had made secret agreements with the American Nazi Party and the Ku Klux Klan.&lt;ref name=gardell/&gt;

Rockwell and other white supremacists (e.g. [[Willis Carto]]) also supported less well-known groups, such as Hassan Jeru-Ahmed's Blackman's Army of Liberation, in reference to which Rockwell told ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' reporter [[Michael Drosnin]] in 1967 that "Any Negro wants to go back to Africa, I'll carry him piggy-back."&lt;ref name=drosnin&gt;{{cite news|title=U.S. Negro Group Plans Own Nation in Africa: 'Blackman's Army'|author=Michael Drosnin|work=Los Angeles Times|date=June 5, 1967|page=29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

More recently, [[Tom Metzger (white supremacist)|Tom Metzger]], erstwhile [[Ku Klux Klan]] leader from California, spoke at an NOI rally in [[Los Angeles]] in September 1985 and donated $100 to the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bedfellows: The Klan Connection|work=New York Times|date=October 6, 1985|page=E20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October of that same year, over 200 prominent white supremacists met at former Klan leader [[Robert E. Miles]]'s farm to discuss an alliance with [[Louis Farrakhan]], head of the NOI.&lt;ref name=voice/&gt;  In attendance were Edward Reed Fields of the [[National States' Rights Party]], [[Richard Girnt Butler]] of [[Aryan Nations]], [[Don Black (white nationalist)|Don Black]], [[Roy Frankhouser]], and Metzger, who said that "America is like a rotting carcass. The Jews are living off the carcass like the parasites they are. Farrakhan understands this."&lt;ref name=voice/&gt;

==See also==
{{colbegin|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Afrocentrism]]
*[[Alt-right]]
*[[Anti-miscegenation laws]]
*[[Aryan Brotherhood]]
*''[[The Birth of a Nation]]'' (movie)
*[[Black supremacy]]
*[[Eurocentrism]]
*[[Hate group]]
*''[[Heroes of the Fiery Cross]]'' (book)
*[[Institutional racism]]
*[[Jim Crow laws]]
*[[Master race]]
*[[Race and intelligence]]
*[[Scientific racism]]
*[[Frances Cress Welsing]]
*"[[The White Man's Burden]]" (poem)
*[[White power music]]
*[[Superiority complex]]
*[[White nationalism]]
*[[List of white nationalist organizations]]
{{colend}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*Dobratz, Betty A. and Shanks-Meile, Stephanie. ''"White power, white pride!": The white separatist movement in the United States'' (JHU Press, 2000) ISBN 978-0-8018-6537-4
*Lincoln Rockwell, George. ''White Power'' (John McLaughlin, 1996)
*MacCann, Ronnarae. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=xj_T3QCgNgsC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=%22White+supremacy%22+juvenile White Supremacy in Children's Literature]'' (Routledge, 2000)

==External links==
*[http://www.docsonline.tv/Archives/description.php?doc=187 ''Heart of Whiteness''] documentary film about what it means to be white in South Africa
*[http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/voices/transcript/?content=20110303 ''Voices on Antisemitism'' Interview with Frank Meeink] from the [[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum|U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum]]
{{white people}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:White Supremacy}}
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Social history of the United States]]
[[Category:Neo-Nazi concepts]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Racial segregation]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Reconstruction Era]]
[[Category:Neo-fascism]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination]]
[[Category:White supremacy| ]]
[[Category:Racism in the United States]]
[[Category:White nationalism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>