<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171121202531|811467464" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33178" pageid="33178" ns="0" title="White supremacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-22T00:33:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''White supremacy''' or '''white supremacism''' is a [[racism|racist ideology]] based upon the belief that [[white people]] are superior in many ways to people of other [[race (human classification)|races]] and that therefore [[white people]] should be dominant over other races. White supremacy has roots in [[scientific racism]] and it often relies on [[pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] arguments. Like most similar movements such as [[neo-Nazism]], white supremacists typically oppose [[Person of color|people of color]], Jews, and non-Protestants.

The term is also typically used to describe a [[political ideology]] that perpetuates and maintains the [[society|social]], [[politics|political]], [[historical revisionism|historical]] or [[institutional racism|institutional]] domination by white people (as evidenced by historical and contemporary sociopolitical structures such as the [[Atlantic slave trade]], [[Jim Crow laws]] in the [[United States]], and ''[[apartheid]]'' in [[South Africa]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Privilege Revealed: How Invisible Preference Undermines America |last=Wildman |first=Stephanie M. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1996 |publisher=NYU Press |location= |isbn=0-8147-9303-7 |page=87}}&lt;/ref&gt; Different forms of white supremacism put forth different conceptions of who is considered white, and different forms of white supremacists identify various racial and cultural groups as their primary enemy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Spaces of Hate: Geographies of Discrimination and Intolerance in the U.S.A. |last=Flint |first=Colin |year=2004 |publisher=Routledge |location= |isbn=0-415-93586-5 |page=53 |quote=Although white racist activists must adopt a political identity of whiteness, the flimsy definition of whiteness in modern culture poses special challenges for them. In both mainstream and white supremacist discourse, to be white is to be distinct from those marked as non-white, yet the placement of the distinguishing line has varied significantly in different times and places.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In academic usage, particularly in usage which draws on the [[critical race theory]], the term "white supremacy" can also refer to a political or socio-economic system where white people enjoy a structural advantage ([[Privilege (social inequality)|privilege]]) over other ethnic groups, both at a collective and an individual level.

==History of white supremacy==
White supremacy has ideological foundations that at least date back to 17th-century [[scientific racism]], the predominant paradigm of human variation that helped shape international and intra-national relations from the latter part of the [[Age of Enlightenment]] (in European history) through the era of the [[White Man's Burden]] until the late 20th century (marked by decolonization and the abolition of [[apartheid]] in [[South Africa]] in 1991, followed by that country's [[South African general election, 1994|first multiracial elections in 1994]]).

[[File:One side of the monument erected to race prejudice New Orleans Louisiana 1936.jpg|thumb|From the [[Battle of Liberty Place Monument|Battle of Liberty Place monument]] in Louisiana. An inscription added in 1932 states that the [[1876 US Presidential Election]] "recognized white supremacy in the South and gave us our state."]]

===United States===
{{maincat|White supremacy in the United States}}

White supremacy was dominant in the [[United States]] even after the [[American Civil War]] and it also persisted for decades after the [[Reconstruction Era]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Fredrickson | first = George | title = White Supremacy | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford Oxfordshire | year = 1981 | isbn = 0-19-503042-7 |page=162}}&lt;/ref&gt; In large areas of the U.S. this included the holding of non-whites (specifically [[African Americans]]) in [[slavery in the United States|chattel slavery]] with four million of them denied freedom from bondage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=How the end of slavery led to starvation and death for millions of black Americans|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/jun/16/slavery-starvation-civil-war|publisher=The Guardian|date=September 3, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The outbreak of the Civil War saw the desire to uphold white supremacy being cited as a cause for state secession&lt;ref&gt;[http://avalon.law.yale.edu/19th_century/csa_texsec.asp A Declaration of the Causes which Impel the State of Texas to Secede from the Federal Union]: "We hold as undeniable truths that the governments of the various States, and of the confederacy itself, were established exclusively by the white race, for themselves and their posterity; that the African race had no agency in their establishment; that they were rightfully held and regarded as an inferior and dependent race, and in that condition only could their existence in this country be rendered beneficial or tolerable. That in this free government all white men are and of right ought to be entitled to equal civil and political rights; that the servitude of the African race, as existing in these States, is mutually beneficial to both bond and free, and is abundantly authorized and justified by the experience of mankind, and the revealed will of the Almighty Creator, as recognized by all Christian nations; while the destruction of the existing relations between the two races, as advocated by our sectional enemies, would bring inevitable calamities upon both and desolation upon the fifteen slave-holding states."&lt;/ref&gt; and the formation of the [[Confederate States of America]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://teachingamericanhistory.org/library/index.asp?documentprint=76 The controversial "Cornerstone Speech", Alexander H. Stephens (Vice President of the Confederate States), March 21, 1861, Savannah, Georgia]: "Our new government is founded upon exactly the opposite idea; its foundations are laid, its cornerstone rests, upon the great truth that the negro is not equal to the white man; that slavery—subordination to the superior race—is his natural and normal condition."&lt;/ref&gt; In an editorial about [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] in 1890, author [[L. Frank Baum]] wrote: "The Whites, by law of conquest, by justice of civilization, are masters of the American continent, and the best safety of the frontier settlements will be secured by the total annihilation of the few remaining Indians."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.northern.edu/hastingw/baumedts.htm |title=L. Frank Baum's Editorials on the Sioux Nation |accessdate=2007-12-09 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071209193251/http://www.northern.edu/hastingw/baumedts.htm |archivedate=December 9, 2007 |df= }} Full text of both, with commentary by professor A. Waller Hastings&lt;/ref&gt;

In some parts of the United States, many people who were considered non-white were [[disfranchisement|disenfranchised]], barred from government office, and prevented from holding most government jobs well into the second half of the 20th century. Since the founding of the United States, when the right to vote was restricted to white men of property, professor Leland T. Saito of [[University of Southern California|USC]] writes: "Throughout the history of the United States race has been used by whites for legitimizing and creating difference and social, economic and political exclusion."&lt;ref&gt;Leland T. Saito (1998). "Race and Politics: Asian Americans, Latinos, and Whites in a Los Angeles Suburb". p. 154. University of Illinois Press&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Naturalization Act of 1790]] limited U.S. citizenship to whites only.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Schultz|first=Jeffrey D.|title=Encyclopedia of Minorities in American Politics: African Americans and Asian Americans|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WDV40aK1T-sC&amp;pg=PA284&amp;dq=African+Americans+discriminated+by+Naturalization+Act+of+1790&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|page=284|year=2002|accessdate=2010-03-25|isbn=9781573561488}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The denial of social and political freedom continued into the mid-20th century, resulting in the [[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1954–1968)|Civil Rights Movement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.archives.gov/kansas-city/press/2013/13-29.html |title=50th Anniversary of the 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom Panel Discussion at the Black Archives of Mid-America |accessdate=October 3, 2015 |format=press release |publisher=The U.S. National Archives and Records Administration |date=August 7, 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151004044615/http://www.archives.gov/kansas-city/press/2013/13-29.html |archivedate=October 4, 2015 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; On the U.S. immigration laws prior to 1965, sociologist Stephen Klineberg cited the laws as clearly declaring "that [[Northern European]]s are a superior subspecies of the white race."&lt;ref name="Immigration law"/&gt; The [[Immigration and Nationality Act of 1965]] dramatically opened entry to the U.S. to immigrants other than traditional Northern European and [[Germanic peoples|Germanic groups]], and as a result it would significantly alter the demographic mix in the U.S.&lt;ref name="Immigration law"&gt;{{cite web |title= 1965 immigration law changed face of America |author=Jennifer Ludden |url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5391395 |publisher=NPR}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[U.S. state]]s banned [[interracial marriage]] through [[anti-miscegenation laws]] until 1967, when these laws were invalidated by the [[Supreme Court of the United States]]' decision in ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]''. Additionally, white leaders often viewed Native Americans as obstacles to economic and political [[progress (history)|progress]] with respect to the natives' claims to land and rights.

===Germany===
[[Nazism]] promoted the idea of a superior [[Germanic people]] or [[Aryan race]] in [[Germany]] during the early 20th century. Notions of white supremacy and Aryan racial superiority were combined in the 19th century, with white supremacists maintaining the belief that white people were members of an Aryan "[[master race]]" which is superior to other races, particularly the [[Jews]] who were described as the "Semitic race", [[Slavs]] and [[Names of the Romani people|Gypsies]], which they associated with "cultural sterility". [[Arthur de Gobineau]], a French racial theorist and aristocrat, blamed the fall of the [[Ancien Régime|ancient ''régime'']] in France on racial degeneracy caused by racial intermixing, which he argued had destroyed the purity of the Nordic or Germanic race. Gobineau's theories, which attracted a strong following in Germany, emphasized the existence of an irreconcilable polarity between Aryan or Germanic peoples and Jewish culture.&lt;ref&gt;Blamires, Cyprian; Jackson, Paul. "World Fascism: A Historical Encyclopedia": Volume 1. Santa Barbara, California, USA: ABC-CLIO, Inc, 2006. p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the [[Nazi Party]]'s chief racial theorist, [[Alfred Rosenberg]] oversaw the construction of a human racial "ladder" that justified [[Racial policy of Nazi Germany|Hitler's racial and ethnic policies]]. Rosenberg promoted the [[Nordic theory]] which regarded [[Nordic race|Nordics]] as the "master race", superior to all others, including other Aryans (Indo-Europeans).&lt;ref&gt;Though Rosenberg does not use the word "master race". He uses the word "Herrenvolk" (i.e. ruling people) twice in his book ''The Myth'', first referring to the [[Amorite]]s (saying that [[Archibald Sayce|Sayce]] described them as fair skinned and blue eyed) and secondly quoting [[Victor Wallace Germains]]' description of the English in "The Truth about Kitchener". ("The Myth of the Twentieth Century") - Pages 26, 660 - 1930&lt;/ref&gt; Rosenberg got the racial term ''[[Untermensch]]'' from the title of [[Klansman]] [[Lothrop Stoddard]]'s 1922 book ''The Revolt Against Civilization: The Menace of the Under-man''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Stoddard, Lothrop| authorlink = Lothrop Stoddard| year = 1922| title = The Revolt Against Civilization: The Menace of the Under Man| publisher = [[Charles Scribner's Sons]]| location = New York| isbn =| url = https://archive.org/details/revoltagainstciv00stoduoft}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was later adopted by the Nazis from that book's German version ''Der Kulturumsturz: Die Drohung des Untermenschen'' (1925).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal| author = Losurdo, Domenico| authorlink = Domenico Losurdo| others = Translated by Marella &amp; Jon Morris| year = 2004| title = Toward a Critique of the Category of Totalitarianism| journal = [[Historical Materialism (journal)|Historical Materialism]]| publisher = [[Brill Publishers|Brill]]| volume = 12| issue = 2| pages = 25–55, here p. 50| issn = 1465-4466| doi = 10.1163/1569206041551663| url = http://www.pssp.org/bbs/data/document/1/Losurdo___Critique_of_Totalitarianism_%282004%29.pdf| format = PDF, 0.2 MB}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rosenberg was the leading Nazi who attributed the concept of the East-European "under man" to Stoddard.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book| author = Rosenberg, Alfred| authorlink = Alfred Rosenberg| year = 1930| title = Der Mythus des 20. Jahrhunderts: Eine Wertung der seelischgeistigen Gestaltungskämpfe unserer Zeit|trans-title=The Myth of the Twentieth Century| publisher = Hoheneichen-Verlag| location = Munich| page = 214| isbn =| url = https://www.scribd.com/doc/2628285/Der-Mythus-des-20-Jahrhunderts-Alfred-Rosenberg| language = German}}&lt;/ref&gt; An advocate of the U.S. immigration laws that favored Northern Europeans, Stoddard wrote primarily on the alleged dangers posed by "[[colored]]" peoples to white civilization, and wrote ''[[The Rising Tide of Color Against White World-Supremacy]]'' in 1920. In establishing a restrictive entry system for Germany, in 1925 Hitler wrote of his admiration for America's immigration laws: “The American Union categorically refuses the immigration of physically unhealthy elements, and simply excludes the immigration of certain races."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofisrael.com/american-laws-against-coloreds-influenced-nazi-racial-planners/ "American laws against ‘coloreds’ influenced Nazi racial planners"]. Times of Israel. Retrieved August 26, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

German praise for America's institutional racism, previously found in Hitler's ''Mein Kampf'', was continuous throughout the early 1930s, and radical Nazi lawyers were advocates of the use of American models.&lt;ref name="Whitman"/&gt; Race based U.S. citizenship laws and anti-miscegenation laws (no race mixing) directly inspired the Nazi's two principal [[Nuremberg Laws|Nuremberg racial laws]]—the Citizenship Law and the Blood Law.&lt;ref name="Whitman"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Whitman|first1=James Q.|title=Hitler's American Model: The United States and the Making of Nazi Race Law|date=2017|publisher=Princeton University Press|pages=37–43}}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to preserve the Aryan or [[Nordic race]] the Nazis had introduced the Nuremberg Laws in 1935, which forbade sexual relations and marriages between Germans and Jews, and later between Germans and [[Romani people|Romani]] and [[Slavs]]. The Nazis used the [[Mendelian inheritance]] theory to argue that social traits were innate, claiming that there was a racial nature associated with certain general traits such as inventiveness or criminal behavior.&lt;ref&gt;Henry Friedlander. The Origins of Nazi Genocide: From Euthanasia to the Final Solution. Chapel Hill, North Carolina, USA: University of North Carolina Press, 1995. p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; 

According to the 2012 annual report of Germany's interior intelligence service, the [[Federal Office for the Protection of the Constitution]], at the time there were 26,000 right-wing extremists living in Germany, including 6000 [[Neo-Nazism|Neo-Nazis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.verfassungsschutz.de/de/oeffentlichkeitsarbeit/publikationen/verfassungsschutzberichte/vsbericht-2012|title=Bundesamt für Verfassungsschutz - Verfassungsschutzbericht 2012|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===South Africa and Rhodesia===
A number of [[Southern Africa]]n nations experienced severe racial tension and conflict during global [[decolonization]], particularly as [[white Africans of European ancestry]] fought to protect their preferential social and political status. Racial segregation in South Africa began in colonial times under the [[Dutch Empire]], and it continued when the British took over the [[Cape of Good Hope]] in 1795. [[Apartheid]] was introduced as an officially structured policy by the [[Afrikaners|Afrikaner]]-dominated [[National Party (South Africa)|National Party]] after the [[South African general election, 1948|general election of 1948]]. Apartheid's legislation divided inhabitants into four racial groups—"black", "white", "coloured", and "Indian", the last two of which were divided into several sub-classifications.&lt;ref&gt;Baldwin-Ragaven, Laurel; London, Lesley; du Gruchy, Jeanelle (1999). ''An ambulance of the wrong colour: health professionals, human rights and ethics in South Africa.'' Juta and Company Limited. p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; In 1970, the Afrikaner-run government [[Separate Representation of Voters Amendment Act, 1968|abolished non-white political representation]], and starting that year [[black people]] were deprived of South African citizenship.&lt;ref&gt;John Pilger (2011). "Freedom Next Time". p. 266. Random House&lt;/ref&gt; South Africa abolished apartheid in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title = abolition of the White Australia Policy |url = http://www.immi.gov.au/media/fact-sheets/08abolition.htm | publisher = Australian Government | date= November 2010 | accessdate =October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url =http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/555568/South-Africa/259494/The-apartheid-years | title = Encyclopædia Britannica, South Africa the Apartheid Years | publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica | accessdate = October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Rhodesia]], a predominantly white government issued its own [[Rhodesia's Unilateral Declaration of Independence|unilateral declaration of independence]] from the United Kingdom during an unsuccessful attempt to avoid immediate majority rule.&lt;ref name="africapolitics"&gt;{{cite book|last=Gann|first=L.H.|title=Politics and Government in African States 1960–1985|pages=162–202}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the [[Rhodesian Bush War]] which was fought by [[African nationalism|African nationalists]], Rhodesian prime minister [[Ian Smith]] acceded to biracial political representation in 1978 and the state achieved recognition from the United Kingdom as [[Zimbabwe]] in 1980.&lt;ref name="zimstudy"&gt;{{cite book|last=Nelson|first=Harold|title=Zimbabwe: A Country Study|pages=1–317}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Russia===
[[Neo-Nazism|Neo-Nazi]] organisations embracing white-supremacist ideology are present in many countries of the world. In 2007 it was claimed that Russian Neo-Nazis accounted for "half of the world's total".&lt;ref&gt;"[http://abcnews.go.com/Nightline/story?id=3718255&amp;page=1#.UCDbiaA4SuI Violence 'in the Name of the Nation']." ''[[ABC News]]''. October 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academic use of the term==
The term ''white supremacy'' is used in academic studies of racial power to denote a system of structural or [[societal racism]] which privileges white people over others, regardless of the presence or the absence of racial hatred. White racial advantages occur at both a collective and an individual level (''[[ceteris paribus]]'', {{Nowrap|i. e.}}, when individuals are compared that do not relevantly differ except in ethnicity). Legal scholar Frances Lee Ansley explains this definition as follows:
{{quote|By "white supremacy" I do not mean to allude only to the self-conscious racism of white supremacist [[hate group]]s. I refer instead to a political, economic and cultural system in which whites overwhelmingly control power and material resources, conscious and unconscious ideas of white superiority and entitlement are widespread, and relations of white dominance and non-white subordination are daily reenacted across a broad array of institutions and social settings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ansley|first=Frances Lee|title=Stirring the Ashes: Race, Class and the Future of Civil Rights Scholarship|journal=Cornell Law Review|year=1989|volume=74|pages=993ff}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Temple University Press | isbn = 978-1-56639-532-8 | editor1 = Richard Delgado |editor2= Jean Stefancic | last = Ansley | first = Frances Lee | title = Critical white studies: Looking behind the mirror | chapter = White supremacy (and what we should do about it) | date = 1997-06-29 | page = 592}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

This and similar definitions have been adopted or proposed by Charles Mills,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | pages = 35–48 | last = Mills | first = C.W. | title = White supremacy as sociopolitical system: A philosophical perspective | journal = White out: the continuing significance of racism | year = 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[bell hooks]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Pluto Press | isbn = 978-0-7453-1663-5 | last = Hooks | first = Bell | title = Feminist theory: From margin to center | date = 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Gillborn]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1177/1468796806068323 | issn = 1468-7968 | volume = 6 | issue = 3 | pages = 318–40 | last = Gillborn | first = David | title = Rethinking White Supremacy Who Counts in 'WhiteWorld' | journal = Ethnicities | accessdate = 2012-03-14 | date = 2006-09-01 | url = http://etn.sagepub.com/content/6/3/318}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jessie Daniels,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher =  Routledge | isbn = 9780415912891 | last = Daniels| first = Jessie | title = White Lies: race, class, gender and sexuality in white supremacist discourse | date = 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and Neely Fuller Jr,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = SAGE | asin = B0007BLCWC | last = Fuller | first = Neely | title = The united-independent compensatory code/system/concept: A textbook/workbook for thought, speech, and/or action, for victims of racism (white supremacy) | year = 1984 | page = 334}}&lt;/ref&gt; and they are widely used in [[critical race theory]] and [[Intersectionality|intersectional feminism]]. Some [[anti-racism|anti-racist]] educators, such as Betita Martinez and the Challenging White Supremacy workshop, also use the term in this way. The term expresses historic continuities between a pre–[[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1954–1968)|Civil Rights Movement]] era of open white supremacism and the current racial power structure of the United States. It also expresses the visceral impact of structural racism through "provocative and brutal" language that characterizes racism as "nefarious, global, systemic, and constant".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis US | isbn = 978-0-415-98980-0 | editor1 = Jeanette Davidson | editor2 = George Yancy | last = Davidson | first = Tim | title = Critical perspectives on Bell Hooks | chapter = bell hooks, white supremacy, and the academy | date = 2009-02-23 | page = 68}}&lt;/ref&gt; Academic users of the term sometimes prefer it to ''racism'' because it allows for a disconnection between racist feelings and white racial advantage or [[white privilege|privilege]].&lt;ref&gt;"Why is it so difficult for many white folks to understand that racism is oppressive not because white folks have prejudicial feelings about blacks (they could have such feelings and leave us alone) but because it is a system that promotes domination and subjugation?" {{Cite book | publisher = Turnaround Publisher Services Limited | isbn = 978-1-873262-02-3 | last = hooks | first = bell | title = Black Looks: Race and Representation | date = 2009-02-04 | page = 12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Grillo and Wildman cite hooks to argue for the term ''racism/white supremacy'': "hooks writes that liberal whites do not see themselves as either prejudiced or interested in domination through coercion, and they do not acknowledge the ways in which they contribute to and benefit from the system of white privilege." {{Cite book | publisher = Temple University Press | isbn = 978-1-56639-532-8 | editor1 = Richard Delgado | editor2 = Jean Stefancic | last1 = Grillo | first1 = Trina |author2= Stephanie M. Wildman | title = Critical white studies: Looking behind the mirror | chapter = The implications of making comparisons between racism and sexism (or other isms) | date = 1997-06-29 | page = 620}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term's rise in popularity among [[Left-wing politics|leftist]] activists in 2016{{Citation needed|date=August 2017|reason=Do we have evidence that the term became more popular among leftist activists in 2016? Or did some commentators just complain about it in 2016?}} has been characterized by some as counterproductive. A specialist in both language and race relations, [[John McWhorter]] has described its use as straying from commonly accepted meaning to encompass much less extreme issues which thereby cheapens the term and can shut-down productive discussion.&lt;ref name="left language"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wnyc.org/story/left-language-right-language/|title=Left Language, Right Language|accessdate=3 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="McWhorter"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://time.com/4584161/white-supremacy/|title=The Difference Between Racial Bias and White Supremacy|website=TIME |last1=McWhorter|first1=John|accessdate=3 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Political columnist [[Kevin Drum]] attributes the term's growing popularity in 2016 to frequent use by [[Ta-Nehisi Coates]], and he describes it as a "terrible fad" which fails to convey nuance and should be reserved for those who are trying to promote the idea that whites are inherently superior to blacks and not used for any type of less severe racist belief or action.&lt;ref name="MotherJ"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.motherjones.com/kevin-drum/2016/11/lets-please-kill-white-supremacy-fad|title=Let's Be Careful With the "White Supremacy" Label|website=Mother Jones|accessdate=4 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Friedersdorf"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2016/11/the-scourge-of-the-left-too-much-stigma-not-enough-persuasion/508961/|title='The Scourge of the Left': Too Much Stigma, Not Enough Persuasion|last=Friedersdorf|first=Conor|access-date=2016-12-04|language=en-US|newspaper=The Atlantic}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of the academic definition of the term white supremacy has been criticized by Conor Friedersdorf for the confusion it creates for the general public in how it differs from the more common dictionary definition and he argues that it is likely to alienate those it hopes to convince.&lt;ref name="Friedersdorf" /&gt;

==Ideologies and movements==
Supporters of [[Nordic race#Nordicism|Nordicism]] consider the "Nordic peoples" to be a superior race.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nordicism|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/nordicism|website=Merriam Webster}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the early 19th century, white supremacy was attached to emerging theories of racial hierarchy. The German philosopher [[Arthur Schopenhauer]] attributed civilisational primacy to the white race:
{{quote|The highest civilization and culture, apart from the ancient [[Hinduism|Hindus]] and [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptians]], are found exclusively among the white races; and even with many dark peoples, the ruling caste or race is fairer in colour than the rest and has, therefore, evidently immigrated, for example, the [[Brahman]]s, the [[Inca Empire|Incas]], and the rulers of the [[Polynesia|South Sea Islands]]. All this is due to the fact that necessity is the mother of invention because those tribes that emigrated early to the north, and there gradually became white, had to develop all their intellectual powers and invent and perfect all the arts in their struggle with need, want and misery, which in their many forms were brought about by the climate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Schopenhauer | first = Arthur | authorlink = Arthur Schopenhauer | title = ''[[Parerga and Paralipomena]]'' | year = 1851 | pages = Vol. 2, Section 92}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[File:Klan-in-gainesville.jpg|thumb|left|Members of the second [[Ku Klux Klan]] at a rally in 1923.]]

[[File:Flag of the NSDAP (1920–1945).svg|thumb|right|Flag of the [[Nazi Party|Nazi Party (NSDAP)]] led by [[Adolf Hitler]].]]

The [[eugenics|eugenicist]] [[Madison Grant]] argued in his 1916 book, ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'', that the Nordic race had been responsible for most of humanity's great achievements, and that [[Miscegenation|admixture]] was "race suicide".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Grant | first = Madison | title = The Passing of the Great Race | publisher = C. Scribner's sons | year = 1921 | edition = 4 | page = xxxi | url = https://archive.org/stream/passingofgreatra00granuoft/passingofgreatra00granuoft_djvu.txt}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this book, Europeans who are not of Germanic origin but have Nordic characteristics such as blonde/red hair and blue/green/gray eyes, were considered to be a Nordic admixture and suitable for [[Aryanization (Nazism)|Aryanization]].&lt;ref name="Grant1916"&gt;[[Madison Grant|Grant, Madison]] (1916). ''The Passing of the Great Race''. Charles Scribner's Sons, New York.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, the [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK) is the group most associated with the white supremacist movement. Many white supremacist groups are based on the concept of preserving genetic purity, and they do not focus solely on [[discrimination]] based on skin color.&lt;ref name="law.jrank.org"&gt;http://law.jrank.org/pages/11302/White-Supremacy-Groups.html White Supremacy Groups&lt;/ref&gt; The KKK's reasons for supporting [[racial segregation]] are not primarily based on religious ideals, but some Klan groups are openly [[Protestantism|Protestant]]. The KKK and other white supremacist groups like [[Aryan Nations]], [[The Order (white supremacist group)|The Order]] and the [[White Patriot Party]] are considered [[Antisemitism in the United States|antisemitic]].&lt;ref name="law.jrank.org"/&gt;
[[File:Good Citizen Pillar of Fire Church July 1926.jpg|right|thumb|''[[The Good Citizen]]'' 1926, published by [[Pillar of Fire International|Pillar of Fire Church]]]]

[[Nazi Germany]] promulgated white supremacy based on the belief that the [[Aryan race]], or the Germans, were the ''[[master race]]''. It was combined with a [[Nazi eugenics|eugenics programme]] that aimed for [[racial hygiene]] through compulsory sterilization of sick individuals and extermination of [[Untermensch]]en ("subhumans"): [[Anti-Slavic sentiment|Slavs]], Jews and [[antiziganism|Romani]], which eventually culminated in [[the Holocaust]].&lt;ref&gt;Gumkowski, Janusz; Leszczynski, Kazimierz; Robert, Edward (translator) (1961). Hitler's Plans for Eastern Europe (PAPERBACK). Poland Under Nazi Occupation (First ed.) (Polonia Pub. House). p. 219. ASIN B0006BXJZ6. Retrieved March 12, 2014. at Wayback machine.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Peter Longerich]] (15 April 2010). Holocaust: The Nazi Persecution and Murder of the Jews. Oxford University Press. p. 30. {{ISBN|978-0-19-280436-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="USHMM"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://digitalassets.ushmm.org/photoarchives/detail.aspx?id=10049&amp;search=EUTHANASIA+%28PATIENTS%2FVICTIMS%29&amp;index=25 | title=Close-up of Richard Jenne, the last child killed by the head nurse at the Kaufbeuren-Irsee euthanasia facility. | publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum | accessdate=July 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ian Kershaw]], ''Hitler: A Profile in Power'', Chapter VI, first section (London, 1991, rev. 2001)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Snyder, S. &amp; D. Mitchell. Cultural Locations of Disability. University of Michigan Press. 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Christian Identity]] is another movement closely tied to white supremacy. Some white supremacists identify themselves as [[Heathenry (new religious movement)|Odinists]], although many Odinists reject white supremacy. Some white supremacist groups, such as the [[South Africa]]n [[Boeremag]], conflate elements of [[Christianity]] and Odinism. [[Creativity (religion)|Creativity]] (formerly known as "The World Church of the Creator") is [[atheism|atheistic]] and it denounces Christianity and other [[Theism|theistic religions]].&lt;ref name="Atheistic"&gt;{{cite book|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=HB1wyFPRGm4C&amp;pg=PA23&amp;dq=atheism+white+supremacy#v=onepage&amp;q=atheistic&amp;f=false|title =The new white nationalism in America: its challenge to integration|publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]]|quote=For instance, Ben Klassen, founder of the atheistic Church of the Creator and author of ''The White Man's Bible'', discusses Christianity extensively in his writings and denounces it as a religion that has brought untold horror into the world and has divided the white race.|accessdate = 2011-03-27|isbn =9780521808866|date =2002-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Atheism"&gt;{{cite book|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=rBgn3xB75ZcC&amp;pg=PA493&amp;dq=competing+atheistic+white+racist+movement#v=onepage&amp;q=competing%20atheistic%20white%20racist%20movement&amp;f=false|title =The World's Religions: Continuities and Transformations|publisher = [[Taylor &amp; Francis]]|quote=A competing atheistic or panthestic white racist movement also appeared, which included the Church of the Creator/ Creativity (Gardell 2003: 129–34).|accessdate = 2011-03-27|isbn =9781135211004|date =2009-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aside from this, its ideology is similar to that of many Christian Identity groups because it believes in the [[List of conspiracy theories#Antisemitic conspiracy theories|antisemitic conspiracy theory]] that there is a "Jewish conspiracy" in control of governments, the banking industry and the media. [[Matthew F. Hale]], founder of the World Church of the Creator, has published articles stating that all races other than white are "mud races," which is what the group's religion teaches.&lt;ref name="law.jrank.org"/&gt;

The white supremacist ideology has become associated with a racist faction of the [[skinhead]] [[subculture]], despite the fact that when the skinhead culture first developed in the [[United Kingdom]] in the late 1960s, it was heavily influenced by [[black]] fashions and music, especially [[Jamaica]]n [[reggae]] and [[ska]], and African American [[soul music]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ska.about.com/musicperform/ska/library/1999/aa081699a.htm |title=Smiling Smash: An Interview with Cathal Smyth, a.k.a. Chas Smash, of Madness |accessdate=2001-02-19 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20010219175613/http://ska.about.com/musicperform/ska/library/1999/aa081699a.htm |archivedate=February 19, 2001 |df= }}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reggaereggaereggae.com/Special%20Articles.htm Special Articles&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081217000127/http://www.reggaereggaereggae.com/Special%20Articles.htm |date=2008-12-17 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="skinheads"&gt;{{cite book |last=Old Skool Jim |first= |title=Trojan Skinhead Reggae Box Set liner notes |publisher=Trojan Records |date= |location=London |id=TJETD169}}&lt;/ref&gt;

White supremacist recruitment activities are primarily conducted at a [[grassroots]] level as well as on the [[Internet]]. Widespread access to the Internet has led to a dramatic increase in white supremacist websites.&lt;ref name="Adversity"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=1Adams |first1=Josh |first2=Vincent J. |last2=Roscigno |title=White Supremacists, Oppositional Culture and the World Wide Web |work=University on North Carolina Press 84 (2005): 759–88 |date=20 November 2009 |jstor=3598477}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Internet provides a venue to openly express white supremacist ideas at little [[social cost]], because people who post the information are able to remain anonymous.

==See also==
{{colbegin|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Afrocentrism]]
*[[Alt-right]]
*[[Anti-miscegenation laws]]
*[[Aryan Brotherhood]]
*''[[The Birth of a Nation]]'' (movie)
*[[Black separatism]]
*[[Black supremacy]]
*[[Eurocentrism]]
*[[Hate group]]
*''[[Heroes of the Fiery Cross]]'' (book)
*[[Institutional racism]]
*[[Jim Crow laws]]
*[[Master race]]
*[[Neo-Confederate]]
*[[Race and intelligence]]
*[[Scientific racism]]
*[[Frances Cress Welsing]]
*"[[The White Man's Burden]]" (poem)
*[[White power music]]
*[[Superiority complex]]
*[[White nationalism]]
*[[List of white nationalist organizations]]
*[[White separatism]]
{{colend}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*Dobratz, Betty A. and Shanks-Meile, Stephanie. ''"White power, white pride!": The white separatist movement in the United States'' (JHU Press, 2000) {{ISBN|978-0-8018-6537-4}}
*Lincoln Rockwell, George. ''White Power'' (John McLaughlin, 1996)
*MacCann, Ronnarae. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=xj_T3QCgNgsC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=%22White+supremacy%22+juvenile White Supremacy in Children's Literature]'' (Routledge, 2000)

==External links==
* [http://www.docsonline.tv/Archives/description.php?doc=187 ''Heart of Whiteness'']—A documentary film about what it means to be white in South Africa
* [https://www.ushmm.org/confront-antisemitism/antisemitism-podcast/frank-meeink "Voices on Antisemitism"]—Interview with Frank Meeink from the [[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum|U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum]]
* [https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/acts-of-faith/wp/2017/08/14/russell-moore-white-supremacy-angers-jesus-but-does-it-anger-his-church/ "Russell Moore: White supremacy angers Jesus, but does it anger his church?" the president of the Ethics &amp; Religious Liberty Commission of the Southern Baptist Convention.]
{{white people}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:White Supremacy}}
[[Category:White supremacy| ]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Neo-fascism]]
[[Category:Neo-Nazi concepts]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination]]
[[Category:Racial segregation]]
[[Category:Racism in the United States]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Reconstruction Era]]
[[Category:Social history of the United States]]
[[Category:White nationalism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>