<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112185719|87376801" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33178" pageid="33178" ns="0" title="White supremacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-12T19:52:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''White supremacy''' is a [[racism|racist]] ideology which holds that the [[White (people)|white people]] are superior to other [[race]]s. 

White supremacy is often associated with anti-[[Black people|black]] racism and with [[anti-Semitism]], though it has also been used to justify [[prejudice]] and [[discrimination]] against other supposed ''non-white'' groups suchs as [[Asians]], [[Hispanics]], [[Arabs]], [[Native Americans]] and also [[Australian Aboriginals]]. There are different forms of white supremacy, with their own definitions of ''white.'' For example, [[Nordic theory|Nordicism]] classified [[southern Europe]]ans (i.e. [[Italian people|Italian]], [[Greeks|Greek]], [[Spanish people|Spanish]], [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]]) and [[eastern Europe]]ans (i.e. [[Poles|Polish]], [[Ukrainians|Ukranian]], [[Slavic peoples|Slav]]) as inferior non-white peoples, whereas pan-Europeanists would consider them as acceptable. People of [[multiracial|mixed race]] may also be targeted. 

The term ''white supremacy'' is sometimes specifically used to describe a philosophical belief that whites are not only superior to others, but should rule over them. [[White separatist]] and [[white nationalist]] groups often use this more limited definition in order to differentiate themselves from white supremacists, though these ideologies often overlap.

White supremacy, as with [[supremacism]] in general, is rooted in [[ethnocentrism]] and a desire for [[hegemony]]. It contains varying degrees of [[racism]] and [[xenophobia]]. White supremacy is often associated with [[ethnic cleansing]] and [[racial separation]].

A distinguishing feature of modern [[Nazism|Nazi]]-influenced white supremacy is the claim that [[white people]] are innately superior to some or all other races, and therefore should rule over them. White supremacists almost always believe that dark-skinned people (especially those with [[sub-Saharan Africa]]n ancestry) are inferior. Many consider certain white (non-[[Protestant]]s, [[atheist]]s, [[homosexuals]]) and non-white people ([[Jew]]s and [[Gypsies]]) to be inferior based on non-racial grounds.

==History==
In the 18th century, some [[naturalist]]s and [[philosophers]] — including [[David Hume]], [[Immanuel Kant]], [[Linnaeus]] and [[Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon|Georges-Louis Leclerc]] — promoted variations of white supremacy.{{fact}} Politically, socially and economically, white supremacy was dominant in the [[United States]] before the [[American Civil War]] and for decades after [[Reconstruction]]. The same is true of [[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|Apartheid-era]] [[South Africa]] and of parts of [[Europe]] at various time periods; most notably under [[Nazi]] [[Germany]]'s [[Third Reich]]. The extent and nature of white supremacy's continuing influence in western culture is a subject of ongoing debate.

In some parts of the [[United States]], many non-whites were disenfranchised and prevented from holding government office (or even serving in most government jobs) well into the second half of the twentieth century; [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] in the U.S. and [[First Nations|Canada]] and [[Australian Aborigine|Aborigines]] in [[Australia]] were often viewed as obstacles to progress, rather than settlers in their own right; many European-settled countries bordering the [[Pacific Ocean]] at times limited immigration and naturalization from the Asian Pacific countries, usually on a cultural basis; the United States in some states banned interracial marriage until 1967 (see ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]''); [[Rhodesia]] (modern [[Zimbabwe]]) held out as an overtly white supremacist regime until 1979, and [[South Africa]] into the 1990s.{{fact}}

==Contemporary white supremist ideologies==
There is considerable variation amongst different groups of white supremacists as to who they classify as ''white,'' and which races or other groups they claim to be superior to. 

===Nordicism===
Those who follow the ideology of ''[[Nordic theory|Nordicism]]'' and ''[[Germanicism]]'' only consider Northern European people who are Nordic or Germanic (and often Celtic) to be white, shunning Southern and Eastern Europe along with anyone whose ethnic heritage is not European. In [[Madison Grant]]'s 1916 book, ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'', Europeans who were not of Germanic origin and had Nordic characteristics such as blonde hair and light eyes were considered to be a Nordic admixture and suitable for [[Aryanization]]. &lt;ref name="Grant1916"&gt;[[Madison Grant|Grant, Madison]]. ''The Passing of the Great Race''. Charles Scribner's Sons, New York, 1916.&lt;/ref&gt; These beliefs were central to [[Nazism]] and lay at the core of the [[Nordic theory]].

===Pan Europeanism===
''Pan Europeanism'' accepts all native and original European peoples, ranging from fair skinned [[Sweden|Swedes]], [[Great Britian|Britons]] and [[Germany|Germans]] to darker complexioned Italians, Spaniards, Portuguese, and Greeks.

===Pan Aryanism===
Another variant, ''Pan Aryanism'', accepts native Europeans from all of continental Europe and extends its acceptance to non-European Caucasoids, such as some Middle Easterners, North Africans, and Central/West Asians. Yet this is usually on an individual basis and not all people from these regions are accepted by Pan-Aryanists as white. With regard to the acceptance of Middle Easterners in Pan-aryanist ideology, Syrians, Lebanese, [[Turkish people|Turks]] (who are often considered European), and Iranians are accepted as white, but Saudis and Yemenites ''as a whole'' are not.

South Asian Caucasoids (Pakistanis, Northern Indians etc) ''as a whole'' may generally not be accepted in this ideology as well, however some Pan-Aryanists acknowledge and have disputing beliefs on lighter skinned people descended from [[Aryans]] in this region. An example is a textbook for those taking entrance examinations for the [[British Civil Service]] in the early 1900s categorically stated that [[Afghan people|Afghans]] and [[Berber people|Berbers]] were in the highest classification, along with Northern Europeans, but above the [[Spanish people|Spanish]] and [[Italian people|Italians]] &lt;ref name=gotw1904&gt;''Geography of the World''. [[British Civil Service|Civil Service]] Book Depot, 1904.&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Religious movements===
In the United States, some claim white supremacist movements are linked to [[fundamentalist]] [[Christianity]], but most Christians denounce the movement as fundamentally non-Christian. The [[Christian Identity]] movement, which tends to regard other branches of Christianity as heretical, is closely tied to white supremacism. Some white supremacists such as [[Matthew F. Hale]], consider violence to be a legitimate way to further their cause and dismiss mainstream Christianity as a mongrel or "suicidal" faith. Hale's group, the [[Creativity Movement]] is an atheist organization that depises Christianity and worships its own ethnicity.{{fact}}

Other white supremacist groups identify themselves as [[Ásatrú|Odinists]]. Most Odinists reject white supremacism, and white supremacists make up only a small fraction of those who believe in Odinism. The white supremacist version of Odinism believes that the universe is composed of "worlds of light" (white people) and "worlds of dark" (non-white people).{{fact}} Odinists believe in the old [[Norse mythology|Norse gods]] and do not believe in the divinity of [[Jesus]]. Some groups, such as the [[South Africa]]n [[Boeremag]], conflate elements of Christianity and Odinism.

Not all white supremacist groups adhere to [[Christian Identity]] or other religious doctrines. Groups such as the [[American Nazi Party]] or the Greek [[Hrisi Avgi]] are largely politically, rather than religiously, motivated. The [[Ku Klux Klan]]'s reasons for supporting racial segregation are not primarily based on religious ideals, although some Klan groups are openly [[Christian Identity]] or [[Protestant]], with some branches now accepting [[Roman Catholic]] members.{{fact}}

==Contemporary white supremacist groups==
White supremacist groups can be found in most countries with a significant white population, including the [[United States]], [[Canada]], [[Australia]], [[New Zealand]], [[South Africa]], [[Europe]] and parts of [[Latin America]]. In all of these places, their views represent a relatively small minority of the population, and active membership of the groups is quite small. However, a [[backlash]] to the influx of non-white immigrants into various European nations has spurred a rise in membership in such organizations, as well as an escalation in white supremacist demonstrations and [[hate crimes]].{{fact}}

The militant approach taken by some groups has caused them to be watched closely by law enforcement officials. In some [[European countries]], white supremacist groups are banned by various laws. These include laws that forbid [[hate speech]], in addition to laws that forbid organizations deemed to be fundamentally opposed to any multi-ethnic, multi-racial, and democratic society.

Many white supremacist organizations seem to have shown a tendency to splinter easily, and modern-day white supremacist movements existing on the Internet show a great deal of strife within the movement. Different groups and individuals have feuds and rivalries. It could be observed that too many people within the movement want to be leaders as opposed to followers. Less extreme white supremacists, along with followers of and groups associated with [[white nationalism]] and [[paleo-conservatism]] are considered to be cowards and traitors by a lot of white supremacists, the latter two groups reciprocating with a conviction that white supremacists and neo-Nazis especially make them all look bad.

==Violent actions==
The World Church of the Creator, now called the [[Creativity Movement]], presents a recent example of violence perpetrated by white supremacists. [[Ben Klassen]], the sect's founder, believed that a person's race is his religion. Aside from this central belief, its ideology is similar to many Christian Identity groups, in the conviction that there is a Jewish [[Conspiracy theory|conspiracy]] in control of the federal government, international banking, and the media. They dictate that ''RAHOWA,'' a [[Racial Holy War]], is destined to ensue , to rid the world of Jews and "mud races." In the early 1990s, there was a dramatic increase in membership due to the growing belief in the [[apocalypse]], and that ''RAHOWA'' was imminent. In 1996, [[Matthew F. Hale]], who was denied a license to practice law in Illinois, was appointed the leader of the Church of the Creator. Hale made a number of changes to the group, including changing the name of the organization to the World Church of the Creator. The TE-TA-MA "Truth" Foundation's [[Church of the Creator]] legally trademarked the name ''Church of the Creator'' and won a lawsuit in 1996.[http://www.churchofthecreator.org/TM/TMindex.html]

WCOTC members in Southern Florida are thought to be tied to several racially motivated beatings. Within the last year, four Florida members were convicted for the pistol-whipping and robbery of a Jewish video store owner. They were supposedly trying to raise money for a revolution.{{fact}}

==List of white supremacists==
The people listed here are current or recent supporters of white supremacy. (Note that many people in the "[[White Power]]" movement regard themselves as [[Racial segregation|racial separatists]] or [[Nationalism#Racism|racial nationalists]] and publicly denounce supremacism. 

{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}

'''Australia'''
* [[Jack van Tongeren]]
* [[Jim Saleam]]

'''Canada'''
* [[Don Andrews]]
* [[Glenn Bahr]]
* [[William John Beattie]]
* [[Raphael Bergmann]]
* [[Wolfgang Droege]]
* [[Paul Fromm]]
* [[Melissa Guille]]
* [[Peter Kouba]]
* [[Alex Kulbashian]]
* [[Marc Lemire]]
* [[Jason Ouwendyk]]
* [[James Scott Richardson]]
* [[Terry Tremaine]]
* [[Donna Upson]]
* [[Martin Weiche]]
* [[Tomasz Winnicki]]
* [[Ernst Zündel]] (now in Germany)

'''Germany'''
* [[Horst Mahler]]
* [[Christian Worch]]

'''Norway'''
* [[Varg Vikernes]]

'''South Africa'''
* [[Eugène Terre'Blanche]]

'''Sweden'''
* [[Robert Vesterlund]]

{{col-2}}

'''United Kingdom'''
* [[John Bean]]
* [[Andrew Brons]]
* [[Mark Collett]]
* [[David Copeland]]
* [[Ray Hill]]
* [[Derek Holland]]
* [[Tom Holmes]]
* [[Colin Jordan]]
* [[David Kerr]]
* [[Michael McLaughlin]]
* [[David Myatt]]
* [[Charlie Sargent]]
* [[John Tyndall (politician)|John Tyndall]]
* [[Richard Verrall]]
* [[Martin Webster]]
* [[Martin Wingfield]]

'''United States of America'''
* [[Louis Beam]]
* [[Don Black (nationalist)|Don Black]]
* [[Richard Girnt Butler]]
* [[Willis Carto]]
* [[Frank Collin]]
* [[David Duke]]
* [[Leo Felton]]
* [[Matthew F. Hale]]
* [[August Kreis III]]
* [[David Lane (Neo-Nazi)|David Lane]]
* [[Alex Linder]]
* [[Martin Lindstedt]]
* [[James Mason (National Socialist)|James Mason]]
* [[Tom Metzger]]
* [[Glenn Miller (White Patriot Party)|Glenn Miller]]
* [[William Luther Pierce]]
* [[Ingrid Rimland]]
* [[Jeff Schoep]]
* [[Benjamin Nathaniel Smith]]
* [[Hal Turner]]
* [[Bill White (neo-Nazi)|Bill White]]
* [[James Wickstrom]]

{{col-end}}

==List of organizations==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Afrikaner Weerstandsbeweging]]
* [[American Front]]
* [[American Nazi Party]]
* [[Aryan Brotherhood]]
* [[Aryan Nations]]
* [[Australia First]]
* [[Blood and Honour]] 
* [[British National Front]]
* [[Canadian Ethnic Cleansing Team]]
* [[Canadian Heritage Alliance]]
* [[Church of the Rahowa]] 
* [[Combat 18]]
* [[Council of Conservative Citizens]]
* [[Confederate Hammer Skins]]
* [[Creativity Movement]] (formerly World Church of the Creator)
* [[Forsyth County Defense League]]
* [[Hammerskin Nation]] 
* [[Heritage Front]] 
* [[Hrisi Avgi]]
* [[Ku Klux Klan]] 
{{col-break}}
* [[Libertarian National Socialist Green Party]]
* [[National Alliance]]
* [[National Association for the Advancement of White People]]
* [[National Socialist Movement of Denmark]]
* [[National Socialist Movement (United Kingdom)]]
* [[National Socialist Movement (United States)]] 
* [[Nationalist Party of Canada]]
* [[Northern Alliance (White supremacist organization)]]
* [[Imperium Europa]]
* [[Patriotic Youth League]]
* [[Russian National Unity]]
* [[The Order (group)|The Order]]
* [[The Posse Comitatus]]
* [[Tri-City Skins]]
* [[Vigrid]]
* [[Volksfront]]
* [[Westboro Baptist Church]]
* [[Western Canada For Us]]
* [[White Aryan Resistance]] 
* [[White Citizens' Council]]
* [[White Patriot Party]]
{{col-end}}

==See also==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Apartheid]]
* [[Dixiecrat]]
* [[Eugenics]]
* [[Institutional racism]]
* [[Jim Crow law]]
* [[Lynchings]]
* [[Master race]]
* [[nadir of American race relations]]
* [[Neo-Nazi groups of the United States]]
* [[Nordic theory]]
* [[Pigmentocracy]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[White Australia policy]]
* [[Zionist Occupation Government]]

{{col-break}}
===Compare===
* [[Black supremacy]]
* [[Racism]] and [[anti-racism]]
* [[Asian power]], [[Black power]] and [[White Power]]
* [[Asian pride]], [[Black pride]] and [[White pride]]
* [[White nationalism]] and [[Black nationalism]]
* [[White separatism]] and [[Black separatism]]
* [[Kahanism]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
''Alleged or stated white supremacist websites:''
*[http://www.awb.co.za Afrikaner Wehrstandsbewegung web site]
*[http://www.solargeneral.com Solar General]
*[http://bnp.org.uk BNP web site]
*[http://www.imperium-europa.org Imperium Europa] 
*[http://www.stormfront.org Stormfront home page]
*[http://www.nationalvanguard.org/ National Vanguard home] 
*[http://www.natall.com/ National Alliance home page] 
*[http://www.govnn.com Vanguard News Network home page]
*[http://www.panf.info/upload/index.php?styleid=1 Pan-Aryan National Front home page]
*[http://www.thephora.net/forum/index.php The Phora - A Culture of Racialism]
*[http://www.originaldissent.com/forums/index.php Original Dissent Forum (White Supremacist/Christian Nationalist fusion site)]
* [http://www.aryan-nations.org Aryan Nations website] - Led by [[August Kreis III]]
* [http://www.kkkau.com Australian Website against racism]
*[http://resist.com The Insurgent] (AKA White Aryan Resistance) [[Tom Metzger]]'s website
&lt;!-- Categorization --&gt;

&lt;!-- Localization --&gt;

[[Category:Neo-Nazi movements and concepts]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Ethnic supremacy]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Political theories]]

[[es:Supremacismo blanco]]
[[ja:白人至上主義]]
[[pl:Biała supremacja]]
[[fi:Valkoinen ylivalta]]
[[sv:Vit makt]]
[[zh:白人至上主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>