<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041106225450|7170990" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33178" pageid="33178" ns="0" title="White supremacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-06T22:55:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''white supremacy movement''' considers [[white]] people to be superior to people of other (and of mixed) [[race|races]] and/or [[ethnicity|ethnicities]]. Members often term the movement '''White Pride''' or '''White Power'''.

==Ideology==

White supremacists are vehemently opposed to racial mixing, especially [[interracial]] relationships and marriages. Keeping white "blood" pure is a major tenet of the movement. White supremacists make many claims about the intellectual, ethical and spiritual inferiority of [[black#Human|blacks]], [[Jew]]s, [[Hispanic]]s, [[Asian]]s, [[Arab]]s, Non-[[Protestant]]s, [[atheist]]s, and [[homosexuality|homosexuals]]. (''See also'': [[Race and intelligence]], ''[[The Bell Curve]]''.) Some [[White separatist]]s claim that they do not wish to harm non-white people, but rather they only wish to keep their blood or genes pure.

These beliefs have much in common with [[Nazism]]. Some white supremacist groups, particularly in German-speaking countries, actively proclaim themselves Nazis, and the groups are commonly collectively labelled [[neo-Nazi]].

In the United States white supremacy movements are sometimes linked to [[fundamentalist]] [[Christianity]] or [[Christian Identity]], but most Christians, even those who identify themselves as "fundamentalists", denounce the movement as fundamentally non-Christian. Some white supremacists consider violence to be a legitimate way to further their cause.

Some white supremacy groups identify themselves as [[Asatru|Odinists]],. The white supremacist version of Odinism has little to do with Christian Identity but there is one key similarity: their version of Odinism provides dualism - as does Christian Identity - with regard to the universe being made up of worlds of light (white people) and worlds of dark (non-white people). The most fundamental difference between the two ideologies is that Odinists believe in the old [[Norse mythology|Norse gods]], and do not believe in the divinity of [[Jesus Christ]]. However, there are enough similarities between the myths and legends of Odinism and the beliefs of Christian Identity to make a smooth transition from Christian Identity to Odinism for some racist individuals. Some groups, such as the [[South Africa]]n [[Boeremag]], even conflate elements of Christianity and Odinism.

Many white supremacy groups do not necessarily adhere to [[Christian Identity]] or other religious doctrines. White supremacy groups such as the [[American Nazi Party]] are largely politically, rather than religiously, motivated. The [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK), one of the most recognized white supremacist groups in the United States, proposes racial segregation that is not generally based on religious ideals.

==Distribution and prominence==

White supremacist groups can be found in most countries with a significant white population, including the [[United States]], [[Europe]], parts of Latin America, [[Australia]], and [[South Africa]].  However, in all of these places, their views represent a small minority of the population, and active membership of the groups is quite small.  

The militant approach taken by some groups has caused them to be watched closely by law enforcement officials. In some European countries, which have more recent experience of the effect of such beliefs in [[World War II]], white supremacist groups are banned by various laws. These include laws which forbid [[hate speech]] in addition to laws that forbid organisations who are deemed to be fundamentally opposed to any multi-ethnic, multi-racial, and democratic society.

==Violent activism==

The National Alliance is probably best known for its former leader, [[William Luther Pierce|William Pierce]], who was one of the most recognized names in the [[White separatist]] movement (the National Alliance maintains its position is White separatist, rather than white supremacy). Pierce wrote ''[[The Turner Diaries]]'' and hosted a weekly radio program, ''American Dissident Voices''. Via these outlets, Pierce was able to provide his followers with an ideological and practical framework for committing violent acts. The rhetoric of these groups largely shadows that of [[Adolf Hitler]]'s in content and in political ideology. Pierce's religion, [[cosmotheism]] , was influenced by ideas of "racial purity" and [[eugenics]]. In 1997, Pierce stated that:

:"Ultimately we must separate ourselves from the Blacks and other non-whites and keep ourselves separate, no matter what it takes to accomplish this. We must do this not because we hate Blacks, but because we cannot survive if we remain mixed with them. And we cannot survive if we permit the Jews and the traitors among us to remain among us and to repeat their treachery. Eventually we must hunt them down and get rid of them."

The World Church of the Creator, now called the [[Creativity Movement]], presents a recent example of violence perpetrated by a white supremacist in order to bring about a race war. [[Ben Klassen]], the sect's founder, believed that one's race is his religion. Aside from this central belief, its ideology is similar to many Christian Identity groups in the conviction that there is a Jewish [[conspiracy]] in control of the federal government, international banking, and the media. They also dictate that RAHOWA, a [[Racial Holy War|RAcial HOly WAr]], is destined to ensue to rid the world of Jews and &amp;#8220;mud races.&amp;#8221;  In the early 1990s, there was a dramatic increase in membership due to the growing belief in the Apocalypse and that RAHOWA was imminent. In 1996, [[Matthew Hale|Matt Hale]], who came upon recent fame by being denied a license to practice law in Illinois, was appointed the new leader of the Church of the Creator. Hale made a number of changes to the group, including changing the name of the organization to the World Church of the Creator, to give it the feel of a widespread movement.

Recent incidents have demonstrated the willingness of members to take part in violent action. WCOTC members in Southern Florida are thought to be tied to several racially motivated beatings. Within the last year, four Florida members were convicted for the pistol-whipping and robbery of a Jewish video store owner. They were supposedly trying to raise money for "the revolution."

Many believe in the necessity of becoming martyrs for their cause. For example, [[Robert Jay Mathews|Bob Mathews]], the leader of [[The Order (group)|The Order]], died in a confrontation with law enforcement. Also, William King relished the fact that he would receive the death penalty for his act of murdering James Byrd, Jr.

==White Supremacy organizations==

* [[Afrikaner Weerstandsbeweging]] (AWB) (South Africa)
* [[American Nazi Party]]
* [[Aryan Brotherhood]]
* [[Aryan Nations]]
* [[Christian Conservative Church]]
* [[Christian Identity]]
* [[Combat 18]] (British Group)
* [[Heritage Front]]
* [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK)
* [[National Alliance]] ''(The group disputes this categorization, labelling itself "[[White separatist]]")''
* [[Nationalist Party of Canada]]
* [[New Zealand National Front]]
* [[The Posse Comitatus]]
* [[The Order (group)|The Order]]
* [[White Aryan Resistance]] (WAR)
* [[White Patriot Party]]
* World Church of the Creator/[[Creativity Movement]] (WCOTC)
* [[White Revolution (white supremacist)]]: a recent group to emerge, led by Billy Roper

==See also==

* [[Master race]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Eugenics]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Apartheid]]
* [[Zionist Occupation Government]]
* [[Stormfront]]
* ''[[American History X]]''
* ''Compare:'' [[Black supremacy]], [[Black power]]

[[Category:Neo-Nazi movements and concepts]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>