<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081114181431|251808619" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33178" pageid="33178" ns="0" title="White supremacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T02:01:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''White supremacy''' is the belief that [[white people]] are superior to other [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial groups]]. The term is sometimes used specifically to describe a [[political ideology]] that advocates the [[Society|social]] and [[Politics|political]] dominance of whites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Privilege Revealed: How Invisible Preference |last=Wildman |first=Stephanie M. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1996 |publisher=NYU Press |location= |isbn=0814793037 |pages=p. 87}}&lt;/ref&gt;

White supremacy, as with racial [[supremacism]] in general, is rooted in [[ethnocentrism]] and a desire for [[hegemony]]{{Fact|date=November 2008}}. It is associated with varying degrees of racism as well as a desire for [[racial separation]]. White supremacy has often resulted in anti-[[Black people|black]] racism and [[antisemitism]].{{Fact|date=November 2008}}

Different forms of white supremacy have different conceptions of [[whiteness]], and not all white supremacist organizations agree on which group is their greatest enemy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Spaces of Hate: Geographies of Discrimination and Intolerance in the U.S.A. |last=Flint  |first=Colin |year=2004 |publisher=Routledge |location= |isbn=0415935865 |pages=53 |quote=Although white racist activists must adopt a political identity of whiteness, the flimsy definition of whiteness in modern cultrue poses special challenges for them. In both mainstream and white supremacist discourse, to be white os to be distinct from those marked as nonwhite, yet the placement of the distinguishing line has varied significantly in different times and places. }}&lt;/ref&gt; White supremacists frequently consider [[Jew]]s to be the gravest threat to their cause, because Jews are thought to be able to assimilate much more easily than other ethnic groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Hate Crimes: Causes, Controls, and Controversies |last=Gerstenfeld |first=Phyllis B. |year=2003 |publisher=
Sage Publications Inc. |location= |isbn=0761928146 |pages=155 |quote=The third reason that Jews may be so vilified is that, compared with people of color, they can much more easily assimilate; they can easily "pass." This represents a particular threat to white supremacy because Jews can infiltrate the white power structure in a way that people of color cannot. }} &lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Politically, socially and economically, white supremacy was dominant in the [[United States]] before the [[American Civil War]] and for decades after [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]]; a core, unifying part of the separate Southern identity at the outbreak of the War was an uncompromising commitment to white supremacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Fredrickson | first = George | title = White Supremacy | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford Oxfordshire | year = 1981 | isbn = 0195030427 |pages=p.162}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same is true of [[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|Apartheid-era South Africa]] and of parts of [[Europe]] at various time periods; most notably under [[Nazi Germany]]'s [[Third Reich]]. The extent and nature of white supremacy's continuing influence in western culture is a subject of ongoing debate. In some parts of the United States, many people who were considered non-white were [[Disfranchisement|disenfranchised]], barred from government office, and prevented from holding most government jobs — well into the second half of the twentieth century. White leaders often viewed [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] (known as [[First Nations]] in [[Canada]]) and [[Australian Aborigine]]s as obstacles to economic and political progress, rather than as [[settler]]s in their own right. Many [[Europe]]an-settled countries bordering the [[Pacific Ocean]] limited immigration and naturalization from the Asian Pacific countries, usually on a cultural basis. Many [[U.S. state]]s banned [[interracial marriage]] through so-called "[[anti-miscegenation laws]]" until 1967, when these laws were declared unconstitutional. [[South Africa]] maintained its white supremacist-like Apartheid system until the early 1990s.

The white supremacist ideology has become associated with a [[Racism|racist]] faction of the [[skinhead]] [[subculture]], despite the fact that when the skinhead scene first developed in the [[United Kingdom]] in the late 1960s, it was heavily influenced by [[Jamaica]]n [[rude boy]]s and British [[Mod (lifestyle)|mods]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20010219175613/ska.about.com/musicperform/ska/library/1999/aa081699a.htm Smiling Smash: An Interview with Cathal Smyth, a.k.a Chas Smash, of Madness]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reggaereggaereggae.com/Special%20Articles.htm Special Articles&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="skinheads"&gt;{{cite book |last=Old Skool Jim |first= |title=Trojan Skinhead Reggae Box Set liner notes |publisher=Trojan Records |date= |location=London |id=TJETD169}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the 1980s, 
a sizable and vocal [[white power skinhead]] faction had formed.{{Fact|date=December 2007}}

==White supremacist movements and ideologies==
White supremacist groups can be found in most countries and regions with a significant white population, including [[North America]], [[Europe]], [[Australia]],  [[New Zealand]], [[South Africa]], and  [[Latin America]]. In all of these locations, their views represent a relatively small minority of the population, and active membership of the groups is quite small. However, a [[backlash]] to the influx of non-white immigrants into various European nations has spurred a rise in membership in such organizations,{{when?}} as well as an escalation in militant white supremacist demonstrations. The militant approach taken by white supremacist groups has caused them to be watched closely by law enforcement officials. Some European countries have laws forbidding [[hate speech]], as well as other laws that ban or restrict some white supremacist organizations but not all.

===Pan Aryanism===
Another variant, ''Pan Aryanism'', accepts native Europeans from all of continental Europe and extends its acceptance to non-European Caucasoids, such as some Middle Easterners, North Africans, and Central/West/South Asians. Yet this is usually on an individual basis and not all people from these regions are accepted by Pan-Aryanists as white. The acceptance of Middle Easterners in Pan-Aryanist ideology, Syrians, Lebanese, [[Turkish people|Turks]], and Persians are accepted as white, but Saudis and Yemenites ''as a whole'' are not.{{Or|date=November 2008}}

South Asian Caucasoids (Pakistanis, Northern Indians etc) ''as a whole'' may generally not be accepted in this ideology as well, however some Pan-Aryanists acknowledge and have disputing beliefs on lighter skinned people descended from [[Indo-Europeans]] in this region. An example is a textbook for those taking entrance examinations for the [[British Civil Service]] in the early 1900s categorically stated that [[Afghan people|Afghans]] and [[Berber people|Berbers]] were in the highest classification, along with Northern Europeans, but above the [[Spanish people|Spanish]] and [[Italians]]. &lt;ref name=gotw1904&gt;''Geography of the World''. [[British Civil Service|Civil Service]] Book Depot, 1904.&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Nordicism===
Those who follow the ideology of ''[[Nordic theory|Nordicism]]'' and ''[[Germanism]]'' consider Northern European people who are Nordic (Scandinavians, Germans, and Dutch) to be superior, shunning those of Southern and Eastern Europe (who may have darker features and different cultures) along with anyone whose ethnic heritage is not European. In [[Madison Grant]]'s 1916 book, ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'', Europeans who were not of Germanic origin and had Nordic characteristics such as blonde hair and light eyes were considered to be a Nordic admixture and suitable for [[Aryanization]].&lt;ref name="Grant1916"&gt;[[Madison Grant|Grant, Madison]]. ''The Passing of the Great Race''. Charles Scribner's Sons, New York, 1916.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religious movements===
[[Image:Klan-in-gainesville.jpg|thumb|left|Members of the second [[Ku Klux Klan]] at a rally in 1923.]]
The [[Christian Identity]] movement, which is regarded by other branches of [[Christianity]] as heretical, is closely tied to white supremacy.{{Fact|date=November 2008}} Although the [[Ku Klux Klan]]'s reasons for supporting [[racial segregation]] are not primarily based on religious ideals, some Klan groups are openly Christian [[Protestant]] because of their northern European/Germanic roots.
Some white supremacists identify themselves as [[Ásatrú|Odinists]], although most Odinists reject white supremacy, and white supremacists make up only a small fraction of those who support Odinism (belief in the gods of [[Norse mythology]]). Some white supremacist groups, such as the [[South Africa]]n [[Boeremag]], conflate elements of Christianity and Odinism.

The World Church of the Creator, now called the [[Creativity Movement]], believed that a person's race is his [[religion]]. Aside from this central belief, its ideology is similar to many Christian Identity groups, in the conviction that there is a [[Jew]]ish [[Conspiracy theory|conspiracy]] in control of the [[United States]] government, international banking, and the media. They claim that a [[Racial Holy War]] (''RAHOWA''), is destined to happen, which would eliminate Jews and "mud races" from the planet. In the early 1990s, there was a dramatic increase in membership, due to the growing belief in the [[apocalypse]].

==See also==
* [[Apartheid]], a system of rule by white people in South Africa
* [[Institutional racism]], racism created and reinforced by institutional power structures
* [[Master race]], the belief that one race is or ought to be dominant
* [[Race and intelligence]], a body of research investigating the differences in intelligence between races
* [[White Australia policy]], an immigration policy in 20th century Australia which discriminated in favour of white people
* [[Jim Crow laws]], racist laws made in the Southern United States during the 19th and 20th Centuries

== Footnotes ==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Dobratz, Betty A. and Shanks-Meile, Stephanie. ''"White power, white pride!": The white separatist movement in the United States'' (Twayne Publishers, NY, 1997).
* Lincoln Rockwell, George. ''White Power'' (John McLaughlin, 1996).

==External links==
*[http://reactor-core.org/white-power.html "White Power" by George Lincoln Rockwell]
*[http://www.adl.org/hate_symbols/music.asp Anti-Defamation League article on white power music]
{{white people}}
{{White supremist organizations}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Neo-Nazi movements and concepts]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:White supremacy| ]]

[[de:White Supremacy]]
[[es:Supremacismo blanco]]
[[ko:백인 우월주의]]
[[id:Supremasi putih]]
[[he:כוח לבן (גזענות)]]
[[ja:白人至上主義]]
[[pl:Biała supremacja]]
[[pt:Supremacia branca]]
[[fi:Valkoinen ylivalta]]
[[sv:Vit makt]]
[[zh:白人優越主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>