<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020805124916|366590" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33178" pageid="33178" ns="0" title="White supremacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-10-18T13:18:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The &lt;b&gt;white supremacy movement&lt;/b&gt; considers white people to be superior to people of other (and of mixed) [[race|races]] and/or [[ethnicity|ethnicities]]. White supremacy is sometimes linked to other extreme right views including [[fundamentalist]] [[Christianity]], but even fundamentalist Christians usually denounce the movement. Many white supremacists consider violence to be a legitimate way to further their cause. White supremacy groups are usually dominated by men.

White supremacist groups can be found in most countries with a significant white population, including the [[United States]], most of [[Europe]] (notably including [[Germany]]), and [[Australia]].  However, in all of these places, their views represent a small minority of the population, and active membership of the groups is quite small.  

White supremacists make many claims about the supposed intellectual, ethical and spiritual inferiority of blacks, [[Jews]], Hispanics, Asians and [[homophobia|homosexuals]]. (See [[race and intelligence]], [[The Bell Curve]])

White supremacists do not usually call themselves by that name. They often refer to themselves as White Pride or White Power. They claim that they do not wish to harm non-white people, but rather they only wish to keep their blood pure. They are vehemently opposed to racial mixing, especially interracial relationships and marriages. Keeping "white blood" pure is a major tenet of the movement.

These beliefs have much in common with [[Nazism]], and some white supremacist groups, particularly in German-speaking countries, actively proclaim themselves Nazis.  

Many white supremacy groups believe that a [[race war]] is going to happen soon. Some have armed themselves and built quasi-military installations in remote locations, where they expect to hold out through the coming race war.

The militant approach taken by some groups, such as those who are preparing for race war, have caused some of them to be watched closely by law enforcement officials.  

In some European countries, which have more recent experience of the effect of such beliefs in [[World War II]], white supremacist groups are banned by various laws.

Compare: [[Black supremacy]], [[Black power]]

See also: [[racism]], [[Ku Klux Klan]], [[Aryan Brotherhood]], [[apartheid]], [[Matthew Hale]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>