<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051110215933|27961669" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33178" pageid="33178" ns="0" title="White supremacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T08:42:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''White supremacy''' is an ideology which holds that the [[whites|white race]] is superior to other [[race|races]]. White supremacy is most often thought of in connection with anti-black [[racism]] and [[anti-Semitism]], though it has also been used to justify [[discrimination]] against [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]], [[Chinese people|Chinese]], [[Irish people|Irish]], [[Southeast Asia]]ns, [[Arabs]] and others. 

For example, politically, socially and economically, the United States before and after [[Reconstruction]] was white supremacist, as was [[apartheid]]-era [[South Africa]]. The extent and nature of white supremacy's continuing influence in Western culture is a subject of ongoing debate.

White supremacy is sometimes used in a more limited sense to indicate a philosophical belief that whites are not only superior to others, but should rule over them.  [[White separatist]] and [[white nationalist]] groups often use this more limited definition in order to distinguish themselves from white supremacists.

White supremacy, as with [[supremacism]] in general, is rooted in [[ethnocentrism]] and a desire for [[hegemony]]. It contains varying degrees of [[racism]] and [[xenophobia]]. Associations of white supremacy with [[ethnic cleansing]] and [[racial separation]] are common, but not necessarily intrinsic.

== White supremacy in the United States ==
In many states of the [[United States]], non-whites were effectively disenfranchised and prevented from holding government office (or even serving in most government jobs) well into the second half of the 20th century; [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] in the U.S. and [[First Nations|Canada]] and [[Australian Aborigine|Aborigines]] in [[Australia]] were often viewed as little more than obstacles to white settlement, rather than human beings in their own right; many European-settled countries bordering the [[Pacific Ocean]] at times severely limited immigration and naturalization from the Asian Pacific countries, usually on an overtly white supremacist basis; the United States allowed individual states to ban interracial marriage as late as 1967 (see ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]''); [[Rhodesia]] held out as an overtly white supremacist regime until 1979 and [[South Africa]] into the 1990s.

In the United States, the ideology of white supremacy was particularly strong. At the time of the nation's founding, there were African American [[slavery|slaves]] even in such northern states as [[New York]]. The U.S. [[United States Southern States|South]] until the [[United States Civil War|Civil War]] sustained a plantation economy based on [[blacks|Black]] slaves. Even in those parts of the South where African Americans constituted the majority, except for the brief period of the [[Reconstruction]] (1866-1877), they were routinely disenfranchised; resistance was successfully held down by state and local governments and by organizations such as the [[Ku Klux Klan]] who, as late as the early 1960s practiced [[Lynching in the United States|lynching]]&amp;mdash;extra-judicial execution&amp;mdash;with impunity.

In the rest of the United States, the regime was generally milder, but&amp;mdash;again, at least into the second half of the 20th century&amp;mdash;non-whites were generally expected to "know their place". For example, few of the country's leading colleges and universities admitted non-white students, or if they did, they admitted them under very restrictive quotas. These restrictions applied not only to African Americans, but also, during much of the 19th and 20th centuries, to Asians, Native Americans, and Jews. Those African Americans who received a higher education mostly did so in what are now known as the [[Historically Black colleges and universities]]. Few African Americans held public office: after Reconstruction, no African American served in the [[United States Senate]] until [[Edward W. Brooke]] in 1966.  There has never been a non-white United States president. [[George Ariyoshi]] of [[Hawaii]] became, in 1974, the first [[Asian American]] governor of a state.

[[Charles W. Mills]] argues (Racial Contract, 1997) that 'White supermacy' is a [[political system]], or at least forms a part of most of today's political systems.

==Ideology in contemporary White Supremacy==

While white supremacists share with white separatists a general opposition to racial mixing, especially [[interracial]] relationships and marriages, a distinguishing feature of modern [[Nazi]]-influenced white supremacy is the claim that [[Whites]] who are [[Nordic]] or [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] should rule over [[Blacks]], [[Jew]]s, [[Muslim]]s, [[Hispanic]]s, [[Asian]]s, [[Southern European]]s, [[Eastern European]]s, [[Middle Easterner]]s, [[North African]]s, non-[[Protestant]]s, [[atheist]]s, and [[homosexuality|homosexuals]] by virtue of the supposed innate superiority of so-called "pure" whites, upon which white supremacy is posited. (''See also'': [[Race and intelligence]], ''[[The Bell Curve]]''.) 

There are different types of white supremacy; groups that would generally be classified as White supremacist may vary greatly in their ideology of race. White supremacists who follow the ideology of ''Nordicism'' and ''Germanicism'' only consider Northern European people who are Nordic or Germanic to be white, shunning Southern and Eastern Europe. ''Pan Europeanism'' is a White supremacist belief that accepts all native Europeans as White, a population that ranges from fair skinned Swedes to dark skinned Italians. Then there is ''Pan Aryanism'', which accepts native Europeans from all of continental Europe and extends its definition to non-European Caucasoids such as some Middle Easterners, North Africans, and Central/West Asians. Yet not all Middle Easterners, North Africans and Central/West Asians are accepted by Pan-Aryanists as white. With regard to the acceptance of Middle Easterners from Pan Aryan White supremacists, Syrians, Lebanese, Turks (not as often as the other two), and Iranians are accepted as White, but Saudis and Yemenites are not.

These beliefs have much in common with [[Nazism]]. Some white supremacist groups, particularly in German-speaking countries, actively proclaim themselves Nazis; and, collectively, the groups commonly are labeled [[neo-Nazi]].

Many who adhere to racialist doctrines do not use the term 'supremacist' because of the connotations it has with the desire to rule over those of other races. However, many of them do believe that the white race is superior to  other races. 

In the United States, white supremacist movements sometimes are linked to [[fundamentalist]] [[Christianity]] or [[Christian Identity]]; but most Christians, even those who identify themselves as "fundamentalists", denounce the movement as fundamentally non-Christian.  Some white supremacists consider violence to be a legitimate way to further their cause and dismiss Christianity as a mongrel or "suicidal" faith.

Other white supremacist groups identify themselves as [[Ásatrú|Odinists]]. The white supremacist version of Odinism has little to do with Christian Identity, but there is one key similarity: their version of Odinism provides dualism - as does Christian Identity - with regard to the universe being composed of 'worlds of light' (white people) and 'worlds of dark' (non-white people). The most fundamental difference between the two ideologies is that Odinists believe in the old [[Norse mythology|Norse gods]] and do not believe in the divinity of [[Jesus]].  Some groups, such as the [[South Africa]]n [[Boeremag]], even conflate elements of Christianity and Odinism.

Many white supremacist groups do not necessarily adhere to [[Christian Identity]] or other religious doctrines. Groups such as the [[American Nazi Party]] are largely politically, rather than religiously, motivated. The [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK), one of the most recognized white supremacist groups in the United States, proposes racial segregation that generally is not based on religious ideals.

==Distribution and prominence of contemporary white supremacist groups==

White supremacist groups can be found in most countries with a significant white population, including the [[United States]], [[Australia]], [[South Africa]], and in the nations of [[Europe]] and parts of Latin America.  In all of these places, their views represent a relatively small minority of the population, and active membership of the groups is quite small.  However, a backlash to the influx of non-white immigrants into various European nations in the last 25 years has spurred a rise in membership in such organizations, as well as an escalation white supremacist demonstrations and [[hate crimes]].

The militant approach taken by some groups has caused them to be watched closely by law enforcement officials. In some European countries, which have more recent experience with the effects of such beliefs in [[World War II]], white supremacist groups are banned by various laws. These include laws which forbid "[[hate speech]]" in addition to laws which forbid organizations deemed to be fundamentally opposed to any multi-ethnic, multi-racial, and democratic society.

==Violent activism by contemporary white supremacist groups==

The World Church of the Creator, now called the [[Creativity Movement]], presents a recent example of violence perpetrated by a white supremacist in order to bring about a race war. [[Ben Klassen]], the sect's founder, believed that one's race is his religion. Aside from this central belief, its ideology is similar to many Christian Identity groups in the conviction that there is a Jewish [[conspiracy]] in control of the federal government, international banking, and the media. They also dictate that RAHOWA, a [[Racial Holy War|Racial Holy War]], is destined to ensue to rid the world of Jews and “mud races.”  In the early 1990s, there was a dramatic increase in membership due to the growing belief in the Apocalypse and that RAHOWA was imminent. In 1996, [[Matthew F. Hale]], who came upon recent fame by being denied a license to practice law in Illinois, was appointed the new leader of the Church of the Creator. Hale made a number of changes to the group, including changing the name of the organization to the World Church of the Creator, to give it the feel of a widespread movement.

Recent incidents have demonstrated the willingness of members to take part in violent action. WCOTC members in Southern Florida are thought to be tied to several racially motivated beatings. Within the last year, four Florida members were convicted for the pistol-whipping and robbery of a Jewish video store owner. They were supposedly trying to raise money for "the revolution."

Many believe in the necessity of becoming martyrs for their cause. For example, [[Robert Jay Mathews|Bob Mathews]], the leader of [[The Order (group)|The Order]], died in a confrontation with law enforcement. Also, William King relished the fact that he would receive the death penalty for his act of murdering [[James Byrd, Jr.]]

==Inter-/Intra-Group Problems==
Many racist organizations seem to have shown a tendency to splinter easily, and modern-day racist movements existing on the Internet show a great deal of strife within "The Movement". Different groups have feuds and rivalries, different figures have personal feuds with different figures, etc. It could be observed that too many people within the movement want to be leaders as opposed to followers. Less extreme white supremacists or white supremacist groups, along with followers of and groups associated with [[white nationalism]] and [[paleo-conservatism]] are considered to be cowards and traitors by a lot of white supremacists, the latter two groups reciprocate with a conviction that white supremacists and neo-Nazis especially make them all look bad. 

==Contemporary White Supremacists ==

A list of famous white supremacists would be far too long to include in this article; just as a beginning, it would have to include most of the political rulers of the United States before 1960, most of the political rulers of [[apartheid]] era South Africa, of the [[Confederacy]], and of [[Nazi]] Germany.  What follows, therefore, is merely a list of contemporary figures who are primarily known for their support of white supremacy.

{{Main|List of White supremacists}}

* [[Don Andrews]]
* [[John Bean]]
* [[Don Black (nationalist)|Don Black]]
* [[Andrew Brons]]
* [[George Burdi]]
* [[Dan Burros]]
* [[Richard Girnt Butler]]
* [[Willis Carto]]
* [[Mark Collett]]
* [[Frank Collin]]
* [[David Copeland]]
* [[Mark Cotterill]]
* [[Nicky Crane]]
* [[Françoise Dior]]
* [[Ian Stuart Donaldson]]
* [[Wolfgang Droege]]
* [[David Duke]]
* [[Leo Felton]]
* [[Roberto Fiore]]
* [[Andrew Fountaine]]
* [[Paul Fromm]]
* [[Nick Griffin]]
* [[Matthew F. Hale]]
* [[Wolf Rüdiger Hess]]
* [[Ray Hill]]
* [[Derek Holland]]
* [[Tom Holmes]]
* [[David Irving]]
* [[Colin Jordan]]
* [[David Kerr]]
* [[Ben Klassen]]
* [[David Lane]]
* [[Arnold Leese]]
* [[Marc Lemire]]
* [[Alex Linder]]
* [[Martin Lindstedt]]
* [[James H. Madole]]
* [[Horst Mahler]]
* [[James Mason (National Socialist)|James Mason]]
* [[Robert Jay Mathews]]
* [[Michael McLaughlin]]
* [[Tom Metzger]]
* [[Frazier Glenn Miller]]
* [[Savitri Devi Mukherji]]
* [[David Myatt]]
* [[Fred Phelps]]
* [[William Luther Pierce]]
* [[John Kingsley Read]]
* [[Otto Ernst Remer]]
* [[Ingrid Rimland]]
* [[George Lincoln Rockwell]]
* [[Charlie Sargent]]
* [[Benjamin Nathaniel Smith]]
* [[John Ross Taylor]]
* [[Eugène Terre'Blanche]]
* [[Jean-François Thiriart]]
* [[Joseph Tommasi]]
* [[John Tyndall (politician)|John Tyndall]]
* [[Donna Upson]]
* [[Richard Verrall]]
* [[Robert Vesterlund]]
* [[Varg Vikernes]]
* [[Martin Webster]]
* [[Bill White (neo-Nazi)|Bill White]]
* [[Martin Wingfield]]
* [[Francis Parker Yockey]]
* [[Ernst Zündel]]

==Organizations==

* [[Afrikaner Weerstandsbeweging]] (AWB) (South Africa)
* [[American Nazi Party]]
* [[Aryan Brotherhood]]
* [[Aryan Nations]]
* [[Aryan Revolutionary Front]]
* [[British National Party]]
* [[Christian Conservative Church]] 
* [[Christian Identity]]
* [[Combat 18]] (British Group)
* [[Council of Conservative Citizens]]
* [[Confederate Hammer Skins]]
* [[Forsyth County Defense League]] &lt;!--Added by an editor likely connected to the group. --&gt;
* [[Hammerskins]]
* [[Heritage Front]]
* [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK)[NOTE: There are many groups of the Ku Klux Klan]
* [[Legion of Aryan Warriors]]
* [[Libertarian National Socialist Green Party]]
* [[National Association for the Advancement of White People]]
* [[National Socialist Skinheads]]
* [[Nationalist Party of Canada]]
* [[New Zealand National Front]]
* [[Nordic Thunder]]
* [[The Order (group)|The Order]]
* [[The Posse Comitatus]]
* [[Westboro Baptist Church]]
* [[White Aryan Resistance]] (WAR)
* [[White Citizens' Council]]
* [[White Patriot Party]]
* [[White Revolution (white supremacist)]]: a recent group to emerge, led by Billy Roper
* World Church of the Creator/[[Creativity Movement]] (WCOTC)

==Related topics==
* ''[[American History X]]''
* [[Apartheid]]
* [[Dixiecrat]]
* [[Eugenics]]
* [[Forsyth_County%2C_Georgia_v._The_Nationalist_Movement|Forsyth County, Georgia v. The Nationalist Movement]]
* [[Institutional racism]]
* [[Master race]]
* [[nadir of American race relations]]
* [[Neo-Nazi groups of the United States]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Zionist Occupation Government]]

=== Compare ===

* [[Black supremacy]]
* [[Racism]] and [[anti-racism]]
* [[Black power]] and [[White Power]] 
* [[White pride]] and [[Black pride]]
* [[White nationalism]] and [[Black nationalism]] 
* [[White separatism]] and [[Black separatism]]

==External links==
''Alleged or stated white supremacist websites: ''
*[http://www.stormfront.org Stormfront home page]
*[http://www.cosmotheism.net Cosmotheism Community Church]
*[http://www.nationalvanguard.org/ National Vanguard home] The Acting National Chairman of National Vanguard is the ex-Media Director of the old National Alliance, Kevin Alfred Strom, This group is widely perceived as the new, reorganized successor to the old National Alliance, in the wake of the resignation of scandal-plagued N.A. National Chairman Erich Gliebe in early 2005.
*[http://www.natall.com/ National Alliance home page] This is the so-called "rump" National Alliance, presently led by Erich Gliebe's close personal associate and alleged co-conspirator, Shaun Walker.
*[http://www.govnn.com Vanguard News Network home page]
*[http://www.panf.info/upload/index.php?styleid=1 Pan-Aryan National Front home page]
*[http://www.originaldissent.com/forums/index.php Original Dissent Forum (White Supremacist/Christian Nationalist fusion site)]

&lt;!-- Categorization --&gt;
[[Category:Neo-Nazi movements and concepts]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Ethnic supremacy]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Political theories]]

&lt;!-- Localization --&gt;

[[es:Supremacismo blanco]]
[[pl:Biała supremacja]]
[[fi:Valkoinen ylivalta]]
[[sv:Vit makt]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>