<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181124062140|870354612" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33178" pageid="33178" ns="0" title="White supremacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-24T06:24:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-pc1|small=yes}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}} 

'''White supremacy''' or '''white supremacism''' is the [[racist]] belief that [[white people]] are superior to people of other [[Race (human classification)|races]] and therefore should be dominant over them. White supremacy has roots in [[scientific racism]], and it often relies on [[pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] arguments. Like most similar movements such as [[neo-Nazism]], white supremacists typically oppose members of other races as well as [[Jews]].

The term is also typically used to describe a [[political ideology]] that perpetuates and maintains the [[society|social]], [[politics|political]], [[historical revisionism|historical]], or [[institutional racism|institutional]] domination by white people (as evidenced by historical and contemporary sociopolitical structures such as the [[Atlantic slave trade]], [[Jim Crow laws]] in the [[United States]], and ''[[apartheid]]'' in [[South Africa]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Privilege Revealed: How Invisible Preference Undermines America |last=Wildman |first=Stephanie M. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1996 |publisher=NYU Press |location= |isbn=0-8147-9303-7 |page=87}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Helms 2016 6–7"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Helms|first=Janet|date=2016|title=An election to save White Heterosexual Male Privilege|url=|journal=Latina/o Psychology Today|volume=3|pages=6–7|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Different forms of white supremacism put forth different conceptions of who is considered white, and different groups of white supremacists identify various racial and cultural groups as their primary enemy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Spaces of Hate: Geographies of Discrimination and Intolerance in the U.S.A. |last=Flint |first=Colin |year=2004 |publisher=Routledge |location= |isbn=0-415-93586-5 |page=53 |quote=Although white racist activists must adopt a political identity of whiteness, the flimsy definition of whiteness in modern culture poses special challenges for them. In both mainstream and white supremacist discourse, to be white is to be distinct from those marked as non-white, yet the placement of the distinguishing line has varied significantly in different times and places.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In academic usage, particularly in usage which draws on [[critical race theory]] or [[Intersectionality]], the term "white supremacy" can also refer to a political or socioeconomic system, in which white people enjoy a structural advantage ([[Privilege (social inequality)|privilege]]) over other ethnic groups, on both a collective and individual level.

==History==
White supremacy has ideological foundations that date back to 17th-century [[scientific racism]], the predominant paradigm of human variation that helped shape international relations and racial policy from the latter part of the [[Age of Enlightenment]] until the late 20th century (marked by decolonization and the abolition of [[apartheid]] in [[South Africa]] in 1991, followed by that country's [[South African general election, 1994|first multiracial elections in 1994]]).

[[File:One side of the monument erected to race prejudice New Orleans Louisiana 1936.jpg|thumb|upright=1.1|The [[Battle of Liberty Place Monument|Battle of Liberty Place monument]] in Louisiana was erected in 1891 by the white dominated New Orleans government. An inscription added in 1932 states that the [[1876 US Presidential Election]] "recognized white supremacy in the South and gave us our state". It was removed in 2017 and placed in storage.]]

===United States===
{{maincat|White supremacy in the United States}}
{{seealso|Racism in the United States}}

White supremacy was dominant in the [[United States]] both before and after the [[American Civil War]], and it persisted for decades after the [[Reconstruction Era]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Fredrickson | first = George | title = White Supremacy | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford Oxfordshire | year = 1981 | isbn = 0-19-503042-7 |page=162}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[antebellum South]], this included the holding of [[African Americans]] in [[slavery in the United States|chattel slavery]], with four million of them denied freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=How the end of slavery led to starvation and death for millions of black Americans|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/jun/16/slavery-starvation-civil-war|publisher=The Guardian|date=September 3, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The outbreak of the Civil War saw the desire to uphold white supremacy being cited as a cause for state secession&lt;ref&gt;[http://avalon.law.yale.edu/19th_century/csa_texsec.asp A Declaration of the Causes which Impel the State of Texas to Secede from the Federal Union]: "We hold as undeniable truths that the governments of the various States, and of the confederacy itself, were established exclusively by the white race, for themselves and their posterity; that the African race had no agency in their establishment; that they were rightfully held and regarded as an inferior and dependent race, and in that condition only could their existence in this country be rendered beneficial or tolerable. That in this free government all white men are and of right ought to be entitled to equal civil and political rights; that the servitude of the African race, as existing in these States, is mutually beneficial to both bond and free, and is abundantly authorized and justified by the experience of mankind, and the revealed will of the Almighty Creator, as recognized by all Christian nations; while the destruction of the existing relations between the two races, as advocated by our sectional enemies, would bring inevitable calamities upon both and desolation upon the fifteen slave-holding states."&lt;/ref&gt; and the formation of the [[Confederate States of America]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://teachingamericanhistory.org/library/index.asp?documentprint=76 The controversial "Cornerstone Speech", Alexander H. Stephens (Vice President of the Confederate States), March 21, 1861, Savannah, Georgia]: "Our new government is founded upon exactly the opposite idea; its foundations are laid, its cornerstone rests, upon the great truth that the negro is not equal to the white man; that slavery—subordination to the superior race—is his natural and normal condition."&lt;/ref&gt; In an editorial about [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] in 1890, author [[L. Frank Baum]] wrote: "The Whites, by law of conquest, by justice of civilization, are masters of the American continent, and the best safety of the frontier settlements will be secured by the total annihilation of the few remaining Indians."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.northern.edu/hastingw/baumedts.htm |title=L. Frank Baum's Editorials on the Sioux Nation |accessdate=2007-12-09 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071209193251/http://www.northern.edu/hastingw/baumedts.htm |archivedate=December 9, 2007 |df= }} Full text of both, with commentary by professor A. Waller Hastings&lt;/ref&gt;

In some parts of the United States, many people who were considered non-white were [[disfranchisement|disenfranchised]], barred from government office, and prevented from holding most government jobs well into the second half of the 20th century. Professor Leland T. Saito of the [[University of Southern California]] writes: "Throughout the history of the United States, race has been used by whites for legitimizing and creating difference and social, economic and political exclusion."&lt;ref&gt;Leland T. Saito (1998). "Race and Politics: Asian Americans, Latinos, and Whites in a Los Angeles Suburb". p. 154. University of Illinois Press&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Naturalization Act of 1790]] limited U.S. citizenship to whites only.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Schultz|first=Jeffrey D.|title=Encyclopedia of Minorities in American Politics: African Americans and Asian Americans|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WDV40aK1T-sC&amp;pg=PA284&amp;dq=African+Americans+discriminated+by+Naturalization+Act+of+1790&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|page=284|year=2002|accessdate=2010-03-25|isbn=9781573561488}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The denial of social and political freedom for minorities continued into the mid-20th century, resulting in the [[civil rights movement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.archives.gov/kansas-city/press/2013/13-29.html |title=50th Anniversary of the 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom Panel Discussion at the Black Archives of Mid-America |accessdate=October 3, 2015 |format=press release |publisher=The U.S. National Archives and Records Administration |date=August 7, 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151004044615/http://www.archives.gov/kansas-city/press/2013/13-29.html |archivedate=October 4, 2015 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sociologist Stephen Klineberg has stated that U.S. immigration laws prior to 1965 clearly declared "that [[Northern European]]s are a superior subspecies of the white race".&lt;ref name="Immigration law"/&gt;  The [[Immigration and Nationality Act of 1965]] opened entry to the U.S. to immigrants other than traditional Northern European and [[Germanic peoples|Germanic groups]], and significantly altered the demographic mix in the U.S as a result.&lt;ref name="Immigration law"&gt;{{cite web |title= 1965 immigration law changed face of America |author=Jennifer Ludden |url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5391395 |publisher=NPR}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[U.S. state]]s banned [[interracial marriage]] through [[anti-miscegenation laws]] until 1967, when these laws were invalidated by the [[Supreme Court of the United States]]' decision in ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]''. These mid-century gains had a major impact on white Americans' political views; segregation and white racial superiority, which had been publicly endorsed in the 1940s, became minority views within the white community by the mid-1970s, and continued to decline into 1990s polls to a single-digit percentage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Racial Attitudes in America: Trends and Interpretations|last1=Schuman|first1=Howard|last2=Steeh|first2=Charlotte|last3=Bobo|first3=Lawrence|last4=Krysan|first4=Maria|date=1997|publisher=Harvard University Press|year=|isbn=978-0-674-74568-1|location=|pages=103ff|quote="The questions deal with most of the major racial issues that became focal in the middle of the twentieth ecntury: integration of public accommodations, school integration, residential integration, and job discrimiantion [and] racial intermarriage and willingness to vote for a black presidential candidate. … The trends that occur for most of the principle items are quite similar and can be illustrated …using attitudes toward school integration as an example. The figure shows that there ha been a massive and continuing movement of the American public from overwhelming acceptance of the ''principle'' of segregated schooling in the early 1940s toward acceptance of the ''principle'' of integrated schooling. … by 1985, more than nine out of ten chose the pro-integration response."}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Pine Forge Press| isbn = 978-1-4129-4107-5| last1 = Healey| first1 = Joseph F.| last2 = O'Brien| first2 = Eileen| title = Race, Ethnicity, and Gender: Selected Readings| date = 2007-05-08 | quote = "In 1942 only 42 percent of a national sample of whites reported that they believed blacks to be equal to whites in innate intelligence; since the late 1950s, however, around 80 percent of white Americans have rejected the idea of inherent black inferiority."}}&lt;/ref&gt; For sociologist Howard Winant, these shifts marked the end of "monolithic white supremacy" in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Winant|first=Howard|date=1997|title=Behind Blue Eyes: Whiteness and Contemporary US Racial Politics|journal=New Left Review|issue=225|pages=73 | quote="white racial attitudes shifted dramatically in the postwar period. … So, monolithic white supremacy is over, yet in a more concealed way, white power and privilege live on."|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MpLnnmp3IGgC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Behind%20Blue%20Eyes%3A%20Whiteness%20and%20Contemporary%20US%20Racial%20%22&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ku Klux Klan parade7.jpg|thumb|Ku Klux Klan parade in [[Washington, D.C.]] in 1926]]
After the mid-1960s, white supremacy remained an important ideology in the American far-right.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Guilford Publications| isbn = 978-1-4625-3760-0| last1 = Berlet| first1 = Chip| last2 = Lyons| first2 = Matthew N.| title = Right-Wing Populism in America: Too Close for Comfort| date = 2018-03-08 | quote = "While the New Right and Christian Right flourished in the 1970s and 1980s, the Far Right also rebounded… The Far Right—encompassing Ku Klux Klan, neonazi, and related organizations—attracted a much smaller following than the New Right, but its influence reverberated in its encouragement of widespread attacks against members of oppressed groups and in broad-based scapegoating campaigns"}}&lt;/ref&gt; Howard Winant writes that, "On the far right the cornerstone of white identity is belief in an ineluctable, unalterable racialized difference between whites and nonwhites."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Winant|first=Howard|date=1997|title=Behind Blue Eyes: Whiteness and Contemporary US Racial Politics|journal=New Left Review|issue=225|pages=73}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Kathleen Belew, a historian of race and racism in the United States, white militancy shifted after the Vietnam War from supporting the existing racial order to a more radical position—self-described as "white power" or "white nationalism"—committed to overthrowing the United States government and establishing a white homeland.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| isbn = 978-0-674-28607-8| last = Belew| first = Kathleen| title = Bring the war home: The white power movement and paramilitary America| date = 2018 | quote = "The white power movement that emerged from the Vietnam era shared some common attributes with earlier racist movements in the United States, but it was no mere echo. Unlike previous iterations of the Ku Klux Klan and white supremacist vigilantism, the white power movement did not claim to serve the state. Instead, white power made the state its target, declaring war against the federal government in 1983."}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.thenation.com/article/declaration-of-war/|title=How Did Vietnam Transform White Supremacy?|last=Blanchfield|first=Patrick|date=June 20, 2018|work=The Nation|access-date=2018-08-11|language=en-US|issn=0027-8378}}&lt;/ref&gt; White supremacist groups such as the [[Ku Klux Klan]], neo-Nazi organizations, the Christian Identity movement, and racist skinheads make up two of the three major strands of violent right-wing  movements in the United States (the third is anti-government militia organizations).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite conference|last=Perliger|first=Arie|date=2012|title=Challengers from the Sidelines: Understanding America's Violent Far-Right|location=West Point, NY|publisher=Combatting Terrorism Center, US Military Academy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/u-s-sees-300-violent-attacks-inspired-far-right-every-year|title=U.S. sees 300 violent attacks inspired by far right every year|date=2017-08-13|work=PBS NewsHour|accessdate=2018-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some academics argue that outcomes from the 2016 United States Presidential Election reflect ongoing challenges with white supremacy. Psychologist Janet Helms suggested that the norming behaviors of social institutions of education, government, and healthcare are organized around the "birthright of...the power to control society's resources and determine the rules for [those resources]".&lt;ref name="Helms 2016 6–7"/&gt; Educators, literary theorists, and other political experts have raised similar questions, connecting the [[scapegoating]] of disenfranchised populations to white superiority.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.democracynow.org/2016/12/1/cornel_west_on_donald_trump_this|title=Cornel West on Donald Trump: This is What Neo-Fascism Looks Like|last=|first=|date=Dec 1, 2016|website=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/live/events/the-politics-of-gender-2016/2016/|title=Politics of Gender: Women, Men, and the 2016 Campaign|last=|first=|date=December 13, 2016|website=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===British Empire===
In 1937, [[Winston Churchill]] told the Palestine Royal Commission: "I do not admit for instance, that a great wrong has been done to the Red Indians of America or the black people of Australia. I do not admit that a wrong has been done to these people by the fact that a stronger race, a higher-grade race, a more worldly wise race to put it that way, has come in and taken their place." British historian [[Richard Toye]], author of Churchill's Empire, said that "Churchill did think that white people were superior."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The 10 greatest controversies of Winston Churchill's career |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-29701767 |work=BBC News |date=26 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Deutsches_Historisches_Museum_Der_St%C3%BCrmerplakat.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.02|Poster of the Nazi paper ''[[Der Stürmer]]'' (1935) condemning relations between Jews and non-Jewish Germans]]
===Germany===
[[Nazism]] promoted the idea of a superior [[Germanic people]] or [[Aryan race]] in [[Germany]] during the early 20th century. Notions of white supremacy and Aryan racial superiority were combined in the 19th century, with white supremacists maintaining the belief that white people were members of an Aryan "[[master race]]" which was superior to other races, particularly the [[Jews]], who were described as the "Semitic race", [[Slavs]], and [[Names of the Romani people|Gypsies]], which they associated with "cultural sterility". [[Arthur de Gobineau]], a French racial theorist and aristocrat, blamed the fall of the [[Ancien Régime|''ancien régime'']] in France on racial degeneracy caused by racial intermixing, which he argued had destroyed the "purity" of the Nordic or Germanic race. Gobineau's theories, which attracted a strong following in Germany, emphasized the existence of an irreconcilable polarity between Aryan or Germanic peoples and Jewish culture.&lt;ref&gt;Blamires, Cyprian; Jackson, Paul. "[http://search.proquest.com/openview/9c41b2e7d5a2e90cf01120ea183d7874/1?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;cbl=40834 World Fascism: A Historical Encyclopedia]": Volume 1. Santa Barbara, California, USA: ABC-CLIO, Inc, 2006. p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the [[Nazi Party]]'s chief racial theorist, [[Alfred Rosenberg]] oversaw the construction of a human racial "ladder" that justified [[Racial policy of Nazi Germany|Hitler's racial and ethnic policies]]. Rosenberg promoted the [[Nordic theory]], which regarded [[Nordic race|Nordics]] as the "master race", superior to all others, including other Aryans (Indo-Europeans).&lt;ref&gt;Though Rosenberg does not use the word "master race". He uses the word "Herrenvolk" (i. e., ruling people) twice in his book ''The Myth'', first referring to the [[Amorite]]s (saying that [[Archibald Sayce|Sayce]] described them as fair skinned and blue eyed) and secondly quoting [[Victor Wallace Germains]]' description of the English in "The Truth about Kitchener". ("The Myth of the Twentieth Century") - Pages 26, 660 - 1930&lt;/ref&gt; Rosenberg got the racial term ''[[Untermensch]]'' from the title of [[Klansman]] [[Lothrop Stoddard]]'s 1922 book ''The Revolt Against Civilization: The Menace of the Under-man''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Stoddard, Lothrop| authorlink = Lothrop Stoddard| year = 1922| title = The Revolt Against Civilization: The Menace of the Under Man| publisher = [[Charles Scribner's Sons]]| location = New York| isbn =| url = https://archive.org/details/revoltagainstciv00stoduoft}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was later adopted by the Nazis from that book's German version ''Der Kulturumsturz: Die Drohung des Untermenschen'' (1925).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal| author = Losurdo, Domenico| authorlink = Domenico Losurdo| others = Translated by Marella &amp; Jon Morris| year = 2004| title = Toward a Critique of the Category of Totalitarianism| journal = [[Historical Materialism (journal)|Historical Materialism]]| publisher = [[Brill Publishers|Brill]]| volume = 12| issue = 2| pages = 25–55, here p. 50| issn = 1465-4466| doi = 10.1163/1569206041551663| url = http://www.pssp.org/bbs/data/document/1/Losurdo___Critique_of_Totalitarianism_%282004%29.pdf| format = PDF, 0.2 MB}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rosenberg was the leading Nazi who attributed the concept of the East-European "under man" to Stoddard.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book| author = Rosenberg, Alfred| authorlink = Alfred Rosenberg| year = 1930| title = Der Mythus des 20. Jahrhunderts: Eine Wertung der seelischgeistigen Gestaltungskämpfe unserer Zeit| trans-title = The Myth of the Twentieth Century| publisher = Hoheneichen-Verlag| location = Munich| page = 214| isbn = | url = https://www.scribd.com/doc/2628285/Der-Mythus-des-20-Jahrhunderts-Alfred-Rosenberg| language = German| deadurl = yes| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20121104014921/http://www.scribd.com/doc/2628285/Der-Mythus-des-20-Jahrhunderts-Alfred-Rosenberg| archivedate = 2012-11-04| df = }}&lt;/ref&gt; An advocate of the U.S. immigration laws that favored Northern Europeans, Stoddard wrote primarily on the alleged dangers posed by "[[colored]]" peoples to white civilization, and wrote ''[[The Rising Tide of Color Against White World-Supremacy]]'' in 1920. In establishing a restrictive entry system for Germany in 1925, Hitler wrote of his admiration for America's immigration laws: "The American Union categorically refuses the immigration of physically unhealthy elements, and simply excludes the immigration of certain races."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofisrael.com/american-laws-against-coloreds-influenced-nazi-racial-planners/ "American laws against 'coloreds' influenced Nazi racial planners"]. Times of Israel. Retrieved August 26, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

German praise for America's institutional racism, previously found in Hitler's ''Mein Kampf'', was continuous throughout the early 1930's, and Nazi lawyers were advocates of the use of American models.&lt;ref name="Whitman"/&gt; Race-based U.S. citizenship and anti-miscegenation laws directly inspired the Nazi's two principal [[Nuremberg Laws|Nuremberg racial laws]]—the Citizenship Law and the Blood Law.&lt;ref name="Whitman"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Whitman|first1=James Q.|title=Hitler's American Model: The United States and the Making of Nazi Race Law|date=2017|publisher=Princeton University Press|pages=37–43}}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to preserve the Aryan or [[Nordic race]] the Nazis introduced the Nuremberg Laws in 1935, which forbade sexual relations and marriages between Germans and Jews, and later between Germans and [[Romani people|Romani]] and [[Slavs]]. The Nazis used the [[Mendelian inheritance]] theory to argue that social traits were innate, claiming that there was a racial nature associated with certain general traits such as inventiveness or criminal behavior.&lt;ref&gt;Henry Friedlander. The Origins of Nazi Genocide: From Euthanasia to the Final Solution. Chapel Hill, North Carolina, USA: University of North Carolina Press, 1995. p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the 2012 annual report of Germany's interior intelligence service, the [[Federal Office for the Protection of the Constitution]], at the time there were 26,000 right-wing extremists living in Germany, including 6000 [[Neo-Nazism|neo-Nazis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.verfassungsschutz.de/de/oeffentlichkeitsarbeit/publikationen/verfassungsschutzberichte/vsbericht-2012|title=Bundesamt für Verfassungsschutz - Verfassungsschutzbericht 2012|publisher=|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150321183652/http://www.verfassungsschutz.de/de/oeffentlichkeitsarbeit/publikationen/verfassungsschutzberichte/vsbericht-2012|archivedate=2015-03-21|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{clear left}}

===South Africa===
{{see|Apartheid|Baasskap}}
A number of [[Southern Africa]]n nations experienced severe racial tension and conflict during global [[decolonization]], particularly as [[white Africans of European ancestry]] fought to protect their preferential social and political status. Racial segregation in South Africa began in colonial times under the [[Dutch Empire]], and it continued when the British took over the [[Cape of Good Hope]] in 1795. [[Apartheid]] was introduced as an officially structured policy by the [[Afrikaners|Afrikaner]]-dominated [[National Party (South Africa)|National Party]] after the [[South African general election, 1948|general election of 1948]]. Apartheid's legislation divided inhabitants into four racial groups—"black", "white", "coloured", and "Indian", with coloured divided into several sub-classifications.&lt;ref&gt;Baldwin-Ragaven, Laurel; London, Lesley; du Gruchy, Jeanelle (1999). ''An ambulance of the wrong colour: health professionals, human rights, and ethics in South Africa.'' Juta and Company Limited. p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; In 1970, the Afrikaner-run government [[Separate Representation of Voters Amendment Act, 1968|abolished non-white political representation]], and starting that year [[black people]] were deprived of South African citizenship.&lt;ref&gt;John Pilger (2011). "Freedom Next Time". p. 266. Random House&lt;/ref&gt; South Africa abolished apartheid in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title = abolition of the White Australia Policy |url = http://www.immi.gov.au/media/fact-sheets/08abolition.htm | publisher = Australian Government | date= November 2010 | accessdate =October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url =http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/555568/South-Africa/259494/The-apartheid-years | title = Encyclopædia Britannica, South Africa the Apartheid Years | publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica | accessdate = October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rhodesia===
In [[Rhodesia]], a predominantly white government issued its own [[Rhodesia's Unilateral Declaration of Independence|unilateral declaration of independence]] from the United Kingdom during an unsuccessful attempt to avoid immediate majority rule.&lt;ref name="africapolitics"&gt;{{cite book|last=Gann|first=L.H.|title=Politics and Government in African States 1960–1985|pages=162–202}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the [[Rhodesian Bush War]] which was fought by [[African nationalism|African nationalists]], Rhodesian prime minister [[Ian Smith]] acceded to biracial political representation in 1978 and the state achieved recognition from the United Kingdom as [[Zimbabwe]] in 1980.&lt;ref name="zimstudy"&gt;{{cite book|last=Nelson|first=Harold|title=Zimbabwe: A Country Study|pages=1–317}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Russia===
[[Neo-Nazism|Neo-Nazi]] organisations embracing white supremacist ideology are present in many countries of the world. In 2007, it was claimed that Russian neo-Nazis accounted for "half of the world's total".&lt;ref&gt;"[http://abcnews.go.com/Nightline/story?id=3718255&amp;page=1#.UCDbiaA4SuI Violence 'in the Name of the Nation']." ''[[ABC News]]''. October 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"[https://www.reuters.com/article/us-russia-medvedev-nationalism/russias-medvedev-calls-for-crackdown-on-neo-nazis-idUSTRE70G4DP20110117 Russia's Medvedev calls for crackdown on neo-Nazis]". Reuters. January 17, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ukraine===
In June 2015, Democratic Representative [[John Conyers]] and his Republican colleague [[Ted Yoho]] offered bipartisan amendments to block the U.S. military training of Ukraine's [[Azov Battalion]] — called a “neo-Nazi paramilitary militia” by Conyers and Yoho.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.bloombergview.com/articles/2015-06-12/ukraine-s-neo-nazis-won-t-get-u-s-money Ukraine's Neo-Nazis Won't Get U.S. Money]". [[Bloomberg News|Bloomberg]]. 12 June 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.jpost.com/Diaspora/US-lifts-ban-on-funding-neo-Nazi-Ukrainian-militia-441884 US lifts ban on funding 'neo-Nazi' Ukrainian militia]". ''The Jerusalem Post.'' 18 January 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"[https://www.thenation.com/article/congress-has-removed-a-ban-on-funding-neo-nazis-from-its-year-end-spending-bill/ Congress Has Removed a Ban on Funding Neo-Nazis From Its Year-End Spending Bill]". ''[[The Nation]]''. January 14, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; Some members of the battalion are openly white supremacists.&lt;ref&gt;"[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/ukraine/11025137/Ukraine-crisis-the-neo-Nazi-brigade-fighting-pro-Russian-separatists.html Ukraine crisis: the neo-Nazi brigade fighting pro-Russian separatists]". ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]''. 11 August 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academic use of the term==
The term ''white supremacy'' is used in academic studies of racial power to denote a system of structural or [[societal racism]] which privileges white people over others, regardless of the presence or the absence of racial hatred. White racial advantages occur at both a collective and an individual level (''[[ceteris paribus]]'', {{Nowrap|i. e.}}, when individuals are compared that do not relevantly differ except in ethnicity). Legal scholar Frances Lee Ansley explains this definition as follows:
{{quote|By "white supremacy" I do not mean to allude only to the self-conscious racism of white supremacist [[hate group]]s. I refer instead to a political, economic and cultural system in which whites overwhelmingly control power and material resources, conscious and unconscious ideas of white superiority and entitlement are widespread, and relations of white dominance and non-white subordination are daily reenacted across a broad array of institutions and social settings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ansley|first=Frances Lee|title=Stirring the Ashes: Race, Class and the Future of Civil Rights Scholarship|journal=Cornell Law Review|year=1989|volume=74|pages=993ff}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Temple University Press | isbn = 978-1-56639-532-8 | editor1 = Richard Delgado |editor2= Jean Stefancic | last = Ansley | first = Frances Lee | title = Critical white studies: Looking behind the mirror | chapter = White supremacy (and what we should do about it) | date = 1997-06-29 | page = 592}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

This and similar definitions have been adopted or proposed by Charles Mills,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | pages = 35–48 | last = Mills | first = C.W. | title = White supremacy as sociopolitical system: A philosophical perspective | journal = White out: the continuing significance of racism | year = 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[bell hooks]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Pluto Press | isbn = 978-0-7453-1663-5 | last = Hooks | first = Bell | title = Feminist theory: From margin to center | date = 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Gillborn]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1177/1468796806068323 | issn = 1468-7968 | volume = 6 | issue = 3 | pages = 318–40 | last = Gillborn | first = David | title = Rethinking White Supremacy Who Counts in 'WhiteWorld' | journal = Ethnicities | accessdate = 2012-03-14 | date = 2006-09-01 | url = http://etn.sagepub.com/content/6/3/318}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jessie Daniels,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Routledge | isbn = 9780415912891 | last = Daniels| first = Jessie | title = White Lies: race, class, gender and sexuality in white supremacist discourse | date = 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Neely Fuller Jr,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = SAGE | asin = B0007BLCWC | last = Fuller | first = Neely | title = The united-independent compensatory code/system/concept: A textbook/workbook for thought, speech, and/or action, for victims of racism (white supremacy) | year = 1984 | page = 334}}&lt;/ref&gt; and they are widely used in [[critical race theory]] and [[Intersectionality|intersectional feminism]]. Some [[anti-racism|anti-racist]] educators, such as Betita Martinez and the Challenging White Supremacy workshop, also use the term in this way. The term expresses historic continuities between a pre–[[civil rights movement]] era of open white supremacism and the current racial power structure of the United States. It also expresses the visceral impact of structural racism through "provocative and brutal" language that characterizes racism as "nefarious, global, systemic, and constant".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis US | isbn = 978-0-415-98980-0 | editor1 = Jeanette Davidson | editor2 = George Yancy | last = Davidson | first = Tim | title = Critical perspectives on Bell Hooks | chapter = bell hooks, white supremacy, and the academy | date = 2009-02-23 | page = 68}}&lt;/ref&gt; Academic users of the term sometimes prefer it to ''racism'' because it allows for a distinction to be drawn between racist feelings and white racial advantage or [[white privilege|privilege]].&lt;ref&gt;"Why is it so difficult for many white folks to understand that racism is oppressive not because white folks have prejudicial feelings about blacks (they could have such feelings and leave us alone) but because it is a system that promotes domination and subjugation?" {{Cite book | publisher = Turnaround Publisher Services Limited | isbn = 978-1-873262-02-3 | last = hooks | first = bell | title = Black Looks: Race and Representation | date = 2009-02-04 | page = 12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Grillo and Wildman cite hooks to argue for the term ''racism/white supremacy'': "hooks writes that liberal whites do not see themselves as either prejudiced or interested in domination through coercion, and they do not acknowledge the ways in which they contribute to and benefit from the system of white privilege." {{Cite book | publisher = Temple University Press | isbn = 978-1-56639-532-8 | editor1 = Richard Delgado | editor2 = Jean Stefancic | last1 = Grillo | first1 = Trina |author2= Stephanie M. Wildman | title = Critical white studies: Looking behind the mirror | chapter = The implications of making comparisons between racism and sexism (or other isms) | date = 1997-06-29 | page = 620}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Pollock|first1=Nicolas|last2=Myszkowski|first2=Sophia|title=Hate Groups Are Growing Under Trump|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/video/index/536793/hate-groups-are-growing-under-trump/|website=The Atlantic|accessdate=28 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term's recent rise in popularity among [[Left-wing politics|leftist]] activists has been characterized by some as counterproductive. [[John McWhorter]], a specialist in language and race relations, has described its use as straying from its commonly accepted meaning to encompass less extreme issues, thereby cheapening the term and potentially derailing productive discussion.&lt;ref name="left language"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wnyc.org/story/left-language-right-language/|title=Left Language, Right Language|accessdate=3 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="McWhorter"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://time.com/4584161/white-supremacy/|title=The Difference Between Racial Bias and White Supremacy|website=TIME |last1=McWhorter|first1=John|accessdate=3 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://heterodoxacademy.org/2017/12/14/an-interview-with-john-mcwhorter/|title=An Interview with John McWhorter about Politics and Protest|date=2017-12-14|work=HeterodoxAcademy.org|access-date=2017-12-15|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Political columnist [[Kevin Drum]] attributes the term's growing popularity to frequent use by [[Ta-Nehisi Coates]], describing it as a "terrible fad" which fails to convey nuance. He claims that the term should be reserved for those who are trying to promote the idea that whites are inherently superior to blacks and not used to characterize less blatantly racist beliefs or actions.&lt;ref name="MotherJ"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.motherjones.com/kevin-drum/2016/11/lets-please-kill-white-supremacy-fad|title=Let's Be Careful With the "White Supremacy" Label|website=Mother Jones|accessdate=4 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Friedersdorf"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2016/11/the-scourge-of-the-left-too-much-stigma-not-enough-persuasion/508961/|title='The Scourge of the Left': Too Much Stigma, Not Enough Persuasion|last=Friedersdorf|first=Conor|access-date=2016-12-04|language=en-US|newspaper=The Atlantic}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of the academic definition of white supremacy has been criticized by Conor Friedersdorf for the confusion it creates for the general public inasmuch as it differs from the more common dictionary definition; he argues that it is likely to alienate those it hopes to convince.&lt;ref name="Friedersdorf" /&gt;

==Ideologies and movements==
Supporters of [[Nordic race#Nordicism|Nordicism]] consider the "Nordic peoples" to be a superior race.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nordicism|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/nordicism|website=Merriam Webster}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the early 19th century, white supremacy was attached to emerging theories of racial hierarchy. The German philosopher [[Arthur Schopenhauer]] attributed cultural primacy to the white race:
{{quote|The highest civilization and culture, apart from the ancient [[Hinduism|Hindus]] and [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptians]], are found exclusively among the white races; and even with many dark peoples, the ruling caste or race is fairer in colour than the rest and has, therefore, evidently immigrated, for example, the [[Brahman]]s, the [[Inca Empire|Incas]], and the rulers of the [[Polynesia|South Sea Islands]]. All this is due to the fact that necessity is the mother of invention because those tribes that emigrated early to the north, and there gradually became white, had to develop all their intellectual powers and invent and perfect all the arts in their struggle with need, want and misery, which in their many forms were brought about by the climate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Schopenhauer | first = Arthur | authorlink = Arthur Schopenhauer | title = ''[[Parerga and Paralipomena]]'' | year = 1851 | pages = Vol. 2, Section 92}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:Good Citizen Pillar of Fire Church July 1926.jpg|thumb|''[[The Good Citizen]]'' 1926, published by [[Pillar of Fire International|Pillar of Fire Church]]]]

The [[eugenics|eugenicist]] [[Madison Grant]] argued in his 1916 book, ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'', that the Nordic race had been responsible for most of humanity's great achievements, and that [[Miscegenation|admixture]] was "race suicide".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Grant | first = Madison | title = The Passing of the Great Race | publisher = C. Scribner's sons | year = 1921 | edition = 4 | page = xxxi | url = https://archive.org/stream/passingofgreatra00granuoft/passingofgreatra00granuoft_djvu.txt}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this book, Europeans who are not of Germanic origin but have Nordic characteristics such as blonde/red hair and blue/green/gray eyes, were considered to be a Nordic admixture and suitable for [[Aryanization (Nazism)|Aryanization]].&lt;ref name="Grant1916"&gt;[[Madison Grant|Grant, Madison]] (1916). ''The Passing of the Great Race''. Charles Scribner's Sons, New York.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Klan-in-gainesville.jpg|thumb|left|267px|Members of the second [[Ku Klux Klan]] at a rally in 1923.]]

In the United States, the [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK) is the group most associated with the white supremacist movement. Many white supremacist groups are based on the concept of preserving genetic purity, and do not focus solely on [[discrimination]] based on skin color.&lt;ref name="law.jrank.org"&gt;http://law.jrank.org/pages/11302/White-Supremacy-Groups.html White Supremacy Groups&lt;/ref&gt; The KKK's reasons for supporting [[racial segregation]] are not primarily based on religious ideals, but some Klan groups are openly [[Protestantism|Protestant]]. The KKK and other white supremacist groups like [[Aryan Nations]], [[The Order (white supremacist group)|The Order]] and the [[White Patriot Party]] are considered [[Antisemitism in the United States|antisemitic]].&lt;ref name="law.jrank.org"/&gt;

[[Nazi Germany]] promulgated white supremacy based on the belief that the [[Aryan race]], or the Germans, were the ''[[master race]]''. It was combined with a [[Nazi eugenics|eugenics programme]] that aimed for [[racial hygiene]] through compulsory sterilization of sick individuals and extermination of [[Untermensch]]en ("subhumans"): [[Anti-Slavic sentiment|Slavs]], Jews and [[antiziganism|Romani]], which eventually culminated in [[the Holocaust]].&lt;ref&gt;Gumkowski, Janusz; Leszczynski, Kazimierz; Robert, Edward (translator) (1961). Hitler's Plans for Eastern Europe (PAPERBACK). Poland Under Nazi Occupation (First ed.) (Polonia Pub. House). p. 219. ASIN B0006BXJZ6. Retrieved March 12, 2014. at Wayback machine.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Peter Longerich]] (15 April 2010). Holocaust: The Nazi Persecution and Murder of the Jews. Oxford University Press. p. 30. {{ISBN|978-0-19-280436-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="USHMM"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://digitalassets.ushmm.org/photoarchives/detail.aspx?id=10049&amp;search=EUTHANASIA+%28PATIENTS%2FVICTIMS%29&amp;index=25 | title=Close-up of Richard Jenne, the last child killed by the head nurse at the Kaufbeuren-Irsee euthanasia facility. | publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum | accessdate=July 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ian Kershaw]], ''Hitler: A Profile in Power'', Chapter VI, first section (London, 1991, rev. 2001)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Snyder, S. &amp; D. Mitchell. Cultural Locations of Disability. University of Michigan Press. 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Christian Identity]] is another movement closely tied to white supremacy. Some white supremacists identify themselves as [[Heathenry (new religious movement)|Odinists]], although many Odinists reject white supremacy. Some white supremacist groups, such as the [[South Africa]]n [[Boeremag]], conflate elements of [[Christianity]] and Odinism. [[Creativity (religion)|Creativity]] (formerly known as "The World Church of the Creator") is [[atheism|atheistic]] and it denounces Christianity and other [[Theism|theistic religions]].&lt;ref name="Atheistic"&gt;{{cite book|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=HB1wyFPRGm4C&amp;pg=PA23&amp;dq=atheism+white+supremacy#v=onepage&amp;q=atheistic&amp;f=false|title =The new white nationalism in America: its challenge to integration|publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]]|quote=For instance, Ben Klassen, founder of the atheistic Church of the Creator and author of ''The White Man's Bible'', discusses Christianity extensively in his writings and denounces it as a religion that has brought untold horror into the world and has divided the white race.|accessdate = 2011-03-27|isbn =9780521808866|date =2002-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Atheism"&gt;{{cite book|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=rBgn3xB75ZcC&amp;pg=PA493&amp;dq=competing+atheistic+white+racist+movement#v=onepage&amp;q=competing%20atheistic%20white%20racist%20movement&amp;f=false|title =The World's Religions: Continuities and Transformations|publisher = [[Taylor &amp; Francis]]|quote=A competing atheistic or panthestic white racist movement also appeared, which included the Church of the Creator/ Creativity (Gardell 2003: 129–34).|accessdate = 2011-03-27|isbn =9781135211004|date =2009-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aside from this, its ideology is similar to that of many Christian Identity groups because it believes in the [[List of conspiracy theories#Antisemitic conspiracy theories|antisemitic conspiracy theory]] that there is a "Jewish conspiracy" in control of governments, the banking industry and the media. [[Matthew F. Hale]], founder of the World Church of the Creator, has published articles stating that all races other than white are "mud races", which is what the group's religion teaches.&lt;ref name="law.jrank.org"/&gt;

The white supremacist ideology has become associated with a racist faction of the [[skinhead]] [[subculture]], despite the fact that when the skinhead culture first developed in the [[United Kingdom]] in the late 1960s, it was heavily influenced by black fashions and [[Black music|music]], especially [[Jamaica]]n [[reggae]] and [[ska]], and African American [[soul music]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ska.about.com/musicperform/ska/library/1999/aa081699a.htm |title=Smiling Smash: An Interview with Cathal Smyth, a.k.a. Chas Smash, of Madness |accessdate=2001-02-19 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20010219175613/http://ska.about.com/musicperform/ska/library/1999/aa081699a.htm |archivedate=February 19, 2001 |df= }}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reggaereggaereggae.com/Special%20Articles.htm Special Articles&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081217000127/http://www.reggaereggaereggae.com/Special%20Articles.htm|date=2008-12-17}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="skinheads"&gt;{{cite book |last=Old Skool Jim |first= |title=Trojan Skinhead Reggae Box Set liner notes |publisher=Trojan Records |date= |location=London |id=TJETD169}}&lt;/ref&gt;

White supremacist recruitment activities are primarily conducted at a [[grassroots]] level as well as on the [[Internet]]. Widespread access to the Internet has led to a dramatic increase in white supremacist websites.&lt;ref name="Adversity"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=1Adams |first1=Josh |first2=Vincent J. |last2=Roscigno |title=White Supremacists, Oppositional Culture and the World Wide Web |work=University on North Carolina Press 84 (2005): 759–88 |date=20 November 2009 |jstor=3598477}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Internet provides a venue to openly express white supremacist ideas at little [[social cost]], because people who post the information are able to remain anonymous.

==See also==
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
*[[Alt-right]]
*[[Anti-miscegenation laws]]
*[[Aryan Brotherhood]]
*''[[The Birth of a Nation]]'' (film)
*[[Eurocentrism]]
*[[Hate group]]
*''[[Heroes of the Fiery Cross]]'' (book)
{{col-break|gap=4em}}
*[[Institutional racism]]
*[[Jim Crow laws]]
*[[Master race]]
*[[Neo-Confederate]]
*[[Race and intelligence]]
*[[Scientific racism]]
{{col-break|gap=4em}}
*[[Superiority complex]]
*[[Frances Cress Welsing]]
*"[[The White Man's Burden]]" (poem)
*[[White power music]]
*[[White nationalism]]
*[[List of white nationalist organizations|White nationalist organizations]]
*[[White separatism]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{reflist}}

'''Further reading'''
*Dobratz, Betty A. and Shanks-Meile, Stephanie (2000) ''"White Power, White Pride!": The White Separatist Movement in the United States''. Johns Hopkins University Press. {{ISBN|978-0-8018-6537-4}}
*MacCann, Donnarae (2000) [https://books.google.com/books?id=xj_T3QCgNgsC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=%22White+supremacy%22+juvenile ''White Supremacy in Children's Literature: Characterizations of African Americans, 1830-1900'']. New York: Routledge. {{isbn|9780415928908}}
*[[George Lincoln Rockwell|Rockwell, George Lincoln]] (1996) ''White Power''. John McLaughlin. {{isbn|9780965649285}}

==External links==
*[https://www.docsonline.tv/documentary/heart-of-whiteness "Heart of Whiteness"]—A documentary film about what it means to be white in South Africa
*[https://www.ushmm.org/confront-antisemitism/antisemitism-podcast/frank-meeink "Voices on Antisemitism"]—Interview with Frank Meeink from the [[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum|U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum]]
*[https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/acts-of-faith/wp/2017/08/14/russell-moore-white-supremacy-angers-jesus-but-does-it-anger-his-church/ "Russell Moore: White supremacy angers Jesus, but does it anger his church?" the president of the Ethics &amp; Religious Liberty Commission of the Southern Baptist Convention.]

{{White people}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:White Supremacy}}
[[Category:White supremacy| ]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Neo-fascism]]
[[Category:Neo-Nazi concepts]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination]]
[[Category:Racial segregation]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Reconstruction Era]]
[[Category:White nationalism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>