<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031018012440|1582998" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33178" pageid="33178" ns="0" title="White supremacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-18T01:25:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The &lt;b&gt;white supremacy movement&lt;/b&gt; considers white people to be superior to people of other (and of mixed) [[race|races]] and/or [[ethnicity|ethnicities]]. In the United States white supremacy is sometimes linked to [[fundamentalist]] [[Christianity]], but many Christians denounce the movement as fundamentally non-Christian. Some white supremacists consider violence to be a legitimate way to further their cause. White supremacy groups are usually led by men.

White supremacist groups can be found in most countries with a significant white population, including the [[United States]], [[Europe]], parts of Latin America, and [[Australia]].  However, in all of these places, their views represent a small minority of the population, and active membership of the groups is quite small.  

White supremacists make many claims about the intellectual, ethical and spiritual inferiority of blacks, [[Jews]], Hispanics, Asians and [[homosexuality|homosexuals]]. (See [[race and intelligence]], [[The Bell Curve]].)

White supremacists usually refer to themselves as White Pride or White Power. Some claim that they do not wish to harm non-white people, but rather they only wish to keep their blood pure. They are vehemently opposed to racial mixing, especially interracial relationships and marriages. Keeping white blood pure is a major tenet of the movement.

These beliefs have much in common with [[Nazism]], and some white supremacist groups, particularly in German-speaking countries, actively proclaim themselves Nazis.  

The militant approach taken by some groups has caused them to be watched closely by law enforcement officials. In some European countries, which have more recent experience of the effect of such beliefs in [[World War II]], white supremacist groups are banned by various laws.

There are a number of white supremacy groups that do not necessarily adhere to [[Christian Identity]] or other religious doctrines. White supremacy groups such as the [[National Alliance]], the [[American Nazi Party]] and the National Socialist White People’s Party are largely politically, rather than religiously, motivated.

The National Alliance is probably best known for its leader, [[William Pierce]], who is one of the most recognized names in the radical right. Pierce wrote [[The Turner Diaries]] and Hunter and hosts a weekly radio program, American Dissident Voices. Via these outlets, Pierce is able to provide his followers with an ideological and practical framework for committing violent acts. The rhetoric of these groups largely shadows that of [[Adolf Hitler]]’s in content and political ideology. In 1997, Pierce stated that:

:Ultimately we must separate ourselves from the Blacks and other non-whites and keep ourselves separate, no matter what it takes to accomplish this. We must do this not because we hate Blacks, but because we cannot survive if we remain mixed with them. And we cannot survive if we permit the Jews and the traitors among us to remain among us and to repeat their treachery. Eventually we must hunt them down and get rid of them.

There are also white supremacist groups which adhere to the general supremacist ideology, but are not political or religious in nature. For example, the [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK) proposes racial segregation that is not generally based on religious ideals. The KKK is one of the most recognized white supremacist groups in the United States. Its history is expansive and its actions of cross burnings and rhetoric of hate are well known. There is currently not a singular KKK group with a hierarchical structure, but many different KKK groups with a common ideology.

The [[World Church of the Creator]] (WCOTC) presents a recent example of violence perpetrated by a white supremacist in order to bring about a race war.  [[Ben Klassen]], the sect's founder, believed the religion is that one's race is his religion. Aside from this central belief, its ideology is similar to many Christian Identity groups in the conviction that there is a Jewish [[conspiracy]] in control of the federal government, international banking, and the media. They also dictate that RAHOWA, a RAcial HOly WAr, is destined to ensue to rid the world of Jews and “mud races.”  In the early 1990s, there was a dramatic increase in membership due to the growing belief in the Apocalypse and that RAHOWA was imminent.

In 1996, [[Matthew Hale|Matt Hale]], who has come upon recent fame by being denied a license to practice law in Illinois, was appointed the new leader of the Church of the Creator. Hale made a number of changes to the group, including changing the name of the organization to the World Church of the Creator, giving it the feel of a widespread movement.

There have been recent incidents that have demonstrated the willingness of members to take part in violent action. WCOTC members in Southern Florida are thought to be tied to several racially motivated beatings. Within the last year, four Florida members were convicted for the pistol-whipping and robbery of a Jewish video store owner. They were supposedly trying to raise money for "the revolution."

Many [[Asatru|Odinists]] believe in the necessity of becoming martyrs for their cause. For example, [[Robert Jay Matthews|Bob Matthews]], the leader of The Order, died in a confrontation with law enforcement. Also, William King relished the fact that he would receive the death penalty for his act of murdering James Byrd, Jr. Odinism has little to do with Christian Identity but there is one key similarity: Odinism provides dualism - as does Christian Identity - with regard to the universe being made up of worlds of light (white people) and worlds of dark (non-white people). The most fundamental difference between the two ideologies is that Odinists do not believe in [[Jesus Christ]].  However, there are enough similarities between the myths and legends of Odinism and the beliefs of Christian Identity to make a smooth transition from Christian Identity to Odinism for those racist individuals whose penchant for violence is not being satisfied.

==White Supremacy Organizations==
* [[Aryan Brotherhood]]
* [[Aryan Nations]]
* [[Christian Conservative Church]]
* [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK)
* [[Posse Comitatus]]
* [[White Aryan Resistance]] (WAR)
* [[White Patriot Party]]
* [[World Church of the Creator]] (WCOTC)


See also: [[Master race]], [[Racism]], [[Apartheid]], [[Matthew Hale]], [[Zionist Occupation Government]]

Compare: [[Black supremacy]], [[Black power]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>