<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071031214923|168385740" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33178" pageid="33178" ns="0" title="White supremacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-07T23:14:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Citations missing|date=January 2007}}

'''White supremacy''' is a [[Racism|racist]] ideology based on the assertion that [[white people]] are superior to other [[race]]s. The term is sometimes used specifically to describe a political ideology that advocates [[Society|social]] and [[Politics|political]] dominance for whites.

White supremacy, as with racial [[supremacism]] in general, is rooted in [[ethnocentrism]] and a desire for [[hegemony]]. It is associated with varying degrees of racism and [[xenophobia]] as well as a desire for [[racial separation]]. White supremacy has often resulted in anti-[[Black people|black]] racism and [[antisemitism]], although it has also involved [[prejudice]] and [[discrimination]] against a wide variety of "non-white" groups, including [[Arab]]s and the various [[Asian people]]s. 

Different forms of white supremacy have different definitions of 'white', and not all white supremacist organizations agree on which group is the greatest enemy. White supremacists frequently consider [[Jew]]s to be the gravest threat to their cause, and accuse them of manipulating other minority groups for their own gain.

==History==
Politically, socially and economically, white supremacy was dominant in the [[United States]] before the [[American Civil War]] and for decades after [[Reconstruction]]. The same is true of [[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|Apartheid-era South Africa]] and of parts of [[Europe]] at various time periods; most notably under [[Nazi Germany]]'s [[Third Reich]]. The extent and nature of white supremacy's continuing influence in western culture is a subject of ongoing debate. In some parts of the United States, many people who were considered non-white were [[Disfranchisement|disenfranchised]], barred from government office, and prevented from holding most government jobs — well into the second half of the twentieth century. White leaders often viewed [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] (known as [[First Nations]] in [[Canada]]) and [[Australian Aborigine]]s as obstacles to economic and political progress, rather than as [[settler]]s in their own right. Many [[Europe]]an-settled countries bordering the [[Pacific Ocean]] limited immigration and naturalization from the Asian Pacific countries, usually on a cultural basis. Many [[U.S. state]]s banned [[interracial marriage]] through so-called "[[anti-miscegenation laws]]" until 1967, when these laws were declared unconstitutional. [[South Africa]] maintained the white supremacist Apartheid system until the early 1990s.

==Specific white supremacist ideologies==
There is considerable disagreement between different types of white supremacists about which people should be classified as [[White people|white]], and about which people they are supposedly superior to. 

===Pan Europeanism===
''Pan Europeanism'' accepts all native and original Western European peoples, ranging from fair-skinned [[Sweden|Swedes]], [[Great Britain|Britons]] and [[Germany|Germans]] to darker complexioned Italians, Spaniards, Portuguese,and Greeks.

===Pan Aryanism===
Another variant, ''Pan Aryanism'', accepts native Europeans from all of continental Europe and extends its acceptance to non-European Caucasoids, such as some Middle Easterners, North Africans, and Central/West Asians. Yet this is usually on an individual basis and not all people from these regions are accepted by Pan-Aryanists as white. With regard to the acceptance of Middle Easterners in Pan-Aryanist ideology, Syrians, Lebanese, [[Turkish people|Turks]] (who are often considered European), and Persians are accepted as white, but Saudis and Yemenites ''as a whole'' are not.

South Asian Caucasoids (Pakistanis, Northern Indians etc) ''as a whole'' may generally not be accepted in this ideology as well, however some Pan-Aryanists acknowledge and have disputing beliefs on lighter skinned people descended from [[Aryans]] in this region. An example is a textbook for those taking entrance examinations for the [[British Civil Service]] in the early 1900s categorically stated that [[Afghan people|Afghans]] and [[Berber people|Berbers]] were in the highest classification, along with Northern Europeans, but above the [[Spanish people|Spanish]] and [[Italian people|Italians]] &lt;ref name=gotw1904&gt;''Geography of the World''. [[British Civil Service|Civil Service]] Book Depot, 1904.&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Nordicism===
Those who follow the ideology of ''[[Nordic theory|Nordicism]]'' and ''[[Germanicism]]'' only consider Northern European people who are Nordic or Germanic (and often Celtic) to be white, shunning Southern and Eastern Europe (who often have darker complexion and are of totally different cultures) along with anyone whose ethnic heritage is not European. In [[Madison Grant]]'s 1916 book, ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'', Europeans who were not of Germanic origin and had Nordic characteristics such as blonde hair and light eyes were considered to be a Nordic admixture and suitable for [[Aryanization]]. &lt;ref name="Grant1916"&gt;[[Madison Grant|Grant, Madison]]. ''The Passing of the Great Race''. Charles Scribner's Sons, New York, 1916.&lt;/ref&gt;  .

===Religious movements===
The [[Christian Identity]] movement, which regards other branches of [[Christianity]] as heretical, is closely tied to white supremacy. The [[Ku Klux Klan]]'s reasons for supporting [[racial segregation]] are not primarily based on religious ideals, although some Klan groups are openly Christian [[Protestant]] because of their northern European/Germanic roots.
Some white supremacists identify themselves as [[Ásatrú|Odinists]], although most Odinists reject white supremacy, and white supremacists make up only a small fraction of those who support Odinism (belief in the gods of [[Norse mythology]]). The white supremacist version of Odinism claims that the universe is composed of "worlds of light" ([[white people]]) and "worlds of dark" (non-white people).{{Fact|date=January 2007}}  Some white supremacist groups, such as the [[South Africa]]n [[Boeremag]], conflate elements of Christianity and Odinism.

The World Church of the Creator, now called the [[Creativity Movement]],  believed that a person's race is his [[religion]]. Aside from this central belief, its ideology is similar to many Christian Identity groups, in the conviction that there is a [[Jew]]ish [[Conspiracy theory|conspiracy]] in control of the [[United States]] government, international banking, and the media. They claim that a [[Racial Holy War]] (''RAHOWA''), is destined to happen, which would eliminate Jews and "mud races" from the planet.  In the early 1990s, there was a dramatic increase in membership, due to the growing belief in the [[apocalypse]]. A different (non-racist) group called [[Church of the Creator]] legally trademarked the name and won a lawsuit in 1996, leading to the white supremacist group to change its name to the Creativity Movement.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.churchofthecreator.org/TM/TMindex.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contemporary white supremacist groups==
{{refimprove|section|date=May 2007}}
White supremacist groups can be found in most countries and regions with a significant white population, including [[North America]], [[Europe]], [[Australia]],  [[New Zealand]], [[South Africa]], and parts of [[Latin America]]. In all of these locations, their views represent a relatively small minority of the population, and active membership of the groups is quite small. However, a [[backlash]] to the influx of non-white immigrants into various European nations has spurred a rise in membership in such extremist organizations, as well as an escalation in militant white supremacist demonstrations and [[hate crime]]s.  The militant approach taken by white supremacist groups has caused them to be watched closely by law enforcement officials. Some European countries have laws forbidding [[hate speech]], as well as other laws that ban or restrict white supremacist organizations but not all.

==See also==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Apartheid]]
* [[Dixiecrat]]
* [[Eugenics]]
* [[Germanic mysticism]]
* [[Institutional racism]]
* [[Jim Crow law]]
* [[Lynchings]]
* [[Master race]]
* [[nadir of American race relations]]
* [[Neo-Nazism#United States|Neo-Nazi groups of the United States]]
* [[Nordic theory]]
* [[Pigmentocracy]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[White Australia policy]]
* [[Zionist Occupation Government]]

{{col-break}}
===Compare===
* [[Black supremacy]]
* [[Racism]] and [[anti-racism]]
* [[Black power]] and [[White Power]]
* [[Asian pride]], [[Black pride]] and [[White pride]]
* [[White nationalism]] and [[Black nationalism]]
* [[White separatism]] and [[Black separatism]]
* [[Kahanism]]
{{col-end}}

== Footnotes ==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;&lt;references/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

{{White supremist organizations}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:White supremacy|*]]
[[Category:Ethnic supremacy]]
[[Category:Neo-Nazi movements and concepts]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Racism]]

[[es:Supremacismo blanco]]
[[ko:백인 우월주의]]
[[ja:白人至上主義]]
[[pl:Biała supremacja]]
[[fi:Valkoinen ylivalta]]
[[zh:白人優越主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>