<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051101213639|27104781" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="27165" pageid="27165" ns="0" title="Sexism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T04:52:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:National Association Against Woman Suffrage.jpg|thumb|The sign of the headquarters of the National Association Opposed To Woman Suffrage]]
'''Sexism''' is commonly considered to be [[discrimination]] against people based on their [[sex]] rather than their individual merits, but can also refer to any and all differentiations based on sex. 
'''Sexism''' can refer to three subtly different beliefs or attitudes:
*The belief that one [[sex]] is superior to the other.
*The belief that [[men]] and [[women]] are very different and that this should be strongly reflected in society, language, the right to have sex, and the law.
*It can also refer to simple hatred of women ([[misogyny]]) or hatred of men ([[misandry]]).

Many peoples' beliefs range along a continuum. Some people believe that women should have equal access to all jobs except a few religious positions. Others believe that while women are superior to men in a few aspects, in most aspects men are superior to women.

Sexist beliefs are a species of [[essentialism]], which holds that individuals can be understood (and often judged) based on the characteristics of the group to which they belong&amp;mdash;in this case, their sex group (male or female). This assumes that all individuals clearly fit into the category of "male" or "female."

Sexism against women is often called [[chauvinism]], though chauvinism is actually a wider term for any extreme and unreasoning partisanship on behalf of a group to which one belongs, especially when the partisanship includes malice and hatred towards a rival group. 

While the view that women are superior to men is also sexism, only in recent years has an awareness of this "[[reverse sexism]]" begun to develop in public discourse.

Certain forms of sexual [[discrimination]] are illegal in many countries, but nearly all countries have laws that give special rights, privileges, or responsibilities to one sex. 

== Language ==

It has been argued that language plays a part in sexism, though it is disputed whether certain language causes sexism or sexism causes certain language (see the [[Sapir-Whorf hypothesis|Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis]]). At the most trivial level, [[Sexist_joke#Sexist_jokes|sexist joke]]s play a part in the acts of many [[comedian]]s, both male and female. Another example is [[gender-neutral language]] &amp;mdash; the avoidance of [[gender-specific job title]]s, [[non-parallel usage]], and other usage that is felt by some to be sexist. Opponents of such ideas often dismiss them as "[[political correctness]] gone mad."

''See also:'' [[stereotype]], [[gender role]], [[racism]], [[rankism]], [[triple oppression]], [[penis envy]], [[Jane Crow]], [[sex in advertising]], [[rape]]

== Relation of sexism with homophobia ==

Some [[gender theorist]]s interpret the fact that male-male relationships often incite a stronger reaction in those with [[homophobia]] than female - female ([[lesbian]]) as meaning that the homophobic person feels threatened by the perceived subversion of the [[gender paradigm]] in male - male sexual activity. To quote D.A. Miller, the "only necessary content of male heterosexuality is not a desire for women, but the negation of the desire for men." As Miller continues, this necessary negation is such that "straight men unabashedly ''need'' gay men, whom they forcibly recruit (as the object of their blows or, in better circles, their jokes) to enter into a polarization that exorcises the 'woman' in man, by assigning it to a class of man who may be considered to be no 'man' at all." (Thomas 2000)  They regard the reason male homosexuality is treated worse compared to female homosexuality as [[sexist]] in its underlying belief that men are superior to women and therefore for a man to ''"replace"'' a woman during intercourse with another man he is then subjecting himself to inferiority.

== Sexism and pornography==
Some express the view that [[pornography]] is a kind of sexism, because in usual pornographic performances the part of women is limited to a "pleasure-object" for a male spectator. The [[Germany|German]] feminist [[Alice Schwarzer]] is one representative of this point of view. She has brought this topic up again and again since the [[1970s]], in particular in the feminist magazine "Emma".
 
On the other hand, some famous pornographic actresses such as [[Teresa Orlowski]] and [[Timea Vagvoelgyi]] have publically stated that they don't feel themselves to be victims of male sexism.

==See also==
*[[Gender role]]
*[[Heterosexism]]
*[[Homophobia]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Rankism]]
*[[Rape]]
*[[Sex in advertising]]
*[[Stereotype]]
*[[Triple oppression]]

[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Sexism|*]]

[[als:Sexismus]]
[[bg:Сексизъм]]
[[ca:Sexisme]]
[[de:Sexismus]]
[[el:Σεξισμός]]
[[es:Sexismo]]
[[fa:جنسیت‌گرایی]]
[[fr:Sexisme]]
[[it:Sessismo]]
[[he:אפליה מינית]]
[[nl:Seksisme]]
[[ja:性差別]]
[[pl:Seksizm]]
[[pt:Sexismo]]
[[simple:Sexism]]
[[ru:Сексизм]]
[[sv:Sexism]]
[[zh:性别歧视]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>