<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131120113619|582510816" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="27165" pageid="27165" ns="0" title="Sexism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-20T11:38:42Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|cleanup-reorganize=February 2012|globalize=January 2012|POV-check=March 2012}}
{{Feminism sidebar}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Sexism''' is prejudice or discrimination based on a person's sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/sexism |title=Sexism - Definition and More from the Free Merriam-Webster Dictionary |publisher=Merriam-webster.com |date=August 31, 2012 |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sexist attitudes may stem from traditional [[stereotype]]s of [[gender role]]s,&lt;ref&gt;Matsumoto, 2001. P.197.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nakdimen KA The American Journal of Psychiatry [1984, 141(4):499-503]&lt;/ref&gt; and may include the belief that a person of one sex is intrinsically superior to a person of the other.&lt;ref&gt;[Doob, Christopher B. 2013. Social Inequality and Social Stratification in US Society. Upper Saddle River, NJ: Pearson Education, Inc.]&lt;/ref&gt; A job applicant may face discriminatory hiring practices, or (if hired) receive [[Gender pay gap|unequal compensation]] or treatment compared to that of their opposite-sex peers.&lt;ref&gt;Macionis, Gerber, John, Linda (2010). Sociology 7th Canadian Ed. Toronto, Ontario: Pearson Canada Inc.. pp. 298.&lt;/ref&gt; Extreme sexism may foster [[sexual harassment]], [[rape]] and other forms of [[sexual violence]].&lt;ref&gt;[Forcible Rape Institutionalized Sexism in the Criminal Justice System|  Gerald D. Robin Division of Criminal Justice, University of New Haven]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Origin of the term ==
According to [[Fred R. Shapiro]], in ''American Speech'' (Vol. 60, No. 1, Spring 1985), the term "sexism" was most likely coined on November 18, 1965, by [[Pauline M. Leet]] during the "Student-Faculty Forum" at [[Franklin and Marshall College]].&lt;ref name="wordpress2007"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://finallyfeminism101.wordpress.com/2007/10/19/feminism-friday-the-origins-of-the-word-sexism/ |title=Feminism Friday: The origins of the word "sexism" |work=Finallyfeminism101.wordpress.com |date=October 19, 2007 |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term appears in Leet's forum contribution titled "Women and the Undergraduate", in which she defines it by comparing it to racism, saying in part, "When you argue…that since fewer women write good poetry this justifies their total exclusion, you are taking a position analogous to that of the racist — I might call you in this case a "sexist"… Both the racist and the sexist are acting as if all that has happened had never happened, and both of them are making decisions and coming to conclusions about someone’s value by referring to factors which are in both cases irrelevant."&lt;ref name="wordpress2007"/&gt;

Also according to Shapiro, the first time the term "sexism" appeared in print was in Caroline Bird's speech "On Being Born Female", which was published on November 15, 1968, in ''Vital Speeches of the Day'' (p.&amp;nbsp;6).&lt;ref name="wordpress2007"/&gt; In this speech she said in part, "There is recognition abroad that we are in many ways a sexist country. Sexism is judging people by their sex when sex doesn’t matter. Sexism is intended to rhyme with racism. Both have used to keep the powers that be in power."&lt;ref name="wordpress2007"/&gt;

[[Sheldon Vanauken]] is sometimes falsely claimed to have coined the term "sexism" in his pamphlet "Freedom for Movement Girls – Now".&lt;ref name="wordpress2007"/&gt; In the pamphlet the term "sexism" appears without any citation of Leet or Bird, thus leading to the false idea that Vanauken coined it himself.&lt;ref name="wordpress2007"/&gt;

=={{anchor|History of gender discrimination}} History ==
[[File:A Hindoo Widow Burning Herself with the Corpse of her Husband.jpg|thumb|240px|[[sati (practice)|Sati]], or self-immolation by widows was prevalent in [[Hindu]] society during the Middle Ages.]]
Certain forms of sex discrimination are illegal in some countries; in others, discrimination may be legally sanctioned under a variety of circumstances.&lt;ref name="Neuwirth"&gt;Neuwirth, Jessica (2004). [http://www.msmagazine.com/summer2004/globalwomenlaw.asp "Unequal: A Global Perspective on Women Under the Law"]. ''Ms. Magazine''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{anchor|Ancient sexism}} Ancient world ===
According to [[Peter Sterns]], women in pre-agricultural societies held equal positions with men; it was only after the adoption of agriculture and sedentary cultures that men began to institutionalize the concept that women were inferior to men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= A Brief History of the World Course No. 8080 [Audio CD]|author= Peter N. Stearns (Narrator)|publisher= The Teaching Company|asin=B000W595CC}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Definitive examples of sexism in the ancient world included written laws preventing women from participating in the political process; for example, Roman women could not vote or hold [[Roman magistrate|political office]].&lt;ref&gt;Bruce W. Frier and Thomas A.J. McGinn, ''A Casebook on Roman Family Law'' (Oxford University Press: American Philological Association, 2004), pp. 31–32, 457, ''et passim''.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Coverture and other marriage regulations ===
{{main|Coverture}}
Until the 20th century U.S. and [[English law]] observed the system of [[coverture]], where "by marriage, the husband and wife are one person in law; that is the very being or legal existence of the woman is suspended during the marriage".&lt;ref&gt;Blackstone, William. ''Commentaries on the Laws of England.''http://www.mdx.ac.uk/WWW/STUDY/xBlack.htm&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. women were not legally defined as "persons" until 1875 (''[[Minor v. Happersett]]'', 88 U.S. 162).&lt;ref name="legacy98.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legacy98.org/timeline.html |title=Legacy '98: Detailed Timeline |publisher=Legacy98.org |date=2001-09-19 |accessdate=2010-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[France]] married women received the right to work without their husband's permission in 1965,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tandf.co.uk/journals/explore/cmcf-vsi-women-in-france.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parisvoice.com/-archives-97-86/282-frances-leading-women-show-the-way |title=France's leading women show the way |publisher=Parisvoice.com |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.womeninworldhistory.com/TWR-07.html |title=Lesson - The French Civil Code (Napoleonic Code) - Teaching Womens Rights From Past to Present |publisher=Womeninworldhistory.com |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in [[West Germany]] women obtained this right in 1977 (women in [[East Germany]] enjoyed more rights).&lt;ref&gt;.http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/06/world/europe/06iht-letter.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=all&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.diw.de/documents/publikationen/73/diw_01.c.356386.de/dp998.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Spain]] during the [[Francisco Franco|Franco]] era a married woman required her husband's consent (''permiso marital'') for nearly all economic activities, including employment, ownership of property and traveling away from home; the ''permiso marital'' was abolished in 1975.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://countrystudies.us/spain/43.htm |title=Spain - Social Values And Attitudes |publisher=Countrystudies.us |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In many countries, women still lose significant legal rights at [[marriage]]. For example, [[Yemen]]i marriage regulations state that a wife must obey her husband and must not leave home without his permission.&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrc/docs/ngos/Yemen%27s%20darkside-discrimination_Yemen_HRC101.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Iraq]] husbands have a legal right to "punish" their wives. The criminal code states at Paragraph 41 that there is no crime if an act is committed while exercising a legal right; examples of legal rights include: "The punishment of a wife by her husband, the disciplining by parents and teachers of children under their authority within certain limits prescribed by law or by custom".&lt;ref&gt;http://law.case.edu/saddamtrial/documents/Iraqi_Penal_Code_1969.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Democratic Republic of Congo]] the Family Code states that the husband is the head of the household; the wife owes her obedience to her husband; a wife has to live with her husband wherever he chooses to live; and wives must have their husbands' authorization to bring a case in court or to initiate other legal proceedings.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrw.org/reports/2002/drc/Congo0602-09.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gender stereotypes ==
[[File:Bettie Page driving.jpg|thumb|300px|alt=Series of photographs lampooning women drivers|1952 magazine feature stereotypical women drivers.]]
Gender stereotypes are widely-held beliefs about the characteristics and behavior of women and men.&lt;ref&gt;Manstead, A. S. R.; Hewstone, Miles; et al. ''The Blackwell Encyclopedia of Social Psychology''. Oxford, UK; Cambridge, Mass., USA: Blackwell, 1999, 1995, pp. 256 &amp;ndash; 57, ISBN 978-0-631-22774-8.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Empirical]] studies have found widely-shared cultural beliefs that men are more socially valued and more competent than women in a number of activities.&lt;ref&gt;Wagner, David G. and Joseph Berger (1997). ''Gender and Interpersonal Task Behaviors: Status Expectation Accounts.'' Sociological Perspectives, Vol. 40, No. 1, pp. 1-32.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Williams, John E. and Deborah L. Best. ''Measuring Sex Stereotypes: A Multinational Study.'' Newbury Park, CA: Sage, 1990, ISBN 978-0-8039-3815-1.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, [[Susan Fiske]] and her colleagues surveyed nine diverse samples from different regions of the United States. Fiske found that members of these samples, regardless of age, consistently rated the category of "men" higher than the category of "women" on a multidimensional scale of competence.&lt;ref&gt;Fiske, Susan T., Amy J. C. Cuddy, Peter Glick, Jun Xu (2002). [http://www.nd.edu/~wcarbona/Fiske-et-al-2002.pdf ''A Model of (Often Mixed) Stereotype Content: Competence and Warmth Respectively Follow From Perceived Status and Competition.''] Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, Vol. 82, No. 6, p. 892.&lt;/ref&gt; Dustin B. Thoman and others (2008) hypothesize that “The socio-cultural salience of ability versus other components of the gender-math stereotype may impact women pursuing math”. Through the experiment comparing the math outcomes of women under two various gender-math stereotype components, which are the ability of math and the effort on math respectively, Thoman and others found that women’s math performance is more likely to be affected by the negative ability stereotype, which is influenced by socio-cultural beliefs in the United States, rather than the effort component.  As a result of this experiment and the socio-cultural beliefs in the United States, Thoman and others concluded that individuals’ academic outcomes can be affected by the gender-math stereotype component that is influenced by the socio-cultural beliefs (Thoman et al. 2008).&lt;ref&gt;Thoman, Dustin B., Paul H. White, Niwako Yamawaki, and Hirofumi Koishi. "Variations of Gender–math Stereotype Content Affect Women’s Vulnerability to Stereotype Threat." Sex Roles 58.9-10 (2008): 702-12. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

There are huge areal differences in attitudes towards appropriate gender roles. For example, in the ''[[World Values Survey]]'', responders were asked if they thought that wage work should be restricted to only men in the case of shortage in jobs. While in [[Iceland]] the proportion that agreed was 3.6%, in [[Egypt]] it was 94.9%.&lt;ref&gt;Fortin, Nicole, "Gender Role Attitudes and the Labour Market Outcomes of Women Across OECD Countries", Oxford Review of Economic Policy, 2005, 21, 416–438.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some people believe a phenomenon known as [[stereotype threat]] can lower women's performance on mathematics tests, creating a self-fulfilling stereotype of women having inferior quantitative skills compared to men.&lt;ref&gt;Shih, Margaret, Todd L. Pittinsky and Nalini Ambady (1999). [https://www.amherst.edu/media/view/120864/original/Shin%2Bet%2Bal--stereotype%2Bsusceptibility.pdf ''Stereotype Susceptibility: Identity, Salience and Shifts in Quantitative Performance.''] Psychological Science, Vol. 10, No. 1, pp. 80-3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Claude M. Steele|Steele, Claude M.]] (1997). [http://www.nber.org/sewp/events/2005.01.14/Bios+Links/Krieger-rec5-Steele_Threat-in-the-Air.pdf ''A Threat Is in the Air: How Stereotypes Shape Intellectual Identity and Performance.''] American Psychologist, Vol. 52, No. 6, pp. 613-29.&lt;/ref&gt; Stereotypes can also affect self-assessment; studies found that specific stereotypes (e.g., women have lower mathematical abilities) affect women's and men’s perceptions of those abilities, and men assess their own task ability higher than women who perform at the same level. These "biased self-assessments" have far-reaching effects, because they can shape men and women’s educational and career decisions.&lt;ref&gt;Correll, Shelley J. (2001). [http://www.chaire-crsng-inal.fsg.ulaval.ca/fileadmin/docs/documents/Article/Gender_and_career_choice_process_2001.pdf ''Gender and the career choice process: The role of biased self-assessments.''] American Journal of Sociology, Vol. 106, Issue 6, pp. 1691-1730.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Correll, Shelley J. (2004). [http://people.uncw.edu/maumem/soc500/Correll2004.pdf ''Constraints into Preferences: Gender, Status, and Emerging Career Aspirations.''] American Sociological Review, Vol 69, Issue 1, pp. 93-113.&lt;/ref&gt;

== In language ==
{{See also|Gender-neutral language}}

=== Sexist and gender-neutral language ===
Research indicates that the use of "he" in the [[English language]] as a generic pronoun evokes a disproportionate number of male images, excluding women in non gender-specific instances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bojarska|first=Katarzyna|title=Responding to lexical stimuli with gender associations: A Cognitive-Cultural Model|journal=Journal of Language and Social Psychology|date=23 October 2012|doi=10.1177/0261927X12463008|volume=32|page=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Miller, Megan M. and Lorie E. James (2009). [http://www.jstor.org/pss/27784423 ''Is the generic pronoun he still comprehended as excluding women?''] American Journal of Psychology, Vol. 122, No. 4, pp. 483-496.&lt;/ref&gt; Results also suggest that while the plural "they" functions as a generic pronoun for both males and females, males may comprehend "he/she" in a manner similar to "he", since "he" is usually placed before the slash and "she" after it. This is seen by some as a linguistic convention, not driven by gender roles.&lt;ref&gt;Gastil, John (1990) [http://www.springerlink.com/content/u817g2142392445v/ ''Generic Pronouns and sexist language: The oxymoronic character of masculine generics.''] Sex Roles, Vol. 23, Nos. 11/12, pp. 629-643.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 20th century there was a rise in gender-neutral language in the western world, often attributed to the rise of [[feminism]]. [[Gender-neutral language]] is the avoidance of [[gender-specific job title]]s, non-parallel usage and other usage considered sexist. Supporters claim that gender-specific language may imply a systemic bias to exclude individuals based on gender, or is as unnecessary as language based on (for example) race, religion or height.

=== Anthropological linguistics and gender-specific language ===
{{Unreferenced section|date=December 2012}}
Unlike the [[Indo-European languages]], [[gender-specific pronouns]] in many other [[languages]] are a relatively recent phenomenon (occurring during the early 20th century). Cultural revolution resulted from [[colonialism]] in many parts of the world, with attempts to modernize and westernize local languages with gender-specific and animate-inanimate pronouns. As a result, [[gender-neutral pronoun]]s became gender-specific (see, for example, [[Gender-neutrality in languages without grammatical gender#Turkish|gender-neutrality in languages without grammatical gender: Turkish]]).

=== Gender-specific pejorative terms ===
Gender-specific pejorative terms intimidate or harm another person because of their gender. Sexism can be expressed in language with negative gender-oriented implications,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anti-bullyingalliance.org.uk/pdf/SST%20Quick%20Guide.pdf ]{{dead link|date=July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as [[Disdain|condescension]]. Other examples include obscene language. &lt;!-- Do not list swear words here. --&gt;Some words are offensive to transgender people, including "tranny", "she-male", or "he-she". Intentional misgendering (assigning the wrong gender to someone) and the pronoun "it" are also considered pejorative.&lt;ref name="Mills College Report on Inclusion of Transgender and Gender Non-Conforming Students Best Practices, Assessment and Recommendations"&gt;Mills College Transgender Best Practices Taskforce &amp; Gender Identity and Expression Sub-Committee of the Diversity and Social Justice Committee. [http://www.mills.edu/diversity/Transgender-Best-Practices-02-18-2013.pdf ''Report on Inclusion of Transgender and Gender Non-Conforming Students Best Practices, Assessment and Recommendations''.] Oakland, Calif.: Mills College, February 2013, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="San Diego LGBT Weekly"&gt;Anti-transgender Language [http://lgbtweekly.com/2011/02/03/anti-transgender-language/ ''Commentary: Trans Progressive'' by Autumn Sandeen] San Diego, Calif.: San Diego LGBT Weekly, February 3, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Occupational sexism ==
{{Main|Occupational sexism}}
Occupational sexism refers to [[discriminatory]] practices, statements or actions, based on a person's [[sex]], occurring in the workplace. One form of occupational sexism is [[wage discrimination]].

In 2008 the  [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]] (OECD) found that while female employment rates have expanded and gender employment and wage gaps have narrowed nearly everywhere, on average women still have 20% less chance to have a job and are paid 17% less than men.&lt;ref name="oecd1"/&gt; The report stated: &lt;blockquote&gt;[In] many countries, labour market [[discrimination]] – i.e. the unequal treatment of equally productive individuals only because they belong to a specific group – is still a crucial factor inflating disparities in employment and the quality of job opportunities [...] Evidence presented in this edition of the ''Employment Outlook'' suggests that about 8% of the variation in gender employment gaps and 30% of the variation in gender wage gaps across OECD countries can be explained by discriminatory practices in the labour market.&lt;ref name="oecd1"&gt;[[OECD]]. [http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/8/19/40937574.pdf ''OECD Employment Outlook - 2008 Edition Summary in English''.] OECD, Paris, 2008, p. 3-4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oecd2"&gt;[[OECD]]. [http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/36/17/43244511.pdf ''OECD Employment Outlook. Chapter 3: The Price of Prejudice: Labour Market Discrimination on the Grounds of Gender and Ethnicity''.] OECD, Paris, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

It also found that despite the fact that almost all OECD countries, including the U.S.,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Facts About Compensation Discrimination
|author=The U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission
|url=http://www.eeoc.gov/facts/fs-epa.html
|accessdate=2008-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; have established anti-discrimination laws, these laws are difficult to enforce.&lt;ref name="oecd1"/&gt;

=== Gender stereotypes ===
Gender roles are behaviors and tasks which society associates with each gender. In the United States, men are typically expected to be stoic, decisive, direct, athletic, strong, driven, and brave; women are expected to be emotional, nurturing, weak, affectionate, home-oriented and forgiving.&lt;ref&gt;Susan Rachael SeemM, D. C. (2006). Healthy women, healthy men, and healthy adults: An evaluation of gender role stereotypes in the twenty-first century. Sex Roles, 55(3-4), 247-258. doi: http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11199-006-9077-0&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[OECD]], women's labor-market behavior "is influenced by learned cultural and social values that may be thought to discriminate against women (and sometimes against men) by stereotyping certain work and life styles as 'male' or 'female'". The organization contends that women's educational choices "may be dictated, at least in part, by their expectations that [certain] types of employment opportunities are not available to them, as well as by gender stereotypes that are prevalent in society".&lt;ref name="oecd.org" /&gt;

Professional discrimination against women in the workplace continues. One study found that 50 percent of women in government jobs reported that they had experienced discrimination while performing a work-related task, and 20 percent of female government employees reported that they experienced gender discrimination at work.&lt;ref&gt;Lawn-Day, G.A. and Ballard, S.  “Speaking out: Perceptions of women managers in public service.”  Review of Public Personnel Administration, Vol. 16 No. 1,1996, pp. 41-58&lt;/ref&gt; Women do not receive [[Equal Pay Act of 1963|equal pay]] for equal work, and are less likely to be promoted.&lt;ref&gt;Ashraf, J.  “Is Gender Pay Discrimination on the Wane?  Evidence from Panel Data, 1968-1989”, Industrial and Labor Relations Review, Vol. 49 No.3, 1996, p.539&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1833, women working in factories earned one-quarter of what men earned; in 2007, women's median annual paychecks were $0.78 for every $1.00 earned by men. A study showed that women comprised 87% of workers in the child-care industry, and 86 percent of the health-aide industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.now.org/issues/economic/factsheet.html |title=Women Deserve Equal Pay |publisher=Now.org |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others contest the wage gap, saying the difference in pay primarily reflects different career and work-hours choices by men and women rather than sexism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-505125_162-28246928/the-gender-pay-gap-is-a-complete-myth/ |title=The Gender Pay Gap is a Complete Myth |publisher=CBS News |date=March 8, 2011 |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2009 study found that being overweight harms women's career advancement, but presents no barrier for men. [[Overweight]] or [[obese]] women were significantly underrepresented among company bosses; however, a significant proportion{{quantify|date=October 2013}} of male executives were overweight or obese. The author of the study stated that the results suggest that "the 'glass ceiling effect' on women's advancement may reflect not only general negative stereotypes about the competencies of women, but also weight bias that results in the application of stricter appearance standards to women. Overweight women are evaluated more negatively than overweight men. There is a tendency to hold women to harsher weight standards."&lt;ref&gt;Roehling, Patricia V., Mark V. Roehling, Jeffrey D. Vandlen, Justin Blazek, William C. Guy (2009). ''Weight discrimination and the glass ceiling effect among top US CEOs.'' Equal Opportunity International, Vol. 28, Iss. 2, pp.179 - 196, {{doi|10.1108/02610150910937916}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Moult, Julie. [http://www.heraldsun.com.au/news/national/gender-divide-in-career-belly/story-e6frf7l6-1225697154065 ''Women's careers more tied to weight than men -- study.''] [[Herald Sun]], April 11, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Transgender people also experience workplace discrimination and harassment.&lt;ref&gt;Badgett, M.L., Lau, H., Sears, B., &amp; Ho, D. (2007) ''Bias in the Workplace: Consistent Evidence of Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity Discrimination.'' Los Angeles: The Williams Institute. http://williamsinstitute.law.ucla.edu/research/workplace/bias-in-the-workplace-consistent-evidence-of-sexual-orientation-and-gender-identity-discrimination/&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike sex-based discrimination, the refusal to hire (or firing) a worker for their gender identity or expression is legal in most countries and U.S. states.

=== Wage gap ===
{{Main|Gender pay gap}}
[[File:EU 27 Gender Pay Gap.001.png|thumb|300px|alt=Bar graph showing the gender pay gap in European countries|Gender pay gap in average gross hourly earnings according to [[Eurostat]] 2008&lt;ref name="EC stats" /&gt;]]
Several studies have found that women earn a smaller average wage than men. Many economists and feminist scholars have argued that this is the result of systemic gender-based discrimination in the workplace. Others,however, maintain that the wage gap is a result of differences between the choices that men and women make in the workplace, such as more women than men choosing to be full-time parents or work fewer hours to be part-time parents.

[[Eurostat]] found a persistent, average gender pay gap of 17.5 percent in the 27 [[Member state of the European Union|EU member states]] in 2008.&lt;ref name="EC stats"&gt;[[European Commission]]. [http://ec.europa.eu/justice/gender-equality/gender-pay-gap/situation-europe/index_en.htm ''The situation in the EU''.] Retrieved on August 19, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the [[OECD]] found that female full-time employees earned 17 percent less than their male counterparts in OECD countries in 2009.&lt;ref name="oecd1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="oecd2"/&gt;

In the United States, the female-to-male earnings ratio was 0.77 in 2009; female full-time, year-round (FTYR) workers earned 77 percent as much as male FTYR workers. Women's earnings relative to men's fell from 1960 to 1980 (60.7 percent to 60.2 percent), rose rapidly from 1980 to 1990 (60.2 to 71.6 percent), leveled off from 1990 to 2000 (71.6 to 73.7 percent) and rose from 2000 to 2009 (73.7 to 77.0 percent).&lt;ref name="census 2009"&gt;U.S. Census Bureau. [http://www.census.gov/prod/2010pubs/p60-238.pdf ''Income, Poverty, and Health Insurance Coverage in the United States: 2009.''] Current Population Reports, P60-238, U.S. Government Printing Office, Washington, DC, 2010, pp. 7 and 50.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Institute for Women's Policy Research. [http://www.iwpr.org/publications/pubs/the-gender-wage-gap-2009 ''The Gender Wage Gap: 2009''.] Retrieved March 31, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; When the first [[Equal Pay Act of 1963|Equal Pay Act]] was passed in 1963, female full-time workers earned 58.9 percent as much as male full-time workers.&lt;ref name="census 2009"/&gt;

The gender pay gap has been attributed to differences in personal and workplace characteristics between women and men (such as education, hours worked and occupation), innate behavioral and biological differences between men and women and discrimination in the labor market (such as gender stereotypes and customer and employer bias). Women interrupt their careers to take on child-rearing responsibilities more frequently than men.&lt;ref&gt;The Open University: Learning Space.[http://www.saylor.org/site/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/ECON303-8.2.1.pdf “Economics Explains Discrimination in the Labour Market."] Accessed June 29, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; A study by professor Linda Babcock in her book ''Women Don't Ask'' shows that men are eight times more likely to ask for a pay raise, suggesting that pay inequality may be partly a result of behavioral differences between the sexes.&lt;ref&gt;Women Don't Ask:
Negotiation and the Gender Divide Linda Babcock &amp; Sara Laschever 2003 Princeton UP. First chapter online: http://press.princeton.edu/chapters/i7575.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; However, studies generally find that a portion of the gender pay gap remains unexplained after accounting for factors assumed to influence earnings; the unexplained portion of the wage gap is attributed to gender discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;[[United States Congress Joint Economic Committee]]. [http://jec.senate.gov/public/?a=Files.Serve&amp;File_id=9118a9ef-0771-4777-9c1f-8232fe70a45c ''Invest in Women, Invest in America: A Comprehensive Review of Women in the U.S. Economy.''] Washington, DC, December 2010, p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates of the discriminatory component of the gender pay gap vary. The OECD estimated that approximately 30% of the gender pay gap across OECD countries is due to discrimination.&lt;ref name="oecd1"/&gt; Australian research shows that discrimination accounts for approximately 60 percent of the wage differential between women and men.&lt;ref name="natsem"&gt;National Centre for Social and Economic Modelling. [http://www.actu.org.au/Images/Dynamic/attachments/6895/NATSEM_report.pdf ''The impact of a sustained gender wage gap on the economy''.] Report to the Office for Women, Department of Families, Community Services, Housing and Indigenous Affairs, 2009, p. v-vi.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ian Watson (2010). [http://www.business.curtin.edu.au/files/295watson1.pdf ''Decomposing the Gender Pay Gap in the Australian Managerial Labour Market''.] Australian Journal of Labour Economics, Vol. 13, No. 1, pp. 49-79.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Male–female income disparity in the United States#Explaining the gender pay gap|Studies examining the gender pay gap in the United States]] show that a large portion of the wage differential remains unexplained, after controlling for factors affecting pay. One study of college graduates found that the portion of the pay gap unexplained after all other factors are taken into account is five percent one year after graduating and twelve percent a decade after graduation.&lt;ref name="denverpost.com"&gt;Carman, Diane. [http://www.denverpost.com/news/ci_5735341 ''Why do men earn more? Just because.''] Denver Post, April 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Arnst, Cathy. [http://www.businessweek.com/careers/workingparents/blog/archives/2007/04/working_women_a.html ''Women and the pay gap.''] Bloomberg Businessweek, April 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;American Management Association. [http://www.amanet.org/training/articles/Bridging-the-Gender-Pay-Gap.aspx ''Bridging the Gender Pay Gap.''] October 17, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dey, Judy Goldberg and Catherine Hill. [http://www.aauw.org/learn/research/upload/behindPayGap.pdf ''Behind the Pay Gap.''] American Association of University Women Educational Foundation, April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; A study by the American Association of University Women ([http://www.aauw.org/ AAUW]) found that women graduates are paid less than men doing the same work and majoring in the same field.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Morrison|first=Megan|title=Persistent Pay Gap Affects Women Just One Year Out of College|url=http://www.aauw.org/article/persistent-pay-gap-affects-women-just-one-year-out-of-college/|accessdate=2013-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:US gender pay gap, by sex, race-ethnicity.001.png|thumb|330px|Median weekly earnings of full-time wage and salary workers, by sex, race, and ethnicity, U.S., 2009.&lt;ref name="bls 2009"&gt;U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics. [http://www.bls.gov/cps/cpswom2009.pdf ''Highlights of Women’s Earnings in 2009.''] Report 1025, June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Wage discrimination is theorized as contradicting the economic concept of [[supply and demand]], which states that if a good or service (in this case, labor) is in demand and has value it will find its price in the market. If a worker offered equal value for less pay, supply and demand would indicate a greater demand for lower-paid workers. If a business hired lower-wage workers for the same work, it would lower its costs and enjoy a [[competitive advantage]]. According to supply and demand, if women offered equal value demand (and wages) should rise since they offer a better price (lower wages) for their service than men do.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.swifteconomics.com/2009/09/21/lies-damned-lies-and-statistics-the-wage-gap/ |title=Lies, Damned Lies and Statistics: The Wage Gap |publisher=Swift Economics |date=September 21, 2009 |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research at [[Cornell University]] and elsewhere indicates that mothers are less likely to be hired than equally-qualified fathers and, if hired, receive a lower salary than male applicants with children.&lt;ref&gt;Folbre, Nancy. [http://economix.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/03/26/family-responsibility-discrimination-would-ayn-like-fred/ ''The Anti-Mommy Bias.''] New York Times, March 26, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ellen Goodman|Goodman, Ellen]]. [http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/oped/articles/2007/05/11/a_third_gender_in_the_workplace/ ''A third gender in the workplace.''] Boston Globe, May 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cahn, Naomi and June Carbone. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/05/28/AR2010052802268.html ''Five myths about working mothers.''] The Washington Post, May 30, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Young, Lauren. [http://www.businessweek.com/careers/workingparents/blog/archives/2009/06/the_motherhood.html ''The Motherhood Penalty: Working Moms Face Pay Gap Vs. Childless Peers.''] Bloomsberg Businessweek, June 05, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Correll, Shelley, Stephen Benard, In Paik (2007.) [http://www.unc.edu/courses/2006spring/geog/203/001/motherhoodpenalty.pdf ''Getting a job: Is there a motherhood penalty?''] American Journal of Sociology, Vol 112, No. 5, pp. 1297-1338, {{doi|10.1086/511799}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;News.cornell.edu. [http://www.news.cornell.edu/stories/Aug05/soc.mothers.dea.html ''Mothers face disadvantages in getting hired.''] August 4, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[OECD]] found that "a significant impact of children on women’s pay is generally found in the United Kingdom and the United States".&lt;ref name="oecd.org"&gt;OECD (2002). [http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/28/58/18960381.pdf ''Emplyoment Outlook, Chapter 2: Women at work: who are they and how are they faring?''] Paris: OECD 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; Fathers earn [[USD|$]]7,500 more, on average, than men without children do.&lt;ref name="womensmedia.com"&gt;Lips, Hilary. "Blaming Women's Choices for the Gender Pay Gap." http://www.womensmedia.com/new/Lips-Hilary-blaming-gender-pay-gap.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

===={{anchor|Proposed Explanations}} Possible causes ====
According to Denise Venable at the [[National Center for Policy Analysis]], the "wage gap" is not the result of discrimination but of differences in lifestyle choices. Venable's report found that women are less likely than men to sacrifice personal happiness for increases in income or to choose full-time work. She found that among adults working between one and thirty-five hours a week and part-time workers who have never been married, women earn more than men. Venable also found that among people aged 27 to 33 who have never had a child, women's earnings approach 98% of men's and "women who hold positions and have skills and experience similar to those of men face wage disparities of less than 10 percent, and many are within a couple of points".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncpa.org/pub/ba392 |title=The Wage Gap Myth |publisher=NCPA |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Venable concluded that women and men with equal skills and opportunities in the same positions face little or no wage discrimination: "Claims of unequal pay almost always involve comparing apples and oranges".

=== Glass ceiling ===
{{Main|Glass ceiling}}
The term "glass ceiling" is used to describe a barrier to advancement based on gender discrimination. In academic achievement, improvements have been made. However, as of 1995 in the United States women received about half of all master's degrees but 95–97% of the senior managers of Fortune 1000 and Fortune 500 companies were male;&lt;ref name="DOL2"&gt;Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling2.pdf ''Solid Investments: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital''.] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, November 1995, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; of ''Forbes'' Global 2000 companies, 5% of senior managers were women.

The [[United Nations]] asserts that "progress in bringing women into leadership and decision making positions around the world remains far too slow."&lt;ref name="UN-IWD2006"&gt;{{cite web
|first=
|authorlink=
|coauthors=
|title=Women still struggle to break through glass ceiling in government, business, academia
|work=
|publisher=United Nations
|date=2006-03-08
|url=http://www.un.org/events/women/iwd/2006/PressReleaseIWD8March.pdf
|format=PDF|doi=
|accessdate=2008-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Objectification ==
[[File:Menu.jpg|thumb|An example of [[sexual objectification]] of women on a wine menu{{OR|date=October 2013}}]]
Objectification is treating a person, usually a woman, as an object.&lt;ref&gt;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-objectification/&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Sexual objectification]] is where a person is viewed primarily in terms of sexual appeal or as a source of sexual gratification. This is sometimes regarded as a form of sexism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Free Dictionary|url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/sex+object|publisher=Random House Kernerman Webster's College Dictionary|accessdate=2013-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In advertising===
Traditionally, in Western countries, advertising was regulated under "obscenity" laws. These dealt with nudity and "indecent" poses, not with objectification itself.

Today, some countries (for example [[Norway]] and [[Denmark]]) have laws against [[Sex in advertising|sexual objectification in advertising]].&lt;ref name="Holmes"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7365722.stm | work=BBC News | title=Scandinavian split on sexist ads | date=2008-04-25 | accessdate=2010-04-06 | first=Stephanie | last=Holmes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nudity is not banned, and nude people can be used to advertise a product if they are relevant to the product advertised. Sol Olving, head of Norway's Kreativt Forum (an association of the country's top advertising agencies) explained, "You could have a naked person advertising shower gel or a cream, but not a woman in a bikini draped across a car".&lt;ref name="Holmes"/&gt;

Other countries continue to ban nudity (on traditional obscenity grounds), but also make explicit reference to sexual objectification, such as [[Israel]]'s ban of [[bilboard]]s that "depicts sexual humiliation or abasement, or presents a
human being as an object available for sexual use". (Art 214)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.oecd.org/investment/anti-bribery/anti-briberyconvention/43289694.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Pornography ===
{{See also|Feminist views on pornography}}
Feminist [[Catharine MacKinnon]] argues that [[pornography]] contributes to sexism by objectifying women and portraying them in submissive roles.&lt;ref&gt;MacKinnon, Catharine (1987). ''Feminism Unmodified: Discourses on Life and Law''. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press. p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robin Morgan]] and Catharine MacKinnon suggest that certain types of pornography also contribute to [[violence against women]] by eroticizing scenes in which women are dominated, coerced, humiliated or [[sexually assault]]ed.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan, Robin. (1974). "Theory and Practice: Pornography and Rape". In: ''Going Too Far: The Personal Chronicle of a Feminist''. (1977). Random House. 333 p. ISBN 0-394-48227-1. (1978 ed, ISBN 0-394-72612-X.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mackinnon-guardian&gt;{{Cite news| last = Jeffries| first = Stuart| title = Are women human? (interview with Catharine MacKinnon)|work = [[The Guardian]]| accessdate = 2009-09-01| date = 2006-04-12| url = http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/apr/12/gender.politicsphilosophyandsociety}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some people opposed to pornography (such as MacKinnon) charge that the production of pornography entails physical, psychological and economic [[coercion]] of the women who perform and model in it.&lt;ref name=stanford-shrage&gt;Shrage, Laurie. (2007-07-13). [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminist-sex-markets/#Por "Feminist Perspectives on Sex Markets: Pornography"]. In: ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mackinnon, Catherine A. (1984) "Not a moral issue." ''Yale Law and Policy Review'' 2:321-345. Reprinted in: Mackinnon (1989). ''Toward a Feminist Theory of the State'' Harvard University Press. ISBN 0-674-89645-9 (1st ed), ISBN 0-674-89646-7 (2nd ed). "Sex forced on real women so that it can be sold at a profit to be forced on other real women; women's bodies trussed and maimed and raped and made into things to be hurt and obtained and accessed, and this presented as the nature of women; the coercion that is visible and the coercion that has become invisible—this and more grounds the feminist concern with pornography"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pbs.org"&gt;{{Cite episode| title = A Conversation With Catherine MacKinnon (transcript)| series = [[Think Tank (TV series)|Think Tank]]|network= PBS| accessdate = 2009-09-01| year = 1995| url = http://www.pbs.org/thinktank/transcript215.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Opponents of pornography charge that it presents a distorted image of sexual relations and reinforces sexual myths; it shows women as continually available and willing to engage in sex at any time, with any men, on their terms, responding positively to any requests. MacKinnon states:

{{quote|Pornography affects people's belief in rape myths. So for example if a woman says "I didn't consent" and people have been viewing pornography, they believe rape myths and believe the woman did consent no matter what she said. That when she said no, she meant yes. When she said she didn't want to, that meant more beer. When she said she would prefer to go home, that means she's a lesbian who needs to be given a good corrective experience. Pornography promotes these rape myths and desensitises people to violence against women so that you need more violence to become sexually aroused if you're a pornography consumer. This is very well documented.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/apr/12/gender.politicsphilosophyandsociety | location=London | work=The Guardian | first=Stuart | last=Jeffries | title=Stuart Jeffries talks to leading feminist Catharine MacKinnon | date=April 12, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Defenders of pornography and anti-censorship activists (including [[sex-positive feminists]]) argue that pornography does not seriously impact a mentally healthy individual, since the viewer can distinguish between pornography and reality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Michael |last=Bader |url=http://www.alternet.org/story/104863/the_great_porn_misunderstanding%3A_pornography_is_mostly_about_fantasy,_not_reality |title=The Great Porn Misunderstanding: Pornography Is Mostly About Fantasy, Not Reality |publisher=Alternet |date=October 27, 2008 |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; They contend that both sexes are objectified in pornography (particularly [[sadism and masochism (as medical terms)|sadistic]] or [[masochist]]ic pornography, in which men are objectified and sexually used by women).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.seejane.org/downloads/Hatton_Trautner_Sexuality_and_Culture.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prostitution===
[[File:Prostata Prostitute.jpg|thumb|Scene from [[Amsterdam]]'s [[De Wallen|red light district]]]]
Some people argue that [[prostitution]] is a form of exploitation of women, which is the result of discrimination of women (lack of professional opportunities for women, poverty) and of patriarchal views on sexuality which stipulate that unwanted sex with a woman is acceptable, that men's desires must be satisfied at any cost, and that women exist to serve men sexually. They argue that the consent of the prostitute is seriously undermined by direct (pimps) or indirect (social circumstances) coercion.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.soc.iastate.edu/sapp/Prostitution.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1300/J015v26n03_06#.UjsrJH9edO6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2006/jan/18/ukcrime.prisonsandprobation&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2007/sep/10/endingatradeinmisery&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://ressourcesfeministes.files.wordpress.com/2012/01/mackinnon-prostitution-and-civil-rights.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.ro/books?id=9mlFgjEBYWYC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=the+industrial+vagina&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=BVQ7UqTUN-Tl4gTIoYGADg&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=the%20industrial%20vagina&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt; The [[European Women's Lobby]] condemned prostitution as "an intolerable form of male violence".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.womenslobby.eu/spip.php?article472&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Carole Pateman]] writes that:&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.ro/books?id=jH2KPvZF1L0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;hl=ro&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;
:"Prostitution is the use of a woman's body by a man for his own satisfaction. There is no desire or satisfaction on the part of the prostitute. Prostitution is not mutual, pleasurable exchange of the use of bodies, but the unilateral use of a woman's body by a man in exchange for money".

=== Media portrayals ===
Some feminist scholars believe that media portrayals of demographic groups can both maintain and disrupt attitudes and behaviors toward those groups.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, E., &amp; Henderson Daniel, J. (Eds.). (2005). ''Featuring females: Feminist analyses of media.'' Washington, DC: American Psychological Association. doi:10.1037/11213-000&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=February 2013}}&lt;ref&gt;Halliwell, E., Malson, H., &amp; Tischner, I. (2011). Are contemporary media images which seem to display women as sexually empowering actually harmful to women? ''Psychology of Women Quarterly, 35'', 34-45. doi: 10.1177/0361684310385217&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Entman, R., &amp; Rojecki, A. (2000). ''The Black image in the White mind: Media and race in America.'' Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=February 2013}} These images are often harmful, particularly to women and racial and ethnic minority groups. For example, a study of African American women found they feel that media portrayals of African American women often reinforce stereotypes of this group as overly sexual and idealize images of lighter-skinned, thinner African American women (images African American women describe as objectifying).&lt;ref&gt;Watson, L. B., Robinson, D., Dispenza, F., &amp; Nazari, N. (2012). African American women's sexual objectification experiences: A qualitative study. ''Psychology of Women Quarterly, 36'', 227-239. doi: [http://pwq.sagepub.com/ 10.1177/0361684312454724]&lt;/ref&gt; In a recent analysis of images of Haitian women in the Associated Press photo archive from 1994 to 2009, several themes emerged emphasizing the "otherness" of Haitian women and characterizing them as victims in need of rescue.&lt;ref&gt;Rendon, M. J., &amp; Nicolas, G. (2012). Deconstructing the portrayals of Haitian women in the media: A thematic analysis of images in the Associated Press Photo Archive. ''Psychology of Women Quarterly, 36'', 227-239. doi: [http://pwq.sagepub.com/ 10.1177/0361684311429110]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sexist jokes ===
Sexist jokes can be a form of sexual objectification, which reduces the subject of the joke to an object (e.g., "What do you do when your dishwasher won't work?" Answer: "You hit her"). They not only objectify women or men, but can also condone violence or prejudice against men or women.{{citation needed|date=December 2012}} "Sexist humor—the denigration of women through humor—for instance, trivializes sex discrimination under the veil of benign amusement, thus precluding challenges or opposition that nonhumorous sexist communication would likely incur."&lt;ref name="ford"&gt;Ford, Thomas E., Christie F. Boxer, Jacob Armstrong, and Jessica R. Edel. 2007. More Than "Just a Joke": The Prejudice Releasing Function of Sexist Humor. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin. 34: 159-170.&lt;/ref&gt; A study of 73 male undergraduate students by Ford (2007) found that "sexist humor can promote the behavioral expression of prejudice against women amongst sexist men".&lt;ref name="ford" /&gt; According to the study, when sexism is presented in a humorous manner it is viewed as tolerable and socially acceptable. "Disparagement of women through humor 'freed' sexist participants from having to conform to the more general and more restrictive norms regarding discrimination against women."&lt;ref name="ford" /&gt;

== Gender discrimination in politics ==
[[File:Suffragette arrest, London, 1914.jpg|thumb|170px|A [[Women's suffrage in the United Kingdom|suffragette]] arrested in the street by two police officers in [[London]] in 1914]]
[[Suffrage]] is the civil right to vote. Gender is sometimes used as a criterion for the right to vote. Some Western countries allowed women the right to vote relatively recently: [[Switzerland|Swiss]] women gained the right to vote in federal elections in 1971,&lt;ref name="switzerland-chronology"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://history-switzerland.geschichte-schweiz.ch/chronology-womens-right-vote-switzerland.html |title=The Long Way to Women's Right to Vote in Switzerland: a Chronology |publisher=History-switzerland.geschichte-schweiz.ch |date= |accessdate=2011-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Appenzell Innerrhoden]] became the last [[Cantons of Switzerland|canton]] to grant women the right to vote on local issues (in 1991, when it was forced to do so by the [[Federal Supreme Court of Switzerland]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2003/WOM1373.doc.htm |title=United Nations press release of a meeting of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women (CEDAW), issued on 14 January 2003 |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[France|French]] women were granted the right to vote in 1944.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jean-Pierre Maury |url=http://mjp.univ-perp.fr/france/co1944-2.htm |title=Ordonnance du 21 avril 1944 relative à l'organisation des pouvoirs publics en France après la Libération |publisher=Mjp.univ-perp.fr |date= |accessdate=2011-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.assemblee-nationale.fr/histoire/femmes/citoyennete_politique_de-Gaulle.asp |title=La citoyenneté politique des femmes&amp;nbsp;– La décision du Général de Gaulle |author=Assemblée nationale |accessdate=2007-12-19 |language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Greece]], women obtained the right to vote in 1952.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.db-decision.de/CoRe/Greece.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
The first country to grant unrestricted rights to vote and stand for parliament was [[Finland]] (then the [[Grand Duchy of Finland]]) in 1906.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/5036602.stm Finland's trailblazing path for women BBC news]&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Women's suffrage in the United States]] was achieved gradually at the state and local levels during the 19th and early 20th centuries, culminating in 1920 with passage of the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Nineteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution]]: "The right of citizens of the United States to vote shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of sex." Since women gained the right to vote in the U.S., they have emerged in local and state politics and as presidential candidates. Although women are capable of gaining political power, gender stereotypes persist in politics. Data from the 2006 American National Election Studies Pilot Study measured "perceptions of women's and men's issue competency".&lt;ref name=Sanbonmatsu&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sanbonmatsu|first=Kira|coauthors=Kathleen Dolan|title=Do Gender Stereotypes Transcend Party?|journal=Political Research Quarterly|year=2009|month=September|volume=62|issue=3|pages=485–494|doi=10.1177/1065912908322416}}&lt;/ref&gt; One question asked was "Who would do a better job in the U.S. Congress handling crime—a [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrat]] who is a man, a Democrat who is a woman or would they equally do a good or bad job?"&lt;ref name=Sanbonmatsu /&gt; The same question was rephrased, replacing "Democrat" with "[[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]" The data indicates that voters use gender stereotypes for both Democrats and Republicans. When asked the question, voters stated that the male would do a better job in handling crime. When "handling crime" was changed to "handling education", they said that women would do a better job. The researchers believe that the voters responded as they did because "women politicians are perceived to possess typically feminine traits such as being warm and sensitive and are believed to be expert on 'so called' woman issues such as education. Moreover, male politicians are perceived to possess typically masculine traits, such as being assertive and tough".&lt;ref name=Sanbonmatsu /&gt; About 2 percent of voters (average: 1.9% Democrats in [[United States Congress|Congress]], 2.3% Republicans in Congress) believed that men would do a better job handling education, while about 6.4% (average 6.8% Democrats in Congress, 6.2% Republicans in Congress) said that women would do a better job. While voters may believe that women do a better job in certain areas than men (and vice versa), the survey then limits the analysis to respondents affiliated with a specific political party. When Republicans were asked the same questions about issue competency in education and crime, the results show that about 26 percent of Democratic women state that female Democratic politicians would do a better job handling education while just under 20 percent of Republican women held the same belief. More Republicans believed that Republican men are better able to handle crime (36 percent) than Democrats believed of Democratic men (14%).&lt;ref name=Sanbonmatsu /&gt;

The researchers conclude that "although it is often argued that any gender effect will disappear in the presence of the party cue, [they] find that gender stereotypes transcend party. Both Democratic and Republican politicians are believed to differ by gender in perceived issue competency and issue positions...Democrats are more likely to hold gender stereotypes that benefit women in politics. Democrats are more likely than Republicans to see an advantage for women on the issue of education and are less likely than Republicans to see a men advantage on the issue of crime".&lt;ref name=Sanbonmatsu /&gt; While Democrats are more likely to believe that women are better able to handle education, Republicans believe that men are better able to handle crime. "Overall, gender stereotypes appear to be more detrimental to the electoral chances of Republican women than Democratic women. In the end, this research offers support for the notion that women and men who run for office are viewed through multiple lenses by a public employing a range of stereotypes to the degree that people continue to see women and men as possessing different issue competencies".&lt;ref name=Sanbonmatsu /&gt; This indicates sexism, since one's gender should not indicate capability in handling crime or education. The split by political parties demonstrates that, based on the data and conclusions, Democrats believe that women are better able to handle education while Republicans believe that men are better fit to handle crime.&lt;ref name=Sanbonmatsu /&gt;

== Examples ==
Sexism takes a number of forms, and is sometimes subtle or unconscious.

=== Art ===
The [[Smithsonian American Art Museum]] reported in its 2011 survey of American civic art that there were 5,193 public statues in the United States of individuals; of these, 394 depicted females.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1= |first1= |date=July 2011 |title=Harper's Index |journal=[[Harper's]] |publisher=Harper's Foundation |volume=323 |issue=1,934 |page=17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{synthesis-inline|date=October 2013}}

=== Child marriage ===
{{Main|Child marriage}}
{{See|Dowry|Bride price}}
[[File:Termitwoman.jpg|thumb|Termitwoman|200 px|A tribal woman in [[Niger]]. Niger is estimated to have the highest rate of child marriage in the world.]]

A child marriage is a [[marriage]] where one or both spouses are under 18.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"&gt;http://www.unicef.org/protection/57929_58008.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hrw.org"&gt;http://www.hrw.org/news/2013/06/14/q-child-marriage-and-violations-girls-rights&lt;/ref&gt; Girls are disproportionately the most affected.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt; Child marriages are most common in [[South Asia]], the [[Middle East]] and [[Sub-Saharan Africa]], but occur in other parts of the world, too. The practice of marrying young girls is rooted in patriarchal ideologies of control of female behavior, and is also sustained by traditional practices such as [[dowry]] and [[bride price]]. Child marriage is strongly connected with the protection of female [[virginity]].&lt;ref name="bbc.co.uk"&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/people/features/ihavearightto/four_b/casestudy_art16.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; UNICEF states that:&lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt;
:"Marrying girls under 18 years old is rooted in [[gender discrimination]], encouraging premature and continuous child bearing and giving preference to boys' education. Child marriage is also a strategy for economic survival as families marry off their daughters at an early age to reduce their economic burden."

Consequences of child marriage include restricted [[education]] and [[employment]] prospects, increased risk of [[domestic violence]], [[child sexual abuse]], [[pregnancy]] and [[birth]] complications, [[social isolation]].&lt;ref name="hrw.org"/&gt;&lt;ref name="bbc.co.uk"/&gt; Early and forced marriage are defined as forms of modern-day [[slavery]] by the International Labour Organisation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2013/sep/02/nigeria-child-brides-religion |title=Nigeria's child brides: 'I thought being in labour would never end' |publisher=''[[The Guardian]]'' |date=September 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

According to the UN, the ten countries with the highest rates of child marriage are: [[Niger]] (75%), [[Chad]] and [[Central African Republic]] (68%), [[Bangladesh]] (66%), Guinea, Mozambique, Mali, Burkina Faso, South Sudan, and Malawi.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/releases/2013/child_marriage_20130307/en/&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Controlling women's dressing attire ===
[[File:Taliban beating woman in public RAWA.jpg|right|thumb|200px|A member of the Taliban's [[Mutaween#Other groups|religious police]] beating an Afghan woman in [[Kabul]] on August 26, 2001. [[Political violence|State violence]] against women is a form of discrimination against women.]]
Laws that dictate how women must dress are seen by many international human rights organizations, such as [[Amnesty International]], as a form of gender discrimination.&lt;ref name="doc.es.amnesty.org"&gt;https://doc.es.amnesty.org/cgi-bin/ai/BRSCGI/WOMENS%20RIGHT%20TO%20CHOOSE%20THEIR%20DRESS%20FREE%20OF%20COERCION?CMD=VEROBJ&amp;MLKOB=29309215959&lt;/ref&gt; Amnesty International states that:&lt;ref name="doc.es.amnesty.org"/&gt;

:"Interpretations of religion, culture or tradition cannot justify imposing rules about dress on those who choose to dress differently. States should take measures to protect individuals from being coerced to dress in specific ways by family members, community or religious groups or leaders."

In many places, women who do not dress in socially and legally proscribed ways are often subjected to violence (for instance by the authorities, such as the [[religious police]], by family members, or by the community).&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/6900111.stm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/1874471.stm&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{anchor|Crime sentencing gender gap}} Criminal Justice===
{{Globalize|discuss=Talk:Sexism#sexism in criminal justice|date=September 2013|section}}
Studies have shown that for identical crimes, men are given harsher sentences than women. Controlling for arrest offense, criminal history and other pre-charge variables, sentences are over 60 percent heavier for men. Women are more likely to avoid charges entirely, and to avoid imprisonment if convicted.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.com"&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/09/11/men-women-prison-sentence-length-gender-gap_n_1874742.html |title=Men Sentenced To Longer Prison Terms Than Women For Same Crimes, Study Says |publisher=Huffington Post |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="University of Michigan"&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.law.umich.edu/newsandinfo/features/Pages/starr_gender_disparities.aspx|title=Study finds large gender disparities in federal criminal cases|accessdate=August 30, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The gender disparity varies according to the nature of the case (for example, there is a smaller gender gap in fraud cases than in drug trafficking and firearms). This disparity occurs in U.S. federal courts, despite guidelines designed to avoid differential sentencing.&lt;ref name="etd.ohiolink.edu"&gt;[http://etd.ohiolink.edu/view.cgi?acc_num=bgsu1237482038 ]{{dead link|date=July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are many reasons postulated for the gender disparity. One of the most common is the larger caregiving role of women.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.com"/&gt;&lt;ref name="University of Michigan"/&gt;&lt;ref name="etd.ohiolink.edu"/&gt; Other possible reasons include the "girlfriend theory" (whereby women are seen as tools of their boyfriends),&lt;ref name="University of Michigan"/&gt; the theory that female defendants are more likely to cooperate with authorities,&lt;ref name="University of Michigan"/&gt; and that women are often successful at turning their violent crime into victimhood by citing defenses such as [[postpartum depression]] and [[battered wife syndrome]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Pearson|first=Patricia|title=When She Was Bad: How and Why Women Get Away With Murder|year=1998|publisher=Penguin Books|location=New York|isbn=0140243887|pages=236–239}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, none of these theories can account for the total disparity,&lt;ref name="University of Michigan"/&gt; and sexism has also been suggested as an underlying cause.&lt;ref&gt;"Unlike race and ethnic discrimination, however, the evidence is more consistent that part of this gap is due to different treatment of offenders based on their gender."{{cite web|url=http://www.ussc.gov/Research_and_Statistics/Research_Projects/Miscellaneous/15_Year_Study/chap4.pdf|title=Chapter Four: Racial, Ethnic, and Gender Disparities In Federal Sentencing Today|accessdate=August 30, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Transgender people are consistently discriminated against in jails and prisons. They are almost always put in the jail based on their sex and not their gender identity and are denied the ability to be able to take hormones or get sexual reassignment surgery and if they do they are never moved to prisons of the other gender. Studies show that trans people face an enormous amount of harassment and are at higher risk for sexual assault when they are not placed in prisons that match their gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;"Unlike race and ethnic discrimination, however, the evidence is more consistent that part of this gap is due to different treatment of offenders based on their gender."{{cite web|url=http://www.autostraddle.com/real-life-sophia-bursets-transgender-women-face-a-nightmare-in-mens-prisons-186876/|title=Real life Sophia Bursets Transgender Women face a nightmare in Men's Prisons|accessdate=October 18, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

=== Domestic violence ===
{{Main|Domestic violence}}
{{See|Honor killing|Stoning|Acid throwing}}
[[File:Acid attack victim.jpg|thumb|250px|Acid attack victim in [[Cambodia]]]]
Domestic violence takes a number of forms (including verbal, physical and psychological abuse), which vary across the gender spectrum. Domestic violence is tolerated and even legally accepted in many parts of the world. For instance, in 2010, the [[United Arab Emirates]] (UAE)'s Supreme Court ruled that a man has the right to physically discipline his wife and children if he does not leave physical marks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://articles.cnn.com/2010-10-19/world/uae.court.ruling_1_islamic-law-sharia-law-ruling?_s=PM:WORLD |title=Court in UAE says beating wife, child OK if no marks are left |publisher=CNN |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a report of the Special Rapporteur submitted to the 58th session of the [[United Nations Commission on Human Rights]] (2002) concerning cultural practices in the family that reflect violence against women (E/CN.4/2002/83):

{{quote|The Special Rapporteur indicated that there had been contradictory decisions with regard to the honour defense in [[Brazil]], and that legislative provisions allowing for partial or complete defense in that context could be found in the penal codes of [[Argentina]], [[Ecuador]], [[Egypt]], [[Guatemala]], [[Iran]], [[Israel]], [[Jordan]], [[Peru]], [[Syria]], [[Venezuela]] and the [[Palestinian National Authority]].&lt;ref name="unhchr"&gt;''Working towards the elimination of crimes against women committed in the name of honour: Report of the Secretary-General''. 2 July 2002. United Nations General Assembly.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Honor killings]] are a form of domestic violence which continues to be practiced in several parts of the world. The victims of honor killings are usually women.&lt;ref name=Maris2001&gt;{{cite journal|last=Maris|first=Cees|coauthors=Sawitri Saharso|title=Honour Killing: A Case for Cultural Defense?|journal=Pluralism and Law: Procedings of the 20th IVR World Congress, Amsterdam, 2001|year=2001|volume=3|page=108}}&lt;/ref&gt; Victims of honor killings are killed for reasons such as refusing to enter an arranged marriage, being in a relationship that is disapproved by their relatives, having sex outside marriage, becoming the victim of rape, dressing in ways which are deemed inappropriate, or engaging in homosexual relations.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/honourcrimes/crimesofhonour_1.shtml#h3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://edition.cnn.com/2012/01/13/world/europe/turkey-gay-killing&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://edition.cnn.com/2011/CRIME/02/23/arizona.iraqi.father/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Stoning]] (a form of punishment in which a group throws stones at a person, usually until the victimn dies) is associated with domestic disputes, especially those involving accusations of loss of chastity, adultery or the refusal of an arranged marriage.{{citation needed|date=January 2013}} Recently, several people have been sentenced to death by stoning after being accused of adultery in Iran, Somalia, Afghanistan, Sudan, Mali and Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Akbar |first=Ali |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/12/25/iran-stoning-woman-adultery_n_1169429.html |title=Iran Stoning: Woman To Be Executed For Adultery |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/8366197.stm |title=Somali woman stoned for adultery |publisher=BBC News |date=2009-11-18 |accessdate=2010-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Robert Tait and Noushin Hoseiny |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/jul/21/iran.humanrights |title=Eight women and a man face stoning in Iran for adultery |work= The Guardian |date= 2008-07-21|accessdate=2010-06-24 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,479752,00.html "Two Men Stoned to Death for Adultery in Iran".]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-10983494 | work=BBC News | title=Taliban 'kill adulterous Afghan couple' | date=2010-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sommerville |first=Quentin |url=http://www.rawa.org/temp/runews/2011/01/27/woman-stoned-to-death-in-north-afghanistan.html |title=Woman stoned to death in north Afghanistan |publisher=Rawa.org |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/may/31/sudanese-woman-stoning-death-adultery | location=London | work=The Guardian | first=David | last=Smith | title=Sudanese woman sentenced to stoning death over adultery claims | date=2012-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2012/08/02/world/africa/mali-couple-stoned/index.html |title=Islamists: Two stoned to death for committing adultery in Mali |publisher=CNN |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author== |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/jul/18/couple-sentenced-pakistan |title=Pakistani couple face death by stoning threat after conviction for adultery |publisher=The Guardian |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Practices such as [[honor killing]]s and stoning continue to be supported by mainstream politicians and other officials in some countries. In [[Pakistan]], after the 2008 [[Balochistan honour killings]] in which five women were killed by tribesmen of the [[Umrani|Umrani Tribe]] of [[Balochistan (Pakistan)|Balochistan]], Pakistani Federal Minister for Postal Services [[Israr Ullah Zehri]] defended the practice:&lt;ref name="times"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/asia/article4678530.ece |title=Three teenagers buried alive in 'honour killings' |accessdate=2008-09-05 |work=Times Online | location=London | first=Zahid | last=Hussain | date=2008-09-05}}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; "These are centuries-old traditions, and I will continue to defend them. Only those who indulge in immoral acts should be afraid."&lt;ref name="telegraph"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/pakistan/2660881/Pakistani-women-buried-alive-for-choosing-husbands.html |title=Pakistani women buried alive 'for choosing husbands'|accessdate=2008-09-01 |work=Telegraph | location=London | date=2008-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the 2006 case of [[Sakineh Mohammadi Ashtiani]] (which has placed [[Iran]] under international pressure for its stoning sentences), [[Mohammad-Javad Larijani]] (a senior envoy and chief of Iran’s Human Rights Council) defended the practice of stoning; he claimed it was a "lesser punishment" than [[Capital punishment|execution]], because it allowed those convicted a chance at survival.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/outrage-iran-human-rights-officials-defense-stoning/story?id=12193085#.UE4Qi64Zh0I |title=Outrage Over Iran Human Rights Official's Defense of Stoning |publisher=Abcnews.go.com |date=November 19, 2010 |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Hate-motivated sexual assault ===
Rape and sexual assault are considered to be acts of hate. Their relationship to sexism is the frequent desire on the part of the perpetrator for power over the victim. The Center for Women Policy Studies stated that "victims almost always are chosen for what they are rather than who they are"; a woman is more likely to be attacked because of her gender than her individuality.&lt;ref&gt;The National Center for Victims of Crime&lt;/ref&gt;

Research into factors motivating perpetrators of [[rape]] against women frequently reveals a pattern of hatred towards women and pleasure in inflicting psychological and physical trauma, rather than sexual interest.&lt;ref name=Lisak1988&gt;{{cite journal | author = Lisak, D.  |authorlink=David Lisak | coauthors = Roth, S. | year = 1988  | title = Motivational factors in nonincarcerated sexually aggressive men | journal = J Pers Soc Psychol  | volume = 55 | issue = 5 | pages = 795–802 | pmid = 3210146 | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.55.5.795}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mary Odem posits that rape is the result not of pathology but of systems of male dominance, cultural practices and beliefs which objectify and degrade women.&lt;ref name=Odem&gt;{{Cite book | author=Odem, Mary E.; | coauthors=Clay-Warner, Jody | title=Confronting rape and sexual assault | year=1998 | publisher=Scholarly Resources | location=Wilmington, Del.  | isbn=978-0-8420-2599-7 | pages=i-x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bangalore protests following Delhi gang-rape (photo - Jim Ankan Deka).jpg|thumb|People in [[Bangalore]], [[India]] demanding justice for young student who was [[2012 Delhi gang rape case|gang-raped in Delhi]] in December 2012]]
Mary Odem, Jody Clay-Warner and [[Susan Brownmiller]] consider that sexist attitudes are propagated by a series of myths about rape and rapists.&lt;ref name="Odem" /&gt;{{rp|130–140}} &lt;ref name=Brownmiller&gt;{{Cite book | author=Brownmiller, Susan | title=Against Our Will: Men, Women and Rape | year=1992 | publisher=Penguin Books, Limited | location=New York  | isbn=978-0-14-013986-0 | page=480}}&lt;/ref&gt; They state that in contrast to those myths, rapists often plan a rape before they choose a victim&lt;ref name="Odem"/&gt; and [[acquaintance rape]] (not assault by a stranger) is the most common form of rape.&lt;ref name="Odem" /&gt;{{rp|xiv}}&lt;ref name=Bohmer&gt;{{Cite book | editor=Parrot, Andrea; Bechhofer, Laurie | author=Bohmer, Carol | chapter=Acquaintance rape and the law | title=Acquaintance rape: the hidden crime | year=1991 | publisher=Wiley | location=New York  | isbn=978-0-471-51023-9 | pages=317–333}}&lt;/ref&gt; Odem also asserts that these rape myths propagate sexist attitudes about men, by perpetuating the belief that men cannot control their sexuality.&lt;ref name=Odem&gt;{{Cite book | author=Odem, Mary E.; | coauthors=Clay-Warner, Jody | title=Confronting rape and sexual assault | year=1998 | publisher=Scholarly Resources | location=Wilmington, Del.  | isbn=978-0-8420-2599-7 | page=135}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to [[acquaintance rape]], the "Men Can Stop Rape" movement has been implemented.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mencanstoprape.org/&lt;/ref&gt;  The U.S. military has begun a similar movement, with the slogan "My strength is for defending".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defense.gov/releases/release.aspx?releaseid=13379 |title=News Release: DOD Releases Annual Sexual Assault Response and Prevention Report |publisher=Defense.gov |date=March 12, 2009 |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Yes Means Yes: Visions of Female Sexual Power and A World Without Rape''
by [[Jaclyn Friedman]] and [[Jessica Valenti]], it is argued that in the US rape is most often popularly depicted (in the media, in public discourse, in movies etc.) as stranger-rape (with a stereotypical stranger who "jumps out of the bushes"), despite the fact that most rapes do not fit this stereotype. In presenting rape in this way to the public, patriarchal society ensures that women are kept under control, at home/indoors, living their life according to traditional gender roles and expectations, dressed 'modestly'. This leads to an ideology that women are safe at home (ignoring rape by family members/partners), and to [[victim blaming|blaming of victims]].&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.ro/books?id=NyicMIxzkUwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Yes+Means+Yes:&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=YW48UpOlH8KGtAb8p4CQCQ&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=Yes%20Means%20Yes%3A&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Education ===
Women have traditionally had limited access to higher education.&lt;ref&gt;Solomon, Barbara Miller. ''In the Company of Educated Women.''&lt;/ref&gt; When women ''were'' admitted to higher education, they were encouraged to major in less-intellectual subjects; the study of [[English literature]] in American and British colleges and universities was instituted as a field considered suitable to women's "lesser intellects".&lt;ref&gt;Eagleton, Terry. ''Literary Theory.''&lt;/ref&gt;

World literacy is lower for females than for males. Latest data from CIA World Factbook shows that 79.7% of women are literate, compared to 88.6% of men (aged 15 and over).&lt;ref&gt;https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/xx.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In some parts of the world, girls continue to be excluded from proper public or private education. In parts of [[Afghanistan]], girls who go to school face serious violence from some local community members and religious groups.&lt;ref name="edition.cnn.com"&gt;http://edition.cnn.com/2012/08/02/world/meast/cnnheroes-jan-afghan-school/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="edition.cnn.com"/&gt;

Girls' educational opportunities and results have greatly improved in the West. Since 1991, the proportion of women enrolled in college in the United States has exceeded the enrollment rate for men; the gap has widened over time.&lt;ref&gt;National Center for Education Statistics, http://nces.ed.gov/pubs2005/2005028.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2007, women made up the majority—54 percent—of the 10.8&amp;nbsp;million college students enrolled in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prb.org/Articles/2007/CrossoverinFemaleMaleCollegeEnrollmentRates.aspx |title=The Crossover in Female-Male College Enrollment Rates |publisher=Prb.org |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research has found that discrimination continues; boys receive more attention and praise (and  more blame and punishment) in the grammar-school classroom,&lt;ref&gt;Halpern, Diane F. ''Sex differences in cognitive abilities.'' Laurence Erlbaum Associates, 2000. ISBN 080582792. Page 259.&lt;/ref&gt; and "this pattern of more active teacher attention directed at male students continues at the postsecondary level".&lt;ref&gt;Sadker, Myra, and David Sadker. "Confronting Sexism in the College Classroom." In ''Gender in the Classroom: Power and Pedagogy.'' Ed. Susan L. Gabriel and Isaiah Smithson. Page 177.&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, female students speak less in a classroom setting.&lt;ref&gt;Sadker, Myra, and David Sadker. "Failing at Fairness: Hidden Lessons." In ''Mapping the social landscape: readings in sociology.'' Ed. Sandra J. Ferguson, [[Susan J. Ferguson]]. Taylor &amp; Francies, 1999. ISBN 0-7674-0616-8. Page 350.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is also argued that the educational system has become "feminized", allowing girls more of a chance at success with a more "girl-friendly" environment in the classroom;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Gerry |last=Garibaldi |url=http://www.city-journal.org/html/16_3_schools_boys.html |title=How the Schools Shortchange Boys |publisher=City-journal.org |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; this is seen to hinder boys by punishing "masculine" behaviour and diagnosing boys with [[Emotional and behavioral disorders|behavioural disorders]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Carolyn |last=Abraham |url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/time-to-lead/failing-boys/part-3-are-we-medicating-a-disorder-or-treating-boyhood-as-a-disease/article1762859/ |title=Part 3: Are we medicating a disorder or treating boyhood as a disease? |publisher=The Globe and Mail |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011 a [[United States Bureau of Labor Statistics]] report found that women are more likely than men to earn a [[bachelor's degree]] by age 23.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/02/10/post_644_n_821577.html |title=More Women Earn Bachelor's Degrees Than Men, Study Shows |publisher=Huffington Post |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bls.gov/ |title=U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics |publisher=Bls.gov |date=July 16, 2013 |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; A survey conducted by the [[Council of Graduate Schools]] similarly found that in the 2008–09 school year, women earned 50.9% of [[doctorate]]s and 60% of [[master's degrees]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2010/09/20/education/20iht-educBriefs20.html?_r=0&lt;/ref&gt;

Girls earn higher grades than boys until the end of high school; in some districts, girls achieve higher marks despite similar (or lower) scores than boys on standardised tests.&lt;ref&gt;Public Policy Sources, http://www.fraserinstitute.org/commerce.web/product_files/BoysGirlsandGradesIntro.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Female genital mutilation===
{{Main|Female genital mutilation}}
[[Female genital mutilation]] (FGM), also known as female genital cutting and female circumcision, is defined by the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO) as "all procedures that involve partial or total removal of the external female genitalia, or other injury to the female genital organs for non-medical reasons". WHO states that:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs241/en/&lt;/ref&gt;
:"The procedure has no health benefits for girls and women."

and

:"Procedures can cause severe bleeding and problems urinating, and later cysts, infections, infertility as well as complications in childbirth increased risk of newborn deaths."

and

:"FGM is recognized internationally as a violation of the human rights of girls and women. It reflects deep-rooted [[gender inequality|inequality between the sexes]], and constitutes an extreme form of [[gender discrimination|discrimination against women]]".

According to a 2013 UNICEF report, 125 million women and girls in Africa and the Middle East have experienced FGM.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;http://www.unicef.org/media/files/FGCM_Lo_res.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
The highest prevalence in Africa is documented in [[Somalia]] (98 percent of women affected), [[Guinea]] (96 percent), [[Djibouti]] (93 percent), Egypt (91 percent), Eritrea (89 percent), Mali (89 percent), Sierra Leone (88 percent), Sudan (88 percent), Gambia (76 percent), Burkina Faso (76 percent), Ethiopia (74 percent), Mauritania (69 percent), Liberia (66 percent), and Guinea-Bissau (50 percent).&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;

=== Female infanticide and sex-selective abortion ===
{{Main|Sex-selective abortion|Missing women of Asia}}
[[File:Something you wouldn't see in America.jpg|thumb| Female infanticide is still a major problem in India.]]
[[Female infanticide]] is the killing of very young female children. It is an extreme form of [[gender based violence]].&lt;ref name="eige.europa.eu"&gt;http://eige.europa.eu/content/what-is-gender-based-violence&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/abortion/medical/infanticide_1.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gsdrc.org/go/topic-guides/gender/gender-based-violence&lt;/ref&gt; Female infanticide is more common than male infanticide, and is especially prevalent in parts of [[Asia]], such as parts of [[India]] and [[People's Republic of China|China]].&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/6934540.stm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.domesticviolenceservices.com/female-infanticide.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Recent studies suggest that over 90 million [[Missing women of Asia|girls and women are missing]] in China and India as a result of systematic sex discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/24/opinion/24iht-edswami.html?_r=0 Missing: 50 million Indian girls]". The New York Times. November 25, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://iussp2005.princeton.edu/download.aspx?submissionId=51345 |title=Estimation of the Number of Missing Females in China: 1900-2000 |date= |accessdate=2013-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sex-selective abortion involves terminating a pregnancy based upon the predicted gender of the baby. The [[abortion]] of female fetuses is most common in areas where the culture values male children over females,&lt;ref name="Goodkind"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Goodkind, Daniel |year=1999 |title=Should Prenatal Sex Selection be Restricted?: Ethical Questions and Their Implications for Research and Policy |journal=Population Studies |volume=53 |issue=1 |pages=49–61 |jstor=2584811 |doi=10.1080/00324720308069}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as parts of the [[People's Republic of China]], [[India]], [[Pakistan]], [[Korea]], [[Taiwan]], and the [[Caucasus]].&lt;ref name="Goodkind"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Gettis"&gt;A. Gettis, J. Getis, and J. D. Fellmann (2004). Introduction to Geography, Ninth Edition. New York: McGraw-Hill. pp. 200. ISBN 0-07-252183-X&lt;/ref&gt; One reason for this preference is that males are seen as generating more income than females. A 2011 report on ''[[Science Daily]]'' stated that the trend grew steadily during the previous decade, and would probably cause a future shortage of women.&lt;ref&gt;Canadian Medical Association Journal (2011, March 14). The impact of sex selection and abortion in China, India and South Korea. ScienceDaily. Retrieved March 26, 2012, from http://www.sciencedaily.com /releases/2011/03/110314132244.ht&lt;/ref&gt;

===Forced sterilization and forced abortion===
[[Forced sterilization]] and [[forced abortion]] are forms of gender-based violence.&lt;ref name="eige.europa.eu"/&gt;

Forced sterilization was practiced during the first half of the 20th century by many Western countries (including the US) and there are reports of this practice being currently employed in some countries, such as [[Uzbekistan]] and [[People's Republic of China|China]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17612550&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b01fjx63&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.globalpost.com/dispatch/news/regions/asia-pacific/china/130409/china-mother-dies-after-forced-sterilization-one-child-policy&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/thousands-risk-forced-sterilization-china-2010-04-22&lt;/ref&gt;

Forced abortions are today associated mostly with China. Although they are not an official policy of the country, they result from government pressure on local officials who, in turn, employ strong-arm tactics on pregnant mothers. In 2012, a highy publicized case of a forced abortion involving the photo of the fetus has sparked international outrage.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-18435126&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Military service ===
{{see also|Military service|Israel#Military|l2=Israeli military}}
Military service has been considered a gender-specific duty. Some countries, such as [[Israel]], require military service regardless of gender. Others (such as [[Conscription in Turkey|Turkey]] and [[Conscription in Singapore|Singapore]]) still use a system of [[conscription]] which only requires military service for men, although women are permitted to serve voluntarily.

In the United States, all men must register with the [[Selective Service System]] within 30 days of their 18th birthday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sss.gov/default.htm |title=Selective Service System: Welcome |publisher=Sss.gov |date= |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The system does not require women to register, leading to criticism that it discriminates against men by forcing them into a dangerous role based on gender.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://haergar06.wordpress.com/2008/01/19/selective-service-is-one-the-worst-and-most-sexist-discriminations-against-men/ |title=Selective Service is one of the Worst And Most Sexist Discriminations against Men &amp;#124; The Marketplace of Ideas |publisher=Haergar06.wordpress.com |date=January 19, 2008 |accessdate=July 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Misandry ===
{{Main|Misandry}}
Misandry is the hatred of men and boys as a societal group or as individuals.

=== Misogyny ===
{{Main|Misogyny}}
Misogyny is the hatred of women and girls as a societal group or as individuals.

=== War rape ===
{{Main|War rape}}
[[File:DRC raped women.jpg|thumb|Meeting of victims of [[sexual violence]] in the Democratic Republic of the Congo.]]
War rapes are [[rape]]s committed by soldiers, other combatants or civilians during armed conflict, [[war]] or military occupation, and are distinguished from in-service sexual assault and rape committed amongst troops.&lt;ref&gt;[http://theconservativeblog.co.uk/?p=2382 "30% of Women in USA Military Raped Whilst Serving by Fellow Soldiers"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=103844570 "The Nation: The Plight of Women Soldiers"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inthesetimes.com/article/3848/ "Why Soldiers Rape - Culture of misogyny, illegal occupation, fuel sexual violence in military"]&lt;/ref&gt; It also encompasses situations in which women are forced into prostitution or [[sexual slavery]] by an occupying power, such as Japanese [[comfort women]] during World War II. Sexual violence and rape as a weapon of war also affects a large number of men, although it is less-often reported.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2011/jul/17/the-rape-of-men|title=The rape of men|last1=Storr|first1=Will|date=16 July 2011|work=The Observer|accessdate=8 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The war-torn [[Sexual violence in the Democratic Republic of the Congo|Democratic Republic of the Congo]] has been described as the "rape capital of the world" with more than 400,000 rapes reported in just one year.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/africa/400000-rapes-in-congo-in-one-year-2283102.html 400,000 rapes in Congo in one year]". ''[[The Independent]]''. May 12, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sexual slavery ===
{{Main|Sexual slavery}}
Sexual slavery occurs when people are coerced into [[slavery]] for [[Human sexual activity|sexual]] [[exploitation]]. The incidence of sexual slavery by country has been studied and tabulated by [[UNESCO]] (the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization) with the cooperation of a number of international agencies.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unescobkk.org/fileadmin/user_upload/culture/Trafficking/project/Graph_Worldwide_Sept_2004.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Sexual slavery also includes single-owner slavery, the ritual slavery associated with certain religious practices, slavery for primarily non-sexual purposes where non-consensual [[sex]] is common and [[forced prostitution]].

=== Transphobia ===
{{Main|Transphobia}}
{{See also|Phobia#Terms_for_prejudice_or_discrimination|l1=Phobia - terms for prejudice or discrimination}}
Transphobia refers to prejudice against transsexuality and transsexual (or transgender) people based on their gender identification. Whether intentional or not, transphobia can have negative consequences for the object of the negative attitude. The lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender ([[LGBT]]) movement opposes sexism against transsexuals. One form of sexism against transsexuals is "women-only" and "men-only" events and organizations, which have been criticized for excluding trans women and trans men.&lt;ref&gt;"Michigan Women's Music Festival ends policy of discrimination against Transwomen" http://www.intraa.org/story/newmwmfpolicy&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lesfest. http://www.lesbian.com/news/international_2003_1006.html&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Oppressive fashions and gender stereotypes in fashion ===
{{See also|Foot binding}}
[[File:High Heel Shoe.jpg|100 px|thumb|alt=A foot in a black high-heeled shoe|High-heeled shoe]]
95% of feminist agree that most fashion trends have been oppressive to women; they restrict women's movements, increase their vulnerability and endanger their health.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jeffreys|first1=Sheila|title=Beauty and Misogyny:Harmful cultural practices in the west|url=http://www.feministes-radicales.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/Jeffreys_Beauty_and_Misogyny_Harmful_Cultural_Practices_in_the_West__Women_and_Psychology_1.pdf|accessdate=March 8, 2013|year=2005|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis e-Library|location=East Sussex|isbn=0-203-69856-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fashion industry is dealing with a great deal of criticism, as their association of thin-models and beauty has said to encourage [[bulimia]] and [[anorexia nervosa]] within women, as well as locking female consumers into "false" feminine identities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hollows|first=Joanne|title=Feminism, Femininity and Popular Culture|url=http://books.google.com/?id=sXWjnG5LWO0C&amp;lpg=PA139&amp;dq=Oppressive%20fashions%20feminism&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=Oppressive%20fashions%20feminism&amp;f=false |accessdate=March 11, 2013|year=2000|publisher=Manchester University Press|location=Manchester, UK|isbn=0-7190-4394-8|page=139}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The assigning of gender specific baby clothes from young ages is often seen as sexism as it can instil in children from young ages a belief in strong gender stereotypes.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/commentators/julie-bindel-boys-arent-born-wanting-to-wear-blue-6293688.html&lt;/ref&gt; An example of this is the assignment in some countries of the color [[pink]] to girls and [[blue]] to boys. This fashion, however, is a recent one; at the beginning of the 20th century the trend was the opposite: blue for girls and pink for boys. In the early 1900s, The Women's Journal wrote: "That pink being a more decided and stronger colour, is more suitable for the boy, while blue, which is more delicate and dainty, is prettier for the girl." ''DressMaker'' magazine also explained: "The preferred colour to dress young boys in is pink. Blue is reserved for girls as it is considered paler, and the more dainty of the two colours, and pink is thought to be stronger (akin to red)."&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/7817496.stm&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:LouisXVchild.jpg|thumb|150 px|right|[[Louis XV]] in 1712, as a boy, wearing a pink dress]]
[[File:Rwandan school children.jpg|thumb|150 px|left|Children in [[Rwanda]]. Notice how all children, regardless of sex, have very short hair (these children are wearing their school uniforms: girls are in skirts and boys in shorts)]].

Today, in most countries of the world, it is considered inappropriate for boys to wear dresses and skirts, but this, again, is a modern worldview: for example, from the mid-16th century&lt;ref&gt;Melanie Scheussler suggests a date of post-1540 for England, France, and the Low Countries; see Scheussler, "'She Hath Over Grown All that She Ever Hath': Children's Clothing in the Lisle Letters, 1533-40", in Netherton, Robin, and Gale R. Owen-Crocker, editors, ''Medieval Clothing and Textiles'', Volume 3, p. 185.  Before roughly this date various styles of long robes were in any case commonly worn by adult males of various sorts, so boys wearing them could probably not be said to form a distinct phenomenon.&lt;/ref&gt; until the late 19th or early 20th century, young boys in the [[Western world]] were [[Breeches|unbreeched]] and wore [[gown]]s or [[dress]]es until an age that varied between two and eight.&lt;ref&gt;Baumgarten, Linda: ''What Clothes Reveal: The Language of Clothing in Colonial and Federal America'', p. 166&lt;/ref&gt; Also, throughout much of the history, in most cultures, men have worn skirt like clothes and worn long hair. In many parts of the world, such as much of sub-Saharan Africa, it is considered "normal" for women to wear very short hair, with the hairstyles of boys being the same to those of girls.

== Antisexism movements ==
{{See also|Women's rights|Men's rights}}
In [[Ecuador]], the Pink Helmets (''Cascos Rosas''), created in May 2011 by 18-year-olds Freddy Caleron and Damian Valencia, sought to unite young men against [[machismo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saynotoviolence.org/join-say-no/ecuador-pink-helmets-say-no-violence-against-women Saynotoviolence.com].&lt;/ref&gt; The Pink Helmets published a manual with suggestions to end violence in society, relationships, within families, and among friends. The Pink Helmets' founders and participating members, who call themselves ''neomasculinos'' and are 15–20 years old, visit schools and the streets to give talks and participate in festivals (such as the [[Quito Fest]]) in collaboration with [[UN Women]] (part of the United Nations) to increase awareness of violence and the movement against it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unwomen.org/2011/11/espanol-los-jovenes-lideran-la-lucha-por-la-igualdad-y-contra-la-violencia-de-genero-en-ecuador/ UN Women].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chauvinism]] and violence are common in Ecuador, with 40% of children under age 15 saying that they have witnessed acts of violence at home.{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}} According to the ''National Plan for the Eradication of Gender Violence of the Government of Ecuador'', 80% of women have been victims of violence at least once and 21% of children and adolescents have been sexually abused&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elmundo.es/america/2011/10/02/noticias/1317569157.html "Unos jóvenes combaten el machismo en Ecuador con cascos rosas"], ''El Mundo''.&lt;/ref&gt; (no official data provide a concrete number of women who have been killed or injured by men). The movement aims to promote gender equality, eliminate gender violence against women and encourage a "dialogue of respect between men and women from adolescence without hesitation to criticize sexist concepts that live in their culture".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.larepublica.pe/02-10-2011/ecuador-jovenes-combaten-el-machismo-con-cascos-rosas LaRepublica].&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Div col|cols=2|small=no}}
* [[Airline sex discrimination policy controversy]]
* [[Antifeminism]]
* [[Cybersexism]]
* [[Face-ism]]
* [[Femicide]]
* [[Androcide]]
* [[Gender apartheid]]
* [[Gender-blind]]
* [[Separatist feminism]] (20% of feminism)
* [[Equity and gender feminism|Gender Feminism]] (75% of feminism)
* [[Gender discrimination in Pakistan]]
* [[Gender egalitarianism]]
* [[Gender neutrality]]
* [[Glass cliff]]
* [[Gender inequality]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Hypermasculinity]]
* [[Intersectionality]]
* [[LGBT stereotypes]]
* [[Male privilege]]
* [[Masculinity]]
* [[Masculism]]
* [[Men and feminism]] (can also be [[Misandry]])
* [[Missing women of Asia]]
* [[National Organization for Women]]
* [[Patriarchy]]
* [[Rape culture]]
* [[Sex Roles (journal)]]
* [[Sex segregation]]
* [[Sexism in India]]
* [[Triple oppression]]
* [[Victim blaming]]
* [[Wife selling]]
{{Div col end}}

==Sources==
* {{cite journal |last=Bojarska |first=Katarzyna |year=2012 |title=''"Responding to lexical stimuli with gender associations: A Cognitive–Cultural Model"'' |journal=Journal of Language and Social Psychology |doi=10.1177/0261927X12463008 |volume=32 |page=46}}.
* Matsumoto, David. ''"The Handbook of Culture and Psychology"'' [[Oxford University Press]], 2001. ISBN 0195131819.

== Further reading ==
* Haberfeld, Yitchak. "Employment Discrimination: An Organizational Model." Academy Of
 	Management Journal 35.1 (1992): 161-180. Business Source Complete. 
* Kail, R., &amp; Cavanaugh, J. (2010). Human Growth and Development (5 ed.). Belmont, Ca: Wadworth Learning.

== Notes ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Sexism}}
* [http://finduslaw.com/taxonomy_menu/12/23/13 Gender Discrimination Law in the United States]
* [http://genderstereotype.nomaki.jp/ Gender Stereotypes - Changes in People's Thoughts]

{{Discrimination}}
{{Sexual identities}}

[[Category:Sexism| ]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Dispositional beliefs]]
[[Category:Hatred]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Words to avoid]]
[[Category:Chauvinism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>