<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081110220953|250967691" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="27165" pageid="27165" ns="0" title="Sexism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-13T04:28:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Citations missing|date=November 2007}}
[[Image:National Association Against Woman Suffrage.jpg|thumb|The sign of the headquarters of the National Association Opposed To Woman Suffrage.]]

'''Sexism''' is the belief or attitude that one [[gender]] or [[sex]] is inferior to or less valuable than the other and can also refer to [[hatred]] or distrust towards either [[gender|sex]] as a whole (see also [[misogyny]] and [[misandry]]), or creating [[stereotype]]s of [[masculinity]] for [[men]] or [[femininity]] for [[women]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |last=Brittan
 |first=Arthur
 |title=Sexism, racism and oppression
 |publisher=Blackwell
 |date=1984
 |pages=236
 |isbn=9780855206748}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also called male and female [[chauvinism]].

== Generalization and partition ==
In philosophy, sexist attitudes can be understood or judged on the basis of the [[essentialism|essential characteristics]] of the group to which an individual belongs&amp;mdash;in this case, their sexual group, as men or women. This assumes that all individuals fit into the category of ''male'' or ''female'' and does not take into account [[intersex]]ed people who are born with a mixture of male and female sexual characteristics.&lt;!-- Note: the mixed sexual characteristics are not necessarily _primary_ sexual characteristics. Ambiguous genitalia (primary) are not a _sine qua non_ of intersexuality. See the page on Intersex for more details. --&gt; This also assumes a significant degree of [[wiktionary:Homogeneity|homogeneity]] in the characteristics of men and women respectively, and generally does not take into account the differences that exist within these groups. [[46,XY|XY males]] and [[46,XX|XX females]] who are genetically one sex but have developed the characteristics of the opposite sex during the foetal stage are usually considered with respect to their [[wiktionary:Phenotype|phenotypes]] under this system.&lt;ref&gt;"What is AIS?" AISSG. 13 Sep 2006. http://www.medhelp.org/www/ais/21_overview.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Certain forms of sexual [[discrimination]] are illegal in many countries, but nearly all countries have laws that give special rights, privileges, or responsibilities to one sex or two sexes.&lt;ref&gt;Neuwirth, Jessica. "Unequal-A Global Perspective on Women Under the Law." Ms. Magazine. 2004. http://www.msmagazine.com/summer2004/globalwomenlaw.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class="wikitable"
|-
! sex
! condition of
! hatred
! fears
! discriminatory
! anti-discriminatory
|-
! colspan=2 |
! colspan=2 | discrimination of
! colspan=2 | movement of
|-
| [[female]] ♀
| [[femininity]]
| [[misogyny]]
| [[gynophobia]]
| [[gynocentrism]]
| [[feminism]]
|-
| [[male]] ♂
| [[masculinity]]
| [[misandry]]
| [[androphobia]]
| [[androcentrism]]
| [[masculism]]
|-
| [[intersex]]
| intersexuality
| misandrogyny
| androgynophobia
|
| [[LGBTIQ]]
|-
| [[transsex]]
| transsexuality
|
| [[transphobia]]
|
| [[LGBT]]
|}

=== Sexism against women ===
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
The view that men are superior to women is a form of sexism.  The term 'sexism' is sometimes used by itself to mean sexism against women.  When expressed by men, sexism against women may be called [[male chauvinism]]. Related terms are ''[[misogyny]]'', which implies a ''hatred'' of women, and ''[[wikt:gynophobia|gynophobia]]'', which refers to a ''fear'' of women or [[femininity]].  

The idea that men benefit from certain rights and privileges not available to women is referred to as [[male privilege]].

Historically, in many [[patriarchal]] societies, women have been and are viewed as the "weaker sex". Women's lower status can be seen in cases in which women were not even recognized as [[person]]s under the law of the land. The [[feminism|feminist]] [[feminist movement|movement]] promotes [[women's rights]] to end sexism against women by addressing issues such as equality under the law, political representation of women, access to education and employment, women victims of domestic violence, self-ownership of a woman's body, and the possible impact of [[pornography]] on women.&lt;ref name=Bell&gt;Bell, Linda A., 'Introduction' in ''Overcoming Racism and Sexism'' (eds) Murr Linda A. Bell and David Blumenfeld (Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 1995), ISBN 9780847680312&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Holland&gt;Holland, J: "Misogyny: The World's Oldest Prejudice," pp. 12-13. Avalon Publishing Group, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sexism against men ===
The view that women are superior to men is another form of sexism, and when expressed by a woman may be called [[female chauvinism]].  The hatred of men is called ''[[misandry]]'', while ''[[androphobia]]'' refers to the fear of men or [[masculinity]].

[[Wendy McElroy]] refers to male stereotyping when she claims that in some "[[Gender feminism|gender feminist]]" views, all men are considered irreconcilable rapists, wife-beating brutes, and useless as partners or fathers to women.&lt;ref&gt;Wendy McElroy, ''Sexual Correctness: The Gender-Feminist Attack on Women'', p.{{specify|date=February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; McElroy and Camille Paglia claim that certain feminists they refer to as "gender feminists" view women as innocent victims who never make irresponsible or morally questionable choices.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.menweb.org/paglsomm.htm Guests: Camille Paglia &amp; Christina Hoff Sommers ''Has Feminism Gone Too Far?'' Think Tank With Ben Wattenberg - aired: 4 Nov 1994] accessed 6 Jan 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Other feminists such as Kate Fillion have questioned the idea that women are always innocent victims and men always the guilty victimizers when the interests of each collide with those of the other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.beatrice.com/interviews/fillion/|title=Kate Fillion, ''Lip Service: The Truth About Women's Darker Side in Love, Sex and Friendship''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997, the Canadian Advertising Foundation ruled that a National Ad campaign that featuring [[Nicole Brown Simpson]]'s sister Denise with the slogan, "Stop violence against Women" was in fact portraying only men as aggressors, and that it was not providing a balanced message and was in fact contributing to gender stereotyping. (The murder of Nicole Simpson also included the murder of [[Ronald Goldman]])&lt;ref&gt;''The Power of One'', [[Pamela Bron]], Chronicle-Journal, Thunder Bay, Ontario, Canada, April 18, 1997, p. B1&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sexism against transsexuals ===
{{main|Transphobia}}
Transphobia refers to prejudice against transsexuality and transsexual or transgender people, based on their personal gender identification (see [[Phobia#Terms indicating prejudice or class discrimination|Phobia - terms indicating prejudice or class discrimination]]). Whether intentional or not, transphobia can have severe consequences for the person the object of the negative attitude. The [[LGBT]] movement has campaigned against sexism against transsexuals. The most typical forms of sexism against transsexuals are how many "women-only" and "men-only" events and organizations have been criticized for rejecting transfemales, and transmales respectively.{{Fact|date=April 2008}}

== Sexism and sexual expression ==
The expression of sexual intimacy is a part of the [[human condition]]. However, various aspects of human sexuality have been argued as having contributed to sexism.

=== The Sexual Revolution ===
During the [[sexual revolution]], there was a change in the cultural perception of sexual morality and sexual behavior. The sexual revolution has been known as the [[sexually liberal feminism|sexual liberation]] by [[feminist]]s since some saw this new development in the West as a leveling ground for females to have as many choices concerning their sexuality as males--hoping to eliminate the problematic virgin/whore dichotomy of traditional Western society.

Modern feminists like [[Ariel Levy]] have claimed that the current state of commercial sexuality has created a "[[Raunch Culture]]"{{Fact|date=June 2007}}. This cultural development, (which has largely occurred in the West) the commercialization of the sexual objectification of women, has been criticized as being limiting for men and women. Rather than being liberating, some feminists argue that the "pornification" of Western society has reduced and equated the scope of feminine power to sexual power only. Some feminists argue that women are themselves objectifying other women by becoming producers and promoters of the "Raunch Culture".

Some [[masculist]] theorists posit that prior to the sexual revolution the idealized male was expected to be virile while the idealized female was expected to be modest. They note that after the sexual revolution, women were given more liberty to express virility while the reverse has not been true for men, who have yet to be given a choice to be non-virile. They argued that the dual identity of [[hypersexuality]] and [[asexuality]] is a luxury and special status that only exists for women. However, many feminists{{Who|date=July 2008}} believe that this dual identity rather allows men to condemn a women for her sexuality for being either modest or virile (see [[double standard]]).

=== Pornography ===
Some individuals express the view that [[pornography]] is contributing to sexism, arguing that in usual pornographic performances for male spectators the actresses are sexually objectified. They claim that the narrative is usually formed around men's pleasure as the only goal of sexual activity. The [[Germany|German]] feminist [[Alice Schwarzer]] is one representative of this point of view. She has brought this topic up repeatedly since the 1970s, in particular in the feminist magazine ''Emma''. The reverse, where female spectators are objectifying male actors, has also been identified as sexism.

On the other hand, some famous pornographic actresses such as [[Teresa Orlowski]] have publicly stated that they do not feel themselves to be victims of sexism against women. In fact, many female pornographic stars and [[sex-positive feminist]]s view pornography to be progressive, since they are paid money for performing consensual acts, and also since many directors and managers of the industry are women as well. Porn positive feminists often support their position by pointing out the situation of women in countries with strict pornography laws (e.g., Saudi Arabia) versus women in countries with liberal pornography laws (e.g., the Netherlands). Many opponents of pornography believe that pornography gives a distorted view of men and women's bodies, as well as the actual sexual act, often showing the performers with synthetic implants or exaggerated expressions of pleasure. Some opponents believe pornographic films tend to show women in particular as being extremely passive, or that the acts women perform are degrading and solely for the pleasure of their sexual partner, and that this is evidence of sexism.

== Sexism and linguistics ==
It has been argued that sexual dichotomies exist in language, though it is disputed whether certain language causes sexism or sexism causes certain language (see the [[Sapir-Whorf hypothesis]]).

&lt;!-- === Sexist and gender-neutral language ===
Nearing the end of the 20th century, there is a rise in the use of gender-neutral language in western worlds. This is often attributed to the rise of [[feminism]]. [[Gender-neutral language]] is the avoidance of [[gender-specific job title]]s, [[Non-parallel usage#Disputed issues|non-parallel usage]], and other usage that is felt by some to be sexist. Supporters feel that having gender-specific titles and gender-specific pronouns either implies a system bias to exclude individuals based on their crusted vagina, or else is as unnecessary in most cases as race-specific pronouns, religion-specific pronouns, or persons-height-specific pronouns. Some of those who support gender-specific pronouns assert that promoting gender-neutral language is a kind of "[[semantics]] injection" itself. Some opponents dismiss this trend as "political correctness gone mad"{{Fact|date=June 2007}} and protest against what they see as [[censorship]]. Others like [[misandry]] researchers Nathonson and Young see the term 'gender' as a biased "front" for what they call "ideological" feminism{{Fact|date=June 2007}}.

=== Anthropological linguistics and gender-specific language ===
Unlike the [[Indo-European languages]] in the west, for many other [[languages]] around the world, [[gender-specific pronouns]] are a recent phenomenon that occur around the early-20th century. As a result of [[colonialism]], cultural revolution occurred in many parts of the world with attempts to "modernize" and "westernize" by adding gender-specific pronouns and animate-inanimate pronouns to local languages. This ironically resulted in the situation of what was [[gender-neutral pronouns]] a century ago suddenly becoming gender-specific. (See for example [[Gender-neutrality in languages without grammatical gender#Turkish|Gender-neutrality in languages without grammatical gender: Turkish]].)
{{Confusing|date=September 2007}}
In those parts of the world, some feminists, who are unaware of the etymology of their own language, complain about what they perceived as "sexist language" with arguments like "traditional language fails to reflect the presence of women in modern society adequately"{{Fact|date=June 2007}} similar to the west. However, other feminists, who are aware of historical linguistics, realize that the traditional language in their part of the world is inherently gender-neutral. They instead decide to revive the original gender-neutral usage from over a century ago with [[Reclaiming|reclamation]] projects.
For example, when the sex of something is unknown, is it always referred to as a "he," or when using the term "one," typically "himself" is used also. As well as those examples, in the phrase "him and her," the "him" always comes first. Furthermore, in some combined words such as "postman", the word man, which is clearly not gender neutral, is used, whereas woman, or a gender neutral alternative (which does not even exist in many languages), is never used.

=== Reappropriation and reclamation ===
'''Reappropriation''' (aka '''reclamation projects''') describe a cultural process by which certain groups reclaim or re-appropriate terms, symbols, and artifacts that were previously used to discriminate. Within the [[English language]], terms like '[[bitch]]' and '[[slut]]', which had been historically used as [[pejorative]] sexist remarks against females. They have since been used to refer to a "strong, independent, unattached female" and a "[[Sexually liberal feminism|sexually liberal]], [[hypersexual]] female"{{Fact|date=June 2007}}. Similarly, terms like '[[girlie men]]' and '[[transgender|tranny']], which has been historically used as pejorative sexist remarks against [[transsex]]es, have since been used to refer to the varying degree of transexuality for "pre-operation" and "non-operation" as whether they had undergone or will undergo sex-reassignment or not. The success of these cultural process has been disputed.

On the flip side, the word 'dude' as a pejorative has crossed the sexes and is being applied to males. In politics, the term 'girlie men' has also been used by [[Governor Schwarzenegger]] to attack his political opponents, who are not transsexes. This has led to Schwarzenegger being accused of being sexist.
 --&gt;

==Occupational sexism==
{{main|Occupational sexism}}
Occupational sexism refers to any [[discriminatory]] practices, statements, actions, etc. based on a person's [[sex]] that are present or occur in a place of [[employment]]. One form of occupational sexism is wage discrimination, which is prohibited in the US.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Facts About Compensation Discrimination
|author=The U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission
|url=http://www.eeoc.gov/facts/fs-epa.html
|accessdate=2008-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Sexual discrimination==
{{seealso|Discrimination}}

Though sexism refers to beliefs and [[attitude]]s in relation to the [[gender]] of a person, such beliefs and attitudes are of a social nature and do not, normally, carry any legal consequences. [[Discrimination|Sex discrimination]], on the other hand, may have legal consequences. Though what constitutes sex discrimination varies between countries, the essence is that it is an adverse action taken by one person against another person that would not have occurred had the person been of another sex. Discrimination of that nature in certain enumerated circumstances is illegal in many countries.

Sexual discrimination can arise in different contexts. For instance an employee may be discriminated against by being asked discriminatory questions during a job interview, or because an [[employer]] did not hire, promote or wrongfully terminated an employee based on his or her gender, or employers pay unequally based on gender. In an educational setting there could be claims that a student was excluded from an educational institution, program, opportunity, loan, student group, or scholarship due to his or her gender. In the housing setting there could be claims that a person was refused negotiations on seeking a house, contracting/leasing a house or getting a loan based on his or her gender. 

Socially, sexual differences have been used to justify different roles for men and women, in some cases giving rise to claims of primary and secondary roles.{{Fact|date=May 2008}} While there are non-physical differences between men and women, there is little agreement as to what those differences are.{{Fact|date=May 2008}}

The [[United Nations]] has stated (2006) that women struggle to break through a "glass ceiling," and that "progress in bringing women into leadership and decision-making positions around the world remains far too slow."&lt;ref name="UN-IWD2006"&gt;{{cite web
|first=
|authorlink=
|coauthors=
|title=Women still struggle to break through glass ceiling in government, business, academia
|work=
|publisher=United Nations
|date=2006-03-08
|url=http://www.un.org/events/women/iwd/2006/PressReleaseIWD8March.pdf
|format=
|doi=
|accessdate=2008-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Special Adviser to the Secretary-General on Gender Issues, Rachel Mayanja, said, "The past ten years have seen the fastest growth in the number of women
in parliaments, yet even at this rate, parity between women and men in parliaments
will not be reached until 2040."&lt;ref name="UN-IWD2006" /&gt;

The term "glass ceiling" is used to describe a perceived barrier to advancement in employment and government based on discrimination, especially sex discrimination. In the [[United States]], the Glass Ceiling Commission, a government-funded group, stated: "Over half of all Master’s degrees are now awarded to women, yet 95% of senior-level managers, of the top Fortune 1000 industrial and 500 service companies are men. Of them, 97% are white." In its report, it recommended [[affirmative action]], which is the consideration of an employee's gender and race in hiring and promotion decisions, as a means to end this form of discrimination.&lt;ref name="Glass Ceiling Commission"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://digitalcommons.ilr.cornell.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1117&amp;context=key_workplace
|title=A Solid Investment: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital
|date=1995-11
|accessdate=2008-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[transsexualism|Transgendered]] individuals, both male to female and female to male, often experience problems which often lead to dismissals, underachievement, difficulty in finding a job, social isolation, and, occasionally, violent attacks against them.

==See also==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
*[[Occupational sexism]]
* [[Chauvinism]]
*[[Equal Pay Act]]
*[[Gender Egalitarianism]]
*[[Gender role]]
*[[Intersectionality]]
*[[LGBT stereotypes]]
*[[Masculinity]]
{{col-2}}
*[[Misandry]]
*[[Misogyny]]
*[[Sexual harassment]]
*[[Sexual objectification]]
*[[Sex in advertising]]
*[[Sexism in India]]
*[[Stereotype]]
*[[Triple oppression]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.nomas.org/ National Organisation of Men Against Sexism NOMAS, USA]
*[http://finduslaw.com/taxonomy_menu/12/23/13 Federal and California Sex Discrimination Laws]
*[http://finduslaw.com/equal_pay_act_of_1963_epa_29_u_s_code_chapter_8_206_d Equal Pay Act - Actual Text]
*[http://finduslaw.com/taxonomy_menu/12/23/13 Gender Discrimination Law in the United States]


{{Template group
|list =
{{Discrimination}}
{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
}}

[[Category:Sexism| ]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]

[[als:Sexismus]]
[[ar:عنصرية جنسية]]
[[be-x-old:Сэксізм]]
[[bg:Полова дискриминация]]
[[ca:Sexisme]]
[[cs:Sexismus]]
[[da:Kønsdiskrimination]]
[[de:Sexismus]]
[[et:Seksism]]
[[el:Σεξισμός]]
[[es:Sexismo]]
[[eo:Seksismo]]
[[fa:جنسیت‌گرایی]]
[[fr:Sexisme]]
[[ko:성 차별]]
[[hr:Seksizam]]
[[id:Seksisme]]
[[is:Kynjamismunun]]
[[it:Sessismo]]
[[he:אפליה מינית]]
[[lv:Seksisms]]
[[lt:Seksizmas]]
[[nl:Seksisme]]
[[ja:性差別]]
[[no:Kjønnsdiskriminering]]
[[pl:Seksizm]]
[[pt:Sexismo]]
[[ru:Сексизм]]
[[scn:Sissismu]]
[[simple:Sexism]]
[[sk:Sexizmus]]
[[sl:Seksizem]]
[[sr:Сексизам]]
[[sh:Seksizam]]
[[fi:Seksismi]]
[[sv:Sexism]]
[[th:เพศนิยม]]
[[tr:Cinsiyetçilik]]
[[uk:Сексизм]]
[[zh:性別歧視主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>