<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131112095607|581310686" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="432459" pageid="432459" ns="0" title="Bullying"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-15T02:50:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Selfref|For the Wikipedia guidance essay, see [[Wikipedia:WikiBullying]]}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}{{pp-move-indef}}
[[File:Bullying Irfe.jpg|220px|thumb|A 2001 survey reports that bullying is detrimental to students' well-being and development.&lt;ref name="NCES2005-310"/&gt; In the picture, a student suffering bullying at [[Instituto Regional Federico Errázuriz]], [[Santa Cruz, Chile|Santa Cruz]] (Chile)]]

'''Bullying''' is the use of force, threat, or [[coercion]] to [[abuse]], [[intimidate]], or aggressively to impose domination over others. The behavior is often repeated and habitual.  One essential prerequisite is the perception, by the bully or by others, of an imbalance of social or physical [[Power (social and political)|power]]. Behaviors used to assert such domination can include verbal [[harassment]] or [[threat]], physical [[assault]] or coercion, and such acts may be directed repeatedly towards particular targets.  Justifications and rationalizations for such behavior sometimes include differences of [[social class|class]], [[Race (classification of humans)|race]], [[religion]], [[gender]], [[Sexual orientation|sexuality]], [[human physical appearance|appearance]], [[Eccentricity (behavior)|behavior]], strength, size or [[disability|ability]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Children who are bullying or being bullied | work = Cambridgeshire County Council: Children and families | publisher =Cambridgeshire County Council | date =2013-07-24 | url = http://www.cambridgeshire.gov.uk/childrenandfamilies/parenting/childsbehaviour/bullying.htm | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Ericson | first =Nels | title =Addressing the Problem of Juvenile Bullying | journal =OJJDP Fact Sheet #FS-200127| volume =27 | publisher =U.S. Department of Justice: Office of Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention | date =2001-06 | url =https://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/ojjdp/fs200127.pdf | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; If bullying is done by a group, it is called [[mobbing]].&lt;ref name="DavenportSchwartz1999"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Noa Davenport|author2=Ruth Distler Schwartz|author3=Gail Pursell Elliott|title=Mobbing: Emotional Abuse in the American Workplace|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=JlJoyD84BfAC|accessdate=2013-10-28|date=1999-07-01|publisher=Civil Society Publishing|isbn=978-0-9671803-0-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; "Targets" of bullying are also sometimes referred to as "victims" of bullying.

Bullying can be defined in many different ways. The [[United Kingdom|UK]] currently has no legal definition of bullying,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =The University of Manchester Dignity at Work and Study Policy | publisher =The University of Manchester | date =2012-01 | url = http://documents.manchester.ac.uk/display.aspx?DocID=2753 | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; while some [[United States|U.S.]] states have laws against it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =State Laws Related to Bullying Among Children and Youth | work = U.S. Department of Health and Human Services - Health Resources and Services Administration - Maternal and Child Health Bureau | publisher =U.S. Department of Health and Human Services | url = http://web.archive.org/web/20040529052056/http://stopbullyingnow.hrsa.gov/HHS_PSA/pdfs/SBN_Tip_6.pdf | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bullying consists of four basic types of abuse &amp;ndash; [[Psychological abuse|emotional]] (sometimes called relational), [[Verbal abuse|verbal]], [[Physical abuse|physical]], and cyber.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Brank | first =Eve M. | last2 =Hoetger | first2 =Lori A. | last3 =Hazen | first3 =Katherine P. | title =Bullying | journal =Annual Review of Law and Social Science | volume =8 | pages =213–230 | publisher =Annual Reviews | date =2012-12 | url =http://www.annualreviews.org/doi/abs/10.1146/annurev-lawsocsci-102811-173820 | doi =10.1146/annurev-lawsocsci-102811-173820 | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; It typically involves subtle methods of coercion such as intimidation.

Bullying ranges from simple one-on-one bullying to more complex bullying in which the bully may have one or more "lieutenants" who may seem to be willing to assist the primary bully in his or her bullying activities. Bullying in school and the workplace is also referred to as peer abuse.&lt;ref name="Bennett2006"&gt;{{cite book|author=Elizabeth Bennett|title=Peer Abuse Know More!: Bullying from a Psychological Perspective|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GF06aB7mLdIC|accessdate=2013-10-29|date=1 January 2006|publisher=Infinity|isbn=978-0-7414-3265-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert W. Fuller]] has analyzed bullying in the context of [[rankism]].

A [[bullying culture]] can develop in any context in which human beings interact with each other. This includes [[School bullying|school]], family, the [[Workplace bullying|workplace]], home, and neighborhoods. In a 2012 study of male adolescent football players, "the strongest predictor was the perception of whether the most influential male in a player's life would approve of the bullying behavior".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Steinfeldt | first =Jesse A. | last2 =Vaughan | first2 =Ellen L.  | last3 =LaFollette | first3 =Julie R. | last4 =Steinfeldt | first4 =Matthew C. | title =Bullying among adolescent football players: Role of masculinity and moral atmosphere | journal =Psychology of Men and Masculinity | volume =13 | issue =4 | pages =340–353 | publisher =American Psychological Association | date =2012-10 | url =http://psycnet.apa.org/index.cfm?fa=buy.optionToBuy&amp;id=2012-01737-001 | accessdate = 2013-10-28 | doi =10.1037/a0026645}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:IRFE bull.png|thumb|right|240px|[[Happy slapping]] in the [[Instituto Regional Federico Errázuriz]], Santa Cruz, Chile]]

==Definitions and etymology==

===Definitions===
Bullying may be defined as the activity of repeated, aggressive behavior intended to hurt another person, physically or mentally. Bullying is characterized by an individual behaving in a certain way to gain [[power (philosophy)|power]] over another person.&lt;ref name="Besag1989"&gt;{{cite book|author=Valerie E. Besag|title=Bullies and victims in schools: a guide to understanding and management|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=t2pHAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=2013-10-29|year=1989|publisher=Open University Press|isbn=978-0-335-09542-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Norwegian researcher Dan Olweus&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =History | work =OLWEUS Bullying Prevention Program | publisher =OLWEUS Bullying Prevention Program | url = http://www.clemson.edu/olweus/history.html | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; says bullying occurs when a person is: &lt;blockquote&gt;'exposed, repeatedly and over time, to negative actions on the part of one or more other persons'. He says negative actions occur 'when a person intentionally inflicts injury or discomfort upon another person, through physical contact, through words or in other ways.'{{citation needed|date=October 2012}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Etymology===
The word "bully" was first used in the 1530s meaning "sweetheart", applied to either sex, from the Dutch ''boel'' "lover, brother", probably diminutive of Middle High German ''buole'' "brother", of uncertain origin (compare with the German ''buhle'' "lover"). The meaning deteriorated through the 17th century through "fine fellow", "blusterer", to "harasser of the weak". This may have been as a connecting sense between "lover" and "ruffian" as in "protector of a prostitute", which was one sense of "bully" (though not specifically attested until 1706). The verb "to bully" is first attested in 1710.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =bully | work =Online Etymology Dictionary | publisher =Douglas Harper | url = http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=bully | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
High-level forms of violence such as assault and murder usually receive most media attention, but lower-level forms of violence such as bullying have only by the 2000s started to be addressed by researchers, parents and guardians, and authority figures.&lt;ref name="NASW"&gt;{{cite journal | last =Witted | first =Kathryn S. | last2 =Dupper | first2 = David R. | title =Best Practices for Preventing or Reducing Bullying in Schools | journal =Children &amp; Schools | volume =27 | issue =3 | pages =167–175 | publisher =National Association of Social Workers | date =2005 | url =http://www.centerforviolenceprevention.org/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=EJcJSOFRmrY%3D&amp;tabid=176&amp;mid=616 | doi =10.1093/cs/27.3.167 | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is only in recent years that bullying has been recognised and recorded as a separate and distinct offence, but there have been well documented cases that have been recorded over the centuries.{{which|date=November 2013}} [[Virginia Woolf]] considered fascism to be a form of bullying, and wrote of Hitler and the Nazis in 1934 as "these brutal bullies".&lt;ref name="Zwerdling1986"&gt;{{cite book|author=Alex Zwerdling|title=Virginia Woolf and the Real World|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=9YkTuYctVEwC&amp;pg=PA263|accessdate=2013-10-28|year=1986|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-06184-2|page=263}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Pawlowski2001"&gt;{{cite book|author=Merry M. Pawlowski|title=Virginia Woolf and Fascism: Resisting the Dictators' Seduction|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=LkaqoFngBokC&amp;pg=PA104|accessdate=2013-10-29|date=18 August 2001|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=978-0-333-80115-4|pages=104–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-bullying movement===
In the 2000s and 2010s, a cultural movement against bullying gained popularity in the English-speaking world.  The first [http://www.bullyingawarenessweek.org National Bullying Prevention Week] was conceived of in Canada in 2000 by Canadian educator and anti-bullying activist Bill Belsey. The charity [[Act Against Bullying]] was formed in the UK in 2003. In 2006, [[National Bullying Prevention Month]] was declared in the United States. The [[Suicide of Phoebe Prince]] in 2010 brought attention to the issue in Massachusetts, and sparked reforms in state education.  The [[It Gets Better Project]] was started in 2010 to combat gay teen suicides, and [[Lady Gaga]] announced the Born This Way Foundation in partnership with Harvard's [[Berkman Center for Internet &amp; Society]] in 2011.

A 2012 paper from the Berkman Center, "An Overview of State Anti-Bullying Legislation and Other Related Laws," notes that, as of January 2012, 48 U.S. states had anti-bullying laws, though there is wide variation in their strength and focus. Sixteen states acknowledge that bullies often select their targets based on "creed or religion, disability, gender or sex, nationality or national origin, race, and sexual orientation." Each of the 16 employs a wide array of additional parameters, the paper notes, ranging from age and weight to socioeconomic status. Of the 38 states that have laws encompassing electronic or "cyberbullying" activity, 32 put such offenses under the broader category of bullying and six states define this type of offense separately, the authors report.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Weigel | first =Margaret | title =Overview of state anti-bullying legislation and other related news | work =Harvard Kennedy School Joan Shorenstein Center: Journalist's Resource | publisher =Harvard Kennedy School | date =2012-03-07 | url = http://journalistsresource.org/studies/society/education/federal-state-anti-bullying-legislation-laws/# | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characteristics==

===Of bullying in general===
Bullying consists of three basic types of [[abuse]] &amp;ndash; [[Psychological abuse|emotional]], [[Verbal abuse|verbal]], and [[Physical abuse|physical]]. It typically involves subtle methods of [[coercion]] such as [[intimidation]]. Bullying behavior may include name calling, [[Verbal abuse|verbal]] or written abuse, exclusion from activities, exclusion from social situations, [[physical abuse]], or [[coercion]].&lt;ref name="NASW"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Carey | first =Timothy A. | title =Improving the Success of ANti-Bullying Intevention Programs: A tool for Matching Programs with Purposes | journal =International Journal of Reality Therapy | volume =22 | issue =2 | pages =16 | publisher =William Glasser Institute US | date =2003-05 | url =http://connection.ebscohost.com/c/articles/10024628/improving-success-anti-bullying-intervention-programs-tool-matching-programs-purposes | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the U.S. National Center for Education Statistics (2007),  approximately 32% of U.S. school children reported being bullied at school; nearly 4% reported being cyber-bullied. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Student Reports of Bullying and Cyber-Bullying: Results From the 2007 School Crime Supplement to the National Crime Victimization Survey - NCES 2011 316 | work =Institute of Education Sciences: National Center for Education Statistics: Web Tables | publisher =U.S. Department of Education | date =2011-05 | url = http://nces.ed.gov/pubs2011/2011316.pdf | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The Center suggests (2001) that bullying can be classified into two categories: 
# direct bullying, and
# indirect bullying (which is also known as social aggression).&lt;ref name="NCES2005-310"&gt;{{cite journal | last =DeVoe | first =Jill F. | last2 =Kaffenberger | first2 =Sarah | last3 =Chandler | first3 =Kathryn | title =Results From the 2001 School Crime Supplement to the National Crime Victimization Survey: Statistical Analysis Report - NCES 2005-310 | publisher =U.S. Department of Education Institute of Education Sciences | date =2005-07 | url =http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:http://nces.ed.gov/pubs2005/2005310.pdf | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ross states that direct bullying involves a great deal of physical [[aggression]], such as shoving and poking, throwing things, slapping, choking, punching and kicking, beating, stabbing, pulling hair, scratching, [[Bite|biting]], scraping, and pinching.&lt;ref name="RossFederation1998"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Peter N. Ross|author2=Ontario Public School Teachers' Federation|title=Arresting Violence : a Resource Guide for Schools and Their Communities|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=o3tiXwAACAAJ|accessdate=2013-10-29|year=1998|publisher=Ontario Public School Teachers' Federation|isbn=978-0-9680759-5-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He also suggests that social aggression or indirect bullying is characterized by attempting to [[social isolation|socially isolate]] the target. This isolation is achieved through a wide variety of techniques, including spreading [[gossip]], refusing to socialize with the target, bullying other people who wish to socialize with the target, and [[Criticism|criticizing]] the target's manner of dress and other socially-significant markers (including the target's race, religion, disability, sex, or sexual preference, etc.). Ross&lt;ref name="RossFederation1998"/&gt; outlines an array of nonviolent behavior which can be considered "indirect bullying", at least in some instances, such as name calling, the [[silent treatment]], [[Chewbacca defense|arguing others into submission]], [[Psychological manipulation|manipulation]], gossip/false gossip, [[lie]]s, [[rumor]]s/[[slander|false rumors]], [[staring]], giggling, laughing at the target, saying certain words that trigger a reaction from a past event, and mocking. The UK based children's charity, [[Act Against Bullying]], was set up in 2003 to help children who were targets of this type of bullying by researching and publishing [[coping skills]].

It has been noted that there tend to be differences in how bullying manifests itself between the sexes. Males tend to be more likely to be physically aggressive whereas females tend to favour [[exclusion]] and mockery, though it has been noticed that females are becoming more physical in their bullying.&lt;ref name="Besag1989"/&gt; There can be a tendency in both sexes to opt for exclusion and mockery rather than physical aggression when the target is perceived to be too strong to attack without risk, or the use of violence would otherwise cause problems for the bullies such as criminal liability, or the bullies see physical aggression as immature (particularly when bullying occurs among adults). {{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

Gay and lesbian youth are more likely to report bullying &lt;ref name="Berlan et al., 2010"&gt;{{cite journal | last =Berlan | first =Elise D. | last2 =Corliss | first2 =Heather L. | last3 =Field | first3 =Alison E. | last4 =Goodman | first4 =Elizabeth | last5 =Austin | first5 =S. Bryn | title =Sexual Orientation and Bullying Among Adolescents in the Growing Up Today Study | journal =Journal of Adolescent Health | volume =46 | issue =4 | pages =366–371 | publisher =Elsevier | date =2010-01-28 | url =http://www.journals.elsevierhealth.com/periodicals/jah/article/S1054-139X(09)00647-8/fulltext | doi =10.1016/j.jadohealth.2009.10.015 | accessdate = 2013-10-28 | pmid =20307826 | pmc =2844864}}&lt;/ref&gt; and may suffer more bullying and more negative effects &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Swearer | first =Susan M. | last2 =Turner | first2 =Rhonda K. | last3 =Givens | first3 =Jami E. | title ="You're So Gay!": Do Different Forms of Bullying Matter for Adolescent Males? | journal =School Psychology Review | volume =37 | issue =2 | pages =160–173 | publisher =National Association of School Psychologists | date =2008 | url =http://www.nasponline.org/publications/spr/abstract.aspx?ID=1893
 | issn =0279-6015 | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}

&lt;/ref&gt;

Clayton R. Cook and co-authors  examined 153 studies from the last 30 years. They found that boys bully more than girls, and bullies and targets both have poor social problem-solving skills. More than anything else, poor academic performance predicts those who will bully.&lt;ref name="APS2010"&gt;{{cite journal | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | title =Predictors of Bullying and Victimization in Childhood and Adolescence: A Meta-analytic Investigation | journal =School Psychology Quarterly | volume =25 | issue =2 | pages =65–83 | publisher = American Psychological Association | date =2010 | url =http://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/releases/spq-25-2-65.pdf | doi =10.1037/a0020149 | accessdate = 2013-10-28 | last1 = Cook | first1 = Clayton R. | last2 = Williams | first2 = Kirk R. | last3 = Guerra | first3 = Nancy G. | last4 = Kim | first4 = Tia E. | last5 = Sadek | first5 = Shelly}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Of bullies and bully accomplices===
Studies have shown that [[envy]] and [[resentment]] may be motives for bullying.&lt;ref name="Einarsen2003"&gt;{{cite book|author=Ståle Einarsen|title=Bullying and Emotional Abuse in the Workplace: International Perspectives in Research and Practice|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=dQhz3uFOuaYC|accessdate=2013-10-29|year=2003|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-0-415-25359-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research on the [[self-esteem]] of bullies has produced equivocal results.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Cardemil | first =Alisha R. | last2 =Cardemil | first2 =Esteban V. | last3 =O'Donnell | first3 =Ellen H. | title =Self-Esteem in Pure Bullies and Bully/Victims: A Longitudinal Analysis | journal =Journal of Interpersonal Violence | volume =25 | issue =8 | pages =1489–1502 | publisher =Sage Publications | date =2010-08 | language = | url =http://jiv.sagepub.com/content/25/8/1489 | doi =10.1177/0886260509354579 | accessdate = 2013-10-29 | pmid =20040706}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bkn&gt;{{Cite journal|first1=George M. |last1=Batsche |first2=Howard M. |last2=Knoff |year=1994 |title=Bullies and their victims: Understanding a pervasive problem in the schools |journal=School Psychology Review |volume=23 |issue=2 |pages=165–175 |url=http://faculty.buffalostate.edu/hennesda/BULLIES_AND_THEIR_VICTIMS.doc}}&lt;/ref&gt; While some bullies are [[:wikt:arrogant|arrogant]] and [[narcissistic]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Those who can, do.  Those who can't, bully. | work = Bully OnLine | publisher =Tim Field | url = http://www.bullyonline.org/workbully/faq.htm | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; bullies can also use bullying as a tool to conceal [[shame]] or [[anxiety]] or to boost self-esteem: by demeaning others, the abuser feels empowered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author = Syiasha | title =Presentation Bullying | work =Scribd | publisher =Scribd Inc. | url = http://www.scribd.com/doc/7882659/Presentation-Bullying | accessdate = 2013-10-28/}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bullies may bully out of [[jealousy]] or because they themselves are bullied.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Levinson | first =Edward M. | title =Assessment of Bullying: A Review of Methods and Instruments | journal =Journal of Counselling &amp; Development | volume =82 | issue =4 | pages =496–503 | publisher =American Counselling Association | date =2004 | url =http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/j.1556-6678.2004.tb00338.x/abstract | doi =10.1002/j.1556-6678.2004.tb00338.x | accessdate = 2013-10-29 | first2 =Edward M.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some have argued that a bully reflects the environment of his home, repeating the model he learned from his parents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Matonismo es la principal forma de violencia en el 'cole'|url=http://www.nacion.com/2010-05-16/ElPais/FotoVideoDestacado/ElPais2369897.aspx|work=[[La Nación (San José){{!}}La Nación]]|date=16 May 2010|quote=Orlando Urroz, subdirector del Hospital Nacional de Niños, explicó que el matonismo en los infantes es un reflejo del ambiente que viven en sus hogares. 'El bullying no surge por generación espontánea, es un proceso de aprendizaje, de repetir los modelos de los padres', detalló.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead link|date=October 2013}}

Researchers have identified other risk factors such as [[Depression (mood)|depression]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Patterson G |title=The bully as victim? |journal=Paediatric Nursing |volume=17 |issue=10 |pages=27–30 |year=2005 |month=December |pmid=16372706|doi=10.7748/paed2005.12.17.10.27.c981}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[personality disorders]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Kumpulainen | first =K. | title =Psychiatric conditions associated with bullying | journal =International Journal of Adolescent Medicine and Health | volume =20 | issue =2 | pages =121–132 | publisher =National Center for Biotechnology Information, U.S. National Library of Medicine | date =2008 | url =http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18714551 | pmid= 18714551 | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as quickness to [[anger]] and use of force, [[Behavioral addiction|addiction]] to [[Aggression|aggressive behaviors]], mistaking others' actions as hostile, concern with preserving [[self image]], and engaging in obsessive or rigid actions.&lt;ref name=vari2&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1177/0143034397181001 |title=Areas of Expert Agreement on Identification of School Bullies and Victims |year=1997 |last1=Hazlerr |first1=R. J. |last2=Carney |first2=J. V. |last3=Green |first3=S. |last4=Powell |first4=R. |last5=Jolly |first5=L. S. |journal=School Psychology International |volume=18 |page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; A combination of these factors may also be causes of this behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1016/S0191-8869(97)00145-1 |title=The relationship among bullying, victimization, depression, anxiety, and aggression in elementary school children |year=1998 |last1=Craig |first1=W.M.|journal=Personality and Individual Differences |volume=24 |issue=1 |pages=123–130}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In one recent study of youth, a combination of antisocial traits and depression was found to be the best predictor of youth violence, whereas video game violence and television violence exposure were not predictive of these behaviors.&lt;ref name="Ferguson, 2011"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ferguson|first=Christopher J.|year=2011|title=Video Games and Youth Violence: A Prospective Analysis in Adolescents|journal=Journal of Youth and Adolescence|volume=40|issue=4|url=http://www.tamiu.edu/~cferguson/Video%20Games%201%20Year.pdf|doi=10.1007/s10964-010-9610-x|pages=377–91|pmid=21161351}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to some researchers, bullies may be inclined toward negativity and perform poorly academically. Dr. Cook says that "a typical bully has trouble resolving problems with others and also has trouble academically. He or she usually has negative attitudes and beliefs about others, feels negatively toward himself/herself, comes from a family environment characterized by conflict and poor parenting, perceives school as negative and is negatively influenced by peers".&lt;ref name="APS2010"/&gt;

Contrarily, some researchers have suggested that some bullies are "psychologically strongest" and have "high social standing" among their peers, while their targets are "emotionally distressed" and "socially marginalized".&lt;ref&gt;Juvonen (2003) [http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/112/6/1231.abstract ''Bullying Among Young Adolescents: The Strong, the Weak and the Troubled''] in ''Pediatrics'', December 2003, {{cite web
|year = 2004
|url = http://www.kimberlyswygert.com/archives/001765.html
|title = The benefits of bullying
|accessdate = 2011-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other researchers also argued that a minority of the bullies, those who are not in turn bullied, "enjoy going to school, and are least likely to take days off sick".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | coauthors = | title ='Bullies are the healthiest pupils' | newspaper =BBC News | section = Education | publisher =BBC | date =1999-12-14 | url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/564923.stm | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is often suggested that bullying behavior has its origin in childhood. As a child who is inclined to act as a bully ages, his or her related behavior patterns may also become more sophisticated. Schoolyard pranks and "rough-housing" may develop into more subtle activities such as administrative end-runs, planned and orchestrated attempts at [[character assassination]], or other less obvious, yet equally forceful forms of coercion. {{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

Research indicates that adults who bully have [[authoritarian]] personalities, combined with a strong need to control or [[dominance (ethology)|dominate]].&lt;ref name="Brodsky1976"&gt;{{cite book|author=Carroll M. Brodsky|title=The Harassed Worker|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=MZEeAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=2013-10-29|year=1976|publisher=Lexington Books|isbn=978-0-669-01041-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been suggested that a prejudicial view of subordinates can be a particularly strong risk factor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Ashforth | first =Blake | title =Petty Tyranny in Organizations | journal =Human Relations | volume =47 | issue =7 | pages =755–778 | publisher =The Tavistock Institute | date =1994 | url =http://hum.sagepub.com/content/47/7/755.abstract | doi =10.1177/001872679404700701 | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Of typical bystanders===
Often bullying takes place in the presence of a large group of relatively uninvolved bystanders. In many cases, it is the bully's ability to create the illusion that he or she has the support of the majority present that instills the fear of "speaking out" in protestation of the bullying activities being observed by the group. Unless the "bully mentality" is effectively challenged in any given group in its early stages, it often becomes an accepted, or supported, norm within the group.&lt;ref name = "bystander attitudes"&gt;{{cite web | last = | first =	 | title =Bullies, Victims, and Bystanders | work =athealth.com: Consumer: Issues | publisher =Athealth.com | url = http://www.athealth.com/Consumer/issues/BulliesVictimsBystanders3.html | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}
&lt;/ref&gt;{{cite news | title =New Tactics To Tackle Bystander's Role In Bullying | newspaper =Science Daily | section = Science News | publisher =Science Daily, LLC | date =2009-01-27 | url =http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2009/01/090125193150.htm | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}

In such groups where the "bully mentality" has been allowed to become a dominant factor in the group environment, injustice and abuse often become regular and predictable parts of the group experience. Bystanders to bullying activities are often unable or unwilling to recognize the true costs that silence regarding the bullying can have, both to the target or targets, and to the group. Bystanders often feel unwilling to empathize with the target, regardless of their feelings towards the bully. The reversal of a culture of bullying within a group is usually an effort which requires much time, energy, careful planning, coordination with others, and usually requires some undertaking of "risk" by group members. {{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

It is the general unwillingness of bystanders to expend these types of energies and to undertake this type of risk that bullies often rely upon in order to maintain their power. Unless action is taken, a "culture of bullying" is often perpetuated within a group for months, years, or longer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =419: Petty Tyrant | work =This American Life: Radio Archive | publisher =Chicago Public Media &amp; Ira Glass | date =2010-11-12 | url = http://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/419/petty-tyrant | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bystanders who have been able to establish their own "friendship group" or "support group" have been found to be far more likely to opt to speak out against bullying behavior than those who have not.&lt;ref name = "jim porter video"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://video.tbo.com/m/34698658/hands-on-hero.htm?pageid=110466
| title= Pasco County Students Making Friends and Stopping Bullying
| accessdate = 2010-11-27}} Psychologist Jim Porter reports on the correlation between making friends and speaking out against bullying. (See "Program Helps Students Combat Bullying" reference below.)
&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead link|date=October 2013}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title =Pasco students get 'hero' training to stop bullying | newspaper =TBO.com (The Tampa Tribune) | section = pasco-county | publisher =Tampa Media Group, LLC | date =2010-10-12 | url =http://tbo.com/pasco-county/pasco-students-get-hero-training-to-stop-bullying-24060 | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document | title =Program Helps Students Combat Bullying - Students participate with enthusiasm | work =Winning Harmony Counselling | location =Clearwater, Florida, U.S.A. | publisher =Jim Porter | date =2010-10-04 | url =http://www.winningharmony.com/News_and_Events.php | accessdate = 2013-10-29 | postscript =&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to "." for the cite to end in a ".", as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to communication of clear expectations that bystanders should intervene and increasing individual self-efficacy, there is growing research that suggests interventions should build on the foundation that children’s belief that bullying is morally wrong. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Thornberg | first =Robert | last2 =Tenenbaum | first2 =Laura | last3 =Varjas | first3 =Kris | last4 =Meyers | first4 =Joel | last5 =Jungert | first5 =Tomas | last6 =Vanegas | first6 =Gina | title =Bystander Motivation in Bullying Incidents: To Intervene or Not to Intervene? | journal =Western Journal of Emergency Medicine | volume =13 | issue =3 | pages =247–252 | publisher =National Center for Biotechnology Information, U.S. National Library of Medicine | date =2012-08 | language =  | doi =10.5811/westjem.2012.3.11792| pmc =3415829 | pmid =22900122}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among adults, being a bystander to workplace bullying was linked to depressive symptoms, particularly for women. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Jensen | first =I. B. | title =The impact of bystanding to workplace bullying on symptoms of depression among women and men in industry in Sweden: an empirical and theoretical longitudinal study | journal =International Archives of Occupational and Environmental Health | volume =86 | issue =6 | pages =709–716 | publisher =Springer Berlin Heidelberg | date =2013-08 | url =http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2Fs00420-012-0813-1 | jstor = | issn =1432-1246 | doi =10.1007/s00420-012-0813-1 | accessdate = 2013-10-29 | first2 =A. | first3 =J. | first4 =I. B. | pmid =22940902 | pmc =3722445}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Of those bullied===
Dr. Cook says that "A typical victim is likely to be aggressive, lack social skills, think negative thoughts, experience difficulties in solving social problems, come from a negative family, school and community environments and be noticeably rejected and isolated by peers".&lt;ref name="APS2010"/&gt;

The results of a  [[metanalysis]] conducted by Cook and  published by the [[American Psychological Association]] in 2010  concluded the main risk factors for children and adolescents being bullied, and also  for becoming bullies,  are the lack of social problem-solving skills.&lt;ref name="APS2010"/&gt;

====Effects of bullying on those who are targeted====
Mona O'Moore of the Anti-Bullying Centre at Trinity College in Dublin, has written, "There is a growing body of research which indicates that individuals, whether child or adult, who are persistently subjected to abusive behavior are at risk of stress related illness which can sometimes lead to suicide".{{cite web | title =Anti-Bullying Centre | work =Trinity College Dublin | publisher =| url = http://www.abc.tcd.ie/ | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Those who have been the targets of bullying can suffer from long term emotional and behavioral problems. Bullying can cause [[loneliness]], [[Depression (mood)|depression]], [[anxiety]], lead to low [[self-esteem]] and increased susceptibility to illness.&lt;ref name="WilliamsForgas2013"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Kipling D. Williams|author2=Joseph P. Forgas|author3=William Von Hippel|title=The Social Outcast: Ostracism, Social Exclusion, Rejection, and Bullying|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=FHWhtvCm5LAC&amp;pg=PR2|accessdate=2013-10-29|date=13 May 2013|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-1-135-42338-4|pages=2–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bullying has also been shown to cause maladjustment in young children, and targets of bullying who were also bullies themselves exhibit even greater social difficulties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Arsenault|first=Louise PhD|coauthors=Walsh, Elizabeth MD; Trzesniewski, Kali PhD; et al.|title=Bullying Victimization Uniquely Contributes to Adjustment Problems in Young Children: A Nationally Representative Cohort Study|journal=Pediatrics|year=2006|month=July|volume=118|issue=1|pages=130–138|doi=10.1542/peds.2005-2388|url=http://www.pediatrics.org/cgi/doi/10.1542/peds.2005-2388|accessdate=22 February 2013|publisher=American Academy of Pediatrics|issn=0031 4005|pmid=16818558}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the long term it can lead to [[posttraumatic stress disorder]] and an inability to form relationships. {{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

=====Suicide=====
{{Main|Bullycide}}
There is evidence that bullying increases the risk of [[suicide]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Kim YS, Leventhal B |title=Bullying and suicide. A review |journal=International Journal of Adolescent Medicine and Health |volume=20 |issue=2 |pages=133–54 |year=2008 |pmid=18714552|doi=10.1515/IJAMH.2008.20.2.133|last2=Leventhal}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is estimated that between 15 and 25 children commit suicide every year in the UK alone, because they are being bullied.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.coastkid.org/si-sob.html Statistics on bullying]&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead link|date=October 2013}}

There have been cases of apparent bullying suicides that have been reported closely by the media. These include the deaths of [[Suicide of Ryan Halligan|Ryan Halligen]], [[Suicide of Phoebe Prince|Phoebe Prince]], [[Suicide of Dawn-Marie Wesley|Dawn-Marie Wesley]], [[Kelly Yeomans]], Jessica Haffer,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Jessica Kassandra Haffer | publisher =Keith &amp; Jeralyn Haffer | url = http://www.jessicahaffer.com/ | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hamed Nastoh,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Hamed Nastoh | url = http://www.angelfire.com/bc2/hamed/ | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; April Himes,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Caruso | first =Kevin | title =April Himes Memorial | work =Suicide.org | publisher =Suicide.org | url = http://www.suicide.org/memorials/april-himes.html | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cherice Moralez&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =McLaughlin | first =Elliot C. | title =Montana teen loved pit bulls, poetry before rape and suicide | work =CNN | section = U.S. | publisher =Cable News Network | date =2013-08-30 | url =http://edition.cnn.com/2013/08/30/us/montana-teacher-rape-victim-profile/index.html  | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Rebecca Ann Sedwick.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Pearce | first =Matt | coauthors = | title =Florida girl, 12, found dead after bullies said 'kill yourself' | newspaper =Los Angeles Times | section = U.S.: Nation Now | publisher =Los Angeles Times | date =2013-09-12 | url =http://www.latimes.com/nation/nationnow/la-na-nn-florida-cyberbullying-20130912,0,1429218.story#axzz2j8q54wL8 | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Violence=====
Bullied students [[Eric Harris and Dylan Klebold]] carried out the 1999 [[Columbine High School massacre]]. Since then, bullying has been more closely linked to high school violence in general.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Boodman | first =Sandra G. | title =Gifted and Tormented | newspaper =The Washington Post | section = Health | publisher =The Washington Post | date =2006-05-16 | url =http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/05/15/AR2006051501103.html | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Serial killers]] were frequently bullied through direct and indirect methods as children or adolescents. [[Henry Lee Lucas]], a serial killer and diagnosed [[psychopath]], said the ridicule and rejection he suffered as a child caused him to hate everyone. [[Kenneth Bianchi]], a serial killer and member of the [[Hillside Stranglers]], was teased as a child because he urinated in his pants and suffered twitching, and as a teenager was ignored by his peers.{{cite web | last =Scott | first =	Shirley Lynn | title =What Makes Serial Killers Tick? | work =Crime library | publisher =Turner Entertainment Networks, Inc. A Time Warner Company | url = http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/notorious/tick/victims_1.html | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}

=====Positive development=====
Some have argued that bullying can teach life lessons and instill strength. Helene Guldberg, a child development academic, sparked controversy when she argued that being a target of bullying can teach a child "how to manage disputes and boost their ability to interact with others", and that teachers should not intervene, but leave children to respond to the bullying themselves:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author =Tanya | title =Child Development Academician Says Bullying Is Beneficial To Kids | work =Med India | section = News | publisher =Medindia | date =2009-02-02 | url =http://www.medindia.net/news/Child-Development-Academician-Says-Bullying-Is-Beneficial-To-Kids-46992-1.htm | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
:"If boys or girls are able to stand up for themselves, being attacked by enemies can help their development. Studies have shown that children become more popular among, and respected by, teachers and fellow pupils if they repay hostility in kind. They remember such experiences more vividly than friendly episodes, helping them to develop healthy social and emotional skills".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/education/article7133986.ece|title=Education Article | location=London | newspaper=[[The Times]] | first=Fiona | last=Hamilton|accessdate=2013-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead link|date=October 2013}}
Bullying can also sometimes cause targets to adopt social or physical lifestyle changes that can result in greater mental or physical health over the long term. For example, weight-based victimization (WBV) has been shown to sometimes influence overweight individuals to lose weight.&lt;ref name="ncbi_23266918"&gt;{{cite journal
|author=Puhl, R.M., Peterson, J.L., &amp; Luedicke, J.
|year=2013
|title=Weight-based victimization: bullying experiences of weight loss treatment-seeking youth
|journal=Pediatrics
|pmid=23266918
|url=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23266918
|doi=10.1542/peds.2012-1106
|volume=131
|issue=1
|pages=e1–9
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Despite the fact that the majority of those who may find themselves to be the targets of bullying behavior may ultimately feel "harmed" by such targeting, a few  studies have pointed up some potentially positive outcomes from bullying behavior.&lt;ref name="fight back"&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1280625/Bullying-good-children-Study-finds-fight-popular.html Study describing how "learning to fight back" can help students to mature.]&lt;/ref&gt;  These studies have found that with some individuals, as a result of their having been targeted with bullying behavior, this certain minority of former bullying "targets" have actually experienced being "enabled" through their experiences with bullying to develop various coping strategies which included "standing up for themselves" in ways which acted to "re-balance" former imbalances of power.  Such former bullying targets have reported such things as "becoming a better person" as a result of their former bullying ordeals.&lt;ref name = "fight back"/&gt;  The teaching of such anti-bullying coping skills to "would-be-targets" and to others has been found to be an effective long term means of reducing bullying incidence rates and a valuable skill-set for individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.careforkids.com.au/childcarenews/2010/july/bullying.html Positive Anti-Bullying Strategies by Melissa Graham] &lt;/ref&gt;

==Intervention==
Despite the large number of individuals who do not approve of bullying, there are very few who will intervene on behalf of a target. Most people remain [[bystanders]], and may accept the bullying or even support the bully. In 85% of bullying incidents, bystanders are involved in teasing the target or egging on the bully.&lt;ref name="IGS"&gt;{{cite journal | last =Liepe-Levinson | first =Katherine | last2 =Levinson | first2 =Martin H. | title =A General Semantics Approach To School-Age Bullying | journal =ETC: A Review of General Semantics | volume =62 | issue =1 | pages =4 | publisher =The Institute of General Semantics | date =2005-01 | url =http://www.generalsemantics.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/articles/etc/62-1-liepe-levinson.pdf | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the [[bully]] encounters no negative response from observers, it encourages continuation of the behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Nelson | first =E. D. | last2 =Lambert | first2 =R. D. | title =Sticks, Stones and Semantics: The Ivory Tower Bully's Vocabulary of Motives | journal =Qualitative Sociology | volume =24 | issue =1 | pages =83-106 | publisher =Kluwer Academic Publisher-Plenum Publishers | date =2001 | url =http://link.springer.com/article/10.1023%2FA%3A1026695430820 | issn =1573-7837 | doi =10.1023/A:1026695430820 | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are many reasons why individuals choose not to intervene. They may be relieved that the target of a normal and generally-present danger is someone else, they may take [[vicarious]] satisfaction in the bullying, or they may worry that they risk becoming the next target through intervention. An intuitive understanding that others will be similarly unwilling to assist them if they do become the next target likely strengthens the motivation to remain passive. {{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

Researchers have been considered the [[just-world phenomenon|just-world belief theory]] to explore a posited decline in anti-bullying [[Attitude (psychology)|attitudes]]. "This is the idea that people get what they deserve and deserve what they get". The study determined that children do seek to understand, justify, and rectify the different injustices they come across in everyday life. However, further research is needed to link the two together.&lt;ref name="IGS"/&gt;

===School-Based Intervention===
The following has been found to be effective in school-based anti-bullying programs:

* training in emotional control,
* peer counseling,
* school policy on bullying. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Lee | first =S. | last =Kim | first =C. J.   | last =Kim | first =D. H. | title =A meta-analysis of the effect of school-based anti-bullying programs | journal =Journal of Child Health Care:  | date =2013-10-03 | language = | url =http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24092871 | jstor = | pmid=24092871 | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===US Federal intervention===
In 2010, under the leadership of then Assistant Deputy Secretary [[Kevin Jennings]] and Education Secretary [[Arne Duncan]], the [[U.S. Department of Education]] held the first "Federal Partners in Bullying Prevention Summit," bringing together over 150 researchers, parents, students and executive leadership from both non-profit and corporate organizations involved in bullying prevention efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Federal Partners in Bullying Prevention | work =Juvenile Justice Vermont: Juvenile Justice, Youth Advocacy | publisher =Juvenile Justice Vermont | date =2010-10-16 | url = http://www.juvenilejusticevt.org/juvenile-justice/federal-partners-in-bullying-prevention-summit/ | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October, 2010, the U.S. Department of Education's Office for Civil Rights released a letter clarifying the overlap between bullying and harassment covered under several Federal Civil Rights Laws that require schools to adequately address the behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Dear Colleague Letter | work =Ed.gov: Office for Civil Rights | publisher =U.S. Department of Education | date =2010-10-26 | url = http://www2.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/letters/colleague-201010.html | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; With increasing public attention in late 2010 and early 2011, President Barack Obama and First Lady Michelle Obama hosted the first ever White House Conference on Bullying Prevention on March 10, 2011 to "dispel the myth that bullying is just a harmless rite of passage or an inevitable part of growing up".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | title =Background on White House Conference on Bullying Prevention | publisher =The White House Office of the Press Secretary | date =2011-03-10 | url =http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2011/03/10/background-white-house-conference-bullying-prevention | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Lee | first =Jesse | title =President Obama &amp; the First Lady at the White House Conference on Bullying Prevention | work =The White House Blog | publisher =www.whitehouse.gov | date =2011-03-10 | url = http://www.whitehouse.gov/blog/2011/03/10/president-obama-first-lady-white-house-conference-bullying-prevention | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; At that Conference, the U.S. Federal Government's central repository on bullying prevention, StopBullying.gov officially launched.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Huang | first =Sherry | title =White House Debuts StopBullying.gov | work =www.parents.com | publisher =Meredith Corporation | date =2011-03-10 | url = http://www.parents.com/blogs/goodyblog/2011/03/white-house-debuts-stopbullying-gov/ | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Together with the Departments of Health and Human Services, Justice, Defense, Agriculture, the Interior, as well as the National Council on Disability, the FTC and the White House Initiative on AAPI, which made up the Federal Partners in Bullying Prevention, the Department of Education hosted two additional summits in 2011 and 2012, again bringing together the growing anti-bullying field.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Federal Partners will Come Together at Second Annual Summit to Discuss Continued Strategies for Combating Bullying | work = U.S. Department of Education: News: Media-Advisories | publisher =U.S. Department of Education | url = http://www.ed.gov/news/media-advisories/federal-partners-will-come-together-second-annual-summit-discuss-continued-str | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title =Education Dept. Hosts Third Annual Bullying Prevention Summit | work =C-span: Events | publisher =National Cable Satellite Corporation | date =2012-08-06 | url =http://www.c-span.org/Events/Education-Dept-Hosts-Third-Annual-Bullying-Prevention-Summit/10737432871/ | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April, 2012, StopBullying.gov was relaunched to include additional information as well as a map tracking state anti-bullying laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Announcing the Relaunch of Stop Bullying website | work =ED.gov: news | publisher =U.S. Department of Education | date =2012-04-11 | url = http://www.ed.gov/oese-news/announcing-relaunch-stop-bullying-website | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October, 2012 the Departments of Education and Health and Human Services launched a PSA campaign with the [[Ad Council]] and other partners targeted at parents to talk to their kids about being "more than a bystander".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | title =Bullying Prevention Campaign to Empower Parents Launches During National Bullying Prevention Month | publisher =Ad Council | date =2012-10-18 | url =http://www.adcouncil.org/News-Events/Press-Releases/Bullying-Prevention-Campaign-to-Empower-Parents-Launches-During-National-Bullying-Prevention-Month | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Secretary Jennings left the U.S. Department of Education in July, 2011, many of these efforts were spearheaded by Research and Policy Coordinator for Bullying Prevention Initiatives, Deborah Temkin, who was recognized for her work with a nomination for the [[Samuel J. Heyman Service to America Medals]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Chandler | first = Michael Alison | title =Bullying-prevention official Temkin nominated for Heyman medal | newspaper =The Washington Post | section = Education | publisher =The Washington Post | date =2012-08-08 | url =http://articles.washingtonpost.com/2012-08-08/local/35493939_1_bullying-prevention-temkin-graduate-school | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Anti-bullying-program success rates ===
Results from a Texas anti-bullying program "study" which were reported on by CBS News (Sept 2013) at first seemed to indicate that anti-bullying programs were actually counterproductive.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dfw.cbslocal.com/2013/10/08/are-anti-bullying-programs-having-an-opposite-effect/ Anti-Bullying Programs Having an Opposite Effect?]&lt;/ref&gt;  However, these study results were later found to be inconclusive, because the Texas study did not actually compare pre-anti-bullying-program incident rates with post-anti-bullying-program incident rates within the same school districts, in other words: these results may have only highlighted the fact that school districts with pronounced bullying problems tend to be more likely to adopt anti-bullying programs, than school districts without pronounced bullying problems.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenewamerican.com/reviews/opinion/item/16721-study-anti-bullying-programs-increase-bullying Reviewer Selwyn Duke acknowledges that Texas study did not track individual program impacts within any given school districts.]&lt;/ref&gt;  Other more comprehensive studies which did review these rates within the same anti-bullying-program school districts have indeed found mixed results, with some school districts achieving up to 50% reductions in incident rates, while other districts even experienced slightly increased incident rates.&lt;ref&gt;[http://greatergood.berkeley.edu/article/item/the_bully_problem Summary of longitudinal studies of various anti-bullying-program results.]&lt;/ref&gt;  In this study it was found that a higher level of participation by a school's central administration generally resulted in a higher success level for the anti-bullying-program.

==Chronic bullying cycle==
While on the surface, chronic bullying may appear to be simply the actions of an "aggressor" (or aggressors) perpetrated upon an unwilling "targeted individual" (or individuals), on a certain deeper level, for it to succeed, the bullying-cycle must also be viewed as necessarily including a certain chronic inadequate response on the part of the target (or targets). That is, a response that is seen by both the bully and the target as insufficient to prevent the chronic bullying-cycle from repeating itself between the given individuals. A suitable response to any given attempt at bullying varies with the occasion, and can range from ignoring a bully to turning a prank around so that it makes a "pranksteree" out of the would be prankster,&lt;ref name = "churchill and lady astor"&gt;{{cite web | last =Hawkins | first =	John | title =RWN's Favorite Quotations from Winston Churchill | work =Rightwing News | publisher = Rightwing News | date =2012-04-05 | url = http://www.rightwingnews.com/quotes/rwns-favorite-quotations-from-winston-churchill-2/ | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; to even summoning legal intervention. In any case, the targeted individual must necessarily somehow demonstrate to the would-be bully that one will not allow one's self to be daunted, intimidated, or otherwise "cowed" by the bully.  Those individuals or groups who are capable of reacting to initial bullying attempts in ways that tend to sufficiently discourage potential bullies from repeated attempts are less likely to be drawn into this destructive cycle. Those individuals or groups who most readily react to stressful situations by perceiving themselves as "[[victim mentality|victims]]" tend to make the most suitable candidates for becoming the "targets" of chronic bullying.&lt;ref name = "bully-victim-predictors"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.micheleborba.com/blog/2010/09/22/problem-solving-to-prevent-bullying/
| title= Problem Solving to Prevent Bullying
| accessdate = 2010-10-31}} Discussion of typical psychological profiles of both bullies and their targets.
&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead link|date=October 2013}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Borba | first =	Michele | title =Teaching Problem Solving to Reduce Bullying | work =Dr. Michele Borba: Blog | url = http://micheleborba.com/blog/problem-solving-to-prevent-bullying/ | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under some circumstances, targets may be chosen in what may be a completely random or arbitrary process, especially in groups in which the "bully mentality" may have already succeeded in achieving domination within the group. In such groups, the defense mechanisms of the entire group may have already been "broken down", and therefore the targeting of individuals no longer requires the seeking out of "certain personality types" to become the "next target". The reversal of such chronic and well entrenched bullying behavior in such groups sometimes requires a much more carefully planned, coordinated, determined, and multi-individual response from a would-be target than in a group in which either the "bully mentality" may not (yet) prevail, or ideally in a group that may have already taken a pro-active preventative approach towards bullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Shultz | first =	Fred | title =Bullying and Hazing: What Can We Do About These Problems? | work =Lawyers.com: Law Blog | publisher =LexisNexis | date =2010-10-26 | url = http://personal-injury.lawyers.com/blogs/archives/9520-Bullying-and-Hazing-What-Can-We-Do-About-These-Problems.html | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "a pro-active approach against bullying"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.conflictmediation.net/bullies.html
| title= Safe schools: Breaking the cycle of violence
| accessdate = 2010-11-27}} Discussion of pro-active anti-bullying school plans by certified mediator, Meadow Clark.
&lt;/ref&gt;

Typically, the bullying-cycle must include both an act of aggression on the part of a potential bully, and a response by a potential target that is perceived by both as a certain sign of submission. The cycle is only set in motion when both of these two essential elements are present. Once both of these two elements manifest themselves, the bullying cycle often proceeds to feed on itself over time, and may last for months, years, or even decades. The cycle is most easily broken at its initial onset; however, it can also be broken at any later point in its progression by simply removing either one of its two essential ingredients. While group involvement may seem to complicate bullying activities, the act is most often an implied agreement in principle between a chief bully or instigator and the target that the one has "submitted" to the other. In the act of bullying, the bully attempts to make a public statement to the effect of: "See me and fear me, I am so powerful that I have the ability to inflict pain upon the intended target at the time and manner of my choice without having to pay any consequences". Should an intended target exhibit a "defeated attitude" in response to chronic bullying, then the bullying is likely to continue. In circumstances where a "bullying pattern" has not yet fully established itself, should the intended target respond with a clear attitude of self-confidence that somehow demonstrates that the bully's attempt to dominate is futile, then the bullying attempt will often quickly diminish or end all-together. Established patterns of bullying may require greater and more persistent effort to reverse. Institutions and organs of society often reinforce bullying, often by implying to or telling targets of bullies that they are responsible for defending themselves, and then punishing targets if they fight back.
&lt;ref name = "nbc-on-jay-banks"&gt;{{cite web | last =Banks | first =	Jay | title =NBC TV-10 (Roanoke, VA) | work =YouTube | publisher = YouTube | date =2009-11-06 | url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wzLukEtsgCA | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "jay-banks-youtube-homepage"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.youtube.com/profile?user=jaybanksproductions#g/u
| title= Jay Banks Productions Youtube Homepage
| accessdate = 2010-10-31}} Compilation of anti-bullying videos by anti-bullying expert, Jay Banks
&lt;/ref&gt;

==In different contexts==

===Cyberbullying===
{{Main|Cyberbullying}}
Cyber-bullying is any bullying done through the use of technology. This form of bullying can easily go undetected because of lack of parental/authoritative supervision. Because bullies can pose as someone else, it is the most anonymous form of bullying. Cyber bullying includes, but is not limited to, abuse using email, instant messaging, text messaging, websites, social networking sites, etc.&lt;ref name="BoltonGraeve2005"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Jose Bolton|author2=Stan Graeve|title=No Room for Bullies: From the Classroom to Cyberspace|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=WOUWBckRIBIC|accessdate=2013-10-29|year=2005|publisher=Boys Town Press|isbn=978-1-889322-67-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Particular watch dog organizations have been designed to contain the spread of cyber-bullying.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}}

===Disability bullying===
{{Main|Disability bullying}}
It has been noted that disabled people are disproportionately affected by bullying and abuse, and such activity has been cited as a hate crime.&lt;ref name="Quarmby2011"&gt;{{cite book|author=Katherine Quarmby|title=Scapegoat: Why We Are Failing Disabled People|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=lglMYgEACAAJ|accessdate=2013-10-29|year=2011|publisher=Portobello Books Limited|isbn=978-1-84627-321-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bullying is not limited to those who are visibly disabled such as wheelchair-users or physically deformed such as those with a [[cleft lip]] but also those with [[learning disabilities]] such as [[autism]]&lt;ref name="Sainsbury2009"&gt;{{cite book|author=Clare Sainsbury|title=Martian in the Playground: Understanding the Schoolchild with Asperger's Syndrome|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=TbGwEaH8eAIC|accessdate=2013-10-29|date=30 September 2009|publisher=SAGE Publications|isbn=978-1-4462-4398-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Attwood2006"&gt;{{cite book|author=Tony Attwood|title=The Complete Guide to Asperger's Syndrome|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ZwQGsuCNMPYC|accessdate=2013-10-29|year=2006|publisher=Jessica Kingsley Publishers|isbn=978-1-84310-495-7|pages=95–111}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[developmental coordination disorder]].&lt;ref name="Kirby2002"&gt;{{cite book|author=Amanda Kirby|title=Dyspraxia: The Hidden Handicap|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=so-3-vIf0lkC|accessdate=2013-10-29|date=1 October 2002|publisher=Souvenir Press|isbn=978-0-285-63512-8|pages=106–113}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Brookes2005"&gt;{{cite book|author=Geoff Brookes|title=Dyspraxia|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wZDqe-SckjIC|accessdate=2013-10-29|date=January 2005|publisher=Continuum|isbn=978-0-8264-7581-7|pages=43–46}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the latter case, this is linked to a poor ability in physical education, and this behaviour can be encouraged by the unthinking physical education teacher. Abuse of the disabled is not limited to schools. There are many known cases in which the disabled have been abused by staff of a "care institution", such as the case revealed in a [[BBC]] Panorama programme on a Castlebeck care home ([[Winterbourne View]]) near [[Bristol]] which led to its closure and the suspension and sacking of some of the staff.&lt;ref name="BBC News"&gt;{{cite news | title =Four arrests after patient abuse caught on film | newspaper =BBC News | section = UK | publisher =BBC | date =2011-06-01 | url =http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-13548222 | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is an additional problem that those with learning disabilities are often not as able to explain things to other people so are more likely to be disbelieved or ignored if they do complain.

===Gay bullying===
{{Main|Gay bashing}}
Gay bullying and gay bashing are expressions used to designate [[verbal abuse|verbal]] or [[physical abuse|physical]] actions that are direct or indirect in nature by a person or group against a person who is [[gay]], [[lesbian]], [[bisexual]], [[transgendered]] ([[LGBT]]), or of questionable sexual orientation, or one who is perceived to be so, because of [[rumors]] or fitting gay [[stereotype]]s.  Gay and lesbian youth are more likely to report bullying. &lt;ref name="Berlan et al., 2010"/&gt;

===Legal bullying===
{{Main|Legal abuse}}
Legal bullying is the bringing of a [[Vexatious litigation|vexatious legal action]] to control and punish a person.  Legal bullying can often take the form of frivolous, repetitive, or burdensome lawsuits brought to intimidate the defendant into submitting to the litigant's request, not because of the legal merit of the litigant's position, but principally due to the defendant's inability to maintain the legal battle.  This can also take the form of [[Strategic lawsuit against public participation|SLAPPs]].  It was partially concern about the potential for this kind of abuse that helped to fuel the [[protests against SOPA and PIPA]] in the United States in 2011 and 2012.

===Military bullying===
{{Main|Bullying in the military}}
In 2000, the UK [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] (MOD) defined bullying as: "...&amp;nbsp;the use of physical strength or the [[abuse of authority]] to [[intimidate]] or [[Victimization|victimize]] others, or to give unlawful punishments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Dannatt | first =Sir Richard | title =Values and Standards of the British Army | section =Lawful: Paragraph 20 | publisher =the British Army | date =2008 | url = http://www.army.mod.uk/documents/general/v_s_of_the_british_army.pdf | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some argue that this behaviour should be allowed, due to ways in which "soldiering" is different from other occupations. Soldiers expected to risk their lives should, according to them, develop strength of body and spirit to accept bullying.&lt;ref name="CallaghanKernic2003"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Jean M. Callaghan|author2=Franz Kernic|title=Armed Forces and International Security: Global Trends and Issues|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tvnCKuSdOEwC&amp;pg=PA19|accessdate=2013-10-29|year=2003|publisher=LIT Verlag Münster|isbn=978-3-8258-7227-4|pages=19–|chapter=Chapter 2: "Social Psychology" of the Individual Soldier}}&lt;/ref&gt; This attitude can be seen as paralleled by the training expected by the Ancient Greek city state of [[Sparta]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

However, the role of a soldier has widened to peace-keeping where overt aggression is usually counterproductive and services auxiliary to the military often do some soldiering as well as another role such as engineering. {{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

===Parental bullying===
Parents who may [[Displacement (psychology)|displace]] their anger, insecurity, or a persistent need to dominate and control, upon their children in excessive ways have been proven to increase the likelihood that their own children will in turn become overly aggressive or controlling towards their peers.&lt;ref name = "parent bullying"&gt;{{cite web | last =Priesnitz | first =	Wendy | title =Parental Bullying Creates Bullies | work =Natural Child Magazine | publisher =Wendy Priesnitz | url = http://www.naturalchildmagazine.com/news/parental_bullying_creates_bullies.htm | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[American Psychological Association]] advises on its website that parents who may suspect that their own children may be engaging in bullying activities amongst their peers, should carefully consider the examples which they themselves may be setting for their own children, regarding how they typically interact with their own peers, colleagues, and children.  Do the parents typically motivate their peers and their children with positive and self-confidence building incentives, or do they most often attempt to motivate their peers and children with certain "threats" of one form of "punishment" or "reprisal" or another (emotional or physical blackmail)? &lt;ref name = "APA on parental bullying"&gt;{{cite web | title =Bullying: How parents, teachers, and kids can take action to prevent bullying | work =American Psychological Association | publisher =American Psychological Association | url = http://www.apa.org/helpcenter/bullying.aspx# | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prison bullying===
{{Main|Prisoner abuse}}
Another environment known for bullying is a country's prison service. This is almost inevitable when many of the people incarcerated are there for aggressive crimes and many were bullies at school. An additional complication is the staff and their relationships with the inmates. Thus the following possible bullying scenarios are possible:
* Inmate bullies inmate (echoing school bullying);
* Staff bullies inmate;
* Staff bullies staff (a manifestation of workplace bullying);
* Inmate bullies staff.

===School bullying===
{{Main|School bullying}}
Bullying can occur in nearly any part in or around the school building, though it may occur more frequently in [[physical education]] classes and activities, [[Recess (break)|recess]], [[hallway]]s, bathrooms, on [[school bus]]es and while waiting for buses, and in classes that require group work and/or after school activities. Bullying in school sometimes consists of a group of students taking advantage of or isolating one student in particular and gaining the loyalty of bystanders who want to avoid becoming the next target. These bullies may taunt and tease their target before physically bullying the target. Bystanders may participate or watch, sometimes out of fear of becoming the next target.

Bullying can also be perpetrated by teachers and the school system itself: There is an inherent power differential in the system that can easily predispose to subtle or covert abuse ([[relational aggression]] or [[passive aggression]]), [[humiliation]], or exclusion — even while maintaining overt commitments to anti-bullying policies.&lt;ref name="GarbarinodeLara2003"&gt;{{cite book|author1=James Garbarino|author2=Ellen deLara|title=And Words Can Hurt Forever: How to Protect Adolescents from Bullying, Harassment, and Emotional Violence|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3XPx-OLgQjQC|accessdate=2013-10-29|date=2 September 2003|publisher=Free Press|isbn=978-0-7432-2899-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last =Witted | first =Kathryn Suzanne | title =Student Reports of Physical and Psychological Maltreatment in Schools: An Under Explored Aspect of Student Victimization in Schools | work = PhD dissertation, University of Tennessee | year =2005 | url =http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3874&amp;context=utk_graddiss | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1177/0013124507304487 |title=Do Teachers Bully Students?: Findings From a Survey of Students in an Alternative Education Setting |year=2007 |last1=Whitted |first1=K. S. |last2=Dupper |first2=D. R. |journal=Education and Urban Society |volume=40 |page=329|issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexual bullying===
{{Main|Sexual bullying}}
{{See also|Slut shaming}}
Sexual bullying is "any bullying behaviour, whether physical or non-physical, that is based on a person's sexuality or gender. It is when sexuality or gender is used as a weapon by boys or girls towards other boys or girls - although it is more commonly directed at girls. It can be carried out to a person's face, behind their back or through the use of technology."&lt;ref name=NSPCC02 &gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nspcc.org.uk/Inform/resourcesforteachers/classroomresources/sexual_bullying_definition_wdf68769.pdf |title=The NSPCC working definition of Sexual Bullying |publisher=[[National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children|NSPCC]] |date= |accessdate=22 April 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Workplace bullying===
{{Main|Workplace bullying}}
According to the Workplace Bullying and Trauma Institute workplace bullying is "repeated, health-harming mistreatment, [[verbal abuse]], or conduct which is threatening, [[humiliating]], [[intimidating]], or [[sabotage]] that interferes with work, or some combination of the three".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =The WBI Definition of Workplace Bullying | work =Workplace Bullying Institute | publisher = Workplace Bullying Institute | url = http://www.workplacebullying.org/individuals/problem/definition/ | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Statistics show that bullying is 3 times as prevalent as illegal [[discrimination]] and at least 1,600 times as prevalent as [[workplace violence]]. Statistics also show that while only one employee in every 10,000 becomes a target of workplace violence, one in six experiences bullying at work. Bullying is a little more common than [[sexual harassment]] but not verbal abuse which occurs more than bullying.

Unlike the more physical form of [[school bullying]], workplace bullying often takes place within the established rules and policies of the organization and society. Such actions are not necessarily illegal and may not even be against the firm's regulations; however, the damage to the targeted employee and to [[workplace morale]] is obvious.

====In academia====
{{Main|Bullying in academia}}
Bullying in academia is workplace bullying of scholars and staff in [[academia]], especially places of [[higher education]] such as [[college]]s and [[universities]]. It is believed to be common, although has not received as much attention from researchers as bullying in some other contexts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Keashly | first =Loraleigh | last2 =Neuman | first2 =Joel H. | title =Faculty Experiences with Bullying in Higher Education - Causes, Consequences, and Management | journal =Administrative Theory &amp; Praxis | volume =32 | issue =1 | pages =48-70 | publisher =Public Administration Theory Network | date =2010 | url = http://www.ccas.net/files/ADVANCE/Keashly_Bullying.pdf | doi =10.2753/ATP1084-1806320103 | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====In blue collar jobs====
Bullying has been identified as prominent in [[blue collar]] jobs including on the oil rigs and in mechanic shops and machine shops. It is thought that [[intimidation]] and fear of [[retributive justice|retribution]] cause decreased incident reports. This is also an industry dominated by males, typically of little education, where disclosure of incidents are seen as [[wikt:effeminate|effeminate]], which, in the socioeconomic and cultural milieu of such industries, would likely lead to a [[vicious circle]]. This is often used in combination with [[psychological manipulation|manipulation]] and [[coercion]] of facts to gain favour among higher ranking [[administrator (business)|administrators]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Notelaers | first =Guy | last2 =Vermunt | first2 =Jeroen K. | last3 =Baillien | first3 =Elfi | last4 =Einarsen | first4 =Ståle | last5 =De Witte | first5 =Hans  | title =Exploring Risk Groups Workplace Bullying with Categorical Data | journal =Industrial Health | volume =49 | issue = 1 | pages =73-88 | publisher =Industrial Health | date =2011 | url =http://unimaas.academia.edu/GuyNotelaers/Papers/278637/Exploring_Risk_Groups_and_Risk_Factors_for_Workplace_Bullying | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====In information technology====
{{Main|Bullying in information technology}}
A culture of bullying is common in [[information technology (IT)]], leading to high sickness rates, low [[morale]], poor [[productivity]], and high [[Turnover (employment)|staff turnover]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Thomson | first =Rebecca | title =IT profession blighted by bullying | work = ComputerWeekly.com: Feature | publisher =TechTarget | url = http://www.computerweekly.com/feature/IT-profession-blighted-by-bullying | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Deadline-driven project work and stressed-out managers take their toll on IT workers.&lt;ref name="RichardsEdwards2008"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Ann Richards|author2=Sharon L. Edwards|title=A Nurse's Survival Guide to the Ward|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ytmEHQjia0AC|accessdate=2013-10-29|year=2008|publisher=Churchill Livingstone|isbn=978-0-443-06897-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====In medicine====
{{Main|Bullying in medicine}}
Bullying in the [[medical profession]] is common, particularly of student or trainee doctors and of nurses. It is thought that this is at least in part an outcome of conservative traditional [[Hierarchical organization|hierarchical structures]] and [[teaching methods]] in the medical profession, which may result in a bullying cycle.

====In nursing====
{{Main|Bullying in nursing}}
Bullying has been identified as being particularly prevalent in the [[nursing]] [[profession]] although the reasons are not clear. It is thought that [[relational aggression]] (psychological aspects of bullying such as [[gossipping]] and [[intimidation]]) are relevant. Relational aggression has been studied amongst girls but not so much amongst adult women.&lt;ref name="RichardsEdwards2008"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Ann Richards|author2=Sharon L. Edwards|title=A Nurse's Survival Guide to the Ward|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ytmEHQjia0AC|accessdate=2013-10-29|year=2008|publisher=Churchill Livingstone|isbn=978-0-443-06897-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Dellasega | first =Cheryl A. | title =Bullying Among Nurses | journal =American Journal of Nursing | volume =109 | issue =1 | pages =52-58 | publisher =Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins | date =2009 | url =http://journals.lww.com/ajnonline/Abstract/2009/01000/Bullying_Among_Nurses.28.aspx | doi =10.1097/01.NAJ.0000344039.11651.08 | accessdate = 2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====In teaching====
{{Main|Bullying in teaching}}
[[School]] [[teachers]] are commonly the subject of bullying but they are also sometimes the originators of bullying within a school environment.

===In other areas===
As the verb ''to bully'' is defined as simply "forcing one's way aggressively or by intimidation", the term may generally apply to ''any'' life experience where one is motivated primarily by intimidation instead of by more positive goals such as mutually shared interests and benefits. As such, any figure of authority or power which may use intimidation as a primary means of motivating others, such as a neighborhood "protection racket don", a national dictator, a childhood ring-leader, a terrorist, a terrorist organization, or even a ruthless business CEO, could rightfully be referred to as a bully. According to psychologist Pauline Rennie-Peyton, we each face the possibility of being bullied in any phase of our lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Karim | first = Nadiya | title =Bullying in Universities: It exists | newspaper =The Independent | section = News: Education: Higher | publisher =The Independent | date =2010-01-15 | url =http://www.independent.co.uk/news/education/higher/bullying-in-universities-it-exists-1869267.html | accessdate = 2013-10-29}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|2|
* ''[[The Bully: A Discussion and Activity Story]]'' (book)
* [[Abuse]]
* [[Complex post-traumatic stress disorder]]
* ''[[Bully (2011 film)|Bully]]''
* [[Bullycide]]
* [[Happy slapping]]
* [[Hate crime]]
* [[Hazing]]
* [[Mobbing]]
* [[Passive aggression]]
* [[Psychological manipulation]]
* [[Psychological trauma]]
* [[Relational aggression]]
* [[Scapegoating]]
* [[School violence]]
* [[Social exclusion]]
* [[Social isolation]]
* [[Social undermining]]
* [[Taunting]]
* [[Teasing]]
* ''[[The Twisted Sisterhood: Unraveling the Dark Legacy of Female Friendships]]'' (book)
* [[Victim blaming]]
* [[Victim playing]]
* [[Victimisation]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Kohut MR The Complete Guide to Understanding, Controlling, and Stopping Bullies &amp; Bullying: A Complete Guide for Teachers &amp; Parents (2007)
* ''Bullies and Victims in Schools: a guide to understanding and management'' by Valerie E. Besag (1989)
* ''The Fight That Never Ends'' by Tim Brown
* ''Odd Girl Out: The Hidden Culture of Aggression in Girls" by Rachel Simmons ISBN 0-15-602734-8
* ''Bullycide, Death at Playtime'' by Neil Marr and [[Tim Field]] ISBN 0-9529121-2-0
* ''Bullycide in America: Moms Speak Out about the Bullying/Suicide Connection'' &amp;ndash; by Brenda High, [http://www.bullycide.org Bullycide.org]
* [http://www.outofbullying.com ''A Journey Out of Bullying: From Despair to Hope''] by Patricia L. Scott
* "Peer Abuse Know More! Bullying From A Psychological Perspective" By Elizabeth Bennett
* ''New Perspectives on Bullying'' by Ken Rigby
* [[James Garbarino|Garbarino, J.]] &amp; de Lara, E. (2003). [http://www.enotalone.com/article/5451.html ''And Words ''Can'' Hurt Forever: How to Protect Adolescents from Bullying, Harassment, and Emotional Violence.''] The Free Press: New York NY.
* Joanne Scaglione, Arrica Rose Scaglione [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/custom/portlets/recordDetails/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=ED493726&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=ED493726 ''Bully-proofing children: a practical, hands-on guide to stop bullying'' 2006]
* [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=ED410007&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=ED410007 ''Why Is Everybody Always Picking on Me: A Guide to Handling Bullies for Young People.''] by Terrence Webster-Doyle. Book and Teaching curriculum.
* [http://www.paulgraham.com/nerds.html "Why Nerds are Unpopular"], by [[Paul Graham (computer programmer)|Paul Graham]]. This essay is an example of how even medium differences, in a hierarchical, zero-sum, or negative environments, can lead to ostracism or persecution.
* ''[[Lord of the Flies]]'' by William Golding (1954). A famous work describing how a group of schoolboys trapped on an island descends into savagery.

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://www.bullyingnoway.com.au/ Bullying. No Way! (Australian Education Authorities)]
* [http://www.dfes.gov.uk/bullying Bullying in schools (UK &amp;ndash; schools)]
* [http://pbskids.org/itsmylife/friends/bullies/print_books.html PBSKids.org "Great Books About Bullies"]
* [http://app.thearit.com/uft-brave/bebraveagainstbullying.html Be Brave Against Bullying, a UFT project] 
* [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/simpleSearch.jsp?newSearch=true&amp;eric_sortField=&amp;searchtype=basic&amp;pageSize=10&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=bullying&amp;eric_displayStartCount=1&amp;_pageLabel=ERICSearchResult&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=kw U.S. Department of Education's Education Resources Information Center (ERIC)]

{{Bullying}}
{{abuse}}
{{Psychological manipulation}}
{{Conformity}}

[[Category:Bullying| ]]
[[Category:Social psychology]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Aggression]]
[[Category:Injustice]]
[[Category:Persecution]]
[[Category:Psychological abuse]]
[[Category:Interpersonal conflict]]
[[Category:Human behavior]]

{{Link GA|cs}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>