<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091022001143|321295254" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="432459" pageid="432459" ns="0" title="Bullying"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-10-23T16:49:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{worldwide}}

[[Image:Bullying Irfe.jpg|thumb|Bullying is detrimental to students’ well-being and development. This photo was taken on [[Instituto Regional Federico Errázuriz]], [[Santa Cruz, Chile]].&lt;ref name=nces-2005-310/&gt;]]
'''Bullying''' is repeated acts over time that involves a real or perceived imbalance of power with the more powerful child or group attacking those who are less powerful. (U.S. Dept. of Justice, Fact Sheet #FS-200127) Bullying can be verbal [[harassment]], physical [[assault]], or other more subtle methods of [[coercion]] such as [[psychological manipulation|manipulation]]. Bullying can be defined in many different ways. Although the UK currently has no legal definition of bullying,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.campus.manchester.ac.uk/equalityanddiversity/harassmentdiscriminationandbullying/ Harassment, Discrimination and Bullying Policy] - [[University of Manchester]]&lt;/ref&gt; some US states have laws against it. Bullying is usually done to coerce others by fear or threat.&lt;ref&gt;At least 15 states have passed laws
addressing bullying among school children.[http://72.14.205.104/search?q=cache:ao8az0gkKqMJ:stopbullyingnow.hrsa.gov/HHS_PSA/pdfs/SBN_Tip_6.pdf+bullying+legislation&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=3&amp;gl=us&amp;client=firefox-a]&lt;/ref&gt; Bullying can be prevented when children are taught [[social skill]]s to successfully interact with people. This will help them to be productive adults when interacting with bothersome people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://childparenting.about.com/cs/childdevelopment/a/socialskills.htm] Teaching social skills to children, accessed September 17, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Bullying in school and the workplace is also referred to as peer abuse.

In colloquial speech, bullying often describes a form of harassment perpetrated by an abuser who possesses more physical and/or social power and dominance than the victim.  The victim of bullying is sometimes referred to as a target.  The harassment can be verbal, physical and/or emotional. Sometimes bullies will pick on people bigger or smaller than their size. Bullies hurt people verbally and physically. There are many reasons for that. One of them is because the bullies themselves are or have been the victim of bullying&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/677299&amp;referer=brief_results ''The anatomy of human destructiveness by Eric Fromm'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1667130&amp;referer=brief_results ''Man Against Himself by Karl A. Menninger'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.worldcat.org/search?q=Neurotic+Styles+by+David+Shapiro&amp;qt=owc_search ''Neurotic Styles by David Shapiro'']&lt;/ref&gt; (e.g. a bullying child who is abused at home, or bullying adults who are abused by their colleagues).

Many programs have been started to prevent bullying at schools with promotional speakers. Bullying consists of three types - verbal, physical and emotional.

Norwegian researcher Dan Olweus defines bullying as when a person is "''exposed, repeatedly and over time, to negative actions on the part of one or more other persons.''" He defines negative action as "''when a person intentionally inflicts injury or discomfort upon another person, through physical contact, through words or in other ways.''"&lt;ref name=olweusdef&gt;Olweus, D. [http://www.cobb.k12.ga.us/~preventionintervention/Bully/Definition%20of%20Bullying.pdf A Research Definition of Bullying]&lt;/ref&gt; See also a reference to the Olweus Bullying Prevention Program at Clemson University: http://www.clemson.edu/olweus/ .

Bullying can occur in any setting where human beings interact with each other. This includes [[school]], [[Church (building)|church]], the [[workplace]], [[home]] and [[neighborhoods]]. It is even a common [[Immigration|push factor]] in [[human migration|migration]]. Bullying can exist between social groups, social classes and even between [[countries]] (see ''[[Jingoism]]'').

==Definition==
[[File:IRFE bull.png|200px|thumb|Guys knocking themselves.]]
Bullying is an act of repeated aggressive behavior in order to intentionally hurt another person, physically or mentally. Bullying is characterized by an individual behaving in a certain way to gain power over another person (Besag, 1989). Behaviors may include name calling, verbal or written abuse, exclusion from activities, exclusion from social situations, physical abuse, or coercion (Carey, 2003; Whitted &amp; Dupper, 2005). Bullies may behave this way to be perceived as popular or tough or to get attention. They may bully out of jealousy or be acting out because they themselves are bullied (Crothers &amp; Levinson, 2004).

USA National Center for Education Statistics suggests that bullying can be broken into two categories: Direct bullying, and indirect bullying which is also known as social aggression.&lt;ref name=nces-2005-310&gt;[http://nces.ed.gov/pubs2005/2005310.pdf ''Student Reports of Bullying''], Results From the 2001 School Crime Supplement to the National Crime Victimization Survey, US National Center for Education Statistics&lt;/ref&gt;

Ross states that direct bullying involves a great deal of physical [[aggression]] such as shoving and poking, throwing things, slapping, choking, punching and kicking, beating, stabbing, pulling hair, scratching, biting, scraping and pinching.&lt;ref name=ross&gt;Ross, P.N. (1998). Arresting violence: A resource guide for schools and their communities.  Toronto: Ontario Public School Teachers' Federation.&lt;/ref&gt;

He also suggests that social aggression or indirect bullying is characterized by threatening the victim into [[social isolation]]. This isolation is achieved through a wide variety of techniques, including spreading gossip, refusing to socialize with the victim, bullying other people who wish to socialize with the victim, and criticizing the victim's manner of dress and other socially-significant markers (including the victim's race, religion, disability, etc).
Ross (1998)&lt;ref name=ross/&gt; outlines other forms of indirect bullying which are more subtle and more likely to be verbal, such as name calling, the silent treatment, arguing others into submission, manipulation, gossip/ false gossip, lies, rumors/ false rumors, staring, giggling, laughing at the victim, saying certain words that trigger a reaction from a past event, and mocking. Children's charity [[Act Against Bullying]] was set up in 2003 to help children who were victims of this type of bullying by researching and publishing coping skills.

==Effects==
[[File:Rebecca1917version.jpg|220px|thumb|Physical bullying at school.]]
The effects of bullying can be serious and even fatal. Mona O’Moore Ph. D of the Anti-Bullying Centre, Trinity College Dublin, said, "There is a growing body of research which indicates that individuals, whether child or adult who are persistently subjected to abusive behavior are at risk of stress related illness which can sometimes lead to suicide".&lt;ref name=tcd/&gt;

Victims of bullying can suffer from long term emotional and behavioral problems. Bullying can cause [[loneliness]], [[Depression (mood)|depression]], [[anxiety]], lead to low [[self-esteem]] and increased susceptibility to illness.&lt;ref name=Williams/&gt;

The National Conference of State Legislatures said:
:''"In 2002, a report released by the U.S. Secret Service concluded that bullying played a significant role in many school shootings and that efforts should be made to eliminate bullying behavior."''&lt;ref name=ncsl&gt;[http://www.ncsl.org/programs/educ/SchBullying.htm ''School Bullying.''] National Conference of State Legislatures, Washington, D.C. (retrieved 7 December 2007).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Suicide===

Theres a strong link between bullying and suicide. [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18714552] Bullying leads to several suicides every year. It is estimated that between 15 and 25 children commit suicide every year in UK alone, because they are being bullied. [http://www.coastkid.org/si-sob.html]

==Characteristics of bullies==

{{Contradict|date=May 2009}}

Research indicates that adults who bully have personalities that are authoritarian, combined with a strong need to control or [[dominance (biology)|dominate]].&lt;ref name=brodsky&gt;''The Harassed Worker'', Brodsky, C. (1976), [[D.C. Heath and Company]], Lexington, Massachusetts.&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been suggested that a prejudicial view of subordinates can be particular a risk factor.&lt;ref name=ashforth&gt;''Petty tyranny in organizations '', Ashforth, Blake, Human Relations, Vol. 47, No. 7, 755-778 (1994)&lt;/ref&gt;

Further studies have shown that while [[envy]] and [[resentment]] may be motives for bullying,&lt;ref name=vari&gt;''Bullying and emotional abuse in the workplace. International perspectives in research and practice'', Einarsen, S., Hoel, H., Zapf, D., &amp; Cooper, C. L. (Eds.)(2003), Taylor &amp; Francis, London.&lt;/ref&gt; there is little evidence to suggest that bullies suffer from any deficit in [[self esteem]] (as this would make it difficult to bully).&lt;ref name=bkn&gt;''Bullies and their victims: Understanding a pervasive problem in the schools'', Batsche, G. M., &amp; Knoff, H. M. (1994) School PSYCHOLOGY REVIEW, 23 (2), 165-174. EJ 490 574.&lt;/ref&gt; However, bullying can also be used as a tool to conceal shame or anxiety or to boost self esteem: by demeaning others, the abuser him/herself feels empowered{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}.

Researchers have identified other risk factors such as quickness to [[anger]] and use of force, [[addiction]] to aggressive behaviors, mistaking others' actions as hostile, concern with preserving [[self image]], and engaging in obsessive or rigid actions.&lt;ref name=vari2&gt;''Areas of Expert Agreement on Identification of School Bullies and Victims'', Hazler, R. J., Carney, J. V., Green, S., Powell, R., &amp; Jolly, L. S. (1997). School Psychology International, 18, 3-12.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bullying may also be "tradition" in settings where an age group or higher rank feels superior than lowerclassmen, such as in the Russian Army where conscripts in their second year of service typically bully and control first year conscripts.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}

It is often suggested that bullying behavior has its origin in childhood:

:"If aggressive behaviour is not challenged in childhood, there is a danger that it may become habitual.  Indeed, there is research evidence, to indicate that bullying during childhood puts children at risk of criminal behaviour and domestic violence in adulthood."&lt;ref name=tcd&gt;[http://www.abc.tcd.ie/ ''Anti-Bullying Center'' Trinity College, Dublin],&lt;/ref&gt;

Bullying does not necessarily involve criminality or physical violence. For example, bullying often operates through [[psychological abuse]] or [[Insult|verbal abuse]].{{Or|date=August 2009}}

Bullying can often be associated with [[street gangs]], especially at school.{{Or|date=August 2009}}

==History of bullying==

High-level forms of violence such as assault and murder usually receive most media attention, but lower-level forms of violence such as bullying, has only in recent years started to be addressed by researchers, parents and guardians and authority figures (Whitted &amp; Dupper, 2005).

It is only in recent years that bullying has been recognised and recorded as a separate and distinct offence, but there have been well documented cases that were recorded in a different context. The Fifth Volume of the Newgate Calendar &lt;ref&gt;[http://tarlton.law.utexas.edu/lpop/etext/completenewgate.htm Complete Newgate Calendar] Tarlton Law Library
The University of Texas School of Law &lt;/ref&gt; contains at least one example where Eton Scholars George Alexander Wood and Alexander Wellesley Leith were charged, at Aylesbury Assizes, with killing and slaying the Hon. F. Ashley Cooper on [[February 28]], [[1825]] in an incident that would now, surely be described as "lethal [[hazing]]"&lt;ref&gt;[http://tarlton.law.utexas.edu/lpop/etext/newgate5/woodg.htm GEORGE ALEXANDER WOOD AND ALEXANDER WELLESLEY LEITH] The Complete Newgate Calendar Volume V, Tarlton Law Library
The University of Texas School of Law&lt;/ref&gt;. The Newgate calendar contains several other examples that, while not as distinct, could be considered indicative of situations of bullying.

==Types of bullying==
===School bullying===
[[File:School bullying laws in the United States.svg|right|thumb|Some states in the United States have implemented laws to address school bullying.{{legend|#000080|Law prohibits bullying of students based on sexual orientation and gender identity}} {{legend|#0066FF|Law prohibits bullying of students based on sexual orientation}} {{legend|#AACCFF|School regulation or ethical code for teachers that address bullying of students based on sexual orientation}}
{{legend|#FFD42A|Law prohibits bullying in school but lists no categories of protection}}
{{legend|#D40000|No statewide law that specifically prohibits bullying in schools}}]]
{{Main|School bullying}}
In schools, bullying occurs in all areas of school. It can occur in nearly any part in or around the school building, though it more often occurs in [[Physical education|PE]], [[Recess (break)|recess]], [[hallway]]s, bathrooms, on [[school bus]]es and waiting for buses, classes that require group work and/or after school activities. Bullying in school sometimes consists of a group of students taking advantage of or isolating one student in particular and gaining the loyalty of bystanders who want to avoid becoming the next victim.  These bullies taunt and tease their target before physically bullying the target. Targets of bullying in school are often pupils who are considered strange or different by their peers to begin with, making the situation harder for them to deal with.

Some children bully because they have been isolated, and they have a deep need for belonging, but they do not possess the social skills to effectively keep [[friend]]s (''see [[social rejection]]'').&lt;ref name=Williams&gt;Williams, K.D., Forgás, J.P. &amp; von Hippel, W. (Eds.) (2005). [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/184169424X ''The Social Outcast: Ostracism, Social Exclusion, Rejection, &amp; Bullying.''] Psychology Press: New York, NY.&lt;/ref&gt; "When you're miserable, you need something more miserable than yourself." This may explain the negative actions toward others that bullies exhibit.{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}} However, there is some research suggesting that a significant proportion of "normal" school children may not evaluate school-based violence (student-on-student victimization) as negatively or as being unacceptable as much as adults generally do and may even derive enjoyment from it. They may thus not see a reason to prevent it if it brings them joy on some level.&lt;ref&gt;Kerbs, J.J. &amp; Jolley, J.M. [http://www.springerlink.com/content/v5u762558723143x/ The Joy of Violence: What about Violence is Fun in Middle-School?] ''American Journal of Criminal Justice.'' Vol. 32, No. 1-2/ Oct. 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bullying can also be perpetrated by teachers and the school system itself: There is an inherent power differential in the system that can easily predispose to subtle or covert abuse ([[relational aggression]] or [[passive aggression]]), humiliation, or exclusion — even while maintaining overt commitments to anti-bullying policies.&lt;ref&gt;Garbarino, J. &amp; de Lara, E. (2003). [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0743228995 ''And Words CAN Hurt Forever: How to Protect Adolescents from Bullying, Harassment, and Emotional Violence.''] The Free Press: New York NY.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Whitted, K.S. (2005). [http://proquest.umi.com/pqdlink?Ver=1&amp;Exp=12-10-2012&amp;FMT=7&amp;DID=990282831&amp;RQT=309&amp;attempt=1 ''Student reports of physical and psychological maltreatment in schools: An under-explored aspect of student victimization in schools.''] University of Tennessee.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Whitted, K. S. &amp; Dupper, D. R. [http://eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/custom/portlets/recordDetails/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=EJ785643&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=EJ785643 Do Teachers Bully Students?: Findings from a Survey of Students in an Alternative Education Setting.] ''Education and Urban Society'', 2008, 40(3), 329-341.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[School shootings]] are a bullying-related phenomenon that receive an enormous amount of media attention. An investigation undertaken by the [[United States Secret Service]] found that in over 2/3 of cases, attackers in school shooting incidents "felt persecuted, bullied, threatened, attacked, or injured by others prior to the incident" and discredits the idea that school shooters are "loners" who "just snap". Though observing that, "clearly, not every child who is bullied in school presents a risk for targeted violence in school", the investigation report states that, "a number of attackers had experienced bullying and harassment that was longstanding and severe.  In those cases, the experience of bullying appeared to play a major role in motivating the attack at school". The report also observes "in a number of cases, attackers described experienced of being bullied in terms that approached torment". The report concluded that, "(t)hat bullying played a major role in a number of these school shootings should strongly support ongoing efforts to combat bullying in American schools".&lt;ref&gt;Vossekuil, B., Reddy, M., Fein, R.; Borum, R.; &amp; Modzeleski, W. (2000).  [http://www.ustreas.gov/usss/ntac/ntac_ssi_report.pdf USSS Safe School Initiative: An Interim Report on the Prevention of Targeted Violence in Schools], Washington, DC: US Secret Service National Threat Assessment Center.&lt;/ref&gt; See also &lt;ref&gt; Fein, R.A., Vossekuil, B., Pollack, W., Borum, R., Reddy, M.,&amp; Modzeleski, W. Threat assessment in schools: A guide to managing threatening situations and creating safe school climates. U.S. Department of Education and U.S. Secret Service, May, 2002. &lt;/ref&gt;

Anti-bullying programs are designed to teach students cooperation, as well as training peer moderators in [[intervention]] and [[dispute resolution]] techniques, as a form of [[peer support]].{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

American victims and their families have [[legal recourse]], such as suing a school or teacher for failure to adequately supervise, racial or gender [[discrimination]], or other [[civil rights]] violations.  Special education students who are victimized may sue a school or school board under the [[Americans with Disabilities Act|ADA]] or [[Section 504]]. In addition, the victims of some school shootings have sued both the shooters' families and the schools.&lt;ref&gt;Brownstein, A. [http://www.thefreelibrary.com/The+bully+pulpit:+post-Columbine+harassment+victims+take+schools+to...-a097175612 The Bully Pulpit: Post-Columbine, Harassment Victims Take School To Court.] ''TRIAL - the Journal of the Association of Trial Lawyers of America'', December 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Workplace bullying===
{{Main|Workplace bullying}}
According to the Workplace Bullying and Trauma Institute workplace bullying is "''repeated, health-harming mistreatment, verbal abuse, or conduct which is threatening, humiliating, intimidating, or sabotage that interferes with work or some combination of the three''."&lt;ref name=namiedef&gt;Namie, Gary and Ruth [http://www.workplacebullying.org/targets/problem/definition.html Workplace Bullying Institute Definition]&lt;/ref&gt; Statistics show that bullying is 3 times as prevalent as illegal [[discrimination]] and at least 1,600 times as prevalent as workplace [[violence]]. Statistics also show that while only one employee in every 10,000 becomes a victim of workplace violence, one in six experiences bullying at work.  Bullying is a little more common than [[sexual harassment]] but not [[verbal abuse]] which occurs more than bullying.

Unlike the more physical form of [[school bullying]], workplace bullying often takes place within the established rules and policies of the organization and society. Such actions are not necessarily illegal and may not even be against the firm's regulations; however, the damage to the targeted employee and to workplace morale is obvious.

Particularly when perpetrated by a group, workplace bullying is sometimes known as [[mobbing]]. It can also be known as "career assassination" in political circles.

===Cyberbullying===
{{Main|Cyber-bullying}}
According to Canadian educator Bill Belsey, it:

{{quote|...involves the use of information and communication technologies such as e-mail, cell phone and pager text messages, instant messaging, defamatory personal Web sites, blogs, online games and defamatory online personal polling Web sites, to support deliberate, repeated, and hostile behaviour by an individual or group, that is intended to harm others.|Cyberbullying: An Emerging Threat to the Always On Generation&lt;ref name=cyber2&gt;''Belsey, W [http://www.cyberbullying.ca/pdf/Cyberbullying_Article_by_Bill_Belsey.pdf Cyberbullying: An Emerging Threat to the Always On Generation]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Bullies will even create blogs to intimidate victims worldwide.&lt;ref name=cyber&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4912766.stm|title=Striking back at the cyberbullies|author=Page, Chris|publisher=BBC News|date=2006-04-16|accessdate=2009-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political bullying===
{{Main|Jingoism}}
[[Jingoism]] occurs when one country imposes its will on another. This is normally done with military force or threats. With threats, it is common to ensure that aid and grants will not be given to the smaller country or that the smaller country will not be allowed to join a trading organization. Often [[political corruption]]s, [[coup d'état]]s, and [[Kleptocracy|kleptocracies]] are the solution and response to the countries being bullied.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

===Military bullying===
In 2000, the UK [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] (MOD) defined bullying as: “...the use of physical strength or the abuse of authority to intimidate or victimize others, or to give unlawful punishments.”&lt;ref name=mod&gt;''The Values and Standards of the British Army – A Guide to Soldiers'', Ministry of Defence, UK March 2000, paragraph 23.&lt;/ref&gt;  A review of a number of deaths by suicide at [[Princess Royal Barracks, Deepcut]] by Nicholas Blake [[Queen's Counsel|QC]] indicated that whilst a culture of bullying existed during the mid to late 1990s many of the issues were being addressed as a result of the [[Defence Training Review]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deepcutreview.org.uk/Home/home/Home Deepcut Review] accessed 14 Jan 07&lt;/ref&gt;

Some argue that this behaviour should be allowed because of a general academic consensus that "soldiering" is different from other occupations. Soldiers expected to risk their lives should, according to them, develop strength of body and spirit to accept bullying.&lt;ref name=diff&gt;''Social Psychology of the Individual Soldier'', Jean M. Callaghan and Franz Kernic 2003  Armed Forces and International Security: Global Trends and Issues, Lit Verlag, Munster&lt;/ref&gt;

In some countries, ritual [[hazing]] among recruits has been tolerated and even lauded as a [[rite of passage]] that builds character and toughness; while in others, systematic bullying of lower-ranking, young or physically slight recruits may in fact be encouraged by military policy, either tacitly or overtly (see ''[[dedovschina]]''). Also, the Russian army usually have older/more experienced candidates abusing - kicking or punching - less experienced soldiers.&lt;ref name=bbcmil&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/4477960.stm ''Military bullying a global problem''], BBC, UK Monday, 28 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hazing===
{{Main|Hazing|Ragging}}
Hazing is an often ritualistic test which may constitute harassment, abuse, or humiliation with requirements to perform meaningless tasks; sometimes as a way of initiation into a social group. The term can refer to either physical (sometimes violent) or mental (possibly degrading) practices. It is a subjective matter where to draw to line between 'normal' hazing (somewhat abusive) and a mere [[rite of passage]] (essentially bonding; proponents may argue they can coincide), and there is a gray area where exactly the other side passes over into sheer degrading, even harmful abuse that should not even be tolerated if accepted voluntarily (serious but avoidable accidents do still happen; even deliberate abuse with similar grave medical consequences occurs, in some traditions even rather often). Furthermore, as it must be a ritual ''initiation'', a different social context may mean a same treatment is technically hazing for some, not for others, e.g. a [[line-crossing ceremony]] when passing the equator at sea is hazing for the sailor while the extended (generally voluntary, more playful) application to passengers is not.

Hazing has been reported in a variety of social contexts, including:
*Sports teams
*Academic [[fraternities]] and [[sororities]] (see [[fraternities and sororities#Hazing issues|fraternities and sororities]])These practices are not limited to American schools. Swedish students undergo a similar bonding period, known as nollningen, in which all members of the entering class participate.
*College and universities in general.
*Associated groups, like fan clubs, school bands
*Secret societies and even certain [[service club]]s, or rather their local sections (such as some modern US [[Freemasonry|Freemasons]]; not traditional masonic lodges)
*Similarly various other competitive sports teams or clubs, even 'soft' and non-competitive ones (such as arts)
*The armed forces — e.g., in the U.S., hard hazing practices from [[World War I]] [[boot camp]]s were introduced into colleges. In [[Poland]] army hazing is called Polish ''fala'' "wave" adopted pre-World War I from non-Polish armies. In the [[Russian army]] (formerly the [[Red Army]]) hazing is called "[[Dedovshchina]]".
*Police forces (often with a [[paramilitary]] tradition)
*Rescue services, such as lifeguards (also drilled for operations in military style)
*In workplaces
*Inmate hazing is also common at confinement facilities around the world, including frequent reports of beatings and sexual assaults by fellow inmates.

Hazing is considered a [[felony]] in several US states, and anti-hazing legislation has been proposed in other states.

==See also==
{{columns-list|2|
*[[Abuse]]
*[[Aggression]]
*[[Discrimination]]
*[[Extortion]]
*[[List of books on bullying]]
*[[Oppression]]
*[[Organized crime]]
*[[Passive aggression]]
*[[Posttraumatic stress disorder]] (PTSD)
*[[Protection racket]]
*[[Psychological manipulation]]
*[[Psychological trauma]]
*[[Relational aggression]]
*[[Sexual harassment]]
*[[Social defeat]]
*[[Social rejection]]
*[[Taunt]]
*[[Teasing]]
*[[Torture]]
*[[School shooting]]
*[[Workplace bullying]]
}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
&lt;!--===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================--&gt;
&lt;!--| DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF |--&gt;
&lt;!--| LINKS. If you think that your link might be useful, do not add it here, |--&gt;
&lt;!--| but put it on this article's discussion page first or submit your link  |--&gt;
&lt;!--| to the appropriate category at the Open Directory Project (www.dmoz.org)|--&gt;
&lt;!--| and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.             |--&gt;
&lt;!--|                                                                         |--&gt;
&lt;!--|           Links that have not been verified WILL BE DELETED.            |--&gt;
&lt;!--|  See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details    |--&gt;
&lt;!--===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================--&gt;
* [http://www.bullying.org Bullying.org]
* [http://www.bullyfreezone.co.uk Bully Free Zone (UK)]
* [http://www.bullyingnoway.com.au/ Bullying. No Way! (Australian Education Authorities)]
* [http://www.dfes.gov.uk/bullying Bullying in schools (UK - schools)]
* [http://www.kickbully.com/ Bullying in the Workplace]

&lt;!-- Article in Spanish wikipedia does not reflect what bullying is

--&gt;

{{abuse}}
[[Category:Bullying]]
[[Category:Social psychology]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Aggression]]
[[Category:Injustice]]
[[Category:Persecution]]

[[cs:Šikana]]
[[cy:Bwlio]]
[[de:Schikane]]
[[es:Acoso escolar]]
[[eo:Ĉikanado]]
[[fr:Bullying]]
[[ko:집단 따돌림]]
[[it:Bullismo]]
[[lt:Patyčios]]
[[nl:Pesten (gedrag)]]
[[ja:いじめ]]
[[pt:Bullying]]
[[ru:Буллинг]]
[[simple:Bullying]]
[[sk:Šikanovanie]]
[[fi:Kiusaaminen]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>