<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041014181007|6872017" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="432459" pageid="432459" ns="0" title="Bullying"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-26T10:00:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''bully''' is an individual who tends to [[torment]] others.  Bullying is generally seen as a form of [[harassment]] typically performed by a [[child]] who is older, stronger, or otherwise more powerful socially, upon weaker [[peer]]s.  Even when not referring to children (for example, in [[college]] [[hazing]], or [[workplace]] harassment), the power structure is typically evident between the bully and [[victim]].  At times, the bully's power depends only upon the perception of the victim, with the victim being too [[intimidation|intimidated]] to make an effective resistance.  Modern schools try to discourage bullying, with programs designed to teach students cooperation, as well as training peer [[moderator]]s in [[intervention]] techniques.

== Bullying ==

Bullying is when someone keeps doing or saying things to have power over another person.
Some of the ways they bully other people are by: calling them names, saying or writing nasty things about them, leaving them out of activities, not talking to them, threatening them, making them feel uncomfortable or scared, taking or damaging their things, hitting or kicking them, or making them do things they don't want to do. 

Bullying can occur in schools, families and in workplaces. Both school and workplace bullying has come increasingly to public attention and is now one of the most contentious issues in the [[OH&amp;S]] arena.

There are few localities that are governed by legislation which specifically targets workplace bullying.  This is because law-makers fear that those rules could be used as leverage in other industrial or interpersonal matters. 

==Effects of bullying==

Persistent bullying may have a number of effects on an individual, and in the workplace can affect the working environment. Some of these effects are: 

* [[Clinical depression|Depression]]
* [[Posttraumatic stress disorder]]
* [[Anxiety]]
* Loss of [[self esteem]]
* Loss of productivity
* Loss of morale
* Relationship problems
* Drug and alcohol abuse
* Accidents in the workplace and schoolyard
* [[Suicide]]
* [[Inferiority complex]]
* Legal action

==External links==
* [http://www.bullying.org Bullying.org] "Where you are NOT alone!" (the number one Web site about bullying in the world)
* [http://www.cyberbullying.ca "Always On? Always Aware!"] the world's first and only Web site about the emerging issue of cyberbullying
* http://www.bullyonline.org/schoolbully   Bully online (USA - schools)
* http://www.education.unisa.edu.au/bullying   Bullying in schools (Australia - schools)
* http://www.bullying.co.uk   Bullying online (UK - schools)
* http://www.police.govt.nz/service/yes/nobully   No Bully (NZ - schools)
* http://www.bullyonline.org   Bully online (UK - workplaces)
* http://www.workplacebullying.com   Workplace Bullying.com (USA - workplaces)
* http://www.sangrea.net/bully   Bullying - what can be done about it? (Australia - workplaces)
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/2002-3/bullying.htm Bullying]
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/2003-4/bullying.html Bullying in Early Adolescence: The Role of the Peer Group]
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/1997-4/bullying.htm Bullying in Schools]
** [http://nielsenhayden.com/makinglight/archives/003756.html The story of J. Daniel Scruggs]
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/2003-1/bullying.htm Preventing Bullying]
* [http://www.yaerd.org Young Adults Educating Responsible Drinking]
See also:  [[Bully_(movie)]], [[Teasing]]

[[ja:&amp;#12356;&amp;#12376;&amp;#12417;]]
[[es:toril]]
[[nl:pesten]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>