<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101117225215|397393376" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="432459" pageid="432459" ns="0" title="Bullying"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-17T23:03:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-vandalism|small=yes}}{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Expert-subject-multiple|Psychology|Sociology|date=January 2010}}
{{Incomplete|article|date=January 2010}}
[[File:Bullying Irfe.jpg|220px|thumb|Bullying is detrimental to students’ well-being and development.&lt;ref name=nces-2005-310/&gt;]]
[[File:Bullying en IRFE, 7° Básico B, 2007.ogg|thumb|Students knocking themselves.]]
'''Bullying''' is a form of [[abuse]]. It involves repeated acts over time attempting to create or enforce one person's (or group's) power over another person (or group) , thus an "imbalance of power".&lt;ref&gt;(U.S. Dept. of Justice, Fact Sheet #FS-200127)&lt;/ref&gt;  
The "imbalance of power" may be social power and/or physical power. The victim of bullying is sometimes referred to as a target.  Bullying types of behavior are often rooted in a would-be bully's inability to empathize with those whom he or she would target. 

Bullying consists of three basic types of abuse &amp;ndash; [[Psychological abuse|emotional]], [[Verbal abuse|verbal]] and [[Physical abuse|physical]]. It typically involves subtle methods of [[coercion]] such as [[psychological manipulation]]. Bullying can be defined in many different ways. Although the [[United Kingdom|UK]] currently has no legal definition of bullying,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.campus.manchester.ac.uk/equalityanddiversity/harassmentdiscriminationandbullying/ Harassment, Discrimination and Bullying Policy] &amp;ndash; [[University of Manchester]]&lt;/ref&gt; some [[United States|US]] states have laws against it.&lt;ref&gt;At least 15 states have passed laws
addressing bullying among school children. [http://72.14.205.104/search?q=cache:ao8az0gkKqMJ:stopbullyingnow.hrsa.gov/HHS_PSA/pdfs/SBN_Tip_6.pdf+bullying+legislation&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=3&amp;gl=us&amp;client=firefox-a Google Search]&lt;/ref&gt;

Bullying in school and the workplace is also referred to as peer abuse.&lt;ref&gt;Bennett, Elizabeth ''Peer Abuse Know More: Bullying From a Psychological Perspective'' (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert W. Fuller]] has analyzed bullying in the context of [[rankism]].

Bullying can occur in any context in which human beings interact with each other. This includes [[School bullying|school]], [[church (building)|church]], [[family]], the [[Workplace bullying|workplace]], [[home]] and [[neighborhood]]s. It is even a common [[Immigration|push factor]] in [[human migration|migration]]. Bullying can exist between [[social group]]s, [[social class]]es and even between countries (see [[Jingoism]]).  In fact on an international scale, perceived or real imbalances of power between nations, in both economic systems and in treaty systems, are often cited as some of the primary causes of both World War I and World War II. 
&lt;ref name = "power_imbalance_caused_wwI"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.sparknotes.com/history/european/1871-1914/section8.rhtml
| title= The Balance of Power in Europe (1871-1914)
| accessdate = 2010-10-30}} Description of how an imbalance of power in Europe precipitated WWI.
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "peace_consequences"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2005
| url = http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/15776
| title= The Economic Consequences of the Peace 
| accessdate = 2010-10-30}} Describes likely connection between imbalanced Treaty of Versailles and World War II
&lt;/ref&gt;
Put simply, historically and from this perspective, certain international 'bullying' between nations is seen as having resulted in at least two very major and costly international wars.

==Definition==
[[Image:Warning signs at CHS.jpg|thumb|200px|right|Some schools with bullying problems have addressed the issue by adding [[CCTV]] cameras.]]
Bullying is an act of repeated aggressive behavior in order to intentionally hurt another person, physically or mentally. Bullying is characterized by an individual behaving in a certain way to gain power over another person.&lt;ref&gt;Besag, V. E. (1989) Bullies and Victims in Schools. Milton Keynes, England: Open University Press&lt;/ref&gt;

Norwegian researcher Dan Olweus defines bullying as when a person is &lt;blockquote&gt;"exposed, repeatedly and over time, to negative actions on the part of one or more other persons." He defines negative action as "when a person intentionally inflicts injury or discomfort upon another person, through physical contact, through words or in other ways".&lt;ref name=olweusdef&gt;Olweus, D., [http://www.olweus.org/public/bullying.page Olweus.org]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==General==
Bullying behavior may include name calling, [[Verbal abuse|verbal]] or written abuse, exclusion from activities, exclusion from social situations, [[physical abuse]], or [[coercion]].&lt;ref name=Whitted&gt;Whitted, K.S. &amp; Dupper, D.R. (2005). Best Practices for Preventing or Reducing Bullying in Schools. ''Children and Schools'', Vol. 27, No. 3, July 2005, pp. 167-175(9).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carey, T.A. (2003) Improving the success of anti-bullying intervention programs: A tool for matching programs with purposes. International Journal of Reality Therapy, 23(2), 16-23&lt;/ref&gt; Bullies may behave this way to be perceived as popular or tough or to get attention. They may bully out of [[jealousy]] or be acting out because they themselves are bullied.&lt;ref&gt;Crothers, L. M. &amp; Levinson, E. M. (2004, Fall). Assessment of Bullying: A review of methods and instruments. Journal of Counseling &amp; Development, 82(4), 496–503.&lt;/ref&gt;

USA National Center for Education Statistics suggests that bullying can be classified into two categories: Direct bullying, and indirect bullying which is also known as social aggression.&lt;ref name=nces-2005-310&gt;[http://nces.ed.gov/pubs2005/2005310.pdf ''Student Reports of Bullying''], Results From the 2001 School Crime Supplement to the National Crime Victimization Survey, US National Center for Education Statistics&lt;/ref&gt;

Ross states that direct bullying involves a great deal of physical [[aggression]] such as shoving and poking, throwing things, slapping, choking, punching and kicking, beating, stabbing, pulling hair, scratching, biting, scraping and pinching.&lt;ref name=ross&gt;Ross, P. N. (1998). Arresting violence: A resource guide for schools and their communities. Toronto: Ontario Public School Teachers' Federation.&lt;/ref&gt;

He also suggests that social aggression or indirect bullying is characterized by threatening the victim into [[social isolation]]. This isolation is achieved through a wide variety of techniques, including spreading [[gossip]], refusing to socialize with the victim, bullying other people who wish to socialize with the victim, and [[Criticism|criticizing]] the victim's manner of dress and other socially-significant markers (including the victim's race, religion, disability, etc).
Ross&lt;ref name=ross/&gt; outlines other forms of indirect bullying which are more subtle and more likely to be verbal, such as name calling, the [[silent treatment]], arguing others into submission, [[Psychological manipulation|manipulation]], gossip/false gossip, [[lie]]s, [[rumor]]s/false rumors, [[staring]], giggling, laughing at the victim, saying certain words that trigger a reaction from a past event, and mocking. The children's charity [[Act Against Bullying]] was set up in 2003 to help children who were victims of this type of bullying by researching and publishing coping skills.

==Effects of bullying on those who are targeted==
The effects of bullying can be serious and even fatal. Mona O’Moore of the Anti-Bullying Centre at Trinity College in Dublin, has written, "There is a growing body of research which indicates that individuals, whether child or adult, who are persistently subjected to abusive behavior are at risk of stress related illness which can sometimes lead to suicide."&lt;ref name=tcd/&gt;
Those who have been the targets of bullying can suffer from long term emotional and behavioral problems. Bullying can cause [[loneliness]], [[Depression (mood)|depression]], [[anxiety]], lead to low [[self-esteem]] and increased susceptibility to illness.&lt;ref name=Williams&gt;Williams, K. D., Forgás, J. P. &amp; von Hippel, W. (Eds.) (2005). [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/184169424X ''The Social Outcast: Ostracism, Social Exclusion, Rejection, &amp; Bullying.''] Psychology Press: New York, NY.&lt;/ref&gt;

The National Conference of State Legislatures said:
:''"In 2002, a report released by the U.S. Secret Service concluded that bullying played a significant role in many school shootings and that efforts should be made to eliminate bullying behavior."''&lt;ref name=ncsl&gt;[http://www.ncsl.org/programs/educ/SchBullying.htm ''School Bullying.''] National Conference of State Legislatures, Washington, D.C. (retrieved 7 December 2007).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Suicide===
There is a strong link between bullying and [[suicide]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Kim YS, Leventhal B |title=Bullying and suicide. A review |journal=International Journal of Adolescent Medicine and Health |volume=20 |issue=2 |pages=133–54 |year=2008 |pmid=18714552}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bullying leads to several suicides every year. It is estimated that between 15 and 25 children commit suicide every year in the UK alone, because they are being bullied.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.coastkid.org/si-sob.html Statistics on bullying]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characteristics of bullies and 'bully lieutenants'==
Research indicates that adults who bully have personalities that are [[authoritarian]], combined with a strong need to control or [[dominance (biology)|dominate]].&lt;ref name=brodsky&gt;''The Harassed Worker'', Brodsky, C. (1976), [[D.C. Heath and Company]], Lexington, Massachusetts.&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been suggested that a prejudicial view of subordinates can be particular a risk factor.&lt;ref name=ashforth&gt;''Petty tyranny in organizations '', Ashforth, Blake, Human Relations, Vol. 47, No. 7, 755-778 (1994)&lt;/ref&gt;

Further studies have shown that [[envy]] and [[resentment]] may be motives for bullying.&lt;ref name=vari&gt;''Bullying and emotional abuse in the workplace. International perspectives in research and practice'', Einarsen, S., Hoel, H., Zapf, D., &amp; Cooper, C. L. (Eds.)(2003), Taylor &amp; Francis, London.&lt;/ref&gt;  Research on the [[self-esteem]] of bullies has produced equivocal results.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Pollastri AR, Cardemil EV, O'Donnell EH |title=Self-Esteem in Pure Bullies and Bully/Victims: A Longitudinal Analysis |journal=Journal of Interpersonal Violence |volume= 25|issue= 8|pages= 1489–502|year=2009 |month=December |pmid=20040706 |doi=10.1177/0886260509354579}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bkn&gt;{{Cite journal|first1=George M. |last1=Batsche |first2=Howard M. |last2=Knoff |year=1994 |title=Bullies and their victims: Understanding a pervasive problem in the schools |journal=School Psychology Review |volume=23 |issue=2 |pages=165–175 |url=http://faculty.buffalostate.edu/hennesda/BULLIES_AND_THEIR_VICTIMS.doc}}&lt;/ref&gt; While some bullies are [[arrogant]] and [[narcissistic]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bullyonline.org/workbully/faq.htm Answers to frequently asked questions about workplace bullying]&lt;/ref&gt; others can use bullying as a tool to conceal [[shame]] or [[anxiety]] or to boost self esteem: by demeaning others, the abuser him/herself feels empowered.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/doc/7882659/Presentation-Bullying Presentation Bullying]&lt;/ref&gt;

Researchers have identified other risk factors such as [[Depression (mood)|depression]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Patterson G |title=The bully as victim? |journal=Paediatric Nursing |volume=17 |issue=10 |pages=27–30 |year=2005 |month=December |pmid=16372706}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[personality disorders]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Kumpulainen K |title=Psychiatric conditions associated with bullying |journal=International Journal of Adolescent Medicine and Health |volume=20 |issue=2 |pages=121–32 |year=2008 |pmid=18714551}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as quickness to [[anger]] and use of force, [[Behavioral addiction|addiction]] to [[Aggression|aggressive behaviors]], mistaking others' actions as hostile, concern with preserving [[self image]], and engaging in obsessive or rigid actions.&lt;ref name=vari2&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1177/0143034397181001 |title=Areas of Expert Agreement on Identification of School Bullies and Victims |year=1997 |last1=Hazlerr |first1=R. J. |last2=Carney |first2=J. V. |last3=Green |first3=S. |last4=Powell |first4=R. |last5=Jolly |first5=L. S. |journal=School Psychology International |volume=18 |pages=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; A combination of these factors may also be cause of this behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1016/S0191-8869(97)00145-1 |title=The relationship among bullying, victimization, depression, anxiety, and aggression in elementary school children |year=1998 |last1=Craig |first1=W.M.|journal=Personality and Individual Differences |volume=24 |issue=1 |pages=123–130}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is often suggested that bullying behavior has its origin in childhood.  As a person who is inclined to act as a bully matures, his or her related behavior patterns will often also mature.  Schoolyard pranks and 'rough-housing' may mature into more subtle, yet equally effective adult level activities such as administrative end-plays, well planned and orchestrated attempts at character assassination, or other less obvious, yet equally forceful forms of coercion.
{{Quote|"If aggressive behaviour is not challenged in childhood, there is a danger that it may become habitual. Indeed, there is research evidence, to indicate that bullying during childhood puts children at risk of criminal behaviour and [[domestic violence]] in adulthood."  &lt;ref name=tcd&gt;[http://www.abc.tcd.ie/ ''Anti-Bullying Center'' Trinity College, Dublin],&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Bullies may bully because they themselves have been the victim of bullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Fromm, Erich |title=The anatomy of human destructiveness |publisher=Holt, Rinehart and Winston |location=New York |year=1973 |pages= |isbn=0-03-007596-3}}{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1667130&amp;referer=brief_results ''Man Against Himself by Karl A. Menninger'']{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldcat.org/search?q=Neurotic+Styles+by+David+Shapiro&amp;qt=owc_search ''Neurotic Styles by David Shapiro'']{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also evidence that bullies have a much higher likelihood to be [[incarcerated]] in the future.&lt;ref&gt;[http://heinonline.org/HOL/Page?collection=journals&amp;handle=hein.journals/cjrr19&amp;id=159 {{cite journal |doi= |title=Developmental Crime Prevention |year=1995 |last1=Tremblay |first1=R. E. |last2=Craig |first2=W.M. |journal=Crime and Justice: A Review of Research |pages=p.151}}]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characteristics of typical bystanders==
Often bullying takes place in the presence of a large group of relatively uninvolved bystanders.  In many cases, it is the bully's ability to create the illusion that he or she has the support of the majority present, that instills the fear of 'speaking out' in protestation of the bullying activities being observed by the group.  Unless the 'bully mentality' is effectively challenged in any given group in its earlier stages, often the 'bully mentality' becomes an accepted norm within the group.  &lt;ref name = "bystander attitudes"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.athealth.com/Consumer/issues/BulliesVictimsBystanders3.html
| title= Bullies, Victims, and Bystanders- Bystanders
| accessdate = 2010-11-17}} Description of typical attitudes of bystanders to bullying.
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "bystander programs"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2009/01/090125193150.htm
| title= New Tactics To Tackle Bystander’s Role In Bullying
| accessdate = 2010-11-17}} Science Daily website reviews effectiveness of several bullying-bystander awareness programs.
&lt;/ref&gt;
In such groups where the 'bully mentality' has been allowed to become a dominant factor in the group environment, a steady stream of injustices and abuses often becomes a regular and predictable group experience.  Such a toxic environment often remains as the status-quo of the group for an extended period of time, until somehow the bullying-cycle should eventually come to an end.  Bystanders to bullying activities are often unable to recognize the true cost that silence regarding the bullying activities has to both the individual and to the group.  A certain inability to fully empathize is also usually present in the typical bystander, but to a lesser degree than in the bully.  The reversal of a 'bully mentality' within a group is usually an effort which requires much time, energy, careful planning, coordination with others, and usually the undertaking of a certain 'risk'.  

It is the general unwillingness of bystanders to expend these types of energies and to undertake these types of risks that bullies often rely upon in order to maintain their monopolies of power.  Until or unless at least one individual who has at least some abilities to work with others, opts to expend whatever energies may be needed to reverse the 'bully mentality' of the group, the 'bully mentality' is often perpetuated within a group for months, years or even decades.&lt;ref name = "petty tyrant-text"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/419/petty-tyrant
| title= Petty Tyrant: Text intro: NPR documentary (see audio link below)
| accessdate = 2010-11-17}} Exposé of workplace bullying in Schenectady NY school district.  An in depth view of how a workplace bully rose to power and how he fell.  Detailed discussion of how bystanders coerced into allowing workplace bullying.
&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name = "petty tyrant-audio"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.thisamericanlife.org/sites/all/play_music/play_full.php?play=419&amp;podcast=1
| title= Petty Tyrant: Audio link
| accessdate = 2010-11-17}} Audio link to 'Petty Tyrant' NPR documentary.
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characteristics of likely targets of chronic bullying==
While on the surface, chronic bullying may appear to be simply the actions of an 'aggressor' (or aggressors) perpetrated upon an unwilling 'targeted individual' (or individuals), on a certain deeper level, for it to succeed, the bullying-cycle must also be viewed as necessarily including a certain chronic inadequate response on the part of the target (or targets).  That is, a response that is seen by both the bully and the target as insufficient to prevent the chronic bullying-cycle from repeating itself between the given individuals.  Those individuals or groups who are capable of reacting to initial bullying attempts in ways that tend to sufficiently discourage potential bullies from repeated attempts, are naturally relatively exempt from this destructive cycle.  Those individuals or groups who most readily react to stressful situations by perceiving themselves as 'victims' tend to make the most suitable candidates for becoming the 'targets' of chronic bullying.&lt;ref name = "bully-victim-predictors"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.micheleborba.com/blog/2010/09/22/problem-solving-to-prevent-bullying/
| title= Problem Solving to Prevent Bullying
| accessdate = 2010-10-31}} Discussion of typical psychological profiles of both bullies and their targets.
&lt;/ref&gt;

Typically the bullying-cycle must include both an act of aggression on the part of a potential bully, and a response by a potential target that is perceived by both as a certain sign of submission.  The cycle is only set in motion when both of these two essential elements are present.  Once both of these two elements manifest themselves, the bullying cycle often proceeds to feed on itself over time, and may last for months, years, or even decades.   The cycle is most easily broken at its initial onset, however it can also be broken at any later point in its progression by simply removing either one of its two essential ingredients.  While group involvement may seem to complicate bullying activities, the act remains an implied agreement in principal between the chief bully and the target that the one has 'submitted' to the other.  In the act of bullying the bully attempts to make a public statement to the effect of: 'See me and fear me, I am so powerful that I have the ability to inflict pain upon the intended target at the time and manner of my choice without having to pay any consequences.'  Should an intended target exhibit a 'defeated attitude' in response to chronic bullying, then the bullying is likely to continue.  Should the intended target respond with a clear attitude of self-confidence that somehow demonstrates that the bully's attempt to dominate is futile, then the bullying attempt will almost certainly quickly diminish or end all-together.
&lt;ref name = "nbc-on-jay-banks"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wzLukEtsgCA
| title= Jay Banks NBC TV-10 "STAMP Out Bullying"
| accessdate = 2010-10-31}} Youtube video of NBC report on Jay Banks' anti-bullying program, advising targets to "project self-confidence".
&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name = "jay-banks-youtube-homepage"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2010
| url = http://www.youtube.com/profile?user=jaybanksproductions#g/u
| title= Jay Banks Productions Youtube Homepage
| accessdate = 2010-10-31}} Compilation of anti-bullying videos by anti-bullying expert, Jay Banks
&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of bullying==
High-level forms of violence such as assault and murder usually receive most media attention, but lower-level forms of violence such as bullying has only in recent years started to be addressed by researchers, parents and guardians and authority figures.&lt;ref name=Whitted/&gt;

It is only in recent years that bullying has been recognised and recorded as a separate and distinct offence, but there have been well documented cases that were recorded in a different context. The Fifth Volume of the Newgate Calendar&lt;ref&gt;[http://tarlton.law.utexas.edu/lpop/etext/completenewgate.htm Complete Newgate Calendar] Tarlton Law Library
The University of Texas School of Law&lt;/ref&gt; contains at least one example where Eton Scholars George Alexander Wood and Alexander Wellesley Leith were charged, at Aylesbury Assizes, with killing and slaying the Hon. F. Ashley Cooper on February 28, 1825 in an incident that would now, surely be described as "lethal [[hazing]]."&lt;ref&gt;[http://tarlton.law.utexas.edu/lpop/etext/newgate5/woodg.htm George Alexander Wood and Alexander Wellesley Leith] The Complete Newgate Calendar Volume V, Tarlton Law Library
The University of Texas School of Law&lt;/ref&gt; The Newgate calendar contains several other examples that, while not as distinct, could be considered indicative of situations of bullying.

==Types of bullying==
===School bullying===
[[File:Rebecca1917version.jpg|220px|thumb|Physical bullying at school, as depicted in the film ''[[Rebecca of Sunnybrook Farm]]''.]]
[[File:School bullying laws in the United States.svg|right|thumb|Some states in the United States have implemented laws to address school bullying.{{legend|#000080|Law prohibits bullying of students based on sexual orientation and gender identity; bullying for other reasons is allowed}} {{legend|#0066FF|Law prohibits bullying of students based on sexual orientation only; bullying for other reasons is allowed}} {{legend|#AACCFF|School regulation or ethical code for teachers that address bullying of students based on sexual orientation}}
{{legend|#FFD42A|Law prohibits bullying in school but lists no specific categories of protection}}
{{legend|#D40000|No statewide law that specifically prohibits bullying in schools}}]]
{{Main|School bullying}}
In schools, bullying occurs in all areas of school. It can occur in nearly any part in or around the school building, though it more often occurs in [[Physical education|PE]], [[Recess (break)|recess]], [[hallway]]s, bathrooms, on [[school bus]]es and waiting for buses, classes that require group work and/or after school activities. Bullying in school sometimes consists of a group of students taking advantage of or isolating one student in particular and gaining the loyalty of bystanders who want to avoid becoming the next victim. These bullies taunt and tease their target before physically bullying the target. Targets of bullying in school are often pupils who are considered strange or different by their peers to begin with, making the situation harder for them to deal with.

One student or a group can bully another student or a group of students. Bystanders may participate or watch, sometimes out of fear of becoming the next victim. However, there is some research suggesting that a significant proportion of "normal" school children may not evaluate school-based violence (student-on-student victimization) as negatively or as being unacceptable as much as adults generally do, and may even derive enjoyment from it, and they may thus not see a reason to prevent it if it brings them joy on some level.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1007/s12103-007-9011-1 |title=The Joy of Violence: What about Violence is Fun in Middle-School? |year=2007 |last1=Kerbs |first1=John J. |last2=Jolley |first2=Jennifer M. |journal=American Journal of Criminal Justice |volume=32 |pages=12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bullying can also be perpetrated by teachers and the school system itself: There is an inherent power differential in the system that can easily predispose to subtle or covert abuse ([[relational aggression]] or [[passive aggression]]), [[humiliation]], or exclusion — even while maintaining overt commitments to anti-bullying policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Ellen deLara; Garbarino, James |title=And Words Can Hurt Forever: How to Protect Adolescents from Bullying, Harassment, and Emotional Violence |publisher=Free Press |location=New York |year=2003 |pages= |isbn=0-7432-2899-5}}{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Whitted, K.S. (2005). [http://proquest.umi.com/pqdlink?Ver=1&amp;Exp=12-10-2012&amp;FMT=7&amp;DID=990282831&amp;RQT=309&amp;attempt=1 ''Student reports of physical and psychological maltreatment in schools: An under-explored aspect of student victimization in schools.''] University of Tennessee.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1177/0013124507304487 |title=Do Teachers Bully Students?: Findings From a Survey of Students in an Alternative Education Setting |year=2007 |last1=Whitted |first1=K. S. |last2=Dupper |first2=D. R. |journal=Education and Urban Society |volume=40 |pages=329}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anti-bullying programs are designed to teach students cooperation, as well as training peer moderators in [[intervention]] and [[dispute resolution]] techniques, as a form of [[peer support]].{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

American victims and their families have [[legal recourse]], such as suing a school or teacher for failure to adequately supervise, racial or gender [[discrimination]], or other [[civil rights]] violations. Special education students who are victimized may sue a school or school board under the [[Americans with Disabilities Act|ADA]] or [[Section 504]]. In addition, the victims of some school shootings have sued both the shooters' families and the schools.&lt;ref&gt;Brownstein, A. [http://www.thefreelibrary.com/The+bully+pulpit:+post-Columbine+harassment+victims+take+schools+to...-a097175612 The Bully Pulpit: Post-Columbine, Harassment Victims Take School To Court.] ''TRIAL &amp;ndash; the Journal of the Association of Trial Lawyers of America'', December 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Workplace bullying===
{{Main|Workplace bullying}}
According to the Workplace Bullying and Trauma Institute workplace bullying is "''repeated, health-harming mistreatment, [[verbal abuse]], or conduct which is threatening, [[humiliating]], [[intimidating]], or [[sabotage]] that interferes with work or some combination of the three''."&lt;ref name=namiedef&gt;Namie, Gary and Ruth [http://www.workplacebullying.org/targets/problem/definition.html Workplace Bullying Institute Definition]&lt;/ref&gt; Statistics show that bullying is 3 times as prevalent as illegal [[discrimination]] and at least 1,600 times as prevalent as workplace [[violence]]. Statistics also show that while only one employee in every 10,000 becomes a victim of workplace violence, one in six experiences bullying at work. Bullying is a little more common than [[sexual harassment]] but not verbal abuse which occurs more than bullying.

Unlike the more physical form of [[school bullying]], workplace bullying often takes place within the established rules and policies of the organization and society. Such actions are not necessarily illegal and may not even be against the firm's regulations; however, the damage to the targeted employee and to workplace morale is obvious.

Particularly when perpetrated by a group, workplace bullying is sometimes known as [[mobbing]]. It can also be known as "career assassination" in political circles.

===Cyberbullying===
{{Main|Cyber-bullying}}
According to Canadian educator Bill Belsey, it:
{{quote|...involves the use of information and communication technologies such as e-mail, cell phone and pager text messages, instant messaging, defamatory personal Web sites, blogs, online games and defamatory online personal polling Web sites, to support deliberate, repeated, and hostile behaviour by an individual or group, that is intended to harm others.|Cyberbullying: An Emerging Threat to the Always On Generation&lt;ref name=cyber2&gt;''Belsey, W.; [http://www.cyberbullying.ca/pdf/Cyberbullying_Article_by_Bill_Belsey.pdf Cyberbullying: An Emerging Threat to the Always On Generation]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Bullies will even create blogs to intimidate victims worldwide.&lt;ref name=cyber&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4912766.stm|title=Striking back at the cyberbullies|author=Page, Chris|publisher=BBC News|date=2006-04-16|accessdate=2009-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political bullying===
{{Main|Jingoism}}
[[Jingoism]] occurs when one country imposes its will on another. This is normally done with military force or threats. With threats, it is common to ensure that aid and grants will not be given to the smaller country or that the smaller country will not be allowed to join a trading organization. Often [[political corruption]]s, [[coup d'état]]s, and [[Kleptocracy|kleptocracies]] are the solution and response to the countries being bullied.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

===Protection racket bullying===
One revenue generating scheme often employed by underworld figures is sometimes referred to as the "protection-racket" scheme.  In this scheme, local businesses are forced to regularly pay a local underworld figure a certain portion of their profits.  The alternative to paying such a 'protection-fee' to the local underworld figure is usually the threat of some form of costly vandalism, theft or even the bodily injury of the non-submitting business operator or his family.

===Military bullying===
In 2000, the UK [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] (MOD) defined bullying as: “...the use of physical strength or the [[abuse of authority]] to [[intimidate]] or [[Victimization|victimize]] others, or to give unlawful punishments.”&lt;ref name=mod&gt;''The Values and Standards of the British Army – A Guide to Soldiers'', Ministry of Defence, UK March 2000, paragraph 23.&lt;/ref&gt; A review of a number of deaths by suicide at [[Princess Royal Barracks, Deepcut]] by Nicholas Blake [[Queen's Counsel|QC]] indicated that whilst a culture of bullying existed during the mid to late 1990s many of the issues were being addressed as a result of the [[Defence Training Review]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deepcutreview.org.uk/Home/home/Home Deepcut Review] accessed 14 January 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Some argue that this behaviour should be allowed because of a general academic consensus that "soldiering" is different from other occupations. Soldiers expected to risk their lives should, according to them, develop strength of body and spirit to accept bullying.&lt;ref name=diff&gt;''Social Psychology of the Individual Soldier'', Jean M. Callaghan and Franz Kernic 2003 Armed Forces and International Security: Global Trends and Issues, Lit Verlag, Munster&lt;/ref&gt;

In some countries, ritual [[hazing]] among recruits has been tolerated and even lauded as a [[rite of passage]] that builds character and toughness; while in others, systematic bullying of lower-ranking, young or physically slight recruits may in fact be encouraged by military policy, either tacitly or overtly (see ''[[dedovschina]]''). Also, the Russian army usually have older/more experienced candidates abusing &amp;ndash; kicking or punching &amp;ndash; less experienced soldiers.&lt;ref name=bbcmil&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/4477960.stm ''Military bullying a global problem''], BBC, UK Monday, 28 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hazing===
{{Main|Hazing|Ragging}}
Hazing is an often ritualistic test which may constitute harassment, abuse, or humiliation with requirements to perform meaningless tasks; sometimes as a way of initiation into a social group. The term can refer to either physical (sometimes violent) or mental (possibly degrading) practices. It is a subjective matter where to draw to line between 'normal' hazing (somewhat abusive) and a mere [[rite of passage]] (essentially bonding; proponents may argue they can coincide), and there is a gray area where exactly the other side passes over into sheer degrading, even harmful abuse that should not even be tolerated if accepted voluntarily (serious but avoidable accidents do still happen; even deliberate abuse with similar grave medical consequences occurs, in some traditions even rather often). Furthermore, as it must be a ritual ''initiation'', a different social context may mean a same treatment is technically hazing for some, not for others, e.g. a [[line-crossing ceremony]] when passing the equator at sea is hazing for the sailor while the extended (generally voluntary, more playful) application to passengers is not.

Hazing has been reported in a variety of social contexts, including:
*Sports teams
*Academic [[fraternities]] and [[sororities]] (see [[fraternities and sororities#Hazing issues|fraternities and sororities]]) These practices are not limited to American schools. Swedish students undergo a similar bonding period, known as nollningen, in which all members of the entering class participate.
*College and universities in general.
*Associated groups, like fan clubs, school bands
*Secret societies and even certain [[service club]]s, or rather their local sections (such as some modern US [[Freemasonry|Freemasons]]; not traditional masonic lodges)
*Similarly various other competitive sports teams or clubs, even 'soft' and non-competitive ones (such as arts)
*The armed forces — e.g., in the U.S., hard hazing practices from [[World War I]] [[boot camp]]s were introduced into colleges. In [[Poland]] army hazing is called Polish ''fala'' "wave" adopted pre-World War I from non-Polish armies. In the [[Russian army]] (formerly the [[Red Army]]) hazing is called "[[Dedovshchina]]".
*Police forces (often with a [[paramilitary]] tradition)
*Rescue services, such as lifeguards (also drilled for operations in military style)
*In workplaces
*Inmate hazing is also common at confinement facilities around the world, including frequent reports of beatings and sexual assaults by fellow inmates.

Hazing is considered a [[felony]] in several US states, and anti-hazing legislation has been proposed in other states.

==See also==
{{columns-list|2|
*[[Abuse]]
*[[Aggression]]
*''[[The Bully: A Discussion and Activity Story]]'' (book)
*[[Bullycide]]
*[[Character assassination]]
*[[Complex post-traumatic stress disorder]]
*[[Gay bullying]]
*[[Mobbing]]
*[[Passive aggression]]
*[[Psychological manipulation]]
*[[Psychological trauma]]
*[[Rankism]]
*[[Relational aggression]]
*[[Scapegoating]]
*[[School bullying]]
*[[School violence]]
*[[Social undermining]]
*[[Taunting]]
*[[Teasing]]
*[[Victim blaming]]
*[[Victim playing]]
*[[Victimisation]]
*[[Workplace bullying]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* ''The Fight That Never Ends'' by Tim Brown
* ''Odd Girl Out: The Hidden Culture of Aggression in Girls" by Rachel Simmons ISBN 0156027348
* ''Bullycide, Death at Playtime'' by Neil Marr and [[Tim Field]] ISBN 0-9529121-2-0
* ''Bullycide in America: Moms Speak Out about the Bullying/Suicide Connection'' &amp;ndash; by Brenda High, [http://www.bullycide.org Bullycide.org]
* [http://www.outofbullying.com   ''A Journey Out of Bullying: From Despair to Hope''] by Patricia L. Scott
* "Peer Abuse Know More! Bullying From A Psychological Perspective" By Elizabeth Bennett
* ''New Perspectives on Bullying'' by Ken Rigby
* [[James Garbarino|Garbarino, J.]] &amp; de Lara, E. (2003). [http://www.enotalone.com/article/5451.html ''And Words ''Can'' Hurt Forever: How to Protect Adolescents from Bullying, Harassment, and Emotional Violence.''] The Free Press: New York NY.
* Joanne Scaglione, Arrica Rose Scaglione [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/custom/portlets/recordDetails/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=ED493726&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=ED493726 ''Bully-proofing children: a practical, hands-on guide to stop bullying'' 2006]
* [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=ED410007&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=ED410007 ''Why Is Everybody Always Picking on Me: A Guide to Handling Bullies for Young People.''] by [[Terrence Webster-Doyle]]. Book and Teaching curriculum.

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://www.bullyfreezone.co.uk Bully Free Zone (UK)]
* [http://www.bullyingnoway.com.au/ Bullying. No Way! (Australian Education Authorities)]
* [http://www.dfes.gov.uk/bullying Bullying in schools (UK &amp;ndash; schools)]
* [http://www.kickbully.com/ Bullying in the Workplace]
* [http://www.bullysolutions.com Bully Solutions]
* [http://pbskids.org/itsmylife/friends/bullies/print_books.html PBSKids.org 'Great Books About Bullies']
* [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/simpleSearch.jsp?newSearch=true&amp;eric_sortField=&amp;searchtype=basic&amp;pageSize=10&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=bullying&amp;eric_displayStartCount=1&amp;_pageLabel=ERICSearchResult&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=kw U.S. Department of Education's Education Resources Information Center (ERIC)]

&lt;!-- Article in Spanish wikipedia does not reflect what bullying is

--&gt;
{{Bullying}}
{{abuse}}
{{Psychological manipulation}}

[[Category:Bullying]]
[[Category:Social psychology]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Aggression]]
[[Category:Injustice]]
[[Category:Persecution]]

{{Link GA|cs}}
{{Link GA|de}}

[[ar:تنمر]]
[[cs:Šikana]]
[[cy:Bwlio]]
[[de:Mobbing]]
[[eo:Ĉikanado]]
[[fr:Bullying]]
[[ko:집단 따돌림]]
[[it:Bullismo]]
[[he:בריונות]]
[[lt:Patyčios]]
[[ms:Buli]]
[[ja:いじめ]]
[[pt:Bullying]]
[[ru:Задирание]]
[[simple:Bullying]]
[[sk:Šikanovanie]]
[[fi:Kiusaaminen]]
[[uk:Цькування (психологія)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>