<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113215843|87621527" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="432459" pageid="432459" ns="0" title="Bullying"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T22:12:40Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Bully}}
{{unreferenced}}
{{POV-check}}
{{abuse}}

'''Bullying''' involves intentional torment of others through verbal [[harassment]], physical [[assault]], or other more subtle methods of [[coercion]] such as [[manipulation]]. 

== The Basics of Bullying ==

In colloquial speech, bullying is most often used to describe a form of harassment perpetrated by someone who is in some way more powerful, physically or socially, than a weaker [[peer group|peer]]. 

Researchers generally accept that bullying contains four essential elements:{{ref|nces}} 

#the behavior is aggressive and negative; 
#the behavior is carried out repeatedly;
#the behavior occurs in a relationship where there is an imbalance of power between the parties involved
#the behavior is purposeful 

Bullying is broken into two categories:{{ref|nces}}

#direct bullying
#indirect bullying, also known as social aggression  

Direct bullying is the form most common to male bullies.

Social aggression or indirect bullying is most common to female bullies and young children, and is characterized by forcing the victim into social isolation.  This isolation is achieved through a wide variety of techniques, including:  
*spreading [[gossip]] 
*refusing to socialize with the victim
*bullying other people who wish to socialize with the victim 
*criticizing the victim's manner of dress and other socially-significant markers (including the victim's race, religion, disability, etc).

Bullying can occur in any situation in which human beings interact with each other. This includes [[school]], [[workplace]], the home, and between [[countries]] (see ''[[Jingoism]]''). Whatever the situation, the power structure is typically evident between the bully and the victim. To those outside the conflict, it seems that the bully's power depends only upon the perception of the victim, with the victim being too [[intimidation|intimidated]] to put up effective resistance. However, the victim usually has just cause to be afraid of the bully due to [[threats]], and previous encounters with bullies.

===Teasing Versus Bullying===

Stones (1993, p. 70) states that when teased:
* Someone is making fun of you in a good-humoured way.
* The Person doing the teasing is someone who knows you well and cares about you.
* The teasing is not something to be taken seriously - usually you will find it funny also.
* If you do feel upset by the teasing, it is a mild feeling that soon goes away.
* Teasing is a two-way thing - someone who teases will soon get teased and someone who is teased will soon become a teaser.

==Characteristics of bullies ==
Research indicates that adults who bully have personalities that are authoritarian, combined with a strong need to control or [[dominance (biology)|dominate]].{{ref|brodsky}}  It has also been suggested  that a deficit in [[social skills]] and a prejudicial view of subordinates can be particular risk factors.{{ref|ashforth}} 

Further studies have shown that while envy and resentment may be motives for bullying,{{ref|vari}} there is little evidence to suggest bullies suffer from any deficit in [[self esteem]].{{ref|bkn}} However there are instances where bullying takes place only for humor. It is generally used in this instance by children who were bullied earlier in their lives. The fact that those who bullied them derrived fun from their acts this would teach the victims to do the same. 

Researchers have identified other risk factors such as quickness to anger and use of force, addiction to aggressive behaviors, mistaking others' actions as hostile, concern with preserving self image, and engaging in obsessive or rigid actions. {{ref|vari2}} It should also be noted that in most schools there is reward for bullies such as apearing aggressive and more attractive while drawing lines that they are better than their victims.

Bullying may also be "tradition" in settings where an age group or higher rank feels superior than lowerclassmen.

It is often suggested that bullying behavior has its origin in childhood:

:"If aggressive behaviour is not challenged in childhood, there is a danger that it may become habitual.  Indeed, there is research evidence, to indicate that bullying during childhood puts children at risk of criminal behaviour and domestic violence in adulthood."{{ref|tcd}}

Bullying does not necessarily involve criminality or physical violence. For example, bullying often operates through [[psychological abuse]] or [[verbal abuse]].

&lt;!--==Characteristics of bully targets==--&gt;

== Types of bullying ==


===School Bullying===

In schools, bullying usually occurs in areas with minimal or no adult supervision. It can occur in nearly any part in or around the school building, though it more often occurs in PE, exploratory classes, hallways, bathrooms, classes that require group work and/or afterschool activities. 

An extreme case of schoolyard bullying is that of an eighth grader named [[Curtis Taylor]] at a middle school in Iowa. He had been the victim of continuous bullying for three years, which included name-calling, being bashed into a locker, having chocolate milk poured down his sweatshirt, and the vandalism of his belongings. In reaction to the continuous harassment, Curtis Taylor committed [[suicide]] on [[March 21]], [[1993]]. Some bully experts have termed this extreme reaction "[[bullycide]]".

In the 1990's, the United States saw an epidemic of school shootings (of which the most notorious was the [[Columbine High School massacre]]). Many of the children behind these shootings claimed that they were victims of bullying and that they resorted to [[violence]] only after the school administration repeatedly failed to intervene. In many of these cases, the victims of the shooters sued both the shooters' families and the schools.  

As a result of these trends, schools in  many countries strongly discourage bullying, with programs designed to teach students cooperation, as well as training peer moderators in [[intervention]] and [[dispute resolution]] techniques, as a form of [[peer support]]. Even with these measures, in general if a victim were to report a bully to the staff the bully will generally get a small punishment and then come back more angry than ever.

Since media coverage has exposed just how widespread bullying is, juries are now more likely to sympathize with victims. In recent years, many victims have been suing bullies directly for [[intentional infliction of emotional distress]], and including their school as a [[defendant]] under the principle of [[joint and several liability]].  American victims and their families have other legal recourse, such as suing a school or teacher for failure to adequately supervise, racial or gender [[discrimination]], or other [[civil rights]] violations.  Special education students who are victimized may sue a school or school board under the [[Americans with Disabilities Act|ADA]] or [[Section 504]].

===Workplace Bullying===

{{Main|Workplace bullying}}
Workplace bullying, like childhood bullying, is the tendency of individuals or groups to use aggressive or unreasonable behavior to achieve their ends.  When perpetrated by a group, workplace bullying is often called [[mobbing]].  Unlike the more physical form of schoolyard bullying, workplace bullying often takes place within the established rules and policies of the organization and society.  For instance, a workplace bully might use the "rumor mill" to circulate a lie about a co-worker.  An employee who dislikes a co-worker for personal reasons may incessantly criticize everything that co-worker does. Such actions are not necessarily illegal and may not even be against the firm's regulations; however, the damage to the targeted employee and to workplace morale is obvious.

According to the [[Workplace Bullying and Trauma Institute]], workplace bullying is "the repeated mistreatment of one employee targeted by one or more employees with a malicious mix of humiliation, intimidation and sabotage of performance."  Statistics show that bullying is 3 times as prevalent as illegal [[discrimination]] and at least 1,600 times as prevalent as workplace [[violence]]. Statistics also show that while only one employee in every 10,000 becomes a victim of workplace violence, one in six experiences bullying at work.  Bullying is also far more common than [[sexual harassment]] and [[verbal abuse]].

===Cyber-bullying===

{{Main|Cyber-bullying}}
Cyberbullying occurs in electronic space{{ref|cyber}}. According to Canadian educator Bill Belsey, the creator of the term, it: 
:"involves the use of information and communication technologies such as e-mail, cell phone and pager text messages, instant messaging, defamatory personal Web sites, blogs, online games and defamatory online personal polling Web sites, to support deliberate, repeated, and hostile behaviour by an individual or group, that is intended to harm others".
Bullies will even create blogs to intimidate victims worldwide.

===Neighbourhood Bullying===

Between neighbours, bullying normally takes the form of intimidating behaviour, such as excessive noise to disturb sleep and other normal living patterns, and reports to authorities, such as the police, for minor or made-up incidents. Known as '''jurisdiction bullying''', its purpose is to make the victim so uncomfortable that they move from their property.{{fact}}

===Political Bullying===
{{main|Jingoism}}
Jingoism occurs when one country imposes its will on another. This is normally done with military force or threats. With threats, it is common to ensure that aid and grants will not be given to the smaller country or that the smaller country will not be allowed to join a trading organisation. Often [[political corruption]]s, [[coup d'état]]s, and [[Kleptocracy|kleptocracies]] are the solution and response to the countries being bullied.{{fact}}

=== Military Bullying ===

In 2000, the UK [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] (MOD) defined bullying as: “...the use of physical strength or the abuse of authority to intimidate or victimize others, or to give unlawful punishments,”{{ref|mod}}

Yet it is claimed that military bullying is still shielded from open investigation. [[Deepcut Barracks]] in the UK is one example of the government refusing to conduct a full public enquiry into possible military bullying. 

Some argue that this behaviour should be allowed because of a general academic consensus that "soldiering" is different from other occupations. Soldiers expected to risk their lives should, according to them, develop strength of body and spirit to accept bullying.{{ref|diff}}  

Sometimes the bullying is unavoidable and even necessary, but comes down from above: the drill sergeant. This is the basis of boot camp training: to create a fighting unit where loyalty will lead to protecting the unit at any cost to the individual. Old group affiliations are weakened, the new group forged into one entity of incredibly strong allegiance and bonding by this sanctioned bullying.  

In some countries, ritual [[hazing]] among recruits has been tolerated and even lauded as a [[rite of passage]] that builds character and toughness; while in others, systematic bullying of lower-ranking, young or physically slight recruits may in fact be encouraged by military policy, either tacitly or overtly (see ''[[dedovschina]]''). Also, the Russian army usually have older/more experienced candidates abusing - kicking or punching - less experienced soldiers.{{ref|bbcmil}}.

Military environment hazing and bullying is also found in the military academies of the various armed forces.  The abuse includes sexual objectifying, sexual harassment and even rape.

=== Derogatory Labels ===

Normally a [[nickname]] is given by a family member or friend.  It may be a short commonly used form of the given name or it might be a pet name given in early childhood.{{fact}}  

However, in bullying, rather than friendly nicknames, a derogatory label is associated with the victim.  In early childhood, the label most often draws attention to a feature or characteristic that distinguishes the victim from the rest of the crowd.  In some cases, the targeted characteristic is not one the victim wants to be noticed. A redhead might be called "carrot top", or someone with glasses might be called "four eyes."  Bullies might also choose nicknames that target physical oddities such as birthmarks or muscular disorders. These nicknames can be so changed from the original that they appear entirely harmless and can be taken up by teachers and other adults further alienating the victim unintentionally.{{fact}} 

Sometimes others follow the bully by adopting the cruel nickname.  Feelings of ostracism are frequent and can severely impact socialization and academic performance.  Teachers may notice the harassment, but it is usually perceived as harmless, often because the jabs are too subtle to recognize.  Often the teacher will respond to a target's pleas for intervention by the recitation of the refrain, "Sticks and stones may break my bones, but words can never hurt me."  Unfortunately, it is often a false assessment.{{fact}} 

Derogatory nicknames are not limited to the schoolyard. Adult bullies may also participate in labeling others in the workplace or social circle. These labels are more likely to characterize perceived or suspected personality, character or incompetency.  Adult labeling is often paired with other harassing and undermining behaviors.{{fact}}

===Hazing===
{{main|Hazing|Ragging}}
Hazing is an often ritualistic test, which may constitute harassment, abuse or humiliation with requirements to perform meaningless tasks; sometimes as a way of initiation into a social group. The term can refer to either physical (sometimes violent) or mental (possibly degrading) practices. It is a subjective matter where to draw to line between 'normal' hazing (somewhat abusive) and a mere [[rite of passage]] (essentially bonding; proponents may argue they can coincide), and there is a gray area where exactly the other side passes over into sheer degrading, even harmful abuse that should not even be tolerated if accepted voluntarily (serious but avoidable accidents do still happen; even deliberate abuse with similar grave medical consequences occurs, in some traditions even rather often). Furthermore, as it must be a ritual ''initiation'', a different social context may mean a same treatment is technically hazing for some, not for others, e.g. a [[line-crossing ceremony]] when passing the equator at sea is hazing for the sailor while the extended (generally voluntary, more playful) application to passengers is not.

Hazing has been reported in a variety of social contexts, including: 
*Sports Teams
*Academic [[fraternities]] and [[sororities]] (see [[Fraternities and sororities#Hazing issues|Fraternities and sororities]]) 
*College and Universities in general. This practice occurs no less in smaller institutions such as the officially sanctioned '[[Kangaroo Court]]' at [[Quincy University]], Illinois. In India, this process is termed [[Ragging]].
*associated groups, like fan clubs, school bands
*secret societies and even certain [[service club]]s, or rather their local sections (such as some modern US [[Freemasonry|Freemasons]]; not traditional masonic lodges) 
* similarly various other competitive sports teams or clubs, even 'soft' and non-competitive ones (such as arts)
*The armed forces — e.g. in the US, hard hazing practices from [[World War I]] [[boot camp]]s were introduced into colleges. In [[Poland]] army hazing is called Polish ''fala'' "wave" adopted pre-World War I from non-Polish armies. In the [[Russian army]] (formerly the [[Red Army]]) still often excessive hazing is called "[[Dedovshchina]]".
*Police forces (often with a [[paramilitary]] tradition)
*Rescue services, such as lifeguards (also drilled for operations in military style)
*In workplaces 
*Inmate hazing is also common at confinement facilities around the world, including frequent reports of beatings and sexual assaults by fellow inmates. 

Hazing is considered a felony in several US states, and anti hazing legislation has been proposed in other states.

==Strategies to cope with bullying==
&lt;!---This is an important section but the text currently here badly needs improving---&gt;
===Legal action===
It may be possible to take legal action against a bully either through civil or criminal courts. 

On July 31, 2006 for example, five girls from the Casey County High School in Kentucky filed a lawsuit claiming that the school administration ignored their repeated reports of bullying. According to the lawsuit, one of the girls and her parents went to principal who allegedly said there was nothing to be done and he told her to "ride it out".  In another incident mentioned in the suit, a girl went to her teacher after one student punched her. According to the girl, the teacher did nothing but say, "She's mad at you." In addition, another girl went to the assistant principal with her mother to complain. According to the mother, the assistant principal told her that her daughter should "toughen up". Linda Hatter, president of the administration was named defendant in the case, which is still pending.{{fact}}

===Helping Victims at School===

One of the responsibilities of members of a school team is that they need to help the victims of bullying.
The following strategies may be considered:

# If a person voluntarily comes to someone for help then they need to listen.  Sometimes this is all that the victim wants and needs.  
# After investigating the situation, it may be that intervention is necessary with the bully or bullies.  The situation needs to be addressed and hopefully a resolution to the problem can be found.  
# Inform the parents of the victim and of the bully.  Discuss possible solutions with them.  Arrange a meeting with them if possible.  
# Follow up in communicating with the victim, the parents and the teachers about the situation.
# Monitor the behaviour of the bully and the safety of the victim on a school-wide basis.

==References==
*{{note|brodsky}}''The Harassed Worker'', Brodsky, C. (1976), [[D.C. Heath and Company]], Lexington, Massachusetts. 
* {{note|nces}}[http://nces.ed.gov/pubs2005/2005310.pdf ''Student Reports of Bullying''], Results From the 2001 School Crime Supplement to the National Crime Victimization Survey, US National Center for Education Statistics
* {{note|tuc}}''Beat Bullying at Work: a Guide for Trade Union Representatives and Personnel Managers.'' Trades Union Congress (TUC) (1998), London, UK.
* {{note|stress}}''[http://www.bullyonline.org/stress/health.htm Bullyonline: Stress, injury to health, trauma, PTSD]'' Field, Tim, Success Unlimited, UK.
* {{note|cyber}}''[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4912766.stm Striking back at the cyberbullies ]'' Page, Chris, BBC, UK.
* {{note|vari}}''Bullying and emotional abuse in the workplace. International perspectives in research and practice'', Einarsen, S., Hoel, H., Zapf, D., &amp; Cooper, C. L. (Eds.)(2003), Taylor &amp; Francis, London.
* {{note|ashforth}}''Petty tyranny in organizations '', Ashforth, Blake, Human Relations, Vol. 47, No. 7, 755-778 (1994)
* {{note|vari2}}''Areas of Expert Agreement on Identification of School Bullies and Victims'', Hazler, R. J., Carney, J. V., Green, S., Powell, R., &amp; Jolly, L. S. (1997). School Psychology International, 18, 3-12.
* {{note|tcd}}[http://www.abc.tcd.ie/ ''Anti-Bullying Center'' Trinity College, Dublin],
* {{note|bkn}}''Bullies and their victims: Understanding a pervasive problem in the schools'', Batsche, G. M., &amp; Knoff, H. M. (1994) School PSYCHOLOGY REVIEW, 23 (2), 165-174. EJ 490 574.
* {{note|bbcmil}}[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/4477960.stm ''Military bullying a global problem''], BBC, UK Monday, 28 November 2005
* {{note|mod}}''The Values and Standards of the British Army – A Guide to Soldiers'', Ministry of Defence, UK March 2000, paragraph 23.
* {{note|diff}}''Social Psychology of the Individual Soldier'', Jean M. Callaghan and Franz Kernic 2003  Armed Forces and International Security: Global Trends and Issues, Lit Verlag, Munster
* {{note|cause}}''Internet Infidels Discussion Boards'', http://www.iidb.org/vbb/showthread.php?t=170922

==See also== 
*[[Scapegoating]]
*[[Stalking]]
*[[Gaslighting]]
*[[Teasing]] 
*[[Bullying Online|Bullying Online UK charity]]
*[[List of books on bullying]]

==External links== 
* [http://www.beatbullying.org/index.html?template=text Beatbullying: Creating a world where bullying is unacceptable]
* [http://www.bullying.org Bullying.org "Where you are NOT alone!"] 
* [http://www.childline.org.uk/Bullying.asp Childline (UK) - talk to someone in confidence (0800 1111)]
* [http://www.safecanada.ca/topic_e.asp?category=28 Canadian anti-bullying safety database]
* [http://www.education.unisa.edu.au/bullying Bullying in schools (Australia - schools)] 
* [http://www.dfes.gov.uk/bullying Bullying in schools (UK - schools)]
* [http://www.msn.co.uk/customercare/protect/cyberbullying/Default.asp MSN on Cyberbullying]
* [http://www.bullywhys.com BullyWhys]
* [http://www.recoveryourlife.com/Bullying/School_Bullying/default.aspx School Bullying]
* [http://www.school-survival.net/kit/bullying.php How to stop bullies from bothering you]
* [http://www.lfcc.on.ca/bully.htm Bullying: Information for Parents and Teachers]
* [http://www.nfh.org.uk Neighbours From Hell in Britain]
* [http://www.bullying-in-school.info VISIONARY - A European Portal on School Bullying and Violence] 
* [http://www.bullyonline.org/schoolbully/index.htm Bully OnLine]
* [http://www.transpacificradio.com/2006/11/04/seijigiri-11-november-3-2006-seijigiri-toughens-up-and-goes-to-school/  Discussion on bullying in Japanese schools] (Streaming audio &amp; mp3)


[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:People]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Aggression]]
[[Category:Educational psychology]]
[[Category:Injustice]]
[[Category:Persecution]]

[[cs:Šikana]]
[[de:Bullying]]
&lt;!-- Article in Spanish wikipedia does not reflect what bullying is
[[es:Acoso escolar]]
--&gt;
[[it:Bullismo]]
[[nl:Pesten]]
[[fi:Simputus]]
[[ja:いじめ]]
[[zh:校園欺凌]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>