<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231120192142|1186072040" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="432459" pageid="432459" ns="0" title="Bullying"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-11-28T01:14:17Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Use of force or coercion to abuse or intimidate others}}
{{redirect|Bully}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
[[File:Bullying Físico.JPG|thumb|A depiction of a student being bullied by three other students. A bystander is seen in the background, paying no attention.]]
[[File:Share of children who report being bullied, OWID.svg|thumb|upright=1.3|Share of children who report being bullied (2015)]]
'''Bullying''' is the use of force, [[coercion]], hurtful [[teasing]] or threat, to [[abuse]], aggressively [[wikt:domination|dominate]] or [[intimidate]]. The behavior is often repeated and habitual. One essential prerequisite is the perception (by the bully or by others) of an imbalance of physical or [[Power (social and political)|social]] power. This imbalance distinguishes bullying from conflict.&lt;ref name="School bullying is not a conflict"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Burger C | journal=International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health | title=School bullying is not a conflict: The interplay between conflict management styles, bullying victimization and psychological school adjustment | volume=19 | issue=18 | page=11809 | date= 2022 | issn=1661-7827 | doi=10.3390/ijerph191811809| pmid=36142079 | pmc=9517642 | doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author1=Juvonen, J. | author2=Graham, S. | s2cid=207640520 | title = Bullying in Schools: The Power of Bullies and the Plight of Victims | journal =[[Annual Review of Psychology]]| volume = 65 | date = 2014 | pages=159–85 | doi=10.1146/annurev-psych-010213-115030 | pmid=23937767 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Bullying is a subcategory of aggressive behavior characterized by hostile intent, imbalance of power and repetition over a period of time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Burger|first1=Christoph|last2=Strohmeier|first2=Dagmar|last3=Spröber|first3=Nina|last4=Bauman|first4=Sheri|last5=Rigby|first5=Ken|date=2015|title=How teachers respond to school bullying: An examination of self-reported intervention strategy use, moderator effects, and concurrent use of multiple strategies|journal=Teaching and Teacher Education|volume=51|pages=191–202|doi=10.1016/j.tate.2015.07.004}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Bullying can be done individually or by a group, called [[mobbing]],&lt;ref name="DavenportSchwartz1999"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JlJoyD84BfAC|title=Mobbing: Emotional Abuse in the American Workplace|author1=Noa Davenport|author2=Ruth Distler Schwartz|author3=Gail Pursell Elliott|date=1999-07-01|publisher=Civil Society Publishing|isbn=978-0-9671803-0-4|access-date=2013-10-28|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140101074041/http://books.google.com/books?id=JlJoyD84BfAC|archive-date=2014-01-01|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; in which the bully may have one or more followers who are willing to assist the primary bully or who reinforce the bully by providing positive feedback such as laughing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Pouwels JL, Lansu TA, Cillessen AH | journal=Aggression and Violent Behavior | title=A developmental perspective on popularity and the group process of bullying | volume=43 | pages=64–70 | date= 2018 | issn=1359-1789 | doi=10.1016/j.avb.2018.10.003| hdl=2066/196743 | s2cid=150289090 | hdl-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Bullying in school and the workplace is also referred to as "peer abuse".&lt;ref name="Bennett2006"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GF06aB7mLdIC|title=Peer Abuse Know More!: Bullying from a Psychological Perspective|author=Elizabeth Bennett|date=1 January 2006|publisher=Infinity|isbn=978-0-7414-3265-0|access-date=2013-10-29|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140914150852/http://books.google.com/books?id=GF06aB7mLdIC|archive-date=14 September 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert W. Fuller]] has analyzed bullying in the context of [[rankism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | vauthors=Fuller RW | date= 2017 | chapter=Learning to Seek | title=Learning in a Dignitarian World | publisher=Routledge | pages=29–40 | isbn=978-0-203-78742-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Swedish-Norwegian researcher [[Dan Olweus]] says bullying occurs when a person is "exposed, repeatedly and over time, to negative actions on the part of one or more other persons",&lt;ref name="History"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.clemson.edu/olweus/history.html|title=History|work=OLWEUS Bullying Prevention Program|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029204025/http://www.clemson.edu/olweus/history.html|archive-date=2013-10-29|url-status=live|access-date=2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that negative actions occur "when a person intentionally inflicts injury or discomfort upon another person, through physical contact, through words or in other ways".&lt;ref name="History" /&gt; Individual bullying is usually characterized by a person behaving in a certain way to gain [[Power (social and political)|power]] over another person.&lt;ref name="Besag1989"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=t2pHAAAAMAAJ|title=Bullies and victims in schools: a guide to understanding and management|author=Valerie E. Besag|publisher=Open University Press|year=1989|isbn=978-0-335-09542-1|access-date=2013-10-29|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140707234508/http://books.google.com/books?id=t2pHAAAAMAAJ|archive-date=2014-07-07|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A bullying culture can develop in any context in which humans interact with each other. This may include [[School bullying|school]], family, the [[Workplace bullying|workplace]],&lt;ref name="SilentEpidemic"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/wired-success/201105/the-silent-epidemic-workplace-bullying|title=The Silent Epidemic: Workplace Bullying|last=Williams|first=Ray|date=3 May 2011|work=Psychology Today|archive-url=https://archive.today/20151121235011/https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/wired-success/201105/the-silent-epidemic-workplace-bullying|archive-date=2015-11-21|access-date=2016-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; the home, and neighborhoods. The main platform for bullying in contemporary culture is on social media websites.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Whittaker|first=E|date=2016|title=Cyberbullying via social media|journal=[[Journal of School Violence]]|pages=11–29}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dubious|Predominantly a phenomenon of 'social media'?|date=May 2023}} In a 2012 study of male adolescent American football players, "the strongest predictor [of bullying] was the perception of whether the most influential male in a player's life would approve of the bullying behavior."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Steinfeldt|first1=Jesse A.|last2=Vaughan|first2=Ellen L.|last3=LaFollette|first3=Julie R.|last4=Steinfeldt|first4=Matthew C.|date=October 2012|title=Bullying among adolescent football players: Role of masculinity and moral atmosphere|journal=Psychology of Men and Masculinity|volume=13|issue=4|pages=340–353|doi=10.1037/a0026645|hdl=2022/14023|hdl-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study by ''[[The Lancet]]'' Child &amp; Adolescent Health in 2019 showed a relationship between social media use by girls and an increase in their exposure to bullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://baltimore.cbslocal.com/2019/08/13/social-media-use-may-harm-teens-mental-health-by-disrupting-positive-activities-study-says/|title=Social Media Use May Harm Teens' Mental Health By Disrupting Positive Activities, Study Says|date=2019-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bullying may be defined in many different ways. In the United Kingdom, there is no legal definition of bullying,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =The University of Manchester Dignity at Work and Study Policy | publisher =The University of Manchester | date =January 2012 | url =http://documents.manchester.ac.uk/display.aspx?DocID=2753 | access-date =2013-10-28 | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131029210026/http://documents.manchester.ac.uk/display.aspx?DocID=2753 | archive-date =2013-10-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; while some states in the United States have laws against it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=State Laws Related to Bullying Among Children and Youth |work=U.S. Department of Health and Human Services - Health Resources and Services Administration - Maternal and Child Health Bureau |publisher=U.S. Department of Health and Human Services |url=http://stopbullyingnow.hrsa.gov/HHS_PSA/pdfs/SBN_Tip_6.pdf |access-date=2013-10-28 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110304062718/http://www.stopbullyingnow.hrsa.gov/HHS_PSA/pdfs/SBN_Tip_6.pdf |archive-date=March 4, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Bullying is divided into four basic types of abuse: [[Psychological abuse|psychological]] (sometimes called emotional or relational), [[Verbal abuse|verbal]], [[Physical abuse|physical]], and [[cyberbullying|cyber]], though an encounter can fall into multiple of these categories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 =Brank | first1 =Eve M. | last2 =Hoetger | first2 =Lori A. | last3 =Hazen | first3 =Katherine P. | title =Bullying | journal =[[Annual Review of Law and Social Science]] | volume =8 | pages =213–230 | date =December 2012 | doi =10.1146/annurev-lawsocsci-102811-173820 | issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Behaviors used to assert such domination may include physical [[assault]] or coercion, verbal [[harassment]], or [[threat]], and such acts may be directed repeatedly toward particular targets. [[Rationalization (making excuses)|Rationalizations]] of such behavior sometimes include differences of social class, race, religion, gender, sexual orientation, appearance, behavior, body language, personality, reputation, lineage, strength, size, or ability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cambridgeshire.gov.uk/childrenandfamilies/parenting/childsbehaviour/bullying.htm|title=Children who are bullying or being bullied|date=2013-07-24|work=Cambridgeshire County Council: Children and families|publisher=Cambridgeshire County Council|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029215401/http://www.cambridgeshire.gov.uk/childrenandfamilies/parenting/childsbehaviour/bullying.htm|archive-date=2013-10-29|access-date=2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ericson|first=Nels|date=June 2001|title=Addressing the Problem of Juvenile Bullying|url=https://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/ojjdp/fs200127.pdf|url-status=live|journal=OJJDP Fact Sheet #FS-200127|volume=27|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150626170748/https://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/ojjdp/fs200127.pdf|archive-date=2015-06-26|access-date=2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Meyer|first=Doug|year=2016|title=The Gentle Neoliberalism of Modern Anti-bullying Texts: Surveillance, Intervention, and Bystanders in Contemporary Bullying Discourse|journal=Sexuality Research and Social Policy|volume=13|issue=4|pages=356–370|doi=10.1007/s13178-016-0238-9|s2cid=148471672}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
The word "bully" was first used in the 1530s meaning "sweetheart", applied to either sex, from the {{lang-nl|boel}}, "lover, brother", probably diminutive of {{lang-gmh|buole}}, "brother", of uncertain origin (compare with the German ''buhle'' "lover"). The meaning deteriorated through the 17th century through "fine fellow", "blusterer", to "harasser of the weak". This may have been as a connecting sense between "lover" and "ruffian" as in "protector of a [[prostitute]]", which was one sense of "bully" (though not specifically attested until 1706). The verb "to bully" is first attested in 1710.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=bully|title=bully|work=Online Etymology Dictionary|publisher=Douglas Harper|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029195402/http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=bully|archive-date=2013-10-29|url-status=live|access-date=2013-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the past, in American culture, the term has been used differently, as an exclamation/exhortation, in particular famously associated with [[Theodore Roosevelt]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shapell.org/manuscript/theodore-roosevelt-bully-for-you ''TR Correspondence 27 September 1907''] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160416024951/http://www.shapell.org/manuscript/theodore-roosevelt-bully-for-you|date=16 April 2016}} "bully for you" in the positive sense&lt;/ref&gt; and continuing to the present in the [[bully pulpit]], Roosevelt's [[Protologism|coining]] and also as faint/deprecating praise ("bully for him").

== Types ==
Bullying has been classified by the body of literature into different types. These can be in the form of nonverbal, verbal, or physical behavior. Another classification is based on perpetrators or the participants involved, so that the types include individual and collective bullying. Other interpretation also cite emotional and relational bullying in addition to physical harm inflicted towards another person or even property.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=McGrath|first=Mary Jo|title=School Bullying: Tools for Avoiding Harm and Liability|date=2007|publisher=Corwin Press|isbn=978-1-4129-1571-7|location=Thousand Oaks, CA|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also the case of the more recent phenomenon called cyberbullying.

Physical, verbal, and relational bullying are most prevalent in primary school and could also begin much earlier while continuing into later stages in individuals lives.

=== Individual ===
Individual bullying tactics are perpetrated by a single person against a victim or victims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://respect2all.org/bullying-definitions/ |title=Bullying Definitions |access-date=2016-02-26 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304140405/http://respect2all.org/bullying-definitions/ |archive-date=2016-03-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Individual bullying can be classified into four types.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Invitation to the Life Span|last = Berger|first = Kathleen Stassen|publisher = Worth Publishers|year = 2014|isbn = 978-1-4641-7205-2|location = New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Physical ====
Physical bullying is any bullying that hurts someone's body or damages their possessions. Stealing, shoving, hitting, fighting, and intentionally destroying someone's property are types of physical bullying. Physical bullying is rarely the first form of bullying that a victim will experience. Often bullying will begin in a different form and later progress to physical violence. In physical bullying the main weapon the bully uses is his/her body, or some part thereof; or an object as a weapon when attacking his/her victim. Sometimes groups of young adults will target and alienate a peer because of some adolescent prejudice. This can quickly lead to a situation where they are being taunted, tortured, and "beaten up" by their classmates. Physical bullying will often escalate over time, and can lead to a detrimental or fatal ending, and therefore many try to stop it quickly to prevent any further escalation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://nobullying.com/physical-bullying/|title=no bullying|website=nobullying.com/physical-bullying/|access-date=30 November 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161201023450/https://nobullying.com/physical-bullying/|archive-date=1 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Verbal ====
Verbal bullying is one of the most common types of bullying. This is any bullying that is conducted by speaking, other use of the voice, or some form of body language and does not involve any physical contact. Bullying usually begins at this stage and includes any of the following:

*[[Pejorative|Derogatory]] name-calling and [[nickname|nicknaming]]
*Spreading rumors or lying about someone
*Threatening someone
*Yelling at or talking to someone in a rude or unkind tone of voice, especially without justifiable cause
*Mocking someone's voice or style of speaking
*Laughing at someone
*Use of [[body language]] (i.e., the [[the finger|middle finger]]) to torment someone
*Making insults or otherwise making fun of someone

In verbal bullying, the main weapon the bully uses is voice. In many cases, verbal bullying is common in both genders, but girls are more likely to perform it. Girls, in general, are more subtle with insults than boys. Girls use verbal bullying, as well as social exclusion techniques, to dominate and control other individuals and show their superiority and power, often to try to impress someone they idolize. Many boys are subtle enough to use verbal techniques for domination when they want to avoid the trouble that can come with physically bullying someone else.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.bullyingstatistics.org/content/verbal-bullying.html|title=What is Verbal Bullying and How to Handle Verbal Bullies - Bullying Statistics|date=2015-07-08|newspaper=Bullying Statistics|access-date=2016-11-30|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161125110622/http://www.bullyingstatistics.org/content/verbal-bullying.html|archive-date=2016-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Relational ====
Relational bullying (sometimes referred to as social aggression) is the type of bullying that uses relationships to hurt others.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Breakstone|first1=Steve|title=How to Stop Bullying and Social Aggression: Elementary Grade Lessons and Activities That Teach Empathy, Friendship, and Respect|last2=Dreiblatt|first2=Michael|last3=Dreiblatt|first3=Karen|date=2009|publisher=Corwin Press|isbn=978-1-4129-5810-3|location=Thousand Oaks, CA|page=9}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term also denotes any bullying that is done with the intent to hurt somebody's reputation or social standing which can also link in with the techniques included in physical and verbal bullying. Relational bullying is a form of bullying common among youth, but particularly upon girls. Social exclusion (slighting or making someone feel "left out") is one of the most common types of relational bullying. Relational bullying can be used as a tool by bullies to both improve their social standing and control others. Unlike physical bullying which is obvious, relational bullying is not overt and can continue for a long time without being noticed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://antibullyingsoftware.com/what-is-the-definition-of-relational-bullying-social-bullying/|title=What is the Definition of Relational Bullying / Social Bullying - BRIM Anti-Bullying Software|last=Norton|first=Chris|newspaper=BRIM Anti-Bullying Software|access-date=2016-11-30|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161201080421/https://antibullyingsoftware.com/what-is-the-definition-of-relational-bullying-social-bullying/|archive-date=2016-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Cyber ====
[[Cyberbullying]] is the use of technology to harass, threaten, embarrass, or target another person. When an adult is involved, it may meet the definition of '''cyber-harassment''' or [[cyberstalking]], a crime that can have legal consequences and involve jail time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://kidshealth.org/en/parents/cyberbullying.html|title=Cyberbullying|website=kidshealth.org|access-date=2016-11-30|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161201165708/http://kidshealth.org/en/parents/cyberbullying.html|archive-date=2016-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; This includes bullying by use of email, instant messaging, social media websites (such as [[Facebook]]), text messages, and cell phones. It is stated that Cyberbullying is more common in secondary school than in primary school.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

The internet provides people with limited accountability and no filter.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Affairs (ASPA) |first=Assistant Secretary for Public |date=2019-09-24 |title=What Is Cyberbullying |url=https://www.stopbullying.gov/cyberbullying/what-is-it |access-date=2023-02-28 |website=StopBullying.gov |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of technology for bullying can be detrimental to someones online reputation.  The information put out online will stay there forever, unless taken down by the person who put it out there and sometimes not even then. Future jobs and people will be able to see others' digital footprint and how you treated others. Another problem with cyberbullying is that other people can get involved. Technology, especially the use of social media, allows others to repost or share content whether it is positive or negative.

=== Collective ===
Collective bullying tactics are employed by more than one individual against a victim or victims. Collective bullying is known as mobbing, and can include any of the individual types of bullying. [[Internet troll|Trolling behavior]] on social media, although generally assumed to be individual in nature by the casual reader, is sometime organized efforts by sponsored [[astroturfing|astroturfers]].

==== Mobbing ====
{{Main|Mobbing}}
Mobbing refers to the bullying of an individual by a group, in any context, such as a [[family]], [[peer group]], [[school]], [[workplace]], [[neighborhood]], [[community]], or online. When it occurs as [[emotion]]al [[abuse]] in the workplace, such as "ganging up" by co-workers, [[Hierarchy|subordinate]]s or [[Superior (hierarchy)|superior]]s, to force someone out of the workplace through [[rumor]], [[innuendo]], [[intimidation]], [[humiliation]], [[discrediting]], and [[Isolation to facilitate abuse|isolation]], it is also referred to as malicious, nonsexual, nonracial/racial, general [[harassment]].&lt;ref&gt;Mobbing: Emotional Abuse in the American Workplace by Noa Davenport, Ruth D. Schwartz and Gail Pursell Elliott.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Characteristics ==

=== Bullies and accomplices ===
Studies have shown that [[envy]] and resentment may be motives for bullying.&lt;ref name="Einarsen2003"&gt;{{cite book|author=Ståle Einarsen|title=Bullying and Emotional Abuse in the Workplace: International Perspectives in Research and Practice|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dQhz3uFOuaYC|access-date=2013-10-29|year=2003|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-0-415-25359-8|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140102040519/http://books.google.com/books?id=dQhz3uFOuaYC|archive-date=2014-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research on the self-esteem of bullies has produced equivocal results.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 =Cardemil | first1 =Alisha R. | last2 =Cardemil | first2 =Esteban V. | last3 =O'Donnell | first3 =Ellen H. | title =Self-Esteem in Pure Bullies and Bully/Victims: A Longitudinal Analysis | journal =Journal of Interpersonal Violence | volume =25 | issue =8 | pages =1489–1502 | date =August 2010 | doi =10.1177/0886260509354579 | pmid =20040706 | s2cid =26698674 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bkn&gt;{{Cite journal |first1=George M. |last1=Batsche |first2=Howard M. |last2=Knoff |year=1994 |title=Bullies and their victims: Understanding a pervasive problem in the schools |journal=School Psychology Review |volume=23 |issue=2 |pages=165–175 |doi=10.1080/02796015.1994.12085704 |url=http://faculty.buffalostate.edu/hennesda/BULLIES_AND_THEIR_VICTIMS.doc |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120302213726/http://faculty.buffalostate.edu/hennesda/BULLIES_AND_THEIR_VICTIMS.doc |archive-date=2012-03-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt; While some bullies are arrogant and narcissistic,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Those who can, do. Those who can't, bully. | work =Bully OnLine | publisher =Tim Field | url =http://www.bullyonline.org/workbully/faq.htm | access-date =2013-10-28 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20130707153041/http://www.bullyonline.org/workbully/faq.htm | archive-date =2013-07-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt; they can also use bullying as a tool to conceal shame or anxiety or to boost self-esteem: by demeaning others, the abuser feels empowered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author =Syiasha | title =Presentation Bullying | work =Scribd | publisher =Scribd Inc. | url =https://www.scribd.com/doc/7882659/Presentation-Bullying | access-date =2013-10-28 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131029215602/http://www.scribd.com/doc/7882659/Presentation-Bullying | archive-date =2013-10-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Bullies may bully out of jealousy or because they themselves are bullied.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 =Levinson | first1 =Edward M. | title =Assessment of Bullying: A Review of Methods and Instruments | journal =Journal of Counseling &amp; Development | volume =82 | issue =4 | pages =496–503 | year =2004 | doi =10.1002/j.1556-6678.2004.tb00338.x | first2 =Edward M. | last2 =Levinson }}&lt;/ref&gt; Psychologist [[Roy Baumeister]] asserts that people who are prone to abusive behavior tend to have inflated but fragile egos. Because they think too highly of themselves, they are frequently offended by the criticisms and lack of deference of other people, and react to this disrespect with violence and insults.&lt;ref&gt;Roy Baumeister. ''Evil: Inside Human Violence and Cruelty''&lt;/ref&gt;{{full citation needed|date=August 2015}}

Researchers have identified other risk factors such as depression&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Patterson G |s2cid=34334649 |title=The bully as victim? |journal=Paediatric Nursing |volume=17 |issue=10 |pages=27–30 |date=December 2005 |pmid=16372706|doi=10.7748/paed2005.12.17.10.27.c981}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[personality disorders]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Kumpulainen | first =K. | title =Psychiatric conditions associated with bullying | journal =International Journal of Adolescent Medicine and Health | volume =20 | issue =2 | pages =121–132 | year =2008 | pmid= 18714551 | doi=10.1515/ijamh.2008.20.2.121| s2cid =32858078 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as quickness to anger and use of force, addiction to aggressive behaviors, mistaking others' actions as hostile, concern with preserving [[self-image]], and engaging in obsessive or rigid actions.&lt;ref name=vari2&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1177/0143034397181001 |title=Areas of Expert Agreement on Identification of School Bullies and Victims |year=1997 |last1=Hazlerr |first1=R. J. |last2=Carney |first2=J. V. |last3=Green |first3=S. |last4=Powell |first4=R. |last5=Jolly |first5=L. S. |journal=School Psychology International |volume=18 |pages=5–14 |issue=1|s2cid=144789919 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A combination of these factors may also be causes of this behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Craig|first1=W.M.|author-link=Wendy Craig (psychologist)|year=1998|title=The relationship among bullying, victimization, depression, anxiety, and aggression in elementary school children|journal=Personality and Individual Differences|volume=24|issue=1|pages=123–130|doi=10.1016/S0191-8869(97)00145-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In one study of youth, a combination of antisocial traits and depression was found to be the best predictor of youth violence, whereas video game violence and [[Research on the effects of violence in mass media|television violence]] exposure were not predictive of these behaviors.&lt;ref name="Ferguson, 2011"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ferguson|first=Christopher J.|year=2011|title=Video Games and Youth Violence: A Prospective Analysis in Adolescents|journal=Journal of Youth and Adolescence|volume=40|issue=4|url=http://www.tamiu.edu/~cferguson/Video%20Games%201%20Year.pdf|doi=10.1007/s10964-010-9610-x|pages=377–91|pmid=21161351|s2cid=207206722|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120525061300/http://www.tamiu.edu/~cferguson/Video%20Games%201%20Year.pdf|archive-date=2012-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bullying may also result from a genetic predisposition or a brain abnormality in the bully.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Genetic and environmental influences on victims, bullies and bully-victims in childhood|last = Ball|first = H.A.|date = Jan 2008|journal = Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry|doi = 10.1111/j.1469-7610.2007.01821.x|pmid = 18181884|volume=49|issue=1|pages=104–12}}&lt;/ref&gt; While parents can help a toddler develop emotional regulation and control to restrict aggressive behavior, some children fail to develop these skills due to insecure attachment with their families, ineffective discipline, and environmental factors such as a stressful home life and hostile siblings.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Moreover, according to some researchers, bullies may be inclined toward negativity and perform poorly academically. Dr. Cook says, "A typical bully has trouble resolving problems with others and also has trouble academically. He or she usually has negative attitudes and beliefs about others, feels negatively toward himself/herself, comes from a family environment characterized by conflict and poor parenting, perceives school as negative and is negatively influenced by peers."&lt;ref name="APS2010"&gt;{{cite journal | title = Predictors of Bullying and Victimization in Childhood and Adolescence: A Meta-analytic Investigation | journal = School Psychology Quarterly | volume = 25 | issue = 2 | pages = 65–83 | year = 2010 | url = http://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/releases/spq-25-2-65.pdf | doi = 10.1037/a0020149 | access-date = 2013-10-28 | last1 = Cook | first1 = Clayton R. | last2 = Williams | first2 = Kirk R. | last3 = Guerra | first3 = Nancy G. | last4 = Kim | first4 = Tia E. | last5 = Sadek | first5 = Shelly | hdl = 10818/11372 | url-status = live | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140307231300/http://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/releases/spq-25-2-65.pdf | archive-date = 2014-03-07 | citeseerx = 10.1.1.617.7810 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Contrarily, some researchers have suggested that some bullies are psychologically strongest and have high social standing among their peers, while their targets are emotionally distressed and socially marginalized.&lt;ref&gt;Juvonen (2003) [http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/112/6/1231.abstract ''Bullying Among Young Adolescents: The Strong, the Weak and the Troubled''] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110818110341/http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/112/6/1231.abstract |date=2011-08-18 }} in ''Pediatrics'', December 2003, {{cite web
|year = 2004
|url = http://www.kimberlyswygert.com/archives/001765.html
|title = The benefits of bullying
|access-date = 2011-09-03
|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20110928054438/http://www.kimberlyswygert.com/archives/001765.html
|archive-date = 2011-09-28
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peer groups often promote the bully's actions, and members of these peer groups also engage in behaviors, such as mocking, excluding, punching, and insulting one another as a source of entertainment.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Other researchers also argued that a minority of the bullies, those who are not in-turn bullied, enjoy going to school, and are least likely to take days off sick.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title =Bullies are the healthiest pupils | newspaper =BBC News | department =Education | publisher =BBC | date =1999-12-14 | url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/564923.stm | access-date =2013-10-29 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131030192122/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/564923.stm | archive-date =2013-10-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research indicates that adults who bully have authoritarian personalities, combined with a strong need to control or dominate.&lt;ref name="Brodsky1976"&gt;{{cite book|author=Carroll M. Brodsky|title=The Harassed Worker|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MZEeAQAAIAAJ|access-date=2013-10-29|year=1976|publisher=Lexington Books|isbn=978-0-669-01041-1|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140708002355/http://books.google.com/books?id=MZEeAQAAIAAJ|archive-date=2014-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been suggested that a prejudicial view of subordinates can be a particularly strong risk factor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last =Ashforth | first =Blake | title =Petty Tyranny in Organizations | journal =Human Relations | volume =47 | issue =7 | pages =755–778 | year =1994 | doi =10.1177/001872679404700701 | s2cid =145699243 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a recent study, bullies showed lower school performance-related self-esteem than non-involved students. They also showed higher social self-esteem than victims of traditional bullying.&lt;ref name="Perpetration and victimization in o"&gt;{{cite journal
 | author1= Burger, C. |author2= Bachmann, L.
 | year = 2021
 | title =  Perpetration and victimization in offline and cyber contexts: A variable- and person-oriented examination of associations and differences regarding domain-specific self-esteem and school adjustment.
 | journal = Int J Environ Res Public Health | volume = 18
 | issue = 19 
 |page= 10429
 | doi = 10.3390/ijerph181910429
 | pmid= 34639731
 |pmc= 8508291
 |doi-access= free
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Brain studies have shown that the section of the brain associated with reward becomes active when bullies are shown a video of someone inflicting pain on another.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/7714072.stm|title=Bullying tendency wired in brain|date=2008-11-07|access-date=2020-03-30|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Bystanders ===
Often, bullying takes place in the presence of a large group of relatively uninvolved bystanders. In many cases, it is the bully's ability to create the illusion they have the support of the majority present that instills the fear of "speaking out" in protestation of the bullying activities being observed by the group. Unless the "bully mentality" is effectively challenged in any given group in its early stages, it often becomes an accepted, or supported, [[Norm (social)|norm]] within the group.&lt;ref name="bystander attitudes"&gt;{{cite web | title =Bullies, Victims, and Bystanders | work =athealth.com: Consumer: Issues | publisher =Athealth.com | url =http://www.athealth.com/Consumer/issues/BulliesVictimsBystanders3.html | access-date =2013-10-29 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20140305091427/http://www.athealth.com/Consumer/issues/BulliesVictimsBystanders3.html | archive-date =2014-03-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title =New Tactics To Tackle Bystander's Role In Bullying | newspaper =Science Daily | department =Science News | publisher =Science Daily, LLC | date =2009-01-27 | url =https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2009/01/090125193150.htm | access-date =2013-10-29 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131029184804/https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2009/01/090125193150.htm | archive-date =2013-10-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Unless action is taken, a "[[Bullying culture|culture of bullying]]" is often perpetuated within a group for months, years, or longer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =419: Petty Tyrant | work =This American Life: Radio Archive | publisher =Chicago Public Media &amp; Ira Glass | date =2010-11-12 | url =http://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/419/petty-tyrant | access-date =2013-10-29 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131010093611/http://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/419/petty-tyrant | archive-date =2013-10-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bystanders who have been able to establish their own "friendship group" or "support group" have been found to be far more likely to opt to speak out against bullying behavior than those who have not.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title =Pasco students get 'hero' training to stop bullying | newspaper =[[The Tampa Tribune]] | department =Pasco County | publisher =Tampa Media Group, LLC | date =2010-10-12 | url =http://tbo.com/pasco-county/pasco-students-get-hero-training-to-stop-bullying-24060 | access-date =2013-10-29 | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20140502001344/http://tbo.com/pasco-county/pasco-students-get-hero-training-to-stop-bullying-24060 | archive-date =2014-05-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | title =Program Helps Students Combat Bullying - Students participate with enthusiasm | journal =Winning Harmony Counselling | date =2010-10-04 | url =http://www.winningharmony.com/News_and_Events.php | access-date =2013-10-29 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20130513031048/http://www.winningharmony.com/News_and_Events.php | archive-date =2013-05-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to communication of clear expectations that bystanders should intervene and increasing individual [[self-efficacy]], there is growing research to suggest interventions should build on the foundation that bullying is morally wrong.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 =Thornberg | first1 =Robert | last2 =Tenenbaum | first2 =Laura | last3 =Varjas | first3 =Kris | last4 =Meyers | first4 =Joel | last5 =Jungert | first5 =Tomas | last6 =Vanegas | first6 =Gina | title =Bystander Motivation in Bullying Incidents: To Intervene or Not to Intervene? | journal =Western Journal of Emergency Medicine | volume =13 | issue =3 | pages =247–252 | date =August 2012 | doi =10.5811/westjem.2012.3.11792| pmc =3415829 | pmid =22900122}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among adults, being a bystander to workplace bullying was linked to depression.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 =Jensen | first1 =I. B. | title =The impact of bystanding to workplace bullying on symptoms of depression among women and men in industry in Sweden: an empirical and theoretical longitudinal study | journal =International Archives of Occupational and Environmental Health | volume =86 | issue =6 | pages =709–716 | date =August 2013 | issn =1432-1246 | doi =10.1007/s00420-012-0813-1 | first2 =A. | last3 =Hagberg | first3 =J. | last4 =Jensen | first4 =I. B. | pmid =22940902 | pmc =3722445| last2 =Alipour }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bystander effect can be detrimental to the person being bullied.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Bystander Effect {{!}} Psychology Today |url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/bystander-effect |access-date=2023-02-28 |website=www.psychologytoday.com |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; People are less likely to stand up for someone or something when others are around. In the case of cyberbullying, people that see bullying happen on social media are less likely to say something back, whether online or in person. People can have good intentions and want to help, but with no action nothing will be accomplished. "The act of others stepping in is what will stop bullying".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Bystander Effect {{!}} Psychology Today |url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/basics/bystander-effect |access-date=2023-03-07 |website=www.psychologytoday.com |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; To stop the Bystander effect, people should be confident and stand up for what they believe in. Do not worry what people think of you, rather think of what the benefits can be for the person being bullied.

=== Victims ===
Dr. Cook says, "A typical victim is likely to be aggressive, lack social skills, think negative thoughts, experience difficulties in solving social problems, come from a negative family, school and community environments and be noticeably rejected and isolated by peers."&lt;ref name="APS2010"/&gt; Victims often have characteristics such as being physically and mentally weak, as well as being easily distraught emotionally. They may also have physical characteristics that make them easier targets for bullies such as being overweight or having some type of physical deformity. Boys are more likely to be victims of physical bullying while girls are more likely to be bullied indirectly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Paediatrics and Child Health|year= 2010 |volume=20 |issue=7|pages=315–320|last1=Vanderbilt |first1=Douglas |last2=Augustyn |first2=Marilyn |title=The effects of bullying |doi=10.1016/j.paed.2010.03.008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Low levels of self-esteem has been identified as a frequent antecedent of bullying victimization. Victims of traditional bullying tend to have lower global, social, body-related, and emotional self-esteem compared to uninvolved students.&lt;ref name="Perpetration and victimization in o"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 | author1= Andreou E.
 | year = 2000
 | title =  Bully/victim problems and their association with psychological constructs in 8-to 12-year-old Greek schoolchildren.
 | journal = Aggressive Behavior
 | volume = 26
 | issue = 1 
 | pages = 49–56
 | doi = 10.1002/(SICI)1098-2337(2000)26:1&lt;49::AID-AB4&gt;3.0.CO;2-M
 
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 | author1= Austin S. |author2= Joseph S.
 | year = 1996
 | title =  Assessment of bully/victim problems in 8 to 11 year-olds.
 | journal = British Journal of Educational Psychology
 | volume = 66
 | issue = 4 
 |pages= 447–456
 | doi = 10.1111/j.2044-8279.1996.tb01211.x
 | pmid= 9008423
 | url = https://bpspsychub.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.2044-8279.1996.tb01211.x?sid=nlm%3Apubmed
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 | author1= Callaghan S. |author2= Joseph S.
 | year = 1995
 | title =  Self-concept and peer victimization among schoolchildren.
 | journal = Personality and Individual Differences
 | volume = 18
 | issue = 1 
 | pages = 161–163
 | doi = 10.1016/0191-8869(94)00127-E
 | url = https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/019188699400127E
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 | author1= Neary A. |author2= Joseph S.
 | year = 1994
 | title =  Peer victimization and its relationship to self-concept and depression among schoolgirls.
 | journal = Personality and Individual Differences
 | volume = 16
 | issue = 1
 |pages= 183–186
 | doi = 10.1016/0191-8869(94)90122-8
 | url = https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/0191886994901228
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; 
Victims of cyberbullying, on the other hand, may not have lower self-esteem scores than uninvolved students but might have higher body-related self-esteem than both victims of traditional bullying and bullies.&lt;ref name="Perpetration and victimization in o"/&gt;

It has also been shown that victims are more likely to employ self-defeating or self-deprecating humor intended to entertain others at the expense of themselves and their own feelings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Burger C | journal=International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health | title=Humor styles, bullying victimization and psychological school adjustment: Mediation, moderation and person-oriented analyses | volume=19 | issue=18 | page=11415 | date= 2022 | issn=1661-7827 | doi=10.3390/ijerph191811415| pmid=36141686 | pmc=9517355 | doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The results of a [[meta-analysis]] conducted by Cook and published by the [[American Psychological Association]] in 2010 concluded the main risk factors for children and adolescents being bullied, and also for becoming bullies, are the lack of [[social problem-solving]] skills.&lt;ref name="APS2010"/&gt;

Children who are bullied often show physical or emotional signs, such as: being afraid to attend school, complaining of headaches or a loss of appetite, a lack of interest in school activities, or in spending time with friends or family, reluctance to go out in public for fear they may encounter their bullies in public places other than school, and having an overall sense of sadness.

== Effects ==
{{Undue weight section|date=May 2014}}
Mona O'Moore of the Anti-Bullying Centre at Trinity College in Dublin, has written, "There is a growing body of research which indicates that individuals, whether child or adult, who are persistently subjected to abusive behavior are at risk of stress related illness which can sometimes lead to [[suicide]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Anti-Bullying Centre | work =Trinity College Dublin | url =http://www.abc.tcd.ie/ | access-date =2013-10-28 | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131125190018/http://www.abc.tcd.ie/ | archive-date =2013-11-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Those who have been the targets of bullying can develop long-term emotional and behavioral problems. Bullying can cause [[loneliness]], [[Depression (mood)|depression]], [[anxiety]], lead to low [[self-esteem]] and increased susceptibility to illness.&lt;ref name="WilliamsForgas2013"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Kipling D. Williams|author2=Joseph P. Forgas|author3=William Von Hippel|title=The Social Outcast: Ostracism, Social Exclusion, Rejection, and Bullying|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FHWhtvCm5LAC&amp;pg=PR2|access-date=2013-10-29|date=13 May 2013|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-1-135-42338-4|pages=2–|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140103014229/http://books.google.com/books?id=FHWhtvCm5LAC&amp;pg=PR2|archive-date=3 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bullying has also been shown to cause maladjustment in young children, and targets of bullying who were also bullies themselves exhibit even greater social difficulties.&lt;ref name="Perpetration and victimization in o"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Arsenault|first=Louise PhD|author2=Walsh, Elizabeth |author3=Trzesniewski, Kali |s2cid=28961503|title=Bullying Victimization Uniquely Contributes to Adjustment Problems in Young Children: A Nationally Representative Cohort Study|journal=Pediatrics|date=July 2006|volume=118|issue=1|pages=130–138|doi=10.1542/peds.2005-2388|issn=0031-4005|pmid=16818558|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; A mental health report also found that bullying was linked to eating disorders, anxiety, body dysmorphia and other negative psychological effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=UK Mental Health Study|url=https://www.brandwatch.com/reports/uk-mental-health-study/|website=Brandwatch|publisher=Brandwatch, Ditch the Label}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both victims and perpetrators have been shown to exhibit higher levels of loneliness.&lt;ref name="Perpetration and victimization in o"/&gt;

=== Suicide ===
{{Main|Bullying and suicide|List of suicides that have been attributed to bullying}}
Even though there is evidence that bullying increases the risk of suicide, bullying alone does not cause suicide. [[Depression (mood)|Depression]] is one of the main reasons why kids who are bullied die by suicide.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Kim YS |author2=Leventhal B |title=Bullying and suicide. A review |journal=International Journal of Adolescent Medicine and Health |volume=20 |issue=2 |pages=133–54 |year=2008 |pmid=18714552|doi=10.1515/IJAMH.2008.20.2.133 |s2cid=41651943 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is estimated that between 15 and 25 children die by suicide every year in the UK alone because they are being bullied.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.coastkid.org/si-sob.html Statistics on bullying] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050217152258/http://www.coastkid.org/si-sob.html |date=February 17, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Certain groups seem to incur a higher risk for suicide, such as [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native American]]s, [[Alaskan Native]]s, [[Asian American]]s, and [[LGBT]] people. When someone feels unsupported by family or friends, it can make the situation much worse for the victim.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stopbullying.gov/at-risk/effects/#suicide Effects of Bullying | StopBullying.gov&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151120072457/http://www.stopbullying.gov/at-risk/effects |date=2015-11-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a self-report study completed in New York by 9th through 12th graders, victims of bullying reported more depressive symptoms and psychological distress than those who did not experience bullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=BRUNSTEIN KLOMEK|first1=ANAT | author-link1=Anat Brunstein Klomek |last2=MARROCCO|first2=FRANK|last3=KLEINMAN|first3=MARJORIE|last4=SCHONFELD|first4=IRVIN S.|last5=GOULD|first5=MADELYN S.|date=January 2007|title=Bullying, Depression, and Suicidality in Adolescents|journal=Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry|volume=46|issue=1|pages=40–49|doi=10.1097/01.chi.0000242237.84925.18|pmid=17195728|issn=0890-8567|url=https://academicworks.cuny.edu/cc_pubs/309}}&lt;/ref&gt; All types of involvement in bullying among both boys and girls is associated with depression even a couple years later.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Kaltiala-Heino|first1=Riittakerttu|last2=Fröjd|first2=Sari|last3=Marttunen|first3=Mauri|date=2009-07-09|title=Involvement in bullying and depression in a 2-year follow-up in middle adolescence|journal=European Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry|volume=19|issue=1|pages=45–55|doi=10.1007/s00787-009-0039-2|pmid=19588185|s2cid=23077909|issn=1018-8827|url=http://www.ssoar.info/ssoar/handle/document/20289}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another study that followed up with Finnish teens two years after the initial survey showed that depression and suicidal ideation is higher with teens who are bullied than those who did not report experiencing bullying.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; A Dutch longitudinal study on elementary students reported that boys who are bully-victims, who play both roles of a victim and a bully, were more likely to experience depression or serious suicidal ideation than the other roles, victims or bullies only, while girls who have any involvement in bullying have a higher level of risk for depression.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Fekkes|first1=M.|last2=Pijpers|first2=F. I. M.|last3=Verloove-Vanhorick|first3=S. P.|date=2005-02-01|title=Bullying: who does what, when and where? Involvement of children, teachers and parents in bullying behavior|journal=Health Education Research|volume=20|issue=1|pages=81–91|doi=10.1093/her/cyg100|pmid=15253993|issn=0268-1153|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a study of high school students completed in Boston, students who self reported being victims of bullying were more likely to consider suicide when compared to youth who did not report being bullied.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Hepburn|first1=Lisa|last2=Azrael|first2=Deborah|last3=Molnar|first3=Beth|last4=Miller|first4=Matthew|date=July 2012|title=Bullying and Suicidal Behaviors Among Urban High School Youth|journal=Journal of Adolescent Health|volume=51|issue=1|pages=93–95|doi=10.1016/j.jadohealth.2011.12.014|pmid=22727083|issn=1054-139X}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same study also showed a higher risk of suicidal consideration in youth who report being a perpetrator, victim, or victim-perpetrator. Victims and victim-bullies are associated with a higher risk of suicide attempts. The place where youth live also appears to differentiate their bullying experiences such that those living in more urban areas who reported both being bullied and bullying others appear to show higher risk of suicidal ideation and suicide attempts.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; A national survey given to American 6th through 10th grade students found that cyberbullying victims experience a higher level of depression than victims experiencing other forms of bullying. This can be related to the anonymity behind social media.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Wang|first1=Jing|last2=Nansel|first2=Tonja R.|last3=Iannotti|first3=Ronald J.|date=April 2011|title=Cyber and Traditional Bullying: Differential Association With Depression|journal=Journal of Adolescent Health|volume=48|issue=4|pages=415–417|doi=10.1016/j.jadohealth.2010.07.012|issn=1054-139X|pmc=3058261|pmid=21402273}}&lt;/ref&gt; If a teen is being bullied and is displaying symptoms of depression it should be questioned and interventions should be implemented.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The Danish study showed that kids who are bullied talked to their parents and teachers about it and some reported a decrease in bullying or a stop in the bullying after a teacher or parent intervened. The study emphasizes the importance of implementing program-collaborations in schools to have programs and anti-bullying interventions in place to prevent and properly intervene when it occurs.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; The study also shows the importance of having parents and teachers talk to the bullies about their bullying behavior in order to provide the necessary support for those experiencing bullying.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

While some people find it very easy to ignore a bully, others may find it very difficult and reach a breaking point. There have been cases of apparent bullying suicides that have been reported closely by the media. These include the deaths of [[Suicide of Ryan Halligan|Ryan Halligan]], [[Suicide of Phoebe Prince|Phoebe Prince]], [[Suicide of Dawn-Marie Wesley|Dawn-Marie Wesley]], [[Suicide of Nicola Ann Raphael|Nicola Ann Raphael]], [[Suicide of Megan Meier|Megan Meier]], [[Suicide of Audrie Pott|Audrie Pott]], [[Suicide of Tyler Clementi|Tyler Clementi]], [[Suicide of Jamey Rodemeyer|Jamey Rodemeyer]], [[Suicide of Kenneth Weishuhn|Kenneth Weishuhn]], [[Suicide of Jadin Bell|Jadin Bell]], [[Suicide of Kelly Yeomans|Kelly Yeomans]], [[Suicide of Rehtaeh Parsons|Rehtaeh Parsons]], [[Suicide of Amanda Todd|Amanda Todd]], [[Brodie's Law (act)|Brodie Panlock]],&lt;ref name="fine"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/men-who-tormented-suicide-waitress-brodie-panlock-fined/news-story/45a1de04af03cae09f0b6afc9ebd76c2 | title=Men who tormented suicide waitress Brodie Panlock fined |newspaper=Daily Telegraph | access-date=14 August 2017| date=2010-02-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Jessica Haffer,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Jessica Kassandra Haffer | publisher =Keith &amp; Jeralyn Haffer | url =http://www.jessicahaffer.com/ | access-date =2013-10-28 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20140104102027/http://jessicahaffer.com/ | archive-date =2014-01-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Suicide of Hamed Nastoh|Hamed Nastoh]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Hamed Nastoh | url =http://www.angelfire.com/bc2/hamed/ | access-date =2013-10-28 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131029222924/http://www.angelfire.com/bc2/hamed/ | archive-date =2013-10-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Suicide of Sladjana Vidovic|Sladjana Vidovic]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.clevescene.com/scene-and-heard/archives/2010/08/23/family-of-sladjana-vidovic-16-year-old-who-committed-suicide-suing-mentor-schools|title=Family of Sladjana Vidovic, 16-Year-Old Who Committed Suicide, Suing Mentor Schools|last=Grzegorek|first=Vince|date=2010-08-23|access-date=2018-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; April Himes,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Caruso | first =Kevin | title =April Himes Memorial | work =Suicide.org | url =http://www.suicide.org/memorials/april-himes.html | access-date =2013-10-28 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20121227145112/http://www.suicide.org/memorials/april-himes.html | archive-date =2012-12-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Cherice Moralez&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =McLaughlin | first =Elliot C. | title =Montana teen loved pit bulls, poetry before rape and suicide | work =CNN | department =U.S. | publisher =Cable News Network | date =2013-08-30 | url =http://edition.cnn.com/2013/08/30/us/montana-teacher-rape-victim-profile/index.html | access-date =2013-10-29 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131017010102/http://edition.cnn.com/2013/08/30/us/montana-teacher-rape-victim-profile/index.html | archive-date =2013-10-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Suicide of Rebecca Ann Sedwick|Rebecca Ann Sedwick]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Pearce | first =Matt | title =Florida girl, 12, found dead after bullies said 'kill yourself' | newspaper =Los Angeles Times | department =U.S.: Nation Now | date =2013-09-12 | url =https://www.latimes.com/nation/nationnow/la-na-nn-florida-cyberbullying-20130912,0,1429218.story#axzz2j8q54wL8 | access-date =2013-10-29 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131030125706/http://www.latimes.com/nation/nationnow/la-na-nn-florida-cyberbullying-20130912%2C0%2C1429218.story#axzz2j8q54wL8 | archive-date =2013-10-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the suicide awareness voices for education, suicide is one of the leading causes of death for youth from 15 to 24 years old. Over 16 percent of students seriously consider suicide, 13 percent create a plan, and 8 percent have made a serious attempt.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=bullying suicide statistics|url=http://nobullying.com/bullying-suicide-statistics/|access-date=2019-02-06|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180315013632/https://nobullying.com/bullying-suicide-statistics/|archive-date=2018-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Strength and wisdom ===
Some have argued that bullying can teach life lessons and instill strength. Helene Guldberg, a child development academic, sparked controversy when she argued that being a target of bullying can teach a child "how to manage disputes and boost their ability to interact with others", and that teachers should not intervene but leave children to respond to the bullying themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author =Tanya | title =Child Development Academician Says Bullying Is Beneficial To Kids | work =Med India | department =News | publisher =Medindia | date =2009-02-02 | url =http://www.medindia.net/news/Child-Development-Academician-Says-Bullying-Is-Beneficial-To-Kids-46992-1.htm | access-date =2013-10-29 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131101060052/http://www.medindia.net/news/Child-Development-Academician-Says-Bullying-Is-Beneficial-To-Kids-46992-1.htm | archive-date =2013-11-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Others, however, have pointed out that this is only true for normal peer conflicts but not for bullying cases.&lt;ref name="School bullying is not a conflict"/&gt;

The teaching of anti-bullying coping skills to children, carers and teachers has been found to be an effective long-term means of reducing bullying incidence rates and a valuable skill-set for individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.careforkids.com.au/childcarenews/2010/july/bullying.html Positive Anti-Bullying Strategies by Melissa Graham] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131110160827/http://www.careforkids.com.au/childcarenews/2010/july/bullying.html |date=2013-11-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Testosterone production ===
Statistically controlling for age and pubertal status, results indicated that on average verbally bullied girls produced less testosterone, and verbally bullied boys produced more testosterone than their nonbullied counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Vaillancourt |first1=T |title=Androgen dynamics in the context of children's peer relations: an examination of the links between testosterone and peer victimization |journal=Aggressive Behavior |volume=35 |issue=1 |pages=103–13 |date=2009 |pmid=19021234 |doi=10.1002/ab.20288 |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Dark triad ==
{{Main|Dark triad}}
Research on the dark triad ([[narcissism]], [[Machiavellianism (psychology)|Machiavellianism]], and [[psychopathy]]) indicate a correlation with bullying as part of evidence of the aversive nature of those traits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Chabrol H. |author2=Van Leeuwen N. |author3=Rodgers R. |author4=Séjourné S.| year = 2009 | title = Contributions of psychopathic, narcissistic, Machiavellian, and sadistic personality traits to juvenile delinquency|journal = Personality and Individual Differences|volume =47|issue=7|pages=734–39|doi=10.1016/j.paid.2009.06.020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Projection ==
{{Main|Psychological projection}}
A bully may project his/her own feelings of vulnerability onto the target(s) of the bullying activity. Despite the fact that a bully's typically denigrating activities are aimed at the bully's targets, the true source of such negativity is ultimately almost always found in the bully's own sense of personal insecurity and/or vulnerability.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Gilbert, ''Overcoming Depression'' (1999) p.{{nbsp}}185–6&lt;/ref&gt; Such aggressive projections of displaced [[negative emotion]]s can occur anywhere from the micro-level of interpersonal relationships, all the way up through to the macro-level of international politics, or even international armed conflict.&lt;ref name="micro and macro projection"&gt;Carl G. Jung ed., ''Man and his Symbols'' (London 1978) p.{{nbsp}}181–2&lt;/ref&gt;

== Emotional intelligence ==
{{Main|Bullying and emotional intelligence}}
Bullying is abusive social interaction between peers which can include aggression, harassment, and violence. Bullying is typically repetitive and enacted by those who are in a position of [[Abusive power and control|power]] over the victim. A growing body of research illustrates a significant relationship between bullying and [[emotional intelligence]] (EI). [[John D. Mayer|Mayer]] et al., (2008) defines the dimensions of overall EI as "accurately perceiving emotion, using emotions to facilitate thought, understanding emotion, and managing emotion".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Mayer | first1 = J.D. | last2 = Roberts | first2 = R.D | last3 = Barasade | first3 = S.G. | year = 2008 | title = Human abilities: Emotional intelligence | journal = [[Annual Review of Psychology]] | volume = 59 | issue = 1| pages = 507–536 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.psych.59.103006.093646 | pmid = 17937602 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The concept combines emotional and intellectual processes.&lt;ref name="Tolegenova"&gt;{{Cite journal | doi=10.1016/j.sbspro.2012.12.142|title = A Theoretical Formation of Emotional Intelligence and Childhood Trauma among Adolescents| journal=Procedia - Social and Behavioral Sciences| volume=69| pages=1891–1894|year = 2012|last1 = Tolegenova|first1 = A.A.| last2=Jakupov| first2=S.M.| last3=Chung| first3=Man Cheung| last4=Saduova| first4=S.| last5=Jakupov| first5=M.S.| doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lower emotional intelligence appears to be related to involvement in bullying, as the bully and/or the victim of bullying. EI seems to play an important role in both bullying behavior and [[victimization]] in bullying; given that EI is illustrated to be malleable, EI education could greatly improve bullying prevention and intervention initiatives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Mckenna | first1 = J. | last2 = Webb | first2 = J. | year = 2013 | title = Emotional intelligence | journal = British Journal of Occupational Therapy | volume = 76 | issue = 12| page = 560 | doi = 10.1177/030802261307601202 | s2cid = 208741104 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Context ==

=== Internet ===
{{Main|Cyberbullying}}
Cyberbullying is any bullying done through the use of technology. This form of bullying can easily go undetected because of lack of authoritative (including parental) supervision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Kokkinos CM, Antoniadou N, Asdre A, Voulgaridou K | journal=Deviant Behavior | title=Parenting and internet behavior predictors of cyber-bullying and cyber-victimization among preadolescents | volume=37 | issue=4 | pages=439–455 | date= 2016 | issn=0163-9625 | doi=10.1080/01639625.2015.1060087| s2cid=146951404 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Because bullies can pose as someone else, it is the most anonymous form of bullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Barlett CP, DeWitt CC, Maronna B, Johnson K | journal=Violence and Gender | title=Social media use as a tool to facilitate or reduce cyberbullying perpetration: A review focusing on anonymous and nonanonymous social media platforms | issue=vio.2017.0057 | date= 2018 | volume=5 | pages=147–152 | issn=2326-7836 | doi=10.1089/vio.2017.0057| s2cid=240271795 | doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Cyberbullying includes abuse using email, instant messaging, text messaging, websites, and social networking sites.&lt;ref name="BoltonGraeve2005"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Jose Bolton|author2=Stan Graeve|title=No Room for Bullies: From the Classroom to Cyberspace|url=https://archive.org/details/noroomforbullies0000bolt|url-access=registration|access-date=2013-10-29|year=2005|publisher=Boys Town Press|isbn=978-1-889322-67-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Particular watchdog organizations have been designed to contain the spread of cyberbullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmc = 3477910 | pmid=22401525 | doi=10.2105/AJPH.2011.300608 | volume=102 | title=Social media and suicide: a public health perspective | year=2012 | journal=Am J Public Health | pages=S195–200 | last1 = Luxton | first1 = DD | last2 = June | first2 = JD | last3 = Fairall | first3 = JM| issue=Suppl 2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Disability ===
{{Main|Disability bullying}}
Disabled people are disproportionately affected by bullying and abuse, and such activity has been cited as a [[hate crime]].&lt;ref name="Quarmby2011"&gt;{{cite book|author=Katherine Quarmby|title=Scapegoat: Why We Are Failing Disabled People|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lglMYgEACAAJ|access-date=2013-10-29|year=2011|publisher=Portobello Books Limited|isbn=978-1-84627-321-6|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140101120453/http://books.google.com/books?id=lglMYgEACAAJ|archive-date=2014-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bullying is not limited to those who are visibly disabled, such as wheelchair users or physically deformed such as those with a cleft lip, but also those with developmental disabilities such as [[autism]]&lt;ref name="Sainsbury2009"&gt;{{cite book|author=Clare Sainsbury|title=Martian in the Playground: Understanding the Schoolchild with Asperger's Syndrome|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TbGwEaH8eAIC|access-date=2013-10-29|date=30 September 2009|publisher=SAGE Publications|isbn=978-1-4462-4398-5|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140101120424/http://books.google.com/books?id=TbGwEaH8eAIC|archive-date=1 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Attwood2006"&gt;{{cite book|author=Tony Attwood|title=The Complete Guide to Asperger's Syndrome|url=https://archive.org/details/completeguidetoa00attw|url-access=registration|access-date=2013-10-29|year=2006|publisher=Jessica Kingsley Publishers|isbn=978-1-84310-495-7|pages=[https://archive.org/details/completeguidetoa00attw/page/95 95]–111}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[developmental coordination disorder]].&lt;ref name="Kirby2002"&gt;{{cite book|author=Amanda Kirby|title=Dyspraxia: The Hidden Handicap|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=so-3-vIf0lkC|access-date=2013-10-29|date=1 October 2002|publisher=Souvenir Press|isbn=978-0-285-63512-8|pages=106–113|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140101120440/http://books.google.com/books?id=so-3-vIf0lkC|archive-date=1 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Brookes2005"&gt;{{cite book|author=Geoff Brookes|title=Dyspraxia|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wZDqe-SckjIC|access-date=2013-10-29|date=January 2005|publisher=Continuum|isbn=978-0-8264-7581-7|pages=43–46|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140101120352/http://books.google.com/books?id=wZDqe-SckjIC|archive-date=2014-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is an additional problem that those with learning disabilities are often not as able to explain things to other people, so are more likely to be disbelieved or ignored if they do complain.{{citation needed|date=December 2014}}

=== Homosexuality ===
{{Main|LGBT bullying}}
Gay bullying and [[gay bashing]] designate direct or indirect [[verbal abuse|verbal]] or [[physical abuse|physical]] actions by a person or group against someone who is gay or lesbian, or perceived to be so due to rumors or because they are considered to fit gay stereotypes. Gay and lesbian youth are more likely than straight youth to report bullying, as well as be bullied.&lt;ref name="Berlan et al., 2010"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 =Berlan | first1 =Elise D. | last2 =Corliss | first2 =Heather L. | last3 =Field | first3 =Alison E. | last4 =Goodman | first4 =Elizabeth | last5 =Austin | first5 =S. Bryn | title =Sexual Orientation and Bullying Among Adolescents in the Growing Up Today Study | journal =Journal of Adolescent Health | volume =46 | issue =4 | pages =366–371 | date =2010-01-28 | url =http://www.journals.elsevierhealth.com/periodicals/jah/article/S1054-139X(09)00647-8/fulltext | doi =10.1016/j.jadohealth.2009.10.015 | access-date = 2013-10-28 | pmid =20307826 | pmc =2844864}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Meyer|first=Doug|title=The Disregarding of Heteronormativity: Emphasizing a Happy Queer Adulthood and Localizing Anti-Queer Violence to Adolescent Schools|journal=Sexuality Research &amp; Social Policy|volume=14|issue=3|pages=331–344|doi=10.1007/s13178-016-0272-7|year=2017|s2cid=151482192}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Law ===
{{Main|Legal abuse}}
Legal bullying is the bringing of a [[Vexatious litigation|vexatious legal action]] to control and punish a person. Legal bullying can often take the form of frivolous, repetitive, or burdensome lawsuits brought to intimidate the defendant into submitting to the litigant's request, not because of the legal merit of the litigant's position, but principally due to the defendant's inability to maintain the legal battle. This can also take the form of [[Strategic Lawsuit Against Public Participation]] (SLAPP). It was partially concern about the potential for this kind of abuse that helped to fuel the [[protests against SOPA and PIPA]] in the United States in 2011 and 2012.{{citation needed|date=August 2020}}

=== Military ===
{{Main|Bullying in the military|Dedovshchina}}
In 2000, the UK [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] (MOD) defined bullying as "the use of physical strength or the [[abuse of authority]] to intimidate or victimize others, or to give unlawful punishments".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Dannatt | first =Sir Richard | title =Values and Standards of the British Army | chapter =Lawful: Paragraph 20 | publisher =the British Army | year =2008 | chapter-url =http://www.army.mod.uk/documents/general/v_s_of_the_british_army.pdf | access-date =2013-10-29 | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20130817150435/http://www.army.mod.uk/documents/general/v_s_of_the_british_army.pdf | archive-date =2013-08-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some argue that this behaviour should be allowed, due to ways in which "soldiering" is different from other occupations. Soldiers expected to risk their lives should, according to them, develop strength of body and spirit to accept bullying.&lt;ref name="CallaghanKernic2003"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Jean M. Callaghan|author2=Franz Kernic|title=Armed Forces and International Security: Global Trends and Issues|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tvnCKuSdOEwC&amp;pg=PA19|access-date=2013-10-29|year=2003|publisher=LIT Verlag Münster|isbn=978-3-8258-7227-4|pages=19–|chapter=Chapter 2: "Social Psychology" of the Individual Soldier|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140101120837/http://books.google.com/books?id=tvnCKuSdOEwC&amp;pg=PA19|archive-date=2014-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Parenting ===
{{See also|Child abuse|Narcissistic parent|Parental narcissistic abuse}}
Parents who may [[Displacement (psychology)|displace]] their anger, insecurity, or a persistent need to dominate and [[Abusive power and control|control]] upon their children in excessive ways have been proven to increase the likelihood that their own children will in turn become overly aggressive or controlling towards their peers.&lt;ref name="parent bullying"&gt;{{cite web | last =Priesnitz | first =Wendy | title =Parental Bullying Creates Bullies | work =Natural Child Magazine | publisher =Wendy Priesnitz | url =http://www.naturalchildmagazine.com/news/parental_bullying_creates_bullies.htm | access-date =2013-10-29 | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131031134551/http://www.naturalchildmagazine.com/news/parental_bullying_creates_bullies.htm | archive-date =2013-10-31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[American Psychological Association]] advises on its website that parents who may suspect their own children may be engaging in bullying activities among their peers should carefully consider the examples which they themselves may be setting for their own children regarding how they typically interact with their own peers, colleagues, and children.&lt;ref name = "APA on parental bullying"&gt;{{cite web | title =Bullying: How parents, teachers, and kids can take action to prevent bullying | work =American Psychological Association | url = http://www.apa.org/helpcenter/bullying.aspx | access-date = 2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Prison ===
{{Main|Prisoner abuse}}
The prison environment is known for bullying. An additional complication is the staff and their relationships with the inmates. Thus, the following possible bullying scenarios are possible:
* Inmate bullies inmate (echoing school bullying)
* Staff bullies inmate
* Staff bullies staff (a manifestation of workplace bullying)
* Inmate bullies staff

=== School ===
{{Main|School bullying}}
[[File:CDC DASH anti-bullying PSA.jpg|thumb|A [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]] graphic presenting school anti-bullying guidelines]]
It is important to distinguish school bullying that per definition has the goal of harming the victim from normal peer conflict that is an inherent part of everyday school life and often promotes social development.&lt;ref name="School bullying is not a conflict"/&gt; Unlike normal conflict, bullying is a systematic and repeated abuse committed intentionally by another student who has more power (physical, social, or otherwise). School bullies may taunt and tease their target before finally physically bullying them. Bystanders typically choose to either participate or watch, sometimes out of fear of becoming the next target.

Bullying can occur in nearly any part in or around the school building, although it may occur more frequently during physical education classes and activities such as recess. Bullying also takes place in school hallways, bathrooms, on school buses and while waiting for buses, and in classes that require group work and/or after school activities. Bullying in school sometimes consists of a group of students taking advantage of or isolating one student in particular and gaining the loyalty of bystanders who want to avoid becoming the next target. The 2011 documentary [[Bully (2011 film)|''Bully'']] showcases the lives of five American public school students who face bullying in school and while on the school bus. The bullying is shown to affect the students both at school and in their homes.

Teachers play an important role in bullying prevention and intervention because they are the adults who spend most of their time with the students.&lt;ref name="dx.doi.org"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Burger C, Strohmeier D, Kollerová L | journal=Journal of Youth and Adolescence | title=Teachers can make a difference in bullying: Effects of teacher interventions on students' adoption of bully, victim, bully-victim or defender roles across time | date= 2022 | volume=51 | issue=12 | pages=2312–2327 | issn=0047-2891 | doi=10.1007/s10964-022-01674-6| pmid=36053439 | pmc=9596519 | s2cid=252009527 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Yoon JS, Kerber K | journal=Research in Education | title=Bullying: Elementary teachers' attitudes and intervention strategies | volume=69 | issue=1 | pages=27–35 | date= 2003 | issn=0034-5237 | doi=10.7227/rie.69.3| s2cid=219984495 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Bullying can, however, also be perpetrated by teachers and the school system itself; there is an inherent power differential in the system that can easily predispose to subtle or covert abuse ([[relational aggression]] or [[passive aggression]]), [[humiliation]], or exclusion—even while maintaining overt commitments to anti-bullying policies.&lt;ref name="GarbarinodeLara2003"&gt;{{cite book|author1=James Garbarino|author2=Ellen deLara|title=And Words Can Hurt Forever: How to Protect Adolescents from Bullying, Harassment, and Emotional Violence|url=https://archive.org/details/andwordscanhurtf00garb|url-access=registration|access-date=2013-10-29|date=2 September 2003|publisher=Free Press|isbn=978-0-7432-2899-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last=Witted |first=Kathryn Suzanne |title=Student Reports of Physical and Psychological Maltreatment in Schools: An Under Explored Aspect of Student Victimization in Schools |work=PhD dissertation, University of Tennessee |year=2005 |url=http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3874&amp;context=utk_graddiss |access-date=2013-10-29 |url-status=live |archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131031121558/http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3874&amp;context=utk_graddiss |archive-date=2013-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1177/0013124507304487 |title=Do Teachers Bully Students?: Findings From a Survey of Students in an Alternative Education Setting |year=2007 |last1=Whitted |first1=K. S. |last2=Dupper |first2=D. R. |journal=Education and Urban Society |volume=40 |pages=329–341|issue=3|s2cid=143894407 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, in Canada, a North American legal precedent was set by a mother and her son, after the son was bullied in his public school. The mother and son won a court case against the Ottawa-Carleton District School Board, making this the first case in North America where a school board has been found negligent in a bullying case for failing to meet the standard of care (the "duty of care" that the school board owes to its students). Thus, it sets a precedent of a school board being found liable in negligence for harm caused to a child, because they failed to protect a child from the bullying actions of other students. There has been only one other similar bullying case and it was won in Australia in 2013 (''Oyston v. St. Patricks College'', 2013).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ottawacommunitynews.com/news-story/6773614-family-wins-precedent-setting-case-against-public-school-board/ |title=Ottawa News &amp;#124; Latest Information, Updates &amp; Articles &amp;#124; Ottawa Citizen |access-date=2016-07-22 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170210080755/http://www.ottawacommunitynews.com/news-story/6773614-family-wins-precedent-setting-case-against-public-school-board/ |archive-date=2017-02-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Heterosexuality ===
{{Main|Sexual bullying}}
{{See also|Slut-shaming}}
Sexual bullying is "any bullying behaviour, whether physical or non-physical, that is based on a person's sexuality or gender. It is when sexuality or gender is used as a weapon by boys or girls towards other boys or girls – although it is more commonly directed at girls. It can be carried out to a person's face, behind their back or through the use of technology."&lt;ref name=NSPCC02&gt;{{cite web |url=http://w1.qehs.net/moodle2/pluginfile.php/10744/mod_resource/content/1/Sexual%20bullying.pdf |title=The NSPCC working definition of Sexual Bullying |publisher=[[National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children|NSPCC]] |access-date=13 September 2016 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220065205/http://w1.qehs.net/moodle2/pluginfile.php/10744/mod_resource/content/1/Sexual%20bullying.pdf |archive-date=20 December 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Transsexuality ===
{{Main|Trans bashing}}
Trans bashing is the act of [[victimizing]] a person physically, sexually, or verbally because they are [[transgender]] or [[Transsexualism|transsexual]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news.com.au/heraldsun/story/0,21985,20774504-5005961,00.html Guilty plea over transsexual bashing] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080502173830/http://www.news.com.au/heraldsun/story/0%2C21985%2C20774504-5005961%2C00.html |date=2008-05-02 }} By Mariza O'Keefe in ''Herald Sun''&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike [[gay bashing]], it is committed because of the target's actual or perceived [[gender identity]], not [[sexual orientation]].

=== Work ===
{{Main|Workplace bullying}}
Workplace bullying occurs when an employee experiences a persistent pattern of mistreatment from others in the workplace that causes harm.&lt;ref&gt;Rayner, C. &amp; Keashley, L. (2005). Bullying at work: A perspective from Britain and North America. In S. Fox &amp; P. E. Spector (eds.) Counterproductive work behavior: Investigations of actors and targets (pp. 271-296). Washington DC: American Psychological Association.&lt;/ref&gt; Workplace bullying can include such tactics as [[verbal abuse|verbal]], [[nonverbal]], [[psychological abuse|psychological]], [[physical abuse|physical]] abuse and [[humiliation]]. This type of [[workplace aggression]] is particularly difficult because, unlike the typical forms of [[school bullying]], workplace bullies often operate within the established rules and policies of their organization and their society. Bullying in the workplace is in the majority of cases reported as having been perpetrated by someone in authority over the target. Bullies can also be peers, and occasionally can be subordinates.&lt;ref&gt;Rayner, C., &amp; Cooper, C. L. (2006). Workplace Bullying. In Kelloway, E., Barling, J. &amp; Hurrell Jr., J. (eds.), Handbook of workplace violence (pp. 47-90). Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first known documented use of "workplace bullying" is in 1992 in a book by [[Andrea Adams]] called ''Bullying at Work: How to Confront and Overcome It''.&lt;ref&gt;
[https://books.google.com/ngrams/graph?content=workplace+bullying&amp;case_insensitive=on&amp;year_start=1990&amp;year_end=2008&amp;corpus=15&amp;smoothing=3&amp;share=&amp;direct_url=t4%3B%2Cworkplace%20bullying%3B%2Cc0%3B%2Cs0%3B%3Bworkplace%20bullying%3B%2Cc0%3B%3BWorkplace%20Bullying%3B%2Cc0%3B%3BWorkplace%20bullying%3B%2Cc0 Google ngrams]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Andrea Adams|Adams, Andrea]] with contributions from Crawford, Neil ''Bullying at Work: How to Confront and Overcome It'' (1992)&lt;/ref&gt;

Research has also investigated the impact of the larger organizational context on bullying as well as the group-level processes that impact on the incidence, and maintenance of bullying behavior.&lt;ref&gt;Ramsay, S., Troth, A &amp; Branch, S. (2010). Work-place bullying: A group processes framework ''Journal of Occupational and Organizational Psychology, 84(4), 799-816.''&lt;/ref&gt; Bullying can be covert or overt. It may be missed by superiors or known by many throughout the organization. Negative effects are not limited to the targeted individuals, and may lead to a decline in [[employee morale]] and a change in [[organizational culture]].&lt;ref name="SilentEpidemic" /&gt; A [[Cochrane (organisation)|Cochrane Collaboration]] [[systematic review]] has found very low quality [[Scientific evidence|evidence]] to suggest that organizational and individual interventions may prevent bullying behaviors in the workplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|volume = 1|pages = CD009778|last1=Gillen|first1=Patricia A|last2=Sinclair|first2=Marlene|last3=Kernohan|first3=W George|last4=Begley|first4=Cecily M|last5=Luyben|first5=Ans G|date=2017-01-30|doi=10.1002/14651858.cd009778.pub2|pmid = 28134445|pmc = 6464940|title = Interventions for prevention of bullying in the workplace|journal = Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews| issue=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Academia ====
{{Main|Bullying in academia}}
Bullying in academia is workplace bullying of scholars and staff in academia, especially places of higher education such as colleges and universities. It is believed to be common, although has not received as much attention from researchers as bullying in some other contexts.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal | last1 =Keashly | first1 =Loraleigh | last2 =Neuman | first2 =Joel H. | title =Faculty Experiences with Bullying in Higher Education - Causes, Consequences, and Management | journal =Administrative Theory &amp; Praxis | volume =32 | issue =1 | pages =48–70 | year =2010 | url =http://www.ccas.net/files/ADVANCE/Keashly_Bullying.pdf | doi =10.2753/ATP1084-1806320103 | s2cid =142766958 | access-date =2013-10-29 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131031193910/http://www.ccas.net/files/ADVANCE/Keashly_Bullying.pdf | archive-date =2013-10-31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Blue-collar jobs ====
Bullying has been identified as prominent in blue-collar jobs, including on oil rigs and in mechanic shops and machine shops. It is thought that intimidation and fear of retribution cause decreased incident reports. In industry sectors dominated by males, typically of little education, where disclosure of incidents are seen as effeminate, reporting in the socioeconomic and cultural milieu of such industries would likely lead to a [[vicious circle]]. This is often used in combination with [[Manipulation (psychology)|manipulation]] and [[coercion]] of facts to gain favour among higher-ranking [[administrator (business)|administrators]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal | last1 =Notelaers | first1 =Guy | last2 =Vermunt | first2 =Jeroen K. | last3 =Baillien | first3 =Elfi | last4 =Einarsen | first4 =Ståle | last5 =De Witte | first5 =Hans | title =Exploring Risk Groups Workplace Bullying with Categorical Data | journal =Industrial Health | volume =49 | issue =1 | pages =73–88 | year =2011 | url =https://unimaas.academia.edu/GuyNotelaers/Papers/278637/Exploring_Risk_Groups_and_Risk_Factors_for_Workplace_Bullying | access-date =2013-10-29 | doi =10.2486/indhealth.ms1155 | pmid =20823631 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20120425093442/http://unimaas.academia.edu/GuyNotelaers/Papers/278637/Exploring_Risk_Groups_and_Risk_Factors_for_Workplace_Bullying | archive-date =2012-04-25 | doi-access =free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Information technology ====
{{Main|Bullying in information technology}}
A culture of bullying is common in information technology (IT), leading to high sickness rates, low morale, poor productivity, and high staff-turnover.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Thomson | first =Rebecca | title =IT profession blighted by bullying | work =ComputerWeekly.com: Feature | publisher =TechTarget | url =http://www.computerweekly.com/feature/IT-profession-blighted-by-bullying | access-date =2013-10-29 | url-status =live | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20131029225711/http://www.computerweekly.com/feature/IT-profession-blighted-by-bullying | archive-date =2013-10-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Deadline-driven project work and stressed-out managers take their toll on IT workers.&lt;ref name="RichardsEdwards2008"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Ann Richards|author2=Sharon L. Edwards|title=A Nurse's Survival Guide to the Ward|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ytmEHQjia0AC|access-date=2013-10-29|year=2008|publisher=Churchill Livingstone|isbn=978-0-443-06897-3|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140101122142/http://books.google.com/books?id=ytmEHQjia0AC|archive-date=2014-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Courts ====
{{Main|Bullying in the legal profession}}
Bullying in the [[legal profession]] is believed to be more common than in some other professions. It is believed that its adversarial, hierarchical tradition contributes towards this.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unswlawjournal.unsw.edu.au/sites/default/files/t1_le_mire_and_owens.pdf Le Mire, Suzanne; Owens, Rosemary ''A propitious moment?: Workplace bullying and regulation of the legal profession'' University of New South Wales Law Journal, The Volume 37 Issue 3 (Dec 2014)] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150201001112/http://www.unswlawjournal.unsw.edu.au/sites/default/files/t1_le_mire_and_owens.pdf |date=2015-02-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Women, trainees and solicitors who have been qualified for five years or less are more affected, as are ethnic minority lawyers and lesbian, gay and bisexual lawyers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.journalonline.co.uk/News/1009923.aspx Society publishes guidance on tackling bullying in solicitor profession] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150201001313/http://www.journalonline.co.uk/News/1009923.aspx |date=2015-02-01 }} The Journal of the Law Society of Scotland 27 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Medicine ====
{{Main|Bullying in medicine|Bullying in nursing}}
Bullying in the [[medical profession]] is common, particularly of student or trainee doctors and of nurses. It is thought that this is at least in part an outcome of conservative traditional hierarchical structures and teaching methods in the medical profession, which may result in a bullying cycle.

Even though The [[American Nurses Association]] believes that all nursing personnel have the right to work in safe, non-abusive environments, bullying has been identified as being particularly prevalent in the nursing profession although the reasons are not clear. It is thought that relational aggression (psychological aspects of bullying such as gossiping and intimidation) are relevant. Relational aggression has been studied among girls but not so much among adult women.&lt;ref name="RichardsEdwards2008"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nursingworld.org/Bullying-Workplace-Violence |title=Violence, Incivility, &amp; Bullying |date=14 October 2017 |publisher=American Nurses Association |access-date=21 April 2022}};  {{cite journal | last =Dellasega | first =Cheryl A. | title =Bullying Among Nurses | journal =American Journal of Nursing | volume =109 | issue =1 | pages =52–58 | year =2009 | doi =10.1097/01.NAJ.0000344039.11651.08 | pmid =19112267 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Teaching ====
{{Main|Bullying in teaching}}
[[School]] [[teachers]] are commonly the subject of bullying but they are also sometimes the originators of bullying within a school environment.

=== Machines ===
Children have been observed bullying anthropomorphic robots designed to assist the elderly. Their attacks start with blocking the robots' paths of movement and then escalate to verbal abuse, hitting and destroying the object. Seventy-five percent of the kids interviewed perceived the robot as "human-like" yet decided to abuse it anyway, while 35% of the kids who beat up the robot did so "for enjoyment".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/kids-attack-bully-robot-japanese-mall-danger-avoidance-ai-2015-8?IR=T|title=Scientists are teaching robots to avoid children — because kids can be surprisingly mean|work=Business Insider|access-date=2017-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prevention ==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:File-Bully Prevention.jpg|thumbnail|right|October is the month used to educate and raise awareness to prevent bullying. ]] --&gt;
Bullying prevention is the collective effort to prevent, reduce and stop bullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=((National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine)) |editor1-last=Rivara|editor1-first=Frederick|editor2-last=Suzanne|editor2-first=Le Menestrel|title=Preventing Bullying Through Science, Policy, and Practice|date=2016|publisher=[[National Academies Press]]|isbn=978-0-309-44067-7|doi=10.17226/23482|pmid=27748087|s2cid=156853266 |url=http://www.nap.edu/catalog/23482/preventing-bullying-through-science-policy-and-practice|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160518032731/http://www.nap.edu/catalog/23482/preventing-bullying-through-science-policy-and-practice|archive-date=2016-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many campaigns and events are designated to bullying prevention throughout the world. Bullying prevention campaigns and events include [[Anti-Bullying Day]], [[Anti-Bullying Week]], [[International Day of Pink]], [[International STAND UP to Bullying Day]] and [[National Bullying Prevention Month]]. [[anti-bullying legislation|Anti-bullying laws]] in the U.S. have also been enacted in 23 of its 50 states, making bullying in schools illegal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmc = 2791686 | pmid=20514181 | doi=10.1901/jaba.2009.42-747 | volume=42 | issue=4 | title=Bully prevention in positive behavior support. | year=2009 | pages=747–59 | journal=Journal of Applied Behavior Analysis | last1 = Ross | first1 = SW | last2 = Horner | first2 = RH}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2019 study by McCallion &amp; Feder found that school-based anti-bullying programs may lower the incidence of bullying by 25%.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=TXABC |url=https://www.txabc.org/ |access-date=2023-11-09 |website=TXABC |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bullying prevention programs allow schools to help decrease cyberbullying within he realm of school. The prevention methods are targeted mainly for middle schoolers, where we see the most bullying occur.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Wölfer |first1=Ralf |last2=Schultze-Krumbholz |first2=Anja |last3=Zagorscak |first3=Pavle |last4=Jäkel |first4=Anne |last5=Göbel |first5=Kristin |last6=Scheithauer |first6=Herbert |date=December 2014 |title=Prevention 2.0: Targeting Cyberbullying @ School |url=http://link.springer.com/10.1007/s11121-013-0438-y |journal=Prevention Science |language=en |volume=15 |issue=6 |pages=879–887 |doi=10.1007/s11121-013-0438-y |pmid=24122481 |s2cid=22915480 |issn=1389-4986}}&lt;/ref&gt; To help decrease cyberbullying, people need to take preventative measures. One preventative method was implemented to determine the effectiveness against cyberbullying. This program called "Media Heroes" showed how educating teachers on bullying behaviors in school can help them educate and stop students from bullying. This educational program decreased bullying in their schools. Having trusted adults become educated on what can go on online, can help prevent further cyberbullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Wölfer |first1=Ralf |last2=Schultze-Krumbholz |first2=Anja |last3=Zagorscak |first3=Pavle |last4=Jäkel |first4=Anne |last5=Göbel |first5=Kristin |last6=Scheithauer |first6=Herbert |date=2014-12-01 |title=Prevention 2.0: Targeting Cyberbullying @ School |journal=Prevention Science |language=en |volume=15 |issue=6 |pages=879–887 |doi=10.1007/s11121-013-0438-y |pmid=24122481 |s2cid=22915480 |issn=1573-6695|url=https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:4869203e-568d-4ee3-973c-6c1cac275bb5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Responses ==
Bullying is typically ongoing and not isolated behaviour. Common responses are to try to ignore it, to confront the bullies, or to turn to an authority figure.

Ignoring it often does nothing to stop the bullying continuing, and it can become worse over time.&lt;ref&gt;W. Craig et al., [http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0143034307084136 "Responding to bullying, what works"]&lt;/ref&gt;
It can be important to address bullying behaviour early on, as it can be easier to control the earlier it is detected.&lt;ref&gt;W. Ci, [https://carleton.ca/economics/wp-content/uploads/bullying_paper_1-6.pdf "What can be done to stop bullying among children? Evidence from Canada"]&lt;/ref&gt;
Bystanders play an important role in responding to bullying, as doing nothing can encourage it to continue, while small steps that oppose the behaviour can reduce it.&lt;ref&gt;Bully-zero Australia Foundation, [http://bzaf.org.au/respond-to-bullying/ "Respond to bullying"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180526185909/http://bzaf.org.au/respond-to-bullying/ |date=2018-05-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Authority figures can play an important role, such as parents or teachers in child or adolescent situations, or supervisors, human-resources staff or parent-bodies in workplace and volunteer settings. In the school context, teachers who set clear boundaries, communicate seriously that bullying behavior is unacceptable and will not be tolerated, and involve school administrators have been shown to reduce bullying.&lt;ref name="dx.doi.org"/&gt; Discussing bullying and its consequences with the whole class is also an important intervention that not only reduces bullying, but also encourages other students to step in and stop bullying even before it reaches its full form.&lt;ref name="dx.doi.org"/&gt; In general, authority figures can be influential in recognising and stopping bullying behaviour, and creating an environment that does not encourage or promote bullying.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stopbullying.gov/respond/on-the-spot/index.html "Stop bullying on the spot"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Safe work Australia, [https://www.safeworkaustralia.gov.au/doc/guide-preventing-and-responding-workplace-bullying "Guide for preventing and responding to workplace bullying"]&lt;/ref&gt;

In many situations, authority figures are untrained and unqualified, do not know how to respond, and can make the situation worse.&lt;ref&gt;Veronica Birkett, [https://www.independent.co.uk/news/education/education-news/bullied-dont-tell-the-teacher-1361862.html "Bullied? Don't tell the teacher"]&lt;/ref&gt;
In some cases the authority figures even support the people doing the bullying, facilitating it continuing and increasing the isolation and marginalising of the target.&lt;ref&gt;[https://ethicsinvolunteering.wordpress.com/responding-to-bullying-in-arc-unsw-sports/ "Responding to bullying in Arc UNSW sports"]&lt;/ref&gt;
Some of the most effective ways to respond are to recognise that harmful behaviour is taking place, and to create an environment where it will not continue.&lt;ref name=field03&gt;E. Field, [http://www.aph.gov.au/parliamentary_business/committees/house_of_representatives_committees?url=ee/bullying/subs/sub58.pdf "The prevalence of workplace bullying in Australia"]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{clear}}
{{columns-list|colwidth=25em|
* [[Abuse]]
* [[Abusive power and control]]
* [[Bashing (pejorative)]]
* [[Brodie's Law (act)]]
* [[Bully (2011 film)|''Bully'' (2011 film)]]
* [[Bullying and suicide]]
* [[Bullying of students in higher education]]
* [[Discrimination]]
* [[Harassment]]
* [[Hate crime]]
* [[Hazing]]
* [[Mobbing]]
* [[Passive-aggressive behavior]]
* [[Psychological trauma]]
* [[Relational aggression]]
* [[Scapegoating]]
* [[Social dominance orientation]]
* [[Social exclusion]]
* [[Social media and suicide]]
* [[Social rejection]]
* [[Social undermining]]
* [[Taunting]]
* [[Teasing]]
* ''[[The Bully: A Discussion and Activity Story]]'' (book)
* [[Victimisation]]
* [[Workplace bullying]]
}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Kohut MR The Complete Guide to Understanding, Controlling, and Stopping Bullies &amp; Bullying: A Complete Guide for Teachers &amp; Parents (2007)
* ''Bullies and Victims in Schools: a guide to understanding and management'' by Valerie E. Besag (1989)
* ''The Fight That Never Ends'' by Tim Brown
* ''Odd Girl Out: The Hidden Culture of Aggression in Girls'' by Rachel Simmons {{ISBN|0-15-602734-8}}
* ''Bullycide, Death at Playtime'' by Neil Marr and [[Tim Field]] {{ISBN|0-9529121-2-0}}
* ''Bullycide in America: Moms Speak Out about the Bullying/Suicide Connection'' &amp;ndash; by Brenda High, [http://www.bullycide.org Bullycide.org]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20180807172430/http://outofbullying.com/ ''A Journey Out of Bullying: From Despair to Hope''] by Patricia L. Scott
* "Peer Abuse Know More! Bullying From A Psychological Perspective" By Elizabeth Bennett
* ''New Perspectives on Bullying'' by Ken Rigby
* [[James Garbarino|Garbarino, J.]] &amp; de Lara, E. (2003). [http://www.enotalone.com/article/5451.html ''And Words ''Can'' Hurt Forever: How to Protect Adolescents from Bullying, Harassment, and Emotional Violence.''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927130613/http://www.enotalone.com/article/5451.html |date=2011-09-27 }} The Free Press: New York NY.
* Joanne Scaglione, Arrica Rose Scaglione [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/custom/portlets/recordDetails/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=ED493726&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=ED493726 ''Bully-proofing children: a practical, hands-on guide to stop bullying'' 2006]
* [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=ED410007&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=ED410007 ''Why Is Everybody Always Picking on Me: A Guide to Handling Bullies for Young People.''] by Terrence Webster-Doyle. Book and Teaching curriculum.
* [http://www.paulgraham.com/nerds.html "Why Nerds are Unpopular"], by [[Paul Graham (computer programmer)|Paul Graham]]. This essay is an example of how even medium differences, in a hierarchical, zero-sum, or negative environments, can lead to ostracism or persecution.
* ''[[Lord of the Flies]]'' by William Golding (1954). A famous work describing how a group of schoolboys trapped on an island descends into savagery.

== External links ==
{{sisterlinks|d=Q240126|wikt=bullying|n=no|v=no|voy=no|m=no|mw=no|s=no|species=no|c=Category:Bullying}}&lt;!--No single source at en.wb but lots of individual pages--&gt;
{{Library resources box
|by=no
|onlinebooks=no
|others=yes
|lcheading=Bullying}}
*{{Curlie|Society/Issues/Violence_and_Abuse/Youth/Bullying/}}
* [https://www.citizensadvice.org.uk/about-us/how-we-provide-advice/advice/Get-advice/ Citizens Advice in the UK]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20020802052441/http://www.bullyingnoway.com.au/ Bullying. No Way! (Australian Education Authorities)]
* [http://www.dfes.gov.uk/bullying Bullying in schools (UK &amp;ndash; schools)]
* [http://pbskids.org/itsmylife/friends/bullies/print_books.html PBSKids.org "Great Books About Bullies"]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20121103113237/http://app.thearit.com/uft-brave/bebraveagainstbullying.html Be Brave Against Bullying, a UFT project] 
* [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/simpleSearch.jsp?newSearch=true&amp;eric_sortField=&amp;searchtype=basic&amp;pageSize=10&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=bullying&amp;eric_displayStartCount=1&amp;_pageLabel=ERICSearchResult&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=kw U.S. Department of Education's Education Resources Information Center (ERIC)]
* [http://bullyonline.org/index.php Bully Online]

{{Bullying|state=expanded}}
{{abuse}}
{{Manipulation (psychology)}}
{{Conformity}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Harassment and bullying| ]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Aggression]]
[[Category:Injustice]]
[[Category:Persecution]]
[[Category:Psychological abuse]]
[[Category:Interpersonal conflict]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>