<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051112215558|28146874" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21378368" pageid="21378368" ns="0" title="Bisexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-12T21:57:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Sexual orientation}}
'''Bisexuality''' in human sexual behavior refers to one or more of [[aesthetic]] attraction, [[romantic love]] and [[sexual desire]] without regard to gender. For some writers, the term expresses a contrast with [[homosexuality]] and [[heterosexuality]], while for others the term expresses a blend of the two.

Although observed in a variety of forms in most societies throughout recorded history, bisexuality has only been the subject of serious study since the second half of the [[20th century]], and some disagreement remains about its prevalence and nature.

==Description==

Bisexual orientation can fall anywhere between the two extremes of [[homosexuality]] and [[heterosexuality]]; a bisexual person is not necessarily attracted equally to both genders, and many tend to prefer one or the other. Another view of bisexuality is that homosexuality and heterosexuality are two [[monosexual]] orientations, whereas bisexuality encompasses them both. However, some argue that bisexuality is a legitimate [[sexual orientation]] in its own right.

Individuals attracted to both males and females, like people of any other orientation, may live a variety of sexual lifestyles. These include: lifelong [[monogamy]], [[serial monogamy]], [[polyamory]], [[polyfidelity]], [[promiscuity|casual sexual activity]] with individual partners, casual [[group sex]], and [[celibacy]]. For those with more than one sexual partner, these may or may not be all be of the same gender.

Some bisexual people consider themselves to be [[gay]] or [[lesbian]] -- for example, a bisexual woman who considers herself a lesbian may do so on the basis that a lesbian might be defined as any woman who is attracted to women (even one who is also attracted to men), or a woman who is primarily attracted to other women. Some lesbian and gay people object, asserting that exclusivity is part of the definition. Other bisexuals consider themselves distinct from homosexuals but part of the larger [[LGBT]] or [[queer]] community. Some bisexuals may be supportive of lesbian and gay people, but still consider themselves [[straight]], and still others consider any labels irrelevant to their situations.

==Bisexuality in history==

Historical and literary records from most literate societies indicate that male bisexuality was common and indeed expected. These relationships were generally age-structured (as in the practice of [[pederasty]] in the [[Mediterranean Basin]] of [[Classical antiquity|antiquity]], or the practice of [[shudo]] in pre-modern Japan) or gender-structured (as in the [[Two-Spirit]] North American tradition or the [[Central Asia]]n [[bacchá]] practices). Male heterosexuality and homosexuality, while also documented, appear mostly as exceptions, unless we are examining cultures influenced by the [[Abrahamic religion]]s, where heterosexuality was privileged, and bisexuality and homosexuality forcefully suppressed. In fact, most of the commonly cited examples of male "homosexuality" in previous cultures would more properly be categorized as bisexuality. Determining the history of female bisexuality is more problematic, in that women in most of the studied societies were under the domination of the males, and on one hand had less self-determination and freedom of movement and expression, and on the other were not the ones writing or keeping the literary record.

In [[Ancient Greece]] it is believed that males generally went through a homosexual stage in adolescence, followed by a bisexual stage characterized by [[pederasty|pederastic relationships]] in young adulthood, followed by a (mostly) heterosexual stage later in life, when they married and had children. Ancient [[Rome]], Arab countries up to and including the present, [[China]], and [[Japan]], all exhibit patterns of analogous bisexual behavior. In Japan in particular, due to its practice of [[shudo]] and the extensive art and literature associated with it, the record of a primarily bisexual lifestyle is both detailed and quite recent, dating back as recently as the [[19th century]].

Perhaps the most famous example is [[Alexander the Great]] who had many wives, but also at least two male lovers, [[Hephaestion]] being his life-long friend. The same could be said of most Roman emperors, the shoguns of Japan, many Chinese emperors, and others.

However, it should be noted that the terms ''heterosexual'', ''bisexual'', ''homosexual'', and the concept of "sexual orientation" itself are all modern sociological constructs, and may not be appropriate in historical contexts, in which ''behavior'' might be considered homosexual, but ''people'' were not labeled using such terms.

=== Ancient Greece ===

Ancestral law in ancient [[Sparta]] mandated same-sex relationships with youths who were coming of age for all adult men, so long as the men eventually took wives and produced children. The Spartans thought that love and erotic relationships between experienced and novice soldiers would solidify combat loyalty and encourage heroic tactics as men vied to impress their lovers. Once the younger soldier reached maturity the relationship was supposed to become non-sexual, but it is not clear how strictly this was followed. There was some stigma attached to young men who continued their relationships with their mentors into adulthood.

Greek religious texts, reflecting cultural practices, incorporated bisexual themes. The subtexts varied, from the mystical to the didactic. See ''[[Mythology of same-sex love]]''.

===Middle Eastern cultures===

[[Image:Shah Abbas and Wine Boy.jpg|left|thumb|150px|[[Shah Abbas I]] embracing his wine boy.]]

In the [[Middle East]], sexual behavior between males is common; a few sources describe it as near-ubiquitous. It was also a topic celebrated by some of the greatest artists, from the [[Middle Ages|medieval]] times until the nineteenth century, such as the famous poet [[Abu Nuwas]] and the [[Persians|Persian]] painter [[Reza Abbasi]]. This is despite prohibitions against overt homosexual behavior (as opposed to attraction, which is expected) in the [[Qur'an]] and severe penalties for offenders, including the death penalty, in some nations.

The Qur'an however requires that the transgression be witnessed by four men or eight women in order to convict the participants. Therefore, while bisexual behavior is known to be common, men are not given much trouble about these behaviors so long as they also marry and raise families and fulfill other societal duties. It is something that remains very covert, and an open declaration of homosexual preference would be unacceptable. In this way, [[bisexuality in the Arab world]] and [[Persian Empire|Persian]] world is somewhat similar to the [[down-low|DL]] culture prevalent in some African-American and Latino communities.

== Modern Western prevalence of bisexuality ==
''Main articles: [[Demographics of sexual orientation]] and [[Kinsey Reports]]''

Some modern surveys report about 2%-6% of modern western populations as "bisexual", but there are still many methodological difficulties with regard to randomness and size of the sample population, and the accuracy of self-reports of such personal information. (The accuracy of these numbers is [[Talk:Demographics of sexual orientation|disputed]].) Different studies also use different standards for bisexuality. Some studies ignore bisexual phenomena entirely, or separate it into same-sex and opposite-sex components. Reported results disagree over whether homosexuality is more common than bisexuality (with various definitions for each). Anecdotal reports from areas outside the west suggest much higher rates of bisexual expression.

Some studies, notably [[Alfred C. Kinsey|Alfred Kinsey]]'s ''Sexual Behavior in the Human Male'' (1948) and ''Sexual Behavior in the Human Female'' (1953), have indicated that the majority of people appear to be at least somewhat bisexual. The studies report that most people have some attraction to either sex, although usually one sex is preferred. According to some (falsely attributed to Kinsey), only about 5-10% of the population can be considered to be fully heterosexual or homosexual. On the other hand, an even smaller minority has no distinct preference for one gender or the other.

==Social status of bisexuality==

Historically, bisexuality has largely been free of the social stigma associated with homosexuality, prevalent even where bisexuality was the norm. In Ancient Greece [[pederasty]] was not problematic as long as the men eventually married and had children. All over the world among upper-class men of good social standing (i.e., properly married) homosexual affairs were tolerated, and heterosexual marriage was often successfully used as a defense against accusations of homosexuality.

Some in the gay and lesbian communities accuse those who call themselves "bisexual" of duplicity, believing they are really homosexuals who are attempting to hold onto the social approval through their heterosexual activity. They may be accused of "not doing their part" in gaining acceptance of "true" homosexuality. Gay and lesbian people may also suspect that a self-described bisexual is merely a homosexual in the initial stage of questioning their presumed heterosexuality, and will eventually accept that they are gay; this is expressed by a glib saying in gay culture: "Bi now, gay later." These situations can and do take place, but do not appear to be true of the majority of self-described bisexuals. Nonetheless, bisexuals do sometimes experience lesser acceptance from gay and lesbian people, because of their declared orientation.

Bisexuals are often associated with men who engage in [[men who have sex with men|same-sex activity]] while [[the closet|closeted]] and heterosexually [[marriage|married]], a practice which has led to high rates of HIV infection among, for example, black women in the USA. The majority of such men - said to be "living on the [[down-low]]" - do not self-identify as "bisexual", they just "[[Men who have sex with men|do that]]" occasionally.

Because many bisexual people do not feel that they fit into either the [[gay community]] or the heterosexual world, and because they have a tendency to be "invisible" in public (fitting in rather seamlessly into both homosexual and heterosexual society), some bisexual persons are committed to forming their own communities, culture, and political movements.

[[image:Bi-flag-large.png|thumb|200px|right|The bisexual pride flag]]A common symbol of bisexual identity is a pair of overlapping pink and blue triangles (the pink triangle being a well-known symbol for the gay community), forming purple where they intersect. Another symbol is the [[bisexual pride flag]], which has a deep pink stripe at the top for homosexuality, a blue one on the bottom for heterosexuality, and a purple one (blended from the pink and blue) in the middle to represent bisexuality.

==Terminology==

The term ''bisexual'' was coined by botanists c. 1809. It originally applied to plants that had both male and female sex organs. It is not known when the term was first applied to the context of sexual orientation. Some bisexuals and sex researchers are dissatisfied with the term, and have developed a variety of alternative or supplementary terms to describe aspects and forms of bisexuality. Many are [[neologism]]s not widely recognized by the larger society.

*''Pansexual'', ''omnisexual'', and ''[[pomosexual]]'' ([[postmodernism|postmodern]] sexuality) are substitute terms that rather than referring to ''both'' or "bi" gender attraction, refer to ''all'' or "omni" gender attraction, and are used mainly by those who wish to express acceptance of ''all'' gender possibilities including [[transgender]] and [[intersex]] people, not just two. Pansexuality sometimes includes an attraction for less mainstream sexual activities, such as [[BDSM]].

*''[[Bi-permissive]]'' describes someone who does not actively seek out sexual relations with a given gender, but is open to them. Such a person may self-identify as heterosexual or homosexual, and engage predominantly in sexual acts with individuals of the corresponding gender, and might be rated ''1'' or ''5'' on Kinsey's scale.

*''Ambisexual'' indicates a primarily indiscriminate attraction to either sex. A person who self-identifies as ambisexual might be attracted with equal intensity on physical, emotional, intellectual, and spiritual levels to partner(s) regardless of sex or gender presentation, while upholding selectivity standards in other areas. Some might experience equally intense attractions that could be triggered by sex- or gender-specific traits in given the partner(s). A person with this orientation might fall in the ''3'' category on Kinsey's scale, as would some who subscribe to the ''2'' or ''4'' rating (although some individuals in these latter categories consider themselves Bi-permissive).

*''[[Bi-curious]]'', has several distinct and sometimes contradictory meanings. It is commonly found in personal ads from those who identify as heterosexual but are interested in homosexual "experimentation". Such people are commonly suspected - not necessarily correctly - of being homosexuals or bisexuals in [[denial]] of their homosexuality. It can also be used to describe someone as being [[passively-bi]], bi-permissive or open to indirect bisexual contact.

*''Trisexual'' (sometimes ''trysexual'') is either an extension of, or a pun on ''bisexual''. In its more serious usage, it indicates an interest in transgender persons as well as men and women. In its more humorous usage, it refers to someone who will ''try'' any ''sexual'' experience.

*''[[Biphobia]]'' describes a fear or condemnation of bisexuality, usually based in a belief that only heterosexuality and homosexuality are genuine orientations and appropriate lifestyles. Bisexual persons may also be the target of [[homophobia]] from those who consider only heterosexuality appropriate. The reverse can also apply in that bisexual persons may be targets of [[heterophobia]] or discrimination by some gays/homosexuals.

*''[[Passively-bi]], aka [[open-minded]]'' is a non-gender specific term that describes a straight or bi-curious person who is ''open to'' incidental or direct contact (typically in a [[Group sex]] scenario) from a [[MOTSS]], usually without reciprocation.

*''[[Actively-bi]]'' is a non-gender specific term that describes a bi-curious/bisexual person who ''initiates'' direct contact with a [[MOTSS]].

==Bisexuality in modern Western entertainment==
Comparatively positive and notable portrayals of bisexuality can be found in mainstream movies such as: ''[[Goldfish Memory]]''; ''[[The Rocky Horror Picture Show]]''; and ''[[Henry and June]]''. In [[popular music]], many of the songs of [[The Smiths]] are commonly cited as classic examples. In notable [[graphic novel]]s, ''[[Love &amp; Rockets]]'' subtly portrays bisexuality. ''[[Krazy Kat]]'' is an early comic-strip character whose loves are not limited by gender. Notable novels containing significant bisexual characters are: Sean David Wright's ''Two For One--a novel about having choices''; [[Anne Rice]]'s ''Cry To Heaven''; [[Rosamond Lehmann]]'s ''Dusty Answer''; [[Mary Renault]]'s ''The Last of the Wine'' and ''The Persian Boy''; [[Colette]]'s ''Claudine'' novels; [[David Leavitt]]'s ''The Lost Language of Cranes'' and ''While England Sleeps''; [[Jeanette Winterson]]'s ''The Passion''; [[Marge Piercy]]'s ''Woman on the Edge of Time''; and [[Jane Rule]]'s ''Young in One Another's Arms''. Non-fiction scholarship, such as [[Camille Paglia]]'s ''Sexual Personae'' (1990) and Louis Crompton's ''Byron and Greek Love'' (1985), has uncovered previously hidden histories of bisexuality. On the TV show [[Will &amp; Grace]], the character of Karen is described as "omnisexual" and although is married to a man, often kisses Grace and appears to have had many female lovers throughout her life.

There are also negative media portrayals, reflecting prejudices and stereotypes. For instance, the television show ''[[Friends]]'' sported a short song about the topic that expresses a common prejudice on the subject:
&lt;div&gt;
:''Sometimes men love women,''
:''Sometimes men love men,''
:''Then there are bisexuals''
:''Though some people say they're kidding themselves''
&lt;/div&gt;

And a ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' joke ran thus:
:''"A bisexual is a person who reaches down the front of somebody's pants and is satisfied with whatever they find."'' -- [[Dana Carvey]] as the church lady, ''Saturday Night Live''.

Prejudice is also expressed in the storylines of movies in which the bisexual characters conceal murderous neuroses (''[[Basic Instinct]]'', ''Black Widow'', ''[[Blue Velvet]],'' ''Cruising,'' ''Girl Interrupted'').

==See also==
*[[List of gay, lesbian or bisexual people]]
*[[List of bisexuals]]
*[[List of LGBT-related organizations]]

==References==
{{wiktionarypar|bisexuality}}
;General
*[[Louis Crompton]]. ''Homosexuality and Civilization,'' Cambridge, Mass. and London, 2003. ISBN 067401197X
*[[Michel Larivière]]. ''Homosexuels et bisexuels célèbres,'' Delétraz Editions, 1997. ISBN 2911110196

;Ancient Greece
*[[Kenneth J. Dover]]. ''Greek Homosexuality,'' New York; Vintage Books, 1978. ISBN 0394742249
*[[Thomas K. Hubbard]]. ''Homosexuality in Greece and Rome,'' U. of California Press, 2003. [http://www.utexas.edu/courses/cc348hubbard/] ISBN 0520234308
*Herald Patzer. ''Die Griechische Knabenliebe [Greek Pederasty],'' Wiesbaden: Franz Steiner Verlag, 1982. In: Sitzungsberichte der Wissenschaftlichen Gesellschaft an der Johann Wolfgang Goethe-Universität Frankfurt am Main, Vol. 19 No. 1.
*W. A. Percy III.'' Pederasty and Pedagogy in Archaic Greece,'' University of Illinois Press, 1996. ISBN 0252022092

;Muslim Lands
*[[Stephen O. Murray]] and [[Will Roscoe]], et al. ''Islamic Homosexualities: Culture, History, and Literature,'' New York: New York University Press, 1997. ISBN 0814774687
*J. Wright &amp; Everett Rowson. ''Homoeroticism in Classical Arabic Literature''. 1998.
*'Homosexuality' &amp; other articles in the ''[http://www.iranica.com/ Encyclopædia Iranica]''

See also: [[Abu Nuwas]], [[Hafez]].

;Japan
*[[Gary Leupp]]. ''Male Colors: The Construction of Homosexuality in Tokugawa Japan,'' Berkeley, University of California Press, 1995. ISBN 0520209001
*[[Tsuneo Watanabe]] &amp; [[Jun'ichi Iwata]]. ''The Love of the Samurai. A Thousand Years of Japanese Homosexuality,'' London: GMP Publishers, 1987. ISBN 0854491155

== External links ==
* [http://www.biresource.org/ Bisexual Resource Center (international)]
* [http://www.bitribune.com/ Bi Tribune Magazine (US)]
* [http://www.bisexual.org/ The Bi Foundation]
* [http://www.bimagazine.org/ Bi Magazine (US)]
* [http://www.bimarried.com/ Bi Married Men's Support Group]
* [http://www.bimen.org/ Bi Men's Support Group]
* [http://www.bisexualplayground.com/ Bisexual Playground] Bisexual Online Community
* [http://serf.org/~jon/soc.bi/faq/a.html &lt;code&gt;soc.bi&lt;/code&gt; newsgroup FAQ] Bi newsgroup.
* [http://www.biresource.org/resources/ Bi Resources].
* [http://www.biresource.org/category/publications/ Bi Pamphlets].
* [http://www.bitheway.org/ BiTheWay.org] Bi community online resource (international)]
* [http://www.bitheway.org/Bi/About.htm/ All-encompassing info about the bisexual lifestyle]
* [http://www.binetusa.org/ BiNet USA]
* [http://www.biflag.com Bi Flag].
* [http://www.bi.org/ Bi.org] Serving the World Bisexual Community (international)
* [http://www.bicafe.com/ Bi Cafe] International Bisexual forum
* [http://www.androphile.org The Androphile Project] Extensive resource of gay and bisexual history.
* [http://www.bicommunitynews.co.uk/ ''BCN'' magazine]. The long-running UK bi cultural/political magazine.
*[http://www.beyondbarriers.org.uk/docs/Bisexual_Participatory_Appraisal_Research.pdf Exploring Biphobia]. (144 KB [[PDF]]). Report on the problems caused by stereotyping of bisexuals.
* [[AfterEllen.com]] [http://www.afterellen.com/TV/karenwalker.html] News,Reviews and Commentary on Lesbian and Bisexual Women in Entertainment and the Media.
* [[AfterEllen.com]] [http://www.afterellen.com/TV/coupling.html] News,Reviews and Commentary on Lesbian and Bisexual Women in Entertainment and the Media.

== References ==
* Bryant, Wayne M.. ''Bisexual Characters in Film: From Anais to Zee''. Haworth Gay &amp; Lesbian Studies, 1997. ISBN: 1560238941

{{Wikiquote}}
[[Category:LGBT]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and identity]]

[[bg:Бисексуалност]]
[[de:Bisexualität]]
[[et:Biseksuaalsus]]
[[es:Bisexualidad]]
[[eo:Ambaŭseksamo]]
[[fr:Bisexualité]]
[[gd:Dà-mhiannachd]]
[[he:ביסקסואליות]]
[[id:Biseksualitas]]
[[nl:Biseksualiteit]]
[[pt:Bissexualidade]]
[[ro:Bisexualitate]]
[[ru:Бисексуальность]]
[[fi:Biseksuaalisuus]]
[[sv:Bisexualitet]]
[[zh:双性恋]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>