<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031019002407|1607196" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21378368" pageid="21378368" ns="0" title="Bisexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-22T16:25:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Bisexualität]][[fr:Bisexualité]][[nl:Biseksualiteit]][[zh:&amp;#21452;&amp;#24615;&amp;#24651;]]

In [[human sexuality]], a '''bisexual''' or '''bi''' person (more rarely, '''pansexual''') can be sexually attracted, sexually active, and/or in love with people of either [[sex]].
Note that the attraction to both sexes is not always equal; a bisexual can be more attracted to people of one sex than the other. 
Other [[sexual orientation]]s are [[homosexuality]] and [[heterosexuality]]. 

''Pansexuality'' is a [[neologism]] that expresses essentially the same concept as bisexuality. The difference is that it refers to someone who is attracted to ''all'' sexes/genders, rather than ''both'' sexes. It is used mainly by people who wish to express their understanding and acceptance of [[transgender]]ism or recognizing the existence of the [[intersex]] genders. Pansexuality can include an attraction for less mainstream forms of sexuality, principally [[BDSM]].

''Trysexual'' is a [[neologism]] and a pun on ''bisexual''. It is used as a humorous term for someone who will try any sexual experience at least once.

== Incidence of bisexuality ==

Some studies, notably ''[[Sexual Behavior in the Human Male]]'' (1948) and ''[[Sexual Behavior in the Human Female]]'' (1953) by Dr. [[Alfred C. Kinsey]], note that when asked to rate themselves on a continuum from completely heterosexual to completely homosexual, and when the individual's behavior as well as their identity is analyzed, the majority of people appear to be at least somewhat bisexual. Most people have some attraction to either sex, although usually one sex is preferred. According to Kinsey, therefore, only a minority (5-10%) can be considered to be fully heterosexual or homosexual. Conversely, an even smaller minority can be considered "fully" bisexual, if that term is defined as having no preference for one sex over another.

Because bisexuals sometimes do not feel like they fit into the [[gay community]] at large, and because bisexuals have a tendency to become invisible in public (fitting in rather seamlessly into both [[homosexual]] and [[heterosexual]] society), some are committed to forming their own communities and movement. In an effort to create both more visibility, and a symbol for the bisexual community to gather behind, Michael Page created the [[bisexual pride flag]].

''[[Biphobia]]'' is a [[neologism]] that describes either the view that people are either [[heterosexual]] or [[homosexual]], or that bisexuals are "contaminated." Bisexuals may also be victimised by the more common [[homophobia]].

== Bisexual heritage ==

Bisexuality has a militaristic heritage. Examples include most people who had [[homosexual]] relationships in [[Ancient Greece]] since most also had wives. Perhaps the most famous and militaristic example is [[Alexander the Great]] who had many wives, but also a sexual relationship with his close friend [[Hephaestion]].

Ancient [[Sparta]] also encouraged homosexual relationships among their troops so long as the men also had wives and produced children. The Spartans thought that physical relationships between military men would solidify combat loyalty and encourage heroic tactics in the defense of their lover. It is not known the extent that this played in Sparta's military success but they were regarded as the premier fighting force of their day. 

==Bisexual Things==

Though not all bisexuals observe these things there are some things that are common among bisexuals. These include the Bisexual flag, which has a pink or red stripe at the top for homosexuality, a blue one on the bottom for heterosexuality and a purple one in the middle to represent bisexuality, as purple is from the combination of red and blue. 

Bisexuals also usually believe, while sexual orientation is genetic, they do not make a big issue of the matter. The reason for this usually that love is seen as positive and to say "I was born that way" is like excusing it as though it were a sexual disability. However, they still defend their rights saying they should be protected for the same reason as religious or political belief. The new bisexual communities sometimes take an active stand in other sexual freedom-related issues, such as polyamorist rights, prostitution and pornographic rights, and other sexual issues, which they usually side with free love. Though the mistake should not be made that all bisexuals observe polyamory and prostitution.

==Bisexuality in Western Culture==

As homosexuality often is seen as having a graver [[social stigma]], "bisexual" might be used as a [[euphemism]] for persons who haven't publicly announced themselves as homosexual. This tends to annoy real bisexuals.
The opposite of bisexual is '''monosexual'''. Often times those who claim to be bisexual but exhibit an obvious tendency towards their own sex are pegged as using the bisexual label only as an escape from admitting their own homosexuality. This theme is visited often in popular culture, in film, television and in music. The television show "[[Friends]]" sported a short song about the topic that expresses a common (if misinformed) opinion on the subject:

::"Sometimes men love women,
::Sometimes men love men,
::Then there are bisexuals
::Though some people say they're kidding themselves"

See also: [[Famous gay lesbian or bisexual people]], [[Heteronormativity]], [[sexual orientation]], [[list of bisexuals]]

== External links ==
* [http://serf.org/~jon/soc.bi/faq/a.html &lt;code&gt;soc.bi&lt;/code&gt; newsgroup FAQ]
* http://www.biresource.org/
* http://www.biflag.com</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>