<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041111143303|7341249" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21378368" pageid="21378368" ns="0" title="Bisexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-11T15:14:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Category:LGBT]]
'''Bisexuality''' is a [[sexual orientation]] characterized by [[romantic love]] or [[sexual desire]] for members of either or both [[gender]]s, contrasted with [[homosexuality]], [[heterosexuality]], and [[asexuality]].  

The terms '''pansexual''', '''omnisexual''' and '''pomosexual''' are generally used synonymously with one another, but compare [[#Terminology]] below.  Bisexual people may have simultaneous relationships with partners of any gender, practice [[serial monogamy]] with partners of either gender, have relationships with partners of only one gender, or practice [[celibacy]].  Bisexuality refers to desires and self-concept, not necessarily behavior.

Many bisexual people consider themselves to be [[gay]] or [[lesbian]] (or part of the [[LGBT]] community), and there is an argument that Bisexualtiy, defined as neither exclusively straigth nor exclusively homosexual, is the majority sexual preference, but is typically repressed (see [[Alfred C. Kinsey|Alfred Kinsey]])

Bisexual orientation can fall anywhere between the two [[sexual orientation]]s of [[homosexuality]] and [[heterosexuality]], and can be a unique combination of characteristics. Another view of bisexuality is that both homosexuality and heterosexuality are monosexualities, whereas bisexuality encompasses all monosexual orientations.

==Terminology==

''Pansexual'',''omnisexual'' and ''pomosexual'' (post-modern sexual) are [[neologism]]s that also refer to people who are attracted to more than one gender.  Rather than ''both'' or "bi" gender attraction, they refer to ''all'' or "omni" gender attraction, and are often used mainly by those who wish to express their understanding and acceptance of ''all'' gender possibilities including [[transgender]] and [[intersex]] people, not just two. Pansexuality sometimes includes an attraction for less mainstream sexual activities, such as [[BDSM]].

''Trysexual'' (sometimes "trisexual") is a neologism and a pun on ''bisexual''. It is used as a humorous term for someone who will try any sexual experience at least once.

People who are not bisexual are either "monosexual" (attracted to only one gender) or [[asexual]] (attracted to no genders).

== Prevalence of bisexuality ==

Some studies, notably [[Alfred C. Kinsey|Alfred Kinsey]]'s ''[[Sexual Behavior in the Human Male]]'' (1948) and ''[[Sexual Behavior in the Human Female]]'' (1953), have found that the majority of people appear to be at least somewhat bisexual. Most people have some attraction to either sex, although usually one sex is preferred. According to Kinsey, only about 5-10% of the population can be considered to be fully heterosexual or homosexual. An even smaller minority can be considered truly bisexual, that is, having no distinct preference for one gender or the other.

== History of bisexuality==

Bisexuality has a universal history. People in most known societies have exhibited varying degrees of bisexuality, and most of what is called homosexuality in previous cultures is in fact bisexuality (it should be noted, however, that the terms heterosexuality and bisexuality, and particularly homosexuality, may not be appropriate in the historical context.  In most ancient societies, ''behaviour'' was considered homosexual while people were not labeled using such terms.  Similarly, heterosexuality and bisexuality are also relatively modern concepts). 

For example, in [[Ancient Greece]] men often engaged in same-sex relationships, yet most also had wives.  Ancient Rome, Arab countries up to and including the present, China and Japan, all exhibit patterns of bisexual behaviour. Perhaps the most famous and militaristic example is [[Alexander the Great]] who had many wives, but also a sexual relationship with his close friend [[Hephaestion]], but the same could be said of almost all the Roman emperors, the shoguns of Japan, the Chinese emperors, and others in every country and every age.

Ancient [[Sparta]] also tolerated same-sex relationships among their troops so long as the men also had wives and produced children. The Spartans thought that physical relationships between older and younger soldiers would solidify combat loyalty and encourage heroic tactics as men vied to impress their lovers.  Once the younger soldier passed a certain age, the relationship was supposed to become non-sexual, but it is not clear how strictly this was followed.

In the modern [[Arab]] world, same-sex sexual behavior between men is very common; some sources describe it as near-ubiquitous. This is despite prohibitions against homosexual behavior in the [[Qur'an]] and severe penalties for offenders in some nations, including the death penalty. While among Arabs bisexual behaviour is known to be very common, and men are not given much trouble about these behaviors so long as they marry and raise families and fulfill other societal duties, it is something which remains very covert, and an open declaration of homosexual preference would be unacceptable. In this way, bisexuality in the Arab world is somewhat similar to the [[down-low|DL]] culture prevalent in some African-American communities.

==Bisexuality in Western Culture==

Gay and lesbian people have sometimes perceived (and adopted) the bisexual label as a way of holding on to heterosexual privilege. This often leads to the misperception that anyone who identifies as bisexual is really gay or lesbian but afraid to admit it. This misperception is often evident in popular culture, in film, television and in music and in the popular saying in gay culture: 'Bi now gay later'. The television show "[[Friends]]" sported a short song about the topic that expresses a common (if misinformed) opinion on the subject:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''"Sometimes men love women,''&lt;br /&gt;
''Sometimes men love men,''&lt;br /&gt;
''Then there are bisexuals''&lt;br /&gt;
''Though some people say they're kidding themselves"''&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Because many bisexual people often do not feel that they fit into either the [[gay community]] or the heterosexual world, and because they have a tendency to become invisible in public (fitting in rather seamlessly into both [[homosexual]] and [[heterosexual]] society), some bisexual persons are committed to forming their own communities and movement.

''[[Biphobia]]'' is a neologism that describes either the view that people are either [[heterosexual]] or [[homosexual]], or expresses disapproval of bisexuals.  Bisexual persons may also be the target of [[homophobia]].

:''"A bisexual is a person who reaches down the front of somebody's pants and is satisfied with whatever they find."'' -- [[Dana Carvey]] as the church lady, [[Saturday Night Live]]

==The bisexual pride flag==

[[image:Bi-flag-large.png|thumb|250px|right|The bisexual pride flag]]In an effort to create both more visibility, and a symbol for the bisexual community to gather behind, Michael Page created the [[bisexual pride flag]].

The bisexual flag, which has a pink or red stripe at the top for homosexuality, a blue one on the bottom for heterosexuality and a purple one in the middle to represent bisexuality, as purple is from the combination of red and blue.

==See also==

*[[Famous gay lesbian or bisexual people]]
*[[Heteronormativity]]
*[[Sexual orientation]]
*[[List of bisexuals]]

== External links ==
* [http://serf.org/~jon/soc.bi/faq/a.html &lt;code&gt;soc.bi&lt;/code&gt; newsgroup FAQ] Bi newsgroup
* [http://www.biresource.org/ Bi Resources]
* [http://www.biflag.com Bi Flag]
* [http://www.androphile.org The Androphile Project] Extensive resource of gay and bisexual history

{{Wikiquote}}

[[de:Bisexualität]]
[[eo:Amba&amp;#365;seksamo]]
[[fr:Bisexualité]]
[[nl:Biseksualiteit]]
[[fi:Biseksuaalisuus]]
[[sv:Bisexualitet]]
[[zh:&amp;#21452;&amp;#24615;&amp;#24651;]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>