<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020813071251|211343" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21378368" pageid="21378368" ns="0" title="Bisexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-09-11T12:00:46Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''bisexual''' person can be sexually attracted, sexually active, and/or in love with people of either [[sex]].  Note that the attraction to both sexes is not always equal; a bisexual can be more attracted to people of one sex than the other.

Some studies, notably [[Sexual Behavior in the Human Male]] (1948) and [[Sexual Behavior in the Human Female]] (1953) by Dr. [[Alfred C. Kinsey]], note that when asked to rate themselves on a continuum from completely heterosexual to completely homosexual, and when the individual's behavior as well as their identity is analyzed, the majority of people appear to be at least somewhat bisexual. Most people have some attraction to either sex, although usually one sex is preferred. According to Kinsey, therefore, only a minority (5-10%) can be considered to be fully heterosexual or homosexual. Conversely an even smaller minority can be considered "fully" bisexual, if that term is defined as having no preference for one sex over another.


See also [[sexual orientation]], [[homosexual]] and [[homosexuality]], [[Famous gay lesbian or bisexual people]]; [[heterosexual]] and [[heterosexuality]].</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>