<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181123070756|870215565" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56522" pageid="56522" ns="0" title="Right-wing politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-24T20:55:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Right-wing|the term used in sports|Winger (sports)}}
{{Redirect|Political right|political freedoms|Civil and political rights}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2017}}
{{Party politics}}

'''Right-wing politics''' hold that certain [[social order]]s and [[Social stratification|hierarchies]] are inevitable, natural, normal or desirable,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=A Political Glossary|url=http://www.auburn.edu/~johnspm/gloss/right-wing|publisher=Auburn University website|last=Johnson|first=Paul|title=Right-wing, rightist|year=2005|accessdate=23 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Bobbio|first1=Norberto|last2=Cameron|first2=Allan|title=Left and Right: The Significance of a Political Distinction|date=1996|publisher=[[University of Chicago Press]]|location=Chicago|isbn=978-0-226-06246-4|pages=51, 62}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Goldthorpe|first1=J.E.|title=An Introduction to Sociology|date=1985|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|location=Cambridge|isbn=0-521-24545-1|page=156|edition=Third}}&lt;/ref&gt; typically supporting this position on the basis of [[natural law]], [[economics]] or [[tradition]].&lt;ref name="Carlisle"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Carlisle|first1=Rodney P.|title=Encyclopedia of Politics: The Left and the Right|date=2005|publisher=[[SAGE Publications|SAGE Publishing]]|location=Thousand Oaks [u.a.]|isbn=1-4129-0409-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|p. 693, 721}}&lt;ref name="T. Alexander Smith 2003. p. 30"&gt;T. Alexander Smith, Raymond Tatalovich. ''Cultures at war: moral conflicts in western democracies''. Toronto, Canada: Broadview Press, Ltd, 2003. p. 30. "That viewpoint is held by contemporary sociologists, for whom 'right-wing movements' are conceptualized as 'social movements whose stated goals are to maintain structures of order, status, honor, or traditional social differences or values' as compared to left-wing movements which seek 'greater equality or political participation.' In other words, the sociological perspective sees preservationist politics as a right-wing attempt to defend privilege within the ''social hierarchy''."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Allan Cameron pg. 37"&gt;''Left and right: the significance of a political distinction'', Norberto Bobbio and Allan Cameron, p. 37, [[University of Chicago Press]], 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Fuchs, D. 1990. p. 203"&gt;[[Seymour Martin Lipset]], cited in Fuchs, D., and Klingemann, H. 1990. The left-right schema. pp. 203–34 in Continuities in Political Action: A Longitudinal Study of Political Orientations in Three Western Democracies, ed.M.Jennings et al. Berlin:de Gruyter&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Lukes&gt;Lukes, Steven. 'Epilogue: The Grand Dichotomy of the Twentieth Century': concluding chapter to T. Ball and R. Bellamy (eds.), The Cambridge History of Twentieth-Century Political Thought. pp.610–612&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Clark"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Clark|first1=William Roberts|title=Capitalism, Not Globalism: Capital Mobility, Central Bank Independence, and the Political Control of the Economy|date=2003|publisher=[[University of Michigan Press]]|location=Ann Arbor [u.a.]|isbn=0-472-11293-7|edition=[Online-Ausg.].}}{{page needed|date=August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hierarchy and [[Social inequality|inequality]] may be viewed as natural results of traditional social differences&lt;ref&gt;Smith, T. Alexander and Raymond Tatalovich. ''Cultures at War: Moral Conflicts in Western Democracies'' (Toronto, Canada: Broadview Press, Ltd., 2003) p. 30. "That viewpoint is held by contemporary sociologists, for whom 'right-wing movements' are conceptualized as 'social movements whose stated goals are to maintain structures of order, status, honor, or traditional social differences or values' as compared to left-wing movements which seek 'greater equality or political participation.'&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Bacchetta, Paola Power, Margaret|title=Right-Wing Women: From Conservatives to Extremists Around the World|year=2013|publisher=Routledge|page=4|quotation=For us, if there is anything that actually distinguishes (both the center and far) right from other political tendencies, it is the right's reliance on some form of internal or external Other. Right wings differentially draw on, produce, and mobilize naturalized and/or culturalized self/Other criteria to reify or forge hierarchical differences. These are based in gender, sexuality, class, ethnicity, religion, race, caste, or at their various intersections.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5SdW2L3V-gIC&amp;pg=PA4&amp;dq=right+wing+other+center&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjMrPe5_4jRAhUL2IMKHWSICh8Q6AEIMjAE#v=onepage&amp;q=right%20wing%20other%20center&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; or the competition in market economies.&lt;ref&gt;Scruton, Roger "A Dictionary of Political Thought" "Defined by contrast to (or perhaps more accurately conflict with) the left the term right does not even have the respectability of a history. As now used it denotes several connected and also conflicting ideas (including) 1)conservative, and perhaps authoritarian, doctrines concerning the nature of civil society, with emphasis on custom, tradition, and allegiance as social bonds ... 8) belief in free enterprise free markets and a capitalist economy as the only mode of production compatible with human freedom and suited to the temporary nature of human aspirations ..." pp. 281–2, Macmillan, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Goldthorpe|first1=J.E.|title=An Introduction to Sociology|date=1985|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge|isbn=0-521-24545-1|page=156|edition=3rd|quote="There are ... those who accept inequality as natural, normal, and even desirable. Two main lines of thought converge on the Right or conservative side...the truly Conservative view is that there is a natural hierarchy of skills and talents in which some people are born leaders, whether by heredity or family tradition. ... now ... the more usual right-wing view, which may be called 'liberal-conservative', is that unequal rewards are right and desirable so long as the competition for wealth and power is a fair one."}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term right-wing can generally refer to "the [[Conservatism|conservative]] or [[reactionary]] section of a political party or system".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/right_wing|title=right wing – definition of right wing in English &amp;#124; Oxford Dictionaries|publisher=En.oxforddictionaries.com|date=20 April 2014|accessdate=15 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The political terms "[[Left-wing politics|Left]]" and "Right" were first used during the [[French Revolution]] (1789–1799) and referred to seating arrangements in the [[French parliament]]: those who sat to the right of the chair of the parliamentary president were broadly supportive of the institutions of the monarchist [[Ancien Régime|Old Regime]].&lt;ref name="Parliaments 1988 pp. 287–302"&gt;Goodsell, Charles T., "The Architecture of Parliaments: Legislative Houses and Political Culture", British Journal of Political Science, Vol. 18, No. 3 (July 1988), pp. 287–302.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Linski, Gerhard, ''Current Issues and Research In Macrosociology'' (Brill Archive, 1984) p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clark, Barry ''Political Economy: A Comparative Approach'' (Praeger Paperback, 1998), pp. 33–34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Knapp"/&gt; The original Right in France was formed as a reaction against the "Left" and comprised those politicians supporting hierarchy, tradition and [[clericalism]].&lt;ref name="Carlisle"/&gt;{{rp|693}} The use of the expression {{lang|fr|la droite}} ("the right") became prominent in France after the [[Bourbon Restoration#Second Restoration|restoration of the monarchy in 1815]], when it was applied to the [[Ultra-royalist]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Gauchet, Marcel, "Right and Left" in Nora, Pierre, ed., ''Realms of Memory: Conflicts and Divisions'' (1996) pp. 247–248.&lt;/ref&gt; The people of English-speaking countries did not apply the terms "right" and "left" to their own politics until the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;''The English Ideology: Studies in the Language of Victorian Politics'', George Watson Allen Lane, London, 1973, p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the right-wing originated with [[Traditionalist conservatism|traditional conservatives]], [[Monarchism|monarchists]] and reactionaries, the term extreme right-wing has also been applied to movements including [[Fascism|fascists]], [[Nazism|Nazis]] and [[Racial supremacy|racial supremacists]].&lt;ref&gt;Iain McLean and Alistair McMillan, ''The Concise Oxford Dictionary of Politics'', ''Right(-wing)...and for extreme right parties racism and fascism.'', p. 465, Oxford, 2009, {{ISBN|978-0-19-920780-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt; From the 1830s to the 1880s, there was a shift in the [[Western world]] of [[social class]] structure and the economy, moving away from [[nobility]] and [[aristocracy]] towards [[capitalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Alan S. Kahan. ''Mind Vs. Money: The War Between Intellectuals and Capitalism''. New Brunswick, New Jersey: [[Transaction Publishers]], 2010. p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; This general economic shift toward capitalism affected [[Centre-right politics|centre-right]] movements such as the [[Conservative Party (UK)|British Conservative Party]], which responded by becoming supportive of [[capitalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Ian Adams. ''Political Ideology Today''. Manchester, England, UK; New York, New York, USA: [[Manchester University Press]], 2001. p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, the Right includes both economic and [[Social conservatism|social conservatives]].&lt;ref&gt;Jerome L. Himmelstein, ''To the right: The transformation of American conservatism'' (1992).&lt;/ref&gt; In Europe, economic conservatives are usually considered liberal and the Right includes [[Nationalism|nationalists]], [[Nativism (politics)|nativist]] [[opposition to immigration]], religious conservatives and historically a significant presence of right-wing movements with [[Anti-capitalism|anti-capitalist]] sentiments including conservatives and fascists who opposed what they saw as the selfishness and excessive [[materialism]] inherent in contemporary capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;Leonard V. Kaplan, Rudy Koshar, ''The Weimar Moment: Liberalism, Political Theology, and Law'' (2012) p 7-8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alan S. Kahan, ''Mind Vs. Money: The War Between Intellectuals and Capitalism'' (2010), p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{See also|Left–right politics}}
[[File:Estatesgeneral.jpg|thumb|5 May 1789, opening of the Estates-General in Versailles in 1789, as the conservatives sat on the right]]

The political term right-wing was first used during the [[French Revolution]], when [[Liberalism|liberal]] deputies of the [[Estates-General of 1789|Third Estate]] generally sat to the left of the president's chair, a custom that began in the [[Estates General (France)|Estates General]] of 1789. The nobility, members of the [[Estates General (France)|Second Estate]], generally sat to the right. In the successive [[Legislative Assembly (France)|legislative assemblies]], [[Monarchism|monarchists]] who supported the [[Ancien Régime|Old Regime]] were commonly referred to as rightists because they sat on the right side. A major figure on the right was [[Joseph de Maistre]], who argued for an [[Authoritarianism|authoritarian]] form of [[conservatism]]. Throughout the [[France in the 19th century|19th century]], the main line dividing [[Politics of France|Left and Right in France]] was between supporters of the republic (often secularists) and supporters of the monarchy (often Catholics).&lt;ref name="Knapp"&gt;{{cite book|author=Andrew Knapp and Vincent Wright|url=https://books.google.com/?id=67ttjXHhT3wC&amp;dq=the+government+and+politics+of+france&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;q=|title=The Government and Politics of France|year=2006|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-35732-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the right, the [[Legitimists]] and [[Ultra-royalist]]s held [[counter-revolutionary]] views, while the [[Orléanist]]s hoped to create a [[constitutional monarchy]] under their preferred branch of the royal family, a brief reality after the 1830 [[July Revolution]]. The centre-right Gaullists in post-World War II France advocated considerable social spending on education and infrastructure development as well as extensive economic regulation, but limited the wealth redistribution measures characteristic of [[social democracy]].{{citation needed|date=February 2016}}

In British politics, the terms "right" and "left" came into common use for the first time in the late 1930s in debates over the [[Spanish Civil War]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Charles Loch Mowat]], ''Britain Between the Wars: 1918–1940'' (1955), p. 577.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Right has gone through five distinct historical stages: (I) the reactionary right sought a return to aristocracy and established religion; (II) the moderate right distrusted intellectuals and sought limited government; (III) the radical right favored a romantic and aggressive nationalism; (IV) the extreme right proposed anti-immigration policies and implicit racism; and (V) the [[Neoliberalism|neo-liberal]] right sought to combine a market economy and economic deregulation with the traditional right-wing beliefs in patriotism, elitism and law and order.&lt;ref name="Clark"/&gt;{{page needed|date=August 2018}}&lt;ref&gt;Ball, T. and R. Bellamy, eds., ''The Cambridge History of Twentieth-Century Political Thought'', pp. 610–612.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Positions==
The meaning of right-wing "varies across societies, historical epochs, and political systems and ideologies".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Augoustinos|first1=Martha|last2=Walker|first2=Iain|last3=Donaghue|first3=Ngaire|title=Social Cognition: An Integrated Introduction|date=2006|publisher=Sage Publications|location=London|isbn=9780761942191|page=320|edition=2nd|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CYjEwFRPEQgC&amp;pg=PA230}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''The Concise Oxford Dictionary of Politics'', in liberal democracies, the political right opposes socialism and social democracy. Right-wing parties include conservatives, Christian democrats, classical liberals, nationalists and on the far-right; racists and fascists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=McLean|first1=Iain|last2=McMillan|first2=Alistair|title=The Concise Oxford Dictionary of Politics|page=465|date=2008|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|isbn=9780199205165|edition=3rd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Roger Eatwell and Neal O'Sullivan divide the right into five types: reactionary, moderate, radical, extreme and new.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; Chip Berlet argues that each of these "styles of thought" are "responses to the left", including liberalism and socialism, which have arisen since the 1789 French Revolution.&lt;ref name="Berlet, p. 117"&gt;Berlet, p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; The reactionary right looks toward the past and is "aristocratic, religious and authoritarian".&lt;ref name="Berlet, p. 117"/&gt; The moderate right, typified by the writings of [[Edmund Burke]], is tolerant of change, provided it is gradual and accepts some aspects of liberalism, including the rule of law and capitalism, although it sees radical ''laissez-faire'' and individualism as harmful to society. The moderate right often promotes nationalism and social welfare policies.&lt;ref&gt;Eatwell: 1999, p. 284.&lt;/ref&gt; Radical right is a term developed after World War II to describe groups and ideologies such as [[McCarthyism]], the [[John Birch Society]], [[Thatcherism]] and the [[Republikaner Party]]. Eatwell stresses that this use has "major typological problems" and that the term "has also been applied to clearly democratic developments".&lt;ref&gt;Eatwell: 2004, pp. 7–8.&lt;/ref&gt; The radical right includes [[right-wing populism]] and various other subtypes.&lt;ref name="Berlet, p. 117"/&gt; Eatwell argues that the extreme right' has four traits: "1) anti-democracy; 2) nationalism; 3) racism; and 4) the strong state".&lt;ref&gt;Eatwell: 2004, p. 8, "Today four other traits feature most prominently in definitions: 1) anti-democracy; 2) nationalism; 3) racism; 4) the strong state".&lt;/ref&gt; The New Right consists of the liberal conservatives, who stress small government, free markets and individual initiative.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Vincent|first1=Andrew|title=Modern Political Ideologies|date=1995|publisher=Blackwell|location=Oxford [u.a.]|isbn=978-0-631-19507-8|edition=2nd|quote=Who to include under the rubric of the New Right remains puzzling. It is usually seen as an amalgam of traditional liberal conservatism, Austrian liberal economic theory ... extreme libertarianism (anarch-capitalism) and crude populism.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other authors make a distinction between the centre-right and the far-right.&lt;ref&gt;Betz &amp; Immerfall 1998; Betz 1994; Durham 2000; Durham 2002; Hainsworth 2000; Mudde 2000; Berlet &amp; Lyons, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Parties of the centre-right generally support liberal democracy, capitalism, the market economy (though they may accept government regulation to control monopolies), private property rights and a limited welfare state (for example, government provision of education and medical care). They support conservatism and economic liberalism and oppose socialism and communism. By contrast, the phrase "far-right" is used to describe those who favor an absolutist government, which uses the power of the state to support the dominant ethnic group or religion and often to criminalize other ethnic groups or religions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=YYdTvMmSYpEC&amp;dq=%22far+right%22&amp;printsec=frontcover|title=The Routledge Companion to Fascism and the Far Right|publisher=Books.google.ca|date=|accessdate=13 May 2010|isbn=978-0-415-21495-7|year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=Ual1NR2WPasC&amp;dq=%22far+right%22&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPR7,M1|title=The Christian Right, the Far Right and the Boundaries of American Conservatism|publisher=Books.google.ca|date=|accessdate=13 May 2010|isbn=978-0-7190-5486-0|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=sVZ8EUvJjJ4C&amp;dq=%22far+right%22&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPR5,M1|title=Right-wing Extremism in the Twenty-first Century|publisher=Books.google.ca|date=30 June 2000|accessdate=13 May 2010|isbn=978-0-7146-5182-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=JcJ5nr2MZfUC&amp;dq=%22far+right%22&amp;printsec=frontcover|title=Western Democracies and the New Extreme Right Challenge|publisher=Books.google.ca|date=|accessdate=13 May 2010|isbn=978-0-415-36971-8|year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1857918.stm|title=Pim Fortuyn: The far-right Dutch maverick|publisher=BBC News|date=7 March 2002|accessdate=1 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Typical examples of leaders to whom the far-right label is often applied are: [[Francisco Franco]] in [[Spain]], [[Benito Mussolini]] in [[Italy]], [[Adolf Hitler]] in [[Nazi Germany]] and [[Augusto Pinochet]] in [[Chile]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=6069233|title=A Dictator's Legacy of Economic Growth|date=14 September 2006|accessdate=15 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Greenwald|first=Glenn|url=http://www.salon.com/opinion/greenwald/2007/05/04/politico_funding/|title=Glenn Greenwald|publisher=Salon.com|date=31 May 2012|accessdate=1 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Canovan"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Canovan|first1=Margaret|title=Populism|date=1981|publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich|location=New York|isbn=978-0151730780|edition=1st}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=November 2016}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Betz|first=Hans-Georg|title=Radical Right-Wing Populism in Western Europe|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|year=1994|isbn=978-0-312-08390-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Michael E. Brown, Owen R. Cote Jr., ''Nationalism and Ethnic Conflict'', "Anti-immigrant and anti-refugee feeling is being exploited by extreme right-wing parties throughout Europe...", p. 442, MIT Press, 2001, {{ISBN|978-0-262-52315-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Department of Homeland Security]] defines right-wing extremism in the United States as "broadly divided into those groups, movements, and adherents that are primarily hate-oriented (based on hatred of particular religious, racial or ethnic groups), and those that are mainly anti-government, rejecting federal authority in favor of state or local authority, or rejecting government authority entirely. It may include groups and individuals that are dedicated to a single issue, such as opposition to abortion or immigration." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://fas.org/irp/eprint/rightwing.pdf|title=Rightwing Extremism: Current Economic and Political Climate Fueling Resurgence in Radicalization and Recruitment|publisher=United States Department of Homeland Security|format=PDF|accessdate=16 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social stratification===
Right-wing politics involves in varying degrees the rejection of some [[Egalitarianism|egalitarian]] objectives of [[left-wing politics]], claiming either that [[Social inequality|social]] or [[economic inequality]] is natural and inevitable or that it is beneficial to society.&lt;ref name="autogenerated68"&gt;''Left and right: the significance of a political distinction'', Norberto Bobbio and Allan Cameron, pg. 68, [[University of Chicago Press]], 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; Right-wing ideologies and movements support [[social order]]. The original French right-wing was called "the party of order" and held that France needed a strong political leader to keep order.&lt;ref name="Knapp"/&gt; British conservative scholar R. J. White, who rejects egalitarianism, wrote: "Men are equal before God and the laws, but unequal in all else; hierarchy is the order of nature, and privilege is the reward of honourable service".&lt;ref name="autogenerated2003"&gt;Moyra Grant. ''Key Ideas in Politics''. Cheltenham, England, UK: Nelson Thornes, Ltd., 2003. p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; American conservative [[Russell Kirk]] also rejected egalitarianism as imposing sameness, stating: "Men are created different; and a government that ignores this law becomes an unjust government for it sacrifices nobility to mediocrity".&lt;ref name="autogenerated2003"/&gt; Kirk took as one of the "canons" of conservatism the principle that "civilized society requires orders and classes".&lt;ref name="heritage.org"&gt;{{cite web|last=John|first=David C.|url=http://www.heritage.org/Research/PoliticalPhilosophy/HL811.cfm|title=The Origins of the Modern American Conservative Movement|publisher=heritage.org|date=21 November 2003|accessdate=13 May 2010|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100308173749/http://www.heritage.org/Research/PoliticalPhilosophy/HL811.cfm|archivedate=8 March 2010|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Right-libertarianism|Right libertarians]] reject collective or state-imposed equality as undermining reward for personal merit, initiative and enterprise.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2003"/&gt; In their view, it is unjust, limits personal freedom and leads to social uniformity and mediocrity.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2003"/&gt;

===Anti-communism===
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2017}}
The original use of "right-wing" in reference to communism had the conservatives on the right, the liberals in the centre and the communists on the left. Both the conservatives and the liberals were strongly anti-communist. The history of the use of the term "right-wing" to mean anti-communist is a complicated one.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hendershot|first1=Cyndy|title=Anti-Communism and Popular Culture in Mid-Century America|date=2003|publisher=McFarland|location=Jefferson, N.C.|isbn=978-0786414406}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early Marxist movements were at odds with the traditional monarchies that ruled over much of the [[Europe]]an continent at the time. Many European monarchies outlawed the public expression of communist views and the ''[[The Communist Manifesto|Communist Manifesto]]'', which began "[a] spectre [that] is haunting Europe", stated that monarchs feared for their thrones. Advocacy of communism was illegal in the [[Russian Empire]], the [[German Empire]] and [[Austria-Hungary]], the three most powerful monarchies in continental Europe prior to [[World War I]]. Many monarchists (except [[Constitutional monarchy|constitutional monarchists]]) viewed inequality in wealth and political power as resulting from a divine natural order. The struggle between monarchists and communists was often described as a struggle between the Right and the Left.

By [[World War I]], in most European monarchies, the divine right of kings had become discredited and replaced by [[Liberalism|liberal]] and [[Nationalism|nationalist]] movements. Most European monarchs became figureheads or accepted a lesser degree of powers while elected governments held the day-to-day power. The most conservative European monarchy, the Russian Empire, was replaced by the communist Soviet Union. The Russian Revolution inspired a series of other communist revolutions across Europe in the years 1917–1922. Many of these, such as the [[German Revolution]], were defeated by nationalist and monarchist military units. In this period, nationalism began to be considered right-wing, especially when it opposed the internationalism of the communists.

The 1920s and 1930s saw the fading of traditional right-wing politics. The mantle of conservative anti-communism was taken up by the rising [[Fascism|fascist]] movements on the one hand and by [[United States|American]]-inspired [[Liberal conservatism|liberal conservatives]] on the other. When communist groups and political parties began appearing around the world, their opponents were usually [[Colonialism|colonial authorities]] and the term right-wing came to be applied to [[colonialism]].

After [[World War II]], communism became a global phenomenon and anti-communism became an integral part of the domestic and foreign policies of the [[United States]] and its [[NATO]] allies. Conservatism in the post-war era abandoned its monarchist and aristocratic roots, focusing instead on patriotism, religious values and nationalism. Throughout the [[Cold War]], colonial governments in [[Asia]], [[Africa]] and [[Latin America]] turned to the United States for political and economic support. Communists were also enemies of capitalism, portraying [[Wall Street]] as the oppressor of the masses. The United States made anti-communism the top priority of its foreign policy and many American conservatives sought to combat what they saw as communist influence at home. This led to the adoption of a number of domestic policies that are collectively known under the term "[[McCarthyism]]". While both liberals and conservatives were anti-communist, the followers of Senator McCarthy were called right-wing and those on the right called liberals who favored free speech, even for communists; leftist.

===Economics===
In France after the French Revolution, the Right fought against the rising power of those who had grown rich through commerce and sought to preserve the rights of the hereditary nobility. They were uncomfortable with capitalism, the Enlightenment, individualism and industrialism and fought to retain traditional social hierarchies and institutions.&lt;ref name="Parliaments 1988 pp. 287–302"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Appleby"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Marty|first1=Martin E.|last2=Appleby|first2=R. Scott|title=Fundamentalisms Observed|date=1994|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|isbn=0-226-50878-1|page=91|edition=2nd|quote=Reactionary right-wing themes emphasizing authority, social hierarchy, and obedience, as well as condemnations of liberalism, the democratic ethos, the "rights of man" associated with the legacy of the Enlightenment and the French Revolution, and the political and cultural ethos of modern liberal democracy are especially prominent in the writings and public statements of Archbishop Lefebere.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Europe's history, there have been strong [[Collectivism|collectivist]] right-wing movements, such as in the [[Catholic social teaching|social Catholic right]] that has exhibited hostility to all forms of [[liberalism]] (including [[economic liberalism]]) and has historically advocated for paternalist class harmony involving an organic-hierarchical society where workers are protected while hierarchy of classes remain.&lt;ref&gt;''Modern Catholic Social Teaching: The Popes Confront the Industrial Age'', 1740–1958. Paulist Press, 2003, p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the nineteenth century, the Right had shifted to support the newly rich in some European countries (particularly England) and instead of favouring the nobility over industrialists, favoured capitalists over the working class. Other right-wing movements, such as [[Carlism]] in Spain and nationalist movements in France, Germany and Russia, remained hostile to capitalism and industrialism. However, there are still a few right-wing movements today, notably the French [[Nouvelle Droite]], [[CasaPound]] and American [[paleoconservatives]], that are often in opposition to capitalist ethics and the effects they have on society as a whole, which they see as infringing upon or causing the decay of social traditions or hierarchies that they see as essential for social order.&lt;ref name="Fascism"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Payne|first1=Stanley G.|title=Fascism: Comparison and Definition|date=1983|publisher=University of Wisconsin Press|location=Madison, Wisc.|isbn=978-0-299-08064-8|page=19|quote=Right radicals and conservative authoritarians almost without exception became corporatists in formal doctrines of political economy, but the fascists were less explicit and in general less schematic.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In modern times, "right-wing" is sometimes used to describe [[Laissez-faire|''laissez-faire'' capitalism]]. In Europe, capitalists formed alliances with the Right during their conflicts with workers after 1848. In France, the Right's support of capitalism can be traced to the late-nineteenth century.&lt;ref name="Knapp"/&gt; The so-called [[Neoliberalism|neoliberal]] Right, popularised by [[US President]] [[Ronald Reagan]] and [[UK Prime Minister]] [[Margaret Thatcher]], combines support for [[free markets]], [[privatisation]] and [[deregulation]] with traditional right-wing support for social conformity.&lt;ref name="Lukes"/&gt; [[Right-libertarianism|Right-wing libertarianism]] (sometimes known as [[libertarian conservatism]] or [[conservative libertarianism]]) supports a decentralised economy based on [[economic freedom]] and holds [[property rights]], [[free markets]] and [[free trade]] to be the most important kinds of freedom. Russell Kirk believed that freedom and property rights were interlinked.&lt;ref name="heritage.org"/&gt; Anthony Gregory has written that right-wing libertarianism "can refer to any number of varying and at times mutually exclusive political orientations". Gregory holds that the issue is neither right or left, but "whether a person sees the state as a major hazard or just another institution to be reformed and directed toward a political goal".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.lewrockwell.com/gregory/gregory127.html|title=Left, Right, Moderate and Radical by Anthony Gregory|publisher=Archive.lewrockwell.com|date=21 December 2006|accessdate=15 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Conservative authoritarians and those on the [[Far-right politics|far-right]] have supported [[fascism]] and [[corporatism]].&lt;ref name="Fascism"/&gt;

===Nationalism===
In France, [[nationalism]] was originally a left-wing and Republican ideology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Doyle|first1=William|title=The Oxford History of the French Revolution|date=2002|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford [u.a.]|isbn=978-0-19-925298-5|edition=2nd|quote="An exuberant, uncompromising nationalism lay behind France's revolutionary expansion in the 1790s...", "The message of the French Revolution was that the people are sovereign; and in the two centuries since it was first proclaimed it has conquered the world."}}&lt;/ref&gt; After [[Georges Ernest Boulanger|the period of ''boulangisme'']] and the [[Dreyfus Affair]], nationalism became a trait of the right-wing.&lt;ref&gt;[[Michel Winock|Winock, Michel]] (dir.), ''Histoire de l'extrême droite en France'' (1993).&lt;/ref&gt; Right-wing nationalists sought to define and defend a "true" national identity from elements deemed to be corrupting that identity.&lt;ref name="Knapp"/&gt; Some were [[Supremacism|supremacists]], who in accordance with [[social Darwinism]] applied the concept of "[[survival of the fittest]]" to nations and races.&lt;ref&gt;Adams, Ian ''Political Ideology Today'' (2nd edition), Manchester University Press, 2002, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt; Right-wing nationalism was influenced by [[Romantic nationalism]], in which the state derives its political legitimacy from the organic unity of those it governs. This generally includes the language, race, culture, religion and customs of the nation, all of which were "born" within its culture. Linked with right-wing nationalism is [[cultural conservatism]], which supports the preservation of the heritage of a nation or culture and often sees deviations from cultural norms as an existential threat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Ramet|first1=Sabrina|last2=Griffin|first2=Roger|title=The Radical Right in Central and Eastern Europe since 1989|date=1999|publisher=The Pennsylvania State University Press|location=University Park|isbn=978-0271018119}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=November 2016}}

===Natural law and traditionalism===
Right-wing politics typically justifies a hierarchical society on the basis of [[natural law]] or [[tradition]].&lt;ref name="T. Alexander Smith 2003. p. 30"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Allan Cameron pg. 37"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Fuchs, D. 1990. p. 203"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lukes"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Clark"/&gt;{{page needed|date=August 2018}}&lt;ref name="autogenerated68"/&gt;

Traditionalism was advocated by a group of United States university professors (labeled the "New Conservatives" by the popular press) who rejected the concepts of [[individualism]], [[liberalism]], [[modernity]] and [[social progress]], seeking instead to promote what they identified as cultural and educational renewal&lt;ref&gt;Bruce Frohnen, Jeremy Beer and Jeffrey O. Nelson, ed. (2006) ''American Conservatism: An Encyclopedia'' Wilmington, DE: ISI Books, p. 870.&lt;/ref&gt; and a revived interest in what [[T. S. Eliot]] referred to as "the permanent things" (concepts perceived by traditionalists as truths that endure from age to age alongside basic institutions of western society such as the church, the family, the state and business).

===Populism===
{{Main article|Right-wing populism}}
[[File:TeaPartyByFreedomFan.JPG|thumb|Tea Party protesters walk towards the [[United States Capitol]] during the [[Taxpayer March on Washington]], 12 September 2009]]
[[Right-wing populism]] is a combination of civic/ethno-nationalism with [[anti-elitism]], using populist rhetoric to provide a radical critique of existing political institutions. According to Margaret Canovan, a right-wing populist is "a charismatic leader, using the tactics of politicians' populism to go past the politicians and intellectual elite and appeal to the reactionary sentiments of the populace, often buttressing his claim to speak for the people by the use of referendums".&lt;ref name="Canovan"/&gt;{{page needed|date=November 2016}}

In Europe, right-wing populism often takes the form of distrust of the [[European Union]] and of politicians in general combined with anti-immigrant rhetoric and a call for a return to traditional, national values.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hayward|first1=Jack|title=Elitism, Populism, and European Politics|date=2004|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|isbn=978-0198280354}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=November 2016}} In the United States, the [[Tea Party movement]] states that the core beliefs for membership are the primacy of individual liberties as defined in the Constitution of the United States, small federal government and respect for the rule of law. Some policy positions include an opposition to illegal immigration, a strong national military force, the right to individual gun ownership, cutting taxes, reducing government spending and balancing the budget.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.teaparty.org/about-us/|title=About Us|publisher=Tea Party|date=2 September 2004|accessdate=15 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religion===
Government support for an established religion was associated with the original French Right.&lt;ref name="Appleby"/&gt; [[Joseph de Maistre]] argued for the indirect authority of the [[Pope]] over temporal matters. According to Maistre, only governments founded upon a Christian constitution, implicit in the customs and institutions of all European societies and especially in [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]] [[Europe]]an monarchies, could avoid the disorder and bloodshed that followed the implementation of [[Rationalism|rationalist]] political programs, as in the [[French Revolution]]. The [[Church of England]] was established by [[Henry VIII]] and some churchmen are given seats in the [[House of Lords]], but are considered politically neutral rather than being specifically right or left-wing.

Religious fundamentalists frequently feel that governments should enact laws supporting their religious tenets.&lt;ref name="Appleby"/&gt; The [[Christian right]] is a major force in North America. They generally support laws upholding what they consider religious values, such as [[pro-life movement in the United States|opposition to abortion]], contraception,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Hannah Groch-Begley|url=http://mediamatters.org/blog/2014/03/26/this-conservative-myth-about-birth-control-coul/198623|title=This Conservative Myth About Birth Control Could Sway A Supreme Court Case|publisher=Mediamatters.org|date=26 March 2014|accessdate=15 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; sex outside marriage&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adn.com/article/20110323/sex-outside-marriage-should-be-illegal-says-parnell-nominee|title=Sex outside marriage should be illegal, says Parnell nominee|work=Alaska Dispatch News}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to same-sex marriage and reject scientific positions on [[evolution]] and other matters where science disagrees with the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Diana|last=DeGette|title=Sex, Science, and Stem Cells: Inside the Right Wing Assault on Reason|publisher=[[The Lyons Press]]|year=2008|isbn=978-1-59921-431-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chris Mooney, ''The Republican War on Science: Revised and Updated'', ASIN: B001OQOIPM&lt;/ref&gt; Outside the West, some other religious and ethnicity based political groups are considered right-wing.{{citation needed|date=November 2016}} In India, [[Hindu nationalism]] is sometimes considered a part of the Right. The Hindu nationalist movement has attracted privileged groups fearing encroachment on their dominant positions and also "plebeian" and impoverished groups seeking recognition around a majoritarian rhetoric of cultural pride, order and national strength.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Blom Hansen, ''The Saffron Wave: Democracy and Hindu Nationalism in Modern India'', Princeton University Press, 2001, {{ISBN|1-4008-0342-X}}, 9781400803422.&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[Islamist]] groups have been called "right-wing" including the [[Great Union Party]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.turkishweekly.net/news/68827/rescue-teams-could-not-reach-turkish-party-leader-muhsin-yazicioglu-after-helicopter-crash.html|author=Demirtas, Burcu|title=Rescue Teams Could Not Reach Turkish Party Leader, Muhsin Yazicioglu after Helicopter Crash|publisher=Turkishweekly.net|date=27 March 2009|accessdate=1 June 2012|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120305234419/http://www.turkishweekly.net/news/68827/rescue-teams-could-not-reach-turkish-party-leader-muhsin-yazicioglu-after-helicopter-crash.html|archivedate=5 March 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Combatant Clergy Association]]/Association of Militant Clergy&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uvm.edu/~fgause/168read.htm|title=Readings|publisher=uvm.edu|date=Fall 2007|accessdate=1 June 2012|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121006083545/http://www.uvm.edu/~fgause/168read.htm|archivedate=6 October 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/623899.stm|title=Poll test for Iran reformists|publisher=BBC News|date=10 February 2000|accessdate=1 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Islamic Society of Engineers]] of Iran.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merip.org/mero/mero020101.html|title=Middle East Report Online: Iran's Conservatives Face the Electorate, by Arang Keshavarzian|publisher=Merip.org|date=23 May 1997|accessdate=13 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Anoushiravan Ehteshami and Mahjoob Zweiri, ''Iran and the rise of its neoconservatives: the politics of Tehran's silent revolution'', I.B. Tauris, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term "[[family values]]" has been used as a buzzword by right-wing parties such as the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]] in the United States, the [[Family First Party]] in Australia, the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] in the United Kingdom and the [[Bharatiya Janata Party]] in India to describe support for traditional families and opposition to the changes the modern world has made in how families live. Right-wing supporters of "family values" may oppose [[abortion]], [[euthanasia]], the increasing cultural acceptance of [[homosexuality]], [[divorce]], [[teenage pregnancy]] and [[adultery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2004 Republican Party Platform: A Safer World and a More Hopeful America|url=http://msnbcmedia.msn.com/i/msnbc/Sections/News/Politics/Conventions/RNC-2004platform.pdf|publisher=MSNBC|accessdate=23 July 2012|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
&lt;!-- Please keep entries in alphabetical order &amp; add a short description [[WP:SEEALSO]] --&gt;
{{Div col|colwidth=20em|small=no}}
* [[Alt-right]]
* [[Conservative revolutionary movement]]
* [[Dark Enlightenment]]
* [[Left–right politics]]
* [[List of right-wing political parties]]
* [[New Right#United States|New Right]]
* [[Paternalistic conservatism]]
* [[Right-wing authoritarianism]]
* [[Structural functionalism]]
{{div col end}}
&lt;!-- Please keep entries in alphabetical order --&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Berlet, Chip. "When Alienation turns Right". In Langman, Lauren and Kalekin-Fishman (Eds.) ''The Evolution of Alienation: Trauma, Promise, and the Millennium''.  Lanham, MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2006 {{ISBN|0-7425-1835-3}}, {{ISBN|978-0-7425-1835-3}}
* Davies, Peter. ''The Extreme Right in France, 1789 to the Present: From De Maistre to Le Pen''. New York, NY: Routledge, 2002 {{ISBN|0-415-23982-6}}, {{ISBN|978-0-415-23982-0}}
* Eatwell, Roger. "Introduction: the new extreme right challenge". In Eatwell, Roger and Muddle, Cas (Eds.) ''Western Democracies and the new Extreme Right Challenge.'' London, UK: Routledge, 2004 {{ISBN|0-415-36971-1}}, {{ISBN|978-0-415-36971-8}}
* Eatwell, Roger.  "Conclusion: The 'End of Ideology'". In Eatwell, Roger and Wright, Anthony (Eds.) ''Contemporary Political Ideologies''. Continuum International Publishing Group, 1999 {{ISBN|0-8264-5173-X}}, 9780826451736
* Fielitz, Maik; Laloire, Laura Lotte (eds.). ''Trouble on the Far Right. Contemporary Right-Wing Strategies and Practices in Europe''. Bielefeld: transcript, 2016 {{ISBN|978-3-8376-3720-5}} 
* Bacchetta, Paola; Power, Margaret (eds). Right-Wing Women: From Conservatives to Extremists around the World. New York: Routledge, 2002.
* Gottlieb, Julie; Berethezéne, Clarisse (Eds). ''Rethinking right-wing women: Gender and the Conservative Party, 1880s to the present''. 2017

== External links ==
* {{wikiquote inline|rightism}}

{{Political spectrum}}
{{Political ideologies}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Right-Wing Politics}}
[[Category:Right-wing politics| ]]
[[Category:Capitalism]]
[[Category:Conservatism]]
[[Category:Fascism]]
[[Category:Monarchism]]
[[Category:Nazism]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Political terminology]]
[[Category:Theocracies]]
[[Category:Tradition]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>