<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081114200950|251830157" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56522" pageid="56522" ns="0" title="Right-wing politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T14:17:46Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Articleissues|rewrite=October 2008|POV = October 2008|unbalanced =November 2008|recent=October 2008}}
{{redirect|Right wing|the term used in sports|Winger (sport)}}
{{Party politics}}

In [[politics]], '''''right-wing''''', '''''the political right''''' and '''''the Right''''' are terms applied to a variety of political positions. The term has had different meanings in different countries and time periods. Originally it referred to seating arrangements: during the [[French Revolution]] moderates sat on the right.&lt;ref&gt;The Architecture of Parliaments: Legislative Houses and Political Culture Charles T. Goodsell British Journal of Political Science, Vol. 18, No. 3 (Jul., 1988), pp. 287-302&lt;/ref&gt; In the mid-19th century [[left-wing|the left]] begun to refer to forms of [[socialism]] and [[communism]], whereas the right has been used to describe positions leaning to [[limited government]] and [[free market]]s.&lt;ref&gt;"Right-wing". Concise Encyclopedia Britannica. Published in 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The political term ''right-wing'' originates from the [[French Revolution]] when [[Liberalism|liberal]] deputies from the [[Third Estate]] generally sat to the left of the president's chair, a habit which began in the [[French States-General|Estates General]] of 1789. The nobility, members of the [[Second Estate]], generally sat to the right. In the successive [[Legislative Assembly (France)|legislative assemblies]], [[Monarchism|monarchists]] who supported the [[Ancien Régime]] were commonly referred to as rightists because they sat on the right side. It is still the tradition in the [[French National Assembly]] for the representatives to be seated left-to-right (relative to the Assembly president) according to their political alignment. By the late 19th century, the French political spectrum tended to be perceived as being composed of the [[far left]] ([[socialists]] and [[radicals]]), the [[center-left]] ([[liberalism|Liberal]] [[Republicans]]), the [[political center|center]] ([[Moderate]] and [[Conservative]] Republicans), the [[center-right]] ([[Constitutional monarchy|Constitutional Monarchists]], [[Orleanists]], and [[Bonapartists]]), and the [[far right]] ([[Ultra-Royalists]] and [[Legitimists]]).{{Fact|date=August 2008}} 

Since then, the right wing has come to be associated with preserving individual rights through constraints on government power, and permitting individuals to maintain their respective traditional and religious values.{{Fact|date=November 2008}} [[Adam Smith]]'s ''The Wealth of Nations'', one of the earliest attempts to study the rise of industry and commercial development in Europe, was a precursor to the modern academic discipline of economics. In this and other works, Smith expounded on how rational self-interest and competition can lead to economic prosperity and well-being. It also provided one of the best-known intellectual rationales for [[free trade]] and [[capitalism]], greatly influencing the writings of later economists.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hart|1989}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Pressman, Steven |title=Fifty Major Economists |year=1999 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=0415134811 |page=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 19th century Britain, [[laissez-faire capitalism]] found a small but strong following by [[Manchester Liberalism|Manchester Liberals]] such as [[Richard Cobden]] and Richard Wright. In 1867, this resulted in a free trade treaty being signed between Britain and France, after which several of these treaties were signed among other European countries. The newspaper ''[[The Economist]]'' was founded un 1843, partly in opposition to the [[Corn Laws]]. Free trade was discussed in places such as ''The Cobden Club'', founded in 1866.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Scott Gordon|title=The London Economist and the High Tide of Laissez Faire|year=1955|journal=Journal of Political Economy|volume=63|issue=6|pages=461–488|doi=10.1086/257722}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=London Clubs in the Late Nineteenth Century|url=http://www.nuff.ox.ac.uk/economics/history/paper28/28taddeiweb1.pdf|author=Antonia Taddei|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Austrian school|Austrian scholars]] argue that laissez-faire was never the main doctrine of any nation, and at the end of the 1800s, European countries reintroduced economic protectionism and interventionism.

The [[centre-right]] [[Gaullism|Gaullists]] in post-World War II France advocated considerable social spending on education and infrastructure development, as well as extensive economic regulation and a limited amount of the wealth redistribution measures more characteristic of [[social democracy]].

[[Objectivism (Ayn Rand)|Objectivism]] is a [[philosophy]] developed by [[Ayn Rand]] in the [[20th century philosophy|20th century]].&lt;ref&gt;So identified by sources including:
:Hicks, Stephen. ''Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy'' (2006), s.v. "[http://www.iep.utm.edu/r/rand.htm Ayn Rand]" Retrieved June 22, 2006.&lt;br/&gt; Smith, Tara. Review of "On Ayn Rand." ''The Review of Metaphysics'' 54, no. 3 (2001): 654–655. Retrieved from ProQuest Research Library.&lt;br/&gt;''Encyclopædia Britannica'' (2006), s.v. "[http://www.search.eb.com/eb/article-9062648 Rand, Ayn.]" Retrieved June 22, 2006, from Encyclopædia Britannica Online.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;One source notes: "Perhaps because she so eschewed academic philosophy, and because her works are rightly considered to be works of literature, Objectivist philosophy is regularly omitted from academic philosophy . Yet throughout literary academia, Ayn Rand is considered a philosopher. Her works merit consideration as works of philosophy in their own right." (Jenny Heyl, 1995, as cited in {{cite book|title=Feminist Interpretations of Ayn Rand|editor=Mimi R Gladstein, Chris Matthew Sciabarra(eds)|id=ISBN 0-271-01831-3|publisher=Penn State Press|year=1999}}, [http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0271018313&amp;id=bei61AcYlT0C&amp;pg=PA17&amp;lpg=PA17&amp;sig=FxQ177GbCkq1rn4hiipdSIjjGeE p. 17])&lt;/ref&gt; Objectivism holds that the proper [[moral]] purpose of one's life is the pursuit of one's own [[happiness]] through acting in one's "rational self-interest", and that the only social system consistent with this morality is [[individualism]], embodied in pure, consensual laissez-faire capitalism.

==Contemporary usage==
{{main|Left-Right politics}}

The right tends to support a decentralized economy based on [[economic freedom]], and advocates policies such as [[property rights]], [[free markets]], and [[free trade]], some claim that [[Economic freedom]] correlates with right-leaning governments.&lt;ref name="flow"/&gt;. The left generally advocates [[regulatory economics]] and [[egalitarianism]]. However, many conservative authoritarians and rightist radicals supported [[corporatism]].&lt;ref&gt;''Fascism, Comparison and Definition'', Stanley Payne, University of Wisconsin Press, ISBN 0299080641, 9780299080648, pg 19: "Right radicals and conservative authoritarians almost without exception became corporatists in formal doctrines of political economy, but the fascists were less explicit and in general less schematic."&lt;/ref&gt; Cultural positions vary. Theories of [[economic liberalism]], which is the economic component of [[classical liberalism]], were largely developed by [[Adam Smith]] during the [[Age of Enlightenment]]. Smith advocated minimal interference by government in the economy, but did not oppose the state's provision of a few basic [[public goods]] such as roads, canals, schools, bridges and other [[infrastructure]] that cannot be efficiently implemented by private entities.
&lt;ref&gt;Eric Aaron, ''What's Right?'' (Dural, Australia: Rosenberg Publishing, 2003), 75.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="econlib"&gt;{{cite web|title=Adam Smith|publisher=econlib.org|url=http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/bios/Smith.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Smith preferred that these goods should be paid proportionally to their consumption (e.g., with [[Toll road|tolls]]).

Private [[property]] and individual [[contract]]s form the basis of economic liberalism. These theories began in the eighteenth century with the claim that if everyone is left to their own economic devices to pursue their self-interest (the [[invisible hand]]), instead of being controlled by the state, then the result would be a harmonious and more equal society of ever-increasing prosperity ([[spontaneous order]]).&lt;ref&gt;Adams, Ian. Political Ideology Today. Manchester U Press 2001. p 20&lt;/ref&gt;. This theory includes the caveat that minimum standards of public information and justice should exist, and that no-one should be allowed to coerce or steal. 
Smith also advocated [[Free trade area|retaliatory tariffs]] to bring about free trade, and [[copyright]]s and [[patent]]s to encourage innovation.&lt;ref name=econlib&gt;{{cite web|title=Adam Smith|publisher=econlib.org|url=http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/bios/Smith.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Economic liberal ideas underpinned the move towards a [[Capitalism|capitalist]] economic system in the late 18th century and the subsequent demise of the [[mercantilism|mercantilist]] system.

The annual surveys ''[[Economic Freedom of the World]]'' and ''[[Index of Economic Freedom]]'' are two indices which attempt to measure the degree of economic freedom in the world's nations, using a definition similar to [[laissez-faire]] capitalism. Rafael Di Tella and Robert MacCulloch argue that right-wing governments tend to bring economic freedom, and state that rich countries have consistently more right-leaning governments while poor countries have consistently more left-wing governments.&lt;ref name="flow"&gt;[http://www.people.hbs.edu/rditella/papers/WPLegit06.pdf "Why doesn't Capitalism flow to Poor Countries?"] Rafael Di Tella (Harvard Business School) and Robert MacCulloch (Imperial College London)&lt;/ref&gt;

Right-wing [[libertarianism]] has focused on the preservation of rights through constraints on government power. 
[[Libertarian conservatism]], also known as [[conservative libertarianism]], describes certain movements. [[Ronald Reagan]] often is quoted as saying: "I believe the very heart and soul of conservatism is libertarianism."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reason.com/news/show/29318.html Inside Ronald Reagan], a [[Reason (magazine)| Reason magazine]] Interview with Ronald Reagan, July 1975.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some associate [[ethnic nationalism]] and certain forms of [[populism]] with the right.&lt;ref name="canovan"&gt;Canovan, Margaret. 1981. ''Populism.''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Betz |first=Hans-Georg |title=Radical Right-Wing Populism in Western Europe |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |date= 1994|isbn=978-0312083908}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to most scholars of [[fascism]], there are both left and right influences on fascist ideology, and facism has historically attacked [[communism]], [[liberalism]] and [[conservatism]]. Many scholars argue that fascism is a search for a [[Third position|third way]] among these views.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bastow|first=Steve |title=Third Way Discourse: European Ideologies in the Twentieth Century|publisher=Edinburgh University Press |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=0J9DpxWxi14C&amp;pg=PA93&amp;dq=%22third+way%22+fascism&amp;sig=ACfU3U21wyLLZwse3dYoyA7aXJoN9cYUsw |isbn=074861561X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="macdonal"&gt;{{cite book |last=Macdonald |first=Hamish |title=Mussolini and Italian Fascism |publisher=Nelson Thornes |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=221W9vKkWrcC&amp;pg=PT16&amp;dq=Gabriele+d%27Annunzio+paris+peace&amp;sig=ACfU3U1BTr2IQkCU7gfZKyLAg2TRbp6a8g |isbn=0748733868}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Woolley |first=Donald Patrick |title=The Third Way: Fascism as a Method of Maintaining Power in Italy and Spain |publisher=University of North Carolina at Greensboro |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=SjOyGwAACAAJ&amp;dq=%22third+way%22+fascism}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Heywood |first=Andrew |title=Key Concepts in Politics |publisher=Palgrave |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=221W9vKkWrcC&amp;pg=PT16&amp;dq=Gabriele+d%27Annunzio+paris+peace&amp;sig=ACfU3U1BTr2IQkCU7gfZKyLAg2TRbp6a8g |isbn=0312233817}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Renton |first=Dave |title=Fascism: Theory and Practice|publisher=Pluto Press |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Ojtn0IT6LpgC&amp;pg=PA28&amp;dq=%22third+way%22+fascism&amp;lr=&amp;sig=ACfU3U29w491Co0j3H4s72KUCvx_36hSIQ |isbn=0745314708}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kallis |first=Aristotle A |title=The Fascism Reader |publisher=Routledge |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tP2wXl5nzboC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;dq=%22third+way%22+fascism+eatwell&amp;lr=&amp;sig=ACfU3U049ZN8MGgXE7O87P1E2rKYDdUGnQ |isbn=0415243599}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="natureoffascismo"&gt;{{cite book |last=Griffin |first=Roger |title=The Nature of Fascism |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fcn5ZtaPc7oC&amp;dq=%22third+way%22+fascism+eatwell&amp;lr= |isbn=0312071329}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book  |last=Parla |first=Taha |title=The Social and Political Thought of Ziya Gökalp, 1876-1924 |publisher=Brill |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=63weAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA113&amp;dq=%22third+way%22+fascism&amp;lr=&amp;sig=ACfU3U22B0TsrgAkF0dKzH-tGewY7I5n2g |isbn=9004072292}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Durham |first=Martin |title=Women and Fascism |publisher=Routledge |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=yA1Y5znKY1sC&amp;pg=PA4&amp;dq=%22third+way%22+fascism+eatwell&amp;lr=&amp;sig=ACfU3U00G6DB4k2NLWe5EMGpvsNKqyq5tA |isbn=0415122805}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Italian Facist party was founded by prominent former socialists ([[Benito Mussolini]] was a former socialist), and attracted support from trade unions and labor movement. However, some claim that fascist movements have become "more monolithically right-wing", and fascism has become intertwined with the [[Far right|radical right]].&lt;ref&gt;Roger Griffin, Interregnum or Endgame?: Radical Right Thought in the ‘Post-fascist’ Era, ''The Journal of Political Ideologies,'' vol. 5, no. 2, July 2000, pp. 163-78&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;‘Non Angeli, sed Angli: the neo-populist foreign policy of the "New" BNP', in Christina Liang (ed.) Europe for the Europeans: the foreign and security policy of the populist radical right (Ashgate, Hampshire,2007). ISBN 0754648516&lt;/ref&gt;

==Positions around the world==
===Australia===
The Australian right is represented by the [[Liberal Party of Australia]], whose most recent Prime Minister was John Howard. It advocates close ties with the United Kingdom and the United States, and during its last period of power sent troops to Iraq and was outspoken against Robert Mugabe.

===Botswana===
[[Image:SeretseKhama.jpg|thumb|120px|[[Seretse Khama]], a right-wing pioneer in Africa and the first president of Botswana.]] 

The [[Botswana Democratic Party]] is the major [[Conservatism|conservative]] right-wing party of Botswana, currently led by president [[Ian Khama]]. It was founded by the country's first president [[Seretse Khama]]. Since Botswana's independence in 1966, the party has remained continuously in power. As of the most recent election, the party holds 44 of 57 seats.

The party is considered pro-Western. Supporters of the party believe that it has provided stability again civil unrest, democratic rule, and a level of development that exceeds other African countries. According to the annual [[Economic Freedom of the World]] survey, as of 2008 Botswana ranks 36th out of 157. Botswana is the second highest ranked African country behind Mauritius.

===Estonia===
The right-wing Reform Party's agenda includes low [[flat tax]]es. It wants to end conscription and to introduce a voluntary army.

Estonia's market reforms put it among the economic leaders in the former [[COMECON]] area. In 1994, Estonia became one of the first countries in the world to adopt a flat tax, with a uniform rate of 26% regardless of personal income. In January 2005 the personal income tax rate was reduced to 24%. A subsequent reduction to 23% followed in January 2006. The income tax rate will be decreased by 1% annually to reach 18% by January 2010. The [[Government of Estonia]] finalized the design of Estonia's [[euro coins]] in late 2004, and is now intending to adopt the [[euro]] as the country's currency between 2011 and 2013, later than planned due to continued high [[inflation]]. In 1999, Estonia experienced its worst year economically since it regained independence in 1991, largely because of the impact of the August 1998 [[Russian financial crisis]]. Estonia joined the [[World Trade Organization]] in November 1999. With assistance from the [[European Union]], the [[World Bank]] and the [[Nordic Investment Bank]], Estonia completed most of its preparations for [[European Union]] membership by the end of 2002 and now has one of the strongest economies of the new member states of the [[European Union]].

Estonian government has remained especially confident and highly optimistic. It derives at least some part its optimism and confidence from its financial reserves, which exceeded a 10% of GDP mark by the end of 2006 and which will be further increased by an approximately 3.6% of GDP surplus in the 2007 budget. Estonia's public debt is currently just 3.6% of GDP, which is the lowest in the EU and one of the lowest in the whole world. The 2008 budget is planned to produce a 1.5% of GDP surplus.

===Denmark===
[[Image:Anders Fogh Rasmussen - World Economic Forum Annual Meeting Davos 2008.jpg|120px|thumb|left|[[Anders Fogh Rasmussen]], the Prime Minister of Denmark.]]

[[Venstre]] is the largest [[political party]] in Denmark. Founded with a basis on [[free market]] [[liberalism]], it is now a [[right-wing]] party. The party is a member of [[Liberal International]] and sits with the [[European Liberal Democrat and Reform Party]] in the [[European Parliament]]. In the [[Danish parliamentary election, 2007|2007 parliamentary elections]], it received 26% of the vote, and 46 out of 179 seats. It is led by [[Anders Fogh Rasmussen]], the [[Prime Minister of Denmark|Prime Minister]], and currently governs in coalition with the [[Conservative People's Party (Denmark)|Conservative People's Party]], with support from the [[Danish People's Party]].

''Venstre'' is a liberal party. Some describe it as a [[classical liberalism|classical liberal]] party, since the current leader ([[Anders Fogh Rasmussen]]) is known for his authorship of the book "Fra Socialstat til Minimalstat" (English: From Social State to Minimal State). His book advocated an extensive reform of the Danish [[welfare state]] along classical liberal lines, including lower taxes and less government interference in corporate and individual matters.

===Germany===
[[Image:Angela Merkel (2008) v3.jpg|thumb|120px|[[Angela Merkel]], the first female chancellor of Germany.]]
[[Angela Merkel]]'s first foreign trip took place on the day she was sworn in as Chancellor, and went to Paris for a meeting with the then French president, [[Jacques Chirac]]. In his speech, Chirac emphasized the importance of the Franco-German Companionship for Europe. After the meeting with Chirac, she travelled to [[Brussels]] for talks with EU leaders and the Secretary-General of [[NATO]], [[Jaap de Hoop Scheffer]]. She then traveled to London where she met with the then British Prime Minister, [[Tony Blair]]. On November 28, 2005, she received her first state guest: [[Hifikepunye Pohamba|President Pohamba]] of [[Namibia]], a former colony of Germany. In her first government address on November 30, 2005 she announced her objective of improving the German Economy and reducing unemployment.

Merkel made her first visit to the Middle East as [[President of the European Council|President-in-office of the European Council]] on April 1, 2007. She offered Europe's help to get [[Israel]] and the [[Palestinians]] back to the negotiating table, and tried to restart international efforts for renewed peace talks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Merkel visits Mideast as EU president|publisher=[[International Herald Tribune]]|date=2007-04-01|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/04/01/news/gaza.php|accessdate=2007-04-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===France===
The largest party in France, the right-wing [[Union for a Popular Movement]] - and particularly [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] - has pledged to reform the French system, get rid of the old special interests, and make France more competitive.

[[Nicholas Sarkozy]], the president of France, supports closer political ties with Europe's [[North Africa]]n and [[Mideast]] neighbors on the [[Mediterranean Sea]].

Nicholas Sarkozy would like to see more free trade between Europe and North Africa.

===Iceland===
[[Davíð Oddsson]] became Prime Minister in 1991 and began a program of monetary and fiscal stabilization, privatization, tax rate reduction, definition of exclusive use rights in fisheries, abolition of various government funds for aiding unprofitable enterprises and liberalization of currency transfers and capital markets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Article on Icelandic economic miracle|author=Gissurarson, Hannes H.|date=2004-11-29|url=http://courses.wcupa.edu/rbove/eco343/040Compecon/Scand/Iceland/040129prosper.htm|publisher=The Wall Street Journal|accessdate=2008-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, Iceland was ranked as the [[List of countries by Human Development Index|most developed country]] in the world by the [[Human Development Index|United Nations' Human Development Index]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://hdr.undp.org/en/media/hdr_20072008_en_indicator_tables.pdf untitled&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===
[[Image:Koizumi in Graceland 2006.jpg|thumb|left|[[Junichiro Koizumi]], a leader of the right-wing [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic Party]] (LDP) who won the largest party majority ever in modern Japanese history.]]
The Japan's right-wing [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic Party]]  - which has won most elections for half a century - traditionally identified itself with a number of general goals: rapid, export-based economic growth; close cooperation with the United States in foreign and defense policies; and several newer issues, such as administrative reform. Administrative reform encompassed several themes: simplification and streamlining of government bureaucracy; privatization of [[Japanese public corporations|stateowned enterprises]]; and adoption of measures, including tax reform, needed to prepare for the strain on the economy posed by an aging society.

Other priorities in the early 1990s included promoting a more active and positive role for Japan in the rapidly developing Asia-Pacific region, internationalizing Japan's economy by liberalizing and promoting domestic demand, creating a hightechnology information society, and promoting scientific research. A business-inspired commitment to free enterprise was tempered by the insistence of important small business and [[Agriculture, forestry, and fishing in Japan|agricultural constituencies]] on some form of [[protectionism]] and [[subsidies]].

===Liberia===
[[Image:Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf3.jpg|thumb|130px|[[Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf]]]]
[[Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf]] is the first elected female head of state in Africa. She has pledged to embark [[neoliberal]] reforms.

===Middle East===
The Middle East does not have a left-right axis.&lt;ref&gt;R.J. Dalton&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Tzipi Livni Conference.jpg|thumb|[[Tzipi Livni]], former right-wing leader in [[Likud]], now designated Prime Minister.]]
An exception is [[Israel]] with its Western political system. In [[Israel]], [[Likud]] is the major [[centre-right]] [[List of political parties in Israel|political party]]. Founded in 1973 as an alliance of several right-wing and liberal parties, Likud's victory in the [[Israeli legislative election, 1977|1977 elections]] was a major turning point in the country's political history.&lt;ref&gt;Israel at the Polls, 1992 By Daniel Judah Elazar, Shmuel Sandler&lt;/ref&gt;

The Likud supports [[free market]] [[capitalism]] and [[liberalism]]. The Likud, under the guidance of [[Finance minister]] [[Binyamin Netanyahu]], pushed through legislation reducing [[value added tax]] (VAT), income and corporate taxes significantly, as well as [[customs duty]]. Likewise, it has instituted free-trade (especially with the [[European Union]] and the [[United States|U.S.]]) and dismantled certain monopolies ([[Bezeq]] and the sea ports). Additionally, it has managed to privatize numerous government owned companies ([[El Al|El&amp;nbsp;Al]] and [[Bank Leumi]]). The last Likud Finance minister, now the party leader, [[Benjamin Netanyahu]], was the most ardent free-market Israeli Finance minister to-date.

===South Korea===
The right-wing [[Grand National Party]] is the most popular party in South Korea. Left-wing parties are unpopular, the largest left-wing party receiving only some 3% of votes.

After decades of free market policies, free trade, and low taxation, South Korea is a major [[G20 industrial nations|economic power]] and one of the wealthiest countries in Asia. It had one of the world's fastest growing economies since the 1960s, now highly [[developed country|developed]]&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;[http://travel.state.gov/travel/cis_pa_tw/cis/cis_1018.html Korea, Republic of&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[List of Asian countries by GDP|fourth largest]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper
 |author=IMF
 |title=World Economic Outlook Database, October 2007
|version = 2007
 |publisher=IMF
 |date=2007
 |url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2007/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy=2006&amp;ey=2008&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;pr1.x=56&amp;pr1.y=12&amp;c=512%2C941%2C914%2C446%2C612%2C666%2C614%2C668%2C311%2C672%2C213%2C946%2C911%2C137%2C193%2C962%2C122%2C674%2C912%2C676%2C313%2C548%2C419%2C556%2C513%2C678%2C316%2C181%2C913%2C682%2C124%2C684%2C339%2C273%2C638%2C921%2C514%2C948%2C218%2C686%2C963%2C688%2C616%2C518%2C223%2C728%2C516%2C558%2C918%2C138%2C748%2C196%2C618%2C278%2C522%2C692%2C622%2C694%2C156%2C142%2C624%2C449%2C626%2C564%2C628%2C283%2C228%2C853%2C924%2C288%2C233%2C293%2C632%2C566%2C636%2C964%2C634%2C182%2C238%2C453%2C662%2C968%2C960%2C922%2C423%2C714%2C935%2C862%2C128%2C716%2C611%2C456%2C321%2C722%2C243%2C942%2C248%2C718%2C469%2C724%2C253%2C576%2C642%2C936%2C643%2C961%2C939%2C813%2C644%2C199%2C819%2C184%2C172%2C524%2C132%2C361%2C646%2C362%2C648%2C364%2C915%2C732%2C134%2C366%2C652%2C734%2C174%2C144%2C328%2C146%2C258%2C463%2C656%2C528%2C654%2C923%2C336%2C738%2C263%2C578%2C268%2C537%2C532%2C742%2C944%2C866%2C176%2C369%2C534%2C744%2C536%2C186%2C429%2C925%2C178%2C746%2C436%2C926%2C136%2C466%2C343%2C112%2C158%2C111%2C439%2C298%2C916%2C927%2C664%2C846%2C826%2C299%2C542%2C582%2C443%2C474%2C917%2C754%2C544%2C698&amp;s=PPPGDP&amp;grp=0&amp;a=
 |accessdate=2008-02-12}}
&lt;/ref&gt; in Asia and [[List of countries by GDP (nominal)|13th largest]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper
 |author=IMF
 |title=World Economic Outlook Database, October 2007
|version = 2007
 |publisher=IMF
 |url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2007/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?pr.x=56&amp;pr.y=6&amp;sy=2007&amp;ey=2007&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;c=512%2C941%2C914%2C446%2C612%2C666%2C614%2C668%2C311%2C672%2C213%2C946%2C911%2C137%2C193%2C962%2C122%2C674%2C912%2C676%2C313%2C548%2C419%2C556%2C513%2C678%2C316%2C181%2C913%2C682%2C124%2C684%2C339%2C273%2C638%2C921%2C514%2C948%2C218%2C686%2C963%2C688%2C616%2C518%2C223%2C728%2C516%2C558%2C918%2C138%2C748%2C196%2C618%2C278%2C522%2C692%2C622%2C694%2C156%2C142%2C624%2C449%2C626%2C564%2C628%2C283%2C228%2C853%2C924%2C288%2C233%2C293%2C632%2C566%2C636%2C964%2C634%2C182%2C238%2C453%2C662%2C968%2C960%2C922%2C423%2C714%2C935%2C862%2C128%2C716%2C611%2C456%2C321%2C722%2C243%2C942%2C248%2C718%2C469%2C724%2C253%2C576%2C642%2C936%2C643%2C961%2C939%2C813%2C644%2C199%2C819%2C184%2C172%2C524%2C132%2C361%2C646%2C362%2C648%2C364%2C915%2C732%2C134%2C366%2C652%2C734%2C174%2C144%2C328%2C146%2C258%2C463%2C656%2C528%2C654%2C923%2C336%2C738%2C263%2C578%2C268%2C537%2C532%2C742%2C944%2C866%2C176%2C369%2C534%2C744%2C536%2C186%2C429%2C925%2C178%2C746%2C436%2C926%2C136%2C466%2C343%2C112%2C158%2C111%2C439%2C298%2C916%2C927%2C664%2C846%2C826%2C299%2C542%2C582%2C443%2C474%2C917%2C754%2C544%2C698&amp;s=PPPGDP&amp;grp=0&amp;a= October 2007
 |accessdate=2008-02-12}}
&lt;/ref&gt; in the world. Forming the [[G20 industrial nations]] and the world's top ten [[List of countries by exports|exporters]], it is an [[APEC]] and [[OECD]] member, defined as a High Income Nation by the [[World Bank Group|World Bank]] and an Advanced Economy by the [[International Monetary Fund]] and [[Central Intelligence Agency]]. A [[major non-NATO ally]], it has the world's sixth largest [[List of countries by size of armed forces|armed forces]] and the tenth largest [[List of countries by military expenditures|defence budget]] in the world. The [[Four Asian Tigers|Asian Tiger]] is leading the [[Next Eleven]] nations and is still among the world's fastest growing [[developed country|developed countries]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt; Today, its success story is known as the "[[Miracle on the Han River]]", a role model for many [[developing country|developing countries]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,361781,00.html Seoul's Green Revolution - TIME&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

South Korea is leading several key [[industries]] in the world, particularly in the fields of [[science]] and [[technology]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.duke.edu/~myhan/kaf0401.html ANNOTATED CHRONOLOGY OF KOREA’S SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY (Moo-Young Han, Professor of physics, Duke University / Editor-in-Chief, Society of Korean-American Scholars)]&lt;/ref&gt; It has a very advanced and modern [[infrastructure]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationsencyclopedia.com/economies/Asia-and-the-Pacific/Korea-South-INFRASTRUCTURE-POWER-AND-COMMUNICATIONS.html Korea, South Infrastructure, power, and communications, Information about Infrastructure, power, and communications in Korea, South&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and is a world leader in [[information technology]] such as [[electronics]], [[semiconductor]]s, [[LCD|LCD displays]], [[computer]]s and [[mobile phone]]s, led by [[Samsung Group|Samsung]] and [[LG Group|LG]]. Home of the world's third largest [[steel]] producer, [[POSCO]], it is the world's largest [[shipbuilder]], the world's fourth largest [[oil refiner]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmaster.com/graph/ene_oil_ref_abi-energy-oil-refining-ability NationMaster - Oil refining ability (most recent) by country&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and one of the world's top five [[Automotive industry|automobile]] producers, headed by [[Hyundai Motor Company|Hyundai]] and [[Kia Motors|Kia]]. It is also a leading country in [[biotechnology]], [[construction]], [[engineering]], [[machinery]], [[petrochemical]]s, [[robotics]] and [[textile]]s.

===Netherlands===
[[Image:Ayaan-Hirsi-Ali-VVD.NL-1200x1600.JPG|left|90px|thumb|[[Ayaan Hirsi Ali]], a Dutch right-wing politician and writer.]]
In Netherlands, [[People's Party for Freedom and Democracy]] represents [[conservative liberalism]].

The last ''Liberal Manifesto'' of the VVD was published in September 2005. It develops a broad outline around the themes of [[democracy]], [[security]], [[Freedom (political)|freedom]] and [[citizenship]], along with a vision of the future of party's internal structure. Below some of the points from the Manifesto are presented:
* The Manifesto calls for a directly elected [[Minister-President]], whereby voters can show their preference on the ballot.
* The question of (advisory) [[referendum]]s is left open as a possibility.
* [[Mayor]]s should be directly elected by the people.
* Commitment to the [[Four Freedoms (European Union)|Four Freedoms]] of the [[European Union]].
* People's right to [[euthanasia]].
* Reform of the welfare state and lower taxes in order to increase economic growth, while retaining some policies such as taxpayer-paid daycare for working people.
* Permissive [[cannabis]] policy.

===Sweden===
[[Image:Opposition leaders at the 2006 Sweden elections.jpg|thumb|200px|Leaders of [[Alliance for Sweden]], the right-wing government coalition.]]

The [[Moderate Party]] emphasizes [[free markets]], [[privatisation]], [[Freedom (political)|personal freedom]]  and reduction of the public-sector growth rate, while still supporting most of the [[social benefits]] introduced since the 1930s. The party emphasises issues such as actions against crime, lower taxes, a strong defence and quality in the education system. The party also supports Sweden's membership in the [[European Union]]. They campaigned for changing currency to the [[euro]] in the 2003 referendum.

[[Fredrik Reinfeldt]] is the current Prime Minister of Sweden.

It is a member of the [[European People's Party]] (EPP) and the [[International Democrat Union]] (IDU).

===Republic of China===
[[Image:2006INGTaipeiMarathon-077.jpg|thumb|left|140px|[[Taiwan]]'s current President [[Ma Ying-jeou]], who pledged to expand [[free trade]].]]
In the [[Republic of China]], the right-wing [[Pan-Blue Coalition]] generally seeks warmer relations with the socialist People's Republic of China.

===United Kingdom===
In the United Kingdom, the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] represents the right wing among the two main parties, the other being the historically socialist Labour party. The Conservatives are currently in opposition, but have been in power more than any other political party. Conservative Prime Ministers include [[Lord North]], [[William Pitt the Younger]], [[Spencer Perceval]], the [[Duke of Wellington]], [[Sir Robert Peel]], [[Benjamin Disraeli]], [[Arthur Balfour]], [[Winston Churchill]] and [[Harold Macmillan]]. [[Margaret Thatcher]] was the first female Prime Minister and her [[Thatcherism|thatcherist]] ideas are credited for starting a new era of economic growth.

Currently, the Conservative Party is led by [[David Cameron]]. In recent years, the popularity of the Conservative Party has expanded so much that polls and prediction markets in 2008 showed a possibility to win a landslide absolute majority.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/world/britain/displaystory.cfm?story_id=12305853 Labour's electoral prospects: Dead-cat bounce]. [[The Economist]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===

{{Refimprovesect|date=November 2008}}

From an international perspective, both major political parties in the United States may lean to the right, but this perspective is based on differing boundaries on the political perspective. [[Socialism]] in the United States is considered extreme-left, whereas internationally [[communism]] is usually considered the extreme-left and socialism more moderate. For instance, most left-wing parties in Europe lean to socialism, but the left-wing [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] has never leaned that far. Politicians who have leaned to socialism in the United States, such as Vermont senator [[Bernie Sanders]], while often caucusing with the Democrats, usually have run with no party affiliation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/21/magazine/21Sanders.t.html?pagewanted=1&amp;_r=1 The Socialist Senator]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]] is the major right wing party in the United States and is identified as being [[Conservatism in the United States|conservative]]. Similarly to the Democratic Party, the Republican Party has never leaned to the extreme right. Politicians who do lean further to the right sometimes still identify themselves as Republicans, such as Texas representative [[Ron Paul]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/22/magazine/22Paul-t.html?ei=5124&amp;en=22ee37525a9fc4f5&amp;ex=1343016000&amp;partner=permalink&amp;exprod=permalink&amp;pagewanted=all|title=The Antiwar, Anti-Abortion, Anti-Drug-Enforcement-Administration, Anti-Medicare Candidacy of Dr. Ron Paul|author=Caldwell, Christopher|work=[[New York Times Magazine]]|date=2007-07-22|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; while others, such as former Georgia representative [[Bob Barr]], may affiliate themselves with the [[Libertarian Party (United States)|Libertarian Party]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boston.com/news/nation/articles/2008/05/26/ex_gop_congressman_barr_wins_libertarian_nomination/ Ex-GOP congressman Barr wins Libertarian nomination]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, the right has long been associated with [[small government|minimal government]] and sometimes with [[Law and order (politics)|law and order]]. It tends to support [[free markets]], economic freedom, and [[property rights]].{{Fact|date=November 2008}}

==See also==
* [[Classical liberalism]]
* [[Conservatism]]
* [[Corporatism]]
* [[Economic liberalism]]
* [[Far right]]
* [[Free market]]
* [[Free trade]]
* [[Globalization]]
* [[Ideology]]
* [[Left-Right politics]]
* [[Left-wing politics]]
* [[Liberalism]]
* [[Libertarianism]]
* [[Nolan chart]]
* [[Objectivism (Ayn Rand)|Objectivism]]
* [[Political compass]]
* [[Political spectrum]]
* [[Republicanism]]
* [[Social conservatism]]
* [[World's Smallest Political Quiz]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.politicalcompass.org/ The Political Compass], a two-dimensional political chart
*[http://FreedomKeys.com/nolancharts.htm The Nolan Charts], other alternative political spectra (mostly libertarian-oriented).
*[http://www.idu.org/ IDU : International Democrat Union]
*[http://www.liberal-international.org/ Liberal International (has many right-wing parties)]
*[http://www.epp.eu/ EPP - European People's Party (the largest European-level party of Europe)]

[[Category:Right-wing politics]]
[[Category:Political spectrum]]

[[ca:Dreta]]
[[cs:Pravice (politika)]]
[[da:Højreorienteret]]
[[de:Politische Rechte (Politik)]]
[[el:Δεξιά (πολιτική)]]
[[es:Derecha política]]
[[fr:Droite (politique)]]
[[gl:Dereita política]]
[[id:Sayap kanan]]
[[is:Hægristefna]]
[[it:Destra (politica)]]
[[lt:Dešinė (politikoje)]]
[[hu:Jobboldal]]
[[ms:Politik haluan kanan]]
[[ja:右翼]]
[[nn:Høgresida]]
[[pl:Prawica]]
[[pt:Direita política]]
[[ru:Правые (политика)]]
[[simple:Right-wing]]
[[sr:Десница]]
[[fi:Oikeisto]]
[[sv:Politisk höger]]
[[uk:Права партія]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>