<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041103151419|7085357" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56522" pageid="56522" ns="0" title="Right-wing politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-03T23:46:40Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In [[politics]], '''right-wing''', '''the political right''', or simply '''the right''', are terms which refer, with no particular precision, to the segment of the [[political spectrum]] in opposition to [[left-wing politics]]. It is usually, but not always, associated with [[conservatism]]. (See [[political spectrum]] and [[Left-Right politics|left-right politics]] for a detailed explanation and discussion of this kind of classification.) 

The phrase "right-wing" comes from the seating arrangement of parliamentary partisans during the [[French Revolution]]. The [[monarchism|monarchists]] who supported the [[ancien regime]] were commonly referred to as rightists because they sat on the right side of successive legislative assemblies. As this original reference became obsolete, the meaning of the terms has changed as appropriate to the spectrum of ideas and stances being compared, and the point of view of the speaker.  

==Right wing issues==
Tradition, the means of preserving wealth and power in the hands that have traditionally held them, social stability, and national solidarity and ambition are among the concerns typically associated with the right wing of the political spectrum. Those on the right are sometimes called "[[reactionary]]" by their opponents, a term that first arose to refer to those whose politics was formed in reaction against the [[French Revolution]].

==History of the term==
Since the French Revolution, the political use of the terms "left" and "right" has evolved across linguistic, societal, and national boundaries, sometimes taking on meanings in one time and place that contrast sharply with those in another. For example, the present-day [[as of 2004]] government of [[China]] claims to remain on the "left," despite an evolution that has brought it quite close to what is elsewhere characterized as "right," supporting national cultural traditions, the interests of wealth, privately owned industry, and a rather imperial nationalism. Conversely, the late dictator of [[Spain]], [[Francisco Franco]], who was firmly allied internationally with the right and who brutally suppressed the Spanish left, nonetheless pursued numerous development policies quite similar to those of the [[Soviet Union]] and other [[communist state]]s, which are almost universally considered to be on the "left." Similarly, while "right" originally referred to those who supported the interests of [[aristocracy]], in many countries today (notably the [[United States]]) the left-right distinction is not strongly correlated with wealth or ancestry.

==Fascism and right-wing politics==
Despite the important differences from other right-wing ideologies, fascism is almost universally considered to be a part of "the right". This is somewhat parallel to the customary inclusion of [[communist state|state communism]] (and, in particular, that of the [[Stalinist]] [[Soviet Union]] and [[Maoism|Maoist]] [[China]]) in "the left."  Nonetheless, fascism differs significantly from other politics that are usually classified as right wing, and most right-wingers (even many far right groups) reject any association with it, just like most left-wingers (even many communists) reject any association with Stalinism and Maoism.

Many of the creators of Italian Fascism had originally been supporters of the political left, but eventually turned against their old ideas (for various reasons) and tried to develop a right-wing alternative instead. Philosophers such as [[Robert Michel]], [[Sergio Panunzio]], and [[Giovanni Gentile]] were originally [[syndicalism|syndicalists]], a group normally identified with the left and whose tactical propensity for [[direct action]] became an element in Italian Fascism. [[Benito Mussolini]] himself was originally a socialist, though he had ceased even to claim to be one by the time he was leading the fascist party (and, indeed, many of his old comrades were the first targets of his political police). In the treatise ''[[Doctrine of Fascism]]'' (written by Gentile but approved by Mussolini); fascism is identified as being of the right and it is declared that the 20th century will be the "century of the right".

[[David Schoenbaum]] argued in his book ''Hitler's Social Revolution: Class and Status in Nazi Germany, 1933-1939'' that Nazism contained certain revolutionary and socialist aspects (although more in rhetoric than in reality), and it was no coincidence that the Nazis often found themselves in a struggle with the Communists for the same constituency (although this can be seen as a typical left/right struggle in elections, albeit involving more radical versions of the two sides, and there is no evidence of voters transferring their support from the [[KPD]] to the Nazi party or vice versa, while the Nazis mainly took votes from the [[DNVP]] and the [[DVP]]).  However, it is a historical truth that the [[DAP]], which later became the [[Nazi Party]], was formed in response and in opposition to a brief Communist revolt in Bavaria.  While the Nazis opposed [[individualism]] and ''laissez faire'' [[capitalism]], vigorous opposition to [[socialism]] was a founding and continuing tenet of Nazi fascism. Also, one of the key motivations behind [[World War II]] was Hitler's desire to exterminate [[communism]].

Japanese fascism, while a distinct phenomenon, is also ordinarily understood as an expression of a right-wing philosophy; but like other forms of fascism, it is only unequivocally right wing if the terms of comparison are limited.  Like other forms, it arose in antithesis to the agenda of leftists, Communists, and Socialists.  

In contemporary politics, neofascists and [[neonazi]]s are said to be ''far right''. Authoritarian conservatives such as supporters of the former [[Chile]]an dictator [[Augusto Pinochet]] or supporters of the military [[junta]]s that ruled much of [[Latin America]] in the 1970s are also said to be ''far right''.

== Right wings groups and the [[War on Terrorism]] ==

=== Overview ===

In many cases, the Left-Right dichotomy is nowadays characterized more by their respective positions on national conflicts than their economic differences (and some thinkers, both of the left and the right, see this as a worrying tendency). Examples include the [[War on terror]] campaign, led by the [[United States]], and the [[Israel]]i war against [[Palestinian terrorism]]. While right-wing movements such as the American '''[[Neoconservatism (United States)|Neo Conservative]]s''' are [[hawkish]] and support military operations against states said to be "terror-sponsoring" -- emphasizing the need to oppose [[Islamic terrorism]] (by which they mean [[Al-Qaida]], [[Hamas]] and even [[Arab dictatorships]]) -- most [[left wing]] movements in the United States are [[dovish]] and oppose preemptive military action as a violation of [[human rights]] and [[international law]] (see also: [[Left-wing_politics#Leftism.2C_Pacifism_and_.22War_on_Terror.22|Left wing and the anti-war movement]]).

For example, while the [[War on Terrorism]] and (to a lesser extent) [[Operation Iraqi Freedom]] have been generally supported by most on the Right and many moderates (albeit with some minor criticisms), most voices on the Left have been extremely critical of either the premise of the war (e.g., [[Howard Dean]]) or [[George W. Bush]]'s handling of it.

=== Reasons for support ===

In the United States, many groups seen to be right wing support the use of military measures against [[terrorist organization]]s and [[U.S. list of state sponsors of international terrorism|terror supporting states]]. Many "fringe groups" on the Far Right oppose the "war on terror" however, and many on the Left generally approve a proactive stance against terrorism and dictatorship.

Many believe that the hardliner approach is the only right approach to deal with terrorists and dictators. The most famous example for this is the persistence of [[Sir Winston Churchill]] to fight [[Adolf Hitler]] instead of trying to appease him. Critics argue that it is inappropriate to equate every dictator in the world with Hitler, particularly due to the differences between the present day situation and the Europe of 1939. 

Many, mainly in the [[United States]], also believe it is their moral obligation to free nations from dictators and undemocratic regimes. They believe that the Western enlightened values of [[freedom]], [[democracy]] and [[justice]] are the only proper way to live, and that they should spread them around the globe. In this they vigorously oppose the cultural and [[moral relativism]] of some parts of the left. Hence, many right-wingers advocate a war against certain states that violate [[human rights]] and in their view threaten the world's (or their own state's) security (such as those countries which were controversially branded by Bush "the [[Axis of Evil]]"). Many groups on the left agree with the ideal of spreading democracy and freedom, but disagree with the methods employed by the right.

=== Israeli-Palestinian conflict ===
Mainstream American right-wing groups also tend to support [[Israel]]'s actions in the [[Israeli-Palestinian conflict]], as they perceive Israel as being the only stronghold of [[democracy]] and stability in the [[Middle East]]. The [[Terrorism against Israelis|terrorism attacks]] that struck Israel after the [[Camp David 2000 Summit]] and the [[September 11 terrorist attacks]] on the U.S. increased this sympathy for, and support of, Israel. The [[Christian right]], many of them [[Judeo-Christian]]s or [[Christian Zionists]], support Israel because they believe its existence is essential to bring the [[Messiah]]. (See also [[dispensationalism]])

There are also many [[Far-right]] groups and [[militia]]s in the United States who vigorously oppose any assistance towards Israel, and go so far as to call the United States government a [[Zionist Occupied Government|Zionist-Occupied Government]]. Similarly, [[Muslim]] right-wingers and [[Islamists]] support the Palestinians, as they see Israel and the Jews as "enemies of Islam" and the Arab people. There has been some intermingling of ideas and sympathetic rhetoric between these two groups.

==Political parties on the right== 
One might normally characterize the following parties as on the political right in their respective countries, though they might have relatively little in common with other right-wing groups beyond their opposition to the left.

Naturally, in all cases "left" and "right" express relative positioning. For example, the [[Log Cabin Republicans]] align on the right in the context of the U.S.'s [[gay]] community, but generally appear within the [[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]] as part of the left wing of the party.

===Armenia===

*[[Republican Party of Armenia]]
*[[Liberal Democratic Union of Armenia]]
*[[Democratic Liberal Party of Armenia]]
*[[Christian Democratic Party]]

===Australia===
*[[Liberal Party of Australia]]
*[[National Party of Australia]]
*[[One Nation Party]]
*[[Family First Party]]

===Belgium===
*[[Vlaams Blok]]
*[[Front National]]

===Canada===
*[[Conservative Party of Canada]] - formerly the [[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada]] and the [[Canadian Alliance]].

===Czech Republic===
*[[Civic Democratic Party]] (ODS)

=== Denmark===
*[[Fremskridtspartiet]]
*[[Dansk Folkeparti]]
*[[Venstre]]
*[[Centrumsdemokraterne]]
*[[Det Konservative Folkeparti]]
*[[Kristelig Folkeparti]]

===France===
*[[Front National]]
*[[Mouvement National Republicain]]
*[[Union for a Popular Majority]]

===Germany===
*[[Christian Democratic Union of Germany]] (CDU)
*[[Christian Social Union in Bavaria ]] (CSU)
*The [[Nazi]] Party (defunct and outlawed)

===Greece===
*[[New Democracy| ND - New Democracy]] (Conservative Right)
*[[Popular Orthodox Rally| LA.O.S. - Popular Orthodox Rally]] (Far Right)

===India===
*[[Bharatiya Janata Party]] (BJP)

===Ireland===
This section is about the Republic of Ireland. For right-wing parties in Northern Ireland see the [[Right-wing politics#United Kingdom|United Kingdom]] section below. Also, please note that Irish parties do not fall in the same typical Left/Right categories as political parties in most other European countries, so the inclusion of Irish parties in the "right-wing" is only an approximation.

*[[Fine Gael]] (FG)

===Israel===
* Parties with seats in the [[Knesset]]
** [[Likud]] (center-right conservative party)
** [[Mafdal]] (National Religious Party)
** [[National Union]]
*** [[Moledet]]
*** [[Yisrael Beytenu]] (headed by [[Avigdor Lieberman]])
*** [[Tkuma]]
** [[Shas]] (Ultra-Orthodox Sepharadi party)
** [[United Torah Judaism]] (Ultra-orthodox Ashkenazi party)
* Non-parliamentary:
** [[Gush Emunim]] (Settlers' movement)
** [[Religious Zionism|Kippot Srugot]] (Religious Zionists)
** [[Women in Green]]
** [[Professors For National Strength]] "&amp;#1508;&amp;#1512;&amp;#1493;&amp;#1508;&amp;#1505;&amp;#1493;&amp;#1512;&amp;#1497;&amp;#1501; &amp;#1500;&amp;#1502;&amp;#1506;&amp;#1503; &amp;#1495;&amp;#1493;&amp;#1505;&amp;#1503; &amp;#1502;&amp;#1491;&amp;#1497;&amp;#1504;&amp;#1497;"
* Extremist right
** [[Hilltop Youth]]
** [[Kach]] (outlawed)

===Japan===

* [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)]]
* [[New Clean Government Party]]
* [[Liberal League]]
* [[Midori no Kaigi| Environmental Green Political Assembly]]

===Italy===

* [[Forza Italia]]
* [[Alleanza Nazionale]]

===Latvia===
* [[New Era Party|Jaunais Laiks]]
* [[Tautas Partija]]
* [[Union of Greens and Farmers|Za&amp;#316;o un Zemnieku Savien&amp;#299;ba]]
* [[Latvia First Party|Latvijas Pirm&amp;#257; Partija]]
* [[Tevzemei un Brivibai|T&amp;#275;vzemei un Br&amp;#299;v&amp;#299;bai/LNNK]]

===Netherlands===
*[[Christen-Democratisch Appèl]]
*[[Leefbaar Rotterdam]] (a local party)
*[[Lijst Pim Fortuyn]]
*[[Nieuw Rechts]]
*[[Volkspartij voor Vrijheid en Democratie]]

===New Zealand===
*[[New Zealand National Front|National Front]]
*[[New Zealand National Party]]
*[[ACT New Zealand]]

===Norway===
*[[Fremskrittspartiet]]
*[[Høyre]]

===Poland===
*[[Platforma Obywatelska]]
*[[Prawo i Sprawiedliwosc]]

===South Korea===
*[[Grand National Party]]
*[[United Liberal Democrats]]
*[[New Korea Party of Hope]]

===Spain===
*[[People's Party (Spain)|Partido Popular]]

===Sweden===
*[[Kristdemokraterna]]
*[[Moderata samlingspartiet]]
*[[Folkpartiet]]

===Taiwan===
*[[Kuomintang|Nationalist Party of China]]
*[[People First Party]]
*[[New Party (Taiwan)|New Party]]

===United Kingdom===
*[[British National Party]] 
*[[British National Front|National Front]]
*[[Tory]] or [[Conservative Party (UK)| Conservative Party]]
*[[Ulster Unionist Party]]
*[[United Kingdom Independence Party]]

===United States===
*National Parties (Have fielded candidates for national office)
**American Party
**Christian [[Falange|Falangist]] Party of America
**[[Constitution Party]]
**[[American Independent Party]]
**[[United States Prohibition Party|Prohibition Party]]
**[[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]]
**National Parties that did not field candidates for national office in 2004
***America First Party
***American Heritage Party
***[[American Nazi Party]]
***Constitutional Action Party
***Independent American Party
*Regional/Single-State Parties
**American Heritage Party (Washington)
**Christian Freedom Party (Minnesota)
**[[Conservative Party of New York State]]
**New Jersey Conservative Party
**Reform Party of Michigan (not affiliated with the [[Reform Party USA]] nor the [[American Reform Party]]
**School Choice Party (New York)
**Secessionist (NB: Only those secessionist parties that apparently espouse '''right-wing''' doctrines are listed here.)
***[[Alaskan Independence Party]]
**[[Neo-confederate]] (NB: Most of these parties coordinate with each other, but there is currently no central [[neo-confederate]] party structure within the USA.)
***Kentucky Southern Party
***Southern Independence Party of Tennessee
***Southern Independence Party of Texas
***Southern Party of Georgia
***Southern Party of North Carolina
***Southern Party of South Carolina
***Southern Party of the Southwest (Arizona and New Mexico)

==Other significant right-wing organizations== 
===United States===
*[[Accuracy in Media]]   
*[[Americans for Tax Reform]]   
*[[Christian Coalition]]   
*[[Club for Growth]]   
*[[Concerned Women for America]]   
*[[Council of Conservative Citizens]]   
*[[Criminal Justice Legal Foundation]]   
*[[Family Research Council]]   
*[[Federalist Society]]   
*[[Free Republic]]   
*[[Heritage Foundation]]   
*[[Judicial Watch]]   
*[[Log Cabin Republicans]]   
*[[Media Research Center]]   
*[[National Rifle Association]]   
*[[National Right to Life]]   
*[[National Taxpayers Union]]   
*[[U.S. English (organization)|U.S. English]]

==Related topics==
*[[Anarcho-capitalism]]
*[[Christian democracy]]
*[[Capitalism]]
*[[Conservativism]]
*[[Fascism]]
*[[Left-Right politics]] discusses the range of various writers' meanings when they use the terms "left" and "right" in a political context. 
*[[Left-wing politics]]
*[[Liberalism]]
*[[Libertarianism]]
*[[Monarchy]]
*[[Nazism]]
*[[Neo-nazism]]
*[[Nolan chart]]
*[[Plutocracy]]
*[[Political spectrum]] discusses various writers' views of the usefulness (or not) of the Left/Right dichotomy and of alternative spectra.
*[[Radical centrist politics]]
*[[Reactionary]]
*[[Theocracy]]

==External links== 
*[http://www.politicalcompass.org/ The Political Compass], an alternative view of the political spectrum
*[http://FreedomKeys.com/nolancharts.htm The Nolan Charts], other alternative political spectra (mostly libertarian-oriented)

==References== 
''Hitler's Social Revolution: Class and Status in Nazi Germany, 1933-1939'' by David Schoenbaum, ISBN 0393315541
----

==Other meanings==
'''''Right wing''''' may also refer to a player's position in sports such as [[soccer]] and [[ice hockey]].

[[Category:Politics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>