<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061103091330|85440919" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56522" pageid="56522" ns="0" title="Right-wing politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T08:16:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{mergeto|Left-Right politics}}
{{Political parties}}
{{disputed}}
:'''''Right wing''' is also a term used in several sports; see [[winger (sport)]].''
In [[politics]], '''right-wing''', '''the political right''' or simply '''the right''', are terms that refer to the segment of the [[political spectrum]] often associated with any of several strains of [[monarchism]], [[reactionary|reactionism]], [[conservatism]], the [[religious right]], [[nationalism]], [[fascism]], or simply the opposite of [[left-wing politics]]. 

The term originates from the [[French Revolution]], when [[liberal]] deputies from the [[Third Estate]] generally sat to the left of the president's chair, a habit which began in the [[French States-General|Estates General]] of 1789.  The nobility, members of the [[Second Estate]], generally sat to the right. In the successive [[Legislative Assembly (France)|legislative assemblies]], [[monarchism|monarchists]] who supported the [[Ancien Régime]] were commonly referred to as '''rightists''' because they sat on the right side. It is still the tradition in the French [[Assemblée Nationale]] for the representatives to be seated left-to-right (relative to the Assemblée president) according to their political alignment.

As this original reference became obsolete, the meaning of the term has changed as appropriate to the spectrum of ideas and stances being compared, and the point of view of the speaker. In recent times, the term almost always includes some forms of conservatism. 

Some consider the political Right to include those forms of [[liberalism]] that emphasize the [[free market]] more than [[egalitarianism]] in wealth, but many free-market advocates, including most [[libertarians]], share certain political ideologies with the [[Left-wing politics|left-wing]] and conceive of a two-dimensional political spectrum that they say more accurately portrays their political position.[http://www.la-articles.org.uk/pc.htm] (''See [[Nolan chart]], [[Pournelle Chart]], [[Political Compass]]''). Many anarchists (including [[libertarian socialism|libertarian socialists]]) also avoid placing themselves on the classic political spectrum.

''See [[political spectrum]] and [[Left-Right politics|left-right politics]] for further discussion of this kind of classification.''

==Right-wing issues==
Outside the [[United States]] (where [[capitalism]] is supported by a broad range of politicians and people from the left and the right), the most notable distinction between left and right is in economic policy. The right advanced [[capitalism]], whereas the left advocated [[socialism]] (often democratic socialism) or [[communism]]. Some on the right advocate ''[[laissez faire]]'' capitalism, tending toward [[minarchism]], with little government intervention in the economy other than to control the [[money supply]] and little taxation except to support military and police functions. At the other extreme within what is usually considered right of centre, the centre-right [[Gaullism|Gaullists]] in post-World War II [[France]] advocated considerable social spending on education and infrastructure development, as well as extensive economic regulation and even a limited amount of the wealth redistribution measures more characteristic of [[social democracy]].

More recently as new social issues arise, right wing views have been concerned with keeping "traditional" values (often [[Christian values|Christian]] values) and the preservation of individual and corporate rights through constraints on government power. In a hard-line form the second and third of these priorities are associated with [[libertarianism]], but some on the right reject the most ardent assumptions of libertarianism, especially outside of the [[United States]]. Many libertarians do not consider themselves to be right wing and reject the traditional one-dimensional political spectrum, preferring to think in terms of liberty vs. authority rather than socialism vs. capitalism.

A more obscure strand of right wing thought, often associated with the original right wing from the times of [[monarchy]], supports the preservation of wealth and power in the hands that have traditionally held them, social stability, and national solidarity and ambition.

Strands of right wing thought come in many forms, and individuals who support some of the objectives of one of the above stands will not necessarily support all of the others. At the level of practical political policy, there are endless variations in the means that right wing thinkers advocate to achieve their basic aims.

The values and policy concerns of the right vary in different countries and eras. Also, individual right wing politicians and thinkers often have individual priorities. It is not always possible or helpful to try to work out which of two sets of beliefs or policies is more right-wing (see [[political spectrum]]).

==History of the term== 
{{main|Left-Right politics}}

Since the French Revolution, the political use of the terms "left" and "right" has evolved across linguistic, societal, and national boundaries, sometimes taking on meanings in one time and place that contrast sharply with those in another. For example, as of [[2004]] the  government of the [[People's Republic of China]] claims to remain on the "left," despite an evolution that has brought it quite close to what is elsewhere characterized as "right," supporting national cultural traditions, the interests of wealth, and privately owned industry. Conversely, the late dictator of [[Spain]], [[Francisco Franco]], who was firmly allied internationally with the right and who brutally suppressed the Spanish left, nonetheless pursued numerous development policies quite similar to those of the [[Soviet Union]] and other [[communist state]]s, which are almost universally considered to be on the "left." Similarly, while "right" originally referred to those who supported the interests of [[aristocracy]], in many countries today (notably the [[United States]]) the left-right distinction is not strongly correlated with wealth or ancestry.

[[Fascism]] is generally considered right-wing, although some scholars dispute that classification. Others argue that there are elements of both left and right ideology in the philosophy underlying the development of Fascism. See: [[Far right]] and [[Fascism and ideology]].

==See also==
* [[Left-Right politics]]
** [[Ultra leftism]]
** [[Far-left]]
** [[Left-wing politics]]
** [[Far right]]
* [[Extremism]]
* [[Ideology]]
* [[Glossary of the French Revolution]]
* [[Political spectrum]]
* [[Political compass]]
* [[Nolan chart]]
* ''[[Sinistrisme]]''
* [[World's Smallest Political Quiz]]

==External links== 
*[http://www.politicalcompass.org/ The Political Compass], an alternative view of the political spectrum.
*[http://FreedomKeys.com/nolancharts.htm The Nolan Charts], other alternative political spectra (mostly libertarian-oriented).
*[http://www.publiceye.org/research/chart_of_sectors.html publiceye.org] - A leftist organization's perspective on the right.
*[http://www.la-articles.org.uk/pc.htm The Political Compass and Why Libertarianism is Not Right Wing] by J. C. Lester

[[Category:Political spectrum]]

[[cs:Pravice (politika)]]
[[de:Politisches Spektrum]]
[[es:Derecha política]]
[[fr:Droite (politique)]]
[[ko:우익]]
[[id:Sayap kanan]]
[[is:Hægristefna]]
[[it:Destra (politica)]]
[[nl:Rechts]]
[[ja:右翼]]
[[nn:Høgresida]]
[[pl:Prawica]]
[[pt:Direita]]
[[sr:Десница]]
[[sv:Politisk höger]]
[[zh:右派]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>