<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020811050648|396274" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56522" pageid="56522" ns="0" title="Right-wing politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-10-31T17:57:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Right-wing''' is the opposite to left-wing, with both terms originating
in the [[French Revolution]] as discussed in the article on [[leftism]].

Traditionally the right-wing defends the traditional power of aristocrats, royalty, established religions and the wealthy, as opposed to movements
promoting equal rights or wealth for all.
The term has also come to be used for [[nationalist]] or [[racist]] movements which favour the interests of a majority in the population against
minority groups, with [[fascism]] or [[nazism]] the canonical examples.

Some usages of the term [[conservatism]] are also considered to be right-wing, by leftists. Liberals and other leftist often consider themselves "moderate".

Support for [[free market]] [[economic]]s has at times been classed as both
right and left-wing.  It was left-wing during the French Revolution, since
the concept is opposed to the kind of economic favouritism practiced by the
elite in that country at the time.  In theory anyone has an equal chance in
a free market.  However in practice, a free market is likely (some say
mathematically inevitable) to result in large variations in the relative
prosperity of individuals, with almost all of the real power (wealth, in
a free market) held by a small percentage of the population.  Hence, it
can also be considered a doctrine of the right-wing.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>