<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071109011023|170224044" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56522" pageid="56522" ns="0" title="Right-wing politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-09T05:23:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=October 2007}}
{{Original research|date=October 2007}}
{{Cleanup|date=October 2007}}

{{redirect|Right wing|the term used in sports|winger (sport)}}
{{Political parties}}

In [[politics]], '''right-wing''', '''the political right''', and '''the right''' are terms used in the spectrum of [[Left-Right Politics]], and much like the opposite appellation of ''[[Left-wing]]'', it has a broad variety of definitions: the same name can, in politics, sometimes mean different things. However, it is generally used to refer to the segments of the [[political spectrum]] often associated with any of several strains of [[Conservatism]], [[Traditionalist Conservatism|Traditionalism]], [[Monarchism]], [[Right-libertarianism]], [[Royalist|Royalism]], [[Corporatism]], the [[Religious Right]], [[Nationalism]], [[Militarism]], [[National Socialism]],  [[Producerism]], [[Nativism]], or simply [[Reactionary|Reactionism]] for the sake of being the opposite of left-wing politics.

The term originates from the [[French Revolution]], when [[liberal]] deputies from the [[Third Estate]] generally sat to the left of the president's chair, a habit which began in the [[French States-General|Estates General]] of 1789. The nobility, members of the [[Second Estate]], generally sat to the right. In the successive [[Legislative Assembly (France)|legislative assemblies]], [[monarchism|monarchists]] who supported the [[Ancien Régime]] were commonly referred to as '''rightists''' because they sat on the right side. It is still the tradition in the [[French National Assembly]] for the representatives to be seated left-to-right (relative to the Assembly president) according to their political alignment.

As this original reference became obsolete, the meaning of the term has changed as appropriate to the spectrum of ideas and stances being compared, and the point of view of the speaker. In recent times, the term almost always includes some forms of conservatism. 

Some consider the political Right to include those forms of [[liberalism]] that emphasize the [[free market]] more than [[egalitarianism]] in wealth, but some free-market advocates, including some [[libertarians]], conceive of a two-dimensional political spectrum that they say more accurately portrays their political position. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.la-articles.org.uk/pc.htm&lt;/ref&gt; (''See [[Nolan chart]], [[Pournelle Chart]], [[Political Compass]]''). Many anarchists (including [[libertarian socialism|libertarian socialists]]) also avoid placing themselves on the classic political spectrum.

''See [[political spectrum]] and [[Left-Right politics|left-right politics]] for further discussion of this kind of classification.''

Outside the [[United States]] (where [[capitalism]] is supported by major politicians and people from both the left and right), the most notable distinction between left and right is in [[economic policy]]. The right advances [[capitalism]], whereas the left advocates [[socialism]] (including [[democratic socialism]]) or [[communism]]. Some on the right advocate ''[[laissez faire]]'' capitalism, tending toward [[minarchism]], with little government intervention in the economy other than to control the [[money supply]] and little taxation except to support military and police functions. At the other extreme within what is usually considered right of centre, the centre-right [[Gaullism|Gaullists]] in post-World War II [[France]] advocated considerable social spending on education and infrastructure development, as well as extensive economic regulation and even a limited amount of the wealth redistribution measures more characteristic of [[social democracy]].

More recently as new social issues arise, right wing views have been concerned with keeping "traditional" values (often religious values) and the preservation of individual and corporate rights through constraints on government power. In a hard-line form the second and third of these priorities are associated with [[libertarianism]], but some on the right reject the most ardent assumptions of this philosophy, especially outside of the [[United States]]. Some, but by no means all, libertarians do not consider themselves to be right wing and reject the traditional one-dimensional political spectrum, preferring to think in terms of liberty vs. authority rather than socialism vs. capitalism.

A more obscure strand of right wing thought, often associated with the original right wing from the times of [[monarchy]], supports the preservation of wealth and power in the hands that have traditionally held them, social stability, and national solidarity and ambition.

Strands of right wing thought come in many forms, and individuals who support some of the objectives of one of the above stands will not necessarily support all of the others. At the level of practical political policy, there are endless variations in the means that right wing thinkers advocate to achieve their basic aims.

The values and policy concerns of the right vary in different countries and eras. Also, individual right wing politicians and thinkers often have individual priorities. It is not always possible or helpful to try to work out which of two sets of beliefs or policies is more right-wing (see [[political spectrum]]).

==History of the term== 
{{main|Left-Right politics}}

Since the [[French Revolution]], the political use of the terms "left" and "right" has evolved across linguistic, societal, and national boundaries, sometimes taking on meanings in one time and place that contrast sharply with those in another. 

[[Fascism]] is usually described as right-wing&lt;ref name="fasc"&gt;"Fascism.", The American Heritage® New Dictionary of Cultural Literacy, Third Edition. Houghton Mifflin Company, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;, although there have been scholars (like [[Ludwig von Mises]]) that have disputed that classification. Others argue that there are elements of both left and right ideology in the philosophy underlying the development of Fascism. See: [[Far right]] and [[Fascism and ideology]].

==See also==
* [[Left-Right politics]]
** [[Ultra leftism]]
** [[Far-left]]
** [[Left-wing politics]]
** [[Far right]]
* [[Extremism]]
* [[Ideology]]
* [[Political spectrum]]
* [[Political compass]]
* [[Nolan chart]]
* [[Sinistrisme|Sinisterism]]
* [[World's Smallest Political Quiz]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links== 
*[http://www.politicalcompass.org/ Political Compass]
*[http://FreedomKeys.com/nolancharts.htm The Nolan Charts], other alternative political spectra (mostly libertarian-oriented).
*[http://www.publiceye.org/research/chart_of_sectors.html publiceye.org] - A leftist organization's perspective on the right.
*[http://www.la-articles.org.uk/pc.htm The Political Compass and Why Libertarianism is Not Right Wing] by J. C. Lester

[[Category:Right-wing politics| ]]
[[Category:Political spectrum]]

[[ca:Dreta]]
[[cs:Pravice (politika)]]
[[da:Højreorienteret]]
[[de:Politische Rechte (Politik)]]
[[el:Δεξιά (πολιτική)]]
[[es:Derecha política]]
[[ko:우익]]
[[id:Sayap kanan]]
[[is:Hægristefna]]
[[it:Destra (politica)]]
[[lt:Dešinė (politikoje)]]
[[hu:Jobboldal]]
[[nl:Rechts]]
[[ja:右翼]]
[[nn:Høgresida]]
[[pl:Prawica]]
[[pt:Direita política]]
[[ru:Правые (политика)]]
[[simple:Right-wing]]
[[sr:Десница]]
[[fi:Oikeisto]]
[[sv:Politisk höger]]
[[uk:Права партія]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>