<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20090908042928|312529121" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5966720" pageid="5966720" ns="0" title="Stereotypes of Hispanic and Latino Americans in the United States"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-09-23T22:04:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''[[Ethnic stereotype|Stereotypical]] representations of [[Hispanic and Latino Americans]]''' are often manifested in [[United States]] [[mass media]], [[literature]], [[theater]] and other creative expressions, with very real repercussions for the group in daily interactions and in [[current events]].  

In 2003, Serafín Méndez-Méndez and Diane Alverio of the [[National Association of Hispanic Journalists]] reported the following findings:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nahj.org/NAHJbrownoutreport03.pdf |title=Network Brownout 2003: The Portrayal of Latinos in Network Television News, 2002 |author=Serafín Méndez-Méndez |coauthors=Diane Alverio |accessdate=2008-06-04 |publisher=National Association of Hispanic Journalists |date=December, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Latino-related stories make up less than 1% of all the stories that appear on [[television network|network]] newscasts, even though Latinos make up more than 13% of the [[Demographics of the United States|U.S. population]].
* [[Crime]], [[terrorism]], [[poverty]] and [[welfare]], and [[illegal immigration]] accounted for 66% of all network stories about Latinos in 2001. 
* The arrest of suspected terrorist [[José Padilla (alleged terrorist)|Jose Padilla]], for allegedly plotting to detonate a "[[dirty bomb]]", occupied a central role in the coverage of Latinos in 2001, with 21 network stories or 18% of all stories that aired on Latinos.
* "The number of Latino-related [[crime]] and [[youth gang]] stories in 2002 was grossly excessive when compared to statistics on crimes involving Latinos."
* "Illegal immigration continues to be an important focus of network news coverage of Latinos."

EthnicMajority.com, a minority empowerment organization, states: "Who we see, hear, and read on television, radio, newspapers, and in movies has a great deal of influence on shaping the attitudes of all Americans. How [[African American|African]], [[Hispanic]] (Latino), and [[Asian American]]s are portrayed in these mediums often stereotypes and reinforces negative images of each ethnic group."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ethnicmajority.com/media_home.htm |title=Diversity in the Media and Entertainment Industries |accessdate=2008-06-04 |publisher=EthnicMajority.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
National media watch group [[Fairness and Accuracy In Reporting]] (FAIR) points out that in contrast to the media's overrepresentation of minorities as criminals and druggies is their underrepresentation as experts and analysts. FAIR's studies in the late 1980s and early 1990s documented that 92% of ''[[Nightline (US news program)|Nightline]]''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s  U.S. guests were [[White American|white]], 90% of the ''[[The NewsHour with Jim Lehrer|NewsHour]]'''s guests were white, and 26 out of 27 repeat commentators on [[National Public Radio]] over a four-month period were white.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=2527 |title=Racism and Mainstream Media |last=Cohen |first=Jeff |accessdate=2008-06-04 |publisher=Fairness and Accuracy In Reporting |date=1999-10-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples of Latino stereotypes include: the movie ''[[Scarface (1983 film)|Scarface]]'', which perpetuates the stereotype{{Fact|date=February 2007}} that Latinos are incestuous megalomaniacs. Latinos are often portrayed as knife-wielding, as in the movies [[Fear and Loathing in Las Vegas]], [[Training Day]], [[Robin Williams: Live]] and [[Crocodile Dundee in L.A.]]. Also [[Con Air]] hit several points with the stereotypical [[homosexual]] Latino felon.There is also the image of the trendy and flamboyant homosexual males who often act as secret homosexual lovers of more repressive (and usually caucasian) males, [[hair dresser]]s or fashionable openly gay hipsters as seen in certain television programs of the comedy genre such as [[King of the Hill]], [[The Boondocks]], [[Mad TV]] and MTV's [[The Real World]]. Another example of stereotypes are sayings such as “all Mexicans are illegal immigrants,” “Latino men are lazy,”  “Latina women are ‘easy,’” “ all Latinos are dirty,” and “all Latinos only speak Spanish.” [http://web.uccs.edu/ethnicstudies/site/Rosa%20Parks/Previous/2001/rosaparkswinners.htm] Elia Esparza, a writer for a Hispanic academic journal, believes that the television show called ''[[Chico and the Man]]'' stereotyped by saying “ in one infamous segment, Albertson [actor] says to Chico, ‘Get outta here, and take your flies with you’” (50). [http://web.uccs.edu/ethnicstudies/site/Rosa%20Parks/Previous/2001/rosaparkswinners.htm]. 

[[White Hispanic|White U.S. Hispanics and Latinos]] are often overlooked in the U.S. [[mass media]] and in general American social perceptions, where being "Hispanic or Latino" is often incorrectly given a racial value, usually mixed-race, that is, [[mestizo]], [[mulatto]], or [[zambo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pbs.org/newshour/essays/june97/rodriguez_6-18.html |title=A CULTURAL IDENTITY |author=[[Richard Rodriguez]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rawstory.com/exclusives/tryferis/hispanic.htm |title=Separated by a common language: The case of the white Hispanic}}&lt;/ref&gt; Latinos in general are often depicted as all being part of one homogeneous cultural or ethnic group and/or having no defining characteristics; if a country of origin is specified, it is almost invariably either [[Mexico]] or [[Puerto Rico]], regardless of whence the individual or group in question actually hails.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==See also==   
*[[Ethnic stereotypes in pornography]]
*[[Hispanophobia]]
*[[Racial profiling]]
*[[Stereotype threat]]
*[[Colombia in Popular Culture]]

==Further reading==   
*[http://textmex.blogspot.com/ GalleryBlog on Latina/o Stereotypes]. This blog serves as a constantly updated resource for [http://www.utexas.edu/utpress/books/nertex.html Tex(t)-Mex], a [[University of Texas Press]] volume (2007)


[[Category:Criticism of journalism]]   
[[Category:Ethnocentrism]]     
[[Category:Stereotypes]]   

   
{{ethnic stereotypes}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>