<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20140724145732|618281261" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5966720" pageid="5966720" ns="0" title="Stereotypes of Hispanic and Latino Americans in the United States"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-08-25T00:19:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">
'''[[Ethnic stereotype|Stereotypical]] representations of [[Hispanic and Latino Americans]]''' can be manifested in United States mass media, literature, theater and other creative expressions.

[[White Hispanic and Latino Americans|White U.S. Hispanics and Latinos]], [[Asian Hispanic and Latino Americans|Asian U.S. Hispanics and Latinos]], and [[Black Hispanic and Latino Americans|Black U.S. Hispanics and Latinos]] are often overlooked in the U.S. mass media and in general American social perceptions, where being "Hispanic or Latino" is often incorrectly given a racial value, usually [[multiracial American#Hispanic and Latino Americans|mixed-race]], such as [[Mestizo]] or [[Mulatto]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pbs.org/newshour/essays/june97/rodriguez_6-18.html |title=A CULTURAL IDENTITY |author=[[Richard Rodriguez]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rawstory.com/exclusives/tryferis/hispanic.htm |title=Separated by a common language: The case of the white Hispanic}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://campello.tripod.com/hispanic.html |title=Hispanics:A Culture, Not a Race |publisher=Campello.tripod.com |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; but it is actually an ethnic grouping comprising many different races while, in turn, mixed-race and white U.S. Hispanics and Latinos are overrepresented and admired in the U.S. Hispanic mass media and social perceptions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsweek.com/2003/06/18/y-tu-black-mama-tambien.html |title=Y Tu Black Mama Tambien |work=Newsweek  |date=June 18, 2003 |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?pagename=article&amp;node=&amp;contentId=A19009-2000Aug1&amp;notFound=true |title=The Blond, Blue-Eyed Face of Spanish TV |work=The Washington Post  |date=August 3, 2000 |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://latinola.com/story.php?story=9009 Blonde, Blue-Eyed Euro-Cute Latinos on Spanish TV]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vidadeoro.com/2010/10/latinos-not-reflected-on-spanish-tv.html Latinos Not Reflected on Spanish TV]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bellaonline.com/articles/art40221.asp |title=What are Telenovelas? – Hispanic Culture |publisher=Bellaonline.com |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.sun-sentinel.com/2000-08-06/news/0008060066_1_spanish-latino-leaders-caste |title=Racial Bias Charged On Spanish-Language TV |publisher=Articles.sun-sentinel.com |date=August 6, 2000 |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackelectorate.com/articles.asp?ID=281 |title=Black Electorate |publisher=Black Electorate |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/living/articles/2004/08/19/pride_or_prejudice/ |title=Skin tone consciousness in Asian and Latin American populations |work=Boston Globe  |date=August 19, 2004 |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.antimoon.com/forum/2004/5104-9.htm |title=Differences Between American and Castilian Spanish |publisher=Antimoon.com |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
== News media and crime ==

In 2003, Serafín Méndez-Méndez or Diane Alverio of the [[National Association of Hispanic Journalists]] reported the following findings:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nahj.org/NAHJbrownoutreport03.pdf |title=Network Brownout 2003: The Portrayal of Latinos in Network Television News, 2002 |author=Serafín Méndez-Méndez |author2=Diane Alverio  |accessdate=2008-06-04 |publisher=National Association of Hispanic Journalists |date=December 2003}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Latino-related stories make up less than 1% of all the stories that appear on network newscasts, even though Latinos make up more than 13% of the [[Demographics of the United States|U.S. population]].
* Crime, terrorism, poverty and welfare, and [[illegal immigration]] accounted for 66% of all network stories about Latinos in 2001. 
* The arrest of suspected terrorist [[José Padilla (alleged terrorist)|Jose Padilla]], for allegedly plotting to detonate a "[[dirty bomb]]", occupied a central role in the coverage of Latinos in 2002, with 21 network stories or 18% of all stories that aired on Latinos.
* "The number of Latino-related crime and [[youth gang]] stories in 2002 was grossly excessive when compared to statistics on crimes involving Latinos."
* "Illegal immigration continues to be an important focus of network news coverage of Latinos."

EthnicMajority.com, a minority empowerment organization, states: "Who we see, hear, and read on television, radio, newspapers, and in movies has a great deal of influence on shaping the attitudes of all Americans. How [[African American|African]], [[Hispanic]] (Latino), and Asian Americans are portrayed in these mediums often stereotypes and reinforces negative images of each ethnic group."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ethnicmajority.com/media_home.htm |title=Diversity in the Media and Entertainment Industries |accessdate=2008-06-04 |publisher=EthnicMajority.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Progressive media watch group [[Fairness and Accuracy In Reporting]] (FAIR) points out that in contrast to the media's over-representation of minorities as criminals and drug users is their under representation as experts and analysts. FAIR's studies in the late 1980s and early 1990s documented that 92% of ''[[Nightline (US news program)|Nightline]]''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s  U.S. guests were [[White American|white]], 90% of the ''[[The NewsHour with Jim Lehrer|NewsHour]]'''s guests were white, and 26 out of 27 repeat commentators on [[National Public Radio]] over a four-month period were white.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=2527 |title=Racism and Mainstream Media |last=Cohen |first=Jeff |accessdate=2008-06-04 |publisher=Fairness and Accuracy In Reporting |date=1999-10-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Stereotypes and Misconceptions about Latin America==
Depictions of Latin America in the US fiction sometimes include misconceptions or mistakes which may be perceived as stereotypes. Apart from people, geography can be mistaken; for example, [[Iguazu Falls]] and the [[Amazon Rainforest]] may be treated as if they were close to each other. Cities may be depicted with features which they do not have, or are in other countries. Cities may be depicted as [[shanty town]]s, with monkeys, big cats and alligators roaming free. When characters visit Brazil, it is usually during the [[Brazilian Carnival]].&lt;ref name="tropes"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/TheCapitalOfBrazilIsBuenosAires |title=The capital of Brazil is Buenos Aires |publisher=Tvtropes.org |date=April 21, 1960 |accessdate=December 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As for the Latin American people, they may be depicted as being poor, and women as wearing [[Carmen Miranda]]-style fruit hats. They are also depicted as working in low-income labor jobs and most prominently for males the job is as a gardener and most prominently for women the job is as a maid. Fashion, technology and architecture is depicted between a colonial and a 1950s style.&lt;ref name="tropes"/&gt;

The same stereotypes prevail in U.S. Hispanic media (meaning media created by [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanic Americans]] themselves), where most Latino Americans are often depicted as poor and those who are often depicted as poor are usually of either mixed race, black Hispanic, or indigenous Hispanic heritage. These perceptions of poverty among U.S. Hispanic media and even among the greater Hispanic American communities themselves are so great that Hispanic and Latino American groups that are usually not impoverished and lack widespread crime in their communities are portrayed as such by U.S. Hispanic media. U.S. Hispanic media also in turn do the same in their portrayal of Latin America where countries that are not known for their high crime or poverty rates are either portrayed as such or almost completely dismissed altogether by U.S. media. Countries that are developed nations and possess little to no crime in Latin America such as [[Chile]], [[Uruguay]], [[Cuba]], and [[Costa Rica]] have been portrayed as impoverished or heavily crime ridden in U.S. Hispanic media and U.S. media in general. Countries with moderately low crimes rates in Latin America are [[Haiti]], [[Bolivia]], and [[Peru]].

== Female Hispanics ==

Sexual and racial stereotypes of Latinas are often demonstrated in the US mainstream media.  The women of this ethnic group are often portrayed as being overly sensual, passionate, curvaceous, olive-skinned women.  While at times they are shown in an overly provocative manner, in some instances they are illustrated in an opposing way: virginal, religious, conservative and family-oriented. One such example is [[Colombian people|Colombian]] actress [[Sofia Vergara]], who has often been asked to alter her appearance to fit the ''Latina'' stereotype in her on screen roles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/09/13/sofia-vergara-in-self-im-_n_714953.html |title=Sofia Vergara In 'Self': I'm A Natural Blonde, Hated My Boobs |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date= September 13, 2010|accessdate=July 27, 2012 |first=Katy |last=Hall}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Celebrity Q+A: Sofia Vergara|url=http://www.familycircle.com/teen/parenting/celebrity-parents/sofia-vergara/|publisher=Family Circle|accessdate=17 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|Hispanic and Latino Americans}}
* [[Stereotypes of groups within the United States]]
*[[Hispanophobia]]
*[[Racial profiling]]
*[[Stereotype threat]]
*[[Stereotypes of Argentines]]
*[[Colombia in popular culture]]
*[[Chicano]] and [[Nuyorican]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
*[http://textmex.blogspot.com/ GalleryBlog on Latina/o Stereotypes]. This blog serves as a constantly updated resource for [http://www.utexas.edu/utpress/books/nertex.html Tex(t)-Mex], a [[University of Texas Press]] volume (2007)

{{ethnic stereotypes}}

[[Category:Ethnic and racial stereotypes]]
[[Category:Ethnic and racial stereotypes in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>