<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071113201703|171273220" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5966720" pageid="5966720" ns="0" title="Stereotypes of Hispanic and Latino Americans in the United States"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T06:48:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Ethnic stereotypes|Stereotypical]] representations of [[Hispanics in the United States|Hispanics or Latinos]] are often manifested in [[United States]] [[mass media]], [[literature]], [[theater]] and other creative expressions, but often have very real repercussions for Latinos in daily interactions and in [[current events]].  

In 2003, Serafin Mendez-Mendez and Diane Alverio of the [[National Association of Hispanic Journalists]] reported the following findings:
* Latino-related stories make up less than 1% of all the stories that appear on [[television network|network]] newscasts, even though Latinos make up more than 13% of the [[Demographics of the United States|population]].
* [[Crime]], [[terrorism]], and [[illegal immigration]] accounted for 66% of all network stories about Latinos in 2001. 
* The arrest of suspected terrorist [[José Padilla (alleged terrorist)|Jose Padilla]], for allegedly plotting to detonate a "[[dirty bomb]]", occupied a central role in the coverage of Latinos in 2001, with 21 network stories or 18% of all stories that aired on Latinos.
* The number of Latino-related crime stories in 2002 was grossly excessive when compared to statistics on crimes involving Latinos.
* Illegal immigration continues to be an important focus of network news coverage of Latinos.
* Latinos continue to remain virtually absent from network news coverage. &lt;ref&gt;Mendez-Mendez, Serafin and Alverio, Diane. [http://www.nahj.org/NAHJbrownoutreport03.pdf "Network Brownout 2003: The Portrayal of Latinos in Network Television News, 2002."]&lt;/ref&gt;

EthnicMajority.com, a minority empowerment organization, states: "Who we see, hear, and read on television, radio, newspapers, and in movies has a great deal of influence on shaping the attitudes of all Americans. How [[African American|African]], [[Hispanic]] (Latino), and [[Asian American]]s are portrayed in these mediums often stereotypes and reinforces negative images of each ethnic group." &lt;ref&gt;EthnicMajority.com. [http://www.ethnicmajority.com/media_home.htm Diversity in the Media and Entertainment Industries.]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[University of Michigan]] undergraduates Brian Schulz and Jessica Farris made the following statements in their report, "Latino Representation in the Media":
* Latinos as a whole remain the most underrepresented group on television. Although they encompass about 12.5% of the national population, Latinos only account for 2% of characters on television. Furthermore, when they are represented on television, they are portrayed in unfavorable roles such as janitors, drug-dealers, and perpetrators of crime.
* Latinos are more likely to be seen in mug shots than non-Hispanic whites. Latinos were 10% more likely to be featured in stories about judicial and crime news, news of riots and demonstrations, and accident and disaster news than whites.
* Stories in which Latinos are the victims of violent crimes are less likely to appear on primetime news.
* In "reality" shows such as ''[[COPS (TV series)|Cops]]'' and ''[[America's Most Wanted]]'', Latinos were more likely to be portrayed as criminal perpetrators than non-Hispanic whites. Very few Latino officers were featured in segments of ''Cops''.
* Latinos have historically been portrayed as having difficulty speaking [[English language|English]].
* ''[[Kingpin (TV series)|Kingpin]]'', a Hispanic version of ''[[The Sopranos]]'', has been described as "one of the most violent and sexually explicit television shows ever to be shown on a broadcast network" (''[[USA Today]]'', 2003). Throughout the show, Latinos are brutally violent and often pictured as glorified drug dealers. Latino males are stereotypically portrayed as the "Latin Lover," the "greaser," and the "bandito". Latina women are portrayed as deviant, "frilly señoritas" or "volcanic temptresses," while Latino families are often portrayed as unintelligent, passive, deviant and dependent. &lt;ref&gt;Schulz, Brian and Farris, Jessica. [http://www.umich.edu/~ac213/student_projects/lim/ Latino Representation in the Media.]&lt;/ref&gt;

National media watch group [[Fairness and Accuracy In Reporting]] (FAIR) points out that the flip side of media's over representation of minorities as criminals and druggies is their underrepresentation as experts and analysts. FAIR's studies in the late 1980s and early '90s documented that 92% of ''[[Nightline]]'' 's  guests were white, 90% of the ''[[The NewsHour with Jim Lehrer|NewsHour]]'' 's guests were white, and 26 out of 27 repeat commentators on [[National Public Radio]] over a four-month period were white. &lt;ref&gt;Fairness and Accuracy In Reporting. [http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=2527 Racism and Mainstream Media.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples of Latino stereotypes include: the movie ''[[Scarface (1983 film)|Scarface]]'', which perpetuates the stereotype{{Fact|date=February 2007}} that Latinos are incestuous megalomaniacs. Latinos are often portrayed as knife-wielding, as in the movies [[Fear and Loathing in Las Vegas]], [[Training Day]], [[Robin Williams: Live]]. [[Con Air]] hit several points with the stereotypical [[homosexual]] Latino felon. Another example of stereotypes are sayings such as “all Mexicans are illegal immigrants,” “Latino men are lazy,”  “Latina women are ‘easy,’” “ all Latinos are dirty,” and “all Latinos only speak Spanish.”[http://web.uccs.edu/ethnicstudies/site/Rosa%20Parks/Previous/2001/rosaparkswinners.htm] Elia Esparza, a writer for a Hispanic academic journal, believes that the television show called ''[[Chico and the Man]]'' stereotyped by saying “ in one infamous segment, Albertson [actor] says to Chico, ‘Get outta here, and take your flies with you’” (50). [http://web.uccs.edu/ethnicstudies/site/Rosa%20Parks/Previous/2001/rosaparkswinners.htm]

[[White Hispanic|White U.S. Hispanics]] are often overlooked in the U.S. [[mass media]] and in general American social perceptions, where being "[[Hispanic]]" is often incorrectly given a racial value, usually mixed-race, that is, [[mestizo]], [[mulatto]], or [[zambo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/essays/june97/rodriguez_6-18.html A CULTURAL IDENTITY]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rawstory.com/exclusives/tryferis/hispanic.htm Separated by a common language: The case of the white Hispanic]&lt;/ref&gt; Latinos in general are often depicted as all being part of one homogeneous cultural or ethnic group and/or having no defining characteristics; if a country of origin is specified, it is almost invariably either [[Mexico]] or [[Puerto Rico]], regardless of whence the individual or group in question actually hails.


==See also==
*[[Latino]]
*[[Ethnic stereotype]]
*[[Ethnic stereotypes in pornography]]
*[[Stereotype threat]]
*[[Racial profiling]]

== Further reading ==

*[http://textmex.blogspot.com/ GalleryBlog on Latina/o Stereotypes]; this blog serves as a constantly updated resource for ''Tex(t)-Mex'' a University of Texas Press volume (2007) [http://www.utexas.edu/utpress/books/nertex.html Tex(t)-Mex]

==References==

&lt;references/&gt;

[[Category:Criticism of journalism]]
[[Category:Deception]]
[[Category:Ethnocentrism]]
[[Category:Journalism ethics]]
[[Category:Philosophy of racism]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:History of racism in the United States]]
[[Category:Social sciences]]
[[Category:Stereotypes]]

{{ethnic stereotypes}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>