<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111027170105|457683292" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="391581" pageid="391581" ns="0" title="Gerontocracy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-15T05:47:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Forms of government}}
A '''gerontocracy''' is a form of [[oligarchy|oligarchical]] rule in which an entity is ruled by leaders who are significantly older than most of the adult population. Often the [[political]] structure is such that political power within the ruling class accumulates with age, so that the oldest hold the most power. Those holding the most power may not be in formal leadership positions, but often dominate those who are.

Gerontocracy's stability is seen as its strength, which can be more appropriate for institutions that teach principles that do not vary over time.{{fact|date=March 2011}} In institutions that have to cope with rapid change, the decreased faculties of the aged can potentially be a handicap in providing effective leadership.{{fact|date=March 2011}}

==Gerontocracy in various political systems==

Such a form of leadership is common in [[communist state]]s in which the length of one's service to the party is held to be the main qualification for leadership.  In the time of the [[Eight Immortals of Communist Party of China]], it was quipped, "the 80-year-olds are calling meetings of 70-year-olds to decide which 60-year-olds should retire". For instance, Party leader [[Mao Zedong]] was 82 when he died, while [[Deng Xiaoping]] retained a powerful influence until he was nearly 90. 

===In the USSR===
In the [[Soviet Union]], gerontocracy became increasingly entrenched starting in the 1970s, at least until March 1985, when a dynamic, young, ambitious leadership headed by [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] took power.&lt;ref&gt;Zwass, Adam. ''The Council for Mutual Economic Assistance'', p. 127. M. E. Sharpe, 1989, ISBN 087332496X.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Leonid Brezhnev]], its foremost representative,&lt;ref&gt;Gerner, Kristian and Hedlund, Stefan. ''Ideology and Rationality in the Soviet Model'', p. 346. Routledge, 1989, ISBN 0415021421.&lt;/ref&gt; died in 1982 aged 75, but had suffered a [[Myocardial infarction|heart attack]] in 1975, after which generalized [[arteriosclerosis]] set in, so that he was progressively infirm and had trouble speaking. During his last two years he was essentially a figurehead.&lt;ref&gt;Post, Jerrold M. ''Leaders and Their Followers in a Dangerous World'', p. 96. Cornell University Press, 2004, ISBN 0801441692.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1980, the average [[Politburo of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Politburo]] member was 70 years old (as opposed to 55 in 1952 and 61 in 1964), and by 1982, Brezhnev's [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Soviet Union)|Minister of Foreign Affairs]] [[Andrei Gromyko]], his [[Ministry of Defense (Soviet Union)|Minister of Defense]] [[Dmitriy Ustinov]] and his [[List of Premiers of the Soviet Union|Premier]] [[Nikolai Tikhonov]] were all in their mid-to-late seventies.&lt;ref&gt;Kort, Michael. ''The Soviet Colossus: History and Aftermath'', p. 335. M. E. Sharpe, 2006, ISBN 0765614545.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Yuri Andropov]], Brezhnev's 68-year-old successor, was seriously ill with kidney disease when he took over,&lt;ref&gt;Post, p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt; and after his death fifteen months later, he was succeeded by [[Konstantin Chernenko]], then 72, who lasted thirteen months before his death and replacement with Gorbachev. [[Cuba]] has been characterized as a gerontocracy: "Although the population is now mainly black or [[mulatto]] and young, its rulers form a mainly white gerontocracy."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=Dec 30th 2008|publisher=The Economist|title=The Cuban revolution at 50 - Heroic myth and prosaic failure|url=http://www.economist.com/world/americas/displaystory.cfm?story_id=12851254}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Elsewhere in the Eastern Bloc===
Other Communist countries with leaders in their 70s or 80s have included [[Albania]] (First Secretary [[Enver Hoxha]] was 76 at death), [[Czechoslovakia]] (President [[Gustáv Husák]] was 76 at his resignation), [[East Germany]] (General Secretary and head of state [[Erich Honecker]] was 77 when forced out), [[Hungary]] (General Secretary [[János Kádár]] was 75 when forced out), [[Laos]] (President [[Nouhak Phoumsavanh]] was 83 at retirement), [[North Korea]] (President [[Kim Il-sung]] was 82 at death), [[Romania]] (General Secretary and President [[Nicolae Ceauşescu]] was 70 when executed), [[Vietnam]] (President [[Truong Chinh]] was 80 at retirement), [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] (President [[Josip Broz Tito]] was 87 at death). On the sub-national level, [[Georgian SSR|Georgia]]'s Party head [[Vasil Mzhavanadze]] was 70 when forced out, and his [[Lithuanian SSR|Lithuanian]] counterpart [[Antanas Sniečkus]] was 71 at death. Nowadays, [[Cuba]] has been characterized as a gerontocracy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=Dec 30th 2008|publisher=The Economist|title=The Cuban revolution at 50 - Heroic myth and prosaic failure|url=http://www.economist.com/world/americas/displaystory.cfm?story_id=12851254}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theocracy===
Gerontocracy is also common in religious [[theocracy|theocratic]] states such as [[Iran]] and [[Holy See|The Vatican]], in which leadership is concentrated in the hands of religious [[elder (religious)|elder]]s. Despite the age of the senior religious leaders, however, parliamentary candidates in Iran must be under 75.

===Absolute monarchies===
[[Saudi Arabia]] is considered by some to have a gerontocratic system reminiscent of various late communist countries. Power is held by the Saud family; the King and his most powerful relatives are in their eighties.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/indepth/opinion/2011/10/2011102673844479817.html Al Jazeera English - Saudi Arabia's old regime grows older]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stateless societies===
In Kenya, [[Samburu]] society is said to be a gerontocracy. The power of elders is linked to the belief in their curse, underpinning their monopoly over arranging marriages and taking on further wives. This is at the expense of unmarried younger men, whose development up to the age of thirty is in a state of social suspension, prolonging their adolescent status. The paradox of Samburu gerontocracy is that popular attention focuses on the glamour and deviant activities of these footloose bachelors, which extend to a form of gang warfare, widespread suspicions of adultery with the wives of older men, and theft of their stock.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Spencer, ''The Samburu: a Study of Gerontocracy in a Nomadic Tribe'', Routledge and Kegan Paul, London,1965|ISBN=0415317258, 9780415317252&lt;/ref&gt;

===Democracies===
Some [[United States Senate|U.S. senators]] are very old, and positions of power within the legislatures - such as [[Chair (official)|chairmanships]] of various committees - are usually bestowed upon the [[seniority|more experienced]], that is, older, members of the legislature. For example, [[Strom Thurmond]], a U.S. senator from [[South Carolina]], left office at age 100 after almost half a century in the body, while [[Robert Byrd]] of [[West Virginia]] was born in 1917 and  served in the Senate from 1959 to his death in 2010.  Senators under the age of 40 are virtually unknown.  

The minimum age for Presidential candidacy of 35, could also be considered supportive of American gerontocracy, especially considering that there is no maximum.  Theodore Roosevelt was the youngest President to ever hold the office, and he was 42 when inaugurated.  The youngest President elected, John F. Kennedy, was older still, at 43.

In the Indian state of [[Tamilnadu]], the government headed by [[M. Karunanidhi]] the state's chief minister who is 87 years old, is another real world example of gerontocracy. In another Indian state, West Bengal, Shri [[Jyoti Basu]], was 86 years old when he stepped down from the office of chief minister of the state. But he continued to remain a member of the Politburo of the Communist Party of India (Marxist) until a few months before his death in January 2010 and was consulted on all matters related to governance by the Chief Minister and his Cabinet as well as his other party colleagues.

Historically, it could be argued that 1950s [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]] was a gerontocracy. Due to high levels of emigration of young adults, there was a disproportionately high amount of elderly people remaining in Ireland. The lack of (possibly) progressive young adults is blamed for the relatively staunchly [[social conservative]] nature of Irish politics (compared to other Western democracies) at the time, along with politics being divided along [[Irish Civil War]] lines instead of between [[left-wing politics|left]] and [[right-wing politics|right]].

==Organizational examples==
{{unreferenced-section|date=March 2011}}
Outside the political sphere, gerontocracy may be observed in other institutional hierarchies of various kinds. Generally the mark of a gerontocracy is the presence of a substantial number of [[septuagenarian]] or [[octogenarian]] leaders&amp;mdash;those younger than this are too young for the label to be appropriate, while those older than this have generally been too few to dominate the leadership in numbers. The rare [[centenarian]] who has retained a position of power is generally by far the oldest in the hierarchy.

Gerontocracy generally occurs as a phase in the development of an entity, rather than being part of it throughout its existence. Opposition to gerontocracy may cause weakening or elimination of this characteristic by instituting things like term limits or [[mandatory retirement age]]s.

Judges of the [[United States]] courts, for example, serve for life, but a system of incentives to retire at full pay after a given age and disqualification from leadership for those who fail to do so has been instituted. The [[International Olympic Committee]] instituted a mandatory retirement age in 1965, and [[Pope Paul VI]] removed the right of [[Roman Catholic]] Cardinals to vote for a new Pope once they reached the age of 80 (which was to limit the number of Cardinals that would vote for the new Pope, due to the proliferation of Cardinals that was occurring at the time and is continuing to occur.).

On the other hand, gerontocracy may emerge in an institution not initially known for it. [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] was founded by [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]], a 24-year-old man, who in 1835 constituted the first [[Quorum of the Twelve Apostles]] with members ranging in age from 23 to 35. Once it was established that succession to the church presidency derived from longest tenure in an office held for life, the hierarchy aged markedly, and with the growth of the church the age at which officials were named to the highest bodies continued to rise. Six church presidents have held office past the age of 90; until his death at age 97 in 2008, the church was actively led by [[Gordon B. Hinckley]].

==Fiction==
The science fiction novel ''[[Holy Fire (novel)|Holy Fire]]'' by [[Bruce Sterling]] deals with a future society, in which [[life expectancy]] has been expanded to more than two centuries by means of medicine and technology (see [[transhumanism]]) to the effect that the '''gerontocrats''' wield almost all [[capital (economics)|capital]] and [[political power]]. [[Adolescent]]s and young (and by modern standards [[middle-aged]]) [[adults]] live as outsiders with virtually no access to wealth or [[Power (sociology)|power]].

This social projection [[invert]]s present-day [[ageism]] against seniors, as well as [[gerontophobia]].

In the fantasy series the ''[[The Wheel of Time|Wheel of Time]]'' by [[Robert Jordan]], The [[Kin]], a group of women that at some point failed to become [[Aes Sedai]], do not hold any value in the strength of someone in the [[One Power]], as opposed to Aes Sedai, and only defer to age.

In the TV version of [[Logan's Run]], the city is under the control the '''cabal of elderly citizens'''. The council is made of Elite citizens of the city who have been given the privilege to live beyond the age of 30.

In the [[Frederik Pohl]] novel ''[[Search the Sky]]'', the main character Ross, encounters a planet with a gerontocracy masquerading as a democracy. It uses phrases such as "Old Heads Are Wisest" and gives the population the right to choose who is oldest.

In the opening chapter of the science fiction novel ''[[Consider Phlebas]]'' by [[Ian M. Banks]] the main character, a spy called [[Bora Horza Gobuchul]], is being ritually executed by the 'Gerontocracy of Sorpen' for impersonating one of their ministers. The character is a [[List_of_species_%28The_Culture%29#Changers|Changer]], able to alter his outward appearance at will, and has greatly changed his body so as to appear old enough to make the deception believable.

In the [[Takeshi Kovacs]] series of science-fiction novels by [[Richard K. Morgan]], some worlds, most significantly Earth, are ruled by an incredibly wealthy elite, granted effective immortality by technology which allows the digitisation of the human mind and its transfer between living bodies. Commonly known by the label "[[Methuselah]]s" or "Meths", a reference to the [[Methuselah|biblical figure]], they control most of the economic and political activities of the planet. Several Meths play a major role in the first novel, [[Altered Carbon]].

In the computer game ''[[Sword of the Stars]]'', the dolphin-like Liir are ruled by Elders, who have lived for over 300 years and have grown to whale-like size.

In the 2011 nonfiction economic book ''[[Beyond the Keynesian Endpoint]]: Crushed by Credit and Deceived by Debt'', Tony Crescenzi postulates  on [http://books.google.com/books?id=XvCA39yJmzAC&amp;pg=PA153&amp;lpg=PA153&amp;dq=anthony+crescenzi+gerontocracy&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=p6pXYkNQwW&amp;sig=nnseCzCGGTkhJ5pjb5Gn0qTF_U4&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=dfrBTvjoJczRrQf31PHOCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CBoQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false page 154] that gerontocracy and class war is a potential outcome of current trends:

:What is meant here is not actual rule ... but a sizeable shift in voting power so subtantial that the priorities of the young and of future generations are at risk of being subordinated to senior citizens. When they are, tax dollars are allocated toward healthcare and other priorities near and dear to seniors rather than toward education and infrastructure, two major factors that heavilty influence a nation's economic growth potential.

==See also==
*[[Ageism]]
*[[Gerontophobia]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Aging]]
[[Category:Political systems]]

[[ar:غيرونتوقراطية]]
[[ca:Gerontocràcia]]
[[cs:Gerontokracie]]
[[de:Gerontokratie]]
[[et:Gerontokraatia]]
[[es:Gerontocracia]]
[[fa:پیرسالاری]]
[[fr:Gérontocratie]]
[[hr:Gerontokracija]]
[[it:Gerontocrazia]]
[[kk:Геронтократия]]
[[lt:Gerontokratija]]
[[hu:Gerontokrácia]]
[[nl:Gerontocratie]]
[[ja:長老支配]]
[[nds:Gerontokratie]]
[[pl:Gerontokracja]]
[[pt:Gerontocracia]]
[[ru:Геронтократия]]
[[simple:Gerontocracy]]
[[sl:Gerontokracija]]
[[sh:Gerontokracija]]
[[sv:Gerontokrati]]
[[tt:Геронтократия]]
[[tr:Gerontokrasi]]
[[uk:Геронтократія]]
[[zh:老人政治]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>