<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041001234545|6305791" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="391581" pageid="391581" ns="0" title="Gerontocracy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-03T06:01:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''gerontocracy''' is a form of [[oligarchy|oligarchical]] rule in which an entity is ruled by a small clique of leaders, in which the oldest hold the most power. Those holding the most power may not be in formal leadership positions, but dominate those who do: in the time of the [[Eight Immortals of Communist China]], it was quipped, "the 80-year-olds are calling meetings of 70-year-olds to decide which 60-year-olds should retire".

Such a form of leadership is common in [[communist state]]s in which the length of one's service to the party is held to be the main qualification for leadership. It is also common in religious [[theocracy|theocratic]] states such as [[Iran]] in which leadership is concentrated in the hands of religious [[elder (religious)|elder]]s. (Despite the age of the senior religious leaders, however, parliamentary candidates in Iran must be under 75.)

Outside the political sphere, gerontocracy may be observed in other institutional hierarchies of various kinds. Generally the mark of a gerontocracy is the presence of a substantial number of [[septuagenarian]] or [[octogenarian]] leaders&amp;mdash;those younger than this are too young for the label to be appropriate, while those older than this have generally been too few to dominate the leadership in numbers. The rare [[centenarian]] who has retained a position of power is generally by far the oldest in the hierarchy.

Gerontocracy generally occurs as a phase in the development of an entity, rather than being part of it throughout its existence. Opposition to gerontocracy may cause weakening or elimination of this characteristic by instituting things like term limits or [[mandatory retirement age]]s. Judges of the [[United States]] courts, for example, serve for life, but a system of incentives to retire at full pay after a given age and disqualification from leadership for those who fail to do so has been instituted. The [[International Olympic Committee]] instituted a mandatory retirement age in [[1965]], and [[Pope Paul VI]] removed the right of [[Roman Catholic]] Cardinals to vote for a new Pope once they reached the age of 80.

On the other hand, gerontocracy may emerge in an institution not initially known for it. The [[Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] was founded by [[Joseph Smith, Jr.|a 24-year-old man]], who in [[1835]] constituted the first [[Quorum of the Twelve Apostles]] with members ranging in age from 23 to 35. Once it was established that succession to the church presidency derived from longest tenure in an office held for life, the hierarchy aged markedly, and with the growth of the church the age at which officials were named to the highest bodies continued to rise. Six church presidents have held office past the age of 90, and as of [[2004]] the church is actively led by [[Gordon B. Hinckley|a man]] who remembers the day his father replaced the family horse-wagon with a [[Ford Model T]].

Gerontocracy's strength is seen as its stability, which can be more appropriate for institutions that teach principles that do not vary over time. In institutions that have to cope with rapid change, the decreased faculties of the aged can be a handicap in providing effective leadership.

Gerontocracies of various kinds can be expected to rise and fall. The increase in human [[longevity]] may change the definitions thereof, as ages formerly typified by senescence and survived to by a small proportion of the population are reached by larger numbers of healthier people. For this reason mandatory retirement ages may be raised or face increasing opposition. When [[pope John Paul II]] was elected, about one tenth of the [[College of Cardinals]] was over 80, but today the proportion is close to one-third.

==See Also==
*[[Seniomeritocracy]]

[[Category:Forms of government]]
[[Category:Political systems]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>