<?xml version="1.0"?><api batchcomplete=""><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25614" pageid="25614" ns="0" title="Race (human categorization)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2001-10-12T01:34:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''race''' is the [[taxonomy|taxonomic]] concept of a group of people associated by [[heredity]], [[geography]], [[culture]], [[religion]], and [[politics]]. Heredity is especially emphasized, as those who developed the concept in the 18th and 19th centuries appealed to and were inspired by the evolutionary biological concepts being developed at the time.

The historical definition of race, before the development of evolutionary biology, was that of common lineage, a vague concept interchangeable with [[species]], [[breed]], cultural origin, or characteristic quality. ("The whole race of mankind." --[[Shakespeare]]; "Whence the long race of Alban fathers come" --[[Dryden]]

The 19th-century [[anthropology|anthropological]] concept of ''race'' was based on morphological characteristics such as skin colour, facial characteristics and amount and type of hair. Though such characteristics have since been shown to have a minimal relationship with any other heritable characteristics, it retains popularity because it is easy to immediately distinguish people based on physical appearance. 

Because people of different races can interbreed, this method of classification is weak. (Compare with [[species]].) In other words, ''racial purity'' does not have a clear biological meaning.

Some of the 19th-century naturalists and ethnographers who defined the field were [[Georges Cuvier]], Pritchard, [[Louis Agassiz]], [[Charles Pickering]] (''Races of Man and Their Geographical Distribution'', 1848), and [[Johann Friedrich Blumenbach]]. Cuvier enumerated three races, Pritchard seven, Agassiz eight, and Pickering eleven. Blumenbach's classification was widely adopted:
# the [[Caucasian]], or white race, to which belong the greater part of the European nations and those of Western Asia
# the [[Mongolian]], or yellow race, occupying Tartary, China, Japan, etc.
# the [[Ethiopian]], or negro race, occupying most of Africa (except the north), Australia, Papua, and other Pacific Islands
# the [[American]], or red race, comprising the Indians of North and South America 
# the [[Malayan]], or brown race, which occupies the islands of the Indian Archipelago

Writers in the decades following Blumenbach classified the Malay and American races as branches of the Mongolian, leaving only the Caucasian, Mongolian, and Ethiopian races.


== Politics of race ==
The concept of race was applied at the same time by such political theorists such as [[Johann Gottfried von Herder]] to [[nationalism|nationalist]] theory to develop [[ethnic nationalism]]. They posited the historical existence of races such as the German and French race connected to races which have existed for millenia (such as the [[Aryan]] race), which should determine political institutions.


== Related concepts ==
"[[racism]]", "[[race relations]]", "racial equality", "[[racial purity]]", "racial characteristics",  "racial discrimination", "[[racial superiority]]".

Because individual geography, culture, religion, political association and, above all, heredity can change, ''racial purity'', the concept that wholly distinct racial groupings exist, has little meaning from the perspective of evolutionary biology.

[[Ethnicity]] is the concept of race decoupled from national affiliation. For example, ethnic Germans are people who are not citizens of the nation of Germany but who may be considered racially German.

See also:
* [[anthropology]]
* [[taxonomy]]
* [[population genetics]]
* [[racism]]
* [[ethnicity]]
* [[white trash]]

----

''The following is the old version of this article, which was replaced with the above.  This needs to be more carefully included in the above.''

A &lt;b&gt;race,&lt;/b&gt; in biology, ... ''biologically accurate definition needed''

Because members of different races, by definition, can interbreed, there very often exist individuals that don't clearly belong to any one race. This in no way means that, as some anti-racists claim, races don't exist.
On the other hand, term 'racially pure' is difficult to assign a clear biological meaning.

Usually morphological characteristics (like skin colour, facial characteristics and amount and type of hair) is used to divide populations into races, but that's mostly because they're very easy to apply, not because morphology is more important than other characteristics.


''One person hopes that the experts on human races--anthropologists, cultural historians--will weigh in on the subject, trying to maintain a [[neutral point of view]], of course.''

----

A &lt;b&gt;race&lt;/b&gt; is a competition of speed over distance. A race may be over any distance, and using any means stipulated by the rules of the race. [[Running]] a certain distance is the template of racing, but races are often conducted in [[vehicle]]s, such as [[boat]]s and [[car]]s.

Early records of races are evidient on ancient [[greek]] [[pottery]], where running men are depicted vying for first place.  There is a [[chariot]] race in the ''[[Iliad]]''.

A race and its name are often associated with the place of origin, the means of transport and the distance of the race. As a couple of examples, see the [[Paris-Dakar rally]] or the [[Athens marathon]].

/Talk

----
=== External Links and References ===
[http://work.ucsd.edu:5141/cgi-bin/http_webster?isindex=race&amp;method=exact 1913 dictionary entry]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>