<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061111183220|87177735" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25614" pageid="25614" ns="0" title="Race (human categorization)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-12T02:15:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup-date|October 2006}}
{{worldwideview}}
:''This article concerns the term "race" as used in reference to human beings. For other uses, including in biology and for athletics events and other speed competitions, see [[Race (disambiguation)]].''
The term '''race''' distinguishes one [[population]] of an animal [[species]] (including human) from another of the same [[subspecies]]. The most widely used human racial categories are based on visible [[Trait (biological)|trait]]s (especially [[skin color]] and [[face|facial features]]), [[genes]], and self-identification. Conceptions of race, as well as specific [[racial grouping]]s, vary by culture and time and are often [[controversial issue|controversial]] due to their impact on [[social identity]] and [[identity politics]], and many regard race as a [[social construction|social construct]].  Legal definitions, common usage, and scientific meaning can all be confounded, and care must be taken to note the context in which it is used.

Since the 1940s, [[evolution]]ary scientists have rejected the view of race according to which any number of finite lists of [[Essentialism|essential]] characteristics could be used to determine a like number of races. For example, the [[convention]] of categorizing the human population based on [[human skin color]]s has been used, but hair colors, eye colors, nose sizes, lip sizes, and heights have not.  Many evolutionary and social scientists think common race definitions, or any race definitions pertaining to humans, lack [[taxonomy|taxonomic]] rigour and validity. They argue that race definitions are imprecise, arbitrary, derived from [[custom]], have many exceptions, have many gradations, and that the numbers of races observed vary according to the culture examined. They further maintain that "race" as such is best understood as a [[social construction|social construct]], and they prefer to conceptualize and analyze human genotypic and phenotypic variation in terms of [[population genetics|populations]] and [[cline]]s instead. 

Some scientists, however, have argued that this position is motivated more by political than scientific reasons.  Some others also argue that categories of self-identified race/ethnicity or [[biogeographic ancestry]] are both valid and useful, that these categories correspond to clusters inferred from [[Race and multilocus allele clusters|multilocus genetic data]], and that this correspondence implies that genetic factors might contribute to unexplained phenotypic variation among groups.
   
== History ==

=== Popular concepts of "race" ===

Given visually complex social relationships, humans presumably have always observed and speculated about the physical differences among individuals and groups. But different societies have attributed markedly different meanings to these distinctions. The division of humanity into distinct "races" can be traced as far back as the [[Ancient Egyptian]] sacred text the [[Book of Gates]], which identifies four categories that are now conventionally labelled "Egyptians", "Asiatics", "Libyans", and "Nubians". However, such distinctions tended to merge differences defined by features such as skin color, with [[tribe|tribal]] and [[nation]]al identity. Classical civilizations from Rome to China tended to invest much more importance in family or tribal affiliations than in physical appearance (Dikötter 1992; Goldenberg 2003). [[Ancient Greek]] and [[Ancient Roman|Roman]] authors also attempted to explain and categorize visible biological differences between peoples known to them. Such categories often also included fantastical human-like beings that were supposed to exist in far-away lands. Some Roman writers adhered to an [[environmental determinism]] in which climate could affect the appearance and character of groups (Isaac 2004). But in many ancient civilizations, individuals with widely varying physical appearances could become full members of a society by growing up within that society or by adopting the society's [[culture|cultural]] [[norm (sociology)|norms]] (Snowden 1983; Lewis 1990). [[Medieval]] models of race mixed [[Graeco-Roman|Classical]] ideas with the notion that humanity as a whole was descended from [[Shem]], [[Ham]] and [[Japheth]], the three [[sons of Noah]], producing distinct [[Semitic]] (Asian), [[Hamitic]] (African), and [[Japhetic]] (European) peoples.

After the end of the ''[[Reconquista]]'', the [[Spanish Inquisition]] [[persecution|persecuted]] [[Jews]] and [[Muslims]], theorizing a ''[[limpieza de sangre]]'' ("blood cleansing") doctrine. Furthermore, after the discovery of the [[New World]], [[Bartolomé de Las Casas]] opposed the ''[[conquistador]]es'' theories, upheld by [[Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda|Sepúlveda]], on the pretended [[Amerindians]]'s absence of souls. 

It wasn't until the 16th century that the word '''race''' entered the [[English language]], from the [[French language|French]] ''race'' - "race, breed, lineage" (which in turn was probably a loan from [[Italian language|Italian]] ''razza''). Meanings of the term in the 16th century included "[[wine]]s with a characteristic flavour", "people with common occupation", and "[[generation]]". The meaning "[[tribe]]" or "[[nation]]" emerged in the 17th century. The modern meaning, "one of the major divisions of mankind", dates to the late 18th century, but it never became exclusive (cf. continued use of "the human race"). The ultimate origin of the word is unknown; suggestions include [[Arabic language|Arabic]] ''[[Rho (letter)|ra'is]]'' meaning "head", but also "beginning" or "origin".

In ''Society Must be Defended'' (1978-79), [[Michel Foucault]] traced the "historical and political discourse" of [[Philosophy of history#Michel Foucault's analysis of the historical and political discourse|"race struggle"]] to the 1688 "[[Glorious Revolution]]" in England and [[Louis XIV]]'s reign in France, during which conflicting political values were ascribed to ancestral ethnicities (Saxon, Norman, Frankish etc). According to him, these debates initiated a form of "popular history" based on ethnic identity, as opposed to the classical juridical and philosophical discourse of [[sovereignty]]. In England, it was used by [[Edward Coke]] and [[John Lilburne]] to demand "[[inalienable rights]]" and oppose the [[monarchy]]. In France, [[Boulainvilliers]], [[Nicolas Fréret]], and then [[Sieyès]], [[Augustin Thierry]] and [[Cournot]] reappropriated this discourse. 
During the 19th century, the discourse developed in two different directions. On the one hand, according to Foucault, [[Marxists]] seized this historical and political discourse, replacing the essentialist notion of "race" with the historical and social concept of "[[class struggle]]." On the other hand, also according to Foucault, at the end of the 19th century, the notion of "race" was adopted by [[racist]] [[biologists]] and [[eugenicists]], who gave it the modern sense of "biological race", which was then integrated to "[[state racism]]". This displacement of discourse constitutes one of the basis of Foucault's thought: discourse is not tied to the [[subject (philosophy)|subject]], rather the "subject" is a construction of discourse.

The English word "race", along with many of the ideas now associated with the term, were products of the European era of exploration (Smedley 1999). As Europeans encountered people from different parts of the world, they speculated about the physical, social, and cultural differences among human groups. The rise of the [[Atlantic slave trade|African slave trade]], which gradually displaced an earlier trade in slaves from throughout the world, created a further incentive to categorize human groups to justify the barbarous treatment of African slaves (Meltzer 1993). Drawing on classical sources and on their own internal interactions &amp;mdash; for example, the hostility between the English and Irish was a powerful influence on early thinking about the differences between people (Takaki 1993) &amp;mdash; Europeans began to sort themselves and others into groups associated with physical appearance and with deeply ingrained behaviors and capacities. A set of [[folklore|folk]] [[beliefs]] took hold that linked inherited physical differences between groups to inherited intellectual, behavioral, and moral qualities (Banton 1977). Although similar ideas can be found in other cultures (Lewis 1990; Dikötter 1992), they appear not to have had as much influence on social structures as they did in Europe and the parts of the world colonized by Europeans. However, often brutal conflicts between ethnic groups have existed throughout history and across the world, and racial prejudice against Africans also exists in non-colonised countries such as Japan and China. [http://diaspora.northwestern.edu/mbin/WebObjects/DiasporaX.woa/wa/displayArticle?atomid=711]

=== Scientific concepts of "race" ===
{{further|[[Race (historical definitions)]]}}

The first scientific attempts to categorize race date from the 17th century, along with the development of European imperialism and colonization around the world. The first post-[[Graeco-Roman|Classical]] published classification of humans into distinct races seems to be [[François Bernier]]'s ''Nouvelle division de la terre par les différents espèces ou races qui l'habitent'' ("New division of Earth by the different species or races which inhabit it"), published in 1684.

==== 17th and 18th century ====
In the 18th century, the differences between human groups became a focus of scientific investigation (Todorov 1993). Initially, scholars focused on cataloging and describing "The Natural Varieties of Mankind," as [[Johann Friedrich Blumenbach]] entitled his 1775 text (which established the five major divisions of humans still reflected in some racial classifications). From the 17th through the 19th centuries, the merging of folk beliefs about group differences with scientific explanations of those differences produced what one scholar has called an "[[ideology]] of race" (Smedley 1999). According to this ideology, races are primordial, natural, enduring, and distinct. Some groups might be the result of mixture between formerly distinct populations, but careful study can distinguish the ancestral races that had combined to produce admixed groups.

==== 19th century ====
The 19th century saw attempts to change race from a taxonomic to a biological concept. In the 19th century a number of [[natural science|natural scientists]] wrote on race: [[Georges Cuvier]], [[Charles Darwin]], [[Alfred Wallace]], [[Francis Galton]], [[James Cowles Pritchard]], [[Louis Agassiz]], [[Charles Pickering NMI|Charles Pickering]], and [[Johann Friedrich Blumenbach]].  As the science of [[anthropology]] took shape in the 19th century, European and American scientists increasingly sought explanations for the behavioral and cultural differences they attributed to groups (Stanton 1960). For example, using [[anthropometrics]], invented by [[Francis Galton]] and [[Alphonse Bertillon]], they measured the shapes and sizes of skulls and related the results to group differences in intelligence or other attributes (Lieberman 2001).

These scientists made three claims about race: first, that races are objective, naturally occurring divisions of humanity; second, that there is a strong relationship between biological races and other human phenomena (such as [[forms of activity and interpersonal relations]] and culture, and by extension the relative [[materialism|material success]] of cultures), thus biologizing the notion of "race", as [[Foucault]] demonstrated in his historical analysis; third, that race is therefore a valid scientific category that can be used to explain and predict individual and group behavior. Races were distinguished by [[human skin color|skin color]], [[face|facial]] type, [[cranium|cranial]] profile and size, texture and color of [[hair]]. Moreover, races were almost universally considered to reflect group differences in [[moral]] character and [[intelligence (trait)|intelligence]].

The [[eugenics]] movement of the late 19th and early 20th centuries, inspired by [[Arthur Gobineau]]'s ''[[An Essay on the Inequality of the Human Races]]'' (1853-1855), [[Vacher de Lapouge]]'s "anthroposociology" asserted as self-evident the biological inferiority of particular groups (Kevles 1985). In many parts of the world, the idea of race became a way of rigidly dividing groups by culture as well as by physical appearances (Hannaford 1996). Campaigns of oppression and [[genocide]] were often motivated by supposed racial differences (Horowitz 2001).

In Charles Darwin's most controversial book, ''[[The Descent of Man]]'', he made strong suggestions of racial differences and European superiority.  In Darwin's view, stronger tribes of humans always replaced weaker tribes.  As savage tribes came in conflict with civilized nations, such as England, the less advanced people were destroyed. The destruction of the weaker peoples seemed desirable to many scientists at the time.  It was thought that "fit" people would replace the "unfit" and human evolution would be accelerated. Nevertheless, he also noted the great difficulty naturalists had in trying to decide how many "races" there actually were (Darwin was himself a monogenist on the question of race, believing that all humans were of the same species and finding "race" to be a somewhat arbitrary distinction between groups):
:''Man has been studied more carefully than any other animal, and yet there is the greatest possible diversity amongst capable judges whether he should be classed as a single species or race, or as two (Virey), as three (Jacquinot), as four (Kant), five (Blumenbach), six (Buffon), seven (Hunter), eight (Agassiz), eleven (Pickering), fifteen (Bory St. Vincent), sixteen (Desmoulins), twenty-two (Morton), sixty (Crawfurd), or as sixty- three, according to Burke. This diversity of judgment does not prove that the races ought not to be ranked as species, but it shews that they graduate into each other, and that it is hardly possible to discover clear distinctive characters between them.''

====20th century====
:''See also [[Racism#From "racial theory" to "racism"|From "racial theory" to "racism"]].''

At the beginning of the 20th century, [[anthropologist]]s questioned, and subsequently abandoned, the claim that biologically distinct races are [[isomorphic]] with (related to) distinct linguistic, cultural, and social groups. Then, the rise of [[population genetics]] led some mainstream evolutionary scientists in [[anthropology]] and [[biology]] to question the very validity of race as scientific concept describing an objectively real phenomenon. Those who came to reject the validity of the concept, race, did so for four reasons: empirical, definitional, the availability of alternative concepts, and ethical (Lieberman and Byrne 1993).  

The first to challenge the concept of race on empirical grounds were [[anthropology|anthropologists]] [[Franz Boas]], who demonstrated phenotypic plasticity due to environmental factors (Boas 1912) (see also [http://www.southwestern.edu/~greenmue/boas.htm]), and [[Ashley Montagu]] (1941, 1942), who relied on evidence from genetics. [[Zoology|Zoologists]] Edward O. Wilson and W. Brown then challenged the concept from the perspective of general [[Scientific classification|systematics]], and further rejected the claim that "races" were equivalent to "subspecies" (Wilson and Brown 1953). 

One of the crucial innovations in reconceptualizing [[genotypic]] and [[phenotypic]] variation was anthropologist [[C. Loring Brace]]'s observation that such variations, insofar as they are affected by [[natural selection]], [[migration]], or [[genetic drift]], are distributed along geographic gradations called "[[cline]]s" (Brace 1964). This point called attention to a problem common to phenotypic-based descriptions of races (for example, those based on hair texture and skin color): they ignore a host of other similarities and difference (for example, blood type) that do not correlate highly with the markers for race. Thus, anthropologist [[Frank Livingstone]]'s conclusion that, since clines cross racial boundaries, "there are no races, only clines" (Livingstone 1962: 279). In 1964, biologists [[Paul Ehrlich]] and Holm pointed out cases where two or more clines are distributed discordantly&amp;mdash;for example, [[melanin]] is distributed in a decreasing pattern from the equator north and south; frequencies for the [[haplotype]] for [[beta-S]] [[hemoglobin]], on the other hand, radiate out of specific geographical points in Africa (Ehrlich and Holm 1964). As anthropologists [[Leonard Lieberman]] and [[Fatimah Linda Jackson]] observe, "Discordant patterns of heterogeneity falsify any description of a population as if it were genotypically or even phenotypically homogeneous" (Lieverman and Jackson 1995).

Finally, geneticist [[Richard Lewontin]], observing that 85 percent of human variation occurs within populations, and not between populations, argued that neither "race" nor "subspecies" was an appropriate or useful way to describe populations (Lewontin 1973). This view is described by its opponents as [[Lewontin's Fallacy]]. [[A.W.F._Edwards|Edwards]] claimed in 2003 that Lewontin's conclusion is unwarranted because the argument ignores the fact that most of the information that distinguishes populations is hidden in the correlation structure of the data and not simply in the variation of the individual factors. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=12879450&amp;dopt=Abstract&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Armand_Marie_Leroi|Dr. Leroi]], an evolutionary developmental biologist at Imperial College in London, is one of the scientists that agrees with Edwards. &lt;ref&gt;http://raceandgenomics.ssrc.org/Leroi/&lt;/ref&gt;

Some researchers report the variation between racial groups (measured by [[Sewall Wright|Sewall Wright's]] population structure statistic F&lt;sub&gt;ST&lt;/sub&gt;) accounts for as little as 5% of human genetic variation&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. However, because of technical limitations of F&lt;sub&gt;ST&lt;/sub&gt;, many geneticists now believe that low F&lt;sub&gt;ST&lt;/sub&gt; values do not invalidate the suggestion that there might be different human races (Edwards, 2003). Meanwhile, [[neo-Marxists]] such as [[David Harvey]] (1982, 1984, 1992) believe that race is a social construct that serves in no way to help humans deal with their reality, and is used, instead, to justify and reinforce class differences.

These empirical challenges to the concept of race forced evolutionary sciences to reconsider their definition of race. Mid-century, anthropologist [[William Boyd]] defined race as:
:A population which differs significantly from other populations in regard to the frequency of one or more of the genes it possesses. It is an arbitrary matter which, and how many, [[gene|gene loci]] we choose to consider as a significant "constellation" (Boyd 1950).
Lieberman and Jackson (1994) have pointed out that "the weakness of this statement is that if one gene can distinguish races then the number of races is as numerous as the number of human couples reproducing."  Moreover, anthropologist [[Stephen Molnar]] has suggested that the discordance of clines inevitably results in a multiplication of races that renders the concept itself useless (Molnar 1992).

Alongside empirical and conceptual problems with "race" following the [[Second World War]], evolutionary and social scientists were acutely aware of how beliefs about race had been used to justify [[discrimination]], [[apartheid]], [[slavery]], and [[genocide]]. This questioning gained momentum in the 1960s during the [[American Civil Rights Movement (1955-1968)|American Civil Rights Movement]] and the emergence of numerous [[anti-colonial movement]]s worldwide.

In the face of these issues, some evolutionary scientists have simply abandoned the concept of race in favor of "[[Population genetics|population]]." What distinguishes population from previous groupings of humans by race is that it refers to a breeding population (essential to genetic calculations) and not to a biological [[taxon]]. Other evolutionary scientists have abandoned the concept of race in favor of [[cline]] (meaning, how the frequency of a trait changes along a geographic gradient). The concepts of population and cline are not, however, mutually exclusive and both are used by many evolutionary scientists.

In the face of this rejection of race by some evolutionary scientists, many social scientists have replaced the word race with the word "[[Ethnic group|ethnicity]]" to refer to self-identifying groups based on beliefs in shared [[religion]], [[nationality]], or race. Moreover, they understood these shared beliefs to mean that religion, nationality, and race itself are [[social construct]]s and have no objective basis in the supernatural or natural realm (Gordon 1964). See also the American Anthropological Association's Statement on Race [http://www.aaanet.org/stmts/racepp.htm].

====Summary of different definitions of race====

{| class="wikitable"
|+ Biological definitions of race (Long &amp; Kittles, 2003) ''et al.''
! Concept || Reference || Definition
|-
| Essentialist || Hooton (1926) || "A great division of mankind, characterized as a group by the sharing of a certain combination of features, which have been derived from their common descent, and constitute a vague physical background, usually more or less obscured by individual variations, and realized best in a composite picture."
|-
| Taxonomic || [[Ernst Mayr|Mayr]] (1969) || "An aggregate of phenotypically similar populations of a species, inhabiting a geographic subdivision of the range of a species, and differing taxonomically from other populations of the species."
|-
| Population || [[Theodosius Dobzhansky|Dobzhansky]] (1970) || "Races are genetically distinct Mendelian populations. They are neither individuals nor particular genotypes, they consist of individuals who differ genetically among themselves."
|-
| Lineage || Templeton (1998) || "A subspecies (race) is a distinct evolutionary lineage within a species. This definition requires that a subspecies be genetically differentiated due to barriers to genetic exchange that have persisted for long periods of time; that is, the subspecies must have historical continuity in addition to current genetic differentiation."
|-
| Clade || [[Michael Levin|Levin]] (2002) || Race "connotes geographic ancestry, by continent or large continental subregion" and "is used to denote continental or subcontinental clades". In "Cladistic taxonomy ... the basic taxon [is] the genealogical unit, ancestors-plus-line- (or tree) -of-descent, what according to the present analysis races are."
|}

== Human genetic variation ==
{{main|Human genetic variation}}
=== Physical variation in humans ===
{{further|[[Human skin color]]}}
[[Image:Map of skin hue equi.png|thumb|300px|Map of skin-color distribution for "native populations" collected by [[Renato Biasutti]] prior to [[1930s|1940]].]]
The distribution of many physical traits resembles the distribution of genetic variation within and between human populations (American Association of Physical Anthropologists 1996; Keita and Kittles 1997). For example, ∼90% of the variation in human head shapes occurs within every human group, and ∼10% separates groups, with a greater variability of head shape among individuals with recent African ancestors (Relethford 2002).

A prominent exception to the common distribution of physical characteristics within and among groups is skin color. Approximately 10% of the variance in skin color occurs within groups, and ~90% occurs between groups (Relethford 2002). This distribution of skin color and its geographic patterning—with people whose ancestors lived predominantly near the equator having darker skin than those with ancestors who lived predominantly in higher latitudes—indicate that this attribute has been under strong selective pressure. Darker skin appears to be strongly selected for in equatorial regions to prevent sunburn, skin cancer, the photolysis of folate, and damage to sweat glands (Sturm ''et al.'' 2001; Rees 2003). A leading hypothesis for the selection of lighter skin in higher latitudes is that it enables the body to form greater amounts of vitamin D, which helps prevent rickets (Jablonski 2004). Evidence for this includes the finding that 
a substantial portion of the differences of skin color between Europeans and Africans resides in a single gene, [[SLC24A5]] the threonine-111 allele of which was found in 98.7 to 100% among several European samples, while the alanine-111 form was found in 93 to 100% of samples of Africans, East Asians and Indigenous Americans (Lamason ''et al.'' 2005). However, the vitamin D hypothesis is not universally accepted (Aoki 2002), and lighter skin in high latitudes may correspond simply to an absence of selection for dark skin (Harding ''et al.'' 2000). [[Melanin]] which serves as the pigment, is located in the [[Epidermis (skin)|epidermis]] of the skin, and is based on [[hereditary]] [[gene expression]].

Because skin color has been under strong selective pressure, similar skin colors can result from convergent adaptation rather than from genetic relatedness. Sub-Saharan Africans, tribal populations from southern India, and Indigenous Australians have similar skin pigmentation, but genetically they are no more similar than are other widely separated groups. Furthermore, in some parts of the world in which people from different regions have mixed extensively, the connection between skin color and ancestry has been substantially weakened (Parra ''et al.'' 2004). So, taking them in isolation would appear to get you nowhere. In Brazil, for example, skin color is not closely associated with the percentage of recent African ancestors a person has, as estimated from an analysis of genetic variants differing in frequency among continent groups (Parra ''et al.'' 2003).

Considerable speculation has surrounded the possible adaptive value of other physical features characteristic of groups, such as the constellation of facial features observed in many eastern and northeastern Asians (Guthrie 1996). However, any given physical characteristic generally is found in multiple groups (Lahr 1996), and demonstrating that environmental selective pressures shaped specific physical features will be difficult, since such features may have resulted from sexual selection for individuals with certain appearances or from genetic drift (Roseman 2004).

=== Ancestry ===
{{main|Race and multilocus allele clusters}}
[[Image:Rosenberg 1048people 993markers.jpg|thumb|Human population structure can be inferred from multilocus DNA sequence data (Rosenberg et al. 2002, 2005). Individuals from 52 populations were examined at 993 DNA markers. This data was used to partitioned individuals into K = 2, 3, 4, 5 or 6 clusters. In this figure, the average fractional membership of individuals from each population is represented by horizontal bars partitioned into K colored segments.]]

An alternative to the use of racial or ethnic categories is to categorize individuals in terms of ancestry. Ancestry may be defined geographically (e.g., Asian, sub-Saharan African, or northern European), geopolitically (e.g., Vietnamese, Zambian, or Norwegian), or culturally (e.g., Brahmin, Lemba, or Apache). The definition of ancestry may recognize a single predominant source or multiple sources. Ancestry can be ascribed to an individual by an observer, as was the case with the U.S. census prior to 1960; it can be identified by an individual from a list of possibilities or with use of terms drawn from that person's experience; or it can be calculated from genetic data by use of loci with allele frequencies that differ geographically, as described above. At least among those individuals who participate in biomedical research, genetic estimates of biogeographical ancestry generally agree with self-assessed ancestry (Tang ''et al.'' 2005), but in an unknown percentage of cases, they do not (Brodwin 2002; Kaplan 2003).

Genetic data can be used to infer population structure and assign individuals to groups that often correspond with their self-identified geographical ancestry. The inference of population structure from multilocus genotyping depends on the selection of a large number of informative genetic markers. These studies usually find that groups of humans living on the same continent are more similar to one another than to groups living on different continents. Many such studies are criticized for assigning group identity ''[[A priori (statistics)|a priori]]''. However, even if group identity is stripped and group identity assigned ''[[a posteriori]]'' using only genetic data, population structure can still be inferred. For example, using 993 markers, Rosenberg ''et al.'' (2005) were able to assign 1,048 individuals from 52 populations around the globe to one of six genetic clusters, which correspond to major geographic regions.

However, in analyses that assign individuals to group it becomes less apparent that self-described racial groups are reliable indicators of ancestry. One cause of the reduced power of the assignment of individuals to groups is [[wiktionary:admixture|admixture]]. Some racial or ethnic groups, especially [[Hispanic]] groups, do not have homogenous ancestry. For example, self-described [[African Americans]] tend to have a mix of West African and European ancestry. Shriver ''et al.'' (2003) found that on average African Americans have ~80% African ancestry. Likewise, many white Americans have mixed European and African ancestry, where ~30% of whites have less than 90% European ancestry. In this context, it is becoming more commonplace to describe "race" as fractional ancestry. Without the use of genotyping, this has been approximated by the self-described ancestry of an individual's grand-parents.

Nevertheless, recent research indicates that self-described race is a near-perfect indicator of an individual's genetic profile, at least in the United States. Using 326 genetic markers, Tang ''et al.'' (2005) identified 4 genetic clusters among 3,636 individuals sampled from 15 locations in the United States, and were able to correctly assign individuals to groups that correspond with their self-described race (white, African American, East Asian, or Hispanic) for all but 5 individuals (an error rate of 0.14%). They conclude that ancient ancestry, which correlates tightly with self-described race and not current residence, is the major determinant of genetic structure in the U.S. population.

Genetic techniques that distinguish ancestry between continents can also be used to describe ancestry within continents. However, the study of intra-continental ancestry may require a greater number of informative markers. Populations from neighboring geographic regions typically share more recent common ancestors. As a result, [[allele frequency|allele frequencies]] will be correlated between these groups. This phenomenon is often seen as a cline of allele frequencies. The existence of [[allele|allelic]] clines has been offered as evidence that individuals cannot be allocated into [[haplogroups|genetic cluster]]s (Kittles &amp; Weiss 2003). However, others argue that low levels of differentiation between groups merely make the assignment to groups more difficult, not impossible (Bamshad ''et al.'' 2004).

== Incongruities of racial classifications ==
Even as the idea of "race" was becoming a powerful organizing principle in many societies, the shortcomings of the concept were apparent. In the Old World, the gradual transition in appearances from one group to adjacent groups emphasized that "one variety of mankind does so sensibly pass into the other, that you cannot mark out the limits between them," as Blumenbach observed in his writings on human variation.&lt;ref&gt;J. Marks, ''Human Biodiversity: Genes, Race, and History (New York: Aldine de Gruyter, 1995), 54.&lt;/ref&gt; In parts of the Americas, the situation was somewhat different. The immigrants to the New World came largely from widely separated regions of the Old World—western and northern Europe, western Africa, and, later, eastern Asia and southern and eastern Europe. In the Americas, the immigrant populations began to [[miscegenation|mix]] among themselves and with the [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|indigenous]] inhabitants of the continent. In the United States, for example, most people who self-identify as African American have some European ancestors—in one analysis of genetic markers that have differing frequencies between continents, European ancestry ranged from an estimated 7% for a sample of Jamaicans to ∼23% for a sample of African Americans from New Orleans.&lt;ref&gt;Esteban J. Parra and others, "Estimating African American Admixture Proportions by Use of Population-Specific Alleles," ''American Journal of Human Genetics'' 63 (1998): 1839-51.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, many people who identify as European American have some African or Native American ancestors, either through openly interracial marriages or through the gradual inclusion of people with mixed ancestry into the majority population{{citation needed}}. In a survey of college students who self-identified as [[White people|white]] in a northeastern U.S. university, ∼30% were estimated to have &lt;90% European ancestry.&lt;ref&gt;Mark D. Shriver and others, "Skin Pigmentation, Biogeographical Ancestry, and Admixture Mapping," ''Human Genetics'' 112 (2003): 387-99.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, social and legal conventions developed over time that forced individuals of mixed ancestry into simplified racial categories.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas F. Gossett, ''Race: The History of an Idea in America'', New ed. (New York: Oxford University, 1997).&lt;/ref&gt; An example is the "[[one-drop rule]]" implemented in some state laws that treated anyone with a single known African American ancestor as black.&lt;ref&gt;F. James Davis, ''Who is Black?: One Nation's Definition'' (University Park PA: State University of Pennsylvania, 1991).&lt;/ref&gt; The decennial censuses conducted since 1790 in the United States also created an incentive to establish racial categories and fit people into those categories.&lt;ref&gt;M. Nobles, ''Shades of Citizenship: Race and the Census in Modern Politics'' (Stanford: Stanford University, 2000).&lt;/ref&gt; In other countries in the Americas where mixing among groups was more extensive, social categories have tended to be more numerous and fluid, with people moving into or out of categories on the basis of a combination of socioeconomic status, social class, ancestry, and appearance.&lt;ref&gt;Magnus Mörner, ''Race Mixture in the History of Latin America'' (Boston: Little Brown, 1967).&lt;/ref&gt;

Efforts to sort the increasingly mixed population of the United States into discrete categories generated many difficulties.&lt;ref&gt;P.R. Spickard, "The illogic of American racial categories," in M.P.P. Root, ed., ''Racially mixed people in America'' (Newbury Park CA: Sage, 1992), 12–23.&lt;/ref&gt;. By the standards used in past censuses, many millions of children born in the United States have belonged to a different race than have one of their biological parents. Efforts to track mixing between groups led to a proliferation of categories (such as [[mulatto]] and [[octoroon]]) and "blood quantum" distinctions that became increasingly untethered from self-reported ancestry. A person's racial identity can change over time, and self-ascribed race can differ from assigned race.&lt;ref&gt;N.R. Kressin, et al., "Agreement between administrative data and patients' self-reports of race/ethnicity," ''American Journal of Public Health'', 2003 Oct;93(10):1734-9.&lt;/ref&gt; Until the 2000 census, Latinos were required to identify with a single race despite the long history of mixing in Latin America; partly as a result of the confusion generated by the distinction, 42% of Latino respondents in the 2000 census ignored the specified racial categories and checked "some other race."&lt;ref&gt;V.M. Mays, N.A. Ponce, D.L. Washington, S.D. Cochran, "Classification of race and ethnicity: implications for public health," ''Annual Rev Public Health'' (2003) 24:83–110.&lt;/ref&gt;.

== Current views across disciplines ==
One result of debates over the meaning and validity of the concept "race" is that the current literature across different disciplines regarding human variation lacks [[scientific consensus|consensus]], though within some fields, such as biology, there is strong consensus. Some studies use the word race in its early [[essentialism|essentialist]] [[taxonomic]] sense.  Many others still use the term race, but use it to mean a population, [[clade]], or [[haplogroup]]. Others eschew the word race altogether, and use the word population as a less value laden synonym. 

In the 19th century, race was a central concept of [[anthropology]]. In 1866, [[James Hunt]], the founder of the [[Anthropological Society of London]], declared that anthropology’s primary truth “is the existence of well-marked psychological and moral distinctions in the different races of men.” However, this view became marginalised in the 20th century. Since 1932, [[college]] [[textbook]]s introducing physical anthropology have increasingly come to reject race as a valid concept: from 1932 to 1976, only seven out of thirty-two rejected race; from 1975 to 1984, thirteen out of thirty-three rejected race; from 1985 to 1993, thirteen out of nineteen rejected race. The American Anthropological Association, drawing on biological research, currently holds that "The concept of race is a social and cultural construction. . . . Race simply cannot be tested or proven scientifically," and that, "It is clear that human populations are not unambiguous, clearly demarcated, biologically distinct groups. The concept of 'race' has no validity . . . in the human species"[http://www.aaanet.org/stmts/racepp.htm].  Nevertheless, many scientists, including many anthropologists, reject this position. 

In an ongoing debate, some geneticists argue that race is neither a meaningful concept nor a useful [[heuristic]] device,&lt;ref&gt;(Wilson ''et al.'' 2001), (Cooper ''et al.'' 2003) (given in summary by Bamshad ''et al.'' 2004 p.599)&lt;/ref&gt; and even that genetic differences almong groups are biologically meaningless,&lt;ref&gt;(Schwartz 2001), (Stephens 2003) (given in summary by Bamshad ''et al.'' 2004 p.599)&lt;/ref&gt; on the grounds that more genetic variation exists within such races than among them, and that racial traits overlap without discrete boundaries.&lt;ref&gt;(Smedley and Smedley 2005), (Helms ''et al.'' 2005), [http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0102-311X2004000300003&amp;lng=es&amp;nrm=iso]. Lewontin, for example argues that there is no biological basis for race on the basis of research indicating that more genetic variation exists within such races than among them (Lewontin 1972).&lt;/ref&gt; 
Other geneticists, in contrast, argue that categories of self-identified race/ethnicity or [[biogeographic ancestry]] are both valid and useful.&lt;ref&gt;(Risch ''et al.'' 2002), (Bamshad 2005). [[Neil Risch]] argues: "One could make the same arguments about sex and age! ... you can undermine any definitional system...  In a recent study... we actually had a higher discordance rate between self-reported sex and markers on the X chromosome [than] between genetic structure [based on microsatellite markers] versus [racial] self-description, [which had a] 99.9% concordance...  So you could argue that sex is also a problematic category. And there are differences between sex and gender; self-identification may not be correlated with biology perfectly. And there is sexism. And you can talk about age the same way. A person's chronological age does not correspond perfectly with his biological age for a variety of reasons, both inherited and non-inherited. Perhaps just using someone's actual birth year is not a very good way of measuring age. Does that mean we should throw it out? ... Any category you come up with is going to be imperfect, but that doesn't preclude you from using it or the fact that it has utility"(Gitschier 2005).&lt;/ref&gt; that these categories correspond with clusters [[Race and multilocus allele clusters|inferred from multilocus genetic data]],&lt;ref&gt;(Harpending and Rogers 2000), (Bamshad ''et al.'' 2003), (Edwards 2003), (Bamshad ''et al.'' 2004), (Tang ''et al.'' 2005), (Rosenberg ''et al.'' 2005): "If enough markers are used... individuals can be partitioned into genetic clusters that match major geographic subdivisions of the globe".&lt;/ref&gt; and that this correspondence implies that genetic factors might contribute to unexplained phenotypic variation between groups.&lt;ref&gt;(Mountain and Risch 2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Biological interpretations of race===

According to [[Arthur Jensen]] the traditional races of physical anthropology have been more or less confirmed by the research of Cavalli-Sforza.

On pgs 430-431 of ''the g factor'' Jensen writes:

:''Cavalli-Sforza ''et al.'' transformed the distance matrix to a correlation matrix consisting of 861 correlation coefficients among the forty-two populations, so they could apply principal components (PC) analysis on their genetic data...PC analysis is a wholly objective mathematical procedure. It requires no decisions or judgments on anyone's part and yields identical results for everyone who does the calculations correctly...The important point is that if various populations were fairly homogenous in genetic composition, differing no more genetically than could be attributable only to random variation, a PC analysis would not be able to cluster the populations into a number of groups according to their genetic propinquity. In fact, a PC analysis shows that most of the forty-two populations fall very distinctly into the quadrents formed by using the first and second principal component as axes...They form quite widely separated clusters of the various populations that resemble the "classic" major racial groups-Caucasoids in the upper right, Negroids in the lower right, North East Asians in the upper left, and South East Asians (including South Chinese) and Pacific Islanders in the lower left...I have tried other objective methods of clustering on the same data (varimax rotation of the principal components, common factor analysis, and hierarchical cluster analysis). All of these types of analysis yield essentially the same picture and identify the same major racial groupings.''

[[Image:Fig.2.3.542pop.jpg]]

Elsewhere in Jensen's writings, he equates North East Asians with Mongoloids, which along with Caucasoids and Negroids, form what Jensen describes as the three broadest population groups. To test the reliability of these broadgroupings, Jensen performed his own independent varimax rotated principal component analysis described on paged 518 of the g factor:

''I have used a somewhat different collection of only 26 populations from around the world that were studied by the population genetecists Nei &amp; Roychoudhury (1993), whose article provides the genetic distance matrix among the 26 population samples, based on 29 polymorphic genes with 121 alleles...Note that some groups have major and minor loadings on different components, which represent not discrete categories, but central tendencies. The six rotated components can display clusters that can be identified as follows: (1) Mongoloids, (2) Caucasoids, (3) South Asians and Pacific Islanders, (4) Negroids, (5) North and South Amerindians and Eskimos, (6) aboriginal Australians and Papuan New Guineans. The genetic groupings are clearly similar to those obtained by Cavali-Sforza ''et al.'' using other methods applied to other samples.''

The following chart by [[Cavalli-Sforza]] shows the genetic distance between the major races that Jensen describes and the separate branches they sit on:

[[Image:DNAtree.gif]]

====Criticism====
Dr. Eduardas Valaitas claims the traditional [[Races of physical anthropology]] have been unscientifically appropriated by  geneticists.  Valaitais, a statistician from Yale, has made a genetic similarity chart of the human species.  His genetic distance chart does not coincide with [[Luigi Luca Cavalli-Sforza|Cavalli Sforza's]] genetic distance chart.  Valaitais claims to have made a genetic distance chart by actual Euclidean distances given by the data.  Valaitais contrasts his work with other genetic distance charts such which he claims were categorized in a priori or predefined groups.  Namely, Valaitais accuses other genetic anthropologists of using hand-me-down racial groups from the [[races of physical anthropology|earlier craniofacial races of the 19th century typologists]].&lt;ref&gt;Valaitas, E. Martin. L. DNA Tribes. 2006. October 17, 2006.&lt;http://dnatribes.com/sample-results/dnatribes-global-survey-regional-affinities.pdf&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt;  In particular, the genetic distance interpretations of Cavalli Sforza have been ridiculed for using "a priori" racial groups such as "Caucasian" not given by the actual genetic data itself.  The genetic distance plot of Sforza which mirrors 19th century typological groups, has been used by [[Arthur Jensen]] a race and IQ psychologist to promote the idea that the traditional races of craniofacial anthropology have been confirmed by genetics.

===Social interpretations of race===
{{main|Social interpretations of race}}

[[History|Historians]], [[cultural anthropology|anthropologists]] and [[social sciences|social scientists]] often describe human races as a social construct, preferring instead the term ''population'', which can be given a clear [[operational definition]]. Even those who reject the formal concept of race, however, still use the word ''race'' in day-to-day speech. This may either be a matter of [[semantics]], or an effect of an underlying cultural significance of race in racist societies.

In everyday speech, ''race'' often describes populations better defined as [[ethnic group]]s, often leading to discrepancies between scientific views on race and popular usage of the term.  For instance in many parts of the United States, categories such as [[Hispanic American|Hispanic]] or [[Latino]] are viewed to constitute a race, though others see ''Hispanic'' as a linguistic and cultural grouping coming from a variety of backgrounds. In Europe, such a distinction, suggesting that [[Southern Europe|South Europeans]] are not European or [[whites|white]], would seem odd at least or possibly even insulting. In the United States, in what is referred to as the [[one-drop rule]], the term ''Black'' subsumes people with a broad range of ancestries under one label, even though many who are termed Black could be more accurately described as white through simple anthropologic or taxonomic method. In much of Europe groups such as [[Roma (people)|Roma]] and [[South Asia|South Asians]] are commonly defined as racially distinct from "White" Europeans{{fact}}, though these groups could be considered "Caucasian" by old physical anthropological methods which employed finite nose measurements and skull structure as the standard form of racial classification.

Some argue it is preferable when considering biological relations to think in terms of populations, and when considering cultural relations to think in terms of [[ethnicity]], rather than of race.  Instead of classing people into one "group", say "Caucasians" or Europeans you have [[United Kingdom|Britons]], [[France|Frenchmen]], [[Germany|Germans]], [[Nordic Countries|Nord]]s, western [[Slavs]] and [[Celts]] rather than having a term implying a (possible) ancestry group in the [[Caucasus]] which is definitely too distant for any real consideration, and moreover reaching to groups including eastern [[Slavs]], [[Roma (people)|Roma]], as well as [[Georgians]], and others who differ notably, both in culture, and to a noteworthy extent in physical appearance, from the aforementioned ethnic groups. There can be as much difference between two ethnicities grouped into a single "race" as there can be between ethnicities grouped (often arbitrarily) into an another "race". 

These developments had important consequences.  For example, some scientists developed the notion of "population" to take the place of race.  This substitution is not simply a matter of exchanging one word for another. Populations are, in a sense, simply statistical clusters that emerge from the choice of variables of interest; there is no preferred set of variables. The "populationist" view does not deny that there are physical differences among peoples; it simply claims that the historical conceptions of "race" are not particularly useful in accounting for these differences scientifically. 

Since the 1960s, some anthropologists and teachers of anthropology have re-conceived "race" as a cultural category or [[social construct]], in other words, as a particular way that some people have of talking about themselves and others. As such it cannot be a useful analytical concept; rather, the use of the term "race" itself must be analyzed. Moreover, they argue that biology will not explain why or how people use the idea of race: history and social relationships will.

===Race in physical anthropology===
{{main|Craniofacial Anthropometry|Races of physical anthropology}}

Scientific support for the Caucasoid, Negroid, Mongoloid terminology of racial classification has fallen steadily over the past century. Where 78 percent of the articles in the 1931 ''Journal of Physical Anthropology'' employed these or nearly synonymous terms reflecting a bio-race paradigm, only 36 percent did so in 1965, and just 28 percent did in 1996.&lt;ref&gt;Leonard Lieberman, Rodney C. Kirk, and Alice Littlefield, "Perishing Paradigm: Race—1931-99," ''American Anthropologist'' 105, no. 1 (2003): 110-13. A following article in the same issue, by Mat Cartmill and Kaye Brown, questions the precise rate of decline, but agrees that the Negroid/Caucasoid/Mongoloid paradigm has fallen into near-total disfavor.&lt;/ref&gt; In February, 2001, the editors of the medical journal ''Archives of Pediatrics and Adolescent Medicine'' asked authors to no longer use "race" as an explanatory variable and not to use obsolescent terms. Other prestigious peer-reviewed journals, such as the ''New England Journal of Medicine'' and the ''American Journal of Public Health'', have done the same.&lt;ref&gt; Frederick P. Rivara and Laurence Finberg, "Use of the Terms Race and Ethnicity," ''Archives of Pediatrics &amp; Adolescent Medicine'' 155, no. 2 (2001): 119. For similar author's guidelines, see Robert S. Schwartz, "Racial Profiling in Medical Research," ''The New England Journal of Medicine'', 344 (no, 18, May 3, 2001); M.T. Fullilove, "Abandoning 'Race' as a Variable in Public Health Research: An Idea Whose Time has Come," ''American Journal of Public Health'', 88 (1998), 1297-1298; and R. Bhopal and L. Donaldson, "White, European, Western, Caucasian, or What? Inappropriate Labeling in Research on Race, Ethnicity, and Health." ''American Journal of Public Health'', 88 (1998), 1303-1307.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the National Institutes of Health recently issued a program announcement for grant applications through February 1, 2006, specifically seeking researchers who can investigate and publicize among primary care physicians the detrimental effects on the nation's health of the practice of medical racial profiling using such terms. The program announcement quoted the editors of one journal as saying that, "analysis by race and ethnicity has become an analytical knee-jerk reflex."&lt;ref&gt; See program announcement and requests for grant applications at the NIH website, at URL: http://grants1.nih.gov/grants/guide/pa-files/PA-03-057.html.&lt;/ref&gt; 
These terms originally denoted skull types and sprang from the technique known as ''[[Craniofacial Anthropometry|craniofacial anthropometry]]'', but have fallen somewhat in scientific use over the past century. The terms appear in two main usages today. They are used in ''[[Forensic anthropology|forensic anthropology]]'', and they are used in several fields as euphemisms for terms that came to be seen as offensive by some about thirty years ago. In the past, they were more widely used in [[Craniofacial Anthropometry#In_Phylogeography|craniofacial anthropometry in phylogeography]].

The most recent [[Statistical survey|survey]], taken in 1985 (Lieberman ''et al.'' 1992), asked 1,200 scientists how many '''disagree''' with the following proposition: "There are biological races in the species ''Homo sapiens''."  The responses were:
*'''[[biologist]]s 16%'''
*'''[[developmental psychologist]]s 36%'''
*'''[[physical anthropologist]]s 41%'''
*'''[[cultural anthropologist]]s 53%'''&lt;ref&gt;Bindon, Jim. University of Alabama. "[http://www.as.ua.edu/ant/bindon/ant275/presentations/POST_WWII.PDF#search=%22stanley%20marion%20garn%22 Post World War II"]. 2005. August 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
The figure for physical anthropologists at [[PhD]] granting departments was slightly higher, rising from 41% to 42%, with 50% agreeing.  This survey, however, did not specify any particular definition of race; it is impossible to say whether those who supported the statement thought of race in taxonomic or population terms.

=== Race and intelligence ===
:''Main article: [[Race and intelligence]]''

Researchers have reported significant differences in the average [[IQ]] test scores of various ethnic groups. The interpretation and causes of these differences are highly controversial. Some researchers, such as [[Arthur Jensen]], [[Richard Herrnstein]], and [[Richard Lynn]] have argued that such differences are at least partially genetic. Others, such as [[Stephen Jay Gould]] and [[Richard Lewontin]], believe categories such as "race" and "intelligence" are cultural constructs that render this sort of research scientifically flawed. Some, for example [[Thomas Sowell]], bypass the issue of the origins of categorization and seek to explain test score gaps in terms of social differences that affect how much of one's innate capacities any individual person might achieve.

=== Race in biomedicine ===
:''Main article: [[Race in biomedicine]]''

There is an active debate among biomedical researchers about the meaning and importance of race in their research. The primary impetus for considering race in biomedical research is the possibility of improving the prevention and treatment of [[disease]]s by predicting hard-to-ascertain factors on the basis of more easily ascertained characteristics. Regardless of the name, a working concept of sub-species grouping can be useful, because in the absence of cheap and widespread genetic tests, various race-linked gene mutations (see [[Cystic fibrosis]], [[Lactose intolerance]], [[Tay-Sachs Disease]] and [[Sickle cell anemia]]) are difficult to address without recourse to a category between "individual" and "species". The most well-known examples of genetically-determined disorders that vary in incidence between ethnic groups would be [[sickle cell disease]] and [[thalassaemia]] among black and [[Mediterranean]] populations and [[Tay-Sachs disease]] among people of [[Ashkenazi|Ashkenazi Jewish]] descent. Some fear that the use of racial labels in biomedical research runs the risk of unintentionally exacerbating health disparities, so they suggest alternatives to the use of racial taxonomies.

==Case studies in the social construction of race==
===Race in the United States===

In the United States since its early history, Native Americans, African-Americans and European-Americans were classified as belonging to different races. For nearly three centuries, the criteria for membership in these groups were similar, comprising a person’s appearance, his fraction of known non-White ancestry, and his social circle.&lt;sup&gt;[[#2|2]]&lt;/sup&gt; But the criteria for membership in these races diverged in the late 19th century. During Reconstruction, increasing numbers of Americans began to consider anyone with "[[one-drop theory|one drop]]" of "Black blood" to be Black.&lt;sup&gt;[[#3|3]]&lt;/sup&gt; By the early 20th century, this notion of invisible blackness was made statutory in many states and widely adopted nationwide.&lt;sup&gt;[[#4|4]]&lt;/sup&gt; In contrast, [[Amerindians]] continue to be defined by a certain percentage of "Indian blood" (called ''[[Blood quantum laws|blood quantum]]'') due in large part to [[American slavery ethics]]. Finally, for the past century or so, to be White one had to have "pure" White ancestry. (Utterly European-looking Americans of Hispanic or Arab ancestry are exceptions in being seen as White by most Americans despite traces of known African ancestry.)

Efforts to sort the increasingly mixed population of the United States into discrete categories generated many difficulties (Spickard 1992). By the standards used in past censuses, many millions of children born in the United States have belonged to a different race than have one of their biological parents. Efforts to track mixing between groups led to a proliferation of categories (such as "mulatto" and "octoroon") and "blood quantum" distinctions that became increasingly untethered from self-reported ancestry. A person's racial identity can change over time, and self-ascribed race can differ from assigned race (Kressin ''et al.'' 2003). Until the 2000 census, Latinos were required to identify with a single race despite the long history of mixing in Latin America; partly as a result of the confusion generated by the distinction, 32.9% (U.S. census records) of Latino respondents in the 2000 census ignored the specified racial categories and checked "some other race". (Mays ''et al.'' 2003 claim a figure of 42%)

The difference between how Native American and Black identities are defined today (blood quantum versus one-drop) has demanded explanation. According to anthropologists such as [[Gerald Sider]], the goal of such racial designations was to concentrate power, wealth, privilege and land in the hands of Whites in a society of White hegemony and White privilege (Sider 1996; see also Fields 1990). The differences have little to do with biology and far more to do with the history of [[racism]] and specific forms of [[White supremacy]] (the social, geopolitical and economic agendas of dominant Whites vis-à-vis subordinate Blacks and Native Americans) especially the different roles Blacks and Amerindians occupied in White-dominated nineteenth-century America. The theory suggests that the blood quantum definition of Native American identity enabled Whites to acquire Amerindian lands, while the one-drop rule of Black identity enabled Whites to preserve their agricultural labor force. The contrast presumably emerged because as peoples transported far from their land and kinship ties on another continent, Black labor was relatively easy to control, thus reducing Blacks to valuable [[commodity|commodities]] as agricultural laborers. In contrast, Amerindian labor was more difficult to control; moreover, Amerindians occupied large territories that became valuable as agricultural lands, especially with the invention of new technologies such as railroads; thus, the blood quantum definition enhanced White acquisition of Amerindian lands in a doctrine of [[Manifest Destiny]] that subjected them to marginalization and multiple episodic localized campaigns of extermination.

The political economy of race had different consequences for the descendants of aboriginal Americans and African slaves.  The 19th-century blood quantum rule meant that it was relatively easier for a person of mixed Euro-Amerindian ancestry to be accepted as White. The offspring of only a few generations of intermarriage between Amerindians and Whites likely would not have been considered Amerindian at all&amp;mdash;at least not in a legal sense. Amerindians could have [[treaty rights]] to land, but because an individual with one Amerindian great-grandparent no longer was classified as Amerindian, they lost any legal claim to Amerindian land. According to the theory, this enabled Whites to acquire Amerindian lands. The irony is that the same individuals who could be denied legal standing because they were "too White" to claim property rights, might still be Amerindian enough to be considered as "breeds," stigmatized for their Native American ancestry.

The 20th-century one-drop rule, on the other hand, made it relatively difficult for anyone of known Black ancestry to be accepted as White. The child of an African-American sharecropper and a White person was considered Black. And, significant in terms of the economics of sharecropping, such a person also would likely be a sharecropper as well, thus adding to the employer's labor force.

In short, this theory suggests that in a 20th-century economy that benefited from sharecropping, it was useful to have as many Blacks as possible. Conversely, in a 19th-century nation bent on westward expansion, it was advantageous to diminish the numbers of those who could claim title to Amerindian lands by simply defining them out of existence.

It must be mentioned, however, that although some scholars of the Jim Crow period agree that the 20th-century notion of invisible Blackness shifted the color line in the direction of paleness, thereby swelling the labor force in response to Southern Blacks' great migration northwards, others (Joel Williamson, C. Vann Woodward, George M. Fredrickson, Stetson Kennedy) see the one-drop rule as a simple consequence of the need to define Whiteness as being pure, thus justifying White-on-Black oppression. In any event, over the centuries when Whites wielded power over both Blacks and Amerindians and widely believed in their inherent superiority over people of color, it is no coincidence that the hardest racial group in which to prove membership was the White one.

The identification of Spanish-speaking countries in the Americas as "Latin America" was first promoted by supporters of [[Maximilian I of Mexico|Maximilian]], who had been installed as emperor of Mexico in 1864 by the French emperor [[Napoleon III]], as a way of extending French influence in the Americas. Since French and Spanish are both languages derived from Latin, the French identified Spanish-speakers as "Latin" in order to emphasize a fictive kinship with the French, and in the &amp;mdash; unfulfilled &amp;mdash; hope of legitimizing Maximilian.

The term "Hispanic" as an ethnonym emerged in the twentieth century with the rise of migration of laborers from Spanish-speaking countries to the United States; it thus includes people who had been considered racially distinct (Black, White, Amerindian) in their home countries.  Today, the word "Latino" is often used as a synonym for "Hispanic". In contrast to "Latino," "Anglo" is now used in a similar way to refer to the descendants of British colonists, and values and practices derived from British culture.

====Race Definitions in the United States====
{{main|Race (United States Census)}}
The [[United States]] government has provided definitions regarding race (see for example [[Race (U.S. Census)]]). Racial classification in the U.S. 2000 census was based solely on [[self-identification]], did not pre-suppose [[disjointedness]], and included a category "Hispanic," which is considered an [[ethnicity]], rather than a race, by the U.S. Census. The concept of race as used by the Census Bureau reflects self-identification by people according to the race or races with which they most closely identify. These categories are sociopolitical constructs and should not be interpreted as being scientific or anthropological in nature. They change from one census to another, and the racial categories include both racial and national-origin groups[http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/meta/long_68178.htm].

On the other hand, the [[EEOC]] explicitly defines Hispanics as a separate and distinct "race."&lt;ref&gt;See ''Employer Information Report EEO-1 and Standard Form 100'', Appendix § 4, Race/Ethnic Identification, 1 Empl. Prac. Guide (CCH) § 1881, (1981), 1625.[http://www.eeoc.gov/stats/jobpat/e1instruct.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Race in Brazil===
Compared to 19th-century United States, 20th-century [[Demographics of Brazil|Brazil]] was characterized by a relative absence of sharply defined racial groups. According to anthropologist Marvin Harris (1989) this pattern reflects a different history and different [[social relations]]. Basically, race in Brazil was "biologized," but in a way that recognized the difference between ancestry (which determines genotype) and [[phenotypic]] differences. There, racial identity was not governed by a rigid descent rule. A Brazilian child was never automatically identified with the racial type of one or both parents, nor were there only two categories to choose from. Over a dozen racial categories would be recognized in conformity with the combinations of hair color, hair texture, eye color, and skin color. These types grade into each other like the colors of the spectrum, and no one category stands significantly isolated from the rest. That is, race referred to appearance, not heredity.

Through this system of racial identification, parents and children and even brothers and sisters were frequently accepted as representatives of opposite racial types. In a fishing village in the state of [[Bahia]], an investigator showed 100 people pictures of three sisters and asked them to identify the races of each. In only six responses were the sisters identified by the same racial term. Fourteen responses used a different term for each sister. In another experiment nine portraits were shown to a hundred people. Forty different racial types were elicited. It was found, in addition, that a given Brazilian might be called by as many as thirteen different terms by other members of the community. These terms are spread out across practically the entire spectrum of theoretical racial types. A further consequence of the absence of a descent rule was that Brazilians apparently not only disagreed about the racial identity of specific individuals, but they also seemed to be in disagreement about the abstract meaning of the racial terms as defined by words and phrases. For example, 40% of a sample ranked ''moreno claro'' ("light" person of primarily European ancestry with dark hair) as a lighter type than ''mulato claro'' ("light" person of mixed European and African ancestry), while 60% reversed this order. A further note of confusion is that one person might employ different racial terms to describe the same person over a short time span. [For a solid discussion of Brazilian racial terms, see Livio Sansone's ''Blackness Without Ethnicity'' (2003) and France Winddance Twine's ''Racism in a Racial Democracy'' (1998).] The choice of which racial description to use may vary according to the relationship (be it personal, class-based, or otherwise) between the speaker and the person concerned and moods of the individuals involved. The [[Brazilian census]] lists one's race according to the preference of the person being interviewed. As a consequence, hundreds of races appeared in the census results, ranging from blue (which is blacker than the usual black) to green (which is whiter than the usual white).

So, although the identification of a person by race is far more fluid and flexible in Brazil than in the U.S., there still are racial stereotypes and prejudices. African features have been considered less desirable; Blacks have been considered socially inferior, and Whites superior. These white [[supremacist]] values seem to be an obvious legacy of European colonization and the slave-based [[plantation system]] (Some people argues that in Brazil the racial prejudice is linked to [[social prejudice]]). The complexity of racial classifications in Brazil is reflective of the extent of [[miscegenation]] in [[Brazilian society]], which remains highly, but not strictly, [[social stratification|stratified]] along color lines. Henceforth, the Brazilian [[narrative]] of a perfect "post-racist" country, composed of the "[[La Raza Cósmica|cosmic race]]" celebrated in 1925 by [[José Vasconcelos]], must be met with caution, as sociologist [[Gilberto Freyre]] demonstrated in 1933 in ''Casa Grande e Senzala''.

=== Race in politics and ethics ===

During [[the Enlightenment]], racial classifications were used to justify [[slavery|enslavement]] of those deemed to be of "inferior", non-White races, and thus supposedly best fitted for lives of toil under White supervision. These classifications made the distance between races seem nearly as broad as that between species, easing unsettling questions about the appropriateness of such treatment of humans. The practice was at the time generally accepted by both scientific and lay communities.

[[Arthur Gobineau]]'s ''[[An Essay on the Inequality of the Human Races]]'' (1853-1855) was one of the milestone in the new [[racist]] [[discourse]], along with [[Vacher de Lapouge]]'s "anthroposociology."  They posited the historical existence of national races such as German and French, branching from basal races supposed to have existed for millennia, such as the [[Aryan race|Aryan]] race, and believed political boundaries should mirror these supposed racial ones.

Later, one of [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]]'s favorite sayings was, "Politics is applied biology". It appears he knew a certain amount about politics, but considerably less about biology. Hitler's ideas of racial purity led to unprecedented atrocities in Europe.  Hitler and others enacted race laws used to persecute and murder millions of Jews, who were seen as a race.   Since then, [[ethnic cleansing]] has occurred in the [[Balkans]] and [[Rwandan Genocide|Rwanda]]. In one sense, ''ethnic cleansing'' is another name for the tribal warfare and mass murder that has afflicted human society for ages, but these crimes seem to gain intensity when believed to be scientifically sanctioned, although this may be purely an unjustified assertion arising from anti-scientific prejudice.

Racial inequality has been a concern of United States politicians and legislators since the country's founding. In the 19th century most White Americans (including [[abolitionist]]s) explained racial inequality as an inevitable consequence of biological differences. Since the mid-20th century, political and civic leaders as well as scientists have debated to what extent racial inequality is cultural in origin. Some argue that current inequalities between Blacks and Whites are primarily cultural and historical, the result of past racism, [[slavery]] and [[Racial segregation|segregation]], and could be redressed through such programs as [[affirmative action]] and [[Head Start]]. Others work to reduce tax funding of [[remedial programs]] for minorities. They have based their advocacy on aptitude test data that, according to them, shows that racial ability differences are biological in origin and cannot be leveled even by intensive educational efforts. In [[electoral politics]], many more ethnic minorities have won important offices in Western nations than in earlier times, although the highest offices tend to remain in the hands of Whites.

In his famous ''[[Letter from Birmingham Jail]]'', the Rev. Dr. [[Martin Luther King Jr.]] observed:  
:History is the long and tragic story of the fact that privileged groups seldom give up their privileges voluntarily. Individuals may see the moral light and voluntarily give up their unjust posture; but as [[Reinhold Niebuhr]] has reminded us, groups are more immoral than individuals.

Dr. King's hope, expressed in his [[I Have a Dream]] speech, was that the [[civil rights]] struggle would one day produce a society where people were not "judged by the color of their skin, but by the content of their character."

Because of the identification of the concept of race with political oppression, many natural and social scientists today are wary of using race to describe human variation. Some, however, argue that race is nevertheless of continuing utility and validity in scientific research. Science and politics frequently take opposite sides in debates that relate to human intelligence and biomedicine.

The concept of race is also based on mere [[conventions]], [[traditions]], [[statistics]], and an arbitrary number of [[categories]].  Often the partially unique individual human being is ignored.  The criteria used to divide up the human species is also arbitrary, and often only focuses on skin color, geographical area, and a very few genes.  The varied expression of the same mix of genes is rarely studied.  The exact percentage of exceptions to any probable group, or the margin of error can also be overlooked.  Other possible criteria of height, eye color, hair color, size of feet, and  so on indicate the primary and customary use of skin color to determine groups.

== Race in law enforcement ==
[[Image:RaceMugshots.jpg|thumb|210px|In the U.S., the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] [[anthropometry|identifies fugitives]] to categories they define as sex, physical features, occupation, nationality, and race. From left to right, the FBI assigns the above individuals to the following races: White, Black, Hispanic, Asian. Top row males, bottom row females.]]

In an attempt to provide general descriptions that may facilitate the job of [[law enforcement officer]]s seeking to apprehend suspects, the United States [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] employs the term "race" to summarize the general appearance (skin color, hair texture, eye shape, and other such easily noticed characteristics) of individuals whom they are attempting to apprehend. From the perspective of [[law enforcement]] officers, it is generally more important to arrive at a description that will readily suggest the general appearance of an individual than to make a scientifically valid categorization. Thus in addition to assigning a wanted individual to a racial category, such a description will include: height, weight, eye color, scars and other distinguishing characteristics, etc. [[Scotland Yard]] use a classification based in the ethnic background of [[British society]]: W1 (White-British), W2 (White-Irish), W9 (Any other white background); M1 (White and black Caribbean), M2 (White and black African), M3 (White and Asian), M9 (Any other mixed background); A1 (Asian-Indian), A2 (Asian-Pakistani), A3 (Asian-Bangladeshi), A9 (Any other Asian background); B1 (Black Caribbean), B2 (Black African), B3 (Any other black background); O1 (Chinese), O9 (Any other).

In many countries, the state is legally banned from maintaining data based on race, which often makes the police issue wanted notices to the public  that include labels like "dark skin complexion", etc. There is controversy over the actual relationship between crimes, their assigned punishments, and the division of people into the so called "races." In the United States, the practice of [[racial profiling]] has been ruled to be both [[unconstitutional]] and also to constitute a violation of [[civil rights]]. There is active debate regarding the cause of a marked correlation between the recorded crimes, punishments meted out, and the country's "racially divided" people. Many consider ''de facto'' [[racial profiling]] an example of [[institutional racism]] in law enforcement. 

More recent work in racial taxonomy based on DNA cluster analysis (See [[Lewontin's Fallacy]]) has led law enforcement to pursue suspects based on their racial classification as derived from their DNA evidence left at the crime scene [http://transobj.workopolis.com/servlet/Content/fasttrack/20050625/DNA25?section=Biotech]. While controversial, DNA analysis has been successful in helping police identify the race of both victims and perpetrators. [http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2005-08-16-dna_x.htm]. In an attempt to be less subjective, this classification is called "biogeographical ancestry" rather than "race"[http://appft1.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;p=1&amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsearch-bool.html&amp;r=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;co1=AND&amp;d=PG01&amp;s1=20040229231&amp;OS=20040229231&amp;RS=20040229231] , but the terms for the BGA categories are the same. The difference is that ancestry-informative DNA markers identify continent-of-ancestry admixture, not ethnic self-identity. Hence, they cannot match the U.S. "races". For example, the DNA of an Arab-American, an African-American, and a Hispanic of precisely the same Afro-European genetic admixture would be "racially" indistinguishable. And a "White" woman with, say, 25% African ancestry such as
[[Carol Channing]] would show exactly the same BGA as a "Black" man of the same admixture (like [[Gregory Howard Williams]]).

==See also==
*[[Breed]]
*[[Clan]]
*[[Species]]
*[[Political correctness]]
*[[Cultural difference]]
*[[Population genetics]]
*[[Pre-Adamite]]
*[[Race (historical definitions)]]
*[[Racial stereotypes]]
*[[Race and intelligence]]
*[[Race (fantasy)]]
*[[Race (U.S. census)|Race (US Census)]]
*[[Race in biomedicine]]
*[[Race baiting]]
*[[Race card]]
*[[Racial purity]]
*[[Racial discrimination]]
*[[Racial realism]]
*[[Racial superiority]]
*[[Pierre-André Taguieff]]
*[[The Race of the Future]]
*[[Subspecies]]
*[[Whiteness studies]]

==Footnotes==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

== Bibliography ==
&lt;div class="references-small" style="-moz-column-count:3; column-count:3;"&gt;
* Abizadeh A (2001) [http://www.profs-polisci.mcgill.ca/abizadeh/Ethnicity.htm "Ethnicity, Race, and a Possible Humanity"] ''World Order'' 33.1: 23-34.
* American Association of Physical Anthropologists (1996) AAPA statement on biological aspects of race. Am J Phys Anthropol 101:569–570
* Anonymous (1996) Style matters: ethnicity, race, and culture: guidelines for research, audit, and publication. BMJ 312:1094
* ——— (2000) Census, race, and science. Nat Genet 24:97–98
* ——— (2004) The unexamined "Caucasian." Nat Genet 36:541
* Banton M (1977) The idea of race. Westview Press, Boulder
* Bhopal R (1997) Is research into ethnicity and health racist, unsound, or important science? BMJ 314:1751–1756
* Boas 1912 "Change in Bodily Form of Descendants of Immigrants" in ''American Anthropologist'' 14: 530-562
* Bonham V, Warshauer-Baker E, Collins FS (2005) The complexity of the constructs. Am Psychol 60:9–15   
* Bowler JM, Johnston H, Olley JM, Prescott JR, Roberts RG, Shawcross W, Spooner NA (2003) New ages of human occupation and climatic change at Lake Mungo, Australia. Nature 421:837–840 
* Brace 1964 "A Non-racial Approach Toward the Understanding of Human Diversity" in ''The Concept of Race'', ed. Ashley Montagu
* Braun L (2002) Race, ethnicity, and health: can genetics explain disparities? Perspect Biol Med 45:159–174
* Brodwin P (2002) Genetics, identity, and the anthropology of essentialism. Anthropol Quart 75:323–330
* Burchard EG, Ziv E, Coyle N, Gomez SL, Tang H, Karter AJ, Mountain JL, Perez-Stable EJ, Sheppard D, Risch N (2003) The importance of race and ethnic background in biomedical research and clinical practice. N Engl J Med 348:1170–1175   
* Calafell F (2003) Classifying humans. Nat Genet 33:435–436  
* Calle EE, Kaaks R (2004) Overweight, obesity and cancer: epidemiological evidence and proposed mechanisms. Nat Rev Cancer 4:579–591 * Caspari, Rachel 2003 "From Types to Populations: a Century of Race, Physical Anthropology, and the American Anthropological Association," in ''American Anthropologist'' 105(1): 65-76
* Cardon LR, Palmer LJ (2003) Population stratification and spurious allelic association. Lancet 361:598–604 
* [[Luigi Luca Cavalli-Sforza|Cavalli-Sforza, Luigi Luca]]; et al (1995). ''[[The History and Geography of Human Genes]]''. Princeton University Press.
* Collins-Schramm HE, ''et al.'', (2004) Mexican American ancestry-informative markers: examination of population structure and marker characteristics in European Americans, Mexican Americans, Amerindians and Asian. Human Genetics 114:263-71 
* Cooper RS, Kaufman JS, Ward R (2003) Race and genomics. N Engl J Med 348:1166–1170
* Dobzhansky, T. (1970). ''Genetics of the Evolutionary Process''. New York, NY: Columbia University Press.
* ——— (2005) Race and reification in science. Science 307:1050–1051
* Ehrlich and Holm 1964 "A Biological View of Race" in The Concept of Race, ed. Ashley Montagu
* Frayer, David, M. Wolpoff, A. Thorne, F. Smith, G. Pope "Theories of Modern Origins: The Paleontological Test" ''in American Anthropologist'' 95(1) 14-50
* Gluckman PD, Hanson MA (2004) Living with the past: evolution, development, and patterns of disease. Science 305:1733–1736
* Goldstein DB, Chikhi L (2002) Human migrations and population structure: what we know and why it matters. Ann Rev Genomics Hum Genet 3:129–152
* Guthrie RD (1996) The mammoth steppe and the origin of mongoloids and their dispersal. In: Akazawa T, Szathmary E (eds) Prehistoric Mongoloid dispersals. Oxford University Press, New York, pp 172–186
* Hannaford I (1996) Race: the history of an idea in the West. Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore
* Harpending H, Rogers A (2000) Genetic perspectives on human origins and differentiation. Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet 1:361–385
* Harris, Marvin (1980) Patterns of Race in the Americas.  Greenwood Press    
* Hooton, E.A. (1926). Methods of racial analysis. ''Science'' 63, 75&amp;ndash;81.
* Hutchinson J, Smith AD (eds) (1996) Ethnicity. Oxford University Press, New York
* Jablonski NG (2004) The evolution of human skin and skin color. Annu Rev Anthropol 33:585–623
* Keita SOY, Kittles RA (1997) The persistence of racial thinking and the myth of racial divergence. Am Anthropol 99:534–544
* Klein RG (1999) The human career: human biological and cultural origins, 2nd ed. University of Chicago Press, Chicago
* Krings M, Stone A, Schmitz RW, Krainitzki H, Stoneking M, Pääbo S (1997) Neandertal DNA sequences and the origin of modern humans. Cell 90:19–30
* Lahr MM (1996) The evolution of modern human diversity: a study of cranial variation. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom
* Lahr MM, Foley RA (1998) Towards a theory of modern human origins: geography, demography, and diversity in recent human evolution. Am J Phys Anthropol Suppl 27:137–176
* Lamason RL, Mohideen MA, Mest JR, Wong AC, Norton HL, Aros MC, Jurynec MJ, Mao X, Humphreville VR, Humbert JE, Sinha S, Moore JL, Jagadeeswaran P, Zhao W, Ning G, Makalowska I, McKeigue PM, O'donnell D, Kittles R, Parra EJ, Mangini NJ, Grunwald DJ, Shriver MD, Canfield VA, Cheng KC (2005). SLC24A5, a putative cation exchanger, affects pigmentation in zebrafish and humans. Science 310: 1782-6.
* LaVeist TA (1996) Why we should continue to study race...but do a better job: an essay on race, racism and health. Ethn Dis 6:21–29
* ——— (ed) (2002) Race, ethnicity, and health. Jossey-Bass, San Francisco
* Lee SS, Mountain J, Koenig BA (2001) The meanings of "race" in the new genomics: implications for health disparities research. Yale J Health Policy Law Ethics 1:33–75
* Lewis B (1990) Race and slavery in the Middle East. Oxford University Press, New York
* Li WH, Sadler LA (1991) Low nucleotide diversity in man. Genetics 129:513–523
* Lieberman DE, McBratney BM, Krovitz G (2002) The evolution and development of cranial form in Homo sapiens. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 99:1134–1139
* Lieberman L (2001) How "Caucasoids" got such big crania and why they shrank: from Morton to Rushton. Curr Anthropol 42:69–95
* Leiberman and Jackson 1995 "Race and Three Models of Human Origins" in ''American Anthropologist'' 97(2) 231-242
* Lieberman, Hampton, Littlefield, and Hallead 1992 "Race in Biology and Anthropology: A Study of College Texts and Professors" in ''Journal of Research in Science Teaching'' 29:301-321
* Lewontin 1973 "The Apportionment of Human Diversity" in ''Evolutionary Biology'' 6:381-397
* Lin SS, Kelsey JL (2000) Use of race and ethnicity in epidemiologic research: concepts, methodological issues, and suggestions for research. Epidemiol Rev 22:187–202
* Livingstone 1962 "On the Non-Existence of Human Races" in ''Current Anthropology'' 3: 279-281
* Lohmueller KE, Pearce CL, Pike M, Lander ES, Hirschhorn JN (2003) Meta-analysis of genetic association studies supports a contribution of common variants to susceptibility to common disease. Nat Genet 33:177–182
* Long, J.C. and Kittles, R.A. (2003). Human genetic diversity and the nonexistence of biological races. ''Hum Biol.'' 75, 449&amp;ndash;71. [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=14655871]
* Mahoney MC, Michalek AM (1998) Health status of American Indians/Alaska natives: general patterns of mortality. Fam Med 30:190–195
* Marchini J, Cardon LR, Phillips MS, Donnelly P (2004) The effects of human population structure on large genetic association studies. Nat Genet 36:512–517
* Marks J (1995) Human biodiversity: genes, race, and history. Aldine de Gruyter, New York
* Mayr, E. (1969). ''Principles of Systematic Zoology''. New York, NY: McGraw-Hill.
* Mays VM, Ponce NA, Washington DL, Cochran SD (2003) Classification of race and ethnicity: implications for public health. Annu Rev Public Health 24:83–110
* McDougall I, Brown FH, Fleagle JG (2005) Stratigraphic placement and age of modern humans from Kibish, Ethiopia. Nature 433:733–736
* McKeigue PM (2005) Prospects for admixture mapping of complex traits. Am J Hum Genet 76:1–7
* Meltzer M (1993) Slavery: a world history, rev ed. DaCapo Press, Cambridge, MA
* Miller GH, Magee JW, Johnson BJ, Fogel ML, Spooner NA, McCulloch MT, Ayliffe LK (1999) Pleistocene extinction of Genyornis newtoni: human impact on Australian megafauna. Science 283:205–208
* Montagu (1941). "The Concept of Race in Light of Genetics" in ''Journal of Heredity'' 23: 241-247
* Montagu (1942). ''Man’s Most Dangerous Myth: The Fallacy of Race''
* Morales-Díaz, Enrique, and Gabriel Aquino, and Michael Sletcher, ‘Ethnicity’, in Michael Sletcher, ed., ''New England'', (Westport, CT, 2004).
* Mörner M (1967) Race mixture in the history of Latin America. Little, Brown, Boston
* Morton NE, Collins A (1998) Tests and estimates of allelic association in complex inheritance. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 95:11389–11393
* Mosse GL (1985) Toward the final solution, 2nd ed. University of Wisconsin Press, Madison
* Nobles M (2000) Shades of citizenship: race and the census in modern politics. Stanford University Press, Stanford
* Nordborg M (1998) On the probability of Neanderthal ancestry. Am J Hum Genet 63:1237–1240
* Nordborg M, Tavare S (2002) Linkage disequilibrium: what history has to tell us. Trends Genet 18:83–90
* Ohno S (1996) The Malthusian parameter of ascents: what prevents the exponential increase of one's ancestors? Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 93:15276–15278
* Olson S (2002) Mapping human history. Houghton Mifflin, Boston
* Oppenheimer GM (2001) Paradigm lost: race, ethnicity, and the search for a new population taxonomy. Am J Public Health 91:1049–1055
* Ossorio P, Duster T (2005) Controversies in biomedical, behavioral, and forensic sciences. Am Psychol 60:115–128
* Ota Wang V, Sue S (2005) In the eye of the storm: race and genomics in research and practice. Am Psychol 60:37–45
* Page GP, George V, Go RC, Page PZ, Allison DB (2003) "Are we there yet?": Deciding when one has demonstrated specific genetic causation in complex diseases and quantitative traits. Am J Hum Genet 73:711–719 
* Parra EJ, Kittles RA, Shriver MD (2004) Implications of correlations between skin color and genetic ancestry for biomedical research. Nat Genet 36:S54–S60
* Parra EJ, Marcini A, Akey J, Martinson J, Batzer MA, Cooper R, Forrester T, Allison DB, Deka R, Ferrell RE, Shriver MD (1998) Estimating African American admixture proportions by use of population-specific alleles. Am J Hum Genet 63:1839–1851
* Parra FC, Amado RC, Lambertucci JR, Rocha J, Antunes CM, Pena SD (2003) Color and genomic ancestry in Brazilians. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 100:177–182 [http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=140919]
* Patterson N, Hattangadi N, Lane B, Lohmueller KE, Hafler DA, Oksenberg JR, Hauser SL, Smith MW, O'Brien SJ, Altshuler D, Daly MJ, Reich D (2004) Methods for high-density admixture mapping of disease genes. Am J Hum Genet 74:979–1000
* Pfaff CL, Barnholtz-Sloan J, Wagner JK, Long JC (2004) Information on ancestry from genetic markers. Genet Epidemiol 26:305–315
* Platz EZ, Rimm EB, Willett WC, Kantoff PW, Giovannucci E (2000) Racial variation in prostate cancer incidence and in hormonal system markers among male health professionals. J Natl Cancer Inst 92:2009–2017
* Pritchard JK (2001) Are rare variants responsible for susceptibility to complex diseases? Am J Hum Genet 69:124–137
* Pritchard JK, Cox NJ (2002) The allelic architecture of human disease genes: common disease-common variant...or not? Hum Mol Genet 11:2417–2423
* Provine WB (1986) Geneticists and race. Am Zoologist 26:857–887
* Rawlings JS, Weir MR (1992) Race- and rank-specific infant mortality in a US military population. Am J Dis Child 146:313–316
* Rees JL (2003) Genetics of hair and skin color. Annu Rev Genet 37:67–90
* Reich DA, Lander ES (2001) On the allelic spectrum of human disease. Trends Genet 17:502–510
* Relethford JH (2002) Apportionment of global human genetic diversity based on craniometrics and skin color. Am J Phys Anthropol 118:393–398
* Risch N (2000) Searching for the genetic determinants in a new millennium. Nature 405:847–856
* Risch N, Burchard E, Ziv E, Tang H (2002) Categorization of humans in biomedical research: genes, race and disease. Genome Biol 3 (http://genomebiology.com/2002/3/7/comment/2007) (electronically published July 1, 2002; accessed August 25, 2005)
* Rivara F, Finberg L (2001) Use of the terms race and ethnicity. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med 155:119
* Rohde D, Olson S, Chang J (2004) Modeling the recent common ancestry of all living humans. Nature 431:562–566
* Roseman CC (2004) Detecting interregionally diversifying natural selection on modern human cranial form by using matched molecular and morphometric data. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 101:12824–12829
* Rosenberg NA, Pritchard JK, Weber JL, Cann HM, Kidd KK, Zhivotovsky LA, Feldman MW (2002) Genetic structure of human populations. Science 298:2381–2385 [http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/ijlink?linkType=ABST&amp;journalCode=sci&amp;resid=298/5602/2381]
* Rotimi CN (2004) Are medical and nonmedical uses of large-scale genomic markers conflating genetics and "race"? Nat Genet 36:S43–S47
* Sallout B, Walker M (2003) The fetal origin of adult diseases. J Obstet Gynaecol 23:555–560
* Sarich, Vincent, and Frank Miele. ''Race: The Reality of Human Differences''.  Westview Press, 2004.
* Satta Y, Takahata N (2002) Out of Africa with regional interbreeding? Modern human origins. Bioessays 24:871–875
* Schwartz M, Vissing J (2002) Paternal Inheritance of Mitochondrial DNA.  N Engl J Med 347:576-580
* Serre D, Langaney A, Chech M, Teschler-Nicola M, Paunovic M, Mennecier P, Hofreiter M, Possnert G G, Pääbo S (2004) No evidence of Neandertal mtDNA contribution to early modern humans. PLoS Biol 2:313–317
* Shields AE, Fortun M, Hammonds EM, King PA, Lerman C, Rapp R, Sullivan PF (2005) The use of race variables in genetic studies of complex traits and the goal of reducing health disparities: a transdisciplinary perspective. Am Psychol 60:77–103
* Shipler D (1997) A country of strangers: blacks and whites in America. Knopf, New York
* Shostak S (2003) Locating gene-environment interaction: at the intersections of genetics and public health. Soc Sci Med 56:2327–2342
* Shriver, M. D. ''et al.'' (2003). Skin pigmentation, biogeographical ancestry, and admixture mapping. ''Hum. Genet.'' 112, 387–399. [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=12579416]
* Sider, Gerald 1993 ''Lumbee Indian Histories: Race, Ethnicity, and Indian Identity in the Southern United States''
* Smedley A (1999) Race in North America: origin and evolution of a worldview, 2nd ed. Westview Press, Boulder
* Smelser N, Wilson WJ, Mitchell F (eds) (2001) America becoming: racial trends and their consequences. Vol 2. National Academy Press, Washington, DC
* Smith DJ, Lusis AJ (2002) The allelic structure of common disease. Hum Mol Genet 11:2455–2461
* Smith, Fred 1982 "Upper Pleistocene Hominid Evolution in South-Central Europe: A Review of the Evidence and Analysis of Trends" ''Current Anthropology'' 23: 667-686
* Smith MW, Patterson N, Lautenberger JA, Truelove AL, McDonald GJ, Waliszewska A, Kessing BD, et al (2004) A high-density admixture map for disease gene discovery in African Americans. Am J Hum Genet 74:1001–1013
* Snowden FM (1983) Before color prejudice: the ancient view of blacks. Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA
* Spickard PR (1992) The illogic of American racial categories. In: Root MPP (ed) Racially mixed people in America. Sage, Newbury Park, CA, pp 12–23
* Stanton W (1960) The leopard's spots: scientific attitudes toward race in America, 1815–1859. University of Chicago Press, Chicago
* Stevens J (2003) Racial meanings and scientific methods: changing policies for NIH-sponsored publications reporting human variation. J Health Polit Policy Law 28:1033–1087
* Stringer C (2002) Modern human origins: progress and prospects. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci 357:563–579
* Sturm RA, Teasdale RD, Box NF (2001) Human pigmentation genes: identification, structure and consequences of polymorphic variation. Gene 277:49–62
* Swisher CC 3rd, Curtis GH, Jacob T, Getty AG, Suprijo A, Widiasmoro (1994) Age of the earliest known hominids in Java, Indonesia. Science 263:1118–1121
* Takahata N, Lee S, Satta Y (2001) Testing multiregionality of modern human origins. Mol Biol Evol 18:172–183
* Takaki R (1993) A different mirror: a history of multicultural America. Little, Brown, Boston
* Tang H, Quertermous T, Rodriguez B, Kardia SL, Zhu X, Brown A, Pankow JS, Province MA, Hunt SC, Boerwinkle E, Schork NJ, Risch NJ (2005). Genetic structure, self-identified race/ethnicity, and confounding in case-control association studies. ''Am J Hum Genet'' 76, 268-75. [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15625622]
* Tate SK, Goldstein DB (2004) Will tomorrow's medicines work for everyone? Nat Genet 36:S34–S42
* Templeton AR (1998) Human races: a genetic and evolutionary perspective. Am Anthropol 100:632–650
* ——— (2002) Out of Africa again and again. Nature 416:45–51
* Thienpont, Kristiaan and Cliquet, Robert (eds.) In-group/out-group gedrag in evolutiebiologisch perspectief, Leuven : Garant, 1999. ISBN 90-5350-970-4
* Thomas DC, Witte JS (2002) Point: population stratification: a problem for case-control studies of candidate-gene associations? Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 11:505–512
* Thorne and Wolpoff 1992 "The Multiregional Evolution of Humans" in Scientific American (April) 76-83
* Tishkoff SA, Kidd KK (2004) Implications of biogeography of human populations for "race" and medicine. Nat Genet 36:S21–S27
* Tishkoff SA, Pakstis AJ, Stoneking M, Kidd JR, Destro-Bisol G, Sanjantila A, Lu R-b, Deinard AS, Sirugo G, Jenkins T, Kidd KK, Clark AG (2000) Short tandem-repeat polymorphism/Alu haplotype variation at the PLAT locus: implications for modern human origins. Am J Hum Genet 67:901–925
* Tishkoff SA, Verrelli B (2003) Patterns of human genetic diversity: implications for human evolutionary history and disease. Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet 4:293–340
* Tishkoff SA, Williams SM (2002) Genetic analysis of African populations: human evolution and complex disease. Nat Rev Genet 3:611–621
* Todorov T (1993) On human diversity. Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA
* Trinkaus E, Milota S, Rodrigo R, Mircea G, Moldovan O (2003) An early modern human from the Pestera cu Oase, Romania. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 100:11231–11236
* Underhill PA, Underhill PA, Shen P, Lin AA, Jin L, Passarino G, Yang WH, Kauffman E, Bonne-Tamir B, Bertranpetit J, Francalacci P, Ibrahim M, Jenkins T, Kidd JR, Mehdi SQ, Seielstad MT, Wells RS, Piazza A, Davis RW, Feldman MW, Cavalli-Sforza LL, Oefner PJ (2000) Y chromosome sequence variation and the history of human populations. Nat Genet 26:358–361
* Vega WA, Amaro H (1994) Latino outlook: good health, uncertain prognosis. Annu Rev Public Health 15:39–67
* Venter JC, Adams MD, Myers EW, Li PW, Mural RJ, Sutton GG, Smith HO, et al (2001) The sequence of the human genome. Science 291:1304–1351
* Wacholder S, Rothman N, Caporaso N (2002) Counterpoint: bias from population stratification is not a major threat to the validity of conclusions from epidemiological studies of common polymorphisms and cancer. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 11:513–520
* Wall JD (2000) Detecting ancient admixture in humans using sequence polymorphism data. Genetics 154:1271–1279
* Wallace R, Wallace D, Wallace RG (2004) Coronary heart disease, chronic inflammation, and pathogenic social hierarchy: a biological limit to possible reductions in morbidity and mortality. J Natl Med Assoc 96:609–619
* Waters M (1990) Ethnic options: choosing identities in America. University of California Press, Berkeley
* Weatherall D (1999) From genotype to phenotype: genetics and medical practice in the new millennium. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci 354:1995–2010
* White TD, Asfaw B, DeGusta D, Gilbert H, Richards GD, Suwa G, Howell FC (2003) Pleistocene Homo sapiens from Middle Awash, Ethiopia. Nature 423:742–747
* Whyatt RM, Rauh V, Barr DB, Camann DE, Andrews HF, Garfinkel R, Hoepner LA, Diaz D, Dietrich J, Reyes A, Tang D, Kinney PL, Perera FP (2004) Prenatal insecticide exposures and birth weight and length among an urban minority cohort. Environ Health Perspect 112:1125–1132
* Wiencke JK (2004) Impact of race/ethnicity on molecular pathways in human cancer. Nat Rev Cancer 4:79–84
* Wilson JF, Weale ME, Smith AC, Gratrix F, Fletcher B, Thomas MG, Bradman N, Goldstein DB (2001) Population genetic structure of variable drug response. Nat Genet 29:265–269
* Wilson and Brown 1953 "The Subspecies Concept and Its Taxonomic Application" in ''Systematic Zoology'' 2: 97-110
* Wolpoff, Milford 1993 "Multiregional Evolution: The Fossil Alternative to Eden" in The Human Evolution Sourcebook Russell Ciochon and John Fleagle, eds.
* Wolpoff M, Caspari R (1997) Race and human evolution: a fatal attraction. Simon &amp; Schuster, New York
* Wolpoff M, Hawks J, Frayer DW, Hunley K (2001) Modern human ancestry at the peripheries: a test of the replacement theory. Science 291:293–297
* Yu N, Chen FC, Ota S, Jorde LB, Pamilo P, Patthy L, Ramsay M, Jenkins T, Shyue SK, Li WH (2002) Larger genetic differences within Africans than between Africans and Eurasians. Genetics 161:269–274
&lt;/div&gt;

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}

=== Review articles ===

* [http://genomebiology.com/2002/3/7/comment/2007 Categorization of humans in biomedical research: genes, race and disease] - Neil Risch, ''et al.'' [http://scbe.stanford.edu/events/pdfs/genomebio.pdf PDF]
* [http://www.fiu.edu/~biology/pcb5665/RACEgen.pdf Deconstructing the relationship between genetics and race] - Michael Bamshad, ''et al.''
* [http://www.pubmedcentral.gov/articlerender.fcgi?tool=pubmed&amp;pubmedid=16175499 The use of racial, ethnic, and ancestral categories in human genetics research] -- The Race, Ethnicity, and Genetics Working Group of the National Human Genome Research Institute
*[http://www.lrainc.com/swtaboo/stalkers/jpr01.html "Race as a Biological Concept"] by [[J. Philippe Rushton]]
*[http://www.behavior.org/journals_BP/2002/Levin.pdf The Race Concept: A Defense] by Michael Levin
* [http://www.nature.com/cgi-taf/dynapage.taf?file=/ng/journal/v36/n11s/index.html Genetics for the Human Race] ''Nature Genetics'' supplement, September 2004, Vol 36, Issue 11s.
*  [http://www.ornl.gov/sci/techresources/Human_Genome/elsi/minorities.shtml US Human Genome Project on "Issues of Race"]
* OMB Statistical Directive 15, [http://www.doi.gov/diversity/doc/racedata.htm "Standards for Maintaining, Collecting, and Presenting Federal Data on Race and Ethnicity"], ''Federal Register'', [[30 October]] [[1997]].
* The Importance of Race and Ethnic Background in Biomedical Research and Clinical Practice - Esteban González Burchard, ''et al.'' [http://scbe.stanford.edu/events/pdfs/burchard.pdf PDF]

=== Research papers ===

* Sandra Soo-Jin Lee, Joanna Mountain, and Barbara A. Koenig,  [http://academic.udayton.edu/health/08Research/research01.htm "The Reification of Race in Health Research"]
* Michael Root, [http://philsci-archive.pitt.edu/archive/00001094/ "The Use of Race in Medicine as a Proxy for Genetic Differences"]
* [http://www.pubmedcentral.gov/articlerender.fcgi?tool=pubmed&amp;pubmedid=15625622 Genetic Structure, Self-Identified Race/Ethnicity, and Confounding in Case-Control Association Studies]
* [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=12493913&amp;query_hl=2 "Genetic structure of human populations"], Feldman et al, ''Science''.  - "Self-reported population ancestry likely provides a suitable proxy for genetic ancestry." 
*[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=16357253&amp;query_hl=10 Discovery of the human skin color gene SLC24A5]

=== Popular press ===

* [[Richard Dawkins]]: [http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=6467 Race and creation] (extract from [[The Ancestor's Tale]]: A Pilgrimage to the Dawn of Life) - On race, its usage and a theory of how it evolved. ([http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/ Prospect Magazine] October 2004) (see also [http://www.amren.com/mtnews/archives/2004/09/race_and_creati.php# longer extract here])
* [http://www.pbs.org/race Race - The power of an illusion] Online companion to California Newsreel's 3-part documentary about race in society, science, and history.
* [http://raceandgenomics.ssrc.org/ Is Race "Real"?] - forum organized by the [[Social Science Research Council]], includes a [http://raceandgenomics.ssrc.org/Leroi/ March 2005 op-ed article by A.M. Leroi from the ''New York Times''] advocating biological conceptions of race and responses from scholars in a variety of fields. - [http://www.edge.org/3rd_culture/leroi05/leroi05_index.html More from Leori with responses]
* Steven and Hilary Rose, The Guardian, [http://www.politics.guardian.co.uk/life/science/story/0,12996,1455716,00.html "Why we should give up on race"], [[9 April]] [[2005]]
* Times Online, [http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,8122-1331319,00.html "Gene tests prove that we are all the same under the skin"], [[27 October]] [[2004]].
* Michael J. Bamshad, Steve E. Olson [http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?chanID=sa006&amp;colID=1&amp;articleID=00055DC8-3BAA-1FA8-BBAA83414B7F0000  "Does Race Exist?"], ''Scientific American'', December 2003
* [http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/20/health/20GENE.html "Gene Study Identifies 5 Main Human Populations, Linking Them to Geography"], Nicholas Wade, ''NYTimes'', December 2002.  Covering 
*[http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?chanID=sa006&amp;articleID=00055DC8-3BAA-1FA8-BBAA83414B7F0000 Scientific American Magazine (December 2003 Issue) Does race exists ?].
* [http://www.upi.com/view.cfm?StoryID=15042002-084051-5356r DNA Study published by United Press International showing how 30% of White Americans have at least one Black ancestor]
* Yehudi O. Webster [http://multiracial.com/site/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=213&amp;Itemid=39 Twenty-one Arguments for Abolishing Racial Classification], ''The Abolitionist Examiner'', June 2000

=== Others ===
* [http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/meta/long_68184.htm US Census Bureau: Definition of Race]
*[http://www.southwestern.edu/~greenmue/boas.htm Boas's remarks on race to a general audience]
*[http://www.news-medical.net/?id=9530 Race differences in average IQ are largely genetic, 26-Apr-2005]
* Catchpenny mysteries of ancient Egypt, [http://www.catchpenny.org/race.html "What race were the ancient Egyptians?"], Larry Orcutt.
* Judy Skatssoon, [http://www.abc.net.au/science/news/stories/s1153697.htm "New twist on out-of-Africa theory"], ''ABC Science Online'', Wednesday, [[14 July]] [[2004]].
* [http://www.bloodbook.com/world-abo.html Racial &amp; Ethnic Distribution of ABO Blood Types] - bloodbook.com
*[http://www.snpa.nordish.net/racesofeurope.htm "The Races of Europe" by Carleton S. Coon] - collection of physical anthropolgical data on the indigenous European populations.
*[http://www.jonentine.com/reviews/daily_mail_uk.htm Are White Athletes an Endangered Species? And Why is it Taboo to Talk About It?] Discussion of racial differences in athletics
*[http://kennethomura.tripod.com/asian_genes/ Asian Genes] This website discusses the genetic distance of different Asian groups.&lt;!-- This website is important to this page because it explains the statements about Asian genetics made on this page.--&gt;

&lt;!-- en-US --&gt;

[[Category:Kinship and descent]]
[[Category:Race]]
[[Category:Scientific classification]]
[[Category:Social inequality]]
[[Category:Taxonomy]]

[[bg:Раса]]
[[ca:Raça]]
[[da:Race]]
[[de:Großrasse]]
[[de:Rasse]]
[[es:Raza (biología)]]
[[es:Raza]]
[[eo:Raso]]
[[hr:Rasa]]
[[id:Ras manusia]]
[[he:גזע (אדם)]]
[[lt:Rasė]]
[[nl:Ras (mensheid)]]
[[nl:dierenras]]
[[ja:人種]]
[[no:Menneskerase]]
[[no:Rase]]
[[pl:Rasa]]
[[pt:Raça]]
[[ru:Раса]]
[[fi:Rotu]]
[[sv:Ras]]
[[tr:Irk]]
[[uk:Раса]]
[[zh:种族]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>