<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131118042934|582153560" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="240058" pageid="240058" ns="0" title="Masculinity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-18T04:40:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Masculine|other uses|Masculine (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect|Manliness|the book by Harvey Mansfield|Manliness (book)}}
{{Multiple issues
 | citation style=May 2010
 | cleanup=May 2010
 | tone=May 2010
 | original research=May 2010
 | refimprove=May 2010
}}
[[File:Landsdowne Herakles.jpg|thumb|In Greek mythology, [[Heracles]] is synonymous with [[Apollonian]] masculinity.]]

'''Masculinity''' is a set of qualities, characteristics or roles generally considered typical of, or appropriate to, a man. It can have degrees of comparison: "more masculine", "most masculine'". The opposite can be expressed by terms such as "unmanly'" or ''[[epicene]]''.&lt;ref name=Roget&gt;
''[[Roget's Thesaurus|Roget’s II: The New Thesaurus]]'', 3rd. ed., [[Houghton Mifflin]], 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; A near-[[synonym]] of masculinity is ''[[virility]]'' (from Latin ''[[:la:vir|vir]]'', man). Constructs of masculinity vary across historical and cultural contexts. The [[dandy]], for instance, was regarded as an ideal of masculinity in the 19th century, but is considered [[Effeminacy|effeminate]] by modern standards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Reeser|first=Todd|title=Masculinities in Theory: An Introduction|year=2010|pages=1–3|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=1444358537|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=YMnn8Zf0heoC&amp;dq=reeser+masculinities+in+theory&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Academic]] study of masculinity underwent a massive expansion of interest in the late 1980s and early 1990s, with courses in the United States dealing with masculinity rising from 30 to over 300.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Bradley|first=Rolla M.|title=Masculinity and Self Perception of Men Identified as Informal Leaders|year=2008|publisher=ProQuest|isbn=0549473998|pages=9|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=8MiVG4T2_eYC&amp;dq=gurian+masculinity&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt; This has led to the investigation of the intersection of  masculinity with other axes of social discrimination and also to the use of concepts from other fields – such as feminism's model of the social construct of gender.&lt;ref name="Flood 2007 Viii"&gt;{{cite book|last=Flood|first=Michael|title=International Encyclopaedia of Menand Masculinities|year=2007|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0415333431|pages=Viii|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EUON2SYps-QC&amp;dq=academic+masculinity&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Nature versus nurture==
The extent to which masculinity is a result of [[nature versus nurture|nature or nurture]], a matter of what someone is born with or how they are [[socialization|socialised]], has been the subject of much debate. [[Genome]] research has yielded much information about the development of masculine characteristics and the process of [[sexual differentiation]] specific to the reproductive system of  [[human]] beings.. The [[SRY gene]] on the [[Y chromosome]], which is critical for male sexual development, activates [[SOX9]].&lt;ref name="Moniot"&gt;{{cite journal | last=Moniot | first=Brigitte | last2=Declosmenil | first2=Faustine | last3=Barrionuevo | first3=Francisco | last4=Scherer | first4=Gerd | last5=Aritake | first5=Kosuke | last6=Malki | first6=Safia | last7=Marzi | first7=Laetitia | last8=Cohen-Solal | first8=Ann | last9=Georg | first9=Ina | last10=Klattig | first10=Jürgen | last11=Englert | first11=Christoph | last12=Kim | first12=Yuna | last13=Capel | first13=Blanche | last14=Eguchi | first14=Naomi | last15=Urade | first15=Yoshihiro | last16=Boizet-Bonhoure | first16=Brigitte | last17=Poulat | first17=Francis | year=2009 | title=The PGD2 pathway, independently of FGF9, amplifies SOX9 activity in Sertoli cells during male sexual differentiation| journal=Development| volume=136| issue=11| pages=1813–1821| publisher=The Company of Biologists Ltd. | pmid=19429785 | doi=10.1242/dev.032631}}&lt;/ref&gt; SOX9 associates with [[SF1 (gene)|Sf1]] to increase the level of [[Anti-Müllerian hormone]] to repress female development while activating and forming a feedforward loop with [[FGF9]], which creates the [[testis cords]] and is responsible for the proliferation of [[sertoli cell]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid | 16700629}}&lt;/ref&gt; The activation of SRY interferes with the process of creating a female, causing a chain of events that leads to [[testes]] formation, [[androgen]] production, and a range of pre-natal and post-natal hormonal effects. There is an extensive debate about how children develop [[gender identity|gender identities]]. On the nature side of the debate, it is argued that masculinity is inextricably linked with the male body. In this view, masculinity is something that is associated with the [[male|biological male sex]] and having [[human penis|male genitalia]], for instance, is regarded as a key aspect of masculinity.&lt;ref name="Reeser 2010 3"&gt;{{cite book|last=Reeser|first=Todd|title=Masculinities in Theory: An Introduction|year=2010|page=3|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=1444358537|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=YMnn8Zf0heoC&amp;dq=reeser+masculinities+in+theory&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Others have suggested that while masculinity may be influenced by biological factors, it is also culturally constructed. Proponents of this view argue that women can become men [[Hormone replacement therapy (female-to-male)|hormonally]] and [[Sex reassignment surgery|physically]] &lt;ref name="Reeser 2010 3"/&gt; and that many aspects that are assumed to be natural are linguistically and therefore culturally driven.{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} On the nurture side of the debate, it is argued that masculinity does not have a single source of origin or creator such as the [[Mass media|media]], certain [[institutions]], or certain groups of people. While the [[military]], for example, has a vested interest in constructing and promoting a specific form of masculinity, it does not create it from scratch and masculinity has influenced the creation of the military in the first place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Reeser|first=Todd|title=Masculinities in Theory: An Introduction|year=2010|pages=17–21|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=1444358537|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=YMnn8Zf0heoC&amp;dq=reeser+masculinities+in+theory&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, as an example of socialisation into masculinity, facial hair has been linked to masculinity through language, in such forms as stories about boys becoming men when they start to shave.&lt;ref name="Reeser 2010 30–31"&gt;{{cite book|last=Reeser|first=Todd|title=Masculinities in Theory: An Introduction|year=2010|pages=30–31|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=1444358537|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=YMnn8Zf0heoC&amp;dq=reeser+masculinities+in+theory&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hegemonic masculinity==
{{Main|Hegemonic masculinity}}
[[Image:USMC-10881.jpg|thumb|250px|Direct competition of physical skill and strength is a feature of masculinity which appears in some form in virtually every culture on Earth. Here, two [[United States Marine Corps|U.S. Marines]] compete in a [[wrestling]] match.]]

Traditional avenues for men to gain honor were that of providing adequately for their families and exercising leadership.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;George, A., "Reinventing honorable masculinity" Men and Masculinities&lt;/ref&gt; Connell has labelled the traditional male roles and privileges [[hegemonic masculinity]]. This is the norm, something that men are expected to aspire to and that women are discouraged from adopting. According to Connell: “Hegemonic masculinity can be defined as the configuration of [[gender]] practice which embodies the currently accepted answer to the problem of the legitimacy of [[patriarchy]], which guarantees the dominant position of men and the subordination of women.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Connell|first=R.W.|title=Masculinities|year=1995, 2005|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|pages=77}}&lt;/ref&gt;  (Connell, 2001)

==Critics of masculinity==
It is a subject of debate whether masculinity concepts followed historically should still be applied. However, researchers have argued that there is a harmful current of masculine criticism related to the following:
*The reshaping of contemporary values that traditional masculists uphold.
* The gender war feminist groups have been waging on traditional masculinity values and roles.
* Cultural hostilities that society has placed on masculine values.
* The promotion of masculinity in women and the pressuring of men to become more feminized.

The images of boys and young men presented in the media may lead to the persistence of harmful concepts of masculinity. Men's rights activists argue that the media does not pay serious attention to men's rights issues and that men are often portrayed in a negative light, particularly in advertising.&lt;ref&gt;Farrell, W. &amp; Sterba, J. P. (2008) Does Feminism Discriminate Against Men: A Debate (Point and Counterpoint), New York: Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

Scholar Peter Jackson writes that  the dominant forms of masculinity can be "economically exploitative" and socially oppressive." He asserts, "the form of oppression varies from patriarchal controls over women's bodies and reproductive rights, through ideologies of domesticity, femininity and compulsory heterosexuality, to social definitions of the value of work, the nature of skill and the differential remuneration of 'productive' and reproductive' labor."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title = The Cultural Politics of Masculinity: Towards a Social Geography | journal = Transactions of the Institute of British Geographers | year = 1991 | first = Peter | last = Jackson | volume = 16 | issue = 2 | pages = 199–213 | accessdate = 2013-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Masculine gender role stress===
In 1987, Eisler and Skidmore did studies on masculinity and created the idea of 'masculine stress'. They found three mechanisms of masculinity that accompany masculine gender role often result in emotional stress. They include:

* The emphasis on prevailing in situations requiring body and fitness
* Being perceived as emotional
* The need to feel adequate in regard to sexual matters and financial status

Because of social norms and pressures associated with masculinity, Men with spinal cord injuries have to adapt their self-identity to the losses associated with SCI which may “lead to feelings of decreased physical and sexual prowess with lowered self-esteem and a loss of male identity. Feelings of guilt and overall loss of control are also experienced.”&lt;ref&gt;Hutchinson, Susan L "Heroic masculinity following spinal cord injury: Implications for therapeutic recreation practice and research". Therapeutic Recreation Journal. FindArticles.com. 07 Apr, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Masculinity is something that some{{Who|{{subst:DATE=June 2013}}|date=June 2013}} fear is becoming increasingly challenged, especially in the last century, with the emergence of [[Women's rights]] and the development of the role of women in society.{{Citation needed|No source is provided indicating that women's rights is the reason that "some" (previous weasel word) men feel challenged, nor is this supposed perception of a challenge referenced by a reliable source. As such, the sentence as a whole is unsubstantiated conjecture |date=June 2013}} In recent years many 'Man Laws' and similar [[masculinist]] manifestos have been published, as a way for men to re-affirm their masculinity. A popular example is the Miller Lite [[Man Laws]], and other various sites on the internet offering rules such as: "15. A real man does not need instruction manuals."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.fuckingmanly.com/man-rules|title= List of Man Law Rules/Rules for Men |publisher= Fucking Manly|accessdate=2009-08-20}}{{dead link|date=March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although many of these rules are offered in a humorous fashion, they attempt to define masculinity, and indicate that proper gender is taught and performed rather than intuited.

Research also suggests that men feel social pressure to endorse traditional masculine male models in advertising. Research by Martin and Gnoth (2009) found that feminine men preferred feminine models in private, but stated a preference for the traditional masculine models when their collective self was salient. In other words, when concerned about being classified by other men as feminine, feminine men endorsed traditional masculine models. The authors suggested this result reflected the social pressure on men to endorse traditional masculine norms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Martin | first1 = Brett A. S. | last2 = Gnoth | first2 = Juergen | author-separator =, | author-name-separator= | year = 2009 | title = Is the Marlboro Man the Only Alternative? The Role of Gender Identity and Self-Construal Salience in Evaluations of Male Models | url = http://www.basmartin.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/Martin-Gnoth-2009.pdf | format = PDF | journal = Marketing Letters | volume = 20 | issue = | pages = 353–367 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

An emerging discourse regarding masculinities in relation to other men has emerged and relates to a man's social status and political power. Dr. Joseph Pleck&lt;ref name="nomas.org"&gt;http://www.nomas.org/node/176&lt;/ref&gt; explains that there is an inherent system of relations in male-to-male relationships within North American patriarchal society. Hierarchies are demarcated by levels of masculinity which are equated to physical composition when men are young, and the acquisition of wealth and women when men age.&lt;ref name="nomas.org"/&gt;

Pleck argues that the hierarchy of masculinities among men exist largely in a dichotomy of homo/heterosexual males and explains that "our society uses the male heterosexual-homosexual dichotomy as a central symbol for all the rankings of masculinity, for the division on any grounds between males who are "real men" and have power, and males who are not".&lt;ref name="nomas.org"/&gt; Kimmel &lt;ref&gt;Kimmel, Michael S., and Summer Lewis. Mars and Venus, Or, Planet Earth?: Women and Men in a New Millenium [sic]. Kansas State University, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; furthers this notion and adds that the trope "you're so gay" indicates that one is devoid of masculinity, rather than being sexually attracted to members of the same sex. Pleck argues that to avoid the continuation of male oppression of women and themselves and other men, patriarchal structures, institutions, and discourse must be eliminated from North American society.

In the [[New York Times]] bestselling book, ''Raising Cain: Protecting The Emotional Life of Boys'' authors [[Dan Kindlon]] and Michael Thompson argue that although all boys are born as loving and empathetic creatures, their exposure to gender socialization, specifically to the tough male ideal and [[hypermasculinity]], invalidates the male character and limits the ability for boys and men to function as healthy emotional adults. The authors argue that boys lack the ability to understand and express emotions productively because of the stress of masculine gender roles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Barker|first=Dan Kindlon, Michael Thompson with Teresa|title=Raising Cain : protecting the emotional life of boys|year=2000|publisher=Ballantine Books|location=New York|isbn=0-345-43485-4|pages=1-20|edition=1st trade pbk. ed.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Notion of "masculinity in crisis"===
A mounting discourse of "masculinity in crisis" has emerged arguing that masculinity is in a state of crisis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Horrocks|first=Rooger|title=Masculinities in Crisis: Myths, Fantasies, and Realities|year=1994|publisher=St Martin's Press|isbn=0333593227|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=k24dAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=masculinity+crisis&amp;dq=masculinity+crisis&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=YEEfUc-dI5L24QTBhIHwCA&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAQ}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Marked Men: White Masculinity in Crisis |last= Robinson |first= Sally |authorlink= |year= 2000 |publisher= [[Columbia University Press]] |location= New York |isbn= 978-0-231-50036-4 |page= 5 |pages= |accessdate= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, Australian archeologist Peter McAllister stated, "I have a strong feeling that masculinity is in crisis. Men are really searching for a role in modern society; the things we used to do aren't in much demand anymore".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rogers| first = Thomas| title = The dramatic decline of the modern man|url=http://www.salon.com/2010/11/14/manthropology_interview/singleton/|newspaper = [[Salon (website)|Salon]]|date = November 14, 2010|accessdate = June 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others see the changing labor market as a source of the alleged crisis. [[Deindustrialization]] and the replacement of old [[Smokestack industry|smokestack industries]] with new technologies has allowed more women to enter the labor force and reduced the demand for great physical strength.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| ref=harv| last = Beynon| first = John| authorlink =| title = Masculinities and culture| url =| publisher = [[Open University Press]]| location = Philadelphia | year = 2002| chapter = Chapter 4: Masculinities and the notion of 'crisis'| chapterurl =| pages = 86–89| isbn = 978-0-335-19988-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The supposed crisis has also been frequently attributed to [[feminism]] and a resulting questioning both of men's dominance over women and the rights which had been granted to men solely on the basis of their sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| ref=harv| last = Beynon| first = John| authorlink =| title = Masculinities and culture| url =| publisher = [[Open University Press]]| location = Philadelphia | year = 2002| chapter = Chapter 4: Masculinities and the notion of 'crisis'| chapterurl =| pages = 83–86| isbn = 978-0-335-19988-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; British sociologist John MacInnes argued that "masculinity has always been in one crisis or another" and suggested that the crises arise from the "fundamental incompatibility between the core principle of modernity that all human beings are essentially equal (regardless of their sex) and the core tenet of patriarchy that men are naturally superior to women and thus destined to rule over them."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = MacInnes | first = John | authorlink = | title = The end of masculinity: the confusion of sexual genesis and sexual difference in modern society | year = 1998 | publisher = Open University Press | location = Philadelphia | page = 11 | isbn = 978-0-335-19659-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Academic John Beynon examined the discourse surrounding the notion of masculinity in crisis and found that masculinity and men are often confused and conflated so that it remains unclear whether masculinity, men, or both are supposed to be in crisis.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| ref=harv
| last = Beynon
| first = John
| authorlink =
| title = Masculinities and culture
| url =
| publisher = [[Open University Press]]
| location = Philadelphia
| year = 2002
| chapter = Chapter 4: Masculinities and the notion of 'crisis'
| chapterurl =
| pages = 76
| isbn = 978-0-335-19988-4
}}&lt;/ref&gt; He further argues that the alleged crisis is not a recent phenomenon and points out several periods of masculine crisis throughout history, many of which predate the women's movement and [[Post-industrial society|post-industrial societies]]. He suggests that due to the fact that masculinity is always changing and redefined, "crisis is constitutive of masculinity itself."&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| ref=harv
| last = Beynon
| first = John
| authorlink =
| title = Masculinities and culture
| url =
| publisher = [[Open University Press]]
| location = Philadelphia
| year = 2002
| chapter = Chapter 4: Masculinities and the notion of 'crisis'
| chapterurl =
| pages = 89–93
| isbn = 978-0-335-19988-4
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Film scholar Leon Hunt contends in the same vein, "Whenever masculinity's 'crisis' actually started, it certainly seems to have been in place by the 1970s".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Hunt | first = Leon | year = 1998 | title = British low culture: from safari suits to sexploitation | publisher = [[Routledge]] | location = London, New York | page = 73 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=3dvtQEetWrsC&amp;pg=PA73 | isbn = 978-0-415-15182-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Western trends==
[[File:Model-sixpack.jpg|thumb|left|Male model with muscular body.]]
According to a paper submitted by [[Tracy Tylka]] to the [[American Psychological Association]] (APA), in contemporary America: "Instead of seeing a decrease in [[objectification]] of women in society, there has just been an increase in the objectification of both sexes. And you can see that in the media today." Men and women restrict their food intake in an effort to achieve what they consider an attractively thin body, in extreme cases leading to [[eating disorder]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://researchnews.osu.edu/archive/maleobj.htm Pressure To Be More Muscular May Lead Men To Unhealthy Behaviors]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Thomas Holbrook]], also a psychiatrist, cites a recent Canadian study indicating as many as one in six of those with eating disorders were men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?sec=health&amp;res=9F02EED7133EF936A15755C0A9669C8B63 | work=The New York Times | title=Thinner: The Male Battle With Anorexia | first=Erica | last=Goode | date=2000-06-25 | accessdate=2010-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

"Younger men and women who read fitness and fashion magazines could be psychologically harmed by the images of perfect female and male physiques," according to recent research in the United Kingdom. Some young women and men exercise excessively in an effort to achieve what they consider an attractively fit and muscular body, which in extreme cases can lead to [[body dysmorphic disorder]] or [[muscle dysmorphia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/7318411.stm | work=BBC News | title=Magazines 'harm male body image' | date=2008-03-28 | accessdate=2010-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.askmen.com/sports/bodybuilding/56_fitness_tip.html Muscle dysmorphia – AskMen.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livescience.com/health/060815_bodyimage_men.html Men Muscle in on Body Image Problems | LiveScience&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the actual stereotypes may have remained relatively constant, the value attached to masculine stereotypes have changed over the past few decades and it has been argued that masculinity is an unstable phenomenon and never ultimately achieved.&lt;ref name="Reeser 2010 30–31"/&gt;

[[File:Construction workers not wearing fall protection equipment.jpg|thumb|right|Male construction workers without appropriate fall protection equipment.]]

===Risk-taking===
The driver crash rate per vehicle miles driven is higher for women than for men; although, men are much more likely to cause deaths in the accidents they are involved in.&lt;ref&gt;Johns Hopkins School Of Public Health (1998, June 18). [http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/1998/06/980618032130.htm Women Not Necessarily Better Drivers Than Men.] ScienceDaily.&lt;/ref&gt; Men drive significantly more miles than women, so, on average, they are more likely to be involved in [[road traffic accident|motor vehicle accident]]s. Even in the narrow category of  young (16–20) driver fatalities with a high [[blood alcohol content]] (BAC), a male's risk of dying is higher than a female's risk at the Same BAC level.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-nrd.nhtsa.dot.gov/Pubs/98.010.PDF Crash Data and Rates for Age-Sex Groups of Drivers, 1996], Ezio C. Cerrelli, January 1998, National Center for Statistics &amp; Analysis – Research &amp; Development&lt;/ref&gt; That is, young women drivers need to be more drunk to have the same risk of dying in a fatal accident as young men drivers.

===Health care===
A growing body of evidence is pointing toward the deleterious impact of masculinity (and hegemonic masculinity in particular) on men's health help-seeking behaviour.&lt;ref&gt;Galdas P.M., Cheater F. &amp; Marshall P. (2005) Men and health help-seeking behaviour: Literature review. Journal of Advanced Nursing, 49, 616–23&lt;/ref&gt; American men make 134.5 million fewer physician visits than American women each year. In fact, men make only 40.8% of all physician visits, that is, if women's visits for pregnancy are included, childbirth and associated obstetrical and gynecological visits. A quarter of the men who are 45 to 60 do not have a personal physician. Many men should go to annual heart checkups with physicians but do not, increasing their risk of death from [[heart disease]]. Men between the ages of 25 and 65 are four times more likely to die from [[cardiovascular disease]] than women. Men are more likely to be diagnosed in a later stage of a [[terminal illness]] because of their reluctance to go to the doctor.

Reasons men give for not having annual physicals and not visiting their physician include [[fear]], [[denial]], [[embarrassment]], a dislike of situations out of their control, or not worth the time or cost.

====Media encouragement====
Arran Stibbe (2004) analysed issues of a prominent men's health magazine in the year 2000, and claimed that while ostensibly being focused on health, the magazine also promoted hegemonic (traditional) masculinity. These potentially damaging male behaviors included the excessive consumption of convenience foods and meats, drinking of alcohol, and unsafe sex.

[[File:A Soldier Drinks a Pint of Beer on his Return from Afghanistan MOD 45152497.jpg|thumb|left|A British soldier drinking beer upon his return from Afghanistan.]]

====Alcohol consumption behavior====
Research on beer commercials by [[Lance Strate|Strate]] (Postman, Nystrom, Strate, And Weingartner 1987; Strate 1989, 1990) and by Wenner (1991) show some results relevant to studies of masculinity. In beer commercials, the ideas of masculinity (especially risk-taking) are presented and encouraged. The commercials often focus on situations where a man is overcoming an obstacle in a group. The men will either be working hard or playing hard. For instance the commercial will show men who do physical labor such as construction workers, or farm work, or men who are [[cowboy]]s. Beer commercials that involve playing hard have a central theme of mastery (over nature or over each other), risk, and adventure. For instance, the men will be outdoors [[fishing]], [[camping]], playing sports, or hanging out in [[bar (establishment)|bars]]. There is usually an element of [[Risk|danger]] as well as a focus on movement and speed. This appeals to and emphasizes the idea that real men overcome danger and enjoy speed (i.e. fast cars/driving fast). The bar serves as a setting for the measurement of masculinity (skills like [[billiards|pool]], [[physical strength|strength]] and drinking ability) and serves as a center for male socializing.

==History==
Concepts of masculinity have varied according to time and place and are constantly subject to change and thus, argues Connell, it is more appropriate to talk of masculinities than of a single masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Connell|first=R. W.|title=Masculinities|year=2005|publisher=Polity|isbn=0745634273|pages=185|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=YuR2uFxxvPoC&amp;dq=masculinity+historical&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ancient===
[[File:Odysseus sehnt sich nach Ithaka (Tischbein).jpg|thumb|right|[[Odysseus]], the hero of the ''Odyssey''.]]
"''Viri autem propria maxime est fortitudo''." Cicero, ''[[Tusculanae Quaestiones]]'', 1:11:18.

In translation, [[Cicero]] states: "a man's chief quality is [[courage]]."
Ancient [[literature]] goes back to about 3000 BC. It includes both explicit statements of what was expected of men in [[law]]s, and implicit suggestions about masculinity in [[myth]]s involving [[god]]s and [[hero]]es. In 1000 BC, the [[Hebrew Bible]] states King David of Israel told his son "Be strong, and be a man" upon David's death. Men throughout history have gone to meet exacting cultural standards of what is considered attractive. Kate Cooper, writing about ancient understandings of femininity, suggests that, "Wherever a woman is mentioned a man's character is being judged – and along with it what he stands for."&lt;ref&gt;
Kate Cooper, [http://books.google.com/books?id=QVvn8vUMZdIC&amp;pg=PA19&amp;lpg=PA19&amp;dq=%22wherever+a+woman+is+mentioned+a+man's+character+is+being+judged%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=lYAXvJa29I&amp;sig=LvrybebcK9gPm4PaJWe5934jD5Y ''The Virgin and The Bride: Idealized Womanhood in Late Antiquity'',] (Cambridge, Massachusetts: [[Harvard University Press]], 1996), p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; One well-known representative of this literature is the ''[[Code of Hammurabi]]'' (from about 1750 BC).
*Rule 3: "If any one bring an accusation of any crime before the elders, and does not prove what he has charged, he shall, if it be a capital offense charged, be put to death."
*Rule 128: "If a man takes a woman to wife, but has no intercourse with her, this woman is no wife to him."&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.wsu.edu/~dee/MESO/CODE.HTM ''The Code of Hammurabi''], translated by LW King, 1910.&lt;/ref&gt;
Scholars suggest [[integrity]] and [[social equality|equality]] as masculine values in male-male relationships,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bassi | first1 = Karen | author-separator =, | author-name-separator= | year = 2001 | title = Acting like Men: Gender, Drama, and Nostalgia in Ancient Greece | url = | journal = Classical Philology | volume = 96 | issue = | pages = 86–92 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and virility in male-female relationships. [[Legend]]s of ancient heroes include ''[[Epic of Gilgamesh|The Epic of Gilgamesh]]'', the ''[[Iliad]]'' and the ''[[Odyssey]]''. Such narratives are considered to reveal qualities in the hero that inspired [[respect]], like [[wisdom]] or [[courage]], the knowing of things that other men do not know and the taking of [[risk]]s that other men would not dare.

[[File:Beowulf and the dragon.jpg|thumb|left|Beowulf fighting the dragon.]]

===Medieval===
[[Jeffrey Richards]] describes a European, "medieval masculinity which was essentially Christian and chivalric."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Richards Jeffrey | year = 1999 | title = From Christianity to Paganism: The New Middle Ages and the Values of 'Medieval' Masculinity | url = http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/bpl/cuva/1999/00000003/00000002/art00057 | journal = Cultural Values | volume = 3 | issue = | pages = 213–234 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Again ethics, courage, respect towards women of all classes, and generosity are seen as characteristic of the portrayal of men  in literary history. The [[Anglo Saxon]]s [[Hengest]] and [[Horsa]]{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} and [[Beowulf]] are famous examples of medieval ideals of masculinity. Rosen argues that the traditional view of scholars such as [[J. R. R. Tolkien]] that ''Beowulf'' is a tale of medieval [[heroism]] overlooks the many similarities in description of both Beowulf and Grendel, the monster. Beowulf's masculinity is seen to "cut men off from women, other men, passion and the household".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rosen|first=David|title=The Changing Fictions of Masculinity|year=1993|publisher=University of Illinois Press|isbn=0252063090|pages=11|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=pXgBaWrB4OYC&amp;dq=beowulf+masculinity&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Victorian===
{{Main|Victorian masculinity}}

In the [[Victorian era]] of [[Great Britain]], masculinities were undergoing a transformation from their traditional 'heroic' scripts.  As the Scottish philosopher [[Thomas Carlyle]] wrote in 1831:

{{cquote|The old ideal of Manhood has grown obsolete, and the new is still invisible to us, and we grope after it in darkness, one clutching this phantom, another that; [[The Sorrows of Young Werther|Werterism]], [[Byron]]ism, even [[Beau Brummell|Brummelism]], each has its day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Adams|first=James Eli|title=Dandies and Desert Saints: Styles of Victorian Masculinity|year=1995|publisher=Cornell University Press|isbn=0801482089|pages=1|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=f7gwHwyxZJ4C&amp;dq=victorian+masculinity&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[File:Wwii woman worker-edit.jpg|thumb|right|A female aircraft worker during World War II.]]

===Modern times===
{{further| Model of masculinity under fascist Italy}}
At the beginning of the twentieth century, the traditional family structure consisted of the [[father]] as the bread-winner and the [[mother]] as the [[homemaker]].  Other examples of modern masculinity shifting radically from the masculinities of Victorian and earlier times include the willingness of men to defy stereotypes. For example, regardless of age or nationality, men more frequently rank [[health|good health]], harmonious family life and good relationships with their spouse or partner as important to their quality of life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tricitypsychology.com/blog/men-defy-stereotypes-in-defining-masculinity/ Men defy stereotypes in defining masculinity], August 26, 2008, Tri-City Psychology Services&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==
{{Section OR|date=December 2007}}

[[File:PalmercarpenterA.jpg|thumb|A construction worker.]]

In many cultures, displaying characteristics not typical to one's gender may become a social problem for the individual. Within [[sociology]] such labeling and conditioning is known as [[gender role|gender assumptions]], and is a part of [[socialization]] to better match a culture's [[mores]]. Among men, some non-standard behaviors may be considered a sign of [[homosexuality]], which frequently runs contrary to cultural notions of masculinity. When sexuality is defined in terms of object choice, as in early [[sexology]] studies, male homosexuality is interpreted as [[feminine]] sexuality. The corresponding social condemnation of excessive masculinity may be expressed in terms such as ''[[machismo]]'' or ''[[testosterone poisoning]]''.

The relative importance of the roles of socialization and genetics in the development of masculinity continues to be debated. While [[social conditioning]] obviously plays a role, some, such as [[Innate_bisexuality|Sigmund Freud]] and [[Anima_and_animus|Carl Jung]], hold that certain aspects of the 'feminine' and 'masculine' identity instinctively exist at subconscious levels in males of all human cultures.
The historical development of gender role is addressed by such fields as [[behavioral genetics]], [[evolutionary psychology]], [[human ecology]], [[anthropology]] and [[sociology]]. All human [[culture]]s seem to encourage the development of gender roles, through [[literature]], [[costume]] and [[song]]. Some examples of this might include the epics of [[Homer]], [[Hengest]] and [[Horsa]] tales in English, the [[Norm (philosophy)|normative]] commentaries of [[Confucius]]. More specialized treatments of masculinity may be found in works such as the [[Bhagavad Gita]] or [[bushidō]]'s [[Hagakure]].

Another term for a masculine woman is ''[[Butch and femme|butch]]'', which is associated with [[lesbian]]ism. ''Butch'' is also used within the lesbian community, without a negative connotation, but with a more specific meaning (Davis and Lapovsky Kennedy, 1989).

==See also==
{{multicol}}
*[[Bear (gay culture)]]
*[[Bromance]]
*[[Castro clone]]
*[[Emasculation]]
*[[Gender role]]
*[[Hegemonic masculinity]]

*[[Men's spaces]]
*[[Men's liberation]]
*[[Mens rights]]
*[[Men's movement]]
*[[Men's World Day]]
*[[Model of masculinity under fascist Italy]]
*[[Mythopoetic men's movement]]
*[[Philandry]]
*[[Raewyn Connell]]
*[[Victorian masculinity]]
{{multicol-end}}

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|2}}

;Bibliography
*{{cite book
| ref=harv
| last = Beynon
| first = John
| authorlink =
| title = Masculinities and culture
| url =
| publisher = [[Open University Press]]
| location = Philadelphia
| year = 2002
| chapter = Chapter 4: Masculinities and the notion of 'crisis'
| chapterurl =
| pages = 75–97
| isbn = 978-0-335-19988-4
}}
*{{cite book
| ref=harv
| last = Reeser
| first = Todd W.
| authorlink =
| editor-first =
| editor-last =
| title = Masculinities in theory: an introduction
| url = 
| publisher = [[Wiley-Blackwell]]
| location = Malden, MA
| year = 2010
| chapter = 
| chapterurl = 
| isbn = 978-1-4051-6859-5
}}
*{{cite book
| last = Connell
| first = R.W.
| title = The Social Organization of Masculinity
| url = 
| publisher = Polity
| location = Berkeley and Los Angeles, California
| year = 2001
| chapter = 3
| isbn = 978-0-520-24698-0
}}
*Levine, Martin P. (1998). ''Gay Macho''. New York: New York University Press. ISBN 0-8147-4694-2.
*Stibbe, Arran. (2004). "Health and the Social Construction of Masculinity in Men's Health Magazine." Men and Masculinities; 7 (1) July, pp.&amp;nbsp;31–51.
*[[Lance Strate|Strate, Lance]] "Beer Commercials: A Manual on Masculinity" Men's Lives Kimmel, Michael S. and Messner, Michael A. ed. Allyn and Bacon. Boston, London: 2001

==Further reading==
;Present situation
*Arrindell, Willem A., Ph.D. (1 October 2005) "Masculine Gender Role Stress" Psychiatric Times Pg. 31
*Ashe, Fidelma (2007) The New Politics of Masculinity, London and New York: Routledge.
* [[bell hooks]], ''We Real Cool: Black Men and Masculinity'', Taylor &amp; Francis 2004, ISBN 0-415-96927-1
*Broom A. and Tovey P. (Eds) Men’s Health: Body, Identity and Social Context London; John Wiley and Sons Inc.
*Burstin, Fay "What's Killing Men". Herald Sun (Melbourne, [[Australia]]). October 15, 2005.
*Canada, Geoffrey "Learning to Fight" Men's Lives Kimmel, Michael S. and Messner, Michael A. ed. Allyn and Bacon. Boston, London: 2001
*{{cite book | last = Connell | first = R.W. | author-link = Raewyn Connell | title = Masculinities | publisher = Polity Press | location = Cambridge | year = 2005 | isbn = 0745634273 }}
*Courtenay, Will "Constructions of masculinity and their influence on men's well-being: a theory of gender and health" Social Science and Medicine, yr: 2000 vol: 50 iss: 10 pg: 1385–1401
* {{cite book | last = Donovan | first = Jack | author-link = Jack Donovan | title = The way of men | publisher = Dissonant Hum | location = Milwaukie, Oregon | year = 2012 | isbn = 9780985452308 }}
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Durham | first1 = Meenakshi G. | last2 = Oates | first2 = Thomas P. | authorlink1 = Meenakshi Gigi Durham | title = The mismeasure of masculinity: the male body, 'race' and power in the enumerative discourses of the NFL Draft | journal = Patterns of Prejudice | volume = 38 | issue = 3 | pages = 301–320 | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis Online | doi = 10.1080/0031322042000250475 | year = 2004 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/0031322042000250475 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
*Galdas P.M. and Cheater F.M. (2010) Indian and Pakistani men’s accounts of seeking medical help for angina and myocardial infarction in the UK: Constructions of marginalised masculinity or another version of hegemonic masculinity? Qualitative Research in Psychology
* Juergensmeyer, Mark (2005): ''Why guys throw bombs. About terror and masculinity'' [http://web.fu-berlin.de/gpo/pdf/juergensmeyer/juergensmeyer_e.pdf (pdf)]
*Kaufman, Michael "The Construction of Masculinity and the Triad of Men's Violence". Men's Lives Kimmel, Michael S. and Messner, Michael A. ed. Allyn and Bacon. Boston, London: 2001
*Levant &amp; Pollack (1995) A New Psychology of Men, New York: BasicBooks
*[[Harvey Mansfield|Mansfield, Harvey]]. ''[[Manliness (book)|Manliness]]''. New Haven: [[Yale University Press]], 2006. ISBN 0-300-10664-5
* Reeser, T. ''Masculinities in Theory'', Malden: Wiley-Blackwell, 2010.
*Robinson, L. (October 21, 2005). Not just boys being boys: Brutal hazings are a product of a culture of masculinity defined by violence, aggression and domination. Ottawa Citizen (Ottawa, Ontario).
*Stephenson, June (1995). ''Men are Not Cost Effective: Male Crime in America.'' ISBN 0-06-095098-6
*Simpson, Mark (1994). Male Impersonators: Men Performing Masculinity. New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-41590991-0. Also published by Cassell, London, ISBN 0-304-32808-1 pbk,
* Walsh, Fintan. Male Trouble: Masculinity and the Performance of Crisis. Basingstoke and New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2010.
*Williamson P. "Their own worst enemy" Nursing Times: 91 (48) 29 November 95 p 24–7
*Wray Herbert "Survival Skills" U.S. News &amp; World Report Vol. 139, No. 11; Pg. 63 September 26, 2005
*[http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0014/001465/146514e.pdf "Masculinity for Boys"; published by UNESCO, New Delhi, 2006; ]
*Smith, Bonnie G., Hutchison, Beth. Gendering Disability.  Rutgers University Press, 2004.

;History
*[[Michael Kimmel]], Manhood in America, New York [etc.]:  The Free Press    1996
*A Question of Manhood: A Reader in U.S. Black Mens History and Masculinity, edited by Earnestine Jenkins and Darlene Clark Hine, Indiana University press vol1: 1999, vol. 2: 2001
*Gary Taylor, Castration: An Abbreviated History of Western Manhood, Routledge 2002
*[[Klaus Theweleit]], Male fantasies, Minneapolis : University of Minnesota Press, 1987 and Polity Press, 1987
*Peter N. Stearns, Be a Man!: Males in Modern Society, Holmes &amp; Meier Publishers, 1990
*Shuttleworth, Russell. "Disabled Masculinity." Gendering Disability.  Ed. Bonnie G. Smith and Beth Hutchison.  Rutgers University Press, New Brunswick, New Jersey, 2004. 166–178.

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{wiktionary|masculinity}}
'''Bibliographic'''
*[http://mensbiblio.xyonline.net/ The Men's Bibliography], a comprehensive bibliography of writing on men, masculinities, gender and sexualities, listing over 16,700 works. (mainly from a constructionist perspective)
*[http://www.boyhoodstudies.com Boyhood Studies], features a 2200+ bibliography of young masculinities.
'''Other'''
* [http://www.practicalmanliness.com Practical Manliness], A manly blog that applies "historical ideals to modern men".
*[http://www.mkpchicago.org The ManKind Project of Chicago], supporting men in leading meaningful lives of integrity, accountability, responsibility, and emotional intelligence
*[http://menanddepression.nimh.nih.gov/ NIMH web pages on men and depression], talks about men and their depression and how to get help.
* [http://howellgroup.org/parsifal.html Article entitled "Wounded Masculinity: Parsifal and The Fisher King Wound"] The symbolism of the story as it relates to the Wounded Masculinity of Men by Richard Sanderson M.Ed., B.A.
*[http://www.bullmensfiction.com BULL], Print and online literary journal specializing in masculine fiction for a male audience.
* [http://www.artofmanliness.com Art of Manliness], An online web magazine/blog dedicated to "reviving the lost art of manliness".
* [http://masculinityconspiracy.com The Masculinity Conspiracy], An online book critiquing constructions of masculinity.
* [http://www.udemy.com/futuremasculinity Future Masculinity], An online course critiquing constructions of masculinity.
{{Masculism}}

[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Gender roles]]
[[Category:Masculinity| ]]
[[Category:Men]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>