<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101114155620|396721862" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="240058" pageid="240058" ns="0" title="Masculinity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-15T16:36:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues
 | citation style=May 2010
 | cleanup=May 2010
 | tone=May 2010
 | original research=May 2010
 | refimprove=May 2010
}}
{{Redirect|Masculine|other uses|Masculine (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect|Manliness|the book by Harvey Mansfield|Manliness (book)}}
[[File:Landsdowne Herakles.jpg|thumb|In Greek mythology, [[Heracles]] is synonymous with [[Apollonian]] masculinity.]]

'''Masculinity''' is [[man]]ly character. It can describe anyone, that is personal and human, unlike ''[[male]]'' which can also be used to describe animals, or ''[[masculine (grammar)|masculine]]'' which can also be used to describe noun classes. When ''masculine'' is used to describe men, it can have degrees of comparison—''more masculine'', ''most masculine''. The opposite can be expressed by terms such as ''unmanly'', ''[[epicene]]'' or ''Saskatchewanesque''.&lt;ref name=Roget&gt;
''[[Roget's Thesaurus|Roget’s II: The New Thesaurus]]'', 3rd. ed., [[Houghton Mifflin]], 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;
A typical near-[[synonym]] of masculinity is ''[[virility]]'' (from Latin ''[[:la:vir|vir]]'', man);&lt;ref name=Roget /&gt;
and the usual [[Complement (linguistics)|complement]] is ''[[femininity]].''&lt;ref name=Roget /&gt;

== Literature review ==
=== Ancient ===

[[Cicero]] wrote that "a man's chief quality is [[courage]]."&lt;ref&gt;
"''Viri autem propria maxime est fortitudo''." Cicero, ''[[Tusculanae Quaestiones]]'', 1:11:18.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ancient [[literature]] goes back  to about 3000 BC. It includes both explicit statements of what was expected of men in [[law]]s, and implicit suggestions about masculinity in [[myth]]s involving [[god]]s and [[hero]]es. Men throughout history have gone to meet exacting cultural standards of what is considered attractive. Kate Cooper, writing about ancient understandings of femininity, suggests that, "Wherever a woman is mentioned a man's character is being judged — and along with it what he stands for."&lt;ref&gt;
Kate Cooper, [http://books.google.com/books?id=QVvn8vUMZdIC&amp;pg=PA19&amp;lpg=PA19&amp;dq=%22wherever+a+woman+is+mentioned+a+man's+character+is+being+judged%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=lYAXvJa29I&amp;sig=LvrybebcK9gPm4PaJWe5934jD5Y ''The Virgin and The Bride: Idealized Womanhood in Late Antiquity'',] (Cambridge, Massachusetts: [[Harvard University Press]], 1996), p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;  One well-known representative of this literature is the ''[[Code of Hammurabi]]'' (from about 1750 BC).
*Rule 3: "If any one bring an accusation of any crime before the elders, and does not prove what he has charged, he shall, if it be a capital offense charged, be put to death."
*Rule 128: "If a man takes a woman to wife, but has no intercourse with her, this woman is no wife to him."&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.wsu.edu/~dee/MESO/CODE.HTM ''The Code of Hammurabi''], translated by LW King, 1910.&lt;/ref&gt;
Scholars suggest [[integrity]] and [[social equality|equality]] as masculine values in male-male relationships,&lt;ref&gt;
Karen Bassi, ['Acting like Men: Gender, Drama, and Nostalgia in Ancient Greece', ''Classical Philology'' '''96''' (2001): 86-92.]&lt;/ref&gt; and virility in male-female relationships. [[Legend]]s of ancient heroes include: ''[[Epic of Gilgamesh|The Epic of Gilgamesh]]'', the ''[[Iliad]]'' and the ''[[Odyssey]]''. Such narratives are considered to reveal qualities in the hero that inspired [[respect]], like [[wisdom]] or [[courage]], the knowing of things that other men do not know and the taking of [[risk]]s that other men would not dare.

=== Medieval ===

[[Jeffrey Richards]] describes a European, "medieval masculinity which was essentially Christian and chivalric."&lt;ref&gt;Jeffrey Richards, [http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/bpl/cuva/1999/00000003/00000002/art00057 'From Christianity to Paganism: The New Middle Ages and the Values of ‘Medieval’ Masculinity,'] ''Cultural Values'' '''3''' (1999): 213-234.&lt;/ref&gt; Again ethics, courage and generosity are seen as characteristic of the portrayal of men in literary history. In Anglo Saxon, ''[[Beowulf]]'' and, in several languages, the legends of [[King Arthur]] are famous examples of medieval ideals of masculinity. The documented ideals include many examples of an "exaulted" place for women, in romance and [[courtly love]].

==Masculine physical attributes==
[[Image:Lewis Hine Power house mechanic working on steam pump.jpg|thumb|right|During the first half of the twentieth century, men were often associated with images of [[industrialization]]]]

Some research has indicated that a number{{Clarify|date=February 2009}} of women may be aroused by broad chins and shoulders, high cheekbones, and find large eyes as the most attractive, though there are cultural differences in those preferences. Some research has also indicated that women recognize a good body as indicative of a man of discipline and self-control.

== Biology and culture ==

[[Image:Marines wrestle.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Direct competition of physical skill and strength is a feature of masculinity which appears in some form in virtually every culture on Earth. Here, two [[United States Marine Corps|U.S. Marines]] compete in a [[wrestling]] match.]]

Masculinity has its roots in [[genetics]] (see [[Gender#Biology of gender|gender]]).&lt;ref&gt;John Money, 'The concept of gender identity disorder in childhood and adolescence after 39 years', Journal of Sex and Marital Therapy 20 (1994): 163-77.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
Laura Stanton and Brenna Maloney, [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/graphic/2006/12/18/GR2006121800372.html 'The Perception of Pain',] ''Washington Post'', 19 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore while masculinity looks different in different cultures, there are common aspects to its definition across cultures.&lt;ref&gt;[[Donald Brown (anthropologist)|Donald Brown]], ''[[Human Universals]]''&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some [[gender studies]] scholars will use the phrase "[[hegemonic masculinity]]" to refer to an ideal of male behavior which men are strongly encouraged to aim, which is calculated to guarantee the dominant position of some men over others.

=== Western trends ===
According to a paper submitted by [[Tracy Tylka]] to the [[American Psychological Association]] (APA), in contemporary America: "Instead of seeing a decrease in [[objectification]] of women in society, there has just been an increase in the objectification of both sexes. And you can see that in the media today." Men and women restrict their food intake in an effort to achieve what they consider an attractively thin body, in extreme cases leading to [[eating disorder]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://researchnews.osu.edu/archive/maleobj.htm Pressure To Be More Muscular May Lead Men To Unhealthy Behaviors]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Thomas Holbrook]], also a psychiatrist, cites a recent Canadian study indicating as many as one in six of those with eating disorders were men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?sec=health&amp;res=9F02EED7133EF936A15755C0A9669C8B63 | work=The New York Times | title=Thinner: The Male Battle With Anorexia | first=Erica | last=Goode | date=2000-06-25 | accessdate=2010-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

"Younger men and women who read fitness and fashion magazines could be psychologically harmed by the images of perfect female and male physiques," according to recent research in the United Kingdom. Some young women and men exercise excessively in an effort to achieve what they consider an attractively fit and muscular body, which in extreme cases can lead to [[body dysmorphic disorder]] or [[muscle dysmorphia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/7318411.stm | work=BBC News | title=Magazines 'harm male body image' | date=2008-03-28 | accessdate=2010-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.askmen.com/sports/bodybuilding/56_fitness_tip.html Muscle dysmorphia - AskMen.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livescience.com/health/060815_bodyimage_men.html Men Muscle in on Body Image Problems | LiveScience&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the actual stereotypes may have remained relatively constant, the value attached to the masculine and feminine stereotypes seem to have changed over the past few decades.  

Those associated with recent work in the study of masculinity from a philosophical perspective view masculinity as an unstable phenomenon and never ultimately achieved.&lt;ref&gt;Reeser, T. Masculinities in Theory, Malden: Wiley-Blackwell, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==
{{Original research section|date=December 2007}}
{{Main|Masculine psychology|Gender differences}}

[[File:PalmercarpenterA.jpg|thumb|A construction worker in 1942.]]

A great deal is now known about the development of masculine characteristics and the process of [[sexual differentiation]] specific to the reproductive system of ''Homo sapiens''. The [[SRY gene]] on the [[Y chromosome]] interferes with the process of creating a female, causing a chain of events that leads to [[testes]] formation, [[androgen]] production, and a range of both natal and post-natal hormonal effects. There is an extensive debate about how children develop [[gender identity|gender identities]].

In many cultures, displaying characteristics not typical to one's gender may become a social problem for the individual. Among men, some non-standard behaviors may be considered a sign of [[homosexuality]]. Within [[sociology]] such labeling and conditioning is known as [[gender role|gender assumptions]], and is a part of [[socialization]] to better match a culture's [[mores]]. The corresponding social condemnation of excessive masculinity may be expressed in terms such as ''[[machismo]]'' or ''[[testosterone poisoning]]''.

The relative importance of the roles of socialization and genetics in the development of masculinity continues to be debated. While [[social conditioning]] obviously plays a role, it can also be observed that certain aspects of the feminine and masculine identity exist in almost all human cultures.

The historical development of gender role is addressed by such fields as [[behavioral genetics]], [[evolutionary psychology]], [[human ecology]], and [[sociology]]. All human [[culture]]s seem to encourage the development of gender roles, through [[literature]], [[costume]] and [[song]]. Some examples of this might include the epics of [[Homer]], the [[King Arthur]] tales in English, the [[Norm (philosophy)|normative]] commentaries of [[Confucius]]. More specialized treatments of masculinity may be found in works such as the [[Bhagavad Gita]] or [[bushidō]]'s [[Hagakure]].

Another term for a masculine woman is ''[[Butch and femme|butch]]'', which is associated with [[lesbian]]ism. ''Butch'' is also used within the lesbian community, without a negative connotation, but with a more specific meaning (Davis and Lapovsky Kennedy, 1989). 

===Downside and failure of concept===
It is a subject of debate whether masculinity concepts followed historically should still be applied. Researchers such as Care International have argued that there is a harmful downside due to considerations such as the following:
* The relationship between masculinity and gender-based violence&lt;ref name="UNIFEM GENDER FACT SHEET No.5"&gt;UNIFEM GENDER FACT SHEET No.5&lt;/ref&gt;
* The disempowerment and impoverishment of women and the persistence of gender inequalities through men’s violence&lt;ref name="UNIFEM GENDER FACT SHEET No.5"/&gt;
* The loss of men's dignity and [[self-esteem]] when they are taught to behave violently

Although men may improve their behavior when they are equipped with the proper knowledge and skills, the more deeply rooted gender inequalities that shape sexual encounters are more difficult to transform.&lt;ref&gt;Care internation Research - Vietnam&lt;/ref&gt;

The images of boys and young men presented in the media may lead to the persistence of harmful concepts of masculinity. Men's rights activists argue that the media does not pay serious attention to men's rights issues and that men are often portrayed in a negative light, particularly in advertising.&lt;ref&gt;Farrell, W. &amp; Sterba, J. P. (2008) Does Feminism Discriminate Against Men: A Debate (Point and Counterpoint), New York: Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pressures associated===
In 1987, Eisler and Skidmore did studies on masculinity and created the idea of 'masculine stress'. They found four mechanisms of masculinity that accompany masculine gender role often result in emotional stress. They include:

* The emphasis on prevailing in situations requiring body and fitness
* Being perceived as emotional
* The need to feel adequate in regard to sexual matters and work

Because of social norms and pressures associated with masculinity, Men with spinal cord injuries have to adapt their self identity to the losses associated with SCI which may “lead to feelings of decreased physical and sexual prowess with lowered self-esteem and a loss of male identity. Feelings of guilt and overall loss of control are also experienced.”&lt;ref&gt;Hutchinson, Susan L "Heroic masculinity following spinal cord injury: Implications for therapeutic recreation practice and research". Therapeutic Recreation Journal. FindArticles.com. 07 Apr, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Masculinity is something that is becoming increasingly challenged, especially in the last century, with the emergence of [[Women's rights]] and the development of the role of women in society. Such is the case that in recent years many 'Man Laws' have been created, as a way for men to re-affirm their masculinity. A popular example is the Miller Lite [[Man Laws]], and other various sites on the internet offering rules such as: "15. A real man does not need instruction manuals."  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.fuckingmanly.com/man-rules|title= List of Man Law Rules/Rules for Men |publisher= Fucking Manly|accessdate=2009-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although many of these rules are offered in a humorous fashion, they attempt to define masculinity, and this highlights the change from traditional views on masculinity.

===Risk-taking===
The driver fatality rate per vehicle miles driven is higher for women than for men; although, men are much more likely to cause deaths in the accidents they are involved in.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/1998/06/980618032130.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Men drive significantly more miles than women, so, on average, they are more likely to be involved in [[road traffic accident|motor vehicle accident]]s. Even in the narrow category of  young (16-20) driver fatalities with a high blood alcohol content (BAC), a male's risk of dying is higher than a female's risk at the Same BAC level.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-nrd.nhtsa.dot.gov/Pubs/98.010.PDF]&lt;/ref&gt; That is, young women drivers need to be more drunk to have the same risk of dying in a fatal accident as young men drivers. Men are in fact three times more likely to die in all kinds of accidents than women. In the United States, men make up 92% of workplace deaths, indicating either a greater willingness to perform dangerous work, or a societal expectation to perform this work.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bls.gov/iif/oshwc/cfoi/cfch0005.pdf CFOI Charts, 1992-2006&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Health care===
{{main|Men's health risks}}

A growing body of evidence is pointing toward the deleterious impact of masculinity (and hegemonic masculinity in particular) on men's health help-seeking behaviour &lt;ref&gt;Galdas P.M., Cheater F. &amp; Marshall P. (2005) Men and health help-seeking behaviour: Literature review. Journal of Advanced Nursing, 49, 616-23&lt;/ref&gt;. American men make 134.5 million fewer physician visits than American women each year. In fact, men make only 40.8% of all physician visits, that is, if you include women's visits for pregnancy, childbirth and associated obstetrical and gynecological visits. A quarter of the men who are 45 to 60 do not have a personal physician. Many men should go to annual heart checkups with physicians but do not, increasing their risk of death from [[heart disease]]. Men between the ages of 25 and 65 are four times more likely to die from [[cardiovascular disease]] than women. Men are more likely to be diagnosed in a later stage of a [[terminal illness]] because of their reluctance to go to the doctor. 

Reasons men give for not having annual physicals and not visiting their physician include [[fear]], [[denial]], [[embarrassment]], a dislike of situations out of their control, or not worth the time or cost. 

====Media encouragement====
According to Arran Stibbe (2004), men's health problems and behaviors can be linked to the socialized gender role of men in our culture. In exploring magazines, he found that they promote traditional masculinity and claims that, among other things, men's magazines tend to celebrate "male" activities and behavior such as admiring guns, fast cars, sexually libertine women, and reading or viewing [[pornography]] regularly. In men's magazines, several "ideal" images of men are promoted, and that these images may even entail certain health risks.

====Alcohol consumption behavior====
Research on beer commercials by [[Lance Strate|Strate]] (Postman, Nystrom, Strate, And Weingartner 1987; Strate 1989, 1990) and by Wenner (1991) show some results relevant to studies of masculinity. In beer commercials, the ideas of masculinity (especially risk-taking) are presented and encouraged. The commercials often focus on situations where a man is overcoming an obstacle in a group. The men will either be working hard or playing hard. For instance the commercial will show men who do physical labor such as construction workers, or farm work, or men who are [[cowboy]]s. Beer commercials that involve playing hard have a central theme of mastery (over nature or over each other), risk, and adventure. For instance, the men will be outdoors [[fishing]], [[camping]], playing sports, or hanging out in [[bar (establishment)|bars]]. There is usually an element of [[Risk|danger]] as well as a focus on movement and speed. This appeals to and emphasizes the idea that real men overcome danger and enjoy speed (i.e. fast cars/driving fast) as well as speed as in amphetamines. The bar serves as a setting for the measurement of masculinity (skills like [[billiards|pool]], [[physical strength|strength]] and drinking ability) and serves as a center for male socializing.

==See also==
*[[Emasculation]]
*[[Model of masculinity under fascist Italy]]
*[[Victorian masculinity]]
*[[Hypermasculinity]]
*[[Masculism]]
*[[Men's spaces]]
*[[International Men's Day]] 
*[[Male bonding]]

==== Books ====
* ''[[Manliness (book)]]'' (2006)

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*Levine, Martin P. (1998). ''Gay Macho''. New York: New York University Press. ISBN 0-8147-4694-2.
*Stibbe, Arran. (2004). "Health and the Social Construction of Masculinity in Men's Health Magazine." Men and Masculinities; 7 (1) July, pp.&amp;nbsp;31–51.
*[[Lance Strate|Strate, Lance]] "Beer Commercials: A Manual on Masculinity" Men's Lives Kimmel, Michael S. and Messner, Michael A. ed. Allyn and Bacon. Boston, London: 2001

==Further reading==
====Present situation====
*Arrindell, Willem A., Ph.D. (1 October 2005) "Masculine Gender Role Stress" Psychiatric Times Pg. 31
*Ashe, Fidelma (2007) The New Politics of Masculinity, London and New York: Routledge. 
*Broom A. and Tovey P. (Eds) Men’s Health: Body, Identity and Social Context London; John Wiley and Sons Inc.
*Burstin, Fay "What's Killing Men". Herald Sun (Melbourne, [[Australia]]). October 15, 2005.
*Canada, Geoffrey "Learning to Fight" Men's Lives Kimmel, Michael S. and Messner, Michael A. ed. Allyn and Bacon. Boston, London: 2001
*[[Raewyn Connell]]: ''Masculinities'' (as Robert W. Connell), Cambridge: Polity Press, 1995 ISBN 0-7456-1469-8
*Courtenay, Will "Constructions of masculinity and their influence on men's well-being: a theory of gender and health" Social Science and Medicine, yr: 2000 vol: 50 iss: 10 pg: 1385–1401
* [[bell hooks]], ''We Real Cool: Black Men and Masculinity'', Taylor &amp; Francis 2004, ISBN 0415969271 
*Galdas P.M. and Cheater F.M. (2010) Indian and Pakistani men’s accounts of seeking medical help for angina and myocardial infarction in the UK: Constructions of marginalised masculinity or another version of hegemonic masculinity? Qualitative Research in Psychology
*Levant &amp; Pollack (1995) A New Psychology of Men, New York: BasicBooks
* Juergensmeyer, Mark (2005): ''Why guys throw bombs. About terror and masculinity'' [http://web.fu-berlin.de/gpo/pdf/juergensmeyer/juergensmeyer_e.pdf (pdf)] 
*Kaufman, Michael "The Construction of Masculinity and the Triad of Men's Violence". Men's Lives Kimmel, Michael S. and Messner, Michael A. ed. Allyn and Bacon. Boston, London: 2001
*[[Harvey Mansfield|Mansfield, Harvey]]. ''[[Manliness (book)|Manliness]]''. New Haven: [[Yale University Press]], 2006. ISBN 0300106645
* Reeser, T. ''Masculinities in Theory'', Malden: Wiley-Blackwell, 2010.
*Robinson, L. (October 21, 2005). Not just boys being boys: Brutal hazings are a product of a culture of masculinity defined by violence, aggression and domination. Ottawa Citizen (Ottawa, Ontario).
*Stephenson, June (1995). ''Men are Not Cost Effective: Male Crime in America.'' ISBN 0-06-095098-6
*Williamson P. "Their own worst enemy" Nursing Times: 91 (48) 29 November 95 p 24-7
*Wray Herbert "Survival Skills" U.S. News &amp; World Report Vol. 139 , No. 11; Pg. 63 September 26, 2005
*[http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0014/001465/146514e.pdf "Masculinity for Boys"; published by UNESCO, New Delhi, 2006; ]
*Smith, Bonnie G., Hutchison, Beth. Gendering Disability.  Rutgers University Press, 2004.

====History====
*[[Michael Kimmel]], Manhood in America, New York [etc.]:  The Free Press    1996 
*A Question of Manhood: A Reader in U.S. Black Mens History and Masculinity, edited by Earnestine Jenkins and Darlene Clark Hine, Indiana University press vol1: 1999, vol. 2: 2001
*Gary Taylor, Castration: An Abbreviated History of Western Manhood, Routledge 2002
*[[Klaus Theweleit]], Male fantasies, Minneapolis : University of Minnesota Press, 1987 and Polity Press, 1987
*Peter N. Stearns, Be a Man!: Males in Modern Society, Holmes &amp; Meier Publishers, 1990
*Shuttleworth, Russell. "Disabled Masculinity." Gendering Disability.  Ed. Bonnie G. Smith and Beth Hutchison.  Rutgers University Press, New Brunswick, New Jersey, 2004. 166-178.

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{wiktionary|masculinity}}
'''Bibliographic'''
*[http://mensbiblio.xyonline.net/ The Men's Bibliography], a comprehensive bibliography of writing on men, masculinities, gender and sexualities, listing over 16,700 works. (mainly from a constructionist perspective)
*[http://www.boyhoodstudies.com Boyhood Studies], features a 2200+ bibliography of young masculinities.
'''Other'''
* [http://www.practicalmanliness.com Practical Manliness], A manly blog that applies "historical ideals to modern men".
*[http://www.mkpchicago.org The ManKind Project of Chicago], supporting men in leading meaningful lives of integrity, accountability, responsibility, and emotional intelligence
*[http://menanddepression.nimh.nih.gov/ NIMH web pages on men and depression], talks about men and their depression and how to get help.
* [http://howellgroup.org/parsifal.html Article entitled "Wounded Masculinity: Parsifal and The Fisher King Wound"] The symbolism of the story as it relates to the Wounded Masculinity of Men by Richard Sanderson M.Ed., B.A.
* [http://www.artofmanliness.com Art of Manliness], An online web magazine/blog dedicated to "reviving the lost art of manliness".
* [http://masculinityconspiracy.com The Masculinity Conspiracy], An online book critiquing constructions of masculinity.
{{Masculism}}

[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Men]]

[[ar:ذكورة]]
[[de:Männlichkeit]]
[[es:Masculinidad]]
[[fr:Masculinité]]
[[id:Maskulin]]
[[it:Maschilismo]]
[[he:גבריות]]
[[ja:男らしさ]]
[[no:Maskulinitet]]
[[pl:Maskulinizm]]
[[pt:Masculinidade]]
[[ru:Мужество]]
[[uk:Мужність]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>