<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151119032320|691329011" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="240058" pageid="240058" ns="0" title="Masculinity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-19T03:25:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Masculine|other uses|Masculine (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect|Manliness|the book by Harvey Mansfield|Manliness (book)}}
[[File:Landsdowne Herakles.jpg|thumb|alt=Statue of Heracles, holding a club and caressing a lion|In Greek mythology, [[Heracles]] is synonymous with [[Apollonian]] masculinity.]]
{{masculism sidebar}}

'''Masculinity''' (also called '''boyhood''', '''manliness''' or '''manhood''') is a set of attributes, behaviors and roles generally associated with boys and men. It is a combination of socially-defined and biological factors,&lt;ref name="Wijngaard"&gt;{{cite book |authors =Marianne van den Wijngaard|title=Reinventing the sexes: the biomedical construction of femininity and masculinity. Race, gender, and science|publisher=Indiana University Press|year=1997|pages=171 pages |accessdate=June 3, 2011|ISBN =0-253-21087-9|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Dn5cI9BHbKgC&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=en#v=onepage&amp;q=false
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Martin and Finn"&gt;{{cite book|authors = Hale Martin, Stephen Edward Finn|title=Masculinity and Femininity in the MMPI-2 and MMPI-A|publisher=U of Minnesota Press|year=2010|pages=310 pages|accessdate=June 3, 2011 |ISBN =0-8166-2445-3|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5KLPlmr9T7MC&amp;pg=PA16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dunphy"&gt;{{cite book|authors =Richard Dunphy|title=Sexual politics: an introduction|publisher=Edinburgh University Press|year=2000|pages=240 pages|accessdate=June 3, 2011 |ISBN =0-7486-1247-5|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Sexual_Politics.html?id=NVPQkt0bVpAC}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[sex and gender distinction|distinct]] from the definition of the [[male]] anatomical [[sex]].&lt;ref name=Ferrante&gt;{{cite book|last=Ferrante|first=Joan|title=Sociology: A Global Perspective|publisher=Thomson Wadsworth|location=Belmont, CA|isbn=0-8400-3204-8|edition=7th|pages=269–272}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.who.int/gender/whatisgender/en/ Gender, Women and Health: What do we mean by "sex" and "gender"?']'', The World Health Organization&lt;/ref&gt; Both men and women can exhibit masculine traits and behavior. Those exhibiting both masculine and [[feminine]] characteristics are considered [[androgynous]], and feminist philosophers have  argued that gender ambiguity may blur gender classification.&lt;ref&gt;Butler, Judith (1999 [1990]), Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity (New York and London: Routledge).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Laurie, Timothy (2014), 'The Ethics of Nobody I Know: Gender and the Politics of Description', Qualitative Research Journal, 14 (1), pp. 64-78.URL: https://www.academia.edu/6262250/The_Ethics_of_Nobody_I_Know_Gender_and_the_Politics_of_Description&lt;/ref&gt;

Masculine traits include [[courage]], [[independence]] and [[assertiveness]].&lt;ref name="Vetterling-Braggin"&gt;Vetterling-Braggin, Mary  ''"Femininity," "masculinity," and "androgyny": a modern philosophical discussion''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Worell"&gt;Worell, Judith, ''Encyclopedia of women and gender: sex similarities and differences and the impact of society on gender, Volume 1'' Elsevier, 2001, ISBN 0-12-227246-3, ISBN 978-0-12-227246-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="R. Murray Thomas"&gt;{{cite book|last=Thomas|first=R. Murray|title=Recent Theories of Human Development|year=2000|publisher=[[Sage Publications]]|isbn=0761922474|url=https://books.google.com/books?hl=fr&amp;id=-RxIUDYIuiIC|page=248|quote=Gender feminists also consider traditional feminine traits (gentleness, modesty, humility, sacrifice, supportiveness, empathy, compassion, tenderness, nurturance, intuitiveness, sensitivity, unselfishness) morally superior to the traditional masculine traits (courage, strong will, ambition, independence, assertiveness, initiative, rationality and emotional control).}}&lt;/ref&gt; These traits vary by location and context, and are influenced by social and cultural factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Witt|first=edited by Charlotte|title=Feminist Metaphysics: Explorations in the Ontology of Sex, Gender and Identity|year=2010|publisher=Springer|location=Dordrecht|isbn=90-481-3782-9|page=77}}&lt;/ref&gt; An overemphasis on masculinity and power, often associated with a disregard for consequences and responsibility, is known as [[machismo]].&lt;ref name = "Britannica"&gt;{{cite web|title=Machismo (exaggerated masculinity) - Encyclopædia Britannica|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/1381820/machismo|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.|edition=online|accessdate=6 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
Masculine qualities, characteristics or roles are considered typical of, or appropriate for, a boy or man. They have degrees of comparison: "more masculine" and "most masculine", and the opposite may be expressed by "unmanly" or "[[epicene]]".&lt;ref name=Roget&gt;''[[Roget's Thesaurus|Roget’s II: The New Thesaurus]]'', 3rd. ed., [[Houghton Mifflin]], 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; Similar to masculinity is [[virility]] (from the Latin ''[[:la:vir|vir]]'', "man"). The concept of masculinity varies historically and culturally; although the [[dandy]] was seen as a 19th-century ideal of masculinity, he is considered [[Effeminacy|effeminate]] by modern standards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Reeser|first=Todd|title=Masculinities in Theory: An Introduction|year=2010|pages=1–3|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=1444358537|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YMnn8Zf0heoC}}&lt;/ref&gt; Masculine norms, as described in Ronald F. Levant's ''Masculinity Reconstructed'', are "avoidance of [[femininity]]; restricted emotions; sex disconnected from intimacy; pursuit of achievement and status; self-reliance; [[Physical strength|strength]] and [[aggression]], and [[homophobia]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Levant |first1=Ronald F. |last2=Kopecky |first2=Gini |title=Masculinity Reconstructed: Changing the Rules of Manhood—At Work, in Relationships, and in Family Life |location=New York |publisher=Dutton |year=1995 |isbn=978-0452275416}}&lt;/ref&gt; These norms reinforce [[gender role]]s by associating attributes and characteristics with one gender.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Dornan |first1=Jennifer |title=Blood from the Moon:Gender Ideology and the Rise of Ancient Maya Social Complexity |year=2004 |issn=0953-5233}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The academic study of masculinity received increased attention during the late 1980s and early 1990s, with the number of courses on the subject in the United States rising from 30 to over 300.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Bradley|first=Rolla M.|title=Masculinity and Self Perception of Men Identified as Informal Leaders|year=2008|publisher=ProQuest|isbn=0549473998|pages=9|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8MiVG4T2_eYC}}&lt;/ref&gt; This has sparked investigation of the intersection of  masculinity with other axes of social discrimination and concepts from other fields, such as the [[social construction of gender difference]]&lt;ref name="Flood 2007 Viii"&gt;{{cite book|last=Flood|first=Michael|title=International Encyclopaedia of Men and Masculinities|year=2007|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0415333431|pages=Viii|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EUON2SYps-QC}}&lt;/ref&gt; (prevalent in a number of [[philosophical]] and [[sociological]] theories).

==Development==
[[File:PalmercarpenterA.jpg|thumb|alt=Carpenter in a hard hat using a hand drill outdoors|A construction worker]]
In many cultures, displaying characteristics not typical of one's gender may be a social problem. In [[sociology]], this labeling is known as [[gender role|gender assumptions]] and is part of [[socialization]] to meet the [[mores]] of a society. Non-standard behavior may be considered indicative of [[homosexuality]], despite the fact that gender expression, [[gender identity]] and [[sexual orientation]] are widely accepted as distinct concepts.&lt;ref name=nacua&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nacua.org/nacuanet/visual/nacuanotessample.html |title=Gender Identity and Expression Issues at Colleges and Universities |date=2005-06-02 |accessdate=2007-04-02 |work=[[National Association of College and University Attorneys]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; When sexuality is defined in terms of object choice (as in early [[sexology]] studies), male homosexuality is interpreted as [[effeminacy]].&lt;ref name=chrysler&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid28980.asp |title=Chrysler TV ad criticized for using gay stereotypes |accessdate=2007-04-07 |date=2006-04-07 |work=[[The Advocate]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Social disapproval of excessive masculinity may be expressed as "machismo"&lt;ref name = "Britannica"/&gt; or by [[neologism]]s such as "[[testosterone poisoning]]".&lt;ref&gt;Alan Alda, "What Every Woman Should Know About Men", Ms., New York, October 1975&lt;/ref&gt;

The relative importance of socialization and genetics in the development of masculinity is debated. Although [[social conditioning]] is believed to play a role, [[psychologist]]s and [[psychoanalysts]] such as [[Sigmund Freud]] and [[Carl Jung]] believed that aspects of "feminine" and "masculine" identity are [[subconscious]]ly present in all human males.{{efn|See [[innate bisexuality]] and [[anima and animus]] for more information.}}

The historical development of gender roles is addressed by [[behavioural genetics]], [[evolutionary psychology]], [[human ecology]], [[anthropology]] and sociology. All human cultures seem to encourage gender roles in literature, costume and song; examples may include the epics of [[Homer]], the [[Hengist and Horsa]] tales and the [[Norm (philosophy)|normative]] commentaries of [[Confucius]].{{citation needed|date=June 2015}} More specialized treatments of masculinity may be found in the ''[[Bhagavad Gita]]'' and the [[Bushido|bushidō]] of ''[[Hagakure]]''.

==Nature versus nurture==
The extent to which masculinity is [[Nature versus nurture|inborn or conditioned]] is debated. [[Genome]] research has yielded information about the development of masculine characteristics and the process of [[sexual differentiation]] specific to the human reproductive system. The [[testis determining factor]] (also known as SRY protein) on the [[Y chromosome]], critical for male sexual development, activates the [[SOX9]] [[protein]].&lt;ref name="Moniot"&gt;{{cite journal | last=Moniot | first=Brigitte | last2=Declosmenil | first2=Faustine | last3=Barrionuevo | first3=Francisco | last4=Scherer | first4=Gerd | last5=Aritake | first5=Kosuke | last6=Malki | first6=Safia | last7=Marzi | first7=Laetitia | last8=Cohen-Solal | first8=Ann | last9=Georg | first9=Ina | last10=Klattig | first10=Jürgen | last11=Englert | first11=Christoph | last12=Kim | first12=Yuna | last13=Capel | first13=Blanche | last14=Eguchi | first14=Naomi | last15=Urade | first15=Yoshihiro | last16=Boizet-Bonhoure | first16=Brigitte | last17=Poulat | first17=Francis | year=2009 | title=The PGD2 pathway, independently of FGF9, amplifies SOX9 activity in Sertoli cells during male sexual differentiation| journal=Development| volume=136| issue=11| pages=1813–1821| publisher=The Company of Biologists Ltd. | pmid=19429785 | doi=10.1242/dev.032631}}&lt;/ref&gt; SOX9 works with the [[SF1 (gene)|SF1 protein]] to increase the level of [[anti-Müllerian hormone]], repressing female development while activating and forming a [[Feed forward (control)|feedforward]] loop with the [[FGF9]] protein; this creates the [[testis cords]] and is responsible for [[sertoli cell]]s, which aid in [[sperm]] production.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal 
| last1 = Kim | first1 = Y. 
| last2 = Kobayashi | first2 = A. 
| last3 = Sekido | first3 = R. 
| last4 = Dinapoli | first4 = L. 
| last5 = Brennan | first5 = J. 
| last6 = Chaboissier | first6 = M. C. 
| last7 = Poulat | first7 = F. 
| last8 = Behringer | first8 = R. R. 
| last9 = Lovell-Badge | first9 = R. 
| doi = 10.1371/journal.pbio.0040187 
| last10 = Capel | first10 = B. 
| title = Fgf9 and Wnt4 Act as Antagonistic Signals to Regulate Mammalian Sex Determination 
| journal = PLoS Biology 
| volume = 4 
| issue = 6 
| pages = e187 
| year = 2006 
| pmid = 16700629 
| pmc =1463023 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The activation of SRY halts the process of creating a female, beginning a chain of events leading to [[testicle]] formation, [[androgen]] production and a number of pre- and post-natal hormonal effects.

How a child develops [[gender identity]] is also debated. Some believe that masculinity is linked to the male body; in this view, masculinity is associated with [[human penis|male genitalia]].&lt;ref name="Reeser 2010 3"&gt;{{cite book|last=Reeser|first=Todd|title=Masculinities in Theory: An Introduction|year=2010|page=3|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=1444358537|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YMnn8Zf0heoC}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others have suggested that although masculinity may be influenced by biology, it is also a cultural construct. Proponents of this view argue that women can become men [[Hormone replacement therapy (female-to-male)|hormonally]] and [[Sex reassignment surgery|physically]],&lt;ref name="Reeser 2010 3"/&gt; and many aspects of masculinity assumed to be natural are linguistically and culturally driven.&lt;ref&gt;Mills, Sara. "[http://extra.shu.ac.uk/daol/articles/closed/2003/001/mills2003001-paper.html Third wave feminist linguistics and the analysis of sexism.]" ''Discourse analysis online 2.1'' (2003).&lt;/ref&gt; On the nurture side of the debate, it is argued that masculinity does not have a single source. Although the military has a vested interest in constructing and promoting a specific form of masculinity, it does not create it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Reeser|first=Todd|title=Masculinities in Theory: An Introduction|year=2010|pages=17–21|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=1444358537|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YMnn8Zf0heoC}}&lt;/ref&gt; Facial hair is linked to masculinity through language, in stories about boys becoming men when they begin to shave.&lt;ref name="Reeser 2010 30–31"&gt;{{cite book|last=Reeser|first=Todd|title=Masculinities in Theory: An Introduction|year=2010|pages=30–31|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=1444358537|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YMnn8Zf0heoC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hegemonic masculinity==
{{Main|Hegemonic masculinity}}
[[Image:USMC-10881.jpg|thumb|250px|alt=Two wrestlers, one wearing red and the other blue|Competitions of physical skill and strength are a feature of masculinity appearing in some form in virtually every culture. Here, two [[United States Marine Corps|U.S. Marines]] compete in a wrestling match.]]
Traditional avenues for men to gain honor were providing for their families and exercising leadership.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;George, A., "Reinventing honorable masculinity" Men and Masculinities&lt;/ref&gt; [[Raewyn Connell]] has labeled traditional male roles and privileges [[hegemonic masculinity]], encouraged in men and discouraged in women: "Hegemonic masculinity can be defined as the configuration of gender practice which embodies the currently accepted answer to the problem of the legitimacy of [[patriarchy]], which guarantees the dominant position of men and the subordination of women".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Connell|first=R.W.|title=Masculinities|origyear=1995|year=2005|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|pages=77}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Precarious manhood==
Researchers have argued that the "precariousness" of manhood contributes to traditionally-masculine behavior.&lt;ref&gt;Bosson, J. K., &amp; Vandello, J. A. (2011). Precarious manhood and its links to action and aggression. ''Current Directions in Psychological Science, 20'', 82-86.&lt;/ref&gt; "Precarious" means that manhood is not inborn, but must be achieved. In many cultures, boys endure painful initiation rituals to become men. Manhood may also be lost, as when a man is derided for not "being a man." Researchers have found that men respond to threats to their manhood by engaging in stereotypically-masculine behaviors and beliefs, such as supporting hierarchy, espousing homophobic beliefs, supporting aggression and choosing physical tasks over intellectual ones.&lt;ref&gt;Vandello, J. A., Bosson, J. K., Cohen, D., Burnaford, R. M., &amp; Weaver, J. R. (2008). Precarious manhood. ''Journal of personality and social psychology, 95'', 1325-1339.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, Winegard, Winegard and Geary wrote that the precariousness of manhood involves social status (prestige or dominance), and manhood may be more (or less) precarious due to the avenues men have for achieving status.&lt;ref&gt;Winegard, B., Winegard, B., &amp; Geary, D. C. (2014). Eastwood's brawn and Einstein's brain: An evolutionary account of dominance, prestige, and precarious manhood. ''Review of General Psychology, 18'', 34-48.&lt;/ref&gt; Men who identify with creative pursuits, such as poetry or painting, may not experience manhood as precarious but may respond to threats to their intelligence or creativity. However, men who identify with traditionally-masculine pursuits (such as football or the military) may see masculinity as precarious. According to Winegard, Winegard, and Geary, this is functional; poetry and painting do not require traditionally-masculine traits, and attacks on those traits should not induce anxiety. {{Dubious|date=August 2015}} Football and the military require traditionally-masculine traits, such as pain tolerance, endurance, muscularity and courage, and attacks on those traits induce anxiety and may trigger retaliatory impulses and behavior. This suggests that nature-versus-nurture debates about masculinity may be simplistic. Although men evolved to pursue prestige and dominance (status), how they pursue status depends on their talents, traits and available possibilities. In modern societies, more avenues to status may exist than in traditional societies and this may mitigate the precariousness of manhood (or of traditional manhood); however, it will probably not mitigate the intensity of male-male competition.

==LGBT communities==

===General===
Joseph Pleck argues that a hierarchy of masculinity exists largely as a [[dichotomy]] of homosexual and heterosexual males: "Our society uses the male heterosexual-homosexual dichotomy as a central symbol for all the rankings of masculinity, for the division on any grounds between males who are "real men" and have power, and males who are not".&lt;ref name="nomas.org"/&gt; [[Michael Kimmel]]&lt;ref&gt;Kimmel, Michael S., and Summer Lewis. Mars and Venus, Or, Planet Earth?: Women and Men in a New Millenium [sic]. Kansas State University, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; adds that the [[Trope (literature)|trope]] "You're so gay" indicates a lack of masculinity, rather than homosexual orientation. According to Pleck, to avoid male oppression of women, themselves and other men, [[Patriarchy|patriarchal]] structures, institutions and discourse must be eliminated from North American society. A term for a masculine woman is "[[Butch and femme|butch]]", used in the lesbian, [[gay]], [[Bisexuality|bisexual]], [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) and [[cross-dressing]] [[subculture]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wickens|first=Kathryn|title=Butch–Femme Definitions|url=http://www.butch-femme.net/butchfemmenetwork_016.htm|publisher=Butch–Femme Network, founded in Massachusetts in 1996|accessdate=11 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hollibaugh|first=Amber L.|title=My Dangerous Desires: A Queer Girl Dreaming Her Way Home|year=2000|publisher=Duke University Press|isbn=0822326191|pages=249|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=41bNbaMuyPoC}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Boyd|first=Helen|title=My Husband Betty: Love, Sex and Life With a Cross-Dresser|year=2004|publisher=Sdal Press|isbn=1560255153|pages=64|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vCT70HjI_a4C}}&lt;/ref&gt; to describe a masculine identity and its associated traits, behavior, style and self-perception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kramararae|first=Chris|title=Rutledge International Encyclopaedia of Women|year=2000|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0415920892|pages=133|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YCKLHBXeyyYC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Men===
{{see also|Effeminacy#Effeminacy and gay men}}
Gay men are considered by some to "deviate from the masculine norm" and are [[benevolent prejudice|benevolently stereotyped]] as "gentle and refined", even by other gay men. According to gay human-rights campaigner [[Peter Tatchell]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Contrary to the well-intentioned claim that gays are "just the same" as straights, there is a difference. What is more, the distinctive style of gay masculinity is of great social benefit. Wouldn't life be dull without the flair and imagination of [[queer]] fashion designers and interior decorators? How could the NHS cope with no gay nurses, or the education system with no gay teachers? Society should thank its lucky stars that not all men turn out straight, macho and insensitive. The different hetero and homo modes of maleness are not, of course, biologically fixed.&lt;ref name=Tatchell&gt;{{cite web|last1=Tatchell|first1=Peter|title=What Straight men Could Learn From Gay Men - A Queer Kind of Masculinity?|publisher=Woman's Journal|url=http://www.thescavenger.net/glbtiq-sp-1239/glbtiq/170-what-straight-men-can-learn-from-gay-men-6789.html|accessdate=7 March 2015|date=January 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the documentary ''The Butch Factor'', gay men (one of them [[transgender]]) were asked about their views of masculinity. Masculine traits were generally seen as an advantage in and out of the [[closeted|closet]], allowing "butch" gay men to conceal their [[sexual orientation]] longer while engaged in masculine activities such as sports. [[Effeminacy]] is inaccurately&lt;ref name=nacua/&gt; associated with [[homosexuality]],&lt;ref name=chrysler/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Effeminacy#Effeminacy and gay men|Effeminacy and gay men]]&lt;/ref&gt; and some gay men doubted their sexual orientation; they did not see themselves as effeminate, and felt little connection to [[LGBT culture|gay culture]].&lt;ref name=ifbutscoconuts&gt;{{cite web|author1=ifsbutscoconuts|title=The Butch Factor: Masculinity from a Gay Male Perspective|url=http://ifsbutscoconuts.kinja.com/the-butch-factor-masculinity-from-a-gay-male-perspect-1549893361|accessdate=6 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some effeminate gay men in ''The Butch Factor'' felt uncomfortable about their femininity (despite being comfortable with their sexuality),&lt;ref name="Feminine Gay Man Strength"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Curry|first1=Tyler|title=The Strength in Being a Feminine Gay Man|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/tyler-curry/the-strength-in-being-a-feminine-gay-man_b_3896302.html|accessdate=6 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and feminine gay men may be derided by stereotypically-masculine gays.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Jones|first1=Darianna|title=Why Do Masculine Gay Guys Look Down On Feminine Guys?|url=http://www.queerty.com/why-do-masculine-gay-guys-look-down-on-feminine-guys-20140707|accessdate=6 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Jones|first1=Darianna|title=An Open Letter to Gay Guys Who Look Down On "Fem Guys"|url=http://boldandsugar.com/open-letter-gay-guys-look-fem-guys/|accessdate=6 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Feminine-looking men tended to [[Coming out|come out]] earlier after being labeled gay by their peers. More likely to face bullying and harassment throughout their lives,&lt;ref name=ifbutscoconuts/&gt; they are taunted by derogatory words (such as "[[sissy]]") implying feminine qualities. Effeminate, "[[camp (style)|campy]]" gay men sometimes use what John R. Ballew called "camp humor", such as referring to one another by [[she|female pronouns]] (according to Ballew, "a funny way of defusing hate directed toward us [gay men]"); however, such humor "can cause us [gay men] to become confused in relation to how we feel about being men."&lt;ref name="Gay men and masculinity"&gt;{{cite web|author1=John R. Ballew, M.S., L.P.C.|title=Gay men and masculinity|url=http://bodymindsoul.org/articles/gay-sexuality/gay-men-and-masculinity/|accessdate=6 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|[Heterosexual] men are sometimes advised to get in touch with their "inner feminine." Maybe gay men need to get in touch with their "inner masculine" instead. Identifying those aspects of being a man we most value and then cultivate those parts of our selves can lead to a healthier and less distorted sense of our own masculinity.|John R. Ballew|Gay men and masculinity&lt;ref name="Gay men and masculinity"/&gt;}}

A study by the Center for Theoretical Study at [[Charles University in Prague]] and the [[Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic]] found "significant" differences in shape among the faces of heterosexual and gay men, with gay men having "masculine" features ("undermin[ing] stereotypical notions of gay men as more feminine looking.")&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Saul|first1=Heather|title=Gay and straight men may have different facial shapes, new study suggests|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/gay-and-straight-men-may-have-different-facial-shapes-new-study-suggests-8928519.html|accessdate=6 March 2015|publisher=The Independent|date=8 November 2013|quote=Their results found that homosexual men were rated as more stereotypically 'masculine' than heterosexual men, which they said undermined stereotypical notions of gay men as more feminine looking.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gay men have been presented in the media as feminine and open to ridicule, although films such as ''[[Brokeback Mountain]]'' are countering the stereotype.&lt;ref name="Gay men and masculinity"/&gt; A recent development is the portrayal of gay men in the [[LGBT community]] as "[[bear (gay culture)|bears]]", a [[subculture]] of gay men celebrating rugged masculinity&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.advocate.com/comedy/2014/04/17/tbt-when-advocate-invented-bears|title = When The Advocate Invented Bears|accessdate = 6 March 2015|website = The Advocate|publisher = Here Media Inc.|last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Mazzei"&gt;George Mazzei, (1979). ''Who's Who in the Zoo?''. "The Advocate", pages 42–43.&lt;/ref&gt; and "secondary sexual characteristics of the male: [[facial hair]], [[Androgenic hair|body hair]], proportional size, [[Hair loss|baldness]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Suresha|first=Ron|title=Bears on Bears: Interviews and Discussions|year=2009|publisher=Lethe Press|isbn=1590212444|page=83|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oWQ1Qe3g5hkC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Second-wave feminism|Second-wave]] [[pro-feminism]] paid greater attention to issues of sexuality, particularly the relationship between homosexual men and [[hegemonic masculinity]]. This shift led to increased cooperation between the [[Men's liberation movement|men's liberation]] and [[gay liberation]] movements developing, in part, because masculinity was understood as a [[Social constructionism|social construct]] and in response to the universalization of "men" in previous men's movements. Men's-rights activists worked to stop second-wave feminists from influencing the gay-rights movement, promoting [[hypermasculinity]] as inherent to gay sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;''Unpacking Queer Politics'' by Shiela Jeffreys&lt;/ref&gt;

==Western trends==
According to a paper submitted by Tracy Tylka to the [[American Psychological Association]], "Instead of seeing a decrease in [[objectification]] of women in society, there has just been an increase in the objectification of both sexes. And you can see that in the media today." Men and women restrict food intake in an effort to achieve what they consider an attractively-thin body; in extreme cases, this leads to [[eating disorder]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://researchnews.osu.edu/archive/maleobj.htm Pressure To Be More Muscular May Lead Men To Unhealthy Behaviors]&lt;/ref&gt; Psychiatrist [[Thomas Holbrook]] cited a recent Canadian study indicating that as many as one in six people with eating disorders are men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/25/health/thinner-the-male-battle-with-anorexia.html | work=The New York Times | title=Thinner: The Male Battle With Anorexia | first=Erica | last=Goode | date=2000-06-25 | accessdate=2010-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research in the United Kingdom found, "Younger men and women who read fitness and fashion magazines could be psychologically harmed by the images of perfect female and male physiques." Young women and men exercise excessively in an effort to achieve what they consider an attractively-fit, muscular body, which may lead to [[body dysmorphic disorder]] or [[muscle dysmorphia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/7318411.stm | work=BBC News | title=Magazines 'harm male body image' | date=2008-03-28 | accessdate=2010-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.askmen.com/sports/bodybuilding/56_fitness_tip.html Muscle dysmorphia – AskMen.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livescience.com/health/060815_bodyimage_men.html Men Muscle in on Body Image Problems | LiveScience&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Although the stereotypes may have remained constant, the value attached to masculine stereotypes has changed; it has been argued that masculinity is an unstable phenomenon, never ultimately achieved.&lt;ref name="Reeser 2010 30–31"/&gt;
[[File:Construction workers not wearing fall protection equipment.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Two construction workers positioning a beam|Male construction workers without appropriate fall-protection equipment]]

===Risk-taking===
The crash rate per vehicle-kilometre driven is higher for women than for men, although men are more likely to kill in accidents in which they are involved.&lt;ref&gt;Johns Hopkins School Of Public Health (1998, June 18). [http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/1998/06/980618032130.htm Women Not Necessarily Better Drivers Than Men.] ScienceDaily.&lt;/ref&gt; Men drive more miles than women, and on average are more likely to be involved in [[traffic accident]]s. Even in the category of young-driver (16–20) fatalities with a high [[blood alcohol content]], a male's risk of dying is higher than a female's at a given BAC level; young women drivers need to be more intoxicated to have the same risk of dying in a fatal accident as young men drivers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-nrd.nhtsa.dot.gov/Pubs/98.010.PDF Crash Data and Rates for Age-Sex Groups of Drivers, 1996], Ezio C. Cerrelli, January 1998, National Center for Statistics &amp; Analysis – Research &amp; Development&lt;/ref&gt; A recent study suggests that young men are more risk-averse than those of a generation ago, primarily because they are less motivated and in poorer physical condition than their fathers' generation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Cross|title=Sex differences in sensation-seeking: a meta-analysis |journal=Scientific Reports|laysummary=http://www.redorbit.com/news/science/1112937148/generation-gap-in-thrill-seekers-090213/|laysource=Red Orbit | doi = 10.1038/srep02486}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Health care===
Evidence points to the negative impact of hegemonic masculinity on men's health-related behavior, with American men making 134.5&amp;nbsp;million fewer physician visits per year than women. Men make 40.8 percent of all physician visits, including women's obstetric and gynecological visits. Twenty-five percent of men aged 45 to 60 do not have a personal physician, increasing their risk of death from [[heart disease]]. Men between 25 and 65 are four times more likely to die from [[cardiovascular disease]] than women, and are more likely to be diagnosed with a [[terminal illness]] because of their reluctance to see a doctor. Reasons cited for not seeing a physician include fear, denial, embarrassment, a dislike of situations out of their control and the belief that visiting a doctor is not worth the time or cost.&lt;ref&gt;Galdas P.M., Cheater F. &amp; Marshall P. (2005) Men and health help-seeking behaviour: Literature review. Journal of Advanced Nursing, 49, 616–23&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:A Soldier Drinks a Pint of Beer on his Return from Afghanistan MOD 45152497.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Silhouetted soldier drinking a glass of beer|A British soldier drinks beer after his return from Afghanistan]]
In 2004, Arran Stibbe published an analysis of a well-known men's-health magazine in 2000. According to Stibbe, although the magazine ostensibly focused on health it also promoted traditional masculine behaviors such as excessive consumption of convenience foods and meat, alcohol consumption and unsafe sex.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}

Research on beer-commercial content by [[Lance Strate]]&lt;ref&gt;Postman, Nystrom, Strate, And Weingartner 1987; Strate 1989, 1990 and  Wenner 1991&lt;/ref&gt; yielded results relevant to a study of masculinity. In beer commercials, masculine behavior (especially risk-taking) is encouraged. Commercials often focus on situations in which a man overcomes an obstacle in a group, working or playing hard (construction or farm workers or [[cowboy]]s). Those involving play have central themes of mastery (of nature or each other), risk and adventure: fishing, camping, playing sports or socializing in [[bar (establishment)|bars]]. There is usually an element of danger and a focus on movement and speed (watching fast cars or driving fast). The bar is a setting for the measurement of masculinity in skills such as [[billiards]], strength and drinking ability. Despite the beer industry's encouragement of risk-taking, alcohol consumption has declined in all age groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Alcoholic Beverage Consumption in the U.S.: Patterns and Trends|journal=Alcohol: Problems and Solutions|url=http://www.alcoholproblemsandsolutions.org/Controversies/1116895242.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Since what constitutes masculinity has varied by time and place, according to [[Raewyn Connell]], it is more appropriate to discuss "masculinities" than a single overarching concept.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Connell|first=R. W.|title=Masculinities|year=2005|publisher=Polity|isbn=0745634273|pages=185|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YuR2uFxxvPoC}}&lt;/ref&gt; Study of the history of masculinity emerged during the 1980s, aided by the fields of women’s and (later) gender history. Before women’s history was examined, there was a "strict gendering of the public/private divide"; regarding masculinity, this meant little study of how men related to the household, domesticity and family life.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite book|title = A Man's Place, Masculinity and the Middle-Class Home in Victorian England|last = Tosh|first = John|publisher = Bath|year = 1999|isbn = |location = |pages = 2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although women’s historical role was negated, despite the writing of history by (and primarily about) men a significant portion of the male experience was missing. This void was questioned during the late 1970s, when women’s history began to analyze gender and women to deepen the female experience.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Women’s History in Transition: The European Case,|last = Davis|first = Natalie|date = 1975|journal = Feminist Studies 3|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Joan Scott’s seminal article, calling for gender studies as an analytical concept to explore society, power and discourse, laid the foundation for this field.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = ’Gender: A Useful Category of Historical Analysis’|last = Scott|first = Joan|date = 1986|journal = The American Historical Review, 91/5|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Scott gender should be used in two ways: productive and produced. Productive gender examined its role in creating power relationships, and produced gender explored the use and change of gender throughout history. This has influenced the field of masculinity, as seen in Pierre Bourdieu’s definition of masculinity: produced by society and culture, and reproduced in daily life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Masculini Domination|last = Bourdieu|first = Pierre|publisher = Cambridge|year = 2001|isbn = |location = |pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt; A flurry of work in women’s history led to a call for study of the male role (initially influenced by psychoanalysis) in society and emotional and interpersonal life. Connell wrote that these initial works were marked by a "high level of generality" in "broad surveys of cultural norms". The scholarship was aware of contemporary societal changes aiming to understand and evolve (or liberate) the male role in response to feminism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Masculinities|last = Connell|first = R.W|publisher = |isbn = |location = |pages = 28}}&lt;/ref&gt; John Tosh calls for a return to this aim for the history of masculinity to be useful, academically and in the public sphere.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|title = ‘Culture, cultural studies and the historians’, in L.Grossberd, C.Nelson, P. Tredichler (eds), Cultural Studies|last = Steedman|first = Carolyn|publisher = |year = 1992|isbn = |location = New York|pages = 617}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{anchor|Ancient}}Antiquity===
[[File:Odysseus sehnt sich nach Ithaka (Tischbein).jpg|thumb|right|alt=Painting of Odysseus leaning on a ship|[[Odysseus]], hero of the ''Odyssey'']]
Ancient literature dates back to about 3000 BC, with explicit expectations for men in the form of laws and implied masculine ideals in myths of gods and heroes. In the [[Hebrew Bible]] of 1000 BC, King David of Israel told his son to "be strong, and be a man" after David's death. Throughout history, men have met exacting cultural standards. Kate Cooper wrote about ancient concepts of femininity, "Wherever a woman is mentioned a man's character is being judged – and along with it what he stands for."&lt;ref&gt;Kate Cooper, [https://books.google.com/books?id=QVvn8vUMZdIC&amp;pg=PA19&amp;lpg=PA19 ''The Virgin and The Bride: Idealized Womanhood in Late Antiquity'',] (Cambridge, Massachusetts: [[Harvard University Press]], 1996), p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the ''[[Code of Hammurabi]]'' (about 1750 BC):
*Rule 3: "If any one bring an accusation of any crime before the elders, and does not prove what he has charged, he shall, if it be a capital offense charged, be put to death."
*Rule 128: "If a man takes a woman to wife, but has no intercourse with her, this woman is no wife to him."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wsu.edu/~dee/MESO/CODE.HTM ''The Code of Hammurabi''], translated by LW King, 1910.&lt;/ref&gt;
Scholars cite [[integrity]] and [[social equality|equality]] as masculine values in male-male relationships&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bassi | first1 = Karen | year = 2001 | title = Acting like Men: Gender, Drama, and Nostalgia in Ancient Greece | doi = 10.1086/449528 | journal = Classical Philology | volume = 96 | issue = | pages = 86–92 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and virility in male-female relationships. Legends of ancient heroes include the ''[[Epic of Gilgamesh]]'', the ''[[Iliad]]'' and the ''[[Odyssey]]''. The stories demonstrate qualities in the hero which inspire [[respect]], such as wisdom and courage: knowing things other men do not know and taking risks other men would not dare.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}

[[File:Beowulf and the dragon.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Beowulf, holding a sword, blocks a dragon's fire with his shield.|Beowulf fighting the dragon]]

===Medieval and Victorian eras ===
[[Jeffrey Richards]] describes a European "medieval masculinity which was essentially Christian and chivalric."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Richards Jeffrey | year = 1999 | title = From Christianity to Paganism: The New Middle Ages and the Values of 'Medieval' Masculinity | url = http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/bpl/cuva/1999/00000003/00000002/art00057 | journal = Cultural Values | volume = 3 | issue = | pages = 213–234 | doi=10.1080/14797589909367162}}&lt;/ref&gt; Courage, respect for women of all classes and generosity characterize the portrayal of men in literary history. The [[Anglo-Saxon]]s [[Hengest]] and [[Horsa]]{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} and [[Beowulf]] are examples of medieval masculine ideals. According to David Rosen, the traditional view of scholars (such as [[J. R. R. Tolkien]]) that ''Beowulf'' is a tale of medieval [[heroism]] overlooks the similarities between Beowulf and the monster Grendel. The masculinity exemplified by Beowulf "cut[s] men off from women, other men, passion and the household".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rosen|first=David|title=The Changing Fictions of Masculinity|year=1993|publisher=University of Illinois Press|isbn=0252063090|pages=11|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pXgBaWrB4OYC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Victorian era, [[Victorian masculinity|masculinity]] underwent a transformation from traditional heroism. Scottish philosopher [[Thomas Carlyle]] wrote in 1831: "The old ideal of Manhood has grown obsolete, and the new is still invisible to us, and we grope after it in darkness, one clutching this phantom, another that; [[The Sorrows of Young Werther|Werterism]], [[Byron]]ism, even [[Beau Brummell|Brummelism]], each has its day".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Adams|first=James Eli|title=Dandies and Desert Saints: Styles of Victorian Masculinity|year=1995|publisher=Cornell University Press|isbn=0801482089|pages=1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=f7gwHwyxZJ4C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{anchor|Modern times}}Present day===
[[File:Wwii woman worker-edit.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Woman in an aircraft factory|Female aircraft worker during World War II]]
At the beginning of the twentieth century, a traditional family consisted of the father as  [[breadwinner model|breadwinner]] and the mother as [[homemaker]]. Characteristic of present-day masculinity is men's willingness to counter stereotypes. Regardless of age or nationality, men more frequently rank good health, a harmonious family life and a good relationship with their spouse or partner as important to their quality of life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tricitypsychology.com/blog/men-defy-stereotypes-in-defining-masculinity/ Men defy stereotypes in defining masculinity], August 26, 2008, Tri-City Psychology Services&lt;/ref&gt; 
Technology such as television and the Internet offer men alternative ways to express masculinity, and websites like Reddit, Tumblr, and 4chan are platforms for men and women to discuss masculinity in current culture with others worldwide. Some sites (eg. [[Reddit#Subreddits|subreddit]] /r/MensRights) foster misogyny and regressive ideas about masculinity, according to the [[civil rights]] organisation [[Southern Poverty Law Center]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/intelligence-report/browse-all-issues/2012/spring/misogyny-the-sites/ Misogyny: The Sites], December 10, 2014, Southern Poverty Law Center&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
Two criticisms of the study of the history of masculinity are a concern that it would stabilize the historical process (rather than change it) and a cultural overemphasis on the approach to masculinity lacks the reality of actual experience. According to John Tosh, masculinity has become a conceptual framework used by historians to enhance their cultural explorations instead of a specialty in its own right.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book|title = ‘The history of masculinity: an outdated concept?’ in John Arnold and Sean Brady, What is masculinity? Historical dynamics from antiquity to the contemporary world|last = John|first = Tosh|publisher = |year = 2011|isbn = |location = Basingstoke|pages = 20}}&lt;/ref&gt; This draws attention from reality to representation and meaning, not only in the realm of masculinity; culture was becoming "the bottom line, the real historical reality."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Tosh critiques Martin Francis' work of in this light because popular culture, rather than the experience of family life, is the basis for Francis’ argument.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = A flight from commitment|last = Francis|first = Martin|date = 2007|journal = Gender and History|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Francis uses contemporary literature and film to demonstrate that masculinity was restless, shying away from domesticity and commitment, during the late 1940s and 1950s.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Francis wrote that this flight from commitment was "most likely to take place at the level of fantasy (individual and collective)." In focusing on culture, it is difficult to gauge the degree to which films such as ''[[Scott of the Antarctic (film)|Scott of the Antarctic]]'' represented the era’s masculine fantasies.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Michael Roper’s call to focus on the subjectivity of masculinity addresses this cultural bias, because broad understanding is set aside for an examination "of what the relationship of the codes of masculinity is to actual men, to existential matters, to persons and to their psychic make-up" (Tosh's human experience).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = ‘Slipping out of view: subjectivity and emotion in gender history’,|last = Roper|first = Michael|date = 2005|journal = History Workshop 59|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Tosh, the culture of masculinity has outlived its usefulness because it cannot fulfill the initial aim of this history (to discover how manhood was conditioned and experienced) and he urged "questions of behaviour and agency".&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; His work on Victorian masculinity uses individual experience in letters and sketches to illustrate broader cultural and social customs, such as birthing or Christmas traditions.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

Stefan Dudink believes that the methodological approach (trying to categorize masculinity as a phenomenon) undermined its [[Historiography|historiographic]] development.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = The trouble with men: Problems in the history of masculinity|last = Dudink|first = Stefan|date = 1998|journal = European Journal of Cultural Studies 1|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt; This approach stabilized masculinity, making it appear natural and concrete in the historical record and "placing it beyond history".{{citation needed|date=June 2015}} George Mosse’s work used masculinity as a stable stereotype in normative society: "[Masculinity] was concrete and definite enough, constituting a coherent system that can easily be examined".{{citation needed|date=June 2015}} Abigail Solomou-Godeau’s work on post-revolutionary French art addresses a strong, constant patriarchy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Male Trouble: A Crisis in Representation|last = Solomou-Godeau|first = Abigail|publisher = |year = 1997|isbn = |location = London|pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Jeanne Boydston supports limiting gender as a category of analysis because the concept (as well as femininity and masculinity) has become too rigid in historical thought. This leads to a stable concept, unvarying in all geographic contexts and cultures, and a dichotomy between masculinity and femininity. These issues may be addressed by destabilizing the concept of masculinity, accepting its evolution and focusing on history rather than concept. Dudink calls for an engagement with masculinities (plural) and an analysis of tension between "normativity and individualist that characterises masculinity".{{citation needed|date=June 2015}} Connell’s argument for thinking about masculinities in the plural parallels Boydston’s call for a multifaceted view of social history and Simon Szreter’s work on gender in Britain, which emphasizes the plurality of identity and the intersection between class and gender (because gender cannot be studied in a vacuum) and regional distinctions (to avoid overarching generalizations).{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}

Tosh’s overall assessment is that a shift is needed in conceptualizing the topic&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; back to the history of masculinity as a speciality aiming to reach a broader audience, rather than as an analytical tool of cultural and social history. The importance he places on public history hearkens back to the initial aims of gender history, which sought to use history to enlighten and change the present. Tosh appeals to historians to live up to the "social expectation" of their work,&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; which would also require a greater focus on subjectivity and masculinity. This view is contrary to Dudink’s; the latter called for an "outflanking movement" towards the history of masculinity, in response to the errors he perceived in the study.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; This would do the opposite of what Tosh called for, deconstructing masculinity by not placing it at the center of historical exploration and using discourse and culture as indirect avenues towards a more-representational approach. In a study of the [[Low Countries]], Dudink proposes moving beyond the history of masculinity by embedding analysis into the exploration of nation and nationalism (making masculinity a lens through which to view conflict and nation-building).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = ‘Multipurpose Masculinities Gender and Power in Low Countries Histories of Masculinity’,|last = Dudink|first = Stefan|date = 2012|journal = Low Countries Historical Review|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Martin Francis' work on domesticity through a cultural lens moves beyond the history of masculinity because "men constantly travelled back and forward across the frontier of domesticity, if only in the realm of the imagination"; normative codes of behavior do not fully encompass the male experience.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Media images of boys and young men may lead to the persistence of harmful concepts of masculinity. According to men's-rights activists, the media does not address men's-rights issues and men are often portrayed negatively in advertising.&lt;ref&gt;Farrell, W. &amp; Sterba, J. P. (2008) Does Feminism Discriminate Against Men: A Debate (Point and Counterpoint), New York: Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Peter Jackson called hegemonic masculinity "economically exploitative" and "socially oppressive": "The form of oppression varies from patriarchal controls over women's bodies and reproductive rights, through ideologies of domesticity, femininity and compulsory heterosexuality, to social definitions of the value of work, the nature of skill and the differential remuneration of 'productive' and 'reproductive' labor."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title = The Cultural Politics of Masculinity: Towards a Social Geography | journal = Transactions of the Institute of British Geographers | year = 1991 | first = Peter | last = Jackson | volume = 16 | issue = 2 | pages = 199–213 | accessdate = 2013-04-26 | doi=10.2307/622614}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{anchor|Masculine gender role stress}}Gender-role stress===
In 1987 Eisler and Skidmore studied masculinity, creating the idea of "masculine stress" and finding three elements of masculinity which often result in emotional stress:
* The emphasis on prevailing in situations requiring body and fitness
* Being perceived as emotional
* The need for adequacy in sexual matters and financial status

Because of social norms and pressures associated with masculinity, men with spinal-cord injuries must adapt their self-identity to the losses associated with such injuries; this may "lead to feelings of decreased physical and sexual prowess with lowered self-esteem and a loss of male identity. Feelings of guilt and overall loss of control are also experienced."&lt;ref&gt;Hutchinson, Susan L "Heroic masculinity following spinal cord injury: Implications for therapeutic recreation practice and research". Therapeutic Recreation Journal. FindArticles.com. 07 Apr, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Research also suggests that men feel social pressure to endorse traditional masculine male models in advertising. Brett Martin and Juergen Gnoth (2009) found that although feminine men privately preferred feminine models, they expressed a preference for traditional masculine models in public; according to the authors, this reflected social pressure on men to endorse traditional masculine norms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Martin | first1 = Brett A. S. | last2 = Gnoth | first2 = Juergen | year = 2009 | title = Is the Marlboro Man the Only Alternative? The Role of Gender Identity and Self-Construal Salience in Evaluations of Male Models | url = http://www.basmartin.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/Martin-Gnoth-2009.pdf | format = PDF | journal = Marketing Letters | volume = 20 | issue = | pages = 353–367 | doi=10.1007/s11002-009-9069-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A discussion of masculinities relative to a man's social status and political power has begun. According to Joseph Pleck,&lt;ref name=nomas.org&gt;{{cite web|last1=Pleck|first1=Joseph|title=Understanding Patriarchy and Men's Power|url=http://www.nomas.org/node/176|website=nomas.org|publisher=''National Organization for Men Against Sexism'' (Nomas)|accessdate=21 March 2015|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100301004232/http://www.nomas.org/node/176|archivedate=1 March 2010|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; a system of male-to-male relationships exists in North American patriarchal society. Hierarchies are demarcated by levels of masculinity, equated with physical composition in youth and the acquisition of wealth and women with age.&lt;ref name="nomas.org"/&gt;

In their book ''Raising Cain: Protecting The Emotional Life of Boys'', [[Dan Kindlon]] and Michael Thompson wrote that although all boys are born loving and empathic, exposure to gender socialization (the tough male ideal and [[hypermasculinity]]) limits their ability to function as emotionally-healthy adults. According to Kindlon and Thompson, boys lack the ability to understand and express emotions productively because of the stress imposed by masculine gender roles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Barker|first=Dan Kindlon, Michael Thompson with Teresa|title=Raising Cain : protecting the emotional life of boys|year=2000|publisher=Ballantine Books|location=New York|isbn=0-345-43485-4|pages=1–20|edition=1st trade pbk.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{anchor|Notion of "masculinity in crisis"}}"Masculinity in crisis"===
A theory of "masculinity in crisis" has emerged;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Horrocks|first=Rooger|title=Masculinities in Crisis: Myths, Fantasies, and Realities|year=1994|publisher=St Martin's Press|isbn=0333593227|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=k24dAQAAMAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Marked Men: White Masculinity in Crisis |last= Robinson |first= Sally |authorlink= |year= 2000 |publisher= [[Columbia University Press]] |location= New York |isbn= 978-0-231-50036-4 |page= 5 |pages= |accessdate= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Australian archeologist Peter McAllister said, "I have a strong feeling that masculinity is in crisis. Men are really searching for a role in modern society; the things we used to do aren't in much demand anymore".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rogers| first = Thomas| title = The dramatic decline of the modern man|url=http://www.salon.com/2010/11/14/manthropology_interview/singleton/|newspaper = [[Salon (website)|Salon]]|date = November 14, 2010|accessdate = June 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others see the changing labor market as a source of stress. [[Deindustrialization]] and the replacement of [[Smokestack industry|smokestack industries]] by technology have allowed more women to enter the labor force, reducing its emphasis on physical strength.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| ref=harv| last = Beynon| first = John| authorlink =| title = Masculinities and culture| url =| publisher = [[Open University Press]]| location = Philadelphia | year = 2002| chapter = Chapter 4: Masculinities and the notion of 'crisis'| chapterurl =| pages = 86–89| isbn = 978-0-335-19988-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The crisis has also been attributed to [[feminism]] and its questioning of male dominance and rights granted to men solely on the basis of sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| ref=harv| last = Beynon| first = John| authorlink =| title = Masculinities and culture| url =| publisher = [[Open University Press]]| location = Philadelphia | year = 2002| chapter = Chapter 4: Masculinities and the notion of 'crisis'| chapterurl =| pages = 83–86| isbn = 978-0-335-19988-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; British sociologist John MacInnes wrote that "masculinity has always been in one crisis or another", suggesting that the crises arise from the "fundamental incompatibility between the core principle of modernity that all human beings are essentially equal (regardless of their sex) and the core tenet of patriarchy that men are naturally superior to women and thus destined to rule over them."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = MacInnes | first = John | authorlink = | title = The end of masculinity: the confusion of sexual genesis and sexual difference in modern society | year = 1998 | publisher = Open University Press | location = Philadelphia | page = 11 | isbn = 978-0-335-19659-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

John Beynon examined the disussion of masculinity in crisis, finding that masculinity and men are often conflated and it is unclear whether masculinity, men or both are allegedly in crisis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| ref=harv| last = Beynon| first = John| title = Masculinities and culture| publisher = [[Open University Press]]| location = Philadelphia| year = 2002| chapter = Chapter 4: Masculinities and the notion of 'crisis'| page = 76| isbn = 978-0-335-19988-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Beynon, the "crisis" is not a recent phenomenon; he illustrated several periods of masculine crisis throughout history (some predating the women's movement and [[post-industrial society]]), suggesting that due to masculinity's fluid nature "crisis is constitutive of masculinity itself."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| ref=harv| last = Beynon| first = John| title = Masculinities and culture| publisher = [[Open University Press]]| location = Philadelphia
| year = 2002| chapter = Chapter 4: Masculinities and the notion of 'crisis'| pages = 89–93| isbn = 978-0-335-19988-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Film scholar Leon Hunt agreed: "Whenever masculinity's 'crisis' actually started, it certainly seems to have been in place by the 1970s".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Hunt | first = Leon | year = 1998 | title = British low culture: from safari suits to sexploitation | publisher = [[Routledge]] | location = London, New York | page = 73 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=3dvtQEetWrsC&amp;pg=PA73 | isbn = 978-0-415-15182-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Columns-list|3|
*[[Bear (gay culture)]]
*[[Bromance]]
*[[Castro clone]]
*[[Emasculation]]
*[[Gender role]]
*[[Gender roles in non-heterosexual communities]]
*[[Hegemonic masculinity]]
*[[Leather subculture]]
*[[Men's spaces]]
*[[Men's liberation]]
*[[Men's rights]]
*[[Men's movement]]
*[[Men's World Day]]
*[[Model of masculinity under fascist Italy]]
*[[Mythopoetic men's movement]]
*[[Raewyn Connell]]
*[[Victorian masculinity]]
}}

== Notable works on masculinity ==

* Manhood: a new definition, [[Stephen A. Shapiro]], 1984.
* Absent fathers, lost sons, [[Guy Corneau]], 1985.
* Wild at heart, [[John Eldredge]], 2001.
* The new manhood, [[Steve Biddulph]], 2010.

==Notes==
{{Notes}}

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|30em}}

;Bibliography
*{{cite book
| ref=harv
| last = Beynon
| first = John
| authorlink =
| title = Masculinities and culture
| url =
| publisher = [[Open University Press]]
| location = Philadelphia
| year = 2002
| chapter = Chapter 4: Masculinities and the notion of 'crisis'
| chapterurl =
| pages = 75–97
| isbn = 978-0-335-19988-4
}}
*{{cite book
| ref=harv
| last = Reeser
| first = Todd W.
| authorlink =
| editor-first =
| editor-last =
| title = Masculinities in theory: an introduction
| url = 
| publisher = [[Wiley-Blackwell]]
| location = Malden, MA
| year = 2010
| chapter = 
| chapterurl = 
| isbn = 978-1-4051-6859-5
}}
*{{cite book
| last = Connell
| first = R.W.
| title = The Social Organization of Masculinity
| url = 
| publisher = Polity
| location = Berkeley and Los Angeles, California
| year = 2001
| chapter = 3
| isbn = 978-0-520-24698-0
}}
*Levine, Martin P. (1998). ''Gay Macho''. New York: New York University Press. ISBN 0-8147-4694-2.
*Stibbe, Arran. (2004). "Health and the Social Construction of Masculinity in Men's Health Magazine." Men and Masculinities; 7 (1) July, pp.&amp;nbsp;31–51.
*[[Lance Strate|Strate, Lance]] "Beer Commercials: A Manual on Masculinity" Men's Lives Kimmel, Michael S. and Messner, Michael A. ed. Allyn and Bacon. Boston, London: 2001

==Further reading==
;Contemporary
*Arrindell, Willem A., Ph.D. (1 October 2005) "Masculine Gender Role Stress" Psychiatric Times Pg. 31
*Ashe, Fidelma (2007) The New Politics of Masculinity, London and New York: Routledge.
* [[bell hooks]], ''We Real Cool: Black Men and Masculinity'', Taylor &amp; Francis 2004, ISBN 0-415-96927-1
*Broom A. and Tovey P. (Eds) Men’s Health: Body, Identity and Social Context London; John Wiley and Sons Inc.
*Burstin, Fay "What's Killing Men". Herald Sun (Melbourne, [[Australia]]). October 15, 2005.
*Canada, Geoffrey "Learning to Fight" Men's Lives Kimmel, Michael S. and Messner, Michael A. ed. Allyn and Bacon. Boston, London: 2001
*{{cite book | last = Connell | first = R.W. | author-link = Raewyn Connell | title = Masculinities | publisher = Polity Press | location = Cambridge | year = 2005 | isbn = 0745634273 }}
*Courtenay, Will "Constructions of masculinity and their influence on men's well-being: a theory of gender and health" Social Science and Medicine, yr: 2000 vol: 50 iss: 10 pg: 1385–1401
* {{cite book | last = Donovan | first = Jack | author-link = Jack Donovan | title = The way of men | publisher = Dissonant Hum | location = Milwaukie, Oregon | year = 2012 | isbn = 9780985452308 }}
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Durham | first1 = Meenakshi G. | last2 = Oates | first2 = Thomas P. | authorlink1 = Meenakshi Gigi Durham | title = The mismeasure of masculinity: the male body, 'race' and power in the enumerative discourses of the NFL Draft | journal = Patterns of Prejudice | volume = 38 | issue = 3 | pages = 301–320 | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis Online | doi = 10.1080/0031322042000250475 | year = 2004 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/0031322042000250475 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
*Galdas P.M. and Cheater F.M. (2010) Indian and Pakistani men’s accounts of seeking medical help for angina and myocardial infarction in the UK: Constructions of marginalised masculinity or another version of hegemonic masculinity? Qualitative Research in Psychology
* Juergensmeyer, Mark (2005): ''Why guys throw bombs. About terror and masculinity'' [http://web.fu-berlin.de/gpo/pdf/juergensmeyer/juergensmeyer_e.pdf (pdf)]
*Kaufman, Michael "The Construction of Masculinity and the Triad of Men's Violence". Men's Lives Kimmel, Michael S. and Messner, Michael A. ed. Allyn and Bacon. Boston, London: 2001
* {{Cite journal | last = Lawson | first = Robert | title = The construction of ‘tough’ masculinity: Negotiation, alignment and rejection | journal = [[Gender and Language]] | volume = 7 | issue = 3 | pages = 369–395 | publisher = [[Equinox Publishing (London)|Equinox]] | year = 2013 | url = http://www.equinoxpub.com/journals/index.php/GL/article/view/15627 | ref = harv | postscript = . | doi=10.1558/genl.v7i3.369}}
*Levant &amp; Pollack (1995) A New Psychology of Men, New York: BasicBooks
*[[Harvey Mansfield|Mansfield, Harvey]]. ''[[Manliness (book)|Manliness]]''. New Haven: [[Yale University Press]], 2006. ISBN 0-300-10664-5
* {{Cite journal | last = Lupton | first = Ben | title = Explaining men's entry into female-concentrated occupations: issues of masculinity and social class | journal = [[Gender, Work and Organization]] | volume = 13 | issue = 2 | pages = 103–128 | publisher = [[John Wiley &amp; Sons|Wiley]] | doi = 10.1111/j.1468-0432.2006.00299.x | date = March 2006 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-0432.2006.00299.x | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
* Reeser, T. ''Masculinities in Theory'', Malden: Wiley-Blackwell, 2010.
*Robinson, L. (October 21, 2005). Not just boys being boys: Brutal hazings are a product of a culture of masculinity defined by violence, aggression and domination. Ottawa Citizen (Ottawa, Ontario).
*Stephenson, June (1995). ''Men are Not Cost Effective: Male Crime in America.'' ISBN 0-06-095098-6
*Simpson, Mark (1994). Male Impersonators: Men Performing Masculinity. New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-41590991-0. Also published by Cassell, London, ISBN 0-304-32808-1 pbk,
*Tozer, Malcolm (2015). ''The Ideal of Manliness: The Legacy of Thring's Uppingham''. Truro: Sunnyrest Books, 2015. (ISBN 978-1-326-41574-7, hardback; ISBN 978-1-329-54273-0, paperback).
* Walsh, Fintan. Male Trouble: Masculinity and the Performance of Crisis. Basingstoke and New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2010.
*Williamson P. "Their own worst enemy" Nursing Times: 91 (48) 29 November 95 p 24–7
*Wray Herbert "Survival Skills" U.S. News &amp; World Report Vol. 139, No. 11; Pg. 63 September 26, 2005
*[http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0014/001465/146514e.pdf "Masculinity for Boys"; published by UNESCO, New Delhi, 2006; ]
*Smith, Bonnie G., Hutchison, Beth. Gendering Disability.  Rutgers University Press, 2004.

;Historical
*[[Michael Kimmel]], Manhood in America, New York [etc.]:  The Free Press    1996
*A Question of Manhood: A Reader in U.S. Black Mens History and Masculinity, edited by Earnestine Jenkins and Darlene Clark Hine, Indiana University press vol1: 1999, vol. 2: 2001
*Gary Taylor, Castration: An Abbreviated History of Western Manhood, Routledge 2002
*[[Klaus Theweleit]], Male fantasies, Minneapolis : University of Minnesota Press, 1987 and Polity Press, 1987
*Peter N. Stearns, Be a Man!: Males in Modern Society, Holmes &amp; Meier Publishers, 1990
*Shuttleworth, Russell. "Disabled Masculinity." Gendering Disability.  Ed. Bonnie G. Smith and Beth Hutchison.  Rutgers University Press, New Brunswick, New Jersey, 2004. 166–178.

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{wiktionary|masculinity}}
'''Bibliographic'''
*[http://mensbiblio.xyonline.net/ The Men's Bibliography], a comprehensive bibliography of writing on men, masculinities, gender and sexualities, listing over 16,700 works. (mainly from a constructionist perspective)
*[http://www.boyhoodstudies.com Boyhood Studies], features a 2200+ bibliography of young masculinities.
'''Other'''
* [http://www.practicalmanliness.com Practical Manliness], A manly blog that applies "historical ideals to modern men".
*[http://www.mkpchicago.org The ManKind Project of Chicago], supporting men in leading meaningful lives of integrity, accountability, responsibility, and emotional intelligence
*[http://menanddepression.nimh.nih.gov/ NIMH web pages on men and depression], talks about men and their depression and how to get help.
* [http://howellgroup.org/parsifal.html Article entitled "Wounded Masculinity: Parsifal and The Fisher King Wound"] The symbolism of the story as it relates to the Wounded Masculinity of Men by Richard Sanderson M.Ed., B.A.
*[http://www.bullmensfiction.com BULL], Print and online literary journal specializing in masculine fiction for a male audience.
* [http://www.artofmanliness.com Art of Manliness], An online web magazine/blog dedicated to "reviving the lost art of manliness".
* [http://masculinityconspiracy.com The Masculinity Conspiracy], An online book critiquing constructions of masculinity.
* [http://www.npr.org/series/323986426/men-in-america Men in America], series by National Public Radio
{{Masculism}}

[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Gender roles]]
[[Category:Masculinity]]
[[Category:Men]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>