<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111012154055|455221698" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5741883" pageid="5741883" ns="0" title="Compton&#039;s Cafeteria riot"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-10-12T15:42:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Compton.jpg|thumb|Gene Compton's Cafeteria Riot 40th Anniversary Historical Marker at corner of Taylor and Turk in San Francisco]]
The '''Compton's Cafeteria Riot''' occurred  in August 1966 in  the [[Tenderloin, San Francisco, California|Tenderloin]] district of [[San Francisco]]. This incident was one of the first recorded [[transgender]] riots in United States history, preceding the more famous 1969 [[Stonewall Riots]] in [[New York City]].&lt;ref group=note&gt;A smaller-scale riot broke out in 1959 in Los Angeles, when the drag queens and street [[Male prostitution|hustlers]] who hung out at Cooper's Donuts and who were frequently harassed by the [[Los Angeles Police Department|LAPD]] fought back after police arrested three people, including [[John Rechy]]. Patrons began pelting the police with donuts and coffee cups. The LAPD called for back-up and arrested a number of rioters. Rechy and the other two original detainees were able to escape (Faderman and Timmons, pp. 1–2).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
Compton's Cafeteria was one of a chain of [[cafeteria]]s, owned by Gene Compton, in San Francisco from the 1940s to the 1970s. The Tenderloin location of Compton's at 101 Taylor Street (at Turk)—open from 1954 to 1972—was one of the few places where transgender people could congregate publicly in the city, because they were unwelcome in [[gay bar]]s. In addition, the cafeteria was open all hours until the riots occurred. Back then, trangender people were commonly referred to as ''Hair Fairies''.  Because [[cross-dressing]] was illegal at the time, police could use the presence of transgender people in a bar as a pretext for making a raid and closing the bar.

Many of the militant [[Male prostitutes|hustlers]] and street queens involved in the riot were members of Vanguard, the first known gay youth organization in the United States, which had been organized earlier that year with the help of radical ministers working with [[Glide Memorial Church]], a center for progressive social activism in the Tenderloin for many years. A [[lesbian]] group of street people was also formed called the [[Street Orphans]].&lt;ref name="screaming"&gt;''Screaming Queens: The Riot at Compton's Cafeteria'' (documentary film by Victor Silverman and Susan Stryker, 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cause of the riot==
On the first night of the riot, the management of Compton's called the police when some transgender customers became raucous. When a police officer accustomed to manhandling the Compton's clientele attempted to arrest one of the [[trans women]], she threw her coffee in his face. At that point the riot began, dishes and furniture were thrown, and the restaurant's plate-glass windows were smashed. Police called for reinforcements as the fighting spilled into the street, where a police car had all its windows broken out and a sidewalk newsstand was burned down.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

The next night, more transgender people, [[hustlers]], Tenderloin street people, and other members of the [[LGBT]] community joined in a [[picketing (protest)|picket]] of the cafeteria, which would not allow transgender people back in. The demonstration ended with the newly installed plate-glass windows being smashed again.&lt;ref name="screaming"/&gt;

==Effects of the riot==
The riot marked a turning point in the local LGBT movement.  According to the online encyclopedia [[glbtq.com]]:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/san_francisco,2.html glbtq &gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; San Francisco&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In the aftermath of the riot at Compton's, a network of transgender social, psychological, and medical support services was established, which culminated in 1968 with the creation of the [[National Transsexual Counseling Unit]] [NTCU], the first such peer-run support and advocacy organization in the world.&lt;/blockquote&gt; Serving as an overseer to the NTCU was Sergeant [[Elliott Blackstone]], designated in 1962 as the first [[San Francisco Police Department]] liaison to what was then called the "[[homophile]] community."

==See also==
* [[List of pre-Stonewall LGBT actions in the United States]]

==Notes==
&lt;references group=note/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{IMDb title|0464189|Screaming Queens: The Riot at Compton's Cafeteria}}
*[http://www.sfgov.org/site/uploadedfiles/bdsupvrs/resolutions06/r0310-06.pdf San Francisco resolution commemorating the riot]
*[http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/06/23/BAG7KJILMR17.DTL  San Francisco Chronicle: Pride parade salute for an unlikely ally; Police officer who reached out in 1960s to be grand marshal]
*[http://homepage.mac.com/trannytalk/iMovieTheater111.html TRANNY TALK: Video of 40th Anniversary Commemoration]{{Dead link|date=February 2010}}
*[http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2006-06-24-transgendered_x.htm?POE=click-refer USA TODAY: As gay pride hits stride, transgenders find more acceptance]

{{LGBT |rights=yes |culture=yes}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Compton's Cafeteria Riot}}
[[Category:1966 riots]]
[[Category:Riots and civil disorder in the United States]]
[[Category:LGBT history in the United States]]
[[Category:1960s in LGBT history]]
[[Category:LGBT civil rights demonstrations]]
[[Category:LGBT history in San Francisco, California]]
[[Category:History of LGBT civil rights in the United States]]

[[es:Disturbios de la cafetería Compton's]]
[[it:Sommossa della Compton's Cafeteria]]
[[ja:コンプトンズ・カフェテリアの反乱]]
[[tr:Compton's Cafeteria ayaklanması]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>