<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161013074510|744121902" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5741883" pageid="5741883" ns="0" title="Compton&#039;s Cafeteria riot"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-10-30T00:44:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Plaque commemorating Compton's Cafeteria riot.jpg|thumb|Gene Compton's Cafeteria Riot 40th Anniversary Historical Marker at corner of Taylor and Turk in San Francisco]]
The '''Compton's Cafeteria Riot''' occurred  in August 1966 in  the [[Tenderloin, San Francisco, California|Tenderloin]] district of [[San Francisco]]. This incident was one of the first recorded [[transgender]] riots in United States history, preceding the more famous 1969 [[Stonewall Riots]] in [[New York City]].&lt;ref group=note&gt;A smaller-scale riot broke out in 1959 in Los Angeles, when the drag queens and street [[Male prostitution|hustlers]] who hung out at Cooper's Donuts and who were frequently harassed by the [[Los Angeles Police Department|LAPD]] fought back after police arrested three people, including [[John Rechy]]. Patrons began pelting the police with donuts and coffee cups. The LAPD called for back-up and arrested a number of rioters. Rechy and the other two original detainees were able to escape. [[Lillian Faderman|Faderman, Lillian]] and Stuart Timmons (2006). ''Gay L.A.: A History of Sexual Outlaws, Power Politics, and Lipstick Lesbians''. Basic Books. pp. 1–2. ISBN 0-465-02288-X&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
Compton's Cafeteria was one of a chain of [[cafeteria]]s, owned by Gene Compton, in San Francisco from the 1940s to the 1970s. The Tenderloin location of Compton's at 101 Taylor Street (at Turk)—open from 1954 to 1972—was one of the few places where transgender people could congregate publicly in the city, because they were unwelcome in [[gay bar]]s.&lt;!--this says they were unwelcome in gay bars, but not why Compton's was "one of the few [other] places" they could gather; need to explain--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sandeen|first=Autumn|title=The Compton's Cafeteria Riot|url=http://www.gaylesbiantimes.com/?id=17476|publisher=Gay and Lesbian Times|accessdate=24 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition, the cafeteria was open all hours until the riots occurred. Most of the fights&lt;!--what fights? this is the first use of the term; if this means the "riots" mentioned earlier, should say so; as this is written in the past tense, it suggests the 'fights' preceded the riots--&gt; occurred from 2-3 am so they were forced to close at midnight. Because [[cross-dressing]] was illegal at the time, police could use the presence of transgender people in a bar as a pretext for making a raid and closing the bar.{{citation needed|date = April 2014}}

Many of the militant [[Male prostitutes|hustlers]] and street queens involved in the riot were members of Vanguard, the first known gay youth organization in the United States, which had been organized earlier that year with the help of radical ministers working with [[Glide Memorial Church]], a center for progressive social activism in the Tenderloin for many years. A [[lesbian]] group of street people was also formed called the [[Street Orphans (gang)|Street Orphans]].&lt;ref name="screaming"&gt;''Screaming Queens: The Riot at Compton's Cafeteria'' (documentary film by Victor Silverman and [[Susan Stryker]], 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cause of the riot==
In the 1960s the Compton’s Cafeteria staff began to call the police to crack down on transgender individuals, who would frequent the restaurant.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"&gt;Stryker, Susan. Transgender History. Berkeley: Seal, 2008. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; In response to police arrests, the transgender community launched a picket of Compton’s Cafeteria.&lt;ref name="Screaming Queens 2005"&gt;Screaming Queens: The Riot at Compton's Cafeteria. 2005. Film.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the picket was unsuccessful, it was one of the first demonstrations against transgender violence in San Francisco.&lt;ref name="Screaming Queens 2005"/&gt; On the first night of the riot, the management of Compton's called the police when some transgender customers became raucous. In the 50's and 60's police officers were known to mistreat transgender people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.queerty.com/before-stonewall-there-was-the-coopers-donuts-and-comptons-cafeteria-riots-20111007/2/|title=Before Stonewall, There Was The Cooper’s Donuts And Compton’s Cafeteria Riots|date=7 October 2011|work=Queerty|accessdate=5 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; When one of these known officers attempted to arrest one of the [[trans women]], she threw her coffee in his face. At that point the riot began, dishes and furniture were thrown, and the restaurant's plate-glass windows were smashed. Police called for reinforcements as the fighting spilled into the street, where a police car had all its windows broken out and a sidewalk newsstand was burned down.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"/&gt; The exact date of the riot is unknown because 1960 police records no longer exist and the riot was not covered by newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gaycitynews.com/gcn_526/recallingasanfrancisco.html|title=Recalling a San Francisco Stonewall|work=gaycitynews.com|accessdate=5 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The next night, more transgender people, [[Male prostitution|hustlers]], Tenderloin street people, and other members of the [[LGBT]] community joined in a [[picketing (protest)|picket]] of the cafeteria, which would not allow transgender people back in. The demonstration ended with the newly installed plate-glass windows being smashed again.&lt;ref name="screaming"/&gt;

==Effects of the riot==

[[Image:Felicia "Flames" Elizondo at Compton's Cafeteria Riot 50th anniversary.jpg|thumb|left|[[Felicia Elizondo|Felicia "Flames" Elizondo]] speaks at a celebration of the 50th anniversary of the Compton's Cafeteria Riot.]]

The riot marked a turning point in the local LGBT movement.  According to the online encyclopedia [[glbtq.com]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/san_francisco,2.html|title=glbtq &gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; San Francisco|work=glbtq.com|accessdate=5 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In the aftermath of the riot at Compton's, a network of transgender social, psychological, and medical support services was established, which culminated in 1968 with the creation of the [[National Transsexual Counseling Unit]] [NTCU], the first such peer-run support and advocacy organization in the world.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Serving as an overseer to the NTCU was Sergeant [[Elliott Blackstone]], designated in 1962 as the first [[San Francisco Police Department]] liaison to what was then called the "[[homophile]] community." According to Susan Stryker, Compton’s Cafeteria riot was “the first known incident of collective militant queer resistance to police harassment in U.S. history." Transgender people finally stood up to the abuse and discrimination by police officers.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"/&gt; The riot "did not solve the problems that transgender people in the Tenderloin faced daily", but prompted the city to begin addressing them as citizens rather than as a problem to be removed.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"/&gt; Police brutality towards them decreased over time,&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"/&gt; and they had less fear of being heckled by the police department for dressing how they chose during the daytime.&lt;ref name="Screaming Queens 2005"/&gt;

On June 24, 2016, at the conclusion of the San Francisco [[Trans March]], a new street sign was unveiled, renaming the 100 block of Taylor Street to Gene Compton's Cafeteria Way.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Staver|first1=Sari|title=Street renaming highlights Trans March|url=http://www.ebar.com/news/article.php?sec=news&amp;article=71669|website=[[Bay Area Reporter]]|accessdate=June 25, 2016|date=June 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="missionlocal"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Chavez|first1=Lola M.|title=SF Trans Celebration Boos Pols and Says No to More Police|url=http://missionlocal.org/2016/06/sf-trans-celebration-boos-pols-and-says-no-to-more-police/|website=Mission Local|accessdate=June 25, 2016|date=June 25, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sfist"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Kukura|first1=Joe|title=Video: Politicians Booed As Trans March (Un)Officially Kicks Off SF's Pride Weekend|url=http://sfist.com/2016/06/25/video_politicians_booed_as_trans_ma.php|website=SFist|publisher=Gothamist LLC|accessdate=June 25, 2016|date=June 25, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2016, a number of events were held to celebrate the 50th anniversary of the riot, including a gathering in Boeddeker Park in the Tenderloin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Compton's Cafeteria Riot 50th Anniversary|url=http://www.sfcenter.org/events/comptons-cafeteria-riot-50th-anniversary|website=The SF LGBT Center|accessdate=August 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Calendar of Events for the Compton’s Cafeteria Riot 50th Anniversary|url=http://sfbaytimes.com/calendar-of-events-for-the-comptons-cafeteria-riot-50th-anniversary/|website=[[San Francisco Bay Times]]|accessdate=August 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|LGBT|San Francisco Bay Area}}
*[[List of pre-Stonewall LGBT actions in the United States]]

==Notes==
&lt;references group=note/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{IMDb title|0464189|Screaming Queens: The Riot at Compton's Cafeteria}}
*[http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/06/23/BAG7KJILMR17.DTL  San Francisco Chronicle: Pride parade salute for an unlikely ally; Police officer who reached out in 1960s to be grand marshal]
*[http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2006-06-24-transgendered_x.htm?POE=click-refer USA TODAY: As gay pride hits stride, transgenders find more acceptance]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Early U.S. gay rights movement}}
{{LGBT |rights=yes |culture=yes}}
{{Transgender topics}}
}}

{{coord|37|47|00|N|122|24|39|W|region:US_source:kolossus-jawiki|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Compton's Cafeteria Riot}}
[[Category:LGBT-related riots]]
[[Category:1966 riots]]
[[Category:1966 in LGBT history]]
[[Category:LGBT history in San Francisco]]
[[Category:LGBT civil rights demonstrations]]
[[Category:Riots and civil disorder in California]]
[[Category:History of LGBT civil rights in the United States]]
[[Category:1966 in California]]
[[Category:20th century in San Francisco]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>