<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201011182536|983010748" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5741883" pageid="5741883" ns="0" title="Compton&#039;s Cafeteria riot"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-10-11T18:31:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox civil conflict
| title            =Compton's Cafeteria riot 
| subtitle         = 
| partof           =[[Stonewall riots]] 
| image            = Plaque commemorating Compton's Cafeteria riot.jpg
| caption          = Gene Compton's Cafeteria Riot 40th Anniversary Historical Marker at corner of Taylor and Turk in San Francisco
| date             = {{Start date and age|1966|August|}}
| place            = [[Tenderloin, San Francisco, California|Tenderloin]], [[San Francisco]]. U.S.
| coordinates      = 
| causes           = 
| goals            = 
| methods          = 
| status           = 
| result           = 
| side1            = 
| side2            = 
| side3            = 
| leadfigures1     = 
| leadfigures2     = 
| leadfigures3     = 
| howmany1         = 
| howmany2         = 
| howmany3         = 
| casualties1      = 
| casualties2      = 
| casualties3      = 
| fatalities       =
| injuries         =
| arrests          =
| detentions       =
| charged          =
| fined            =
| casualties_label = 
| notes            = 
| sidebox          =
}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}
The '''Compton's Cafeteria Riot''' occurred in August 1966 in the [[Tenderloin, San Francisco, California|Tenderloin]] district of [[San Francisco]]. The incident was one of the first [[LGBT]]-related riots in United States history, preceding the more famous 1969 [[Stonewall Riots]] in [[New York City]].&lt;ref group=note&gt;In 1959 a smaller riot broke out in Los Angeles, when drag queens, lesbians, gay men, and transgender people who frequented [[Cooper Donuts Riot|Cooper Do-nuts]] and who were often harassed by the [[Los Angeles Police Department|LAPD]] fought back after police arrested three people, including [[John Rechy]]. Patrons began pelting the police with donuts and coffee cups. The LAPD called for back-up and arrested a number of rioters. Rechy and the other two original detainees were able to escape. [[Lillian Faderman|Faderman, Lillian]] and Stuart Timmons (2006). ''Gay L.A.: A History of Sexual Outlaws, Power Politics, and Lipstick Lesbians''. Basic Books. pp. 1–2. {{ISBN|0-465-02288-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; It marked the beginning of [[transgender]] activism in San Francisco.&lt;ref name="boyd"&gt;Boyd, Nan Alamilla (2004). "San Francisco" in the ''Encyclopedia of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgendered History in America'', Ed. Marc Stein. Vol. 3. Charles Scribner's Sons. pp. 71–78.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1960s was a pivotal period for sexual, gender, and ethnic minorities, as social movements championing civil rights and sexual liberation came to fruition. Even churches, like [[Glide Memorial Church|Glide Memorial Methodist Church]] in San Francisco, began reaching out to the transgender community. Nevertheless, many police officers resisted these movements and the increasing visibility of these groups, continuing to harass and abuse transgender people. This simultaneous rise in support for transgender rights on the one side and the unwillingness to accept these new ideas on the other created the strain that fueled the riot at Compton's Cafeteria in the summer of 1966. The incident began when a transgender woman resisted arrest by throwing coffee at a police officer. It was followed by drag queens pouring into the streets, fighting back with their high heels and heavy bags.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008" /&gt;

==Background==
Compton's Cafeteria was one of a chain of cafeterias, owned by Gene Compton, in San Francisco from the 1940s to the 1970s. The Tenderloin location of Compton's at 101 Taylor Street (at Turk)—open from 1954 to 1972—was one of the few places where transgender people, especially trans women&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/21/travel/san-francisco-gay-history.html|title=Uncovering Gay History in San Francisco|access-date=2018-07-20|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; who had spent a long evening hustling {{clarify|date=December 2019}}, could congregate publicly in the city, because they were unwelcome in [[gay bar]]s due to [[transphobia]].&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"&gt;{{cite book| last1=Stryker |first1=Susan |title=Transgender History| isbn=9781580056892 |date=2008  |location= Berkeley, CA |publisher= Seal Press |url=https://www.berkeleypubliclibrary.org/content/transgender-history-roots-todays-revolution}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sandeen|first=Autumn|title=The Compton's Cafeteria Riot|url=http://www.gaylesbiantimes.com/?id=17476|publisher=Gay and Lesbian Times|accessdate=24 August 2013|url-status=usurped|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131109075057/http://www.gaylesbiantimes.com/?id=17476|archivedate=9 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Compton's management and staff, in an effort to deter drag queens and trans women, frequently called the police when they were present causing them to be harassed and arrested for a crime called "female impersonation."&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/05/05/404459634/ladies-in-the-streets-before-stonewall-transgender-uprising-changed-lives|title=Ladies In The Streets: Before Stonewall, Transgender Uprising Changed Lives|work=NPR.org|access-date=2018-07-20|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The cafeteria was open all hours until the riots occurred. Most of the fights&lt;!--what fights? this is the first use of the term; if this means the "riots" mentioned earlier, should say so; as this is written in the past tense, it suggests the 'fights' preceded the riots--&gt; occurred from 2-3 am so they were forced to close at midnight. Because [[cross-dressing]] was illegal at the time, police could use the presence of transgender people in a bar as a pretext for making a raid and closing the bar.&lt;ref&gt;Sears, Clare. “Electric Brilliancy: Cross-Dressing Law and Freak Show Displays in Nineteenth-Century San Francisco.” ''WSQ: Women’s Studies Quarterly'' 36, no. 3 (December 14, 2008): 170–87. {{doi|10.1353/wsq.0.0108}}.
&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the militant [[Male prostitutes|hustlers]] and street queens involved in the riot were members of [[Vanguard (gay liberation organization)|Vanguard]], the first known gay youth organization in the United States founded in 1965, which gained the help of radical ministers working with [[Glide Memorial Church]], a center for progressive social activism in the Tenderloin for many years. A [[lesbian]] group of street people was also formed called the [[Street Orphans (gang)|Street Orphans]].&lt;ref name="screaming"&gt;''Screaming Queens: The Riot at Compton's Cafeteria'' (documentary film by Victor Silverman and [[Susan Stryker]], 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of the women that [[Susan Stryker]] interviewed for the documentary film "Screaming Queens: The Riot at Compton's Cafeteria", who were all members of the transgender community in the Tenderloin District during the time of the riot at Compton's Cafeteria, were involved in street prostitution.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008" /&gt; Among these women was [[Tamara Ching]], who is now a [[Sex workers' rights|sex-workers-rights]] activist. They ended up in the profession, many of them lamented, because they faced job discrimination. Eventually, they stopped trying to seek employment elsewhere, though some “fortunate” ones were saved from the dangers of street prostitution because they could “pass” (i.e. they appeared more feminine and could get jobs as dancers or singers). The women who had to sell sex to survive complained of police harassment and abuse by customers. It is clear that social forces—systematic marginalization and discrimination—have forced these women into prostitution, the only viable source of income.

==Cause of the riot==
In the 1960s the Compton's Cafeteria staff began to call the police to crack down on transgender individuals, who went to the restaurant.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"/&gt; Management felt that transgender customers were loitering and causing them to lose more desirable business. In response, they implemented a service fee directed at transgender individuals and blatantly harassed them in an attempt to get them to leave the restaurant.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"/&gt; In response to police arrests, the transgender community launched a [[picketing (protest)|picket]] of Compton's Cafeteria.&lt;ref name="Screaming Queens 2005"&gt;Screaming Queens: The Riot at Compton's Cafeteria. 2005. Film.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the picket was unsuccessful, it was one of the first demonstrations against police violence directed towards transgender people in San Francisco.&lt;ref name="Screaming Queens 2005"/&gt; On the first night of the riot, the management of Compton's called the police when some transgender customers became raucous. Police officers were known to mistreat transgender people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.queerty.com/before-stonewall-there-was-the-coopers-donuts-and-comptons-cafeteria-riots-20111007/2/|title=Before Stonewall, There Was The Cooper's Donuts And Compton's Cafeteria Riots|date=7 October 2011|work=Queerty|accessdate=5 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; When one of these known officers attempted to arrest one of the [[trans women]], she threw her coffee in his face.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008" /&gt; According to the director of ''Screaming Queens,'' Susan Stryker, the cafeteria "erupted."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; At that point the riot began, dishes and furniture were thrown, and the restaurant's plate-glass windows were smashed. Police called for reinforcements as the fighting spilled into the street, where a police car had all its windows broken out and a sidewalk newsstand was burned down.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"/&gt; Dozens of people fought back against the police who forced them into paddy wagons.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

The next night, more transgender people, hustlers, Tenderloin street people, and other members of the LGBT community joined in a picket of the cafeteria, which did not allow transgender people back in. The demonstration ended with the newly installed plate-glass windows being smashed again.&lt;ref name="screaming"/&gt; The exact date of the riot is unknown because 1960 police records no longer exist and the riot was not covered by newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gaycitynews.com/gcn_526/recallingasanfrancisco.html|title=Recalling a San Francisco Stonewall|work=gaycitynews.com|accessdate=5 July 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140417034918/http://gaycitynews.com/gcn_526/recallingasanfrancisco.html|archive-date=17 April 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effects of the riot==

=== Vanguard Street Actions ===
Following the Compton's riot(s), a queer youth group by the name of Vanguard orchestrated some notable actions.

The group of queer youth—many transgender, many engaged in survival sex work and without stable housing—had formed as a social and political group beginning in 1965.  They initially formed under the Glide Memorial Church, a radical offshoot of the United Methodist Church.  Vanguard's politics highlighted “the issues facing gay and transgender youth in the 1960s produced radical insights into the connections between economic class, police violence, incarceration, and homophobia.”&lt;ref name="worldcat.org"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Captive genders : trans embodiment and the prison industrial complex|others=Stanley, Eric A.,, Smith, Nat|isbn=9781849352345|edition= Expanded second |location=Oakland, CA, USA|oclc=907167460|date = October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early Autumn of 1966, Vanguard hosted a historic “street sweep” in response to the events at Compton's.  About fifty Vanguard members took to the streets of the Tenderloin with push brooms borrowed from the city.  They did so in protest, a direct response to the routine practice of police “sweeping” the streets of known queer neighborhoods—such as the Tenderloin—to remove all the queer people.&lt;ref name="worldcat.org"/&gt;

Many held handmade signs reading “Fall Clean Up: This Is a Vanguard Community Project”, and “All trash is before the broom,” pushing against the idea that they, as people, were in any way disposable or unworthy of human dignity.  Vanguard symbolically called into question the fact that police were treating transgender and queer sex workers like “trash” to be “swept away,” and instead reclaimed public space as their own.&lt;ref name="worldcat.org"/&gt;

=== Later effects of the riot ===
[[Image:Felicia "Flames" Elizondo at Compton's Cafeteria Riot 50th anniversary.jpg|thumb|left|[[Felicia Elizondo|Felicia "Flames" Elizondo]] speaks at a celebration of the 50th anniversary of the Compton's Cafeteria Riot, August 2016.]]

The riot marked a turning point in the local LGBT movement.  According to the online encyclopedia [[glbtq.com]]:
{{quote|In the aftermath of the riot at Compton's, a network of transgender social, psychological, and medical support services was established, which culminated in 1968 with the creation of the [[National Transsexual Counseling Unit]] [NTCU], the first such peer-run support and advocacy organization in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/san_francisco,2.html |title=glbtq &gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; San Francisco |work=glbtq.com |accessdate=5 July 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150705201921/http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/san_francisco%2C2.html |archivedate=5 July 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Felicia Elizondo|Felicia "Flames" Elizondo]], who participated in the Compton's riot,&lt;ref name="hoodline.com"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://hoodline.com/2015/06/tenderloin-pride-remembering-the-compton-s-cafeteria-riot|title=Tenderloin Pride: Remembering The Compton's Cafeteria Riot|website=Hoodline|access-date=2018-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; spoke at a celebration of the 50th anniversary of the Compton's Cafeteria Riot. She said, "A lot of people thought we were sick, mental trash," says Elizondo, who underwent gender reassignment surgery in 1974. "Nobody cared whether we lived or died. Our own families abandoned us and we had nowhere to go."

It was dangerous for queer folks to exist back in 1966 as there were no equality laws and LGBT people were considered "perverts" and "mental cases". Furthermore, transgender people found themselves locked out of most "respectable" jobs and were often forced to turn to prostitution to survive. Many were beaten, and some were brutally murdered.&lt;ref name="hoodline.com"/&gt;

[[File:Trans March San Francisco 20190628-7739.jpg|thumb|right|The intersection of Taylor and Turk Streets, following the 2019 San Francisco [[Trans March]]. A sign under the Taylor street sign reads "Gene Compton's Cafeteria Way".]]

Serving as an overseer to the NTCU was Sergeant [[Elliott Blackstone]], designated in 1962 as the first [[San Francisco Police Department]] liaison to what was then called the "[[homophile]] community." According to [[Susan Stryker]], Compton's Cafeteria riot was “the first known incident of collective militant queer resistance to police harassment in U.S. history." Transgender people finally stood up to the abuse and discrimination by police officers.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008" /&gt; The riot "did not solve the problems that transgender people in the Tenderloin faced daily", but prompted the city to begin addressing them as citizens rather than as a problem to be removed.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008" /&gt; Police brutality towards them decreased over time,&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008" /&gt; and they had less fear of being heckled by the police department for dressing how they chose during the daytime.&lt;ref name="Screaming Queens 2005" /&gt;

On June 24, 2016, at the conclusion of the San Francisco [[Trans March]], a new street sign was unveiled, renaming the 100 block of Taylor Street to Gene Compton's Cafeteria Way.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Staver|first1=Sari|title=Street renaming highlights Trans March|url=http://www.ebar.com/news/article.php?sec=news&amp;article=71669|website=[[Bay Area Reporter]]|accessdate=June 25, 2016|date=June 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="missionlocal"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Chavez|first1=Lola M.|title=SF Trans Celebration Boos Pols and Says No to More Police|url=http://missionlocal.org/2016/06/sf-trans-celebration-boos-pols-and-says-no-to-more-police/|website=Mission Local|accessdate=June 25, 2016|date=June 25, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sfist"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Kukura|first1=Joe|title=Video: Politicians Booed As Trans March (Un)Officially Kicks Off SF's Pride Weekend|url=http://sfist.com/2016/06/25/video_politicians_booed_as_trans_ma.php|website=SFist|publisher=Gothamist LLC|accessdate=June 25, 2016|date=June 25, 2016|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160628150002/http://sfist.com/2016/06/25/video_politicians_booed_as_trans_ma.php|archivedate=June 28, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2016, a number of events were held to celebrate the 50th anniversary of the riot, including a gathering in [[Boeddeker Park]] in the Tenderloin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Compton's Cafeteria Riot 50th Anniversary|url=http://www.sfcenter.org/events/comptons-cafeteria-riot-50th-anniversary|website=The SF LGBT Center|accessdate=August 29, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160911150841/http://www.sfcenter.org/events/comptons-cafeteria-riot-50th-anniversary|archive-date=September 11, 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Calendar of Events for the Compton's Cafeteria Riot 50th Anniversary|url=http://sfbaytimes.com/calendar-of-events-for-the-comptons-cafeteria-riot-50th-anniversary/|website=[[San Francisco Bay Times]]|accessdate=August 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2017, the City of San Francisco recognized the [[Compton's Transgender Cultural District]], the world’s first legally recognized transgender district.&lt;ref name="npr-28jan2019"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Veltman |first1=Chloe |title=San Francisco's Storied Transgender Community Now Has An Official Home |url=https://www.npr.org/2019/01/28/687733897/san-franciscos-storied-transgender-community-now-has-an-official-home |accessdate=June 21, 2019 |work=[[NPR]] |date=January 28, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="guardian-21jun2019"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Levin |first1=Sam |title=Compton's Cafeteria riot: a historic act of trans resistance, three years before Stonewall |url=https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2019/jun/21/stonewall-san-francisco-riot-tenderloin-neighborhood-trans-women |accessdate=June 21, 2019 |work=[[The Guardian]] |date=June 21, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In fiction==
In the first episode of the 2019 [[Netflix]] miniseries ''[[Tales of the City (2019 miniseries)|Tales of the City]]'', Anna Madrigal ([[Olympia Dukakis]]) receives a photograph of herself in front of Compton's, taken shortly after she had arrived in San Francisco. In episode three, her tenant and friend Shawna Hawkins ([[Ellen Page]]) learns about the riot from new friend Claire Duncan ([[Zosia Mamet]]). The two visit the site and lie down together next to the historical marker. The riot is depicted in episode eight of the series, including historical touches like the throwing of the coffee into a cop’s face.&lt;ref name="decider-10jun2019"&gt;{{cite web |last1=White |first1=Brett |title='Tales of the City' on Netflix: Yes, Compton's Cafeteria Riot Really Happened |url=https://decider.com/2019/06/10/tales-of-the-city-netflix-comptons-cafeteria-riot/ |website=[[Decider (website)|Decider]] |accessdate=July 6, 2019 |date=June 10, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

*[[List of LGBT actions in the United States prior to the Stonewall riots]]

{{Portal bar|LGBT|San Francisco Bay Area|Transgender}}

==Notes==
&lt;references group=note/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{IMDb title|0464189|Screaming Queens: The Riot at Compton's Cafeteria}}
*[http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2006/06/23/BAG7KJILMR17.DTL  San Francisco Chronicle: Pride parade salute for an unlikely ally; Police officer who reached out in 1960s to be grand marshal]
*[https://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2006-06-24-transgendered_x.htm?POE=click-refer USA TODAY: As gay pride hits stride, transgenders find more acceptance]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Early U.S. gay rights movement}}
{{LGBT |rights=yes |culture=yes}}
{{Transgender topics}}
}}

{{coord|37|47|00|N|122|24|39|W|region:US_source:kolossus-jawiki|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Compton's Cafeteria Riot}}
[[Category:1966 in California]]
[[Category:1966 in LGBT history]]
[[Category:1966 in San Francisco]]
[[Category:1966 riots]]
[[Category:August 1966 events]]
[[Category:History of LGBT civil rights in the United States]]
[[Category:LGBT civil rights demonstrations]]
[[Category:LGBT history in San Francisco]]
[[Category:LGBT-related riots]]
[[Category:Riots and civil disorder in California]]
[[Category:Transgender culture]]
[[Category:Transgender history in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>