<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041111092205|7336636" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="28661" pageid="28661" ns="0" title="Defamation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-11T12:03:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Verleumdung]]
[[eo:Kalumnio]]
'''Libel''' and '''slander''' are two forms of '''defamation''' (or '''defamation of character'''), which is the [[tort]] of making a false statement of fact that injures someone's reputation. When the communication is in writing, it is termed "libel".  If made via the spoken word, the correct term is "slander", though, in some jurisdictions, where the statement is broadcast on [[radio]] or [[television]] it is "libel" regardless of whether it is a spoken statement or a visual caption.  Both acts share a common legal history, although they may be treated differently under modern legal systems.  The statement need not be derogatory in itself to be actionable, as where it constitutes '''invasion of privacy''' or portrays the person in a '''false light''', as by calling a prominent [[United States Democratic Party|Democrat]] a [[United States Republican Party|Republican]].

Many nations have various civil and criminal penalties for libel and slander, and different conditions for determining whether an offense has occurred.  Some legal systems, including some in the [[United States]], require in some situations that the subject of the communication prove, in a civil court, that the defendant made statement with "malice", meaning either believing it was false or with "reckless disregard" for whether it was.  There are four categories of false statement, however, that are defamatory ''per se'', which means they are so inherently derogatory that a plaintiff need prove only that they were made.  Those are statements accusing a person of:

*having committed a crime
*having a loathsome disease (such as [[leprosy]] long ago or [[AIDS]] now)
*being unchaste (in many jurisdictions this still applies only to females)
*being bad at their trade or business

Other systems, such as that of the [[United Kingdom]], require only that the statements be harmful to a person or company's reputation (more on English defamation law can be found below).

In some jurisdictions, truth does not constitute a defence to charges of libel. Indeed, until the mid-19th century, it was a maxim of UK law that "the greater the truth, the greater the libel", because a true accusation is more damaging to the target&amp;mdash;and hence, more likely to lead to a breach of the peace&amp;mdash;than a false one.

==Origins of libel and slander law==

In most early systems of law verbal injuries were treated as a criminal or quasi-criminal offence, the essence of the injury lying not in pecuniary loss, which may be compensated by damages, but in the personal insult which must be atoned for: a vindictive penalty coming in the place of personal revenge.  By the law of the [[Twelve Tables]], the composition of scurrilous songs and gross noisy public affronts were punished by death.  Minor offences of the same class seem to have found their place under the general conception of injuria, which included ultimately every form of direct personal aggression which involved abuse or insult.

In the later [[Roman law|Roman jurisprudence]], from which many of our modern laws descend, verbal injuries are dealt with in the edict under two heads.  The first comprehended defamatory and injurious statements made in a public manner (''convicium contra bonos mores'').  In this case the essence of the offence lay in the unwarrantable public proclamation.  In such a case the truth of the statements was no justification for the unnecessarily public and insulting manner in which they had been made.  The second head included defamatory statements made in private, and in this case the offence lay in the imputation itself, not in the manner of its publication. The truth was therefore a sufficient defence, for no man had a right to demand legal protection for a false reputation.  Even belief in the truth was enough, because it took away the intention which was essential to the notion of injuria.

The law thus aimed at giving sufficient scope for the discussion of a man's character, while it protected him from needless insult and pain.  The remedy for verbal injuries was long confined to a civil action for a money penalty, which was estimated according to the gravity of the case, and which, although vindictive in its character, doubtless included practically the element of compensation.  But a new remedy was introduced with the extension of the criminal law, under which many kinds of defamation were punished with great severity.  At the same time increased importance attached to the publication of defamatory books and writings, the ''libri'' or ''libelli famosi'', from which we derive our modern use of the word libel; and under the later emperors the latter term came to be specially applied to anonymous accusations or [[pasquil]]s, the dissemination of which was regarded as particularly dangerous, and visited with very severe punishment, whether the matter contained in them were true or false.

==Development of English defamation law==

Modern libel and slander laws, as implemented in many Western nations, are generally descended from [[English defamation law]].  The earlier history of the English law of defamation is somewhat obscure.  Civil actions for damages seem to have been tolerably frequent so far back as the reign of [[Edward I of England|Edward I]] (1272&amp;ndash;1307).  There was no distinction drawn between words written and spoken.  When no pecuniary penalty was involved such cases fell within the old jurisdiction of the [[ecclesiastical court]]s, which were only finally abolished in the eighth century.  It seems, to say the least, uncertain whether any generally applicable criminal process was in use.

The crime of ''[[scandalum magnatum]]'', spreading false reports about the magnates of the realm, was established by statutes, but the first fully reported case in which libel is affirmed generally to be punishable at common law is one tried in the [[Star Chamber]] in the reign of [[James I of England|James I]].  In that case no English authorities are cited except a previous case of the same nature before the same tribunal; the law and terminology appear to be taken directly from Roman sources, with the insertion that libels tended to a breach of the peace; and it seems probable that that not very scrupulous tribunal had simply found it convenient to adopt the very stringent Roman provisions regarding the ''libelli famosi'' without paying any regard to the Roman limitations.  From that time we find both the criminal and civil remedies in full operation.  For more on modern English law, see [[English defamation law]].

==American law==

In the United States, about 75% of defamation lawsuits are filed in state courts, and the remaining 25% in federal courts. A comprehensive discussion of what is and is not libel or slander is difficult, because each state's definition differs.  Some states lump slander and libel together into the same set of laws.  Some states have criminal libel laws on the books, though these are old laws which are infrequently prosecuted.

Most defendants in libel lawsuits are newspapers, which are involved in about twice as many lawsuits as are TV stations.  Most plaintiffs are corporations, business people, entertainers and other public figures, and inmates.  Most states do not allow defamation lawsuits to be filed if the allegedly defamed person is already deceased.  None of the states allow the plaintiff to be a group of people.

In the various states, whether by case law or actual legislation, there are generally several "privileges" that can get a libel case dismissed without proceeding to trial.  These include the allegedly defamatory statement being one of opinion rather than fact; or being "fair comment and criticism", as it is important to society that everyone be able to comment on matters of public interest.

If a defamation lawsuit actually gets to trial, truth is an affirmative defense. Another is if the allegedly defamatory statement is not actually capable of being defamatory&amp;mdash;an insulting statement that does not harm someone's reputation is ''prima facie'' not libelous. Another defense that is presented by accused media companies is "fault"&amp;mdash;a series of court rulings led by ''[[New York Times Co. v. Sullivan]]'' ('''376 U.S. 254''') established that for a plaintiff to win a libel ruling against a newspaper, "actual malice" or "reckless negligence" must be proved on the part of the paper if the statement in question is about a [[public official]] or public figure.  In the case of a private figure, the plaintiff must merely prove negligence.

The [[Associated Press]] estimates that 95% of libel cases involving news stories do not arise from high-profile news stories, but "run of the mill" local stories like news coverage of local criminal investigations or trials, or business profiles.  "Media liability [[insurance]]" is available to newspapers to cover potential damage awards from libel lawsuits.

===History===
Laws regulating slander and libel in the United States began to develop even before the [[American Revolution]].  In one of the most famous cases, [[New York]] publisher [[John Peter Zenger]] was imprisoned in [[1734]] for printing attacks on the governor of the colony.  Zenger won his case by establishing that the truth is an absolute defense against libel charges.  Previous English defamation law had not provided this guarantee.

Zenger's case also established that libel cases, though they were civil rather than criminal cases, could be heard by a jury, which would have the authority to rule on the allegations and to set the amount of monetary damages awarded.

Although the First Amendment of the [[U.S. Constitution]] was designed specifically to protect freedom of the press, the [[U.S. Supreme Court|Supreme Court]] long neglected to use it to rule on libel cases, leaving libel laws mixed across the states.  In [[1964]], however, the court issued an opinion in ''[[New York Times Co. v. Sullivan]]'', dramatically changing the nature of libel law in the United States.  In that case, the court determined that public officials could only win a suit for libel if they could demonstrate "[[actual malice]]" on the part of reporters or publishers.  In that case, "actual malice" was defined as "knowledge that the [[information]] was false" or that it was published "with reckless disregard of whether it was false or not."  This decision was later extended to cover "public figures", although the standard is still considerably lower in the case of private individuals.

In [[1974]], in ''[[Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc.]]'', ('''418 U.S. 323'''), the Supreme Court ruled that a plaintiff could not win a libel suit when the statement(s) in question were of opinion rather than fact.  In the words of the court, "under the First Amendment, there is no such thing as a false idea".  For example, contrast "I think Jo is a bad lawyer", which is opinion, with "Jo doesn't know the law", which is defamatory ''per se''.

In [[1988]], in ''[[Hustler Magazine v. Falwell]]'', ('''485 U.S. 46'''), the Supreme Court ruled that a [[parody advertisement]] claiming [[Jerry Falwell]] had engaged in an [[incest]]uous act with his mother in an outhouse, while false, could not be subject to damages for emotional distress because the statement, in effect, was of a character as being so obviously ridiculous that it was clearly not true, and thus it could not be libelous if no one would seriously believe it.  The court overturned a lower court's upholding of an award where the jury decided against the claim of libel but awarded damages for emotional distress.

==Australian law==

[[Australia]]n law tends to follow United Kingdom law on defamation issues, although one recent judgment by the [[High Court of Australia]] has significant consequences on interpretation of the law.  On [[10 December]], [[2002]], the High Court of Australia handed down its judgment in the Internet defamation  dispute in the case of ''[[Gutnick v. Dow Jones]]''.  The judgment, which established that Internet-published foreign publications could be held accountable under Australian libel law, has gained worldwide attention and is said to be the first of its kind.

==Canadian law==

As with other [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] countries, [[Canada]] also follows United Kingdom law on defamation issues.  A recent [[Supreme Court of Canada]] case, ''[[Hill v. Church of Scientology of Toronto]]'' (1995), has reviewed the relationship of the [[common law]] of libel and its relation to the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]]. It is also the largest libel award ([[Canadian dollar|CAD]] 1,600,000 against the church) upheld in Canada and part of the ongoing legal problems of [[Scientology and the Legal System|Scientology]].   This reasoning in this case specifically rejects the ''actual malice'' test in ''New York Times Co. v. Sullivan'' citing criticism of it, not only in the United States, but in other countries as well.

==See also==
*[[Chilling effect]]
*[[International Freedom of Expression eXchange]]

[[Category:Journalism ethics]]
[[Category:Tort law]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>