<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20070816023703|151523894" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3755654" pageid="3755654" ns="0" title="Allophilia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-09-24T17:04:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Allophilia'''—positive attitudes for a group that is not one’s own—is a term derived from Greek words meaning “liking or love of the other” (Pittinsky, 2005). Studied by [[social scientists]], allophilia is the antonym of negative [[prejudice]]s and the antonym of a host of “–isms”: [[sexism]], [[racism]], [[heterosexism]], [[ageism]], [[anti-Semitism]], [[elitism]]/[[classism]], and [[phallocentrism]]. Allophilia can be felt towards members of a different [[race]], [[sex]], [[gender role|gender]], [[sexual orientation]], [[religion]], [[disability]], [[Social class|class]], [[nationality]], [[school]], [[team]], or workplace ([[List of occupations|occupation]]).

Allophilia has five statistical factors: 1) kinship, 2) engagement, 3) affection, 4) comfort, and 5) enthusiasm (Pittinsky &amp; Rosenthal, 2006). The Allophilia Scale measures each of these factors. 

The image below locates allophilia [[vis-à-vis]] its related constructs of prejudice and [[tolerance]]. The typical remedy for prejudice is to bring conflicting groups into a state of tolerance. However, tolerance is not the logical antithesis of prejudice, but rather is the midpoint between negative feelings and positive feelings toward others. The introduction of allophilia—positive intergroup attitudes—as an anchor, identifies a new domain for theory, research, and practice: allophilia enhancement.

[[Image:Allophilia Scale.jpg|center]]

== References ==
*Pittinsky, T. L. (2005).  Allophilia and intergroup leadership. In N. Huber &amp; M. Walker (Eds.), Building Leadership Bridges: Emergent Models of Global Leadership.  College Park, Maryland: International Leadership Association.
*Pittinsky, T. L. &amp; Rosenthal, S. A. (2006). Moving Beyond Tolerance: Factors and Measurement of Allophilia. Manuscript in preparation.
*[http://www.ksg.harvard.edu/leadership/compass/index.php?itemid=629 ''Compass: A Journal of Leadership'' article, Tolerance Is Not Enough: Allophilia—a framework for effective intergroup leadership]

[[Category:Society]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>