<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101108215308|395620388" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3755654" pageid="3755654" ns="0" title="Allophilia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-08T21:53:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{notability|date=May 2010}}
{{singlesource|date=May 2010}}
'''Allophilia''' is having positive attitude for a group that is not one's own. The term derived from [[Greek language|Greek]] words meaning "liking or love of the other".&lt;ref&gt;Pittinsky, T. L. (2010). A two-dimensional theory of intergroup leadership: The case of national diversity. American Psychologist, 65(3), 194-200.&lt;/ref&gt;

Studied by [[social scientists]], allophilia is the antonym of negative [[prejudice]]s and the antonym of a host of "–isms": [[sexism]], [[racism]], [[speciesism]], [[heterosexism]], [[ageism]], [[anti-Semitism]], [[elitism]]/[[classism]], and [[phallocentrism]]. Allophilia can be felt towards members of a different [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[sex]], [[species]], [[gender role|gender]], [[sexual orientation]], [[religion]], [[disability]], [[Social class|class]], [[nationality]], [[school]], [[team]], or workplace.

Allophilia has five statistical factors: 1. kinship, 2. engagement, 3. affection, 4. comfort, and 5. enthusiasm. The Allophilia Scale measures each of these factors &lt;ref&gt;Pittinsky, T. L., Rosenthal, S. A., &amp; Montoya, R. M. (2010). Measuring positive attitudes toward outgroups: Development and Validation of the Allophilia Scale. In L. Tropp &amp; R. Mallett (Eds.), Beyond Prejudice Reduction: Pathways to Positive Intergroup Relations. Washington, D. C.: American Psychological Association.&lt;/ref&gt; 


The typical remedy for prejudice is to bring conflicting groups into a state of tolerance. However, tolerance is not the logical antithesis of prejudice, but rather is the midpoint between negative feelings and positive feelings toward others. Allophilia enhancement should serve as complement to prejudice reduction &lt;ref name="ref3"&gt;Pittinsky, T. L., &amp; Montoya, R. M. (2009). Symhedonia in intergroup relations: The relationship of empathic joy to prejudice and allophilia. Psicologia Sociale, 3, 347–364.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pittinsky, T. L. (2009). Allophilia: Moving beyond tolerance in the classroom. Childhood Education, 85(4), 212–215.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pittinsky, T. L. (2009). Look both ways. Phi Delta Kappan, 90(5), 363–364.&lt;/ref&gt;

In one study, symhedonia (experiencing empathic joy) has been shown to be more closely associated with allophilia, while sympathy (experiencing empathic sorrow) has been shown to be more strongly associated with prejudice &lt;ref name="ref3"/&gt;


==See also==
* [[Cultural appropriation]]
* [[Xenophily]]
* [[Xenocentrism]]

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Admiration of foreign cultures]]

{{sociology-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>