<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051020202852|26035845" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1936551" pageid="1936551" ns="0" title="Postmodern feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-20T21:33:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Postmodern feminism''' is one approach to [[feminist theory]] that argues that there is no single cause for a [[woman]]'s subordination because sociological [[gender]] is itself [[social construction|constructed]] through [[discourse|language]]. Because the meaning behind this gender is not universal, there is no single approach towards dealing with the issue.

Although [[postmodernism]] resists characterization, it is possible to identify certain themes or orientations that postmodern legal feminists share. [[Mary Joe Frug]] suggested that one "principle" of postmodernism is that human experience is located "inescapably within language."  Power is exercised not only through direct coercion, but also through the way in which language shapes and restricts our reality. This makes [[language]] a potentially fruitful site of political struggle. 

Frug's second postmodern principle is that [[gender]] is not something natural, nor is it something completely determinate and definable. Like all human systems of meaning, it is constantly evolving and capable of infinite variations under individual circumstances. Gender is, therefore, [[social construction|socially constructed]] and completely inescapable (what would it mean to be outside the system of meaning?), but always susceptible to a new interpretation. Gender, like other systems of meaning, is less like a cage, and more like a tool: it constrains but never completely determines what one can do with it.*

*Adapted from Susan H. Williams and David C. Williams' article "A FEMINIST THEORY OF MALEBASHING" published in the Michigan Journal of Gender &amp; Law, 4 Mich. J. Gender &amp; L. 35 (1996)

{{fem-stub}}

[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Postmodern theory]]

[[el:Μεταμοντέρνος φεμινισμός]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>