<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20090930224003|317174145" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1936551" pageid="1936551" ns="0" title="Postmodern feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T03:15:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Expert-subject|Gender Studies|date=November 2008}}
{{Feminism sidebar}}

'''Postmodern feminism''' is an approach to [[feminist theory]] that incorporates [[Postmodern philosophy|postmodern]] and [[post-structuralism|post-structuralist theory]].

==Origins and theory==
The largest departure from other branches of feminism is the argument that [[sex]] is itself [[social construction|constructed]] through [[discourse|language]], a view most notably propounded in [[Judith Butler]]'s 1990 book, ''[[Gender Trouble]]''. She draws on and critiques the work of [[Simone de Beauvoir]], [[Michel Foucault]], and [[Jacques Lacan]]. Butler criticises the distinction drawn by previous feminisms between (biological) sex and (socially constructed) [[gender]]. Butler argues that this does not allow for a sufficient criticism of [[essentialism]]: though recognizing that gender is a social construct, feminists assume it's always constructed in the same way. Her argument implies that [[women]]'s subordination has no single cause or single solution; postmodern feminism is thus criticized for offering no clear path to action.  Butler herself rejects the term "postmodernism" as too vague to be meaningful.&lt;ref&gt;Judith Butler, "Contingent Foundations" in Seyla Benhabib et al., ''Feminist Contentions: A Philosophical Exchange'' (New York: Routledge, 1995), pp. 35-58&lt;/ref&gt;

[[French feminism]] from the 1970s until now, with the psychoanalytic theory writers [[Julia Kristeva]], [[Luce Irigaray]] has forged specific routes in postmodern feminism and in feminist [[psychoanalysis]]. Although [[postmodernism]] resists characterization, it is possible to identify certain themes or orientations that postmodern feminists share. [[Mary Joe Frug]] suggested that one "principle" of postmodernism is that human experience is located "inescapably within language."  Power is exercised not only through direct coercion, but also through the way in which language shapes and restricts our reality. However, because language is always open to re-interpretation, it can also be used to resist this shaping and restriction, and so is a potentially fruitful site of political struggle. 

{{Postmodernism}}
Frug's second postmodern principle is that [[sex]] is not something natural, nor is it something completely determinate and definable. Rather, sex is part of a system of meaning, produced by language. Frug argues that "cultural mechanisms ... encode the female body with meanings," and that these cultural mechanisms then go on explain these meanings "by an appeal to the 'natural' differences between the sexes, differences that the rules themselves help to produce."&lt;ref&gt;Mary Joe Frug, "A Postmodern Feminist Legal Manifesto (An Unfinished Draft)," ''Harvard Law Review'', Vol. 105, No. 5. (Mar., 1992), pp. 1045-1075, at p. 1049.&lt;/ref&gt; Rejecting the idea of a natural basis to sexual difference allows us to see that it is always susceptible to new interpretations. Like other systems of meaning, it is less like a cage, and more like a tool: it constrains but never completely determines what one can do with it.

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

== Bibliography ==
*Susan H. Williams and David C. Williams "A Feminist Theory of Malebashing", ''Michigan Journal of Gender &amp; Law'', 4 Mich. J. Gender &amp; L. 35 (1996)

== See also ==
* [[Cyborg feminism]]
* [[Individualist feminism]]
* [[Standpoint feminism]]
* [[Judith Butler]]
* [[Donna Haraway]]
* [[Luce Irigaray]] 
* [[Julia Kristeva]]

[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Postmodern theory]]
[[Category:Third-wave Feminism]]

[[el:Μεταμοντέρνος φεμινισμός]]
[[he:פמיניזם פוסטמודרני]]
[[sr:Постмодерни феминизам]]
[[sh:Postmoderni feminizam]]
[[sv:Postmodern feminism]]
[[tr:Postmodern feminizm]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>