<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20210525221026|1025131992" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1936551" pageid="1936551" ns="0" title="Postmodern feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-09-08T03:19:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Form of feminism designed to destabilize patriarchal norms.}}
{{more citations needed|date=October 2018}}
{{Feminism sidebar |Variants (general)}}
{{Postmodernism}}

'''Postmodern feminism''' is a mix of [[post-structuralism]], [[postmodernism]], and [[French feminism]].&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Sands|first1=Roberta|last2=Nuccio|first2=Kathleen|date=Nov 1992|title=Postmodern Feminist Theory and Social Work: A Deconstruction|journal=Social Work|volume=37|pages=489|doi=10.1093/sw/40.6.831|issn=1545-6846}}&lt;/ref&gt; The goal of postmodern feminism is to destabilize the [[Patriarchy|patriarchal]] norms entrenched in society that have led to gender inequality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ebert|first=Teresa L.|date=Dec 1991|title=The "Difference" of Postmodern Feminism|journal=College English|volume=53|issue=8|pages=886–904|doi=10.2307/377692|issn=0010-0994|jstor=377692}}&lt;/ref&gt; Postmodern feminists seek to accomplish this goal through rejecting [[essentialism]], philosophy, and universal truths in favor of embracing the differences that exist amongst women to demonstrate that not all women are the same.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/feministthoughtc00tong|url-access=registration|title=Feminist thought : a comprehensive introduction|last=Tong|first=Rosemarie|publisher=Westview Press|year=1989|isbn=9780429493836|location=Boulder, Colorado|pages=[https://archive.org/details/feministthoughtc00tong/page/217 217]–224|oclc=1041706991}}&lt;/ref&gt; These ideologies are rejected by postmodern feminists because they believe if a universal truth is applied to all woman of society, it minimizes individual experience, hence they warn  women to be aware of ideas displayed as the norm in society since it may stem from masculine notions of how women should be portrayed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Postmodern Feminism and Educational Policy Development|last=Wallin|first=Dawn C|publisher=McGill Journal of Education|year=2001|pages=27–43|oclc=967130390}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Postmodern feminists seek to analyze any notions that have led to gender inequality in society. Postmodern feminists analyze these notions and attempt to promote equality of gender through critiquing [[logocentrism]], supporting multiple discourses, deconstructing texts, and seeking to promote [[subjectivity]]. Postmodern feminists are accredited with drawing attention to dichotomies in society and demonstrating how language influences the difference in treatment of genders.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

The inclusion of postmodern theory into feminist theory is not readily accepted by all feminists—some believe postmodern thought undermines the attacks that [[feminist theory]] attempts to create, while other feminists are in favor of the union.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; For this reason, postmodernism and feminism have always had an uneasy relationship.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bolatito|first=A Lanre-Abbas|date=Fall 2003|title=Feminism in the postmodernist age|journal=The Journal of Social, Political, and Economic Studies|volume=28|pages=355–368|id={{ProQuest|216810839}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Origins and theory ==

===Butler===
Postmodern feminism's major departure from other branches of feminism is perhaps the argument that [[sex]], or at least [[gender]], is itself [[social construction|constructed]] through [[discourse|language]], a view notably propounded in [[Judith Butler]]'s 1990 book, ''[[Gender Trouble]]''. She draws on and critiques the work of [[Simone de Beauvoir]], [[Michel Foucault]], and [[Jacques Lacan]], as well as on [[Luce Irigaray]]'s argument that what we conventionally regard as 'feminine' is only a reflection of what is constructed as masculine.&lt;ref&gt;G. Gutting ed., ''The Cambridge Companion to Foucault'' (2002) p. 389&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Digeser |first1=Peter |title=Performativity Trouble: Postmodern Feminism and Essential Subjects |journal=Political Research Quarterly |date=September 1994 |volume=47 |issue=3 |pages=655–673 |doi=10.1177/106591299404700305 |s2cid=144691426 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Butler criticises the distinction drawn by previous feminisms between (biological) sex and (socially constructed) gender. She asks why we assume that material things (such as the body) are not subject to processes of social construction themselves. Butler argues that this does not allow for a sufficient criticism of [[essentialism]]: though recognizing that gender is a social construct, feminists assume it is always constructed in the same way. Her argument implies that [[women]]'s subordination has no single cause or single solution; postmodern feminism is thus criticized for offering no clear path to action.  Butler herself rejects the term "postmodernism" as too vague to be meaningful.&lt;ref&gt;Judith Butler, "Contingent Foundations" in Seyla Benhabib et al., ''Feminist Contentions: A Philosophical Exchange'' (New York: Routledge, 1995), pp. 35-58&lt;/ref&gt;

Paula Moya argues that Butler derives this rejection to postmodernism from misreadings of [[Cherríe Moraga]]'s work. "She reads Moraga's statement that 'the danger lies in ranking the oppressions' to mean that we have no way of adjudicating among different kinds of oppressions—that any attempt to casually relate or hierarchize the varieties of oppressions people suffer constitutes an imperializing, colonizing, or totalizing gesture that renders the effort invalid…thus, although Butler at first appears to have understood the critiques of women who have been historically precluded from occupying the position of the 'subject' of feminism, it becomes clear that their voices have been merely instrumental to her" (Moya, 790) Moya contends that because Butler feels that the varieties of oppressions cannot be summarily ranked, that they cannot be ranked at all; and takes a short-cut by throwing out the idea of not only postmodernism, but women in general.&lt;ref&gt;Moya, Paula M.L. ''From Postmodernism, 'Realism,' and the Politics of Identity: [[Cherríe Moraga]] and [[Chicana feminism|Chicana Feminism]]'' in {{cite book | last1 = Gilbert | first1 = Susan M. | last2 = Gubar | first2 = Susan Eds | title=Feminist literary theory and criticism : a Norton reader | year = 2007 | publisher = W.W. Norton | location = New York | isbn=9780393927900 | pages = 787–797 | edition = 1st | author-link=From Postmodernism, "Realism," and the Politics of Identity: Cherrie Moraga and Chicana Feminism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Frug===
[[Mary Joe Frug]] suggested that one "principle" of postmodernism is that human experience is located "inescapably within language". Power is exercised not only through direct coercion, but also through the way in which language shapes and restricts our reality. She also stated that because language is always open to re-interpretation, it can also be used to resist this shaping and restriction, and so is a potentially fruitful site of political struggle.

Frug's second postmodern principle is that sex is not something natural, nor is it something completely determinate and definable. Rather, sex is part of a system of meaning, produced by language. Frug argues that "cultural mechanisms ... encode the female body with meanings", and that these cultural mechanisms then go on explain these meanings "by an appeal to the 'natural' differences between the sexes, differences that the rules themselves help to produce".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Frug|first=Mary Joe|date=March 1992|title=A Postmodern Feminist Manifesto (An Unfinished Draft)|journal=Harvard Law Review|volume= 105| issue = 5|pages= 1045–1075|doi=10.2307/1341520|jstor=1341520}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===French feminism===
French feminism, as it is known today, is an Anglo-American invention coined by [[Alice Jardine]] to be a section in a larger movement of postmodernism in France during the 1980s. This included the theorizing of the failure of the modernist project, along with its departure. More specifically for feminism, it meant returning to the debate of sameness and difference.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Gambaudo |first1=Sylvie A. |title=French Feminism vs Anglo-American Feminism: A Reconstruction |journal=European Journal of Women's Studies |date=May 2007 |volume=14 |issue=2 |pages=93–108 |doi=10.1177/1350506807075816 |s2cid=144756187 |url=https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00571299/file/PEER_stage2_10.1177%252F1350506807075816.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; The term was further defined by [[Toril Moi]], an academic with a focus on feminist theory, in her book ''Sexual/Textual Politics.'' In this book she further defined French feminism to only include a few authors such as [[Hélène Cixous]], [[Luce Irigaray]], and [[Julia Kristeva]], while also creating a distinction between French feminism and Anglo-American Feminism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Sexual/textual politics: feminist literary theory|last=Moi, Toril|date=2002|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0415280112|edition= 2nd|location=London|oclc=49959398}}&lt;/ref&gt; She states that the difference between the two is that Anglo-American feminists want to find a "woman-centered perspective" and a woman identity since they were not given the chance to have one in the past. French Feminists believe there is no identity for a woman but that "the feminine can be identified where difference and otherness are found."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Elaine Marks, an academic in the field of Women's Studies, noted another difference between French and American feminists. French feminists, specifically [[Radical feminism|radical feminists]], criticized and attacked the systems that benefit men, along with widespread misogyny as a whole, more intensely than their American counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=New French feminisms : an anthology|date=1980|publisher=University of Massachusetts Press|others=Marks, Elaine., De Courtivron, Isabelle.|isbn=978-0870232800|location=Amherst|oclc=5051713|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/newfrenchfeminis00markrich}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through American academics contriving their own concept of French feminism, it separated and ignored the already marginalized self-identifying feminists, while focusing on the women theorists associated with Psych et po ([[Psychanalyse et politique]]) and other academics who did not always identify as feminists themselves. This division ultimately ended up placing more importance on the theories of the French feminists than the political agenda and goals that groups such as radical feminists and the [[Mouvement de libération des femmes|Mouvement de liberation des femmes]] (women's liberation movement) had at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Moses |first1=Claire Goldberg |title=Made in America: "French Feminism" in Academia |journal=Feminist Studies |date=1998 |volume=24 |issue=2 |pages=241–274 |id={{GALE|A21221517}} {{ProQuest|233178967}} |doi=10.2307/3178697 |jstor=3178697 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Critiques ==
[[File:Gloria Steinem crop.jpg|thumb|Feminist Activist Gloria Steinem]]
There have been many critiques of postmodern feminism since it originated in the 1990s. Most of the criticism has been from [[Modernism|modernists]] and feminists supporting modernist thought. They have put a focus on the themes of [[relativism]] and [[nihilism]] as defined by postmodernism. Though modernist critics believe more importantly, that through abandoning the values of Enlightenment thought, postmodern feminism "precludes the possibility of liberating political action."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Gender and Knowledge|last=Hekman|first=Susan J.|publisher=Northeastern University Press|year=1990|location=Boston|pages=152–153}}&lt;/ref&gt; This concern can be seen in critics like [[Meaghan Morris]], who have argued that postmodern feminism runs the risk of undercutting the basis of a politics of action based upon gender difference, through its very anti-essentialism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Theater of Transformation|url=https://archive.org/details/theatertransform00schm|url-access=limited|last=Schmidt|first=K.|year=2005|pages=[https://archive.org/details/theatertransform00schm/page/n129 129]–130}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alison Assiter]] published the book ''Enlightened Women'' to critique postmodernists and postmodern feminists alike, saying that there should be a return to Enlightenment values and modernist feminism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Enlightened Women|last=Assiter|first=Alison|publisher=Routledge|year=1995|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gloria Steinem]] has also criticized feminist theory, and especially postmodernist feminist theory, as being overly academic, where discourse that is full of jargon and inaccessible is helpful to no one.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/jan/17/gender.melissadenes|title='Feminism? It's hardly begun'|last=Denes|first=Melissa|date=2005-01-17|work=The Guardian|access-date=2019-03-29|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Columns-list|colwidth=22em|
* [[Alison Assiter]]
* [[Cyborg feminism]]
* [[Donna Haraway]]
* [[Écriture féminine]]
* [[Individualist feminism]]
* [[Nancy Fraser]]
* [[Post-structural feminism]]
* [[Standpoint feminism]]
* [[Structuralism#Overview|Structuralist feminism]]
* [[Third-wave feminism]]
}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|40em}}

== Bibliography ==
*{{cite book | last = Assiter | first = Alison | title = Enlightened women modernist feminism in a postmodern age | publisher = Routledge | location = London New York | year = 1996 | isbn = 9780415083386 }}
*{{cite book | last = Kottiswari | first = W. S. | title = Postmodern feminist writers | publisher = Sarup &amp; Sons | location = New Delhi | year = 2008 | isbn = 9788176258210 }}
* {{cite journal |last1=Williams |first1=Susan |last2=Williams |first2=David |title=A Feminist Theory of Malebashing |journal=Michigan Journal of Gender &amp; Law |date=1 January 1996 |volume=4 |issue=1 |pages=35–127 |url=https://repository.law.umich.edu/mjgl/vol4/iss1/2/ }}

==External links==
* [http://freepages.rootsweb.com/~gilliamgibbs/genealogy/writings/pmf.html 'Postmodern Feminism in 3 pages']

{{Feminist theory}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Postmodern Feminism}}
[[Category:Postmodern feminism| ]]
[[Category:Third-wave feminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>