<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111028075803|457784781" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="852252" pageid="852252" ns="0" title="Untouchability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-18T06:23:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{other uses|Untouchable (disambiguation)}}

'''Untouchability''' is the social practice of [[Social rejection|ostracizing]] a minority group by segregating them from the mainstream by social custom or legal mandate. The excluded group could be one that did not accept the norms of the excluding group and historically included foreigners, nomadic tribes, law-breakers and criminals and those suffering from a contagious disease such as Leprosy. This exclusion was a method of punishing  law-breakers and also protected against contagion from strangers and the infected. A member of the excluded group is known as an '''untouchable'''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?search=untouchable&amp;searchmode=none Untouchable definition from the Online Etymology Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The term is commonly associated with treatment of the [[Dalit]] communities, who are considered "polluting" among Hindus of [[India]], [[Nepal]] and [[Bangladesh]], but the term has been used for other groups as well, such as the [[Burakumin]] of [[Japan]], [[Cagots]] in Europe, or the [[Al-Akhdam]] in Yemen. Untouchability has been made illegal in post-independence India, and Dalits substantially empowered, although some prejudice against them continues, especially in rural pockets dominated by certain [[other backward caste]] (OBC) groups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2003/06/0602_030602_untouchables.html India's "Untouchables" Face Violence, Discrimination.] Hillary Mayell
for [[National Geographic]] News. June 2, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

==Untouchability in South Asia==
Untouchability is not merely the inability to touch a human being of another caste or sub-caste, it is an attitude on the part of a whole group of people that relates to a deeper psychological process of thought and belief, invisible to the naked eye, translated into various physical acts and behaviours, norms and practices.&lt;ref&gt;[http://navsarjan.org/navsarjan/dalits/WhatIsUntouchability What is "Untouchability"? — Welcome to Navsarjan&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Untouchability is prompted by the spirit of social exclusion and the belief in purity, contagion and self-righteousness that characterise certain societies. It is generally taken for granted that [[Dalits]] pollute people and are at the lowest end of the South Asian society. The jobs considered polluting and impure are expected to be done by Dalits, and many a times Dalits are known to have been prevented from engaging in any work other than removing human waste (known as “[[manual scavenging]]”), dragging away and skinning animal carcasses, tanning leather, making and fixing shoes, and washing clothes. They were supposed to reside outside the village so that their physical presence did not pollute the “main” village. Not only had they been restricted in terms of space, but their houses were inferior in quality and devoid of any facilities like water and electricity.The government of India has, however, introduced many measures like low cost or free housing and free electricity for those below the poverty line, to address these problems.

Untouchability is practised in a number of forms in rural India. At the village level Dalits are sometimes barred from using wells used by non-Dalits, forbidden from going to the barber shop and entering [[temples]], while at the level of job recruitment and employment many Dalits are known to be paid less, ordered to do the most menial work, and rarely promoted, except in the government jobs reserved for them. Even at school, there have been instances of Dalit children being asked to clean toilets and to eat separately, although the government comes down heavily in these cases and punishes the offenders, as soon as these are highlighted by the alert Indian media.

===Untouchability practices and discrimination===
In the name of untouchability, Dalits face nearly 140 forms of work &amp; descent-based discrimination at the hands of the [[Sanskritisation|dominant castes]].  Here are a few:&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.ncdhr.org.in/ncdhr/general-info-misc-pages/wadwiu Who are Dalits? &amp; What is Untouchability? — Portal&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Prohibited from eating with other caste members
*Separate glasses for Dalits in village tea stalls
*Discriminatory seating arrangements and separate utensils in restaurants
*Segregation in seating and food arrangements in village functions and festivals
*Prohibited from entering into village temples
*Prohibited from wearing sandals or holding umbrellas in front of dominant caste members
*[[Devadasi|Devadasi system]] - the ritualized temple prostitution of Dalit women
*Prohibited from entering dominant caste homes
*Prohibited from riding a bicycle inside the village
*Prohibited from using common village path
*Separate burial grounds
*No access to village’s common/public properties and resources (wells, ponds, temples, etc.)
*Segregation (separate seating area) of Dalit children in schools
*Prohibited from contesting in elections and exercising their right to vote
*Forced to vote or not to vote for certain candidates during the elections
*Prohibiting from hoisting the national flag during Independence or Republic days
*Sub-standard wages
*[[Bonded labour|Bonded Labor]]
*Face social boycotts by dominant castes for refusing to perform their "duties"

===Government Action in India===
The 1950 national [[constitution of India]] legally abolishes the practice of untouchability, and there are constitutional [[Reservation in India|reservations]] in both educational institutions and public services for Dalits.

[[Scheduled castes and scheduled tribes|National Commission for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes]] have been formed by government. 
These measures have not always been effective which is visible from anti-dalit feelings which takes the form of caste violence many a times eg.[[Kherlanji massacre]] of Dalits by the Kunbis and killings of Dalits by Jats in 2010 at [[Mirchpur]].

=== Untouchability in Kerala===
[[File:Untouchables of Malabar Kerala Dravidian Australoid.png|thumb|350px|Untouchables of [[Malabar (Northern Kerala)|Malabar]], [[Kerala]] (1906)]]
The declaration by [[princely states]] of [[Kerala]] between 1936 and 1947 that temples were open to all Hindus went a long way towards ending the system of untouchability in Kerala.  However some historical forms of untouchability existed in Kerala, among the [[Nairs]] and [[Namboothiris]], who constituted the [[forward caste]]s; they forbade those belonging to lower castes within certain proximity to them, believing that the presence of lower castes would pollute them. 

A [[Nair]] was expected to instantly cut down a [[Thiyya|Tiar]] or [[Mukkuvar|Mucua]] who presumed to defile him by touching his person, and a similar fate awaited a slave who did not turn out of the road as a Nair passed.&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.com/books?id=FnB3k8fx5oEC&amp;pg=PA291 Castes and tribes of Southern India, Volume 7 By Edgar Thurston, K. Rangachari, p.251&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, the people of the Nayadi, Kanisan and Mukkuvan caste were forbidden to come within 72, 32 and 24 feet respectively from [[Nairs]].  In modern India, observance of untouchability is a criminal offence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nairs.in/acha_a.htm www.nairs.in&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Analogous systems of discrimination in other countries==
Caste and analogous systems of social hierarchy operate across the world, particularly in Asia and Africa, subjecting millions to inhuman treatment on the basis of being born into a certain caste or similar social group. Though the communities themselves may be indistinguishable in appearance from others, unlike with race or ethnicity, socio-economic disparities are glaring, as are the peculiar forms of discrimination practiced against them. It is approximated that around 250 – 300 million people across the world suffer from caste, or work and descent based discrimination, a form of discrimination that impinges on their civil, political, religious, socio-economic and cultural rights.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; 

Common features seen in caste and analogous systems across the world include the following:  
*Physical segregation
*[[Social apartheid|Social segregation]], including prohibition on inter-marriages between caste groups
*Assignment of traditional occupations, often being occupations associated with death or filth, coupled with restrictions on occupational [[Caste system in India|mobility]]
*Pervasive [[debt bondage]] due to poor remuneration for lower-caste occupations
*High levels of [[illiteracy]], poverty and landlessness as compared to so-called higher castes *(f) Impunity for perpetrators of crimes against low-caste communities
*Use of degrading language to describe low-caste communities, based on notions of purity and pollution, filth and cleanliness
*Double or triple discrimination against and exploitation of women of low castes on the basis of sex, class and caste.

Below is a list of some communities in other countries around the world facing discrimination due to caste or some analogous social hierarchical system:

*[[Bangladesh]]: Mehtor community (traditionally sweepers and manual scavengers)
*[[Burkina Faso]]: Bellah community (traditionally slaves, unpaid manual laborers, to other caste ‘owners’)
*[[Czech Republic]]: Roma Gypsies. 
*[[France]]: Roma Gypsies are being officially thrown out of France.
*[[Japan]]: Buraku community (at the bottom of the Japanese class system; traditionally viewed as filthy and/or non-human)
*[[Kenya]]: Watta community (traditionally considered low, worthless, and consigned to a life of servitude from birth)
*[[Mauritania]]: Haratin community (these ‘black moors’ are considered slaves to the Bidan, or ‘white moors’, in Mauritanian society)
*[[Nepal]]: Dalit community (situation is essentially the same as that of Dalits in India)
*[[Nigeria]]: Osu community (traditionally the Osu people are ‘owned’ by deities and considered as outcaste, untouchable, and sub-human)
*[[Pakistan]]: Christians are killed for drinking tea from a cup meant for Muslims only. They are forbidden to eat in many public eating houses, Christian students are forbidden to drink water in a glass in which Muslim students drink water. Even flood aid is denied to Christians and Dalits, although it comes mostly from Christian charities and countries. This is because most of the Christians are converted Dalits, who are despised.
*[[Rwanda]]: Twa community (at bottom of social hierarchy with no legal protections from discrimination and no representation in positions of power/authority)
*[[Senegal]]: Neeno &amp; Nyamakalaw communities (largely blacksmiths and leatherworkers, they are considered impure and face explicit segregation and exclusion)
*[[Somalia]]: Midgan community (minority outcaste group facing violence, refusal of rights, and possessing no legal protections)
*[[Sri Lanka]]: Rodi/Rodiya &amp; Pallar/Paraiyar communities (these groups face discrimination in employment, practices of social distance, and denial of access to resources)

The voices has been raised by many countries to involve caste in the UN resolution against [[racism]] too.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2009/04/22/un-racism-conference-fails-caste-based-discrimination UN Racism Conference Fails on Caste-Based Discrimination | Human Rights Watch&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Untouchable groups==
* [[Dalit]], in India and Nepal
* [[Al-Akhdam]] in Yemen
* [[Burakumin]] in Japan
* [[Baekjeong]] in Korea
* [[Ezhava]] in Kerala and Sri Lanka.
* [[Cagot]]s in France
* [[Vaqueiros de alzada]] in Spain
* [[Madhiban]] in Somalia
* Ragyabpa in Tibet (see [[Social classes of Tibet]])

==See also==
* [[Caste]]
**[[Balinese caste system]]
**[[Caste system in India]]
**[[Caste in Sri Lanka]]
**[[Caste system in Africa]]
* [[Outcast (person)]]
* [[Homo sacer]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Persecution]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Caste]]
[[Category:Indian caste system]]

[[ml:തൊട്ടുകൂടായ്മ]]
[[pl:Niedotykalni]]
[[ta:தீண்டாமை]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>