<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131108095519|580734138" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="852252" pageid="852252" ns="0" title="Untouchability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-08T09:56:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{other uses|Untouchable (disambiguation)}}
{{refimprove|date=June 2012}}
'''Untouchability''' is the social-religious practice of [[Social rejection|ostracizing]] a minority group by segregating them from the mainstream by social custom or legal mandate. The excluded group could be one that did not accept the norms of the excluding group and historically included foreigners, house workers, nomadic tribes, law-breakers and criminals and those suffering from a contagious disease. This exclusion was a method of punishing  law-breakers and also protected traditional societies against contagion from strangers and the infected. A member of the excluded group is known as an '''Untouchable'''.

The term is commonly associated with treatment of the [[Dalit]] communities, who are considered "polluting" among the people of [[South Asia]], but the term has been used for other groups as well, such as the [[Burakumin]] of [[Japan]], [[Cagots]] in Europe, or the [[Al-Akhdam]] in Yemen. Untouchability has been made illegal in post-independence India, and Dalits substantially empowered, although some prejudice against them continues, especially in rural pockets dominated by certain [[other backward caste]] (OBC) groups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2003/06/0602_030602_untouchables.html India's "Untouchables" Face Violence, Discrimination.] Hillary Mayell for [[National Geographic (magazine)|National Geographic]] News. June 2, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

==Untouchability in practice==
[[File:Untouchables of Malabar Kerala Dravidian Australoid.png|thumb|350px|Untouchables of [[Malabar (Northern Kerala)|Malabar]], [[Kerala]] (1906)]]

===Untouchability and discrimination===
In the name of untouchability, Dalits have faced work and descent-based discrimination at the hands of the [[Sanskritisation|dominant castes]]. Instances of this discrimination at different places and times included:&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.ncdhr.org.in/ncdhr/general-info-misc-pages/wadwiu Who are Dalits? &amp; What is Untouchability? — Portal&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Prohibition from eating with other caste members
*Provision of separate glasses for Dalits in village tea stalls
*Discriminatory seating arrangements and separate utensils in restaurants
*Segregation in seating and food arrangements in village functions and festivals
*Prohibition from entering into village temples
*Prohibition from wearing sandals or holding umbrellas in front of higher caste members
*Prohibition from entering other caste homes
*Prohibition from riding a bicycle inside the village
*Prohibition from using common village path
*Separate burial grounds
*No access to village’s common/public properties and resources (wells, ponds, temples, etc.)
*Segregation (separate seating area) of Dalit children in schools
*Sub-standard wages
*[[Bonded labour]]
*Social boycotts by other castes for refusing to perform their "duties"

===Government action in India===
The 1950 national [[constitution of India]] legally abolished the practice of untouchability and provided measures for [[Reservation in India|positive discrimination]] in both educational institutions and public services for Dalits and other social groups who lie within the caste system. These are supplemented by official bodies such as the [[Scheduled castes and scheduled tribes|National Commission for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes]].

Despite this, instances of prejudice against Dalits still occur in some rural areas, as evidenced by events such as the [[Kherlanji massacre]].

==Untouchable groups==
{{unreferenced section|date=October 2012}}
* [[Gypsies]] in India and Europe
* [[Burakumin]] in Japan
* [[Baekjeong]] in Korea
* [[Cagot]]s in France
* [[Dalit]] in [[South Asia]]
* Ragyabpa in Tibet (see [[Social classes of Tibet]])

==See also==
* [[Caste]]
* [[Outcast (person)]]
* [[Homo sacer]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*http://www.csuchico.edu/~cheinz/syllabi/asst001/fall97/adra-hpn.htm

{{Social class}}

[[Category:Persecution]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Caste]]
[[Category:Indian caste system]]

[[pl:Niedotykalni]]
[[ta:தீண்டாமை]]
[[ur:اچھوت]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>