<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091004054129|317788585" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="852252" pageid="852252" ns="0" title="Untouchability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-10-19T07:22:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses|Untouchable}}
'''Untouchability''' is the social practice of ostracising a (usually) minority [[endogamy|endogamous]] group by regarding them as "ritually polluted" and segregating them from the mainstream by social custom or legal mandate. The excluded group could be one that did not accept the norms of the excluding group and historically included foreigners, nomadic tribes, law-breakers and criminals. This exclusion was a method of punishing  law-breakers and also protected against contagion from strangers. A member of the excluded group is known as an '''untouchable'''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?search=untouchable&amp;searchmode=none Untouchable definition from the Online Etymology Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The term is commonly associated with treatment of the [[Dalit]] class among hindus of [[India]], [[Nepal]] and [[Bangladesh]]. Untouchability has been made illegal in post-Independence India but prejudice continues. &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2003/06/0602_030602_untouchables.html India's "Untouchables" Face Violence, Discrimination.] Hillary Mayell
for [[National Geographic]] News. June 2, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

==Untouchable groups==
* [[Dalit]], in India and Nepal
* [[Al-Akhdam]] in Yemen
* [[Burakumin]] in Japan
* [[Baekjeong]] in Korea
* [[Cagots]] in France
* [[Vaqueiros de alzada]] in Spain
* [[Gypsies]] throughout Europe
* [[Jew]]s throughout Europe, including [[Marrano]]s in Spain and Portugal and [[Xueta]] in Majorca
* [[Morisco]]s in Spain and Portugal
* [[Ragyabpa]] in Tibet (see [[Social classes of Tibet]])

===Cultural outgroups===
Since the 19th century most untouchable groups have been officially integrated and exist, if at all, in the form of a cultural outgroup.
* [[African American]]s in the United States (and, in the 19th century, Irish, Chinese, and Japanese immigrants)

===Untouchability in Kerala===
The declaration by princely states of Kerala between 1936 and 1947 that temples were open to all Hindus went a long way towards ending the system of untouchability in Kerala. However some historical forms of untouchability existed in Kerala, [[Nairs]] and [[Namboothiris]], who constituted the [[forward caste]]s forbid those belonging to lower castes within certain proximity to them, believing that the presence of lower castes would pollute them. 

A [[Nair]] was expected to instantly cut down a [[Thiyya|Tiar]], or [[Mukkuvar|Mucua]], who presumed to defile him by touching his person; and a similar fate awaited a slave, who did not turn out of the road as a Nair passed.&lt;ref&gt; [http://books.google.com/books?id=rWAOAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA735&amp;dq=Nair+Sudra#PPA736,M1 A general collection of ... voyages and travels, digested by J. Pinkerton - Page 736]&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, the people of the Nayadi, Kanisan and Mukkuvan caste were forbidden to come within 72, 32 and 24 feet respectively from [[Nairs]]. In modern India, observance of untouchability is a criminal offence. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.nairs.in/acha_a.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==See also==
* [[Caste]]
**[[Balinese caste system]]
**[[Caste system in India]]
**[[Caste in Sri Lanka]]
**[[Caste system in Africa]]
* [[Outcast]]
* [[Homo sacer]]

[[Category:Persecution]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Caste]]


{{culture-stub}}
{{socio-stub}}

[[ml:തൊട്ടുകൂടായ്മ]]
[[pl:Niedotykalni]]
[[ta:தீண்டாமை]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>