<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151111185948|690171977" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="852252" pageid="852252" ns="0" title="Untouchability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-11T19:00:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{other uses|Untouchable (disambiguation)}}
{{refimprove|date=June 2012}}
'''Untouchability''' is the practice of [[Social rejection|ostracising]] a group by segregating them from the mainstream by social custom or legal mandate. The excluded group could be one that did not accept the norms of the excluding group and historically included foreigners, nomadic tribes, law-breakers and criminals and those suffering from a contagious disease. It could also be a group that did not accept change of customs enforced by a certain group. This exclusion was a method of punishing  law-breakers and also protected traditional societies against contagion from strangers and the infected. A member of the excluded group is known as an '''Untouchable'''.

According to Dr. [[B. R. Ambedkar]], untouchability was born about 400 AD, due to the struggle for supremacy between [[Buddhism]] and [[Historical Vedic religion|Brahmanism]] (an ancient term for Brahmanical Hinduism).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/india-news/article-in-rss-mouthpiece-misquotes-ambedkar-on-untouchability/article1-1338054.aspx|title=Top RSS leader misquotes Ambedkar on untouchability}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term is commonly associated with treatment of the [[Dalit]] communities, who are considered "polluting" among the people of [[South Asia]], but the term has been used for other groups as well, such as the [[Burakumin]] of [[Japan]], [[Cagots]] in Europe, or the [[Al-Akhdam]] in [[Yemen]]. However Hinduism has no clear position on untouchability. The [[Bhagavad Gita]], a central text in Hinduism, often challenged the caste system, stating for example that ‘The wise looks with an equal eye upon a noble brahmin, a cow, an elephant, a dog and an outcast (chandala)’.&lt;ref&gt;|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=SfWAAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA263&amp;lpg=PA263&amp;dq=The+wise+looks+with+an+equal+eye+upon+a+noble+brahmin,+a+cow,+an+elephant,+a+dog+and+a+chandala%E2%80%99&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=T3WhQquAHC&amp;sig=-hfjIgNu066i0Oah589Zdt5ieVU&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CCEQ6AEwAGoVChMIv9z07I2OyAIVBqvbCh0Zvw_R#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20wise%20looks%20with%20an%20equal%20eye%20upon%20a%20noble%20brahmin%2C%20a%20cow%2C%20an%20elephant%2C%20a%20dog%20and%20a%20chandala%E2%80%99&amp;f=false|&lt;/ref&gt;

Untouchability has been made illegal in post-independence India, and Dalits substantially empowered, although some prejudice against them continues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Modern Anthropology of India: Ethnography, Themes and Theory|page=164|publisher=Routledge|authors=Peter Berger, Frank Heidemann}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Diverse ethnicities population in South Asia==
[[File:Untouchables of Malabar Kerala Dravidian Australoid.png|thumb|350px|Untouchables of [[Malabar (Northern Kerala)|Malabar]], [[Kerala]] (1906)]]
According to Sarah Pinto, an anthropologist, untouchability in India applies to people whose work relates to "death, bodies, meat, and bodily fluids".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Where There Is No Midwife: Birth and Loss in Rural India |first=Sarah |last=Pinto |publisher=Berghahn Books |year=2013 |isbn=978-0-85745-448-5 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=5V-_NssEMSsC&amp;pg=PA47 |page=47}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the name of untouchability,  Dalits have faced work and descent-based [[Caste discrimination|discrimination]] at the hands of the [[Sanskritisation|dominant castes]]. Instances of caste discrimination at different places and times included:&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.ncdhr.org.in/ncdhr/general-info-misc-pages/wadwiu Who are Dalits? &amp; What is Untouchability? — Portal&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Prohibition from eating with other members
*Provision of separate cups in village tea stalls
*Separate seating arrangements and utensils in restaurants
*Segregation in seating and food arrangements in village functions and festivals
*Prohibition from entering into village temples
*Prohibition from wearing sandals or holding umbrellas in front of higher caste members
*Prohibition from entering other caste homes
*Prohibition from using common village path
*Separate burial grounds
*No access to village's common/public properties and resources (wells, ponds, temples, etc.)
*Segregation (separate seating area) of children in schools
*[[Bonded labour]]
*Social boycotts by other castes for refusing to perform their "duties"

===Government action in India===
The 1950 national [[constitution of India]] legally abolished the practice of untouchability and provided measures for [[Reservation in India|positive discrimination]] in both educational institutions and public services for Dalits and other social groups who lie within the caste system. These are supplemented by official bodies such as the [[Scheduled castes and scheduled tribes|National Commission for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes]].

Despite this, instances of prejudice against Dalits still occur in some rural areas, as evidenced by events such as the [[Kherlanji massacre]].

In recent times, there have been some radical reforms in the social sector of India. The famous [[Vithoba Temple, Pandharpur]] became the first temple in India to allow priests from backward classes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Lord Vithoba temple makes history by having women and lower-caste priests|url=http://news.biharprabha.com/2014/05/lord-vithoba-temple-makes-history-by-having-women-and-lower-caste-priests/|work=IANS|publisher=news.biharprabha.com|accessdate=9 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Untouchable groups==
{{unreferenced section|date=October 2012}}
* [[Cagot]]s in France and Spain
* [[Dalit]] in [[South Asia]]
* [[Burakumin]] in Japan
* [[Baekjeong]] in Korea
* [[Romani people|Romani]] in Europe
* [[Al-Akhdam]] in Yemen
* [[Ragyabpa]] in Tibet (see [[Social classes of Tibet]])
* [[Tanka people|Tanka]] (danhu) ("boat people") in [[Guangdong]], [[Fuzhou Tanka]] in [[Fujian]], [[si-min]] (small people) and [[mianhu]] in [[Jiangsu]], [[Gaibu]] and [[Duomin]] (To min) 惰民 duò mín ("idle/lazy/fallen/indolent people") in [[Zhejiang]], [[jiuxing yumin]] 九姓魚民 jiǔxìng yúmín ("nine name fishermen") in the [[Yangzi River]] region, [[yoh-hu]] ("music people") in [[Shanxi]] in China
* [[Osus]] in Nigeria and Cameroon

==See also==
* [[Caste]]
* [[Outcast (person)]]
* [[Homo sacer]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==

{{Social class}}

[[Category:Persecution]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Caste]]
[[Category:Indian caste system]]

[[pl:Niedotykalni]]
[[ur:اچھوت]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>