<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141106101459|632675360" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25454239" pageid="25454239" ns="0" title="Masculism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-09T20:45:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=April 2012}}
{{grammar|date=October 2014}}
'''Masculism''' (or '''masculinism''') is political, cultural, and economic movements which aim to establish and defend political, economic, and social rights and participation in society for men and boys. More generally, it may refer to any movement, theory or opinion which holds a belief in achieving males' equality with females as its core tenet. In this regard, it is the counterpart of [[feminism]], which seeks to achieve the same goals but from a contradistinct viewpoint. Issues of concern to masculists include legal equalities, such as those relating to [[conscription]], [[child custody]], [[alimony]], and [[equal pay for equal work]]. Its concepts sometimes coincide with those of the men's rights, fathers' rights, and men's liberation movements. {{citation needed|date=March 2014}} Masculinism strives to achieve these aims by advocating for the rights or needs of men; by the adherence to or promotion of opinions, values, and attitudes, regarded as typical of men;&lt;ref name="BunninYu2008"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"&gt;{{cite book|last=Christensen|first=Ferrell|editor=Ted Honderich|title=The Oxford Companion to Philosophy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4ii8AAAAIAAJ|year=1995|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-866132-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=reason&gt;{{cite news|publisher=''[[Reason magazine|Reason]]''|title=Man Troubles: Making Sense of the Men's Movement|author=[[Cathy Young]]|date=July 1994|url=http://law-journals-books.vlex.com/vid/man-troubles-making-sense-men-movement-53432494/ai_16075316/}} "Not to worry" there seems to imply that this conception of masculism poses a threat to women, or to the women's movement. A broader conception of the women's movement, however, recognizes that patriarchy is harmful to both men and women, and therefore that prejudice and discrimination against both genders will need to be recognized and redressed.&lt;/ref&gt; or, alternatively, through an [[Androcentrism|androcentric]] approach,&lt;ref name="Masculinist"&gt;{{cite web|title=masculinist, n|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/masculinist|work=Merriam-Webster|publisher=[[Merriam-Webster]]|accessdate=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Brittan1989"&gt;{{cite book|author=Arthur Brittan|title=Masculinity and Power|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ptFzQgAACAAJ&amp;pg=PA91|accessdate=11 May 2013|year= 1989|publisher= Wiley|isbn= 978-0-631-14167-9|page= 4|quote= Masculinism is the ideology that justifies and naturalizes male domination. As such it is the ideology of patriarchy. Masculinism takes it for granted that there is a fundamental difference between men and women, it assumes that heterosexuality is normal, it accepts without question the sexual division of labour, and it sanctions the political and dominant role of men in the public and private spheres}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the exclusion of [[Woman|women]].&lt;ref name="BunninYu2008"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Nicholas Bunnin|author2=Jiyuan Yu|title=The Blackwell Dictionary of Western Philosophy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=LdbxabeToQYC&amp;pg=PA411|date=15 April 2008|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-0-470-99721-5|page=411|chapter=Masculinism}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==Definition and scope==
The [[Oxford English Dictionary]] regards it as: "Advocacy of the rights of men; adherence to or promotion of opinions, values, etc., regarded as typical of men." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Oxford English Dictionary|website=http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/american_english/masculinist}}&lt;/ref&gt; Philosopher Ferrell Christensen differentiates the words "masculism" and "masculinism"; he defines the latter as promoting the attributes of manliness.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"&gt;{{cite book|last=Christensen|first=Ferrell|editor=Ted Honderich|title=The Oxford Companion to Philosophy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4ii8AAAAIAAJ|year=1995|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-866132-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Political scientist Georgia Duerst-Lahti also distinguishes between the two terms, with masculism being more associated with the early gender egalitarian days of [[men's movement]], while masculinism refers to [[patriarchy]] and its ideology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book  | editor = Goertz, Gary |  editor2 = Mazur, Amy | first2 = Amy. | title = Politics, gender, and concepts : theory and methodology | year = 2008 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | chapter= Gender Ideology:masculinism and femininalism |author=Georgia Duerst-Lahti | isbn = 978-0-521-72342-8 | pages = 159–192 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dupuis-Déri2009"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Dupuis-Déri|first1=Francis|title=Le " masculinisme " : une histoire politique du mot (en anglais et en français)|journal=Recherches féministes|volume=22|issue=2|year=2009|pages=97|issn=0838-4479|doi=10.7202/039213ar}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christensen differentiates between "progressive masculism" and an "extremist version". The former welcomes many of the societal changes promoted by feminists, while stating that many aimed at reducing sexism against women have had the effect of increasing it against men.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt; The latter promotes male supremacy to some degree and is generally based on a belief in women's inferiority. Nicholas Davidson, in his book ''The Failure of Feminism'' describes an extremist version of masculism which he termed "virism". According to Davidson, in this view "What ails society is 'effeminacy'. The improvement of society requires that the influence of female values be decreased and the influence of male values increased…."&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Davidson1988"&gt;{{cite book|author=Nicholas Davidson|title=The failure of feminism|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=pf8pAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA274|year=1988|publisher=Prometheus Books, Publishers|isbn=978-0-87975-408-2|pages=274–}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Gender theory|Gender theories]], which have frequently focussed on woman-based or feminist approaches,  have come to include a "masculism" approach which seeks to examine oppression in a masculinist society from the perspectives of men, most of whom do not benefit from that society.&lt;ref name="HoogensenSolheim2006"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Gunhild Hoogensen|author2=Bruce Olav Solheim|title=Women in power: world leaders since 1960|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ZPThCTMVsZQC&amp;pg=PA21|year=2006|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-275-98190-7|pages=21–}}&lt;/ref&gt;
From a feminist perspective to philosophy, masculinism seeks to value and include only male views, and claim "that anything that cannot be reduced or translated in men's experience should be excluded from the subject-matter of philosophy."&lt;ref name="BunninYu2008"/&gt;

==Topic areas of interest to masculism==

===Education===
Many masculists suggest the abolition of co-educational schooling, believing that single-sex schools are preferred for the well-being of boys.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"&gt;Melissa Blais and Francis Dupuis-Déri. "Masculinism and the Antifeminist Countermovement." ''Social Movement Studies: Journal of Social, Cultural and Political Protest'' 11:1 (2012): 21–39.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Employment===
Data from 1994 in the U.S. reported that 94% of workplace fatalities occur to men. Masculist Warren Farrell has argued that men are often clustered in dirty, physically demanding and hazardous jobs in an unjustifiably disproportionate manner.&lt;ref name=reason/&gt;

===Violence===
{{Violence against men}}
Masculists express concern about violence against men being depicted as humorous, in the media and elsewhere.&lt;ref name=MYTH&gt;Warren Farrell, ''The Myth of Male Power: Why Men Are the Disposable Sex'' (NY: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1993; ISBN 0-671-79349-7).&lt;/ref&gt;

Masculists also express concern about violence against men being ignored, minimalized or taken less seriously than violence against women.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?click_id=13&amp;art_id=vn20081125064002133C731559&amp;set_id= iol.co.za]&lt;/ref&gt; They assert that there is gender symmetry in [[domestic violence]].&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Another concern expressed is that assumptions of female innocence or sympathy for women may result in disproportionate penalties for women and men for similar crimes,&lt;ref name="MYTH" /&gt; lack of sympathy for male victims in [[domestic violence]] cases, and dismissal of female-on-male [[sexual assault]] and [[sexual harassment]] cases.

===Custody===
{{main|Fathers' rights movement}}
"Custody law is perhaps the best-known area of men's rights activism", as it is more common for the mother to obtain custody of children in case of divorce. [[David Benatar]], head of philosophy at the [[University of Cape Town]], argues: "When the man is the primary care-giver his chances of winning custody are lower than when the woman is the primary care-giver. Even when the case is not contested by the mother, he's still not as likely to get custody as when the woman's claim is uncontested".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17907534 "Just who are men's rights activists?"], BBC, 2 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

===Suicide===
Masculinists cite high rates of suicide in men.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;

==Reactions==

===Feminism===
Feminists respond to the different ideologies of masculism in different ways. Masculists who promote gender equality are often considered [[male feminism|male feminists]].&lt;ref&gt;Janet M. Martin and Maryanne Borrelli, ''Other Elites: Women, Politics, &amp; Power in the Executive Branch'' (Lynne Rienner Publishers, 2000; ISBN 1-55587-971-3, ISBN 978-1-55587-971-6).&lt;/ref&gt; It is the general opinion of modern [[Feminism|feminists]] that masculism, when defined as "male superiority or dominance",&lt;ref name="Masculinist"/&gt; is inherently opposed to the equality cause and is a form of [[misogyny]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Reaction and resistance: feminism, law, and social change|author1=Susan B. Boyd|author2=Dorothy E. Chunn|author3=Hester Lessard|pages=65–97|year=2007|publisher=UBC Press|isbn=978-0-7748-1411-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Philosopher Ferrell Christensen states that if masculism and feminism refer to the belief that men/women are systematically discriminated against, and that this discrimination should be eliminated, there is not necessarily a conflict between feminism and masculism, and some assert that they are both.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt;  However, many believe that one sex is more discriminated against, and thus use one label and reject the other.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt;

===Criticisms and responses===

To the extent that masculism is associated with antifeminist masculinism, its primary focus is on "masculinity and the place of white heterosexual men in North America and European societies."&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;

Some masculinists believe that differentiated gender roles are natural. There is considerable evidence for social influences (e.g. gender division of labor, socialization) as the sole or primary origin of gender differentiation.&lt;ref name="Risman, Barbara 2004"&gt;[[Barbara Risman]], "Gender as a Social Structure: Theory Wrestling with Activism." ''Gender &amp; Society'' 18.4 (2004): 429–450.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Susan A. Basow, ''Gender Stereotypes and Roles'' (Pacific Grove, CA: Brooks/Cole, 1992).&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, belief in inherent gender differences allows for inequality and for the dominant group to assert power by means of perceived difference.&lt;ref name="Risman, Barbara 2004"/&gt;
The masculinist movement has to some extent appropriated the concepts of [[evolutionary psychology]]: this theory argues that adaptation during prehistory resulted in complementary but different roles for the different genders, and that this balance has been destabilized by feminism since the 1960s.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;

Some masculinist movements are explicitly antifeminist.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; According to Blais and Dupuis-Déri, "the contents of [masculinist] websites and the testimony of feminists that we questioned confirm that masculinists are generally critical of even moderate feminists and feminists at the head of official feminist organizations."&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Masculinist activism has involved disruption of events organized by feminists and lawsuits against feminist academics, journalists, or activists.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Furthermore, masculinist actions are sometimes extreme; father's rights activists have bombed family courts in Australia and have issued bomb threats in the UK, although it is ambiguous whether there was public and organized militant group involvement.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; They have also engaged in "tire-slashing, the mailing of excrement-filled packages, threats against politicians and their children."&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Spokesmen for these groups have also spoken out against public awareness campaigns to prevent sexual assault, arguing that they portray a negative image of men, and one masculinist group harassed administrators of dozens of battered women's shelters and women's centers.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Men's rights|Discrimination}}
* [[Antifeminism]]
* [[Hypermasculinity]]
* [[Kyriarchy]]
* [[Machismo]]
* [[Masculine psychology]]
* [[Masculinity]]
* [[Matriarchy]]
* [[Men's liberation]]
* [[Men's movement]]
* [[Misandry]]

===Men's organizations===
* [[Fathers 4 Justice]]
* [[International Men's Day]] (19 November: [[Trinidad and Tobago]], [[Jamaica]], [[Australia]], [[India]], [[United States]], [[Singapore]], [[United Kingdom]], [[Malta]], [[South Africa]], [[Hungary]], [[Ireland]], [[Ghana]], and [[Canada]])
* [[Save Indian Family]]

===Notable persons associated with masculism===
* [[Warren Farrell]]
* [[Glenn Sacks]]
* [[Robert Bly]]

===Books===
* ''[[Manliness (book)]]'' (2006)

==Bibliography==
*''[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/6762 Politics]'' of [[Aristotle]] asserts excellence varies with social role, including gender.
*[[s:The Legal Subjection of Men|''The Legal Subjection of Men'']], 1908 antithesis of [[John Stuart Mill]]'s 1869 ''[[The Subjection of Women]]''.
*[[s:The Fraud of Feminism|''The Fraud of Feminism'']] by [[Ernest Belfort Bax]], 1914.
*''The Myth of the Monstrous Male and Other Feminist Fallacies''; John Gordon, Playboy Press, New York, 1982; ISBN 0-87223-758-3
*"La condition masculine dans le Rouge et le Noir" Gilles Aerts, mémoire de maîtrise, University of British Columbia, 1987.
*''The Myth of Male Power: Why Men Are the Disposable Sex''; Warren Farrell, Simon &amp; Schuster, New York, 1993: ISBN 0-671-79349-7
*''Manliness'' by [[Harvey Mansfield]] (2006) Yale Press [http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/book.asp?isbn=0300106645] ISBN 0-300-10664-5
*''Not Guilty: The Case in Defense of Men''; David Thomas, William Morrow and Co., Inc., New York, 1993; ISBN 0-688-11024-X
*''Good Will Toward Men''; Jack Kammer, St. Martin's Press, New York, 1994; ISBN 0-312-10471-5
*''Moral Panic: Biopolitics Rising''; John Fekete, Robert Davies Publishing, Montreal-Toronto, 1994: ISBN 1-895854-09-1
*''The New Men's Studies: A Selected and Annotated Interdisciplinary Bibliography'' (2nd Edition); Eugene R. August, Libraries Unlimited, Inc., Englewood, CO, 1994: ISBN 1-56308-084-2
*''A Man's World: How Real Is Male Privilege – And How High Is Its Price?''; Ellis Cose, Harper Collins, New York, 1995: ISBN 0-06-017206-1
*''Why Men Don't Iron: The Real Science of Gender Studies''; Anne &amp; Bill Moir, Harper Collins, Hammersmith, London, 1998; ISBN 0-00-257035-1 (Trade Paperback); ISBN 0-00-257048-3 (Hardcover)
*''The Strong, Sensitive Boy''; Ted Zeff, Prana Publishing (May 3, 2010); ISBN 0966074521
*''The Church Impotent: The Feminization of Christianity''; Leon J. Podles, Spence Publishing Co., Dallas, TX, 1999. (The title is a play on the Christian theological terms [[Church militant and church triumphant|''church militant'' and ''church triumphant'']].)
*''Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture''; Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young, McGill-Queen's University Press, Montreal, 2001; ISBN 0-7735-2272-7
*''"Feminine" Heterosexual Men: Subverting Heteropatriarchal Sexual Scripts?''; Darryl B. Hill, The Journal of Men's Studies, Spring 2006, Men's Studies Press; ISSN 1060-8265
*''Re-Thinking Men:  Heroes, Villains and Victims''; Anthony Synnott, Ashgate, 2009; ISBN  978-0754677093
*''The Second Sexism''; David Benatar, Wiley-Blackwell, 2012; ISBN  978-0470674512
*''Email to the Universe''; Robert Anton Wilson, New Falcon Publications, 2008; ISBN  978-1561841943
*''Sex Differences, Modern Biology and the Unisex Fallacy'', Yves Christen
*''[[Who Stole Feminism? How Women Have Betrayed Women]]''; [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] ISBN 0-684-80156-6
*''The War Against Boys: How Misguided Feminism Is Harming Our Young Men''; Christina Hoff Sommers ISBN 0-684-84956-9
*''Domestic Violence: The 12 Things You Aren't Supposed to Know'' by Thomas B. James ISBN 1-59330-122-7
*''Ceasefire! : Why Women And Men Must Join Forces To Achieve True Equality''; Cathy Young ISBN 0-684-83442-1
*''The Masculine Mystique''; Andrew Kimbrell ISBN 0-345-38658-2

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|masculinism}}
{{Wiktionary}}
*[http://www.acfc.org American Coalition for Fathers and Children]
*[http://www.fathersforvirginia.org Equal Parental Rights for Fathers]
*[http://www.ncfm.org National Coalition of Free Men]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Masculism}}
{{Discrimination}}
}}

[[Category:Masculism| ]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Men's movement]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1980s]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Civil rights and liberties]]
[[Category:Masculinity]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>