<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171118164413|810962731" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25454239" pageid="25454239" ns="0" title="Masculism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-21T20:20:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{masculism sidebar}}
'''Masculism''' or '''masculinism''' may variously refer to advocacy of the rights or needs of [[Man|men]] and [[boy]]s; and the adherence to or promotion of attributes (opinions, values, attitudes, habits) regarded as typical of men and boys.&lt;ref name="BunninYu2008"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"&gt;{{cite book|last=Christensen|first=Ferrell|editor=Ted Honderich|title=The Oxford Companion to Philosophy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4ii8AAAAIAAJ|year=1995|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-866132-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=reason&gt;{{cite news|publisher=''[[Reason magazine|Reason]]''|title=Man Troubles: Making Sense of the Men's Movement|author=[[Cathy Young]]|date=July 1994|url=http://reason.com/archives/1994/07/01/man-troubles|quote=Masculism (mas'kye liz*'em), n. 1. the belief that equality between the sexes requires the recognition and redress of prejudice and discrimination against men as well as women. 2. the movement organized around this belief. References Warren Farrell, Jack Kammer, and others activists in the men's movement.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Definition and scope==
The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' (OED) defines ''masculism'', or synonymously ''masculinism'', as the "advocacy of the rights of men; adherence to or promotion of opinions, values, etc., regarded as typical of men; (more generally) anti-feminism, machismo."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=masculism, n|work=Oxford English Dictionary Online|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|edition=3rd |year=2000|accessdate=2015-02-17|quote=masculism, n. †1. The possession of masculine physical traits by a woman. Obs. rare. 2. = masculinism n.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oedMasculinism"&gt;{{cite web|title=masculinism, n|work=Oxford English Dictionary Online|publisher=Oxford University Press|edition=3rd |year=2000|accessdate=2015-02-17|quote=masculinism, n. Advocacy of the rights of men; adherence to or promotion of opinions, values, etc., regarded as typical of men; (more generally) anti-feminism, machismo.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, philosopher Ferrell Christensen differentiates "masculism" from "masculinism", defining the latter as promoting the attributes of manliness.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt; 
Political scientist Georgia Duerst-Lahti also distinguishes the two terms, with masculism expressing the ethos of the early gender-egalitarian [[men's movement]], while masculinism refers to the ideology of [[patriarchy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | last = Duerst-Lahti | first = Georgia | contribution = Gender Ideology: masculinism and femininalism |pages=159&amp;ndash;192 |editor1-last=Goertz |editor1-first=Gary |editor2-last=Mazur |editor2-first=Amy G. |title=Politics, gender, and concepts: theory and methodology |year=2008 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=9780521723428}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dupuis-Déri2009"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Dupuis-Déri|first1=Francis|title=Le " masculinisme ": une histoire politique du mot (en Anglais et en Français)| trans-title = “Masculinism”: a political history of the term (in English and French) |journal=Recherches Féministes |volume=22 |issue=2 |pages=97&amp;ndash;123 |url =https://doi.org/10.7202/039213ar |date=2009 |doi=10.7202/039213ar | ref = harv | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christensen differentiates between "progressive masculism" and an "extremist version". The former welcomes many of the societal changes promoted by feminists, while regretting that some measures reducing sexism against women have increased it against men.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt; The extremist version promotes male supremacy to some degree, and is generally based on a belief in women's inferiority. Nicholas Davidson, in his book ''The Failure of Feminism'', describes an extremist version of masculism which he termed "virism": "What ails society is 'effeminacy'. The improvement of society requires that the influence of female values be decreased and the influence of male values increased…."&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Davidson1988"&gt;Christensen, Ferrell (2005), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=WbkSDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA562 Masculism]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Honderich | editor-first = Ted | title = The Oxford companion to philosophy |pages=562&amp;ndash;563 | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford New York | isbn = 9780199264797 }}
* ''Citing'': {{cite book | last = Davidson | first = Nicholas | title = The failure of feminism |page=274 | publisher = Prometheus Books | location = Buffalo, New York | year = 1988 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=pf8pAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA274 | isbn = 9780879754082 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Gender theory|Gender theories]], which have frequently focused on woman-based or feminist approaches, have come to examine oppression in a masculist society also from the perspectives of men, most of whom are also oppressed by that society.&lt;ref name="HoogensenSolheim2006"&gt;Hoogensen, Gunhild; Solheim, Bruce Olav (2006), "[https://books.google.com/?id=ZPThCTMVsZQC&amp;pg=PA21 Women in theory and practice]", in {{cite book | editor-last1 = Hoogensen | editor-first1 = Gunhild | editor-last2 = Solheim | editor-first2 = Bruce Olav |title=Women in power: world leaders since 1960|year=2006|page=21|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=9780275981907}}&lt;/ref&gt; From a feminist perspective to philosophy, masculinism seeks to value and include only male views, and claim "that anything that cannot be reduced or translated in men's experience should be excluded from the subject-matter of philosophy.&lt;ref name="BunninYu2008"/&gt;

==Topic areas of interest==
{{main|Men's rights movement}}

===Education and employment===
Many masculists suggest oppose co-educational schooling, believing that single-sex schools better promote the well-being of boys.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"&gt;
{{cite journal | last1 = Blais | first1 = Melissa | last2 = Dupuis-Déri | first2 = Francis | title = Masculinism and the antifeminist countermovement | journal = [[Social Movement Studies|Social Movement Studies: Journal of Social, Cultural and Political Protest]] | volume = 11 | issue = 1 | pages = 21&amp;ndash;39 | publisher = [[Taylor and Francis]] | doi = 10.1080/14742837.2012.640532 | date = 2012 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/14742837.2012.640532 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other masculists and [[Equity feminism|equity feminists]] note that boys lag behind girls in educational achievement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Sommers |first1=Christina | author-link = Christina Hoff Sommers|title=The war against boys|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2000/05/the-war-against-boys/304659/|work= [[The Atlantic]] | date = May 2000 |accessdate=30 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Data from the U.S. in 1994 reported that men suffer 94% of workplace fatalities. Masculist [[Warren Farrell]] has argued that men do a disproportionate share of dirty, physically demanding, and hazardous jobs.&lt;ref name=reason/&gt;

===Violence and suicide===
{{Violence against men}}
{{See also|Violence against men}}

Masculists cite higher rates of suicide in men than women.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Masculists express concern about violence against men being depicted as humorous, in the media and elsewhere.&lt;ref name=MYTH&gt;{{cite book | last = Farrell | first = Warren | author-link = Warren Farrell | title = [[The Myth of Male Power|The myth of male power: why men are the disposable sex]] | publisher = [[Berkley Books]] | location = New York | year = 2001 | isbn = 9780425181447 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

They also express concern about violence against men being ignored or minimized in comparison to violence against women,&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Mvulane | first = Zama | title = Do men suffer spousal abuse? | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20090221033948/http://www.iol.co.za:80/index.php?click_id=13&amp;art_id=vn20081125064002133C731559&amp;set_id= | archive-date = November 25, 2008 | url = http://www.iol.co.za:80/index.php?click_id=13&amp;art_id=vn20081125064002133C731559&amp;set_id= | work = [[Cape Times]] | via = [[Independent Online (South Africa)|IOL]] | location = South Africa | page = 12 | date = November 25, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; some asserting gender symmetry in [[domestic violence]].&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Another of their concerns is that assumptions of female innocence or sympathy for women may lead to unequal penalties for women and men who commit similar crimes,&lt;ref name="MYTH" /&gt; to lack of sympathy for male victims in [[domestic violence]] cases, and to dismissal of female-on-male [[sexual assault]] and [[sexual harassment]] cases.

===Custody===
{{main|Fathers' rights movement}}
According to [[David Benatar]], head of philosophy at the [[University of Cape Town]], "Custody law is perhaps the best-known area of men's rights activism", as it is more likely in most parts of the world for the mother to obtain custody of children in case of divorce. He argues: "When the man is the primary care-giver his chances of winning custody are lower than when the woman is the primary care-giver. Even when the case is not contested by the mother, he's still not as likely to get custody as when the woman's claim is uncontested".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = de Castella | first = Tom | title = Just who are men's rights activists? | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17907534 | work = [[BBC News Online#Features|BBC News Magazine]] | date = May 2, 2012 | access-date = May 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== South African masculist evangelical movements ==
In the wake of the abolition of apartheid, South Africa has seen a resurgence of masculist Christian evangelical groups, led by two complementary men's and women's movements, the Mighty Men movement and the Worthy Women movement.&lt;ref name="Nadar_Potgieter"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Nadar | first1 = Sarojini | last2 = Potgieter | first2 = Cheryl | title = Liberated through submission?: The Worthy Woman's Conference as a case study of for''men''ism | journal = Journal of Feminist Studies in Religion | volume = 26 | issue = 2 | pages = 141&amp;ndash;151 | publisher = [[Project MUSE]] | date = Fall 2010 | url = https://muse.jhu.edu/article/394797 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Mighty Men movement harkens back to the Victorian idea of Muscular Christianity&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Dube | first = Siphiwe | title = Muscular Christianity in contemporary South Africa: The case of the Mighty Men Conference | journal = HTS [[Theological Studies/Teologiese Studies]] | volume = 71 | issue = 3 | pages = 1&amp;ndash;9 | publisher = AOSIS OpenJournals | date = July 2015 | url = https://hts.org.za/index.php/HTS/article/view/2945/html | ref = harv | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the movement does not lead discussions about institutionalized racism.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Dube | first = Siphiwe | title = Race, whiteness and transformation in the Promise Keepers America and the Mighty Men Conference: A comparative analysis | journal = HTS [[Theological Studies/Teologiese Studies]] | volume = 72 | issue = 1 | pages = 1&amp;ndash;8 | publisher = AOSIS OpenJournals | date = November 2016 | url = http://www.hts.org.za/index.php/HTS/article/view/3476/html | ref = harv | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt; Feminist scholars argue that the movement's lack of attention to women's rights and their historical struggle with racial equality makes it a threat to women and to the stability of the country.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Scholar Miranda Pillay argues that the Mighty Men movement appeal lies in its resistance to gender equality as incompatible with Christian values, and in raising patriarchy to a "hyper-normative status," beyond challenge by other claims to power.&lt;ref&gt;Pillay, Miranda (2015), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=yMTSCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA61 Mighty Men, Mighty Families: A pro-family Christian movement to (re)enforce patriarchal control?]", in {{cite book | editor-last1 = Conradie | editor-first1 = Ernst M. | editor-last2=Pillay| editor-first2=Miranda| title = Ecclesial reform and deform movements in the South African context | pages = 61&amp;ndash;77 | publisher = African SUN MeDIA | location = Stellenbosch, South Africa | isbn = 9781920689766}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Worthy Women movement is a women's auxilliary to Mighty Men in advocating ''men''ism, a belief in the inherent superiority of men over women.&lt;ref name="Nadar_Potgieter" /&gt; Their leader Gretha Wiid She blames South Africa's disorder on the liberation of women, and aims to restore the nation through its families, making women again subservient to their men.&lt;ref&gt;Nortjé-Meyer, Lilly (2015), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=yMTSCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA86 A movement seeking to embody support of patriarchal structures and patterns in church and society: Gertha Wiid's Worthy Women movement]", in {{cite book | editor-last1 = Conradie | editor-first1 = Ernst M. | editor-last2=Pillay| editor-first2=Miranda| title = Ecclesial reform and deform movements in the South African context | pages = 86&amp;ndash;93 | publisher = African SUN MeDIA | location = Stellenbosch, South Africa | isbn = 9781920689766}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her seemingly paradoxical success is attributed to her balancing claims that God created the gender hierarchy, but that women are no less valuable than men&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Nortjé-Meyer | first = Lilly | title = A critical analysis of Gretha Wiid’s sex ideology and her biblical hermeneutics | journal = Verbum et Ecclesia | volume = 32 | issue = 1 | pages = 1&amp;ndash;7 | publisher = AOSIS OpenJournals | date = November 2011 | url = http://verbumetecclesia.org.za/index.php/VE/article/view/472/html | ref = harv | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt;, and that restoration of traditional gender roles relieves existential anxiety in post-apartheid South Africa.&lt;ref name="Nadar_Potgieter"/&gt;

==Reactions==

===Criticisms and responses===
Some critics believe masculism (sometimes called [[androcentrism]]) focuses on [[Chauvinism#Male chauvinism|male superiority]] or dominance&lt;ref&gt;.
''Responses'':
* {{cite web|title=masculinist, n|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/masculinist|website=merriam-webster.com|publisher=[[Merriam-Webster]]|accessdate=July 18, 2011}}
* {{cite book | last = Brittan | first = Arthur | title = Masculinity and power|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ptFzQgAACAAJ&amp;pg=PA4 | publisher = Basil Blackwell | location = Oxford New York | year = 1989 | isbn = 9780631141679 |page= 4|quote= ''Masculinism is the ideology that justifies and naturalizes male domination. As such it is the ideology of patriarchy. Masculinism takes it for granted that there is a fundamental difference between man and women, it assumes that heterosexuality is normal, it accepts without question the sexual division of labour, and it sanctions the political and dominant role of men in the public and private spheres.''}}
* {{cite journal|last=Kahl|first=David H.|title=Analyzing Masculinist Movements: Responding to Antifeminism through Critical Communication Pedagogy|journal=Communication Teacher|volume=29|issue=1|year=2015|pages=21–26|doi=10.1080/17404622.2014.985600}}
* Ruth, Sheila (1990), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=HzYFAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PT7 An introduction to women's studies]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Ruth | editor-first = Sheila | title = Issues in feminism: an introduction to women's studies | page = 7 | publisher = Mayfield | location = Mountain View, California | edition = 2nd | isbn = 9780874849370 | quote = ''Masculine-ism or masculism (sometimes called androcentrism) is the elevation of the masculine, conceptually and physically, to the level of the universal and ideal.'' }}&lt;/ref&gt; to the exclusion of [[Woman|women]].&lt;ref name="BunninYu2008"&gt;Bunnin, Nicholas; Yu, Jiyuan (2004), "[https://books.google.com/books?id=LdbxabeToQYC&amp;pg=PA411 Masculinism]", in {{cite book | editor-last1 = Bunnin | editor-first1 = Nicholas | editor-last2 = Yu | editor-first2 = Jiyuan | title = The Blackwell dictionary of Western philosophy |page=411 | publisher = Blackwell | location = Malden, Massachusetts | year = 2004 | isbn = 9780470997215 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some masculinists believe that differentiated gender roles are natural. There is some evidence for social influences (e.g. gender division of labor, socialization) as the sole or primary origin of gender differentiation.&lt;ref name="Risman, Barbara 2004"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Risman | first = Barbara J. | author-link = Barbara Risman | title = Gender as a social structure: theory wrestling with activism | journal = [[Gender &amp; Society]] | volume = 18 | issue = 4 | pages = 429&amp;ndash;450 | publisher = [[Sage Publications|Sage]] | doi = 10.1177/0891243204265349 | jstor = 4149444 | date = August 2004 | url = https://doi.org/10.1177/0891243204265349 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Basow | first = Susan A. | title = Gender: stereotypes and roles | publisher = Brooks/Cole  | location = Pacific Grove, California | year = 1992 | edition = 3rd | isbn = 9780534121204 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some parts of the masculinist movement have to some extent borrow concepts from [[evolutionary psychology]]: this theory argues that adaptation during prehistory resulted in complementary but different roles for the different genders, and that this balance has been destabilized by feminism since the 1960s.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;

===Feminism===
Some masculinists have been described as explicitly antifeminist by feminist activists.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; According to Blais and Dupuis-Déri, "the contents of [masculinist] websites and the testimony of feminists that we questioned confirm that masculinists are generally critical of even moderate feminists and feminists at the head of official feminist organizations."&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Some masculinist activism has involved disruption of events organized by feminists and lawsuits against feminist academics, journalists, or activists.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Furthermore, masculinist actions are sometimes extreme; father's rights activists have bombed family courts in Australia and have issued bomb threats in the UK, although it is ambiguous whether there was public and organized militant group involvement.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; They have also engaged in "tire-slashing, the mailing of excrement-filled packages, threats against politicians and their children."&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Spokesmen for these groups have also spoken out against public awareness campaigns to prevent sexual assault, arguing that they portray a negative image of men, and one masculinist group harassed administrators of dozens of battered women's shelters and women's centers.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Martin | first1 = Janet M. | last2 = Borrelli | first2 = Maryanne | title = The other elites: Women, politics, and power in the Executive Branch | publisher = Lynne Rienner Publishers | location = Boulder, Colorado | year = 2001 | isbn = 9781555879716 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Philosopher Ferrell Christensen states that if masculism and feminism refer to the belief that men/women are systematically discriminated against, and that this discrimination should be eliminated, there is not necessarily a conflict between feminism and masculism, and some assert that they are both.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt; However, many believe that one sex is more discriminated against, and thus use one label and reject the other.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt;

==See also==
{{Wiktionary|masculinism|masculism}}
{{Div col|2}}
* [[Antifeminism]]
* [[Hegemonic masculinity]]
* [[Hypermasculinity]]
* [[Heteropatriarchy]]
* [[Identity politics]]
* [[Machismo]]
* [[Male privilege]]
* [[Manosphere]]
* [[Masculine psychology]]
* [[Masculinity]]
* [[Matriarchy]]
* [[Men's liberation]]
* [[Men's movement]]
* [[Men's rights]]
* [[Misandry]]
* [[Misogyny]]
* [[Patriarchy]]
{{Div col end}}

;Men's organizations
* [[Fathers 4 Justice]]
* [[International Men's Day]] (19 November) 
::[[Trinidad and Tobago]], [[Jamaica]], [[Australia]], [[India]], [[United States]], [[Singapore]], [[United Kingdom]], [[Malta]], [[South Africa]], [[Hungary]], [[Ireland]], [[Ghana]], and [[Canada]])
* [[Save Indian Family]]

;Notable people associated with masculism
* [[Warren Farrell]]
* [[Robert Bly]]

;Books
* ''[[Manliness (book)|Manliness]]'' (2006)

{{Portalbar|Masculinism|Human Rights|Men's rights|Discrimination}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
;Books
* {{cite book | last = August | first = Eugene | title = The new men's studies: a selected and annotated interdisciplinary bibliography | publisher = Libraries Unlimited | location = Englewood, Colorado | edition = 2nd | year = 1994 | isbn = 9781563080845 }}
* {{cite book | last = Baumeister | first = Roy | author-link = Roy Baumeister | title = Is there anything good about men?: How cultures flourish by exploiting men | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford New York | year = 2010 | isbn = 9780195374100 }}
* {{cite book | last = Bax| first = Ernest Belfort | author-link = Ernest Belfort Bax | title = [[s:The Legal Subjection of Men|The legal subjection of men]] | publisher = New Age Press | location = London | year = 1908 | oclc = 33295675 }}
::''Antithesis of'': {{cite book | last = Mill | first = John Stuart | author-link = John Stuart Mill | title = [[The Subjection of Women|The subjection of women]] | publisher = D. Appleton &amp; Co. | location = New York | year = 1869 | oclc = 15643538}}
* {{cite book | last = Bax| first = Ernest Belfort | author-link = Ernest Belfort Bax | title = [[s:The Fraud of Feminism|The fraud of feminism]] | publisher = Grant Richards | location = London | year = 1913 | oclc = 33342327 }}
* {{cite book | last = Benatar | first = David | title = The second sexism: discrimination against men and boys | publisher = Wiley-Blackwell | location = Malden, MA Oxford | year = 2012 | isbn = 9780470674512 }}

* {{cite book | last = Christen | first = Yves | title = Sex differences: modern biology and the unisex fallacy | publisher = Routledge | year = 2017 | isbn = 9781315129228 }}
* {{cite book | last = Cose | first = Ellis | title = A man's world: how real is male privilege and how high is its price | publisher = Harper Collins Publishers | location = New York, New York | year = 1995 | isbn = 9780060172060 }}
* {{cite book | last = Farrell | first = Warren | title = [[The Myth of Male Power|The myth of male power: why men are the disposable sex]] | publisher = [[Berkley Books]] | location = New York | year = 2001 | isbn = 9780425181447 }}
* {{cite book | last = Fekete | first = John | title = Moral panic: biopolitics rising | publisher = Robert Davies Publishing | location = Montréal | year = 1994 | isbn = 9781895854091 }}
* {{cite book | last = Gordon | first = John | title = The myth of the monstrous male, and other feminist fables | publisher = [[Playboy|Playboy Press]] | location = New York | year = 1982 | isbn = 9780872237582 }}
* {{cite book | last = Hoff Sommers | first = Christina | author-link = Christina Hoff Sommers | title = [[Who Stole Feminism? How Women Have Betrayed Women|Who stole feminism?: how women have betrayed women]] | publisher = Touchstone/Simon &amp; Schuster | location = New York | year = 1995 | isbn = 9780684801568 }}
* {{cite book | last = Hoff Sommers | first = Christina | author-link = Christina Hoff Sommers | title = The war against boys: how misguided feminism is harming our young men | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster | location = New York | year = 2000 | isbn = 9780684849560 }}
* {{cite book | last = James | first = Thomas B. | title = Domestic violence: the 12 things you aren't supposed to know | publisher = Aventine Press | location = Chula Vista, California | year = 2003 | isbn = 9781593301224 }}
* {{cite book | last = Kammer | first = Jack | title = Good will toward men: women talk candidly about the balance of power between the sexes | publisher = St. Martin's Press | location = New York | year = 1994 | isbn = 9780312104719 }}
* {{cite book | last = Kimbrell | first = Andrew | title = The masculine mystique: the politics of masculinity | publisher = Ballantine Books | location = New York | year = 1995 | isbn = 9780345386588 }}
* {{cite book | last = Mansfield | first = Harvey | author-link = Harvey Mansfield | title = Manliness | publisher = Yale University Press | location = New Haven | year = 2006 | url = http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/book.asp?isbn=0300106645 | isbn = 9780300129939 }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Moir | first1 = Anne | last2 = Moir | first2 = Bill | title = Why men don't iron: the fascinating and unalterable differences between men and women | publisher = Citadel Press/Kensington Pub | location = New York | year = 2003 | isbn = 9780806524733 }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Nathanson | first1 = Paul | last2 = Young | first2 = Katherine K. | title = Spreading misandry: the teaching of contempt for men in popular culture | publisher = McGill-Queen's University Press | location = Montreal, Quebec | year = 2001 | isbn = 9780773522725 }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Phoenix | first1 = Ann | last2 = Frosh | first2 = Stephen | last3 = Pattmann | first3 = Ro | author-link1 = Ann Phoenix | title = Young masculinities: understanding boys in contemporary society | publisher = Palgrave | location = Basingstoke | year = 2002 | isbn = 9780333779231 }}
* {{cite book | last = Podles | first = Leon J. | title = The church impotent: the feminization of Christianity | publisher = Spence Pub. | location = Dallas, Texas | year = 1999 | oclc = 894557106 }}
::The title is a play on the Christian theological terms [[Church militant and church triumphant|''church militant'' and ''church triumphant'']].
* {{cite book | last = Synnott | first = Anthony | title = Re-thinking men: heroes, villains and victims | publisher = Ashgate | location = Farnham, England Burlington, VT | year = 2009 | isbn = 9780754677093 }}
* {{cite book | last = Thomas | first = David | title = Not guilty: the case in defense of men | publisher = William Morrow and Co. Inc. | location = New York | year = 1993 | isbn = 9780688110246 }}
* {{cite book | last = Webb | first = Robert | author-link = Robert Webb | title = How not to be a boy | publisher = Canongate | location = Edinburgh | year = 2017 | isbn = 9781786890085 }}
* {{cite book | last = Wilson | first = Robert | title = Email to the universe: and other alterations of consciousness | publisher = New Falcon Publications | location = Tempe, Ariz | year = 2005 | isbn = 9781561841943 }}
* {{cite book | last = Young | first = Cathy | title = Ceasefire!: why women and men must join forces to achieve true equality | publisher = Free Press | location = New York, New York | year = 1999 | isbn = 9780684834429 }}
* {{cite book | last = Zeff | first = Ted | title = The strong sensitive boy: help your son become a happy, confident man | publisher = Prana Publishing | location = San Ramon, California | year = 2010 | isbn = 9780966074529 }}

;Thesis
* {{cite thesis|degree=MA|last=Aerts|first=Gilles|date=1987|title=La condition masculine dans le Rouge et le Noir (mémoire de maîtrise) |publisher=[[University of British Columbia]]|url =https://www.armance.com/La%20condition%20masculine.pdf|isbn=9780315419100}} [https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/20355812 WorldCat link.]

;Journal articles
* {{Cite journal | last = Hill | first = Darryl B. | title = “Feminine” heterosexual men: subverting heteropatriarchal sexual scripts? | journal = [[The Journal of Men's Studies]] | volume = 14 | issue = 2 | pages = 161&amp;ndash;172 | publisher = [[Men's Studies Press]] via [[Sage Publishing|Sage]] | doi = 10.3149/jms.1402.145 | date = March 2007 | url = https://dx.doi.org/10.3149/jms.1402.145 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}

;Websites
*''[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/6762 Politics]'' of [[Aristotle]] asserts excellence varies with social role, including gender.

{{Masculinism|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Civil rights and liberties]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Masculinity]]
[[Category:Masculism| ]]
[[Category:Men's movement]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1980s]]
[[Category:Men's rights]]
[[Category:Men]]
[[Category:Men's health]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>