<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161113165139|749300560" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25454239" pageid="25454239" ns="0" title="Masculism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-13T17:12:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{cite check|date=October 2015}}
{{unfocused|date=July 2015}}
{{Lead too short|date=April 2016}}
}}
{{Masculism sidebar}}

'''Masculism''' or '''masculinism''' may variously refer to advocacy of the rights or needs of [[Man|men]] and [[boy]]s; the adherence to or promotion of opinions, values, attitudes, etc. regarded as typical of men and boys.&lt;ref name="BunninYu2008"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"&gt;{{cite book|last=Christensen|first=Ferrell|editor=Ted Honderich|title=The Oxford Companion to Philosophy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4ii8AAAAIAAJ|year=1995|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-866132-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=reason&gt;{{cite news|publisher=''[[Reason magazine|Reason]]''|title=Man Troubles: Making Sense of the Men's Movement|author=[[Cathy Young]]|date=July 1994|url=http://reason.com/archives/1994/07/01/man-troubles|quote=Masculism (mas'kye liz*'em), n. 1. the belief that equality between the sexes requires the recognition and redress of prejudice and discrimination against men as well as women. 2. the movement organized around this belief. Not to worry: This word is not in the dictionary. But it would be if the decision were up to Warren Farrell, Jack Kammer, and others activists in the men's movement.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Definition and scope==
The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' (OED) defines ''masculism'' as a [[synonym]] of masculinism which the OED regards as the "advocacy of the rights of men; adherence to or promotion of opinions, values, etc., regarded as typical of men; (more generally) anti-feminism, machismo."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=masculism, n|work=Oxford English Dictionary Online|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|edition=3rd |year=2000|accessdate=2015-02-17|quote=masculism, n. †1. The possession of masculine physical traits by a woman. Obs. rare. 2. = masculinism n.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oedMasculinism"&gt;{{cite web|title=masculinism, n|work=Oxford English Dictionary Online|publisher=Oxford University Press|edition=3rd |year=2000|accessdate=2015-02-17|quote=masculinism, n. Advocacy of the rights of men; adherence to or promotion of opinions, values, etc., regarded as typical of men; (more generally) anti-feminism, machismo.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Philosopher Ferrell Christensen differentiates the words "masculism" and "masculinism"; he defines the latter as promoting the attributes of manliness.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt; 
Political scientist Georgia Duerst-Lahti also distinguishes between the two terms, with masculism being more associated with the early gender egalitarian days of [[men's movement]], while masculinism refers to [[patriarchy]] and its ideology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |editor1-last=Goertz |editor1-first=Gary |editor2-last=Mazur |editor2-first=Amy G. |title=Politics, gender, and concepts: theory and methodology |year=2008 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |chapter=Gender Ideology: masculinism and femininalism |author=Georgia Duerst-Lahti |isbn=9780521723428|pages=159&amp;ndash;192}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dupuis-Déri2009"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Dupuis-Déri|first1=Francis|title=Le " masculinisme " : une histoire politique du mot (en anglais et en français)|journal=Recherches féministes|volume=22|issue=2|year=2009|pages=97|issn=0838-4479|doi=10.7202/039213ar}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christensen differentiates between "progressive masculism" and an "extremist version". The former welcomes many of the societal changes promoted by feminists, while stating that many aimed at reducing sexism against women have had the effect of increasing it against men.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt; The latter promotes male supremacy to some degree and is generally based on a belief in women's inferiority. Nicholas Davidson, in his book ''The Failure of Feminism'', describes an extremist version of masculism which he termed "virism". According to Davidson, in this view "What ails society is 'effeminacy'. The improvement of society requires that the influence of female values be decreased and the influence of male values increased…."&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Davidson1988"&gt;{{cite book|author=Nicholas Davidson|title=The failure of feminism|url=https://books.google.com/?id=pf8pAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA274|year=1988|publisher=Prometheus Books, Publishers|isbn=9780879754082|pages=274–}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Gender theory|Gender theories]], which have frequently focused on woman-based or feminist approaches, have come to include a "masculism" approach which seeks to examine oppression in a masculinist society from the perspectives of men, most of whom do not benefit from that society.&lt;ref name="HoogensenSolheim2006"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Gunhild Hoogensen|author2=Bruce Olav Solheim|title=Women in power: world leaders since 1960|url=https://books.google.com/?id=ZPThCTMVsZQC&amp;pg=PA21|year=2006|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=9780275981907|pages=21–}}&lt;/ref&gt;
From a feminist perspective to philosophy, masculinism seeks to value and include only male views, and claim "that anything that cannot be reduced or translated in men's experience should be excluded from the subject-matter of philosophy.&lt;ref name="BunninYu2008"/&gt;

The term masculism was coined by [[Charlotte Perkins Gilman]] who used it a 1914 public lecture series titled "Studies in Masculism".&lt;ref name=gilman&gt;{{cite book|last=Allan|first=Judith A.|title=The Feminism of Charlotte Perkins Gilman: Sexualities, Histories, Progressivism|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|year=2009|isbn=978-0-226-01462-3|pages=[https://books.google.ca/books?id=oMstMHT-n2YC&amp;pg=PA152 152], [https://books.google.com/books?id=oMstMHT-n2YC&amp;pg=PA353 353]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter=masculism, n|title=Oxford English Dictionary|publisher=Oxford University Press|edition=3rd|year=2000|quote=1914 Waterloo (Iowa) Evening Courier 11 Apr. 11/3 Why have women always been fonder of going to church than men have? Because they are more religious? No, answered Mrs. Chalotte Perkins Gilman yesterday in the second lecture on ‘Studies in Masculism’ at the Hotel Astor.}}&lt;/ref&gt; She used the term to refer to androcentrism and opposition to women's rights and, more broadly, to describe men's collective actions on behalf of their own sex.&lt;ref name=gilman/&gt; The Oxford English Dictionary cites the first recorded use of the synonym masculinism in a [[The Freewoman]] article in November 1911.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter=masculinism, n|title=Oxford English Dictionary|publisher=Oxford University Press|edition=3rd|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Topic areas of interest to masculism==
{{main|Men's Rights Movement}}

===Education===
Many masculists suggest the abolition of co-educational schooling, believing that single-sex schools are preferred for the well-being of boys.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"&gt;Melissa Blais and Francis Dupuis-Déri. "Masculinism and the Antifeminist Countermovement." ''Social Movement Studies: Journal of Social, Cultural and Political Protest'' 11:1 (2012): 21–39.&lt;/ref&gt; Other masculists and [[Equity feminism|equity feminists]] indicate that boys are on the weaker side of an education gap.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Sommers|first1=Christina|title=The War Against Boys|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2000/05/the-war-against-boys/304659/|website=theatlantic.com|publisher=Christina Hoff Sommers|accessdate=30 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Employment===
Data from 1994 in the U.S. reported that men make up 94% of workplace fatalities. Masculist [[Warren Farrell]] has argued that men are often clustered in dirty, physically demanding and hazardous jobs in an unjustifiably disproportionate manner.&lt;ref name=reason/&gt;

===Violence===
{{Violence against men}}
{{See also|Violence against men}}

Masculists express concern about violence against men being depicted as humorous, in the media and elsewhere.&lt;ref name=MYTH&gt;Warren Farrell, ''The Myth of Male Power: Why Men Are the Disposable Sex'' (NY: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1993; ISBN 0671793497).&lt;/ref&gt;

Masculists also express concern about violence against men being ignored, minimized, or taken less seriously than violence against women.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?click_id=13&amp;art_id=vn20081125064002133C731559&amp;set_id= iol.co.za]&lt;/ref&gt; Some assert that there is gender symmetry in [[domestic violence]].&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Another concern expressed is that assumptions of female innocence or sympathy for women may result in disproportionate penalties for women and men for similar crimes,&lt;ref name="MYTH" /&gt; lack of sympathy for male victims in [[domestic violence]] cases, and dismissal of female-on-male [[sexual assault]] and [[sexual harassment]] cases.

===Custody===
{{main|Fathers' rights movement}}
According to [[David Benatar]], head of philosophy at the [[University of Cape Town]], "Custody law is perhaps the best-known area of men's rights activism", as it is more likely in most parts of the world for the mother to obtain custody of children in case of divorce. He argues: "When the man is the primary care-giver his chances of winning custody are lower than when the woman is the primary care-giver. Even when the case is not contested by the mother, he's still not as likely to get custody as when the woman's claim is uncontested".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17907534 "Just who are men's rights activists?"], BBC, 2 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

===Suicide===
Masculists cite higher rates of suicide in men than women.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;

==Reactions==

===Criticisms and responses===
Alternatively, masculism (sometimes called [[androcentrism]]) may refer to an approach that is focused on [[Chauvinism#Male chauvinism|male superiority]] or dominance&lt;ref name="Masculinist"&gt;{{cite web|title=masculinist, n|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/masculinist|work=Merriam-Webster|publisher=[[Merriam-Webster]]|accessdate=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Brittan1989"&gt;{{cite book|author=Arthur Brittan|title=Masculinity and Power|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ptFzQgAACAAJ&amp;pg=PA91|accessdate=11 May 2013|year= 1989|publisher= Wiley|isbn= 978-0-631-14167-9|page= 4|quote= Masculinism is the ideology that justifies and naturalizes male domination. As such it is the ideology of patriarchy. Masculinism takes it for granted that there is a fundamental difference between man and women, it assumes that heterosexuality is normal, it accepts without question the sexual division of labour, and it sanctions the political and dominant role of men in the public and private spheres}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kahl|first=David H.|title=Analyzing Masculinist Movements: Responding to Antifeminism through Critical Communication Pedagogy|journal=Communication Teacher|volume=29|issue=1|year=2015|pages=21–26|doi=10.1080/17404622.2014.985600}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ruth|first=Sheila|title=Issues in Feminism: An Introduction to Women's Studies|publisher=Mayfield|location=Mountain View, CA|page=61|edition=2nd|isbn=978-0-87484-937-0|quote=Masculism (sometimes called androcentrism) is the elevation of the masculine, conceptually and physically, to the level of the universal and ideal.}}&lt;/ref&gt; to the exclusion of [[Woman|women]].&lt;ref name="BunninYu2008"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Nicholas Bunnin|author2=Jiyuan Yu|title=The Blackwell Dictionary of Western Philosophy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LdbxabeToQYC&amp;pg=PA411|date=15 April 2008|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-0-470-99721-5|page=411|chapter=Masculinism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To the extent that masculism is associated with antifeminist masculinism, its primary focus is on "masculinity and the place of white heterosexual men in North America and European societies."&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;

Some masculinists believe that differentiated gender roles are natural. There is considerable evidence for social influences (e.g. gender division of labor, socialization) as the sole or primary origin of gender differentiation.&lt;ref name="Risman, Barbara 2004"&gt;[[Barbara Risman]], "Gender as a Social Structure: Theory Wrestling with Activism." ''Gender &amp; Society'' 18.4 (2004): 429–450.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Susan A. Basow, ''Gender Stereotypes and Roles'' (Pacific Grove, CA: Brooks/Cole, 1992).&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, belief in inherent gender differences allows for inequality and for the dominant group to assert power by means of perceived difference.&lt;ref name="Risman, Barbara 2004"/&gt;
Some parts of the masculinist movement have to some extent borrowed concepts of [[evolutionary psychology]]: this theory argues that adaptation during prehistory resulted in complementary but different roles for the different genders, and that this balance has been destabilized by feminism since the 1960s.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;

===Feminism===
Some masculinists have been described as explicitly antifeminist by feminist activists.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; According to Blais and Dupuis-Déri, "the contents of [masculinist] websites and the testimony of feminists that we questioned confirm that masculinists are generally critical of even moderate feminists and feminists at the head of official feminist organizations."&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Some masculinist activism has involved disruption of events organized by feminists and lawsuits against feminist academics, journalists, or activists.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Furthermore, masculinist actions are sometimes extreme; father's rights activists have bombed family courts in Australia and have issued bomb threats in the UK, although it is ambiguous whether there was public and organized militant group involvement.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; They have also engaged in "tire-slashing, the mailing of excrement-filled packages, threats against politicians and their children."&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt; Spokesmen for these groups have also spoken out against public awareness campaigns to prevent sexual assault, arguing that they portray a negative image of men, and one masculinist group harassed administrators of dozens of battered women's shelters and women's centers.&lt;ref name="Blais, Melissa 2012"/&gt;

Feminists{{Who|date=September 2015}} respond to the different ideologies of masculism in different ways. Masculinists who promote gender equality are often considered [[male feminism|male feminists]].&lt;ref&gt;Janet M. Martin and Maryanne Borrelli, ''Other Elites: Women, Politics, &amp; Power in the Executive Branch'' (Lynne Rienner Publishers, 2000; ISBN 1555879713, ISBN 9781555879716).&lt;/ref&gt; 

Philosopher Ferrell Christensen states that if masculism and feminism refer to the belief that men/women are systematically discriminated against, and that this discrimination should be eliminated, there is not necessarily a conflict between feminism and masculism, and some assert that they are both.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt; However, many believe that one sex is more discriminated against, and thus use one label and reject the other.&lt;ref name="Honderich1995"/&gt;

==See also==
{{Wiktionary|masculinism|masculism}}
{{Portal|Men's rights|Discrimination}}
* [[Antifeminism]]
* [[Hegemonic masculinity]]
* [[Hypermasculinity]]
* [[Kyriarchy]]
* [[Heteropatriarchy]]
* [[Identity politics]]
* [[Machismo]]
* [[Male privilege]]
* [[Manosphere]]
* [[Masculine psychology]]
* [[Masculinity]]
* [[Matriarchy]]
* [[Men's liberation]]
* [[Men's movement]]
* [[Men's rights]]
* [[Misandry]]
* [[Misogyny]]
* [[Patriarchy]]

===Men's organizations===
* [[Fathers 4 Justice]]
* [[International Men's Day]] (19 November: [[Trinidad and Tobago]], [[Jamaica]], [[Australia]], [[India]], [[United States]], [[Singapore]], [[United Kingdom]], [[Malta]], [[South Africa]], [[Hungary]], [[Ireland]], [[Ghana]], and [[Canada]])
* [[Save Indian Family]]

===Notable persons associated with masculism===
* [[Warren Farrell]]
* [[Glenn Sacks]]
* [[Robert Bly]]

===Books===
* ''[[Manliness (book)|Manliness]]'' (2006)

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
*[[Roy Baumeister|Baumeister, Roy F.]] (2010). ''Is There Anything Good About Men?: How Cultures Flourish by Exploiting Men.'' Oxford University Press. ISBN 0199752559.
*''[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/6762 Politics]'' of [[Aristotle]] asserts excellence varies with social role, including gender.
*[[s:The Legal Subjection of Men|''The Legal Subjection of Men'']], 1908 antithesis of [[John Stuart Mill]]'s 1869 ''[[The Subjection of Women]]''.
*[[s:The Fraud of Feminism|''The Fraud of Feminism'']] by [[Ernest Belfort Bax]], 1914.
*''The Myth of the Monstrous Male and Other Feminist Fallacies''; John Gordon, Playboy Press, New York, 1982; ISBN 0872237583
*"La condition masculine dans le Rouge et le Noir" Gilles Aerts, mémoire de maîtrise, University of British Columbia, 1987.
*''The Myth of Male Power: Why Men Are the Disposable Sex''; Warren Farrell, Simon &amp; Schuster, New York, 1993: ISBN 0671793497
*''[http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/book.asp?isbn=0300106645 Manliness]'' by [[Harvey Mansfield]] (2006) Yale Press ISBN 0300106645
*''Not Guilty: The Case in Defense of Men''; David Thomas, William Morrow and Co., Inc., New York, 1993; ISBN 068811024X
*''Good Will Toward Men''; Jack Kammer, St. Martin's Press, New York, 1994; ISBN 0312104715
*''Moral Panic: Biopolitics Rising''; John Fekete, Robert Davies Publishing, Montreal-Toronto, 1994: ISBN 1895854091
*''The New Men's Studies: A Selected and Annotated Interdisciplinary Bibliography'' (2nd Edition); Eugene R. August, Libraries Unlimited, Inc., Englewood, CO, 1994: ISBN 1563080842
*''A Man's World: How Real Is Male Privilege – And How High Is Its Price?''; Ellis Cose, Harper Collins, New York, 1995: ISBN 0060172061
*''Why Men Don't Iron: The Real Science of Gender Studies''; Anne &amp; Bill Moir, Harper Collins, Hammersmith, London, 1998; ISBN 0002570351 (Trade Paperback); ISBN 0002570483 (Hardcover)
*''The Strong, Sensitive Boy''; Ted Zeff, Prana Publishing (May 3, 2010); ISBN 0966074521
*''The Church Impotent: The Feminization of Christianity''; Leon J. Podles, Spence Publishing Co., Dallas, TX, 1999. (The title is a play on the Christian theological terms [[Church militant and church triumphant|''church militant'' and ''church triumphant'']].)
*''Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture''; Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young, McGill-Queen's University Press, Montreal, 2001; ISBN 0773522727
*''"Feminine" Heterosexual Men: Subverting Heteropatriarchal Sexual Scripts?''; Darryl B. Hill, The Journal of Men's Studies, Spring 2006, Men's Studies Press; {{ISSN|1060-8265}}
*''Re-Thinking Men: Heroes, Villains and Victims''; Anthony Synnott, Ashgate, 2009; ISBN 9780754677093
*''The Second Sexism''; David Benatar, Wiley-Blackwell, 2012; ISBN 9780470674512
*''Email to the Universe''; Robert Anton Wilson, New Falcon Publications, 2008; ISBN 9781561841943
*''Sex Differences, Modern Biology and the Unisex Fallacy'', Yves Christen
*''[[Who Stole Feminism? How Women Have Betrayed Women]]''; [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] ISBN 0684801566
*''The War Against Boys: How Misguided Feminism Is Harming Our Young Men''; Christina Hoff Sommers ISBN 0684849569
*''Domestic Violence: The 12 Things You Aren't Supposed to Know'' by Thomas B. James ISBN 1593301227
*''Ceasefire!: Why Women And Men Must Join Forces To Achieve True Equality''; Cathy Young ISBN 0684834421
*''The Masculine Mystique''; Andrew Kimbrell ISBN 0345386582
*''Young Masculinities Understanding Boys in Contemporary Society''; [[Ann Phoenix]], Stephen Frosh and Ro Pattmann, Palgrave Macmillan, Basingstoke, 2002; ISBN 9780333779231

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Masculism}}
}}

[[Category:Civil rights and liberties]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Masculinity]]
[[Category:Masculism| ]]
[[Category:Men's movement]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1980s]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>