<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091111190535|325289917" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25454239" pageid="25454239" ns="0" title="Masculism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-11T20:14:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Rights}}

'''Masculism''' is the advocacy of [[men's rights]] and the adherence to, or promotion of, [[social theory|social theories]] and [[moral philosophy|moral philosophies]] concerning issues of gender with respect to the interests and legal protection of [[man|men]]. The term ''masculinism'' was coined as the counterpart of ''[[feminism]]'' in the early 20th century. The shortened form ''masculism'' appears in the 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;[[OED]]; {{cite web|url=http://www.allwords.com/word-masculism.html|title=allwords.com}}; {{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/masculinist|title= Merriam-Webster}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

The masculist political movement originated with [[E. Belfort Bax]]'s 1913 ''The Fraud of Feminism''.&lt;ref&gt;E. Belfort Bax, [http://www.marxists.org/archive/bax/1913/fraud/index.htm ''The Fraud of Feminism''], at [[Marxists.org]]&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''masculism'' itself gained currency in the late 20th century, in the context of changing [[gender role]]s, advocated by authors such as [[Warren Farrell]].

==Masculist concerns==
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
Masculists cite one-sided legislation, selective enforcement, and neglected [[civil rights]] as examples of discrimination against men and boys. Examples of questions raised by masculists may include:

===Violence===

Masculist concerns focus on societal acceptance of violence harming men paired with the stigma against violence harming women, as well as males being taught or expected to take on violent roles.

* Men forced to risk their lives in male-only [[conscript]]ed [[military]] service.
* Violence against men minimalized or taken less seriously than violence against women [http://menz.org.nz/2008/minimization-of-violence-against-men/] [http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?click_id=13&amp;art_id=vn20081125064002133C731559&amp;set_id=]
* Women are more violent than men in some research studies asking both men and women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tidsskriftet.no/index.php?vp_SEKS_ID=850018 Prof. Hilde Pape, University of Oslo. The report is also referring to studies from US in 1977 (In Norwegian)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Professor David Fergusson and Associate Professor Richie Poulton, University of Otago, New Zealand. (Missing the research report itself) [http://www.nzherald.co.nz/nz/news/article.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=10410452]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Depiction of violence against men as humorous, in the media&lt;ref name=MYTH&gt;''The Myth of Male Power: Why Men Are the Disposable Sex''; Warren Farrell, Simon &amp; Schuster, New York, 1993: ISBN 0-671-79349-7&lt;/ref&gt; and elsewhere (see [[Boys are stupid, throw rocks at them!]]), when women are also violent.
* Assumption of female innocence or sympathy for women, which may result in problems such as disproportionate penalties for men and women for similar crimes,&lt;ref name=MYTH /&gt; lack of sympathy for male victims in [[domestic violence]] cases, and dismissal of female-on-male [[rape]] cases.
* Societal failure to address [[prison rape]], including issues such as prevention (e.g., reducing prison crowding that requires sharing of cells), impunity for prison rapists, and even correctional staff punishing prisoners by confining them with known rapists.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrw.org/reports/2001/prison/report8.html#_1_50&lt;/ref&gt; Attention has been drawn to portrayals of male rape by women, or implied rape, as humorous.
* [[Circumcision]] (characterized as harmless tradition by some, and as male genital mutilation by others) being advocated while female genital mutilation is prohibited, although both practices are purported to reduce sexual pleasure and expose the patient to possible health problems.&lt;ref name="Are Baby Boys Entitled to the Same Protection..."&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.noharmm.org/baer.htm|title=Are Baby Boys Entitled to the Same Protection as Baby Girls Regarding Genital Mutilation?|accessdate=2008-11-19|publisher=NOHARMM.org|year=1996|author=Zenas Baer}} However, unlike female circumcision, male circumcision also has health benefits, such as the reduction of AIDS infection and transmission.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Parenting ===
* Equality in [[child custody]], such as [[shared parenting]]
* [[Pregnancy|Pregnancies]] carried to term despite agreements ahead of time that they would not be, subjecting men to unwanted parental responsibilities and/or child support expectations (see ''[[Dubay v. Wells]]'')
* The opposite of the above, where a man who feels he wants to have a child has no say in whether his girlfriend/wife aborts their child (see [[paternal rights and abortion]])
* Equality in adoption rights allowing either unmarried males or females to adopt.

=== Discrimination ===
* Legislation that addresses women's needs without considering the corresponding need in men (e.g., ''Women, Infants, and Children Act''; ''Violence Against Women Act'') 
* Biases in the justice system against men, such as higher incarceration rates and longer sentences for men (compared to women) for the same crimes
* [[Statutory rape]] laws enforced more vehemently in instances where the victim is female and/or the perpetrator is male.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsamericanow.com/archives/2006/03/22/video_debra_lafave_press_confe.html] [http://www.reason.com/cy/cy060402.shtml ''Double Standard: The Bias Against Male Victims of Sexual Abuse'']&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Rape shield law]]s, which may prevent some men from adequately challenging their accuser 
* [[Cathy Young]], who does not consider herself a "masculinist," argues that in rape cases, "the dogma that "women never lie" means that there is, for all intents and purposes, no presumption of innocence for the defendant"[http://dir.salon.com/story/mwt/feature/2004/03/26/rape_shield/index.html?sid=1213003]
* Women are allowed to marry at younger ages than men in some U.S. states. [http://www.law.cornell.edu/topics/Table_Marriage.htm]
* Men pay higher premiums for auto&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDD133BF935A2575BC0A961948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all]&lt;/ref&gt;, life and disability insurance, though discrimination according to race or other criteria is prohibited.
* In some countries, men have to pay more income tax than their female counterparts. E.g. in India the income tax exemption limit for men is Rs 1,50,000 per annum while that for women is Rs 1,80,000 per annum.&lt;ref name="financialexpress.com"&gt;[http://www.financialexpress.com/news/IT-limit-Men-Rs-1.5-lakh-women-Rs-1.8-lakh/278564/ "Difference in income tax exemption limits for men and women in India"]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Men not being believed after having been raped by their wife, girlfriend or fiancee; lesser or no penalty for women that rape men

=== Social concerns ===
* Increasing [[suicide]] rate among young men, four times higher than among young women &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.statistics.gov.uk/statbase/ssdataset.asp?vlnk=5228 National Statistics (UK)]&lt;/ref&gt;; (In the United States, 73% of all suicide deaths are white males;&lt;ref name = "policyalmanac.org-suicide"&gt;[http://www.policyalmanac.org/health/archive/suicide.shtml Suicide in the United States&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, more men than women report a history of attempted suicide, with a gender ratio of 3:1)&lt;ref name = "policyalmanac.org-suicide"/&gt;
* It's usually seen as socially acceptable for a female to try out or follow masculine social norms, whereas if a male does the same for feminine social norms they often attract unwanted attention and are victims of ridicule and insult, with derogatory terms like "pussy" and "faggot" being used.
* Lack of advocacy for men's rights; little domestic abuse support for men.{{Vague|date=November 2008}}
* Bias in health concerns; for example, more advertisements and awareness for breast cancer than prostate cancer, though both cancers kill approximately the same number of people each year.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}
* Incarceration for not paying child support, particularly for unwanted children, in contrast to women's right to abort (see [[Male abortion]])
* Special government agencies for women's affairs with no corresponding agencies for men's affairs 
* Lack of legal ramifications or enforcement for [[paternity fraud]]

=== Education ===
{{Unreferenced section|date=August 2007}}
* Lack of educational aid for boys and men, given that their performance/enrollment at most levels lags behind that of girls and women; some {{Which?|date=October 2009}} states declaring (''de jure'' or ''de facto'') all-male schools illegal and all-female schools legal.

* There is concern that some [[higher education|university]] [[women's studies]] departments are more concerned with teaching feminist ideology than equality of gender. The content and emphasis of these courses vary, and some even discuss "masculinities"; but masculists fear that many such courses contribute to animosity towards men. {{Who|date=October 2009}}

* Some universities also carry [[men's studies]] courses. Some {{Who|date=October 2009}} feminists argue that these are redundant, stating that academia throughout history was predominantly focused on men; however, supporters of these courses note that most subjects throughout history have not dealt with gender directly.

===Employment===
* Harder physical entrance criteria for men in many occupations, such as the army, police and fire service. Requiring men to be physically stronger than women in these occupations leaves men responsible for a greater share of the physical work, for no more pay.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dfas.mil/militarypay/militarypaytables/2009MilitaryPayTables.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
* Legal inequality and protections of paternal vs. maternal leave {{Citation needed|date=August 2007}}

== Differences in masculist ideology ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=July 2007}}
There is no consensus as to what constitutes masculism. Some feel the word describes a belief that the male and female genders should be considered complementary and interdependent by necessity. Such expressions of masculism are built around the belief that differentiated [[gender role]]s are natural and should be exempt from government interference. Others masculists, such as [[Warren Farrell]], support an ideology of equivalence between the sexes, rather than a belief in unchangeable gender differences. A more encompassing definition might be "a movement to empower males in society, and to redress discrimination against men."

Because it is the name of a political and social movement, masculism is sometimes considered synonymous with the [[men's rights]] or [[fathers' rights]] movements. However, many of the fathers' rights movement make a clear distinction between masculism and their own often quite varied approaches to gender relations.

Gender roles in [[religion]] are a source of disagreement among masculists: some support a general leadership role for men, while others argue for relative equality between the genders. Liberal masculists such as Warren Farrell tend to favor a [[secularism|secular]], gender-neutral stance, whereas conservatives tend to prefer a religious approach, such as represented in ''The Inevitability of Patriarchy'' by [[Steven Goldberg]]. Conservatives may promote a "New Patriarchy" by countering feminist ideology with their own. Such liberal-conservative dynamics illustrate the diversity of a movement that nonetheless has a unified purpose of promoting men's welfare.

=== Progressive masculist ===
[[Progressivism|Progressive]] masculists view masculism as a complementary movement to [[feminism]], both movements seeking to correct gender discrimination. Progressive masculists do not reject feminism as a movement nor consider feminism a hostile movement and adopt cooperative vision.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.vanderbiltorbis.com/media/storage/paper983/news/2006/04/03/Masculism/The-Diverse.And.Growing.Mens.Movement-2472232.shtml The Diverse and Growing Men's Movement]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Warren Farrell]], widely seen as a progressive masculist stated in [[The Myth of Male Power]] that both genders are hampered by the "bisexist" roles of the past: sexism that oppresses both genders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Farrell, Ph.D. |first=Warren  |title=The Myth of Male Power |year=1993 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster, Inc. |location=New York, New York |isbn=0425181448}}&lt;/ref&gt; He emphasises the compatibility of both movements: 

{{Quote|I use two podiums to debate myself as a feminist and masculist.|Warren Farrell|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.warrenfarrell.com/pages.php?id=39 |title=Warren Speaking |accessdate=2007-09-21 |format= |work=warrenfarrell.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Another supporter states:

{{Quote|We must not reverse the women's movement; we must accelerate it... [[Men's liberation]] is not a backlash, for there is nothing about traditional sex roles that I want to go back to.|Fred Hayward|Speach to the National Congress for Men, 1981}} Farrell suggests that masculism in his conception can assist and aid the women's movement.

Likewise, gender egalitarians call for both masculists and feminists who are truly interested in equality to unite under one banner of [[gender egalitarianism]]. This philosophy is sympathetic to legitimate grievances of both males and females.

The principle of defining masculism on gendereconomy.com is by reverting the definition of feminism and including the same two levels – men are subordinate to women, this condition has to be changed. Masculism carries assumptions about the proper distribution of power and privilege and serves as the bases for a plan of action. Masculism here is defined as a tool to reveal gender inequality. It focuses on the domination of women over men and claims that men are oppressed by hierarchical structures and stereotypes in different levels of society. The scapegoats of masculism are women and domains of female dominance are claimed to be responsible for all the injustice done to men in particular and society in general. Men and women both are found equally responsible for the unsatisfying relations between sexes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gendereconomy.com/main/index1.html Gendereconomy.com], page Definitions, section Masculism: ''The principle of defining masculism here is by reverting the definition of feminism and including the same two levels – men are subordinate to women, this condition has to be changed. Masculism carries assumptions about the proper distribution of power and privilege and serves as the bases for a plan of action.''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Literary theory==
Masculist literary theory is a response to feminist literary theory. The term was coined by [[Rachel Bishop]] in "The Masculinist Manifesto".{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}}

== See also ==
{{portal|Men's rights|Symbol_mars.svg}}
{{Wiktionary|Masculism}}
* [[Misandry]]
* [[Lad culture]]
* [[Masculine psychology]]
* [[Masculinity]]
* [[Men's spaces]]
* [[Patriarchy]]
* [[Reverse discrimination]]
* [[Complementarianism]]

==== Men's movements and organizations ====
* [[Fathers 4 Justice]]
* [[Men's movement]]
* [[Promise Keepers]]
* [[Save Indian Family]]

==== People associated with masculism ====
* [[Warren Farrell]]
* [[Harvey Mansfield]]
* [[Henry Makow]]

==== Books ====
* ''[[Manliness (book)]]'' (2006)

==Bibliography==
*''[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/6762 Politics]'' of [[Aristotle]] asserts excellence varies with social role, including gender.
*[http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Legal_Subjection_of_Men ''The Legal Subjection of Men''], 1908 antithesis of [[John Stuart Mill]]'s 1869 ''[[The Subjection of Women]]''.
*[http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Fraud_of_Feminism ''The Fraud of Feminism''] by [[Ernest Belfort Bax]], 1914.
*''The Myth of the Monstrous Male and Other Feminist Fallacies''; John Gordon, Playboy Press, New York, 1982; ISBN 0-87223-758-3
*''The Myth of Male Power: Why Men Are the Disposable Sex''; Warren Farrell, Simon &amp; Schuster, New York, 1993: ISBN 0-671-79349-7
*''Manliness'' by [[Harvey Mansfield]] (2006) Yale Press [http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/book.asp?isbn=0300106645] ISBN 0-300-10664-5
*''Not Guilty: The Case in Defense of Men''; David Thomas, William Morrow and Co., Inc., New York, 1993; ISBN 0-688-11024-X
*''Good Will Toward Men''; Jack Kammer, St. Martin's Press, New York, 1994; ISBN 0-312-10471-5
*''Moral Panic: Biopolitics Rising''; John Fekete, Robert Davies Publishing, Montreal-Toronto, 1994: ISBN 1-895854-09-1
*''The New Men's Studies: A Selected and Annotated Interdisciplinary Bibliography'' (2nd Edition); Eugene R. August, Libraries Unlimited, Inc., Englewood, CO, 1994: ISBN 1-56308-084-2
*''A Man's World: How Real Is Male Privilege - And How High Is Its Price?''; Ellis Cose, Harper Collins, New York, 1995: ISBN 0-06-017206-1
*''Why Men Don't Iron: The Real Science of Gender Studies''; Anne &amp; Bill Moir, Harper Collins, Hammersmith, London, 1998; ISBN 0-00-257035-1 (Trade Paperback); ISBN 0-00-257048-3 (Hardcover)
*''The Church Impotent: The Feminization of Christianity''; Leon J. Podles, Spence Publishing Co., Dallas, TX, 1999. (The title is a play on the Christian theological terms [[Church militant and church triumphant|''church militant'' and ''church triumphant'']].)
*''Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture''; Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young, McGill-Queen's University Press, Montreal, 2001; ISBN 0-7735-2272-7

*''Sex Differences, Modern Biology and the Unisex Fallacy'', Yves Christen
*''Who Stole Feminism?: How Women Have Betrayed Women''; Christina Hoff Sommers ISBN 0-684-80156-6
*''The War Against Boys: How Misguided Feminism Is Harming Our Young Men''; Christina Hoff Sommers ISBN 0-684-84956-9
*''Domestic Violence: The 12 Things You Aren't Supposed to Know'' by Thomas B. James ISBN 1-59330-122-7
*''Ceasefire! : Why Women And Men Must Join Forces To Achieve True Equality''; Cathy Young ISBN 0-684-83442-1
*''The Masculine Mystique''; Andrew Kimbrell ISBN 0-345-38658-2

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary}}
*[http://www.reason.com/cy/cy060402.shtml Double Standard: The Bias Against Male Victims of Sexual Abuse]
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/bax/1913/fraud/ Table of Contents for Bax' ''The Fraud of Feminism'']
*[http://www.wabash.edu/magazine/2002/SpringSummer2002/defendingallmale.html Defending All-Male Education: A New Cultural Movement for a Renewed Debate]
*[http://www.che-lives.com/home/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=193 The Post (Liberal) Feminist Condition]
*[http://www.acfc.org American Coalition for Fathers and Children]
*[http://www.fathersforvirginia.org Equal Parental Rights for Fathers]
*[http://www.ncfm.org National Coalition of Free Men]
*[http://www.mensactivism.org Men's Activism] Men's rights Discussion group
*[http://www.wgvdl.com German Men's rights Information and Discussion group]
*[http://www.wikimannia.org German Men's rights Wiki]
*[http://masculinists.org Masculinists Coalition] Unofficial Pitzer College Masculinist Coalition
*[http://www.mkpchicago.org The ManKind Project of Chicago]
*[http://www.gendereconomy.com Masculism-Feminism Duality Concept]
*[http://www.ihatesexism.com/ Sexism Discussion Group]

{{Discrimination}}
{{Masculism}}

[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Men's movement]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1980s]]
[[Category:Social theories]]

[[cs:Maskulinismus]]
[[es:Masculinismo]]
[[fi:Maskulismi]]
[[fr:Masculinisme]]
[[it:Mascolinismo]]
[[ja:マスキュリズム]]
[[ko:남성주의]]
[[pt:Masculinismo]]
[[ru:Маскулизм]]
[[tr:Maskülizm]]
[[zh:男性主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>