<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061107195622|86335508" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20778" pageid="20778" ns="0" title="Misandry"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-07T23:31:59Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{expand}}
'''Misandry''' ([[International Phonetic Alphabet|IPA]] {{IPA|[mɪ.ˈsæn.dri]}}) is the hatred of [[men]]. The word comes from ''misos'' ([[Greek language|Greek]] ''μίσος'', "hatred") + ''andras'' ([[Greek language|Greek]] ''ἀνδρας'', "man"). Although misandry is sometimes confused with ''[[misanthropy]],'' the terms are not interchangeable, since the latter refers to the hatred of humanity. An idea related to misandry is ''[[androphobia]],'' the fear of men (male humans), but not necessarily the hatred of them. 

==Causes of misandry==

Misandry is usually, but not exclusively, associated with [[women]] although [[men]] can also hold misandric views. Misandry is discussed less frequently than [[misogyny]], and is also less understood, there is increasing research into and discussion about the topic.
However, according to pioneering researchers Nathanson and Young (2001), "misandry in popular culture remains a dark secret" and "gender watchdogs" use a double standard that exposes the evils of mysogyny but is "notably silent" about even the existence of misandry. They assert that "unlike misogyny, misandry is still generally unrecognized ''as a problem''".

Nathanson and Young believe that the gynocentric use of the word "gender" as a tool to blame all men "as those who created the problem of "gender" in the first place" form the root assumptions for modern misandry.  To Nathanson and Young, this has meant that men are society's official scapegoats responsible for all evil, women are society's offical victims responsible for all good, and that men must be penalized and women compensated ''collectively'' for crimes against women throughout history.  They believe that underlying "gender" as social construct are core assumptions that "''the end justifies the means''", and that "''collective rights trump individual rights''".

Nathanson and Young (2001) assert that the roots of misandry can be found in 'ideological', (as opposed to other forms of) feminism.  They believe that 'political correctness', academic deconstructionism and what they call "fronts" are strategies used by feminist ideologues to "make the world safe" for promoting a misandric worldview.  They posit that underlying ideological feminism is "an ideology derived from Marxism and romanticism but with class or nation replaced by gender as the central concept" to perpetrate the intolerant hatred of men as a class.

Some [[feminists]] and [[masculists]] posit that the "[[sex war|war of the sexes]]" arising from traditional [[gender role]]s and their breakdown are the primary source of both misogyny and misandry.{{fact}} 

Some [[Masculism|masculists]] maintain that misandry has been endemic since the [[1980s]] (Nathanson &amp; Young, 2001, p. 234) stemming from the spread of anti-male [[Feminism|feminist]] advocacy in popular culture, and thus assert that misandry has become a social pathology. Some feminists, however, controversially claim that [[misogyny]] is a verifiable social disease, but misandry may not exist at all (Nathanson &amp; Young, 2001, p. 18].

==Types of misandrists==
* Male feminists or what Nathanson and Young call "honorary women" who self-righteously defend women from men to seek favor from women.
* Ideological feminists who see all men as evil brutes and all women as 'good' human beings
* Women who justify misandry is a legitimate "choice" for women or a "voice" for those who have been "silenced."
* Women who justify misandry as an expedient for political purposes.
* Women who justify misandry with "something far more sinister in mind: revenge".

Many of the quotes listed in the section below from famous feminist misandrists contain one or more of the types of misandry.

==Types of misandry==

Nathan and Young noted the following types of man-hating behavior in Spreading Misandry (2001):

* Laughing at Men: The Last of Vaudeville
* Looking Down on Men: Separate but Unequal
* Bypassing men: Women Alone Together
* Blaming Men: A History of Their Own
* Dehumanizing Men: From Bad Boys to Beasts
* Demonizing Men: The Devil is a Man

==Degrees of misandry==

Misandry may be exhibited to differing degrees. In its most overt expression, a misandrist openly hates all men simply because they are 'men', exhibiting 'masculine' traits that are not to the speaker's liking. Stereotypically, these 'masculine' traits include [[machismo]], emotional bluntness, and a loutish demeanor. Or, a misandrist might simply hate men for a perceived common physical attribute, such as large muscles, a large gut, or copious body hair.

Other forms of misandry are more subtle. Some misandrists simply hold all men under suspicion, or hate men who do not conform to one or more acceptable categories. Entire cultures may be said to be misandrist if they treat men in ways that are perceived hurtful. Misandry is often not recognised, since it exists under many different guises, disguised and qualified. {Judith Levine, 'My Enemy, My Love', 1992}

Misandry is a negative attitude towards men as a group, and as such need not fully determine a misandrist's attitude towards each individual man. The fact that someone holds misandrist views may not prevent them from having positive relationships with some men. Conversely, simply having positive relationships with some men does not necessarily mean someone does not also hold misandrist views.

==Responses to misandry==

Nathan and Young believe that "many ordinary men have a vested interest in 'not' seeing the pervasive misandry of everyday life.  For a man to see himself as a victim of attacks by women he would have to acknowledge his vulnerability and therefore become less of a man.  This creates a double-bind for men vis a vis confronting misandry because men "who admit to feeling vulnerable are attacked as cowards, and by no group more effectively than women".  Nathan and Young assert that women can easily shame men into silence, "a form of abuse that few women today would tolerate."

Thus despite what Nathan and Young argue is a "massive assault" on men's identities, most men remain too confused to honor their unconscious knowledge that something is wrong.   Most are not "equiped to identify or analyze" misandry.  Those few men who are able to see misandry for what it is are rarely rewarded and are usually shamed for speaking about it in public.  

According to Nathan and Young, until very recently the "few feminists who dared to speak out against misandry were usually declared enemies of feminism, or even enemies of women, and thus effectively silenced."  They state that "most feminists deny misandry" and that "when challenged" most feminist excuse, justify, and/or trivialize misandry.  They note that "despite the vaunted capacity of women for empathy, only a few feminist publications, albeit ones of profound moral significance, have so far expressed sympathy for men in general, except as a way of encouraging men to believe that feminism is in their own interest."

==Misandry in mythology==

The [[Amazons]] of Ancient [[Greek Mythology]] were a nation of women warriors.  The primary depictions generally focus on role-reversal, swapping the classical Greek ideals of "female" passivity and dependence  for "male" strength and ability.  In some versions, the Amazons display misandry through actions such as forbidding men to reside in Amazon country; killing their male offspring (the result of their yearly mating with the all-male [[Gargareans|Gargarean]] tribe) or exiling them to return to the Gargarean fathers (Strabo xi. p. 503).  The women of Lemnos, filling a similar role in the myth of [[Jason]] and the [[Argonauts]], commit acts of [[mariticide]] and [[patricide]] and proceed to rule their island themselves.

However, these are the exceptions to the classic tale.  In other tellings, the Amazons are simply a target of male conquest, as in the tale of [[Heracles]] and [[Theseus]] attempting to obtain the girdle of the Amazonian queen [[Hippolyte]] ([[Apollodorus]] ii. 5).  Furthermore, some tales (e.g. both of the previous) conclude with Amazons welcoming, marrying, or congenially procreating with the male heroes.  &lt;br/&gt;Most modern (20th century) depictions, on the other hand, are not misandric at all.  Instead, the modern Amazon is treated sympathetically and is a character whose respect and cooperation the male heroes are challenged to earn.  (See [[Amazons#Modern depiction of Amazons|Modern Depictions of Amazons]].)

==Misandry in feminist literature==  	 
Some feminist literature contains elements which have misandrous connotations.
&lt;!-- please discuss on Talk page before restoring "circular logic" tangent --&gt;

*#			
: "Marriage is an institution developed from rape as a practice." 	 
: "The penis must embody the violence of the male in order for him to be male. Violence is male; the male is the penis; violence is the penis..." 	 
:: [[Andrea Dworkin]], ''Pornography'' 	 
		 
: "Men's need to dominate women may be based in their own sense of marginality or emptiness." 	 
: "While men strut and fret their hour upon the stage, shout in bars and sports arenas, thump their chests or show their profiles in the legislatures, and explode incredible weapons in an endless contest for status, an obsessive quest for symbolic 'proof' of their superiority, women quietly keep the world going." 	 
: "He can beat or kill the woman he claims to love; he can rape women, whether mate, acquaintance, or stranger; he can rape or sexually molest his daughters, nieces, stepchildren, or the children of a woman he claims to love. The vast majority of men in the world do one or more of the above." 	 
:: [[Marilyn French]], ''the War Against Women''

: "I believe that women have a capacity for understanding and compassion which man structurally does not have, does not have it because he cannot have it. He's just incapable of it." 
:: [[Barbara Jordan]] 

: "Men who are unjustly accused of rape can sometimes gain from the experience." 
:: [[Catherine Comin]] 

: "Men's sexuality is mean and violent, and men so powerful that they can 'reach WITHIN women to fuck/construct us from the inside out.' Satan-like, men possess women, making their wicked fantasies and desires women's own. A woman who has sex with a man, therefore, does so against her will, 'even if she does not feel forced.'"
: "I feel what they feel: man-hating, that volatile admixture of pity, contempt, disgust, envy, alienation, fear, and rage at men. It is hatred not only for the anonymous man who makes sucking noises on the street, not only for the rapist or the judge who acquits him, but for what the Greeks called philo-aphilos, 'hate in love,' for the men women share their lives with--husbands, lovers, friends, fathers, brothers, sons, coworkers." 
:: [[Judith Levine]]

: "Life in this society being, at best, an utter bore and no aspect of society being at all relevant to women, there remains to civic-minded, responsible, thrill-seeking females only to overthrow the government, eliminate the money system, institute complete automation, and destroy the male sex." 
: "To call a man an animal is to flatter him; he's a machine, a walking dildo." 
:: [[Valerie Solanas]] 

: "The male is a domestic animal which, if treated with firmness...can be trained to do most things." 
:: [[Jilly Cooper]]

: "I feel that 'man-hating' is an honorable and viable political act, that the oppressed have a right to class-hatred against the class that is oppressing them." 
:: [[Robin Morgan]]

: "And if the professional rapist is to be separated from the average dominant heterosexual (male), it may be mainly a quantitative difference." 
:: [[Susan Griffin]]

: "MALE:...represents a variant of or deviation from the category of female. The first males were mutants...the male sex represents a degeneration and deformity of the female." 
: "MAN:...an obsolete life form... an ordinary creature who needs to be watched...a contradictory baby-man..."
:: 'A feminist Dictionary', ed. Kramarae and Triechler
:"In general, most men are really selfish. They see only one side of the story. Most women have the ability to see two sides of things...I think I am superior to all men. I think women are superior to men but society doesn't allow them to feel that way. I think most women feel subservient to men. Women really do have all the brains and all the power."
:: [[Joanna Angel]]

==Misandry in popular culture==

An analysis of popular culture (e.g., literature, television, film, greeting cards, comics, advertisements, etc.) provides numerous examples of misandry in modern Western society, such as [Nathanson &amp; Young, 2001 &amp; 2006]:

*General neglect of male issues, such as the facts that:
**Depression affects more than 6 million men in America alone&lt;ref&gt;"[http://menanddepression.nimh.nih.gov/infopage.asp?ID=1 Men and Depression]," National Institute for Mental Health.&lt;/ref&gt;, but the figures may be even higher due to the social stigmas attached to reporting it.
**A much higher percentage of male teenagers commit suicide than female teenagers.
**Men constitute approximately 80% of suicides.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.fathersforlife.org/health/who_suicide_rates.htm Suicide rates in countries throughout the world]," Fathers For Life.&lt;/ref&gt;
**White males commit most suicides (an extreme act of powerlessness) compared to all other groups
**Men make up approximately 90% of the prison population in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/prisons.htm Prison Statistics]," U.S. Department of Justice, 30 June 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
**The majority of alcoholics&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.alcoholaddiction.info/statistics.htm Alcoholism Statistics]," Narcanon Southern California, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt;, drug addicts, and homeless persons are men.
**Men have lower levels of university attendance, do increasingly worse in high schools and middle schools than women, and are far more frequently diagnosed as supposedly being afflicted with learning disorders such as [[ADHD]].
**Men, on average, have a significantly lower life expectancy than women.
*Popular culture often depicts men as sex-crazed, and overbearing, an extreme exaggeration of most men's natural interest in sexuality and evolutionary ability to act aggressively.
*Depictions in [[sitcom]]s, advertising, and other television shows in which men (especially fathers) are shown as bumbling and inept.
*Recounting of death in which the body count as described in terms of "X fatalities, including Y women and children," which reduces the value of the adult male lives lost.
*Numerous cultural double-binds, such as:
**Men and women are expected to be equal, but men are often expected to be the sole monetary contributors towards expenses (for example, buying expensive jewelry, paying for meals, etc.).
**Men are told to be increasingly accepting of women who do not fit their expectations of attractiveness, while simultaneously being told (by advertising, print media, etc.) to make themselves increasingly attractive to women.
**Men are expected to be masculine, aggressive defenders of women, but also to act feminine and embrace typically female traits.
**Men are taught from a very young age that women are to be kept "on a pedestal" and revered, but the same cannot be said about women to men.
**The increasingly popular cultural focus on the importance of having an above-average penis size, while simultaneously depicting focus on breast size, waist-to-hip ratio, and other attributes of female sexuality as sexist.
*There is a dichotomy between how men and women are perceived as attractive — women are often depicted or discussed as being beautiful even to other women, while men are regarded as being innately less attractive.
*Sexual oppression of men, often leading to desperate destructive and/or autodestructive acts, is still rarely discussed, while the sexual repression of women has finally been recognized in the last several decades .
*Men are expected to repress their sexuality, and are taught that admiring women's bodies is wrong.
*Workplaces will often taken the word of women over men when considering sexual harassment claims, even if no evidence supports the women's grievance.
*Rape of men by women is often considered 'desirable' by judges.  There is a huge double standard in criminal sentences for rape, incest and other sex crimes that women commit against men versus those that men commit against women.
*When considering crimes of equal magnitude, men will often be dealt harsher sentences than women.
*Advertising and other media frequently depict men in painful or humiliating circumstances (e.g., being hit in the testicles, threatened with castration, sexually harassed, deliberately denied sexual interactions for control or amusement, raped, verbally assaulted, etc.) as being acceptable or even humorous.

The controversial French movie ''[[Baise Moi]]'' (2000) is sometimes cited as an example of a film which has attitudes of blatant misandry; two women go on a sexual and murderous rampage of various men they encounter.  A similar film by [[Russ Meyer]] entitled ''[[Faster, Pussycat! Kill! Kill!]]'' was released in [[1965]]. The T-shirt slogan "[[Boys are stupid, throw rocks at them]]" has been criticised by some as supporting misandry.

It is also sometimes argued that misandry is present in children's culture, most notably with the saying:

''"Snips and snails and puppy dogs' tails - that's what little boys are made of. Sugar and spice and everything nice - that's what little girls are made of."''

While modern [[gender-neutral language]] has changed gender-positive statements in popular narratives, such as in the case of [[Star Trek]]'s 'to boldly go where no man has gone before' becoming 'to boldly go where no one has gone before'; expressions which may be interpreted as pejorative, such as [[The Shadow]]'s "Who knows what evil lurks in the hearts of men?" remain unchanged: "Anyone who's ever dated one" was then added by [[Entertainment Weekly]] (Nathanson &amp; Young, 2001, p. 234) illustrating the allowability of misandry to be expressed in popular humor.

In ''Are Men Necessary?: When Sexes Collide'' (Putnam, 2005) [[Maureen Dowd]] claims that men are afraid of a strong female identity and rallies against men who are 'becoming extinct' and comparing them to 'ornamentation'. In an interview about the book on [[The Colbert Report]], Dowd denied the book is meant to be misandric, saying the answer to the titular question "is obviously yes", but there are a variety of other examples of similarly abrasive titles, as well as commentators who would claim that Dowd's overall answer to the titular question is not "obviously yes".

In the United States, Federal laws require males to register for a military draft at age 18 but do not make the same national service requirement of females when they reach the age of majority.  Federal, state, and local laws that prevent men of age 18 who have not registered for a military draft from receiving benefits such as educational funding and a driver's license. [http://www.sss.gov]

State laws that make the felony of statutory rape applicable to 18 year old males who have consensual sex with a 17 or 16 year old female. [http://www.sexlaws.org/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=Topics&amp;file=index]

State laws that silently and automatically remove an absent father's legal right to future legal custody of his child.  For example, laws that allow a baby to be placed into adoption without the father's notification or consent. [http://www.thesite.org/sexandrelationships/familyandfriends/pregnancyandparenthood/birthfathersrights]

== See also ==
*[[Antifeminist]]
*[[Boys are stupid, throw rocks at them!]]
*[[Female chauvinism]]
*[[Mariticide]]
*[[Masculism]]
*[[Men's movement]]
*[[Misanthropy]]
*[[Misogyny]]
*[[Gynocentrism]]
*[[Testosterone poisoning]]
*[[Valerie Solanas]]

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
==Bibliography==
*''Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture''; Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young, McGill-Queen's University Press, Montreal, 2001; ISBN 0-7735-2272-7

*''Legalizing Misandry: From Public Shame to Systemic Discrimination against Men''; Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young, McGill-Queen's University Press, Montreal, 2006; ISBN 0-7735-2862-8

*''The War Against Boys: How Misguided Feminism Is Harming Our Young Men''; Christina Hoff Sommers, Simon &amp; Schuster Adult Publishing Group, 2001; ISBN 0-6848-4957-7

*''The War Against Men''; Richard T. Hise, Elderberry Press, LLC, 2004, ISBN 1-9308-5961-9

*''Domestic Violence: The 12 Things You Aren't Supposed to Know''; Thomas P. James, Aventine Press, 2003, ISBN 1-5933-0122-7

*''The Myth of Male Power'', Warren Farrell, Berkley Trade, 2001, ISBN 0-4251-8144-8

*''The Decline of Males: The First Look at an Unexpected New World for Men and Women''; Lionel Tiger, Golden Guides from St. Martin's Press, 2000, ISBN 0-3122-6311-2

==External links==
* [http://www.lulu.com/content/78982/ Misandry by Dani Pratt]
* [http://fathersandhusbands.org/ Society for the Prevention of Misandry in the Media]
* [http://groups.yahoo.com/group/misandryrecovery/ Misandry discussion group]
* [http://antimisandry.com Anti Misandry website, blogs and forum]
* [http://www.lbduk.org/spreading%20misandry.htm The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture] book review
* [http://www.backlash.com/content/gender/1996/4-apr96/wilson04.html Androphobia: The Only Respectable Bigotry] by [[Robert Anton Wilson]]

==News articles==
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]

[[de:Misandrie]]
[[es:Misandria]]
[[fa:مردبیزاری]]
[[fr:Misandrie]]
[[it:Misandria]]
[[nl:Misandrie]]
[[ja:男性差別]]
[[pl:Mizoandria]]
[[tr:Erkek düşmanlığı]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>