<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131120183141|582558130" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20778" pageid="20778" ns="0" title="Misandry"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-20T18:35:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{discrimination sidebar}}
'''Misandry''' {{IPAc-en|m|ɪ|ˈ|s|æ|n|d|r|i}} is the hatred or dislike of [[boy]]s and/or [[men]].&lt;ref&gt;http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/misandry&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/misandry&lt;/ref&gt; Misandry can be manifested in numerous ways that have their parallel in misogyny including sexual discrimination, denigration of men, violence against men, and sexual objectification of men. [[Warren Farrell]] has written of how men are uniquely marginalized in what he calls their 'disposability', the manner in which the most dangerous of societies' jobs throughout history, particularly soldiering, have been left for men to perform. The female counterpart of misandry is [[misogyny]], the hatred or dislike of women; the antonym of misandry is [[philandry]], the love or fondness of men.

==Origin==
The word Misandry can be traced back to at least 1871, when it was used in ''[[The Spectator]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;Review of novel "Blanche Seymour", ''The Spectator'', London, Apr. 1, 1871, p. 359]&lt;/ref&gt; It appeared in ''[[Merriam-Webster's Collegiate Dictionary]]'' (11th ed.) in 1952. Misandry is formed from the Greek misos (μῖσος, "hatred") and anēr, andros (ἀνήρ, gen. ἀνδρός; "man").&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Dictionaries http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/misandry&lt;/ref&gt;

==In literature==

===Ancient Greek literature===
Classics professor [[Froma Zeitlin]] of [[Princeton University]] discussed misandry in her article titled "Patterns of Gender in Aeschylean Drama: Seven against Thebes and the Danaid Trilogy."&lt;ref name="Zeitlin" /&gt; She writes:
{{quote|The most significant point of contact, however, between Eteocles and the suppliant Danaids is, in fact, their extreme positions with regard to the opposite sex: the misogyny of Eteocles' outburst against all women of whatever variety (Se. 181-202) has its counterpart in the seeming misandry of the Danaids, who although opposed to their Egyptian cousins in particular (marriage with them is incestuous, they are violent men) often extend their objections to include the race of males as a whole and view their cause as a passionate contest between the sexes (cf. Su. 29, 393, 487, 818, 951).&lt;ref name="Zeitlin"&gt;{{cite journal|first=Froma I.|last=Zeitlin|title=Patterns of Gender in Aeschylean Drama: Seven against Thebes and the Danaid Trilogy|date=April 1, 1990|url=http://repositories.cdlib.org/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1008&amp;context=ucbclassics|format=PDF|accessdate=2007-12-21}} Princeton University, paper given at the Department of Classics, University of California, Berkeley&lt;/ref&gt;}}

=== Literary criticism ===
In his book, ''Gender and Judaism: The Transformation of Tradition'', Harry Brod, a Professor of [[Philosophy]] and [[Humanities]] in the Department of Philosophy and [[Religion]] at the [[University of Northern Iowa]], writes:
{{quote|
In the introduction to ''The Great Comic Book Heroes'', Jules Feiffer writes that this is Superman's joke on the rest of us. Clark is Superman's vision of what other men are really like. We are scared, incompetent, and powerless, particularly around women. Though Feiffer took the joke good-naturedly, a more cynical response would see here the Kryptonian's misanthropy, his misandry embodied in Clark and his misogyny in his wish that Lois be enamored of Clark (much like Oberon takes out hostility toward Titania by having her fall in love with an ass in Shakespeare's ''Midsummer-Night's Dream'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=SH8r3ntJG8AC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA279 ''Gender and Judaism: The Transformation of Tradition]'', Harry Brod&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

[[Julie M. Thompson]], a [[feminist]] author, connects misandry with envy of men, in particular "[[penis envy]]," a term coined by [[Sigmund Freud]] in 1908, in his theory of female sexual development.&lt;ref&gt;
Emphasis added. Julie M. Thompson, ''Mommy Queerest: Contemporary Rhetorics of Lesbian Maternal Identity'', (Amherst: [[University of Massachusetts Press]], 2002).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Comparisons with other forms of discrimination==
Writer [[Warren Farrell]] compared the dehumanizing stereotyping of men to the dehumanization of [[Slavery in the United States|American slaves]], stating that the male role in most traditional societies is similar to the role of the second class slave, while the female role is similar to the first class slave. The second class slave would labor outside, while the first class slave worked in the home.&lt;ref&gt;Warren Farrell "The Myth of Male Power," Berkeley Publishing Group, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote|In the past quarter century, we exposed biases against other races and called it racism, and we exposed biases against women and called it sexism. Biases against men we call humor.|Warren Farrell|''Women Can't Hear What Men Don't Say''}}

Religious Studies professors Paul Nathanson and Katherine Young made similar comparisons in their 2001, three-book series ''Beyond the Fall of Man'',&lt;ref name="NYspreading-4_6"&gt;{{Harv|Nathanson|Young|2001|pp=4–6}} "The same problem that long prevented mutual respect between Jews and Christians, the teaching of contempt, now prevents mutual respect between men and women."&lt;/ref&gt; which treats misandry as a form of prejudice and discrimination that has become institutionalized in North American society.

In the 2007 book ''International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities'', Marc A. Ouellette directly contrasted misandry and misogyny, arguing that "misandry lacks the systemic, transhistoric, institutionalized, and legislated antipathy of misogyny."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-first=Michael|editor1-last=Flood|editor1-link=Michael Flood|others=''et al.''|title=International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities|url=http://books.google.com/?id=EUON2SYps-QC&amp;pg=PA442&amp;dq=michael+flood+misandry#v=onepage&amp;q=michael%20flood%20misandry&amp;f=false|date=2007-07-18|publisher=Routledge|location=London; New York|isbn=0-415-33343-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anthropology|Anthropologist]] David D. Gilmore argues that while misogyny is a "near-universal phenomenon" there is no male equivalent to misogyny. He writes: &lt;blockquote&gt;Man hating among women has no popular name because it has never (at least not until recently) achieved apotheosis as a social ''fact'', that is, it has never been ratified into public, culturally recognized and approved ''institutions'' (...) As a cultural institution, misogyny therefore seems to stand alone as a gender-based phobia, unreciprocated.&lt;ref name="gilmore"&gt;Gilmore, David G. ''Misogyny: The Male Malady''. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2009, pp. 10–13, ISBN 978-0-8122-1770-4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Gilmore also states that [[neologism]]s like misandry refer "not to the hatred of men as men, but to the hatred of men's traditional male role" and a "culture of machismo". Therefore, he argues, misandry is "different from the intensely ''ad feminam'' aspect of misogyny that targets women no matter what they believe or do".&lt;ref name="gilmore"/&gt;

==Instances==
Academic [[Alice Echols]], in her 1989 book ''Daring To Be Bad: Radical Feminism in America, 1967–1975'', argued that [[Radical feminism|radical feminist]] [[Valerie Solanas]], best known for her [[attempted murder]] of [[Andy Warhol]] in 1968, displayed an extreme level of misandry compared to other radical feminists of the time in her [[tract (literature)|tract]], ''[[SCUM Manifesto|The SCUM Manifesto]]''. Echols stated,
{{quote|Solanas's unabashed misandry—especially her belief in men's biological inferiority—her endorsement of relationships between 'independent women,' and her dismissal of sex as 'the refuge of the mindless' contravened the sort of radical feminism which prevailed in most women's groups across the country.&lt;ref&gt;Echols, Nicole. [http://books.google.com/books?id=6zaVkAjBuPEC&amp;pg=PA104 ''Daring to Be Bad: Radical Feminism in America, 1967–1975'']. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1989, pp. 104-105, ISBN 978-0-8166-1786-9.&lt;/ref&gt;}} The text contains aspects of Freudian [[Psychoanalysis|psychoanalytical]] theory: the biological accident, the incomplete sex and "penis envy" which became "pussy envy."&lt;ref&gt;Castro, Ginette. [http://books.google.com/books?id=DYuBjJXGsZkC&amp;pg=PA73 "American Feminism: A Contemporary History"]. New York: New York University Press, 1990, p. 73, ISBN 978-0-8147-1435-5.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Patricia Juliana. [http://books.google.com/books?id=4bxltKXsftIC&amp;pg=PA68 ''The Queer Sixties'']. New York: Routledge, 1999, p. 68, ISBN 978-0-415-92168-8.&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Paul Nathanson]] and [[Katherine K. Young]] argued that "ideological feminism" has imposed misandry on culture.&lt;ref name="NYspreading-xiv"&gt;{{Harv|Nathanson|Young|2001|p=xiv}} "[ideological feminism,] one form of feminism—one that has had a great deal of influence, whether directly or indirectly, on both popular culture and elite culture—is profoundly misandric".&lt;/ref&gt; Their 2001 book, ''Spreading Misandry'', analyzed "pop cultural artifacts and productions from the 1990s" from movies to greeting cards for what they considered to be pervasive messages of hatred toward men. ''Legalizing Misandry'' (2005), the second in the series, gave similar attention to laws in North America.

In 2002, [[Pundit (expert)|pundit]] [[Charlotte Hays]] wrote "that the anti-male philosophy of radical feminism has filtered into the culture at large is incontestable; indeed, this attitude has become so pervasive that we hardly notice it any longer".&lt;ref&gt;Hays, Charlotte. 'The Worse Half.' ''[[National Review]]'' 11 March 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sociologist Anthony Synnott argues that the reality of misandry is undeniable when one looks to cultural, academic, and media depictions of men. He states that "misandry is everywhere, culturally acceptable, even normative, largely invisible, taught directly and indirectly by men and women, blind to reality, very damaging and dangerous to men and women in different ways and de-humanizing."&lt;ref name=Synnott107&gt;[http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/rethinking-men/201010/why-some-people-have-issues-men-misandry ''Why Some People Have Issues With Men: Misandry]'', ''Psychology Today'', October 6, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; He also criticizes modern scholarship on men as "dehumanizing" and lacking in awareness of statistical reality.

==Wendy McElroy==
{{Main|Wendy McElroy}}
[[Wendy McElroy]], an [[individualist feminist]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.org/aboutus/person_detail.asp?id=488 The Independent Institute]&lt;/ref&gt; wrote in 2001 that some feminists "have redefined the view of the movement of the opposite sex" as "a hot anger toward men seems to have turned into a cold hatred."&lt;ref name="McElroy-05"&gt;{{Harv|McElroy|2001|p=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; She argued it was a misandrist position to consider men, as a class, to be irreformable or [[rape|rapists]]. McElroy stated "a new ideology has come to the forefront... radical or gender, feminism," one that has "joined hands with [the] political correctness movement that condemns the panorama of western civilization as sexist and racist: the product of 'dead white males'."&lt;ref name="McElroy-04_6"&gt;{{Harv|McElroy|2001|pp=4–6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Androphobia]]
* [[Boys are stupid, throw rocks at them! controversy]]
* [[Female chauvinism]]
* [[Men's movement]]
* [[Men's rights]]
* [[Misanthropy]]
* [[Misogyny]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Violence against men]]
* [[Women's studies]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|title=[[Who Stole Feminism? How Women Have Betrayed Women]]|last=Sommers|first=Christina Hoff|authorlink=Christina Hoff Sommers|year=1995|origyear=First published 1994|publisher= [[Simon &amp; Schuster]]|isbn=0-684-80156-6}}
* {{cite book|title=The Myth of Male Power: Why Men Are the Disposable Sex|last=Farrell|first=Warren|authorlink=Warren Farrell|year=2001|origyear= First published 1993|publisher=[[Berkley Books|Berkley Trade]]|location=|isbn=0-425-18144-8}}
* {{cite book|title=Misogyny, Misandry, and Misanthropy|last=Ferguson|first=Frances|authorlink=Frances Ferguson|last2=Bloch|first2=R. Howard|authorlink2=R. Howard Bloch|year=1989|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|isbn=0-520-06546-8}}
* {{cite book|title=My Enemy, My Love: Man-Hating and Ambivalence in Women's Lives|last=Levine|first=Judith|authorlink=Judith Levine|year=1992|publisher=Da Capo Press|isbn=1-56025-568-4}}
* {{cite book|last=McElroy|first=Wendy|title=Sexual Correctness: The Gender-Feminist Attack on Women|series=Harper Paperbacks|year=2001|publisher=McFarland &amp; Company|location=New York|isbn=0-7864-1144-9|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Nathanson|first=Paul|author-link=Nathanson and Young|last2=Young|first2=Katherine R.|author2-link=Nathanson and Young|title=Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture|series=Harper Paperbacks|year=2001|publisher=[[McGill-Queen's University Press]]|place=Montreal|isbn=0-7735-3099-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Nathanson|first=Paul|author-link=Nathanson and Young|last2=Young|first2=Katherine R.|author2-link=Nathanson and Young|title=Legalizing Misandry: From Public Shame to Systemic Discrimination Against Men|year=2006|publisher=[[McGill-Queen's University Press]]|place=Montreal|isbn=0-7735-2862-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=The Revolt of the Primitive: An Inquiry into the Roots of Political Correctness|last=Schwartz|first=Howard|edition=Revised|year=2003|publisher=[[Transaction Publishers]]|isbn=0-7658-0537-5}}

==External links==
* {{cite journal|last=Bailée|first=Susan|year=2001|title=Misandry in the Classroom|journal=The Hudson Review|volume=54|issue=1|pages=148–54|quote=My rough-and-tumble first grader, Mark, came home from school yesterday and nonchalantly told me a story about his day that set me shivering|doi=10.2307/3852834|jstor=3852834|publisher=The Hudson Review, Inc.|last2=Sommers|first2=Christina Hoff|ref=harv}}
* {{cite web|url=http://adonismirror.com/10152006_leader_misandry_and_misanthropy.htm|title=Misandry: From the Dictionary of Fools|accessdate=2007-12-28|last=Leader|first=Richard|year=2007|work=Adonis Mirror}} article critical of the use of the term
* {{cite web|url=http://www.backlash.com/content/gender/1996/4-apr96/wilson04.html|title=Androphobia: The only respectable bigotry|accessdate=2007-12-28|last=Wilson|first=Robert Anton|authorlink=Robert Anton Wilson|year=1996|month=April|work=The Backlash!|publisher=Shameless Men Press}}

{{Sexual abuse}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}

[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Misandry| ]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>