<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071112104004|170939305" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20778" pageid="20778" ns="0" title="Misandry"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-13T07:34:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Otheruses4|misandry in general|the specific theory of misandry as a current social issue|Nathanson and Young}}
{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wiktionary}}{{Discrimination}}
'''Misandry''' ({{pronEng|m&lt;s&gt;ɪ&lt;/s&gt;ˈsændri}}) is the hatred of men as a [[Gender|sex]], hence a type of [[sexism]]. Those holding misandric beliefs can be of either sex. Misandry is not discussed very often compared to [[misogyny]], [[Judith Levine]] called it "the hate that dares not speak its name".&lt;ref&gt;Levine, ''My Enemy, My Love: Man-hating and Ambivalence in Women's Lives''.&lt;/ref&gt; Charlotte Hays notes further, "that the anti-male philosophy of radical feminism has filtered into the culture at large — is incontestable; indeed, this attitude has become so pervasive that we hardly notice it any longer."&lt;ref&gt;Hays, Charlotte. 'The Worse Half'. National Review 11 March, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

A rigorous scientific study of mass media representation of men in Australia has shown quantitatively what others are suggesting qualitatively of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;James Raymond Macnamara, [http://library.uws.edu.au/adt-NUWS/public/adt-NUWS20060210.135125/index.html ''Representations of men and male identities in Australian mass media''], Ph.D. thesis, University of Western Sydney, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Its author, James Macnamara, also notes Lynne Segal's widely cited 1987 description of feminist representations of men as "rapists, batterers, pornographers, child abusers, militarists, exploiters."&lt;ref&gt;Lynne Segal, ''Is the Future Female? Troubled Thoughts on Contemporary Feminism'', (London: Virago, 1987). ISBN: 0 86068 697 3&lt;/ref&gt; Whereas Kaufman and others found 8% of female perpetrators of abuse were teachers and 23% were babysitters, compared to male perpetrators who were 0% and 8% respectively.&lt;ref&gt;K. Kaufman, A. Wallace, C. Johnson and M. Reeder, ''Comparing female and male perpetrator's modus operandi: Victims' reports of sexual abuse''. Journal of Interpersonal Violence '''10''' (1995): 322-333.&lt;/ref&gt;
==Political form of misandry==
[[Wendy McElroy]] believes that some feminists "have redefined the view of the movement of the opposite sex" as "a hot anger toward men seems to have turned into a cold hatred".&lt;ref&gt;Wendy McElroy, ''Sexual Correctness'', p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; Men as a class are considered irreformable, all men are considered rapists, and marriage, rape and prostitution are seen as the same. She says "a new ideology has come to the forefront... radical or gender, feminism", one that has "joined hands with [the] political correctness movement that condemns the panorama of western civilization as sexist and racist: the product of 'dead white males.'"&lt;ref&gt;Wendy McElroy, ''Sexual Correctness'', pp. 4 &amp; 6&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Analogies to other forms of bigotry ===
Several authors draw analogies between misandry and other forms of [[prejudice]] such as misogyny, [[racism]], [[anti-semitism]], and [[homophobia]].  They argue that men are [[stereotyped]] in various ways that [[Dehumanization|dehumanize]] them, and that would be considered unacceptable if applied to other groups such as women and minorities. The purported cause of the public acceptance of misandry as opposed to misogyny is that while some women espouse belief in the existence of misogyny and use it as a "proof" of the beliefs of feminism, men do not usually acknowledge themselves as victims of misandry. This difference in perception thus creates a climate in which it is socially acceptable for feminists to issue charges of gender-based hatred and prejudice against men, and once having done so to treat these charges as fact, while discounting similar charges against women as further proof of their claims.

[[Masculist]] writer [[Warren Farrell]] argues: "In the past quarter century, we exposed [[biases]] against other races and called it racism, and we exposed biases against women and called it sexism.  Biases against men we call [[humor]]." Farrell compares dehumanizing stereotyping of men to dehumanization of the Vietnamese as "[[Gook#G|gooks]]."
&lt;ref name=Farrell-1999&gt;{{cite book 
|last= Farrell 
|authorlink= Warren Farrell 
|first= Warren 
|title= Women Can't Hear What Men Don't Say 
|Publisher= Tarcher 
|Location=  New York 
|Year= 1999 
|id= ISBN 087477988X
|quote =}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Could use another quote in this section. --&gt;

===Misandry and misogyny===
[[Christina Hoff Sommers]] notes what she considers a 'corrosive paradox' of feminism: "that no group of women can wage war on men without at the same time denigrating the women who respect those men".  She says "it is just not possible to incriminate men without implying that large numbers of women are fools or worse". To Hoff Sommers, women who respect men are seen by "gender feminists" (a term she coined in ''Who Stole Feminism'', 1994) as being "in the camp of the enemy". Therefore, misandry becomes misogyny, perpetrated by feminists whom Hoff Sommers sees as a radical minority, representative neither of women nor of feminists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Hoff Sommers
 | first = Christina
 | title = Who Stole Feminism
 | year = 1994
 | publisher = Simon and Schuster
 | isbn = 978-0684801568
 | pages = p. 256
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nathanson and Young===
[[Nathanson and Young|Paul Nathanson and Katherine Young]] treat misandry as a form of prejudice and discrimination that has become institutionalized in North American society, causing real harm to men. They assert in their 2001 book ''Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture'' that misandry primarily stems from the gynocentric use of [[gender]], and is used to blame all men as responsible for imposing gender. To Nathanson and Young this assumption makes men the official scapegoats for the existence of all evil, while women, responsible for all good, are their official victims. The logical outcome of this gynocentric world-view would be men paying reparations to women for their crimes against them throughout history. Nathanson and Young criticize the feminist idea of gender being a social construct containing the underlying assumption that male-determined societal imperatives should trump individual rights.

Nathanson and Young assert that feminists strategically use [[political correctness]], academic deconstructionism, and "fronts" to promote their misandric worldview.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} They posit an "ideological" feminism, which they say is derived from Marxism and romanticism, with class and nation replaced by gender identification to foster the hatred of men as a group.

Positive reviews of Nathanson and Young have been published internationally, in major periodicals, and in academic journals.&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Times Literary Supplement]]'', ''[[National Review]]'', ''[[Quadrant]]'', ''[[The Journal of Men's Studies]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Negative reviews can be found also, at least two such reviews have been published by Canadian journals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.csaa.ca/CRSA/BookReview/Reviews/200311/200311NATHANSON.htm |title=Book Review PAUL NATHANSON and KATHERINE K. YOUNG, Spreading Misandry |accessdate=2007-01-06 |last=Lewis-Horne |first=Nancy |work=The Canadian Review of Sociology and Anthropology |publisher= Canadian Sociology and Anthropology Association 
|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060221214150/http://www.csaa.ca/CRSA/BookReview/Reviews/200311/200311NATHANSON.htm
|archivedate=2006-02-21
|quote= I am not convinced that misandry is a pervasive cultural pattern.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="CJFL-Chunn"&gt;{{cite journal
 | quotes = 
 | last = Chunn
 | first = Dorothy E.
 | year = 2007
 | title = Book Review: Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young, ''Legalizing Misandry: From Public Shame to Systemic Discrimination Against Men''
 | journal = Canadian Journal of Family Law
 | volume = 23
 | issue = 1
 | pages = 93-103
 | url = http://faculty.law.ubc.ca/cdnjfl/art/2312007.html
 | format = fee required
 | accessdate = 2007-04-15
 | quote = ''Legalizing Misandry'' is an exemplar of reaction and resistance to feminism as the turn of the twenty-first century.
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2007, Nathanson and Young's first book, ''Spreading Misandry'', was added to the [[Association of American University Presses]] (AAUP) list of [http://aaupnet.org/librarybooks/300-399Social.html "books selected for public and secondary school libraries".] This list is described by the AAUP as "The Best of the Best from the University Presses".&lt;ref&gt;[http://aaupnet.org/librarybooks/index.html]&lt;/ref&gt; The "Best of the Best" program is presented annually at the Summer [[American Library Association]] (ALA) conference. Public and secondary school librarians form the selection committees, evaluating books against a variety of criteria.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aaupnet.org/programs/marketing/library/bestofbest07.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Judith Levine's views on misandry== 
{{Quote|Man-hating is an emotional problem inasmuch as it creates pain and hostility between women and men. But it is not an individual neurosis à la 'Women Who Hate Men and the Men Who...' Man-hating is a collective, cultural problem &amp;mdash; or to refrain from diagnosing it at all, a cultural ''phenomenon'' &amp;mdash; and men, as the object of man-hating, are part of it too.|[[Judith Levine]]|My Enemy, My Love&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Levine |first= Judith |authorlink=Judith Levine |title= My Enemy, My Love |publisher= [[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]] |year= 1992 |id= ISBN 0385410794}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Judith Levine alternatively focuses on private manifestations of misandry in her 1992 book, ''My Enemy, My Love: Man-hating and Ambivalence in Woman's Lives''. She explicates what she considers as the "intellectually and emotionally rich, little explored, often subterranean world of women's hatred of men" and ambivalence toward men. This she addresses "in a unique examination of the family, trac(ing) the role of man-hating in the unfolding of contemporary feminism".

Levine classifies the following stereotypical men as targets of women's misandry within intimate relationships:
* Infants: the Mama's Boy, the Babbler, the Bumbler and the Invalid;
* Betrayers: the Seducer, the Slave, the Abandoner and the Abductor; and
* Beasts: the Brute, the Pet, the Pervert, the Prick and the Killer.

Within the family, she asserts that father-abandonment of daughters, familial gender standards that discriminate against daughters and paternal neglect of daughters are a root cause of misandry in women. She also says fathers, brothers and husbands are targeted by modern feminism, elaborating that feminism has disrupted the traditional family unit so that a "politically conscious battalion of daughters" could replace male familial roles "by banding together as sisters" to "run everything" by themselves.{{Fact|date=May 2007}}

== See also ==
*[[Antifeminism]]
*[[Boys are stupid, throw rocks at them!]]
*[[Equalism]]
*[[Masculism]]
*[[Men's movement]]
*[[Misanthropy]]
*[[SCUM manifesto]]

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==Bibliography==
* ''Who Stole Feminism: How Women Have Betrayed Women'', Christina Hoff Sommers, 1994
* ''Sexual Correctness: The Gender-Feminist Attack on Women'', Wendy McElroy, 
*''Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture''; Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young, McGill-Queen's University Press, Montreal, 2001; ISBN 0-7735-2272-7
*''Legalizing Misandry: From Public Shame to Systemic Discrimination against Men''; Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young, McGill-Queen's University Press, Montreal, 2006; ISBN 0-7735-2862-8
*''My Enemy, my Love: Man-hating and ambivalence in women's lives'', Judith Levine, 1992.
*''The Myth of Male Power'', Warren Farrell, Berkley Trade, 2001, ISBN 0-425-18144-8

==External links==
*[http://www.backlash.com/content/gender/1996/4-apr96/wilson04.html Androphobia: The Only Respectable Bigotry] by [[Robert Anton Wilson]]
*[http://adonismirror.com/10152006_leader_misandry_and_misanthropy.htm Misandry: From the Dictionary of Fools] by Richard Leader (article critical of the use of the term)
*[http://www.antimisandry.com Anti Misandry Web Site]

[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]

[[de:Misandrie]]
[[es:Misandria]]
[[fa:مردبیزاری]]
[[fr:Misandrie]]
[[it:Misandria]]
[[he:מיזאנדריה]]
[[nl:Misandrie]]
[[ja:男性差別]]
[[pl:Mizoandria]]
[[ru:Мизандрия]]
[[fi:Miesviha]]
[[tr:Erkek düşmanlığı]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>