<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171120143421|811261689" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20778" pageid="20778" ns="0" title="Misandry"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-20T14:35:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Masculism sidebar |topics}}{{discrimination sidebar}}
'''Misandry''' ({{IPAc-en|m|ɪ|ˈ|s|æ|n|d|r|i}}) is the hatred of, contempt for, or prejudice against [[men]] or [[boys]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/234242?redirectedFrom=Misandry#eid "Misandry"] at Oxford English Dictionary Online (ODO), Third Edition, June 2002. Accessed through library subscription on 25 July 2014. Earliest recorded use: 1885. ''Blackwood's Edinb. Mag'', Sept. 289/1   No man whom she cared for had ever proposed to marry her. She could not account for it, and it was a growing source of bitterness, of misogyny as well as misandry.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Misandry" at [http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/misandry [[Merriam-Webster#Services|Merriam-Webster online]]] ("First Known Use: circa 1909")&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="psychologytoday.com"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Synnott|first1=Anthony|title=Why Some People Have Issues With Men: Misandry is not in everyone's dictionary but it's out there|journal=Psychology Today|date=2010-10-06|url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/rethinking-men/201010/why-some-people-have-issues-men-misandry|accessdate=24 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is parallel in form to [[misogyny]], and either "misandrous" or "misandristic" can be used as adjective forms of the word.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Adjective of "misandry"|url=http://community.oxforddictionaries.com/boards/topic/adjective-of-misandry/|website=Oxford Dictionaries|publisher=Oxford University Press|accessdate=24 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Misandry can manifest itself in numerous ways, including [[sexual discrimination]], female privilege,&lt;ref&gt;Smith, J. (2016, July 05). Female Privilege Exists Too. Retrieved July 25, 2017, from https://www.theodysseyonline.com/female-privilege-exists&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wente, M. (2017, January 28). Ladies, check your privilege. Retrieved July 25, 2017, from https://www.theglobeandmail.com/opinion/ladies-check-your-privilege/article33797846/&lt;/ref&gt; denigration of men, [[violence against men]], [[sexual objectification]] of men, "or more broadly, the hatred, fear, anger and contempt of men".&lt;ref name="psychologytoday.com"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theconversation.com/for-fathers-day-give-us-men-who-arent-shown-as-fools-and-clowns-31170|title=For Father's Day, give us men who aren't shown as fools and clowns|author=Peter West|date=5 September 2014|work=The Conversation|accessdate=17 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==
Misandry is parallel in form to '[[misogyny]]', and is formed from the Greek ''misos'' (μῖσος, "hatred") and ''anēr'', ''andros'' (ἀνήρ, gen. ἀνδρός; "man").&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Dictionaries http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/misandry&lt;/ref&gt; Use of the word can be found as far back as the nineteenth century, including an 1871 use in ''[[The Spectator]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title="Misandry" the Word – Its Origin|url=http://unknownmisandry.blogspot.com/2011/02/misandry-word-its-origin.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Review of novel "Blanche Seymour", ''The Spectator'', London, 1 Apr. 1871, p. 389. ''“We cannot, indeed, term her an absolute misandrist, as she fully admits the possibility, in most cases at least, of the reclamation of men from their naturally vicious and selfish state, though at the cost of so much trouble and vexation of spirit to women, that it is not quite clear whether she does not regard their existence as at best a mitigated evil.”''&lt;/ref&gt; It appeared in ''[[Merriam-Webster's Collegiate Dictionary]]'' (11th ed.) in 1952. Translation of the French "Misandrie" to the German "Männerhass" (Hatred of Men)&lt;ref name="german_english_Männerhaß"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.pons.com/translate/german-english/M%C3%A4nnerha%C3%9F |title=Translations for Männerhaß in the German » English dictionary |publisher=PONS GmbH, Stuttgart |work=Pons Dictionary German To English |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6OBt5zfJ5?url=http://en.pons.com/translate/german-english/M%C3%A4nnerha%C3%9F |archivedate=19 March 2014 |deadurl=yes |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; is recorded in 1803.&lt;ref name="Krünitz1803"&gt;{{cite book|author=Johann Georg Krünitz|title=[[wikipedia:Oekonomische Encyklopädie|Oekonomische Encyklopädie]] oder allgemeines System der Staats-, Stadt-, Haus- u. Landwirthschaft: in alphabetischer Ordnung. Von Lebens-Art bis Ledecz : Nebst einer einzigen Fig. Friedrich's des Einzigen, u. 3 Karten|volume=90|year=1803|publisher=Pauli|page=461}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Male disposability==
Activist [[Warren Farrell]] has written of his views on how men are uniquely marginalized in what he calls their "disposability", the manner in which the most dangerous occupations, notably soldiering and mining, were historically performed exclusively by men and remain so today. In his book, ''[[The Myth of Male Power]]'', Farrell argues that patriarchal societies do not make rules to benefit men at the expense of women. Farrell contends that nothing is more telling about who has benefited from "men's rules" than [[Life expectancy#Gender differences|life expectancy]], which is lower in males, and [[Gender differences in suicide|suicide rates]], which are higher in males.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1993"&gt;Warren Farrell, ''The Myth of Male Power'', (N.Y.: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1993), Chp. 2&lt;/ref&gt;

Religious Studies professors [[Paul Nathanson]] and [[Katherine K. Young|Katherine Young]] made similar comparisons in their 2001 three-book series ''Beyond the Fall of Man'',&lt;ref name="NYspreading-4_6"&gt;{{Harv|Nathanson|Young|2001|pp=4–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; which refers to misandry as a "form of prejudice and discrimination that has become institutionalized in North American society", writing, "The same problem that long prevented mutual respect between Jews and Christians, the teaching of contempt, now prevents mutual respect between men and women."&lt;ref name="NathansonSpreading"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Nathanson|first1=Paul|last2=Young|first2=Katherine K.|title=Spreading misandry the teaching of contempt for men in popular culture|date=2001|publisher=McGill-Queen's University Press|location=Montreal, Que.|isbn=9780773569690|page=6|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AIkNxlu8SOcC&amp;pg=PA6&amp;lpg=PA6|accessdate=11 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Radical feminism==
{{Main|Radical feminism}}
Academic [[Alice Echols]], in her 1989 book ''Daring To Be Bad: Radical Feminism in America, 1967–1975'', argued that [[Radical feminism|radical feminist]] [[Valerie Solanas]], best known for her [[attempted murder]] of [[Andy Warhol]] in 1968, displayed an extreme level of misandry compared to other radical feminists of the time in her [[tract (literature)|tract]], ''[[SCUM Manifesto|The SCUM Manifesto]]''. Echols stated,
{{quote|Solanas's unabashed misandry—especially her belief in men's biological inferiority—her endorsement of relationships between 'independent women,' and her dismissal of sex as 'the refuge of the mindless' contravened the sort of radical feminism which prevailed in most women's groups across the country.|&lt;ref&gt;Echols, Nicole. [https://books.google.com/books?id=6zaVkAjBuPEC&amp;pg=PA104 ''Daring to Be Bad: Radical Feminism in America, 1967–1975'']. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1989, pp. 104-105, {{ISBN|978-0-8166-1786-9}}.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Andrea Dworkin]] criticized the [[biological determinist]] strand in radical feminism that, in 1977, she found "with increasing frequency in feminist circles" which echoed the views of Valerie Solanas that males are biologically inferior to women and violent by nature, requiring a [[gendercide]] to allow for the emergence of a "new ''Übermensch'' Womon".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://heresiesfilmproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/heresies6.pdf|title = Biological Superiority: The World's Most Dangerous and Deadly Idea|last = Dworkin|first = Andrea|date = Summer 1978|journal = HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics|access-date = 2015-05-12|publisher = Heresies Collective, Inc.|issue = #6|series = No. 2|location = New York City, NY, USA|volume =  2|page =46|issn = 0146-3411|author-link = Andrea Dworkin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The author [[bell hooks]] (pen name of Gloria Jean Watkins) has discussed the issue of "man hating" during the early period of women's liberation as a reaction to patriarchal oppression and women who have had bad experiences with men in non-feminist social movements. She has also criticized separatist strands of feminism as "reactionary" for promoting the notion that men are inherently immoral, inferior, and unable to help end sexist oppression or benefit from feminism.&lt;ref&gt;hooks, bell. (1984), ''Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center'', South End Press; Boston.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;hooks, bell. (2005), ''The Will To Change: Men, Masculinity and Love'', New York; Washington Square Press.&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Feminism is For Everybody'', hooks laments the fact that feminists who critiqued anti-male bias in the early women's movement never gained mainstream media attention and that "our theoretical work critiquing the demonization of men as the enemy did not change the perspective of women who were anti-male." hooks has theorized previously that this demonization led to an unnecessary rift between the [[men's movement]] and the [[women's movement]].&lt;ref&gt;hooks, bell. Feminist Theory from Margin to Center. Boston, MA: South End, 1984. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although bell hooks doesn't name individual separatist theorists, [[Mary Daly]]'s utopian vision of a world in which men and heterosexual women have been eliminated is an extreme example of this tendency.&lt;ref&gt;Daly, Mary. (1998), ''Quintessence...Realizing The Archaic Future'', Beacon Press; Boston.&lt;/ref&gt; Daly argued that sexual equality between men and women was not possible and that women, due to their superior capacities, should rule men.&lt;ref&gt;Daly, Mary. (1990),  ''Gyn/Ecology: The Metaethics of Radical Feminism'', Boston, Mass.: Beacon Press, pp. 384 &amp; 375–376&lt;/ref&gt; Yet later, in an interview, Daly argued "If life is to survive on this planet, there must be a decontamination of the Earth. I think this will be accompanied by an evolutionary process that will result in a drastic reduction of the population of males."&lt;ref&gt;Ridle, Susan (Fall/Winter 1999). "No Man's Land". ''EnlightenNext'' Magazine&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Paul Nathanson]] and [[Katherine K. Young]] argued that "ideological feminism" as opposed to "egalitarian feminism" has imposed misandry on culture.&lt;ref name="NYspreading-xiv"&gt;{{Harv|Nathanson|Young|2001|p=xiv}} "[ideological feminism,] one form of feminism—one that has had a great deal of influence, whether directly or indirectly, on both popular culture and elite culture—is profoundly misandric".&lt;/ref&gt; Their 2001 book, ''Spreading Misandry'', analyzed "pop cultural artifacts and productions from the 1990s" from movies to greeting cards for what they considered to be pervasive messages of hatred toward men.&lt;ref name="NathansonYoung2001"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Paul Nathanson|author2=Katherine K. Young|title=Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JGocoMfjt_oC|date=16 October 2001|publisher=McGill-Queen's Press - MQUP|isbn=978-0-7735-2272-5|page=ix}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Legalizing Misandry'' (2005), the second in the series, gave similar attention to laws in North America.&lt;ref name="NathansonYoung2006"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Paul Nathanson|author2=Katherine K. Young|title=Legalizing Misandry: From Public Shame to Systemic Discrimination Against Men|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cqKxhhu55SMC|year=2006|publisher=McGill-Queen's Press - MQUP|isbn=978-0-7735-5999-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Wendy McElroy]], an [[individualist feminist]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.org/aboutus/person_detail.asp?id=488 The Independent Institute]&lt;/ref&gt; wrote in 2001 that some feminists "have redefined the view of the movement of the opposite sex" as "a hot anger toward men [that] seems to have turned into a cold hatred."&lt;ref name="McElroy-05"&gt;{{Harv|McElroy|2001|p=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; She argued it was a misandrist position to consider men, as a class, to be irreformable or [[rape|rapists]].

[[Barbara Kay]], a Canadian journalist, has been critical of feminist [[Mary P. Koss]]'s discussion of [[rape culture]], describing the notion that "rape represents an extreme behavior but one that is on a continuum with normal male behavior within the culture" as "remarkably misandric".&lt;ref&gt;Barbara Kay, (2014) ‘Rape culture’ fanatics don’t know what a culture is",  National Post,  http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2014/03/08/barbara-kay-rape-culture-fanatics-dont-know-what-a-culture-is/&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2016 article, author and journalist [[Cathy Young]] described a "current cycle of misandry" in feminism.&lt;ref name="Young"&gt;{{cite news |last=Young |first=Cathy |date=2016-07-04 |title=Feminists treat men badly and it's bad for feminism |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2016/06/30/feminists-treat-men-badly-its-bad-for-feminism |newspaper=The Washington Post |access-date=2016-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; This cycle, she explains, includes the use of the term "mansplaining" and other neologisms using "man" as a derogatory prefix.&lt;ref name="Young"/&gt; The term "mansplaining," according to feminist writer [[Rebecca Solnit]], was coined soon after the appearance in 2008 of her essay ''[[Men Explain Things to Me]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Solnit|first1=Rebecca|title=Men Explain Things to Me|date=2014|publisher=Haymarket Books|location=Chicago IL|isbn=978-1-60846-457-9|chapter=1|quote=The term "mansplaining" was coined soon after the piece appeared, and I was sometimes credited with it. In fact, I had nothing to do with its actual creation, though my essay, along with all the men who embodied the idea, apparently inspired it.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research with references to the origins of misandry==
In a study of 488 college students regarding ambivalent [[sexism]] towards men, researchers found that women who did not identify as feminists were more likely to be hostile towards men than self-identified feminists, but also more likely to hold benevolent views towards men.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, K.J., Kanner, M. and Elsayegh, N. (2009), "[http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1471-6402.2009.01491.x/abstract Are Feminists Man Haters? Feminists' and Nonfeminists' Attitudes Toward Men]", ''Psychology of Women Quarterly'', Vol. 33, pp. 216-224&lt;/ref&gt;

In a study of 503 self-identified heterosexual females, social psychologists found an association between [[Attachment theory#Attachment patterns|insecure attachment styles]] and women's hostile sexism towards men.&lt;ref&gt;Joshua Hart, Peter Glick and Rachel E. Dinero, (2013), "She Loves Him, She Loves Him Not: Attachment Style as a Predictor of Women's Ambivalent Sexism Towards Men",  Psychology of Women Quarterly, Vol. 37: 507-517&lt;/ref&gt;

==Asymmetry with misogyny==
Sociologist Allan G. Johnson argues in ''[[The Gender Knot: Unraveling our Patriarchal Legacy]]''  that accusations of man-hating have been used to put down [[Feminism|feminists]] and to shift attention onto men, reinforcing a male-centered culture.&lt;ref name=Johnson107&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3nnxlqbN-IEC&amp;pg=PA107|page=107|title=The Gender Knot: Unraveling Our Patriarchal Legacy|edition=2, revised|last=Johnson|first=Alan G.|publisher=Temple University Press|year=2005|isbn=1592133843}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnson asserts that culture offers no comparable anti-male ideology to misogyny and that "people often confuse men as individuals with men as a dominant and privileged category of people" and that "[given the] reality of women's oppression, male privilege, and men's enforcement of both, it's hardly surprising that ''every'' woman should have moments where she resents or even hates 'men'".

Marc A. Ouellette makes similar arguments in ''International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities'' (2007), writing that "misandry lacks the systemic, transhistoric, institutionalized, and legislated antipathy of misogyny", despite noting some "racialized" misandries and the existence of a "misandric impulse" in popular culture and literature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-first=Michael|editor1-last=Flood|editor1-link=Michael Flood|others=''et al.''|title=International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities|url=https://books.google.com/?id=EUON2SYps-QC&amp;pg=PA442&amp;dq=michael+flood+misandry#v=onepage&amp;q=michael%20flood%20misandry&amp;f=false|date=2007-07-18|publisher=Routledge|location=London; New York|isbn=0-415-33343-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anthropology|Anthropologist]] David D. Gilmore also argues that misogyny is a "near-universal phenomenon" and that there is no male equivalent to misogyny,&lt;ref name="gilmore"&gt;Gilmore, David G. ''Misogyny: The Male Malady''. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2009, pp. 10–13, {{ISBN|978-0-8122-1770-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt; further defending manifestations of perceived misandry as not "hatred of men's traditional male role" and a "culture of machismo". He argues, misandry is "different from the intensely ''ad feminam'' aspect of misogyny that targets women no matter what they believe or do".&lt;ref name="gilmore"/&gt;

==In literature==
===Ancient Greek literature===
Classics professor [[Froma Zeitlin]] of [[Princeton University]] discussed misandry in her article titled "Patterns of Gender in Aeschylean Drama: Seven against Thebes and the Danaid Trilogy".&lt;ref name="Zeitlin" /&gt; She writes:
{{quote|The most significant point of contact, however, between Eteocles and the suppliant Danaids is, in fact, their extreme positions with regard to the opposite sex: the misogyny of Eteocles' outburst against all women of whatever variety (Se. 181-202) has its counterpart in the seeming misandry of the Danaids, who although opposed to their Egyptian cousins in particular (marriage with them is incestuous, they are violent men) often extend their objections to include the race of males as a whole and view their cause as a passionate contest between the sexes (cf. Su. 29, 393, 487, 818, 951).&lt;ref name="Zeitlin"&gt;{{cite journal|first=Froma I.|last=Zeitlin|title=Patterns of Gender in Aeschylean Drama: Seven against Thebes and the Danaid Trilogy|date=April 1, 1990|url=http://repositories.cdlib.org/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1008&amp;context=ucbclassics|format=PDF|accessdate=2007-12-21}} Princeton University, paper given at the Department of Classics, University of California, Berkeley&lt;/ref&gt;}}

=== Shakespeare ===
Literary critic [[Harold Bloom]] argued that even though the word misandry is relatively unheard of in literature it is not hard to find implicit, even explicit, misandry. In reference to the works of [[Shakespeare]] Bloom argued "I cannot think of one instance of misogyny whereas I would argue that misandry is a strong element. Shakespeare makes perfectly clear that women in general have to marry down and that men are narcissistic and not to be trusted and so forth. On the whole, he gives us a darker vision of human males than human females."&lt;ref&gt;Brockman, Elin Schoen. (25 July 1999) "In the Battle Of the Sexes, This Word Is a Weapon", New York Times,  https://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/25/weekinreview/in-the-battle-of-the-sexes-this-word-is-a-weapon.html?module=Search&amp;mabReward=relbias%3Ar&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Charles Dickens ===
In Dickens' ''[[Great Expectations]]'', the character [[Miss Havisham]] is a caricature of a misandrist. Miss Havisham was jilted on her wedding day, and is consumed with rage about this event, and unable to move on in life. She plots and successfully executes what she thinks of as a "revenge" against the male sex, in the person of the protagonist, Pip. However, she then realises that she has only caused Pip, who is blameless, to suffer in turn what she suffered – a broken heart – and repents and begs Pip's forgiveness.{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

=== Modern literature ===
Critic of mainstream feminism [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] has described [[Eve Ensler]]'s play ''[[The Vagina Monologues]]'' as misandric in that "there are no admirable males&amp;nbsp;... the play presents a rogues’ gallery of male brutes, sadists, child-molesters, genital mutilators, gang rapists and hateful little boys" which she finds out of step with the reality that "most men are not brutes. They are not oppressors".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aei.org/files/2008/11/19/20090108_ContemporaryFeminism.pdf What’s Wrong and What’s Right with Contemporary Feminism?, Hamilton College. Retrieved 2014-01-27.] Sommers, Christina Hoff. (2008), {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120302081135/http://www.aei.org/files/2008/11/19/20090108_ContemporaryFeminism.pdf |date=2 March 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Julie M. Thompson, a [[feminist]] author, connects misandry with envy of men, in particular "[[penis envy]]", a term coined by [[Sigmund Freud]] in 1908, in his theory of female sexual development.&lt;ref&gt;
Emphasis added. Julie M. Thompson, ''Mommy Queerest: Contemporary Rhetorics of Lesbian Maternal Identity'', (Amherst: [[University of Massachusetts Press]], 2002).&lt;/ref&gt;  Nancy Kang has discussed "the misandric impulse" in relation to the works of [[Toni Morrison]].&lt;ref&gt;Kang, N. (2003), [http://muse.jhu.edu/login?auth=0&amp;type=summary&amp;url=/journals/callaloo/v026/26.3kang.html "To Love and Be Loved: Considering Black Masculinity and the Misandric Impulse in Toni Morrison's "Beloved"], ''Callaloo'', Vol. 26, No. 3, pp. 836-854.&lt;/ref&gt;

In his book, ''Gender and Judaism: The Transformation of Tradition'', [[Harry Brod]], a Professor of [[Philosophy]] and [[Humanities]] in the Department of Philosophy and [[Religion]] at the [[University of Northern Iowa]], writes:
{{quote|
In the introduction to ''The Great Comic Book Heroes'', Jules Feiffer writes that this is Superman's joke on the rest of us. Clark is Superman's vision of what other men are really like. We are scared, incompetent, and powerless, particularly around women. Though Feiffer took the joke good-naturedly, a more cynical response would see here the Kryptonian's misanthropy, his misandry embodied in Clark and his misogyny in his wish that Lois be enamored of Clark (much like Oberon takes out hostility toward Titania by having her fall in love with an ass in Shakespeare's ''Midsummer-Night's Dream'').|&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=SH8r3ntJG8AC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA279 ''Gender and Judaism: The Transformation of Tradition]'', Harry Brod&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==See also==
* [[Airline seating sex discrimination controversy]]
* ''[[Are All Men Pedophiles?]]''
* [[Boys are stupid, throw rocks at them! controversy]]
* [[Circumcision controversies]]
* [[Female chauvinism]]
* [[Feminazi]]
* [[Male genital mutilation]]
* [[Men's rights]]
* [[Misanthropy]]
* [[Rape]]
* [[Separatist feminism]]
* [[Hysteria]]
* [[Social justice warrior|Social Justice Warrior]]s
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Testosterone poisoning]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* [[David Benatar|Benatar, D.]] (2012), ''The Second Sexism: Discrimination Against Men and Boys'', Malden; Wiley-Blackwell.
* [[Bell hooks|hooks, bell]]., (2005), ''The Will To Change: Men, Masculinity and Love'', New York; Washington Square Press. 
*{{cite book|title=[[Who Stole Feminism? How Women Have Betrayed Women]]|last=Sommers|first=Christina Hoff|authorlink=Christina Hoff Sommers|year=1995|origyear=First published 1994|publisher= [[Simon &amp; Schuster]]|isbn=0-684-80156-6}}
* {{cite book|title=The Myth of Male Power: Why Men Are the Disposable Sex|last=Farrell|first=Warren|authorlink=Warren Farrell|year=2001|origyear= First published 1993|publisher=[[Berkley Books|Berkley Trade]]|location=|isbn=0-425-18144-8}}
* {{cite book|title=Misogyny, Misandry, and Misanthropy|last=Ferguson|first=Frances|authorlink=Frances Ferguson|last2=Bloch|first2=R. Howard|authorlink2=R. Howard Bloch|year=1989|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|isbn=0-520-06546-8}}
* {{cite book|title=My Enemy, My Love: Man-Hating and Ambivalence in Women's Lives|last=Levine|first=Judith|authorlink=Judith Levine|year=1992|publisher=Da Capo Press|isbn=1-56025-568-4}}
*MacNamara, J.R. (2006), ''Media and Male Identity: The Making and Remaking of Men'', Palgrave Macmillan; New York.
* {{cite book|last=McElroy|first=Wendy|title=Sexual Correctness: The Gender-Feminist Attack on Women|series=Harper Paperbacks|year=2001|publisher=McFarland &amp; Company|location=New York|isbn=0-7864-1144-9|ref=harv}}
* Synnott, Anthony (2009), ''Re-Thinking Men: Heroes, Villains and Victims'', Ashgate Publishing. {{ISBN|1409491951}}.
*Smith, William A., Yosso, Tara J., Solorzano, Daniel G. (2007), "Racial Primes and Black Misandry on Historically White Campuses: Toward Critical Race Accountability in Educational Administration", ''Educational Administration Quarterly'', vol. 43 no. 5, pp.&amp;nbsp;559–585.  
*Rosenblum, Darren (2010), "[http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=7282784 Beyond Victimisation and Misandry]", ''International Journal of Law in Context'', Vol. 6, No. 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;114–116.
* {{cite book|last=Nathanson|first=Paul|author-link=Paul Nathanson|last2=Young|first2=Katherine R.|author2-link=Katherine K. Young|title=Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture|series=Harper Paperbacks|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JGocoMfjt_oC|year=2001|publisher=[[McGill-Queen's University Press]]|place=Montreal|isbn=0-7735-3099-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Nathanson|first=Paul|author-link=Paul Nathanson|last2=Young|first2=Katherine R.|author2-link=Katherine K. Young|title=Legalizing Misandry: From Public Shame to Systemic Discrimination Against Men|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cqKxhhu55SMC|year=2006|publisher=[[McGill-Queen's University Press]]|place=Montreal|isbn=0-7735-2862-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author1=Katherine K. Young|author2=Paul Nathanson|title=Sanctifying Misandry: Goddess Ideology and the Fall of Man|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y8rI7snipZcC|year=2010|publisher=MQUP|isbn=978-0-7735-8544-7}}
*Nathanson, Paul, Young, Katherine  K., (2012), "[http://newmalestudies.com/OJS/index.php/nms/article/viewFile/14/13 Misandry and Emptiness: Masculine Identity in a Toxic Cultural Environment]",  ''New Male Studies: An International Journal'', Vol. 1, No. 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;4–18.
* {{cite book|title=The Revolt of the Primitive: An Inquiry into the Roots of Political Correctness|last=Schwartz|first=Howard|edition=Revised|year=2003|publisher=[[Transaction Publishers]]|isbn=0-7658-0537-5}}
* Nathanson, Paul and Katherine Young. (2009), "[http://mensstudies.metapress.com/content/w071583278134g61/ Coming of Age As a Villain: What Every Boy Needs to Know in A Misandric World]",  ''Thymos: Journal of Boyhood Studies'',  Vol. 3, p.&amp;nbsp;2, pp.&amp;nbsp;155–177.
*[[Esther Vilar|Vilar, Esther]]. ''[[The Manipulated Man]]''. New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 1972.

==External links==
* {{cite journal|last=Bailée|first=Susan|year=2001|title=Misandry in the Classroom|journal=The Hudson Review|volume=54|issue=1|pages=148–54|quote=My rough-and-tumble first grader, Mark, came home from school yesterday and nonchalantly told me a story about his day that set me shivering|doi=10.2307/3852834|jstor=3852834|publisher=The Hudson Review, Inc.|last2=Sommers|first2=Christina Hoff|ref=harv}}
* {{cite web|url=http://adonismirror.com/10152006_leader_misandry_and_misanthropy.htm|title=Misandry: From the Dictionary of Fools|accessdate=2007-12-28|last=Leader|first=Richard|year=2007|work=Adonis Mirror}} article critical of the use of the term
* {{cite web|url=http://www.backlash.com/content/gender/1996/4-apr96/wilson04.html|title=Androphobia: The only respectable bigotry|accessdate=2007-12-28|last=Wilson|first=Robert Anton|authorlink=Robert Anton Wilson|date=April 1996|work=The Backlash!|publisher=Shameless Men Press}}
*[https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2001/aug/14/edinburghfestival2001.edinburghbookfestival2001 Lay off men, Lessing tells feminists.]

{{Sexual abuse}}
{{Sexual identities}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}

[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Crimes against men]]
[[Category:Misandry| ]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender-related prejudices]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Violence against men]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>