<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231127165744|1187125426" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20778" pageid="20778" ns="0" title="Misandry"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-11-27T16:59:42Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Prejudice against, or hatred of, men}}
{{pp-protected|reason=Persistent [[WP:Disruptive editing|disruptive editing]] despite multiple temporary protections. Enough.|small=yes}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expand-social=yes}}
{{Masculism sidebar|topics}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2020}}
'''Misandry''' ({{IPAc-en|m|ɪ|s|ˈ|æ|n|d|r|i}}) is the hatred of, contempt for, or prejudice against [[men]] or boys.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/234242?redirectedFrom=Misandry#eid "Misandry"] at Oxford English Dictionary Online (ODO), Third Edition, June 2002. Accessed through library subscription on 25 July 2014. Earliest recorded use: 1885. ''Blackwood's Edinb. Mag'', Sept. 289/1 No man whom she cared for had ever proposed to marry her. She could not account for it, and it was a growing source of bitterness, of misogyny as well as misandry.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/misandry "Misandry"] at [[Merriam-Webster#Services|Merriam-Webster online]] ("First Known Use: circa 1909")&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Men's rights movement|Men's rights activists]] (MRAs) and other [[masculinist]] groups have characterized modern laws concerning [[divorce]], [[domestic violence]], [[conscription]], [[circumcision]] (known as [[male genital mutilation]] by opponents), and treatment of [[rape of males|male rape victims]] as examples of institutional misandry.

In the [[Internet Age]], users posting on [[manosphere]] internet forums such as [[4chan]] and [[Reddit|subreddits]] addressing men's rights activism have claimed that misandry is widespread, established in the preferential treatment of women, and shown by [[discrimination against men]].&lt;ref name="Ouellette 2007"&gt;{{cite book |last=Ouellette |first=Marc |title=International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities |date=2007 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1-1343-1707-3 |editor1=Flood, Michael |editor1-link=Michael Flood |pages=442–443 |chapter=Misandry |display-editors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Riggio 2020"&gt;{{cite book |last=Riggio |first=Heidi R. |title=Sex and Gender: A Biopsychological Approach |date=2020 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1-000-06630-2 |chapter=Online Sexism and Anti-Feminism Movements}}&lt;/ref&gt; This viewpoint is denied by most [[sociologists]], [[anthropologists]] and scholars of [[gender studies]], who counter that misandry is not a cultural institution, nor equivalent in scope to [[misogyny]], which is far more deeply rooted in society, and more severe in its consequences.&lt;ref name="Gilmore p10"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Ouellette 2007"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Misogyny, Misandry, and Misanthropy |last1=Ferguson |first1=Frances |author-link=Frances Ferguson |last2=Bloch |first2=R. Howard |author-link2=R. Howard Bloch |year=1989 |publisher=University of California Press |page=7 |isbn=978-0-520-06546-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Many scholars criticize MRAs for promoting a [[false equivalence]] between misandry and misogyny,&lt;ref name="Kimmel 2013"/&gt;{{Rp|page=132}}&lt;ref name="Marwick 2018"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Ging 2018"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Ging |first1=Debbie |last2=Siapera |first2=Eugenia |date=July 2018 |title=Online Misogyny: Introduction |pages=515–524 |journal=Feminist Media Studies |doi=10.1080/14680777.2018.1447345 |volume=18 |s2cid=149613969 |url=http://doras.dcu.ie/26989/|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; arguing that modern activism around misandry represents an [[antifeminist]] backlash, promoted by marginalized men.&lt;ref name="Marwick 2018"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Online Misogyny as Hate Crime: A Challenge for Legal Regulation? |last1=Barker |first1=Kim |last2=Jurasz |first2=Olga |date=2018 |publisher=Routledge |page=4 |isbn=978-1-138-59037-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Transforming Scholarship: Why Women's and Gender Studies Students Are Changing Themselves and the World |last1=Berger |first1=Michele Tracy |last2=Radeloff |first2=Cheryl |date=2014 |pages=128–129 |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis |isbn=978-1-135-04519-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Sugiura |first=Lisa |date=2021 |title=The Incel Rebellion: The Rise of the Manosphere and the Virtual War Against Women |publisher=Emerald Group |page=133 |isbn=978-1-83982-256-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor1=Karen Lumsden |editor2=Emily Hamer |title=Online Othering: Exploring Digital Violence and Discrimination on the Web |date=2019 |publisher=Springer |last1=Lumsden |first1=Karen |chapter='I Want to Kill You in Front of Your Children' Is Not a Threat. It's an Expression of Desire': Discourses of Online Abuse, Trolling and Violence on r/MensRights |pages=91–120 |isbn=978-3-030-12633-9 |series=Palgrave Studies in Cybercrime and Cybersecurity}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
Misandry is formed from the Greek ''misos'' (μῖσος, "hatred") and ''anēr'', ''andros'' (ἀνήρ, gen. ἀνδρός; "man").&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Dictionaries http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/misandry {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130921054052/http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/misandry |date=21 September 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; "Misandrous" or "misandrist" can be used as adjectival forms of the word.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Definition of "misandry" |url=https://www.dictionary.com/browse/misandry |access-date=4 November 2018 |website=Dictionary.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Use of the word can be found as far back as the 19th century, including an 1871 use in ''[[The Spectator]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;Review of novel ''Blanche Seymour'', ''[[The Spectator]]'', London, 1 April 1871, p. 389. "We cannot, indeed, term her an absolute misandrist, as she fully admits the possibility, in most cases at least, of the reclamation of men from their naturally vicious and selfish state, though at the cost of so much trouble and vexation of spirit to women, that it is not quite clear whether she does not regard their existence as at best a mitigated evil".&lt;/ref&gt; It appeared in ''[[Merriam-Webster's Collegiate Dictionary]]'' (11th ed.) in 1952. Translation of the French {{lang|fr|misandrie}} to the German {{lang|de|Männerhass}} (Hatred of Men)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://en.pons.com/translate/german-english/M%C3%A4nnerha%C3%9F |title=Translations for Männerhaß in the German–English dictionary |publisher=PONS-Verlag |location=Stuttgart |work=Pons Dictionary German to English |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150506132922/http://en.pons.com/translate/german-english/M%C3%A4nnerha%C3%9F |archive-date=6 May 2015 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; is recorded in 1803.&lt;ref name="Krünitz 1803"&gt;{{cite book |title=Oekonomische Encyklopädie oder allgemeines System der Staats-, Stadt-, Haus- u. Landwirthschaft: in alphabetischer Ordnung. Von Lebens-Art bis Ledecz : Nebst einer einzigen Fig. Friedrich's des Einzigen, u. 3 Karten |author=Johann Georg Krünitz |publisher=Pauli |year=1803 |volume=90 |page=461}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A term with a similar but distinct meaning is ''androphobia'', which describes a fear, but not necessarily hatred, of men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/terms/misandry.htm |title=Misandry}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anthropology|Anthropologist]] David D. Gilmore coined a similar term—"viriphobia"—to show that misandry typically targets the virile male ''[[machismo]]'', "the obnoxious manly {{em|pose}}", along with the oppressive male roles of patriarchy. Gilmore says that misandry is not the hatred of men as men; this kind of loathing is present only in misogyny which is the hatred of women as women.&lt;ref name="Gilmore p10"/&gt;

==Background==
The term ''misandry'' started to be used in [[Men's rights movement|men's rights]] literature and academic literature on structural prejudice in the early 1980s. It has been used on the internet such as [[usenet]], and blogs since at least 1989.&lt;ref name="Marwick 2018" /&gt;{{Rp|page=9}} Usage of the term ''misandry'' in the [[internet age]] is an outgrowth of [[antifeminism]] and [[misogyny]].&lt;ref name="Marwick 2018" /&gt;{{Rp|pages=543–559}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/rethinking-men/201010/why-some-people-have-issues-men-misandry |title=Why Some People Have Issues With Men: Misandry |date=2010-10-10 |last=Synnott |first=Anthony}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source needed|date=August 2023|reason=Blog source, no meaningful editorial oversight}} The term is commonly used in the [[manosphere]],&lt;ref name="Marwick 2018" /&gt;{{Rp|page=4}} such as on [[men's rights movement|men's rights]] discussion forums on websites such as [[4chan]] and [[reddit]], to counter feminist accusations of misogyny.&lt;ref name="Ging 2018"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Riggio 2020"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Hodapp p4"&gt;{{cite book |title=Men's Rights, Gender, and Social Media |last=Hodapp |first=Christa |date=2017 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |pages=4–5 |isbn=978-1-4985-2617-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The critique and parody of the concept of misandry by feminist bloggers was reported on in periodicals such as ''[[The Guardian]]'', ''[[Slate (magazine)|Slate]]'' and ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]''&lt;ref name="Marwick 2018" /&gt;{{Rp|page=11}}&lt;ref name="Hess 2014"/&gt; in 2014.

==Overview==
[[Men's rights movement|Men's rights activists]] and other [[masculinist]] groups have criticized modern laws concerning [[divorce]], [[domestic violence]], the draft, circumcision (known as genital mutilation by opponents), and treatment of [[rape of males|male rape victims]] as examples of institutional misandry.{{r|Ouellette 2007}}&lt;ref&gt;Schmitz R. M., Kazyak E. Masculinities in cyberspace: An analysis of portrayals of manhood in men’s rights activist websites // Social Sciences. – 2016. – V. 5. – №. 2. – p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; The word ''misandry'' forms a core part of the vocabulary of [[manosphere]] online spaces. The use of this term in the manosphere provides justification for harassment of people espousing feminist ideas by online groups, citing [[Gamergate (harassment campaign)|Gamergate]] as an example.&lt;ref name="Marwick 2018"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Marwick |first1=Alice E. |last2=Caplan |first2=Robyn |date=March 2018 |title=Drinking male tears: language, the manosphere, and networked harassment |journal=Feminist Media Studies |edition=Online Misogyny |pages=543–559 |doi=10.1080/14680777.2018.1450568 |volume=18 |issue=4 |s2cid=149246142}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|page=2}} Arguments based on the concept of misandry are used by the [[men's rights movement]] to counter feminist accusations of misogyny.{{r|Hodapp p4}}

Proposed examples of misandry in popular culture include frequent portrayals of men as absent, insensitive, or abusive, as well as a legal process that discriminates against men in divorce proceedings, or in cases of domestic or sexual [[Violence against men|violence where the victim is a man]].&lt;ref name="Farrell 2001"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Farrell |first1=Warren |title=The Myth of Male Power: Why Men are the Disposable Sex |date=2001 |publisher=Berkley Books |location=New York |isbn=978-0-425-18144-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Unbalanced opinion|date=August 2023|reason=Farrell is a men's rights advocate, not a scholar of gender}} Other examples include social problems that lead to men's [[Life expectancy#Sex differences|shorter lifespans]], higher suicide rates, requirements to participate in [[Conscription|military drafts]], and lack of tax benefits afforded to widowers compared to widows.&lt;ref name="Ouellette 2007" /&gt; In a 2016 ''Washington Post'' article, [[Cathy Young]] wrote that terms using "man" as a derogatory prefix, such as [[mansplaining]], [[manspreading]], and [[manterrupting]], are part of a "current cycle of misandry".&lt;ref name="Young 2016"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Young |first1=Cathy |date=30 June 2016 |title=Feminists treat men badly. It's bad for feminism |newspaper=The Washington Post |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2016/06/30/feminists-treat-men-badly-its-bad-for-feminism |quote=Whatever the reasons for the current cycle of misandry — yes, that’s a word, derided but also adopted for ironic use by many feminists — its existence is quite real. Consider, for example, the number of neologisms that use “man” as a derogatory prefix and that have entered everyday media language: 'mansplaining,' 'manspreading' and 'manterrupting.' |url-access=limited}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Undue weight inline|date=August 2023|reason=Op-eds are WP:PRIMARY sources}}

Religious studies professors Paul Nathanson and [[Katherine K. Young|Katherine Young]] examined what they called the institutionalization of misandry in the public sphere in their 2001 three-book series ''Beyond the Fall of Man'', which refers to misandry as a "form of prejudice and discrimination that has become institutionalized in North American society", writing, "The same problem that long prevented mutual respect between Jews and Christians, the teaching of contempt, now prevents mutual respect between men and women."{{sfn|Nathanson|Young|2001|page=6}}{{Unbalanced opinion|date=August 2023|reason=Nathanson &amp; Young have been heavily criticized in more mainstream literature}}

[[Warren Farrell]] is a men's rights activist trained as a [[political scientist]]. Farrell argues that men's rights publications are censored online and it is difficult to publish books on the topic compared to feminist issues.&lt;ref name="Farrell 2008"&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Farrell |first1=Warren |last2=Sterba |first2=James P. |title=Does Feminism Discriminate Against Men?: A Debate |date=2008 |publisher=Oxford University Press |others=With Steven Svoboda |isbn=978-0-19-531282-9 |url=https://archive.org/details/doesfeminismdisc0000farr/page/n4/mode/1up?view=theater |url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|page=91}} He argues that men are often [[Social rejection|socially rejected]] for expressing feelings, while at the same time being blamed for not doing so.&lt;ref name="Farrell 2008" /&gt;{{Rp|page=90}} He argues that there is gender bias, reinforced by feminism, of who is considered to deserve protection and who is held accountable for problems with women tending to be seen as both unaccountable while needing protection, arguing that this needs to change to remove gender roles.&lt;ref name="Farrell 2008" /&gt;{{Rp|page=104}} In response, philosopher [[James P. Sterba]] argues that women may have been excluded from dangerous professions such as the military to protect male status, citing the example of [[Eritrean–Ethiopian War]] where he argues women gained status in society by virtue of fighting in the war and contrasting it with Israel where he says that women's exclusion from military [[national service]] and the military in general diminishes their status and as a result their influence in politics.&lt;ref name="Farrell 2008" /&gt;{{Rp|page=139}}

Sociologist [[Michael Kimmel]] states that claiming an equivalence between misogyny and misandry is "utterly tendentious".&lt;ref name="Glick 2016"/&gt;
Marc A. Ouellette argues in ''International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities'' that "misandry lacks the systemic, transhistoric, institutionalized, and legislated antipathy of misogyny"; in his view, assuming a parallel between misogyny and misandry overly simplifies relations of gender and power.&lt;ref name="Ouellette 2007"/&gt;
David Gilmore argues that misogyny is a "near-universal phenomenon" and that there is no male equivalent to misogyny.&lt;ref name="Gilmore p10"&gt;{{cite book |last=Gilmore |first=David G. |title=Misogyny: The Male Malady |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press |year=2009 |pages=10–13 |isbn=978-0-8122-1770-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; He argues that misandry is "different from the intensely ''ad feminam'' aspect of misogyny that targets women no matter what they believe or do".&lt;ref name="Gilmore p10"/&gt;

== Racialization ==
{{Further|Gendered racism}}
Misandry can be [[Racialization|racialized]].&lt;ref name="Ouellette 2007"/&gt; According to some researchers in [[Black male studies]] such as [[Tommy J. Curry]], Black men and boys face anti-Black misandry.&lt;ref&gt;Bryan N. Remembering Tamir Rice and other Black boy victims: Imagining Black playcrit literacies inside and outside urban literacy education // Urban Education. — 2021. — V. 56. — №. 5. — pp. 744—771.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Curry T. J. Killing boogeymen: Phallicism and the misandric mischaracterizations of Black males in theory // Res Philosophica. — 2018 — pp. 13–21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Curry T. J., Curry G. Taking it to the people: Translating empirical findings about Black men and Black families through a Black public philosophy // Dewey Studies. — 2018. — V. 2. — №. 1. — pp. 42–71.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnson T. H. Is Anti-Black Misandry the New Racism? // Journal of Black Sexuality and Relationships. – 2022. – V. 8. – №. 4. – pp. 77–107.&lt;/ref&gt; E. C. Krell, a gender researcher, uses the term racialized transmisandry describing the experience of Black transmasculine people.&lt;ref&gt;Krell E. C. Is transmisogyny killing trans women of color? Black trans feminisms and the exigencies of white femininity // Transgender Studies Quarterly. – 2017. – V. 4. – №. 2. – pp. 226–242.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Martino W., Omercajic K. A trans pedagogy of refusal: interrogating cisgenderism, the limits of antinormativity and trans necropolitics // Pedagogy, Culture &amp; Society. – 2021. – V. 29. – №. 5. – pp. 679–694&lt;/ref&gt;

==Psychological studies==
{{More science citations needed|section|date=August 2023}}

Glick and Fiske developed [[Psychometrics|psychometric constructs]] to measure the attitudes of individuals towards men in their ''Ambivalence toward Men Inventory, AMI'', which includes a factor ''Hostility toward Men.'' These metrics were based on a small group discussion with women which identified factors, these number of questions were then reduced using statistical methods. ''Hostility toward Men'' was split into three factors: ''Resentment of Paternalism'', the belief men supported male power, ''Compensatory Gender Differentiation'', the belief that men were supported by women and ''Heterosexual Hostility'', which looked at beliefs that men were likely to engage in hostile actions.&lt;ref name="Glick 2016"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Glick |first1=Peter |last2=Fiske |first2=Susan T. |date=2016-06-23 |title=The Ambivalence Toward Men Inventory: Differentiating Hostile and Benevolent Beliefs About Men |journal=Psychology of Women Quarterly |language=en |doi=10.1111/j.1471-6402.1999.tb00379.x |s2cid=145242896 |issn=1471-6402 |volume=23 |pages=519–536}}&lt;/ref&gt; The combined construct, Hostility toward Men, was found to be inversely correlated with measures of gender equality when comparing difference countries&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Glick |display-authors=etal |first=P |date=May 2004 |title=Bad but Bold: Ambivalent Attitudes Toward Men Predict Gender Inequality in 16 Nations |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=86 |issue=5 |pages=713–728 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.86.5.713 |pmid=15161396}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in a study with university students, self-describing feminists were found to have a lower score.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Anderson |first1=Kristin J. |last2=Kanner |first2=Melinda |last3=Elsayegh |first3=Nisreen |date=2009-06-01 |title=Are Feminists man Haters? Feminists' and Nonfeminists' Attitudes Toward Men |journal=Psychology of Women Quarterly |volume=33 |issue=2 |pages=216–224 |language=en |doi=10.1111/j.1471-6402.2009.01491.x |s2cid=144704304 |issn=1471-6402}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Implicit Association Tests find a reflexive distaste for men and preference for women on the part of both sexes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Connor |display-authors=etal |first=Paul |date=2023 |title=Intersectional implicit bias: Evidence for asymmetrically compounding bias and the predominance of target gender. |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=124 |issue=1 |pages=22–48 |doi=10.1037/pspa0000314 |pmid=35587425 |s2cid=248851337 |doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In literature==
===Ancient Greek literature===

Classics professor [[Froma Zeitlin]] of [[Princeton University]] discussed misandry in her article titled "Patterns of Gender in Aeschylean Drama: Seven against Thebes and the Danaid Trilogy".&lt;ref name="Zeitlin 1990" /&gt; She writes:
{{blockquote|The most significant point of contact, however, between Eteocles and the suppliant Danaids is, in fact, their extreme positions with regard to the opposite sex: the misogyny of Eteocles' outburst against all women of whatever variety has its counterpart in the seeming misandry of the Danaids, who although opposed to their Egyptian cousins in particular (marriage with them is incestuous, they are violent men) often extend their objections to include the race of males as a whole and view their cause as a passionate contest between the sexes.&lt;ref name="Zeitlin 1990"&gt;{{cite journal |first=Froma I. |last=Zeitlin |author-link=Froma Zeitlin |title=Patterns of Gender in Aeschylean Drama: Seven against Thebes and the Danaid Trilogy |date=1 April 1990 |journal=Cabinet of the Muses – Rosenmeyer Festschrift |url=https://escholarship.org/uc/item/2j81390f}} Princeton University, paper given at the Department of Classics, University of California, Berkeley&lt;/ref&gt;}}

=== Shakespeare ===

Literary critic [[Harold Bloom]] argued that even though the word misandry is relatively unheard of in literature, it is not hard to find implicit, even explicit, misandry. In reference to the works of [[Shakespeare]], Bloom argued:&lt;ref&gt;Brockman, Elin Schoen. (25 July 1999) "In the Battle of the Sexes, This Word Is a Weapon", New York Times,  https://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/25/weekinreview/in-the-battle-of-the-sexes-this-word-is-a-weapon.html?module=Search&amp;mabReward=relbias%3Ar&lt;/ref&gt; {{blockquote|I cannot think of one instance of misogyny whereas I would argue that misandry is a strong element. Shakespeare makes perfectly clear that women in general have to marry down and that men are narcissistic and not to be trusted and so forth. On the whole, he gives us a darker vision of human males than human females.}}

=== Modern literature ===

Sociologist Anthony Synnott argues that there is a tendency in literature to represent men as villains and women as victims and argues that there is a market for "anti-male" novels with no corresponding "anti-female" market, citing ''[[The Women's Room]]'', by [[Marilyn French]], and ''[[The Color Purple]]'', by [[Alice Walker]]. He gives examples of comparisons of men to Nazi prison guards as a common theme in literature.&lt;ref name="Synnott 2016"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Synnott |first=Anthony |title=Re-Thinking Men: Heroes, Villains and Victims |date=2016 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1-317-06393-3 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|156}}

Racialized misandry occurs in both "high" and "low" culture and literature. For instance, [[African-American]] men have often been disparagingly portrayed as either infantile or as eroticized and hyper-masculine, depending on prevailing cultural stereotypes.{{r|Ouellette 2007}}

Julie M. Thompson, a [[feminist]] author, connects misandry with envy of men, in particular "[[penis envy]]", a term coined by [[Sigmund Freud]] in 1908, in his theory of female sexual development.&lt;ref&gt;
Emphasis added. {{cite book |first=Julie M. |last=Thompson |title=Mommy Queerest: Contemporary Rhetorics of Lesbian Maternal Identity |publisher=[[University of Massachusetts Press]] |date=2002 |isbn=978-1-55849-355-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nancy Kang has discussed "the misandric impulse" in relation to the works of [[Toni Morrison]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=N. |last=Kang |title=To Love and Be Loved: Considering Black Masculinity and the Misandric Impulse in Toni Morrison's "Beloved" |journal=Callaloo |volume=26 |issue=3 |pages=836–854 |date=2003 |doi=10.1353/cal.2003.0092 |jstor=3300729 |s2cid=143786756 |url=http://muse.jhu.edu/login?auth=0&amp;type=summary&amp;url=/journals/callaloo/v026/26.3kang.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his book, ''Gender and Judaism: The Transformation of Tradition'', [[Harry Brod]], a Professor of Philosophy and Humanities in the Department of Philosophy and Religion at the [[University of Northern Iowa]], writes:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Harry |last=Brod |chapter=19. Of Mice and Supermen: Images of Jewish Masculinity |chapter-url={{GBurl|SH8r3ntJG8AC |p=279}} |title=Gender and Judaism: The Transformation of Tradition |publisher=NYU Press |editor-first=Tamar |editor-last=Rudavsky |date=1995 |isbn=978-0-8147-7453-3 |pages=279–294}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{blockquote|In the introduction to ''The Great Comic Book Heroes'', Jules Feiffer writes that this is Superman's joke on the rest of us. Clark is Superman's vision of what other men are really like. We are scared, incompetent, and powerless, particularly around women. Though Feiffer took the joke good-naturedly, a more cynical response would see here the Kryptonian's misanthropy, his misandry embodied in Clark and his misogyny in his wish that Lois be enamored of Clark (much like Oberon takes out hostility toward Titania by having her fall in love with an ass in Shakespeare's ''Midsummer-Night's Dream'').}}

In 2020, the explicitly misandric essay ''[[Moi, les hommes, je les déteste]]'' (''I Hate Men'') by the French writer Pauline Harmange caused controversy in France after a government official threatened its publisher with criminal prosecution.&lt;ref name="Flood 2020"&gt;{{Cite news |last=Flood |first=Alison |date=2020-09-08 |title=French book I Hate Men sees sales boom after government adviser calls for ban |language=en-GB |work=The Guardian |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2020/sep/08/french-book-i-hate-men-sees-sales-boom-after-government-adviser-calls-for-ban-pauline-harmange |access-date=2020-09-10 |issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In feminism==
[[File:Male_tears_embroidery_02.jpg|alt=&lt;nowiki&gt;Embroidery of Male tears&lt;/nowiki&gt;|thumb|250x250px|Entrepreneurs on [[Etsy]] sold embroidery parodying the concept of misandry.&lt;ref name="Hess 2014"&gt;{{Cite web |last=Hess |first=Amanda |date=2014-08-08 |title=The Rise of the Ironic Man-Hater |url=https://slate.com/human-interest/2014/08/ironic-misandry-why-feminists-joke-about-drinking-male-tears-and-banning-all-men.html |access-date=2022-06-05 |website=Slate Magazine |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The role of misandry in [[feminism]] is controversial and has been debated both within and outside feminist movements. [[antifeminism|Opponents of feminism]] often argue that feminism is misandristic; citing examples such as opposition to shared parenting by NOW, or opposition to equal rape and domestic violence laws. The validity of these perceptions and of the concept has been claimed as promoting a [[false equivalence]] between misandry and misogyny.&lt;ref name="Kimmel 2013" /&gt; [[Radical feminism]] has often been associated with misandry in the public consciousness. However, radical feminist arguments have also been misinterpreted, and individual radical feminists such as [[Valerie Solanas]], best known for her attempted murder of [[Andy Warhol]] in 1968, have historically had a higher profile in popular culture than within feminist scholarship.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Pilcher |first1=Jane |title=50 Key Concepts in Gender Studies |last2=Whelehan |first2=Imelda |date=2004-03-18 |publisher=SAGE |isbn=978-1-4129-3207-3 |pages=67 |language=en |author-link=Jane Pilcher}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Payton |first=Joanne |date=2012 |title=Book Review: Anthony Synnott Re-thinking Men: Heroes, Villains and Victims |journal=Sociology |volume=46 |issue=4 |pages=767–8 |doi=10.1177/0038038512444951 |s2cid=146967261 |issn=0038-0385}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historian [[Alice Echols]], in her 1989 book ''Daring To Be Bad: Radical Feminism in America, 1967–1975'', argued that Valerie Solanas displayed an extreme level of misandry in her tract the ''[[SCUM Manifesto]]'', but wrote that it was not typical for radical feminists of the time. Echols stated: "Solanas's unabashed misandry—especially her belief in men's biological inferiority—her endorsement of relationships between 'independent women,' and her dismissal of sex as 'the refuge of the mindless' contravened the sort of radical feminism which prevailed in most women's groups across the country."&lt;ref name="Echols p104"&gt;{{cite book |last=Echols |first=Nicole |title=Daring to Be Bad: Radical Feminism in America, 1967–1975 |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |date=1989 |pages=[[iarchive:daringtobebadrad0000echo/page/104|104]]–5 |isbn=978-0-8166-1786-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Echols also claims that, after her attempted murder, Solanas' ''SCUM Manifesto'' became more popular within radical feminism; but not all radical feminists shared her beliefs.&lt;ref name="Echols p104" /&gt; For example, radical feminist [[Andrea Dworkin]] criticized the [[biological determinist]] strand in radical feminism that, in 1977, she found "with increasing frequency in feminist circles" which echoed the views of Valerie Solanas that males are biologically inferior to women and violent by nature, requiring a [[gendercide]] to allow for the emergence of a "new ''Übermensch'' Womon".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Dworkin |first=Andrea |author-link=Andrea Dworkin |date=Summer 1978 |title=Biological Superiority: The World's Most Dangerous and Deadly Idea |url=http://heresiesfilmproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/heresies6.pdf |journal=Heresies: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics |series=No. 2 |volume=2 |issue=#6 |page=46 |issn=0146-3411 |access-date=2015-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Melinda Kanner and Kristin J. Anderson argue that "man-hater feminist" represents the popular antifeminist myth which has no any scientific evidences, and it's rather the antifeminists who perhaps hate men.&lt;ref&gt;Kanner M., Anderson K. J. The myth of the man-hating feminist // Feminism and women’s rights worldwide. – 2010. – V. 1. – P. 1-25.&lt;/ref&gt;

The author [[bell hooks]] conceptualized the issue of "man hating" during the early period of women's liberation as a reaction to patriarchal oppression and women who had bad experiences with men in non-feminist social movements. She also criticized separatist strands of feminism as "reactionary" for promoting the notion that men are inherently immoral, inferior, and unable to help end sexist oppression or benefit from feminism.&lt;ref name="hooks 1984"&gt;{{cite book |first=bell |last=hooks |title=Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center |publisher=South End Press |location=Boston |date=1984 |isbn=978-0-89608-222-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=bell |last=hooks |title=The Will To Change: Men, Masculinity and Love |publisher=Washington Square Press |location=New York |date=2005 |isbn=978-0-7434-5608-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Feminism is For Everybody'', hooks laments the fact that feminists who critiqued anti-male bias in the early women's movement never gained mainstream media attention and that "our theoretical work critiquing the demonization of men as the enemy did not change the perspective of women who were anti-male." She has theorized previously that this demonization led to an unnecessary rift between the [[Men's movement]] and the [[Women's movement]].&lt;ref name="hooks 1984"/&gt;

Sociologist Anthony Synnott argues that certain forms of [[feminism]] present misandristic view of gender. He argues that men are presented as having power over others regardless of the actual power they possess&lt;ref name="Synnott 2016" /&gt;{{Rp|161}} and that some feminists define the experience of being male inaccurately through writing on [[masculinity]]. He further argues that some forms of feminism create an [[In-group and out-group|in-group]] of women, simplifies the nuances of gender issues,  demonizes those who are not feminists and legimitizes victimization by way of retributive justice.&lt;ref name="Synnott 2016" /&gt;{{Rp|162}}
Reviewing Synnott, Roman Kuhar argues that Synnott might not accurately represent the views of feminism, commenting that "whether it re-thinks men in a manner in which men have not been thought of in feminist theory, is another question."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Kuhar |first=Roman |title=Re-Thinking Men: Heroes, Villains and Victims |url=https://doi.org/10.1177/0094306110391764ccc |journal=Contemporary Sociology: A Journal of Reviews |year=2011 |volume=40 |issue=1 |pages=95–97 |doi=10.1177/0094306110391764ccc |s2cid=144037921 |issn=0094-3061}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Religious scholars Paul Nathanson and [[Katherine K. Young]] argued that "ideological feminism" as opposed to "egalitarian feminism" has imposed misandry on culture.{{sfn|Nathanson|Young|2001|p=xiv|ps=: "[ideological feminism,] one form of feminism—one that has had a great deal of influence, whether directly or indirectly, on both popular culture and elite culture—is profoundly misandric"}}{{Third-party inline|date=August 2023}} Their 2001 book, ''Spreading Misandry'', analyzed "pop cultural artifacts and productions from the 1990s" from movies to greeting cards for what they considered to be pervasive messages of hatred toward men.{{sfn|Nathanson|Young|2001|page=ix}} ''Legalizing Misandry'' (2005), the second in the series, gave similar attention to laws in North America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Paul |last1=Nathanson |first2=Katherine K. |last2=Young |author-link2=Katherine K. Young |title=Legalizing Misandry: From Public Shame to Systemic Discrimination Against Men |year=2006 |publisher=McGill-Queen's Press – MQUP |isbn=978-0-7735-5999-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Third-party inline|date=August 2023}}
The methodology used by Nathanson and Young to research misandry has been criticized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.mcgilldaily.com/2010/01/mcgill_profs_to_testify_against_equal_marriage/ |title=McGill profs to testify against equal marriage |last=Jabir |first=Humera |date=January 14, 2010 |newspaper=[[The McGill Daily]] |access-date=March 7, 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the book ''[[Angry White Men]]'', [[Michael Kimmel]] argues that much of the misandry identified by Nathanson and Young is actually criticizing [[patriarchy]].&lt;ref name="Kimmel 2013"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Kimmel, Michael S. |title=Angry white men : American masculinity at the end of an era |date=5 November 2013 |isbn=978-1-56858-696-0 |location=New York |oclc=852681950}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|132}} Kimmel condemns Nathanson and Young for their "selective, simplistic, and shallow" interpretations of sexism in film and fiction. Kimmel says that the "bad history" produced by Nathanson and Young should only be used as an indicator of how the "male studies enterprise" operates.&lt;ref name="Kimmel 2013" /&gt;{{Rp|84}}

[[Wendy McElroy]], an [[individualist feminist]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Wendy McElroy |url=http://www.independent.org/aboutus/person_detail.asp?id=488 |website=The Independent Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt; wrote in 2001 that some feminists "have redefined the view of the movement of the opposite sex" as "a hot anger toward men [that] seems to have turned into a cold hatred".{{sfn|McElroy|2001|p=5}} She argued it was a misandrist position to consider men, as a class, to be irreformable or [[rape|rapists]].{{Undue weight inline|date=August 2023|reason=non-academic source}}
In a 2016 article, individualist feminist [[Cathy Young]] described a "current cycle of misandry" in feminism.&lt;ref name="Young 2016"/&gt; This cycle, she explains, includes the use of the term "[[mansplaining]]" and other neologisms using "man" as a derogatory prefix.&lt;ref name="Young 2016" /&gt;{{Undue weight inline|date=August 2023|reason=Op-eds are WP:PRIMARY sources}}

Sociologist [[Allan G. Johnson]] argues in ''[[The Gender Knot: Unraveling our Patriarchal Legacy]]'' that accusations of man-hating have been used to put down feminists and to shift attention onto men, reinforcing a male-centered culture.&lt;ref name="Johnson p107"&gt;{{cite book |page=107 |title=The Gender Knot: Unraveling Our Patriarchal Legacy |edition=2, revised |last=Johnson |first=Alan G. |publisher=Temple University Press |year=2005 |isbn=978-1-59213-384-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnson posits that culture offers no comparable anti-male ideology to [[misogyny]] and that "people often confuse men as individuals with men as a dominant and privileged category of people" and that "[given the] reality of women's oppression, male privilege, and men's enforcement of both, it's hardly surprising that ''every'' woman should have moments where she resents or even hates men".

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Airline seating sex discrimination controversy]]
* ''[[Are All Men Pedophiles?]]''
* [[Bachelor tax]]
* [[Boys are stupid, throw rocks at them! controversy]]
* [[Circumcision controversies]]
* [[Female chauvinism]]
* [[Gynocentrism]]
* [[Male expendability]]
* [[Male genital mutilation]]
* [[Men's studies]]
* [[Reverse sexism]]
* [[Separatist feminism]]
* [[TERF]]
* [[Testosterone poisoning]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book |last=McElroy |first=Wendy |author-link=Wendy McElroy |title=Sexual Correctness: The Gender-Feminist Attack on Women |series=Harper Paperbacks |year=2001 |publisher=McFarland &amp; Company |location=New York |isbn=978-0-7864-1144-3}}
* {{cite book |last1=Nathanson |first1=Paul |last2=Young |first2=Katherine K. |author2-link=Katherine K. Young |title=Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture |series=Harper Paperbacks |year=2001 |publisher=[[McGill-Queen's University Press]] |isbn=978-0-7735-3099-7}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |author-link=Roy Baumeister |first=Roy F. |last=Baumeister |title=Is There Anything Good About Men? How Cultures Flourish By Exploiting Men |publisher=Oxford University Press |date=2010 |isbn=978-0-19-537410-0}}
*{{cite book |author-link=David Benatar |first=D. |last=Benatar |title=The Second Sexism: Discrimination Against Men and Boys |publisher=Wiley |date=2012 |isbn=978-0-470-67446-8}}
*{{cite book |title=Who Stole Feminism? How Women Have Betrayed Women |last=Sommers |first=Christina Hoff |author-link=Christina Hoff Sommers |year=1995 |orig-year=1994 |publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]] |isbn=978-0-684-80156-8 |title-link=Who Stole Feminism? |ref=none}}
* {{cite book |title=My Enemy, My Love: Man-Hating and Ambivalence in Women's Lives |last=Levine |first=Judith |author-link=Judith Levine |year=1992 |publisher=Da Capo Press |isbn=978-1-56025-568-0 |ref=none}}
*{{cite book |first=J.R. |last=MacNamara |title=Media and Male Identity: The Making and Remaking of Men |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |date=2006 |isbn=978-0-230-62567-9}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Smith |first1=William A. |last2=Yosso |first2=Tara J. |last3=Solorzano |first3=Daniel G. |title=Racial Primes and Black Misandry on Historically White Campuses: Toward Critical Race Accountability in Educational Administration |journal=[[Educational Administration Quarterly]] |volume=43 |issue=5 |pages=559–585 |date=2007 |doi=10.1177/0013161X07307793 |s2cid=145753160}}
*{{cite journal |first=Darren |last=Rosenblum |title=Beyond Victimisation and Misandry |journal=International Journal of Law in Context |volume=6 |issue=1 |pages=114–6 |date=2010 |doi=10.1017/S1744552309990383 |s2cid=143835898 |url=http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=7282784}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Nathanson |first1=Paul |last2=Young |first2=Katherine K. |title=Coming of Age As a Villain: What Every Boy Needs to Know in A Misandric World |journal=Thymos: Journal of Boyhood Studies |volume=3 |issue=2 |pages=155–177 |date=2009 |doi=10.3149/thy.0301.155}}
* {{cite book |author1=Katherine K. Young |author-link=Katherine K. Young |author2=Paul Nathanson |title=Sanctifying Misandry: Goddess Ideology and the Fall of Man |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y8rI7snipZcC |year=2010 |publisher=MQUP |isbn=978-0-7735-8544-7 |ref=none}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Nathanson |first1=Paul |last2=Young |first2=Katherine K. |title=Misandry and Emptiness: Masculine Identity in a Toxic Cultural Environment |journal=New Male Studies |volume=1 |issue=1 |pages=4–18 |date=2012 |url=http://newmalestudies.com/OJS/index.php/nms/article/viewFile/14/13}}
* {{cite book |title=The Revolt of the Primitive: An Inquiry into the Roots of Political Correctness |last=Schwartz |first=Howard |edition=Revised |year=2003 |publisher=[[Transaction Publishers]] |isbn=978-0-7658-0537-9 |ref=none}}
*{{cite book |author-link=Esther Vilar |title-link=The Manipulated Man |first=Esther |last=Vilar |title=The Manipulated Man |publisher=Farrar, Straus and Giroux |location=New York |date=1972 |isbn=978-0-374-20202-6}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary|Thesaurus:misandrist}}
*{{Commons category-inline}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Bailée |first1=Susan |year=2001 |title=Misandry in the Classroom |journal=The Hudson Review |volume=54 |issue=1 |pages=148–54 |quote=My rough-and-tumble first grader, Mark, came home from school yesterday and nonchalantly told me a story about his day that set me shivering |doi=10.2307/3852834 |jstor=3852834 |last2=Sommers |first2=Christina Hoff |ref=none}}
*{{cite web |url=http://adonismirror.com/10152006_leader_misandry_and_misanthropy.htm |title=Misandry: From the Dictionary of Fools |access-date=2007-12-28 |last=Leader |first=Richard |year=2007 |work=Adonis Mirror |ref=none}} article critical of the use of the term
*{{cite web |url=http://www.backlash.com/content/gender/1996/4-apr96/wilson04.html |title=Androphobia: The only respectable bigotry |access-date=2007-12-28 |last=Wilson |first=Robert Anton |author-link=Robert Anton Wilson |date=April 1996 |work=The Backlash! |publisher=Shameless Men Press |ref=none}}
*[https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2001/aug/14/edinburghfestival2001.edinburghbookfestival2001 "Lay off men, Lessing tells feminists"] by Fiachra Gibbons, ''[[The Guardian]]'', 14 August 2001

{{Sexual abuse}}
{{Sexual identities}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Misandry| ]]
[[Category:Gender-related prejudices]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination by type]]
[[Category:Sexism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>