<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20080818122145|232673400" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="10809813" pageid="10809813" ns="0" title="Global feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-09-02T21:06:46Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism sidebar}}
'''Global Feminism''' is a feminist theory concerned with the forward movement of [[women's rights]] on a global scale.  Global Feminists adopt global causes and start movements which seek to dismantle what they argue are the currently predominant structures of global patriarchy. Global Feminism is also known as Transnational Feminism, World Feminism, and International Feminism.

Global Feminists might argue, for example, that such structures enable the adoption of [[misogynistic]] cultural practices such as [[honor killings]], [[genital mutilation]], and [[human trafficking]].  Another concern of many Global Feminist activists is the impact of [[First World]] women's movements within the global economy as consumers upon the living and working conditions of [[Third World]] women.  For example, if an average feminist in the United States purchases a pair of athletic shoes without first researching the corporation through which they were produced, she may be buying a pair of sneakers that were sewn under [[sweatshop]] conditions and/or sewn in an offshore factory that is polluting the local land and water supply.  

==Further reading==
*Feldman, Shelley. "Exploring Theories of Patriarchy: A Perspective from Contemporary Bangladesh," ''Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society''. 25.4 (Summer 2001), p. 1108.
*Fonow, Mary Margret. "Human Rights, Feminism, and Transnational Labor Solidarity." ''Just Advocacy? Women's Human Rights,Transnational Feminisms, and the Politics of Representation''. Ed. Wendy S. Hasford and Wendy Kozol. New Brunswick: Rutgers UP, 2005. 221-43.
*Mendez, Jennifer Bickham. "Creating Alternatives from a Gender Perspective: Transnational Organizing for Maquila Workers' Rights in Central America". ''Women's Activism and Globalization: Linking Local Struggles and Transnational Politics''. Ed. Nancy A. Naples and Manisha Desai. New York: Routledge Press, 2002. 121-41.

==See also==
*[[Feminism]]
*[[Globalization]]
*[[Revolutionary Association of the Women of Afghanistan|RAWA]]

===External links===
*[http://www.amnesty.org Amnesty International]
*[http://www.behindthelabel.org Behind the Label]
*[http://www.coopamerica.org Co-Op America]
*[http://www.feminist.com feminist.com]
*[http://www.feminist.org The Feminist Majority Foundation]
*[http://www.globalexchange.org Global Exchange]
*[http://www.sweatfreeworld.org SweatFreeWorld]
*[http://www.unitehere.org UNITE HERE]

[[Category:Feminism by country]]
[[Category:Feminist philosophy]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Political philosophy]]
[[Category:Sociological theories]]
[[Category:Multicultural feminism]]

{{Fem-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>