<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050911221151|23062780" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1885001" pageid="1885001" ns="0" title="Male privilege"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-09-27T23:56:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">‘’Male privilege’’ is a term used to describe the rights granted to the [[male]] population in [[society]] on the basis of their biological sex.  The [[female]], [[transsexual]], [[transgender]], and sometimes the [[gay]] male populations are usually denied these rights. Male privilege is only one of many [[power structure]]s within a given society, and levels/manifestations of male privilege differ both between disparate societies as well as in different contexts within the same society. It is vital that male privilege is seen not as a solitary occurrence of the use of power, but rather as one of many systemic power structures that are interdependent and interlinked throughout societies.

Male privilege is not universally acknowledged as a real phenomenon, although the majority of [[Western culture|Western]] societies have enacted [[legislation]] or signed [[treaty|treaties]] committing them to closing the [[gender gap]], thereby acknowledging the disparity through word, if not deed by way of enforcement, an omission leading some to argue that male privilege is simply a pessimistic view of [[natural]] gender differences.  

== Determining Male Privilege ==
In 2005, the [[Geneva]]-based [[World Economic Forum]] published a study entitled Women’s Empowerment: Measuring the Gender Gap.  Using five critical areas, this study quantified the achievements that women in fifty-eight different countries have attained compared to their male counterparts. The five criteria defined by the study were '''economic participation''' representing the principle 'equal remuneration for equal work'; '''economic opportunity''' through access to the general labour market rather than low-paid, unskilled jobs; '''[[political]] empowerment''' reflecting the extent to which women are represented in decision-making structures; '''[[educational]] attainment''' including access to education at all levels; and over-all '''health and well-being''' including access to [[reproductive]] [[healthcare]] ([http://www.weforum.org/site/homepublic.nsf/Content/World+Economic+Forum+Launches+New+%E2%80%9CGender+Gap+Index%E2%80%9D+Measuring+Inequality+between+Women+and+Men+in+58+Countries]).  The report also states, “The survey also provides rare information on issues such as [[childcare]] availability and cost, the impact of [[maternity]] laws on the hiring of women, the prevalence of [[private sector]] employment of women and wage inequality” ([http://www.weforum.org/site/homepublic.nsf/Content/Global+Competitiveness+Programme%5CWomen%27s+Empowerment%3A+Measuring+the+Global+Gender+Gap]).

It is interesting to note that the top five positions are held entirely by [[Nordic]] countries.  The top ten list is as follows: 
#[[Sweden]]
#[[Norway]]
#[[Iceland]]
#[[Denmark]]
#[[Finland]]
#[[New Zealand]]
#[[Canada]]
#[[U.K. ]]
#[[Germany]]
#[[Australia]]

The bottom ten countries in the study are:
#[[Venezuela]]
#[[Greece]]
#[[Brazil]]
#[[Mexico]]
#[[India]]
#[[Korea]]
#[[Jordan]]
#[[Pakistan]]
#[[Turkey]]
#[[Egypt]]

== Cultural Factors Regarding Male Privilege ==
In every aspect of modern life in [[politics]], the [[law]], the [[church|churches]], the [[business]] world, the [[school|schools]], and the [[family]], the issue of [[gender]] discrimination has grown in significance. The core assumption is that [[sexuality]] and [[sexual]] behaviour are not [[natural]] outcomes, a simple result of their [[genetics]] or [[biology]]. Instead, sexuality is said to be a [[social]] construction, that men and women are nurtured and encouraged through societal pressures to become what the majority considers appropriate members of the [[ambient]] society. These assigned [[gender roles]] carry with them packages of [[rights]] and duties, and these packages are different depending on whether the individual is [[male]] or [[female]]. 

Sex- or gender-based differentiation is widely pervasive, although it manifests itself differently in different cultural contexts. For example, it is evidenced by the [[glass ceiling]] and the [[wage]] gap in Western cultures, [[female genital mutilation]] in Africa, [[dowry]]-related violence in Asian cultures, and the [[trafficking]] of women and young girls across the world. A general analysis of the privileged status of men within the existing power structures of each society should be undertaken, and, for this purpose, all barriers to free speech should be removed to enable [[culture|culturally]] local voices to articulate their understandings of male privilege.

== Compensating for Male Privilege ==
Compensation for male privilege takes place in a difficult and ever-changing territory. Most individual males are not directly responsible for male privilege but, as a group, they may resent being directly targeted by anti-discrimination or [[affirmative action]] laws, recognising that they may lose the benefits of [[patriarchal]] power. Most Western countries have enacted [[laws]] supposedly intended to mitigate the disparity between men and women, but these laws have not produced a consistent outcome. Many women fear the ramifications of taking formal action to address perceived gender bias. The practical adverse consequences include loss of work, difficulties in finding a new position, and gaining a reputation as a difficult employee. Because social contacts are very important in the business world, and disapproval from both male and female colleagues can be so strong, many women refrain from litigating problems that arise in an [[social environment|environment]] of male privilege, such as [[sexual harassment]] and [[favouritism]]. Add to this the fact that the courts in many countries are male-dominated and the result is that only a few of the more obvious abuses of male privilege are subjected to effective scrutiny and remedial action.

In other cultures, compensating for male privilege is not even a remote possibility. For example, the disparity between male and female rights in some countries makes murder or ritualised rape an acceptable male response to specified female behaviour. Even in countries that formally enact laws to criminalise [[Honor killings|honour killings]], they are rarely prosecuted. Several cases of [[suttee|sati]] occur each year, and even when death is avoided, widowhood in high-[[caste]] [[Hindu]] cultures can still have unfortunate consequences by Western standards. In other countries, women are not allowed out in public unless accompanied by a male relative, are not allowed to drive cars, and are not allowed to show their faces. Some of these [[regulations]] are based on [[religion|religious]] laws, and some on long-standing [[misogyny]]. In either case, agitation for change in these [[society|societies]] is generally frowned upon. Several [[NGOs]] and women’s groups, however, have been pushing for change within these countries for decades and, in some cases, have achieved and continue to achieve more equitable systems.

== Texts on Power Systems ==
*Judith Butler: ''Bodies That Matter''
*Mary Daly Gyn/Ecology: ''The Metaethics of Radical Feminism''
*[[Simone de Beauvoir]]: ''The Second Sex''
*[[Michel Foucault]]: ''The History of Sexuality, Archeology of Knowledge''
*[[Betty Friedan]]: ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]''
*[[Germaine Greer]]: ''The Female Eunuch''
*Maria Lugones: ''Pilgrimages: Theorizing Coalition Against Multiple Oppressions''
*Catharine MacKinnon: ''Sex Equality: Sexual Harrassment''
*Uma Narayan ''Dis/locating Cultures/Identitites, Traditions, and Third World Feminism''</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>