<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181118064352|869380455" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1885001" pageid="1885001" ns="0" title="Male privilege"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-18T06:44:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Globalize/Eng |date=June 2017}}
{{Feminism sidebar}}

'''Male privilege''' is a concept within [[sociology]] for examining social, economic, and political advantages or rights that are available to [[men]] solely on the basis of their [[sex]]. A man's access to these benefits may vary depending on how closely they match their society's [[hegemonic masculinity|ideal masculine norm]].

[[Feminist]] scholarship in the area of [[women's studies]] during the 1970s produced the earliest academic studies of privilege. These studies began by examining barriers to [[Social equity|equity]] between the sexes. In later decades, researchers began to focus on the [[intersectionality]] and overlapping nature of privileges relating to sex, [[race (human categorization)|race]], [[social class]], [[sexual orientation]], and other forms of social classification.

Male privilege is often examined alongside the [[Patriarchy#Feminist theory|concept of patriarchy]] within the feminist movement. The use of masculine [[pronoun]]s to refer to both sexes in some languages is often cited as an example of the privileged position given to males, as is the preference for sons over daughters in many cultures.

== Overview ==

Special privileges and status are granted to males in [[patriarchal]] societies.&lt;ref name="Phillips &amp; Phillips"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Phillips |first1=Debby A. |last2=Phillips |first2=John R. |editor1-first=Jodi |editor1-last=O'Brien |title=Encyclopedia of Gender and Society: Volume 2 |year=2009 |publisher=SAGE Publications |location=Thousand Oaks, Calif. |isbn= 978-1-4129-0916-7 |pages= 683–685 |chapter=Privilege, Male |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=_nyHS4WyUKEC&amp;pg=PT735}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Keith"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Keith |first1=Thomas |title=Masculinities in Contemporary American Culture: An Intersectional Approach to the Complexities and Challenges of Male Identity |date=2017 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1-31-759534-2 |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=r_niDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT29 |chapter=Patriarchy, Male Privilege, and the Consequences of Living in a Patriarchal Society |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; These are societies defined by male supremacy, in which males hold primary power and predominate in roles of political leadership, moral authority, [[social privilege]] and control of property. With systemic subordination of women, males gain economic, political, social, educational, and practical advantages that are more or less unavailable to women.{{refn|name=Keith}} The long-standing and unquestioned nature of such patriarchal systems, reinforced over generations, tends to make privilege invisible to holders; it can lead males who benefit from such privilege to ascribe their special status to their owned individual merits and achievements, rather than to unearned advantages.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}

In the field of [[sociology]], male privilege is seen as embedded in the structure of social institutions, as when men are often assigned authority over women in the workforce, and benefit from women's traditional caretaking role.&lt;ref name="Rohlinger"&gt;{{cite book |last=Rohlinger |first=Deana A. |editor1-last=Ritzer |editor1-first=G. |editor2-last=Ryan |editor2-first=J.M. |title=The Concise Encyclopedia of Sociology |date=2010 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |isbn=9781444392647 |pages=473–474 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Dz4wU64f_JYC&amp;q=%22male+privilege%22 |chapter=Privilege}}&lt;/ref&gt; Privileges can be classified as either ''positive'' or ''negative'', depending on how they affect the rest of society.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} Women's studies scholar [[Peggy McIntosh]] writes: {{quote|We might at least start by distinguishing between positive advantages that we can work to spread, to the point where they are not advantages at all but simply part of the normal civic and social fabric, and negative types of advantage that unless rejected will always reinforce our present hierarchies.&lt;ref name="McIntosh"&gt;{{cite web |last1=McIntosh |first1=Peggy |title=White Privilege and Male Privilege: A Personal Account of Coming to See Correspondences Through Work in Women's Studies |url=http://www.ehcounseling.com/materials/WHITE_PRIVILEGE_MALE_04-02-2003.pdf |publisher=Wellesley College, Center for Research on Women |location=Wellesley, MA |date=1988 |id=Working Paper 189}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Positive advantages include having such things as adequate nutrition, shelter, and health care, whereas negative advantages accompanying male privilege include such things as the expectation that a man will have a better chance than a comparably qualified woman of being hired for a job, as well as being paid more than a woman for the same job.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}

==Scope==

Privilege is not shared equally by all males. Those who most closely match the ideal masculine norm benefit the most from privilege.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}{{refn|name=Coston &amp; Kimmel}} In patriarchal societies this ideal, which is pervasive but unattainable for most men, has been described as being "white, heterosexual, stoic, wealthy, strong, tough, competitive, and autonomous".{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} [[Men's studies]] scholars refer to this ideal masculine norm as ''[[hegemonic masculinity]]''. While essentially all males benefit from privilege to some degree, those who visibly differ from the norm may not benefit fully in certain situations, especially in the company of other men that more closely match it.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} Men who have experienced [[bullying]] and [[domestic violence]] in youth, in particular, may not accept that they are beneficiaries of privilege. Such forms of coercive violence are linked to the idea of ''[[toxic masculinity]]'', a specific model of manhood that creates hierarchies of dominance in which some are favored and others are harmed.{{refn|name=Keith}}

The invisibility of male privilege can be seen for instance in discussions of the [[gender pay gap in the United States]]; the gap is usually referred to by stating women's earnings as a percentage of men's. However, using women's pay as the baseline highlights the dividend that males receive as greater earnings (32% in 2005).{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} In [[commerce]], male dominance in the ownership and control of [[financial capital]] and other forms of wealth has produced disproportionate male influence over the [[working class]]es and the hiring and firing of employees. In addition, a disproportionate burden is placed upon women in employment when they are expected to be solely responsible for [[child care]]; they may be more likely to be fired or be denied advancement in their profession, thus putting them at an economic disadvantage relative to men.{{refn|name=Keith}}

Biologically "male" privilege is only one of the many [[Hierarchy|power structures]] that may exist within a given society.&lt;ref name="Foucault1976"&gt;{{cite book|last=Foucault|first=Michel |title=The History of Sexuality, Volume I|year=1976|publisher=Vintage|isbn=0-679-72469-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=August 2017}} The term "male privilege" does not apply to a solitary occurrence of the use of power, but rather describes one of many systemic power structures that are interdependent and interlinked throughout societies and cultures.&lt;ref name="Narayan"&gt;{{cite book|last=Narayan|first=Uma|title=Dislocating Cultures: Identities, Traditions, and Third-World Feminism.|year=1997|publisher=London: Routledge|isbn=0-415-91419-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As discussed by Paula Rothernberg in her novel ''Invisible Privilege: A Memoir About Race, Class, and Gender'', male privilege often takes institutionalized and embedded forms from which men may directly benefit. These instances of male privilege systems may attribute to male over empowerment and can help explain man’s sense of centrality in some of the most powerful institutions.&lt;ref name=Rothenberg&gt;{{cite book |last1=Rothernberg |first1=Paula S. |title=Invisible Privilege: A Memoir About Race, Class, and Gender |date=2000 |publisher=University of Kansas}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Primary source inline|date=August 2017}}

An example of male privilege in institutionalized academic settings can be observed by the prevalence of men in how curriculums are formed and history and literature is taught across the [[United States]].{{refn|name=Rothenberg}}{{Better source|date=August 2017}} Historically, all those who have held the title of [[List of Presidents of the United States|President of the United States]] have been male. American government on the national level, including the [[United States Senate]] and the [[United States House of Representatives]], is also predominantly male.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://reports.weforum.org/global-gender-gap-report-2016/economies/#economy=USA|title=Economies|newspaper=Global Gender Gap Report 2016|language=en-US|access-date=2017-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scholarship==

The earliest academic studies of privilege appeared with [[feminist]] scholars' work in the area of [[women's studies]] during the 1970s. Such scholarship began by examining barriers to [[Social equity|equity]] between the sexes. In later decades, researchers began to focus on the [[intersectionality]] and overlapping nature of privileges relating to sex, [[race (human categorization)|race]], [[social class]], [[sexual orientation]], and other forms of social classification.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}

[[Peggy McIntosh]], one of the first feminist scholars to examine male privilege,  wrote about both male privilege and [[white privilege]], using the metaphor of the "invisible knapsack" to describe a set of advantages borne, often unaware and unacknowledged, by members of privileged groups.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} According to McIntosh, privilege is not a result of a concerted effort to oppress those of the opposite gender; however, the inherent benefits that men gain from the systemic bias put women at an innate disadvantage. The benefits of this unspoken privilege may be described as special provisions, tools, relationships, or various other opportunities. According to McIntosh, this privilege may actually negatively affect men's development as human beings, and few question that the existing structure of advantages may be challenged or changed.{{refn|name=McIntosh}}

Efforts to examine the role of privilege in students' lives has become a regular feature of university education in North America.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}&lt;ref name="Coston &amp; Kimmel"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Coston |first1=Bethany M. |last2=Kimmel |first2=Michael |year=2012 |title=Seeing Privilege Where It Isn't: Marginalized Masculinities and the Intersectionality of Privilege |journal=Journal of Social Issues |volume=68 |issue=1 |pages=97–111 |doi=10.1111/j.1540-4560.2011.01738.x |issn=1540-4560}}&lt;/ref&gt; By drawing attention to the presence of privilege (including male, white, and other forms) in the lives of students, educators have sought to foster insights that can help students contribute to [[social justice]].{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} Such efforts include McIntosh's "invisible knapsack" model of privilege and the "Male Privilege Checklist".{{refn|name=Coston &amp; Kimmel}}

==Gender neutrality in English==

{{Further|Gender neutrality in English | Gender-neutrality in languages with grammatical gender | Gender-neutrality in languages without grammatical gender}}
Some linguistic conventions have privileged men and the male perspective and suggested that maleness is the societal norm.&lt;ref name=wildman&gt;{{Cite book |title= Privilege revealed: how invisible preference undermines America  |last= Wildman |first= S. M. |publisher= [[New York University Press]] |location= New York |year= 1996 |page= 15 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LK-aQDstH6kC&amp;pg=PA15 |isbn= 978-0-8147-9303-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=rasta&gt;{{Cite book |last= Barnett |first= M. |title= Rastafari in the new millennium: a Rastafari reader |location= Syracuse, NY |publisher= [[Syracuse University Press]] |year= 2012 |page= 234&amp;ndash;235 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=IYYg_Q3IKeIC&amp;pg=PA234 |isbn= 9780815650799 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bwh&gt;{{Cite book |last1= Briscoe |first1= F. |last2= Arriaza |first2= G. |last3= Henze |first3= R. C. |title= The power of talk: how words change our lives |location= Thousand Oaks, Calif. |publisher= [[Sage Publications|Corwin Press]] |year= 2009 |page= 21 |isbn= 978-1-4129-5601-7 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=BsmoJYf0LT4C&amp;pg=PT33 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In English, nouns such as "man" or "mankind"&lt;ref name=rjm&gt;{{Cite book |last1= Roman |first1= C. |last2= Juhasz |first2= S. |last3= Miller |first3= C. |title= The women and language debate: a sourcebook |location= New Brunswick, N.J. |publisher= [[Rutgers University Press]] |year= 1994 |page = 451 |isbn= 978-0-8135-2011-7 | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=jGWYW_LVmN8C&amp;pg=PA451}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Davies |first= D. |title= Varieties of modern English: an introduction |location= Harlow |publisher= [[Longman|Pearson Longman]] |year= 2005 |isbn= 978-0-582-36996-2 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=sIgr91OV2kYC&amp;pg=PA78 |pages= 78&amp;ndash;79}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Cunningham |first= G. B. |title= Diversity in sport organizations |location= Scottsdale, Ariz. |publisher= Holcomb Hathaway |year= 2007 |isbn= 978-1-890871-77-2 |page= 122 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Anderson |first= K. J. |title= Benign bigotry: the psychology of subtle prejudice |location= Cambridge, UK |publisher= [[Cambridge University Press]] |year= 2010 |page= 203 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_STPJNHE5fAC&amp;pg=PA203 |isbn= 978-0-521-70259-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and forms of address like "you guys" are routinely used for women while it is not accepted to refer to men as women.&lt;ref name=kleinman&gt;{{Cite journal |last= Kleinman |first= S. |title= Why sexist language matters |journal= [[Qualitative Sociology]] |year= 2002 |volume= 25 |issue= 2 |pages= 299&amp;ndash; 304 |doi= 10.1023/A:1015474919530}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Associating a man with something feminine and calling him girl or sissy is usually considered an insult.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Rosenberg |first= R. |year= 2001 |title= Women's studies: an interdisciplinary anthology |location= New York |publisher= [[Peter Lang (publishing company)|Peter Lang]] |isbn= 978-0-8204-4443-7 |page= 78 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Expressions like "freshmen" or occupational titles such as "chairman" are supposed to apply to both sexes&lt;ref name=bwh/&gt;&lt;ref name=kleinman/&gt; and many prestigious occupations are implicitly associated with men so that people use modifiers such as "woman doctor" or "lady doctor" to signal deviations from the norm that doctors are usually men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1= Flood |first1= M. |authorlink1= Michael Flood |last2= Pease |first2= B. |title= Undoing men's privilege and advancing gender equality in public sector institutions |journal= Policy and Society |volume= 24 |issue= 4 |year= 2005 |pages= 199&amp;ndash;138 |doi=  10.1016/S1449-4035(05)70123-5 |url= http://www.xyonline.net/sites/default/files/Flood%20Pease,%20Undoing%20men%27s%20priv.pdf |accessdate= April 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Powell |first= B. |title= Counted out: same-sex relations and Americans' definitions of family |location= New York |publisher= [[Russell Sage Foundation]] |year= 2010 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=QZ07GrUh-fsC&amp;pg=PA172 |page= 172 |isbn= 978-0-87154-687-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In Western culture, male images and exclusively male language for [[deity|deities]] such as referring to [[God]] as "he" or "father" have been argued to have reinforced male privilege.&lt;ref name=lindley/&gt;&lt;ref name=obrien/&gt;&lt;ref name=chandler/&gt;&lt;ref name=lorenzen/&gt; Men's greater resemblance to God has been used to justify men's religious and cultural position.&lt;ref name=lindley&gt;{{Cite book |last= Lindley |first= S. H. |editor1-last= Keller |editor1-first= R. S. |editor2-last= Ruether |editor2-first= R. R. |editor3-last= Cantlon |editor3-first= M |title= Encyclopedia of women and religion in North America |location= Bloomington |publisher= [[Indiana University Press]] |year= 2006 |isbn= 978-0-253-34685-8 |chapter= Gender and social roles |chapterurl= https://books.google.com/books?id=EoJrHDirVQUC&amp;pg=PA26 |page= 26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=obrien&gt;{{Cite book |last= O'Brien |first= J. M. |title= Challenging prophetic metaphor: theology and ideology in the prophets |location= Louisville, KY |publisher= Westminster John Knox |year= 2008 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=nqKJ7XPpnbQC&amp;pg=PA72 |page= 72 |isbn= 978-0-664-22964-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=chandler&gt;{{Cite book |last= Chandler |first= K. J. |title= How to become a 'blackman': exploring African American masculinities and the performance of gender |location= Detroit |publisher= Wayne State University |year= 2007 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=2U6guwPOZVoC&amp;pg=PA184 |page= 184 |isbn= 9780549293866 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lorenzen&gt;{{Cite book |last= Lorenzen |first= L. F. |title= The college student's introduction to the Trinity |location= Collegeville, Minn. |publisher= Liturgical Press |year= 1999 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=PLYZtKCT0fgC&amp;pg=PA73 |page= 73| isbn= 978-0-8146-5518-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, the third-person singular pronoun "[[he]]" is used as a sex-indefinite, [[generic antecedent|generic]] form for all people (e.g. "anyone can do it if he tries") whereas the use of "she" to refer to people in general is not allowed.&lt;ref name=wildman/&gt;&lt;ref name=bwh/&gt;&lt;ref name=kleinman/&gt; Masculine generics were first introduced by [[linguistic prescription|prescriptive grammarians]] in the 19th century who argued that "he" was the only correct sex-indefinite referent.&lt;ref name=henley/&gt;&lt;ref name=bodine/&gt;&lt;ref name=hegarty/&gt; Prior to that, singular "they" and "he or she" had been widely used in written and spoken English.&lt;ref name=henley/&gt;&lt;ref name=bodine/&gt;&lt;ref name=hegarty/&gt; In 1850 a special [[Interpretation Act 1850|Act of Parliament]] was passed in the [[United Kingdom]] that legally proscribed singular "they" and "he or she" in favor of "he", especially to shorten the language used in Acts of Parliament.&lt;ref name=henley&gt;{{Cite book |last= Henley |first= N. M. |editor-last= Penfield |editor-first= J |title= Women and language in transition |year= 1987 |location= Albany |publisher= [[State University of New York Press]] |page= 13 |isbn= 978-0-88706-485-2 |chapter= This new species that seeks a new language: On sexism in language and language change  |chapterurl= https://books.google.com/books?id=Q440jZBUpsMC&amp;pg=PA13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bodine&gt;{{Cite journal |last= Bodine |first= A. |title= Androcentrism in prescriptive grammar: Singular 'they', sex indefinite 'he', and 'he or she' |journal= Language and Society |volume= 4 |issue= 2 |year= 1975 |pages= 129&amp;ndash; 146 |doi= 10.1017/S0047404500004607 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hegarty&gt;{{Cite journal |last1= Hegarty |first1= P. |last2= Buechel |first2= C. |title= Androcentric reporting of gender differences in APA journals 1965&amp;ndash;2004 |journal= Review of General Psychology |volume= 10 |issue= 4 |pages= 377&amp;ndash;389 |url= http://www.apastyle.org/manual/related/hegarty-and-buechel.pdf |accessdate= April 15, 2013 |doi= 10.1037/1089-2680.10.4.377 |year= 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==

Many men may respond to discussions of male privilege by saying that they do not feel that they have been given any unearned advantages, such as in their struggles to find success in employment, education, or relationships.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} Advocates for [[men's rights]] and [[father's rights]] as well as [[anti-feminist]] men often accept that men's traditional roles are damaging to men but deny that men as a group have institutional power and privilege, and argue that men are now victims relative to women.&lt;ref name="Flood 2007 Men"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Clatterbaugh |first=K. |editor1-last=Flood |editor1-first=Michael |display-editors=etal |title=International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities |date=2007 |publisher=Routledge  |location=London |isbn=978-0-415-33343-6 |chapter=Anti-feminism |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jh7y6ELc90YC&amp;pg=PA21#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |pages=21–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the other hand, some self-identified feminist men take active roles in challenging oppressive [[sexism]], arguing that male privilege is deeply linked to the oppression of women. They describe men's oppressive behaviors as cultural traits learned within patriarchal social systems, rather than inborn biological traits.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} Advocates within the broader [[men's movement]] oriented towards [[profeminism]] or anti-sexism argue that traditional [[gender role]]s harm both men and women. "Liberal" profeminism tends to stress the ways men suffer from these traditional roles, while more "radical" profeminism tends to emphasize male privilege and [[sexual inequality]].&lt;ref name="Flood 2007 Men"&gt;{{cite book |last=Flood |first=Michael |author-link=Michael Flood |editor1-last=Flood |editor1-first=Michael |display-editors=etal |title=International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities |date =2007 |publisher=Routledge  |location=London |isbn=978-0-415-33343-6 |chapter= Men's movement |chapterurl=http://www.xyonline.net/sites/default/files/Flood,%20Men's%20Movements,%20IEMM%202007.pdf |pages=418&amp;ndash;422}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some men may be also be advocates of women's rights but fail to realize that their privilege as a whole, is a part of the issue at hand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Shaw|first1=Susan|last2=Lee|first2=Janet|title=Women's Voices Feminist Visions|date=2015|publisher=McGraw-Hill Education|location=New York, New York|isbn=978-0-07-802700-0|page=54|edition=Sixth}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Explain|date=November 2017}}

==Son-preference==
{{Main|Sex selection}}

In many societies including [[India]] and [[China]], male offspring are privileged and favored over female children.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last1= Ryju |editor-first1= S. |editor-last2= Lahiri-Dutt |title= Doing gender, doing geography: emerging research in India |location= New Delhi |publisher= Routledge |year= 2011 |page= 212 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EB63--z4zK0C&amp;pg=PT212 |isbn= 978-0-415-59802-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=weiner&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last1= Weiner |editor-first1= M. |editor-last2= Varshney |editor-first2= A. |editor-last3= Almond |editor-first3= G. A. |title= India and the politics of developing countries |location= Thousand Oaks, Calif. |publisher= SAGE Publications |year= 2004 |page= 187 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=ls38Az4-J64C&amp;pg=PA187 |isbn= 978-0-7619-3287-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last= Joseph |editor-first= W. A. |title= Politics in China: an introduction |location= Oxford |publisher= Oxford University Press |year= 2010 |page= 308 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=kk80evDTZIYC&amp;pg=PA308&amp;lpg=PA308 |isbn= 978-0-19-533530-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lai-wan&gt;{{Cite journal |last1= Lai-wan |last2= Eric |first2= B. |last3= Hoi-yan |first1= C. C. |title= Attitudes to and practices regarding sex selection in China |journal= Prenatal Diagnosis |volume= 26 |issue= 7 |year= 2006 |pages= 610&amp;ndash;613 |doi= 10.1002/pd.1477}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some manifestations of son preference and the devaluation of women are eliminating unwanted daughters through neglect, maltreatment, abandonment, as well as female [[infanticide]] and [[feticide]] despite laws that prohibit infanticide and [[Sex-selective abortion|sex-selective pregnancy termination.]]&lt;ref name=lai-wan/&gt;&lt;ref name=singh&gt;{{Cite journal |url= http://www.frontline.in/static/html/fl2915/stories/20120810291502200.htm |title= Man's world, legally |last= Singh |first= K. |journal= [[Frontline (magazine)|Frontline]] |volume= 29 |issue= 15 |year= 2012 |accessdate= May 13, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last1= Koop |editor-first1= C. E. |editor-link1= C. Everett Koop |editor-last2= Pearson |editor-first2= C. E. |editor-last3= Schwarz |editor-first3= M. R. |title= Critical issues in global health |location= San Francisco, Calif. |publisher= Wiley |year= 2002 |page= 224 |isbn= 978-0-7879-6377-4 |quote= Across the world, male privilege is also variously reflected in giving sons preferential access to health care, sex- selective abortion, female infanticide, or trafficking in women.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In India some of these practices have contributed to skewed sex ratios in favor of male children at birth and in the first five years.&lt;ref name=weiner/&gt; Other examples of privileging male offspring are special "praying for a son" ceremonies during pregnancy, more ceremony and festivities following the birth of a boy, listing and introducing sons before daughters, and common felicitations that associate good fortune and well-being with the number of sons.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Croll |first= E. |title= Endangered daughters: discrimination and development in Asia |chapter= Ethnographic voices: disappointing daughters |chapterurl= https://books.google.com/books?id=npGRm5pNRl0C&amp;pg=PA70 |location= London |publisher= Routledge |year= 2000 |pages= 70&amp;ndash;105 |isbn= 978-0-203-17021-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reasons given for preferring sons to daughters include sons' role in religious family rites, which daughters are not permitted to perform, and the belief that sons are permanent members of the birth family whereas daughters belong to their husband's family after marriage in accordance with [[Patrilocal residence|patrilocal]] tradition. Other reasons include [[Patrilineality|patrilineal]] customs whereby only sons can carry on the family name, the obligation to pay [[dowry]] to a daughter's husband or his family, and the expectation that sons will support their birth parents financially while it is regarded as undesirable or shameful to receive financial support from daughters.&lt;ref name=lai-wan/&gt;&lt;ref name=singh/&gt;

==See also==

{{colbegin}}
*[[Androcentrism]]
*[[Anti-discrimination law]]
*[[Antifeminism]]
*[[Chauvinism]]
*[[Antisexism]]
*[[Gender]]
*[[Honorary male]]
*[[Global Gender Gap Report]]
*[[Privilege (social inequality)]]
*[[Sex-selective abortion]]
{{colend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==

* {{Cite journal | last = Branscombe | first = Nyla R. | title = Thinking about one's gender group's privileges or disadvantages: consequences for well-being in women and men | journal = British Journal of Social Psychology | volume = 37 | issue = 2 | pages = 167–184 | doi = 10.1111/j.2044-8309.1998.tb01163.x | date = June 1998 | url = https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Nyla_Branscombe/publication/13644510_Thinking_about_one's_gender_group's_privileges_or_disadvantages_Consequences_for_well-being_in_women_and_men/links/553819a20cf2239f4e79902b/Thinking-about-ones-gender-groups-privileges-or-disadvantages-Consequences-for-well-being-in-women-and-men.pdf | ref = harv }}
* {{Cite book | last1 = Ferber | first1 = Marianne A. | last2 = Blau | first2 = Francine D. | last3 = Winkler | first3 = Anne E. | author-link1 = Marianne Ferber | author-link2 = Francine D. Blau | title = The economics of women, men, and work | publisher = Pearson | location = Boston | year = 2014 | edition = 7th | isbn = 9780132992817 }}
* {{Cite book | last = Jacobs | first = Michael P. | chapter = Do gay men have a stake in male privilege? | editor-last1 = Gluckman | editor-first1 = Amy | editor-last2 = Reed | editor-first2 = Betsy | title = Homo economics: capitalism, community, and lesbian and gay life | pages = 165–184 | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 1997 | isbn = 9780415913799 | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ll-xBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA165 | ref = harv }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Kimmel | first = Michael S. | author-link = Michael Kimmel | title = Men's responses to feminism at the turn of the century | journal = [[Gender &amp; Society]] | volume = 1 | issue = 3 | pages = 261&amp;ndash;283 | publisher = [[Sage Publications|Sage]] | doi = 10.1177/089124387001003003 | jstor = 189564 | date = September 1987 | url = https://doi.org/10.1177/089124389003001005 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
* {{Cite journal | last = Kolb | first = Kenneth H. | title = 'Supporting our black men': reproducing male privilege in a black student political organization |journal = Sociological Spectrum | volume = 27 | issue = 3 | pages = 257–274 | publisher = Mid-South Sociological Association (MSSA) | doi = 10.1080/02732170701206106 | date = 2007 | url = https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Kenneth_Kolb/publication/238399712_Supporting_our_Black_Men_Reproducing_Male_Privilege_in_a_Black_Student_Political_Organization/links/02e7e534feac81e0f3000000.pdf | ref = harv }}
* {{Cite book |editor1-last=Kimmel |editor1-first=Michael |editor2-last=Ferber |editor2-first=Abby L. |title=Privilege: A Reader |date=2003 |publisher=Westview Press |location=Boulder, Colorado |isbn=978-0-8133-4056-2}}
* {{cite journal | last = Messner | first = Michael A. | author-link = Michael Messner | title = The limits of 'The Male Sex Role': an analysis of the men's liberation and men's rights movements' discourse | journal = [[Gender &amp; Society]] | volume = 12 | issue = 3 | pages = 255&amp;ndash;276 | publisher = [[Sage Publications|Sage]] | doi = 10.1177/0891243298012003002 | jstor = 190285 | date = June 1998 | url = https://doi.org/10.1177/0891243298012003002 | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [http://www.michaelmessner.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/Gender-Society-1998-MESSNER-255-76.pdf Pdf.]
* {{Cite journal |last1= Noble |first1= Carolyn |last2= Pease |first2= Bob |title= Interrogating male privilege in the human services and social work education |journal= Women in Welfare Education |volume= 10 |issue= 1 |pages= 29–38 |doi=  |date= 2011 |url= http://www.anzswwer.org/wiwe/default.htm |deadurl= bot: unknown |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20170823085758/http://www.anzswwer.org/wiwe/default.htm |archivedate= 2017-08-23 |df=  }} [http://dro.deakin.edu.au/eserv/DU:30041409/pease-interrogatingmale-2011.pdf Pdf.]
* {{cite journal |last1=Orelus |first1=Pierre W. |title=Unmasking male, heterosexual, and racial privileges: from naive complicity to critical awareness and praxis |journal=Counterpoints |volume=351 |pages=17–62 | publisher = Peter Lang |date=2010 |jstor = 42980551 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
* {{Cite journal |last1= Pratto |first1= Felicia |last2= Stewart |first2= Andrew L. |title= Group dominance and the half-blindness of privilege |journal= Journal of Social Issues, special issue: Systems of Privilege: Intersections, Awareness, and Applications |volume= 68 |issue= 1 |pages= 28–45 |doi= 10.1111/j.1540-4560.2011.01734.x | date = March 2012 | url = https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1540-4560.2011.01734.x | ref = harv }}
* {{Cite journal |last1= Schmitt |first1= Michael T. |last2= Branscombe |first2= Nyla R. |title= The meaning and consequences of perceived discrimination in disadvantaged and privileged groups |journal= European Review of Social Psychology |volume= 12 |issue= 1 |pages= 167–199 | doi = 10.1080/14792772143000058 | date = 2002 | url = https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Michael_Schmitt8/publication/233204900_The_Meaning_and_Consequences_of_Perceived_Discrimination_in_Disadvantaged_and_Privileged_Social_Groups/links/00b7d53a0a6fa6021d000000.pdf | ref = harv }}

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Men|Privilege]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Privilege (social inequality)]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>