<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20230723194604|1166791086" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1885001" pageid="1885001" ns="0" title="Male privilege"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-07-23T19:48:56Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use American English|date=July 2023}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2023}}
{{Short description|Social privilege of men}}
{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{Feminism sidebar|concepts}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Related}}

'''Male privilege''' is the system of advantages or rights that are available to [[men]] on the basis of their [[sex]]. A man's access to these benefits may vary depending on how closely they match their society's [[hegemonic masculinity|ideal masculine norm]].

Academic studies of male privilege were a focus of [[feminist]] scholarship during the 1970s. These studies began by examining barriers to [[Social equity|equity]] between the sexes. In later decades, researchers began to focus on the [[intersectionality]] and overlapping nature of privileges relating to sex, [[race (human categorization)|race]], [[social class]], [[sexual orientation]], and other forms of social classification.

== Overview ==

Special privileges and status are granted to males in [[patriarchal]] societies.&lt;ref name="Phillips &amp; Phillips"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Phillips |first1=Debby A. |last2=Phillips |first2=John R. |editor1-first=Jodi |editor1-last=O'Brien |title=Encyclopedia of Gender and Society: Volume 2 |year=2009 |publisher=SAGE Publications |location=Thousand Oaks, Calif. |isbn= 978-1-4129-0916-7 |pages= 683–685 |chapter=Privilege, Male |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_nyHS4WyUKEC&amp;pg=PT735}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Keith"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Keith |first1=Thomas |title=Masculinities in Contemporary American Culture: An Intersectional Approach to the Complexities and Challenges of Male Identity |date=2017 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1-31-759534-2 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=r_niDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT29 |chapter=Patriarchy, Male Privilege, and the Consequences of Living in a Patriarchal Society |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; These are societies defined by [[male supremacy]], in which males hold primary power and predominate in roles of political leadership, moral authority, [[social privilege]] and control of property. With systemic subordination of women, males gain economic, political, social, educational, and practical advantages that are more or less unavailable to women.{{refn|name=Keith}} The long-standing and unquestioned nature of such patriarchal systems, reinforced over generations, tends to make privilege invisible to holders; it can lead males who benefit from such privilege to ascribe their special status to their own individual merits and achievements, rather than to unearned advantages.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}

In the field of [[sociology]], male privilege is seen as embedded in the structure of social institutions, as when men are often assigned authority over women in the workforce, and benefit from women's traditional caretaking role.&lt;ref name="Rohlinger"&gt;{{cite book |last=Rohlinger |first=Deana A. |editor1-last=Ritzer |editor1-first=G. |editor2-last=Ryan |editor2-first=J.M. |title=The Concise Encyclopedia of Sociology |date=2010 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |isbn=9781444392647 |pages=473–474 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Dz4wU64f_JYC&amp;q=%22male+privilege%22 |chapter=Privilege}}&lt;/ref&gt; Privileges can be classified as either ''positive'' or ''negative'', depending on how they affect the rest of society.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} Women's studies scholar [[Peggy McIntosh]] writes: {{quote|We might at least start by distinguishing between positive advantages that we can work to spread, to the point where they are not advantages at all but simply part of the normal civic and social fabric, and negative types of advantage that unless rejected will always reinforce our present hierarchies.&lt;ref name="McIntosh"&gt;{{cite web |last1=McIntosh |first1=Peggy |title=White Privilege and Male Privilege: A Personal Account of Coming to See Correspondences Through Work in Women's Studies |url=http://www.ehcounseling.com/materials/WHITE_PRIVILEGE_MALE_04-02-2003.pdf |publisher=Wellesley College, Center for Research on Women |location=Wellesley, MA |date=1988 |id=Working Paper 189}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Some negative advantages accompanying male privilege include such things as the expectation that a man will have a better chance than a comparably qualified woman of being hired for a job, as well as being paid more than a woman for the same job.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}

==Scope==
The term "male privilege" does not apply to a solitary occurrence of the use of power, but rather describes one of many systemic power structures that are interdependent and interlinked throughout societies and cultures.&lt;ref name="Narayan"&gt;{{cite book|last=Narayan|first=Uma|title=Dislocating Cultures: Identities, Traditions, and Third-World Feminism.|year=1997|publisher=London: Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-91419-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Privilege is not shared equally by all males. Those who most closely match an ideal masculine norm benefit the most from privilege.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}{{refn|name=Coston &amp; Kimmel}} In Western patriarchal societies this ideal has been described as being "white, heterosexual, stoic, wealthy, strong, tough, competitive, and autonomous".{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} [[Men's studies]] scholars refer to this ideal masculine norm as ''[[hegemonic masculinity]]''. While essentially all males benefit from privilege to some degree, those who visibly differ from the norm may not benefit fully in certain situations, especially in the company of other men that more closely match it.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}

Men who have experienced [[bullying]] and [[domestic violence]] in youth, in particular, may not accept the idea that they are beneficiaries of privilege. Such forms of coercive violence are linked to the idea of ''toxic masculinity'', a specific model of manhood that creates hierarchies of dominance in which some are favored and others are harmed.{{refn|name=Keith}}

The invisibility of male privilege can be seen for instance in discussions of the [[gender pay gap in the United States]]; the gap is usually referred to by stating women's earnings as a percentage of men's. However, using women's pay as the baseline highlights the dividend that males receive as greater earnings (32% in 2005).{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} In [[commerce]], male dominance in the ownership and control of [[financial capital]] and other forms of wealth has produced disproportionate male influence over the [[working class]]es and the hiring and firing of employees. In addition, a disproportionate burden is placed upon women in employment when they are expected to be solely responsible for [[child care]]; they may be more likely to be fired or be denied advancement in their profession, thus putting them at an economic disadvantage relative to men.{{refn|name=Keith}}

==Scholarship==

The earliest academic studies of privilege appeared with [[feminist]] scholars' work in the area of [[women's studies]] during the 1970s. Such scholarship began by examining barriers to [[Social equity|equity]] between the sexes. In later decades, researchers began to focus on the [[intersectionality]] and overlapping nature of privileges relating to sex, [[race (human categorization)|race]], [[social class]], [[sexual orientation]], and other forms of social classification.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}

[[Peggy McIntosh]], one of the first feminist scholars to examine male privilege,  wrote about both male privilege and [[white privilege]], using the metaphor of the "invisible knapsack" to describe a set of advantages borne, often unaware and unacknowledged, by members of privileged groups.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} According to McIntosh, privilege is not a result of a concerted effort to oppress those of the opposite gender; however, the inherent benefits that men gain from the systemic bias put women at an innate disadvantage. The benefits of this unspoken privilege may be described as special provisions, tools, relationships, or various other opportunities. According to McIntosh, this privilege may actually negatively affect men's development as human beings, and few question that the existing structure of advantages may be challenged or changed.{{refn|name=McIntosh}}

Efforts to examine the role of privilege in students' lives has become a regular feature of university education in North America.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}}&lt;ref name="Coston &amp; Kimmel"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Coston |first1=Bethany M. |last2=Kimmel |first2=Michael |year=2012 |title=Seeing Privilege Where It Isn't: Marginalized Masculinities and the Intersectionality of Privilege |journal=Journal of Social Issues |volume=68 |issue=1 |pages=97–111 |doi=10.1111/j.1540-4560.2011.01738.x |issn=1540-4560}}&lt;/ref&gt; By drawing attention to the presence of privilege (including male, white, and other forms) in the lives of students, educators have sought to foster insights that can help students contribute to [[social justice]].{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} Such efforts include McIntosh's "invisible knapsack" model of privilege and the "Male Privilege Checklist".{{refn|name=Coston &amp; Kimmel}}

==Cultural responses==

Many men have responded to discussions of male privilege by saying that they do not feel that they have been given any unearned advantages, such as in their struggles to find success in employment, education, or relationships.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} Advocates for [[men's rights]] and [[father's rights]] as well as [[anti-feminist]] men often accept that men's traditional roles are damaging to men but deny that men as a group have institutional power and privilege, and argue that men are now victims relative to women.&lt;ref name="Flood 2007 Men"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Clatterbaugh |first=K. |editor1-last=Flood |editor1-first=Michael |display-editors=etal |title=International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities |date=2007 |publisher=Routledge  |location=London |isbn=978-0-415-33343-6 |chapter=Anti-feminism |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jh7y6ELc90YC&amp;pg=PA21 |pages=21–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have taken active roles in challenging oppressive [[sexism]] and [[misogyny]], arguing that male privilege is deeply linked to the oppression of women. They describe men's oppressive behaviors as cultural traits learned within patriarchal social systems, rather than inborn biological traits.{{refn|name=Phillips &amp; Phillips}} Advocates within the broader [[men's movement]] oriented towards [[profeminism]] or anti-sexism argue that traditional [[gender role]]s harm both men and women. "Liberal" profeminism tends to stress the ways men suffer from these traditional roles, while more "radical" profeminism tends to emphasize male privilege and [[sexual inequality]].&lt;ref name="Flood 2007 Men"&gt;{{cite book |last=Flood |first=Michael |author-link=Michael Flood |editor1-last=Flood |editor1-first=Michael |display-editors=etal |title=International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities |date =2007 |publisher=Routledge  |location=London |isbn=978-0-415-33343-6 |chapter= Men's movement |chapter-url=http://www.xyonline.net/sites/default/files/Flood,%20Men's%20Movements,%20IEMM%202007.pdf |pages=418&amp;ndash;422}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some men may also be advocates of women's rights but deny that their privilege as a whole is a part of the issue at hand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Shaw|first1=Susan|last2=Lee|first2=Janet|title=Women's Voices Feminist Visions|date=2015|publisher=McGraw-Hill Education|location=New York, New York|isbn=978-0-07-802700-0|page=54|edition=Sixth}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{POV statement|date=January 2019}}

==Preference of sons over daughters==
{{Main|Sex selection}}

In both [[India]] and [[China]], male offspring are often privileged and favored over female children.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last1= Ryju |editor-first1= S. |editor-last2= Lahiri-Dutt |title= Doing gender, doing geography: emerging research in India |location= New Delhi |publisher= Routledge |year= 2011 |page= 212 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EB63--z4zK0C&amp;pg=PT212 |isbn= 978-0-415-59802-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=weiner&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last1= Weiner |editor-first1= M. |editor-last2= Varshney |editor-first2= A. |editor-last3= Almond |editor-first3= G. A. |title= India and the politics of developing countries |location= Thousand Oaks, Calif. |publisher= SAGE Publications |year= 2004 |page= 187 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=ls38Az4-J64C&amp;pg=PA187 |isbn= 978-0-7619-3287-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last= Joseph |editor-first= W. A. |title= Politics in China: an introduction |location= Oxford |publisher= Oxford University Press |year= 2010 |page= 308 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=kk80evDTZIYC&amp;pg=PA308 |isbn= 978-0-19-533530-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lai-wan&gt;{{Cite journal |last1= Lai-wan |last2= Eric |first2= B. |last3= Hoi-yan |first1= C. C. |title= Attitudes to and practices regarding sex selection in China |journal= Prenatal Diagnosis |volume= 26 |issue= 7 |year= 2006 |pages= 610&amp;ndash;613 |doi= 10.1002/pd.1477|pmid= 16856223 |s2cid= 222098473 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some manifestations of son preference and the devaluation of women are eliminating unwanted daughters through neglect, maltreatment, abandonment, as well as female [[infanticide]] and [[feticide]] despite laws that prohibit infanticide and [[Sex-selective abortion|sex-selective pregnancy termination.]]&lt;ref name=lai-wan/&gt;&lt;ref name=singh&gt;{{Cite journal |url= http://www.frontline.in/static/html/fl2915/stories/20120810291502200.htm |title= Man's world, legally |last= Singh |first= K. |journal= [[Frontline (magazine)|Frontline]] |volume= 29 |issue= 15 |year= 2012 |access-date= May 13, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last1= Koop |editor-first1= C. E. |editor-link1= C. Everett Koop |editor-last2= Pearson |editor-first2= C. E. |editor-last3= Schwarz |editor-first3= M. R. |title= Critical issues in global health |location= San Francisco, Calif. |publisher= Wiley |year= 2002 |page= 224 |isbn= 978-0-7879-6377-4 |quote= Across the world, male privilege is also variously reflected in giving sons preferential access to health care, sex- selective abortion, female infanticide, or trafficking in women.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In India some of these practices have contributed to skewed sex ratios in favor of male children at birth and in the first five years.&lt;ref name=weiner/&gt; Other examples of privileging male offspring are special "praying for a son" ceremonies during pregnancy, more ceremony and festivities following the birth of a boy, listing and introducing sons before daughters, and common felicitations that associate good fortune and well-being with the number of sons.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Croll |first= E. |title= Endangered daughters: discrimination and development in Asia |chapter= Ethnographic voices: disappointing daughters |chapter-url= https://books.google.com/books?id=npGRm5pNRl0C&amp;pg=PA70 |location= London |publisher= Routledge |year= 2000 |pages= 70&amp;ndash;105 |isbn= 978-0-203-17021-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reasons given for preferring sons to daughters include sons' role in religious family rites, which daughters are not permitted to perform, and the belief that sons are permanent members of the birth family whereas daughters belong to their husband's family after marriage in accordance with [[Patrilocal residence|patrilocal]] tradition. Other reasons include [[Patrilineality|patrilineal]] customs whereby only sons can carry on the family name, the obligation to pay [[dowry]] to a daughter's husband or his family, and the expectation that sons will support their birth parents financially while it is regarded as undesirable or shameful to receive financial support from daughters.&lt;ref name=lai-wan/&gt;&lt;ref name=singh/&gt;

==See also==

{{colbegin}}
*[[Androcentrism]]
*[[Anti-discrimination law]]
*[[Chauvinism]]
*[[Gender]]
*[[Gender marking in job titles]]
*[[Gender bias on Wikipedia]]
*[[Harem effect (science)]]
*[[Honorary male]]
*[[Generic antecedent]]
*[[Global Gender Gap Report]]
*[[Male as norm]]
{{colend}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==

* {{Cite journal | last = Branscombe | first = Nyla R. | title = Thinking about one's gender group's privileges or disadvantages: consequences for well-being in women and men | journal = British Journal of Social Psychology | volume = 37 | issue = 2 | pages = 167–184 | doi = 10.1111/j.2044-8309.1998.tb01163.x | date = June 1998 | pmid = 9639862 | url = https://www.researchgate.net/publication/13644510 }}
* {{Cite book | last1 = Ferber | first1 = Marianne A. | last2 = Blau | first2 = Francine D. | last3 = Winkler | first3 = Anne E. | author-link1 = Marianne Ferber | author-link2 = Francine D. Blau | title = The economics of women, men, and work | publisher = Pearson | location = Boston | year = 2014 | edition = 7th | isbn = 9780132992817 }}
* {{Cite book | last = Jacobs | first = Michael P. | chapter = Do gay men have a stake in male privilege? | editor-last1 = Gluckman | editor-first1 = Amy | editor-last2 = Reed | editor-first2 = Betsy | title = Homo economics: capitalism, community, and lesbian and gay life | pages = 165–184 | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 1997 | isbn = 9780415913799 | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ll-xBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA165 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Kimmel | first = Michael S. | author-link = Michael Kimmel | title = Men's responses to feminism at the turn of the century | journal = [[Gender &amp; Society]] | volume = 1 | issue = 3 | pages = 261&amp;ndash;283 | doi = 10.1177/089124387001003003 | jstor = 189564 | date = September 1987 | s2cid = 145428652 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Kolb | first = Kenneth H. | title = 'Supporting our black men': reproducing male privilege in a black student political organization |journal = Sociological Spectrum | volume = 27 | issue = 3 | pages = 257–274 | doi = 10.1080/02732170701206106 | date = 2007 | s2cid = 144812653 | url = https://www.researchgate.net/publication/238399712 }}
* {{Cite book |editor1-last=Kimmel |editor1-first=Michael |editor2-last=Ferber |editor2-first=Abby L. |title=Privilege: A Reader |date=2003 |publisher=Westview Press |location=Boulder, Colorado |isbn=978-0-8133-4056-2}}
* {{cite journal | last = Messner | first = Michael A. | author-link = Michael Messner | title = The limits of 'The Male Sex Role': an analysis of the men's liberation and men's rights movements' discourse | journal = [[Gender &amp; Society]] | volume = 12 | issue = 3 | pages = 255&amp;ndash;276 | doi = 10.1177/0891243298012003002 | jstor = 190285 | date = June 1998 | s2cid = 143890298 }} [http://www.michaelmessner.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/Gender-Society-1998-MESSNER-255-76.pdf Pdf.]
* {{Cite journal |last1= Noble |first1= Carolyn |last2= Pease |first2= Bob |title= Interrogating male privilege in the human services and social work education |journal= Women in Welfare Education |volume= 10 |issue= 1 |pages= 29–38 |date= 2011 |url= http://www.anzswwer.org/wiwe/default.htm |url-status= bot: unknown |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20170823085758/http://www.anzswwer.org/wiwe/default.htm |archive-date= August 23, 2017 }} [http://dro.deakin.edu.au/eserv/DU:30041409/pease-interrogatingmale-2011.pdf Pdf.]
* {{cite journal |last1=Orelus |first1=Pierre W. |title=Unmasking male, heterosexual, and racial privileges: from naive complicity to critical awareness and praxis |journal=Counterpoints |volume=351 |pages=17–62 |date=2010 |jstor = 42980551 }}
* {{Cite journal |last1= Pratto |first1= Felicia |last2= Stewart |first2= Andrew L. |title= Group dominance and the half-blindness of privilege |journal= Journal of Social Issues |volume= 68 |issue= 1 |pages= 28–45 |doi= 10.1111/j.1540-4560.2011.01734.x | date = March 2012 }}
* {{Cite journal |last1= Schmitt |first1= Michael T. |last2= Branscombe |first2= Nyla R. |title= The meaning and consequences of perceived discrimination in disadvantaged and privileged groups |journal= European Review of Social Psychology |volume= 12 |issue= 1 |pages= 167–199 | doi = 10.1080/14792772143000058 | date = 2002 |s2cid= 143953546 | url = https://www.researchgate.net/publication/233204900 }}

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Men]]
[[Category:Gender equality]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Social privilege]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>