<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20220824142316|1106421344" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3880802" pageid="3880802" ns="0" title="Jewish feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-08-29T13:57:52Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Feminist movement within Judaism}}
{{Cleanup|reason=Israel section needs cleanup. Formatting is essentially a bullet list of various events relating to the general topic of women in Israel, not necessarily the women's rights movement in Israel|date=June 2020}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2020}}
{{Jewish feminism}}
{{Feminism sidebar |Variants (religious)}}
{{Jews and Judaism sidebar |Politics}}

'''Jewish feminism''' is a movement that seeks to make the religious, legal, and [[social status]] of Jewish women equal to that of Jewish men in [[Judaism]]. Feminist movements, with varying approaches and successes, have opened up within all major branches of the Jewish religion.

In its modern form, the Jewish feminist movement can be traced to the early 1970s in the [[United States]]. According to [[Judith Plaskow]], the main grievances of early Jewish feminists were women's exclusion from the all-male prayer group or ''[[minyan]]'', women's exemption from [[Positive time-bound mitzvot|positive time-bound]] ''[[Mitzvah|mitzvot]]'' (mitzvot meaning the 613 commandments given in the Torah at Mount Sinai and the seven rabbinic commandments instituted later, for a total of 620), and women's inability to function as witnesses and to initiate [[Jewish view of marriage#Divorce|divorce]] in Jewish religious courts.&lt;ref name=Plaskow1997&gt;Plaskow, Judith. "Jewish Feminist Thought" in Frank, Daniel H. &amp; Leaman, Oliver. ''History of Jewish Philosophy'', Routledge, first published 1997; this edition 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to historian [[Paula Hyman]], two articles published in the 1970s were trailblazers in analyzing the status of Jewish women using feminism: "The Unfreedom of Jewish Women", published in 1970 in the ''Jewish Spectator'' by its editor, [[Trude Weiss-Rosmarin]], and an article by [[Rachel Adler]], then an [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jew]] and currently a professor at the Reform seminary [[Hebrew Union College-Jewish Institute of Religion]], called "[http://jwa.org/sites/jwa.org/files/mediaobjects/the_jew_who_wasnt_there_adler.jpg  The Jew Who Wasn't There: Halacha and the Jewish Woman]", published in 1971 in ''Davka''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/hyman-paula-e |title=Paula E. Hyman &amp;#124; Jewish Women's Archive |publisher=Jwa.org |access-date=2017-06-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Dr. Paula Hyman |url=http://www.myjewishlearning.com/article/american-jewish-feminism-beginnings/ |title=American Jewish Feminism: Beginnings |publisher=My Jewish Learning |date=2014-01-31 |access-date=2017-06-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="blogs1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://velveteenrabbi.blogs.com/blog/2013/01/reprint-interview-with-rachel-adler-in-anticipation-of-ohalah.html |title=Velveteen Rabbi: Reprint: Interview with Rachel Adler (in anticipation of OHALAH) |publisher=Velveteenrabbi.blogs.com |date=2013-01-10 |access-date=2017-06-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/the-state-of-reform-judaism-today |title=The State of Reform Judaism Today |publisher=Jewishvirtuallibrary.org |access-date=2017-06-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Las2015"&gt;{{cite book|author=Nelly Las|title=Jewish Voices in Feminism: Transnational Perspectives|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sa0oDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA85|year=2015|publisher=U of Nebraska Press|isbn=978-0-8032-7704-5|pages=85–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Davka"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/sites/jwa.org/files/mediaobjects/the_jew_who_wasnt_there_adler.jpg|title=THE JEW WHO WASN'T THERE: Halacha and the Jewish Woman |publisher=Jewish Women's Archive }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/adler-rachel |title=Rachel Adler &amp;#124; Jewish Women's Archive |publisher=Jwa.org |access-date=2017-06-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, in 1973, the first [American] National Jewish Women's Conference was held, in New York City; [[Blu Greenberg]] gave its opening address.&lt;ref name="Antler1997"&gt;{{cite book|author=Joyce Antler|title=The Journey Home: Jewish Women and the American Century|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ra-Setymi6cC&amp;pg=PA292|year=1997|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=978-0-684-83444-3|pages=292–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Jewish feminist theology ==

Various versions of [[feminist theology]] exist within the Jewish community.

Some of these theologies promote the idea that it is important to have a feminine characterization of God, and/or more feminist language in general, within the [[siddur]] (Jewish prayerbook) and service.

In 1946, the new Silverman siddur of Conservative Judaism changed the traditional words of thanking God for "not making me a woman", instead using words thanking God for "making me a free person."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Newman |first=Debra |url=http://www.stljewishlight.com/opinion/commentaries/article_c8986454-85df-11e8-b2ce-bb83d5ec9e06.html |title=Conservative movement is closing its gender gap, but there is still work to be done - St. Louis Jewish Light: Commentaries - Conservative movement is closing its gender gap, but there is still work to be done: Commentaries |publisher=Stljewishlight.com |access-date=2018-07-12 |archive-date=12 July 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180712181359/http://www.stljewishlight.com/opinion/commentaries/article_c8986454-85df-11e8-b2ce-bb83d5ec9e06.html |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1976, [[Rita Gross]] published the article "Female God Language in a Jewish Context" (Davka Magazine 17), which Jewish scholar and feminist [[Judith Plaskow]] considers "probably the first article to deal theoretically with the issue of female God-language in a Jewish context".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myjewishlearning.com/beliefs/Issues/Gender_and_Feminism/Feminist_Thought/Theology.shtml |title=Jewish Feminist Theology: A Survey |publisher=My Jewish Learning |access-date=2012-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dhushara.com/book/torah/cardoza/ssin.htm |title=Standing at Sinai |publisher=Dhushara.com |access-date=2012-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; &amp;nbsp;Gross was Jewish herself at this time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SJs-aLqCiF8C&amp;q=rita+gross+jew&amp;pg=PA200 |title=Jewish Mysticism and Kabbalah: New Insights and Scholarship - Frederick Greenspahn - Google Books |date= November 2011|access-date=2012-07-17|isbn=9780814733363 |last1=Greenspahn |first1=Frederick E. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Reconstructionist Judaism|Reconstructionist]] [[Rabbi]] [[Rebecca Alpert]] (''Reform Judaism'', Winter 1991) comments:
{{blockquote|The experience of praying with ''Siddur Nashim'' [the first Jewish prayer book to refer to God using female pronouns and imagery, published by [[Margaret Wenig]] and Naomi Janowitz in 1976&lt;ref name="Weber2019"&gt;{{cite book|author=Shannon Weber|title=Feminism in Minutes|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=buJ6DwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA286|date=4 June 2019|publisher=Quercus|isbn=978-1-63506-142-0|pages=286–}}&lt;/ref&gt;]  ... transformed my relationship with God. For the first time, I understood what it meant to be made in God's image. To think of God as a woman like myself, to see Her as both powerful and nurturing, to see Her imaged with a woman's body, with womb, with breasts – this was an experience of ultimate significance. Was this the relationship that men have had with God for all these millennia? How wonderful to gain access to those feelings and perceptions.}}

In 1990 Rabbi [[Margaret Wenig]] wrote the sermon, "God Is a Woman and She Is Growing Older," which as of 2011 has been published ten times (three times in German) and preached by rabbis from Australia to California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://huc.edu/faculty/faculty/MargaretWenig.shtml |title= StackPath|website=huc.edu |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130623080230/http://huc.edu/faculty/faculty/MargaretWenig.shtml |archive-date=23 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rabbi [[Paula Reimers]] ("Feminism, Judaism, and God the Mother", ''Conservative Judaism'' '''46''' (1993)) comments:
{{blockquote|Those who want to use God/She language want to affirm womanhood and the feminine aspect of the deity. They do this by emphasizing that which most clearly distinguishes the female experience from the male. A male or female deity can create through speech or through action, but the metaphor for creation which is uniquely feminine is birth. Once God is called female, then, the metaphor of birth and the identification of the deity with nature and its processes become inevitable}}

Ahuva Zaches affirms that using both masculine and feminine language for God can be a positive thing, but reminds her Reform Jewish readership that God is beyond gender (''Is God male, female, both or neither? How should we phrase our prayers in response to God's gender?'', in the [[Union for Reform Judaism]]'s iTorah, [https://archive.today/20120715190459/http://urj.org/Articles/index.cfm?id=11422]):

{{blockquote|Feminine imagery of God does not in any way threaten Judaism. On the contrary, it enhances the Jewish understanding of God, which should not be limited to masculine metaphors. All language that humans use to describe God is only a metaphor. Using masculine and feminine metaphors for God is one way to remind ourselves that gendered descriptions of God are just metaphors. God is beyond gender.}}

These views are highly controversial even within liberal Jewish movements.&lt;ref&gt;"This genderless God also represents a profound betrayal of the Torah narrative."  Matthew Berke, "God and Gender in Judaism", in Copyright (c) 1996 ''First Things'' 64 (June/July 1996): 33–38&lt;/ref&gt; [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jews]] and many [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative Jews]]
hold that it is wrong to use English female pronouns for God, viewing such usage as an intrusion of modern feminist ideology into Jewish tradition.{&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Mirsky|first1=Yehudah|title=Feminine Images of God|url=https://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/feminine-images-of-god|website=jwa.org|access-date=30 March 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;} Liberal prayerbooks tend increasingly to also avoid male-specific words and pronouns, seeking that all references to God in translations be made in gender-neutral language. For example, the [[Liberal Judaism (UK)|UK Liberal movement]]'s ''Siddur Lev Chadash'' (1995) does so, as does the [[Reform Judaism (UK)|UK Reform Movement]]'s ''Forms of Prayer'' (2008).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thejc.com/articles/the-slimline-siddur-a-touch-bob-dylan|title=The slimline siddur with a touch of Bob Dylan}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bwpjc.org/slc.htm Siddur Lev Chadash&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080705015023/http://www.bwpjc.org/slc.htm |date= 5 July 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Mishkan T'filah]], the American Reform Jewish prayer book released in 2007, references to God as "He" have been removed, and whenever Jewish patriarchs are named (Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob), so also are the matriarchs (Sarah, Rebecca, Rachel, and Leah).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/03/us/03prayerbook.html?_r=1 | work=The New York Times | first=Laurie | last=Goodstein | title=In New Prayer Book, Signs of Broad Change | date=3 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2015 the Reform Jewish [[High Holy Days]] prayer book [[Mishkan HaNefesh]] was released; it is intended as a companion to Mishkan T'filah.&lt;ref name="jweekly1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jweekly.com/article/full/74278/gates-of-repentance-replacement-advances-reform-trends/ |title='Gates of Repentance' replacement advances Reform trends &amp;#124; j. the Jewish news weekly of Northern California |publisher=Jweekly.com |date=2015-03-26 |access-date=2015-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; It includes a version of the High Holy Days prayer [[Avinu Malkeinu]] that refers to God as both "Loving Father" and "Compassionate Mother."&lt;ref name="jweekly1"/&gt; Other notable changes are replacing a line from the Reform movement's earlier prayerbook, "Gates of Repentance," that mentioned the joy of a bride and groom specifically, with the line "rejoicing with couples under the chuppah [wedding canopy]", and adding a third, non-gendered option to the way worshippers are called to the Torah, offering "mibeit", Hebrew for "from the house of", in addition to the traditional "son of" or "daughter of".&lt;ref name="jweekly1"/&gt;

In 2003 ''The Female Face of God in Auschwitz: A Jewish Feminist Theology of the Holocaust'', the first full-length feminist theology of the Holocaust, written by Melissa Raphael, was published.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Female Face of God in Auschwitz: A Jewish Feminist Theology of the Holocaust (Religion and Gender): Melissa Raphael: 9780415236652: Amazon.com: Books|isbn = 0415236657|last1 = Raphael|first1 = Melissa|year = 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Judith Plaskow]]'s ''Standing Again at Sinai: Judaism from a Feminist Perspective'' (1991), and [[Rachel Adler]]'s ''Engendering Judaism: An Inclusive Theology and Ethics'' (1999) are the only two full-length Jewish feminist works to focus entirely on theology in general (rather than specific aspects such as Holocaust theology).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/feminist-theology|title=Feminist Theology}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, ''Standing Again at Sinai: Judaism from a Feminist Perspective'' (1991) is the first book of Jewish feminist theology ever written.

There is a growing subfield in the study of gender and Judaism, which sees the binaries of male and female as crucial constructs in Jewish thought.&lt;ref&gt;Kosman, Miriam, Circle, Arrow, Spiral, Exploring Gender in Judaism, Menucha Publishers, 2014. ^&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Steven F. Friedell, "The 'Different Voice' in Jewish Law: Some Parallels to a Feminist Jurisprudence," Indiana Law Journal, October 1992&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Neusner, Jacob, 'Androgynous Judaism: Masculine and Feminine in the Dual Torah,' Wipf and Stock Publishers, 1993.  ^&lt;/ref&gt;

While the male/female dialectic first makes its appearance in the story of creation, the Talmud insists that the idea of male and female extends way beyond sex roles: "Everything that God created, He created as male and female...."(Baba Batra 74b)

This dialectic takes on even greater theological significance in light of the Biblical book, Song of Songs, which has been traditionally interpreted as a metaphor for the relationship between God and the Nation of Israel, where the Nation of Israel is cast as feminine towards God, who is represented in the story by the male lover.

Other examples of topics in which the male/female dynamic is used metaphorically include: the relationship between Shabbat and the days of the week[8], the relationship between the Oral and Written Law, the relationship between This World and the Next, the interplay between the legal and extra-legal aspects of Talmud (Halacha and Aggada)[9], and the Jewish calendar, which makes use of both the sun (traditionally symbolic of the male force) and the moon (traditionally symbolic of the female force).&lt;ref&gt;Heshelis, Devorah, The Moon's Lost Light, Targum Press, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

Gender polarity is robustly maintained in both the Bible and in the Oral Law, (Deuteronomy, 22:5, even forbids cross-dressing) and upholding this polarity is seen as critical in achieving synthesis between the masculine and feminine.

This exploration of gender-constructs in primary sources reveals surprising valuation of the feminine prototype in Kabbala-based sources which invites inquiry into the social, ethical, ecological, moral and philosophical ramifications of a feminine perspective within Jewish thought&lt;ref&gt;. Rinder Sarah, "A New, Sophisticated, Haredi View on Gender" The Forward, 24 November 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

== Orthodox Judaism==
The position on feminism within the Orthodox denomination of Judaism is broadly divided along the factional lines of the [[modern Orthodox Judaism|modern Orthodox]] and [[Haredi]] communities, with the modern Orthodox favourable to certain advances for women, provided they are maintained within the framework of [[Halakha|Jewish law]] (''halakha''). Haredi Judaism maintains a stricter stance on issues pertaining to feminism.

===Modern Orthodox approaches===
Orthodox feminism works within the halakhic system and works with rabbis and rabbinical institutions to create more inclusive practices within Orthodox communal life and leadership. Orthodox feminism tends to focus on issues, such as the problems of [[agunah]], fostering women's education, leadership, and ritual participation, women's leadership and making synagogue more women-friendly. Unlike other denominations, Orthodox feminists retain the partition in synagogue and do not count women in a minyan. The all-women's prayer group—Women's Tefilla Group, is an Orthodox practice that began in the 1970s and continues today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=JOFA|title=JOFA [Jewish Orthodox Feminist Alliance]|url=http://www.jofa.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

New educational programs have enabled Modern Orthodox women to study Talmud and other rabbinic literature, at levels intended to be comparable to a yeshivah or kollel for men, including [[Drisha Institute]] (founded in 1979), [[Pardes Institute of Jewish Studies]], and [[Matan Women's Institute for Torah Studies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Women and the Study of Torah|isbn=9780881256901|page=xiv|last1=Wolowelsky|first1=Joel B.|year=2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997, [[Blu Greenberg]] founded the [[Jewish Orthodox Feminist Alliance]] (JOFA) to advocate for women's increased participation and leadership in Modern Orthodox Jewish life and to create a community for women and men dedicated to such change.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jofa.org Jewish Orthodox Feminist Alliance]. Jofa.org (14 April 2011). Retrieved on 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; JOFA has focused on issues including: agunah, bat mitzvah, women's scholarship, women's prayer, ritual, women's synagogue leadership, and women's religious leadership.

Also in 1997, Gail Billig became the first female president of a major Orthodox synagogue, at [[Congregation Ahavath Torah]] in Englewood, N.J.&lt;ref name="womensenews.org"&gt;Klein, Abigail. (13 July 2007) [http://womensenews.org/story/religion/070713/leaders-lift-spirit-in-orthodox-womens-section Leaders Lift Spirit in Orthodox Women's Section]. Women's eNews. Retrieved on 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, the first [[partnership minyan]]s were established—Shira Hadasha in Jerusalem, and Darkhei Noam in New York City. These are Orthodox communities that maximize women's participation in the prayer to the full extent possible within halakha. Although critics of partnership minyan argue that these are not "Orthodox", the communities themselves vehemently insist that they are Orthodox. The fact that the synagogues have partitions and do not count women as part of the minyan (and thus do not allow women to lead any parts of services that require a quorum) demonstrate the loyalty to Orthodox practice. Dr. Elana Sztokman, former executive director of JOFA, wrote extensively about this phenomenon in her book The Men's Section: Orthodox Jewish Men in an Egalitarian World, and examined this dynamic in which the partnership minyan considers itself Orthodox but is often rejected as Orthodox by other members of the community. Today there are over 35 partnership minyans around the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Sztokman|first=Elana|title=The Men's Section: Orthodox Jewish Men in an Egalitarian World|year=2011|publisher=Brandeis University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another major historical event of Orthodox feminism occurred in 2009, when Rabba [[Sara Hurwitz]] became the first publicly ordained Orthodox woman rabbi. [[Avi Weiss]] then launched a training school for Orthodox women in rabbinic positions, [[Yeshivat Maharat]] (acronym for "Morah hilkhatit rabbanit toranit"—a rabbinic, halakhic Torah teacher.) Rabbi Weiss had originally announced that graduates would be called "rabba", but when the Rabbinical Council of America threatened to oust him, he recanted and created the term ''[[maharat]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Sara Hurwitz Adopts the Title of Maharat|url=http://jwa.org/thisweek/jan/27/2010/sara-hurwitz|newspaper=Jewish Women's Archives|date=27 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first cohort of [[maharat]]s graduated in June 2013: Maharats Ruth Balinsky-Friedman, [[Rachel Kohl Finegold]] and [[Abby Brown Scheier]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Reimer-Torn|first=Susan|title=Maharats March into Jewish World First-ever ordination at Orthodox women's seminary seen as 'sea change,' but steep hurdles persist.|url=http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/national-news/maharats-march-jewish-world|access-date=26 February 2014|newspaper=The Jewish Week|date=2013-06-19|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130624092654/http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/national-news/maharats-march-jewish-world|archive-date=24 June 2013|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2015 Yaffa Epstein was ordained as Rabba by the [[Yeshivat Maharat]].&lt;ref name="auto9"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yeshivatmaharat.org/class-of-2015/|title=Class of 2015|work=Yeshivat Maharat|access-date=5 January 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151205231641/http://www.yeshivatmaharat.org/class-of-2015/|archive-date=5 December 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also that year [[Lila Kagedan]] was ordained as Rabbi by the [[Yeshivat Maharat]], making her their first graduate to take the title Rabbi.&lt;ref name="auto10"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cjnews.com/living-jewish/jewish-learning/why-orthodox-judaism-needs-female-rabbis|title=Why Orthodox Judaism needs female rabbis|author=Rabbi Lila Kagedan|date=25 November 2015|work=The Canadian Jewish News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2013 Tamar Frankiel became the president of the [[Academy for Jewish Religion (California)|Academy for Jewish Religion]] in California, making her the first Orthodox woman to lead an American rabbinical school.&lt;ref name="ajrca.org"&gt;[http://ajrca.org/faculty/dr-tamar-frankiel/ Dr. Tamar Frankiel | Academy for Jewish Religion, California&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111228055346/http://ajrca.org/faculty/dr-tamar-frankiel/ |date=28 December 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="jewishjournal.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishjournal.com/los_angeles/article/orthodox_woman_a_first|title=Orthodox woman, a first - Los Angeles|work=Jewish Journal|date=16 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The school itself is transdenominational, not Orthodox.&lt;ref name="jewishjournal.com"/&gt;

In 2013 the Israeli Orthodox rabbinical organization Beit Hillel issued a [[halacha|halachic]] ruling which allows women, for the first time, to say the [[Kaddish]] prayer in memory of their deceased parents.&lt;ref name="ynetnews.com"/&gt;

Also in 2013, the first class of female [[halacha|halachic]] advisers trained to practice in the US graduated; they graduated from the North American branch of [[Nishmat]]'s yoetzet halacha program in a ceremony at Congregation Sheartith Israel, Spanish and Portuguese Synagogue in Manhattan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timesofisrael.com/landmark-us-program-graduates-first-female-halachic-advisers/|title=Landmark US program graduates first female halachic advisers|work=The Times of Israel}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this event was met with only faint enthusiasm among Orthodox feminists for several reasons. One is that Nishmat consistently distances itself from feminism, as its founder Chana Henkin often pronounces that she is not a feminist and that the women who graduate from Nishmat do not adjudicate halakha but always ask male rabbis. Another reason is that against the backdrop of the graduation of women from Yeshivat Maharat, in which women are full leaders with complete authority to adjudicate and function as communal rabbis this event does not necessarily represent the greatest advancement for Orthodox women and is arguably a step backward. That is, women counseling women only on "women's issues" without any real halakhic authority of their own keeps women in a somewhat more official version of traditional gender roles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Graetz|first=Naomi|title=Women and Religion in Israel|year=2003|publisher=Brandeis University Press|location=in Melanie Rich and Kalpana Misra, Jewish feminism in Israel|page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, the first women were elected as national officers of the [[Orthodox Union]]; specifically, three female national vice presidents and two female associate vice presidents were elected.&lt;ref name="jstandard.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jstandard.com/content/item/o.u._acts_to_increase_funding_for_schools_and_votes_first_women_to_national/32193|title=O.U. acts to increase funding for schools and votes first women to national posts}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2015, [[Lila Kagedan]] was ordained by [[Yeshivat Maharat]] and in keeping with newer policies, was given the freedom to choose her own title, and she chose to be addressed as "Rabbi".&lt;ref name="auto11"&gt;''Canadian Jewish News'' [http://www.cjnews.com/living-jewish/jewish-learning/why-orthodox-judaism-needs-female-rabbis Why Orthodoxy Needs Female Rabbis], 25 November 2015&lt;/ref&gt; In 2015, Rabbi Kagedan completed a residency at [[Shira Hadasha]] in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://macroscope.com.au|website=Macroscope}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, in the fall of 2015, the [[Rabbinical Council of America]], representing over a thousand Orthodox rabbis across the United States, formally adopted a policy prohibiting the ordination or hiring of women rabbis by synagogues that operate within the boundaries of their figurative jurisdiction, regardless of title.&lt;ref name="auto12"&gt;''Times of Israel'' [http://www.timesofisrael.com/first-yeshivat-maharat-female-rabbi-hired-by-orthodox-synagogue/ First Yeshivat Maharat Female Rabbi Hired by Orthodox Synagogue], 3 January 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2015, the Israeli Orthodox rabbinical organization Beit Hillel issued a ruling which allows women to give instruction on Jewish law and to issue [[halacha|halachic]] decisions.&lt;ref name="ynetnews.com"/&gt;&lt;ref name="jpost.com1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jpost.com/Israel-News/Beit-Hillel-says-women-can-give-rulings-in-Jewish-law-387019|title=Beit Hillel says women can give rulings in Jewish law|work=The Jerusalem Post - JPost.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beit Hillel claimed that this ruling was the first time women issuing halachic rulings was formally affirmed in a written [[responsa]] of Jewish law.&lt;ref name="jpost.com1"/&gt;

Also in 2015, Jennie Rosenfeld became the first female Orthodox spiritual advisor in Israel (specifically, she became the spiritual advisor, also called manhiga ruchanit, for the community of [[Efrat]].)&lt;ref name="auto2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jns.org/latest-articles/2015/1/26/with-female-spiritual-advisor-efrat-spotlights-womens-empowerment-in-israel#.VMZhzS7lw4I=|title=With female spiritual advisor, Efrat spotlights women's empowerment in Israel|work=JNS.org|access-date=26 January 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150207204326/http://www.jns.org/latest-articles/2015/1/26/with-female-spiritual-advisor-efrat-spotlights-womens-empowerment-in-israel#.VMZhzS7lw4I=|archive-date=7 February 2015|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2015, the first Israeli political party dedicated to Haredi women was unveiled, called "B'Zhutan: Haredi Women Making Change."&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt;

In 2016 it was announced that [[Ephraim Mirvis]] created the job of ma'ayan by which women would be advisers on Jewish law in the area of family purity and as adult educators in Orthodox synagogues.&lt;ref name="thejc.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejc.com/news/uk-news/153491/chief-rabbi-mirvis-launches-new-qualification-female-educators|title=Chief Rabbi Mirvis launches new qualification for female educators}}&lt;/ref&gt; This requires a part-time training course for 18 months, which is the first such course in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name="thejc.com"/&gt;

In 2017, the [[Orthodox Union]] adopted a policy banning women from serving as clergy, from holding titles such as "rabbi", or from doing common clergy functions even without a title, in its congregations in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jweekly.com/2017/02/03/orthodox-union-bars-women-from-serving-as-clergy-in-its-synagogues/ |title=Orthodox Union bars women from serving as clergy in its synagogues – J |date=3 February 2017 |publisher=Jweekly.com |access-date=2017-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Haredi approaches===
The leaders of [[Haredi Judaism]] regularly pronounce all forms of feminism as "Reform," as non-Jewish, or as a threat to Jewish tradition. An article in Cross-currents criticizing advancing women's leadership writes that: "The entirety of traditional Jewish religious life, including its age-old ritual norms and societal norms, even if they lack formal codification, reflects Torah values, be they halachic or hashkafic; every aspect of our multi-millennia traditional religious communal modality is embedded in or predicated upon halachic or hashkafic axioms. These axioms may not be apparent to the uninitiated, yet failure to perceive them does not grant license to negate, dismiss or reform."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gordimer|first=Avrohom|title=Ordaining Women and the Role of Mesorah|url=http://www.cross-currents.com/archives/2013/06/03/what-about-mesorah-do-you-not-understand/#ixzz2uVOmqFmJ|access-date=26 February 2014|newspaper=Cross-currents|date=3 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The haredi claim is that feminism is changing Torah.

Haredi Judaism also espouses strict essentialist differences between men and women, rooted in ideas about God's will and creation. The haredi worldview espouses the idea of womanhood as expressed in King Solomon's poem "A Woman of Valor," which praises a woman for maintaining the home, care for the family, and food preparation, practices which the poem admires in women as part of their wisdom, courage, creativity, dedication, selflessness, and perhaps business acumen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aish.com/ci/w/48955426.html |title=Feminism &amp; Judaism |last=Heller |first=Rebbetzin Tziporah |author-link=Tziporah Heller|publisher=aish.com |date=8 January 2000 |access-date=23 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The most important thrust of haredi education for girls and young women is to educate, train and encourage them to become wives and mothers within large families devoted to the strictest [[Torah Judaism]] way of life. While most haredi women receive schooling in [[Beis Yaakov]] schools designed for them exclusively, the curriculum of these schools does not teach [[Talmud]] and neither encourages nor teaches its female students to study the same subjects as young haredi men in the haredi [[yeshiva]]s. In some haredi communities, the education of girls in secular subjects (such as mathematics) is superior to that of boys.  This is partly because of the greater time devoted to sacred subjects in the case of boys, and partly because many haredi women work in paid jobs to enable their husbands to engage in full-time Torah study or to bring in a second income.

There is currently no movement within haredi Judaism to train women as [[rabbi]]s, and there is no visible movement to advance women's Talmudic knowledge.  
In the fall of 2015, the [[Agudath Israel of America]], which is part of haredi Judaism, denounced moves to ordain women, and went even further, declaring [[Yeshivat Maharat]], [[Yeshivat Chovevei Torah]], [[Open Orthodoxy]], and other affiliated entities to be similar to other dissident movements throughout Jewish history in having rejected basic tenets of Judaism.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hamodia.com/2015/11/03/moetzes-open-orthodoxy-not-a-form-of-torah-judaism/|title=Moetzes: 'Open Orthodoxy' Not a Form of Torah Judaism|work=Hamodia}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="auto7"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jpost.com/Diaspora/Breach-in-US-Orthodox-Judaism-grows-as-haredi-body-rejects-Open-Orthodoxy-institutions-431929|title=Breach in US Orthodox Judaism grows as haredi body rejects 'Open Orthodoxy' institutions|work=The Jerusalem Post - JPost.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="auto8"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://forward.com/news/323887/agudath-rabbis-declare-war-on-open-orthodoxy/|title=Avi Weiss Defends 'Open Orthodoxy' as Agudah Rabbis Declare War|author=Josh Nathan-Kazis|date=3 November 2015|work=The Forward}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, most haredi women are exposed to modern ideas and secular education, unlike most haredi men. Prof. Tamar El-or explored changes in women's lives and the impact of mixed educational cultures on women's empowerment in her seminal book, ''Educated and Ignorant'' about the education of women in the Gur Hassidic community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=El-Or|first=Tamar|title=Educated and Ignorant: Ultraorthodox Jewish Women and their World .|year=1994|publisher=Lynne Rienner Pub.|location=Boulder, CO}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 2016 it was learned that the [[Satmar (Hasidic dynasty)|Satmar]] sect issued a decree warning that university education for women was "dangerous". Written in Yiddish, the decree warned:&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/ultra-orthodox-rabbis-ban-women-from-going-to-university-in-case-they-get-dangerous-secular-a7204171.html |archive-url=https://ghostarchive.org/archive/20220608/https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/ultra-orthodox-rabbis-ban-women-from-going-to-university-in-case-they-get-dangerous-secular-a7204171.html |archive-date=8 June 2022 |url-access=subscription |url-status=live|title=Ultra-Orthodox Jewish sect bans women from going to university|date=2016-08-22|language=en-GB|access-date=2016-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

"''It has lately become the new trend that girls and married women are pursuing degrees in special education. Some attend classes and others online. And so we'd like to let their parents know that it is against the Torah.''

''We will be very strict about this. No girls attending our school are allowed to study and get a degree. It is dangerous. Girls who will not abide will be forced to leave our school. Also, we will not give any jobs or teaching position in the school to girls who've been to college or have a degree.''

''We have to keep our school safe and we can't allow any secular influences in our holy environment. It is against the base upon which our Mosed was built."''&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

There are some signs of a feminist movement beginning to sprout in the haredi world, especially in Israel. During the 2013 Israeli elections, Esti Shushan led a feminist drive to force haredi political parties to allow women to run on their lists (the parties currently forbid women from running). The campaign, called on haredi women to refuse to vote for parties that exclude women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Jeffay|first=Nathan|title=Israeli elections: Charedi women refuse to vote|url=http://www.thejc.com/news/israel-news/97420/israeli-elections-charedi-women-refuse-vote|access-date=26 February 2014|newspaper=The Jewish Chronicle|date=10 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, during the 2013 municipal elections in Israel, three haredi women took an unprecedented step and ran for their local municipalities—Shira Gergi in Safed, Ruth Colian in Petach Tikva, and Racheli Ibenboim in Jerusalem. Gergi is the only one who was elected, becoming the first haredi woman to sit on a municipal council, and becoming the first woman on the Safed council in twenty years.

One of the most interesting voices of haredi feminism is that of [[Adina Bar-Shalom]], daughter of the late Israeli Sephardic Chief Rabbi [[Ovadia Yosef]]. Bar Shalom established the Haredi College of Jerusalem, regularly speaks out about the importance of women's education and work, and in 2013 established a women's-only political party in the haredi town of Elad. In addition, in early 2014 she considered a bid to become the president of Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Haaretz|title=Next goal of Shas leader's daughter: Israeli presidency Adina Bar Shalom, oldest daughter of Ovadia Yosef and founder of ultra-Orthodox college in Jerusalem, said to be angling for Shimon Peres' job.|url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/national/1.569976|access-date=26 February 2014|newspaper=Haaretz|date=22 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2014, Bar-Shalom wrote that the haredi feminist revolution is already here. "The train has left the station," she wrote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Bar-Shalom|first=Adina|title=Haredi feminism is already here|url=http://www.jewfem.com/index.php?option=com_easyblog&amp;view=entry&amp;id=419&amp;Itemid=233|publisher=Translated by Elana Maryles Sztokman}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another emerging haredi voice is that of Esty Reider-Indorsky. She "came out" in March 2014 as a popular haredi columnist who had been writing under a man's name—"Ari Solomon"—and has a large following under her pseudonym. In an article in YNet, Reider-Indorsky claimed that there is a strong feminist movement brewing in the haredi community, and asked non-haredi women to stay out of their own internal revolution. "Don't patronize us," she writes to non-haredi feminists. "Don't make revolutions for us, or try to clean out our backyard. We are doing it in our own way and we are doing it better: There is an abundance of haredi women lawyers and women in start-up.... There are haredi women who choose an academic career, and there are haredi women leading change in every area imaginable... The change will happen. it's already happening."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rieder-Indosrky|first=Esty|title=Dear Israeli women, don't patronize us|url=http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4496840,00.html|access-date=9 March 2014|newspaper=YNet (Hebrew)|date=9 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  
 
These are signs of the beginnings of feminist movement in the haredi community in Israel.{{citation needed|date=May 2020}}

== Women in [[halacha|Jewish religious law]], clergy, schools, groups, and rituals ==
{{see|Women in Judaism|Women rabbis}}
In 1845, rabbis attending the Frankfort Synod of the emerging [[Reform Judaism]] declared women count in a [[minyan]], a formalization of a customary Reform practice dating back to 1811.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://uf.sjc.vic.edu.au/religious-traditions-depth-studies/07/39 |title=Understanding Faith &amp;#124; Title 45: Religious Traditions Depth Studies &amp;#124; Part 7: Significant People and Ideas in Judaism |access-date=2015-02-08 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140821083705/http://uf.sjc.vic.edu.au/religious-traditions-depth-studies/07/39/ |archive-date=21 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1854, [[Fanny Neuda]] wrote the first Jewish prayer book known to have been written by a woman for women, called ''Hours of Devotion''; it was translated into English and published in the United States 12 years later.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jta.org/2015/09/04/news-opinion/world/czech-author-of-first-womens-prayer-book-commemorated |title=Czech author of first women's prayer book commemorated &amp;#124; Jewish Telegraphic Agency |publisher=Jta.org |date=4 September 2015 |access-date=2015-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2015 a plaque honoring her was unveiled in [[Loštice]], where she lived while her husband was a rabbi there.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"/&gt;

In 1884, [[Julie Rosewald]] became America's first female cantor (though she was born in Germany); she served San Francisco's Temple Emanu-El, although she was not ordained.&lt;ref name="auto3"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/blog/Julie-Rosewald|title=Julie Rosewald: America's first woman cantor|access-date=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="auto4"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/short_takes/forgotten_woman_cantor_julie_rosewald_now_getting_her_due|title=The Forgotten Woman Cantor: Julie Rosewald Now Getting Her Due - The Jewish Week|work=The Jewish Week|access-date=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; She served as a cantor there until 1893.&lt;ref name="auto3"/&gt;&lt;ref name="auto4"/&gt;
[[File:RayFrankLitman.jpg|thumb|[[Ray Frank]] became the first Jewish woman to formally preach in a synagogue in 1890]]
On 14 September 1890, [[Ray Frank]] gave the Rosh Hashanah sermon for a community in Spokane, Washington, thus becoming the first woman to preach from a synagogue pulpit, although she was not a rabbi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://jwablog.jwa.org/rayfrank |title=Ray Frank: "Lady Preacher" of the West |publisher=Jwablog.jwa.org |date=2009-09-14 |access-date=2010-11-19 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101105023107/http://jwablog.jwa.org/rayfrank |archive-date=5 November 2010 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 18 March 1922, the American rabbi [[Mordecai Kaplan|Mordecai M. Kaplan]] held the first public celebration of a [[bat mitzvah]] in the United States, for his daughter Judith, at the [[Society for the Advancement of Judaism]], his synagogue in New York City.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Judaism/firstbat.html |title=The First American Bat Mitvah |publisher=Jewishvirtuallibrary.org |date=1922-03-18 |access-date=2013-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Waskow, Arthur Ocean and Phyllis Ocean Berman. Excerpt from ''A Time for Every Purpose Under Heaven'' Farrar, Straus and Giroux, LLC at {{cite web|url=http://www.myjewishlearning.com/lifecycle/Bar_Bat_Mitzvah/History/HistoryBatMitzvah.htm|title=History of Bat Mizvah|access-date=2007-10-10| archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20071013163838/http://myjewishlearning.com/lifecycle/Bar_Bat_Mitzvah/History/HistoryBatMitzvah.htm| archive-date= 13 October 2007 | url-status= live}}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Judith Kaplan Eisenstein|Judith Kaplan]] recited the preliminary blessing, read a portion of that week's Torah portion in Hebrew and English, and then intoned the closing blessing.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Kaplan, who at that time claimed to be an Orthodox rabbi, joined [[Conservative Judaism]] and then became the founder of [[Reconstructionist Judaism]], and influenced Jews from all branches of non-Orthodox Judaism through his position at the [[Jewish Theological Seminary of America]].

Also in 1922, [[Martha Neumark]] and her father attended the [[Central Conference of American Rabbis]] Conference, where she succeeded in convincing the CCAR to ordain women rabbis.&lt;ref name="bare_url_a"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/archive/jsp/perInfo.jsp?personID=1017 |title=Personal Information for Martha Montor |publisher=Jwa.org |access-date=2012-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The CCAR declared in a responsa in 1922, "...woman cannot justly be denied the privilege of ordination," having voted 56 to 11 in favor of that statement.&lt;ref name="bare_url"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Bd_AICOMwccC&amp;q=martha+neumark&amp;pg=PA392 |title=Religions of the United States in Practice - Colleen McDannell - Google Books |date=2001-10-29 |access-date=2012-04-14|isbn=0691010013 |last1=McDannell |first1=Colleen }}&lt;/ref&gt; Yet the board of the college still refused to consider women for ordination, voting (as Neumark recalled) six laymen to two rabbis against it.&lt;ref name="bare_url_a" /&gt;&lt;ref name="bare_url" /&gt; Neumark thus earned a qualification as a religious school principal instead of ordination, though she had spent 7 and a half years in rabbinical school.&lt;ref name="bare_url" /&gt;

Also in 1922 [[Irma Lindheim]] entered the Jewish Institute of Religion in New York City, though she eventually left for the "greater cause of Zionism."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lubbockonline.com/faith/2010-03-29/passover-time-join-tradition#.T4C489WZKVo |title=Passover a time to join in tradition &amp;#124; Lubbock Online &amp;#124; Lubbock Avalanche-Journal |publisher=Lubbock Online |date=2010-03-29 |access-date=2012-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; While there, in 1923, she petitioned the faculty to change her status from that of special student to a regular student in the rabbinic program; in response, in May of that year they unanimously recommended the admission of women to the institute on the same basis as men.&lt;ref name="irma"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SH8r3ntJG8AC&amp;q=%22irma+lindheim%22&amp;pg=PA127 |title=Gender and Judaism: The Transformation of Tradition - Tamar Rudavsky - Google Books |date= March 1995|access-date=2012-04-14|isbn=9780814774526 |last1=Rudavsky |first1=Tamar }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:ReginaJonas.jpg|thumb|Regina Jonas, the first formally ordained female rabbi]]
In 1935, [[Regina Jonas]] became the first formally ordained female rabbi; she was ordained by the liberal Rabbi [[Max Dienemann]], who was the head of the Liberal Rabbis' Association, in [[Offenbach am Main]], Germany.&lt;ref name="jonas"&gt;{{cite web| url= http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/jonas-regina | title=Regina Jonas &amp;#124; Jewish Women's Archive | publisher=Jwa.org | access-date=3 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="jwa"&gt;{{cite web |url= http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/jonas-regina |title=Regina Jonas 1902–1944 |author=Klapheck, Elisa |work=Jewish Women's Archive |access-date=3 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1939, [[Helen Levinthal]] became the first American woman to complete the entire course of study in a rabbinical school, which she did at the Jewish Institute of Religion in New York.&lt;ref name="hadassah"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hadassah.org/site/c.9iKRJcNRIlI2F/b.6504549/k.D5D7/Moonbeams_A_Hadassah_Rosh_Hodesh_GuidebrWomen_Rabbis.htm |archive-url=https://archive.today/20130415043759/http://www.hadassah.org/site/c.9iKRJcNRIlI2F/b.6504549/k.D5D7/Moonbeams_A_Hadassah_Rosh_Hodesh_GuidebrWomen_Rabbis.htm |url-status=dead |archive-date=15 April 2013 |title=– Hadassah Young Women |publisher=hadassah.org |access-date=14 January 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Her thesis was on women's suffrage from the point of view of Jewish law.&lt;ref name="Rabbis"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/rabbis-in-united-states|title=Rabbis in the United States – Jewish Women&amp;#039;s Archive|publisher=jwa.org|access-date=14 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, she only received a Master of Hebrew Letters (and a certificate recognizing her accomplishment) upon graduation, rather than a Master of Hebrew Letters and ordination as the men received, since the faculty felt it was not yet time for women's ordination as rabbis.&lt;ref name="google2"&gt;{{cite book|title=Encyclopedia of Women and Religion in North America: Native American creation stories|author1=Keller, R.S.|author2=Ruether, R.R.|author3=Cantlon, M.|year=2006|publisher=Indiana University Press|isbn=9780253346872|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WPILfbtT5tQC}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="google3"&gt;{{cite book|title=Women Who Would Be Rabbis: A History of Women's Ordination 1889-1985|author=Nadell, P.S.|year=1999|publisher=Beacon Press|isbn=9780807036495|url=https://archive.org/details/womenwhowouldber00nade|url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1955, the [[Committee on Jewish Law and Standards]] of Conservative Judaism declared that women were eligible to chant the blessings before and after the reading of the Torah, a privilege called "Aliyah".&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Jews of the United States|last=Diner|first=Hasia R.|publisher=University of California Press|year=2006|pages=350–358}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ReferenceA2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/conservative-judaism-in-united-states|title=Conservative Judaism in the United States}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 1962, a study found that only eight conservative congregations had fully embraced the ruling while fifty implemented it with conditions and 196 congregations still had not adopted this newfound right of Jewish women.&lt;ref name=":02"/&gt; In the late 1960s, the first Orthodox Jewish women's [[tefillah]] (prayer) group was created, on the holiday of [[Simhat Torah]] at [[Lincoln Square Synagogue]] in Manhattan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/womens-tefillah-movement|title=Women's Tefillah Movement}}&lt;/ref&gt; This development came by the judgement of the synagogue's rabbi, Shlomo Riskin.&lt;ref name=":02"/&gt; Further, the late 1960s saw Bat Mitzvahs, a public coming of age ritual for Jewish girls, become widespread after Reform, Reconstructionist, and Conservative Jews allowed women to partake in and lead a congregation in prayer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Heschel|first=Susannah|date=2007|title=Feminism|journal=Encyclopaedia Judaica|volume=6. 2nd|pages=752–757}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1973, the Committee on Jewish Law and Standards passed a [[takkanah]] (ruling) allowing women to count in a [[minyan]] equally with men.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA2" /&gt; Also in 1973, the United Synagogue of America, Conservative Judaism's congregational association (now called the United Synagogue of Conservative Judaism) resolved to allow women to participate in synagogue rituals and to promote equal opportunity for women for positions of leadership, authority, and responsibility in congregational life.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA2" /&gt; In 1974, the Committee on Jewish Law and Standards adopted a series of proposals that equalized men and women in all areas of ritual, including serving as prayer leaders.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA2" /&gt;

In the early 1970s, new rituals began popularizing. Jewish women staged public ceremonies for the birth of their daughters, sharing the ritual of [[Brit milah|"brit millah"]] which was historically reserved for newborn sons. They started forming special groups for prayer and study on [[Rosh Chodesh|Rosh Hodesh]], the beginning of the new month, with their newfound freedoms to congregate. Women also contributed to the observance of [[Passover]] by placing a goblet of water, called "Miriam's cup", on the Seder table to include her, as Moses' sister, in the narrative of his exodus from Egypt with the Jewish people.&lt;ref name=":02"/&gt;

In 1972 [[Sally Priesand]] became America's first female rabbi ordained by a rabbinical seminary, and the second formally ordained female rabbi, after [[Regina Jonas]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ejewishphilanthropy.com/americas-first-female-rabbi-reflects-on-four-decades-since-ordination/|title=America's First Female Rabbi Reflects on Four Decades Since Ordination|author=eJP|date=8 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lib.usm.edu/spcol/exhibitions/item_of_the_month/iotm_june_2013.html|title=Newspaper clipping highlights one of world's first female rabbis - Special Collections &lt;&gt; The University of Southern Mississippi Libraries}}&lt;/ref&gt; Priesand was ordained by the Reform Jewish Seminary [[Hebrew Union College-Jewish Institute of Religion]] on 3 June 1972, at the [[Plum Street Temple]] in Cincinnati.&lt;ref name="Zola20"&gt;{{cite book | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=_qkP-xe7Lp4C&amp;pg=PA20| title=Women Rabbis: Exploration &amp; Celebration: Papers Delivered at an Academic Conference Honoring Twenty Years of Women in the Rabbinate, 1972-1992 | publisher=Hebrew Union College Press | editor=Zola, Gary Phillip | year=1996 | page=20 | isbn=0-87820-214-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 1972, a group of ten New York Jewish feminists calling themselves ''Ezrat Nashim'' (the [[Mechitza|women's section in a synagogue]], but also "women's help"), took the issue of equality for women to the 1972 convention of the [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] movement's [[Rabbinical Assembly]], presenting a document on 14 March that they named the "[https://archive.org/details/jewishworldinm00jonb/page/116 Call for Change]." The rabbis received the document in their convention packets, but ''Ezrat Nashim'' presented it during a meeting with the rabbis' wives. The Call for Change demanded that women be accepted as witnesses before Jewish law, held obligated to perform all [[Mitzvah|mitzvot]], allowed full participation in religious observances, have equal rights in marriage and be allowed to initiate divorce, be counted in the [[minyan]], and be permitted to assume positions of leadership in the synagogue and within the Jewish community. [[Paula Hyman]], a member of ''Ezrat Nashim'', wrote: "We recognized that the subordinate status of women was linked to their exemption from positive time-bound ''mitzvot'' (commandments), and we therefore accepted increased obligation as the corollary of equality."&lt;ref&gt;[http://jwa.org/feminism/_html/JWA039.htm Paula Hyman], ''Jewish Women and the Feminist Revolution'', Jewish Women's Archive. (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; With supportive persuasion from Gerson Cohen, the chancellor of the Jewish Theological Seminary, the Rabbinical Assembly accepted their proposal in 1973 and the JTS in 1983.&lt;ref name=":02"/&gt;

In 1973, the Committee on Jewish Law and Standards of Conservative Judaism voted to count men and women equally as members of a [[minyan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jta.org/1973/09/11/archive/women-equal-with-men-in-minyan|title=Women Equal with Men in Minyan|work=Jewish Telegraphic Agency|date=11 September 1973}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1974 [[Sandy Eisenberg Sasso]] became the first female rabbi ordained in [[Reconstructionist Judaism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/thisweek/may/19/1974/sandy-sasso/ |title=This Week in History – Sandy Sasso ordained as first female Reconstructionist rabbi &amp;#124; Jewish Women's Archive |publisher=Jwa.org |date=19 May 1974 |access-date=3 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1975, [[Barbara Ostfeld-Horowitz]] became the first female cantor ordained in Reform Judaism.&lt;ref name="jwa.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/cantors-american-jewish-women |title=Cantors: American Jewish Women &amp;#124; Jewish Women's Archive |publisher=Jwa.org |access-date=2012-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Gloria Steinem 1977 ©Lynn Gilbert.jpg|thumb|[[Gloria Steinem]], a prominent Jewish feminist attended [[E. M. Broner|Esther M. Broner's]] 1976 women-only seder]]
In 1976, the first women-only Passover seder was held in [[E. M. Broner|Esther M. Broner's]] New York City apartment and led by her, with 13 women attending, including [[Gloria Steinem]], [[Letty Cottin Pogrebin]], and [[Phyllis Chesler]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://jwa.org/thisweek/mar/01/1993/em-broner This Week in History – E.M. Broner publishes "The Telling" | Jewish Women's Archive]. Jwa.org (1 March 1993). Retrieved on 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Esther Broner and Naomi Nimrod created a women's haggadah for use at this seder.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jbooks.com/nonfiction/NF_Groner.htm Non-Fiction: The Many Seders of Passover]. JBooks.com. Retrieved on 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In the spring of 1976 Esther Broner published this "Women's Haggadah" in Ms. magazine, later publishing it as a book in 1994; this haggadah is meant to include women where only men had been mentioned in traditional haggadahs, and it features the Wise Women, the Four Daughters, the Women's Questions, the Women's Plagues, and a women-centric "[[Dayenu]]".&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.amazon.com/dp/006061143X The Women's Haggadah (9780060611439): E. M. Broner, Naomi Nimrod: Books]. Amazon.com. Retrieved on 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/broner-esther-m Esther M. Broner | Jewish Women's Archive]. Jwa.org. Retrieved on 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The original Women's Seder has been held with the Women's Haggadah every year since 1976, and women-only seders are now held by some congregations as well.&lt;ref name="jwa2.org"&gt;[http://jwa.org/feminism/_html/JWA006.htm Jewish Women and the Feminist Revolution (Jewish Women's Archive)]. Jwa.org (17 June 2005). Retrieved on 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.questia.com/read/1P2-16241579|title=Women-Only Seder Held in Westmoreland County}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://brittdurgin.com/writing/women-celebrate-non-traditional-seder Women celebrate non-traditional Seder – Britt Durgin Journalism] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101102162900/http://brittdurgin.com/writing/women-celebrate-non-traditional-seder |date= 2 November 2010 }}. Brittdurgin.com (2 October 2010). Retrieved on 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Some seders (including the original Women's Seder, but not limited to women-only seders) now set out a cup for the prophet Miriam as well as the traditional cup for the prophet Elijah, sometimes accompanied by a ritual to honor Miriam.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.miriamscup.com/RitualFirst.htm Miriam's Cup: Miriam's Cup rituals for the family Passover seder]. Miriamscup.com. Retrieved on 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Miriam's cup originated in the 1980s in a Boston [[Rosh Chodesh]] group; it was invented by Stephanie Loo, who filled it with mayim hayim (living waters) and used it in a feminist ceremony of [[guided meditation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jweekly.com/article/full/74341/why-miriams-cup-because-without-miriam-jewish-life-would-not-exist/ |title=Why Miriam's Cup? Because without Miriam, Jewish life would not exist &amp;#124; j. the Jewish news weekly of Northern California |publisher=Jweekly.com |date=2015-04-02 |access-date=2015-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miriam's cup is linked to the ''[[midrash]]'' of [[Miriam#Jewish culture|Miriam's well]], which "is a rabbinic legend that tells of a miraculous well that accompanied the Israelites during their 40 years in the desert at the Exodus from Egypt".&lt;ref name="Esserman defrosting"&gt;{{cite news|last=Esserman|first=Rachel|title=Defrosting Judaism: A look at the Ritualwell Website|url=http://www.rrc.edu/sites/default/files/legacy/Defrosting%20Judaism%20-%20Esserman.pdf|access-date=29 January 2014|newspaper=The Reporter|date=1 September 2006|agency=Jewish Federation of Greater Binghamton|location=Binghamton, NY|page=5|format=Print|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140407064500/http://www.rrc.edu/sites/default/files/legacy/Defrosting%20Judaism%20-%20Esserman.pdf|archive-date=7 April 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myjewishlearning.com/holidays/Jewish_Holidays/Passover/The_Seder/Seder_Plate_and_Table/Miriams_Cup.shtml |title=Miriam's Cup |publisher=My Jewish Learning |date=2014-01-22 |access-date=2015-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, some Jews include an orange on the seder plate. The orange represents the fruitfulness for all Jews when all marginalized peoples are included, particularly women and gay people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| author=Tamara Cohen | url = http://www.myjewishlearning.com/holidays/Jewish_Holidays/Passover/The_Seder/Seder_Plate_and_Table/Orange.shtml | title = An Orange on the Seder Plate | access-date = 28 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; An incorrect but common rumor says that this tradition began when a man told [[Susannah Heschel]] that a woman belongs on the bimah as an orange on the seder plate; however, it actually began when in the early 1980s, while when speaking at Oberlin College Hillel, Susannah Heschel was introduced to an early feminist Haggadah that suggested adding a crust of bread on the seder plate, as a sign of solidarity with Jewish lesbians (as some would say there's as much room for a lesbian in Judaism as there is for a crust of bread on the seder plate).&lt;ref name="ritualwell"&gt;[http://www.ritualwell.org/holidays/passover/onthesedertable/primaryobject.2005-07-08.9776011383 Jewish Rituals for On the Seder Table]. Ritualwell.org. Retrieved on 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Heschel felt that to put bread on the seder plate would be to accept that Jewish lesbians and gay men violate Judaism like [[chametz]] violates Passover.&lt;ref name="ritualwell" /&gt; So, at her next seder, she chose an orange as a symbol of inclusion of gays and lesbians and others who are marginalized within the Jewish community.&lt;ref name="ritualwell" /&gt; In addition, each orange segment had a few seeds that had to be spit out—a gesture of spitting out and repudiating the homophobia of traditional Judaism.&lt;ref name="ritualwell" /&gt;

In 1978 [[Linda Rich]] became the first female cantor to sing in a Conservative synagogue, specifically Temple Beth Zion in Los Angeles, although she was not ordained.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/gi_0199-8809585/CONSERVATIVE-FEMALE-CANTOR-FITS-IN.html |title=Conservative Female Cantor Fits in Religion: Linda Rich Follows Sweet-voiced Forefathers' Career Path |publisher=Goliath.ecnext.com |date=1980-01-01 |access-date=2014-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1979 [[Linda Joy Holtzman]] was hired by [[Beth Israel Congregation of Chester County]], which was then located in Coatesville, Pennsylvania.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.jta.org/article/1979/08/23/2985422/22-women-now-ordained-as-rabbis-most-of-them-do-not-have-pulpits|title=22 Women Now Ordained As Rabbis Most of Them Do Not Have Pulpits|work=Jewish Telegraphic Agency|date=23 August 1979|access-date=29 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; She had graduated in 1979 from the [[Reconstructionist Rabbinical College]] in Philadelphia, yet was hired by Beth Israel despite their being a Conservative congregation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1346&amp;dat=19790818&amp;id=xLMwAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5186,1102901|title=First woman rabbi to head template seeks to lead way for more women|author=The New York Times|newspaper=[[The Ledger]]|date=18 August 1979|access-date=21 July 2012|author-link=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Holtzman was thus the first woman to serve as a rabbi for a solely Conservative congregation, as the Conservative movement did not then ordain women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AfCF94AckkwC&amp;q=%22linda+holtzman%22+%22first+woman%22+conservative&amp;pg=PA337 |title=New Jewish Feminism: Probing the Past, Forging the Future - Elyse Goldstein |access-date=2012-07-21|isbn=9781580233590 |last1=Goldstein |first1=Elyse |year=2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Sandy Eisenberg Sasso]] served as rabbi along with her husband at the congregation Beth-El Zedeck in [[Indianapolis]] from 1977 until 2013; Beth El Zedeck is identified with both the Reconstructionist and [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] movements.&lt;ref name="indystar.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indystar.com/article/20130519/LIFE/130519002/-Trail-blazing-Rabbi-Sandy-Sasso-retiring-after-36-years|title=Life - Indianapolis Star - indystar.com|work=Indianapolis Star|access-date=29 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=JWA&gt;
{{cite web
|title=Sandy Sasso ordained as first female Reconstructionist rabbi
|url=http://jwa.org/thisweek/may/19/1974/sandy-sasso
|work=This Week in History
|publisher=Jewish Women's Archive
|access-date=24 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1981 the Jewish feminist group "B'not Esh", Hebrew for "Daughters of Fire", was founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/feminism/_html/JWA057.htm|title=Judith Plaskow - Jewish Women's Archive}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="muse.jhu.edu"&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/bridges_a_jewish_feminists_journal/summary/v016/16.1.brettschneider.html|title=Project MUSE - A Congenial Anarchy: An Affirmation of Jewish Feminist Space|journal=Bridges: A Jewish Feminist Journal|year=2011|volume=16|issue=1|pages=176–181|last1=Brettschneider|first1=Marla|last2=Pegueros|first2=Rosa Maria}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2011, this group meets for five days every year over [[Memorial Day]] weekend at the Grail, a Catholic laywomen's retreat center in Cornwall-on-Hudson, New York.&lt;ref name="muse.jhu.edu"/&gt; There they, to quote [[Merle Feld]], one of their members, "explore issues of spirituality, social change, and the feminist transformation of Judaism".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gZtDEvQSI_wC&amp;q=bnot+esh+jewish+feminist&amp;pg=PA244|title=A Spiritual Life|isbn=9780791441183|last1=Feld|first1=Merle|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 1981, [[Lynn Gottlieb]] became the first female rabbi ordained in [[Jewish Renewal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/feminism/_html/JWA030.htm |title=Jewish Women and the Feminist Revolution (Jewish Women's Archive) |publisher=Jwa.org |date=11 September 2003 |access-date=3 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1983, the [[Jewish Theological Seminary of America|Jewish Theological Seminary]] (JTS), the main educational institution of the Conservative movement, voted, without accompanying opinion, to ordain women as rabbis and as cantors.  [[Paula Hyman]], among others, took part in the vote as a member of the JTS faculty. There had been a special commission appointed by the Conservative movement to study the issue of ordaining women as rabbis, which met between 1977 and 1978, and consisted of 11 men and three women; the women were Marian Siner Gordon, an attorney, Rivkah Harris, an [[Assyriologist]], and [[Francine Klagsbrun]], a writer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/feminism/klagsbrun-francine|title=Francine Klagsbrun &amp;#124; Jewish Women's Archive|publisher=Jwa.org|access-date=2015-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Amy Eilberg]] became the first female rabbi ordained in [[Conservative Judaism]] in 1985.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/eilberg-amy|title=Amy Eilberg &amp;#124; Jewish Women's Archive|publisher=Jwa.org|access-date=3 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In disapproval of such developments, several members of the JTS separated in 1984 and formed the Union for Traditional Conservative Judaism. Later, in 1989, some of the dissidents founded the Institute of Traditional Judaism, an organization committed to "Genuine Faith and Intellectual Honesty", a direct counter-establishment to the liberation of women in religious practice and Jewish society&lt;ref name=":02"/&gt;

In 1987 [[Erica Lippitz]] and [[Marla Rosenfeld Barugel]] became the first female cantors ordained in Conservative Judaism.&lt;ref name="jwa.org"/&gt; However, the [[Cantors Assembly]], a professional organization of cantors associated with Conservative Judaism, did not allow women to join until 1990.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/1990/09/19/nyregion/a-bar-to-women-as-cantors-is-lifted.html | work=The New York Times | first=Ari L. | last=Goldman | title=A Bar to Women as Cantors Is Lifted | date=19 September 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997 Gail Billig became the first female president of a major Orthodox synagogue, at Congregation Ahavath Torah in Englewood, N.J.&lt;ref name="womensenews.org"/&gt;

In 1999 [[Tamara Kolton]] became the very first rabbi (and therefore, since she was female, the first female rabbi) ordained in [[Humanistic Judaism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shj.org/shjbios.htm |title=Society for Humanistic Judaism – Rabbis and Leadership |publisher=Shj.org |access-date=3 May 2012 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130928164758/http://www.shj.org/shjbios.htm |archive-date=28 September 2013 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001 [[Hazzan Deborah Davis|Deborah Davis]] became the first cantor of either sex (and therefore, since she was female, the first female cantor) ordained in Humanistic Judaism; however, Humanistic Judaism has since stopped graduating cantors.&lt;ref name="auto5"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmwc.org/Women/womend.html |title=Contributions of Jewish Women to Music and Women to Jewish Music |publisher=JMWC |access-date=2012-07-09 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160512020657/http://www.jmwc.org/Women/womend.html |archive-date=12 May 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, the Committee on Jewish Law and Standards of Conservative Judaism adapted a [[responsum]] by Rabbi David Fine, [https://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/sites/default/files/public/halakhah/teshuvot/19912000/oh_55_1_2002.pdf ''Women and the Minyan''], which provides an official religious-law foundation for counting women in a minyan and explains the current Conservative approach to the role of women in prayer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/teshuvot/docs/19912000/oh_55_1_2002.pdf |title=Archived copy |access-date=10 December 2006 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101127133632/http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/teshuvot/docs/19912000/oh_55_1_2002.pdf |archive-date=27 November 2010 }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(194&amp;nbsp;KB)}}&lt;/ref&gt; This responsum holds that although Jewish women do not traditionally have the same obligations as men, Conservative women have, as a collective whole, voluntarily undertaken them. Because of this collective undertaking, the Fine responsum holds that Conservative women are eligible to serve as agents and decision-makers for others.  The responsum also holds that traditionally-minded communities and individual women can opt out without being regarded by the Conservative movement as sinning.  By adopting this responsum, the CJLS found itself in a position to provide a considered Jewish-law justification for its egalitarian practices, without having to rely on potentially unconvincing arguments, undermine the religious importance of community and clergy, ask individual women intrusive questions, repudiate the ''halakhic'' tradition, or label women following traditional practices as sinners.

Also in 2002, [[Sharon Hordes]] became the first cantor of either sex (and therefore, since she was female, the first female cantor) ordained in Reconstructionist Judaism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kenesethisrael.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=29&amp;Itemid=43 |title=Cantor Sharon Hordes |publisher=Kenesethisrael.com |access-date=2012-07-09 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110713142907/http://www.kenesethisrael.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=29&amp;Itemid=43 |archive-date=13 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2002, [[Avitall Gerstetter]], who lived in Germany, became the first female cantor ordained in Jewish Renewal (and the first female cantor in Germany).

In 2005, [[The Kohenet Institute]] was founded by Rabbi Jill Hammer and Holly Shere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/thisweek/aug/14/2006/kohenet-hebrew-priestess-institute|title=Kohenet: the Hebrew Priestess Institute, launches its first training institute in Accord, NY}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Kohenet Institute]], based at the [[Isabella Freedman Jewish Retreat Center]] in Connecticut, offers a two-year course of study to women who are then ordained as Jewish priestesses.&lt;ref name="kohenet.org"&gt;[http://www.kohenet.org/institute/ Kohenet: Hebrew Priestess Institute&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131020201418/http://www.kohenet.org/institute/ |date=20 October 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="jweekly.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jweekly.com/article/full/68940/jewish-american-priestess-kohenet-institute-ordains-women-for-a-new-jewish-/|title=Jewish American Priestess: Kohenet Institute ordains women for a new Jewish world|author=emma silvers|date=28 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  "Kohenet" is a feminine variation on "kohan," meaning priest.&lt;ref name="jweekly.com"/&gt; The Kohenet Institute's training involves earth-based spiritual practices that they believe harken back to pre–rabbinic Judaism; a time when, according to Kohenet's founders, women took on many more (and much more powerful) spiritual leadership roles than are commonly taken by women today.&lt;ref name="jweekly.com"/&gt; A Jewish priestess may, according to Kohenet, act as a rabbi, but the two roles are not the same.&lt;ref name="kohenet.org"/&gt;

In 2006, the Committee on Jewish Law and Standards of Conservative Judaism adopted three [[responsum|responsa]] on the subject of [[niddah]], which reaffirmed an obligation of Conservative women to abstain from sexual relations during and following [[menstruation]] and to immerse in a [[mikvah]] prior to resumption, while liberalizing observance requirements including shortening the length of the [[niddah]] period, lifting restrictions on non-sexual contact during niddah, and reducing the circumstances under which spotting and similar conditions would mandate abstinence.&lt;ref name="RabbiIntro"&gt;[http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/docs/Mikveh_Introduction.doc Rabbi Miriam Berkowitz, Mikveh and the Sanctity of Family Relations, Committee on Jewish Law and Standards, Rabbinical Assembly, 6 December 2006] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090320161101/http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/docs/Mikveh_Introduction.doc |date=20 March 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="RabbiGrossman"&gt;[http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/docs/Grossman-Niddah.pdf Rabbi Susan Grossman, MIKVEH AND THE SANCTITY OF BEING CREATED HUMAN, Committee on Jewish Law and Standards, Rabbinical Assembly, 6 December 2006] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080407061730/http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/docs/Grossman-Niddah.pdf |date=7 April 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="RabbiReisner"&gt;[http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/docs/Reisner-Niddah.pdf Rabbi Avram Reisner, OBSERVING NIDDAH IN OUR DAY: AN INQUIRY ON THE STATUS OF PURITY AND THE PROHIBITION OF SEXUAL ACTIVITY WITH A MENSTRUANT, Committee on Jewish Law and Standards, Rabbinical Assembly, 6 December 2006] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080407061721/http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/docs/Reisner-Niddah.pdf |date=7 April 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="RabbiBerkowitz"&gt;[http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/docs/Berkowitz-Niddah.pdf Rabbi Miriam Berkowitz, RESHAPING THE LAWS OF FAMILY PURITY FOR THE MODERN WORLD, Committee on Jewish Law and Standards, Rabbinical Assembly, 6 December 2006] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090320161047/http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/docs/Berkowitz-Niddah.pdf |date=20 March 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2006, [[Susan Wehle]] became the first American female cantor ordained in Jewish Renewal;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://levinejudaica.com/catalog/product_info.php?cPath=0_33_148_712&amp;products_id=11396 |title=Cantorial/Hazzanut/Liturgical - CD Cantor Susan Wehle OB"M Songs of Healing &amp; Hope &amp;#124; J. Levine Books &amp; Judaica &amp;#124; |publisher=Levinejudaica.com |date=2005-07-26 |access-date=2012-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; however she died in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/15/nyregion/15grief.html | work=The New York Times | first=Christine | last=Haughney | title='It's Not Even Six Degrees of Separation. It's One.' | date=15 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2009, [[Avi Weiss]] ordained [[Sara Hurwitz]] with the title "[[maharat]]" (an acronym of ''manhiga hilkhatit rukhanit Toranit''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yeshivatmaharat.org/|title=home - Yeshivat Maharat|access-date=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;) rather than "Rabbi".&lt;ref name="Forward 50"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.forward.com/forward-50-2009/|title=Forward 50, 2009|last=Eisner|first=Jane|date=2009-11-14 |publisher=The Forward|access-date=13 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thejewishweek.com/viewArticle/c52_a16167/Editorial__Opinion/Gary_Rosenblatt.html |title= Between a Rav and a Hard Place|website=www.thejewishweek.com |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090627205247/http://www.thejewishweek.com/viewArticle/c52_a16167/Editorial__Opinion/Gary_Rosenblatt.html |archive-date=27 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2010, Weiss announced that he was changing ''maharat'' to a more familiar-sounding title "rabba".&lt;ref name="Heeb"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.heebmagazine.com/rabba-sara-hurwitz-rocks-the-orthodox/|title="Rabba" Sara Hurwitz Rocks the Orthodox|date=10 March 2010 |publisher=Heeb Magazine|access-date=13 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The goal of this shift was to clarify Hurwitz's position as a full member of the Hebrew Institute of Riverdale rabbinic staff. The change was criticised by both [[Agudath Yisrael]] and the [[Rabbinical Council of America]], who called the move "beyond the pale of Orthodox Judaism".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.momentmag.com/do-1-rabba-2-rabbis-and-1-yeshiva-a-new-denomination/|title=Do 1 Rabba, 2 Rabbis and 1 Yeshiva = a New Denomination?| author=Staff|date = 8 March 2013| publisher=Moment Magazine | access-date=21 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Weiss announced amidst criticism that the term "Rabba" would not be used anymore for his future students. Hurwitz will continue to use the title Rabba and is considered by some to be the first female Orthodox rabbi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jta.org/news/article/2010/03/09/1011006/weiss-backs-away-from-rabba-title-for-women |title=Amid Furor, Weiss Backs Away from 'Rabba' Title for Women |last=Harris |first=Ben |publisher=[[Jewish Telegraphic Agency]] |date=9 March 2010 |access-date=22 March 2010 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110607053602/http://www.jta.org/news/article/2010/03/09/1011006/weiss-backs-away-from-rabba-title-for-women |archive-date=7 June 2011 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:KCRr-i6GiWEJ:columbusjudaism.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/Bulletin-for-website-May-2012.pdf+%22sally+priesand%22+%22first+reform+woman+rabbi%22&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEESiSpc6F3OkisK4Sn_iip26YBRs9D0CBa9i6tdy0Tu-VJRDyMnlg84qQL1dLCGZG6YPhXvUm4AjaDkZr86Nk2vaNNsCN2e_PvlILFbeJR0eckiOekxNRor3PReBXOo1SwYH4msFp&amp;sig=AHIEtbRDDbGrmJUgRyB44ggo5-Ryvj3AAQ {{Bare URL inline|date=June 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="thejewishchronicle.net"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejewishchronicle.net/view/full_story/14065296/matchbin|title=The Jewish Chronicle - Classifieds, News, Business, and Events|access-date=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="celebrate"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/blog/celebrating-the-first-lights-of-women-rabbis|title=Celebrating the First Lights of Women Rabbis|access-date=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However Weiss said other graduates of [[Yeshivat Maharat]], which he founded, would not receive the ''rabba'' title, but the ''[[maharat]]'' [[smicha]]. But in 2015 Yaffa Epstein was ordained as Rabba by the [[Yeshivat Maharat]].&lt;ref name="auto9"/&gt; Also in 2015, [[Lila Kagedan]] was ordained as Rabbi by that same organization, making her their first graduate to take the title Rabbi.&lt;ref name="auto10"/&gt;

Also in 2009 [[Tannoz Bahremand Foruzanfar]], who was born in Iran, became the first [[Persian people|Persian]] woman to be ordained as a cantor in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ajrca.org/alumni/cantor-tannoz-bahremand-forunzanfar/ |title=Cantor Tannoz Bahremand Forunzanfar; Academy for Jewish Religion, California |publisher=Ajrca.org |access-date=10 August 2013 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130320041940/http://ajrca.org/alumni/cantor-tannoz-bahremand-forunzanfar/ |archive-date=20 March 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2009, [[Alysa Stanton]] became the first African-American woman ordained as a rabbi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ijn.com/denver/1468-roots-of-rabbi-alysa-stantons-journey-in-colorado |title=Roots of Rabbi Alysa Stanton's journey in Colorado |publisher=Ijn.com |date=21 January 2010 |access-date=3 May 2012 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120311154330/https://www.ijn.com/denver/1468-roots-of-rabbi-alysa-stantons-journey-in-colorado |archive-date=11 March 2012 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010 the first American women to be ordained as cantors in Jewish Renewal after Susan Wehle's ordination, [[Michal Rubin]] and [[Abbe Lyons]], were both ordained.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tikkunvor.org/Events/index.cfm?id=1392 |title=Tikkun v'Or, Ithaca, NY - Celebration in honor of Cantor Abbe Lyons |publisher=Tikkunvor.org |date=2010-02-07 |access-date=2012-07-09 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120306064843/http://www.tikkunvor.org/Events/index.cfm?id=1392 |archive-date= 6 March 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2013 Tamar Frankiel became the president of the [[Academy for Jewish Religion (California)|Academy for Jewish Religion]] in California, making her the first Orthodox woman to lead an American rabbinical school.&lt;ref name="ajrca.org"/&gt;&lt;ref name="jewishjournal.com"/&gt; The school itself is transdenominational, not Orthodox.&lt;ref name="jewishjournal.com"/&gt;

In 2013 [[Malka Schaps]] became the first female [[haredi]] dean at an Israeli university when she was appointed dean of Bar Ilan University's Faculty of Exact Sciences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/national/1.550156|title=Malka Schaps Becomes First Female Haredi Dean at Israeli University|work=Haaretz.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013 the Israeli Orthodox rabbinical organization Beit Hillel issued a [[halacha|halachic]] ruling which allows women, for the first time, to say the [[Kaddish]] prayer in memory of their deceased parents.&lt;ref name="ynetnews.com"/&gt;

In 2013 SAR High School in Riverdale, New York began allowing girls to wrap tefillin during Shacharit-morning prayer; it is probably the first Modern Orthodox high school in the U.S. to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishpress.com/news/breaking-news/nyc-orthodox-high-school-lets-girls-put-on-tefillin/2014/01/20/|title=The Jewish Press » » NYC Orthodox High School Lets Girls Put on Tefillin|author=Jewish Press News Briefs|work=The Jewish Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 October 2014 Rabbi [[Deborah Waxman]] was inaugurated as the president of the [[Reconstructionist Rabbinical College]] and [[Reconstructionist Judaism|Jewish Reconstructionist Communities]].&lt;ref name="jewishexponent.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jewishexponent.com/community/2014/10/waxman-inaugurated-as-head-of-reconstructionist-rabbinical-college|title=Waxman Inaugurated as Head of Reconstructionist Rabbinical College|work=Jewish Exponent}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rrc.edu/node/1624?hero=1625|title=Video and Audio|work=RRC|access-date=29 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140107154935/http://www.rrc.edu/node/1624?hero=1625|archive-date=7 January 2014|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="auto6"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/national-news/reconstructionists-pick-first-woman-lesbian-denominational-leader|title=Reconstructionists Pick First Woman, Lesbian As Denominational Leader - The Jewish Week|work=The Jewish Week|access-date=29 October 2014|archive-date=19 May 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160519214708/http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/national-news/reconstructionists-pick-first-woman-lesbian-denominational-leader|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://forward.com/articles/185252/trailblazing-reconstructionist-deborah-waxman-reli/?p=all|title=Trailblazing Reconstructionist Deborah Waxman Relishes Challenges of Judaism|date=9 October 2013|work=The Jewish Daily Forward|access-date=29 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Waxman is believed to be the first woman rabbi and first lesbian to lead a Jewish congregational union, and the first woman and first lesbian to lead a Jewish seminary; the Reconstructionist Rabbinical College is both a congregational union and a seminary.&lt;ref name="auto6"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.rrc.edu/sites/default/files/ORPHAN_PDFs/RRC_WaxmanPresidentElect-ForPress3.pdf?hero=1615 |title=Archived copy |access-date=10 October 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924092703/http://www.rrc.edu/sites/default/files/ORPHAN_PDFs/RRC_WaxmanPresidentElect-ForPress3.pdf?hero=1615 |archive-date=24 September 2015 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014 the first ever book of [[halacha|halachic]] decisions written by women who were ordained to serve as [[poskim]] (Idit Bartov and Anat Novoselsky) was published.&lt;ref name="jpupdates.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jpupdates.com/2014/06/26/first-halacha-sefer-women-makes-waves-israel-orthodox-world/|title=First Halacha Sefer By Women Makes Waves in Israeli Orthodox World -|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150325221418/http://jpupdates.com/2014/06/26/first-halacha-sefer-women-makes-waves-israel-orthodox-world/|archive-date=25 March 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The women were ordained by the municipal chief rabbi of Efrat, Rabbi [[Shlomo Riskin]], after completing [[Midreshet Lindenbaum]] women's college's five-year ordination course in advanced studies in Jewish law, as well as passing examinations equivalent to the rabbinate's requirement for men.&lt;ref name="jpupdates.com"/&gt;

In 2014, Dr. Michelle Friedman became the first woman on the [[Beth Din of America]]'s board of directors.&lt;ref name=michelle&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/short-takes/first-woman-joins-board-rca-beth-din|title=First Woman Joins Board of RCA Beth Din|publisher=The Jewish Week|date=12 November 2014|access-date=12 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, the first women were elected as national officers of the [[Orthodox Union]]; specifically, three female national vice presidents and two female associate vice presidents were elected.&lt;ref name="jstandard.com"/&gt;

In June 2015, [[Lila Kagedan]] was ordained by [[Yeshivat Maharat]] and in keeping with newer policies, was given the freedom to choose her own title, and she chose to be addressed as "Rabbi".&lt;ref name="auto11"/&gt; However, in the fall of 2015, the [[Rabbinical Council of America]], representing over a thousand Orthodox rabbis across the United States, formally adopted a policy prohibiting the ordination or hiring of women rabbis by synagogues that operate within the boundaries of their figurative jurisdiction, regardless of title.&lt;ref name="auto12"/&gt; Similarly, in the fall of 2015, the [[Agudath Israel of America]] denounced moves to ordain women, and went even further, declaring [[Yeshivat Maharat]], [[Yeshivat Chovevei Torah]], [[Open Orthodoxy]], and other affiliated entities to be similar to other dissident movements throughout Jewish history in having rejected basic tenets of Judaism.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;&lt;ref name="auto7"/&gt;&lt;ref name="auto8"/&gt;

Also in 2015 the Israeli Orthodox rabbinical organization Beit Hillel issued a ruling which allows women to give instruction on Jewish law and to issue [[halacha|halachic]] decisions.&lt;ref name="ynetnews.com"/&gt;&lt;ref name="jpost.com1"/&gt; Beit Hillel claimed that this ruling was the first time women issuing halachic rulings was formally affirmed in a written [[responsa]] of Jewish law.&lt;ref name="jpost.com1"/&gt;

Also in 2015, Jennie Rosenfeld became the first female Orthodox spiritual advisor in Israel (specifically, she became the spiritual advisor, also called manhiga ruchanit, for the community of [[Efrat]].)&lt;ref name="auto2"/&gt;

Also in 2015, Daryl Messinger became the first female chair of the [[Union for Reform Judaism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Eden |first=Ami |url=http://www.jta.org/2015/11/10/news-opinion/united-states/five-questions-for-the-first-woman-to-chair-the-union-for-reform-judaism |title=Five questions for the first woman to chair the Union for Reform Judaism &amp;#124; Jewish Telegraphic Agency |publisher=Jta.org |date=2015|access-date=2015-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, after four years of deliberation, the Reform seminary [[HUC-JIR]] decided to give women a choice of wording on their ordination certificates, including the option to have the same wording as men.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"&gt;[http://www.jta.org/2016/05/31/life-religion/why-a-small-word-change-is-a-big-deal-for-reform-women-rabbis Why a small word change is a big deal for Reform women rabbis] JTA, 31 May 2016&lt;/ref&gt; Up until then, male candidates' certificates identified them by the Reform movement's traditional "morenu harav," or "our teacher the rabbi," while female candidates' certificates only used the term "rav u'morah," or "rabbi and teacher." Rabbi Mary Zamore, executive director of the Reform movement's [[Women's Rabbinic Network]], explained that the HUC was uncomfortable with giving women the same title as men. In 2012 she wrote to Rabbi [[David Ellenson]], HUC's then president, requesting that he address the discrepancy, which she said was "smacking of gender inequality."&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt;

In June 2015, [[Lila Kagedan]] was ordained by [[Yeshivat Maharat]] and in keeping with newer policies, was given the freedom to choose her own title, and she chose to be addressed as "Rabbi".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cjnews.com/featured/jewish-learning/why-orthodox-judaism-needs-female-rabbis|title=Why Orthodox Judaism needs female rabbis|last=Kagedan|first=Rabbi Lila|date=2015-11-25|website=The Canadian Jewish News|language=en-US|access-date=2019-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; She officially became the first female Modern Orthodox rabbi in the United States of America when the Modern Orthodox Mount Freedom Jewish Center in Randolph, New Jersey hired her as a spiritual leader in January 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.jta.org/2016/01/11/united-states/nj-orthodox-shul-announces-hire-of-woman-using-rabbi-title|title=NJ Orthodox shul announces hire of woman using 'rabbi' title|date=2016-01-11|website=Jewish Telegraphic Agency|language=en-US|access-date=2019-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.jewishpress.com/news/breaking-news/rabbi-lila-kagedan-first-female-rabbi-at-orthodox-shul-in-melbourne/2016/03/21/|title=Rabbi Lila Kagedan, First Female Rabbi at Orthodox Shul in Melbourne|last=Desk|first=Jewish Press News|language=en-US|access-date=2019-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2019, Kagedan is working as the rabbi at [[Congregation Agudath Shalom|Walnut Street Synagogue]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://walnutstreetsynagogue.com/clergy/|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161218221445/http://www.walnutstreetsynagogue.com/clergy/|url-status=dead|archive-date=18 December 2016|title=Clergy|last=admin-walnut|website=Walnut|language=en-US|access-date=2019-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Women as ''sofrot'' (scribes) ===
A Sofer, Sopher, Sofer SeTaM, or Sofer ST"M (Heb: "scribe", סופר סת״ם) is a Jewish scribe who can transcribe Torah scrolls, tefillin and mezuzot, and other religious writings.  (ST"M, סת״ם, is an abbreviation for Sefer Torahs, Tefillin, and Mezuzot. The plural of sofer is "soferim", סופרים.) Forming the basis for the discussion of women becoming soferim, [[Talmud|Talmud Gittin]] 45b states: "Sifrei Torah, tefillin and mezuzot written by a heretic, a star-worshipper, a slave, a woman, a minor, a [[Cuthean]], or an [[Apostasy in Judaism|apostate Jew]], are unfit for ritual use."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.geniza.net/ritual/women.shtml |title= Sofrut|website=www.geniza.net |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091019133505/http://www.geniza.net/ritual/women.shtml |archive-date=19 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rulings on [[Mezuzah]] and [[Tefillin]] are virtually undisputed among those who hold to the [[Talmud|Talmudic Law]]. While [[Arba'ah Turim]] does not include women in its list of those ineligible to write Sifrei Torah, some see this as proof that women are permitted to write a Torah scroll.&lt;ref&gt;Tur, [[Wikisource:Shulchan Aruch/Orach Chaim/271|Orah Hayyim 271]].&lt;/ref&gt; However today, virtually all Orthodox (both Modern and Haredi) authorities contest the idea that a woman is permitted to write a [[Sefer Torah]]. Yet women are permitted to inscribe [[Ketubah|Ketubot]] (marriage contracts), STaM not intended for ritual use, and other writings of [[Sofrut]] beyond simple STaM. In 2003 Canadian [[Aviel Barclay]] became the world's first known traditionally trained female sofer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forward.com/articles/3614/|title=A Female Scribe's Trailblazing Effort|author=Alice Lowenstein|date=3 June 2005|work=The Forward}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwablog.jwa.org/soferet|title=Simchat Torah with a Soferet's Torah|access-date=11 October 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110728044858/http://jwablog.jwa.org/soferet|archive-date=28 July 2011|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007 [[Jen Taylor Friedman]], a British woman, became the first female sofer to scribe a [[Sefer Torah]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forward.com/articles/11604/|title=As New Year Dawns, Jewish Women Mark Milestones|author=Leah Hochbaum Rosner|date=12 September 2007|work=The Forward}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010 the first [[Sefer Torah]] scribed by a group of women (six female sofers, who were from Brazil, Canada, Israel, and the United States) was completed;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jta.org/news/article/2010/10/15/2741313/womens-torah-dedicated-in-seattle|title=Women's Torah dedicated in Seattle|work=Jewish Telegraphic Agency|date=16 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; this was known as the [[Women's Torah Project]].&lt;ref name="ReferenceC"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jweekly.com/article/full/59670/cjms-resident-scribe-takes-part-in-group-torah-project-in-seattle/|title=Julie Seltzer, a female Torah scribe from San Francisco, contributed to the first Torah scroll to be written by a group of women. - j. the Jewish news weekly of Northern California|date=22 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From October 2010 until spring 2011, [[Julie Seltzer]], one of the female sofrot from the Women's Torah Project, scribed a [[Sefer Torah]] as part of an exhibition at the [[Contemporary Jewish Museum]] in [[San Francisco]]. This makes her the first American female sofer to scribe a [[Sefer Torah]]; Julie Seltzer was born in Philadelphia and is non-denominationally Jewish.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thecjm.org/index.php?option=com_ccevents&amp;scope=prgm&amp;task=detail&amp;fid=8&amp;oid=563|title=Page not found - Contemporary Jewish Museum - Art, People, and Ideas, San Francisco, CA|access-date=6 October 2014|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110408164017/http://www.thecjm.org/index.php?option=com_ccevents&amp;scope=prgm&amp;task=detail&amp;fid=8&amp;oid=563|archive-date=8 April 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/08/arts/design/08sfculture.html | work=The New York Times | first=Bruce | last=Weber | title=A Torah Scribe Pushes the Parchment Ceiling | date=8 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jweekly.com/article/full/61328/cjm-to-celebrate-end-of-groundbreaking-torah-project|title=CJM to celebrate end of groundbreaking Torah project|author=andy altman-ohr|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; From spring 2011 until August 2012 she scribed another [[Sefer Torah]], this time for the Reform congregation Beth Israel in San Diego.&lt;ref name="jpost.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jpost.com/JewishWorld/JewishFeatures/Article.aspx?id=286912|title=Torah, she wrote|work=The Jerusalem Post - JPost.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbisd.org/news-and-stories/87-news-and-stories/1158-a-special-open-house-with-torah-scribe-julie-seltzer-observe-the-completion-of-our-torah |archive-url=https://archive.today/20130414105124/http://www.cbisd.org/news-and-stories/87-news-and-stories/1158-a-special-open-house-with-torah-scribe-julie-seltzer-observe-the-completion-of-our-torah |url-status=dead |archive-date=14 April 2013 |title=A Special Open House with Torah Scribe Julie Seltzer: Observe the Completion of our Torah |access-date=30 October 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Seltzer was taught mostly by [[Jen Taylor Friedman]].&lt;ref name="jpost.com"/&gt; On 22 September 2013, [[Congregation Beth Elohim]] of New York dedicated a new Torah, which members of Beth Elohim said was the first Torah in New York City to be completed by a woman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://brooklyn.news12.com/news/congregation-beth-elohim-in-park-slope-dedicates-new-torah-for-150th-anniversary-1.6119015|title=Congregation Beth Elohim in Park Slope dedicates new Torah for 150th anniversary|work=News 12 Brooklyn|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150602035037/http://brooklyn.news12.com/news/congregation-beth-elohim-in-park-slope-dedicates-new-torah-for-150th-anniversary-1.6119015|archive-date=2 June 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Torah was scribed by Linda Coppleson.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://torah.cbebk.org/about/our-soferet/ |title= Sefer Torah Project &amp;#124; Congregation Beth Elohim &amp;#124; Our Soferet|website=torah.cbebk.org |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131012013510/http://torah.cbebk.org/about/our-soferet/ |archive-date=12 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2014, there are an estimated 20 female sofers in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pressherald.com/2014/08/23/female-jewish-scribe-helps-keep-tradition-alive/|title=Female Jewish scribe helps keep tradition alive|work=The Portland Press Herald / Maine Sunday Telegram|date=23 August 2014|access-date=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Women in Humanistic Judaism ==
[[Humanistic Judaism]] is a movement in [[Judaism]] that offers a nontheistic alternative in contemporary Jewish life. It defines Judaism as the cultural and historical experience of the Jewish people and encourages humanistic and secular Jews to celebrate their Jewish identity by participating in Jewish holidays and life cycle events (such as weddings and bar and bat mitzvah) with inspirational ceremonies that draw upon but go beyond traditional literature. Humanistic Judaism ordains both men and women as rabbis, and its first rabbi was a woman, [[Tamara Kolton]], who was ordained in 1999.&lt;ref name="shj"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shj.org/shjbios.htm |title=Society for Humanistic Judaism - Rabbis and Leadership |publisher=Shj.org |access-date=2012-03-12 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130928164758/http://www.shj.org/shjbios.htm |archive-date=28 September 2013 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; Its first cantor was also a woman, [[Hazzan Deborah Davis|Deborah Davis]], ordained in 2001; however, Humanistic Judaism has since stopped ordaining cantors.&lt;ref name="auto5"/&gt; The [[Society for Humanistic Judaism]] issued a statement in 1996 stating in part, "we affirm that a woman has the moral right and should have the continuing legal right to decide whether or not to terminate a pregnancy in accordance with her own ethical standards. Because a decision to terminate a pregnancy carries serious, irreversible consequences, it is one to be made with great care and with keen awareness of the complex psychological, emotional, and ethical implications."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shj.org/Choice.htm Society for Humanistic Judaism - Reproductive Choice Abortion&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040305165842/http://www.shj.org/Choice.htm |date= 5 March 2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They also issued a statement in 2011 condemning the then-recent passage of the "No Taxpayer Funding for Abortion Act" by the U.S. House of Representatives, which they called "a direct attack on a woman's right to choose".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shj.org/NewsAbortionFunding.html Society for Humanistic Judaism Condemns Limit on Choice&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110709054548/http://www.shj.org/NewsAbortionFunding.html |date=9 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012 they issued a resolution opposing conscience clauses that allow religious-affiliated institutions to be exempt from generally applicable requirements mandating reproductive healthcare services to individuals or employees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.shj.org/ConscienceClauses.html |title= Society for Humanistic Judaism Opposes Conscience Clauses|website=www.shj.org |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130725135714/http://www.shj.org/ConscienceClauses.html |archive-date=25 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013 they issued a resolution stating in part, "Therefore, be it resolved that: The Society for Humanistic Judaism wholeheartedly supports the observance of [[Women's Equality Day]] on 26 August to commemorate the anniversary of the passage of the Nineteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution allowing women to vote; The Society condemns gender discrimination in all its forms, including restriction of rights, limited access to education, violence, and subjugation; and The Society commits itself to maintain vigilance and speak out in the fight to bring gender equality to our generation and to the generations that follow."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.shj.org/WomensEqualityDay.html |title= Society for Humanistic Judaism - Gender Equality|website=www.shj.org |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130928161629/http://www.shj.org/WomensEqualityDay.html |archive-date=28 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the mid 19th century, the role of Jewish women in humanistic efforts has also extended to Second-Wave feminism. For instance, [[Ernestine Rose]], an associate of civil rights activists [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] and [[Susan B. Anthony]], led the push for women's rights to inherit property. As the daughter of a Polish rabbi, she simultaneously spoke out against anti-Semitism in her efforts. Additionally, [[Maud Nathan]] became a prominent voice in the suffrage movement of the early 20th century.&lt;ref name=":02"/&gt;

== Israel ==
{{Main|Feminism in Israel}}
{{See also|Women in Israel}}

From 1918 to 1926 women in Palestine fought for representation in the Yishuv movement. This was seen as the first wave of feminism, before the state was established.&lt;ref name="ReferenceD"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/feminism-in-contemporary-israel|title=Feminism in Contemporary Israel {{!}} Jewish Women's Archive|website=jwa.org|access-date=2019-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1947 [[David Ben-Gurion]] agreed that the authority in matters of marriage and divorce would be invested in the hands of the Chief Rabbinate of Israel, and an agreement was signed stating that (among other matters), known as the "status quo letter".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.al-monitor.com/pulse/originals/2013/10/civil-marriage-israel-jews-secular-orthodox-rabbinical-court.html|title=Israel's Rabbis Keep Lock on Jewish Marriage - Al-Monitor: the Pulse of the Middle East|work=Al-Monitor|access-date=13 October 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151121152127/http://www.al-monitor.com/pulse/originals/2013/10/civil-marriage-israel-jews-secular-orthodox-rabbinical-court.html|archive-date=21 November 2015|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1953 the [[Knesset]] enacted the Rabbinical Courts Jurisdiction (Marriage and Divorce) Law, 5713 – 1953.&lt;ref name="jewishvirtuallibrary.org"&gt;[https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/judaica/ejud_0002_0003_0_02840.html Bet Din and Judges&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Section 1 of the Law states, "Matters of marriage and divorce of Jews in Israel, being citizens or residents of the State, shall be under the exclusive jurisdiction of the rabbinical courts."&lt;ref name="jewishvirtuallibrary.org" /&gt; The substantive provision of section 2 of this Law further states: "Marriages and divorces of Jews shall be performed in Israel in accordance with Jewish religious law" (din torah).&lt;ref name="jewishvirtuallibrary.org" /&gt; However, a Muslim woman in Israel may petition for and receive a divorce through the Sharia courts without her husband's consent under certain conditions, and a marriage contract may provide for other circumstances in which she may obtain a divorce without her husband's consent. A Muslim man in Israel may divorce his wife without her consent and without petitioning the court.&lt;ref name="hr2010"&gt;2010 Human Rights Report: Israel and the occupied territories. U.S. Department of state. ''This article incorporates public domain material from this source''.&lt;/ref&gt; Christians in Israel may seek official separations or divorces, depending on the denomination, through ecclesiastical courts.&lt;ref name="hr2010" /&gt;

In 1969, Golda Meir was appointed Israel's first female Prime Minister, during a time when women made up less than seven percent of the Knesset.&lt;ref name="ReferenceD"/&gt;

In 1972 marks the creation of the first radical women's movement in Israel.&lt;&lt;ref name="ReferenceD"/&gt; This period marks the beginning of second wave feminism in Israel. During the Yom Kippur war in 1973, women were not allowed in Military leadership, the civilian administration, and war production. However, women found other ways to become more actively engaged. Overall, the 1970s were a time of major growth and transition for feminism in Israeli society.&lt;ref name="ReferenceD"/&gt;

In 2006, Israel's Supreme Court ruled that women should be allowed to deliver eulogies and that the burial societies, or chevra kadisha, should not impose gender segregation in the cemetery.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishjournal.com/religion/article/israeli_chief_rabbinical_council_oks_eulogies_by_women_20120612|title=Israeli Chief Rabbinical Council OKs eulogies by women - Religion|work=Jewish Journal|date=12 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ruling was in response to an incident in [[Petach Tikvah]] in which a woman was stopped from eulogizing her father.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; However, the court's ruling was not backed up by the Religious Services Ministry until 2012, when Israel's Chief Rabbinical Council ruled that women can deliver eulogies at funerals, but that it is up to the community rabbi to decide on a case-by-case basis.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt;

In 2010, Israel passed the Civil Union Law, allowing a couple to marry civilly in Israel if they are both registered as officially not belonging to any religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myjewishlearning.com/israel/Contemporary_Life/Society_and_Religious_Issues/Freedom_of_Religion/civil_marriage_in_israel.shtml|title=Civil Marriage in Israel|work=My Jewish Learning|access-date=13 October 2013|archive-date=10 April 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150410133915/http://www.myjewishlearning.com/israel/Contemporary_Life/Society_and_Religious_Issues/Freedom_of_Religion/civil_marriage_in_israel.shtml|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 September 2010, the [[Israeli Supreme Court]] outlawed public gender segregation in Jerusalem's [[Mea Shearim]] neighborhood in response to a petition submitted after extremist Haredi men physically and verbally assaulted women for walking on a designated men's only road. However, in January 2011, a ruling of the [[Israeli High Court of Justice]] allowed the continuation of the gender segregation in public buses on a strictly voluntary basis for a one-year experimental period.&lt;ref name="jpost1"&gt;{{cite news |newspaper=Jerusalem Post |title=Court scraps 'mehadrin' buses |date=6 January 2011 |url=http://www.jpost.com/JewishWorld/JewishNews/Article.aspx?ID=202456&amp;R=R1 |access-date=2011-03-08 | first1=Dan |last1=Izenberg |first2=Jonah |last2=Mandel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013 the Israeli Orthodox rabbinical organization Beit Hillel issued a [[halacha|halachic]] ruling which allows women, for the first time, to say the [[Kaddish]] prayer in memory of their deceased parents.&lt;ref name="ynetnews.com"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4396702,00.html|title=Halachic ruling: Women may say Kaddish|work=ynet|date=25 June 2013|access-date=6 October 2014|last1=Novick|first1=Akiva}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2013, the minimum marriage age in Israel became 18 for females and males.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timesofisrael.com/knesset-raise-minimum-marriage-age-from-17-to-18/|title=Israel raises minimum marriage age from 17 to 18|work=The Times of Israel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2013, the [[Religious Judges Law]] in Israel was amended to say that at least four women must be included in the religious judges' nomination committee, including a female advocate in the religious courts, and that the total number of committee members shall be eleven.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israelhayom.com/site/newsletter_article.php?id=9919 Israel Hayom | In a first, women to sit on rabbinic judges selection panel&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2013, Israel's [[Chief Rabbinate]] promised to remove the obstacles preventing women from working as supervisors in the state [[kosher]] certification system, and [[Emunah]] announced the first supervisor certification course for women in Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/national/.premium-1.561459|title=Rabbinate Opens Kashrut Supervision to Women - National - Haaretz|work=Haaretz.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2013, the Minister of Religious Affairs and Chief Rabbis issued statements telling ritual bath attendants only to inspect women who want inspection, putting an end to forced inspections of women at mikvehs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/174499#.UqT7w-Jo2kw|title=End to Forced Inspections for Women at Mikveh|work=Arutz Sheva|date=26 November 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:WOW Founding Members.jpg|thumb|Founding members of [[Women of the Wall]] in Jerusalem]]
In May 2013, after [[Women of the Wall]], led by [[Anat Hoffman]], had engaged in [[civil disobedience]] to exercise freedom of religion, a judge ruled that a 2003 Israeli Supreme Court ruling prohibiting women from carrying a Torah or wearing prayer shawls at the [[Western Wall]] had been misinterpreted and that [[Women of the Wall]] prayer gatherings at the [[Western Wall]] should not be deemed illegal.&lt;ref name=civildisobedience&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/26/world/middleeast/israeli-law-curbing-womens-prayer-up-for-review.html |title=Israel to Review Curbs on Women's Prayer at Western Wall |first=Jodi |last=Rudoren |work=The New York Times |date=25 December 2012 |access-date=25 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2014 Women of the Wall smuggled in a Torah scroll to the Western Wall women's section and held their first Torah reading by a woman at the site, which was part of the [[bat mitzvah]] of Sasha Lutt. However, [[Shmuel Rabinowitz]], the rabbi of the Western Wall, issued a statement saying in part, "In future, efforts will be made to ensure that this does not happen again, and the introduction of Torah scrolls will be banned for everyone - men and women."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shalomlife.com/news/26571/for-the-first-time-ever-women-of-the-wall-hold-torah-reading-at-the-kotel/#?1#?1#WebrootPlugIn#?1#?1#PhreshPhish#?1#?1#agtpwd |title=For the First Time Ever, Women of the Wall Hold Torah Reading at the Kotel |work=Shalom Life |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141027004440/http://www.shalomlife.com/news/26571/for-the-first-time-ever-women-of-the-wall-hold-torah-reading-at-the-kotel/ |archive-date=27 October 2014 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2014 some of the Women of the Wall became the first women to light menorahs at the Western Wall. Specifically, they lit 28 menorahs in the women's section of the Wall. [[Sarah Silverman]] was among those who attended the lighting of the menorahs. However, this event came after the rabbi in charge of the Western Wall had refused a request from Women of the Wall to place a menorah in the women's section.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/12/18/sarah-silverman-western-wall-hanukkah_n_6351040.html|title=Comedian Sarah Silverman Supports Women of the Wall at Hanukkah Menorah Lighting|work=The Huffington Post|date=18 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, the first Israeli political party dedicated to Haredi women was unveiled, called "B'Zhutan: Haredi Women Making Change."&lt;ref name="auto1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/israel-election-2015/.premium-1.637916|title=Israel's first ever ultra-Orthodox women's party makes bold debut|date=20 January 2015|work=Haaretz.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2015, [[Tzohar (organization)|Tzohar]] (a religious Zionist rabbinic organization in Israel), along with the [[Israeli Bar Association]], introduced a prenuptial agreement meant to help ensure divorcing wives will receive a ''[[Get (divorce document)|get]]''; under the agreement the husband commits to paying a high sum of money daily to his spouse in the event of a separation.&lt;ref name="Jta.org"/&gt;

In 2016 it was announced that the [[Supreme Court of Israel|High Court of Justice]] had given the Justice Ministry 30 days to formulate new regulations to allow women to compete equally with men for the position of director of rabbinical courts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/.premium-1.696233|title=Israel High Court Rules to Let Women Compete With Men for Rabbinical Court Role|work=Haaretz.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2016, in a groundbreaking ruling, the Tel Aviv Rabbinical Court ordered a man jailed for thirty days for helping his son refuse to give his daughter-in-law a divorce for eleven years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/.premium-1.708903|title=In Historic Ruling, Israeli Rabbinical Court Jails Father for Abetting Son's Refusal of Divorce|work=Haaretz.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2016, Karmit Feintuch became the first woman to be hired as a communal leader at an Orthodox synagogue in Israel ([[Ramban Synagogue]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Julie Wiener |url=http://forward.com/sisterhood/348239/orthodox-synagogue-hires-female-spiritual-leader-in-first-for-israel/ |title=Orthodox Synagogue Hires Female Spiritual Leader in First for Israel - Sisterhood – |publisher=Forward.com |date=2016-01-13 |access-date=2016-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2017, the Israeli High Court ruled that if the government of Israel could not find "good cause" to prohibit women reading from the Torah in prayer services at the Western Wall within 30 days, women could do so; they also ruled that the Israeli government could no longer argue that the Robinson's Arch area of the plaza is "access to the Western Wall."&lt;ref name="timesofisrael1"&gt;{{cite news|last=Shimoni |first=Rebecca |url=http://www.timesofisrael.com/in-sweeping-decision-high-court-rules-for-womens-western-wall-prayer/ |title=In landmark decision, High Court rules for women's Western Wall prayer |newspaper=The Times of Israel |access-date=2017-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Agunah ==

[[Agunah]] ({{lang-he|עגונה}}, plural: agunot (עגונות); literally 'anchored or chained') is a [[halakha|halachic]] term for a [[Jewish]] woman who is "chained" to her [[marriage]]. The classic case of this is a man who has left on a journey and has not returned, or has gone into battle and is [[missing in action|MIA]]. It also refers to a woman whose husband refuses, or is unable, to grant her an official Jewish bill of [[divorce]], known as a ''[[Get (divorce document)|get]]''. The problem of get-refusal became more widespread when Jews lived in countries where civil divorce was available, separate from religious divorce.  Outside Israel, an ''agunah'' could obtain a civil divorce and remarry via [[civil marriage]], as non-Israeli legal systems generally do not recognize the ''agunah'' status, but an ''agunah'' would not typically pursue a second marriage, since her first marriage is still valid according to halakha, therefore any other sexual relationships would constitute [[adultery]] from her first husband. Furthermore, according to halakha, any children born by an agunah are considered [[mamzer]]im (bastards).

The earliest prenuptial agreement for the prevention of get-refusal was developed and accepted by the Rabbinical Council of Morocco on 16 December 1953.&lt;ref&gt;"Sefer Hatakanot", Vol. 1, The Institute for Moroccan Jewish Tradition, Jerusalem&lt;/ref&gt; The prenuptial agreement gained further approbation in 1981 from Rabbi Shalom Messas, chief rabbi of Jerusalem.&lt;ref&gt;"Sefer Tevuot Shemesh", Jerusalem 1981&lt;/ref&gt; Following Rabbi Messas' involvement, the [[Rabbinical Council of America]] actively pursued this issue.&lt;ref&gt;"The RCA Commission: Solving the Problem of Gittin", Hamevaser, Vol. 22 No. 2, 27 October 1983&lt;/ref&gt; The latest in a series of RCA resolutions—"that since there is a significant agunah problem in America and throughout the Jewish world, no rabbi should officiate at a wedding where a proper prenuptial agreement on get has not been executed"—was passed on 18 May 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rabbis.org/news/article.cfm?id=100772|title=Rabbinical Council of America (RCA)|access-date=12 June 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180725033251/http://www.rabbis.org/news/article.cfm?id=100772|archive-date=25 July 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012 the International Rabbinic Fellowship (IRF), an international organization of (as of 2012) 150 Modern Orthodox rabbis, passed a resolution saying that, "IRF Rabbis may not officiate at a wedding unless the couple has signed a halachic prenuptial agreement. IRF Rabbis are further encouraged to participate ritually only in weddings in which the couple has signed a halachic prenuptial agreement. Ritual participation includes but is not limited to reading the [[ketubah]], serving as a witness, and making one of the [[sheva berachot]]." This makes the IRF the only Orthodox rabbinical organization in the world to require its members to use a halachic pre-nuptial agreement in any wedding at which they officiate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.internationalrabbinicfellowship.org/news/international-rabbinic-fellowship-takes-historic-step-prevent-future-agunot|title=International Rabbinic Fellowship Takes Historic Step to Prevent Future Agunot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning in the 1950s, some Conservative rabbis have used the [[Lieberman clause]], named for Talmudic scholar and [[Jewish Theological Seminary of America|Jewish Theological Seminary]] (JTS) professor [[Saul Lieberman]], in the ''[[ketuba]]'', requiring that a get be granted if a civil divorce is ever issued.  Most Orthodox rabbis have rejected the Lieberman clause, although leaders of the Conservative movement claim that the original intent was to find a solution that could be used by Orthodox and Conservative rabbis alike, and that leaders of Orthodox Judaism's [[Rabbinical Council of America]], and respected Orthodox rabbis, including [[Joseph B. Soloveitchik]], supposedly recognized the clause as valid. Later, because some civil courts viewed the enforcement of a religious document as a violation of the [[U.S. Constitution|constitutional]] principle of the [[separation of church and state]], Conservative rabbis began to require couples to sign a separate letter, stating that the clause had been explained to them as part of pre-marital counseling, and that both parties understood and agreed to its conditions, recognizing that this letter would constitute a separate civil document, enforceable in a civilian court. However, many Conservative rabbis, including some on the movement's own [[Committee on Jewish Law and Standards|law committee]], had growing misgivings about the clause for religious reasons.

In 1968, by a unanimous vote of the law committee, it was decided that the Joint Bet Din of the Conservative movement could annul marriages as a last resort, based on the Talmudic principle of ''hafka'at kiddushin.'' According to Rabbi Mayer Rabinowitz, the Chairman of the Joint Bet Din of the [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative Movement]], just the threat of this action was sometimes enough to compel the former husband to grant a get.

In 1990 Agunah Day was established by ICAR - The International Coalition for Agunah Rights - to raise public awareness of the plight of the Agunah and galvanize action to solve the problem. It is observed on the [[Hebrew calendar|Jewish calendar]] date of the [[Fast of Esther]].

In 1995 the Israeli parliament gave the rabbinical court expanded legal power to sanction men who refuse to give their wives a ''get'' by suspending their driver's licenses, seizing their bank accounts, preventing travel abroad and even imprisoning those who do not comply with an order to grant a divorce; however, women's groups say the 1995 law is not very effective because the court uses sanctions in less than 2% of cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/world/middleeast/la-fg-israel-divorce-problems-20130726,0,4730957.story | work=Los Angeles Times | first=Edmund | last=Sanders | title=Israel divorce law traps women in marriages that died long ago | date=26 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, Justice Menachem HaCohen of the [[Jerusalem]] Family Court offered new hope to ''agunot'' when he ruled that a man refusing his wife a ''get'' must pay her NIS 425,000 in punitive damages, because "[R]efusal to grant a ''get'' constitutes a severe infringement on her ability to lead a reasonable, normal life, and can be considered emotional abuse lasting several years." He noted that "[T]his is not another sanction against someone refusing to give a ''get'', intended to speed up the process of granting a ''get'', and this court is not involving itself in any future arrangements for the granting of a ''get'', but rather, it is a direct response to the consequences that stem from not granting a ''get'', and the right of the woman to receive punitive damages." This ruling stemmed from the Public Litigation Project initiated by the advocacy organization [[Center for Women's Justice Israel|Center for Women's Justice]] as one of a number of successful lawsuits filed in Israeli civil courts claiming financial damages against recalcitrant husbands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Weiss|first=Susan|title=The Tort of Get Refusal: Why Tort and Why Not?|journal=Conversations|series=Orthodoxy: Family &amp; Gender Issues|issue=5|url=http://www.jewishideas.org/articles/tort-get-refusal-why-tort-and-why-not|access-date=19 July 2011| archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20110703092706/http://www.jewishideas.org/articles/tort-get-refusal-why-tort-and-why-not| archive-date= 3 July 2011 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014 the Rabbinate of [[Uruguay]] instituted the requirement for all Jewish couples that marry under its auspices to sign a Rabbinic Pre-nuptial Agreement. The agreement states that in the case of the couple divorcing civilly, the husband is obligated to immediately deliver to his wife a ''get''. The initiative was launched by [[Sara Winkowski]], a director of the Kehila, the Comunidad Israelita del Uruguay (Jewish Community of Uruguay), who is also a Vice President of the World Jewish Congress and longtime activist for the rights of women within Jewish law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vosizneias.com/153024/2014/01/23/montevideo-uruguay-chief-rabbi-institutes-rabbinic-pre-nuptial-agreement/|title=Montevideo - Uruguay Chief Rabbi Institutes Rabbinic Pre-Nuptial Agreement|date=23 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015 [[Tzohar (organization)|Tzohar]] (a religious Zionist rabbinic organization in Israel), along with the [[Israel Bar Association]], introduced a prenuptial agreement meant to help ensure divorcing wives will receive a ''get''; under the agreement the husband commits to paying a high sum of money daily to his spouse in the event of a separation.&lt;ref name="Jta.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jta.org/2015/03/03/news-opinion/israel-middle-east/new-prenup-aims-to-prevent-agunot |title=Israeli rabbinic, legal groups partner for prenup in bid to prevent agunot &amp;#124; Jewish Telegraphic Agency |publisher=Jta.org |date=2015-03-03 |access-date=2015-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2018 the [[Knesset]] passed a law, slated to remain in effect for three years, allowing Israel's rabbinical courts to handle certain cases of Jewish women wishing to divorce their Jewish husbands, even if neither the wife nor the husband is an Israeli citizen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/.premium-israel-gives-rabbinical-courts-unprecedented-control-over-diaspora-jew-1.6216340 |title=Israel gives rabbinical courts unprecedented jurisdiction over Diaspora Jews - Israel News |newspaper=Haaretz |publisher=Haaretz.com |access-date=2018-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[List of Jewish feminists]]
* [[Feminist Jewish ethics]]
* [[Jewish Women's Archive]]
* [[Homosexuality and Judaism]]
* [[Feminism in Israel|Israeli feminism]]
** [[Mizrahi feminism]]
* [[Orthodox Jewish feminism]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Feldman, Emmanuel. {{cite web|url= http://www.ou.org/publications/ja/5760winter/orthodox%20feminism.pdf |title=Orthodox Feminism and Feminist Orthodoxy }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(101&amp;nbsp;KB)}}. ''[[Jewish Action]]'', Winter 1999
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070226163311/http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/newscontent.php3?artid=13679 "Girls Just Wanna Be 'Frum': JOFA conference speaker says feminism lags at Talmud study programs in Israel"], ''NY Jewish Week'', February 2007.
* [[Anita Diamant]]. [http://www.patheos.com/Resources/Additional-Resources/Holding-Up-Half-the-Sky-Feminist-Judaism.html "Holding Up Half the Sky: Feminist Judaism"], ''[[Patheos]]''
*''[http://www.jwa.org/feminism/ Jewish women and the feminist revolution], an exhibit of the Jewish Women's Archive'' &lt;small&gt;([[Adobe Flash|Flash]] interactive site)&lt;/small&gt;
*[http://www.jofa.org Jewish Orthodox Feminist Alliance (JOFA)]
* [[Rachel Adler|Adler, Rachel]]. "[http://jwa.org/sites/jwa.org/files/mediaobjects/the_jew_who_wasnt_there_adler.jpg The Jew Who Wasn't There: Halakha and the Jewish Woman]," ''Davka'', 1971.
* [[Rachel Adler|Adler, Rachel]]. ''Engendering Judaism: An Inclusive Theology and Ethics.'' Beacon Press, 1999.
* [[Rachel Adler|Adler, Rachel]]. [http://www.crosscurrents.org/Adlerwinter2002.htm "Feminist Judaism: Past and Future"], ''Crosscurrents'', Winter 2002, Vol. 51, No 4.
* Fishman, Sylvia Barack. ''A Breath of Life: Feminism in the American Jewish Community''. Brandeis, 1995. {{ISBN|0874517060}}.
* [[Blu Greenberg|Greenberg, Blu]]. "Will There Be Orthodox Women Rabbis?". Judaism 33.1 (Winter 1984): 23–33.
* [[Blu Greenberg|Greenberg, Blu]]. "Is Now the Time for Orthodox Women Rabbis?". Moment Dec. 1992: 50–53, 74.
* [[Rita Gross|Gross, Rita]]. "Female God Language in a Jewish Context." ''Davka'', 1976.
* [[Tova Hartman|Hartman, Tova]], ''Feminism Encounters Traditional Judaism: Resistance and Accommodation''. Brandeis University Press, 2007. {{ISBN|1-58465-658-1}}.
* [[Paula Hyman|Hyman, Paula]]. "The Other Half: Women in the Jewish Tradition" in E. Koltun. ''The Jewish Woman: New Perspectives'', Shocken 1976.
* [[Paula Hyman|Hyman, E. Paula]] &amp; [[Deborah Dash Moore|Dash Moore, Deborah]]. (eds) (1997) [http://ajhs.org/publications/pages/JewishWomen.cfm ''Jewish Women in America: An Historical Encyclopedia''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100227124311/http://www.ajhs.org/publications/pages/JewishWomen.cfm |date=27 February 2010 }}. Routledge, {{ISBN|0-415-91934-7}}
* [[Paula Hyman|Hyman, E. Paula]] &amp; Dalia Ofer. (eds) (2006) [http://jwa.org/encyclopedia ''Jewish Women: A Comprehensive Historical Encyclopedia'']. Jewish Publication Society CD-ROM
* Janowitz, Naomi and [[Margaret Wenig]]. ''Siddur Nashim.'' Self-published, 1976.
* [[Smadar Lavie|Lavie, Smadar]]. "[https://www.academia.edu/1804726/Mizrahi_Feminism_and_the_Question_of_Palestine_JMEWS_ Mizrahi Feminism and the Question of Palestine]." Journal of Middle East Women Studies. Vol. 7 (2): 56-88 
* Nadell, Pamela. ''Women Who Would Be Rabbis: A History of Women's Ordination, 1889–1985''. Beacon Press, 1998. {{ISBN|0-8070-3649-8}}.
* [[Haviva Ner-David|Ner-David, Haviva]].  ''Life on the Fringes: A Feminist Journey Toward Traditional Rabbinic Ordination.''  Needham, MA: JFL Books, 2000.
* Nussbaum Cohen, Debra. "The women's movement, Jewish identity and the story of a religion transformed," ''[[The Jewish Week]]'', 17 June 2004
* [[Cynthia Ozick|Ozick, Cynthia]]. "Notes toward finding the right question" in Heschel, S. ''On Being a Jewish Feminist: A Reader''. Schocken, 1983.
* [[Judith Plaskow|Plaskow, Judith]]. "The right question is theological" in Heschel, S. ''On being a Jewish Feminist: A Reader'', Shocken, 1983(a).
* [[Judith Plaskow|Plaskow, Judith]]. "Language, God and Liturgy: A Feminist Perspective," ''Response'' 44:3–14, 1983(b).
* [[Judith Plaskow|Plaskow, Judith]]. ''Standing again at Sinai: Judaism from a Feminist Perspective'', Harper and Row, 1990(a)
* [[Judith Plaskow|Plaskow, Judith]]. "Beyond Egalitarianism," ''Tikkun'' 5.6:79–81, 1990(b).
* [[Judith Plaskow|Plaskow, Judith]]. "Facing the Ambiguity of God," ''Tikkun''. 6.5:70-1, 1991. 
* Raphael, Melissa. ''The Female Face of God in Auschwitz: A Jewish Feminist Theology of the Holocaust .'' London: Routledge, 2003.
* [[Danya Ruttenberg|Ruttenberg, Danya]]., ed. "Yentl's Revenge: The Next Wave of Jewish Feminism." Seal Press, 2001.
* Scholten-Gutierrez, Melissa. [http://www.patheos.com/Resources/Additional-Resources/Ever-Evolving-Judaism.html "An Ever-Evolving Judaism: Women Meeting the Needs of the Community"], ''[[Patheos]]''
* Teman, Elly. "Birthing a Mother: the Surrogate Body and the Pregnant Self." Berkeley: University of California Press, 2010.
* [[Ellen Umansky|Umansky, E.]] &amp; Ashton, D. (eds) ''Four Centuries of Jewish Women's Spirituality: A Sourcebook'', Beacon, 1992.
* [[Trude Weiss-Rosmarin|Weiss-Rosmarin, Trude]]. "The Unfreedom of Jewish Women", originally published in the ''Jewish Spectator'', 1970.
* [[Joel B. Wolowelsky|Wolowelsky, Joel B.]] "Feminism and Orthodox Judaism", ''Judaism'', 188, 47:4, 1998, 499–507.

{{Women in Judaism|state=expanded}}
{{Jews and Judaism}}
{{Theology}}
{{Relpolnav}}

[[Category:Jewish feminism| ]]
[[Category:Jewish feminists| ]]
[[Category:Judaism and society|Feminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>