<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181106204739|867608727" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8182743" pageid="8182743" ns="0" title="Ethnic hatred"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-10T14:50:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=November 2017}}
'''Ethnic hatred''', '''inter-ethnic hatred''', '''racial hatred''', or '''ethnic tension''' refers to feelings  and acts of [[prejudice]] and hostility towards an [[ethnic group]] in various degrees. See [[list of anti-ethnic and anti-national terms]] for specific cases. 

There are multiple origins for ethnic hatred and the resulting [[ethnic conflict]]s. In some societies it is rooted in [[tribalism]], while in others it originates from a history of non-peaceful co-existence and the resulting actual disputed issues. 

Often ethnic conflict is enhanced by [[nationalism]] and feeling of national superiority. For which reason inter-ethnic hatred borders with [[racism]], and often the two terms are conflated.

Ethnic hatred has often been exploited and even fueled by some political leaders to serve their agenda of seeking to consolidate the nation or gain electorate by calling for a united struggle against a common enemy (real or imaginary).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalpolicy.org/security/issues/ind-pak/2002/0707ethnic.htm Using Ethnic Hatred to Meet Political Ends] (about ethnic problems in Indian subcontinent)&lt;/ref&gt; 

In many countries [[incitement to ethnic or racial hatred]] is a [[criminal offense]].

== Role of media ==
Media persuasion plays a role in dissemination of [[Ethnic group|ethnic]] hatred. Media presence spreads underlying messages that negatively portrays certain ethnic groups to the eye of the public. For example, political elites use media exposure to influence the views of the viewers towards a certain [[propaganda]]. In 1930s Nazi Germany, media presence in exposing propaganda in terms of hatred was effectively organized by Joseph Goebbels.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Petrova|first=Maria|last2=Yanagizawa-Drott|first2=David|date=2016-07-01|title=Media Persuasion, Ethnic Hatred, and Mass Violence: A Brief Overview of Recent Research Advances|url=http://www.oxfordscholarship.com/view/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199378296.001.0001/acprof-9780199378296-chapter-12|language=en-US|doi=10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199378296.001.0001/acprof-9780199378296-chapter-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;Although, Recent US Data (Berelson, Lazarsfeld, and McPhee 1954; Lazarsfeld, Berelson, and Gaudet 1944) shows media as a tool that does not carry “significant independent influence,” media “strengthens people’s predispositions.” &lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;Furthermore, Exogenous variation plays a role in utilizing media content towards escalating ethnic hatred presence according to recent economic studies. &lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;The effects of media on people varies in different platforms strengthening mass medias influence towards the public. Data polled from Muslim countries shows that exposure to Al-Jazeera is associated with higher levels of reported anti-Americanism in contrast to exposure to CNN associating with less anti-Americanism. &lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

There are two types of persuasion: direct and indirect. Direct persuasion in regard to mass media exponentially expands hatred that leads to violence of ethnic groups. Indirect persuasion exports hatred and directs behavior towards executing violence.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

The continuous use of mass media as an apparatus to spread negative image of ethnic groups is seen throughout variations of history. Most media hate speech that amplified worldwide attention are experienced in Rwanda and Yugoslavia. Also, Media’s control of hate speech that Nazi and fascist parties manipulate agitate and attract followers into advocating for hatred and violence. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Arcan|first=H. Esra|date=2013-10-01|title=Ethnic Conflicts and the Role of the Media: The Case of Turkish Media|url=http://www.mcser.org/journal/index.php/mjss/article/view/1196|journal=Mediterranean Journal of Social Sciences|language=en|volume=4|issue=10|pages=338|doi=10.5901/mjss.2013.v4n10p338|issn=2039-2117}}&lt;/ref&gt;Today, [[Social media|Social Media]] plays a role in ethnic conflicts in Kenya. [[Ethnicity]] is a big part in determining voting patterns in Kenya; however, many associate ethnicity with grievances that mobilize patterns of differences, hatred, and violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ndonye|first=Michael  M.|title=Social Media, Ethnic hatred and Peace Journalism: Case of Twitter and FaceBook use in Kenya.|url=http://www.academia.edu/7305771/Social_Media_Ethnic_hatred_and_Peace_Journalism_Case_of_Twitter_and_FaceBook_use_in_Kenya|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:PropagandaNaziStabsBible.gif|thumb|Propaganda designed by Barbara J. Marks that shows viable medium of persuasion and information. ]]

== Propaganda ==
Along with mass media, propaganda plays as much role in distributing messages in terms of ethnic hatred. Propaganda is highly associated with totalitarian regimes in the twentieth century such as 1984 and [[Animal Farm]] by George Orwell that paved a way of commentating the regimes during the time.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Media, Persuasion, and Propaganda|last=Soules|first=Marshall|publisher=Edinburgh University Press Ltd|year=2015|isbn=978 0 7486 4415 5|location=The Tun - Holyrood Road 12 (2f) Jackson's Entry Edinburgh EH8 8PJ|pages=4-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;However, propaganda is dangerous when utilized negatively. In original meaning, propaganda promotes beliefs leading towards action.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;Alternatively, Jowett and O’Donnell defines propaganda as ‘deliberate, systematic attempt to shape perceptions, manipulate cognitions, and direct behavior to achieve a response that furthers the desired intent of the propagandist’.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;The definition shows self-interested manipulation – an assumption that is difficult to prove. Negatively, propaganda presents “organised myth” that limits the chance of discovering the truth. The utilization of propaganda by Stalin, Hitler and Mussolini popularize the false impression of propaganda that hid the truth for an extended time.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;In addition, there are complex influences that emerged during the propaganda campaigns of the [[World War I|Great War]] (1914-18) and [[Russian Revolution]] (1917) such as telegraphs, newspapers, photography, radio, film, large corporations seeking new markets, rise of reform-minded journalism, and the influence of art movements, psychology, sociology, and marketing.The variation of propaganda and psychological warfare are essentially organized processes of persuasion. &lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;             

==See also==
*[[Ethnic cleansing]]
*[[Ethnocide]]
*[[Genocide]]
*[[Hate crime]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Religious hatred]]
*''[[World on Fire (book)|World on Fire]]''

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}
{{Ethnicity}}
[[Category:Anti-national sentiment]]
[[Category:Ethnic conflict]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>