<?xml version="1.0"?><api batchcomplete=""><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8182743" pageid="8182743" ns="0" title="Ethnic hatred"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-03-16T10:25:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Ethnic hatred''', '''inter-ethnic hatred''', '''racial hatred''', or '''ethnic tension''' refers to feelings  and acts of [[prejudice]] and hostility towards an [[ethnic group]] in various degrees. See [[list of anti-ethnic and anti-national terms]] for specific cases. 

There are multiple origins for ethnic hatred and the resulting [[ethnic conflict]]s. In some societies it is rooted in [[tribalism]], while in others it originates from a history of non-peaceful co-existence and the resulting actual disputed issues. 

Often ethnic conflict is enhanced by [[nationalism]] and feeling of national superiority. For which reason inter-ethnic hatred borders with [[racism]], and often the two terms are conflated.

On the opposite side, ethnic conflict may stem from the feeling of real or perceived [[discrimination]] by another ethnic group, see "[[reverse racism]]".

Ethnic hatred has often been exploited and even fueled by some political leaders to serve their agenda of seeking to consolidate the nation or gain electorate by calling for a united struggle against a common enemy (real or imaginary).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalpolicy.org/security/issues/ind-pak/2002/0707ethnic.htm Using Ethnic Hatred to Meet Political Ends] (about ethnic problems in Indian subcontinent)&lt;/ref&gt; 

In many countries [[incitement to ethnic or racial hatred]] is a [[criminal offense]].

==See also==
*[[Racism]]
*[[Ethnic cleansing]]
*[[Genocide]]
*[[Ethnocide]]
*''[[World on Fire]]''
*[[Hate crime]]
*[[Religious hatred]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Ethnicity}}
[[Category:Anti-national sentiment]]
[[Category:Ethnic conflict|*]]

{{sociology-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>