<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241027120603|1253698780" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8182743" pageid="8182743" ns="0" title="Ethnic hatred"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-05T16:12:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Feelings and acts of prejudice and hostility towards an ethnic group}}
{{refimprove|date=November 2017}}{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
'''Ethnic hatred''', '''inter-ethnic hatred''', '''racial hatred''', or '''ethnic tension''' refers to notions and acts of [[prejudice]] and hostility towards an [[Ethnicity|ethnic group]] to varying degrees.

It is a form of [[Racism|racial prejudice]], based on ethnic origin or region of origin. It can be accompanied by the systematic oppression of the [[Minority group|ethnic minority group]]. Unlike under [[Cultural assimilation|assimilationism]], the ethnicity is often in physical danger ([[confrontation]]s, [[dehumanization]], [[pogrom]]s, [[lynching]]s, [[massacre]]s), and can be targeted by [[apartheid]], general hostility or [[Vandalism|property vandalism]]. In special cases [[forced labour]], [[deportation]], revocation of human rights, and property looting.

There are multiple origins of ethnic [[hatred]] and the resulting [[ethnic conflict]]s. In some societies, it is rooted in [[tribalism]], and in other societies, it originates in a history of non-peaceful co-existence and the resulting actual disputed issues. In many countries, [[incitement to ethnic or racial hatred]] is a [[Crime|criminal offense]]. Frequently, ethnic conflict is stoked by [[Nationalism|nationalist]] fervor and sentiments of national superiority—for which reason, inter-ethnic hatred borders on [[racism]], and frequently, the two terms are conflated.

Often the minority itself can identify with the nationalism of the majority, claiming to be of different origins but the same nationality (see [[Neolog Judaism|Neology]]). The ethnicist narrative often uses [[stereotype]]s and [[New Order (Nazism)|predeterministic roles]]. It can stem from [[ethnic nationalism]]. It cannot be compared to [[Nativism (politics)|nativism]], as the question of [[nationality]] is definition-dependent. While racism, [[scientific racism]] and [[Discrimination based on skin tone|colorism]] are based on appearances and the concept of race, ethnicism is instead based on nationalist historical commentary. However, the border between ethnicism and racism are sometimes hard to define, for example, the [[Hispanic]] community can defined as both a race and ethnicity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Lopez |first1=Mark Hugo |last2=Krogstad |first2=Jens Manuel |last3=Passel |first3=Jeffrey S. |name-list-style=and |orig-date=Original date 28 May 2009 |date=2024-09-12 |title=Who is Hispanic? |url=https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2023/09/05/who-is-hispanic/ |access-date=2024-09-30 |website=[[Pew Research Center]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Various political leaders have exploited and even fueled ethnic hatred in the service of their desire to consolidate their power or make electoral gains by calling for the formation of a united front against a common enemy (real or imaginary).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Pocha |first=Jehangir |title=Using Ethnic Hatred to Meet Political Ends |url=https://archive.globalpolicy.org/security/issues/ind-pak/2002/0707ethnic.htm |website=[[Global Policy Forum]] |access-date=30 September 2024 |date=7 June 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An example of ethnic hatred is the reported animosity towards the [[Romani people]] in Europe. The Romani people, also known as Gypsies, are one of the most marginalized and persecuted ethnic groups in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://blog.lboro.ac.uk/london/diplomatic-studies/why-are-roma-also-hated|title= Why are Roma also hated?|date= 15 April 2019|access-date= 3 April 2022|archive-date= 21 October 2020|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20201021192058/https://blog.lboro.ac.uk/london/diplomatic-studies/why-are-roma-also-hated|url-status= dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jews]] are also a group typically targeted by right wing [[propaganda]], both for their ethnicity and [[Judaism|religion]].

== Role of the media ==
Media persuasion plays a role in the dissemination of [[Ethnic group|ethnic]] hatred. A media presence spreads underlying messages that negatively portrays certain ethnic groups in the eyes of the public. For example, political elites use media exposure to influence the opinions of the viewers towards a certain [[propaganda]]. In [[Nazi Germany]] in the 1930s, the media's presence in exposing propaganda in terms of hatred was effectively organized by Joseph Goebbels.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Petrova|first1=Maria|author1-link=Maria Petrova (economist)|last2=Yanagizawa-Drott|first2=David|date=2016-07-01|title=Media Persuasion, Ethnic Hatred, and Mass Violence: A Brief Overview of Recent Research Advances|url=http://www.oxfordscholarship.com/view/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199378296.001.0001/acprof-9780199378296-chapter-12|doi=10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199378296.001.0001|isbn=9780199378296}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although recent US data (Berelson, Lazarsfeld, and McPhee 1954; Lazarsfeld, Berelson, and Gaudet 1944) shows media as a tool that does not carry "significant independent influence," media "strengthens people's predispositions."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Furthermore, exogenous variation plays a role in utilizing media content towards escalating ethnic hatred presence according to recent economic studies.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The effects of media on people varies in different platforms strengthening mass medias influence towards the public. Data polled from Muslim countries shows that exposure to Al-Jazeera is associated with higher levels of reported anti-Americanism in contrast to exposure to CNN associating with less anti-Americanism.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

There are two types of persuasion: direct and indirect. Direct persuasion with regard to mass media exponentially expands hatred that leads to violence against ethnic groups. Indirect persuasion exports hatred and directs behavior towards the execution of [[violence]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

The continuous use of mass media as an apparatus to spread negative image of ethnic groups is seen throughout history. Most media hate speech that amplified worldwide attention are experienced in Rwanda and Yugoslavia. Also, media's control of hate speech that Nazi and fascist parties manipulate agitate and attract followers into advocating for hatred and violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Arcan|first=H. Esra|date=2013-10-01|title=Ethnic Conflicts and the Role of the Media: The Case of Turkish Media|journal=Mediterranean Journal of Social Sciences|volume=4|issue=10|pages=338|doi=10.5901/mjss.2013.v4n10p338|issn=2039-2117|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, [[social media]] plays a role in ethnic conflicts in Kenya. [[Ethnicity]] is a big part in determining voting patterns in Kenya; however, many associate ethnicity with grievances that mobilize patterns of differences, hatred, and violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ndonye |first=Michael M. |title=Social Media, Ethnic hatred and Peace Journalism: Case of Twitter and FaceBook use in Kenya |url=https://www.ijmra.us/project%20doc/2014/IJPSS_JUNE2014/IJMRA-5614.pdf |year=2014 |volume=4 |issue=6 |pages=437–450 |journal=International Journal of Physical and Social Sciences |s2cid=146262985 |issn=2249-5894}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Propaganda ==

[[File:No Dogs-Negroes-Mexicans - Racist Sign from Deep South - National Civil Rights Museum - Downtown Memphis - Tennessee - USA.jpg|thumb|"No Dogs, Negroes, Mexicans" was a policy enforced by the Lonestar Restaurant Association throughout [[Texas]], discriminating against ethnic [[Mexicans]].]]
Along with mass media, propaganda plays as much role in distributing messages in terms of ethnic hatred. Propaganda is highly associated with totalitarian regimes in the twentieth century such as ''[[Nineteen Eighty-Four]]'' and ''[[Animal Farm]]'' by [[George Orwell]] that paved a way of commentating the regimes during the time.&lt;ref name="Soules book"&gt;{{cite book |last=Soules |first=Marshall |title=Media, Persuasion and Propaganda |year=2015 |publisher=[[Edinburgh University Press]] |location=Edinburgh |isbn=978-0-7486-4415-5 |oclc=898316003 |pages=4–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, propaganda is dangerous when utilized negatively. In original meaning, propaganda promotes beliefs leading towards action.&lt;ref name="Soules book" /&gt; Alternatively, Jowett and O'Donnell define propaganda as "deliberate, systematic attempt to shape perceptions, manipulate cognitions, and direct behavior to achieve a response that furthers the desired intent of the propagandist".&lt;ref name="Soules book" /&gt; The definition shows self-interested manipulation – an assumption that is difficult to prove. Negatively, propaganda presents "organised myth" that limits the chance of discovering the truth. The utilization of propaganda by Stalin, Hitler and Mussolini popularize the false impression of propaganda that hid the truth for an extended time.&lt;ref name="Soules book" /&gt; In addition, there are complex influences that emerged during the propaganda campaigns of the [[World War I|Great War]] (1914-18) and [[Russian Revolution]] (1917) such as telegraphs, newspapers, photography, radio, film, large corporations seeking new markets, rise of reform-minded journalism, and the influence of art movements, psychology, sociology, and marketing.The variation of propaganda and psychological warfare are essentially organized processes of persuasion.&lt;ref name="Soules book" /&gt;

However, empirical research casts doubt on the role of propaganda in inciting hatred, finding that it is much less able to change minds than is often assumed. For example, a 2017 review of literature says: "First, propaganda often fails. To take the example of [[Propaganda in Nazi Germany|Nazi propaganda]], it failed to generate support for euthanasia of the handicapped (Kershaw, 1983a; Kuller, 2015), it largely failed to turn people into rabid anti-Semites (Kershaw, 1983b; Voigtländer &amp; Voth, 2015), it failed to generate much liking for the Nazi party (Kershaw, 1983b, 1987), and it soon failed to make Germans more optimistic about the outcome of the war (Kallis, 2008; Kershaw, 1983a; for similar examples regarding Stalinist propaganda, see Brandenberger, 2012; Davies, 1997; Maoist propaganda, see Wang, 1995; North Korean propaganda, see B. R. Myers, 2011).&lt;ref&gt; Mercier, H. (2017). How gullible are we? A review of the evidence from psychology and social science. Review of General Psychology, 21(2), 103-122.https://dx.doi.org/10.1037/gpr0000111&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Dahiya doctrine]]
*[[Discrimination]]
*[[Domicide]]
*[[Ethnic cleansing]]
*[[Ethnic violence]]
*[[Ethnocentrism]]
*[[Ethnocide]]
*[[Fundamentalism]]
*[[Genocide]]
*[[Hate crime]]
*[[Nativism (politics)]]
*[[Oppression]]
*[[Persecution]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Religious discrimination]]
*[[Religious fanaticism]]
*[[Religious intolerance]]
*[[Religious persecution]]
*[[Religious segregation]]
*[[Religious violence]]
*[[Sectarianism]]
*[[Sectarian violence]]
*[[Supremacism]]
*''[[World on Fire (book)|World on Fire]]''
*[[Xenophobia]]
*[[Anti-Romani sentiment]]
*[[Antisemitism]]
*[[Hispanophobia]]
*[[Islamophobia]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}
{{Ethnicity}}
{{Nationalism}}
{{Racism topics}}

[[Category:Anti-national sentiment]]
[[Category:Ethnic conflict]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination by type]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>