<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131118095730|582182412" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="156858" pageid="156858" ns="0" title="Asexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-20T01:17:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|humans who lack sexual attraction or interest in sexual activity|other uses|Asexual (disambiguation){{!}}Asexual}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}
{{good article}}
{{sexual orientation}}
'''Asexuality''' (or '''nonsexuality''')&lt;ref name="asexual"&gt;{{cite web|title=Asexual|publisher=thefreedictionary.com| accessdate=3 December 2011|url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/asexual}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="nonsexual"&gt;{{cite web|title=Nonsexual| publisher=thefreedictionary.com| accessdate=3 December 2011|url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/nonsexual}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Harris"&gt;{{cite web|first=Lynn|last=Harris|title=Asexual and proud!|work=[[Salon (website)|Salon]]|date=26 May 2005|accessdate=3 December 2011|url=http://www.salon.com/2005/05/26/asexual/}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the lack of [[sexual attraction]] to anyone or low or absent interest in [[Human sexual activity|sexual activity]].&lt;ref name= Bogaert2006&gt;Bogaert, Anthony F. (2006). [http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=18172400 "Toward a conceptual understanding of asexuality"]. ''[[Review of General Psychology]]'' '''10''' (3)  241–250. Retrieved 31 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kelly"&gt;{{cite book|last = Kelly| first = Gary F.| authormask =  | authorlink = |title = Sexuality Today: The Human Perspective|url =|edition=7|series =| year = 2004 | publisher = [[McGraw-Hill]] |location=|isbn= 9780072558357|oclc = |doi =|bibcode =|id =| page = 401| pages =| nopp = | at =|chapter  = Chapter 12 | chapterurl =|quote =|ref =| laysummary =|laydate =|separator=|postscript = &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Asexuality is a condition characterized by a low interest in sex.|lastauthoramp =}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Prause"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Prause|first=Nicole|coauthors=Cynthia A. Graham|year=2004|month=August|url=http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/publications/PDF/PrauseGrahamPDF.pdf|title=Asexuality: Classification and Characterization|journal=[[Archives of Sexual Behavior]]|volume=36|pages=341–356|accessdate=31 August 2007|doi=10.1007/s10508-006-9142-3|format=PDF|pmid=17345167|issue=3| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20070927014407/http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/publications/PDF/PrauseGrahamPDF.pdf| archivedate= 27 September 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;|deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; It may be considered the lack of a [[sexual orientation]], or one of the four variations thereof, alongside [[heterosexuality]], [[homosexuality]], and [[bisexuality]].&lt;ref name = Bogaert2004&gt;{{cite journal |last=Bogaert|first=Anthony F. |year=2004 |title=Asexuality: prevalence and associated factors in a national probability sample |journal=[[Journal of Sex Research]] |volume=41 |issue=3 |pages=279–87|accessdate=May 12, 2013 |pmid=15497056 |doi=10.1080/00224490409552235}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Sexual orientation"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Melby|first=Todd|title=Asexuality gets more attention, but is it a sexual orientation?|journal=Contemporary Sexuality|year=2005|month=November|volume=39|issue=11|pages=1, 4–5| issn = 1094-5725|url = http://www.apositive.org/wordpress_backup/?page_id=222 |archiveurl = http://archive.is/z19E| archivedate = 29 Jun 2012&lt;!-- 00:17:32 --&gt;|accessdate=20 November 2011 | postscript = &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[http://journalseek.net/cgi-bin/journalseek/journalsearch.cgi?field=title&amp;query=1094-5725 The journal currently does not have a website]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Sex and society"&gt;{{cite book|editor=Marshall Cavendish|title=Sex and Society|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=aVDZchwkIMEC&amp;pg=PA82|accessdate=27 July 2013|volume=2|year=2010|publisher=Marshall Cavendish|isbn=978-0-7614-7906-2|pages=82–83|contribution=Asexuality}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study in 2004 placed the prevalence of asexuality at 1%.&lt;ref name=Bogaert2004/&gt;&lt;ref name="cnn"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2004/TECH/science/10/14/asexual.study/index.html |title=Study: One in 100 adults asexual |publisher=CNN |accessdate=11 November 2007 | date=15 October 2004| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20071027081628/http://www.cnn.com/2004/TECH/science/10/14/asexual.study/index.html| archivedate= 27 October 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Asexuality is distinct from [[sexual abstinence|abstention from sexual activity]] and from [[celibacy]],&lt;ref name="DePaulo"&gt;{{cite web|first=Bella|last=DePaulo|title=ASEXUALS: Who Are They and Why Are They Important?|publisher=''[[Psychology Today]]''|date=26 September 2011|accessdate=13 December 2011|url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/living-single/200912/asexuals-who-are-they-and-why-are-they-important}}&lt;/ref&gt;  which are behavioral and generally motivated by factors such as an individual's personal or religious beliefs;&lt;ref&gt;''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'' (3d ed. 1992), entries for ''celibacy'' and thence ''abstinence''&lt;/ref&gt; sexual orientation, unlike sexual behavior, is believed to be "enduring".&lt;ref name="apahelp"&gt;{{cite web|title=Sexual orientation, homosexuality and bisexuality|publisher=[[American Psychological Association]]|accessdate=March 30, 2013|url=http://www.apa.org/helpcenter/sexual-orientation.aspx}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some asexual people do engage in sexual activity despite lacking a desire for sex or sexual attraction, due to a variety of reasons, such as a desire to please romantic partners or a desire to have children.&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt;

Acceptance of asexuality as a sexual orientation and field of [[scientific method|scientific research]] is still relatively new,&lt;ref name= Bogaert2006/&gt;&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Sexual orientation"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Overview&gt;{{cite web|title=Overview|url=http://www.asexuality.org/home/overview.html|accessdate=14 October 2011|year=2008|publisher=The Asexual Visibility and Education Network (AVEN)}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a growing body of research from both sociological and psychological perspectives has begun to develop.&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt; While some researchers assert that asexuality is a sexual orientation, other researchers disagree.&lt;ref name="Sexual orientation"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Sex and society"/&gt;

Various asexual communities have started to form since the advent of the Internet and social media. The most prolific and well-known of these communities is the Asexual Visibility and Education Network (AVEN), which was founded in 2001 by [[David Jay]].&lt;ref name="Sex and society"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Swash"&gt;{{cite web|first=Rosie|last= Swash|title=Among the asexuals|publisher=''[[The Guardian]]''|date=February 25, 2012|accessdate=February 2, 2013|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/lifeandstyle/2012/feb/26/among-the-asexuals}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
===Romantic relationships and identity===
{{further|Romantic orientation}}
Asexual people, while lacking sexual attraction to any gender, may engage in purely [[Romance (love)|romantic]] relationships.&lt;ref name="Sex and society"/&gt;&lt;ref name="New Scientist"&gt;{{cite web |author=Westphal, Sylvia Pagan (2004) |url=http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=dn6533 |title=Feature: Glad to be asexual|work=[[New Scientist]] |accessdate=11 November 2007|archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20071219003148/http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=dn6533| archivedate= 19 December 2007 | deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Relationships"&gt;[http://www.asexuality.org/home/relationship.html ''Relationship FAQ''] The Asexual Visibility and Education Network (AVEN), 2008. Retrieved 22 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Wellington"&gt;[http://www.gayline.gen.nz/asexual.htm ''Asexuality''] (Wellington, N.Z.: Gay Line Wellington, 2000–2010). Retrieved 22 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; With regard to the romantic or emotional aspects of [[sexual orientation]] or [[sexual identity]], they may identify as [[Heterosexuality|heterosexual]], [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexuality|bisexual]],&lt;ref name=Overview/&gt; or by the following terms:
* '''aromantic''': lack of romantic attraction towards anyone
* '''biromantic''' (also '''ambiromantic'''): romantic attraction towards men and women (but not necessarily at the same time)&amp;nbsp;, or romantic attraction towards two or more genders – the romantic aspect of bisexuality
* '''heteroromantic''': romantic attraction towards person(s) of a different gender&amp;nbsp;– the romantic aspect of heterosexuality
* '''homoromantic''': romantic attraction towards person(s) of the same gender&amp;nbsp;– the romantic aspect of [[homosexuality]]
* '''panromantic''': romantic attraction towards  person(s) of ''every'' gender&amp;nbsp;– the romantic aspect of [[pansexuality]]
* '''polyromantic''': romantic attraction towards multiple, but not all, genders. The romantic aspect of [[polysexuality]].
* '''andromantic''', '''gyneromantic''', and '''ambiromantic''': romantic attraction towards person(s) expressing masculinity or femininity or [[intersex]]/[[third gender]]-mixing (respectively) without implying the gender of the individual experiencing the attraction; often used by asexuals with a non-[[Gender binary|binary]] [[gender identity]]. The romantic aspect of [[androphilia and gynephilia|androphilia, gynephilia, and ambiphilia]].
* '''demiromantic''' or '''demisexual''': a person who may identify as a "grey asexual" because they may feel sexual desire once a reasonably stable or large emotional connection has been created.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Adler|first=Melissa|chapter=Meeting the Needs of LGBTIQ Library Users and Their Librarians: A Study of User Satisfaction and LGBTIQ Collection Development in Academic Libraries|year=2010|title=Serving LGBTIQ Library and Archives Users|editor-first=Ellen |editor-last=Greenblatt|publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]]|location=[[North Carolina]]|isbn=978-0-7864-4894-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Asexual Visibility and Education Network (AVEN) defines an asexual as "someone who does not experience sexual attraction" and stated, "[a]nother small minority will think of themselves as asexual for a brief period of time while exploring and questioning their own sexuality" and that "[t]here is no litmus test to determine if someone is asexual. Asexuality is like any other identity&amp;nbsp;– at its core, it's just a word that people use to help figure themselves out. If at any point someone finds the word asexual useful to describe themselves, we encourage them to use it for as long as it makes sense to do so."&lt;ref name=Overview/&gt;

Researchers generally define asexuality as the lack of sexual attraction or the lack of sexual interest,&lt;ref name= Bogaert2006/&gt;&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt;&lt;ref name="DePaulo"/&gt; but their definitions vary; they may use the term "to refer to individuals with low or absent sexual desire or attractions, low or absent sexual behaviors, exclusively romantic non-sexual partnerships, or a combination of both absent sexual desires and behaviors".&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt;

As an emerging identity with a broad definition, there is significant variation among people who identify as asexual; for example, asexual-identified individuals who report that they feel sexual attraction but not the inclination to act on it because they have no true desire or need to engage in sexual or even non-sexual activity (cuddling, hand-holding, etc.).&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt;&lt;ref name="DePaulo"/&gt; Some asexuals participate in sexual activity out of curiosity.&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt; Some may [[Masturbation|masturbate]] as a solitary form of release, while others do not feel a need to do so.&lt;ref name="New Scientist" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bridgeman"&gt;{{cite news|first=Shelley|last=Bridgeman|title=No sex please, we're asexual |date=5 August 2007 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]]|accessdate=16 September 2011|url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/lifestyle/news/article.cfm?c_id=6&amp;objectid=10455823&amp;pnum=0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The need or desire for masturbation is commonly referred to as ''[[libido|sex drive]]'' by asexuals and they disassociate it from sexual attraction and being sexual; asexuals who masturbate generally consider it to be a normal product of the human body and not a sign of latent sexuality, and may not even find it pleasurable.&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt; Some asexual men are completely unable to get an erection and sexual activity by attempting penetration is completely impossible for them.&lt;ref name="More to life"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Carrigan|first=Mark|title=There's More to Life Than Just Sex? Difference and Commonality Within the Asexual Community|journal=Sexualities|year=2011|month=August|volume=14|issue=4|pages=462–478|doi=10.1177/1363460711406462}}&lt;/ref&gt; Asexuals also differ in their feelings towards performing sex acts: some are indifferent and may even have sex for the benefit of a romantic partner; others are more strongly averse to the idea, though they do not necessarily dislike people for having sex.&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Overview/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bridgeman"/&gt;

===Sexual orientation and etiology===

There is significant debate over whether or not asexuality is a sexual orientation.&lt;ref name="Sexual orientation"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Sex and society"/&gt; It is most comparable to [[hypoactive sexual desire disorder]] (HSDD), in that both imply a general lack of sexual attraction to anyone, but asexuality is generally not considered a disorder (such as [[anorgasmia]], [[anhedonia]], etc.) or a [[sexual dysfunction]] because asexuality does not necessarily define someone as having a medical problem or problems relating to others socially.&lt;ref name="DePaulo"/&gt; It also does not necessarily imply that lacking sexual attraction causes anxiety; it is considered the lack or absence of sexual attraction as a life-enduring characteristic.&lt;ref name="Bogaert2006"/&gt; Some scholars, however, opine that asexuality is not a meaningful category to add to the continuum of sexual orientations, and say that it is instead the lack of a sexual orientation or sexuality.&lt;ref name="Sexual orientation"/&gt; Others state that it is the denial of one's natural sexuality, and that it is a disorder caused by shame of sexuality, anxiety or [[sexual abuse]], sometimes basing this belief on asexuals who masturbate or occasionally engage in sexual activity simply to please a romantic partner.&lt;ref name="Sexual orientation"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bridgeman"/&gt;&lt;ref name="More to life"/&gt;

Various other scholars assert that asexuality is a sexual orientation, as some asexuals are unable to masturbate even though they reportedly have a normal sex drive, and that there are variations of sexual preferences, arguing that asexuality ought to be included as well.&lt;ref name="Sexual orientation"/&gt;&lt;ref name="More to life"/&gt; They stress that asexuals do not choose to have no sexual desire, and generally start to find out their differences in sexual behaviors around adolescence. Because of these facts coming to light, it is argued that asexuality is much more than a behavioral choice, and is not something that can be cured like a disorder.&lt;ref name="More to life"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Koukounas"&gt;{{cite journal | last1= Over | first1= Ray | last2 = Koukounas | first2= Eric | year= 1995 | title = Habituation of Sexual Arousal: Product and Process | journal= Annual Review of sex Research | volume = 6 | issue = 1 | pages = 187–223 | doi= 10.1080/10532528.1995.10559905 | postscript= &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;See [http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/10532528.1995.10559905 here] }}&lt;br /&gt;Cited from: {{cite book |last= Kelly |first= Gary F. |authorlink = |title=Sexuality Today: The Human Perspective |edition= 7 |year=2004 |publisher=[[McGraw-Hill]] |isbn=9780072558357 |page=401}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Etiology'' in this context is without implication of disease, disorder, or abnormality.&lt;ref&gt;In ''Webster's Third'' (''[[Merriam-Webster]]''), ''etiology'' is defined both with and without reference to disease. The word is defined as "a science or doctrine of causation or of the demonstration of causes" and as "a branch of science dealing with the causes of particular phenomena", thus without implying disease or abnormality. However, it is also defined as "all the factors that contribute to the occurrence of a disease or abnormal condition". ''Webster's Third New International Dictionary of the English Language Unabridged'' ([prob. Springfield, Mass.:] G. &amp; C. Merriam (Merriam-Webster), 1966), entry ''etiology''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In the ''Shorter Oxford Eng. Dict.'' ([4th] ed.), ''etiology'' is defined both with and without reference to disease. The word is defined as "[t]he assignment of a cause", as "the cause assigned", and, as now rare or obsolete, as "[t]he philosophy of causation; the part of a science which treats of the causes of its phenomena". However, it is also defined in medicine as "[t]he causation of disease (usu., of a specified disease), esp. as a subject for investigation". ''The New Shorter Oxford English Dictionary: On Historical Principles'' (Oxford: Clarendon Press, [4th] ed. 1993 (ISBN 0-19-861271-0)), entry ''aetiology'', via entry ''etiology''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In the ''American Heritage Dict.'' (3d ed.), ''etiology'' is defined both with and without reference to disease. The word is defined as "[t]he study of causes or origins" and as "[a]ssignment of a cause, an origin, or a reason for something". However, it is also defined as "[t]he branch of medicine that deals with the causes or origins of disease" and as "[t]he cause or origin of a disease or disorder as determined by medical diagnosis". ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'' (Boston, Mass.: Houghton Mifflin, 3d ed. 1992 (ISBN 0-395-44895-6)), entry ''etiology''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In a nursing dictionary, ''etiology'' is defined relative only to disease. The word is defined as "[t]he study of the causes of disease" and as "[t]he cause of a disease", with no other definitions, in Thomas, Clayton L., ed., ''Taber's Cyclopedic Medical Dictionary'' (Philadelphia: F. A. Davis, ed. 16 8th printing 1989 (ISBN 0-8036-8310-3)), entry ''etiology''. The dictionary is intended for "those in the field of nursing" and others. ''Id''., p. viii (Introduction to Edition 16, by Clayton Lay Thomas).&lt;/ref&gt; Research on the etiology of sexual orientation when applied to asexuality has the definitional problem of sexual orientation not consistently being defined by researchers as including asexuality.&lt;ref&gt;E.g., one study on [[Prenatal hormones and sexual orientation#Prenatal hormones and sexuality-linked characteristics|hormonal influences]] defines sexual orientation as "heterosexuality, homosexuality, or bisexuality" only. Cited in: Garcia-Falgueras, Alicia, &amp; Swaab, Dick F. (2010). "Sexual Hormones and the Brain: An Essential Alliance for Sexual Identity and Sexual Orientation". ''Endocrine Development''. '''17''':24. PMID 19955753. (Article found in Sandro Loche, Marco Cappa, Lucia Ghizzoni, Mohamad Maghnie, &amp; Martin O. Savage, eds. Vol.17 ''Pediatric Neuroendocrinology'') ("sexual orientation (heterosexuality, homosexuality, or bisexuality)"). ISSN 1421-7082.&lt;/ref&gt; Sexual orientation is defined as "enduring" and resistant to change, proving to be generally impervious to interventions intended to change it.&lt;ref name="apahelp"/&gt; While heterosexuality, homosexuality and bisexuality are usually, but not always, determined during the early years of preadolescent life, it is not known when asexuality is determined. "It is unclear whether these characteristics [''viz.'', "lacking interest in or desire for sex"] are thought to be lifelong, or if they may be acquired."&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt;

Non-measurement in some areas of sexual orientation is accepted by the [[American Psychological Association]], the [[American Psychiatric Association]], and the [[National Association of Social Workers]]: "[S]imply to document that a phenomenon occurs, case studies and [[non-probability sample]]s are often adequate. . . . Some groups are sufficiently few in number&amp;nbsp;– relative to the entire population&amp;nbsp;– that locating them with probability sampling is extremely expensive or practically impossible. In the latter cases, the use of non-probability samples is often appropriate."&lt;ref name=amici&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.courts.ca.gov/documents/Amer_Psychological_Assn_Amicus_Curiae_Brief.pdf |page= 30 |title=Case No. S147999 in the Supreme Court of the State of California, In re Marriage Cases Judicial Council Coordination Proceeding No. 4365(...) – APA California Amicus Brief&amp;nbsp;— As Filed |format=PDF |accessdate=19 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In determining etiologies, when asexuals are a small percentage of a large society, asexuals with a given etiology will compose an even smaller percentage, so that etiological information is available only from some individuals, generally not randomly selected.&lt;ref&gt;Levinson, Nick, ''For Men Only: Asexuality'', in ''So to Speak: a feminist journal of language and art'', vol. 14, no. 2 (2005), pp. 51–54.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research==

===Prevalence===
Asexuality is not a new aspect of human sexuality, but it is relatively new to public discourse.&lt;ref name="Sesmith"&gt;{{cite web|first=SE |last= Smith|title= Asexuality always existed, you just didn't notice it |publisher=''[[The Guardian]]''|date=Tuesday 21 August 2012 |accessdate=March 11, 2013|url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2012/aug/21/asexuality-always-existed-asexual }}&lt;/ref&gt; SE Smith of ''[[The Guardian]]'' is not sure asexuality has actually increased, rather leaning towards the belief that it is simply more visible.&lt;ref name="Sesmith" /&gt; In the mid-twentieth century, [[Alfred Kinsey]] rated individuals from 0 to 6 according to their sexual orientation from heterosexual to homosexual, known as the [[Kinsey scale]]. He also included a category he called "X" for individuals with "no socio-sexual contacts or reactions";&lt;ref name="Kinsey-male"&gt;{{Cite book|first=Alfred C.|last=Kinsey|year=1948|title=Sexual Behavior in the Human Male|publisher=W.B. Saunders|isbn=0-253-33412-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kinsey-female"&gt;{{Cite book|first=Alfred C.|last=Kinsey|year=1953|title=Sexual Behavior in the Human Female|publisher=W.B. Saunders|isbn=0-253-33411-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; in modern times, this is categorized as representing asexuality.&lt;ref name="Stange"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Mary Zeiss Stange|author2=Carol K. Oyster|author3=Jane E. Sloan|title=Encyclopedia of Women in Today's World|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=bOkPjFQoBj8C&amp;pg=PA158|accessdate=27 July 2013|date=23 February 2011|publisher=SAGE Publications|isbn=978-1-4129-7685-5|page=158}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kinsey labeled 1.5% of the adult male population as ''X.''&lt;ref name="Kinsey-male"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Kinsey-female"/&gt; In his second book, ''Sexual Behavior in the Human Female'', he reported this breakdown of individuals who are X: unmarried females = 14–19%, married females = 1–3%, previously married females = 5–8%, unmarried males = 3–4%, married males = 0%, and previously married males = 1–2%.&lt;ref name="Kinsey-female" /&gt;

Further empirical data about an asexual demographic appeared in 1994, when a research team in the United Kingdom carried out a comprehensive survey of 18,876 British residents, spurred by the need for sexual information in the wake of the [[Epidemiology of HIV/AIDS|AIDS pandemic]]. The survey included a question on sexual attraction, to which 1.05% of the respondents replied that they had "never felt sexually attracted to anyone at all".&lt;ref&gt;Wellings, K. (1994). ''Sexual Behaviour in Britain: The National Survey of Sexual Attitudes and Lifestyles.'' Penguin Books.&lt;/ref&gt; The study of this phenomenon was continued by the Canadian sexuality researcher Anthony Bogaert in 2004, who explored the asexual demographic in a series of studies. Bogaert believed that the 1% figure was not an accurate reflection of the likely much larger percentage of the population that could be identified as asexual, noting that 30% of people contacted for the initial survey chose not to participate in the survey. Since less sexually experienced people are more likely to refuse to participate in studies about sexuality, and asexuals tend to be less sexually experienced than sexuals, it is likely that asexuals were under-represented in the responding participants. The same study found the number of homosexuals and bisexuals combined to be about 1.1% of the population, which is much smaller than other studies indicate.&lt;ref name="Bogaert2006" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bogaert2004" /&gt;

===Sexual activity and sexuality===
While some asexuals masturbate as a solitary form of release or have sex for the benefit of a romantic partner, others do not.&lt;ref name="Prause"/&gt;&lt;ref name="New Scientist"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bridgeman"/&gt; The [[Kinsey Institute for Research in Sex, Gender, and Reproduction|Kinsey Institute]] sponsored another small survey on the topic in 2007, which found that self-identified asexuals "reported significantly less desire for sex with a partner, lower sexual arousability, and lower sexual excitation but did not differ consistently from non-asexuals in their sexual inhibition scores or their desire to masturbate".&lt;ref name="Prause" /&gt;

A 1977 paper titled ''Asexual and Autoerotic Women: Two Invisible Groups'', by Myra T. Johnson, may be the first paper explicitly devoted to asexuality in humans. Johnson defines asexuals as those men and women "who, regardless of physical or emotional condition, actual sexual history, and marital status or ideological orientation, seem to ''prefer'' not to engage in sexual activity." She contrasts autoerotic women with asexual women: "The asexual woman [...] has no sexual desires at all [but] the autoerotic woman [...] recognizes such desires but prefers to satisfy them alone." Johnson's evidence is mostly letters to the editor found in women's magazines written by asexual/autoerotic women. She portrays them as invisible, "oppressed by a consensus that they are nonexistent," and left behind by both the sexual revolution and the feminist movement. Society either ignores or denies their existence or insists they must be ascetic for religious reasons, neurotic, or asexual for political reasons.&lt;ref&gt;"Asexual and Autoerotic Women: Two Invisible Groups" found in ed. Gochros, H.L.; J.S. Gochros (1977). ''The Sexually Oppressed. Associated Press.'' ISBN 978-0-8096-1915-3&lt;/ref&gt;

In a study published in 1979 in ''Advances in the Study of Affect'', vol. 5, and in another article using the same data and published in 1980 in the ''[[Journal of Personality and Social Psychology]]'', Michael D. Storms of the [[University of Kansas]] outlined his own reimagining of the Kinsey scale. Whereas Kinsey measured sexual orientation based on a combination of actual sexual behavior and fantasizing and eroticism, Storms only used fantasizing and eroticism. Storms, however, placed hetero-eroticism and homo-eroticism on separate axes rather than at two ends of a single scale; this allows for a distinction between bisexuality (exhibiting both hetero- and homo-eroticism in degrees comparable to hetero- or homosexuals, respectively) and asexuality (exhibiting a level of homo-eroticism comparable to a heterosexual and a level of hetero-eroticism comparable to a homosexual, namely, little to none). Storms conjectured that many researchers following Kinsey's model could be mis-categorizing asexual subjects as bisexual, because both were simply defined by a lack of preference for gender in sexual partners.&lt;ref name = Storms1980&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.38.5.783 | last1 = Storms | first1 = Michael D. | year = 1980 | title = Theories of Sexual Orientation | journal = [[Journal of Personality and Social Psychology]] | volume = 38 | issue = 5| pages = 783–792 | url = http://www.williamapercy.com/wiki/images/Theories_of_sexual_orientation.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = Storms1979&gt;Storms, M. D. (1979). Sexual orientation and self-perception. ed. Pliner, Patricia et al. ''Advances in the Study of Communication and Affect. Volume 5: Perception of Emotion in Self and Others'' Plenum Press&lt;/ref&gt;

The first study that gave empirical data about asexuals was published in 1983 by Paula Nurius, concerning the relationship between sexual orientation and mental health. Unlike previous studies on the subject, she used the above-mentioned two-dimensional model for sexual orientation. Six hundred eighty-nine subjects—most of whom were students at various universities in the United States taking psychology or sociology classes—were given several surveys, including four clinical well-being scales and a survey asking how frequently they engaged in various sexual activities and how often they would like to engage in those activities. Based on the results, respondents were given a score ranging from 0 to 100 for hetero-eroticism and from 0 to 100 for homo-eroticism. Respondents who scored lower than 10 on both were labeled "asexual." This consisted of 5% of the males and 10% of the females. Results showed that asexuals were more likely to have low self-esteem and more likely to be depressed than members of other sexual orientations; 25.88% of heterosexuals, 26.54% bisexuals (called "ambisexuals"), 29.88% of homosexuals, and 33.57% of asexuals were reported to have problems with self-esteem. A similar trend existed for depression. Nurius did not believe that firm conclusions can be drawn from this for a variety of reasons. Asexuals also reported much lower frequency and desired frequency of a variety of sexual activities including having multiple partners, anal sexual activities, having sexual encounters in a variety of locations, and autoerotic activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1080/00224498309551174 | last1 = Nurius | first1 = Paula | year = 1983| title = Mental Health Implications of Sexual Orientation | journal = The Journal of Sex Research | volume = 19 | issue = 2| pages = 119–136 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though comparisons with non-human sexuality are problematic, a series of studies done on [[Ram (sheep)|ram]] mating preferences at the United States Sheep Experiment Station in [[Dubois, Idaho]], starting in 2001 found that about 2–3% of the animals being studied had no apparent interest in mating with either sex; the researchers classified these animals as asexual, but found them to be otherwise healthy with no recorded differences in [[hormone]] levels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Charles A.|last=Roselli|year=2002|url=http://www.biolreprod.org/content/67/1/263.full|title=Relationship of serum testosterone concentrations to mate preferences in rams|journal=Biology of Reproduction|volume=67|pages=263–268|accessdate=31 August 2007|doi=10.1095/biolreprod67.1.263|pmid=12080026|last2=Stormshak|first2=F|last3=Stellflug|first3=JN|last4=Resko|first4=JA|issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=J.N.|last=Stellflug|date=1 June 2006|url=http://jas.fass.org/content/84/6/1520.abstract|title=Comparison of cortisol, luteinizing hormone, and testosterone responses to a defined stressor in sexually inactive rams and sexually active female-oriented and male-oriented rams|journal=Journal of Animal Science|volume=84|pages=1520–1525|accessdate=31 August 2007|pmid=16699109|issue=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A paper written by Karli June Cerankowski and Megan Milks, titled ''New Orientations: Asexuality and Its Implications for Theory and Practice'', suggests that asexuality may be somewhat of a question in itself for the studies of gender and sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Cerankowski|first=Karli June|coauthors=Megan Milks|title=New Orientations: Asexuality and Its Implications for Theory and Practice|journal=Feminist Studies|year=2010|volume=36|issue=3|pages=650–654}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cerankowski and Milks have found that asexuality, by means of feminist and queer studies, raises many more questions than it resolves, such as how a person could abstain from having sex which is generally accepted by society to be the most basic of instincts. The article also states that society has either deemed "[LGBT and] female sexuality as empowered or repressed. The asexual movement challenges that assumption by challenging many of the basic tenets of pro-sex feminism already defined as repressive or anti-sex sexualities." Asexual Visibility and Education Network (AVEN) has formulated asexuality as a biologically determined orientation. This formula, if dissected scientifically and proven, would support researcher [[Simon LeVay]]'s blind study of the hypothalamus in gay men, women, and straight men, which found that there is a biological difference between straight men and gay men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Myers|first=David G.|title=Psychology|year=2010|publisher=Worth Publishers|location=New York|isbn=978-1-4292-1597-8|page=474|edition=9th ed.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Community==
{{LGBT symbols}}
[[File:Asexual flag.svg|thumb|The asexual pride flag]]

{{anchor|Flag}} &lt;!-- This is a redirect target; see [[Asexual flag]]. --&gt;
A community of self-identified asexuals coalesced in the early 21st century, aided by the popularity of [[Virtual community|online communities]].&lt;ref name="New Scientist" /&gt; [[Elizabeth Abbott]], author of ''A History of Celibacy'', acknowledges a difference between asexuality and celibacy, and posits that there has always been an asexual element in the population but that asexual people kept a low profile. While the failure to consummate marriage was seen as "an insult to the sacrament of marriage" in medieval Europe, asexuality, unlike homosexuality, has never been illegal, and asexual people have been able to "fly under the radar". However, in the 21st century, the anonymity of online communication and general popularity of [[social network]]ing online has facilitated the formation of a community built around a common asexual identity.&lt;ref name="Duenwald"&gt;{{Cite news|first=Mary|last=Duenwald|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/09/fashion/thursdaystyles/09asexual.html?pagewanted=1&amp;ei=5088&amp;en=520063b1b0fd9ad7&amp;ex=1275969600&amp;partner=rssnyt&amp;emc=rss |title=For Them, Just Saying No Is Easy|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=9 July 2005|accessdate=17 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ace-logo4.svg|thumb|The AVEN triangle representing asexuality. The top line of the triangle represents the [[Kinsey scale]] with the third point representing the other dimension of sexual attraction; the grey area depicting the gradient between sexual and asexual.&lt;ref&gt;Jay, David. (8 March 2009) [http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xa1z2g_asex-101-part-1-of-3_gaylesbianAVENvideos ''Asex 101'', pt. 1 of 3, 8 March 2009 (DailyMotion)]. Retrieved 12 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The Asexual Visibility and Education Network (AVEN) is an organization founded by American asexuality [[Activism|activist]] [[David Jay]] in 2001 that focuses on asexuality issues.&lt;ref name="Sex and society"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Swash"/&gt;&lt;ref name=about&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.asexuality.org/home/about.html |title=About AVEN |work=AVEN |accessdate=22 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its stated goals are "creating public acceptance and discussion of asexuality and facilitating the growth of an asexual community".&lt;ref name=about /&gt; Communities such as AVEN can be beneficial to those in search of answers to solve a crisis of identity with regard to their possible asexuality. Individuals go through a series of emotional processes that end with their identifying with the asexual community. They first realize that their sexual attractions differ from those of most of society. This difference leads to questioning whether the way they feel is acceptable, and possible reasons for why they feel this way. [[Pathology|Pathological]] beliefs tend to follow where, in some cases, they may seek medical help because they feel they have a disease. Self-understanding is usually reached when they find a definition that matches their feelings. Asexuality communities provide support and information that allows newly identified asexuals to move from self-clarification to identifying on a communal level, which can be empowering, because they now have something to associate with, which gives normality to this overall socially-isolating situation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1177/1363460711406462 | last1 = Carrigan | first1 = Mark | year = 2011 | title = There’s more to life than sex? Differences and commonality within the asexual community| journal = Sexualities | volume = 14 | issue = 4 | pages = 462–478}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At this time, asexual organizations and other Internet resources play a key role in informing people about asexuality. The lack of research makes it difficult for doctors to understand the causation. Most people who say they are asexual are self-identified. This can be a problem when asexuality is mistaken for an intimacy or relationship problem or for other symptoms that do not define asexuality. There is also a significant population that either does not understand or does not believe in asexuality, which adds to the importance of these organizations to inform the general population; however, due to the lack of scientific fact on the subject, what these groups promote as information is often questioned.

In 2009, AVEN members participated in the first asexual entry into an American pride parade when they walked in the San Francisco Pride Parade.&lt;ref name="Rufus"&gt;{{cite web|first=Rufus|last=Anneli|title= Stuck. Asexuals at the Pride Parade.|publisher=''[[Psychology Today]]''|date=June 22, 2009|accessdate=July 15, 2013|url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/stuck/200906/asexuals-the-pride-parade}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2010, after a period of debate over having an '''asexual flag''' and how to set up a system to create one, and contacting as many asexual communities as possible, a flag was announced as the '''asexual pride flag''' by one of the team involved. The final flag had been a popular candidate and so had previously seen use in online forums outside of AVEN. The final vote was held on a survey system outside of AVEN where the main flag creation efforts were organized. The flag colors have been used in artwork and referenced in articles about the sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Money &amp;amp; Politics |url=http://recultured.com/uncategorized/09/asexuality-redefining-love-and-sexuality/ |title=Asexuality – Redefining Love and Sexuality |publisher=recultured |date=9 January 2012 |accessdate=7 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discrimination and legal protections==
[[File:WorldPride 2012 - 175.jpg|alt=|thumb|Asexuals marching]]
A 2012 study published in ''[[Group Processes &amp; Intergroup Relations]]'' reports there is more [[prejudice]], [[dehumanization]] and [[discrimination]] toward asexuals than toward other [[Sexual minority|sexual minorities]], such as gay men, lesbians and bisexuals. Both homosexual and heterosexual people thought of asexuals as not only cold, but also animalistic and unrestrained. The same study also found more bias towards sapiosexuals (people who find intelligence the most sexually attractive feature) than towards homosexuals or bisexuals, and that attitudes towards sapiosexuals was the strongest correlate of attitudes towards asexuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Intergroup bias toward "Group X": Evidence of prejudice, dehumanization, avoidance, and discrimination against asexuals |first1=Cara C. |last1=MacInnis |first2=Gordon |last2=Hodson |journal=Group Processes Intergroup Relations |doi=10.1177/1368430212442419 |volume=15 |number=6 |pages=725–743 |year=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Asexual activist and blogger Julie Decker has observed that sexual harassment and violence, such as [[corrective rape]], commonly victimizes the asexual community.&lt;ref name="huff"/&gt; However, a different study found little evidence of serious discrimination against asexuals because of their asexuality.&lt;ref&gt;Gazzola, Stephanie B, and Melanie A. Morrison. "Asexuality: An emergent sexual orientation". ''Sexual Minority Research in the New Millennium''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Asexuals also face prejudice from within the [[LGBT]] community. Upon [[coming out]] as asexual, activist Sara Beth Brooks was told by many LGBT people that asexuals are mistaken in their self-identification and seek undeserved attention within the social justice movement.&lt;ref name="huff"&gt;{{cite web|title=Battling Asexual Discrimination, Sexual Violence, and Corrective Rape|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/06/20/asexual-discrimination_n_3380551.html|publisher=[[Huffington Post]]|date=June 20, 2013|last=Mosbergen|first=Dominique|accessdate=August 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some jurisdictions, asexuals have legal protections. The U.S. state of New York &lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20100316120639/http://www.ag.ny.gov//bureaus/civil_rights/sonda_brochure.html ''The Sexual Orientation Non-Discrimination Act ("SONDA")'' (State of N.Y., Office of the Attorney General, Civil Rights Bureau, 2008)] (possibly written after stated copyright date, Attorney General being stated as Eric T. Schneiderman)&lt;/ref&gt; has labeled asexuals as a [[protected class]]. However, asexuality does not typically attract the attention of the public or major scrutiny; therefore, it has not been the subject of legislation as much as other sexual orientations have.&lt;ref name=Bogaert2004 /&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Sexuality}}
&lt;!--NOTE: Per WP:SEE ALSO, only links that are not linked higher in this article should be in its See also section. --&gt;
* [[Asociality]]: a lack of interest in social relationships in general
* [[Androgyny]]: the mixing of [[Masculinity|masculine]] and [[Femininity|feminine]] characteristics, personality, fashion, or culture
* [[Antisexualism]]: the views of someone who is antagonistic towards sexuality
* [[Platonic love]]: a non-romantic/non-sexual affectionate relationship
* [[Sexless marriage]]: a marriage in which little or no sex is performed
* [[Sexual anorexia]]: a loss of "appetite" for romantic-sexual interaction
* ''[[The Bone People]]'': a 1984 novel with an asexual protagonist, which explicitly makes reference to the subject of asexuality

==References==

&lt;!--This article uses the Cite.php citation mechanism. If you would like more information on how to add references to this article, please see http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Cite/Cite.php --&gt;
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
*{{cite book|last=Bogaert|first=Anthony F.|title=Understanding Asexuality|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=O3v27O00GEYC|accessdate=27 July 2013|date=9 August 2012|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers|isbn=978-1-4422-0101-9|postscript = &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;This timely resource will be one of the first books written on the topic for general readers, and the first to look at the historical, biological, and social aspects of asexuality.}}
*{{cite book
| author = Asexuality Archive
| title         = Asexuality: A Brief Introduction
| url           = http://www.asexualityarchive.com/book
| accessdate    = 2013-02-11
| date      = 27 Jun 2012
| publisher = CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform
| location  = 
| isbn      = 1477428089
}}
* [http://www.yourtango.com/201197887/could-you-possibly-be-asexual "Can you imagine a life without sex?"], Jamye Waxman ''The Stir'', 12 October 2011, [[yourtango.com]]
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/lifeandstyle/2008/sep/08/relationships.healthandwellbeing "We're married, we just don't have sex"], UK ''[[The Guardian|Guardian]]'', 8 September 2008
* [http://www.sfgate.com/health/article/Asexuals-leave-the-closet-find-community-3219180.php Asexuals leave the closet, find community] – [[SFGate.com]]

==External links==
{{ external media
| align = right
| topic = A [[fictional film]] about asexuality at [[Amazon Studios]]
| video1 = [http://studios.amazon.com/movies/3363 Antisex: No Sex and the City]
}}
{{commons category|Human asexuality}}
* [http://www.apositive.org/ Apositive]
* [http://www.asexualawarenessweek.com Asexual Awareness Week]
* [http://www.asexualexplorations.net/home/extantresearch.html Asexual Explorations. ''Existing Research'', an annotated bibliography], as retrieved 23 February 2010.
* [http://www.asexualexplorations.net/ Asexual Explorations: Promoting the Academic Study of Asexuality]
* [http://www.asexuality.org/ AVEN: Asexual Visibility and Education Network]
* [http://www.asexuality.org/wiki/ AVENwiki]





{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Human sexuality}}
{{Sexual identities}}
}}

[[Category:Non-sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]
[[Category:Asexuality| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>