<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061111181509|87174876" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="156858" pageid="156858" ns="0" title="Asexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-11T18:19:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{sexual orientation}}
{{otheruses4|human beings who do not have interest in, or inclination towards, sexual behavior|the form of reproduction|asexual reproduction}}

'''Asexuality''' is a general term or self-designation for people who lack sexual attraction or otherwise find [[human sexual behavior|sexual behavior]] unappealing. There is debate as to whether this is a [[sexual dysfunction]] or a [[sexual orientation]]; furthermore, there is disagreement over the exact definition of the word. The term is sometimes used as a [[gender identity]] by those who believe their lack of sexual attraction places them outside the traditional definitions of [[gender]]. There has been little research done on asexuality, but those studies that have been conducted suggest that, if it is a sexual orientation, it is among the least common.


==Debate==
There is continuing disagreement over whether asexuality is a legitimate sexual orientation. Some argue that it falls under the heading of [[hypoactive sexual disorder]] or [[sexual aversion disorder]]. Among those who do not believe it to be an orientation, other suggested causes include past [[sexual abuse]],&lt;ref name=Aline_Zoldbrod&gt;{{cite web | url = http://archive.salon.com/mwt/feature/2005/05/26/asexual/ | title = Asexual and proud! | accessmonthday = August 27 | accessyear = 2006 | first = Lynn | last = Harris | date = 2006-05-26 | work = Salon.com | publisher = Salon Media Group | pages = 1-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; sexual repression (of [[homosexuality]], [[heterosexuality]], or [[bisexuality]]), [[hormone|hormonal]] problems, delayed development, [[sublimation (psychology)|sublimation]] of sexuality for personal, religious or cultural reasons, or simply not having met the right person. 

Many self-identified asexuals, however, do not believe that such diagnoses apply to them. Others assert that because their asexuality does not cause them distress it should not be viewed as a [[disorder]]. Those who believe that asexuality is not pathological sometimes point to the fact that similar things have been said about homosexuality and bisexuality, which are now viewed by some as legitimate orientations. Alongside this is the debate as to whether the term 'asexual' is an accurate term, given its use in biology to describe a species that reproduces from a single member, whereas in this context pertains to an organism not reproducing at all.

Because of this lack of research on the subject, there is little documented evidence in favor of either side of the debate.

==Research==
A study done on [[Ram (sheep)|rams]] found that about 2% to 3% of the animals being studied had no apparent interest in mating with either sex. Another study was done on [[rats]] and [[gerbils]], in which up to 12% of the males showed no interest in females. Their interactions with other males were not measured, however, so the study is of limited use when it comes to asexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Sylvia|last=Westphal|date=[[2004-10-14]]|url=http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=dn6533|title=Feature: Glad to be asexual|publisher=[[New Scientist]]|accessdate=23 May|accessyear=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[United Kingdom|UK]] survey of sexuality included a question on sexual attraction, and 1% of respondents replied that they had '''"never felt sexually attracted to anyone at all."'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Anthony F.|last=Bogaert|year=2004|month=August|title=Asexuality: prevalence and associated factors in a national probability sample|journal=Journal of Sex Research|volume=41|issue =3 | pages=281 | id = {{PMID|15497056}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Kinsey Institute]] conducted a small survey on the topic, which concluded that "asexuals appear to be better characterized by low sexual desire and sexual excitation than by low levels of sexual behavior or high sexual inhibition" &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Prause|first=Nicole|coauthors=C.A. Graham|url=http://www.asexuality.org/docs/SSSS_2003.ppt|title=Asexuality: A preliminary investigation|format=[[Microsoft Office PowerPoint|ppt]]|accessdate=23 May|accessyear=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;. That study also mentions a conflict regarding the definition of "asexual": the researchers found four different definitions in the literature, and stated that it was unclear whether those identifying as asexual were referring to an orientation.

==Variations==
There are differences among people who identify as asexual, chiefly among them the presence or absence of a sex drive or romantic attraction. Some experience only one of these, while others experience both, and still others neither. There is disagreement as to which of these configurations can genuinely be described as asexual. While a number of people believe all four variations qualify, many others believe that to be asexual, one must lack a sex drive, romantic attraction, or both.

The sex drive of those asexuals who have one is usually not directed at anything, and is only an urge for sexual stimulation or release; one exception is those asexuals who are also [[Fetishism|fetishists]], whose sex drive is focused on the fetish object rather than a person (though many fetishists do not identify themselves as asexual). In either case, the level of sex drive can range from weak to strong, and from rare to frequent. As mentioned above, some identify as asexual yet feel sexual attraction, though some would argue that they are not asexual.  Some asexuals may experience sexual feelings, but have an aversion to sex or no desire to act on them, while others seek sexual release through sexual contact.

For those asexuals who experience feelings of romantic attraction, it can be directed towards any sex or sexes. These asexuals generally desire romantic relationships (ranging from casual liaisons to marriage) but often do not want these relationships to include sexual activity. Because of their romantic orientation, some asexuals describe themselves as [[homosexuality|gay]], [[bisexuality|bisexual]], or [[heterosexuality|straight]] asexuals; this is related to the concept of [[affectional orientation]].

Those asexuals who do want romantic relationships are in a difficult position, as the majority of people are not asexual. Asexuals able to tolerate sex can pair up with non-asexuals, but even then their lack of attraction or desire can be psychologically distressing to their partner, making a long-term romance difficult. Asexuals who cannot tolerate sex must either compromise with their partners and have a certain amount anyway, give their partners permission to seek sex elsewhere, have sexless relationships with those few who are willing, date only other asexuals, or stay single.

Some asexuals use a classification system developed (and then retired) by the founder, David Jay, of the [[Asexual Visibility and Education Network]] [http://www.asexuality.org], one of the major online asexual communities (abbreviated as AVEN). In this system, asexuals are divided into types A through C: a Type A asexual has a sex drive but no romantic attraction, a Type B has romantic attraction but no sex drive, and a Type C neither. The categories are not meant to be entirely discrete or set in stone; one's type can change, or one can be on the border between two types. Note that AVEN itself no longer uses this system, on the basis that it is too exclusive, but a number of asexuals still feel it is a useful tool for explaining their orientation.

Note that asexuality is not the same as [[celibacy]], which is the deliberate abstention from sexual activity; many asexuals do have sex, and most celibates are not asexual.

==Asexuality and religion==
Currently, asexuality faces little religious condemnation.

Several religions or religious sects believe that asexuality is a spiritually superior condition, and some asexuals believe that their lack of "base desires" allows them to feel a deeper spirituality, although other asexuals consider that an elitist attitude. However, some conservative Christians believe that naturally occurring asexuality, like naturally occurring homosexuality, is an impossibility as it was not designed by God and then subsequently instilled in Adam and Eve.  The [[Apostle Paul]] in his [[First Epistle to the Corinthians|first letter to the Corinthians]] stated it would be better that believers remain celibate (1 Cor. 7:8).  However, if they could not do so, it was better to marry (1 Cor. 7:9). 

In other creeds, children are considered a gift from God that should not be refused, a means of spreading religion, or both, though some asexuals do have children, and some religions have praised both asexuality and children. Furthermore, according to some religious beliefs, sexuality itself is sacred or a divine gift; certain varieties of [[Tantra]] involve sex, for example, and some types of [[neopaganism]] and [[New Age]] spirituality include the concept of sacred sexuality.

In a research piece on the subject, Anthony F. Bogaert found that asexuals may exhibit higher rates of religiosity than sexuals. He takes this as support for his hypothesis that some asexuals may have internalized religious attitudes regarding sexual prohibition and [[abstinence]] "to such a degree that they may not admit to arousal, or at least not label it as sexual attraction". &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Anthony F.|last=Bogaert|year=2004|month=August|title=Asexuality: prevalence and associated factors in a national probability sample|journal=Journal of Sex Research|volume=41|pages=280 | id = {{PMID|15497056}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; Informal polls on the AVEN site, on the other hand, show that its membership is less religious than the general public. [http://www.asexuality.org/discussion/viewtopic.php?t=6648&amp;sid=8cf6ab42536a3c8bac88fcf554b6eb87] [http://www.asexuality.org/discussion/viewtopic.php?t=4149&amp;highlight=religion&amp;sid=8cf6ab42536a3c8bac88fcf554b6eb87]

==Famous Asexuals==
* [[Benjamin Banneker]] {{fact}}
* [[J.M. Barrie]]
* [[Jorge Luis Borges]]
* [[Emily Brontë]]
* [[George Washington Carver]]{{fact}}
* [[Paul Erdős]]
* [[Glenn Gould]]
* [[Edward Gorey]]
* [[Immanuel Kant]] {{fact}}
* [[H.P. Lovecraft]] {{fact}}
* [[Isaac Newton]] (disputed)
* [[Florence Nightingale]]
* [[John Ruskin]]
* [[Erik Satie]], French pianist and composer
* [[Sun Ra]], American jazz musician
* [[Nikola Tesla]] {{fact}}
* [[Samuel J. Tilden]]
* [[Simone Weil]]
* [[Hans Christian Andersen]]
* [[Jean Alexander]]
* [[Ed Gein]]
* [[J Edgar Hoover]]
* [[A.C. Green]]
* [[Todd Fuller]]
* [[John Harvey Kellogg]]
* [[Morrissey]] {{fact}}
* [[Joan of Arc]]
* [[Maximilien Robespierre]], French Revolutionary

-Note: Not all are known for certain to be asexual, but are assumed to be.

==Asexuality in fiction==
In his [[science fiction]] novel ''[[Distress (novel)|Distress]]'' ([[1995 in literature|1995]]), [[Greg Egan]] imagines a [[22nd century]] world where "asex" is one out of seven acknowledged [[gender identity|gender]] settings. To quote from ''Distress'':

:"''Asex'' was really nothing but an umbrella term for a broad group of philosophies, styles of dress, cosmetic-surgical changes, and deep-biological alterations. The only thing that one asex person necessarily had in common with another was the view that [[gender-neutral pronoun|vis]] gender parameters (neural, endocrine, chromosomal and genital) were the business of no one but verself, usually (but not always) vis lovers, probably vis doctor, and sometimes a few close friends. What a person actually did in response to that attitude could range from as little as ticking the 'A' box on [[census]] forms, to choosing an asex name, to breast or body-hair reduction, voice timbre adjustment, facial resculpting, empouchment (surgery to render the male genitals retractable), all the way to full physical and/or neural asexuality, [[hermaphroditism]], or exoticism." (Distress, paperback ed., p. 45)

[[Aghora (Metabaron)|Aghora]], one of [[Alejandro Jodorowsky]]'s [[Metabarons]], was an asexual [[transman]].

[[Samuel R. Delany]]'s [[1969 in literature|1969]] short story "[[Aye, and Gomorrah...]]" depicts a society where [[astronauts]] become sexless because cosmic radiation renders their reproductive organs useless.

In the original ''[[Doctor Who]]'' television series (1963–1989), [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|the Doctor]] was almost always depicted as asexual despite his regular stream of attractive young female companions. Since the First Doctor's initial companion, [[Susan Foreman]], was introduced as his granddaughter, it is often assumed, but never confirmed, that the Doctor had had at one time in his early life a partner of the opposite sex with whom he had at least one child. The 1996 [[Doctor Who (1996)|''Doctor Who'' television movie]] caused some controversy among ''Doctor Who'' fans by having the [[Eighth Doctor]] passionately kiss, more than once, his companion [[Grace Holloway|Grace]]. In the [[History of Doctor Who#The new series|new series]] (2005–), the Doctor is occasionally flirtatious, and has a romantically tinged relationship with his companion [[Rose Tyler]]. Actor [[David Tennant]] who currently plays the [[Tenth Doctor]], has assured fans that the relationship is still celibate or "a love story without the shagging." as he puts it. See also [[Doctor (Doctor Who)#The Doctor and romance|The Doctor and romance]].

[[Sir Arthur Conan Doyle]]'s [[Sherlock Holmes]] is often regarded as another quintessentially asexual character. While his friend [[Doctor Watson]] is portrayed as charming and very much attracted to and, in the manner of a stereotypical Victorian gentleman, gallant towards various female characters, and indeed marries at least once, the detective dismisses dealings with women outside of his specific business as 'Your department, Watson' and even once sneeringly tells the doctor that 'the most winning woman' he ever knew committed infanticide for the insurance money. The story ''[[A Scandal in Bohemia]]'' (first published in the ''[[Strand Magazine]]'' in July 1891), however, introduces a female character whom Holmes admires excessively (she outwits him), and it opens with a frank explanation of the character's asexuality as it is seen by the narrator – as (almost) always, Doctor John Watson:

:"To Sherlock Holmes she is always ''the'' woman. I have seldom heard him mention her under any other name. In his eyes she eclipses and predominates the whole of her sex. It was not that he felt any emotion akin to love for Irene Adler. All emotions, and that one particularly, were abhorrent to his cold, precise but admirably balanced mind. He was, I take it, the most perfect reasoning and observing machine that the world has seen, but as a lover he would have placed himself in a false position. He never spoke of the softer passions, save with a gibe and a sneer. They were admirable things for the observer – excellent for drawing the veil from men's motives and actions. But for the trained reasoner to admit such intrusions into his own delicate and finely adjusted temperament was to introduce a distracting factor which might throw a doubt upon all his mental results. Grit in a sensitive instrument, or a crack in one of his own high-power lenses, would not be more disturbing than a strong emotion in a nature such as his."

In the long-running Granada television series starring [[Jeremy Brett]] as Holmes, one feature-length episode, ''[[The Master Blackmailer]]'' (1992) – expanded from Conan Doyle's short story ''[[The Adventure of Charles Augustus Milverton]]'' – had the detective seemingly developing feelings for a woman for once, but only while in character: disguised as a working man in order to infiltrate the household of the blackmailer, Milverton. Embarrassed and uncomfortable, he is nevertheless prepared to go as far as engagement in pursuit of the villain. Once out of the disguise, though, he reverts to normal and is dismissive of the poor girl.

In the [[K. Sandra Fuhr]]'s online strips [[Boy Meets Boy (comic)|Boy Meets Boy]] (ended) and [[Friendly Hostility]] (ongoing), the cynical Collin Sri'Vastra claims to be asexual. He later forms a relationship with his best friend Kailen "Fox" Maharassa, but his romantic/affectionate levels appear to be rather low, at least at the beginning.

One of the central characters of [[Isabel Allende]]'s ''[[The House of Spirits]]'', Clara, could be construed as asexual. In her later years, she expresses a lack of interest in coitus, commenting that it only makes her bones ache.

The eponymous central character in [[Kurt Vonnegut]]'s ''[[Deadeye Dick]]'' is asexual due to childhood trauma.

Many fans of ''[[Neon Genesis Evangelion]]'' believe that [[Rei Ayanami]] is asexual, since she never shows any signs of having a sex drive, the closest thing she comes to doing so is her [[platonic love]] for [[Shinji Ikari]]. Another Evangelion character, [[List of characters in Neon Genesis Evangelion#First Lieutenant Shigeru Aoba|Shigeru Aoba]], is strongly implied to be asexual in ''[[The End of Evangelion]]''.

[[Jughead Jones]] was, for several decades, perhaps the only character of the [[Archie comics|Archie]] gang who is not romantically interested in the opposite sex.

In [[Ian Fleming]]'s ''[[From Russia With Love]]'', [[Red Grant]] is described as being an asexual. However, it is unclear whether or not this trait is passed over into the film version.

In [[John Irving]]'s ''[[A Prayer for Owen Meany]]'', the narrator appears to be asexual. There is a brief mention that, in his teens, he is introduced to several female peers and is clumsy and ineffective in his attempts to make love to them. He remains a virgin when the book ends. In early adolescence he is tied up face-to-face with a major character called Hesther. Although both find the experience uncomfortable and embarrassing, Hesther goes on to have a sexual relationship with the title character.

Kerewin Holmes, lead character of [[Keri Hulme]]'s novel '[[The Bone People]]' also confesses her own asexuality to Joe, and vehemently denies it being result of any kind of abuse at any stage in her life.

Laura Rambotham, from [[Henry Handel Richarson]]'s novel, [[The Getting Of Wisdom]], shows complete carelessness for sex, and sexuality, unlike the rest of the girls at her school.

Spyros Deloglou (played by [[Giorgos Kapoutzidis]]), one of the main characters of the Greek [[sitcom]] ''[[Sto Para Pente]]'', is commented by Dahlia to be asexual, after he confessed he had sexual intercourse only 'one time and a half'

==See also==
*[[Antisexualism]]
*[[Sexual orientation]]
*[[Celibacy]]
*[[Affectional orientation]]
*[[Androgyny]]
*[[Sexless marriage]]

==References==
&lt;!--This article uses the Cite.php citation mechanism. If you would like more information on how to add references to this article, please see http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Cite/Cite.php --&gt;
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
*Egan, Greg (1995). ''Distress''.

== External links ==
*[http://www.asexuality.org/ Asexual Visibility and Education Network (AVEN)]
*[http://avenitesunite.proboards49.com/index.cgi AVEN temporary forums]
*[http://archive.salon.com/mwt/feature/2005/05/26/asexual Asexual and proud!]. ''[[Salon.com|Salon]]'', ([[May 26]], [[2005]]).
*[http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=dn6533 Feature: Glad to be asexual] ''[[New Scientist]]'', ([[October 14]][[2004]]).
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/life/science/story/0,12996,1326893,00.html No sex please, we're asexual]. ''[[The Guardian]]'', ([[14 October]] [[2004]]).
*[http://www.cnn.com/2004/TECH/science/10/14/asexual.study/index.html Study: One in 100 adults asexual]. ''[[CNN]]'', ([[14 October]] [[2004]]).
*[http://www.asexualove.net Asexual personals]
*[http://www.theofficialasexualsociety.com/contact1.html The Official Nonlibidoism Society]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A4455263 BBC website: h2g2 article on Asexuality]

{{Sexual Identities}}

[[Category:Non-sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and identity]]

&lt;!-- The below are interlanguage links. --&gt;
[[br:Amrevelezh]]
[[bg:Асексуалност]]
[[da:Aseksualitet]]
[[de:Asexualität]]
[[et:Aseksuaalsus]]
[[es:Asexualidad]]
[[fr:Asexualité]]
[[hr:Aseksualnost]]
[[it:Asessualità]]
[[he:א-מיניות]]
[[nl:Aseksualiteit]]
[[ja:非性愛]]
[[no:Aseksualitet]]
[[pl:Aseksualizm]]
[[pt:Assexual]]
[[ro:Asexualitate]]
[[ru:Асексуальность]]
[[fi:Aseksuaalisuus]]
[[sv:Asexualitet]]
[[tr:Aseksüel]]
[[zh:無性戀]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>