<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20030725185014|1288719" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="156858" pageid="156858" ns="0" title="Asexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-08-14T09:23:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">Some people are not [[sexual attraction|sexually attracted]] to anyone, and describe themselves as '''asexual'''. This may be viewed as a form of [[sexual orientation]] in itself, although it is sometimes claimed that it is a psycho-sexual problem.

Several religions or religious sects believe that asexuality is a spiritually superior condition. Some Christian religions, based on 1 Corinthians 7:9  ("1 Corinthians 7:9  (RSV)   But if they cannot exercise self-control, they should marry. For it is better to marry than to be aflame with passion. ") endorse sex only within marriage, and then only as a lesser choice than [[chastity]] or [[sexual abstinence]]. In the [[Catholic]] Church, chastity is one of the vows that one takes in order to become a nun or priest. See also [[celibacy]]. This idea that asexuality is the higher way is sometimes referred to as '''asexism'''.

In other creeds, [[child]]ren may be considered a [[gift]] of God that should not be refused, and/or a means of spreading religion. 

In [[fiction]], [[John Braine]]'s novel ''[[The Jealous God]]'' ([[1964 in literature|1964]]) is a good example of sex mainly seen as a sin. On the other hand, in his [[science fiction]] novel ''[[Distress (novel)|Distress]]'' ([[1995 in literature|1995]]), [[Greg Egan]] imagines a world where "asex" is one out of five or seven acknowledged [[gender identity|gender]] settings.

Asexuality is not to be confused with [[asexual reproduction]]. 

See also: [[heteronormativity]]

== External links ==
* http://www.asexuality.org/Links.htm</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>