<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101112182038|396359086" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="156858" pageid="156858" ns="0" title="Asexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-12T18:24:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|sexual orientation in humans|the form of reproduction|Asexual reproduction|the Montreal punk rock band named The Asexuals|Asexuals (band)}}

{{sexual orientation}}

'''Asexuality''' (also known as '''nonsexuality'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wordreference.com/definition/nonsexual&lt;/ref&gt;), in its broadest sense, is the lack of sexual attraction&lt;ref name= Bogaert2006&gt;Bogaert, Anthony F. (2006). [http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=18172400 "Toward a conceptual understanding of asexuality"]. ''Review of General Psychology'' '''10''' (3): 241–250. Retrieved on 31 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="New Scientist"&gt;{{cite web |author=Westphal, Sylvia Pagan (2004) |url=http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=dn6533 |title=Feature: Glad to be asexual |work=[http://www.newscientist.com New Scientist] |accessdate=11 November 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or the lack of interest in and desire for sex.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/Asexual Dictionary.com, ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'' (4th ed.): ''asexual'']: "Lacking interest in or desire for sex."&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes, it is considered a lack of a [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref name = Bogaert2004&gt;Bogaert, Anthony F. (2004). [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m2372/is_3_41/ai_n6274004 "Asexuality: prevalence and associated factors in a national probability sample"]. ''Journal of Sex Research'' '''41''' (3): 281. Retrieved on 31 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; One commonly cited study placed the incidence rate of asexuality at 1%.&lt;ref name="cnn"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2004/TECH/science/10/14/asexual.study/index.html |title=Study: One in 100 adults asexual |work=[http://www.cnn.com CNN.com] |accessdate=11 November 2007 | date=15 October 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Asexuality is distinct from [[sexual abstinence|abstention from sexual activity]] and from [[celibacy]], which are behavioral; the latter is usually, but not always, for a religious reason.&lt;ref&gt;''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'' (3d ed. 1992), entries for ''celibacy'' and thence ''abstinence''.&lt;/ref&gt; (For instance, sexual people in relationships with asexuals may become celibate as a result.) A sexual orientation, unlike a behavior, is definitionally "enduring".&lt;ref&gt;''Brief ''Amici Curiae'' of the American Psychological Association, California Psychological Association, American Psychiatric Association, National Association of Social Workers, and National Association of Social Workers California Chapter in Support of the Parties Challenging the Marriage Exclusion'', in ''In re Marriage Cases'', Case S147999, Calif. Sup. Ct., Sep. 26, 2007, &lt;http://www.courtinfo.ca.gov/courts/supreme/highprofile/documents/Amer_Psychological_Assn_Amicus_Curiae_Brief.pdf&gt;, as accessed Mar. 17, 2010, p. 6 (p. 28 per Adobe Acrobat Reader) (not including asexuality as a sexual orientation).&lt;/ref&gt; Some asexuals do have sex, despite lacking a desire for it.&lt;ref name="Prause"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Prause|first=Nicole|coauthors=Cynthia A. Graham|year=2004|month=August|url=http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/publications/PDF/PrauseGrahamPDF.pdf|title=Asexuality: Classification and Characterization|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|volume=36|pages=341–356|accessdate=31 August 2007|doi=10.1007/s10508-006-9142-3|format=PDF|pmid=17345167|issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prevalence ==

In the mid-twentieth century, [[Alfred Kinsey]] rated individuals from 0 to 6 according to their sexual orientation from heterosexual to homosexual. He also included a category he called "X" for individuals with "no socio-sexual contacts or reactions". He labeled 1.5% of the adult male population as ''X.''&lt;ref name="Kinsey-male"&gt;{{Cite book|first=Alfred C.|last=Kinsey|year=1948|title=Sexual Behavior in the Human Male|publisher=W.B. Saunders|isbn=0-253-33412-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kinsey-female"&gt;{{Cite book|first=Alfred C.|last=Kinsey|year=1953|title=Sexual Behavior in the Human Female|publisher=W.B. Saunders|isbn=0-253-33411-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Kinsey's second book, ''Sexual Behavior in the Human Female'', he reported this breakdown of individuals who are X: unmarried females = 14–19%, married females = 1–3%, previously married females = 5–8%, unmarried males = 3–4%, married males = 0%, and previously married males = 1–2%.&lt;ref name="Kinsey-female" /&gt;

Further empirical data about an asexual demographic appeared in 1994, when a research team in the United Kingdom carried out a comprehensive survey of 18,876 British residents, spurred by the need for sexual information in the wake of the [[AIDS pandemic]]. The survey included a question on sexual attraction, to which 1.05% of the respondents replied that they had "never felt sexually attracted to anyone at all."&lt;ref&gt;Wellings, K. (1994). ''Sexual Behaviour in Britain: The National Survey of Sexual Attitudes and Lifestyles.'' Penguin Books.&lt;/ref&gt; This study of this phenomenon was continued by the Canadian sexuality researcher Dr. Anthony Bogaert in 2004, who explored the asexual demographic in a series of studies. Bogaert believed that the 1% figure was not an accurate reflection of the likely much larger percentage of the population that could be identified as asexual, noting that in the initial survey 30% of people contacted chose not to participate in the survey. Since less sexually experienced people are more likely to refuse to participate in studies about sexuality, and asexuals tend to be less sexually experienced than non-asexuals, it is likely that asexuals were over-represented in the 30% who did not participate, compared to the 70% who did. The same study found the number of homosexuals and bisexuals combined to be about 1.1% of the population, which is much smaller than other studies indicate.&lt;ref name="Bogaert2006" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bogaert2004" /&gt; However, Bogaert's sexuality research has been scrutinized in the past, since he was involved in studies that linked race to sexual behaviors as if they had an evolutionary basis. This study was highly debated by the scientific community as potentially constituting a case of scientific racism.&lt;ref&gt;Rushton, Pillipe and Anthony Bogaert. 1989. Population Differences in Susceptibility to AIDS: An Evolutionary Analysis. Social Science and Medicine 28(2):1211-1220.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1994 U.S. study that did not include asexuality as a sexual orientation, some people reported having had no sex or no partners in a year: 11.9% of adults, 9.8% of men, and 13.6% of women.&lt;ref&gt;Laumann, Edward O., John H. Gagnon, Robert T. Michael, and Stuart Michaels. ''The Social Organization of Sexuality: Sexual Practices in the United States'' (Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press, cloth, [1st printing? printing of 1994?] 1994), pp. [88] &amp; [177] (additional breakdowns available).&lt;/ref&gt; In 5 years, the number of partners was zero for 8.0% of adults: 7.1% of men and 8.7% of women.&lt;ref&gt;Laumann, Edward O., et al. ''The Social Organization of Sexuality'', ''op. cit.'', p. [178] (additional breakdowns available).&lt;/ref&gt; In all of adulthood until the time of surveying (given that surveyed people were of different ages), the number of partners was zero for 2.9% of adults: 3.4% of men and 2.5% of women.&lt;ref&gt;Laumann, Edward O., et al., ''The Social Organization of Sexuality'', ''op. cit.'', p. [179] (additional breakdowns available).&lt;/ref&gt;

Asexuality is denominated by an "X" on the [[Kinsey scale]].

== Romantic relationships ==

Asexuals, while typically lacking in sexual desire for either sex, may engage in purely emotional [[Romance (love)|romantic]] relationships.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asexuality.org/home/relationship.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gayline.gen.nz/asexual.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.yorklgbt.org/LGBT/asexual&lt;/ref&gt; Terms concerning this:
* '''aromantic''': lack of romantic attraction towards anyone of any gender
* '''biromantic''': romantic attraction towards person(s) of either gender
* '''heteroromantic''': romantic attraction towards person(s) of the opposite gender
* '''homoromantic''': romantic attraction towards person(s) of the same gender
* '''panromantic''': romantic attraction towards person(s) of any gender or lack of gender
* '''transromantic''': romantic attraction towards person(s) of variant or ambiguous gender
* '''polyromantic''': romantic attraction towards person(s) of more than one gender or sex but without implying, as biromantic does, that there are only two genders or sexes

== Research ==

The [[Kinsey Institute for Research in Sex, Gender, and Reproduction|Kinsey Institute]] sponsored another small survey on the topic in 2007, which found that self-identified asexuals "reported significantly less desire for sex with a partner, lower sexual arousability, and lower sexual excitation but did not differ consistently from non-asexuals in their sexual inhibition scores or their desire to masturbate".&lt;ref name="Prause" /&gt;

A 1977 paper entitled ''Asexual and Autoerotic Women: Two Invisible Groups'', by Myra T. Johnson, may be the first paper explicitly devoted to asexuality in humans. Johnson defines asexuals as those men and women "who, regardless of physical or emotional condition, actual sexual history, and marital status or ideological orientation, seem to ''prefer'' not to engage in sexual activity." She contrasts autoerotic women with asexual women: "The asexual woman [...] has no sexual desires at all [but] the autoerotic woman [...] recognizes such desires but prefers to satisfy them alone." Johnson's evidence is mostly letters to the editor found in women's magazines written by asexual/autoerotic women. She portrays them as invisible, "oppressed by a consensus that they are nonexistent," and left behind by both the sexual revolution and the feminist movement. Society either ignores or denies their existence or insists they must be ascetic for religious reasons, neurotic, or asexual for political reasons.&lt;ref&gt;"Asexual and Autoerotic Women: Two Invisible Groups" found in ed. Gochros, H.L.; J.S. Gochros (1977). ''The Sexually Oppressed. Associated Press.'' ISBN 9780809619153&lt;/ref&gt;

In a study published in 1979 in ''Advances in the Study of Affect'', vol. 5, and in another article using the same data and published in 1980 in the ''Journal of Personality and Social Psychology'', Michael D. Storms of the University of Kansas outlined his own reimagining of the Kinsey scale. Whereas Kinsey measured sexual orientation based on a combination of actual sexual behavior and fantasizing and eroticism, Storms only used fantasizing and eroticism. Storms, however, placed hetero-eroticism and homo-eroticism on separate axes rather than at two ends of a single scale; this allows for a distinction between bisexuality (exhibiting both hetero- and homo-eroticism in degrees comparable to hetero- or homosexuals, respectively) and asexuality (exhibiting a level of homo-eroticism comparable to a heterosexual and a level of hetero-eroticism comparable to a homosexual, namely, little to none). Storms conjectured that many researchers following Kinsey's model could be mis-categorizing asexual subjects as bisexual, because both were simply defined by a lack of preference for gender in sexual partners.&lt;ref name = Storms1980&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.38.5.783 | last1 = Storms | first1 = Michael D. | year = 1980 | title = Theories of Sexual Orientation | url = | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 38 | issue = | pages = 783–792 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = Storms1979&gt;Storms, M. D. (1979). Sexual orientation and self-perception. ed. Pliner, Patricia et al. ''Advances in the Study of Communication and Affect. Volume 5: Perception of Emotion in Self and Others'' Plenum Press&lt;/ref&gt;

The first study that gave empirical data about asexuals was published in 1983 by Paula Nurius, concerning the relationship between sexual orientation and mental health. Unlike previous studies on the subject, she used the above-mentioned two-dimensional model for sexual orientation. Six hundred eighty-nine subjects—most of whom were students at various universities in the United States taking psychology or sociology classes—were given several surveys, including four clinical well-being scales and a survey asking how frequently they engaged in various sexual activities and how often they would like to engage in those activities. Based on the results, respondents were given a score ranging from 0 to 100 for hetero-eroticism and from 0 to 100 for homo-eroticism. Respondents who scored lower than 10 on both were labeled "asexual." This consisted of 5% of the males and 10% of the females. Results showed that asexuals were more likely to have low self-esteem and more likely to be depressed than members of other sexual orientations; 25.88% of heterosexuals, 26.54% bisexuals (called "ambisexuals"), 29.88% of homosexuals, and 33.57% of asexuals were reported to have problems with self-esteem. A similar trend existed for depression. Nurius did not believe that firm conclusions can be drawn from this for a variety of reasons. Asexuals also reported much lower frequency and desired frequency of a variety of sexual activities including having multiple partners, anal sexual activities, having sexual encounters in a variety of locations, and autoerotic activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1080/00224498309551174 | last1 = Nurius | first1 = Paula | year = 1983| title = Mental Health Implications of Sexual Orientation | url = | journal = The Journal of Sex Research | volume = 19 | issue = 2| pages = 119–136 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another study with both quantitative and qualitative sections has been done recently, but the results have not yet been published, though some of the results can be found online.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indiana.edu/~sexlab/files/pr2007/Brottoetal2007.pdf ''Understanding Asexuality''], Lori Brotto, PhD, R Psych, Assistant Professor, Department of Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC, Canada&lt;/ref&gt;

Though comparisons with non-human sexuality are problematic, a series of studies done on [[Ram (sheep)|ram]] mating preferences at the United States Sheep Experiment Station in [[Dubois, Idaho]], starting in 2001 found that about 2–3% of the animals being studied had no apparent interest in mating with either sex; the researchers classified these animals as asexual, but found them to be otherwise healthy with no recorded differences in [[hormone]] levels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Charles A.|last=Roselli|year=2002|url=http://www.biolreprod.org/cgi/content/full/67/1/263|title=Relationship of serum testosterone concentrations to mate preferences in rams|journal=Biology of Reproduction|volume=67|pages=263–268|accessdate=31 August 2007|doi=10.1095/biolreprod67.1.263|pmid=12080026|last2=Stormshak|first2=F|last3=Stellflug|first3=JN|last4=Resko|first4=JA|issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=J.N.|last=Stellflug|date=1 June 2006|url=http://jas.fass.org/cgi/content/abstract/84/6/1520|title=Comparison of cortisol, luteinizing hormone, and testosterone responses to a defined stressor in sexually inactive rams and sexually active female-oriented and male-oriented rams|journal=Journal of Animal Science|volume=84|pages=1520–1525|accessdate=31 August 2007|pmid=16699109|issue=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etiology ==

''Etiology'' in this context is without implication of disease, disorder, or abnormality.&lt;ref&gt;In ''Webster's Third'' (Merriam-Webster), ''etiology'' is defined both with and without reference to disease. The word is defined as "a science or doctrine of causation or of the demonstration of causes" and as "a branch of science dealing with the causes of particular phenomena", thus without implying disease or abnormality. However, it is also defined as "all the factors that contribute to the occurrence of a disease or abnormal condition". ''Webster's Third New International Dictionary of the English Language Unabridged'' ([prob. Springfield, Mass.:] G. &amp; C. Merriam (Merriam-Webster), 1966), entry ''etiology''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In the ''Shorter Oxford Eng. Dict.'' ([4th] ed.), ''etiology'' is defined both with and without reference to disease. The word is defined as "[t]he assignment of a cause", as "the cause assigned", and, as now rare or obsolete, as "[t]he philosophy of causation; the part of a science which treats of the causes of its phenomena." However, it is also defined in medicine as "[t]he causation of disease (usu., of a specified disease), esp. as a subject for investigation." ''The New Shorter Oxford English Dictionary: On Historical Principles'' (Oxford: Clarendon Press, [4th] ed. 1993 (ISBN 0-19-861271-0)), entry ''aetiology'', via entry ''etiology''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In the ''American Heritage Dict.'' (3d ed.), ''etiology'' is defined both with and without reference to disease. The word is defined as "[t]he study of causes or origins" and as "[a]ssignment of a  cause, an origin, or a reason for something." However, it is also defined as "[t]he branch of medicine that deals with the causes or origins of disease" and as "[t]he cause or origin of a disease or disorder as determined by medical diagnosis." ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'' (Boston, Mass.: Houghton Mifflin, 3d ed. 1992 (ISBN 0-395-44895-6)), entry ''etiology''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In a nursing dictionary, ''etiology'' is defined relative only to disease. The word is defined as "[t]he study of the causes of disease" and as "[t]he cause of a disease", with no other definitions, in Thomas, Clayton L., ed., ''Taber's Cyclopedic Medical Dictionary'' (Philadelphia: F. A. Davis, ed. 16 8th printing 1989 (ISBN 0-8036-8310-3)), entry ''etiology''. The dictionary is intended for "those in the field of nursing" and others. ''Id.'', p. viii (Introduction to Edition 16, by Clayton Lay Thomas).&lt;/ref&gt;

Research on the etiology of sexual orientation when applied to asexuality has the definitional problem that sexual orientation is not consistently defined by all research investigators as including asexuality.&lt;ref&gt;E.g., one study on [[Prenatal_hormones_and_sexual_orientation#Prenatal_hormones_and_sexuality-linked_characteristics|hormonal influences]] defines sexual orientation as "heterosexuality, homosexuality, or bisexuality" only. Garcia-Falgueras, Alicia, &amp; Swaab, Dick F., ''Sexual Hormones and the Brain: An Essential Alliance for Sexual Identity and Sexual Orientation'', in ''Endocrine Development'', vol. 17, p. 24 (2010) (ISSN 1421-7082) (authors are of Netherlands Institute for Neuroscience, of [[Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences]]) (author contact is 2d author) (vol. 17 is Sandro Loche, Marco Cappa, Lucia Ghizzoni, Mohamad Maghnie, &amp; Martin O. Savage, eds., ''Pediatric Neuroendocrinology'') ("sexual orientation (heterosexuality, homosexuality, or bisexuality)").&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sexual orientation]] being "enduring" and resistant to change ("[s]exual orientation has proved to be generally impervious to interventions intended to change it")&lt;ref name="Calif-amici-p6-p11n14"&gt;[http://www.courtinfo.ca.gov/courts/supreme/highprofile/documents/Amer_Psychological_Assn_Amicus_Curiae_Brief.pdf ''Case No. S147999 in the Supreme Court of the State of California'', ''In re Marriage Cases Judicial Council Coordination Proceeding No. 4365'', ''Application For Leave to File Brief Amici Curiae in Support of the Parties Challenging the Marriage Exclusion, and Brief Amici Curiae of the American Psychological Association, California Psychological Association, American Psychiatric Association, National Association of Social Workers, and National Association of Social Workers, California Chapter in Support of the Parties Challenging the Marriage Exclusion'' (California ''amicus'' brief of APA, APA, &amp; NASW)], as accessed Mar. 17, 2010, Brief, p. 6 &amp; p. 11 n. 14, respectively (pp. 28 &amp; 33, respectively, per Adobe Acrobat Reader).&lt;/ref&gt; and asexuality being a sexual orientation, asexuality is enduring and resistant to change.

While heterosexuality, homosexuality, and bisexuality are usually, but not always, determined during the early years of preadolescent life, it is not known when asexuality is determined. "It is unclear whether these characteristics [''viz.'', "lacking interest in or desire for sex"] are thought to be lifelong, or if they may be acquired."&lt;ref name="Asex-Class-Charzn-p342"&gt;[http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/publications/PDF/PrauseGrahamPDF.pdf Prause, Nicole, &amp; Graham, Cynthia A., ''Asexuality: Classification and Characterization'', Mar. 8, 2007 (rec'd Dec. 6, 2005, revised Mar. 20, 2006, &amp; accepted Jul. 8, 2006), in ''Archives of Sexual Behavior'', vol. 36, no. 3 (Jun., 2007)], as accessed Mar. 17, 2010 (DOI 10.1007/s10508-006-9142-3), p. 342 (also [http://www.springerlink.com/content/y1g68862317t1825/ springerlink.com (part)] &amp; [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17345167 PubMed (part))], both as accessed Mar. 17, 2010) (lead author Nicole Prause of Dep't Psychological &amp; Brain Scis., Indiana Univ., author Cynthia A. Graham of Oxford Doctoral Course in Clinical Psychology, Isis Education Centre, Warneford Hospital, Headington, Oxford, &amp; both authors of Kinsey Institute for Research in Sex, Gender, &amp; Reproduction, Indiana Univ.).&lt;/ref&gt;

Nonmeasurement in some areas of sexual orientation is accepted by the American Psychological Association, the American Psychiatric Association, and the National Association of Social Workers: "[S]imply to document that a phenomenon occurs, case studies and nonprobability samples are often adequate. . . . Some groups are sufficiently few in number&amp;nbsp;– relative to the entire population&amp;nbsp;– that locating them with probability sampling is extremely expensive or practically impossible. In the latter cases, the use of nonprobability samples is often appropriate."&lt;ref name="Calif-amici-p4n3"&gt;[http://www.courtinfo.ca.gov/courts/supreme/highprofile/documents/Amer_Psychological_Assn_Amicus_Curiae_Brief.pdf ''Case No. S147999 in the Supreme Court of the State of California'', ''In re Marriage Cases Judicial Council Coordination Proceeding No. 4365'', ''Application For Leave to File Brief Amici Curiae in Support of the Parties Challenging the Marriage Exclusion, and Brief Amici Curiae of the American Psychological Association, California Psychological Association, American Psychiatric Association, National Association of Social Workers, and National Association of Social Workers, California Chapter in Support of the Parties Challenging the Marriage Exclusion'' (California ''amicus'' brief of APA, APA, &amp; NASW)], as accessed Mar. 17, 2010, Brief, p. 4 n. 3 (p. 26, per Adobe Acrobat Reader).&lt;/ref&gt; In determining etiologies, when asexuals are a small percentage of a large society, asexuals with a given etiology will compose an even smaller percentage, so that etiological information is available only from some individuals, generally not randomly selected.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asexuality.org/en/index.php?/topic/7361-my-reason-for-being-asexual/page__view__findpost__p__158589 abc55555 (user), "My Reason For Being Asexual", comment #1, Mar. 20, 2005], as accessed Feb. 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asexuality.org/en/index.php?/topic/34536-one-reason-why-i-dont-like-sex/page__view__findpost__p__1044895 fangless (user), "One Reason Why I Don't Like Sex", comment #1, Sep. 26, 2008], and [http://www.asexuality.org/en/index.php?/topic/34536-one-reason-why-i-dont-like-sex/page__view__findpost__p__1049171 comment #20, Sep. 26, 2008], both as accessed Feb. 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asexuality.org/en/index.php?/topic/34536-one-reason-why-i-dont-like-sex/page__view__findpost__p__1046653 Cheerio_Koroke (user), "One Reason Why I Don't Like Sex", comment #16, Sep. 27, 2008], as accessed Feb. 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nzherald.co.nz/lifestyle/news/article.cfm?c_id=6&amp;objectid=10455823&amp;pnum=0 Bridgeman, Shelley, ''No Sex Please, We're Asexual'', in (New Zealand) ''Herald News'', Aug. 5, 2007], as accessed Feb. 20, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Levinson, Nick, ''For Men Only: Asexuality'', in ''So to Speak: a feminist journal of language and art'', vol. 14, no. 2 (2005), pp. 51–54.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Community ==

A community of self-identified asexuals coalesced in the early 21st century, aided by the popularity of [[Virtual community|online communities]].&lt;ref name="New Scientist" /&gt;

Dr. [[Elizabeth Abbot]], author of ''A History of Celibacy'', acknowledges a difference between asexuality and celibacy and posits that there has always been an asexual element in the population but that asexual people kept a low profile. While failure to consummate marriage was seen as "an insult to the sacrament of marriage" in medieval Europe, asexuality, unlike homosexuality, has never been illegal, and asexual people have been able to "fly under the radar". However, in the 21st century the anonymity of online communication and general popularity of [[social network]]ing online has facilitated the formation of a community built around a common asexual identity.&lt;ref name="Duenwald"&gt;{{Cite news|first=Mary|last=Duenwald|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/09/fashion/thursdaystyles/09asexual.html?pagewanted=1&amp;ei=5088&amp;en=520063b1b0fd9ad7&amp;ex=1275969600&amp;partner=rssnyt&amp;emc=rss |title=For Them, Just Saying No Is Easy|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=9 July 2005|accessdate=17 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Asexual Visibility and Education Network]] (AVEN) was founded in 2001 by [[David Jay]] with two primary goals: to create public acceptance and discussion of asexuality and to facilitate the growth of an asexual community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About AVEN|publisher=Asexual Visibility and Education Network|url=http://www.asexuality.org/home/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=section&amp;id=7&amp;Itemid=34
|accessdate=17 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since that time, it has grown to host the world’s largest online asexual community, serving as an informational resource and meeting place for people who are asexual and questioning, their friends and families, academic researchers, and the press. The network has additional satellite communities in ten languages. Members of AVEN have been involved in media coverage spanning television, print, and radio and participate in lectures, conferences, and Pride events around the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=AVEN Homepage|publisher=Asexual Visibility and Education Network|url=http://www.asexuality.org/home/index.php|accessdate=17 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As an emerging identity with a broad definition, there is an enormous amount of variation among people who identify as asexual. Some asexuals may [[Masturbation|masturbate]] as a solitary form of release, while others do not feel a need to.&lt;ref name="New Scientist" /&gt; The need or desire for masturbation is commonly referred to as a "sex drive" and is disassociated from sexual attraction; asexuals who masturbate generally consider it to be a normal product of the human body and not a sign of latent sexuality. Asexuals also differ in their feelings towards performing sex acts: some are indifferent and may even have sex for the benefit of a partner, while others are more strongly averse to the idea.&lt;ref name="About Asexuality"&gt;{{cite web|title=About Asexuality|publisher=Asexual Visibility and Education Network|url=http://www.asexuality.org/home/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=section&amp;id=6&amp;Itemid=28|accessdate=18 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Religion ==
The notability of asexuality in religious text can vary, and can be misinterpreted as [[celibacy]] or [[sexual abstinence]], but asexuality has been acknowledged in a few works.

In [[Christianity|Christian]] circles, people who are asexual may be assumed celibate. The sexuality of [[Paul of Tarsus|St. Paul]] is cited as one of the few examples of this, but it is nearly impossible to say whether he was indeed asexual or not.

In the religion of [[Satanism]], [[The Satanic Bible]] is one of the few texts that acknowledges asexuality by name.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} About the Satanic Bible, it is asserted that, "In many cases of sexual sublimination (or asexuality), any attempt to emancipate himself sexually would prove devastating to the asexual."&lt;ref name="Baidu-SatanicBible-6-3-maybeblog"&gt;[http://hi.baidu.com/satan%D2%AB%D1%EF/blog/item/3ac8eb3c931e3d08baa167bf.html ''The Satanic Bible ------- 6–3'' ("2009-06-05 20:42")], as accessed Jul. 18, 2010 (possibly this is only a blog about the Satanic Bible).&lt;/ref&gt; It is also asserted that, "Asexuals are invariably sexually sublimated by their jobs or hobbies. All the energy and driving interest which would normally be devoted to sexual activity is channelled into other pastimes or into their chosen occupations. If a person favors other interests over sexual activity, it is his right, and no one is justified in condemning him for it."&lt;ref name="Baidu-SatanicBible-6-3-maybeblog" /&gt;

== Asexual symbols ==
[[Image:Ace-logo4.png|thumb|The asexual or 'AVEN' triangle|150px]]
Asexuals have no one fixed symbol, and none has ever officially been declared as the primary symbol of the community, however some have through the years become more prominent and important than others.

One of the symbols most easily associated with the asexual community is the asexual triangle also known as the AVEN triangle due to its origins on the [[Asexual Visibility and Education Network|AVEN]] forum. It was created by [[David Jay]], the founder of AVEN when he was first starting the forum and before the AVEN community, or any asexual community outside of AVEN had started up proper. The top line of the triangle represents the [[Kinsey Scale]] with the third point representing the other dimension of how strongly one is sexually attracted to people and from there comes the triangle and the gradient representing the fade between sexual and asexual.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xa1z2g_asex-101-part-1-of-3_gaylesbian&lt;/ref&gt; Though it has since become obvious that applying the range of asexual people can be so complicated that it is now used more as a metaphor than an accurate diagram of human sexuality and the asexual community's place in it. It has, at times, been adapted to a gradient filled heart or spade, but the triangle version is by far the more common version.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

[[Image:asexual flag.png|thumb|left|The asexual flag|200px]]
Other common symbols are the [[Ace of Spades]] or the [[Ace]] of [[Hearts (suit)|Hearts]] playing on words, with 'Ace' also being a shortened word for asexual. There is no fixed choice between which one works best though it has been suggested that the Ace of Hearts works for the [[Affectional orientation|romantic]] asexuals and the Ace of Spades for the [[Affectional orientation|aromantic]] asexuals.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asexuality.org/en/index.php?showtopic=43943&amp;st=0&amp;p=1369820&amp;hl=symbol&amp;fromsearch=1&amp;#entry1369820&lt;/ref&gt; This however is not a strict rule by any means nor accepted by all asexuals.

Another common symbol for asexuality is [[cake]], or rather a slice of it. Coming from the idea that 'cake is better than sex' and also as a general feel good welcome, comfort or congratulatory gesture.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asexuality.org/en/index.php?showtopic=40185&lt;/ref&gt; It has  been worn on shirts when AVEN members have marched during [[Pride parade|Pride]] along with a mash up of the AVEN triangle and the Ace of Spades.

Some asexuals wear a black ring on the middle finger of their right hand.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asexuality.org/en/index.php?showtopic=43173&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2010, after a process of trying to get the word out, even outside AVEN&lt;ref&gt;http://queersunited.blogspot.com/2010/07/join-activists-creating-first-ever.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.apositive.org/viewtopic.php?f=31&amp;t=378&lt;/ref&gt; and non-English speaking areas a flag was eventually voted on in a non-AVEN site&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asexuality.org/en/index.php?/topic/53110-asexual-flag-round-three/&lt;/ref&gt; and then elected.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asexuality.org/en/index.php?/topic/53435-asexual-flag-and-the-winner-is/&lt;/ref&gt; It has since been seen used on [[tumblr]] in various LGBTQetc areas, and had in fact been seen alongside other Sexual Orientations flags previous to formal election.&lt;ref&gt;http://queersecrets.tumblr.com/post/900132090&lt;/ref&gt; The black stripe represents asexuality, the grey stripe grey-asexuality and the demisexuals, the white stripe sexuality and the purple stripe community.

== Notable asexuals ==

{{See also|Category:Asexual people}}
&lt;!--DO NOT ADD ANYONE UNDER THIS SECTION UNLESS A RELIABLE SOURCE IS GIVEN, OTHERWISE IT WILL BE DELETED--&gt;
&lt;!--CROSS-CHECK THIS LIST WITH --&gt;

* [[Edward Gorey]], writer and illustrator. Gorey never married or had any known romantic relationships and responded to an interviewer's questioning of his sexual orientation with, "I'm neither one thing nor the other particularly ... I am apparently reasonably undersexed or something." He agreed with the interviewer's suggestion that the "sexlessness" of his books was "a product of his asexuality".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Edward|last=Gorey|year=2002|title=Ascending Peculiarity: Edward Gorey on Edward Gorey|publisher=Harvest Books|isbn=978-0156012911}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Keri Hulme]], author of ''[[The Bone People]]'', winner of the 1985 [[Man Booker Prize|Booker Prize]], discussed asexuality and her involvement with [[AVEN]] in a 2007 interview.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first=Shelley|last=Bridgeman|url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/section/6/story.cfm?c_id=6&amp;objectid=10455823 |title=No Sex Please, We're Asexual|newspaper=[[The New Zealand Herald]]|date=5 August 2007|accessdate=31 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Bradford Cox]], American musician, leader of the bands [[Deerhunter]] and Atlas Sound.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pitchfork.com/features/interviews/7726-atlas-sound/] Pitchfork interview published on 11.16.09.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Emilie Autumn]], an American singer-songwriter, poet, and violinist who is best known for her wide range of musical styles and her usage of theatrics.&lt;ref name="Curve magazine interview"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nxtbook.com/nxtbooks/curve/20_5/?ap=1#/56|title=Interview with Emilie Autumn|author=Steinfeld, Dave|date=June 2010|publisher=Curve Magazine|accessdate=5 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Fictional characters and persons
&lt;!--DO RESEARCH BEFORE POSTING!!! MOST FICTIONAL ORIENTATIONS ARE UNKNOWN AS MANY WORKS WILL NOT DIVE INTO DESCRIBING THE ORIENTATION OF CHARACTERS. MAKE SURE THAT THE CHARACTER HAS PERSONALLY EXPRESSED ASEXUALITY OR ASEXUALITY CHARACTERISTICS BEFORE POSTING!!!--&gt;
&lt;!--I removed Dumbeldore, Rowling stated in an interview that she thought of him as gay, since she is his creator, and thinks he is attracted to men - he's not asexual--&gt;
&lt;!--DO NOT ADD SPONGEBOB SQUAREPANTS!!! THIS PAGE IS DEVOTED TO THE ORIENTATION AND NOT ASEXUAL REPRODUCTION--&gt;
&lt;!--I removed Father Noel Furlong - the show's writers describe him as "someone who has suppressed his homosexuality for so long that it has driven him insane". NOT a good example - he is most definitely not an asexual character--&gt;
&lt;!--I removed Sherlock Holmes. Not wanting a lover does not equal asexuality. Armchair diagnosis.--&gt;

* [[Gerald Tippett]], character from the [[New Zealand]] [[drama]] [[Television program|series]] ''[[Shortland Street]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tearaway.co.nz/asexual-ay/ Tear Away Article]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

{{Portal|Sexuality}}
* [[Androgyny]]: the mixing of [[Masculinity|masculine]] and [[Femininity|feminine]] characteristics, personality, fashion, or culture
* [[Antisexualism]]: the views of someone who is antagonistic towards sexuality
* [[Affectional orientation]]: alternative views on attraction not based on sexuality, but more on purely romantic relationships
* [[Erotophobia]]: psychological fear of sexual intercourse and sexual feelings in general
* [[Genophobia]]: the fear of sexual intercourse
* [[Hypersexuality]]
* [[Platonic love]]: a nonsexual affectionate relationship
* [[Sexless marriage]]: a marriage in which little or no sex is performed throughout the marriage
* [[Sexual anorexia]]

== References ==

&lt;!--This article uses the Cite.php citation mechanism. If you would like more information on how to add references to this article, please see http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Cite/Cite.php --&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.asexuality.org/ AVEN: Asexual Visibility and Education Network]
* [http://www.apositive.org/ Apositive]
* [http://www.asexualexplorations.net Asexual Explorations] Promoting the Academic Study of Asexuality
* [http://www.asexualexplorations.net/home/extantresearch.html Asexual Explorations. ''Existing Research'', an annotated bibliography], as accessed Feb. 23, 2010.
* [http://www.fyne.co.uk/index.php?item=71 "The Fourth Way"], ''[[Fyne Times]] Gay and Lesbian Magazine''
* [http://www.cnn.com/2004/TECH/science/10/14/asexual.study/index.html Study: One in 100 Adults Asexual]
* [http://www.youtube.com/group/aventube AVENTube, a group of asexuals on youtube with videos about asexuality]
* [http://www.asexuality.org/wiki/index.php?title=Asexual_Sites Asexual site listing] A fairly extensive listing of asexual sites on the web.
* [http://www.asexualitic.com Asexualitic&amp;nbsp;– Meet asexual people], ''Build a Platonic Relationship''
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/lifeandstyle/2008/sep/08/relationships.healthandwellbeing "We're married, we just don't have sex"], UK ''Guardian'', September 8, 2008
* [http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/08/24/MNC6194GN4.DTL Asexuals leave the closet, find community] – SFGate.com
{{Human sexuality}}
{{Sexual identities}}

[[Category:Non-sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]
[[Category:Asexuality]]

[[br:Amrevelezh]]
[[bg:Асексуалност]]
[[cs:Asexualita]]
[[cy:Anrhywioldeb]]
[[da:Aseksualitet]]
[[de:Asexualität]]
[[et:Aseksuaalsus]]
[[es:Asexualidad]]
[[fa:بی‌جنسی]]
[[fo:Aseksuellur]]
[[fr:Asexualité]]
[[gl:Asexualidade]]
[[ko:무성애]]
[[hr:Aseksualnost]]
[[it:Asessualità]]
[[he:א-מיניות]]
[[ka:ასექსუალობა]]
[[ku:Aseksûalîte]]
[[hu:Aszexualitás]]
[[mk:Асексуалност]]
[[nl:Aseksualiteit]]
[[ja:非性愛]]
[[no:Aseksualitet]]
[[pl:Aseksualizm]]
[[pt:Assexualidade]]
[[ro:Asexualitate]]
[[ru:Асексуальность]]
[[simple:Asexuality]]
[[sk:Asexualita]]
[[sr:Асексуалност]]
[[fi:Aseksuaalisuus]]
[[sv:Asexualitet]]
[[tr:Aseksüel]]
[[vi:Vô tính]]
[[zh:無性戀]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>