<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041029063948|6951046" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="156858" pageid="156858" ns="0" title="Asexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-29T06:40:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:''This article is about human asexuality; [[asexual reproduction]] is a separate topic.''

'''Asexuality''' is a designation or self-designation for people who claim that they are not [[sexual attraction|sexually attracted]] to anyone.  This may be viewed as a form of [[sexual orientation]] in itself. It can also be viewed as a [[gender]] identification. There has been little research done on asexuality, but it appears to be the least common occurring sexual orientation. The [[Kinsey Institute]] recently conducted a survey on it. 

There is disagreement over whether or not asexuality is a legitimate orientation. Many claim that it is impossible or a [[sexual dysfunction]]. Others attribute it to things such as [[sexual abuse]], repressed [[homosexuality]], or a lack of proper [[hormones]]. 

==Variations==

As with those of any other sexual orientation, there are differences among people that identify as asexual. Some experience romantic attraction, and can be oriented towards one or both genders in this regard: they are interested in "normal" [[romantic relationship|romantic relationships]], either with both genders or exclusively with men or women, but would not want those relationships to include sexual activities. Others have a sex drive, but are not sexually attracted to either gender; in other words, drive and attraction are measured independently, much as they are in any other orientation. 

Some asexuals use a classification system developed (and then retired) by the founder of the [http://www.asexuality.org/ Asexual Visibility and Education Network] (one of the major asexual online communities, and abbreviated as AVEN). In this system, asexuals are divided into types A through D: a type A asexual has a sex drive but no romantic attraction, a type B experiences romantic attraction but no sex drive, a type C experiences both, and a type D neither. The categories are not meant to be entirely discrete or set in stone; one's type can change, or one can be on the border between two types. Note that AVEN itself no longer uses this system, on the basis that it is too exclusive.

The common link between all of these types is that none of them experience sexual attraction. Those that do feel a desire to engage in romantic relationships are therefore in a difficult position, as the majority of people are not asexual. They either must compromise with their partners, only date asexuals, or decide to live alone.

==Views of Asexuality==

Several religions or religious sects believe that asexuality is a spiritually superior condition. In other creeds, [[child|children]] may be considered a [[gift]] of [[God]] that should not be refused, or a means of spreading religion, or both. Furthermore, some religions feel that [[sexuality]] itself is a divine gift.

Currently, unlike [[homosexuality|homosexuals]], [[bisexuality|bisexuals]], and others, asexuals are not a main target of conservative religious groups. It is possible, though, that they could be subject to scrutiny from these religious groups in the future for challenging the belief that [[heterosexuality]] is the only normal sexual orientation.

==See also==
*[[Sexual orientation]]
*[[Celibacy]]
*[[List of asexuals]]

== External links ==
*[http://www.asexuality.org/ Asexual Visibility and Education Network]
*[http://www.asexuality.org/docs/SSSS_2003.ppt Kinsey Survey on Asexuality] (Power Point File)
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/life/science/story/0,12996,1326893,00.html ''Guardian'' article on asexuality]
*[http://www.cnn.com/2004/TECH/science/10/14/asexual.study/index.html CNN article on asexuality]
*[http://www.newscientist.com/news/news.jsp?id=ns99996533 New Scientist article on asexuality (14 October 04)]

[[Category:Sexology]]
[[de:Asexualität]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>