<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050918181450|23473044" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1694303" pageid="1694303" ns="0" title="Adultism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-21T14:15:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup-date|October 2005}} 
'''Adultism''' is a term, originating from [[Co-Counselling|co-counseling]], used to refer to the "oppression of young people through attitudinal, cultural, and systematic discrimination against children and youth". It is also used to refer to any bias against young people, and is distinguished from [[ageism]]&amp;mdash;which is simply prejudice on the grounds of age, not youth particularly. It is seen in co-counseling as the basis for all other [[oppression]] and [[discrimination]] in society, as well as for most [[psychological]] problems. 

Adultism refers to "behaviors and attitudes that are based on the assumption that adults are better than young people, and entitled to act upon them without their agreement." It is characterized by "disrespect towards the intelligence, judgment, emotional life, leadership, or physical being of young people." [http://www.schoolmediation.com/newsletters/2004/01_04.html#article1]

==Implications==
Adults may sometimes assume a young person is incapable of performing a task, doing it in their stead. This may result in lost opportunities for the young person to learn or experience the challenge.

Adults may at times blame young people for the challenges they face without taking into account their environments. Young people may internalize this, believing themselves at fault for difficulties that are, in reality, largely out of their control.

Some adults may avoid the company of young people, helping to perpetuate a lack of understanding between [[generations]]. As a result, besides the missed opportunities for social fulfillment for both groups, many programs created for youth may be created from the point of view of the adults, causing the young people to feel alienated and misunderstood.

Adults are sometimes condenscending of young people, belittling their abilities or dismissing otherwise socially inappropriate behavior. This is apparent even in some facets of our language, for instance when we say someone is acting "childish", as if certain behavior is to be implicitly expected of children.

According to this view of adultism, young people face systemic oppression by adults in the areas of [[incarceration]], [[education]], and [[military]] [[recruitment]].

==Examples==
Personal/Attitudinal forms of adultism are present in the common phrases,

* “Don't interrupt when adults are talking!”
* “You’re so smart for fifteen!”
* “When are you going to grow up?”
* “Don’t touch that, you’ll break it!”
* “She doesn’t understand anything.” (about a baby)
* "You are too old for that!” or “You’re not old enough!”
* “Oh, it’s only puppy love.”
* "What do you know? You haven’t experienced anything!”
* “It’s just a stage. You’ll outgrow it.”
* “You’re being childish.”

==Outcomes==
Research has shown that social stratification between age groups causes [[stereotype|stereotyp]]ing and generalization; for instance, the media-perpetuated myth that all adolescents are equally immature, violent and rebellious. Advocates of the concept of adultism contend that this has led to growing number of youth, academics, researchers, and other adults rallying against adultism and ageism, such as organizing education programs, protesting statements, and creating organizations devoted to publicizing the concept and addressing it.

==External links==
*[http://freechild.org/bell.htm Understanding Adultism]
*[http://freechild.org/adultism.htm Resources on Adultism]
*[http://www.cocowebs.com/liberaterc/roots.htm Adultism and the Roots of Authoritarianism]
*[http://www.youthrights.org/adultismculture.shtml Adultism and Cultural Competence] (by the [http://www.youthrights.org/ National Youth Rights Association] - NYRA)

[[Category:prejudice and discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>