<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061103021419|85390785" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1694303" pageid="1694303" ns="0" title="Adultism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-03T02:17:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{citations missing}}
{{npov}}

'''Adultism''' is a term used to describe the oppression of and discrimination against young people. It is also used to refer to any bias against young people, and is distinguished from [[ageism]], which is simply prejudice on the grounds of age; not specifically against youth.

==Consequences==
{{inappropriate tone}}
According to J. Sazama [http://www.youthonboard.org1], "''Young people are systemically mistreated and disrespected by society, with adults as the agents of the oppression. The basis of young people's oppression is disrespect. Manifestations of the oppression include: systematic invalidation, denial of voice or respectful attention, physical abuse, lack of information, misinformation, denial of any power, economic dependency, lack of rights, and any combination of the above.''"
 
Examples include:

* Parents setting fixed bedtimes or curfews, even though they sleep the required amount
* Youth workers forcing youth to stop using the telephone
* Police forcing youth to be accountable for their actions without regard to their denial
* Teachers forcing youth to study or work towards higher education irrespective of their occupational goals
* Religious leaders forcing youth to conform to a [[Freedom of religion|specific religion]] like [[Christianity]] or [[Islam]] despite their resistance

Adultist theory [http://www.ysa.org/pdffiles/yv/Youth_Voice_Definition.pdf3] states that most adults do not do this out of caprice or malice, but out of the belief that they are better able, through experience, and mental and physical maturity, to make decisions for young people.

Adultism may restrict youth's desire to engage in actions that may be harmful such as drinking an entire 2-litre bottle of [[Soft drink|soda]] (which the digestive system cannot handle and will certainly result in [[vomiting]]), spending hours playing video games in pursuit of a game goal (e.g. catching all the pokemon in a game like [[Pokemon]]), or engaging in [[sexual activities]] (e.g. [[teen sex]]). It may also result in restrictions on less objectionable, or completely innocuous, activities that simply differ from the expectations or desires of the adult making these restrictions; for example, parents may block "[[Wicca|occult/witchcraft]]" sites on the internet.

Adults may at times blame young people for the challenges they face in disregard with [[Peer pressure|circumstances]]. For example, some young women are prevented from wearing revealing clothing that is fashionable amongst their peers.  Many rules are created based on the judgements of adults, without consulting the affected youth.  Some people say that adults should consult youth before passing significant laws, like setting the [[legal drinking age]] to 21 or increaseing or decreasing the [[age of consent]], even though it does not violate the liberties of those above a given age.  However, this ignores the fact that youth have a vested interest in the outcome of this decision, and that they lack the experience - and, often but not always, maturity - of the adults who make legal decisions.  In particular to drinking and driving, youth are responsible for more fatalities than any other age group, making decisions which increase their access to alcohol problematic.

According to this view of adultism, youth face total control by adults who implement informal policies that disregard the idea that youth are dignified humans who have the ability of choice and whose rights should be respected.

==Results==

Research that has been compiled from two sources (a Cornell University nation-wide study, and a Harvard University study on youth) has shown that social stratification between age groups causes [[stereotype|stereotyp]]ing and generalization; for instance, the media-perpetuated myth that all adolescents are equally immature, violent and rebellious. Advocates of the concept of adultism contend that this has led to growing number of youth, academics, researchers, and other adults rallying against adultism and ageism, such as organizing education programs, protesting statements, and creating organizations devoted to publicizing the concept and addressing it.

However, there is research to support the idea that youth are physiologically less capable of making decisions and understanding the consequences of their actions.  For instance, many countries have something similar to Canada's [[Young Offenders Act]]. But, in this case, the parents and other care providers may come into question for not making such issues relevant to the child.

==Sources==

The term possibly originated from [[Co-Counselling|co-counseling]] in the early 1990s, and today is widely used in organizations that serve youth around the world, including community-based organizations and K-12 schools (see external links). Co-counseling addresses adultism as a common experience shared by all individuals, related to other forms of [[oppression]], but not the exclusive source of racism, heterosexism, or any other [[discrimination]]. [http://www.youthonboard.org Youth On Board] is the recognized international expert organization, providing literature, training, and consultation.

See:

* Bell, J. (2002). "[http://freechild.org/bell.htm Understanding adultism: A key to developing positive youth-adult relationships.]" Olympia, WA: The Freechild Project. 
* Sazama, J. (1999). "Understanding and supporting young people." Boston, MA: Youth On Board.
* Sazama, J. (2001). "Get the word out." Boston, MA: Youth On Board.

==External links==
* [http://hrw.org/reports/2005/us1005/6.htm The Difference between Youth and Adults]
* [http://www.freechild.org/bell.htm Freechild.org on Adultism]
* [http://www.cocowebs.com/liberaterc/roots.htm Adultism and the Roots of Authoritarianism]
* [http://www.youthrights.org/adultismculture.shtml Adultism and Cultural Competence] (by the [http://www.youthrights.org/ National Youth Rights Association] - [[National Youth Rights Association|NYRA]])

==See also==

* [[Ageism]]
* [[Ephebiphobia]]
* [[youth voice]]
* [[youth participation]]

[[Category:prejudice and discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>