<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161112061547|749073364" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="15726826" pageid="15726826" ns="0" title="Racism in Africa"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-12T06:17:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=June 2015}}
&lt;!---Only add contributions related to "Racism in Africa". Information SOLELY about slavery or ethnic conflicts in individual African countries should be moved to their respective articles.---&gt;

'''Racism in Africa''' is multi-faceted and dates back several centuries. It is a phenomenon that may have been strengthened by European colonialism, under which boundaries were drawn that did not take into consideration the different peoples dwelling within the newly formed provinces. The boundaries were little changed when former European colonies gained independence. As a consequence, some African nations have been plagued with inner conflicts, racist attitudes and tribal warfare.

[[Race (human classification)|Race]] and [[racism]] continues to be a factor in the post-colonial context.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.culanth.org/articles/702-race-in-africa-today-a-commentary|title=Race in Africa Today: A Commentary|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Colonial era racism==
Racism and colonization were interrelated.&lt;ref name="reunionblackfamily.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reunionblackfamily.com/apps/blog/show/17999836-racism-and-colonialism-were-symmetrically-related-in-africa-under-white-rule|title=Racism and colonialism were symmetrically related in Africa under white rule|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racism was used to justify colonialism, and it resulted in the conquest of African nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/sartre/works/critic/racism-algeria.htm|title=Racism and Colonialism as Praxis and Process by Jean-Paul Sartre 1960|author=Jean-Paul Sartre|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The colonists believed that Africans had to move from their "primitive" existence to a modern European one. Africans were seen as backward mainly due to the racist ideas of [[Social Darwinism]].&lt;ref name="reunionblackfamily.com"/&gt;

==Ivory Coast==
In the past recent years, [[Ivory Coast]] has seen a resurgence in ethnic tribal hatred and religious intolerance.  In addition to the many victims among the various tribes of the northern and southern regions of the country that have perished in the ongoing conflict, [[White people|white]] foreigners residing or visiting Ivory Coast have also been subjected to violent attacks. According to a report by Human Rights Watch, the Ivory Coast government is guilty of fanning ethnic hatred for its own political ends.&lt;ref&gt;
[news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/Africa/1932930.stm Ivory Coast "fanning ethnic hatred"]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, the [[Congrès Panafricain des Jeunes et des Patriotes|Young Patriots]] of Abidjan, a strongly [[nationalist]] organisation, rallied by the state media, plundered possessions of foreign nationals in [[Abidjan]]. Calls for violence against whites and non-Ivorians were broadcast on national radio and TV after the Young Patriots seized control of its offices. Rapes, beatings, and murders of persons of European and Lebanese descent followed. Thousands of expatriates and white or ethnic Lebanese Ivorians fled the country. The attacks drew international condemnation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/11/19/wapp19.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2004/11/19/ixnewstop.html|title=News|work=Telegraph.co.uk|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/newsitems/200411/s1242699.htm Europeans flee Ivory Coast violence. 13 November 2004. ABC News Online]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mauritania==
{{Main|Slavery in Mauritania}}
{{further|Slavery in modern Africa}}
[[Slavery in Mauritania]] persists despite its abolition in 1980 and mostly affects the descendants of black Africans abducted into [[slavery]] who now live in [[Mauritania]] as "black [[Moors]]" or ''[[haratin]]'' and who partially still serve the "white Moors", or ''bidhan'', as slaves. The practice of slavery in Mauritania is most dominant within the traditional upper class of the Moors. For centuries, the ''haratin'' lower class, mostly poor black Africans living in rural areas, have been considered natural slaves by these Moors. Social attitudes have changed among most urban Moors, but in rural areas, the ancient divide remains.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L18334379.htm|title=Thomson Reuters Foundation|author=Thomson Reuters Foundation|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ruling ''bidanes'' (literally white-skinned people) are descendants of the [[Sanhaja]] [[Berber people|Berbers]] and [[Beni Ḥassān]] Arab tribes who emigrated  to northwest Africa and present-day [[Western Sahara]] and Mauritania during the [[Middle Ages]]. Many descendants of the Beni Ḥassān tribes today still adhere to the [[supremacist]] ideology of their ancestors, which has caused the oppression, discrimination and even enslavement of other groups in Mauritania.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?ReportId=70522|title=IRIN Africa - MAURITANIA: Fair elections haunted by racial imbalance - Mauritania - Governance - Human Rights|work=IRINnews|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to some estimates, as many as 600,000 black Mauritanians, or 20% of the population, are still enslaved, many of them used as [[bonded labour]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/specials/1458_abolition/page4.shtml|title=BBC World Service - The Abolition season on BBC World Service|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Slavery in Mauritania was criminalized in August 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6938032.stm|title=BBC NEWS - Africa - Mauritanian MPs pass slavery law|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Namibia==
{{Main|Herero and Namaqua genocide}}

On 12 January 1904, the [[Herero people]], led by [[Samuel Maharero]], rebelled against [[Germany|German]] [[German colonial empire|colonial rule]]. In August, German general [[Lothar von Trotha]] defeated the Herero in the [[Battle of Waterberg]] and drove them into the desert of [[Omaheke]], where most of them died of thirst. In October, the [[Nama people]] also rebelled against the Germans, suffering a similar fate.

The violence eventually led to a genocide of the Herero and Nama people by the Germans, known as the [[Herero and Namaqua genocide]]. It is considered the first [[genocide]] of the 20th century. In total, 24,000 to 100,000 Herero and 10,000 Nama died.&lt;ref&gt;Colonial Genocide and Reparations Claims in the 21st Century: The Socio-Legal Context of Claims under International Law by the Herero against Germany for Genocide in Namibia, 1904-1908 (PSI Reports) by Jeremy Sarkin-Hughes&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Empire, Colony, Genocide: Conquest, Occupation and Subaltern Resistance in World History (War and Genocide) (War and Genocide) (War and Genocide) A. Dirk Moses -page 296(From Conquest to Genocide: Colonial Rule in German Southwest Africa and German East Africa. 296, (29). Dominik J. Schaller)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Imperialist Imagination: German Colonialism and Its Legacy (Social History, Popular Culture, and Politics in Germany) by Sara L. Friedrichsmeyer, Sara Lennox, and Susanne M. Zantop page 87 University of Michigan Press  1999&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Walter Nuhn 1904"&gt;Walter Nuhn: ''Sturm über Südwest. Der Hereroaufstand von 1904.'' Bernard &amp; Graefe-Verlag, Koblenz 1989. ISBN 3-7637-5852-6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marie-Aude Baronian, Stephan Besser, Yolande Jansen, "Diaspora and memory: figures of displacement in contemporary literature, arts and politics", [https://books.google.com/books?id=LItBN2keNpQC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;dq=Herero+starvation pg. 33] Rodopi, 2007,&lt;/ref&gt; The genocide was characterized by a high number of deaths from starvation and thirst; the Herero who fled the violence were prevented from returning from the [[Namib Desert]]. Some sources also claim that the German colonial army systematically poisoned desert wells.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Totten, William S. Parsons, Israel W. Charny, "Century of genocide: critical essays and eyewitness accounts" [https://books.google.com/books?id=5Ef8Hrx8Cd0C&amp;pg=PA51&amp;dq=Herero+Poisoned+wells pg. 51], Routledge, 2004,&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=kroll&gt;Dan Kroll, "Securing our water supply: protecting a vulnerable resource", PennWell Corp/University of Michigan Press, pg. 22&lt;/ref&gt; The genocide took place between 1904 and 1907 in [[German South-West Africa]] (now modern day [[Namibia]]), during the [[Herero Wars]].

In 1926, except for archive copies, records of the genocide were withdrawn and destroyed following a decision of the then Legislative Assembly.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.namibian.com.na/index.php?id=28&amp;tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D=54620&amp;no_cache=1, ‘Stolen’ Blue Book was just misplaced] 23.04.2009
 accessed 17 Dec 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Gewald, Jan-Bart |title=Herereo Heroes: A Socio-Political History of the Herero of Namibia 1890-1923 |publisher=Ohio University Press |year=1999 |page=242 |quote="Of late it has been claimed that the infamous 'Blue Book' which detailed the treatment of Africans in GSWA was little more than a piece of propaganda put about to further South Africa's territorial ambitions and Britain's position at the negotiating table. Granted that the book was used to strengthen Britain's position vis-a-vis Germany, it must however be borne in mind that the bulk of the evidence contained in the 'Blue Book' is little more than the literal translation of German texts published at the time which were the findings of a German commission of inquiry into the effects of corporal punishment." Thus, when the Blue Book was withdrawn from the public after Germany and England came to an agreement about how to share access to GSWA minerals, this was not censorship; it was just business}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Survivors, majority of whom were women and children, were eventually put in [[concentration camp]]s, such as the one at [[Shark Island Concentration Camp|Shark Island]], where the German authorities forced them to work as slaves for German military and settlers. All prisoners were categorized into groups fit and unfit for work, and pre-printed death certificates indicating "death by exhaustion following privation" were issued.&lt;ref&gt;The colonising camera: photographs in the making of Namibian history Wolfram Hartmann, Jeremy Silvester, Patricia Hayes, page 118, University of Cape Town Press, 1999&lt;/ref&gt; The British government published their widely known account of the German genocide of the Nama and Herero peoples in 1918.&lt;ref&gt;Jan-Bart Gewald, Jeremy Silvester, "Words Cannot Be Found: German Colonial Rule in Namibia : An Annotated Reprint of the 1918 Blue Book (Sources on African History, 1)", Brill Academic Publishers, annotated edition (1 June 2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Herero died later of disease, overwork and malnutrition.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=The Dark Side of Democracy: Explaining Ethnic Cleansing |last=Michael Mann |page=105 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Hitler's African Victims: The German Army Massacres of Black French Soldiers in 1940 |page=83 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Camps, such as that in Windhoek, had mortality rates as high as 61%&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=The continuities of German history: nation, religion, and race across the Long Nineteenth Century |last=Helmut Walser Smith |page=199 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The mortality rate in the camps was 45% in 1908.&lt;ref name="HBV"&gt;''Hitler's Black Victims: The Historical Experiences of European Blacks, Africans and African Americans During the Nazi Era'' (Crosscurrents in African American History) by [[Clarence Lusane]], page 50-51 Routledge 2002&lt;/ref&gt; The death rates are calculated to be between 69% and 74%.&lt;ref&gt;Steinmetz, George, ''The devil's handwriting'', pp 196-216&lt;/ref&gt;

Food in the camps was extremely scarce, consisting of rice with no additions.&lt;ref&gt;The practice of war Production, Reproduction and Communication of Armed Violence Edited by Aparna Rao, Michael Bollig and Monika Böck, page 92, Berghahn Books; 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Shootings, hangings and beatings were common,&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Rethinking resistance: revolt and violence in African history |page=282 |last=Klaas van Walraven |publisher=Brill Academic Publishers |year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[sjambok]] was used by guards who treated the forced labourers harshly. Medical experiments were performed on the Herero and Nama people by the Germans, similar to those performed on the [[European Jews]] during the [[Holocaust]]. [[Eugen Fischer]], a German anthropologist, came to the concentration camps to conduct medical experiments on race,&lt;ref name="Mamdani, p. 12"&gt;Mamdani, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; using children of Herero people and [[mulatto]] children of Herero women and German men as test subjects.&lt;ref name="Mamdani, p. 12"/&gt; Other experiments were made by Dr Bofinger, who injected Herero that were suffering from scurvy with various substances including arsenic and opium; afterwards he researched the effects of these substances by performing autopsies on the dead bodies&lt;ref&gt;The Kaiser's Holocaust: Germany's Forgotten Genocide and the Colonial Roots of Nazism, page 225, Casper Erichsen, David Olusoga,  Faber and Faber  2010&lt;/ref&gt;

With the closure of concentration camps, all surviving Herero were distributed as labourers for settlers in the German colony, and from then on, all Herero over the age of seven were forced to wear a metal disc with their labour registration number,&lt;ref name="Mamdani, p. 12"/&gt; and banned from owning land or cattle, a necessity in pastoral society.&lt;ref&gt;Production, Reproduction and Communication of Armed Violence Aparna Rao, Michael Bollig and Monika Böck,page 89, Berghahn Books 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

It is believed that the Herero and Namaqua genocide influenced the [[Nazis]] and [[Nazi Germany]].

In 1985, the [[United Nations]]' [[Sub-Commission on the Promotion and Protection of Human Rights#Whitaker Report|Whitaker Report]] classified the aftermath as an attempt to exterminate the Herero and Nama peoples of [[South-West Africa]], and therefore one of the earliest attempts at genocide in the 20th century. The German government recognised and apologised for the events in 2004, but has ruled out financial compensation or land reparation for the victims' descendants.&lt;ref name="BBC08142004"&gt;{{Cite news|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/3565938.stm|title = Germany admits Namibia genocide|date = 2004-08-14|accessdate = 2008-04-23|publisher = [[BBC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, there was only minor media attention in Germany on this matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| first=Alexander| last=Krabbe| url=http://english.ohmynews.com/articleview/article_view.asp?menu=c10400&amp;no=180988&amp;rel_no=1| title=Remembering Germany's African Genocide| work=[[OhmyNews International]] | accessdate=2004-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

About 4,000 commercial land owners, mostly whites, own over 50% of the arable land across the country despite a [[Land reform in Namibia|land reform process]] undertaken by the Namibian government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3242829.stm Namibians plan white farm grabs] in [[BBC News]], 5 November 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|4pdVrQjuzvE}} [[Al Jazeera]], 2012&lt;/ref&gt; When the country was known as [[South West Africa]], [[White Namibians]] enjoyed a highly privileged position due to [[South Africa under apartheid|apartheid laws]] enforcing strict segregation and white domination.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D71E3CF935A15751C1A96E948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=1 Amid Namibia's White Opulence, Majority Rule Isn't So Scary Now] in the [[New York Times]], 26 December 1988&lt;/ref&gt;

==Niger==
In October 2006, [[Niger]] announced that it would deport to Chad the "[[Diffa Arabs]]", [[Arabs]] living in the Diffa region of eastern Niger.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6087048.stm|title=BBC NEWS - Africa - Niger starts mass Arab expulsions|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their population numbered about 150,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L25138454.htm|title=Thomson Reuters Foundation|author=Thomson Reuters Foundation|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the government was rounding up Arabs in preparation for the deportation, two girls died, reportedly after fleeing government forces, and three women suffered miscarriages. Niger's government eventually suspended their controversial decision to deport the Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6081416.stm|title=BBC NEWS - Africa - Niger's Arabs to fight expulsion|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/refworld/rwmain?docid=469638881e|title=Refworld - The Leader in Refugee Decision Support|author=United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|work=Refworld|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Niger, while the practice of [[slavery]] was outlawed in 2003, a study has found that more than 800,000 people are still slaves, almost 8% of the population.&lt;ref name="The Shackles of Slavery in Niger"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/Story?id=813618&amp;page=1|title=The Shackles of Slavery in Niger|author=ABC News|work=ABC News|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/4250709.stm Born to be a slave in Niger] By Hilary Andersson, BBC Africa Correspondent, Niger&lt;/ref&gt; Slavery dates back centuries in Niger and was criminalised after five years of lobbying by [[Anti-Slavery International]] and Nigerian human-rights group, Timidria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0310/p07s01-woaf.html|title=On the way to freedom, Niger's slaves stuck in limbo|author=The Christian Science Monitor|work=The Christian Science Monitor|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Descent-based slavery, where generations of the same family are born into [[debt bondage|bondage]], is traditionally practiced by at least four of Niger's eight ethnic groups. The slave masters are mostly from the lighter-skinned [[nomadic]] tribes: the [[Tuareg people|Tuareg]], [[Fulani]], [[Toubou]] and Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smithsonianmagazine.com/issues/2005/september/bondage.php?page=3|title=History, Travel, Arts, Science, People, Places - Smithsonian|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is especially rife among the warlike Tuareg, located in the wild deserts of north and west Niger, who roam near the borders with Mali and Algeria. In the region of Say on the right bank of the river Niger, it is estimated that three-quarters of the population around 1904&amp;ndash;1905 was composed of slaves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.antislavery.org/homepage/resources/PDF/Full%20English%20Slavery%20in%20Niger.pdf|title=Anti-Slavery|author=dotMailer|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, the Tuareg swelled the ranks of their black slaves by conducting war raids into other peoples’ lands. War was the main source of supply of slaves, although many were bought at slave markets, run mostly by indigenous peoples.&lt;ref name="The Shackles of Slavery in Niger"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=53497|title=IRIN Africa - NIGER: Slavery - an unbroken chain - Niger - Gender Issues - Human Rights|work=IRINnews|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==South Africa==
{{Expand section|date=June 2016}}
{{See also|South African Human Rights Commission}}

Racism is still prevalent in [[South Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.univie.ac.at/ecco/stichproben/Nr6_Interview_Moleah.pdf|format=PDF|title=Interview with Prof. Alfred Tokollo Moleah, South African Ambassador to Vienna |last=Englert|first=Birgit|publisher=Universität Wien|accessdate=2008-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The end of [[South Africa under apartheid|apartheid]] might have removed the legal framework allowing [[institutionalised racism]], however, racism in South Africa both predates and encompasses more than just the institutionalised racism of apartheid.

===Colonial racism===
The establishment of the [[Dutch East India Company]] settlement at the [[Cape of Good Hope]] in 1652 brought with it the established slave labor practices of the company.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.iziko.org.za/sh/resources/slavery/slavery_world.html|title=Slavery at the Cape|publisher=Iziko Museums of Cape Town|accessdate=2008-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these slaves were imported from the company's more established settlements in India and the East Indies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.anc.org.za/ancdocs/history/solidarity/indiasa3.html|title=Indian Slaves in South Africa|publisher=[[African National Congress]]|accessdate=2008-11-19 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080622023927/http://www.anc.org.za/ancdocs/history/solidarity/indiasa3.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Slavery was by no means restricted to the European slave trade. During the [[Difaqane]], the [[Zulu Kingdom|Zulu]] under [[Shaka]] overran many smaller tribes and enslaved them.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.isic.org/sisp/index.htm?fx=destination&amp;loc_id=131114&amp;section=culture|title=Destinations: South Africa - Pre 20th Century History|publisher=International Student Travel Conveduration|accessdate=2008-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Slavery in South Africa was officially [[Abolitionism|abolished]] in 1833 with the [[Slavery Abolition Act 1833|Slavery Abolition Act of the Parliament of the United Kingdom]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/huk-1833act.htm|title=Slavery Abolition Act 1833|date=1833-10-29|publisher=Houses of Parliament, Palace of Westminster, London.|accessdate=2008-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are many examples of racism and discriminatory practices during the colonial period, such as the allocation of rations during the [[Siege of Ladysmith]]
{{quote|For Whites—Biscuit, 1/4 lb.; Maize meal, 3 oz.&lt;br&gt;
For Indians and Kaffirs—Maize meal, 8 oz.&lt;br&gt;
Europeans—Fresh meat, 1 lb.&lt;br&gt;
Kaffirs—Fresh meat, 1-1/4 lbs. (Chiefly horseflesh.)&lt;br&gt;
For White men—Coffee or tea, 1/12 oz.; pepper, 1/64 oz.; salt, 1/3 oz.; sugar, 1 oz.; mustard, 1/20 oz.; Vinegar, 1/12 gill.&lt;br&gt;
For Indians—a little rice.| H. W. Nevinson &lt;ref&gt;{{Gutenberg|no=16603|name=Ladysmith, The Diary of a Siege by Henry W. Nevinson}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Even [[Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi|Mohandas Gandhi]] who worked to eradicate racism and in particular racism that affected the Indian communities in South Africa, was prone to making racist remarks during this period. In one of his [[Gandhi#Early South African articles|early articles]] for the ''[[Indian Opinion]]'' he writes:
{{quote|Kaffirs are as a rule uncivilised - the convicts even more so. They are troublesome, very dirty and live almost like animals.| Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Collected Works of Mahatma Gandhi|volume=8|pages=199}}&lt;/ref&gt; }}

===Apartheid racism===
{{See also|South Africa under apartheid}}
Apartheid (Afrikaans pronunciation: [ɐˈpartɦɛit]; an Afrikaans word meaning "separateness", or "the state of being apart", literally "apart-hood") was a system of racial segregation in South Africa enforced through legislation by the National Party (NP), the governing party from 1948 to 1994. Under apartheid, the rights, associations, and movements of the majority black inhabitants and other ethnic groups were curtailed, and white minority rule was maintained. Apartheid was developed after World War II by the Afrikaner-dominated National Party and Broederbond organizations. The ideology was also enforced in South West Africa, which was administered by South Africa under a League of Nations mandate (revoked in 1966 via United Nations Resolution 2145), until it gained independence as Namibia in 1990. By extension, the term is currently used for forms of systematic segregation established by the state authority in a country against the social and civil rights of a certain group of citizens due to ethnic prejudices.

==Sudan==
{{Main|Racism in Sudan}}
{{See also|War in Darfur|South Sudan|Slavery in Sudan}}
In the [[Sudan]], [[black people|black]] African captives in the civil war were often [[slavery in modern Africa|enslaved]], and female prisoners were often abused sexually,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/05/30/wdarf30.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2004/05/30/ixworld.html|title=News|work=Telegraph.co.uk|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; with their [[Arab]] captors claiming that Islamic law grants them permission.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.brandeis.edu/projects/fse/Pages/islamandslavery.html Islam and Slavery&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  According to [[CBS News]], slaves have been sold for US$50 a piece.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/1999/01/25/world/main29927.shtml Curse Of Slavery Haunts Sudan] CBS News. January 25, 1998&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2000, the [[U.S. State Department]] alleged that "the Sudanese government's support of slavery and its continued military action which has resulted in numerous deaths are due in part to the victims' religious beliefs."&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2000/US/09/05/state.dept.religion/index.html U.S. State Department report says 'religious intolerance remains far too common' around world. September 6, 2000] CNN US News&lt;/ref&gt; Jok Madut Jok, professor of history at [[Loyola Marymount University]], states that the abduction of women and children of the south is [[slavery]] by any definition. The government of Sudan insists that the whole matter is no more than the traditional tribal [[feud]]ing over resources.&lt;ref&gt;Jok Madut Jok (2001), p.3&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States government's [[Sudan Peace Act]] of October 21, 2002 accused Sudan of genocide in an [[Second Sudanese Civil War|ongoing civil war]] which has cost more than 2,000,000 lives and has displaced more than 4,000,000 people since the war started in 1983.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2002/14531.htm U.S. Department of State: Sudan Peace Act] October 21, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Second Sudanese Civil War]], people were taken into slavery; estimates of abductions range from 14,000 to 200,000. Abduction of [[Dinka people|Dinka]] women and children was common.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Slavery, Abduction and Forced Servitude in Sudan|url=http://www.state.gov/p/af/rls/rpt/2002/10445.htm|publisher=US Department of State|accessdate=20 March 2014|date=22 May 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, it became publicly known that there was an [[Darfur conflict|organised campaign]] by Janjaweed militias (nomadic Arab shepherds with the support of Sudanese government troops) to get rid of 80 black African groups from the [[Darfur]] region of western Sudan. These peoples include the Fur, Zaghawa and Massalit.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Clayton ''[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,3-1107849_2,00.html Desert hides world's worst humanitarian crisis]'' in [[The Times]] May 13, 2004, Page 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hilary Andersson''[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2089-1358234_1,00.html Genocide lays waste Darfur’s land of no men]'' in [[The Sunday Times (UK)|Sunday Times]] November 14, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

Mukesh Kapila ([[United Nations]] humanitarian coordinator) is quoted as saying: "This is more than just a conflict. It is an organised attempt [by Khartoum] to do away with a group of people. The only difference between [[Rwandan Genocide|Rwanda]] [in 1994] and Darfur now is the numbers of dead, murdered, tortured and raped involved"&lt;ref&gt;Fred Bridgland ''[http://www.sundayherald.com/41183 Darfur: Africa’s hidden holocaust?]'' in [[Sunday Herald]]'' April 11, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parliament.uk/parliamentary_committees/international_development/ind_04_05_14.cfm Darfur, Sudan: Crisis, response and lessons] UK Parliament Press Notice 14, Session 2004-05&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Collins, Robert O., "Civil Wars and Revolution in the Sudan: Essays on the Sudan, Southern Sudan, and Darfur, 1962-2004
", (p. 156), Tsehai Publishers (US), (2005) ISBN 0-9748198-7-5 .&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Power, Samantha  "Dying in Darfur:
Can the ethnic cleansing in Sudan be stopped?"[http://www.newyorker.com/fact/content/?040830fa_fact1], ''The New Yorker'', 30 August 2004.
Human Rights Watch, [http://hrw.org/english/docs/2004/05/05/darfur8536.htm "Q &amp; A: Crisis in Darfur"] (web site, retrieved 24 May 2006).
Hilary Andersson, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/3752871.stm "Ethnic cleansing blights Sudan"], ''BBC News'', 27 May 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; A July 14, 2007 article noted that in the past two months up to 75,000 Arabs from [[Chad]] and [[Niger]] crossed the border into Darfur. Most have been relocated by the Sudanese government to former villages of displaced non-Arab people. Some 2.5 million have now been forced to flee their homes after attacks by Sudanese troops and Janjaweed militia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.independent.co.uk/world/africa/article2768232.ece|title=The Independent - 404|work=The Independent|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tunisia==
The accession of the Almohade dynasty to the throne of the [[Maghreb]] provinces in 1146 proved disastrous to the [[Jews]] of [[Tunis]]. Jews as well as [[Christians]] were compelled either to embrace [[Islam]] or to leave the country. [[Abd al-Mu'min]]'s successors pursued the same course, and their severe measures resulted either in emigration or in forcible conversions. Soon becoming suspicious of the sincerity of the new converts, the Almohades compelled them to wear a special garb, with a yellow cloth for a head-covering.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sefarad.org/publication/lm/045/8.html|title=THE HISTORY OF THE JEWS OF TUNISIA|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mistranslations of Arab scholars and geographers from this time period have led many to attribute certain racist attitudes that were not prevalent until the 18th and 19th century to writings made centuries ago.&lt;ref&gt;Translation and the Colonial Imaginary: Ibn Khaldun Orientalist, by Abdelmajid Hannoum  © 2003 Wesleyan University. {{JSTOR|3590803}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although bias against those of very black complexion existed in the Arab world in the 15th century, it did not carry as much stigma as it later would. Older translations of Ibn Khaldun, for example in [https://books.google.com/books?id=6swTAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA61 The Negro land of the Arabs Examined and Explained] which was written in 1841 gives excerpts of older translations that were not part of later colonial propaganda and show black Africans in a generally positive light.

:'' When the conquest of the West (by the Arabs) was completed, and merchants began to penetrate into the interior, they saw no nation of the Blacks so mighty as Ghanah, the dominions of which extended westward as far as the Ocean. The King's court was kept in the city of Ghanah, which, according to the author of the Book of Roger (El Idrisi), and the author of the Book of Roads and Realms (El Bekri), is divided into two parts, standing on both banks of the Nile, and ranks among the largest and most populous cities of the world. The people of Ghanah had for neighbours, on the east, a nation, which, according to historians, was called Susu; after which came another named Mali; and after that another known by the name of Kaukau; although some people prefer a different orthography, and write this name Kagho. The last-named nation was followed by a people called Tekrur. The people of Ghanah declined in course of time, being overwhelmed or absorbed by the Molaththemun (or muffled people;that is, the Morabites), who, adjoining them on the north towards the Berber country, attacked them, and, taking possession of their territory, compelled them to embrace the Mohammedan religion. The people of Ghanah, being invaded at a later period by the Susu, a nation of Blacks in their neighbourhood, were exterminated, or mixed with other Black nations.

Ibn Khaldun suggests a link between the decline of Ghana and rise of the Almoravids. however, there is little evidence of there actually being an Almoravid conquest of Ghana [&lt;ref&gt;http://www.arts.ualberta.ca/~amcdouga/Hist446/readings/conquest_in_west_african_historiography.pdf Not Quite Venus from the Waves: The Almoravid Conquest of Ghana in the Modern Historiography of Western Africa by Pekka Masonen; Humphrey J. Fisher 1996&lt;/ref&gt;]&lt;ref&gt;The Conquest That Never Was: Ghana and the Almoravids, 1076. I. The External Arabic Sources, by David Conrad and Humphrey Fisher  © 1982 African Studies Association {{JSTOR|3171598}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uganda==
Former British colonies in [[Sub-Saharan Africa]] have many citizens of [[South Asian]] descent. They were brought by the [[British Empire]] from [[British India]] to do clerical work in imperial service.&lt;ref name="Amin-Indophobia"&gt;General Amin and the Indian Exodus from Uganda
Hasu H. Patel, ''Issue: A Journal of Opinion'', Vol. 2, No. 4 (Winter, 1972), pp. 12-22 {{doi|10.2307/1166488}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most prominent case of anti-Indian racism was the [[ethnic cleansing]] of the Indian (called Asian) minority in [[Uganda]] by strongman [[dictator]] and [[human rights]] violator [[Idi Amin]].&lt;ref name="Amin-Indophobia"/&gt;

The 1968 Committee on "Africanization in Commerce and Industry" in Uganda made far-reaching Indophobic proposals. A system of work permits and trade licenses
was introduced in 1969 in order to restrict the role of Indians in economic and professional activities. Indians were segregated and discriminated against in all walks of life. After Amin came to power, he exploited these divisions to spread propaganda against Indians, [[stereotyping]] and [[scapegoating]] the Indian minority. Indians were stereotyped as "only traders" and so "inbred" to their profession. Indians were attacked as "dukawallas" (an occupational term that degenerated into an anti-Indian slur during Amin's time).&lt;ref name="Amin-Indophobia"/&gt;

In the 1970s Uganda and other East African nations{{which|date=June 2016}} implemented racist policies that targeted the Asian population of the region. Uganda under Idi Amin's leadership was particularly virulent in its anti-Asian policies. In August 1972, Idi Amin declared what he called an "economic war", a set of policies that included the expropriation of properties owned by Asians and Europeans. Uganda's 80,000 Asians were mostly Indians born in the country, whose ancestors had come to Uganda when the country was still a British colony.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ugandamission.net/aboutug/articles/amin.html|title=Idi Amin|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/august/7/newsid_2492000/2492333.stm | work=BBC News | title=1972: Asians given 90 days to leave Uganda | date=1972-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indians were stereotyped as "greedy" and "conniving", without any racial identity or loyalty but "always cheating, conspiring and plotting" to subvert Uganda. Amin used this propaganda to justify a campaign of "de-Indianization", eventually resulting in the expulsion and ethnic cleansing of Uganda's Indian minority.&lt;ref name="Amin-Indophobia"/&gt;
India refused to accept the expelled people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/business/uk-indians-taking-care-of-business/2006/03/07/1141701511987.html|title=UK Indians taking care of business|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the expelled Indians settled in Britain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/legacies/immig_emig/england/suffolk/article_1.shtml|title=BBC - Legacies - Immigration and Emigration - England - Suffolk - Uganda's loss, Britain's gain - Article Page 1|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The forced expulsion of Uganda's entire Asian population attests to the persecution of Asian peoples residing in the country at the time. Today, Asian/Indian residents of Uganda continue to face marginalization, being given an inferior status.

==Zimbabwe==
{{main|Racism in Zimbabwe}}
{{POV|date=October 2014}}&lt;!--all emphasis on post=80 action, need prior ones too--&gt;

[[Racial discrimination]] has occurred against [[White people in Zimbabwe|White Zimbabwean]] communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeslive.co.za/ilive/2012/02/28/zimbabwe-has-its-racists-too-ilive |title=Zimbabwe has its racists too: iLIVE |publisher=Times LIVE |date=2012-02-28 |accessdate=2012-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/comment/4264747/We-will-not-tolerate-racism-except-in-Zimbabwe.html |title=We will not tolerate racism, except in Zimbabwe |publisher=Telegraph |date= 2001-08-12|accessdate=2012-07-31 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newzimbabwe.com/showbiz-5525-Beauty%20queen%20tells%20of%20racist%20abuse/showbiz.aspx |title=Beauty queen tells of racist abuse |publisher=Newzimbabwe.com |date=2010-03-17 |accessdate=2012-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The government has forcefully evicted them from their farms and committed ethnic cleansing against them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Jeff Koinange |url=http://articles.cnn.com/2005-03-30/world/zimbabwe.farmers_1_white-owned-farms-white-farmers-thousands-of-black-laborers?_s=PM:WORLD |title=Tale of two farms in Zimbabwe - CNN |publisher=Articles.cnn.com |date=2005-03-30 |accessdate=2012-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.goldcoast.com.au/article/2008/12/31/35715_editorial-news.html |title=Zimbabwe champions new racism Editorial News &amp;#124; goldcoast.com.au &amp;#124; Gold Coast, Queensland, Australia |publisher=goldcoast.com.au |date=2008-12-31 |accessdate=2012-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since independence, in recent years there has been a surge in violence and racism against the dwindling white community and particularly against white farmers. On 18 September 2010 white people were chased away in droves from participating in the constitutional outreach programme in Harare during the weekend, in which violence and confusion marred the process with similar incidents occurring in Graniteside. In [[Mount Pleasant, Harare|Mount Pleasant]], white families were subjected to a torrent of abuse by suspected Zanu PF supporters who later drove them away shouting racial slurs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zimdiaspora.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=4026:racism-against-white-zimbabweans-reach-shocking-levels&amp;catid=38:travel-tips&amp;Itemid=18|title=Racism against white Zimbabweans reach shocking levels|author=editor|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; There have also been many illegal seizures of farm land owned by white farmers by the government and pro government supporters. Most of the seizures have taken place in Nyamandhalovu and [[Inyati]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/expat/expatnews/7818110/White-farmers-in-Zimbabwe-struggle-against-increasing-violence.html |location=London |work=The Daily Telegraph  | first=Leah | last=Hyslop | title=White farmers in Zimbabwe struggle against increasing violence | date=11 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the beating to death of a prominent white farmer in September 2011, the head of the [[Commercial Farmers' Union]] decried the attack saying its white members continue to be targeted by violence without protection from the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.yahoo.com/zimbabwes-white-farmers-still-target-violence-142808799.html|title=Zimbabwe's white farmers still target of violence|date=5 September 2011|work=Yahoo News|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gregory Stanton|Genocidewatch.org]] has declared the violence against whites in Zimbabwe a stage 5 case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.genocidewatch.org/zimbabwe.html|title=Genocide Watch|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Racism by country]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Africa topic|Racism in}}
{{Racism topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Racism In Africa}}
[[Category:Racism by region|Africa]]
[[Category:Racism in Africa| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>