<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221126014520|1123854897" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="15726826" pageid="15726826" ns="0" title="Racism in Africa"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-26T10:36:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Overview of racism in Africa}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{confusing|date=March 2019}}
{{original research|date=March 2019}}
{{more citations needed|date=June 2015}}
{{Lead too short|date=March 2022}}
}}
&lt;!---Only add contributions related to "Racism in Africa". Information SOLELY about slavery or ethnic conflicts in individual African countries should be moved to their respective articles.---&gt;
'''[[Racism]] in [[Africa]]''' is multi-faceted and it dates back several centuries.
[[File:A Mulolo (Congo) warrior and his wife from the central Congo regions; Bantu.png|thumb|A Mulolo (Congo) warrior and his wife from the central Congo regions; Bantu]]
Ethnic [[Pygmy peoples|pygmy]] populations in [[Central Africa]] suffer from racialized discrimination from [[Bantu peoples|Bantu]] peoples.&lt;ref name="Pygmy1"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.survivalinternational.org/tribes/pygmies/racism|title='Pygmies': Racism|last=International|first=Survival|website=www.survivalinternational.org|language=en|access-date=2018-12-23|archive-date=2018-08-12|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180812213401/https://www.survivalinternational.org/tribes/pygmies/racism|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pygmies and Bantus differ physically and genetically due to long lasting evolutionary segregation until the [[Bantu expansion]] brought them back into close contact.&lt;ref name="Pygmy2"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Quintana-Murci|first1=Lluís|last2=Heyer|first2=Evelyne|last3=Bahuchet|first3=Serge|last4=Froment|first4=Alain|last5=Gessain|first5=Antoine|last6=Hombert|first6=Jean-Marie|last7=Veen|first7=Lolke Van der|last8=Kidd|first8=Judith R.|last9=Kidd|first9=Kenneth K.|date=2009-04-10|title=Inferring the Demographic History of African Farmers and Pygmy Hunter–Gatherers Using a Multilocus Resequencing Data Set|journal=PLOS Genetics|language=en|volume=5|issue=4|pages=e1000448|doi=10.1371/journal.pgen.1000448|issn=1553-7404|pmc=2661362|pmid=19360089}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pygmies have been targeted for [[slavery]] by Bantu populations continuing into the modern age.&lt;ref name="Pygmy1" /&gt; They are frequently [[Ostracism|ostracized]] from participation into the wider society in the various African countries that they live in and are seen as [[Untouchables (caste)|untouchables]].&lt;ref name="Pygmy1" /&gt; Racially-motivated attacks occur on Pygmies including rape and cannibalization.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ohchr.org/en/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=23263&amp;LangID=E|title=UN Experts conclude crimes against humanity and war crimes committed in Kasai, warn against risk of new wave of ethnic violence|last=Lori|first=Brumat|date=26 June 2018|website=United Nations Human Rights|publisher=United Nations Human Rights - Office of the High Commissioner}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.scmp.com/news/world/africa/article/2153725/mass-rape-cannibalism-body-parts-medals-un-team-finds-congo-war|title=Mass rape, cannibalism, body parts as medals: UN team finds Congo war atrocities that 'beggar description'|agency=Reuters|date=4 July 2018|website=South China Morning Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Botswana==
Since the mid-1990s the central government of [[Botswana]] has been trying to move [[Bushmen]] out of the [[Central Kalahari Game Reserve]] even though the national constitution guarantees the Bushmen the right to live there in perpetuity. As of October 2005, the government has resumed its policy of forcing all Bushmen off their lands in the game reserve using armed police and threats of violence or death.&lt;ref name="Daily Telegraph"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2005/10/29/wbot29.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2005/10/29/ixworld.html
|title=Bushmen forced out of desert after living off land for thousands of years |publisher=The Daily Telegraph |accessdate=2005-10-29|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the involuntarily displaced Bushmen live in squalid resettlement camps and some have resorted to [[prostitution]] and [[alcoholism]]. About 250 others remain in the game reserve or have surreptitiously returned to the [[Kalahari]] to resume their independent lifestyles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2004/09/0914_040914_labushmen_2.html|title=African Bushmen Tour U.S. to Fund Fight for Land|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

"How can you have [[Stone Age]] creatures continue to exist in the age of computers?" asked Botswana's president [[Festus Mogae]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.motherjones.com/news/dispatch/2005/01/01_800.html|title=Exiles of the Kalahari|work=Mother Jones|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A report released by the [[United Nations]] Committee on the Elimination of
Racial Discrimination condemns Botswana's treatment of the 'Bushmen' as racist.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.survival-international.org/news/tribes/bushmen/2002 News by tribe |Survival International]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.survival-international.org/news/1454|title=UN condemns Botswana government over Bushman evictions|author=Survival International|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Burundi==
{{Further|Burundian Genocide}}
{{See also|Dominant minority}}

Beginning about 1880, [[Catholicism|Roman Catholic]] missionaries arrived in the Great Lakes region. Later, when German forces occupied the area during [[World War I]], the conflict and efforts for Catholic [[Religious conversion|conversion]] became more pronounced. As the Tutsi resisted conversion, the missionaries found success only among the [[Hutu]]. In an effort to reward conversion, the colonial government confiscated traditionally Tutsi land and reassigned it to Hutu tribes, igniting a conflict that has lasted into the 21st century.&lt;ref name="Berg"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.kulanu.org/tutsi/jews-africa.php|first=Irwin M.|last=Berg|publisher=Kulanu  Highlights|title=Jews in Central Africa|accessdate=2010-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The area was ruled as a colony by [[Germany]] (before [[World War I]]) and [[Belgium]]. Because Tutsis had been the tradiitional governing elite, both colonial powers kept this system and allowed only the Tutsi to be educated and only they could participate in the colonial government. Such discriminatory policies engendered resentment.

When the Belgians took over the colony, they believed the colony could be better governed if they continued to identify the different populations. In the 1920s, they required people to identify with a particular ethnic group and classified them in censuses. European colonists viewed Africans in general as children who needed to be guided, but noted the Tutsi to be the ruling culture in Rwanda-Burundi. {{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} In 1959, Belgium reversed its stance and allowed the majority Hutu to assume control of the government through universal elections after independence. This partly reflected internal Belgian domestic politics, who later saw the discrimination against the Hutu majority as similar to oppression within Belgium  suffered from the Flemish-Walloon conflict. They saw the democratization and empowerment of the Hutu as a just response to the Tutsi domination. The Belgian policies wavered and flip-flopped considerably during this period leading up to [[Burundi#Independence and civil war|independence of Burundi]] and [[History of Rwanda#Strife and independence|Rwanda]].

The Hutu majority had [[Rwanda Revolution|revolted]] against the Tutsi but was unable to take power. Tutsis fled and created exile communities outside Rwanda in Uganda and Tanzania. Since the nation's independence, more extremist Tutsi came to power and oppressed the Hutus, especially those who were educated.&lt;ref name="Michael Bowen 1972, p. 49"&gt;Michael Bowen, ''Passing by;: The United States and genocide in Burundi'', 1972, (Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1973), p. 49&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="René Lemarchand 1974"&gt;René Lemarchand, ''Selective genocide in Burundi'' (Report - Minority Rights Group; no. 20, 1974)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Rene Lemarchand 1996"&gt;Rene Lemarchand, ''Burundi: Ethnic Conflict and Genocide'' (New York: Woodrow Wilson Center and [[Cambridge University Press]], 1996)
*Edward L. Nyankanzi, ''Genocide: Rwanda and Burundi'' (Schenkman Books, 1998)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;Christian P. Scherrer, ''Genocide and crisis in Central Africa: conflict roots, mass violence, and regional war''; foreword by Robert Melson. Westport, Conn.: Praeger, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="usip.org"&gt;Weissman, Stephen R. "[http://www.usip.org/pubs/peaceworks/pwks22.html Preventing Genocide in Burundi Lessons from International Diplomacy]", [[United States Institute of Peace]]&lt;/ref&gt; Their actions led to the deaths of up to 200,000 Hutus.&lt;ref name="allan.stam.googlepages.com"&gt;[http://allan.stam.googlepages.com/Rwandaoped0405042.pdf Christian Davenport and Allan Stam, "Rwanda 1994: Genocide + Politicide"]&lt;/ref&gt; Overt discrimination from the colonial period was continued by different Rwandan and Burundian governments, including identity cards that distinguished Tutsi and Hutu.

The Belgian-sponsored [[Rwandan monarchy|Tutsi monarchy]] survived until 1959, when [[Kigeli V of Rwanda|Kigeli V]] was exiled from the colony (then called [[Ruanda-Urundi]]). In Burundi, Tutsis, who are the minority, maintained control of the government and military.

In [[Burundi]], [[Ikiza|a campaign of genocide]] was conducted against the country's Hutu population in 1972,&lt;ref name="usip.org"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Michael Bowen, ''Passing by;: The United States and genocide in Burundi'', 1972, (Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1973), 49 pp&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;René Lemarchand, ''Selective genocide in Burundi'' (Report - Minority Rights Group; no. 20, 1974), 36 pp.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rene Lemarchand, ''Burundi: Ethnic Conflict and Genocide'' (New York: Woodrow Wilson Center and [[Cambridge University Press]], 1996), 232 pp.
*Edward L. Nyankanzi, ''Genocide: Rwanda and Burundi'' (Schenkman Books, 1998), 198 pp.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Christian P. Scherrer, ''Genocide and crisis in Central Africa: conflict roots, mass violence, and regional war''; foreword by Robert Melson. Westport, Conn.: Praeger, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; and an estimated 100,000 Hutus died.&lt;ref name="allan.stam.googlepages.com"/&gt; In 1993, Burundi's first democratically elected president, [[Melchior Ndadaye]], who was Hutu, was believed to be assassinated by Tutsi officers, as was the person constitutionally entitled to succeed him.&lt;ref&gt;International Commission of Inquiry for Burundi: Final Report. Part III: Investigation of the Assassination. Conclusions at [http://www.usip.org/library/tc/doc/reports/burundi_coi/burundi_coi1996pt3.html#VII USIP.org]&lt;/ref&gt; This sparked [[1993 ethnic violence in Burundi|a period of civil strife]] between Hutu political structures and the Tutsi military, in which an estimated 500,000 Burundians died.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}} There were many mass killings of Tutsis and moderate Hutus; these events were deemed genocide by the United Nations International Commission of Inquiry for Burundi.&lt;ref name=ICIBFR-496&gt;International Commission of Inquiry for Burundi (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ethiopia==
{{main|Racism in Ethiopia}}
{{See also|Shanqella}}

Racism in [[Ethiopia]] has traditionally been directed at the country's [[Nilotic peoples|Nilotic]] ethnic minorities, as well as other individuals with similarly pronounced "[[Negroid]]" physical features. Collectively, these groups are locally known as [[Shanqella]] or ''barya'', derogatory terms originally denoting slave descent, irrespective of the individual's family history.&lt;ref name="Suhlig"&gt;{{cite book|last=Uhlig|first=Siegbert|title=Encyclopaedia Aethiopica: A-C, Volume 1|year=2003|publisher=Otto Harrassowitz Verlag|isbn=3447047461|pages=489–490|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=nobesFx6E7oC}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Thomson"&gt;{{cite book|last=Thomson|first=Blair|title=Ethiopia: The Country That Cut Off Its Head: A Diary of the Revolution|year=1975|publisher=Robson Books|isbn=0903895501|page=117|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Q7sJAQAAIAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, the Shanqella constituted most of the slave labour in the ruling local [[Afro-Asiatic languages|Afro-Asiatic]] societies.&lt;ref name="Cidsaeeet"&gt;{{cite book|last=Congrès international des sciences anthropologiques et ethnologiques, Pierre Champion|title=VIe [i.e. Sixième] Congrès international des sciences anthropologiques et ethnologiques, Paris, 30 juillet-6 août 1960: Ethnologie. 2 v|year=1963|publisher=Musée de l'homme|page=589|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=EksRAQAAMAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Abyssinians ([[Habesha people|Habesha]] highlanders) were also noted as having actively hunted the Shanqella during the 19th century.&lt;ref name="Rsfisher"&gt;{{cite book|last=Fisher|first=Richard Swainson|title=The Book of the World|year=1852|page=622|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ik4BAAAAQAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the abolition of the slave trade in the 1940s, the freed Shanqella and ''barya'' were typically employed as unskilled labour.&lt;ref name="Cidsaeeet"/&gt; Racial discrimination against the ''barya'' or Shanqella communities in Ethiopia still exists, affecting access to political and social opportunities and resources.&lt;ref name="Suhlig"/&gt;

Traditionally, racism against perceived ''barya'' transcended class and remained in effect regardless of social position or parentage. As a result, former President of Ethiopia [[Mengistu Haile Mariam]] was virtually absent from the country's controlled press in the first few weeks of his seizure of power. He also consciously avoided making public appearances, here too on the belief that his "Negroid" appearance would not sit well with the country's deposed political elite, particularly the [[Amhara people|Amhara]].&lt;ref name="Nwswket"&gt;{{cite book|title=Newsweek, Volume 85, Issues 1-8|year=1975|publisher=Newsweek|page=13|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=KibkAAAAMAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; By contrast, Mengistu's rise to prominence was hailed by the southern Shanqella groups as a personal victory, with one of their own having made good.&lt;ref name="Thomson"/&gt;

Although other populations in Ethiopia have faced varying degrees of discrimination, little of that adversity has by contrast been on account of racial differences. It is instead more typically rooted in disparities in class and competition for economic status. The often socio-economically disadvantaged [[Oromo people|Oromo]] and [[Gurage people|Gurage]] are thus not considered by the highlander groups as being racially ''barya'', owing to their similar physical features and common Afro-Asiatic ancestry.&lt;ref name="Cidsaeeet"/&gt;

In terms of traditional perceptions, the Shanqella likewise racially contrast themselves from the Afro-Asiatic populations. The Anywaa ([[Anuak people|Anuak]]) Nilotes of southern Ethiopia consequently regard the Amhara, Oromo, [[Tigray-Tigrinya people|Tigray]] and other Afro-Asiatic groups collectively as ''gaala'' in contradistinction to themselves.&lt;ref name="Kfukui"&gt;{{cite book|last=Katsuyoshi Fukui, Eisei Kurimoto, Masayoshi Shigeta|title=Ethiopia in Broader Perspective: Papers of the XIIIth International Conference of Ethiopian Studies, Kyoto, 12-17 December 1997, Volume 2|year=1997|publisher=Shokado Book Sellers|isbn=487974977X|page=804|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ILRyAAAAMAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ivory Coast==
In 2001, [[Ivory Coast]] saw a resurgence in ethnic hatred and religious intolerance.  In addition to the many victims among the various tribes of the northern and southern regions of the country that have perished in the ongoing conflict, foreigners residing or visiting Ivory Coast have also been subjected to violent attacks. According to a report by Human Rights Watch in 2001, the Ivory Coast government was guilty of fanning ethnic hatred for its own political ends.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/1512884.stm Ivory Coast "fanning ethnic hatred"]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, the [[Congrès Panafricain des Jeunes et des Patriotes|Young Patriots]] of Abidjan, a strongly [[nationalist]] organisation, rallied by the state media, plundered possessions of foreign nationals in [[Abidjan]]. Rapes and beatings of persons of European and Lebanese descent followed. No deaths were reported. Thousands of expatriates and white or ethnic Lebanese Ivorians fled the country. The attacks drew international condemnation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/11/19/wapp19.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2004/11/19/ixnewstop.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071113163822/http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/11/19/wapp19.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2004/11/19/ixnewstop.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=13 November 2007|title=News|work=Telegraph.co.uk|access-date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/newsitems/200411/s1242699.htm Europeans flee Ivory Coast violence. 13 November 2004. ABC News Online]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Libya==
{{main|Racism in Libya}}
&lt;!-- Slave trade? --&gt;

== Liberia ==
According to Article 27_b of the [[Constitution of Liberia|Liberian Constitution]], Liberian nationality is limited to 'persons who are Negroes or of Negro descent'.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Tannenbaum|first1=Jessie|last2=Valcke|first2=Anthony|last3=McPherson|first3=Andrew|date=2009-05-01|title=Analysis of the Aliens and Nationality Law of the Republic of Liberia|location=Rochester, NY|ssrn=1795122}}&lt;/ref&gt; (see also [[Liberian nationality law]]).

==Mauritania==
{{Main|Slavery in Mauritania}}
{{further|Slavery in modern Africa}}
[[Slavery in Mauritania]] persists despite its abolition in 1980 and mostly affects the descendants of black Africans abducted into [[slavery]] who now live in [[Mauritania]] as "black [[Moors]]" or ''[[haratin]]'' and who partially still serve the "white Moors", or ''bidhan'', as slaves. The practice of slavery in Mauritania is most dominant within the traditional upper class of the Moors. For centuries, the ''haratin'' lower class, mostly poor black Africans living in rural areas, have been considered natural slaves by these Moors. Social attitudes have changed among most urban Moors, but in rural areas, the ancient divide remains.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L18334379.htm|title=Thomson Reuters Foundation|author=Thomson Reuters Foundation|access-date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ruling ''bidanes'' are descendants of the [[Sanhaja]] [[Berber people|Berbers]] and [[Beni Ḥassān]] Arab tribes who emigrated to northwest Africa and present-day [[Western Sahara]] and Mauritania during the [[Middle Ages]]. Many descendants of the Beni Ḥassān tribes today still adhere to the [[supremacist]] ideology of their ancestors, which has caused the oppression, discrimination and even enslavement of other groups in Mauritania.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?ReportId=70522|title=IRIN Africa - MAURITANIA: Fair elections haunted by racial imbalance - Mauritania - Governance - Human Rights|work=IRINnews|access-date=17 June 2015|date=2007-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to some estimates, as many as 600,000 black Mauritanians, or 20% of the population, are still enslaved, many of them used as [[bonded labour]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/specials/1458_abolition/page4.shtml|title=BBC World Service - The Abolition season on BBC World Service|access-date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Slavery in Mauritania was criminalized in August 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6938032.stm|title=BBC NEWS - Africa - Mauritanian MPs pass slavery law|access-date=17 June 2015|date=2007-08-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Namibia==
{{Main|Herero and Namaqua genocide}}
[[File:Photograph of Herero chief Samuel Maharero.jpg|thumb|a photo of Herero chief Samuel Maharero]]
On 12 January 1904, the [[Herero people]], led by [[Samuel Maharero]], rebelled against [[Germany|German]] [[German colonial empire|colonial rule]]. In August, German general [[Lothar von Trotha]] defeated the Herero in the [[Battle of Waterberg]] and drove them into the desert of [[Omaheke]], where most of them died of thirst. In October, the [[Nama people]] also rebelled against the Germans, suffering a similar fate.

The violence eventually led to a genocide of the Herero and Nama people by the Germans, known as the [[Herero and Namaqua genocide]]. In total, 24,000 to 100,000 Herero and 10,000 Nama died.&lt;ref&gt;Colonial Genocide and Reparations Claims in the 21st Century: The Socio-Legal Context of Claims under International Law by the Herero against Germany for Genocide in Namibia, 1904-1908 (PSI Reports) by Jeremy Sarkin-Hughes&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Empire, Colony, Genocide: Conquest, Occupation and Subaltern Resistance in World History (War and Genocide) (War and Genocide) (War and Genocide) A. Dirk Moses -page 296(From Conquest to Genocide: Colonial Rule in German Southwest Africa and German East Africa. 296, (29). Dominik J. Schaller)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Imperialist Imagination: German Colonialism and Its Legacy (Social History, Popular Culture, and Politics in Germany) by Sara L. Friedrichsmeyer, Sara Lennox, and Susanne M. Zantop page 87 University of Michigan Press 1999&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Walter Nuhn 1904"&gt;Walter Nuhn: ''Sturm über Südwest. Der Hereroaufstand von 1904.'' Bernard &amp; Graefe-Verlag, Koblenz 1989. {{ISBN|3-7637-5852-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marie-Aude Baronian, Stephan Besser, Yolande Jansen, "Diaspora and memory: figures of displacement in contemporary literature, arts and politics", [https://books.google.com/books?id=LItBN2keNpQC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;dq=Herero+starvation pg. 33] Rodopi, 2007,&lt;/ref&gt; The genocide was characterized by a high number of deaths from starvation and thirst; the Herero who fled the violence were prevented from returning from the [[Namib Desert]]. Some sources also claim that the German colonial army systematically poisoned desert wells.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Totten, William S. Parsons, Israel W. Charny, "Century of genocide: critical essays and eyewitness accounts" [https://books.google.com/books?id=5Ef8Hrx8Cd0C&amp;pg=PA51&amp;dq=Herero+Poisoned+wells pg. 51], Routledge, 2004,&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=kroll&gt;Dan Kroll, "Securing our water supply: protecting a vulnerable resource", PennWell Corp/University of Michigan Press, pg. 22&lt;/ref&gt; The genocide took place between 1904 and 1907 in [[German South-West Africa]] (now modern day [[Namibia]]), during the [[Herero Wars]].

In 1926, except for archive copies, records of the genocide were withdrawn and destroyed following a decision of the then Legislative Assembly.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.namibian.com.na/index.php?id=28&amp;tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D=54620&amp;no_cache=1, ‘Stolen’ Blue Book was just misplaced] 23.04.2009
 accessed 17 Dec 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Gewald, Jan-Bart |title=Herereo Heroes: A Socio-Political History of the Herero of Namibia 1890-1923 |publisher=Ohio University Press |year=1999 |page=242 |quote="Of late it has been claimed that the infamous 'Blue Book' which detailed the treatment of Africans in GSWA was little more than a piece of propaganda put about to further South Africa's territorial ambitions and Britain's position at the negotiating table. Granted that the book was used to strengthen Britain's position vis-a-vis Germany, it must however be borne in mind that the bulk of the evidence contained in the 'Blue Book' is little more than the literal translation of German texts published at the time which were the findings of a German commission of inquiry into the effects of corporal punishment." Thus, when the Blue Book was withdrawn from the public after Germany and England came to an agreement about how to share access to GSWA minerals, this was not censorship; it was just business}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Survivors, majority of whom were women and children, were eventually put in [[concentration camp]]s, such as the one at [[Shark Island Concentration Camp|Shark Island]], where the German authorities forced them to work as slaves for German military and settlers. All prisoners were categorized into groups fit and unfit for work, and pre-printed death certificates indicating "death by exhaustion following privation" were issued.&lt;ref&gt;The colonising camera: photographs in the making of Namibian history Wolfram Hartmann, Jeremy Silvester, Patricia Hayes, page 118, University of Cape Town Press, 1999&lt;/ref&gt; The British government published their widely known account of the German genocide of the Nama and Herero peoples in 1918.&lt;ref&gt;Jan-Bart Gewald, Jeremy Silvester, "Words Cannot Be Found: German Colonial Rule in Namibia : An Annotated Reprint of the 1918 Blue Book (Sources on African History, 1)", Brill Academic Publishers, annotated edition (1 June 2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Herero died later of disease, overwork and malnutrition.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=The Dark Side of Democracy: Explaining Ethnic Cleansing |last=Michael Mann |page=105 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Hitler's African Victims: The German Army Massacres of Black French Soldiers in 1940 |page=83 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Camps, such as that in Windhoek, had mortality rates as high as 61%&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=The continuities of German history: nation, religion, and race across the Long Nineteenth Century |last=Helmut Walser Smith |page=199 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The mortality rate in the camps was 45% in 1908.&lt;ref name="HBV"&gt;''Hitler's Black Victims: The Historical Experiences of European Blacks, Africans and African Americans During the Nazi Era'' (Crosscurrents in African American History) by [[Clarence Lusane]], page 50-51 Routledge 2002&lt;/ref&gt; The death rates are calculated to be between 69% and 74%.&lt;ref&gt;Steinmetz, George, ''The devil's handwriting'', pp 196-216&lt;/ref&gt;

Food in the camps was extremely scarce, consisting of rice with no additions.&lt;ref&gt;The practice of war Production, Reproduction and Communication of Armed Violence Edited by Aparna Rao, Michael Bollig and Monika Böck, page 92, Berghahn Books; 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Shootings, hangings and beatings were common,&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Rethinking resistance: revolt and violence in African history |page=282 |last=Klaas van Walraven |publisher=Brill Academic Publishers |year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[sjambok]] was used by guards who treated the forced labourers harshly. Medical experiments were performed on the Herero and Nama people by the Germans, similar to those performed on the [[European Jews]] during the [[Holocaust]]. [[Eugen Fischer]], a German anthropologist, came to the concentration camps to conduct medical experiments on race,&lt;ref name="Mamdani, p. 12"&gt;Mamdani, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; using children of Herero people and [[mulatto]] children of Herero women and German men as test subjects.&lt;ref name="Mamdani, p. 12"/&gt; Other experiments were made by Dr Bofinger, who injected Herero that were suffering from scurvy with various substances including arsenic and opium; afterwards he researched the effects of these substances by performing autopsies on the dead bodies&lt;ref&gt;The Kaiser's Holocaust: Germany's Forgotten Genocide and the Colonial Roots of Nazism, page 225, Casper Erichsen, [[David Olusoga]],  Faber and Faber 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

With the closure of concentration camps, all surviving Herero were distributed as labourers for settlers in the German colony, and from then on, all Herero over the age of seven were forced to wear a metal disc with their labour registration number,&lt;ref name="Mamdani, p. 12"/&gt; and banned from owning land or cattle, a necessity in pastoral society.&lt;ref&gt;Production, Reproduction and Communication of Armed Violence Aparna Rao, Michael Bollig and Monika Böck, page 89, Berghahn Books 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1985, the [[United Nations]]' [[Sub-Commission on the Promotion and Protection of Human Rights#Whitaker Report|Whitaker Report]] classified the aftermath as an attempt to exterminate the Herero and Nama peoples of [[South-West Africa]], and therefore one of the earliest attempts at genocide in the 20th century. The German government recognised and apologised for the events in 2004, but has ruled out financial compensation or land reparation for the victims' descendants.&lt;ref name="BBC08142004"&gt;{{cite news|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/3565938.stm|title = Germany admits Namibia genocide|date = 2004-08-14|access-date = 2008-04-23|work = [[BBC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, there was only minor media attention in Germany on this matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| first=Alexander| last=Krabbe| url=http://english.ohmynews.com/articleview/article_view.asp?menu=c10400&amp;no=180988&amp;rel_no=1| title=Remembering Germany's African Genocide| work=[[OhmyNews International]] | access-date=2004-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

About 4,000 commercial land owners, mostly whites, own over 50% of the arable land across the country despite a [[Land reform in Namibia|land reform process]] undertaken by the Namibian government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3242829.stm Namibians plan white farm grabs] in [[BBC News]], 5 November 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|4pdVrQjuzvE}} [[Al Jazeera]], 2012&lt;/ref&gt; When the country was known as [[South West Africa]], [[White Namibians]] enjoyed a highly privileged position due to [[South Africa under apartheid|apartheid laws]] enforcing strict segregation and white domination.&lt;ref&gt;[https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D71E3CF935A15751C1A96E948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=1 Amid Namibia's White Opulence, Majority Rule Isn't So Scary Now] in the [[New York Times]], 26 December 1988&lt;/ref&gt;

==Niger==
[[File:Diffa in Niger.svg|thumb|Diffa in Niger]]
In October 2006, [[Niger]] announced that it would deport to Chad the "[[Diffa Arabs]]", [[Arabs]] living in the Diffa region of eastern Niger.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6087048.stm|title=BBC NEWS - Africa - Niger starts mass Arab expulsions|access-date=17 June 2015|date=2006-10-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their population numbered about 150,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L25138454.htm|title=Thomson Reuters Foundation|author=Thomson Reuters Foundation|access-date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the government was rounding up Arabs in preparation for the deportation, two girls died, reportedly after fleeing government forces, and three women suffered miscarriages. Niger's government eventually suspended their controversial decision to deport the Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6081416.stm|title=BBC NEWS - Africa - Niger's Arabs to fight expulsion|access-date=17 June 2015|date=2006-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/refworld/rwmain?docid=469638881e|title=Refworld - The Leader in Refugee Decision Support|author=United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|work=Refworld|access-date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Niger, while the practice of [[slavery]] was outlawed in 2003, a study has found that more than 800,000 people are still slaves, almost 8% of the population.&lt;ref name="The Shackles of Slavery in Niger"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://abcnews.go.com/International/Story?id=813618&amp;page=1|title=The Shackles of Slavery in Niger|work=ABC News|access-date=17 June 2015|date=2006-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/4250709.stm Born to be a slave in Niger] By Hilary Andersson, BBC Africa Correspondent, Niger&lt;/ref&gt; Slavery dates back centuries in Niger and was criminalised after five years of lobbying by [[Anti-Slavery International]] and Nigerian human-rights group, Timidria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0310/p07s01-woaf.html|title=On the way to freedom, Niger's slaves stuck in limbo|author=The Christian Science Monitor|journal=The Christian Science Monitor|access-date=17 June 2015|date=2005-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Descent-based slavery, where generations of the same family are born into [[debt bondage|bondage]], is traditionally practiced by at least four of Niger's eight ethnic groups. The slave masters are mostly from the lighter-skinned [[nomadic]] tribes: the [[Tuareg people|Tuareg]], [[Fulani]], [[Toubou]] and Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smithsonianmagazine.com/issues/2005/september/bondage.php?page=3|title=History, Travel, Arts, Science, People, Places - Smithsonian|access-date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is especially rife among the warlike Tuareg, located in the wild deserts of north and west Niger, who roam near the borders with Mali and Algeria. In the region of Say on the right bank of the river Niger, it is estimated that three-quarters of the population around 1904&amp;ndash;1905 was composed of slaves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.antislavery.org/homepage/resources/PDF/Full%20English%20Slavery%20in%20Niger.pdf|title=Anti-Slavery|author=dotMailer|access-date=17 June 2015|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090306073532/http://www.antislavery.org/homepage/resources/PDF/Full%20English%20Slavery%20in%20Niger.pdf|archive-date=6 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, the Tuareg swelled the ranks of their black slaves by conducting war raids into other peoples’ lands. War was the main source of supply of slaves, although many were bought at slave markets, run mostly by indigenous peoples.&lt;ref name="The Shackles of Slavery in Niger"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=53497|title=IRIN Africa - NIGER: Slavery - an unbroken chain - Niger - Gender Issues - Human Rights|work=IRINnews|access-date=17 June 2015|date=2005-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Republic of the Congo==
In the [[Republic of Congo]], where Pygmies make up 2% of the population, many Pygmies live as [[slaves]] to [[Bantu peoples|Bantu]] masters. The nation is deeply stratified between these two major ethnic groups.  The Pygmy slaves belong from birth to their Bantu masters in a relationship that the Bantus call a time-honored tradition.  Even though the Pygmies are responsible for much of the hunting, fishing and manual labor in jungle villages, Pygmies and Bantus alike say Pygmies are often paid at the master's whim; in cigarettes, used clothing, or even nothing at all. As a result of pressure from [[UNICEF]] and human-rights activists, a law that would grant special protections to the Pygmy people is awaiting a vote by the Congo parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.newsobserver.com/110/story/552528.html |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090228160138/http://newsobserver.com/110/story/552528.html |archivedate=2009-02-28 |title=Congo's Pygmies live as slaves |work=The News &amp; Observer |first=Katie |last=Thomas |date=March 12, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1997/06/16/world/as-the-world-intrudes-pygmies-feel-endangered.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm |title=As the World Intrudes, Pygmies Feel Endangered |author=Nicholas D. Kristof |date=June 16, 1997 |work=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rwanda==
{{Further|Rwandan Genocide}}
{{See also|Dominant minority}}

Beginning about 1880, [[Catholicism|Roman Catholic]] missionaries arrived in the Great Lakes region. Later, when German forces occupied the area during [[World War I]], the conflict and efforts for Catholic [[Religious conversion|conversion]] became more pronounced. As the Tutsi resisted conversion, the missionaries found success only among the [[Hutu]]. In an effort to reward conversion, the colonial government confiscated traditionally Tutsi land and reassigned it to Hutu tribes, igniting a conflict that has lasted into the 21st century.&lt;ref name="Berg"/&gt;

The area was ruled as a colony by [[Germany]] (before [[World War I]]) and [[Belgium]]. Because Tutsis had been the tradiitional governing elite, both colonial powers kept this system and allowed only the Tutsi to be educated and only they could participate in the colonial government. Such discriminatory policies engendered resentment.

When the Belgians took over the colony, they believed the colony could be better governed if they continued to identify the different populations. In the 1920s, they required people to identify with a particular ethnic group and classified them in censuses. European colonists viewed Africans in general as children who needed to be guided, but noted the Tutsi to be the ruling culture in Rwanda-Burundi. {{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} In 1959, Belgium reversed its stance and allowed the majority Hutu to assume control of the government through universal elections after independence. This partly reflected internal Belgian domestic politics, who later saw the discrimination against the Hutu majority as similar to oppression within Belgium  suffered from the Flemish-Walloon conflict. They saw the democratization and empowerment of the Hutu as a just response to the Tutsi domination. The Belgian policies wavered and flip-flopped considerably during this period leading up to [[Burundi#Independence and civil war|independence of Burundi]] and [[History of Rwanda#Strife and independence|Rwanda]].

The Hutu majority had [[Rwanda Revolution|revolted]] against the Tutsi but was unable to take power. Tutsis fled and created exile communities outside Rwanda in Uganda and Tanzania. Since the nation's independence, more extremist Tutsi came to power and oppressed the Hutus, especially those who were educated.&lt;ref name="Michael Bowen 1972, p. 49"/&gt;&lt;ref name="René Lemarchand 1974"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Rene Lemarchand 1996"/&gt;&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="usip.org"/&gt; Their actions led to the deaths of up to 200,000 Hutus.&lt;ref name="allan.stam.googlepages.com"/&gt; Overt discrimination from the colonial period was continued by different Rwandan and Burundian governments, including identity cards that distinguished Tutsi and Hutu.

The Belgian-sponsored [[Rwandan monarchy|Tutsi monarchy]] survived until 1959, when [[Kigeli V of Rwanda|Kigeli V]] was exiled from the colony (then called [[Ruanda-Urundi]]). In Rwanda, the political power was transferred from the minority Tutsi to the majority Hutu.&lt;ref&gt;Adekunle, Julius. 2007. Culture and Customs of Rwanda. P.17&lt;/ref&gt;

In Rwanda, a Tutsi rebel group, the [[Rwandan Patriotic Front]], invaded Rwanda from Uganda, which started a civil war against Rwanda's Hutu government in 1990. A peace agreement was signed, but violence erupted again, culminating in the [[Rwandan Genocide]] of 1994, when Hutu extremists killed&lt;ref name="PBS"&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/evil/etc/slaughter.html| title = Timeline of the genocide| accessdate = 2006-12-30| publisher = PBS}}&lt;/ref&gt; an estimated 800,000 Rwandans, mostly Tutsis.&lt;ref name="BBC"&gt;{{cite news | title = How the genocide happened | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/1288230.stm | publisher = BBC| date = 2004-04-01| accessdate = 2006-10-31}} {{Dead link|date=April 2014|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; About 30% of the [[Great Lakes Twa|Twa]] population of Rwanda were also killed.&lt;ref name="irin"&gt;{{cite news | title = Minorities Under Siege: Pygmies today in Africa | url = http://www.irinnews.org/webspecials/pygmy/52529.asp | publisher = UN Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs| year = 2006| accessdate = 2006-12-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Somalia==
The [[Somali Bantu]] ethnic minority face significant [[stigmatization]] in Somali society due to their differing physical appearance and ancestry from the [[Cushitic]]-origin majority of Somalia. Racialized [[epithets]] targeted at the Somali Bantu community exist such as 'adoon' (slave) similar in connotation to the Arabic term [[abeed]]. The [[marginalization]] of the Somali Bantu community is primarily based on [[racial|ethnoracial]] factors, unlike the marginalization of the [[Madhiban]] and other Somali-origin minorities which is primarily based on their status as a [[socially constructed]] [[caste]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Eno|first1=Mohamed A.|last2=Kusow|first2=Abdi M.|date=2014-01-01|title=Racial and caste prejudice in Somalia|url=https://journals.co.za/content/aa_joss/1/2/EJC167583|journal=Journal of Somali Studies|language=en|volume=1|issue=2|issn=2056-5674}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ethnic [[Somalis]] and populations of [[Bantu peoples|Bantu]] stock are genetically divergent.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Hodgson|first1=Jason A.|last2=Mulligan|first2=Connie J.|last3=Al-Meeri|first3=Ali|last4=Raaum|first4=Ryan L.|date=2014-06-12|title=Early Back-to-Africa Migration into the Horn of Africa |journal=PLOS Genetics |volume=10|issue=6|pages=e1004393|doi=10.1371/journal.pgen.1004393 |pmc=4055572|pmid=24921250}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Schlebusch|first1=Carina M.|last2=Malmström|first2=Helena|last3=Günther|first3=Torsten|last4=Sjödin|first4=Per|last5=Coutinho|first5=Alexandra|last6=Edlund|first6=Hanna|last7=Munters|first7=Arielle R.|last8=Vicente|first8=Mário|last9=Steyn|first9=Maryna|date=2017-11-03|title=Southern African ancient genomes estimate modern human divergence to 350,000 to 260,000 years ago|journal=Science|language=en|volume=358|issue=6363|pages=652–655|doi=10.1126/science.aao6266|issn=0036-8075|pmid=28971970|bibcode=2017Sci...358..652S|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racially-motivated attacks on Somali Bantus have occurred.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.radiodalsan.com/sawirro-nin-muqdisho-lagu-dilay-kadibna-la-gubay/|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180921060220/https://www.radiodalsan.com/sawirro-nin-muqdisho-lagu-dilay-kadibna-la-gubay/|url-status=dead|archive-date=2018-09-21|title=Dalsan Warar Sugan|website=www.radiodalsan.com|language=en-US|access-date=2018-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.caasimada.net/muqdisho-nin-kasoo-jeeda-qabiil-laga-awood-badan-yahay-oo-loo-dilay-loona-gubay-gabar-uu-guursaday/|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180921060057/https://www.caasimada.net/muqdisho-nin-kasoo-jeeda-qabiil-laga-awood-badan-yahay-oo-loo-dilay-loona-gubay-gabar-uu-guursaday/|url-status=dead|archive-date=2018-09-21|title=Caasimada|website=www.caasimada.net|date=2018-09-21|access-date=2018-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Journalists who bring attention to discrimination against Somali Bantus have suffered from death threats and some have fled the country as a result.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2021-11-16|title=No where to run: Journalists in Jowhar face new threats from state officials|url=https://hornobserver.com:443/articles/1451/No-where-to-run-Journalists-in-Jowhar-face-new-threats-from-state-officials|access-date=2021-12-19|website=hornobserver.com|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2020-02-13|title=Somali journalists targeted for speaking out|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2020/02/somali-journalists-targeted-for-speaking-out/|access-date=2021-12-19|website=Amnesty International|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Transitional federal parliament, Republic of Somalia#Composition|4.5 parliamentary formula]] under the [[Transitional federal government, Republic of Somalia|Transitional Federal Government]] has been criticized as a form of legislative [[apartheid]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Bantu-Jareer Somalis : unearthing apartheid in the Horn of Africa|last=Eno|first=Mohamed A.|date=2008|publisher=Adonis &amp; Abbey Publishers|isbn=978-1905068944|edition= 1st|location=London, UK|oclc=638660234}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==South Africa==
{{main|Racism in South Africa}}
{{See also|South African Human Rights Commission}}

Racism is still prevalent in [[South Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.univie.ac.at/ecco/stichproben/Nr6_Interview_Moleah.pdf|title=Interview with Prof. Alfred Tokollo Moleah, South African Ambassador to Vienna |last=Englert|first=Birgit|publisher=Universität Wien|access-date=2008-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The end of [[South Africa under apartheid|apartheid]] might have removed the legal framework allowing [[institutionalised racism]], however, racism in South Africa both predates and encompasses more than just the institutionalised racism of apartheid.

===Colonialism===
The establishment of the [[Dutch East India Company]] settlement at the [[Cape of Good Hope]] in 1652 brought with it the established slave labor practices of the company.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.iziko.org.za/sh/resources/slavery/slavery_world.html|title=Slavery at the Cape|publisher=Iziko Museums of Cape Town|access-date=2008-11-19|archive-date=2008-09-16|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080916133751/http://www.iziko.org.za/sh/resources/slavery/slavery_world.html|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these slaves were imported from the company's more established settlements in India and the East Indies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.anc.org.za/ancdocs/history/solidarity/indiasa3.html|title=Indian Slaves in South Africa|publisher=[[African National Congress]]|access-date=2008-11-19 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20080622023927/http://www.anc.org.za/ancdocs/history/solidarity/indiasa3.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archive-date = 2008-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Slavery in South Africa was officially [[Abolitionism|abolished]] in 1833 with the [[Slavery Abolition Act 1833|Slavery Abolition Act]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/huk-1833act.htm|title=Slavery Abolition Act 1833|date=1833-10-29|publisher=Houses of Parliament, Palace of Westminster, London.|access-date=2008-11-19|archive-date=2008-04-29|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080429205055/http://www.anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/huk-1833act.htm|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are many examples of racism and discriminatory practices during the colonial period, such as the allocation of rations during the [[Siege of Ladysmith]]
{{quote|For Whites—Biscuit, 1/4 lb.; Maize meal, 3 oz.&lt;br&gt;
For Indians and [[Kaffir (racial term)|Kaffirs]]—Maize meal, 8 oz.&lt;br&gt;
Europeans—Fresh meat, 1 lb.&lt;br&gt;
Kaffirs—Fresh meat, 1-1/4 lbs. (Chiefly [[Horse meat|horseflesh]].)&lt;br&gt;
For White men—Coffee or tea, 1/12 oz.; pepper, 1/64 oz.; salt, 1/3 oz.; sugar, 1 oz.; mustard, 1/20 oz.; Vinegar, 1/12 gill.&lt;br&gt;
For Indians—a little rice.| H. W. Nevinson&lt;ref&gt;{{Gutenberg|no=16603|name=Ladysmith, The Diary of a Siege by Henry W. Nevinson}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Apartheid racism===
{{See also|South Africa under apartheid}}
Apartheid (Afrikaans pronunciation: {{IPA-af|aˈpartɦɛit}}; an Afrikaans word meaning "separateness", or "the state of being apart", literally "apart-hood") was a system of racial segregation in South Africa enforced through legislation by the National Party (NP), the governing party from 1948 to 1994. Under apartheid, the rights, associations, and movements of the majority black inhabitants and other ethnic groups were curtailed, and white minority rule was maintained. Apartheid was developed after World War II by the [[Afrikaners|Afrikaner]]-dominated National Party and Broederbond organisations. The ideology was also enforced in South West Africa, which was administered by South Africa under a League of Nations mandate (revoked in 1966 via United Nations Resolution 2145), until it gained independence as Namibia in 1990. By extension, the term is currently used for forms of systematic segregation established by the state authority in a country against the social and civil rights of a certain group of citizens due to ethnic prejudices.

=== Post-Apartheid racism ===

{{Main|Racism in South Africa#Post-Apartheid racism|l1=Post-Apartheid racism}}

Foreign nationals from other African countries are increasingly subjected to violent xenophobic and racist attacks by black South Africans.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2019-04-15|title=South Africa: Attacks on Foreign Nationals|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2019/04/15/south-africa-attacks-foreign-nationals|access-date=2021-06-04|website=Human Rights Watch|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Post Apartheid South Africa has seen increasingly [[Anti White Racism]] against [[White South Africans]].

==Sudan==
{{Main|Racism in Sudan}}
{{See also|War in Darfur|South Sudan|Slavery in Sudan}}
In the [[Sudan]], [[black people|black]] African captives in the civil war were often [[Slavery in modern Africa|enslaved]], and female prisoners were often [[Sexual abuse|abused sexually]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/05/30/wdarf30.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2004/05/30/ixworld.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051203160903/http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/05/30/wdarf30.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2004/05/30/ixworld.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=3 December 2005|title=News|work=Telegraph.co.uk|access-date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; with their [[Arab]] captors claiming that Islamic law grants them permission.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.brandeis.edu/projects/fse/Pages/islamandslavery.html Islam and Slavery&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071012161707/http://www.brandeis.edu/projects/fse/Pages/islamandslavery.html |date=2007-10-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to [[CBS News]], slaves have been sold for US$50 a piece.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/1999/01/25/world/main29927.shtml Curse Of Slavery Haunts Sudan] CBS News. January 25, 1998&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2000, the [[U.S. State Department]] alleged that "the Sudanese government's support of slavery and its continued military action which has resulted in numerous deaths are due in part to the victims' religious beliefs."&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2000/US/09/05/state.dept.religion/index.html U.S. State Department report says 'religious intolerance remains far too common' around world. September 6, 2000] CNN US News&lt;/ref&gt; Jok Madut Jok, professor of history at [[Loyola Marymount University]], states that the abduction of women and children of the south is [[slavery]] by any definition. The government of Sudan insists that the whole matter is no more than the traditional tribal [[feud]]ing over resources.&lt;ref&gt;Jok Madut Jok (2001), p.3&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States government's [[Sudan Peace Act]] of October 21, 2002 accused Sudan of genocide in an [[Second Sudanese Civil War|ongoing civil war]] which has cost more than 2,000,000 lives and has displaced more than 4,000,000 people since the war started in 1983.&lt;ref&gt;[https://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2002/14531.htm U.S. Department of State: Sudan Peace Act] October 21, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Second Sudanese Civil War]], people were taken into slavery; estimates of abductions range from 14,000 to 200,000. Abduction of [[Dinka people|Dinka]] women and children was common.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Slavery, Abduction and Forced Servitude in Sudan|url=https://2001-2009.state.gov/p/af/rls/rpt/2002/10445.htm|publisher=US Department of State|access-date=20 March 2014|date=22 May 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, it became publicly known that there was an [[Darfur conflict|organised campaign]] by Janjaweed militias (nomadic Arab shepherds with the support of Sudanese government troops) to get rid of 80 black African groups from the [[Darfur]] region of western Sudan. These peoples include the Fur, Zaghawa and Massalit.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Clayton ''[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,3-1107849_2,00.html Desert hides world's worst humanitarian crisis]'' in [[The Times]] May 13, 2004, Page 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hilary Andersson''[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2089-1358234_1,00.html Genocide lays waste Darfur’s land of no men]'' in [[The Sunday Times (UK)|Sunday Times]] November 14, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

Mukesh Kapila ([[United Nations]] humanitarian coordinator) is quoted as saying: "This is more than just a conflict. It is an organised attempt [by Khartoum] to do away with a group of people. The only difference between [[Rwandan genocide|Rwanda]] [in 1994] and Darfur now is the numbers of dead, murdered, tortured and raped involved"&lt;ref&gt;Fred Bridgland ''[http://www.sundayherald.com/41183 Darfur: Africa’s hidden holocaust?] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050527001311/http://www.sundayherald.com/41183 |date=2005-05-27 }}'' in [[Sunday Herald]]'' April 11, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parliament.uk/parliamentary_committees/international_development/ind_04_05_14.cfm Darfur, Sudan: Crisis, response and lessons] UK Parliament Press Notice 14, Session 2004-05&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Collins, Robert O., "Civil Wars and Revolution in the Sudan: Essays on the Sudan, Southern Sudan, and Darfur, 1962-2004
", (p. 156), Tsehai Publishers (US), (2005) {{ISBN|0-9748198-7-5}} .&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Power, Samantha  "Dying in Darfur:
Can the ethnic cleansing in Sudan be stopped?"[http://www.newyorker.com/fact/content/?040830fa_fact1], ''The New Yorker'', 30 August 2004.
Human Rights Watch, [http://hrw.org/english/docs/2004/05/05/darfur8536.htm "Q &amp; A: Crisis in Darfur"] (web site, retrieved 24 May 2006).
Hilary Andersson, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/3752871.stm "Ethnic cleansing blights Sudan"], ''BBC News'', 27 May 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; A July 14, 2007 article noted that in the past two months up to 75,000 Arabs from [[Chad]] and [[Niger]] crossed the border into Darfur. Most have been relocated by the Sudanese government to former villages of displaced non-Arab people. Some 2.5 million have now been forced to flee their homes after attacks by Sudanese troops and Janjaweed militia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.independent.co.uk/world/africa/article2768232.ece|title=The Independent - 404|work=The Independent|access-date=17 June 2015|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070716155314/http://news.independent.co.uk/world/africa/article2768232.ece|archive-date=16 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tanzania==
Black Tanzanians portray Indian Tanzanians as miserly because of their status as a business minority who owns most businesses in [[Dar es Salaam]]. Whereas black Tanzanians are seen as lazy thieves and profiteers who have no culinary taste. In Indian-owned service businesses, it is said that black Tanzanians are served last after Indians, Arabs and white people. Black Tanzanians report to be looked down upon by Indians Tanzanians with the same education level, that Indian Tanzanians do not want to intermingle with black Tanzanians nor learn kiswahili, which they deem to be an inferior language.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Fouéré|first=Marie-Aude|date=2015 |editor-last=Michel|editor-first=Adam|title= Indian Africa : Minorities of Indian-Pakistani Origin in Eastern Africa  |publisher=Africae |pages=359-396  |chapter=“Indians are Exploiters and Africans Idlers!” : Identity formation and socio-economic conditions in Tanzania |isbn=9782957305810}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tunisia==

The accession of the Almohade dynasty to the throne of the [[Maghreb]] provinces in 1146 proved disastrous to the [[Jews of Tunis]]. Jews as well as [[Christians]] were compelled either to embrace [[Islam]] or to leave the country. [[Abd al-Mu'min]]'s successors pursued the same course, and their severe measures resulted either in emigration or in forcible conversions. Soon becoming suspicious of the sincerity of the new converts, the Almohades compelled them to wear a special garb, with a yellow cloth for a head-covering.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sefarad.org/publication/lm/045/8.html|title=THE HISTORY OF THE JEWS OF TUNISIA|access-date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Rue des Nègres (El Ouesfane) نهج الوصفان.jpg|thumb|Street plate in [[Medina of Tunis]] showing, in Arabic and French, Negroes street.]]
Mistranslations of Arab scholars and geographers from this time period have led many to attribute certain racial attitudes that were not prevalent until the 18th and 19th century to writings made centuries ago. French translators portrayed groups like Arabs and [[Berbers]] as distinct ethnic groups with set characteristics, while [[Ibn Khaldun]] and his contemporaries understood them to be diverse and changing in terms of makeup and behavior.&lt;ref&gt;Translation and the Colonial Imaginary: Ibn Khaldun Orientalist, by Abdelmajid Hannoum  © 2003 Wesleyan University. {{JSTOR|3590803}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Ibn Khaldun suggests a link between the decline of Ghana and rise of the [[Almoravid dynasty|Almoravids]]. However, there is little evidence of there actually being an Almoravid conquest of Ghana &lt;ref&gt;http://www.arts.ualberta.ca/~amcdouga/Hist446/readings/conquest_in_west_african_historiography.pdf Not Quite Venus from the Waves: The Almoravid Conquest of Ghana in the Modern Historiography of Western Africa by Pekka Masonen; Humphrey J. Fisher 1996&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Conquest That Never Was: Ghana and the Almoravids, 1076. I. The External Arabic Sources, by David Conrad and Humphrey Fisher  © 1982 African Studies Association {{JSTOR|3171598}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2018, more than seven years after the fall of the [[Zine El Abidine Ben Ali|Ben Ali regime]], Law 50 was introduced to protect black Tunisians from racial discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Tunisia racism: 'I lost the will to leave my home' |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-62376905 |first=Abdirahim |last=Saeed |date=27 August 2022 |access-date=28 August 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uganda==
Former British colonies in [[Sub-Saharan Africa]] have many citizens of [[South Asian]] descent. They were brought by the [[British Empire]] from [[British India]] to do clerical work in imperial service.&lt;ref name="Amin-Indophobia"&gt;General Amin and the Indian Exodus from Uganda
Hasu H. Patel, ''Issue: A Journal of Opinion'', Vol. 2, No. 4 (Winter, 1972), pp. 12-22 {{doi|10.2307/1166488}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most prominent case of anti-Indian racism was the [[ethnic cleansing]] of the Indian (called Asian) minority in [[Uganda]] by strongman [[dictator]] and [[human rights]] violator [[Idi Amin]].&lt;ref name="Amin-Indophobia"/&gt;

The 1968 Committee on "Africanization in Commerce and Industry" in Uganda made far-reaching Indophobic proposals. A system of work permits and trade licenses
was introduced in 1969 in order to restrict the role of Indians in economic and professional activities. Indians were segregated and discriminated against in all walks of life. After Amin came to power, he exploited these divisions to spread propaganda against Indians, [[stereotyping]] and [[scapegoating]] the Indian minority. Indians were stereotyped as "only traders" and so "inbred" to their profession. Indians were attacked as "dukawallas" (an occupational term that degenerated into an anti-Indian slur during Amin's time).&lt;ref name="Amin-Indophobia"/&gt;

In the 1970s Uganda and other East African nations{{which|date=June 2016}} implemented racist policies that targeted the Asian population of the region. Uganda under Idi Amin's leadership was particularly virulent in its anti-Asian policies. In August 1972, Idi Amin declared what he called an "economic war", a set of policies that included the expropriation of properties owned by Asians and Europeans. Uganda's 80,000 Asians were mostly Indians born in the country, whose ancestors had come to Uganda when the country was still a British colony.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ugandamission.net/aboutug/articles/amin.html|title=Idi Amin|access-date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/august/7/newsid_2492000/2492333.stm | work=BBC News | title=1972: Asians given 90 days to leave Uganda | date=1972-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indians were stereotyped as "greedy" and "conniving", without any racial identity or loyalty but "always cheating, conspiring and plotting" to subvert Uganda. Amin used this propaganda to justify a campaign of "de-Indianization", eventually resulting in the expulsion and ethnic cleansing of Uganda's Indian minority.&lt;ref name="Amin-Indophobia"/&gt;
India refused to accept the expelled people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/business/uk-indians-taking-care-of-business/2006/03/07/1141701511987.html|title=UK Indians taking care of business|access-date=17 June 2015|date=2006-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the expelled Indians settled in Britain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/legacies/immig_emig/england/suffolk/article_1.shtml|title=BBC - Legacies - Immigration and Emigration - England - Suffolk - Uganda's loss, Britain's gain - Article Page 1|access-date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The forced expulsion of Uganda's entire Asian population attests to the persecution of Asian peoples residing in the country at the time.{{According to whom|date=June 2020}}

==Zimbabwe==
{{Main|Racism in Zimbabwe}}
Racism in Zimbabwe first started during the [[Company rule in Rhodesia|colonial era]] in the 19th century, when immigrating [[White people|white]] settlers started to [[Racial discrimination|racially discriminate]] against Black people in the region. White settlers held full citizenship rights, as well as other significant economic and legal advantages over indigenous African people. Racial division would continue under [[Rhodesia]]n governance, sparking an armed struggle to overthrow white rule led by the [[Zimbabwe African People's Union]] (ZAPU) and the [[Zimbabwe African National Union]] (ZANU). This conflict culminated in the establishment of the modern state of [[Zimbabwe]]. The coalition of African forces was fragile, and the government led by [[Robert Mugabe]] and the majority-[[Shona people|Shona]] ZANU committed massacres against [[Northern Ndebele people]] in ZAPU strongholds, producing resentment between the African ethnic groups.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Mlambo|first=Alois S.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Yr8dAwAAQBAJ&amp;q=A+history+of+Zimbabwe&amp;pg=PR10|title=A History of Zimbabwe|date=2014-04-07|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-1-139-86752-8|pages=222–224, 254–256|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the end of armed conflict, the white minority in Zimbabwe continued to exert disproportionate control over the economy, owned the majority of arable land in Zimbabwe, and maintained racially segregated social circles. White settlers were protected by generous provisions established by the [[Lancaster House Agreement]], and thus continued to exert significant political and legal control over the African population. Wide disparities existed in access to sports, education and housing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Masocha|first1=Vincent|last2=Mugari|first2=Abisha|date=2015-11-30|title=Sport and Racial Inequality: An Analysis of Pre-Independence Zimbabwe (1890-1979)|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/285236038|journal=Greener Journal of Sport and Physical Education}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The ZANU-led government did not engage in significant expropriation of white settlers despite promising land reform to the African population, with one white commercial farmer commenting that Mugabe's government in the early 1980s was "the best government for farmers that this country has ever seen". Dissatisfaction with the slow pace of land reform led to the illegal seizing of white-owned land by African peasants.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The government responded with heavy-handed repression against the African peasants.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Mlambo|first=Alois S.|date=2012-11-26|title=Becoming Zimbabwe or becoming Zimbabwean : identity, nationalism and state building in the historical context of Southern Africa.|hdl=2263/20491|url=https://repository.up.ac.za/handle/2263/20491|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Resentment of continued white control of the economy continued through the 1990s, spurred by the perception that the white business community was disinterested in improving the economic lot of the African population or otherwise changing the status quo.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Cheater|first=Angela|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YKOEAgAAQBAJ&amp;q=%22racism+in+zimbabwe%22&amp;pg=PA117|title=The Anthropology of Power|date=2003-12-16|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-134-65048-4|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 2000, as the [[ZANU–PF|ZANU-PF]] government grew political isolated, it increasingly criticized the white population's segregationism and racism,&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; and began to encourage violent farm invasions against the white population, which drew condemnations from the international community.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Zimbabwe today continues to be fractured by enmity along racial lines.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Abednico|first=Siambombe|date=2017-06-01|title=A wrong without design : assessing racism and white color crime in Zimbabwe|url=https://journals.co.za/content/journal/10520/EJC-9d895db50|journal=AFFRIKA Journal of Politics, Economics and Society|language=en|volume=7|issue=1|pages=127–134|doi=10.31920/2075-6534/2017/v7n1a7|issn=1998-4936}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Geography of antisemitism|Antisemitism in Africa]]
*[[Racism by country]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Africa topic|Racism in}}
{{Racism topics}}

[[Category:Racism in Africa| ]]
[[Category:Racism by region|Africa]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>