<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171115171821|810501171" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="31124119" pageid="31124119" ns="0" title="Social stigma of obesity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-15T18:21:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Merge|Weight stigma|date=November 2016}}
{{Merge|Sizeism|date=January 2017}}
{{Merge|Anti-fat bias|date=January 2017}}
The '''social stigma of obesity''' has created negative psychosocial impacts and has caused disadvantages for overweight and [[obesity|obese]] people. The [[social stigma]] can span one's entire life, as long as the excess weight is present, starting from a young age and lasting into adulthood.&lt;ref name="Süddeutsche1"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sueddeutsche.de/leben/adipositas-dicke-sind-faul-und-dumm-1.598030|title=Dicke sind faul und dumm|date=August 11, 2008|publisher=[[Süddeutsche Zeitung]]|language=German|accessdate=March 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several studies from across the world (e.g., United States, [[University of Marburg]], [[University of Leipzig]]) indicate overweight and obese individuals experience higher levels of stigma relative to their thinner counterparts. In addition, they marry less often, experience fewer educational and opportunities, and on average earn a lesser income than normal weight individuals.&lt;ref name="Süddeutsche1" /&gt; Although public support regarding disability services, civil rights and anti-workplace discrimination laws for obese individuals have gained support across the years,&lt;ref name="Süddeutsche1" /&gt; overweight and obese individuals still experience discrimination, which may have implications to physiological and psychological health. These issues are compounded with the significant negative physiological effects associated with obesity.&lt;ref name="CDC"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.cdc.gov/healthyweight/effects/|title=The Health Effects of Overweight and Obesity|date=August 11, 2011|publisher=[[Center for Disease Control]]|language=English|accessdate=January 17, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Obesity stigma stands to be one of the few acceptable forms of discrimination in Western society.  Media, in general, under represents overweight individuals and when these roles are present, they are often minor, stereotyped roles. They are more commonly seen eating, and are less likely to be involved in a romantic relationship compared to the average weight television character.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Puhl|first=R.M.|last2=Heuer|first2=C.A.|last3=Brownell|first3=K.D.|title=Stigma and social consequences of obesity|journal=Clinical obesity in adults and children|volume=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theoretical explanations for weight-stigma==

In order to understand weight-biased attitudes, theories have been proposed to explain the discrimination.  Crandall’s Social Ideology Perspective draws on traditional North American values of self-determination, individualism and self-discipline. Based on these values, anti-fat attitudes may derive from directing blame towards individuals who are overweight.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Puhl|first=R.M.|last2=Brownell|first2=K.D.|title=Stigma, discrimination, and obesity.|journal=Eating Disorders and Obesity: A Comprehensive Handbook|volume=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the [[attribution theory]] suggests that attitudes towards obese individuals are dependent on how much control they are perceived to have over their weight.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;  Throughout the literature, numerous studies have shown support for this theory.  One study conducted a multinational examination of weight bias across four countries (Canada, United States, Iceland, and Australia) with comparable obesity rates.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=A multinational examination of weight bias: Predictor of anti-fat attitudes across four countries|journal=International Journal of Obesity|volume=39}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The study found that attributions of behavioral causes of obesity were associated with greater weight bias.  Further, these individuals were more likely to view obesity as being due to lack of willpower.  There appears to be decreased weight bias when weight was attributed to factors that were less within the individual’s control, or when individuals are perceived as trying to lose weight.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Beames|first=Joanne R.|last2=Black|first2=Melissa J.|last3=Vartanian|first3=Lenny R.|title=Prejudice toward individuals with obesity: Evidence for a pro-effort bias.|url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/xap0000079|journal=Journal of Experimental Psychology: Applied|volume=22|issue=2|pages=184–195|doi=10.1037/xap0000079}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Weight discrimination in education ==

In regards to more direct weight bias, obese individuals were 40-50% more likely to report major discrimination compared to those of average weight across a multitude of settings.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Carr|first=Deborah|last2=Friedman|first2=Michael A.|date=2005-09-01|title=Is Obesity Stigmatizing? Body Weight, Perceived Discrimination, and Psychological Well-Being in the United States|url=http://hsb.sagepub.com/content/46/3/244|journal=Journal of Health and Social Behavior|language=en|volume=46|issue=3|pages=244–259|doi=10.1177/002214650504600303|issn=0022-1465|pmid=16259147}}&lt;/ref&gt;  More specifically, studies have shown that those who are overweight face discrimination throughout the educational and employment systems. In the educational setting, those who are overweight as youth often face peer rejection.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wardle|first=Jane|last2=Cooke|first2=Lucy|title=The impact of obesity on psychological well-being|url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1521690X05000382|journal=Best Practice &amp; Research Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism|volume=19|issue=3|pages=421–440|doi=10.1016/j.beem.2005.04.006}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As individuals grow older they may be less likely to be admitted into a college compared to average weight persons, and in some cases, individuals were admitted to academic institutions and dismissed due to weight.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;  Research suggests that within the classroom teachers may perceive overweight individuals’ work more poorly compared to average weight individuals, and the attention the teacher provides to these two groups may differ.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;  Research has also found that overweight females receive less financial support for education from their families than average weight females, after controlling for ethnicity, family size, income, and education.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

== Weight discrimination in the workplace ==

Studies suggest that obese individuals are less likely to be hired and once hired, have greater termination rates than average weight individuals.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;  Specifically, a national survey found that obese individuals were 26% more likely not to be hired, not receive a promotion, or to be fired compared to average weight persons.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;  Such outcomes may be a result of employers viewing them as less agreeable, less competent and lazier than average weight individuals.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

== Weight discrimination in politics ==

[[File:Chris Christie by Gage Skidmore 5.jpg|thumb|250px|New Jersey Governor [[Chris Christie]] is a politician who may have suffered from weight related discrimination at times during his political career.]]
A study, by [[Michigan State University]] researchers, shows evidence overweight political candidates tend to receive fewer votes than their thinner opponents. The researchers analyzed data from the 2008 and 2012 U.S. Senate elections. Using a previously established scientific method, research assistants determined from color photos whether the candidates in 126 primary and general elections were normal weight, overweight or obese.

Both obese men and women were often less likely to get on the ballot in the first place. When it came to merely being overweight, women were seen underrepresented on the ballot, though men were not. This is consistent with previous research showing men who are slightly heavy tend not to experience the same discrimination of a slightly overweight women.

However, when it came to the voting, both male and female candidates, whether obese or simply overweight, tend to get a lower share of the vote total than their more slender opponents. Some politicians have resorted to extreme weight loss measures, including surgery,  to increase their elect-ability to political office. 
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2014/05/140519160753.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Weight discrimination in health care ==

Medical professionals may be more likely to view obese individuals in negative terms such as weak willed, unsuccessful, hopeless, and non-compliant with their treatments. As such, these individuals may receive poorer care compared to average weight people. Doctors have reported less intervention and an avoidance of weight-related discussion with obese patients.  Additionally, nurses have reported a reluctance to touch obese persons during treatment.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;  A national survey found that individuals who were overweight reported a 3xs more likely to be denied medical care than average weight people.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;  Further, health professionals who specialize in obesity showed strong implicit and explicit anti-fat bias as measured by self-report and the [[Implicit-association test|Implicit Associations Test]] (IAT).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Schwartz|first=Marlene B.|last2=Chambliss|first2=Heather O'Neal|last3=Brownell|first3=Kelly D.|last4=Blair|first4=Steven N.|last5=Billington|first5=Charles|date=2003-09-01|title=Weight Bias among Health Professionals Specializing in Obesity|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1038/oby.2003.142/abstract|journal=Obesity Research|language=en|volume=11|issue=9|pages=1033–1039|doi=10.1038/oby.2003.142|issn=1550-8528|pmid=12972672}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, such biases were mixed amongst dietitians and nutritionists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Jung|first=Franziska U. C. E.|last2=Luck-Sikorski|first2=Claudia|last3=Wiemers|first3=Nina|last4=Riedel-Heller|first4=Steffi G.|date=2015-10-14|title=Dietitians and Nutritionists: Stigma in the Context of Obesity. A Systematic Review|url=http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0140276|journal=PLOS ONE|volume=10|issue=10|pages=e0140276|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0140276|issn=1932-6203|pmid=26466329|pmc=4605484}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Weight discrimination in early development ==

This external stigmatization and its internalized effects have been examined across different age groups. Overweight and obese children and adolescents experience stigmatization from parents, teachers, and peers.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Puhl|first=Rebecca M.|last2=Latner|first2=Janet D.|title=Stigma, obesity, and the health of the nation's children.|url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0033-2909.133.4.557|journal=Psychological Bulletin|volume=133|issue=4|pages=557–580|doi=10.1037/0033-2909.133.4.557|pmid=17592956}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peer stigmatization, especially, may be difficult for overweight adolescents considering the role of peer support in promoting identity development and self-esteem.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Janssen|first=Ian|last2=Craig|first2=Wendy M.|last3=Boyce|first3=William F.|last4=Pickett|first4=William|date=2004-05-01|title=Associations between overweight and obesity with bullying behaviors in school-aged children|journal=Pediatrics|volume=113|issue=5|pages=1187–1194|issn=1098-4275|pmid=15121928|doi=10.1542/peds.113.5.1187}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some research suggests that negative attitudes about being overweight are even held by overweight and obese children themselves. Specifically, weight bias may become internalized and increase throughout childhood, then decrease and level-off during late adolescence and adulthood.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

Weight-based teasing in childhood and adolescence has been associated with a handful of costs to psychosocial health, including reduced [[self-esteem]] and lower [[self-concept]],&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Davison|first=Kirsten Krahnstoever|last2=Birch|first2=Leann Lipps|title=Processes linking weight status and self-concept among girls from ages 5 to 7 years.|url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0012-1649.38.5.735|journal=Developmental Psychology|volume=38|issue=5|pages=735–748|doi=10.1037/0012-1649.38.5.735}}&lt;/ref&gt; higher rates of [[Depression (mood)|depression]] and [[anxiety disorder]]s,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Associations of weight-based teasing and emotional well-being among adolescents|journal=Archives of Pediatric and Adolescent Medicine|volume=157}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Russell-Mayhew|first=Shelly|last2=McVey|first2=Gail|last3=Bardick|first3=Angela|last4=Ireland|first4=Alana|date=2012-06-24|title=Mental Health, Wellness, and Childhood Overweight/Obesity|url=http://www.hindawi.com/journals/jobe/2012/281801/|journal=Journal of Obesity|language=en|volume=2012|pages=1–9|doi=10.1155/2012/281801|issn=2090-0708}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Keery|first=Helene|last2=Boutelle|first2=Kerri|last3=Berg|first3=Patricia van den|last4=Thompson|first4=J. Kevin|title=The impact of appearance-related teasing by family members|url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1054139X05000923|journal=Journal of Adolescent Health|volume=37|issue=2|pages=120–127|doi=10.1016/j.jadohealth.2004.08.015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and even greater likelihood of endorsing suicidal thoughts.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Further, weight-based teasing has been associated with higher rates of [[binge eating]] and unhealthy weight control (e.g., fasting, self-induced vomiting, laxatives, diet pills, skipped meals, smoking).&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Weight-teasing among adolescents: Correlations with weight status and disordered eating behaviors|journal=International Journal of Obesity|volume=26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Haines|first=Jess|last2=Neumark-Sztainer|first2=Dianne|last3=Eisenberg|first3=Marla E.|last4=Hannan|first4=Peter J.|date=2006-02-01|title=Weight Teasing and Disordered Eating Behaviors in Adolescents: Longitudinal Findings From Project EAT (Eating Among Teens)|url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/117/2/e209|journal=Pediatrics|language=en|volume=117|issue=2|pages=e209–e215|doi=10.1542/peds.2005-1242|issn=0031-4005|pmid=16452330}}&lt;/ref&gt; Overweight adolescents who were bullied were also more likely to meet criteria for bulimia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kaltiala-Heino|first=R.|last2=Rissanen|first2=A.|last3=Rimpela|first3=M.|last4=Rantanen|first4=P.|date=1999-07-01|title=Bulimia and bulimic behaviour in middle adolescence: more common than thought?|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1600-0447.1999.tb10911.x/abstract|journal=Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica|language=en|volume=100|issue=1|pages=33–39|doi=10.1111/j.1600-0447.1999.tb10911.x|issn=1600-0447}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A survey of 7,266 children aged 11 to 16 conducted by the [[World Health Organization]] reported higher rates of physical victimization (e.g., being shoved) with increasing body mass index among girls. Additionally, these results showed relational victimization (i.e., being excluded or having rumors spread about you) was reported more often at increasing body mass index by both girls and boys.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; A separate survey of 7,825 students aged 11 to 17 also noted that, compared to average-weight peers, obese boys and overweight girls were more likely to be victims of bullying. Additionally, obese girls were more likely to be victims and perpetrators of bullying than their peers. Notably, overweight and obese adolescent girls also reported higher rates of smoking, drinking, and marijuana use relative to their normal-weight peers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Farhat|first=Tilda|last2=Iannotti|first2=Ronald J.|last3=Simons-Morton|first3=Bruce G.|title=Overweight, Obesity, Youth, and Health-Risk Behaviors|url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0749379709008265|journal=American Journal of Preventive Medicine|volume=38|issue=3|pages=258–267|doi=10.1016/j.amepre.2009.10.038}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Health-related outcomes associated with weight discrimination ==

In adulthood, individuals who experience weight discrimination are more likely to identify themselves as overweight regardless of their actual weight status.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Schafer|first=Markus H.|last2=Ferraro|first2=Kenneth F.|date=2011-03-01|title=The Stigma of Obesity Does Perceived Weight Discrimination Affect Identity and Physical Health?|url=http://spq.sagepub.com/content/74/1/76|journal=Social Psychology Quarterly|language=en|volume=74|issue=1|pages=76–97|doi=10.1177/0190272511398197|issn=0190-2725}}&lt;/ref&gt; The experience of weight stigma can function as motivation to avoid stigmatizing environments, and although it may motivate one to escape stigma through weight loss, it undermines one’s capacity to do so.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hunger|first=Jeffrey M.|last2=Major|first2=Brenda|last3=Blodorn|first3=Alison|last4=Miller|first4=Carol T.|date=2015-06-01|title=Weighed Down by Stigma: How Weight-Based Social Identity Threat Contributes to Weight Gain and Poor Health|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/spc3.12172/abstract|journal=Social and Personality Psychology Compass|language=en|volume=9|issue=6|pages=255–268|doi=10.1111/spc3.12172|issn=1751-9004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers have linked weight stigma to decreases in physical activity,&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bombak|first=Andrea E.|date=2015-01-01|title=Obese persons’ physical activity experiences and motivations across weight changes: a qualitative exploratory study|url=https://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s12889-015-2456-0|journal=BMC Public Health|volume=15|pages=1129|doi=10.1186/s12889-015-2456-0|issn=1471-2458|pmid=26577260|pmc=4650293}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Puhl|first=Rebecca M.|last2=King|first2=Kelly M.|title=Weight discrimination and bullying|url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1521690X12001182|journal=Best Practice &amp; Research Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism|volume=27|issue=2|pages=117–127|doi=10.1016/j.beem.2012.12.002}}&lt;/ref&gt; decreases in seeking health care&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt; and increases in maladaptive eating patterns such as binge eating.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt; In addition, those who have experienced weight stigma have shown altered cardiovascular reactivity, increased cortisol level, oxidative stress, and inflammation.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

In terms of psychological health, researchers demonstrated that obese individuals demonstrated lower sense of well-being relative to non-obese individuals if they had perceived weight stigmatization even after controlling for other demographic factors such as age and sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Jackson|first=Sarah E.|last2=Beeken|first2=Rebecca J.|last3=Wardle|first3=Jane|date=2015-05-01|title=Obesity, perceived weight discrimination, and psychological well-being in older adults in England|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/oby.21052/abstract|journal=Obesity|language=en|volume=23|issue=5|pages=1105–1111|doi=10.1002/oby.21052|issn=1930-739X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Overweight and obese individuals report experiencing forms of internalized stigma such as body dissatisfaction as well as decreased social support and feelings of loneliness.&lt;ref name=":8"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Phelan|first=Sean M.|last2=Burgess|first2=Diana J.|last3=Puhl|first3=Rebecca|last4=Dyrbye|first4=Liselotte N.|last5=Dovidio|first5=John F.|last6=Yeazel|first6=Mark|last7=Ridgeway|first7=Jennifer L.|last8=Nelson|first8=David|last9=Perry|first9=Sylvia|date=2015-07-15|title=The Adverse Effect of Weight Stigma on the Well-Being of Medical Students with Overweight or Obesity: Findings from a National Survey|url=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11606-015-3266-x|journal=Journal of General Internal Medicine|language=en|volume=30|issue=9|pages=1251–1258|doi=10.1007/s11606-015-3266-x|issn=0884-8734}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sikorski|first=Claudia|last2=Luppa|first2=Melanie|last3=Luck|first3=Tobias|last4=Riedel-Heller|first4=Steffi G.|date=2015-02-01|title=Weight stigma "gets under the skin"—evidence for an adapted psychological mediation framework—a systematic review|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/oby.20952/abstract|journal=Obesity|language=en|volume=23|issue=2|pages=266–276|doi=10.1002/oby.20952|issn=1930-739X}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, similar to findings in adolescence, weight stigma in adulthood is associated with lower self-esteem, higher rates of depression, anxiety, and substance use.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Obesity]]
[[Category:Social stigma|Obesity]]
[[Category:Stereotypes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>