<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221127193000|1124186701" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="31124119" pageid="31124119" ns="0" title="Social stigma of obesity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-27T19:36:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Type of discrimination based on weight}}
{{Globalize|article|USA|2name=the United States|date=November 2018}}
{{Merge from|Obesity social stigma in television|date=December 2021}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expand-social=yes}}
{{Human body weight}}

'''Social stigma of obesity''' is broadly defined as [[bias]] or [[discrimination|discriminatory]] behaviors targeted at overweight and obese individuals because of their weight.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Psychosocial origins of obesity stigma: toward changing a powerful and pervasive bias|journal = Obesity Reviews|date = 2003-11-01|issn = 1467-789X|pages = 213–227|volume = 4|issue = 4|doi = 10.1046/j.1467-789X.2003.00122.x|pmid = 14649372|first1 = Rebecca M.|last1 = Puhl|first2 = Kelly D.|last2 = Brownell|s2cid = 31481832|author-link2=Kelly D. Brownell}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|title = The Stigma of Obesity: A Review and Update|journal = Obesity|date = 2009-05-01|issn = 1930-739X|pages = 941–964|volume = 17|issue = 5|doi = 10.1038/oby.2008.636|pmid = 19165161|first1 = Rebecca M.|last1 = Puhl|first2 = Chelsea A.|last2 = Heuer|s2cid = 152352|doi-access = free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such [[social stigma]]s can span one's entire life, as long as excess weight is present, starting from a young age and lasting into adulthood.&lt;ref name="Süddeutsche1"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sueddeutsche.de/leben/adipositas-dicke-sind-faul-und-dumm-1.598030|title=Dicke sind faul und dumm|date=August 11, 2008|publisher=[[Süddeutsche Zeitung]]|language=de|access-date=March 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several studies from across the world (e.g., [[United States]], [[University of Marburg]], [[University of Leipzig]]) indicate [[overweight]] and [[Obesity|obese]] individuals experience higher levels of stigma relative to their thinner counterparts. In addition, they marry less often, experience fewer educational and career opportunities, and on average earn a lesser income than [[Body mass index|normal weight]] individuals.&lt;ref name="Süddeutsche1" /&gt; Although public support regarding disability services, civil rights, and anti-workplace discrimination laws for obese individuals have gained support across the years, overweight and obese individuals still experience discrimination, which may have detrimental implications in relation to both physiological&lt;ref name="Muennig2008"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Muennig |first1=P |title=The body politic: the relationship between stigma and obesity-associated disease. |journal=BMC Public Health |date=2008 |volume=8 |page=128 |doi=10.1186/1471-2458-8-128|pmid=18426601 |pmc=2386473 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and psychological health. These issues are compounded by the significant negative physiological effects that are already associated with obesity,&lt;ref name="CDC"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.cdc.gov/healthyweight/effects/|title=The Health Effects of Overweight and Obesity|date=August 11, 2011|publisher=[[Center for Disease Control]]|language=en|access-date=January 17, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; which some have proposed may be caused by stress from the social stigma of obesity, rather than from obesity per se.&lt;ref name="Muennig2008" /&gt;

Anti-fat bias refers to [[prejudice|prejudicial]] assumptions that are based on an assessment of a person as being overweight or obese. It is also known as "'''fat shaming'''". Anti-fat bias can be found in many facets of society,&lt;ref name="PuhlBrownell" /&gt; and [[fat acceptance movement|fat activists]] commonly blame popular media for the pervasiveness of this phenomenon.&lt;ref name=UFM&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1080/10640260802115852| pmid = 18568920| title = Internalization of the Ultra-Thin Ideal: Positive Implicit Associations with Underweight Fashion Models are Associated with Drive for Thinness in Young Women| journal = Eating Disorders| volume = 16| issue = 4| pages = 294–307| year = 2008| last1 = Ahern | first1 = A. L. | last2 = Bennett | first2 = K. M. | last3 = Hetherington | first3 = M. M. | s2cid = 2473526}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=david&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1080/10640260490267751| title = The Impact of Exposure to the Thin-Ideal Media Image on Women| journal = Eating Disorders| volume = 12| issue = 1| pages = 35–50| year = 2004| last1 = Hawkins | first1 = N. | last2 = Richards | first2 = P. S. | last3 = Granley | first3 = H. M. C. | last4 = Stein | first4 = D. M. | pmid=16864303| s2cid = 28802161}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prevalence==
Research indicates that self-reported incidents of weight-based [[discrimination]] increased from 1995 to 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Changes in Perceived Weight Discrimination Among Americans, 1995–1996 Through 2004–2006|journal = Obesity|date = 2008-05-01|issn = 1930-739X|pages = 1129–1134|volume = 16|issue = 5|doi = 10.1038/oby.2008.35|pmid = 18356847|first1 = Tatiana|last1 = Andreyeva|first2 = Rebecca M.|last2 = Puhl|first3 = Kelly D.|last3 = Brownell|citeseerx = 10.1.1.175.3676|s2cid = 15323829}}&lt;/ref&gt; Individuals who are subjected to weight-related stigma appear to be rated more negatively when compared with other groups, such as [[Sexual minority|sexual minorities]] and those with [[Mental disorder|mental illness]].&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Primum Non Nocere: Obesity Stigma and Public Health|journal = Journal of Bioethical Inquiry|date = 2013-01-04|issn = 1176-7529|pages = 49–57|volume = 10|issue = 1|doi = 10.1007/s11673-012-9412-9|pmid = 23288439|first1 = Lenny R.|last1 = Vartanian|first2 = Joshua M.|last2 = Smyth|s2cid = 8752139}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anti-fat bias has been observed in groups hoping to become physical education instructors. In a study published in 2007, a group of 344 psychology or [[physical education]] majors at a New Zealand University were compared, and it was found that the prospective physical education teachers were more likely to display implicit anti-fat attitudes than the psychology majors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1038/sj.ijo.0803398|last1=O'Brien|first1=K.S.|first2=J.A.|last2=Hunter|first3=M.|last3=Banks|year=2007
|title=Implicit anti-fat bias in physical educators: Physical attributes, ideology and socialization|journal=International Journal of Obesity|volume=31|issue=2|pages=308–314|pmid=16733526|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of studies have found that [[Health Care Providers|health care providers]] frequently have explicit and/or implicit biases against overweight people, and it has been found that overweight patients may receive lower quality care as a result of their weight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Phelan|first1=S. M.|last2=Burgess|first2=D. J.|last3=Yeazel|first3=M. W.|last4=Hellerstedt|first4=W. L.|last5=Griffin|first5=J. M.|last6=van Ryn|first6=M.|title=Impact of weight bias and stigma on quality of care and outcomes for patients with obesity|journal=Obesity Reviews|date=April 2015|volume=16|issue=4|pages=319–326|doi=10.1111/obr.12266|pmid=25752756|pmc=4381543}}&lt;/ref&gt; Medical professionals who [[Bariatrics|specialize in the treatment of obesity]] have been found to have strong negative associations toward obese individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1038/sj.ijo.0801745|last1=Teachman|first1=B.A.|first2=K.D.|last2=Brownell|year=2001|title=Implicit anti-fat bias among health professionals: Is anyone immune?|journal=International Journal of Obesity|volume=25|issue=10|pages=1525–1531|pmid=11673776|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; The stress from obesity-related stigma may also cause negative health outcomes.&lt;ref name="Muennig2008" /&gt;

In one study, [[preschool]]-aged children reported a preference for average-sized children over overweight children as friends.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1093/jpepsy/jsh063|last1=Musher-Eizenman|first1=D.|first2=S.|last2=Holub|first3=A.|last3=Miller|first4=S.|last4=Goldstein|first5=L.|last5=Edwards-Leeper|year=2004|title=Body size stigmatization in preschool children: The role of control attributions|journal=Journal of Pediatric Psychology|volume=29|issue=8|pages=613–620|pmid=15491983|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Overweight individuals often find themselves suffering repercussions in many facets of society, including legal and employment issues later in their life.&lt;ref name="PuhlBrownell"&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1038/oby.2001.108|last1=Puhl|first1=R.|first2=K.|last2=Brownell|year=2001|title=Bias, discrimination, and obesity|journal=Obesity Research|volume=9|issue=12|pages=788–805|pmid=11743063|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a 2010 review of published studies, interventions seeking to reduce prejudice and [[social stigma]] against fat and [[obesity]] are largely ineffective.&lt;ref&gt;Daníelsdóttir S, O'Brien KS, Ciao A. Anti-fat prejudice reduction: A review of published studies. Obesity Facts 2010; 3: 47–58.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characteristics==
Weight-related stigma can be characterized by the following aspects: 
# An individual does not have to be overweight or obese to experience weight-related stigma.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Carr|first1=Deborah|last2=Friedman|first2=Michael A.|date=2005-09-01|title=Is Obesity Stigmatizing? Body Weight, Perceived Discrimination, and Psychological Well-Being in the United States|journal=Journal of Health and Social Behavior|volume=46|issue=3|pages=244–259|doi=10.1177/002214650504600303|issn=0022-1465|pmid=16259147|citeseerx=10.1.1.407.990|s2cid=8396227}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Studies have indicated that experiencing weight stigma reinforces lifestyle behaviors that contribute to obesity.&lt;ref name="Puhl"/&gt;
# Many groups who are subjected to stigmatisation tend to be minorities. Overweight and obese individuals make up the majority of the population in the United States and in other parts of the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Ogden|first1=Cynthia L|last2=Carroll|first2=Margaret D|last3=Kit|first3=Brian K|last4=Flegal|first4=Katherine M|title=Prevalence of childhood and adult obesity in the United States, 2011-2012.|journal=JAMA|date=26 February 2014|volume=311|issue=8|pages=806–14|pmid=24570244|doi=10.1001/jama.2014.732|pmc=4770258}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Individuals who are overweight or obese tend to devalue their own in-group and prefer the out-group (i.e. thinner individuals).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Weighing obesity stigma: the relative strength of different forms of bias|journal = International Journal of Obesity|date = 2008-04-15|issn = 0307-0565|pages = 1145–1152|volume = 32|issue = 7|doi = 10.1038/ijo.2008.53|pmid = 18414421|first1 = Janet D.|last1 = Latner|first2 = Kerry S.|last2 = O'Brien|first3 = Laura E.|last3 = Durso|first4 = L. A.|last4 = Brinkman|first5 = T.|last5 = MacDonald|doi-access = free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theoretical explanations==
In order to understand weight-biased attitudes, theories have been proposed to explain these biases and the subsequent discrimination they cause.  Christian S. Crandall discusses the "Justification of Stigmatization".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Social Psychology of Stigma|last=Heatherton|first=Todd F.|publisher=Guilford Press|year=2003|isbn=978-1572309425|location=New York London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also his Social Ideology Perspective draws on traditional North American values of self-determination, individualism, and self-discipline. Based on these values, anti-fat attitudes may derive from directing blame for being overweight towards individuals who are overweight.&lt;ref name=":1b"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Puhl|first1=R.M.|last2=Brownell|first2=K.D.|title=Stigma, discrimination, and obesity.|journal=Eating Disorders and Obesity: A Comprehensive Handbook}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the [[attribution theory]] suggests that attitudes towards obese individuals are dependent on how much control they are perceived to have over their weight.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;  Throughout the literature, numerous studies have shown support for this theory.  One study conducted a multinational examination of weight bias across four countries (Canada, United States, Iceland, and Australia) with comparable obesity rates.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=A multinational examination of weight bias: Predictor of anti-fat attitudes across four countries|journal=International Journal of Obesity|volume=39|issue=7|pages=1166–1173|doi=10.1038/ijo.2015.32 |pmid=25809827|year=2015|last1=Puhl|first1=R. M.|last2=Latner|first2=J. D.|last3=O'Brien|first3=K.|last4=Luedicke|first4=J.|last5=Danielsdottir|first5=S.|last6=Forhan|first6=M.|s2cid=7917104}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The study found that attributions of behavioral causes of obesity were associated with greater weight bias. Similarly, viewing obesity as being caused by a lack of willpower was also associated with greater weight bias. There appears to be a decrease in weight bias when weight is attributed to factors that are less within the individual's control, or when individuals are perceived as trying to lose weight.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Beames|first1=Joanne R.|last2=Black|first2=Melissa J.|last3=Vartanian|first3=Lenny R.|title=Prejudice toward individuals with obesity: Evidence for a pro-effort bias.|journal=Journal of Experimental Psychology: Applied|volume=22|issue=2|pages=184–195|doi=10.1037/xap0000079|pmid=26866441|year=2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, evidence also exists showing that biases against obese individuals also include disgust towards them, which can persist regardless of if one knows that obesity is not caused by obese individuals' actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Vartanian |first1=L R |title=Disgust and perceived control in attitudes toward obese people |journal=International Journal of Obesity |date=March 2010 |volume=34 |issue=8 |pages=1302–1307 |doi=10.1038/ijo.2010.45 |pmid=20195287 |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fatphobia is a socially constructed phenomenon of particular prevalence in the western world. Societies produce the sort of bodies they need.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Scheper-Hughes, Lock |first1=N., M. |title=The Mindful Body: A Prolegomenon to Future Work in Medical Anthropology |journal=Medical Anthropology Quarterly |date=1987 |volume=1 |issue=1 |pages=8 |publisher=Wiley, American Anthropological Association|doi=10.1525/maq.1987.1.1.02a00020 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The west values healthy and strong bodies that prioritize agility, endurance and fertility&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Scheper-Hughes, Lock |first1=N., M. |title=The Mindful Body: A Prolegomenon to Future Work in Medical Anthropology |journal=Medical Anthropology Quarterly |date=1987 |volume=1 |issue=1 |pages=25 |publisher=Wiley, American Anthropological Association|doi=10.1525/maq.1987.1.1.02a00020 }}&lt;/ref&gt; - with focus on achievement and individual responsibility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Trainer, Hardin, SturtzSreetharan, Wutich, Brewis |first1=S., J.,C., A., B. |title=Fat is all my fault: Globalized Metathemes of Body Self-Blame |journal=Medical Anthropology Quarterly |date=2021 |volume=36 |issue=1 |pages=6 |publisher=American Anthropology Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; Not only do such bodies associate the western world with similar ideals, but Lloyd deMause suggests the ‘fitness/toughness craze’ may also reflect preparations for war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=deMause |first1=L. |title=Reagan's America |date=1984 |publisher=New York: Creative Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ’fattening huts’ of young girls in Nigeria however, represent beauty, marriageability and money – a direct reflection of the value of economic resource and food.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Brown |first1=P. |title=Culture and the Evolution of Obesity |journal=Human Nature (Hawthorne, N.Y.) |date=1991 |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=48 |publisher=New York: Emory University|doi=10.1007/BF02692180 |pmid=24222189 |s2cid=37346271 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Fatness is a welcome sign of health, prosperity and maternity - linked to self-worth and sexuality also.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Brown |first1=P. |title=Culture and the Evolution of Obesity |journal=Human Nature (Hawthorne, N.Y.) |date=1991 |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=46 |publisher=New York: Emory University|doi=10.1007/BF02692180 |pmid=24222189 |s2cid=37346271 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fatphobia does not fear ‘fat’ but prejudice, discrimination, exclusion and preventable disease too - fears directly attributable to the myriad of social, political, historical, economic and cultural processes at work (that do not similarly exist in other cultures).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Brown |first1=P. |title=Culture and the Evolution of Obesity |journal=Human Nature (Hawthorne, N.Y.) |date=1991 |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=31–57 |publisher=New York: Emory University|doi=10.1007/BF02692180 |pmid=24222189 |s2cid=37346271 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In this way, fatphobia is a culturally-derived phenomenon influencing relationships to food as well to the female form. Trends in ‘blame, shame and stigma'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Trainer, Hardin, SturtzSreetharan, Wutich, Brewis |first1=S., J.,C., A., B. |title=Fat is all my fault: Globalized Metathemes of Body Self-Blame |journal=Medical Anthropology Quarterly |date=2021 |volume=36 |issue=1 |pages=7 |publisher=American Anthropology Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; have contributed to fat positivity and ‘health at every size’ movements, that create digital ‘safe spaces’ for activism and radical fat acceptance that seek to resist/shift such powerful cultural perspectives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kost, Jamie |first1=C., K. |title='It has literally been a lifesaver': The Role of "knowing kinship" in Supporting fat Women to Navigate Medical Fatphobia |journal=Fat Studies |date=2022 |pages=2 |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis Group}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Trait attribution==
Anti-fat bias leads people to associate individuals who are overweight or obese with negative personality traits such as "lacking willpower",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=O'Brien |first1=KS |last2=Hunter |first2=JA |last3=Banks |first3=M |title=Implicit anti-fat bias in physical educators: physical attributes, ideology, and socialization. |journal=Int J Obes |date=2007 |volume=31|issue=2 |pages=308–314 |doi=10.1038/sj.ijo.0803398 |pmid=16733526 |s2cid=22804583 }}&lt;/ref&gt; "lazy", "gluttonous", "stupid", "incompetent", or "unmotivated".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Puhl |first1=Rebecca |last2=King |first2=Kelly |title=Weight discrimination and bullying |journal=Best Practice &amp; Research Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism |date=2013 |volume=27 |issue=3 |pages=117–127 |doi=10.1016/j.beem.2012.12.002 |pmid=23731874 |url=https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1521690X12001182 |access-date=16 May 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; This bias is not restricted to [[clinically obese]] individuals. It also encompasses those whose [[body shape]] is found to be unacceptable when compared to modern society's perception of the ideal body type (although still within the normal or overweight [[body mass index]] (BMI) range).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1037/h0027966 |last1=Lerner|first1=R. |first2=E.|last2=Gellert |year=1969 |title=Body build identification, preference and aversion in children|journal=Developmental Psychology |volume=1|issue=5 |pages=456–462}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fat-shaming is fairly common in the United States, even though most adult Americans are overweight. ''Huffington Post'' wrote "two-thirds of American adults are overweight or obese. Yet [[overweight]] and obese individuals are subject to discrimination from employers, healthcare professionals, and potential romantic partners".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title = LOOK: The Bravest Woman We've Met This Week|url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/02/07/haley-morris-cafiero-photographer-wait-watchers-fat-acceptance-weight-stigma_n_2631439.html |newspaper = The Huffington Post|access-date = 2015-11-11|date = 2013-02-07 |last1 = Bahadur |first1 = Nina }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Unreliable source?|reason=Opinion piece.|date=September 2020}}

Anti-fat bias can be moderated by giving a mitigating context to the individual's appearance of obesity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1037/0278-6133.22.1.68 |last1=Teachman|first1=B.A. |first2=K.D.|last2=Gapinski |first3=K.D.|last3=Brownell |first4=M.|last4=Rawlins |first5=S.|last5=Jeyaram |year=2003 |title=Demonstrations of implicit anti-fat bias: The impact of providing causal information and evoking empathy|journal=Health Psychology |volume=22|issue=1 |pages=68–78 |pmid=12558204|citeseerx=10.1.1.457.4126}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, when told an individual was obese because of "[[overeating]]" and "[[Sedentary lifestyle|lack of exercise]]", a higher implicit bias was found among study participants than those not provided with context.  When the group was told that "[[Genetics of obesity|genetics]]" was to blame, they did not exhibit a lowered implicit bias after the explanation.

Anti-fat bias is not a strictly Western cultural phenomenon. Instances of implicit anti-fat bias have been found across several cultures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Crandall|first1=C. |first2=S.|last2=D'Anello |first3=N.|last3=Sakalli |first4=E.|last4=Lazarus |first5=G.|last5=Nejtardt |first6=N.|last6=Feather |year=2001 |title=An attribution-model of prejudice: Anti-fat attitudes in six nations|journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin |volume=27 |issue=1|pages=30–37 |doi=10.1177/0146167201271003 |s2cid=145687152 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, recent work around physical appearance issues, [[body image]], and anti-fat or obesity prejudice suggests that feelings about one's own appearance may stimulate downward physical comparisons with obese individuals in order to make one feel better about one's own physical appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = O'Brien | first1 = KS | last2 = Hunter | first2 = JA | last3 = Halberstadt | first3 = J | last4 = Anderson | first4 = J | year = 2007 | title = Body image and explicit and implicit anti-fat attitudes: The mediating role of physical appearance comparisons | journal = Body Image | volume = 4 | issue = 3| pages = 249–256 | doi=10.1016/j.bodyim.2007.06.001| pmid = 18089271 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = O'Brien | first1 = KS | last2 = Caputi | first2 = P | last3 = Minto | first3 = R | last4 = Peoples | first4 = G | last5 = Hooper | first5 = C | last6 = Kell | first6 = S |display-authors=etal | year = 2009 | title = Upward and Downward Physical Appearance-Related Comparisons: Development of a Measure and Examination of Predictive Qualities | journal = Body Image | volume = 6 | issue = 3| pages = 201–206 | doi=10.1016/j.bodyim.2009.03.003| pmid = 19447692 | url = https://www.research.manchester.ac.uk/portal/en/publications/upward-and-downward-physical-appearance-comparisons-development-of-scales-and-examination-of-predictive-qualities(e9023536-f0f9-4d17-b76e-162fec13261a).html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Weight discrimination==
Weight stigma is present in multiple settings including healthcare, education, interpersonal situations, multiple media forms and outlets, and across many levels of employment.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

===In the media===
{{see also|Obesity social stigma in television}}
Media, in general, overrepresents underweight individuals and underrepresents overweight individuals. One-third of women in television are classified as underweight, while only 5% of the general population falls into that category.&lt;ref name=":9"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Himes|first1=Susan M.|last2=Thompson|first2=J. Kevin|date=March 2007|title=Fat Stigmatization in Television Shows and Movies: A Content Analysis|journal=Obesity|volume=15|issue=3|pages=712–718|doi=10.1038/oby.2007.635|pmid=17372322|issn=1930-7381|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conversely, a study on over a thousand major television characters from 2003 identified 14% of female characters and 24% of male characters to be overweight, despite the real-world percentages being more than double those reported numbers.&lt;ref name=":10"&gt;{{Cite web|last=Averill|first=Linsey|date=August 2017|title=Fattitude The Movie: Theory and Praxis of Creating a Documentary that Examines Fat Representation and Fat Social Justice |url=https://fau.digital.flvc.org/islandora/object/fau%3A37996/datastream/OBJ/view/Fattitude_The_Movie__Theory_and_Praxis_of_Creating_a_Documentary_that_Examines_Fat_Representation_and_Fat_Social_Justice.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.2105/AJPH.93.8.1342 |last1=Greenberg|first1=B.|first2=M.|last2=Eastin|first3=L.|last3=Hofschire|first4=K.
|last4=Lachlan|first5=K.|last5=Brownell|year=2003|title=Portrayals of Overweight and Obese Individuals on Commercial Television|journal=American Journal of Public Health|volume=93|issue=8|pages=1342–1348|pmid=12893625|pmc=1447967}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Even when overweight people are included in television, they often play minor, stereotyped roles. Nearly two thirds of the most popular children's movies contain negative portrayals of fat people, stereotyping them to be unintelligent, lazy, and evil.&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt; Fat television characters are more commonly seen eating and are less likely to be involved in romantic relationships compared to average weight television characters.&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt; Male characters are less commonly portrayed as having close friendships.&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt;

In 2007, another analysis sampled 135 scenes featuring overweight individuals from popular television programs and movies and coded for anti-fat humor. The majority of anti-fat humor found was verbal and directed at the individual in their presence.&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt; Additionally, a relationship was found between audience laughter and a male character poking fun at a female character's body, but that same relationship wasn't there when it was a female character ridiculing a fat male.&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt;

There is a great deal of empirical research to support the idea of [[The Thin Ideal|Thin Ideal]] media, or the idea that the media tends to glorify and focus on thin actors and actresses, models, and other public figures while avoiding the use of overweight individuals.

Puhl et al. (2009) also reviewed how in entertainment, news reporting, and advertising, media is a particularly potent source of weight stigma. News reports have blamed individuals who are overweight and obese for various societal issues including prices of fuel, global temperature trends, and precipitating weight gain among their peers.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The news media repeatedly engages in the "Headless Fatties" phenomenon, coined by [[Charlotte Cooper (author)|Charlotte Cooper]], in which images and videos only depict overweight individuals as bodies by cropping out their heads. This objectification happens in 72% of all news reports on obesity.&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt;

The [[University of California, Los Angeles]], conducted a study that analyzed scientific research on weight and the news reports on such research. They looked for disparities in language, the cited causes of obesity, and proposed solution. News stories were more likely than the scientific articles to dramatized language, words such as epidemic, crisis, war, and terrorism, and were more likely to cite individual behaviors as the causes and solutions to obesity, ignoring the systemic issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Saguy|first1=Abigail C.|last2=Almeling|first2=Rene|date=2008|title=Fat in the Fire? Science, the News Media, and the "Obesity Epidemic"|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/20110247|journal=Sociological Forum|volume=23|issue=1|pages=53–83|doi=10.1111/j.1600-0838.2004.00399.x-i1|jstor=20110247|issn=0884-8971}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 29, 2011, prominent nationally syndicated columnist [[Michael Kinsley]] (founding editor of ''Slate'' magazine) wrote, "New Jersey Governor Chris Christie cannot be president: He is just too fat ... why should Christie's weight be more than we can bear in a president? Why should it even be a legitimate issue if he runs? One reason is that a presidential candidate should be judged on behavior and character ... Perhaps Christie is the one to help us get our national appetites under control. But it would help if he got his own under control first."&lt;ref name="Kinsley"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-09-30/requiem-for-a-governor-before-he-s-in-the-ring-michael-kinsley.html|first=Michael|last=Kinsley|date=September 29, 2011|title=Requiem for a Governor Before He's in the Ring: Michael Kinsley|newspaper=Bloomberg.com|publisher=[[Bloomberg View]]|access-date=2011-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Governor Christie responded on October 4, 2011, stating "The people who pretend to be serious commentators who wrote about this are among the most ignorant I've ever heard in my life. To say that, because you're overweight, you are therefore undisciplined—you know, I don't think undisciplined people get to achieve great positions in our society, so that kind of stuff is just ignorant."&lt;ref name="Christie"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/05/us/politics/christie-says-jokes-are-ok-but-not-political-debate-on-weight.html|first=Chris|last=Christie|date=October 4, 2011|title=Pundits Pack Meaner Punch Than Comedians' Fat Jokes|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|access-date=2011-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, [[Haley Morris-Cafiero]]'s photography project "Wait Watchers", in which she photographed the reactions to her presence by random passers-by, went viral.  ''New York'' magazine wrote, "The frequency with which Morris-Cafiero succeeds at documenting passersby's visible disdain for her body seems pretty depressing".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nymag.com/thecut/2014/11/photographer-who-captures-fat-shaming-on-film.html|title=The Photographer Who Captures Fat-Shaming on Camera|last=Schwiegershausen|first=Erica|work=[[New York (magazine)|The Cut]]|date=November 19, 2014|access-date=November 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is also evidence that especially young adults and adolescents experience weight stigma on social media. For example, a study suggests that adolescent patients with obesity experience derogatory comments about weight and visual self-presentation in their online social networks. The study found that this was particularly evident among girls and that they avoided sharing weight-related images on social media (such as close-up images of their bodies or pictures of food that they perceive as "unhealthy" or "fattening").&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Holmberg|first1=Christopher|last2=Berg|first2=Christina|last3=Hillman|first3=Thomas| last4=Lissner|first4=Lauren|last5=Chaplin|first5=John E.|date=2018-10-16|title= Self-presentation in digital media among adolescent patients with obesity: Striving for integrity, risk-reduction, and social recognition|journal=Digital Health|volume=4|pages=205520761880760|doi=10.1177/2055207618807603|pmid=30349733|pmc=6195003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In education===
In regards to more direct weight bias, obese individuals were 40–50% more likely to report a perception of major discrimination compared to those of average weight across a multitude of settings.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Carr|first1=Deborah|last2=Friedman|first2=Michael A.|date=2005-09-01|title=Is Obesity Stigmatizing? Body Weight, Perceived Discrimination, and Psychological Well-Being in the United States|journal=Journal of Health and Social Behavior|language=en|volume=46|issue=3|pages=244–259|doi=10.1177/002214650504600303|issn=0022-1465|pmid=16259147|citeseerx=10.1.1.407.990|s2cid=8396227}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the educational setting, those who are overweight as youth often face peer rejection&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Wardle|first1=Jane|last2=Cooke|first2=Lucy|title=The impact of obesity on psychological well-being|journal=Best Practice &amp; Research Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism|volume=19|issue=3|pages=421–440|doi=10.1016/j.beem.2005.04.006|pmid=16150384|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are bullied more.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Wann|first=Marilyn|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt9qg2bh|title=The Fat Studies Reader|date=2009|publisher=NYU Press|jstor=j.ctt9qg2bh|isbn=978-0-8147-7630-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Overweight children have poorer school performance if they experience weight-based teasing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Krukowski|first1=Rebecca A.|last2=Smith West|first2=Delia|last3=Philyaw Perez|first3=Amanda|last4=Bursac|first4=Zoran|last5=Phillips|first5=Martha M.|last6=Raczynski|first6=James M.|date=2009|title=Overweight children, weight-based teasing and academic performance|url=http://informahealthcare.com/doi/abs/10.3109/17477160902846203|journal=International Journal of Pediatric Obesity|language=en|volume=4|issue=4|pages=274–280|doi=10.3109/17477160902846203|pmid=19922042|issn=1747-7166}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between fifth and eighth grade, a child's increase in BMI results in a decrease in their teacher's perception of that student's ability,&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt; and 50% of principals believe fatness is just a result of lacking self control.&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt; Teachers, particularly those teaching physical education classes, sometimes express negative attitudes towards overweight individuals.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Research suggests that within the classroom teachers may perceive overweight individuals' work more poorly compared to average weight individuals.&lt;ref name="Kenney Redman Criss Sonneville pp. 141–152"&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Kenney | first1=Erica L. | last2=Redman | first2=Morgan T. | last3=Criss | first3=Shaniece | last4=Sonneville | first4=Kendrin R. | last5=Austin | first5=S. Bryn | title=Are K-12 school environments harming students with obesity? A qualitative study of classroom teachers | journal=Eating and Weight Disorders - Studies on Anorexia, Bulimia and Obesity | publisher=Springer Science and Business Media LLC | volume=22 | issue=1 | date=2016-03-15 | issn=1124-4909 | doi=10.1007/s40519-016-0268-6 | pages=141–152| pmid=26980318 | s2cid=30817927 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Students also perceive overweight individuals as being likely to have lower GPAs, and students are less likely to want to do groupwork with overweight individuals compared to average weight individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Alexander |first1=KE |last2=Alexander |first2=RG |title=Evidence of Weight Bias in the College Classroom: A Call for Inclusive Teaching Practices for Students of All Sizes |journal=College Teaching |date=2021 |pages=1–8 |doi=10.1080/87567555.2021.1978378|s2cid=239199555 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Research has also found that overweight females receive less financial support for education from their families than average weight females, after controlling for ethnicity, family size, income, and education.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; As individuals grow older they may be less likely to be admitted to college than individuals of an average weight, and in some cases, people were admitted to academic institutions then dismissed due to their weight.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Puhl and colleagues (2009) concluded from their review of weight stigma in education that current trends indicate students with obesity face barriers to educational success at every level of education.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Reviewed research demonstrates that educators, particularly physical education teachers, report antifat attitudes toward their students with obesity, which may undermine educational achievement.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Importantly, the education disparities for students with obesity appear to be strongest for students attending schools where obesity is not the norm. Several studies have evidenced that in environments such as these, students with obesity face greater educational disadvantages and are less likely to attend college, an effect that is particularly strong among women.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Moreover, weight stigma in educational settings also affects interpersonal relationships (see "Interpersonal situations" below).&lt;ref name=":4b" /&gt;

===In employment===
Studies suggest that obese individuals are less likely to be hired and once hired, have greater termination rates than average weight individuals.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;  Specifically, a national survey found that obese individuals were 26% more likely not to be hired, not receive a promotion, or to be fired compared to average weight persons.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;  Such outcomes may be a result of employers viewing them as less agreeable, less competent and lazier than average weight individuals.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Weight stigma can lead to difficulty obtaining a job, worse job placement, lower wages and compensation, unjustified denial of promotions, harsher discipline, unfair job termination, and commonplace derogatory jokes and comments from coworkers and supervisors.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; In their review, Rebecca M. Puhl et al. find that employees with obesity report their weight as the most influential factor contributing to losing their job.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Another review by Giel and colleagues (2010) found that certain stereotypes about employees with obesity are highly endorsed by employers and supervisors, in particular that they have poorer job performance and that they lack interpersonal skills, motivation, and self-control.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Weight Bias in Work Settings – a Qualitative Review|journal = Obesity Facts|pages = 33–40|volume = 3|issue = 1|doi = 10.1159/000276992|pmid = 20215793|first1 = Katrin Elisabeth|last1 = Giel|first2 = Ansgar|last2 = Thiel|first3 = Martin|last3 = Teufel|first4 = Jochen|last4 = Mayer|first5 = Stephan|last5 = Zipfel|date = March 2010|pmc = 6452122}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In politics===
[[File:Chris Christie by Gage Skidmore 5.jpg|thumb|250px|New Jersey Governor [[Chris Christie]] is a politician who was subjected to weight-related discrimination during his political career.&lt;ref name="Kinsley" /&gt;]]
A study by [[Michigan State University]] researchers shows evidence that overweight political candidates tend to receive fewer votes than their thinner opponents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Weight bias plagues U. S. elections |url=https://msutoday.msu.edu/news/2014/weight-bias-plagues-us-elections/ |access-date=7 February 2021 |agency=MSUToday |publisher=Michigan State University |date=May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The researchers analyzed data from the 2008 and 2012 U.S. Senate elections. Using a previously established scientific method, research assistants determined from color photos whether the candidates in 126 primary and general elections were of normal weight, overweight, or obese.

Both obese men and women were often less likely to get on the ballot in the first place. When it came to merely being overweight, women were seen underrepresented on the ballot, though men were not. This is consistent with previous research showing slightly overweight men tend not to experience the same discrimination as slightly overweight women.

However, when it came to the voting, both male and female candidates, whether obese or simply overweight, tend to get a lower share of the vote total than their more slender opponents. Some politicians have resorted to extreme weight loss measures, including surgery, to increase their elect-ability to political office. 
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2014/05/140519160753.htm|title=Weight bias plagues U.S. elections, study finds|website=ScienceDaily}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Unreliable source?|reason=Dubious.|date=September 2020}}

===In healthcare===
Medical professionals may be more likely to view obese individuals in negative terms (such as annoying or undisciplined), have less patience with obese individuals, and assume non-compliance with their treatments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hebl |first1=M |last2=Xu |first2=J. |title=Weighing the care: physicians' reactions to the size of a patient |journal=International Journal of Obesity |date=August 2001 |volume=25 |issue=8 |pages=1246–1252 |doi=10.1038/sj.ijo.0801681 |pmid=11477511 |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, these individuals may receive poorer care compared to average weight people. Doctors have reported less intervention and an avoidance of weight-related discussion with obese patients.{{cn|date=August 2022}} Additionally, nurses have reported a reluctance to touch obese persons during treatment.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; A national survey of the United States found that individuals who were overweight reported a three times higher likelihood to be denied medical care than average weight people.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;  In the UK, 25 out of 91 primary care trusts have bans for the treatment of obese individuals in addition to weight loss requirements.&lt;ref name="The Observer"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Campbell |first1=Denis |title=Doctors back denial of treatment for smokers and the obese |url=https://www.theguardian.com/society/2012/apr/28/doctors-treatment-denial-smokers-obese |website=The Guardian |date=28 April 2012 |publisher=The Observer |access-date=3 March 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, a 2012 survey revealed that 54% of doctor respondents believe the National Health Service should have the ability to withhold non-emergency treatment from obese individuals.&lt;ref name="The Observer"/&gt; Further, health professionals who specialize in obesity showed strong implicit and explicit anti-fat bias as measured by self-report and the [[Implicit-association test|Implicit Associations Test]] (IAT).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Schwartz|first1=Marlene B.|last2=Chambliss|first2=Heather O'Neal|last3=Brownell|first3=Kelly D.|last4=Blair|first4=Steven N.|last5=Billington|first5=Charles|date=2003-09-01|title=Weight Bias among Health Professionals Specializing in Obesity|journal=Obesity Research|language=en|volume=11|issue=9|pages=1033–1039|doi=10.1038/oby.2003.142|issn=1550-8528|pmid=12972672|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, such biases were mixed amongst dietitians and nutritionists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Jung|first1=Franziska U. C. E.|last2=Luck-Sikorski|first2=Claudia|last3=Wiemers|first3=Nina|last4=Riedel-Heller|first4=Steffi G.|date=2015-10-14|title=Dietitians and Nutritionists: Stigma in the Context of Obesity. A Systematic Review|journal=PLOS ONE|volume=10|issue=10|pages=e0140276|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0140276|issn=1932-6203|pmid=26466329|pmc=4605484|bibcode=2015PLoSO..1040276J|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In their 2009 review, Puhl and colleagues found that many studies provide evidence supporting the notion that health professionals (including doctors, nurses, medical students, fitness professional, and dietitians) consistently endorse negative stereotypes about patients with obesity, in particular ascribing to them culpability for their weight status.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Weight stigma in the healthcare settings leads to impaired patient-provider communication, poorer doctor-patient relationships, poorer medical care and treatment (for example doctors spending less time with patients), and avoidance of the healthcare system all together on the part of the patient.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; However, it is important to point out that the evidence that has been reviewed thus far comes primarily from self-report studies. Therefore, Puhl and colleagues concluded that research examining actual health outcomes is needed.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Overall, the impact of weight stigma in healthcare has become so problematic that many scholars have suggested that obesity-prevention programs should make minimizing stigma a priority.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Obesity, stigma and public health planning|journal = Health Promotion International|date = 2009-03-01|issn = 0957-4824|pmid = 19131400|pages = 88–93|volume = 24|issue = 1|doi = 10.1093/heapro/dan041|first1 = Lynne|last1 = MacLean|first2 = Nancy|last2 = Edwards|first3 = Michael|last3 = Garrard|first4 = Nicki|last4 = Sims-Jones|first5 = Kathryn|last5 = Clinton|first6 = Lisa|last6 = Ashley|doi-access = free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Interpersonal situations===
Although a less studied topic than employment and healthcare, several studies reviewed by Puhl and colleagues (2009) provide evidence that overweight and obese women in particular face weight stigma from many interpersonal sources including family, friends, and romantic partners.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Another recent review by Puhl and Suh (2015) also documented that in school settings weight-based bullying is one of the most prevalent types of harassment reported by parents, teachers, and students.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; Experiencing interpersonal weight stigma is related to myriad negative physical and mental health consequences (see "[[#Mental health and psychological consequences|Mental health and psychological consequences]]" below).

In a 2017 study, results showed that 89% of obese adults had been bullied by romantic partners.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Influence of Experienced and Internalized Weight Stigma and Coping on Weight Loss Outcomes among Adults |author=Lenz, Erin M. |date=2017 |url=https://opencommons.uconn.edu/dissertations/1556 |journal=Doctoral Dissertations |access-date=2021-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Hobbes|first=Michael|title=Everything You Know About Obesity Is Wrong|url=https://highline.huffingtonpost.com/articles/en/everything-you-know-about-obesity-is-wrong/|access-date=2021-09-14|website=The Huffington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In early development===
This external stigmatization and its internalized effects have been examined across different age groups. Overweight and obese children and adolescents experience stigmatization from parents, teachers, and peers.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Puhl|first1=Rebecca M.|last2=Latner|first2=Janet D.|title=Stigma, obesity, and the health of the nation's children.|journal=Psychological Bulletin|volume=133|issue=4|pages=557–580|doi=10.1037/0033-2909.133.4.557|pmid=17592956|year=2007|citeseerx=10.1.1.175.4474}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peer stigmatization, especially, may be difficult for overweight adolescents considering the role of peer support in promoting identity development and self-esteem.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Janssen|first1=Ian|last2=Craig|first2=Wendy M.|last3=Boyce|first3=William F.|last4=Pickett|first4=William|date=2004-05-01|title=Associations between overweight and obesity with bullying behaviors in school-aged children|journal=Pediatrics|volume=113|issue=5|pages=1187–1194|issn=1098-4275|pmid=15121928|doi=10.1542/peds.113.5.1187}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some research suggests that negative attitudes about being overweight are even held by overweight and obese children themselves. Specifically, weight bias may become internalized and increases throughout childhood. It then decreases and levels-off during late adolescence and adulthood.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

Weight-based teasing in childhood and adolescence has been associated with a variety of damages to psychosocial health, including reduced [[self-esteem]] and lower [[self-concept]],&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Davison|first1=Kirsten Krahnstoever|last2=Birch|first2=Leann Lipps|author-link2=Leann Birch|title=Processes linking weight status and self-concept among girls from ages 5 to 7 years.|journal=Developmental Psychology|volume=38|issue=5|pages=735–748|doi=10.1037/0012-1649.38.5.735|pmid=12220051|pmc=2530914|year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; higher rates of [[Depression (mood)|depression]] and [[anxiety disorder]]s,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Associations of weight-based teasing and emotional well-being among adolescents|journal=Archives of Pediatrics and Adolescent Medicine|volume=157}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Russell-Mayhew|first1=Shelly|last2=McVey|first2=Gail|last3=Bardick|first3=Angela|last4=Ireland|first4=Alana|date=2012-06-24|title=Mental Health, Wellness, and Childhood Overweight/Obesity|journal=Journal of Obesity|language=en|volume=2012|pages=281801|doi=10.1155/2012/281801|pmid=22778915|pmc=3388583|issn=2090-0708|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Keery|first1=Helene|last2=Boutelle|first2=Kerri|last3=Berg|first3=Patricia van den|last4=Thompson|first4=J. Kevin|title=The impact of appearance-related teasing by family members|journal=Journal of Adolescent Health|volume=37|issue=2|pages=120–127|doi=10.1016/j.jadohealth.2004.08.015|pmid=16026721|date=August 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; and even greater likelihood of entertaining suicidal thoughts.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Further, weight-based teasing has been associated with higher rates of [[binge eating]] and unhealthy weight control (e.g., fasting, self-induced vomiting, laxatives, diet pills, skipped meals and smoking).&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Weight-teasing among adolescents: Correlations with weight status and disordered eating behaviors|journal=International Journal of Obesity|volume=26|issue=1|pages=123–131|doi=10.1038/sj.ijo.0801853 |pmid=11791157|year=2002|last1=Neumark-Sztainer|first1=D.|last2=Falkner|first2=N.|last3=Story|first3=M.|last4=Perry|first4=C.|last5=Hannan|first5=PJ|last6=Mulert|first6=S.|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Haines|first1=Jess|last2=Neumark-Sztainer|first2=Dianne|last3=Eisenberg|first3=Marla E.|last4=Hannan|first4=Peter J.|date=2006-02-01|title=Weight Teasing and Disordered Eating Behaviors in Adolescents: Longitudinal Findings From Project EAT (Eating Among Teens)|url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/117/2/e209|journal=Pediatrics|language=en|volume=117|issue=2|pages=e209–e215|doi=10.1542/peds.2005-1242|issn=0031-4005|pmid=16452330|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Overweight adolescents who were bullied were also more likely to meet criteria for bulimia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Kaltiala-Heino|first1=R.|last2=Rissanen|first2=A.|last3=Rimpela|first3=M.|last4=Rantanen|first4=P.|date=1999-07-01|title=Bulimia and bulimic behaviour in middle adolescence: more common than thought?|journal=Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica|language=en|volume=100|issue=1|pages=33–39|doi=10.1111/j.1600-0447.1999.tb10911.x|pmid=10442437|s2cid=33760723|issn=1600-0447}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A survey of 7,266 children aged 11 to 16 conducted by the [[World Health Organization]] reported higher rates of physical victimization (e.g., being shoved) with increasing [[body mass index]] (BMI) among girls. Additionally, these results showed relational victimization (i.e., being excluded or having rumors spread about you) was reported more often at increasing BMI by both girls and boys.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; A separate survey of 7,825 students aged 11 to 17 also noted that, compared to average-weight peers, obese boys and overweight girls were more likely to be victims of bullying. Additionally, obese girls were more likely to be victims and perpetrators of bullying than their peers. Notably, overweight and obese adolescent girls also reported higher rates of smoking, drinking, and marijuana use relative to their normal-weight peers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Farhat|first1=Tilda|last2=Iannotti|first2=Ronald J.|last3=Simons-Morton|first3=Bruce G.|title=Overweight, Obesity, Youth, and Health-Risk Behaviors|journal=American Journal of Preventive Medicine|volume=38|issue=3|pages=258–267|doi=10.1016/j.amepre.2009.10.038|pmid=20171527|pmc=2826832|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Health-related outcomes associated with weight discrimination ==
In adulthood, individuals who experience weight discrimination are more likely to identify themselves as overweight regardless of their actual weight status.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Schafer|first1=Markus H.|last2=Ferraro|first2=Kenneth F.|date=2011-03-01|title=The Stigma of Obesity Does Perceived Weight Discrimination Affect Identity and Physical Health?|journal=Social Psychology Quarterly|language=en|volume=74|issue=1|pages=76–97|doi=10.1177/0190272511398197|s2cid=43671749|issn=0190-2725}}&lt;/ref&gt; The experience of weight stigma can function as motivation to avoid stigmatizing environments, and although it may motivate one to escape stigma through weight loss, it undermines one's capacity to do so.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Hunger|first1=Jeffrey M.|last2=Major|first2=Brenda|last3=Blodorn|first3=Alison|last4=Miller|first4=Carol T.|date=2015-06-01|title=Weighed Down by Stigma: How Weight-Based Social Identity Threat Contributes to Weight Gain and Poor Health|journal=Social and Personality Psychology Compass|language=en|volume=9|issue=6|pages=255–268|doi=10.1111/spc3.12172|pmid=29225670|pmc=5720363|issn=1751-9004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers have linked weight stigma to decreases in physical activity,&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bombak|first=Andrea E.|date=2015-01-01|title=Obese persons' physical activity experiences and motivations across weight changes: a qualitative exploratory study|journal=BMC Public Health|volume=15|pages=1129|doi=10.1186/s12889-015-2456-0|issn=1471-2458|pmid=26577260|pmc=4650293}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Puhl|first1=Rebecca M.|last2=King|first2=Kelly M.|title=Weight discrimination and bullying|journal=Best Practice &amp; Research Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism|volume=27|issue=2|pages=117–127|doi=10.1016/j.beem.2012.12.002|pmid=23731874|year=2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; decreases in seeking health care&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt; and increases in maladaptive eating patterns such as binge eating.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt; In addition, those who have experienced weight stigma have shown altered cardiovascular reactivity, increased cortisol level, oxidative stress, and inflammation.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;{{Unreliable source?|reason=Conclusion unwarranted.|date=September 2020}}

People who expect to be fat-shamed by healthcare providers are less likely to seek care for medical issues or for weight loss, even if the weight gain is caused by medical problems.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://longreads.com/2017/10/26/no-fatties-when-healthcare-hurts/|title='No Fatties': When Health Care&amp;nbsp;Hurts|last=Purcell|first=Carey|date=2017-10-26|work=Longreads|access-date=2018-05-06|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In terms of psychological health, researchers found that obese individuals demonstrated a lower sense of well-being relative to non-obese individuals if they had perceived weight stigmatization even after controlling for other demographic factors such as age and sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Jackson|first1=Sarah E.|last2=Beeken|first2=Rebecca J.|last3=Wardle|first3=Jane|date=2015-05-01|title=Obesity, perceived weight discrimination, and psychological well-being in older adults in England|journal=Obesity|language=en|volume=23|issue=5|pages=1105–1111|doi=10.1002/oby.21052|pmid=25809860|pmc=4414736|issn=1930-739X|url=http://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/1464272/3/Jackson.oby21052-1.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Overweight and obese individuals report experiencing forms of internalized stigma such as body dissatisfaction as well as decreased social support and feelings of loneliness.&lt;ref name=":8"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Phelan|first1=Sean M.|last2=Burgess|first2=Diana J.|last3=Puhl|first3=Rebecca|last4=Dyrbye|first4=Liselotte N.|last5=Dovidio|first5=John F.|last6=Yeazel|first6=Mark|last7=Ridgeway|first7=Jennifer L.|last8=Nelson|first8=David|last9=Perry|first9=Sylvia|date=2015-07-15|title=The Adverse Effect of Weight Stigma on the Well-Being of Medical Students with Overweight or Obesity: Findings from a National Survey|journal=Journal of General Internal Medicine|language=en|volume=30|issue=9|pages=1251–1258|doi=10.1007/s11606-015-3266-x|pmid=26173517|pmc=4539327|issn=0884-8734}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Sikorski|first1=Claudia|last2=Luppa|first2=Melanie|last3=Luck|first3=Tobias|last4=Riedel-Heller|first4=Steffi G.|date=2015-02-01|title=Weight stigma "gets under the skin"—evidence for an adapted psychological mediation framework—a systematic review|journal=Obesity|language=en|volume=23|issue=2|pages=266–276|doi=10.1002/oby.20952|pmid=25627624|s2cid=8497074|issn=1930-739X|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, similar to findings in adolescence, weight stigma in adulthood is associated with lower self-esteem, higher rates of depression, anxiety, and substance abuse.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt;

In both adults and children with obesity, several reviews of the literature have found that across a variety of studies, there is a consistent relationship between experiencing weight stigma and many negative mental and physical health outcomes.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1b" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":3b"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Papadopoulos|first1=Stephanie|last2=Brennan|first2=Leah|date=2015-09-01|title=Correlates of weight stigma in adults with obesity: A systematic literature review|journal=Obesity|volume=23|issue=9|pages=1743–1760|doi=10.1002/oby.21187|pmid=26260279|issn=1930-739X|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":4b"&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Health Consequences of Weight Stigma: Implications for Obesity Prevention and Treatment|journal = Current Obesity Reports|date = 2015-04-01|issn = 2162-4968|pages = 182–190|volume = 4|issue = 2|doi = 10.1007/s13679-015-0153-z|pmid = 26627213|first1 = Rebecca|last1 = Puhl|first2 = Young|last2 = Suh|s2cid = 24953213}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":5c"&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Stigma and Eating and Weight Disorders|journal = Current Psychiatry Reports|date = 2015-02-05|issn = 1523-3812|pages = 552|volume = 17|issue = 3|doi = 10.1007/s11920-015-0552-6|pmid = 25652251|first1 = Rebecca|last1 = Puhl|first2 = Young|last2 = Suh|s2cid = 207338325}}&lt;/ref&gt; These will be discussed separately in the sections below, although physical and mental health consequences are often intertwined, in particular those related to eating disorders.

Papadopoulos and Brennan (2015) recently found that across many reviewed studies of weight loss treatment-seeking adults,&lt;ref name=":3b" /&gt; relationships emerged between experiencing weight stigma and both BMI and difficulty losing weight.  However the findings are somewhat mixed. They also report evidence that experiencing weight stigma is related to poor medication adherence. Among weight loss treatment-seeking adults, experiencing weight stigma might exacerbate weight- and health-related quality of life issues.&lt;ref name=":3b" /&gt; This review along with reviews by Vartanian and Smyth (2013) and Puhl and Suh (2015) have also found that across several studies and in both adults and children, experiencing weight stigma is related to decreased exercise behavior overall, as well as decreased motivation to exercise, decreased exercise [[self-efficacy]], and increased food craving and tendency to overeat.&lt;ref name=":1b" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":3b" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; It is important to note that these effects of weight stigma on exercise and physical activity emerge independent of body mass index, suggesting that weight stigma becomes a unique barrier to physical activity outside of barriers that may be associated with obesity in particular. Finally, across many studies, Puhl and Suh (2015) also found that experiencing weight stigma is related to many physiological consequences as well, including increased [[blood pressure]], augmented [[Glucocorticoid receptor|cortisol]] reactivity, elevated [[oxidative stress]], impaired glycemic control/elevated [[Glycated hemoglobin|HbA&lt;sub&gt;1c&lt;/sub&gt;]], and increased systemic [[inflammation]],&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":5c" /&gt; all of which have notable consequences for physical health and disease.

=== Mental health and psychological consequences ===
Broadly speaking, experiencing weight stigma is associated with psychological distress. There are many negative effects connected to anti-fat bias, the most prominent being that societal bias against fat is ineffective at treating obesity, and leads to long-lasting body image issues, eating disorders, suicide, and depression.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=S. Gavin|first1=Gabriel C.|title=What's Wrong With 'Fat Shaming?'|url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/wiring-the-mind/201501/whats-wrong-fat-shaming|website=psychologytoday.com|publisher=Psychology Today|access-date=7 November 2017|date=4 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Papadopoulos's 2015 review of the literature found that across several studies, this distress can manifest in [[anxiety]], [[Major depressive disorder|depression]], lowered [[self-esteem]], and [[substance use disorder]]s, both in weight loss treatment-seeking individuals as well as community samples.&lt;ref name=":3b" /&gt; Many empirical reviews have found that weight stigma has clear consequences for individuals suffering from eating and weight disorders (including [[anorexia nervosa]], [[bulimia nervosa]], and [[binge eating disorder]]), as it plays a unique role, over and above other risk factors, in perpetuating disordered eating psychopathology.&lt;ref name=":3b" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":5c" /&gt; These results have emerged in both adult and adolescent, as well as in male and female samples.

== Policy ==
Over the past few decades, many scholars{{who|date=October 2021}} have identified weight stigma as a long-standing form of social stigma and one of the last remaining socially acceptable forms of prejudice.&lt;ref name="Jovančević Jović p=003329412110051"&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Jovančević | first1=Ana | last2=Jović | first2=Miljan | title=The Relation Between Anti-Fat Stereotypes and Anti-Fat Prejudices: The Role of Gender as a Moderator | journal=Psychological Reports | publisher=SAGE Publications | date=2021-03-31 | volume=125 | issue=3 | pages=1687–1713 | issn=0033-2941 | doi=10.1177/00332941211005123 | pmid=33789533 | s2cid=232481900 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It follows then that individuals who are targets because of overweight and obesity, still face uniquely socially acceptable discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Bias, Discrimination, and Obesity|journal = Obesity Research|date = 2001-12-01|issn = 1550-8528|pages = 788–805|volume = 9|issue = 12|doi = 10.1038/oby.2001.108|first1 = Rebecca|last1 = Puhl|first2 = Kelly D.|last2 = Brownell|pmid=11743063|doi-access = free}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Obesity and Socioeconomic Status – A Complex Relation|journal = New England Journal of Medicine|date = 1993-09-30|issn = 0028-4793|pmid = 8366906|pages = 1036–1037|volume = 329|issue = 14|doi = 10.1056/NEJM199309303291411|author-link1=Albert Stunkard|first1 = Albert J.|last1 = Stunkard|first2 = Thorkild I.A.|last2 = Sorensen}}&lt;/ref&gt; Civil rights legislation such as [[Civil Rights Act of 1964|Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964]] prohibits discrimination based on race and several other domains, but weight is not included in this act. At the local level, only one state in the US ([[Michigan]]) has policy in place for prohibiting weight-related employment discrimination and very few local municipalities have human rights ordinances in place to protect individuals of large body size.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tehran, Elizabeth E. (2005). Legal theory on weight discrimination. In K. Brownell, R. Puhl, M. Schwartz, &amp; L. Rudd (Eds.), ''Weight bias: nature, consequences, and'' remedies'' (pp. 195–211). New York, NY.''&lt;/ref&gt; Typically, the only type legislation that overweight and obese individuals can cite in lawsuits is related to disability. For example, the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990|Americans with Disabilities Act]] is one such avenue, but as Puhl et al. (2009) report, it is difficult for many individuals with obesity to qualify as disabled according to the criteria included in this statute.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== Public health ==
The existing literature largely does not support the notion that weight stigma might encourage weight loss; as cited above, experiencing weight stigma (both interpersonally as well as exposure to stigmatizing media campaigns) is consistently related to a lack of motivation to exercise and a propensity to overeat.&lt;ref name=":1b" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":3b" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; In a 2010 review examining whether weight stigma is an appropriate public health tool for treating and preventing overweight and obesity, Puhl and Heuer concluded that stigmatizing individuals with obesity is detrimental in three important ways: (1) it threatens actual physical health, (2) it perpetuates health disparities, and (3) it actually undermines obesity treatment and intervention initiatives.&lt;ref name="Puhl"&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Obesity Stigma: Important Considerations for Public Health|journal = American Journal of Public Health|date = 2010-06-01|issn = 0090-0036|pmc = 2866597|pmid = 20075322|pages = 1019–1028|volume = 100|issue = 6|doi = 10.2105/AJPH.2009.159491|first1 = Rebecca M.|last1 = Puhl|first2 = Chelsea A.|last2 = Heuer}}&lt;/ref&gt; In line with this, another recent review of the consequences of experiencing weight stigma, this one conducted by Puhl and Suh (2015), concluded that considering the myriad negative physical and mental health consequences associated with experiencing weight stigma, it should be a target, instead of a tool, in obesity prevention and treatment.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; These authors further recommend that a necessary first step in reducing weight stigma is raising broader awareness of its negative consequences.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

== Race intersection ==
With higher representation of black people being categorized as overweight by the BMI, the social stigma of obesity disproportionately affects black people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Ogden |first1=Cynthia L. |last2=Carroll |first2=Margaret D. |last3=Kit |first3=Brian K. |last4=Flegal |first4=Katherine M. |date=2014-02-26 |title=Prevalence of Childhood and Adult Obesity in the United States, 2011-2012 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/jama.2014.732 |journal=JAMA |volume=311 |issue=8 |pages=806–814 |doi=10.1001/jama.2014.732 |pmid=24570244 |pmc=4770258 |issn=0098-7484}}&lt;/ref&gt; More than 80% of African American women are categorized as overweight using the Body Mass Index.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Hart |first1=Erica A. |last2=Sbrocco |first2=Tracy |last3=Carter |first3=Michele M. |date=2016-01-21 |title=Ethnic Identity and Implicit Anti-fat Bias: Similarities and Differences between African American and Caucasian Women |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.18865/ed.26.1.69 |journal=Ethnicity &amp; Disease |volume=26 |issue=1 |pages=69–76 |doi=10.18865/ed.26.1.69 |pmid=26843798 |pmc=4738857 |issn=1945-0826}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yet, the BMI was created based on a group of European men and cutoffs have been altered in the US in a non-scientifically verified way, with no distinguishing between appropriate cutoffs for different races.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=Body Mass Index (BMI) |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/springerreference_179795 |work=SpringerReference |year=2011 |place=Berlin/Heidelberg |publisher=Springer-Verlag |doi=10.1007/springerreference_179795 |access-date=2022-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sociologist Sabrina Strings writes, in her book ''Fearing the Black Body'', about the historical ways in which fatphobia emerged out of an attempt by white people to distance themselves from black people. In 1751, [[Denis Diderot]] published the ''Encyclopédie'', which was the first publications to claim that black people were "fond of gluttony."&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last=Sabrina. |first=Strings |title=Fearing the Black Body |date=2020 |url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/1251720412 |publisher=Tantor Media, Inc |oclc=1251720412 |access-date=2022-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1853, French aristocrat [[Arthur de Gobineau]] claimed, about black people, that their "gluttonous nature to be one of their more base characteristics."&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Strings |first=Sabrina |url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1050457278 |title=Fearing the black body : the racial origins of fat phobia |date=2019 |isbn=978-1-4798-8675-3 |location=New York |oclc=1050457278}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1910, [[Charles Davenport]] founded the [[Eugenics Record Office|Eugenic Record Office]], and he claimed that "obesity was a vile condition to be avoided. It was, moreover, racially inherited."&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; [[Eugenics]] sentiment toward black people regarding their size was prevalent.

Body standards differ between black and white communities, but whiteness, and therefore thinness, is seen as the cultural norm.{{clarify|reason=The next sentence says that the cultural norm is thickness in the black communities, not thinness|date=May 2022}} Scholar Elizabeth Hughes discusses this in "I'm Supposed to be Thick:" Managing Body Anxieties Among Black American Women," citing the norm of a "thick" body type, in other words curvier bodies, in the black community.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Hughes |first=Elizabeth |date=2020-11-12 |title="I'm Supposed To Be Thick": Managing Body Image Anxieties Among Black American Women |url=https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0021934720972440 |journal=Journal of Black Studies |volume=52 |issue=3 |pages=310–330 |doi=10.1177/0021934720972440 |s2cid=228879159 |issn=0021-9347}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Black bodies are already stigmatized, which can result in violence when interacting with the social stigma of obesity. In a 2017 article published in the [[African American Review]], one author cited the killing of [[Killing of Eric Garner|Eric Garner]] as an example of this, as some excuses for using excessive force on Garner were his size, as he was an overweight man.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |date=2017-06-22 |title=Unvictimizable: Toward a Fat Black Disability Studies. |url=https://go.gale.com/ps/i.do?p=LitRC&amp;sw=w&amp;issn=10624783&amp;v=2.1&amp;it=r&amp;id=GALE%7CA675550747&amp;sid=googleScholar&amp;linkaccess=abs |journal=African American Review |language=English |volume=50 |issue=2 |pages=105–123|doi=10.1353/afa.2017.0016 |s2cid=149222407 |last1=Mollow |first1=Anna }}&lt;/ref&gt; The article explains how [[ableism]], fatphobia, and racism interact to form a "double bind" in which violence is excused because fatness is already causing inherent injury, but necessary because the size of a large black person is a threat.

A paper published by the [[American Journal of Preventive Medicine]] titled “Intersectionality: An Understudied Framework for Addressing Weight Stigma”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Himmelstein |first1=Mary S. |last2=Puhl |first2=Rebecca M. |last3=Quinn |first3=Diane M. |date=2017-10-01 |title=Intersectionality: An Understudied Framework for Addressing Weight Stigma |url=https://www.ajpmonline.org/article/S0749-3797(17)30224-6/abstract |journal=American Journal of Preventive Medicine |language=English |volume=53 |issue=4 |pages=421–431 |doi=10.1016/j.amepre.2017.04.003 |issn=0749-3797 |pmid=28579331}}&lt;/ref&gt; focused on highlighting the intersectionality between weight stigma and health-related coping responses across several non-white racial and gendered groups. The findings of this publication demonstrated that there were no significant differences in weight stigma as a function of race or gender, having an overall equal representation across all racial groups analyzed. Nonetheless, results additionally demonstrated that different racial groups had differing ways of internalizing and coping with weight and health-related stigmas, which as a result heightened health risks.{{clarify|reason=unclear if having a difference between two groups means that both groups have heightened health risks, and unclear what the specific health risks are|date=May 2022}} Results revealed that white women and men reported higher weight bias internalization in comparison to black women and men. Additionally, Hispanic women demonstrated to cope with weight stigma via disordered eating patterns more than black and white women. The results of this research article highlighted the importance of needing to increase research and policy attention to addressing weight and health-related stigma as an issue regarding prevention and treatment for obesity in order to consequently decrease weight-driven inequalities in communities and differing groups, primarily focused on race and gender.

== Language and identity ==
Preference regarding language varies widely amongst overweight individuals, though there is some consensus on generally unaccepted terms.

[[Person-first language|Person first language]] is not ubiquitous among [[fat acceptance movement]]s, and in fact people{{who|date=May 2022}} view it as an “inherent adverse judgment.”{{citation needed|date=May 2022}} Those who promote person-first language, i.e. using terminology such as a person with obesity, seem to have done so without consultation in fat activist groups.&lt;ref name="Meadows 1527"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Meadows |first1=Angela |last2=Daníelsdóttir |first2=Sigrún |date=2016-10-05 |title=What's in a Word? On Weight Stigma and Terminology |journal=Frontiers in Psychology |volume=7 |pages=1527 |doi=10.3389/fpsyg.2016.01527 |issn=1664-1078 |pmc=5051141 |pmid=27761122|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics of person-first language cite problems with the desire to separate a person from that characteristic, as separating it implies that there is something wrong with being overweight, which contributes to further stigma.&lt;ref name="Meadows 1527"/&gt; Furthermore, person-first language contributes to the [[medicalization]] of obesity, as the language is commonly used when referring to disease.&lt;ref name="Meadows 1527"/&gt;

The term "fat" appears to result in more stigma and judgement from the broader community. Various studies of overweight people seeking [[weight loss]] as well as a semantics study of varied terminology used to describe an overweight individual conclude that using the word fat elicits a negative reaction from people already critical of obesity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=BROCHU |first1=PAULA M. |last2=ESSES |first2=VICTORIA M. |date=August 2011 |title=What's in a Name? The Effects of the Labels "Fat" Versus "Overweight" on Weight Bias1 |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/j.1559-1816.2011.00786.x |journal=Journal of Applied Social Psychology |volume=41 |issue=8 |pages=1981–2008 |doi=10.1111/j.1559-1816.2011.00786.x |issn=0021-9029}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Smith |first1=Christine A. |last2=Schmoll |first2=Karissa |last3=Konik |first3=Julie |last4=Oberlander |first4=Shawna |date=May 2007 |title=Carrying Weight for the World: Influence of Weight Descriptors on Judgments of Large-Sized Women |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/j.1559-1816.2007.00196.x |journal=Journal of Applied Social Psychology |volume=37 |issue=5 |pages=989–1006 |doi=10.1111/j.1559-1816.2007.00196.x |issn=0021-9029}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regarding other terms, "[[obesity]]" was found in one study to be equally as undesirable as "fat" when considering language preferences of overweight individuals.&lt;ref name="Meadows 1527"/&gt;

Yet, "fat" is the preferred term within the fat acceptance movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite thesis |last= Harker |first=Yasmin |date= 2015|title= Fat Rights and Fat Discrimination: An Annotated Bibliography|publisher=CUNY School of Law|url= https://academicworks.cuny.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1095&amp;context=cl_pubs}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fat activists have reclaimed the term as a neutral descriptor in order to work against the stigma typically associated with the term.&lt;ref name="Meadows 1527"/&gt; In fact, many fat activists will censor the word "obesity" when tweeting or citing it as "ob*sity" due to its pathologizing nature.{{citation needed|date=May 2022}} The word "obesity" directly stems from the latin word "obesus" which means "that has eaten itself fat".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=obesity {{!}} Etymology, origin and meaning of obesity by etymonline |url=https://www.etymonline.com/word/obesity |access-date=2022-04-19 |website=www.etymonline.com |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fat activists will also use this latin definition to show stigma in the word "obese" itself, as it places blame on the individual for their state.&lt;ref name=":12"&gt;{{Cite web |last=Gordon |first=Aubrey |date=2021-05-28 |title='Fat' Isn't a Bad Word—It's Just the Way I Describe My Body |url=https://www.self.com/story/fat-isnt-bad-word |access-date=2022-03-30 |website=SELF |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fat activist [[Aubrey Gordon]] argues that "disavowing the term fat reinforces its negative meanings."&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt; Although studies have not been conducted among fat activists on preferred terminology, books such as ''What We Don't Talk About When We Talk About Fat, Happy Fat,'' ''Things No One Tells Fat Girls,'' and ''Fat! So?'' all have the word Fat in the title in a non-derogatory sense. Likewise, The [[National Association to Advance Fat Acceptance]] (NAAFA) was founded in 1969, with the descriptor of the community being "fat."&lt;ref name=":12"/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Fat acceptance movement]]
* ''[[Fattitude]]''—2017 documentary on fat discrimination
* [[Height discrimination]]
* [[Controversial Reddit communities#FatPeopleHate|Reddit anti-fat communities]]
* [[Sizeism]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite news |last1=Hobbes |first1=Michael |date=19 September 2018 |title=Everything You Know About Obesity Is Wrong |url=https://highline.huffingtonpost.com/articles/en/everything-you-know-about-obesity-is-wrong/ |department=Highline |work=[[The Huffington Post]]}}

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Obesity]]
[[Category:Social stigma|Obesity]]
[[Category:Stereotypes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>