<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112180916|87368686" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="37056" pageid="37056" ns="0" title="Sexual revolution"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-12T19:15:42Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{NPOV}}
{{unreferenced}}
{{cleanup-date|January 2006}}
The '''sexual revolution''' refers to a change in [[sexual morality]] and [[human sexual behavior|sexual behavior]] throughout the [[Western world]]. In general use, the term refers to a later trend of equalizing sexual behavior which occurred primarily during the 1960s and 1970s and remerged during the late-[[1990s]] and [[2000s]], although the term has been used at least since the late 1920s.

==Introduction==
The term appeared as early as 1929; the book ''Is Sex Necessary?'', by Thurber &amp; White, has a chapter titled ''The Sexual Revolution: Being a Rather Complete Survey of the Entire Sexual Scene''. 

One suggested trigger for the modern revolution was the development of the [[The Pill|birth control pill]] in 1960, which gave women access to easy and reliable contraception. Other data suggests the "revolution" was more directly influenced by the financial independence gained by many women who entered the workforce during and after [[World War II]], making the revolution more about individual equality rather than biological independence. Many people, however, feel that one specific cause can not be selected for this large phenomenon&lt;ref&gt; Alan Petigny, "Illegitimacy, Postwar Psychology, and the Reperiodization of the Sexual Revolution" Journal of Social History, fall 2004&lt;/ref&gt;.

Some historians argue that sexual revolution was not a complete break from earlier Western sexual attitudes but rather a liberalization after a conservative period that only existed between the 1930s and 1950s. They note that the [[Cold War]] sparked a socially conformist identity which tended to be self-conscious of its appearance to the outside world. Within the United States, this conformity took on [[puritanism|puritanical]] overtones which contradicted natural or even, ironically, culturally-established human sexual behaviors. It was this period of ''Cold War puritanism'' some say, which logically led to a cultural rebellion in the form of the "sexual revolution.". 

The extent to which the ''sexual revolution'' involved major changes in sexual behavior, however, is questionable. Many observers have suggested that the main change was not that people had more sex or different types of sex, it was simply that they talked about it more openly than previous generations had done. Historian [[David Allyn]] argues it was a time of coming-out:  about premarital sex, [[masturbation]], erotic fantasies, pornography use, and homosexuality.

It is clear that sexual behaviour ''did'' change radically for the vast majority of women, but only a generation after the "revolution" had begun. Women reaching sexual maturity after about [[1984]] have behaviours much more in common with the men of a generation earlier. Some had more partners (two to three times), starting at an earlier age (by three to five years), than women of the generation of the [[1970s]]. Nevertheless this rather radical change in ''actual'' behaviour is rarely reported on, being regarded as no longer newsworthy.

==Historical development==
The sexual revolution can be seen an outgrowth of a process in recent history. It was a development in the [[modern world]] which saw the significant loss of power by the [[values]] of a [[morality]] rooted in the [[Christian]] tradition and the rise of [[permissive society|permissive societies]], of attitudes that were accepting of greater sexual freedom and experimentation that spread all over the world and were captured in the phrase ''[[free love]]''.

Throughout the 1960s and 1970s [[Sweden]] was an international leader in what is now referred to as the "sexual revolution," with [[gender equality]] particularly promoted during this time.

==Modern revolutions==
The [[Industrial Revolution]] during the [[nineteenth century]] and the growth of [[science]] and [[technology]], [[medicine]] and [[health care]], resulted in better [[contraceptives]] being manufactured. Advances in the manufacture and production of [[rubber]] made possible the design and production of [[condoms]] that could be used by hundreds of millions of men and women to prevent [[pregnancy]] at little cost. Advances in [[steel]] production and [[immunology]] made [[abortion]] readily available. Advances in [[chemistry]], [[pharmacology]], and knowledge of [[biology]], and human [[physiology]] and all sorts of new [[medication|drugs]] led to the discovery and perfection of [[oral contraceptives]] also known as "[[The Pill]]". New drugs like [[Viagra]] helped [[impotent]] men have an [[erection]] and increased the potency of others. Purchasing an [[aphrodisiac]] and various [[sex toy]]s became "normal". [[Sado-masochism]] ("[[Sadism and masochism|S&amp;M]]") gained popularity, and "no-fault" unilateral [[divorce]] became legal and easier to obtain in many countries during the [[1960s]] and [[1970s]].	 

All these developments took place alongside and combined with an increase in world [[literacy]] and decline in religious observances. Old values such as the notion of "be fruitful and multiply" rooted in the Bible, for example, were cast aside as people continued to feel alienated from the past and adopted the life-styles of modernizing [[westernized]] cultures.	 

Another thing that helped bring about this more modern revolution of sexual freedom was the writing of [[Herbert Marcuse]] and [[Wilhelm Reich]], who took the philosophy of Karl Marx and other such philosophers, and mixed together this chant for freedom of sexual rights and release in our modern culture.

==Freudian school==
[[Doctor (title)|Doctor]] [[Sigmund Freud]] of [[Vienna]] believed the roots of human behavior were rooted in the [[libido]]. This new modern "science" of [[psychoanalysis]] revolutionized an entire culture's self image. [[Victorian morality|Victorian prudishness]] was shoved aside by a new [[consciousness]] of a [[sex drive]]. Men had an [[Oedipus complex]] and women had [[penis envy]] according to Freud. The mother's breast was the source of all later [[erotic]] [[sensation]]. This new [[philosophy]] was the new intellectual and cultural underpinning [[ideology]] of the new age of sexual frankness. Nonetheless, much of his research is widely discredited by professionals in the field.

The [[Anarchism|Anarchist]] Freud scholars Otto Gross and [[Wilhelm Reich]] (who famously coined the phrase "Sexual Revolution") developed a sociology of sex in the 1920s and 1930s.

==Kinsey and Masters &amp; Johnson==
In the late [[1940s]] and early [[1950s]], [[Alfred C. Kinsey]] published two surveys of modern sexual behavior. In [[1948]], Alfred C. Kinsey and his co-workers, responding to a request by female students at [[Indiana University Bloomington|Indiana University]] for more information on human sexual behavior, published the book ''[[Kinsey Reports|Sexual Behavior in the Human Male]]''. They followed this five years later with ''[[Kinsey Reports|Sexual Behavior in the Human Female]]''. These books began a revolution in social awareness of, and public attention given to, human sexuality.

It is said that at the time, [[public morality]] severely restricted open discussion of sexuality as a human characteristic, and specific sexual practices, especially sexual behaviors that did not lead to procreation. Kinsey's books contained studies about controversial topics such as the frequency of homosexuality, and the sexuality of minors ages 3-13.  Scientists working for Kinsey reported data which led to the conclusion that we are capable of sexual stimulation from birth.

These books laid the groundwork for [[Masters and Johnson]]'s life work. A ground breaking study called ''[[Human Sexual Response]]'' in [[1966]] revealed the nature and scope of the sex practices of young Americans.

== ''Lady Chatterley's Lover'', ''Tropic of Cancer'', and ''Fanny Hill'' ==
In the United States in the years [[1959]] through [[1966]], bans on three books with explicit erotic content were challenged and overturned.

Prior to this time, a patchwork of regulations (as well as local customs and vigilante actions) governed what could and could not be published. For example, it was the [[United States Customs Service|U. S. Customs]] authority that "banned" [[James Joyce]]'s ''[[Ulysses (novel)|Ulysses]]'' by refusing its importation into the country. The [[Roman Catholic Church]]'s ''[[Index Librorum Prohibitorum]]'' carried great weight among Catholics and amounted to an effective and instant boycott of any book appearing on it. Boston's [[Watch and Ward Society]], a largely Protestant creation inspired by [[Anthony Comstock]], made "[[banned in Boston]]" a national by-word.

In [[1959]], [[Grove Press]] published an unexpurgated version of ''[[Lady Chatterley's Lover]]'' by [[D. H. Lawrence]]. The [[United States Postal Service|U. S. Post Office]] confiscated copies sent through the mail. Lawyer [[Charles Rembar]] sued the New York city postmaster, and won in New York and then on federal appeal. In 1965, [[Tom Lehrer]] was to celebrate the erotic appeal of the novel in his cheerfully satirical song "Smut" with the couplet "Who needs a hobby like tennis or [[philately]]?/I've got a hobby: rereading ''Lady Chatterley''."

[[Henry Miller]]'s [[1934]] novel, ''[[Tropic of Cancer (novel)|Tropic of Cancer]]'', had explicit sexual passages and could not be published in the United States; an edition was printed by the [[Obelisk Press]] in Paris and copies were smuggled into the United States. ([[As of 2003]], used book dealers asked $7500 and up for copies of this edition.) In [[1961]], Grove Press issued a copy of the work, and lawsuits were brought against dozens of individual booksellers in many states for selling it. The issue was ultimately settled by the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U. S. Supreme Court]]'s [[1973]] decision in [[Miller v. California]]. In this decision, the court defined obscenity by what is now called the [[Miller test]].

In [[1965]], Putnam published [[John Cleland]]'s [[1750]] novel ''[[Fanny Hill]]''. This was the turning point, because [[Charles Rembar]] appealed a restraining order against it all the way to the U.S. Supreme Court and won.  In ''Memoirs v. Massachusetts'', 383 U.S. 413, the court ruled that sex was "a great and mysterious motive force in human life," and that its expression in literature was protected by the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]]. Only books primarily appealing to "prurient interest" could be banned. In a famous phrase, the court said that obscenity is "utterly without redeeming social importance"&amp;mdash;meaning that, conversely, any work with redeeming social importance was not obscene, even if it contained isolated passages that could "deprave and corrupt" some readers.

This decision was especially significant, because, of the three books mentioned, ''Fanny Hill'' has by far the largest measure of content that seems to appeal to prurient interest, and the smallest measures of [[literary merit]] and "redeeming social importance". Whereas an expurgated version of ''Lady Chatterley's Lover'' had actually once been published, no expurgated version of ''Fanny Hill'' has ever been (and it is difficult even to imagine what such a work could possibly consist of). By permitting the publication of ''Fanny Hill,'' the Supreme Court set the bar for any ban so high that Rembar himself called the [[1966]] decision "the end of obscenity."

== Mead's ''Coming of Age in Samoa'' ==

The publication of renowned anthropologist and student of Franz Boas, [[Margaret Mead]]'s "Coming of Age in Samoa" brought the sexual revolution to the public scene, as her thought concerning sexual freedom pervaded academia. Published in 1928, Mead's ethnography focused on the psychosexual development of adolescent children on the island of [[Samoa]] in French Polynesia. She recorded that their adolescence was not in fact a time of "storm and stress" as Erikson's stages of development suggest, but that the sexual freedom experienced by the adolescents actually permitted them an easy transition from childhood to adulthood. 

Her findings were later invalidated as a fabrication by anthropologist Freeman who later investigated her claims of promiscuity and conducted his own ethnography of Samoan society. Mead called for a change in suppression of sexuality in America and her work directly resulted in the advancement of the sexual revolution in the 1930's.
== Nonfiction sex manuals ==

The court decisions that legalized the publication of ''Fanny Hill'' had an even more important effect: freed from fears of legal action, nonfiction works about sex and sexuality started to appear.

In [[1962]], [[Helen Gurley Brown]] published ''[[Sex and the Single Girl]]: The Unmarried Woman's Guide to Men, Careers, the Apartment, Diet, Fashion, Money and Men.'' The title itself would have been unthinkable a decade earlier. (In [[1965]] she went on to transform ''Cosmopolitan'' magazine into a life manual for young career women).

In [[1969]], [[Terry Garrity|Joan Garrity]], identifying herself only as "J.", published ''The Way to Become the Sensuous Woman,'' replete with everything from exercises for improving the dexterity of the tongue, to how to have anal sex.

The same year saw the appearance of Dr. [[David Reuben]]'s book ''[[Everything You Always Wanted to Know About Sex (But Were Afraid to Ask)]].'' Despite the dignity of Reuben's medical credentials, this book was light-hearted in tone. For many readers, it delivered quite literally on its promise. One middle-aged matron from a small town in Wisconsin was heard to say "Until I read this book, I never actually knew precisely what it was that homosexuals ''did''".

In [[1970]], the Boston Women's Health Collective published ''Women and their Bodies'' (which became far better known a year later under its subsequent title, ''[[Our Bodies, Ourselves]]''). Not an erotic treatise or sex manual, the book nevertheless included frank descriptions of sexuality, and contained illustrations that could have caused legal problems just a few years earlier.

[[Alex Comfort]]'s ''[[The Joy of Sex]]: A Gourmet Guide to Love Making.'' appeared in [[1972]]. In later editions though, Comfort's libertarianism was tamed as a response to [[AIDS]]. 

In [[1975]] [[Will McBride (photographer)|Will McBride]]'s ''Zeig Mal!'', [[Show Me!]], written with psychologist Helga Fleichhauer-Hardt for children and their parents, appeared in bookstores on both sides of the Atlantic. Appreciated by many parents for its frank depiction of pre-adolescents discovering and exploring their sexuality, it scandalized others and eventually it was pulled from circulation in the United States and some other countries. It was followed up in [[1989]] by ''Zeig Mal Mehr!'' ("Show Me More!").

These books had a number of things in common. They were factual and, in fact, educational. They were available to a mainstream readership. They were stacked high on the tables of discount bookstores, they were book club selections, and their authors were guests on late-night talk shows. People were seen reading them in public. In a respectable middle-class home, ''[[Playboy]]'' magazine and ''Fanny Hill'' might be present but would usually be kept out of sight. But at least some of these books might well be on the coffee table. Most important, all of these books acknowledged and celebrated the conscious cultivation of erotic pleasure.

The contribution of such books to the sexual revolution cannot be overstated. Earlier books such as ''What Every Girl Should Know'' ([[Margaret Sanger]], [[1920]]) and ''A Marriage Manual'' (Hannah and Abraham Stone, [[1939]]) had broken the utter silence in which many people, women in particular, had grown up. By the [[1950s]], in the United States, it had finally become rare for women to go into their wedding nights literally not knowing what to expect. But the open discussion of sex as pleasure, and descriptions of sexual practices and techniques, was truly revolutionary. There were practices which, perhaps, some had heard of. But many adults did not know for sure whether they were realities, or fantasies found only in pornographic books. Were they "normal," or were they examples of [[psychopathology]]?  (When we use words such as ''[[fellatio]]'' we are still using the terminology of [[Richard Freiherr von Krafft-Ebing|Krafft-Ebing]]'s ''[[Psychopathia Sexualis]]''). Did married ladies do these things, or only prostitutes? The Kinsey report revealed that these practices were, at the very least, surprisingly frequent. These other books asserted, in the words of a 1980 book by Dr. Irene Kassorla, that ''Nice Girls Do -- And Now You Can Too''.

== Medicine and sex ==
The development of [[antibiotic]]s in the [[1940s]] made most of the severe [[venereal disease]]s of the time curable, removing the threat of sexually transmitted diseases such as [[syphilis]].

In the early [[1960s]], [[The Pill]] became available; at first for married women only, but demand and changes in attitudes later led to it becoming available to unmarried women as well.

With the twin threats of disease and pregnancy removed, many of the traditional constraints on sexual behavior seemed unjustified.

With the notion that sexually transmitted diseases were easily treatable, much of the maturing [[post-WW2 baby boom]] generation experimented with sex without the need for [[marriage]].

== Contraception ==
New methods of [[contraception]] allowed men and women to gain control of their own reproduction. The cheap availability of [[rubber]] [[condoms]] for men and both [[IUD]]'s and [[oral contraceptives]] for women added to a sense of freedom from [[pregnancy]] resulting from [[sexual intercourse]].

==The sexual revolution in the UK==
In the [[United Kingdom|UK]] the new generation growing up after the [[Second World War]] had grown tired of the rationing and austerity of the [[1940s]] and [[1950s]] and the Victorian values of their elders, so the [[1960s]] were a time of rebellion against the fashions and social mores of the previous generation.

An early inkling of changing attitudes came in [[1960]], when the government of the day tried unsuccessfully to prosecute [[Penguin Books]] for obscenity, for publishing the [[D.H. Lawrence]] novel ''[[Lady Chatterley's Lover]]'', which had been banned since the [[1920s]] for its racy (for the time) content.

As evidence of how old-fashioned the attitudes of the [[establishment]] were, the prosecution counsel Mervyn Griffith-Jones famously stood in front of the jury and asked, in his closing statement: "Is it a book you would wish your wife or servants to read?".

When the case collapsed, the novel went on to become a best seller, selling 2 million copies. The Pill became available free of charge on the [[National Health Service]] in the [[1960s]], at first restricted to married women, but late in the decade its availability was extended to all women.

==Free love==
Beginning in San Francisco in the mid [[1960s]], a new culture of "[[free love]]" with tens of thousands of young people becoming "[[hippies]]" arose who preached the power of [[love]] and the beauty of [[sex]] as part of ordinary student life. This is part of a [[counter culture]] that exists to the present. By the start of the [[1970s]] it was acceptable for colleges to allow co-educational housing where male and female students mingled freely.

Free love continued in different forms throughout the [[1970s]] and at least into the early [[1980s]], but its more assertive manifestations ended abruptly when the public first became aware of [[AIDS]], a deadly sexually transmitted disease, in the mid 1980s.

==Explicit sex on screen==
Swedish filmakers like Ingmar Bergman and Vilgot Sjöman contributed to sexual liberation with sexually themed films that challenged conservative international stardards.  The 1951 film "Hon dansade en sommarnatt" (She Danced a Summer Night) starring Ulla Jacobsson and Folke Sundquist depicted scenes that were at the time considered too sexual, but by today's standards would be fairly mild.  This film, as well as Bergman's "Sommaren med Monika" ("the Summer with Monika"), caused an international uproar, not least in the USA where the films were charged with violating indecency.  Vilgot Sjöman's film "Jag är nyfiken gul" ("I am Curious Yellow"), also created an international uproar, but it was very popular in the United States.  Another of his films, "491", highlighted homosexuality among other things.  "Kärlekens språk", ("the Language of Love"), was an informative documentary about sex and sexual techniques that featured the first real act of sex in film, and inevitably it caused intense debate around the world, including in the US.  From these films the concept of "the Swedish sin", (licentiousness) developed, even though Swedish society was at the time still fairly conservative regarding sex, and the international concept of Swedish sexuality was and is largely exaggerated.  The films caused debate there as well.  The films eventually helped the public's attitudes toward sex progress, especially in Sweden and other northern European countries, which today tend to be more sexually liberal than others.

Explicit sex on screen and acceptance of [[frontal nudity]] by men and women on stage became the norm in many American and European countries, as the twentieth century ended. Special places of entertainment offering [[striptease]] and [[lap dancing]] proliferated. The famous [[Playboy Bunny|Playboy Bunnies]] set a trend. Men came to be entertained by [[topless]] women at night-clubs which also hosted "[[peep show]]s."

==Pre-marital sex==
[[Pre-marital sex]] was openly adopted by the adherents of the 'counterculture' and spread to the majority of young people in the 1970s. Also in the 1970s pregnancies could be ended as [[abortion]] became more easily available. This led to perceptions of the times being an "age of [[promiscuity]]," [[decadence]] and [[hedonism]], and there was even a backlash in America in the [[1980s]] as many people sought to return to [[family values]].

==The politics of sex==
[[Politics]] in the USA has become intertwined with sexually related issues, called the "politics of sex". A woman's right to an abortion pitted traditionalist [[Pro-Life]] activists against [[Pro-Choice]] permitting abortions. Sex between people of the same gender, the [[homosexuality]] that was strictly taboo in times when the Church dominated [[society]], was no longer stigmatized. [[Lesbian]] women and [[gay]] men demanded and received many rights previously reserved for [[heterosexual]] couples. Women and men who lived with each other without [[marriage]] sought "[[palimony]]" equal to the [[alimony]] a [[divorced]] husband pays his ex-wife. Teenagers assumed their right to a sexual life with whomever they pleased. And bathers fought for the right to be [[topless]] or nude at beaches.

==''Playboy'' magazine and redefining pornography==
[[Pornography]] was not as stigmatized, and more mainstream movies depicted [[sexual intercourse]] as "entertainment," with hardly a stir of protest indicative of how far the sexual revolution had come. Magazines depicting nudity and sexual acts, such as the popular ''[[Playboy]]'' magazine, won acceptance as respectable journals where public figures felt safe expressing their opinions, arguing successfully that they were guaranteed [[freedom of speech]] by the [[United States Constitution]]. However, some figures in the [[feminist]] movement objected to the depiction of women as "objects" in these pornographic magazines and in such events as the annual "[[Miss World]]" and "[[Miss Universe]]" contests. The [[gay porn]] industry also became much more widespread. Throughout the [[1950s]] and [[1960s]] pornography depicting [[homosexual]] acts was rare and even illegal in some states.

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==See also==

*[[cohabitation]]
*[[Cosmopolitan magazine]]
*[[feminism]]
*[[free love]]
*''[[The Joy of Sex]]''
*[[Alfred Kinsey]]
*[[Kinsey Reports]]
*[[nudity]] and [[toplessness]]
*[[open marriage]]
*[[Permissive society]]
*[[The Pill]]
*[[Playboy]]
*[[Playgirl]]
*[[Revolution]]s
*[[Margaret Sanger]]
*[[sex-positive feminism]]   
*[[Swinging]]

[[Category:History of human sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]

[[ar:ثورة جنسية]]
[[de:Sexuelle Revolution]]
[[es:Revolución sexual]]
[[fr:Révolution sexuelle]]
[[it:Rivoluzione sessuale]]
[[nl:Seksuele revolutie]]
[[fi:Seksuaalinen vallankumous]]
[[sv:Sexuella revolutionen]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>