<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20021108054148|411546" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="37056" pageid="37056" ns="0" title="Sexual revolution"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-11-08T07:59:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''sexual revolution''' refers to a substantial change in sexual behaviour throughout [[the West]] and particularly in the [[United States]],  [[United Kingdom]] and other wealthy English-speaking countries in the late [[1960s]] and early [[1970s]]. 

With [[oral contraceptives]] becoming widely available and the sexually-transmitted diseases present at the time mostly being easily treatable, much of the maturing [[Baby Boomer]] generation experimented with sex, outside the boundaries of [[marriage]].  Sex was much more explicitly discussed in books, music, and other media, with the publication of guides to sexual techniques.  Sexual practices that were previously considered unsuitable for discussion, such as [[oral sex]] and [[homosexuality]], were openly talked about.  Some historians argue that the sexual revolution was not a completely break from earlier Western sexual attitudes but rather a liberalization after a conservative period that only existed between the 1930's and 1950's.

British writer [[Philip Larkin]]'s poem "Annus Mirabilis" (1974) captures the spirit of the Sexual Revolution rather well. Here is the first [[stanza]]:

  Sexual intercourse began
  In nineteen sixty-three
  (which was rather late for me) -
  Between the end of the "[[Lady Chatterley's Lover|Chatterley]]" ban
  And the [[Beatles]]' first [[LP]].

Read the [http://alt.venus.co.uk/weed/writings/poems/plam.htm whole poem].

Social attitudes toward sexuality became notably more conservative
in the 1980's in part because of the fear of [[AIDS]].</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>