<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20090816222513|308370568" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12650282" pageid="12650282" ns="0" title="Discrimination against lesbians"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-10-15T18:00:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{LGBT sidebar}}

'''Lesbophobia''' (sometimes '''Lesbiphobia''') comprises various forms of negativity toward [[lesbian]] [[Woman|women]] as individuals, as a couple or as a [[Group (sociology)|social group]]. Based on the categories of [[Biology of gender|sex or biological gender]], [[sexual orientation]], lesbian [[Identity (social science)|identity]], and [[gender]] expression, this negativity encompasses [[prejudice]], [[discrimination]], and [[abuse]] in addition to [[Attitude (psychology)|attitudes]] and feelings ranging from [[disdain]] to [[hostility]]. As such, lesbophobia is [[sexism]] against women that [[Intersectionality|intersects]] with [[homophobia]] and vice-versa. Cynthia Petersen, a professor of law at [[University of Ottawa]], has defined ''lesbophobia'' as also including "the fear that women have of loving other women, as well as the fear that men (including [[gay]] men) have of women not loving them."&lt;ref name="petersen"&gt;Petersen, Cynthia. (1994) "Living Dangerously: Speaking Lesbian, Teaching Law."  ''Canadian Journal of Women &amp; the Law'' 7(2).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Related terminology==
While some people use only the more general term [[homophobia]] to describe this sort of prejudice or behavior, others believe that the terms ''[[homosexual]]'' and ''homophobia'' do not adequately reflect the specific concerns of lesbians. In particular, some lesbians argue that they experience the double discrimination of both classic homophobia and [[sexism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=[[2006-12-18]] |title=What is “Lesbophobia”? |publisher=ILGA |url=http://www.ilga.org/news_results.asp?LanguageID=1&amp;FileCategory=1&amp;FileID=997 |accessdate=2007-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[bisexual]] women may prefer to use the term [[biphobia]] to refer to prejudice or abuse that they encounter which is based on their [[bisexual]] identity or behaviour, as people who identify as [[transgender]] often prefer to use the word [[transphobia]].{{Fact|date=August 2007}}

==Extent of lesbophobia==
The idea that lesbians are dangerous, while [[heterosexuality|heterosexual]] interactions are natural, normal and spontaneous is a common example of beliefs which are lesbophobic. Like homophobia, this belief is classed as [[heteronormative]], as it assumes that heterosexuality is dominant, presumed and normal, and that other sexual or relationship arrangements are abnormal and unnatural.&lt;ref&gt;Jillian Todd Weiss, [http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/tulane.htm "The Gender Caste System - Identity, Privacy, and Heteronormativity"] ''10 Law &amp; Sexuality 123'' (Tulane Law School, 2001)&lt;/ref&gt; A stereotype that has been identified as lesbophobic is that female athletes are always or predominantly lesbians.&lt;ref&gt;Peper, Karen, "Female athlete=Lesbian: a complex myth constructed from gender role expectations and lesbiphobia", ''Queer words, queer images: communications and the construction of homosexuality'', pages 193-208 (New York University Press, 1994)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Darcy Plymire and Pamela Forman, "Breaking the Silence: Lesbian Fans, the Internet, and the Sexual Politics of Women's Sport", ''International Journal of Sexuality and Gender Studies'', pages 1566-1768 (Springer Netherlands, April 2000)&lt;/ref&gt; Lesbians encounter lesbophobic attitudes not only in straight men and women, but from gay men as well.&lt;ref&gt;Megan Radclyffe, ''Lesbophobia!: Gay Men and Misogyny'' (Continuum, October 2005)&lt;/ref&gt; Lesbophobia in gay men is regarded as manifest in the perceived subordination of lesbian issues in the campaign for [[LGBT social movements|gay rights]].&lt;ref&gt;Kristen Raizada, "An Interview with the Guerrilla Girls, Dyke Action Machine (DAM!), and the Toxic Titties", ''NWSA Journal'', pages 39-58 (Volume 19, Number 1, Spring 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lesbophobic violence===
Lesbophobia is sometimes demonstrated through crimes of violence, including [[rape]] and even [[murder]]. In [[South Africa]], Sizakele Sigasa, a lesbian activist living in [[Soweto]], and her partner Salome Masooa were raped, [[torture]]d, and murdered in July 2007 in an attack that South African lesbian-[[gay rights]] organizations, including the umbrella-group [[Joint Working Group]], said were driven by lesbophobia. Two other rape/murders of lesbians occurred in South Africa earlier in summer 2007: Simangele Nhlapo, member of an [[HIV-positive]] support group was raped and murdered in June, along with her two-year-old daughter; and Madoe Mafubedu, aged 16, was raped and stabbed to death. In 2006, Zoliswa Nkonyana, aged 19, was killed for being openly lesbian by about 20 young men in the [[Cape Town]] township of Khayelitsha, who clubbed and kicked her to death. [[Eudy Simelane]], the [[Banyana Banyana]] soccer player, was also raped and killed in South Africa. Zanele Muholi, community relations director of a lesbian rights group, reports having recorded 50 rape cases over the past decade involving black lesbians in townships, stating, "The problem is largely that of [[patriarchy]]. The men who perpetrate such crimes see rape as curative and as an attempt to show women their place in society."&lt;ref name="bridgland"&gt;Bridgland, Fred. (2007-07-14). [http://www.sundayherald.com/international/shinternational/display.var.1546316.0.0.php "Lesbian couple killed in execution-style murder: Hate crimes increase despite equal rights law."] ''[[Sunday Herald]]'' (Glasgow, Scotland). Retrieved on 2007-08-11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="cogswell"&gt;Cogswell, Kelly Jean. (2007-07-26). [http://www.gaycitynews.com/site/news.cfm?newsid=18630253&amp;BRD=2729&amp;PAG=461&amp;dept_id=585504&amp;rfi=6 "Cut It Off — And Stop AIDS."] ''Gay City News''. Retrieved on 2007-08-11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/29676829/&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Societal attitudes toward homosexuality]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Violence against LGBT people]]
* [[History of lesbianism]]
* [[Lesbianism in erotica]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Discrimination|state=uncollapsed}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Homophobia| ]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:Lesbianism]]

[[br:Lesbofobiezh]]
[[bg:Лесбофобия]]
[[el:Λεσβοφοβία]]
[[es:Lesbofobia]]
[[fr:Lesbophobie]]
[[pl:Lesbofobia]]
[[pt:Lesbofobia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>