<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031017204845|1588751" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18956166" pageid="18956166" ns="0" title="Stereotype"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-19T02:03:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[pl:stereotyp]]

Originally a '''stereotype''' was an impression taken from a form of movable lead type and used for printing instead of the original type. This was generalized into a [[metaphor]] for repeating a set of ideas identically with no changes (as would have been possible in a form of movable type).

In modern usage, the metaphorical meaning predominates. The term is generally used to describe an oversimplified mental picture of some group of people who are sharing a certain characteristic (or ''stereotypical'') qualities. The term is thus often used in a negative sense, with stereotypes being seen by many as illogical yet deeply held-beliefs that can only be changed through education. 

In computing, the negative connotation does not apply; ''stereotype'' is also a concept in the [[Unified Modeling Language]], where it is used to encapsulate behaviors. Thus, a ''stereotype'' is used as a vehicle for communicating software requirements and designs. 

Common stereotypes of the past included a variety of allegations about various racial groups (see: [[racial stereotype]] and [[racial profiling]]) and predictions of behavior based on social status and wealth (See [[social stereotype]]). 

In literature and art, stereotypes are [[cliche|clich&amp;eacute;d]] or predictable characters or situations. For example, the stereotypical [[devil]] is a red, impish character with horns and a pitchfork. 

== Common stereotypical characters ==

* The "hard-boiled" [[private eye]]
* The [[aging]] absent-minded [[professor]] (sometimes speaking incoherently)
* The dizzy busty blonde woman
* The dowdy [[library|librarian]] (who becomes instantly attractive when she takes her glasses off)
* The degenerate [[aristocrat]] with top hat, [[tuxedo]], and [[monocle]]
* The snobbish [[butler]] (speaking with a non-[[American English]] [[accent (language)|accent]])
* The [[nerd]]y scientist (with black wiry-framed [[eyeglasses]], black bowtie, white coat, speaking in technobabble)
* The primly dressed schoolmarm with her pointer and "Now, class" address 
* The peg-legged [[pirate]] with an [[eye patch]] and [[parrot]]
* The overweight, [[doughnut]]-eating cop who believes [[Skateboarding is not a crime|skateboarding is a crime]]
* The [[prostitute]] with a heart of gold
* The brightly colored court jester
* The [[villain]] with black clothes, moustache like two needles and generalized Central or Eastern European accent
* The jolly Middle Eastern or South Asian [[cornershop]] owner with his collection of trinkets
* The picky [[chef]] with his [[toque]] and piquant [[French language|French]] accent
* The overdelivering [[game show]] host with his giant smile
* The tobacco-spitting [[baseball]] player
* The [[effeminate]] [[homosexual]] male
* The [[tomboy]]ish [[lesbian]]
* The [[senior|old lady]] who sits on the porch, reminiscing and [[knitting]]

''See also:'' [[archetype]], [[stock character]], [[counterstereotype]] (antonym)</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>