<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071112094234|170933352" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18956166" pageid="18956166" ns="0" title="Stereotype"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T15:36:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=October 2006}}
{{otheruses}}
'''Stereotypes''' are generalizations about groups and individual members thereof, based primarily on membership in that group. They may be positive or negative, they may be accurate or inaccurate regarding average characteristics of a group, and may be used to justify certain [[discrimination|discriminatory behaviors]]. Some people consider all stereotypes to be negative because they are unjust to individuals who vary from group characteristics. Stereotypes may be accurate, based on some kernel of truth yet exaggerated, or completely fabricated.  Different disciplines give different accounts of how stereotypes develop: Psychologists focus on how experience with groups, patterns of communication about the groups, and intergroup conflict. Sociologists focus on the relations among groups and position of different groups in a social structure. Psychoanalytically-oriented humanists have argued (e.g., Sander Gilman) that stereotypes, ''by definition'', are never accurate representations, but a projection of an individual's fears onto others, regardless of the reality of others. Although stereotypes are rarely entirely accurate, statistical studies have shown that in some cases stereotypes do represent measurable facts. 

== Description ==
Stereotypes are assumed characteristics based on a large group of individuals whose beliefs, habits, and actions are perceived to be similar.

Stereotype production can be based on:
*Historical factors 
*Simplification
*Rubbish                  
*Exaggeration
*Presentation of cultural attributes as being 'natural'
*Racism, sexism, homophobia and other forms of discrimination
*Guilt by association

Stereotypes are seen by many as undesirable beliefs imposed to justify the acts of discrimination and oppression.  It is thought that education and/or familiarization can change these incorrect beliefs.  Others believe them to be sometimes accurate generalizations which may have utility when individual judgement is impossible or impractical. These persons believe that experience shows that familiarization often strengthens stereotypes and can deepen hostilities.

Possible prejudicial effects of stereotypes are:

*justification of ill-founded prejudices or ignorance
*unwillingness to rethink one's attitudes and behavior towards stereotyped group
*self-fulfilling prophecy for both stereotyping and stereotyped group (white people treat black people in a more hostile way because they are afraid of them; black people accordingly react more aggressively, thus confirming the stereotype...)
*preventing some people of stereotyped groups from succeeding in activities or fields (i.e. white people who are trying to get into the [[hip hop music|hip hop]] industry; gay men who are trying to be in the [[National Basketball Association|NBA]]; black people trying to get a bachelors degree, and Asian actors who have lead roles in movies). 

There's usually more than one stereotype for the same group.  For example, according to [[black stereotypes | stereotypes about Black Americans]], 
Black men are generally supposed to be good musicians and basketball players, but at the same time seen as aggressive, prone to lives of crime, and likely to be on drugs.
Stereotypes can have positive and negative effects:
Students who were implicitly made aware of their gender behaved as the stereotype suggested:

Asian-American women performed better in math tests when being aware of being Asian, and did worse when being reminded of being women.[http://www.understandingprejudice.org/apa/english/page14.htm]

Stereotyping can also be created by the media, showing an incorrect judgment of a culture or place.

Often the terms ''stereotype'' and ''[[prejudice]]'' are confused:
* Stereotypes are a generalization of characteristics; they reduce complexity.
* [[Prejudices]] are either an abstract-general preconception or an [[attitude]] towards individuals.

==Stereotype inevitability==
{{main|stereotype inevitability}}
{{sect-stub}}
''Prejudices'' are usually based on general ''Stereotypical conceptions'' of our everyday "reality" (including ''persons [even ourselves], objects processes, facts, value-norms, rules'' etc.). 
&lt;br /&gt;However, they need to be converted into "attitudes", in order to be considered as "prejudices", and they usually carry a negative connotation.
&lt;!-- What does this mean? --&gt;
&lt;!-- D. Mallios --&gt;

==Of groups==
Common stereotypes include a variety of allegations about groups based on [[Ageing|age]], [[Ethnic group|ethnicity]], [[gender]], [[nationality]], disability, [[profession]], [[sexual orientation]], [[race]], [[religion|religious]] belief, size, [[Stereotypes of animals|species]], physical appearance, and [[social class]] (see [[social stereotype]]).  Stereotypes can also be based on individual impairments.

==In culture==
{{Original research|date=September 2007}}
Stereotypes are common in the world of [[drama]], where the term is often used as a form of dramatic [[shorthand]] for "[[stock character]]". Increasingly the ''active use'' of stereotypes in [[drama]] is a prerequisite for an audience accepting them as legitimate. The unwitting use of stereotypes appears hackneyed to a postmodern audience which refuses to tolerate the representation of individuals as simply the stereotype. Examples of ''active use'' are found in the work of Brecht and other dramatic styles which allow the actor to demonstrate a character with a degree of ''role distance'', thus showing the ''active use''.  The Italian [[commedia Dell'arte]] was known for its [[stock character]]s and stock situations, which could be considered drama stereotypes. Retrospectively these [[stock characters]] have been illuminated by the work of [[Brecht]], [[Dario Fo]] and [[Jacques Lecoq]], and revealed to be far from simple stereotypes in their current [[evolution]], despite their original reference to local [[Italy|Italian]] stereotypes in their early [[genesis]]. Importantly in drama the actor does not create a stereotype rather their [[characterisation]] may be simple in that they represent an uncritical reflection of the stereotype, and it is this simplicity which aggravates a [[postmodern]] audience. A subtle and detailed [[characterisation]], especially of the commedia Dell'arte stock characters, results in a unique and immediate performance that will be enjoyed by an audience due to the clear active use of the characters by the actor.  

In [[literature]] and [[art]], stereotypes are [[cliché]]d or predictable characters or situations. For example, the stereotypical [[devil]] is a red, impish character with horns, bifurcated tail, and a [[trident]], whilst the stereotypical [[sales]]man is a slickly-dressed, fast-talking individual who cannot usually be trusted. Throughout history, storytellers have drawn from stereotypical characters and situations, in order to quickly connect the audience with new tales. Sometimes such stereotypes can be very complex and sophisticated, such as [[Shakespeare]]'s [[Shylock]] in ''The Merchant of Venice''. Arguably a stereotype that becomes complex and sophisticated ceases to be a stereotype ''per se'' by its unique [[characterisation]]. Thus while [[Shylock]] remains politically unstable in being a stereotypical [[Jew]], the subject of [[prejudicial]] derision in [[Shakespeare's]] era, his many other detailed features raise him above a simple stereotype and into a unique character, worthy of modern performance. Simply because a feature of a character can be categorized as being typical does not make the entire character a stereotype.

Despite their proximity in etymological roots, [[cliché]] and stereotype are not used synonymously in cultural spheres. For example a [[cliché]] is a high criticism in [[narratology]] where [[genre]] and [[categorization]] automatically associates a story within its recognizable group. Labelling a situation or character in a story as ''typical'' suggests it is fitting for its [[genre]] or [[Category (taxonomy)|category]]. Whereas declaring that a storyteller has relied on [[cliché]] is to pejoratively observe a simplicity and lack of originality in the tale. To criticize [[Ian Fleming]] for a ''stereotypically'' unlikely escape for [[James Bond]] would be understood by the reader or listener, but it would be more appropriately criticized as a [[cliché]] in that it is overused and reproduced. [[Narrative]] [[genre]] relies heavily on ''typical'' features to remain recognizable and generate meaning in the reader/viewer. 

Of course, there is plenty of room for criticizing the representation of the '[[Bond girls]]' as stereotypical.

The instantly recognisable nature of stereotypes mean that they are very useful in producing effective [[advertising]] and [[situation comedy]].  Media stereotypes change and evolve over time - for instance, we now instantly recognize only a few of the stereotyped characters shown to us in [[John Bunyan]]'s ''[[The Pilgrim's Progress]]''.
The teen [[sitcom]], [[Saved By The Bell]] features a typical group of high school stereotypes such as a class clown ([[Zack Morris]]), a jock ([[A.C. Slater]]), a nerd ([[Samuel "Screech" Powers]]), a cheerleader ([[Kelly Kapowski]]), a feminist ([[Jessie Spano]]), and a superficial fashion plate ([[Lisa Turtle]]). Some observed the sitcom, like many teen sitcoms of that time, in addition to stereotyping people, stereotyping an institution itself, that of high school. TV stereotypes of high schools have often promoted a "typical American school" as football games, fashion styles, skirt chasing, and not much devotion to academics or studying.

==Etymology==
The word ''stereotype'' was invented by [[Firmin Didot]] in the world of [[printing]]; it was originally a duplicate impression of an original [[typographic]]al element, used for [[printing]] instead of the original. American journalist [[Walter Lippmann]] coined the metaphor, calling a stereotype a "picture in our heads" saying "Whether right or wrong, ...imagination is shaped by the pictures seen... Consequently, they lead to stereotypes that are hard to shake." ([[Public Opinion]], 1922, 95-156).&lt;ref&gt;Ewen and Ewen, ''[[Typecasting: On the Arts and Sciences of Human Inequality]]'',  2006, 3-10.&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, ''[[cliché]]'' and stereotype were both originally printers' words, and in their literal printers' meanings were synonymous. Specifically, [[cliché]] was a French word for the printing surface for a stereotype.&lt;ref&gt;Merriam-Webster's Dictionary of English Usage. Springfield, Illinois: Merriam-Webster, Inc., 1994. p. 250. &lt;http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0877791325&amp;id=2yJusP0vrdgC&amp;pg=PA250&amp;lpg=PA250&amp;ots=nXvVkdB_U4&amp;dq=cliche+origin&amp;sig=f5UQIqottU546aRBe3zlm-9Q7kM#PPA250,M1&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

The first reference to "stereotype", in its modern, English use was in 1850, in the noun, meaning "image perpetuated without change".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=stereotype&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ethology==
In [[ethology]], '''stereotyped''' behavior or [[fixed action pattern]] is an [[innate]], pre-programed response that is repeated when an animal is exposed to an environmental [[innate releasing mechanism]].

==See also==
* [[Archetype]]
* [[Animal stereotypes]]
* [[Sexual stereotyping]]
* [[Counterstereotype]] (antonym)
* [[Ethnic stereotype]]
** [[Stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims]]
** [[Stereotypes of East and Southeast Asians]]
** [[Stereotypes of Hispanics]]
** [[Stereotypes of Native Americans]]
** [[Stereotypes of West and Central Asians]]
** [[Stereotypes of blacks]]
** [[Stereotypes of whites]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[LGBT stereotypes]]
* [[Prejudices]]
* [[Racial profiling]]
* [[Role]]
* [[Stock character]]
* [[Stigmatization]]
* [[Stereotype threat]]
* [[Psychology]]:
** [[Negativity effect]]
** [[Outgroup homogeneity bias]]
** [[Physical attractiveness stereotype]]
** [[Trait ascription bias]]

==Lists==
* [[Stock character|List of stereotypical characters in the world of drama]]

==External links==
*A dedicated site for discussion on stereotypes [http://letsbuildanation.org/asialinkforum/index.php]
*[http://www.understandingprejudice.org/apa/english/page11.htm Social Psychology Network] Stereotyping
*[http://school.discovery.com/lessonplans/programs/stereotypes/ Understanding Stereotypes] - Educational information about stereotypes.
*[http://www.aegee.tv/movies/archive/movies/202.html Short movie: Stereotypes in conflict] - Reaction from people in shopping center on business men, weird &amp; slutty types and goths.
*[http://www.datingdames.com/the-subject-of-stereotypes-risk-or-opportunity/ Stereotypes: Risk or Opportunity?] - Thoughts on stereotypes and how stereotyping influences our preferences.
*[http://www.bu.edu/africa/outreach/materials/handouts/goldtodross.html SEPARATING the GOLD from the DROSS: a guide to multicultural literature]
*[http://letsbuildanation.org/asialinkforum/index.php On Stereotypes and Cultural Differences]
*[http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/special_initiatives/toolkit/stereotypes/what_are_stereotypes.cfm Media Awareness Network. What is a stereotype?]  Definition, role of stereotyping in the media, more links
*[http://textmex.blogspot.com A Galleryblog on stereotypes] A  blog dedicated to the study of stereotypes in American mass culture; in particular, stereotypes of Latinas/os, Mexicans, and other Hispanic "types."  The blog is a continuation of a discussion in [http://www.utexas.edu/utpress/books/nertex.html Tex(t)-Mex] --a University of Texas Press book (2007).
*[http://www.theonion.com/content/node/33210 Stereotypes Are A Real Time-Saver] (Parody)
*[http://dictionary.reference.com/search?r=2&amp;q=stereotype Dictionary - Sterotype] Online Dictionary

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}
Stereotype is spelled wrong in reference to the online dictionary

==Bibliography==
*Stuart Ewen, Elizabeth Ewen, ''Typecasting: On the Arts and Sciences of Human Inequality''. New York (Seven Stories Press) 2006
*[http://www.stereotypeandsociety.typepad.com Stereotype &amp; Society] A Major Resource: Constantly updated and archived
*[http://www.understandingprejudice.org/apa/english/page11.htm Social Psychology Network] Stereotyping
*[http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/special_initiatives/toolkit/stereotypes/what_are_stereotypes.cfm Media Awareness Network. What is a stereotype?]  Definition, role of stereotyping in the media, more links
* [http://www.in-mind.org/artikelen/are-blonds-really-dumb.html Are Blonds Really Dumb?] An article on Stereotyping(registration required)

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Social psychology]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Stereotypes| ]]
[[Category:Fiction]]
[[Category:Fictional character types]]

[[ast:Estereotipu]]
[[ca:Estereotip]]
[[da:Stereotyp]]
[[de:Stereotyp]]
[[et:Stereotüüp]]
[[es:Estereotipo]]
[[fr:Stéréotype]]
[[gd:Dlùth-chlòdh]]
[[io:Stereotipo]]
[[id:Stereotipe]]
[[it:Stereotipo]]
[[he:סטריאוטיפ]]
[[lt:Stereotipas]]
[[mk:Стереотип]]
[[nl:Stereotype]]
[[ja:ステレオタイプ]]
[[no:Stereotyp]]
[[pl:Stereotyp]]
[[pt:Estereótipo]]
[[ru:Стереотип]]
[[simple:Stereotype]]
[[fi:Yleistys]]
[[sv:Stereotyp]]
[[tr:Basmakalıp]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>