<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112113224|87320187" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18956166" pageid="18956166" ns="0" title="Stereotype"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-12T11:34:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{for|the term used in computing|stereotype (computing)}}
{{for2|the term used in its original printing sense|[[#Etymology|etymology below]]}}
{{unreferenced}}
'''Stereotypes''' are ideas held by some individuals about members of particular groups, based solely on membership in that group. They are often used in a negative or [[prejudicial]] sense and are frequently used to justify certain [[discrimination|discriminatory behaviors]]. More benignly, they may express sometimes-accurate [[Folk psychology|folk wisdom]] about [[social reality]].

== Explanation ==
Assumed characteristics on a large group of individuals whose beliefs, habits, and realities often disagree with the imposed image.

Stereotype production is based on:
*Simplification                                       
*Exaggeration or distortion
*Generalization
*Presentation of cultural attributes as being 'natural'.

Stereotypes are seen by many as undesirable beliefs imposed to justify the acts of discrimination and oppression.  It is thought, education and/or familiarization can change these misbeliefs.

Often the terms stereotype and [[prejudice]] are confused:
* Stereotypes are a generalization of existing characteristics (facts), they reduce complexity and offer also opportunities to identify oneself with others.
* [[Prejudices]] are either an abstract-general preconception or an [[attitude]] towards individuals.

==Stereotypes of groups==
Common stereotypes include a variety of allegations about groups based on [[race]], [[ethnicity]], [[gender]], [[nationality]], or [[religion|religious]] belief, along with [[profession]] and [[social class]] (see [[social stereotype]]).  Stereotypes can also be based on an individual's physical size, handicaps or other characteristic.

==Stereotypes within groups==
A variety of stereotypes usually exist within major social groups, and relate to the variety of identified  that exist within their own group.  For instance, the western urban [[lesbian]] sub-culture has strong sub-group stereotypes regarding [[butch and femme]] lesbians; [[bisexuality|bisexual]]s; [[granola]] [[dyke (lesbian)|dyke]]s; and many other sub-groups within the lesbian subculture.

==Stereotypes in culture==
Stereotypes are common in the world of [[drama]], where the term is often used as a form of dramatic [[shorthand]] for "[[stock character]]".  In [[literature]] and [[art]], stereotypes are [[cliche|clichéd]] or predictable characters or situations. For example, the stereotypical [[devil]] is a red, impish character with horns, bifurcated tail, and a [[trident]], whilst the stereotypical [[sales|salesman]] is a slickly-dressed, fast-talking individual who cannot usually be trusted. The Italian [[Commedia Dell'arte]] was known for its [[stock character]]s and stock situations, which could be considered drama stereotypes. Throughout history, storytellers have drawn from stereotypical characters and situations, in order to quickly connect the audience with new tales. Sometimes such stereotypes can be very complex and sophisticated, such as [[Shakespeare]]'s [[Shylock]] in ''The Merchant of Venice''.

The instantly recognisable nature of stereotypes mean that they are very useful in producing effective [[advertising]] and [[situation comedy]].  Media stereotypes change and evolve over time - for instance, we now instantly recognize only a few of the stereotyped characters shown to us in [[John Bunyan]]'s ''[[The Pilgrim's Progress]]''.
The teen [[sitcom]], [[Saved By The Bell]] features a typical group of high school stereotypes such as a "prep" ([[Zack Morris]]), a "jock" ([[A.C. Slater]]), a "nerd" ([[Samuel "Screech" Powers]]), a cheerleader ([[Kelly Kapowski]]), a feminist ([[Jessie Spano]]) and a superficial fashion plate ([[Lisa Turtle]]).

==Etymology==
The word ''stereotype'' was invented by [[Firmin Didot]] in the world of [[printing]]; it was originally a duplicate impression of an original [[typographic]]al element, used for [[printing]] instead of the original. American journalist [[Walter Lippmann]] coined the metaphor, calling a stereotype a "picture in our heads" saying "Whether right or wrong, ...imagination is shaped by the pictures seen... Consequently, they lead to stereotypes that are hard to shake." ([[Public Opinion]], 1922, 95-156). To note, ''[[cliche|cliché]]'' and stereotype were both originally printers' words, and in their literal printers' meanings were synonymous. Specifically, [[cliche|cliché]] was an [[onomatopoeia|onomatopoetic]] word for the sound that was made during the stereotyping process when the matrix hit molten metal.''

==Ethology==
In [[ethology]], '''stereotyped''' behaviour or [[fixed action pattern]] is an [[innate]], pre-programed response that is repeated when an animal is exposed to an environmental [[innate releasing mechanism]]. 

==See also==
* [[Archetype]]
* [[Cliché]]
* [[Counterstereotype]] (antonym)
* [[Ethnic stereotype]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[Prejudices]]
* [[Racial profiling]]
* [[Stock character]]
* [[Ethnic stereotypes in American media]]
* [[Psychology]]:
** [[Negativity effect]]
** [[Outgroup homogeneity bias]]
** [[Physical attractiveness stereotype]]
** [[Trait ascription bias]]

==Lists==
* [[Stock character|List of stereotypical characters in the world of drama]]
* [[List of common phrases based on stereotypes]]

==External links==
*[http://school.discovery.com/lessonplans/programs/stereotypes/ Understanding Stereotypes] - Educational information about stereotypes.
*[http://www.aegee.tv/movies/archive/movies/202.html Short movie: Stereotypes in conflict] - Reaction from people in shopping center on business men, weird &amp; slutty types and goths.
*[http://www.datingdames.com/the-subject-of-stereotypes-risk-or-opportunity/ Stereotypes: Risk or Opportunity?] - Thoughts on stereotypes and how stereotyping influences our preferences.
*[http://www.bu.edu/africa/outreach/materials/handouts/goldtodross.html SEPARATING the GOLD from the DROSS: a guide to multicultural literature]
*[http://letsbuildanation.org/asialinkforum/index.php On Stereotypes and Cultural Differences]


[[Category:Social psychology]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Stereotypes| ]]

[[ru:Стереотип]]
[[ca:Estereotip]]
[[da:Stereotyp]]
[[de:Stereotyp (allgemein)]]
[[et:Stereotüüp]]
[[es:Estereotipo]]
[[fr:Stéréotype]]
[[gd:Dlùth-chlòdh]]
[[io:Stereotipo]]
[[it:Stereotipo]]
[[he:סטריאוטיפ]]
[[lt:Stereotipas]]
[[mk:Стереотип]]
[[nl:Stereotype]]
[[ja:ステレオタイプ]]
[[no:Stereotyp]]
[[pl:Stereotyp]]
[[fi:Yleistys]]
[[sv:Stereotyp]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>