<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051109230945|27864988" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18956166" pageid="18956166" ns="0" title="Stereotype"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-09T23:10:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:''For the term used in computing, see [[stereotype (computing)]].''

Stereotypes are considered to be a group concept, held by one social group about another. They are often used in a negative or prejudicial sense and are frequently used to justify certain discriminatory behaviours. This allows powerful social groups to legitimize and protect their dominant position.

Often a stereotype is a negative [[caricature]] or inversion of some positive characteristic possessed by members of a group, exaggerated to the point where it becomes repulsive or ridiculous.  

Stereotype production is based on :
*Simplification                                       
*Exaggeration or distortion
*Generalisation
*Presentation of cultural attributes as being 'natural'.

Stereotypes are seen by many as undesirable beliefs which can be altered through education and/or familiarization. However, stereotypes need not be confined to negative characterizations about individuals or groups, and can thus have positive characterizations. &lt;br /&gt;
There are also genuinely positive stereotypes about groups. Some groups have, as a deliberate political strategy, tried to evolve new genuine positive stereotypes for themselves.

==Stereotypes of groups by other groups==

Common stereotypes include a variety of allegations about groups based around: [[race]], [[ethnicity]], [[gay|sexuality]], [[national stereotypes|nationality]], and [[religion|religious]] belief, and also [[profession]], [[social status]] and [[wealth]] (see [[social stereotype]]).

(See also: [[racial stereotype]], [[ethnic stereotype]], and [[racial profiling]]).

==Stereotypes within groups==

A variety of stereotypes usually exist within major social groups, and relate to the variety of identified sub-groups that exist within their own group.  For instance, western urban [[lesbian]] sub-culture has strong sub-group stereotypes about: [[butch and femme]] lesbians; [[bisexual]]s; [[granola]] [[dyke (lesbian)|dyke]]s; and many other sub-groups within the lesbian subculture.

==Stereotypes in culture==

Stereotypes are common in the world of [[drama]], where the term is often used as a form of dramatic shorthand for "[[stock character]]".  In [[literature]] and [[art]], stereotypes are [[cliche|clich&amp;eacute;d]] or predictable characters or situations. For example, the stereotypical [[devil]] is a red, impish character with horns and a [[pitchfork]] (actually a [[trident]]), whilst the stereotypical [[salesman]] is a slickly-dressed, fast-talking individual who cannot usually be trusted. The Italian [[Commedia Dell'arte]] was known for its [[stock character]]s and stock situations, which could be considered drama stereotypes. Throughout history, storytellers have drawn from stereotypical characters and situations, in order to quickly connect the audience with new tales. Sometimes such stereotypes can be very complex and sophisticated, such as [[Shakespeare]]'s [[Shylock]] in ''The Merchant of Venice''.

The instantly recognisable nature of stereotypes mean that they are very useful in producing effective [[advertising]] and [[situation comedy]].  Media stereotypes change and evolve over time - for instance, we now instantly recognise only a few of the stereotyped characters shown to us in [[John Bunyan]]'s ''[[The Pilgrim's Progress]]'', and the stereotypical [[1970s]] effete [[gay man]] depicted by [[John Inman]] in ''[[Are You Being Served?]]'' is rarely seen in the media today and may even completely baffle young viewers in future decades.

==Origins of the word==

The word ''stereotype'' was invented by [[Firmin Didot]] in the world of [[printing]]; it was originally a duplicate impression of an original [[typographic]]al element, used for [[printing]] instead of the original. Over time, this became a [[metaphor]] for any set of ideas repeated identically, en masse, with minor changes. In fact, ''[[cliche|clich&amp;eacute;]]'' and stereotype were both originally printers' words, and in their literal printers' meanings were synonymous. Specifically, [[cliche|clich&amp;eacute;]] was an [[onomatopoeia|onomatopoetic]] word for the sound that was made during the stereotyping process when the matrix hit molten metal.

==See also==
* [[Archetype]]
* [[National stereotypes]]
* [[Nurse stereotypes]]
* [[Stock character]]
* [[Counterstereotype]] (antonym)

===[[Lists]]=== 
* [[List of stereotypical characters in the world of drama]]
* [[List of common phrases based on stereotypes]]

===[[Psychology]]===
* [[Negativity effect]]
* [[Outgroup homogeneity bias]]
* [[Physical attractiveness stereotype]]
* [[Trait ascription bias]]

===[[References]]===
*Steele CM, Aronson J. (1994). Stereotype vulnerability and African-American intellectual performance. In E. Aronson (Ed.), ''Readings About the Social Animal''. New York: Freeman &amp; Co.
*Steele CM, Aronson J. (1995). Stereotype threat and the intellectual test performance of African-Americans. ''Journal of Personality and Social Psychology'', 69, 797-811.
*Steele CM. (1997). A threat in the air: How stereotypes shape the intellectual identities and performance of women and African Americans. ''American Psychologist'', 52, 613-629.
*Aronson J, Steele CM, Salinas MF, Lustina MJ (1998). The effects of stereotype threat on the standardized test performance of college students. In E. Aronson (Ed.), ''Readings About the Social Animal'' (8th Edition). New York: Freeman.
*Steele CM. (1998). Stereotyping and its threat are real. ''American Psychologist'', 53, 680-681.
*Steele CM, Aronson J. (1998). Stereotype threat and the test performance of academically successful African Americans. In C. Jencks &amp; M. Phillips (Eds.), ''Black-White Test Score Gap''. Brookings Institution Press.
*Aronson J, Lustina MJ, Good C, Keough K, Steele CM, Brown J. (1999). When white men can’t do math: Necessary and sufficient factors in stereotype threat. ''Journal of Experimental Social Psychology'', 35, 29-46.
*Spencer SJ, Steele CM, Quinn DM. (1999). Stereotype threat and women’s math performance. ''Journal of Experimental Social Psychology'', 35, 4-28.
*Steele, C. M. &amp; Davies, P. G. Stereotype threat and employment testing: a commentary. (2003) Human Performance, 16, 311-326.



==External links==
* [http://samvak.tripod.com/stereotype.html The psychological and social role of stereotypes]
* [http://www.suite101.com/article.cfm/17172/111173 Suite 101: Shark Tale stereotypes troubling: CNYU Professor]


[[Category:Lists of fictional characters]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[category:Stereotypes|*]]

[[da:Stereotyp]]
[[de:Stereotyp]]
[[es:Estereotipo]]
[[fr:Stéréotype]]
[[he:סטריאוטיפ]]
[[io:Stereotipo]]
[[it:Stereotipo]]
[[mk:Стереотип]]
[[ja:固定観念]]
[[pl:Stereotyp]]
[[fi:Yleistys]]
[[sv:Stereotyp]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>