<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091116043529|326106862" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18956166" pageid="18956166" ns="0" title="Stereotype"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T14:12:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses}}
{{Article issues|article=October 2008|refimprove = May 2008|cleanup = July 2008}}
{{ globalize
|date=September 2009
|discuss=Talk:Stereotype
| 1=Stereotype| 2= USA
}}
{{wiktionary|stereotype}}
A '''stereotype''' is a commonly held public belief about specific social groups, or types of individuals. The concepts of  "stereotype" and "[[prejudice]]" are often confused with many other different meanings. Stereotypes are standardized and simplified conceptions of groups, based on some prior assumptions. 

Stereotypes are created based on some idea of abstract [[familiarity]]. For example, the same [[behavior]] or [[trait]] being repeatedly observed by multiple witnesses over an extended period of time. For a stereotype [[meme]] to develop and 'stick' in the popular imagination, a stereotype cannot be completely false, and must have an element of [[social recognition]].

A stereotype can be deemed 'positive', or 'negative'. Concepts of ''stereotype'' are rarely invoked in instances of positive stereotypes being held about a group. The moniker 'stereotype' is more likely to be deployed in relation to stereotypes deemed to be negative. 

==Etymology==
The word ''stereotype'' is of Greek origin (στερεότυπος), literally meaning "solid-kind". It was invented by [[Firmin Didot]] in the world of [[printing]]; it was originally a duplicate impression of an original [[typographic]]al element, used for [[printing]] instead of the original. American journalist [[Walter Lippmann]] coined the metaphor, calling a stereotype a "picture in our heads" saying "Whether right or wrong, ...imagination is shaped by the pictures seen... Consequently, they lead to stereotypes that are hard to shake." (''[[Public Opinion]]'', 1922, 95-156).&lt;ref&gt;Ewen and Ewen, ''[[Typecasting: On the Arts and Sciences of Human Inequality]]'',  2006, 3-10.&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, ''cliché'' and stereotype were both originally printers' words, and in their literal printers' meanings were synonymous. Specifically, cliché was a French word for the printing surface for a stereotype.&lt;ref&gt;&lt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0877791325&amp;id=2yJusP0vrdgC&amp;pg=PA250&amp;lpg=PA250&amp;ots=nXvVkdB_U4&amp;dq=cliche+origin&amp;sig=f5UQIqottU546aRBe3zlm-9Q7kM#PPA250,M1 Merriam-Webster's Dictionary of English Usage.]&gt; Springfield, Illinois: Merriam-Webster, Inc., 1994. p. 250. &lt;/ref&gt;

The term "stereotype" derives from [[Greek language|Greek]] ''στερεός'' (''stereos'') "solid, firm"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3D%2396561 Stereos], Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', at Perseus&lt;/ref&gt; + ''τύπος'' (''tupos'') "blow, impression, engraved mark"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3D%23105942 Tupos], Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', at Perseus&lt;/ref&gt; hence "solid impression".
The term, in its modern psychology sense, was first used by [[Walter Lippmann]] in his 1922 work ''[[Public Opinion]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Hate Prejudice and Racism
|publisher=State University of New York Press
|date=August 1993
|isbn=079141535X
|author=Milton Kleg}}&lt;/ref&gt; although in the [[Stereotype (printing)|printing]] sense it was first coined 1798. 

==Dynamics==
[[Sociologists]] believe that mental categorizing (or [[labelling]]) is necessary and inescapable.  One perspective on how to understand stereotyping process is through the categories or ingroups and outgroups.  Ingroups are viewed as normal and superior, and are generally the group that one associates with or aspires to join.  An outgroup is simply all the other groups.  They are seen as lesser or inferior than the ingroups.

A second perspective is that of automatic and implicit or subconscious and conscious.  Automatic or subconscious stereotyping is that which everyone does without noticing.  Automatic stereotyping is quickly preceded by an implicit or conscious check which permits time for any needed corrections.  Automatic stereotyping is affected by implicit stereotyping because frequent conscious thoughts will quickly develop into subconscious stereotypes.

A third method to categorizing stereotypes is general types and sub-types.  Stereotypes consist of hierarchical systems consisting of broad and specific groups being the general types and sub-types respectively.  A general type could be defined as a broad stereotype typically known among many people and usually widely accepted, whereas the sub-group would be one of the several groups making up the general group.  These would be more specific, and opinions of these groups would vary according to differing perspectives.

Certain circumstances can affect the way an individual stereotypes.  For instance: Studies have shown that women stereotype more negatively than men, and that women read into appearance more than men.  Some theorists argue in favor of the conceptual connection and that one’s own subjective thought about someone is sufficient information to make assumptions about that individual. Other theorists argue that at minimum there must be a casual connection between mental states and behavior to make assumptions or stereotypes. Thus results and opinions may vary according to circumstance and theory. An example of a common, incorrect assumption is that of assuming certain internal characteristics based on external appearance.  The explanation for one’s actions is his or her internal state (goals, feeling, personality, traits, motives, values, and impulses), not his or her appearance.

Sociologist Charles E. Hurst of the College of Wooster states that, “One reason for stereotypes is the lack of personal, concrete familiarity that individuals have with persons in other racial or ethnic groups. Lack of familiarity encourages the lumping together of unknown individuals.&lt;ref name="Hurst"&gt;Hurst, Charles E. Social Inequality: Forms, Causes, and Consequences. 6. Boston: Pearson Education, Inc, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; 

Stereotypes focus upon and thereby exaggerate differences between groups.  Competition between groups minimizes similarities and magnifies differences.&lt;ref name="In-group"&gt;
{{cite journal
  |last=Brewer |first=M
  |title=In-group bias in the minimal intergroup situation: A cognitive-motivational analysis
  |journal=Psychological Bulletin
  |volume=86
  |issue=
  |pages=307–324
  |date=1979
  |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.86.2.307
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
This makes it seem as if groups are very different when in fact they may be more alike than different. For example, among [[African Americans]], identity as an American citizen is more salient than racial background; that is, African Americans are more American than African.&lt;ref name="African"&gt;
{{cite journal
  |last=McAndrew
  |first=FT
  |coauthors=Akande, A
  |title=African perceptions of Americans of African and European descent
  |journal=Journal of Social Psychology
  |volume=135
  |issue=5
  |pages=649–655
  |date=1995
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Yet within American culture, Black and White Americans are increasingly seen as completely different groups.

==== Theories ====
Different disciplines give different accounts of how stereotypes develop: Psychologists focus on how experience with groups, patterns of communication about the groups, and intergroup conflict. Sociologists focus on the relations among groups and position of different groups in a social structure. Psychoanalytically-oriented humanists have argued (e.g., Sander Gilman) that stereotypes, ''by definition'', the representations are not accurate, but a projection of one to another.

Many scientific theories have derived from the sociological studies of stereotyping and prejudicial thinking.  During the early studies it was believed or suggested that stereotypes were only used by rigid, repressed, and authoritarian people. Sociologists concluded that this was a result of conflict, poor parenting, and inadequate mental and emotional development. They now know differently.  Scientist and theorists have concluded that stereotypes do not only exist, but are actually a never ending chain of thoughts.

One theory as to why people stereotype is that it is too difficult to take in all of the complexities of other people as individuals. Even though stereotyping is inexact, it is an efficient way to mentally organise large blocks of information. Categorization is an essential human capability because it enables us to simplify, predict, and organize our world. Once one has sorted and organized everyone into tidy categories, there is every incentive to avoid processing new or unexpected information about each individual. Assigning general group characteristics to members of that group saves time and satisfies the need to predict the social world in a general sense.

Another theory is that people stereotype because of the need to feel good about [[Self (psychology)|oneself]]. Stereotypes protect one from anxiety and enhance [[self-esteem]].  By designating one’s own group as the standard or normal group and assigning others to groups considered inferior or abnormal, it provides one with a sense of worth. 

Some believe that childhood influences are some of the most complex and influential factors in developing stereotypes.  Though they can be absorbed at any age, stereotypes are usually acquired in early childhood under the influence of parents, teachers, peers, and the media. Once a stereotype is learned, it often becomes self-perpetuating.

==Effects, accuracy, terminology==
{{Main|Stereotype threat}}
Stereotypes can have a negative and positive impact on individuals. Joshua Aronson and Claude M. Steele have done research on the psychological effects of stereotyping, particularly its effect on African-Americans and women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Steele CM, Aronson J |title=Stereotype threat and the intellectual test performance of African Americans |journal=J Pers Soc Psychol |volume=69 |issue=5 |pages=797–811 |year=1995 |month=November |pmid=7473032 |doi= 10.1037/0022-3514.69.5.797|url=http://content.apa.org/journals/psp/69/5/797}}&lt;/ref&gt; They argue that psychological research has shown that competence is highly responsive to situation and interactions with others.&lt;ref name=AronsonBook&gt;Aronson J, Steele CM. (2005). [http://books.google.com/books?id=B14TMHRtYBcC&amp;printsec=frontcover#PRA1-PA436,M1 Chapter 24:Stereotypes and the Fragility of Academic Competence, Motivation, and Self-Concept]. In ''Handbook of Competence'', [ p. 436].&lt;/ref&gt; They cite, for example, a study which found that bogus feedback to college students dramatically affected their IQ test performance, and another in which students were either praised as very smart, congratulated on their hard work, or told that they scored high. The group praised as smart performed significantly worse than the others. They believe that there is an 'innate ability bias'. These effects are not just limited to minority groups. Mathematically competent white males, mostly math and engineering students, were asked to take a difficult math test. One group was told that this was being done to determine why Asians were scoring better. This group performed significantly worse than the other group.&lt;ref name=AronsonBook/&gt;{{rp|443}}

Possible prejudicial effects of stereotypes are:
*Justification of ill-founded prejudices or ignorance 
*Unwillingness to rethink one's attitudes and behavior towards stereotyped group 
*Preventing some people of stereotyped groups from entering or succeeding in activities or fields

The effects of stereotyping can fluctuate, but for the most part they are negative, and not always apparent until long periods of time have passed.  Over time, some victims of negative stereotypes display self-fulfilling prophecy behavior, in which they assume that the stereotype represents norms to emulate.  Negative effects may include forming inaccurate opinions of people, scapegoating, erroneously judgmentalism, preventing emotional identification, distress, and impaired performance.  Stereotyping painfully reminds those being judged of how society views them.

==Role in art and culture==
{{Unreferenced|date=December 2008}}

Stereotypes are common in various cultural [[media (communication)|media]], where they take the form of dramatic [[stock character]]s. These characters are found in the works of playwright [[Bertolt Brecht]], [[Dario Fo]], and [[Jacques Lecoq]], who characterize their actors as stereotypes for theatrical effect. In [[commedia dell'Arte]] this is similarly common. The instantly recognizable nature of stereotypes mean that they are effective in [[advertising]] and [[situation comedy]]. These stereotypes change, and in modern times only a few of the stereotyped characters shown in [[John Bunyan]]'s ''[[The Pilgrim's Progress]]'' would be recognizable.

In [[literature]] and [[art]], stereotypes are [[cliché]]d or predictable characters or situations. Throughout history, storytellers have drawn from stereotypical characters and situations, in order to connect the audience with new tales immediately. Sometimes such stereotypes can be sophisticated, such as [[Shakespeare]]'s [[Shylock]] in ''The Merchant of Venice''. Arguably a stereotype that becomes complex and sophisticated ceases to be a stereotype ''per se'' by its unique characterization. Thus while [[Shylock]] remains politically unstable in being a stereotypical [[Jew]], the subject of [[prejudicial]] derision in Shakespeare's era, his many other detailed features raise him above a simple stereotype and into a unique character, worthy of modern performance. Simply because one feature of a character can be categorized as being typical does not make the entire character a stereotype.

Despite their proximity in etymological roots, cliché and stereotype are not used synonymously in cultural spheres. For example a cliché is a high criticism in [[narratology]] where [[genre]] and [[categorization]] automatically associates a story within its recognizable group. Labeling a situation or character in a story as ''typical'' suggests it is fitting for its [[genre]] or [[Category (taxonomy)|category]]. Whereas declaring that a storyteller has relied on cliché is to pejoratively observe a simplicity and lack of originality in the tale. To criticize [[Ian Fleming]] for a ''stereotypically'' unlikely escape for [[James Bond]] would be understood by the reader or listener, but it would be more appropriately criticized as a cliché in that it is overused and reproduced. [[Narrative]] [[genre]] relies heavily on ''typical'' features to remain recognizable and generate meaning in the reader/viewer. 

The teen [[sitcom]], ''[[Saved By The Bell]]'' features a typical group of high school stereotypes such as a class clown ([[Zack Morris]]), a jock ([[A.C. Slater]]), a nerd ([[Samuel "Screech" Powers]]), a cheerleader ([[Kelly Kapowski]]), a feminist ([[Jessie Spano]]), and a superficial fashion plate ([[Lisa Turtle]]). Some observed the sitcom, like many teen sitcoms of that time, in addition to stereotyping people, stereotyping an institution itself, that of high school. [[TV]] stereotypes of high schools have often promoted a "typical American school" as football games, fashion styles, [[skirt chasing]], and not much devotion to [[academics]] or studying.

In movies and TV the [[halo effect]] is often used. This is when, for example, attractive men and women are assumed to be happier, stronger, nicer people, explained by Greenwald and Banaji from Psychological Review.

==Racial and ethnic stereotyping==
===Native Americans===
{{Seealso|Stereotypes of Native Americans}}

Native Americans have been stereotyped by others in both a negative and positive sense. There has long been an admiration of Native Americans as fitting the archetype of the [[noble savage]] within European thought, stemming from a cultural sympathy grounded within the post-[[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] theory of [[primitivism]].&lt;ref&gt;Anthony Pagden, ''The Fall of the Natural Man: the American Indian and the origins of comparative ethnology.'' ''Cambridge Iberian and Latin American Studies.''(Cambridge University Press, 1982)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See Paul Hazard, ''The European Mind (1680-1715)'' (Cleveland, Ohio: Meridian Books [1937], [1969]): 13-14, and passim.&lt;/ref&gt; These positive portrayals of Native Americans as being noble, peaceful people, who lived in harmony with nature and each other continue within modern culture, e.g. the 1990 film [[Dances with Wolves]].

Over time, as settlers spread west, Native Americans were seen as obstacles and their image became more negative. Native Americans were portrayed in popular media as wild, primitive, uncivilised, dangerous people who continuously attack white settlers, cowboys, and stagecoaches and ululate while holding one hand in front of their mouths. They speak invariably in a deep voice and use stop words like "How" and "Ugh". 

In drawings their skin colour was depicted as deep red. In westerns and other media portrayals they are usually called "Indians". Examples of this stereotypical image of Native Americans can be found in many American westerns until the early 1960s, and in cartoons like Peter Pan. In other stereotypes, they smoked peace pipes, wore face paint, danced round totem poles (often with a hostage tied to them), sent smoke signals, lived in tepees, wore feathered head-dresses, scalped their foes, and said 'um' instead of 'the' or 'a'.

As colonisation continued in the US, groups were separated into categories like “Christians” and “heathens” and “civilised” and “savage”. Many Whites view Native Americans as devoid of self-control and unable to handle responsibility. Malcolm D. Holmes and Judith A. Antell hypothesise that such ideas about Native Americans form the ideology that is used today to justify the disparity between Whites and Native Americans.[10] Today, a 19th century stereotype of Native Americans lives on for many people. Modern Native Americans as they live today are rarely portrayed in popular culture.

Due to somewhat recent reparations made by the U.S. government to the tribes which allow unregulated construction of casinos, along with unmonitored revenue received from the gambling, it has become a modern stereotype that a Native American must either own a casino or be in the family of one who does.

===Inuit stereotypes===
[[Inuit]] or [[Eskimo]] people are usually dressed in [[parka]]s, carving out trinkets, living in [[igloo]]s, going fishing with a [[harpoon]], traveling by [[sleigh]] and [[husky|huskies]], eating [[cod-liver oil]] and the men are usually called [[Nanook]] in reference to the famous documentary ''[[Nanook of the North]]''. Eskimo children may have a [[Pinniped|seal]] for a best friend. Eskimos are often believed to have an [[Eskimo words for snow|unusually large number of words for snow]]. This is however an [[urban legend]]. 

Eskimos are sometimes shown rubbing each other noses together as some sort of greeting ritual ([[Eskimo kissing]]). They're also often depicted surrounded by [[polar bear]]s, [[walrus]]es and inaccurately, with [[penguin]]s, which only live in the [[Southern hemisphere]] and not on the [[North Pole]]. Sometimes Eskimos themselves are depicted living on the South Pole, which is again wrong for the same reason.

===Black stereotypes===
{{Seealso|Stereotypes of African Americans}}

====Early stereotypes====
[[File:Virginia Minstrels, 1843.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Early
[[minstrel shows]] lampooned the supposed stupidity of black people. Detail from cover of ''The Celebrated Negro Melodies, as Sung by the Virginia Minstrels'', 1843]]

In centuries before and during the first half of the 20th century black people were often depicted as dumb, evil, lazy, poor, animalistic, smelly, uncivilised, un-Christian &lt;ref name="Hurst" /&gt; people. The early British colonists brought these initial thoughts with them to the US. White colonists commonly believed that black people were inferior to white people. These thoughts helped to justify black [[slavery]] and the institution of many laws that continually condoned inhumane treatment and perpetuated to keep black people in a lower socioeconomic position.&lt;ref name="Hurst" /&gt; 

Black people were usually depicted as [[slaves]] or [[servant]]s, working in [[Sugarcane|cane]] fields or carrying large piles of [[cotton]]. They were often portrayed as devout Christians going to church and singing [[gospel]] music. In many [[vaudeville]] shows, [[minstrel]] acts, [[cartoon]]s, [[comics]] and [[animated cartoon]]s of this period they were depicted as sad, lazy, dim-witted characters with big lips who sing [[blues]]y songs and are good dancers, but get excited when confronted with [[dice games]], [[chickens]] or [[watermelons]] (examples: all the characters portrayed by [[Stepin Fetchit]] and black characters in cartoons like "[[Sunday Go to Meetin' Time]]" and "[[All This and Rabbit Stew]]"). 

A more joyful black image, yet still very stereotypical, was provided by eternally happy black characters like [[Uncle Tom]], [[Uncle Remus]] and [[Louis Armstrong]]'s equally joyous stage persona. Another popular stereotype from this era was the black who is scared of ghosts (and usually turns white out of fear). [[Butler]]s were sometimes portrayed as black (for example the butler in many [[Shirley Temple]] movies). [[Housemaid]]s were usually depicted as black, heavy-set middle-aged women who dress in large skirts (examples of this type are [[Mammy Two-Shoes]], [[Aunt Jemima]], [[Beulah]] and more recently the title character of ''[[Big Momma's House]]''). Children are often [[pickaninnies]] like [[Little Black Sambo]] and [[Golliwog]]. Black [[jive (dialect)]] was also often used in comedy, like for instance in the show ''[[Amos 'n Andy]]''. 

African black people were usually depicted as primitive, [[child]]like, [[cannibal]]istic persons who live in tribes, carry spears, believe in [[witchcraft]] and worship their [[wizard]]. White colonists are depicted tricking them by selling junk in exchange for valuable things and/or scaring them with modern technology. A well-known example of this image is [[Tintin in Africa]]. When white people are caught by African tribes they are usually put in a large, black [[cauldron]] so they can be cooked and eaten. Sometimes black Africans are depicted as [[pygmies]] with childlike behavior so that they can be ridiculed as being similar to children. 

Other stereotypical images are the male black African dressed in [[lip plates]] or with a bone sticking through his [[nasal septum]]. Stereotypical female black African depictions include the bare breasted woman with large breasts and notably fat buttocks (examples of this stereotype are the 19th century [[sideshow]] attraction [[Saartjie Baartman]] and [[Robert Crumb]]'s comic strip character [[Angelfood McSpade]]) or the [[Ndebele people (South Africa)|woman who wears multiple rings around her giraffe-like neck]] (note: this type of neck ornament is also common in [[Burma]] with women from the [[Kayan (Burma)|Kayan]] tribe, but is generally associated with Africa (like in the [[Bugs Bunny]] cartoon "[[Which Is Witch]]").

[[Secretary of State]] [[John C. Calhoun]] arguing for the extension of slavery in 1844 said ''"Here (scientific confirmation) is proof of the necessity of slavery. The African is incapable of self-care and sinks into lunacy under the burden of freedom. It is a mercy to give him the guardianship and protection from mental death."''

Even after slavery ended the intellectual capacity of Black people was still frequently questioned. Lewis Terman wrote in ''The Measurement of Intelligence'' in 1916: &lt;blockquote&gt;"(Black and other ethnic minority children) are ineducable beyond the nearest rudiments of training. No amount of school instruction will ever make them intelligent voters or capable citizens in the sense of the world…their dullness seems to be racial, or at least inherent in the family stock from which they come…Children of this group should be segregated in special classes and be given instruction which is concrete and practical. They cannot master abstractions, but they can be made efficient workers…There is no possibility at present of convincing society that they should not be allowed to reproduce, although from a eugenic point of view they constitute a grave problem because of their unusual prolific breeding.)"&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Modern black stereotypes====
{{Seealso|Acting white|Counterstereotype}}

Since the 1960s the stereotypical image of black people has changed in some media.  More positive depictions appeared where black people and African-Americans are portrayed as great athletes and superb singers and dancers. In many films and television series since the 1970s black people are depicted as good natured, kind, honest and intelligent persons. Often they are the best friend of the white protagonist (examples: ''[[Miami Vice]]'', ''[[Lethal Weapon]]'', ''[[Magnum Force]]''). 

Some critics believed this [[political correctness]] led to another stereotypical image where black people are often depicted too positively. [[Spike Lee]] popularized the term ''[[Magical negro]]'', deriding the [[archetype]] of the "super-duper magical negro" in 2001 while discussing films with students at [[Washington State University]] and at [[Yale University]].&lt;ref name="strangehorizons"&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.strangehorizons.com/2004/20041025/kinga.shtml |title= Stephen King's Super-Duper Magical Negroes |first= Nnedi | last = Okorafor-Mbachu | authorlink = Nnedi Okorafor-Mbachu| work = Strange Horizons |date= [[2004-10-25]] | accessdate = 2006-12-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SpikeLee"&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.yale.edu/opa/arc-ybc/v29.n21/story3.html | title = Director Spike Lee slams 'same old' black stereotypes in today's films | first = Susan | last = Gonzalez | work = Yale Bulletin &amp; Calendar | publisher =[[Yale University]] | date = [[2001-03-02]] | accessdate = 2008-12-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One media survey in 1989 showed that blacks were more likely than whites to be described in demeaning intellectual terms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aafla.org/9arr/ResearchReports/ResearchReport4_.htm The Portrayal of Race, Ethnicity and Nationality in Televised International Athletic Events]&lt;/ref&gt; Political activist and one-time presidential candidate [[Rev. Jesse Jackson]] said in 1985 that the news media portray blacks as ''less intelligent than we are.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E2DC1739F93AA2575AC0A963948260 Jackson Assails Press On Portrayal of Blacks] (NYT)&lt;/ref&gt; Film director [[Spike Lee]] explains that these images have negative impacts. "In my neighborhood, we looked up to athletes, guys who got the ladies, and intelligent people," and the images widely portrayed black Americans as living in inner-city areas, very low-income and under-educated than whites.

Even so-called positive images of Black people can lead to stereotypes about intelligence. In ''Darwin's Athletes: how sport has damaged Black America and preserved the myth of race'', [[John Hoberman]] writes that the prominence of African-American athletes encourages a de-emphasis on academic achievement in black communities.&lt;ref&gt;''Darwin's Athletes: how sport has damaged Black America and preserved the myth of race'' By [[John Hoberman|John Milton Hoberman]] ISBN 0395822920&lt;/ref&gt; 

In a 1997 study on racial stereotypes in sports, participants were shown a photograph of a white or a black basketball player. They then listened to a recorded radio broadcast of a basketball game. White photographs were rated as exhibiting significantly more intelligence in the way they played the game, even though the radio broadcast and target player represented by the photograph were the same throughout the trial.&lt;ref&gt;''"White Men Can't Jump": Evidence for the Perceptual Confirmation of Racial Stereotypes Following a Basketball Game'' Jeff Stone, W. Perry, John M. Darley. Basic and Applied Social Psychology 1997, Vol. 19, No. 3, Pages 291-306&lt;/ref&gt; Several other authors have said that sports coverage that highlights 'natural black athleticism' has the effect of suggesting white superiority in other areas, such as intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;''The Ball Curve: Calculated Racism and the Stereotype of African American Men'' Ronald E. Hall Journal of Black Studies, Vol. 32, No. 1 (Sep., 2001), pp. 104-119&lt;/ref&gt;
	
Patricia J. Williams, writer for ''[[The Nation]]'', said this of [[Jar Jar Binks]], a character from the 1999 and 2002 [[Star Wars]] films ''The Phantom Menace'' and ''Attack of the Clones'', respectively: "...intentionally or not, Jar Jar's pratfalls and high jinks borrow heavily from the genre of minstrelsy. Despite the amphibian get-up, his manchild-like idiocy is imported directly from the days of [[Amos 'n' Andy]]." Many aspects of Jar Jar's character are believed to be highly reminiscent of the archetypes portrayed in [[blackface]] [[Minstrel show|minstrelsy]].&lt;ref
name="Williams"&gt;Patricia J. Williams: {{cite web
     |title=Racial Ventriloquism
     |publisher=The Nation
     |url=http://www.thenation.com/doc/19990705/williams
     |accessdate=June 11
     |accessyear=2006
     |date=[[June 17]], [[1999]]
   }}
 &lt;/ref&gt;)

===Middle Eastern and Muslim stereotypes===
{{See|Stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims|Western stereotypes of West and Central Asians}}
Stereotypes of Muslims often involve themes associated with [[violence]]. Other stereotypes may revolve around negative treatment of women, gay people, and non-Muslims. Also related is the concept of [[Islamophobia]], about the fear, hatred and dislike of Muslims.

===White stereotypes===
{{Main|Stereotypes of white people|White Anglo-Saxon Protestant|List of terms for white people in non-Western cultures}}
A classic, negative example is [[Homer Simpson]], the obese, lazy and dim-witted middle American from the cartoon, [[The Simpsons]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Kelly Whiteside|coauthors=Andy Gardiner|title=USA needs to find the net|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/soccer/worldcup/2006-06-20-us-ghana-preview_x.htm|publisher=[[USA Today]]|date=2006-08-20|accessdate=2008-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The show itself parodies many aspects of American life, culture and society.&lt;ref name=Turner,p78&gt;Turner, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Ugly American|American tourists travelling overseas of often stereotyped as loud, demanding and badly dressed]];&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/8143780.stm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Irish stereotypes===
[[File:Irish-stereotypes.jpg|thumb|right|200px|The cartoon above (New Physiognomy, New York, 1866), contrasts Florence Nightingale, the [[Crimean War]] nurse, with "Bridget McBruiser", the stereotypical Irish woman.]]
[[File:Scientific racism irish.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Scientific Racism from an American magazine, [[Harper’s Weekly]], says that the Irish are similar to 'Negroes.']]
An analysis of nineteenth-century British attitudes by [[Mary J. Hickman]] and Bronwen Walter wrote that the 'Irish Catholic' was one viewed as an "[[Other#The Other in the Social Sciences|other]]", or a different race in the construction of the English nationalist myth. Likewise, the Irish considered the English "other" and fought hard to break away and create their own homeland, which they finally did in the 1920s. &lt;ref&gt;''Deconstructing Whiteness: Irish Women in Britain'' Mary J. Hickman, Bronwen Walter
''Feminist Review'', No. 50, The Irish Issue: The British Question (Summer, 1995), pp. 5-19 doi:10.2307/1395487&lt;/ref&gt;

Benign in comparison to some of the more vulgar generalizations against other ethnicities but nonetheless incorrect are those accusing the [[Irish people|Irish]] as quick-tempered brawlers and alcoholics.  One 19th century British cartoonist even depicted [[Irish people|Irish]] immigrants as [[Ape|simian]] and racially different from Anglo-Saxons. One American doctor in the 1850s, [[James Redfield]], argued that "facial angle" was a sign of intelligence and character; likening the physiognomies of human ethnic groups to animals. Thus [[Irish people|Irishmen]] resembled dogs, Yankees were like bears, Germans like lions, Negroes like elephants and Englishmen like bulls.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0766179842&amp;id=qJW5iuEKdCMC&amp;pg=PA13&amp;lpg=PA13&amp;ots=8CX0kmAm4f&amp;dq=James+Redfield+1852+Comparative+physiognomy&amp;sig=uYg9nTMRiF1XF1w7m37elYwKyZ0#PPA11,M1]&lt;/ref&gt;
In the 20th century physical stereotypes survived in the comic books until the 1950s, with Irish characters like Mutt and Jeff, and Jiggs and Maggie appearing daily in hundreds of newspapers. &lt;ref&gt; Kerry Soper, "Performing 'Jiggs': Irish Caricature and Comedic Ambivalence toward Asøsimilation and the American Dream in George McManus's Bringing Up Father." ''Journal of the Gilded Age and Progressive Era'' 4.2 (2005): 72 pars. 30 Mar. 2007 [http://www.historycooperative.org/cgi-bin/justtop.cgi?act=justtop&amp;url=http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/jga/4.2/soper.html online]. &lt;/ref&gt;

Irish are also stereotypically viewed as stupid and the butt of many jokes. An example of this would be the "[[an Englishman, an Irishman and a Scotsman]]" joke, which usually ends in the Irishman doing something stupid.

===Italian stereotypes ===
See also [[Anti-Italianism]] about stereotypes and prejudice towards [[Italian people]].

=== Polish stereotypes ===
See also [[Anti-Polonism]] about stereotypes and prejudice towards [[Polish people]].

=== Jewish stereotypes===
[[File:Antisemitic caricature 1873.jpg|thumb|[[Antisemitic]] caricature based on racial stereotypes, 1873]]
{{main|Stereotypes of Jews}}
{{See also|Antisemitism|Racial antisemitism}}

[[Jew|Jewish people]] have been stereotyped throughout the centuries as [[scapegoats]] for a multitude of societal problems. [[Antisemitism]] continued throughout the centuries and reached a climax in the [[Third Reich]] during [[World War II]]. Jews are still stereotyped as greedy, nit-picky, stingy [[miser]]s. They have been often shown counting money or collecting [[diamond]]s. Early films such as Cohen's Advertising Scheme (1904, silent) stereotyped Jews as "scheming merchants."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lib.berkeley.edu/MRC/imagesjews.html The Movies, Race, and Ethnicity: Jews]&lt;/ref&gt;. 

In caricatures and cartoons they're often depicted having curly hair, large hook-noses, thick lips, and wearing [[kippah]]s. Common objects, phrases and traditions used to emphasize or ridicule Jewishness include [[bagel]]s, playing [[violin]], [[klezmer]], [[circumcision]], [[haggling]] and phrases like "[[Mazal Tov]]", "[[Shalom]]" and "[[Oy Vey]]". 

Other Jewish stereotypes are the [[rabbi]], the complaining and guilt-inflicting [[Jewish mother|Jewish mother stereotype]], the spoiled and materialistic [[Jewish-American Princess]] and the often meek [[Nice Jewish Boy]].

===East Asian and South Asian Stereotypes===
{{main|Stereotypes of Asians}}

See also [[Stereotypes of East Asians]] such as [[Chinese people]] and [[Stereotypes of South Asians]] such as [[East Indians]].

===Hispanic/Latino Stereotypes===
{{main|Stereotypes of Hispanics}}

See also [[Hispanophobia]] on fear, hatred and dislike of [[Latinos]].

== Sexually oriented stereotypes ==
===Sexual orientation stereotypes===
{{main|LGBT stereotypes}}
People with negative views of [[gay]], [[lesbian]], and [[transgender]] people often use stereotypes about them to justify their attacks. Sometimes, it has also fueled [[violence against LGBT people]]. According to [[ABC News]], "Gay activists often criticize media coverage of gay pride parades, saying, correctly, that the media focus on the extreme, the more flamboyantly feminine men and very masculine women. But that's not us, they say. Most of us are just like everyone else."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Gay Stereotypes: Are They True?|publisher=[[ABC News]]|url=http://i.abcnews.com/2020/Story?id=2449185&amp;page=3|date=Sept. 15, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Gay====
Gay individuals are often stereotyped as being sexually promiscuous, alcoholics, [[Party and play|as having substance abuse problems]], using cliche vocabulary, and as being wealthy. They are also stereotyped [[Effeminacy|as having feminine characteristics]].

====Lesbian====
Often characterized as either butch "[[Dyke (slang)|dykes]]", or [[Lipstick lesbians]]. Relationships are portrayed often as [[Butch and femme|one acting male and one acting female]].

====Bisexual====
Bisexual individuals are stereotyped as being sexually promiscuous and not wanting commitment. Male bisexuals are stereotyped as acting zealously homophobic but with secret homosexual tendencies which often surface when under the influence of [[alcohol]] of other [[controlled substance]]. Female bisexuals are depicted as nymphomaniacs with low standards regarding sexual partners or as being "attention starved".

====Pedophiles====
Pedophiles are stereotyped as being sexually violent, having exclusive attractions to children. Appearance-wise, pedophiles are stereotyped as the trench-coat clad "dirty old-man" or as socially awkward overweight middle-aged Caucasian males who act too friendly around children. They are also stereotyped as owning  and driving vans and carrying sweets and toys to lure children.

== Gender stereotypes ==
{{See also|Gender role|Masculinity|Femininity|Gender differences}}

===Masculine Gender===
{{See|Testosterone poisoning}}

===Feminine Gender===
{{See|Dumb blonde|Portrayal of women in video games}}

===Transgender===
Labels such as transgender serve both to challenge normative gender and at the same time are self stigmatizing. Individuals who do not fit the gendered binary are often stereotyped as being sexually promiscuous, sex workers, and as having drinking problems and drug addictions.

===Transexual===
The first reference to "stereotype", in its modern, English use was in 1850, in the noun, meaning "image perpetuated without change".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=stereotype Online Etymology Dictionary&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Socioeconomic Stereotypes ==
=====Homeless Stereotypes=====
[[Homeless]] individuals are stereotyped as having behavior problems, substance abuse problems, being lazy, and being dirty and/or smelly.

=====Working class stereotypes=====
Members of the [[working class]] or [[blue collar]]s are stereotyped as being poorly educated or being neglectful of their education either out of laziness or because they perceive the more educated members of society as "naive" and lacking "street smarts"(See [[Reverse snobbery]]). Working class males are stereotyped as placing more value on strength and athletic ability over intellect as intellectuals are perceived as being physically weak in the eyes of working class males. This is related to the "dumb jock" stereotype as jocks are often stereotyped as only being able to work blue-collar jobs later in life.

[[Spousal abuse]] and other [[violent crime]]s are also elements related to the stereotype as well as [[Binge drinking|excessive alcohol consumption]].

==Specialised use in ethology==
In [[ethology]], '''stereotyped''' behavior or [[fixed action pattern]] is an [[innate]], pre-programmed response that is repeated when an animal is exposed to an environmental [[innate releasing mechanism]].

== Criminal Profiling ==
[[Offender profiling]] is a criminal investigative tool which uses details relating to a criminal's [[Modus Operandi]] in order to develop a detailed set of psychological characteristics of the offender.

==By group==
* [[Stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims]]
* [[Stereotypes of East and Southeast Asians]]
* [[Stereotypes of East and Southeast Asians in the United States]]
* [[Stereotypes of Hispanics]]
* [[Stereotypes of Native Americans]]
* [[Stereotypes of South Asians]]
* [[Stereotypes of West and Central Asians]]
* [[Stereotypes of blacks]]
* [[Stereotypes of white people|Stereotypes of whites]]
* [[LGBT stereotypes]]
* [[Nurse stereotypes]]
* [[Animal stereotypes]]
* [[Ethnic stereotype]]
* [[Physical attractiveness stereotype]]

==See also==
{{Portal|Psychology|Psi.PNG}}
{{Portal|Sociology|Logo_sociology.svg}}

{{MultiCol}}
* [[Archetype]]
* [[Assumption]]
* [[Attribute substitution]]
* [[Attributional bias]]
* [[Cognitive bias]]
* [[Communication noise]]
* [[Counterstereotype]] (antonym)
* [[Labeling theory]]
{{ColBreak}}
* [[Milieu control]]
* [[Stock character]]
* [[Social control theory]]
* [[Stigmatization]]
* [[Stereotype threat]]
* [[Negativity effect]]
* [[Outgroup homogeneity bias]]
* [[Trait ascription bias]]
{{EndMultiCol}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* Stuart Ewen, Elizabeth Ewen, ''Typecasting: On the Arts and Sciences of Human Inequality''. New York (Seven Stories Press) 2006
* [http://www.stereotypeandsociety.typepad.com Stereotype &amp; Society] A Major Resource: Constantly updated and archived
* [http://www.understandingprejudice.org/apa/english/page11.htm Social Psychology Network] Stereotyping
* [http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/special_initiatives/toolkit/stereotypes/what_are_stereotypes.cfm Media Awareness Network. What is a stereotype?]  Definition, role of stereotyping in the media, more links
* {{Citation
 | last=Regenberg | first=Nina
 | year=2007
 | title=Are Blonds Really Dumb?
 | journal=in mind (magazine)
 | issue=3
 | date= 11-06-2007
 | url=http://www.in-mind.org/issue-3/are-blonds-really-dumb.html
}}
* [http://www.in-mind.org/issue-5/are-stereotypes-true.html Are Stereotypes True?]
* [http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1111/1467-9280.00111 Stereotype Susceptibility: Identity Salience and Shifts in Quantitative Performance, Margaret Shih, Todd L. Pittinsky, Nalini Ambady] Research about the effects of 'positive' and negative stereotypes on encouraging/discouraging performance.
*{{cite book
 |last=Turner |first=Chris
 |title=[[Planet Simpson: How a Cartoon Masterpiece Documented an Era and Defined a Generation]]
 |isbn=0-679-31318-4
 |year=2004
 |publisher=Random House Canada |location=Toronto
}}
*Crawford, M. &amp; Unger, R. (2004). Women and Gender: A Feminist Psychology. McGraw Hill New York. New York. 45-49.* 
*Spitzer, B.L., Henderson, K, A., &amp; Zavian, M. T. (1999). Gender differences in population versus media body sizes: A comparison over four decades. Sex Roles, 40, 545-565.*
*{{cite journal
 |author=Terracciano A, Abdel-Khalek AM, Adám N, ''et al.''
 |title=National character does not reflect mean personality trait levels in 49 cultures
 |journal=Science
 |volume=310 |issue=5745
 |pages=96–100
 |year=2005 |month=Oct
 |pmid=16210536
 |doi=10.1126/science.1117199
}}

==External links==
*[http://www.understandingprejudice.org/apa/english/page11.htm Social Psychology Network] Stereotyping
*[http://school.discovery.com/lessonplans/programs/stereotypes/ Understanding Stereotypes] - Educational information about stereotypes.
*[http://www.bu.edu/africa/outreach/materials/handouts/goldtodross.html SEPARATING the GOLD from the DROSS: a guide to multicultural literature]
*[http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/special_initiatives/toolkit/stereotypes/what_are_stereotypes.cfm Media Awareness Network. What is a stereotype?] Definition, role of stereotyping in the media, more links

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Stereotypes]]
[[Category:Social psychology]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;

[[ar:نمطية]]
[[ast:Estereotipu]]
[[ca:Estereotip]]
[[cs:Stereotyp]]
[[de:Stereotyp]]
[[et:Stereotüüp]]
[[es:Estereotipo]]
[[eo:Stereotipo]]
[[fa:کلیشه]]
[[fr:Stéréotype]]
[[hr:Stereotip]]
[[io:Stereotipo]]
[[id:Stereotipe]]
[[it:Stereotipo]]
[[he:סטריאוטיפ]]
[[lv:Stereotips]]
[[lt:Stereotipas]]
[[mk:Стереотип]]
[[ml:വാര്‍പ്പുമാതൃക]]
[[ms:Stereotaip]]
[[nl:Stereotype]]
[[ja:ステレオタイプ]]
[[no:Stereotyp]]
[[pl:Stereotyp]]
[[pt:Estereótipo]]
[[ru:Стереотип]]
[[simple:Stereotype]]
[[sk:Stereotyp]]
[[sr:Стереотип]]
[[sh:Stereotip]]
[[fi:Yleistys]]
[[sv:Stereotyp]]
[[th:สามัญทัศน์]]
[[zh:刻板印象]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>