<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081115043921|251907266" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18956166" pageid="18956166" ns="0" title="Stereotype"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T13:03:14Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Mergefrom|Social stereotype|date=October 2008}}
{{Articleissues|article=October 2008|refimprove = May 2008|cleanup = July 2008}}
{{otheruses}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{wiktionary|stereotype}}
A '''stereotype''' (from [[Greek language|Greek]]: ''stereo'' + ''týpos'' = "solid impression") is a generalized perception of first impressions: 
behaviors presumed by a group of people judging with the eyes/criticizing ones outer appearance (or a population in general) to be associated with another specific group. Stereotypes, therefore, can instigate [[prejudice]] and false assumptions about entire groups of people, including the members of different ethnic groups, social classes, religious orders, the opposite sex, etc. A stereotype can be a conventional and oversimplified conception, opinion, or image, based on the assumption that there are attributes that members of the "other group" have in common. Stereotypes are forms of social consensus rather than individual judgments. Stereotypes are sometimes formed by a previous [[illusory correlation]], a false association between two variables that are loosely correlated if correlated at all. Though generally viewed as negative perceptions, stereotypes may be either positive ''or'' negative in tone.

== Causes ==
[[Sociologist]] Charles E. Hurst of the College of Wooster states that, “One reason for stereotypes is the lack of personal, concrete familiarity that individuals have with persons in other racial or ethnic groups. Lack of familiarity encourages the lumping together of unknown individuals” &lt;ref name="Hurst"&gt;Hurst, Charles E. Social Inequality: Forms, Causes, and Consequences. 6. Boston: Pearson Education, Inc, 2007&lt;/REF&gt;. Different disciplines give different accounts of how stereotypes develop: Psychologists focus on how experience with groups, patterns of communication about the groups, and intergroup conflict. Sociologists focus on the relations among groups and position of different groups in a social structure. Psychoanalytically-oriented humanists have argued (e.g., Sander Gilman) that stereotypes, ''by definition'', the representations are not accurate, but a projection of one to another. 

Stereotypes are not accurate representations of groups, rather they arise as a means of explaining and justifying differences between groups, or [[system justification]].  Social status or group position determines stereotype content, not the actual personal characteristics of group members.&lt;ref name="Fact"&gt;{{cite journal
  |last=Jost
  |first=JT
  |coauthors=Banaji, MB
  |title=The role of stereotyping in system-justification and the production of false consciousness
  |journal=British Journal of Social Psychology
  |volume=33
  |issue=
  |pages=1–27
  |date=1994 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Groups which enjoy fewer social and economic advantages will be stereotyped in a way which helps explain disparities, such as lower employment rates.  Although disadvantaged group members may have greater difficulty finding a job due to in-group favoritism, racism, and related social forces, the disadvantaged group member is unjustifiably characterized as 'unmotivated' (he could find a job if he looked hard enough), 'unintelligent' (he's not smart enough to have that job), and 'lazy' (he would rather take hand-outs than work). 

Stereotypes focus upon and thereby exaggerate differences between groups.  Competition between groups minimizes similarities and magnifies differences.  
&lt;ref name="In-group"&gt;{{cite journal
  |last=Brewer
  |first=M
  |title=In-group bias in the minimal intergroup situation: A cognitive-motivational analysis
  |journal=Psychological Bulletin
  |volume=86
  |issue=
  |pages=307–324
  |date=1979
  |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.86.2.307 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
This makes it seem as if groups are very different when in fact they may be more alike than different. For example, among [[African Americans]], identity as an American citizen is a more salient categorization than racial background; that is, African Americans are more American than African.
&lt;ref name="African"&gt;{{cite journal
  |last=McAndrew
  |first=FT
  |coauthors=Akande, A
  |title=African perceptions of Americans of African and European descent
  |journal=Journal of Social Psychology
  |volume=135
  |issue=5
  |pages=649–655
  |date=1995 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Yet within American culture, Black and White Americans are often seen as completely different groups.

For as long as there has been a human species, individuals have been different from one another. Persons have gravitated to groups of other persons like themselves. People create and develop categories of qualities by which to classify the groups; some were based on ancestry. Many of these groupings have become the key factors in determining which groups have political, social, and economic power in the world.{{Fact|date=May 2008}}

Automatic stereotype activation can be totally involuntary, and is described as the activation of categorically associated "nodes", according to Leopold and Brown from the Journal of Personality and Social Psychology.

== Effects, accuracy, terminology ==
For individual people there can be both positive and negative effects of a stereotype which is seen to apply to them. The overall effects of stereotyping are seen by many to always be negative.

Some people believe that stereotypes are generally based on actual differences. Others believe that they are always false generalizations (by definition).

For some individual people the effects of this might be positive or negative - a separate issue to whether they are positive or negative for society. 

Stereotypes can be self-fulfilling to at least some extent.

Stereotypes can be deeply embedded in a culture. The term 'stereotype' is more often used once those perceived truths are put into arguments.

There are some complicating factors which arise when the accuracy of stereotypes is discussed. One of these is that a factor leading to stereotyping can be the existence of a group of people who do share a characteristic. For instance, there might be a reasonably significant number of men working in sales roles, and showing little integrity and honesty ('significant' in this context does not imply a majority). This can lead to the creation of a stereotype of a 'salesman' figure. In this limited sense it might be seen that the stereotype is based on a real group of people (i.e. salesmen who behave with little integrity). 

Possible prejudicial effects of stereotypes are:
*Justification of ill-founded prejudices or ignorance 
*Unwillingness to rethink one's attitudes and behavior towards stereotyped group 
*Preventing some people of stereotyped groups from succeeding in activities or fields

Often the terms ‘’stereotype’’ and ‘’[[prejudice]]’’ are confused.  Stereotypes are ‘’standardized’’ and ‘’simplified’’ conceptions of groups, based on some prior assumptions. Stereotypes are created based on some idea of abstract familiarity.  Prejudices are more specific - they are predispositions to differential behavior patterns.

==Role in art and culture==
[[Image:National Conveniences 1024.jpg|thumbnail|300px|English prejudice in 1796 was fundamental]]
Stereotype is often used as a form of dramatic [[shorthand]] for "[[stock character]]". Stereotypes change with time. The unwitting use of some stereotypes appears awkward to a present-day audience which refuses to tolerate a representation of individuals based on that stereotype. Many other stereotypes pass unnoticed, sometimes even by those being stereotyped. Examples of ''active use'' are found in the work of Brecht and other dramatic styles which allow the actor to demonstrate a character's level of ''role distance'', thus showing the ''active use''. Retrospectively these [[stock characters]] have been illuminated by the work of [[Brecht]], [[Dario Fo]] and [[Jacques Lecoq]], despite their original reference to local [[Italy|Italian]] stereotypes in their early [[genesis]]. Importantly in drama the actor does not create a stereotype; rather their [[characterisation]] may be simple in that they represent an uncritical reflection of the stereotype, and it is this simplicity which aggravates a present-day audience. A subtle and detailed characterisation, especially of the [[commedia Dell'arte]] stock characters, results in a unique and immediate performance that will be enjoyed by an audience due to the clear active use of the characters by the actor.  

In [[literature]] and [[art]], stereotypes are [[cliché]]d or predictable characters or situations. Throughout history, storytellers have drawn from stereotypical characters and situations, in order to connect the audience with new tales immediately. Sometimes such stereotypes can be sophisticated, such as [[Shakespeare]]'s [[Shylock]] in ''The Merchant of Venice''. Arguably a stereotype that becomes complex and sophisticated ceases to be a stereotype ''per se'' by its unique characterisation. Thus while [[Shylock]] remains politically unstable in being a stereotypical [[Jew]], the subject of [[prejudicial]] derision in Shakespeare's era, his many other detailed features raise him above a simple stereotype and into a unique character, worthy of modern performance. Simply because a feature of a character can be categorized as being typical does not make the entire character a stereotype.

Despite their proximity in etymological roots, cliché and stereotype are not used synonymously in cultural spheres. For example a cliché is a high criticism in [[narratology]] where [[genre]] and [[categorization]] automatically associates a story within its recognizable group. Labeling a situation or character in a story as ''typical'' suggests it is fitting for its [[genre]] or [[Category (taxonomy)|category]]. Whereas declaring that a storyteller has relied on cliché is to pejoratively observe a simplicity and lack of originality in the tale. To criticize [[Ian Fleming]] for a ''stereotypically'' unlikely escape for [[James Bond]] would be understood by the reader or listener, but it would be more appropriately criticized as a cliché in that it is overused and reproduced. [[Narrative]] [[genre]] relies heavily on ''typical'' features to remain recognizable and generate meaning in the reader/viewer. 

The instantly recognisable nature of stereotypes mean that they are very useful in producing effective [[advertising]] and [[situation comedy]].  Media stereotypes change and evolve over time - for instance, we now instantly recognize only a few of the stereotyped characters shown to us in [[John Bunyan]]'s ''[[The Pilgrim's Progress]]''.
The teen [[sitcom]], [[Saved By The Bell]] features a typical group of high school stereotypes such as a class clown ([[Zack Morris]]), a jock ([[A.C. Slater]]), a nerd ([[Samuel "Screech" Powers]]), a cheerleader ([[Kelly Kapowski]]), a feminist ([[Jessie Spano]]), and a superficial fashion plate ([[Lisa Turtle]]). Some observed the sitcom, like many teen sitcoms of that time, in addition to stereotyping people, stereotyping an institution itself, that of high school. [[TV]] stereotypes of high schools have often promoted a "typical American school" as football games, fashion styles, [[skirt chasing]], and not much devotion to [[academics]] or studying.

In movies and TV the [[halo effect]] is often used. This is when, for example, attractive men and women are assumed to be happier, stronger, nicer people, explained by Greenwald and Banaji from Psychological Review.

==Racial and ethnic stereotyping==
{{Refimprovesect|date=October 2008}}
===Native Americans===

{{Seealso|Stereotypes of Native Americans}}

The stratification and separation of groups, especially racial minorities, in the United States began in the nation’s earliest years of colonization. With the colonists’ first contact with the [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]], the stereotype of “the savage” was born. &lt;ref name="Hurst" /&gt; They were first thought of as "noble savages" by the European because of their ability to subsist on the land. Over time, as colonists spread west, Natives American were seen as obstacles and their image became more negative. Native Americans were portrayed in popular media as wild, primitive, uncivilized, dangerous people who continuously attack white settlers, [[cowboy]]s, and [[stagecoach]]es and [[ululate]] while holding one hand in front of their mouths. They speak invariably in a deep voice and use [[stop words]] like "How" and "Ugh". In cartoons, comic strips and animated cartoons their skin color was depicted as deep red. In westerns and other media portrayals they are usually called "Indians". Examples of this stereotypical image of Native Americans can be found in many American [[western]]s until the early 1960s and cartoons like [[Peter Pan (1953 film)]]. 

As colonization continued in the US, groups were separated into categories like “Christians” and “heathens” and “civilized” and “savage” &lt;ref name="Hurst" /&gt;. It took merely decades for these attitudes and ideas to firmly plant themselves in the minds of Americans; today’s stereotypes of Native Americans are rooted in the colonists’ initial thoughts. The media perpetuates these stereotypes by portraying Native Americans in a negative light, such as savage and hostile &lt;ref name="Hurst" /&gt;. Many Whites view Native Americans as devoid of self-control and unable to handle responsibility. Malcolm D. Holmes and Judith A. Antell hypothesize that such ideas about Native Americans form the ideology that is used today to justify the disparity between Whites and Native Americans &lt;ref&gt;Holmes, Malcolm D., and Judith A. Antell. 2001. “The Social Construction of American Indian Drinking: Perceptions of American Indian and White Officials.” Sociological Quarterly 42:151-173&lt;/ref&gt;. This very rigid, fixed framework on the perception of Native Americans and other stereotypical depictions of other races and nationalities has been continued in many books, films, cartoons, comic strips, plays and songs. Today, the 19th century stereotype of Native Americans lives on for the majority of people. Modern Native Americans as they live today are rarely portrayed in popular culture, one notable exception being Chief from [[One Flew Over The Cuckoo's Nest]].

===Black stereotypes===
{{Seealso|Stereotypes of African Americans}}

====Early stereotypes====
[[Image:Virginia Minstrels, 1843.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Early
[[minstrel shows]] lampooned the supposed stupidity of Blacks. Detail from cover of ''The Celebrated Negro Melodies, as Sung by the Virginia Minstrels'', 1843]]

In centuries before and during the first half of the 20th century black people were often depicted as dumb, evil, lazy, poor, animalistic, uncivilized, un-Christian &lt;ref name="Hurst" /&gt; people. The early Anglo-Saxon colonists brought these initial thoughts with them to the US. White colonists commonly believed that black people were inferior to white people. These thoughts helped to justify black [[slavery]] and the institution of many laws that continually condoned inhumane treatment and perpetuated to keep black people in a lower socioeconomic position. &lt;ref name="Hurst" /&gt;. Black people were usually depicted as [[slaves]] or [[servant]]s, working in [[cane]] fields or carrying large piles of [[cotton]]. They were often portrayed as devout Christians going to church and singing [[gospel]] music. In many [[vaudeville]] shows, [[minstrel]] acts, [[cartoon]]s, [[comics]] and [[animated cartoon]]s of this period they were depicted as sad, lazy, dim-witted characters with big lips who sing [[blues]]y songs and are good dancers, but get excited when confronted with [[dice games]], [[chickens]] or [[watermelons]] (examples: all the characters portrayed by [[Stepin Fetchit]] and black characters in cartoons like [[Sunday Go to Meetin' Time]] and [[All This and Rabbit Stew]]). A more joyful black image, yet still very stereotypical, was provided by eternally happy black characters like [[Uncle Tom]], [[Uncle Remus]] and [[Louis Armstrong]]'s equally joyous stage persona. Another popular stereotype from this era was the black who is scared of ghosts (and usually turns white out of fear). [[Butler]]s were sometimes portrayed as black (for example the butler in many [[Shirley Temple]] movies). [[Housemaid]]s were usually depicted as black, heavy-set middleaged women who dress in large skirts (examples of this type are [[Mammy Two-Shoes]], [[Aunt Jemima]], [[Beulah]] and more recently the title character of [[Big Momma's House]]). Children are often [[pickaninnies]] like [[Little Black Sambo]] and [[Golliwogg]]. Black [[jive (dialect)]] was also often used in comedy, like for instance in the show [[Amos 'n Andy]]. 

African black people were usually depicted as primitive, [[child]]like, [[cannibal]]istic persons who live in tribes, carry spears, believe in [[witchcraft]] and worship their [[wizard]]. White colonists are depicted tricking them by selling junk in exchange for valuable things and/or scaring them with modern technology. A well-known example of this image is [[Tintin in Africa]]. When white people are caught by African tribes they are usually put in a large, black [[cauldron]] so they can be cooked and eaten. Sometimes black Africans are depicted as [[pygmies]] with childlike behavior so that they can be ridiculed as being similar to children. Other stereotypical images are the male black African dressed in [[lip plates]] or with a bone sticking through his [[nasal septum]]. Stereotypical female black African depictions include the bare breasted woman with large breasts and notably fat buttocks (examples of this stereotype are the 19th century [[sideshow]] attraction [[Saartjie Baartman]] and [[Robert Crumb]]'s comic strip character [[Angelfood McSpade]]) or the [[Ndebele people (South Africa)|woman who wears multiple rings around her giraffe-like neck]] (note: this type of neck ornament is also common in [[Burma]] with women from the [[Kayan (Burma)]] tribe, but is generally associated with Africa (like in the [[Bugs Bunny]] cartoon [[Which Is Witch]]).

[[Secretary of State]] [[John C. Calhoun]] arguing for the extension of slavery in 1844 said ''"Here (scientific confirmation) is proof of the necessity of slavery. The African is incapable of self-care and sinks into lunacy under the burden of freedom. It is a mercy to give him the guardianship and protection from mental death."''

Even after slavery ended the intellectual capacity of Black people was still frequently questioned. Lewis Terman wrote in ''The measurement of intelligence'' in 1916 &lt;blockquote&gt;"(Black and other ethnic minority children) are uneducable beyond the nearest rudiments of training. No amount of school instruction will ever make them intelligent voters or capable citizens in the sense of the world…their dullness seems to be racial, or at least inherent in the family stock from which they come…Children of this group should be segregated in special classes and be given instruction which is concrete and practical. They cannot master abstractions, but they can be made efficient workers…There is no possibility at present of convincing society that they should not be allowed to reproduce, although from a eugenic point of view they constitute a grave problem because of their unusual prolific breeding.)"&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Modern black stereotypes====
{{Seealso|Acting white}}

Since the 1960s the stereotypical image of black people has changed in some media.  More positive depictions appeared where black people and African-Americans are portrayed as great athletes and superb singers and dancers. In many films and television series since the 1970s black people are depicted as good natured, kind, honest and intelligent persons. Often they are the best friend of the white protagonist (examples: [[Miami Vice]], [[Lethal Weapon]], [[Magnum Force]],...). Some critics believed this [[political correctness]] lead to another stereotypical image where black people are often depicted too positive 1989 showed that blacks were more likely than whites to be described in demeaning intellectual terms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aafla.org/9arr/ResearchReports/ResearchReport4_.htm The Portrayal of Race, Ethnicity and Nationality in Televised International Athletic Events]&lt;/ref&gt; Political activist and one-time presidential candidate [[Rev. Jesse Jackson]] said in 1985 that the news media portray blacks as ''less intelligent than we are.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E2DC1739F93AA2575AC0A963948260 Jackson Assails Press On Portrayal of Blacks] (NYT)&lt;/ref&gt; Film director [[Spike Lee]] explains that these images have negative impacts. "In my neighborhood, we looked up to athletes, guys who got the ladies, and intelligent people,".

Even so-called positive images of Black people can lead to stereotypes about intelligence. In ''Darwin's Athletes: how sport has damaged Black America and preserved the myth of race'', [[John Hoberman]] writes that the prominence of African-American athletes encourages a de-emphasis on academic achievement in black communities.&lt;ref&gt;''Darwin's Athletes: how sport has damaged Black America and preserved the myth of race'' By [[John Hoberman|John Milton Hoberman]] ISBN 0395822920&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1997 study on racial stereotypes in sports, participants were shown a photograph of a white or a black basketball player. They then listened to a recorded radio broadcast of a basketball game. White photographs were rated as exhibiting significantly more intelligence in the way they played the game, even though the radio broadcast and target player represented by the photograph were the same throughout the trial.&lt;ref&gt;''"White Men Can't Jump": Evidence for the Perceptual Confirmation of Racial Stereotypes Following a Basketball Game'' Jeff Stone, W. Perry, John M. Darley. Basic and Applied Social Psychology 1997, Vol. 19, No. 3, Pages 291-306&lt;/ref&gt; Several other authors have said that sports coverage that highlights 'natural black athleticism' has the effect of suggesting white superiority in other areas, such as intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;''The Ball Curve: Calculated Racism and the Stereotype of African American Men'' Ronald E. Hall Journal of Black Studies, Vol. 32, No. 1 (Sep., 2001), pp. 104-119&lt;/ref&gt;
	
Patricia J. Williams, writer for [[The Nation]], said this of [[Jar Jar Binks]], a character from the 1999 and 2002 [[Star Wars]] films ''The Phantom Menace'' and ''Attack of the Clones'', respectively: "...intentionally or not, Jar Jar's pratfalls and high jinks borrow heavily from the genre of minstrelsy. Despite the amphibian get-up, his manchild-like idiocy is imported directly from the days of [[Amos 'n' Andy]]." Many aspects of Jar Jar's character are believed to be highly reminiscent of the archetypes portrayed in [[blackface]] [[Minstrel show|minstrelsy]].&lt;ref
name="Williams"&gt;Patricia J. Williams: {{cite web
     |title=Racial Ventriloquism
     |publisher=The Nation
     |url=http://www.thenation.com/doc/19990705/williams
     |accessdate=June 11
     |accessyear=2006
     |date=[[June 17]], [[1999]]
   }}
 &lt;/ref&gt;)

===Arabic, North African and Middle Eastern stereotypes===
{{Seealso|Stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims}}
{{Seealso|Western stereotypes of West and Central Asians}}

Especially in [[United States|American]] and [[European]] Cultures, They are often depicted as fanatical [[Muslim]]s who are often out on the kill and shout out or chant gibberish with many "ch-"sounds. Their noses, mustaches and beards are often exaggerated in caricature. Popular images are the Muslim flying on a carpet, climbing on an erect rope, riding a [[camel]], drawing out [[dagger]]s or [[sabre]]s or sitting in a tent smoking a [[water pipe]]. Arabic people are often depicted as rich oil sheiks with sunglasses and a [[turban]] (often mocked by comedians as being a [[towel]] or a [[diaper]]) on their head. Women are dressed in [[burka]]s and often carry a vase on their head. Young Arabic women are often shown as [[belly dance]]rs. Since the 1970s and especially since the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]] the negative depiction of Arabic people as [[terrorist]]s has increased throughout the world. In many Western countries they are seen as uneducated, aggressive, criminal, [[antisemitism|antisemitic]], [[misogyny|misogynistic]] and dangerous people who don't work but live on government funding, slaughter sheep in their kitchens, have many children and plot to take over the world. Many [[far right]] parties and organizations use this stereotypical image for [[propaganda]] uses. Just like Indian or Pakistani people, Arabic people are often depicted as shopkeepers or managers of supermarkets.An example of stereotyping is offered by the town of Herouxville in Quebec, Canada. A declaration issued by the town in January 2007, which was designed to inform immigrants, "that the way of life which they abandoned when they left their countries of origin cannot be recreated here [i.e. Herouxville]". It then went on to state that the immigrant population would therefore have to refrain from their cultural norms and activities such as to "kill women by stoning them in public, burning them alive, burning them with acid, circumcising them, etc."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kwintessential.co.uk/cultural-services/articles/stereotypes-intercultural.html Stereotyping: An Intercultural No-No]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indian, Pakistani, Hindu and other South Asian stereotypes===
{{Seealso|Stereotypes of South Asians}}

Indians and other South Asians are often depicted as shopkeepers, supermarket store clerks, [[guru]]s, [[snake charmer]]s etc. They are shown riding on elephants, worshiping cows, watching [[Bollywood]] movies, and eating hot spices and [[curry]]. Women are dressed in [[sari]]. Another popular image is the near-naked [[fakir]], hypnotist or illusionist who can stick knives in his body, fly on a carpet, climb on an [[Indian rope trick|erect rope]], walk barefoot on burning coals, refuses all food, [[levitation|levitates]], [[meditation|meditates]], remains underground with his head or body and sit or sleep on a [[bed of nails]]. A famous example of a Indian stereotype is [[Apu Nahasapeemapetilon]]. However modern day Indian Americans are often stereotyped as either software programmers or students. In the US the stereotypical [[Gujarati]]s run motels, [[Punjabi]]s drive cabs and [[South India]]ns work in the IT arena.

===East Asian stereotypes===
{{Seealso|Stereotypes of East and Southeast Asians in the United States}}
{{Seealso|Japanese stereotypes}}
Asians have generally been portrayed in the media as intelligent in math, but unsociable. They have also been portrayed as having no peripheral vision (which attributes to poor motor skills such as "bad driving"). Common stereotypes include [[martial art]]ists, geeks, exotic women, and foreigners. In Westerns, they are usually depicted as proprietors of [[laundries]]. Chinese people have often been portrayed in the media as [[rice]] eating, idiotically grinning people who have long [[Queue (hairstyle)|queues]], wear [["douli"]] on their heads and walk around with their hands hidden in long robes. They usually mutter gibberish with many words that rhyme on "-ng"-sounds. In more modern media this image has changed and was replaced by the image of the Asian as a martial art expert. Japanese people are often represented as extremely polite and obedient but dislike foreigners. They bow extensively and are very good business people. Their stop words are: "honourable" (or honorable), "regrettable" and "please". Chinese and Japanese people are often depicted as replacing the letters "-l" and "-r" with each other. Old Chinese or Japanese people are often depicted as extremely wise, bearded men who speak in [[aphorism]]s and are forever trying to calm down their young, enthusiastic students (an example of this stereotype is the martial master in [[Karate Kid]]). Young East Asian women are also depicted as being attractive and working as exotic dancers, massues' and manicurists.  In China, Japan, and Korea they are also noted to have lots of plastic surgeons/surgeries. East Asian cuisine is stereotyped, as well; Japan is known for seafood, such as fish eggs and whales. Chinese delicacies like [[thousand-year-old egg]] and [[bird nest soup]] are well-known among Westerners, and Koreans are said to favor kimchi.

===White stereotypes===
{{Seealso|Stereotypes of White people }}
The social definition of "White" has changed over the years, and several White groups have at times been portrayed by the media as unintelligent.  This includes ethnic groups such as the British, Irish, and Slavs.&lt;ref&gt;Leo W. Jeffres, K. Kyoon Hur (1979) White Ethnics and their Media Images Journal of Communication 29 (1), 116–122.&lt;/ref&gt;

====White American stereotypes====
Especially in [[Europe]]an countries, Americans are stereotyped as brash, ignorant, self-important, unintelligent, decadent, prudish on sexual matters, and obese. The image of the obese American could be due to perception of the American diet, such as the popularity and global spread of American [[fast food]] franchises such as [[McDonald's]] and [[Burger King]], which has fueled America's obesity crisis&lt;ref&gt; [[Brian Wansink]] and [[Mike Huckabee]] (2005), “De-Marketing Obesity,” California Management Review, 47:4 (Summer), 6-18.&lt;/ref&gt;. Another popular American stereotype is the [[cowboy]], the overconfident cigar chomping business man (see for instance [[Tintin in America]], where both stereotypes are present) and the ignorant tourist couple who has no interest or respect for authentic culture (see for instance the American couple depicted in the [[Fawlty Towers]] episode [[Waldorf Salad (Fawlty Towers)|Waldorf Salad]] and the one in [[Monty Python's Meaning of Life]] as well as the couple in the English [[Flushed Away]]). The international image of America and Americans changed drastically during the 1960s and 1970s at the height of the [[Vietnam War]]. Since then Americans are seen globally in a more negative light as arrogant, gung-ho, ruthless, [[imperialism|imperialistic]], [[capitalism|capitalistic]] warmongers and destroyers of authentic international cultures and the [[natural environment]].This negative stereotypical image has remained intact over the years, also due to negative foreign news or documentary reports that often show Americans who are either [[racism|racist]], obese, supporters of wars in foreign countries, [[gun]] crazy, obsessed with [[God]] and [[Jesus]] or reacting against sex or nudity in the media. In recent years, some stereotypes of whites living in the rural [[Western United States]] have emerged. Although these stereotypes show some similarities with southern redneck stereotypes, they are unique, usually revolving around cowboy culture, [[survivalism]], or [[Mormonism]]. One stereotype is the shotgun-toting, antisocial, fundamentalist conspiracy theorist who lives in a wooden shack and fears outsiders. He is typically waiting and preparing for some sort of apocalyptic event involving the [[Antichrist]] and/or a government that attempts to dismantle the constitution. This stereotype is likely the result of various incidents during the [[1990's]].

A lot of these American stereotypes are based on American sitcoms where characters like [[Al Bundy]] and [[Archie Bunker]] are seen as representative for the typical dumb, cultureless white American. There are many other examples throughout the media, but the classic example is [[Homer Simpson]], the obese, lazy and dim-witted middle American from the cartoon, [[The Simpsons]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Kelly Whiteside|coauthors=Andy Gardiner|title=USA needs to find the net|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/soccer/worldcup/2006-06-20-us-ghana-preview_x.htm|publisher=[[USA Today]]|date=2006-08-20|accessdate=2008-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;. The show itself parodies many aspects of American life, culture and society&lt;ref name=Turner,p78&gt;Turner, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;.

In the US itself white people from the Southern states are frequently used as comic characters. They are depicted as angry and/or dimwitted [[redneck]]s and/or [[yokel]]s who are ultraconservative, devoutly religious, [[Ku Klux Klan]] members, still carry the [[Confederate Flag]] around, grab their guns when encountering strangers and speak in a typical slang. Sometimes [[incest]] relations between them and their siblings are suggested. Examples of these stereotypes are [[Cletus Spuckler]], [[The Beverly Hillbillies]], several characters in the films [[Deliverance]] and [[O Brother, Where Art Thou?]] and the [[Family Guy]] episode [[To Love and Die in Dixie]].

====Canadian stereotypes====
Canadian people are stereotyped as beer-obsessed, [[tuque]]-wearing, somewhat slow-witted [[ice hockey]] players who always end their sentences with "[[eh]]". (This last stereotype is based on the characters [[Bob and Doug McKenzie]] from the Canadian sketch comedy show ''[[Second City Television|SCTV]]''). Canada is viewed as always cold. Canadians are often stereotypically represented as [[Royal Canadian Mounted Police|Mounties]]. Films depicting stereotypical views of Canadians include ''[[Canadian Bacon]]'' and ''[[Strange Brew]]''.

====English stereotypes====
The [[English people]] are stereotyped as inordinately proper, phlegmatic, polite and sophisticated. In many countries, especially on the European continent,  they are seen as incredibly awful cooks, something that has been spoofed in [[Asterix in Britain]] (see also [[English cuisine]]). In [[Canada]] and the [[United States]] British people are often depicted as having bad teeth (for instance in the [[The Simpsons|Simpsons]] episode [[Last Exit to Springfield]], the [[Family Guy]] episode [[One If by Clam, Two If by Sea]] and the film [[Austin Powers: International Man of Mystery]]). &lt;ref&gt; [http://www.guardian.co.uk/notesandqueries/query/0,5753,-22429,00.html "A staple of American humor about the UK is the population's bad teeth."] &lt;/ref&gt;  A popular English stereotype is the [[upper class]] man dressed in [[bowler hat]], black suit who always carries an [[umbrella]], believes in [[tradition]] and the [[monarchy]] and interrupts everything for the sake of having his [[tea (meal)|tea time]]. English stereotypes are often depicted as stiff [[businessperson|business men]], [[nanny|nannies]] (for instance: [[Mary Poppins (film)|Mary Poppins]]), [[aviator]]s, [[sailor]]s, [[officer (armed forces)|military commanders]] and [[gardener]]s.  Characters in historical movies often have English accents even when the setting has nothing to do with England. Upper-class characters are also often given English accents. In more recent times, many movie villains, including Benedict from ''[[Last Action Hero]]'', [[Scar (The Lion King)|Scar]] from ''[[The Lion King]]'', and [[Hannibal Lecter]] from ''[[The Silence of the Lambs (film)|The Silence of the Lambs]]'' and even most of the members of "The Empire" in [[Star Wars]] with the notable exception of the [[Sith]], have all been portrayed by British actors or given English accents. They are usually represented as intellectual, eloquent, [[snob]]bish geniuses, who in the end are humiliated by someone who is more egalitarian. Colonials and military commanders are sometimes depicted as stiff, pompous English people (examples are Colonel Hathi in [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]]'s [[The Jungle Book (1967 film)|Jungle Book]]). Another stereotype is the redcoat, a traditional British soldier with a musket, cannon, or on a wooden ship, as shown in the [[South Park]] episode [[The Snuke]].

Notably, in Disney films from the 1990s onward, English accents are generally employed to serve one of two purposes: [[slapstick]] [[comedy]] or evil genius.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A891155 "Why Villains in Movies Have English Accents".] January 15, 2003 &lt;/ref&gt; Examples include ''The Lion King'' ([[Zazu]] and Scar, respectively), ''[[The Hunchback of Notre Dame (1996 film)|The Hunchback of Notre Dame]]'' (Victor the Gargoyle and Frollo, respectively), and ''[[Pocahontas (1995 film)|Pocahontas]]'' (Wiggins and Ratcliffe, respectively, both of whom happen to be played by the same actor, American [[David Ogden Stiers]]).

'''English Rose'''

A typical female stereotype of the English is the sexy and beautiful "English Rose" type which can be seen in many forms, from fashionista Victoria Beckham, sophisticated Elizabeth Hurley to the glamorous Katie Price.

====Scottish stereotypes====
Scots are often depicted as dour [[miser]]s, [[grouchy]] red bearded people who are dressed in [[kilt]]s and play [[bagpipes]]. They drink [[scotch]] whisky and eat [[haggis]]. Sometimes they are depicted playing [[golf]] or [[Highland Games]]. Invariably they have names starting with "Mac...". Stereotypical words used are "aye", "laddie", "wee" and a strong emphasis on the letter "r". Scots are often depicted as being fatalistic and with chips on their shoulders. Examples of stereotypical Scottish people are [[Groundskeeper Willie]], James Saksa, and [[Fat Bastard]].

====Welsh stereotypes====

Welsh people are often regarded as stoic, if somewhat dull people with rare talents when it comes to singing and an obsession with rugby union. The Welsh are often shown as being a nation of druids and coal miners - insular, and unwelcoming to the English but kindly to other races. They are also known for their foods, and their ability to hold their liquor. They are also known for showing great courage in the face of overwhelming odds. They are often portrayed as having sexual relationships with sheep due to Wales being primarily agricultural, which has led to the term "[[Sheepshagger]]". They are predominately shown with the "sing song" accent of the South Wales valleys though this one of the least common accents. They are shown singing in [[choirs]], and having a thing for the [[Arthurian legends]].

====Irish stereotypes====
{{Seealso|Irish jokes}}
[[Image:Irish-stereotypes.jpg|thumb|right|200px|The cartoon above (New Physiognomy, New York, 1866), contrasts Florence Nightingale, the [[Crimean War]] nurse, with "Bridget McBruiser", the stereotypical Irish woman.]]
[[Image:Scientific racism irish.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Scientific Racism from an American magazine, [[Harper’s Weekly]], says that the Irish are similar to 'Negroes.']]
Although the Irish, Germans, French, etc are considered ethnic groups today, the common term in the 19th century was "race". Much was made of Celtic versus Anglo-Saxon racial characteristics, regarding historic identity and behavior patterns. An analysis of nineteenth-century British attitudes by [[Mary J. Hickman]] and Bronwen Walter wrote that the 'Irish Catholic' was one viewed as an "[[Other#The Other in the Social Sciences|other]]," or a different race in the construction of the British nationalist myth [of course this view no longer exists in any way, the Irish are now seen as fellow inhabitants of the British Isles]. Likewise the Irish considered the English "other" and fought hard to break away and create their own homeland, which they finally did in the 1920s. &lt;ref&gt;''Deconstructing Whiteness: Irish Women in Britain'' Mary J. Hickman, Bronwen Walter
''Feminist Review'', No. 50, The Irish Issue: The British Question (Summer, 1995), pp. 5-19 doi:10.2307/1395487&lt;/ref&gt;

One 19th century British cartoonist even depicted [[Irish people|Irish]] immigrants as ape-like and as racially different. One American doctor in the 1850s [[James Redfield]], argued that "facial angle" was a sign of intelligence and character.  He likened the facial characteristics of the human races to animals. Thus Irishmen resembled dogs, Yankees were like bears, Germans like lions, Negroes like elephants, Englishmen like bulls, Turks like turkeys, Persians like peacocks, Greeks like sheep, Hindus like swans, Jews like goats, and Frenchmen like frogs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0766179842&amp;id=qJW5iuEKdCMC&amp;pg=PA13&amp;lpg=PA13&amp;ots=8CX0kmAm4f&amp;dq=James+Redfield+1852+Comparative+physiognomy&amp;sig=uYg9nTMRiF1XF1w7m37elYwKyZ0#PPA11,M1]&lt;/ref&gt;
In the 20th century physical stereotypes survived in the comic books until the 1950s, with Irish characters like Mutt and Jeff, and Jiggs and Maggie appearing daily in hundreds of newspapers. &lt;ref&gt; Kerry Soper, "Performing 'Jiggs': Irish Caricature and Comedic Ambivalence toward Asøsimilation and the American Dream in George McManus's Bringing Up Father." ''Journal of the Gilded Age and Progressive Era'' 4.2 (2005): 72 pars. 30 Mar. 2007 [http://www.historycooperative.org/cgi-bin/justtop.cgi?act=justtop&amp;url=http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/jga/4.2/soper.html online]. &lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gnome]]s and [[leprechaun]]s sometimes speak with dubious Irish accents, probably due to the popular Irish folkloric image of gnomes and dwarves.

Contemporary stereotypes attempt to portray the Irish as frivolous drunkards, with an innate proclivity for brawling and misbehavior. They are shown using the phrase 'so it is' at the end of statements.

====Australian stereotypes====
A lot of these stereotypes are reflected in [[Crocodile Dundee]] and [[Monty Python]]'s [[Bruces sketch]] and the character [[Sir Les Patterson]]. Australian stereotypical characters always use expressions like "Crikey!", "G'day, mate" and "Put another [[shrimp]] on the [[barbecue|barbie]]."(despite the fact they use the term prawn) They are often represented as being unsophisticated and obsessed with [[beer]] and [[surfing]],  [[boomerang]]s and [[kangaroo]]s. Australian men are often shown as being macho, misogynistic brutes.
The 'Ozzie' woman is seen as a beach babe with a sexy accent or conversely a more loutish tomboy figure who swears often. However due to people like [[Germaine Greer]] and [[Dame Edna]] they are also generally seen as independent, well educated and forthright to a fault.

====French stereotypes====
{{Unreferencedsection|date=November 2008}}
French people are often depicted as dirty, unshaven, curly moustached people wearing berets, striped shirts and carrying [[baguette]]s under the arm or as onion sellers. They are often depicted as being [[arrogant]], dirty, rude to foreigners, lazy and always speaking English like [[Maurice Chevalier]]. Often, in reference to [[World War II]], they are depicted as being cowards who surrender immediately when confronted with sudden danger. They will frequently be seemingly addicted to [[croissant]]s or tarts, or, in a more positive image, are depicted as excellent [[cooks]] (Examples are Louis in [[The Little Mermaid]] and the cooks in [[Ratatouille (2007 film)|Ratatouille]]). French stereotypes are used quite a lot in comedies or animated cartoons where these characters always talk in the same way: "the" and "this" are pronounced "zee" and "zis", the words "mais oui", "ami" or "mon chéri" are used non-stop and the "w" is pronounced "ooweee". Examples are [[Inspector Clouseau]], [[Lumière]] in [[Beauty and The Beast]] and [[Pepe Le Pew]]. Sometimes, like in the movie [[Shrek]], people are depicted as being French for no apparent reason other than evoking laughs while using the accent.

====German stereotypes====
{{Unreferencedsection|date=November 2008}}
German people have been portrayed with a number of stereotypes that can be grouped into several categories.

'''Ubermensch Stereotype'''

One stereotypical rendition of German people portrays them as austere, humorless, hyper-organized, bureaucratic, and mechanical. In appearance, they are imposingly tall, often slender, though possibly portly, with sharply chiseled facial features. The "Ubermensch" is generally portrayed working as a scientist, professor, military leader, businessman, or generic aristocrat. In their speech, they normally tend toward a soft, wily tone of voice which quickly erupts into a harsh, guttural bark when they are provoked. At no time will they be given to excessive words. They may have subtle or overt racist tendencies harking not just to [[Nazism]] but [[Nietzsche]]ian philosophy of the [[Übermensch]]. Modern depictions of the "Ubermensch" extend to the enjoyment of harsh, austere forms of music such as [[industrial]], [[Krautrock]], and [[techno]], and many German bands of these genres intentionally play up those stereotypical aspects.

'''Die Frau'''

Die Frau is essentially the female version of the Ubermensch. With her hair pulled back into a suffocatingly tight bun, she tends to bark her imperious will in a shrill, abrasive tone and is unvaryingly depicted in a dominant role. Die Frau is often used as the facade of Nazi female kommandants and BDSM dominatrices as such roles call for an extremely authoritative and domineering woman.

'''Bavarian Stereotype'''

In sharp contrast to the "Ubermensch", the "Bavarian" is portrayed as warm and cuddly. The males wear [[lederhosen]], [[Tyrolean hats]], and mustaches, while the women wear [[dirndls]], and both sexes are clad in a mix of mostly white and green with red trim. This rendition of Germans sees them rejecting the austerity of the "Ubermensch" stereotype and enjoying the simple pleasures in life. Such Germans are seen drinking beer from [[beer stein|steins]] in great quantity, feasting on [[schnitzel]], [[sauerkraut]], and [[sauerbraten]], and dancing to [[oompa]] music. It should be noted that this stereotype derives from stereotypical views of southern Germans, the Bavarians, as well as the Austrians, but is invoked as a stereotype for all Germans today.

'''Beermaiden Stereotype'''

The "Beermaiden" is generally portrayed as a subset of the "Bavarian". "Beermaidens" are pretty but robust women with long blonde hair in pigtails, ample breasts, and powerful arms capable of delivering a dozen steins of beer, in accordance with "Bavarian" stereotypes (and to some degree, reality). This stereotype is an amalgam of various ideals of Teutonic women, ranging from the Nazis' view of the Aryan womanhood - capable of as much physical labor as men, but with very feminine and maternal physical characteristics to produce a new generation of Aryans - to [[Richard Wagner|Wagnerian]] depictions of the female warrior [[Brynhildr]] as portrayed in [[Der Ring des Nibelungen]].

'''Recent and other Stereotypes'''

One new avatar of the German citizen becoming popular in Britain is that of the conscientious post-[[World War II]] German. This stereotype is popularly applied to German tourists who are depicted as being incredibly polite and respectful and growing nervous at the mention of the War. The stereotype derives from the intense and public guilt of the German people for war crimes committed in the '30s and '40s, as demonstrated by draconian restrictions on speech, and especially proscriptions against denying the [[Holocaust]].

Other portrayals of Germans, usually applied in alliance with one of the above stereotypes, include [[pickelhaube]]-wearing warmongers (stemming from Germany's role in the two world wars, though other [[Axis Powers|Axis]]/[[Central Powers|Central]] powers do not seem to share this stereotype), monocle-wearing mad scientists with generally more malicious ends than beneficent ones, absent-minded professors, and very robust opera singers playing the role of the aforementioned Brynhildr (Brunhilde in German).

====Italian stereotypes====
{{Unreferencedsection|date=November 2008}}
Italian people have evolved a diverse range of stereotypes stemming from a very regular and unwavering set of core characteristics, those being physicality, sensuality, melodrama, and most of all, Catholicism. Italians and Southern Europeans as a whole acquired a reputation as being rather alien to European American culture mostly on basis of their (from the WASP viewpoint) heretical spirituality. Thus traits of profligacy, hedonism, and loudness are usually depicted in stereotypical Italians. Excessively cerebral traits are usually not ascribed to Italians, the very noteworthy exception being art, as it stems from their sensuality. Thus Italians and Italian Americans are seen as first-rate singers, painters, fashion designers, and sculptors while seldom as professors, engineers, physicists, and computer programmers.

'''The Don'''

The Don stereotype depicts the storied old-world aged Italian male. Most often portrayed as a mafioso, the Don is late-middle-aged to elderly with a wisdom earned more from life experience than academia and as such echoes the portrayals of elderly Asian males. The Don exhibits a refined dignity in keeping with European values rather than the thuggish mentality of his equally caricatured Italo-American subjects, and speaks in a husky voice with his Italian accent intact. The Don, when not involved with the mafia or when retired, is shown to enjoy quintessentially Italian pastimes such as tending an olive or tomato garden at a villa against an iconic Tuscan backdrop. Vito Corleone of [[The Godfather (film)|The Godfather]] is the best known example of the Don.

'''The Wop'''

The rank and file Italian stereotype, the Wop embodies the most basic and simplistic of traits ascribed to Italians. Most often wearing a mustache (and when portrayed in historical or humorous contexts, a waxed handlebar mustache), the Wop talks in a comical rendition of the Italian accent in which the schwa is inserted semirandomly into English speech such that it flows similarly to their native tongue, as in "I ain't-a gonna make-a pasta no more!" while illustrating his speech with exaggerated gesticulations. The Wop is often depicted as a chef with impeccable cooking skills, and indeed who lives for his cooking, or he may be portrayed as a market vendor selling fruit or ice cream (gelato). The Wop may display any combination of basic Italian stereotypes and lack others, ranging from hypermasculinity and an antediluvian attitude toward women to a short, angry temper. Famous examples of the Wop are the iconic [[Mario Bros.]] and the character portrayed by [[Chico Marx]].

'''The Guido'''

The Guido is the Wop's American cousin. Generally at least a second generation American, or one with no first-hand knowledge of authentic Italian culture, the Guido practices a lifestyle based upon the Italian one but through an American lens, and speaks most commonly in an Italian-inflected [[New York accent]]. The Guido most frequently prizes machismo and physicality over delicate intellectualism, viewing women as potential conquests. While Guidos are seen as thugs in some contexts, they are as often revered for their coolness and masculinity, as in the culture of "greasers". The Guido frequently goes by the diminutive form of his often Italian first name, such as Johnny, Danny, Nicky, or Richie. In the post-50s world, the Guido culture remained alive and well with some changes and additions. The IROC Camaro gained infamy for its alternative acronym, "Italian Retards Out Cruising". Well-known avatars of the Guido include Danny Zucco of [[Grease (film)|Grease]], and Arthur Fonzarelli.

'''The Italian Stallion'''

Either Italian or Italo-American, the Italian Stallion is the personification of the Italians' reputation for sensuality, physicality, and masculinity. The Italian Stallion is as mysterious and exotic as the Guido is transparent and simple. Often, the Stallion will walk around in public with an open shirt to display his pectoral muscles and substantial chest hair as a peacock does his feathers. The Italian Stallion is generally of an economic status such that he can afford exquisite fashions such as Armani suits and ties, and Gucci loafers. He may be seen driving an ostentatious Italian sports car or stealthily tooling around town on a more modest yet classy Vespa. The Stallion is, of course, known best for his sexual prowess both in the bedroom and leading up to, and for his potent genitalia, the reputation of which rivals that of black men. [[Fabio]] is a real-life, though comically extreme, example of the Italian Stallion, while [[Marcello Mastroianni]] is another example.

'''The Bombshell'''

Based upon such real-world examples as [[Sophia Loren]], [[Gina Lollobrigida]] and [[La Cicciolina]], the Bombshell is the female counterpart of the Italian Stallion. Possessing a self-confidence and sensual character alien to that of Anglo-American women, the Bombshell also sports a buxom, curvaceous body clearly evolved to fulfill a singular need of sexual fulfillment. The Bombshell is mysterious and mildly predatory, a femme fatale, and thus is as much a metaphor for the dangers of succumbing to the appeal of a woman who is not of the Protestant, Anglo-American culture as she is a character in her own right.

'''The Nona'''

Where the Bombshell represents the danger and mystery of Catholic Southern European people, the Nona represents their homey, familiar qualities. Universally an excellent cook, though less interested in concocting haute cuisine than in nourishing meals, the Nona talks in an Italian accent, and is indeed from Italy most often, and always has something baking in the oven for her grandchildren whom she spoils to no end. The Nona is a popular marketing icon for Italian food companies.

====Swedish Stereotypes ====
{{Unreferencedsection|date=November 2008}}
Swedish people have a limited but varied number of stereotypes stemming from essentially two core sources: the [[Vikings]] of the [[Dark Ages]] and modern [[Sweden]]'s liberal attitudes toward sex. As well, Swedish cultural fixtures figure into stereotypes, such as [[IKEA]], the cradle-to-grave [[welfare state]] (and its attendant taxation), [[Volvo]]s, and the singsong accent parodied by [[The Swedish Chef]].

'''The Blonde Babe'''

Inspired by real-life blonde women, [[Victoria Silvstedt]], [[Ulrika Jonsson]], [[Britt Ekland]], [[Agnetha Fältskog]], the Blonde Babe of Sweden is universally blonde, blue-eyed, fair-skinned, and soft-featured. Blonde Babes are tall, slender, sexually precocious, and seldom known for their stunning intellect. Indeed, where the Italian Bombshell archetype is wily, seductive, and a solitary predator, the Blonde Babe is in a word, fun.

'''Sven'''

The archetypal Swedish male name, Sven is the basic Swedish male stereotype. As tall, fair-featured, and pretty as his female counterpart, Sven does not particularly prize virility as it is traditionally viewed. Interested in cerebral pursuits such as art and aesthetics, history, and culture, Sven is a sensitive intellectual who nevertheless enjoys sex, epecially with Blonde Babes. Sven doesn't worry too much about life for he lives in a comfortable flat with colorful, sleek IKEA furniture, is cared for by a welfare system, and can't be bothered with thuggish behavior.

'''The Viking'''

The Viking is just as often not actually a Viking. Rather the Viking represents the perception of Swedish males prior to the liberal welfare state. That is to say the Viking is tall, blue eyed, and blonde, but ruggedly built to survive Nordic winters in austere conditions. Obsessed with his country's pagan past and the stark beauty of the north, the Swedish Viking is a creature of the forest (in contrast to the Norwegian stereotype, Swedes are a sylvan people while Norwegians are maritime), rhapsodizing about trolls, kobolds, and elves and exploring as his medieval forebears once did. The Viking often practices [[Asatru]], the traditional Norse paganism, can write in runic, and most likely wears a beard. The stereotype of the Viking inspires and is in turn inspired by the [[heavy metal]] community of Sweden, and indeed Sweden is as much known today for death metal as it is for IKEA and Volvo. Real-life examples of the "Viking" include [[Andreas Hedlund]] (Vintersorg), [[Tomas Lindberg]] of [[At the Gates]], and the members of [[Einherjer]].

====Slavic Eastern European and Russian stereotypes====
{{Unreferencedsection|date=November 2008}}
They are usually depicted as harsh, [[primitive]], miserable, poor [[peasant]]s or workers. Sometimes they cook [[soup]], [[stew]], [[goulash]] or eat [[yoghurt]], [[paprika]] or [[salami]]. Men always have moustaches/beards and carry bearskin hats and women [[babushka]]s. When they have finished drinking a glass with strong liquor, they throw the glass over their shoulder while it crashes against the wall or the ground. The population is often involved in [[espionage]] or spied upon by the [[secret police]]. Many of these stereotypes still date back to the [[Cold War]] era and [[Dracula]] movies, who are [[often]] set in [[Romania]]. Men often shout with an angry, booming voice. Women are sometimes depicted as being more masculine than feminine. [[Gypsies]] are also often associated with Eastern Europe. More positive stereotypical depictions of Eastern Europeans and Russians are the excellent [[ballet]] dancer(s) and [[violin]]ists. Their speech often puts a strong emphasis on the letter "r" and "g"-sounds are put in front of words beginning with the letter "h". Other popular cliché expressions are "njet" ("no") and "da!" ("yes"). 
    
Before (and long after) the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Revolution]] Russians were often represented as black bearded [[Cossack]]s with heavy [[eyebrow]]s, who dance [[trepak]]s, ride in [[troika]]'s, play [[violin]], eat [[caviar]] or drink [[vodka]] in snowy landscapes. During the Cold War Russians and Eastern Europeans were often depicted as evil or primitive in anti[[communist]] [[propaganda]]. Since the 1990s the depiction of Russians as part of the [[Russian mafia]] has increased.

====Jewish stereotypes====
[[Image:Antisemitic caricature 1873.jpg|thumb|[[Antisemitic]] caricature based on racial stereotypes, 1873]]
{{Seealso|Racial antisemitism}}

To this day Jewish people are sometimes stereotyped in media as being intellectually gifted,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.interfaithfamily.com/site/apps/nl/content2.asp?c=ekLSK5MLIrG&amp;b=297398&amp;ct=3525311 Not Crazy About Goy Crazy] By Lynn Melnick&lt;/ref&gt;, nit-picky, and focused on money. Other stereotypes are the [[rabbi]], the complaining and guilt inflicting [[Jewish mother|Jewish mother stereotype]], the spoiled and materialistic [[Jewish-American Princess]] and the [[Nice Jewish Boy]].

In early films such as Cohen's Advertising Scheme (1904, silent) stereotyped Jews as "scheming merchants"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lib.berkeley.edu/MRC/imagesjews.html The Movies, Race, and Ethnicity: Jews]&lt;/ref&gt;

In many modern day comedy and films, Jews are often depicted as having curly hair, large noses, and wearing kippahs.

===Hispanic, Latino, Middle and South-American stereotypes===  
{{Unreferencedsection|date=November 2008}}
{{Seealso|Stereotypes of Hispanic and Latino Americans}}
They are often depicted as hot-blooded, proud, lazy people who prefer to take [[siesta]]s instead of working. Typical activities are playing guitar in group (often songs like [[La Cucaracha]]) or alone, while singing a [[serenade]] to their loved one. Young Latinos are often seen as [[gang]] related groups who often speak [[Spanglish]]. Other activities are bull fighting, cooking olives or extremely hot food and drinking strong liquor. Typical expressions are shouting "Olé!" or "Ayayayayayayay" when they are excited about something. Everybody is called "señor" or "señorita". The men always have long black moustaches. Presidents in [[Latin America]]n settings are depicted having short reigns and are deposed by "[[Revolution|una revolución]]". Afterwards they are shot by [[firing squad]]s. Men are frequently cast as [[drug dealers]], [[dictators]], [[soccer]] fanatics or cigar smoking [[guerrillero]]'s. Women are usually loosely dressed and [[promiscuity|promiscuous]], big breasted, long haired beauties. In recent popular culture Latinos are often depicted as illegal [[immigrant]]s. Examples or these Hispanic stereotypes are: [[Bumblebee Man]], [[Speedy Gonzales]], and the characters in [[Asterix in Spain]] and [[Tintin and the Broken Ear]].

==Sex and gender stereotyping==
{{Refimprovesect|date=October 2008}}
{{Seealso|Gender roles}}
{{Seealso|LGBT stereotypes}}
Sex and gender stereotyping could be classified as a single idea. Although sex is usually defined as a person's biological traits, gender is defined as how a person identifies themselves to the world. Gender relates to those affectations that are attributed to men and those affectations that are attributed to women. It is important to understand that in this discussion it requires a social structure that tends to enforce a binary sex and gender role based on a person's biological characteristics.

Gender stereotypes are those ideas, usually imposed by society of what is expected of men and women in the social structure. In most modern Western cultures, men are expected to be assertive, risk-taking, tough, unfeeling, insensitive, combative, the owner or ruler of the home, whereas women are expected to be the nurturers, caregivers, demure, polite, the family homemaker. Younger men are often depicted as obnoxious, prideful about promiscuous and sometimes violent behavior.

Stereotypes of women may include lesser capabilities and/or competencies in math and science in comparison to men. (Crawford &amp; Unger, 2004) Aside from dealing with stereotypes of cognitive capabilities , women also have to confront stereotypes about their physical appearance. Young women may suffer from low self-esteem and develop distorted conceptions of bodies. Various media outlets and entertainment such as Playboy ©, Barbie ©, the Miss America Pageant and images seen in women’s magazines, television and movies lead to stereotypes of how girls and women should strive to be in society. From the 1950s through the ‘90s, the depiction of woman’s body in the Miss America contest and Playboy centerfolds became steadily thinner. (Spitzer, Henderson, &amp; Zivian, 1999) Such portrayals of women’s bodies leads to unnecessary standards for weight and size.

==Homosexual Stereotyping==
Homosexuality has led to many stereotypes.  One example is the girly man gay guy, who is feminine, wimpy, and knows designers.  Their stereotypical jobs are usually involved in fashion, such as designing clothes.  Another stereotype is the drag queen, who dresses up in womens clothing.  Lesbians, on the other hand, are often depicted as butch man-girls, who love sex and all things sexual.

==Etymology==
The word ''stereotype'' is of Greek origin (στερεότυπος), literally meaning "solid-kind". It was invented by [[Firmin Didot]] in the world of [[printing]]; it was originally a duplicate impression of an original [[typographic]]al element, used for [[printing]] instead of the original. American journalist [[Walter Lippmann]] coined the metaphor, calling a stereotype a "picture in our heads" saying "Whether right or wrong, ...imagination is shaped by the pictures seen... Consequently, they lead to stereotypes that are hard to shake." ([[Public Opinion]], 1922, 95-156).&lt;ref&gt;Ewen and Ewen, ''[[Typecasting: On the Arts and Sciences of Human Inequality]]'',  2006, 3-10.&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, ''cliché'' and stereotype were both originally printers' words, and in their literal printers' meanings were synonymous. Specifically, cliché was a French word for the printing surface for a stereotype.&lt;ref&gt;&lt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0877791325&amp;id=2yJusP0vrdgC&amp;pg=PA250&amp;lpg=PA250&amp;ots=nXvVkdB_U4&amp;dq=cliche+origin&amp;sig=f5UQIqottU546aRBe3zlm-9Q7kM#PPA250,M1 Merriam-Webster's Dictionary of English Usage.]&gt; Springfield, Illinois: Merriam-Webster, Inc., 1994. p. 250. &lt;/ref&gt;

The first reference to "stereotype", in its modern, English use was in 1850, in the noun, meaning "image perpetuated without change".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=stereotype Online Etymology Dictionary&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Specialised use in Ethology==
In [[ethology]], '''stereotyped''' behavior or [[fixed action pattern]] is an [[innate]], pre-programmed response that is repeated when an animal is exposed to an environmental [[innate releasing mechanism]].

==See also==
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-1-of-3}}
* [[Archetype]]
* [[Animal stereotypes]]
* [[Counterstereotype]] (antonym)
* [[Ethnic stereotype]]
* [[Stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims]]
* [[Stereotypes of East and Southeast Asians]]
* [[Stereotypes of Hispanics]]
* [[Stereotypes of Native Americans]]
* [[Stereotypes of West and Central Asians]]
* [[Stereotypes of blacks]]
* [[Stereotypes of whites]]
{{Col-2-of-3}}
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[LGBT stereotypes]]
* [[Milieu control]]
* [[Nurse stereotypes]]
* [[Prejudices]]
* [[Race and Inequality]]
* [[Racial profiling]]
* [[Role]]
* [[Stock character]]
* [[Social control theory]]
* [[Stigmatization]]
* [[Stereotype threat]]
{{Col-3-of-3}}
* [[Psychology]]:
* [[Negativity effect]]
* [[Outgroup homogeneity bias]]
* [[Physical attractiveness stereotype]]
* [[Trait ascription bias]]
* [[Urban legend]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
*Stuart Ewen, Elizabeth Ewen, ''Typecasting: On the Arts and Sciences of Human Inequality''. New York (Seven Stories Press) 2006
*[http://www.stereotypeandsociety.typepad.com Stereotype &amp; Society] A Major Resource: Constantly updated and archived
*[http://www.understandingprejudice.org/apa/english/page11.htm Social Psychology Network] Stereotyping
*[http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/special_initiatives/toolkit/stereotypes/what_are_stereotypes.cfm Media Awareness Network. What is a stereotype?]  Definition, role of stereotyping in the media, more links
* [http://www.in-mind.org/issue-3/are-blonds-really-dumb-2.html Are Blonds Really Dumb?] An article on Stereotyping
* [http://www.in-mind.org/issue-5/are-stereotypes-true.html Are Stereotypes True?]
* [http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1111/1467-9280.00111 Stereotype Susceptibility: Identity Salience and Shifts in Quantitative Performance, Margaret Shih, Todd L. Pittinsky, Nalini Ambady] Research about the effects of 'positive' and negative stereotypes on encouraging/discouraging performance.
*{{cite book |last=Turner |first=Chris |title=[[Planet Simpson: How a Cartoon Masterpiece Documented an Era and Defined a Generation]] |id=ISBN 0-679-31318-4}}
*Crawford, M. &amp; Unger, R. (2004). Women and Gender: A Feminist Psychology. McGraw Hill New York. New York. 45-49.* 
*Spitzer, B.L., Henderson, K, A., &amp; Zavian, M. T. (1999). Gender differences in population versus media body sizes: A comparison over four decades. Sex Roles, 40, 545-565.*

==External links==
*[http://www.understandingprejudice.org/apa/english/page11.htm Social Psychology Network] Stereotyping
*[http://school.discovery.com/lessonplans/programs/stereotypes/ Understanding Stereotypes] - Educational information about stereotypes.
*[http://www.aegee.tv/movies/archive/movies/202.html Short movie: Stereotypes in conflict] - Reaction from people in shopping center on business men, weird &amp; slutty types and goths.
*[http://www.bu.edu/africa/outreach/materials/handouts/goldtodross.html SEPARATING the GOLD from the DROSS: a guide to multicultural literature]
*[http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/special_initiatives/toolkit/stereotypes/what_are_stereotypes.cfm Media Awareness Network. What is a stereotype?]  Definition, role of stereotyping in the media, more links
*[http://dictionary.reference.com/search?r=2&amp;q=stereotype Dictionary - Stereotype] Online Dictionary

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Stereotypes]]
[[Category:Social psychology]]

&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;
[[ast:Estereotipu]]
[[ca:Estereotip]]
[[da:Stereotyp]]
[[de:Stereotyp]]
[[et:Stereotüüp]]
[[es:Estereotipo]]
[[fr:Stéréotype]]
[[gd:Dlùth-chlòdh]]
[[hr:Stereotip]]
[[io:Stereotipo]]
[[id:Stereotipe]]
[[it:Stereotipo]]
[[he:סטריאוטיפ]]
[[lt:Stereotipas]]
[[mk:Стереотип]]
[[nl:Stereotype]]
[[ja:ステレオタイプ]]
[[no:Stereotyp]]
[[pl:Stereotyp]]
[[pt:Estereótipo]]
[[ru:Стереотип]]
[[simple:Stereotype]]
[[sk:Stereotyp]]
[[sr:Стереотип]]
[[fi:Yleistys]]
[[sv:Stereotyp]]
[[tr:Basmakalıp]]
[[zh:刻板印象]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>