<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20210727210618|1035816277" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="61759333" pageid="61759333" ns="0" title="Tatarophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-08-03T15:46:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Fear, hatred towards, demonization of, or prejudice against people generally referred to as Tatars}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
'''Anti-Tatar sentiment''' or '''Tatarophobia''' ({{lang-ru|Татарофобия|Tatarofobiya}}) refers to the fear, hatred towards, demonization of, or prejudice against people generally referred to as [[Tatars]], including but not limited to [[Volga Tatars|Volga]], [[Siberian Tatars|Siberian]], and [[Crimean Tatars]], although negative attitudes against the latter are by far the most severe, largely in part due to the long history of Soviet media only depicting them in a negative way and promoting negative stereotypes to help politically justify their deportation and marginalization.

== Against Crimean Tatars ==
=== Soviet era ===
After the [[deportation of the Crimean Tatars]] in May 1944, the government strongly promoted existing negative stereotypes of Crimean Tatars and built up upon them; declaring them to be "traitors", "bourgeoisie", "counter-revolutionary", and falsely implied that they were "Mongols" with no historical connection to the Crimean peninsula. Political agitation by party members encouraged other citizens at deportation destinations to abuse them and conferences in Crimea dedicated to promoting and sharing anti-Crimean-Tatar sentiments was held. Traces of Crimean Tatar presence in the peninsula were wiped off the peninsula after the deportation in 1944, with thousands of villages previously bearing Tatar names being given new Russian names, officially [[Detatarization of Crimea|detatarizing the peninsula]]. The deported Crimean Tatars who worked in Central Asia lived under the "special settler" regime, which deprived them of many civil rights that other Soviet citizens enjoyed and confined them within a small perimeter.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xabnCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA114|title=The Crimean Tatars: From Soviet Genocide to Putin's Conquest|last=Williams|first=Brian Glyn|date=2015|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=9780190494704|pages=105–114|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; People involved in the Crimean Tatar civil rights movement repeatedly noted strong similarities between the conditions suffered by designated "special settlers" and victims of [[apartheid]] as well as [[Palestinians]] under Israeli occupation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Appazov|first=Refat|author-link=Refat Appazov|title=Следы в сердце и в памяти|publisher=Dolya|year=2001|location=Simferopol}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Ablyazov|first=Emir|date=8 December 2017|title=Четыре обыска Юрия Османова|url=http://goloskrimanew.ru/chetyire-obyiska-yuriya-osmanova.html|access-date=2020-12-03|website=goloskrimanew.ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?newbks=1&amp;newbks_redir=0&amp;id=ux4jAQAAIAAJ|title=The Ukrainian Quarterly|date=2004|publisher=Ukrainian Congress Committee of America.|pages=54|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== In modern times ===
While still very prevalent in modern society, Tatarophobia generates more controversy and pushback in modern times than it did in the past. While no longer officially a state-mandated institution, it remains pervasive throughout government and society; a notable example being when Russian consul Vladimir Andreev demanded that none of the invited Russian citizens attend the debut of ''[[Haytarma]]'', a film about Crimean Tatar twice Hero of the Soviet Union [[Amet-khan Sultan]], because it did not depict the Crimean Tatar population in a sufficiently negative light. Andreev admitted that he did not actually see the movie when he told people not to attend, but said that he felt it would be historically inaccurate because it was directed by a Crimean Tatar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://scholarcommons.usf.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=https://www.google.com/&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=1273&amp;context=gsp|journal=Genocide Studies and Prevention|title=Genocide's Aftermath: Neostalinism in Contemporary Crimea|date=2015|volume=9|last=Uehling|first=Greta}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Izmirli|first=Idil|date=16 June 2013|title=Russian consul general to Crimea resigns following offensive comments|url=http://ukrweekly.com/archive/2013/The_Ukrainian_Weekly_2013-24.pdf|journal=The Ukrainian Weekly|pages=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Confusion about different Tatar peoples has been taken advantage of by propaganda, which will celebrate the relative equality experienced by Volga Tatar in order to lead uneducated recipients of propaganda to confuse them with Crimean Tatars and be led to believe that interethnic relations are overwhelmingly positive. It is not unusual for Volga Tatars to be praised and lauded as brotherly peoples by the same institutions that simultaneously engage in Tatarophobia against Crimean Tatars, and it is not unusual for the relative lack of hostility towards Volga Tatars to be pointed out as an excuse to avoid correcting xenophobia towards Crimean Tatars. Despite the Crimean Tatar language being very distant from the Kazan Tatar language, the Soviet Union long opposed the request by the Crimean Tatar civil rights movement for their autonomy to be restored in Crimea, and offered to create an autonomous region in Tatarstan for them instead - insulting much of the Crimean Tatar leadership.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=epkQDAAAQBAJ|title=Татары Перми: история и культура|last=Chernykh|first=Aleksandr|publisher=Санкт-Петербург Mametov|year=2015|isbn=9785040071074|location=Saint Petersburg|pages=65|language=ru|oclc=978278427}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.litsovet.ru/index.php/material.read?material_id=499487|title=Национального Движения Крымских Татар (Попытка краткого анализа участника движения)|last=Eminov|first=Ruslan|date=27 January 2016|website=litsovet.ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=S8YakB12QEUC&amp;pg=PA92|title=The Crimean Tatars: The Diaspora Experience and the Forging of a Nation|last=Williams|first=Brian Glyn|date=2001|publisher=BRILL|isbn=9789004121225|pages=92|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Against Volga Tatars ==
Historically the [[Volga Tatars]] have been lauded as a "[[model minority]]" in [[Russia]] and the [[Soviet Union]] and treated much better than the Crimean Tatars. Nevertheless, prejudices against Volga Tatars exists and there have been some attempts to de-Tatarize Tatarstan by Russian nationalists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Halim|first=Aydar|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wywwAAAAMAAJ|title=Убить империю!: Кипарис домой вернулся, или, "Хотят ли русские войны"|publisher=Kalkan|year=1997|isbn=978-5-87898-118-7|location=Kazan|pages=319|language=ru|oclc=605977944}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xW5SXUxZnckC&amp;pg=PA373|title=USAK Yearbook of International Politics and Law 2010, Vol. 3|publisher=USAK Books|isbn=9786054030262|pages=373|language=en|oclc=1030115376}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, a young Tatar man was stabbed to death by a group of people on his way to work in [[Saint Petersburg|St. Petersburg]]. The Tatar community stated that the murder was racially motivated and a consequence of [[Islamophobia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=13 July 2007|title=Tatars Say St. Petersburg Murder Was Racist Attack|url=https://www.rferl.org/a/1077606.html|access-date=2020-11-01|website=[[RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty]]|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; After [[Elmira Abdrazakova]] was crowned [[Miss Russia]] in 2013, she was bombarded with racial slurs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rferl.org/a/tatar-miss-russia-ethnic-slurs/24919923.html|title=Ethnic Tatar Miss Russia Winner Targeted By Ethnic Slurs On Internet|last=Kurmasheva|first=Alsu|date=5 May 2013|website=rferl.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Deportation of the Crimean Tatars]]
* [[Racism in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Racism in Russia]]
* [[Turkophobia]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Anti-cultural sentiment}}

[[Category:Tatarophobia| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>