<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241113024239|1257071907" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="285200" pageid="285200" ns="0" title="ACT UP"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-24T09:57:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|International AIDS activism, direct action and advocacy group}}
{{for|the City Girls song|Act Up (song)}}
{{use mdy dates|date=July 2024}}

{{Infobox organization
| name                = AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power
| image               = ACT UP logo.png
| image_border        =
| size                = &lt;!-- default 200px --&gt;
| alt                 = Logo
| caption             =
| abbreviation        = ACT UP
| formation           = {{start date and age|1987|03|12}}
| type                = &lt;!-- [[Governmental organization|GO]], [[Non-governmental organization|NGO]], [[Intergovernmental organization|IGO]], [[International nongovernmental organization|INGO]], etc --&gt;
| purpose             = [[HIV/AIDS]]
| membership          =
| key_people          = [[Larry Kramer]]
| affiliations        = [[ActUp/RI]]
| num_volunteers      =
| website             = {{URL|https://actupny.com}}
}}'''AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power''' ('''ACT UP''') is an international, [[grassroots]] political group working to end the [[AIDS pandemic]]. The group works to improve the lives of [[people with AIDS]] through [[direct action]], medical research, treatment and advocacy, and working to change legislation and public policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.actupny.org/|title=ACT UP new york|work=actupny.org|access-date=19 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="crimp1"&gt;{{cite book |last=Crimp |first=Douglas |title=AIDS Demographics |publisher=Bay Press |year=1990}} (Comprehensive early history of ACT UP, discussion of the various signs and symbols used by ACT UP).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia
 | last =Blotcher
 | first =Jay
 | editor-last=Gerstner
 | editor-first=David A.
 | title =ACT UP
 | encyclopedia = Routledge International Encyclopedia of Queer Culture
 | edition= 1st
 | pages =3–7
 | publisher =[[Routledge]]
 | language =English
 | date =2006
 | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=XS_SnVPixE8C
 | isbn = 9780415306515
 | accessdate = 2022-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ACT UP was formed on March 12, 1987, at the [[Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Community Services Center|Lesbian and Gay Community Services Center]] in [[New York City]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last=Zafir|first=Lindsay|title=Act Up|date=2019|encyclopedia=Global Encyclopedia of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer (LGBTQ) History|volume=1|pages=1–8|editor-last=Chiang|editor-first=Howard|place=Farmington Hills, MI|publisher=Charles Scribner's Sons|language=English|editor2-last=Arondekar|editor2-first=Anjali|editor3-last=Epprecht|editor3-first=Marc|editor4-last=Evans|editor4-first=Jennifer}}&lt;/ref&gt; Co-founder [[Larry Kramer]] was asked to speak as part of a rotating speaker series, and his well-attended speech focused on action to fight AIDS. Kramer spoke out against the state of the [[Gay Men's Health Crisis]] (GMHC), which he perceived as politically impotent.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Leland|first=John|date=2017-05-19|title=Twilight of a Difficult Man: Larry Kramer and the Birth of AIDS Activism (Published 2017)|language=en-US|work=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/05/19/nyregion/larry-kramer-and-the-birth-of-aids-activism.html|access-date=2021-01-16|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kramer had co-founded the GMHC but had resigned from its board of directors in 1983. According to [[Douglas Crimp]], Kramer posed a question to the audience: "Do we want to start a new organization devoted to political action?" The answer was "a resounding yes." Approximately 300 people met two days later to form ACT UP.&lt;ref name="crimp1"/&gt;

At the [[Second National March on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights]], in October 1987, ACT UP New York made their debut on the national stage, as an active and visible presence in both the march, the main rally, and at the [[civil disobedience]] at the [[United States Supreme Court Building]] the following day.&lt;ref name="crimp1"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Stein&gt;{{cite web |last=Stein |first=Marc |url=http://outhistory.org/exhibits/show/march-on-washington/exhibit/by-marc-stein |title=Memories of the 1987 March on Washington |website=OutHistory.org |date=August 2013 |access-date=October 11, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Inspired by this new approach to radical, direct action, other participants in these events returned home to multiple cities and formed local ACT UP chapters in Boston, Chicago, Los Angeles, Rhode Island, San Francisco, Washington, D.C., and other locations.&lt;ref name="crimp1"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Stein/&gt;&lt;ref name=Northeastern/&gt; ACT UP spread internationally. In many countries separate movements arose based on the American model. For example, the famous gay rights activist [[Rosa von Praunheim]] co-founded ACT UP in Germany.

==ACT UP New York actions==
[[File:A pink triangle against a black backdrop with the words 'Silence=Death' representing an advertisement for The Silence = Death Project used by permission by ACT-UP, The AIDS Coalition To Unleash Power. Wellcome L0052822.jpg|thumb|"[[Silence=Death Project|Silence=Death]]" poster]]
Much of the documentation chronicling ACT UP's history is drawn from Douglas Crimp's history of ACT UP, the ACT UP Oral History Project,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.actuporalhistory.org/ |title=ACT UP Oral History Project}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the online Capsule History of ACT UP, New York.&lt;ref name="ACTUPNY"&gt;{{cite web |website=ACT UP New York |title=Capsule History |url=http://www.actupny.org/documents/capsule-home.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wall Street===
On March 24, 1987, 250 ACT UP members demonstrated at [[Wall Street]] and Broadway to demand greater access to experimental AIDS drugs and for a coordinated national policy to fight the disease.&lt;ref name="ACTUPNY1"&gt;ACT UP New York: First Demonstration Flyer, [http://www.actupny.org/documents/1stFlyer.html Actupny.org]&lt;/ref&gt;  An op-ed article by Larry Kramer published in ''[[The New York Times]]'' the previous day described some of the issues ACT UP was concerned with.&lt;ref name="kramer1"&gt;Kramer, Larry. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. February 16, 2005. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  December 11, 2005, [http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/kramer.pdf Actuporalhistory.org] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170517152516/http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/kramer.pdf |date=2017-05-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Seventeen ACT UP members were arrested during this [[civil disobedience]].&lt;ref name="ACTUPNY2"&gt;ACT UP New York: Capsule History - 1987, [http://www.actupny.org/documents/cron-87.html Actupny.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 24, 1988, ACT UP returned to Wall Street for a larger demonstration in which over 100 people were arrested.&lt;ref name="ACTUPNY3"&gt;ACT UP New York: Capsule History - 1988, [http://www.actupny.org/documents/cron-88.html Actupny.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 14, 1989, seven ACT UP members infiltrated the [[New York Stock Exchange]] and chained themselves to the VIP balcony to protest the high price of the only approved AIDS drug, [[Zidovudine|AZT]]. The group displayed a banner that read, "SELL WELLCOME" referring to the pharmaceutical sponsor of AZT, [[Burroughs Wellcome]], which had set a price of approximately $10,000 per patient per year for the drug, well out of reach of nearly all [[HIV]] positive persons. Several days following this demonstration, Burroughs Wellcome lowered the price of AZT to $6,400 per patient per year.&lt;ref name="ACTUPNY4"&gt;ACT UP New York: Capsule History - 1989, [http://www.actupny.org/documents/cron-89.html Actupny.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

===General Post Office===
ACT UP held their next action at the New York City General Post Office on the night of April 15, 1987, to an audience of people filing last minute tax returns. This event also marked the beginning of the conflation of ACT UP with the [[Silence=Death Project]], which created a poster consisting of a right side up [[pink triangle]] (an upside-down pink triangle was used to mark gays in [[Nazi concentration camps]]) on a black background with the text "SILENCE = DEATH." Douglas Crimp said this demonstration showed the "media savvy" of ACT UP because the [[broadcasting|television media]] "routinely do stories about down-to-the-wire tax return filers." As such, ACT UP was virtually guaranteed media coverage.&lt;ref name="crimp1"/&gt;

===''Cosmopolitan'' magazine===
In January 1988, ''[[Cosmopolitan (magazine)|Cosmopolitan]]'' magazine published an article by [[Robert E. Gould]], a psychiatrist, entitled "Reassuring News About AIDS: A Doctor Tells Why You May Not Be At Risk."&lt;ref name="crimp1"/&gt; The main contention of the article was that in unprotected vaginal sex between a man and a woman who both had "healthy genitals" the risk of HIV transmission was negligible, even if the male partner was infected. Women from ACT UP who had been having informal "dyke dinners" met with Gould in person, questioning him about several misleading facts (that penis to vagina transmission is impossible, for example) and questionable journalistic methods (no [[peer review]], bibliographic information, failing to disclose that he was a psychiatrist and not a practitioner of [[internal medicine]]), and demanded a retraction and apology.&lt;ref name="maggenti1"&gt;Maggenti, Maria. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. February 16, 2005. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  December 11, 2005, [http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/maggenti.pdf Actupralhistory.org] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210423235136/http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/maggenti.pdf |date=2021-04-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When he refused, in the words of Maria Maggenti, they decided that they "had to shut down Cosmo." According to those who were involved in organizing the action, it was significant in that it was the first time the women in ACT UP organized separately from the main body of the group.&lt;ref name="carlomusto1"&gt;Carlomusto, Jean. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. February 16, 2005. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  December 11, 2005, [http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/carlomusto.pdf Actuporalhistory.org] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210423213335/http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/carlomusto.pdf |date=2021-04-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, filming the action itself, the preparation and the aftermath were all consciously planned and resulted in a video short directed by [[Jean Carlomusto]] and [[Maria Maggenti]], titled, "Doctor, Liars, and Women: AIDS Activists Say No To Cosmo." The action consisted of approximately 150 activists protesting in front of the [[Hearst Tower (Manhattan)|Hearst Building]] (parent company of ''Cosmopolitan'') chanting "Say no to Cosmo!" and holding signs with slogans such as "Yes, the Cosmo Girl CAN get AIDS!"&lt;ref name="crimp1"/&gt; Although the action did not result in any arrests, it brought significant television media attention to the controversy surrounding the article. [[Phil Donahue]], ''Nightline'', and a local talk show called "People Are Talking" all hosted discussions of the article. On the latter, two women, Chris Norwood and Denise Ribble took the stage after the host, [[Richard Bey]], cut Norwood off during an exchange about whether heterosexual women are at risk from AIDS.&lt;ref&gt;Treichler, Paula. ''How To Have Theory In An Epidemic''. Duke University Press, 1999. (Discussion of the Cosmopolitan controversy and media representation)&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Women and the CDC's AIDS Definition===
Following their participation in the Cosmopolitan protest, ACT UP's Women's Caucus targeted the Center for Disease Control for its narrow definition of what constituted HIV/AIDS. While causes of HIV transmission, like unprotected vaginal or anal sex, were similar among both men and women, the symptoms of the virus varied greatly. As historian Jennifer Brier noted, "for men, full-blown AIDS often caused [[Kaposi's sarcoma]], while women experienced bacterial pneumonia, pelvic inflammatory disease, and cervical cancer." Since the CDC's definition did not account for such symptoms as a result of AIDS, American women in the 1980s were often diagnosed with AIDS Related Complex (or ARC) or HIV. "In this process," Brier explained, "these women effectively were denied the Social Security benefits that men with AIDS had fought hard to secure, and won, in the late 1980s."&lt;ref&gt;Brier 2009, p. 173.&lt;/ref&gt;
In October 1990, attorney Theresa McGovern filed suit representing 19 New Yorkers who claimed they were unfairly denied disability benefits because of the CDC's narrow definition of AIDS. At an October 2, 1990, protest to raise attention for McGovern's lawsuit, two hundred ACT UP protesters gathered in Washington and chanted "How many more have to die before you say they qualify," and carried posters to the rally with the tagline "Women Don't Get AIDS/ They Just Die From It."&lt;ref name = brier174&gt;Brier 2009, p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt;
The CDC's initial reaction to calls of the revising the AIDS definition included setting the threshold of AIDS for both men and women at a T cell count of under 200. However, McGovern dismissed this suggestion. "Lots of women who show up at hospitals don't get T cells taken. No one knows they have HIV. I knew how many of our clients were dying of AIDS and not counted."  Rather, McGovern, along with the ACLU and the New Jersey Women and AIDS Network, called for adding fifteen conditions to the list of the CDC's surveillance case definition, which was eventually adopted in January 1993. Six months later, the Clinton administration revised federal criteria for evaluating HIV status and making it easier for women with AIDS to secure Social Security benefits.&lt;ref&gt;Laurence 1997, p. 148-149&lt;/ref&gt; The Women's Caucus's role in altering the CDC's definition helped to not only drastically increase availability of federal benefits to American women, but helped uncover a more accurate number of HIV/AIDS infected women in the United States; "under the new model, the number of women with AIDS in the United States increased almost 50 percent."&lt;ref name = brier174/&gt;

Members of the ACT UP Women's Caucus collectively authored a handbook for two teach-ins held prior to the 1989 CDC demonstration, where ACT UP members learned about issues motivating the action. The handbook, edited by [[Maria Maggenti]], formed the basis for the ACT UP/New York Women and AIDS Book Group's book titled Women, AIDS and Activism, edited by Cynthia Chris and Monica Pearl, and assembled by Marion Banzhaf, Kim Christensen, Alexis Danzig, Risa Denenberg, [[Zoe Leonard]], Deb Levine, Rachel (Sam) Lurie, [[Catherine Gund|Catherine Saalfield (Gund)]], Polly Thistlethwaite, Judith Walker, and Brigitte Weil.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The ACT UP women's caucus: women and AIDS handbook|last1=Rosenblum|first1=Illith|last2=Maggenti|first2=Maria|last3=ACT UP (Organization)|date=1989|publisher=AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power|location=New York, N.Y.|language=en|oclc = 23144032}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book was published in Spanish in 1993 titled La Mujer, el SIDA, y el Activismo.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=La mujer, el SIDA y el activismo|last1=Banzhaf|first1=Marion|last2=ACT UP (Organization)|last3=New York Women and AIDS Book Group|date=1993|publisher=South End Press|isbn=0896084558|location=Boston, Mass.|language=es|oclc = 32616186}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the original Women and AIDS Handbook Group included Amy (Jamie) Bauer, Heidi Dorow, Ellen Neipris, [[Ann Northrop]], Sydney Pokorney, Karen Ramspacher, [[Maxine Wolfe]], and Brian Zabcik.{{citation needed|date=September 2022}}

===FDA===
On October 11, 1988, ACT UP had one of its most successful demonstrations (both in terms of size and in terms of national media coverage) when it successfully shut down the Food &amp; Drug Administration (FDA) for a day.&lt;ref name="LAFDA"&gt;{{cite news | title = Police Arrest AIDS Protesters Blocking Access to FDA Offices | work = [[Los Angeles Times]] | date = 11 October 1988  | url = https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1988-10-11-mn-3909-story.html | access-date = 2012-12-07  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="AtlanticFDA"&gt;{{cite news | last = Crimp | first = Douglas | title = Before Occupy: How AIDS Activists Seized Control of the FDA in 1988 | publisher = [[The Atlantic]]| date = 6 December 2011  | url = https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2011/12/before-occupy-how-aids-activists-seized-control-of-the-fda-in-1988/249302/ | access-date = 2012-12-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Media reported that it was the largest such demonstration since demonstrations against the Vietnam War.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

{{blockquote|The AIDS activists shut down the large facility by blocking doors, walkways and a road as FDA workers reported to work. Police told some workers to go home rather than wade through the throng.

"Hey, hey, FDA, how many people have you killed today?" chanted the crowd, estimated by protest organizers at between 1,100 and 1,500. The protesters hoisted a black banner that read "Federal Death Administration."

Police officers, wearing surgical gloves and helmets, started rounding up the hundreds of demonstrators and herding them into buses shortly after 8:30 a.m. Some protesters blocked the buses from leaving for 20 minutes.

Authorities arrested at least 120 protesters, and demonstration leaders said they were aiming for 300 arrests by day's end.&lt;ref name="LAFDA"/&gt;}}

Among the protestors was artist [[David Wojnarowicz]], then HIV/AIDS positive, wearing painted jean jacket that read: "If I die of AIDS—forget burial—just drop my body on the steps of the F.D.A."— a nascent meme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = The Jacket | work = [[Pioneer Works]] | date = 11 November 2020  | url = https://pioneerworks.org/broadcast/the-jacket-david-wojnarowicz-lauren-oneill-butler/ | access-date = 2020-11-11  }}&lt;/ref&gt; At this action, and via their campaigning in general, activists demonstrated their thorough knowledge of the FDA drug approval process.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=3CR |last2=Hammond |first2=Holly |last3=Schulman |first3=Sarah |date=2023-03-08 |title=Lessons from Campaigning for AIDs Activism with Sarah Schulman |url=https://commonslibrary.org/commons-conversation-podcast-with-sarah-schulman-lessons-from-campaigning-for-aids-activism/ |access-date=2024-09-14 |website=The Commons Social Change Library |language=en-AU}}&lt;/ref&gt; ACT UP presented precise demands for changes that would make experimental drugs available more quickly, and more fairly. "The success of SEIZE CONTROL OF THE FDA can perhaps best be measured by what ensued in the year following the action. Government agencies dealing with AIDS, particularly the FDA and NIH, began to listen to us, to include us in decision-making, even to ask for our input."&lt;ref name="AtlanticFDA"/&gt;

==={{anchor|"Stop the Church"}}"Stop the Church"===
{{main|Stop the Church}}
{{See also|Anti-Catholicism in the United States}}
ACT UP disagreed with Cardinal [[John O'Connor (cardinal)|John Joseph O'Connor]] on the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of New York|Roman Catholic Archdiocese]]'s public stand against [[safe sex]] education in New York City Public Schools, [[condom]] distribution, the Cardinal's public condemnation of homosexuality, as well as the Church's opposition to [[abortion]]. This led to the first Stop the Church protest on December 10, 1989, at [[St. Patrick's Cathedral, New York]].&lt;ref name="ACTUPNY"/&gt;&lt;ref name=pose/&gt;&lt;ref name=crouch/&gt;{{sfn|Faderman|2015|p=434}}

Originally, the plan was just to be a "die-in" during the homily but it descended into "pandemonium."&lt;ref name=pose/&gt; A few dozen activists interrupted Mass, chanted slogans, blew whistles, "kept up a banchee screech," chained themselves to pews, threw condoms in the air, waved their fists, and lay down in the aisles to stage a "die-in."&lt;ref name=Wages/&gt;{{sfn|Faderman|2015|pp=433-435}}&lt;ref name=Hunter&gt;{{cite book |last=Hunter |first=James Davison |title=Culture Wars: The Struggle to Define America |publisher=Basic Books |date=1991 |page=153 |isbn=978-0975372500}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=pose/&gt;&lt;ref name=plague1&gt;{{cite podcast |url= https://www.americamagazine.org/faith/2019/12/01/surviving-aids-crisis-gay-catholic |title= Surviving the AIDS crisis as a gay Catholic |website= Plague: Untold Stories of AIDS &amp; the Catholic Church  |publisher=[[America (magazine)|America]] |host= Michael O'Loughlin |date= 1 December 2019|access-date= 10 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; While O'Connor went on with mass, activists stood up and announced why they were protesting.{{sfn|Faderman|2015|p=434}} One protester, "in a gesture large enough for all to see,"{{sfn|Faderman|2015|pp=434-435}} [[Host desecration|desecrated the Eucharist]] by spitting it out of his mouth, crumbling it into pieces, and dropping them to the floor.&lt;ref name=rude/&gt;&lt;ref name=keane/&gt;&lt;ref name="ACTUPNY"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wages/&gt;&lt;ref name=scalia/&gt;&lt;ref name=carroll/&gt;&lt;ref name=plague1/&gt;{{excessive citations inline|date=September 2022}}

One hundred and eleven protesters were arrested, including 43 inside the church.&lt;ref name=Sindelar&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/before-pussy-riot-act-up-confronted-church-and-won/24668230.html|title=Decades Before Pussy Riot, U.S. Group Protested Catholic Church -- And Got Results|author=Daisy Sindelar|date=2012-08-06|publisher=Radio Free Europe Radio Liberty}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some who refused to move had to be carried out of the church on stretchers.&lt;ref name=pose/&gt; The protests were widely condemned by public and church officials, members of the public, the mainstream media, and some in the gay community.&lt;ref name=carroll/&gt;

===Saint Vincent's Catholic Medical Center===

In the 1980s, as the gay population of Greenwich Village and New York began succumbing to the AIDS virus, [[Saint Vincent's Catholic Medical Center]] established the first AIDS Ward on the East Coast and second only to one in San Francisco, and soon became "Ground Zero" for the AIDS-afflicted in NYC.&lt;ref name=boynton&gt;[http://www.newyorker.com/culture/culture-desk/remembering-st-vincents Boynton, Andrew. "Remembering St. Vincent's," ''The New Yorker'', May 16, 2013]&lt;/ref&gt; The hospital "became synonymous" with care for AIDS patients in the 1980s, particularly poor gay men and drug users.&lt;ref name=plague2/&gt; It became one of the best hospitals in the state for AIDS care with a large research facility and dozens of doctors and nurses working on it.&lt;ref name=plague2/&gt;

ACT UP protested the hospital one night in the 1980s due to its Catholic nature.&lt;ref name=plague2/&gt; They took over the emergency room and covered crucifixes with condoms.&lt;ref name=plague2/&gt; Their intent was both to raise awareness and offend Catholics.&lt;ref name=plague2/&gt; Instead of pressing charges, the sisters who ran the hospital decided to meet with the protesters to better understand their concerns.&lt;ref name=plague2&gt;{{cite podcast |url=https://www.americamagazine.org/faith/2019/12/08/how-catholic-hospital-eventually-became-safe-haven-gay-community |title= The Catholic hospital that pioneered AIDS care |website= Plague: Untold Stories of AIDS &amp; the Catholic Church  |publisher=[[America (magazine)|America]] |host= Michael O'Loughlin |date=December 8, 2019 |access-date= January 10, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Storm the NIH===
[[File:Demonstrators at the "Storm the NIH" Event (14358485404).jpg|thumb|Demonstrators at the "Storm the NIH" Event]]
On May 21, 1990, around 1000 ACT UP members initiated a choreographed demonstration at the [[National Institutes of Health]] (NIH) in [[Bethesda, Maryland]], splitting into sub-groups across the campus. The protest was in part directed at [[National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Disease]] and its director, [[Anthony Fauci]]. Activists were angered by what they felt was slow progress on promised research and treatment efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Anderson |first1=Andrea |title=Demonstrating Discontent, May 21, 1990 |newspaper=The Scientist Magazine |url=https://www.the-scientist.com/foundations/demonstrating-discontent-may-21-1990-31227 |publisher=The Scientist |access-date=20 June 2020 |date=16 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Kramer, this was their best demonstration, but was almost completely ignored by the media because of a large fire in Washington, D.C., on the same day.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

===Day of Desperation===
On January 22, 1991, during [[Operation Desert Storm]], ACT UP activist John Weir and two other activists entered the studio of the [[CBS Evening News]] at the beginning of the broadcast. They shouted "AIDS is news. Fight AIDS, not Arabs!" and Weir stepped in front of the camera before the control room cut to a commercial break. The same night ACT UP demonstrated at the studios of the [[MacNeil/Lehrer Newshour]]. The next day activists displayed banners in [[Grand Central Terminal]] that said "Money for AIDS, not for war" and "One AIDS death every 8 minutes."  One of the banners was handheld and displayed across the train timetable and the other attached to bundles of balloons that lifted it up to the ceiling of the station's enormous main room. These actions were part of a coordinated protest called "Day of Desperation."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.actupny.org/diva/synDesperation.html Day of Desperation Synopsis]. ACT UP New York.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Seattle schools===
In December 1991, ACT UP's Seattle chapter distributed over 500 safer-sex packets outside Seattle high schools.  The packets contained a pamphlet titled "How to Fuck Safely," which was photographically illustrated and included two men performing fellatio.  The Washington state legislature subsequently passed a "Harmful to Minors" law making it illegal to distribute sexually explicit material to underage persons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Graphic Anti-Aids Pamphlet Disgusting, Say Teens -- 'We Don't Need A Four-Letter Word To Get The Point Across' At Franklin|url=https://archive.seattletimes.com/archive/19911203/1320783/graphic-anti-aids-pamphlet-disgusting-say-teens----we-dont-need-a-four-letter-word-to-get-the-point-across-at-franklin|access-date=27 March 2012 | work=The Seattle Times|first=Paula|last=Bock|date=December 3, 1991}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Macy's Herald Square===
On November 29, 1991, the Black Friday shopping day, ACT UP activists dressed in Santa Claus costumes chained themselves inside Macy's flagship Herald Square department store to protest the store's decision not to rehire an HIV-positive Santa, Mark Woodley. They sang protest Christmas songs with lyrics such as, ''"Santa Claus has HIV, fa-la-la-la-la-la-la-la-la/Macy's won't rehire he, fa-la-la-la-la-la-la-la-la."'' Nineteen activists were arrested at the action.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/90338647/no-miracle-on-34th-st-for/|title=No miracle on 34th St. for AIDS-infected man|date=November 30, 1991|agency=Associated Press|work=Danville News (Danville, PA)|access-date=December 10, 2021|page=1|via=Newspapers.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode |title=The day Santas stormed Macy's to protest for AIDS awareness|series=Morning Edition|date=December 10, 2021|url=https://www.npr.org/2021/12/10/1062598719/santas-macys-aids-awareness-protest|network=NPR}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Boston and New England==
"In January 1988, [ACT UP/Boston] held its first protest at the Boston offices of the Department of Health and Human Services, regarding delays and red tape surrounding approval of AIDS treatment drugs. ACT UP/Boston's agenda included demands for a compassionate and comprehensive national policy on AIDS; a national emergency AIDS project; intensified drug testing, research, and treatment efforts; and a full-scale national educational program within reach of all. The organization held die-ins and sleep-ins, provided freshman orientation for Harvard Medical School students, negotiated successfully with a major pharmaceutical corporation, affected state and national AIDS policies, pressured health care insurers to provide coverage for people with AIDS, influenced the thinking of some of the nation's most influential researchers, served on the Massachusetts committee that created the nation's first online registry of clinical trials for AIDS treatments, distributed information and condoms to the congregation at Cardinal [[Bernard Francis Law]]'s Confirmation Sunday services at [[Cathedral of the Holy Cross (Boston)|Holy Cross Cathedral in Boston]], and made aerosolized [[pentamidine]] an accessible treatment in New England."&lt;ref name=Northeastern&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hdl.handle.net/2047/D20297047 |title=ACT UP/Boston Historical Records |publisher=Northeastern University Libraries Archives |date=January 2008 |hdl=2047/D20297047 |access-date=2018-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 1988 ACT UP Boston, in collaboration with ACT UP New York, Mass ACT OUT, and Cure Aids Now demonstrated at both the [[1988 Democratic Party presidential primaries|Democratic]] and [[1988 Republican Party presidential primaries|Republican]] presidential debates and primaries in [[New Hampshire]], and at other events during the [[1988 United States presidential election|presidential race]].&lt;ref name=Northeastern2&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hdl.handle.net/2047/D20297047 |title=ACT UP / Boston (Raymond Schmidt and Stephen Skuce) collection |publisher=Northeastern University Libraries Archives |date=1987–2007 |hdl=2047/D20297047 |access-date=2021-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During an ordination of priests in Boston in 1990, ACT UP and the Massachusetts Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights chanted and protested outside during the service.&lt;ref name=law/&gt;&lt;ref name=pilot/&gt;&lt;ref name=crimson/&gt;  The protesters marched, chanted, blew whistles, and sounded airhorns to disrupt the ceremony.&lt;ref name=law/&gt;  They also threw condoms at people as they left the ordination and were forced to stay back behind police and police barricades.&lt;ref name=law/&gt;  One man was arrested.&lt;ref name=assails/&gt;  The demonstration was condemned by [[Leonard P. Zakim]], among others.&lt;ref name=assails/&gt;

== Los Angeles ==

ACT UP Los Angeles (ACT UP/LA) was founded December 4, 1987, and continued holding demonstrations until the early 2000s. During their run they tackled healthcare access, political issues related to LGBTQ civil rights, and supported national ACT UP campaigns.&lt;ref name="Roth-B"&gt;Benita, Roth. The Life and Death of ACT UP/LA: Anti-Aids Activism in Los Angeles from the 1989s to the 2000s. New York, Cambridge University Press,  2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of their more local work focused on policy regarding the migration of HIV-positive people into the U.S., pushing for AIDS clinical trials,  promoting needle exchange programs for intravenous drug users, and surveying speaking out against discrimination by health care and insurance providers.&lt;ref&gt;Erik Meers. “In your Face: On its tenth anniversary of Act UP shows signs of becoming a victim of its own success. “ The Advocate, 18, March 1997, 41.&lt;/ref&gt; They were effective in distributing their research on Antiviral Therapy (AZT), local and international actions, and updates on the different caucuses through their ACT UP/LA newsletter. The newsletter also served as both an educational outreach and fundraising tool.{{citation needed|date=September 2022}}

Memorable actions by ACT UP/LA are the protests and demonstrations in county-based locations such as the USC county hospital, Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors, and the Los Angeles County Department of Health Services.&lt;ref&gt;[http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/p15799coll4/id/5799 ACT UP/LA Archival images available at the ONE National Gay and Lesbian Archives at USC]&lt;/ref&gt; ACT UP/LA and about fifteen other organizations formed an "Alternative Budget Coalition," rented the Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors' meeting room, and held a mock hearing on the county's $10+ billion budget, saying it spent too little on fighting AIDS.&lt;ref name="Roth-49"&gt;Roth, 2017, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent activists in this period included [[Connie Norman]], one of the people who led ACT UP's push for a bill (AB101) to protect workers from being fired because of their sexuality, California governor [[Pete Wilson]]'s veto of which led to the [[AB101 Veto Riot]].&lt;ref name="Roth-65"&gt;Roth, 2017, p. 65&lt;/ref&gt; ACT UP/LA and its associated Women's Caucus put on a “Week of Outrage” in conjunction with the national organization, which consisted of demonstrations, a teach-in, safe-sex vending event.&lt;ref&gt;[https://ucla.on.worldcat.org/oclc/26785950 ACT UP Los Angeles news, housed at UCLA's Southern Regional Library Facility]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women's Caucus ACT UP/LA===
The Women's Caucus (WC) of ACT UP/LA served an important collaboration between men and women who were being affected by HIV and AIDS.&lt;ref name="oac.cdlib.org"&gt;[https://oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/c81g0pcv/ Finding Aid for the ACT UP/Los Angeles records, 1990-1992 located in the UCLA Library Special Collections]&lt;/ref&gt; WC within the ACT UP/LA organization was unique because in this chapter they had a significant amount of control over how they included women's issues into the organizations larger gay male actions. Men were present in the WC, but only as allies, which harvested a collaboration for effective actions, rallies, and any acts of resistance for the whole organization as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;Roth, Benita. “Feminist Boundaries in the Feminist-Friendly Organization: The Women's Caucus of ACT UP/LA.” Gender &amp; Society, vol. 12, no. 2, 1998, 129-145.&lt;/ref&gt; While the collaboration was not always perfect, at the end it created a stronger force against discrimination of HIV+ people in Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;[[Verta Taylor|Taylor, Verta]], [[Leila J. Rupp|Rupp, Leila J.]] “Women's Culture and Lesbian Feminist Activism.” Community Activism and Feminist Politics, edited by Nancy A. Naples, Routledge, 1988, 57-79.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the work that the WC did was distribute statistical information about women who are HIV+, the lack of appropriate screening and health care access, information about safer sex practices (in English and Spanish), as well as acts of action to push for better. Lauren Leary was an integral in the organization because her work revolved around gathering existing research about HIV and AIDS in women and men and current treatment options. An ACT UP national collective of women came together to create the “Women's Treatment and Research Agenda” in 1991.&lt;ref name="oac.cdlib.org"/&gt;

==Washington D.C.==

===Giant condom over Senator's home===
[[Peter Staley]] and other activists affiliated with ACT-UP wrapped the [[Arlington, Virginia]] home of Senator [[Jesse Helms]] in a 15-foot condom on September 5, 1991. The protest condemned the [[Helms AIDS Amendments]], which continued to block funding for education, as well as his ongoing opposition to [[People With AIDS]], including numerous homophobic falsehoods about HIV and AIDS. Helms had actively passed laws stigmatizing the disease, and his staunch attempts to block federal funding for, and education about, HIV and AIDS had significantly increased the death toll. Some of the harmful legislation he enacted is still in place.&lt;ref name="yt2"&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TS-w4Pqvkuw TAG Helms: when ACT UP put a Giant Condom over Sen. Jesse Helms's House - YouTube&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The condom was inflated and the message on it read: "A CONDOM TO PREVENT UNSAFE POLITICS. HELMS IS DEADLIER THAN A VIRUS." The event was captured live on the news.&lt;ref name="yt1"&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FuKlz8TGOic ACT-UP Unfurls Giant Condom Engulfing Jesse Helms' Home - YouTube&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first action of the affinity ACT group TAG (Treatment Action Guerillas).&lt;ref name="helms1"&gt;{{Cite web|date=2012-06-03|title=The Condom on Jesse Helms' House|url=https://actipedia.org/project/condom-jesse-helms-house|access-date=2020-08-03|website=Actipedia|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the police were called, no one was arrested, and the group was allowed to take the condom down, though they did receive a parking ticket.&lt;ref name="helms1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="yt2"/&gt; The event was dramatized, with fictionalized characters, in a 2019 episode of the FX television series ''[[Pose (TV series)|POSE]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.out.com/television/2019/7/31/poses-condom-over-house-scene-actually-happened-heres-how Pose's ‘Condom Over the House’ Scene Actually Happened — Here's How]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ashes Actions===
In October 1992 and October 1996, during displays of the [[NAMES Project AIDS Memorial Quilt]] and just before presidential elections, ACT UP activists held two Ashes Actions.&lt;ref name="Silverstein"/&gt; Inspired by a passage in [[David Wojnarowicz]]'s 1991 memoir ''Close to the Knives'', these actions scattered the ashes of people who had died of AIDS, including Wojnarowicz and activist Connie Norman, on the [[White House]] lawn, in protest of the federal government's inadequate response to AIDS.&lt;ref name="Silverstein"&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/why-the-ashes-of-aids-victims-on-the-white-house-lawn-matter | work=VICE News| title=Critic's Notebook: Why the Ashes of AIDS Victims on the White House Lawn Matter | date=August 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Canada==
=== Vancouver ===
Formed in 1989, ACT UP [[Vancouver]] began at a public meeting to determine how to respond to the government's inaction on the AIDS crisis,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Kozachenko |first=John |date=2016-10-14 |title=Kozachenko, 2014, p. 10, Interview AIDS Activist History Project |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.ca/interviews/vancouver-interviews/ |access-date=2023-01-27 |website=AIDS Activist History Project |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and focused their activism on the provincial political crises surrounding AIDS.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Kaleta |first=Janis |date=2016-10-14 |title=Kaleta, 2019, p. 4, Interview AIDS Activist History Project }}&lt;/ref&gt; The first ACT UP event took place in [[Robson Square]] as a public display of art in which three mummies wrapped in linen hung upside down to depict the inaction and neglect of the provincial government on those affected by AIDS.  They organized and participated in various protests, including the Les Misérables at the [[Queen Elizabeth Theatre|Queen Elizabeth Theater]].  They protested against the Premier of British Columbia [[Bill Vander Zalm]] who was in favor of enacting quarantine legislation (Bill 34). There was a diverse range of activist groups from the community who protested against Bill 34, there were many members from ACT UP,  support from the First Nations community, and politically left-leaning people.&lt;ref name="AAHP"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kozachenko |first1=John |title=Aids Activist History Project vancouver interview transcript 18 |url=https://www.aidsactivisthistory.ca/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/aahp-john-kozachenko.pdf |website=AIDS Activist History Project |access-date=31 January 2024}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite its impact, the organization eventually dissolved around 1991, following their State of the Province protest.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Kaleta |first=Janis |date=2016-10-14 |title=Kaleta, 2019, p. 12, Interview AIDS Activist History Project |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.ca/interviews/vancouver-interviews/ |access-date=2023-01-27 |website=AIDS Activist History Project |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; They stated their dissolution was not due to a lack of commitment from members, but rather a lack of expertise and negative press stemming from arrests, which led to other organizations distancing themselves from ACT UP.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Kaleta |first=Janis |date=2016-10-14 |title=Kaleta, 2019, p. 6, Interview AIDS Activist History Project |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.ca/interviews/vancouver-interviews/ |access-date=2023-01-27 |website=AIDS Activist History Project |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the arrested members, John Kozachenko, was accused of vehicle damage, though he asserted his innocence and the charges were later dropped.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Kozachenko |first=John |date=2016-10-14 |title=Vancouver Interviews |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.ca/interviews/vancouver-interviews/ |access-date=2023-01-27 |website=AIDS Activist History Project |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members felt the incident interfered with the groups's ability to initiate reforms in conservative [[Vancouver]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Brooke |first=Cynthia |date=2016-10-14 |title=Cynthia, 2019, p. 7, Interview AIDS Activist History Project |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.ca/interviews/vancouver-interviews/ |access-date=2023-01-27 |website=AIDS Activist History Project |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Montreal ===
The AIDS crisis in [[Montreal]] was very pronounced and is often underrepresented in discussion about the pandemic. ACT UP worked to end the AIDS pandemic and to combat the extreme homophobia that gay men faced as a result of stigma and stereotypes. ACT UP NYC protested the Fifth [[International AIDS Conference]] in 1989 and inspired the creation of ACT UP MTL. They also confronted Montreal prisons about their high rates of HIV, which they suggested were due to condoms not being available to prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2016-10-13|title=Montreal Interviews|url=https://aidsactivisthistory.ca/interviews/montreal-interviews/|access-date=2022-01-27|website=AIDS Activist History Project|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ACT UP MTL was formed in March 1990. Despite discouragement by the provincial government and Minister of Health, who felt that public information about [[HIV/AIDS|AIDS]] prevention would encourage [[homosexuality]] and drug use, ACT UP MTL was responsible for translating English [[AIDS prevention]] resources into French and creating their own informational flyers that were accessible to Quebec's [[Francophone Canadians|Francophone]] population. The chapter was also responsible for several demonstrations in a Montreal city park to raise awareness about those living with AIDS and those lost to [[HIV/AIDS]] complications. In 1994, the park was officially named [[:fr:Parc de l'Espoir|Le Parc de l’Espoir]] and an AIDS memorial monument was constructed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2016-10-13 |title=Montreal Interviews |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.ca/interviews/montreal-interviews/ |access-date=2023-08-18 |website=AIDS Activist History Project |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Halifax ===
The creation of ACT UP [[Halifax, Nova Scotia|Halifax]] is credited to Dan Hart, an activist and leader of the queer movement in Halifax in the 1980s who even hosted many of ACT UP's events in his own home.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Barnes |first=Brenda |date=November 29, 2017 |title=Interview Transcript 61: Brenda Barnes |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.files.wordpress.com/2020/04/aahp-brenda-barnes-final.pdf |website=AIDS Activist History Project}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web |last=Smith |first=Eric |date=July 24, 2014 |title=Interview Transcript 13: Eric Smith |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/aahp-eric-m-smith.pdf |website=AIDS Activist History Project}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite web |last=Metcalfe |first=Robin |date=July 10, 2014 |title=Interview Transcript: Robin Metcalfe |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/10/aahp-robin-metcalfe.pdf |website=AIDS Activist History Project}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite web |last=Allan |first=Robert |date=July 9, 2014 |title=Interview Transcript: Robert Allan |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/aahp_-_robert_allan.pdf |website=AIDS Activist History Project}}&lt;/ref&gt; While this branch of ACT UP is less known in comparison to the larger cities in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]], it has made some notable actions during its time. On [[World AIDS Day|December 1st]], 1990 a protest march was held on [[Barrington Street]]. What made this march different was the attendance of Pedro the Donkey, brought by the protestors to be used as a disruption method during the protest.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Chöga Martin |first=Sangyé |date=November 15, 2014 |title=Interview Transcript: Sangyé Chöga Martin |url=https://aidsactivisthistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/aahp_-_sangyecc81_chocc88ga_martin.pdf |website=AIDS Activist History Project}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pedro held true to his purpose and refused to move when protesters were asked to vacate the street. This allowed Halifax's ACT UP group to [[Nonviolent resistance|peacefully protest]] while staying within the confines of the law.

== England and Scotland ==

=== London ===
Formed in January 1989, by Rob Archer and Rae Trewartha, ACT UP [London] was the first ACT UP chapter in Europe.&lt;ref name="Capital Gay 367"&gt;Capital Gay no 376 page 1 &amp; 9 January 27th 1989&lt;/ref&gt;

Its first action was at Wellcome's annual shareholder meeting, the parent company of Burroughs Wellcome, the makers of [[Zidovudine|AZT]], the first treatment that targeted HIV directly.&lt;ref name="Capital Gay 367"/&gt;

This was quickly followed by a protest at Pentonville Prison, where condoms were floated over the walls.&lt;ref&gt;pink paper issue 59 page 3 weekending 11 February ’89 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tribune 10 February 1989 page 2&lt;/ref&gt;

The next action was to highlight employment discrimination. It was at Texaco's UK headquarters.  It was the first of a serious of protests against Texaco.&lt;ref&gt;Tribune 24 March 1989 page 2&lt;/ref&gt; They later targeted YHA employment discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;Capital Gay May 18th 1990&lt;/ref&gt;

The next action blocked traffic at Elephant and Castle, South London's busiest road junction. It called on the government to end the 6 month delay for social security benefits for newly diagnosed people living with AIDS, and to improve the rate. A follow up in October, saw the first arrests in the UK. Three people were arrested including Kenny Lieske from Edinburgh ACT UP.&lt;ref&gt;Pink Paper issue 95 21 October'89 page 1&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1990, members of ACT UP London chained themselves to the gates of Downing Street on budget day.

ACT UP London's last protest was a march in Kennington on World AIDS Day (1 December 1993). This was on cuts to social security benefits for disability benefits.

The group was revived by Dan Glass in 2014. The second incarnation came about to campaign for PreP to be made freely available on the NHS. Prep is a pill that if taken regularly prevents HIV infection and transmission.&lt;ref&gt;United Queerdom by Dan Glass&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Edinburgh ===
Formed in October 1989, by Kenny Lieske, Rob Archer and Tim Hopkins. Edinburgh had the highest number of HIV cases in Europe, most cases being among drug users.

Edinburgh ACT UP's first protest was on 1 December 1989, World AIDS Day  After a march along Princes Street ending in a rally where balloons were released. One black balloon was released for each person who had died in Scotland, and one white balloon for each person alive living with AIDS.

Edinburgh ACT UP's next action was actually in London, inside Wellcome's annual shareholders' meeting a year after ACT UP London's protest. It got extensive positive coverage in the Scottish print media (before&lt;ref&gt;The Scotsman 12 January 1990 page 7&lt;/ref&gt; and after&lt;ref&gt;The Scotsman 17 January 1990 page 3&lt;/ref&gt; the action) and likewise with the English quality newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;Capital Gay January 19th 1990 page 4&lt;/ref&gt;

Edinburgh ACT UP's most successful campaign was to change how the government funded AIDS in Scotland. The AIDS budget was poorly allocated often not spent on AIDS services at all. The campaign was to target the funding where it was most needed prioritising regions with the most people with HIV. Edinburgh ACT UP's biggest protest blocked traffic outside of the Scottish Office. It attracted MPs and received extensive media coverage. Within a few months the government had capitulated.&lt;ref&gt;https://livingmemory.org.uk/rememberWhen/activism/ Tim Hopkins on ACT-UP&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Leeds ===
It was one of the more active chapters in the UK. It successfully changed Leeds Hospital Fund pay out policy to include people with AIDS. Other ACT UPs include Manchester, Glasgow&lt;ref&gt;Edinburgh ACT UP News Issue 1 page 1&lt;/ref&gt; and Norwich.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/bbcthree/article/7b375363-45e9-4a60-927a-456a8f305948 ...ACT UP groups in cities including Manchester, Norwich and Edinburgh.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Structure of ACT UP==
[[File:Uganda Anti-Homosexuality Bill protest.jpg|thumb|right|ACT UP protests in [[New York City]] against [[Uganda]]'s [[The Anti-Homosexuality Act, 2014|Anti-Homosexuality Bill]]]]
ACT UP was organized as effectively leaderless; there was a formal committee structure. Bill Bahlman recalls there were initially two main committees.  There was the Issues Committee that scrupulously studied the issues surrounding an advancement the group wanted to achieve and the Actions Committee that would plan a Zap or Demonstration to achieve that particular goal. This was intentional on Larry Kramer's part: he describes it as "democratic to a fault."&lt;ref name="kramer1"/&gt; It followed a committee structure with each committee reporting to a coordinating committee meeting once a week. Actions and proposals were generally brought to the coordinating committee and then to the floor for a vote, but this was not required - any motion could be brought to a vote at any time.&lt;ref name="carlomusto1"/&gt; [[Gregg Bordowitz]], an early member, said of the process:

&lt;blockquote&gt;This is how grassroots, democratic politics work. To a certain extent, this is how democratic politics is supposed to work in general. You convince people of the validity of your ideas. You have to go out there and convince people.&lt;ref name="bordowitz1"&gt;Bordowitz, Gregg. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. February 16, 2005. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  December 11, 2005, [http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/bordowitz.pdf Actuporalhistory.org] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210423213332/http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/bordowitz.pdf |date=2021-04-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This is not to say that it was in practice purely anarchic or democratic. Bordowitz and others admit that certain people were able to communicate and defend their ideas more effectively than others. Although Larry Kramer is often labeled the first "leader" of ACT UP, as the group matured, those people that regularly attended meetings and made their voice heard became conduits through which smaller "affinity groups" would present and organize their ideas. Leadership changed hands frequently and suddenly.&lt;ref name="bordowitz1"/&gt;
* Some of the Committees were:{{citation needed|date=September 2022}}
** Issues Committee
** Action Committee
** Finance Committee
** Outreach Committee
** Treatment and Data Committee
** Media Committee
** Graphics Committee
** Housing Committee
Note: As ACT UP had no formal organizing plan, the titles of these committees are somewhat variable and some members remember them differently than others.

In addition to Committees, there were also Caucuses, bodies set up by members of particular communities to create space to pursue their needs. Among those active in the late 1980s and/or early 1990s were the Women's Caucus (sometimes referred to as the Women's Committee)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://herstories.prattinfoschool.nyc/omeka/exhibits/show/nomoreinvisiblewomenexhibition|title=No More Invisible Women Exhibition · Herstories: Audio/Visual Collections of the LHA|website=herstories.prattinfoschool.nyc|language=en-US|access-date=2017-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Latino/Latina Caucus.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://nacla.org/article/latinos-act-transnational-aids-activism-1990s|title=Latinos ACT UP: Transnational AIDS Activism in the 1990s|website=NACLA|language=en|access-date=2017-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with committees and caucuses, ACT UP New York relied heavily on "affinity groups."  These groups often had no formal structure, but were centered on specific advocacy issues and personal connections, often within larger committees.  Affinity groups supported overall solidarity in larger, more complex political actions through the mutual support provided to members of the group.  Affinity groups often organized to perform smaller actions within the scope of a larger political action, such as the "Day of Desperation," when the Needle Exchange group presented NY City Health Department officials with thousands of used syringes they had collected through their exchange (contained in water cooler bottles).{{citation needed|date=September 2022}}

=== Gran Fury ===
[[Gran Fury]] functioned as the anonymous art collective that produced all of the artistic media for ACT UP. The group remained anonymous because it allowed the collective to function as a cohesive unit without any one voice being singled out. The mission of the group was to bring an end to the AIDS Crisis by making reference to the issues plaguing society at large, especially homophobia and the lack of public investment in the AIDS epidemic, through bringing art works into the public sphere in order to reach the maximum audience. The group often faced censorship in their proceedings, including being rejected for public billboard space and being threatened with censorship in art exhibitions. When faced with this censorship, Gran Fury often posted their work illegally on the walls of the streets.&lt;ref&gt;Gober, Robert, Bob Gober, and Gran Fury. "Gran Fury." ''BOMB'', no. 34 (1991): 8–13.&lt;/ref&gt;

===DIVA-TV===
[[Diva TV (video collective)|DIVA-TV]], an acronym for "Damned Interfering Video Activist Television," was an affinity group within ACT UP that videotaped and documented [[AIDS]] activism. Its founding members are [[Catherine Gund]], [[Ray Navarro]], [[Ellen Spiro]], [[Gregg Bordowitz]], Robert Beck, Costa Pappas, [[Jean Carlomusto]], Rob Kurilla, George Plagianos.&lt;ref&gt;Alex Juhaz, "Diva TV and ACT UP," Encyclopedia of Social Movement Media, editor John D. H. Downing.&lt;/ref&gt; One of their early works is "Like a Prayer" (1991), documenting the 1989 ACT UP protests at [[St. Patrick's Cathedral, New York|St. Patrick's Cathedral]] against New York [[John O'Connor (cardinal)|Cardinal O'Connor]]'s position on AIDS and [[contraception]]. In the video, Ray Navarro, an ACT UP/DIVA TV activist,&lt;ref name="Leap Into the Void"&gt;A Day Without an Artist: Ray Navarro [http://imoralist.blogspot.com/2008/12/day-without-artist-ray-navarro.html Leap Into the Void]&lt;/ref&gt; serves as the narrator, dressed up as [[Jesus Christ|Jesus]]. The documentary aims to show mass media bias as it juxtaposes original protest footage with those images shown on the nightly news.

Although less as a "collective" after 1990, DIVA TV continued documenting (over 700 camera hours) the direct actions of ACT UP, activists, and the community responses to HIV/AIDS, producing over 160 video programs for public access television channels - as the weekly series "AIDS Community Television" from 1991 to 1996&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.actupny.org/divatv|title=DIVA TV (Damned Interfering Video Activists)|work=actupny.org|access-date=19 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and from 1994 to 96 the weekly call-in public access series "ACT UP Live"; film festival screenings; and continuing on-line documentation and streaming internet webcasts. The video activism of DIVA TV ultimately switched media in 1997 with the establishing and continuing development of the ACT UP (New York) website.   The most recent DIVA TV-genre video program documenting the history and activism of ACT UP (New York) is the feature-length documentary: "Fight Back, Fight AIDS: 15 Years of ACT UP" (2002), screened at the Berlin Film Festival and exhibited worldwide. DIVA TV programs and camera-original videotapes are currently re-mastered, archived and preserved, and publicly accessible in the collection of the "AIDS Video Activist Video Preservation Project" at the New York Public Library.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://digilib.nypl.org/dynaweb/ead/human/mssroyal/|title=AIDS Activist Videotape Collection, 1983-2000: Table of Contents|work=nypl.org|access-date=19 February 2017|archive-date=20 February 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170220011614/http://digilib.nypl.org/dynaweb/ead/human/mssroyal/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Institutional independence===
ACT UP had an early debate about whether to register the organization as a [[501(c)(3)]] nonprofit in order to allow contributors [[tax exemption]]s. Eventually they decided against it, because as Maria Maggenti said, "they didn't want to have anything to do with the government."&lt;ref name="maggenti1"/&gt; This kind of uncompromising ethos characterized the group in its early stages;{{editorializing|date=August 2021}} eventually it led to a split between those in the group who wanted to remain wholly independent and those who saw opportunities for compromise and progress by "going inside [the institutions and systems they were fighting against]."&lt;ref name="harrington1"&gt;Harrington, Mark. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. February 16, 2005. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  December 11, 2005, [http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/harrington.pdf Actuporalhistory.org] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210424012157/http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/harrington.pdf |date=2021-04-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later years==
[[File:Existrans 2017 (37599463410).jpg|thumb|Change of civil status, free and [[gay liberation|liberated]], ACTUP [[Paris]], [[trans march]], [[Paris]] 2017]]

ACT UP, while extremely prolific and certainly effective at its peak, suffered from extreme internal pressures over the direction of the group and of the AIDS crisis. After the action at NIH, these tensions resulted in an effective severing of the Action Committee and the Treatment and Data Committee, which reformed itself as the [[Treatment Action Group]] (TAG).&lt;ref name="harrington1"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wolfe, Maxine. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. February 16, 2005. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  December 11, 2005, [http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/wolfe.pdf Actuporalhistory.org] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210424080456/http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/wolfe.pdf |date=2021-04-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several members describe this as a "severing of the dual nature of ACT UP."

In 2000, ACT UP/Chicago was inducted into the [[Chicago Gay and Lesbian Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glhalloffame.org/index.pl?page=inductees&amp;todo=year |title=Chicago Gay and Lesbian Hall of Fame |access-date=2015-11-01 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151017032241/http://www.glhalloffame.org/index.pl?page=inductees&amp;todo=year |archive-date=2015-10-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

ACT UP chapters continue to meet and protest, albeit with a smaller membership.  ACT UP/NY and ACT UP/Philadelphia are particularly robust, with other chapters active elsewhere.  Activists from this group started giving out syringes illegally as [[Prevention Point Philadelphia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Gutman |first=Abraham |date=2018-10-05 |title='An argument that made no sense at all': Why Ed Rendell supported needle exchange during the AIDS epidemic and safe injection sites today {{!}} Perspective |url=https://www.inquirer.com/philly/opinion/commentary/opioids-safe-injection-sites-needle-exchange-ed-rendell-safehouse-20181005.html |access-date=2023-09-01 |website=The Philadelphia Inquirer |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Housing Works]], New York's largest AIDS service organization and Health GAP, which fights to expand treatment for people with AIDS throughout the world, are direct outgrowths of ACT UP.

==Factionalism in San Francisco==
In 2000, [[ACT UP/Golden Gate]] changed its name to Survive AIDS, to avoid confusion with ACT UP/San Francisco (ACT UP/SF). The two had previously split apart in 1990, but continued to share the same essential philosophy. In 1994, ACT UP/SF began [[AIDS denialism|rejecting the scientific consensus]] regarding the cause of AIDS and the connection to HIV, and the two groups became openly hostile to each other, with mainstream gay and AIDS organizations also condemning ACT UP/SF.&lt;ref name="Vicious"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sfweekly.com/content/printVersion/306128 |title=Men Behaving Viciously; How ACT UP San Francisco spreads spit, fake blood, used cat litter, and potentially deadly misinformation through the AIDS community |publisher=San Francisco Weekly |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090117015600/http://www.sfweekly.com/content/printVersion/306128 |archive-date=2009-01-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ACT UP/SF would link up with [[PETA|People For the Ethical Treatment of Animals (PETA)]] against animal research into AIDS cures.&lt;ref name="Vicious"/&gt; Restraining orders have been granted after ACT UP/SF members physically attacked AIDS charities that help HIV-positive patients,&lt;ref name="ChronOrder"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/chronicle/archive/2000/11/11/MN113803.DTL|title=S.F.'s ACT UP Ordered to Back Off|publisher=San Francisco Chronicle | first=Christopher | last=Heredia | date=September 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and activists associated with the chapter have been found guilty of misdemeanor charges laid after threatening phone calls to journalists and public health officials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://gay.com/news/article.html?2003/08/06/1 |title=Activists sentenced for misdemeanors |publisher=Gay.com |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050308204209/http://gay.com/news/article.html?2003%2F08%2F06%2F1 |archive-date=2005-03-08 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
'''Organizations'''
* [[ActUp/RI]]: the [[Rhode Island]] chapter
* [[Bash Back!]]: group of "radical queers" influenced by ACT UP
* [[Fed Up Queers]]: group founded through ACT UP
* [[Fierce Pussy]]: NYC lesbian feminist art collective involved with ACT UP promotion and AIDS awareness
* [[Gran Fury]]: AIDS activist artist collective associated with ACT UP
* [[Housing Works]]
* [[Lesbian Avengers]]
* [[Queer Nation]]: group founded after meetings between members of ACT UP NYC and MassActOut

'''People'''
* [[Chris Bartlett (activist)]]: member of ACT UP Philadelphia.
* [[J. Quinn Brisben]]
* [[Spencer Cox (activist)|Spencer Cox]]: member of ACT UP New York
* [[David B. Feinberg]]
* [[Avram Finkelstein]]: founding member of ACT UP New York and co-founder of [[Silence=Death Project]]
* [[Robert Garcia (AIDS activist)|Robert Garcia]]: member of ACT UP New York
* [[Gregg Gonsalves]]
* [[Keith Haring]]
* [[Marsha P. Johnson]]: [[Stonewall riots|Stonewall veteran]], participant in meetings and actions with ACT UP New York, Boston, MassActOut, and what would become the [[Michael Petrelis#ACT UP Presidential Project|ACT UP Presidential Project]] in New Hampshire
* [[Larry Kramer]]: playwright, founding member of [[Gay Men's Health Crisis]], early member of ACT UP New York
* [[Kiyoshi Kuromiya]]: member of ACT UP Philadelphia
* [[Didier Lestrade]]: ACT UP Paris co-founder
* [[Luke Montgomery]]: member of ACT UP Seattle
* [[Maria Maggenti]]: member of ACT UP New York, filmmaker and documentarian, director of ''[[The Incredibly True Adventure of Two Girls in Love]]'', participant in the ''ACT UP'' Oral History Project&lt;ref name="maggenti1"/&gt;
* [[Mary Patten]]: member of ACT UP Chicago
* [[Michael Petrelis]]: co-founding member of ACT UP New York, helped organize chapters in several cities nationwide, including the ACT UP Presidential Project; founding member of [[Queer Nation]]
* [[Hunter Reynolds]]: member of ACT UP New York, co-founded ART + Positive
* [[Thierry Schaffauser]]: [[sex worker]] activist and writer, former member of ACT UP Paris
* [[Sarah Schulman]]: member of ACT UP New York, director of the ''ACT UP Oral History Project''
* [[Peter Tatchell]]: helped found ACT UP London
* [[Shatzi Weisberger]]: member of ACT UP New York

'''Media and Research'''
* ''[[How to Survive a Plague]]'': documentary, 2012
* ''[[United in Anger: A History of ACT UP]]'': documentary, 2012
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170401233400/https://smalltownrage.com/ Small Town Rage: Fighting Back in the Deep South]: documentary, 2017
* [[BPM (Beats per Minute)]]'':'' film (about ACT UP Paris), 2017
* [https://www.theaidsactivistproject.org the AIDS activist project] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220921021837/https://theaidsactivistproject.org/ |date=2022-09-21 }}: documentary book, 2018
* ''[[Let the Record Show: A Political History of ACT UP New York, 1987-1993]]'', book by [[Sarah Schulman]], 2020
* ''[https://uncpress.org/book/9781469661339/to-make-the-wounded-whole/ To Make the Wounded Whole: The African American Struggle Against HIV/AIDS]'', book by Dan Royles with material on ACT UP Philadelphia, 2020
* Deborah B. Gould, ''Moving Politics. Emotion and Act Up's Fight Against AIDS''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Gould|first=Deborah B.|url=http://dx.doi.org/10.7208/chicago/9780226305318.001.0001|title=Moving Politics|date=2009|publisher=University of Chicago Press|doi=10.7208/chicago/9780226305318.001.0001|isbn=978-0-226-30530-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|35em|refs=

&lt;ref name=law&gt;{{cite news|title=Hundreds protest Cardinal Law at ordination |newspaper=The Boston Sunday Globe |page=25 |first=Irene |last=Sege |date=June 17, 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pilot&gt;{{cite news | url = https://www.thebostonpilot.com/articleprint.asp?id=177277 | title = Bishop Mark O'Connell: 'I plan on being a happy bishop' | date = 26 August 2016 | first = Doris | last = Tracy | newspaper = The Pilot | access-date = 12 March 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=crimson&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.thecrimson.com/article/1990/11/30/catholic-students-protest-tactics-of-gay/ | title = Catholic Students Protest Tactics of Gay Activists | first = Ivan | last = Oransky | date = 30 November 1990 | newspaper = The Harvard Crimson | access-date = 12 March 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=assails&gt;{{cite news|title=Pilot editorial assails protest |date=June 22, 1990 |newspaper=The Boston Globe |page=19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pose&gt;{{cite news | url = https://www.americamagazine.org/arts-culture/2019/06/21/pose-revisits-controversial-aids-protest-inside-st-patricks-cathedral | title = 'Pose' revisits controversial AIDS protest inside St. Patrick's Cathedral | first = Michael J. | last = O’Loughlin | date = June 21, 2019 | access-date = June 24, 2019 | publisher = America }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=crouch&gt;{{cite web|last = Crouch|first = Stanley|work = [[Salon.com|Salon]]|url = http://www.salon.com/news/col/crouch/2000/05/10/cardinal|url-status = dead|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20040918060031/http://dir.salon.com/news/col/crouch/2000/05/10/cardinal/index.html|archive-date = 2004-09-18|title = Mourning the loss of Cardinal O'Connor|date = 10 May 2000|access-date = 2006-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=rude&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1990/01/03/nyregion/rude-rash-effective-act-up-shifts-aids-policy.html |title=Rude, Rash, Effective, Act-Up Shifts AIDS Policy |first=Jason |last=DeParle |date=January 3, 1990 |newspaper=New York Times |page=B1 |access-date=August 7, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=keane&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/keane.pdf |title=ACTUP Oral History Project, Interviewee: Tom Keane, Interview Number: 176 |date=February 24, 2015 |access-date=August 3, 2018 |publisher=The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival, Inc |pages=20–21 |quote="I put my hands out, and suddenly I have the Communion wafer in my hands, and the priest says, “This is the body of Christ,” and I say, “Opposing safe-sex education is murder.” Then I sort of—I didn't really know what to do, and I think in some sense, some part of me was sort of saying, “Well, fine. You guys think you can tell us that you reject us, that we don't belong, so I'm going to reject you.” So I took it and I crushed it and dropped it." |archive-date=September 2, 2020 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200902214032/http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/keane.pdf |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=scalia&gt;{{cite web|title=The Priest, and the Pieces of Christ's Body He Protects |url=https://aleteia.org/2015/11/10/the-priest-and-the-pieces-of-christs-body-he-protects/ |first=Elizabeth |last=Scalia |date=November 10, 2015 |access-date=October 8, 2018 |publisher=Alteia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=carroll&gt;{{cite book|last=Carroll|first=Tamar W. |title=Mobilizing New York: AIDS, Antipoverty, and Feminist Activism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rzHtBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA158|date=April 20, 2015|publisher=University of North Carolina Press|isbn=978-1-4696-1989-7|pages=157–158}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Wages&gt;{{citation|last=Allen|first=Peter L. |title=The Wages of Sin: Sex and Disease, Past and Present|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lpL5WGCNMwAC|access-date=July 27, 2018|date=June 2002|publisher=University of Chicago Press|isbn=978-0-226-01461-6|page=143}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==Works cited==
* ACT UP/New York Women and AIDS Book Group (1990). "Women, AIDS, and Activism." South End Press.
* ACT UP/New York Women and AIDS Book Group (1993). "La Mujer, el SIDA, y el Activismo." South End Press.
* Brier, Jennifer (2009). "Infectious Ideas: U.S. Political Responses to the AIDS Crisis." University of North Carolina Press.
* Laurence, Leslie (1997). "Outrageous Practices: How Gender Bias Threatens Women's Health." Rutgers University Press.
* {{cite book | first = Lillian | last = Faderman | title = The Gay Revolution | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=eT8jBQAAQBAJ | year = 2015 | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster | isbn = 9781451694130 }}

==Further reading==
* [http://hdl.handle.net/2047/D20297079 ACT UP/Boston (David Stitt) collection, 1986-1994] and the [http://hdl.handle.net/2047/D20297047 ACT UP / Boston (Raymond Schmidt and Stephen Skuce) collection, 1987-2007 (bulk 1988-1995)] are housed at the Northeastern University Libraries, Archives and Special Collections Department, Boston, MA.
* [http://archives.nypl.org/mss/3622 AIDS Activist Videotape Collection, 1983-2000] (630 VHS tapes) is housed at the [[New York Public Library]] Manuscripts and Archives Division.
* [http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/EAD/htmldocs/RMM07574.html Robert Garcia Papers, 1988-1993] (9 cubic feet) are housed at the [[Cornell University Library]].
* [http://archives.nypl.org/mss/3376 Women's Action Coalition Records, 1991-1997] (8 linear feet) are housed at the [[New York Public Library]] Manuscripts and Archives Division.
* [http://www.nypl.org/sites/default/files/archivalcollections/pdf/actupny_0.pdf ACT UP New York records, 1969, 1982-1997], Manuscripts and Archives, New York Public Library.
* [http://www.nypl.org/archives/70436 Photographs and film regarding ACT UP New York and The Costas, 1987-1991, 2008], Manuscripts and Archives, New York Public Library.
* [http://digilib.nypl.org/dynaweb/ead/human/mssroyal/ AIDS Activist Videotape Collection at the New York Public Library] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170220011614/http://digilib.nypl.org/dynaweb/ead/human/mssroyal/ |date=2017-02-20 }}
* [http://www.actupny.org/video/index.html  Documentary "ACT UP, Fight Back, Fight AIDS: 15 Years of ACT UP" (2002)]
* [http://www.unitedinanger.com/  Documentary, "UNITED IN ANGER: A History of ACT UP" (2012), by Jim Hubbard &amp; Sarah Schulman]
* [http://www.outweek.net/ OutWeek Internet Archive]
* [http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/fales/bytsura/ Bill Bytsura ACT UP Photography Collection at The Fales Library &amp; Special Collections of NYU]
* [http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/fales/klein/index.html Alan Klein papers at The Fales Library &amp; Special Collections of NYU]
* [http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/fales/blotcher/index.html Jay Blotcher papers at The Fales Library &amp; Special Collections of NYU]
* "The Making of an AIDS Activist: Larry Kramer" and "ACT UP", pp.&amp;nbsp;162–166, Johansson, Warren and Percy, William A.  [https://web.archive.org/web/20060221073017/http://williamapercy.com/pub-Outing.htm ''Outing:  Shattering the Conspiracy of Silence.'']  New York and London: Haworth Press, 1994.
* "AIDS Assaults Courts Controversy with [[Andrew Cornell Robinson]]'s Obscene Ceramics", SOWEBO, ACT UP Exhibition, Baltimore, MD. 1991 Group Show &amp; ACT UP benefit courts controversy, Harry Newspaper, Baltimore, MD, July 1991, Vol 2, p.&amp;nbsp;1
* Curley, Mallory. ''A Cookie Mueller Encyclopedia'', Randy Press, 2010.
* Lowery, Jack. ''It Was Vulgar and It Was Beautiful: How AIDS Activists Used Art to Fight a Pandemic''. New York: Bold Type Books, 2022.

==External links==
* [http://www.actupny.org/ ACT UP New York]
* [[hdl:10079/fa/beinecke.kramer|Larry Kramer Papers]]. Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.

{{LGBTQ|state=collapsed|history=expanded}}
{{AIDS|state=collapsed}}
{{Larry Kramer}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:ACT UP}}
[[Category:HIV/AIDS activism]]
[[Category:Health and disability rights organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:LGBTQ political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:HIV/AIDS organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:LGBTQ organizations based in New York City]]
[[Category:LGBTQ history in San Francisco]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1987]]
[[Category:1987 establishments in New York City]]
[[Category:1987 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Critics of the Catholic Church]]
[[Category:Direct action]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>