<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061020170540|82653946" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="285200" pageid="285200" ns="0" title="ACT UP"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-21T20:41:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''ACT UP''', or the '''AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power''', "is a diverse, non-partisan group of individuals ... committed to [[direct action]] to end the [[AIDS]] crisis." - from the ACT UP/New York website.

ACT UP was effectively formed on March 10, [[1987]] at the [[Lesbian]] and [[Gay]] Community Services Center in [[New York City|New York]]. [[Larry Kramer]] was asked to speak as part of a rotating speaker series, and his well-attended speech focused on action to fight AIDS. Kramer spoke out against the [[Gay Men's Health Crisis]] (GMHC), which he perceived as politically impotent. Kramer had co-founded the GMHC but had resigned from its board of directors in 1983. According to [[Douglas Crimp]], Kramer posed a question to the audience: "Do we want to start a new organization devoted to political action?" The answer was "a resounding yes." Approximately 300 people met two days later to form ACT UP.&lt;ref name="crimp1"&gt;Crimp, Douglas.  ''AIDS Demographics''. Bay Press, 1990. (Comprehensive early history of ACT UP, discussion of the various signs and symbols used by ACT UP).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Actions==

Because ACT UP and its affinity groups organized so many diverse actions in a relatively short period of time, it is difficult and perhaps counter-productive to classify them in any particular way. As such, the actions are presented in no particular order with no particular weight given. Accounts of the actions are drawn from Douglas Crimp's history of ACT UP as well as the [[ACT UP Oral History Project]].

===Wall Street===

On March 24th, 1987, 250 ACT UP members came to [[Wall Street]] to disrupt the opening bell and protest against what they saw as exorbitant prices for the new antiviral drug [[AZT]]. [[Bourroughs Wellcome]], a [[pharmaceutical]] company, had recently acquired the patent for the drug and begun selling it for approximately $10,000 per year per patient, well out of reach of nearly all [[HIV]] positive persons. In this case, it seemed especially egregious because the original research and development of the drug done in the 1960s was partially federally funded.&lt;ref name="crimp1" /&gt; Larry Kramer had an Op/Ed article published in the [[New York Times]] the previous day which described some of the issues ACT UP was concerned with.&lt;ref name="kramer1"&gt;Kramer, Larry. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. [[16 February]] [[2005]]. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  [[11 December]] [[2005]] &lt;http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/kramer.pdf&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; Members partially occupied the trading floor and delayed the sounding of the opening bell. Additionally, some members hanged in effigy [[Frank Edward Young]], the commissioner of the FDA at the time. Seventeen ACT UP members were arrested for this [[civil disobedience]].&lt;ref name="crimp1" /&gt;

===General Post Office===

ACT UP held their next action at the New York City General Post Office on the night of April 15, 1987, to a "captive audience" of people filing last minute tax returns. This event also marked the beginning of the conflation of ACT UP with the [[Silence = Death Project]], which created the famous poster consisting of a right side up pink triangle (an upside-down pink triangle was used to mark gays in Nazi concentration camps) on a black background with the text "SILENCE = DEATH." Douglas Crimp speaks of the "media savvy" of ACT UP at this demonstration, because the [[television media]] "routinely do stories about down-to-the-wire tax return filers." As such, ACT UP was virtually guaranteed media coverage.&lt;ref name="crimp1" /&gt;

===Cosmo===
In January [[1988]] [[Cosmopolitan Magazine]] published an article by [[Robert E. Gould]], a psychiatrist, entitled "Reassuring News About AIDS: A Doctor Tells Why You May Not Be At Risk."&lt;ref name="crimp1" /&gt; The main contention of the article was that in unprotected vaginal sex between a man and a woman who both had "healthy genitals" the risk of HIV transmission was negligible, even if the male partner was infected. Women from ACT UP who had been having informal "dyke dinners" met with Dr. Gould in person, questioned him about several misleading facts (that penis to vagina transmission is impossible, for example), questionable journalistic methods (no [[peer review]], bibliographic information, failing to disclose that he was a psychiatrist and not a practitioner of [[internal medicine]]), and demanded a retraction and apology.&lt;ref name="maggenti1"&gt;Maggenti, Maria. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. [[16 February]] [[2005]]. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  [[11 December]] [[2005]] &lt;http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/maggenti.pdf&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; When he refused, in the words of Maria Maggenti, they decided that they "had to shut down Cosmo." According to those who were involved in organizing the action, it was significant in that it was the first time the women in ACT UP organized separately from the main body of the group.&lt;ref name="carlomusto1"&gt;Carlomusto, Jean. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. [[16 February]] [[2005]]. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  [[11 December]] [[2005]] &lt;http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/carlomusto.pdf&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, filming the action itself, the preparation and the aftermath were all consciously planned and resulted in a video short titled, "Doctor, Liars, and Women: AIDS Activists Say No To Cosmo." The action consisted of approximately 150 activists protesting in front of the Hearst building (parent company of Cosmopolitan) chanting "Say no to Cosmo!" and holding signs with slogans such as "Yes, the Cosmo Girl CAN get AIDS!"&lt;ref name="crimp1" /&gt; Although the action did not result in any arrests, it brought significant television media attention to the controversy surrounding the article. Phil Donahue, Nightline, and a local talk show called "People Are Talking" all hosted discussions of the article. On the latter, two women, Chris Norwood and Denise Ribble took the stage after the host, Richard Bey, cut Norwood off during an exchange about whether heterosexual women are at risk from AIDS.&lt;ref&gt;Treichler, Paula. ''How To Have Theory In An Epidemic''. Duke University Press, 1999. (Discussion of the Cosmopolitan controversy and media representation)&lt;/ref&gt; Footage from all of these media appearances were edited into "Doctors, Liars, and Women." Cosmopolitan eventually issued a partial retraction of the contents of the article.&lt;ref name="maggenti1" /&gt;

===NIH demonstration===
In May [[1990]], ACT UP organized a large choreographed demonstration at the [[National Institutes of Health]] (NIH) Campus. According to Kramer, this was their best demonstration, but was almost completely ignored by the media because of a large fire in Washington, D.C. on the same day.

===Day of Desperation===
On January 22, 1991, during [[Operation Desert Storm]], ACT UP activist John Weir and two other activists entered the studio of the [[CBS Evening News]] at the beginning of the broadcast. They shouted "Fight AIDS, not Arabs!" and Weir upstaged [[anchorman]] [[Dan Rather]] before the control room cut to a commercial break. The same night ACT UP demonstrated at the studios of the [[MacNeil/Lehrer Newshour]]. The next day activists displayed banners in [[Grand Central Station]] that said "Money for AIDS, not for war" and "One AIDS death every 8 minutes." These actions were part of a coordinated protest called "Day of Desperation."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.actupny.org/diva/synDesperation.html Day of Desperation Synopsis]. ACT UP New York.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Seattle schools===
In December [[1991]], ACT UP's Seattle chapter distributed over 500 safer-sex packets outside Seattle high schools.  The packets contained a pamphlet titled "How to Fuck Safely," which was photographically illustrated and included two men performing fellatio.  The Washington state legislature subsequently passed a "Harmful to Minors" law making it illegal to give sexually explicit material to underage persons.

==Structure of ACT UP==

ACT UP was intentionally organized as leaderless and effectively [[anarcho-democratic]]. This was intentional on Larry Kramer's part - he describes it as "democratic to a fault."&lt;ref name="kramer1" /&gt; It followed a committee structure with each committee reporting to a coordinating committee meeting once a week. Actions and proposals were generally brought to the coordinating committee and then to the floor for a vote, but this wasn't required - any motion could be brought to a vote at any time.&lt;ref name="carlomusto1" /&gt; Gregg Bordowitz, an early member, said of the process:
:"This is how grassroots, democratic politics work. To a certain extent, this is how democratic politics is supposed to work in general. You convince people of the validity of your ideas. You have to go out there and convince people."&lt;ref name="bordowitz1"&gt;Bordowitz, Gregg. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. [[16 February]] [[2005]]. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  [[11 December]] [[2005]] &lt;http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/bordowitz.pdf&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt;
This is not to say was in practice purely anarchic or democratic. Bordowitz and others admit that certain people were able to communicate and defend their ideas more effectively than others. Although Larry Kramer is often labeled the first "leader" of ACT UP, as the group matured, those people that regularly attended meetings and made their voice heard became conduits through which smaller "affinity groups" would present and organize their ideas. Leadership changed hands frequently and suddenly.&lt;ref name="bordowitz1" /&gt;
*Some of the Committees were:
**Action Committee 
**Finance Committee
**Outreach Committee
**Treatment and Data Committee
**Media Committee
**Graphics Committe
Note: As ACT UP had no formal organizing plan, the titles of these committees are somewhat variable and some members remember them differently than others. 

===DIVA-TV===
An acronym for “Damned Interfering Video Activist Television” -- an affinity group within ACT UP that videotaped and documented [[AIDS]] activism. One of their early works is “[[Like a Prayer (video)|Like a Prayer]]” (1991), documenting the ACT UP protests at [[St. Patrick's Cathedral, New York|St. Patrick's Cathedral]] against New York [[John Cardinal O'Connor|Cardinal O'Connor]]’s position on AIDS and [[contraception]]. Although less as a "collective" after 1990, DIVA TV continued documenting the direct actions of ACT UP and AIDS activists, producing over 160 video programs for public access television channels (as the weekly series "AIDS Community Television" from 1991-1996); film festival screenings; and continuing on-line documentation and streaming internet webcasts. The video activism of DIVA TV ultimately switched media in 1997 with the establishing and continuing development of the ACT UP (New York) website.  The most recent DIVA TV-genre video program documenting the history and activism of ACT UP (New York) is the feature-length documentary: "Fight Back, Fight AIDS: 15 Years of ACT UP" (2002), screened at the Berlin Film Festival and exhibited worldwide. DIVA TV programs and camera-original videotapes are currently re-mastered, archived and preserved, and publicly accessible in the collection of the "AIDS Video Activist Video Preservation Project" at the New York Public Library.

===Institutional independence===
ACT UP had an early debate about whether to register the organization as a [501(c)3] nonprofit in order to allow contributors [tax exemptions]. Eventually they decided against it, because as Maria Maggenti said, "they didn't want to have anything to do with the government."&lt;ref name="maggenti1" /&gt; This kind of uncompromising ethos characterized the group in its early stages; eventually it led to a split between those in the group that wanted to remain wholly independent and those that saw opportunities for compromise and progress by "going inside [the institutions and systems they were fighting against]."&lt;ref name="harrington1"&gt;Harrington, Mark. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. [[16 February]] [[2005]]. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  [[11 December]] [[2005]] &lt;http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/harrington.pdf&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later years==
ACT UP, while extremely prolific and certainly effective in its heydey, suffered from extreme internal pressures over the direction of the group and of the AIDS crisis. After the action at NIH, these tensions resulted in an effective severing of the Action Committee and the Treatment and Data Committee, which reformed itself as the Treatment Advocacy Group (TAG). &lt;ref name="harrington1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wolfe, Maxine. Interview with Sarah Schulman and Jim Hubbard. ACTUP Oral History Project. [[16 February]] [[2005]]. MIX: The New York Lesbian &amp; Gay Experimental Film Festival.  [[11 December]] [[2005]] &lt;http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/images/wolfe.pdf&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; Several members describe this as a "severing of the dual nature of ACT UP."

In recent years, with the changing nature of the AIDS crisis, ACT UP's membership has dwindled, though many chapters continue to meet.

==Influence==
In the early [[1990s]], [[activists]] from ACT UP founded two other direct action [[gay rights]] groups, [[Queer Nation]] and [[Lesbian Avengers]].

==Factionalism in San Francisco==
In 2000, [[ACT UP/Golden Gate]] changed its name to Survive AIDS, to avoid confusion with ACT UP/San Francisco (ACT UP/SF). The two had previously split apart in 1990, but continued to share the same essential philosophy. In 1994, ACT UP/SF diverged from the established point of view regarding the cause of AIDS and the connection to HIV, and the two groups became openly hostile to each other, with mainstream gay and AIDS organizations also condemning ACT UP/SF. ACT UP/SF continues to operate within the sphere of [[AIDS denial]]ism ["The fact is that there is no plague of contagious AIDS,"– as quoted from the ACT UP/SF website] and animal rights activism. [http://www.aegis.com/news/wb/2000/WB000301.html]

==Criticism and controversy==
The organization, or offshoots of it, have at times faced criticism for being too militant. Their disagreements with [[Cardinal John O'Connor]] on issues related to sex education in New York City Public Schools, as well as the Cardinal's public views on homosexuality, led to the first Stop the Church protest on [[December 10]] [[1989]] at [[St. Patrick's Cathedral, New York]],&lt;ref&gt;Crouch, Stanley. Obit at [[Salon.com|Salon]] &lt;http://www.salon.com/news/col/crouch/2000/05/10/cardinal/&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; in which it's estimated 4500 ACT-UP and [[Women%E2%80%99s_Health_Action_and_Mobilization|WHAM!]] members gathered outside St. Patrick's Cathedral to protest the Church's opposition to [[safe sex|safer sex education]], the Church's [[homophobia]], and the Church's attempts to block access to [[pro-choice|safe and legal abortions]]. 111 activists were arrested. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.actupny.org/documents/cron-89.html ACTUP Capsule History 1989]&lt;/ref&gt; Some activists entered the Cathedral, and interrupted Mass, threw used condoms at the altar, chained themselves to the pews, chanted slogans during the mass or lay down in the aisles. As a result of the St. Patrick's Cathedral action, ACT-UP was publicly condemned by Mayor [[Edward Koch]] and some media for what they viewed as militancy and disrespect.  ACT-UP's account of the event notes that "The news media choose to focus on, and distort, a single Catholic demonstrator's personal protest involving a communion wafer." 

As is the case with many grass-roots protest groups, internal issues also sometimes lead to schisms and splintering.

==See also==
*[[Didier Lestrade]], ACT UP Paris co-founder
*[[Luke Sissyfag]], ACT UP Seattle activist

==References==

&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.actupny.org/ ACT UP New York]
*[http://www.actupparis.org/ ACT UP Paris]
*[http://www.critpath.org/actup/ ACT UP Philadelphia]
*[http://www.actupsf.org/ ACT UP San Francisco]
*[http://www.actuporalhistory.org/ ACT UP Oral History Project]

==Outside References==
"The Making of an AIDS Activist: Larry Kramer" and "ACT UP," pp. 162-166, Johansson, Warren and Percy, William A.  [http://williamapercy.com/pub-Outing.htm ''Outing:  Shattering the Conspiracy of Silence.'']  New York and London: Haworth Press, 1994.

{{AIDS}}

[[Category:Health and Disability rights organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:AIDS activism]]
[[Category:LGBT organizations]]


[[de:Act Up]]
[[fr:Act Up]]
[[gl:ACT UP]]
[[fi:ACT UP]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>