<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111019193305|456402400" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="648470" pageid="648470" ns="0" title="Oppression"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-10-30T02:55:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Oppressed|the Welsh band|The Oppressed|other uses|Oppression (disambiguation)}}
{{Rewrite|date=March 2011}}
{{Original research|date=October 2007}}
{{Synthesis|date=March 2011}}
{{NPOV|date=March 2011}}
{{Systemic bias|date=March 2011}}

[[File:1904 Russian Tsar-Stop your cruel oppression of the Jews-LOC hh0145s.jpg|thumb|right|360px|Oppression derives from the concept of being weighted down, and is often depicted as such. Here, a [[political cartoon|cartoon]] [[Jew]] labors under the metaphorical oppression of the [[Czarist Russia|Russian]] [[Tsar]]]]

'''Oppression''' is the exercise of authority or power in a burdensome, cruel, or unjust manner.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aolsvc.merriam-webster.aol.com/dictionary/oppression definition from Merriam Webster Online].&lt;/ref&gt;   It can also be defined as an act or instance of oppressing, the state of being oppressed, and the feeling of being heavily burdened, mentally or physically, by troubles, adverse conditions, and anxiety.



Oppression is a popular topic in debates, such as in the QDU league in secondary schools. {{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

==Social oppression==
The systematic; socially supported mistreatment and exploitation of a group or category of people by anyone.

==Institutionalized oppression==
"Institutional Oppression occurs when established laws, customs, and practices systematically reflect and produce inequities based on one’s membership in targeted social identity groups. If oppressive consequences accrue to institutional laws, customs, or
practices, the institution is oppressive whether or not the individuals maintaining those practices have oppressive intentions." &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcc.edu/resources/illumination/documents/institutionalized-oppression-definitions.pdf Definition from pcc.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Systematic oppression==
[[Anarchism|Anarchists]] and other [[Libertarian socialism|libertarian socialists]] argue that [[police]] and [[law]] themselves are oppression. The term ''oppression'' in such instances to refer to the subordination of a given group or social category by [[justice|unjust]] use of [[force]], [[authority]], or societal [[Norm (sociology)|norms]] in order to achieve the effects noted above. When institutionalized, formally or informally, it may achieve the dimension of ''systematic oppression''. Oppression is customarily experienced as a consequence of, and expressed in, the form of a prevailing, if unconscious, assumption that the given target is in some way inferior. Oppression is rarely limited solely to formal [[government]] action: an individual may be the particular focus of oppression or persecution and in such circumstances have no group membership in which to share, and thus maybe mitigate, the burden of [[ostracism]].

In [[psychology]], racism, sexism and other prejudices are often studied as individual beliefs which, although not necessarily oppressive in themselves, can lead to oppression if they are codified in law or become parts of a culture. By comparison, in [[sociology]], these prejudices are often studied as being institutionalized systems of oppression in some societies. In sociology, the tools of oppression include a progression of denigration, [[dehumanization]], and [[demonization]]; which often generate [[scapegoating]], which is used to justify [[aggression]] against targeted groups and individuals.

The [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] and the concept of "[[human rights]]" in general were designed to limit oppression by giving a clear articulation of what fundamental freedoms any system should allow to all of the people over whom it has power.

When oppression is systematized through coercion, threats of violence, or violence by government agencies or non-government paramilitiaries with a political motive, it is often called [[Political repression]]. More subtle forms of political oppression/repression can be produced by [[blacklisting]] or individualized investigations such as happened during [[McCarthyism]] in the United States.

Transnational systems of oppression include [[colonialism]], [[imperialism]], and [[totalitarianism]], and can generate a [[resistance movement]] to challenge the oppressive status quo.

==Internalized oppression==
In [[sociology]] and [[psychology]], internalized oppression is the manner in which an oppressed group comes to use against itself the methods of the oppressor. For example, sometimes members of marginalized groups hold an oppressive view toward their own group, or start to believe in negative

==Indirect oppression==
Indirect oppression is oppression that is effected by psychological attack, situational constraints or other indirect means. It has been a popular tactic practiced in single power{{Clarify|date=November 2009}}, power monopoly or other authoritarian or totalitarian regimes.

==Resistance==
Several movements have arisen that specifically aim to oppose, analyse and counter oppression in general; examples include [[Liberation Theology]] in the Christian world, and [[Re-evaluation Counseling|Re-evaluation Counselling]] in the psychotherapeutic arena. Modern-day groups that actively oppose oppression include Ligali, a British African organization headed by civil rights activist [[Toyin Agbetu]].

==See also==
* [[Oppressors-oppressed distinction]]
* [[Anti-oppressive practice]]
* [[Authoritarianism]]
* [[Civil rights movement]]
* [[Ethnic cleansing]]
** [[Mass racial violence in the United States]]
** [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union|Mass deportations in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Terrible Triangle]]
* [[Feminist movement]]
* [[Intersectionality]]
* [[Political repression]]
* [[Police oppression]]
* [[Totalitarianism]]
* [[Poverty]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Guillaumin, Colette. 1995. ''Racism, Sexism, Power and Ideology''. London: Routledge.
* Hobgood, Mary Elizabeth. 2000. ''Dismantling Privilege: An Ethics of Accountability''. Cleveland, OH: Pilgrim Press.
* Young-Bruehl, Elisabeth. 1996. ''The Anatomy of Prejudices''. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.
* Noël, Lise. 1994. ''Intolerance, A General Survey''. Montreal: McGill-Queen’s University Press.bany, NY: State University of New York Press.
* Smith, Morgan. 2008.  ''Why I stick it to the man, and why you should too''. New York: HarperCollins Publishers
* Omi, Michael and Howard Winant. 1994. ''Racial Formation in the United States: From the 1960s to the 1990s''. New York: Routledge.
* Feagin, Joe R. and Hernan Vera. 1995. ''White Racism: The Basics''. New York: Routledge.
* Pincus, Fred L. 1999 and Howard J. Ehrlich, eds. 1999. ''Race and Ethnic Conflict: Contending Views on Prejudice, Discrimination, and Ethnoviolence''. Boulder, Colo.: Westview.
* Beck, Aaron, M.D. 1999 ''Prisoners Of Hate''. New York: HarperCollins Publishers
* Solzhenitsyn, Alexandr, "The Gulag Archipelago," Harper and Row, 1973
* Kiernan, Ben, "The Pol Pot Regime: Race, Power, and Genocide in Cambodia under the Khmer Rouge, 1975-79," Yale University Press, 1996
* Cudd, Ann E. 2006. ''Analyzing Oppression''. Oxford: Oxford University Press.
*  Deutsch, Morton. 2006. A Framework for Thinking about Oppression and Its Change. "Social Justice Research", Vol. 19, No.1, March 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;7–41.

==External links==
{{Commonscat}}
*[http://www.oppression.org/ Oppression.org: Raising awareness on issues that are often ignored because they concern a people and place that, to some, seem so foreign]

{{Secret police of Communist Europe}}
{{Abuse}}

[[Category:Neuroethology]]
[[Category:Metaphysics]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Causality]]
[[Category:Negative Psychology]]

[[ca:Opressió]]
[[cs:Útlak]]
[[de:Unterdrückung]]
[[fr:Oppression]]
[[he:דיכוי]]
[[ja:弾圧]]
[[pl:Opresja społeczna]]
[[pt:Opressão]]
[[ru:Иго]]
[[simple:Oppression]]
[[sr:Опресија]]
[[sv:Förtryck]]
[[zh:迫害]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>