<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151110055901|689923240" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="648470" pageid="648470" ns="0" title="Oppression"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-10T05:59:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Oppressed|the Welsh band|The Oppressed|other uses|Oppression (disambiguation)}}
{{cleanup-rewrite|date=March 2011}}

[[File:1904 Russian Tsar-Stop your cruel oppression of the Jews-LOC hh0145s.jpg|thumb|Oppression derives from the concept of being weighted down, and is often depicted as such. Here, a [[political cartoon]] shows a [[Jew]] laboring under the metaphorical oppression of the [[Czarist Russia|Russian]] [[Tsar]]]]
'''Oppression''' is the exercise of authority or power in a burdensome, cruel, or unjust manner.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aolsvc.merriam-webster.aol.com/dictionary/oppression definition from Merriam Webster Online]. &lt;/ref&gt;  It can also be defined as an act or instance of oppressing, the state of being oppressed, and the feeling of being heavily burdened, mentally or physically, by troubles, adverse conditions or people, and anxiety.

==Social oppression==
Social oppression is the socially supported mistreatment and exploitation of a group, category, or team of people or individuals.

==Institutionalized oppression==
"Institutional Oppression occurs when established laws, customs, and practices systematically reflect and produce inequities based on one’s membership in targeted social identity groups. If oppressive consequences accrue to institutional laws, customs, or
Practices, the institution is oppressive whether or not the individuals maintaining those practices have oppressive intentions."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pcc.edu/resources/illumination/documents/institutionalized-oppression-definitions.pdf |title=Definition from pcc.edu |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Resistance==
Several movements have arisen that specifically aim to oppose, analyze and counter oppression in general; examples include [[Liberation Theology]] in the Christian world, and [[Re-evaluation Counseling|Re-evaluation Counselling]] in psychotherapy.

==See also==
{{Columns-list|2|
* [[Abuse of power]]
* [[Anti-oppressive practice]]
* [[Authoritarianism]]
* [[Civil rights movement]]
* [[Ethnic cleansing]]
* [[Humiliation]]
* [[Intersectionality]]
* [[Oppressors-oppressed distinction]]
* [[Political repression]]
* [[Police oppression]]
* [[Economic oppression]]
* [[Power and control in abusive relationships]]
* [[Privilege (social inequality)]]
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Totalitarianism]]
}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{Commons category}}
{{Lacking ISBN|date=March 2013}}
{{further reading cleanup|date=March 2013}}
* Guillaumin, Colette. 1995. ''Racism, Sexism, Power and Ideology''. London: Routledge.
* Hobgood, Mary Elizabeth. 2000. ''Dismantling Privilege: An Ethics of Accountability''. Cleveland, OH: Pilgrim Press.
* Young-Bruehl, Elisabeth. 1996. ''The Anatomy of Prejudices''. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.
* Noël, Lise. 1994. ''Intolerance, A General Survey''. Montreal: McGill-Queen’s University Press.bany, NY: State University of New York Press.
* Smith, Morgan. 2008.  ''Why I stick it to the man, and why you should too''. New York: HarperCollins Publishers
* Omi, Michael and Howard Winant. 1994. ''Racial Formation in the United States: From the 1960s to the 1990s''. New York: Routledge.
* Feagin, Joe R. and Hernan Vera. 1995. ''White Racism: The Basics''. New York: Routledge.
* Pincus, Fred L. 1999 and Howard J. Ehrlich, eds. 1999. ''Race and Ethnic Conflict: Contending Views on Prejudice, Discrimination, and Ethnoviolence''. Boulder, Colo.: Westview.
* Beck, Aaron, M.D. 1999 ''Prisoners Of Hate''. New York: HarperCollins Publishers
* Solzhenitsyn, Alexandr, "The Gulag Archipelago," Harper and Row, 1973
* Kiernan, Ben, "The Pol Pot Regime: Race, Power, and Genocide in Cambodia under the Khmer Rouge, 1975-79," Yale University Press, 1996
* Cudd, Ann E. 2006. ''Analyzing Oppression''. Oxford: Oxford University Press.
*  Deutsch, Morton. 2006. A Framework for Thinking about Oppression and Its Change. "Social Justice Research", Vol. 19, No.1, March 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;7–41.
*muvirimi learnmore.the oppressor behaviour .2013 university of Zimbabwe press.
{{Secret police of Communist Europe}}
{{Abuse}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{Authority control}}
[[Category:Neuroethology]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Injustice]]
[[Category:Causality]]
[[Category:Corruption]]
[[Category:Social concepts]]
[[Category:Social inequality]]
[[Category:Social problems]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]
[[Category:Power (social and political)]]
[[Category:Privilege (social inequality)]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[Ar:اضطهاد]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>