<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071105165203|169404114" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="648470" pageid="648470" ns="0" title="Oppression"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-12T09:47:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=October 2007}}
{{otheruses}}

'''Oppression''' is the negative outcome experienced by people targeted by the biased exercise of [[power (sociology)|power]] in a society or social group. It is particularly closely associated with nationalism and derived social systems, wherein identity is built by antagonism to the other. The term itself derives from the idea of being "weighted down."

==Systematic oppression==
{{Discrimination2}}
The term oppression is primarily used to describe how a certain group is being ''kept down'' by [[justice|unjust]] use of [[force]], [[authority]], or societal [[norms]]. When this is institutionalized formally or informally in a society, it is referred to as "systematic oppression". Oppression is most commonly felt and expressed by a widespread, if unconscious, assumption that a certain group of people are inferior. Oppression is rarely limited solely to government action. Individuals can be victims of oppression, and in this case have no group membership to share their burden of being ostracized.

In [[psychology]], racism, sexism and other prejudices are often studied as individual beliefs which, although not necessarily oppressive in themselves, can lead to oppression if they are acted on, or codified into law or other systems.  By comparison, in [[sociology]], these prejudices are often studied as being institutionalized systems of oppression in some societies.  In sociology, the tools of oppression include a progression of denigration, [[dehumanization]], and [[demonization]]; which often generate [[scapegoating]], which is used to justify [[aggression]] against targeted groups and individuals.

The [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] and the concept of [[Human Rights]] in general were designed to challenge oppression by giving a clear articulation of what limits should be placed on the power of any entity to unfairly control an individual or group of people.

When oppression is systematized through coercion, threats of violence, or violence by government agencies or non-government paramilitiaries with a political motive, it is often called [[Political repression]]. More subtle forms of political oppression/repression can be produced by [[blacklisting]] or individualized investigations such as happened during [[McCarthyism]] in the United States. 

Transnational systems of oppression include [[colonialism]], [[imperialism]], and [[totalitarianism]], and can generate a [[resistance movement]] to challenge the oppressive status quo.

Oppression is noted by living with constant fear.

==Hierarchy of oppression==
A hierarchy of oppression is a ranking ([[hierarchy]]) of relative oppressions according to arbitrariness and cruelty, or according to the perceived negative effects on oppressed communities. Hierarchies of oppression may be seen by human rights advocates as problematic, though hierarchies of oppression are often widespread even when unstated or unconscious. 

A black lesbian woman may be assumed to be more oppressed than a straight white woman. However, political and social activists and theorists find such hierarchies of oppression counterproductive because they prevent [[coalition]]s from being formed between oppressed groups and individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[[Audre Lorde]] "There is no hierarchy of oppressions." Homophobia and Education. New York: Council on Interracial Books for Children. 1983&lt;/ref&gt; A hierarchy of oppression may constitute a hierarchy of victimization and also a hierarchy of [[guilt]]. Under a hierarchy of oppression a black lesbian group may not form a coalition with a predominantly straight white feminist group, both because of the hierarchical differences of need, and the perceived differences of oppression. Hierarchies of oppression may create a competition between oppressed groups, with the most oppressed as the winners.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glsen.org/cgi-bin/iowa/all/library/record/1279.html] How Does Homophobia Hurt Us All?  Warren J. Blumenfeld&lt;/ref&gt;

==Internalized oppression==
In [[sociology]] and [[psychology]], internalized oppression is the manner in which an oppressed group comes to use against itself the methods of the oppressor. For example, sometimes members of marginalized groups hold an oppressive view toward their own group, or start to believe in negative stereotypes of themselves.

For example, internalized racism is when blacks believe the stereotypes of blacks are true. Some blacks believe that they are less intelligent, better dancers, or academically inferior to whites. Any minority group can internalize prejudice.

==Indirect oppression==
Indirect oppression is oppression that is effected by psychological attack, situational constraints or other indirect means. It has been a popular tactic practiced in single power, power monopoly or other authoritarian or totalitarian regimes.

==Resistance==
Several movements have arisen that specifically aim to oppose, analyse and counter oppression in general; examples include [[Liberation Theology]] in the Catholic world, and [[Re-evaluation Counseling|Re-evaluation Counselling]] in the psychotherapuetic arena.

==See also==
* [[wage slavery]]
* [[indirect oppression]]
* [[intersectionality]]
* [[authoritarianism]]
* [[political repression]]
* [[police oppression]]
* [[totalitarianism]]
* [[taxation]]
* [[Black Iron Prison|black iron prison]]
* [[domination]]
* [[hierarchy]]


==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.oppression.org/ Oppression.org: Raising awareness on issues that are oftentimes ignored because they concern a people and place that, to some, seem so foreign]
*[http://www.copshots.org/ COPSHOTS.org: Documenting Police Brutality, Documenting the Police]
*[http://www.helium.com/tm/428349/crossing-boundaryfor-ordered-society A Short Essay on the History of Oppression]

==Bibliography==
* Guillaumin, Colette. 1995. ''Racism, Sexism, Power and Ideology''. London: Routledge.
* Hobgood, Mary Elizabeth. 2000. ''Dismantling Privilege: An Ethics of Accountability''. Cleveland, OH: Pilgrim Press.
* Young-Bruehl, Elisabeth. 1996. ''The Anatomy of Prejudices''. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.
* Noël, Lise. 1994. ''Intolerance, A General Survey''. Montreal: McGill-Queen’s University Press.
* Felice, William F. 1996. ''Taking Suffering Seriously: The Importance of Collective Human Rights''. Albany, NY: State University of New York Press.
* Omi, Michael and Howard Winant. 1994. ''Racial Formation in the United States: From the 1960s to the 1990s''. New York: Routledge.
* Feagin, Joe R. and Hernan Vera. 1995. ''White Racism: The Basics''. New York: Routledge. 
* Pincus, Fred L. 1999 and Howard J. Ehrlich, eds. 1999. ''Race and Ethnic Conflict: Contending Views on Prejudice, Discrimination, and Ethnoviolence''. Boulder, Colo.: Westview.
* Beck, Aaron, M.D. 1999 ''Prisoners Of Hate''. New York: HarperCollins Publishers 
* Solzhenitsyn, Alexandr, "The Gulag Archipelago," Harper and Row, 1973
* Kiernan, Ben, "The Pol Pot Regime: Race, Power, and Genocide in Cambodia under the Khmer Rouge, 1975-79," Yale University Press, 1996
* Cudd, Ann E. 2006. ''Analyzing Oppression''. Oxford: Oxford University Press.

[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]
[[Category:Psychological abuse]]
[[Category:Sociology]]

[[de:Unterdrückung]]
[[pt:Opressão]]
[[he:דיכוי]]
[[ja:弾圧]]
[[sv:Förtryck]]
[[zh:迫害]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>