<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101025080019|392747452" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="53277" pageid="53277" ns="0" title="Fat acceptance movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-09T09:10:52Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move|small=yes}}
The '''fat acceptance movement''' (also known as the '''size acceptance movement''', '''fat liberation movement''', and '''fat power''') is a [[grassroots]] effort to change societal attitudes towards [[obesity|fat, obese, and overweight]] people.

== Background ==
Activism concerning the societal acceptance of fat people covers numerous fronts but generally can be described as attempting to alter societal, internal, and medical attitudes.

The movement argues that overweight people are targets of [[hatred]] and [[discrimination]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.enoughdiscrimination.com/ Enoughdiscrimination.com]&lt;/ref&gt; and that obese women are subjected to more social pressure than obese men.&lt;ref name="ifonly" /&gt;&lt;ref name=naafapolicies&gt;[http://www.naafaonline.com/dev2/about/docs.html Official Policies &amp; Newsletters], [[National Association to Advance Fat Acceptance]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cswd.org/docs/faq.html Council on Size and Weight Discrimination - Discrimination FAQ&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Hatred and disrespect towards fat people are seen in multiple places, including media outlets, where fat people are often ridiculed&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.health24.com/dietnfood/Weight_Centre/15-51-89,14715.asp Health 24 - Diet, Weight loss - Related&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cswd.org/docs/media.html Council on Size and Weight Discrimination - Weight Discrimination on Television&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Greenberg BS, Eastin M, Hofschire L, Lachlan K, Brownell KD (2003). "Portrayals of overweight and obese individuals on commercial television." Am J Public Health. Aug;93(8):1342-8.&lt;/ref&gt; or held up as objects of pity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timeout.com/chicago/articles/out-there/24098/weighing-in Weighing in - Time Out Chicago&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Discrimination comes in the form of lack of equal access to transportation and employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1023/A:1007712500496}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Proponents argue that anti-fat stigma and aggressive diet promotion have led to an increase in psychological and physiological problems among fat people.&lt;ref name="ifonly" /&gt; Proponents of fat acceptance maintain that people of all shapes and sizes can strive for fitness and physical health.&lt;ref&gt;Ikeda JP, Hayes D, Satter E, Parham ES, Kratina K, Woolsey M, Lowey M, Tribole E (1999). "A commentary on the new obesity guidelines from NIH." J Am Diet Assoc. Aug;99(8):918-9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naafa.org/documents/policies/fitness.html Naafa Policy On Physical Fitness&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;], naafa.org&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.size-acceptance.org/rfh/ ISAA's Respect | Fitness | Health Initiative&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sizediversityandhealth.org/home Sizediversityandhealth.org - Home - Mission&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; They believe health to be independent of, not dependent on, body weight. Thus, proponents promote "[[Health at Every Size|health at every size]]", the philosophy that one can pursue mental and physical health regardless of their physical appearance or size.  

Through the works of authors such as [[Paul Campos]] and [[Sandy Szwarc]], the fat acceptance movement has argued that doctors should treat the health problems of people of all sizes, believing that health issues are not defined by weight and are shared by people of all sizes, fat and thin. Some in the movement have argued that the health risks of fatness and obesity have been exaggerated or misrepresented, and used as cover for cultural and aesthetic prejudices against fat.

Fat activism remains a marginal movement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bitchmagazine.org/article/big-trouble Big Trouble | Bitch Magazine&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;], bitchmagazine.org&lt;/ref&gt; Organizations such as the [[National Association to Advance Fat Acceptance]] (NAAFA) and the [[International Size Acceptance Association]] (ISAA) have relatively small memberships, and people interested in the movement tend to be clustered in larger cities and spread across medium- to small-sized web communities.

== History ==
During the early part of the 20th century, obesity was seen as detrimental to the community, by means of decreasing human efficiency, and that obese people interfere with labor productivity in the coastal areas of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1111/1467-9566.00289}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This kind of history and visibility gave rise to the Fat Acceptance movement which originated in the late 1960s, although its grassroots nature makes it difficult to precisely chart its milestones.&lt;ref name="autogenerated4" /&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt; Like other social movements from this time period, the fat acceptance movement, initially known as "Fat Pride," "Fat Power," or "Fat Liberation," often consisted of people acting in an impromptu fashion. A "Fat-in" was staged in New York's Central Park in 1967.&lt;ref&gt;"Curves Have Their Day in Park; 500 at a 'Fat-in' Call for Obesity," New York Times. June 5, 1967, pg. 54&lt;/ref&gt;  Called by a radio personality, Steve Post, the "Fat-in" consisted of a group of 500 people eating, carrying signs and photographs of [[Sophia Loren]] (an actress famous for her figure), and burning diet books.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1913858,00.html | work=Time | title=The Fat-Acceptance Movement | first=Dan | last=Fletcher | date=2009-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several groups formed during this period to promote a fat acceptance agenda.  In 1969, William Fabrey founded a social club promoting "Fat Pride" called the National Association to Aid Fat Americans, subsequently renamed the National Association to Advance Fat Acceptance ([[NAAFA]]). In 1973, a radical NAAFA chapter spun off to become an independent group, the Fat Underground, promoting a stronger activist philosophy. They were inspired by the philosophy of the Radical Therapy Collective, a feminist group that believed that many psychological problems were caused by oppressive social institutions and practices.  The Fat Underground, founded by Sara Fishman (then Sara Aldebaran) and Judy Freespirit, took issue with the growing bias against obesity in the scientific community. They coined the saying, "a diet is a cure that doesn't work for a disease that doesn't exist".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.largesse.net/Archives/FU/index.html The Fat Underground&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;], largesse.net&lt;/ref&gt;
    
Shortly afterwards, Fishman moved to [[New Haven]], CT, where she, along with Karen Scott-Jones, founded the New Haven Fat Liberation Front, an organization similar to the Fat Underground in its scope and focus. In 1983, they collaborated to publish a germinal book in the field of Fat Activism, ''Shadow on a Tightrope.''&lt;ref&gt;Shadow on a Tightrope:   is Writings by Women on Fat Oppression, eds. Lisa Schoenfielder and Barb Wieser.  Iowa City, IA:  Aunt Lute Books, 1983&lt;/ref&gt; The book collected several fat activist position papers initially distributed by the Fat Underground, as well as poems and essays from other writers.

The 1980s and 1990s witnessed an increase in activist organizations, publications, and conferences.&lt;ref name="autogenerated4"&gt;[http://www.radiancemagazine.com/issues/1998/winter_98/fat_underground.html Life In The Fat Underground by Sara Fishman&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;[http://members.tripod.com/bigastexas/2001event/keynote2001.html Big As Texas 2001 Event-Keynote Address&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;], members.tripod.com&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1980s, new anti-dieting programs and models began to appear in the research literature in response to new information dispelling common myths about obesity.&lt;ref name="ifonly"&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1037/0735-7028.27.2.175|title=The "If Only I Were Thin..." Treatment Program: Decreasing the Stigmatizing Effects of Fatness|journal=Professional psychology, research and practice|year=1996|first=Robinson|last=B. E.|coauthors=Bacon, J. G.|volume=27|issue=2|pages=175–183|publisher=[[American Psychological Association]]|location=[[Arlington, Virginia]], [[United States]]|issn=0735-7028|oclc=8996897|accessdate=2009-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Modern movement ==

Members of the contemporary movement perceive negative societal attitudes as persistent, and as being based on the presumption that fatness reflects negatively on a person's character.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"&gt;Murray, S (2005). "(Un/Be)Coming Out? Rethinking Fat Politics" Social Semiotics Vol. 15 No. 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|11743063}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, the fat acceptance movement continues to strive for change in societal, internal, and medical attitudes toward fat people. Proponents engage in public education about what they describe as myths concerning fat and fat people.&lt;ref&gt;NAAFA has a brochure titled [http://www.naafa.org/documents/brochures/myths.html Dispelling common myths about fat people]&lt;/ref&gt;  Organizations hold conferences and conventions: including "NAAFA",&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naafaonline.com/dev2/community/events.html NAAFAonline.com]&lt;/ref&gt; the "Association for Size Diversity and Health",&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sizediversityandhealth.org/ SizeDiversityAndHealth.org]&lt;/ref&gt; the "No Lose Annual Conference",&lt;ref&gt;[http://nolose.org/ NoLose.org]&lt;/ref&gt; and "FatGirl Speaks".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fatgirlspeaks.com FatGirlSpeaks.com]&lt;/ref&gt;  Several books have been written on the topic, including ''Fat!So? You don’t have to apologize for your size'', By Marilyn Wann, ''Tipping the Scales of Justice: Fighting Weight-Based Discrimination'', by Sondra Salami, ''Largely Happy: Changing your mind about your body'', by Lynda Finn, and ''Don’t Diet'', by Dale Atrens.

In recent years, more writers have written to promote fat acceptance: related online [[zine]]s include''Fat!So''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fatso.com/ Fatso.com]&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Figure 8'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/ponyboypress/figure8zine.html&amp;date=2009-10-26+00:40:07  Geocities.com]&lt;/ref&gt; related [[blog]]s include ''Kate Harding's Shapely Prose'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kateharding.net/ KateHarding.net]&lt;/ref&gt;''Big Fat Blog'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bigfatblog.com BigFlatBlog.com]&lt;/ref&gt; and ''The F Word''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.the-f-word.org/blog/ The-F-Word.org]&lt;/ref&gt; Several websites have sprung up to help connect fat people with fat-friendly service providers and products.  Many books have been published challenging the medical claim that fat produces ill health and highlighting the issue of weight-based discrimination that fat people are subjected to by medical professionals and society at large.&lt;ref&gt;The Obesity Myth (2004) by Paul Campos republished as The Diet Myth&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sandy Szwarc’s in depth examination of obesity research in the online magazine [http://www.tcsdaily.com/Authors.aspx?id=238 “Tech Central Station”]&lt;/ref&gt; Size discrimination has been increasingly addressed in the arts, as well. Performance art groups such as [[Padded lilies|The Padded Lilies]], Big Burlesque and the Fat Bottom Revue, among others, intentionally feature fat bodies in their shows. 

There has also been an emerging body of fat political and sociological studies, some with a fat activist agenda, developing within the academy.  The American Popular Culture Association has an area in fat studies and regularly includes panels on the subject.  In addition, student groups with a fat activist agenda have emerged in a number of colleges including Hampshire, Smith, and Antioch colleges.

In addition to what the movement is doing to raise public awareness, there have been a surge in studies both for and against fatness in scientific journals. {{Citation needed|date=September 2010}} 

=== Issues within the movement ===
{{wikinews|Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks}}
[[File:Kira Nerusskaya 2 by David Shankbone.jpg|thumb|Self-described fat activist&lt;ref name=AJC&gt;[http://www.ajc.com/health/content/health/stories/2008/03/26/SIZE_BIAS_web.html State weighs law against size discrimination], Dan Ring, [[Atlanta Journal-Constitution]]'', March 26, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://newyork.timeout.com/articles/dating-in-nyc/71544/fetish-finder/10.html Dating in NYC], ''[[Time Out New York]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Kira Nerusskaya feels that how people describe themselves depends upon their comfort level with their bodies.&lt;ref name=WN&gt;[[n:Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks|Wikinews interview]]&lt;/ref&gt;]]

One point of contention in the movement is found between those fat people who are attempting to lose weight and those who are not. Opponents of weight loss attempts cite the high failure rate of all permanent weight loss attempts, and the many dangers of "[[Yo-yo dieting|yo-yo weight fluctuations]]" and [[Bariatrics#Surgical procedures|weight loss surgeries]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} 

Due to intrinsic linguistic misunderstandings and differing definitions of the word acceptance, some fat activists believe the phrase refers to any fat person fighting for equal rights and opportunities, regardless of whether or not that person believes that the pursuit of reduction in a person's body mass is feasible. Other fat activists define fat acceptance more strictly, applying that phrase only to fat people who are not pursuing a reduction in their body mass, and use phrases such as fat activist to describe fat people and allies working more generally on civil rights issues pertaining to fat people.

In practice, the only way to know the position of any particular individual member of the group on weight loss attempts is to ask, or read specific position papers on the issue.

Another common division in the fat acceptance community is the differing attitudes towards general society, specifically thin people. The fat acceptance community generally divides into two categories.  One is those who feel discrimination towards thin people hinders their cause.  The other side views thin people as the enemy, or the partial cause of their social stigma; some cater to this group with mockery of thin people.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| title       =The Top 8 Things Skinny Girls Can't Do
| url         =http://www.bbwcupid.com/the-top-8-things-skinny-girls-cant-do.cfm 
| work        =[http://www.bbwcupid.com/ BBWCupid.com]
| publisher   =[http://www.cupidmedia.com/ Cupid Media]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Related law==
[[Michigan]], [[Washington, D.C.]], and the [[California]] cities of [[San Francisco]] and [[Santa Cruz, California|Santa Cruz]] have passed laws prohibiting weight discrimination. {{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

== Criticism ==
===Health problems===
Despite advocates' claims to the contrary, many studies show that people who are [[obese]] are more likely than others to be in poor health, at a time when [[health care]] costs are rising,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/guidelines/obesity/ob_gdlns.pdf NIH.gov]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hms.harvard.edu/news/pressreleases/df/0902high_startch.html Harvard Medicine&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;], hms.harvard.edu&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hms.harvard.edu/news/pressreleases/meei/0603bodymassindex.html Harvard Medicine&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;], hms.harvard.edu&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hms.harvard.edu/news/pressreleases/df/0703obesity_coloncancer.html Harvard Medicine&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;], hms.harvard.edu&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://health.msn.com/health-topics/breast-cancer/articlepage.aspx?cp-documentid=100193435&amp;GT1=10904 Obesity Raises Cancer Risk - MSN Health &amp; Fitness - Breast Cancer&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; though activists claim this may be partially attributed to stigma that people who are overweight face in everyday life, and these people avoiding doctors because of perceived weight discrimination in the medical profession.&lt;ref&gt;[http://xnet.kp.org/permanentejournal/sum03/stigma.html Stigma and Discrimination in Weight Management and Obesity], xnet.kp.org&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, the [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention|CDC]] estimated that 10 percent of current health care costs are due to obesity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.chron.com/sciguy/archives/2006/11/should_fat_peop_1.html SciGuy: Should fat people pay higher insurance premiums?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;], blogs.chron.com&lt;/ref&gt;  A Dutch study concluded that lifetime cost of obesity are less as these individuals die at an earlier age, while obese individuals have higher annual health care costs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1371/journal.pmed.0050029}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

There are many health related problems associated with obesity, including heart disease, cancer, diabetes, high blood pressure, and joint problems caused by overloading the skeleton with too much weight. Studies show that obesity reduces life expectancy.&lt;ref name="Calle EE, Thun MJ, Petrelli JM, Rodriguez C, Heath CW 1999 1097–105"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Calle EE, Thun MJ, Petrelli JM, Rodriguez C, Heath CW |title=Body-mass index and mortality in a prospective cohort of U.S. adults |journal=N. Engl. J. Med. |volume=341 |issue=15 |pages=1097–105 |year=1999 |month=October |pmid=10511607 |doi= 10.1056/NEJM199910073411501|url=http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/full/341/15/1097}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name="Peeters A, Barendregt J, Willekens F, Mackenbach J, Al Mamun A, Bonneux L 2003 24-32"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Peeters A, Barendregt J, Willekens F, Mackenbach J, Al Mamun A, Bonneux L |title=Obesity in Adulthood and Its Consequences for Life Expectancy: A Life-Table Analysis |journal=Annals of Internal Medicine |volume=138 |issue=1 |pages=24–32 |year=2003 |month=January |pmid=12513041 |url=http://www.annals.org/content/138/1/24.abstract}}&lt;/ref&gt; Public health officials regard widespread obesity as posing significant  [[Obesity#Economic_impact|costs to society]].

===Social criticism===

Fat acceptance advocates' positions have sparked criticism.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} While acknowledging that fat and obese individuals are subject to inappropriate discrimination or pressure, some critics hold that fat acceptance advocates' goal of unconditional acceptance of obesity is itself unhealthy. One study concluded that "the risk of death from all causes, cardiovascular disease, cancer, or other diseases increases throughout the range of moderate and severe overweight for both men and women in all age groups."&lt;ref name="Calle EE, Thun MJ, Petrelli JM, Rodriguez C, Heath CW 1999 1097–105"/&gt; The same study also found that the mortality risk associated with "overweight" is greater for whites than for blacks, raising questions about whether one set of standards for what constitutes health can be applied uniformly across demographic groups. 

Critics also contend that accepting fatness will make people less likely to aspire to achieve a healthy weight. The common fat acceptance [[mantra]] that "diets don't work" is considered by some {{Who|date=April 2010}} to be an [[oversimplification]] that may discourage a person in need of a healthier lifestyle from making responsible and potentially beneficial changes in eating habits.  Research has shown that obesity is most commonly caused by a combination of excessive [[Food energy|dietary calories]], lack of physical activity, and [[Polygenic inheritance|genetic susceptibility]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Kushner, Robert |title=Treatment of the Obese Patient (Contemporary Endocrinology) |publisher=Humana Press |location=Totowa, NJ |year=2007 |pages=158 |isbn=1-59745-400-1 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=vWjK5etS7PMC&amp;pg=PA121&amp;lpg=PA121&amp;dq=measurement+of+metabolism+in+obese+Bessesen |doi= |accessdate=April 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Anes2000&gt;{{cite journal |author=Adams JP, Murphy PG |title=Obesity in anaesthesia and intensive care |journal=Br J Anaesth |volume=85 |issue=1 |pages=91–108 |year=2000 |month=July |pmid=10927998 |doi= 10.1093/bja/85.1.91|url=http://bja.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/85/1/91}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Experts at The [[London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine]] published a study suggesting that, as the obese eat 18% more than average, they are unfairly contributing to world hunger and climate change. Dr David Haslam, of the National Obesity Forum (UK) responded "Really, it (the study) is discriminatory towards obese people. They are an easy target at the moment, but I think the causes of climate change and rising food prices is much more complex." &lt;ref name=BBC&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/7404268.stm Obese blamed for the world's ills], BBC, [[British Broadcasting Corporation]]'', Friday, 16 May 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Anti-fat bias]]
* [[Eating disorder]]
* [[Minnesota Starvation Experiment]]
* [[Obesity]]

==References==
(A) Medical Practitioners' Guide to Benefits of Adapting Environments for the Obese
Michigan State University study by Angela Berg MD and Joyce Burke MD
[http://www.msu.edu/user/burkejoy/frame_b.htm MSU.edu]
{{Reflist|3}}
===Sources===
====Academic journals====
{{Div col|cols=3|small=yes}}
*{{cite pmid|16477791}}
*{{cite pmid|10340803}}
*{{cite jstor|3090142}}
*{{cite doi|10.1038/oby.2007.84}}
*{{cite doi|10.1002/hrm.20157}}
*{{cite pmid|16737356}}
*{{cite pmid|12972672}}
*{{cite doi|10.1080/00497870590964165}}
{{Div col end}}

====Other publications====
*{{cite web
  | authorlink = Juliet Samuel
  | title = Fat Pride World Wide: The growing movement for avoirdupois acceptance
  | work = [[Reason Magazine]]
  | publisher = [[Reason Foundation]]
  | date = October 23, 2007
  | url = http://www.reason.com/news/show/123151.html
  | accessdate = 2009-08-17}}

==External links==
&lt;!--==========================({{NoMoreLinks}})============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA  |
    | IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS NOR SHOULD IT BE USED FOR ADVERTISING. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    =========================({{NoMoreLinks}})=============================--&gt;
{{Dmoz|Society/Issues/Health/Body_Image/Fat_Acceptance|''Fat Acceptance''}}

===Organizations===
====Fat Acceptance organizations====
*[http://www.size-acceptance.org/ International Size Acceptance Association], size-acceptance.org
*[http://www.naafa.org/ National Association to Advance Fat Acceptance], naafa.org
*[http://www.cswd.org/ Council on Size and Weight Discrimination], cswd.org
*[http://www.fatrights.org/ TFRC: The Fat Rights Coalition], fatrights.org
*[http://www.haescommunity.org/ Health At Every Size], haescommunity.org/

====Other organizations====
*The [[Yale University]] ''[http://www.yaleruddcenter.org/ Rudd Center for Food Policy and Obesity]'', section on [http://www.yaleruddcenter.org/what_we_do.aspx?id=10 Weight Bias and Stigma], yaledruddercenter.org

{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fat Acceptance Movement}}
[[Category:Obesity]]
[[Category:Identity politics]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[fr:Acceptation des gros]]
[[id:Fat acceptance movement]]
[[pt:Movimento pró-obesidade]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>