<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161113211459|749341634" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="53277" pageid="53277" ns="0" title="Fat acceptance movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-13T21:30:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:LA2-vx06-konsthallen-skulptur.jpg|thumb|right|280px|The sculpture ''Bronskvinnorna'' (The women of bronze) outside of the art museum (Konsthallen), [[Växjö]], [[Sweden]]. The sculpture is a work by [[Marianne Lindberg De Geer]]. It displays one [[emaciation|emaciated]] and one [[obesity|obese]] woman as a reaction to body fixation.]]

The '''fat acceptance movement''' (also known as the '''size acceptance''', '''fat liberation''', '''fat activism''', '''fativism''', or '''fat power''' movement) is a [[social movement]] seeking to change [[anti-fat bias]] in [[social attitude]]s.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|title = The Stigma of Obesity: A Review and Update|url = http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1038/oby.2008.636/abstract|journal = Obesity|date = 2009-05-01|issn = 1930-739X|pages = 941–964|volume = 17|issue = 5|doi = 10.1038/oby.2008.636|first = Rebecca M.|last = Puhl|first2 = Chelsea A.|last2 = Heuer}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Areas of contention include the [[aesthetic]], legal, and [[medical]] approaches to people whose bodies are fatter than the [[social norm]]. The movement, however, has been criticized, with [[Cathy Young]], writing for the ''[[Boston Globe]]'', claiming that "the fat acceptance movement is hazardous to our health",&lt;ref name="Young2013"&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.bostonglobe.com/opinion/2013/12/30/fat-acceptance-hazardous-health/1ojfoW46R2elWpHLarA19M/story.html | title=Pro-fat an unhealthy status quo | work=The Boston Globe | date=December 30, 2013 | accessdate=June 19, 2015 | author=Young, Cathy}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Barbara Kay]], writing for the ''[[National Post]]'', stating that "fat-acceptance is not the answer to obesity."&lt;ref name="Kay2013"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.nationalpost.com/full-comment/barbara-kay-fat-acceptance-is-not-the-answer-to-obesity | title=Fat-acceptance is not the answer to obesity | work=National Post | date=September 11, 2013 | accessdate=June 19, 2015 | author=Kay, Barbara}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, studies have shown that stress is linked to obesity,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Torres|first=Susan J.|last2=Nowson|first2=Caryl A.|date=2007-11-01|title=Relationship between stress, eating behavior, and obesity|url=http://www.nutritionjrnl.com/article/S0899-9007(07)00249-3/abstract|journal=Nutrition|language=English|volume=23|issue=11-12|pages=887–894|doi=10.1016/j.nut.2007.08.008|issn=0899-9007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that encouraging fat people to focus on their excess weight has been linked to an increase in over-eating.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/aug/05/obesity-awareness-may-be-causing-overeating-finds-international-study|title=Obesity awareness may be causing overeating, finds international study|last=Boseley|first=Sarah|date=2015-08-04|website=the Guardian|access-date=2016-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Besides its [[political]] role, the fat acceptance movement also constitutes a [[subculture]] that acts as a social group for its members.&lt;ref name="Rothblum and Sondra Solovay 2009 xi"&gt;{{cite book|last=Rothblum and Sondra Solovay|first=Esther D.|title=The Fat Studies Reader|year=2009|publisher=NYU Press|isbn=9780814776407|page=xi|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XtLWPWNO8gUC&amp;dq=Fat+studies}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The history of the fat acceptance movement can be dated back to 1967 when 500 people met in New York's Central Park to protest against [[anti-fat bias]]. Sociologist [[Charlotte Cooper (author)|Charlotte Cooper]] has argued that the history of the fat activist movement is best understood in waves, similar to the [[feminist movement]], with which she believes it is closely tied. Cooper believes that fat activists have suffered similar waves of activism followed by burnout, with activists in a following wave often unaware of the history of the movement, resulting in a lack of continuity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Cooper |first=Charlotte |title=What's Fat Activism? |url=http://www3.ul.ie/sociology/docstore/workingpapers/wp2008-02.pdf |format=PDF |publisher=University of Limerick |accessdate=Feb 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===First wave===
First wave activities consisted of isolated activists drawing attention to the dominant model of [[obesity]] and challenging it as only one of a number of possible models.

There are many possible reasons for the development of weight discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cswd.org/docs/faq.html |title=Council on Size and Weight Discrimination – Discrimination FAQ |publisher=Cswd.org |date= |accessdate=2011-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the early part of the 20th century, obesity was seen as detrimental to the community, by means of decreasing human efficiency, and that obese people interfere with [[labor productivity]] in the coastal areas of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| first1 = V. W.| first2 = N. A.| title = Medical modelling of obesity: a transition from action to experience in a 20th century American medical textbook| last1 = Chang| journal = Sociology of Health &amp; Illness| volume = 24| issue = 2| pages = 151–177| year = 2002| doi = 10.1111/1467-9566.00289| last2 =  Christakis}}&lt;/ref&gt; This kind of history and visibility gave rise to the fat acceptance movement {{Original research inline|date=February 2013}} which originated in the late 1960s, although its grassroots nature makes it difficult to precisely chart its milestones. Like other [[social movements]] from this time period, the fat acceptance movement, initially known as "Fat Pride", "Fat Power", or "Fat Liberation", often consisted of people acting in an impromptu fashion. A "fat-in" was staged in New York's Central Park in 1967.&lt;ref&gt;"Curves Have Their Day in Park; 500 at a 'Fat-in' Call for Obesity," ''New York Times''. June 5, 1967, pg. 54&lt;/ref&gt;  Called by radio personality Steve Post, the "Fat-in" consisted of a group of 500 people eating, carrying signs and photographs of [[Sophia Loren]] (an actress famous for her figure), and burning diet books.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1913858,00.html | work=Time | title=The Fat-Acceptance Movement | first=Dan | last=Fletcher | date=2009-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1967, Lew Louderback wrote an article in the Saturday Evening Post called "More People Should be FAT" in response to discrimination against his wife. The article led to a meeting between Louderback and William Fabrey, who went on to found the first organisation for fat people and their supporters, originally named the 'National Association to Aid Fat Americans' and currently called [[NAAFA]] ('National Association to Advance Fat Acceptance'), was founded in America, in 1969, by Bill Fabrey in response to discrimination against his wife. He primarily intended it to campaign for fat rights,  however a reporter attending the 2001 NAAFA conference notes that few attendees were active in fat rights politics and that most women came to shop for fashion, wear it on the conference catwalk or to meet a potential partner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Saggy |first=Abigail |title=What's Wrong With Fat? |year=2013 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=0199857083 |page=55 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7_kVC1XP05MC&amp;pg=PA55&amp;dq=naafa+fat&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=CeYoUeHBB6nH0QWOmIGQBQ&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=naafa%20fat&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fabrey currently works with the Council on Size and Weight Discrimination, specialising in the history of the size acceptance movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Council Directors and Project Managers |url=http://www.cswd.org/docs/aboutus.html |publisher=Council on Size &amp; Weight Discrimination |accessdate=Feb 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1973 the feminist group The Fat Underground was formed. It began as a radical chapter of NAAFA and spun off to become independent when NAAFA expressed concerns about its promotion of a stronger activist philosophy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radiancemagazine.com/issues/1998/winter_98/fat_underground.html |title=Life In The Fat Underground by Sara Fishman |publisher=Radiancemagazine.com |date= |accessdate=2011-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The FU were inspired by and, in some cases, members of the [[Radical Therapy Collective]], a [[feminist]] group that believed that many psychological problems were caused by oppressive social institutions and practices. Founded by Sara Fishman (then Sara Aldebaran) and Judy Freespirit, the Fat Underground took issue with what they saw as a growing bias against obesity in the scientific community. They coined the saying, "a diet is a cure that doesn't work, for a disease that doesn't exist".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.largesse.net/Archives/FU/index.html The Fat Underground&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;], largesse.net{{full citation needed|date=April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards, Fishman moved to Connecticut, where, along with Karen Scott-Jones, she founded the New Haven Fat Liberation Front, an organization similar to the Fat Underground in its scope and focus. In 1983, the two groups collaborated to publish a seminal book in the field of fat activism, ''Shadow on a Tightrope'', which collected several fat activist position papers initially distributed by the Fat Underground, as well as poems and essays from other writers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Simic|first=Zora|editor=Caroline Walters|others=Helen Hester|title=Fat Sex: New Directions in Theory and Activism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dVjUCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT28|year=2015|publisher=Ashgate|isbn=9781472432568|page=28ff|chapter=Far as a Feminist Issue: A History}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1979 Carole Shaw coined the term [[Big Beautiful Woman]] (BBW) and launched a fashion and lifestyle magazine of the same name aimed at [[plus-size clothing|plus-sized]] women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=BBW Past and Present |url=http://www.bbwmagazine.com/pastandpresent_3.htm |publisher=Big Beautiful Woman Magazine |accessdate=Mar 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original print magazine closed in the late 1990s but the term BBW has become widely used to refer to any fat woman.

In the UK The London Fat Women's Group was formed, the first British fat activist group, and was active between approximately 1985 and 1989.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last = Cooper|first = Charlotte|title = What’s Fat Activism?|url = http://www3.ul.ie/sociology/docstore/workingpapers/wp2008-02.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other first wave activities included the productions of [[zines]] such as ''Figure 8'' and ''Fat!So?'', by [[Marilyn Wann]] which later became a [[FAT!SO?|book of the same name]].

===Second wave===
In the second wave, the fat acceptance movement became more widespread in the USA and started to spread to other countries. Ideas from the movement began to appear in the mainstream. Publishers became more willing to publish fat acceptance themed literature.

By the 1990s, input from the fat acceptance movement began to be incorporated into  research papers by some members of the medical professions such as new anti-dieting programs and models of [[obesity]] management.&lt;ref name="ifonly"&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/0735-7028.27.2.175 |title=The "If Only I Were Thin..." Treatment Program: Decreasing the Stigmatizing Effects of Fatness |journal=Professional psychology, research and practice |year=1996 |last1=B.E.|first1=Robinson |last2=J.G.|first2=Bacon |volume=27 |issue=2 |pages=175–183 |publisher=[[American Psychological Association]] |location=Arlington, Virginia, United States |issn=0735-7028 |oclc=8996897}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1980s witnessed an increase in activist organizations, publications, and conferences.{{citation needed|date=September 2015}}  In 1989 a group of people including actress Anne Zamberlan formed the first French organisation for fat acceptance, ''Allegro fortissimo''.&lt;sup&gt;[59]&lt;/sup&gt;

Organisations began holding conferences and conventions, including [[NAAFA]].

===Third wave===
The fat acceptance movement has seen a diversification of projects during the third wave.{{citation needed|date=May 2016}} Activities have addressed issues of both fat and race, class, sexuality and other issues. Size discrimination has been increasingly addressed in the arts, as well. Performance art groups such as Pretty Porky &amp; Pissed Off, The [[Padded Lilies]], a water ballet troupe of large sized women, Big Moves&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bigmoves.org&lt;/ref&gt; and the Fat Bottom Revue,&lt;ref&gt;https://ww2.kqed.org/spark/fat-bottom-revue/&lt;/ref&gt; a Big Burlesque touring show founded by fat activist, [[Heather MacAllister]], "LEFTOVERS, the Ups &amp; Downs of a Compulsive Eater",&lt;ref&gt;https://books.google.com/books?id=j2BhBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA155&amp;lpg=RA1-PA155&amp;dq=leftovers+the+ups+and+downs+of+a+compulsive+eater&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=KWc3PfyVkv&amp;sig=a6YmjeLkkbEZd6TRwx8oW5Vvhco&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwi8j5_CvIXPAhVJcT4KHSE9CUoQ6AEIQzAJ#v=onepage&amp;q=leftovers%20the%20ups%20and%20downs%20of%20a%20compulsive%20eater&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt; among others, intentionally feature fat people in their shows.{{citation needed|date=May 2016}}

The fat acceptance movement increased in the 2000s, with the creation of the "fatosphere"&lt;ref&gt;https://books.google.com/books?id=FDADDMWxis4C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=fatosphere&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiqx-78v4XPAhUQ2GMKHQoaDZQQ6AEIJDAB#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt; and the "Fat Liberation Feed",&lt;ref&gt;https://bigliberty.wordpress.com/the-fat-liberation-feed/&lt;/ref&gt; providing online communities of blogs and social media dedicated to the fat acceptance movement. Notable fat activists within the "fatosphere" include Marianne Kirby&lt;ref&gt;http://mariannekirby.com&lt;/ref&gt; of ''The Rotund''&lt;ref&gt;https://fatheffalump.wordpress.com/category/the-rotund/&lt;/ref&gt; and Kate Harding of ''Shapely Prose'', who co-wrote the book ''Lessons from the Fat-o-sphere: Quit Dieting and Declare a Truce with Your Body.''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Fat Sex: New Directions in Theory and Activism|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=dVjUCQAAQBAJ|publisher = Ashgate Publishing, Ltd.|date = 2015-07-03|isbn = 9781472432568|first = Dr Caroline|last = Walters|first2 = Dr Helen|last2 = Hester}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, the Fat Studies listserv, Health At Every Size (HAES)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/21604851.2016.1218741?journalCode=ufts20&lt;/ref&gt; was created by Marilyn Wann as a place for scholars to find more fat positive information.

The individual blogs of the second wave have mainly been overtaken by larger scale [[social networking]] sites such as ''PeopleOfSize.com'',&lt;ref&gt;http://www.peopleofsize.com&lt;/ref&gt; while several websites have sprung up to help connect fat people with fat-friendly service providers and products, such as ''fatshionista''.{{citation needed|date=September 2015}} Size discrimination has been increasingly addressed in the arts, as well.{{citation needed|date=September 2015}}

==Campaigning themes==
The fat acceptance movement argues that fat people are targets of [[hatred]] and [[discrimination]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Jaffa|first=Karen|title=Forming Fat Identities|year=2008|publisher=ProQuest|isbn=9780549889717|pages=169–70|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=T2EGyNDnohMC&amp;dq=Are+fat+people+discriminated+against}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, that obese women are subjected to more social pressure than obese men.&lt;ref name="ifonly" /&gt; The movement argues that these attitudes comprise a [[obesophobia|fat phobic]] entrenched [[societal norm]], evident in many [[social institutions]], including the [[mass media]]; where fat people are often ridiculed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cswd.org/docs/media.html|title=Council on Size and Weight Discrimination – Weight Discrimination on Television|publisher=Cswd.org|accessdate=2011-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Greenberg BS, Eastin M, Hofschire L, Lachlan K, Brownell KD (2003). "Portrayals of overweight and obese individuals on commercial television." Am J Public Health. Aug;93(8):1342-8.&lt;/ref&gt; or held up as objects of pity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Jennings|first=Laura Lynn|title=Place Settings: Social Aspects of the Body Image/Eating Relationship|year=2008|publisher=ProQuest|isbn=0549641262|page=9|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eCEtM886GHwC&amp;dq=Pity+fat+people+media}}&lt;/ref&gt; Discrimination includes lack of equal access to transportation and employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| first1 = C. L.| first2 = A. F.| last1 = Maranto| journal = Employee Responsibilities and Rights Journal| volume = 12| pages = 9–1| year = 2000| doi = 10.1023/A:1007712500496| last2 =  Stenoien|title=Weight Discrimination: A Multidisciplinary Analysis}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the fat acceptance movement perceive negative societal attitudes as persistent, and as being based on the presumption that fatness reflects negatively on a person's character.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"&gt;Murray, S (2005). "(Un/Be)Coming Out? Rethinking Fat Politics" Social Semiotics Vol. 15 No. 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
| last1 = Puhl | first1 = R.
| last2 = Brownell | first2 = D.
| title = Bias, discrimination, and obesity 
| volume = 9
| journal = Obesity Research 
| issue = 12 
| pages = 788–805 
| date=Dec 2001 | issn = 1071-7323 
| pmid = 11743063 
| doi = 10.1038/oby.2001.108
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fat activists continue to strive for change in societal, personal, and medical attitudes toward fat people. Fat acceptance organisations engage in [[public education]] about what they describe as myths concerning fat people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hemmenway|first=Carrie|title=Dispelling common myths about fat persons.|url=http://world.std.com/~naafa/documents/brochures/myths.html|publisher=NAAFA|accessdate=Feb 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Discrimination ===
Fat individuals experience weight-based discrimination in a number of avenues within their lives.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; This discrimination is experienced in healthcare, employment, education, interpersonal relationships, and in media.{{Citation needed|date=March 2016}} Discrimination can impact both the physical and psychological health of those experiencing it.{{Citation needed|date=December 2015}}

===Health===
{{main article|Health at Every Size|Obesity#Effects on health}}

Fat activists argue that anti-fat stigma and aggressive diet promotion have led to an increase in psychological and physiological problems among fat people.&lt;ref name="ifonly" /&gt; Concerns are also raised that modern culture's focus on weight loss may not have a foundation in scientific research, but instead is an example of using science as a means to control [[Deviance (sociology)|deviance]], as a part of society's attempt to deal with something that it finds disturbing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JvgytwAACAAJ|title=Fat as Deviance: Fat Phobia and the Social Control of Women's Bodies|author=Abigail B. Hulme|publisher=Books.google.com|year=1998|accessdate=2012-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Diet critics cite the high failure rate of permanent weight loss attempts,&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; and the dangers of [[Yo-yo dieting|"yo-yo" weight fluctuations]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Coon|first=Dennis|title=Introduction to Psychology: Gateways to Mind and Behaviour|year=2008|publisher=Cengage Learning|isbn=0495599115|page=328|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vw20LEaJe10C&amp;dq=dangers+of+yo-yo+dieting}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Bariatrics#Surgical procedures|weight loss surgeries]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kelly|first=Evelyn B.|title=Obesity|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=0313334609|page=138|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4uRpT-eOV4IC&amp;dq=dangers+of+bariatric+surgery|date=2006-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fat activists argue that the health issues of [[obesity]] and being [[overweight]] have been exaggerated or misrepresented, and that the health issues are used as a cover for [[cultural]] and [[aesthetic]] prejudices against fat.

Proponents of fat acceptance maintain that people of all shapes and sizes can strive for fitness and physical health.&lt;ref&gt;Ikeda JP, Hayes D, Satter E, Parham ES, Kratina K, Woolsey M, Lowey M, Tribole E (1999). "A commentary on the new obesity guidelines from NIH." J Am Diet Assoc. Aug;99(8):918-9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.size-acceptance.org/rfh/|title=ISAA's Respect &amp;#124; Fitness &amp;#124; Health Initiative|publisher=Size-acceptance.org|accessdate=2011-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Physical Fitness|url=http://www.naafaonline.com/dev2/about/Policies/PHYSICALFITNESS.pdf|publisher=NAAFA|accessdate=Feb 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; They believe health to be independent of body weight. Informed by this approach, psychologists who were unhappy with the treatment of fat people in the medical world initiated the [[Health at Every Size]] movement. It has five basic tenets: 1. Enhancing health, 2. Size and self-acceptance, 3. The pleasure of eating well, 4. The joy of movement, and 5. An end to weight bias.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Burgard|first=Deb|chapter=What Is "Health at Every Size"?|year=2009|editor1-last =Solovay|editor1-first=Sandra|editor2-last=Wann|editor2-first=Marilyn|title=The Fat Studies Reader|publisher=New York University Press|publication-date=2009|isbn=0-8147-7630-2|pages=42–49}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the consensus within the scientific community is that obesity has a negative impact on the health of an individual. Numerous medical studies have challenged the 'healthy obesity' concept.&lt;ref name="Is Healthy Obesity a Myth"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/news/fullstory_145981.html|title=Is Healthy Obesity a Myth?|publisher=nlm.nih.gov|date=30 April 2014|accessdate=31 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="British Heart Foundation"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bhf.org.uk/default.aspx?page=16993|title=Dispelling the myth of 'healthy obesity'|publisher=British Heart Foundation|date=1 May 2014|accessdate=31 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="KramerMetaAnalysis"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Kramer|first1=CK|last2=Zinman|first2=B|last3=Retnakaran|first3=R|title=Are metabolically healthy overweight and obesity benign conditions?: A systematic review and meta-analysis.|journal=Ann Intern Med|date=Dec 3, 2013|volume=11|issue=159|doi=10.7326/0003-4819-159-11-201312030-00008|pmid=24297192|pages=758–69}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BeyondBMI"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Roberson|first1=Lara L|last2=Aneni|first2=Ehimen C|last3=Maziak|first3=Wasim|last4=Agatston|first4=Arthur|last5=Feldman|first5=Theodore|last6=Rouseff|first6=Maribeth|last7=Tran|first7=Thinh|last8=Blaha|first8=Michael J|last9=Santos|first9=Raul D|last10=Sposito|first10=Andrei|last11=Al-Mallah|first11=Mouaz H|last12=Blankstein|first12=Ron|last13=Budoff|first13=Matthew J|last14=Nasir|first14=Khurram|title=Beyond BMI: The "Metabolically healthy obese" phenotype &amp; its association with clinical/subclinical cardiovascular disease and all-cause mortality – a systematic review|journal=BMC Public Health|date=Jan 8, 2014|volume=14|issue=1|doi=10.1186/1471-2458-14-14|pmid=24400816|pmc=3890499|pages=14}}&lt;/ref&gt; One complicating factor in these studies is that definitions of metabolically-healthy obesity are not standardized across studies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Blüher|first1=S|last2=Schwarz|first2=P|title=Metabolically healthy obesity from childhood to adulthood — Does weight status alone matter?|journal=Metabolism|date=Jun 19, 2014|volume=14|issue=9|pages=1084–92|doi=10.1016/j.metabol.2014.06.009|pmid=25038727}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gender===

====Fat women====
{{main article|Big Beautiful Woman|Fat feminism}}
{{wikinews|Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks}}
[[File:Kira Nerusskaya 2 by David Shankbone.jpg|left|thumb|Documentary filmmaker Kira Nerusskaya released her film ''The [[Big Beautiful Woman|BBW]] World: Under the Fat!'' In 2008.]]

The issues faced by fat women in society have been a central theme of the fat acceptance movement since its inception. Although the first organisation,  NAAFA, and the first book, ''Fat Power'' (1970), were both created by men, in each case they were responses to weight discrimination experienced by their wives. Women soon started campaigning on their own behalf with the first feminist group, 'The Fat Underground', being formed in 1973. Issues addressed regarding women have included [[body image]], and in particular [[The Thin Ideal]] and its effect on women.

====Fat men====
The fat acceptance movement has primarily focused on a [[feminist]] model of [[patriarchal]] oppression of fat women, most clearly represented by the encouragement of women to diet. However, Sander L. Gilman argues that, until the 20th century, dieting has historically been a man's activity. He continues, "[[Obesity]] eats away at the idealised image of the [[masculine]] just as surely as it does the idealised image of the [[feminine]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Gilman|first=Sander L.|title=Fat Boys: A Slim Book|year=2004|publisher=University of Nebraska|isbn=0803221835|pages=1–10|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ShdaOI8TmBAC&amp;dq=fat+men}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Banting]] was the author of an 1863 booklet called ''Letter On Corpulence'' which modern diets have used as a model. Men respond to being [[overweight]] differently, (i.e., having a [[Body Mass Index]] of 25 or more), being half as likely as women to [[dieting|diet]], a quarter as likely to undergo [[bariatric|weightloss]] surgery and only a fifth as likely to report feeling [[shame]] about their weight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Oliver|first=J. Eric|title=Fat Politics: The Real Story Behind America's Obesity Epidemic|year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0195347021|page=80|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DtQ0olwnQ4AC&amp;dq=fat+men}}&lt;/ref&gt; Irmgard Tischner identifies this behaviour as rooted in notions of masculinity that require a disregard for healthcare: "Men do not have to care about their size or health, as they have women to care about those things for them".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Tischner|first=Irmgard|title=Fat Lives: A Feminist Psychological Exploration|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0415680948|pages=105–6|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Oyz6VaOi7kQC&amp;dq=Men+sexualise+fat}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some gay men have moved beyond disregard for size to fat acceptance and fat activism with movements like the [[Chub (gay slang)|chub culture]], which started as Mirth &amp; Girth clubs in San Francisco in 1976&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=CiscoRobco|title=Girth &amp; Mirth San Francisco 1976, Boston 1977, New York City 1978|url=http://backinthegays.com/girth-mirth-san-francisco-1976-boston-1977-new-york-city-1978/|publisher=Back in the Gays|accessdate=Mar 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Bear (gay culture)|bear culture]] which [[Sexual fetishism|fetishises]] big, hairy men. Ganapati Durgadas argues that fat bisexual and gay men "are reminders of the feminine [[social stigma|stigma]] with which [[heterosexism]] still tars queer men". In a comparison of queer fat positive [[zine]]s, the lesbian-produced ''Fat Girl'' was found to have political debate content absent from gay male orientated zines such as ''Bulk Male'' and ''Big Ad''. Joel Barraquiel Tan comments: "If fat is a feminist issue, then fat or heft is a fetishised one for gay men. Gay men have a tendency to sexualise difference, where lesbians have historically politicised it."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=LeBesco|first=Kathleen|title=Revolting Bodies? The Struggle To Redefine Fat Identity|year=2004|publisher=University of Massachusetts Press|isbn=1558494294|page=90|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=W7Wz4EKksUcC&amp;dq=men+sexualize+their+fat}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A fat heterosexual man is known as a "Big Handsome Man", in counterpart to a Big Beautiful Woman. Like some fat and gay men, BHMs have sexualized their difference and receive validation of this identity from BBWs or from straight women known as "Female Fat Admirers".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Monaghan|first=Lee F.|title=Men and the War on Obesity: A Sociological Study|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0415407125|page=53|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fP14YLpzR_kC&amp;dq=big+Handsome+Men}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legislation===
In the 1980s fat people in the United States began seeking legal redress for discrimination on the basis of weight, primarily in the workplace but also for being denied access to, or treated differently in regards to, services or entertainment. The results of these cases has varied considerably, although in some instances the [[Americans with Disabilities Act]] (ADA) has been successfully used to argue cases of discrimination against fat people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Theran|first=Elizabeth E.|title=Legal Theory on Weight Discriminationin Weight Bias: Nature, Consequences, And Remedies|year=2005|publisher=Guildford Press|isbn=1593851995|page=195|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FRszpOfV5o0C&amp;dq=weight+discrimination+laws}}&lt;/ref&gt; Roth and Solovay argue that, as with [[transgender]] people, a major cause for the variation in success is the extent to which litigants are apologetic for their size:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
What is the difference between a million-dollar weight case award and a losing case? Like the difference between many winning and losing transgender cases, it's all about the attitude. Does the claimant's attitude and experience about weight/gender reinforce or challenge dominant [[stereotype]]s? Winning cases generally adopt a legal posture that reinforces [[social prejudice]]s. Cases that challenge societal prejudices generally lose.&lt;ref name="Dylan Roth and 2009 170"&gt;{{cite book|last=Dylan Roth and|first=Sandra Solovay|title=No Apology: Shared Struggles in Fat and Transgender Law in Fat Studies Reader|year=2009|publisher=NYU Press|isbn=9780814776407|page=170|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XtLWPWNO8gUC&amp;dq=fat+acceptance+gender}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The ADA act continues to be used as there is no USA federal law against weight discrimination; however, the state of
[[Michigan]] has passed a law against weight discrimination. The cities of [[Washington D.C.]], [[San Francisco]] (2000), [[Santa Cruz, California|Santa Cruz]], [[Binghamton, New York|Binghamton]], [[Urbana, Illinois|Urbana]] (1990s) and [[Madison, Wisconsin|Madison]] (1970s) have also passed laws prohibiting weight discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Weight Discrimination Laws|url=http://www.naafaonline.com/dev2/education/laws.html|work=NAAFA Online|publisher=NAAFA|accessdate=5 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the cities that have a weight discrimination law it is rare for more than 1 case a year to be brought, except for San Francisco which may have as many as 6. Opinions amongst city enforcement workers vary as to why the prosecution numbers are so low, although they all suggested that both overweight people and employers were unaware of the protective legislation and it was also noted that the cities with weight discrimination laws tended to be liberal college towns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Weight Bias Laws: Tipping the Scales Against Prejudice?|url=http://mn.gov/mdhr/education/articles/rs10_2weightlaws.html|publisher=Minnesota Dept. Human Rights|accessdate=Feb 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, not all legal changes have protected the rights of fat people. Despite recommendations from the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] to the contrary, the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit]] has decided that fat people will only qualify as [[disabled]] if it can be proved that their weight is caused by an underlying condition, supporting the concept that being obese is not inherently a disability.&lt;ref name="Dylan Roth and 2009 170"/&gt;

Other countries besides the United States have considered legislation to protect the rights of fat people. In the UK an All Party Parliamentary Group published a report in 2012 called ''Reflections on Body Image'' that found that 1 in 5 British people had been victimised because of their weight. The report recommended that [[Member of Parliament|Members of Parliament]] Investigated putting "appearance-based discrimination" under the same legal basis as sexual or racial discrimination via the [[Equality Act 2010]] which makes it illegal to harass, victimise or discriminate against anyone on the basis of a number of named categories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Adams|first=Stephen|title=Calling someone 'fatty' could become a hate crime|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/health/healthnews/9297496/Calling-someone-fatty-could-become-a-hate-crime.html|accessdate=Mar 2013|newspaper=The Telegraph|date=May 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fat studies===
There has also been an emerging body of academic studies with a fat activist agenda. [[Marilyn Wann]] argues that fat studies moved beyond being an individual endeavour to being a field of study with the 2004 conference ''Fat Attitudes: An Examination of an American Subculture and the Representation of the Female Body''&lt;ref name="Rothblum and Sondra Solovay 2009 xi"/&gt; The [[American Popular Culture Association]] regularly includes panels on the subject. In a number of colleges, student groups with a fat activist agenda have emerged, including Hampshire, Smith, and Antioch. Fat studies is now available as an [[interdisciplinary]] course of study at some colleges, taking a similar approach to other identity studies such as [[women's studies]], [[queer studies]] and [[African American studies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = 'Fat Studies' Go to College|url = http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2010/11/03/fat-studies-colleges-hot-new-course.html|website = The Daily Beast|date = 3 November 2010|publisher = The Daily Beast Company|last = Binder|first = Eve}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2011, there were 2 Australian courses and 10 American courses that were primarily focussed on fat studies or on [[Health at Every Size|health at every size]], and numerous other courses that had some fat acceptance content.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Watkins|first=Patti Lou|title=Teaching Fat Studies From Conception to Reception|url=http://www.tandfonline.com/toc/ufts20/current|publisher=Oregan State University|accessdate=Feb 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Taylor &amp; Francis publish an online Fat Studies journal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Fat Studies|url=http://www.tandfonline.com/toc/ufts20/current|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|accessdate=Feb 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the UK, the first national Fat Studies seminar was held at York in May 2008, leading to the 2009 publication ''Fat Studies in the UK'', edited by Corinna Tomrley and Ann Kalosky Naylor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Fat Studies in the UK|url=http://www.rawnervebooks.co.uk/FSUK.html|publisher=Raw Nerve. Books|accessdate=Mar 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Debates within the movement==
The fat acceptance movement has been divided in its response to proposed legislation defining morbidly obese people as disabled. [[NAAFA]] board member Peggy Howell says: "There's a lot of conflict in the size acceptance community over this. I don't consider myself disabled, and some people don't like 'fat' being considered a disability."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wilkie|first=Christina|title=Obesity Discrimination on the Job Provokes Dispute Over Best Remedy|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/10/04/obesity-discrimination_n_1939385.html|newspaper=Huffing ton Post|year=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; An example of the positive perspective of obesity being classified as a disability on wider society is noted by one researcher: "She makes a point to tell me how impressed she is with the way many do make quiet and polite accommodations for her."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Erdman Farrell|first=Amy|title=Fat Shame:!Stigma and the Fat Body in American Culture|year=2011|publisher=NYU Press|isbn=0814727689|page=165|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XsHmeJqR4uAC&amp;dq=Men+fat+acceptance}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another common division in the fat acceptance community is the differing attitudes towards general society, specifically thin people. The fat acceptance community generally divides into two categories. One is those who feel discrimination towards thin people hinders the fat acceptance cause. The other side views thin people as at least a partial cause of their social stigma.{{citation needed|date=February 2013}}

Women are particularly active within the fat acceptance movement and membership of fat acceptance organizations is dominated by middle-class women in the heaviest 1–2% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Saguy|first=Abigail|title=What's Wrong with Fat?|year=2013|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0199857083|page=63|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7_kVC1XP05MC&amp;dq=fat+acceptance+men}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members have criticized the lack of representation in the movement from men, people of color, and people of lower socioeconomic status.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.xojane.com/issues/why-im-over-the-size-acceptance-movement-or-hey-sa-what-have-you-done-for-me-lately|title=Why I'm Over The Size Acceptance Movement or Hey, SA, What Have You Done For Me Lately?|last=Webb|first=Cary|date=4 January 2014|website=XOJane.com|publisher=XOJANE|access-date=4 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
The fat acceptance movement has been criticised from a number of perspectives. Primarily there has been a conflict over the medicalisation of fat and health professionals have criticised proponents of fat acceptance for ignoring health issues that many studies have shown to be linked to obesity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Worth|first1=Tammy|title=Is the fat acceptance movement bad for our health?|url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/HEALTH/01/06/fat.acceptance/index.html|accessdate=9 December 2015|publisher=CNN|date=6 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fat acceptance has also been challenged from a moral perspective and finally the movement has been criticised for being out of touch with the mainstream.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Miller|first1=Steve|title=Why Getting Tough on Fat Is the Kindest Gesture|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/stevemiller/why-getting-tough-on-fat-_b_6230628.html|website=The Huffington Post|accessdate=9 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Lionel Shriver]], American journalist and author, wrote a column in ''[[Standpoint (magazine)|Standpoint magazine]]'' strongly criticizing the fat acceptance movement. She condemned the movements' demand for respect for fatness in itself, which promotes the same unhealthy lifestyle that she believes killed her brother, who was morbidly obese and died at the age of 55. She also criticized the movements' repeated comparison of sizeism with racism or homophobia, saying that this approach casts obesity in the light of being an unchangeable state.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2009/dec/01/lionel-shriver-my-obese-brother|title=Lionel Shriver: My brother is eating himself to death|last=Shriver|first=Lionel|date=2009-12-01|website=the Guardian|access-date=2016-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Cathy Young]], writing for ''[[The Boston Globe|The]]'' [[The Boston Globe|''Boston Globe'']], claimed that the movement was responsible for normalizing and promoting the acceptance of a controllable disease with clear health complications. While she recognizes the value in fighting against self-loathing, she draws the line at advocating for acceptance of an "unhealthy status quo." She says that by normalizing obesity, the fat acceptance movement leads people to underestimate the associated health hazards, and that the movement has also grown intolerant, exhibiting signs of elitism and treading on personal freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bostonglobe.com/opinion/2013/12/30/fat-acceptance-hazardous-health/1ojfoW46R2elWpHLarA19M/story.html|title=Fat acceptance is hazardous to US health - The Boston Globe|last=Young|first=Cathy|website=BostonGlobe.com|publisher=Boston Globe Media Partners|access-date=2016-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The movement has also been criticized for its treatment of women with eating disorders or who follow diets for health-related reasons, since they are seen as betraying the movement. Lily-Rygh Glen, a writer, musician, and former fat acceptance activist, interviewed multiple women who claimed to be rejected by their peers within the movement and labeled "traitors" when they consciously changed their diets. One female activist admitted to living in fear that her binge eating disorder and consequent body image issues would be discovered. Glen states, "It is precisely because eating disorders are ''not'' openly discussed that many fat people who suffer from bulimia, binge-eating disorder, and pathorexia (defined as disordered appetite, and used to refer to an entire spectrum of disordered eating) feel they aren't welcome in the fat acceptance movement." The author also claimed that while in the process of interviewing and writing the article, which was featured in ''Lost &amp; Found'' magazine, she received wide condemnation from the fat acceptance community, and was labeled fatphobic and healthist.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Glen|first=Lily-Rygh|date=1 January 2008|title=Big Trouble: Are Eating Disorders the Lavender Menace of the Fat Acceptance Movement?|url=https://bitchmedia.org/article/big-trouble|journal=Lost &amp; Found|publisher=Bitch Media|issue=38|doi=|pmid=|access-date=4 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Medical criticism===
The fat acceptance movement has been criticized for not adding value to the debate over human health, with some critics accusing the movement of "promoting a lifestyle that can have dire health consequences".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/Story?id=7823614&amp;page=1#.UA2vrSOVthE|title=Fat Acceptance: 'Young, Fat and Fabulous' Say No to Yo-Yo Diets|publisher=[[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]|accessdate=July 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/22/health/22fblogs.html|title=In the Fatosphere, Big Is In, or at Least Accepted|publisher=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=July 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.cnn.com/2010-01-06/health/fat.acceptance_1_heart-health-metabolic-syndrome-obesity?_s=PM:HEALTH|title=Is the fat acceptance movement bad for our health?|publisher=CNN|accessdate=July 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response, proponents of fat acceptance claim that being fat in and of itself is not a health problem and that long-term weight-loss is unsuccessful in the majority of cases.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Weight Science: Evaluating the Evidence for a Paradigm Shift|url = http://www.nutritionj.com/content/10/1/9/abstract|journal = Nutrition Journal|date = 2011-01-24|issn = 1475-2891|pmc = 3041737|pmid = 21261939|pages = 9|volume = 10|issue = 1|doi = 10.1186/1475-2891-10-9|first = Linda|last = Bacon|first2 = Lucy|last2 = Aphramor}}&lt;/ref&gt; Barry Franklin Ph.D.  director of a cardio rehab facility states: "I don't want to take on any specific organisation but... A social movement that  would suggest health at any size in many respects can be misleading".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Worth|first=Tammy|title=Is the Fat Acceptance Movement Bad for Our Health?|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2010/HEALTH/01/06/fat.acceptance/index.html?_s=PM:HEALTH|publisher=[[CNN]]|accessdate=30 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fat Acceptance campaigners also argue that current approaches constitute [[fat-shaming]] which, rather than leading to weight loss, results in psychological issues like [[eating disorder]]s and more often functions counter-productively, resulting in weight gain.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==See also==
* [[Anti-fat bias]]
* [[Fat tax]]
* [[Hanne Blank]]
* [[Obesity paradox]]
* [[Obesophobia]]
* [[Plus size model]]
* [[Sizeism]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Other publications===

* {{cite web|authorlink=Juliet Samuel|title=Fat Pride World Wide: The growing movement for avoirdupois acceptance|work=[[Reason Magazine]]|publisher=[[Reason Foundation]]|date=October 23, 2007|url=http://www.reason.com/news/show/123151.html|accessdate=2009-08-17}}
* (A) Medical Practitioners' Guide to Benefits of Adapting Environments for the Obese, Michigan State University study by Angela Berg MD and Joyce Burke MD, [http://www.msu.edu/user/burkejoy/frame_b.htm MSU.edu]

==External links==
* [https://ulir.ul.ie/bitstream/handle/10344/3628/Cooper_2008_fat.pdf What's Fat Activism?] History of fat activism from a UK perspective.
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
* {{Dmoz|Society/Issues/Health/Body_Image/Fat_Acceptance|Fat Acceptance}}
{{Prone to spam|date=November 2012}}
{{Z148}}&lt;!--     {{No more links}}

       Please be cautious adding more external links.

Wikipedia is not a collection of links and should not be used for advertising.

     Excessive or inappropriate links will be removed.

 See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.

If there are already suitable links, propose additions or replacements on
the article's talk page, or submit your link to the relevant category at
the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) and link there using {{Dmoz}}.

--&gt;

{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fat Acceptance Movement}}
[[Category:Fat acceptance movement| ]]
[[Category:Obesity]]
[[Category:Identity politics]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>