<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051102205929|27189318" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="53277" pageid="53277" ns="0" title="Fat acceptance movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-04T13:29:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''fat acceptance movement''', also referred to as the '''fat liberation movement''', is a grass-roots effort to change societal attitudes about people who are fat. The movement, generally accepted as having started in 1969, has gained steam since the [[1980s]] and [[1990s]], and now includes several activist organizations, publications and conferences.

== History == 
In 1969, William Fabrey founded the National Association to Aid Fat Americans, later renamed the National Association to Advance Fat Acceptance ([[NAAFA]]). A few years later in Los Angeles, Sara Fishman (then going by Aldebaran) and Judy Freespirit, founders of a local NAAFA chapter, separated from NAAFA in 1973 to form their own radical activism group, the Fat Underground. Four years later, Fishman moved to New Haven where she, along with Karen Scott-Jones, founded the New Haven Fat Liberation Front, an organization similar to the Fat Underground in its radical (for the time) actions. 

Their writings, along with those of others, were published to a wide audience for the first time in 1983, with the release of ''Shadow on a Tightrope''.

After a relative lull in the mid-[[1980s]] to early-[[1990s]], the independent [[zine]] community began addressing fat liberation again, with zines like [[Marilyn Wann]]'s ''Fat!So?'' beginning in [[1993]], Nomy Lamm's [[I'm So Fucking Beautiful]], and the collectively produced 'zine "[http://www.sizequeenzine.org/order.html FaT GiRL -- the 'zine for fat dykes and the women who want them.]" More Recently, Sabrina Darling has collaborated with other members of the new generation of fat liberation to release the zine [[Two By Four]], Krissy Durden has produced the zine Figure 8 since 2001 and Max Airborne and Cherry Midnight have produced "[http://www.sizequeenzine.org Size Queen: For Queen-size Queers and Our Loyal Subjects.]" In addition to zines, there has recently been a steady stream of books written on the subject including Wann's book of the same title as her zine (1998), [[Sondra Solovay]]'s "Tipping the Scales of Justice: Fighting Weight-Based Discrimination" (2000), a collection of short stories by fat people (''What Are You Looking At?'' 2003) and Paul Campos's examination of the health fallacies regarding fatness (''The Obesity Myth'' 2004). In addition, there is an emerging body of fat theory developing in academia.

[http://www.susanstinson.net Susan Stinson's] novels and poetry such as Belly Songs (1993), Fat Girl Dances with Rocks (1994), Martha Moody (1995) and Venus of Chalk (2004), have integrated the insights of fat liberation into literature.   

Recently, fat performance art has made a positive and fun impact in the fight against sizeism. Groups like The Padded Lillies, Big Burlesque and the Fat Bottom Revue and [[radical cheerleading]] groups like F.A.T.A.S.S pdx, The Bod Squad have received a lot of attention.

Finally and most recently, there has been a flourishing of national conferences devoted to the subject of fat activism, including '''NOLOSE''' in New Jersey, the conference of the former National Organization of Lesbians of SizE (now just NOLOSE); '''NAAFA's''' annual convention held alternately on the west and east coasts; and the largest conference, Stacy Bias's '''FatGirl Speaks''' in Portland, Oregon.

== Background ==
Fat acceptance covers several fronts but generally can be described as attempting to change societal, internal, and medical attitudes about fat people.

Societal: The movement argues that fat people are targets of [[hatred]] and [[discrimination]], with women in particular subject to more social pressure. Hatred is seen in multiple places including media outlets, where fat people are often ridiculed or held up as objects of pity. Discrimination, it is argued, comes in the form of lack of equal accessibility to transportation and employment.

Internal: The movement also argues that people of all shapes and sizes should accept themselves as they are, at any size. It promotes "[[health at any size]]," which places one's mental and physical health before physical appearance and size.

Medical: Through the works of authors such as [[Paul Campos]] and Sandy Swzarc, the fat acceptance movement has arguably improved its standing on health at any size. The movement's stance is that doctors should treat the problems of fat people independent of weight.

The movement faces challenges internally as well. Organizations such as the National Association to Advance Fat Acceptance (NAAFA) and the [[International Size Acceptance Association]] (ISAA) are small, numbers-wise, and people interested in the movement tend to be clustered in larger cities - and spread across medium- to small-sized web communities. In addition, NAAFA's history has been entangled with [[Dimensions Magazine]], a highly visible website for men who have sexual preferences for fat women. NAAFA has recently changed leadership in order to cut these ties, and has made several policy changes (including taking a stance against feederism, the practice of weight gain for sexual pleasure) which were applauded in the fat community. The role of sites such as Dimensions in the movement is a contested issue.

Fat acceptance is a social acceptance issue and has ties and common ground with the [[feminist movement]] and is associated with broader civil rights movements.

== Visible People in Fat Acceptance ==
*[[Marilyn Wann]], author of ''FAT!SO?'' and Activism Chair of NAAFA.
*[[Nomy Lamm]], performance artist and writer of ''I'm So Fucking Beautiful.''
*[[Paul Campos]], author of books such as ''The Obesity Myth.''
*[[Paul McAleer]], author of Big Fat Blog.
*[[Daniel Pinkwater]], author of The Afterlife Diet and other books
*Sandy Szwarc, author of articles challenging widely-held beliefs on fat and health[http://www2.techcentralstation.com/1051/searchauthor.jsp?Bioid=BIOSZWARCSANDY]
*Allen Steadham, President of ISAA.
*Sondra Solovay, weight discrimination lawyer and author of the book "Tipping the Scales of Justice: Fighting Weight-Based Discrimination"
*Stacy Bias, founder of FatGirl Speaks [Portland, ORE]
*Heather MacAllister, founder of Big Burlesque and the Fat Bottom Review

==External links==
*[http://www.nolose.org/ NOLOSE]
*[http://www.fatgirlspeaks.com/ FatGirl Speaks]
*[http://www.naafa.org/ National Association to Advance Fat Acceptance]
*[http://www.size-acceptance.org/ International Size Acceptance Association]
*[http://www.plususa.com/ Plus USA Woman Convention and Pageant]
*[http://www.bigfatblog.com/ Big Fat Blog, the fat acceptance weblog]
*[http://www.rundnaund.ch/ Rund, na und?? Swiss fat acceptance site]
*[http://www.allegrofortissimo.com/ Allegro Fortissimo French fat acceptance site]
*[http://www.sizenet.com/ SizeNet, A European pro-information site for size acceptance and self esteem]
*[http://www.yourplussizepregnancy.com/ Your Plus-Size Pregnancy: a friendly and supportive site for plus-size pregnant women]
[[Category:Obesity]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[fr:Acceptation des gros]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>