<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041111182457|7359076" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="92656" pageid="92656" ns="0" title="Same-sex marriage"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-11T22:22:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{SSM}}
'''Same-sex marriage''' (also called '''gay marriage''', '''marriage equality''', and&amp;mdash;less frequently&amp;mdash;'''homosexual marriage''') is [[marriage]] between partners of the same [[gender]]. 

For [[#Other forms of same-sex partnership|other forms of same-sex unions]] that are different from marriages, see the articles linked in that section.

Currently, same-sex marriages are legal in only a few countries around the world. (See reference table to the right). In [[Belgium]] and the [[Netherlands]], it is fully legal. In [[Canada]] and the [[United States]], the degree of legality of same-sex marriage/civil union varies between provinces or states. All other countries do not recognize same-sex marriages as legally valid, nor do they allow them to occur. In the United States, the debate over whether or not to make same sex marriages legally binding remains one of the most polarizing and divisive political debates of the early [[21st century]] and it is discussed with great passion all over the world. 

During 2004, 13 US States amended their constitutions to define marriage as being only between one man and one woman.  Some people, including many [[gay rights]] advocates, view restrictions such as these as being an example of the [[tyranny of the majority]] in action.

==Controversy==

The [[moral]] legitimacy of marriage between two people of the same sex hinges on how the authoritative definition of [[marriage]] is derived. If marriage is to have a religious foundation, the interpretation of religious texts and traditions will be key; if marriage is a [[social institution]] or even a purely economic coupling, pragmatic arguments will have more force, though moral issues will no doubt still arise. [[Gay rights]] advocates assert that marriage is a right which should not be limited to opposite-sex couples. Their opponents assert that same-sex marriage cannot be allowed on moral and/or religious grounds, or on the grounds that it will lead to a breakdown of [[society]].

The debate is often perceived as being same sex marriage advocates vs. religious (e.g. fundamentalist) or moral opponents. However, corporations and other fiscally concerned parties sometimes oppose same-sex marriages not on any religious or moral grounds but instead with the aim of preserving the status quo to avoid extending benefits, such as insurance coverage, to the families (i.e. any married partners) of homosexual employees. Those in favour of same-sex marriage, however, argue that gays and lesbians contribute as much as straight people to the funding for private and public family coverage even when they have no access to it.

==Competing definitions of "marriage"==

===Marriage===

Nearly all people at all times have defined "marriage" in such a way that at least one male and one female were involved. Some societies have from ancient times permitted a man to have multiple wives, but those wives had congress only with the man -- not each other. But some rare variations have appeared such as [[polyandry]] (one woman with multiple husbands) and "[[group marriage]]".

Though religions will perform marriages based on their own doctrinal definitions, these may or may not be recognized by the government depending on local laws. Governments will often provide opportunity for state-sanctioned legal marriages that are entirely secular and without religious influence (commonly called 'civil marriages'). They may or may not be recognized by certain religions. Some countries require all marriages to be civil, and expect the religious ceremony to occur at some later time. Generally, it is the government's definition of marriage that the same-sex marriage debate centers around. See [[marriage]].

The definition of ''[[marriage]]'' proposed by [[gay rights]] [[Advocacy|advocates]] seeks to include both homosexual and heterosexual relationships by recognizing only the common attributes between them. They define marriage to be:
:A socially sanctioned, voluntary, committed, monogamous, [[law|legal]]ly contracted union, of two adult people, which the [[government]] and/or [[society]] recognizes by conferring certain [[right]]s, privileges and [[responsibility|responsibilities]], such as finances, taxes, and inheritance, child-raising, [[adoption]], visitation, and [[medicine|medical]] decision-making. 

For same-sex marriage proponents, the above achieves equalization of the male-male, female-female, and male-female relationship. Being able to marry whomever they choose is seen as a civil right that should not be abridged by the government.

Some countries and states/provinces have judicial rulings that set precedence for the above definition. However, popular majorities continue to assert that the traditional concept of marriage cannot exist outside of a heterosexual relationship. To them, the male-female relationship has unique capacities and qualities that marriage was meant to recognize and foster that are not adequately acknowledged by the above definition. 

Defenders of traditional marriage argue that only a heterosexual union can provide the procreative foundation of the family unit that has been a chief social building block of civilization. They argue that the definition proposed by same-gender marriage advocates changes the social importance of marriage from [[Sexual morality|morality]] to [[custom]]. As any customary relationship may be considered &amp;quot;marriage&amp;quot some argue that this then leads to undue legislative burden and an affront to the social value and responsibility of parenting your own children. 

Some same-sex marriage proponents, such as [[Andrew Sullivan]], argue that their definition retains enough moral underpinning to support the familial role marriage plays in society even though they are unable to directly parent children between them. Others argue that marriage no longer retains a procreative interest to the government, and that the other measures should replace marriage in ensuring parental responsibility.

Historic alterations in the customs and protocols of marriage give rise to the argument that marriage is dynamic and same-gender acceptance is the latest evolution of marriage. Some societies have from ancient times permitted spouses to have multiple concurrent marriages while many societies discourage this practice today. Having more than one marriage at the same time is called [[polygamy]] for men and [[polyandry]] for women. Marriages that involve more than two people at one time in a single act of matrimony are considered to be a "[[group marriage]]" and are even more rare.

There have been many ritual homosexual unions practiced historically that provide many of the same benefits entitled traditionally to marriages. Some cultures have considered a set of strictly defined and regulated homosexual qualities to denote a gender that trancended both male and female. As a third state of gender they were allowed to marry men or women. Some people in the position to write the law for their country indulged themselves in calling some of their same-gender relationships a marriage, though they assumed no familial attachment. Calling a heterosexual union the same legal term as a homosexual union for a whole state or society is only a recent occurrence.

===Same-sex===

In the context of same-sex marriages, and throughout this article, ''same-sex'' refers to two people of the same [[sex|gender]]. In this context, ''same-sex'' is not synonymous with ''[[gay]],'' ''[[lesbian]],'' or ''[[homosexual]],'' nor with ''[[bisexual]],'' ''[[transgender]]ed'' or ''[[transsexual]],'' but "same-sex marriage" may, depending on the couple and the jurisdiction, refer to marriages between two adults from any of those groups. In nearly all jurisdictions, unrelated and consenting men and women can marry each other, while two men or two women cannot do so.

In this article, the inclusive term "same-sex marriage" is used throughout. Where necessary for clarity, the terms "gay", "lesbian", "bisexual," and "transsexual" are used (there are a number of reasons for this; please see the [[talk:same-sex marriage|talk page]] for more details).

==History of same-sex unions==

===The east===

''For detailed information, see [[Homosexuality in Japan]], [[Homosexuality in China]], [[History of homosexuality]].''

Same-gender romantic love or sexual desire has been recorded from ancient times in the east. Such desire often took the form of same-sex unions, usually between men, and often included some difference in age (there is far less information available on relationships among women in ancient times. There are a number of possible reasons for this: an attitude that women were not important enough to write about; or that same-sex attraction between women was not valued as it was between men; or that women were not afforded equal status with men, so that, while men were free to pursue sexual and romantic pleasure both within and without marriage, women often were not).

In [[China]], especially in the southern province of [[Fujian]] where male love was especially cultivated, men would marry youths in elaborate ceremonies. The marriages would last a number of years, at the end of which the elder partner would help the younger find a (female) wife and settle down to raise a family.

===The west===

There is a long history of same-sex unions in the western world.
That many early western societies tolerated, and even celebrated, same sex relationships is well-known. Evidence of same-sex '''marriage''', however, is less clear, but there exists some evidence, often controversial, of same-sex marriages in [[ancient]] [[Rome]] and [[Greece]], and even in [[medieval]] [[Europe]]. Same-sex unions have also been recorded among Native Americans and Africans.

In ancient Rome, for example, the Emperor [[Nero]] is reported to have married, at different times, two other men in wedding ceremonies. Other Roman [[Emperor]]s are reported to have done the same thing. The increasing influence of [[Christianity]], which promoted marriage for procreative purposes, is linked with the increasing intolerance of homosexuality in Rome.

Same-sex marriage has been documented in many societies that were not subject to [[Christian]] influence. In North America, among the [[Native American]] societies, it has taken the form of [[two-spirit]]-type relationships, in which some members of the tribe, from an early age, heed a calling to take on female gender with all its responsibilities. They are prized as wives by the other men in the tribe, who enter into formal marriages with these [[two-spirit]] men. They are also respected as being especially powerful shamans.

In [[Africa]], among the [[Azande]] of the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congo]], men would marry youths for whom they had to pay a bride-price to the father. These marriages likewise were understood to be of a temporary nature.

Finally, in [[Europe]] during [[Hellenic]] times, [[pederasty| pederastic]] relationships between [[Hellenic Greece|Greek]] men (''[[erastes]]'') and youths (''[[eromenos]]'') who had come of age were analogous to marriage in several aspects. The age of the youth was similar to the age at which women married (the mid-teens), and the relationship could only be undertaken with the consent of the father. This consent, just as in the case of a daughter's marriage, was contingent on the suitor's social standing. The relationship, just like a marriage, consisted of very specific social and religious responsibilities, and also had an erotic component.

==Modern same-sex civil marriage==

Same-sex civil marriages currently are legally recognized nationwide only in the [[Netherlands]] and [[Belgium]]. 

In [[Canada|Canadian]], court rulings in the provinces of [[Ontario]], [[British Columbia]], [[Quebec]], [[Manitoba]], [[Nova Scotia]], and [[Saskatchewan]], as well as the [[Yukon | Yukon Territory]], have found the prohibition of same-sex marriage to be unconstitutional, thus legalizing it in those jurisdictions. The Canadian [[federal]] government has drafted amendments to the Canadian ''Marriage Act'' that would legalize same-sex marriage nationally. These amendments have been referred to the [[Supreme Court of Canada]] to determine whether they are consistent with the equality provisions of the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]]. 

The [[Sweden|Swedish]] government is similarly preparing legislation to legalize same-sex marriage across the country [http://www.365gay.com/newscon04/03/030304swedenMarr.htm]. 

Shortly after his election in June 2004 the [[Spain|Spanish]] Prime Minister confirmed his intention to push for legalization of same-sex marriage [http://www.dailynews.com/Stories/0,1413,200~20954~2151089,00.html]. On [[1 October]] [[ 2004]], the [[Spain|Spanish]] Government approved a bill to legalise same-sex marriage. The bill now needs parliamentary approval, and is expected to come into force in 2005. For more information see ''[[Same-sex marriage in Spain]]

Same-sex marriage is legal in the [[United States|US]] state of [[Massachusetts]], following a [[November 2003]] court ruling. The Superior Court of Washington State has also declared banning same-sex marriage to be unconstitutional and the case, [[Andersen v. Sims]], is currently before the state Supreme Court in Olympia. [http://www.metrokc.gov/kcsc/docs/Andersen%20v.%20Sims.pdf] Several local government bodies in the [[United States]] are also performing same-sex marriages, on various degrees of legal footing. 

Recently, the term "same-sex marriage" has been displacing "gay marriage", the term being perceived as less value-laden for the union of two partners of the same sex and also being more inclusive of [[bisexuality|bisexuals]] and [[transsexual]] people - who in some states of the United States and in other countries, are not allowed to change their assigned gender on their birth certificates following [[sex reassignment surgery]].

===Other forms of same-sex partnership===

The movement towards the legal recognition of same-sex marriages has resulted in changes in the law in many jurisdictions, though the extent of the changes have varied:

* [[Civil union]]s provide most of the rights and responsibilities of same-sex marriage, but use a different name for the arrangement. They exist in several European countries ([[Denmark]], [[Finland]], [[France]], [[Germany]], [[Iceland]], [[Norway]], [[Sweden]], and [[Switzerland]]) as well as in the [[U.S. state]] of [[Vermont]], the Canadian provinces of [[Quebec]] and [[Nova Scotia]], and the city of [[Buenos Aires]], [[Argentina]].
* [[Domestic partnership]]s or registered partnerships provide varying degrees of privileges and responsibilities, usually far fewer than those found in civil unions. Their purpose is not limited to same-sex arrangements and they exist in many jurisdictions.

Even in jurisdictions where they are not legally recognized, many [[gay]] and [[lesbian]] couples choose to have [[wedding]]s (also called "commitment ceremonies" in this context) to celebrate and affirm their relationship, fulfilling the social aspect of a marriage. Such ceremonies have no legal validity, however, and as such do not deal with issues such as inheritance, property rights or social security. 

Some writers have advanced the idea that the term "marriage" should be restricted to a religious context and that state and federal governments should not be involved in a religious rite. Some regard this as a governmental intrusion into religion; they believe that all statutes involving domestic contracts should replace the word "marriage" with "domestic partnership" and thus bypass the controversy of gender. This would then allow a domestic contract between any two individuals who have attained their majority.

==Legal recognition of same-sex marriage==

In the late [[20th century|20th]] and early [[21st century|21st]] centuries, there has been a growing movement in a number of countries to regard marriage as a right which should be extended to same-sex couples. Legal recognition of a marital union opens up a wide range of entitlements, including social security, taxation, inheritance and other benefits unavailable to couples unmarried in the eyes of the law. Restricting legal recognition to opposite-sex couples excludes same-sex couples from gaining legal access to these benefits, and while opposite-sex unmarried couples without other legal impediments have the option of marrying in law and so gaining access to these rights, that option is unavailable to same-sex couples. Similarly, though certain rights extending from marriage can be replicated by legal means (for example, by drawing up contracts), many cannot; thus, despite the presence of legal contracts, same-sex couples may still face insecurity in areas such as inheritance, hospital visitation and immigration. Lack of legal recognition also makes it more difficult for same-sex couples to [[adoption|adopt children]].

Canada and several other countries recognize same-sex unions as "marriage" on a legal par with opposite-sex marriage, while the [[United States]] does not. (See [[Defense of Marriage Act]].)

On Feb. 24, 2004 [[George W. Bush|President George W. Bush]] called for a [[Federal Marriage Amendment|Constitutional Amendment]] to prohibit same-sex marriages at the federal level.

Use of the term Same-Sex "marriage" (versus "unions") is considered a key question in the United States for several reasons, but in terms of strict legal interpretation, previous Supreme Court rulings overturned laws against "[[crime against nature|crimes against nature]]" based on first an idea that such acts could not be prohibited in marriage. Using this precedent, they used reference to the idea of equal rights and that things not prohibited to some classes of people (married people) could not be prohibited from non-married people. In [[Loving v. Virginia]], this line of argument to overturn sodomy laws was rejected. Some think that if same sex marriage were granted as a good concept by the courts, this would clearly overturn all sodomy laws once and for all.

As of November 11th, 2004 the Canadian federal government's immigration department considers same-sex marriages valid for the purposes of sponsoring a spouse to immigrate.  See: http://www.cic.gc.ca/english/sponsor/index.html

''See also [[Same-sex marriage in Canada]]''

==Opponents of same-sex marriage==

Some opponents object to same-sex marriage on [[religion and homosexuality|religious grounds]], arguing that extending marriage to same-sex couples undercuts the conventional meaning of marriage in various traditions, does not fulfill any procreational role, or sanctions a partnership centered around "abhorrent" or "immoral" sexual acts. In countries with [[monogamous]] marriages only, some opponents also claim that allowing same-sex marriage will blur other common law precedents and lead to the legalization of [[polyamory|polyamorous]] marriage, or to marriage between family members (incest), or to marriages of convenience contracted for tax or other reasons. Some object on the grounds that same-sex couples should not be allowed to have or adopt children, and that same-sex marriage would make those adoptions easier. Others simply do not recognize any pressing need for same-sex marriages.

A fundamental concern is that its legalization will lead to a direct attack via lawsuits against traditional churches to force those churches to perform marriage ceremonies that the church does not approve of. This is a realistic fear only in jurisdictions which fail to distinguish between civil and religious marriages, or have established religions. Additionally, in litigious societies, there are concerns about bankrupting established churches through these types of lawsuits. 

Some [[libertarianism|libertarians]] object to same-sex marriage because they are opposed to any form of state-sanctioned marriage, including opposite-sex unions. They are not necessarily opposed to the idea of a same-sex wedding itself, only that the government should not have any role in the event, nor for that matter should government approval be sought for opposite-sex marriages. 

Some other people object to same-sex marriage on the grounds that the purpose of marriage is a procreative partnership and that the same-sex partnership is inherently sterile. Some who hold this view see marriage as the social codification of an evolved long-term mating strategy, with economic and legal benefits to facilitate family growth and stability. These people generally do not carry over their objections to sterile heterosexual couples, often due to privacy concerns.

Many other people, while tolerant towards the sexual behaviour of others, see no reason to alter their society or government's traditional attitudes towards marriage and family.

==Proponents of same-sex marriage==
[[Image:Civil marriage is a civil right.JPG|right|thumb|250px|Some churches, such as the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]], advocate marriage rights for gays as well as straights.]]
Proponents point out that traditional concepts of marriage have already given way to liberalization in other areas, such as the availability of no-fault [[divorce]] and the elimination of [[miscegenation|anti-miscegenation laws]]. They also suggest that many people in modern societies no longer subscribe to the religious beliefs which inform traditional limits upon marriage, and no longer wish these beliefs to constitute the law, and that their laws should be protected from religion under the principle of [[separation of church and state]]. In fact, there are some religions that celebrate same-sex weddings or commitment ceremonies already. In Canada, for example, the [[United Church of Canada]], the country's largest [[Protestant]] denomination, has supported for the legalization of same-sex marriage. Same-sex marriages are also performed in [[Unitarian]] churches, some Reform [[synagogues]], [[Quaker]] ([[Friends General Conference]]) congregations, and by the [[Metropolitan Community Church]].

In the [[United States]], proponents of equal marriage rights for same-sex couples point out that there are over 1,049 federal laws in which marital status is a factor. A legal denial of rights or benefits afforded to others, they say, directly contradicts the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th Amendment of the US Constitution]] which provides for [[equal protection]] and substantive [[due process]] under the law, meaning that rights conferred to one person cannot be denied to another. In the 2003 case before the Supreme Court titled ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'', the court held that intimate consensual sexual conduct was part of the liberty protected by substantive due process under the Fourteenth Amendment. Many proponents of same-sex marriage have noted that this ruling paves the way for a subsequent decision invalidating state laws prohibiting same-sex marriage. 

In June 2003, the British Government published what was described as a consultation document for [[England]] and [[Wales]]: "Civil Partnership - a framework for the legal recognition of same-sex couples" which describes a system of official registration of same-sex partnerships.

On 30 September 2003, the Scottish Executive published a consultation paper concerning a similar scheme for [[Scotland]].

King [[Norodom Sihanouk]] of [[Cambodia]] announced in [[February 2004]] that he believed his country ought to legalize same-sex marriage.

In [[May 2004]], the largest opposition party in [[France]], the [[French Socialist Party]], announced its support for same-sex marriage. A poll by [[ELLE]] found that 64% of France supports same-sex marriage. [http://www.liberation.fr/page.php?Article=204455&amp;AG]

Some [[conservatism|conservative]] proponents of equal marriage also say that the institution of marriage would be strengthened by making it available to more people, and argue further that same-sex marriage would encourage gays and lesbians to settle down with one partner and raise families.

==Publicly noted Same-Sex unions==
===[[2004]]===

* [[September 10]] - [[Toronto]],[[Canada]] - [[Uzi Even]], former Israeli [[Knesset]] member and Amit Kama, legal civil marriage

* [[August 1]] - [[Boston]],[[Massachussets]] - [[Cheryl Jacques]], former Mass. State Senator and gay rights activist and Jennifer Chrisler, legal marriage

* [[April 1]] - [[Michael Hendricks and René Leboeuf]], first same-sex couple to marry in Quebec

* [[March 8]] - [[San Francisco]],[[California]] - [[Jackie Goldberg]], State Assemblywoman and Sharon Sticker, later voided by California Supreme Court

* [[February 26]] - [[San Francisco]],[[California]] - [[Rosie O'Donnell]], Ex-TV Host and Kelli Carpenter, later voided by California Supreme Court

* [[February 12]] - [[San Francisco]],[[California]] - [[Del Martin and Phyllis Lyon]], life-long gay activists, later voided by California Supreme Court

===[[2003]]===

* [[November 15]] - [[British Columbia]],[[Canada]] - [[Ted Nebbeling]] former BC Cabinet Minister and Jan Holmberg, legal civil marriage

* [[September 20]] - [[Malibu]],[[California]] - [[Melissa Etheridge]], Grammy-award winning singer and actress Tammy Lynn Michaels, private union ceremony

===[[2002]]===

* [[January 4]] - [[Stockholm]],[[Sweden]] - [[Per-Kristian Foss]], [[Norway|Norwegian]] Finance minister (2001-) and Jan Erik Knarbakk, Norwegian legal union at the Norwegian Embassy

===[[1989]]===

* [[October 1]] - [[Copenhagen]] [[Denmark]] - [[Axel Axgil]] and [[Eigil Axgil]], gay rights campaigners and business-men, legal civil union

==Terminology==
The term "mixed marriage" usually does not refer to marriage of two persons with the same sexual orientation, but to marriage of two persons of different [[religion]]s, [[culture]]s or [[race]]s.

==See also==	 
* [[Religion and homosexuality]]
* [[Marriage#Rights_and_obligations|Marriage rights and obligations]]	 
* [[Log Cabin Republicans]]	 
* [[Special rights]]

==Bibliography==
*&lt;i&gt;Why Marriage?: The History Shaping Today's Debate Over Gay Equality&lt;/i&gt; by George Chauncey 
(Basic Books, 2004).	 
*''Marriage Under Fire: Why We Must Win This Battle'' by Dr. James Dobson (Multnomah, 2004)

==External links==	 
*[http://search.looksmart.com/p/browse/us1/us317836/us317916/us65573/us63782/us541243/us539808 LookSmart - Same-Sex Marriages]	 
*[http://dmoz.org/Society/Gay,_Lesbian,_and_Bisexual/Law/Marriage_and_Domestic_Partnership/ Open Directory Project - GLB Marriage and Domestic Partnership]	 
*[http://dir.yahoo.com/Society_and_Culture/Cultures_and_Groups/Lesbians__Gays__and_Bisexuals/Relationships/Marriage_and_Domestic_Partnership/ Yahoo! - Gay and Lesbian Marriage and Domestic Partnership]	 
*[http://www.hrc.org/Content/ContentGroups/Issues1/Marriage/FAQ_Goodridge.htm Frequently Asked Questions: Goodridge et al. v. The Department of Public Health] by the [[Human Rights Campaign]]	 *[http://www.metrokc.gov/kcsc/docs/Andersen%20v.%20Sims.pdf The August decision from the Superior Court in Washington State legalizing same-sex marriage.]	 
*[http://glad.org/marriage Same-Sex Marriage in Massachusetts] by [http://glad.org Gay &amp;amp; Lesbian Advocates and Defenders]	 
*[http://SupportEquality.org Defending Same-Sex Marriage Rights in Massachusetts]	 
*[http://www.stonewall.org.uk/stonewall/current_campaigns/partnership.html Stonewall campaign in the UK for links to government papers in PDF format]	 
		 
[[Category:Same-sex marriage]]	 
[[Category:Marriage]]	 
		 
&lt;!-- Interlanguage links --&gt;	 
[[es:Matrimonio del mismo sexo]]	 
[[fr:Mariage homosexuel]] 	 
[[zh:&amp;#21516;&amp;#24615;&amp;#23130;&amp;#23035;]]	 
[[nl:homohuwelijk]]
[[ja:&amp;#21516;&amp;#24615;&amp;#32080;&amp;#23130;]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>