<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114192858|171495711" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="92656" pageid="92656" ns="0" title="Same-sex marriage"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T19:30:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Wedded couple on Taiwan Pride 2006.jpg|right|thumb|One of four newly wedded same-sex couples in a public wedding at [[Taiwan Pride]] 2006.]]
{{SSM}}
'''Same-sex marriage''' is a term for a [[government]]ally, [[social]]ly, or [[religion|religiously]] recognized [[marriage]] in which two people of the same sex live together as a family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/same-sex%20marriage
   |title      = ''same-sex marriage'' defined
   |publisher  = WordNet - Princeton University
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other terms for this type of relationship include "gay marriage", "gender-neutral marriage," "equal marriage," "lesbian marriage," "same-sex civil marriage", "marriage equality", "homosexual marriage," "single-sex marriage", "civil partnership", "same-gender marriage" or just simply "marriage".

== Debates over terminology ==
Proponents of same-sex marriage often use the term "equal marriage" to stress that they seek equality as opposed to special rights;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
   |url        = http://www.samesexmarriage.ca/
   |title      = Equal Marriage for Same-Sex Couples
   |publisher  = Kevin Bourassa and Joe Varnell
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; the term "equal marriage" has also been used by feminists to describe any marriage, regardless of the sex of the partners, in which the partners have equal status within the marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://www.now.org/issues/lgbi/marr-rep.html
   |title      = Same-Sex Marriage is a Feminist Issue
   |publisher  = National Organization for Women
   |date       = 17 May 2004
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Opponents argue that equating same-sex and opposite-sex marriage changes the meaning of marriage and its traditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://atheism.about.com/od/gaymarriage/a/MarriageSacred.htm
   |title      = Arguments Against Gay Marriage: Marriage is a Sacred Religious Sacrament
   |publisher  = About.com
   |author     = Austin Cline
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some opponents use the term "homosexual marriage", and surveys have suggested that the word "homosexual" is more stigmatizing than the word "gay".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid17177.asp
   |title      = New Poll: Americans Ambivalent About Homosexuality
   |publisher  = the Advocate
   |date       = 24 May 2005 
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some publications that oppose same-sex marriage put the word marriage in [[scare quotes]] when referring to it. Notable publications that practice this are ''[[The Washington Times]]'' and ''[[LifeSite]]''. [[Cliff Kincaid]], a writer for the American conservative-based media watchdog group [[Accuracy in Media]], agrees with this method arguing that "marriage" is a word that same-sex couples merely want to apply to themselves, but have no legal ability to do so in most states.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://www.aim.org/media_monitor/A466_0_2_0_C/
   |title      = Honest Versus Slanted Journalism
   |publisher  = Accuracy In Media
   |author     = Kincaid, Cliff
   |date       = 26 Feb 2004
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Same-sex marriage supporters argue that it is editorializing and implying inferiority, and point out that the quotes are even used when referring to same-sex marriages in locations where it is legal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://atheism.about.com/b/a/087136.htm
   |title      = Washington Times Dismisses Gay “Marriages”
   |publisher  = About.com
   |author     = Austin Cline
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have suggested reserving the word "marriage" for religious contexts, and in civil and legal contexts using a uniform concept of [[civil unions]]. [[Harvard Law School|Harvard Law]] professor [[Alan Dershowitz]], for instance, wrote that such an arrangement would "strengthen the wall of separation between church and state by placing a sacred institution entirely in the hands of the church while placing a secular institution under state control".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://www.rossde.com/editorials/Dershowitz_marriage.html
   |title      = Government Should Quit the Marriage Business
   |publisher  = Los Angeles Times
   |author     = Dershowitz, Alan M.
   |date       = 3 Dec 2003
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Conservative critics like ''[[National Review]]'s'' [[Jennifer Morse]] contend that the conflation of marriage with contractual agreements is itself a threat to marriage that "has undermined more heterosexual marriages than anything, with the possible exception of adultery".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://www.nationalreview.com/comment/morse200405200926.asp
   |title      = ''Not'' a Social Contract
   |publisher  = National Review
   |author     = Morse, Jennifer Roback
   |date       = 20 May 2004 
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, in the case of one state in which same-sex marriages are recognized, Massachusetts, there is a long history of marriage being regarded as purely a civil institution, as illustrated in the Reverend [[William Bradford]]'s history &lt;em&gt;[[Of Plymouth Plantation]]&lt;/em&gt;:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
May 12 was the first marriage in this place [i.e., Plymouth] which, according to the laudable custom of the Low Countries, in which they had lived, was thought most requisite to be performed by the magistrate, as being a civil thing, upon which many questions about inheritances do depend, with other things most proper to their cognizance and most consonant to the Scriptures (Ruth iv) and nowhere found in the Gospel to be laid on the ministers as a part of their office. 
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite 
   |url        = http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1650bradford.html#New%20governor,%20first%20marriage
   |title      = Of Plymouth Plantation
   |author     = Bradford, William
   |accessdate = 2007-08-29
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== History ==
{{main|History of same-sex unions}}

== Current status ==
{{main|Status of same-sex marriage}}
[[Image:Gay March celebrating 2005 Pride Day and Same-Sex Marriage Law in Spain.jpg|left|thumb|frame|A [[gay pride parade|Pride March]] in [[2005]], celebrating the legalization of [[same-sex marriage in Spain]]]]
Full marriage is presently available to same-sex couples in seven jurisdictions. [[Same-sex marriage in the Netherlands|The Netherlands]] was the first country to allow same-sex marriage in 2001. Same-sex marriages are also recognized in [[Same-sex marriage in Belgium|Belgium]], [[Same-sex marriage in Canada|Canada]], [[Same-sex marriage in South Africa|South Africa]], [[Same-sex marriage in Spain|Spain]], and the [[U.S. state]] of [[Same-sex marriage in Massachusetts|Massachusetts]] and in dispute in [[Iowa]] as of early September 2007 where a district court judge issued a stay of his ruling that Iowa's ban on gay marriage was unconstitutional. Two male college students became the first same-sex couple to marry in Iowa before Judge Robert Hanson, in Polk County District Court, filed an order to delay the issuing of any more marriage licenses to same-sex couples in Iowa pending further review of the district court's ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
   |url        = http://www.cnn.com/2007/US/law/08/30/iowa.samesexmarriage/index.html?eref=onion
   |title      = Iowa court rules same-sex couples can marry.
   |date       = 30 Aug 2007
   |accessdate = 2007-08-30
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;   [[Rhode Island]] and [[New Mexico]]  residents are also permitted to marry in Massachusetts, for same-sex marriages performed within Massachusetts. On August 31, 2007, [[Iowa]] [[Judge]] [[Robert Hanson]] allowed gay weddings, annulling a [[law]] allowing [[marriage]] only between men and women, however, Hanson issued a stay on the ruling by request of the county attorney until the appeal is resolved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/US/08/31/iowa.samesex.ap/index.html|title=Couple weds before same-sex marriages halted|publisher=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Only [[Massachusetts]] and [[Iowa]] allow gay marriages while 9 others - including [[New Jersey]], [[New Hampshire]], [[Connecticut]] and [[Vermont]] - offer [[civil]] unions which grant [[gay]] couples the same [[legal]] rights as  in [[heterosexual]] marriages.
  
Marriage equality has also been passed in the California state legislature. The bill would redefine marriage as "a civil contract between two persons," but would retain the right of religious institutions to refuse to sanction the unions. A similar bill passed in 2005 and met a veto by Gov. [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]].  Gov. Schwarzenegger is expected to veto the bill again.  Similarly a gay marriage bill has passed in the New York state assembly in 2007, strongly supported by New York Governor Eliot Spitzer; the Republican run state senate has kept the bill from reaching the floor for a vote. 

[[Same-sex marriage in Israel|Israel]]'s High Court of Justice ruled to recognize same-sex marriages performed in other countries, although it is still illegal to perform them within the country.  A bill was raised in [[Knesset]] to rescind the Israeli High Court's ruling, but the Knesset has not advanced the bill since December [[2006]].

[[Same-sex marriage in Canada|Canada]] and [[Same-sex marriage in Spain|Spain]] are the only countries where the legal status of same-sex marriage is exactly the same as that of opposite-sex marriage, though [[Same-sex marriage in South Africa|South Africa]] is due to fully harmonize its marriage laws. Other nations all have residency requirements that apply to same-sex marriage that do not apply to opposite-sex marriage.

[[Image:World homosexuality laws.svg|thumb|350px|Map showing the status of homosexuality laws of the world.

{{legend|#c0c0c0|No information}}
'''Homosexuality legal'''
{{legend|#57781f|Same sex marriages}}
{{legend|#99b453|Same sex unions}}
{{legend|#bed688|No same sex unions}}
'''Homosexuality illegal'''
{{legend|#f9dc36|Minimal penalty}}
{{legend|#ec8028|Large penalty}}
{{legend|#e73e21|Life in prison}}
{{legend|#8c210f|Death penalty}}
{{legend|#a9a9a9|No info on penalty}}]]

=== Civil unions ===
{{main|Civil union}}

The first same-sex union in modern history with government recognition was obtained in Denmark in [[1989]].

[[Civil union]]s, [[Civil partnership]], [[domestic partnership]]s, [[Unregistered partnership]] or [[registered partnership]]s offer varying amounts of the benefits of marriage and are available in: [[Andorra]], [[Colombia]], [[Croatia]], [[Czech Republic]], [[Denmark]], [[Finland]], [[France]], [[Germany]], [[Hungary]], [[Iceland]], [[Israel]], [[Luxembourg]], [[New Zealand]], [[Norway]], [[Portugal]], [[Slovenia]], [[South Africa]], [[Sweden]], [[Switzerland]] and the [[United Kingdom]]. They are also available in '''some parts''' of [[Argentina]], [[Brazil]] ([[Rio Grande do Sul]]), [[Mexico]], the [[United States|U.S.]] states of [[California]], [[Connecticut]], [[Hawaii]], [[Maine]], [[New Hampshire]] (effective January 1, 2008), [[New Jersey]], [[Oregon]] (effective January 1, 2008), [[Vermont]], [[Washington]] state, and the [[District of Columbia]] (Washington, D.C.); [[Uruguay]] (effective November 1, 2007).

In the United Kingdom, [[civil partnerships]] have identical legal status to a marriage, and partners gain all the same benefits and associated legal rights; ranging from tax exemptions and joint property rights, to [[next-of-kin]] status and shared parenting responsibilities. Partnership ceremonies are performed by a marriage registrar in exactly the same manner as a [[secular]] [[civil marriage]]. 
[[Civil unions in New Zealand]] are identical to British civil partnerships in their association with equivalent spousal rights and responsibilities to fully-fledged heterosexual marriage.

[[Australia]] provides under all states, territories and two council areas either a registry system - Sydney, Melbourne, Tasmania and Victoria (effective December 1, 2007); or a domestic partnership - Queensland, South Australia, Northern Territory, Norfolk Island, Western Australia, Australian Capital Territory and New South Wales. However, Commonwealth law provisions and statutes prohibit the recognition of civil unions, civil partnerships and same-gender marriages; fifty-eight acts in commonwealth law use the phrase 'member of the opposite sex'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.humanrights.gov.au/media_releases/2007/43_07.html |title = Simple changes could end discrimination for thousands of Australian couples |date = 21 Jun 2007 |accessdate = 2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007 Grace Abrams and Fiona Power became Australia's first legally recognised same sex married couple [http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2007/10/16/2060485.htm] after Grace Abrams had gender modification surgery and was later officially granted a passport with female status. 

A [[registered partnership]] in [[Scandinavia]] is nearly equal to marriage, including legal adoption rights in Sweden and, since June, in Iceland as well.  These partnership laws are short laws that state that wherever the word "marriage" appears in the country's law will now also be construed to mean "registered partnership" and wherever the word "spouse" appears will now also be construed to mean "registered partner" - thereby transferring the body of marriage laws onto same-sex couples in registered partnerships.  In these countries, registered partnerships are generally called marriage in daily speech.

In some countries with legal recognition the actual benefits are minimal.  Many people consider civil unions, even those which grant equal rights, inadequate, as they create a separate status, and think they should be replaced by gender-neutral marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/john-bohrer/nj-civil-unions-nothing-_b_36351.html
   |title      = NJ Civil Unions: Nothing to Celebrate 
   |publisher  = The Huffington Post
   |author     = John R. Bohrer
   |date       = 14 Dec 2006
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== International organizations ===
The terms of employment of the staff of [[international organizations]] (not businesses) are not, in most cases, governed by the laws of the country in which their offices are located. Agreements with the host country safeguard these organizations' impartiality with regard to the host and member countries. [[Recruitment|Hiring]] and [[firing]] practices, [[working hours]] and environment, [[holiday]] time, [[pension]] plans, [[health insurance]] and [[life insurance]], [[salaries]], expatriation benefits and general conditions of employment are managed according to rules and regulations proper to each organization. The independence of these organizations gives them the freedom to implement human resource policies which are even contrary to the laws of their host and member countries. A person who is otherwise eligible for employment in Belgium may not become an employee of [[NATO]] unless he or she is a citizen of a NATO member state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://www.nato.int/structur/recruit/info.htm
   |title      = NATO Recruitment service
   |publisher  = NATO 
   |date       = 07 Dec 2006
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[World Health Organization]] has recently banned the recruitment of cigarette smokers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://www.who.int/employment/recruitment/en/
   |title      = What are we looking for?
   |publisher  = World Health Organization
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Agencies of the [[United Nations]] coordinate some human resource policies amongst themselves.

Despite their relative independence, few organizations currently recognise same-sex partnerships without condition. The [[Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development]] (OECD) and the agencies of the [[United Nations]] voluntarily [[discriminate]] between opposite-sex marriages and same-sex marriages, as well as discriminating between employees on the basis of nationality. These organizations recognize same-sex marriages only if the country of citizenship of the employees in question recognizes the marriage. In some cases, these organizations do offer a limited selection of the benefits normally provided to opposite-sex married couples to de facto partners or [[domestic partner]]s of their staff, but even individuals who have entered into an opposite-sex [[civil union]] in their home country are not guaranteed full recognition of this union in all organizations. However, the [[World Bank]] does recognize domestic partners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/EXTHRJOBS/0,,contentMDK:20522360~menuPK:1353209~pagePK:64262408~piPK:64262191~theSitePK:1058433,00.html
   |title      = Jobs - Compensation &amp; Benefits
   |publisher  = The World Bank Group
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Anticipated demand in the United Kingdom ===
In the [[United Kingdom]], the government is reported to have anticipated demand for same sex civil partnerships as being around 11,000 to 22,000 by [[2010]]. However, this appears to have been an underestimate; as of December 2006 some 15,657 such partnerships had been registered in around 9 months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://www.guardian.co.uk/frontpage/story/0,,1964183,00.html
   |title      = More than 15,500 civil partnerships prove popularity of legislation
   |publisher  = the Guardian
   |author     = Lucy Ward 
   |date       = 5 Dec 2006
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Transsexual and Intersex persons ===
{{wikinews|Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson}}
When sex is defined legally, it may be defined by any one of several criteria: the [[XY sex-determination system]], the type of [[gonad]]s, or the type of external sexual features.  By all of these definitions both [[transsexual]]s and [[intersex]]ed individuals are legally categorized into confusing gray areas, and could be prohibited from marrying partners of the "opposite" sex or permitted to marry partners of the "same" sex due to arbitrary legal distinctions. This could result in long-term marriages, as well as recent same-sex marriages, being overturned.

An example of the problem with chromosomal definition would be a woman with [[Androgen insensitivity syndrome|Complete Androgen Insensitivity Syndrome]] (CAIS), who would have a 46,XY karyotype, which is typically male.  Although she may have been legally registered as female on her birth certificate, been raised as a female her entire life, have engaged in typical heterosexual female relationships, and may even have married before the status of her condition was known, using the chromosomal definition of sex could prevent or annul the marriage of a woman with this condition to a man, and similarly allow her to legally marry another woman.  These same issues were faced by the [[IOC]] to determine who qualified as a female for the women's competitions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper
   |url        = http://www.uksport.gov.uk/assets/File/Generic_Template_Documents/Standards_in_Sport/transsexuals.pdf
   |title      = Transsexual people and sport
   |publisher  = UK Department for Culture, Media and Sport
   |format     = .PDF
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The problems of defining gender by the existence/non-existence of gonads or certain sexual features is complicated by the existence of [[Gender Reassignment Surgery|surgical methods]] to alter these features.  Although it has not been exhaustively stated by a court, it is possible that a court could find that if a person has their gonads removed, they would enter a sexual limbo status and fail to meet either set of criteria, thus excluding them from any allowance to marriage.  This situation could easily occur through exclusionary findings by separate courts in a state that already does not recognize transexual marriages to people of the same sex as their birth-sex, as in the case of Linda Kantaras vs. Michael Kantaras. Basing the distinction on genital appearance is complicated by available [[Sex reassignment surgery male-to-female|surgery]] converting typically male genitalia to typically female genitalia, which has advanced to the point where, even were a genital inspection necessary, many transgendered women would pass this inspection without question.

Requiring a surgical reassignment for definition of gender for the purpose of declaring a marriage valid comes with further problems.  The [[Sex reassignment surgery female-to-male|female-to-male sex reassignment surgery]] is expensive and does not provide results as satisfactory as its counterpart; therefore many female-to-male transsexuals choose not to undergo this procedure.  In a situation where genitalia legally defines gender and same-sex marriage is not permitted, the transsexual man would therefore only be allowed to legally marry another man if he wished to marry.

These complications are probably more likely than one would think at first glance; according to the highest estimates (Fausto-Sterling et al., 2000) perhaps 1 percent of live [[childbirth|birth]]s exhibit some degree of sexual ambiguity, and between 0.1% and 0.2% of live births are ambiguous enough to become the subject of specialist medical attention, including sometimes involuntary [[surgery]] to address their sexual ambiguity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://www.isna.org/faq/frequency
   |title      = How common is intersex?
   |publisher  = Intersex Society of North America
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In any legal jurisdiction where marriages are defined without distinction of a requirement of a male and female, these complications do not occur, and some legal jurisdictions may recognize a legal and official change of gender, which would allow one to satisfy the requirement of either "male" or "female" according to their gender-identity within their legal definition of marriage. Although some legal jurisdictions continue to only recognize the "immutable traits determined at birth". (Linda Kantaras vs. Michael Kantaras)

{{main|Legal aspects of transsexualism}}

In the United Kingdom, recent legislation allows transsexual persons to be officially recognized in their new gender, but this has the effect of annulling any previous marriage. However the couple will now be able to register a civil partnership, to come into force immediately upon the dissolution of their marriage

In countries with legal systems based on the [[Napoleonic code]]s, being legally recognized as one's transitioned gender may require conditions of infertility, where if a transsexual were ever found to have had a child, it would result in a reversal of a legal sex change and spontaneous annulment of the marriage if that country does not recognize same-sex marriages.

In the United States, transsexual and intersexual marriages typically run into the complications detailed above.  As definitions and enforcement of marriage is defined by the state, these complications will vary from state to state.  In Massachusetts no problem should arise in seeking to get a marriage, or enforcing that marriage, however marriage in states that have more prohibitive definitions, ''any'' marriage with a transsexual could face challenge in a court based on any number of criteria.

(For discussions on the status of marriages involving transgendered persons see Julie A. Greenberg, Defining Male and Female: Intersexuality and the Collision Between Law and Biology, 41 Ariz. L. Rev. 265 (Summer 1999); and Michael L. Rosin, Intersexuality and Universal Marriage, 14 L. &amp; Sex. 51 (2005) as well as the references they contain.)

== Controversy ==
{{Refimprove|date=December 2006}}

[[Image:OutMagazineCover.jpg|thumb|[[Out (magazine)|Out Magazine]] covers the marriage of [[Bob Paris]] and [[Rod Jackson]] in March 1994]]

In 2004, the [[American Anthropological Association]] released this statement:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aaanet.org/press/ma_stmt_marriage.htm Statement on Marriage and the Family from the American Anthropological Association]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The results of more than a century of [[anthropological]] research on [[household]]s, [[kinship]] relationships, and [[Family|families]], across cultures and through time, provide no support whatsoever for the view that either [[civilization]] or viable [[social order]]s depend upon marriage as an exclusively heterosexual institution. Rather, anthropological research supports the conclusion that a vast array of family types, including families built upon same-sex partnerships, can contribute to stable and humane societies.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The legitimacy of marriage depends on the authoritative definition(s) of marriage. Most of the current controversy centers around governmental definitions of marriage, rather than the [[blessing of same-sex unions]] by individual religious organizations, which may or may not be recognized as civil marriages. Some disagree with the idea of government involvement in the institution of marriage at all but especially the benefits received from becoming married that are largely seen as a "reward". Within this interpretation, giving benefits to married couples, regardless of sexual preference is a problem in and of itself. The government's only function is to uphold the legal agreement between the partners, regardless of sexual orientation. This view can be found with individuals that align themselves with the [[Libertarian perspectives on gay rights|Libertarian Party and fits well within their ideals]].

As such, [[Gay rights]] advocates assert that marriage is a fundamental [[Civil Rights|civil right]] and that any government should not restrict the right of consenting adults from full rights in male-male, female-female, and male-female relationships. Supporters also believe that the definition of traditional marriage has changed drastically over time; polygamy, formerly a common practice, is illegal in the United States and few people would openly espouse the idea of "wife as chattel."  Moreover, the "traditional" view of "love marriages" has only been in existence since the latter 18th century. Supporters also argue that homosexuals contribute as much as heterosexuals to the funding for private and public family coverage even when they have no access to it, and that discrimination decreases productivity. Also, supporters argue that the procreation argument is not valid since there is no legal requirement to have children in any marriage, either same-sex or opposite-sex.

However, opponents to same-sex marriage assert that marriage is a [[natural right]] based on the biological need of procreation not a civil right and can be restricted by law. They believe that the perpetuation of humanity relies fully on the ability of procreation and trying to "equalize" same-sex marriage legally will only create gross social distortions to accommodate the gulf between such law and the observable facts of human nature. Finally, opponents state that changing the definition of marriage, to include same-sex couples, fractures traditional understandings of marriage.  

=== Religious arguments ===
{{POV-section}}
[[Image:Sergebac7thcentury.jpg|thumb|250px|Historian [[John Boswell (historian)|John Boswell]] claims the 4th century Christian martyrs [[Saints Sergius and Bacchus|Saint Sergius and Saint Bacchus]] were united in the rite of [[adelphopoesis]], or brother-making, which he calls an early form of religious same-sex marriage]]

Some opponents object to same-sex marriage on purely [[homosexuality and religion|religious grounds]]. Opponents often claim that extending marriage to same-sex couples will undercut the conventional purpose of marriage as interpreted by cultural, religious, and traditional understanding. Furthermore, opponents argue that same-sex marriage cannot fulfill common procreational roles, and/or sanctions a partnership that is centered around sexual acts that their respective religion prohibits. For example, [[James Dobson]], in ''Marriage Under Fire'' and elsewhere, states that legalization or even tolerance of same-sex marriage would redefine the family, damage traditional family unions, and lead to an increase in the number of homosexual couples. Catholic apologetics groups, such as [[Catholic Answers]], have offered similar arguments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | url = http://www.catholic.com/library/gay_marriage.asp
  | title      = Special Report: Gay Marriage
  | publisher  = Catholic Answers
  | date       = 2004
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Conservative Christianity|Conservatives]] and some moderate Christians further claim that homosexuality goes against biblical teaching, and extend this to same-sex marriage. As an example, there is the Bible verse Genesis 19:5 which refers to the behavior which biblically contributed to the destruction of the ancient cities [[Sodom and Gomorrah]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | chapter    = Genesis 19 
  | chapterurl = http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Genesis%2019%20;&amp;version=31;
  | title      = New International Version
  | publisher  = BibleGateway.com
  | accessdate = 2007-03-08
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other passages are Leviticus 18:22, Leviticus 20:13, and in the New Testament of the Bible, First Corinthians 6:8-10 and Romans 1:24-27, although none of these outright define marriage in a purely heterosexual way.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | chapter    = Romans 1:24-27
  | chapterurl = http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Romans%201:24-27%20&amp;version=31
  | title      = New International Version 
  | publisher  = BibleGateway.com
  | accessdate = 2007-03-08
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, other moderate and [[Liberal Christianity|liberal Christians]] claim that these passages are taken out of full textual, historical and cultural contexts, and are not applicable to homosexual relationships as we know them today. They view the passages about Sodom and Gomorrah as referring to systematic rape and inhospitality. They view the passages in Leviticus as part of the [[Holiness Code]] and strictly reserved to the Israelites of that time. Some of this Holiness Code is not practiced by contemporary Christians (e.g., prohibitions on wearing mixed fabrics, a proscription of the consumption of pork, the sacrifice of animals as atonement for sins), while other parts such as the prohibitions on incestuous relations still are. For some modern Christians, the passage in Romans is seen as relating more to specific instances of Greco-Roman temple sex acts and idolatrous worship and it is not intended to address contemporary homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper
   |url        = http://members.cox.net/paulmcc/mcc/samegen.html
   |title      = Same Gender Sexual Behavior and the Scriptures
   |publisher  = Metropolitan Community Church of Topeka, authors and 
   |author     = Loppnow, Rev. Jonathan; Evans, Rev. Paul C.
   |format     = .HTML; .SIT
   |date       = 7 Jan 1998
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

There are some people, who despite having a moral or religious stance that same-sex marriage is wrong, still feel that it is not their place to take their religious sentiments into the secular realm, and enforce their beliefs on others, who may disagree.  So, while these religious people do not approve of homosexual couples, and continue to refuse to recognize their marriages from a religious aspect, they still nevertheless recognize and tolerate their secular marriage.

Some modern religions and denominations perform same-sex weddings. At the 1996 [[Unitarian Universalism|Unitarian Universalist]] [[General Assembly (Unitarian Universalist Association)|General Assembly]], delegates voted overwhelmingly that because of "the inherent worth and dignity of every person" same-sex couples should have the same freedom to marry that other couples have.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://www.uua.org/news/freedomtomarry/index.html
   |title      = Freedom to Marry, for All People
   |publisher  = Unitarian Universalist Association
   |date       = 2006
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://www.femdomale.com/samesex/marriage/index.html
   |title      = Same-Sex "Marriage": Should America Allow "Gay Rights" Activists to Cross The Last Cultural Frontier?
   |publisher  = Christian Leadership Ministries
   |author     = Anton N. Marco
   |date       = 1999
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Social arguments ===
Those who advocate that marriage should be defined exclusively as the union of one man and one woman argue that heterosexual unions provide the procreative foundation of the family unit that is the chief social building block of civilization. Libertarians and others may see marriage not as a legal construct of the state, but as a naturally occurring "pre-political institution" that the state must recognize as it recognizes other natural institutions such as jobs and families. "Government does not create marriage any more than government creates jobs."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://www.policyreview.org/apr05/morse.html
   |title      = Marriage and the Limits of Contract
   |publisher  = the Hoover Institution
   |author     = Jennifer Morse
   |date       = May 2005
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; They argue that the definition proposed by same-sex marriage advocates changes the social importance of marriage from its natural function of reproduction into a mere legality or freedom to have sex. These sides of the argument may refer to themselves as "defenders" of traditional marriage. As any customary relationship may be considered "marriage", some argue that this then leads to undue legislative burden and an affront to the social value and responsibility of parenting one's own children.

The dissent by Justice Martha Sosman in the decision of the Massachusetts high court that legalized same-sex marriage in that state makes a societal argument without specifying the harm that would occur from this change.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://911fantasy.blogspot.com/1995/12/transcript-of-martha-sossmans-dissent.html
   |title      = Transcript of Martha Sossman's Dissent
   |publisher  = blogspot.com
   |date       = 23 Dec 1995
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Asserting the ''[[A priori and a posteriori (philosophy)|a priori]]'' importance of marriage as an institution, she questions whether the burden of proof that this would be harmless has been met. Her analysis can be seen as an example of [[precautionary principle]], which states that if an action or policy might cause severe or irreversible harm to the public, in the absence of a scientific consensus that harm would not ensue, the burden of proof falls on those who would advocate taking the action.

A common objection to same-sex marriage is that the purpose of marriage is a result of naturally occurring sexual attraction that leads to procreation and that the same-sex partnership is inherently sterile. Some who hold this view see marriage as the social codification of an evolved long term mating strategy, with economic and legal benefits to facilitate family growth and stability.
Others argue that because the law does not prohibit marriage between sterile heterosexual couples, or to women past [[menopause]], the procreation argument cannot reasonably be used against same-sex marriage, particularly since technological advances allow gay couples to have their own related biological children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_marint2.htm
   |title      = Is Same-Sex Marriage (SSM) a Bad Idea?
   |publisher  = Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance
   |author     = B.A. Robinson
   |date       = 10 Apr 2004
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another view is that all marriages should thus be viewed legally as "[[civil union]]s". These civil unions would then only receive the [[Rights and responsibilities of marriages in the United States|benefits of marriage]] which do not require expenditures from the government (e.g. tax breaks), and any monetary benefits would only be awarded based on the number of children living in a household.

Some same-sex marriage proponents, such as [[Andrew Sullivan]], argue that same-sex marriage is moral enough to support the family centered role marriage plays in society despite the absence of biological children. Supporters also argue that the institution of marriage would be strengthened by making it available to more people, and furthermore that same-sex marriage would encourage gays and lesbians to settle down with one partner and raise families. Others argue that marriage no longer retains a procreative function of the government since many governments offer child tax credits and assistance regardless of marital status.

Also, many people argue in favor of same-sex marriage because they say that sexual orientation is uncontrollable.  They cite many scientific studies which claim &lt;ref&gt;[http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/facts_changing.html Attempts to Change Sexual Orientation]&lt;/ref&gt; that no one can choose, nor change, their sexual orientation, and that forbidding marriage between two people of the same sex is like forbidding marriage between two people of the same eye color, skin color, or nose length.  Some even go as far as to say that sexual orientation is a [[gene]] just like these traits, and thus should not be treated as a basis for discrimination.

=== Arguments about tradition ===
Proponents of same-sex marriage point out that "traditional" concepts of marriage in actuality have already undergone [[History of civil marriage in the U.S.|significant change]].

Polygamy has been prohibited, married women are no longer considered the property of their husbands, [[divorce]] is legal, [[birth control|contraception]] within wedlock is allowed, and [[miscegenation|anti-miscegenation laws]] forbidding [[interracial marriage]] have been eliminated in most modern societies.

The fact that changes in the customs and protocols of marriage often occur gives rise to the argument that marriage is dynamic, and same-sex marriage is only the latest evolution of the institution.

=== Arguments concerning children ===
{{main|LGBT parenting}}

In opposing same-sex marriage in various state courts, a common key state's argument against allowing same-sex marriage has been the use of legal marriage to foster the state's interest in human reproduction.  In ''[[Anderson et al. v. King County]]'' in which several same-sex couples argued that the state of Washington's version of the Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA) was unconstitutional, the [[Washington Supreme Court]] ruled 5 to 4 that the law was constitutional.  Writing in the majority opinion, Justice Barbara Madsen wrote in 2006:
&lt;blockquote&gt;''The Legislature was entitled to believe that limiting marriage to opposite-sex couples furthers procreation, essential to the survival of the human race and furthers the well-being of children by encouraging families where children are reared in homes headed by children's biological parents.''&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;

(See also [[Same-sex marriage in Washington]])

In responding to this argument in 2007, the Washington Defense of Marriage Alliance, a supporter of same-sex marriage, began a petition drive to place a ballot measure on the November 2007 ballot that would require opposite-sex couples who marry to have children within three years or have their marriages become legally unrecognized.  Couples seeking a marriage license would also have to show they can produce children.  The group admits this ballot initiative aims at calling attention to the Washington Supreme Court's decision in ''Anderson'' and the logical extension of this reasoning to childless and/or sterile heterosexual couples.&lt;p&gt;

In terms of numbers, the [[United States Census, 2000|2000 U.S. Census]] reports more than 600,000 same-sex couples (''unmarried domestic partners'' on the Census form) in the United States.  The Census Bureau estimates that this number would be over 770,000 in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper
   |url        = http://www.law.ucla.edu/williamsinstitute/publications/SameSexCouplesandGLBpopACS.pdf
   |title      = Same-sex Couples and the Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual Population: New Estimates from the American Community Survey  
   |author     = Gary J. Gates, PhD
   |publisher  = The Williams Institute of UCLA Law School
   |format     = .PDF 
   |date=October 2006
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;  While a post-Census study by UCLA economist Dr. M.V. Lee Badgett found that there was a significant undercount of same-sex couples in 2000, the Census reports that among the couples answering they are a same-sex couple:  one-third of lesbian couples and one-fifth of gay male couples have children under 18 living in the home.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper
   | url       = http://www.iglss.org/media/files/c2k_leftout.pdf
   | author    = M. V. Lee Badgett, Ph.D; Marc A. Rogers, Ph.D.
   | date      = 2003
   | format    = .PDF
   | title     = Left Out of the Count:  Missing Same-Sex Couples in Census 2000 
   | publisher = Institute for Gay and Lesbian Strategic Studies
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some object on the grounds that same-sex couples should not be allowed to adopt or raise children or to have access to reproductive technologies, and that same-sex marriage would make such arrangements easier. A number of health and child welfare organizations, however, disagree. They include the Child Welfare League of America, North American Council on Adoptable Children, [[American Academy of Pediatrics]], [[American Psychiatric Association]], [[American Psychological Association]], and the [[National Association of Social Workers]].&lt;ref name="aclu1"&gt;{{cite web
   |url        = http://www.aclu.org/LesbianGayRights/LesbianGayRights.cfm?ID=17245&amp;c=104 
   |title      = BAD LINK &lt;!-- Too High A Price: The Case Against Restricting Gay Parenting --&gt;
   |publisher  = American Civil Liberties Union
   |author     = 
   |date       = 
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 28, 2004, the American Psychological Association's Council of Representatives adopted a resolution supporting legalization of same-sex civil marriages and opposes discrimination against lesbian and gay parents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
   |url        = http://www.apa.org/releases/gaymarriage.html
   |title      = APS Supports Legalization of Same-sex Civil Marriages...
   |publisher  = American Psychological Association
   |date       = 28 July 2004
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Arguments concerning divorce rates ===
{{limitedgeographicscope}}
{{Refimprove|date=July 2007}}
On an international scale, the most comprehensive study to date on the effect of same-sex marriage / partnership on heterosexual marriage and divorce rates was conducted looking at over 15 years of data from the Scandinavian countries.  The study (later part of a book), by researcher [[Darren Spedale]], found that, 15 years after Denmark had granted same-sex couples the rights of marriage, rates of heterosexual marriage in those countries had gone up, and rates of heterosexual divorce had gone down - contradicting the concept that same-sex marriage would have a negative effect on traditional marriage.&lt;ref&gt;[[Darren Spedale]], William Eskridge and Hans Ytterberg  ''Nordic Bliss? Scandinavian Registered Partnerships and the Same-Sex Marriage Debate'', Journals of Legal Scholarship:Issues in Legal Scholarship i.5, The Berkeley Electronic Press, January 2004 [http://www.freedomtomarry.org/pdf/ScandinaviaBEPressArticle.pdf courtesy link pp 29-30]&lt;/ref&gt;

All US states submit monthly summaries of vital statistics on births, deaths, marriages, and divorces to the US Center For Disease Control's National Center For Health Statistics (NCHS) who then prepares monthly and yearly reports. The following statistics are based on that NCHS material. Over three years have passed now since same sex marriage was legalized in Massachusetts and data from all of 2004 and 2005 are now available. 

The current divorce trends in Massachusetts counter claims of same-sex marriage having a negative impact on traditional marriage. In fact, for several years now the Commonwealth has had the lowest divorce rate of any state in the union. In 2004 the Massachusetts divorce rate, at 2.2 per 1,000 residents per year, was considerably lower than the US national average rate for that year, 3.8 per 1,000 and close to the national average of 2.0 back in 1940. In the first two years of same-sex marriage in the Bay State, the rate of divorce showed a steady decline making it likely that Massachusetts will continue to have the lowest divorce rate in the nation. The institution of marriage in Massachusetts since same-sex marriage was legalized, as measured by the rate of divorce, has not been healthier in at least half a century regardless of dire predictions of Christian Right leaders and Catholic Bishops.

The conservative "red states" that have taken aggressive action against same sex marriage, have not done nearly as well during the two year period of legal same sex marriage in Massachusetts. The preliminary data from 2004 and 2005—from the 17 US states which have provided data on divorce for 2004 and 2005 and whose voters also passed state constitutional amendments prohibiting same sex marriage—presents a striking picture: the group of US states arguably most hostile to divorce, those which have passed both state laws and also state constitutional amendments prohibiting same sex marriage, lag dramatically in terms of divorce rate improvement when compared to same sex marriage friendly states.

Among those US states that are most opposed to same sex marriage which have also provided divorce data for the time period — AR, KS, KY, MI, MS, MO, NE, NV, ND, OH, OK, OR, UT, TX — the average divorce rate ( unadjusted for population changes ) for 2004 and 2005 increased 1.75%. This group contains 4 of the 5 states with the highest divorce rate increases in the US during 2004 and the first 11 months of 2005.

=== Arguments concerning equality ===
[[Image:Newlywed.jpg|left|thumb|Newlywed male same-sex couple at Gaypride 2006 in [[Reykjavik]].]]
In the [[United States]], there are at least 1,138 federal laws "in which marital status is a factor."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper
   |url        = http://www.gao.gov/new.items/d04353r.pdf
   |title      = Defense of Marriage Act: Update to Prior Report
   |publisher  = United States General Accounting Office
   |date       = 2004
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; (See [[Rights and responsibilities of marriages in the United States]] for a partial list) A denial of rights or benefits without substantive [[due process]], assert the proponents of same-sex marriage, directly contradicts the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] which provides for [[Equal Protection Clause|equal protection]] of all citizens. For instance, a heterosexual US citizen who marries a foreign partner immediately qualifies to bring that person to the United States, while long-term gay and lesbian binational partners who have spent decades together are denied the same rights, forcing foreign gay partners to seek expensive temporary employer or school-sponsored visas or face separation. See [http://www.immigrationequality.org/familyunvalued.php Immigration Equality] and [http://hrw.org/reports/2006/us0506/ Human Rights Watch] report on this and other forms of discrimination against same-sex couples. 

In a 2003 case titled ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'', the Supreme Court held that the [[rights|right]] to private consensual sexual conduct was protected under the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]]. The court noted "moral disapproval does not constitute a legitimate governmental interest under the Equal Protection Clause." Both supporters and detractors of same-sex marriage have noted that this ruling paved the way for subsequent decisions invalidating state laws prohibiting same-sex marriage. U.S. Supreme Court Justice [[Antonin Scalia]] noted as such in his dissenting opinion to ''Lawrence''.

Some opponents of extending marriage to same-sex couples claim that equality can be achieved with [[civil union]]s or other forms of legal recognition that don't go as far as to use the word "marriage" that's used for opposite-sex couples. An opposing argument, used by the [[Massachusetts Supreme Judicial Court]] in ''[[Goodridge v. Department of Public Health]]'', is the following: ''"the dissimilitude between the terms "civil marriage" and "civil union" is not innocuous; it is a considered choice of language that reflects a demonstrable assigning of same-sex, largely homosexual, couples to second-class status"'' and also that ''"The history of our nation has demonstrated that separate is seldom, if ever, equal."'' For instance, in matters under federal purview such as immigration, a bi-national same-sex couple committed under civil union do not have the same rights as their married heterosexual counterparts in sponsoring their [[alien (law)|alien]] partner for [[permanent residency]]. There is however, a bill pending in the [[United States Congress]] since 2000, called [[Uniting American Families Act]] pertaining to this discrimination.

=== Parallels to interracial marriage ===
Opponents of same-sex marriage argue that men and women are fundamentally different from one another, whereas interracial couples still fit within the "one man and one woman" definition of marriage.&lt;ref name="mmarriage"&gt;{{cite video
   |url        = http://www.secureminnesotaformarriage.org/ss/live/index.php?action=viewprod&amp;sid=64&amp;pid=149&amp;pageid=258 
   | title      = The Battle for Marriage in Minnesota
   | publisher  = Minnesota for Marriage
   | medium     = Video
   | format     = MPEG-4; WM9
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Louisiana State University law professor Katherine Spaht has characterized the debate as follows: “the fundamental understanding of marriage has always been, by definition, a man and a woman. Never did Webster’s dictionary define the term marriage in terms of the races. There is an inherent difference between interracial marriage and same-sex “marriage” because homosexuals cannot procreate." [[Focus on the Family|Focus on the Family’s]] Glenn Stanton told the Baptist Press that “knocking down bans on interracial marriage did not redefine marriage, it affirmed marriage by saying that any man has a right to marry any woman under the law. But what same-sex ‘marriage’ proponents seek to do is to radically redefine the very definition of marriage to say it’s not about gender.  Marriage is about bringing the genders together, not keeping the races apart.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://www.bpnews.net/bpnews.asp?ID=17988
   |title      = Bans on interracial marriage, same-sex ‘marriage’ -- parallels?
   |publisher  = Baptist Press
   |author     = Michael Foust
   |date       = 2 Apr 2004
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Proponents of same-sex marriage make a comparison between [[racial segregation]] and segregation of homosexual and heterosexual marriage classifications in civil law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://hnn.us/articles/4708.html
   |title      = Why the Ugly Rhetoric Against Gay Marriage Is Familiar to this Historian of Miscegenation
   |publisher  = History News Network of George Mason University
   |author     = Peggy Pascoe
   |date       = 19 Apr 2004
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }} &lt;/ref&gt; They argue that dividing the concept of same-sex marriage and different-sex marriage is tantamount to "[[separate but equal]]" policies (like that overturned in the US Supreme Court case [[Brown v. Board of Education]]), or [[anti-miscegenation laws]] that were also overturned by the Supreme Court in 1967 in ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]''. Furthermore, the arguments used against interracial marriage are very similar to those now being used against same-sex marriages.

In 1972, after the Minnesota Supreme Court's ruling in ''[[Baker v. Nelson]]'' specifically distinguished ''Loving'' as not being applicable to the same-sex marriage debate, the United States Supreme Court dismissed the appeal "for want of a substantial federal question." This type of dismissal usually constitutes a decision [[on the merits]] of the case; as such, Baker appeared—at least for a time &amp;mdash; to be binding precedent on all lower federal courts.

It is unclear whether ''Baker v. Nelson'' remains as a potential bar to the federal courts from hearing cases regarding same-sex marriage.  The federal [[Defense of Marriage Act]] of 1996 (DOMA) simultaneously created (1) a federal definition of marriage, {{UnitedStatesCode|1|7}}, and (2) a new rule under the [[Full Faith and Credit Act]] (passed pursuant to Congress's authority under the federal Constitution's [[Full Faith and Credit Clause]]), {{UnitedStatesCode|28|1738C}}, purporting to limit mandatory interstate recognition of same-sex marriages.  By "federalizing" marriage with statutes that are susceptible of judicial scrutiny, Congress effectively — albeit perhaps unintentionally — expanded the subject-matter jurisdiction of the federal courts, seemingly superseding Baker's dismissal "for want of a substantial federal question."

This loophole in jurisdiction recently came to light when a same-sex couple was granted standing to sue in federal district court on a claim that DOMA is unconstitutional under the federal Constitution.  See ''Smelt v. County of Orange'', 374 F. Supp. 2d 861 ([[United States District Court for the Central District of California|C.D. Cal.]], 2005), aff'd in part and rev'd in part, 447 F.3d 673 (9th Cir. 2006), cert. denied, 127 S. Ct. 396 (2006).  In ''Smelt'', the district court applied Pullman abstention to one part of the claim, but it proceeded to the merits on another part, finding DOMA to be constitutional.  The [[United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit]] affirmed the district court on the abstention question, but it reversed the district court on the merits, holding that the couple lacked standing to sue.  The Ninth Circuit raised the standing question ''[[sua sponte]]'', but only because the couple had not demonstrated the requisite injury.  The Ninth Circuit left open the possibility that another couple with a demonstrable injury could bring the same suit in the future.  Importantly, ''Baker v. Nelson'' is mentioned nowhere in the Ninth Circuit's opinion; its continuing relevance is therefore highly suspect.

Beginning in 2003, members of Congress have annually introduced a "court-stripping" provision that would prevent all federal courts from hearing claims challenging the constitutionality of DOMA.  See, e.g., Marriage Protection Act of 2003, H.R. 3313 (108th Cong., 1st Sess.).  This proposed court-stripping provision has itself been challenged as being of dubious constitutionality.  See Jason J. Salvo, Comment, Naked Came I: Jurisdiction-Stripping and the Constitutionality of House Bill 3313, 29 Seattle U. L. Rev. 963 (Summer 2006); Maxim O. Mayer-Cesiano, On Jurisdiction-Stripping: The Proper Scope of Inferior Federal Courts' Independence from Congress, 8 U. Pa. J. Const. L. 559 (May 2006); J. Spencer Jenkins, Note, 'Til Congress Do Us Part: The Marriage Protection Act, Federal Court-Stripping, and Same-Sex Marriage, 40 New Eng. L. Rev. 619 (Winter 2006); Sarah Kroll-Rosenbaum, Note, The Marriage Protection Act: A Lesson in Congressional Over-Reaching, 50 N.Y. L. Sch. L. Rev. 809 (2005-2006); Michael J. Gerhardt, The Constitutional Limits to Court-Stripping, 9 Lewis &amp; Clark L. Rev. 347 (Summer 2005); Theodore J. Weiman, Comment, Jurisdiction Stripping, Constitutional Supremacy, and the Implications of Ex Parte Young, 153 U. Pa. L. Rev. 1677 (2005).

=== Economic arguments ===
Economic arguments on the impact of same-sex marriage focus on the effects on same-sex couples, businesses, employers, and governments. UCLA Law School economist and policy researcher Dr. M. V. Lee Badgett has studied the impact of same-sex legal marriage on all four of these groups. 

'''Impact on Same-sex Couples:'''  Badgett finds that exclusion from legal marriage has an economic impact on same-sex couples.  According to a 1997 General Accounting Office study requested by Rep. [[Henry Hyde]] (R), at least 1,049 US Federal laws and regulations grant rights and responsibilities to legally married couples.  A later 2004 study by the Congressional Budget Office finds 1,138 statutes related to marriage benefits.&lt;ref name=cbo1&gt;{{cite paper
   |url        = http://www.cbo.gov/showdoc.cfm?index=5559&amp;sequence=0
   |title      = The Potential Budgetary Impact of Recognizing Same-Sex Marriages
   |publisher  = Congressional Budget Office 
   |format     = .HTML; .PDF
   |date       = 21 Jun 2004
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these laws govern property rights, benefits, and taxation.  Same-sex couples are ineligible for spousal and survivor Social Security benefits.  Badgett's research finds the resulting difference in Social Security income for same-sex couples compared to opposite-sex married couples is US$5,588 per year.  The federal ban on same-sex marriage and benefits through the 1996 Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA) extends to federal government employee benefits.  For example, after the 2006 death of former Massachusetts Congressman [[Gerry Studds]] (D), the first openly gay member of Congress, his legal spouse Dean Hara was denied the estimated $114,337 annual pension to which Hara would have been eligible if their Massachusetts marriage was recognized on the federal level.  According to Badgett's work, same-sex couples face other financial challenges against which legal marriage at least partially shields opposite-sex couples:

* potential loss of couple's home from medical expenses of one partner caring for another gravely ill one

* costs of supporting two households, travel, or emigration out of the US for an American citizen unable to legally marry a non-US citizen

* higher cost of purchasing private insurance for partner and children if company is not one of 18% that offer domestic partner benefits

* higher taxes:  unlike a company's contribution to an employee's spouse's health insurance, domestic partner benefits are taxed as additional compensation

* legal costs associated with obtaining domestic partner documents to gain some of the power of attorney, health care decision-making, and inheritance rights granted through legal marriage

* higher health costs associated with lack of insurance and preventative care:  20% of same-sex couples have a member who is uninsured compared to 10% of married opposite-sex couples

* current tax law allows a spouse to inherit an unlimited amount from the deceased without incurring an estate tax but an unmarried partner would have to pay the estate tax on the inheritance from her/his partner

* same-sex couples are not eligible to file jointly or separately as a married couple and thus cannot take the advantages of lower taxes via the marriage bonus

While state laws grant full marriage rights (Massachusetts) or some or all of the  benefits under another name (Vermont, New Jersey, California, etc.), these state laws do not extend the benefits of marriage on the Federal level, and most states do not currently recognize same-sex marriages or civil unions from other states.

One often overlooked aspect of same-sex marriage are the potential ''negative'' effects on same-sex couples.  While the legal benefits of marriage are numerous, same-sex couples would face the same financial constraints of legal marriage as opposite-sex married couples.  Such potential effects include the [[marriage penalty]] in taxation.  Similarly, while social service providers usually do not count one partner's assets toward the income means test for welfare and disability assistance for the other partner, a legally married couple's joint assets are normally used in calculating whether a married individual qualifies for assistance.

'''Impact on Businesses:''' Dr. M. V. Lee Badgett's research estimates the potential impact on businesses of same-sex marriage legalization to be $2 billion to the wedding industry alone.  Badgett derives this estimate by calculating the amount spent on weddings if a) half of same-sex couples marry and b) each couple spends 1/4 the average amount spent on an opposite-sex wedding (US$27,600 average wedding cost / 4 = US$6,900 per same-sex couple).

'''Impact on Employers''': In terms of employers where marriage opponents fear higher benefit costs, Badgett and Mercer Human Resources Consulting  separately find less than 1% of employees with a same-sex partner sign up for domestic partner benefits when a company offers them.  Badgett finds less than 0.3% of Massachusetts firms' employees signed up for spousal benefits when that state legalized same-sex marriage.  

'''Impact on Governments''': A 2004 Congressional Budget Office (CBO) report examines the impact of allowing the 1.2 million Americans in same-sex domestic partnerships in the 2000 Census to marry and finds the impact to be comparatively small in terms of the huge Federal budget. While some spending on Federal programs would increase, these outlays would be offset by more savings in other spending areas.  The report predicts that if same-sex marriage was legalized in all 50 states and on the Federal level, the U.S. government would bring in a net surplus of US$1 billion per year over the next 10 years.&lt;ref name=cbo1/&gt; In terms of specific programs' spending the report states:  

&lt;blockquote&gt;''Recognizing same-sex marriages would increase outlays for Social Security and for the Federal Employees Health Benefits (FEHB) program, CBO estimates, but would reduce spending for Supplemental Security Income (SSI), Medicaid, and Medicare. Effects on other programs would be negligible. Altogether, CBO concludes, recognizing same-sex marriages would affect outlays by less than $50 million a year in either direction through 2009 and reduce them by about $100 million to $200 million annually from 2010 through 2014.''&lt;ref name=cbo1/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The CBO study counters the economic argument by some U.S. critics of same-sex marriage against governmental recognition on the grounds that the public should not have to shoulder the burden of increased taxes and insurance premiums to cover the associated costs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://www.opinionjournal.com/editorial/feature.html?id=110004735
   |title      = For Better or for Worse? 
   |publisher  = WSJ OpinionJournal
   |author     = Mary Ann Glendon
   |date       = 25 Feb 2004
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other arguments ===
''[[The Weekly Standard]]'' commentator Stanley Kurtz argues allowing same-sex marriage blurs other common law precedents and [[Slippery-slope argument|will lead to the legalization of a variety of non-traditional relationships]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/002/938xpsxy.asp
   |title      = Beyond Gay Marriage
   |publisher  = Weekly Standard
   |author     = Stanley Kurtz
   |date       = 4 Aug 2003
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Polygamy]]. The gist of this argument is that the traditional definition of marriage involves two components, a commitment to one person of the opposite sex, and that changing one of these components (restricting it to members of opposite sexes) would necessarily lead to a change in the other component (restricting it to only one person).
* [[Polyamory]]. Defined as the practice whereby a person has more than one long term [[love|loving relationship]] in their life, with the knowledge and acceptance of others they are involved with, in whatever form is chosen by those involved. This can include long term stable [[group marriage]]s, or stable couples who have external partners as well as their 'primary' partner. A polyamorous civil union in the Netherlands in 2005 sparked many comparisons with gay marriage on American conservative blogs.  Most practitioners of polyamory in the United States are skeptical of all forms of marriage, however.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/006/494pqobc.asp 
   |title      = Here Come the Brides
   |publisher  = The Weekly Standard
   |author     = Stanley Kurtz
   |date       = 26 Dec 2005
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Incest]]uous marriages.  The natural aversion most people feel toward incestuous relationships does not vary depending on sexual orientation, yet this is a logical consequence of redefining marriage to accommodate a group.
* [[Marriage of convenience|Marriages of convenience]] for tax or other reasons.  This however, seems to be more of an argument against government-sanctioned marriage in general, not just same-sex marriage.
* [[Human-animal marriage]]. Non-human animals, however, do not have the legal standing to consent into a marriage contract.

== Etiquette ==
{{limitedgeographicscope}}
The standard form of address for same-sex spouses is that where the couple has taken the same surname, they may be addressed as "The [[Mr.|Messrs.]] William and Harry Fitzgibbon" or "[[Mrs.|Mmes.]] Emily and Lucia March"; otherwise, they may be addressed individually, as is done for other married couples with different surnames:  "Jane Smith and Mary Doe."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
   |url        = http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A405-2004Jul20.html
   |title      = Marriage Titles Revisited
   |publisher  = The Washington Post
   |author     = 
   |date       = 21 July 2004
   |accessdate = 2007-03-08
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{commonscat|Same-sex marriage}}
{{Portal|LGBT|Portal LGBT.svg}}
* ''[[A Union in Wait]]''
* [[Adelphopoiesis]]
* [[Blessing of same-sex unions in Christian churches]]
* [[Adoption by same-sex couples]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Marriage gap]]
* [[Marriage#Rights and obligations relating to marriage|Marriage rights and obligations]]
* [[:Category:Marriage, unions and partnerships by country|Marriage, unions and partnerships by country]]
* [[Religion and sexuality]]
* [[United States Census, 2000#Gay and Lesbian controversy|Same-sex controversy in the U.S. Census 2000]]
* [[Timeline of same-sex marriage]]
* [[Traditional marriage movement]]
* [[Uniting American Families Act]]
* [[List of LGBT couples]]

== Notes and references ==
{{Reflist|2}}
{{refbegin|2}}
* [http://www.breakinglegalnews.com/entry/Mass-governor-orders-26-gay-marriages-registered Mass. governor orders 26 gay marriages registered], Breaking Legal News, April 3, 2007
{{refend}}

== Bibliography ==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
* {{cite book | last = Boswell | first = John | authorlink = John Boswell (historian)| year = 1995 | title = The Marriage of Likeness: Same-sex Unions in Pre-modern Europe | publisher = Simon Harper and Collins | location = New York | id = ISBN 0-00-255508-5}}
* {{cite book | last = Wolfson | first = Evan | authorlink = Evan Wolfson | year = 2004 | title = Why Marriage Matters: America, Equality, and Gay People's Right to Marry | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster | location = New York | id = ISBN 0-7432-6459-2}}
* {{cite book | last = Boswell | first = John | authorlink = John Boswell | year = 1994 | title = Same-sex Unions in Premodern Europe | publisher = Villard Books | location = New York | id = ISBN 0-679-43228-0}}
* {{cite book  | last = Farrow | first = Douglas| last = Cere | first = Daniel | authorlink = Daniel Cere | year = 2004 | title = Divorcing Marriage: Unveiling the Dangers in Canada's New Social Experiment | publisher = McGill-Queen's University Press| location = Montreal | id = ISBN 0-7735-2895-4}}
* {{cite book | last = Chauncey | first = George | authorlink = George Chauncey | year = 2004 | title = Why Marriage?: The History Shaping Today's Debate over Gay Equality | publisher = Basic Books | location = New York | id = ISBN 0-465-00957-3}}
* {{cite book | last = Dobson | first = James C. | authorlink = James Dobson | year = 2004 | title = Marriage Under Fire|Marriage under Fire: Why We Must Win This War | publisher = Multnomah | location = Sisters, Or. | id = ISBN 1-59052-431-4}}
* {{cite book | last = Larocque | first = Sylvain | authorlink = Sylvain Larocque | year = 2006 | title = [[Gay Marriage|Gay Marriage: The Story of a Canadian Social Revolution]] | publisher = James Lorimer &amp; Company | location = Toronto | id = ISBN 1-55028-927-6}}
* {{cite book | last = Spedale | first = Darren | authorlink = Darren Spedale | year = 2006 | title = Gay Marriage: For Better or For Worse? What We've Learned From the Evidence | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = New York | id = ISBN 0-19-518751-2}}
* {{cite book | editor = Robert P. George, [[Jean Bethke Elshtain]] (Eds.) | year = 2006 | title = The Meaning of Marriage: Family, State, Market, And Morals | publisher = Spence Publishing Company | location = Dallas | id = ISBN 1-890626-64-3}}
*Caramagno, Thomas C.  "Irreconcilable Differences? Intellectual Stalemate in the Gay Rights Debate."  Westport, CT: Praeger, 2002.  ISBN 0-275-97721-8
&lt;/div&gt;

{{Same-sex marriage}}
{{LGBT-footer|history=yes|culture=yes|rights=yes}}

[[Category:Marriage]]
[[Category:LGBT civil rights]]
[[Category:Same-sex marriage|Same-sex marriage]]

[[af:Gay-huwelik]]
[[br:Dimezioù etre paotred pe etre maouezed]]
[[bg:Еднополов брак]]
[[de:Gleichgeschlechtliche Ehe]]
[[es:Matrimonio entre personas del mismo sexo]]
[[fr:Mariage homosexuel]]
[[gl:Casamento homosexual]]
[[ko:동성 결혼]]
[[it:Matrimonio omosessuale]]
[[he:נישואים חד מיניים]]
[[nl:Homohuwelijk]]
[[ja:同性結婚]]
[[no:Likekjønnet ekteskap]]
[[pl:Małżeństwo homoseksualne]]
[[pt:Casamento entre pessoas do mesmo sexo]]
[[ro:Căsătorie între persoane de acelaşi sex]]
[[sh:Istopolni brak]]
[[fi:Homoavioliitto]]
[[sv:Samkönat äktenskap]]
[[wuu:同性婚姻]]
[[zh:同性婚姻]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>