<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020927130454|319806" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="92656" pageid="92656" ns="0" title="Same-sex marriage"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-09-28T01:52:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Same-sex marriage''' (also called '''gay marriage''') is [[marriage]] between two partners of the same [[gender]].  [[Gay]] marriages are currently only recognized in the [[Netherlands]].  Recently, the term "same-sex marriage" has been displacing "gay marriage", as a less value-laden term for the union of two members of the same gender.

In recent years there has been a growing movement in a number of countries to extend the right to marry to [[gay]] and [[lesbian]] couples. Married couples are frequently entitled to a wide range of social security, taxation and other benefits denied to unmarried couples. Prohibiting gay marriage denies gay couples access to these benefits. (Heterosexual couples without other legal impediments, on the other hand, can always marry.)  It also makes it more difficult for them to adopt children. Those who oppose this movement argue that restricting marriage to heterosexual couples preserves the traditional understanding of the nature of marriage. Some opponents also claim that allowing same-sex marriage will open the door to the legalization of [[polyamory|polyamorous]] marriage.

This movement has resulted in changes in the law in many local jurisdictions, though the extent of the changes have varied:
*some jurisdictions have created formal legal recognition for homosexual relations, but which are more limited than marriage, e.g. [[domestic partnership]] laws
*others have created a separate status from marriage, with however equal rights to married couples: e.g. [[civil union]]s;
*others have allowed homosexual couples to marry, and have identical legal status to heterosexual legal couples. Such an approach has been adopted in the [[Netherlands]], and is in varying stages of development in [[Belgium]], [[Finland]], and [[Canada]].

Even in jurisdictions where they are not legally recognized, many [[gay]] and [[lesbian]] couples choose to have [[wedding]]s (also called "[[commitment ceremonies]]") to celebrate and affirm their relationship, fulfilling the social aspect of a marriage.

--------

=== Gay marriage in the [[Netherlands]] ===

A "registered partnership" system became active on [[January 1]]st, [[1998]].  However after a court
case brought about by a gay couple it was concluded that restricting marriage to partners of mixed sex
was in violation of the constitution, which forbids discrimination against homosexuals.  Hence the marriage
law was changed and since [[April 1]]st, [[2001]] homosexual marriages have been permitted. Note that registered partnerships, although originally introduced to enable gay couples to make their partnership official, are open to couples of mixed gender as well.

There was strong opposition from fundamentalist religious groups to the introduction of gay marriage, e.g.,
see [[Khalil el-Moumni]].  Individual churches have retained the right to decide whether or not to conduct
such ceremonies: in practice many have been willing to do so.

While regional government offices are obliged to perform civil gay
marriages, some uncertainty has remained about whether individual officials have the right to refuse to perform
them.

The rules about [[nationality]] and residence are the same as for any other marriage in the [[Netherlands]]:
at least one partner must either have [[Netherland]]s [[nationality]] or reside in the country.  There is no
guarantee that a gay marriage will be recognised in other countries, most likely it will be accepted in those and only those countries that have themselves a form of registered partnership for gay couples.

According to provisional figures from the [[Netherlands]] Central Bureau of Statistics, for the first six months gay marriages made up 3.6 percent of the total number of marriages: a peak of around 6 percent in the first month followed by around 3 percent in the remaining months: about 2100 men and 1700 women in total.

Gay marriages are fully equivalent to normal marriages in the Netherlands (except that if a married lesbian has a child, her wife will not count as the child's father or mother; unless and until she adopts the child, she will count for the law as a stepmother).

*[http://www.ministerievanjustitie.nl:8080/a_beleid/fact/same-sexmarriages.htm Netherlands Ministry of Justice factsheet] (in [[English language|English]])
------------

=== Gay marriage in [[Canada]] ===

Supreme Court decisions in [[Ontario]] ([[July 12]], [[2002]]) and [[Quebec]] ([[September 6]], [[2002]]) require the federal government to implement full gay marriage within the next two years, although the Liberal government announced that it would appeal. 

In [[1999]], homosexual couples in Canada were ruled to have the right to [[common-law marriage]] in the [http://www.pfc.org.uk/news/1999/gm-mh2.htm M ''v.'' H decision.] The provinces of [[Quebec]] and [[Nova Scotia]] currently recognize [[civil union]]s.

------------

=== Other forms of same-sex partnership ===

A small but increasing number of jurisdictions recognize gay "civil unions" or "registered partnerships", which provide much of the same rights and responsibilities as marriage but use a different name for the arrangement. Examples are [[Denmark]], [[Sweden]], [[Finland]], [[Norway]], [[Iceland]], [[Germany]], the [[Canada|Canadian]] provinces of [[Quebec]] and [[Nova Scotia]], and the [[United States of America|American]] state of [[Vermont]].

For information on these, see [[civil union]].

Many more areas in the world (usually local municipalites and counties) allow [[domestic partnership]]s that have varying degrees of privileges and responsibilities, usually far fewer than those found in civil unions.

----------

=== The fight over gay marriage in the [[United States]] ===

''To be expanded - [[Defense of Marriage Act]], etc.''</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>