<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031026143342|1630634" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="92656" pageid="92656" ns="0" title="Same-sex marriage"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-26T23:06:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Same-sex marriage''' (also called '''gay marriage''' and '''same-gender marriage''') is [[marriage]] between two partners of the same [[sex]]. This article deals with [[civil marriage|civil or state marriage]], not the religious concept of marriage as espoused by various faiths. For more information on that topic, please see [[Religion and homosexuality]]. For other forms of same-sex unions that are different from civil marriages, see the links below.

Same-sex marriages currently are legally performed only in the [[Netherlands]] and [[Belgium]]. For the time being, the [[Canada|Canadian]] provinces of [[Ontario]] and [[British Columbia]] have also legalized same-sex marriage. Recently, the term "same-sex marriage" has been displacing "gay marriage", the term being perceived as less value-laden for the union of two partners of the same sex. 

In the late [[20th century|20th]] and early [[21st century|21st]] centuries, there has been a growing movement in a number of countries to regard marriage as a right which should be extended to [[gay]] and [[lesbian]] couples. Legal recognition of a marital union opens up a wide range of entitlements, including social security, taxation, inheritance and other benefits unavailable to couples unmarried in the eyes of the law. Restricting legal recognition to heterosexual unions excludes same-sex couples from gaining legal access to these benefits. (While opposite-sex unmarried couples without other legal impediments have the option of marrying in law and so gaining access to these rights, that option is unavailable to same-sex couples.)  Lack of legal recognition also makes it more difficult for same-sex couples to [[adoption|adopt children]]. 

Opponents object to same-sex marriage often on [[religion and homosexuality|religious grounds]], arguing that extending marriage to homosexual couples undercuts the conventional meaning of marriage in various traditions.  In countries with [[monogamous]] marriages only, some opponents also claim that allowing same-sex marriage will re-open the door to the legalization of [[polyamory|polyamorous]] marriage, or other forms they find objectionable. They also feel that same-sex couples should not be allowed to have or adopt children, and that same-sex marriage would make those adoptions easier; they hold that same-sex households are not an adequate environment for children to be raised in, and that living in group homes is better for the children than adoption by a same-sex couple. Some also don't see any need for same-sex marriages.

In response, proponents point out that traditional concepts of marriage have already given way to liberalization in other areas, such as the availability of no-fault [[divorce]] and the elimination of [[miscegenation|anti-miscegenation laws]]. They also suggest that many people in modern societies no longer subscribe to the religious beliefs which inform traditional limits upon marriage, and no longer wish these beliefs to constitute the law.  Furthermore, a number of religions celebrate same-sex weddings or commitment ceremonies already; in Canada, the [[United Church of Canada]], the country's largest Protestant denomination, has striven for the legalization of same-sex marriage.

Some [[libertarianism|libertarians]] object to same-sex civil marriages because they are opposed to any form of state-sanctioned marriage, including opposite-sex unions.

==Other forms of same-sex partnership==

The movement towards the legal recognition of same-sex marriages has resulted in changes in the law in many jurisdictions, though the extent of the changes have varied:

* [[Civil union]]s provide most of the rights and responsibilites of same-sex marriage, but use a different name for the arrangement. They exist in a several European countries as well as in the [[U.S. state]] of [[Vermont]], the Canadian provinces of [[Quebec]] and [[Nova Scotia]], and the city of [[Buenos Aires]], [[Argentina]].
* [[domestic partner|Domestic partnerships]] or registered partnerships provide varying degrees of privileges and responsibilities, usually far fewer than those found in civil unions. Their purpose is not limited to same-sex arrangements and they exist in many jurisdictions.

Even in jurisdictions where they are not legally recognized, many [[gay]] and [[lesbian]] couples choose to have [[wedding]]s (also called "commitment ceremonies" in this context) to celebrate and affirm their relationship, fulfilling the social aspect of a marriage. Such ceremonies have no legal validity, however, and as such do not deal with issues such as inheritance, property rights or social security. 

Some writers have advanced the idea that the term "marriage" should be restricted to a religious context and that state and federal governments should not be involved in a religious rite. Some regard this as a governmental intrusion into religion; they believe that all statutes involving domestic contracts should replace the word "marriage" with "domestic partnership" and thus bypass the controversy of gender. This would then allow a domestic contract between any two individuals who have attained their majority.  

==Terminology==
The term "mixed marriage" usually does not refer to sex but to religion, culture or race.

==Related links==
*[[Same-sex marriage in Belgium]]
*[[Same-sex marriage in Canada]]
*[[Same-sex marriage in the Netherlands]]
*[[Same-sex marriage in the United States]]

&lt;!-- Interlanguage links --&gt;
[[fr:Mariage homosexuel]]
[[zh:&amp;#21516;&amp;#24615;&amp;#23130;&amp;#23035;]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>