<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061103175046|85507805" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1530922" pageid="1530922" ns="0" title="Limpieza de sangre"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-03T18:13:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:'''''Limpieza de sangre''' is also a novel in the [[Captain Alatriste]] series by [[Arturo Pérez-Reverte]].''

'''''Limpieza de sangre''''' (in [[Spanish language|Spanish]]), '''''Limpeza de sangue''''' (in [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]), both meaning "cleanliness of [[blood]]" was a concept of [[Iberian peninsula|Iberian]] [[Modern Age|Modern]] History.
It referred to being [[ethnic cleansing|ethnically pure]] "[[Old Christian]]", without [[Jewish]] or [[Muslim]] ancestors.

After the end of the [[Reconquista]] and the expulsion of [[Sephardic]] Jews, the population of [[Spain]] and [[Portugal]] was all nominally Christian.
However, the descendants of the Christian conquerors despised the [[New Christians]], descendants of baptized Jews ([[Converso]]s or [[Marrano]]s) or [[Mudejar]]s ([[Morisco]]s).
Besides social and economic causes, the accusation was that the New Christians were false converts, keeping their former religion in their homes ([[Crypto-Jew]]s).
This was sometimes true, but even people later declared to be Saints by the Church could be suspected.
Cleanliness of blood was an issue of ancestry, not of personal religion.

This stratification meant that the Old Christian [[commoner]]s could assert a right to honor even if they were not in the [[nobility]].
The [[military order]]s, [[guild]]s and other organizations incorporated in their [[bylaw]]s clauses demanding proof of cleanliness of blood.
Upwardly mobile New Christian families had to either contend with their plight, or bribe and falsify documents attesting generations of good Christian ancestry.
The [[Spanish Inquisition|Spanish]] and [[Portuguese Inquisition]]s was more concerned with repressing the New Christians and [[heresy]] than chasing [[witchcraft|witches]], which was considered to be more a psychological than a religious issue, or [[Protestantism]], which was promptly suffocated.

The claim to universal ''[[hidalgo (Spanish nobility)|hidalguía]]'' (lowest nobility) of the [[Basque people|Basques]] was justified because the Arab invasion didn't reach the Basque territory, so it was believed that Basques had maintained their original purity, while the rest of Spain was suspect of [[miscegenation]].
Even in the 19th century, the [[Basque nationalism]] of [[Sabino Arana]] demanded a list of original Basque surnames to rule out mixes with Spaniards.

In spite of the abolition of the rules with the demise of the [[Ancien Regime]], the discrimination was still present into the twentieth century in some places like Majorca.  No [[Xueta]] (descendant of the Majorcan Conversos) priest was allowed to say Mass in the cathedral until the 1960s{{ref|JPerez}}.

==See also==
*[[Caste system]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Apartheid]]
*[[Nuremberg laws]]
*[[Black Legend]]

==Reference==
* {{note|JPerez}} ''Los judíos en España'', [[Joseph Pérez]]. Marcial Pons. Madrid (2005).

[[Category:Basque history]]

* Douglass, William A. 2004. ‘Sabino’s sin: racism and the founding of Basque nationalism’ in Daniele Conversi (ed.), ''Ethnonationalism in the Contemporary World''. London: Routledge, pp. 95–112 [http://easyweb.easynet.co.uk/conversi/ethnonat link title]



[[Category:Al-Andalus]]
[[Category:Jewish Spanish history]]
[[Category:Spanish Inquisition]]
[[Category:History of Portugal]]
[[Category:Racism]]
 
[[es:Estatutos de limpieza de sangre]]
[[eo:Limpieza de sangre]]
[[fr:Limpieza de sangre]]
[[he:טוהר הדם]]


{{christianity-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>