<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101023205349|392473125" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1530922" pageid="1530922" ns="0" title="Limpieza de sangre"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-10-23T21:08:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:'''''Limpieza de sangre''' is also a novel in the [[Captain Alatriste]] series by [[Arturo Pérez-Reverte]].''

'''''Limpieza de sangre''''' (in Spanish), ({{lang-pt|'''Limpeza de sangue'''}}), both meaning "cleanliness of blood" played an important role in [[Modern Age|modern]] [[Iberian peninsula|Iberian]] history.
It referred to those who were considered pure "[[Old Christian]]s", without [[Jewish]] or [[Muslim]] ancestors.

== After the Reconquista ==
After the end of the [[Reconquista]] and the expulsion or conversion of [[Sephardim]] (Jews) and [[Mudéjar]]s (Muslims), the population of Portugal and Spain was all nominally Christian. However, the ruling class and much of the populace distrusted the recently-converted "[[New Christians]]", referring to them as [[converso]]s or [[marrano]]s if they were baptized Jews or descended from them, or [[Morisco]]s if they were baptized Muslims or descended from them. A commonly-leveled accusation was that the New Christians were false converts, secretly practicing their former religion as [[Crypto-Jew]]s or [[Crypto-Muslim]]s.  Nevertheless, the concept of cleanliness of blood came to be more focused on ancestry than of personal religion. The first statute of purity of blood appeared in [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]], 1449&lt;ref name="Chami"&gt;[http://pachami.com/Inquisicion/LimpiezaSangre.html Estatutos de Limpieza de Sangre], Pablo A. Chami.&lt;/ref&gt;, where an anti-Converso riot succeeded in obtaining a ban on Conversos and their posterity from most official positions. Initially these statutes were condemned by the monarchy and the Church. In 1496, [[Alexander VI]] approved a purity statute for the [[Hieronymites|Hieronymite Order]]&lt;ref name="Chami"/&gt;.

This stratification meant that the Old Christian [[commoner]]s could assert a right to [[honor]] even if they were not in the [[nobility]]. The religious and [[military order]]s, [[guild]]s and other organizations incorporated in their [[bylaw]]s clauses demanding proof of cleanliness of blood. Upwardly mobile New Christian families had to either contend with their plight, or bribe and falsify documents attesting generations of good Christian ancestry. The [[Spanish Inquisition|Spanish]] and [[Portuguese Inquisition]]s were more concerned with repressing the New Christians and [[heresy]] than chasing [[witchcraft|witches]], which was considered to be more a psychological than a religious issue, or [[Protestantism]], which was promptly suffocated.

The claim to universal ''[[hidalgo (Spanish nobility)|hidalguía]]'' (lowest nobility) of the [[Basque people|Basques]] was justified by erudites like [[Manuel de Larramendi]] (1690–1766)&lt;ref name="Larramendi"&gt;[[Manuel de Larramendi]], ''Corografía de la muy noble y muy leal provincia de Guipúzcoa'', Bilbao, 1986, facsimile edition of that from Editorial [[Ekin]], Buenos Aires, 1950. (Also published by Tellechea Idígoras, San Sebastián, 1969.) Quoted in ''[http://www.uv.es/rseapv/Anales/97_98/A_117_139_La_idea_de_Espanya.pdf La idea de España entre los vascos de la Edad Moderna]'', by Jon Arrieta Alberdi, ''Anales 1997-1998'', Real Sociedad Económica Valenciana de Amigos del País.&lt;/ref&gt; because the Arab invasion hadn't reached the Basque territories, so it was believed that Basques had maintained their original purity, while the rest of Spain was suspect of [[miscegenation]]. In fact, the Arab invasion also reached the Basque country and there had been a significant Jewish minority in Navarre, but the hidalguía helped many Basques to official positions in the administration&lt;ref name="Auñamendi"&gt;[http://www.euskomedia.org/aunamendi/100471 Limpieza de sangre] in the Spanish-language [[Auñamendi Encyclopedia]]&lt;/ref&gt;. 

Even in the 19th century, the [[Basque nationalism]] of [[Sabino Arana]]&lt;ref name="Arana"&gt;"Original ancestry from [[Biscay|Bizkaya]]: this is what cleanliness of blood meant for the Bizkaians of that time. Original ancestry from [[Euskeria]]: this is what means [[race purity]] for the nationalist Bizkaians of today"([[Sabino Arana|Arana Goiri, Sabino]], 1980, ''Obras completas''. San Sebastián: Sendoa. 2nd edition, tome II, page 1170). Translated into English from ''[http://www.ucm.es/info/circulo/no14/fulloa.htm Figuras retóricas en el discurso político nacionalista de Sabino Arana]'', Teresa Fernández Ulloa, Círculo de Lingüística Aplicada a la Comunicación 14, Mayo 2003. ISSN 1576-4737.&lt;/ref&gt; demanded a list of original Basque surnames to rule out mixes with Spaniards. In this case the motivation was to create a Basque identity to claim independence from Spain, depicting often other Spaniards as imperialistic invaders and oppressors of the Basque people.

Tests of ''limpieza de sangre'' had begun to lose their utility by the 19th century, rarely did persons have to endure the grueling inquisitions into distant parentage through birth records. However, laws to officially suppress these tests were late in adoption. For example an edict of 8 March 1804 by King Ferdinand VII resolved that no knight of the [[Military Order]]s could wed without having a council vouch for the ''limpieza de sangre'' of his spouse&lt;ref&gt;Codigos Españoles Tome X. Page 225&lt;/ref&gt;.

Official suppression of such entry requirements for the Army were enacted into law in 16  May 1865 &lt;ref&gt;''Colección Legislativa de España'' (1870), p. 364&lt;/ref&gt;, and extended to naval appointments on 31 August, of the same year. In 5 November 1865, a decree allowed children born out of wedlock or illegitimate, for whom ancestry could not be verified, to be able to enter into religious higher education (canons)&lt;ref&gt;''Colección Legislativa de España'' (1870), page 365&lt;/ref&gt;. In 26 October 1866, the test of blood purity were outlawed for the purposes of determining who could be admitted to college education. In 20 March 1870, a decree suppressed all use of blood purity standards in determining eligibility to any government position or any licensed profession&lt;ref&gt;''Colección Legislativa de España'' (1870), page 366&lt;/ref&gt;.

The rise to power of [[Francisco Franco]] and the [[Falange]], which had developed alliances to the racist governments of [[Nazi Germany]] and [[Fascist Italy]], there was some renewed focus by the government on the "unity" of the Spaniards under one religion and one people. However, no statutes were officially enacted to enforce racial purity.  The discrimination was still present into the twentieth century in some places like Majorca.  No [[Xueta]] (descendants of the Majorcan Conversos) priests were allowed to say Mass in a cathedral until the 1960s.&lt;ref name="JPerez"&gt;''Los judíos en España'', [[Joseph Pérez]]. Marcial Pons. Madrid (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Historical genesis of Blue Blood===
{{Expand|date=November 2007}}
:"It was the Spaniards who gave the world the notion that an aristocrat's blood is not red but blue. The Spanish nobility started taking shape around the ninth century in classic military fashion, occupying land as warriors on horseback. They were to continue the process for more than five hundred years, clawing back sections of the peninsula from its Moorish occupiers, and a nobleman demonstrated his pedigree by holding up his sword arm to display the filigree of blue-blooded veins beneath his pale skin--proof that his birth had not been contaminated by the dark-skinned enemy." 
:[[Robert Lacey]], ''Aristocrats.'' Little, Brown and Company, 1983, p. 6.

==Spanish colonies==
''Limpieza de sangre'' was a very important concept among Spaniards who settled in the [[Americas]].
The [[Laws of the Indies]] repeatedly banned descendants of Conversos and those reconciliated with the Inquisition of settling in the Americas (the reiteration suggests that the laws were often ineffectual)&lt;ref name="Chami"/&gt;. The philosophy led to the separation of the various peoples in the colonies and created a very intricate list of nomenclature to describe one's precise race and, by consequence, one's place in society. To illustrate how complex this nomenclature became the following list was in use in [[New Spain]] (Mexico) during the eighteenth century:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Yelvington
  | first =Kevin A.
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Understanding Contemporary Latin America
  | publisher =Lynne Rienner
  | year =2005
  | location =Boulder, Colorado
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =ISBN 158826341X
  | page =246  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Spaniard and Indian = ''[[Mestizo]]'' (1/2 European and 1/2 Native American)
*Mestizo and Spanish woman = ''[[Castizo]]'' (3/4 European and 1/4 Native American)
*Castizo woman and Spaniard = Spaniard (7/8 European and 1/8 Native American)
*Spanish woman and black man = ''[[Mulatto]]'' (1/2 European and 1/2 African)
*Spaniard and Mulatto = ''[[Morisco]]'' (3/4 European and 1/4 African)
*Morisco woman and Spaniard = ''Albino'' (7/8 European and 1/8 African)
*Spaniard and Albino woman = ''[[Torna atrás]]'' ("turn back") (15/16 European and 1/16 African)
*Indian man and Torna atrás woman = ''[[Zambo|Lobo]]'' (1/2 Native American, 15/32 European, and 1/32 African)
*Lobo and Indian woman = ''[[Zambaigo]]'' (3/4 Native American, 15/64 European, and 1/64 African)
*Zambaigo and Indian woman = ''[[Cambujo]]'' (7/8 Native American, 15/128 European, and 1/128  African)
*Cambujo and mulatto woman = ''[[Albarazado]]'' (7/16 Native American, 79/256 European, and 65/128 African)
*Albarazado and Mulatto woman = ''[[Barcino]]'' (13/32 European, 7/32 Native American, and 3/8 African)
*Barcino and Mulatto woman = ''[[Cholo|Coyote]]'' (117/256 European, 7/64 Native American, and 111/256 African) 
*Coyote woman and Indian man = ''[[Chamiso]]'' (29/128 European, 227/4096, Native American, and 3405/4096 African)
*Chamiso woman and Mestizo = ''Coyote mestizo'' (93/256 European, 135/256 Native American, and 7/64 African)
*Coyote mestizo and Mulatto woman = ''[[Ahí te estás]]'' ("there you stay") (3535/8192 European, 2161/8192 Native American, and 1248/4096 African)

This list represents only some of the existing social and legal terms put in place by the colonizing Spaniards to firmly establish how far away one is from pure European blood. Every Spanish colony had its own, equally complex, system of determining one's racial genealogy.
They did not block intermixing but placed the result of interracial relations in the caste system.

==See also==
*[[Caste system]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[South Africa under apartheid]]
*[[Nuremberg laws]]
*[[Black Legend]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
* Douglass, William A. (2004) ''Sabino's sin: racism and the founding of Basque nationalism'' in [[Daniele Conversi]] (ed.), ''[http://easyweb.easynet.co.uk/conversi/ethnonat Ethnonationalism in the Contemporary World]''. London: Routledge, pp.&amp;nbsp;95–112.
*{{cite book| first=| last=| year=1850| title=''Códigos Españoles Concordados y Anotados'' Tomo Décimo. | editor = | pages= | publisher=[[M. Rivadeneyra]] |location=Calle Jesús del Valle #6, Madrid; [[Google Books]]|id= | url=http://books.google.com/books?id=MrgCAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA225&amp;dq=limpieza+de+Sangre&amp;as_brr=1#PPA5,M1| authorlink=}}
*{{cite book| first=| last=| year=1870| title=''Colección legislativa de España: Continuación de la colección de decretos (Primer Semestre de 1870)'' (Tomo CIII)| editor = | pages= | publisher=Ministerio de Gracia y Justicia. 
 |location=Madrid; Google Books|id= | url=http://books.google.com/books?id=kMs2AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=RA3-PA1237&amp;dq=Primer+Semestre+de+1870&amp;as_brr=1#PPA1,M1| authorlink=}}

==External links==
*[http://pachami.com/Inquisicion/LimpiezaSanMartin.html Attestment of the purity of blood] of [[Justo Rufino de San Martín]] (brother of [[José de San Martín|José]]) in [[Paredes de Nava]], 1794.

{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Limpieza De Sangre}}
[[Category:Al-Andalus]]
[[Category:Basque history]]
[[Category:Jewish Mexican history]]
[[Category:Jewish Portuguese history]]
[[Category:Jewish Spanish history]]
[[Category:Portuguese Inquisition]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Spanish Inquisition]]

{{Link GA|fr}}

[[bg:Изискване за чистота на кръвта]]
[[es:Estatutos de limpieza de sangre]]
[[eo:Limpieza de sangre]]
[[fr:Limpieza de sangre]]
[[he:טוהר הדם]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>