<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121118194942|523718906" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1530922" pageid="1530922" ns="0" title="Limpieza de sangre"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-18T22:17:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:'''''Limpieza de sangre''' is also a novel in the [[Captain Alatriste]] series by [[Arturo Pérez-Reverte]].''
{{POV|date=February 2012}}
'''''Limpieza de sangre''''' ({{IPA-es|limˈpjeθa ðe ˈsaŋɡɾe|lang}}), '''''Limpeza de sangue''''' ({{IPA-pt|lĩˈpezɐ ðɨ ˈsɐ̃ɡɨ|lang}}, {{IPA-gl|limˈpeθa ðe ˈsaŋɡe|lang}}) or '''''Neteja de sang''''' ({{IPA-ca|nəˈtɛʒə ðə ˈsaŋ|lang}}), meaning "cleanliness of blood", played an important role in [[Modern Age|modern]] [[Iberian peninsula|Iberian]] history.
It referred to those who were considered pure "[[Old Christian]]s", without [[Muslim]] or [[Jewish]] ancestors, or within the context of the empire ([[New Spain]] and [[Portuguese India]]) those without [[Amerindian]], [[Mongoloid|Asian]] or [[Negroid|African]] ancestry.

== After the Reconquista ==
After the end of the [[Reconquista]] and the expulsion or conversion of Muslim [[Mudéjar]]s (Moors) and [[Sephardic Jews]], the population of [[Portugal]] and [[Spain]] was all nominally European Christian. However, the ruling class and much of the populace distrusted the recently-converted "[[New Christians]]", referring to them as [[converso]]s or [[marrano]]s if they were baptized Jews or descended from them, or [[Morisco]]s if they were baptized Muslims or descended from them. A commonly-leveled accusation was that the New Christians were false converts, secretly practicing their former religion as [[Crypto-Jew]]s or [[Crypto-Muslim]]s.  Nevertheless, the concept of cleanliness of blood came to be more focused on ancestry than of personal religion. The first statute of purity of blood appeared in [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]], 1449,&lt;ref name="Chami"&gt;[http://pachami.com/Inquisicion/LimpiezaSangre.html Estatutos de Limpieza de Sangre], Pablo A. Chami.&lt;/ref&gt; where an anti-Converso riot succeeded in obtaining a ban on Conversos and their posterity from most official positions. Initially, these statutes were condemned by the monarchy and the Church; however, in 1496, Pope [[Alexander VI]] approved a purity statute for the [[Hieronymites|Hieronymite Order]].&lt;ref name="Chami"/&gt;

This stratification meant that the Old Christian [[commoner]]s could assert a right to [[honor]] even if they were not in the [[nobility]]. The religious and [[military order]]s, [[guild]]s and other organizations incorporated in their [[bylaw]]s clauses demanding proof of cleanliness of blood. Upwardly mobile New Christian families had to either contend with their plight, or bribe and falsify documents attesting generations of good Christian ancestry. The [[Spanish Inquisition|Spanish]] and [[Portuguese Inquisition]]s were more concerned with repressing the New Christians and [[heresy]] than chasing [[witchcraft|witches]], which was considered to be more a psychological than a religious issue, or [[Protestantism|Protestants]], who were promptly suffocated.

The claim to universal ''[[hidalgo (Spanish nobility)|hidalguía]]'' (lowest nobility) of the [[Basque people|Basques]] was justified by intellectuals like [[Manuel de Larramendi]] (1690–1766)&lt;ref name="Larramendi"&gt;[[Manuel de Larramendi]], ''Corografía de la muy noble y muy leal provincia de Guipúzcoa'', Bilbao, 1986, facsimile edition of that from Editorial [[Ekin]], Buenos Aires, 1950. (Also published by Tellechea Idígoras, San Sebastián, 1969.) Quoted in ''[http://www.uv.es/rseapv/Anales/97_98/A_117_139_La_idea_de_Espanya.pdf La idea de España entre los vascos de la Edad Moderna]'', by Jon Arrieta Alberdi, ''Anales 1997-1998'', Real Sociedad Económica Valenciana de Amigos del País.&lt;/ref&gt; because the [[Moors|Moorish]] [[Umayyad conquest of Hispania|conquest of Iberia]] had not reached the Basque territories, so it was believed that Basques had maintained their original purity, while the rest of Spain was suspect of [[miscegenation]]. In fact, the Moorish invasion also reached the Basque country and there had been a significant Jewish minority in [[Navarre]], but the hidalguía helped many Basques to official positions in the administration.&lt;ref name="Auñamendi"&gt;[http://www.euskomedia.org/aunamendi/100471 Limpieza de sangre] in the Spanish-language [[Auñamendi Encyclopedia]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Tests of ''limpieza de sangre'' had begun to lose their utility by the 19th century; rarely did persons have to endure the grueling inquisitions into distant parentage through birth records. However, laws requiring ''limpieza de sangre'' were still sometimes adopted even into the 19th century. For example, an edict of 8 March 1804 by King [[Ferdinand VII of Spain|Ferdinand VII]] resolved that no knight of the [[Military Order]]s could wed without having a council vouch for the ''limpieza de sangre'' of his spouse.&lt;ref&gt;Codigos Españoles Tome X. Page 225&lt;/ref&gt;

Official suppression of such entry requirements for the Army were enacted into law in 16 May 1865,&lt;ref&gt;''Colección Legislativa de España'' (1870), p. 364&lt;/ref&gt; and extended to naval appointments on 31 August of the same year. In 5 November 1865, a decree allowed children born out of wedlock or illegitimate, for whom ancestry could not be verified, to be able to enter into religious higher education (canons).&lt;ref&gt;''Colección Legislativa de España'' (1870), page 365&lt;/ref&gt; In 26 October 1866, the test of blood purity were outlawed for the purposes of determining who could be admitted to college education. In 20 March 1870, a decree suppressed all use of blood purity standards in determining eligibility for any government position or any licensed profession.&lt;ref&gt;''Colección Legislativa de España'' (1870), page 366&lt;/ref&gt;

The discrimination was still present into the 20th century in some places like Majorca. No [[xueta]] (descendants of the Majorcan [[conversos]]) priests were allowed to say Mass in a cathedral until the 1960s.&lt;ref name="JPerez"&gt;''Los judíos en España'', [[Joseph Pérez]]. Marcial Pons. Madrid (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Historical genesis of Blue Blood===
{{Expand section|date=November 2007}}
:"It was the Spaniards who gave the world the notion that an aristocrat's blood is not red but blue. The Spanish nobility started taking shape around the ninth century in classic military fashion, occupying land as warriors on horseback. They were to continue the process for more than five hundred years, clawing back sections of the peninsula from its Moorish occupiers, and a nobleman demonstrated his pedigree by holding up his sword arm to display the filigree of blue-blooded veins beneath his pale skin--proof that his birth had not been contaminated by the dark-skinned enemy."
:[[Robert Lacey]], ''Aristocrats.'' Little, Brown and Company, 1983, p. 6.

===Procedure to judge Purity of Blood===
The earliest known case judging ''Limpieza de Sangre'' comes from the Church of Cordoba, that explained the procedure to judge the purity of blood of a candidate as follows: Kneeling, with his right hand placed over the image of a crucifix on a Bible, the candidate confirmed not being of either Jewish or Moorish extraction. Then the candidate provided the names of the parents and grandparents, as well as places of birth. Two delegates of the council, church or other public place would then research the information to make sure it was truthful. If the investigation had to be carried out of Cordoba, a person, not necessarily a member of the council, would be appointed to examine the witnesses appointed by the candidate. This researcher would receive a sum per diem according to the rank of the person, the distance traveled and the time spent. Having collected all the reports, the secretary or the notary must read them all to the council and a vote would decide whether the candidate was approved. A simple majority was sufficient, after which the candidate had to promise to obey all the laws and customs of the Church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Los estatutos de Limpieza de Sangre | author=Sicroff, Albert A. | pages=121}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Spanish colonies==
Being a medieval concept that targeted exclusively the Jewish or Moorish population in Spain, ''Limpieza de sangre'' was never an issue among the native population in the colonies of the [[Spanish Empire]] {{citation needed|date=December 2011}}. However, those who applied to enroll at the service of the Spanish Army or the Catholic Church in the Spanish colonies and their spouses had to obtain a certificate in the same way as those in the Peninsula did, that proved that they had no Jewish or Moorish ancestors.

Additionally, as early as the sixteenth century, shortly after the discovery of America, several regulations were enacted in the [[Laws of the Indies]] to prevent members of those religious groups and their descendants to emigrate and settle in the overseas colonies. These provisions are repeatedly stressed upon on following editions of the Laws, which provides an indication that the regulations were often ignored,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Encyclopedia of the Jewish diaspora: origins, experiences, and culture | publisher=ABC-CLIO | author=Avrum Ehrlich, Mark | year=2009 | page=689 | isbn=1-85109-873-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; most likely because colonial authorities at the time looked the other way, as the skills of those immigrants were badly needed.

==See also==
* The discussion of [[Casta]] makes it appear as if differentiation based upon privileges applied only to the distinction between mulattos, blacks and others in Nueva España. However, originally limpieza de sangre was used in the Iberian Peninsula to distinguish clearly between Spaniards and Moors/Jews.
*[[Caste system]]
*[[Ethnic cleansing]] (or ethnic purification)

==References==
{{reflist}}
* Douglass, William A. (2004) ''Sabino's sin: racism and the founding of Basque nationalism'' in [[Daniele Conversi]] (ed.), ''[http://easyweb.easynet.co.uk/conversi/ethnonat Ethnonationalism in the Contemporary World]''. London: Routledge, pp.&amp;nbsp;95–112.
*{{cite book| first=| last=| year=1850| title=''Códigos Españoles Concordados y Anotados'' Tomo Décimo. | editor = | pages= | publisher=[[M. Rivadeneyra]] |location=Calle Jesús del Valle #6, Madrid; [[Google Books]]|id= | url=http://books.google.com/books?id=MrgCAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA225&amp;dq=limpieza+de+Sangre&amp;as_brr=1#PPA5,M1| authorlink=}}
*{{cite book| first=| last=| year=1870| title=''Colección legislativa de España: Continuación de la colección de decretos (Primer Semestre de 1870)'' (Tomo CIII)| editor = | pages= | publisher=Ministerio de Gracia y Justicia.
 |location=Madrid; Google Books|id= | url=http://books.google.com/books?id=kMs2AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=RA3-PA1237&amp;dq=Primer+Semestre+de+1870&amp;as_brr=1#PPA1,M1| authorlink=}}

==External links==
*[http://translate.google.com/translate?js=n&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;layout=2&amp;eotf=1&amp;sl=es&amp;tl=en&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fpachami.com%2FInquisicion%2FLimpiezaSanMartin.html&amp;act=url Attestment of the purity of blood] of [[Justo Rufino de San Martín]] (brother of [[José de San Martín|José]]) in [[Paredes de Nava]], 1794. Note - Google translation from Spanish to English.

{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Limpieza De Sangre}}
[[Category:Al-Andalus]]
[[Category:Basque history]]
[[Category:Jewish Mexican history]]
[[Category:Jewish Portuguese history]]
[[Category:Jewish Spanish history]]
[[Category:Portuguese Inquisition]]
[[Category:Racism in Spain]]
[[Category:Spanish Inquisition]]
[[Category:Morisco]]

{{Link GA|fr}}

[[bg:Изискване за чистота на кръвта]]
[[ca:Neteja de sang]]
[[es:Estatutos de limpieza de sangre]]
[[eo:Limpieza de sangre]]
[[fr:Limpieza de sangre]]
[[he:טוהר הדם]]
[[pl:Limpieza de sangre]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>