<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050814214519|21021047" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1530922" pageid="1530922" ns="0" title="Limpieza de sangre"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-08-31T17:14:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''''[[Limpieza de sangre]]''' is also a novel in the [[Captain Alatriste]] series by [[Arturo Pérez-Reverte]].''
-----
'''''Limpieza de sangre''''' (in Spanish), '''''Limpeza de sangue''''' (in Portuguese), both meaning "cleanliness of [[blood]]" was a concept of [[Iberian peninsula|Iberian]] [[Modern Age|Modern]] History.
It refered to being [[ethnic cleansing|ethnically pure]] "[[Old Christian]]", without [[Jewish]] or [[Muslim]] ascendants.

After the end of the [[Reconquista]] and the expulsion of [[Sephardic]] Jews, the population of Spain and Portugal was all nominally Christian.
However, the descendants of the Christian conquerors despised the [[New Christians]], descendants of baptized Jews ([[Converso]]s or [[Marrano]]s) or [[Mudejar]]s ([[Morisco]]s).
Besides social and economic causes, the accusation was that the New Christians were false converts, keeping their former religion in their homes ([[Crypto-Jew]]s).
This was sometimes certain, but even people later declared saint by the Church could be suspected.
Cleanliness of blood was an issue of ancestry, not of personal religion.

This stratification made that the Old Christian [[commoner]]s could assert a right to honor (''[[honra]]'') even if they were not in the [[nobility]].
The [[military order]]s, [[guild]]s and other organizations started incorporating in their [[bylaw]]s, clauses demanding proof of cleanliness of blood.
Upward mobile New Christian families had to either content with their sort or bribe and falsify documents attesting generations of good Christians.
The [[Spanish Inquisition|Spanish]] and [[Portuguese Inquisition]]s had the New Christians as their main targets, since [[witchcraft]] was considered more a psychiatrical than a religious issue and [[Protestantism]] was promptly suffocated.

The claim to universal ''[[hidalgo|hidalguía]]'' (lowest nobility) of the [[Basque people|Basques]] was justified as the Arab invasion didn't reach the Basque territory, hence Basques had maintained the original purity while the rest of Spain was suspect of [[miscegenation]].
Even in the 19th century, the [[Basque nationalism]] of [[Sabino Arana]] demanded a list of original Basque surnames to rule out mixes with Spaniards.

==See also==
*[[Racism]]
*[[Apartheid]]
*[[Nuremberg laws]]
*[[Black Legend]]

{{christianity-stub}}

[[Category:Basque history]]
[[Category:Islamic history]]
[[Category:Jewish Spanish history]]
[[Category:Spanish Inquisition]]
[[Category:History of Portugal]]
[[Category:Racism]]

[[fr:Limpieza de sangre]]
[[es:Limpieza de sangre]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>