<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211009070104|1048996261" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1530922" pageid="1530922" ns="0" title="Limpieza de sangre"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-24T04:56:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Spanish oppressive policies against crypto-Jews and crypto-Muslims}}
{{Distinguish|text=''Limpieza de sangre'', a novel in the [[Captain Alatriste]] series by [[Arturo Pérez-Reverte]]}}
{{Italic title}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2020}}
The concept of {{lang|es|'''limpieza de sangre'''}} ({{IPA-es|limˈpjeθa ðe ˈsaŋɡɾe|lang}}), {{lang|pt|'''limpeza de sangue'''}} ({{IPA-pt|lĩˈpezɐ ðɨ ˈsɐ̃ɡɨ|lang}}, {{IPA-gl|limˈpeθɐ ðɪ ˈsaŋɡɪ|lang}}) or {{lang|ca|'''neteja de sang'''}} ({{IPA-ca|nəˈtɛʒə ðə ˈsaŋ|lang}}), literally "cleanliness of blood" and meaning "blood purity", was a system of [[racist]] discrimination used in [[Spanish Empire|early modern Spain]] and [[Portuguese Empire|Portugal]].

The label referred to those who were considered "[[Old Christian]]s", without recent ancestry from people who had not been Christian, such as [[Muslim]] or [[Jews|Jewish]] ancestors. In the context of the Spanish Empire, the concept defined castes of those of Spanish or Portuguese ancestry, as opposed to the non-Christian aboriginal populations of Asia, Africa and the Americas.

== After the Reconquista ==
By the end of the [[Reconquista]] and the conversion or expulsion of Muslim [[mudéjar]]s and [[Sephardi Jews]], the populations of [[Portugal]] and [[Spain]] were all nominally Christian. Spain's population of 7 million included up to a million recent converts from Islam and 200,000 converts from Judaism, who were collectively referred to as "[[New Christian]]s". Converts from Judaism were referred to as [[converso]]s and converts from Islam were known as [[Morisco]]s. A commonly leveled accusation was that the New Christians were false converts, secretly practicing their former religion as [[Crypto-Judaism|Crypto-Jews]] or [[Crypto-Islam|Crypto-Muslims]], many of whom indeed kept their traditions and customs secretly alive, such as (former) Jews keeping Sabbath or even deliberately working on Sundays. The concept of purity of blood came to be focused more on ancestry than of personal religion. 

The first statute of purity of blood was enacted in [[Toledo, Spain]], 1449,&lt;ref name="Chami"&gt;[http://pachami.com/Inquisicion/LimpiezaSangre.html Estatutos de Limpieza de Sangre], Pablo A. Chami.&lt;/ref&gt; where an anti-converso riot succeeded in gaining a ban on conversos and their descendants from most official positions. Initially, these statutes were condemned by the monarchy and the Church; however, in 1496, [[Pope Alexander VI]] approved a purity statute for the [[Hieronymites]].&lt;ref name="Chami"/&gt;

This stratification meant that the Old Christian [[commoner]]s might assert a right to [[honor]] even if they were not in the [[nobility]]. The religious and [[Military order (monastic society)|military order]]s, [[guild]]s and other organizations incorporated in their [[by-law]]s clauses demanding proof of cleanliness of blood. Upwardly mobile New Christian families had to either contend with discrimination, or bribe officials and falsify documents attesting generations of Christian ancestry.&lt;ref&gt;Maria Elena Martínrez, ''Genealogical Fictions: Limpieza de sangre, religion, and gender in colonial Mexico''. Stanford, Calif: Stanford University Press 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The claim to universal ''[[hidalgo (nobility)|hidalguía]]'' (lowest nobility) of the [[Basques]] was justified by intellectuals such as Manuel Larramendi (1690–1766).&lt;ref name="Larramendi"&gt;[[Manuel de Larramendi]], ''Corografía de la muy noble y muy leal provincia de Guipúzcoa'', Bilbao, 1986, facsimile edition of that from Editorial Ekin, Buenos Aires, 1950. (Also published by Tellechea Idígoras, San Sebastián, 1969.) Quoted in ''[http://www.uv.es/rseapv/Anales/97_98/A_117_139_La_idea_de_Espanya.pdf La idea de España entre los vascos de la Edad Moderna]'', by Jon Arrieta Alberdi, ''Anales 1997-1998'', Real Sociedad Económica Valenciana de Amigos del País.&lt;/ref&gt; Because the [[Umayyad conquest of Hispania]] had not reached the Basque territories, it was believed that Basques had maintained their original purity, while the rest of Spain was suspect of [[miscegenation]]. The universal hidalguía of Basques helped many of them to positions of power in the administration.&lt;ref name="Auñamendi"&gt;[http://www.euskomedia.org/aunamendi/100471 Limpieza de sangre] in the Spanish-language ''[[Auñamendi Encyclopedia]]''&lt;/ref&gt; This idea was reinforced by the fact that, as a result of the Reconquista, numerous Spanish noble lineages were already of Basque origin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Aranzadi, Juan|title=Milenarismo vasco: Edad de Oro, etnia y nativismo|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=D9C_ZQawvZkC&amp;pg=PT508|date=7 March 2012|publisher=Penguin Random House Grupo Editorial España|isbn=978-84-306-1581-0|pages=508–509}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Tests of ''limpieza de sangre'' had begun to lose their utility by the 19th century; rarely did persons have to endure the grueling inquisitions into distant parentage through birth records. However, laws requiring ''limpieza de sangre'' were still sometimes adopted even into the 19th century. For example, an edict of 8 March 1804 by King [[Ferdinand VII of Spain|Ferdinand VII]] resolved that no knight of the military orders might wed without having a council vouch for the ''limpieza de sangre'' of his spouse.&lt;ref&gt;Codigos Españoles Tome X. p. 225&lt;/ref&gt;

Official suppression of such entry requirements for the Army was enacted into law on 16 May 1865,&lt;ref&gt;''Colección Legislativa de España'' (1870), p. 364&lt;/ref&gt; and extended to naval appointments on 31 August of the same year. On 5 November 1865, a decree allowed children born out of wedlock, for whom ancestry could not be verified, to be able to enter into religious higher education (canons).&lt;ref&gt;''Colección Legislativa de España'' (1870), p. 365&lt;/ref&gt; On 26 October 1866, the test of blood purity was outlawed for the purposes of determining who might be admitted to college education. On 20 March 1870, a decree suppressed all use of blood purity standards in determining eligibility for any government position or any licensed profession.&lt;ref&gt;''Colección Legislativa de España'' (1870), p. 366&lt;/ref&gt;

The discrimination was still present into the 20th century in some places such as Majorca. No [[Xueta]] (descendants of the Majorcan conversos) priests were allowed to say Mass in a cathedral until the 1960s.&lt;ref name="JPerez"&gt;''Los judíos en España'', [[Joseph Pérez]]. Marcial Pons. Madrid (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Procedure to judge purity of blood===
The earliest known case judging ''Limpieza de Sangre'' comes from the Church of Cordoba, that explained the procedure to judge the purity of blood of candidates as follows: kneeling, with right hand placed over the image of a crucifix on a Bible, the candidates confirmed themselves as being of neither Jewish or Moorish extraction. Then the candidate provided the names and birthplaces of their parents and grandparents. Two delegates of the council, church or other public place would then research the information to make sure it was truthful. If the investigation had to be undertaken outside [[Córdoba, Spain|Córdoba]], a person, not necessarily a member of the council, would be appointed to examine the witnesses chosen by the candidate. This researcher would receive a sum per diem according to the that person's rank, the distance traveled and time spent. Having collected all the reports, the secretary or the notary had to read them all to the council, and a simple majority vote would decide whether the candidate was approved; after approval the candidate had to promise to obey all the laws and customs of the Church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Los estatutos de Limpieza de Sangre | author=Sicroff, Albert A. | page=121}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Spanish colonies==
{{See also|Casta}}
The concept of ''limpieza de sangre'' was a significant barrier for many Spaniards to emigrate to the Americas, since some form of proof of not having recent Muslim or Jewish ancestors was required to emigrate to the [[Spanish Empire]]. However, within Spain's overseas territories the concept evolved to be linked with racial purity for both Spaniards and indigenous.&lt;ref&gt;Maria Elena Martinez, ''Genealogical Fictions: Limpieza de Sangre, Religion, and Gender in Colonial Mexico.'' Stanford: Stanford University Press 2008, p. 270.&lt;/ref&gt; Proofs of racial purity were required in a variety of circumstances in both Spain and its overseas territories. Candidates for office and their spouses had to obtain a certificate of purity that proved that they had no Jewish or Muslim ancestors and in New Spain, proof of whiteness and absence of any in the lineage who had engaged in work with their hands.&lt;ref&gt;Martinez, ''Genealogical Fictions'', p. 273.&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, as early as the sixteenth century, shortly after the Spanish colonization of the Americas was initiated, several regulations were enacted in the [[Laws of the Indies]] to prevent Jews and Muslims and their descendants from emigrating to and settling in the overseas colonies.&lt;ref&gt;Maria Elena Martínez, "Limpieza de Sangre" in ''Encyclopedia of Mexico'', vol. 1, p. 751. Chicago: Fitzroy Dearborn 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; There was a thriving business in creating false documentation to allow conversos to emigrate to Spain's overseas territories.&lt;ref&gt;Alicia Gojman de Backal, "Conversos" in ''Encyclopedia of Mexico'', Chicago: Fitzroy Dearborn 1997, vol. 1, p.341.&lt;/ref&gt; The provisions banning emigration were repeatedly stressed in later editions of the Laws, which provides an indication that the regulations were often ignored,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Encyclopedia of the Jewish diaspora: origins, experiences, and culture | url=https://archive.org/details/encyclopediajewi00ehrl | url-access=limited | publisher=ABC-CLIO | author=Avrum Ehrlich, Mark | year=2009 | page=[https://archive.org/details/encyclopediajewi00ehrl/page/n721 689] | isbn=978-1-85109-873-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; most likely because colonial authorities at the time looked the other way as the skills of those immigrants were badly needed.  During the period when Portugal and Spain were ruled by the [[Iberian Union|same monarch]] (1580{{endash}}1640), Portuguese merchants, many of whom were [[Crypto-Judaism|crypto-Jews]], passing as Christians, became important members of the merchant communities in the viceregal capitals of Mexico City and Lima.  When Portugal successfully revolted in 1640 from Spain, the Holy Office of the [[Inquisition]] in both capitals initiated intensive investigations to identify and prosecute crypto-Jews, resulting in spectacular [[auto-da-fé|autos-da-fé]] in the mid-seventeenth century.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan I. Israel, ''Race, Class, and Politics in Colonial Mexico, 1610-1670.'' Oxford: Oxford University Press 1975, p. 245-46.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Society of Jesus==
[[Ignatius Loyola]], the founder of the [[Society of Jesus]] (Jesuits), said that "he would take it as a special grace from our Lord to come from Jewish lineage".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
|last=Reites |first=James W.|year=1981|title=St. Ignatius of Loyola and the Jews|url=https://ejournals.bc.edu/ojs/index.php/jesuit/article/viewFile/3714/3292 |journal=Studies in the Spirituality of Jesuits|volume=13|issue=4|location=St. Louis, Missouri|publisher=American Assistancy Seminar on Jesuit Spirituality |issn=2328-5575|access-date=18 June 2017 |page=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the first 30 years of the Society of Jesus, many Jesuits were ''[[converso]]s''. However, an anti-''converso'' faction led to the ''Decree de genere'' (1593), which proclaimed that either Jewish or Muslim ancestry, no matter how distant, was an insurmountable impediment for admission to the Society of Jesus - effectively applying the Spanish principle of ''Limpieza de sangre'' to Jesuits Europe-wide and world-wide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rosa |first1=De La |last2=Coello |first2=Alexandre |url=http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=24437295 |title=El Estatuto de Limpieza de Sangre de la Compañía de Jesús (1593) y su influencia en el Perú Colonial |journal=Archivum Historicum Societatis Iesu |pages=45–93 |publisher=Institutum Societatis Iesu |year=1932 |issn=0037-8887 |access-date=7 December 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141026074808/http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=24437295 |archive-date=26 October 2014 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Aleksander Maryks interprets the 1593 ''"Decree de genere"'' as preventing, despite [[St Ignatius of Loyola|Ignatius's]] desires, any Jewish or Muslim ''conversos'' and, by extension, any person with Jewish or Muslim ancestry, ''no matter how distant'', from admission to the Society of Jesus. Jesuit scholar John Padberg states that the restriction on Jewish/Muslim converts was limited only to the degree of parentage. Fourteen years later this was extended back to the fifth degree.  This 16th-century ''Decree de genere'' remained in force far longer among the Jesuits than in the Spanish state, though over time the restriction relating to Muslim ancestry was dropped&lt;ref name="padberg"&gt;{{cite book|last=Padberg|first=John W.|year=1994|title=For Matters of Greater Moment:The First Thirty Jesuit General Congregations|location=St. Louis, Missouri|publisher=Institute of Jesuit Sources|isbn=978-1-880810-06-4 |page=204}}&lt;/ref&gt; leaving only people of Jewish ancestry to be excluded. In 1923, the 27th Jesuit General Congregation reiterated that "The impediment of origin extends to all who are descended from the Jewish race, unless it is clear that their father, grandfather, and great grandfather have belonged to the Catholic Church." Only in 1946, in the aftermath of the Second World War, did the 29th General Congregation drop the requirement, but it still called for "cautions to be exercised before admitting a candidate about whom there is some doubt as to the character of his hereditary background".&lt;ref name="padberg"/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Nobility|Blue blood]]
* [[Cagot]]
* [[Casta]]
* [[Caste]]
* [[Converso]]
* [[Crypto-Judaism]]
* [[Inquisition]]
* [[Judaizer]]
* [[Marrano]]
* [[Malinchism]]
* [[One-drop rule]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*Alberro, Solange. ''Inquisición y sociedad en México, 1571-1700''. Mexico City: Fondo de Cultura Económica 1993.
*Beinart, Haim. ''Conversos ante la inquisición''. Jerusalem: Hebrew University 1965.
*Gitlitz, David. Secrecy and Deceit: The Religion of the Crypto-Jews, Albuquerque, NM: University of New Mexico Press, 2002. {{ISBN|082632813X}}
*Gojman de Backal, Alicia. "Conversos" in ''Encyclopedia of Mexico''. Chicago: Fitzroy Dearborn 1997, vol. 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;340–344.
*Gojman Goldberg, Alicia. ''Los conversos en la Nueva España''. Mexico City: Enep-Acatlan, UNAM 1984.
*Greenleaf, Richard E. ''The Mexican Inquisition in the Sixteenth Century''. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press 1969.
*Hering Torres, Max S., et al., eds. ''Race and Blood in the Iberian World''. Berlin: Lit, 2012.
*Kamen, Henry. ''The Spanish Inquisition''. London: Weidenfeld and Nicolson 1965.
*Lafaye, Jacques. ''Cruzadas y Utopias: El judeocristianismo en las sociedades Ibéricas''. Mexico City: Fondo de Cultura Económica 1984.
*[[John Tate Lanning|Lanning, John Tate]]. "Legitimacy and ''Limpieza de Sangre'' in the Practice of Medicine in the Spanish Empire." ''Jahrbuch für Geschicte 4 (1967)
*Liebman, Seymour. ''Los Judíos en México y en América Central''. Mexico city: Siglo XXI 1971.
*Martínez, Maria Elena. "Limpieza de Sangre" in ''Encyclopedia of Mexico'', vol. 1, pp. 749-752. chicago: Fitzroy Dearborn 1997.
*Roth, Norman, Conversos, Inquisition, and the Expulsion of the Jews from Spain, Madison, WI: University of Wisconsin Press, 1995. {{ISBN|0299142302}}
*Seed, Patricia. ''To Love, Honor, and Obey in Colonial Mexico: Conflicts over Marriage Choices, 1574-1821''. Stanford: Stanford University Press 1988.
*[[Sicroff, Albert A.]] ''Los estatutos de limpieza de sangre''. Translated by Mauro Armiño. Madrid: Tauros 1985.
{{div col end|2}}

==External links==
* [https://translate.google.com/translate?js=n&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;layout=2&amp;eotf=1&amp;sl=es&amp;tl=en&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fpachami.com%2FInquisicion%2FLimpiezaSanMartin.html&amp;act=url Attestment of the purity of blood] of [[Justo Rufino de San Martín]] (brother of [[José de San Martín|José]]) in [[Paredes de Nava]], 1794. Note - Google translation from Spanish to English.
* Douglass, William A. (2004) ''Sabino's sin: racism and the founding of Basque nationalism'' in [[Daniele Conversi]] (ed.), ''[https://web.archive.org/web/20061213222925/http://easyweb.easynet.co.uk/conversi/ethnonat Ethnonationalism in the Contemporary World]''. London: Routledge, pp.&amp;nbsp;95–112.
*{{cite book| year=1850| title=''Códigos Españoles Concordados y Anotados'' Tomo Décimo. | publisher=[[M. Rivadeneyra]] |location= Madrid |via= [[Google Books]]| url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MrgCAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=limpieza+de+Sangre&amp;pg=PA225}}
*{{cite book| year=1870| title=''Colección legislativa de España: Continuación de la colección de decretos (Primer Semestre de 1870)'' (Tomo CIII)| publisher=Ministerio de Gracia y Justicia.
 |location=Madrid; Google Books| url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kMs2AAAAIAAJ&amp;q=Primer+Semestre+de+1870&amp;pg=RA3-PA1237}}

{{Discrimination}}
{{Segregation by type}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Limpieza De Sangre}}
[[Category:Basque history]]
[[Category:Jewish Mexican history]]
[[Category:Jewish Portuguese history]]
[[Category:Jewish Spanish history]]
[[Category:Portuguese Inquisition]]
[[Category:Racism in Spain]]
[[Category:Spanish Inquisition]]
[[Category:Moriscos]]
[[Category:History of the conversos]]
[[Category:Racial antisemitism]]
[[Category:Latin American caste system]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>