<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081105201640|249899269" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="292285" pageid="292285" ns="0" title="State religion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T18:27:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Religion by Country}}
[[Image:State Religions.svg|right|thumb|300px|Nations with state religions:
{{legend|#EBCF16|[[Theravada Buddhism]] or [[Vajrayana Buddhism]]}}
{{legend|#158706|[[Islam]]}}
{{legend|#2FEB16|[[Shi'a Islam]]}}
{{legend|#0F5D05|[[Sunni Islam]]}}
{{legend|#0774F1|[[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox Christianity]]}}
{{legend|#062A87|[[Protestantism]] and [[Anglicanism]]}}
{{legend|#04E3F1|[[Roman Catholicism]]}}
]]

A '''state religion''' (also called an '''official religion''',  '''established church''' or '''state church''') is a [[religion|religious]] body or [[creed]] officially endorsed by the [[state]]. Practically, a state without a state religion is called a [[secular state]]. The term ''state church'' is associated with [[Christianity]], and is sometimes used to denote a specific national branch of Christianity. Closely related to state churches are what [[sociology|sociologists]] call [[ecclesia (sociology of religion)|ecclesiae]], though the two are slightly different. State religions are examples of the official or government-sanctioned [[establishment of religion]], as distinct from [[theocracy]]. It is also possible for a [[national church]] to become established without being under state control.

==Types of state churches==
The degree and nature of state backing for denomination or creed designated as a state religion can vary. It can range from mere endorsement and financial support, with freedom for other faiths to practice, to prohibiting any competing religious body from operating and to persecuting the followers of other sects. In Europe, competition between Catholic and Protestant denominations for state sponsorship in the 16th century evolved the principle ''[[cuius regio eius religio]]'' ("states follow the religion of the ruler") embodied in the text of the [[treaty]] that marked the [[Peace of Augsburg]], 1555. In [[England]] the monarch imposed Protestantism in 1533, with himself taking the place of the Pope, while in [[Scotland]] the [[Church of Scotland]] became the established Kirk in opposition to the religion of the ruler. 

In some cases, a state may have a set of state-sponsored religious denominations that it funds; such is the case in [[Alsace-Moselle]] in [[France]], following the pattern in [[Germany]].

In some [[communist state]]s, notably the [[People's Republic of China]], the state sponsors religious organizations, and activities outside those state-sponsored religious organizations are met with various degrees of official disapproval. In these cases, state religions are widely seen as efforts by the state to prevent alternate sources of authority.  

===State church vs state religion===
There is also a difference between a "state church" and  "state religion". A "state church" is created by a monarch,{{Fact|date=January 2008}} as in the cases of the [[Anglican Church]], created by [[Henry VIII]] or the [[Church of Sweden]], created by [[Gustav Vasa]]. An example of "state religion" is Argentina's acceptance of Catholicism as its religion. In the case of the former, the state has absolute control over the church, but in the case of the latter, in this example, the [[Holy See|Vatican]] has control over the church.

===Sociology of state churches===
[[Image:Secularmap.PNG|thumb|280px|Countries of the world with [[state religion]]s in red, those without in blue.]]
Sociologists refer to mainstream non-state religions as [[religious denomination|denominations]]. State religions tend to admit a larger variety of opinion within them than denominations. Denominations encountering major differences of opinion within themselves are likely to split; this option is not open for most state churches, so they tend to try to integrate differing opinions within themselves. 

However, state churches have divided, with the dissidents losing the advantages of state support. The [[Church of Scotland]] has split several times in the past for doctrinal reasons, including the meaning and acceptability of state support. Attempts by the monarch to impose [[bishop]]s on the Kirk led to the splitting off of the non-established [[Scottish Episcopal Church]]. Its largest offshoots from a [[Disruption of 1843|later disruption]] were the [[Free Church of Scotland (1843-1900)|Free Church of Scotland]] and later the [[United Free Church of Scotland]]. These offshoots lost the established status of their parent, but since 1929 the (partially) reunited Church of Scotland has considered itself to be a "[[national church]]" rather than an established church, as it is entirely independent of state control in matters spiritual. Legally, it remains established.  

Many sociologists now consider the effect of a state church as analogous to a chartered [[monopoly]] in religion. 

Where state religions exist, it is usually true the majority of residents are officially considered adherents; however, much of this support is little more than nominal; many members of the church rarely attend it. But the population's allegiance towards the state religion is often strong enough to prevent them from joining competing religious groups. 

A denomination's status as official religion does not always imply that the jurisdiction prohibits the existence or operation of other sects or religious bodies. It all depends upon the government and the level of tolerance the citizens of that country have for each other. Some countries with official religions have laws that guarantee the freedom of worship, full liberty of conscience, and places of worship for all citizens; and implement those laws more than other countries that do not have an official or established state religion.

==Disestablishment==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Liberal Party (UK)]] --&gt;
{{See|secular state}}
'''Disestablishment''' is the process of divesting a church of its status as an organ of the state. In England there was a campaign by [[The Liberal Party (UK)|Liberals]], [[dissenter]]s and [[nonconformists]] to disestablish the [[Church of England]] in the late 19th century; it failed in [[England]], but demands for the measure persist to this day. The [[Church of Ireland]] was disestablished in 1869 (effective 1871) and the Church of England was disestablished in Wales in 1920, the [[Church in Wales]] becoming separated from the Church of England in the process - it had formerly effectively been the Church of England and Wales. Those who wish to continue with an established church take a position of [[antidisestablishmentarianism]]. 

The [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] to the [[Constitution of the United States|US Constitution]] explicitly forbids the U.S. [[Federal government of the United States|federal]] [[government]] from enacting any law respecting a religious establishment, and thus forbids either designating an official church for the United States, or interfering with State and local official churches &amp;mdash; which were common when the First Amendment was enacted. It did not prevent [[state government]]s from establishing official churches. [[Connecticut]] continued to do so until it replaced its colonial [[Fundamental Orders of Connecticut|Charter]] with the [[History of Connecticut#The 1818 Constitution (1818-1890)|Connecticut Constitution of 1818]]; Massachusetts did not disestablish its official church until 1833, more than forty years after the ratification of the First Amendment; and local official establishments of religion persisted even later.

The [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] to the [[Constitution of the United States|US Constitution]], ratified in 1868, makes no mention of religious establishment, but forbids the states to "abridge the privileges or immunities" of U.S. citizens, or to "deprive any person of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law". In the 1947 case of [[Everson v. Board of Education]], the United States Supreme Court held that this later provision [[Incorporation (Bill of Rights)|incorporates]] the First Amendment's Establishment Clause as applying to the States, and thereby prohibits state and local religious establishments. The exact boundaries of this prohibition are still disputed, and are a frequent source of cases before the [[Supreme Court of the United States|US Supreme Court]] &amp;mdash; especially as the Court must now balance, on a state (equivalent to province) level, the First Amendment prohibitions on government establishment of official religions with the First Amendment prohibitions on government interference with the free exercise of religion. See [[school prayer]] for such a controversy in contemporary US politics.

All current U.S. state constitutions include guarantees of religious liberty parallel to the First Amendment, but eight ([[Arkansas]], [[Maryland]], [[Massachusetts]], [[North Carolina]], [[Pennsylvania]], [[South Carolina]], [[Tennessee]], and [[Texas]]) also contain clauses that prohibit atheists from holding public office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.godlessgeeks.com/LINKS/StateConstitutions.htm
|title=State Constitutions that Discriminate Against Atheists
|publisher=www.godlessgeeks.com
|accessdate=2007-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/texas.htm
|title=Religious laws and religious bigotry - Religious discrimination in U.S. state constitutions
|publisher=www.religioustolerance.com
|accessdate=2007-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, these clauses have been held by the [[United States Supreme Court]] to be unenforceable in the 1961 case of ''[[Torcaso v. Watkins]]'', where the court ruled unanimously that such clauses constituted a religious test incompatible with First and Fourteenth Amendment protections.

==Present state religions==
Currently, the following religions are recognized as state religions in some countries: some form of [[Christianity]], [[Islam]] and [[Buddhism]].

===Christian countries===
The following states recognize some form of [[Christianity]] as their state or official religion (by denomination):

====Roman Catholic====
Jurisdictions which recognize [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]] as their state or official religion:
*[[Argentina]]
*[[Bolivia]]
*[[Costa Rica]]
*[[El Salvador]]
*[[Liechtenstein]]
*[[Malta]]
*[[Monaco]]
*Some [[cantons of Switzerland]] (state religion):
**[[Appenzell Innerrhoden]] (declared "religion of the people of Appenzell Innerrhoden")
**[[Nidwalden]]
**[[Canton of Schwyz|Schwyz]]
**[[Canton of Uri|Uri]]
*[[Vatican City]] (official religion)

====Eastern Orthodox====
Jurisdictions which recognize one of the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]]es as their state religion:
*[[Greece]] ([[Church of Greece]])
*[[Cyprus]] ([[Cypriot Orthodox Church]])
*[[Finland]]: [[Finnish Orthodox Church]] has a special relationship with the Finnish state. The internal structure of the church is described in the Orthodox Church Act. The church has a power to tax its members and corporations, the majority of which is owned by them. The church does not consider itself a state church, as the state does not have the authority to affect its internal workings or theology.

====Lutheran====
Jurisdictions which recognize a [[Lutheranism|Lutheran]] church as their state religion:
*[[Denmark]] ([[Church of Denmark]])
*[[Iceland]] ([[Church of Iceland]])
*[[Norway]] ([[Church of Norway]])
*[[Finland]]: [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]] has a special relationship with the Finnish state, its internal structure being described in a special law, the Church Act. The Church Act can be amended only by a decision of the Synod of the Evangelical Lutheran Church and subsequent ratification by the parliament. The church has a power to tax its members and all corporations, except those the majority of which is owned by members of the [[Finnish Orthodox Church]]. The state collects these taxes for the church, for a fee. On the other hand, the church is required to give a burial place for everyone in its graveyards.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.eroakirkosta.fi/media/english/status_of_the_finnish_state_church_in_2007.html#privileges
|title=Status of the Finnish State Church in 2007&amp;mdash;Privileges of the State Church
|date=[[7 October]], [[2007]]
|publisher=eroakirkosta.fi
|accessdate = 2007-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Finnish president also decides the themes for the intercession days. The church does not consider itself a state church, as the Finnish state does not have the power to influence its internal workings or its theology, although it has a veto in those changes of the internal structure which require changing the Church Act. Neither does the Finnish state accord any precedence to Lutherans or the Lutheran faith in its own acts.

====Anglican====
Jurisdictions that recognise an [[Anglican]] church as their state religion:
*[[England]] ([[Church of England]])

====Reformed====
Jurisdictions which recognize a [[Reformed churches|Reformed]] church as their state religion:
*Some [[cantons of Switzerland]] ([[Swiss Reformed Church]]):
**[[Aargau]]
**[[Basel-Country]]
**[[Berne]]
**[[Glarus]]
**[[Graubünden]]
**[[Schwyz]]
**[[Thurgau]]
**[[Canton of Uri|Uri]]
**[[Canton of Zürich|Zurich]]
*[[Scotland]] – the [[Church of Scotland]] is the [[national church]], but is not a "state church" and has complete independence from the state in spiritual matters, thus being both established and free.&lt;ref name=OSCE&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://italy.usembassy.gov/pdf/other/rellib1.pdf
|format=PDF| title = Religious Liberty: The legal framework in selected OSCE countries.
| accessdate = 2007-04-06
| year = 2000
| month = May
| publisher = Law Library, U.S. Library of Congress
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;p.161&lt;/sup&gt; The [[Monarch of the United Kingdom]] is an ''ex officio'' member.

====Old Catholic====
Jurisdictions which recognize an [[Old Catholic Church|Old Catholic]] church as their state religion:
*Some [[cantons of Switzerland]] ([[Christian Catholic Church of Switzerland]]):
**[[Aargau]]
**[[Basel-Country]]
**[[Berne]]

===Islamic countries===
Countries which recognize [[Islam]] as their official religion. Although the [[separation of church and state]] is a concept that originated in a western context, there is the notion of [[religious toleration|toleration]] for [[people of the book]] in Islam.

*[[Afghanistan]] (Islamic state)
*[[Algeria]]
*[[Bahrain]]
*[[Bangladesh]]
*[[Brunei]]
*[[Comoros]]
*[[Egypt]]
*[[Indonesia]] (recognizes Islam as one of the six recognized religions, along with [[Protestantism]], [[Catholicism]], [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]], and [[Confucianism]]). Indonesia uses Islamic jurisprudence in private law. 
*[[Iran]] (Islamic state)
*[[Iraq]]
*[[Jordan]]
*[[Kuwait]]
*[[Libya]]
*[[Malaysia]]
*[[Maldives]]
*[[Mauritania]]
*[[Morocco]]
*[[Oman]]
*[[Pakistan]] (Islamic state)
*[[Qatar]]
*[[Sahrawi Arab Democratic Republic]] 
*[[Saudi Arabia]] (Islamic kingdom)
*[[Somalia]] 
*[[Somaliland]]
*[[Tunisia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.servat.unibe.ch/law/icl/ts00000_.html
|title=Tunisia - Constitution
|publisher=International Constitutional Law Project
|year=1991}}: "Article 1  [State] Tunisia is a free State, independent and sovereign; its religion is the Islam, its language is Arabic, and its form is the Republic"&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[United Arab Emirates]] 
*[[Yemen]] (Islamic state)

====Sunni Islam====

*[[Algeria]]
*[[Comoros]]
*[[Malaysia]]
*[[Maldives]]
*[[Mauritania]]
*[[Pakistan]] (as national-sanctioned religion)
*[[Saudi Arabia]] (as state-sanctioned religion)
*[[Somalia]]
*[[Jordan]]

====Shi'a Islam====

*[[Iran]] (as state-sanctioned religion)

===Buddhism as state religion===
Governments which recognize [[Buddhism]], either a specific form of, or the whole, as their official religion:

*[[Bhutan]] ([[Drukpa Kagyu]] school of [[Tibetan Buddhism]])&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.constitution.bt/draft_constitution_3rd_en.pdf
|title=Draft of Tsa Thrim Chhenmo
|date=[[August 1]], [[2007]]
|publisher=www.constitution.bt
|format=pdf
|accessdate=2007-10-18}}Article 3, Spiritual Heritage&lt;br /&gt;
1. Buddhism is the spiritual heritage of Bhutan, which promotes the principles and values of peace, non-violence, compassion and tolerance.&lt;br /&gt;
2. The Druk Gyalpo is the protector of all religions in Bhutan.&lt;br /&gt;
3. It shall be the responsibility of religious institutions and personalities to promote the spiritual heritage of the country while also ensuring that religion remains separate from politics in Bhutan. Religious institutions and personalities shall remain above politics.&lt;br /&gt;
4. The Druk Gyalpo shall, on the recommendation of the Five Lopons, appoint a learned and respected monk ordained in accordance with the Druk-lu, blessed with the nine qualities of a spiritual master and accomplished in ked-dzog, as the Je Khenpo.
5. His Holiness the Je Khenpo shall, on the recommendation of the Dratshang Lhentshog, appoint monks blessed with the nine qualities of a spiritual master and accomplished in ked-dzog as the Five Lopons.&lt;br /&gt;
6. The members of the Dratshang Lhentshog shall comprise:&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;(a) The Je Khenpo as Chairman;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;(b) The Five Lopons of the Zhung Dratshang; and&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;(c) The Secretary of the Dratshang Lhentshog who is a civil servant.&lt;br /&gt;
7. The Zhung Dratshang and Rabdeys shall continue to receive adequate funds and other facilities from the State.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Cambodia]] ([[Theravada Buddhism]])&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.constitution.org/cons/cambodia.htm
|title=Constitution of Cambodia
|publisher=constitution.org
|accessdate=2007-10-18}} (Article 43)&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Kalmykia]], a republic within the [[Russian Federation]] ([[Tibetan Buddhism]] - sole Buddhist entity in Europe)
*[[Sri Lanka]] ([[Theravada Buddhism]] - The constitution accords Buddhism the "foremost place," but Buddhism is not recognized as the state religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.priu.gov.lk/Cons/1978Constitution/
|title=The Constitution of the Republic of Sri lanka
|chapter=Chapter II &amp;mdash; Buddhism
|chapter-url=http://www.priu.gov.lk/Cons/1978Constitution/Chapter_02_Amd.html
|publisher=The Official Website of the Government of Sri Lanka
|accessdate=2007-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Thailand]] ([[Theravada Buddhism]])
*[[Tibet Government in Exile]] ([[Gelugpa]] school of [[Tibetan Buddhism]])

===Additional notes===
* [[Israel]] is defined in several of its laws as a democratic Jewish state. However, the term "[[Jew]]ish" is a [[polysemy|polyseme]] that can relate equally to the Jewish people or religion (see: [[Who is a Jew?]]). The debate about the meaning of the term Jewish and its legal and social applications (considering that it comes alongside the term "[[democratic]]") is one of the most profound issues with which Israeli society deals. At present, there is no specific law or official statement establishing the Jewish ''religion'' as the state's religion. However, the State of Israel supports religious institutions, particularly [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jewish]] ones, and recognizes the "religious communities" as carried over from those recognized under the British Mandate. These are: Jewish and Christian (Eastern Orthodox, Latin [Catholic], Gregorian-Armenian, Armenian-Catholic, Syrian [Catholic], Chaldean [Uniate], Greek Catholic Melkite, Maronite, and Syrian Orthodox). The fact that the Muslim population was not defined as a religious community is a vestige of the Ottoman period{{Fact|date=February 2008}} during which Islam was the dominant religion and does not affect the rights of the Muslim community to practice their faith. At the end of the period covered by this report, several of these denominations were pending official government recognition; however, the Government has allowed adherents of not officially recognized groups freedom to practice. In 1961, legislation gave Muslim Shari'a courts exclusive jurisdiction in matters of personal status. Three additional religious communities have subsequently been recognized by Israeli law &amp;ndash; the [[Druze]] (prior under Islamic jurisdiction), the Evangelical Episcopal Church, and the [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'í]].[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2003/24453.htm] These groups have their own religious courts as official state courts for personal status matters (see [[Millet (Ottoman Empire)|millet system]]). The structure and goals of the [[Chief Rabbinate of Israel]] are governed by Israeli law, but the law does not say explicitly that it is a state Rabbinate. Non-recognition of other streams of Judaism is the cause of some controversy. As of 2007, there is no civil marriage in Israel, although there is recognition of marriages performed abroad.

*[[Nepal]] was once the world's only Hindu state, but has ceased to be so following a declaration by the Parliament in 2006. 

* Many countries indirectly fund the activities of different religious denominations by granting tax-exempt status to churches and religious institutions which qualify as [[charitable organization]]s.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p1828.pdf
|format=PDF| title = Tax guide for churches and Religious Institutions
| accessdate = 2006-11-23
| author = Internal Revenue Service
| publisher = United States Department of the Treasury
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.irs.gov/charities/charitable/article/0,,id=96099,00.html
| title = Exemption Requirements
| accessdate = 2006-11-23
| accessmonthday = 
| accessyear = 
| author = Internal Revenue Seervice
| publisher = United States Department of the Treasury
}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, these religions are not established as state religions.

==Ancient state religions==
===Egypt and Sumer===
The concept of state religions was known as long ago as the empires of [[Egypt]] and [[Sumer]], when every city state or people had its own god or gods. Many of the early Sumerian rulers were priests of their patron city god. Some of the earliest semi-mythological kings may have passed into the pantheon, like [[Dumuzid]], and some later kings came to be viewed as divine soon after their reigns, like [[Sargon the Great]] of [[Akkad]]. One of the first rulers to be proclaimed a god during his actual reign was [[Gudea]] of [[Lagash]], followed by some later kings of [[Ur]], such as [[Shulgi]]. Often, the state religion was integral to the power base of the reigning government, such as in Egypt, where Pharaohs were often thought of as embodiments of the god Horus. 

===Persian empire===
[[Zoroastrianism]] was the state religion of the [[Sassanid dynasty]] which lasted until 651, when Persia was conquered by the forces of Islam. However, it persisted as the state religion of the independent state of [[Hyrcania]] until the 15th century. 

The tiny kingdom of [[Adiabene]] in northern Mesopotamia converted to Judaism around 34 AD.

===Greek city-states===
Many of the Greek city-states also had a 'god' or 'goddess' associated with that city. This would not be the 'only god' of the city, but the one that received special honors. In ancient Greece the city of [[Athens]] had [[Athena]], [[Sparta]] had [[Artemis]], [[Delos]] had [[Apollo]] and Artemis, and [[Olympia, Greece|Olympia]] had [[Zeus]].

===Roman Religion and Christianity===
In Rome, the office of ''[[Pontifex Maximus]]'' came to be reserved for the emperor, who was often —declared a 'god' posthumously, or sometimes during his reign. Failure to worship the emperor as a god was at times punishable by death, as the Roman government sought to link emperor worship with loyalty to the Empire. Many Christians and Jews were subject to persecution, torture and death in the Roman Empire, because it was against their beliefs to worship the emperor.

In 311, Emperor [[Galerius]], on his deathbed, declared a religious indulgence to Christians throughout the Roman Empire, focusing on the ending of anti-Christian persecution. [[Constantine I]] and [[Licinius]], the two ''Augusti'', by the [[Edict of Milan]] of 313, enacted a law allowing religious freedom to everyone within the Roman Empire. Furthermore, the Edict of Milan cited that Christians may openly practice their religion unmolested and unrestricted, and provided that properties taken from Christians be returned to them unconditionally. Although the Edict of Milan allowed religious freedom throughout the empire, it did not abolish nor disestablish the Roman state cult (Roman polytheistic paganism). The Edict of Milan was written in such a way as to implore the blessings of the deity.

Constantine called up the [[First Council of Nicaea]] in 325, although he was not a baptised Christian until years later. Despite enjoying considerable popular support, Christianity was still not the official state religion in Rome, although it was in some neighboring states such as [[Armenia]] and [[Kingdom of Aksum|Aksum]].

[[Roman Religion]] ([[Neoplatonic]] [[Religion in ancient Greece|Hellenism]]) was restored for a time by [[Julian the Apostate]] from 361 to 363. Julian does not appear to have reinstated the persecutions of the earlier [[Roman emperors]].

[[Catholic]] Christianity, as opposed to Arianism and other heretical{{POV-statement|date=December 2007}} and schismatic groups, was declared to be the state religion of the [[Roman Empire]] on [[February 27]] [[380]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Theodosian Code |url=http://www.ancienttexts.org/library/latinlibrary/theod.html |work=THE LATIN LIBRARY at Ad Fontes Academy|publisher=Ad Fontes Academy |accessdate=2006-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; by the decree ''De Fide Catolica'' of Emperor [[Theodosius I]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Theodosian Code XVI.i.2 |url=http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/theodcodeXVI.html |work=Medieval Sourcebook: Banning of Other Religions |first=Paul |last=Halsall |year=1997 |month=June |publisher=Fordham University |accessdate=2006-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Han Dynasty Confucianism and Sui Dynasty Buddhism===
In China, the [[Han Dynasty]] (206 BC &amp;ndash; 220 AD) advocated [[Confucianism]] as the ''de facto'' state religion, establishing tests based on Confucian texts as an entrance requirement into government service. The Han emperors appreciated the societal order which is a central concept of Confucianism. Confucianism would continue on as the state religion until the [[Sui Dynasty]] (581-618), when it was replaced by [[Buddhism]]. [[Neo-confucianism]] returned as the ''de facto'' state religion sometime in the 10th century. Note however, there is a debate over whether Confucianism (including Neo-confucianism) is a religion or purely a philosophical system.

==Modern era==
===Empire of Japan===
From the [[Meiji era]] to the first part of the [[Showa era]], '' [[State Shinto|Koshitsu Shinto]]'' was established in Japan as the national religion. According to this, the [[emperor of Japan]] was an [[arahitogami]], an incarnate divinity and the offspring of goddess [[Amaterasu]]. As the emperor was, according to the constitution, "head of the empire" and "supreme commander of the Army and the Navy", every Japanese citizen had to obey his will and show absolute loyalty.

==States without any state religion==
These states do not profess any state religion, and are generally [[secularism|secular]] or [[Laïcité|laist]]. Countries which officially decline to establish any religion include:

*[[Australia]]
*[[Azerbaijan]]
*[[Brazil]] Laist State since 1988.
*[[Canada]]
*[[Chile]]
*[[Cuba]]
*[[People's Republic of China]]
*[[France]]
*[[Hungary]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.legislationline.org/upload/legislations/cd/86/39b1e5cc4b9b9b6a97c2830f3608.htm Constitution of the Republic of Hungary]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.magyarorszag.hu/english/keyevents/a_alpolg/a_allampolgarsagemberijogok/a_alapjog20050805/a_gondlelkiismjog20060627.html The right of thought, the freedom of conscience and religion –Hungary.hu]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[India]]
*[[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]]
*[[Israel]] (which considers itself a "democratic Jewish state", although "[[Jewish]]" might be construed to refer to the people rather than the religion)
*[[Jamaica]]
*[[Japan]] (Shinto until end of WWII)
*[[Kosovo]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kushtetutakosoves.info/?cid=2,247 Draft Constitution of the Republic of Kosovo]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Lebanon]] (although president must always remain a Maronite Catholic, and prime minister a Sunni Muslim)
*[[Mexico]]
*[[Montenegro]]
*[[Nepal]] (declared a secular state on [[May 18]], [[2006]], by the newly resumed House of Representatives)
*[[New Zealand]]
*[[Nigeria]]
*[[North Korea]]
*[[Philippines]] ([[Roman Catholic Church]] is a ''de facto'' state religion)
*[[Romania]]
*[[Russia]]
*[[Singapore]]
*[[South Africa]]
*[[South Korea]]
*[[Spain]]
*[[Sweden]] ([[Lutheran]] ([[Church of Sweden]]) until [[December 31]], [[1999]].)
*[[Turkey]]
*[[United States]]
*[[Venezuela]]
*[[Vietnam]]

==Established churches and former state churches==

{| class="sortable wikitable"
! Country || Church || Denomination || Disestablished
|-
| [[Albania]]{{ref|Albania|1}} || none since independence ||N/A || n/a
|-
| [[Andorra]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || ?
|-
| [[Anhalt]] || [[Evangelical Church of Anhalt]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Armenia]] || [[Armenian Apostolic Church]] || [[Oriental Orthodox]] || 1921
|-
| [[Austria]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1918
|-
| [[Baden, Germany|Baden]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] and the [[Evangelical Church of Baden]] || [[Catholic]] and [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Bavaria]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1918
|-
| [[Brazil]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1890
|-
| [[Brunswick-Lüneburg]] || [[Protestant Lutheran State Church of Brunswick|Evangelical Lutheran State Church of Brunswick]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Bulgaria]] || [[Bulgarian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1946
|-
| [[Chile]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1925
|-
| [[Cuba]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1902
|-
| [[Cyprus]] || [[Cypriot Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1977
|-
| [[Czechoslovakia]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1920
|-
| [[Denmark]] || [[Church of Denmark]] || [[Lutheran]] || no
|-
| [[England]] || [[Church of England]] || [[Anglican]] || no
|-
| [[Estonia]] || [[Estonian Apostolic Orthodox Church|Church of Estonia]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1940
|-
| [[Finland]]{{ref|Finland|2}} || [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1870/1919
|-
| [[France]]{{ref|France|3}} || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1905
|-
| [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] || [[Georgian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1921
|-
| [[Greece]] || [[Church of Greece|Greek Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] ||  no
|-
| [[Guatemala]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1871
|-
| [[Haiti]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1987
|-
| [[Hesse]] || [[Evangelical Church of Hesse and Nassau]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Hungary]]{{ref|Hungary|4}} || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1848
|-
| [[Iceland]] || [[National Church of Iceland|Lutheran Evangelical Church]] || [[Lutheran]] || no
|-
| [[Ireland]] || [[Church of Ireland]] || [[Anglican]] || 1871
|-
| [[Italy]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1984
|-
| [[Lebanon]] || [[Maronite Catholic Church]]/[[Islam]] || [[Catholic]]/[[Islam]] || no
|-
| [[Liechtenstein]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || no
|-
| [[Lippe]] || [[Church of Lippe]] || [[Reformed churches|Reformed]] || 1918
|-
| [[Lithuania]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1940
|-
| [[Lübeck]] || [[North Elbian Evangelical Church]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Luxembourg]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || ?
|-
| [[Republic of Macedonia]] || [[Macedonian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || no
|-
| [[Malta]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || no
|-
| [[Mecklenburg]] || [[Evangelical Church of Mecklenburg]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Mexico]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1874
|-
| [[Monaco]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || no
|-
| [[Mongolia]] || [[Buddhism]] || n/a || 1926
|-
| [[Netherlands]] || [[Dutch Reformed Church]] || [[Reformed churches|Reformed]] || 1795
|-
| [[Norway]] || [[Church of Norway]] || [[Lutheran]] || no
|-
| [[Oldenburg]] || [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in Oldenburg|Evangelical Lutheran Church of Oldenburg]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Panama]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1904
|-
| [[Philippines]]{{ref|Philippines|5}} || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1902
|-
| [[Poland]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1939
|-
| [[Portugal]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1910
|-
| [[Prussia]] || [[Evangelical Church in Germany|13 provincial churches]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Romania]] || [[Romanian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1947
|-
| [[Russia]] || [[Russian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1917
|-
| [[Thuringia]] || [[Evangelical Church in Thuringia]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Saxony]] || [[Evangelical Church of Saxony]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Schaumburg-Lippe]] || [[Evangelical Church of Schaumburg-Lippe]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Scotland]]{{ref|Scotland|6}}  || [[Church of Scotland]] || [[Presbyterian]] || no
|-
| [[Serbia]] || [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern]] || ? 
|-
| [[Spain]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1978
|-
| [[Sweden]] || [[Church of Sweden]] || [[Lutheran]] || 2000
|-
| [[Switzerland]] || none since the adoption of the Federal Constitution (1848) || n/a || n/a
|-
| [[Turkey]] || [[Islam]] || [[Islam]] || 1928
|-
| [[Uruguay]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1919
|-
| [[Waldeck (principality)|Waldeck]] || [[Evangelical Church of Hesse-Kassel and Waldeck]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Wales]]{{ref|Wales|7}} || [[Church in Wales]] || [[Anglican]] || 1920
|-
| [[Württemberg]] || [[Evangelical Church of Württemberg]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|}

{{note|Albania|Note 1:}}
In 1967, the Albanian government made [[state atheism|atheism]] the "state religion". This designation remained in effect until 1991.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite book
 | last = Zickel 
 | first = Raymond
 | editor = Walter R. Iwaskiw
 | title = Albania: A Country Study 
 | url = http://countrystudies.us/albania/index.htm
 | accessdate = 2007-04-25
 | series = Area Handbook Series
 | year = 1994
 | month = June
 | publisher = Headquarters Dept. of Army; 2nd ed
 | isbn = 0844407925
 | chapter = Hoxha's Antireligious Campaign
 | chapterurl = http://countrystudies.us/albania/56.htm
 | quote = All previous decrees that had officially sanctioned the nominal existence of organized religion were annulled in 1967. Subsequently, the 1976 constitution banned all "fascist, religious, warmongerish, antisocialist activity and propaganda," and the penal code of 1977 imposed prison sentences of three to ten years for "religious propaganda and the production, distribution, or storage of religious literature."
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{note|Finland|Note 2:}}
Finland's State Church was the [[Church of Sweden]] until 1809. As an autonomous Grand Duchy under Russia 1809-1917, Finland retained the Lutheran State Church system, and a state church separate from Sweden, later named the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]], was established. It was detached from the state as a separate judicial entity when the new church law came to force in 1870. After Finland had gained independence in 1917, religious freedom was declared in the constitution of 1919 and a separate law on religious freedom in 1922. Through this arrangement, the Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland lost its position as a state church but gained a constitutional status as a national church alongside with the [[Finnish Orthodox Church]], whose position however is not codified in the constitution.

{{note|France|Note 3:}}
In France the [[Concordat of 1801]] made the Roman Catholic, [[Calvinist]] and [[Lutheran]] churches state-sponsored religions, as well as [[Judaism]]. 

{{note|Hungary|Note 4:}}
In Hungary the constitutional laws of 1848 declared five established churches on equal status: the [[Roman Catholic]], [[Calvinist]], [[Lutheran]], [[Eastern Orthodox]] and [[Unitarianism|Unitarian]] Church. In 1868 the law was ratified again after the [[Ausgleich]]. In 1895 [[Judaism]] was also recognized as the sixth established church. In 1948 every distinction between the different denominations were abolished.

{{note|Philippines|Note 5:}}
Disestablished by the Philippine Organic Act of 1902, although the Roman Catholic Church itself is often treated as a ''de facto'' state religion in the country today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.chanrobles.com/philippinebillof1902.htm
|title=Philippine Organic Act of 1902
|publisher=Chanrobles law library
|date=[[july 1]], [[1902]]
|accessdate=2007-07-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{note|Scotland|Note 6:}}
The Church of Scotland is "established" in the sense that its system of church courts was set up by
Parliament, but over the centuries it has resisted interference by secular authorities. The Church of Scotland Act
1921 recognizes its exclusive authority to decide ecclesiastical issues, and the statute incorporates and accepts
the Church's Declaratory Articles as lawful.&lt;ref name=OSCE/&gt;&lt;sup&gt;p.161&lt;/sup&gt;

{{note|Wales|Note 7:}}
The [[Church in Wales]] was split from the [[Church of England]] in 1920 by [[Welsh Church Act 1914]]; at the same time becoming disestablished.

==Former state churches in British North America==
===Protestant colonies===
*The colonies of [[Plymouth Colony|Plymouth]], [[Massachusetts Bay Colony|Massachusetts Bay]], [[New Haven Colony|New Haven]], and [[Province of New Hampshire|New Hampshire]] were founded by Puritan, Calvinist, Protestants.
*[[New Netherland]] was founded by [[Dutch Reformed]] Calvinists.
*The colonies of [[Province of New York|New York]], [[Colony of Virginia|Virginia]], [[Province of North Carolina|North Carolina]], [[Province of South Carolina|South Carolina]], and [[Province of Georgia|Georgia]] were officially [[Anglican]].

===Catholic colonies===
*When [[New France]] was transferred to [[Great Britain]] in 1763, the [[Roman Catholic Church]] remained under toleration, but [[Huguenot]]s were allowed entrance where they had formerly been banned from settlement by Parisian authorities.
*The [[Colony of Maryland]] was founded by a charter granted in 1632 to George Calvert, secretary of state to Charles I, and his son Cecil, both recent converts to Roman Catholicism. Under their leadership many English Catholic gentry families settled in Maryland. However, the colonial government was officially neutral in religious affairs, granting toleration to all Christian groups and enjoining them to avoid actions which antagonized the others. On several occasions low-church dissenters led insurrections which temporarily overthrew the Calvert rule. In 1689, when William and Mary came to the English throne, they acceded to demands to revoke the original royal charter. In 1701 the Anglican Church was established, and in the course of the eighteenth century Maryland Catholics were first barred from public office, then disenfranchised, although not all of the laws passed against them (notably laws restricting property rights and imposing penalties for sending children to be educated in foreign Catholic institutions) were enforced, and some Catholics even continued to hold public office.
*[[Spanish Florida]] was ceded to [[Great Britain]] in 1763, the British divided Florida into two colonies. Both East and West Florida continued a policy of toleration for the Catholic Residents.

===Colonies with no established church===
*The [[Province of Pennsylvania]] was founded by [[Religious Society of Friends|Quakers]], but the colony never had an established church.
*[[West Jersey]], also founded by [[Quakers]], prohibited any establishment. 
*[[Delaware Colony]] had no established church.
*The [[Colony of Rhode Island and Providence Plantations]], founded by religious dissenters forced to flee the Massachusetts Bay colony, is widely regarded as the first polity to grant religious freedom to all its citizens.

===Tabular Summary===
{| class="wikitable"
! Colony || Denomination || Disestablished{{ref|Disestablishment|1}}
|-
| [[Connecticut Colony|Connecticut]] || [[Congregational church|Congregational]] || 1818
|-
| [[Province of Georgia|Georgia]] || [[Church of England]] || 1789{{ref|GA|2}}
|-
| [[Province of Maryland|Maryland]] || [[Church of England]] || 1776
|-
| [[Province of Massachusetts Bay|Massachusetts]] || [[Congregational church|Congregational]] || 1780{{ref|MA|3}}
|-
| [[New Brunswick]] || [[Church of England]] ||
|-
| [[Province of New Hampshire|New Hampshire]] || [[Congregational church|Congregational]] || 1790{{ref|NH|4}}
|-
| [[Colony of Newfoundland|Newfoundland]] || [[Church of England]]
|-
| [[Province of North Carolina|North Carolina]] || [[Church of England]] || 1776{{ref|NC|5}}
|-
| [[Nova Scotia]] || [[Church of England]] || 1850
|-
| [[Prince Edward Island]] || [[Church of England]] ||
|-
| [[Province of South Carolina|South Carolina]] || [[Church of England]] || 1790
|-
| [[Canada West]] || [[Church of England]] || 1854
|-
| [[West Florida]] || [[Church of England]] || N/A{{ref|WFL|6}}&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;{{ref|EWFL|8}}
|-|
| [[East Florida]] || [[Church of England]] || N/A{{ref|EFL|7}}&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;{{ref|EWFL|8|noid=noid}}
|-
| [[Virginia Colony|Virginia]] || [[Church of England]] || 1786{{ref|VA|9}}
|-
| [[West Indies]] || [[Church of England]] || 1868
|}
{{Note|Disestablishment|Note 1:}}
In several colonies, the establishment ceased to exist in practice at the [[American Revolution|Revolution]], about 1776;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Rights of the People: Individual freedom and the Bill of Rights |url=http://usinfo.state.gov/products/pubs/rightsof/roots.htm |year=2003 |month=December |publisher=US State Department |accessdate=2007-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; this is the date of permanent legal abolition. 

{{Note|GA|Note 2:}}
in 1789 the Georgia Constitution was amended as follows:
"Article IV. Section 10. No person within this state shall, upon any pretense, be deprived of the inestimable privilege of worshipping God in any manner agreeable to his own conscience, nor be compelled to attend any place of worship contrary to his own faith and judgment; nor shall he ever be obliged to pay tithes, taxes, or any other rate, for the building or repairing any place of worship, or for the maintenance of any minister or ministry, contrary to what he believes to be right, or hath voluntarily engaged. To do. No one religious society shall ever be established in this state, in preference to another; nor shall any person be denied the enjoyment of any civil right merely on account of his religious principles."

{{Note|MA|Note 3:}}
From 1780 Massachusetts had a system which required every man to belong to a church, and permitted each church to tax its members, but forbade any law requiring that it be of any particular denomination. This was objected to, as in practice establishing the Congregational Church, the majority denomination, and was abolished in 1833. 

{{Note|NH|Note 4:}}
Until 1877 the New Hampshire Constitution required members of the State legislature to be of the Protestant religion.

{{Note|NC|Note 5:}}
The North Carolina Constitution of 1776 disestablished the Anglican church, but until 1835 the NC Constitution allowed only Protestants to hold public office. From 1835-1876 it allowed only Christians (including Catholics) to hold public office. Article VI, Section 8 of the current NC Constitution forbids only atheists from holding public office.&lt;ref&gt;[http://statelibrary.dcr.state.nc.us/nc/stgovt/article_vi.htm Article VI of the North Carolina state constitition]&lt;/ref&gt;  Such clauses were held by the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] to be unenforceable in the 1961 case of [[Torcaso v. Watkins]], when the court ruled unanimously that such clauses constituted a religious test incompatible with [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First]] and [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth]] Amendment protections. 

{{Note|WFL|Note 6:}}
Religious Tolerance for Catholics with an Established Church of England were policy in the former Spanish Colonies of East and West Florida while under British rule.

{{Note|EFL|Note 7:}}
Religious tolerance for Catholics with an established Church of England were policy in the former Spanish Colonies of East and West Florida while under British rule.

{{Note|EWFL|Note 8:}}
In [[Treaty of Paris (1783)]], which ended the [[American Revolutionary War]], the British ceded both East and West Florida back to Spain (see [[Spanish Florida]]).

{{Note|VA|Note 9:}}
Tithes for the support of the Anglican Church in Virginia were suspended in 1776, and never restored. 1786 is the date of the [[Virginia Statute of Religious Freedom]], which prohibited any coercion to support any religious body.

==State of Deseret==
The [[State of Deseret]] was a provisional [[US State|state]] of the [[United States]], proposed in 1849 by [[Mormon]] settlers in [[Salt Lake City]]. The provisional state existed for slightly over two years, but attempts to gain recognition by the United States government floundered for various reasons. The [[Utah Territory]] which was then founded was under Mormon control, and repeated attempts to gain statehood met resistance, in part due to concerns over the principle of separation of church and state conflicting with the practice of members of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] of placing their highest value on "following counsel" in virtually all matters relating to their church-centered lives. The state of [[Utah]] was eventually admitted to the union on [[January 4]] [[1896]], after the various issues had been resolved.&lt;ref&gt;[http://historytogo.utah.gov/utah_chapters/statehood_and_the_progressive_era/struggleforstatehood.html Struggle For Statehood] Edward Leo Lyman, ''Utah History Encyclopedia''&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[Civil religion]]
* [[Political religion]]
* [[Separation of church and state]]
* [[Freedom of religion]]
* [[Status of religious freedom by country]]
* [[Religious toleration]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{cite journal
 | quotes = 
 | last = McConnell
 | first = Michael W. 
 | authorlink = 
 | coauthors = 
 |year=2003
 | month = April
 | title = Establishment and Disestablishment at the Founding, Part I: Establishment of Religion
 | journal = William and Mary Law Review, provided by Questia.com
 | volume = 44
 | issue = 5
 | pages = 2105
 | doi = 
 | id = 
 | url = http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=5002019127&amp;er=deny
 | format = 
 | accessdate = 2006-11-23
 }}

[[Category:Religious law]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Separation of church and state]]

[[am:የመንግሥት ሃይማኖት]]
[[ar:ديانة رسمية]]
[[da:Statskirke]]
[[de:Staatsreligion]]
[[es:Estado confesional]]
[[fr:Religion d'État]]
[[ko:국교]]
[[mk:Државна религија]]
[[nl:Staatsgodsdienst]]
[[ja:国家宗教]]
[[no:Statskirke]]
[[nn:Statsreligion]]
[[pl:Religia państwowa]]
[[pt:Estado confessional]]
[[ro:Religie de stat]]
[[ru:Государственная религия]]
[[simple:State religion]]
[[fi:Valtionuskonto]]
[[sv:Statsreligion]]
[[zh:國教]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>