<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112233601|87427750" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="292285" pageid="292285" ns="0" title="State religion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T06:34:42Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:State Religions.png|right|thumb|300px|Nations with state religions:
{{legend|#04E3F1|[[Roman Catholic Church]]}}
{{legend|#062A87|[[Protestantism]]}}
{{legend|#0774F1|[[Orthodox Christianity]]}}
{{legend|#158706|[[Islam]]}}
{{legend|#0F5D05|[[Sunni Islam]]}}
{{legend|#2FEB16|[[Shi'a Islam]]}}
{{legend|#EBCF16|[[Buddhism]]}}]]

A '''state religion''' (also called an '''official religion''',  '''established church''' or '''state church''') is a [[religion|religious]] body or [[creed]] officially endorsed by the [[state]]. The term ''state church'' is associated with [[Christianity]], and is sometimes used to denote a specific national branch of Christianity. Closely related to state churches are what [[sociology|sociologists]] call [[ecclesia (sociology of religion)|ecclesiae]], though the two are slightly different. State religions are examples of the official or government-sanctioned [[establishment of religion]], as distinct from [[theocracy]]. It is also possible for a [[national church]] to become established without being under state control.

==Types of state churches==
The degree and nature of state backing for denomination or creed designated as a state religion can vary. It can range from mere endorsement and financial support, with freedom for other faiths to practice, to prohibiting any competing religious body from operating and to persecuting the followers of other sects. In Europe, competition between Catholic and Protestant denominations for state sponsorship in the 16th century evolved the principle ''[[cuius regio eius religio]]'' ("states follow the religion of the ruler") embodied in the text of the [[treaty]] that marked the [[Peace of Augsburg]], [[1555]]. In [[England]] the monarch imposed Protestantism, with himself taking the place of the Pope, while in [[Scotland]] the [[Church of Scotland]] became the established Kirk in opposition to the religion of the ruler. 

In some cases, a state may have a set of state-sponsored religious denominations that it funds; such is the case in [[Alsace-Moselle]] in [[France]], following the pattern in [[Germany]].

In some [[communist state]]s, notably the [[People's Republic of China]], the state sponsors religious organizations, and activities outside those state-sponsored religious organizations are met with various degrees of official disapproval. In these cases, state religions are widely seen as efforts by the state to prevent alternate sources of authority.  

===Sociology of state churches===
Sociologists refer to mainstream non-state religions as [[religious denomination|denominations]]. State religions tend to admit a larger variety of opinion within them than denominations. Denominations encountering major differences of opinion within themselves are likely to split; this option is not open for most state churches, so they tend to try to integrate differing opinions within themselves. 

However, state churches have divided, with the dissidents losing the advantages of state support. The [[Church of Scotland]] has split several times in the past for doctrinal reasons, including the meaning and acceptability of state support. Attempts by the monarch to impose [[bishop]]s on the Kirk led to the splitting off of the non-established [[Scottish Episcopal Church]]. Its largest offshoots from a [[Disruption of 1843|later disruption]] were the [[Free Church of Scotland]] and the [[United Free Church of Scotland]].  These offshoots did lose the established status of their parent, but since 1929 the (partially) reunited Church of Scotland has considered itself to be a "[[national church]]" rather than an established church, as it is entirely independent of state control in matters spiritual. Legally, it remains established.  

Many sociologists now consider the effect of a state church as analogous to a chartered [[monopoly]] in religion. 

Where state religions  exist, it is usually true the majority of residents are officially considered adherents; however, much of this support is little more than nominal; many members of the church rarely attend it. But the population's allegiance towards the state religion is often strong enough to prevent them from joining competing religious groups. 

A denomination's status as official religion does not always imply that the jurisdiction prohibits the existence or operation of other sects or religious bodies.  It all depends upon the government and the level of tolerance the citizens of that country have for each other.  Some countries with official religions have laws that guarantee the freedom of worship, full liberty of conscience, and places of worship for all citizens; and implement those laws  than other countries that do not have an official or established state religion.

==Disestablishment==
{{See|secular state}}
'''Disestablishment''' is the process of divesting a church of its status as an organ of the state. In England there was a campaign by [[The Liberal Party (UK)|Liberals]], [[dissenter]]s and [[nonconformists]] to disestablish the [[Church of England]] in the late 19th century; it failed in [[England]], but demands for the measure persist to this day. The [[Church of Ireland]] was disestablished in 1869 and the Church of England was disestablished in Wales in 1920, becoming the [[Church in Wales|Church ''in'' Wales]] rather than the Church ''of'' Wales.   Those who wish to continue with an established church take a position of [[antidisestablishmentarianism]]. 

The [[First Amendment]] to the [[Constitution of the United States|US Constitution]] explicitly forbids the U.S. [[Federal government of the United States|federal]] [[government]] from enacting any law respecting a religious establishment, and thus forbids either designating an official church for the United States, or interfering with State and local official churches &amp;mdash; which were common when the First Amendment was enacted.  It did not prevent [[state government]]s from establishing official churches.  [[Connecticut]] continued to do so until she replaced her colonial [[Fundamental Orders of Connecticut|Charter]] with the [[History of Connecticut#The 1818 Constitution (1818-1890)|Connecticut Constitution of 1818]]; Massachusetts did not disestablish its official church until 1833, more than forty years after the ratification of the First Amendment; and local official establishments of religion persisted even later.

The [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] to the [[Constitution of the United States|US Constitution]], ratified in 1868, makes no mention of religious establishment, but forbids the states to "abridge the privileges or immunities" of U.S. citizens, or to "deprive any person of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law."  However, since [[1947]], [[Everson v. Board of Education]], the United States Supreme Court has held that this later provision [[Incorporation (Bill of Rights)|incorporates]] the First Amendment's Establishment Clause as applying to the States, and thereby presumably prohibits state and local religious establishments.  The exact boundaries of this prohibition are still disputed, and are a frequent source of cases before the [[Supreme Court of the United States|US Supreme Court]] &amp;mdash; especially as the court must now reconcile this post-1947 view with the original First Amendment clause that explicitly prohibits any restraint on the free exercise of religion.

All current U.S. state constitutions include guarantees of religious liberty parallel to the First Amendment, but eight ([[Arkansas]], [[Maryland]], [[Massachusetts]], [[North Carolina]], [[Pennsylvania]], [[South Carolina]], [[Tennessee]], and [[Texas]]) also contain clauses that prohibit atheists from holding public office.[http://www.godlessgeeks.com/LINKS/StateConstitutions.htm] However, these clauses have been held by the [[United States Supreme Court]] to be unenforceable in the 1961 case of ''[[Torcaso v. Watkins]]'', when the court ruled unanimously that such clauses constituted a religious test incompatible with First and Fourteenth Amendment protections.[http://www.religioustolerance.org/texas.htm]

==Christian countries==
The following states recognize some form of [[Christianity]] as their official religion (by denomination):

===Roman Catholic===
Jurisdictions which recognize [[Catholicism]] as their official religion:

*[[Argentina]]
*[[Bolivia]]
*[[Costa Rica]]
*[[El Salvador]]
*[[Haiti]]
*[[Liechtenstein]]
*[[Malta]]
*[[Monaco]]
*Some [[canton (subnational entity)|cantons]] of [[Switzerland]]
*[[Vatican City]]

===Eastern Orthodox===
Jurisdictions which recognize one of the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]]es as their official religion:

*[[Cyprus]]
*[[Greece]]
*[[Finland]]

===Lutheran===
Jurisdictions which recognize a [[Lutheranism|Lutheran]] church as their official religion:
*[[Denmark]]
*[[Iceland]]
*[[Norway]]
*[[Finland]]

===Anglican===
Jurisdictions that recognise an [[Anglican]] church as their state religion:

*[[England]] - [[Church of England]]

===Reformed===
Jurisdictions which recognize a [[Reformed]] church as their official religion:

*Some cantons of [[Switzerland]]

==Islamic countries==
Countries which recognize [[Islam]] as their official religion:

*[[Afghanistan]] (State religion)
*[[Algeria]]
*[[Bahrain]]
*[[Bangladesh]] (State religion)
*[[Brunei]]
*[[Iran]]
*[[Iraq]]
*[[Jordan]]
*[[Kuwait]]
*[[Libya]]
*[[Maldives]] (State religion)
*[[Mauritania]]
*[[Morocco]]
*[[Oman]]
*[[Pakistan]] (State religion)
*[[Qatar]]
*[[Saudi Arabia]] (Religion of the Kingdom)
*[[Somalia]]
*[[Tunisia]]
*[[United Arab Emirates]]
*[[Yemen]]

===Sunni Islam===

*[[Algeria]]
*[[Malaysia]]
*[[Pakistan]] (as National-sanctioned religion)
*[[Saudi Arabia]] (as state-sanctioned religion)
*[[Somalia]]

===Shi'a Islam===

*[[Iran]] (as state-sanctioned religion)

==Buddhist countries==
Countries which recognize [[Buddhism]] as their official religion:

*[[Bhutan]] ([[Drukpa Kagyu]] school of [[Tibetan Buddhism]])
*[[Cambodia]] ([[Theravada Buddhism]])
*[[Kalmykia]], a republic within the [[Russian Federation]] ([[Tibetan Buddhism]] - sole Buddhist entity in Europe)
*[[Sri Lanka]] ([[Theravada Buddhism]] - The constitution accords Buddhism the "foremost place," but Buddhism is not recognized as the state religion. )
*[[Thailand]] ([[Theravada Buddhism]])
*[[Tibet Government in Exile]] ([[Gelugpa]] school of [[Tibetan Buddhism]])

==Others==
* [[Israel]] is defined as a Jewish state, meaning that it is the state of the Jewish people, successor to the League of Nations mandate for Palestine that provided for a "National Home for the Jewish People." Some have deliberately misconstrued "Jewish State" as referring to the Jewish religion, either to justify imposition of theocratic laws, or contrarily, to discredit Israel as a "religious" state. At present there is no established religion in Israel. However, Israel recognizes Orthodox Jewish, Muslim and Christian religious courts as official state courts for personal status matters (see [[Millet (Ottoman Empire)|millet system]]). Non-recognition of other streams of Judaism is the cause of some controversy. There is no civil marriage in Israel as of this writing.

* [[United States]] and other countries indirectly fund religions of different denominations by granting tax exempt status to Church and religious institutions.

==Ancient state religions==
===Egypt and Sumer===
The concept of state religions was known as long ago as the empires of [[Egypt]] and [[Sumer]], when every city state or people had its own god or gods.  Many of the early Sumerian rulers were priests of their patron city god. Some of the earliest semi-mythological kings may have passed into the pantheon, like [[Dumuzid]], and some later kings came to be viewed as divine soon after their reigns, like [[Sargon the Great]] of [[Akkad]]. One of the first rulers to be proclaimed a god during his actual reign was [[Gudea]] of [[Lagash]], followed by some later kings of [[Ur]], such as [[Shulgi]].  Often, the state religion was integral to the power base of the reigning government, such as in Egypt, where Pharaohs were often thought of as embodiments of the god Horus. 

===[[Persian empire]]===
[[Zoroastrianism]] was the state religion of the [[Sassanid dynasty]] which lasted from (226 - 651).

===Greek city-states===
Many of the Greek city-states also had a 'god' or 'goddess' associated with that city.  This would not be the 'only god' of the city, but the one that received special honors.  In ancient Greece the city of [[Athens]] had [[Athena]], [[Sparta]] had [[Artemis]], [[Delos]] had [[Apollo]] and Artemis, and [[Olympia]] had [[Zeus]].

===Roman Religion and Christianity===
In Rome, the office of ''Pontifex Maximus'' came to be reserved for the emperor, who was often declared a 'god' posthumously, or sometimes during his reign.  Failure to worship the emperor as a god was at times punishable by death, as the Roman government sought to link emperor worship with loyalty to the Empire.  Many Christians and Jews were subject to persecution, torture and death in the Roman Empire, because it was against their beliefs to worship the emperor.

In [[311]] AD the Emperor [[Galerius]], on his deathbed, declared religious freedom throughout the Roman Empire, especially focusing on the ending of anti-Christian persecution. By the [[Edict of Milan]] of [[313]], his successor [[Constantine the Great]], who had switched his patron from [[Apollo]] to [[Christ]]us, disestablished Roman paganism, and afterward he reorganised the Church, setting up the [[Council of Nicea]], although he was not actually baptised himself until later.  Despite enjoying considerable popular support, Christianity was still not an "official" state religion in Rome, although it was in some neighboring states such as [[Armenia]] and [[Kingdom of Aksum|Aksum]].

[[Roman Religion]] ([[Neoplatonic]] [[Hellenism]]) was restored for a time by [[Julian the Apostate]] from 361 to 363.  Julian does not appear to have reinstated the persecutions of the earlier [[Roman emperors]].

Christianity was declared to be the state religion of the [[Roman Empire]] in [[392]] by decree of [[Theodosius I]].{{fact}}

===Han Dynasty Confucianism and Sui Dynasty Buddhism===
In China, the [[Han Dynasty]] (206 BC -- 220 AD) advocated [[Confucianism]] as the de facto state religion, establishing tests based on Confucian texts as an entrance requirement into government service.  The Han emperors appreciated the societal order which is a central concept of Confucianism.  Confucianism would continue as the state religion until the [[Sui Dynasty]] (581 - 618 AD), when it was replaced by [[Buddhism]].  [[Neo-confucianism]] returned as the state religion sometime in the 10th century.

== States without any state religion ==

These states do not profess any state religion. Countries which officially decline to establish any religion include:

*[[Australia]]
*[[Azerbaijan]]
*[[Canada]]
*[[Chile]]
*[[People's Republic of China]]
*[[Colombia]]
*[[France]]
*[[India]]
*[[Japan]]
*[[Nepal]]
*[[New Zealand]]
*[[Philippines]]
*[[Romania]]
*[[Singapore]]
*[[South Africa]]
*[[South Korea]]
*[[Turkey]]
*[[United States of America]]

== Established churches and former state churches in Europe ==

{| class="wikitable"
! Country || Church || Denomination || Disestablished
|-
| [[Albania]]&lt;sup id="fn_1_back"&gt;[[#fn 1|1]]&lt;/sup&gt; ||colspan="3" align="center"| none since independence
|-
| [[Andorra]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || ?
|-
| [[Anhalt]] || [[Evangelical Church of Anhalt]] || [[Lutheran]] || [[1918]]
|-
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Armenia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Armenian Apostolic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Oriental Orthodox]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1921]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Austria]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Baden, Germany|Baden]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]] and the [[Evangelical Church of Baden]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]] and [[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt; &lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Bavaria]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Belarus]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD align=center colspan =3&gt;none since independence (1990/91) &lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Belgium]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD align=center colspan =3&gt;none since independence (1830) &lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]&lt;TD align=center colspan =3&gt;none since independence (1992) &lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Brunswick-Lüneburg]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Church of Brunswick]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Bulgaria]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Bulgarian Orthodox Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1946]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Croatia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD align=center colspan =3&gt;none since independence&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Cyprus]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Cypriot Orthodox Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;1977&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Czechoslovakia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;1948&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Denmark]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Church of Denmark]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;no&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[England]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Church of England]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Anglican]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;no&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Estonia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Church of Estonia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1940]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Finland]]&lt;sup id="fn_2_back"&gt;[[#fn 2|2]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;1870/1919&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[France]]&lt;sup&gt;[[#fn 3|3]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1905]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Georgian Orthodox Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1921]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Greece]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Church of Greece|Greek Orthodox Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;no&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Hesse]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Church of Hesse and Nassau]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Hungary]]&lt;sup&gt;[[#fn 4|4]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1848]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Iceland]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[National Church of Iceland|Lutheran Evangelical Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;no&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Ireland]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Church of Ireland]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Anglican]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1871]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Italy]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1984]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Latvia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD align=center colspan =3&gt;none since independence (1991) &lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Liechtenstein]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;?&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lippe]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Church of Lippe]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Reformed churches|Reformed]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lithuania]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1940]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lübeck]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[North Elbian Evangelical Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Luxembourg]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;?&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Republic of Macedonia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Macedonian Orthodox Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;1797&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Malta]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;no&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Mecklenburg]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Church of Mecklenburg]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Moldova]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD align=center colspan =3&gt;none since independence (1991) &lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Monaco]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;?&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Netherlands]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Dutch Reformed Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Reformed churches|Reformed]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;1795&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Norway]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Church of Norway]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;no&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Oldenburg]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Church of Oldenburg]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Paraguay]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1967]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Poland]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;1918&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Portugal]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;1976&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Prussia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Church in Germany|13 provincial churches]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Romania]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Romanian Orthodox Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1947]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Russia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Russian Orthodox Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1917]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Thuringia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Church in Thuringia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Saxony]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Church of Saxony]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Schaumburg-Lippe]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Church of Schaumburg-Lippe]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Scotland]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Church of Scotland]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Presbyterian]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;no&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Serbia and Montenegro]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Serbian Orthodox Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;?&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Slovakia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD align=center colspan =3&gt;none since independence (1993) &lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Slovenia]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD align=center colspan =3&gt;none since independence (1991) &lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Spain]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Catholic]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;1978&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Sweden]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Church of Sweden]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[January 2000]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Switzerland]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD align=center colspan =3&gt;none since the adoption of the Federal Constitution (1848) &lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Turkey]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD align=center colspan =2&gt;[[Islam]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1928]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Ukraine]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD align=center colspan =3&gt;none since independence (1991) &lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Waldeck (principality)|Waldeck]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Church of the Hesse Electorate and Waldeck]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Wales]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Church in Wales]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Anglican]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1920]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Württemberg]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Evangelical Church of Württemberg]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[Lutheran]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;TD&gt;[[1918]]&lt;/TD&gt;&lt;/TR&gt;
|}

&lt;cite id="fn_1"&gt;[[#fn 1 back|Note 1:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
In [[1967]], the Albanian government made [[state atheism|atheism]] the "state religion". This designation remained in effect until [[1991]]. &lt;BR&gt;

&lt;cite id="fn_2"&gt;[[#fn 2 back|Note 2:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
Finland's State Church was the [[Church of Sweden]] until [[1809]]. As an autonomous Grand Duchy under Russia 1809-1917, Finland retained the Lutheran State Church system, and a state church separate from Sweden, later named the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]], was established. It was detached from the state as a separate judicial entity when the new church law came to force in 1870. After Finland had gained independence in [[1917]], religious freedom was declared in the constitution of [[1919]] and a separate law on religious freedom in [[1922]]. Through this arrangement, the Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland lost its position as a state church but gained a constitutional status as a national church alongside with the [[Finnish Orthodox Church]], whose position however is not codified in the constitution.

&lt;cite id="fn_3"&gt;[[#fn 3 back|Note 3:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
The [[Concordat of 1801]] made the Roman Catholic, [[Calvinist]] and [[Lutheran]] churches state-sponsored religions, as well as [[Judaism]]. 

&lt;cite id="fn_4"&gt;[[#fn 3 back|Note 3:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
In Hungary the constitutional laws of 1848 declared five established churches on equal status: the [[Roman Catholic]], [[Calvinist]], [[Lutheran]], [[Eastern Orthodox]] and [[Unitarian]] Church. In 1868 the law was ratified again after the [[Ausgleich]]. In 1895 [[Judaism]] was also recognized as the sixth established church. In 1948 every distinction between the different denominations were abolished.

== Former state churches in [[British North America]] ==

===Protestant colonies===
*[[Plymouth Colony]] was founded by [[Pilgrims|Separatists]].
*[[Colony of Rhode Island and Providence Plantations]] was founded by [[Baptist]]s.
*[[Province of Pennsylvania]] was founded by [[Religious Society of Friends|Quakers]].

===Catholic colonies===
*When [[New France]] was transferred to [[Great Britain]] in 1763, the [[Roman Catholic Church]] remained under toleration, but [[Huguenot]]s were allowed entrance where they had formerly been banned from settlement by Parisian authorities.
*[[Province of Maryland]] was founded by [[Irish Catholic]]s in a state known as [[recusancy]], but was stripped of this independence during the [[English Civil War]] by [[Roundhead]]s--much as it was in the [[Cromwellian conquest of Ireland]].
*[[Spanish Florida]] was ceded to the [[Great Britain]] in 1763, the British divided Florida into two colonies.  Both East and West Florida contiuned a policy of toleration for the Catholic Residents.

{| class="wikitable"
! Colony || Denomination || Disestablished&lt;sup id="fn_1_back"&gt;[[#fn 1|1]]&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
| [[Connecticut Colony|Connecticut]] || [[Congregationalist Church|Congregational]] || 1818
|-
| [[Province of Georgia|Georgia]] || [[Church of England]] || 1789&lt;sup id="fn_7_back"&gt;[[#fn 7|7]]
|-
| [[Province of Massachusetts Bay|Massachusetts]] || [[Congregationalist Church|Congregational]] || 1780&lt;sup id="fn_2_back"&gt;[[#fn 2|2]]
|-
| [[New Brunswick]] || [[Church of England]] ||
|-
| [[Province of New Hampshire|New Hampshire]] || [[Congregationalist Church|Congregational]] || 1790&lt;sup id="fn_3_back"&gt;[[#fn 3|3]]
|-
| [[Newfoundland]] || [[Church of England]]
|-
| [[Province of North Carolina|North Carolina]] || [[Church of England]] || 1776&lt;sup id="fn_4_back"&gt;[[#fn 4|4]]
|-
| [[Nova Scotia]] || [[Church of England]] || 1850
|-
| [[Prince Edward Island]] || [[Church of England]] ||
|-
| [[Province of South Carolina|South Carolina]] || [[Church of England]] || 1790
|-
| [[Upper Canada]] || [[Church of England]] || 1854
|-
| [[West Florida]] || [[Church of England]] || N/A &lt;sup id="fn_5_back"&gt;[[#fn 5|5]]
|-|
| [[East Florida]] || [[Church of England]] || N/A &lt;sup id="fn_6_back"&gt;[[#fn 6|6]]

|-
| [[Virginia Colony|Virginia]] || [[Church of England]] || 1786
|-
| [[West Indies]] || [[Church of England]] || 1868
|}

&lt;cite id="fn_1"&gt;[[#fn 1 back|Note 1:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
In several colonies, the establishment ceased to exist in practice at the [[American Revolution|Revolution]], about [[1776]]{{fact}}; this is the date of legal abolition.

&lt;cite id="fn_2"&gt;[[#fn 2 back|Note 2:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
From 1780  Massachusetts had a system which required every man to belong to a church, and permitted each church to tax its members, and did not require that it be a Congregational church. This was objected to, as in practice establishing the Congregational Church, and was abolished in 1833. 

&lt;cite id="fn_3"&gt;[[#fn 3 back|Note 3:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
Until 1877 the New Hampshire Constitution required members of the State legislature to be of the Protestant religion.

&lt;cite id="fn_4"&gt;[[#fn 4 back|Note 4:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
The North Carolina Constitution of 1776 disestablished the Anglican church, but until 1835 the NC Constitution allowed only Protestants to hold public office.  From 1835-1876 it allowed allowed only Christians (including Catholics) to hold public office.  The current NC Constitution forbids only atheists from holding public office, and this provision is not enforced{{fact}}.

&lt;cite id="fn_5"&gt;[[#fn 5 back|Note 5:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
Religious Tolerance for Catholics with an Established Church of England were policy in the former Spanish Colonies of East and West Florida while under British rule. East Florida was lost to Spain in 1781.

&lt;cite id="fn_6"&gt;[[#fn 6 back|Note 6:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
Religious tolerance for Catholics with an established Church of England were policy in the former Spanish Colonies of East and West Florida while under British rule. East Florida was returned to Spain in 1783.

&lt;cite id="fn_7"&gt;[[#fn 7 back|Note 7:]]&lt;/cite&gt;
in 1789 the Georgia Constitution was amended as follows:
"Article IV. Section 10. No person within this state shall, upon any pretense, be deprived of the inestimable privilege of worshipping God in any manner agreeable to his own conscience, nor be compelled to attend any place of worship contrary to his own faith and judgment; nor shall he ever be obliged to pay tithes, taxes, or any other rate, for the building or repairing any place of worship, or for the maintenance of any minister or ministry, contrary to what he believes to be right, or hath voluntarily engaged. To do. No one religious society shall ever be established in this state, in preference to another; nor shall any person be denied the enjoyment of any civil right merely on account of his religious principles."

==[[State of Deseret]]==

[[Mormon]]s attempted to create a state religion in what is now [[Utah]], during the [[19th century]].  The American government and most citizens objected, so there was a short conflict which forestalled any further official movement towards realisation of that goal.

==References==
* [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=5002019127 McConnell, Michael W. "Establishment and Disestablishment at the Founding, Part I: Establishment of Religion" ''William and Mary Law Review'', Vol. 44, 2003 pp 2105+] for United States

==See also==
* [[Civil religion]]
* [[Political religion]]
* [[Separation of church and state]]
* [[Freedom of religion]]
* [[Status of religious freedom by country]]
* [[Religious toleration]]

[[Category:Religious law]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Separation of church and state]]

[[da:Statskirke]]
[[de:Staatsreligion]]
[[fr:Religion d'État]]
[[ko:국교]]
[[nl:Staatsgodsdienst]]
[[ja:国家宗教]]
[[no:Statskirke]]
[[pl:Religia państwowa]]
[[fi:Valtionuskonto]]
[[sv:Statsreligion]]
[[zh:國教]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>