<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171112091606|809918393" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="292285" pageid="292285" ns="0" title="State religion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-14T18:59:46Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2012}}
[[File:Map of state religions.svg|border|thumb|550x550px|Countries with state religion.
{|
|- valign=top
|
{{legend|#0000FF|[[Christianity]]}}
| {{nbsp|1}}
|
{{legend|#158706|[[Islam]]}}
| {{nbsp|1}}
|
{{legend|#EBCF16|[[Buddhism]]}}
|}
]]
A '''state religion''' (also called an '''established religion''' or '''official religion''') is a [[religion|religious]] body or [[creed]] officially endorsed by the [[Sovereign state|state]]. A state with an official religion, while not [[secular state|secular]], is not necessarily a [[theocracy]], a country whose rulers have both secular and spiritual authority. State religions are official or government-sanctioned establishments of a religion, but the state does not need be under the control of the religion (as in a theocracy) nor is the state-sanctioned religion necessarily under the control of the state.

Official religions have been known throughout [[History of the world|human history]] in almost all types of cultures, reaching into the [[Ancient Near East]] and prehistory. The relation of religious cult and the state was discussed by [[Varro]], under the term of ''[[theologia civilis]]'' ("civic theology"). The first state-sponsored [[Christian church]] was the [[Armenian Apostolic Church]], established in 301 AD.&lt;ref&gt;The Journal of Ecclesiastical History&amp;nbsp;– Page 268 by Cambridge University Press, Gale Group, C.W. Dugmore&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Christianity]], as the term ''church'' is typically applied to a Christian place of worship or organisations incorporating such ones, the term ''[[state church]]'' is associated with Christianity as sanctioned by the government, historically the [[state church of the Roman Empire]] in the last centuries of the Empire's existence, and is sometimes used to denote a specific modern national branch of Christianity. Closely related to state churches are [[ecclesia (sociology of religion)|ecclesiae]], which are similar but carry a more minor connotation.

In the [[Middle East]], many states with primarily Islamic population have [[Islam]] as their state religion, either as the [[Shiite]] or [[Sunni]] variety, though the degree of religious restrictions on the citizen's everyday life varies by country. Rulers of [[Saudi Arabia]] use both secular and religious power, while [[Iran]]'s secular presidents are supposed to follow the decisions of religious authorities since the [[Iranian Revolution|revolution of 1979]]. [[Turkey]], which also has a primarily Muslim population, became a secular country after [[Atatürk's Reforms]], though unlike the [[Russian Revolution]] of the same time period, it did not result in the adoption of [[state atheism]].

The degree to which an official religion is imposed upon citizens in contemporary society varies considerably; from high as in [[Saudi Arabia]] to minimal or none at all as in [[Denmark]], [[England]], [[Iceland]] and [[Greece]].

==Types of state religion==
The degree and nature of state backing for denomination or creed designated as a state religion can vary. It can range from mere endorsement (with or without financial support) with freedom for other faiths to practice, to prohibiting any competing religious body from operating and to persecuting the followers of other sects. In Europe, competition between Catholic and Protestant denominations for state sponsorship in the 16th century evolved the principle ''[[cuius regio eius religio]]'' ("states follow the religion of the ruler") embodied in the text of the [[treaty]] that marked the [[Peace of Augsburg]], 1555. In [[England]], [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]] broke with Rome in 1534, being declared the "[[Supreme Head of the Church of England]]",&lt;ref&gt;The headship was administrative and jurisdictional but did not include the ''potestas ordinis'' (the right to preach, ordain, administer the sacraments and rites of the Church which were reserved to the clergy) &amp;ndash;Bray, Gerald. ''Documents of the English Reformation'' James Clarke &amp; Cº(1994), p.114&lt;/ref&gt; the official religion of England continued to be "Catholicism without the Pope" until after his death in 1547,&lt;ref&gt;Neill, Stephen. ''Anglicanism'' Penguin (1960), p.61&lt;/ref&gt; while in [[Scotland]] the [[Church of Scotland]] opposed the religion of the ruler.

In some cases, an administrative region may sponsor and fund a set of religious denominations; such is the case in [[Alsace-Moselle]] in [[France]] under its [[Local law in Alsace-Moselle|local law]], following the pre-1905 French concordatry legal system and patterns in [[Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;The concerned religious communities are the [[Diocese of Metz|dioceses of Metz]] and [[Archdiocese of Strasbourg|of Strasbourg]], the Lutheran [[EPCAAL]] and the Reformed [[EPRAL]] and the three [[Consistory (Judaism)|Israelite consistories]] in Colmar, Metz and Strasbourg.&lt;/ref&gt;

In some [[communist state]]s, notably in [[Religion in North Korea|North Korea]] and [[Religion in Cuba|Cuba]], the state sponsors religious organizations, and activities outside those state-sponsored religious organizations are met with various degrees of official disapproval. In these cases, state religions are widely seen as efforts by the state to prevent alternate sources of authority.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===State churches===
There is also a difference between a "state church" and the broader term of "state religion".{{citation needed|date=May 2016}} A "state church" is a state religion created by a state for use exclusively by that state.{{citation needed|date=March 2016}}{{clarify|Please give an example of a "state religion created by a state for use exclusively by that state" or otherwise make it much clearer|date=March 2016}} An example of a "state religion" that is not also a "state church" is [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]] in [[Costa Rica]], which was accepted as the state religion in the 1949 Constitution, despite the lack of a national church. In the case of a "state church", the state has absolute control over the church, but in the case of a "state religion", the church is ruled by an exterior body; in the case of Catholicism, the [[Holy See|Vatican]] has control over the church. In either case, the official state religion has some influence over the ruling of the state.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}} As of 2012, there are only five state churches left,{{what|Whiche ones?|date=November 2016}} as most countries that once featured state churches have [[Separation of church and State|separated the church from their government]].{{cn|date=November 2016}}

===Disestablishment===
&lt;!---This section is linked from [[Liberal Party (UK)]]---&gt;
{{further|Secular state}}

Disestablishment is the process of repealing a church's status as an organ of the state. Opponents of disestablishment of the [[Church of England]] were known as [[Antidisestablishmentarianism|antidisestablishmentarians]].

==Current state religions==
Currently, the following religions have been established as state religions in some countries. All are versions of [[Christianity]], [[Islam]] or [[Buddhism]].

===Christian countries===
{{main article|Christian state|Christianity and politics|Christian democracy|Christendom}}
The following states recognize some form of [[Christianity]] as their state or official religion (by denomination):

====Roman Catholicism====
Jurisdictions where [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]] has been established as a state or official religion:

* {{Flag|Costa Rica}}: article 75 of the [[constitution of Costa Rica]] confirms that ''"The Roman Catholic and Apostolic Religion is the religion of the State, which contributes to its maintenance, without preventing the free exercise in the Republic of other forms of worship that are not opposed to universal morality or good customs."''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.costaricalaw.com/Constitutional-Law/costa-rica-constitution-in-english.html|title=Costa Rica Constitution in English - Constitutional Law - Costa Rica Legal Topics|author=Super User|work=costaricalaw.com|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150906224713/http://costaricalaw.com/Constitutional-Law/costa-rica-constitution-in-english.html|archivedate=6 September 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Liechtenstein}}: the [[constitution of Liechtenstein]] describes the Catholic Church as the state religion and enjoying ''"the full protection of the State"''. The constitution does however ensure that people of other faiths ''"shall be entitled to practise their creeds and to hold religious services to the extent consistent with morality and public order."''&lt;ref name=LiechtensteinConstitution&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090326162534/http://www.liechtenstein.li/en/pdf-fl-staat-verfassung-sept2003.pdf |date=26 March 2009 |title=Constitution Religion }} (archived from [http://www.liechtenstein.li/en/pdf-fl-staat-verfassung-sept2003.pdf the original] on 2009-03-26).&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Malta}}: Article 2 of the [[Constitution of Malta]] declares that "the religion of Malta is the Roman Catholic Apostolic Religion"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mjha.gov.mt/DownloadDocument.aspx?app=lom&amp;itemid=8566|title=Constitution of Malta (Article 2)|publisher= mjha.gov.mt }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Monaco}}: article 9 of the [[constitution of Monaco]] describes ''"La religion catholique, apostolique et romaine"'' [the catholic, [[apostolic succession|apostolic]] and Roman religion]" as the religion of the state.&lt;ref name=MonacoReligion&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927091747/http://www.gouv.mc/devwww/wwwnew.nsf/1909$/036c62fe5f92f2efc1256f5b0054fa42gb?OpenDocument&amp;3Gb |date=27 September 2011 |title=CONSTITUTION DE LA PRINCIPAUTE }} (French): Art. 9., Principaute De Monaco: Ministère d'Etat (archived from [http://www.gouv.mc/devwww/wwwnew.nsf/1909$/036c62fe5f92f2efc1256f5b0054fa42gb?OpenDocument&amp;3Gb the original] on 2011-09-27).&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{Flag|Italy}}: according to the [[Lateran Treaty]], which was signed during the time of Italian Fascism, the Catholic Church was established as the state religion of Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Article 1: "Italy recognizes and reaffirms the principle established in the first Article of the Statute of the Kingdom of 4 March 1848, according to which the Catholic, Apostolic and Roman Religion is the only religion of the State."{{cite web|title=TREATY BETWEEN THE HOLY SEE AND ITALY|url=http://www.vaticanstate.va/content/dam/vaticanstate/documenti/leggi-e-decreti/Normative-Penali-e-Amministrative/LateranTreaty.pdf|website=vaticanstate.va|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lateran Treaty has never been rescinded by subsequent governments of Italy.
* {{Flag|Vatican City}}: the Vatican is an [[Elective monarchy|Elective]], [[Theocracy|Theocratic]], or [[Sacerdotal state|sacerdotal]] [[Absolute Monarchy]]&lt;ref name=pages&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catholic-pages.com/vatican/vatican_city.asp |title=Vatican City |publisher=Catholic-Pages.com |accessdate=12 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ruled by the [[Pope]], who is also the [[Vicar]] of the Catholic Church. The highest state functionaries are all [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] clergy of various national origins. It is the sovereign territory of the [[Holy See]] ({{lang-la|Sancta Sedes}}) and the location of the Pope's official residence, referred to as the [[Apostolic Palace]].

Jurisdictions that give various degrees of recognition in their constitutions to Roman Catholicism without establishing it as the state religion:

* {{flag|Andorra}}
* {{flag|Argentina}} – article 2 of the [[Constitution of Argentina|Constitution]] explicitly states that the government supports the Roman Catholic Apostolic Faith, but the constitution does not establish a state religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Argentina_1994.pdf?lang=en|title=Argentina's Constitution of 1853, Reinstated in 1983, with Amendments through 1994|work=constituteproject.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.argentina.gob.ar/pais/56-religion.php|title=Argentina - Religión|work=argentina.gob.ar}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Dominican Republic}}
* {{flag|El Salvador}}
* {{Flag|Panama}} – the [[Constitution of Panama|Constitution]] recognizes Catholicism as "the religion of the majority" of citizens but does not designate it as the official state religion.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.state.gov/documents/organization/222609.pdf Executive Summary - Panama], 2013 [[Report on International Religious Freedom]], United States Department of State.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Paraguay}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Constitution of the Republic of Paraguay|url=http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/pa00000_.html|quote=The role played by the Catholic Church in the historical and cultural formation of the Republic is hereby recognized.|postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Peru}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Constitution of the Republic of Peru|url=http://www.congreso.gob.pe/_ingles/CONSTITUTION_29_08_08.pdf|quote=Within an independent and autonomous system, the State recognizes the Catholic Church as an important element in the historical, cultural, and moral formation of Peru and lends it its cooperation. The State respects other denominations and may establish forms of collaboration with them.|postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Poland}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Constitution of the Republic of Poland|date=1997-04-02|url=http://sejm.gov.pl/prawo/konst/angielski/kon1.htm|quote=The relations between the Republic of Poland and the Roman Catholic Church shall be determined by international treaty concluded with the Holy See, and by statute. The relations between the Republic of Poland and other churches and religious organizations shall be determined by statutes adopted pursuant to agreements concluded between their appropriate representatives and the Council of Ministers.|postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Eastern Orthodoxy====
The jurisdictions below give various degrees of recognition in their constitutions to [[Eastern Orthodoxy]], but without establishing it as the state religion:
* {{flag|Greece}}: The [[Church of Greece]] is recognized by the Greek Constitution as the prevailing religion in Greece.&lt;ref name=GreeceConstitution&gt;[http://www.hri.org/docs/syntagma/artcl25.html#A3] THE CONSTITUTION OF GREECE: SECTION II RELATIONS OF CHURCH AND STATE: Article 3, [http://www.hri.org/ Hellenic Resources network].&lt;/ref&gt; However, this provision does not give official status to the Church of Greece, while all other religions are recognized as equal and may be practiced freely.&lt;ref name=GreeceConstitution2&gt;[http://www.hri.org/docs/syntagma/artcl25.html#A13] THE CONSTITUTION OF GREECE: PART TWO INDIVIDUAL AND SOCIAL RIGHTS: Article 13&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, this provision is considered a dead letter and can only be interpreted as a nationalistic historical remnant.
* {{flag|Georgia}}: [[Georgian Orthodox Church]] is not the state church of Georgia but has a special constitutional agreement with the state, with the constitution recognising ''"the special role of the Apostolic Autocephalous Orthodox Church of Georgia in the history of Georgia and its independence from the state."''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parliament.ge/en/kanonmdebloba/constitution-of-georgia-68 Constitution of Georgia] Article 9(1&amp;2) and 73(1a{{sup|1}})&lt;/ref&gt; (See also [[Concordat of 2002]])
* {{flag|Bulgaria}}: in the Bulgarian Constitution, the [[Bulgarian Orthodox Church]] is recognized as "the traditional religion" of the Bulgarian people, but the state itself remains secular.

====Protestantism====

=====Anglicanism=====
The Anglican [[Church of England]] is the established church in the [[England]] as well as all three of the [[Crown Dependencies]].

* {{flag|England}}: the [[Church of England]] is the established church in England, but not in the [[United Kingdom]] as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cofe.anglican.org/about/history/ |title=The History of the Church of England |publisher=The Archbishops' Council of the Church of England|accessdate=2006-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the only established Anglican church worldwide. The Anglican [[Church in Wales]], the [[Scottish Episcopal Church]] and the [[Church of Ireland]] are not established churches and they are independent from the Church of England. The [[British monarchy|British monarch]] is the titular [[Supreme Governor of the Church of England]]. The 26 most senior bishops in the Church of England are [[Lords Spiritual]] and have seats in the [[House of Lords]] of the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|UK Parliament]]. 
* {{flag|Isle of Man}}: the [[Church of England]] is the established church on the Isle of Man. The [[Bishop of Sodor and Man]] is an ex officio member of the [[Legislative Council of the Isle of Man|Legislative Council]] of the upper house of the [[Tynwald]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Gell|first1=Sir James|title=Gell on Manx Church|url=http://www.isle-of-man.com/manxnotebook/manxsoc/msvol31/gell.htm|website=Isle Of Man Online|publisher=IOM Online|accessdate=7 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Jersey}}: the [[Church of England]] is the established church in [[Bailiwick of Jersey|Jersey]], and the leader of the church on the island is the [[Dean of Jersey]], a non-voting member of the [[States of Jersey]]. 
* {{flag|Guernsey}}: the [[Church of England]] is the established church in the [[Bailiwick of Guernsey]], and the leader of the Church of England in the territory is the Dean of Guernsey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About|url=http://www.churchofengland.org.gg/about|website=Guernsey Deanery|publisher=Church of England}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Calvinism=====
* {{flag|Tuvalu}}: The [[Church of Tuvalu]] is the state religion, although in practice this merely entitles it to "the privilege of performing special services on major national events".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.refworld.org/docid/4cf2d05cc.html|title=Refworld - 2010 Report on International Religious Freedom - Tuvalu|first=United Nations High Commissioner for|last=Refugees|publisher=|accessdate=23 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Constitution of Tuvalu]] guarantees freedom of religion, including the freedom to practice, the freedom to change religion, the right not to receive religious instruction at school or to attend religious ceremonies at school, and the right not to "take an oath or make an affirmation that is contrary to his religion or belief".&lt;ref&gt;Constitution of Tuvalu, article 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Lutheranism=====
Jurisdictions where a [[Lutheranism|Lutheran]] church has been established as a state religion include the [[Nordic countries]] (as of 2012 Norway does not have a public religion&lt;ref&gt;https://snl.no/religion_i_Norge&lt;/ref&gt;).
* {{flag|Denmark}}: section 4 of the [[Constitution of Denmark]] confirms the [[Church of Denmark]] as the "established" church.&lt;ref name=DenmarkConstitution&gt;[http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/da00000_.html Denmark – Constitution]: Section 4 State Church, [http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/ International Constitutional Law].&lt;/ref&gt;
** {{flag|Faroe Islands}}: the [[Church of the Faroe Islands]] is the state church of the [[Faroe Islands]], an [[autonomous administrative division|autonomous]] country within the [[Danish Realm]].{{cn|date=May 2017}}
** {{flag|Greenland}}: the [[Church of Denmark]] is the state church of [[Greenland]], an [[autonomous administrative division|autonomous]] country within the [[Danish Realm]].
* {{flag|Iceland}}: the [[Constitution of Iceland]] confirms the [[Church of Iceland]] as the state church of Iceland.&lt;ref name=IcelandConstitution&gt;[http://www.government.is/constitution/ Constitution of the Republic of Iceland]: Article 62, [http://www.government.is/ Government of Iceland].&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Norway}}: A bill passed in 2016 and effective as of 1 January 2017 created the Church of Norway as an independent legal entity.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.regjeringen.no/no/aktuelt/offisielt-fra-statsradet/id2501869/ Offisielt frå statsrådet 27. mai 2016] regjeringen.no «Sanksjon av Stortingets vedtak 18. mai 2016 til lov om endringer i kirkeloven (omdanning av Den norske kirke til eget rettssubjekt m.m.)
Lovvedtak 56 (2015-2016)  Lov nr. 17 Delt ikraftsetting av lov 27. mai 2016 om endringer i kirkeloven (omdanning av Den norske kirke til eget rettssubjekt m.m.). Loven trer i kraft fra 1. januar 2017 med unntak av romertall I § 3 nr. 8 første og fjerde ledd, § 3 nr. 10 annet punktum og § 5 femte ledd, som trer i kraft 1. juli 2016.»&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://stortinget.no/no/Saker-og-publikasjoner/Vedtak/Beslutninger/Lovvedtak/2015-2016/vedtak-201516-056/ Lovvedtak 56 (2015–2016) Vedtak til lov om endringer i kirkeloven (omdanning av Den norske kirke til eget rettssubjekt m.m.)] Stortinget.no &lt;/ref&gt; The [[Constitution of Norway]] Article 16 stipulates that ''"The [[Church of Norway]], an Evangelical-Lutheran church, will remain the Established Church of Norway and will as such be supported by the State"''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stortinget.no/globalassets/pdf/constitutionenglish.pdf The Constitution of Norway, Article 16 (English translation, published by the Norwegian Parliament)] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150908050922/https://www.stortinget.no/globalassets/pdf/constitutionenglish.pdf |date=8 September 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Norwegian wording in Article 16 "folkekirke" (literally "people's church") is officially translated as "established church".  The actual meaning and implications of "folkekirke" remain contested.&lt;ref&gt;http://fritanke.no/reportasje/ingen-vet-egentlig-hva-folkekirke-betyr/19.10357&lt;/ref&gt; This was amended in 2012, from ''"Evangelical-Lutheran religion remains the public religion of the State"''&lt;ref name="abcnyheter"&gt;[http://www.abcnyheter.no/nyheter/080410/losere-band-men-fortsatt-statskirke Løsere bånd, men fortsatt statskirke] {{webarchive|url=https://www.webcitation.org/6DEb3MkkC?url=http://www.abcnyheter.no/nyheter/080410/losere-band-men-fortsatt-statskirke|date=27 December 2012}}, ABC Nyheter&lt;!-- https://www.webcitation.org/6DEb3MkkC?url=http://www.abcnyheter.no/nyheter/080410/losere-band-men-fortsatt-statskirke --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nrk.no/nyheter/norge/1.8076910 Staten skal ikke lenger ansette biskoper], NRK&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fritanke.no/index.php?page=vis_nyhet&amp;NyhetID=8840|title=Ingen avskaffelse: / Slik blir den nye statskirkeordningen|author=Human-Etisk Forbund|work=Fritanke.no}}&lt;/ref&gt; and since 2012 Norway does not have a public religion.&lt;ref&gt;https://snl.no/religion_i_Norge&lt;/ref&gt; The Church of Norway will still obtain financial support from the state of Norway, along with other religious communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christianpost.com/news/norway-ends-500-year-old-lutheran-church-partnership-biggest-change-since-reformation-172480/|title=Norway Ends 500-Y-O Lutheran Church Partnership, 'Biggest Change Since the Reformation'|publisher=|accessdate=23 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://fritanke.no/kommentar/forskjellsbehandling-i-gjare-uttalelser-lover-ikke-godt/19.10325&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Finland}}: the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]] has a special relationship with the Finnish state, its internal structure being described in a special law, the Church Act.&lt;ref name=FinlandConstitution&gt;[http://servat.unibe.ch/icl/fi00000_.html Finland – Constitution], Section 76 The Church Act, http://servat.unibe.ch/icl/fi00000_.html.&lt;/ref&gt; The Church Act can be amended only by a decision of the synod of the Evangelical Lutheran Church and subsequent ratification by the [[Parliament of Finland]]. The Church Act is protected by the [[Constitution of Finland]] and the state can not change the Church Act without changing the constitution. The church has a power to tax its members. The state collects these taxes for the church, for a fee. On the other hand, the church is required to give a burial place for everyone in its graveyards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eroakirkosta.fi/media/english/status_of_the_finnish_state_church_in_2007.html#privileges |title=Status of the Finnish State Church in 2007—Privileges of the State Church |date=7 October 2007 |publisher=eroakirkosta.fi |accessdate=2007-10-23 |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[President of Finland]] also decides the themes for intercession days. The church does not consider itself a state church, as the Finnish state does not have the power to influence its internal workings or its theology, although it has a veto in those changes of the internal structure which require changing the Church Act. Neither does the Finnish state accord any precedence to Lutherans or the Lutheran faith in its own acts. The [[Union of Freethinkers of Finland]] has criticized the official endorsement of the two churches by the Finnish state, and has campaigned for the separation of church and state.&lt;ref&gt;[[Eroakirkosta.fi]] - [http://eroakirkosta.fi/media/taustatietoa/toiminta-ajatus.html Palvelun tavoite: Kirkko on erotettava valtiosta]&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Sweden}}: the [[Church of Sweden]] was until 2000 the official state church of Sweden, and Lutheranism was therefore the state religion of Sweden. In spite of the separation between the state and the church in 2000, the [[Church of Sweden]] still has a special status in Sweden. Sweden is therefore often seen as a midway between having a state religion and not. The church has its own legal regulation in the 1998 Church of Sweden Act, which regulates the church's basic structure, creeds and right to tax members of the church. According to the Act, the Church of Sweden must be a democratic, Lutheran people's church. Only the Swedish [[Riksdag]] can change this fact. The connections to the [[Swedish royal family]] are complicated. For example, the Swedish constitution stipulates that the [[Monarch of Sweden]] must be a true Lutheran, accepting the doctrine of the Church of Sweden. All members of the [[royal house]] must accept the same doctrine to be able to inherit the [[Monarchy of Sweden|Throne of Sweden]]. The parishes of the Church of Sweden were the smallest administrative entities in Sweden and were used as civil registration and taxation units until 1 January 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.raa.se/2014/06/framtidens-folkbokforing-efter-distrikt-istallet-for-forsamling-2/ |title= Framtidens folkbokföring efter distrikt istället för församling|publisher=Swedish National Heritage Board |language= Swedish |author=Cecilia Olla |date=12 June 2014 |accessdate= 31 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other/Mixed====
* {{flag|France}}: The [[local law in Alsace-Moselle]] accords official status to four religions in this specific region of France: [[Judaism]], [[Roman Catholicism]], [[Lutheranism]] and [[Calvinism]]. The law is a remnant of the Napoleonic [[Concordat of 1801]], which was abrogated in the rest of France by the [[1905 French law on the separation of Church and State|law of 1905]] on the [[separation of church and state]].  However, at the time, Alsace-Moselle had been [[Alsace-Lorraine|annexed by Germany]]. The Concordat therefore remained in force in these areas, and it was not abrogated when France regained control of the region in 1918. Therefore, the separation of church and state, part of the French concept of [[Laïcité]], does not apply in this region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= Church-state tie opens door for mosque
|publisher=[[New York Times]]
|date=2008-10-07
|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/07/world/europe/07iht-alsace.1.16744303.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0
|accessdate=2013-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Hungary}}: The preamble to the [[Constitution of Hungary|Hungarian Constitution of 2011]] describes Hungary as "part of Christian Europe" and acknowledges "the role of Christianity in preserving nationhood", while Article VII provides that "the State shall cooperate with the Churches for community goals". However, the constitution also guarantees freedom of religion and separation of church and state.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Hungary_2011.pdf Hungary's Constitution of 2011]. Retrieved 9 February 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Samoa}}: In June 2017, Parliament voted to amend the wording of Article 1 of the constitution, thereby making Christianity the state religion. The status of the religion had previously only been mentioned in the preamble, which prime minister [[Tuilaepa Aiono Sailele Malielegaoi]] considered legally inadequate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Wyeth|first1=Grant|title=Samoa Officially Becomes a Christian State|url=http://thediplomat.com/2017/06/samoa-officially-becomes-a-christian-state/|accessdate=16 June 2017|work=The Diplomat|date=16 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Feagaimaali’i-Luamanu|first1=Joyetter|title=Constitutional Amendment Passes; Samoa Officially Becomes 'Christian State'|url=http://www.pireport.org/articles/2017/06/08/constitutional-amendment-passes-samoa-officially-becomes-christian-state|accessdate=16 June 2017|publisher=Pacific Islands Report|date=8 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Zambia}}: The preamble to the [[Constitution of Zambia|Zambian Constitution of 1991]] declares Zambia to be "a Christian nation", while also guaranteeing freedom of religion.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.ilo.org/dyn/natlex/docs/ELECTRONIC/26620/90492/F735047973/ZMB26620.pdf Constitution of Zambia]. REtrieved 19 October 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Muslim countries===
{{main article|Political aspects of Islam|Sharia|Caliphate|Islamic religious police|Islamism}}
Many [[List of Muslim-majority countries|Muslim-majority countries]] have constitutionally established Islam, or a specific form of it, as a state religion. [[Proselytism]] (converting people to another religion) is often illegal.

* {{flag|Afghanistan}}: Article 2 of the [[Constitution of Afghanistan]]: "The sacred religion of Islam is the religion of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.afghanembassy.us/about-afghanistan/constitution/|title=The Constitution|last=|first=|date=|publisher=Embassy of Afghanistan|website=The Embassy of Afghanistan in Washington DC|access-date=August 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Algeria}}: Article 2 of the [[Algerian Constitution of 2016]]: "Islam shall be the religion of the State."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=AVANT PROJET DE REVISION DE LA CONSTITUTION|url=http://www.constitutionnet.org/sites/default/files/algeria_french.pdf|website=constitutionnet.org|accessdate=29 October 2017|language=French|date=28 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Bahrain}}: Article 2 of the [[Constitution of Bahrain]]: "The religion of the State is Islam."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bahrain's Constitution of 2002 with Amendments through 2012|url=https://constituteproject.org/constitution/Bahrain_2012.pdf?lang=en|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Brunei}}: Article 3 of the [[Constitution of Brunei]]: "The official religion of Brunei Darussalam shall be the Islamic Religion..."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Brunei_2006.pdf?lang=en|title=Brunei Darussalam's Constitution of 1959 with Amendments through 2006|last=|first=|date=6 June 2017|website=https://www.constituteproject.org|access-date=August 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Comoros}}: Preamble to the 2001 [[Constitution of the Comoros]]: "...to draw from Islam, the religion of the state..."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Comoros_2009.pdf?lang=en|title=Comoros's Constitution of 2001 with Amendments through 2009|last=|first=|date=6 June 2017|website=https://www.constituteproject.org|access-date=August 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Djibouti}}: Article 1 of the [[Constitution of Djibouti]]: "Islam is the Religion of the State."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Djibouti's Constitution of 1992 with Amendments through 2010|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Djibouti_2010.pdf?lang=en|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017|date=6 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Egypt}}: Article 2 of the [[Egyptian Constitution of 2014]]: "Islam is the religion of the State".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sis.gov.eg/Newvr/Dustor-en001.pdf Unofficial translation of the 2014 constitution]&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Iran}}: Article 12 of the [[Constitution of Iran]]: "The official religion of Iran is Islam and the [[Twelver]] [[Ja'fari jurisprudence|Ja'farî school]] [in usul al-Dîn and fiqh], and this principle will remain eternally immutable."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Iran (Islamic Republic of)'s Constitution of 1979 with Amendments through 1989|url=https://constituteproject.org/constitution/Iran_1989.pdf?lang=en|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Iraq}}: Article 2 of the [[Constitution of Iraq]]: "Islam is the official religion of the State and is a foundation source of legislation..."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Iraqi Constitution |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161128152712/http://www.iraqinationality.gov.iq/attach/iraqi_constitution.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Jordan}}: Article 2 of the [[Constitution of Jordan]]: "Islam is the religion of the State and Arabic is its official language."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Constitution of The Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan|url=http://www.kinghussein.gov.jo/constitution_jo.html|accessdate=29 October 2017|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130426230052/http://www.kinghussein.gov.jo/constitution_jo.html|archivedate=26 April 2013|date=January 1, 1952}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Kuwait}}: Article 2 of the [[Constitution of Kuwait]]: "The religion of the State is Islam and Islamic Law shall be a main source of legislation."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Kuwait's Constitution of 1962, Reinstated in 1992|url=https://constituteproject.org/constitution/Kuwait_1992.pdf?lang=en|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Libya}}: Article 1 of the [[Libyan interim Constitutional Declaration]]: "Islam is the Religion of the State and the principal source of legislation is Islamic Jurisprudence (Shari'a)."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Draft Constitutional Charter For the Transitional Stage|url=http://portal.clinecenter.illinois.edu/REPOSITORYCACHE/114/w1R3bTIKElG95H3MH5nvrSxchm9QLb8T6EK87RZQ9pfnC4py47DaBn9jLA742IFN3d70VnOYueW7t67gWXEs3XiVJJxM8n18U9Wi8vAoO7_24166.pdf|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Maldives}}: Article 10 of the [[Constitution of the Maldives|Maldives's Constitution of 2008]]: "The religion of the State of the Maldives is Islam. Islam shall be the one of the basis of all the laws of the Maldives."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Maldives's Constitution of 2008|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Maldives_2008.pdf?lang=en|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Malaysia}}: Article 3 of the [[Constitution of Malaysia]]: "Islam is the religion of the Federation;"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=FEDERAL CONSTITUTION Incorporating all amendments up to P.U.(A) 164/2009|url=http://www.jac.gov.my/images/stories/akta/federalconstitution.pdf|publisher=LAWS OF MALAYSIA|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Mauritania}}: Article 5 of the [[Constitution of Mauritania]]: "Islam is the religion of the people and of the State."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mauritania's Constitution of 1991 with Amendments through 2012|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Mauritania_2012.pdf|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Morocco}}: Article 3 of the [[Constitution of Morocco]]: "Islam is the religion of the State, which guarantees to all the free exercise of beliefs [cultes]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Morocco Draft Text of the Constitution Adopted at the Referendum of 1 July 2011|url=http://www.constitutionnet.org/sites/default/files/morocco_eng.pdf|website=constitutionnet.org|publisher=William S. Hein &amp; Co., Inc.|accessdate=29 October 2017|location=Buffalo, New York|date=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Oman}}: Article 2 of the [[Constitution of Oman]]: "The religion of the State is Islam and Islamic Sharia is the basis for legislation."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Oman's Constitution of 1996 with Amendments through 2011|url=https://constituteproject.org/constitution/Oman_2011.pdf?lang=en|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Pakistan}}: Article 2 of the [[Constitution of Pakistan]]: "Islam shall be the State religion of Pakistan."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pakistani.org/pakistan/constitution/part1.html |title=Part I: "Introductory" |publisher=Pakistani.org |date= |accessdate=4 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Qatar}}: Article 1 of the [[Constitution of Qatar]]: "Qatar is an independent sovereign Arab State. Its religion is Islam and Shari'a law shall be a main source of its legislations."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Constitution|url=http://english.mofa.gov.qa/details.cfm?id=80|accessdate=29 October 2017|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20041024231923/http://english.mofa.gov.qa/details.cfm?id=80|archivedate=24 October 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Saudi Arabia}}: Article 1 of the [[Basic Law of Saudi Arabia]]: "The Kingdom of Saudi Arabia is a sovereign Arab Islamic State. Its religion is Islam."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=THE BASIC LAW OF GOVERNANCE|url=http://www.saudiembassy.net/about/country-information/laws/The_Basic_Law_Of_Governance.aspx|accessdate=29 October 2017|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140323165604/http://www.saudiembassy.net/about/country-information/laws/The_Basic_Law_Of_Governance.aspx|archivedate=23 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Somalia}}: Article 2 of the [[Constitution of Somalia|Provisional Constitution of the Federal Republic of Somalia]]: "Islam is the religion of the State."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Federal Republic of Somalia  Provisional Constitution|url=http://www.somaliweyn.com/pages/news/Aug_12/Somalia_Constitution_English_FOR_WEB.pdf|accessdate=29 October 2017|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130124010543/http://www.somaliweyn.com/pages/news/Aug_12/Somalia_Constitution_English_FOR_WEB.pdf|archivedate=24 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Tunisia}}: Article 1 of the [[Tunisian Constitution of 2014]]: "Tunisia is a free, independent, sovereign state; its religion is Islam..."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=THE CONSTITUTION OF THE TUNISIAN REPUBLIC|url=http://www.constitutionnet.org/sites/default/files/2014.01.26_-_final_constitution_english_idea_final.pdf|website=constitutionnet.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|United Arab Emirates}}: Article 7 of the [[Constitution of the United Arab Emirates]]: "Islam shall be the official religion of the Union."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=United Arab Emirates's Constitution of 1971 with Amendments through 2004|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/United_Arab_Emirates_2004.pdf|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Yemen}}: Article 2 of the [[Constitution of Yemen]]: "Islam is the religion of the state, and Arabic is its official Language."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Constitution of the Republic of Yemen As amended on 20 February 2001|url=http://www.constitutionnet.org/sites/default/files/2001_constitution_of_the_republic_of_yemen.pdf|website=constitutionnet.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Buddhist countries===
Governments where [[Buddhism]], either a specific form of, or the whole, has been established as an official religion:
* {{Flag|Bhutan}}: The [[Constitution of Bhutan|Constitution]] defines Buddhism as the "spiritual heritage of Bhutan" and mandates that [[Druk Gyalpo]] (King) should appoint [[Je Khenpo]] and [[Dratshang Lhentshog]] (The Commission for the Monastic Affairs).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.constitution.bt/draft_constitution_3rd_en.pdf |title=Draft of Tsa Thrim Chhenmo |date=1 August 2007 |publisher=www.constitution.bt |format=PDF |accessdate=2007-10-18 |postscript=.}}
: Article 3, Spiritual Heritage
:# Buddhism is the spiritual heritage of Bhutan, which promotes the principles and values of peace, non-violence, compassion and tolerance.
:# The ''[[Druk Gyalpo]]'' is the protector of all religions in Bhutan.
:# It shall be the responsibility of religious institutions and personalities to promote the spiritual heritage of the country while also ensuring that religion remains separate from politics in Bhutan. Religious institutions and personalities shall remain above politics.
:# The ''Druk Gyalpo'' shall, on the recommendation of the Five ''Lopon''s, appoint a learned and respected monk ordained in accordance with the ''Druk-lu'', blessed with the nine qualities of a spiritual master and accomplished in ''ked-dzog'', as the ''[[Je Khenpo]]''.
:# His Holiness the ''Je Khenpo'' shall, on the recommendation of the ''[[Dratshang Lhentshog]]'', appoint monks blessed with the nine qualities of a spiritual master and accomplished in ''ked-dzog'' as the Five ''Lopon''s.
:# The members of the ''Dratshang Lhentshog'' shall comprise:&lt;br/&gt;{{pad|2.4em}}(a) The ''Je Khenpo'' as Chairman;&lt;br/&gt;{{pad|2.4em}}(b) The Five ''Lopon''s of the ''Zhung Dratshang''; and&lt;br/&gt;{{pad|2.4em}}(c) The Secretary of the ''Dratshang Lhentshog'' who is a civil servant.
:# The ''Zhung Dratshang'' and ''Rabdeys'' shall continue to receive adequate funds and other facilities from the State.{{cite web|title=Bhutan's Constitution of 2008|url=https://constituteproject.org/constitution/Bhutan_2008.pdf?lang=en|website=constituteproject.org/|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Cambodia}}: The [[Constitution of Cambodia|Constitution]] declared Buddhism as official religion of the country. About 97% of the Cambodia's population is Buddhists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cambodia.org/facts/?government=The+Constitution+of+Cambodia |title=Constitution of Cambodia |publisher=cambodia.org |accessdate=2011-04-13 |postscript=.}} (Article 43).&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Laos}}: According to Laos constitution, Buddhism has given a special privilege in the society of the country.&lt;ref&gt;Article 9: The State respects and protects all lawful activities of Buddhists and of followers of other religions, [and] mobilises and encourages Buddhist monks and novices as well as the priests of other religions to participate in activities that are
beneficial to the country and people.{{cite web|title=Lao People's Democratic Republic's Constitution of 1991 with Amendments through 2003|url=https://constituteproject.org/constitution/Laos_2003.pdf?lang=en|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Myanmar}}: Section 361 of the [[Constitution of Myanmar|Constitution]] states that "The Union recognizes special position of Buddhism as the faith professed by the great majority of the citizens of the Union."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Myanmar's Constitution of 2008|url=https://constituteproject.org/constitution/Myanmar_2008.pdf?lang=en|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;    
* {{Flag|Sri Lanka}}: the [[constitution of Sri Lanka]] accords Buddhism the "foremost place", although it does not identify it as a state religion. Buddhism has given special privileges in Sri Lankan constitution.&lt;ref&gt;Article 9: "The Republic of Sri Lanka shall give to Buddhism the foremost place and accordingly it shall be the duty of the State to protect and foster the [[Śāsana|Buddha
Sasana]], while assuring to all religions the rights granted by Articles 10 and 14(1)(e)."{{cite web|title=Sri Lanka's Constitution of 1978 with Amendments through 2015|url=https://constituteproject.org/constitution/Sri_Lanka_2015.pdf?lang=en|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Flag|Thailand}}: According to [[Thai constitution]] the country is secular and freedom of religion is guaranteed but some important privileges are also given to Buddhism such as giving money to Buddhist monks to construct Buddhist temple.&lt;ref&gt;Article 67:&lt;br&gt;"The State should support and protect Buddhism and other religions.&lt;br&gt;
In supporting and protecting Buddhism, [...] the State should promote and support education and dissemination of dharmic principles of Theravada Buddhism [...], and shall have measures and mechanisms to prevent Buddhism from being undermined in any form. The State should also encourage Buddhists to participate in implementing such measures or mechanisms."{{cite web|title=CONSTITUTION OF THE KINGDOM OF THAILAND*|url=http://www.constitutionnet.org/sites/default/files/2017-05/CONSTITUTION%2BOF%2BTHE%2BKINGDOM%2BOF%2BTHAILAND%2B%28B.E.%2B2560%2B%282017%29%29.pdf|website=constitutionnet.org|accessdate=29 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Status of religion in Israel===
{{See also|Jewish state}}
[[Israel]] is defined in several of its laws as a "[[Jewish and democratic state]]" (''medina yehudit ve-demokratit''). However, the term "[[Jew]]ish" is a [[Polysemy|polyseme]] that can describe the Jewish people [[Who is a Jew?|as either an ethnic or a religious group]]. The debate about the meaning of the term "Jewish" and its legal and social applications is one of the most profound issues with which Israeli society deals. The problem of the status of religion in Israel, even though it is relevant to all religions, usually refers to the status of [[Judaism]] in Israeli society. Thus, even though from a constitutional point of view Judaism is not the state religion in Israel, its status nevertheless determines relations between religion and state and the extent to which religion influences the political center.&lt;ref&gt;Trouble in Utopia: The Overburdened Polity of Israel, by Dan Horowitz and Moshe Lissak, p51-52&lt;/ref&gt;

The State of Israel supports religious institutions, particularly [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jewish]] ones, and recognizes the "religious communities" as carried over from those recognized under the British Mandate - in turn derived from the pre-1917 Ottoman system of [[Millet (Ottoman Empire)| Millets]]. These are: Jewish and Christian (Eastern Orthodox, Latin [Catholic], Gregorian-Armenian, Armenian-Catholic, Syrian [Catholic], Chaldean [Uniate], Greek Catholic Melkite, Maronite, and Syrian Orthodox). The fact that the Muslim population was not defined as a religious community is a vestige of the Ottoman period{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}} during which Islam was the dominant religion and does not affect the rights of the Muslim community to practice their faith. At the end of the period covered by the 2009 U.S. International Religious Freedom Report, several of these denominations were pending official government recognition; however, the Government has allowed adherents of not officially recognized groups freedom to practice. In 1961, legislation gave Muslim Shari'a courts exclusive jurisdiction in matters of personal status. Three additional religious communities have subsequently been recognized by Israeli law: the [[Druze]] (prior under Islamic jurisdiction), the Evangelical Episcopal Church, and the [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'í]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2009/127349.htm International Religious Freedom Report 2009 : Israel and the occupied territories], U.S. Department of State, Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor.&lt;/ref&gt; These groups have their own religious courts as official state courts for personal status matters (see [[Millet (Ottoman Empire)|millet system]]).

The structure and goals of the [[Chief Rabbinate of Israel]] are governed by Israeli law, but the law does not say explicitly that it is a state Rabbinate. However, outspoken Israeli secularists such as [[Shulamit Aloni]] and [[Uri Avnery]] have long maintained that it is that in practice. Non-recognition of other streams of Judaism such as [[Reform Judaism]] and [[Conservative Judaism]] is the cause of some controversy; rabbis belonging to these currents are not recognized as such by state institutions and marriages performed by them are not recognized as valid. As pointed out by Avnery and Aloni, the essential problem is that Israel carries on the top-down Ottoman [[Millet (Ottoman Empire)| Millet]] system, under which the government reserves the complete discretion of recognizing some religions groups and not recognizing others. {{As of|2015}} [[marriage in Israel]] provides no provision for [[civil marriage]], marriage between people of different religions, marriages by people who do not belong to one of nine recognised religious communities, or [[same-sex marriage]]s, although there is recognition of marriages performed abroad.

===Political religions===
In some countries, there is a [[List of political ideologies|political ideology]] sponsored by the government that may be called [[political religion]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Gentile |first=Emilio |year=2006 |origyear=2001 |title=Le religioni della politica. Fra democrazie e totalitarismi |trans-title=Politics as Religion |url= |location= |publisher=Princeton University Press |isbn= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{Flag|North Korea}}: the North Korean government has promulgated ''[[Juche]]'' as a political alternative to traditional religion. The doctrine advocates a strong nationalist propaganda basis and is fundamentally opposed to [[Christianity]] and [[Buddhism]], the two largest religions on the Korean peninsula. ''Juche'' theoreticians have, however, incorporated religious ideas into the state ideology. According to government figures, ''Juche'' is the largest political religion in [[North Korea]]. The public practice of all other religions is overseen and subject to heavy surveillance by the state.

===Additional notes===
* {{flag|Indonesia}} does not declare or designate a state religion. However, [[Government of Indonesia|the government]] does only recognize 6 religions: [[Islam]], [[Protestantism]], [[Catholicism]], [[Buddhism]], [[Hinduism]] and [[Confucianism]]. The [[Constitution of Indonesia]] guarantees the freedom of religion and the practice of other religions and beliefs, including the [[Animism|animistic]] indigenous ones, is not prohibited by any laws. Indonesians practicing traditional polytheistic and animists as well as [[Sikhs]] and [[Jains]] are often counted as "Hindu" for government purposes.{{citation needed|date=October 2014}} [[Atheism]] or [[agnosticism]], although not prosecuted, is discouraged by the state ideology of [[Pancasila (politics)|Pancasila]]. In addition, the province of [[Aceh]] receives a special status and a higher degree of autonomy, in which it may enact laws ([[Qanun (law)|qanuns]]) based on the [[Sharia]] and enforce it, especially to its [[Muslim]] residents.
* {{flag|Nepal}} was once the world's only Hindu Kingdom during the monarch rule, but has ceased to be so following a declaration by the Parliament in 2006. The official religion of Nepal is Hinduism but in 2006 Nepal became democratic country and constitution declared it as a [[Secular state]] with freedom of religion is guaranteed by Constitution. Now [[Secularism]] is one of the fundamental right of Nepali citizens.

== Former state religions ==

===Pre-modern era===

====Egypt and Sumer====
{{see also|History of religion}}

The concept of state religions was known as long ago as the empires of [[Egypt]] and [[Sumer]], when every city state or people had its own god or gods. Many of the early Sumerian rulers were priests of their patron city god. Some of the earliest semi-mythological kings may have passed into the pantheon, like [[Dumuzid the Shepherd|Dumuzid]], and some later kings came to be viewed as divine soon after their reigns, like [[Sargon the Great]] of [[Akkadian Empire|Akkad]]. One of the first rulers to be proclaimed a god during his actual reign was [[Gudea]] of [[Lagash]], followed by some later kings of [[Ur]], such as [[Shulgi]]. Often, the state religion was integral to the power base of the reigning government, such as in Egypt, where Pharaohs were often thought of as embodiments of the god Horus.

====Sassanid Empire====
[[Zoroastrianism]] was the state religion of the [[Sassanid dynasty]] which lasted until 651, when Persia was conquered by the [[Rashidun Caliphate]]. However, it persisted as the state religion of the independent state of [[Hyrcania]] until the 15th century.

The tiny kingdom of [[Adiabene]] in [[northern Mesopotamia]] converted to [[Judaism]] around 34&amp;nbsp;CE.

====Greek city-states====
Many of the Greek city-states also had a god or goddess associated with that city. This would not be its only god/dess, but the one that received special honors. In ancient Greece, the city of [[Athens]] had [[Athena]], [[Sparta]] had [[Ares]], [[Delphi]] had [[Apollo]] and [[Artemis]], [[Olympia, Greece|Olympia]] had [[Zeus]], [[Corinth]] had [[Poseidon]] and [[Thebes, Greece|Thebes]] had [[Demeter]].

====Roman religion and Christianity====
In Rome, the office of ''[[Pontifex Maximus]]'' came to be reserved for the Emperor, who was often [[Apotheosis|declared a god]] posthumously, or sometimes during his reign. Failure to worship the Emperor as a god was at times punishable by death, as the Roman government sought to link emperor worship with loyalty to the Empire. Many Christians and Jews were subject to persecution, torture and death in the Roman Empire, because it was against their beliefs to worship the Emperor.

In 311, Emperor [[Galerius]], on his deathbed, declared a religious indulgence to Christians throughout the Roman Empire, focusing on the ending of anti-Christian persecution. [[Constantine I]] and [[Licinius]], the two ''Augusti'', by the [[Edict of Milan]] of 313, enacted a law allowing religious freedom to everyone within the Roman Empire. Furthermore, the Edict of Milan cited that Christians may openly practice their religion unmolested and unrestricted, and provided that properties taken from Christians be returned to them unconditionally. Although the Edict of Milan allowed religious freedom throughout the Empire, it did not abolish nor disestablish the Roman state cult (Roman polytheistic paganism). The Edict of Milan was written in such a way as to implore the blessings of the deity.

Constantine called up the [[First Council of Nicaea]] in 325, although he was not a baptised Christian until years later. Despite enjoying considerable popular support, Christianity was still not the official state religion in Rome, although it was in some neighboring states such as [[Kingdom of Armenia (antiquity)|Armenia]], [[Kingdom of Iberia|Iberia]], and [[Kingdom of Aksum|Aksum]].

[[Religion in ancient Rome|Roman Religion]] ([[Neoplatonic]] [[Religion in ancient Greece|Hellenism]]) was restored for a time by [[Julian the Apostate]] from 361 to 363. Julian does not appear to have reinstated the persecutions of the earlier [[Roman emperors]].

[[Catholic]] Christianity, as opposed to Arianism and other ideologies deemed heretical, was declared to be the [[State church of the Roman Empire|state religion of the Roman Empire]] on 27 February 380&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Theodosian Code |url=http://www.ancienttexts.org/library/latinlibrary/theod.html |work=THE LATIN LIBRARY at Ad Fontes Academy|publisher=Ad Fontes Academy |accessdate=2006-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; by the decree ''De Fide Catolica'' of Emperor [[Theodosius I]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Theodosian Code XVI.i.2 |url=http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/theodcodeXVI.html |work=Medieval Sourcebook: Banning of Other Religions |first=Paul |last=Halsall |date=June 1997 |publisher=Fordham University |accessdate=2006-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Han dynasty Confucianism====
In China, the [[Han dynasty]] (206 BC – 220 AD) advocated [[Confucianism]] as the ''de facto'' state religion, establishing tests based on Confucian texts as an entrance requirement into government service—although, in fact, the "Confucianism" advocated by the Han emperors may be more properly termed a sort of Confucian [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalism]] or "State Confucianism". This sort of Confucianism continued to be regarded by the emperors, with a few notable exceptions, as a form of state religion from this time until the overthrow of the imperial system of government in 1911.  Note however, there is a debate over whether Confucianism (including Neo-confucianism) is a religion or purely a philosophical system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Confucian Religiosity: A Partial Bibliography  |url=http://www2.kenyon.edu/Depts/Religion/Fac/Adler/Reln471/Confucian%20religiosity%20bib.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Yuan dynasty Buddhism====
During the Mongol [[Yuan dynasty]] (1271 – 1368 AD), [[Tibetan Buddhism]] was established as the ''de facto'' state religion by the Mongol ruler [[Kublai Khan]], the founder of the Yuan dynasty. The top-level department and government agency known as the [[Bureau of Buddhist and Tibetan Affairs]] (Xuanzheng Yuan) was set up in [[Khanbaliq]] (modern [[Beijing]]) to supervise [[Buddhist monk]]s throughout the empire. Since Kublai Khan only esteemed the [[Sakya]] sect of Tibetan Buddhism, other religions became less important. Before the end of the Yuan dynasty, 14 leader of the Sakya sect had held the post of [[Imperial Preceptor]] (Dishi), thereby enjoy special power.&lt;ref&gt;History of civilizations of Central Asia.: A.D. 750 to the end of the fifteenth century. Part two : The achievements, p59&lt;/ref&gt;

====Golden Horde and Ilkhanate====
[[Shamanism]] and [[Buddhism]] were once the dominant religions among the ruling class of the Mongol khanates of [[Golden Horde]] and [[Ilkhanate]], the two western khanates of the [[Mongol Empire]]. In the early days, the rulers of both khanates increasingly adopted [[Tibetan Buddhism]], similar to the Yuan dynasty at that time. However, the Mongol rulers [[Ghazan]] of Ilkhanate and [[Öz Beg Khan|Uzbeg]] of Golden Horde converted to [[Islam]] in 1295 AD because of the Muslim Mongol emir [[Nawrūz (Mongol emir)|Nawruz]] and in 1313 AD because of [[Sufi]] [[Bukhara]]n [[sayyid]] and [[sheikh]] [[Ibn Abdul Hamid]] respectively. Their official favoring of Islam as the state religion coincided with a marked attempt to bring the regime closer to the non-Mongol majority of the regions they ruled. In Ilkhanate, [[Christian]] and [[Jewish]] subjects lost their equal status with Muslims and again had to pay the poll tax; [[Buddhists]] had the starker choice of conversion or expulsion.&lt;ref&gt;''Medieval Persia 1040–1797'', [[David Morgan (historian)|David Morgan]] p.72&lt;/ref&gt; In Golden Horde, Buddhism and Shamanism among the Mongols were proscribed, and by 1315, Uzbeg had successfully Islamicized the Horde, killing Jochid princes and Buddhist [[lama]]s who opposed his religious policy and succession of the throne.

===Modern era===
{{Globalize|article|North America|date=August 2015}}

====Europe====
* {{Flag|Netherlands}}: Article 133 of the 1814 [[Constitution of the Netherlands|Constitution]] stipulated the [[King of the Netherlands|Sovereign Prince]] should be a member of the [[Dutch Reformed Church|Reformed Church]]; this provision was dropped in the 1815 Constitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.denederlandsegrondwet.nl/9353000/1/j9vvihlf299q0sr/vi6ei64fdgg2|title=Artikel 133: Vorst belijdt de christelijke hervormde Godsdienst - Nederlandse grondwet|publisher=|accessdate=23 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1815 Constitution also provided for a state salary and pension for the priesthood of established religions at the time (Protestantism, Catholicism and Judaism). This settlement, nicknamed ''de zilveren koorde'' (the silver cord), was abolished in 1983.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.denederlandsegrondwet.nl/9353000/1/j9vvihlf299q0sr/vi6jejckwezy|title=Artikel 194: Traktementen, pensioenen en andere inkomsten - Nederlandse grondwet|publisher=|accessdate=23 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rug.nl/research/portal/files/14622151/Deontknopingvandezilverenkoorde21.pdf!null&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wetten.overheid.nl/BWBR0003640/1994-01-01|title=wetten.nl - Regeling - Wet beëindiging financiële verhouding tussen Staat en Kerk - BWBR0003640|publisher=|accessdate=23 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Former state churches in British North America====

=====Protestant colonies=====
* The colonies of [[Plymouth Colony|Plymouth]], [[Massachusetts Bay Colony|Massachusetts Bay]], [[Connecticut Colony|Connecticut]], [[New Haven Colony|New Haven]], and [[Province of New Hampshire|New Hampshire]] were founded by [[Puritan]] Calvinist Protestants, and had [[Congregational church|Congregational]] established churches.
* The colonies of [[Province of New York|New York]], [[Colony of Virginia|Virginia]], [[Province of North Carolina|North Carolina]], [[Province of South Carolina|South Carolina]], and [[Province of Georgia|Georgia]] maintained the [[Church of England]] as the established church.
* The [[Colony of Maryland]] was founded by a charter granted in 1632 to George Calvert, secretary of state to Charles I, and his son Cecil, both recent converts to Roman Catholicism. Under their leadership many English Catholic gentry families settled in Maryland. However, the colonial government was officially neutral in religious affairs, granting toleration to all Christian groups and enjoining them to avoid actions which antagonized the others. On several occasions, low-church dissenters led insurrections which temporarily overthrew the Calvert rule. In 1689, when William and Mary [[Glorious Revolution|came to the English throne]], they acceded to demands to revoke the original royal charter. In 1701, the Church of England was proclaimed, and in the course of the 18th century Maryland Catholics were first barred from public office, then disenfranchised, although not all of the laws passed against them (notably laws restricting property rights and imposing penalties for sending children to be educated in foreign Catholic institutions) were enforced, and some Catholics even continued to hold public office.

=====Catholic colonies=====
* When [[New France]] was transferred to [[Great Britain]] in 1763, the [[Roman Catholic Church]] remained under toleration, but [[Huguenot]]s were allowed entrance where they had formerly been banned from settlement by Parisian authorities.
* When [[Spanish Florida]] was ceded to [[Great Britain]] in 1763, the British divided Florida into two colonies, East and West Florida, which both continued a policy of toleration for the Catholic residents.

=====Colonies with no established church=====
* The [[Province of Pennsylvania]] was founded by [[Religious Society of Friends|Quakers]], but the colony never had an established church.
* The [[Province of New Jersey]], without official religion, had a significant [[Quaker]] lobby, but Calvinists of all types also had a presence.
* [[Delaware Colony]] had no established church, but was contested between Catholics and Quakers.
* The [[Colony of Rhode Island and Providence Plantations]], founded by religious dissenters forced to flee the Massachusetts Bay colony, is widely regarded as the first polity to grant religious freedom to all its citizens, although Catholics were barred intermittently. Baptists, Seekers/Quakers and Jews made this colony their home.  The [[Rhode Island Royal Charter|King Charles Charter]] of 1663 guaranteed "full liberty in religious concernments".

=====Tabular summary=====
{| class="sortable wikitable"
! Colony || Denomination || Disestablished{{#tag:ref|In several colonies, the establishment ceased to exist in practice at the [[American Revolution|Revolution]], about 1776;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Roots of Religious Liberty|work=Rights of the People: Individual freedom and the Bill of Rights |url=http://usinfo.state.gov/products/pubs/rightsof/roots.htm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040603161945/http://usinfo.state.gov/products/pubs/rightsof/roots.htm|archivedate=2004-06-03 |date=December 2003 |publisher=US State Department |accessdate=2007-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; this is the date of permanent legal abolition.|group=note}}
|-
| [[Connecticut Colony|Connecticut]] || [[Congregational church|Congregational]] || 1818&lt;ref&gt;See [[History of the Connecticut Constitution]].&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Province of Georgia|Georgia]] || [[Church of England]] || 1789&lt;ref group=note&gt;In 1789 the Georgia Constitution was amended as follows:
"Article IV. Section 10. No person within this state shall, upon any pretense, be deprived of the inestimable privilege of worshipping God in any manner agreeable to his own conscience, nor be compelled to attend any place of worship contrary to his own faith and judgment; nor shall he ever be obliged to pay tithes, taxes, or any other rate, for the building or repairing any place of worship, or for the maintenance of any minister or ministry, contrary to what he believes to be right, or hath voluntarily engaged. To do. No one religious society shall ever be established in this state, in preference to another; nor shall any person be denied the enjoyment of any civil right merely on account of his religious principles."&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Province of Maryland|Maryland]] || [[Church of England]] || 1776
|-
| [[Province of Massachusetts Bay|Massachusetts]] || [[Congregational church|Congregational]] || 1834 (parish church system)&lt;ref group=note&gt;From 1780 to 1824, Massachusetts residents were all required to attend a [[parish church]], the denomination of which was chosen by majority vote of town residents, but in effect this de facto established Congregationalism as the state religion. For details see [[Constitution of Massachusetts#Declaration of Rights|Constitution of Massachusetts]].&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[New Brunswick]] || [[Church of England]] ||
|-
| [[Province of New Hampshire|New Hampshire]] || [[Congregational church|Congregational]] || 1790&lt;ref group=note&gt;Until 1877 the New Hampshire Constitution required members of the State legislature to be of the Protestant religion. Until 1968 the Constitution allowed for state funding of Protestant classrooms but not Catholic classrooms.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Colony of Newfoundland|Newfoundland]] || [[Church of England]]
|-
| [[Province of North Carolina|North Carolina]] || [[Church of England]] || 1776&lt;ref group=note&gt;The North Carolina Constitution of 1776 disestablished the Anglican church, but until 1835 the NC Constitution allowed only Protestants to hold public office. From 1835–1876 it allowed only Christians (including Catholics) to hold public office. Article VI, Section 8 of the current NC Constitution forbids "any person who shall deny the being of Almighty God" from holding public office. Such clauses were held by the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] to be unenforceable in the 1961 case of ''[[Torcaso v. Watkins]]'', when the court ruled unanimously that the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First]] and [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth]] Amendment protections prohibiting federal religious tests also applied to the states under the doctrine of [[Incorporation of the Bill of Rights|incorporation]].&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Nova Scotia]] || [[Church of England]] || 1850
|-
| [[Prince Edward Island]] || [[Church of England]] ||
|-
| [[Province of South Carolina|South Carolina]] || [[Church of England]] || 1790
|-
| [[Canada West]] || [[Church of England]] || 1854
|-
| [[West Florida]] || [[Church of England]]&lt;ref name=WEFL group=note&gt;
Religious tolerance for Catholics with an established Church of England was policy in the former Spanish Colonies of East and West Florida while under British rule.&lt;/ref&gt; || 1783&lt;ref name=EWFL group=note&gt;In [[Peace of Paris (1783)#Treaty with Spain|1783 Peace of Paris]], which ended the [[American Revolutionary War]], the British ceded both East and West Florida back to Spain (see [[Spanish Florida]]).&lt;/ref&gt;
|-|
| [[East Florida]] || [[Church of England]]&lt;ref name=WEFL group=note /&gt; || 1783&lt;ref name=EWFL group=note /&gt;
|-
| [[Virginia Colony|Virginia]] || [[Church of England]] || 1786&lt;ref group=note&gt;Tithes for the support of the Anglican Church in Virginia were suspended in 1776, and never restored. 1786 is the date of the [[Virginia Statute of Religious Freedom]], which prohibited any coercion to support any religious body.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[West Indies]] || [[Church of England]] || 1868 (Barbados, not until 1969)
|}

{{reflist|group=note|close}}

====Non-British colonies====
These areas were disestablished and dissolved, yet their presences were tolerated by the English and later British colonial governments, as [[Foreign Protestants]], whose communities were expected to observe their own ways without causing controversy or conflict for the prevalent colonists. After the Revolution, their ethno-religious backgrounds were chiefly sought as the most compatible non-British Isles immigrants.

* [[New Netherland]] was founded by [[Dutch Reformed]] Calvinists.
* [[New Sweden]] was founded by [[Church of Sweden]] Lutherans.

====State of Deseret====
The [[State of Deseret]] was a provisional [[US State|state]] of the [[United States]], proposed in 1849, by [[Mormon]] settlers in [[Salt Lake City]]. The provisional state existed for slightly over two years, but attempts to gain recognition by the United States government foundered for various reasons. The [[Utah Territory]] which was then founded was under Mormon control, and repeated attempts to gain statehood met resistance, in part due to concerns over the principle of separation of church and state conflicting with the practice of members of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] of placing their highest value on "following counsel" in virtually all matters relating to their church-centered lives. The state of [[Utah]] was eventually admitted to the union on 4 January 1896, after the various issues had been resolved.&lt;ref&gt;[http://historytogo.utah.gov/utah_chapters/statehood_and_the_progressive_era/struggleforstatehood.html Struggle For Statehood] [[Edward Leo Lyman]], ''Utah History Encyclopedia''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Established churches and former state churches==
{| class="sortable wikitable"
|-
! Country || Church || Denomination || Disestablished
|-
| [[Duchy of Anhalt|Anhalt]] || [[Evangelical State Church of Anhalt]] || [[united and uniting churches|united Protestant]] || [[German Revolution of 1918-1919|1918]]
|-
| [[Armenia]] || [[Armenian Apostolic Church]] || [[Oriental Orthodox]] || 1921
|-
| [[Austria]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[Federal Constitutional Law|1918]]
|-
| [[Grand Duchy of Baden|Baden]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] and the [[Evangelical Church of Baden|United Evangelical Protestant State Church of Baden]] || [[Catholic]] and [[united and uniting churches|united Protestant]] || [[German Revolution of 1918-1919|1918]]
|-
| [[Kingdom of Bavaria|Bavaria]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[German Revolution of 1918-1919|1918]]
|-
| [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]] || [[Bosnian Church]] || [[Heretic]] || 1463
|-
| [[Bolivia]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[Constitution of Bolivia|2009]]
|-
| [[Brazil]]{{#tag:ref|[http://www.v-brazil.com/government/laws/titleIII.html Brazilian Laws - the Federal Constitution - The Organization of State]. V-brazil.com. Retrieved 5 May 2012. [[Brazil]] had [[Roman Catholicism]] as the state religion from the country's [[Independence of Brazil|independence]], in 1822, until the fall of the [[Brazilian Empire]]. The [[República Velha|new Republican government]] passed, in 1890, Decree 119-A {{cite web|title=Decreto 119-A|url=http://www.planalto.gov.br/ccivil_03/decreto/1851-1899/d119-a.htm|quote=Prohibits federal and state authorities to intervene on religion, granting freedom of religion.}} (still in force), instituting the separation of church and state for the first time in Brazilian law. [[Positivist]] thinker [[Demétrio Nunes Ribeiro]] urged the new government to adopt this stance. The 1891 Constitution, the first under the Republican system of government, abolished privileges for any specific religion, reaffirming the separation of church and state. This has been the case ever since – the 1988 [[Constitution of Brazil]], currently in force, does so in its Nineteenth Article. The Preamble to the Constitution does refer to "God's protection" over the document's [[promulgation]], but this is not legally taken as endorsement of belief in any deity.|group=note}} || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] ||[[History of the Constitution of Brazil#Old Republic|1890]]
|-
| [[Duchy of Brunswick|Brunswick]] || [[Protestant Lutheran State Church of Brunswick|Evangelical Lutheran State Church in Brunswick]] || [[Lutheran]] || [[German Revolution of 1918-1919|1918]]
|-
| [[Bulgaria]] || [[Bulgarian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1946
|-
| [[Chile]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[Chilean Constitution of 1925|1925]]
|-
| [[Colombia]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1936&lt;ref&gt;John Gunter, ''Inside Latin America'' (1941), p. 166&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Cuba]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1902
|-
| [[Cyprus]] || [[Cypriot Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1977 with the death of the Ethnarch [[Makarios III]]
|-
| [[Czechoslovakia]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[Czechoslovak Constitution of 1920|1920]]
|-
| [[Denmark]] || [[Church of Denmark]] || [[Lutheran]] || no
|-
| [[England]] || [[Church of England]] || [[Anglican]] || no
|-
| [[Ethiopian Empire|Ethiopia]] || [[Ethiopian Orthodox Church]] || [[Oriental Orthodox]] || [[Derg|1974]]
|-
| [[Faroe Islands]] || [[Church of the Faroe Islands]] || [[Lutheran]] || no, elevated from a diocese of the [[Church of Denmark]] in 2007 (the two remain in close cooperation)
|-
|rowspan="2"| [[Finland]] || [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1869
|-
|[[Finnish Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] ||?
|-
| [[France]]{{#tag:ref|In France the [[Concordat of 1801]] made the Roman Catholic, [[Calvinist]] and [[Lutheran]] churches state-sponsored religions, as well as [[Judaism]].|group=note}} || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[1905 French law on the Separation of the Churches and the State|1905]]
|-
| [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] || [[Georgian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1921
|-
| [[Greece]] || [[Church of Greece|Greek Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]]&lt;ref name=GreeceConstitution/&gt; ||   The [[Church of Greece]] is recognized by the Greek Constitution as the "prevailing religion" in Greece.&lt;ref name=GreeceConstitution/&gt; However, this provision does not give official status to the Church of Greece, while all other religions are recognized as equal and may be practiced freely.&lt;ref name=GreeceConstitution2/&gt;
|-
| [[Greenland]] || [[Church of Denmark]] || [[Lutheran]] || no, under discussion to be elevated from [[Diocese of Greenland|The Diocese of Greenland in the Church of Denmark]] to a state church for Greenland, along‐the‐lines the [[Church of the Faroe Islands|Faroese Church]] took in 2007
|-
| [[Guatemala]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1871
|-
| [[Haiti]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[Constitution of Haiti|1987]]
|-
| [[Grand Duchy of Hesse|Hesse]] || [[Evangelical Church of Hesse and Nassau|Evangelical Church in Hesse]] || [[united and uniting churches|united Protestant]] || [[German Revolution of 1918-1919|1918]]
|-
| [[Hungary]]{{#tag:ref|In Hungary the constitutional laws of 1848 declared five established churches on equal status: the [[Roman Catholic]], [[Calvinist]], [[Lutheran]], [[Eastern Orthodox]] and [[Unitarianism|Unitarian]] Church. In 1868 the law was ratified again after the [[Ausgleich]]. In 1895 [[Judaism]] was also recognized as the sixth established church. In 1948 every distinction between the different denominations were abolished.&lt;ref&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080220121400/http://www.legislationline.org/upload/legislations/cd/86/39b1e5cc4b9b9b6a97c2830f3608.htm |date=20 February 2008 |title=Constitution of the Republic of Hungary }} (archived from [http://www.legislationline.org/upload/legislations/cd/86/39b1e5cc4b9b9b6a97c2830f3608.htm the original] on 2008-02-20)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070523210720/http://www.magyarorszag.hu/english/keyevents/a_alpolg/a_allampolgarsagemberijogok/a_alapjog20050805/a_gondlelkiismjog20060627.html |date=23 May 2007 |title=The right of thought, the freedom of conscience and religion –Hungary.hu }} (archived from [http://www.magyarorszag.hu/english/keyevents/a_alpolg/a_allampolgarsagemberijogok/a_alapjog20050805/a_gondlelkiismjog20060627.html the original] on 2007-05-23)&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}} || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1946
|-
| [[Iceland]] || [[National Church of Iceland|Lutheran Evangelical Church]] || [[Lutheran]] || no
|-
| [[Ireland]]{{#tag:ref|In the [[Kingdom of Ireland]] the [[Church of Ireland]] was established [[Reformation in Ireland|in the Reformation]].&lt;ref name="LivingstoneSparks2013"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Livingstone|first1=E. A.|last2=Sparks|first2=M. W. D.|last3=Peacocke|first3=R. W.|title=The Concise Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DZecAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA286|accessdate=3 December 2014|date=2013-09-12|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=9780199659623|page=286|chapter=Ireland}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Act of Union 1800]] created the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland]] with the [[United Church of England and Ireland]] established outside Scotland. The [[Irish Church Act 1869]] demerged and disestablished the Church of Ireland,&lt;ref name="LivingstoneSparks2013" /&gt; and the island was [[Partition of Ireland|partitioned in 1922]]. The Republic of Ireland's [[Constitution of Ireland|1937 constitution]] prohibits an established religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irishstatutebook.ie/en/constitution/index.html#article44|title=CONSTITUTION OF IRELAND|work=[[Irish Statute Book]]|pages=Article 44|accessdate=3 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally, it recognized the "special position" of the Roman Catholic Church "as the guardian of the Faith professed by [[Roman Catholicism in Ireland|the great majority of the citizens]]", and recognized "the [[Church of Ireland]], the [[Presbyterian Church in Ireland]], the [[Methodist Church in Ireland]], the [[Religious Society of Friends]] in Ireland, as well as the [[Jews in Ireland|Jewish Congregations]] and the other religious denominations existing in Ireland at the date of the coming into operation of this Constitution".&lt;ref name="KeoghMcCarthy2007"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Keogh|first1=Dermot|last2=McCarthy|first2=Dr. Andrew|title=The Making of the Irish Constitution 1937: Bunreacht Na HÉireann|date=2007-01-01|publisher=Mercier Press|isbn=9781856355612|page=172}}&lt;/ref&gt; These provisions were [[Fifth Amendment of the Constitution of Ireland|deleted in 1973]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irishstatutebook.ie/1972/en/act/cam/0005/index.html|title=Fifth Amendment of the Constitution Act, 1972.|work=[[Irish Statute Book]]|accessdate=3 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}} || [[Church of Ireland]] || [[Anglican]] || 1871
|-
| [[Italy]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[Lateran Treaty#History|18 February 1984]] (into force 25 April 1985&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author1=Andrea Mammone|author2=Giuseppe A. Veltri|title=Italy today: the sick man of Europe|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7YWKJ00Dw7QC|year=2010|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-0-415-56159-4|pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=7YWKJ00Dw7QC&amp;pg=PA168 168] (Note 1)}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
|-
| [[Liechtenstein]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;ref name=LiechtensteinConstitution /&gt; || [[Catholic]] || no
|-
| [[Principality of Lippe|Lippe]] || [[Church of Lippe]] || [[Reformed churches|Reformed]] || 1918
|-
| [[Lithuania]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1940
|-
| [[Free City of Lübeck|Lübeck]] || [[North Elbian Evangelical Lutheran Church|Evangelical Lutheran Church in the State of Lübeck]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Luxembourg]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || ? (no official state church)&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.state.gov/documents/organization/171706.pdf Luxembourg]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Republic of Macedonia]] || [[Macedonian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1921
|-
| [[Malta]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || no
|-
| [[Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Schwerin|Mecklenburg-Schwerin]] || [[Evangelical Church of Mecklenburg|Evangelical Lutheran State Church of Mecklenburg-Schwerin]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Strelitz|Mecklenburg-Strelitz]] || [[Evangelical Church of Mecklenburg|Mecklenburg-Strelitz State Church]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Mexico]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[constitution of 1857|1857]] (reestablished between 1864 and 1867)
|-
| [[Monaco]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || no
|-
| [[Mongolia]] || [[Tibetan Buddhism]] || n/a || 1926
|-
| [[Netherlands]] || [[Dutch Reformed Church]] || [[Reformed churches|Reformed]] || 1795
|-
| [[Norway]] || [[Church of Norway]] || [[Lutheran]] || 2017&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://christiandaily.com/article/norways-church-and-state-to-divorce-after-almost-500-years/59710.htm|title=Norway's church and state to divorce after almost 500 years|website=christiandaily.com|access-date=2017-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://kirken.no/nb-NO/om-kirken/aktuelt/2017---et-kirkehistorisk-merkear/|title=2017 - et kirkehistorisk merkeår|last=|first=|date=2017-12-30|website=Den norske kirke, Kirkerådet|publisher=|access-date=2017-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Grand Duchy of Oldenburg|Oldenburg]] || [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in Oldenburg|Evangelical Lutheran Church of Oldenburg]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Panama]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1904
|-
| [[Paraguay]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1992&lt;ref&gt;Under the 1967 Constitution, Roman Catholicism was the state religion as stated in Article 6: "The Roman Catholic Apostolic religion is the state religion, without prejudice to religious freedom, which is guaranteed in accordance with the provisions of this Constitution. Official relations of the republic with the Holy See shall be governed by concordats or other bilateral agreements." The 1992 Constitution, which replaced the 1967 one, establishes Paraguay as a secular state, as mentioned in section (1) of Article 24: "Freedom of religion, worship, and ideology is recognized without any restrictions other than those established in this Constitution and the law. The State has no official religion."&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Philippines]]{{#tag:ref|The Philippines was among several possessions ceded by [[Spain]] to the [[United States]] in 1898; religious freedom was subsequently guaranteed in the archipelago. This was codified in the [[Philippine Organic Act (1902)]], section 5:  "... That no law shall be made respecting an establishment of religion or prohibiting the free exercise thereof, and that the free exercise and enjoyment of religious profession and worship, without discrimination or preference, shall forever be allowed." A similarly-worded provision still exists in the [[1987 Constitution|present Constitution]]. Catholicism remains the predominant religion, wielding considerable political and cultural influence.|group=note}} || [[Roman Catholic Church in the Philippines|Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1898 
|-
| [[Poland]]{{#tag:ref|Article 25 of [http://www.sejm.gov.pl/prawo/konst/angielski/kon1.htm the constitution] states: "1. Churches and other religious organizations shall have equal rights. 2. Public authorities in the Republic of Poland shall be impartial in matters of personal conviction". Article 114 of the Polish [[March Constitution of Poland|March Constitution of 1921]] declared the Roman Catholic Church to hold "the principal position among religious denominations equal before the law" (in reference to the idea of ''[[primus inter pares|first among equals]]''). The article was continued in force by article 81 of the [[April Constitution of Poland|April Constitution of 1935]]. The Soviet-backed [[PKWN Manifesto]] of 1944 reintroduced the March Constitution, which remained in force until it was replaced by the [[Small Constitution of 1947]].|group=note}}|| [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1947
|-
| [[Portugal]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || 1910, 1976 (reestablished between 1933 and 1974)
|-
| [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussia]]&lt;br&gt;pre 1866 provinces || [[Evangelical State Church of Prussia's older Provinces]] with nine ecclesiastical provinces || [[united and uniting churches|united Protestant]] || 1918
|-
| Prussia&lt;br&gt;[[Province of Hanover]] || [[Evangelical Reformed Church - Synod of Reformed Churches in Bavaria and Northwestern Germany|Evangelical Reformed State Church of the Province of Hanover]] || [[Continental Reformed church|Reformed]] || 1918
|-
| Prussia&lt;br&gt;Province of Hanover || [[Evangelical Lutheran State Church of Hanover]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| Prussia&lt;br&gt;[[Province of Hesse-Nassau]] (partially)|| [[Evangelical Church of Hesse and Nassau|Evangelical State Church of Frankfurt upon Main]] || [[united and uniting churches|united Protestant]] || 1918
|-
| Prussia&lt;br&gt;Province of Hesse-Nassau (partially)|| [[Evangelical Church of Hesse-Kassel and Waldeck|Evangelical Church of Electoral Hesse]] || [[united and uniting churches|united Protestant]] || 1918
|-
| Prussia&lt;br&gt;Province of Hesse-Nassau (partially)|| [[Evangelical Church of Hesse and Nassau|Evangelical State Church in Nassau]] || [[united and uniting churches|united Protestant]] || 1918
|-
| Prussia&lt;br&gt;[[Province of Schleswig-Holstein|Prov. of Schleswig-Holstein]] || [[North Elbian Evangelical Lutheran Church|Evangelical Lutheran Church of Schleswig-Holstein]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Quebec]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[Quiet Revolution|1960]]
|-
| [[Romania]] || [[Romanian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1947
|-
| [[Russia]] || [[Russian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox]] || 1917
|-
| [[Thuringia]] || [[Evangelical Church in Thuringia|church bodies in principalities which merged in Thuringia in 1920]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Kingdom of Saxony|Saxony]] || [[Evangelical Lutheran State Church of Saxony]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Principality of Schaumburg-Lippe|Schaumburg-Lippe]] || [[Evangelical State Church of Schaumburg-Lippe]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|-
| [[Scotland]]{{#tag:ref|The modern Church of Scotland has always disclaimed recognition as an "established" church. The Church of Scotland Act 1921 formally recognised the Kirk's independence from the state.}}  || [[Church of Scotland]] || [[Presbyterian]] || State control disclaimed since 1638. Formally recognised as not an established church in 1921
|-
| [[Serbia]] || [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] || [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern]] || 1921
|-
| [[Spain]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[Spanish Constitution of 1978|1978]]
|-
| [[Sweden]] || [[Church of Sweden]] || [[Lutheran]] || 2000
|-
| [[Switzerland]] || separate Cantonal Churches («Landeskirchen») || [[Zwinglianism]] &amp; [[Calvinism]] or [[Catholic]] || during the 20th century
|-
| [[Turkey]] || [[Ottoman Caliphate]] || [[Sunni Islam]] || 1928
|-
| [[Tuvalu]] || [[Church of Tuvalu]] || [[Reformed]] || no
|-
| [[Uruguay]] || [[Roman Catholic Church]] || [[Catholic]] || [[Constitution of Uruguay of 1918|1918]] (into effect in 1919)
|-
| [[United States]]{{#tag:ref|The [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] to the [[Constitution of the United States|U.S. Constitution]] explicitly forbids the [[Federal government of the United States|federal government]] from enacting any law respecting a religious establishment, and thus forbids either designating an official church for the United States, or interfering with [[U.S. State|State]] and local official churches — which were common when the First Amendment was enacted. It did not prevent [[state government]]s from establishing official churches. [[Connecticut]] continued to do so until it replaced its colonial [[Fundamental Orders of Connecticut|Charter]] with the [[History of Connecticut#The 1818 Constitution (1818–1890)|Connecticut Constitution of 1818]]; Massachusetts retained an establishment of religion in general until 1833.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=James H. Hutson|title=Religion and the new republic: faith in the founding of America|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YwW_g8qr68MC|year=2000|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=978-0-8476-9434-1|pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=YwW_g8qr68MC&amp;pg=PA22 22]}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{as of|2010}}, Article III of the Massachusetts constitution still provided, "... the legislature shall, from time to time, authorize and require, the several towns, parishes, precincts, and other bodies politic, or religious societies, to make suitable provision, at their own expense, for the institution of the public worship of God, and for the support and maintenance of public Protestant teachers of piety, religion and morality, in all cases where such provision shall not be made voluntarily."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malegislature.gov/Laws/Constitution CONSTITUTION OF THE COMMONWEALTH OF MASSACHUSETTS], [http://malegislature.gov/ malegislature.gov].&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] to the [[Constitution of the United States|U.S. Constitution]], ratified in 1868, makes no mention of religious establishment, but forbids the states to "abridge the privileges or immunities" of U.S. citizens, or to "deprive any person of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law". In the 1947 case of [[Everson v. Board of Education]], the United States Supreme Court held that this later provision [[Incorporation (Bill of Rights)|incorporates]] the First Amendment's Establishment Clause as applying to the States, and thereby prohibits state and local religious establishments. The exact boundaries of this prohibition are still disputed, and are a frequent source of cases before the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] — especially as the Court must now balance, on a state level, the First Amendment prohibitions on government establishment of official religions with the First Amendment prohibitions on government interference with the free exercise of religion. See [[school prayer]] for such a controversy in contemporary American politics.

All current State constitutions do mention a Creator, but include guarantees of religious liberty parallel to the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]]. The constitutions of eight states ([[Arkansas]], [[Maryland]], [[Massachusetts]], [[North Carolina]], [[Pennsylvania]], [[South Carolina]], [[Tennessee]], and [[Texas]]) also contain clauses that prohibit atheists from holding public office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.godlessgeeks.com/LINKS/StateConstitutions.htm |title=State Constitutions that Discriminate Against Atheists |publisher=www.godlessgeeks.com |accessdate=2007-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/texas.htm
|title=Religious laws and religious bigotry – Religious discrimination in U.S. state constitutions |publisher=www.religioustolerance.com |accessdate=2007-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, these clauses were held by the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] to be unenforceable in the 1961 case of ''[[Torcaso v. Watkins]]'', where the court ruled unanimously that such clauses constituted a religious test incompatible with the religious test prohibition in [[no religious test clause|Article 6 Section 3]] of the United States Constitution.

The [[Church of Hawaii]] was the state church of Hawaii from 1862–1893.|group=note}}
 || none since 1776, which was made explicit in the [[United States Bill of Rights|Bill of Rights]] in 1792 || none || n/a; some state legislatures required all citizens in those states to be members of a church, and some had official churches, such as [[Congregational church|Congregationalism]] in some [[New England]] states such as [[Massachusetts]]. This eventually ended in 1833 when Massachusetts was the last state to disestablish its church.
|-
| [[Waldeck (principality)|Waldeck]] || [[Evangelical Church of Hesse-Kassel and Waldeck|Evangelical State Church of Waldeck and Pyrmont]] || [[united and uniting churches|united Protestants]] || 1918
|-
| [[Wales]]{{#tag:ref|The [[Church in Wales]] was split from the [[Church of England]] in 1920, by [[Welsh Church Act 1914]]; at the same time becoming disestablished.|group=note}} || [[Church of England]] || [[Anglican]] || 1920
|-
| [[Kingdom of Württemberg|Württemberg]] || [[Evangelical State Church in Württemberg]] || [[Lutheran]] || 1918
|}

{{reflist|group=note|close}}

==See also==
* [[Blasphemy law]]
* [[Civil religion]]
* ''[[Cuius regio, eius religio]]''
* [[Confessional state]]
* [[Divine rule]]
* [[Elite religion]]
* [[Freedom of religion]]
* [[Major religious groups]]
* [[Political religion]]
* [[Religious toleration]]
* [[Secular religion]]
* [[Secular state]]
* [[Separation of church and state]]
* [[State atheism]]
* [[Status of religious freedom by country]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|group="Notes"}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Rowlands, John Henry Lewis (1989). ''Church, State, and Society, 1827-1845: the Attitudes of John Keble, Richard Hurrell Froude, and John Henry Newman''. Worthing, Eng.: P. Smith [of] Churchman Publishing; Folkestone, Eng.: distr. ... by Bailey Book Distribution. {{ISBN|1-85093-132-1}}

==External links==
* {{cite journal |quotes= |last=McConnell |first=Michael W. |authorlink= |coauthors= |date=April 2003 |title=Establishment and Disestablishment at the Founding, Part I: Establishment of Religion |journal=William and Mary Law Review, provided by Questia.com |volume=44 |issue=5 |page=2105 |doi= |id= |url=https://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=5002019127&amp;er=deny |accessdate=2006-11-23 |postscript=.}}

{{Religion topics |state=expanded}}
{{Religious persecution}}
{{Relpolnav}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:State Religion}}
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Separation of church and state]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>