<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191123144708|927596882" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="67084" pageid="67084" ns="0" title="Transphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-23T19:10:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Globalize |date=June 2018 }}
{{Transgender sidebar}}
{{LGBT sidebar}}

'''Transphobia''' encompasses a range of negative attitudes, feelings or actions toward [[transgender]] or [[transsexual]] people, or toward [[transsexuality]]. Transphobia can include fear, aversion, hatred, violence, anger, or discomfort felt or expressed towards people who do not conform to society's [[gender]] expectation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Hate Crime: Impact, Causes and Responses|last = Chakraborti |first = Neil |last2 = Garland |first2 = Jon |publisher = SAGE Publications, Ltd.|year = 2009|isbn = 978-1412945684|location = |pages = 77}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Handbook of Gender Research in Psychology, Volume 2|last = Chrisler |first = Donald R. |last2 = McCreary |first2 = Joan C.|publisher = Springer|year = 2010|isbn = 978-1441913555|location = |pages = 366}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is often expressed alongside [[Homophobia|homophobic]] views and hence is often considered an aspect of homophobia.&lt;ref name="Adams"&gt;{{cite book |author1=Maurianne Adams |author2=Lee Anne Bell |author3=Pat Griffin |title=Teaching for Diversity and Social Justice|isbn =978-1135928506|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=2007|pages=198–199|accessdate=December 27, 2014 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zgGUAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA198|quote=Because of the complicated interplay among gender identity, gender roles, and sexual identity, transgender people are often assumed to be lesbian or gay (See ''Overview: Sexism, Heterosexism, and Transgender Oppression''). ... Because transgender identity challenges a binary conception of sexuality and gender, educators must clarify their own understanding of these concepts. ... Facilitators must be able to help participants understand the connections among sexism, heterosexism, and transgender oppression and the ways in which gender roles are maintained, in part, through homophobia.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Spijkerboer"&gt;{{cite book|author=Thomas Spijkerboer|title=Fleeing Homophobia: Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity and Asylum|isbn =978-1134098354|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=2013|page=122|accessdate=December 27, 2014|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oOxBtViD0KcC&amp;pg=PA122|quote=Transgender people subjected to violence, in a range of cultural contexts, frequently report that transphobic violence is expressed in homophobic terms. The tendency to translate violence against a trans person to homophobia reflects the role of gender in attribution of homosexuality as well as the fact that hostility connected to homosexuality is often associated with the perpetrators' prejudices about particular gender practices and their visibility.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transphobia is a type of [[prejudice]] and [[discrimination]], similar to racism and [[sexism]],&lt;ref&gt;Judith A. Lewis, Michael D. Lewis, Judy A. Daniels, ''Community Counseling: A Multicultural-Social Justice Perspective'' (2010, {{ISBN|113317003X}})&lt;/ref&gt; and transgender [[Person of color|people of color]] are often subjected to all three forms of discrimination at once.&lt;ref&gt;Doug Meyer, ''Violence Against Queer People: Race, Class, Gender'' (2015, {{ISBN|0813573181}}), pp. [https://books.google.com/books?id=h2HXCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA14 14]–[https://books.google.com/books?id=h2HXCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA15 15] (Alternate: [https://books.google.com/books?id=rSs_DQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT18 14], [https://books.google.com/books?id=rSs_DQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT19 15])&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Transgender youth|Child victims]] of transphobia experience [[Sexual harassment|harassment]], [[school bullying]], and/or violence in [[School violence|school]], [[foster care]], and [[Welfare|social programs]]. Adult victims experience [[Mockery|public ridicule]], harassment including misgendering, [[Taunting|taunts]], [[Assault (tort)|threats of violence]], robbery, and [[false arrest]]; many feel unsafe in public. A high percentage report being victims of [[sexual violence]]. Some are [[Transgender rights in the United States#Healthcare|refused healthcare]] or suffer [[Transgender rights in the United States#Discrimination|workplace discrimination]], including being fired for being transgender, or feel under siege by [[Conservatism|conservative]] political or religious groups who [[LGBT rights opposition|oppose]] laws to protect them. There is even discrimination from some people within the [[LGBT social movements|movement for the rights of gender and sexual minorities]].

Besides the increased risk of violence and other threats, the [[Stress (psychological)|stress]] created by transphobia can cause negative emotional consequences which may lead to [[substance abuse]], [[Runaway (dependent)|running away from home]] (in minors), and a higher rate of suicide.

In the [[Western world]], there have been gradual changes towards the establishment of policies of non-discrimination and equal opportunity. The trend is also taking shape in [[Developing country|developing nations]]. In addition, campaigns regarding the LGBT community are being spread around the world to improve acceptance; the "Stop the Stigma" campaign by the UN is one such development.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Issues/Discrimination/LGBT_discrimination.pdf|title=Tackling Discrimination on Grounds of Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity|last=|first=|date=|website=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology and use==
The word ''transphobia'' is a [[classical compound]] patterned on the term ''[[homophobia]]''. The first component is the [[English prefixes#Neo-classical|neo-classical prefix]] '''''trans-''''' (originally meaning "across, on the far side, beyond") from ''transgender'', and the second component '''''-phobia''''' comes from the {{lang-el|φόβος}}, ''phóbos'', "fear". Along with ''[[lesbophobia]]'', ''[[biphobia]]'' and ''homophobia'',  ''transphobia'' is a member of the family of terms used when [[Bigotry|intolerance]] and discrimination is directed toward [[LGBT]] people.

''Transphobia'' is not a [[phobia]] as defined in [[clinical psychology]] (i.e., an [[anxiety disorder]]). Its meaning and usage parallels ''[[xenophobia]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Transpeople: Repudiation, Trauma, Healing|last = Shelley |first = Christopher A.|publisher = University of Toronto Press|year = 2008|isbn = 978-0802097842|location =Toronto |pages = 32–35}}&lt;/ref&gt; The noun ''transphobe'' denotes someone who harbors transphobia. The [[Adjective|adjectival]] form ''transphobic'' may be used to describe a transphobe, or things{{vague|date=November 2019}} or qualities related to transphobia.{{citation needed|date=April 2019}} The words ''transphobia'' and ''transphobic'' were added to the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://public.oed.com/the-oed-today/recent-updates-to-the-oed/previous-updates/june-2013-update/new-words-list-june-2013/|title=New words list |date=June 2013|website=public.oed.com|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==
[[Transfeminism|Transfeminist]] theorist and author [[Julia Serano]] argues in her book ''[[Whipping Girl]]'' that transphobia is rooted in [[sexism]], and locates the origins of both transphobia and homophobia in what she calls "oppositional sexism", the belief that male and female are "rigid, mutually exclusive categories, each possessing a unique and nonoverlapping set of attributes, aptitudes, abilities, and desires". Serano contrasts oppositional sexism with "traditional sexism", the belief that males and [[masculinity]] are superior to females and [[femininity]]. Furthermore, she writes that transphobia is fueled by insecurities people have about gender and gender norms.&lt;ref name=serano&gt;Julia Serano. ''Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Sexism and the Scapegoating of Femininity'', Seal Press, 2007. {{ISBN|978-1-58005-154-5|1-58005-154-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other transgender rights authors argue that a significant part of the oppositional sexist origin of transphobia, and especially of the forms that incite violence towards transsexual people, is linked to psychological claims of difference between male sexuality and female sexuality in the brain's protection mechanisms from committing sex crimes. These authors argue that the assumption that men's acceptable sexuality is based on category-specific [[sexual arousal]] while women's acceptable sexual behavior is said to be due to lower sex drive and especially higher sexual inhibitions causes allegations that transsexual people have neither safety system in the brain and are sex criminals, and recommend information about flaws in studies that claim to show such sex differences (including the possibility that fear of being alleged to be inappropriately sexually aroused may deter more men than women from taking part in sexual arousal studies) as a remedy.&lt;ref&gt;Protection of Sexual Minorities Since Stonewall: Progress and Stalemate in Developed and Developing Countries: Phil C. W. Chan Routledge, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sexuality and Equality Law; Suzanne B. Goldberg 2017&lt;/ref&gt;{{clarify|this whole paragraph is hard to follow. "safety system in the brain" needs elaboration!|date=December 2017}}

Transgender author and critic Jody Norton believes that transphobia is an extension of homophobia and [[misogyny]]. She argues that transgender people, like gays and lesbians, are hated and feared for challenging and undermining [[Gender role|gender norms]] and the [[gender binary]]. Norton writes that the "male-to-female transgender incites transphobia through her implicit challenge to the binary division of gender upon which male cultural and political hegemony depends".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Norton|first=Jody|title="Brain Says You're a Girl, But I Think You're a Sissy Boy": Cultural Origins of Transphobia|journal=International Journal of Sexuality and Gender Studies|year=1997|volume=2|pages=139–164|doi=10.1023/A:1026320611878|issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=={{anchor|cissexism|cisgenderism|cisnormativity}}Related concepts==
The related concept of '''cissexism''' (also termed '''cisgenderism''', '''cisnormativity''' or '''cissexual assumption''', occasionally used synonymously with '''transphobia''') is the appeal to norms that enforce the [[gender binary]] and [[gender essentialism]], resulting in the oppression of [[gender variant]], [[non-binary gender|non-binary]], and transgender [[gender identity|identities]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://everydayfeminism.com/2014/03/everyday-cissexism/|title=3 Examples of Everyday Cissexism|author=Sian Ferguson|work=Everyday Feminism|accessdate=7 June 2015|date=2014-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{better source|date=October 2019}} Cisgenderism refers to the assumption that, due to human [[sexual differentiation]], one's [[gender]] is determined solely by a [[biological sex]] of male or female (based on the assumption that all people must have either an [[XY sex-determination system|XX or XY]] sex-[[chromosome]] pair, or, in the case of cisgenderism, a bivalent male or female expression), and that trans people are inferior to [[cisgender]] people due to being in "defiance of nature".&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{cite journal|last= Lennon|first= Erica|last2= Mistler|first2= Brian|date= 2014|title= Cisgenderism |journal=[[TSQ: Transgender Studies Quarterly]] |volume=1 |issue=1–2 |pages=63–64 |doi= 10.1215/23289252-2399623}}&lt;/ref&gt; '''Cisgender privilege''' is the "set of unearned advantages that individuals who identify with their biological sex accrue solely due to having a cisgender identity".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Walls|first1=N. E.|last2=Costello|first2=K.|title=Explorations in diversity: Examining privilege and oppression in a multicultural society, 2nd ed.|date=2010|publisher=Brooks/Cole|location=Belmont, CA|pages=81−93}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Harassment and violence directed against transgender people is often called [[trans bashing]], and can be physical, sexual or verbal. Whereas [[gay bashing]] is directed against a target's real or perceived [[sexual orientation]], trans bashing is directed against the target's real or perceived expressed [[gender identity]]. The term has also been applied to [[hate speech]] directed at transgender people&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonblade.com/2007/4-27/view/columns/10484.cfm Demagogues of defamation Gay: Where is the outrage when cable TV's talking heads trash trans people?]&lt;/ref&gt; and to depictions of transgender people in the media that reinforce negative [[stereotype]]s about them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Mary|last=McNamara|title=Transgender Artists, Work Gaining Acceptance|newspaper=Los Angeles Times|date=2001-02-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Notable victims of violent crimes motivated by transphobia include [[Brandon Teena]], [[Gwen Araujo]], [[Angie Zapata]], [[Nizah Morris]], and [[Lauren Harries]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/4218250.stm |title=Transsexual to move to 'safer' LA |work=BBC News |date=6 September 2005}}]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- PLEASE NOTE: When the article Transprejudice was merged into this article, consensus was reached ([[Talk:Transphobia/Archive 2#Merge proposal]]) that that term must remain in this article. Thus, please do not remove references to the term "transprejudice" from this article without discussing it first. --&gt;
'''Transprejudice''' is a term similar to transphobia, and refers to the negative valuing, stereotyping, and discriminatory treatment of individuals whose appearance and/or identity does not conform to current social expectations or conventional conceptions of gender.&lt;ref&gt;King, M., Webster, B., &amp; Winter, S. (2007). Transprejudice in Hong Kong: Chinese Attitudes Towards Transgenderism and Transgender Civil Rights (under review)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Manifestations==

===Harassment and violence===
{{see also|Violence against LGBT people}}

As homophobia and transphobia are correlated, many trans people experience homophobia and [[heterosexism]]; this is due to people who associate trans people's gender identity with [[homosexuality]], or because trans people may also have a [[sexual orientation]] that is [[non-heterosexual]].&lt;ref name="Adams"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lives" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Spijkerboer"/&gt; Author Thomas Spijkerboe stated, "Transgender people subjected to violence, in a range of cultural contexts, frequently report that transphobic violence is expressed in homophobic terms."&lt;ref name="Spijkerboer"/&gt; Attacking someone on the basis of a perception of their gender identity rather than a perception of their sexual orientation is known as "[[trans bashing]]", analogous to "[[gay bashing]]".

According to the [[American Psychological Association]], transgender children are more likely than other children to experience harassment and violence in school, foster care, residential treatment centers, homeless centers and juvenile justice programs.&lt;ref name="Cisgenderism"&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Cisgenderism in psychology: pathologising and misgendering children from 1999 to 2008|year = 2011|url = http://epubs.surrey.ac.uk/72252/2/YGA%20%26%20PH%202011%20Cisgenderism.pdf|last = Ansara and Peter Hegarty|first = Y. Gavriel|journal = Psychology &amp; Sexuality|accessdate = 20 September 2013|doi = 10.1080/19419899.2011.576696|volume=3|issue = 2|pages=137–160}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers say trans youth routinely experience taunting, teasing and bullying at school, and that nearly all trans youth say they were verbally or physically harassed in school, particularly during gym class, at school events, or when using single-sex restrooms. Three-quarters report having felt unsafe.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

As adults, transgender people are frequently subjected to ridicule, stares, taunting and threats of violence, even when just walking down the street or walking into a store.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Transgender Voices: Beyond Women and Men|last = Girshick|first = Lori B.|publisher = University Press of New England|year = 2008|isbn = 978-1584658382|location = Hanover and London|pages = 133–144}}&lt;/ref&gt; A U.S. survey of 402 older, employed, high-income transgender people found that 60% reported violence or harassment because of their gender identity. 56% had been harassed or verbally abused, 30% had been assaulted, 17% had had objects thrown at them, 14% had been robbed and 8% had experienced what they characterized as an unjustified arrest.&lt;ref name="Lives"&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Lives of Transgender People|last = Beemyn|first = Genny|publisher = Columbia University Press|year = 2011|isbn = 978-0231143073|location = New York|pages = 91}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A study of 81 transgender people in [[Philadelphia]] found 30% reported feeling unsafe in public because they were transgender, with 19% feeling uncomfortable for the same reason. When asked if they had ever been forced to have sex, experienced violence in their home, or been physically abused, the majority answered yes to each question.&lt;ref name=":9"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Transgender Health and HIV Prevention: Needs Assessment Studies from Transgender Communities Across the United States|last = Bockting|first = Walter O.|publisher = CRC Press|year = 2006|isbn = 978-0789030153|location = |pages = 41–53}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A review of American studies on sexual violence towards transgender people found that it is "shockingly common" and while reported rates vary considerably among studies for methodological and other reasons the most common finding is that around 50% of transgender people have been sexually assaulted.&lt;ref name="Stotzer-2009"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Stotzer |first=Rebecca |title=Violence against transgender people: A review of United States data|journal=Aggression and Violent Behavior |year=2009 |volume=14 |issue=3 |pages=170–179 |doi=10.1016/j.avb.2009.01.006 }}, (full text: [https://www.researchgate.net/publication/222055542 &amp;#91;pdf&amp;#93;])&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sexual violence====
In 2009 researcher Rebecca L. Stotzer published an article in ''[[Aggression and Violent Behavior]]'' that compiled information from numerous studies reporting violence against transgender people.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stotzer|first=Rebecca L.|title=Violence against transgender people: A review of United States data|journal=Aggression and Violent Behavior|volume=14|issue=3|pages=170–179|doi=10.1016/j.avb.2009.01.006|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the article Stotzer noted that transgender people have a high risk of experiencing sexual violence throughout their lifetimes.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

====Physical violence====
Perpetrators of physical violence against transgender people are reported to have been influenced by negative attitudes against transgender people, many of whom do not report their assault to the police.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Xavier|first=Jessica|date=|title=A needs assessment of transgendered people of color living in Washington, D.C. |journal=International Journal of Transgenderism|volume=|pages=31–47|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; When transgender people are murdered, they are often shot, struck or stabbed repeatedly.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Encyclopedia of Educational Psychology|last = Salkind|first = Neil|publisher = Sage|year = 2008|isbn = 978-1412916882|location = |pages = 462}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Misgendering and exclusion===
{{anchor|deadnaming}}
[[File:Transphobic Graffito.jpg|thumb|right|A transphobic graffito on a bathroom wall.]]
Misgendering is the act of labelling others with a gender that does not match their gender identity.&lt;ref name="Serano2009"&gt;{{cite book|author=Julia Serano|title=Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Sexism and the Scapegoating of Femininity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fR5ji5h5g1MC|date=20 May 2009|publisher=Seal Press|isbn=978-0-7867-4791-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Misgendering can be deliberate or accidental. It ordinarily takes the form of a person using pronouns to describe someone that are not the ones they use,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Transgender Explained For Those Who Are Not|last = Herman|first = Joanne|publisher = AuthorHouse|year = 2009|isbn = 978-1449029579|pages = 50–51}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":24"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Transgender Employment Experiences: Gendered Perceptions and the Law|last = Bender-Baird|first = Kyla|publisher = SUNY Press|year = 2011|isbn = 978-1438436746|pages = 5–24}}&lt;/ref&gt; calling a person "ma'am" or "sir" in contradiction to the person's gender identity,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Looking Queer: Body Image and Identity in Lesbian, Bisexual, Gay, and Transgender Communities (Haworth Gay &amp; Lesbian Studies)|last = DeCecco|first = John|publisher = Routledge|year = 2012|isbn = 978-0789004635|location = New Jersey|pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt; using a pre-transition name for someone instead of a post-transition one&lt;ref name=":24" /&gt; (called "'''deadnaming'''"),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Meredith Ramirez |last=Talusan |title=What 'deadnaming' means, and why you shouldn't do it to Caitlyn Jenner |work=Fusion |date=June 4, 2015 |url=http://fusion.net/story/144324/what-deadnaming-means-and-why-you-shouldnt-do-it-to-caitlyn-jenner/ |accessdate=2015-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Fae|first1=Jane|title=Changing your name should be a joyous moment, but for many it's a nightmare|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/may/19/changing-your-name-nightmare-trans|website=Comment is Free|accessdate=8 July 2015|date=19 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; or insisting that a person must adhere to the roles or norms assigned to their sex rather than the ones that align with their gender identity; for example, using a bathroom designated for males even though the person identifies as female.

Transgender people are often excluded from entitlements or privileges reserved for people whose gender identity they share, but whose assigned gender they do not. It is very common, for example, for transgender women to be stopped or questioned when they use public bathrooms designated for women.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":24" /&gt; Homeless shelters, hospitals and prisons have denied trans women admission to women's areas and forced them to sleep and bathe in the presence of men.&lt;ref name="transparent"&gt;{{cite book |last= Beam|first= Cris |title= Transparent |publisher= Harvest Books |date=January 2008|isbn= 978-0-15-603377-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people may also be denied service in restaurants.{{citation needed|date=August 2019}}

The experience of being misgendered is common for all transgender people before they transition, and for many afterwards as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Sexual Deceit: The Ethics of Passing|last = Harrison|first = Kelby|publisher = Lexington Books|year = 2013|isbn = 978-0739177051|location = |pages = 12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people are regularly misgendered by doctors,&lt;ref name="Cisgenderism" /&gt; police, media and peers, experiences that they have described as mortifying,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Cisgenderism in Medical Settings: Challenging Structural Violence Through Collaborative Partnerships|date = |url = http://ansaraonline.com/yahoo_site_admin/assets/docs/Chapter_Seven_Ansara_with_Reference.19690148.pdf|last = Ansara|first = Y. Gavriel|accessdate = 20 September 2013|doi = |page = 95}}&lt;/ref&gt; hurtful, especially to [[transgender youth]],&lt;ref name=":16"&gt;{{cite news|title = Shouting Disrupts Vigil For Murdered Transgender Woman Islan Nettles|date = 28 August 2013|url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/08/28/islan-nettles_n_3832004.html|last = Shapiro|first = Lila|work = Huffington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; cruel,&lt;ref name=":17"&gt;{{Cite news|title = Gender Block: Media misgendering and Chelsea Manning|date = 16 September 2013|url = http://this.org/blog/2013/09/16/gender-block-media-misgendering-and-chelsea-manning/|last = Di Menna|first = Hillary|publisher = This Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; and "only making our lives harder".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title = The happy story of my transgender coming-out|date = 23 August 2013|url = http://www.salon.com/2013/08/23/the_happy_story_of_my_transgender_coming_out/|last = Molloy|first = Parker Marie|publisher = Salon magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2018 study of 129 transgender and other gender-expansive youth,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Grossman|first=Arnold H.|last2=Li|first2=Gu|last3=Pollitt|first3=Amanda M.|last4=Russell|first4=Stephen T.|date=2018-10-01|title=Chosen Name Use Is Linked to Reduced Depressive Symptoms, Suicidal Ideation, and Suicidal Behavior Among Transgender Youth|url=https://www.jahonline.org/article/S1054-139X(18)30085-5/abstract|journal=Journal of Adolescent Health|language=English|volume=63|issue=4|pages=503–505|doi=10.1016/j.jadohealth.2018.02.003|issn=1054-139X|pmc=6165713|pmid=29609917}}&lt;/ref&gt; published in the ''[[Journal of Adolescent Health]]'', found that "for each additional social context in which a youth's chosen name was used, there was a statistically significant decrease in depressive symptoms, suicidal ideation, and suicidal behaviors."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Vance|first=Stanley R.|date=2018-10-01|title=The Importance of Getting the Name Right for Transgender and Other Gender Expansive Youth|url=https://www.jahonline.org/article/S1054-139X(18)30335-5/abstract|journal=Journal of Adolescent Health|language=English|volume=63|issue=4|pages=379–380|doi=10.1016/j.jadohealth.2018.07.022|issn=1054-139X|pmid=30286897}}&lt;/ref&gt; Deliberately misgendering a transgender person is considered extremely offensive by transgender individuals.&lt;ref name=":16" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":17" /&gt;

===As users of healthcare===
{{See also|Healthcare and the LGBT community}}
A study of 81 transgender people in [[Philadelphia]] found 14% said they had been refused routine medical care because they were transgender. 18% answered yes when asked if, when they went in for a check-up, "being transgender created a problem" for them.&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt;

Transgender people depend largely on the medical profession to receive not only [[Hormone replacement therapy (trans)|hormone replacement therapy]], but also vital care. In one case, [[Robert Eads]] died of ovarian cancer after being refused treatment by more than two dozen doctors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ftminfo.net/sundance.html |title=FTM Informational Network |accessdate=2009-11-24 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080509154651/http://www.ftminfo.net/sundance.html |archivedate=2008-05-09 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In the United States–based National Center For Transgender Equality's 2011 survey, 19% had been [[Omission (criminal law)#Failure to provide medical treatment|refused medical care]] due to their transgender or gender non-conforming status,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Injustice at Every Turn A Report of the National Transgender Discrimination Survey |url=http://transequality.org/PDFs/Executive_Summary.pdf |publisher=transequality.org |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131112122305/http://transequality.org/PDFs/Executive_Summary.pdf |archivedate=2013-11-12 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; showing that refusal of treatment due to transphobia is not uncommon.
Another example of this is the case of [[Tyra Hunter]]. Hunter was involved in an automobile accident, and when [[Emergency medical services|rescue workers]] discovered she was transgender, they backed away and stopped administering treatment. She later died in a hospital.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.glaa.org/archive/1998/margiehunter1211.shtml|title=Victory in Tyra Hunter case&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;|accessdate=2009-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In many European countries, laws require that any transgender person who wishes to change their legal gender must first be sterilized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pazulka|first=Nicole|title=17 European Countries Force Transgender Sterilization|url=https://www.motherjones.com/mojo/2012/02/most-european-countries-force-sterilization-transgender-people-map|accessdate=August 24, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sweden repealed [[Compulsory sterilisation in Sweden|its law]] in December 2012,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Nelson |first=Rebecca |title=Transgender People in Sweden No Longer Face Forced Sterilization |url=http://newsfeed.time.com/2013/01/14/transgender-people-in-sweden-no-longer-face-forced-sterilization/ |journal=TIME |date=14 January 2013 |accessdate=13 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the European Court of Human Rights struck down such laws in 2017.&lt;ref&gt;Liam Stack, ''[https://www.nytimes.com/2017/04/12/world/europe/european-court-strikes-down-required-sterilization-for-transgender-people.html European Court Strikes Down Required Sterilization for Transgender People]'' (April 12, 2017)&lt;/ref&gt;

===In the workplace===
Transphobia also manifests itself in the workplace. Some transgender people lose their [[employment|jobs]] when they begin to transition. A study from [[Willamette University]] stated that a transgender person fired for following the recommended course of treatment rarely wins it back through federal or state statutes.&lt;ref name="TransEmploy"&gt;{{cite web
 |author=JoAnna McNamara
 |title=Employment discrimination and the Transsexual
 |publisher=[[Willamette University]]
 |date=30 August 1996
 |url=http://www.willamette.edu/~rrunkel/gwr/mcnamara
 |accessdate=10 September 2006
 |url-status=dead
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060910091802/http://www.willamette.edu/~rrunkel/gwr/mcnamara
 |archivedate=10 September 2006
 |df=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

News stories from the ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'' and [[Associated Press]] cite a 1999 study by the [[San Francisco Department of Public Health]] finding a 70% unemployment rate amongst the city's transgender population. On February 18, 1999, the San Francisco Department of Public Health issued the results of a 1997 survey of 392 trans women and 123 trans men, which found that 40% of those trans women surveyed had earned money from full or part-time employment over the preceding six months. For trans men, the equivalent statistic was 81%. The survey also found that 46% of trans women and 57% of trans men reported [[employment discrimination]].&lt;ref name="transhealth"&gt;{{cite web |author=The Transgender Community Health Project |title=Sociodemographics |work=Descriptive Results |publisher=HIVInSite |date=18 February 1999 |url=http://hivinsite.ucsf.edu/InSite?page=cftg-02-02#S5.1X |accessdate=7 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2002 American study found that among educators, trans educators are 10–20% more likely to experience workplace harassment than their gay and lesbian colleagues.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

In the hiring process, discrimination may be either open or covert, with employers finding other ostensible reasons not to hire a candidate or just not informing prospective employees at all as to why they are not being hired. Additionally, when an employer fires or otherwise discriminates against a transgender employee, it may be a "mixed motive" case, with the employer openly citing obvious wrongdoing, [[job performance]] issues or the like (such as excessive tardiness, for example) while keeping silent in regards to transphobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sears|first=Brad|last2=Mallory|first2=Christy|date=2011-07-01|title=Documented Evidence of Employment Discrimination &amp; Its Effects on LGBT People|url=http://escholarship.org/uc/item/03m1g5sg|journal=The Williams Institute, UCLA|language=en|volume=|pages=|via=eScholarship}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Workplace discrimination|Employment discrimination]] on the basis of gender identity and expression is [[Legal aspects of transsexualism in the United States#Discrimination|illegal in some U.S. cities, towns and states]]. Such discrimination is outlawed by specific legislation in the State of New Jersey and might be in other states (as it is in the states of California, Illinois, Maine, Minnesota, New Mexico and Washington) or city ordinances; additionally, it is covered by case law in some other states. (For example, Massachusetts is covered by cases such as ''Lie vs. Sky Publishing Co.'' and ''Jette vs. Honey Farms''.) Several other states and cities prohibit such discrimination in public employment. Sweden and the United Kingdom has also legislated against employment discrimination on the grounds of gender identity. Sometimes, however, employers discriminate against transgender employees in spite of such legal protections.&lt;ref name="TransEmploy2"&gt;{{cite web|author=barbara findlay, Q.C. |title=Transgendered people and Employment: An equality analysis |publisher=Barbara Findlay Law Office |date=June 1999 |url=http://www.barbarafindlay.com/articles/43.pdf |accessdate=10 September 2006 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070620100912/http://www.barbarafindlay.com/articles/43.pdf |archivedate=20 June 2007 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As an example of a high-profile employment-related court case unfavorable to transgender people, in 2000 the southern U.S. grocery chain [[Winn-Dixie (supermarket)|Winn-Dixie]] fired long-time employee Peter Oiler, despite a history of repeatedly earning raises and promotions, after management learned that the married, heterosexual truck driver occasionally [[crossdressing|cross-dressed]] off the job. Management argued that this hurt Winn-Dixie's corporate image. The [[American Civil Liberties Union]] filed a lawsuit against Winn-Dixie on behalf of Oiler but a judge dismissed it.&lt;ref name="ACLUWinnDixie"&gt;{{cite web|author=Ronald L. Wilson |title=Oliver v. Winn-Dixie Complaint |date=23 October 2000 |url=http://www.aclufl.org/legislature_courts/legal_department/briefs_complaints/oiler_complaint.cfm |accessdate=15 October 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120403014712/http://www.aclufl.org/legislature_courts/legal_department/briefs_complaints/oiler_complaint.cfm |archivedate=3 April 2012 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sometimes transgender people facing employment discrimination turn to [[sex industry|sex work]] [[Forced prostitution#Voluntary vs involuntary prostitution|to survive]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Jacques|first=Juliet|title=No wonder many transsexual people end up in sex work|url=https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2010/aug/25/transsexual-people-sex-work|accessdate=30 March 2012|newspaper=The Guardian|date=25 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; placing them at additional risk of such things as encountering troubles with the law, including arrest and criminal prosecution; enduring workplace violence; and possibly contracting [[sexually transmitted disease]]s such as [[HIV]].&lt;ref name="transhealth" /&gt;

The transgender community faces huge amount of employment discrimination due to their gender identity, and there are very few laws that protect the employment rights of this community. It results in limited career options for the transgender community leaving them economically vulnerable. A study conducted by Anneliese Singh and Vel McKleroy on transgender people of color revealed that difficulty finding a job or losing a job due to transphobia in workplace resulted in some of the transgender people living in crime-ridden neighborhoods, and getting involved in abusive relationships.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Singh|first=Anneliese A|last2=McKleroy|first2=Vel S|date=2011|title="Just Getting Out of Bed Is a Revolutionary Act" The Resilience of Transgender People of Color Who Have Survived Traumatic Life Events.|journal=Traumatology|volume=17|issue=2|pages=34–44|doi=10.1177/1534765610369261|citeseerx=10.1.1.1017.9594}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lack of employment has also resulted in the transgender community resorting to illegal activities like selling drugs or sex work for the income support.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|pmid=20416495|last=Bith-Melander|first=Pollie|date=2010|title=Understanding sociocultural and psychological factors affecting transgender people of color in San Francisco|journal=Journal of the Association of Nurses in AIDS Care|volume=21|issue=3|pages=207–220|doi=10.1016/j.jana.2010.01.008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===From government===
{{See also|Transgender disenfranchisement in the United States}}

Transgender people also face the denial of [[right of asylum]] or inhuman treatment in process of asylum-seeking. For example, Fernada Milan, a transgender woman from [[Guatemala]] was placed in an asylum center for males in [[Denmark]] and while there, was raped by several men. She was in danger of deportation into Guatemala where transgender people have no rights and face possible execution, but has since been granted entry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uncommon-scents.blogspot.co.uk/2012/08/what-im-most-afraid-of-when-i-go-back.html|title=UnCommon Sense|author=Natacha|accessdate=7 June 2015|date=2012-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Transgender disenfranchisement is the practice of creating or upholding barriers that keep transgender individuals from [[voting]] and therefore restrict the principles of [[universal suffrage]].

===In education===
Within the school system, many transgender teens are harassed and mistreated with reported negative effects on both victim and the school's population in general.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{Cite web|title = Transgender Bullying: A National Epidemic|url = http://nobullying.com/transgender-bullying/|website = nobullying.com|access-date = 2016-02-22|language = English}}&lt;/ref&gt; "Transgender youth frequently report fear and anxiety about using restrooms and locker rooms at school because they had experienced harassment by both peers and adults when using them."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.eusccr.com/10.%20national%20center%20for%20transgender%20equality.pdf |title=Peer Violence and Bullying Against Transgender and Gender Nonconforming Youth |date=May 2011 |access-date=30 December 2016 |website=National Center for Transgender Equality |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161005200553/http://www.eusccr.com/10.%20national%20center%20for%20transgender%20equality.pdf |archivedate=5 October 2016 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Over 80% of transgender teens report feeling unsafe in a school environment, more than 40% report having been physically abused, and over 65% report being bullied online or via social media.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt; Through official channels, such discrimination is generally underreported.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}}

A study done on Canadian High School students between December 2007 and June 2009 illustrated how the LGBTQ students feel unsafe at the school, and are exposed to insults and discrimination by their peers and sometimes even by their teachers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Taylor|first=Catherine|date=2011|title=Final report on the first national climate survey on homophobia, biphobia, and transphobia in Canadian schools|journal=. Every Class in Every School|volume=|pages=|hdl=10680/1265}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even the heterosexual students and the teachers fear the attack by transphobia on account of supporting or having a transgender friend or family. Most of the administrators and educators are unaware about the extent of damage that has been caused to the transgender students on account of underestimating the gravity of transphobia in their schools.

===From the religious right===

====Christianity====
{{Unreliable sources|section|date=January 2018}}
The [[Christian right]] in North America, including organizations such as the [[American Family Association]], [[Family Research Council]], [[Focus on the Family]], [[National Association for Research and Therapy of Homosexuality]] believe that transgenderism is "unnatural" and that transgender people are and remain their birth sex, and they oppose laws and policies intended to accommodate transgender people, such as allowing them to change their legal sex, use the washroom corresponding to the gender with which they identify, or become ordained Christian ministers. They say that God created people's bodies as they are meant to be, that accepting transgender people would violate scripture and [[natural law]], and that the Bible refers to male and female.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/transsexu9a.htm|title=Beliefs among religious conservatives about the causes &amp; cures of transsexuality (Cont'd)|accessdate=7 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Ontario Consultants for Religious Tolerance website, under [[Pope John Paul II]], the [[Holy See|Vatican]] first stated its opposition to reassignment surgery in 2000, although it was not made public until 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/transsexu15.htm|title=Catholic beliefs about the causes &amp; cures of transsexuality|accessdate=7 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Transgender people face particular challenges in attempting to integrate their faith with their gender identity. One author says "expectations [based on gender] are usually predicated upon our genitalia and begin from the moment of birth, continuing throughout our lives."&lt;ref&gt;Sheridan, V. 2001. Crossing over: Liberating the transgendered Christian, Cleveland, OH: The Pilgrim Press. [Google Scholar], p.&amp;nbsp;31.&lt;/ref&gt; Many Christian denominations use biblical notions of gender and gender roles to support their views. These include "So God created man in His own image, in the image of God He created him; male and female He created them" (Genesis 1:27) and "The woman shall not wear that which pertaineth unto a man, neither shall a man put on a woman's garment: for all that do so are an abomination unto the Lord thy God" (Deuteronomy 22:5).&lt;ref name="Denise L 2013"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Levy|first1=Denise L.|title=Transgender, Transsexual, and Gender Queer Individuals with a Christian Upbringing: The Process of Resolving Conflict Between Gender Identity and Faith.|journal=Journal of Religion &amp; Spirituality in Social Work: Social Thought|date=15 Feb 2013|volume=32|issue=1|pages=60–83|doi=10.1080/15426432.2013.749079}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Views of gender identity based on the Christian faith do not always coincide with the ideologies of transgender individuals. However, if they do not conform to these expectations, they may face rejection. Many transgender Christians seek out an "individualized relationship with God", often facing "a period of denial and struggle" as well as depression, disconnection, dissatisfaction, and spiritual difficulty before "discovering a sense of self that feels integral and true"&lt;ref&gt;Tanis, J. 2003. Trans-gendered: Theology, ministry, and communities of faith, Cleveland, OH: The Pilgrim Press. [Google Scholar], p.&amp;nbsp;38.&lt;/ref&gt; However, after discovering their gender identity, many transgender individuals still face barriers within the church such as, "fear and unfamiliarity on the part of the congregation, language issues, physical layout that separates people by gender, programs that exclude or separate by gender, pathologizing or designating trans issues as sinful, and overt hostility"&lt;ref&gt;Tanis, J. (2003). ''Trans-gendered: Theology, ministry, and communities of faith'', Cleveland, OH: The Pilgrim Press. p.&amp;nbsp;116.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Denise L 2013"/&gt;

====Islam====

The Islamic faith ordinarily supports a heteronormative binary of gender identification which is reinforced by their cultural norms and traditional readings of sacred texts which prohibit the wide range of identities that are present in today's society. Transgender men and women are acknowledged and accepted in many Islamic cultures around the world. In actuality, the idea of a man or woman identifying as a member of the opposite gender is more likely to be approved than that of a man or woman expressing sexual desire for someone of their own gender.

In 1988, gender reassignment surgery was declared acceptable under Islamic law by scholars at Egypt's Al-Azhar, the world's oldest Islamic university. In Iran during 1987, Ayatollah Khomeini, the supreme religious leader of the Islamic Republic of Iran at that time, also declared transgender surgical operations as acceptable (see [[transgender rights in Iran]]). The foundation for this accepting attitude is the belief that a person is born transgender but chooses to be homosexual, thus making homosexuality a sin. Nonetheless, transgender individuals within the Muslim community still face particular challenges.

Some communities of worship are more tolerant—[[Muslims for Progressive Values]] has founded Unity Mosques in Atlanta, Georgia; Columbus, Ohio; and Los Angeles, California. The [[Muslim Alliance for Sexual and Gender Diversity]] hosts an annual retreat for LGBTQ+ Muslims in Pennsylvania each May.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrc.org/resources/stances-of-faiths-on-lgbt-issues-islam|title=Stances of Faiths on LGBTQ Issues: Islam – Sunni and Shi'a|website=Human Rights Campaign|publisher=Human Rights Campaign}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In feminism===
{{See also|Feminist views on transgender topics}}

Some positions within feminism have been considered transphobic. This may include criticism of [[Transitioning (transgender)|transitioning]] or [[sex reassignment surgery]] as a personal choice or medical invention, or the position that trans women are not women in a literal sense and should not be in women-only spaces.&lt;ref name="Goldberg"/&gt; Some [[Second-wave feminism|second-wave feminists]] perceive trans men and women respectively as "traitors" and "infiltrators" to womanhood.&lt;ref name="Erickson-Schroth 2014"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Erickson-Schroth |first1=Laura |title=Trans Bodies, Trans Selves: A Resource for the Transgender Community |date=2014-05-12 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |isbn=978-0199325351 |pages=568–569 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7Ef1AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA568|quote="Some feminists have perceived transmasculine people as traitors—that is, as women who identify politically with men. When inclusive of trans men, these feminists have  often gendered them as women.  Conversely, these feminists have tended to  perceive transfeminine people as infiltrators of womanhood and of women's space. Many commentators refer to feminists who think in these ways as 'trans-exclusionary radical feminsts' (TERFs).&amp;nbsp;...'The fetishistic (often infantalizing) embrace of trans men by lesbian communities is ungendering, othering, and transphobic.'"}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Second-wave feminist]] and activist [[Gloria Steinem]] expressed concerns in 1977 about transsexuality and [[sex reassignment surgery]] (SRS), writing that in many cases, transsexuals "surgically mutilate their own bodies."&lt;ref name="Steinem-OutrageousActs"/&gt;{{rp|227}} She concluded that "feminists are right to feel uncomfortable about the need for and uses of transsexualism."&lt;ref name="Steinem-OutrageousActs"/&gt;{{rp|228}} For some years, this led to Steinem being characterized as transphobic.&lt;ref name="bm-trans-exclusion-steinem"/&gt; In 2013, she repudiated the interpretation of her text as an altogether condemnation of SRS, stating that her position was informed by accounts of gay men choosing to transition as a way of coping with societal [[homophobia]]. She added that she sees transgender people as living "authentic lives" that should be "celebrated."&lt;ref name="advocate-steinem-oped"/&gt;

Radical feminist [[Janice Raymond]]'s 1979 book, ''The Transsexual Empire'', was and still is controversial due to its unequivocal condemnation of transsexual surgeries.&lt;ref name="Goldberg"/&gt; In the book Raymond says, "All transsexuals rape women's bodies by reducing the real female form to an artifact, appropriating this body for themselves .... Transsexuals merely cut off the most obvious means of invading women, so that they seem non-invasive."&lt;ref name="Raymond 1994"/&gt; 
Another site of conflict between feminists and [[trans women]] has been the [[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]]. In the early 1990s, the festival ejected a transsexual woman, Nancy Burkholder.&lt;ref name="vangelder"/&gt; In 2014, the festival "passionately rejected" accusations that it believed transgender "womyn are 'less than' other womyn."&lt;ref name="michfest-vogel"/&gt; The activist group [[Camp Trans]] had protested the "womyn-born-womyn" intention and advocated for greater acceptance of trans women within the feminist community. The festival had considered allowing only post-operative trans women to attend, however this was criticized as [[Class discrimination|classist]], as many trans women cannot afford sex reassignment surgery.&lt;ref name="sreedhar-transforming-feminism"/&gt;

Trans women such as [[Sandy Stone (artist)|Sandy Stone]] challenged the feminist conception of "biological woman". Stone worked as a sound engineer for [[Olivia Records]] from about 1974 to 1978, resigning as the controversy over a trans woman working for a lesbian-identified enterprise increased.&lt;ref name="Goldberg-Stone"/&gt; The debate continued in Raymond's book,&lt;ref name="Raymond 1994"/&gt; which devoted a chapter to criticism of "the transsexually constructed lesbian-feminist." Groups like [[Lesbian Organization of Toronto]] then voted to exclude trans lesbians.&lt;ref name="ross1995"/&gt; [[Sheila Jeffreys]] labeled transgenderism "deeply problematic from a feminist perspective and [stated] that transsexualism should be seen as a violation of human rights."&lt;ref name="jeffreys1997"/&gt;

In 2017, with regard to the question of whether trans women are women, [[Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie]] expressed the view that "trans women are trans women", meaning that while she acknowledges them to face discrimination on the basis of being transgender and sees this as a serious issue, she thinks that their experiences should not be conflated with those of women who face oppression on the basis of being born [[female]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.vox.com/identities/2017/3/15/14910900/chimamanda-ngozi-adichie-transgender-women-comments-apology |title=The controversy over Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie and trans women, explained |author=Emily Crockett |publisher=Vox |date=March 15, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; After sustaining severe criticism for her views, Adichie opined that the American [[Left-wing politics|Left]] is "creating its own decline" and is "very cannibalistic." She explained that she sees trans women as women despite her views, but stood behind her position.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/chimamanda-ngozi-adichie-says-the-american-left-is-creating-its-own-decline_us_59db6dbae4b072637c454c4d |title=Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie Says The American Left 'Is Creating Its Own Decline' |author=Claire Fallon |newspaper=Huffington Post |date=October 9, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Otherwise, cisgender feminist support came from the work of [[poststructuralist]] feminist and lesbian [[Judith Butler]], particularly her books ''Gender Trouble'' (1990) and ''Bodies That Matter'' (1993), which argue that the "violent inscription" of gender as a social construct on human bodies leads to violence against those that violate such binaristic gender dichotomies.&lt;ref name="butler-1990"/&gt;&lt;ref name="butler-1993"/&gt;

Feminists who oppose the inclusion of trans women in women's spaces have been labeled "[[TERF]]s", short for "trans-exclusionary radical feminists".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.irishtimes.com/life-and-style/health-family/transgender-for-beginners-trans-terf-cis-and-safe-spaces-1.3769653|title=Transgender for beginners: Trans, terf, cis and safe spaces|last=O'Connell|first=Jennifer|website=The Irish Times|language=en|access-date=2019-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those at whom the term is directed, in turn, have perceived their labeling as "TERF" to be a [[pejorative|slur]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine | url=http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2014/08/04/woman-2 | title=What Is a Woman? | magazine=The New Yorker | date=August 4, 2014 | author=Michelle Goldberg | quote=TERF stands for "trans-exclusionary radical feminist." The term can be useful for making a distinction with radical feminists who do not share the same position, but those at whom it is directed consider it a slur.}}{{pb}}{{cite news | url=http://bitchmagazine.org/post/the-long-history-of-transgender-exclusion-from-feminism | title=It's Time to End the Long History of Feminism Failing Transgender Women | work=[[Bitch Media]] | date=February 17, 2014 | accessdate=April 18, 2014 | author=Vasquez, Tina | quote=Drawing from that history, Brennan, fellow attorney Elizabeth Hungerford, and other modern-day feminists continue to actively question the inclusion of trans people in women's spaces. These feminists refer to themselves as "radical feminists" or "gender critical feminists." In 2008, trans women and trans advocates started referring to this group as "trans-exclusionary radical feminists" or TERFs, a term Brennan considers a slur.}}{{pb}}{{cite magazine | url=http://www.counterpunch.org/2013/08/02/sex-is-not-gender/ | title=Sex is Not Gender | magazine=[[CounterPunch]] | date=2–4 August 2013 | accessdate=10 August 2014 | author=Hungerford, Elizabeth | quote=Make no mistake, this is a slur. TERF is not meant to be explanatory, but insulting. These characterizations are hyperbolic, misleading, and ultimately defamatory. They do nothing but escalate the vitriol and fail to advance the conversation in any way.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Feminist journalist Sarah Ditum, who writes for ''[[The Guardian]]'' and the ''[[New Statesman]]'', said that the term is used to silence feminists through guilt by association.&lt;ref name="fc-terf-ditum"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.feministcurrent.com/2014/07/29/how-terf-works/ | title=How 'TERF' works | publisher=Feminist Current | date=July 29, 2014 | author=Sarah Ditum | quote=Am I a TERF? West didn't have the time to check: avoiding any association with a tainted form of feminism took precedence over sharing a message about domestic violence. And she acted perfectly rationally in this: to associate herself with me, even by merely [[retweet|RTing]] a statement she agreed with, could be enough to make her a "known TERF" in turn and lead to her being similarly denounced in public. But note the end result of this: a feminist has withdrawn support for another feminist speaking against male violence, ''because a man told her to.''}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meghan Murphy, founder of Canadian feminist website Feminist Current, opined that "TERF" should be considered [[hate speech]] after a woman was physically assaulted and several people defended or celebrated the assault on the grounds that the woman was a "TERF" and as such deserving of violence.&lt;ref name="fc-terf-hate-speech"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.feministcurrent.com/2017/09/21/terf-isnt-slur-hate-speech/ | title='TERF' isn't just a slur, it's hate speech | date=September 21, 2017 | author=Meghan Murphy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="speakers-corner"/&gt;

===In gay, lesbian, and bisexual communities===
Transphobia is documented in the [[lesbian]], [[gay]] and [[bisexual]] ([[LGBT|LGB]]) communities, despite historic cooperation between these communities in campaigns for equality, such as in the [[Stonewall Riots]].&lt;ref name=TransAdvocate1&gt;{{cite web|last1=Williams|first1=Christian|title=Interview With an Actual Stonewall Riot Veteran: The Ciswashing of Stonewall Must End!|url=http://www.transadvocate.com/interview-with-an-actual-stonewall-riot-veteran-the-ciswashing-of-stonewall-must-end_n_8750.htm|website=transadvocate.com|accessdate=27 December 2014|date=2013-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Unreliable source?|date=September 2017}}&lt;ref name=Prospect1&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Talusan |first1=Meridith |title=45 Years After Stonewall, the LGBT Movement Has a Transphobia Problem |url=http://prospect.org/article/45-years-after-stonewall-lgbt-movement-has-transphobia-problem |journal=The American Prospect |accessdate=27 December 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150101233619/http://prospect.org/article/45-years-after-stonewall-lgbt-movement-has-transphobia-problem |archivedate=1 January 2015 |df= |date=2014-06-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TheFrisky&gt;{{cite web|last1=Brink|first1=Rebecca Vipond|title=The Soapbox: On The Stonewall Rebellion's Trans History|url=http://www.thefrisky.com/2014-06-06/the-soapbox-on-the-stonewall-rebellions-trans-history/|work=[[The Frisky (website)|The Frisky]] |publisher=Spin Entertainment|accessdate=27 December 2014|date=2014-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AutoStraddle&gt;{{cite web|author=Cara|title=Yet Another News Outlet Fails Queer History 101 by Erasing Trans* People from Stonewall|url=http://www.autostraddle.com/yet-another-news-outlet-fails-queer-history-101-by-erasing-trans-people-from-stonewall-154998/|website=autostraddle.com|accessdate=27 December 2014|date=2013-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Authors and observers, such as transgender author Jillian Todd Weiss, have written that "there are social and political forces that have created a split between gay/lesbian communities and bisexual/transgender communities, and these forces have consequences for civil rights and community inclusion. 'Biphobia' and 'transphobia' are a result of these social and political forces, not psychological forces causing irrational fears in aberrant individuals."&lt;ref name="weiss2004"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Weiss | first1 = JT | year = 2004 | title = GL vs BT The archaeology of biphobia and transphobia within U.S. gay and lesbian community | journal = [[Journal of Bisexuality]] | volume = 3 | issue = 3–4| pages = 25–55 | doi=10.1300/j159v03n03_02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sears"&gt;Sears, J.T., and Williams, W.L. (1997). Overcoming Heterosexism and Homophobia. New York: Columbia University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":fone"&gt;Fone, B.R.S. (1998). ''The Columbia Anthology of Gay Literature: Readings from Western Antiquity to the Present Day.'' Columbia University Press, {{ISBN|9780231096706}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Gay and lesbian communities====
[[File:Ticked Off Trannies protesters Shankbone 2010.jpg|thumb|Protesters outside the 2010 premiere of ''[[Ticked-Off Trannies With Knives]]'', written and directed by gay filmmaker [[Israel Luna]], objecting to what they considered to be transphobic portrayals in the film and its trailer, which referred to several notable real-life murders of transgender people before being taken down.&lt;ref name=Tribeca&gt;[http://blogs.reuters.com/fanfare/2010/04/25/ticked-off-trannies-and-detractors-take-on-tribeca/ "Ticked-Off Trannies," and detractors, take on Tribeca] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100701101412/http://blogs.reuters.com/fanfare/2010/04/25/ticked-off-trannies-and-detractors-take-on-tribeca/ |date=2010-07-01 }}, Edith Honan, Reuters, April 25, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Historian [[Joanne Meyerowitz]] documented transphobia within the [[gay rights movement]] in the mid 20th century in response to publicity surrounding the transition of [[Christine Jorgensen]]. Jorgensen, who made frequent [[Homophobia|homophobic]] remarks and insisted she was not connected to or identified with gay men, was a polarizing figure among activists:

&lt;blockquote&gt;In 1953, for example, ''ONE'' magazine published a debate among its readers as to whether gay men should denounce Jorgensen. In the opening salvo, the author Jeff Winters accused Jorgensen of a "sweeping disservice" to gay men. "As far as the public knows," Winters wrote, "you were merely another unhappy homosexual who decided to get drastic about it." For Winters, Jorgensen's story simply confirmed the false belief that all men attracted to other men must be basically feminine," which, he said, "they are not." Jorgensen's precedent, he thought, encouraged the "reasoning" that led "to legal limitations upon the homosexual, mandatory injections, psychiatric treatment – and worse." In the not-so-distant past, scientists had experimented with castrating gay men.&lt;ref name="mayerowitz2002"&gt;Meyerowitz, Joanne (2002). ''How Sex Changed: A History of Transsexuality in the United States.'' Harvard University Press {{ISBN|978-0674009257}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Several prominent figures in [[second wave feminism]] have also been accused of transphobic attitudes, culminating in 1979 with the publication of ''[[The Transsexual Empire]]'' by [[Radical feminism|radical lesbian feminist]] [[Janice Raymond]], who popularized the term ''[[shemale]]'' as derogatory slur referring to [[trans women]] in 1994,&lt;ref name="Raymond 1994"/&gt; and her statements on transsexuality and transsexual people have been criticized by many in the [[LGBT]] and [[feminism|feminist]] communities as extremely [[transphobic]] and as constituting [[hate speech]].&lt;ref name="rose2004"&gt;Rose, Katrina C. (2004) "The Man Who Would be Janice Raymond." ''Transgender Tapestry'' 104, Winter 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="serano2007"&gt;[[Julia Serano]] (2007) ''Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Sexism and the Scapegoating of Femininity'', pp. 233–234&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="namaste2000"&gt;Namaste, Viviane K. (2000) ''Invisible Lives: The Erasure of Transsexual and Transgendered People'', pp. 33–34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hayes2003"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Hayes | first1 = Cressida J | year = 2003 | title = Feminist Solidarity after Queer Theory: The Case of Transgender | journal = Signs | volume = 28 | issue = 4| pages = 1093–1120 | doi=10.1086/343132}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1950s America, there was a debate among gay men and women about those who felt they were of the opposite sex.  Gay men and women who were trying to melt quietly into the majority society criticized them as "freaks" who brought unwanted disreputable attention upon them. Such attitudes were widespread at the time.&lt;ref name="GLBTphobia"&gt;{{cite web |last=Weiss |first=Jillian Todd |title=GL vs. BT: The Archaeology of Biphobia and Transphobia Within the U.S. Gay and Lesbian Community |url=http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/glvsbt.htm |accessdate=7 July 2006 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160329150447/http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/glvsbt.htm |archivedate=2016-03-29 }}{{better source|date=April 2016|reason=professor cut/paste of a published journal paper is not the best source and may be copyvio }} quoting Kay Brown of Transhistory.net [defunct since 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[trans men]] face rejection from lesbian communities they had been part of prior to transition. Journalist Louise Rafkin writes, "there are those who are feeling curiously uncomfortable standing by as friends morph into men. Sometimes there is a generational flavor to this discomfort; many in the over-40 crowd feel particular unease", stating that this was "shaking the foundation of the lesbian-feminist world".&lt;ref name="rafkin"&gt;Rafkin, Louise (June 22, 2003) [http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2003/06/22/CM254728.DTL Straddling Sexes: Young lesbians transitioning into men are shaking the foundation of the lesbian-feminist world.] ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Trans men were part of the protest at the 2000 [[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]], the first time the '[[womyn-born womyn]] only' policy has been used against trans males, women supporting the transgender community and young gender-variant women.&lt;ref name="mantilla2000"&gt;Mantilla, Karla (October 1, 2000). Michigan: transgender controversy. ''[[Off Our Backs]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1970s, conflicts began to emerge due to different syntheses of lesbian, [[feminist]] and transgender political movements, particularly in the United States. San Francisco trans activist and entertainer [[Beth Elliott]] became the focus of debate over whether to include transgender lesbians in the movement, and she was eventually blacklisted by her own movement.&lt;ref name="rubin2003"&gt;Henry Rubin (2003). ''Self-made Men: Identity and Embodiment Among Transsexual Men.'' Vanderbilt University Press, {{ISBN|978-0-8265-1435-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="nettick"&gt;Geri Nettick, Beth Elliot (1996). "Mirrors: Portrait of a Lesbian Transsexual." Badboy Books {{ISBN|978-1-56333-435-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Bisexual communities and binarism====
One view is that the word ''bisexual'' is transphobic, as "bi" means "two" (thus implying a belief in the [[gender binary|binary view of gender]]). Some people, such as scholar Shiri Eisner, say that some make the claim that the term "erases nonbinary genders and sexes out of existence",&lt;ref name=Eisner1&gt;{{cite book|last1=Eisner|first1=Shiri|title=Bi: Notes for a Bisexual Revolution|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CbJaZIosLwQC&amp;pg=PT27|date=2 July 2013|publisher=Seal Press|isbn=978-1580054751|accessdate=28 December 2014|quote=Yet another way in which bisexuality has been recently imagined is as inherently binary, and therefore intrinsically transphobic. [...] As the argument classically goes, since the word bisexuality has bi (literally: two) in it, it inherently refers to a two-gender structure. This means it erases nonbinary genders and sexes out of existence.|pages=27}}&lt;/ref&gt; as many dictionaries define bisexuality as "of, relating to, or having a sexual orientation to persons of either sex",&lt;ref name=Freedict1&gt;{{cite web|title=Bisexual - definition of bisexual by The Free Dictionary |url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/bisexual|website=thefreedictionary.com |publisher=The Free Dictionary|accessdate=28 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; "sexually attracted to both men and women"&lt;ref name=OxfordDicts&gt;{{cite web|title=bisexual: definition of bisexual in Oxford dictionary (British &amp; World English)|url=http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/bisexual|website=oxforddictionaries.com|publisher=Oxford Dictionaies|accessdate=28 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and other similar definitions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Definition of Bisexual by Merriam-Webster |url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/bisexual|website=merriam-webster.com|publisher=Merriam-Webster Online|accessdate=28 December 2014|quote=sexually attracted to both men and women}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Google&gt;{{cite web|title=Google Search: Bisexual definition|url=https://www.google.co.uk/webhp?complete=0&amp;gws_rd=cr&amp;ei=EUGgVLC5G4nsUvyfgKAL#complete=0&amp;q=bisexual+define|website=google.co.uk|quote=sexually attracted to both men and women.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, some bisexual individuals and scholars object to the notion that bisexuality means sexual attraction to only two genders, arguing that since ''bisexual'' is not simply about attraction to two sexes and encompasses gender as well, it can include attraction to more than one&lt;ref name="biresource.net"&gt;{{cite web|title=BRC Brochure 2010 |year=2010 |publisher=Bisexual Resource Council/[[Bisexual Resource Center]] |work=biresource.net |accessdate=July 8, 2013 |url=http://www.biresource.net/BRC_Brochure_2010.pdf |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130731101822/http://www.biresource.net/BRC_Brochure_2010.pdf |archivedate=July 31, 2013 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; or more than two genders&lt;ref name="bisexual.org"&gt;{{cite web|title=Doesn't identifying as bisexual reinforce a false gender binary?|publisher=[[American Institute of Bisexuality]]|date=2014|accessdate=May 27, 2014|url=http://bisexual.org/qna/doesnt-identifying-as-bisexual-reinforce-a-false-gender-binary/}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is occasionally defined as such.&lt;ref name="Eisner1"/&gt; Others, such as the [[American Institute of Bisexuality]], say that the term "is an open and inclusive term for many kinds of people with same-sex and different-sex attractions"&lt;ref name="bisexual.org2"&gt;{{cite web|title=What is the difference between bisexual and terms like pansexual, polysexual, omnisexual, ambisexual, and fluid?|publisher=[[American Institute of Bisexuality]]|date=2014|accessdate=May 27, 2014|url=http://bisexual.org/qna/what-is-the-difference-between-bisexual-and-terms-like-pansexual-polysexual-omnisexual-ambisexual-and-fluid/}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that "the scientific classification ''bisexual'' only addresses the physical, biological sex of the people involved, not the gender-presentation."&lt;ref name="bisexual.org"/&gt;

In order to deal with issues related to transphobia and the gender binary, many individuals have taken on terms such as ''[[pansexual]]'', ''omnisexual'' (an alternative word for pansexual) or ''[[polysexual]]'' in place of the term ''bisexual''. The American Institute of Bisexuality argues that these terms "describe a person with homosexual and heterosexual attractions, and therefore people with these labels are also bisexual"&lt;ref name="bisexual.org2"/&gt; and that the notion that bisexuality is a reinforcement of a gender binary is a concept that is founded upon "anti-science, anti-Enlightenment philosophy that has ironically found a home within many Queer Studies departments at universities across the Anglophone world".&lt;ref name="bisexual.org"/&gt; Eisner agrees with this view, stating that "allegations of binarism have little to do with bisexuality's actual attributes or bisexual people's behavior in real life" and that the allegations are an attempt to separate the bisexual and transgender communities politically.&lt;ref name="Eisner1"/&gt;

==Consequences==
[[File:Graffiti left by angry trans people in Baltimore.jpg|thumb|left|Angry graffiti left by trans individuals in [[Baltimore]], [[Maryland]] expressing disenfranchisement with the world in which they live.]]
Whether intentional or not, transphobia and cissexism have severe consequences for the target of the negative attitude. Transphobia creates significant stresses for transgender people which can lead them to feel shame, low [[self-esteem]], [[social alienation|alienation]] and inadequacy. Transgender youth often try to cope with the stress by running away from home, dropping out of school, using drugs or [[Self-mutilation|self-harming]].&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Disparities in Psychiatric Care: Clinical and Cross-Cultural Perspectives|last = Ruiz MD|first = Pedro|publisher = Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins|year = 2009|isbn = 978-0781796392|location = |pages = 111}}&lt;/ref&gt; Suicide rates among transgender people are thought to be especially high, because of how they are treated by their families and by society.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

===Problems at home and at school===
The 2015 United States Transgender Survey, the largest such survey ever carried out (with 27,715 respondents), found that one in ten respondents suffered transphobic violence at the hands of a family member and 8% were kicked out of their homes for being transgender. The majority of those who were openly transgender or perceived as transgender at school were victims of some form of mistreatment on account of this, including verbal abuse (54%), physical attacks (24%), and sexual assault (13%). 17% experienced such severe mistreatment that they had to leave school. Support from one's community or family was correlated with more positive outcomes related to mental health and social functioning.&lt;ref name="usts"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.transequality.org/sites/default/files/docs/USTS-Executive-Summary-FINAL.PDF|title=Executive Summary|work=U.S. Transgender Survey|publisher=National Center for Transgender Equality|location=Washington}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

62% of lawsuits involving transgender people state that defendants face family problems.&lt;ref name="Suicide"/&gt;{{clarify|in what country? what does "family problems" mean/entail?|date=December 2017}}

===Poverty and homelessness===
Nearly one third of U.S. transgender people responding to the 2015 U.S. Transgender Survey lived in poverty, compared to 14% of the population. During the 12 months prior to the survey, 30% of employed transgender people were either fired or mistreated for being transgender, from verbal abuse to sexual violence. 30% had been homeless at some point in their life, and 12% had been homeless during the previous year. Family and community support were correlated with significantly lower rates of homelessness and poverty.&lt;ref name="usts"/&gt;

===Violence and harassment===
During the year prior to the 2015 U.S. survey, 46% of respondents had been verbally harassed and 9% had been physically attacked for being transgender. 10% had been sexually assaulted during the previous year, and 47% had been sexually assaulted at some point in their life.&lt;ref name="usts"/&gt;

====In public restrooms====
During the year prior to the 2015 U.S. survey, 12% of respondents reported being verbally harassed in a public restroom. 1% reported being sexually assaulted in a public restroom for being transgender, and 1% reported being otherwise physically assaulted for being transgender. 9% reported being denied the right to use a public restroom consistent with their gender.&lt;ref name="usts"/&gt;

===Health===
During the year prior to the 2015 U.S. survey, 59% of respondents reported avoiding using a public restroom out of fear of violence or harassment. 32% limited the amount they ate or drink in order to avoid using a public restroom. 8% reported suffering a urinary tract infection, kidney infection, or other kidney problem as a result of avoiding public restrooms.&lt;ref name="usts"/&gt;

33% reported having negative experiences with a healthcare professional related to being transgender, such as verbal harassment or denial of treatment. 23% reported that they did not seek treatment for a condition out of fear of being mistreated, while 33% did not seek treatment because they were unable to afford it.&lt;ref name="usts"/&gt;

During the month prior to the survey, 39% of American transgender people experienced major psychological distress, compared to 5% of the general population of the United States. 40% had attempted suicide at some point in their life, compared to 4.6 percent of the American population. Family and community support were correlated with far lower rates of suicide attempts and of major psychological distress.&lt;ref name="usts"/&gt;

A study conducted on transgender women of color in San Francisco has shown a higher correlation between transphobia and risk of transgender women engaging in HIV risk behavior. The study shows that the transgender youth face social discrimination, and they may not have a social role model. The young adults in this group have shown a higher risk of engaging in unprotected receptive anal intercourse when the exposure to transphobia is high. Therefore, as per the study shows a correlation between transphobia and high risk of HIV.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sugano|first=Eiko|last2=Nemoto|first2=Tooru|last3=Operario|first3=Don|date=2006|title=The Impact of Exposure to Transphobia on HIV Risk Behavior in a Sample of Transgendered Women of Color in San Francisco|journal=AIDS and Behavior|volume=10|issue = 2|pages=217–225|doi=10.1007/s10461-005-9040-z|pmid=16362237|citeseerx=10.1.1.554.5857}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Mental health====
People who are transgender are more likely to experience some type of psychological distress because of the harassment and discrimination that comes with transphobia. Student Affairs Administrators in Higher Education conducted a nationwide survey on college campuses examining the psychological effects on transgender people, with a sample size of 86. Out of these 86 participants, 54% stated they have attended psychological counseling before and 10% had been hospitalized for reasons related to mental health. The final results of the study show that over twice as many participants who considered themselves transgender (43%) had engaged in self-injurious behavior, versus those who considered themselves male or female (16%).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hayes|first=J.|date=|title=The Center for Collegiate Mental Health: Practice and research working together |journal=Journal of College Counseling|volume=|pages=101–104|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Effrig|first=Jessica C.|last2=Bieschke|first2=Kathleen J.|last3=Locke|first3=Benjamin D.|date=2011-09-01|title=Examining Victimization and Psychological Distress in Transgender College Students|journal=Journal of College Counseling|language=en|volume=14|issue=2|pages=143–157|doi=10.1002/j.2161-1882.2011.tb00269.x|issn=2161-1882}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Virupaksha, Muralidhar, and Ramakrishna, suicide attempts among transgender people globally range from 32% to 50%. In India, 31% to 50% of transgender people have tried to commit suicide before age 20. 50% of transgender people in Australia and 45% of those in England have attempted suicide at least once.&lt;ref name="Suicide"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Virupaksha|first=H. G.|last2=Muralidhar|first2=Daliboyina|last3=Ramakrishna|first3=Jayashree|date=2016|title=Suicide and Suicidal Behavior among Transgender Persons|journal=Indian Journal of Psychological Medicine|volume=38|issue=6|pages=505–509|doi=10.4103/0253-7176.194908|issn=0253-7176|pmc=5178031|pmid=28031583}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, suicide attempts reported by transgender and gender nonconforming adults exceed the rate of the general population: 41% versus 4.6 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite techreport |first=Ann H. |last=Haas |author2=Philip Rodgers |title=Suicide Attempts Among Transgender and Gender Non-Conforming Adults |number= |institution=American Foundation for Suicide Prevention and Williams Institute, UCLA School of Law |year=2014 | url = http://williamsinstitute.law.ucla.edu/wp-content/uploads/AFSP-Williams-Suicide-Report-Final.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; In San Francisco alone, the suicide rate among transgender people is 32% overall, and for those under age 25 it is 50%.&lt;ref name="Suicide"/&gt;

According to the study ''Transphobia Among Transgenders of Color'' by the University of California, San Francisco, transphobia affects the psychological vulnerability of transgender people of color as compared to those of other ethnicities. Acts of transphobia such as undue denial of services, unfair dismissal from work places or stigmatization have far-reaching effects on the subjects such as low self-esteem, under-performance, stress, withdrawal or even depression. When it comes to the minorities, who are already proven to be undergoing various forms of discrimination, the consequences are even more exaggerated. Transgender people of color are more significantly associated with depression than their white counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://prevention.ucsf.edu/uploads/pubs/presentations/pdf/APHA_Nemoto.pdf|title=Transphobia Among Transgenders of Color|work=Center for AIDS Prevention Studies, University of California, San Francisco|date=November 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Transgender}}
{{div col|colwidth=20}}
* [[Discrimination against non-binary gender people]]
* [[GATE (organization)|GATE]]
* [[Hate crime]]
* [[Corrective rape]]
* [[LGBT people in prison]]
* [[LGBT rights opposition]]
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[List of unlawfully killed transgender people]]
* [[Press for Change]] – UK law organisation for transgender people
* [[Transgender Day of Remembrance]]
* [[Transgender Europe]]
* [[Transgender inequality]]
* [[Transgender Law Center]]
* [[Transmisogyny]]
* [[Trans panic defense]] – a legal defense for assault or murder where the victim is trans.
* [[Yogyakarta Principles]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|refs=

&lt;ref name="Goldberg"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Goldberg|first1=Michelle|title=What Is a Woman?|journal=The New Yorker|date=August 4, 2014|url=http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2014/08/04/woman-2|accessdate=November 20, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Raymond 1994"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Raymond|first=J.|year=1994|title=The Transsexual Empire|publisher=Teachers College Press|edition=2nd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="hp-what-is-terf"&gt;{{Cite web|title = Trans-Exclusionary Radical Feminism: What Exactly Is It, And Why Does It Hurt?|url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/kelsie-brynn-jones/transexclusionary-radical-terf_b_5632332.html|website = The Huffington Post|accessdate = 2015-12-24|date = 2014-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="raymond-fictions-and-facts"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://janiceraymond.com/fictions-and-facts-about-the-transsexual-empire/ | title=Fictions and Facts About the Transsexual Empire | author=Janice Raymond | quote=The NCHCT took these submissions and published a report on "Transsexual Surgery" in its 1981 Assessment Report Series. My findings were quoted neutrally in one sentence of the 15 page final report. "Some have held that it would be preferable to modify society's sex role expectations of men and women than to modify either the body or the mind of individuals to fit these expectations. (Raymond 1980)." This was the only part of my paper that made it into the published report. The conclusion of the report was that transsexual surgery is "controversial" and "must be considered experimental." To give my submission credit for these conclusions is fatuous in the context of reading a report that was obviously informed by multiple sources.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Steinem-OutrageousActs"&gt;{{cite book |last=Steinem |first=Gloria |authorlink=Gloria Steinem |title=Outrageous Acts and Everyday Rebellions |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KVHmzw43TgkC |accessdate=13 December 2017 |series=EBL-Schweitzer |date=15 May 2012 |publisher=Open Road Media |pages=206–210 |isbn=978-1-4532-5018-1 |oclc=894737151 |orig-year=1st pub. 1983}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="bm-trans-exclusion-steinem"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://bitchmagazine.org/post/the-long-history-of-transgender-exclusion-from-feminism | title=It's Time to End the Long History of Feminism Failing Transgender Women | work=[[Bitch Media]] | date=February 17, 2014 | accessdate=April 18, 2014 | author=Vasquez, Tina | quote=Steinem was long considered transphobic because of the stance she took in writing about professional tennis player Renée Richards, who transitioned in the 1970's. Steinem's 1983 book ''Outrageous Acts and Everyday Rebellion'' cited Janice Raymond's work and discussed how transsexuals "mutilate their own bodies."}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="advocate-steinem-oped"&gt;{{cite web |last=Steinem |first=Gloria |title=Op-ed: On Working Together Over Time |url=http://www.advocate.com/commentary/2013/10/02/op-ed-working-together-over-time |date=October 2, 2013 |website=The Advocate |publisher=Here Publishing |accessdate=December 13, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="vangelder"&gt;Van Gelder, Lindsy; and Pamela Robin Brandt. ''The Girls Next Door: Into the Heart of Lesbian America'', p. 73. Simon and Schuster, {{ISBN|978-0-684-83957-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="michfest-vogel"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Vogel|first1=Lisa|title=Michfest Response to Equality Michigan's Call For Boycott|url=http://michfest.com/statement-from-michigan-womyns-music-festival-8_1_4/|website=Michigan Womyn's Music Festival|date=August 1, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="sreedhar-transforming-feminism"&gt;{{cite book
| last                  = Sreedhar
| first                 = Susanne
| editor-last           = Scott-Dixon
| editor-first          = Krista
| title                 = Trans/Forming Feminisms: Trans/Feminist Voices Speak Out
| year                  = 2006
| publisher             = Sumach Press
| location              = Toronto
| isbn                  = 978-1-894-54961-5
| oclc                  = 70839321
| pages                 = 164–65
| nopp                  =
| chapter               = The Ethics of Exclusion: Gender and Politics at the Michigan Womyn's Music Festival
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Goldberg-Stone"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Goldberg |first1=Michelle |title=What Is a Woman? |journal=The New Yorker |date=August 4, 2014 |url=http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2014/08/04/woman-2 |accessdate=November 20, 2015 |quote=Stone received death threats, but ultimately it was the threat of a boycott that drove her out of the collective.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="ross1995"&gt;Ross, Becki (1995). ''The House that Jill Built: A Lesbian Nation in Formation.'' University of Toronto Press, {{ISBN|978-0-8020-7479-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="jeffreys1997"&gt;Jeffreys, Sheila (1997). Transgender Activism: A Lesbian Feminist Perspective. "Journal of Lesbian Studies", Vol. 1(3/4) 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="butler-1990"&gt;Judith Butler (1990). ''Gender Trouble''. New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="butler-1993"&gt;Judith Butler (1993). ''Bodies That Matter''. New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- [[WP:LDR]] not currently used in the article:

&lt;ref name="Goldberg-terf"&gt;{{cite magazine | url=http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2014/08/04/woman-2 | title=What Is a Woman? | magazine=The New Yorker | date=August 4, 2014 | author=Michelle Goldberg | quote=TERF stands for "trans-exclusionary radical feminist." The term can be useful for making a distinction with radical feminists who do not share the same position, but those at whom it is directed consider it a slur.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="bm-trans-exclusion-terf"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://bitchmagazine.org/post/the-long-history-of-transgender-exclusion-from-feminism | title=It's Time to End the Long History of Feminism Failing Transgender Women | work=[[Bitch Media]] | date=February 17, 2014 | accessdate=April 18, 2014 | author=Vasquez, Tina | quote=Drawing from that history, Brennan, fellow attorney Elizabeth Hungerford, and other modern-day feminists continue to actively question the inclusion of trans people in women's spaces. These feminists refer to themselves as "radical feminists" or "gender critical feminists." In 2008, trans women and trans advocates started referring to this group as "trans-exclusionary radical feminists" or TERFs, a term Brennan considers a slur.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="cp-sex-gender"&gt;{{cite magazine | url=http://www.counterpunch.org/2013/08/02/sex-is-not-gender/ | title=Sex is Not Gender | magazine=[[CounterPunch]] | date=2–4 August 2013 | accessdate=10 August 2014 | author=Hungerford, Elizabeth | quote=Make no mistake, this is a slur. TERF is not meant to be explanatory, but insulting. These characterizations are hyperbolic, misleading, and ultimately defamatory. They do nothing but escalate the vitriol and fail to advance the conversation in any way.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="fc-terf-ditum"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.feministcurrent.com/2014/07/29/how-terf-works/ | title=How 'TERF' works | publisher=Feminist Current | date=July 29, 2014 | author=Sarah Ditum | quote=Am I a TERF? West didn't have the time to check: avoiding any association with a tainted form of feminism took precedence over sharing a message about domestic violence. And she acted perfectly rationally in this: to associate herself with me, even by merely [[retweet|RTing]] a statement she agreed with, could be enough to make her a "known TERF" in turn and lead to her being similarly denounced in public. But note the end result of this: a feminist has withdrawn support for another feminist speaking against male violence, ''because a man told her to.''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="fc-terf-hate-speech"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.feministcurrent.com/2017/09/21/terf-isnt-slur-hate-speech/ | title='TERF' isn't just a slur, it's hate speech | date=September 21, 2017 | author=Meghan Murphy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;
&lt;ref name="speakers-corner"&gt;
{{cite magazine | url=https://www.newstatesman.com/politics/feminism/2017/09/trans-rights-terfs-and-bruised-60-year-old-what-happened-speakers-corner | title=Trans rights, TERFs, and a bruised 60-year-old: what happened at Speakers' Corner? | magazine=New Statesman | date=September 14, 2017 | author=Anoosh Chakelian }}
{{pb}}
{{cite news | url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/trans-group-ath-condones-punching-feminists-n6mz06pj3 | title=Trans group ATH 'condones punching feminists' | newspaper=The Sunday Times | date=September 24, 2017 | author=James Gillespie }}
{{pb}}
{{cite web | url=http://www.morningstaronline.co.uk/a-eb98-Misogynist-violence-at-Speakers-Corner | title=Misogynist violence at Speakers' Corner | publisher=Morning Star | date=September 19, 2017 | author=Jen Izakson }}
{{pb}}
{{cite web | url=http://www.feministcurrent.com/2017/09/15/historic-speakers-corner-becomes-site-anti-feminist-silencing-violence/ | title=Historic Speaker's Corner becomes site of anti-feminist silencing and violence | date=September 15, 2017 | publisher=Feminist Current | author=Meghan Murphy }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==Further reading==
* [http://ec.europa.eu/justice/discrimination/files/trans_and_intersex_people_web3_en.pdf "Thematic report on Discrimination against trans and intersex people on the grounds of sex, gender identity and gender expression"], [[The European Commission]], 2012.

==External links==
* [http://www.gender.org/remember/ Remembering our Dead]
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/rcip//sbh.html Survivor bashing – bias motivated hate crimes]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100715024953/http://new.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=2111&amp;Itemid=1837&amp;lang=en Translatina documentary (2010)]

{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Transgender}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Prejudice against LGBT people]]
[[Category:Transphobia| ]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender-related prejudices]]
[[Category:Hatred]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>