<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101115025216|396832066" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="67084" pageid="67084" ns="0" title="Transphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-15T15:35:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{for|the phenomenon encountered in coordination chemistry|transphobia effect}}
{{Globalize|date=November 2009}}
&lt;!---PLEASE NOTE: When the article Transprejudice was merged into this article, consensus was reached that that term must remain in this article. Thus, please do not remove references to the term "transprejudice" from this article. Thank you.
-----&gt;{{Discrimination sidebar}}{{Transgender sidebar}}
'''Transphobia''' (or less commonly, '''transprejudice''' and '''trans-misogyny''', referring to transphobia directed toward [[transwomen]], or '''trans-misandry''', referring to transphobia directed toward [[transmen]]) refers to discrimination against [[transsexualism]] and transsexual or [[transgender]] people, based on the expression of their internal gender identity (see [[Phobia#Terms for prejudice or discrimination|Phobia – terms indicating prejudice or class discrimination]]). Whether intentional or not, transphobia can have severe consequences for the target of the negative attitude. Many transpeople also experience [[homophobia]] from people who incorrectly associate their [[gender identity]] with [[homosexuality]].&lt;ref name="MetPoliceDefs"&gt;{{cite web |title=Crime reduction – Police crack down on hate crimes |publisher=Metropolitan Police |url=http://cms.met.police.uk/news/policy_organisational_news_and_general_information/crackdown_on_hate_crimes |accessdate=6 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Attacking someone on the basis of a perception of their [[gender identity]] rather the perception of their [[sexual orientation]] is known as "[[trans-bashing]]", as opposed to "[[gay bashing]]".

== Examples ==
There are many recorded examples of transphobia in many of its different forms and manifestations throughout society. Some instances clearly involve violence and extreme malice, while others involve little more than a lack of understanding or experience of the condition, sometimes involving unconscious predisposition based upon various religious edicts or social conventions.

=== Difficulties encountered by transgender people ===
Sometimes homeless shelters and prisons have engaged in practices that have a demeaning impact on transwomen, refusing, for example, admission to women's areas and forcing them to sleep and bathe in the presence of men.&lt;ref name="transparent"&gt;{{cite book |last= Beam|first= Cris |title= Transparent |publisher= Harvest Books |year= 2008|month= January|isbn= 9780156033770 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This situation has been changing in some areas, however. For example, on February 8, 2006, New York City's Department of Homeless Services announced an overhaul of its housing policy with the goal of specifically ending discrimination against transgender people in its shelters.&lt;ref name="housing"&gt;{{cite web
  |title=NYC's Department of Homeless Services Issues a Trans-Affirmative Housing Policy
  |publisher=The Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Center
  |date=5 February 2006
  |url=http://www.gaycenter.org/news/press/News.2006-02-07.3578982442/news_view
  |accessdate=6 September 2006 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060615050747/http://www.gaycenter.org/news/press/News.2006-02-07.3578982442/news_view &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 15 June 2006}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some notable victims of violent crimes motivated by transphobia include [[Brandon Teena]], [[Gwen Araujo]], [[Angie Zapata]], [[Nizah Morris]], and [[Lauren Harries]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/4218250.stm|title=Transsexual to move to 'safer' LA|publisher=[[BBC News]]|date=6 September 2005}}]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Transphobia in healthcare ===
Transgender people depend largely on the medical profession to receive not only [[Hormone replacement therapy (trans)|hormone replacement therapy]], but also other vital care. Often it can be difficult for gender patients to receive proper health care and treatment, because medical [[gatekeeper]]s who are transphobic (or who misunderstand the nature of gender identity disorder) will refuse to administer necessary treatment; in at least one case that included the refusal to treat [[Robert Eads]], a [[transman]], for ovarian cancer, of which he subsequently died.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ftminfo.net/sundance.html|title=FTM Informational Network&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;|accessdate=2009-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gender.org/remember/about/core.html|title=Remembering Our Dead&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;|accessdate=2009-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another example of this is the case of [[Tyra Hunter]]. Ms. Hunter was involved in an automobile accident, and when [[Emergency medical services|rescue workers]] discovered she was transgender, they backed away and stopped administering treatment. She later died in hospital.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.glaa.org/archive/1998/margiehunter1211.shtml|title=Victory in Tyra Hunter case&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;|accessdate=2009-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Transphobia in employment ===
Transphobia can also manifest itself in the workplace. Sometimes transsexuals lose their jobs when they begin to transition. A study from [[Willamette University]] states that discrimination is so rife that it is virtually impossible to find a job at all.&lt;ref name="TransEmploy"&gt;{{cite web |author=JoAnna McNamara
|title=Employment discrimination and the Transsexual|publisher=[[Willamette University]]|date=30 August 1996|url=http://www.willamette.edu/~rrunkel/gwr/mcnamara|accessdate=10 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

News stories from the ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'' and [[Associated Press]] have cited a 1999 study by the [[San Francisco Department of Public Health]] finding a 70 percent [[unemployment]] rate amongst the city's transgender population. On February 18, 1999, the San Francisco Department of Public Health issued the results of a 1997 survey of 392 MTF (male-to-female) and 123 FTM (female-to-male) transgender people, showing amongst other things that only 40 percent of those MTF transgender people surveyed had earned money from full or part-time employment over the preceding six months' period. For FTMs, the equivalent statistic was 81 percent. The survey also found that 46 percent of MTFs and 57 percent of FTMs reported employment discrimination.&lt;ref name="transhealth"&gt;{{cite web |author=The Transgender Community Health Project |title=Sociodemographics|work=Descriptive Results|publisher=[http://hivinsite.ucsf.edu HIVInSite]|date=18 February 1999|url=http://hivinsite.ucsf.edu/InSite?page=cftg-02-02#S5.1X|accessdate=7 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the hiring process, discrimination may be either open or covert, with employers finding other ostensible reasons not to hire a candidate or just not informing prospective employees at all as to why they are not being hired. Additionally, when an employer fires or otherwise discriminates against a transgender employee, it may be a "mixed motive" case, with the employer openly citing obvious wrongdoing, job performance issues or the like (such as excessive tardiness, for example) while keeping silent in regards to transphobia.&lt;ref name="TransEmploy2"&gt;{{cite web |author=Barbara Findlay, Q.C.
|title=Transgendered people and Employment: An equality analysis|publisher=[http://www.barbarafindlay.com/ Barbara Findlay Law Office]|date=June 1999|url=http://www.barbarafindlay.com/articles/43.pdf|accessdate=10 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Employment discrimination on the basis of gender identity and expression is [[Legal aspects of transsexualism in the United States#Discrimination|illegal in a number of U.S. cities, towns and states]]. Such discrimination is outlawed by specific legislation in the State of New Jersey and might be in other states (as it is in the states of California, Illinois, Maine, Minnesota, New Mexico and Washington) or city ordinances; additionally, it is covered by case law in some other states. (For example, Massachusetts is covered by cases such as Lie vs. Sky Publishing Co. and Jette vs. Honey Farms.) Several other states and cities prohibit such discrimination in public employment. [[Sweden]] and the [[United Kingdom]] has also legislated against employment discrimination on the grounds of [[gender identity]]. Sometimes, however, employers discriminate against transgender employees in spite of such legal protections.&lt;ref name="TransEmploy2" /&gt;

There is at least one high-profile employment-related court case unfavorable to transgender people. In 2000, the Southern U.S. grocery chain [[Winn-Dixie (supermarket)|Winn-Dixie]] fired longtime employee Peter Oiler, despite a history of repeatedly earning raises and promotions, after management learned that the married, heterosexual truck driver occasionally [[crossdressing|cross-dressed]] off the job. Management argued that this hurt Winn-Dixie's corporate image. The [[American Civil Liberties Union]] filed a lawsuit against Winn-Dixie on behalf of Oiler but a judge dismissed it. The case, however, led to a picket of the company's [[Jacksonville, Florida]], headquarters and a boycott against the company.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

Sometimes transgendered people facing employment discrimination turn to [[sex industry|sex work]] to survive, placing them at additional risk of such things as encountering troubles with the law, including arrest and criminal prosecution; enduring workplace violence; and possibly contracting [[sexually transmitted disease]]s such as [[HIV]].&lt;ref name="transhealth" /&gt;

== Transprejudice ==
''Transprejudice'' is a similar term to transphobia, and refers to the negative valuing, stereotyping, and discriminatory treatment of individuals whose appearance and/or identity does not conform to current social expectations or conventional conceptions of gender.&lt;ref&gt;King, M., Webster, B., &amp; Winter, S. (2007). Transprejudice in Hong Kong: Chinese Attitudes Towards Transgenderism and Transgender Civil Rights (under review)&lt;/ref&gt;

Transprejudice may be manifested in ways similar to other prejudicial beliefs, such as [[homophobia]] or sexual prejudice. As Blumenfeld (1992) suggests, homophobia functions on four distinct, yet interrelated, levels: personal, interpersonal, institutional, and cultural (also referred to as collective or societal).&lt;ref&gt;Blumenfeld, W. J. (1992). Homophobia: How We All Pay the Price: Beacon Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Adapting Blumenfeld’s framework for use with transprejudice, personal transprejudice would refer to an individual’s belief system (prejudices) about transgender and transsexual individuals. Interpersonal transprejudice would be evident when a personal prejudice transforms into discriminatory behavior. Institutional transprejudice would be seen in the ways in which government, business, religious, educational, and professional organizations (e.g., the medical and psychiatric community) systematically discriminate against transgender and transsexual individuals. Finally, cultural transprejudice would refer to the social cognition that influences attitudes toward transgender and transsexual persons. {{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

==Transphobia in the lesbian, gay and bisexual community==
Some members of the [[LGBT]] communities are uncomfortable with transgender individuals and issues. For example, [[transwomen]] (male-to-female transgender and transsexual people) are sometimes denied entry to women's spaces, and the explanations given for such actions betray a degree of transphobia. The [[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]], for instance, has caused much debate for limiting its attendance to "[[womyn]]-born womyn".&lt;ref name="womynfest"&gt;{{cite web
  |last=Taormino
  |first=Tristan
  |authorlink=Tristan Taormino
  |title=Trouble in Utopia
  |publisher=The Village Voice
  |date=13 September 2000
  |url=http://www.villagevoice.com/people/0037,taormino,18110,24.html
  |accessdate=7 September 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Kay Brown of transhistory.net (“Transsexual, Transgender and Intersex History”) has set forth a long chronology of the ejection of those whom we now know as “transgendered” from gay organizations starting in the 1970s.&lt;ref name="GLBTphobia"&gt;{{cite web |last=Weiss|first=Jillian Todd|title=GL vs. BT: The Archaeology of Biphobia and Transphobia Within the U.S. Gay and Lesbian Community|url=http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/glvsbt.htm|accessdate=7 July 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some trans men face ostracism and rejection from [[lesbian]] communities they had been part of prior to transition. Journalist Louise Rafkin writes, "There are those who are feeling curiously uncomfortable standing by as friends morph into men. Sometimes there is a generational flavor to this discomfort; many in the over-40 crowd feel particular unease."&lt;ref name="rafkin"&gt;Rafkin, Louise (June 22, 2003) [http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2003/06/22/CM254728.DTL Straddling Sexes: Young lesbians transitioning into men are shaking the foundation of the lesbian-feminist world.] ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Trans men were part of the protest at the 2000 [[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]], "the first time the 'womyn-born womyn only' policy has been used against trannie boys, boydykes, FTM's, [[Lesbian Avengers]] and young [[gender-variant]] women."&lt;ref name="mantilla2000"&gt;Mantilla, Karla (October 1, 2000). Michigan: transgender controversy. ''[[Off Our Backs]]''&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the early 1970s, conflicts began to emerge due to different syntheses of [[lesbian]], [[feminist]] and [[transgender]] political movements, particularly in the United States. San Francisco activist and entertainer Beth Elliott became the focus of debate over whether to include transsexual lesbians in the movement, and she was eventually blacklisted by her own movement.&lt;ref name="rubin2003"&gt;Henry Rubin (2003). ''Self-made Men: Identity and Embodiment Among Transsexual Men.'' Vanderbilt University Press, ISBN 978-0-8265-1435-6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="nettick"&gt;Geri Nettick, Beth Elliot (1996). "Mirrors: Portrait of a Lesbian Transexual."  Badboy Books  ISBN 978-1-56333-435-1&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Ticked Off Trannies protesters Shankbone 2010.jpg|thumb|Protesters outside the 2010 premiere of ''Ticked Off Trannies with Knives'' for what they considered to be offensive trans portrayals in the [[Camp (style)|camp]] film.&lt;ref name=Tribeca&gt;[http://blogs.reuters.com/fanfare/2010/04/25/ticked-off-trannies-and-detractors-take-on-tribeca/ “Ticked-Off Trannies,” and detractors, take on Tribeca], Edith Honan, Reuters, April 25, 2010; accessed October 5, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;]]While many gays and lesbians feel that ''transgender'' is simply a name for a part of their own community (i.e. the [[LGBT]] community), others actively reject the idea that transgender people are part of their community, seeing them as entirely separate and distinct. Some feel that [[bisexual]]ity and [[transgender]]ism are detrimental to the social and political acceptance of gays and lesbians.  This phenomenon has been called ''[[internalized homophobia]]'', meaning an irrational fear and dislike of other homosexuals.&lt;ref&gt;See Fone, B.R.S. (2000). Homophobia.  New York: Metropolitan Books; Sears, J.T., and Williams, W.L. (1997).  Overcoming Heterosexism and Homophobia.  New York: Columbia University Press&lt;/ref&gt;
This presumes that transgender people are, in fact, "homosexuals", a descriptor which is often hotly debated, but with little real meaning due to the nature of the differences between gender and sexuality – for example, if a [[transwoman]] is attracted only to other women, then she is either lesbian by nature of being a woman, or is otherwise a heterosexual man. However, the latter statement could only be made by someone who is deeply transphobic.

The nature of the terms ''man'' and ''woman'' also become unclear in a similar way under this philosophy, and many feel that the only real recourse is to accept that the mind and feeling of a person is the only thing that gives that person identity, and so a person that has a female identity and mind is indeed a woman, as agreed by much legislation in Europe enabling transsexual people to have the sex recorded on their birth certificates amended accordingly.&lt;ref name="GRAnotes"&gt;{{cite web
  |title=UK Gender recognition act, Explanatory notes paragraph 4
  |publisher=UK Office of public Sector Information
  |date=8 July 2004
  |url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/en2004/2004en07.htm
  |accessdate=8 September 2006 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; According to this thinking, it becomes clear that in at least a categorical sense, transgendered people should only be accepted in the [[gay]] and [[lesbian]] community if they themselves self-identify as gay or lesbian as any other homosexual person does, and the blanket assumption on the part of some gay and lesbian people on the nature of those transgendered people who are in their [[LGBT|LGB]] community with a view to dis-inclusion constitutes an issue of transphobia.&lt;ref name="GLBTphobia"&gt;GLBTphobia&lt;/ref&gt;  The implacability of this question has been overcome by the rise in the 1990s of [[queer theory]] and the [[queer]] community, which defines ''queer'' as embracing all variants of sexual identity, sexual desire, and sexual acts that fall outside normative definitions of heterosexuality; thus a heterosexual man or woman as well as a transgender person of any sex can be included in the category of queer through their own choice.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Transgender}}
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Transgender Day of Remembrance]]
* [[Violence against LGBT people]]
* [[List of unlawfully killed transgender people]]
* [[Transfeminism]]
* [[Transgender Law Center]]
* [[Trans-bashing]]
* [[The Yogyakarta Principles]]
* [[LGBT rights opposition]]
* [[Janice Raymond]]

==References==
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.pfc.org.uk/audio/by/title/transphobia_-_what_is_it_and Press For Change: Transphobia – What is it and what is its impact?,] [[Stephen Whittle]] OBE
* [http://www.gender.org/remember/ Remembering our Dead]
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/rcip//sbh.html Survivor bashing – bias motivated hate crimes]
* [http://www.transgenderlaw.org/index.htm Transgenderlaw.org]
* Brown, K. (2001). Transsexual, Transgender and Intersex History: Gay, Lesbian and Feminist Backlash. Retrieved May 26, 2003 from   [http://www.transhistory.net/ www.transhistory.net, see "TransHistory"]
* [http://www.transgenderlawcenter.org Transgender Law Center]
* [http://new.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=2111&amp;Itemid=1837&amp;lang=en Translatina documentary (2010)]

{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Transgender]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]

[[de:Transphobie]]
[[es:Transfobia]]
[[fr:Transphobie]]
[[hr:Transfobija]]
[[it:Transfobia]]
[[nl:Transfobie]]
[[ja:トランスフォビア]]
[[pl:Transfobia]]
[[pt:Transfobia]]
[[ro:Transfobie]]
[[ru:Трансфобия]]
[[sh:Transfobija]]
[[tr:Transfobi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>