<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051021220031|26133802" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="67084" pageid="67084" ns="0" title="Transphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-08T18:07:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{unsourced}}
'''Transphobia''' (by analogy with [[homophobia]]) refers to various kinds of aversions towards [[transsexual]]ity and  [[transsexual]]/[[transgender]]ed people. It often takes the form of refusal to accept a person's new [[gender identity]] and is rarely rancorous.

Whether intentional or not, transphobia can have severe consequences for the targeted person; also, many transpeople experience homophobia as well, from people who associate [[gender identity disorder]] as a form of [[homosexuality]] (see [[Homosexuality and Transgender]]).

Like other forms of discrimination such as homophobia, the discriminatory or intolerant behaviour can be direct (e.g. [[harassment]], [[assault]], or even [[murder]]) or indirect (e.g. refusing to take steps to ensure that transgender people are treated in the same way as [[cisgender]] (non-transgender) people.)

However, direct forms of transphobia can manifest themselves in ways that are not related to violence. One example of this is the case of [[Tyra Hunter]]. Ms. Hunter was involved in an automobile accident, and when [[rescue worker]]s discovered she was transgender, they backed away and stopped administering treatment. Two well-noted transsexual victims were [[Brandon Teena]] and [[Gwen Araujo]]. 

[[Transwomen]] (male-to-female transgender and transsexual people) are sometimes denied entry to women's spaces, and the explanations given for such denials are often felt as being transphobic. (The [[Michigan Women's Music Festival]], for instance, has caused much debate for limiting its attendance to "[[womyn]]-born womyn".)

Transgender people depend largely on the medical profession to receive not only [[Hormone replacement therapy (trans)|hormone replacement therapy]] and [[sex reassignment surgery]], but also other vital care. Often it can be difficult for gender patients to receive proper health care and treatment, because medical [[gatekeeper]]s who are transphobic (or who misunderstand the nature of gender identity disorder) will refuse to administer necessary treatment; in at least one case that included the refusal to treat [[Robert Eads]], a [[transman]], for ovarian cancer, of which he subsequently died. 

Although the word transphobia is widely used, the phenomenon can be thought of, in some instances, as an [[aversion]] more than a [[phobia]].



==See also==
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Violence against gays, lesbians, bisexuals, and the transgendered]]
* [[gay-bashing]]

==External links==
* [http://www.gender.org/remember/ Remembering our Dead]

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Transgender]]
[[pt:Transfobia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>