<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161017204422|744852933" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="23480361" pageid="23480361" ns="0" title="Unpaid work"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-10-17T20:45:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:... Woman in girlhood, wifehood, motherhood; her responsibilities and her duties at all periods of life; a guide in the maintenance of her health and that of her children (1906) (14587342817).jpg|thumb|Woman participating in unpaid domestic work by cooking meal for family]]'''Unpaid work''' is labor [[employment]] done without giving any [[wage]] to the worker.  These may be either members of a [[family]] or [[cooperative]]; [[conscripts]] or [[forced labour]]; [[volunteer]] workers who work for [[charity (practice)|charity]] or [[amusement]];&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=q5QOAAAAQAAJ |year=1993 |title=Volunteers |isbn=978-0-415-09427-6 |author=Jone L. Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[student]]s who take [[intern]] positions as [[work experience]]; or conventional workers who are not paid because their enterprise is short of [[money]] or subject to [[embezzlement]].

One common form of unpaid work is unpaid domestic work. The burden of this type of unpaid work generally falls on the women in a household. Contributing so much time to unpaid domestic work has major effects on women and their participation in the labor market, which consequently affects children, society, and the state.

==Unpaid domestic work==

===Definition===

Unpaid domestic work is often a controversial topic within [[feminist economics]], as it is significantly influenced by traditional family views. Unpaid domestic workers are often women who do not seek employment but instead work within the household and engage in [[Domestic worker|domestic labor]]. The known factors behind a woman’s employment decisions include but are not limited to: the support of their spouse, the modernization degree of [[gender role]]s as well as the pressure of family responsibility.
Regarding unofficial employment (including [[self-employment]], a position within self-run enterprises and unpaid domestic labor) of women in the western world, such work is more commonly treated as a part-time occupation. In contrast, in many other parts of the world  unofficial employment refers almost directly to unpaid domestic labor, not as an occupation but instead as an extension of a pre-existing family role. The working position is placed within the framework of the family, and the laborer is required to both see to family matters as well as the occupation.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.un-ngls.org/orf/women-2005.pdf|year=2005 | title=UNIFEM: Progress for the World's Women 2005|pages=6–9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Types of Unpaid Work ===

==== Unpaid Domestic Work ====
Unpaid domestic work is all the unpaid work done within the home other than caring for children and family members. This primarily includes cleaning and maintaining the home.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

==== Unpaid Care Work ====
Unpaid [[care work]] is the care a person provides to their own family and household members.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hirway|first=Indira|date=March 2015|title=Unpaid Work and the Economy: Linkages and Their Implications|url=|journal=Indian Journal of Labour Economics|volume=58|issue=1|page=|pages=1–21|doi=10.1007/s41027-015-0010-3|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== History ===
The traditional view of a family involves a woman in unpaid domestic labor supporting the household; however, under trends of dual earner couples and a gradually aging population, the commercialization of housework and domestic care has become inevitable. Arguments have been made that the value of unpaid domestic labor must always be considered to prevent the exploitation of unpaid workers, and thus should be seen as legitimate employment. There are also arguments that a "[[caregiver]] allowance" should be provided to unpaid domestic workers to protect the labor value of their work.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=UNIFEM: Progress for the World's Women 2005|url=http://www.un-ngls.org/orf/women-2005.pdf|year=2005|pages=58–73}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Regardless of the methodology used, a variety of studies have shown that the division of household labor results in a disproportionate burden falling on the wives in married couples' households. While this is the case, it has also been shown that the disparity between men and women in married households has been shrinking to some degree.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/135457000337679|title=Working Time as Gendered Time|last2=Negrey|first2=Cynthia|website=Feminist Economics|pages=59–76|doi=10.1080/135457000337679|last1=Sirianni|first1=Carmen}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, during the Great Recession of the 2000s, low income men increased their contributions to their households by completing more hours of unpaid domestic work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Khitarishvili|first=Tamar|last2=Kim|first2=Kijong|date=2015|title=The Great Recession and Unpaid Work Time in the United States - Does Poverty Matter?|url=|journal=International Journal of Time Use Research|volume=12|issue=1|pages=19–48|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Entry into Unpaid Domestic Work ===

Based on societal pressures and norms, women often are pressured to take on the majority of unpaid work within the home, regardless of whether the woman is employed outside the home or not.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; [[Female employment]] demographics indicate that the employment of married women is affected greatly by marriage and childbirth. Due to a husband’s employment, a woman can often be pushed into the role of an unpaid domestic worker through traditional as well as economic pressure. Even when women are employed full-time outside the house, they may perform a greater share of household chores and childcare activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Working Time as Gendered Time|last = Sirianni|first = Carmen|date = |journal = Feminist Economics|doi = 10.1080/135457000337679|pmid = |access-date = |last2 = Negrey|first2 = Cynthia|issue = 1|year = 2000|pages = 59–76|series = 6 |volume=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gender-based pay inequity in the labor market contributes to this phenomenon. Women face lower wages and fewer promotional opportunities and adjust their time in the labor market to respond to demands at home.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Working Time as Gendered Time|last = Sirianni|first = Carmen|date = |journal = Feminist Economics|doi = 10.1080/135457000337679|pmid = |access-date = |last2 = Negrey|first2 = Cynthia|year = 2000|page = 63|series = 6|issue = 1 |volume=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Effects===

Because the burden of unpaid work falls disproportionately on women, unpaid work has a number of negative effects on women, their children, and society. On the other hand, when this work is provided by family members for free, it has a positive effect on a state's budget.

==== Effects of Unpaid Domestic Work on Women ====
[[Time-use survey|Time use surveys]] show that women spend far more time doing unpaid work than men.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; With women spending more time providing unpaid domestic work than men, women are also spending less time in the workforce and, therefore, bringing in lower incomes to the household.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Because women are traditionally believed to bring in less income than men, women are discouraged from investing in education and skills.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; This further entrenches women into domestic unpaid work, creating a cycle of social norms that is difficult to break.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Even if women do enter the workforce, they are usually still held accountable for the majority of the domestic unpaid work at home.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; This phenomenon of having to work a full day in the workforce and then come home and complete a full day of unpaid domestic work is known as the [[double burden]]. The double burden negatively effects women because it gives them less time to spend in the workforce, resulting in men dedicating more time to the workforce, and, therefore, likely getting promoted over women.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The double burden also negatively effects women's personal wellbeing because it means women have less time for taking care of themselves and sleeping.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; This can also negatively effect their job performance in the workforce, encouraging male promotion over female.    
[[File:Two children share a book.jpg|thumb|left|Older child caring for younger child as a form of unpaid care work]]

==== Effects of Unpaid Domestic Work on Children ====
Statistics show that many children, particularly in poorer countries and households, are forced to contribute to the unpaid domestic work of a household.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Because unpaid domestic work is traditionally the role of women in many societies, the burden of unpaid domestic work falls particularly on young girls who are forced to drop out of school to assist with the unpaid work within their households.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Marphatia|first=Akanksha|last2=Moussie´|first2=Rachel|date=2013|title=A question of gender justice: Exploring the linkages between women’sunpaid care work, education, and gender equality|url=|journal=International Journal of Educational Development|volume=33|pages=585–594|doi=10.1016/j.ijedudev.2013.05.005|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Effects of Unpaid Domestic Work on the Economy ====
Some economists argue that unpaid domestic work should be included as economic contributions.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Unpaid work contributes to the economy by producing important goods and services such as meals and cleanliness of the home.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; This allows other household members to enter the workforce and contribute to the overall economy via paying jobs.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; For this reason, Indira Hirway argues that unpaid domestic work should be considered [[Production (economics)|economic production]] rather than [[Consumption (economics)|consumption]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Hirway also notes that unpaid domestic work has the attributes of a standard [[Good (economics)|economic good]] because it is neither free nor unlimited.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

[[International Monetary Fund|IMF]] estimates that a country could significantly increase its [[Gross domestic product|GDP]] if women could fully participate in the workforce.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; For instance, if unpaid work were incorporated when measuring GDP, it would have raised the GDP by 26 percent in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.bea.gov/scb/pdf/2012/05%20May/0512_household.pdf|year=2012 | title=Accounting for Household Production in the National Accounts|page=23 |author1=Benjamin Bridgman |author2=Andrew Dugan |author3=Mikhael Lal |author4=Matthew Osborne |author5=Shaunda Villones  |last-author-amp=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Unpaid work also effects the [[Labour supply|labor supply]] of the economy because fewer women are entering into the workforce due to their domestic unpaid work duties.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==== Effects of Unpaid Domestic Work on the State ====
Unpaid domestic work has a positive effect on a [[State budget|state's budget]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Unpaid domestic work is typically the type of work that a state would provide for its citizens if family members were not already providing for their family.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; This includes things like [[child care]], [[Elderly care|elder care]], [[Health care|medical care]], and [[nutrition]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Because these things are being provided by an unpaid domestic worker, the state does not need to expend resources to provide its citizens with these services.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Therefore, unpaid domestic work can decrease the amount of money a state must spend to otherwise provide these services.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Note, however, that when a state cuts care services for the young, elderly, sick and disabled, the burden of this care is generally placed on female family members, meaning decreases in a state's spending on care can have a negative effect on female participation in the workforce.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

=== Time Use Surveys ===
One way to measure unpaid domestic work is through [[Time-use survey|time use surveys]].&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Folbre|first=Nancy|date=July 2006|title=Measuring Care: Gender, Empowerment, and the Care Economy|url=|journal=Journal of Human Development|volume=7|issue=2|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; These surveys attempt to evaluate how much time is spent providing different services, such as time spent in the workforce versus time spent on unpaid domestic work, such as cooking.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; More than 20 countries have conducted time use surveys to learn more about the division of unpaid work in domestic households.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; For example, Sarah Gammage conducted time use surveys in Guatemala to measure time spent doing unpaid domestic work within households and between family members.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gammage|first=Sarah|date=September 9, 2010|title=Time Pressed and Time Poor: Unpaid Household Work in Guatemala|url=|journal=Feminist Economics|volume=16|issue=3|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this study, Gammage found women completed approximately 70% of all unpaid domestic work within a household.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Similarly, Debbie Budlenger conducted time use surveys across six different countries and found women in each country conducted the majority of the unpaid domestic work each day.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Budlender|first=Debbie|date=December 2008|title=The Statistical Evidence on Care and Non-Care Work across Six Countries|url=http://www.unrisd.org/80256B3C005BCCF9/(httpAuxPages)/F9FEC4EA774573E7C1257560003A96B2/$file/BudlenderREV.pdf|journal=United Nations Research Institute for Social Development|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The results of her findings are summarized in the chart below: 
{| class="wikitable"
|+'''Minutes Per Day Spent Doing Unpaid Household Work'''
|-
|'''Country''' 
|'''Men''' 
|'''Women'''
|-
|Argentina 
|101
|293
|-
|India 
|36
|354
|-
|Republic of Korea
|38
|224
|-
|Nicaragua
|66
|318 
|-
|South Africa
|91
|273 
|-
|Tanzania
|44
|262
|}
In a different time use survey, Liangshu Qi and Xiao-yuan Dong found that, in China men complete an average of 58 minutes of unpaid work a day compared to the 139 minutes of unpaid work a day that women complete.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Liangshu|first=Qi|last2=Dong|first2=Xiao-yuan|date=May 8, 2015|title=Unpaid Care Work's Interference with Paid Work and the Gender Earnings Gap in China|url=|journal=Feminist Economics|volume=22|issue=2|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Valuation  ===
There are three different ways to measure the value of unpaid domestic work: the opportunity cost method, the replacement cost method, and the input/out cost method.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

==== Opportunity Cost Method ====
The opportunity cost method measures the value of unpaid domestic work by calculating the amount of money unpaid domestic workers could be making if instead of doing unpaid work they were working in the labor market.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Luxton|first=Meg|date=June 1997|title=The UN, women, and household labour: Measuring and valuing unpaid work|url=|journal=Women's Studies International Forum|volume=20|issue=3|pages=431–439|doi=10.1016/s0277-5395(97)00026-5|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, if a former female attorney is now a stay-at-home mother conducting unpaid domestic work, the value of an hour of unpaid domestic work is the hourly rate she could make if she were working as an attorney.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; The major flaw with this method is that two unpaid domestic workers can do the same job at the same proficiency level, but the value of the work will fluctuate based on the workers' prior education and skill level.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; It is also a problem for women who never held a job, because it is unclear how much money they would be making if they were participating in the work force, rather than working unpaid at home.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

==== Replacement Cost Method ====
The replacement cost method measures the value of unpaid domestic work by calculating the monetary cost of purchasing that service instead.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; For example, to value unpaid child care, look at the cost of hiring a nanny, or to value the cost of cooking a meal, look at the cost of eating a similar meal at a restaurant.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The flaw with this method is that it cannot account for the added sentimental value of having a mother stay at home with her children rather than a stranger.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

==== Input/Output Cost Method ====
The input/output cost method measures the value of unpaid domestic work by calculating the monetary value of the economic goods and services produced by unpaid domestic work and how much these goods and services would sell for in the open market.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

=== Double Burden ===

==== Definition of the Double Burden ====
A [[double burden]], otherwise known as a double day, is the phenomenon that a woman holds a paying job in the labor market and then must come home and work a full day's worth of unpaid domestic work within the home.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=MacDonald|first=Martha|last2=Phipps|first2=Shelley|last3=Lethbridge|first3=Lynn|date=March 2005|title=Takings Its Toll: The Influence of Paid and Unpaid Work on Women's Well-Being|url=|journal=Feminist Economics|volume=11|issue=1|pages=63–94|doi=10.1080/1354570042000332597|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to societal norms and expectations, the burden of unpaid work primarily falls on the female in the household even if she and her husband work the same hours in the labor market.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

==== Effect of the Double Burden on Women ====
Because women are expected to complete the unpaid domestic work within a house, even if she is working full-time, the responsibilities and burdens of unpaid work are proven to increase women's stress levels.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; In a study conducted by Martha MacDonald, Shelley Phipps, and Lynn Lethbridge, they found that women conducted the majority of the unpaid household work even when they held paying jobs.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; They also found that this burden increased the stress level of the women surveyed.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; In the same study, they found some unpaid domestic work was more stressful than others.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; Specifically, the pressures of eldercare and household work like cleaning proved to be the most stress-inducing for women experiencing a double day whereas childcare was found to be less stressful.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;  The study also asked men about the stresses of having to do unpaid domestic work and have a paying job, but found that because men are typically not responsible for the majority of the unpaid domestic work, they were on average not stressed at all by the few unpaid work hours they contributed to the household.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

===Controversy===

As the issue of unpaid domestic workers is closely tied to concepts within [[gender equality]], there have been many discussions over the subject. In 2010, The New York Times released an article detailing the stigma of [[Housewife|housewives]] and domestic labor in northern European countries as well as much of the developed world. As education levels of women continue to rise, unpaid domestic workers are beginning to be seen as “lazy” and a drain upon GDP, leading to the negative image of an unemployed housewife.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/07/21/world/europe/21iht-LETTER.html?_r=2&amp;|year=2010 | title=The Stigma of Being a Housewife,The New York Times }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Unpaid student interns in the United States ==
There are three quarters of a million unpaid [[internship]] positions in the [[United States]] every year. Internships should provide training for students, not to be used by employers to save costs according to [[labor law]]. Two lawsuits have been recently  launched by [[student]]s who claim they were utilized as cheap (free) labor by their so-called [[employer]]s to replace paid-[[worker]]s.&lt;ref&gt;"Fewer unpaid internships in works" USA Today published March 8, page B1&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Online volunteering]]
* [[Feminist economics]]
* [[Care work]] 
* [[Child care]]
* [[Double burden]] 
* [[Housewife]] 
* [[Hobby]]
* [[Voluntary slavery]]
* [[Crowdsourcing]]
* [[Creative Crowdsourcing]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Volunteering]]
[[Category:Slavery]]
[[Category:Unpaid work| ]]
[[Category:Labour law]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>