<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151016155632|686037731" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="23480361" pageid="23480361" ns="0" title="Unpaid work"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-10-16T15:57:32Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Unpaid work''' is labor [[employment]] done without giving any [[wage]] to the worker.  These may be either members of a [[family]] or [[cooperative]]; [[conscripts]] or [[forced labour]]; [[volunteer]] workers who work for [[charity (practice)|charity]] or [[amusement]];&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://books.google.com/?id=q5QOAAAAQAAJ |year=1993 |title=Volunteers |isbn=978-0-415-09427-6 |author=Jone L. Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[student]]s who take [[intern]] positions as [[work experience]]; or conventional workers who are not paid because their enterprise is short of [[money]] or subject to [[embezzlement]].

==Unpaid student interns in the United States==
There are three quarters of a million unpaid [[internship]] positions in the [[United States]] every year. Internships should provide training for students, not to be used by employers to save costs according to [[labor law]]. Two lawsuits have been recently  launched by [[student]]s who claim they were utilized as cheap (free) labor by their so-called [[employer]]s to replace paid-[[worker]]s.&lt;ref&gt;"Fewer unpaid internships in works" USA Today published March 8, page B1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Unpaid domestic work==
===Definition===

Unpaid domestic work is often a controversial topic within [[feminist economics]], as it is significantly influenced by traditional family views. Unpaid domestic workers are often women who do not seek employment but instead work within the household and engage in domestic labor. The known factors behind a woman’s employment decisions include but are not limited to: The support of their spouse, the modernization degree of gender roles as well as the pressure of family responsibility.
Regarding unofficial employment (including self-employment, a position within self-run enterprises and unpaid domestic labor) of women in the western world, such work is more commonly treated as a part-time occupation. In contrast, in many other parts of the world  unofficial employment refers almost directly to unpaid domestic labor, not as an occupation but instead as an extension of a pre-existing family role. The working position is placed within the framework of the family, and the laborer is required to both see to family matters as well as the occupation.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.un-ngls.org/orf/women-2005.pdf|year=2005 | title=UNIFEM: Progress for the World's Women 2005|pages=6-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cause===

Female employment demographics indicate that the employment of married women is affected greatly by marriage and childbirth. Due to a husband’s employment, a woman can often be pushed into the role of an unpaid domestic worker through traditional as well as economic pressure. Even when women are employed full-time outside the house, they may perform a greater share of household chores and childcare activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Working Time as Gendered Time|last = Sirianni|first = Carmen|date = |journal = Feminist Economics|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |last2 = Negrey|first2 = Cynthia|issue = 1|year = 2000|pages = 59-76|series = 6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gender-based pay inequity in the labor market contributes to this phenomenon. Women face lower wages and fewer promotional opportunities and adjust their time in the labor market to respond to demands at home.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Working Time as Gendered Time|last = Sirianni|first = Carmen|date = |journal = Feminist Economics|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |last2 = Negrey|first2 = Cynthia|year = 2000|page = 63|series = 6|issue = 1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Effects===

Recent research in the United States has revealed the cost of hiring laborers to work in positions usually taken by unpaid domestic workers. The value for individual families is significant: it increases personal income by 30 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.bea.gov/scb/pdf/2012/05%20May/0512_household.pdf|year=2012 | title=Accounting for Household Production in the National Accounts|page=33 |author=Benjamin Bridgman, Andrew Dugan, Mikhael Lal, Matthew Osborne, and Shaunda Villones}}&lt;/ref&gt; But the effect on the economy is also noteworthy. If this work were incorporated when measuring GDP, it would have raised it by 26 percent in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.bea.gov/scb/pdf/2012/05%20May/0512_household.pdf|year=2012 | title=Accounting for Household Production in the National Accounts|page=23 |author=Benjamin Bridgman, Andrew Dugan, Mikhael Lal, Matthew Osborne, and Shaunda Villones}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Development===

The traditional view of a family involves a woman in unpaid domestic labor supporting the household; however, under trends of dual earner couples and a gradually aging population, the commercialization of housework and domestic care has become inevitable. Arguments have been made that the value of unpaid domestic labor must always be considered to prevent the exploitation of unpaid workers, and thus should be seen as legitimate employment. There are also arguments that a "[[caregiver]] allowance" should be provided to unpaid domestic workers to protect the labor value of their work.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.un-ngls.org/orf/women-2005.pdf|year=2005 | title=UNIFEM: Progress for the World's Women 2005|pages=58–73 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Controversy===

As the issue of unpaid domestic workers is closely tied to concepts within gender equality, there have been many discussions over the subject. In 2010, The New York Times released an article detailing the stigma of housewives and domestic labor in northern European countries as well as much of the developed world. As education levels of women continue to rise, unpaid domestic workers beginning to be seen as “lazy” and a drain upon GDP, leading to the negative image of a housewife not officially employed.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/07/21/world/europe/21iht-LETTER.html?_r=2&amp;|year=2010 | title=The Stigma of Being a Housewife,The New York Times }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Online volunteering]]
* [[Feminist economics]]
* [[Hobby]]
* [[Voluntary slavery]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Volunteerism]]
[[Category:Slavery]]
[[Category:Free labor]]
[[Category:Labour law]]
[[Category:Criticism and refusal of work]]


{{Economics-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>