<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081115150116|251967220" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21387353" pageid="21387353" ns="0" title="Freak show"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T18:00:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup-restructure|date=March 2008}}{{Refimprove|date=February 2007}}
{{dablink|For other uses of this word, see [[Freakshow (disambiguation)]].}}

[[Image:FreakShowConeyIsland.jpg|thumb|[[Coney Island]] and its popular on-going freak show.]]
[[Image:J_Kanef.jpg|thumb|An member of a freak show.]]
Generally considered in contemporary times as a highly inappropriate and [[dehumanize|dehumanizing]] term, a '''freak show''' is an exhibition of rarities, "freaks of nature" — such as unusually tall or short humans, and people with [[intersexuality|both male and female secondary sexual characteristics]] — and performances that are expected to be shocking to the viewers. Heavily [[tattoo]]ed or [[body piercing|pierced]] people have sometimes been seen in freak shows, as have [[fire eater|fire-eating]] and [[Sword swallowing|sword-swallowing]] acts.

==History==
[[Image:Freak show 1941.jpg|left|thumb|A freak show in [[Rutland, Vermont]] in 1941.]]
Freak shows were popular in the United States from around 1840 to 1940,and were often, but not always, associated with [[circus]]es and [[carnival]]s. Some shows also exhibited deformed animals (such as two-headed cows, one-eyed pigs, and four-horned goats) and famous hoaxes, or simply "science gone wrong" exhibits (such as deformed babies). 

Advances in [[medicine]] and political changes all but sounded the [[wiktionary:death knell|death knell]] for the freak show. As previously mysterious anomalies were scientifically explained as [[genetic mutations]] or [[diseases]], freaks became the objects of pity rather than fear or disdain. The [[eugenics]] movement saw human anomalies as unfortunate mistakes of nature. In 1937, [[Germany]] passed a law outlawing freak shows, decrying them as [[exploitation]] (this however made it legal for the [pro-eugenics] [[Nazis]] to arrest freak show acts and experiment on them{{Fact|date=August 2007}}). Thus the term "freak show" has become archaic, and is widely considered as insulting, demeaning and [[pejorative]], in manners that dehumanize individuals based upon their appearance. Shows such as [[Jim Rose Circus]] sideshow, and those at [[Coney Island]] are more accurately termed [[sideshow]]s. However, [[Cut Throat Freak Show]] still uses the term, as do many other self proclaimed freak and [[sideshow]] performers.  
Today, freak shows are outlawed in a number of U.S. states.  For example, Michigan law forbids the "exhibition [of] any deformed human being or human monstrosity, except as used for scientific purposes". &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.legislature.mi.gov/(sqktze55ua0uru45dvse3qv0)/mileg.aspx?page=getObject&amp;objectName=mcl-750-347 Michigan Penal Code (Excerpt), Act 328 of 1931: Section 750.347, Deformed human beings; exhibition.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contemporary examples==
Freak shows are extremely rare today, and there are only a few left in the world. A freak show with born living human oddities and medical anomalies is the ''999 Eyes Authentic Freakshow''.  This show features people born with medical anomalies such as the Black Scorpion aka [[Lobster Bro]], [[Jackie the Half Girl]], [[Peg Leg the Modern-Day Elephant Man]], [[Lobster Girl]], and the [[Dame Demure Madame Miniature]] along with a museum that includes [[pickled punks]] and many items from [[John Strong]]'s collection, including Patches a stuffed [[polycephaly|two-headed calf]].
Ken Harck's ''Bros. Grim Sideshow'' also tours with a combination of human oddities and working acts.

Although widely referred to as freaks, a distinction must be made between self-made freaks and "born" freaks. Generally, the most extreme examples of self-made freaks are referred to as "Human Marvels". [[Katzen]], [[The Enigma (person)|The Enigma]], [[The Lizardman]] and both the Scottish and Texan Leopard men are all human marvels. 

With the rise of the [[Internet]], the freak show mentality has been given a new lease on life as sites such as [[rotten.com]] arose, allowing people to gaze at "freakish"  abnormalities that would not have been seen during the [[television]] era due to ideas about aesthetic [[taste (sociology)|taste]]. {{Fact|date=February 2007}}

==Historical timeline== 
The exhibition of human oddities can be seen as far back as recorded history: 

;1630s: [[Lazarus and Joannes Baptista Colloredo|Lazarus Colloredo]], and his parasitic twin brother, John Baptista, who was attached at Lazarus' sternum, tour Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Armand Marie LeRoi, ''Mutants'', Penguin Books, pp. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
;1704&amp;ndash;1718: [[Peter the Great]] collects human oddities at the [[Kunstkammer]] in what in now St. Petersburg, Russia. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kunstkamera.ru/en/history/the_history_of_kunstkammer/ The History of Kunstkammer]&lt;/ref&gt;

;1738: The exhibition of an exhibit who "was taken in a wook at Guinea; 'tis a female about four feet high in every part like a woman excepting her head which nearly resembles the ape." &lt;ref&gt;Bogdan, R. (1988). ''Freak Show.'' Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press. pp. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;

;Late 18th century: The science of [[teratology]] changed the belief that freaks were evil omens and the work of Satan or witches.  Instead, people believed the theory that freaks were part of God's great order of creatures.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1829: [[Chang and Eng Bunker|Chang and Eng]], “the original [[conjoined twins|Siamese twins]],” were exhibited in America. {{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1839: J.G. Milligan writes “curiosities of medical experiments” in which freaks are described. {{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1844: [[P. T. Barnum]] arrives in London to exhibit [[General Tom Thumb|Tom Thumb]], the famous midget. {{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1860: Hiram and Barney Davis are presented as [[Wild Men of Borneo]].  The guide book for Barnum American museum list 13 human curiosities.  [[Zip the Pinhead]] begins his six-decade career with Barnum. {{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1863: Barnum uses his brilliant showman skills to get the civil war and emancipation proclamation pushed off the front pages and replaced by a midget wedding. {{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1870-1890: [[Dime museum]]s are at the height of their popularity, with the freakshow as the main attraction. {{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1876: Wild men of Borneo, wild Australian children, man-eating [[fiji mermaid]]s, and the {{convert|602|lb|abbr=on}} woman are exhibited at the first [[World’s Fair]] in Philadelphia. {{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1880: First freakshow at [[Coney Island]].{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1884: Freak recruiting becomes a career and full time occupation.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1889: British medical journal describes [[Myrtle Corbin]], the "four-legged girl," and verifies that both sets of reproductive organs as workable and capable of birthing children.

;1890: The Jones twins, Siamese twins joined at buttocks and sharing a rectum die on carnival tour at fifteen months old.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;Late 19th century: The theory that freaks are biological throwbacks to earlier races of humans and apes is introduced.  The theory of [[maternal impression]] attributes traumatic or significant events experienced by the pregnant woman as an explanation for deformities.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;Early 20th century: The resurgence of [[Mendel]]’s law of genetics coupled with [[Charles Darwin|Darwin]]'s ''[[The Origin of Species|Origin of Species]]'' introduced the idea that freaks could "taint the gene pool".

;1904: Silbey devises the "[[sideshow|Ten-In-One]]" show and creates jobs for talkers.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1908: An article in [[Scientific American]] introduces concept of freak exhibitions being inhumane and barbaric.

;1915: San Francisco exposition includes a midget village and dime museum freakshow.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1922: "Professor" Sam Wagner starts the [[World Circus Sideshow|World's Circus]] freak show at Coney Island. General public can read articles in popular press explaining the diseases behind oddities.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1925: Freaks can be seen performing on the [[vaudeville]] stage.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1932: [[Tod Browning]]'s [[Pre-Code]]-[[era]] [[film]] ''[[Freaks]]'' tells the story of a traveling freakshow. The use of real freaks in the film provoked public outcries and was widely unsuccessful until its re-release at the 1962 [[Cannes Film Festival]]. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.missinglinkclassichorror.co.uk/freaks.htm Missing Link reviews Tod Browning's ''Freaks'' (1932)]&lt;/ref&gt;

;1933: [[Century of Progress|Chicago Expo]] features a pit show with a "live two-headed baby" in a jar of formaldehyde.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;Late 1930s: The switch in social view of those with physical or mental anomalies from fabulous freaks and curiosities to diseased people with disorders was complete.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1940: Freakshow is on the ropes and the dime museum essentially dead.  The three-legged man, [[Frank Lentini]], opens a freakshow.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1950: Historical sideshow died as public demands freaks be given "dignity" and not exhibited, at this time many went into institutions or on the welfare system.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1952: The "Human Torso" is still on exhibit.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1960:  [[Albert Karas|Albert-Alberta Karas]]&lt;ref&gt;''[http://digilib.syr.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/eisenmann&amp;CISOPTR=1933&amp;REC=8 Albert-Alberta Karas]'', photographer unknown, Syracuse University Digital Library, retrieved May 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; (two siblings, each half man, half woman) exhibits with Bobby Reynolds on sideshow tour.

;1969: John Strong purchases Patches the two headed cow for $150 begins his freak animal show.{{Fact|date=November 2007}})

;1972: At north fair Sealo and the dwarf Pete Terhune confront charges against them for exhibiting themselves. The charges equated freakshows with pornography{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1980s: Bobby Reynolds is arrested for exhibiting [[pickled punks]].{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1983: Coney Island USA, founded by Dick D. Zigun, opens Sideshows by the Seashore, starting a sideshow revival in Coney Island. {{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1984: Freak show performer Otis Jordan (the frog boy) is barred from exhibiting himself at the New York State Fair on the basis that the exhibition of human oddities is exploitative.  Barbara Baskin, a "disability rights activist," led this fight and Otis was out of a job for two years before he beat the case and could perform again. {{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;1992: [[Grady Stiles]] (the lobster boy) is shot in his home in [[Gibsonton, Florida]].&lt;ref&gt;{{imdb|0830183|name=Grady Stiles, Jr.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;1996: Chicago shock-jock Mancow Muller presented Mancow's Freak Show at the United Center in the Summer of 1996, to crowd of 30,000. The show included Kathy Stiles and her brother Grady III as the Lobster Twins. {Mancow Muller (with John Calkins) Dad, Dames, Demons &amp; a Dwarf Regan Books 2004 pp. 121, 137-147} 

;1998: The Brazilian TV show "Ratinho Livre", whose main performer was Carlos "Ratinho" Massa became a kind of freak show, exhibiting mainly children with serious physical anomalies, such as hundreds of facial tumors (Eleandro, the Elephant Boy), tails, amputations, et cetera. Later, near 2000, the Brazilian justice prohibited such appearances on TV shows.{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;2000&amp;ndash;2008: Ken Harck's Brothers Grim Sideshow debuted at the Great Circus Parade in Milwaukee, WI in the summer of 2000. The Milwaukee run included a fat lady and bearded lady Melinda Maxi, as well as self made freaks The Enigma and Katzen. In later years the show has included Half-boy Jesse Stitcher and [[Jesus "Chuy" Aceves]] the Mexican Werewolf Boy. Bros. Grim toured with the Ozz Fest music festival in 2006 and 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/kenharck/ Chicago Reader: Wanna See Something Really Weird?]&lt;/ref&gt;

;2005: Ward Hall begins his sideshow, exhibiting "born freaks."{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

;2005&amp;ndash;2008: The 999 Eyes Authentic Freakshow takes modern-day freaks on tours.&lt;ref name="eyes"&gt;[http://www.999eyes.com 999 Eyes of Endless Dream Carnival Museum &amp; Sideshow]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:blackscorpion2007.jpg|thumb|A "lobster boy".|{{deletable image-caption|1=Tuesday, 18 November 2008}}]]

;2007: [[Wayne Schoenfeld]] bring together several sideshow performers to "The L.A. Circus Congress of Freaks and Exotics," to photograph sideshows folks for "Cirque Du Soleil - Circus of the Past." In attendance were: Bill  quinn, the halfman; Percilla, the fat lady; Mighty Mike Murga the Mighty Dwarf; [http://www.circusfolks.com/oddities/elnegritoeng.html Dieguito El Negrito], a wildman; fireeaters; sword swallowers, and more.&lt;ref name="wayne"&gt;[http://www.wayneschoenfeld.com Wayne Schoenfeld]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name="cast"&gt;[http://www.zootsuitclown.com/thecast.html credits]&lt;/ref&gt;


;2008: Laurie Bennett won freaky feet of the year in Skipton Castle.

==In media==
*[[Freaks]], [[Tod Browning]]'s 1932 film, centers on the people in a freak show who wreak their revenge on the able-bodied circus-performing couple who exploit them.
*[[Katherine Dunn]]'s novel [[Geek Love]] deals with a family of genetically engineered circus freaks.
* [[Freaked]], a 1993 [[comedy film]] about mutated victims to an amoral entrepreneur.
*The song ''[[The Ragpicker's Dream|Devil Baby]]'' by [[Mark Knopfler]] deals with freaks and freakshows.
*The book ''[[Cirque Du Freak]]'', by [[Darren Shan]].
*[[Tom Waits]]' song Table Top Joe is based on the life of freak show performer [[Johnny Eck]].
*[[Twiztid]]'s album [[Freekshow]].
*[[Britney Spears]]' song "Freakshow" from her album ''[[Blackout (Britney Spears album)|Blackout]]''
* [[Dalton Trumbo]]'s ''[[Johnny Got His Gun]]'', is told from the standpoint of a wounded WWI soldier who requests to be put in  a freak show to demonstrate the monstrosties of war.
* There is a song called "Freakshow" by the industrial metal band [[Dimension f3h]].
* John Renshaw had a sports radio show called "The Freak Show" on 810 AM in Kansas City.
* A fanmade video entitled "Dark Woods Circus", created using the Japanese program [[Vocaloid]], features several [[Vocaloid]] characters as freakshow performers; namely a [[straitjacket]]-wearing cannibal, a 'deformed diva', and a two-headed person.

==See also==
* [[Human zoo]]

==Read also==
* Martin Monestier: Human Freaks, encyclopedic book on the Human Freaks from the beginning to today. (In French: Les Monstres humains: Oubliés de Dieu ou chefs-d'œuvres de la nature).
==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.freakshow.com Freakshow.com]
* [http://www.blackforpresident.com/ the BLACK SCORPION]
* [http://www.coneyisland.com/ Coney Island USA]
* [http://www.showhistory.com Showhistory.com]
* [http://www.shockedandamazed.com Shocked and Amazed! The only peri-odd-ical devoted to sideshow &amp; variety entertainment!]
* [http://www.sideshowworld.com Sideshowworld.com Preserving the past... promoting the future]
* [http://www.houseofdeception.com/Carnival_Sideshow_History.html HouseofDeception.com]
* [http://www.reneedodd.com/ Renee Dodd, Author of sideshow novel, A Cabinet of Wonders]

[[Category:Circuses]]
[[Category:Sideshows]]

[[ja:見世物小屋]]
[[sv:Freak show]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>