<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131017221509|577633206" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21387353" pageid="21387353" ns="0" title="Freak show"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-10-28T16:14:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Two other uses|an exhibition of biological rarities|the TV series|Freak Show (TV series)|Silverchair's album|Freak Show (album)}}
{{refimprove|date=August 2010}}
{{Disability}}[[Image:Coney2008.jpg|thumb|[[Coney Island]] and its popular on-going freak show.]]

A '''freak show''' is an exhibition of biological rarities, referred to as "freaks of nature".  Typical features would be physically unusual humans, such as those uncommonly large or small, those with [[intersexuality|both male and female secondary sexual characteristics]], people with other extraordinary diseases and conditions, and performances that are expected to be shocking to the viewers. Heavily [[tattoo]]ed or [[body piercing|pierced]] people have sometimes been seen in freak shows, as have attention-getting physical performers such as [[fire eater|fire-eating]] and [[Sword swallowing|sword-swallowing]] acts.

==History==

In the mid-16th century, freak shows began to become popular pastimes in England.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://thingssaidanddone.wordpress.com/2010/09/26/strange-and-bizarre-the-history-of-freak-shows/|title=Strange and Bizarre: The History of Freak Shows|accessdate=2012-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Deformities began to be treated as objects of interest and entertainment, and the crowds flocked to see them exhibited. A famous [[Early modern Europe|early modern]] example was the exhibition at the court of [[Charles I of England|Charles I]] of [[Lazarus and Joannes Baptista Colloredo]], two conjoined brothers born in [[Genoa]], [[Italy]]. While Lazarus was handsome and functioning, his parasitic brother just dangled before him in a mass of limbs from his chest. When Lazarus was not exhibiting himself, he covered his brother with his cloak to avoid unnecessary attention.&lt;ref&gt;Bondeson, Jan. (2000) ''The Two-Headed Boy, and Other Medical Marvels'' ISBN 978-0-8014-3767-0&lt;/ref&gt;

As well as royal exhibitions, freak shows were popular in the [[tavern]]s and fairgrounds where the freaks were often combined with talent displays. For example in the 18th century, [[Matthias Buchinger]], born without arms or lower legs, entertained crowds with astonishing displays of magic and musical ability, both in England and later, [[Ireland]].&lt;ref name=penny&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.libraryireland.com/articles/BuchingerDPJ1-44/index.php |title=Matthew Buchinger  |accessdate=2009-06-03 |date=April 27, 1833 |quote=Matthew Buchinger was born in Germany, without hands or feet, on the 3rd of June, 1674. He came over to England, from Hanover, in the retinue of George the first, with whom he expected to have ingratiated himself, by presenting to his Majesty a musical instrument of his own invention, resembling, we believe, a flute, and on which he played with considerable skill. ... |publisher=[[Dublin Penny Journal]] at the [[National Library of Ireland]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Freak show 1941.jpg|left|thumb|A freak show in [[Rutland (city), Vermont|Rutland, Vermont]] in 1941.]]
It was in the 19th century, both in [[England]] and the [[United States]], where freak shows finally reached maturity as successful commercially run enterprises.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://thingssaidanddone.wordpress.com/2010/09/26/strange-and-bizarre-the-history-of-freak-shows/|title=Strange and Bizarre: The History of Freak Shows|accessdate=2012-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[P. T. Barnum]] in the United States was a major figure in popularizing the entertainment.
In 1842, Barnum introduced his first major hoax, a creature with the head of a monkey and the tail of a fish, known as the [[Fiji mermaid|"Feejee" mermaid]].&lt;ref&gt;Schweitzer, Marlis. "Barnum's Last Laugh? General Tom Thumb's Wedding Cake In The Library Of Congress." ''Performing Arts Resources'' 28.(2011): 116. ''Associates Programs Source Plus.'' Web. 8 Dec. 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stabile, Susan M. "Still(Ed) Lives." ''Early American Literature'' 45.2 (2010): 371-395. Academic Search Premier. Web. 8 Dec. 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Barnum followed that with the exhibition of Charles Stratton, the dwarf "[[General Tom Thumb]]" who was then four years of age but was stated to be 11. Charles had stopped growing after the first six months of his life, at which point he was 25 inches (64&amp;nbsp;cm) tall and weighed 15 pounds (6.8&amp;nbsp;kg). With heavy coaching and natural talent, the boy was taught to imitate people from Hercules to Napoleon. By five, he was drinking wine and by seven smoking cigars for the public's amusement. During 1844–45, Barnum toured with Tom Thumb in Europe and met [[Victoria of the United Kingdom|Queen Victoria]], who was amused&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.phrases.org.uk/meanings/401800.html Queen Victoria and Tom Thumb]&lt;/ref&gt; and saddened by the little man, and the event was a publicity coup.&lt;ref name="Philip B. Kunhardt, et al., p. 73"&gt;{{harvnb|Kunhardt|Kunhardt|Kunhardt|1995|p=73}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1860, Barnum introduced the "man-monkey" William Henry Johnson, a  [[microcephalic]] black dwarf who spoke a mysterious language created by Barnum. In 1862, he discovered the giantess [[Anna Swan]] and [[Commodore Nutt]], a new Tom Thumb, with whom Barnum visited President [[Abraham Lincoln]] at the White House. During the [[American Civil War|Civil War]], Barnum's museum drew large audiences seeking diversion from the conflict.

Barnum's English counterpart was [[Tom Norman]], a renowned Victorian [[showman]], whose traveling exhibitions featured Eliza Jenkins, the "Skeleton Woman", a "Balloon Headed Baby" and a woman who bit off the heads of live rats—the "most gruesome" act Norman claimed to have seen.&lt;ref name=odnb&gt;{{Citation  | last = Osborne  | first = Peter  | title = Merrick, Joseph Carey &lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;Elephant Man&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; (1862–1890)  | work=[[Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]]  | publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]  | date = September 2004  | url = http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/37759  | doi = 10.1093/ref:odnb/37759   | accessdate =24 May 2010  | last2 = Harrison  | first2 = B.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=shef&gt;{{Citation |last=Toulmin|first = Vanessa | title = 'It Was Not The Show It Was The Tale That You Told' : The Life And Legend Of Tom Norman, the Silver King  | newspaper=''National Fairground Archive''  | publisher=[[University of Sheffield]]  | year = 2007  | url = http://www.nfa.dept.shef.ac.uk/history/shows/norman.html  | accessdate =19 May 2010&lt;!-- |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5roZsoIcy|archivedate=7 August 2010 --&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other acts included fleas, fat ladies, giants, dwarves and retired white seamen, painted black and speaking in an invented language, billed "savage Zulus".&lt;ref name=Howell69&gt;[[#Howell|Howell &amp; Ford (1992)]], p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; He displayed a "family of [[midget]]s" which in reality was composed of two men and a borrowed baby.&lt;ref name=Howell70&gt;[[#Howell|Howell &amp; Ford (1992)]], p. 70&lt;/ref&gt; He operated a number of shops in London and [[Nottingham]], and exhibited travelling shows throughout the country.&lt;ref name=odnb /&gt; 

Most famously, in 1884, Norman came into contact with [[Joseph Merrick]] the Elephant Man, a young man from Leicester who suffered from extreme deformities. Merrick arrived in London and into Norman's care. Norman, initially shocked by Merrick's appearance and reluctant to display him, nonetheless exhibited him at his penny gaff shop at 123 [[Whitechapel Road]], directly across the road from the [[London Hospital]].&lt;ref name=odnb /&gt;&lt;ref name=Howell72&gt;[[#Howell|Howell &amp; Ford (1992)]], p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; Because of its proximity to the hospital, the shop received medical students and doctors as visitors.&lt;ref name=Howell5&gt;[[#Howell|Howell &amp; Ford (1992)]], p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; One of these was a young surgeon named [[Sir Frederick Treves, 1st Baronet|Frederick Treves]] who arranged to have Merrick brought to the hospital to be examined.&lt;ref name=Howell77&gt;[[#Howell|Howell &amp; Ford (1992)]], p. 77&lt;/ref&gt;  The exhibition of the Elephant Man was reasonably successful, particularly with the added income from a printed pamphlet about Merrick's life and condition. 

At this time, however, public opinion about freak shows was starting to change and the display of human novelties was beginning to be viewed as distasteful. After only a few weeks with Norman, the Elephant Man exhibition was shut down by the police, and Norman and Merrick parted ways.&lt;ref name=Howell30&gt;[[#Howell|Howell &amp; Ford (1992)]], p. 30&lt;/ref&gt; Treves later arranged for Merrick to live at the London Hospital until his death in 1890. In Treves' 1923 memoir, ''The Elephant Man and Other Reminiscences'' made Norman infamous as a drunk who cruelly exploited Merrick.&lt;ref name=odnb /&gt;&lt;ref name=shef /&gt; Norman counteracted these claims in a letter in the ''World's Fair'' newspaper that year, as well as his own autobiography.&lt;ref name=odnb /&gt; Norman's opinion was that he provided Merrick (and his other exhibits) a way of making a living and remaining independent, but that on entering the London Hospital, Merrick remained a freak on display, only with no control over how or when he was viewed.&lt;ref name=Durbach34&gt;[[#Durbach|Durbach (2009)]], p. 34&lt;/ref&gt;

These changing attitudes about physical differences led to the decline of the freak show as a form of entertainment towards the end of the 19th century.{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} As previously mysterious anomalies were scientifically explained as [[genetic mutations]] or [[diseases]], freaks became the objects of sympathy rather than fear or disdain.{{citation needed|date=February 2013}} Laws were passed restricting freak shows for these reasons.  For example, [[Michigan]] law forbids the "exhibition [of] any deformed human being or human monstrosity, except as used for scientific purposes".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legislature.mi.gov/(S(40sppzifqwh50ey2tigyahzx))/mileg.aspx?page=getObject&amp;objectName=mcl-750-347 |title=Michigan Penal Code (Excerpt), Act 328 of 1931: Section 750.347, Deformed human beings; exhibition |publisher=Legislature.mi.gov |date=1931-09-18 |accessdate=2013-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in many places freak shows are still popular features.

==Historical timeline==
[[File:Extended mouthpiece for pipe smoking woman.jpg|thumb|Madam Gustika of the Duckbill tribe smoking a pipe with an extended mouthpiece for her large lips during a show in a circus. United States, New York, 12 April 1930. ([[Spaarnestad Photo]])]]
The exhibition of human oddities has a long history:

;1630s: [[Lazarus and Joannes Baptista Colloredo|Lazarus Colloredo]], and his conjoined twin brother, [[John Baptista]], who was attached at Lazarus' sternum, tour Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Armand Marie LeRoi, ''[[Mutants]]'', [[Penguin Books]], pp. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

;1704–1718: [[Peter I of Russia|Peter the Great]] collected human oddities at the [[Kunstkammer]] in what is now St. Petersburg, Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kunstkamera.ru/en/history/the_history_of_kunstkammer/ |title=The History of Kunstkammer |publisher=Kunstkamera.ru |date= |accessdate=2013-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;1738: The exhibition of a creature who "was taken in a wook at Guinea; 'tis a female about four feet high in every part like a woman excepting her head which nearly resembles the ape."&lt;ref&gt;Bogdan, R. (1988). ''[[Freak Show]].'' Chicago and London: [[The University of Chicago Press]]. pp. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;

;1810–1815: [[Sarah Baartman]] (aka "Hottentot Venus") exhibited in England and France.&lt;ref name=bbcnews2002&gt;{{cite news |title='Hottentot Venus' goes home|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/1957240.stm |publisher=BBC|date=29 April 2002|accessdate=13 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;1884: [[Joseph Merrick]], exhibited as "The Elephant Man" by [[Tom Norman]] in [[East End of London|London's East End]].&lt;ref&gt;Howell, Michael; Ford, Peter (1992). ''[[The True History of the Elephant Man]]'' (3rd ed.). p. 74. London: [[Penguin Books]]&lt;/ref&gt;

;1932: [[Tod Browning]]'s [[Pre-Code]]-[[era]] [[film]] ''[[Freaks]]'' tells the story of a traveling freakshow. The use of real freaks in the film provoked public outcries, and the film was relegated to obscurity until its re-release at the 1962 [[Cannes Film Festival]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.classichorror.free-online.co.uk/freaks.htm |title=Missing Link reviews Tod Browning's '&amp;#39;Freaks'&amp;#39; (1932) |publisher=Classichorror.free-online.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2013-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;1960:  [[Albert Karas|Albert-Alberta Karas]]&lt;ref&gt;''[http://digilib.syr.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/eisenmann&amp;CISOPTR=1933&amp;REC=8 Albert-Alberta Karas]'', photographer unknown, [[Syracuse University]] Digital Library, retrieved May 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; (two siblings, each half man, half woman) exhibits with Bobby Reynolds on sideshow tour.

;1991: [[Jim Rose Circus]] plays the [[Lollapalooza]] Festival, starting a new wave of performers and resurgence of interest in the genre. 

;1992: [[Grady Stiles]] ([[the lobster boy]]) is shot in his home in [[Gibsonton, Florida]].&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb name|0830183|name=Grady Stiles, Jr.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

;1996: Chicago shock-jock [[Mancow Muller]] presented [[Mancow's Freak Show]] at the United Center in the Summer of 1996, to crowd of 30,000. The show included [[Kathy Stiles]] and her brother [[Grady III]] as the [[Lobster Twins]].&lt;ref&gt;Mancow Muller (with [[John Calkins]]) [[Dad, Dames, Demons &amp; a Dwarf]] [[Regan Books]] 2004 pp.&amp;nbsp;121, 137-147&lt;/ref&gt;

;2000–2010: [[Ken Harck]]'s [[Brothers Grim Sideshow]] debuted at the [[Great Circus Parade]] in Milwaukee, WI. The Milwaukee run included a fat lady and bearded lady [[Melinda Maxi]], as well as self made freaks [[The Enigma (performer)|The Enigma]] and [[Katzen (performer)|Katzen]]. In later years the show has included Half-boy [[Jesse Stitcher]] and [[Jesus "Chuy" Aceves]] the [[Mexican Werewolf Boy]] and [[Stalking Cat]]. Brothers Grim toured with the Ozz Fest music festival in 2006,2007 and 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20070125163320/http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/kenharck/ |title=Chicago Reader: Wanna See Something Really Weird? |location=Chicago, Illinois |publisher=Web.archive.org |date= |accessdate=2013-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;2005: "999 Eyes Freakshow" founded, touting itself as the "last genuine traveling freakshow in the United States." 999 Eyes portrays freaks in a very positive light, insisting that "what is different is beautiful." Freaks include [[Black Scorpion (performer)|Black Scorpion]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.999eyes.com/biopage.htm|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090126002426/http://www.999eyes.com/biopage.htm|archivedate=2009-01-26 |title=999 EYES BIO |publisher=999eyes.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;2007: [[Wayne Schoenfeld]] bring together several sideshow performers to "[[The L.A. Circus Congress of Freaks and Exotics]]," to photograph sideshows folks for "[[Cirque Du Soleil]] - Circus of the Past." In attendance were: [[Bill Quinn]], the halfman; [[Percilla]], the fat lady; Mighty Mike Murga the Mighty Dwarf; [[Dieguito El Negrito]], a wildman; fireeaters; sword swallowers, and more.&lt;ref name="wayne"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wayneschoenfeld.com/ |title=Wayne Schoenfeld |publisher=Wayne Schoenfeld |date= |accessdate=2013-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="cast"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zootsuitclown.com/thecast.html |title=credits |publisher=Zootsuitclown.com |date= |accessdate=2013-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern freak shows==
[[Image:LobsterBoy.jpg|thumb|The [[Black Scorpion (performer)|Black Scorpion]] performing in 2007.]]
The entertainment appeal of the traditional "freak shows" is arguably echoed in numerous programmes made for television. ''[[Extraordinary People (2005 TV series)|Extraordinary People]]'' on the British television channel [[Five (TV channel)|Five]] or [[BodyShock]] show the lives of severely disabled or deformed people, and can be seen as the modern equivalent of circus freak shows.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Logged in as click here to log out |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/culture/tvandradioblog/2008/feb/21/lastnightstvextraordinaryp |title=Last night's TV: Extraordinary People: The Boys Joined at the Head &amp;#124; Media |publisher=The Guardian |date= 2008-02-21|accessdate=2009-04-13 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/tv_and_radio/article1509917.ece |title=Last Night's TV - Times Online |publisher=Entertainment.timesonline.co.uk |date= 2007-03-14|accessdate=2009-04-13 | location=London | first=Kevin | last=Maher}}&lt;/ref&gt; However in order to make the shows respectable, the subjects are usually portrayed as heroic and attention is given to their family and friends and the way they help them overcome their disabilities. On ''[[The Guardian]]'', Chris Shaw however comments that "one man's freak show is another man's portrayal of heroic triumph over medical adversity" and carries on with "call me prejudiced but I suspect your typical twentysomething watched this show with their jaw on the floor rather than a tear in their eye".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2006/feb/20/broadcasting.comment |title=The lure of the weird &amp;#124; Media &amp;#124; MediaGuardian |publisher=Guardian |date= 2006-02-20|accessdate=2009-04-13 | location=London | first=Chris | last=Shaw}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Human zoo]]
* [[Comprachicos]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* [[Martin Monestier]], ''Human Freaks, Encyclopedic Book on the Human Freaks from the Beginning to Today''. (In French: ''Les Monstres humains: Oubliés de Dieu ou chefs-d'œuvres de la nature'')

==External links==
* [http://www.showhistory.com/ Showhistory.com]
* [http://www.shockedandamazed.com/ Shocked and Amazed] - periodical devoted to sideshow and variety entertainment
* [http://freaks.monstrous.com/ Freaks and prodigies] - Section of Monstrous.Com dedicated to freaks and prodigies
* [http://www.sideshowworld.com/ Sideshow World] - "Preserving the past... promoting the future"
* [http://www.missioncreep.com/mundie/images/sideshow.htm Congress of Oddities: James G. Prodigies] - freakshow ephemera from the collection of artist [[James G Mundie]]
* [http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:FHCL.Hough:hou02245 Collection Guide to Human curiosity prints, playbills, broadsides and other printed material, 1695-1937] at [http://hcl.harvard.edu/libraries/houghton/ Houghton Library], Harvard University

{{DEFAULTSORT:Freak Show}}
[[Category:Circuses]]
[[Category:Sideshows]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>