<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061101221337|85126333" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21387353" pageid="21387353" ns="0" title="Freak show"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-05T14:19:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:''For the Silverchair album , see [[Freak Show (album)]], for the cartoon series, see [[Freak Show (TV series)]], for the Marvel Comics character, see [[Freakshow (comics)]], for Danny Phantom Villain see [[Freakshow (Danny Phantom)]]''

{{not verified}}

[[Image:FreakShowConeyIsland.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Coney Island]] and its popular on-going freak show.]]A '''freak show''' is an exhibition of rarities, "freaks of nature" — such as unusually tall or short humans, and people with [[intersexuality|both male and female secondary sexual characteristics]] — and performances that are expected to be shocking to the viewers. Heavily [[tattoo]]ed people have sometimes been seen in freak shows, as have [[fire eater|fire-eating]] and [[Sword swallowing|sword-swallowing]] acts.

==History==

Freak shows were popular in the United States from around 1840 to 1940, and were often, but not always, associated with [[circus]]es and [[carnival]]s. Some shows also exhibited deformed animals (such as two-headed cows, one-eyed pigs, and four-horned goats), famous hoaxes (such as the famous beheaded [[swamp monster]], which was found to be the buttocks of a deer with false eyes and fangs) or simply "science gone wrong" exhibits (such as deformed babies). With the increased mobility brought by the [[automobile]], the audience for travelling shows dwindled as Americans began to seek out entertainment farther from home.

Advances in [[medicine]] and political changes all but spelled the [[wiktionary:death knell|death knell]] for the freak show. As previously mysterious anomalies were scientifically explained as [[genetic mutations]] or [[diseases]], freaks became the objects of pity rather than fear or disdain. The [[eugenics]] movement saw human anomalies as unfortunate mistakes of nature. In [[1937]], [[Germany]] passed a law outlawing freak shows, decrying them as exploitation. 

Today, freak shows are outlawed in a number of U.S. states.  For example, Michigan law forbids the "exhibition [of] any deformed human being or human monstrosity, except as used for scientific purposes". [http://www.legislature.mi.gov/(sqktze55ua0uru45dvse3qv0)/mileg.aspx?page=getObject&amp;objectName=mcl-750-347]

==Today==

The term "freak show" is archaic and widely seen as [[pejorative]]; shows such as mentioned above, [[Jim Rose Circus]] sideshow, and at [[Coney Island]] are more politely termed [[sideshow]]s. However, [[Cut Throat Freak Show]] still uses the term, as do many other freak show and [[sideshow]] performers.

Freak shows are rare today, often reduced to [[museum]] displays containing newspaper clippings, photographs, statues, and other memorabilia of the freak shows of earlier times.

However, with the rise of the [[Internet]], the freakshow mentality has been given a new lease on life as sites such as [[rotten.com]] arose, allowing people to gaze at "freakish"  abnormalities that would not have been seen during the [[television]] era due to ideas about aesthetic [[taste]]. Some extreme [[Internet pornography]] can be placed in this category, too.

All of this is a far cry from the freak shows of old, which featured real living human oddities and medical anomalies - people that are born truly physically different from the "norm".  Although widely referred to as freaks, a distinction must be made between self-made freaks and born freaks. Generally, the most extreme examples of self-made freaks are referred to as "Human Marvels". [[Katzen]], [[The Enigma (person)|The Enigma]], the [[Lizardman]] and both the Scottish and Texan Leopard men are all human marvels. Currently, the only travelling freak show known to feature born living human oddities and medical anomalies is the ''999 Eyes of Endless Dream'' sideshow. This show features people born with medical anomalies such as [[Jackie the Half Girl]], [[Peg Leg the Modern-Day Elephant Man]], [[Lobster Girl]], and the [[Dame Demure Madame Miniature]].

==A historical timeline of the Freakshow== 

The exhibition of human oddities seen as far back as recorded history - we start in the year 1738.

'''1738''' - The exhibition of an exhibit who "was taken in a wook at Guinea; 'tis a female about four feet high in every part like a woman excepting her head which nearly resembles the ape."

By the late 18th century, the science of [[teratology]] changed the belief that freaks were evil omens and the work of Satan or witches.  Instead, people believed the theory that freaks were part of gods great order of creatures.

'''1822''' - The [[Fiji mermaid|FeeJee Mermaid]] is discovered in Indonesia by Captain Eades.

'''1829''' - [[Chang and Eng Bunker|Chang and Eng]] “the original [[conjoined twins|Siamese twins]]” were exhibited in America.

'''1839''' - J.G. Milligan writes “curiosities of medical experiments” in which freaks are described.

'''1844''' - [[P. T. Barnum]] arrives in London to exhibit [[General Tom Thumb|Tom Thumb]], the famous midget.

'''1860''' - Barney and Hiram are presented as wild men from the island of Borneo.  The guide book for Barnum American museum list 13 human curiosities.  [[Zip the Pinhead]] begins his six-decade career with Barnum.

'''1863''' - Barnum uses his brilliant showman skills to get the civil war and emancipation proclamation pushed off the front pages and replaced by a midget wedding.

'''1870-1890''' - [[Dime museum]]s are at the height of their popularity, with the freakshow as the main attraction.

'''1876''' - Wild men of Borneo, wild Australian children, man-eating FeeJee Mermaids and the 602lb woman are exhibited at the first [[World’s Fair]] in Philadelphia.

'''1880''' - First freakshow at [[Coney Island]].

'''1884''' - Freak recruiting becomes a career and full time occupation.

'''1889''' - British medical journal describes [[Myrtle Corbin]], the "four-legged girl," and verifies that both sets of reproductive organs as workable and capable of birthing children.

'''1890''' - The Jones twins, Siamese twins joined at buttocks and sharing a rectum die on carnival tour at fifteen months old.

Latter part of the 19th century - The theory that freaks are biological throwbacks to earlier races of humans and apes is introduced.  The theory of [[maternal impression]] attributes traumatic or significant events experienced by the pregnant woman as an explanation for deformities.

Turn of the 20th century - The resurgence of [[Mendel]]’s law of genetics coupled with [[Charles Darwin|Darwin]]'s ''[[The Origin of Species|Origin of Species]]'' introduced the idea that freaks could "taint the gene pool".

'''1904''' - Silbey devises the "[[sideshow|Ten-In-One]]" show and creates jobs for talkers.

'''1908''' - An article in [[Scientific American]] introduces concept of freak exhibitions being inhumane and barbaric.

'''1915''' - San Francisco exposition includes a midget village and dime museum freakshow.

'''1922''' - Professor Sam Wagner starts the World's Circus freakshow at Coney Island. General public can read articles in popular press explaining the diseases behind oddities.

'''1925''' - Freaks can be seen performing on the [[vaudeville]] stage.

'''1932''' - [[Tod Browning]]'s [[Pre-Code]]-[[era]] [[film]] ''[[Freaks]]'' tells the story of a travelling freakshow. The use of real freaks in the film provoked public outcries

'''1933''' - [[World's Fair|Chicago Expo]] features a pit show with a "live two-headed baby" in a jar of formaldehyde.

'''1937''' - Nazis banned freakshows making it legal to arrest these "useless" members of society and experiment on them. Often they were sent to infamous Nazi doctor [[Josef Mengele]].

Late 1930's - The switch in social view of those with physical or mental anomalies from fabulous freaks and curiosities to diseased people with disorders was complete.

'''1940''' - Freakshow is on the ropes and the dime museum essentially dead.  The three-legged man, [[Frank Lentini]], opens a freakshow.

'''1950''' - Historical sideshow died as public demands freaks be given "dignity" and not exhibited, at this time many went into institutions or on the welfare system.

'''1952''' - The "Human Torso" is still on exhibit.

'''1960''' - It is said as more freaks lost their jobs with the freakshow that many of them joined up with [[Anton LaVey|Anton Szandor LaVey]]. Albert-Alberta Karas[http://digilib.syr.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/eisenmann&amp;CISOPTR=1933&amp;REC=8] (siblings each half man, half woman) exhibits with Bobby Reynolds on sideshow tour.

'''1969''' - John Strong saves $150 and purchases Patches the two headed cow and begins his freak animal show.

'''1972''' - At north fair Sealo and the dwarf Pete Terhune confront charges against them for exhibiting themselves. The charges equated freakshows with pornography

'''1980's''' Bobby Reynolds is arrested for exhibiting [[pickled punks]].

'''1984''' - Freakshow performer Otis Jordan (the frog boy) is barred from exhibiting himself at the New York State Fair on the basis that the exhibition of human oddities is exploitative.  Barbara Baskin, a "disability rights activist" led this fight and Otis was out of a job for two years before he beat the case and could perform again.

'''1992''' - Grady Stiles (the lobster boy) is shot in his home in Gibsonton Florida.

'''1998''' - The Brazilian TV show "Ratinho Livre", whose main performer was Carlos "Ratinho" Massa became a kind of freak show, exhibiting mainly children with serious physical anomalies, such as hundreds of facial tumors (Eleandro, the Elephant Boy), tails, amputations, et cetera. Later, near 2000, the Brazilian justice prohibited such appearances on TV shows.

'''2005&amp;ndash;2006''' - Ward Hall is still going strong with his sideshow where he still exhibits some born freaks. The [http://www.999eyes.com/ 999 Eyes of Endless Dream Sideshow]begins scouring the streets for modern-day freaks. 

'''2006''' A new "Lobster-Boy" known as ''[http://www.blackforpresident.com/ BLACK]'' is found living in Austin, Texas and is recuirted by the [http://www.999eyes.com/ 999 Eyes of Endless Dream Sideshow]. You can visit his website [http://www.lobster-boy.com/ Lobster-Boy.com].

==See also==
* [[Freaks]], a [[1932]] [[horror film]] from the [[Pre-Code]] era about [[sideshow]] performers, directed by [[Tod Browning]].
* [[Freaked]], a [[1993]] [[comedy film]] about mutated victims to an amoral entrepeneur.
* [[Human zoo]]
* [[Sideshow]]
* [[Kunstkamera]]
* [http://www.999eyes.com The 999 Eyes of Endless Dream Carnival Sideshow of the Damned]
* [http://www.showhistory.com Showhistory.com]
* [http://www.sideshowworld.com Sideshowworld.com Preserving the past... promoting the future]
* [http://www.reneedodd.com/ Renee Dodd, Author of sideshow novel, A Cabinet of Wonders]
* [http://www.thehumanmarvels.com/ The Human Marvels: A Historical Reference Site run by J. Tithonus Pednaud, Teratological Historian]

==References==
* ''[http://digilib.syr.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/eisenmann&amp;CISOPTR=1933&amp;REC=8 Albert-Alberta Karas]'', photographer unknown, Syracuse University Digital Library, retrieved May 6, 2006.

[[Category:Circuses]]

[[ja:見世物小屋]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>