<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051024024112|26326368" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21387353" pageid="21387353" ns="0" title="Freak show"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T08:51:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''freak show''' is an exhibition of rarities, "freaks of nature"—such as unusually tall or short humans, and people with both male and female secondary sexual characteristics—and performances that are expected to be shocking to the viewers. Heavily [[tattoo]]ed people have sometimes been seen in freak shows, as have [[fire eater|fire-eating]] and [[Sword swallowing|sword-swallowing]] acts.

==History==

Freak shows were popular in the United States from around 1840 to 1940, and were often, but not always, associated with [[circus]]es and [[carnival]]s. Some shows also contain exhibits containing deformed animals (such as two-headed cows, one-eyed pigs, and four-horned goats), famous hoaxes (such as the famous beheaded [[swamp monster]] that was found to be the [[buttocks]] of a [[deer]] with false eyes and fangs) or simply 'science gone wrong' exhibits (deformed babies caused by smoking, people with tumors covering their faces, etc.).

==Today==

The term "freak show" is archaic and widely seen as [[pejorative]];
shows such as mentioned above, [[Jim Rose Circus]] sideshow, and at [[Coney Island]] are more politely termed [[sideshow]]s. However, [[Cut Throat Freak Show]] still uses the term, as do many other freak show and [[sideshow]] performers.

Freak shows are rare today, often reduced to [[museum]] displays containing newspaper clippings, photographs, statues, and other memorabilia of the freak shows of earlier times.

[[Rotten.com]] is a modern-day Internet freak show.

A freak show is a central theme of the [[Lemony Snicket]] book [[The Carnivorous Carnival]], featuring a contortionist, an ambidextrous individual, and a hunchback, as well as, later, the disguised [[A Series of Unfortunate Events|Baudelaires]]. The book uses the freak show to make the point that people often exaggerate differences idiotically.

==See also==
* [[Sideshow]]
* [[Kunstkamera]]

{{Theat-stub}}

[[Category:Circuses]]

[[ja:見世物小屋]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>