<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241009234433|1250359746" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="61296215" pageid="61296215" ns="0" title="Perpetual foreigner"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-10-10T00:08:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Stereotype}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Social}}

The '''perpetual foreigner''', '''forever foreigner''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author-last=Loh-Hagan | author-first=Virginia | title=What is the Forever Foreigner Stereotype? | isbn=9781668900505 | date=January 1, 2022 | publisher=Cherry Lake Publishing | series=21st Century Skills Library}}&lt;/ref&gt; or '''perpetual other'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=&lt;!---none cited---&gt; | title=Allosemitism (noun) - Jews as the perpetual 'other'| work=Jewish Journal | date=August 7, 2008 | url=https://jewishjournal.com/news/worldwide/65224/}}&lt;/ref&gt; stereotype is a racist or xenophobic form of [[Nativism (politics)|nativism]] in which [[Naturalization|naturalized]] and even [[Jus soli|native-born citizens]] (including families that have lived in a country for generations) are perceived by some members of society as foreign because they belong to a minority ethnic or racial group.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite book|last1=Dei|first1=George J. Sefa|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=z559DwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA40|title=Cartographies of Race and Social Difference|last2=Hilowle|first2=Shukri|date=2018-12-04|publisher=Springer|isbn=9783319970769|pages=40|language=en|quote=Concurrent with the "model minority" stereotype is the view of Asian Americans as "perpetual foreigners" who are permanent outsiders to the norms of North American culture and the dominant inner circle. As argued by Omi (2008), "this image is reflective of the process of racializing people in terms of their presumed affiliation with foreign places" (par. 7). This perpetual foreigner view is demonstrated in a survey by Kang (2001) which showed that 28% of Americans believed that Chinese Americans were more loyal to China than the United States. ... This example serves to demonstrate that the "perpetual foreigner" stereotype is not just applied to recent Asian immigrant groups but also to fourth-generation Asian immigrants who have gained a certain level of economic success in Canada.}}&lt;/ref&gt; When citizenship has been granted and yet the group of people is persistently viewed as foreign, the term '''alien citizen''' has been also used to in some scholarship describe these groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author-last=Kılınç | author-first=Ramazan | title=Alien Citizens: The State and Religious Minorities in Turkey and France | series= Cambridge Studies in Social Theory, Religion and Politics | publisher=Cambridge University Press | isbn= 9781108692649 | doi=10.1017/9781108692649 | date=September 2019 | s2cid=204426327 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rYK0DwAAQBAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The term '''perpetual immigrant''' has been used for cases of migration, [[forced displacement]], or other reasons for relocation, where no citizenship is possible despite the individual's long-term residency, wish to become a citizen, and even (though not necessarily) birth in the land.&lt;ref name="Kasimis, Perpetual Immigrant, full book"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Kasimis|first=Demetra|title=The Perpetual Immigrant and the Limits of Athenian Democracy|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9781107052437|year=2018|location=New York|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RY1HtQEACAAJ | oclc=1030904084 | doi=10.1017/9781107280571|s2cid=158074459 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, '''noncitizen nationals''', or persons who hold nationality but not citizenship, have also been argued to fall under this stereotypical image.&lt;ref name="Roman, Noncitizen Nationals"&gt;{{cite journal | author-last=Roman | author-first=Ediberto | title=Alien-Citizen Paradox and Other Consequences of U.S. Colonialism | year=1998 | journal=Florida State University Law Review | volume=26 | pages=1–50 | ssrn=1625826 | url=https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1625826#}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Naturalization]] laws vary, and some countries follow a rule of ''[[jus sanguinis]]'' in various forms.  For example, [[Myanmar nationality law]] regards the [[Rohingya people]] as foreign.

Some countries have many refugees or other [[resident alien]]s with some groups, such as religious and ethnic [[in-group and out-group|out-groups]] of the country in question, often experiencing more barriers to citizenship compared to their [[in-group and out-group|in-group]] peers.&lt;ref name="PNAS study, Ryo&amp;Humphrey"&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; A [[diaspora]] such as the [[overseas Chinese]] is often regarded as belonging to their ancestral homeland rather than to the country in which they live. Note that part of the phenomenon where a person is of a separate nationality (and/or when considered different in the legal structure of the country, citizenship) from which they live can also be cases where the person is not seeking the nationality and/or citizenship of the country where they are, usually temporarily, living.  Such persons are generally called expatriates, especially [[expatriate#business expatriate|business expatriates]] or [[student exchange program|exchange students]] who live outside the country of their nationality for business or educational purposes, generally for a temporary period of time. They usually do not desire citizenship (given the choice in countries and time periods where there is one) or a change in nationality (whatever or whichever legal structure is pertinent to the country in question) and should not be confused with this stereotype.

==Ancient history==

===Athens===
Like other [[Ancient Greece|Greek]] [[city-state]]s of this time period, immigrants known as [[metics]] ([[Ancient Greek]]: {{lang|grc|metoikoi}}) came to [[Athens]] without a path to citizenship and could not participate in [[Athenian democracy]]. Recent scholarship has begun to examine Ancient Greek writings on contemporary sentiments of the day. It seems to show that people of the day were divided over anxieties around the intermingling and passing of these groups of people and the desire to continue to deny political agency to such members of society, while other contemporaries argued that such thinking was part of what turned democracy into a "noble lie".&lt;ref name="Kasimis, Perpetual Immigrant, full book"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Kasimis|first=Demetra|title=The Perpetual Immigrant and the Limits of Athenian Democracy|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9781107052437|year=2018|location=New York|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RY1HtQEACAAJ | oclc=1030904084 | doi=10.1017/9781107280571|s2cid=158074459 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Blockquote|"What makes this habit curious is that the [[Republic (Plato)|''Republic''{{'}}s]] narrative frame actually presents the idea that one's political "kind" ({{lang|grc|genos}}) expresses a pregiven, stable nature as a regulatory fiction. In these scenes, Socrates contrives the noble lie as an "artifice" ({{lang|grc|mēchanē}}) by which regimes, including the Athens of the dialogue's setting, found and reproduce membership status as a naturalized category."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Kasimis|first=Demetra|chapter=Plato's Open Secret |title=The Perpetual Immigrant and the Limits of Athenian Democracy|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9781107280571|year=2018|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RY1HtQEACAAJ|doi=10.1017/9781107280571.005 |page=84 | format=online| chapter-url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/abs/perpetual-immigrant-and-the-limits-of-athenian-democracy/platos-open-secret/9409B4915ECC1927BAC441C2909D976B | oclc=1030904084&lt;!---format follows the isbn number's format---&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Roman Empire===
In the context of the [[Roman Empire]], the politics of difference has generally been considered by scholars to look considerably different than notions around modern definitions of [[race (human categorization)|race]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author-last=Woolf | author-first=Greg | title=An empire of many colours? Race and imperialism in Ancient Rome | website=OUPblog | publisher=Oxford University Press | access-date=September 14, 2023 | date=September 21, 2021 | url=https://blog.oup.com/2021/09/an-empire-of-many-colours-race-and-imperialism-in-ancient-rome/ &lt;!----much of the following paragraph is paraphrased from this article!---&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; as has been recently discussed by [[Greg Woolf]] on the [[Oxford University Press]] Blog. Instead, Roman slave owners worried that one could not tell the difference between the enslaved and the free peoples of the Empire. Examples of Roman paranoia include a story told by [[Lucius Annaeus Seneca the Younger|Seneca]] where the [[Roman Senate]] once debated about requiring all slaves to wear a particular costume, until they realized this would reveal just how many slaves there were in Rome. And Pliny is recorded as recounting an encounter where a senator while in the [[Roman baths]] was mistaken for a slave.

However, this is not to say that Romans were immune from distinguishing themselves on the basis of certain characteristics. [[Vergil]] once referred to his people as ''gens togata'' (the 'toga-ed race' or 'the people who wear a [[toga]]'). Often differences such as manner of speech, what people wore, how they ate, and other habits were the target of definitions of "strangeness", including but not limited to cases where Roman senators needed to [[Accent reduction|change their speech]] before holding office. And this was not to say that the Roman Empire was entirely made up of European peoples. Sites as far north as [[Roman Britain#Demographics|England have shown the movement of different peoples]] throughout the Empire, including from Africa and DNA analysis of 2,000-year-old remains in an Ancient Roman cemetery show that at least one person was of East Asian heritage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=&lt;!---not cited---&gt; | title=DNA testing on 2,000-year-old bones in Italy reveal East Asian ancestry | work=Science Daily | date=February 2, 2010 | access-date=September 24, 2023 | url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2010/02/100201171756.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; As pointed out by Woolf, ways of othering were simply not along the lines of modern notions of racialization and that the relative lack of physical differences between those who had freedom in the society and those who did not was a source of anxiety amongst the Roman elite.

==United States==
Recent scholarship and analysis of immigration and citizenship law in the United States is reckoning with the historical construction of citizenship in the country and its effects on different populations,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last=Bavery | first=Ashley Johnson | title=Contingent Citizens: Inclusion, Exclusion, and the Shifting Boundaries of American Immigration Laws | journal=Reviews in American History | pages=634–639 | volume=45 | number=4 | date=December 2017 | access-date=September 12, 2023 | jstor=48558657 | doi=10.1353/rah.2017.0093 | publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press | s2cid=148848954 | url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/680642}}&lt;/ref&gt; most especially in the gap between the perception of foreignness compared to actual foreignness (when discussed as a process within current psycho-social theories such as [[in-group and out-group | in-group and out-group hypothesis]] can also be referred to generally as "othering" or "the process of othering"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Curle | first=Clint| title=Us vs. Them: The process of othering | publisher=Canadian Museum for Human Rights | date=January 24, 2020&lt;!---last update date---&gt; | url=https://humanrights.ca/story/us-vs-them-process-othering | access-date=September 25, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;). In the work ''Making Foreigners: Immigration and Citizenship Law in America, 1600-2000,''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Parker | first=Kunal M. | title=Making Foreigners: Immigration and Citizenship Law in America, 1600–2000 | publisher=Cambridge University Press | location=New York, NY, USA | url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/making-foreigners/B3D2569D364C9399364ADFAF15D4D98A | date=5 September 2015 &lt;!---first published date---&gt; | edition=1st | oclc=904400075 | isbn=9781107698512 | doi=10.1017/CBO9781139343282}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kunal M Parker writes:

{{Blockquote|"The special powerlessness of the immigrant has its source, we are wont to think, in the fact that the foreigner comes from elsewhere. The foreigner's origins outside the community supposedly make it possible and permissible for the community to deny his or her claims upon it. An entrenched constitutional tradition in the United States under-girds this view. Political theorists have offered elaborate arguments defending it. My own particular experience of the powerlessness of the immigrant seeking admission led me to wonder exactly what it is about an individual's coming from elsewhere that makes it possible to deny his or her claims on the community. I turned to the archives, if not for definitive answers, then at least for ways to transcend my own experience by learning about the experiences of others. What I discovered was that the experience of foreignness – and of the powerlessness associated with it – has never been unique to those coming from outside the United States. Over the centuries, Americans have named and treated like foreigners not only immigrants from outside the country, but also Native Americans, blacks, Latino Americans, Asian Americans, women, the poor, and political minorities. Designation as foreign is not a function of coming from the territorial outside. It is a political strategy that has been used inside ''and'' outside the country and to multiple ends."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Parker | first=Kunal M. | title=Making Foreigners: Immigration and Citizenship Law in America, 1600–2000 | chapter=Preface and Acknowledgments | page=ix | publisher=Cambridge University Press | location=New York, NY, USA | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=351rCgAAQBAJ | chapter-url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/abs/making-foreigners/preface-and-acknowledgments/269985775A0EB3E691EDF1A622CDEAE3 | format=online &lt;!---format follows the isbn number's format---&gt;| oclc=927149403 | access-date=September 12, 2023 | date=5 September 2015 &lt;!---first published date---&gt; | isbn= 9781139343282 | doi=10.1017/CBO9781139343282.001}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The early history of the United States was marked by a period of ethnic and racially-based naturalization laws. The first [[naturalization]] act was passed by Congress on March 26, 1790, stated:

{{Blockquote|"That any alien, other than an enemy alien, being a ''free white person'', who shall have resided within the limits and under the jurisdiction of the United States for the term of two years, may be admitted to become a citizen thereof, on application to any common law court of record in any one of the States wherein he shall have resided for the term of one year at least..."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | institution=U.S. Capital Visitor Center |title=H. R. 40, Naturalization Bill, March 4, 1790|url=https://www.visitthecapitol.gov/artifact/h-r-40-naturalization-bill-march-4-1790 | date=4 March 1790 &lt;!---date originally penned---&gt; | access-date=September 12, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The law was updated on January 29, 1795, to a length of five years,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Bolger | first=Eilleen | title=Background History of the United States Naturalization Process | date=2013 | access-date=September 12, 2023 | url=https://socialwelfare.library.vcu.edu/federal/naturalization-process-in-u-s-early-history/ | publisher=Virginia Commonwealth University | agency=VCU Libraries Social Welfare History Project}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the rest of the act remained fundamentally unchanged. Citizenship hinged partly on the definition of being considered "a free white". Despite being challenged as early as 1857 in [[Dred Scott v. Sanford]] by [[Dred Scott]] and his wife Harriet, it was not until the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment's]] [[Citizenship Clause]] written 1868 that began to take a significant step towards [[Jus soli|birthright citizenship]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=&lt;!--not stated--&gt;| title=Reconstructing Citizenship | publisher=Smithsonian Institution | department=National Museum of African American History &amp; Culture | date=n.d.|access-date=September 13, 2023 | url=https://nmaahc.si.edu/explore/exhibitions/reconstruction/citizenship}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Scholarship studying [[freak shows]] in the 19th century and contemporary popular periodicals like ''[[Harper's Weekly]]'' and the ''San Francisco Golden Era'' were further used to illustrate who was, and who was not, an American.&lt;ref name="Frost, Freakshows"&gt;{{cite book | last=Frost | first=Linda | title=Never One Nation: Freaks, Savages, and Whiteness in U.S. Popular Culture, 1850–1877 | publisher=University of Minnesota Press | year=2005 | isbn=9780816644902 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bf0RHKWK82sC | oclc=56686376}}&lt;/ref&gt; This exotification has been discussed as minimizing the individual, minimizing the complexity of their heritage, turning them into an object, and as having been used to further reinforce their 'un-Americanness'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Nadal | first=Andrea | title=Exotification: minimizing the individual | date=November 16, 2020 | url=https://thetacomaledger.com/2020/11/16/exotification-minimizing-the-individual/ | website=The Tacoma Ledger | access-date=September 12, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sometimes by direct reference, other times by indirect reference as has been argued with the [[Circassian beauty#Nineteenth-century sideshow attraction|Circassian Beauties]] who combined both [[Edward Said | Edward Said's]] description of [[Orientalism (book)|Orientalism]] with a hairstyle similar to the 1970s [[Afro]] into a singular depiction of 'the other'.&lt;ref name="Frost, Freakshows"&gt;{{cite book | last=Frost | first=Linda | title=Never One Nation: Freaks, Savages, and Whiteness in U.S. Popular Culture, 1850–1877 | publisher=University of Minnesota Press | year=2005 | isbn=9780816644902 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bf0RHKWK82sC | oclc=56686376}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1909 [[Armenians]], [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]], and Jews were finally permitted exception from being barred from naturalization (as [[Jewish Americans#History|Jews had been in America since around the mid-1600s]] and [[Armenian Americans#History|Armenians since the early 1600s]] with Assyrian Americans being the most recent [[Assyrian Americans#History|in the late 1800s]]) like other "Asiatics" and was announced in a statement from the New York Times that read:&lt;ref name="Ghoogasian"&gt;{{cite web | last=Ghoogasian | first=Aram | title=How Armenian-Americans Became "White": A Brief History | date=August 29, 2017 | access-date=September 12, 2023 | website=Ajam Media Collective | url=https://ajammc.com/2017/08/29/armenian-whiteness-america/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Blockquote|"...Western Asiatics have become so mixed with Europeans during the past twenty-five centuries that it is impossible to tell whether they are white or should come under the statutes excluding the inhabitants of that part of the world and usually applied to the yellow race."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Citizenship for Armenians. Circuit Court Declines to Bar them on Government's Plea | newspaper=New York Times | date=December 24, 1909 | author=&lt;!---not stated!---&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ghoogasian"&gt;{{cite web | last=Ghoogasian | first=Aram | title=How Armenian-Americans Became "White": A Brief History | date=August 29, 2017 | access-date=September 12, 2023 | website=Ajam Media Collective | url=https://ajammc.com/2017/08/29/armenian-whiteness-america/}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Notably [[George Washington]] wrote in 1790 to the Hebrew Congregations of Newport, Rhode Island stating that the United States "gives to bigotry no sanction, to persecution no assistance".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Antisemitism Uncovered: Antisemitism in American History | publisher=Anti-Defamation League | location=New York, NY, USA | url=https://antisemitism.adl.org/antisemitism-in-american-history/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Sachar | first=Howard M. | title=A History of the Jews in America |chapter=A Foothold in the Early Americas: Prefigurations of Comprehensive Emancipation | location=New York, NY, USA | publisher=Alfred A. Knopf | isbn=9780394573533 | format=hardcover&lt;!---follows the isbn number, which goes to the hardback edition---&gt;|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/A_History_of_the_Jews_in_America.html?id=DeFsAAAAQBAJ &lt;!---note: link goes to the reprint edition by First Vintage Books (although both have the quote on the same page!---&gt;| year=1992 | page=26}}&lt;/ref&gt; It should not be overlooked either that Jews have occupied a place where they've been considered white on one hand, yet not on another in the history of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Kaur | first= Harmeet | title=What does it mean to be Jewish in the US? | publisher=CNN | date=April 4, 2023 | url=https://www.cnn.com/2023/04/04/us/us-jewish-racial-identity-religion-explained-cec/index.html | access-date=September 12, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1898, Wong Kim Ark, who was born in the United States, was denied re-entry in the United States after a brief visit to China, prompting a landmark decision in the [[United States v. Wong Kim Ark]] case where the Supreme Court declared the denial unconstitutional. American actress [[Anna May Wong]], despite having been a third-generation American and born in America, was issued a special "Certificate of Identity", signed by an immigration officer that was required to be carried by all "Chinese persons" as of its issuance in the 1920s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Blue | first=Victoria | title=Chinese American Actress's Story Illustrates 'Othering' of Immigrants | website=National Archives News |publisher=The U.S. National Archives and Records Administration| date=May 10, 2022 | orig-date=March 30, 2021 | access-date=September 9, 2023 | url=https://www.archives.gov/news/articles/anna-may-wong-chinese-american-perpetual-foreigner}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the late 1800s there was a series of mob massacres of persons of [[East Asian]] heritage in the United States, including but not limited to the [[Los Angeles Chinese massacre of 1871]] and the [[Hells Canyon Massacre | Hells Canyon Massacre of 1887]].

For [[Native Americans in the United States|Indigenous Americans]], the story of citizenship was (and is) a bit more complicated. Laws such as the [[Dawes Act]] conditionally granted citizenship upon acceptance of agriculture and individual land parcels,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=The Dawes Act | author=Staff | publisher=U.S. National Park Service | date=July 9, 2021 | access-date=September 24, 2023 | url=https://www.nps.gov/articles/000/dawes-act.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; one of many [[forced assimilation]] policies. All Indigenous Americans were granted citizenship status on June 2, 1924, by President Calvin Coolidge in the [[Indian Citizenship Act]], this act on one hand opened up voting opportunities and on another denied the sovereignty of the Indigenous Nations. Currently, many Indigenous Americans hold a sense of [[dual citizenship]], recognizing both Indigenous sovereignty and their American identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author-last=Weaver | author-first=Jace | title=Native Americans: Befriending, Resisting and Enduring | work=Teaching American History | url=https://teachingamericanhistory.org/blog/native-americans-befriending-resisting-and-enduring/ | date= November 29, 2022 | access-date=September 24, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A survey conducted in 2005 notes that the implicit stigma that ‘white’ equals American persists to this day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author-last=Devos | author-last2=Banaji | author-first=Thierry | author-first2=Mahzarin R. | title=American = White? | doi= 10.1037/0022-3514.88.3.447 | journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | date=March 2005 | volume=88 | number=3 | pages=447–466 | pmid=15740439 | url=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15740439/}}&lt;/ref&gt; This correlation was also observed in a pop culture experiment where the American actress [[Lucy Liu]] was perceived as less American than the European actress [[Kate Winslet]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author-last=Devos | author-last2=Ma | author-first=Thierry | author-first2=Debbie S.| title=Is Kate Winslet more American than Lucy Liu? The impact of construal processes on the implicit ascription of a national identity | doi= 10.1348/014466607X224521 | journal=The British Journal of Social Psychology | date= June 2008 | pages=191–215 | volume=47 | number=Pt 2 | pmid=17621413 | pmc=3676889 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Notably, all groups deemed less ‘American’ have all been denied ‘’citizenship’’ status at one time or another during United States history. Additionally, naturalization barriers between ‘whites’ and other groups continue to persist. According to a study in 2022, non-Hispanic whites are still more likely to be granted citizenship status compared to all other persons, although studied in particular with respect to African, persons from Muslim-majority countries, and Hispanic immigrants, when seeking naturalization.&lt;ref name="PNAS study, Ryo&amp;Humphrey"&gt;{{cite journal| author-last=Ryo | author-last2=Humphrey | author-first=Emily | date=February 22, 2022 | doi=10.1073/pnas.2114430119 | author-first2=Reed | title=The importance of race, gender, and religion in naturalization adjudication in the United States | journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume=119 | number=9| doi-access=free | pmid=35193975 | pmc=8892311 | bibcode=2022PNAS..11914430R }}&lt;/ref&gt;

This stereotype has been popularly discussed as a negative [[Stereotypes of East Asians in the United States#Perpetual foreigner|stereotype of Asian Americans]], but it has also affected other minority groups, which have been considered to be "[[Other (philosophy)|the other]]"&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=I4Mrc4PEHxQC&amp;pg=PT192|title=Faith and Race in American Political Life|last1=Jacobson|first1=Robin Dale|last2=Wadsworth|first2=Nancy D.|date=2012-02-02|publisher=University of Virginia Press|isbn=9780813932057|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and therefore [[judicial aspects of race in the United States|legally unassimilable]], either historically or currently. In personal interactions, it can take the form of an act of [[microaggression]] in which a member of a minority group may be asked, "Where are you from?" It can also take the form of an explicit act of aggression in which a member of a minority group may be told, "Go back to where you came from."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jyzcuvgTaIMC&amp;pg=PA37|title=Microaggressions in Everyday Life: Race, Gender, and Sexual Orientation|last=Sue|first=Derald Wing|date=2010-02-09|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=9780470594155|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; African Americans have been told "go [[back to Africa]]" as a racial insult,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.miamiherald.com/news/local/community/community-conversations-blog/article232844217.html|title=I was told to 'Go Back to Africa.' Here's why I'm not going anywhere, Mr. Trump|last=Hines|first=Bea L.|date=July 19, 2019|work=Miami Herald|access-date=21 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite the fact that on average, they are more likely to have a multi-generational family history in the United States than [[white Americans]] are.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=Gallup News Service | date=2001-07-10 | title=Majority of Americans Identify Themselves as Third Generation Americans|url=https://news.gallup.com/poll/4621/Majority-Americans-Identify-Themselves-Third-Generation-Americans.aspx|access-date=2020-08-11 |website=Gallup.com |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Furthermore, comments such as these also affect Indigenous Americans. In 2017 during a protest, "go back to where you came from" was shouted at Indigenous protestors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Estes | first=Nick | title=Go Back to Where You Came From | date=November 4, 2019 | website=San Francisco Museum of Modern Art (SFMOMA) | url=https://openspace.sfmoma.org/2019/11/go-back-to-where-you-came-from | issue=Issue 13: Alcatraz Is Not an Island | access-date=September 24, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[United States |American]] [[Cree]] comedian [[Charlie Hill]] was recorded as saying, "A redneck told me to go back to where I came from, so I put up a tipi in his backyard!"

The [[U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] defines workplace comments like "[[Go back where you came from]]" as a potentially illegal form of ethnic harassment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.cbsnews.com/news/eeoc-go-back-where-you-came-from-discrimination-federal-law-trump-tweets/|title=U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission specifically lists "go back to where you came from" as example of discrimination|last=Silverstein|first=Jason|date=July 17, 2019|work=CBS News|access-date=19 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The message conveys a sense that the person is "not supposed to be there, or that it isn't their place," and it is often encountered when the minority person is "speaking out in predominantly white spaces."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/16/us/politics/aoc-trump-tlaib-omar-pressley.html|title=The Painful Roots of Trump's 'Go Back' Comment|last=Rogers|first=Katie|date=July 16, 2019|work=The New York Times|access-date=17 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Hate crimes]], such as the [[murder of Vincent Chin]], are described as the most brutal form of the perpetual foreigner syndrome.&lt;ref&gt;Wu, Frank H. "Where are you really from? Asian Americans and the perpetual foreigner syndrome." ''Civil Rights Journal'', vol. 6, no. 1, 2002, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-Soviet states==
[[Crimean Tatars]] are an indigenous people of Crimea with clearly established pre-Golden Horde Scythian, Greek, and [[Goths|Goth]] roots, but authorities and nativists long have treated them as perpetual foreigners. When Crimean Tatars [[deportation of the Crimean Tatars|who had been forcibly exiled in the Stalin era]] attempted to return to Crimea before [[perestroika]], they were frequently met with severe hostility by officials who took violent measures to keep them out and had orders to prevent them from returning to their native land. Meanwhile, Russian publications referred to deported Crimean Tatars returning to the places of their birth as foreigners.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1jbHAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA82|title=Constructing Ethnopolitics in the Soviet Union: Samizdat, Deprivation and the Rise of Ethnic Nationalism|last=Zisserman-Brodsky|first=Dina|date=2003|publisher=Springer|isbn=9781403973627|pages=82–83|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://comments.ua/politics/341390-vlasti-krima-schitayut-krimskih.html|title=Власти Крыма считают крымских татар диаспорой|date=2012-05-30|website=Комментарии Украина|language=ru|access-date=2019-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Volga Germans]] had citizenship in the Soviet Union and later in the Russian Federation, but also in Germany under [[jus sanguinis]]. [[Nazi Germany]] had a policy of ''[[Heim ins Reich]]'' to encourage them to return to Germany. During World War II they were distrusted as foreigners and many were deported to Siberia. After the [[Fall of the soviet union]] many returned to their ancestral homeland, Germany, where they are often seen as Russians.

==Haitians in the Dominican Republic==
{{See also|Haitians in the Dominican Republic}}

Before 2010, the [[Constitution of the Dominican Republic]] generally granted citizenship to anyone born in the country, except children of diplomats and persons "in transit".&lt;ref name="kirksemple" /&gt; The 2010 constitution was amended to define all undocumented residents as "in transit".&lt;ref name="kirksemple" /&gt; On September 23, 2013, the Dominican Republic Constitutional Court issued a ruling that retroactively applied this definition to 1929,&lt;ref name="randallarchibold"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2013/10/24/world/americas/dominicans-of-haitian-descent-cast-into-legal-limbo-by-court.html|title=Dominicans of Haitian Descent Cast Into Legal Limbo by Court|work=The New York Times|date=24 October 2013|first=Randal C.|last=Archibold}}&lt;/ref&gt; the year Haiti and the Dominican Republic formalized the border.&lt;ref name="rojas"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-dominicanrepublic-citizenship-idUSBRE99B01Z20131012|title=Dominican court ruling renders hundreds of thousands stateless|work=Reuters|date=12 October 2013|first=Ricardo|last=Rojas}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kushner |first1=Jacob |title=Birthright Denied |date=4 September 2015 |url=https://www.momentmag.com/birthright-denied/ |work=Moment Magazine |access-date=12 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The decision stripped Dominican citizenship from about 210,000 people who were born in the Dominican Republic after 1929 but are descended from undocumented immigrants from Haiti.&lt;ref name="rojas" /&gt; Many Haitians born in the Dominican Republic do not have Haitian citizenship and have never been to Haiti;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/2015/06/17/415274544/haitians-face-deportation-from-dominican-republic-as-deadline-nears|title=Haitians Face Deportation From Dominican Republic As Deadline Nears|work=NPR|date=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; hence the decision rendered them at least temporarily [[Statelessness|stateless]].&lt;ref name="kirksemple"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2013/10/18/nyregion/dominican-courts-ruling-on-citizenship-stirs-emotions-in-new-york.html|title=Dominican Court's Ruling on Citizenship Stirs Emotions in New York|work=The New York Times|date=17 October 2013|first=Kirk|last=Semple}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="randallarchibold" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ijdh.org/2013/09/topics/immigration-topics/dominican-court-ruling-strips-haitians-citizenship/|title=DR Court Strips Citizenship from Dominican-born Haitians}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other uses==
In work done by [[Ediberto Roman]] ''The Alien-Citizen Paradox and other Consequences of U.S. Colonialism'',&lt;ref name="Roman, Noncitizen Nationals"&gt;{{cite journal | author-last=Roman | author-first=Ediberto | title=Alien-Citizen Paradox and Other Consequences of U.S. Colonialism | year=1998 | journal=Florida State University Law Review | volume=26 | pages=1–50 | ssrn=1625826 | url=https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1625826#}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ediberto discussed the complexity of the continuum between 'alien' and 'citizen' to describe the status of U.S. noncitizen nationals&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=How does FEMA define non-citizen national and qualified non-citizen? | author=Staff | work=FEMA | url=https://www.fema.gov/node/how-does-fema-define-non-citizen-national-and-qualified-non-citizen | date=May 17, 2022 | access-date=September 24, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[U.S. Territories]] where the residents are at once American nationals, but without the same rights as citizens including but not limited to voting rights, and are otherwise considered foreign despite nationality status.

==Critical responses==
The Asian American Education Project, founded in 2005 by [[Stewart Kwoh]] and aimed at educating students of primary school through secondary school age (in the United States, K-12 grades)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=About Us | website=the Asian American Education Project | author=&lt;!---none cited---&gt; | date=n.d. | access-date=September 14, 2023 | url=https://asianamericanedu.org/about.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; includes dedicated sections on the Perpetual Foreigner Stereotype in the context of Asian Americans. Attempts to deconstruct this and other community-relevant stereotypes have been through movements mandating Asian American studies in an effort to show that members of the community do indeed belong in America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Bellamy-Walker | first=Tat | date=January 18, 2022 | orig-date=January 7, 2022 | title=Schools are starting to mandate Asian American Studies. More could follow suit. | publisher=NBC News |department=NBC Asian America |url=https://www.nbcnews.com/news/asian-america/schools-are-starting-mandate-asian-american-studies-follow-suit-rcna11118 | access-date=September 14, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; Controversially, this has included Florida governor since 2019 [[Ron DeSantis]] who was criticized by the Asian American community for the mandate while simultaneously banning courses on [[institutionalized racism]], one of the fears being the use of Asian American history to promote discrimination against other minorities through an "untruthful representation" including but not limited to highlighting the divisive idea of [[model minority|Asian exceptionalism]] against the wishes of many in the Asian American community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Yam | first=Kimmy | title=DeSantis criticized for mandating Asian American history while banning courses on 'systemic racism' | date=May 17, 2023 | publisher=NBC News |department=NBC Asian America| url=https://www.nbcnews.com/news/asian-america/desantis-criticized-mandating-asian-american-history-banning-courses-s-rcna84972 | access-date=September 14, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; Diversity, equity, and inclusion practitioner and corporate educator Lily Zheng has advocated in her book ''DEI Deconstructed: Your No-Nonsense Guide to Doing the Work and Doing it Right'' for the need for better practices in the field,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Zheng | first=Lily | title=DEI Deconstructed: Your No-Nonsense Guild to Doing the Work and Doing it Right | publisher=Berrett-Koehler Publishers, Inc. | location=Oakland, California, USA | year=2023&lt;!----copyright date---&gt; | isbn=9781523002771 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WmNxEAAAQBAJ }}&lt;/ref&gt; referencing in part the Harvard Business Review article ''Why Diversity Programs Fail'' and the statistics that after many DEI programs were implemented the hiring of all groups except for white men decreased during the surveyed interval.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Dobbin | last2=Kalev | first1=Frank | first2=Alexandra | title=Why Diversity Programs Fail | journal=Harvard Business Review | date=July–August 2016 | access-date=September 14, 2023 | url=https://hbr.org/2016/07/why-diversity-programs-fail}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | page=14 | chapter=Foundation| last=Zheng | first=Lily | title=DEI Deconstructed: Your No-Nonsense Guild to Doing the Work and Doing it Right | publisher=Berrett-Koehler Publishers, Inc. | location=Oakland, California, USA | year=2023&lt;!----copyright date---&gt; | isbn=9781523002771 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WmNxEAAAQBAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A wide variety of art forms including but hardly limited to literature, music, film, and photography have also attempted to grapple in small ways with this stereotype (among others) and provide a place to rework the script of identity and belonging. Some examples include [[Langston Hughes | Langston Hughes']] poem and notable work of the [[Harlem Renaissance]] "[[I, Too]]" which proclaims at the end "I, too, am America".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Hughes | first=Langston | title=I, Too | website=Poetry Foundation | url=https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/47558/i-too | via=The Collected Works of Langston Hughes | date &lt;!---website source date given, the poem is much older---&gt;=2004 | access-date=September 7, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Cheung | first=Floyd | page=189 | chapter=On Recovering Early Asian American Literature | chapter-url=https://scholarworks.smith.edu/eng_books/3/ | title=Asian American Literature in Transition, 1965-1996 | volume=3 | publisher=Cambridge University Press | editor-last=Nadkarni | editor-last2=Schlund-Vials | editor-first=Asha | editor-first2=Cathy J. | year=2021 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HzorEAAAQBAJ | doi=10.1017/9781108920605.012 &lt;!---chapter doi, not book---&gt; | isbn=9781108920605 | s2cid=237883700 | format=online&lt;!---format follows the isbn number's format---&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The American [[Dakota people|Dakota]] writer [[Zitkala-Sa|Zitkála-Šá]] penned the poem ''The Red Man's America'' comments generally on the experiences of [[Indigenous people]] in America as outsiders to "liberty and equality" in the new nation and ends with the plea "give us just human right".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | display-editors=etal |editor-last=Harjo | editor-first=Joy | title=When the Light of the World Was Subdued, Our Songs Came Through: A Norton Anthology of Native Nations Poetry | publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Company | page=104 | chapter=Plains and Mountains | date=2020 | location=New York, NY, USA |isbn=9780393356816 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5Z-6DwAAQBAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; The music anthology [[jazz]]-[[blues]]-[[soul music|soul]] fusion album "[[Asian Americans in music#Asian American Movement|A Grain of Sand: Music for the Struggle by Asians in America]]" first released in 1973,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine | last=Kim | first=Sojin | title=A Grain of Sand: Music for the Struggle by Asians in America | magazine=Smithsonian Folkways Magazine | department=Smithsonian Folkways Recordings | publisher=Smithsonian Institution | url=https://folkways.si.edu/magazine-spring-2011-grain-sand-struggle-asians-america/protest-folk/music/article/smithsonian}}&lt;/ref&gt; sought in part to claim the historical presence of Asian Americans in the United States and evolved from the artist's involvement in the [[Asian American Movement]]. For example, the track ''Wandering Chinaman'' covers the narrator's common experiences with other Americans, from losing his money in the [[Great Depression]] to one of his son's deaths serving in the [[Vietnam War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=roonleng| title=Wandering Chinaman: Chris Kando Iijima, Joanne Nobuka Miyamoto, "Charlie" Chin | website=Genius | url=https://genius.com/Chris-kando-iijima-joanne-nobuko-miyamoto-charlie-chin-wandering-chinaman-lyrics | series=Lyrics}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album also covered a diverse range of other topics, including solidarity with other American communities, including African Americans, Latino/a Americans and Indigenous Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | date=March 20, 2009 | title=Striking a Cord | author=APA Staff | department=International Institute | publisher=University of California, Los Angeles | url=https://international.ucla.edu/institute/article/106074}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine | last=Kim | first=Sojin | title=A Grain of Sand: Music for the Struggle by Asians in America | magazine=Smithsonian Folkways Magazine | department=Smithsonian Folkways Recordings | publisher=Smithsonian Institution | url=https://folkways.si.edu/magazine-spring-2011-grain-sand-struggle-asians-america/protest-folk/music/article/smithsonian}}&lt;/ref&gt; The academic work of literary analysis ''LatinAsian Cartographies''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Thananopavarn | first=Susan | title=LatinAsian Cartographies: History, Writing, and the National Imaginary | publisher=Rutgers University Press | date=March 19, 2018 | isbn=9780813589848 &lt;!---paperback edition---&gt; | url=https://www.rutgersuniversitypress.org/book-details/9780813589848}}&lt;/ref&gt; by Susan Thananopavarn argues for the importance of both Latina/o and Asian American writers in illuminating how American national identity has been constructed historically and continues to be constructed to this day. Photographer Andrew Kung and creative director Kathleen Namgung visually explore the concept of exploring Asian American belonging in everyday American spaces in the collection titled "Perpetual Foreigner".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Tham | first=Dan Q. | title='Perpetual foreigner': Photos explore Asian American belonging in everyday spaces | date=May 27, 2021 | access-date=September 14, 2023 | publisher=CNN | series=Hyphenated | url=https://www.cnn.com/style/article/andrew-kung-perpetual-foreigner-hyphenated/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine | author-last=Tam | author-first=Arthur | title=This Powerful New Photo Series Reflects on the Asian American Experience | date=August 11, 2021 | magazine=AnOther | access-date=September 25, 2023 | url=https://www.anothermag.com/art-photography/13495/this-powerful-new-photo-series-reflects-on-the-asian-american-experience}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine | author-last=Fulleylove | author-first=Rebecca | title=Photo series Perpetual Foreigner reflects on the Asian American experience | magazine=Creative Review | date=June 9, 2021 | url=https://www.creativereview.co.uk/perpetual-foreigner-andrew-kung-kathleen-namgung-photography/ | access-date=September 25, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Covering the topic of the complexity of identity in then [[French North Africa]] during [[World War II]], the French film [[Days of Glory (2006 film)|Days of Glory]] by the director [[Rachid Bouchareb]] depicts the struggle of North Africans who were fighting for a country they had never seen, were a part of yet separate within the structure of [[colonialism|colonial rule]], and not given the same privileges as other French soldiers, including the continued denial of [[war pension]]s until at least partial recognition after the film's release.

In her review of the film ''[[Minari (film)|Minari]]'', American author, journalist and vice-chair for the board of Christians for Social Action Kathy KyoungAh Khang reflected on her own story where immigration was learned as part of her family's past rather than present reality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newsletter | last=Khang | first=Kathy KyoungAh | title=Journeying with "Minari": a reflection on the film | date=February 18, 2021 | magazine=Christians for Social Action | url=https://christiansforsocialaction.org/resource/minari-film | access-date=September 14, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; in further reflection, she states:

{{Blockquote|"While constant reminders that I am not a 'real' American are exhausting and dangerous because they feed anti-Asian racism and xenophobia, the flipside is that God and I both know my belovedness doesn't rely on how American or white I become but rather on how God sees me... The practices of communal worship, communion, and even prayers that are spoken in different languages across the ages bind us together and tell a story of faith. We pray words that Jesus spoke more than 2,000 years ago, and in doing so we embrace, remember, and build our lives on the lived experiences of a Jewish refugee, and that matters – or at least it should."|Kathy KyoungAh Khang}}

The Canadian YouTube video essay channel ''Accented Cinema'' has commented on this stereotype in some videos, most notably in his video essay on the blockbuster American movie ''[[Shang-Chi (film)|Shang-Chi]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite AV media | author=Accented Cinema | date=September 15, 2021 &lt;!---upload date as cited by YouTube---&gt; | website=YouTube | title=Shang-Chi and the Perpetual Foreigners &lt;!----all quotes in this section come from this video essay---&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; stating that although the film broke new ground for Asians in Hollywood in many ways, especially in the beginning, the second arc where the main protagonists travel to China is "more about coming home" where "the American side of [[Shang-Chi | Shang-Chi's]] Asian American identity no longer matters". Drawing partly on his own experiences in [[Montreal]] where speaking with a classmate from China would elicit 'you are in [[Quebec]], we speak French here' and regular 'go back to China' comments reflected that "my culture, my language, and my skin color are not welcome here" and in visiting China where "Chinese people would instantly recognize me as someone from outside." He goes on further "I was really hoping it was a story about a man being sandwiched between a world that doesn't welcome him and one that doesn't love him anymore" as this would reflect experiences common to many people of Asian heritage in North America. Ultimately he concludes that the film was in general "more eager to represent China than Asian Americans".

Furthermore, as noted in the video essay ''When Hollywood Speaks Chinese, I Cringe'' on the topic of the use of [[Chinese languages]] in Hollywood movies&lt;ref&gt;{{cite AV media | author=Accented Cinema | date=January 5, 2022 &lt;!---upload date as cited by YouTube---&gt; | website=YouTube | title=When Hollywood Speaks Chinese, I Cringe &lt;!---all quotes in this section come from this essay unless supporting material is otherwise noted---&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; he goes on to mention the lack of acknowledgment for the development of regional dialectal differences in North American Cantonese (and also in Australian Cantonese) speakers&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Eje | first=Jefbeck | title=Cantonese Accent: 10 Unique Regional Differences To Know | website=Ling | url=https://ling-app.com/yue/cantonese-accent | date=July 18, 2023 | access-date=September 7, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; as the language as part of the American story:

{{Blockquote|"We've previously talked about the perpetual foreigner trope on this channel and much of the Chinese language stereotypes stem from this trope. Chinese languages are perceived as 'foreign' and 'exotic'. It makes people, including filmmakers, less likely to want to understand it. But just as [[Chinatown]] is an iconic part of many US cities, the collection of Chinese languages is also a significant part of US culture... Chinese Americans developed their own accents with their own American identities. Treating languages with respect isn't just good film-making, it also better reflects the diversity of the American people and culture. So, here is my plea to all Hollywood film makers. The United States is a very colorful place. Its complexity is precisely why it is beautiful." &lt;!---from the cited video essay by Accented Cinema ---&gt; |''Accented Cinema''}}

In China, growing animosity towards [[Americans]] has equally affected [[Chinese Americans|Americans of Chinese heritage]] as much as other Americans, where "go back to where you came from" is becoming an increasingly common insult, viewed as equally foreign in China as in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Wang | first=Selina | title=Too Chinese for the US, too American for China. Where can Asian Americans like me call home? | work=CNN | url=https://www.cnn.com/2021/04/10/asia/asian-american-racism-us-china-intl-hnk/index.html | date=April 10, 2021 | access-date=September 6, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the [[November 2015 Paris attacks|November 2015 terrorist attacks in Paris]] on French magazine ''[[Charlie Hebdo]]'', the [[Israeli Prime Minister]] in 2015 [[Benjamin Netanyahu]] was known for stating "To all the Jews of France, all the Jews of Europe, I would like to say that Israel is not just the place in whose direction you pray, the State of Israel is your home...All Jews who want to immigrate to Israel will be welcomed here warmly and with open arms" and in a separate speech "Jews have a right to live in many countries...But I believe they know deep down in their hearts that they have only one country, the State of Israel". These comments prompted partial commentary by some Jewish European citizens due to the divisive implication that any other place a Jewish person may choose to call home isn't really home at all and critiquing such use of Jewishness for the nationalistic ends of Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Klug | first=Brain | title=Symposium on the Arab and Jewish Questions | url=https://contendingmodernities.nd.edu/theorizing-modernities/unasking-europes-jewish-question | institution=University of Notre Dame Keough School of Global Affairs | series=Contending Modernities | &lt;!---was unsure how to put this here, the article consists of unhyperlinked sections, the title of which makes for easier navigation to the relevant points---&gt;at=Section 2 "Europe and the Jewish Question" | date=September 16, 2021 | access-date=September 6, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning in the 1950s and ending roughly in 1984, [[North Korea]] targeted [[Zainichi Korean|ethnic Koreans living in Japan]] to emigrate with promises of a "paradise on earth"&lt;ref name="Bangkok Post, N. Korea"&gt;{{cite news | author=AFP | work=Bangkok Post | title='Paradise on Earth': Ghost of N. Korea propaganda still haunts | date=February 21, 2019 | access-date=September 6, 2023 | url=https://www.bangkokpost.com/world/1632646 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!---following sentences up until Yang Yong-hi's films come from this source---&gt;. Approximately 90,000 people moved from Japan to North Korea in the intervening years. This has allegedly included the cooperation of the Red Cross Societies in Japan and sponsorship by the controversial organization [[Chongryon]].&lt;ref name="Bangkok Post, N. Korea"&gt;{{cite news | author=AFP | work=Bangkok Post | title='Paradise on Earth': Ghost of N. Korea propaganda still haunts | date=February 21, 2019 | access-date=September 6, 2023 | url=https://www.bangkokpost.com/world/1632646 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sentiment amongst the [[Zainichi Koreans]] was not helped by the stripping of Japanese nationality by contemporary policy makers or [[Imperial Japanese|Imperial Japan's]] policies that at times included forced deportation of Koreans to Japan during World War II. In looking back on the incident, Harunori Kojima, a former head of the repatriation support office remarked "I was actively involved in the project, believing it was something positive. But as a result, I led people into Hell".&lt;ref name="Bangkok Post, N. Korea"&gt;{{cite news | author=AFP | work=Bangkok Post | title='Paradise on Earth': Ghost of N. Korea propaganda still haunts | date=February 21, 2019 | access-date=September 6, 2023 | url=https://www.bangkokpost.com/world/1632646 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Film director and author [[Yang Yong-hi]] has made several movies regarding her family's personal experiences with these events as a [[Zainichi Korean]] family torn between living in Japan and returning to Korea. Through her films ''[[Dear Pyongyang]]'' (and her book of the same name that expands on the themes of the movie), ''Sona, the Other Myself'' and ''[[Our Homeland]]'' she explores the propaganda of North Korea at the time, her father's strong ideological beliefs, his decision to send his three sons to North Korea, the lasting toll this decision has had on her family, and explores her perspective on the concept of homeland. She states in an interview with [[Korea JoongAng Daily]], "I can't wear any T-shirts bearing a country's flag. I am almost allergic to that. In the movie, homeland is a place, not a specific country...I chose the word as a title because I also want to search for a place where I can call home."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Park | first=Eun-jee | title='Our Homeland' a story of repatriation, reunion | work=Korea JoongAng Daily | date=October 11, 2012 | access-date=September 25, 2023 | url=https://koreajoongangdaily.joins.com/2012/10/11/artsDesign/Our-Homeland-a-story-of-repatriation-reunion/2960674.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Allosemitism]]
* [[Armenian genocide]]
* [[Nuremberg Laws]]
* [[Joseph Stalin and antisemitism]]
* [[Koreans in Japan]]
* [[Laowai]]
* [[Pendatang asing]]
* [[Right of return]]
* [[Citizenship]]
* [[Nationality]]
* [[Rootless cosmopolitan]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==

===Academic books===
* {{cite book|last=Kasimis|first=Demetra|title=The Perpetual Immigrant and the Limits of Athenian Democracy|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9781107052437|year=2018|location=New York|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RY1HtQEACAAJ | oclc=1030904084 | doi=10.1017/9781107280571|s2cid=158074459 }}
* {{cite book | last=Parker | first=Kunal M. | title=Making Foreigners: Immigration and Citizenship Law in America, 1600-2000 | publisher=Cambridge University Press | location=New York, NY, USA | url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/making-foreigners/B3D2569D364C9399364ADFAF15D4D98A | date=5 September 2015 &lt;!---first published date---&gt; | edition=1st | oclc=904400075 | isbn=9781107698512 | doi=10.1017/CBO9781139343282}}
* {{cite book | author-last=Kılınç | author-first=Ramazan | title=Alien Citizens: The State and Religious Minorities in Turkey and France | series= Cambridge Studies in Social Theory, Religion and Politics | publisher=Cambridge University Press | isbn= 9781108692649 | doi=10.1017/9781108692649 | date=September 2019 | s2cid=204426327 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rYK0DwAAQBAJ | oclc=1264363873}}
* {{cite book | editor-last=Lawrance | editor-last2=Stevens | editor-first=Benjamin N. | editor-first2=Jacqueline | title=Citizenship in Question: Evidentiary Birthright and Statelessness | date=February 2017 | publisher=Duke University Press | isbn=9780822362913 | url=https://www.dukeupress.edu/citizenship-in-question | oclc=945583033}}
* {{cite book | last=Frost | first=Linda | title=Never One Nation: Freaks, Savages, and Whiteness in U.S. Popular Culture, 1850-1877 | publisher=University of Minnesota Press | year=2005 | isbn=9780816644902 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bf0RHKWK82sC | oclc=56686376}}
*{{cite book | author-last=Thananopavarn | author-first=Susan | title=LatinAsian Cartographies: History, Writing, and the National Imaginary | date=Mar 19, 2018 | series=Latinidad: Transnational Cultures in the United States | publisher=Rutgers University Press | isbn=9780813589848 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=E0xODwAAQBAJ | oclc=982445252}}
* {{cite book | author-last=Ben Rafael | author-first=Eliezer | chapter=2 Antisemitism and Allosemitism | date=2014 | title=Confronting Allosemitism in Europe: The Case of Belgium Jews | pages=18–35 | doi=10.1163/9789004274068_003 | chapter-url=https://brill.com/display/book/9789004274068/B9789004274068_003.xml | isbn=9789004274068 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9YeOAwAAQBAJ | oclc=879947711 | publisher=Brill}}

===Online readings===
* {{cite web | last=Klug | first=Brain | series=Symposium on the Arab and Jewish Questions | title=Unasking Europe's Jewish Question |  url=https://contendingmodernities.nd.edu/theorizing-modernities/unasking-europes-jewish-question | institution=University of Notre Dame Keough School of Global Affairs | website=Contending Modernities | date=September 16, 2021}}
* {{cite web | author=&lt;!---none cited---&gt; | title=Allosemitism (noun) - Jews as the perpetual 'other'| work=Jewish Journal | date=August 7, 2008 | url=https://jewishjournal.com/news/worldwide/65224/}}&lt;!---if thinking of deleting this, please read article before doing so--I didn't come up with the title, it is more of a discussion than a pure definitional entry----&gt;

===Background===
* {{cite web | last=Curle | first=Clint| title=Us vs. Them: The process of othering | publisher=Canadian Museum for Human Rights | date=January 24, 2020&lt;!---last update date---&gt; | url=https://humanrights.ca/story/us-vs-them-process-othering}}

===Children's books===
* {{cite book | author-last=Loh-Hagan | author-first=Virginia | title=What is the Forever Foreigner Stereotype? | isbn=9781668900505 | date=January 1, 2022 | publisher=Cherry Lake Publishing | series=21st Century Skills Library}}

==External links==
* {{cite web | title=Perpetual Foreigner | website= Asian American Education Project | url=https://asianamericanedu.org/perpetualforeigner.html}}

{{Discrimination}}
{{authority control}}

&lt;!---Anti-Christian sentiment is discussed in Alien Citizens by Ramazan Kılınç with respect to Turkey where Christianity is a religious minority---&gt;

[[Category:Anti-Chinese sentiment in the United States]]
[[Category:Anti-Asian sentiment in the United States]]
[[Category:Anti-indigenous racism]]
[[Category:Anti-Indian sentiment]]
[[Category:Anti-Islam sentiment]]
[[Category:Anti-Christian sentiment]]
[[Category:Anti-immigration politics in the United States]]
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:Asian-Australian issues]]
[[Category:Citizenship]]
[[Category:Ethnic and racial stereotypes in the United States]]
[[Category:Racism in the United States]]
[[Category:Race legislation in the United States]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Stereotypes of black people]]
[[Category:White supremacy]]
[[Category:Xenophobia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>