<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112085736|87306741" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34141" pageid="34141" ns="0" title="Xenophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T00:09:17Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{wiktionarypar|xenophobia}}
'''Xenophobia''' denotes a [[phobic attitude]] towards strangers or of the unknown. It comes from the [[Greek language|Greek]] words ξένος (''xenos''), meaning "foreigner," "stranger," and φόβος (''phobos''), meaning "fear."  The term is typically used to describe fear or dislike of [[alien (law)|foreigner]]s or in general of people different from one's self. For example, [[racism]] is sometimes described as a form of xenophobia, but in most cases racism has nothing to do with a real [[phobia]].  Xenophobia implies a belief that the target is in some way foreign. Prejudice against women cannot be considered xenophobic in this sense, except in the limited case of all-male clubs or institutions.  The term [[xenophilia]] is used for the opposite behavior, attraction to or love for foreign persons. 

The [[American Psychiatric Association]]'s [[DSM-IV|Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]], 4th edition ("DSM-IV") includes in its description of a [[phobia]] an "intense anxiety" which follows exposure to the "object of the phobia, either in real life or via imagination or video..." For xenophobia there are two main objects of the phobia. The first is a population group present within a society, which is  not considered part of that society. Often they are recent [[immigration|immigrants]], but xenophobia may be directed against a group which has been present for centuries. This form of xenophobia can elicit or facilitate hostile and violent reactions, such as mass expulsion of immigrants, or in the worst case, [[genocide]].

The second form of xenophobia is primarily cultural, and the objects of the phobia are cultural elements which are considered alien. All cultures are subject to external influences, but cultural xenophobia is often narrowly directed, for instance at foreign loan words in a national language. It rarely leads to aggression against persons, but can result in political campaigns for cultural or linguistic purification. [[Isolationism]], a general aversion of foreign affairs, is not accurately described as xenophobia.  Additionally, in the world of [[science fiction]], xenophobia usually refers to a fear or hatred of [[extraterrestrial]] cultures or beings.
&lt;!-- Xenophobia was a major problem after [[World War I]] when returning soldiers found themselves competing for jobs and housing with foreigners. This led to riots, racial tensions, etc.. (in the US?? - citation needed) --&gt;

==External links==

* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A223859 h2g2 Xenophobia Edited Guide Entry]

==See also==
* [[Discrimination]]
* [[Exophilia]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Nativism]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Sinophobia]]
* [[Xenophily]]
* [[Xenology]]
* [[Xenophobe]]

[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]

[[bg:Ксенофобия]]
[[cs:Xenofobie]]
[[da:Xenofobi]]
[[de:Xenophobie]]
[[es:Xenofobia]]
[[eo:Ksenofobio]]
[[eu:Xenofobia]]
[[fr:Xénophobie]]
[[hr:Ksenofobija]]
[[id:Xenofobia]]
[[it:Xenofobia]]
[[he:שנאת זרים]]
[[ka:ქსენოფობია]]
[[hu:Xenofóbia]]
[[nl:Xenofobie]]
[[ja:外国人恐怖症]]
[[no:Xenofobi]]
[[pl:Ksenofobia]]
[[pt:Xenofobia]]
[[ro:Xenofobie]]
[[ru:Ксенофобия]]
[[fi:Ksenofobia]]
[[sv:Främlingsfientlighet]]
[[tr:Zenofobi]]
[[uk:Ксенофобія]]

{{psych-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>