<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141113184227|633699317" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34141" pageid="34141" ns="0" title="Xenophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-19T00:35:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{for|the video game|Xenophobe (video game)}}
{{Refimprove|article|date=August 2013}}

'''Xenophobia''' (a form of discrimination) is the unreasoned fear of that which is perceived to be foreign or strange.&lt;ref&gt;http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/xenophobia?q=xenophobia&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/xenophobia&lt;/ref&gt; It comes from the [[Greek language|Greek]] words ξένος (''xenos''), meaning "strange", "foreigner", and φόβος (''phobos''), meaning "fear".&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Standard English Dictionary' (OED). Oxford Press, 2004, CDROM version.&lt;/ref&gt; Xenophobia can manifest itself in many ways involving the relations and perceptions of an [[ingroup]] towards an [[Outgroup (sociology)|outgroup]], including a fear of losing identity, suspicion of its activities, aggression, and desire to eliminate its presence to secure a presumed purity.&lt;ref&gt;Guido Bolaffi. ''Dictionary of race, ethnicity and culture''. SAGE Publications Ltd., 2003. Pp. 332.&lt;/ref&gt; Xenophobia can also be exhibited in the form of an "uncritical exaltation of another culture" in which a culture is ascribed "an unreal, stereotyped and exotic quality".&lt;ref&gt;Guido Bolaffi. ''Dictionary of race, ethnicity and culture''. SAGE Publications Ltd., 2003. Pp. 332.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vienna Declaration and Programme of Action]] urges all governments to take immediate measures and to develop strong policies to prevent and combat all forms and manifestations of racism, xenophobia or related intolerance, where necessary by enactment of appropriate legislation including penal measure.&lt;ref&gt;[[Vienna Declaration and Programme of Action]], Part II para 20&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
Dictionary definitions of ''xenophobia'' include: deep-rooted, irrational hatred towards foreigners (Oxford English Dictionary; OED),
unreasonable fear or hatred of the unfamiliar (Webster's).&lt;ref&gt;Webster's New Universal Unabridged Dictionary, Dorset and Baber, Simon and Schuster&lt;/ref&gt;

==Two forms==
The first is a population group present within a [[society]] that is not considered part of that society.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} Often they are recent [[immigration|immigrants]], but xenophobia may be directed against a group which has been present for centuries, or became part of this society through conquest and territorial expansion. This form of xenophobia can elicit or facilitate hostile and violent reactions, such as mass expulsion of immigrants, [[pogroms]] or in other cases, [[genocide]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2013}}

The second form of xenophobia is primarily cultural, and the objects of the phobia are cultural elements which are considered alien. All cultures are subject to external influences, but cultural xenophobia is often narrowly directed, for instance, at foreign [[loan words]] in a national language. It rarely leads to aggression against individual persons, but can result in political campaigns for cultural or linguistic purification. In addition, entirely xenophobic societies tend not to be open to interactions from anything "outside" themselves, resulting in [[isolationism]] that can further increase xenophobia.{{Citation needed|date=August 2013}}

==Causes==
The following are ways one would develop a general and more often a specific type of xenophobia:{{OR|date=August 2013}}

* A physically, emotional, or economically negative experience with a particular group which is then over-generalized to all members of that group.
* [[Classical conditioning]], that is when someone is conditioned to having a fear or repulse from aliens generally, or, from specific group. Ways to instill it would be [[dehumanization]], mostly by [[propaganda]], for example: a video containing group members shown distorted, erroneous, and in proportional phases of [[Horror and terror|horror]] sounding.
*[[imitation|Imitating]] others, mainly those that are close to the [[individual]], or, in many cases, societal norms of a nation.

==See also==
* [[Chauvinism]]
* [[Ethnocentrism]]
* [[List of anti-cultural, anti-national, and anti-ethnic terms]]
* [[List of phobias]]
* [[Xenophily]]
* [[Xenocentrism]]
* [[Xenophobia in South Africa]]
* [[European Commission against Racism and Intolerance]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Xenophobia}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Ethnicity}}
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Xenophobia]]
[[Category:Racism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>