<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121020075331|518841045" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34141" pageid="34141" ns="0" title="Xenophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-10-21T01:46:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{dablink|For the video game, see [[Xenophobe (video game)]].}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Xenophobia''' is a dislike or fear of people from other countries or of that which is foreign or strange.  Some definitions suggest xenophobia as arising from irrationality or unreason.&lt;ref&gt;http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/xenophobia?q=xenophobia&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/xenophobia&lt;/ref&gt; It comes from the [[Greek language|Greek]] words ξένος (''xenos''), meaning "stranger," "foreigner," and φόβος (''phobos''), meaning "fear."&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Standard English Dictionary' (OED). Oxford Press, 2004, CDROM version.&lt;/ref&gt;

Xenophobia can manifest itself in many ways involving the relations and perceptions of an [[ingroup]] towards an [[Outgroup (sociology)|outgroup]], including a fear of losing identity, suspicion of its activities, aggression, and desire to eliminate its presence to secure a presumed purity.&lt;ref&gt;Guido Bolaffi. ''Dictionary of race, ethnicity and culture''. SAGE Publications Ltd., 2003. Pp. 332.&lt;/ref&gt; Xenophobia can also be exhibited in the form of an "uncritical exaltation of another culture" in which a culture is ascribed "an unreal, stereotyped and exotic quality".&lt;ref&gt;Guido Bolaffi. ''Dictionary of race, ethnicity and culture''. SAGE Publications Ltd., 2003. Pp. 332.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vienna Declaration and Programme of Action]] urges all governments to take immediate measures and to develop strong policies to prevent and combat all forms and minifestations of racism, xenophobia or related intolerance, where necessary by enactment of appropriate legislation including penal measure.&lt;ref&gt;[[Vienna Declaration and Programme of Action]], Part II para 20&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
Dictionary definitions of ''xenophobia'' include: deep-rooted, irrational hatred towards foreigners (Oxford English Dictionary; OED),
unreasonable fear or hatred of the unfamiliar.(Webster's)&lt;ref&gt;Webster's New Universal Unabridged Dictionary, Dorset and Baber, Simon and Schuster&lt;/ref&gt;

A xenophobic person has to genuinely think or believe at some level that the target is in fact a foreigner. This arguably separates xenophobia from ordinary [[prejudice]]. In various contexts, the terms "xenophobia" and "[[racism]]" seem to be used interchangeably, though they can have wholly different meanings (xenophobia can be based on various aspects, racism being based solely on [[ethnicity]], and [[ancestry]]). Xenophobia can also be directed simply to anyone outside a [[culture]]. Basically, a completely biased opinion regarding foreign matters.

==Two forms==
The first is a population group present within a [[society]] that is not considered part of that society.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} Often they are recent [[immigration|immigrants]], but xenophobia may be directed against a group which has been present for centuries, or became part of this society through conquest and territorial expansion. This form of xenophobia can elicit or facilitate hostile and violent reactions, such as mass expulsion of immigrants, [[pogroms]] or in other cases, [[genocide]].

The second form of xenophobia is primarily cultural, and the objects of the phobia are cultural elements which are considered alien. All cultures are subject to external influences, but cultural xenophobia is often narrowly directed, for instance, at foreign [[loan words]] in a national language. It rarely leads to aggression against individual persons, but can result in political campaigns for cultural or linguistic purification. In addition, entire xenophobic societies tend not to be open to interactions from anything "outside" themselves, resulting in [[isolationism]] that can further increase xenophobia.

==Ways of acquiring==
The following are ways one would develop a general, and more often a specific type of Xenophobia:

*bad emotional experience with other groups or specific alien populist group.
*allegedly rational, or, analytical reasons for the revulsion.
*[[Classical conditioning]], that is when someone is conditioned to having a fear or repulse from aliens generally, or, from specific group. ways to instill it would be [[Dehumanization]], mostly by [[propaganda]], for example: a video containing group members shown distorted, erroneous, and in proportional [[phase]]s of [[Horror and terror|horror]] sounding.
*[[imitation|imitating]] others, mainly these that are close to the [[individual]], or, in many cases, societal norms of a nation.

==See also==
* [[Criticism of multiculturalism]]
* [[Opposition to immigration]]
* [[Chauvinism]]
* [[Ethnocentrism]]
* [[List of phobias]]
* [[Nativism (politics)|Nativism]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Xenophily]]
* [[Xenocentrism]]
* [[European Commission against Racism and Intolerance]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Ethnicity}}
{{Commons category|Xenophobia}}

[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

[[af:Xenofobie]]
[[ar:كراهية الأجانب]]
[[az:Ksenofobiya]]
[[be:Ксенафобія]]
[[bg:Ксенофобия]]
[[ca:Xenofòbia]]
[[cs:Xenofobie]]
[[da:Xenofobi]]
[[de:Fremdenfeindlichkeit]]
[[et:Ksenofoobia]]
[[el:Ξενοφοβία]]
[[es:Xenofobia]]
[[eo:Ksenofobio]]
[[eu:Xenofobia]]
[[fa:بیگانه‌هراسی]]
[[fr:Xénophobie]]
[[gl:Xenofobia]]
[[ko:외국인 혐오증]]
[[hi:अज्ञातव्यक्तिभीति]]
[[hr:Ksenofobija]]
[[id:Xenofobia]]
[[is:Útlendingahatur]]
[[it:Xenofobia]]
[[he:שנאת זרים]]
[[ka:ქსენოფობია]]
[[kk:Үргедектік]]
[[la:Xenophobia]]
[[lt:Ksenofobija]]
[[hu:Xenofóbia]]
[[nl:Xenofobie]]
[[ja:外国人嫌悪]]
[[no:Xenofobi]]
[[nn:Xenofobi]]
[[pl:Ksenofobia]]
[[pt:Xenofobia]]
[[ro:Xenofobie]]
[[ru:Ксенофобия]]
[[simple:Xenophobia]]
[[sk:Xenofóbia]]
[[sl:Ksenofobija]]
[[sr:Ксенофобија]]
[[fi:Ksenofobia]]
[[sv:Främlingsfientlighet]]
[[tl:Xenopobya]]
[[te:జెనోఫోబియా]]
[[th:อาการกลัวคนแปลกหน้า]]
[[tr:Zenofobi]]
[[uk:Ксенофобія]]
[[zh:仇外]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>