<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091102211808|323545462" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34141" pageid="34141" ns="0" title="Xenophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-02T21:24:27Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Article issues| article =February 2009
| globalize = December 2008
| POV = November 2008
| recent = May 2008
| refimprove = December 2008
}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Xenophobia''' is a dislike and/or fear of that which is unknown or different from oneself. It comes from the [[Greek language|Greek]] words ξένος (''xenos''), meaning "stranger," "foreigner" and φόβος (''phobos''), meaning "fear." The term is typically used to describe a fear or dislike of [[alien (law)|foreigners]] or of people significantly different from oneself, usually in the context of visibly differentiated [[Minority Group#Racial or ethnic minorities|minorities]].{{Fact|date=July 2009}}

==General==
[[Image:Npdplakat2008.jpg|thumb|200px|left|A political poster of the [[far right]] [[National Democratic Party of Germany]]. The text reads, "We clean up".]]

According to the ''Oxford English Dictionary'' (OED), the word '''xenophobia''' consists of two parts: ''xeno'' (a combining form meaning "guest, stranger, person that looks different, foreigner") and ''phobia'', ("fear, horror or aversion, especially if morbid").&lt;ref&gt; Oxford English Dictionary' (OED). Oxford Press, 1971, eighteenth printing 1979.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is more broadly defined in the ''Dictionary of Psychology'' "a fear of strangers". &lt;ref&gt;Dictionary of Psychology, Chapman, Dell Publishing, 1975 fifth printing 1979. &lt;/ref&gt; As defined by the OED, it can mean a fear of or aversion to, not only persons from other countries, but other cultures, subcultures and subsets of belief systems; in short, anyone who meets any list of criteria about their origin, religion, personal beliefs, habits, language, orientations, or any other criteria. While some will state that the "target" group is a set of persons not accepted by the society, in reality only the phobic person need hold the belief that the target group is not (or should not be) accepted by society. While the phobic person is aware of the aversion (even hatred) of the target group, they may not identify it or accept it as a fear.

As with all [[phobias]], a xenophobic person has to genuinely think or believe at some level that the target is in fact a foreigner. This arguably separates xenophobia from [[racism]] and ordinary [[prejudice]] in that someone of a different race does not necessarily have to be of a different [[nationality]]. In various contexts, the terms "xenophobia" and "racism" seem to be used interchangeably, though they can have wholly different meanings (xenophobia can be based on various aspects, racism being based solely on [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]] and [[ancestry]]).

Xenophobia has two main objects: 

The first is a population group present within a [[society]] that is not considered part of that society. Often they are recent [[immigration|immigrants]], but xenophobia may be directed against a group which has been present for centuries, or became part of this society through conquest and territorial expansion. This form of xenophobia can elicit or facilitate hostile and violent reactions, such as mass expulsion of immigrants, [[pogroms]] or in the worst case, [[genocide]].

The second form of xenophobia is primarily cultural, and the objects of the phobia are cultural elements which are considered alien. All cultures are subject to external influences, but cultural xenophobia is often narrowly directed, for instance, at foreign [[loan words]] in a national language. It rarely leads to aggression against individual persons, but can result in political campaigns for cultural or linguistic purification. [[Isolationism]], a general aversion of foreign affairs, is not accurately described as xenophobia.

==See also==
* [[Racism by country]]
* [[Discrimination]]
* [[Ethnic cleansing]]
* [[Genocide]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[List of phobias]]
* [[List of xenophobic terms]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Nativism]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Xenophily]]
* [[Xenophobe]]
* [[Race and crime]]
* [[Tribalism]]
* [[Xenocentrism]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Template group
|list =
{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}
}}

[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

[[af:Xenofobie]]
[[ar:كره الأجانب]]
[[az:Ksenofobiya]]
[[bg:Ксенофобия]]
[[ca:Xenofòbia]]
[[cs:Xenofobie]]
[[da:Xenofobi]]
[[de:Xenophobie]]
[[et:Ksenofoobia]]
[[es:Xenofobia]]
[[eo:Ksenofobio]]
[[eu:Xenofobia]]
[[fa:بیگانه هراسی]]
[[fr:Xénophobie]]
[[hr:Ksenofobija]]
[[id:Xenofobia]]
[[is:Útlendingahatur]]
[[it:Xenofobia]]
[[he:שנאת זרים]]
[[ka:ქსენოფობია]]
[[lt:Ksenofobija]]
[[hu:Xenofóbia]]
[[nl:Xenofobie]]
[[ja:外国人嫌悪]]
[[no:Xenofobi]]
[[pl:Ksenofobia]]
[[pt:Xenofobia]]
[[ro:Xenofobie]]
[[ru:Ксенофобия]]
[[simple:Xenophobia]]
[[sk:Xenofóbia]]
[[sl:Ksenofobija]]
[[sr:Ксенофобија]]
[[fi:Ksenofobia]]
[[sv:Främlingsfientlighet]]
[[tr:Zenofobi]]
[[uk:Ксенофобія]]
[[zh:仇外]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>