<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111113124522|460433519" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34141" pageid="34141" ns="0" title="Xenophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-13T12:45:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup-rewrite|date=August 2010}}
{{refimprove|date=January 2011}}
{{dablink|For the video game, see [[Xenophobe (video game)]].}}

'''Xenophobia''' is defined as "an unreasonable fear of foreigners or strangers or of that which is foreign or strange".&lt;ref&gt;http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/xenophobia&lt;/ref&gt; It comes from the [[Greek language|Greek]] words ξένος (''xenos''), meaning "stranger," "foreigner" and φόβος (''phobos''), meaning "fear."&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Standard English Dictionary' (OED). Oxford Press, 2004, CDROM version.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
Xenophobia can manifest itself in many ways involving the relations and perceptions of an [[ingroup]] towards an [[Outgroup (sociology)|outgroup]], including a fear of losing identity, suspicion of its activities, aggression, and desire to eliminate its presence to secure a presumed purity.&lt;ref&gt;Guido Bolaffi. ''Dictionary of race, ethnicity and culture''. SAGE Publications Ltd., 2003. Pp. 332.&lt;/ref&gt; Xenophobia can also be exhibited in the form of an "uncritical exaltation of another culture" in which a culture is ascribed "an unreal, stereotyped and exotic quality".&lt;ref&gt;Guido Bolaffi. ''Dictionary of race, ethnicity and culture''. SAGE Publications Ltd., 2003. Pp. 332.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
Dictionary definitions of ''xenophobia'' include: deep-rooted antipathy towards foreigners (Oxford English Dictionary; OED),
unreasonable fear or hatred of the unfamiliar, especially people of other races (Webster's)&lt;ref&gt;Webster's New Universal Unabridged Dictionary, Dorset and Baber, Simon and Schuster, 1983&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Dictionary of Psychology'' defines it  as "a fear of strangers".&lt;ref&gt;Dictionary of Psychology, Chapman, Dell Publishing, 1975 fifth printing 1979.&lt;/ref&gt; As defined by the OED, it can mean a fear of or aversion to, not only people from other countries, but other cultures, subcultures and subsets of belief systems; in short, anyone who meets any list of criteria about their origin, religion, personal beliefs, habits, language, orientations, or any other criteria. While some will state that the "target" group is a set of persons not accepted by the society, in reality only the phobic person need hold the belief that the target group is not (or should not be) accepted by society. While the phobic person is aware of the aversion (even hatred) of the target group, they may not identify it or accept it as a fear.

A clinical definition is:{{Clarify|date=August 2010}} An irrational fear of members of a certain race foreign to one's own, often adjunct and secondary to [[Post Traumatic Stress Disorder]]. Also: One of the attitude groupings characteristic of The Authoritarian Personality.&lt;ref&gt;http://courses.ed.asu.edu/nelsen/edp530/pdf/Lect03Psychoanalysis.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; A Vietnam veteran witnessed members of the [[Viet Cong]] skinning his fellow soldiers alive. He developed hatred of people with Mongol eyelids. In both cases, the xenophobia was adjunct to PTSD.&lt;ref&gt;17 U. Puget Sound L. Rev. 381 (1993-1994), From Agoraphobia to Xenophobia: Phobias and Other Anxiety Disorders under the Americans with Disabilities Act, John M. Casey&lt;/ref&gt;

A xenophobic person has to genuinely think or believe at some level that the target is in fact a foreigner. This arguably separates xenophobia from [[racism]] and ordinary [[prejudice]] in that someone of a different race does not necessarily have to be of a different [[nationality]]. In various contexts, the terms "xenophobia" and "racism" seem to be used interchangeably, though they can have wholly different meanings (xenophobia can be based on various aspects, racism being based solely on [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[ethnicity]], and [[ancestry]]). Xenophobia can also be directed simply to anyone outside a [[culture]], not necessarily one particular race or people.

==Two forms==
The first is a population group present within a [[society]] that is not considered part of that society.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} Often they are recent [[immigration|immigrants]], but xenophobia may be directed against a group which has been present for centuries, or became part of this society through conquest and territorial expansion. This form of xenophobia can elicit or facilitate hostile and violent reactions, such as mass expulsion of immigrants, [[pogroms]] or in other cases, [[genocide]].

The second form of xenophobia is primarily cultural, and the objects of the phobia are cultural elements which are considered alien. All cultures are subject to external influences, but cultural xenophobia is often narrowly directed, for instance, at foreign [[loan words]] in a national language. It rarely leads to aggression against individual persons, but can result in political campaigns for cultural or linguistic purification. In addition, entire xenophobic societies tend not to be open to interactions from anything "outside" themselves, resulting in [[isolationism]] that can further xenophobia.

==See also==

* [[Chauvinism]]
* [[Ethnocentrism]]
* [[List of phobias]]
* [[List of xenophobic terms]]
* [[Nativism]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Xenophily]]
* [[Xenocentrism]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Ethnicity}}
{{Commons category|Xenophobia}}

[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[af:Xenofobie]]
[[ar:كره الأجانب]]
[[az:Ksenofobiya]]
[[bg:Ксенофобия]]
[[ca:Xenofòbia]]
[[cs:Xenofobie]]
[[da:Xenofobi]]
[[de:Fremdenfeindlichkeit]]
[[et:Ksenofoobia]]
[[el:Ξενοφοβία]]
[[es:Xenofobia]]
[[eo:Ksenofobio]]
[[eu:Xenofobia]]
[[fa:بیگانه‌هراسی]]
[[fr:Xénophobie]]
[[gl:Xenofobia]]
[[hi:अज्ञातव्यक्तिभीति]]
[[hr:Ksenofobija]]
[[id:Xenofobia]]
[[is:Útlendingahatur]]
[[it:Xenofobia]]
[[he:שנאת זרים]]
[[ka:ქსენოფობია]]
[[kk:Үргедектік]]
[[la:Xenophobia]]
[[lt:Ksenofobija]]
[[hu:Xenofóbia]]
[[nl:Xenofobie]]
[[ja:外国人嫌悪]]
[[no:Xenofobi]]
[[nn:Xenofobi]]
[[pl:Ksenofobia]]
[[pt:Xenofobia]]
[[ro:Xenofobie]]
[[ru:Ксенофобия]]
[[simple:Xenophobia]]
[[sk:Xenofóbia]]
[[sl:Ksenofobija]]
[[sr:Ксенофобија]]
[[fi:Ksenofobia]]
[[sv:Främlingsfientlighet]]
[[tl:Xenopobya]]
[[te:జెనోఫోబియా]]
[[th:อาการกลัวคนแปลกหน้า]]
[[tr:Zenofobi]]
[[uk:Ксенофобія]]
[[zh:仇外]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>