<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061101050256|84980934" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="505730" pageid="505730" ns="0" title="Cultural assimilation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-04T04:42:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup-date|February 2006}}

'''Cultural assimilation''', or 'assimilation' for short (but that word also had other meanings), is an intense process of consistent integration whereby members of an ethno-cultural group, typically [[immigration|immigrants]], or other [[minority group]]s, are "absorbed" into an established, generally larger community. This presumes a loss of all or many characteristics which make the newcomers different.  A region or society where assimilation is occurring is sometimes referred to as a "'''[[melting pot]]'''."  

==Degrees of choice==
Assimilation may be voluntary, which is usually the case with immigrants, or forced upon a group, as is usually the case with the receiving "host" group or country. Immigration, as held by some, is often thought to be in the interest of the politically and economically powerful elites more than in the interest of the weak (usually motivated by individual 'no choice', not collective goals).  Where national groups are strongly urged to assimilate, there is often much resistance in spite of the use of governmental force.  

If a government puts extreme emphasis on national unity and identity, it may resort, especially in the case of minorities originating from historical foes, to harsh, even extreme measures to 'exterminate' the minority culture, sometimes to the point of considering the only alternative its physical elimination (expulsion or even genocide).

Sometimes there are two contradictory tendencies at work. When a numerical minority and/or less developed culture achieves political power, usually by military conquest, it is in a formal position to impose elements of its culture on the counterpart, which usually happens at least at the start and in 'public' domains such as administration, but often this is more than compensated by a natural tendency for the older, richer culture and/or the law of numbers to see itself imitated by the new masters, e.g. the victorious [[Roman Republic]] adopted more from the [[Hellenistic]] cultures then it imposed in most domains, except such Roman specialities as law and the military.

==Immigration==
[[Immigration]] (also called [[migration]]) is the forced or voluntary movement of a [[people]] or group to another country or region.

==Minority cultures==
Assimilation can have negative implications for national minorities or aboriginal cultures, in that after assimilation the distinctive features of the original culture will be minimized and may disappear altogether. This is especially true in situations where the institutions of the dominant culture initiate programs to assimilate or integrate minority culture.  The assumption of integration, the making into one society, lies behind efforts for [[affirmative action]].

Assimilation is or has been the official [[language policy]] of many countries around the world.

==Assimilation for the individual==
While it is widely held that a given ethnic group may assimilate to its host culture over a period of time, rhetoric espoused by the host culture rarely takes into account the difficulties for the individuals involved. In fact, the question may be asked "is it possible for an individual to assimilate at all, and if so, till what age is it impossible?"

Children born in host countries to ethnic minority parents who have regular association with non-ethnic minority people rarely have trouble assimilating. The problem with this point is that seeing that the child will receive most of its social stimulus from the host culture, the process can hardly be described as "assimilation". 

It may be argued that past occurrences of assimilation are really only occurrences of compatibility of cultures. It is hard to distinguish between situations where a given ethnic group has assimilated and situations where said group has merely become a contributing sector of society. 

Some contemporary scholars of immigration, such as George De Vos, Celia Jaes Falicov, Takeyuki Tsuda, Min Zhou, and Carl L. Bankston III, argue that immigrants and children of immigrants often fit into host societies through ''adaptation'', more selectively than assimilation: they retain or re-shape elements of their ethnic culture depending on how the culture meets their needs in the host society.

===Named cases===
The terms used for such processes usually derive from a name for the group the minority is supposed to be blended into, rather symbolically, e.g.
*[[Americanization]]
*[[Albanisation]]
*[[Anglicisation]]
*[[Arabization]]
*[[Bulgarisation]]
*[[Croatisation]]
*[[Finnicization]]
*[[Germanisation]]
*[[Hellenization]]
*[[Italianization]]
*[[Magyarization]]
*[[Polonization]]
*[[Romanization (cultural)]]
*[[Romanianization]]
*[[Russification]]
*[[Serbianisation]]
*[[Sinhalisation]]
*[[Sinicization]]
*[[Slovakization]]
*[[Thaification]]
*[[Turkification]]

==Religious assimilation==
Assimilation also includes to the (often forced) conversion or secularization of religious members of a minority group, especially Judaism. Until the mid-[[19th century]], most Jews were forced to live in small towns and were restricted from entering universities or high-level professions. The only way to get ahead in the host culture was to abandon their identification with co-religionists and become "assimilated Jews." Well-known assimilated Jews of this period include [[Moses Mendelssohn]], [[Karl Marx]], and [[Sigmund Freud]], who became dissociated with [[Orthodox Judaism]]. In the second half of the [[20th century]], rampant assimilation in the form of Jewish-Christian [[intermarriage]] decimated the ranks of Orthodox Judaism even further. Jewish law ([[Halakha]]) does not recognize children of non-Jewish mothers as Jewish, and further, the children of intermarriage may not be raised with a strong Jewish identity and tend to intermarry themselves.

==See also==
* [[Acculturation]]
* [[Americanization (of Native Americans)]]
* [[Cultural imperialism]]
* [[Cultural appropriation]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Forced conversion]]
* [[Hegemony]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[Language shift]]
* [[Linguicide]]
* [[Media and ethnicity]]
* "[[More Irish than the Irish themselves]]"
* [[Racial integration|Integration]]
*[[Stolen generation]]

==Sources, references and external links==
*[http://www.asian-nation.org/assimilation.shtml Asian-Nation: Asian American Assimilation &amp; Ethnic Identity]
*[http://ambassadors.net/archives/issue19/opinions2.htm From Paris to Cairo: Resistance of the Unacculturated]

[[Category:Cultural assimilation|*]]
[[Category:Cultural geography]]

[[de:Assimilation (Soziologie)]]
[[fr:Rayonnement culturel]]
[[it:Assimilazione culturale]]
[[he:התבוללות]]
[[lt:Asimiliacija (sociologija)]]
[[nl:Assimilatie (sociologie)]]
[[ru:Ассимиляция (этнография)]]
[[sr:Асимилационизам]]
[[sv:Assimilation (sociologi)]]
[[zh:同化]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>