<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051102024716|27129531" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="505730" pageid="505730" ns="0" title="Cultural assimilation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-12T18:40:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{limitedgeographicscope}}
In the [[sociology|social sciences]], '''assimilation''' is the process of integration whereby [[immigration|immigrants]], or other [[minority]] groups, are "absorbed" into a generally larger community. This presumes a loss of all characteristics which make the newcomers different.  A region where assimilation is occurring is sometimes referred to as a "'''[[melting pot]]'''".  

Assimilation can be voluntary, which is usually the case with immigrants, or forced upon a group, as is usually the case with the receiving "host" group. Immigration, as held by some, is generally thought to be in the interest of the politically and economically powerful elites and not in the interest of the weak.  This [[integration]], or "making many into one", is one of the goals of [[affirmative action]].  Where national groups are strongly urged to assimilate, there is often much resistance in spite of the use of governmental force.  

==Immigration==

Socially pressured to adapt, the immigrant is generally the one who takes the steps to integrate the new environment he is in. Learning the language of the country or region, making new friends, new contacts, finding a job or going to school is all that is needed. The adaptation is made more difficult when the immigrant does not speak the language of his or her new home.  Host, or "majority", cultures adapt by accepting newcomers as their own, and often giving them preferential treatment over themselves.  Many times large scale immigration causes political unrest in societies which permit meaningful elections.

==Minority cultures==

Assimilation can have negative implications for national minorities or aboriginal cultures, in that after assimilation the distinctive features of the original culture will be minimized and may disappear altogether. This is especially true in situations where the institutions of the dominant culture initiate programs to assimilate or integrate minority cultures.  The assumption of integration, the making into one society, lies behind efforts for [[affirmative action]].

Assimilation is or has been the official [[language policy]] of many countries around the world.

==Religious assimilation==

Assimilation also refers to the secularization of religious members of a group, especially Judaism. Until the mid-[[19th century]], most Jews were forced to live in small towns and were restricted from entering universities or high-level professions. The only way to get ahead in the host culture was to abandon their identification with co-religionists and become "assimilated Jews." Well-known assimilated Jews of this period include [[Moses Mendelssohn]], [[Karl Marx]], and [[Sigmund Freud]], all of whom rose to prominence because of their dissociation with [[Orthodox Judaism]]. In the [[20th century]], rampant assimilation in the form of Jewish-Christian [[intermarriage]] decimated the ranks of Orthodox Judaism even further. Jewish law ([[Halakha]]) does not recognize children of non-Jewish mothers as Jewish, and further, the children of intermarriage are not raised with a strong Jewish identity and tend to intermarry themselves.

==See also==

*[[Acculturation]]
*[[Hegemony]]
*[[Linguicide]]
*[[Germanization]]
*[[Russification]]
*[[Ukrainization]]
*[[Polonization]]
*[[Americanization]]
*[[Sinicization]]
*[[Media_and_ethnicity]]
*[[Cultural_imperialism]]
[[Category:Sociology]]

==External links==
* [http://www.asian-nation.org/assimilation.shtml Asian-Nation: Asian American Assimilation &amp;amp; Ethnic Identity]

[[he:התבוללות]]
[[lt:Asimiliacija (sociologija)]]
[[nl:Assimilatie (sociologie)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>