<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101113160311|396526808" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7194871" pageid="7194871" ns="0" title="Discrimination against atheists"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-13T17:01:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{atheism2}}
'''Discrimination against atheists''' includes the persecution and discrimination faced by [[atheist]]s and those labelled as atheists in the past and in the current era.  Differing definitions of atheism historically and culturally mean those discriminated against might not be considered truly atheist by modern Western standards.  In constitutional democracies, legal discrimination against atheists is uncommon, but some [[atheism|atheist]]s and atheist groups, particularly those in the [[United States]], have protested laws, regulations and institutions they view as being discriminatory. In some Islamic countries, atheists face discrimination including lack of legal status or even a death sentence in the case of [[apostasy]].

==Ancient times==
Historians including [[Lucien Febvre]] agree atheism in its modern sense did not exist before the end of the seventeenth century.&lt;ref name="davidson"&gt;{{cite book|last=Davidson|first=Nicholas|title=Atheism from the Reformation to the Enlightenment|editor=Michael Hunter; David Wootton|publisher=Oxford University Press|date=1992|pages=55–86|chapter=Unbelief and Atheism In Italy|isbn=9780198227366}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Armstrong |first=Karen |title=A History of God: The 4000-year Quest of Judaism, Christianity, and Islam |publisher=Random House, Inc. |pages=286–87|date=1994|url= http://books.google.com/?id=_n3cCF2I2FUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=A+History+of+God| isbn=9780345384560}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="kelley"&gt;{{cite book|last=Kelley|first=Donald R. |title=Frontiers of History: Historical Inquiry in the Twentieth Century |publisher=Yale University Press|date=2006|pages=115|isbn=9780300120622|url=http://books.google.com/?id=K-wVctit5U8C&amp;pg=PA115}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, as governmental authority rested on the notion of [[divine right]], it was threatened by those who denied the existence of the local god. Philosophers such as [[Plato]] argued atheism was a danger to society and should be punished as a crime.&lt;ref name="gey 250"&gt;{{cite book|last=Gey|first=Steven G.|title=The Cambridge Companion to Atheism|editor=Martin, Michael|publisher=Cambridge University Press|date=2007|chapter=Atheism and the Freedom of Religion|pages=250–253, 260–2 |isbn=9780521842709|url=http://books.google.com/?id=tAeFipOVx4MC&amp;pg=PA250}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Those labeled as atheist, which included early Christians and Muslims, were as a result targeted for legal persecution.&lt;ref name="gey 250"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Armstrong |first=Karen |title=A History of God: The 4000-year Quest of Judaism, Christianity, and Islam |publisher=Random House, Inc. |page=98, 147|date=1994|url= http://books.google.com/?id=_n3cCF2I2FUC&amp;printsec=frontcover|isbn=9780345384560}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Medieval Era and Reformation==
During the [[Middle Ages]], the term "atheist" was used as an insult and applied to a broad range of people, including those who held opposing theological beliefs, as well as suicides, immoral or self-indulgent people, and even opponents of the belief in witchcraft.&lt;ref name="davidson"/&gt;&lt;ref name="laursen"&gt;{{cite book|last=Laursen|first=John Christian |coauthors=Nederman, Cary J.|title=Beyond the Persecuting Society: Religious Toleration Before the Enlightenment  |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|date=1997|pages=142|isbn= 9780812215670|url=http://books.google.com/?id=r2j6ZHgXZWkC&amp;pg=PA142}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Armstrong |first=Karen |title=A History of God: The 4000-year Quest of Judaism, Christianity, and Islam |publisher=Random House, Inc. |pages=286–87|date=1994|url= http://books.google.com/?id=_n3cCF2I2FUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=A+History+of+God |isbn=9780345384560}}&lt;/ref&gt; Atheistic beliefs continued to be seen as threatening to order and society by philosophers such as [[Thomas Aquinas]].  Lawyer and scholar [[Thomas More]] asserted that religious tolerance should be extended to all except those who did not believe in a deity or the immortality of the soul.&lt;ref name="gey 250"/&gt;  Even [[John Locke]], a founder of modern notions of religious liberty, argued that atheists (as well as Catholics and Muslims) should not be granted full citizenship rights.&lt;ref name="gey 250"/&gt;

During the Inquisition, several of those accused of atheism and/or blasphemy met gruesome fates.  These included a priest [[Giulio Cesare Vanini]] who was strangled and burned in 1619 and a Polish nobleman [[Kazimierz Łyszczyński]] who was executed in Warsaw,&lt;ref name="davidson"/&gt;&lt;ref name="brooke"&gt;{{cite book|last= Brooke|first=John Hedley|others= Maclean, Ian |title=Heterodoxy in Early Modern Science and Religion |publisher=Oxford University Press|date=2005|isbn=9780199268979|url=http://books.google.com/?id=W9o_OEvMQTcC&amp;pg=PA66}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kłoczowski |first=Jerzy |title=A History of Polish Christianity |publisher=Cambridge University Press|date=2000 |pages=155|isbn=9780521364294|url=http://books.google.com/?id=ecdye8hk_tgC&amp;pg=PA155}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[Etienne Dolet]], a Frenchman executed in 1546. Though heralded as  atheist martyrs during the nineteenth century, recent scholars hold that the beliefs espoused by Dolet and Vanini are not atheistic in modern terms.&lt;ref name="kelley" /&gt;&lt;ref name="onfray"&gt;{{cite book|last=Onfray|first=Michel|others=Leggatt, Jeremy (translator) |title=Atheist manifesto: the case against Christianity, Judaism, and Islam |publisher=Arcade Publishing|date=2007|pages=24|isbn=9781559708203|url=http://books.google.com/?id=QpEAYMo7pFkC&amp;pg=PA24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="chadwich"&gt;{{cite book|last=Chadwick |first=Owen |title=The Early Reformation on the Continent By |publisher= Oxford University Press|date=2003|isbn=9780199265787|url=http://books.google.com/?id=VR1yNW8mgoEC&amp;pg=PA413}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early modern times==

During the nineteenth century, British atheists, though few in number, were subject to discriminatory practices.&lt;ref name="cookson"&gt;{{cite book | author = Larson, Timothy| chapter= Victorian England | title = Encyclopedia of religious freedom | editor= Cookson, Catharine| publisher = Routledge | location = New York | date = 2003 | pages = | isbn = 0-415-94181-4 | oclc = | doi = | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Those unwilling to swear Christian oaths during judicial proceedings were unable to give evidence in court to obtain justice until the discrimination was ended by Acts passed in 1869 and 1870.&lt;ref name="cookson"/&gt; In addition, the poet [[Percy Bysshe Shelley]] was expelled from the [[University of Oxford]] and denied custody of his two children after publishing a pamphlet on ''[[The Necessity of Atheism]]''.&lt;ref name="gey253" /&gt;  Atheist [[Charles Bradlaugh]] was elected as a [[Member of Parliament#United Kingdom|Member of the British Parliament]] in 1880. He was denied the right to affirm rather than swear his oath of office, and was then denied the ability to swear the oath as other Members objected that he had himself said it would be meaningless. Bradlaugh was re-elected three times before he was finally able to take his seat in 1886 when the Speaker of the House permitted him to take the oath.&lt;ref name="gey253"&gt;{{cite book|last=Gey|first=Steven G.|title=The Cambridge Companion to Atheism|editor=Martin, Michael|publisher=Cambridge University Press|date=2007|chapter=Atheism and the Freedom of Religion|pages=253–255|isbn=9780521842709|url=http://books.google.com/?id=tAeFipOVx4MC&amp;pg=PA253}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Germany during the Nazi era, a 1933 decree stated that "No National Socialist may suffer detriment... on the ground that he does not make any religious profession at all".&lt;ref name="Baynes"/&gt; However, the regime strongly opposed "godless communism",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Christian|title=Disruptive religion: the force of faith in social-movement activism|publisher=Routledge|date=1996|pages=156–57|isbn=9780415914055|url=http://books.google.com/?id=39SoSG4NGAoC&amp;pg=PA156}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Stackelberg|first=Roderick|title=The Routledge Companion to Nazi Germany	|publisher=Routledge|date=2007|pages=136–8|isbn=9780415308601|url=http://books.google.com/?id=cpXIR9yOMuoC&amp;pg=PA136}}&lt;/ref&gt; and most of Germany's atheist and largely left-wing [[freethought]] organizations were banned the same year; some right-wing groups were tolerated by the Nazis until the mid 1930s.&lt;ref name="may"&gt;{{cite book |last= Bock| first= Heike | chapter= Secularization of the modern conduct of life? Reflections on the religiousness of early modern Europe| editor=Hanne May |title=Religiosität in der säkularisierten Welt |publisher=VS Verlag fnr Sozialw |location= |date=2006 |pages= 157|isbn=3-8100-4039-8 |oclc= |url= http://books.google.com/?id=nfQ0pqA53Z8C&amp;pg=PA157|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=kaiser&gt;{{cite book|last=Kaiser|first=Jochen-Christoph|title=Atheismus und religiöse Indifferenz|editor=Christel Gärtner|publisher=VS Verlag|date=2003|volume=Organisierter Atheismus|pages= 122, 124–6|isbn=9783810036391|url=http://books.google.com/?id=YXOr4xQFSJsC&amp;pg=PA124}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a speech made later in 1933, Hitler claimed to have "stamped [atheism] out".&lt;ref name="Baynes"&gt;{{cite book|last=Baynes|first=Norman Hepburn|title=The Speeches of Adolf Hitler, April 1922 – August 1939'|publisher=H. Fertig|date=1969|pages=378|quote= Without pledging ourselves to any particular Confession, we have restored faith to its pre-requisites because we were convinced that the people needs [sic] and requires [sic] this faith. We have therefore undertaken the fight against the atheistic movement, and that not merely with a few theoretical declarations: we have stamped it out. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern era==
===Western countries===

Modern theories of constitutional democracy assume that citizens are intellectually and spiritually autonomous and that governments should leave matters of religious belief to individuals and not coerce religious beliefs using sanctions or benefits.  The constitutions, human rights conventions and the religious liberty jurisprudence of most constitutional democracies provides legal protection of atheists and agnostics.  In addition, freedom of expression provisions and legislation separating church from state also serve to protect the rights of atheists. As a result, open legal discrimination against atheists is not common in most Western countries.&lt;ref name="gey 250" /&gt;

====South and Central America====
{{Expand section|date=May 2010}}

====Europe====
In Europe, atheists are elected to office at high levels without controversy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://ibka.org/en/articles/miz08/politics-religion-usa|title="Most American secularists have few expectations..." An Interview with AAI president Stuart Bechman   |last=Hartmann|first=René|date=March 2008|work=MIZ Magazine|accessdate=2009-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some atheist organizations in Europe have expressed concerns regarding issues of separation of church and state, such as administrative fees for leaving the Church charged in [[Germany]],&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://ibka.org/en/fee-european-court
|title=Fee for leaving church is brought before European Court of Human Rights | I
|publisher=International League of Non-religious and Atheists (IBKA)
|accessdate=2009-03-14}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and sermons being organized by the Swedish parliament.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.jo.se/Page.aspx?MenuId=106&amp;MainMenuId=106&amp;Language=sv&amp;ObjectClass=DynamX_SFS_Decision&amp;Id=2100
|title=Anmälan till JO – Riksdagens ombudsmän
|publisher=www.jo.se
|accessdate=2009-03-14
|last=
|first=
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ireland]] requires religious training from Christian colleges in order to work as a teacher in government funded schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2010/0202/1224263575172.html
|title=Why must agnostics be obliged to teach faith?
|publisher=Irish Times
|accessdate=2010-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Freedom of speech issues, such as discrimination in advertising, are characterized by the [[Atheist Bus Campaign]] in the UK.
In the UK one third of state-funded primary schools are faith based.

====Canada====
{{Expand section|date=April 2010}}
Canadian [[secular humanist]] groups have worked to end the recitation of prayers during government proceedings, viewing them as discriminatory.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.humanistcanada.com/no-prayers-in-ont-legislature
|title=No More Prayers in Legislature
|publisher=www.humanistcanada.com
|accessdate=2009-03-14
|last=
|first=
}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thestar.com/article/423192|title=Stirring up yet another religious storm|last=Hurst|first=Lynda|date=  May 9, 2008 |work=Toronto Star|accessdate=2009-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United States====
Some atheists assert that they are discriminated against in the United States and compare their situation to the discrimination faced by ethnic minorities, [[LGBT]] communities, and women.&lt;ref name="dawkins" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Harris"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.latimes.com/news/opinion/sunday/commentary/la-op-harris24dec24,0,3481836.story?coll=la-sunday-commentary|title= 10 myths – and 10 truths – about atheism|last=Harris|first=Sam|date=December 24, 2006 |work=Los Angeles Times|accessdate=2009-03-12}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="fi-md"&gt;{{cite journal | title = Discrimination against atheists: the facts | author = Downey, Margaret | authorlink = Margaret Downey | journal = [[Free Inquiry]] | volume = 24 | issue = 4 | month = June–July | date = 2004 | pages = 41–43|url= http://www.secularhumanism.org/library/fi/downey_24_4.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ffrf.org/fttoday/1995/december95/zellner.html|title=Deep In The Bible Belt – One Atheist Professor's Experience|last=Zellner|first=William W. |date=December 1995|work=Freethought Today |accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  "Americans still feel it's acceptable to discriminate against atheists in ways considered beyond the pale for other groups," asserted Fred Edwords of the [[American Humanist Association]].&lt;ref name="AHA"&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.americanhumanist.org/press/petestark
|title=Humanists Praise Pete Stark for “Coming Out” as a Nontheist
|publisher=American Humanist
|accessdate=2009-03-17
|last=
|first=
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Other atheists reject these comparisons, arguing that while [[Freedom_of_religion_in_the_United_States#Situation_of_atheists|atheists may face disapproval]] they have not faced significant oppression or discrimination.&lt;ref name="thornton"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/opinion/la-oew-thornton18apr18,0,5841004.story|title=Disliked, not oppressed I may be a reviled atheist, but that doesn't mean I can claim equal victimhood with truly repressed minorities  |last=Thornton|first=Paul|date= April 18, 2007 |work=Los Angeles Times|accessdate=2009-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Grothe|first=D.J.|coauthors=Dacey, Austin|title=Atheism Is Not a Civil Rights Issue|journal=Free Inquiry|volume=24|issue=2|url=http://www.secularhumanism.org/library/fi/grothe-dacey_24_2.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, seven state constitutions officially include religious tests that would effectively prevent atheists from holding public office, and in some cases being a juror/witness, though these have not generally been enforced since the early nineteenth century.&lt;ref name="acl" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Giacalone|first=Robert A|coauthors=Jurkiewicz, Carole L. |title=Handbook of Workplace Spirituality and Organizational Performance |publisher=M.E. Sharpe|date=2005 |isbn=9780765617439|url=http://books.google.com/?id=jlRv-eYAOlMC&amp;pg=PA247}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Urofsky|first=Melvin I.|title=Religious Freedom: Rights and Liberties Under the Law  |publisher=ABC-CLIO|date= 2002 |pages=39–40|isbn=9781576073124|url=http://books.google.com/?id=7urB3-9TfUIC&amp;pg=PA40}}&lt;/ref&gt; The US Constitution allows for an [[Affirmation in law|affirmation]] instead of an [[oath]] in order to accommodate atheists and others in court or seeking to hold public office.&lt;ref name="acl" /&gt;&lt;ref name="csm"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1207/p01s03-uspo.html?s=u|title=At swearing in, congressman wants to carry Koran. Outrage ensue|last=Lampman|first=Jane |date=December 7, 2006   |work=The Christian Science Monitor|accessdate=2009-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1961, the [[United States Supreme Court]] explicitly overturned the Maryland provision in the [[Torcaso v. Watkins]] decision, holding that laws requiring "a belief in the existence of God" in order to hold public office violated freedom of religion provided for by the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution]].&lt;ref name="acl"&gt;{{cite book|last=West|first=Ellis M.|title=Encyclopedia of American Civil Liberties |editor= Finkelman,  Paul|publisher=CRC Press|date=2006|pages= 1314–5|chapter=Religious Tests of Office-Holding|url=http://books.google.com/?id=YoI14vYA8r0C&amp;pg=PA1314|isbn=9780415943420}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="acl119"&gt;{{cite book|last=Douglas|first=Davison M.|title=Encyclopedia of American Civil Liberties |editor= Finkelman,  Paul|publisher=CRC Press|date=2006|pages= 119|chapter=Belief-Action Distinction  in Free Exercise Clause History|url=http://books.google.com/?id=YoI14vYA8r0C&amp;pg=PA119|isbn=9780415943420}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Belknap|first=Michal R.|title=The Supreme Court Under Earl Warren, 1953–1969  |publisher= Univ of South Carolina Press|date=2005|isbn=9781570035630|url=http://books.google.com/?id=x7UIUme1JYYC&amp;pg=PA136}}&lt;/ref&gt; This decision is generally understood to also apply to witness oaths.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Friedman |first=Dan|title=The Maryland State Constitution: A Reference Guide |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|date=2005|pages=44|isbn=9780313320446|url=http://books.google.com/?id=MoTGJ8bk11wC&amp;pg=PA44&amp;lpg=PA44}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several American atheists have used court challenges to assert discrimination against atheists. [[Michael Newdow]] challenged inclusion of the phrase "under God" in the United States [[Pledge of Allegiance]] on behalf of his daughter, claiming that the phrase was discriminatory against non-theists.&lt;ref name="bishop"&gt;{{cite book|last=Bishop|first=Ronald|title=Taking on the Pledge of Allegiance: The News Media and Michael Newdow's Constitutional Challenge  |publisher=SUNY Press|date=2007|pages=39–40|isbn=9780791471814|url=http://books.google.com/?id=T6v-hpqD654C&amp;pg=PA39}}&lt;/ref&gt; He won the case at an initial stage, but the Supreme Court dismissed his claim, ruling that Newdow did not have [[standing (law)|standing]] to bring his case, thus disposing of the case without ruling on the constitutionality of the pledge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/low/americas/3806181.stm|title=US to keep 'under God' pledge|date=14 June 2004|work=BBC News|accessdate=2009-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-8128948_ITM|title=U.S. Supreme Court Dismisses Pledge Challenge|last=Mintz|first=Howard|date=June 15, 2004|work= San Jose Mercury News |accessdate=2009-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the [[Boy Scouts of America]] does not allow atheists as members, atheist families and the [[American Civil Liberties Union|ACLU]] from the 1990s onwards have launched a [[Boy Scouts of America membership controversies|series of court cases arguing discrimination against atheists]].  In response to ACLU lawsuits,  the Pentagon in 2004 ended sponsorship of [[Scouting]] units,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aclu-il.org/legal/courtdocuments/2004/11/winkler_v_chicago_school_refor.shtml Winkler v. Chicago School Reform Board]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usdoj.gov/opa/pr/2004/November/04_civ_751.htm Department of Defense settles part of litigation challenging its involvement with the Boy Scouts of America]&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2005 the BSA agreed to transfer all Scouting units out of government entities such as public schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aclu-il.org/news/press/2005/03/national_boy_scout_organizatio.shtml|work=American Civil Liberties Union of Illinois|title=National Boy Scout Organization Agrees to End All Local Government Direct Sponsorship of Troops and Packs|accessdate=2006-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/metro/20041116-115229-4427r.htm|work=Washington Times|title=Boy Scouts Jamboree to Stay at Army Base|accessdate=2006-03-02|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060419175333/http://www.washingtontimes.com/metro/20041116-115229-4427r.htm|archivedate=2006-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Atheists note that few politicians have been willing to identify as non-theists, since until recently such revelations would have been "political suicide",&lt;ref name="SFC"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2007/03/14/MNG7BOKV111.DTL |title=Stark's atheist views break political taboo|last=Marinucci|first=Carla|publisher=San Francisco Chronicle|accessdate=2009-03-12 | date=2007-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nysun.com/national/california-lawmaker-becomes-highest-ranking/50312/ California Lawmaker Becomes Highest-Ranking Official To Say He's a Nonbeliever]&lt;/ref&gt; and welcomed [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] [[California]]  Representative [[Pete Stark]]'s  2007 decision to come out as the first openly nontheistic member of Congress.&lt;ref name="AHA"&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.americanhumanist.org/press/petestark.php
|title=Humanists Praise Pete Stark for “Coming Out” as a Nontheist
|publisher=American Humanist
|accessdate=2009-03-17
|last=
|first=
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, City Councilman [[Cecil Bothwell]] of Asheville, North Carolina was called "unworthy of his seat" because of his open atheism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/12/14/critics-say-atheist-nc-city-councilman-unworthy-seat/ Critics Say Atheist N.C. City councilman Unworthy of Seat]&lt;/ref&gt;.  Indeed, several polls have shown that about 50 percent of Americans would not vote for a well-qualified atheist for president.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url = http://www.MotherJones.com/news/exhibit/2004/09/09_200.html | title = Faith in the System | journal = [[Mother Jones (magazine)|Mother Jones]] | month = September/October | date = 2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2007-03-11-politics-diversity-cover_N.htm|title=2008 race has the face of a changing America|last=Page|first=Susan|work=USA Today|accessdate=2009-03-13 | date=2007-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2006 study found that 40% of respondents characterized atheists as a group that did "not at all agree with my vision of American society", and that 48% would not want their child to marry an atheist. In both studies, percentages of disapproval of atheists were above those for Muslims, [[African-American]]s and homosexuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Penny Edgell |first= |authorlink= | coauthors=  Joseph Gerteis, and Douglas Hartmann |date=2006 |month=April |title=Atheists As “Other”: Moral Boundaries and Cultural Membership in American Society |journal=American Sociological Review |volume=71 |issue=2 |pages=218 |id= |url=http://www.soc.umn.edu/~hartmann/files/atheist%20as%20the%20other.pdf|accessdate= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prominent atheists and atheist groups have asserted that discrimination against atheists is illustrated by a statement allegedly said by [[George H. W. Bush]] during a public press conference during his campaign for the presidency in 1987.&lt;ref name="dawkins" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.atheistsforhumanrights.org/mugged.htm
|title= Your money and/or your life: mugged by the mythmakers
|publisher=Atheists For Human Rights
|accessdate=2009-02-27
|last=Castle
|first=Marie Alena
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.positiveatheism.org/writ/ghwbush.htm
|title=George H. W. Bush: "Atheists Neither Citizens Nor Patriots
|publisher=American Atheists
|accessdate=2009-02-27
|last=O'Hair
|first=Madalyn
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name ="saxon"&gt;{{cite news|title= Godless in Tucson; Atheists—the least-trusted group in America—speak out|last=Burns|first=Saxon|date=November 30, 2006 |work=Tucson Weekly|url=http://www.tucsonweekly.com/gbase/Currents/Content?oid=89764|accessdate=2009-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; When asked by atheistic journalist [[Robert Sherman]] about the equal citizenship and patriotism of American atheists, Sherman reports that Bush answered, "No, I don't know that atheists should be considered as citizens, nor should they be considered patriots. This is one nation under God."&lt;ref name="dawkins" /&gt;&lt;ref name="saxon" /&gt; The accuracy of the quote has been questioned, however, as Sherman did not tape the exchange and no other journalist reported on it.&lt;ref name="dawkins"&gt;{{cite book|last=Dawkins|first=Richard|title=The God Delusion|publisher=Houghton
Mifflin Harcourt|date=2006|pages=43–46|isbn=9780618680009|url=http://books.google.com/?id=yq1xDpicghkC&amp;pg=PA43}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic countries===
Atheists, or those accused of holding atheistic beliefs, may be subject to discrimination and persecution in some Islamic countries. According to popular interpretations of Islam, Muslims are not free to change religion or become an atheist: denying Islam and thus becoming an [[apostasy|apostate]] is traditionally punished by death in men and by life imprisonment in women, though in only three Islamic countries is apostasy currently subject to capital punishment. Since an apostate can be considered a Muslim whose beliefs cast doubt on the Divine, and/or [[Koran]], claims of atheism and [[apostasy]] have been made against Muslim scholars and political opponents throughout history.&lt;ref name="kamrava"&gt;{{cite book|last=Kamrava|first=Mehran|title=The new voices of Islam: reforming politics and modernity : a reader |publisher=I.B.Tauris|date=2006|pages=123–24|isbn=9781845112752|url=http://books.google.com/?id=wTYJv7mwCoIC&amp;pg=PA123}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="isbn90-411-1105-0"&gt;{{cite book| last = Hamad|first= Ahmad| chapter= Legal plurality and legitimation of human rights abuses | editors = Al-Zwaini, Laila; Baudouin Dupret; Berger, Maurits | title = Legal pluralism in the Arab world | publisher = Kluwer Law International | location = The Hague | date = 1999 | page = 221 | isbn = 90-411-1105-0 | oclc = | url = http://books.google.com/?id=VAcOB1eMa5QC&amp;pg=PA221 | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="apost"&gt;{{cite book | author = Zaki Badawi, M.A.| chapter= Islam | title = Encyclopedia of religious freedom | editor= Cookson, Catharine| publisher = Routledge | location = New York | date = 2003 | pages = 204–8| isbn = 0-415-94181-4 | oclc = | doi = | url = http://books.google.com/?id=R0PrjC1Ar7gC&amp;pg=PA206 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Iran]], atheists do not have any recognized legal status, and must declare that they are Muslim, Christian, Jewish or Zoroastrian, in order to claim some legal rights, including applying for entrance to university,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fidh.org/IMG/pdf/ir0108a.pdf|title=Discrimination against religious minorities in IRAN|date=August 2003|work=Fédération Internationale des Ligues des Droits de l`Homme and the Ligue de Défense des Droits de l’Homme en Iran|accessdate=2009-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; or becoming a lawyer.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/MDE13/045/2001/en/73a8bc2a-d8ae-11dd-ad8c-f3d4445c118e/mde130452001en.html
|title=Iran: A legal system that fails to protect freedom of expression and association
|publisher=Amnesty International
|accessdate=2009-03-14
|last=
|first=
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[Jordan]] requires atheists to associate themselves with a recognized religion for official identification purposes,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2008/108485.htm
|title=International Religious Freedom Report 2008-Jordan
|publisher= US of Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor
|accessdate=2009-03-14
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and atheists in [[Indonesia]] experience official discrimination in the context of registration of births and marriages, and the issuance of identity cards.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90137.htm
|title=International Religious Freedom Report 2007-Indonesia
|publisher= US of Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor
|accessdate=2009-03-14
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
In [[Egypt]], intellectuals suspected of holding atheistic beliefs have been prosecuted by judicial and religious authorities.  Novelist Alaa Hamad was convicted of publishing a book that contained atheistic ideas and apostasy that were considered to threaten national unity and social peace.&lt;ref name="boyle"&gt;{{cite book|last=Boyle|first=Kevin|coauthors=Sheen, Juliet |title=Freedom of Religion and Belief: A World Report  |publisher=Routledge |date=1997|pages=30|isbn=9780415159784|url=http://books.google.com/?id=MFUZkWWgOtMC&amp;pg=RA1-PA30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="al"&gt;{{cite book | author =Al-Boray, Nagad | chapter= Egypt| title = Secrecy and Liberty: National Security, Freedom of Expression and Access to Information (International Studies in Human Rights) | publisher = Springer | location = Berlin | date = 1999 | pages = | isbn = 90-411-1191-3 | oclc = | doi = | url = http://books.google.com/?id=72IynQKXt3sC&amp;pg=PA251}}&lt;/ref&gt; Compulsory religious instruction in [[Turkey|Turkish]] schools is also considered discriminatory towards atheists.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/docid/47665e602.html
|title= A Quest for Equality: Minorities in Turkey
|date= 2007
|publisher= Minority Rights Group International
|accessdate=2009-03-14
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Africa===
In [[Algeria]], the study of Islam is a requirement in public and private [[school]]s for every Algerian child, irrespective of his/her religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.algerie-dz.com/article841.html|title=Ecoles privées en Algérie : Plaidoyer pour le bilinguisme|language=French|accessdate=29 August 2010|date=30 June 2004|author=Djamila Kourta|work=[[El Watan]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Atheist or agnostic men are prohibited from marrying Muslim women ([[Algerian Family Code]] I.II.31).[http://www.lexalgeria.net/droitdelafamille.htm],  A marriage is legally nullified by the apostasy of the husband (presumably from Islam, although this is not specified; Family Code I.III.33.)
Atheists and agnostics cannot inherit (Family Code III.I.138.).{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}

==See also==
*[[Boy Scouts of America membership controversies]]
*[[Out Campaign]]
*[[Religious discrimination]]
*[[Secularization]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Atheism}}
{{Belief systems}}

[[Category:Atheism]]
[[Category:Religious discrimination|Atheists]]

[[es:Discriminación contra los ateos]]
[[fr:Discrimination contre les athées]]
[[id:Diskriminasi terhadap ateis]]
[[pl:Dyskryminacja ateistów]]
[[fi:Ateistien syrjintä]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>