<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161123073454|751082703" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7194871" pageid="7194871" ns="0" title="Discrimination against atheists"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-23T14:36:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2011}}
[[File:States with death penalty for apostasy.svg|right|thumb|350px|Countries in which, as of 2007, [[apostasy]] of the local or state religion was punishable by execution under national (''black'') or regional (''dark gray'') law. Currently, this occurs only in [[Apostasy in Islam|Islamic]] nations.&lt;ref name= Indy1 &gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/the-13-countries-where-being-an-atheist-is-punishable-by-death-a6960561.html |title= The 13 countries where being an atheist is punishable by death |date= 30 March 2016 |first1= Siobhan |last1= Fenton |publisher= [[The Independent]] |accessdate= 22 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="reuters131210"/&gt;&lt;ref name= "iheu report"/&gt;&lt;ref name= FreethoughtReport&gt;{{cite web |url= http://freethoughtreport.com/download-the-report/ |title= The Freedom of Thought Report |date= 2015 |publisher= [[International Humanist and Ethical Union]] |accessdate = 20 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Status of religious freedom |persecution}}
{{Irreligion sidebar|atheism}}
{{Atheism sidebar|people}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Social}}
'''Discrimination against atheists''' (sometimes called '''atheophobia''' or '''atheistophobia''', '''anti-atheism''', or '''anti-atheist sentiment'''), both at present and historically, includes the [[Religious persecution|persecution]] of those identifying themselves or labeled by others as [[Atheism|atheists]], as well as the [[Religious discrimination|discrimination]] against them. Discrimination against atheists may also refer to and comprise the negative attitudes towards, prejudice, hostility, hatred, fear, and/or intolerance towards atheists and/or atheism. As atheism can be defined in various ways, those discriminated against or persecuted on the grounds of being atheists might not have been considered as such in a different time or place. As of 2015, 19 countries punish their citizens for apostasy, and in 13 of those countries it is punishable by death.&lt;ref name="reuters131210"/&gt;

Legal discrimination against atheists is uncommon in [[constitutional democracy|constitutional democracies]], although some atheists and atheist groups, particularly in the [[United States]], have protested against laws, regulations, and institutions that they view as discriminatory. In some [[Muslim world|Islamic countries]], atheists face persecution and severe penalties such as the withdrawal of [[Status (law)|legal status]] or, in the case of [[Apostasy in Islam|apostasy]], [[Capital punishment#Islam|capital punishment]].

==Ancient times==
Some historians, such as [[Lucien Febvre]], have postulated that atheism in its modern sense did not exist before the end of the seventeenth century,&lt;ref name="davidson"&gt;{{cite book|last=Davidson|first=Nicholas|title=Atheism from the Reformation to the Enlightenment|editor=Michael Hunter; David Wootton|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1992|pages=55–86|chapter=Unbelief and Atheism In Italy|isbn=978-0-19-822736-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="books.google"&gt;{{cite book|last=Armstrong |first=Karen |title=A History of God: The 4000-year Quest of Judaism, Christianity, and Islam |publisher=Random House, Inc. |pages=286–87|year=1994|url= https://books.google.com/?id=_n3cCF2I2FUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=A+History+of+God| isbn=978-0-345-38456-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="kelley"&gt;{{cite book|last=Kelley|first=Donald R. |title=Frontiers of History: Historical Inquiry in the Twentieth Century |publisher=Yale University Press|year=2006|page=115|isbn=978-0-300-12062-2|url=https://books.google.com/?id=K-wVctit5U8C&amp;pg=PA115}}&lt;/ref&gt; though the contrary is also argued.&lt;ref name="whitmarsh"&gt;{{cite book|last=Whitmarsh|first=Tim|title=Battling the Gods: Atheism in the Ancient World|publisher=Knopf|year=2015|isbn=978-0-307-95833-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, as governmental authority rested on the notion of [[Divine right of kings|divine right]], it was threatened by those who denied the existence of the local god. Those labeled as atheist, including early Christians and Muslims, were as a result targeted for legal persecution.&lt;ref name="gey 250"&gt;{{cite book|last=Gey|first=Steven G.|title=The Cambridge Companion to Atheism|editor=Martin, Michael|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2007|chapter=Atheism and the Freedom of Religion|pages=250–253, 260–2 |isbn=978-0-521-84270-9|url=https://books.google.com/?id=tAeFipOVx4MC&amp;pg=PA250}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Armstrong |first=Karen |title=A History of God: The 4000-year Quest of Judaism, Christianity, and Islam |publisher=Random House, Inc. |pages=98, 147|year=1994|url= https://books.google.com/?id=_n3cCF2I2FUC&amp;printsec=frontcover|isbn=978-0-345-38456-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early modern period and Reformation==
{{Further|Atheism in the Age of Enlightenment}}
During the [[early modern period]], the term "atheist" was used as an insult and applied to a broad range of people, including those who held opposing theological beliefs, as well as suicides, immoral or self-indulgent people, and even opponents of the belief in witchcraft.&lt;ref name="davidson"/&gt;&lt;ref name="books.google"/&gt;&lt;ref name="laursen"&gt;{{cite book|last=Laursen|first=John Christian |author2=Nederman, Cary J.|title=Beyond the Persecuting Society: Religious Toleration Before the Enlightenment |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|year=1997|page=142|isbn= 978-0-8122-1567-0|url=https://books.google.com/?id=r2j6ZHgXZWkC&amp;pg=PA142}}&lt;/ref&gt; Atheistic beliefs were seen as threatening to order and society by philosophers such as [[Thomas Aquinas]]. Lawyer and scholar [[Thomas More]] said that religious tolerance should be extended to all except those who did not believe in a deity or the immortality of the soul.&lt;ref name="gey 250"/&gt; [[John Locke]], a founder of modern notions of religious liberty, argued that atheists (as well as Catholics and Muslims) should not be granted full citizenship rights.&lt;ref name="gey 250"/&gt;

During the Inquisition, several of those accused of atheism or blasphemy, or both, were tortured or executed. These included the priest [[Giulio Cesare Vanini]] who was strangled and burned in 1619 and the Polish nobleman [[Kazimierz Łyszczyński]] who was executed in Warsaw,&lt;ref name="davidson"/&gt;&lt;ref name="brooke"&gt;{{cite book|last= Brooke|first=John Hedley|others= Maclean, Ian |title=Heterodoxy in Early Modern Science and Religion |publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2005|isbn=978-0-19-926897-9|url=https://books.google.com/?id=W9o_OEvMQTcC&amp;pg=PA66}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kłoczowski |first=Jerzy |title=A History of Polish Christianity |publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2000 |page=155|isbn=978-0-521-36429-4|url=https://books.google.com/?id=ecdye8hk_tgC&amp;pg=PA155}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[Etienne Dolet]], a Frenchman executed in 1546. Though heralded as atheist martyrs during the nineteenth century, recent scholars hold that the beliefs espoused by Dolet and Vanini are not atheistic in modern terms.&lt;ref name="kelley"/&gt;&lt;ref name="onfray"&gt;{{cite book|last=Onfray|first=Michel|others=Leggatt, Jeremy (translator) |title=Atheist manifesto: the case against Christianity, Judaism, and Islam |publisher=Arcade Publishing|year=2007|page=24|isbn=978-1-55970-820-3|url=https://books.google.com/?id=QpEAYMo7pFkC&amp;pg=PA24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="chadwich"&gt;{{cite book|last=Chadwick |first=Owen |title=The Early Reformation on the Continent By |publisher= Oxford University Press|year=2003|isbn=978-0-19-926578-7|url=https://books.google.com/?id=VR1yNW8mgoEC&amp;pg=PA413}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern era==
During the nineteenth century, British atheists, though few in number, were subject to discriminatory practices.&lt;ref name="cookson"&gt;{{cite book | author = Larson, Timothy| chapter= Victorian England | title = Encyclopedia of religious freedom | editor= Cookson, Catharine| publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 2003 | isbn = 0-415-94181-4 | oclc = }}&lt;/ref&gt; The poet [[Percy Bysshe Shelley]] was expelled from the University of Oxford and denied custody of his two children after publishing a pamphlet titled ''[[The Necessity of Atheism]]''.&lt;ref name="gey253" /&gt; Those unwilling to swear Christian oaths during judicial proceedings were unable to give evidence in court to obtain justice until this requirement was repealed by Acts passed in 1869 and 1870.&lt;ref name="cookson"/&gt; 

Atheist [[Charles Bradlaugh]] was elected as a [[Member of Parliament (UK)|Member of the British Parliament]] in 1880. He was denied the right to affirm rather than swear his oath of office, and was then denied the ability to swear the oath as other Members objected that he had himself said it would be meaningless. Bradlaugh was re-elected three times before he was finally able to take his seat in 1886 when the Speaker of the House permitted him to take the oath.&lt;ref name="gey253"&gt;{{cite book|last=Gey|first=Steven G.|title=The Cambridge Companion to Atheism|editor=Martin, Michael|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2007|chapter=Atheism and the Freedom of Religion|pages=253–255|isbn=978-0-521-84270-9|url=https://books.google.com/?id=tAeFipOVx4MC&amp;pg=PA253}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nazi Germany===
{{Further information|Irreligion in Nazi Germany}}
In Germany during the Nazi era, a 1933 decree stated that "No National Socialist may suffer detriment... on the ground that he does not make any religious profession at all".&lt;ref name="Baynes"/&gt; However, the regime strongly opposed "godless communism",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Christian|title=Disruptive religion: the force of faith in social-movement activism|publisher=Routledge|year=1996|pages=156–57|isbn=978-0-415-91405-5|url=https://books.google.com/?id=39SoSG4NGAoC&amp;pg=PA156}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Stackelberg|first=Roderick|title=The Routledge Companion to Nazi Germany	|publisher=Routledge|year=2007|pages=136–8|isbn=978-0-415-30860-1|url=https://books.google.com/?id=cpXIR9yOMuoC&amp;pg=PA136}}&lt;/ref&gt; and all of Germany's atheist and largely left-wing [[freethought]] organizations were banned the same year; some right-wing groups were tolerated by the Nazis until the mid-1930s.&lt;ref name="may"&gt;{{cite book |last= Bock| first= Heike | chapter= Secularization of the modern conduct of life? Reflections on the religiousness of early modern Europe| editor=Hanne May |title=Religiosität in der säkularisierten Welt |publisher=VS Verlag fnr Sozialw |year=2006 |page= 157|isbn=3-8100-4039-8 |oclc= |url= https://books.google.com/?id=nfQ0pqA53Z8C&amp;pg=PA157}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=kaiser&gt;{{cite book|last=Kaiser|first=Jochen-Christoph|title=Atheismus und religiöse Indifferenz|editor=Christel Gärtner|publisher=VS Verlag|year=2003|volume=Organisierter Atheismus|pages= 122, 124–6|isbn=978-3-8100-3639-1|url=https://books.google.com/?id=YXOr4xQFSJsC&amp;pg=PA124}}&lt;/ref&gt; During negotiations leading to the Nazi-Vatican Concordat of April 26, 1933 Hitler stated that "Secular schools can never be tolerated" because of their irreligious tendencies.&lt;ref&gt;Ernst Helmreich, ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=I6DYAAAAMAAJ The German Churches Under Hitler]''. Detroit: Wayne State Univ. Press, 1979, p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt; Hitler routinely disregarded this undertaking, and the [[Reich concordat]] as a whole and by 1939, all Catholic denominational schools had been disbanded or converted to public facilities.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, Richard J. (2005). The Third Reich in Power. New York: Penguin. ISBN 978-0-14-303790-3; pp. 245-246&lt;/ref&gt;

In a speech made later in 1933, Hitler claimed to have "stamped out" the  ''Gottlosenbewegung'' atheistic movement.&lt;ref name="Baynes"&gt;{{cite book|last=Baynes|first=Norman Hepburn|title=The Speeches of Adolf Hitler, April 1922 – August 1939'|publisher=H. Fertig|year=1969|page=378|quote= Without pledging ourselves to any particular Confession, we have restored faith to its pre-requisites because we were convinced that the people needs [sic] and requires [sic] this faith. We have therefore undertaken the fight against the atheistic movement, and that not merely with a few theoretical declarations: we have stamped it out.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word Hitler used, "Gottlosenbewegung", means "Godless Movement" in German, and refers to the communist [[freethought]] movement, though might not refer to atheism in general. The historian [[Richard J. Evans]] wrote that, by 1939, 95% of Germans still called themselves Protestant or Catholic, while 3.5% were so called "''[[gottgläubig]]''" (lit. "believers in god", a non-denominational nazified outlook on god beliefs, often described as predominately based on creationist and deistic views&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TIZSO31iSO4C&amp;pg=PA48&amp;dq=gottglaubig&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=sltlU7HVO8-u7AbuxYDgBw&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwADge#v=onepage&amp;q=gottglaubig&amp;f=false|title=Himmler's Auxiliaries|publisher=|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;) and 1.5% atheist. According to Evans, those members of the affiliation ''gottgläubig'' "were convinced Nazis who had left their Church at the behest of the Party, which had been trying since the mid 1930s to reduce the influence of Christianity in society".&lt;ref&gt;[[Richard J. Evans]]; ''The Third Reich at War''; Penguin Press; New York 2009, p. 546&lt;/ref&gt; [[Heinrich Himmler]], who was fascinated with [[Germanic paganism]],{{citation needed|date=May 2014}} was a strong promoter of the ''gottgläubig'' movement and didn't allow atheists into the [[SS]], arguing that their "refusal to acknowledge higher powers" would be a "potential source of indiscipline".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=l5gcZpnL5QUC&amp;pg=PA196&amp;dq=gottglaubig&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=RVtlU-L_HNGe7AbJ64DoBg&amp;ved=0CE8Q6AEwBjgK#v=onepage&amp;q=gottglaubig&amp;f=false|title=The Third Reich|publisher=|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the three million Nazi Party members continued to pay their church taxes and register as either [[Roman Catholic]] or [[German Evangelical Church Confederation|Evangelical Protestant]] Christians.&lt;ref&gt;The Nazi Persecution of the Churches, 1933-1945 By John S. Conway p. 232; Regent College Publishing&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contemporary era==

===Human rights===
{{main|History of human rights}}
Article 18 of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] is designed to protect the right to freedom of thought, conscience, and religion. In 1993, the UN's human rights committee declared that article 18 of the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] "protects theistic, non-theistic and atheistic beliefs, as well as the right not to profess any religion or belief."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.minorityrights.org/3273/normative-instruments/ccpr-general-comment-22-300793-on-iccpr-article-18.html|title=CCPR General Comment 22: 30/07/93 on ICCPR Article 18|work=Minorityrights.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; The committee further stated that "the freedom to have or to adopt a religion or belief necessarily entails the freedom to choose a religion or belief, including the right to replace one's current religion or belief with another or to adopt atheistic views." Signatories to the convention are barred from "the use of threat of physical force or penal sanctions to compel believers or non-believers" to recant their beliefs or convert. Despite this, minority religions still are persecuted in many parts of the world.&lt;ref name="fdih1"&gt;{{cite web |date=1 August 2003|title=Discrimination against religious minorities in Iran|author=International Federation for Human Rights|publisher=fdih.org|accessdate=3 March 2009|url=http://www.fidh.org/IMG/pdf/ir0108a.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.law2.byu.edu/lawreview/archives/2002/2/dav2.pdf|title=The Evolution of Religious Liberty as a Universal Human Right|accessdate=3 March 2009|last=Davis|first=Derek H.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Western countries===
Modern theories of constitutional democracy assume that citizens are intellectually and spiritually autonomous and that governments should leave matters of religious belief to individuals and not coerce religious beliefs using sanctions or benefits.  The constitutions, human rights conventions and the religious liberty jurisprudence of most constitutional democracies provide legal protection of atheists and agnostics.  In addition, freedom of expression provisions and legislation separating church from state also serve to protect the rights of atheists. As a result, open legal discrimination against atheists is not common in most Western countries.&lt;ref name="gey 250" /&gt; However, prejudice against atheists does exist in Western countries. A [[UBC|University of British Columbia]] study conducted in the United States found that believers distrusted atheists as much they did [[rapists]]. The study also showed that atheists had lower employment prospects.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www2.psych.ubc.ca/~will/Gervais%20et%20al-%20Atheist%20Distrust.pdf|title=Do You Believe in Atheists? Distrust Is Central to Anti-Atheist Prejudice|first1=Will M.|last1=Gervais|first2=Azim F.|last2=Shariff|first3=Ara|last3=Norenzayan|journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|year=2011|volume=101|issue=6|pages=1189–1206|accessdate=April 22, 2012|doi=10.1037/a0025882}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/religion/story/2011-12-10/religion-atheism/51777612/1&lt;/ref&gt;

====Europe====
{{Further information|Irreligion in Europe}}
In most of Europe, atheists are elected to office at high levels in many governments without controversy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://ibka.org/en/articles/miz08/politics-religion-usa|title="Most American secularists have few expectations..." An Interview with AAI president Stuart Bechman   |last=Hartmann|first=René|date=March 2008|work=MIZ Magazine|accessdate=2009-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some atheist organizations in Europe have expressed concerns regarding issues of separation of church and state, such as administrative fees for leaving the Church charged in Germany,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://ibka.org/en/fee-european-court
|title=Fee for leaving church is brought before European Court of Human Rights &amp;#124; I
|publisher=International League of Non-religious and Atheists (IBKA)
|accessdate=2009-03-14}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and sermons being organized by the Swedish parliament.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.jo.se/Page.aspx?MenuId=106&amp;MainMenuId=106&amp;Language=sv&amp;ObjectClass=DynamX_SFS_Decision&amp;Id=2100
|title=Anmälan till JO – Riksdagens ombudsmän
|publisher=jo.se
|accessdate=2009-03-14
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Ireland requires religious training from Christian colleges in order to work as a teacher in government-funded schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2010/0202/1224263575172.html
|title=Why must agnostics be obliged to teach faith?
|work=The Irish Times
|accessdate=2010-02-02
|date=2 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In the UK one-third of state-funded schools are faith-based.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.runnymedetrust.org/uploads/publications/Summaries/RightToDivide-Summary.pdf|title=Right to Divide? Faith Schools and Community Cohesion|last=Berkeley|first=Rob|author2=Savita Vij|date=December 2008|publisher=[[Runnymede Trust]]|page=4|accessdate=7 December 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, there are no restrictions on atheists holding public office – the former [[Deputy Prime Minister of the United Kingdom]], [[Nick Clegg]], is an atheist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Peev |first=Gerri |url=http://news.scotsman.com/politics/I-don39t-believe-in-God.3607087.jp |title=Religion: I don't believe in God |work=The Scotsman |date= 20 December 2007|accessdate=14 April 2010 |location=Edinburgh}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 2012 poll, 25% of the [[Turks in Germany]] believe atheists are inferior human beings.&lt;ref&gt;Liljeberg Research International: [https://d171.keyingress.de/multimedia/document/228.pdf ''Deutsch-Türkische Lebens und Wertewelten 2012''], July/August 2012, p. 68&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Die Welt]]: [http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article108659406/Tuerkische-Migranten-hoffen-auf-muslimische-Mehrheit.html ''Türkische Migranten hoffen auf muslimische Mehrheit''], 17 August 2012, retrieved 23 August 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Portugal has elected two presidents, [[Mário Soares]] and [[Jorge Sampaio]], who have openly expressed their irreligion. On the contrary, in Greece, the right-wing New Democracy government stated that "the Greek people have a right to know whether Mr. [[Alexis Tsipras|Tsipras]] is an atheist", citing their political opponent's irreligiosity as a reason he should not be elected, even though they granted that "it is his right".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.skai.gr/news/politics/article/250179/nd-o-ellinikos-prepei-na-gnorizei-an-o-tsipras-einai-atheosd/|title=ΝΔ: Ο ελληνικός λαός πρέπει να γνωρίζει αν ο Τσίπρας είναι άθεος - η απάντηση ΣΥΡΙΖΑ|work=skai.gr}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Elder Pastitsios]] case, a 27-year-old was sentenced to imprisonment for satirizing a popular apocalyptically-minded Greek Orthodox monk, while several [[Metropolitan bishop|metropolitans]] of the Greek Orthodox Church (which is not separated from the state) have also urged their flock "not to vote unbelievers into office", even going so far as to warn Greek Orthodox laymen that they would be "sinning if they voted atheists into public office."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pentapostagma.gr/2014/05/%CE%BC%CE%B5%CF%83%CE%BF%CE%B3%CE%B1%CE%AF%CE%B1%CF%82-%CE%BD%CE%B9%CE%BA%CF%8C%CE%BB%CE%B1%CE%BF%CF%82-%CE%B1%CE%BC%CE%B1%CF%81%CF%84%CE%AF%CE%B1-%CE%B1%CE%BD-%CE%B4%CF%8E%CF%83%CE%BF%CF%85.html|title=Μεσογαίας Νικόλαος: "Αμαρτία αν δώσουμε ψήφο σε ανθρώπους χωρίς πίστη, αξίες και σεβασμό στην ιστορία"|work=Pentapostagma.gr|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.topontiki.gr/article/65820|title=Μητροπολίτης Γόρτυνος: "Το ράσο μου πετάει τριφασικό ρεύμα" (Video)|publisher=|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Brazil====
{{Further|Irreligion in Brazil}}
A 2009 survey showed that atheists were the most hated demographic group in Brazil, among several other minorities polled, being almost on par with drug addicts. According to the research, 17% of the interviewees stated they felt either hatred or repulsion for atheists, while 25% felt antipathy and 29% were indifferent.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.paulopes.com.br/2009/05/ateus-e-usuarios-de-drogas-sao-os-mais.html|title=Ateus e drogados são os mais odiados pelos brasileiros|work=Paulopes.com.br|date=May 3, 2009|accessdate=August 4, 2013|language=Portuguese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Canada====
{{Further|Irreligion in Canada}}
Canadian [[secular humanist]] groups have worked to end the recitation of prayers during government proceedings, viewing them as discriminatory.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.humanistcanada.com/no-prayers-in-ont-legislature
|title=No More Prayers in Legislature
|publisher=humanistcanada.com
|accessdate=2009-03-14
|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090904171238/http://www.humanistcanada.com/no-prayers-in-ont-legislature/
|archivedate=2009-09-04
|deadurl=yes
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thestar.com/article/423192|title=Stirring up yet another religious storm|last=Hurst|first=Lynda|date=  9 May 2008 |work=Toronto Star|accessdate=2009-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Scouts Canada]] states that while a belief in God or affliation with organized religion is not a requirement to join, members must have "a basic spiritual belief"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scouts.ca/ca/frequently-asked-questions|title=Frequently Asked Questions|publisher=|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and one of the core values is "Duty to God: Defined as, The responsibility to adhere to spiritual principles, and thus to the religion that expresses them, and to accept the duties therefrom."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scouts.ca/ca/values|title=Values|publisher=|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United States====
{{Further|Irreligion in the United States}}
{{See also|Anti-atheist sentiment in the United States|Religion in the United States#Agnosticism, atheism, and humanism}}
[[File:Why Do Atheists Hate America billboard.jpg|thumb|right|Anti-atheist [[propaganda]] billboard posted in Chambersburg, Pennsylvania, in February 2008]]
Discrimination against atheists in the United States occurs in legal, personal, social, and professional contexts. Many American atheists compare their situation to the discrimination faced by ethnic minorities, [[LGBT]] communities, and women.&lt;ref name="dawkins" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Harris"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.latimes.com/news/opinion/sunday/commentary/la-op-harris24dec24,0,3481836.story?coll=la-sunday-commentary|title= 10 myths – and 10 truths – about atheism|last=Harris|first=Sam|date=24 December 2006 |work=Los Angeles Times|accessdate=2009-03-12|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080417012525/http://www.latimes.com/news/opinion/sunday/commentary/la-op-harris24dec24,0,3481836.story?coll=la-sunday-commentary|archivedate=17 April 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="fi-md"&gt;{{cite journal | title = Discrimination against atheists: the facts | author = Downey, Margaret | authorlink = Margaret Downey | journal = [[Free Inquiry]] | volume = 24 | issue = 4 |date=June–July 2004 | pages = 41–43|url= http://www.secularhumanism.org/library/fi/downey_24_4.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://ffrf.org/legacy/fttoday/1995/december95/zellner.html|title=Deep In The Bible Belt – One Atheist Professor's Experience|last=Zellner|first=William W. |date=December 1995|work=Freethought Today |accessdate=2013-05-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  "Americans still feel it's acceptable to discriminate against atheists in ways considered beyond the pale for other groups," asserted [[Fred Edwords]] of the [[American Humanist Association]].&lt;ref name="AHA"&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.americanhumanist.org/press/petestark.php |title=Humanists Praise Pete Stark for "Coming Out" as a Nontheist |publisher=American Humanist |accessdate=2009-03-17 |deadurl=unfit |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080705020101/http://www.americanhumanist.org/press/petestark.php |archivedate=5 July 2008 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; The degree of discrimination, persecution, and [[social stigma]] atheists face in the United States, compared to other persecuted groups in the United States has been the subject of study and a matter of debate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20090220134411/http://secularhumanism.org/library/fi/tabash_24_4.htm Atheism is Indeed A Civil Rights Issue]; Free Inquiry magazine, Volume 24, Number 4; Eddie Tabash; May 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="thornton"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/opinion/la-oew-thornton18apr18,0,5841004.story|title=Disliked, not oppressed I may be a reviled atheist, but that doesn't mean I can claim equal victimhood with truly repressed minorities |last=Thornton|first=Paul|date= 18 April 2007 |work=Los Angeles Times|accessdate=2009-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Grothe |first=D.J. |author2=Dacey, Austin |title=Atheism Is Not a Civil Rights Issue |journal=Free Inquiry |volume=24 |issue=2 |url=http://www.secularhumanism.org/library/fi/grothe-dacey_24_2.htm |deadurl=unfit |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130429181944/http://www.secularhumanism.org/library/fi/grothe-dacey_24_2.htm |archivedate=29 April 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://scienceblogs.com/pharyngula/2007/06/29/polarizing-is-a-dirty-word-so/ "Polarizing" is a dirty word, so atheists should surrender]; ''[[Pharyngula]]''; PZ Meyers; June 29, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://scienceblogs.com/evolutionblog/2007/06/28/is-atheism-a-civil-rights-issu/ | title=Is Atheism a Civil Rights Issue? | work=EvolutionBlog | date=June 28, 2007 | accessdate=July 1, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.patheos.com/blogs/daylightatheism/2007/07/atheism-is-a-civil-rights-issue/ | title=Atheism Is a Civil Rights Issue | work=Patheos | date=July 2, 2007 | accessdate=July 1, 2016 | author=Lee, Adam}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://camcambanks.files.wordpress.com/2009/10/positian-to-be-posted1.pdf | title=Atheism is a Civil Rights Issue | date=2010 | accessdate=July 1, 2016 | author=Banks, Cameron}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://onegoodmove.org/1gm/1gmarchive/2004/05/atheism_is_a_ci.html | title=Atheism is a Civil Rights Issue | work=onegoodmove | date=May 6, 2004 | accessdate=July 1, 2016 | author=Jenson, Chris}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.msatheists.org/2008/03/atheism-as-civil-rights-issue.html | title=Atheism as a Civil Rights Issue | work=Mississippi Atheists | date=March 13, 2008 | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090717021526/http://www.msatheists.org/2008/03/atheism-as-civil-rights-issue.html | archivedate=17 July 2009 | deadurl=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.skepticmoney.com/atheism-new-gay-civil-rights-issue/ | title=Atheism as the New Gay, Civil Rights Issue | work=Skeptic Money | date=December 11, 2013 | accessdate=July 1, 2016 | author=Newman, Jim}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://scienceblogs.com/framing-science/2007/06/28/atheism-is-not-a-civil-rights/ | title=ATHEISM IS NOT A CIVIL RIGHTS ISSUE | work=Framing Science | date=June 28, 2007 | accessdate=July 1, 2016 | author=Matthew C. Nisbet}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{overcite}}

In the United States, [[#seven|seven state constitutions]] include religious tests that would effectively prevent atheists from holding public office, and in some cases being a juror/witness, though these have not generally been enforced since the early twentieth century.&lt;ref name="acl" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Giacalone|first=Robert A|author2=Jurkiewicz, Carole L. |title=Handbook of Workplace Spirituality and Organizational Performance |publisher=M.E. Sharpe|year=2005 |isbn=978-0-7656-1743-9|url=https://books.google.com/?id=jlRv-eYAOlMC&amp;pg=PA247}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Urofsky|first=Melvin I.|title=Religious Freedom: Rights and Liberties Under the Law  |publisher=ABC-CLIO|year= 2002 |pages=39–40|isbn=978-1-57607-312-4|url=https://books.google.com/?id=7urB3-9TfUIC&amp;pg=PA40}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States Constitution|U.S. Constitution]] permits an [[Affirmation in law|affirmation]] in place of an [[oath]] to allow atheists to give testimony in court or to hold public office.&lt;ref name="acl" /&gt;&lt;ref name="csm"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/1207/p01s03-uspo.html?s=u|title=At swearing in, congressman wants to carry Koran. Outrage ensues.|last=Lampman|first=Jane |date=7 December 2006 |work=The Christian Science Monitor|accessdate=2009-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, a United States Supreme Court case reaffirmed that the United States Constitution prohibits States and the Federal Government from requiring any kind of religious test for public office, in the specific case, as a notary public.&lt;ref name="acl"&gt;{{cite book|last=West|first=Ellis M.|title=Encyclopedia of American Civil Liberties |editor= Finkelman,  Paul|publisher=CRC Press|year=2006|pages= 1314–5|chapter=Religious Tests of Office-Holding|url=https://books.google.com/?id=YoI14vYA8r0C&amp;pg=PA1314|isbn=978-0-415-94342-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="acl119"&gt;{{cite book|last=Douglas|first=Davison M.|title=Encyclopedia of American Civil Liberties |editor= Finkelman,  Paul|publisher=CRC Press|year=2006|page= 119|chapter=Belief-Action Distinction  in Free Exercise Clause History|url=https://books.google.com/?id=YoI14vYA8r0C&amp;pg=PA119|isbn=978-0-415-94342-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Belknap|first=Michal R.|title=The Supreme Court Under Earl Warren, 1953–1969  |publisher= Univ of South Carolina Press|year=2005|isbn=978-1-57003-563-0|url=https://books.google.com/?id=x7UIUme1JYYC&amp;pg=PA136}}&lt;/ref&gt; This decision is generally understood to also apply to witness oaths.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Friedman |first=Dan|title=The Maryland State Constitution: A Reference Guide |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|year=2005|page=44|isbn=978-0-313-32044-6|url=https://books.google.com/?id=MoTGJ8bk11wC&amp;pg=PA44&amp;lpg=PA44}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several American atheists have used court challenges to address discrimination against atheists. [[Michael Newdow]] challenged inclusion of the phrase "under God" in the United States [[Pledge of Allegiance]] on behalf of his daughter, claiming that the phrase amounted to government endorsement of discrimination against atheists.&lt;ref name="bishop"&gt;{{cite book|last=Bishop|first=Ronald|title=Taking on the Pledge of Allegiance: The News Media and Michael Newdow's Constitutional Challenge |publisher=SUNY Press|year=2007|pages=39–40|isbn=978-0-7914-7181-4|url=https://books.google.com/?id=T6v-hpqD654C&amp;pg=PA39}}&lt;/ref&gt; He won the case at an initial stage, but the Supreme Court dismissed his claim, ruling that Newdow did not have [[standing (law)|standing]] to bring his case, thus disposing of the case without ruling on the constitutionality of the pledge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/low/americas/3806181.stm|title=US to keep 'under God' pledge|date=14 June 2004|work=BBC News |accessdate=2009-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-8128948_ITM|title=U.S. Supreme Court Dismisses Pledge Challenge|last=Mintz|first=Howard|date=15 June 2004|work= San Jose Mercury News |accessdate=2009-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Respondents to a survey were less likely to support a kidney transplant for hypothetical atheists and agnostics needing it, than for Christian patients with similar medical needs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pitzer.edu/academics/faculty/zuckerman/Zuckerman_on_Atheism.pdf Atheism, Secularity, and Well-Being: How the Findings of Social Science Counter Negative Stereotypes and Assumptions, Phil Zuckerman*]&lt;/ref&gt; As the [[Boy Scouts of America]] [[Boy Scouts of America membership controversies#Position on religious belief|does not allow atheists as members]], atheist families and the [[American Civil Liberties Union|ACLU]] from the 1990s onwards have launched a series of court cases arguing discrimination against atheists. In response to ACLU lawsuits, the Pentagon in 2004 ended sponsorship of [[Scouting]] units,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aclu-il.org/legal/courtdocuments/2004/11/winkler_v_chicago_school_refor.shtml|year=2004|title=Winkler v. Chicago School Reform Board|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120607215939/http://www.aclu-il.org/legal/courtdocuments/2004/11/winkler_v_chicago_school_refor.shtml|archivedate=2012-06-07|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usdoj.gov/opa/pr/2004/November/04_civ_751.htm |title=Department of Defense settles part of litigation challenging its involvement with the Boy Scouts of America |publisher=Usdoj.gov |date=16 November 2004 |accessdate=4 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2005 the BSA agreed to transfer all Scouting units out of government entities such as public schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aclu-il.org/news/press/2005/03/national_boy_scout_organizatio.shtml|work=American Civil Liberties Union of Illinois|title=National Boy Scout Organization Agrees to End All Local Government Direct Sponsorship of Troops and Packs|accessdate=2006-03-02|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081121085949/http://www.aclu-il.org/news/press/2005/03/national_boy_scout_organizatio.shtml|archivedate=2008-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/metro/20041116-115229-4427r.htm|work=Washington Times|title=Boy Scouts Jamboree to Stay at Army Base|accessdate=2006-03-02|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060419175333/http://www.washingtontimes.com/metro/20041116-115229-4427r.htm|archivedate=2006-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite polling showing that nonbelievers make up an increasingly large part of the population there is only one public atheist in all of the state legislatures across the nation. Few politicians have been willing to acknowledge their lack of belief in supreme beings, since such revelations have been considered "political suicide".&lt;ref name="SFC"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2007/03/14/MNG7BOKV111.DTL |title=Stark's atheist views break political taboo|last=Marinucci|first=Carla|work=San Francisco Chronicle|accessdate=2009-03-12 | date=2007-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nysun.com/national/california-lawmaker-becomes-highest-ranking/50312/ |title=California Lawmaker Becomes Highest-Ranking Official To Say He's a Nonbeliever |publisher=Nysun.com |accessdate=4 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On September 20, 2007, Pete Stark became the first nontheist United States congressman to openly acknowledge a lack of belief, joining the millions of Americans whom have long kept their views secret for fear of discrimination in their communities.&lt;ref name="AHA"/&gt; [[Cecil Bothwell]], who has publicly stated he doesn't believe in gods and that it's "certainly not relevant to public office", was elected on November 3, 2009, to the Asheville, North Carolina city council after he won the third highest number of votes in the city election. Following the election, political opponents of Bothwell threatened to challenge his election on the grounds that the North Carolina Constitution does not allow for atheists to hold public office in the state. However, that provision, dating back to 1868, is unenforceable and invalid because the United States Constitution prevents religious tests for public office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/12/14/critics-say-atheist-nc-city-councilman-unworthy-seat/ |title=Critics Say Atheist N.C. City councilman Unworthy of Seat |publisher=Fox News |date=7 April 2010 |accessdate=4 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several polls have shown that about 50 percent of Americans would not vote for a qualified atheist for president.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url = http://www.MotherJones.com/news/exhibit/2004/09/09_200.html | title = Faith in the System | journal = [[Mother Jones (magazine)|Mother Jones]] |date=September–October 2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2007-03-11-politics-diversity-cover_N.htm|title=2008 race has the face of a changing America|last=Page|first=Susan|work=USA Today|accessdate=2009-03-13 | date=2007-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2006 study found that 40% of respondents characterized atheists as a group that did "not at all agree with my vision of American society", and that 48% would not want their child to marry an atheist. In both studies, percentages of disapproval of atheists were above those for Muslims, African-Americans and homosexuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Penny Edgell |author2=Joseph Gerteis|author3=Douglas Hartmann |date=April 2006 |title=Atheists As "Other": Moral Boundaries and Cultural Membership in American Society |journal=American Sociological Review |volume=71 |issue=2 |page=218 |id= |url=http://www.soc.umn.edu/~hartmann/files/atheist%20as%20the%20other.pdf|quote= |doi=10.1177/000312240607100203}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Many of the respondents associated atheism with [[immorality]], including criminal behaviour, extreme materialism, communism and [[elitism]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.authentichistory.com/1946-1960/4-cwhomefront/7-comics/tcgodless/This_Godless_Communism_1961.html&lt;/ref&gt; The studies also showed that rejection of atheists was related to the respondent's lack of exposure to diversity, education and political orientations.&lt;ref name="UMN News"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www1.umn.edu/news/news-releases/2006/UR_RELEASE_MIG_2816.html |title=Atheists identified as America's most distrusted minority, according to new U of M study |publisher=UMN News |accessdate=2006-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Atheists and atheist organizations have alleged discrimination against atheists in the military,&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|P7d2rpN4cc4|(2009). Mandatory Prayer in the Army}}. Retrieved on November 28, 2010{{dead link|date=December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.militaryatheists.org/ |title=MAAF (2009). Military Association of Atheists &amp; Freethinkers. Retrieved November 28, 2010 from http |publisher=militaryatheists.org|date=27 April 2011 |accessdate=4 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armytimes.com/news/2008/09/airforce_lakenheath_suit_093008/ |author=LaGrone, S.|date=September 30, 2008|title=Soldier alleges religious bias at Lakenheath|publisher=Armytimes.com |accessdate=4 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.militaryreligiousfreedom.com|title=MILITARYRELIGIOUSFREEDOM.COM|publisher=|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/11/02/air-force-academy-cites-p_n_777937.html |author1=Jones, W. |title=Air Force Academy Cites Progress In Tackling Religious Intolerance|work=Huffington Post  |date=28 September 2010 |accessdate=4 December 2011 |editor=Fleet, Josh}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.militaryatheists.org/rptchap.html |title=Military Association of Atheists and Freethinkers Report on chaplains|publisher=militaryatheists.org|accessdate=4 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and recently, with the development of the [[Comprehensive Soldier and Family Fitness|Army's Comprehensive Soldier Fitness program]], atheists have alleged [[institutionalized discrimination]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/01/06/army-faces-questions-over_n_805524.html|author= Banks, Adelle|title= Army Faces Questions Over 'Spiritual Fitness' Test|work=Huffington Post  |date=16 January 2011 |accessdate=4 December 2011 |editor=Fleet, Josh}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.militaryreligiousfreedom.org/docs/spirituality_testing_cnd.pdf |work=MAAF|date=December 30, 2010|title=The Comprehensive Soldier Fitness Program's Unconstitutional Soldier Fitness Tracker and Global Assessment Tool |format=PDF |accessdate=4 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In several [[child custody]] court rulings, atheist parents have been discriminated against, either directly or indirectly. As [[child custody laws in the United States]] are often based on the subjective opinion of family court judges, atheism has frequently been used to deny custody to non-religious parents on the basis that a parent's lack of faith displays a lack of morality require to raise a child.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www2.law.ucla.edu/volokh/custody.pdf|year=2006|format=PDF|title=Parent-child speech and child custody speech restrictions|first=Eugene|last=Volokh|journal=New York University Law Review|volume=81|page=631}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.pitzer.edu/academics/faculty/zuckerman/Zuckerman_on_Atheism.pdf|title=Atheism, Secularity, and Well-Being: How the Findings of Social Science Counter Negative Stereotypes and Assumptions|first=Phil|last=Zuckerman|journal=Sociology Compass|volume=3|issue=6|year=2009|pages=949–971|doi=10.1111/j.1751-9020.2009.00247.x|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141228104545/http://www.pitzer.edu/academics/faculty/zuckerman/Zuckerman_on_Atheism.pdf|archivedate=28 December 2014 |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prominent atheists and atheist groups have said that discrimination against atheists is illustrated by a statement reportedly made by [[George H. W. Bush]] during a public press conference just after announcing his candidacy for the presidency in 1987.&lt;ref name="dawkins" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.atheistsforhumanrights.org/mugged.htm
|title= Your money and/or your life: mugged by the mythmakers
|publisher=Atheists For Human Rights
|accessdate=2009-02-27
|last=Castle
|first=Marie Alena
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.positiveatheism.org/writ/ghwbush.htm
|title=George H. W. Bush: "Atheists Neither Citizens Nor Patriots
|publisher=American Atheists
|accessdate=2009-02-27
|last=O'Hair
|first=Madalyn
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="saxon"&gt;{{cite news|title= Godless in Tucson; Atheists—the least-trusted group in America—speak out|last=Burns|first=Saxon|date=30 November 2006 |work=Tucson Weekly|url=http://www.tucsonweekly.com/gbase/Currents/Content?oid=89764|accessdate=2009-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; When asked by journalist Robert Sherman about the equal citizenship and patriotism of American atheists, Sherman reported that Bush answered, "No, I don't know that atheists should be regarded as citizens, nor should they be regarded as patriotic. This is one nation under God."&lt;ref name="dawkins" /&gt;&lt;ref name="saxon" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Frequently misquoted as "No, I don't know that atheists should be considered as citizens, nor should they be considered patriots.", starting with {{cite journal |date=Fall 1988 | title = On the Barricades: Bush on Atheism&lt;!--column title: news brief title--&gt; | author = GALA Interim&lt;!--attribution of news brief--&gt; | journal = [[Free Inquiry]] | volume = 8 | issue = 4 | issn = 0272-0701 | page = 16 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; Sherman did not tape the exchange and no other newspaper ran a story on it at the time.&lt;ref name="dawkins"&gt;{{cite book|last=Dawkins|first=Richard|title=The God Delusion|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|year=2006|pages=43–46|isbn=978-0-618-68000-9|url=https://books.google.com/?id=yq1xDpicghkC&amp;pg=PA43}}&lt;/ref&gt;

George H. W. Bush's son, [[George W. Bush]], responded to a question about the role of faith in his presidency during a November 3, 2004 press conference, "I will be your president regardless of your faith. And I don't expect you to agree with me, necessarily, on religion. As a matter of fact, no president should ever try to impose religion on our society. The great - the great tradition of America is one where people can worship the - the way they want to worship. And if they choose not to worship, they're just as patriotic as your neighbor."&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/04/politics/04BUSHTRANS.html?pagewanted=4
|title= Transcript of President Bush's News Conference
|publisher=New York Times
|accessdate=2012-01-17
|date=4 November 2004
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
{{anchor|seven}}

=====Atheists ineligible to hold office=====

The constitutions of seven "[[Bible Belt]]" U.S. states ban atheists from holding public office. However, these laws are unenforceable due to conflicting with the first amendment and article VI of the constitution:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/articlevi|title=Article VI|publisher=Legal Information Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/first_amendment|title=U.S. Constitution – First Amendment|publisher=Legal Information Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:Arkansas:
::Article 19, Section 1
::"No person who denies the being of a God shall hold any office in the civil departments of this State, nor be competent to testify as a witness in any Court."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Constitution of the State of Arkansas|url=http://www.arkleg.state.ar.us/assembly/Summary/ArkansasConstitution1874.pdf|publisher=Arkansas State Legislature|location=Little Rock, AR|accessdate=17 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:Maryland:
::Article 37
::"That no religious test ought ever to be required as a qualification for any office of profit or trust in this State, other than a declaration of belief in the existence of God; nor shall the Legislature prescribe any other oath of office than the oath prescribed by this Constitution."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msa.md.gov/msa/mdmanual/43const/html/00dec.html|title=Constitution of Maryland|date=June 10, 2011|publisher=Maryland State Archives|accessdate=17 July 2012|location=Annapolis, MD}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:Mississippi:
::Article 14, Section 265
::"No person who denies the existence of a Supreme Being shall hold any office in this state."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sos.ms.gov/links/ed_pubs/pubs/Mississippi_Constitution.pdf |title=Constitution of the State of Mississippi |publisher=Secretary of State, State of Mississippi |page=117 |accessdate=17 July 2012 |location=Jackson, MS |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150421040130/http://www.sos.ms.gov/links/ed_pubs/pubs/Mississippi_Constitution.pdf |archivedate=21 April 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
:North Carolina:
::Article 6, Section 8
::"The following persons shall be disqualified for office: First, any person who shall deny the being of Almighty God."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncga.state.nc.us/legislation/constitution/ncconstitution.html|title=North Carolina State Constitution Article VI Section 8.|accessdate=2012-12-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:South Carolina:
::Article 17, Section 4
::"No person who denies the existence of a Supreme Being shall hold any office under this Constitution."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scstatehouse.gov/scconstitution/a17.php|title=South Carolina Constitution Article 17 Section 4.|accessdate=2012-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:Tennessee:
::Article 9, Section 2
::"No person who denies the being of God, or a future state of rewards and punishments, shall hold any office in the civil department of this state."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Tennessee Blue Book 2011-2012|url=http://www.tn.gov/sos/bluebook/11-12/TS5_TNFoundingDocs.pdf|publisher=Secretary of State, State of Tennessee|location=Nashville, TN|chapter=Article IX, Disqualifications}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:Texas:
::Article 1, Section 4
::"No religious test shall ever be required as a qualification to any office, or public trust, in this State; nor shall any one be excluded from holding office on account of his religious sentiments, provided he acknowledge the existence of a Supreme Being."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.statutes.legis.state.tx.us/Docs/CN/htm/CN.1.htm|title=Texas Constitution, Article 1, Section 4.|accessdate=2012-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An eighth state constitution affords special protection to theists.
:Pennsylvania:
::Article 1, Section 4
::"No person who acknowledges the being of a God and a future state of rewards and punishments shall, on account of his religious sentiments, be disqualified to hold any office or place of trust or profit under this Commonwealth."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://sites.state.pa.us/PA_Constitution.html | title=Pennsylvania Constitution, Article 1, Section 4.| accessdate=2012-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic countries===
{{see also|Persecution of atheists in the Middle East|Islam and atheism|Apostasy in Islam}}
Atheists, and those accused of defection from the official religion, may be subject to discrimination and persecution in many Islamic countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/12/10/us-religion-atheists-idUSBRE8B900520121210|title=Atheists around world suffer persecution, discrimination: report|author=Robert Evans|date=Dec 9, 2012|newspaper=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[International Humanist and Ethical Union]], compared to other nations, "unbelievers... in Islamic countries face the most severe – sometimes brutal – treatment".&lt;ref name= "iheu report"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://iheu.org/story/you-can-be-put-death-atheism-13-countries-around-world|title=International Humanist and Ethical Union - You can be put to death for atheism in 13 countries around the world|publisher=|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Atheists and religious skeptics can be executed in at least thirteen nations: [[Afghanistan]], [[Iran]], [[Malaysia]], [[Maldives]], [[Mauritania]], [[Nigeria]], [[Pakistan]], [[Qatar]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Somalia]], [[Sudan]], the [[United Arab Emirates]] and [[Yemen]].&lt;ref name=reuters131210&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/12/10/us-religion-atheists-idUSBRE9B900G20131210|title=Atheists face death in 13 countries, global discrimination: study|author=Robert Evans|date=December 9, 2013|publisher=[[Reuters]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url = http://freethoughtreport.com/download-the-report/|title = International Humanist and Ethical Union (IHEU),|date = 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to popular interpretations of Islam, Muslims are not free to change religion or become an atheist: denying Islam and thus becoming an [[apostasy|apostate]] is traditionally punished by death for men and by life imprisonment for women. The death penalty for apostasy is apparent in a range of Islamic states including: Iran,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/middleeast/iran/3179465/Hanged-for-being-a-Christian-in-Iran.html|title=Hanged for being a Christian in Iran|date=11 October 2008|work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2011/01/31/uk-iran-execution-apostasy-idUKTRE70U41D20110131|title=Iran hangs man convicted of apostasy|publisher=[[Reuters]]|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Egypt,&lt;ref name="Supporting Islam's apostates"&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2007/sep/17/supportingislamsapostates, "Supporting Islam's apostates"]&lt;/ref&gt; Pakistan,&lt;ref name="Supporting Islam's apostates"/&gt; Somalia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/7833621.stm|title=Somali executed for 'apostasy'|work=[[BBC News]]|publisher=[[BBC]]|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; United Arab Emirates,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://freedomcenterstudents.org/2010/05/crimes-punishable-by-death-in-the-uae-include-apostasy/|title=Crimes punishable by death in the UAE include…apostasy - Freedom Center Students|publisher=|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Qatar,&lt;ref name=barnabasfund&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.barnabasfund.org/news/archives/article.php?ID_news_items=295|title=/news/archives/article.php|publisher=|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yemen&lt;ref name=barnabasfund/&gt; and Saudi Arabia.&lt;ref name="Supporting Islam's apostates"/&gt; Although there have been no recently reported executions in Saudi Arabia,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ctv.ca/CTVNews/World/20060327/muslims_conversion_060327/ CTV news, "'Apostasy' laws widespread in Muslim world"], quote: "Islamic Shariah law considers conversion to any religion apostasy and most Muslim scholars agree the punishment is death. Saudi Arabia considers Shariah the law of the land, though there have been no reported cases of executions of converts from Islam in recent memory."&lt;/ref&gt; a judge in Saudi Arabia has recently recommended that imprisoned blogger [[Raif Badawi]] go before a high court on a charge of apostasy, which would carry the death penalty upon conviction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Abdelaziz |first=Salma |date=2013-12-26 |title=Wife: Saudi blogger recommended for apostasy trial |url=http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/25/world/meast/saudi-blogger-death-sentence/index.html |publisher=Cnn.com |accessdate=2014-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; While a death sentence is rare, it is common for atheists to be charged with blasphemy or inciting hatred.&lt;ref name=Econ20121124&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.economist.com/news/international/21567059-ex-muslim-atheists-are-becoming-more-outspoken-tolerance-still-rare-no-god-not|title=No God, not even Allah: Ex-Muslim atheists are becoming more outspoken, but tolerance is still rare|date=Nov 24, 2012|newspaper=Economist}}&lt;/ref&gt; New "Arab Spring" regimes in Tunisia and Egypt have jailed several outspoken atheists.&lt;ref name=Econ20121124 /&gt;

Since an apostate can be considered a Muslim whose beliefs cast doubt on the Divine, and/or [[Koran]], claims of atheism and [[apostasy]] have been made against Muslim scholars and political opponents throughout history.&lt;ref name="kamrava"&gt;{{cite book|last=Kamrava|first=Mehran|title=The new voices of Islam: reforming politics and modernity : a reader |publisher=I.B.Tauris|year=2006|pages=123–24|isbn=978-1-84511-275-2|url=https://books.google.com/?id=wTYJv7mwCoIC&amp;pg=PA123}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="isbn90-411-1105-0"&gt;{{cite book| last = Hamad|first= Ahmad| chapter= Legal plurality and legitimation of human rights abuses | editors = Al-Zwaini, Laila; Baudouin Dupret; Berger, Maurits | title = Legal pluralism in the Arab world | publisher = Kluwer Law International | location = The Hague | year = 1999 | page = 221 | isbn = 90-411-1105-0 | oclc = | url = https://books.google.com/?id=VAcOB1eMa5QC&amp;pg=PA221 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="apost"&gt;{{cite book | author = Zaki Badawi, M.A.| chapter= Islam | title = Encyclopedia of religious freedom | editor= Cookson, Catharine| publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 2003 | pages = 204–8| isbn = 0-415-94181-4 | oclc = | url = https://books.google.com/?id=R0PrjC1Ar7gC&amp;pg=PA206 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Both fundamentalists and moderates agree that "blasphemers will not be forgiven" although they disagree on the severity of an appropriate punishment.&lt;ref name=Econ20121124/&gt; In northwestern [[Syria]] in 2013 during the [[Syrian Civil War]], [[Islamic extremism|jihadists]] beheaded and defaced a sculpture of [[Al-Maʿarri]] (973–1058 CE), one of several outspoken Arab and Persian atheist intellectuals who lived and taught during the [[Islamic Golden Age]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/02/12/us-syria-crisis-statue-idUSBRE91B13420130212 ''Syria Violence Claims Head of Ancient Arab Poet'']. Reuters, 12 Feb. 2013. Accessed 15 Dec. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://observers.france24.com/content/20130214-jihadists-behead-statue-syrian-poet-abul-ala-al-maari ''Jihadists Behead Statue of Syrian Poet Abul Ala Al-Maari'']. The Observers, France 24. 14 Feb. 2013. Accessed 15 Dec. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jordan]] requires atheists to associate themselves with a recognized religion for official identification purposes.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2008/108485.htm
|title=International Religious Freedom Report 2008-Jordan
|publisher= US of Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor
|accessdate=2009-03-14
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
In [[Egypt]], intellectuals suspected of holding atheistic beliefs have been prosecuted by judicial and religious authorities.  Novelist Alaa Hamad was convicted of publishing a book that contained atheistic ideas and apostasy that were considered to threaten national unity and social peace.&lt;ref name="boyle"&gt;{{cite book|last=Boyle|first=Kevin|author2=Sheen, Juliet |title=Freedom of Religion and Belief: A World Report  |publisher=Routledge |year=1997|page=30|isbn=978-0-415-15978-4|url=https://books.google.com/?id=MFUZkWWgOtMC&amp;pg=RA1-PA30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="al"&gt;{{cite book | author =Al-Boray, Nagad | chapter= Egypt| title = Secrecy and Liberty: National Security, Freedom of Expression and Access to Information (International Studies in Human Rights) | publisher = Springer | location = Berlin | year = 1999 | isbn = 90-411-1191-3 | oclc = | url = https://books.google.com/?id=72IynQKXt3sC&amp;pg=PA251}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Algeria====
The study of Islam is a requirement in public and private schools for every Algerian child, irrespective of his/her religion.

Atheist or agnostic men are prohibited from marrying Muslim women ([[Algerian Family Code]] I.II.31).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lexalgeria.net/droitdelafamille.htm |title=de beste bron van informatie over Lexalgeria. Deze website is te koop! |publisher=lexalgeria.net |date=2 January 2011 |accessdate=4 December 2011|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040623101746/http://www.lexalgeria.net/droitdelafamille.htm|archivedate=23 June 2004 |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; A marriage is legally nullified by the apostasy of the husband (presumably from Islam, although this is not specified; Family Code I.III.33).
Atheists and agnostics cannot inherit (Family Code III.I.138).

====Bangladesh====
{{main|Attacks on secularists in Bangladesh}}
{{See also|Persecution of atheists in Bangladesh|Religion in Bangladesh#Atheism|Freedom of religion in Bangladesh#Persecution of atheists}}
Several Bangladeshi atheists have been assassinated, and a "hit list" exists issued by the Bangladeshi Islamic extremist organization, the ''[[Ansarullah Bangla Team]]''.  Activist atheist bloggers are leaving Bangladesh under threat of assassination.&lt;ref name=Bengali_assassination_of_atheists&gt;{{Cite news |first1 = Staff |last1 = Writer  |title = ‘You’ll be next’: Bangladeshi blogger gets death threat on Facebook |publisher = The times of India |date = May 30, 2015 |location = Kolkata |newspaper = Times of India |url = http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/world/south-asia/Youll-be-next-Bangladeshi-blogger-gets-death-threat-on-Facebook/articleshow/47477859.cms}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Indonesia====
{{Further|Anti-atheist sentiment in Indonesia}}
{{See also|Religion in Indonesia#Atheism|Islam in Indonesia#Religious freedom}}
Atheists in [[Indonesia]] experience official discrimination in the context of registration of births and marriages, and the issuance of identity cards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90137.htm
|title=International Religious Freedom Report 2007-Indonesia
|publisher= US of Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor
|accessdate=2009-03-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, Indonesian atheist [[Alexander Aan]] was beaten by a mob, lost his job as a civil servant and was sentenced to two and a half years in jail for expressing his views online.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejakartaglobe.com/archive/amnesty-calls-for-release-of-jailed-indonesian-atheist/524453/|title=Amnesty Calls for Release of Jailed Indonesian Atheist|work=Jakarta Globe|date= 15 June 2012|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130921223626/http://www.thejakartaglobe.com/archive/amnesty-calls-for-release-of-jailed-indonesian-atheist/524453/|archivedate=21 September 2013|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/may/03/indonesia-atheists-religious-freedom-aan|title=Indonesia's atheists face battle for religious freedom|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=3 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Iran====
{{Further|Irreligion in Iran}}
In Iran, atheism is not recognised as a belief in a legal sense. The law specifies that all citizens must declare themselves as Muslim, Christian, Jewish or Zoroastrian, with adherents of the latter three religions counted as religious minorities. The four recognised religions provide rights such as applying for entrance to university,&lt;ref name="fidh.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fidh.org/IMG/pdf/ir0108a.pdf|title=Discrimination against religious minorities in IRAN|date=August 2003|work=Fédération Internationale des Ligues des Droits de l`Homme and the Ligue de Défense des Droits de l'Homme en Iran|accessdate=2009-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Iranian Atheists Association: Issues|publisher= Iranian Atheists Association|url= https://iranianatheists.org/issues-1.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; or becoming a lawyer, with the position of judge reserved for Muslims only.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/MDE13/045/2001/en/73a8bc2a-d8ae-11dd-ad8c-f3d4445c118e/mde130452001en.html
|title=Iran: A legal system that fails to protect freedom of expression and association
|publisher=Amnesty International
|accessdate=2009-03-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Penal Code is also based upon the religious affiliation of the victim and perpetrator, with the punishment oftentimes more severe on non-Muslims.&lt;ref name="fidh.org"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Apostasy in the Islamic Republic of Iran|url=http://www.iranhrdc.org/english/publications/reports/1000000512-apostasy-in-the-islamic-republic-of-iran.html|website=Iranian Human Rights Documentation Center|accessdate=22 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous writers, thinkers and philanthropists have been accused of apostasy and sentenced to death for questioning the prevailing interpretation of Islam in Iran.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Iranian Writer Sentenced to Death for Apostasy|url=http://www.iranhrdc.org/english/news/inside-iran/1000000588-iranian-writer-sentenced-to-death-for-apostasy.html|website=Iran Human Rights Documentation Center|accessdate=22 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Human Rights Questions: Human Rights Situations and Reports of Special Rapporteurs and Representatives -- Situation of Human Rights in the Islamic Republic of Iran|url=http://www.iranhrdc.org/english/human-rights-documents/aadel-collection/11756-human-rights-questions-human-rights-situations-and-reports-of-special-rapporteurs-and-representatives-situation-of-human-rights-in-the-islamic-republic-of-iran.html|website=Iran Human Rights Documentation Center|accessdate=22 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Witness Statement: Mahmoud Roghani|url=http://www.iranhrdc.org/english/publications/witness-testimony/1000000543-witness-statement-of-hasan-yousefi-eshkevari.html|website=Iran Human Rights Documentation Center.|accessdate=22 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The Iranian Atheists Association was established in 2013 to form a platform for Iranian atheists to start debates and to question the current Islamic regime's attitude towards atheists, apostasy, and human rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Iranian Atheists Association: About Us|publisher= Iranian Atheists.org |date=|url= http://Iranianatheists.org/about-us.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Saudi Arabia====
{{Main|Irreligion in Saudi Arabia}}
Atheism is prohibited in [[Saudi Arabia]] and can come with a [[Capital punishment in Saudi Arabia|death penalty]], if one is charged as an atheist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Why Are Saudis Tearing Up the Quran? |publisher= [[Vocativ]]|date=|url= 
http://www.vocativ.com/world/saudi-arabia-world/blasphemy-land-two-holy-mosques/|accessdate=2014-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Atheists Classified As Terrorists Under New Saudi Arabian Laws |publisher= [[Huffington Post]]|date=|url= 
http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/2014/04/02/atheists-classified-terrorists-new-saudi-arabian-laws_n_5075129.html?utm_hp_ref=uk-religion|accessdate=2014-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Saudi Arabia: A wave of atheism or a misunderstanding|publisher= [[Al Arabiya]]|date=|url= http://english.alarabiya.net/views/2012/05/23/215974.html|accessdate=2012-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2014, the Saudi interior ministry issued a royal decree branding all atheists as terrorists, which defines [[terrorism]] as "calling for atheist thought in any form, or calling into question the fundamentals of the Islamic religion on which this country is based".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Adam Withnall |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/saudi-arabia-declares-all-atheists-are-terrorists-in-new-law-to-crack-down-on-political-dissidents-9228389.html |title=Saudi Arabia declares all atheists are terrorists in new law to crack down on political dissidents - Middle East - World |publisher=The Independent |date=1 April 2014 |accessdate=27 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Turkey====
{{Further|Irreligion in Turkey}}
Although officially a secular state, the vast majority of Turks are Muslim, and the state grants a number of special privileges to Muslims and to Islam itself. Compulsory religious instruction in [[Turkey|Turkish]] schools is also considered discriminatory towards atheists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/docid/47665e602.html|title= A Quest for Equality: Minorities in Turkey|year= 2007|publisher= Minority Rights Group International|accessdate=2009-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Atheists and agnostics are also not counted in the official census of the country.

==See also==
{{div col|3}}
*[[American Humanist Association]]
*[[Atheist Bus Campaign]]
*[[Boy Scouts of America membership controversies]]
*[[Center for Inquiry]]
*[[Christian privilege]]
*[[International Humanist and Ethical Union]]
*[[McCarthyism]]
*[[Military Association of Atheists &amp; Freethinkers]]
*[[Out Campaign]]
*[[Persecution by Christians]]
*[[Religious persecution]]
*[[Religious discrimination]]
*[[Richard Dawkins Foundation for Reason and Science]]
*[[Secular Coalition for America]]
*[[Atheist Centre]]
*[[Secularization]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|atheophobia}}
* [http://www.americanhumanist.org/system/storage/63/14/a/3436/2012_IRF_Report.pdf 2012 report on discrimination against atheists, humanists and the non-religious]
* [http://nation.com.pk/blogs/27-Sep-2015/atheistophobia-it-s-time-to-talk-about-the-most-persecuted-minority-in-the-world Atheistophobia: It’s time to talk about the most persecuted minority in the world]
{{Discrimination}}
{{Irreligion}}
{{Belief systems}}
{{Religious persecution}}
{{Portal bar|Discrimination|Atheism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Discrimination Against Atheists}}
[[Category:Atheism]]
[[Category:Religious discrimination|Atheists]]
[[Category:Religious persecution|Atheists]]
[[Category:Discrimination against atheists]]
[[Category:Persecution by Christians]]
[[Category:Persecution by Muslims]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination]]
[[Category:Discrimination|Atheists]]
[[Category:Persecution|Atheists]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>