<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071029013703|167753430" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7194871" pageid="7194871" ns="0" title="Discrimination against atheists"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-10-31T21:01:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{discrimination2}}
'''Discrimination against atheists''' is a negative categorical bias against [[atheism|atheists]] or [[secularism]]. Such prejudice and discrimination is a type of [[religious intolerance]] and a form of [[religious discrimination]]. Anti-atheist prejudice can be held by individuals or groups, and may be the result of religious [[fanaticism]] or [[bigotry]]. Anti-atheist discrimination is practised by members of religions, as well as opponents of secularism. As a mental and emotional attitude, anti-atheist discrimination leads to [[stereotyping]], [[hate]], and [[oppression]]. Anti-atheist prejudice results in the dissemination of [[hate speech]], the commission of [[hate crimes]], and the formation of hate groups, as well as other forms of discriminatory behaviour. Widespread anti-atheist discrimination may attach [[social stigma]] to atheists or those of secular beliefs, and may result in an experience of [[social inequality]] by atheists. In nations where [[freedom of religion|freedom of belief]] is biased towards established religions, the issue becomes [[persecution of atheists]].

==International examples==
===Denmark===
Even though religious freedom is guaranteed in the [[Danish constitution]] some laws exists that are considered discriminatory against non-religious citizens.
* Denmark has an official state church, the [[Danish National Church]].
* The state church is partially subsidized by public funds. The state pays for the salaries and pensions of bishops, the pensions of priests and provost, 40 % of the salaries of priests and provosts and all expences concerning the conduction of church services in [[Ertholmene]]. Furthermore the state pays at least 14.000.000 [[Danish Krone|DKK]] each year for the restoration of churches, historical church interiors and historical grave sites.
* The king is required to be a member of the state church by the [[Constitution of Denmark|Danish Constitution]].
* Public schools teach a non-compulsory subject ''kristendomskundskab'' (Teachings on Christianity) that has Christianity as its main focus.
* Each year the [[Folketing|Danish parliament]] is opened with a church service.

===Norway===
In 2007, the European court of Human Rights ruled in favor of Norwegian parents who had sued the Norwegian state. The case was about a subject in compulsory school, ''kristendomskunnskap med religions- og livssynsorientering'' (Teachings of Christianity with orientation about religion and philosophy), KRL. The applicants complained that the refusal to grant full exemption from KRL prevented them from ensuring that their children received an education in conformity with their atheist views and philosophical convictions. A few years earlier, in 2004, the UN Committee on Human Rights in Geneva had given its support to the parents.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.human.no/templates/Page____6828.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sweden===
Even in [[Sweden]], generally considered one of the most secularized countries in the world,&lt;ref&gt;see e.g. [http://www.worldvaluessurvey.org/statistics/some_findings.html the Inglehart Values Map]&lt;/ref&gt; there exist laws that could be considered discriminatory towards atheists:

* The king of Sweden must according to the law be a Christian. This is seen as an endorsement of Christianity by many atheists. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.riksdagen.se/templates/R_PageExtended____6311.aspx The Act of Succession]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Until the year 2000, Sweden had an official state church. Even after the law was changed, there is a special law that regulates the church and its affairs.&lt;ref&gt;Lag (1998:1591) om Svenska kyrkan]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In many public schools, the commencement after each semester is held in a church and a priest delivers a sermon. Sometimes schools go to church to celebrate holidays. When atheists have objected to this "tradition", politicians have defended it. On the 26th of October 2006, the Swedish minister of schools, Jan Björklund, stated that "We should not have any general rules in Sweden that you may not continue to have school commencements or ceremonies in a church any longer. There will definitely be no change on that issue."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.riksdagen.se/webbnav/index.aspx?nid=101&amp;dok_id=GU0915&amp;bet=2006/07:15&lt;/ref&gt;

* In October 2006, the [[Humanisterna|Swedish Humanists]] filed a complaint to the [[ombudsmen]] of parliament&lt;ref&gt;Registration number [http://www.jo.se/Page.aspx?MenuId=106&amp;MainMenuId=106&amp;Language=sv&amp;ObjectClass=DynamX_SFS_Decision&amp;Id=2100 4882-2006]&lt;/ref&gt; and The Chancellor of Justice&lt;ref&gt;Registration number 6726-06-21&lt;/ref&gt; about sermons arranged by the parliament because, the Humanists claimed, it was contrary to secularization, and thus discriminating against non-Christians, including atheists. Both the ombudsmen and the chancellor concluded that they had no jurisdiction over the issue and chose not to comment further on the case. Thus, these sermons will continue.

* There is special funding to religious NGOs, "trossamfund", Lag (1998:1593) om trossamfund. According to Swedish law, in order to register a trossamfund one must organize divine services. Thus secular and/or atheist organisations who fill the same purpose as religious groups are discriminated from this funding. There is no equivalent funding for secular groups &lt;ref&gt;Lag (1998:1593) om trossamfund]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Victorian England ===
[[Image:Charles Bradlaugh.jpg|thumb|left|Charles Bradlaugh]]
In [[Victorian era|Victorian England]] the atheist [[Charles Bradlaugh]] was elected MP for [[Northampton]]. His request to be allowed to affirm on taking his seat was denied, and he was also prevented from taking the (religious) oath as an alternative. During the lengthy dispute, he was fined and even briefly imprisoned, despite being repeatedly elected to his office. Ultimately he was able to get a bill passed securing the right of affirmation.

===United States===
In the [[1988]] U.S. presidential campaign, Republican presidential candidate [[George H. W. Bush]] reportedly said, "I don't know that atheists should be regarded as citizens, nor should they be regarded as patriotic." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.RobSherman.com/information/liberalnews/2002/0303.htm|title=Vice President Bush Quote Regarding Atheists}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
In the United States, there is widespread disapproval of atheists. For example, according to motherjones.com, 52% of Americans claim they would not vote for a well-qualified atheist for president.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.MotherJones.com/news/exhibit/2004/09/09_200.html&lt;/ref&gt; More recently a 2007 Gallup poll produced nearly identical results.&lt;ref&gt;http://HotlineBlog.NationalJournal.com/archives/2007/02/usa_todaygallup_1.html&lt;/ref&gt; A 2006 study at the University of Minnesota showed atheists to be the most mistrusted minority among Americans. Notwithstanding such attitudes, atheists are legally protected from discrimination in the United States. They have been among the strongest advocates of the legal [[separation of church and state]]. American courts have regularly, if controversially, interpreted the constitutional requirement for separation of church and state as protecting the freedoms of non-believers, as well as prohibiting the establishment of any state religion. Atheists often sum up the legal situation with the phrase: ''Freedom of religion also means freedom from religion.''

In the 1994 case&lt;ref&gt;http://caselaw.lp.FindLaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=000&amp;invol=U10355&lt;/ref&gt; [[Board of Education of Kiryas Joel Village School District v. Grumet]], Justice Souter wrote in the opinion for the Court that: "''government should not prefer one religion to another, or religion to irreligion''." &lt;ref&gt;http://supct.Law.Cornell.edu/supct/html/93-517.ZS.html&lt;/ref&gt; [[Everson v. Board of Education]] established that "''neither a state nor the Federal Government can pass laws which aid one religion, aid all religions, or prefer one religion over another''". This applies the Establishment Clause to the states as well as the federal government. &lt;ref&gt;http://Atheism.About.com/library/decisions/religion/bl_l_BoEEverson.htm&lt;/ref&gt; However, several state constitutions make the protection of persons from religious discrimination conditional on their acknowledgement of the existence of a deity, apparently making freedom of religion in those states inapplicable to atheists. These state constitutional clauses have not been tested. Civil rights cases are typically brought in federal courts; so such state provisions are mainly of symbolic importance.

In the [[Elk Grove Unified School District v. Newdow|Newdow case]], after a father challenged the phrase "''under God''" in the United States [[Pledge of Allegiance]], the Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals found the phrase unconstitutional. Although the decision was stayed pending the outcome of an appeal, there was the prospect that the pledge would cease to be legally usable without modification in schools in the western United States, over which the Ninth Circuit has jurisdiction. This resulted in political furor, and both houses of Congress passed resolutions condemning the decision, unanimously.&lt;ref name="CNN_Senators..."&gt;http://Archives.CNN.com/2002/ALLPOLITICS/06/26/senate.resolution.pledge/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;. On June 26&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, a Republican dominated group of 100-150 congressmen stood outside the capital and recited the pledge - showing how much they disagreed with the decision.&lt;ref name="CNN_Senators..." /&gt; The Supreme Court subsequently reversed the decision, ruling that [[Michael Newdow]] did not have standing to bring his case, thus disposing of the case without ruling on the constitutionality of the pledge.

Several private organizations, the most notable being the [[Boy Scouts of America]], do not allow atheist members. However, this policy has come under fire by organizations who assert that the Boy Scouts of America do profit from taxpayer money and thus cannot be called a truly private organization, and thus must admit atheists (along with homosexuals and others currently barred from membership). An organization called [[Scouting for All]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ScoutingForAll.org&lt;/ref&gt; founded by [[Eagle Scout (Boy Scouts of America)|Eagle Scout]] [[Steven Cozza]], is at the forefront of the movement to expose perceived hypocrisy on the part of the Boy Scouts of America. Cozza and others allege that when the BSA wants to discriminate, they act as a private organization; when they want money or the use of publicly-funded buildings, venues, or property, they act as a public organization.

====State constitutions====   
Some state constitutions in the US require a religious test as a qualification for holding public office or being a witness, though a unanimous 1961 U.S. Supreme Court decision in [[Torcaso v. Watkins]] held that the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First]] and [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth]] Amendments to the federal Constitution override the state requirements.&lt;ref&gt;http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=367&amp;page=488&lt;/ref&gt; The states which still have religious tests on the books include:

* Arkansas' Constitution of 1874 (Article 19, Section 1) states: "Atheists disqualified from holding office or testifying as witness. No person who denies the being of a God shall hold any office in the civil departments of this State, nor be competent to testify as a witness in any Court."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sos.arkansas.gov/ar-constitution/arcart19/arcart19-1.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

* North Carolina's Constitution of 1971 (Article 6, Section 8) states: "Disqualifications of office. The following persons shall be disqualified for office: First, any person who shall deny the being of Almighty God...."&lt;ref&gt;http://statelibrary.dcr.state.nc.us/nc/stgovt/article_vi.HTM&lt;/ref&gt;. This was challenged and overturned by Voswinkel v. Hunt (1979).

* South Carolina's Constitution of 2006 (Article 6, Section 2) states: "Person denying existence of Supreme Being not to hold office. No person who denies the existence of the Supreme Being shall hold any office under this Constitution."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.scstatehouse.net/scconstitution/a06.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

* Tennessee's Constitution/Bill of Rights (Article 9, Section 2) states: "No person who denies the being of God, or a future state of rewards and punishments, shall hold any office in the civil department of this state."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tncrimlaw.com/law/constit/IX.html#2&lt;/ref&gt;

* Texas' Constitution: The Bill of Rights (Article I, Section 4) last amended on [[September 13]], [[2003]] states that an official may be "excluded from holding office" if she/he does not "acknowledge the existence of a Supreme Being."&lt;ref&gt;http://tlo2.tlc.state.tx.us/txconst/sections/cn000100-000400.html&lt;/ref&gt; Overturned by O'Hair v. Hill (1978-84).

* Maryland's Bill of Rights:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.msa.md.gov/msa/mdmanual/43const/html/00dec.html&lt;/ref&gt;
** Article 36: "That as it is the duty of every man to worship God in such manner as he thinks most acceptable to Him, all persons are equally entitled to protection in their religious liberty; wherefore, no person ought by any law to be molested in his person or estate, on account of his religious persuasion, or profession, or for his religious practice, unless, under the color of religion, he shall disturb the good order, peace or safety of the State, or shall infringe the laws of morality, or injure others in their natural, civil or religious rights; nor ought any person to be compelled to frequent, or maintain, or contribute, unless on contract, to maintain, any place of worship, or any ministry; nor shall any person, otherwise competent, be deemed incompetent as a witness, or juror, on account of his religious belief; provided, he believes in the existence of God, and that under His dispensation such person will be held morally accountable for his acts, and be rewarded or punished therefore either in this world or in the world to come."
** Article 37: "That no religious test ought ever to be required as a qualification for any office of profit or trust in this State, other than a declaration of belief in the existence of God; nor shall the Legislature prescribe any other oath of office than the oath prescribed by this Constitution."
**Overturned by SCOTUS in [[Torcaso v. Watkins]].&lt;ref&gt;http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=367&amp;page=488&lt;/ref&gt;

==Typology==
The first attempts to define or develop a typology of atheism were in religious [[apologetics]]. These attempts were expressed in terms and in contexts that reflected the religious assumptions and prejudices of the writers. A diversity of atheist opinion has been recognized at least since [[Plato]], and common distinctions have been established between ''practical atheism'' and ''speculative'' or ''contemplative atheism''.

Practical atheism was said to be caused by moral failure, hypocrisy, willful ignorance and infidelity. Practical atheists were said to behave as though God, morals, ethics and social responsibility did not exist; they abandoned duty and embraced hedonism. Maritain's typology of atheism&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| year=1953| last= Maritain| chapter= Chapter 8, The Meaning of Contemporary Atheism| first=Jacques| authorlink=Jacques Maritain| title=The Range of Reason| location=London| publisher= Geoffrey Bles| url=http://www.nd.edu/Departments/Maritain/etext/range08.htm| pages=103-117}} Note: Chapter 8 is reprinted from {{cite journal| journal=Review of Politics| volume=11| issue=3| month= July| year=1949| pages=267-280| url=http://www.nd.edu/Departments/Maritain/jm3303.htm| title=The Meaning of Contemporary Atheism}} A version also appears in {{cite journal| journal=The Listener| volume=43| issue=1102| month=9 March| year=1950| pages=427-429,432| title=The Meaning of Contemporary Atheism}}&lt;/ref&gt; proved influential in Catholic circles; it was followed in the ''[[New Catholic Encyclopedia]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Reid| year=1967| title=New Catholic Encyclopedia| first= J.P.| chapter=Atheism| location= New York| publisher=McGraw-Hill| pages=1000-1003}}&lt;/ref&gt; He identified, in addition to practical atheism, ''pseudo-atheism'' and ''absolute atheism'' (and subdivided theoretical atheism in a way that anticipated Flew). For an atheist critique of Maritain, see Smith (1979, Chapter 1, Section 5).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|url=http://www.positiveatheism.org/writ/smith.htm
|title=Atheism: The Case Against God
|first=George H.
|last=Smith
|publisher=Prometheus Books
|id=ISBN 0-87975-124-X
|year=1980
|authorlink=George H. Smith
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the French Catholic philosopher Étienne Borne, 'Practical atheism is not the denial of the existence of God, but complete godlessness of action; it is a moral evil, implying not the denial of the absolute validity of the moral law but simply rebellion against that law.'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| year=1961| pages=10| first=Étienne| last= Borne| title= Atheism| location=New York| publisher=Hawthorn Books}} [Originally published in France under the title Dieu n’est pas mort: essai sur l’atheisme contemporain. Librairie Arthème Fayard, 1959]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Karen Armstrong]] (1999):

&lt;blockquote&gt; During the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, the word 'atheist' was still reserved exclusively for polemic… In his tract ''Atheism Closed and Open Anatomized'' (1634), John Wingfield claimed: 'the hypocrite is an Atheist; the loose wicked man is an open Atheist; the secure, bold and proud transgressor is an Atheist: he that will not be taught or reformed is an Atheist'. For the [[Wales|Welsh]] poet [[William Vaughan (Welsh writer and colonial investor)|William Vaughan]] (1577 [sic]&amp;ndash;1641), who helped in the colonization of [[Colony of Newfoundland|Newfoundland]], those who raised rents or enclosed commons were obvious atheists. The English dramatist [[Thomas Nashe]] (1567-1601) proclaimed that the ambitious, the greedy, the gluttons, the vainglorious and prostitutes were all atheists. The term 'atheist' was an insult. Nobody would have dreamed of calling ''himself'' an atheist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=Karen| last=Armstrong| pages=331-332| year=1999| title=A History of God| location=London| publisher=Vintage| id= ISBN 0-09-927367-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

On the other hand, the existence of serious, speculative atheism was often denied. That anyone might ''reason'' their way to atheism was thought to be impossible. The existence of God was self-evident, and (apparently) necessary for the proper functioning of society. Thus, speculative atheism was collapsed into a form of practical atheism, and conceptualized as hatred of God or a fight against righteous social mores. This is why Borne finds it necessary to say, 'to put forward the idea, as some apologists rashly do, that there are no atheists except in name but only ''practical atheists'' who through pride or idleness disregard the divine law, would be, at least at the beginning of the argument, a rhetorical convenience or an emotional prejudice evading the real question.'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=Étienne| last=Borne| pages=18| year=1961| title=Atheism}}&lt;/ref&gt; Martin suggests that practical atheism would be better described as ''alienated theism''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Martin| year=1990| pages=465-466| first=Michael| title=Atheism: A philosophical justification| location= Philadelphia, PA| publisher=Temple University Press| id= ISBN 0-87722-943-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other pejorative definitions===
When denial of the existence of speculative atheism became unsustainable, atheism was nevertheless often repressed and criticized by narrowing definitions, applying charges of dogmatism, and otherwise misrepresenting atheist positions. One of the reasons for the popularity of euphemistic alternative terms like [[secularism|secularist]], [[empiricism|empiricist]], [[agnosticism|agnostic]], or [[Brights movement|bright]] is that ''atheism'' still has pejorative connotations arising from attempts at suppression and from its association with practical atheism. During the Cold War, U.S. politicians often characterized their foreign opponents as ''Godless Communists,'' and '''godless''' is still used as an abusive epithet today.

Mynga Futrell and Paul Geisert, the originators of the term ''bright'', made this explicit in an essay published in 2003:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Our personal frustration regarding labels reached culmination last fall when we were invited to join a march on Washington as 'Godless Americans'. The causes of the march were worthy, and the march itself well-planned and conducted. However, to unite for common interests under a disparaging term like 'godless' (it also means 'wicked') seemed ludicrous! Why accept and utilize the very derogatory language that so clearly hampers our own capacity to play a positive and contributing role in our communities and in the nation and world?&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.the-brights.net/vision/essays/futrell_geisert_nix.html
|title=Nixing "Nonbelief"—The Brights
|accessdate=2006-03-05
|first=Mynga
|last= Futrell
|coauthors= Paul Geisert
|year=2003
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Gaskin (1989) abandoned the term ''atheism'' in favor of ''unbelief'', citing 'the pejorative associations of the term, its vagueness, and later the tendency of religious apologists to define atheism so that no one could be an atheist...'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| editor=J.C.A. Gaskin| year=1989| pages=4 | title= Varieties of Unbelief: from Epicurus to Sartre| location= New York| publisher= Macmillan| id= ISBN 0-02-340681-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite these considerations, for others ''atheist'' has always been the preferred name. [[Charles Bradlaugh]] once said, in debate with [[George Jacob Holyoake]], [[10 March]] [[1870]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;I maintain that the opprobrium cast upon the word Atheism is a lie. I believe Atheists as a body to be men deserving respect... I do not care what kind of character religious men may put round the word Atheist, I would fight until men respect it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=Bradlaugh| last= Bonner| year=1908| pages=334| coauthors= Hypatia| title=Charles Bradlaugh: a record of his life and work| location= London| publisher=T. Fisher Unwin}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
*[[Boy Scouts of America membership controversies]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
For more on repressive definitions of atheism, see:

* Berman, David (1990). A History of Atheism in Britain: from Hobbes to Russell. London: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-04727-7.
* Berman, David (1983). David Hume and the Suppression of Atheism. in Journal of the History of Philosophy, Vol. 21 (3), July 1983, p.375-387.
* Berman, David (1982). The Repressive Denials of Atheism in Britain in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries in Proceedings of the Royal Irish Academy, Vol. 82c, (9), p.211-246.

{{Atheism}}
{{Belief systems}}

[[Category:Atheism]]
[[Category:Discrimination|Atheists]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>