<?xml version="1.0"?><api batchcomplete=""><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11185" pageid="11185" ns="0" title="Feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2001-11-07T20:08:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;b&gt;Feminism&lt;/b&gt; is a social and political movement that has been called "the radical notion that women are people" &lt;i&gt;(attributed to Cheris Kramer and Paula Treichler)&lt;/i&gt;. Note that by all but the most radical definitions, a "feminist" need not be a woman -  many men are proud to identify themselves as feminists.

Over the course of modern history, the immediate goals of feminists have changed to suit the times. However, the overarching goal has always been the promotion of equality for women both legally and socially. It has been argued that at times the movement has stepped far outside of that stated goal, which is probably true in some cases. Feminists in general take a holistic approach to politics, believing the saying of [[Martin Luther King Jr.]], "A threat to justice anywhere is a threat to justice everywhere". In that belief, feminists usually support other movements such as the [[civil rights movement]] and the [[gay rights movement]].

Feminism has effected many changes on society, including womens' suffrage, broad employment for women at equivalent wages ("equal pay for equal work"), the right to [[divorce]], the right to [[abortion]], and many others. As society has become increasingly accepting of feminist principles, some of these are no longer seen as specifically feminist, because they have been adopted by all or most people. Some beliefs that were radical for their time are now mainstream political thought. Almost no one in Western societies today questions the right of women to vote, a concept that seemed quite strange 200 years ago.

In some cases (notably equal pay for equal work) major advances have been made but feminists still struggle to achieve their complete goals.

Feminists are often proponents of [[political correctness]], using "Ms." to refer to both married and unmarried women, for example, or using the term [[herstory]] instead of [[history]]. This view of language is similar to the [[Sapir-Whorf hypothesis]], although feminists in most cases advance their desired language to affect the tone of political discourse rather than in the belief that language directly affects reality.

Some notable feminists include:

*[[Susan B. Anthony]]
*[[Susan Faludi]]
*[[Camile Pagilia]] 
*[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]
*[[Gloria Steinem]]
*[[Mary Wollstonecraft]]



----

See also [[Feminist Spirituality]], [[Feminist science fiction]]

See also [[Lesbian]] (suggest we leave this link here for convenience until more pages are produced.)

----

/Talk</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>