<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20021016085305|376499" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11185" pageid="11185" ns="0" title="Feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-10-22T09:39:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Feminism''' is the belief in political, economic, and social equality of the genders. It is a set of social theories and political practices that are critical of past and current social relations and primarily motivated and informed by the experience of women. Feminists take actions that they believe promote women's rights and interests.

Feminism questions the relationship between gender, sexuality, and power in social relationships.  The '''feminist movement''' (or '''equality feminism''') calls for social, economic, and/or political equality between genders through an increase in '''women's rights'''; central concerns include [[womens suffrage|women's suffrage]], salary equivalency, and control over [[reproductive issues|reproduction]].  

'''Gender feminism''', which argues that gender and sexuality are themselves social constructs, questions prevalent assumptions about gender and sexual difference.

'''Radical feminists''' consider [[patriarchy]] to be the root cause of most social problems.  Some radical feminists advocate separatism; others question not only the relationship between "men" and "women," but the very meaning of "man" and "woman" as well.  For radical feminists, feminism is the primary means to human liberation (i.e. the liberation of men as well as women, and men and women from other social problems).

Other feminists acknowledge that other problems (e.g. racism or class divisions) may be separate from or prior to patriarchy; they see feminism as one movement of liberation that is different from, but may and often must work alongside, other movements.  Many such feminists are more narrowly concerned with achieving equal rights for women. 

Although the leaders of feminism have been women, not all women are feminists and not all feminists are women.  Some feminists argue that men should not take positions of leadership in the movement, but most accept or seek the support of men.  Compare [[pro-feminist]], [[humanism]], [[masculism]]. 

==== History ====

Feminism began in the 19th century as a response to the perception that women are oppressed by a society in which most of the advantages fall upon males (see [[patriarchy]]), and the feminist movement is rooted in the West and especially the [[reform movement]] of the 19th century. The organised movement is dated from the first woman's rights convention at [[Seneca Falls convention|Seneca Falls]], New York, in 1848. Over a century and a half the movement has grown to include diverse perspectives on what constitutes discrimination against women. Early feminists are often called the [[first wave feminism|first wave]] and feminists after about 1960 the [[second wave feminists|second wave]].

==== Attitude towards men and women ====

The earliest works on 'the woman question' criticised the restrictive role of women without necessarily claiming that women were disadvantaged or that men were to blame. [[Mary Wollstonecraft]]'s ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Woman]]'' is one of the few works written before the 19th century that can unambiguously be called feminist.  By modern standards her metaphor of women as nobility, the elite of society, coddled, fragile and in danger of intellectual and moral sloth, sounds like a [[masculism|masculist]] argument.  Wollstonecraft believed that both sexes contributed to this situation and took it for granted that women had considerable power over men. 

In the [[United States]], this view had begun to evolve by the [[1830s]]. Early feminists active in the [[abolition movement]] began to increasingly compare women's situation with the plight of African American slaves.  This new polemic squarely blamed men for all the restrictions of women's role, and claimed that the relationship between the sexes was one-sided, controlling and oppressive.

Most of the early women's advocates were [[Christian|Christians]], especially [[Quakers]].  It started with [[Lucretia Mott]]'s involvement as one of the first women, allowed by the Quaker [[abolitionist]] men, to help out with the abolitionist movement.  The result was that [[Quaker]] women like Lucretia Mott learned how to organize and pull the levers of [[representative government]].  Starting in the mid-[[1830]]'s, they decided to use those skills for women's advocacy.  It was those early Quaker women who taught other women their advocacy skills, and for the first time used for exclusive women's advocacy.  As these new women's advocates began to expand on ideas about men and women, religious beliefs were also used to justify them. [[Sarah Grimke|Sarah Grimké]] suggested in her [[Sarah Grimke/Letters on the Equality of the Sexes|Letters on the Equality of the Sexes]] (1837) that the curse placed upon Eve in the Garden of Eden, was God's prophecy of a period of universal oppression of women by men.  Early feminists set about compiling lists of examples of women's plight, in foreign countries and in ancient times.  

At the [[Seneca Falls convention]] in 1848 [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] modeled her [[Seneca Falls declaration of sentiments|declaration of sentiments]] on the [[United States Declaration of Independence]]. Men were said to be in the position of a tyrannical government over women. This simplistic separation of the sexes into two warring camps was to become increasingly popular in feminist thought, despite the large number of reform minded men such as [[William Lloyd Garrison]] and [[Wendel Phillips]] who supported the early women's movement.

As the movement broadened to include many women like [[Susan B. Anthony]] from the [[temperance movement]], the slavery metaphor was joined by the stereotype of the drunkard husband who batters his wife. Feminist prejudice that women were morally superior to men reflected the social attitudes of the day. It also led to the to focus on women's suffrage over more practical issues in the latter half of the 19th century. Feminists assumed that once women had the vote, they would have the political will to deal with any other issues. 

[[Victoria Woodhull]] argued in the 1870's that the [[United_States_Constitution/Amendment_Fourteen|14th amendment]] to the [[United_States_Constitution]] already guaranteed equality of voting rights to women. She anticipated the arguments of the [[United_States_Supreme_Court]] a century later. But there was a strong movement opposed to suffrage, and it was delayed another 50 years, during which time most of the practical issues feminists campaigned for, including the [[United_States_Constitution/Amendment_Eighteen|18th amendment]]'s prohibition on alcohol, had already been won.

Feminists of the second wave focused more on lifestyle and economic issues; "The personal is the political" became a catchphrase.  As the reality of women's status increased, the feminist rhetoric against men became more vitriolic.  The dominant metaphor describing the relationship of men to women became rape; men raped women physically, economically and spiritually. [[radical feminism|Radical feminists]] argued that rape was the defining characteristic of men, and introduced a new phase of total hostility to maleness. [[lesbian separatist|Lesbian separatists]] even went so far as to condemn normal sexual relations with men.

Radical feminists, particularly [[Catharine MacKinnon]], began to dominate feminist jurisprudence.  Whereas [[first wave feminism]] had concerned itself with challenging laws restricting women, the second wave tended to campaign for laws that curtailed men's legal rights, or introduced explicit discrimination on the basis of gender.  The sentiment was that somehow men had it coming.  The feminist concept that men had universally oppressed women began to take on a legal status as judicial decisions echoed it, even in the [[United States Supreme Court]].  

One of the largest, earliest and most influential feminist organizations in the U.S., the [[National Organization for Women]] (NOW) illustrates the strong influence of [[radical feminism]].  Created in 1967 with [[Betty Friedan]] as president, the organization's name was deliberately chosen to say ''for women'', and not ''of women''. By 1968 the New York chapter lost many members who saw NOW as too mainstream.  There was constant friction, most notably over the defence of [[Valerie Solanas]]. Solanas had shot [[Andy Warhol]] after authoring the [[SCUM manifesto]], a hate filled anti-male propaganda manifesto, calling for the extermination of men.  [[Ti-Grace Atkinson]], the New York chapter president of NOW described her as, "the first outstanding champion of women's rights". Another member, [[Florynce Kennedy]] represented Solanas at her trial. Within a year of the split the new group limited the number of women members who live with men to 1/3 of the groups membership. By 1971, all married women were excluded from the breakaway group and Atkinson had also defected.

Friedan denounced the [[lesbian]] radicals as the [[lavender menace]] and tried to distance NOW from lesbian activities and issues.  The radicals accused her of [[homophobia]].  There was a constant fight for control of NOW which eventually Friedan lost.  By 1992 Olga Vives, chair of the NOW's national lesbian rights taskforce estimated that 40 percent of NOW members were lesbians. However NOW remains open to male members in contrast to some groups.

Feminists disagree over the role of men as participants within the movement. Some female feminists on college campuses feel that it is inappropriate to call feminist men 'feminist' and instead prefer the title [[pro-feminist]] man; however, in most of American society this terminology has not caught on. 

Feminists are sometimes wary of the [[transgender]]ed movement because they blur the distinction between men and women. Transgendered women are rejected by some feminists who say that no one born male can truly understand the oppression women face. On the other hand, transgendered women are quick to retort that the discrimination they face due to their gender identity more than makes up for any they may have "missed out on" growing up.

==== Relation to other movements ====

Most feminists take a holistic approach to politics, believing the saying of [[Martin Luther King Jr.]], "A threat to justice anywhere is a threat to justice everywhere". In that belief, feminists usually support other movements such as the [[civil rights movement]] and the [[gay rights movement]]. At the same time many black feminists such as [[bell hooks]] criticise the movement for being dominated by white women. Feminist claims about the disadvantages women face are often less relevant to the lives of black women. Many black feminist women prefer the term [[womanism]] for their views. This, however, is not strictly feminism; rather this is an intersection between feminism and other social movements.

==== Impact ====

Feminism has effected many changes on society, including women's suffrage, broad employment for women at more equitable wages ("equal pay for equal work"); the right to initiate [[divorce]] proceedings and "no fault" divorce; the right to control their own bodies and medical decisions, including obtaining birth control devices if unmarried,  [[abortion]], and many others.  Most feminists would argue, however, that there is still much to be done on these fronts.  As society has become increasingly accepting of feminist principles, some of these are no longer seen as specifically feminist, because they have been adopted by all or most people. Some beliefs that were radical for their time are now mainstream political thought. Almost no one in Western societies today questions the right of women to vote or own land, a concept that seemed quite strange 200 years ago.

In some cases (notably equal pay for equal work) major advances have been made but feminists still struggle to achieve their complete goals.

Feminists are often proponents of using [[non-sexist language]], using "[[Ms.]]" to refer to both married and unmarried women, for example, or the ironic use of the term [[herstory]] instead of [[history]]. They are also often proponents of using ''gender-inclusive'' language, such as "humanity" instead of "mankind", or "he or she" in place of "he" where the gender is unknown. Feminists in most cases advance their desired use of language either to promote a respectful treatment of women or to affect the tone of political discourse, rather than in the belief that language directly affects perception of reality (compare [[Sapir-Whorf hypothesis]]).

==== Perspective: the nature of the modern movement ====

Some modern feminists believe that much discrimination against women still exists in the USA and European nations.  

There is a great variety of ideas within the movement as to how much of a problem exists, and how to confront it. Extremes on the one hand include some radical feminists such as [[Mary Daly]] who advocate the genocide of men.  There are also dissidents, such as [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] or [[Camille Paglia]], who identify themselves as feminist but who accuse the movement of anti-male prejudices. Many feminists  question the use of the "feminist" label as applying to these individuals.

There are also debates between [[Difference Feminists]] such as [[Carol Gilligan]] on the one hand, who believe that there are important differences between the sexes (which may or may not be inherent, but which cannot be ignored), and those who believe that there are no essential differences between the sexes, and that the roles observed in society are due to conditioning.

==== Notable feminists: ====

Early pioneers

*[[George Sand]]

First wave

*[[Susan B. Anthony]]
*[[Sarah Grimke|The Grimké sisters]]
*[[Lucretia Mott]]
*[[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]]
*[[Frances Wright]]
*[[Lucy Stone]]
*[[Mary Wollstonecraft]]
*[[Victoria Woodhull]]
*[[Virginia Woolf]]

Second wave

*[[Simone de Beauvoir]]
*[[Susan Brownmiller]]
*[[Charlotte Bunch]]
*[[Mary Daly]]
*[[Angela Davis]]
*[[Andrea Dworkin]]
*[[Susan Faludi]]
*[[Shulamith Firestone]]
*[[Jo Freeman]]
*[[Marilyn French]]
*[[Betty Friedan]]
*[[Carol Gilligan]]
*[[Germaine Greer]]
*[[bell hooks]]
*[[Catharine MacKinnon]]
*[[Robin Morgan]]
*[[Alice Schwarzer]]
*[[Gloria Steinem]]
*[[Naomi Wolf]]

Ecofeminists

*[[Charlotte Perkins Gilman]]
*[[Carol J. Adams]]
*[[Helene Aylon]]
*[[Judi Bari]]
*[[Bernadette Cozart]]
*[[Françoise d'Eaubonne]]
*[[Lois Marie Gibbs]]
*[[Susan Griffin]]
*[[Petra Kelly]]
*[[Winona LaDuke]]
*[[Wangari Maathai]]
*[[Vandana Shiva]]
*[[Charlene Spretnak]]
*[[Starhawk]]

Dissident feminists

*[[Donna LaFramboise]]
*[[Wendy McElroy]]
*[[Camile Paglia]]
*[[Christina Hoff Sommers]]

Other Feminists

*[[Flora Brovina]]
*[[William Moulton Marston]]

----

See also [[Ecofeminism]], [[Feminist science fiction]], [[Feminist spirituality]], [[Feminist theology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>