<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071113013946|171098312" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11185" pageid="11185" ns="0" title="Feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-13T02:30:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{sprotected2}}
{{Feminism}} 
{{redirect|Feminists|list of feminists|List of feminists}}
'''Feminism''' comprises a number of social, cultural and [[political movement]]s, [[Theory|theories]] and [[Ethics|moral philosophies]] concerned with [[Discrimination#Gender discrimination|gender inequalities]] and [[Women's rights|equal rights for women]].  

According to some, the history of feminism consists of three waves.&lt;ref name=Humm&gt; Humm, Maggie. 1995. The Dictionary of Feminist Theory. Columbus: Ohio State University Press, p. 251&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Walker1992/&gt;  The first wave in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, the second in the 1960s and 1970s and the third from the 1990s to the present.&lt;ref name="Suffragettes to Grrls"/&gt;  Feminist Theory developed from the feminist movement.&lt;ref name=Chodorow1989/&gt;&lt;ref name=gilligan1977/&gt;  It takes a number of forms in a variety of disciplines such as [[feminist geography]], [[feminist history]] and [[feminist literary criticism]].  Feminism has changed aspects of Western society. Feminist political activists have been concerned with issues such as a woman's right of contract and property,  a woman's right to bodily integrity and [[autonomy]] (especially on matters such as [[reproductive rights]], including the right to [[abortion]], access to [[contraception]] and quality prenatal care); for protection from [[domestic violence]]; against [[sexual harassment]] and [[rape]];&lt;ref name=Echols&gt;Echols, Alice, Daring to Be Bad: Radical Feminism in America, 1967-1975’’ (University of Minnesota Press,1989) ISBN 978 0816617876&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Cornell&gt;Cornell, Drucilia, At the Heart of Freedom: Feminism, Sex, and Equality (Princeton UP,1998)   p. X, ISBN 978069102896-5&lt;/ref&gt; for workplace rights, including [[maternity leave]] and equal pay; and against other forms of discrimination.&lt;ref name=shildrick&gt;''Feminist Theory and the Body: A Reader'' ed. by Janet Price and Margrit Shildrick (Edinburgh University Press, 1999) ISBN 9780748610891&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Butler2/&gt;&lt;ref name=Messer-Davidow/&gt;  Throughout most of its history, most leaders of feminist social and political movements, and feminist theorists, have been middle-class white women, predominantly in Britain, France and the US.  At least since [[Sojourner Truth|Sojourner Truth's]] 1851 speech to US Feminists, however, [[multiracial feminism|women of other races]] have proposed alternative feminisms.  This trend accelerated in the 1960s with the Civil Rights movement in the United States and the collapse of European colonialism in Africa and Southeast Asia.  Since that time, women in former European colonies and the [[Third World]] have proposed alternative "post-colonial" and "Third World" feminisms as well.&lt;ref name=Narayan/&gt;  Some Third World feminists or [[postcolonial feminism|Postcolonial feminists]], such as [[Chandra Talpade Mohanty]], are critical of western feminism for being [[ethnocentric]].&lt;ref name=Mohanty/&gt;  Black feminists, such as [[Angela Davis]] and [[Alice Walker]], share this view.&lt;ref name=walker/&gt;''  

Since the 1980s, [[Standpoint feminism|standpoint feminists]] have argued that the feminist movement should address global issues (such as rape, [[incest]], and [[prostitution]]) and culturally specific issues (such as [[female genital mutilation]] in some parts of Africa and the Middle East and [[glass ceiling]] practices that impede women's advancement in developed economies) in order to understand how gender inequality interacts with [[racism]], [[homophobia]], [[lesbophobia]], [[colonialism]], and [[classism]] in a "matrix of domination."&lt;ref&gt;Hill Collins, P. (2000): ''Black Feminist Thought: Knowledge, consciousness, and the politics of empowerment'' (New York: Routledge)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Harding2003&gt; Harding, Sandra, ''The Feminist Standpoint Theory Reader: Intellectual and Political Controversies'' (Routledge, 2003), ISBN 9780415945011&lt;/ref&gt;  Some feminists have argued that gendered and sexed identities, such as "man" and "woman", are [[social construct]]s.&lt;ref name=debeauvoir1973/&gt;&lt;ref name=Butler/&gt;&lt;ref name=West&amp;Zimmerman&gt;Candace West and Don H. Zimmerman, 'Doing Gender'  in ''Gender and Society'', Vol. 1, No. 2(June, 1987) pp. 125-151&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of feminism==
[[Image:8marta.jpg|thumb|130px|A 1932 Soviet poster for [[International Women's Day]].]]
{{main|History of feminism}}
Feminists have divided feminism's history into three 'waves.' The [[First-wave feminism|first-wave]] refers to the feminism movement of the nineteenth through early twentieth centuries, which dealt mainly with the [[Women's Suffrage|Suffrage]] movement.  The [[Second-wave feminism|second-wave]] (1960s-1980s) dealt with the inequality of laws, as well as [[culture|cultural]] inequalities.  The [[Third-wave feminism|third-wave of Feminism]] (1990s-present), is seen as both a continuation and a response to the perceived failures of the second-wave.&lt;ref name="Suffragettes to Grrls"&gt;Krolokke, Charlotte  and Anne Scott Sorensen, 'From Suffragettes to Grrls' in ''Gender Communication Theories and Analyses:From Silence to Performance'' (Sage, 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

===First-wave feminism===
{{main|First-wave feminism}}
First-wave feminism  refers to a period of [[feminist]] activity during the nineteenth century and early twentieth century in the [[United Kingdom]] and the [[United States]]. Originally it focused on equal rights of contract and property and opposition to chattel marriage and ownership of married women (and their children) by husbands. [[Mary Wollstonecraft]]'s [[Vindication of the Rights of Women]] is considered the seminal essay of feminism. By the end of the nineteenth century, activism focused primarily on gaining political power -  the right of women's [[suffrage]], though feminists like [[Voltairine de Cleyre]] and [[Margaret Sanger]] were still active in campaigning for women's sexual and [[reproductive rights| reproductive]] and [[economic rights]] at this time. The term, "first-wave," was coined retrospectively after the term ''[[second-wave feminism]]'' began to be used to describe a newer feminist movement that focused as much on fighting social and cultural inequalities as further political inequalities.&lt;ref name=Freedman&gt; Freedman, Estelle B., ''No Turning Back: The History of Feminism and the Future of Women'' (London: Ballantine Books, 2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[UK|Britain]] the [[Suffragette]]s campaigned for the women's vote. In 1918 the [[Representation of the People Act 1918]] was passed granting the vote to women over the age of 30 who owned houses.  In 1928 this was extended to all women over eighteen.&lt;ref name=Phillips&gt; Phillips, Melanie, ''The Ascent of Woman: A History of the Suffragette Movement '' (Abacus, 2004), ISBN 9780349116600&lt;/ref&gt;  In the [[United States]] leaders of this movement include [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] and [[Susan B. Anthony]], who each campaigned for the abolition of slavery prior to championing women's right to vote. Other important leaders include [[Lucy Stone]], [[Olympia Brown]], and [[Helen Pitts]].  American first-wave feminism involved a wide range of women, some belonging to conservative Christian groups (such as [[Frances Willard (suffragist)|Frances Willard]] and the [[Woman's Christian Temperance Union]]), others resembling the diversity and radicalism of much of [[second-wave feminism]] (such as [[Matilda Joslyn Gage]] and the [[National Woman Suffrage Association]]).  In the [[United States]] first-wave feminism is considered to have ended with the passage of the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] (1919), granting women the right to vote.&lt;ref name= DuBois&gt; DuBois, Ellen Carol, ''Harriot Stanton Blatch and the Winning of Woman Suffrage'' (Yale University Press, 1997) ISBN 9780300065620&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Flexner&gt; Flexner, Eleanor, ''Century of Struggle: The Woman's Rights Movement in the United States'' (The Belknap Press, 1996), ISBN 9780674106539&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= Wheeler&gt; Wheeler, Marjorie Spruill, ed., ''One Woman, One Vote: Rediscovering the Woman Suffrage Movement'' (NewSage Press, 1995) ISBN 9780939165260&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Stevens&gt; Stevens, Doris, ''Jailed for Freedom: American Women Win the Vote'' (NewSage Press, 1995), ISBN 9780939165252&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second-wave feminism===
{{main|Second-wave feminism}}
Second-wave feminism refers to a period of feminist activity beginning in the early 1960s &amp; lasting through the late 1980s and, as Imelda Whelehan suggests, it was a continuation of the earlier phase of feminism that involved the suffragettes in the UK and USA.&lt;ref name=Whelehan&gt; Whelehan, Imelda , ''Modern Feminist Thought'' (Edinburgh UP, 1995), ISBN 9780748606214&lt;/ref&gt;  Second-wave Feminism has existed continuously since then, and continues to coexist with what is termed third-wave Feminism.  The second-wave feminism saw cultural and political inequalities as inextricably linked. The movement encouraged women to understand aspects of their own personal lives as deeply politicized, and reflective of a [[sexism|sexist]] structure of power. If first-wave feminism focused upon absolute rights such as suffrage, second-wave feminism was largely concerned with other issues of equality, such as the end to discrimination.&lt;ref name=Freedman/&gt;

Carol Hanisch with her essay ''The Personal is Political'' coined a slogan that became synonymous with the second-wave and was related to the women's liberation movement.&lt;ref name=Echols/&gt;

====Women's Liberation in the USA====
The phrase “Women’s Liberation” was first used in 1964,&lt;ref name="sarachild"&gt;Sarachild, Kathie. Consciousness-Raising: A Radical Weapon, in Sarachild, K, Hanisch, C, Levine, F, Leon, B, Price, C (eds.) Feminist Revolution. Random House N.Y. 1978 pp. 144-150.&lt;/ref&gt;
and appeared in print in 1966.&lt;ref name=Mitchell&gt; Mitchell, Juliet, 'Women: The longest revolution' in ''New Left Review'', 1966, Nov-Dec, pp. 11-37&lt;/ref&gt;  By 1968, although the term Women’s Liberation Front appeared in “[[Ramparts (magazine)|Ramparts]]” it was starting to refer to the whole women’s movement.&lt;ref name=Hinckle&gt;Hinckle, Warren and Marianne Hinckle. Women Power. Ramparts 1968 February 22-31&lt;/ref&gt;  [[History of brassieres#Feminist protests, Miss America and "Bra burning"|bra-burning]] became associated with the movement.&lt;ref name=Jo_Freeman&gt;Freeman, Jo. The politics of women's liberation. David McKay N.Y. 1975&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the most vocal critics of the whole movement has been [[bell hooks]], who
comments on a lack of voice by the most oppressed within the movement, and their glossing over of race and class, which she says was part of its failure to address "the issues that divided women".&lt;ref name=hooks1984&gt;hooks, bell, ''Feminist theory from margin to center'' (South End Press, 1984)&lt;/ref&gt;

=====The Feminine Mystique=====
[[Image:Mystique.jpg|thumb|120px|Betty Friedan's ''The Feminine Mystique'']]
{{main|The Feminine Mystique}}
''The Feminine Mystique'' was written in 1963 by Betty Friedan. It criticized the idea that women could only find fulfillment through childbearing and [[homemaker|homemaking]]. According to Friedan's obituary in the ''The New York Times'' ''The Feminine Mystique'' “ignited the contemporary women's movement in 1963 and as a result permanently transformed the social fabric of the United States and countries around the world” and “is widely regarded as one of the most influential nonfiction books of the 20th century.”&lt;ref name=NYTimes&gt; Fox, Margalit, 'Betty Friedan, Who Ignited Cause in 'Feminine Mystique,' Dies at 85' in ''The New York Times'' [[February 5]] [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt; In the book Friedan hypothesizes that women are victims of a false belief system that requires them to find identity and meaning in their lives through their husbands and children. Such a system causes women to completely lose their identity in that of their family. Friedan specifically locates this system among post-[[World War II]] [[middle-class]] [[suburban]] communities. At the same time, America's post-war economic boom had led to the development of new technologies that were supposed to make household work less difficult, but that often had the result of making women's work less meaningful and valuable. It also critiqued [[Freud]]'s theory of [[penis envy]] and was a factor in freeing women from being strictly confined to the role of a housewife during the Post-War economic expansion.&lt;ref name=Friedan&gt; Friedan, Betty, ''The Feminine Mystique'' (W.W. Norton and Company Inc., 1963), ISBN 9780393084361&lt;/ref&gt;



===Third-wave feminism===
{{main|Third-wave feminism}}
The Third-wave of feminism began in the early 1990s. The movement arose as a response to perceived failures of the second-wave. It was also a response to the backlash against initiatives and movements created by the second-wave.  Third-wave feminism seeks to challenge or avoid what it deems the second-wave's "[[Essentialism|''essentialist'']]" definitions of [[femininity]], which (according to them) over-emphasized the experiences of upper middle class white women.  A [[Post-structuralism|post-structuralist]] interpretation of gender and sexuality is central to much of the third-wave's ideology.  Third-wave feminists often focus on "micropolitics," and challenged the second-wave's paradigm as to what is, or is not, good for females.&lt;ref name=Freedman/&gt;&lt;ref name=Henry&gt; Henry, Astrid, ''Not My Mother's Sister: Generational Conflict and Third-Wave Feminism'' (Indiana University Press, 2003), ISBN 9780253217134&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gillis&gt; Gillis, Stacy, Gillian Howie &amp; Rebecca Munford (eds), ''Third Wave Feminism: A Critical Exploration'' (Palgrave Macmillan, 2007), ISBN 9780230521742&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Faludi&gt; Faludi, Susan, ''Backlash: The Undeclared War Against Women'' (Vintage, 1993), ISBN 9780099222712&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1991, [[Anita Hill]] accused Clarence Thomas, a man nominated to the Supreme Court, of sexual harassment.  Thomas denied the accusations and after extensive debate, the US Senate voted 52-48 in favor of Thomas.&lt;ref name=Gillis&gt; Gillis, Stacy, Gillian Howie &amp; Rebecca Munford, ''Third Wave Feminism: A Critical Exploration'' (Palgrave, 2004), ISBN 978140391821X&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Walker&gt; Walker, Rebecca, ''To Be Real: Telling the Truth and Changing the Face of Feminism'' (Anchor, 1995) ISBN 9780385472625&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Heywood&gt; Heywood, Leslie; Jennifer Drake eds., ''Third Wave Agenda: Being Feminist, Doing Feminism'' (University of Minnesota Press, 1997), ISBN 9780816630054&lt;/ref&gt;  In response to this case, [[Rebecca Walker]] published an article entitled "Becoming the Third Wave" in which she stated, "I am not a post-feminism feminist. I am the third-wave."&lt;ref name=Walker1992&gt; Walker, Rebecca, 'Becoming the Third Wave' in ''Ms.'' (January/February, 1992) pp. 39-41&lt;/ref&gt;

The third-wave has its origins in the mid 1980s. Feminist leaders rooted in the second-wave like [[Gloria Anzaldua]], [[bell hooks]], Chela Sandoval, [[Cherrie Moraga]], [[Audre Lorde]], [[Maxine Hong Kingston]], and many other black feminists, called for a new subjectivity in feminist voice.  They sought to negotiate prominent space within feminist thought for consideration of race related subjectivities.&lt;ref name=Gillis/&gt;&lt;ref name=Walker/&gt;&lt;ref name=Heywood/&gt;

===Contemporary feminism===
Contemporary feminism is made up of a number of different philosophical strands.  These movements sometimes disagree about current issues and how to confront them.  One side of the spectrum includes a number of radical feminists, such as [[Mary Daly]], who argue that society would benefit if there were dramatically fewer men.&lt;ref name=Daly&gt; Daly, Mary, ''Gyn/Ecology: Metaethics of Radical Feminism'' (Women's Press Ltd, 1979), ISBN 9780704338500&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, figures such as [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] and [[Camille Paglia]] identify themselves as feminist but accuse the movement of anti-male prejudice. &lt;ref name=sommers&gt; Sommers, Christina Hoff, ''Who Stole Feminism? - How women have betrayed women'' (Simon &amp; Schuster Ltd, 1996) ISBN 9780684801568&lt;/ref&gt;	&lt;ref name=paglia&gt; Paglia, Camille, ''Vamps and Tramps: New Essays'' (Penguin, 1995), ISBN 9780140248289&lt;/ref&gt;
Some feminists, like [[Katha Pollitt]] (see her book ''Reasonable Creatures'') or [[Nadine Strossen]], consider feminism to hold simply that "women are people." Views that separate the sexes rather than unite them are considered by these writers to be ''sexist'' rather than ''feminist''.&lt;ref name=Pollitt&gt; Pollitt, Katha, ''Reasonable Creatures: Essays on Women and Feminism '' (Vintage, 1995) ISBN 9780679762782&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Strossen&gt; Strossen, Nadine, ''Defending Pornography: Free Speech, Sex, and the Fight for Women's Rights'' (Prentice Hall &amp; IBD, 1995), ISBN 9780684197494&lt;/ref&gt;  There are also debates between [[difference feminism|difference feminists]] such as [[Carol Gilligan]], who believe that there are important differences between the sexes (which may or may not be inherent, but which cannot be ignored), and those who believe that there are no essential differences between the sexes, and that the societal roles are due to conditioning.&lt;ref name=Gilligan&gt; Gilligan, Carol, ''In a Different Voice: Psychological Theory and Women's Development '' (Harvard University Press, 1990), ISBN 9780674445444&lt;/ref&gt; [[Individualist feminist]]s such as [[Wendy McElroy]] are concerned with equality of rights, and criticize sexist/classist forms of feminism as "gender feminism."

===French feminism===
{{main|Feminism in France}}

==== Simone de Beauvoir ====
[[Image:0679724516.01.LZZZZZZZ.jpg|120px|thumb|''The Second Sex'' a major feminist work by [[Simone de Beauvoir]]]]
{{main|Simone de Beauvoir}}
[[Simone de Beauvoir]] was a [[France|French]] [[author]] and [[philosopher]]. She wrote novels, monographs on philosophy, politics, and social issues, essays, biographies, and an autobiography. She is now best known for her metaphysical novels, including ''She Came to Stay'' and ''[[The Mandarins]]'', and for her 1949 treatise ''[[The Second Sex]]'', a detailed analysis of women's oppression and a foundational tract of contemporary [[feminism]].
Simone de Beauvoir's ''The Second Sex'' was published in French in 1949.  It sets out a feminist existentialism which prescribes a moral revolution. As an existentialist, de Beauvoir accepts the precept that ''[[existence precedes essence]]''; hence "one is not born a woman, but becomes one". Her analysis focuses on the concept of [[Other|The Other]]. It is the (social) construction of Woman as the quintessential Other that Beauvoir identifies as fundamental to women's oppression.&lt;ref name=debeauvoir1973&gt; de Beauvoir, Simone The Second Sex(Vintage Books, 1973)&lt;/ref&gt;  She argues that women have historically been considered deviant, abnormal. She submits that even [[Mary Wollstonecraft]] considered men to be the ideal toward which women should aspire. Beauvoir says that this attitude has limited women's success by maintaining the perception that they are a deviation from the normal, and are outsiders attempting to emulate "normality". For feminism to move forward, this assumption must be set aside.&lt;ref name=debeauvoir1973/&gt;

====1970s - present====
French feminists approach feminism with a the concept of ''écriture féminine'' (which translates as female, or feminine, writing).&lt;ref name=Wright2000/&gt;  [[Helene Cixous]] argues that writing and philosophy are 'phallocentric' and along with other French feminists such as [[Luce Irigaray]] emphasize "writing from the body" as a subversive exercise.&lt;ref name=Wright2000/&gt;  Another theorist working in France (but originally from [[Bulgaria]]) is [[Julia Kristeva]], her work on [[Julia Kristeva#The semiotic|the semiotic]] and [[abjection]] has influenced feminist criticism.  However, as Elizabeth Wright points out, "none of these French feminists align themselves with the feminist movement as it appeared in the [[Anglophone]] world."&lt;ref name=Wright2000/&gt;&lt;ref name=Moi1986&gt; Moi, Toril, ed., ''The Kristeva Reader'' (Basil Blackwell, 1986)&lt;/ref&gt;



==Feminist theory==
{{main|Feminist theory}}
{{related|[[Feminist history]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Feminist geography]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Feminist sexology]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Feminist economics]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Psychoanalytic feminism]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Feminist philosophy]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Feminist anthropology]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Feminist film theory]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Feminist literary criticism]]}}

Feminist theory is the extension of feminism into theoretical, or [[philosophy|philosophical]], fields.  It encompasses work in a variety of disciplines, including approaches to women's roles and lived experiences; feminist politics in [[anthropology]] and [[sociology]], [[economics]], [[women's studies|women's]]; [[gender studies]]; [[feminist literary criticism]]; and [[philosophy]]&lt;ref&gt;Brabeck and Brown, 1997&lt;/ref&gt;.  Feminist theory aims to understand gender inequality and focuses on gender politics, power relations and sexuality.   While providing a critique of [[social]] relations, much of feminist theory also focuses on analyzing gender inequalities and the promotion of women's rights, interests, and issues.  Themes explored in feminism include [[discrimination]], [[stereotyping]], [[objectification]] (especially [[sexual objectification]]), [[oppression]], and [[patriarchy]].&lt;ref name=gilligan1977&gt; Gilligan, Carol, 'In a Different Voice: Women's Conceptions of Self and Morality' in ''Harvard Educational Review'' (1977)&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name=Chodorow1989&gt; Chodorow, Nancy J., ''Feminism and Psychoanalytic Theory'' (Yale University Press: 1989, 1991)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Elaine Showalter]] describes the development of Feminist theory as having a number of phases. The first she calls "feminist critique" - where the feminist reader examines the ideologies behind literary phenomena.  The second Showalter calls [[Gynocriticism|"Gynocritics"]] - where the "woman is producer of textual meaning" including "the [[psychodynamics]] of female creativity; [[linguistics]] and the problem of a female language; the trajectory of the individual or collective female literary career [and] [[literary history]]".  The last phase she calls "gender theory" - where the "ideological inscription and the literary effects of the [[sex/gender distinction|sex/gender system]]" are explored."&lt;ref name=showalter1979&gt; Showalter, Elaine. 'Toward a Feminist Poetics: Women’s Writing and Writing About Women' in ''The New Feminist Criticism: Essays on Women, Literature and Theory'' (Random House, 1988), ISBN 9780394726472&lt;/ref&gt;  This model has been criticized by [[Toril Moi]] who sees it as an [[essentialism|essentialist]] and [[determinism|deterministic]] model for female subjectivity.  She also criticized it for not taking account of the situation for women outside the west.&lt;ref name=Moi&gt;Moi, Toril, ''Sexual/Textual Politics'' (Routledge, 2002), ISBN 9780415280129 &lt;/ref&gt;

==Feminism's many forms==
Several subtypes of feminist [[ideology]] have developed over the years, some of the major subtypes are listed as follows.&lt;br /&gt;

===Liberal feminism===
[[Image:Betty Friedan 1960.jpg|thumb|120px|[[Betty Friedan]] in 1960]]
{{main|Liberal feminism}}
Liberal feminism asserts the equality of men and women through political and legal reform.  It is an individualistic form of feminism and theory, which focuses on women’s ability to show and maintain their equality through their own actions and choices.  Liberal feminism looks at the personal interactions of men and women as the starting ground from which to transform society into a more gender-equitable place.  According to liberal feminists, all women are capable of asserting their ability to achieve equality, therefore it is possible for change to happen without altering the structure of society.  Issues important to liberal feminists include reproductive and abortion rights, sexual harassment, voting, education, "equal pay for equal work," affordable childcare, affordable health care, and bringing to light the frequency of sexual and domestic violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;hooks, bell. "Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center" Cambridge, MA: South End Press 1984&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

;People of interest
* [[Betty Friedan]] 
* [[Gloria Steinem]]
* [[Rebecca Walker]]
* [[Naomi Wolf]]

===Radical feminism===
{{main|Radical feminism}}
{{related|[[Sex-positive feminism]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Separatist feminism]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Anarcha-feminism]]}}
Radical feminism sees the capitalist sexist hierarchy as the defining feature of women’s oppression.  Radical feminists believe that women can free themselves only when have done away with what they consider an inherently oppressive and dominating system.  Radical feminists feel that the male-based authority and power structure are responsible for oppression and inequality, and that as long as the system and its values are in place, society will not be able to reform in any significant way.  Radical feminism sees capitalism as a barrier to ending oppression.  Most radical feminists see no alternatives other than the total uprooting and reconstruction of society in order to achieve their goals.&lt;ref&gt;Echols, Alice. "Daring to be Bad" University of Minnesota Press 1990&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Separatist feminism]] is one form of radical feminism, it does not support [[heterosexual]] relationships due to its belief that the [[sexism|sexual disparities]] between [[men]] and [[women]] are unresolvable. Separatist feminists generally do not feel that men can make positive contributions to the feminist movement and that even well-intentioned men replicate the dynamics of [[patriarchy]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Sarah Hoagland]], "Lesbian Ethics."&lt;/ref&gt;  Author [[Marilyn Frye]] describes separatist feminism as "separation of various sorts or modes from men and from institutions, relationships, roles and activities that are male-defined, male-dominated, and operating for the benefit of males and the maintenance of male privilege &amp;mdash; this separation being initiated or maintained, at will, ''by women''."&lt;ref&gt;Marilyn Frye, "Some Reflections on Separatism and Power." In ''Feminist Social Thought: A Reader'', Diana Tietjens Meyers (ed.) (1997) New York: Routledge, pp. 406-414.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:A. Dworkin.jpg|thumb|160px|[[Andrea Dworkin]] in New York, January 1986]]
Both the self-proclaimed ''[[sex-positive]]'' and the so-called ''[[sex-negative]]'' forms of present-day feminism can trace their roots to early radical feminism. Ellen Willis's 1981 essay, "Lust Horizons: Is the Women's Movement Pro-Sex?" is the origin of the term, "[[pro-sex feminism]]". In it, she argues against feminism making alliances with the political [[right-wing politics|right]] in opposition to pornography and [[prostitution]], as occurred, for example, during the [[Meese Commission]] hearings in the United States. Willis argued for a feminism that embraces sexual freedom, including men's sexual freedom, rather than condemn [[pornography]], consensual [[BDSM]], and in some cases [[sexual intercourse]] and [[fellatio]]. &lt;ref&gt;Ellen Willis, [http://villagevoice.com/specials/0543,50thewill,69320,31.html Lust Horizons: The 'Voice' and the women's movement], ''Village Voice'' 50th Anniversary Issue, 2007. This is not the original "Lust Horizons" essay, but a retrospective essay mentioning that essay as the origin of the term. Accessed online 7 July 2007. A lightly revised version of the original "Lust Horizons" essay can be found in ''No More Nice Girls'', p. 3–14.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another strand of radical feminism is [[Anarcha-feminism]] (also called anarchist feminism or anarcho-feminism).  It combines feminist ideas and [[anarchist]] beliefs. Anarcha-feminists view patriarchy as a manifestation of hierarchy, believing that the struggle against patriarchy is an essential part of [[class struggle]] and the [[anarchism|anarchist]] struggle against the [[state]].&lt;ref name=farrow&gt; Farrow, Lynne, ''Quiet Rumours: An Anarcha-feminist Reader'' (AK Press, 2003), ISBN 9781902593401&lt;/ref&gt; Anarcha-feminists like Susan Brown see the anarchist struggle as a necessary component of feminist struggle, in Brown's words "anarchism is a political philosophy that opposes all relationships of power, it is inherently feminist". &lt;ref name=Brown&gt;Brown, Susan. "Beyond Feminism:  Anarchism and Human Freedom" 'Anarchist Papers 3' Black Rose Books (1990) p. 208&lt;/ref&gt; Recently, [[Wendy McElroy]] has defined a position (she describes it as "ifeminism" or "individualist feminism") that combines feminism with anarcho-capitalism or libertarianism, arguing that a pro-capitalist, anti-state position is compatible with an emphasis on equal rights and empowerment for women.&lt;ref&gt;Wendy McElroy, ''[http://www.wendymcelroy.com/xxx/ XXX: A Woman's Right to Pornography]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Individualist anarchist feminism has grown from the [[United States|US]]-based [[individualist anarchism]] movement.&lt;ref&gt;"Feminism: Anarchist" by Judy Greenway. 2000. Routledge International Encyclopedia of Women: Global Women's Issues and Knowledge. Kramara, Cheris &amp; Spender, Dale eds. Routledge. p. 712&lt;/ref&gt;

;People of interest
*[[Charlotte Bunch]]
*[[Susan Brownmiller]]
*[[Mary Daly]] 
*[[Andrea Dworkin]]
*[[Melissa Farley]]
*[[Shulamith Firestone]]
*[[Catharine Mackinnon]]
*[[Adrienne Rich]]

===Individualist feminism===
[[Image:Wendy McElroy 144x206.jpg|thumb|115px|&lt;small&gt;[[Wendy McElroy]]: Canadian individualist anarchist, "anarcho-capitalist" and sex-positive feminist.&lt;/small&gt;]]
Individualist feminists define [[Individualist feminism]] in opposition to political or gender feminism.&lt;ref name=mcelroy1&gt; McElroy, Wendy, ''Liberty for Women: Freedom and Feminism in the Twenty-First Century '' (Ivan R Dee, 2002), ISBN 9781566634359&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sommers/&gt;  Some individualist feminists trace the movement's roots to the classical liberal tradition.&lt;ref&gt;Mary Wollstonecraft by Wendy McElroy[http://www.fff.org/freedom/fd0602f.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;  It is closely linked to the [[libertarian]] ideas of individuality and personal responsibility of both women and men.  Some other feminists believe that it reinforces patriarchal systems because it does not view the rights or political interests of men and women as being in conflict nor does it rest upon class/gender analysis.&lt;ref&gt;Good Will Toward Men by Wendy McElroy [http://www.ncc-1776.org/tle2001/libe153-20011224-02.html]&lt;/ref&gt;  Individualist feminists attempt to change legal systems in order to eliminate class privileges, including gender privileges and to ensure that individuals have an equal right, an equal claim under law to their own persons and property. Individualist feminism encourages women to take full responsibility over their own lives. It also opposes any government interference into the choices adults make with their own bodies.&lt;ref name=wwwifeministsnet&gt;{{cite web | title = ifeminists.net| url =http://www.ifeminists.net/introduction/| accessdate = 2007-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mcelroy2&gt; McElroy, Wendy, ed. ''Liberty for Women: Freedom and Feminism in the Twenty-First Century'' (Ivan R Dee Inc., 2002), ISBN 9781566634359&lt;/ref&gt;

===Black feminism===
[[Image:Angela-Davis-Mar-28-2006.jpg|thumb|150px|[[Angela Davis]] speaking at the University of Alberta, [[28 March]] [[2006]]]]
{{main|Black feminism|Womanism}}
Black feminism argues that [[sexism]] and [[racism]] are inextricable from one another&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/modern/Defining-Black-Feminist-Thought.html Defining Black Feminist Thought], retrieved on [[May 31]] [[2007]].&lt;/ref&gt;. Forms of feminism that strive to overcome [[sexism]] and [[Social class|class]] oppression but ignore race  can discriminate against many people, including women, through racial bias. Black feminists argue that the liberation of black women entails [[Freedom (political)|freedom]] for all people, since it would require the end of racism, sexism, and class oppression.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/modern/Black-Feminist-Statement.html A Black Feminist Statement - 1974], retrieved on [[May 31]] [[2007]].&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the theories that evolved out of this movement was [[Alice Walker|Alice Walker's]] [[Womanism]].  
It emerged after the early feminist movements that were led specifically by white women who advocated social changes such as woman’s suffrage.  These movements were largely a white middle-class movements and ignored oppression based on [[racism]] and [[classism]]. Alice Walker and other Womanists pointed out that black women experienced a different and more intense kind of oppression from that of white women. &lt;ref name=walker&gt; Walker, Alice, ''In Search of Our Mothers' Gardens'' (Phoenix, 2005), ISBN 9780753819609&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Angela Davis]] was one of the first people who formed an argument centered on intersection of race, gender and class in her book, "Women, Race, and Class."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/blackwomen.html List of Books written by Black Feminists], retrieved on [[May 31]] [[2007]].&lt;/ref&gt;  Kimberle Crenshaw, prominent feminist law theorist, gave the idea a name while discussing [[Identity Politics]] in her essay, 'Mapping the Margins: Intersectionality, Identity Politics and Violence Against Women of Color.'

;People of interest
*[[Alice Walker]]
*[[Angela Davis]]
*[[Barbara Smith]]
*[[Hattie Gossett]]
*[[Patricia Hill Collins]]

===Socialist and Marxist feminisms===
{{main|Socialist feminism|Marxist feminism}}
[[Image:Zetkin luxemburg1910.jpg|thumb|130px|Clara Zetkin and [[Rosa Luxemburg]], 1910]]
Socialist feminism connects the oppression of women to Marxist ideas about exploitation, oppression and labor.  Socialist feminists see women as being held down as a result of their unequal standing in both the workplace and the domestic sphere.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/domesticity.html Monstrous Domesticity by Faith Wilding], retrieved on [[May 31]] [[2007]].&lt;/ref&gt;  Prostitution, domestic work, childcare, and marriage are all seen as ways in which women are exploited by a patriarchal system which devalues women and the substantial work that they do. Socialist feminists focus their energies on broad change that affects society as a whole, and not just on an individual basis.  They see the need to work alongside not just men, but all other groups, as they see the oppression of women as a part of a larger pattern that affects everyone involved in the capitalist system.&lt;ref&gt;Ehrenreich, Barbara. "What is Socialist Feminism" WIN Magazine, 1976&lt;/ref&gt;

Marx felt that when class oppression was overcome, gender oppression would vanish as well. According to socialist feminists, this view of gender oppression as a sub-class of class oppression is naive and much of the work of socialist feminists has gone towards separating gender phenomena from class phenomena.&lt;ref name=Marx&gt; Marx, Karl, ''Capital'' translated by B. Fowkes (Penguin classics, 1990), ISBN 9780140445688&lt;/ref&gt;  Some contributors to socialist feminism have criticized these traditional marxist ideas for being largely silent on gender oppression except to subsume it underneath broader class oppression.&lt;ref name=round-table_discussion&gt; 'Feminism and Class Politics: A Round-Table Discussion'
Clara Connolly, Lynne Segal, Michele Barrett, Beatrix Campbell, Anne Phillips, Angela Weir, Elizabeth Wilson in ''Feminist Review'', No. 23, ''Socialist-Feminism: Out of the Blue'' (Summer, 1986), pp. 13-30&lt;/ref&gt;  Other socialist feminists, notably two long-lived [[United States|American]] organizations [[Radical Women]] and the [[Freedom Socialist Party]], point to the classic Marxist writings of [[Frederick Engels]] &lt;ref name=Engels&gt; Engels, Fredrich, ''The Origin of the Family, Private Property and the State'', translated by A. West, (Lawrence &amp; Wishart Ltd, 1972), ISBN 9780853152606&lt;/ref&gt; and [[August Bebel]]&lt;ref name = Bebel&gt; Bebel, August, ''Woman under Socialism'' (University Press of the Pacific, 2004), ISBN 9781410215642&lt;/ref&gt; as a powerful explanation of the link between gender oppression and class exploitation. 

In the late nineteenth century and early twentieth century both Clara Zetkin and Eleanor Marx were against the demonization of men and supported a [[proletariate|proletarian]] revolution that would overcome as many male-female inequalities as possible.&lt;ref name=Stokes&gt; Stokes, John, ''Eleanor Marx (1855-1898): Life, Work, Contacts, and: Socialist Women: Britain, 1880s to 1920s'' (Ashgate, 2000), ISBN 9780754601135&lt;/ref&gt; 

;People of interest
*[[Michelè Barrett]]
*[[Friedrich Engels]]
*[[Clara Fraser]]
*[[Emma Goldman]]
*[[Sheila Rowbotham]]
*[[Clara Zetkin]]
*[[Eleanor Marx]]

{{seealso|Post-Communism Gender Roles in Eastern Europe}}

===Post-structural feminism and postmodern feminism===
{{related|[[French feminism]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Deconstruction]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Postmodern feminism]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Poststructuralism]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Postmodernism]]}}
Post-structural feminism, also referred to as French feminism, use the insights of various [[epistemology|epistemological]] movements, including psychoanalysis, linguistics, political theory (Marxist and neo-Marxist theory), race theory, literary theory, and other intellectual currents for feminist concerns.&lt;ref name=Johnson&gt;Johnson, Barbara. ''The Feminist Difference: Literature, Psychoanalysis, Race and Gender'', Harvard University Press, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;  Many post-structural feminists maintain that difference is one of the most powerful tools that females possess in their struggle with patriarchal domination, and that to equate feminist movement only with equality is to deny women a plethora of options as equality is still defined against within masculine or patriarchal perspective.&lt;ref name=Johnson/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Irigaray, Luce. "When Our Lips Speak Together" in ''Feminist Theory and the Body: A Reader'' ed. by Janet Price &amp; Margrit Shildrick, Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Judith Butler.jpg|thumb|150px|Judith Butler at a lecture at the [[University of Hamburg]].]]
Postmodern Feminism is an approach to [[feminist theory]] that incorporates [[Postmodern philosophy|postmodern]] and [[post-structuralism|post-structuralist theory]].  The largest departure from other branches of feminism, is the argument that sex as well as gender is [[social construction|constructed]] through [[discourse|language]].&lt;ref name=ButlerOnSexGender&gt;  Butler, Judith, "Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity" (Routledge, 1999), p.7, ISBN 9780415924993&lt;/ref&gt; The most notable proponent of this argument is [[Judith Butler]], in her 1990 book, ''[[Gender Trouble]]'', which draws on, and criticizes the work of [[Simone de Beauvoir]], [[Michel Foucault]] and [[Jacques Lacan]]. Butler criticizes the distinction drawn by previous feminisms between (biological) [[sex]] and (socially constructed) gender. She says that this does not allow for a sufficient criticism of [[essentialism]].  For Butler "[[women]]" and "[[woman]]" are fraught categories, complicated by [[Social class|class]], [[ethnicity]], [[Human sexuality|sexuality]], and other facets of identity.  She suggests that [[gender  performativity|gender is performative]].  This argument leads to the conclusion that there is no single cause for [[women]]'s subordination, and no single approach towards dealing with the issue.&lt;ref name=Butler&gt; Butler, Judith, "Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity" (Routledge, 1999), ISBN 9780415924993 &lt;/ref&gt;  
[[Image:Donna Haraway and Cayenne.jpg|150px|thumb|Donna Haraway, author of ''A Cyborg Manifesto'', with her dog Cayenne]]
In ''A Cyborg Manifesto'' [[Donna Haraway]] criticizes traditional notions of feminism, particularly its emphasis on identity, rather than affinity.  She uses the metaphor of a [[cyborg]] in order to construct a postmodern feminism that moves beyond [[dualisms]] and moves beyond the limitations of traditional gender, feminism, and politics.&lt;ref name=Harraway&gt; Harraway, Donna, 'Cyborg Manifesto: Science, Technology, and Socialist-Feminism in the Late Twentieth Century' in ''Simians, Cyborgs and Women: The Reinvention of Nature'' (Routledge, 1991), pp.149-181 [http://www.stanford.edu/dept/HPS/Haraway/CyborgManifesto.html]&lt;/ref&gt;  Haraway's cyborg is an attempt to break away from [[Oedipal]] narratives and [[Christian]] origins doctrines like [[Genesis]].  In the Cyborg Manifesto, she writes:
"The cyborg does not dream of community on the model of the organic family, this time without the oedipal project. The cyborg would not recognize the Garden of Eden; it is not made of mud and cannot dream of returning to dust."&lt;ref name=Harraway/&gt;
  
Other postmodern feminist works emphasizes [[stereotype|stereotypical]] female [[gender roles|roles]], only to portray them as parodies of the original beliefs.  The history of feminism is not important in this section, but only what is going to be done about it.  In fact, the history is dismissed and used to depict better how ridiculous the past beliefs were.  Modern feminist theory has been extensively criticized as being predominantly, though not exclusively, associated with western middle class [[academia]]. Mainstream feminism has been criticized as being too narrowly focused, and inattentive to related issues of [[race]] and [[Social class|class]].&lt;ref name=Frug&gt;Mary Joe Frug, "A Postmodern Feminist Legal Manifesto (An Unfinished Draft)," Harvard Law Review, Vol. 105, No. 5. (Mar., 1992), pp. 1045-1075&lt;/ref&gt;

;People of interest
*[[Judith Butler]]
*[[Helene Cixous]]
*[[Mary Joe Frug]]
*[[Donna Haraway]]
*[[Luce Irigaray]]
*[[Julia Kristeva]]
*[[Monique Wittig]]

===Postcolonial feminism and third-world feminism===
{{main|Postcolonial feminism}}
{{related|[[Multiracial feminism]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Transnational feminism]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Postcolonialism]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Orientalism]]}}
Postcolonial feminism emerged from the gendered history of [[colonialism]].  Colonial powers often imposed [[Western culture|Western]] norms on colonized regions.  In the 1940s and 1950s, after the formation of the [[United Nations]], former colonies were monitored by the West for what was considered "social progress". The status of women in the [[developing world]] has been monitored by organizations such as the [[United Nations]], as a result traditional practices and roles taken up by women -- sometimes seen as distasteful by Western standards -- could be considered a form of rebellion against colonial oppression.&lt;ref name=Mohanty88&gt; Mohanty, Chandra Talpade, 'Under Western Eyes' in ''Feminist Review'', No. 30 (Autumn, 1988), pp. 61-88&lt;/ref&gt;  Postcolonial feminists today struggle to fight gender oppression within their own cultural models of society rather than through those imposed by the Western colonizers.&lt;ref name=Bulbeck&gt; Bulbeck, Chilla, ''Re-orienting Western Feminisms: Women's Diversity in a Postcolonial World'' (Cambridge University Press, 1997), ISBN 9780521580304&lt;/ref&gt;

Postcolonial feminists argue that oppressions relating to the colonial experience, particularly racial, class, and ethnic oppressions, have marginalized women in postcolonial societies. They challenge the assumption that gender oppression is the primary force of patriarchy.  Postcolonial feminists object to portrayals of women of non-Western societies as passive and voiceless victims, as opposed to the portrayal of Western women as modern, educated and empowered.&lt;ref&gt;Mills, S (1998): "Postcolonial Feminist Theory" page 106 in S. Jackson and J. Jones eds., ''Contemporary Feminist Theories'' (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press) pp.98-112&lt;/ref&gt;

Postcolonial feminism is critical of Western forms of feminism, notably [[radical feminism]] and [[liberal feminism]] and their universalization of female experience. Postcolonial feminists argue that cultures impacted by [[colonialism]] are often vastly different and should be treated as such.  Colonial oppression may result in glorification of pre-colonial culture, which, in cultures with traditions of stratification of power along lines of gender, could mean the acceptance of, or refusal to deal with, inherent issues of gender inequality.&lt;ref&gt;Greenwald, A: "[http://www.scholars.nus.edu.sg/post/achebe/greenwald3.html  Postcolonial Feminism in Anthills of the Savannah]", 2002&lt;/ref&gt;  Postcolonial feminists can be described as feminists who have reacted against both universalizing tendencies in Western feminist thought and a lack of attention to gender issues in mainstream [[Postcolonialism|postcolonial]] thought.&lt;ref&gt;Mills, S (1998): "Postcolonial Feminist Theory" page 98 in S. Jackson and J. Jones eds., ''Contemporary Feminist Theories'' (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press) pp.98-112&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Taslima nasrin.jpg|115px|thumb|Taslima Nasrin: author, physician &amp; feminist human rights activist]]
The feminist movement called third-world feminism has been described as a group of feminist theories developed by feminists who acquired their views and took part in feminist politics in so-called [[third world]] countries&lt;ref name=Narayan&gt; Narayan, U. (1997): ''Dislocating Cultures: Identities, Traditions, and Third-World Feminism'' (New York:Routledge)&lt;/ref&gt;. Although women from the [[third world]] have been engaged in the feminist movement, [[Chandra Talpade Mohanty]] criticizes [[Western culture|Western]] feminism on the grounds that it is [[ethnocentrism|ethnocentric]] and does not take into account the unique experiences of women from third world countries or the existence of feminisms [[Indigenous knowledge|indigenous]] to third world countries.  According to her, women in the third world feel that western feminism bases its understanding of women on "internal [[racism]], [[classism]] and [[homophobia]]"&lt;ref name=Mohanty&gt; Mohanty, C (1991): "Introduction" page 7 in  ''Third World Women and the Politics of Feminism'' (Indiana: Indiana University Press) pp.1-50&lt;/ref&gt;.  This discourse is strongly related to [[Africa]]n feminism and [[postcolonial feminism]]. Its development is also associated with concepts such as black feminism, womanism&lt;ref name=Walker/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ogunyemi, C. O. (1985): "Womanism: The Dynamics of the Black Female Novel in English", ''Signs'' 11(1) pp63-80&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kolawale, M. (1997): ''Womanism and African Consciousness'' (Africa World Press)&lt;/ref&gt;, "Africana womanism"&lt;ref&gt;Hudson-Weems, C. (1993), ''Africana womanist: Reclaiming ourselves'' (Troy, MI: Bedford)&lt;/ref&gt;, "motherism"&lt;ref&gt;Acholonu, C. O. (1995): ''Motherism: The Afrocentric Alternative to Feminism'' (Owerri, Nigeria: Afa Publications)&lt;/ref&gt;, "Stiwanism"&lt;ref&gt;Ogundipe-Leslie, M. (1994): ''Re-Creating Ourselves: African Women &amp; Critical Transformations'' (Africa World Press)&lt;/ref&gt;, "negofeminism"&lt;ref&gt;Nnaemeka, O. (1995): "Feminism, Rebellious Women, and Cultural Boundaries", ''Research in African Literatures&lt;/ref&gt;, [[chicana feminism]] and "femalism".

;People of interest
*[[Gayatri Spivak]]
*[[Chandra Talpade Mohanty]]
*[[Trinh T. Minh-ha]]
*[[Uma Narayan]]
*[[Chandra Talpade Mohanty]]
*[[Taslima Nasrin]]

===Ecofeminism===
[[Image:Vandana shiva 20070610.jpg|thumb|140px|Vandana Shiva 2007 in Cologne, Germany]]
{{main|Ecofeminism}}
Ecofeminism links [[ecology]] with feminism.  Ecofeminists see the domination of women as stemming from the same ideologies that bring about the domination of the environment. Patriarchal systems, where men own and control the land, are seen as responsible for the oppression of women and destruction of the natural environment.  Since the men in power control the land, they are able to exploit it for their own profit and success.  In this same situation, women are exploited by men in power for their own profit, success, and pleasure.  Women and the environment are both exploited as passive pawns in the race to domination.  Those people in power are able to take advantage of them distinctly because they are seen as passive and rather helpless.  Ecofeminism connects the exploitation and domination of women with that of the environment.  As a way of repairing social and ecological injustices, ecofeminists feel that women must work towards creating a healthy environment and ending the destruction of the lands that most women rely on to provide for their families.&lt;ref&gt;MacGregor, Sherilyn. "Beyond Mothering Earth: Ecological Citizenship" Vancouver: UBC Press 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Ecofeminism argues that there is a connection between women and nature that comes from their shared history of oppression by a patriarchal western society.  Vandana Shiva explains how women's special connection to the environment through their daily interactions with it have been ignored.  She says that "women in subsistence economies, producing and reproducing wealth in partnership with nature, have been experts in their own right of holistic and ecological knowledge of nature’s processes.  But these alternative modes of knowing, which are oriented to the social benefits and sustenance needs are not recognized by the [capitalist] reductionist paradigm, because it fails to perceive the interconnectedness of nature, or the connection of women’s lives, work and knowledge with the creation of wealth.”&lt;ref name=Shiva&gt; Shiva, Vandana, ''Staying Alive: Women Ecology and Development'' (Zed Books Ltd, 1989), ISBN 9780862328238&lt;/ref&gt;  Ecofeminists also criticize Western lifestyle choices, such as consuming food that has traveled thousands of miles and playing sports (such as [[golf]] and [[bobsledding]]) which inherently require ecological destruction.

Feminist and [[social ecology|social ecologist]] [[Janet Biehl]] has criticized ecofeminism for focusing too much on a mystical connection between women and nature, and not enough on the actual conditions of women.&lt;ref name= Biehl&gt; Biehl, Janet, ''Rethinking Ecofeminist Politics'' (South End Press, 1991), ISBN 9780896083929&lt;/ref&gt;

;People of interest
*[[Vandana Shiva]]
*[[Wangari Maathai]]
*[[Karen J. Warren]]
*[[Gerda Lerner]]
*[[Val Plumwood]]

{{seealso|Environmentalism}}

===Post-feminism===
{{main|Post-feminism}}
Post-feminism comprises a wide range of theories, some of which argue that feminism is no longer relevant to today's society.&lt;ref&gt;Modleski, Tania. Feminism without Women: Culture and Criticism in a “Postfeminist” Age. New York: Routledge, 1991, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the earliest uses of the term was in Susan Bolotin's 1982 article "Voices of the Post-Feminist Generation," published in ''[[New York Times Magazine]]''.  This article was based on a number of interviews with women who largely agreed with the goals of feminism, but did not identify as feminists.&lt;ref&gt;Rosen, Ruth. The World Split Open: How the Modern Women's Movement Changed America. New York: Viking, 2000, 275, 337. &lt;/ref&gt;  The post-feminist texts which emerged in the 1980s and '90s often portrayed [[second-wave feminism]] as a monolithic entity, thereby allowing the author to criticize these generalizations.&lt;ref name=Jones&gt; Jones, Amelia. ''Postfeminism, Feminist Pleasures, and Embodied Theories of Art: New Feminist Criticism: Art, Identity, Action'', ed. by Joana Frueh, Cassandra L. Langer and Arlene Raven (Harper Collins, 1994), pp. 16-41, 20. &lt;/ref&gt;

Elizabeth Wright says that [[Postfeminism]] considers the issue of [[postmodern]] dispersed and unstable subjectivity in relation to feminist ideas.  Postfeminism is continuously in process, taking a critical approach to previous feminist discourses.  Wright says that this critical approach includes a challenge to second-wave ideas.&lt;ref name=Wright2000&gt; Wright, Elizabeth, ''Lacan and Postfeminism'' (Icon books, 2000), ISBN 9781840461829&lt;/ref&gt;  Wright points out that there is a negative meaning to the term "post-feminism" which "indicates that feminism can now be dispensed with."&lt;ref name=Wright2000/&gt;  Sarah Gamble argues that feminists such as [[Naomi Wolf]], Katie Roiphe and [[Natasha Walter]] are labelled as 'anti-feminists' whereas they define themselves as feminists who have shifted from second-wave ideas towards an "individualistic liberal agenda".&lt;ref name=Gamble1999&gt; Gamble, Sarah, ed., ''The icon Critical Dictionary of Feminism and Postfeminism'' (Icon books, 1999)&lt;/ref&gt;  

Gamble points out that post-feminists like Rene Denfeld are criticized as "pawns of a conservative 'backlash' against feminism.&lt;ref name=Gamble1999/&gt;  Denefeld has distanced herself from feminists who see pornography and heterosexuality as oppressive.  She also criticized what she sees as the second-wave's "reckless" use of the term [[patriarchy]].&lt;ref name=Denefeld&gt; Denefeld, Rene, ''The new Victorians: A Young Woman's Challenge to the old Feminist Order'' (Simon and Schuster, 1995)&lt;/ref&gt;

;People of interest
*[[Camille Paglia]]
*[[Katie Roiphe]]
*[[Natasha Walter]]
*[[Naomi Wolf]]

==Issues in defining feminism ==  	 
One of the difficulties in defining and circumscribing a complex and heterogeneous concept such as feminism&lt;ref&gt;Cott, Nancy F. What’s In a Name? The Limits of ‘Social Feminism’; or, Expanding the Vocabulary of Women’s History. Journal of American History 76 (December 1989): 809–829&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shulman, Alix K. Emma Goldman: 'Anarchist Queen', in Spender 1983 op. cit. at 223&lt;/ref&gt; is the extent to which women have rejected the term from a variety of semantic and political standpoints. Many women engaged in activities intimately grounded in feminism have not considered themselves feminists.  Likewise, it is assumed that only women can be feminists.  However, feminism is not grounded in the basis of one's gender, but in rejecting and refuting sexist oppression politically, socially, privately, linguistically, and otherwise. (Though there are people &amp;mdash; both men and women &amp;mdash; who claim feminism itself can be biased in its approach to gender relations.) Redefining feminism in this way illustrates and reflects today's reality of both men and women openly supporting feminism and also openly adhering to sexist ideals.&lt;ref name="walters"&gt; Walters, Margaret. "Feminism: A very short introduction". Oxford 2005 (ISBN 0-19-280510-X)&lt;/ref&gt; From a political vantage, the term "feminism" has been rejected both because of fears of labeling, and because of its innate ability to attract broad misogyny.&lt;ref&gt;Mitchell, Julie and Ann Oakley (eds.). "Who's Afraid of Feminism?: Seeing Through the Backlash", New Press, 1997. ISBN 1-56584-385-1&lt;/ref&gt; 	 
Historically [[Virginia Woolf]] was one of the more prominent women to reject the term&lt;ref&gt;Woolf, Virginia. "[[Three Guineas]]" 1938&lt;/ref&gt; early in its history in 1938, although it would be easy to overstate Woolf's position,&lt;ref&gt;Park SS. Suffrage and Virginia Woolf: ‘The Mass Behind the Single Voice’ The Review of English Studies 2005 56(223):119-134&lt;/ref&gt; considering that she is regarded as an icon of feminism.&lt;ref&gt;Silver, Brenda. "Virginia Woolf: Icon" University of Chicago Press 1999&lt;/ref&gt;  However [[Betty Friedan]] would revisit this concern in 1981 in ''[[The Second Stage]]''. 	 
Nevertheless, defining ideas does not necessarily imply tagging the individual. Ann Taylor,&lt;ref name="taylor"&gt;[http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/ahr/104.4/ah001085.html Allen, Ann Taylor, Feminism, Social Science, and the Meanings of Modernity: The Debate on the Origin of the Family in Europe : and the United States, 1860–1914. The American Historical Review 104.4 (1999): 53 pars. [[1 December]]. 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; for instance, offers the following definition of a feminist, after Karen Offen:&lt;ref&gt;Offen, Karen. Defining Feminism: A Comparative Historical Approach. Signs 14 (Autumn 1988): 152.&lt;/ref&gt; 	 
Any person who recognizes "''the validity of women's own interpretation of their lived experiences and needs," protests against the institutionalized injustice perpetrated by men as a group against women as a group, and advocates the elimination of that injustice by challenging the various structures of authority or power that legitimate male prerogatives in a given society''. Another way of expressing this concept is that a primary goal is to correct androcentric bias.&lt;ref&gt;Marler, Joan. The Myth of Universal Patriarchy: A Critical Response to Cynthia Eller’s Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory. Feminist Theology, Vol. 14, No. 2, 163-187 (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; 	 
 		 
Other attempts at defining feminism have been made by the United Nations.&lt;ref&gt;Sen, G., Grown, C. Development, crisis and alternative visions: Third World women’s perspectives. Monthly Review Press, N.Y. 1987&lt;/ref&gt; However, one of feminism's unique characteristics, strengths and weaknesses is its persistent defiance of being constrained by definition. Charlotte Witt observes that this reflects the "''contested nature of the "us" of contemporary feminism ... and is a part of, on-going debates within feminism over its identity and self-image ... in the final analysis, the result of debate within feminist philosophy over what feminism is, and what its theoretical commitments should be, and what its core values are.''"&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-femhist/ Witt, Charlotte. Feminist History of Philosophy, in Stanford Encyclopaedia of Philosophy]&lt;/ref&gt;  This is the subject of one of the more lively debates in feminism, that which Nannerl Keohane has called the "''perpetual oscillation between [[essentialism]] and [[nominalism]] ([[Social constructionism|constructionism]]) in feminist theory.''"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dukemagazine.duke.edu/alumni/dm30/books.html Keohane, Nannerl. Review: Moi, Toril. What is a Woman? And Other Essays. Duke University Alumni Magazine No. 30: September - October 2000]&lt;/ref&gt;  Briefly, "''to essentialise is to reduce a complex idea or object to simplistic characteristics, thereby denying diversity, multiple meanings and alternative interpretations''" in the words of Joan Marler, an opponent of essentialism in feminism.&lt;ref&gt;Marler, Joan. The Myth of Universal Patriarchy: A Critical Response to Cynthia Eller’s Myth of Matriarchal Prehistory. Feminist Theology, Vol. 14, No. 2, 163-187 (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent times some women and men have distanced from the term ''"femin"''ism in favor of more inclusive terminology such as "equal rights activist/advocate", "equalist" or similar non-gendered phrasings.&lt;ref&gt;Christina Scharff:  Perspectives on feminist (dis-) identification in the German and British contexts&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rachael Williams and Michele Andrissin Wittig write: "..it's likely that the gendered connotation of the term itself plays a role in their avoidance of the label" in "I'm not a feminist, but … ": factors contributing to the discrepancy between pro-feminist orientation and feminist social identity" in ''Sex Roles: a Journal of Research'' (1997)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Feminism and society==
{{main|Feminist movement}}
[[Image:Woman suffrage headquarters Cleveland.jpg|thumb|145px|By campaigning for the right to vote, suffragettes began the feminist struggle for equality in the West. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;small&gt;Woman Suffrage Headquarters, Cleveland, 1912&lt;/small&gt;]]
The feminist movement has effected change in Western society, including women's suffrage; the right to initiate [[divorce]] proceedings and "no fault" divorce; and the right of women to make individual decisions regarding pregnancy (including access to contraceptives and abortion).&lt;ref name=Messer-Davidow&gt; Messer-Davidow, Ellen, ''Disciplining feminism : from social activism to academic discourse'' (Duke University Press, 2002), ISBN 9780822328437&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Butler2&gt; Butler, Judith, 'Feminism in Any Other Name', ''differences'' vol. 6, numbers 2-3, pp. 44-45&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civil rights===
Feminism has effected many changes in Western society, including [[women's suffrage]], broad employment for women at more equitable wages, the right to initiate [[divorce]] proceedings and the introduction of [[No fault divorce|"no fault" divorce]], the right to obtain contraception and safe abortions, and access to [[university]] education.
According to studies by the [[United Nations]], when both paid employment and unpaid household tasks are accounted for, on average women work more than men. In rural areas of selected developing countries women performed an average of 20% more work than men, or an additional 102 minutes per day. In the [[OECD]] countries surveyed, on average women performed 5% more work than men, or 20 minutes per day.&lt;ref&gt; [url=http://hdr.undp.org/reports/global/2004/pdf/hdr04_HDI.pdf] Section 28: Gender, Work Burden, and Time Allocation in ''United Nations Human Development Report 2004''&lt;/ref&gt;  At the UN's  Pan Pacific Southeast Asia Women's Association twenty first International Conference in 2001 it was stated that "in the world as a whole, women comprise 51 percent of the population, do 66 percent of the work, receive 10 percent of the income and own less than one percent of the property."&lt;ref&gt;[url=http://www.ppseawa.org/Bulletin/01May/conference.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Language===
{{main|Gender-neutral language in English}}
Gender-neutral language is a description of [[Word usage|language usages]] which are aimed at minimizing assumptions regarding the biological [[sex]] of human [[reference|referents]].  The advocacy of gender-neutral language reflects, at least, two different agenda: one aims to clarify the ''inclusion'' of both sexes or genders (gender-inclusive language); the other proposes that gender, as a category, is rarely worth marking in language (gender-neutral language).  Gender-neutral language is sometimes described as ''non-sexist language'' by advocates, and ''politically-correct language'' by opponents.&lt;ref&gt;"Gender Neutral Language." ''University of Saskatchewan Policies,'' 2001. http://www.usask.ca/policies/2_03.htm. Accessed [[March 25]] [[2007]].&lt;/ref&gt;
{{seealso|Gender-neutrality in languages with grammatical gender|Gender-neutrality in languages without grammatical gender}}

===Heterosexual relationships===
The increased entry of women into the workplace beginning in the twentieth and century has effected gender roles and [[division of labor]] within households.  The [[sociologist]], [[Arlie Russell Hochschild]], presents evidence in her books, ''The Second Shift'' and ''The Time Bind'', that in two-career couples, men and women on the average spend about equal amounts of time working, but women still spend more time on housework.&lt;ref name=Hochschild1&gt; Hochschild, Arlie Russell, ''The Second Shift'' (Penguin, 2003), ISBN 9780142002926&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hochschild2&gt; Hochschild, Arlie Russell, ''The Time Bind: When Work Becomes Home and Home Becomes Work'' (Owl Books U.S, 2003), ISBN 9780805066432&lt;/ref&gt;

Feminist criticisms of men's contributions to child care and domestic labor in the Western middle class are typically centered around the idea that it is unfair for women to be expected to perform more than half of a household's domestic work and child care when both members of the relationship also work outside the home.  Several studies provide statistical evidence that higher or lower financial income of married men, does not influence them in terms of attending to the household duties as much their wives.&lt;ref&gt;Scott J. South and Glenna Spitze, "Housework in Marital and Nonmarital Households," ''American Sociological Review'' 59, no. 3 (1994):327-348&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Fenstermaker Berk and Anthony Shih, "Contributions to Household Labour: Comparing Wives' and Husbands' Reports,", in Berk, ed., ''Women and Household Labour''&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Dubious Conceptions'', [[Kristin Luker]] discusses the effect of feminism on teenage women's choices to bear a child, both in and out of wedlock. She says that as childbearing out of wedlock has become more socially acceptable; young women, especially poor young women, while not bearing children at a higher rate than in the 1950s, now see less reason to get married before having a child. Her explanation for this is that economic prospects for poor men are slim, hence poor women have a low chance of finding a husband who will be able to provide reliable financial support.&lt;ref&gt; Luker, Kristin, ''Dubious Conceptions: The Politics of the Teenage Pregnancy Crisis''. Harvard University Press (1996)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religion===
{{main|Feminist theology}}
Feminist theology is a movement that reconsiders the traditions, practices, [[scripture]]s, and theologies of their religion from a [[feminism|feminist]] perspective.  Some of the goals of feminist theology include increasing the role of [[women]] among the [[clergy]] and religious authorities, reinterpreting male-dominated imagery and language about [[God]], determining women's place in relation to [[career]] and [[motherhood]], and studying images of women in the religion's [[sacred texts]].&lt;ref name=Bundesen&gt; Bundesen, Linda, ''The Feminine Spirit: Recapturing the Heart of Scripture'' (Jossey Bass Wiley, 2007), ISBN 9780787984953&lt;/ref&gt;
{{see also|God and gender|Difference feminism}}

====Christian feminism====
{{main|Christian feminism}}
Christian feminism is a branch of [[feminist theology]] which seeks to interpret and understand [[Christianity]] in the scope of the [[sexual equality|equality]] of [[women]] and [[men]] morally, socially, and in leadership. Because this equality has been historically ignored, Christian [[feminist]]s believe their contributions are necessary for a complete understanding of Christianity. While there is no standard set of beliefs among Christian feminists, most agree that [[God]] does not [[discriminate]] on the basis of biologically-determined characteristics such as gender. Their major issues are the [[ordination of women]], male dominance in Christian [[marriage]], and claims of moral deficiency and inferiority of abilities of women compared to men. They also are concerned with issues such as the balance of [[parenting]] between [[mother]]s and [[father]]s and the overall treatment of women in the church. &lt;ref name=Haddad&gt; Haddad, Mimi, "Egalitarian Pioneers: Betty Friedan or Catherine Booth?" Priscilla Papers, Vol. 20, No. 4 (Autumn 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=andeson&gt; [[Pamela Sue Anderson|Anderson, Pamela Sue]] and Beverley Clack, eds., ''Feminist philosophy of religion: critical readings'' (London: Routledge, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Jewish feminism====
[[Image:BluGreenberg.jpg|thumb|[[Blu Greenberg]], an American writer and Jewish feminist.]]
{{main|Jewish feminism}}
'''Jewish feminism''' is a movement that seeks to improve the religious, legal, and social status of women within [[Judaism]] and to open up new opportunities for religious experience and leadership for Jewish women. Feminist movements, with varying approaches and successes, have opened up within all major branches of Judaism.  In its modern form, the movement can be traced to the early 1970s in the [[United States]]. According to [[Judith Plaskow]], who has focused on feminism in [[Reform Judaism]], the main issues for early Jewish feminists in these movements were the exclusion from the all-male prayer group or ''[[minyan]]'', the exemption from positive time-bound ''[[Mitzvah|mitzvot]]'', and women's inability to function as witnesses and to initiate [[Jewish view of marriage#Divorce|divorce]].&lt;ref name=Plaskow1997&gt;Plaskow, Judith. "Jewish Feminist Thought" in Frank, Daniel H. &amp; Leaman, Oliver. ''History of Jewish Philosophy'', Routledge, first published 1997; this edition 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

;People of interest
*[[Rachel Adler]]
*[[Nina Hartley]]
*[[Tova Hartman]]
*[[Susan Sontag]]
*[[Yona Wallach]]

====Islamic feminism====
[[Image:Mukhtaran Mai2005.jpg|120px|thumb|[[Mukhtaran Bibi]], [[Glamour (magazine)|Glamour Magazine]] Woman of the Year 2005]]
{{main| Islamic feminism}}
Islamic feminism is a form of [[feminism]] concerned with the role of [[Women and Islam|women in Islam]].  It aims for the full equality of all [[Muslims]], regardless of gender, in public and private life. Islamic feminists advocate [[women's rights]], [[gender equality]], and [[social justice]] grounded in an Islamic framework.  Although rooted in [[Islam]], the movement's pioneers have also utilized secular and Western feminist discourses and recognize the role of Islamic feminism as part of an integrated global feminist movement&lt;ref&gt;http://www.feminismeislamic.org/eng/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;.  Advocates of the movement seek to highlight the deeply rooted teachings of equality in the [[Quran]] and encourage a questioning of the [[patriarchal]] interpretation of [[Islamic]] teaching through the Quran (holy book), ''[[hadith]]'' (sayings of [[Muhammed]]) and ''[[sharia]]'' (law) towards the creation of a more equal and just society.&lt;ref&gt;http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2002/569/cu1.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

;People of interest
*[[Fadela Amara]]
*[[Asma Barlas]]
*[[Samira Bellil]]
*[[Mukhtaran Bibi]]
*[[Zilla Huma Usman]]
*[[Amina Wadud]]

==Scientific research into feminist issues==
Some natural and social scientists have considered feminist ideas and feminist forms of scholarship using scientific methods.

One core scientific controversy involves the issue of the social construction vs the biological formation of gender or sex associated identities.   Modern feminist science is based on the view that most if not all differences between the sexes are based on socially constructed gender identities rather than on biological sex differences.  For example, [[Anne Fausto-Sterling]]'s book ''Myths of Gender'' explores the assumptions embodied in scientific research that purports to support a biologically [[essentialist]] view of gender.&lt;ref name=Fausto-Sterling&gt; Fausto-Sterling, Anne ''Myths of Gender:Biological Theories About Men and Women '' (Basic Books Inc., 1992), ISBN 978978&lt;/ref&gt;  However, in ''The Female Brain'', Louann Brizendine argues that brain differences between the sexes are a biological reality with significant implications for sex-specific functional differences.&lt;ref name=Brizendine&gt; Brizendine, Louann ''The Female Brain'' (Bantam Press, 2007), ISBN 9780593058077&lt;/ref&gt; Steven Rhoads' book ''Taking Sex Differences Seriously'' illustrates sex-dependent differences across a wide scope.&lt;ref name=Rhoads&gt; Rhoads, Steven, ''Taking Sex Differences Seriously'' (Encounter Books, 2004), ISBN 9781893554931&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Carol Tavris]], in ''The Mismeasure of Woman'' (the title is a play on [[Stephen Jay Gould]]'s ''[[The Mismeasure of Man]]''), uses psychology, sociology, and analysis in a critique of theories that use biological [[reductionism]] to explain differences between men and women.  She argues rather than using evidence of innate gender difference there is an over-changing hypothesis to justify inequality and perpetuate stereotypes.&lt;ref name= Tavris&gt;{{cite book 
|last=Tavris |first=Carol |work=The Mismeasure of Woman: : Why Women Are Not the Better Sex, inferior or Opposite Sex |publisher= Simon &amp; Schuster, 1992 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Evelyn Fox Keller]] has argued that the rhetoric of science reflects a masculine perspective, and questions the idea of [[scientific objectivity]]. [[Primatologist]] [[Sarah Blaffer Hrdy]] notes the prevalence of masculine-coined stereotypes and theories, such as the non-sexual female, despite ;''the accumulation of abundant openly available evidence contradicting it''".&lt;ref name=Hrdy&gt;{{cite book 
|last=Blaffer Hrdy |first=Sarah |work=Infanticide: Comparative and Evolutionary Perspectives: Mother Nature: A History of Mothers, Infants and Natural Selection |publisher= Pantheon, 1999 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sarah Kember - drawing from numerous areas such as [[evolutionary biology]], [[sociobiology]], [[artificial intelligence]], and [[cybernetics]] in development with a new evolutionism - discusses the biologization of technology.  She notes how feminists and sociologists have become suspect of [[evolutionary psychology]], particularly inasmuch as sociobiology is subjected to [[complexity]] in order to strengthen sexual difference as [[immutable]] through pre-existing cultural value judgments about [[human nature]] and [[natural selection]].  Where feminist theory is criticized for its "false beliefs about human nature," Kember then argues in conclusion that "feminism is in the interesting position of needing to do more biology and evolutionary theory in order not to simply oppose their renewed hegemony, but in order to understand the conditions that make this possible, and to have a say in the construction of new ideas and artefacts."  &lt;ref&gt;Kember, Sarah. (2001). "Resisting the New Evolutionism," Women:  ''A Cultural Review'', Vol. 12, No. 1, pp. 1-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other concepts==
===Pro-feminism===
{{main|Pro-feminism}}
Pro-feminism is support of [[feminism]] without implying that the supporter is a member of the [[feminist movement]]. The term is most often used in reference to [[men]] who are actively supportive of feminism and of efforts to bring about [[gender equality]]  The activities of pro-feminist men's groups include anti-violence work with boys and young men in schools, offering [[sexual harassment]] workshops in workplaces, running community education campaigns, and counseling male perpetrators of violence.  Pro-feminist men also are involved in men's health, activism against pornography including anti-pornography legislation, [[men's studies]], the development of gender equity curricula in schools, and many other areas. This work is sometimes in collaboration with feminists and women's services, such as domestic violence and rape crisis centers.  Some activists of both genders will not refer to men as "feminists" at all, and will refer to all pro-feminist men as "pro-feminists".&lt;ref name=Kimmel&gt;[[Michael Kimmel|Kimmel, Michael S.,]] and Thomas E. Mosmiller ''Against the Tide: Pro-Feminist Men in the United States, 1776-1990 a Documentary History'' (Beacon, 1992), ISBN 9780807067673&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Lingard&gt; Lingard, Bob and Peter Douglas, ''Men Engaging Feminisms: Pro-feminism, Backlashes and Schooling'' (open University Press, 1999), ISBN 0335198177&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-feminism===
{{main|Anti-feminism}}
Opposition to [[feminism]] comes in many forms, either criticizing feminist ideology and practice or arguing that it be restrained. Antifeminism is often equated with [[male chauvinism]].

Feminists such as [[Camille Paglia]], [[Christina Hoff Sommers]], [[Jean Bethke Elshtain]] and [[Elizabeth Fox-Genovese]] have been labeled "antifeminists" by other feminists &lt;ref&gt;Judith Stacey, ''Is Academic Feminism an Oxymoron?'', Signs, Vol. 25, No. 4, Feminisms at a Millennium. (Summer, 2000), pp. 1189-1194&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth Kamarck Minnich, Review: 'Feminist Attacks on Feminisms: Patriarchy's Prodigal Daughters', Feminist Studies, Vol. 24, No. 1. (Spring, 1998), pp. 159-175 &lt;/ref&gt;. Patai and Koerge argue that in this way the term "antifeminist" is used to silence academic debate about feminism.&lt;ref&gt;Patai and Koerge, ''Professing Feminism: Education and Indoctrination in Women's Studies'', (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Nathanson and Young|Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young's]] books ''Spreading Misandry'' and ''Legalizing Misandry'' explore what they argue is feminist-inspired [[misandry]].&lt;ref name="Legalizing Misandry"&gt;Nathanson, P. and K. K. Young, ''Legalizing Misandry: From Public Shame to Systemic Descrimination Against Men'' (McGill-Queen's University Press)&lt;/ref&gt;.  [[Christina Hoff-Sommers]] argues feminist misandry leads directly to [[misogyny]] by what she calls "establishment feminists" against (the majority of) women who love men in ''Who Stole Feminism: How Women Have Betrayed Women''.

"Marriage rights" advocates criticize feminists like Shelia Cronan who take the view that marriage constitutes slavery for women, and that freedom for women cannot be won without the abolition of marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| title = The Married Professional Woman: A Study in the Tolerance of Domestication
| author = Poloma M. M., Garland T. N.
| journal = Journal of Marriage and the Family
| year = 1971
| volume = 33
| issue = 3
| pages = 531-540
| url =  http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-2445%28197108%2933%3A3%3C531%3ATMPWAS%3E2.0.CO%3B2-%23
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable feminists==
* See [[List of feminists]]
* See [http://www-scf.usc.edu/~saddawik/Famous/famous.html Famous Feminists]

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

==See also==
*[[Equal pay for women]]
*[[Equal Rights Amendment]]
*[[European Feminist Forum]]
*[[Feminist history in the United States]]
*[[Feminist history in the United Kingdom]]
*[[Feminism in Poland|Feminist history in Poland]]
*[[Feminist history in Latin America]]
*[[Feminist therapy]]
*[[Hate speech]]
*[[Teaching for social justice]]
*[[Lesbian feminism]]
*[[New feminism]]
*[[Social criticism]]
*[[Women's cinema]]
*[[Women's Environment &amp; Development Organization]]
*[[Women's music]]
*[[Sex/gender distinction]]

;Masculist movements
*[[Men's Rights]]
*[[Masculism]]

;Derogatory neologisms
*[[Feminazi]]

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{wiktionary}}
{{wikiversity|Women's Studies}}
{{commons|Feminism}}

*[http://www.awpsych.org/ Association for Women in Psychology]
*[http://www.AdvanceWomen.org/ Center for the Advancement of Women]
*[http://www.cawinfo.org/ Committee for Asian Women]
*[http://www.europeanfeministforum.org/ European Feminist Forum]
*[http://www.feministinitiative.ca/ FemINist INitiative of Canada]
*[http://now.org NOW] - National Organization for Women in the United States.
*[http://www.wluml.org/english/ Women living under Muslim laws]
*[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0405/24/i_ins.00.html Muslim Women Rebel In France]
*[http://www.ffeusa.org Feminists for Free Expression]
*[http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/index.html The Feminist eZine] - 1001 Feminist Links.
*[http://www.womensforumaustralia.org/ Women's Forum Australia]
*[http://www.radicalwomen.org/ Radical Women]
*[http://www.rawa.org/ Revolutionary Association of the Women of Afghanistan (RAWA)]
*[http://www.owl-national.org/ Older Women's League - The Voice of Midlife and Older Women (OWL)]
*[http://www.roks.se/ ROKS - Swedish women's organization]
*[http://www.fnsa.org/ Feminism &amp; Nonviolence Studies]
*[http://www.susanbrownmiller.com Susan Brownmiller.com: Where Feminism Lives]
*[http://www.fembio.org/default.shtml FemBio - Notable Women International]
*[http://www.mediaradar.org/ RADAR]
*[http://organizenow.net/cco/right/antifem.html Female Anti-Feminism for Fame and Profit], by Jennifer Pozner
*[http://www.irfi.org/articles/articles_101_150/religious_conservatism.htm Riffat Hasan on ''Religious conservatism: Feminist theology as a means of combating injustice towards women in Muslim communities/culture'']
*[http://www.jwa.org/feminism Jewish Women and the Feminist Revolution] from the Jewish Women's Archive
*[http://www.liberalislam.net/women.html Islam from Patriarch]

{{Discriminationfooter}}
{{Ideologies}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Feminism}}
[[Category:Feminism| ]]
[[Category:Sociological paradigms]]
[[Category:Sociological theories]]
[[Category:Civil rights]]

{{Link FA|el}}
{{Link FA|pt}}

[[ar:أنثوية]]
[[bn:নারীবাদ]]
[[bs:Feminizam]]
[[bg:Феминизъм]]
[[ca:Feminisme]]
[[cs:Feminismus]]
[[da:Feminisme]]
[[de:Feminismus]]
[[et:Feminism]]
[[el:Φεμινισμός]]
[[es:Feminismo]]
[[eo:Feminismo]]
[[eu:Feminismo]]
[[fa:فمینیسم]]
[[fr:Féminisme]]
[[gd:Boireann-dhligheachas]]
[[gl:Feminismo]]
[[ko:여성주의]]
[[hi:नारीवाद]]
[[hr:Feminizam]]
[[id:Feminisme]]
[[ia:Feminismo]]
[[ie:Feminisme]]
[[it:Femminismo]]
[[he:פמיניזם]]
[[ka:ფემინიზმი]]
[[lt:Feminizmas]]
[[hu:Feminizmus]]
[[mk:Феминизам]]
[[ms:Feminisme]]
[[nl:Feminisme]]
[[ja:フェミニズム]]
[[no:Feminisme]]
[[nn:Feminisme]]
[[pl:Feminizm]]
[[pt:Feminismo]]
[[ro:Feminism]]
[[ru:Феминизм]]
[[scn:Fimminismu]]
[[simple:Feminism]]
[[sk:Feminizmus (hnutie)]]
[[sl:Feminizem]]
[[sr:Феминизам]]
[[sh:Feminizam]]
[[fi:Feminismi]]
[[sv:Feminism]]
[[ta:பெண்ணியம்]]
[[tr:Feminizm]]
[[uk:Фемінізм]]
[[wa:Feminisse]]
[[zh:女權主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>