<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081112205833|251412863" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12987" pageid="12987" ns="0" title="Gerrymandering"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-12T21:26:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{globalize/USA}}
{{Mergefrom|Electoral geography|date=July 2008}}
{{Elections}}

'''Gerrymandering''' is a form of [[Redistribution (election)|redistribution]] in which electoral district or [[constituency]] boundaries are manipulated for electoral advantage. Gerrymandering may be used to help or hinder particular [[constituent (politics)|constituent]]s, such as members of a political, racial, linguistic, religious or class group. 

The term gerrymandering is derived from [[Elbridge Gerry]] (1744&amp;ndash;1814), the governor of Massachusetts from 1810 to 1812. The term first appeared in the [[Boston Gazette]] on March 26, 1812 (see image). In 1812, Governor Gerry signed a bill into law that redistricted his state to benefit his [[Democratic-Republican]] party.

==Voting systems==
Gerrymandering is used most often in favor of ruling [[incumbent]]s&lt;ref&gt;Michel Balinski, "Fair Majority Voting (or How to Eliminate Gerrymandering)" ''Amer. Math. Monthly'' '''115''' 2 (2008): 97. "Incumbent candidates, in tailored districts, are almost certain of reelection (over 98% in 2002, over 94% in 2006).&lt;/ref&gt; or a specific [[political party]]. Societies whose legislatures use a single-winner [[voting system]] are the most likely to have political parties that gerrymander for advantage.{{Fact|date=October 2008}} Most notably, gerrymandering is particularly effective in [[Voting system#Non-proportional and semi-proportional methods|non-proportional systems]] that tend towards fewer parties, such as ''[[first past the post]]''.

Most democracies have partly proportional electoral systems, where several political parties are proportionally represented in the national parliaments, in proportion to the total numbers of votes of the parties in the regional or national elections. In these more or less [[proportional representation]] systems, gerrymandering has little or less significance.

Some countries, such as the [[United Kingdom|UK]] and [[Canada]], authorize non-partisan organizations to set constituency boundaries to prevent gerrymandering. Gerrymandering is most common in countries where elected politicians are responsible for defining constituency boundaries. They have obvious self interest in determining boundaries to their and their party's interest. The [[United States of America]] is an example of such a system.

[[Image:The Gerry-Mander.png|thumb|right|right|Printed in 1812, this political cartoon illustrates the electoral districts drawn by the [[Massachusetts]] legislature to favor the incumbent [[Democratic-Republican]] party candidates of Governor Elbridge Gerry over the [[Federalists]], from which the term gerrymander is derived. The cartoon depicts the bizarre shape of a district in [[Essex County, Massachusetts]] as a [[dragon#Mythology|dragon]].]]
[[Image:AZ-districts-109-02.gif|thumb|[[Arizona's 2nd congressional district]].]]

Gerrymandering should not be confused with [[Apportionment (politics)#Malapportionment|malapportionment]], whereby the number of eligible voters per elected representative can vary widely. Nevertheless the ''~mander'' suffix has been applied to particular malapportionments, such as the "[[Playmander]]" in [[South Australia]] and the "[[Bjelkemander]]" in [[Queensland]]. Sometimes political representatives use both gerrymandering and malapportionment to try to maintain power.&lt;br clear="left"&gt;

==Etymology==

The word "gerrymander" is named for the [[Governor]] of [[Massachusetts]] [[Elbridge Gerry]] ([[July 17]], [[1744]] &amp;ndash; [[November 23]], [[1814]]),&lt;ref&gt; Gerry pronounced his name {{IPAEng|ˈgɛri}} (with a hard ''G'')&lt;/ref&gt; and is a blend (or [[portmanteau]]) of his name with the word "[[Salamander (legendary creature)|salamander]]," used to describe the shape of a tortuous electoral district pressed through the Massachusetts legislature in 1812. [[Jeffersonian democrat]]s devised the boundaries —and Gerry reluctantly signed the district into law — to reduce competition by their electoral opponents in the upcoming senatorial election.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/treasures/trr113.html The Gerrymander].&lt;/ref&gt; "Gerrymander" is used both as a [[verb]], meaning "to divide into political units to give special advantages to one group", as well as a [[noun]] to describe the resulting electoral geography. Although Elbridge Gerry's name was pronounced with an initial /g/ (a [[hard g]]), the "jerry" pronunciation has become most common.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.randomhouse.com/wotd/index.pperl?date=19990202 The Mavens' Word of the Day&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; President Ronald Reagan always used the hard G and some older professors in the US still pronounce gerrymandering with the "hard g."&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.byui.edu/directory/employees/OfficeHours.aspx?User=INAMAB Bob Inama&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

=="Packing and cracking"==
[[Image:Ca23 109.gif|thumb|left| An example of the "packing" style of districting: [[California's 23rd congressional district]] ]]
[[Image:Columbus Ohio Congressional Districts.gif|thumb|An example of "cracking" style Gerrymandering, where the urban (and mostly liberal) concentration of [[Columbus, Ohio]], located at the center of the map in [[Franklin County, Ohio|Franklin County]], is split into thirds, each segment then attached to&amp;mdash;and outnumbered by&amp;mdash;largely conservative [[suburb]]s.]]

The two aims of gerrymandering are to maximize the effect of supporters’ votes and to minimize the effect of opponents' votes. One strategy, ''packing'', is to concentrate as many voters of one type into a single electoral district to reduce their influence in other districts. A second strategy, ''cracking'', involves spreading out voters of a particular type among many districts in order to deny them a sufficiently large voting block in any particular district. The strategies are typically combined, creating a few "forfeit" seats for packed voters of one type in order to secure even greater representation for voters of another type.

Gerrymandering is effective because of the [[wasted vote effect]]. By packing opposition voters into districts they will already win (increasing excess votes for winners) and by cracking the remainder among districts where they are moved into the minority (increasing votes for eventual losers), the number of wasted votes among the opposition can be maximized. Similarly, with supporters holding narrow margins in the unpacked districts, the number of wasted votes among supporters is minimized.

[[Image:Gerrymandering 36-28.png‎|thumb|400px|right|'''How Gerrymandering can influence electoral results on a [[Voting_system#Non-proportional_and_semi-proportional_methods|non-proportional system]].''' Example for a state with 4 districts and a 36:28 Green (G) party majority. '''Top left:''' Magenta (M) party wins the urban district, while G party wins the 3 rural/suburban districts — the result expresses and enhances the fact that G is the state-wide majority party. '''Top right:''' by redesigning the 4 districts, there is a 2:2 tie, with G dominating the 2 new rural districts and M dominating the 2 new urban/suburban districts — closer to proportionality, but masking the fact that G is the state-wide majority party. '''Bottom left:''' Creating 4 mixed-type districts can yield a 4:0 win to G — a disproportional result considering the state-wide reality. '''Bottom right:''' With classical Gerrymandering techniques it is even possible to ensure a 1:3 win to the state-wide minority, M party.]]

==Effects of gerrymandering==
&lt;!-- We should mention the claim that contention over districts creates a major distraction for the legislature --&gt;

===Reduction in electoral competition and voter turnout===
The most immediate and obvious effect of gerrymandering is that elections become less competitive in all districts, particularly packed ones. As electoral margins of victory become significantly greater and politicians have [[safe seat]]s, the incentive for meaningful campaigning is reduced.

As the chance of influencing electoral results by voting is reduced, [[voter turnout]] is likely to decrease. Correspondingly, political campaigns are less likely to expend resources to encourage turnout. &lt;!-- an example fact here regarding turnout stats or efforts to encourage turnout in competitive/noncompetitive elections would be great --&gt;With a reduction in competition, a candidate puts more effort into securing party [[nomination]] for a given district rather than gaining approval of the general electorate. In a gerrymandered district, the candidate is virtually assured of a win once nominated. In 2004, for example, when California's 3rd [[Congressional District]] became an [[open seat]] after Republican Congressman [[Doug Ose]] ran for higher office, the state's three strongest Republican congressional candidates campaigned vigorously against one another for nomination in the district's [[primary election]]. Several other districts were uncontested with no Republican nominees making even a token campaign effort.

===Increased incumbent advantage and campaign costs===
The effect of gerrymandering for incumbents is particularly advantageous, as incumbents are far more likely to be reelected under conditions of gerrymandering. For example, in 2002, according to political scientists [[Norman Ornstein]] and [[Thomas E. Mann|Thomas Mann]], only four challengers were able to defeat incumbent members of the US Congress, the lowest number in modern American history.&lt;ref name="7_buck_trust.html"&gt;[http://www.centrists.org/pages/2004/07/7_buck_trust.html Centrists.Org - Iowa's Redistricting Process: An Example of the Right Way to Draw Legislative&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Incumbents are likely to be of the majority party orchestrating a gerrymander, and incumbents are usually easily renominated in subsequent elections, including incumbents among the minority.

This demonstrates that gerrymandering can have a deleterious effect on the principle of democratic accountability. With uncompetitive seats/districts reducing the fear that incumbent politicians may lose office, they have less incentive to represent the interests of their constituents, even when those interests conform to majority support for an issue across the electorate as a whole. Incumbent politicians may look out more for their party's interests than for those of their constituents.

Gerrymandering can have an impact on campaign costs for district elections. If districts become increasingly stretched out, candidates must pay increased costs for transportation and trying to develop and present [[campaign advertising]] across a district.{{Fact|Apr 2008|date=April 2008}} The incumbent's advantage in securing campaign funds is another benefit of his or her having a gerrymandered secure seat.

===Less descriptive representation===
[[Image:CA 11thCD clip.png|frame|right|A gerrymandered Congressional District, the 11th CD of CA (now occupied by Democrat [[Jerry McNerney]]), drawn to favor Republican [[Richard Pombo]]. While the Danville area is a traditional Republican stronghold, Morgan Hill is not, and that largely Democratic district was added to obtain the proper population numbers for the 11th after [[Livermore, California|Livermore]] was assigned to the 10th at the behest of the incumbent Democrat ([[Ellen Tauscher]]), since it contains the [[Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory]] (located near the "''580''" shield) and she sits in the House Energy Committee. The 10th CD is immediately north of the 11th in Contra Costa and Solano Counties. See the [[California 11th congressional district election, 2006]] for an unexpected result that overcame this gerrymander.]]

[[Image:California District 38 2004.png|thumb|right|Aided by computer, District 38 was produced by [[Politics of California#Bi-partisan gerrymandering|California's incumbent gerrymandering]], as home to [[Grace Napolitano|Grace Flores Napolitano]], a [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrat]], who ran unopposed in 2004 (compare to Republican Texas District 22, below).]]

Gerrymandering also has significant effects on the [[representation (politics)|representation]] received by voters in gerrymandered districts. Because gerrymandering is designed to increase the number of wasted votes among the electorate, the relative representation of particular groups can be drastically altered from their actual share of the voting population. This effect can significantly prevent a gerrymandered system from achieving [[proportional representation|proportional]] and [[descriptive representation]], as the winners of elections are increasingly determined by who is drawing the districts rather than the preferences of the voters.

Gerrymandering may be advocated to improve representation within the legislature among otherwise underrepresented minority groups by packing them into a single district. This can be controversial, as it may lead to those groups' remaining marginalized in the government as they become confined to a single district. Candidates outside that district no longer need to represent them to win election.

As an example, much of the redistricting conducted in the United States in the early 1990s involved the intentional creation of additional "majority-minority" districts where racial minorities such as [[African Americans]] were packed into the majority. This "[[maximization policy]]" drew support by both the Republican Party (who had limited support among African Americans and could concentrate their power elsewhere) and by minority representatives elected as [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrat]]s from these constituencies, who then had "[[safe seat]]s." &lt;!-- cite a famous politician or political scientist that has a good quote of this here --&gt;

===Incumbent gerrymandering===

Gerrymandering can also be done to help [[incumbent]]s as a whole, effectively turning every district into a packed one and greatly reducing the potential for competitive elections. This is particularly likely to occur when the minority party has significant obstruction power — unable to enact a partisan gerrymander, the legislature instead agrees on ensuring their own mutual reelection.

In an unusual occurrence in 2000, for example, the two dominant parties in the state of [[California]] [[Politics of California#Bi-partisan gerrymandering|cooperatively redrew]] both state and Federal legislative districts to preserve the status quo, ensuring the electoral safety of the politicians from unpredictable voting by the electorate. This move proved completely effective, as no State or Federal legislative office changed party in the [[U.S. House election, 2004|2004 election]], although 53 congressional, 20 state senate, and 80 state assembly seats were potentially at risk.

In 2006, the term "70/30 District" came to signify the equitable split of two evenly split (i.e. 50/50) districts. The resulting districts gave each party a guaranteed seat and retained their respective power base.

==Changes to achieve competitive elections==
Due to many issues associated with gerrymandering and its impact on competitive elections and democratic accountability, numerous countries have enacted reforms making the practice either more difficult or less effective. Countries such as the UK, Australia, Canada and most of those in Europe have transferred responsibility for defining constituency boundaries to neutral or cross-party bodies.

In the United States, however, such reforms are controversial and frequently meet particularly strong opposition from groups that benefit from gerrymandering. In a more neutral system, they might lose considerable influence.

[[Image:TX22 109 abcdef.gif|thumb|left|Aided by computer, District 22 was produced by [[2003 Texas Redistricting|Redistricting in Texas]] for former Rep. [[Tom DeLay]], a Republican (compare to Democratic California District 38, above).]]

===Redistricting by neutral or cross-party agency===
The most commonly advocated electoral reform proposal targeted at gerrymandering is to change the redistricting process. Under these proposals, an independent and presumably objective commission is created specifically for redistricting, rather than having the legislature do it. This is the system used in the [[United Kingdom]], where the independent [[Boundary Commission (United Kingdom)|Boundary Commission]] determines the boundaries for [[United Kingdom constituencies|constituencies]] in the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]] and regional legislatures, subject to ratification by the body in question (almost always granted without debate).

To help ensure neutrality, members of a redistricting agency may be appointed from relatively apolitical sources such as retired judges or longstanding members of the [[civil service]], possibly with requirements for adequate representation among competing political parties. Additionally, members of the board can be denied access to information that might aid in gerrymandering, such as the demographic makeup or voting patterns of the population. As a further constraint, [[consensus]] requirements can be imposed to ensure that the resulting district map reflects a wider perception of fairness, such as a requirement for a [[supermajority]] approval of the commission for any district proposal. Consensus requirements, however, can lead to deadlock, such as occurred in [[Missouri]] following the 2000 census. There, the equally numbered partisan appointees were unable to reach consensus in a reasonable time, and consequently the courts had to determine district lines.

In the US state of [[Iowa]], the nonpartisan Legislative Services Bureau (LSB) (akin to the US [[Congressional Research Service]]) determines boundaries of electoral districts. Aside from satisfying federally mandated contiguity and population equality criteria, the LSB mandates unity of counties and cities. Consideration of political factors such as location of incumbents, previous boundary locations, and political party proportions is specifically forbidden. Since Iowa's counties are chiefly regularly shaped [[polygons]], the LSB process has led to districts that follow county lines.&lt;ref name="7_buck_trust.html"/&gt;

In 2005, the US state of [[Ohio]] had a ballot measure to create an independent commission whose first priority was competitive districts, a sort of "reverse gerrymander". A complex mathematical formula was to be used to determine the competitiveness of a district. The measure failed voter approval chiefly due to voter concerns that communities of interest would be broken up.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smartvoter.org/2005/11/08/oh/state/issue/4/ Issue 4: Independent Redistricting Process - Ohio State Government&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Changing the voting system===
Because gerrymandering relies on the wasted vote effect, the use of a different [[voting system]] with fewer wasted votes can help reduce gerrymandering. In particular, the use of [[multimember district]]s alongside voting systems establishing [[proportional representation]] such as [[single non-transferable vote]] or [[cumulative voting]] can greatly reduce the proportion of wasted votes, and therefore the potential for gerrymandering. Due to their relative simplicity and similarity to ''[[first past the post]]''{{Fact|date=November 2008}} electoral reformers often advocate them as replacement systems{{Fact|date=November 2008}}.

Electoral systems with different forms of proportional representation are now found in nearly all European countries. In this way, they have multi-party systems (with many parties represented in the parliaments) with higher voter attendance in the elections{{Fact|date=November 2008}}, fewer wasted votes, and a wider variety of political opinions represented.

Electoral systems with election of just one candidate in each district, and no proportional distribution of extra mandates to smaller parties, tend to create two-party systems ([[Duverger's Law]]). In these, just two parties effectively compete in the national elections and thus the national political discussions are forced into a narrow two-party frame, where loyalty and forced statements inside the two parties distort the political debate.

===Changing the size of districts and the elected body===
If a proportional or semi-proportional voting system alongside multimember districts is used, then increasing the number of winners in any given district will reduce the number of wasted votes. This can be accomplished both by merging separate districts together and by increasing the total size of the body to be elected. Since gerrymandering relies on exploiting the wasted vote effect to secure electoral advantage, reducing the number of wasted votes by increasing the number of winners in a district can greatly reduce the potential for gerrymandering. Unless all districts are merged, however, this method cannot eliminate gerrymandering entirely.

In contrast to proportional methods, if a nonproportional voting system with multiple winners (such as [[plurality-at-large voting|block voting]]) is used, then increasing the size of the elected body while keeping the number of districts constant will not reduce the amount of wasted votes, leaving the potential for gerrymandering the same. While merging districts together under such a system can reduce the potential for gerrymandering, doing so also amplifies the tendency of block voting to produce [[landslide victory|landslide victories]], creating a similar effect to gerrymandering by concentrating wasted votes among the opposition and denying them representation.

If a system of single-winner elections is used, then increasing the size of the elected body will implicitly increase the number of districts to be created. This change can actually make gerrymandering easier when raising the number of single-winner elections, as opposition groups can be more efficiently packed into smaller districts without accidentally including supporters, further increasing the number of wasted votes amongst the opposition.

===Using fixed districts===
Another way to avoid gerrymandering is simply to stop redistricting altogether and use existing political boundaries such as state, county, or provincial lines. Any existing advantage may become deeply ingrained. The [[United States Senate]], for instance, has more competitive elections than the House of Representatives due to the use of existing state borders rather than gerrymandered districts — Senators are elected by their entire state, while Representatives are elected in legislatively-drawn districts.

The use of fixed districts creates an additional problem, however, in that fixed districts do not take into account changes in population. Individual voters can come to have very different degrees of influence on the legislative process. This [[malapportionment]] can greatly affect representation after long periods of time or large population movements. In the United Kingdom during the [[industrial revolution]], several constituencies which had been fixed since they gained representation in the Parliament of England became so small that they could be won with only a handful of voters (''[[rotten borough]]s''). Similarly, in the US the state legislature of Alabama refused to redistrict for more than 60 years, despite major changes in population patterns. By 1960 less than a quarter of the state's population (from rural areas) controlled the majority of seats in the legislature.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Michael McDonald, US Elections Project: Alabama Redistricting Summary [http://elections.gmu.edu/Redistricting/AL.htm Dept. of Public and International Affairs
George Mason University], accessed 6 Apr 2008&lt;/ref&gt; By contrast, [[Switzerland]] and [[Spain]] have bicameral national legislatures like the United States, but both of its houses use fixed districts - However, those use proportional representation and not [[Plurality_voting_system#First_past_the_post|FPTP]]. The Supreme Court decision ''[[Baker v. Carr]]'' established a rule of "[[one man one vote]]," effectively banning fixed districts (even by existing municipal boundaries such as counties) in state legislatures, although if combined with multiple [[at-large]] representatives within more populous districts, it would theoretically be legal.

[[Image:Illinois District 4 2004.png|thumb|right|The unusual "earmuff" shape of the [[Illinois' 4th congressional district|4th Congressional District of Illinois]] connects two Hispanic neighborhoods while remaining connected by narrowly tracing [[Interstate 294]]. A similar district is [[New York's 28th congressional district]] which connects the heavily Democratic cities of [[Rochester, New York|Rochester]] and [[Buffalo, New York|Buffalo]] with a narrow strip of territory hugging the [[Lake Ontario]] and [[Niagara River]] coastlines to connect them.]]

===Objective rules to create districts===
Another means to reduce gerrymandering is to create objective, precise criteria to which any district map must comply. Courts in the United States, for instance, have ruled that congressional districts must be contiguous in order to be constitutional. This, however, is not a particularly binding constraint, as very narrow strips of land with few or no voters in them may be used to connect separate regions for inclusion in one district. Another objective criterion is maximized [[Compactness measure of a shape|compactness]], subject to other constraints such as geographic features and boundaries of local governments. &lt;!-- other rules: equal population, concave. also note these rules are either not implemented, or not enforced. --&gt;

One idea is to define within the constitution a specific '''minimum [[isoperimetric quotient]]''' &lt;ref&gt;[http://mathworld.wolfram.com/IsoperimetricQuotient.html Isoperimetric Quotient - from Wolfram MathWorld&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;, or minimum ratio, between the area and perimeter of any given congressional voting district. Computer algorithms could ensure that population districts were drawn in such a way so as to minimize [[Isoperimetric inequality]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://mathworld.wolfram.com/IsoperimetricInequality.html Isoperimetric Inequality - from Wolfram MathWorld&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and effectively eliminate gerrymandering. Although technologies presently exist to define districts in this manner, there are no rules in place mandating their use, and no national movement to implement such a policy. Such rules would prevent incorporation of jagged natural boundaries, such as rivers or mountains. When such boundaries are required (such as at the edge of a state), certain districts may not be able to meet the required minima.

Another method is to define a '''minimum district to [[convex polygon]] ratio'''. To use this method, every proposed district is circumscribed by the smallest possible convex polygon (similar to the concept of a [[convex hull]]). Then, the area of the district is divided by the area of the polygon; or, if at the edge of the state, by the portion of the area of the polygon within state boundaries. The advantages of this method are that it allows a certain amount of human intervention to take place (thus solving the Colorado problem of splitline districting); it allows the borders of the district to follow existing jagged subdivisions, such as neighborhoods or voting districts (something isoperimetric rules would discourage); and it allows concave coastline districts, such as the Florida gulf coast area. It would mostly eliminate "bent" districts, but still permit long, straight ones. However, since human intervention is still allowed, the gerrymandering issues of packing and cracking would still occur, just to a lesser extent.

====Shortest splitline algorithm====
The [[Center for Range Voting]] has proposed&lt;ref&gt;http://www.RangeVoting.org/GerryExamples.html&lt;/ref&gt; a way to draw districts by a simple [[algorithm]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.RangeVoting.org RangeVoting.org - Center for Range Voting]&lt;/ref&gt; Because the algorithm uses only the shape of the state, the number N of districts wanted, and the population distribution as inputs — and does not know the party loyalties of those people — the result cannot be biased. The algorithm (slightly simplified) is:
# Start with the boundary outline of the state.
# Let N=A+B where A and B are as nearly equal whole numbers as possible. (For example, 7=4+3.)
# Among all possible dividing lines that split the state into two parts with population ratio A:B, choose the ''shortest''.
# We now have two hemi-states, each to contain a specified number (namely A and B) of districts. Handle them recursively via the same splitting procedure.
This district-drawing algorithm has the advantage of simplicity, ultra-low cost, clear unbiasedness, and it produces simple boundaries that do not meander needlessly. It has the disadvantage of ignoring geographic features such as rivers, cliffs, and highways and cultural features such as tribal boundaries. This landscape oversight causes it to produce districts differently than those an unbiased human would produce.  Not ignoring geographic features can induce very complicated boundaries.

Also, splitline districts sometimes do not work well when one of the first few splitlines cuts through a large metropolitan area. This is most evident in the splitline allocation of [[Colorado]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rangevoting.org/SSHR/co_final.png&lt;/ref&gt;

As of July 2007, shortest-splitline redistricting pictures are now available for all 50 states.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.RangeVoting.org/SplitLR.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Use of databases and computer technology==
{{See also|Geographic information system}}
The introduction of modern [[computer]]s alongside the development of elaborate [[voter database]]s and special districting software has made gerrymandering a far more precise science. Using such databases, political parties can obtain detailed information about every household including political party registration, previous campaign donations, and the number of times residents voted in previous elections and combine it with other predictors of voting behavior such as age, income, race, or education level. With this data, gerrymandering politicians can predict the voting behavior of each potential district with an astonishing degree of precision, leaving little chance for creating an accidentally competitive district.

==National examples of gerrymandering==
Among western democracies, Israel and the Netherlands employ electoral systems with only one (nationwide) voting district for election of national representatives. This precludes gerrymandering.

===Canada===
Early in [[Canada|Canadian]] history, both the federal and provincial levels used gerrymandering to try to maximize partisan power. Since responsibility for drawing electoral boundaries was handed over to independent agencies, this problem has essentially been eliminated. Manitoba was the first province to authorize a non-partisan group to define constituency boundaries in the 1950s. In 1964, the federal government delegated the drawing of boundaries for national seats to the "arm's length" [[Elections Canada]]. As a result, gerrymandering is not generally a major issue in Canada.

In 2006, a controversy arose on [[Prince Edward Island]] over the provincial government's decision to throw out an electoral map drawn by an independent commission. Instead they created two new maps. The government adopted the second of these, designed by the [[caucus]] of the governing party. Opposition parties and the media attacked Premier [[Pat Binns]] for what they saw as gerrymandering of districts. Among other things, the government adopted a map that ensured that every current [[Member of the Legislative Assembly]] from the premier's party had a district to run in for re-election, whereas in the original map, several had been redistricted. Despite this, in the [[Prince Edward Island general election, 2007|2007 provincial election]] only seven of 20 incumbent Members of the Legislative Assembly were re-elected (seven did not run for re-election).

The current federal electoral district boundaries in [[Saskatchewan]] have also been labelled as gerrymandered — the province's two major cities, [[Saskatoon]] and [[Regina, Saskatchewan|Regina]], are both "cracked" into multiple districts which group parts of the [[New Democratic Party]]-friendly cities with large [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative]]-leaning rural areas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elections.ca/scripts/fedrep/searchengine/search_by_maps.asp Current electoral map of Saskatchewan]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chile===

After Chileans voted General [[Augusto Pinochet]] out of power in a 1988 plebiscite, the military government began working on a law to define the new electoral system for the 1989 elections. The [[Electoral division of Chile|60 electoral districts]] for the [[Chamber of Deputies of Chile|Chamber of Deputies]] (lower house) were designed so that — if the results of the 1988 plebiscite were extrapolated to the coming parliamentary elections — in no district would the NO option duplicate the YES option. (The NO option was for removing Pinochet from power and to trigger democratic elections.) The rationale for this — in a system in which only two candidates are elected per district and where a coalition needed to duplicate the vote of the opponent to gain both district seats — was that the voters who favoured the NO option would vote for the [[Concert of Parties for Democracy|Centre-Left coalition]], which opposed the Pinochet dictatorship, and the ones that favoured the YES option would be inclined to vote for the candidates of the [[Alliance for Chile|right]], which supported the military government.

In the [[Senate of Chile|Senate]] —where a whole [[Regions of Chile|administrative region]] consists of one or two constituencies— gerrymandering of districts had a limited effect. Therefore, the government, to ensure that the winning majority (the Center-Left coalition, as it was expected) would be unable to reach the [[quorum]] necessary to change the [[Constitution of Chile|Constitution]] by itself, allocated a number of seats to appointed senators.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psr.keele.ac.uk/docs/chile.htm The Chilean Electoral System].&lt;/ref&gt; These unelected senators were eliminated in the 2005 constitutional reforms, but the electoral map remains untouched.

===Germany===
When the electoral districts in [[Germany]] were redrawn in 2000, the ruling Social Democratic Party ([[Social Democratic Party of Germany|SPD]]) was accused of gerrymandering to marginalize the socialist [[Left Party (Germany)|PDS]] party. The SPD combined traditional PDS strongholds in eastern [[Berlin]] with new districts made up of more populous areas of western Berlin, where the PDS had very limited following.

After having won four seats in Berlin in the 1998 national election, the PDS was able to retain only two seats altogether in the 2002 elections. Under German electoral law, a [[political party]] has to win either more than five percent of the votes, or at least three directly-elected seats, to qualify for top-up seats under the [[Additional Member System]]. The PDS thus were unable to qualify for top-up seats and were confined to just two members of the [[Bundestag]], the German federal [[parliament]]. But the elected representatives held their seats as individuals. In the election of 2005, the PDS (renamed the "Left Party") gained 8.7% of the votes and thus qualified for top-up seats.

&lt;!--Ugly paragraph and very confusing - needs more explanation--&gt;However, the number of Bundestag seats of parties which traditionally get over 5% of the votes cannot be affected very much by gerrymandering, because seats are awarded to these parties on a proportional basis. Only when a party wins so many districts in any one of the 16 federal states that those seats alone count for more than its proportional share of the vote in that same state does the districting have some influence on larger parties — those extra seats, called "[[Overhang seat|Überhangmandate]]", remain.

===Greece===
Gerrymandering has been rather common in Greek history since organised parties with national ballots only appeared after the 1926 Constitution. The only case before that was the creation of the Piraeus electoral district in 1906, in order to give the Theotokis party a safe district. The most infamous case of gerrymandering was in the 1956 elections, which was incidentaly the first election where women voted. While in all other post [[World War II]] national elections the districts were based on the [[perfecture]] (νομός) for 1956 the country was split in districts of varying sizes, others being the size of perfectures, others the size of sub-perfectures (επαρχία) and others somewhere inbetween. In small districts the winning party would take all sears, in intermediate size it would take most and there was proportional representation in the largest districts. The districts though were chosen in such a way that small districts were those that traditionally voted for the right while large districts were those that voted against the right. This system has become known as the three-phase (τριφασικό) system or the baklava system (because like baklava is split in full pieces and corner pieces the country was also split in disproportionate pieces) The oppositions being composed of the center and the left formed a coalition with the sole intent to change the electoral law to be more representative and call new elections, despite the fact that only 7 years earlier the center and the left had fought each other in the [[Greek Civil War]]. Despite the opposition winning the popular vote (1,620,007 votes against 1,594,992), the right wing [[ERE]] won the majority of seats (165 to 135) and was to lead the country for the next 2 years

===Ireland===
Until the 1980s [[Dáil Éireann|Dáil]] boundaries in the state of Ireland were drawn not by an independent commission but by government ministers. Successive arrangements by governments of all political characters have been attacked as gerrymandering. Ireland uses the [[Single Transferable Vote]] and as well as the actual boundaries drawn the main tool of gerrymandering has been the seat size used, with three-seat constituencies normally benefiting the strongest parties in an area, whereas four-seat constituencies normally helped the second strongest party.

In 1947 the rapid rise of new party [[Clann na Poblachta]] threatened the position of the governing party [[Fianna Fáil]]. The government of [[Éamon de Valera]] introduced the [[Electoral Amendment Act, 1947]] which increased the size of the Dáil from 138 to 147 and increased the number of three-seat constituencies from fifteen to twenty-two. The result has been described as "a blatant attempt at gerrymander which no [[Northern Ireland|Six County]] Unionist could have bettered."&lt;ref name="coogan637"&gt;Tim Pat Coogan, ''De Valera: Long Fellow, Long Shadow'' (Hutchinson, London, 1993) hardback. page 637 ISBN 009175030X&lt;/ref&gt; The following February the [[Irish general election, 1948|1948 general election]] was held and Clann na Poblachta secured ten constituencies instead of the nineteen they would have received proportional to their vote.&lt;ref name="coogan637" /&gt;

===="Tullymandering"====
In the mid-1970s, the Minister for Local Government, [[James Tully (politician)|James Tully]], attempted to arrange the multi-member [[Single Transferable Vote]] constituencies to ensure that the governing [[Fine Gael]]/[[Labour Party (Ireland)|Labour]] [[National Coalition]] would win a parliamentary majority. The [[Electoral (Amendment) Act 1974]] was planned as a major reversal of previous gerrymandering by the [[Fianna Fáil]] party (then in opposition). Tully ensured that there were as many as possible three-seat constituencies where the governing parties were strong, in the expectation that the governing parties would each win a seat in many constituencies, relegating the [[Fianna Fáil]] party to one out of three. In areas where the governing parties were weak, four-seat constituencies were used so that the governing parties had a strong chance of still winning two. The election results created substantial change, as there was a larger than expected collapse in the vote, with Fianna Fáil winning a landslide victory, two out of three seats in many cases, relegating the National Coalition parties to fight for the last seat. Consequently, the term '''[[Tullymandering]]''' was used to describe the phenomenon of a failed attempt at gerrymandering.

===Latvia===

In 1989 and 1990 elections, some accused the [[Popular Front of Latvia]] (PFL) of gerrymandering in favor of ethnic Latvians. For example, in 1990 the nearly pure Latvian-ethnic [[Ventspils district]] (with about 0.6% of population) was awarded 3 constituencies out of 201 (1.5%), with 2 of PFL candidates running unopposed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saeima.lv/Informacija/velesanas/apgabali.html Constituencies in 1990 elections] — see Ugāles, Tārgales, Ziru constituencies, # 199—201&lt;/ref&gt;. In 1991, most native Russians were [[Non-citizens (Latvia)|denied citizenship]] and therefore had no voting rights. Naturalization of native Russians began in 1995. In 1993 the country returned to proportional representation.

===Northern Ireland===
In the 1920s and 1930s, the [[Ulster Unionist Party]] created electoral boundaries for the [[Londonderry County Borough Council]] to ensure election of a [[Unionists (Ireland)|Unionist]] council in a city where [[Irish nationalism|Nationalists]] had a marginal majority.&lt;ref name="whyte"&gt;[http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/issues/discrimination/whyte.htm CAIN: Issues - Discrimination: John Whyte, 'How much discrimination was there under the Unionist regime, 1921-1968?'&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Initially local parties drew the boundaries, but in the 1930s the [[Parliament of Northern Ireland|province-wide government]] redrew them to reinforce the gerrymander.&lt;ref name="whyte" /&gt; The [[Northern Ireland Civil Rights Association]] was formed in part in reaction to the injustice of the gerrymander.{{Fact|date=October 2008}}

[[Image:TheGerry-mander.jpg|thumb|250px|right|"The Gerry-mander" first appeared in this cartoon-map in the ''[[Boston Gazette]]'', 26 March 1812.]]

In 1929 the [[Parliament of Northern Ireland]] passed a bill shifting the Parliament's electoral system from the relatively proportional [[single transferable vote]] (STV) to the less proportional [[first past the post]] or [[block voting]] system. The only exception was for the election of four Stormont MPs to represent the [[Queen's University Belfast|Queen's University of Belfast]]. Many scholars believe that the boundaries were gerrymandered to underrepresent Nationalists.{{Who|date=October 2008}} Some geographers and historians, for instance Professor [[John H. Whyte]], disagree.&lt;ref name="whyte" /&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ark.ac.uk/elections/hnihoc.htm Northern Ireland House of Commons, 1921-1972&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; They have argued that the electoral boundaries for the [[Parliament of Northern Ireland]] were not gerrymandered to a greater level than that produced by any single-winner election system, and that the actual number of Nationalist MPs barely changed under the revised system. Most observers have acknowledged that the change to a single-winner system was a key factor, however, in stifling the growth of smaller political parties, such as the [[Northern Ireland Labour Party]] and Independent Unionists.

The United Kingdom suspended the Parliament of Northern Ireland and its government in 1972. It restored the single transferable vote (STV) for elections to the Northern Ireland Assembly in the following year, using the same definitions of constituencies as for the Westminster Parliament. Currently in Northern Ireland, all elections use the STV except those for positions in the [[Westminster Parliament]], which follow the pattern in the rest of the United Kingdom by using "first past the post."

===Singapore===
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Singapore]] --&gt;
In recent decades, critics have accused the ruling [[People's Action Party]] (PAP) of unfair electoral practices to maintain significant majorities in the [[Parliament of Singapore]]. Among the complaints are that the government uses gerrymandering.&lt;ref&gt;[[Yawning Bread]], "Electoral boundary changes: as opaque as ever", March 2006. http://www.yawningbread.org/arch_2006/yax-553.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Elections Department]] was established as part of the executive branch under the [[Prime Minister's Office|Prime Minister of Singapore]], rather than as an independent body. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pmo.gov.sg/AboutPMOffice/OurDepartments/ Prime Minister's Office], Our Departments &lt;/ref&gt; Critics have accused it of giving the ruling party the power to decide polling districts and polling sites through electoral engineering, based on poll results in previous election. &lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com.sg/books?id=ve4vY9ZosRMC&amp;pg=PA81&amp;lpg=PA81&amp;dq=Electoral+engineering+in+Singapore&amp;source=web&amp;ots=-k5mbicG3e&amp;sig=tQSkykbxlsBMdfgz5N8rE6kokrI&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=result Electoral Engineering: Voting Rules and Political Behavior], Pippa Norris&lt;/ref&gt;Opposition parties have alleged that the Elections Department decisions have given unfair advantage to the ruling party and have affected the outcome of some electoral battles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://yoursdp.org/index.php/truth-about/elections About Elections], Singapore Democratic Party&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wp.sg/wp/beliefs/manifesto.php Manifesto], The Workers' Party of Singapore&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics point out the dissolution of the Group Representation Constituencies (GRC) of [[Cheng San Group Representation Constituency|Cheng San GRC]] and [[Eunos Group Representation Constituency|Eunos GRC]]. Each was dissolved by the Elections Department with voters redistributed to other constituencies after opposition parties gained ground in elections. &lt;ref&gt;[http://forum.rp.sg/viewtopic.php?f=21&amp;t=863 Republic Polytechnic Forum]&lt;/ref&gt; Such action was controversial. Critics have speculated about the possibility of the Elections Department's dissolving next the [[Aljunied Group Representation Constituency|Aljunied GRC]] in the next General Elections, likely in 2010 or 2011. The opposition Workers' Party gained ground there in the General Elections in 2006, when it earned approximately 44% of the votes.

PAP strongholds, such as [[Tanjong Pagar Group Representation Constituency|Tanjong Pagar GRC]] and [[Ang Mo Kio Group Representation Constituency|Ang Mo Kio GRC]], where Minister Mentor Lee Kuan Yew and Prime Minister Lee Hsien Loong respectively contest, have seldom been contested by the opposition. When Ang Mo Kio GRC was last contested in 2006, the PAP has [[Singaporean general election, 2006#Electorate|won]] 66% of the votes.

===United States===
[[Image:TravisCountyDistricts.png|thumb|left|U.S. congressional districts covering [[Travis County, Texas]] (outlined in red) in 2002, left, and 2004, right. In 2003, the majority of Republicans in the Texas legislature [[2003 Texas redistricting|redistricted the state]], diluting the voting power of the heavily Democratic county by parceling its residents out to more Republican districts.]]

The United States has a long tradition of gerrymandering which precedes the 1789 election of the [[1st United States Congress|First U.S. Congress]]. In 1788, [[Patrick Henry]] and his [[Anti-Federalism|Anti-Federalist]] allies were in control of the [[Virginia]] [[Virginia House of Delegates|House of Delegates]]. They drew the boundaries of [[Virginia's 5th congressional district]] in an attempt to keep [[James Madison]] out of the [[U.S. House of Representatives]].&lt;ref&gt;Labunski, Richard. ''James Madison and the Struggle for the Bill of Rights''', New York: Oxford University Press, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, each state legislature has used gerrymandering to try to control the political makeup of its United State House delegation. Partisan legislators typically try to maximize the number of congressional delegation seats under the control of the legislature's majority party.

The practice of gerrymandering the borders of new states continued past the Civil War and into the late 19th century. Congress split territories in the [[Rocky Mountains]] area into separate, relatively low-population states rather than fewer, larger ones to help the [[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]] maintain control of the Presidency {{Fact|date=February 2007}}. By the rules for representation in the [[United States Electoral College|Electoral College]], each new state carried at least three electoral votes regardless of its population.&lt;ref&gt;Compare a map of the United States in 1860 [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/united_states/us_terr_1860.jpg] with a map from 1870 [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/united_states/us_terr_1870.jpg]. &lt;!-- These images need to be put in wikimedia commons, rather than external links--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

All redistricting in the United States has been contentious because it has been controlled by political parties vying for power. Under the [[U.S. constitution|constitution]], districts for members of the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] are to be redrawn every ten years following each [[census]]. In many states, state legislatures have redrawn boundaries for state legislative districts at the same time.

When faced with losing power, however, members of some legislatures simply refused to redistrict. Early struggles for power were between rural and urban interests, as well as between political parties. The state legislature of Alabama, for instance, refused to redistrict from 1901 to the 1960s, despite changing conditions in a state that was industrializing and where population was rapidly moving to cities. Rural interests became prevalent in state politics, hampering the state's progress for most of the 20th century. In 1960, approximately a quarter of the state's population controlled the state legislature. When the state legislature could not agree on boundaries, a federal court worked with a new non-partisan body to conclude defining new districts in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Michael McDonald, US Elections Project: Alabama Redistricting Summary [http://elections.gmu.edu/Redistricting/AL.htm George Mason University, Dept. of Public and International Affairs], accessed 6 Apr 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Intense political battles over contentious redistricting typically take place within state legislatures responsible for creating the electoral maps. Since passage of the Voting Rights Act of 1965, federal courts may be involved to ensure that historical patterns of discrimination are not perpetuated.

This process can create strange bedfellows interested in securing reelection; in some states, Republicans have cut deals with opposing black Democratic state legislators to create majority-black districts. By packing black Democratic voters into a single district, they can essentially ensure the election of a black Congressman or reelection of a black state legislator due to the packed concentration of Democratic voters — however, the surrounding districts are more safely Republican in areas like the South, where white conservatives have increasingly shifted from the Democratic to the Republican Party in national elections in the last four decades.

In Pennsylvania, the Republican-dominated state legislature used gerrymandering to eliminate Democratic representative [[Frank Mascara]]. Mascara was elected to Congress in 1994. In 2002 the Republican Party altered the boundaries of his original district so much that he was pitted against fellow Democratic candidate [[John Murtha]] in the election. The shape of Mascara’s newly drawn district formed a finger that stopped at his street, encompassing his house though not the spot where he parked his car. Murtha won the election in the newly formed district.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/features/2006/0611.morris.html | title= The Race to Gerrymander | author=Rachel Morris | publisher=[[The Washington Monthly]]|date=November 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

State legislatures have used gerrymandering along racial or ethnic lines both to decrease and increase minority representation in state governments and congressional delegations. In the state of Ohio, a conversation between Republican officials was recorded that demonstrated that redistricting was being done to aid their political candidates. Furthermore, the discussions assessed race of voters as a factor in redistricting, because African-Americans had backed Democratic candidates. Republicans removed approximately 13,000 African American voters from the district of Jim Raussen, a Republican candidate for the House of Representatives, in an attempt to tip the scales in what was once a competitive district for Democratic candidates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.wcpo.com/wcpo/localshows/iteam/cdd905.html | title= Republican Party Politics (Part II) | author=AP | publisher=[[WCPO]]|date=[[29 April]] [[2002]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

International election observers from the [[OSCE]] Office for Democratic Institutions and Human Rights, who were invited to observe and report on the [[United States presidential election, 2004|2004 national elections]], expressed criticism of the U.S. congressional redistricting process and made a recommendation that the procedures be reviewed to ensure genuine competitiveness of Congressional election contests.&lt;ref&gt;[http://osce.org/documents/odihr/2005/03/13658_en.pdf XI&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Voting Rights Act of 1965====
{{Unreferencedsection|date=July 2008}}
After Reconstruction and the granting of citizenship and suffrage to freedmen, state legislatures developed new constitutions with provisions to make voter registration and elections more complicated, such as [[poll taxes]], residency requirements, [[literacy tests]] and [[grandfather clause]]s. These were designed to, and effectively succeeded in [[disfranchisement after the Civil War|disfranchising]] most African Americans and many poor whites in southern states. In areas where African American and other minorities succeeded in registering, some states created districts that were gerrymandered to reduce the voting impact of minorities.

With the Civil Rights Movement and passage of the Voting Rights Act of 1965, additional federal enforcement and protections of suffrage for all citizens were enacted. Gerrymandering for the purpose of reducing the political influence of a racial or ethnic minority group was prohibited. Poll taxes for federal elections were prohibited by ratification of the [[Twenty-fourth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Twenty-fourth Amendment]] in 1964, and a later Supreme Court case struck down poll taxes as a prerequisite for any election. Gerrymandering for political gain has remained possible under the Constitution.

After the Voting Rights Act of 1965 was passed, some states created "majority-minority" districts. This practice, also called "affirmative gerrymandering", was supposed to redress historic discrimination and ensure that ethnic minorities would gain some seats in government. Since the 1990s, however, gerrymandering based solely on racial data has been ruled unconstitutional by the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] under the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]], first in ''[[Shaw v. Reno]]'' (1993) and subsequently in ''[[Miller v. Johnson]]'' (1995).

The constitutionality of using racial considerations to create districts remains difficult to assess, despite past injustices. In ''[[Hunt v. Cromartie]]'' (1999), the Supreme Court approved a racially focused gerrymandering of a congressional district on the grounds that the definition was not pure racial gerrymandering but instead partisan gerrymandering, which is constitutionally permissible. With the increasing racial polarization of parties in the South in the US as conservative whites move from the Democratic to the Republican Party, gerrymandering may become partisan and also achieve goals for ethnic representation.

In a few circumstances, the use of goal-driven district boundaries may be used for positive social goals (at least considered so from less partisan viewpoints). When the state legislature considered representation for [[Arizona]]'s Native American reservations, they thought each needed their own House member, because of historic conflicts between the [[Hopi]] and [[Navajo Nation|Navajo]] nations. Since the Hopi reservation is completely surrounded by the Navajo reservation, the legislature created an unusual district configuration which features a fine filament along a river course several hundred miles in length to attach two Navajo regions.

In another case (frequently cited as an outrageous example of gerrymandering), the California state legislature created a congressional district that extends over a narrow coastal strip for several hundred miles. It ensures that a common community of interest will be represented, rather than the coastal areas' being dominated by inland concerns. These are illustrative of factoring in communities of common interest in drawing district boundaries.

====Recent steps====
In a [[League of United Latin American Citizens v. Perry|decision]] on June 28, 2006, the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] upheld most of a Texas congressional map engineered in 2003 by former [[Party leaders of the United States House of Representatives|House Majority Leader]] [[Tom DeLay]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/POLITICS/06/28/scotus.texasredistrict/index.html | title= High court upholds most of Texas redistricting map | author=AP | publisher=[[CNN]]|date=[[28 June]] [[2006]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 7-2 decision allows state legislatures to redraw and gerrymander districts as often as they like (not just after the decennial census). Thus they may work to protect their political parties' standing and number of seats, so long as they do not harm racial and ethnic minority groups. A 5-4 majority declared one Congressional district unconstitutional in the case because of harm to an ethnic minority.

Rather than allowing more political influence, some states' citizens are considering shifting redistricting authority from politicians and giving it to non-partisan commissions. For instance, Washington state created the [[standing committee|standing]] [[Washington State Redistricting Commission]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.redistricting.wa.gov Washington State Redistricting Commission&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and Arizona the [[Arizona Independent Redistricting Commission]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.azredistricting.org Arizona Independent Redistricting Commission&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Rhode Island Reapportionment Commission]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.riredistricting.org Temporarily Disabled&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[New Jersey Redistricting Commission]] are ''[[ad hoc]]'' but developed the past two decennial reapportionments tied to new census data.

According to its [[municipal charter]], the city of [[San Diego]] uses a third party commission to define district boundaries.

==Justification== 
===United States===
{{Unreferencedsection|date=July 2008}}
====Inherent political right====
Many politicians{{Who|date=July 2008}} argue that because constituencies were to be made by politicians (such as the case in the United States and elsewhere), they have the right to manipulate it so that it gives them an advantage. The voters will still be represented, and an unpopular incumbent may still be unseated.

====Better representation of minority groups====
Gerrymandering can be used to create districts that better represent certain minorities. Such districts have been created to ensure representation for African American, Hispanic, and [[Asian American]] ethnic communities in the USA, particularly in [[California]], [[Texas]], and other states in the [[South]].{{Fact|date=July 2008}}

==See also==
*[[History of 19th century congressional redistricting in Ohio]]
*[[Representation (politics)]]
*[[Election fraud]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{wiktionarypar2|gerrymander|gerrymandering}}
*[http://www.aceproject.org/regions-en/americas/americas-case-studies/chile-constitutional-and-electoral-reform-1998/ Ending the Gerrymander in Chile: the constitutional reforms of 1988] — a case study from the [http://www.aceproject.org ACE Project]
*[http://www.aceproject.org/ace-en/topics/bd/bdy/bdy_my Alleged Gerrymandering in Malaysia: Over-representation of rural districts] — an article from the [http://www.aceproject.org ACE Project]
*[http://www.aceproject.org/ace-en/topics/bd/bdy/bdy_sg Alleged Gerrymandering in Singapore] — an article from the [http://www.aceproject.org ACE Project]
*[http://www.idea.int/publications/esd/index.cfm A handbook of electoral system Design] from [http://www.idea.int International IDEA]
*[http://www.fairvote.org/articles/bbcnews100804.htm Gerrymandering in the US]
*[http://www.aceproject.org/ace-en/topics/bd/bdy/bdy_us/ Reapportionment and Redistricting in the US] an article from the [http://www.aceproject.org ACE Project]
*[http://www.abc.net.au/elections/federal/2004/items/200408/s1172393.htm Anti-Gerrymandering policy in Australia]
*[http://www.westmiller.com/fairvote2k/in_gerry.htm A collection of bizarre and unconstitutional districts from recent history, dedicated to Governor Eldridge Gerry.] (Broken link)
*[http://www.worldpolicy.org/globalrights/democracy/2003-0529-CSM-gerrymandering.html Beyond gerrymandering and Texas posses: US electoral reform]
*[http://www.RangeVoting.org/GerryExamples.html Gerrymandering pages at the Center for Range Voting]
*[http://www.commoncensus.org The CommonCensus Map Project] — Draws internal US boundaries based on cultural affinities, not politics
*[http://www.motherjones.com/news/featurex/2006/09/gerrymander.html Egregious Cases] an article from Mother Jones Magazine
*[http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jteigen/gerry.html Gerryminder] — An online redistricting simulation.
*[http://dca.tufts.edu/features/aas A New Nation Votes: American Election Returns 1787-1825]
*[http://www.redistrictinggame.com/ The Redistricting Game — An online game designed to teach about Gerrymandering]

[[Category:Political corruption]]
[[Category:Voting systems]]
[[Category:American political terms]]
[[Category:Ethically disputed political practices]]

[[af:Afbakeningsknoeiery]]
[[ca:Gerrymandering]]
[[cy:Cyffindwyllo]]
[[da:Gerrymandering]]
[[de:Gerrymandering]]
[[es:Gerrymandering]]
[[eo:Gerrymander]]
[[fr:Découpage électoral]]
[[ko:게리맨더링]]
[[hr:Gerrymandering]]
[[is:Kjördæmahagræðing]]
[[it:Gerrymandering]]
[[he:הטיה בקביעת מחוזות בחירה]]
[[hu:Választókerület-manipuláció]]
[[nl:Kiesrechtgeografie]]
[[ja:ゲリマンダー]]
[[pl:Gerrymandering]]
[[pt:Gerrymandering]]
[[sr:Џеримандеринг]]
[[sv:Gerrymander]]
[[zh:傑利蠑螈]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>