<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041107175639|7289540" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12987" pageid="12987" ns="0" title="Gerrymandering"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-10T08:14:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Gerrymandering''' is a controversial form of [[redistricting]] in which [[electoral district]]/[[constituency]] boundaries are manipulated for electoral advantage, usually of [[incumbents]] or a specific [[political party]].  Gerrymandering may also be used to advantage a particular racial, linguistic, religious or class group.  The word '''gerrymander''' serves both as a verb meaning to perpetrate the abuse and as a noun describing the resulting electoral geography.

==Origins of the term==
[[Image:Gerrymander.jpeg|right|Gerrymander]]
The term is named for an early [[Massachusetts]] Governor, [[Elbridge Gerry]]. In [[1812]], the Massachusetts legislature redrew legislative district lines to favor the Jeffersonian Republican party candidates. Two reporters were looking at the new election map and one commented that one of the new districts looked just like a [[salamander]].  The other retorted that it looked like a Gerry-mander. The name stuck and is now used by [[political science|political scientists]] everywhere. (While Elbridge Gerry pronounced his name with a "hard G" as in "gate," the word "gerrymander" is usually pronounced with a "soft G" as in "gestate")

==Overview ==
Gerrymandering is most effective in [[voting system|electoral systems]] with districts that elect a single representative, which include [[first-past-the-post|First-past-the-post]] a.k.a. single member district/plurality electoral systems and majority run-off a.k.a. single member district/majority electoral systems.  Gerrymandering is possible, however, in any electoral system with multiple electoral districts. Among western democracies, only [[Israel]] and the [[Netherlands]] have electoral systems with only one (nationwide) electoral district.  

One form of gerrymandering occurs when the boundaries of a constituency are changed in order to eliminate some area with a high concentration of people who vote in a similar way (e.g for a certain political party).  Another form occurs when an area with a high concentration of similar voters is split among several districts, ensuring that the party has a small majority in several districts rather than a large majority in one. A converse method is to draw boundaries so that a group opposing those manipulating the boundaries are concentrated in as few areas as possible, so as to minimise their representation and influence. Often, such gerrymandering is held to redress a long-overlooked imbalance, as when creating a black majority district.

Many [[Electoral Reform]] packages advocate fixed or neutrally defined district borders to eliminate this manipulation. One such scheme of neutrally defined district borders is [[bioregional democracy]] which follows the borders of [[terrestrial ecoregions]] as defined by [[ecology]]. Presumably, scientific criteria would be immune to politically motivated manipulation, although of course this is debatable as scientists are people with political interests too.

The problem with geographically static districting systems (which is not what most Reform packages suggest) is that they do not take in to account changes in population, meaning that individual electors can grow to have vastly different degrees of influence on the legislative process.  This is particularly a problem during times of large population movements, and was especially prominent in the [[United Kingdom]] during the [[industrial revolution]].  (See: [[Reform Act]] and [[rotten borough]])

For this reason, scientists have proposed [[algorithm]]ic ways of dividing constituencies. Desirable criteria for the outcomes are:
* the system should be simple enough to be understood by most of the general population;
* the constituencies must be connected (i.e. each in a single piece);
* the constituencies should not be too elongated;
* the constituencies should have the same population or at least almost the same.

Gerrymandering is also possible in multi-member electoral systems, but generally the drawing of boundaries are only effective at determining which party wins the last seat in a close contest.

==The Dame Shirley Porter case==
Yet another method is to attempt to move the population within the existing boundaries. This occurred in [[Westminster]], in the United Kingdom. The local government was controlled by the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative party]], and the leader of the council, [[Dame Shirley Porter]], conspired with others to implement the policy of [[council house]] sales in such a way as to shore up the Conservative vote in marginal wards by selling the houses there to people thought likely to vote Conservative.  An inquiry by the district auditor found that these actions had resulted in financial loss to tax payers and Porter and three others were surcharged to cover the loss. Porter was accused of "disgraceful and improper gerrymandering" by district auditor [[John Magill]]. Those surcharged resisted this ruling with a legal challenge, but, in December [[2001]], the appeal court upheld the district auditor's ruling. Despite further lengthy legal argument Porter eventually accepted a deal to end the long-running saga, and paid £12 million (out of an original claimed £27 million plus costs and interest) to [[Westminster]] Council in July, [[2004]].

==Gerrymandering in Northern Ireland==
A particularly famous case occurred in [[Northern Ireland]], where the [[Ulster Unionist Party]] government created electoral boundaries for local councils which, coupled with restrictions on voting rights based on economic status, ensured the election of unionist candidates in electoral areas where nationalists were in the overwhelming majority. This policy, coupled with a policy that gave council houses to unionists at the expense of nationalists (in one famous case, giving a council house to an unmarried protestant woman rather than a large catholic family), to ensure unionist control of electoral wards, produced the ''Civil Rights Movement.'' The battle for civil rights in local government, and an end to gerrymandered discrimination, led to [[The Troubles]].

Apologists dismiss the gerrymandering of the [[Northern Ireland Assembly]] to be popular myth, saying that the electoral boundaries for the [[Parliament of Northern Ireland]] were not gerrymandered to any great extent, and the electoral system originally used for this body [[Single Transferable Vote]] (STV) made it difficult to gerrymander successfully.  However, this system of [[proportional representation]] was abolished in the late [[1920s]] in favour of  first-past-the-post. The Parliament of Northern Ireland was abolished in [[1973]], and STV was restored for elections to the Northern Ireland Assembly.  (See '''Tullymandering''' below.)

==Gerrymandering in the United States==
In the [[United States]], gerrymandering has been used to cut minority populations in half to keep all minorities in the minority, in as many districts as possible.  This led to a major civil rights conflict; Gerrymandering for the purpose of reducing the political influence of a racial or ethnic minority group is illegal in the United States under the [[Voting Rights Act of 1965]], but [[redistricting]] for political gain is constitutional.

The carving of [[territory|territories]] into [[US states]] was also subject to gerrymandering, where before the [[American Civil War]] states were admitted on a formula of "one free state for each slave state". This caused [[Maine]] to be split from [[Massachussetts]], and decided that [[Texas]] and [[California]] would both enter as single, large, states. During the late [[19th century]] the territories of the [[Rocky Mountains]] were split up into relatively small states to help the [[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]] maintain control of the [[White House]] -- each new state brought in 3 [[U.S. Electoral College|electoral votes]]. While the slave state/free state distinction is now a matter of history, the carving up of the Rocky Mountains continues to affect [[U.S._presidential_election|presidential election]]s until today, still giving Republicans an advantage in case of a close vote; this made the Presidency of [[George W. Bush]] possible in [[2000]].

As for state-internal gerrymandering, there have been attempts to create 'majority minority' districts, so called "affirmative gerrymandering" or "racial gerrymandering", to ensure higher ethnic minority representation in government. However, gerrymandering on the basis of race only has been ruled unconstitutional by the [[Supreme Court of the United States|US Supreme Court]], under the [[Fourteenth Amendment|Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] first by [[Shaw v. Reno]] ([[1993]]) and by subsequent cases, including [[Miller v. Johnson]] ([[1995]]) and [[Hunt v. Cromartie]] (1999).

The possibility of gerrymandering makes the process of redistricting extremely politically contentious within the United States.  Under U.S. law, districts for members of the House of Representatives are redrawn every ten years following each [[census]] and it is common practice for state legislative boundaries to be redrawn at the same time.  Battles over contentious redistricting take place within state legislatures, which are responsible for creating the electoral maps in most states, as well as federal courts.  Sometimes this process creates strange bedfellows; in some states, Republicans have cut deals with African American Democratic state legislators to create majority black districts.  These districts essentially ensure the election of an African American Congressman, but due to voting patterns, end up concentrating the Democratic vote in such a way that surrounding districts are more likely to vote Republican.

The introduction of computers has made redistricting a more precise science, but the incentives for certain groups to create maps that increase their delegation in Congress remain. Many political analysts have argued that the [[United States House of Representatives]] has been gerrymandered to the point that there are now very few contested seats, and have also argued that this has a number of detrimental effects, among which is that the lack of contested seats makes it unnecessary for candidates to attract middle voters and compromise.

==Tullymandering==
In the [[Republic of Ireland]] in the mid 1970s, the Minister for Local Government, [[James Tully]], attempted to arrange constituencies to ensure that the governing [[National Coalition]] would win a parliamentary majority. This he did by ensuring as many as possible three-seat constituencies where the governing parties were strong, in the expectation that the governing parties would each win a seat in many constituencies, relegating the opposition [[Fianna Fáil]] party to one out of three. In areas where the governing parties were weak four-seat constituencies were used so that the governing parties had a strong chance of winning two still. In fact the process backfired spectacularly due to a larger than expected collapse in the vote, with Fianna Fáil winning two out of three in many cases, relegating the National Coalition parties to fight for the last seat. His attempted gerrymander came to be called a '''Tullymander'''.

==See also==
*[[List of democracy and elections-related topics]]
*[[redistricting]]
*[[stage migration]]

== External Links ==
*[http://www.fairvote.org/articles/bbcnews100804.htm Gerrymandering in the US]
*[http://www.abc.net.au/elections/federal/2004/items/200408/s1172393.htm Anti-Gerrymandering policy in Australia]

[[Category:Political terms]]
[[Category:Portmanteaus]]

[[de:Gerrymandering]]
[[eo:Gerrymander]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>