<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020910194353|410934" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12987" pageid="12987" ns="0" title="Gerrymandering"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-11-07T23:29:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[eo:Gerrymander]][[de:Gerrymandering]]

'''Gerrymandering''' is the deliberate manipulation of [[political borders]] 
(in the US, specifically, "electoral district boundaries") for short-term electoral advantage, usually of incumbents.  

The term is named for an early Massachusetts Governor, [[Elbridge Gerry]].  Two reporters were looking at the new election map and one commented that one of the new districts looked just like a salamander.  The other retorted that it looked like a Gerrymander.  The name stuck and is now used by [[political science|political scientists]] everywhere.

It is an issue most often associated with single member [[first past the post|first-past-the-post]] electoral systems in which the district boundaries can have a crucial impact on the number of persons elected by a party to a legislature.  

One form of gerrymandering occurs when the boundaries of a constituency are changed in order to eliminate some area with a high concentration of people who vote for a certain political party.  Another form occurs when an area with a high concentration of voters for a certain party is split among several districts, insuring that the party has a small majority in several districts rather than a large majority in one. Often, such gerrymandering is held to redress a long-overlooked imbalance, as when creating a black majority district.

Yet another method is to attempt to move the population within the existing boundaries. This occurred in [[Westminster]], in the [[United Kingdom]]. The local government was controlled by the [[UK Conservative party|Conservative party]], and the leader of the council, with others conspired to only offer state funded housing to people who were thought to vote Conservative. The council leader was [[Dame Shirley Porter]], who lost in court, and was forced to pay millions of pounds in punitive damages. Recently (December 2001), an appeal court has ordered that she will remain liable for the full amount of the damages.

It was decisive in the elimination of [[multi-member districts]] in the United States electoral system as candidates realized they could gain "safe" seats by controlling the boundaries to include supporters and exclude opponents.  Simultaneously, minorities, especially [[African-Americans]], realized that their strong constituency in cities was being politically diluted for lack of "safe" seats of their own in one inner city district. 

Others realized that gerrymandering was cutting minority populations in half to keep all minorities in the minority, in as many districts as possible.  This led to a major civil rights conflict; Gerrymandering for the purpose of reducing the political influence of a minority group is illegal in the United States under the [[Voting Rights Act of 1965]], however the [[United States Supreme Court]] has ruled that gerrymandering for the purpose of increasing or reducing the influence of political party is not illegal.

The possibility of gerrymandering makes the process of redistricting extremely politically contentious within the United States.  Under U.S. law, districts for members of the House of Representatives are redrawn every ten years following each [[census]] and it is common practice for state legislative boundaries to be redrawn at the same time.  What usually results is a contentious fight between the political parties to insure that the
districts most advantageous to them are adopted.  

Many [[Electoral Reform]] packages advocate fixed or neutrally defined district borders to eliminate this manipulation. One such scheme of neutrally defined district borders is [[bioregional democracy]] which follows the borders of [[terrestrial ecoregions]] as defined by [[ecology]], in the hope that such scientific criteria would be immune to politically motivated manipulation.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>