<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061109010746|86615801" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="355849" pageid="355849" ns="0" title="Equal opportunity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T00:11:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Equal opportunity''' is a descriptive term for an approach intended to give equal access to a certain [[social environment]], or to ensure people are not specifically excluded from participating in activities such as [[education]], [[employment]], or [[health care]] on the basis of [[immutable]] traits. This is inherent in the term [[EOE/M/F/D/V]], which means [[Equal Opportunity Employer]] / [[Male]] / [[Female]] / [[Disabled]] / [[Veteran]]. Equal opportunity practices include measures taken by organizations to ensure fairness in the employment process.

Equal opportunity practices that are [[race-blind]] or [[gender-blind]] may be distinguished from practices that involve or require [[affirmative action]] or [[reverse discrimination]] (referred to as 'positive discrimination' in the UK). The [[United States federal government]] and various state and [[local government]]s require affirmative action in terms of governmental hiring and contracting; many other countries make such action illegal. Executive 11246 requires any group or company doing business with or receiving money from the government to have an equal opportunity for all workers, including an affirmative action plan. This has been debated because many feel affirmative action actually causes an inequal opportunity.

The method of providing equal opportunity is often a subject of controversy, as is the means by which to measure the success or failure of equal opportunity policies. ''Opportunity'' itself is often difficult - if not impossible - to accurately measure. Thus, in practice, equal opportunity is said to exist when people with similar abilities reach similar results ([[equality of outcome]]) after doing a similar amount of work. Indeed, equal opportunity and equality of outcome are often seen as complementary. For example, as long as inequalities can be passed from one [[generation]] to another through gifts and wealth [[inheritance]], it is unclear that equality of opportunity for children can be achieved without greater equality of outcome for parents.

Societies must choose whether their conception of equality is to be based on immutable traits (eg. gender, race) or extended to include mutable traits (eg. hair style, education, language, wealth).  It is claimed that equal opportunity does not diminish the ability of individuals to reap the rewards of their merit in a [[meritocracy]].  Equality pursued through programs such as [[affirmative action]] ([[positive discrimination]]) and [[income redistribution]] are the pursuit of [[equality|equal outcomes]] or "[[social justice]]".

A basic premise for achievement of equal opportunity is equal right to:
* participation in selection of government
* freedom of expression (speech) and
* access to knowledge and information.

==Criticism of the Equal Opportunity Approach==
The concept of equal opportunity is often criticized by [[libertarians]] and [[free market]] advocates as fundamentally flawed and logically incompatible with the [[liberal]] concept of
[[equal rights]]. It is easy to provide a logical proof that as long as people differ in their innate abilities and motivation, any attempt to equalize economic outcomes will inevitably result in systemic [[legal]] discrimination against those who are born with traits conductive to their professional success. 

This tension between [[social equality]] and [[equal rights]] was generally understood and accepted by early 20-th century [[socialists]] and [[communists]], resulting in the explicit policies of [[socialist]] governments designed to instill literal equality in people by means of both forced over-education and over-training of laggards, and officially unacknowledged but rampant suppression and slowing down of achievers with dull and repetitive tasks. These efforts were covered by the offical communist [[propaganda]] as "development of harmonically endowed personae".  The intended ideologic consequence of such homogenization of population was cessation of [[division of labor]] and consequently, abolition of [[trade]] and [[money]]. It is undeniable that the results of these large-scale experiments in promotion of [[social equality]] by means of [[statist]] policies were disastrous, leading to massive suffering of millions of people and collapse of socialist states.

The second criticism of the concept of equal opportunity is based on the fact that any legalistic attempt to end [[discrimination]] amounts to application of [[violence]] to the people unwilling to part with their putative prejudices.  To anyone who is consistent in the belief that no violence is morally acceptable, or that only defensive violence can be morally justified, this makes the equal opportunity laws morally reprehensible and unethical.  The only defense against the claim to the moral inadmissibility of the enforced equalization is stated as the belief that violence by the [[collectives]] (such as [[states]]) under some condition is not really a violence.  However, such argument can be equally applied to justification of even the worst excesses of [[fascist]] and [[communist]] regimes.

The victims of collectivist violence (even in its milder forms) resulting from the enforcement of the equal opportunity policies become justifiably aggravated, resulting in increase of social tensions (especially [[racial]] tension) and hatreds. At the same time, fear of persecution for the "discrimination" moves those vulnerable to such persecution (i.e. employers) to reduce the risks by discouraging members of protected classes from getting employed in the first place, resulting in real (as opposed to potential) discrimination even against those members of protected classes who did not intend to enlist state enforcers to the improvement of their social and economic position.

Finally, the equal opportunity is often criticized on [[utilitarian]] grounds because the burden of equal opportunity regulations results in decreased productivity of the businesses, thus reducing well-being of all classes (including, in the longer term, members of the protected classes). In academia, the equal opportunity enforcement resulted in declining quality of education and research, which led to the abolition or drastic curtailing of the [[affirmative action]] by leading universities.

==See also==
* [[Asset-based egalitarianism]]
* [[Equal Opportunity Employment]]
* [[Universal access]]
* [[Centre for Equal Opportunities and Opposition to Racism]] (Belgium)
* [[Commission for Racial Equality|Commission for Racial Equality (UK)]]
* [[Disability Rights Commission|Disability Rights Commission (UK)]]
* [[Egovernment]]
* [[Egrants.mobi]]
* [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission|Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (US)]]
* [[Equal Opportunities Commission|Equal Opportunities Commission (UK)]] - gender equality
* [[Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission|Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (Australia)]]
* [[Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity|Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity (US)]]
* [[New Brunswick Equal Opportunity program]]
* [[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]]

==External links==
*United Kingdom
**World Bank [http://www.doingbusiness.org Doing Business project]
**[http://www.womenandequalityunit.gov.uk/ UK Governmen Women &amp; Equality Unit]
**[http://www.scoutbase.org.uk/library/hqdocs/eqopps/index.htm The Scout Association of the UK]
*United States
**[http://www.eeoc.gov/ U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) (US)] - the branch of the U.S. government that enforces equal opportunity laws in workplaces.
**[http://www.nafeo.org/ NAFEO - National Association For Equal Opportunity In Higher Education (US)]
**[http://www.doi.gov/diversity/ Department of the Interior Office for Equal Opportunity (US)]
**[http://www.ceousa.org/ Center for Equal Opportunity (US)] - an advocacy group against affirmative action 
*[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/equal-opportunity/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy entry on Equality of Opportunity]
**[http://www.emeraldinsight.com/info/journals/eoi/eoi.jsp Equal Opportunities International (established in 1982, a journal by Emerald Press)]

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Social justice]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]
[[Category:Anti-racism]]

[[de:Chancengleichheit]]
[[nl:Gelijkwaardige behandeling]]
[[fi:Mahdollisuuksien tasa-arvo]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>