<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191121180337|927314049" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="313075" pageid="313075" ns="0" title="Identity politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-21T18:29:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2018}}

'''Identity politics''' is a political approach and analysis based on people prioritizing the concerns most relevant to their particular racial, religious, ethnic, sexual, social, cultural or other ''[[identity (social science)|identity]]'', and forming exclusive political alliances with others of this group, instead of engaging in more traditional, broad-based [[party politics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Identity politics|url=https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/identity_politics|publisher=Oxford Living Dictionaries|access-date=18 February 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190217203946/https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/identity_politics|archive-date=17 February 2019|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those who prioritize their particular type of identity politics may promote their group's interests without regard for the interests of larger, more diverse political groups that are based in shared theory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Identity politics|url=https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/identity%20politics|publisher=Merriam-Webster|access-date=18 February 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190219072904/https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/identity%20politics|archive-date=19 February 2019|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In academic usage, the term ''identity politics'' has been used to refer to a wide range of political activities and theoretical analysis rooted in experiences of injustice shared by different social groups. In this usage, identity politics typically aims to reclaim greater self-determination and political freedom for marginalized groups through understanding each interest group's distinctive nature and challenging externally imposed characterizations, instead of organizing solely around belief systems or party affiliations.&lt;ref name=Stanford/&gt; ''Identity'' is used "as a tool to frame political claims, promote political ideologies, or stimulate and orient social and political action, usually in a larger context of inequality or injustice and with the aim of asserting group distinctiveness and belonging and gaining power and recognition."&lt;ref name=OB&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|encyclopedia=Oxford Bibliographies|author=Vasiliki Neofotistos|title=Identity Politics|url=http://www.oxfordbibliographies.com/view/document/obo-9780199766567/obo-9780199766567-0106.xml|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2013|date=|access-date=18 February 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181027214156/http://www.oxfordbibliographies.com/view/document/obo-9780199766567/obo-9780199766567-0106.xml|archive-date=27 October 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ''identity politics'' has been in use in various forms since the 1960s or 1970s, but has been applied with, at times, radically different meanings by different populations.&lt;ref name="Wiarda-2016" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/|title=Identity Politics|first=Cressida|last=Heyes|journal=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|publisher=Metaphysics Research Lab, [[Center for the Study of Language and Information|CSLI]], [[Stanford University]]|access-date=2012-11-11|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060830015202/http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/|archive-date=30 August 2006|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has gained currency with the emergence of social movements such as the [[feminist movement]], the [[civil rights movement]] in the U.S., the [[LGBTQ]] movement, as well as [[nationalist]] and postcolonial movements.&lt;ref name=OB/&gt;

Examples include identity politics based on age, religion, social class, profession, culture, language, disability, education, race or ethnicity, language, sex, [[gender identity]], occupation, [[sexual orientation]], urban or rural habitation, and veteran status.

== History ==
The term ''identity politics'' has been used in political discourse since at least the 1970s.&lt;ref name="Wiarda-2016"&gt;{{cite book |last=Wiarda |first=Howard J. |title=Political Culture, Political Science, and Identity Politics: An Uneasy Alliance |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1hHtCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA150 |date=8 April 2016 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |location=[[Abingdon-on-Thames|Abingdon]] |isbn=978-1-317-07885-2 |oclc=982044314 |orig-year=1st pub. [[Ashgate]]:2014 |access-date=21 February 2018 |quote=There are disputes regarding the origins of the term 'identity politics' .... Almost all authors, even while disagreeing over who was the first to use the term, agree that its original usage goes back to the 1970s and even the 1960s. |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170819161909/https://books.google.com/books?id=1hHtCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA150 |archive-date=19 August 2017 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; One aim of identity politics has been for those feeling oppressed by and actively suffering under systemic social inequities to articulate their suffering and felt oppression in terms of their own experience by processes of [[consciousness-raising]] and collective action. One of the older written examples of it can be found in the April 1977 statement of the [[black feminist]] group, [[Combahee River Collective]], which was reprinted in a number of anthologies,&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g., ''Capitalist Patriarchy and the Case for Socialist Feminism'', ed. Zillah R. Eisenstein (New York: Monthly Review Press, 1978)&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Barbara Smith]] and the Combahee River Collective have been credited with coining the term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Collier-Thomas|first1=edited by Bettye|last2=Franklin|first2=V.P.|title=Sisters in the struggle African American women in the civil rights-black power movement|date=2001|publisher=New York University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-8147-1603-8|page=39|edition=[Online-Ausg.].|url=https://books.google.com.au/books?id=iR6NVzFEntgC&amp;pg=PA194|access-date=11 October 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180617165603/https://books.google.com.au/books?id=iR6NVzFEntgC&amp;pg=PA194|archive-date=17 June 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harris, Duchess. ''From the Kennedy Commission to the Combahee Collective: Black Feminist Organizing, 1960–1980'', in ''Sisters in the Struggle: African American Women in the Civil Rights-Black Power Movement'', eds: Bettye Collier-Thomas, V. P. Franklin, [[NYU Press]], 2001, {{ISBN|0-8147-1603-2}}, p. 300&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in their terminal  statement, they  said:&lt;ref name=Stanford/&gt;

{{Quote
| quote     = [A]s children we realized that we were different from boys and that we were treated different—for example, when we were told in the same breath to be quiet both for the sake of being 'ladylike' and to make us less objectionable in the eyes of white people. In the process of consciousness-raising, actually life-sharing, we began to recognize the commonality of our experiences and, from the sharing and growing consciousness, to build a politics that will change our lives and inevitably end our oppression....We realize that the only people who care enough about us to work consistently for our liberation are us. Our politics evolve from a healthy love for ourselves, our sisters and our community which allows us to continue our struggle and work. This focusing upon our own oppression is embodied in the concept of identity politics. We believe that the most profound and potentially most radical politics come directly out of our own identity, as opposed to working to end somebody else's oppression.
| author    = [[Socialist feminism#Zillah R. Eisenstein|Zillah R. Eisenstein]] (1978)
| title     = "The Combahee River Collective Statement"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://circuitous.org/scraps/combahee.html|title=The Combahee River Collective Statement|publisher=|access-date=4 April 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170224021117/http://circuitous.org/scraps/combahee.html|archive-date=24 February 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

Identity politics, as a mode of categorizing, are closely connected to the ascription that some social groups are oppressed (such as women, [[ethnic minorities]], and [[sexual minorities]]); that is, the claim that individuals belonging to those groups are, by virtue of their identity, more vulnerable to forms of oppression such as [[cultural imperialism]], [[violence]], [[exploitation of labour]], [[marginalization]], or powerlessness.&lt;ref name=Stanford&gt;{{cite web|last1=Heyes|first1=Cressida|title=Identity Politics|url=https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/|website=The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|publisher=Metaphysics Research Lab, Stanford University|access-date=3 May 2017|date=1 January 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170327180804/https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/|archive-date=27 March 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, these lines of social difference can be seen as ways to gain empowerment or avenues through which to work towards a more equal society.&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt;

Some groups have combined identity politics with [[Marxist]] [[social class]] analysis and [[class consciousness]]—the most notable example being the [[Black Panther Party]]—but this is not necessarily characteristic of the form. Another example is the group [[MOVE]], which mixed [[black nationalism]] with [[anarcho-primitivism]] (a radical form of [[green politics]] based on the idea that civilization is an instrument of oppression, advocating the return to a [[hunter gatherer]] society).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=by Committee|title=Philadelphia Special Investigation Commission (MOVE) Records {{!}} Temple University Libraries|url=https://library.temple.edu/scrc/philadelphia-special-1|website=library.temple.edu|access-date=3 May 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170501205105/https://library.temple.edu/scrc/philadelphia-special-1|archive-date=1 May 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=no attrib.|title=On a Move – Website of the MOVE Organization|url=http://onamove.com/|website=onamove.com|access-date=3 May 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170429085111/http://onamove.com/|archive-date=29 April 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Identity politics can be left-wing or right-wing, with examples of the latter being [[Ulster Loyalism]], [[Islamism]] and [[Christian Identity]] movements.

During the 1980s, the politics of identity became very prominent and it was linked to a new wave of social movement activism.&lt;ref name='Calhoun'&gt;{{cite book |last1=Calhoun |first1=Craig |authorlink1=Craig Calhoun |title=Social Theory and the Politics of Identity|editor=Craig Calhoun|publisher=Blackwell |year=1994 |isbn=978-1-55786-473-4}}{{page needed|date=September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The mid-2010s have seen a marked rise of identity politics, including [[White nationalism|white identity politics in the United States]].  This phenomenon is attributed to increased demographic diversity and the prospect of whites becoming a minority in America.  Such shifts have driven many to affiliate with conservative causes including those not related to diversity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Bartels |first=Larry |date=16 April 2014 |title=Can the Republican Party thrive on white identity? |url= |newspaper=The Washington Post |location= |access-date= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

This includes the presidential election of [[Donald Trump]], who was supported by prominent white supremacists such as [[David Duke]] and [[Richard B. Spencer]] (both of whom Trump disavowed).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.cnn.com/2016/03/03/politics/donald-trump-disavows-david-duke-kkk/index.html|title=Trump denounces David Duke, KKK|access-date=22 August 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180821031058/https://www.cnn.com/2016/03/03/politics/donald-trump-disavows-david-duke-kkk/index.html|archive-date=21 August 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://thehill.com/blogs/blog-briefing-room/news/346326-david-duke-charlottesville-protests-about-fulfilling-promises|title=David Duke: Charlottesville protests about ‘fulfilling promises of Donald Trump’|date=12 August 2017|work=The Hill|access-date=2017-12-02|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170813071135/http://thehill.com/blogs/blog-briefing-room/news/346326-david-duke-charlottesville-protests-about-fulfilling-promises|archive-date=13 August 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2017/aug/23/richard-spencer-alt-right-figure-trump-has-never-d/|title=Richard Spencer, alt-right figure: ‘Trump has never denounced the Alt-Right. Nor will he’|date=23 August 2017|work=The Washington Times|access-date=2017-02-12|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171203153905/https://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2017/aug/23/richard-spencer-alt-right-figure-trump-has-never-d/|archive-date=3 December 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.weeklystandard.com/the-primal-scream-of-identity-politics/article/2010234|title=The Primal Scream of Identity Politics|date=27 October 2017|work=Weekly Standard|access-date=2017-11-30|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171030103530/http://www.weeklystandard.com/the-primal-scream-of-identity-politics/article/2010234|archive-date=30 October 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Debates and criticism==
===Nature of the movement===
The term ''identity politics'' has been applied and misapplied retroactively to varying movements that long predate its coinage. Historian [[Arthur Schlesinger Jr.]] discussed identity politics extensively in his 1991 book ''[[The Disuniting of America]]''.  Schlesinger, a strong supporter of liberal conceptions of [[civil rights]], argues that a [[liberal democracy]] requires a common basis for [[culture]] and [[society]] to function. Rather than seeing civil society as already fractured along lines of power and powerlessness (according to race, ethnicity, sexuality, etc), Schlesinger suggests that basing politics on group marginalization is itself what fractures the civil polity, and that identity politics therefore works against creating real opportunities for ending marginalization. Schlesinger believes that:
{{quote|movements for civil rights should aim toward full acceptance and integration of marginalized groups into the mainstream culture, rather than … perpetuating that marginalization through affirmations of difference.&lt;ref&gt;M.A. Chaudhary &amp; Gautam Chaudhary, Global Encyclopaedia of Political Geography, New Delhi, 2009, {{ISBN|978-81-8220-233-7}}, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Similarly [[Brendan O'Neill (journalist)|Brendan O'Neill]] has suggested that identity politics causes (rather than simply recognizing and acting on) political schisms along lines of social identity. Thus, he contrasts the politics of [[gay liberation]] and identity politics by saying:
{{quote|[[Peter Tatchell|[Peter] Tatchell]] also had, back in the day, … a commitment to the politics of liberation, which encouraged gays to come out and live and engage. Now, we have the politics of identity, which invites people to stay in, to look inward, to obsess over the body and the self, to surround themselves with a moral forcefield to protect their worldview—which has nothing to do with the world—from any questioning."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Brendan|first1=O'Neill|title=Identity politics has created an army of vicious, narcissistic cowards|url=http://blogs.spectator.co.uk/coffeehouse/2015/02/identity-politics-has-created-an-army-of-vicious-narcissists/|work=The Spectator|access-date=28 June 2015|date=19 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150630173221/http://blogs.spectator.co.uk/coffeehouse/2015/02/identity-politics-has-created-an-army-of-vicious-narcissists/|archive-date=30 June 2015|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
In these and other ways, a political perspective oriented to one's own well being can be recast as causing the divisions that it insists upon making visible.

In this same vein, author [[Owen Jones (writer)|Owen Jones]] argues that identity politics often marginalize the [[working class]], saying that: {{quote|In the 1950s and 1960s, left-wing intellectuals who were both inspired and informed by a powerful labour movement wrote hundreds of books and articles on working-class issues. Such work would help shape the views of politicians at the very top of the Labour Party. Today, progressive intellectuals are far more interested in issues of identity. ... Of course, the struggles for the emancipation of women, gays, and ethnic minorities are exceptionally important causes. New Labour has co-opted them, passing genuinely progressive legislation on gay equality and women's rights, for example. But it is an agenda that has happily co-existed with the sidelining of the working class in politics, allowing New Labour to protect its radical flank while pressing ahead with Thatcherite policies.|Owen Jones|''[[Chavs: The Demonization of the Working Class]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jones|first1=Owen|title=Chavs: The Demonization of the Working Class|date=2012|publisher=Verso|location=London|isbn=978-1-84467-864-8|page=255|edition=updated}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===LGBT issues===
{{See also|LGBT social movements|Queer nationalism|Political lesbianism|Bisexual politics}}
The [[gay liberation]] movement of the late 1960s through the mid-1980s urged [[lesbian]]s and [[gay men]] to engage in radical [[direct action]], and to counter societal shame with [[gay pride]].&lt;ref name=HoffmanIntro&gt;{{cite book|last=Hoffman|first= Amy |title=An Army of Ex-Lovers: My life at the Gay Community News |year=2007 |publisher=University of Massachusetts Press |isbn=978-1558496217 |pages=xi–xiii}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[feminism|feminist]] spirit of the personal being political, the most basic form of activism was an emphasis on [[coming out]] to family, friends and colleagues, and living life as an openly lesbian or [[gay]] person.&lt;ref name=HoffmanIntro/&gt; While the 1970s were the peak of "gay liberation" in New York City and other urban areas in the United States, "gay liberation" was the term still used instead of "gay pride" in more oppressive areas into the mid-1980s, with some organizations opting for the more inclusive, "lesbian and gay liberation".&lt;ref name=HoffmanIntro/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hoffman2007&gt;{{cite book|last=Hoffman|first= Amy |title=An Army of Ex-Lovers: My life at the Gay Community News |year=2007 |publisher=University of Massachusetts Press |isbn=978-1558496217 }}&lt;/ref&gt; While women and [[transgender]] activists had lobbied for more inclusive names from the beginning of the movement, the [[initialism]] [[LGBT]], or "[[Queer]]" as a counterculture shorthand for [[LGBT]], did not gain much acceptance as an umbrella term until much later in the 1980s, and in some areas not until the '90s or even '00s.&lt;ref name=HoffmanIntro/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hoffman2007/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hollibaugh&gt;{{cite web|author1=phoenix|title=Gay Rights Are Not Queer Liberation|url=http://www.autostraddle.com/gay-rights-are-not-queer-liberation-the-nation-interviews-amber-hollibaugh-140431/|website=autostraddle.com|access-date=1 March 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402122449/http://www.autostraddle.com/gay-rights-are-not-queer-liberation-the-nation-interviews-amber-hollibaugh-140431/|archive-date=2 April 2015|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this period in the United States, identity politics were largely seen in these communities in the definitions espoused by writers such as self-identified, "black, dyke, feminist, poet, mother" [[Audre Lorde]]'s [[Audre Lorde#Personal identity|view]], that [[lived experience]] matters, defines us, and is the only thing that grants authority to speak; that, "If I didn't define myself for myself, I would be crunched into other people's fantasies for me and eaten alive."&lt;ref name=Zami&gt;{{Cite book|title=Zami: A New Spelling of My Name|last=Lorde|first=Audre|publisher=Crossing Press|year=1982|isbn=978-0-89594-123-7|location=New York|pages=|title-link=Zami: A New Spelling of My Name}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kemp&gt;Kemp, Yakini B. (2004). "Writing Power: Identity Complexities and the Exotic Erotic in Audre Lorde's writing". ''Studies in the Literary Imagination''. '''37''': 22–36.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Leonard&gt;Leonard, Keith D. (28 September 2012). [https://muse.jhu.edu/article/486572 ""Which Me Will Survive": Rethinking Identity, Reclaiming Audre Lorde"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220052903/https://muse.jhu.edu/article/486572 |date=20 December 2016 }}. ''Callaloo''. '''35''' (3): 758–77. {{doi|10.1353/cal.2012.0100}}. {{ISSN|1080-6512}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 2000s, in some areas of [[postmodernism|postmodern]] [[queer studies]], notably those around [[gender]], the idea of "identity politics" began to shift away from that of naming and claiming lived experience, and authority arising from lived experience, to one emphasizing choice and performance.&lt;ref name=4-encylopedia&gt;{{cite web|title=Queer Theory and the Social Construction of Sexuality|work=Homosexuality|publisher=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|access-date=15 November 2011|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/homosexuality/#QueTheSocConSex|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111209062102/http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/homosexuality/#QueTheSocConSex|archive-date=9 December 2011|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some who draw on the work of authors like [[Judith Butler]], stress the importance of not assuming an already existing identity, but of remaking and unmaking identities through "performance".&lt;ref name=ButlerPerformative&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Performative Acts and Gender Constitution: An Essay in Phenomenology and Feminist Theory|last = Butler|first = Judith|date = 1988 |journal = Theatre Journal |volume=40 |issue=4 |pages=519–531|doi = 10.2307/3207893|jstor = 3207893}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writers in the field of [[Queer theory]] have at times taken this to the extent as to now argue that "queer", despite generations of specific use, no longer needs to refer to any specific sexual orientation at all; that it is now only about disrupting the mainstream, with author [[David M. Halperin]] arguing that straight people may now also self-identify as "queer,"&lt;ref name=Halperin&gt;{{cite book |author=Halperin, David M. |title=One Hundred Years of Homosexuality: And Other Essays on Greek Love |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |year=1990 |isbn=978-0-415-90097-3 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=|title-link=One Hundred Years of Homosexuality }}&lt;/ref&gt; which some believe, is a form of [[cultural appropriation]] which robs gays and lesbians of their identity and makes invisible and irrelevant the actual, lived experience that causes them to be marginalized in the first place. "It desexualizes identity, when the issue is precisely about a sexual identity."&lt;ref name=Jagose&gt;[[Annamarie Jagose|Jagose, Annamarie]], 1996. ''Queer Theory: An Introduction''. New York: New York University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=4-encylopedia/&gt; See [[Queer heterosexuality]].

Some supporters of identity politics take stances based on [[Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak]]'s work (namely, "Can the Subaltern Speak?") and have described some forms of identity politics as [[strategic essentialism]], a form which has sought to work with [[Hegemony|hegemonic]] discourses to reform the understanding of "universal" goals.&lt;ref name=Spivak&gt;{{Cite book|title=Other Asias|last=Spivak|first=Gayatri Chakrovotry|publisher=Blackwell Publishing|year=2008|isbn=978-1405102070|location=Malden, M.A.|pages=260}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Abraham&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Abraham|first=Susan|year=2009|title=Strategic Essentialism in Nationalist Discourses: Sketching a Feminist Agenda in the Study of Religion|url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/266799|journal=Journal of Feminist Studies in Religion|volume=25|issue=1|pages=156–161|via=Project Muse|doi=10.2979/fsr.2009.25.1.156|access-date=17 December 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171018190808/https://muse.jhu.edu/article/266799|archive-date=18 October 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Ritze&gt;G. Ritze/J. M. Ryan eds., ''The Concise Encyclopedia of Sociology'' (2010) p. 193&lt;/ref&gt;

===Critiques of identity politics===
[[File:Anti-capitalism color— Restored.png|right|thumb|The [[Industrial Workers of the World]] poster "[[Pyramid of Capitalist System]]" (1911)]] Critics argue that groups based on a particular shared identity (e.g. race, or gender identity) can divert energy and attention from more fundamental issues, similar to the history of [[divide and rule]] strategies. [[Chris Hedges]] has criticized identity politics as one of the factors making up a form of "corporate capitalism" that only masquerades as a political platform, and which he believes "will never halt the rising social inequality, unchecked militarism, evisceration of civil liberties and omnipotence of the organs of security and surveillance."&lt;ref name=HedgesTD&gt;{{cite news |last=Hedges |first=Chris |date=5 February 2018 |title=The Bankruptcy of the American Left |url=https://www.truthdig.com/articles/bankruptcy-american-left/ |work=Truthdig |location= |access-date=9 February 2018 |authorlink=Chris Hedges |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180209135923/https://www.truthdig.com/articles/bankruptcy-american-left/ |archive-date=9 February 2018 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sociologist [[Charles Derber]] asserts that the American left is "largely an identity-politics party" and that it "offers no broad critique of the political economy of capitalism. It focuses on reforms for blacks and women and so forth. But it doesn’t offer a contextual analysis within capitalism." Both he and [[David North (socialist)|David North]] of the [[Socialist Equality Party (United States)|Socialist Equality Party]] posit that these fragmented and isolated identity movements which permeate the left have allowed for a far-right resurgence.&lt;ref name=HedgesTD/&gt;

Critiques of identity politics have also been expressed on other grounds by writers such as [[Eric Hobsbawm]],&lt;ref&gt;Hobsbawm, Eric (2 May 1996). "[http://banmarchive.org.uk/articles/1996%20annual%20lecture.htm Identity Politics and the Left] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170918013136/http://banmarchive.org.uk/articles/1996%20annual%20lecture.htm |date=18 September 2017 }}". 1996 Trust Lecture. Barry Amiel&amp;nbsp;&amp;amp; Norman Melburn Trust. amielandmelburn.org.uk. Retrieved 4 September 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Todd Gitlin]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.pbs.org/thinktank/transcript235.html PBS.org] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170804215455/http://www.pbs.org/thinktank/transcript235.html |date=4 August 2017 }}, Thinktank transcript 235&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michael Tomasky]], [[Richard Rorty]], [[Sean Wilentz]], [[Robert W. McChesney]],{{citation needed|date=March 2018}} and [[Jim Sleeper]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ppionline.org/ppi_ci.cfm?knlgAreaID=115&amp;subsecID=172&amp;contentID=2049|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100116130524/http://www.ppionline.org/ppi_ci.cfm?knlgAreaID=115&amp;subsecID=172&amp;contentID=2049 |archive-date=16 January 2010 |last=Sleeper |first=Jim |title=In Defense of Civic Culture |date=1 January 1993|publisher=[[Progressive Policy Institute]]. ppionline.org |access-date=4 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{clarify|date=September 2017|reason=Several authors are mentioned, without any indication of the content of their critiques}} Hobsbawm criticized nationalisms and the principle of national self-determination adopted in many countries after [[World War I]], since national governments are often merely an expression of a ruling class or power, and their proliferation was a source of the wars of the 20th century. Hence, Hobsbawm argues that identity politics, such as [[queer nationalism]], [[Islamism]], [[Cornish nationalism]] or [[Ulster loyalism]] are just other versions of [[bourgeois nationalism]].{{citation needed|date=June 2015}} The view that identity politics (rooted in challenging racism, sexism, and the like) obscures class inequality is widespread in the United States and other Western nations. This framing ignores how class-based politics are identity politics themselves, according to [[Jeff Sparrow]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/18/class-and-identity-politics-are-not-mutually-exclusive-the-left-should-use-this-to-its-benefit|title=Class and identity politics are not mutually exclusive. The left should use this to its benefit {{!}} Jeff Sparrow|last=Sparrow|first=Jeff|date=17 November 2016|website=the Guardian|language=en|access-date=2018-07-17|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180718030629/https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/18/class-and-identity-politics-are-not-mutually-exclusive-the-left-should-use-this-to-its-benefit|archive-date=18 July 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Intersectional critiques ===
In her journal article ''Mapping the Margins: Intersectionality, Identity Politics and Violence against Women of Color,'' [[Kimberle Crenshaw]] treats identity politics as a process that brings people together based on a shared aspect of their identity. Crenshaw applauds identity politics for bringing African Americans (and other non-white people), gays and lesbians, and other oppressed groups together in community and progress.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Crenshaw|first=Kimberle|author-link=Kimberle Crenshaw|date=1 January 1991|title=Mapping the Margins: Intersectionality, Identity Politics, and Violence against Women of Color|jstor=1229039|journal=Stanford Law Review|volume=43|issue=6|pages=1241–99|doi=10.2307/1229039|citeseerx=10.1.1.695.5934}}&lt;/ref&gt; But she critiques it because "it frequently conflates or ignores intragroup differences."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Crenshaw argues that for black women, at least two aspects of their identity are the subject of oppression: their race and their sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Demarginalizing the Intersection of Race and Sex: A Black Feminist Critique of Antidiscrimination Doctrine, Feminist Theory and Antiracist Politics|last=Crenshaw|first=Kimberle|publisher=University of Chicago Legal Forum|year=1989|isbn=|location=|pages=139–68}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, although identity politics are useful, we must be aware of the role&amp;nbsp;[[intersectionality]]. Nira Yuval-Davis supports Crenshaw's critiques&amp;nbsp;in ''Intersectionality and Feminist Politics''&amp;nbsp;and explains that "Identities are individual and collective narratives that answer the question 'who am/are I/we?"&amp;nbsp;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Yuval-Davis|first=Nira|date=1 August 2006|title=Intersectionality and Feminist Politics|url=http://ejw.sagepub.com/content/13/3/193|journal=European Journal of Women's Studies|language=en|volume=13|issue=3|pages=193–209|doi=10.1177/1350506806065752|issn=1350-5068|access-date=11 April 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161103075104/http://ejw.sagepub.com/content/13/3/193|archive-date=3 November 2016|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Mapping the Margins'', Crenshaw illustrates her point using the&amp;nbsp;[[Clarence Thomas Supreme Court nomination|Clarence Thomas]]/[[Anita Hill]] controversy. Anita Hill [[Clarence_Thomas_Supreme_Court_nomination#Anita_Hill_testimony|accused]] US Supreme Court Justice nominee Clarence Thomas of sexual harassment; Thomas would be the second African American judge on the Supreme Court. Crenshaw argues that Hill was then deemed anti-black in the movement against racism, and although she came forward on the feminist issue of sexual harassment, she was excluded because when considering feminism, it is the narrative of white middle-class women that prevails.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Crenshaw concludes that acknowledging intersecting categories when groups unite on the basis of identity politics is better than ignoring categories altogether.&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt;

== Examples ==
{{Main category|Identity politics}}

A ''[[Le Monde]]''/[[IFOP]] poll in January 2011 conducted in France and Germany found that a majority felt Muslims are "scattered improperly"; an analyst for ''IFOP'' said the results indicated something "beyond linking immigration with security or immigration with unemployment, to linking Islam with a threat to identity".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = European Poll: An Islamic Threat? | date = 6 January 2011 | url = http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/features/2011/01/201116112228783789.html | work = [[Al Jazeera]] | access-date = 19 October 2012 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20121014114808/http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/features/2011/01/201116112228783789.html | archive-date = 14 October 2012 | url-status = live | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Racial and ethnocultural ===
Ethnic and racial identity politics are commonly referenced in popular culture,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.newsweek.com/2019/11/15/literary-influences-superstar-musician-david-bowie-1468145.html |title=The Literary Influences of Superstar Musician David Bowie|authorlink=|author=John O'Connell|quote=As the husband of a Muslim woman from Somalia, [[David Bowie|Bowie]] couldn't help but be highly attuned to racial identity politics.|date=31 October 2019|work=[[Newsweek]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are increasingly analyzed in media and social commentary as an interconnected part of politics and society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://time.com/5444761/donald-trump-midterms-race-candidates/ |title=How President Trump Put Race at the Center of the Midterms|authorlink=|author=Tessa Berenson|quote=Some Republicans worry that Trump’s focus on racial identity politics so close to the election is undercutting their message to swing voters on subjects like the economy and health care.|date=6 November 2018|work=[[TIME]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.smh.com.au/national/opponents-on-the-left-pouring-gasoline-on-donald-trump-s-fires-20190818-p52i92.html |title=Opponents on the left pouring gasoline on Donald Trump's fires|authorlink=James Kirchick|author=James Kirchick|quote=Trump’s game isn’t difficult to discern. He is practicing the same resentment-based, racial-identity politics that has fuelled his political rise since the earlier part of this decade, when he began expressing doubts that the first black American president was actually born in the United States.|date=19 August 2019|work=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both a majority and minority group phenomenon, racial identity politics can develop as a reaction to the historical legacy of race-based oppression of a people,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Tamar Mayor|authorlink1=|title=Gender Ironies of Nationalism: Sexing the Nation|date=2012|publisher=[[Routledge]]|location=|isbn=978-0415162555|page=331|quote=For example, where a legacy of oppression based on race exists, an identity politics of race can be formed in opposition to that form of oppression, and can help to provide an occasion for racial pride and resistance to that oppression.}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as a general group identity issue:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Racial identity politics utilizes racial consciousness - or the group's collective memory and experiences - as the essential framework for interpreting the actions and interests of all other social groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=James Jennings|authorlink1=|title=Blacks, Latinos, and Asians in Urban America: Status and Prospects for Politics and Activism|date=1994|publisher=[[Praeger Publishing]]|location=|isbn=978-0275949341|page=35|chapter=Building Coalitions|quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Carol M. Swain]] has argued that non-white ethnic pride and an "emphasis on racial identity politics" is fomenting the rise of [[white nationalism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Carol M. Swain|authorlink1=Carol M. Swain|title=The New White Nationalism in America: Its Challenge to Integration|date=2004|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|location=|isbn=978-0521545587|page=xvi|chapter=Preface|quote=The continued emphasis on racial identity politics and the fostering of an ethnic group pride on the part of nonwhite minority groups.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anthropologist [[Michael Messner]] has suggested that the [[Million Man March]] was an example of racial identity politics in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Michael A. Messner|authorlink1=Michael Messner|title=Politics of Masculinities: Men in Movements|date=1997|publisher=[[SAGE Publications]]|location=|isbn=978-0803955776|page=79-80|chapter=Racial and sexual identity politics|quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Arab identity politics ====
{{See also|Arab identity|Arab nationalism}}
Arab identity politics concerns the identity-based politics derived from the racial or ethnocultural consciousness of [[Arab people]]. In the [[regionalism]] of the [[Middle East]], it has particular meaning in relation to the national and cultural identities of non-Arab countries, such as Turkey and Iran.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Arshin Adib-Moghaddam|title=Middle East Review (IDE-JETRO)|date=2010|publisher=[[Institute of Developing Economies]]|location=[[Japan External Trade Organization]]|isbn=978-0980415810|edition=Volume 7|chapter=The myth of "National Identity": Psycho-nationalism in Iran and the Arab world|quote=Iranian and Arab identity politics thwarted, perverted, and dismembered communitarian thinking for long periods in the twentieth century and the same applies to other forms of psycho-nationalism in Turkey}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Elizabeth Monier|title=''[[Contemporary Politics (journal)|Contemporary Politics]]''|chapter=The Arabness of Middle East regionalism: the Arab Spring and competition for discursive hegemony between Egypt, Iran and Turkey|date=2014|publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]]|edition=Volume 20, No. 4|isbn=|page=421-434|quote=To explore the role played by Arab identity politics in regionalism with regard to the status of non-Arab states, this article presents a study of the competing hegemonic regional discourses employed by Turkey, Iran and Egypt}}&lt;/ref&gt; In their 2010 ''Being Arab: Arabism and the Politics of Recognition'', academics [[Christopher Wise]] and [[Paul James (academic)|Paul James]] challenged the view that, in the post-[[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|Afghanistan]] and [[Iraq War|Iraq]] invasion era, Arab identity-driven politics were ending. Refuting the view that had "drawn many analysts to conclude that the era of Arab identity politics has passed", Wise and James examined its development as a viable alternative to [[Islamic fundamentalism]] in the Arab world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Christopher Wise|author2=Paul James|authorlink1=Christopher Wise|authorlink2=Paul James (academic)|title=Being Arab: Arabism and the Politics of Recognition|date=2010|publisher=[[Arena (Australian publishing co-operative)|Arena Publications]]|location=|isbn=978-0980415810|page=|edition=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Marc Lynch]], the post-[[Arab Spring]] era has seen increasing Arab identity politics, which is "marked by state-state rivalries as well as state-society conflicts". Lynch believes this is creating a new [[Arab Cold War]], no longer characterized by Sunni-Shia sectarian divides but by a reemergent [[Arab identity]] in the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Lynch|first1=Mark|authorlink=Marc Lynch|title=The Arab Uprisings Explained: New Contentious Politics in the Middle East|date=2019|publisher=[[Columbia University Press]]|location=|isbn=978-0231158855|page=119|edition=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Najla Said]] has explored her lifelong experience with Arab identity politics in her book ''Looking for Palestine''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.salon.com/2013/07/28/najla_said_my_arab_american_story_is_not_typical_in_any_way/|title=Najla Said: "My Arab-American story is not typical in any way"|publisher=[[Salon (website)]]|date=28 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Māori identity politics ====
{{See also|Māori identity|Māori nationalism}}
Due to somewhat competing tribe-based versus pan-Māori concepts, there is both an internal and external utilization of Māori identity politics in New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Roger Maaka|author2=Augie Fleras|title=The Politics of Indigeneity: Challenging the State in Canada and Aotearoa New Zealand|date=2005|publisher=[[Otago University Press]]|location=|isbn=978-1877276538|page=67|chapter=|quote=The tensions created by the intersection of tribe as identity, versus tribe as organisation, are central to Maori identity politics.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Projected outwards, Māori identity politics has been a disrupting force in the [[politics of New Zealand]] and post-colonial conceptions of nationhood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Tatiana Tökölyová|title=Journal of Nationalism, Memory &amp; Language Politics|date=2005|publisher=[[Walter de Gruyter]]|location=[[University of International and Public Relations Prague]]|isbn=|page=67|edition=Volume 11, Edition 1|chapter=Transnationalism in the Pacific Region as a Concept of State Identity|quote=Maori identity politics have disrupted the colonially-inspired constructions of the New Zealand nation and state from a base of indigeneity.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its development has also been explored as causing parellel ethnic identity developments in non-Māori popuations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Hal B. Levine|title=Constructing collective identity: a comparative analysis of New Zealand Jews, Maori, and urban Papua New Guineans|date=1997|publisher=[[Peter Lang (publisher)]]|location=|isbn=978-3631319444|page=11|chapter=|quote=The material on biculturalism particularly shows how ethnicity interdigitates with identity politics for Maori and stimulates parallel developments among non-Maori New Zealanders.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Academic [[Alison Jones]], in her co-written ''Tuai: A Traveller in Two Worlds'', suggests that a form of Māori identity politics, directly oppositional to [[Pākehā]] (white New Zealanders), has helped provide a "basis for internal collaboration and a politics of strength".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1=Te Kawehau Hoskins|editor2=Alison Jones|title=Critical Conversations in Kaupapa Maori|date=2005|publisher=[[Huia Publishers]]|location=|isbn=978-1775503286|page=|chapter=|quote=As Jones and Jenkins (2008) point out, an oppositional Māori identity politics has been the 'basis for internal collaboration and a politics of strength' (p.475).}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2009, [[Ministry of Social Development (New Zealand)|Ministry of Social Development]] journal identified Māori identity politics, and societal reactions to it, as the most prominent factor behind significant changes in self-identification from the 2006 New Zealand census.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Tahu Kukutai|author2=Robert Didham|title=Social Policy Journal of New Zealand|date=2009|publisher=[[Ministry of Social Development (New Zealand)]]|location=|isbn=|page=|edition=In Search of Ethnic New Zealanders: National Naming in the 2006 Census|quote=Māori identity politics and Treaty settlements, as well as their reactions – the latter included challenges to historical settlements and so-called “race-based” funding.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=15em}}
* [[Adversarial process]]
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Afrophobia]]
* [[Auto-segregation]]
* [[Blue-collar worker]]
* [[White-collar worker]]
* [[Client politics]]
* [[Conflict theory]]
* [[Conviction politics]]
* [[Culture war]]
* [[Diaspora politics]]
* [[Divide and rule]]
* [[Endogamy]]
* [[Ethnic interest group]]
* [[False consciousness]]
* [[Group polarization]]
* [[Group rights]]
* [[Identity (social science)]]
* [[Identitarianism]]
* [[Interest group liberalism]]
* [[Marx's theory of alienation#Alienation of the worker from other workers|Marx's theory of alienation]]
* [[Minority influence]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[New social movements]]
* [[Objectification]]
* [[Opposition to immigration]]
* [[Political consciousness]]
* [[Political correctness]]
* [[Queer theory]]
* [[Racialism]]
* [[Sectarianism]]
* [[Separatism]]
* [[Social conflict theory]]
* [[Standpoint theory]]
* [[Toxic masculinity]]
* [[Tribalism]]
* [[Voting bloc]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20161206100016/http://belfercenter.ksg.harvard.edu/project/57/religion_in_international_affairs.html Initiative on Religion in International Affairs] at Harvard
*[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/ "Identity politics"], ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]'', 16 July 2002
*Joan Mandel. [https://userpages.umbc.edu/~korenman/wmst/identity_pol.html "How Political Is the Personal?: Identity Politics, Feminism and Social Change"], [[University of Maryland, Baltimore County]]
*[https://www.seattleweekly.com/news/a-marxist-critiques-identity-politics/ "A Marxist Critiques Identity Politics"]. ''[[Seattle Weekly]]''. 25 April 2017.
*[https://www.jacobinmag.com/2017/08/identity-politics-gay-rights-neoliberalism-stonewall-feminism-race "Identity Politics Can Only Get Us So Far"]. ''[[Jacobin (magazine)|Jacobin]]''. 3 August 2017.
*[https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/jul/14/identity-politics-right-left-trump-racism "Why identity politics benefits the right more than the left"]. ''[[The Guardian]]''. 14 July 2018.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Identity politics}}
[[Category:Identity politics| ]]
[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:Political terminology]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>