<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20030906235031|1402736" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="313075" pageid="313075" ns="0" title="Identity politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-09-07T00:26:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Identity politics''' are [[politics]] primarily concerned about the interests and identity of a particular group, rather than the policy issues which relate to all members of the community.  The group identity can be based on [[race]], [[social class|class]], [[religion]], [[sex]], [[sexuality]] or other criteria.  

This article is about group-based movements in politics which claim to represent the interests of their exclusive group. Although most political parties target particular constituencies or demographics more than others, this is typically not the core part of their ideology.

Often identity politics is a form of [[victim politics]], where a group identifies themselves as oppressed, and seek either to end that oppression, or to use that oppression to justify their actions in other spheres. Even majority groups often want to see themselves as oppressed.

Alternatively, groups may engage in [[supremacism|supremacist]] politics, where they seek to dominate other groups for what they see as legitimate reasons.

A middle way between these two extremes is [[separatism]], where the group seek to isolate themselves from other groups, something which is rarely possible in practical politics.

[[Nationalism]] in general may be regarded as a form of identity politics within the wider international community.

Examples of identity politics within nations:
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Gay rights]]
* [[Masculism]]
* [[White separatism]]
* [[Black separatism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>