<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191106164314|924900359" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="41986649" pageid="41986649" ns="0" title="TERF (acronym)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-14T07:30:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-30-500|small=yes}}
{{about|the word TERF|a broader discussion of related issues|Feminist views on transgender topics|the telomere-binding proteins|TERF1|and|TERF2}}
{{italic title}}
{{Pov|date=July 2019}}
{{short description|Acronym for "trans-exclusionary radical feminist".}}
{{Transgender sidebar|rights}}
{{Feminism sidebar}}
'''''TERF''''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|t|ɜːr|f}}, also written '''''terf''''') is an [[acronym]] for '''trans-exclusionary radical feminist'''. The term was coined in 2008.{{R|Smythe 2018}} It was originally applied to a minority of [[radical feminist]]s espousing sentiments that other feminists consider [[transphobic]], such as the rejection of the assertion that trans women are [[women]], the exclusion of [[trans women]] from [[women's spaces]], and opposition to [[transgender rights]] legislation. The sense has since expanded to refer more broadly to people with trans-exclusive views who may have no involvement with radical feminism.{{R|Lewis 2019|Miller 2018}}
Those referred to with the word ''TERF'' typically reject the term or consider it a [[Pejorative|slur]]. Some identify themselves as ''gender critical''.{{R|Vasquez 2014}} Critics of the word ''TERF'' point to its use in insults and violent rhetoric.{{R|BennettBullies|HeuchanGI|Allen et al.|Flaherty 2018}} In academic discourse there is no consensus on whether ''TERF'' constitutes a slur.{{R|McKinnon2018|Allen et al.|Davis and McCready}}

==Coinage and usage==
Trans-inclusive [[cisgender]] radical feminist [[blogger]] Viv Smythe has been credited with popularizing the term in 2008 as an online [[shorthand]].&lt;ref name="Miller 2018"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://theoutline.com/post/6536/british-feminists-media-transphobic |title=Why Is British Media So Transphobic? |last1=Miller |first1=Edie |date=5 November 2018 |publisher=[[The Outline (website)|The Outline]] |language=en |accessdate=3 May 2019|quote=The truth is, while the British conservative right would almost certainly be more than happy to whip up a frenzy of transphobia, they simply haven’t needed to, because some sections of the left over here are doing their hate-peddling for them. The most vocal source of this hatred has emerged, sadly, from within circles of radical feminists. British feminism has an increasingly notorious TERF problem. ... The application of the term has shifted somewhat over time to encompass most people espousing trans-exclusionary politics that follow a particular “TERF logic,” regardless of their involvement with radical feminism.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Smythe 2018"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Smythe |first1=Viv |title=I'm credited with having coined the word 'Terf'. Here's how it happened |newspaper=[[The Guardian]] |date=28 November 2018 |accessdate=13 April 2019 |url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/nov/29/im-credited-with-having-coined-the-acronym-terf-heres-how-it-happened|quote=Due to a short series of blogposts from 2008, I have retrospectively been credited as the coiner of the acronym “Terf” (Trans Exclusionary Radical Feminists) ... a shorthand to describe one cohort of feminists who self-identify as radical and are unwilling to recognise trans women as sisters, unlike those of us who do.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was used to describe a minority of [[Feminism|feminists]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2014/08/04/woman-2|title=What Is a Woman?|last=Goldberg|first=Michelle|date=2014-07-28|access-date=2019-11-06|language=en|issn=0028-792X}}&lt;/ref&gt; who espouse sentiments that other feminists consider [[transphobia|transphobic]]&lt;ref name="Miller 2018"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Dastagir 2017"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Dastagir |first1=Alia |url=https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/2017/03/16/feminism-glossary-lexicon-language/99120600/ |title=A feminist glossary because we didn't all major in gender studies |work=[[USA Today]] |date=16 March 2017 |accessdate=24 April 2019 |quote=TERF: The acronym for 'trans exclusionary radical feminists,' referring to feminists who are transphobic.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Lewis 2019"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/02/07/opinion/terf-trans-women-britain.html|title=Opinion {{!}} How British Feminism Became Anti-Trans|last=Lewis|first=Sophie|date=7 February 2019|work=The New York Times|accessdate=5 May 2019|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331|quote=If the idea that transphobic harassment could be “feminist” bewilders you, you are not alone. ... With time, the term TERF has become a catchall for all anti-trans feminists, radical or not.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.lgbtqnation.com/2018/12/famous-lesbian-site-taken-anti-trans-feminists-now-lesbian-media-standing/|title=Famous lesbian site taken over by anti-trans 'feminists'. Now lesbian media is standing up.|last=Bollinger|first=Alex|date=19 December 2018|website=www.lgbtqnation.com|accessdate=5 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the rejection of the view, predominant in feminist organizations, that trans women are women,&lt;ref name="Williams 2016" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Dalbey 2018" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Flaherty 2018" /&gt; opposition to [[transgender rights]], and the exclusion of trans women in women's spaces and organizations.&lt;ref name="O'Connell 2019"&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.irishtimes.com/life-and-style/health-family/transgender-for-beginners-trans-terf-cis-and-safe-spaces-1.3769653 |title=Transgender for beginners: Trans, terf, cis and safe spaces |last1=O'Connell |first1=Jennifer |newspaper=[[The Irish Times]] |language=en |date=26 January 2019 |accessdate=24 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On her transgender rights website, ''The TransAdvocate'', Cristan Williams defined the term as referencing "a brand of 'radical feminism' that is so rooted in sex [[essentialism]] and its resulting biologism, it actively campaigns against the existence, equality, and/or inclusion of trans people."&lt;ref name="Williams 2013"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.transadvocate.com/you-might-be-a-terf-if_n_10226.htm |title=You might be a TERF if&amp;nbsp;... |date=24 September 2013 |publisher=The TransAdvocate |last1=Williams |first1=Cristan }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dalbey 2018"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Dalbey |first1=Alex |title=TERF wars: Why trans-exclusionary radical feminists have no place in feminism |url=https://www.dailydot.com/irl/terf-meaning/ |accessdate=27 January 2019 |work=[[The Daily Dot]] |date=12 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Smythe has been credited with having coined the term ''TERF'', due to a blog post she wrote reacting to the [[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]]'s [[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival#"Womyn-born womyn" policy|policy]] of denying admittance to trans women. She wrote that she rejected the alignment of all radical feminists with "trans-exclusionary radfem (TERF) activists".&lt;ref name="Smythe 2018" /&gt; In a 2014 interview with ''The TransAdvocate'', Smythe said:
{{quote|"It was meant to be a deliberately technically neutral description of an activist grouping. We wanted a way to distinguish TERFs from other RadFems with whom we engaged who were trans*-positive/neutral, because we had several years of history of engaging productively/substantively with non-TERF RadFems."&lt;ref name="Williams 2016"&gt;{{cite journal |url=https://read.dukeupress.edu/tsq/article-abstract/3/1-2/254/91781/Radical-InclusionRecounting-the-Trans-Inclusive |title=Radical Inclusion: Recounting the Trans Inclusive History of Radical Feminism |journal=TSQ: Transgender Studies Quarterly |volume=3 |issue=1–2 |pages=254–258 |date=1 May 2016 |publisher=[[Duke University Press]] |last1=Williams |first1=Cristan|doi=10.1215/23289252-3334463 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

While Smythe initially used ''TERF'' to refer to a particular type of feminist whom she characterized as "unwilling to recognise trans women as sisters", she has noted that the term has taken on additional connotations, and that it has been "weaponised at times" by both inclusionary and exclusionary groups.&lt;ref name="Smythe 2018" /&gt;

Writing in ''The New York Times'' in 2019, [[Feminist theory|feminist theorist]] Sophie Lewis noted that the term ''TERF'' had become "a catchall for all anti-transgender feminists, regardless of whether they are radical".&lt;ref name="Lewis 2019"/&gt; Edie Miller, writing in ''[[The Outline (website)|The Outline]]'', said that the term was applied to "most people espousing trans-exclusionary politics that follow a particular 'TERF logic', regardless of their involvement with radical feminism".&lt;ref name="Miller 2018"/&gt; The term ''TERFy'' has also been used to describe things "that queer millennials deem uncool" such as [[Bangs (hair)|bangs]].&lt;ref name="Wilson 2018"&gt;{{cite web|website=Slate|url=https://slate.com/human-interest/2018/08/lesbian-history-terfs-and-queer-culture-do-queer-women-have-to-reject-all-second-wave-feminism-to-be-inclusive.html|title=Do I Have to Give Up Lesbian History to Participate in Queer Culture?|last=Wilson|first=Lena|date=August 16, 2018|quote=TERF, as an insult, has become so far removed from its original activist intentions (rightly criticizing trans exclusion in feminism) that, at this point, it’s also a word for anything that queer millennials deem uncool. Things I’ve seen called “TERFy” on Twitter and Tumblr include tampon ads, the word “female,” the non-word “womxn,” Janelle Monae’s “Pynk,” the Venus symbol, bangs, Jill Stein, Cardi B, and … trans women.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opposition to the word==
Feminists described as ''TERFs'' generally object to the term and sometimes refer to themselves as "gender critical".{{What|Reason=Using term without saying what it means is pointless|date=October 2019}}&lt;ref name="Goldberg 2015"&gt;{{cite magazine |last1=Goldberg |first1=Michelle |title=The Trans Women Who Say That Trans Women Aren't Women |url=https://slate.com/human-interest/2015/12/gender-critical-trans-women-the-apostates-of-the-trans-rights-movement.html |accessdate=12 April 2019|magazine=[[Slate (magazine)|Slate]] |date=9 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Flaherty 2018"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Flaherty |first1=Colleen |date=29 August 2018 |title='TERF' War – Philosophers object to a journal's publication 'TERF,' in reference to some feminists. Is it really a slur? |website=[[Inside Higher Ed]] |url=https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2018/08/29/philosophers-object-journals-publication-terf-reference-some-feminists-it-really |accessdate=12 April 2019 |language=en|quote=While the term has become controversial over time, especially with its often hateful deployment on social media, it originally described a subgroup of feminists who believe that the interests of cisgender women (those who are born with vaginas) don’t necessarily intersect with those of transgender women (primarily those born with penises)...TERF 'is widely used across online platforms as a way to denigrate and dismiss the women (and some men) who disagree with the dominant narrative on trans issues...Targeted groups include 'lesbians who merely maintain that same-sex attraction is not equivalent to transphobia,' and 'women who believe that women’s oppression is sex-based, and are concerned about erasing the political importance of female bodies...."}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Vasquez 2014"&gt;{{cite magazine |magazine=Bitch |last1=Vasquez |first1=Tina |title=It's Time to End the Long History of Feminism Failing Transgender Women |publisher=[[Bitch Media]] |date=17 February 2014 |url=https://www.bitchmedia.org/post/the-long-history-of-transgender-exclusion-from-feminism |accessdate=13 April 2019|quote=[Cathy] Brennan, fellow attorney Elizabeth Hungerford, and other modern-day feminists continue to actively question the inclusion of trans people in women’s spaces. These feminists refer to themselves as “radical feminists” or “gender critical feminists.” In 2008, trans women and trans advocates started referring to this group as “trans-exclusionary radical feminists” or TERFs, a term Brennan considers a slur.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Serano n.d." /&gt; British columnist Sarah Ditum wrote in 2017 that "the bar to being called a 'terf' is remarkably low."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last1=Ditum|first1=Sarah|date=29 September 2017|title=What is a Terf? How an internet buzzword became a mainstream slur|url=https://www.newstatesman.com/politics/feminism/2017/09/what-terf-how-internet-buzzword-became-mainstream-slur|magazine=[[New Statesman]]|accessdate=13 April 2019|quote=On the other hand, if you are a feminist, the bar to being called a 'terf' is remarkably low. Woman's Hour presenter Jenni Murray achieved it by writing an article in which she pointed out that someone born and raised male will not have the same experiences of sexism as a woman; novelist Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie likewise made the grade by answering 'transwomen are transwomen' when asked whether she believed that 'transwomen are women'.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Some self-described gender critical feminists say they cannot accurately be described as trans-exclusionary because they say they are inclusive of trans men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Flaherty |first1=Colleen |date=29 August 2018 |title='TERF' War – Philosophers object to a journal's publication 'TERF,' in reference to some feminists. Is it really a slur? |website=[[Inside Higher Ed]] |url=https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2018/08/29/philosophers-object-journals-publication-terf-reference-some-feminists-it-really |accessdate=12 April 2019 |language=en |quote=Allen objected&amp;nbsp;... 'most radical feminists who are apparently described' by the term TERF are inclusive of trans men, and so are not 'trans-exclusionary' anyway, she said.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kennedy |first1=Natacha |title=Anti-Trans Activism – Not What It Seems |url=http://www.progressonline.org.uk/2016/12/15/anti-trans-activism-not-what-it-seems/|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170511094932/http://progressonline.org.uk/2016/12/15/anti-trans-activism-not-what-it-seems/|archivedate=11 May 2017 |publisher=[[Progress (organisation)|Progress]] |accessdate=29 April 2019 |date=15 December 2016 |quote=Beyond that, it's also entirely inaccurate, radical feminism is inclusionary of trans men (who are female by birth), it only excludes males—as a female liberation movement&amp;nbsp;...}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some critics have called this reasoning "divisive and contradictory" and say that it represents "[[transmisogyny|transmisogynist]] ideology".&lt;ref name="Erickson-Schroth 2014"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Erickson-Schroth |first1=Laura |title=Trans Bodies, Trans Selves: A Resource for the Transgender Community |date=12 May 2014 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |isbn=978-0199325351 |page=568–569 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7Ef1AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA568|quote="Some feminists have perceived transmasculine people as traitors—that is, as women who identify politically with men. When inclusive of trans men, these feminists have  often gendered them as women.  Conversely, these feminists have tended to  perceive transfeminine people as infiltrators of womanhood and of women's space. Many commentators refer to feminists who think in these ways as 'trans-exclusionary radical feminists' (TERFs).&amp;nbsp;...'The fetishistic (often {{Sic|infantalizing}}) embrace of trans men by lesbian communities is ungendering, othering, and transphobic.'"}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Wylder and Westing 2018"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Wylder|first1=Danelle|last2=Westing|first2=Corrie|title=Terfs Have No Place on the Left|url=https://socialistworker.org/2018/08/21/terfs-have-no-place-on-the-left|accessdate=28 April 2019|newspaper=[[Socialist Worker]]|date=21 August 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190503083334/http://socialistworker.org/2018/08/21/terfs-have-no-place-on-the-left|archivedate=3 May 2019|quote=It is worth noting, however, the divisive and contradictory position they held, wherein trans men were allowed on the land because TERFs considered them '[[Womyn-born womyn|women-born]]' as part of their [[Transmisogyny|transmisogynist]] ideology.|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2015 article, American feminist scholar [[Bonnie J. Morris]] argued that ''TERF'' was initially a legitimate analytical term but quickly developed into a defamatory word associated with sexist insults. She described the word as "emblematic of the unresolved tensions between our LGBT community's L and T factions" and called on scholars and journalists to stop using it.&lt;ref name="Morris 2015"&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Morris|first=Bonnie J.|author-link=Bonnie J. Morris|date=July-August 2015|volume=22|issue=4|pp=13&amp;ndash;15|journal=[[The Gay &amp; Lesbian Review Worldwide]]|url=|title=The Hijacking of Lesbian History|quote=TERF is an important new slur, emblematic of the unresolved tensions between our LGBT community's L and T factions. ... It began as a legitimate means of isolating and critiquing the work of a very few controversial feminist authors, namely Janice Raymond and Sheila Jeffreys ... TERF is a unique new insult for non-transgender lesbians by other LGBT activists, and it bears monitoring. Those women relegated to the TERF bin of bad feminism are now being subjected to traditional sexist canards, including charges of unattractiveness, mental instability, and penis envy. ... My charge to every responsible editor, journalist, feminist scholar, and LGBT historian is to please stop recycling the acronym TERF; it is defamatory.}} [http://www.glreview.org/wp-content/uploads/DigitalEditions/mtdownload7894_2015.07.01_11.55/files/assets/common/downloads/page0013.pdf p. 13], [http://www.glreview.org/wp-content/uploads/DigitalEditions/mtdownload7894_2015.07.01_11.55/files/assets/common/downloads/page0014.pdf p. 14], [http://www.glreview.org/wp-content/uploads/DigitalEditions/mtdownload7894_2015.07.01_11.55/files/assets/common/downloads/page0015.pdf p. 15]&lt;/ref&gt; 

British journalist [[Catherine Bennett (journalist)|Catherine Bennett]] has described the word as "a bullying tool" which has "already succeeded in repressing speech – and maybe even research".&lt;ref name="BennettBullies"&gt;{{cite news|first=Catherine|last=Bennett|title=Bullies everywhere delight in coming up with new insults|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=19 November 2017|url=https://www.theguardian.com/society/commentisfree/2017/nov/19/bullies-everywhere-take-delight-in-coming-up-with-new-insults|quote=the advance of terf, as a bullying tool, has already succeeded in repressing speech – and maybe even research ... ugly terf, fucking terf scum}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BennettBullies" /&gt;&lt;ref name="BennettViolent"&gt;{{cite news|last=Bennett|first=Catherine|date=29 April 2018|title=Violent misogyny is unfortunately not confined to the internet's 'incels'|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/apr/29/violent-misogyny-not-confined-to-internet-incels|work=[[The Guardian]]|quote=Photographs of one vitrine, featuring a red bespattered T-shirt reading: “I punch terfs!” (trans-exclusionary radical feminists/women who disagree with me), may have struck a chord with anyone following the current UK debate about the government’s self-ID proposals. To date, threats, from one side, which echo, inescapably, some of those in the pro-Rodger playbook (“die in a fire terf scum”) have yet to generate comparably widespread concern, even after a woman was punched. Her assailant had earlier expressed the wish to “fuck up some terfs”.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Feminist blogger Claire Heuchan argues that the word is often used alongside "violent rhetoric".&lt;ref name="Heuchan 2017" /&gt;&lt;ref name="HeuchanGI"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://glasgowinternational.org/artists/claire-heuchan/|title=Claire Heuchan|date=30 January 2018|website=[[Glasgow International]]|accessdate=5 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Phrases like "Kill a TERF!" or "Punch a TERF!" are also posted by [[Internet troll|trolls]] online and there have been other depictions of violence aimed at TERFs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Pilgrim|first=David|date=2018-10-20|title=The transgender controversy: a reply to Summersell|url=https://doi.org/10.1080/14767430.2018.1539825|journal=Journal of Critical Realism|volume=17|issue=5|pages=523–528|doi=10.1080/14767430.2018.1539825|issn=1476-7430}}&lt;/ref&gt; Heuchan adds that language of this type is used to "[[dehumanise]] women", often lesbians.&lt;ref name="Heuchan 2017"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Heuchan |first1=Claire |url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2017/oct/06/feminist-linda-bellos-women-trans-male-violence |title=If feminist Linda Bellos is seen as a risk, progressive politics has lost its way |work=[[The Guardian]] |date=6 October 2017 |quote=Terf stands for trans-exclusionary radical feminist. Online, {{sic|it often it|nolink=y}} appears alongside violent rhetoric: punch a Terf, stab a Terf, kill a Terf. This language is used to dehumanise women who are critical of gender as part of a political system.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The 2018 [[All-party parliamentary group|All Party Parliamentary Group]] (APPG) on Hate Crime stated that they received several submissions that indicated a high degree of tension between trans activists and feminists groups opposed to transgender rights legislation, with reports on both sides detailing incidents of extreme or abusive language. The report noted that some women had submitted reports which argued that "women who object to the inclusion of trans women as female are being attacked both online and, in the street, with the term 'trans-exclusionary radical feminist' or (TERF) being used as a term of abuse."&lt;ref name=APPG2019&gt;{{cite web|author=All Party Parliamentary Group on Hate Crime|title=How Do We Build Community Cohesion When Hate Crime Is On The Rise?|url=http://www.appghatecrime.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/APPG%20on%20Hate%20Crime%20Report%20Hate%20Crime%20and%20Community%20Cohesion.pdf|publisher=[[House of Commons of the United Kingdom]]|date=2019|accessdate=2 November 2019|page=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Slur debate==

The people at whom the word ''TERF'' is directed often characterize it as a [[pejorative|slur]] or [[hate speech]].&lt;ref name="Vasquez 2014" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Compton 2019"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Compton |first1=Julie |title='Pro-lesbian' or 'trans-exclusionary'? Old animosities boil into public view |url=https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/pro-lesbian-or-trans-exclusionary-old-animosities-boil-public-view-n958456 |accessdate=19 March 2019 |publisher=[[NBC News]] |date=14 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Goldberg 2014"&gt;{{cite magazine |last1=Goldberg |first1=Michelle |title=What Is a Woman? |magazine=[[The New Yorker]] |date=2014-08-04 |url=http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2014/08/04/woman-2 |accessdate=20 November 2015 |quote=TERF stands for 'trans-exclusionary radical feminist.' The term can be useful for making a distinction with radical feminists who do not share the same position, but those at whom it is directed consider it a slur.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a July 2018 solicitation of essays regarding "transgender identities", British magazine ''[[The Economist]]'' required writers to "avoid all slurs, including TERF", stating that the word is used to try to silence opinions and sometimes incite violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Transgender identities: a series of invited essays |newspaper=[[The Economist]] |date=29 June 2018 |url=https://www.economist.com/open-future/2018/06/29/transgender-identities-a-series-of-invited-essays |accessdate=19 March 2019 |quote=In the interests of fostering open debate we have set ground rules, both for essays and reader comments: use the pronouns people want you to use, and avoid all slurs, including TERF (trans-exclusionary radical feminist), which may have started as a descriptive term but is now used to try to silence a vast swathe of opinions on trans issues, and sometimes to incite violence against women.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Transgender]] rights activist&lt;ref name=bbc&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/sport/46453958|title=Transgender women in sport: Are they really a 'threat' to female sport?|date=18 December 2018|publisher=|via=www.bbc.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Philosophy of language]] professor [[Rachel McKinnon]] has maintained the word is not a slur. She argues that merely being "a term used to denigrate women" does not make a word a slur, that being "an absurd, nonsensical view of the nature of slurs".&lt;ref name="McKinnon2018"/&gt; In a YouTube video she further argues that ''TERF'' can be used in a purely descriptive way, while slurs and all derogatory terms are necessarily derogatory in all contexts.&lt;ref name="McKinnon 2017"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lmDauuQOOdU |title=Trans 101 #4: 'TERF' is Not a Slur |last1=McKinnon |first1=Rachel |work=[[YouTube]] |date=24 May 2017 |accessdate=22 April 2019|quote=We don't need a non-pejorative correlate for TERF. The acronym Trans Exclusionary Radical Feminist ''is'' the non-pejorative term. It can't be a slur if the term itself is its own non-pejorative correlate. So, that's strike 1 for TERF as a slur and frankly it's a pretty big one. ... TERF is not even a derogatory term, it is much closer to 'short' than it is to 'runt' and it's nowhere near the seriousness of a slur.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2018, seven British philosophers wrote on the website ''[[Daily Nous]]'' that two articles by Rachel McKinnon&lt;ref name="McKinnon2018"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=McKinnon |first1=Rachel |title=The Epistemology of Propaganda |journal=[[Philosophy and Phenomenological Research]] |date=7 March 2018 |volume=96 |issue=2 |pages=483–489 |doi=10.1111/phpr.12429 |url=https://storage.googleapis.com/wzukusers/user-32241190/documents/5bf5e044e681bCc43WKe/16%20Rachel%20McKinnon%20-%20The%20Epistemology%20of%20Propaganda.pdf|quote=many contemporary TERFs accuse trans women of coining the phrase/term—and, ludicrously, claim that ‘TERF’ is a misogynistic slur. ... The idea—it seems to be—is that ‘TERF’ is a term used to denigrate women, and so it is a slur. However, this is an absurd, nonsensical view of the nature of slurs.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Jason Stanley&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Stanley |first1=Jason |title=Replies |journal=[[Philosophy and Phenomenological Research]] |date=7 March 2018 |volume=96 |issue=2 |pages=497–511 |doi=10.1111/phpr.12427|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; published in the journal ''[[Philosophy and Phenomenological Research]]'' normalized the term. They described the term as "at worst a slur and at best derogatory", and argued that the term had been used to denigrate those "who disagree with the dominant narrative on trans issues".&lt;ref name="Weinberg 2018"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Weinberg |first1=Justin |title=Derogatory Language in Philosophy Journal Risks Increased Hostility and Diminished Discussion |url=http://dailynous.com/2018/08/27/derogatory-language-philosophy-journal-hostility-discussion/ |publisher=[[Daily Nous]] |accessdate=19 March 2019 |date=27 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Flaherty 2018" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Allen et al."&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Allen |first1=Sophie R. |last2=Finneron-Burns |first2=Elizabeth |last3=Leng |first3=Mary |last4=Lawford-Smith |first4=Holly |last5=Jones |first5=Jane Clare |last6=Reilly-Cooper |first6=Rebecca |last7=Simpson |first7=R. J. |title=On an Alleged Case of Propaganda: Reply to McKinnon |date=24 September 2018 |url=https://philpapers.org/archive/ALLOAA-3.pdf|quote=representative examples of derogatory uses of the term: ‘kill all TERFs’; ‘shoot a terf today’; ‘all TERFs deserve to be shot in the head’; ‘somebody slap this TERF c*nt across the face’; ‘literally kill all TERFs’ ... To summarize, we’ve considered three specific accounts of slurs, Anderson and Lepore’s account which appeals to whether those targeted by the term take it to be a slur, Nunberg’s account on which slurs signal in-group membership, and Swanson’s account on which slurs cue harmful ideologies. We’ve argued that ‘TERF’ is a slur on all three of the specific accounts surveyed.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response, Ernest Sosa, the journal's editor in chief, stated that scholars consulted by the journal advised that the term "might evolve to become a slur", but that its use as a denigrating term in some contexts was still "compatible with its having a descriptive meaning".&lt;ref name="Flaherty 2018" /&gt;

In a 2018 draft paper, linguists Christopher Davis and Elin McCready argue that three properties make a term a slur: it must be derogatory towards a particular group, it must be used to subordinate them within some structure of power relations, and the derogated group must be defined by an intrinsic property. Davis and McCready write that the term ''TERF'' satisfies the first condition, fails the third condition, and that the second condition is contentious, in that it depends on how each group sees itself in relation to the other group.&lt;ref name="Davis and McCready"&gt;{{cite journal |title=The Instability of Slurs |publisher=Semantics Archive |date=19 November 2018 |last=Davis |first=Christopher |last2=McCready |first2=Elin |journal = Prepublication |url=https://semanticsarchive.net/Archive/2Y0NTg2Y/Davis-McCready-Instability_of_Slurs.pdf |accessdate=24 April 2019|quote=The term has subsequently become viewed as a slur by people subscribing to the ideology described by the acronym, and certainly it has been used with derogatory force by some people. But is it technically a slur in our sense? ... It clearly does not satisfy condition (iii), because holding this ideology is completely optional and in no sense an inherent property. If this condition correctly delimits the domain of slurs, then ‘TERF’ cannot be a slur after all for it too is not an inherent property, but an ideological one.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Transfeminism|Transfeminist]] and author [[Julia Serano]] has argued that because the word was originally created by radical feminists as a neutral term, it cannot be a slur, and "if the term has since accrued negative connotations, it is simply because most contemporary feminists view trans-exclusion as invalid, and TERF rhetoric as unnecessarily disparaging".&lt;ref name="Serano n.d."&gt;{{cite web |last1=Serano |first1=Julia |title=TERFs |url=http://www.juliaserano.com/terminology.html#TERF |date=n.d. |accessdate=21 April 2019 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transwoman author [[Andrea Long Chu]] describes the claim that ''TERF'' is a slur as "a grievance that would be beneath contempt if it weren't also true, in the sense that all bywords for bigots are intended to be defamatory."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Chu|first=Andrea Long|title=On Liking Women|journal=N+1 Magazine|url=https://nplusonemag.com/issue-30/essays/on-liking-women/|issue=30|date=Winter 2018|quote=They also don’t much like the name TERF, which they take to be a slur—a grievance that would be beneath contempt if it weren’t also true, in the sense that all bywords for bigots are intended to be defamatory.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On her blog, ''Language: A Feminist Guide'', [[Oxford University]] linguist [[Deborah Cameron (linguist)|Deborah Cameron]], whose academic research is focused on the relationship of language to gender and sexuality, wrote that arguments about whether ''TERF'' is a neutral descriptive term or a derogatory slur "raise a question which linguists and philosophers have found quite tricky to answer", but that "many individuals who have been described as TERFs have called it a slur".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://debuk.wordpress.com/2016/11/06/what-makes-a-word-a-slur/ |title=What makes a word a slur? |last=Cameron |first=Deborah |date=6 November 2016 |website=Language: A Feminist Guide |accessdate=19 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Feminist philosopher Talia Mae Bettcher argues that, regardless of whether the term is accurately classified as a slur, it "has at least become offensive to those designated by the term", which suggests it might be best to avoid "in case one wants to have a conversation across deep difference".&lt;ref name="bettcher_2017"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Bettcher |first1=Talia Mae |title=Trans Feminism: Recent Philosophical Developments. |journal=Philosophy Compass |date=November 2017 |volume=12 |issue=17 |page=7 |doi=10.1111/phc3.12438|quote=Part of the issue, however, concerns whether the expression continues to be used as a mere abbreviation for a description of a position (i.e., Trans-Exclusive Radical Feminist) as it was originally coined or whether it has also acquired a derogatory use. The issues here are delicate ... it seems that caution should at least be deployed in case one wants to have a conversation across deep difference. This seems particularly important since much of trans politics is deeply committed to the importance of self-naming and respect for self-identities.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Wiktionary|TERF}}

* [[Feminist theory]]
* [[Feminist views on transgender topics]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{LGBT slang}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:TERF}}
[[Category:Acronyms]]
[[Category:English words]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:LGBT-related controversies]]
[[Category:LGBT slang]]
[[Category:Slang terms for women]]
[[Category:Trans-exclusionary radical feminism| ]]
[[Category:Women-related neologisms]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 2000s]]
[[Category:Feminism and transgender]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>