<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081111221218|251193262" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="42327" pageid="42327" ns="0" title="Sex education"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-11T22:34:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:VictorianPostcard.jpg|right|thumb|350px|An early 20th century post card documents the problem of unwanted pregnancy.]]

'''Sex education''' is a broad term used to describe [[education]] about human [[sex organ|sexual anatomy]], [[sexual reproduction]], [[sexual intercourse]], [[reproductive health]], emotional relations, [[reproductive rights]] and responsibilities, [[contraception]], and other aspects of [[human sexual behavior]]. Common avenues for sex education are parents or caregivers, school programs, and public health campaigns.

== Overview ==
Sex education may also be described as "sexuality education," which means that it encompasses education about all aspects of sexuality, including information about [[family planning]], [[reproduction]] ([[fertilization]], [[Conception (biology)|conception]] and development of the [[embryo]] and [[fetus]], through to [[childbirth]]), plus information about all aspects of one's sexuality including: [[body image]], [[sexual orientation]], [[sexual pleasure]], [[values]], [[decision making]], [[communication]], [[dating]], [[relationships]], [[sexually transmitted infection]]s (STIs) and how to avoid them, and [[birth control]] methods.

Sex education may be taught informally, such as when someone receives information from a conversation with a [[parent]], [[friend]], [[religious]] leader, or through the [[Mass media|media]]. It may also be delivered through sex [[self-help]] authors, magazine [[advice columnist]]s, [[sex columnist]]s, or through sex education web sites. Formal sex education occurs when schools or health care providers offer sex education. 

Sometimes formal sex education is taught as a full course as part of the [[curriculum]] in [[junior high school]] or [[high school]]. Other times it is only one unit within a more broad [[health]] class, [[home economics]] class, or [[physical education]] class. Some schools offer no sex education, since it remains a [[controversy|controversial]] issue in several countries, particularly the United States (especially with regard to the age at which children should start receiving such education, the amount of detail that is revealed, and topics dealing with [[human sexual behavior]], eg. [[safe sex]] practices, [[masturbation]], [[premarital sex]], and [[sexual ethics]]).

In 1936, [[Wilhelm Reich]] commented that sex education of his time was a work of [[deception]], focusing on biology while concealing [[sexual arousal|excitement-arousal]], which is what a [[pubescent]] individual is mostly interested in. Reich added that this emphasis obscures what he believed to be a basic psychological principle: that all worries and difficulties originate from unsatisfied sexual impulses.&lt;ref&gt;Reich (1936) ''[[Die Sexualität im Kulturkampf]]''. Part one "the failure.." 6. The puberty problem - (3°) "A reflection.." - c. sexual relationships of pubescents - paragraph 4.a (pp.198-9 of italian edition)&lt;/ref&gt;  

When sex education is contentiously debated, the chief controversial points are whether covering [[child sexuality]] is valuable or detrimental; the use of birth control such as [[condom]]s and [[hormonal contraception]]; and the impact of such use on pregnancy outside marriage, [[teenage pregnancy]], and the transmission of STIs. Increasing support for [[abstinence-only sex education]] by conservative groups has been one of the primary causes of this controversy. Countries with conservative attitudes towards sex education (including the UK and the U.S.) have a higher incidence of STIs and teenage pregnancy.&lt;ref name="Joy of sex education"&gt; [http://education.guardian.co.uk/schools/comment/story/0,,1214047,00.html "Joy of sex education" by George Monbiot], ''The Guardian'', 11 May 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

The existence of [[AIDS]] has given a new sense of urgency to the topic of sex education. In many [[African]] nations, where AIDS is at epidemic levels (see [[HIV/AIDS in Africa]]), sex education is seen by most scientists as a vital [[public health]] strategy. Some international organizations such as [[Planned Parenthood]] consider that broad sex education programs have global benefits, such as controlling the risk of [[overpopulation]] and the advancement of [[women's rights]] (see also [[reproductive rights]]).

According to [[SIECUS]], the Sexuality Information and Education Council of the United States, 93% of adults they surveyed support sexuality education in high school and 84%  support it in junior high school.&lt;ref&gt;SIECUS Report of Public Support of Sexuality Education(1999)[http://www.siecus.org/school/sex_ed/sex_ed0002.html SIECUS Report Online]&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, 88% of parents of junior high school students and 80% of parents of high school students believe that sex education in school makes it easier for them to talk to their adolescents about sex.&lt;ref&gt;Sex Education in America.(Washington, DC: National Public Radio, Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation, and Kennedy School of Government, 2004), p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, 92% of adolescents report that they want both to talk to their parents about sex and to have comprehensive in-school sex education.&lt;ref&gt;Sari Locker, (2001) Sari Says: The real dirt on everything from sex to school. HarperCollins: New York.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sex education worldwide==
=== Africa===

[[Image:SIDA posters Abidjan.jpg|thumb|right|370px|AIDS posters in [[Côte d'Ivoire]]]]

Sex education in Africa has focused on stemming the growing [[HIV/AIDS in Africa|AIDS epidemic]]. Most governments in the region have established AIDS education programs in partnership with the [[World Health Organization]] and international [[Non-governmental organization|NGO]]s. These programs have been undercut significantly by the Global Gag Order, an initiative put in place by President Reagan, suspended by President Clinton, and re-instated by current President Bush.  The incidences of new HIV transmissions in Uganda decreased dramatically when Clinton supported a comprehensive sex education approach (including information about contraception and abortion).&lt;ref name="uganda"&gt;[http://www.who.int/inf-new/aids2.htm Uganda reverses the tide of HIV/AIDS]&lt;/ref&gt;  The gag order refuses government funding for any efforts that promote condom and contraception use in addition to abstinence and monagamy. &lt;ref name=PEPFAR&gt;[http://www.healthgap.org/camp/pepfar.html Health Gap: Pepfar Policies&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  According to Ugandan AIDS activists, the Global Gag Order will undermine community efforts to reduce HIV prevalence and HIV transmission. &lt;ref name=PEPFAR /&gt;  The plight of Uganda is indicative of AIDS "prevention" efforts across the continent, and the sharp decrease in AIDS transmissions in an era of comprehensive sex education vs. current rates of new infections clearly elucidates which system is more effective. 

[[Egypt]] teaches knowledge about male and female reproductive systems, sexual organs, contraception and STDs in public schools at the second and third years of the middle-preparatory phase (when students are aged 12–14). There is currently a coordinated program between [[UNDP]], [[UNICEF]], and the ministries of health and education to promote sexual education at a larger scale in rural areas and spread awareness of dangers of [[female genital cutting]].

=== Asia===
The state of sex education programs in Asia is at various stages of development. [[Indonesia]], [[Mongolia]], [[South Korea]] and [[Sri Lanka]] have a systematic policy framework for teaching about sex within schools. [[Malaysia]], the [[Philippines]] and [[Thailand]] have assessed adolescent reproductive health needs with a view to developing adolescent-specific training, messages and materials. [[India]] has programs that specifically aims at school children at the age group of nine to sixteen years. These are included as subjects in the curriculum and generally involves open and frank interaction with the teachers. In India, there is a huge debate on the curriculum of sex education and when should it be increased. Attempts by state governments to introduce sex education as a compulsory part of the school curriculum have often been met with harsh criticism by political parties, who claim that sex education "is against Indian culture" and would mislead children.[http://www.ibnlive.com/news/sex-education-on-hold-in-maharashtra-govt-schools/63811-3.html] ([[Bangladesh]], [[Myanmar]], [[Nepal]] and [[Pakistan]] have no coordinated sex education programs.&lt;ref name="escap"&gt; [http://www.unescap.org/esid/psis/population/icpd/sec7.asp Adolescents In Changing Times: Issues And Perspectives For Adolescent Reproductive Health In The ESCAP Region] United Nations Social and Economic Commission for Asia and the Pacific &lt;/ref&gt;)

In [[Japan]], sex education is mandatory from age 10 or 11, mainly covering biological topics such as menstruation and ejaculation. &lt;ref name="swedsexed"/&gt;

In [[China]], sex education traditionally consists in reading the reproduction section of biology textbooks. However, in 2000 a new five-year project was introduced by the China Family Planning Association to "promote reproductive health education among Chinese teenagers and unmarried youth" in twelve urban districts and three counties. This includes discussion about sex within human relationships as well as pregnancy and HIV prevention. &lt;ref name="chinasexed"&gt;[http://www.chinadevelopmentbrief.com/node/57 Sex education begins to break taboos] China Development Brief, 2005-06-03 &lt;/ref&gt;

The [[International Planned Parenthood Federation]] and the [[BBC World Service]] ran a 12-part series known as [http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/sci_tech/features/health/sexwise/ Sexwise], which discussed sex education, family life education, contraception and parenting. It was first launched in South Asia and then extended worldwide.&lt;ref name="sexwise"&gt; [http://www.unesco.org/courier/2000_07/uk/apprend3.htm Involve The Young!] Interview with Dr Pramilla Senanayake, assistant director-general of the International Planned Parenthood Federation&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
====Finland====
In [[Finland]], sexual education is usually incorporated into various obligatory courses, mainly as part of biology lessons (in lower grades) and later in a course related to general health issues. The Population and Family Welfare Federation provides all 15-year-olds an introductory sexual package that includes an information brochure, a condom and a cartoon love story.

====France====
In [[France]], sex education has been part of school curricula since 1973. Schools are expected to provide 30 to 40 hours of sex education, and pass out condoms, to students in grades eight and nine. In January 2000, the French government launched an information campaign on contraception with TV and radio spots and the distribution of five million leaflets on contraception to high school students.&lt;ref name=" britsexed "/&gt;

====Germany====
In [[Germany]], sex education has been part of school curricula since 1970. It normally covers all subjects concerning the growing-up process, the changing of the body, emotions, the biological process of reproduction, sexual activity, partnership, homosexuality, unwanted pregnancies and the complications of abortion, the dangers of sexual violence, child abuse, and sex-transmitted diseases, but sometimes also things like sex positions. Most schools offer courses on the correct usage of contraception. There are also other media of sex education, in first place the youth magazine "Bravo", which always contains a topic where teenagers pose questions about partnership and sexuality. Though it has to be added that the importance of this particular purpose of the magazine has faded somewhat since the 1990's, mostly due to teenagers getting the desired information from the Internet. {{Fact|date=December 2007}}

====The Netherlands====
Subsidized by the [[Netherlands|Dutch]] government, the “Lang leve de liefde” (“Long Live Love”) package, developed in the late 1980s, aims to give teenagers the skills to make their own decisions regarding health and sexuality. Nearly all secondary schools provide sex education as part of biology classes and over half of primary schools discuss sexuality and contraception. The curriculum focuses on biological aspects of reproduction as well as on values, attitudes, communication and negotiation skills. The media has encouraged open dialogue and the health-care system guarantees confidentiality and a non-judgmental approach. The Netherlands has one of the lowest teenage pregnancy rates in the world, and the Dutch approach is often seen as a model for other countries.&lt;ref name="dutchmodel"&gt; [http://www.unesco.org/courier/2000_07/uk/apprend2.htm The Dutch model] ''UNESCO Courier'' &lt;/ref&gt;

====Sweden====
In [[Sweden]], sex education has been a mandatory part of school education since 1956. The subject is usually started between ages 7 and 10, and continues up through the grades, incorporated into different subjects such as biology and history. &lt;ref name="swedsexed"&gt; [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,978575-2,00.html Sex Has Many Accents] ''TIME''&lt;/ref&gt;

====Switzerland====
In [[Switzerland]], the content and amount of sex education is decided at the [[Cantons of Switzerland|cantonal]] level. In [[Geneva]], courses have been given at the secondary level since the 1950s. Interventions in primary schools were started more recently, with the objective of making children conscious of what is and isn't allowed, and able to say "No". In secondary schools (age 13-14), condoms are shown to all pupils, and are demonstrated by unfolding over the teacher's fingers. For this, classes are usually separated into girl-only and boy-only subgroups. Condoms are not distributed, however, except among older adolescents engaged in state-run non-compulsory education (age 16-17).{{Fact|date=December 2007}}

====United Kingdom====
In [[England]] and [[Wales]], sex education is not compulsory in schools as parents can refuse to let their children take part in the lessons. The curriculum focuses on the reproductive system, fetal development, and the physical and emotional changes of adolescence, while information about contraception and safe sex is discretionary. Britain has one of the highest teenage pregnancy rates in Europe and sex education is a heated issue in government and media reports. In a 2000 study by the University of Brighton, many 14 to 15 year olds reported disappointment with the content of sex education lessons and felt that lack of confidentiality prevents teenagers from asking teachers about contraception.&lt;ref name=" britsexed "&gt; [http://www.unesco.org/courier/2000_07/uk/apprend.htm Britain: Sex Education Under Fire] ''UNESCO Courier'' &lt;/ref&gt; In a 2008 study conducted by [[YouGov]] for [[Channel 4]] it was revealed that almost three in ten teenagers say they need more sex and relationships education.&lt;ref name="sex stats"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://sexperienceuk.channel4.com/teen-sex-survey|title=Teen Sex Survey|accessdate=2008-09-11|publisher=Channel 4|year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Scotland]], the main sex education program is ''Healthy Respect'', which focuses not only on the biological aspects of reproduction but also on relationships and emotions. Education about [[Birth control|contraception]] and [[sexually transmitted diseases]] are included in the program as a way of encouraging good sexual health. In response to a refusal by Catholic schools to commit to the program, however, a separate sex education program has been developed for use in those schools. Funded by the [[Scottish Government]], the program ''Call to Love'' focuses on encouraging children to delay sex until marriage, and does not cover contraception, and as such is a form of [[abstinence-only sex education]].{{Fact|date=December 2007}}

===United States=== 
{{see also|Adolescent sexuality in the United States | Abstinence-only sex education}}
Almost all U.S. students receive some form of sex education at least once between grades 7 and 12; many schools begin addressing some topics as early as grades 5 or 6.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|coauthors=David J. Landry, Susheela Singh and Jacqueline E. Darroch |year=2000 |month=September/October |title=Sexuality Education in Fifth and Sixth Grades in U.S. Public Schools, 1999 |journal=Family Planning Perspectices |volume=32 |issue=5 |pages= |id= |url=http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/journals/3221200.html |accessdate=2007-05-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, what students learn varies widely, because curriculum decisions are so decentralized. Many states have laws governing what is taught in sex education classes or allowing parents to opt out. Some state laws leave curriculum decisions to individual school districts.&lt;ref name="Kaiser 2002"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kff.org/youthhivstds/upload/Sex-Education-in-the-U-S-Policy-and-Politics.pdf |title=Sex Education in the U.S.: Policy and Politics |accessdate=2007-05-23 |year=2002 |month=October |format=PDF |work=Issue Update |publisher=Kaiser Family Foundation }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

For example, a 1999 study by the [[Guttmacher Institute]] found that most U.S. sex education courses in grades 7 through 12 cover puberty, [[HIV]], [[Sexually Transmitted Infection|STI]]s, [[abstinence]], implications of teenage [[pregnancy]], and how to resist peer pressure. Other studied topics, such as methods of [[birth control]] and infection prevention, [[sexual orientation]], [[sexual abuse]], and factual and ethical information about [[abortion]], varied more widely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |coauthors=Jacqueline E. Darroch, David J. Landry and Susheela Singh |year=2000 |month=September/October |title=Changing Emphases in Sexuality Education In U.S. Public Secondary Schools, 1988-1999  |journal=Family Planning Perspectives |volume=32 |issue=6 |url=http://www.guttmacher.org/tables/3220400t.html#t3 }} See especially Table 3.&lt;/ref&gt;  

Two main forms of sex education are taught in American schools: comprehensive and [[Abstinence-only sex education| abstinence-only]]. Comprehensive sex education covers abstinence as a positive choice, but also teaches about contraception and avoidance of STIs when sexually active. A 2002 study conducted by the [[Kaiser Family Foundation]] found that 58% of secondary school principals describe their sex education curriculum as comprehensive.&lt;ref name="Kaiser 2002"/&gt;

Abstinence-only sex education tells teenagers that they should be sexually abstinent until marriage and does not provide information about contraception. In the Kaiser study, 34% of high-school principals said their school's main message was abstinence-only.

The federal government plays a large role in which form of sex education is taught in public schools. In 1996, Congress passed a law to fund abstinence-only sex education. The federal government only funds abstinence-only sex education.

The difference between these two approaches, and their impact on teen behavior, remains a controversial subject in the U.S. Teenage birth rates had been dropping in the U.S. since 1991, but a 2007 report showed 3% increase from 2005 to 2006.&lt;ref name="CDC"&gt;{{cite press release |title=Teen Birth Rate Rises for First Time in 14 Years |publisher=CDC National Center for Health Statistics |date=2007-12-05 |url=http://www.cdc.gov/od/oc/media/pressrel/2007/r071205.htm |accessdate=2007-12-05 |quote=The report shows that between 2005 and 2006, the birth rate for teenagers aged 15-19 rose 3 percent, from 40.5 live births per 1,000 females aged 15-19 in 2005 to 41.9 births per 1,000 in 2006. This follows a 14-year downward trend in which the teen birth rate fell by 34 percent from its all-time peak of 61.8 births per 1,000 in 1991.}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 1991 to 2005, the percentage of teens reporting that they had ever had sex or were currently sexually active showed small declines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cdc.gov/HealthyYouth/YRBS/pdf/trends/2005_YRBS_Sexual_Behaviors.pdf |title=National Youth Risk Behavior Survey: 1991-2005 |accessdate=2007-05-25 | format=PDF |publisher=U.S. Department of Health and Human Services: Centers for Control and Prevention}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the U.S. still has the highest teen birth rate and one of the highest rates of STIs among teens in the industrialized world.&lt;ref name="Advocates for Youth" /&gt; Public opinion polls conducted over the years have found that the vast majority of Americans favor broader sex education programs over those that teach only abstinence, although abstinence educators recently published poll data with the opposite conclusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/tgr/04/1/gr040109.html |title=Sex Education: Politicians, Parents, Teachers and Teens |accessdate=2007-05-23 |last=Dailard |first=Cynthia |year=2001 |month=February |work=The Guttmacher Report on Public Policy |publisher=Guttmacher Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.siecus.org/policy/public_support.pdf |title=On Our Side: Public Support for Comprehensive Sexuality Education |accessdate=2007-05-23 |format=Fact Sheet |work=SIECUS }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.abstinenceassociation.org/newsroom/050307_zogby_key_findings.html |title=NAEA Executive Summary of Key Findings |accessdate=2007-05-24 |date=2007-05-03 |work=National Abstinence Education Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Proponents of comprehensive sex education, which include the [[American Psychological Association]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apa.org/releases/sexeducation.html Comprehensive Sex Education is More Effective at Stopping the Spread of HIV Infection&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; the [[American Medical Association]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ama-assn.org/apps/pf_new/pf_online?f_n=browse&amp;doc=policyfiles/HnE/H-170.968.HTM AMA Policy Finder - American Medical Association&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; the [[National Association of School Psychologists]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://nasponline.org/about_nasp/pospaper_sexed.aspx NASP Position Statement on Sexuality Education&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; the [[American Academy of Pediatrics]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/reprint/108/2/498 Sexuality Education for Children and Adolescents - Committee on Psychosocial Aspects of Child and Family Health and Committee on Adolescence 108 (2): 498 - Pediatrics&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; the [[American Public Health Association]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apha.org/advocacy/policy/policysearch/default.htm?id=1334 APHA: Policy Statement Database&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Society for Adolescent Medicine]]&lt;ref name="Adolescent Health"/&gt; and the [[American College Health Association]],&lt;ref name="Adolescent Health"&gt;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;ct=res&amp;cd=8&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.adolescenthealth.org%2FPositionPaper_Abstinence_only_edu_policies_and_programs.pdf&amp;ei=XpBYR8iOMpPs0AS50O35Cg&amp;usg=AFQjCNFxZwyxgsY99vfZ232IXgnvHRMPgQ&amp;sig2=SvcPtDT5aBQeYdHIudHmsg&lt;/ref&gt; argue that sexual behavior after puberty is a given, and it is therefore crucial to provide information about the risks and how they can be minimized; they also claim that denying teens such factual information leads to unwanted pregnancies and STIs. 

On the other hand, proponents of abstinence-only sex education object to curricula that fail to teach their standard of moral behavior; they maintain that a morality based on sex only within the bounds of marriage is "healthy and constructive" and that value-free knowledge of the body may lead to immoral, unhealthy, and harmful practices. Within the last decade, the federal government has encouraged abstinence-only education by steering over a billion dollars to such programs.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |url=http://legalmomentum.org/legalmomentum/programs/sexualityandfamilyrights/2006/09/federal_funding_for_abstinence_1.php |title=Abstinence-Only Programs: Harmful to Women &amp; Girls: Federal Funding for Abstinence-Only Programs | accessdate=2007-05-25 |publisher=Legal Momentum }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some 15 states now decline the funding so that they can continue to teach comprehensive sex education.&lt;ref&gt;States that decline abstinence-only funding include California, Colorado, Connecticut, Maine, Massachusetts, Minnesota, Montana, New Jersey, New Mexico, Pennsylvania, Ohio, Rhode Island, Virginia, Washington, and Wisconsin.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Maine Declines Federal Funds for Abstinence-Only Sex Education Programs, Says New Guidelines Prohibit 'Safe-Sex' Curriculum | url=http://www.medicalnewstoday.com/medicalnews.php?newsid=30992 |publisher=Medical News Today |date=2005-09-23 | accessdate=2007-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=P.J. |last=Huffstutter|title=States refraining from abstinence-only sex education |url=http://www.boston.com/news/nation/articles/2007/04/09/states_refraining_from_abstinence_only_sex_education/ |work=Boston Globe |publisher=Los Angeles Times |date=2007-04-09 |accessdate=2007-05-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.legalmomentum.org/legalmomentum/publications/OverviewofAbs.pdf |title=An Overview of Federal Abstinence-Only Funding |accessdate=2007-05-25 |publisher=Legal Momentum | format=PDF |year=2007 | month=February }}[http://www.legalmomentum.org/legalmomentum/publications/OverviewofAbs.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; Funding for one of the federal government's two main abstinency-only funding programs, Title V, was extended only until December 31, 2007; Congress is debating whether to continue it past that date.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Melissa |last=Mixon |title=Abstinence programs brace for major funding cut |url=http://www.statesman.com/news/content/news/stories/local/10/06/1006abstinence.html |publisher=Austin American-Statesman |date=2007-10-06 |accessdate=2007-10-17 }} 
&lt;/ref&gt;

The impact of the rise in abstinence-only education remains a question. To date, no published studies of abstinence-only programs have found consistent and significant program effects on delaying the onset of intercourse.&lt;ref name="Advocates for Youth"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.advocatesforyouth.org/publications/stateevaluations/index.htm |title=Five Years of Abstinence-Only-Until-Marriage Education: Assessing the Impact  |accessdate=2007-05-23 |last=Hauser |first=Debra |year=2004  |publisher=Advocates for Youth}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, a study ordered by the U.S. Congress found that middle school students who took part in abstinence-only sex education programs were just as likely to have sex (and use contraception) in their teenage years as those who did not.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Study: Abstinence programs no guarantee |url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/EDUCATION/04/13/abstinence.study.ap/index.html?eref=rss_education |work=CNN.com |publisher=Associated Press |date=[[2007-04-14]] |accessdate=2007-04-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Abstinence-only advocates claimed that the study was flawed because it was too narrow and  began when abstinence-only curricula were in their infancy, and that other studies have demonstrated positive effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | title =Mathematica Findings Too Narrow | publisher =National Abstinence Education Association | date= 2007-04-13 | url =http://www.abstinenceassociation.org/newsroom/pr_041307_mathematica.html | accessdate =2007-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Morality of sex education ==
One approach to sex education is to view it as necessary to reduce risk behaviours such as unprotected sex, and equip individuals to make informed decisions about their personal sexual activity. Additionally, some proponents and opponents of comprehensive sex education contend that education about homosexuality encourages tolerance and understanding that homosexuality isn't something that is wrong.

Another viewpoint on sex education, historically inspired by sexologists like [[Wilhelm Reich]] and psychologists like [[Sigmund Freud]] and [[James W. Prescott]], holds that what is at stake in sex education is control over the body and liberation from social control. Proponents of this view tend to see the political question as whether society or the individual should teach sexual [[mores]]. Sexual education may thus be seen as providing individuals with the knowledge necessary to liberate themselves from socially organized [[sexual oppression]] and to make up their own minds. In addition, sexual oppression may be viewed as socially harmful. 

To another group in the sex education debate, the question is whether the [[state]] or the [[family]] should teach sexual [[mores]]. They believe that sexual mores should be left to the family, and sex-education represents state interference. They claim that some sex education curricula break down pre-existing notions of [[modesty]] and encourage acceptance of practices that those advocating this viewpoint deem immoral, such as [[homosexuality]] and [[premarital sex]]. They cite web sites such as that of the [[Coalition for Positive Sexuality]] as examples. Naturally, those that believe that homosexuality and premarital sex are a normal part of the range of human sexuality disagree with them.

Many religions teach that sexual behavior outside of marriage is immoral, so their adherents feel that this morality should be taught as part of sex education. Other religious conservatives believe that sexual knowledge is unavoidable, hence their preference for curricula based on [[abstinence]].&lt;ref&gt;PBS, February 4, 2005 [http://www.pbs.org/wnet/religionandethics/week823/feature.html Religion &amp; Ethics Newsweekly, Episode 823] Accessed 2006-12-30&lt;/ref&gt;

==Lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender youth==
[[Image:Youth and his father.jpg|thumb|right|300px|'''Youth seeking his father's advice on love'''&lt;br&gt;From the ''Haft Awrang'' of [[Jami]], in the story ''A Father Advises his Son About Love.'' His counsel is to choose that lover who desires him for his inner beauty. ''See [[Pederasty#Sufi outlook|Sufi outlook on male love]]'' Freer and Sackler Galleries, [[Smithsonian Institution]], Washington, DC.]]

[[Lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexuality|bisexual]], [[transgender]], ([[LGBT]]) youth, and those with other sexual practices, are often ignored in sex education classes, including a frequent lack of discussion about safer sex practices for [[Mutual masturbation|manual]], [[oral sex|oral]], and [[anal sex]], despite these activities' different risk levels for [[sexually transmitted disease]]s.

Some people do not agree with comprehensive sexual education that references or discusses such practices, believing that including this additional information might be seen as encouraging homosexual behavior. Proponents of such comprehensive curricula hold that by excluding discussion of these issues or the issues of [[homosexuality]], [[bisexuality]], or [[transgender]]edness, feelings of isolation, loneliness, guilt and shame as well as [[depression (mood)|depression]] are made much worse for students who belong or believe they may belong to one of these categories, or are unsure of their sexual identity. Supporters of including [[LGBT]] issues as an integral part of comprehensive sexuality education argue that this information is still useful and relevant and reduces the likelihood of [[suicide]], sexually transmitted disease, 'acting out' and [[maladaptive]] behavior in these students. In the absence of such discussion, these youths are said to be ''de facto'' forced to remain in [[the closet]], while youths are left without guidance on dealing with their own possible same-gender attractions and with their LGBT classmates.

Supporters of comprehensive sex education programs argue that abstinence-only curricula (that advocate that youth should abstain from sex until marriage) ignore and marginalize lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender youth, who are often unable to [[same-sex marriage|marry]] a partner due to legal restrictions. Proponents of abstinence-only education often have a more conservative view of homosexuality and bisexuality and are against them being taught as normal, acceptable orientations or placed in equal footing to heterosexual acts/relations, and so they generally do not see this as a problem. Supporters of comprehensive programs feel that this is a major problem as it could lead [[LGBT]] youth to feel even more alienated and ashamed of their sexual orientation.

== Scientific study of sex education ==
The debate over [[teenage pregnancy]] and STDs has spurred some research into the effectiveness of different approaches to sex education. In a meta-analysis, DiCenso ''et al.'' have compared comprehensive sex education programs with abstinence-only programs.&lt;ref name=" DiCenso"&gt; DiCenso A. ''et al.'': [http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/324/7351/1426 Interventions to Reduce Unintended Pregnancies Among Adolescents]: [[Systematic review|Systematic Review]] of [[Randomized controlled trial|Randomized Controlled Trials]]. ''British Medical Journal'' 2002;324:1426. &lt;/ref&gt; Their review of several studies shows that abstinence-only programs did not reduce the likelihood of pregnancy of women who participated in the programs, but rather increased it. Four abstinence programs and one school program were associated with a pooled increase of 54% in the partners of men and 46% in women ([[confidence interval]] 95% 0.95 to 2.25 and 0.98 to 2.26 respectively). The researchers conclude:

:"''There is some evidence that prevention programs may need to begin much earlier than they do. In a recent [[systematic review]] of eight trials of [[day care]] for disadvantaged children under 5 years of age, long term follow up showed lower pregnancy rates among [[adolescent]]s. We need to investigate the social determinants of unintended pregnancy in adolescents through large longitudinal studies beginning early in life and use the results of the multivariate analyses to guide the design of prevention interventions. We should carefully examine countries with low pregnancy rates among adolescents. For example, the [[Netherlands]] has one of the lowest rates in the world (8.1 per 1000 young women aged 15 to 19 years), and ''Ketting &amp; Visser'' have published an analysis of associated factors.&lt;ref name=" Ketting"&gt;Ketting, E. &amp; Visser, A., ''Contraception in the Netherlands: the low abortion rate explained.'' Patient Education and Counseling 23 &lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, the rates are:
:* 93.0 per 1000 in the [[United States]] (85.8/1000 in 1996)
:* 62.6 per 1000 in [[England]] and [[Wales]]
:* 42.7 per 1000 in [[Canada]]
:* 15.1 per 1000 in [[Belgium]] (1996)&lt;ref name="ethesis"&gt;[http://www.ethesis.net/clb/clb.htm www.ethesis.net] {in Dutch) &lt;/ref&gt;

:''We should examine effective programs designed to prevent other high risk behaviors in adolescents. For example, Botvin ''et al.'' found that school based programs to prevent [[drug abuse]] during junior [[high school]] (ages 12–14 years) resulted in important and durable reductions in use of [[tobacco]], [[alcoholic beverage|alcohol]], and [[Cannabis (drug)|cannabis]] if they taught a combination of social resistance skills and general life skills, were properly implemented, and included at least two years of booster sessions.

: ''Few sexual health interventions are designed with input from adolescents. Adolescents have suggested that sex education should be more positive with less emphasis on [[anatomy]] and scare tactics; it should focus on [[negotiation]] [[skill]]s in sexual relationships and [[communication]]; and details of sexual health clinics should be advertised in areas that adolescents frequent (for example, school toilets, shopping centres)."&lt;ref name=" DiCenso"/&gt;

Also, a U.S. review, "Emerging Answers", by the National Campaign To Prevent Teenage Pregnancy examined 250 studies of sex education programs.&lt;ref name="Kirby"&gt;Douglas Kirby, Ph. D.: Emerging Answers: Research Findings on Programs to Reduce Teen Pregnancy. ''National Campaign to Prevent Teen Pregnancy, 2001.'' [http://www.teenpregnancy.org/resources/data/report_summaries/emerging_answers/default.asp Homepage of the study.]&lt;/ref&gt; The conclusion of this review was that "the overwhelming weight of evidence shows that sex education that discusses contraception does not increase sexual activity".

== See also == 
* [[About Your Sexuality]]
* [[Adolescent sexuality]]
* [[Facts of Life]]
* ''[[Harmful to Minors]]'', a book by [[Judith Levine]], which deals with [[sexual morality]] and sex education in the United States
* [[Harm reduction]]
* [[Our Whole Lives]]
* [[Permissive society]]
* [[Promiscuity]]
* [[Refusal skills]]
* [[Section 28]] (UK)
* [[Sex manual]]
* [[Sexual morality]]
* [[Sexual orientation]]
* [[Sexual revolution]]
* [[Social conservatism]]
* [[Teenage pregnancy]]
* [[The birds and the bees]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.siecus.org/ Sexuality Information and Education Council of the United States (SIECUS)]
*[http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/fb_sexEd2006.html Facts on Sex Education in the United States] From the Guttmacher Institute
*[http://www.teachers.tv/pshe Teachers' TV] Sex and relationship education site for schools
*[http://www.doinitright.org/ Doinitright.org] Place where teens can ask anonymous questions about sexual health
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/09/health/09virg.html Patterns of Deceit Raise Concerns About Teenage Sex Surveys] in ''[[The New York Times]]'', about [[virginity pledge]]s
*[http://www.unesco.org/courier/2000_07/uk/apprend2.htm The Dutch model] ''UNESCO Courier'' on the success of the Netherlands. 
*[http://www.nvsh.nl/english/index.htm Sex information website] by the "Nederlandse Vereniging voor Seksuele Hervorming" ([[Dutch Society for Sexual Reform]])
*[http://www.ruthinking.co.uk Sexwise] Sex information for teenagers in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] 
*[http://www.youth-policy.com Youth-Policy] Youth reproductive health and HIV/AIDS policy in developing countries
*[http://www2.rz.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/GUS/GUS_MAIN_INDEX.HTM Project Growing Up Sexually]
*Free [http://www.sexualityandu.ca/teachers/tools-9.aspx downloadable slide presentations] for teaching sexual education
*[http://www.teensource.org/ TeenSource.org] Sex education site for teens
*[http://sexetc.org/ Sex, Etc.] The national magazine and Web site written by teens, for teens, on sexual health issues. 
*[http://www.soc.ucsb.edu/sexinfo UCSB's SexInfo] A website where anyone can ask a question about sex. Also has many articles on sex related topics.
*[http://www.sexedlibrary.org The SexEdLibrary] A comprehensive resource for sexuality education teachers.
*[http://www.indypendent.org/?p=181 Sex and the CDC, The Indypendent]
*[http://www.thehealthyprostate.com/anatomy An example of sex education for adults using flash animation and video]
*[http://cdcnpin.org/scripts/news/NewsList.asp#49842 "No Matter the Approach, Sex Ed Works"]
*[http://hk101.org/content/view/32/26/ Sex ed needs a push] An article written by a journalism student in HK

{{Sex}}
{{Education by subject}}
{{Sexual ethics}}

[[Category:Education by subject]]
[[Category:Sex education]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]

[[cs:Sexuální výchova]]
[[da:Seksualoplysning]]
[[de:Sexuelle Aufklärung]]
[[el:Σεξουαλική διαπαιδαγώγηση]]
[[es:Educación sexual]]
[[fr:Éducation sexuelle]]
[[hi:यौन शिक्षा]]
[[it:Educazione sessuale]]
[[he:חינוך מיני]]
[[sw:Malezi ya kijinsia]]
[[mr:लैंगिक शिक्षण]]
[[ms:Pendidikan seks]]
[[nl:Relationele en seksuele vorming]]
[[ja:性教育]]
[[pl:Edukacja seksualna]]
[[ro:Educaţie sexuală]]
[[simple:Sex education]]
[[sk:Sexuálna výchova]]
[[sr:Сексуално образовање]]
[[fi:Seksuaalikasvatus]]
[[sv:Sex- och samlevnadsundervisning]]
[[ta:பாலியற் கல்வி]]
[[th:เพศศึกษา]]
[[zh:性教育]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>