<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061110101846|86913859" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="42327" pageid="42327" ns="0" title="Sex education"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-10T10:22:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Sex education''' is a broad term used to describe [[education]] about human [[sex organ|sexual anatomy]], [[sexual reproduction]], [[sexual intercourse]], and other aspects of [[human sexual behavior]].

== Overview ==
Education about reproduction typically describes the creation and development of a new human being, from [[Fertilisation|conception]] and the development of the [[embryo]] and [[fetus]], through to [[childbirth]]. It often includes topics such as [[sexually transmitted disease]]s (STDs) and how to avoid them, as well as [[birth control]] methods.

Although some form of sex education is part of the [[curriculum]] at many schools, it remains a [[controversy|controversial]] issue in several countries, particularly with regard to the age at which children should start receiving such education, the amount of detail which is revealed, and topics dealing with [[human sexuality]] and behavior (eg. [[safe sex]] practices and [[masturbation]], and [[sexual ethics]].

In the [[United States]] in particular, sex education raises much contentious debate. Chief among controversial points is whether covering [[child sexuality]] is valuable or detrimental; the use of birth control such as [[condom]]s and [[oral contraceptive]]s; and the impact of such use on pregnancy outside marriage, [[teenage pregnancy]], and the transmission of STDs. Increasing support for [[abstinence only sex education]] by conservative groups has been one the primary cause of this controversy. Countries with more conservative attitudes towards sex education (including the U.K. and the U.S.) have a higher incidence of STDs and teenage pregnancy.&lt;ref name="Joy of sex education"&gt;  [http://education.guardian.co.uk/schools/comment/story/0,,1214047,00.html "Joy of sex education" by George Monbiot], ''The Guardian'', 11 May 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

The existence of [[AIDS]] has given a new sense of urgency to the topic of sex education. In many [[Africa]]n nations, where AIDS is at epidemic levels (see [[HIV/AIDS in Africa]]), sex education is seen by most scientists as a vital [[public health]] strategy. Some international organizations such as [[Planned Parenthood]] consider that broad sex education programs have global benefits, such as controlling the risk of [[overpopulation]] and the advancement of [[women's rights]] (see also [[reproductive rights]]).

==Sex education worldwide==
===United States===
Almost 60% of adults think that sexually active teenagers should have easy access to [[contraception]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.teenpregnancy.org/genlfact.htm The National Campaign to Prevent Teen Pregnancy]&lt;/ref&gt;  A 1997 study found that about 48% of [[high school]] students are sexually active.

Some advocates have successfully worked toward the introduction of "[[abstinence]]-only" [[curriculum|curricula]].  Under such instruction, teens are told that they should be sexually abstinent until marriage, and information about contraception is not provided.  Opponents argue this approach denies teens needed, factual information and leads to unwanted pregnancies, [[abortions]], and propagation of STDs. 

Some curricula are advocated on the grounds that they are intended to reduce sexual disease or out-of-wedlock or teenage pregnancy, but no abstinence-only program has ever been shown to reduce teen sexual activity, pregnancy, or STDs. A curriculum ostensibly aimed at reducing pregnancy among high school students, which advocates the use of [[condom]]s, could potentially lower the pregnancy rate.  Proponents of this view argue that sexual behavior after puberty is a given, and it is therefore crucial to provide information about the risks and how they can be minimized.  They hold that conventional or [[social conservatism|conservative]] [[moral]]izing will only alienate students and thus weaken the message.

In turn, opponents of comprehensive sexuality education object that curricula which fail to teach moral behavior actually serve to prevent adolescents from making informed decisions; they maintain that curricula should include the claim that conventional (or conservative) morality is "healthy and constructive", and that value-free knowledge of the body may lead to immoral, unhealthy and harmful practices.

In December of 2004 [[Henry A. Waxman]], a United States Congressman from [[California]], released [http://www.democrats.reform.house.gov/Documents/20041201102153-50247.pdf a report] that provides several examples of inaccurate information being included in federally funded [[Abstinence only sex education|abstinence-only sex education]] programs.  This report bolstered the claims of those Americans arguing that abstinence-only programs deprive teenagers of critical information.

The [[August 29]]/[[September 5]], [[2005]], issue of ''[[The Nation (U.S. periodical)|The Nation]]'' reported that money from the [[Federal Government of the United States|Federal Government]] used to create [[high school]] abstinence clubs was being used to train "young abstinence advocates", who were being encouraged to engage in politics and support issues like overturning [[abortion]]. The article states that although the program's official language has been secularized, a list of its grant recipients "reads like a who's who list of the [[religious right]]."

===Europe===
In the [[United Kingdom]], sex education is compulsory in secondary school, but parents have the right to withdraw their children from lessons. The curriculum focuses on the reproductive system, fetal development, and the physical and emotional changes of adolescence, while information about contraception and safe sex is discretionary. Britain has the highest teenage pregnancy rate in Europe and sex education is a heated issue in government and media reports. In a 2000 study by the University of Brighton, many 14 to 15 year olds reported disappointment with the content of sex education lessons and felt that lack of confidentiality prevents teenagers from asking teachers about contraception. &lt;ref name=" britsexed "&gt;  [http://www.unesco.org/courier/2000_07/uk/apprend.htm Britain: Sex Education Under Fire] ''UNESCO Courier'' &lt;/ref&gt;. 

In [[Scotland]], the main sex education program is ''Healthy Respect'' which focuses not only on the biological aspects of reproduction but also on relationships and emotions.  Education about [[contraception]] and [[sexually transmitted diseases]] are included in the program as a way of encouraging good sexual health.  In response to a refusal by Catholic schools to commit to the program, however, a seperate sex education program has been developed for use in those schools.  Funded by the [[Scottish Executive]], the program ''Call to Love'' focuses on encouraging children to delay sex until marriage, and does not cover contraception, and as such is a form of [[abstinence only sex education]].

In [[France]], sex education has been part of school curricula since 1973. Schools are expected to provide 30 to 40 hours of sex education, and pass out condoms, to students in grades eight and nine. In January 2000, the French government launched an information campaign on contraception with TV and radio spots and the distribution of five million leaflets on contraception to high school students. &lt;ref name=" britsexed "/&gt;

In [[Germany]], sex education has been part of school curricula since 1970. It normally covers all subjects concerning the growing-up process, the changing of the body, emotions, the biological process of reproduction, sexual activity, partnership, homosexuality,unwanted pregnancies and the complications of abortion, the dangers of sexual violence, child abuse, and sex-transmitted diseases, but sometimes also things like sex-positions. Most schools offer courses on the correct usage of contraception. There are also other medias of sex education, in first place the youth magazine "Bravo" wich always contains a topic where teenagers pose questions about partnership and sexuality.

Subsidised by the [[Netherlands|Dutch]] government, the “Lang leve de liefde” (“Long Live Love”) package, developed in the late 1980s, aims to give teenagers the skills to take their own decisions regarding health and sexuality. Nearly all secondary schools provide sex education as part of biology classes and over half of primary schools discuss sexuality and contraception. The curriculum focuses on biological aspects of reproduction as well as on values, attitudes, communication and negotiation skills. The media has encouraged open dialogue and the health-care system guarantees confidentiality and a non-judgmental approach. The Netherlands has one of the lowest teenage pregnancy rates in the world, and the Dutch approach is often seen as a model for other countries. &lt;ref name="dutchmodel"&gt; *[http://www.unesco.org/courier/2000_07/uk/apprend2.htm The Dutch model] ''UNESCO Courier'' &lt;/ref&gt;

=== Asia===
The state of sex education programs in Asia is at various stages of development. [[Indonesia]], [[Mongolia]], [[South Korea]] and [[Sri Lanka]] have a systematic policy framework for teaching about sex within schools. [[Malaysia]], the [[Philippines]] and [[Thailand]] have assessed adolescent reproductive health needs with a view to developing adolescent-specific training, messages and materials. [[India]] has programs specifically aimed at female adolescents. [[Bangladesh]], [[Myanmar]], [[Nepal]] and [[Pakistan]] have no coordinated sex education programs. &lt;ref name="escap"&gt; [http://www.unescap.org/esid/psis/population/icpd/sec7.asp Adolescents In Changing Times: Issues And Perspectives For Adolescent Reproductive Health In The ESCAP Region] United Nations Social and Economic Commission for Asia and the Pacific &lt;/ref&gt;

The [[International Planned Parenthood Federation]] and the [[BBC World Service]] ran a 12-part series known as Sexwise, which discussed sex education, family life education, contraception and parenting. It was first launched in South Asia and then extended worldwide. &lt;ref name="sexwise"&gt; [http://www.unesco.org/courier/2000_07/uk/apprend3.htm Involve The Young!] Interview with Dr Pramilla Senanayake, assistant director-general of the International Planned Parenthood Federation &lt;/ref&gt;

=== Africa===
Sex education in Africa has focused on stemming the growing [[HIV/AIDS in Africa|AIDS epidemic]]. Most governments in the region have established AIDS education programs in partnership with the [[World Health Organization]] and international [[Non-governmental organization|NGO]]s. These programs commonly teach the 'ABC' of HIV prevention: a combination of abstinence (A), fidelity to your partner (Be faithful) and condom use (C). (See [[Abstinence, be faithful, use a condom]].) The efforts of these educational campaigns appear now to be bearing fruit. In [[Uganda]], condom use has increased, youths are delaying the age at which sexual intercourse first occurs, and overall rates of HIV infection have been going down. &lt;ref name="uganda"&gt; [http://www.who.int/inf-new/aids2.htm Uganda reverses the tide of HIV/AIDS]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Morality of sex education ==
One approach to sex education is to view it as necessary to reduce risk behaviours such as unprotected sex, and equip individuals to make informed decisions about their personal sexual activity.  Additionally, some proponents of comprehensive sex education contend that education about homosexuality encourages tolerance and understanding that homosexuality isn't something that is wrong.  

Another viewpoint on sex education, historically inspired by sexologists like [[Wilhelm Reich]] and psychologists like [[Sigmund Freud]] and [[James W. Prescott]], holds that what is at stake in sex education is control over the body and liberation from social control.  Proponents of this view tend to see the political question as whether society or the individual should teach sexual [[mores]]. Sexual education may thus be seen as providing individuals with the knowledge necessary to liberate themselves from socially organized [[sexual oppression]] and to make up their own minds.  In addition, sexual oppression may be viewed as socially harmful.  

To another group in the sex education debate, the political question is whether the [[state]] or the [[family]] should teach sexual mores.  They believe that sexual mores should be left to the family, and sex-education represents state interference.  They claim that some sex education curricula break down pre-existing notions of [[modesty]] and encourage acceptance of practices that those advocating this viewpoint deem immoral, such as [[homosexuality]] and [[premarital sex]].  They cite web sites such as that of the [[Coalition for Positive Sexuality]] as examples.  Naturally, those that believe that homosexuality and premarital sex are a normal part of the range of human sexuality disagree with them.

Many religious conservatives believe that sexuality is a subject that should not be taught at all.  They believe that the longer a teenager is kept unaware of sexuality, the less likely they will become involved in sexual behavior.  Conservative religions believe that sexual behavior outside of marriage is immoral.

Other religious conservatives believe that sexual knowledge is unavoidable, and so desire to teach curricula based on [[abstinence]].

Some believe that when a person explains sexual matters to a teenager without a formal education program and without consent from the parents that it is inappropriate, and may in some cases be interpreted as [[child grooming]].

==Lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender youth==
[[Image:Youth and his father.jpg|thumb|right|300px|'''Youth seeking his father's advice on love'''&lt;br&gt;From the ''Haft Awrang'' of [[Jami]], in the story ''A Father Advises his Son About Love.'' His counsel is to choose that lover who desires him for his inner beauty. ''See [[Pederasty#Sufi outlook|Sufi outlook on male love]]'' Freer and Sackler Galleries, [[Smithsonian Institution]], Washington, DC.]]

[[Lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexuality|bisexual]], and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) youth are often ignored in sex education classes, including a frequent lack of discussion about safer sex practices for [[Mutual masturbation|manual]], [[oral sex|oral]], and [[anal sex]], despite these activities' different risk levels for [[sexually transmitted disease]]s.  

Some people do not agree with comprehensive sexual education that references or discusses such practices, believing that including this additional information might be seen as 'encouraging homosexual behavior'. Proponents of such comprehensive curricula hold that by excluding discussion of these issues or the issues of [[homosexuality]], [[bisexuality]], or [[transgender]]edness, feelings of isolation, loneliness, guilt and shame as well as [[depression (mood)|depression]] are made much worse for students who belong or believe they may belong to one of these categories, or are unsure of their sexual identity.  Supporters of including [[LGBT]] issues as an integral part of comprehensive sexuality education argue that this information is still useful and relevant and reduces the likelihood of [[suicide]], sexually transmitted disease, 'acting out' and [[maladaptive]] behavior in these students.  In the absence of such discussion, these youths are said to be ''de facto'' forced to remain in [[the closet]], while youths are left without guidance on dealing with their own possible same-gender attractions and with their LGB and Transgender classmates.

Supporters of comprehensive sex education programs argue that abstinence-only curricula (that advocate that youth should abstain from sex until marriage) ignore and marginalize lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender youth, who are often unable to [[same-sex marriage|marry]] a partner due to legal restrictions.  Proponents of abstinence-only education often have a more conservative view of homosexuality and bisexuality and are against them being taught as normal, acceptable orientations, or placed in equal footing to heterosexual acts/relations, and so they generally do not see this as a problem.

== Scientific study of sex education ==
The debate over [[teenage pregnancy]] and STDs has spurred some research into the effectiveness of different approaches to sex education.  In a meta-analysis, DiCenso et al. have compared comprehensive sex education programs with abstinence-only programs. &lt;ref name=" DiCenso"&gt; DiCenso A. et al.: [http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/324/7351/1426 Interventions to Reduce Unintended Pregnancies Among Adolescents]: [[Systematic review|Systematic Review]] of [[Randomized controlled trial|Randomized Controlled Trials]]. ''British Medical Journal'' 2002;324:1426. &lt;/ref&gt;
Their review of several studies shows that abstinence-only programs not only did not reduce the likelihood of pregnancy of women who participated in the programs, but that 'abstinence- only' actually ''increased'' it.  Four abstinence programs and one school program were associated with a pooled increase of 54% in the partners of men and 46% in women ([[confidence interval]] 95% 0.95 to 2.25 and 0.98 to 2.26 respectively).  The researchers conclude:

:"''There is some evidence that prevention programs may need to begin much earlier than they do.  In a recent [[systematic review]] of eight trials of [[day care]] for disadvantaged children under 5 years of age, long term follow up showed lower pregnancy rates among [[adolescent]]s.  We need to investigate the social determinants of unintended pregnancy in adolescents through large longitudinal studies beginning early in life and use the results of the multivariate analyses to guide the design of prevention interventions.  We should carefully examine countries with low pregnancy rates among adolescents.  For example, the [[Netherlands]] has one of the lowest rates in the world (8.1 per 1000 young women aged 15 to 19 years), and ''Ketting &amp; Visser'' have published an analysis of associated factors.&lt;ref name=" Ketting"&gt;Ketting, E. &amp; Visser, A., ''Contraception in the Netherlands: the low abortion rate explained.'' Patient Education and Counseling 23 &lt;/ref&gt;  In contrast, the rates are:
:* 93.0 per 1000 in the [[United States]] (85.8/1000 in 1996)
:* 62.6 per 1000 in [[England]] and [[Wales]], and
:* 42.7 per 1000 in [[Canada]]
:* 15.1 per 1000 in [[Belgium]] (1996)&lt;ref name="ethesis"&gt;[http://www.ethesis.net/clb/clb.htm www.ethesis.net] {in Dutch) &lt;/ref&gt;

:''We should examine effective programs designed to prevent other high risk behaviors in adolescents.  For example, Botvin et al. found that school based programs to prevent [[drug abuse]] during junior [[high school]] (ages 12-14 years) resulted in important and durable reductions in use of [[tobacco]], [[alcoholic beverage|alcohol]], and [[marijuana]] if they taught a combination of social resistance skills and general life skills, were properly implemented, and included at least two years of booster sessions.

: ''Few sexual health interventions are designed with input from adolescents.  Adolescents have suggested that sex education should be more positive with less emphasis on [[anatomy]] and scare tactics; it should focus on [[negotiation]] [[skill]]s in sexual relationships and [[communication]]; and details of sexual health clinics should be advertised in areas that adolescents frequent (for example, school toilets, shopping centres)."&lt;ref name=" DiCenso"/&gt;

Also, in answer to the criticism of conservatives, a US review, "Emerging Answers", by the National Campaign To Prevent Teenage Pregnancy examined 250 studies of sex education programs.&lt;ref name="Kirby"&gt;Douglas Kirby, Ph.D.: Emerging Answers: Research Findings on Programs to Reduce Teen Pregnancy. ''National Campaign to Prevent Teen Pregnancy, 2001.'' [http://www.teenpregnancy.org/resources/data/report_summaries/emerging_answers/default.asp Homepage of the study.]&lt;/ref&gt; The conclusion of this review was that "the overwhelming weight of evidence shows that sex education that discusses contraception does not increase sexual activity".  Regarding abstinence-only programs, the summary notes:

:"''Emerging Answers'' says that the jury is still out about the effectiveness of abstinence-only programs.  That is, current evidence about the success of these programs is inconclusive.  This is due, in part, to the very limited number of high-quality evaluations of abstinence-only programs available and because the few studies that have been completed do not reflect the great diversity of abstinence-only programs currently offered.  However, the early evidence about abstinence-only programs is not encouraging.  Fortunately there is currently a high-quality, federally funded evaluation of abstinence-only programs under way which should offer more definitive results soon."

There is a movement separate from school-based programs to encourage sexual abstinence; [[scientific]] [[research]] on these programs indicates decreased use of contraceptives among participants who become sexually active (see [[sexual abstinence]]).

Recently a tool called [[MyBlackBook|VDNote]] was released - part of [[MyBlackBook]], which is the Internet's first secure and confidential on-line sexual history tracker.  The service was developed to help combat the spread of sexually transmitted diseases, by promoting safe sex.  The VDNote tool analyzes the user's account - giving them the probability of obtaining a [[sexually transmitted disease]] based on their entries and account.

== See also == 
* [[About Your Sexuality]]
* [[Facts of Life]]
* ''[[Harmful to Minors]]'', a book by [[Judith Levine]] which deals with [[sexual morality]] and sex education in the United States
* [[Harm reduction]]
* [[Permissive society]]
* [[Promiscuity]]
* [[Refusal skills]]
* [[Section 28]] (UK)
* [[Sexual morality]]
* [[Sexual orientation]]
* [[Sexual revolution]]
* [[Social conservatism]]
* [[Teenage pregnancy]]
* [[The birds and the bees]]

==References==
*[http://www.nvsh.nl/english/index.htm Sex information website] by the "Nederlandse Vereniging voor Seksuele Hervorming" ([[Dutch Society for Sexual Reform]])

==Notes==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.doinitright.org/ Doinitright.org] Place where teens can ask anonymous questions about sexual health
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/09/health/09virg.html Patterns of Deceit Raise Concerns About Teenage Sex Surveys] in ''[[The New York Times]]'', about false [[virginity pledge]]s  (available for a fee, only)
*[http://www.unesco.org/courier/2000_07/uk/apprend2.htm The Dutch model] ''UNESCO Courier'' on the success of the Netherlands. 
*[http://www.leliathomas.com/2005/07/08/sex-aids-and-the-pursuit-of-happiness/ Sex, AIDS, and the Pursuit of Happiness]
*[http://www.ruthinking.co.uk Sexwise] Sex information for teenagers in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] 
*[http://www.youth-policy.com Youth-Policy] Youth reproductive health and HIV/AIDS policy in developing countries
*[http://www2.rz.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/GUS/GUS_MAIN_INDEX.HTM Project Growing Up Sexually]
*[http://www.teensource.org/ TeenSource] California site for teens
*[http://sxetc.org/ Sex Etc] Sex resource guide for teens

[[Category:Education by subject]]
[[Category:Sex education| ]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]

[[cs:Sexuální výchova]]
[[da:Seksualoplysning]]
[[de:Sexuelle Aufklärung]]
[[es:Educación Sexual]]
[[fr:Éducation sexuelle]]
[[he:חינוך מיני]]
[[nl:Seksuele voorlichting]]
[[ja:性教育]]
[[simple:Sex education]]
[[zh:性教育]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>