<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20150915085638|681120241" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="32581021" pageid="32581021" ns="0" title="Counter-jihad"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-08T15:35:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Globalize |date=April 2015 |discuss=Talk:Counterjihad#Globalize }}
{{Islamophobia}}
'''Counterjihad''' is a political current. 
It has been variously dubbed  [[Criticism of Islam|anti-Islamic]],&lt;ref name=svd.se&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.svd.se/kultur/understrecket/diffus-rorelse-med-muslimer-som-hatobjekt_6364272.svd|title=Diffus rörelse med muslimer som hatobjekt|work=Svenska Dagbladet|date=3 August 2011|accessdate=6 August 2011|language=sv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CBSNews&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-201_162-57432640/pentagon-suspends-counterjihad-class-on-islam/|title=Pentagon suspends "counterjihad" class on Islam|work=[[CBS News]]|date=11 May 2012|accessdate=3 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/apr/14/breivik-trial-norway-mass-murderer The Guardian: Far-right anti-Muslim network on rise globally as Breivik trial opens]&lt;/ref&gt; or [[islamophobia|islamophobic]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.svd.se/opinion/brannpunkt/risk-att-breivik-ses-som-profet_7065745.svd|title=Risk att Breivik ses som profet|work=Svenska Dagbladet|author=Anna-Lena Lodenius|language=sv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Mattias Wåg|url=http://www.goteborgsfria.se/artikel/89385| title=Den nya högerextremismens terroristiska uttryck|newspaper=Göteborgs fria|date=28 Jul 2011|language=sv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Denes/&gt; or [[Far-right politics|far-right]].&lt;ref name=svd.se/&gt;&lt;ref name=Denes&gt;{{cite journal|last=Denes|first=Nick|title=Welcome to the Counterjihad: "Uncivil" Networks and European Social Space|journal=Dahrendorf Symposia Series|volume=2012-12|publisher=Dahrendorf Symposia|location=Berlin|year=2012|url=http://www.dahrendorf-symposium.eu/fileadmin/Content_Images/Papers/Dahrendorf_Symposia_Series/DSS_12.pdf|accessdate=2012-08-26|doi=10.1080/17448689.2012.738894}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alexander Meleagrou-Hitchens, Hans Brun, ''[http://icsr.info/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/ICSR-ECJM-Report_Online.pdf A Neo-Nationalist Network: The English Defence League and Europe’s Counter-Jihad Movement]'', [[The International Centre for the Study of Radicalisation and Political Violence|International Centre for the Study of Radicalisation and Political Violence]], March 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;  
The roots of the movement go back to the 1980s, but it did not gain significant momentum until after the [[September 11 attacks]].&lt;ref name=tnyt1/&gt;

==Counter-jihad ideology==
In the words of Toby Archer, a scholar of political extremism and terrorism, &lt;blockquote&gt;"Counter-jihad discourse mixes valid concerns about [[Islamic terrorism|jihad-inspired terrorism]] with far more complex political issues about immigration to Europe from predominantly Muslim countries. It suggests that there is a threat not just from terrorism carried out by Islamic extremists but from Islam itself. Therefore, by extension, all European Muslims are a threat."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.rusi.org/publications/monitor/articles/keywords:counter-jihad/ref:A48A5851376CB9/|title=Countering the counter-jihad|first=Toby |last=Archer|date=15 August 2008|accessdate=28 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Arun Kundnani, in a report published by the International Centre for Counter-terrorism, writes that the counterjihad movement has evolved from earlier European far-right movements through a shift from race to values as identity markers: "In moving from neo‐Nazism to counter‐jihadism, the underlying structure of the narrative remains the same." Continuing on this note, he writes that comparing the counterjihadist worldview to the older, neo-nazi one, "Muslims have taken the place of blacks and multiculturalists are the new Jews."&lt;ref name=Kundnani&gt;{{cite web|author=Arun Kundnani|title=Blind Spot? Security Narratives and Far-Right Violence in Europe|publisher=[[International Centre for Counter-terrorism]]|format=pdf|url=http://www.icct.nl/download/file/ICCT-Kundnani-Blind-Spot-June-2012.pdf|date=June 2012|accessdate=July 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to prominent counterjihadist [[Edward S. May]], writing under the [[pseudonym]] Baron Bodissey, the counterjihadist movement is based on the belief that &lt;blockquote&gt;"Islam is above all a totalitarian political ideology, sugar-coated with the trappings of a primitive desert religion to help veil its true nature. The publicly stated goal of Islamic theology and political ideology is to impose the rule of Islam over the entire world, and make it part of Dar al-Islam, the 'House of Submission'."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://gatesofvienna.blogspot.com/2009/11/counterjihad-manifesto.html|title=The Counterjihad Manifesto|first=Baron|last=Bodissey|date=20 November 2009|accessdate=28 August 2011|work=[[Gates of Vienna]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; [[Cas Mudde]] argues that various [[conspiracy theories]] with roots in [[Bat Ye'Or]]'s [[Eurabia]] are important to the movement. The main theme of these theories is an allegation that European leaders allow a Muslim dominance of Europe, whether by intention or not, through multicultural policies and lax [[immigration laws]].&lt;ref name=MorgEur&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://morgenbladet.no/samfunn/2011/eurabiske_vers |title=Eurabiske vers |language=Norwegian |trans_title=Eurabian verses |publisher=[[Morgenbladet]] |date=August 19, 2011 |accessdate=April 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Hope not Hate]] counterjihad have largely replaced earlier neo-nazism and the traditional far right thus making their ideas more respectable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hopenothate.org.uk/counter-jihad/ Conter-Jihad Report]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:EDL6.jpg|thumb|300px|left|English Defence League rally in Newcastle, UK, 2010]]

[[Toby Archer]] detects a difference between the European and American wings of the movement. The American wing emphasizes an external threat, essentially terrorist in nature. The European wing sees a cultural threat to European traditions stemming from immigrant Muslim populations. While Archer notes that the perceived failure of multi-culturalism is shared across much of the political spectrum, he argues the counter-jihad movement is a particular conservative manifestation of this trend. He acknowledges the movement’s conservative defense of human rights and the rule of law but he believes by rejecting progressive policy it rejects much of what Europe is today.&lt;ref name="svd.se"/&gt;

The views of the counterjihad movement have been criticized as a source of support for the anti-Muslim views of individuals inspired to take violent direct action.&lt;ref name=tnyt2&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/25/us/25debate.html?pagewanted=1&amp;_r=3|title=Killings in Norway Spotlight Anti-Muslim Thought in U.S.|first=Scott |last=Shane|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=24 July 2011|accessdate=30 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anders Behring Breivik]], responsible for the [[2011 Norway attacks]], published a manifesto explaining his views which drew heavily on the work of counterjihad bloggers such as [[Fjordman]].&lt;ref name="tnyt1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="dsp"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/0,1518,776413,00.html|title=Blogging Hate - Anders Breivik's Roots in Right-Wing Populism|first=Frank |last=Patalong|work=[[Der Spiegel]]|date=25 July 2011|accessdate=30 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Daniel Pipes]] argues that a “close reading of his manifesto suggests” that Breivik wanted to discredit and undermine the counterjihad movement's dedication to democratic change to further Breivik’s “dreamed-for revolution” as the only alternative.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalreview.com/articles/272804/norway-s-terrorism-context-daniel-pipes|title=Norway’s Terrorism in Context: The damage Behring Breivik did to the counterjihad may well have been purposeful|last=Pipes|first=Daniel|publisher=National Review Online|date=July 27, 2011|accessdate=April 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bruce Bawer]] argues that the association of criticism of Islam with violence implies that  "to be opposed to jihad is, by definition, not only a bad but a downright dangerous thing."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://frontpagemag.com/2012/04/20/the-scandalous-lies-of-hope-not-hate/|last=Bawer|first=Bruce|date=April 20, 2012|title=The Scandalous Lies of ‘Hope Not Hate’}}&lt;/ref&gt; Breivik has later identified himself as a [[Fascism|fascist]] and voiced support for [[Neo-Nazism|neo-Nazis]], stating that he had exploited counterjihad rhetoric in order to protect "[[Ethnic nationalism|ethno-nationalists]]", and instead start a media drive against what he deemed "anti-nationalist counterjihad"-supporters.&lt;ref name="Expo14"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://expo.se/2014/breivik-vill-deportera-illojala-judar_6336.html|title=Breivik vill deportera "illojala judar" [Breivik wants to deport "disloyal Jews"]|work=[[Expo (magazine)|Expo]]|date=10 January 2014|language=Swedish|author=Daniel Vergara }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/09/05/us-norway-breivik-idUSKBN0H01NG20140905 "Mass killer Breivik says wants to create fascist party"]. ''Reuters''. Sep 5, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

Executive director of the [[Institute of Race Relations]], Liz Fekete, has argued that although most of the counter-jihad movement "stops short of advocating violence to achieve their goals", the most extreme parts share much of Breivik's discursive frameworks and vocabulary. She counterposits this with more mainstream counterjihadists, that warn of Islamisation as a result of naïvety or indecisiveness, whom she identifies as a source of legitimacy for the former.&lt;ref name=Fekete2012&gt;{{cite journal |last=Fekete |first=Liz |title=The Muslim conspiracy theory and the Oslo massacre |journal=Race &amp; Class |volume=53 |issue=3 |year=2012 |pages=30–47 |doi=10.1177/0306396811425984 |url=http://rac.sagepub.com/content/53/3/30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Theologist and philosopher Marius Timmann Mjaaland has described the [[Christianism|role]] given to [[Christianity]] in some parts of the counterjihad movement and has identified some aspects of the movement's ideology that he says links it to [[Christofascism|fascism-like]] conspiracy theories: 
#The establishment of an allegedly continuous and coherent connection between the present-day conflict between the Christian West and Muslims, whereas analyses based on established historical science will dismiss any such claim as unfounded.
#A claim that mainstream politicians and media in Western countries have in effect become internal enemies or "traitors", by respectively allowing the creation of [[Multiculturalism|multicultural]] societies and advocating "marxism" and "political correctness".
#This, in turn, has allowed Muslims to settle in Western lands, and thereby allegedly opened them to attack from within.
#And, lastly, a [[Friedrich Nietzsche|Nietzschean]], post-Christian worldview where the distinction between good and evil is given little attention, to the point where Christianity's ideal of "[[The Golden Rule|loving one's neighbour]]" is entirely omitted. Christianity is reduced from a system of belief to an identity marker, and a political mythology is built, that draws heavily on the [[crusades]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.aftenposten.no/meninger/kronikker/article4239821.ece|title=Korstog mot hellig krig (Crusade against Holy War)|first=Marius Timman |last=Mjaaland|work=[[Aftenposten]]|date=28 September 2011|accessdate=28 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Counterjihad movement has been compared to the [[anti-communism]] of the [[Cold War]]. [[Geert Wilders]], Dutch politician and speaker at Conterjihadi events, argues that Islam is a political ideology that, like [[Communism]], is a [[totalitarian]] threat to a liberal social order.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://frontpagemag.com/2010/geert-wilders/islam-the-communism-of-today/|title=Islam: the Communism of Today|author=Geert Wilders|date=Oct 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] compares both as similar exaggerated threats. “Like the communists that an earlier generation believed to be hiding behind every rock, infiltrated “Islamist” operatives today are said to be diabolically preparing for a forcible takeover.”&lt;ref name=SPLC&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/intelligence-report/browse-all-issues/2011/summer/the-anti-muslim-inner-circle ] The Anti-Muslim Inner Circle. By Robert Steinback| Intelligence Report| Summer 2011| Issue Number: 142&lt;/ref&gt;

The Cold War parallel is taken further by social commentator [[Bruce Bawer]]. He not only compares counterjihad with anti-communism but compares those who criticize the counterjihad movement with anti-anti-communists. The latter damned anti-Communists as “fanatical, paranoid conspiracy theorists” while “remaining all but silent about the evils of Communism itself.” Today it is fashionable to hold that “the good guys are the counter-counterjihadists – the journalists, activists, and others who make a career of slamming” counterjihadists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://frontpagemag.com/2013/bruce-bawer/notes-on-counterjihad/|title=Notes on ‘Counterjihad’|date=July 29, 2013|newspaper=Front Page Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; Author, [[Roger Kimball]], agrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://pjmedia.com/rogerkimball/2013/07/30/from-anti-communist-to-counter-jihadist/|title=From ‘Anti-Communist’ to ‘Counterjihadist’|date=July 30, 2013|author=Roger Kimball|newspaper=PJ Media}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization==
[[File:Paulbelien.jpg|thumb|300px|left|Paul Beliën, the editor of counterjihad blog The Brussels Journal]]

Blogs such as ''[[Jihad Watch]]'', ''[[Pamela Geller|Atlas Shrugs]]'', ''[[Politically Incorrect (Blog)|Politically Incorrect]]'', ''[[Gates of Vienna]]'' and ''[[The Brussels Journal]]'' are central to the counterjihad movement. Notable figures include the blogs' editors, respectively [[Robert Spencer (author)|Robert Spencer]], [[Pamela Geller]], [[Daniel Pipes]], Edward S. May and [[Paul Beliën]], as well as writers such as [[Bat Ye'or]], [[David Horowitz]] and [[Fjordman]].&lt;ref name=svd.se/&gt;&lt;ref name=tnyt1&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/31/opinion/sunday/the-rise-of-the-macro-nationalists.html|work=[[The New York Times]]|title=The Rise of the Macro-Nationalists|first=Thomas|last=Hegghammer|authorlink=Thomas Hegghammer|date=30 July 2011|accessdate=31 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=tnyt2 /&gt; Think tanks such as the [[International Free Press Society]] and the [[David Horowitz Freedom Center]] have had an important role in providing funds and establishing international links.&lt;ref name=Kundnani/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fekete2012/&gt; In time, a network of formal organisations has been established, with its main centers in Europe and the United States.&lt;ref name=Townsend&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/apr/14/breivik-trial-norway-mass-murderer|title=Far-right anti-Muslim network on rise globally as Breivik trial opens|publisher=The Guardian|date=April 14, 2012|accessdate=April 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Transatlantic relations|transatlantic]] [[umbrella organisations|umbrella organisation]] was established in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/01/20/idUS122494+20-Jan-2012+PRN20120120|work=[[Reuters]] (Press release)|title=Stop Islamization of Nations (SION) Calls on UN to Protect Christians of Syria|date=January 20, 2012|accessdate=April 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The International Free Press Society lists representatives from many parts of the counterjihad spectrum on its board of advisors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Anders Hvass|title=Lars Hedegaard ude af DF|language=Danish|trans_title=Lars Hedegaard leaves Danish People's Party|publisher=[[Berlingske tidene]]|url=http://www.b.dk/politik/lars-hedegaard-ude-af-df|accessdate=July 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Luban&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=45928|work=[[InterPress Service]]|title=Dutch Foe of Islam Ignores US Allies' Far Right Ties|first=Daniel |last=Luban|author2=Eli Clifton|date=28 February 2009|accessdate=28 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eurabia theorist Bat Ye'Or is on the board of advisors, while owner of the blog ''Gates of Vienna'', Edward S. May, serves as outreach co-ordinator on its board of directors.&lt;ref name="Luban"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Nick Lowles|title=International ‘Counter-Jihadist’ organisations - The International Free Press Society (IFPS) Network|publisher=[[Hope not hate]]|date=June 2012|url=http://www.hopenothate.org.uk/counter-jihad/organisations/Free-Press-Society|accessdate=July 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
The "Counter Jihad 2007" conference, which took place in Belgium, has been regarded as a crucial event in the movement's history.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2011/07/25/breivik_s_swamp?page=0,1|title=Breivik's swamp|first=Toby |last=Archer|date=25 July 2011|accessdate=28 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this first large conference, the [[Belgium|Belgian]], [[Flemish Movement|Flemish-nationalist]] party [[Vlaams Belang]] acted as host, allowing the conference access to the [[European parliament]] building as a venue.&lt;ref name=Luban/&gt; A March 2012 Counterjihad-conference in Denmark drew 200-300 supporters from throughout Europe. Ten times the number of left-wing protesters staged a counter-demonstration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=149759573|title=80 Arrested After Anti-Islam Protest In Denmark|publisher=Associated Press|date=March 31, 2012|accessdate=April 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2012 conference in Denmark, was alleged by its organisers, the [[English Defence League]] to mark the starting point of a pan-European movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://cphpost.dk/news/national/islam-debate-takes-centre-stage-aarhus|title=Islam debate takes centre stage in Aarhus|publisher=The Copenhagen Post|date=April 4, 2012|accessdate=April 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The umbrella organization, [[Stop Islamisation of Europe]], was founded by [[Anders Gravers Pedersen]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2011/07/23/uk-norway-killer-group-idUKTRE76M37M20110723 |title=Fringe group barred suspected Norway killer from forum |publisher=[[Reuters]] |date=July 23, 2011 |accessdate=April 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.dagbladet.no/2011/08/24/nyheter/anders_behring_breivik/innenriks/terrorangrepet/17803023/ |title=Her er Breiviks meningsfeller |language=Norwegian |trans_title=These are the people who share Breivik's opinions |publisher=[[Dagbladet]] |date=August 25, 2011 |accessdate=April 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.tv2nord.dk/artikel/121586:Krimi--Anders-Gravers-Pedersen-vaeltet-omkuld-under-demonstration |title=Anders Gravers Pedersen væltet omkuld under demonstration |language=Danish |trans_title=Anders Gravers Pedersen scuffled during demonstration|publisher=TV2 Nord |date=May 21, 2010 |accessdate=April 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; who also sits on the board of the Stop Islamisation of Nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/sion-to-hold-international-congress-and-media-workshop-to-address-islamic-supremacist-war-against-free-speech-142749465.html |title=SION to Hold International Congress and Media Workshop to Address Islamic Supremacist War Against Free Speech (Press Release) |publisher=PR Newswire |date=March 15, 2012 |accessdate=April 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are numerous affiliated "Stop the islamisation of..." and "Defense Leagues" in several European countries,&lt;ref name=Townsend/&gt; among them [[Stop Islamisation of Denmark]], [[Stop Islamisation of Norway]], and the English Defence League.

===United States===
[[File:Robert Spencer.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Robert Spencer, joint leader of Stop Islamization of America and editor of counterjihad blog Jihad Watch]]
The U.S.-based [[Stop Islamization of America]] (SIOA) is currently being led by Pamela Geller and Robert Spencer,&lt;ref name=MorgEur/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDB113CF933A25753C1A9669D8B63&amp;scp=3&amp;st=cse&amp;pagewanted=all |title=Outraged, And Outrageous |publisher=[[The New York Times]] |date=October 10, 2010 |accessdate=April 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a programme under their American Freedom Defense Initiative (AFDI). According to the AFDI website, the initiative aims, among other activities, to:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://freedomdefense.typepad.com/fdi/2011/07/american-freedom-defense-initiative-action-plan.html|title=American Freedom Defense Initiative Action Plan|author=[[Pamela Geller]]|date=July 31, 2011|accessdate=April 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Create state organizations that work towards the initiative's aims at a local level
* Organize grass root small groups at the local level to fight what it labels "specific Islamic supremacist initiatives" in American cities
* Build strategic alliances with activist groups in Europe and Israel to engage in open and stealthy counter jihad measures
* Promote candidates who "fight against the march of Islamic supremacists"
* Host conferences "that educate Americans about Leftist indoctrination and Islam’s quest for domination"

SIOA has been accused by the [[Anti-Defamation League]] of
&lt;blockquote&gt;promot[ing] a conspiratorial anti-Muslim agenda under the guise of fighting radical Islam. The group seeks to rouse public fears by consistently vilifying the Islamic faith and asserting the existence of an Islamic conspiracy to destroy "American" values.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adl.org/main_Extremism/sioa.htm|title=	
Backgrounder: Stop Islamization of America (SIOA)|publisher=[[Anti-Defamation League]]|date=March 25, 2011|accessdate=April 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col|colwidth=20em}}
*[[Counter-terrorism]]
*[[Islamofascism]]
*[[Islam and violence]]
*[[Islamic fundamentalism]]
*[[Jihad]]([[Jihadism|ism]])
*[[Persecution of Christians#Muslim world|Persecution of Christians in Muslim countries]]
*[[War against Islam]]
{{Div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

*{{cite thesis|type=Ph.D.|chapter=V|title=Warblog without end: online anti-Islamic discourses as persuadables |url=http://ir.uiowa.edu/etd/715/ |last=Munksgaard |first=Daniel Carl |year=2010 |publisher=The University of Iowa |accessdate=2012-08-26 }}

[[Category:Opposition to Islam in North America]]
[[Category:Opposition to Islam in Europe]]
[[Category:Criticism of Islam]]
[[Category:Offensive jihad]]
[[Category:Anti-Islam]]
[[Category:Far-right politics in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>