<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111108220336|459700514" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="32581021" pageid="32581021" ns="0" title="Counter-jihad"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-09T00:03:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Counterjihad''' is an [[Islamophobia|Islamophobic]], [[far-right]]&lt;ref name=svd.se&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.svd.se/kultur/understrecket/diffus-rorelse-med-muslimer-som-hatobjekt_6364272.svd|title=Diffus rörelse med muslimer som hatobjekt|work=Svenska Dagbladet|date=3 August 2011|accessdate=6 August 2011}} {{sv icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; intellectual&lt;ref name=tnyt1/&gt; political current. The roots of the movement goes back to the 1980s, but it did not gain significant momentum until after the [[September 11 attacks]].&lt;ref name=tnyt1/&gt;.

==Counter-jihad ideology==
In the words of Toby Archer, a scholar of political extremism and terrorism, "Counter-jihad discourse mixes valid concerns about jihad-inspired terrorism with far more complex political issues about immigration to Europe from predominantly Muslim countries. It suggests that there is a threat not just from terrorism carried out by Islamic extremists but from Islam itself. Therefore, by extension, all European Muslims are a threat."&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.rusi.org/publications/monitor/articles/keywords:counter-jihad/ref:A48A5851376CB9/|title=Countering the counter-jihad|first=Toby |last=Archer|date=15 August 2008|accessdate=28 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adherents to the movement frequently espouse the [[Eurabia]] [[conspiracy theory]]. According to prominent counterjihadist [[Edward S. May]], writing under the [[pseudonym]] Baron Bodissey, the counterjihadist movement is based on the belief that "Islam is above all a totalitarian political ideology, sugar-coated with the trappings of a primitive desert religion to help veil its true nature. The publicly stated goal of Islamic theology and political ideology is to impose the rule of Islam over the entire world, and make it part of Dar al-Islam, the 'House of Submission'."&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://gatesofvienna.blogspot.com/2009/11/counterjihad-manifesto.html|title=The Counterjihad Manifesto|first=Baron |last=Bodissey|coauthors=a.k.a. [[Ned May]]|date=20 November 2009|accessdate=28 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The views of the counterjihad movement have been criticized as a source of support for the anti-Islamist views of individuals inspired to take violent direct action.&lt;ref name=tnyt2&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/25/us/25debate.html?pagewanted=1&amp;_r=3|title=Killings in Norway Spotlight Anti-Muslim Thought in U.S.|first=Scott |last=Shane|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=24 July 2011|accessdate=30 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anders Behring Breivik]], responsible for the [[2011 Norway attacks]], published a manifesto explaining his views which drew heavily on the work of counterjihad bloggers such as [[Fjordman]].&lt;ref name=dsp&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/0,1518,776413,00.html|title=Blogging Hate - Anders Breivik's Roots in Right-Wing Populism|first=Frank |last=Patalong|work=[[Der Spiegel]]|date=25 July 2011|accessdate=30 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike the traditional far right, the movement's adherents generally reject neo-nazism and are strongly supportive of Israel, seeing it as the frontline in a '[[clash of civilizations]]' between the Islamic World and the west.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://maxblumenthal.com/2011/07/anders-behring-breivik-a-perfect-product-of-the-axis-of-islamophobia/|title=Anders Behring Breivik, a perfect product of the Axis of Islamophobia|first=Max |last=Blumenthal|work=Max Blumenthal|date=23 July 2011|accessdate=6 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Still, some analysts and advocacy groups focusing on far-right extremism consider prominent counterjihadists, such as Fjordman and [[Filip Dewinter]] to be [[fascism|fascist]]&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://oyvindstrommen.be/2011/08/05/journalist-resource-so-whats-the-deal-with-fjordman/|title=Journalist resource: So, what’s the deal with Fjordman?|first=Øyvind |last=Strømmen|date=5 August 2011|accessdate=28 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Nazism|nazi]]-apologetic,&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.blokwatch.be/content/view/440/1/lang,en/|title=Nazis and antisemites, the old friends of Filip Dewinter|first=Marc |last=Spruyt|date=29 May 2005|accessdate=28 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; respectively.

Theologist and philosopher Marius Timmann Mjaaland has described the role given to [[Christianity]] in some parts of the counterjihad movement and has identified three aspects of the movement's ideology that supposedly links it to fascism-like conspiracy theories: Firstly, the establishment of an allegedly continuous and coherent connection between the present-day conflict between the Christian West and Muslims, whereas analyses based on established historical science will dismiss any such claim as unfounded. Secondly, a claim that mainstream politicians and media in Western countries have in effect become internal enemies or "traitors", by respectively allowing the creation of [[Multiculturalism|multicultural]] societies and advocating "marxism" and "political correctness". This, in turn, has allowed Muslims to settle in Western lands, and thereby allegedly opened them to attack from within. And, lastly, a [[Friedrich Nietzsche|nietzscheian]], post-Christian worldview where the distinction between good and evil is given little attention, to the point where Christianity's ideal of "[[The Golden Rule|loving one's neighbour]]" is entirely omitted. Christianity is reduced from a system of belief to an identity marker, and a political mythology is built, that draws heavily on the [[Crusade|crusades]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.aftenposten.no/meninger/kronikker/article4239821.ece|title=Korstog mot hellig krig (Crusade against Holy War)|first=Marius Timman |last=Mjaaland|work=[[Aftenposten]]|date=28 September 2011|accessdate=28 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization==
Counterjihad as a movement is mainly Internet-based, and centers around blogs such as  ''[[Jihad Watch]]'', ''[[Pamela Geller|Atlas Shrugs]]'' and ''[[Gates of Vienna]]'' and ''[[The Brussels Journal]]''. Notable figures include the blogs' editors, respectively [[Robert Spencer]], [[Pamela Geller]], [[Edward S. May]] and [[Paul Beliën]], as well as writers such as [[Bat Ye'or]], [[David Horowitz]] and [[Fjordman]].&lt;ref name=svd.se/&gt;&lt;ref name=tnyt1&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/31/opinion/sunday/the-rise-of-the-macro-nationalists.html|work=[[The New York Times]]|title=The Rise of the Macro-Nationalists|first=Thomas|last=Hegghammer|date=30 July 2011|accessdate=31 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://ftpapp.app.com.pk/en_/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=145872&amp;Itemid=39|title=Norway killings put U.S. extremists in spotlight: Report |date=25 July 2011|accessdate=31 July 2011|location=New York|work=[[Associated Press of Pakistan]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, several conferences gathering European politicians, analysts and internet activists have taken place using the term as heading, and the "Counter Jihad 2007" conference, which took place in Belgium, has been regarded as a crucial event in the movement's history.&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2011/07/25/breivik_s_swamp?page=0,1|title=Breivik's swamp|first=Toby |last=Archer|date=25 July 2011|accessdate=28 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this first large conference, the [[Belgium|Belgian]], [[Flemish Movement|Flemish-nationalist]] party [[Vlaams Belang]] acted as host, allowing the conference access to the [[European parliament]] building as a venue.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=45928|work=[[InterPress Service]]|title=Dutch Foe of Islam Ignores US Allies' Far Right Ties|first=Daniel |last=Luban|coauthors=Eli Clifton|date=28 February 2009|accessdate=28 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==See also==
*[[Islamophobia]]
*[[Eurabia]]
*[[Stop Islamization of America]]
*[[Stop Islamisation of Europe]]
*[[English Defence League]]

[[Category:Criticism of Islam]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>