<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081112201127|251404139" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="158479" pageid="158479" ns="0" title="Reverse discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-12T20:11:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{globalize/USA}}
{{POV|date=January 2008}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Reverse Discrimination''' (also called "positive discrimination") is, in its simplest form&lt;ref&gt;Compact Oxford English Dictionary[http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/positivediscrimination?view=uk]&lt;/ref&gt;, the practice of favouring a historically disadvantaged group at the expense of members of a historically advantaged group. The term "reverse discrimination" reflects the fact that the group now ''being discriminated against'' had previously been the one doing the ''discriminating''.  The term is often used to describe the actual or perceived discriminatory effects of government policies (most notably [[affirmative action]]).

==In the United States==
In the United States, the term reverse discrimination has been used in past discussions of [[racial quota]]s for collegiate admission to government-run educational institutions. Such policies were held to be unconstitutional in the United States, while non-quota race preferences are legal. Harvard professor [[Roland G. Fryer Jr|Roland Fryer]], however, has argued that there is no logically tenable difference between "quotas" and "goals." &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/fryer/papers/fryer_loury_jepfinal.pdf Harvard Econ Department - Contact Info for Roland Fryer&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Reverse discrimination has been practised in the United States for several decades.{{Fact|date=July 2008}} The practice has been applied to university admissions, employment, and other situations.&lt;ref&gt;Encarta[http://encarta.msn.com/encnet/features/dictionary/DictionaryResults.aspx?refid=1861702027], Wordsmyth[http://www.wordsmyth.net/live/home.php?script=search&amp;matchent=reverse+discrimination&amp;matchtype=exact]&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Critics of affirmative action===

While the term is used in casual speech, many academic and expert opponents of racial or gender based affirmative action policies, such as [[Carl Cohen]], would avoid the term "reverse discrimination" on the grounds that "[[discrimination]] is discrimination" and that the label "reverse" is a misnomer.  Groups such as the American Civil Rights Institute, run by [[Ward Connerly]], have opted for the more legally precise terms "race preference", "gender preference," or "preferential treatment" generally, since these terms are contained and defined within existing [[civil rights]] law, such as the [[1964 Civil Rights Act]].

Cohen, who was a supporter of Michigan's Proposal 2 (see below), and other academics, have argued that the term "affirmative action" should be defined differently than "race preference," and that while socio-economically based or anti-discrimination types of affirmative action should be permissible, those that give preference to individuals based solely on their race or gender should not be permitted. Cohen also helped find evidence in 1996 through the Freedom of Information Act that led to the cases filed by Jennifer Gratz and Barbara Grutter against the [[University of Michigan]] for its undergraduate and law admissions policy, cases which were decided by the [[U.S. Supreme Court]] on [[June 23, 2003]].

Ward Connerly has promoted a series of ballot initiatives to remove "preferential treatment" in the states of California ([[California Proposition 209 (1996)]]), Washington (1998 - I-200), and Michigan (the [[Michigan Civil Rights Initiative]] - MCRI, or Proposal 2, 2006).

==In the United Kingdom==
In the UK, the term is usually related to university admissions or employee hiring. &lt;ref&gt;Encarta[http://encarta.msn.com/encnet/features/dictionary/DictionaryResults.aspx?refid=1861702027], Wordsmyth[http://www.wordsmyth.net/live/home.php?script=search&amp;matchent=reverse+discrimination&amp;matchtype=exact]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Expand-section|date=November 2008}}

==In India==
For example, in [[India]], the term is often used by citizens protesting against [[Reservation in India|reservation and quotas]].&lt;ref&gt;Devanesan Nesiah. ''Discrimination With Reason? The Policy of Reservations in the United States, India and Malaysia''. 1997. [[Oxford University Press]]. 0195639839.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindu.com/2006/10/24/stories/2006102401031300.htm  Excess reservation will cause reverse discrimination, cautions Supreme Court]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;R. Kent Greenawalt. ''Discrimination and Reverse Discrimination''. 1983. Knopf. ISBN 0394335775.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Expand-section|date=November 2008}}

==See also==
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Color blindness (race)]]
* [[Gender-blind]]
* [[White privilege]]

==References==
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://communities.homeoffice.gov.uk/raceandfaith/ UK Home Office Employment Targets]
*[http://www.cre.gov.uk/legal/rra_positive.html Positive action in employment] under the UK [[Race Relations Act]]
*[http://www.discriminations.us/ John Rosenberg's Discriminations], 
*[http://www.adversity.net Tim Fay's Adversity.net],
*[http://www.chetlyzarko.com/b2evolution/index.php Chetly Zarko's Power, Politics, &amp; Money].

[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[bg:Позитивна дискриминация]]
[[ja:逆差別]]
[[sv:omvänd diskriminering]]
[[zh:逆向歧視]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>