<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051021005613|26057187" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="158479" pageid="158479" ns="0" title="Reverse discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-21T01:07:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__
'''Reverse discrimination''' is a term used to describe [[discrimination|discriminatory]] policies or acts that benefit a historically sociopolitically nondominant group (typically [[minorities]]), rather than the historically sociopolitically dominant group.

The term "reverse discrimination" is sometimes considered synonymous with the terms '''[[affirmative action]]''' and '''positive discrimination'''.  Some countries, such as the [[United Kingdom]], use the term "reverse discrimination" to describe the policies termed "affirmative action" in other countries, such as the [[US]].
==History==
In the late [[20th century]], as numerous societies and countries began to believe that both contemporary and historic discrimination had resulted in an unfair and unjust social structure, some [[government]]s and [[company|companies]] instituted policies intended to redress this imbalance. Some minority advocacy groups argued that reversal policies were needed. The most widespread of such policies is known as [[affirmative action]].

==Effects and criticism==
Proponents of such policies argue that they bring about a closer equality of opportunities among groups by creating an increase in opportunities for historically disadvantaged groups.  The line defining [[protected groups]] is not always simple, with some historically disadvantaged groups, such as some groups of [[Asian Americans]], as well as poor [[European Americans]], possibly being disadvantaged by reverse discrimination policies.[[model minority|&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;]]  Critics of reverse discrimination, typically in the politically and socially dominant groups, believe proponents take a situational stand where a [[principles|principled]] stand is more appropriate, arguing that the practice replaces one form of discrimination with another.  As a form of discrimination, reverse discrimination is considered illegal in some countries, such as the United Kingdom. 

Examples of the effects can be seen in both the job market and college admissions. With quotas of minorities to fill, it may be necessary for the common sociopolitical groups to be passed over in certain circumstances to select a candidate solely due to their sociopolitical background. It is worth noting that [[Racial quota|racial quotas]] for collegiate admission are illegal and unconstitutional in the United States, by decision of the supreme court case [[Regents of the University of California v. Bakke]]

==Criticism of the term itself==
The term ''reverse discrimination'' has been criticized as casting affirmative action in a negative light, without due consideration of its aims.  It is also criticized as being politically charged.

Using "reverse" or "positive" as qualifiers has been criticized as diminishing the significance of this kind of discrimination, since it seems to imply a special status for "ordinary" discrimination against women and minorities.

==See also==
===Discrimination===
*[[Discrimination]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Sexism]]
===Counter-discrimination===
*[[Anti-racism]]
*[[Affirmative action]]
*[[Racial quota]]
===Cases involving counter-discriminatory practices===
*[[Bakke case]]
*''[[Grutter v. Bollinger]]''
===Miscellaneous===
*[[Model minority]] - A minority group that&amp;#8217;s highly successful despite a history of discrimination (e.g. Asian Americans)
* [[Race and intelligence]]
* [[Affirmative action bake sale]] &amp;#8211; A critical bake sale organized on college campuses demonstrating "affirmative action pricing structures."

==External links==
*[http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/comrace/race/employment.html UK Home Office Employment Targets]

[[ja:逆差別]]
[[sv:omvänd diskriminering]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>