<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071101120741|168491820" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="158479" pageid="158479" ns="0" title="Reverse discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-01T15:42:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=January 2007}}
{{Expand|date=January 2007}}
{{Discrimination}}
'''Reverse discrimination''' is a term that is used to describe policies or acts that are seen to benefit a historically socio-politically non-dominant group, at the expense of a historically socio-politically dominant group.

For example, in [[India]], the term is often used by the citizens protesting against [[Reservation in India|reservation and quotas]]. In [[China]], minorities are exempted from [[One Child Policy]].{{Fact|date=August 2007}}

In the United States, it has been used in discussions of [[racial quota]]s for collegiate admission to government-run educational institutions. Such policies were held to be unconstitutional in the United States, while non-quota race preferences are legal. Harvard professor [[Roland G. Fryer Jr|Roland Fryer]], however, has argued that there is no logically tenable difference between "quotas" and "goals." &lt;ref&gt;http://www.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/fryer/papers/fryer_loury_jepfinal.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The term has also been used in discussions about the practice of specifically awarding government contracts to businesses owned by women or minorities.

Those challenging specific government or university policies have sought redress through the courts. Many legal cases involving claims of "reverse discrimination" are settled before they go to court. [http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761580666/Affirmative_Action.html]

==Nomenclature, usage, and opponents of preferential treatment==
The phrase '''reverse discrimination''' has been in use in the United States for several decades.

While the term is used in casual speech, most academic and expert opponents of racial or gender based affirmative action policies, such as [[Carl Cohen]], would avoid the term "reverse discrimination" on the grounds that "[[discrimination]] is discrimination" and that the label "reverse" is a misnomer (a point that experts on both sides of issue generally agree with).  Groups such as the American Civil Rights Institute, run by [[Ward Connerly]], have opted for the more legally precise terms "race preference", "gender preference," or "preferential treatment" generally, since these terms are contained and defined within existing [[civil rights]] law, such as the [[1964 Civil Rights Act]].

Cohen, who was a supporter of Michigan's Proposal 2 (see below), and other academics have argued that the term "affirmative action" should be defined differently than "race preference," and that while socio-economically based or anti-discrimination types of affirmative action should be permissible, those that give preference to individuals solely based on their race or gender should not be permitted. Cohen also helped find evidence in 1996 through the Freedom of Information Act that lead to the cases filed by Jennifer Gratz and Barbara Grutter against the [[University of Michigan]] for its undergraduate and law admissions policy - cases which were decided by the [[U.S. Supreme Court]] on [[June 23, 2003]].

Ward Connerly has promoted a series of ballot initiatives to remove "preferential treatment" in the states of California ([[California Proposition 209 (1996)]]), Washington (1998 - I-200), and Michigan (the [[Michigan Civil Rights Initiative]] - MCRI, or Proposal 2, 2006). All three of these initiatives have passed. California's initiative was co-authored by academics Tom Wood and Glynn Custred in the mid-1990s and was taken up by Connerly after he was appointed in 1994 by Governor [[Pete Wilson]] to the [[University of California]] [[Board of governors|Board of Regents]].  Connerly plans what he calls a "[[Super Tuesday|Super-Tuesday]]" of five additional states in [[2008]].{{Fact|date=September 2007}}

==See also==
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Gender-blind]]
* [[Race-blind]]
* [[White privilege (sociology)|White privilege]]

==External links==
*[http://communities.homeoffice.gov.uk/raceandfaith/ UK Home Office Employment Targets]
*[http://www.cre.gov.uk/legal/rra_positive.html Positive action in employment] under the UK [[Race Relations Act]]
*[http://www.discriminations.us/ John Rosenberg's Discriminations], 
*[http://www.adversity.net Tim Fay's Adversity.net],
*[http://www.chetlyzarko.com/b2evolution/index.php Chetly Zarko's Power, Politics, &amp; Money].

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[bg:Позитивна дискриминация]]
[[ja:逆差別]]
[[sv:omvänd diskriminering]]
[[zh:逆向歧視]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>