<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101028151627|393438817" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="158479" pageid="158479" ns="0" title="Reverse discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-10-30T18:50:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Reverse discrimination''', also known as '''positive'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/positivediscrimination?view=uk Compact Oxford English Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; '''discrimination''', is a controversial specific form of discrimination against members of a dominant or majority group, or in favor of members of a minority or historically disadvantaged group. Groups may be defined in terms of [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[gender]], [[ethnicity]], or other factors. This discrimination may seek to redress [[social inequalities]] where minority groups have been denied access to the same privileges of the majority group. In such cases it is intended to remove discrimination that minority groups may already face. "Reverse discrimination" may also be used to highlight the discrimination inherent in [[affirmative action]] programs.

==United States==
In the [[United States|United States of America]], the term "reverse discrimination" has been used in past discussions of [[racial quota]]s or gender quotas for collegiate admission to government-run educational institutions. Such policies were held to be unconstitutional in the United States, while non-quota based methods, which may include race as a factor, including some [[affirmative action]] programs (race as a factor, ethnic minorities, and physical, mental, or learning disabilities) can be legal. 

Nevertheless, some city governments still utilize racial quotas when awarding government contracts. The city of [[Chicago]] has mandated that all government construction contracts must award 25% of their value to minority owned businesses.&lt;ref&gt;Chicago Municipal Code, Ch. 2-92, Ch. 2-92-430 and Ch. 2-91-445.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first [[United States Supreme Court]] case to challenge reverse discrimination is [[Regents of the University of California v. Bakke]]. In [[Parents Involved in Community Schools v. Seattle School District No. 1]] [551 U.S. 701 (2007)], Chief Justice [[John Roberts]] wrote in the majority opinion, "The way to stop discrimination on the basis of race is to stop discriminating on the basis of race."&lt;ref name=case&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=000&amp;invol=05-908 PARENTS INVOLVED IN COMMUNITY SCHOOLS v. SEATTLE SCHOOL DISTRICT NO. 1 et al.]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, a group of firefighters in [[New Haven, Connecticut]] filed suit against the city for reverse discrimination after promotion test results were thrown out because no African-American firefighters passed the test. Sixteen Caucasian and three Hispanic firefighters passed the test. The Roberts Court in [[Ricci v. DeStefano]] found that disregarding the test results was unconstitutional. &lt;ref&gt;''[http://laws.findlaw.com/us/000/07-1428.html Ricci v. DeStefano]'' (June 29, 2009). This is the full text of the U.S. Supreme Court decision, via Findlaw.&lt;/ref&gt;

Opponents of reverse discrimination view it as a violation of [[equal protection]] under law.&lt;ref name=case/&gt;&lt;ref name=CNN&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2009/POLITICS/06/29/supreme.court.discrimination/index.html High court backs firefighters in reverse discrimination suit]. CNN, June 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==India==
In [[India]], the term is often used by citizens protesting against [[Reservation in India|reservation and quotas]].&lt;ref&gt;Devanesan Nesiah. ''Discrimination With Reason? The Policy of Reservations in the United States, India and Malaysia''. 1997. [[Oxford University Press]]. 0195639839.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindu.com/2006/10/24/stories/2006102401031300.htm  Excess reservation will cause reverse discrimination, cautions Supreme Court]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;R. Kent Greenawalt. ''Discrimination and Reverse Discrimination''. 1983. Knopf. ISBN 0394335775.&lt;/ref&gt;

==United Kingdom==
In November of 2007, David Rosin, a former vice-president of the [[Royal College of Surgeons]] wrote in the magazine ''Hospital Doctor'': “It is time that someone spoke up concerning the reverse discrimination with respect to merit awards” and criticising the fact that "female and ethnic minority consultants are being given preferential treatment to meet artificial quotas".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/health/article2890947.ece|title='Doctor's Revolt at Anti-White Bias' |publisher=[[The Times]]|date=2007-11-18|accessdate=2010-06-30 | location=London | first=Sarah-Kate | last=Templeton}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Northern Ireland==

Since the standing down of the [[RUC]], the [[PSNI]] has opperated a policy of 50/50 recruitment in terms of [[Catholics in Ireland|Catholic]] and [[Protestant]] applicants regardless of a greater number of more suitable candidates from either background. This policy is due to end in 2011 and was instigated to address the imbalance of Catholics in the police force. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.newsletter.co.uk/news/PSNI39s-5050-recruitment-may-end.3849478.jp&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{reflist}}
== Further reading ==
* {{cite book|chapter=Reverse discrimination|pages=72&amp;ndash;73|title=Philosophy: the basics|author=Nigel Warburton|edition=4th|publisher=Routledge|date=2004|isbn=0415327725|isbn13=9780415327725}}
* {{cite book|title=Reverse discrimination in EC law|volume=64|series=European monographs|author=Alina Tryfonidou|publisher=Kluwer Law International|date=2009|isbn=9041127518|isbn13=9789041127518}}
* {{cite book|title=Reverse discrimination: dismantling the myth|author=Fred L. Pincus|publisher=Lynne Rienner Publishers|date=2003|isbn=1588262030|isbn13=9781588262035}}
==See also==
'''General'''
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Afrocentrism]]

'''Race'''
* [[Color blindness (race)]]
* [[New Haven Fire Department reverse discrimination case]]
* [[Land reform in Zimbabwe]] (although directed towards a minority)
* [[Black Economic Empowerment]] in [[South Africa]]

'''Gender'''
* [[All-women shortlists]]
* [[Women and children first (saying)]]

'''Other'''
* [[Reservation in India]]

==External links==
*[http://www.cre.gov.uk/legal/rra_positive.html Positive action in employment] under the UK [[Race Relations Act]]

[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Affirmative action]]

[[bg:Позитивна дискриминация]]
[[de:Umgekehrte Diskriminierung]]
[[ja:逆差別]]
[[pl:Dyskryminacja pozytywna]]
[[sv:omvänd diskriminering]]
[[tr:Tersine ayrımcılık]]
[[zh:逆向歧視]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>