<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091102032546|323406401" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="158479" pageid="158479" ns="0" title="Reverse discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-05T04:51:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{POV|date=October 2009}}
{{partisan|date=October 2009}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Reverse discrimination''' is denial of equal protection of the laws and is viewed as discrimination on the basis of race by opponents of [[racial quotas|racial quota]] programs (a.k.a. '''reverse racism'''),&lt;ref name=case/&gt;&lt;ref name=CNN&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2009/POLITICS/06/29/supreme.court.discrimination/index.html High court backs firefighters in reverse discrimination suit]. CNN, June 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; while proponents of racial quotas and [[affirmative action]] programs generally view it as discrimination against members of a dominant or majority group in order to promote members of a minority or consistently disadvantaged group ('''benign discrimination''').&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/positivediscrimination?view=uk Compact Oxford English Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt;  However, to the individuals concerned it still discriminates against one in favour of another based on race/gender/disability.

==In the United States==
In the United States, the terms "reverse discrimination" and "reverse racism" have been used in past discussions of [[racial quota]]s or gender quotas for collegiate admission to government-run educational institutions. Such policies were held to be unconstitutional in the United States, while non-quota based methods, which may include race as a factor, including some [[affirmative action]] programs (race as a factor, ethnic minorities, and physical, mental, or learning disabilities) can be legal.

The first [[United States Supreme Court]] case to challenge reverse discrimination is [[Regents of the University of California v. Bakke]]. In [[Parents Involved in Community Schools v. Seattle School District No. 1]] [551 U.S. 701 (2007)], Chief Justice John Roberts wrote in the majority opinion, "The way to stop discrimination on the basis of race is to stop discriminating on the basis of race."&lt;ref name=case&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=000&amp;invol=05-908 PARENTS INVOLVED IN COMMUNITY SCHOOLS v. SEATTLE SCHOOL DISTRICT NO. 1 et al.]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Split|date=October 2009}}

==In India==
For example, in [[India]], the term is often used by citizens protesting against [[Reservation in India|reservation and quotas]].&lt;ref&gt;Devanesan Nesiah. ''Discrimination With Reason? The Policy of Reservations in the United States, India and Malaysia''. 1997. [[Oxford University Press]]. 0195639839.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindu.com/2006/10/24/stories/2006102401031300.htm  Excess reservation will cause reverse discrimination, cautions Supreme Court]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;R. Kent Greenawalt. ''Discrimination and Reverse Discrimination''. 1983. Knopf. ISBN 0394335775.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Color blindness (race)]]
* [[White privilege]]
* [[New Haven Fire Department reverse discrimination case]]
* [[Land reform in Zimbabwe]]

'''Gender:'''
* [[All-women shortlists]]
* [[Women and children first (saying)]]

==References==
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.cre.gov.uk/legal/rra_positive.html Positive action in employment] under the UK [[Race Relations Act]]

[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Affirmative action]]

[[bg:Позитивна дискриминация]]
[[de:Umgekehrte Diskriminierung]]
[[ja:逆差別]]
[[pl:Dyskryminacja pozytywna]]
[[sv:omvänd diskriminering]]
[[tr:Tersine ayrımcılık]]
[[zh:逆向歧視]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>