<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131110051925|581001134" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="35197358" pageid="35197358" ns="0" title="Slut-shaming"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-13T17:36:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Inappropriate tone|date=November 2013}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{Feminism sidebar}}
'''Slut shaming''' (also hyphenated, as '''slut-shaming''') is a concept in  philosophy on sexuality. It is a [[neologism]] used to describe the act of making any person feel [[Guilt (emotion)|guilty]] or inferior for  certain sexual behaviors or desires that deviate from traditional or orthodox gender expectations, or that which may be considered to be contrary to natural or religious law. Some examples of behaviors over which women are said to be "slut-shamed" include: violating accepted [[dress code]]s by dressing in sexually provocative ways, requesting access to birth control,&lt;ref name="Lamb B14–B15"&gt;{{cite journal | url=https://chronicle.com/article/The-Right-Sexuality-for/13770 | title=The 'Right' Sexuality for Girls. | date=27 June 2008 | last=Lamb | first=Sharon | journal=[[Chronicle of Higher Education]] | volume=54 | issue=42 | pages=B14–B15 | issn=00095982 | quote=In Dilemmas of Desire: Teenage Girls Talk About Sexuality (Harvard University Press, 2002), Deborah L. Tolman complained that we've "desexualized girls' sexuality, substituting the desire for relationship and emotional connection for sexual feelings in their bodies." Recognizing that fact, theorists have used the concept of desire as a way to undo the double standard that applauds a guy for his lust, calling him a player, and shames a girl for hers, calling her a slut.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Albury |first1=Kath |last2=Crawford |first2=Kate |title=Sexting, consent and young people's ethics: Beyond ''Megan's Story'' |journal=[[Continuum: Journal of Media &amp; Cultural Studies]] |date=18 May 2012 |volume=26 |issue=3 |pages=463–473 |doi=10.1080/10304312.2012.665840 |quote=Certainly the individualizing admonishment to 'think again' offers no sense of the broader legal and political environment in which sexting might occur, or any critique of a culture that requires young women to preserve their 'reputations' by avoiding overt demonstrations of sexual knowingness and desire. Further, by trading on the propensity of teenagers to feel embarrassment about their bodies and commingling it with the anxiety of mobiles being ever present, the ad becomes a potent mix of technology fear and body shame.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="limbaugh"/&gt; having [[Premarital sex|premarital]] or [[casual sex]], or [[Victim blaming|being raped or sexually assaulted]].&lt;ref name="asking" /&gt;

==Overview==
Slut shaming is defined by many as a process in which women are attacked for their transgression of accepted codes of sexual conduct,&lt;ref name="Ringrose2012"&gt;{{cite book|author=Jessica Ringrose|title=Postfeminist Education?: Girls and the Sexual Politics of Schooling|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=1jbsSXc9rUQC&amp;pg=PA93|accessdate=16 May 2013|date=21 August 2012|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-136-25971-5|page=93}}&lt;/ref&gt;  i.e., of admonishing them for behavior or desires that are more sexual than society finds acceptable.&lt;ref name="FoyDale2013"&gt;{{cite book|author=Denise Du Vernay|title=Feminism, Sexism, and the Small Screen|pages=163–182}} in {{cite book|author1=Joseph J. Foy|author2=Timothy M. Dale|title=Homer Simpson Ponders Politics: Popular Culture as Political Theory|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=dvnAmHgqTX4C&amp;|accessdate=16 May 2013|date=24 April 2013|publisher=University Press of Kentucky|isbn=978-0-8131-4151-0|page=164}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Emily Bazelon]] says that slut shaming is "retrograde, the opposite of feminist.  Calling a girl a slut warns her that there's a line: she can be sexual but not ''too'' sexual."&lt;ref name="Bazelon2013"&gt;{{cite book|author=Emily Bazelon|title=Sticks and Stones: Defeating the Culture of Bullying and Rediscovering the Power of Character and Empathy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5Z9QxYZ4J1kC&amp;pg=PA95|accessdate=16 May 2013|date=19 February 2013|publisher=Random House Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-679-64400-2|page=95}} Emphasis in original.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many have stated that slut shaming is used against women by both men and women.&lt;ref name="Psy.D.Eagleson2010"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Belisa Vranich, Psy.D.|author2=Holly Eagleson|title=Boys Lie: How Not to Get Played|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4cToqrySVDAC&amp;pg=PA52|accessdate=16 May 2013|date=1 July 2010|publisher=HCI|isbn=978-0-7573-1364-6|page=52}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Jessica Ringrose has argued that it functions among women as a way of [[Sublimation (psychology)|sublimating]] sexual jealousy "into a socially acceptable form of social critique of girls' sexual expression."&lt;ref name="Ringrose2012"/&gt; Some also use this term to describe what they call [[victim blaming]] for [[rape]] and [[sexual assault]], e.g. by stating that the crime was caused (either in part or in full) by the woman wearing revealing clothing or previously acting in a forward, sexual manner, before not consenting to sex,&lt;ref name="asking" /&gt; and thereby absolving the perpetrator of guilt.

Men and women alike are culprits of "slut-shaming": The study "Birds of a feather? Not when it comes to sexual permissiveness," published in the ''Journal of Social and Personal Relationships'', notes that sexually lenient individuals are judged more negatively than non-permissive peers, which places those who are more permissive  risk of social isolation.&lt;ref name="spr.sagepub.com"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Vrangalova|first=Z.|coauthors=Bukberg, R. E.; Rieger, G.|title=Birds of a feather? Not when it comes to sexual permissiveness|journal=Journal of Social and Personal Relationships|date=19 May 2013|doi=10.1177/0265407513487638|url=http://spr.sagepub.com/content/early/2013/05/16/0265407513487638.full.pdf+html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The researchers from Cornell University found that similar sentiments appeared in nonsexual, same-sex friendship context as well.&lt;ref name="spr.sagepub.com"/&gt; The researchers had college women read a vignette describing an imaginary female peer, “Joan,” then rate their feelings about her personality.&lt;ref name="spr.sagepub.com"/&gt; To one group of women, Joan was described as having two lifetime sexual partners; to another group, she had had twenty partners.&lt;ref name="slate.com"&gt;http://www.slate.com/blogs/xx_factor/2013/06/07/slut_shaming_study_women_discriminate_against_promiscuous_women_but_so_do.html&lt;/ref&gt; The study found that women—even women who were more promiscuous themselves—rated the Joan with 20 partners as “less competent, emotionally stable, warm, and dominant than the Joan who’d only boasted two”.&lt;ref name="spr.sagepub.com"/&gt;&lt;ref name="slate.com"/&gt;

An article in the ''[[New York Daily News]]'' described yet another mode of "slut-shaming": in meme-dorm.&lt;ref name="nydailynews.com"&gt;http://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/adolescents-memes-cyber-bully-article-1.1235246&lt;/ref&gt; Young girls, and increasingly boys, have begun to generate memes on Tumblr and Facebook to offer mock – and often insulting – advice to their peers.&lt;ref name="nydailynews.com"/&gt; For example: "Hey Girls. Did you know? That you spread Nutella...Not your legs," reads one such viral post.&lt;ref name="nydailynews.com"/&gt;”

== In the media ==

[[File:SlutWalk NYC October 2011 Shankbone 4.JPG|thumb|right|Two women protesting about victim-blaming and slut-shaming at New York City's [[SlutWalk]] in October 2011.]]

The [[SlutWalk]] protest march started in [[Toronto]] in response to an incident where a Toronto Police officer told a group of students that they could avoid sexual assault by not dressing like "sluts".&lt;ref name="asking"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=McCormack |first1=Clare |last2=Prostran |first2=Nevena |title=Asking for It |journal=[[International Feminist Journal of Politics]] |year=2012 |volume=14 |issue=3 |pages=410–414 |doi=10.1080/14616742.2012.699777}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Ringrose |first1=Jessica |last2=Renold |first2=Emma |title=Slut-shaming, girl power and 'sexualisation': thinking through the politics of the international SlutWalks with teen girls |journal=Gender and Education |year=2011 |month=October |volume=24 |issue=3 |pages=333–343 |doi=10.1080/09540253.2011.645023 |url=http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=EJ964730&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=EJ964730}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.slutwalktoronto.com/ SlutWalk Toronto]&lt;/ref&gt;

The term has since been used when describing the comments of [[Rush Limbaugh]] during the [[Rush Limbaugh–Sandra Fluke controversy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Ball |first=Krystal |title=Boycott Rush |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/krystal-ball/rush-limbaugh-sandra-fluke_b_1315805.html |work=The Blog |publisher=Huffington Post |accessdate=13 December 2012 |date=3 February 2012 |quote=This type of despicable behavior is part and parcel of a time-worn tradition of Slut-Shaming. When women step out line, they are demeaned and degraded into silence. If you say Herman Cain sexually harassed you, you are a slut. If you say Supreme Court Justice Clarence Thomas sexually harassed you, you are a slut.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is speculated that the controversy that erupted may have long-term effects on the incidence of slut-shaming in broadcast media.{{how|date=May 2013}}&lt;ref name="limbaugh"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Legge |first1=Nancy J. |last2=DiSanza |first2=James R. |last3=Gribas |first3=John |last4=Shiffler |first4=Aubrey |title="He sounded like a vile, disgusting pervert..." An Analysis of Persuasive Attacks on Rush Limbaugh During the Sandra Fluke Controversy |journal=Journal of Radio &amp; Audio Media |year=2012 |volume=19 |issue=2 |pages=173–205 |doi=10.1080/19376529.2012.722468 |quote=It is also possible that the Limbaugh incident has turned "slut-shaming," or other similar attacks on women, into a "Devil-term." It may be possible that Limbaugh's insults were so thoroughly condemned that he and others (such as Bill Maher) will have a more difficult time insulting women who are not virgins, or attacking them in other sexist ways.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

James Miller, editor-in-chief, for the [[Ludwig von Mises Institute]] of Canada wrote a controversial article defending slut shaming.&lt;ref name="Why Slut-Shame"&gt;http://townhall.com/tipsheet/kateandrews/2013/09/03/editorinchief-of-mises-institute-in-canada-advocates-slut-shaming-n1690262&lt;/ref&gt;  The article was later taken down, but still received criticism from some libertarians, such as Gina Luttrell of ''Thoughts on Liberty'', an all-female [[libertarian]] blog.&lt;ref name="Misogynists Gonna Misogynate"&gt;http://thoughtsonliberty.com/misogynists-gonna-misogynate-or-more-issues-with-that-mises-ca-post&lt;/ref&gt;

At an August 2013 [[Eminem]] performance at the [[Slane Concert]] in the Irish village of [[Slane]], a 17-year-old girl was photographed giving oral sex to a man in the middle of a crowd. The photos were shared hundreds of times across social media platforms, reaching message boards like [[4Chan]] and [[Reddit]], eventually attracting widespread online ridicule of the teen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/witw/articles/2013/08/22/behind-slanegirl-young-girl-hospitalized-after-photographed-having-oral-sex.html|title=Behind #SlaneGirl: Teenaged Girl Hospitalized After Being Photographed Having Oral Sex|work=[[The Daily Beast]]|date=2013-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/soraya-chemaly/slanegirl-misogyny-slut-shaming_b_3805391.html|title= Sticks, Stones and #Slanegirl or Why Shaming Girls Is a Blood Sport |work=[[Huffington Post]]|date=2013-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2013/sep/01/slane-girl-twitter-scandal-women|title=The Slane Girl Twitter scandal proves that women can't make mistakes|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=2013-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The young girl who is is being victimized through slut shaming, claims that she was sexually assaulted Gardai launched an investigation when the pictures went viral. The complaint does is not related to the man in the viral photos. The young girl was involved in another incident at the concert. After the photos emerged, another video showed up online of the young girl surrounded by up to 8 men who were pushing her around and heckling her as she kisses a young man &lt;ref name="mirror.co.uk"&gt;http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/world-news/slane-girl-police-awaiting-blood-2199533&lt;/ref&gt;  At the concert, the girl sought assistance at the medical tent, which led to Gardai being notified about the situation. The girl was treated at a hospital in the midlands prior to heading back to her home in West of Ireland. When the images appeared online the next day, the girl was so panic-stricken that she was re-admitted and sedated before undergoing medical tests &lt;ref&gt;http://www.herald.ie/news/slane-girl-tells-gardai-that-she-was-assaulted-29539826.html&lt;/ref&gt; 
A statement was made that the girl is believed to come from an extremely respectable family from the West of Ireland and has no history of reckless or promiscuous behaviour.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sundayworld.com/top-stories/news/slane-girl-makes-statement-  about-attack&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Facebook]], [[Instagram]] and [[Twitter]] removed the images after the investigation was launched; keeping in mind the girl is underage.&lt;ref name="knowyourmeme.com"&gt;http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/events/slanegirl&lt;/ref&gt;  Twitter’s spokesperson made a public statement that they do not tolerate “child sexual exploitation” &lt;ref name="mirror.co.uk"/&gt; 
After the photos were made public, the viral image-turned-meme became a site of controversial site of [[gender bias]] and sexual [[cyber bullying]];&lt;ref name="knowyourmeme.com"/&gt; online forums were overflowing with aggressive messages criticizing and judging the girl. In response, a Twitter trend #SlaneGirlSolidarity was started in support of the girl.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sundayworld.com/top-stories/news/slane-on-you&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, the performance apparel and dance-moves of pop-star [[Miley Cyrus]] at the 2013 VMA Awards created "slut-shaming" uproar.&lt;ref name="articles.washingtonpost.com"&gt;http://articles.washingtonpost.com/2013-08-26/entertainment/41447063_1_cyrus-is-miley-cyrus-diplo&lt;/ref&gt; Her performance of "We Can’t Stop," which was performed as a duet with [[Robin Thicke]]'s "Blurred Lines," was called "lewd, grotesque and shameful."&lt;ref name="articles.washingtonpost.com"/&gt; Notably, the Washington Post notes the lack of criticism towards Robin Thicke: "While Cyrus was condemned for grinding on Thicke, very little criticism has been laid on the singer himself for his role in the performance."&lt;ref name="articles.washingtonpost.com"/&gt;

== In literature ==

Slut-shaming also occurs in the literary realm as well. Such an example includes Hester Prynn, forced to wear a scarlet letter "A," which stands for Adultery, in Nathaniel Hawthorne's "The Scarlet Letter."&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.com"&gt;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/10/07/book-characters-sex_n_3960991.html&lt;/ref&gt; Yet another example includes Anna Karenina, from Leo Tolstoy's "Anna Karenina," who has a highly public affair with the affluent Count Vronsky: Anna Karenina is rejected by her friends, while the reputation of Count Vronsky remains more or less untarnished.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.com"/&gt; In these novels, the author of the article notes that the men—while some experience personal setbacks—are never shunned publicly in the way that their female counterparts are for engaging in the relationships deemed socially inappropriate.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.com"/&gt;

== Stopping slut-shaming ==

Members of The Arts Effect All-Girl Theater Company have developed a play, "Slut," in which they address the damaging impact of slut shaming and slut culture.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/lauren-hersh/nyc-girls-challenge-weiner_b_3691859.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sluttheplay.com"&gt;http://sluttheplay.com/why/&lt;/ref&gt; The creators note that their play "is a call to action – a reminder" that slut-shaming is happening every day, almost everywhere.&lt;ref name="sluttheplay.com"/&gt; "Slut" is inspired by real-life experiences of 14-17 year-old girls from New York, New Jersey, Connecticut, and Pennsylvania.&lt;ref name="sluttheplay.com"/&gt; The play was shown at the 2013 New York Fringe Festival.&lt;ref name="sluttheplay.com"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://shine.yahoo.com/love-sex/teenage-peta-pinup-speaks-out-205112851.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In her statement on the production, and of slut-shaming in general,  author of ''Slut! Growing Up Female with a Bad Reputation'', Leora Tenenbaumn writes: "A teenage girl today is caught in an impossible situation.  She has to project a sexy image and embrace, to some extent, a 'slutty' identity.  Otherwise, she risks being mocked as an irrelevant prude. But if her peers decide she has crossed an invisible, constantly shifting boundary and has become too 'slutty,' she loses all credibility.  Even if she was coerced into sex, her identity and reputation are taken from her.  Indeed, the power to tell her own story is wrested from her. The Arts Effect's SLUT written by Katie Cappiello vividly represents this irrational, harmful, terrible circumstance...This play is the most powerful and authentic representation of the sexual double standard I have ever seen."&lt;ref name="sluttheplay.com"/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Sexual bullying]]
*[[Victim blaming]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

[[Category:Bullying]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Misogyny]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender-related slurs]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>