<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171115231936|810549384" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="35197358" pageid="35197358" ns="0" title="Slut-shaming"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-16T02:57:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism sidebar}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expanded =all}}
'''Slut-shaming''' is the practice of criticizing women and girls who are perceived to violate expectations of behavior and appearance regarding issues related to sexuality. Examples are violating [[dress code]] policies by dressing in perceived sexually provocative ways, requesting access to [[birth control]],&lt;ref name="Lamb B14–B15"&gt;{{cite journal | last=Lamb | first=Sharon| author-link = Sharon Lamb | title=The 'Right' Sexuality for Girls |date=27 June 2008 | journal=[[Chronicle of Higher Education]] | volume=54 | issue=42 | pages=B14–B15 | url=https://chronicle.com/article/The-Right-Sexuality-for/13770 | issn=0009-5982 | subscription = yes | quote=In Dilemmas of Desire: Teenage Girls Talk About Sexuality (Harvard University Press, 2002), Deborah L. Tolman complained that we've 'desexualized girls' sexuality, substituting the desire for relationship and emotional connection for sexual feelings in their bodies.' Recognizing that fact, theorists have used the concept of desire as a way to undo the double standard that applauds a guy for his lust, calling him a player, and shames a girl for hers, calling her a slut.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Albury |first1=Kath |last2=Crawford |first2=Kate |title=Sexting, consent and young people's ethics: Beyond ''Megan's Story'' |journal=[[Continuum: Journal of Media &amp; Cultural Studies]] |date=18 May 2012 |volume=26 |issue=3 |pages=463–473 |doi=10.1080/10304312.2012.665840 |quote=Certainly the individualizing admonishment to 'think again' offers no sense of the broader legal and political environment in which sexting might occur, or any critique of a culture that requires young women to preserve their 'reputations' by avoiding overt demonstrations of sexual knowingness and desire. Further, by trading on the propensity of teenagers to feel embarrassment about their bodies and commingling it with the anxiety of mobiles being ever present, the ad becomes a potent mix of technology fear and body shame.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="limbaugh" /&gt; having [[Premarital sex|premarital]], [[casual sex|casual]], or [[promiscuous]] sex, engaging in [[prostitution]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Tesla|first=Carrasquillo,|date=2014-01-01|title=Understanding Prostitution and the Need for Reform|url=http://digitalcommons.tourolaw.edu/lawreview/vol30/iss3/11/|journal=Touro Law Review|volume=30|issue=3|issn=8756-7326}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?redir_esc=y&amp;id=BbETAAAAQBAJ&amp;q=slut+shaming#v=snippet&amp;q=slut%20shaming&amp;f=false|title=Sex Workers Unite: A History of the Movement from Stonewall to Slutwalk|last=Chateauvert|first=Melinda|date=2014-02-07|publisher=Beacon Press|year=|isbn=9780807061398|location=|pages=49|language=English|quote=It encouraged women to be angry about whore stigma and slut shaming for pursuing sexual pleasure or trading sex for money|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; or when being [[victim blaming|victim blamed]] for being [[rape]]d or otherwise [[sexually assaulted]].&lt;ref name="asking" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://bhttps://books.google.com/books?redir_esc=y&amp;q=slut+shaming#v=snippet&amp;q=slut%20shaming&amp;f=false|title=Sex Workers Unite: A History of the Movement from Stonewall to SlutWalk|last=Chateauvert|first=Melinda|date=2014-01-07|publisher=Beacon Press|year=|isbn=9780807061404|location=|pages=|language=en|quote=Slut-shaming implies that victims of sex violence "asked for it" because they were sexually promiscuous or dressed provocatively.|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions and characteristics==
Slut-shaming is also defined many as criticizing women for their transgression of accepted codes of sexual conduct,&lt;ref name="Ringrose2012"&gt;{{cite book|author=Jessica Ringrose|title=Postfeminist Education?: Girls and the Sexual Politics of Schooling|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1jbsSXc9rUQC&amp;pg=PA93|accessdate=16 May 2013|date=21 August 2012|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-136-25971-5|page=93}}&lt;/ref&gt; i.e., of admonishing them for behavior, attire or desires that are more sexual than society finds acceptable.&lt;ref name="FoyDale2013"&gt;{{cite book|author=Denise Du Vernay|title=Feminism, Sexism, and the Small Screen|pages=163–182}} in {{cite book|author1=Joseph J. Foy|author2=Timothy M. Dale|title=Homer Simpson Ponders Politics: Popular Culture as Political Theory|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dvnAmHgqTX4C&amp;|accessdate=16 May 2013|date=24 April 2013|publisher=University Press of Kentucky|isbn=978-0-8131-4151-0|page=164}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bazelon2013"&gt;{{cite book|author=Emily Bazelon|title=Sticks and Stones: Defeating the Culture of Bullying and Rediscovering the Power of Character and Empathy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5Z9QxYZ4J1kC&amp;pg=PA95|accessdate=16 May 2013|date=19 February 2013|publisher=Random House Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-679-64400-2|page=95}} Emphasis in original.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Schalet|first=Amy T.|title=Not Under My Roof: Parents, Teens, and the Culture of Sex|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hVBV86xxG10C|year=2011|publisher=University of Chicago Press|isbn=978-0-226-73620-4|pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=hVBV86xxG10C&amp;pg=PA12 12], [https://books.google.com/books?id=hVBV86xxG10C&amp;pg=PA156 156]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Tolman|first1=Deborah L.|title=Dilemmas of desire teenage girls talk about sexuality.|date=2005|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=9780674018563|edition=1. Harvard Univ. Press paperback}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Slut-shaming is used by men and women.&lt;ref name="Psy.D.Eagleson2010"&gt;{{cite book|author1=[[Belisa Vranich]], Psy.D.|author2=Holly Eagleson|title=Boys Lie: How Not to Get Played|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4cToqrySVDAC&amp;pg=PA52|accessdate=16 May 2013|date=1 July 2010|publisher=HCI|isbn=978-0-7573-1364-6|page=52}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://america.aljazeera.com/articles/2014/5/9/political-sex-scandalsmonicalewinskysexismslutshaming.html Monica Lewinsky’s return and the sexism 2.0 of political scandals]&lt;/ref&gt; Slut-shaming functions among women as a way of [[Sublimation (psychology)|sublimating]] sexual jealousy" into a socially acceptable form of social critique of girls' sexual expression."&lt;ref name="Ringrose2012"/&gt; The term is also used to describe [[victim blaming]] for [[rape]] and other [[sexual assault]]. This is done by stating the crime was caused (either in part or in full) by the woman wearing revealing clothing or acting in a sexually provocative manner, before refusing consent to sex,&lt;ref name="asking" /&gt; thereby absolving the perpetrator of guilt. Sexually lenient individuals can be at risk of social isolation.&lt;ref name="spr.sagepub.com"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Vrangalova |first1=Z. |author2=Bukberg, R. E.; Rieger, G.|title=Birds of a feather? Not when it comes to sexual permissiveness|journal=Journal of Social and Personal Relationships |date=19 May 2013 |doi=10.1177/0265407513487638 |url=http://spr.sagepub.com/content/early/2013/05/16/0265407513487638.full.pdf+html |volume=31 |pages=93–113}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Researchers from Cornell University found that similar sentiments appeared in nonsexual, same-sex friendship context as well.&lt;ref name="spr.sagepub.com"/&gt; The researchers had college women read a vignette describing an imaginary female peer, "Joan", then rate their feelings about her personality.&lt;ref name="spr.sagepub.com"/&gt; To one group of women, Joan was described as having two lifetime sexual partners; to another group, she had had twenty partners.&lt;ref name="slate.com"&gt;{{cite web|last=Hess |first=Amanda |url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/xx_factor/2013/06/07/slut_shaming_study_women_discriminate_against_promiscuous_women_but_so_do.html |title=Slut-shaming study: Women discriminate against promiscuous women, but so do men |publisher=Slate.com |date=7 June 2013 |accessdate=11 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study found that women—even women who were more promiscuous themselves—rated the Joan with 20 partners as "less competent, emotionally stable, warm, and dominant than the Joan who'd only boasted two".&lt;ref name="spr.sagepub.com"/&gt;&lt;ref name="slate.com"/&gt;

== In the media ==
[[File:SlutWalk NYC October 2011 Shankbone 4.JPG|thumb|right|Two women protesting about victim-blaming and slut-shaming at New York City's [[SlutWalk]] in October 2011]]
The [[SlutWalk]] protest march had its origins in [[Toronto]] in response to an incident when a Toronto Police officer told a group of students that they could avoid sexual assault by not dressing like "'sluts'".&lt;ref name="asking"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=McCormack |first1=Clare |last2=Prostran |first2=Nevena |title=Asking for it: a first-hand account from slutwalk |journal=[[International Feminist Journal of Politics]] |year=2012 |volume=14 |issue=3 |pages=410–414 |doi=10.1080/14616742.2012.699777 | publisher = [[Taylor and Francis]] | url = https://dx.doi.org/10.1080/14616742.2012.699777 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Ringrose | first1 = Jessica | last2 = Renold | first2 = Emma | title = Slut-shaming, girl power and ‘sexualisation’: thinking through the politics of the international SlutWalks with teen girls | journal = [[Gender and Education]], special issue: Making Sense of the Sexualisation Debates: Schools and Beyond | volume = 24 | issue = 3 | pages = 333–343 | publisher = [[Taylor and Francis]] | doi = 10.1080/09540253.2011.645023 | date = May 2012 | url = https://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09540253.2011.645023 | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [http://eprints.ioe.ac.uk/11877/1/Ringrose_and_renold_Slutwalk_2012.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slutwalktoronto.com/|title=SlutWalk Toronto - BECAUSE WE'VE HAD ENOUGH - SlutWalk Toronto|work=slutwalktoronto.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Nathanson"&gt;[http://blogs.villagevoice.com/runninscared/2011/10/slutwalk_rally.php SlutWalk Rally Against Sexual Violence Draws Huge Crowd of Feminists], Rebecca Nathanson, ''[[The Village Voice]]'', October 2, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; [[Amber Rose]]'s second annual walk in Los Angeles in 2016 had "several hundred" participants.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.laweekly.com/arts/amber-roses-slutwalk-was-reality-tv-ready-7456324|title=Amber Rose's SlutWalk Was Reality TV Ready|last=Lecaro|first=Lina|date=2016-10-03|access-date=2016-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; A similar event occurred in Washington DC in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://townhall.com/tipsheet/cortneyobrien/2013/08/08/slutwalkdc-n1659540|title=Cortney O'Brien - This Weekend, 'Sluts' Will March Through DC|last=O'Brien|first=Cortney|work=Townhall|access-date=2017-11-14|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term has been used by a commentator who used the term to describe the comments of [[Rush Limbaugh]] during the [[Rush Limbaugh–Sandra Fluke controversy]]: "If you are a woman who stands up for your rights, you are a slut and your parents should be ashamed of you and we should all have the right to view your sex tapes online. This type of despicable behavior is part and parcel of a time-worn tradition of Slut-Shaming."&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/krystal-ball/rush-limbaugh-sandra-fluke_b_1315805.html|title=Boycott Rush|last=Ball|first=Krystal|date=3 February 2012|work=HuffPost|accessdate=13 December 2012|quote=|series=The Blog}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

{{Quote box
| quote = This type of despicable behavior is part and parcel of a time-worn tradition of Slut-Shaming. When women step out line, they are demeaned and degraded into silence. If you say Herman Cain sexually harassed you, you are a slut. If you say Supreme Court Justice Clarence Thomas sexually harassed you, you are a slut.
| align = left
| width = 40em
}}The condemnation of Limbaugh following the incident is argued to have brought public attention to women being characterized as sluts for supporting the use of birth control.&lt;ref name="limbaugh"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Legge |first1=Nancy J. |last2=DiSanza |first2=James R. |last3=Gribas |first3=John |last4=Shiffler |first4=Aubrey |title="He sounded like a vile, disgusting pervert..." An Analysis of Persuasive Attacks on Rush Limbaugh During the Sandra Fluke Controversy |journal=Journal of Radio &amp; Audio Media |year=2012 |volume=19 |issue=2 |pages=173–205 |doi= 10.1080/19376529.2012.722468 | url = https://dx.doi.org/10.1080/19376529.2012.722468 |quote=It is also possible that the Limbaugh incident has turned "slut-shaming", or other similar attacks on women, into a "Devil-term". It may be possible that Limbaugh's insults were so thoroughly condemned that he and others (such as Bill Maher) will have a more difficult time insulting women who are not virgins, or attacking them in other sexist ways.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Slut-shaming has been used as a form of bullying on social media, with some people using [[revenge porn]]ography tactics to spread intimate photos without consent. In 2012, a California teenager, [[Suicide of Audrie Pott|Audrie Pott]], was sexually assaulted by three boys at a party. She committed suicide eight days after photos of her being assaulted were distributed among her peer group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/10/30/slut-shaming-teen-girls_n_4178812.html|title = Teen Girls Take A Stand Against Slut Shaming: What It Is, And Why You Should Care|accessdate = |series = Huff Post Teen|website = The Huffington Post|last = Menza|first = Kaitlin|date=October 30, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

James Miller, editor-in-chief, for the [[Ludwig von Mises Institute]] of Canada wrote a controversial article defending slut shaming.&lt;ref name="Why Slut-Shame"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://townhall.com/tipsheet/kateandrews/2013/09/03/editorinchief-of-mises-institute-in-canada-advocates-slut-shaming-n1690262 |title=Editor-In-Chief of Mises Institute in Canada Advocates "Slut-Shaming" – Kate Andrews |publisher=Townhall.com |date=3 September 2013 |accessdate=11 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The article was later taken down, but still received criticism from some libertarians, such as Gina Luttrell of ''Thoughts on Liberty'', an all-female [[libertarian]] blog.&lt;ref name="Misogynists Gonna Misogynate"&gt;{{cite web|last=Robinson |first=Elizabeth |url=http://thoughtsonliberty.com/misogynists-gonna-misogynate-or-more-issues-with-that-mises-ca-post |title=Misogynists Gonna…Misogynate? (or, More Issues with That Mises.ca Post) |publisher=Thoughts on Liberty |date=5 September 2013 |accessdate=11 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Comedians  Krystyna Hutchinson and Corinne Fischer of ''Sorry About Last Night'' host a podcast entitled “Guys We F****d, The Anti-slut shaming podcast”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/03/13/guys-we-fucked-corinne-fisher-krystyna-hutchinson_n_4951770.html|title=This Is The Sexiest Podcast You'll Ever Hear|last=Editor|first=Emma Gray Executive Women's|last2=Post|first2=The Huffington|date=2014-03-13|work=HuffPost|access-date=2016-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2014/02/18/the-podcast-too-hot-for-itunes.html|title=The Podcast Too Hot for iTunes|last=Goldstein|first=Rich|date=2014-02-18|website=The Daily Beast|access-date=2016-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; This podcast has over 200,000 listeners on each episode that is on SoundCloud.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://soundcloud.com/guyswefucked|title=Guys We F****d|website=SoundCloud|access-date=2016-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;  iTunes originally did not make the podcast available and "...would not comment on whether the show is subject to an official ban”.  The podcast exists to de-stigmatize discussing  sex so that slut-shaming becomes less of an issue, Hutchinson explains in an interview with ''The Huffington Post'': “We want to make people feel more comfortable in their own skin. We just got a message from a girl from New Delhi, India, about how she loves the podcast because it makes her feel like it’s OK to be comfortable with your sexuality and enjoy sex. And that made me so happy.” &lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== In culture ==
Slut-shaming is prevalent on [[social media]] platforms, including [[YouTube]] and [[Facebook]]. “[T]he medium [of YouTube] is increasingly being used to attack and malign female reputations and criticize female sexual behavior.”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Shame transfigured: Slut-shaming from Rome to cyberspace|url = http://ojphi.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/5464|journal = First Monday|date = 2015-04-02|issn = 1396-0466|volume = 20|issue = 4|language = en|first = Lewis Mark|last = Webb|doi=10.5210/fm.v20i4.5464}}&lt;/ref&gt; Slut-shaming has occurred on  Facebook in controversial exchanges between users that have resulted in convictions to menace, harrass and cause offence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = This Woman Received Rape Threats for Quoting Drake on Tinder|url = http://mic.com/articles/124646/olivia-melville-was-slut-shamed-and-received-rape-threats-for-quoting-drake-on-her-tinder-profile#.I0vMKyLgT|website = Mic|accessdate = 2015-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url = https://www.theguardian.com/media/2016/jul/30/how-facebook-troll-came-undone|author = Elle Hunt|date = 30 July 2016|accessdate = 30 July 2016|newspaper = [[The Guardian]]|title = 'What law am I breaking?' How a Facebook troll came undone}}&lt;/ref&gt; School [[dress codes]] can be a form of slut shaming.&lt;ref name="Carroll"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Carroll|first1=Rory|title=Students protest 'slut shaming' high school dress codes with mass walkouts|url=https://www.theguardian.com/education/2014/sep/24/us-high-schools-dress-codes-protest-sexism-hemline|website=The Guardian|accessdate=8 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One example of a character in literature has been described as being a recipient of 'slut-shaming' is the character [[Lily Bart]] in [[Edith Wharton]]’s “[[The House of Mirth|House of Mirth]]”&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.com"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/10/07/book-characters-sex_n_3960991.html| work= The Huffington Post| last=Triska | first=Zoë| title=9 Female Book Characters Punished For Having Sex | date=7 October 2013| accessdate=24 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Activism ==
Activism against slut-shaming takes place worldwide. Participants have covered their bodies in messages reading "Don't Tell Me How to Dress" and "I am not a slut but I like having consensual sex" and march under a giant banner with the word slut on it. Activism has occurred in Vancouver, New York City, Rio, Jerusalem, Hong Kong and others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Nguyen|first1=Tram|title=From SlutWalks to SuicideGirls: Feminist Resistance in the Third Wave and Postfeminist Era|journal=Women's Studies Quarterly|date=1 January 2013|volume=41|issue=3/4|pages=157–172|doi=10.1353/wsq.2013.0102|jstor=23611512}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, hundreds of South African women protested the local taxi rank wearing miniskirts and t-shirts that read, "Pissed-OffWomen." after a taxi driver and multiple hawkers confronted a young girl about wearing a short denim miniskirt and penetrated her with their fingers, calling her "slut" repeatedly. Protesters wanted to make their message clear; they wanted men to stop harassing women no matter how short their skirts were and that no matter how short it may be, it is never an invitation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Wininger|first1=K. J.|title=Stomp &amp; Holler: Because We've Had Enough! The Transformation of SlutWalks|journal=Transformations: The Journal of Inclusive Scholarship and Pedagogy|date=1 January 2012|volume=22|issue=2|pages=144–151|doi=10.5325/trajincschped.22.2.0144|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/trajincschped.22.2.0144}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the gang rape of an unconscious sixteen year old girl in Steubenville, Ohio, August 2012, football players spread videos of the assault to other classmates whom some of which posted the videos to Twitter and Instagram. The pictures and video were later removed by authorities, however that didn't stop people from hash-tagging "Whore status" or "I have no sympathy for whores" on their tweets. Members of the collective Anonymous reported names of the rapists and classmates who spread the footage to local authorities. They took to the streets and internet requesting help from the community to bring justice to the Jane Doe who was raped.   
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Hate Crimes in Cyberspace|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=9780674368293|pages=95–119|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zsws7.7|chapter=Civil Rights Movements, Past and Present}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Members of The Arts Effect All-Girl Theater Company have developed a play, ''[[Slut: The Play]]'', in which they address the damaging impact of slut-shaming and slut culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/lauren-hersh/nyc-girls-challenge-weiner_b_3691859.html |title=NYC Girls Challenge Weiner Campaign: Stop Slut-Shaming |first=Lauren|last=Hersh |work=[[The Huffington Post]] |date= 2 August 2013|accessdate=11 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sluttheplay.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sluttheplay.com/why/ |title=Why Slut — Slut |publisher=Sluttheplay.com |date= |accessdate=11 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The creators note that their play "is a call to action – a reminder" that slut-shaming is happening every day, almost everywhere.&lt;ref name="sluttheplay.com" /&gt; "Slut" is inspired by real-life experiences of 14- to 17-year-old girls from New York, New Jersey, Connecticut, and Pennsylvania.&lt;ref name="sluttheplay.com" /&gt; The play was shown at the 2013 New York Fringe Festival.&lt;ref name="sluttheplay.com" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://shine.yahoo.com/love-sex/teenage-peta-pinup-speaks-out-205112851.html |title=Meet the Teen Star of PETA's Latest Controversy. We Love Her. |website=Love + Sex – Yahoo Shine |publisher=Shine.yahoo.com |date=8 August 2013 |accessdate=11 April 2014 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140404050810/https://shine.yahoo.com/love-sex/teenage-peta-pinup-speaks-out-205112851.html |archivedate=April 4, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In her statement on the production, and of slut-shaming in general, author of ''Slut! Growing Up Female with a Bad Reputation'', [[Leora Tanenbaum]] writes: "A teenage girl today is caught in an impossible situation. She has to project a sexy image and embrace, to some extent, a 'slutty' identity. Otherwise, she risks being mocked as an irrelevant prude. But if her peers decide she has crossed an invisible, constantly shifting boundary and has become too 'slutty,' she loses all credibility. Even if she was coerced into sex, her identity and reputation are taken from her. Indeed, the power to tell her own story is wrested from her. The Arts Effect's SLUT written by Katie Cappiello vividly represents this irrational, harmful, terrible circumstance...This play is the most powerful and authentic representation of the sexual double standard I have ever seen."&lt;ref name="sluttheplay.com"/&gt;

After experiencing slut-shaming first-hand, Olivia Melville, Paloma Brierly Newton and approximately a dozen other Australian women founded the organization, Sexual Violence Won’t Be Silenced, on August 25, 2015. The association seeks to raise awareness of cyber-bullying and online sexual violence. The founders also launched a petition to the Australian government, requesting that they better train and educate law enforcement officers on how to prevent and punish violent harassment on social media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mic.com/articles/124646/olivia-melville-was-slut-shamed-and-received-rape-threats-for-quoting-drake-on-her-tinder-profile#.I0vMKyLgT|title=A Woman Was Slut-Shamed and Received Rape Threats for Quoting Drake on Her Tinder Profile|author=Mic|work=Mic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Among gay men==
&lt;!--The drug [[Tenofovir/emtricitabine|Truvada]] has been approved for [[pre-exposure prophylaxis]] for [[prevention of HIV/AIDS]] in some countries, after studies demonstrated it can lower the risk of new HIV infections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Preexposure Chemoprophylaxis for HIV Prevention in Men Who Have Sex with Men | pmc=3079639 | pmid=21091279 | doi=10.1056/NEJMoa1011205 | volume=363 | date=December 2010 | journal=N. Engl. J. Med. | pages=2587–99 | last1 = Grant | first1 = RM | last2 = Lama | first2 = JR | last3 = Anderson | first3 = PL | display-authors = 3 | last4 = et al}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;US Public Health Service [5 October 2014]; Preexposure Prophylaxis for the Prevention of HIV Infection in the United States - 2014 Clinical Practice Guideline https://www.cdc.gov/hiv/pdf/PrEPguidelines2014.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; A number of HIV researchers like [[Anthony S. Fauci]] have been positive about the drug,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/2010/11/24/131569907/dr-fauci-optimisitic-about-hiv-drug-truvada|title=Dr. Fauci Optimisitic About HIV Drug Truvada|date=24 November 2010|work=NPR.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://time.com/4114402/aids-hiv-drug-prep/|title=PrEP Truvada: AIDS Drug Prevents HIV Infections, Study Finds|author=Alice Park|work=TIME.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[AIDS Healthcare Foundation]] has written to the [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention|CDC]] expressing concern that Truvada promotion would harm [[safer sex]] messaging that encourages condom use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis to Prevent HIV Infection: Current Status, Future Opportunities and Challenges | pmc=4354703 | pmid=25673022 | doi=10.1007/s40265-015-0355-4 | volume=75 | year=2015 | journal=Drugs | pages=243–51 | last1 = Krakower | first1 = DS | last2 = Mayer | first2 = KH}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2015/12/truvada-hiv-prep-stigma/418119/|title=The Danger in Comparing the HIV-Prevention Pill to Condoms|author=John Byrne|work=The Atlantic}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://reason.com/archives/2014/05/08/truvada-chill-pill-or-party-drug |title=Truvada: Chill Pill or Party Drug? |first=Scott |last=Shackford |work=reason.com |date=8 May 2014 |accessdate=15 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dish.andrewsullivan.com/2014/04/09/why-arent-gay-men-on-the-pill/|title=Why Aren’t Gay Men On The Pill? « The Dish|work=The Dish}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wsEgg6EOpNM|title=Stopping HIV? The Truvada Revolution (Full Length)|date=26 June 2015|work=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase "Truvada whore" has been used in the media&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=How Stigma Surrounding the Use of HIV Preexposure Prophylaxis Undermines Prevention and Pleasure: A Call to Destigmatize "Truvada Whores" | pmc=4566537 | pmid=26270298 | doi=10.2105/AJPH.2015.302816 | volume=105 | journal=Am J Public Health | pages=1960–4 | last1 = Calabrese | first1 = SK | last2 = Underhill | first2 = K}}&lt;/ref&gt; and some openly gay men are afraid to disclose that they use Truvada,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.out.com/news-opinion/2013/09/09/hiv-prevention-new-condom-truvada-pill-prep|title=The pill Truvada can prevent HIV: So why are so few gay men taking it?|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; while take up rates have been lower than expected. Some reports indicate that gay men who use Truvada to lower their risk of contracting HIV are shamed for doing so, based on perceptions that Truvada users are more promiscuous.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/sep/18/truvada-mircle-pill-prevent-hiv-controversy|title=Truvada has been called the 'miracle' HIV pill – so why is uptake so slow?|author=Amanda Holpuch|work=the Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.smh.com.au/good-weekend/truvada--the-other-little-blue-pill-20141128-11l1od.html|title=Truvada – the other little blue pill|work=The Sydney Morning Herald}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

Some gay rights activists have said that environments which have bottom-shaming are more likely to lead to gay men engaging in practices which lead to increased rates of HIV infection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.advocate.com/commentary/2014/09/08/op-ed-slut-shaming-cause-hiv |title=Op-ed: It Is Time to End Bottom-Shaming |work=[[The Advocate]] |date=8 September 2014 |accessdate=15 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--One opinion on slut-shaming in men is that calling a man a "slut" is not as pejorative as it is in using the word against women, and that the term has more of a positive connotation with men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.salon.com/2012/02/10/she_called_me_a_manwhore/ |title=She called me a "manwhore" |first=Tracy |last=Clark-Flory |work=[[Salon (website)|Salon]] |date=9 February 2012 |accessdate=15 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Some gay males see the behaviors which are said to encourage slut-shaming as actually being positive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.gmfa.org.uk/Sites/fsmagazine/pages/gay-slut-shaming-stop-it-stop-it-right-now |title=Gay slut shaming – stop it, stop it right now! |first=Saif |last=A |website=GMFA|date=April 2013 |accessdate=15 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

==See also==
*[[Honor killing]]
*[[Madonna–whore complex]]
*[[Post-assault treatment of sexual assault victims]]
*[[Sexual bullying]]
*[[Victim blaming]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

[[Category:Bullying]]
[[Category:Feminism and sexuality]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Misogyny]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]
[[Category:Misogynistic slurs]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination]]
[[Category:Birth control]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>