<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041106054733|7147772" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="38899" pageid="38899" ns="0" title="Mattachine Society"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-06T05:49:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''Mattachine Society of New York, Inc.''' was an early [[gay rights]] organization. It was founded by [[Harry Hay]] and first met in [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]] on November 11, [[1950]] with Harry, Rudi Gernreich, Bob Hull, Chuck Rowland, and Dale Jennings in attendance, but was not incorporated until [[1961]]. Several other related organizations were formed shortly afterward in [[New York]], [[Boston]], [[Chicago]], [[Denver, Colorado|Denver]], the [[District of Columbia]], and [[Philadelphia]].  The primary goal of the society was to encourage the public to view homosexuals as a persecuted minority rather than mental deviants.

All of the Mattachine founders were affiliated with Communism and based the organization on the cell structure of the [[Communist Party USA|American Communist Party]].  As the [[Red Scare]] progressed the communist associations concerned some members and supporters, and Hay stepped down as the society's leader.  Others who were similarly ousted were replaced by comparitavely conservative leaders.

The Mattachine Society was named after [[Mattacino]] (or the Anglicized Mattachino), a character in Italian theater. Mattacino was a kind of court [[jester]], who would speak the truth to the king when nobody else would.  The "mattachin" (from Arabic mutawajjihin&amp;mdash;"mask-wearers") were originally Moorish (Hispano-Arab) sword-dancers who wore elaborate, colorful costumes and masks.

The Mattachine Society's goal was to liberate the oppressed homosexual community and provide a variety of services to the gay community, including referral services for legal and other professionals, and counselling. They also lobbied for the repeal of sodomy laws and other laws gay people considered discriminatory.

It was associated with other groups in ECHO ([[East Coast Homophile Organizations]]).

During the [[1960s]], Mattachine was one of the foremost gay rights groups in the United States. Following the [[Stonewall riots]] of [[1969]], it became increasingly seen as stodgy and traditional, and not willing enough to be confrontational. It lost support, and fell prey to infighting. Eventually it closed due to impending bankruptcy, and was disbanded in January of [[1987]].

[[Category:LGBT rights organizations]]
[[Category:U.S. history of LGBT rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>