<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221030231550|1119141437" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="38899" pageid="38899" ns="0" title="Mattachine Society"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-09T12:12:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American gay male advocacy group}}
{{use mdy dates|date=June 2019}}
{{Infobox organization
| bgcolor       = &lt;!-- header background color --&gt;
| fgcolor       = &lt;!-- header text color --&gt;
| image         = Mattachine Review 1959.jpg
| image_border  = 
| size          = 150px
| alt           = Front cover of the May 1959 issue of the Mattachine Review, an American LGBT magazine
| caption       = The May 1959 issue of the ''Mattachine Review'', an American LGBT magazine
| map           = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| msize         = &lt;!-- map size, optional, default 250px --&gt;
| malt          = &lt;!-- map alt text --&gt;
| mcaption      = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| map2          = 
| abbreviation  = 
| motto         = 
| predecessor   = 
| successor     = 
| formation     = 1950 &lt;!-- {{Start date and years ago|YYYY|MM|DD}} --&gt;
| extinction    = &lt;!-- date of extinction, optional --&gt;
| type          = &lt;!-- [[Governmental organization|GO]], [[Non-governmental organization|NGO]], [[Intergovernmental organization|IGO]], [[International nongovernmental organization|INGO]], etc --&gt;
| status        = &lt;!-- ad hoc, treaty, foundation, etc --&gt;
| purpose       = [[Civil and political rights]] for [[homosexual men]]
| headquarters  = [[Los Angeles]], [[California]], United States
| location      = 
| coords        = &lt;!-- Coordinates of location using a coordinates template --&gt;
| region_served = 
| membership    = 
| language      = English
| general       = &lt;!-- Secretary General --&gt;
| leader_title  = &lt;!-- position title for the leader of the org --&gt;
| leader_name   = &lt;!-- name of leader --&gt;
| leader_title2 = 
| leader_name2  = 
| leader_title3 = 
| leader_name3  = 
| leader_title4 = 
| leader_name4  = 
| key_people    = [[Harry Hay]]
| main_organ    = &lt;!-- gral. assembly, board of directors, etc --&gt;
| parent_organization = &lt;!-- if one --&gt;
| affiliations  = &lt;!-- if any --&gt;
| budget        = 
| num_staff     = 
| num_volunteers = 
| website       = 
| remarks       = 
| former name   = 
}}
The '''Mattachine Society''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|m|æ|t|ə|ʃ|iː|n}}), founded in 1950, was an early national [[LGBT social movements|gay rights]] organization in the [[United States]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Alexandra|first=Rae|date=November 26, 2019|title=The Transgender Community Builder Who Educated Doctors—Including Kinsey|url=https://www.kqed.org/arts/13870056/the-transgender-community-builder-who-educated-doctors-including-kinsey|url-status=live|access-date=2021-11-28|website=KQED|language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt; perhaps preceded only by [[Chicago]]'s [[Society for Human Rights]].{{citation needed|date=March 2021}} Communist and labor activist [[Harry Hay]] formed the group with a collection of male friends in [[Los Angeles]] to protect and improve the rights of [[gay men]]. Branches formed in other cities, and by 1961 the Society had splintered into regional groups.

At the beginning of gay rights protest, news on [[Cuba]]n prison work camps for homosexuals inspired Mattachine Society to organize protests at the [[United Nations]] and the [[White House]] in 1965.&lt;ref name=DB&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://www.thedailybeast.com/fidel-castros-horrific-record-on-gay-rights|title=Fidel Castro's Horrific Record on Gay Rights|date=27 November 2016|journal=Daily Beast|last1=Kirchick|first1=James}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=jA8l8EYcnHsC&amp;pg=PA76| title = Rethinking the Gay and Lesbian Movement| first = Marc |last=Stein| date = 2012| publisher = Routledge| isbn = 978-0-415-87410-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Name ==
The Mattachine Society was named by Harry Hay at the suggestion of James Gruber, inspired by a French medieval and renaissance [[masque]] group he had studied while preparing a course on the history of popular music for a workers' education project. In a 1976 interview with Jonathan Ned Katz, Hay was asked the origin of the name Mattachine. He mentioned the medieval-Renaissance French ''[[Sociétés Joyeuses]]'':

{{blockquote|One [[masque]] group was known as the "Société Mattachine." These societies, lifelong secret fraternities of unmarried townsmen who never performed in public unmasked, were dedicated to going out into the countryside and conducting dances and rituals during the [[Feast of Fools]], at the Vernal [[Equinox]]. Sometimes these dance rituals, or masques, were peasant protests against oppression—with the maskers, in the people's name, receiving the brunt of a given lord's vicious retaliation. So we took the name Mattachine because we felt that we 1950s Gays were also a masked people, unknown and anonymous, who might become engaged in morale building and helping ourselves and others, through struggle, to move toward total redress and change.|Jonathan Katz|''Gay American History''. Crowell Publishers, 1976.&lt;ref name="katz"&gt;Katz, Jonathan. ''Gay American History''. Crowell Publishers; 1976.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

This French group was named in turn after [[Mattaccino]] (or the Anglicized Mattachino), a character in Italian theater. Mattaccino was a kind of court [[jester]], who would speak the truth to the king when nobody else would. The "mattachin" (from [[Arabic language|Arabic]] ''mutawajjihin''—"mask-wearers") were originally [[Moors|Moorish]] (Hispano-Arab) sword-dancers who wore elaborate, colorful costumes and masks.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Johansson|Percy|1994|p=92}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mattachine Society used so-called [[harlequin]] diamonds as their [[emblem]]. The design consisted of four diamonds arranged in a pattern to form a larger diamond.

== Foundation ==
[[Harry Hay]] conceived the idea of a gay activist group in 1948.&lt;ref name=NMAH_AC&gt;{{cite web|last1=Robinson| first1=Franklin A. Jr. |title=Guide to the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender (LGBT) Collection, NMAH.AC.1146|url=http://amhistory.si.edu/archives/AC1146.pdf|website=Smithsonian Institution National Museum of American History Archives Center|publisher=Smithsonian Institution|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150606230829/http://amhistory.si.edu/archives/AC1146.pdf|archive-date=2015-06-06|pages=55–58| date=2009 | url-status =&lt;!--live--&gt; dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; After signing a petition for [[Progressive Party (United States, 1948)|Progressive Party]] presidential candidate [[Henry A. Wallace]], Hay spoke with other gay men at a party about forming a gay support organization for him called "Bachelors for Wallace".&lt;ref name = miller333 /&gt; Encouraged by the response he received, Hay wrote the organizing principles that night, a document he referred to as "The Call".&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hay|1996|p=61}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the men who had been interested at the party were less than enthusiastic the following morning.&lt;ref name = miller333&gt;Miller, p. 333&lt;/ref&gt; Over the next two years, Hay refined his idea, finally conceiving of an "international... fraternal order" to serve as "a service and welfare organization devoted to the protection and improvement of Society's Androgynous Minority".&lt;ref&gt;Hay, quoted in {{harvnb|Hay|1996|p=63}}&lt;/ref&gt; He planned to call this organization "Bachelors Anonymous" and envisioned it serving a similar function and purpose as [[Alcoholics Anonymous]].&lt;ref&gt;Hay, quoted in {{harvnb|Hay|1996|p=65}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hay met [[Rudi Gernreich]] in July 1950. The two became partners,{{efn|Hay and Gernreich were together until 1952, when Gernreich ended the relationship.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hay|1996|p=359}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} and Hay showed Gernreich The Call. Gernreich, declaring the document "the most dangerous thing [he had] ever read",&lt;ref name=progressive&gt;{{cite news |last = Cusac |first = Anne-Marie |title = Harry Hay Interview |work = The Progressive |date = September 1999 |url = http://progressive.org/mag_cusachay |access-date = 2009-04-26 |url-status = live |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20090519203033/http://progressive.org/mag_cusachay |archive-date = 2009-05-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; became an enthusiastic financial supporter of the venture, although he did not lend his name to it&lt;ref&gt;Ehrenstein,{{who|date=June 2019}} p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; (going instead by the initial "R").&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Emilio|1983|p=62}}&lt;/ref&gt; Finally on November 11, 1950, Hay, along with Gernreich and friends [[Dale Jennings (activist)|Dale Jennings]] and partners [[Bob Hull]] and Chuck Rowland, held the first meeting of the Mattachine Society in Los Angeles, under the name '''Society of Fools'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hogan|Hudson|1998|pp=382–3}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[James Gruber]] and Konrad Stevens joined the Society in April 1951 and they are generally considered to be original members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Van |first=Jim |url=http://www.ebar.com/news/article.php?sec=news&amp;article=5543 |title=James Gruber, last original Mattachine member, dies |publisher=Ebar.com |access-date=2013-12-05 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140104205608/http://www.ebar.com/news/article.php?sec=news&amp;article=5543 |archive-date=2014-01-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Also that month the group changed its name to ''Mattachine Society'', a name suggested by Gruber and chosen by Hay, after Medieval French secret societies of masked men who, through their anonymity, were empowered to criticize ruling monarchs with impunity.&lt;ref name=rhh&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bostonphoenix.com/boston/news_features/other_stories/documents/02511115.htm|title=The real Harry Hay|date=2002-11-07|access-date=2008-11-16|first=Michael|last=Bronski|newspaper=[[The Phoenix (newspaper)|The Phoenix]]|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090530123601/http://bostonphoenix.com/boston/news_features/other_stories/documents/02511115.htm|archive-date=2009-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Mattxmas.jpg|200px|thumb|Members of the Mattachine Society in a rare group photograph. Pictured are Harry Hay (upper left), then (l–r) Konrad Stevens, Dale Jennings, Rudi Gernreich, Stan Witt, Bob Hull, Chuck Rowland (in glasses), Paul Bernard. Photo by James Gruber.]]

As Hay became more involved in his Mattachine work, he correspondingly became more concerned that his orientation would negatively affect the Communist Party, which like most other organizations at the time was anti-homosexual and did not allow gay people to be members. Hay himself approached party leaders and recommended his own expulsion. The party decided to expel him as a "security risk", but declared him a "Lifelong Friend of the People" in recognition of his previous work for the party.&lt;ref name="workers"&gt;{{Cite news |title=Harry Hay: Painful partings |first=Leslie |last=Feinberg |date=June 28, 2005 |access-date=2007-11-01 |url=http://www.workers.org/2005/us/lavender-red-40/ |periodical=[[Workers World Party|Workers World]] |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070930015105/http://www.workers.org/2005/us/lavender-red-40/ |archive-date=September 30, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mattachine was originally organized in similar structure to the Communist Party, with cells, oaths of secrecy and five different levels of membership, each of which required greater levels of involvement and commitment. As the organization grew, the levels were expected to subdivide into new cells, creating both the potential for horizontal and vertical growth.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Emilio|1983|p=64}}&lt;/ref&gt; The founding members constituted the so-called "Fifth Order" and from the outset remained anonymous. The primary goals of the society were to

# "Unify homosexuals isolated from their own kind";
# "Educate homosexuals and heterosexuals toward an ethical homosexual culture paralleling the cultures of the Negro, Mexican and Jewish peoples";
# "Lead the more socially conscious homosexual to provide leadership to the whole mass of social variants"; and
# "Assist gays who are victimized daily as a result of oppression".&lt;ref name="katz" /&gt;

Mattachine's membership grew slowly at first but received a major boost in February 1952 when founder Jennings was arrested in a Los Angeles park and charged with lewd behavior. Often, men in Jennings' situation would simply plead guilty to the charge and hope to quietly rebuild their lives. Jennings and the rest of the Fifth Order saw the charges as a means to address the issue of police entrapment of homosexual men. The group began publicizing the case (under the name "Citizens Committee to Outlaw Entrapment") and the publicity it generated brought in financial support and volunteers. Jennings admitted during his trial to being a homosexual but insisted he was not guilty of the specific charge. The jury deadlocked and Mattachine declared victory.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Emilio|1983|pp=69–70}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Affiliations ==
Most of the Mattachine founders were [[communist]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Gutterman |first1=Lauren Jae |title=Her Neighbor's Wife: A History of Lesbian Desire Within Marriage |date=1 November 2019 |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press |isbn=978-0-8122-5174-6 |page=79 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WzPEDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA79 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Edsall |first1=Nicholas C. |title=Toward Stonewall: Homosexuality and Society in the Modern Western World |date=2006 |publisher=University of Virginia Press |isbn=978-0-8139-2543-1 |page=276 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0qjwZeKNyh4C&amp;pg=PA276 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the [[Second Red Scare|Red Scare]] progressed, the association with communism concerned some members as well as supporters and Hay, a dedicated member of the [[Communist Party USA|CPUSA]] for 15 years, stepped down as the Society's leader. Others were similarly ousted, and the leadership structure became influenced less by communism,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Peattie |first1=Lisa Redfield |title=The Blue Guitar |date=30 March 2014 |publisher=Lisa Redfield Peattie |isbn=978-1-311-62368-3 |page=68 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ke3-AgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT68 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; replaced by a moderate ideology similar to that espoused by the liberal reformist [[civil rights]] organizations that existed for [[African American]]s. Although Hay claimed "never to have even heard" of the earlier [[gay liberation]] struggle in [[Germany]]—by the people around [[Adolf Brand]], [[Magnus Hirschfeld]] and the [[Austrian-Hungarian]] [[Leontine Sagan]]—he is known to have talked about it with German émigrés in America, including the [[Austria]]n-born [[Rudi Gernreich]].{{citation needed|date=February 2015}}

The Mattachine Society existed as a single national organization headquartered first in Los Angeles and then, beginning around 1956, in San Francisco. Outside of Los Angeles and San Francisco, chapters were established in New York; Washington, D.C.; Chicago; and other locales. Due to internal disagreements, the national organization disbanded in 1961. The San Francisco national chapter retained the name "Mattachine Society", while the New York chapter became "[[Mattachine Society of New York, Inc]]" and was commonly known by its acronym MSNY. Other independent groups using the name Mattachine were formed in Washington, D.C. ([[Frank Kameny|Mattachine Society of Washington]], 1961),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Rainbow History Project |url=http://www.rainbowhistory.org/kameny.htm |title=Kameny |publisher=Rainbowhistory.org |date=1964-07-22 |access-date=2009-11-05 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090707035005/http://www.rainbowhistory.org/kameny.htm |archive-date=2009-07-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt; in Chicago ([[Mattachine Midwest]], 1965),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.glhalloffame.org/index.pl?item=29&amp;todo=view_item |title=Chicago Gay and Lesbian Hall of Fame |publisher=Glhalloffame.org |access-date=2009-11-05 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090520005109/http://www.glhalloffame.org/index.pl?item=29&amp;todo=view_item |archive-date=2009-05-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and in Buffalo ([[Mattachine Society of the Niagara Frontier]], 1970).&lt;ref&gt;[[Madeline Davis]]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1963 Congressman [[John Dowdy]] introduced a bill which resulted in congressional hearings to revoke the license for solicitation of funds of the Mattachine Society of Washington; the license was not revoked.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Johnson | first = David K. | title = The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government | place = Chicago | publisher = University of Chicago Press | year = 2004 | page =186 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=gbfOrkS5ziAC&amp;pg=PA186 | isbn = 0-226-40481-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A largely amicable split within the national Society in 1952 resulted in a new organization called [[ONE, Inc.]] ONE admitted women and, together with Mattachine, provided help to the [[Daughters of Bilitis]] in the launching of that group's magazine, ''[[The Ladder (magazine)|The Ladder]]'', in 1956. The [[Daughters of Bilitis]] were an independent [[lesbian]] organization who occasionally worked with the predominantly male Mattachine Society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Metcalf|first=Meg|title=Research Guides: LGBTQIA+ Studies: A Resource Guide: The Daughters of Bilitis|url=https://guides.loc.gov/lgbtq-studies/before-stonewall/daughters-of-bilitis|url-status=live|access-date=2021-08-18|website=guides.loc.gov|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Janus Society]] grew out of lesbian and gay activists meeting regularly, beginning in 1961, in hopes of forming a Mattachine Society chapter. The group was not officially recognized as such a chapter, however, and so instead named itself the Janus Society of Delaware Valley. In 1964 they renamed themselves the Janus Society of America due to their increasing national visibility.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/kt3779r083/|title = Finding aid of the Janus Society Records}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 1962 [[East Coast Homophile Organizations]] (ECHO) was established, with its formative membership including the Mattachine Society chapters in New York and Washington D.C., the [[Janus Society]], and the [[Daughters of Bilitis]] chapter in New York. ECHO was meant to facilitate cooperation between homophile organizations and outside administrations.&lt;ref&gt;ECHO Monthly, 26 Jan.-1 Sept., 1963&lt;/ref&gt; In 1964, ECHO received a $500 settlement from the Manger Hamilton hotel upon the hotel's last minute cancellation of ECHO's conference in their location. This out of court settlement was portrayed by the organization as an affirmation to the homophile community that they were not to mess with and that any matters that violated their rights would be handled in accordance with the law.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=June 1966 |title=The Homosexual Citizen |url=http://www.rainbowhistory.org/THC0666.pdf |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120214121714/http://www.rainbowhistory.org/THC0666.pdf |archive-date=14 February 2012 |access-date=2022-05-20 |website=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the eve of January 1, 1965, several homophile organizations in San Francisco, California - including Mattachine, the [[Daughters of Bilitis]], the [[Council on Religion and the Homosexual]], and the [[Society for Individual Rights]] - held a fund-raising ball for their mutual benefit at California Hall on Polk Street.&lt;ref name="miller_p348"&gt;Miller, Neil (1995). ''Out of the Past: Gay and Lesbian History from 1869 to the present.'' New York: Vintage Books. pp. 348. {{ISBN|978-0679749882}}.&lt;/ref&gt; San Francisco police had agreed not to interfere; however, on the evening of the ball, the police surrounded the building and focused numerous [[Klieg lights]] on its entrance. As each of the 600 plus persons entering the ball approached the entrance, the police took their photographs.&lt;ref name="miller_p348" /&gt;  Police vans were parked in plain view near the entrance to the ball.&lt;ref name="miller_p348" /&gt; [[Evander Smith]], a (gay) lawyer for the groups organizing the ball, and gay lawyer [[Herb Donaldson (lawyer)|Herb Donaldson]] tried to stop the police from conducting the fourth "inspection" of the evening; both were arrested, along with two heterosexual lawyers - Elliott Leighton and Nancy May - who were supporting the rights of the participants to gather at the ball.&lt;ref name="miller_p348" /&gt; But twenty-five of the most prominent lawyers in San Francisco joined the defense team for the four lawyers, and the judge directed the jury to find the four not-guilty before the defense had even had a chance to begin their argumentation when the case came to court.&lt;ref name="miller_p348" /&gt; This event has been called "San Francisco's [[Stonewall riots|Stonewall]]" by some historians;&lt;ref name="miller_p348" /&gt; the participation of such prominent litigators in the defense of Smith, Donaldson and the other two lawyers marked a turning point in gay rights on the West Coast of the United States.&lt;ref name="cain"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Cain|first=Patricia A.|title=Litigating for Lesbian and Gay Rights: A Legal History|journal=Virginia Law Review|date=Oct 1993|volume=79|issue=7 Symposium on Sexual Orientation and the Law|pages=1551–1641|doi=10.2307/1073382|jstor=1073382|url=https://digitalcommons.law.scu.edu/facpubs/277}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Decline ==
Following the Jennings trial, the group expanded rapidly, with founders estimating membership in California by May 1953 at over 2,000 with as many as 100 people joining a typical discussion group. Membership diversified, with more women and people from a broader political spectrum becoming involved. With that growth came concern about the radical left slant of the organization. In particular, [[Hal Call]] and others out of San Francisco along with Ken Burns from Los Angeles wanted Mattachine to amend its constitution to clarify its opposition to so-called "subversive elements" and to affirm that members were loyal to the United States and its laws (which declared homosexuality illegal). In an effort to preserve their vision of the organization, the Fifth Order members revealed their identities and resigned their leadership positions at Mattachine's May 1953 convention. With the founders gone, Call, Burns and other like-minded individuals stepped into the leadership void,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Loughery|1998|pp=228–29}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Mattachine officially adopted non-confrontation as an organizational policy. Some historians argue that these changes reduced the effectiveness of this newly organized Mattachine and led to a precipitous drop in membership and participation.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hogan|Hudson|1998|p=383}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other historians contend that the Mattachine Society between 1953 and 1966 was enormously effective as it published a magazine, developed relationships with allies in the fight for homosexual equality, and influenced public opinion on the topic too.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Meeker|2006|pp=37–76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1960s, the various unaffiliated Mattachine Societies, especially the Mattachine Society in San Francisco and MSNY, were among the foremost gay rights groups in the United States, but beginning in the middle 1960s and, especially, following the [[Stonewall riots]] of 1969, they began increasingly to be seen as too traditional, and not willing enough to be confrontational. Like the divide that occurred within the [[Civil Rights Movement]], the late 1960s and the 1970s brought a new generation of activists, many of whom felt that the gay rights movement needed to endorse a larger and more radical agenda to address other forms of oppression, the [[Vietnam War]], and the [[sexual revolution]]. Several unaffiliated entities that went under the name Mattachine eventually lost support or fell prey to internal division.{{citation needed|date=December 2021}}

In 1973 Hal Call opened the Cinemattachine, a venue showing both Mattachine newsreels and pornographic movies.  The Cinemattachine was an extension of the Mattachine Society's Sex Education Film Series and branded as being presented by both The Mattachine Society and The Seven Committee.  In 1976 a venue with the name ''Cinemattachine Los Angeles at the ONE'' opened. The same screenings as the San Francisco establishment were shown there. Mattachine co-founder Chuck Rowland indicated that he did not feel that Call associating this venue with The Mattachine Society was appropriate.&lt;ref name="Cinemattachine"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hilderbrand |first=Lucas |date=June 1, 2016 |title=The uncut version: The Mattachine Society's pornographic epilogue |doi=10.1177/1363460715599159 |journal=Sexualities |volume=19 |issue=4 |pages=449–464|s2cid=147679455 |url=https://escholarship.org/uc/item/79f5x20t }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legacy ==
[[File:The Mattachine Steps 2017.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Mattachine Steps]] in 2017.]]
In the ''[[Quantum Leap]]'' comic book titled ''Up Against a Stonewall'' (1992), the Mattachine Society and the [[Daughters of Bilitis]] are mentioned as two groups campaigning for LGBT rights prior to the [[Stonewall riots]].

The 1995 film ''[[Stonewall (1995 film)|Stonewall]]'' included members of the Mattachine Society of New York among its characters. Mattachine members are seen leafleting, attending meetings and participating in the [[Annual Reminder]] picket in Philadelphia. However, the film sets the Reminder earlier in the summer than it really was, predating the June 28 [[Stonewall riots]].

In 2002 Mattachine Midwest was inducted into the [[Chicago Gay and Lesbian Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glhalloffame.org/index.pl?page%3Dinductees%26todo%3Dyear |title=Chicago Gay and Lesbian Hall of Fame |access-date=2016-01-10 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151017032241/http://www.glhalloffame.org/index.pl?page=inductees&amp;todo=year |archive-date=2015-10-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009 the Mattachine Society and its founders became the subjects of the play ''[[The Temperamentals]]'' by [[Jon Marans]]. After workshop performances in 2009, the play opened [[Off-Broadway]] at [[New World Stages]] in early 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |last        = Brantley
 |first       = Ben
 |title       = The Churning Insides of a Quiet Revolution
 |work        = The New York Times
 |date        = 2010-03-01
 |url         = http://theater.nytimes.com/2010/03/01/theater/reviews/01temper.html?pagewanted=1
 |access-date  = 2010-05-23
 |url-status     = live
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20120329104437/http://theater.nytimes.com/2010/03/01/theater/reviews/01temper.html?pagewanted=1
 |archive-date = 2012-03-29
}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Temperamentals'' received a [[Drama Desk Award]] for Best Ensemble Cast. [[Michael Urie]], who originated the role of Rudi Gernreich, received a [[Lucille Lortel Awards|Lucille Lortel Award]] for Outstanding Lead Actor.&lt;ref name=arts&gt;{{cite news
 |last        = Healy
 |first       = Patrick
 |title       = Honors and the End for 'Temperamentals'
 |work        = The New York Times
 |date        = 2010-05-10
 |url         = https://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/06/theater/06arts-HONORSANDTHE_BRF.html
 |access-date  = 2010-05-23
 |url-status     = live
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20100512200753/http://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/06/theater/06arts-HONORSANDTHE_BRF.html
 |archive-date = 2010-05-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A new [[Mattachine Society of Washington]], D.C. was formed in 2011 and is dedicated to original archival research of LGBT political history.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.washingtonblade.com/2014/05/14/new-mattachine-society-d-c-uncovers-lgbt-history/ "New Mattachine Society of D.C. uncovers LGBT history"] ''Washington Blade'', May 14, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The Playboy Club]]'', a 2011 television series on [[NBC]], includes a lesbian [[Playboy Bunny]] in a [[lavender marriage]] with a gay man. The two are members of the Chicago Mattachine chapter.

The [[Mattachine Steps]], also known as the Cove Avenue stairway, is an outdoor staircase in [[Silver Lake, Los Angeles|Silver Lake]], [[Los Angeles]], dedicated to the Mattachine Society in 2012 in memory of its founder [[Harry Hay]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://blogs.presstelegram.com/outinthe562/2014/03/21/gay-history-silver-lake-steps-dedicated-to-pioneering-los-angeles-gay-rights-group-mattachine-society/|title=Gay History: Silver Lake steps dedicated to pioneering Los Angeles gay rights group Mattachine Society|date=2014-03-21|work=Out in the 562|access-date=2018-06-17|language=en-US|archive-date=June 17, 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180617042855/http://blogs.presstelegram.com/outinthe562/2014/03/21/gay-history-silver-lake-steps-dedicated-to-pioneering-los-angeles-gay-rights-group-mattachine-society/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://la.curbed.com/2016/6/1/11836978/silver-lake-mattachine-society-steps-hay|title=How Steps in Silver Lake Honor LA's LGBT Movement|work=Curbed LA|access-date=2018-06-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zpnOaFgMTa8C&amp;pg=PA222|title=Land of Smoke and Mirrors: A Cultural History of Los Angeles|last=Brook|first=Vincent|date=2013-01-22|publisher=Rutgers University Press|isbn=9780813554587|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, a gay bar called Bar Mattachine opened in downtown Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://la.eater.com/2015/10/6/9463581/bar-mattachine-downtown-los-angeles-gay-craft-cocktail-bar#4847752|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160611194617/http://la.eater.com/2015/10/6/9463581/bar-mattachine-downtown-los-angeles-gay-craft-cocktail-bar |archive-date=2016-06-11|title=Bar Mattachine Is a Classy Gay Cocktail Bar for Downtown Los Angeles|first=Matthew|last=Kang|date=October 6, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[podcast]] "[[Making Gay History]]" (season 1, episode 7) is about Mattachine co-founder Chuck Rowland, and another episode is about Mattachine co-founder [[Harry Hay]] (season 4, episode 3).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://makinggayhistory.com/season-four/ |title=Season Four |publisher=Making Gay History |date=2018-11-24 |access-date=2020-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://makinggayhistory.com/season-one/ |title=Season One |publisher=Making Gay History |access-date=2020-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Julius (restaurant)|Julius’ bar]] in Manhattan has held a monthly party called "Mattachine" honoring the early gay rights pioneers.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;[http://www.villagevoice.com/news/0825,before-stonewall,471396,1.html Before Stonewall: Remembering that, before the riots, there was a Sip-In] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080701034431/http://www.villagevoice.com/news/0825%2Cbefore-stonewall%2C471396%2C1.html|date=July 1, 2008}} ''The Village Voice''. June 17, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|LGBT}}
* [[Dick Leitsch]]
* [[LGBT rights in the United States]]
* [[List of LGBT rights organizations]]
* [[Radical Faeries]]
* [[Timeline of LGBT history]]

== References ==
'''Notes'''
{{notelist}}

'''Citations'''
{{Reflist}}

'''Bibliography'''
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=D'Emilio|first=John|date=1983|title=Sexual Politics, Sexual Communities: The Making of a Homosexual Minority in the United States, 1940–1970|location=Chicago|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|isbn=0-226-14265-5|oclc=300567643|url=https://archive.org/details/sexualpoliticsse00demi}}
* {{cite book|last=Hay|first=Harry|editor-first=Will|editor-last=Roscoe|date=1996|title=Radically Gay: Gay Liberation in the Words of its Founder|location=Boston|publisher=Beacon Press|isbn=0-8070-7080-7|oclc=33333896}}
* {{cite book|last1=Hogan|first1=Steve|first2=Lee|last2=Hudson|date=1998|title=Completely Queer: The Gay and Lesbian Encyclopedia|location=New York|publisher=Henry Holt and Company|isbn=0-8050-3629-6|oclc=34731659}}
* {{cite book|last1=Johansson|first1=Warren|first2=William A.|last2=Percy|date=1994|title=Outing: Shattering the Conspiracy of Silence|url=https://archive.org/details/outing00warr|url-access=registration|location=New York|publisher=Haworth Press|isbn=1-56024-419-4|oclc=28026413}}
* {{cite book|last=Loughery|first=John|date=1998|title=The Other Side of Silence: Men's Lives and Gay Identities: A Twentieth-Century History|location=New York, Henry Holt and Company|isbn=0-8050-3896-5|oclc=38096858|url=https://archive.org/details/othersideofsile000loug}}
* {{cite book|last=Meeker|first=Martin|date=2006|title=Contacts Desired: Gay and Lesbian Communications and Community, 1940s–1970s|publisher=University of Chicago Press|url=http://www.press.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/hfs.cgi/00/167324.ctl|access-date=November 1, 2006|archive-date=December 11, 2006|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061211073557/http://www.press.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/hfs.cgi/00/167324.ctl|url-status=dead}}
* Miller, Neil (1995). ''Out of the Past: Gay and Lesbian History from 1869 to the Present''. New York: Vintage Books. {{ISBN|0-09-957691-0}}. {{oclc|33009776}}.
{{Refend}}

== Further reading ==
* Boyd, Nan Alamilla. [http://www.ucpress.edu/books/pages/9912.html ''Wide Open Town: A History of Queer San Francisco to 1965'']. University of California Press, 2003.
* Bullough, Vern L. [https://web.archive.org/web/20060221073022/http://williamapercy.com/pub-Stonewall.htm ''Before Stonewall: Activists for Gay and Lesbian Rights in Historical Context'']. Harrington Park Press, 2002.
* Carter, David. [http://www.holtzbrinckpublishers.com/stmartins/search/SearchBookDisplay.asp?BookKey=2587092 ''Stonewall: The Riots That Sparked the Gay Revolution'']. St. Martin's Press, 2004.
* Dynes, Wayne R. (ed.). [https://web.archive.org/web/20060222150409/http://williamapercy.com/pub-EncyHom.htm ''Encyclopedia of Homosexuality'']. New York and London: Garland Publishing, 1990.
* Johnson, David. [http://www.press.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/hfs.cgi/00/15801.ctl ''The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060928052036/http://www.press.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/hfs.cgi/00/15801.ctl |date=September 28, 2006 }}. University of Chicago Press, 2004.
* [http://www.worldcat.org/search?qt=worldcat_org_all&amp;q=mattachine+society Mattachine Society Today], Mattachine Society, 1965.
* Poling, John D. ''Mattachine Midwest: The History of a Chicago Gay Rights Organization, 1965 to 1986'' (thesis, M.S., Illinois State University, 2002).
* Sears, James T. [https://web.archive.org/web/20060512202229/http://www.jtsears.com/mattachine.htm ''Behind the Mask of the Mattachine'']. Harrington Park Press, 2006.
* White, C. Todd. [https://books.google.com/books?id=FnrlybSVp0sC ''Pre-Gay L.A'']. University of Illinois Press, 2009.

== External links ==
* [http://mattachinesocietywashingtondc.org/ Mattachine Society of Washington, D.C.]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120419214800/http://www.williamapercy.com/wiki/images/Mattachine.pdf Mattachine Society, Encyclopedia of Homosexuality]
* [http://www.xanga.com/themattachinesociety Mattachine Society, Shreveport, Louisiana]
* [http://vault.fbi.gov/mattachine-society FBI file on the Mattachine Society]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110718122702/http://www.rainbowhistory.org/msw.htm Documents from the Mattachine Society's archives]
* [http://www.kamenypapers.org/correspondence.htm Mattachine-related correspondence of Franklin Kameny]

{{Early U.S. gay rights movement}}
{{LGBT}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Mattachine Society| ]]
[[Category:1950 establishments in California]]
[[Category:1950s in LGBT history]]
[[Category:Communism in the United States]]
[[Category:Defunct LGBT organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:Gay history]]
[[Category:History of LGBT civil rights in the United States]]
[[Category:LGBT culture in Los Angeles]]
[[Category:LGBT history in California]]
[[Category:LGBT political advocacy groups in California]]
[[Category:LGBT political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1950]]
[[Category:Secret societies in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>