<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050925140016|23995686" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="38899" pageid="38899" ns="0" title="Mattachine Society"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-17T21:45:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''Mattachine Society of New York, Inc.''' was an early [[gay rights]] organization. 

It was founded by [[Harry Hay]] and first met in [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]], on November 11, [[1950]], with Harry, [[Rudi Gernreich]], Bob Hull, Chuck Rowland, and Dale Jennings in attendance, but was not incorporated until [[1961]].  Several other related organizations were formed shortly afterward in [[New York City, New York|New York City]], [[Boston, Massachusetts|Boston]], [[Chicago, Illinois|Chicago]], [[Denver, Colorado|Denver]], the [[District of Columbia]], and [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|Philadelphia]].  The primary goal of the society was to encourage the public to view [[homosexual]]s as a persecuted [[minority]] rather than mental deviants.

The Mattachine Society was named after [[Mattacino]] (or the Anglicized Mattachino), a character in Italian theater.  Mattacino was a kind of court [[jester]], who would speak the truth to the king when nobody else would.  The "mattachin" (from [[Arabic language|Arabic]] ''mutawajjihin''&amp;mdash;"mask-wearers") were originally [[Moorish]] (Hispano-Arab) sword-dancers who wore elaborate, colorful costumes and masks. The Mattachine Society used so-called [[harlequin diamond pattern|harlequin diamonds]] as their [[emblem]]. The design consisted of four diamonds arranged in a pattern to form a larger diamond.

All of the Mattachine founders were affiliated with [[Communism]] and based the organization on the cell structure of the [[Communist Party USA|American Communist Party]].  As the [[Red Scare]] progressed, the association with communism concerned some members as well as supporters and Hay stepped down as the society's leader.  Others were similarly ousted, and the leadership structure became more [[democratic]], with the [[ideology]] of the organization becoming more in tune with the reformist [[civil rights]] organizations that existed for [[African Americans]].

Although Harry Hay claimed "never to have even heard" of the earlier gay liberation struggle in [[Germany]] - by the people around [[Adolf Brand]], [[Magnus Hirschfeld]] and [[Leontine Sagan]] - he is known to have talked about it with German emigrés in America, including Rudi Gernreich.

The Mattachine Society's goal was to liberate the oppressed homosexual community and provide a variety of services to the gay community, including referral services for legal and other professionals, and counselling.  They also lobbied for the repeal of [[sodomy law]]s and other laws that gay people considered discriminatory.  It published ''The Mattachine Review''.

The Mattichine Society was associated with other groups in ECHO ([[East Coast Homophile Organizations]]). There was an amicable split within the Society in 1952, resulting in a new organization called [[ONE, Inc.]].  ONE admitted women, and together with Mattachine, provided vital help to the [[Daughters of Bilitis]] in the launching of Bilitis' newsletter ''The Ladder: a lesbian review'' in [[1956]].  The Daughters of Bilitis was the counterpart lesbian organization to the Mattachine Society, and the two organizations worked together on some campaigns.  Bilitis came under attack, however, in the early 1970s for "siding" with Mattachine rather than with the new separatist [[feminist]]s.

During the [[1960s]], Mattachine was one of the foremost gay rights groups in the United States, but following the [[Stonewall riots]] of [[1969]], it became increasingly seen as stodgy and traditional and not willing enough to be confrontational.  Like the divide that occurred within the black civil rights movement, the late 1960s and the 1970s brought a new generation of gay men who felt that the gay rights movement needed to endorse a larger and more radical agenda to address other forms of oppression, the [[Vietnam War]], and the [[sexual revolution]].  It lost support and fell prey to infighting.  Eventually it closed due to impending [[bankruptcy]] and was disbanded in January of [[1987]].

[[Category:LGBT rights organizations]]
[[Category:U.S. history of LGBT rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>