<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201116045341|988948084" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56103154" pageid="56103154" ns="0" title="Discrimination against drug addicts"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-20T05:15:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{POV|date=May 2020}}
{{More sources|date=May 2020}}
{{cleanup|reason=tone, cohesion, grammar|date=January 2019}}
{{Globalize|article|USA|date=May 2020}}
}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Discrimination against drug addicts''' is a form of [[discrimination]] against individuals who suffer from a [[drug addiction]]. In the process of [[stigmatization]], drug addicts are [[stereotype]]d as having a particular set of undesirable traits, in turn causing other individuals to act in a [[fear]]ful or [[prejudicial]] manner toward them.&lt;ref name="Stigma of addiction part I 2017 review"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Corrigan P, Schomerus G, Shuman V, Kraus D, Perlick D, Harnish A, Kulesza M, Kane-Willis K, Qin S, Smelson D | title = Developing a research agenda for understanding the stigma of addictions Part I: Lessons from the Mental Health Stigma Literature | journal = The American Journal on Addictions | volume = 26 | issue = 1 | pages = 59–66 | date = January 2017 | pmid = 27779803 | doi = 10.1111/ajad.12458 | quote = Social psychologists have distinguished the largely private experience of stigma in general—stereotypes and prejudice—from the more public, behavioral result which is discrimination.[11] Stereotypes are harmful and disrespectful beliefs about a group. Table 1 lists several examples of stereotypes applied to people with addictions including blame, dangerousness, and unpredictability. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Stigma of addiction part II 2017 review"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Corrigan PW, Schomerus G, Shuman V, Kraus D, Perlick D, Harnish A, Kulesza M, Kane-Willis K, Qin S, Smelson D | title = Developing a research agenda for reducing the stigma of addictions, part II: Lessons from the mental health stigma literature | journal = The American Journal on Addictions | volume = 26 | issue = 1 | pages = 67–74 | date = January 2017 | pmid = 27875626 | doi = 10.1111/ajad.12436 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Health professional prejudice and discrimination 1996 review"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = McLaughlin D, Long A | title = An extended literature review of health professionals' perceptions of illicit drugs and their clients who use them | journal = Journal of Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing | volume = 3 | issue = 5 | pages = 283–8 | date = October 1996 | pmid = 9004621 | doi = 10.1111/j.1365-2850.1996.tb00127.x }}&lt;/ref&gt; Drug use discrimination also leads to many users being secretive about drug use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Palamar JJ | title = A pilot study examining perceived rejection and secrecy in relation to illicit drug use and associated stigma | journal = Drug and Alcohol Review | volume = 31 | issue = 4 | pages = 573–9 | date = June 2012 | pmid = 22176135 | doi = 10.1111/j.1465-3362.2011.00406.x }}&lt;/ref&gt; As it relates to healthcare stigmatizing attitudes surrounding drug use can cause barriers to treatment uptake and engagement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Gorrell |first=Michael Gorrell | name-list-style = vanc |date=2011 |title=E-books on EBSCOhost: Combining NetLibrary E-books with the EBSCOhost Platform |journal=Information Standards Quarterly |volume=23 |issue=2 |pages=31 |doi=10.3789/isqv23n2.2011.07 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In some of its manifestations, discrimination against drug addicts involves a violation of [[human rights]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mignews.com/news/society/world/110309_65334_04116.html |title=Комиссар ООН призвала прекратить дискриминацию наркоманов |trans-title=The UN Commissioner urged to stop discrimination of drug addicts |publisher=Mignews |date=2009-03-11 |access-date=2017-12-22 |language=Russian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

People with [[Substance abuse|substance use disorders]] are often depicted as human beings who are not capable of staying drug-free and are often addressed using derogatory terms. The reasoning for not helping patients seek the treatments needed are often due to the terms used to identify them, such as "crackhead" or "junkie".&lt;ref name=":04"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.drugpolicy.org/issues/discrimination-against-drug-users|title=Discrimination Against Drug Users|website=Drug Policy Alliance|language=en|access-date=2018-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The name-calling and stigma place a sense of shame in people with substance use disorder for a disease that takes control of them physically and psychologically. Self-stigmatization is the shame experienced by persons labeled as addict. Their perception of insignificance originates from the biased and uninformed public stigma that excludes the addict from social acceptance. This social exclusion derives from the belief that addiction is a moral defect resulting in negative stereotypes. The negative stereotypes placed on those experiencing addiction is internalized into feelings of shame and guilt, and a motivating factor to continue self-destructive using behaviors.&lt;ref&gt;Matthews S, Dwyer R, Snoek A. “[https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5527047/?report=classic Stigma and Self-Stigma in Addiction.” Journal of bioethical inquiry] vol. 14,2 (2017): 275-286. doi:10.1007/s11673-017-9784-y&lt;/ref&gt; 

Discrimination against people who use an illegal substance is very common in the workplace, a familiar example happens when employers give random drug test to see if the employee will pass it.&lt;ref name=":12"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.asam.org/resources/publications/magazine/read/article/2015/12/15/patients-with-a-substance-use-disorder-need-treatment---not-stigma|title=Patients with Addiction Need Treatment - Not Stigma|website=www.asam.org|access-date=2018-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to the [[Rehabilitation Act of 1973]], employers are supposed to ensure that alcoholics and other drug addicts get help and the accommodations that they need.&lt;ref name=":32"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://eds.b.ebscohost.com/eds/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?vid=2&amp;sid=76b7c82d-df8e-4ed9-9e35-565406e6ea4e@sessionmgr103|title=Laws Prohibiting Employment Discrimination Against the Alcoholic and the Dr...: Discovery Service for Xavier Univ of Louisiana.|website=eds.b.ebscohost.com|language=en|access-date=2018-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The lack of job opportunities and treatment for drug addicts often results in relapses or in jail.

== Basic information ==
{{transcluded section|source=Discrimination}}
{{trim|{{#section-h:Discrimination|Drug use}}}}

Drug abusers often choose the jail system because being in the real world exposes them to the very things that made them turn to drugs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://oceanhillsrecovery.com/blog/leaving-addicted-person-jail-right-choice/|title=Leaving an Addicted Person in Jail: The Right Choice? {{!}} Ocean Hills Recovery|date=2017-12-01|work=Ocean Hills Recovery|access-date=2018-11-27|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many drug users choose jail so they can utilize the Drug Court Program.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.drugwarfacts.org/chapter/drug_courts|title=Drug Courts &amp; Treatment Alternatives to Incarceration|work=Drug War Facts|access-date=2018-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first drug court program was started in 1989 in Florida. The purpose of the drug court program was to put the court's authority in motion to reduce the drug crime rate by offering rehabilitation to drug addicts. In 2015, up to 3,000 drug courts were available in the U.S. and merely 120,000 defendants were being worked with per year. The overall goal of the drug court program is to reduce the need for drugs and the crimes that accompany them. Statistics have led researchers to believe drug court may be an effective resolution to end drug addiction.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://psmag.com/news/drug-courts-are-the-answer-64444|title=Drug Courts Are the Answer: Save Money and Reduce Prison Populations|work=Pacific Standard|access-date=2018-11-27|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Problematic Patterns ==
Drugs (especially [[opioid]]s and [[stimulant]]s) can change the motivational patterns of a person and lead to [[desocialization]] and degradation of personality. Acquisition of the drugs some times involves [[black market]] activities and leads to criminal a social circle.

== Institutional patterns ==

Stigma by health care professionals stems from a belief that people with substance use disorder are not interested in their health as much as they are seeking drugs. This results in people with substance use disorders receiving unfair medical care. As well as hiding their underlying medical concerns and not receiving the medical and recovery care that is needed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Livingston |first1=James D |last2=Milne |first2=Teresa |last3=Fang |first3=Mei Lan |last4=Amari |first4=Erica |title=The effectiveness of interventions for reducing stigma related to substance use disorders: a systematic review |journal=Addiction |date=2012 |volume=107 |issue=1 |pages=39–50 |doi=10.1111/j.1360-0443.2011.03601.x |pmid=21815959 |pmc=3272222 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Healthcare providers have effective tools such as medications for opioid and alcohol addiction that can help prevent many overdoses. These tools are not used widely in the United States healthcare system. The stigma that surrounds drug addicts is the main cause of why the healthcare system does not use these tools and medications. In the United States healthcare system there has not been much done to remove this stigmatism. Many healthcare providers do not view addiction as a disease and a mental illness. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Volkow |first1=Nora |title=Addressing the Stigma that Surrounds Addiction |url=https://www.drugabuse.gov/about-nida/noras-blog/2020/04/addressing-stigma-surrounds-addiction |website=National Institute on Drug Abuse |publisher=National Institute on Drug Abuse |accessdate=16 November 2020 |ref=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The drugs Ritalin ([[methylphenidate]]) and Adderall ([[amphetamine]]) are stimulants often prescribed for ADHD.&lt;ref&gt;https://childmind.org/article/understanding-adhd-medications/&lt;/ref&gt; In colleges there has been an influx of this type of drug trafficked. These drugs stimulate your nervous system making you awake and attentive. 

Prescribing opioids to patients and related overdose has become a serious problem in the US.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.cfr.org/backgrounder/us-opioid-epidemic&lt;/ref&gt;

== Lack of objective information about drugs ==
An important role in the process of discrimination is played by the lack of objective information about drug addiction and drug addicts, caused by legislative barriers to scientific research, the displacement of such information by [[propaganda]] of various kinds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://credonew.ru/content/view/324/28/ |title=Опасности моральной паники по поводу наркотиков |trans-title=The danger of moral panic about drugs |author=П. Мейлахс |date=2003 |publisher=Кредо-Нью |access-date=2017-12-22 |language=Russian |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190209124106/http://credonew.ru/content/view/324/28/ |archive-date=2019-02-09 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Drug addiction has been categorized as a subcategory of mental illness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | vauthors = O'Leary D | date = 2016 | title = Addiction &amp; Mental Illness: Does One Cause the Other? | work = Dual Diagnosis | publisher = Foundations Recovery Network |url=https://www.dualdiagnosis.org/addiction-mental-illness-one-cause/ }}&lt;/ref&gt; They are referred to as co-occurring disorders, which means if a person is dealing with an addiction, they may also struggle with a mental illness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Taylor MF, Coall D, Marquis R, Batten R | title = Drug addiction is a scourge on the earth and my grandchildren are its victims: The tough love and resilient growth exhibited by grandparents raising the children of drug-dependent mothers. | journal = International Journal of Mental Health and Addiction | date = December 2016 | volume = 14 | issue = 6 | pages = 937–51 | doi = 10.1007/s11469-016-9645-7 | s2cid = 38102148 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Most individuals who suffer from drug dependency are nearly twice as likely to suffer from a mental illness as well.&lt;ref&gt;Proudfoot, Jesse. 2017. “Drugs, Addiction, and the Social Bond.” Geography Compass 11 (7): n/a-N.PAG. doi:10.1111/gec3.12320.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration, about 8.9 million adults who have an addiction also have a psychiatric disorder. When dealing with either a mental illness or a drug addiction some symptoms people will experience are being incapable of controlling their own impulses and mood swings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Canbolat F, Kul A, Özdemï M, Atïk U, Aydini A, Özden ST, Tarhan KN | title = Substance Abuse Profiles of Patients Admitted to the Alcohol and Drug Addiction Research, Treatment, and Education Center in Turkey. | journal = Turkish Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences | date = December 2017 | volume = 14 | issue = 3 | pages = 294–303 | doi = 10.4274/tjps.50470 | pmid = 32454628 | pmc = 7227934 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

When an individual falls victim to drug addiction, they will undergo the five stages of addiction which are the first use, the continued use, tolerance, dependence, and addiction.&lt;ref name="pmid28001458"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wang Z, Li WX, Zhi-Min L | title = Similarity and Difference in Drug Addiction Process Between Heroin- and Methamphetamine-Dependent Users | journal = Substance Use &amp; Misuse | volume = 52 | issue = 4 | pages = 459–467 | date = March 2017 | pmid = 28001458 | doi = 10.1080/10826084.2016.1245331 | s2cid = 3649040 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The first use stage, is the stage where individuals experiment with drugs and alcohol. This is the stage where individuals will partake in drug use because of curiosity, peer pressure, emotional problems etc. They discover how the drug will make them feel. In the continued use stage, individuals know how the drug makes them feel and is likely to notice that they're not getting “high” as quickly as they use to. In the tolerance stage, the brain and the body have adjusted to the drug and it takes longer to get the “high” an individual is seeking. Tolerance arrives after a period of continued use and is one of the first warning signs of addiction. In the dependence stage, the brain becomes accustomed to the drug and doesn't function well without it. Substance abusers become physically ill without the use of drugs and will begin to develop symptoms of withdrawal. This is sign that the addiction is beginning to take hold of the individual. In the addiction stage,  individuals find it impossible to stop using drugs even if they do not enjoy it or if their behavior has caused problems within an individual's life.

With the increasing number of adults that suffer with an addiction, only a few will receive treatment due to the complexity of health care systems.&lt;ref name="pmid28252892"&gt;{{cite book | title = Facing Addiction in America: The Surgeon General's Report on Alcohol, Drugs, and Health | date = November 2016 | pmid = 28252892 | url = https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK424857/ | publisher =  US Department of Health and Human Services | author1 = Substance Abuse Mental Health Services Administration (US) | author2 = Office of the Surgeon General (US) }}&lt;/ref&gt; Most health care systems do not have insurance coverage for addiction recovery and many health care providers have little to no training in treating addiction. Some doctors do not feel comfortable treating an addiction due to their lack of knowledge and training of the topic. This is one of the reasons why drug dependence is difficult to recover from.

== Drugs and HIV infection ==
Among injecting drug users, the incidence of [[HIV]] infection is higher than among other drug addicts, however punitive and discriminatory measures against drug addicts are not able to eliminate either the spread of drug addiction or HIV. 

Nathan Kim and his associates once conducted a study on the HIV status of people who inject drugs and found that the HIV rate in those individuals in San Francisco increased by 16.1% from the year 2009 when the HIV rate was 64.4%, to 80.5% in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;Kim, Kim. “Undiagnosed and Untreated HIV Infection Among Persons Who Inject Drugs: Results of Three National HIV Behavioral Surveillance Surveys, San Francisco, 2009–2015.” AIDS and behavior 23.6 (2019): 1586–1589. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers say that around 90% of people that choose to inject drugs have missed prior opportunities for HIV testing that were provided.&lt;ref&gt; Stulpin, Caitlyn. “90% Of Injection Drug Users Miss Opportunities for HIV or HCV Testing.” ''Healio'', Feb. 2020, www.healio.com/news/infectious-disease/20200220/90-of-injection-drug-users-miss-opportunities-for-hiv-or-hcv-testing. &lt;/ref&gt;

=== Africa ===
Africa has an estimated number 28 million substance users.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Budambula V, Matoka C, Ouma J, Ahmed AA, Otieno MF, Were T | title = Socio-demographic and sexual practices associated with HIV infection in Kenyan injection and non-injection drug users | journal = BMC Public Health | volume = 18 | issue = 1 | pages = 193 | date = January 2018 | pmid = 29378631 | pmc = 5789578 | doi = 10.1186/s12889-018-5100-y }}&lt;/ref&gt; This number is impacted by the rising availability of injection'''-'''based drugs such as heroin, cocaine, and methamphetamines.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Socio-demographic factors are often primary determinants of the health status of drug users.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; These factors contribute to individual drug use behaviors such as the sharing of needles and the solicitation of sex in exchange for police protection or more drugs.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Nutritional status, family support, stigma/discrimination, adherence to medication, and recovery from addiction are also impacted by these socio-demographic factors.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Research shows that the majority of drug users transition from the use of non-injection substances to injection substances or use both simultaneously.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

=== Kenya ===
In Kenya there is a link between injection'''-'''related discrimination, mental health, physical health, and the quality of life for those who inject drugs.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mburu G, Ayon S, Tsai AC, Ndimbii J, Wang B, Strathdee S, Seeley J | title = "Who has ever loved a drug addict? It's a lie. They think a 'teja' is as bad person": multiple stigmas faced by women who inject drugs in coastal Kenya | journal = Harm Reduction Journal | volume = 15 | issue = 1 | pages = 29 | date = May 2018 | pmid = 29801494 | pmc = 5970466 | doi = 10.1186/s12954-018-0235-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The rates of discrimination are linked to higher levels of psychological distress and risk behaviors.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; Women in Kenya account for 10% of drug users.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; These women tend to experience the regular discrimination faced by drug users in addition to gender related discrimination.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; Levels of discrimination are often higher for those that are also HIV positive.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;


=== Canada ===

In Vancouver Canada, there have been significant efforts in reducing opioid-related deaths. In an article published by the Canadian Medical Association Journal, it delves into the new efforts to create safe injection sites for people struggling with opioid addiction. Vancouver politicians have created these sites for people to safely use drugs that they are addicted to without the risk of infection or prosecution by the police. At safe injection sites, sterilized needles are provided to limit the reuse of needles that leads to the spread of HIV and other diseases. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Jones |first1=Deborah |title=Time for a New Approach to Heroin Addiction, Vancouver Says |url=www.cmaj.ca/content/168/13/1699.2 |journal=CMAJ : Canadian Medical Association Journal = Journal de l'Association Medicale Canadienne |year=2003 |volume=168 |issue=13 |page=1699 |publisher=CMAJ |pmid=12821633 |pmc=161627 |accessdate=16 November 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Cognitive liberty]]
* [[Drug liberalization]]
* [[Legalisation of marijuana]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Jones |first1=Deborah |title=Time for a New Approach to Heroin Addiction, Vancouver Says |url= https://www.cmaj.ca/content/168/13/1699.2 |journal=CMAJ : Canadian Medical Association Journal = Journal de l'Association Medicale Canadienne |year=2003 |volume=168 |issue=13 |page=1699 |publisher=CMAJ |pmid=12821633 |pmc=161627 |accessdate=16 November 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Volkow |first1=Nora |title=Addressing the Stigma that Surrounds Addiction |url=https://www.drugabuse.gov/about-nida/noras-blog/2020/04/addressing-stigma-surrounds-addiction |website=National Institute on Drug Abuse |publisher=National Institute on Drug Abuse |accessdate=16 November 2020 |ref=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Addiction}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Drug culture]]
[[Category:Addiction]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>