<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061009085519|80382211" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1239941" pageid="1239941" ns="0" title="Age of candidacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-09T08:57:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Age of candidacy''' is the minimum age at which a person can legally qualify to hold certain elected government offices. In many cases, it also determines the age at which a person may be granted [[ballot access]] for an election.

==Controversy surrounding age requirements==

Many [[youth rights]] groups view age of candidacy requirements as unjustified [[Ageism|age discrimination]]. Occasionally people who are younger than the minimum age will run for an office in protest of the requirement (or because they don't know that the requirement exists). On extremely rare occasions, young people have been elected to offices they do not qualify for and have been deemed ineligible to assume the office.

In 1956, [[Richard Fulton]] won election to the [[Tennessee]] State Senate. The Senate, however, refused to let Fulton assume office because he was only 29 years old at the time. The State Constitution required that Senators be at least 30 years old. Rather than hold a new election, the incumbent, [[Clifford Allen]], was allowed to stay in office for another term. Fulton went on to win the next State Senate election in 1958 and was later elected to the [[United States House of Representatives|US House of Representatives]] where he served for 10 years.

In 2004, [[Arrin Hawkins]] was the vice-presidential candidate of the [[Socialist Workers Party (USA)|Socialist Workers Party]] in the [[U.S. presidential election, 2004|U.S. presidential election]]. Because she was younger than 35 years old, she was not able to receive ballot access in several states in which she otherwise qualified.

==Reform efforts==

In the United States many groups have attempted to lower age of candidacy requirements in various states.

In 1994, [[South Dakota]] voters rejected a ballot measure that would have lowered the age requirements to serve as a State Senator or State Congressperson from 25 to 18. In 1998, however, they approved a similar ballot measure that reduced the age requirements for those offices from 25 to 21.

In 2002, [[Oregon]] voters rejected a ballot measure that would have reduced the age requirement to serve as a State Congressperson from 21 to 18.

==Age of candidacy in various countries==

===Australia===
In [[Australia]], a person must be 18 years of age or older may stand for election to public office at Federal, state or local government level. 

===Canada===
In [[Canada]], any person 18 years of age or older may stand for election to public office. However, to be appointed to the Senate, one must be at least 30 years of age, must possess land worth at least $4,000 in the province for which he or she is appointed, and must own real and personal property worth at least $4,000, above his or her debts and liabilities. These restrictions were most recently enforced in 1997. (See Sister [[Peggy Butts]].)

===Denmark===
In [[Denmark]], any adult 18 years of age or older can become a candidate and be elected in any public election.

===Italy===
In [[Italy]] a person must be at least 50 to be President of the Republic, 40 to be a [[Italian_Senate|Senator]], or 25 to be a [[Italian_Chamber_of_Deputies|Deputy]], as specified in the 1947 [[Constitution of Italy]]. 18 years of age is sufficient, however, to be elected member of the Council of Regions, Provinces, and Municipalities (Communes).

===Mexico===
In [[Mexico]] a person must be at least 35 to be President, 35 to be a Senator, or 25 to be a Congressional Deputy, as specified in the [[1917 Constitution of Mexico]].

===Nigeria===
In [[Nigeria]], a person must be at least 40 years of age to be elected [[President of Nigeria|President]] or [[Vice President of Nigeria|Vice President]], 35 to be a Senator or State Governor, and 30 to be a Representative in parliament.

===United Kingdom===
In the [[United Kingdom|UK]] a person must be at least 18 to stand in [[Elections in the United Kingdom|elections]] to all parliaments, assemblies, and councils at the European, UK, [[devolution|devolved]], or local level. This age requirement also applies in elections to any individual elective public office; the main example is that of an [[Elected mayors in the United Kingdom|elected mayor]], whether of [[Mayor of London|London]] or a [[Local government in the United Kingdom|local authority]]. There are no higher age requirements for particular positions in public office.

Section 17 of the [[Electoral Administration Act|Electoral Administration Act 2006]], passed on [[11 July]] [[2006]], reduced the age of candidacy to 18 for all public elections.  It is yet to enter into force, and will do so by way of an order made by the [[Secretary of State (United Kingdom)|Secretary of State]] at a future date.

===United States===
In the [[United States]] a person must be at least 35 to be President or Vice President, 30 to be a Senator, or 25 to be a Representative, as specified in the [[United States Constitution|U.S. Constitution]]. Most states in the U.S. also have age requirements for the offices of Governor, State Senator, and State Representative. Some states have a minimum age requirement to hold any elected office (usually 21 or 18). Most states will not allow ballot access to people who do not meet the age requirement of the office they are running for. Below are some examples of state public office age requirements in the U.S.:

'''New Jersey'''
:Governor: 30
:State Senator: 30
:State Representative: 21
:Any county or local office: 21

'''Oregon'''
:Governor: 30
:State Senator: 21
:State Representative: 21

'''South Dakota'''
:Governor: 21
:Lieutenant Governor: 21
:State Senator: 21
:State Representative: 21
:Public Utilities Commissioner: 25

'''Tennessee'''
:Governor: 30
:State Senator: 30
:State Representative: 25

'''Texas'''
:Any county or local office: 18

==See also==

*[[Ageism]]
*[[Ballot access]]
*[[Electoral reform]]
*[[Voting age]]

[[Category:Aging]][[Category:Electoral restrictions]]
[[Category:Legal terms]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>