<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131117030057|581999514" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1239941" pageid="1239941" ns="0" title="Age of candidacy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-17T04:44:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Age of candidacy''' is the minimum age at which a person can legally qualify to hold certain elected government offices. In many cases, it also determines the age at which a person may be [[nomination rules|eligible to stand]] for an election or be granted [[ballot access]].

The first known example of a law enforcing age of candidacy was the ''Lex Villia Annalis'', a Roman law enacted in 180 BCE which set the minimum ages for senatorial [[Roman Magistrates|magistrates]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Magistrates of the Roman Republic|first=Thomas|last=Broughton|coauthors=Marcia Patterson|publisher=American Philological Association|year=1951|page=388}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversies==
[[Image:Jenness-for-president.jpg|thumb|right|In 1972, [[Linda Jenness]] ran for President of the United States although she was only 31 at the time.]]
Many [[youth rights]] groups view current age of candidacy requirements as unjustified [[Ageism|age discrimination]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=BYC Youth Manifesto |publisher=British Youth Council |year=2008 |url=http://www.byc.org.uk/asset_store/documents/amd5a_youth_manifesto_(annual_meeting_version).pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=2008-07-28|quote=Young people believe that the age to stand as candidates for local, regional, national and European elections should be 16, as should the age to become a trustee of a charity. Young people have significant responsibilities to society at the age of 16 and can have significant responsibilities in the private sector as company directors; this inconsistency should be rectified. Young people have lots to offer and the decision of their appointment to positions of political authority or governance of organisations should be in the hands of the electorate or membership respectfully.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Occasionally people who are younger than the minimum age will run for an office in protest of the requirement or because they don't know that the requirement exists. On extremely rare occasions, young people have been elected to offices they do not qualify for and have been deemed ineligible to assume the office.

In 1934, [[Rush D. Holt, Sr.|Rush Holt]] of West Virginia was elected to the [[Senate of the United States]] at the age of 29. Since the [[United States Constitution|U.S. Constitution]] requires senators to be at least 30, Holt was forced to wait until his 30th birthday, six months after the start of the session, before being sworn in.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,930751,00.html Unsworn Senators]". ''Time Magazine'' (January 14, 1935).&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1954, [[Richard Fulton]] won election to the [[Tennessee Senate]]. Shortly after being sworn in, Fulton was ousted from office because he was only 27 years old at the time. The [[Tennessee State Constitution]] required that senators be at least 30.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Dick|last=Battle|coauthors=Tom Flake|title=Senate Vote Ousts Fulton|work=Nashville Banner|date=January 5, 1955}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rather than hold a new election, the previous incumbent, [[Clifford Allen]], was allowed to resume his office for another term. Fulton went on to win the next State Senate election in 1956 and was later elected to the [[United States House of Representatives|US House of Representatives]] where he served for 10 years.

On several occasions, the [[Socialist Workers Party (USA)]] has nominated candidates too young to qualify for the offices they were running for. In 1972, [[Linda Jenness]] ran as the SWP presidential candidate, although she was only 31 at the time. Since the U.S. Constitution requires that the President and Vice President be at least 35 years old, Jenness was not able to receive [[ballot access]] in several states in which she otherwise qualified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Jo|last=Freeman|title=We Will Be Heard: Women's Struggles for Political Power in the United States|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|year=2008|quote=Only 31, Linda Jenness did not meet the Constitutional age requirement to hold the office of President, but the SWP was on the ballot in 25 states — six more than in 1968.|page=91}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this handicap, Jenness still received 83,380 votes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1972 Presidential General Election Results|work=Dave Leip's Atlas of U.S. Presidential Elections|url=http://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/national.php?year=1972&amp;minper=0|accessdate=2008-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, the SWP nominated [[Arrin Hawkins]] as the party's vice-presidential candidate, although she was only 28 at the time. Hawkins was also unable to receive ballot access in several states due to her age.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Presidency 2004 |url=http://www.politics1.com/swp04.htm | work=Politics1.com | accessdate=2007-10-16 | quote= Since they weren't going to be elected anyways, the Socialist Workers Party didn't care that they nominated a ticket entirely ineligible to be elected. Why? Because Róger Calero is both foreign born and also not a US citizen; and Arrin Hawkins is too young. To avoid [[ballot access]] problems for the SWP, as the constitutional ineligibility may also render them unable to be listed on the ballot in some states, the 2000 SWP ticket of James Harris for President and Margaret Trowe for Vice President are being used in states that will not permit the Calero-Hawkins slate to be listed. |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070730141140/http://www.politics1.com/swp04.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reform efforts==

In the United States many groups have attempted to lower age of candidacy requirements in various states. In 1994, [[South Dakota]] voters rejected a ballot measure that would have lowered the age requirements to serve as a State Senator or State Congressman from 25 to 18. In 1998, however, they approved a similar ballot measure that reduced the age requirements for those offices from 25 to 21. In 2002, [[Oregon]] voters rejected a ballot measure that would have reduced the age requirement to serve as a State Congressman from 21 to 18. However, in [[New York State]], the age requirement for State Senator or Assemblyman is 18.

During the early 2000s, the [[British Youth Council]] and other groups successfully campaigned to lower age of candidacy requirements in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name="byc"&gt;{{cite press release |title=How old is old enough? |publisher=British Youth Council |date=October 2003 |url=http://www.byc.org.uk/downloads/Campaigns/HowOldIsOldEnough.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=2008-07-16|quote=BYC believes that at the age of 18 a person may hold elected office. A candidate’s breadth of life experience is something that can be evaluated by the electorate... BYC strongly believes that the age of voting should be lowered to 16 and candidacy age should be lowered to 18...}}&lt;/ref&gt; The age of candidacy was reduced from 21 to 18 in [[England]], [[Wales]] and [[Scotland]] on 1 January 2007,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opsi.gov.uk/si/si2006/20063412.htm The Electoral Administration Act 2006 (Commencement No. 2, Transitional and Savings Provisions) Order 2006], article 3 and Schedule 1(14)(d).&lt;/ref&gt; when section 17 of the [[Electoral Administration Act|Electoral Administration Act 2006]] entered into force.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2006/ukpga_20060022_en_6#pt5-l1g17 The Electoral Administration Act 2006 - Part 5, Section 17]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Age of candidacy in various countries==

===Australia===
In [[Australia]], any person 18 years of age or older may stand for election to public office at federal, state or local government level.

The youngest ever member of the [[Australian House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] was 20 year old [[Wyatt Roy]] elected in the 2010 federal election after the [[Commonwealth Electoral Act 1918|Electoral Act 1918]] was amended to reduce the age of candidacy for that office from 21 to 18.{{citation needed|date=January 2013}}

===Austria===
In [[Austria]], a person must be 18 years of age or older to stand in elections to the [[European Parliament]] or [[National Council of Austria|National Council]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parlinkom.gv.at/pls/portal/docs/page/PG/DE/XXIII/I/I_00129/FNAMEORIG_079516.HTML 31/BNR (XXIII. GP) Bundes-Verfassungsgesetz], ss. 2 and 6, Republik Österreich Parlament (German).  Retrieved on 1 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Diets of regional [[States of Austria|''Länder'']] are able to set a minimum age lower than 18 for candidacy in elections to the Diet itself as well as to municipal councils in the Land.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ris.bka.gv.at/erv/erv_1930_1.pdf Bundes-Verfassungsgesetz - Federal Constitutional Law 1920, 1929 version]. Retrieved on 3 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  In presidential elections the candidacy age is 35.

===Belize===
According to the [[Constitution of Belize]], a person must be at least 18 years old to be elected as a member of the [[House of Representatives (Belize)|House of Representatives]] and must be at least 30 to be Speaker of the House. A person must be at least 18 years old to be appointed to the [[Senate (Belize)|Senate]] and must be at least 30 to be President or Vice-President of the Senate. As only members of the House of Representatives are eligible to be appointed Prime Minister, the [[List of Prime Ministers of Belize|Prime Minister]] must be at least 18 years old. A person must also be at least 18 years old to be elected to a village council.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.belizelaw.org/web/lawadmin/ Laws of Belize], Volume II, Title VIII, Chapter 88, Part III. "Any person shall be eligible to be elected as a member of a council who: is a citizen of Belize; and has ordinarily resided in the village for at least one year immediately preceding the election; and is at least eighteen years old."&lt;/ref&gt;

===Brazil===
The [[Brazil]]ian Constitution (Article 14, Section 3 (VI)) defines 35 years as the minimum age for someone to be elected President, Vice-President or Senator; 30 years for state Governor or Vice-Governor; 21 for Federal or State Deputy, Mayor or Vice-Mayor; and 18 for city Councilman.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.planalto.gov.br/ccivil_03/constituicao/constituicao.htm Brazilian Constitution (in Portuguese)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
In [[Canada]], any person 18 years of age or older may stand for election to public office. However, to be appointed to the [[Senate of Canada|Senate]], one must be at least 30 years of age, must possess land worth at least $4,000 in the province for which he or she is appointed, and must own real and personal property worth at least $4,000, above his or her debts and liabilities. These restrictions were most recently enforced in 1997.{{citation needed|date=May 2013}}

===Chile===
In [[Chile]] the minimum age required to be elected [[President of Chile|President of the Republic]] is 35 years on the day of the election. Before the 2005 reforms the requirement was 40 years, and from 1925 to 1981 it was 30 years. For [[Senate of Chile|senators]] it is 35 years (between 1981 and 2005 it was 40 years) and for [[Chamber of Deputies of Chile|deputies]] it is 21 years (between 1925 and 1970 it was 35 years).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leychile.cl/ |title=Ley Chile - Biblioteca del Congreso Nacional |publisher=leychile.cl |date= |accessdate=2013-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cyprus===
In [[Cyprus]] the minimum age to be elected president is 35 years.

===Denmark===
In [[Denmark]], any adult 18 years of age or older can become a candidate and be elected in any public election.

===Estonia===
In [[Estonia]], any citizen 18 years of age or older [[Elections in Estonia|can be elected]] in [[local election]]s, and 21 years or older in [[Riigikogu|parliamentary elections]]. Minimum age for the [[President of Estonia]] is 40.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.president.ee/en/estonia/constitution.php Constitution of the Republic of Estonia]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===
In [[Germany]], any citizen 18 years of age or older [[Elections in Germany|can be elected]] in national, regional or local elections. Minimum age for the [[President of Germany]] is 40 by constitution.

===Hong Kong===
In Hong Kong a person must be at least 21 to be candidate in a district council or Legislative Council election. A person must be at least 40 to be candidate in the [[Chief Executive (Hong Kong)|Chief Executive]] election, and also at least 40 to be candidate in the election for the [[President of the Legislative Council of Hong Kong|President of the Legislative Council]] from among the members of the Legislative Council.

===Indonesia===
In [[Indonesia]] a person must be at least:
*35 to be [[President of Indonesia|President]] or [[Vice President of Indonesia|Vice President]] as specified in the [[Constitution of Indonesia]]
*30 to be Governor or Lieutenant Governor, as specified in the 2004 Regional Government Act
*25 to be Regent, Vice Regent, Mayor, or Deputy Mayor, as specified in the 2004 Regional Government Act
*21 to be Senator or Representative in both national and local parliament, as specified in the 2008 Election Act

===Italy===
In [[Italy]] a person must be at least 50 to be President of the Republic, 40 to be a [[Italian Senate|Senator]], or 25 to be a [[Italian Chamber of Deputies|Deputy]], as specified in the 1947 [[Constitution of Italy]]. 18 years of age is sufficient, however, to be elected member of the Council of Regions, Provinces, and Municipalities (Communes).

===Iran===
In [[Iran]] a person must be at least 21 years old to run for President.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Piven|first=Ben|title=Infographic: Choosing Iran's next president|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/interactive/2013/06/2013611135620419515.html|work=Al Jazeera English|accessdate=12 June 2013|coauthors=Ben Willers|date=11 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mexico===
In [[Mexico]] a person must be at least 35 to be President, 25 to be a Senator, or 21 to be a Congressional Deputy, as specified in the [[1917 Constitution of Mexico]].

===Netherlands===
In the [[Netherlands]], any adult 18 years of age or older can become a candidate and be elected in any public election.

===Nigeria===
In [[Nigeria]], a person must be at least 40 years of age to be elected [[President of Nigeria|President]] or [[Vice President of Nigeria|Vice President]], 35 to be a Senator or State Governor, and 30 to be a Representative in parliament.

===Philippines===
*[[President of the Philippines|President]] and [[Vice President of the Philippines|Vice President]]: 40
*[[Senate of the Philippines|Senator]]: 35
*Regional governor: 35
*Member of the [[House of Representatives of the Philippines|House of Representatives]]: 25
*[[Province of the Philippines|Provincial-level]] elected official: 23
*[[City of the Philippines|City-level]] elected official: 21
*[[Municipality of the Philippines|Municipal-level]] elected official: 21
*Member of the regional legislative assembly: 21
*[[Barangay]]-level elected official: 18
*Member of [[Sangguniang Kabataan|youth councils]]: 15

===South Africa===
Section 47, Clause 1 of the 1996 Constitution of South Africa states that "Every citizen who is qualified to vote for the National Assembly is eligible to be a member of the Assembly", defaulting to Section 46 which "provides for a minimum voting age of 18 years" in National Assembly elections; Sections 106 and 105 provide the same for provincial legislatures.

===Turkey===
In [[Turkey]], a person must be at least 40 to be [[President of Turkey|President]]. The age of candidacy for the [[Prime Minister of Turkey|Premiership]] is the same as the age for parliamentary eligibility. In 2006, a proposal was submitted by the ruling [[Justice and Development Party (Turkey)|Justice and Development Party]] to reduce the age for parliamentary eligibility from 30 to 25. The [[Grand National Assembly of Turkey|Parliament]] approved the proposal on October 2006. {{As of|2012}}, Turkey is considering lowering the age of candidacy to 18.{{clarify|date=November 2012}}

===United Kingdom===
In the [[United Kingdom|UK]] (other than in [[Northern Ireland]]) a person must be aged 18 or over to stand in [[Elections in the United Kingdom|elections]] to all parliaments, assemblies, and councils at the European, UK, [[devolution|devolved]], or local level. This age requirement also applies in elections to any individual elective public office; the main example is that of an [[Elected mayors in the United Kingdom|elected mayor]], whether of [[Mayor of London|London]] or a [[Local government in the United Kingdom|local authority]]. There are no higher age requirements for particular positions in public office. Candidates are required to be aged 18 on both the day of nomination and the day of the poll. This was reduced from 21 by the [[Electoral Administration Act 2006]].

===United States===
{{main|Age of candidacy laws in the United States}}
In the [[United States]], a person must be at least 35 to be President or Vice President, 30 to be a Senator, or 25 to be a Representative, as specified in the [[Article Two of the United States Constitution#Clause 5: Qualifications for office|U.S. Constitution]]. Most states in the U.S. also have age requirements for the offices of Governor, State Senator, and State Representative.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://definitions.uslegal.com/a/age-of-candidacy/|title=Age of Candidacy Law &amp; Legal Definition|publisher=USLegal.com |accessdate=2012-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some states have a minimum age requirement to hold any elected office (usually 21 or 18). Most states will not allow ballot access to people who do not meet the age requirement of the office they are running for.

===Venezuela===
In [[Venezuela]], a person must be at least 30 to be [[President of Venezuela|President]] or [[Vice President of Venezuela|Vice President]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psuv.org.ve/constitucion/titulo5-capitulo2/ Constitution of the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela - Part 5, Chapter II, Article 227]&lt;/ref&gt; 21 to be a deputy for the [[National Assembly of Venezuela|National Assembly]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psuv.org.ve/constitucion/titulo5-capitulo1/ Constitution of the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela - Part 5, Chapter I, Article 188, Section 2]&lt;/ref&gt; and 25 to be the Governor of a [[States of Venezuela|state]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psuv.org.ve/constitucion/titulo4-capitulo3/ Constitution of the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela - Part 4, Chapter III, Article 160]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

*[[Ageism]]
*[[Ballot access]]
*[[Electoral reform]]
*[[Voting age]]

==Notes and references==
{{reflist}}

{{Law country lists}}

[[Category:Age and society]]
[[Category:Electoral restrictions]]
[[Category:Legal terms]]
[[Category:Lists by country]]
[[Category:Minimum ages]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>