<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131014205346|577186287" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="247171" pageid="247171" ns="0" title="Biphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-10-14T20:57:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{expert-subject|LGBT studies|reason=there is quite a bit of unsourced information|date=June 2013}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Biphobia''' is aversion toward [[bisexuality]] and bisexual people as a [[social group]] or as individuals. People of any [[sexual orientation]] can experience such feelings of aversion. Biphobia is a source of [[discrimination]] against bisexuals, and may be based on negative bisexual [[stereotype]]s or irrational fear.

== Etymology and use ==
''Biphobia'' is a [[portmanteau word]] patterned on the term ''[[homophobia]]''. It derives from the English [[English prefixes#Neo-classical|neo-classical prefix]] ''bi-'' (meaning "two") from ''bisexual'' and the root ''-phobia'' (from the {{lang-el|φόβος}}, ''phóbos'', "fear") found in ''homophobia''. Along with ''[[transphobia]]'', ''homophobia'' and ''biphobia'' are members of the family of terms used when [[Bigotry|intolerance]] and discrimination is directed toward [[LGBT]] people.

''Biphobia'' need not be a [[phobia]] as defined in [[clinical psychology]] (i.e., an [[anxiety disorder]]). Its meaning and use typically parallel those of ''[[xenophobia]]''.

The [[adjective|adjectival]] form ''biphobic'' describes things or qualities related to biphobia, whereas the noun ''biphobe'' is a label for people thought to harbor biphobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Eliason, MJ|title=The prevalence and nature of biphobia in heterosexual undergraduate students|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|volume=26|issue=3|year=1997|pages=317–26|pmid=9146816|doi=10.1023/A:1024527032040}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Negative stereotypes ==
While biphobia and homophobia are distinct phenomena, they do share some traits: attraction to one's own gender being a part of bisexuality, the [[heterosexist]] view of heterosexuality as the only “proper” attraction or lifestyle apply to bisexual people as well as to gay people. However, bisexuals are also stigmatized in other ways: two classifications of negative stereotypes about them center on the belief that bisexuality does not exist and the generalization that bisexual people are promiscuous.

=== Denialism ===
The belief that bisexuality does not exist stems from [[Binary thinking|binary]] views of sexuality, that people are assumed to be exclusively homosexual ([[gay]]/[[lesbian]]) or heterosexual (straight), with bisexuals either [[The closet|closeted]] gay people wishing to appear heterosexual,&lt;ref&gt;Michael Musto, April 7, 2009. [http://blogs.villagevoice.com/dailymusto/archives/2009/04/ever_meet_a_rea.php Ever Meet a Real Bisexual?], ''The Village Voice''&lt;/ref&gt; or experimenting with their sexuality,&lt;ref name="bisexual erasure"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Yoshino |first=Kenji |authorlink=Kenji Yoshino |title=The Epistemic Contract of Bisexual Erasure |journal=[[Stanford Law Review]] |volume=52 |issue=2 |pages=353–461 |publisher=[[Stanford Law School]] |date=January 2000 |url=http://www.kenjiyoshino.com/articles/epistemiccontract.pdf |doi=10.2307/1229482 |jstor=1229482 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gold star"&gt;{{cite web|title=Why Do Lesbians Hate Bisexuals?|publisher=lesbilicious.co.uk|date=April 11, 2008|accessdate=March 26, 2011|url=http://www.lesbilicious.co.uk/community/why-do-lesbians-hate-bisexuals/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bisexual workers"&gt;{{cite web|first=Jessica|last=Geen|title=Bisexual workers 'excluded by lesbian and gay colleagues'|date=October 28, 2009|accessdate=March 26, 2011|url=http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2009/10/28/bisexual-workers-excluded-by-lesbian-and-gay-colleagues}}&lt;/ref&gt; and cannot be bisexual unless they are equally attracted to both sexes.&lt;ref name="Dworkin"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dworkin, SH |title=Treating the bisexual client|journal=Journal of Clinical Psychology|volume=57|issue=5|year=2001|pages=671–80 | pmid=11304706 |doi=10.1002/jclp.1036}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aphorism|Maxims]] such as ''People are either gay, straight or lying'' embody this [[dichotomous]] view of sexual orientations.&lt;ref name="Dworkin"/&gt;

Resulting negative stereotypes represent bisexuals as confused, undecided, dabblers, insecure, experimenting or "just going through a phase".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bisexualindex.org.uk/index.php/Main/ItsJustAPhase "It's Just A Phase" Is Just A Phrase], The Bisexual Index&lt;/ref&gt;  Attractions toward both sexes are considered fashionable as in "[[bisexual chic]]" or [[gender bending]]. Relations are dismissed as a substitute for sex with members of the "right" sex or as a more accessible source of [[sexual gratification]]. [[Situational homosexuality]] due to [[Sex segregation|sex-segregated]] environments or groups such as the armed forces, schools, sports teams, religious orders, and [[prison sexuality|prisons]] is another facet of explaining why someone is allegedly temporarily gay. Conversely, heterosexuality and opposite-sex relationships are viewed as "caving in to" society’s pressures, fostering oppressions, condoning discrimination, keeping up appearances, retaining [[Heteronormativity|straight privilege]], hiding in [[Closeted|the closet]], being self-hating or in [[self-denial]], suffering from [[internalized homophobia]], etc.

=== Promiscuity ===
Categorizing bisexual people as being promiscuous is a [[hasty generalization]]. Moreover, having more than one sexual partner in one’s lifetime, in addition to being commonplace in the world, is not restricted to bisexuals. The strict association of bisexuality with promiscuity stems from a variety of negative stereotypes targeting bisexuals as mentally or socially unstable people convinced that sexual relations only with men, only with women or only with one person is not enough. As a result bisexuals bear a [[Stigma (sociological theory)|social stigma]] from accusations of cheating on or betraying their partners, leading a [[double life]], being "on the [[Down-low (sexual slang)|down-low]]", and spreading [[sexually transmitted disease]]s such as [[HIV]]/[[AIDS]]. They are characterized as being "slutty", insatiable, “easy”, indiscriminate, and in the case of women, [[nymphomaniac]]s. Furthermore, they are strongly associated with [[polyamory]], [[swinging]], and [[polygamy]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glaad.org/programs/cim/birepresentations.php GLAAD: Cultural Interest Media] {{Wayback |url=http://www.glaad.org/programs/cim/birepresentations.php |date=20060419203924 |bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; the last being an established heterosexual tradition sanctioned by some religions and legal in several countries. People of any sexual orientation can change partners, practice [[serial monogamy]] or have multiple casual sex partners. The fact that bisexuals are potentially sexually attracted to both men and women does not imply that they must simultaneously engage in sexual relationships with both men and women to be satisfied, any more than the ability of a heterosexual or homosexual person to be attracted to multiple persons of their preferred gender means they cannot be satisfied in a monogamous relationship.

== Current issues of debate ==

Apparently validating the above belief and generalization and their related stereotypes are current issues of debate connected to identity and human sexuality in general.

# The [[nature versus nurture]] debate over homosexuality complicates matters. Supporting a polar view of sexual orientations, discussion here revolves around possible causes for a homosexual orientation and not a heterosexual or bisexual one. ''See separate articles on [[Kinsey scale]] and [[Klein Sexual Orientation Grid]]''
# In line with the nurture side of the previous debate is [[Sigmund Freud]]’s term for sexual disposition and gratification in the first five years of a child’s development: the [[polymorphous perverse]]. This theory is misinterpreted as meaning that all people are (born) bisexual,&lt;ref&gt;[http://combine.org.ohio-state.edu/resources/Myths%20About%20Bisexuality.pdf Myths About Bisexuality] (PDF pamphlet from Bisexual Resource Center)&lt;/ref&gt; that [[socialization]] is the key factor in determining whether people will be heterosexual or homosexual, or that people eventually choose their sexual orientation toward one or the other sex, but not both.
# People do not always choose to identify themselves strictly according to their sexual orientation. Just as someone can feel pressured not to disclose his or her homosexual orientation and claim heterosexuality, so too can a person claim bisexuality. Mainly out of oppression from negative bisexual stereotypes, the reverse is true for some bisexual people choosing to identify or state that they are straight, gay or lesbian depending on company and the situation.
# The concept of bisexuality may not exist in a given culture or may be encompassed by [[transgender]] identities as in some [[indigenous culture]]s such as those of [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]], [[Aboriginal peoples in Canada]] or the [[Zapotec civilization|Zapotec]] in [[Oaxaca]], [[Mexico]].
# Having sexual relations with people of the same as well as different genders is perceived as a direct indication of a person’s sexual attractions and, hence, a bisexual orientation. This perception explains how the [[Kinsey Scale]] is used to label sexual orientation despite its original design and use to explain a person’s sexual history or past. Moreover, in many parts of the world, gay men and lesbian women still lead so-called straight [[lifestyle (sociology)|lifestyles]]. The reasons cited are discrimination, internalized homophobia, strong personal or religious beliefs about the family, and a lack of information on and visibility of same-sex relations and sexuality.
# Regardless of their actual sexual orientation it is sometimes assumed by those not in the industry that all [[sex workers]] or [[actors]]/[[actresses]] opt to participate in [[homosexual]] sex scenes only as part of their jobs. Confusing fantasy and [[acting]] with reality, this has been dubbed “[[gay-for-pay]]”, this myth has been used to create further confusion and reinforce biphobia.

== Bisexual erasure ==
[[Bisexual erasure]] or ''bisexual invisibility'' is the tendency to ignore, remove, falsify, or reexplain evidence of [[bisexuality]] in [[history]], [[academia]], the [[news media]], and other [[primary source]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://queersunited.blogspot.com/2008/05/word-of-gay-bisexual-erasure.html Word Of The Gay: BisexualErasure] May 16, 2008 "Queers United"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ronsuresha.com/?p=1018 The B Word] Suresha, Ron. "The B Word," Options (Rhode Island), November 2004&lt;/ref&gt; In its most extreme form, bisexual erasure can include denying that bisexuality exists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hutchins |first=Loraine |authorlink=Loraine Hutchins |title=Sexual Prejudice: The erasure of bisexuals in academia and the media |journal=[[American Sexuality magazine]] |volume=3 |issue=4 |publisher=[[National Sexuality Resource Center]] |year=2005 |url=http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0 | title = Sexual Prejudice - The erasure of bisexuals in academia and the media | accessdate = 2007-07-19 | last = Hutchins | first = Loraine | authorlink = Loraine Hutchins | work = American Sexuality Magazine | publisher = National Sexuality Resource Center, San Francisco State University | location = San Francisco, CA 94103, United States | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071216065035/http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0 | archivedate = 2007-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is often a manifestation of biphobia, although it does not necessarily involve overt antagonism.

However, there is also increasing support, inclusion, and visibility in both bisexual and non-bisexual communities, especially in the [[LGBT]] community.&lt;ref name="Queers United"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://queersunited.blogspot.com/ |title=Queers United }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="the task force"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/issues/bisexuality |title=Task Force Report On Bisexuality }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="HRC"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hrc.org/issues/coming_out/bisexual/bisexual_articles.asp?listpage=2 |title=HRC article on bisexuality}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GLAAD"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://glaadbackup.com/2009/documents/GLAADNRI2009.pdf|title=GLAAD TV Report }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Maria, September 24, 2009. [http://bisocialnews.com/how-far-have-we-come|title= How Far Have We Come?], ''BiSocial News''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Thirteen"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ausiellofiles.ew.com/2008/10/27/greys-anatomy-s-3/ |title=Thirteen On House }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Monosexism ==
Monosexism is a term used to refer to beliefs, structures, and actions that promote [[monosexuality]] (either exclusive heterosexuality or homosexuality) as the only legitimate or right sexual orientation, excluding [[bisexual]] or other non-[[monosexual]] orientations.&lt;ref name="Highleyman"&gt;Highleyman, Liz (1995). [http://www.black-rose.com/articles-liz/bipol.html "Identities and Ideas: Strategies for Bisexuals"], from the anthology ''Bisexual Politics: Theories, Queries, and Visions''. Haworth Press. ''Black Rose Web Pages''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="rust"&gt;[[Paula Rodriguez Rust|Rust, Paula C Rodriguez]] (2002). [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3778/is_200201/ai_n9069533/pg_18 "Bisexuality: The state of the union, Annual Review of Sex Research, 2002"], ''BNET''. {{dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term may be considered analogous to biphobia.&lt;ref name="rust"/&gt;

The term is primarily used in discussions of [[sexual orientation]] to denote  aversion towards all non-[[monosexual]] people as a social group or as individuals. It was likely adopted in place of [[unisexual]], which is already used in biology and would produce confusion. It is sometimes considered derogatory by the people to whom it is applied,.&lt;ref&gt;Hamilton, Alan (2000). ''{{waybackdate|site=http://www.biresource.org/pamphlets/glossary.html|date=20070805044122}} ''of "LesBiGay and Transgender Glossary", ''[http://www.biresource.net/ Bisexual Resource Center]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

The proportion of people who fit into the category depends on how one uses the word.  If the term is used to mean exclusively monosexual in behavior, then according to [[Alfred Kinsey]]'s [[Kinsey Reports|studies]], 63% of men and 87% of women are what may now be termed "monosexual" as determined by experiences leading to [[orgasm]].&lt;ref&gt;(1999). [http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/resources/bib-homoprev.html "Prevalence of Homosexuality"], ''The Kinsey Institute''. Note that Kinsey does use the term, which did not exist, but that he uses "exclusively homosexual" and "exclusively heterosexual".&lt;/ref&gt; Freud thought that no one was born monosexual and that it had to be taught by parents or society though most people appear to believe that monosexuals are in fact the majority and identify as such.&lt;ref&gt;Rethinking Marxism: A Journal of Economics, Culture &amp; Society, Volume 8, Issue 3, 1995, Feminist Economies, DOI:10.1080/08935699508685453, Margaret Nash, pages 66-78.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Controversial studies ==
A 2002 study said that a sample of men self-identifying as bisexual did not respond equally to pornographic material involving only men, and to pornography involving only women, but instead showed four times more arousal to one than the other. However, bisexuality does not imply equal attraction towards both genders. In addition, opponents state that genital arousal to homosexual pornographic material is not a good indicator of orientation both because the material is chosen by the researchers, ignoring the study participants' preferences (i.e. body types, looks, scenarios, particular fetishes, presentation of relationships, etc.), and because tumescence is problematic as an indicator of arousal (some tumescence may be caused or prevented by anxiety, and erectile dysfunction should be considered before such studies commence). They also state that the study showed a third of men had no arousal, and ask why this does not mean that one third of men are really [[Asexuality|asexual]].&lt;ref name="Carey"&gt;{{cite news |last=Carey |first=Benedict |title=Straight, Gay or Lying? Bisexuality Revisited |work=The New York Times |date=5 July 2005 |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F20714FB3B550C768CDDAE0894DD404482 |accessdate=24 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ngltf"&gt;[[National Gay and Lesbian Task Force]] (July 2005). [http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/reports/NYTBisexualityFactSheet.pdf The Problems with "Gay, Straight, or Lying?"] ([[PDF]]) Retrieved 24 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="FAIR"&gt;{{Cite web|title=New York Times Suggests Bisexuals Are 'Lying.' Paper fails to disclose study author's controversial history|publisher=[[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] |date=July 8, 2005|accessdate=June 22, 2013|url=http://fair.org/take-action/action-alerts/new-york-times-suggests-bisexuals-are-quotlyingquot/}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is likely to suggest a heavy bias to the sample, especially as the men were recruited via "advertisements in gay and alternative newspapers". The study, and ''[[The New York Times]]'' article which reported it in 2005, were subsequently criticized as flawed and biphobic.&lt;ref name="Carey"/&gt;&lt;ref name="ngltf"/&gt;&lt;ref name="FAIR"/&gt; [[Lynn Conway]] criticized the author of the study, [[J. Michael Bailey]], citing his controversial history and stating that the study has not been scientifically repeated and confirmed by any independent researchers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TS/Bailey/Bisexuality/Bisexuality-NYT%207-05-05.html "Straight, Gay or Lying? Bisexuality Revisted" J. Michael Bailey attacks the identities of bisexual men]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, a new article published in ''The New York Times'', mentioned a new study elaborated by Jerome Cerny and Erick Janssen showing evidence of bisexuality in men and therefore contradicting Bailey's study.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/23/health/23bisexual.html | work=The New York Times | first=David | last=Tuller | title=No Surprise for Bisexual Men: Report Indicates They Exist | date=August 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; While both studies have been criticized for the aforementioned flaws in their methodology, this study attempts to resolve the sampling bias, by finding subjects from bisexual-specific communities who had experience with sex and relationships involving both sexes.

== See also ==
{{Portal|LGBT}}

* [[Bisexual community]]
* [[Duclod Man]]
* [[Heteronormativity]]
* [[Bisexual American history]]
* [[List of media portrayals of bisexuality]]
* [[List of phobias]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* [[Marjorie Garber|Garber, Marjorie]] (1995). ''Bisexuality and the Eroticism of Everyday Life'', pp.&amp;nbsp;20–21, 28, 39.
* [[Mariam Fraser|Fraser, M.]], ''Identity Without Selfhood: Simone de Beauvoir and Bisexuality'', Cambridge and New York: Cambridge University Press 1999. p.&amp;nbsp;124–140.

== External links ==
* [http://www.bialogue.org/Pages/InfoPackets/MentalHealth.html Bialogue/GLAAD Bisexuality Packet for Mental Health Professionals]
* [http://www.advocate.com/exclusive_detail_ektid49066.asp Fairy Tales], by Job Brother in [[The Advocate]] September 21, 2007
* [http://marksimpson.com/pages/journalism/curiouser.html Curiouser and curiouser] by [[Mark Simpson (journalist)|Mark Simpson]]
* [http://out.ucr.edu/pdf/BiBasics.pdf Bisexuality Basics, UC Riverside LGBT Resource Center, Riverside, CA]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Bisexuality topics}}
{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Discrimination}}
}}

[[Category:Bisexuality]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Hatred]]
[[Category:LGBT terms]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>