<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161108234320|748576331" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="247171" pageid="247171" ns="0" title="Biphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-18T05:31:49Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Bi flag.svg|thumb|[[Bisexual Pride Flag]]]]
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{LGBT sidebar}}

'''Biphobia''' is aversion toward [[bisexuality]] and bisexual people as a [[social group]] or as individuals. People of any [[sexual orientation]] can experience or perpetuate such feelings of aversion. Biphobia is a source of [[discrimination]] against bisexual people, and may be based on negative bisexual [[stereotype]]s or irrational fear.

== Etymology and usage ==
''Biphobia'' is a [[portmanteau word]] patterned on the term ''[[homophobia]]''. It derives from the English [[English prefixes#Neo-classical|neo-classical prefix]] ''bi-'' (meaning "two") from ''bisexual'' and the root ''-phobia'' (from the {{lang-el|φόβος}}, ''phóbos'', "fear") found in ''homophobia''. Along with ''[[transphobia]]'', ''homophobia'' and ''biphobia'' are members of the family of terms used when [[Bigotry|intolerance]] and discrimination are directed toward [[LGBT]] people.

''Biphobia'' need not be a [[phobia]] as defined in [[clinical psychology]] (i.e., an [[anxiety disorder]]). Its meaning and use typically parallel those of ''[[xenophobia]]''.

The [[Adjective|adjectival]] form ''biphobic'' describes things or qualities related to biphobia, whereas the noun ''biphobe'' is a label for people thought to harbor biphobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Eliason, MJ|title=The prevalence and nature of biphobia in heterosexual undergraduate students|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|volume=26|issue=3|year=1997|pages=317–26|pmid=9146816|doi=10.1023/A:1024527032040}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Negative stereotypes ==
While biphobia and homophobia are distinct phenomena, they do share some traits: with attraction to one's own gender being a part of bisexuality, the [[heterosexist]] view that heterosexuality is the only true attraction applies to bisexual people as well as to gay people. However, bisexual people are also stigmatized in other ways.

=== Denialism ===
The belief that bisexuality does not exist stems from [[Binary thinking|binary]] views of sexuality, that people are assumed to be exclusively homosexual ([[gay]]/[[lesbian]]) or heterosexual ([[Heterosexuality|straight]]), with bisexuals either [[The closet|closeted]] gay people wishing to appear heterosexual,&lt;ref&gt;Michael Musto, April 7, 2009. [http://blogs.villagevoice.com/dailymusto/archives/2009/04/ever_meet_a_rea.php Ever Meet a Real Bisexual?] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100413152614/http://blogs.villagevoice.com/dailymusto/archives/2009/04/ever_meet_a_rea.php |date=April 13, 2010 }}, ''The Village Voice''&lt;/ref&gt; or experimenting with their sexuality,&lt;ref name="bisexual erasure"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Yoshino |first=Kenji |authorlink=Kenji Yoshino |title=The Epistemic Contract of Bisexual Erasure |journal=[[Stanford Law Review]] |volume=52 |issue=2 |pages=353–461 |publisher=[[Stanford Law School]] |date=January 2000 |url=http://www.kenjiyoshino.com/articles/epistemiccontract.pdf |doi=10.2307/1229482 |jstor=1229482 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gold star"&gt;{{cite web|title=Why Do Lesbians Hate Bisexuals?|publisher=lesbilicious.co.uk|date=April 11, 2008|accessdate=March 26, 2011|url=http://www.lesbilicious.co.uk/community/why-do-lesbians-hate-bisexuals/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bisexual workers"&gt;{{cite web|first=Jessica|last=Geen|title=Bisexual workers 'excluded by lesbian and gay colleagues'|date=October 28, 2009|accessdate=March 26, 2011|url=http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2009/10/28/bisexual-workers-excluded-by-lesbian-and-gay-colleagues}}&lt;/ref&gt; and cannot be bisexual unless they are equally attracted towards men and women.&lt;ref name="Dworkin"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dworkin, SH |title=Treating the bisexual client|journal=Journal of Clinical Psychology|volume=57|issue=5|year=2001|pages=671–80 | pmid=11304706 |doi=10.1002/jclp.1036}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aphorism|Maxims]] such as "People are either gay, straight or lying" embody this [[dichotomous]] view of sexual orientations.&lt;ref name="Dworkin"/&gt; Bisexuals often face this type of discrimination from the heterosexual community, but are frequently eyed with suspicion by gay people as well, usually with the notion that bisexuals are able to escape oppression from heterosexuals because of their attraction towards the opposite gender. This leaves some that identify as bisexual to be perceived as "not enough of either" or "not real."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Compulsory Bisexuality?: The Challenges of Modern Sexual Fluidity|url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15299710903316661|journal = Journal of Bisexuality|date = 2009-11-13|issn = 1529-9716|pages = 431–449|volume = 9|issue = 3-4|doi = 10.1080/15299710903316661|first = Breanne|last = Fahs}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Resulting negative stereotypes represent bisexuals as confused, undecided, dabblers, insecure, experimenting or "just going through a phase."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bisexualindex.org.uk/index.php/Main/ItsJustAPhase "It's Just A Phase" Is Just A Phrase], The Bisexual Index&lt;/ref&gt; Another negative stereotype that persists against bisexuality is stating that bisexuality is a trend. By saying this one is disproving the existence of the sexuality itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Ka'ahumanu|first1=Lani|last2=Yaeger|first2=Rob|title=Biphobia|url=https://lgbt.ucsd.edu/education/biphobia.html|website=LGBT Resource Center UC San Diego|publisher=UC San Diego|accessdate=September 22, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sexual attractions toward both sexes are also considered fashionable as in "[[bisexual chic]]" or [[gender bending]]. This fashionability affects bisexual males, as they are often invalidated more than females in terms of their sexuality not being viewed as "hot."{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}} Another discriminatory tendency that often affects exclusively males is the stereotype that women can be bisexual, but men cannot. Relations are dismissed as a substitute for sex with members of the "right" sex or as a more accessible source of [[sexual gratification]]. [[Situational homosexuality]] due to [[Sex segregation|sex-segregated]] environments or groups such as the armed forces, schools, sports teams, religious orders, and [[prison sexuality|prisons]] is another facet of explaining why someone is allegedly temporarily gay.

=== Promiscuity ===
The association of bisexuality with promiscuity stems from a variety of negative stereotypes targeting bisexuals as mentally or socially unstable people for whom sexual relations only with men, only with women, or only with one person is not enough. These stereotypes may result from cultural assumptions that "men and women are so different that desire for one is an entirely different beast from desire for the other" ("a defining feature of [[heterosexism]]"), and that "verbalizing a sexual desire inevitably leads to attempts to satisfy that desire."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pepperminty.com/writing/bis-and-slut-myth.pdf "Bisexuals and the Slut Myth"], presented at the 9th [[International Conference on Bisexuality]]&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result, bisexuals bear a [[Stigma (sociological theory)|social stigma]] from accusations of cheating on or betraying their partners, leading a [[double life]], being "on the [[Down-low (sexual slang)|down-low]]", and spreading [[sexually transmitted disease]]s such as [[HIV]]/[[AIDS]]. They are characterized as being "slutty", insatiable, "easy", indiscriminate, and in the case of women, [[Hypersexuality|nymphomaniacs]]. Furthermore, they are strongly associated with [[polyamory]], [[Swinging (sexual practice)|swinging]], and [[polygamy]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glaad.org/programs/cim/birepresentations.php GLAAD: Cultural Interest Media] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060419203924/http://www.glaad.org/programs/cim/birepresentations.php |date=April 19, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the last being an established heterosexual tradition sanctioned by some religions and legal in several countries. People of any sexual orientation can change partners, practice [[serial monogamy]] or have multiple casual sex partners or multiple romantic relationships. The fact that bisexuals are potentially sexually attracted to both men and women does not mean that they must simultaneously engage in sexual relationships with both men and women to be satisfied; they can be happily married or in an exclusive relationship with one person of either gender.{{citation needed|date=November 2015}}

== Mental and sexual health effects ==
The mental and sexual health effects of biphobia on bisexuals are numerous. Studies show that bisexuals are often trapped in between the binaries of heterosexuality and homosexuality, creating a form of invalidation around their sexual identity. This often leads to recognized indicators of mental health issues such as low self-esteem and self-worth. These indicators and pressures to 'choose' a [[sexual identity]] can, in many cases, lead to [[depression (mood)|depression]] as they may feel they live in a culture that does not recognize their existence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Individual and Social Factors Related to Mental Health Concerns among Bisexual Men in the Midwestern United States|journal = Journal of bisexuality|date = 2012-01-01|issn = 1529-9716|pmc = 3383005|pmid = 22745591|pages = 223–245|volume = 12|issue = 2|first = Brian|last = Dodge|first2 = Phillip W.|last2 = Schnarrs|first3 = Michael|last3 = Reece|first4 = Omar|last4 = Martinez|first5 = Gabriel|last5 = Goncalves|first6 = David|last6 = Malebranche|first7 = Barbara|last7 = Van Der Pol|first8 = Ryan|last8 = Nix|first9 = J. Dennis|last9 = Fortenberry|doi=10.1080/15299716.2012.674862}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While doing research on sexual tendencies of women who have sex with women, one study, from the Journal of Bisexuality, concluded that bisexual women are more likely to engage in various high risk behaviors and were at a higher risk of contracting HIV and other sexually transmitted diseases.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Sexual and drug-use risk factors for HIV and STDs: a comparison of women with and without bisexual experiences.|url = http://ajph.aphapublications.org/doi/pdf/10.2105/AJPH.89.12.1841|journal = American Journal of Public Health|pages = 1841–1846|volume = 89|issue = 12|doi = 10.2105/ajph.89.12.1841|first = V|last = Gonzales|first2 = K M|last2 = Washienko|first3 = M R|last3 = Krone|first4 = L I|last4 = Chapman|first5 = E M|last5 = Arredondo|first6 = H J|last6 = Huckeba|first7 = A|last7 = Downer}}&lt;/ref&gt; These behaviors have been attributed to the unlikeliness of bisexuals to discuss their sexuality and proper protection with health professionals for fear of judgement or discrimination, leaving them uneducated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://www.lgbthealtheducation.org/wp-content/uploads/12-054_LGBTHealtharticle_v3_07-09-12.pdf|title = IMPROVING THE HEALTH CARE OF LESBIAN, GAY, BISEXUAL AND TRANSGENDER PEOPLE: Understanding and Eliminating Health Disparities|last = Makadon MD|first = Harvey J|date = 7/9/2012|journal = Fenway Institute|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |last2 = Ard MD, MPH|first2 = Kevin L|publisher = U.S. Department of Health and Human Services}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bisexual erasure ==
[[Bisexual erasure]] or ''bisexual invisibility'' is the tendency to ignore, remove, falsify, or reexplain evidence of [[bisexuality]] in [[history]], [[academia]], the [[news media]], and other [[primary source]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://queersunited.blogspot.com/2008/05/word-of-gay-bisexual-erasure.html Word Of The Gay: BisexualErasure] May 16, 2008 "Queers United"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ronsuresha.com/?p=1018 The B Word] Suresha, Ron. "The B Word," Options (Rhode Island), November 2004&lt;/ref&gt; In its most extreme form, bisexual erasure can include denying that bisexuality exists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hutchins |first=Loraine |authorlink=Loraine Hutchins |title=Sexual Prejudice: The erasure of bisexuals in academia and the media |journal=[[American Sexuality magazine]] |volume=3 |issue=4 |publisher=[[National Sexuality Resource Center]] |year=2005 |url=http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071216065035/http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0 |archivedate=2007-12-16 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0 | title = Sexual Prejudice - The erasure of bisexuals in academia and the media | accessdate = 2007-07-19 | last = Hutchins | first = Loraine | authorlink = Loraine Hutchins | work = American Sexuality Magazine | publisher = National Sexuality Resource Center, San Francisco State University | location = San Francisco, CA 94103, United States | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071216065035/http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0 | archivedate = 2007-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is often a manifestation of biphobia, although it does not necessarily involve overt antagonism. However, there is also increasing support, inclusion, and visibility in both bisexual and non-bisexual communities, especially in the [[LGBT]] community.&lt;ref name="Queers United"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://queersunited.blogspot.com/ |title=Queers United }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="the task force"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/issues/bisexuality |title=Task Force Report On Bisexuality |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140216071740/http://www.thetaskforce.org/issues/bisexuality |archivedate=2014-02-16 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="HRC"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hrc.org/issues/coming_out/bisexual/bisexual_articles.asp?listpage=2 |title=HRC article on bisexuality}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GLAAD"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://glaadbackup.com/2009/documents/GLAADNRI2009.pdf|title=GLAAD TV Report }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Maria, September 24, 2009. [http://bisocialnews.com/how-far-have-we-come How Far Have We Come?], ''BiSocial News''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Thirteen"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ausiellofiles.ew.com/2008/10/27/greys-anatomy-s-3/ |title=Thirteen On House }}{{dead link|date=November 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another place that biphobia often manifests is within the LGBTQI movement itself. While the name specifically claims inclusivity making reference to lesbians, gays, bisexuals, transsexuals, queer identifying individuals, and intersex people, the needs of the BTQI community are often not prioritized in the same way as the needs of the LG community{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}}. While the beginnings of the gay rights movement started in the late seventeen hundreds within groups of militant "sodomite-citizens" in Paris, it was not until 1997 that the UK’s first bisexual youth group was established.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Including the B-word: Reflections on the place of bisexuality within lesbian and gay activism and psychology|last = Barker|first = Meg|date = 2004|journal = Lesbian and Gay Psychology Review|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1992, despite requests from the bisexual community for a more appropriate and inclusive category, the groundbreaking bisexual anthology ''[[Bi Any Other Name: Bisexual People Speak Out]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |title=Bi Any Other Name: Bisexual People Speak Out Review 
 |publisher=International Gay &amp; Lesbian Review 
 |url=http://gaybookreviews.info/review/2488/548 
 |accessdate=2007-11-25 
 |deadurl=yes 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070928141453/http://gaybookreviews.info/review/2488/548 
 |archivedate=2007-09-28 
 |df= 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Loraine Hutchins]] and [[Lani Kaahumanu]] was forced to compete (and lose) in the category "Lesbian Anthology" in the [[Lambda Literary Award]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |title=1991 Lambda Literary Awards Recipients
 |publisher=Lambda Literary Foundation
 |url=http://www.lambdaliterary.org/awards/previous_winners/paw_1988_1991.html#1991
 |accessdate=2007-11-25 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070927024201/http://www.lambdaliterary.org/awards/previous_winners/paw_1988_1991.html#1991 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, in 2005, ''Directed by Desire: Collected Poems'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |title=Directed by Desire: Collected Poems
 |publisher=Copper Canyon Press
 |url=http://www.poetryfoundation.org/article/178530
 |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; a posthumous collection of the bisexual [[Jamaican American]] writer [[June Jordan|June Jordan's]] work, had to compete (and win) in the category "Lesbian Poetry".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |title=2005 Lambda Literary Awards Recipients
 |publisher=Lambda Literary Foundation
 |url=http://www.lambdaliterary.org/winners-finalists/04/09/lambda-literary-awards-2005/ |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Led by [[BiNet USA]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |last=Curry
 |first=Wendy
 |authorlink=Wendy Curry
 |title=What makes a book bisexual?
 |work=Curried Spam
 |publisher=BiNet USA
 |year=2007
 |url=http://www.binetusa.org/curriedspam.html#bibook
 |accessdate=2007-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; and assisted by other bisexual organizations including the [[American Institute of Bisexuality]], [[BiPOL]], and [[Bialogue]], the bisexual community launched a multi-year struggle that eventually culminated in 2006 with the addition of a Bisexual category.

The marginalization of bisexuals also manifests regularly in terms of social acceptability of discrimination against bisexuals. For example, habits of letting biphobic comments and jokes that would not be acceptable, were they about gays or lesbians, go unchallenged. Another way this occurs is when people ask intrusive questions about a person’s bisexuality that would be considered offensive in relation to other’s monosexualities. While this primarily affects bisexuals on a social level this social discrimination also leads to institutional marginalization, which can result in exclusion from anti-discrimination policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = The Bisexuality Report: Bisexual inclusion in LGBT equality and diversity|last = Barker|first = Meg|date = February 2012|journal = Centre for Citizenship, Identities and Governance and Faculty of Health and Social Care|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Monosexism ==
Monosexism is a term used to refer to beliefs, structures, and actions that promote [[monosexuality]] (either exclusive heterosexuality or homosexuality) as the only legitimate or right sexual orientation, excluding bisexual or other non-monosexual orientations.&lt;ref name="Highleyman"&gt;Highleyman, Liz (1995). [http://www.black-rose.com/articles-liz/bipol.html "Identities and Ideas: Strategies for Bisexuals"], from the anthology ''Bisexual Politics: Theories, Queries, and Visions''. Haworth Press. ''Black Rose Web Pages''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="rust"&gt;[[Paula Rodriguez Rust|Rust, Paula C Rodriguez]] (2002). [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3778/is_200201/ai_n9069533/pg_18 "Bisexuality: The state of the union, Annual Review of Sex Research, 2002"], ''BNET''. {{dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term may be considered analogous to biphobia.&lt;ref name="rust"/&gt;

The term is primarily used in discussions of sexual orientation to denote aversion towards all non-monosexual people as a social group or as individuals. It was likely adopted in place of [[unisexual]], which is already used in biology and would produce confusion. It is sometimes considered derogatory by the people to whom it is applied.&lt;ref&gt;Hamilton, Alan (2000). ''{{cite web|url=http://www.biresource.org/pamphlets/glossary.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-06-04 |deadurl=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070805044122/http://www.biresource.org/pamphlets/glossary.html |archivedate=2007-08-05 |df= }} ''of "LesBiGay and Transgender Glossary", ''[http://www.biresource.net/ Bisexual Resource Center]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

The proportion of people who fit into the category depends on how one uses the word. If the term is used to mean exclusively monosexual in behavior, then according to [[Alfred Kinsey]]'s [[Kinsey Reports|studies]], 63% of men and 87% of women are what may now be termed "monosexual" as determined by experiences leading to [[orgasm]].&lt;ref&gt;(1999). [http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/resources/bib-homoprev.html "Prevalence of Homosexuality"], ''The Kinsey Institute''. Note that Kinsey did not use the term "bisexual", but that he uses "exclusively homosexual" and "exclusively heterosexual".&lt;/ref&gt; Freud thought that no one was born monosexual and that it had to be taught by parents or society, though most people appear to believe that monosexuals are in fact the majority and identify as such.&lt;ref&gt;Rethinking Marxism: A Journal of Economics, Culture &amp; Society, Volume 8, Issue 3, 1995, Feminist Economies, DOI:10.1080/08935699508685453, Margaret Nash, pages 66-78.&lt;/ref&gt;

Monosexism could also be attributed to the belief in sexuality as a binary. The notion of sexuality as a binary is not new. Throughout the 1980s, modern research on sexuality was dominated by the idea that heterosexuality and homosexuality were the only legitimate sexualities, dismissing bisexuality as "secondary homosexuality".&lt;ref name="ProQuest"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Managing Heterosexism and Biphobia: A Revealing Black Bisexual Male Perspective|url = https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=lang_en&amp;id=5iayOla-7qcC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR3&amp;dq=%2522Managing+Heterosexism+and+Biphobia:+A+Black+Bisexual+Male+Perspective&amp;ots=f6xf6Kx-0s&amp;sig=U0rv73VAXngWQt2HeAaQ-u9ZBK0#v=onepage&amp;q=%2522Managing%2520Heterosexism%2520and%2520Biphobia%253A%2520A%2520Black%2520Bisexual%2520Male%2520Perspective&amp;f=false|publisher = ProQuest|date = 2008-01-01|isbn = 9780549622482}}&lt;/ref&gt; These ideas persisted until the development of alternative models such as the [[Kinsey scale]]. The Kinsey scale was developed by Kinsey in 1953 and instituted a paradigm shift that completely changed the way that people looked at sexuality.&lt;ref name="ProQuest"/&gt; His seven-point scale redefined sexuality, as it allowed people to identify at various points throughout the scale with 0 being exclusively heterosexual and 6 being exclusively homosexual. The scale is now widely used and seeks to eliminate the dominance of the binary that is often the cause of biphobia.{{citation needed|date=November 2015}}

== In feminism ==
Feminist positions on [[bisexuality]] range greatly, from acceptance of bisexuality as a feminist issue to rejection of bisexuality as reactionary and anti-feminist [[Backlash (sociology)|backlash]] to [[lesbian feminism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Wilkinson |first1=Sue |authorlink1= |last2= |first2= |authorlink2= |editor1-first=Lynne |editor1-last=Harne |editor1-link= |others=Elaine Miller |title=All the Rage: Reasserting Radical Lesbian Feminism |trans_title= |url= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |type= |edition= |series= |volume= |date= |year= 1996|month= |origyear= |publisher= [[Teachers College, Columbia University|Teacher's College Press]]|location= New York City|isbn= 0-807-76285-7 |oclc= 35202923|doi= |id= |page= |pages=75–89 |at= |trans_chapter= |chapter=Bisexuality as Backlash |chapterurl= |quote= |ref= |bibcode= |laysummary= |laydate= |author-mask= |display-authors= |postscript= |lastauthoramp=}}&lt;!--|accessdate=October 4, 2012 --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Bisexuality|bisexual]] woman filed a lawsuit against the lesbian feminist magazine ''[[Common Lives/Lesbian Lives]]'', alleging discrimination against bisexuals when her submission was not published.&lt;ref name="sdrc.lib.uiowa.edu"&gt;[http://sdrc.lib.uiowa.edu/iwa/findingaids/html/CommonlIves.html Common Lives/Lesbian Lives Records, Iowa Women's Archives, University of Iowa Libraries, Iowa City, Iowa]&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of women who were at one time involved in lesbian-feminist activism have since [[Coming out|come out]] as bisexual after realizing their attractions to men. A widely studied example of lesbian-bisexual conflict within feminism was the Northampton Pride March during the years between 1989 and 1993, where many feminists involved debated over whether bisexuals should be included and whether or not bisexuality was compatible with feminism. Common lesbian-feminist critiques leveled at bisexuality were that bisexuality was [[Antifeminism|anti-feminist]], that bisexuality was a form of [[false consciousness]], and that bisexual women who pursue relationships with men were "deluded and desperate." However, tensions between bisexual feminists and lesbian feminists have eased since the 1990s, as bisexual women have become more accepted within the feminist community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Routledge International Encyclopedia of Queer Culture|last= Gerstner|first= David A.|authorlink= |year= 2006|publisher= [[Routledge]]|location= United Kingdom|isbn= 978-0-415-30651-5|page= |pages= 82–3|accessdate=October 3, 2012 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XS_SnVPixE8C&amp;pg=PA82&amp;lpg=PA82&amp;dq=%22bisexual+feminism%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=n32nIC-3XC&amp;sig=h7jkH9Tq2dtkR0gs9Q7hmvNMzZ4&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=zrdsUIKQLeWC0QHKqYHwAQ&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, some lesbian feminists such as [[Julie Bindel]] are still critical of bisexuality. Bindel has described female bisexuality as a "fashionable trend" being promoted due to "sexual hedonism" and broached the question of whether bisexuality even exists.&lt;ref name="Bindel"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/julie-bindel/where-is-the-politics-in-_b_1589435.html |title=Where's the Politics in Sex? |publisher=''[[The Huffington Post]]'' |accessdate=2012-10-03 |first=Julie |last=Bindel |date=June 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; She has also made [[tongue-in-cheek]] comparisons of bisexuals to [[Animal fancy|cat fanciers]] and [[Satanism|devil worshippers]].&lt;ref name="guardian.co.uk"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2008/nov/08/lesbianism |title=It's not me. It's you |publisher=''[[The Guardian]]'' |accessdate=2012-10-03 |location=London |first=Julie |last=Bindel |date=November 8, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lesbian feminist [[Sheila Jeffreys]] writes in ''The Lesbian Heresy'' (1993) that while many feminists are comfortable working alongside gay men, they are uncomfortable interacting with bisexual men. Jeffreys states that while gay men are unlikely to [[Sexual harassment|sexually harass]] women, bisexual men are just as likely to be bothersome to women as heterosexual men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Lesbian Heresy|last= Jeffreys|first= Sheila|authorlink= |year= 1993|publisher= Spinifex Press Pty Ltf|location= [[Melbourne]], [[Australia]] |isbn= 1-875559-17-5|page= 124|pages= |accessdate=October 4, 2012 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0FFWxDu9gn0C&amp;pg=PA124&amp;lpg=PA124&amp;dq=feminism+%22bisexual+men%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=984-PHC0xm&amp;sig=931FU6VoBpDMW9GZgw_bdEQOA2g&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=bQptUK-eOaXE0AGd2IDIBw&amp;ved=0CEwQ6AEwBTge#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Donna Haraway]] was the inspiration and genesis for [[cyberfeminism]] with her 1985 essay "A Cyborg Manifesto: Science, Technology, and Socialist-Feminism in the Late Twentieth Century" which was reprinted in ''Simians, Cyborgs and Women: The Reinvention of Nature'' (1991). Haraway's essay states that the cyborg "has no truck with bisexuality, pre-oedipal symbiosis, unalienated labor, or other seductions to organic wholeness through a final appropriation of all powers of the parts into a higher unity." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egs.edu/faculty/donna-haraway/articles/donna-haraway-a-cyborg-manifesto/ |title=Donna Haraway - A Cyborg Manifesto |publisher=Egs.edu |date= |accessdate=2015-09-15 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130922114218/http://www.egs.edu/faculty/donna-haraway/articles/donna-haraway-a-cyborg-manifesto/ |archivedate=2013-09-22 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, ''Cyberfeminism and Bisexuality'' by Jane Cyborg, a short essay published as a book in 2015, states, "Cyborgs can be bisexual, and cyberfeminism can and should be accepting of bisexuality."&lt;ref&gt;''Cyberfeminism and Bisexuality'' by Jane Cyborg (2015)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Intersectional perspective ==
While the general bisexual population as a whole faces biphobia, this oppression is also aggravated by other factors such as race. In his examination of the bisexual male perspective, entitled, ''Managing Heterosexism and Biphobia: A Revealing Black Bisexual Male Perspective'', Grady L. Garner delves into the oppression that he faces as both a black and bisexual male. He explains that the internalization of negative sociocultural messages, reactions, and attitudes can be incredibly distressing as bisexual black males attempted to translate or transform these negative experiences into positive bisexual identity sustaining ones.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Bisexuality in the United States: A Social Science Reader|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=EwcABAApgR8C|publisher = Columbia University Press|date = 2000-01-01|isbn = 9780231102278|first = Paula C.|last = Rust}}&lt;/ref&gt; The experience of bisexual black males is different from that of bisexual white males. As the demands and tribulations of black bisexual males appear to be comparatively more distressing than those that black and white, homo- and heterosexual individual's encounter, this acknowledgement is important and vital to the understanding of biphobia from an intersectional perspective.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"/&gt;

== Bailey study ==
{{Further information|Bisexuality#Perceptions and discrimination}}
A 2005 article in ''[[The New York Times]]'' used the word ''biphobic'' when criticizing a study about male bisexuality. The study, which was by Gerulf Rieger, [[Meredith Chivers|Meredith L. Chivers]], and [[J. Michael Bailey]], and took place in 2002, said that a sample of men self-identifying as bisexual did not respond equally to pornographic material involving only men, and to pornography involving only women, but instead showed four times more arousal to one than the other. The article criticized the method of measurement of arousal as too crude to capture the richness (erotic sensations, affection, admiration) that constitutes sexual attraction.&lt;ref name="Carey"&gt;{{cite news |last=Carey |first=Benedict |title=Straight, Gay or Lying? Bisexuality Revisited |work=The New York Times |date=5 July 2005 |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F20714FB3B550C768CDDAE0894DD404482 |accessdate=24 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ngltf"&gt;[[National Gay and Lesbian Task Force]] (July 2005). [http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/reports/NYTBisexualityFactSheet.pdf The Problems with "Gay, Straight, or Lying?"] ([[PDF]]) Retrieved 24 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="FAIR"&gt;{{Cite web|title=New York Times Suggests Bisexuals Are 'Lying.' Paper fails to disclose study author's controversial history|publisher=[[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] |date=July 8, 2005|accessdate=June 22, 2013|url=http://fair.org/take-action/action-alerts/new-york-times-suggests-bisexuals-are-quotlyingquot/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Institute of Bisexuality]] stated that Bailey's study was misinterpreted and misreported by both ''The New York Times'' and the study's critics.&lt;ref name=bibrain.org&gt;{{cite web|title=Controversy over Professor J. Michael Bailey and the Existence of Bisexuality |publisher=[[American Institute of Bisexuality]] |year=2012 |accessdate=15 March 2015 |url=http://www.bibrain.org/ControversyOverBaileyV2.0.pdf |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130820150533/http://www.bibrain.org/ControversyOverBaileyV2.0.pdf |archivedate=August 20, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|LGBT}}

* [[Bisexual American history]]
* [[Bisexual community]]
* [[Duclod Man]]
* [[Heteronormativity]]
* [[History of bisexuality]]
* [[International Day Against Homophobia, Transphobia and Biphobia]] (biphobia was added to the name of the day in 2015)
* [[List of media portrayals of bisexuality]]
* [[List of phobias]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|40em}}

== Further reading ==
* [[Marjorie Garber|Garber, Marjorie]] (1995). ''Bisexuality and the Eroticism of Everyday Life'', pp.&amp;nbsp;20–21, 28, 39.
* [[Mariam Fraser|Fraser, M.]], ''Identity Without Selfhood: Simone de Beauvoir and Bisexuality'', Cambridge and New York: Cambridge University Press 1999. p.&amp;nbsp;124–140.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110204071248/http://www.xtra.ca/public/viewstory.aspx?AFF_TYPE=3&amp;STORY_ID=1901&amp;PUB_TEMPLATE_ID=2 The fencesitters? Suspicions still haunt the bi/homo divide] - article in Xtra, Gay &amp; Lesbian news site, 2006]

== External links ==
* [http://www.bialogue.org/Pages/InfoPackets/MentalHealth.html Bialogue/GLAAD Bisexuality Packet for Mental Health Professionals]
* [http://www.advocate.com/exclusive_detail_ektid49066.asp Fairy Tales], by Job Brother in [[The Advocate]] September 21, 2007
* [http://marksimpson.com/pages/journalism/curiouser.html Curiouser and curiouser] by [[Mark Simpson (journalist)|Mark Simpson]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100701174350/http://out.ucr.edu/pdf/BiBasics.pdf Bisexuality Basics, UC Riverside LGBT Resource Center, Riverside, CA]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Bisexuality topics}}
{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Discrimination}}
}}

[[Category:Bisexuality]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Hatred]]
[[Category:LGBT terminology]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender-related prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>