<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061031042409|84773572" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="247171" pageid="247171" ns="0" title="Biphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-11T01:16:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Portal|LGBT|Gay flag.svg|50px}}
'''Biphobia''' is the fear of, discrimination against, or hatred of [[bisexuality|bisexuals]] (although in practice it extends to [[pansexual]] people too). It need not include [[homophobia]] or [[heterophobia]], because there are [[stereotype]]s that are specific to bisexuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Eliason, MJ | title=The prevalence and nature of biphobia in heterosexual undergraduate students. | journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior | volume=26 | issue=3 | year=1997 | pages=317-26}} PMID 9146816&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biphobic stereotypes==
{{gay rights}}Some bisexual stereotypes include, but are not limited to: [[promiscuity]], [[polygamy]], living the [[swinging]] lifestyle, and being "confused."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.glaad.org/programs/cim/birepresentations.php&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, bisexuals are accused of bringing [[sexually transmitted disease]] into the heterosexual community or into the lesbian community. A related stereotype is one in which a bisexual is presumed to be willing to have sex with just about anyone. This stereotype leads to unwanted attention of a sexual nature directed at bisexual [[female]]s by swingers and heterosexual males while often stereotyping bisexual males as walking [[AIDS]] risks.

Often, however, heterosexuals and homosexuals will add more stereotypes based on homophobia or heterophobia. Homophobes may think that bisexuals are gender nonconformist. Heterophobes will often think of bisexuals as maintaining privilege and collaborating with the homophobes while simultaneously enjoying the LGBT lifestyle. Some consider the belief that people are either heterosexual or homosexual (a somewhat common belief among both heterosexuals and homosexuals, both of which fall under the category of [[monosexual]]s), and thus that bisexuality does not truly exist, to be biphobic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Dworkin, SH | title=Treating the bisexual client | journal=Journal of Clinical Psychology | volume=57 | issue=5 | year=2001 | pages=671-80}} PMID 11304706&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2002 study claimed that a sample of men self-identifying as bisexual did not respond equally to pornographic material involving only men, and to pornography involving only women, but instead showed four times more arousal to one than the other. However, bisexuality does not imply equal attraction towards both genders. In addition, opponents claim that genital arousal to homosexual pornographic material is not a good indicator of orientation. They also point out that the study showed a third of men had no arousal, and ask why this doesn't mean that one third of men are really asexual.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thetaskforce.org/media/NYTBiArt/LettersFromTheCommunity.cfm&lt;/ref&gt; The study, and the New York Times article which reported it in 2005&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/05/health/05sex.html Straight, Gay or Lying? Bisexuality Revisited] New York Times, July 5, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;, were subsequently criticized as flawed and biphobic.&lt;ref&gt;http://zzz.pridesource.com/article.shtml?article=15015&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lynn Conway]] criticised the author of the study, [[J. Michael Bailey]], citing his controversial history, and pointing out that the study has not been scientifically repeated and confirmed by any independent researchers.&lt;ref&gt;http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TS/Bailey/Bisexuality/Bisexuality-NYT%207-05-05.html&lt;/ref&gt;

{{sexual orientation}}One common motive for negative attitudes toward bisexuality among [[lesbian]]s is the fear that a bisexual [[woman]] will leave a woman for a [[man]]; and vice versa with gay males fearing that they would be dumped for a woman. The heterosexual male is seen as having an unfair systemic advantage both due to [[sexism]] and due to homophobia.  Bisexual persons may also be the target of homophobia from those who consider only heterosexuality appropriate.  The reverse can also apply in that bisexual persons may be targets of heterophobia or discrimination by some gays/homosexuals - this is especially prevalent amongst bisexual men.&lt;ref&gt;Weiss, Jillian T., ''GL vs. BT: The Archaeology of Biphobia and Transphobia Within the U.S. Gay and Lesbian Community'', Journal of Bisexuality (Haworth Press 2004), available at [http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/glvsbt.htm http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/glvsbt.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

Many anti-bisexuals also believe that bisexuality is a trend, especially a teenage one, popularised by bisexual musicians, actors, etc. (i.e. the term, he built a window in his closet): some also believe it is a stage in adolescence which happens to everyone which people grow out of and that therefore bisexuals are worse people for making an issue out of it. Some also believe bisexuals are just seeking attention for comfort or sex. However, these claims have no scientific grounds at all. 

Some [[radical feminism|radical]] [[Lesbian feminism|lesbian feminists]] think that bisexual women are giving in to [[patriarchy]]. Others say that people against bisexuals are insecure about their sexuality themselves, similarly to homophobia. It is fair to note many anti-bisexuals are also [[Anti-homosexualism|anti-homosexual]], while maintaining there are only heterosexual and homosexual as sexual preferences, and a common stereotype is that female bisexuals are attention seeking heterosexuals, while male ones are just self-denying homosexuals too afraid to acknowledge their true orientation.

==See also==
*[[Bigotry]]
*[[Prejudice]]
*[[Bisexual erasure]]
*[[Sexual hierarchy]]
*[[Homophobia]]
*[[Monosexism]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
* [[Kenji Yoshino|Yoshino, Kenji]] (2000). ''The Epistemic Contract of Bisexual Erasure'' [http://www.kenjiyoshino.com/articles/epistemiccontract.pdf]. ''[[Stanford Law Review]]'', 52 (2).
* [http://groups.yahoo.com/group/BiMHP/ Association of Bi Mental Health Professionals]
* [http://www.bialogue.org/index.html Dear Fellow Non-existent Beings: countering current attempts to erase bisexuality [[Bialogue]] ]
* [http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0] [[Loraine Hutchins | Hutchins, Loraine]]; ''Sexual Prejudice: The erasure of bisexuals in academia and the media''; American Sexuality Magazine, Volume 3, No. 4 (2005)
* [http://www.bialogue.org/Pages/InfoPackets/MentalHealth.html Bialogue/GLAAD Bisexuality Packet for Mental Health Professionals]

[[Category:bisexual community]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]

[[da:Bifobi]]
[[de:Biphobie]]
[[fr:Biphobie]]
[[hr:bifobija]]
[[nl:Bifobie]]
[[zh:雙性戀恐懼症]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>