<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081015052608|245384675" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="247171" pageid="247171" ns="0" title="Biphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-06T04:30:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{weasel|date=June 2008}}
{{Original research|date=June 2008}}
{{Bisexuality topics sidebar}}
'''Biphobia''' is a term used to describe the fear of, aversion to, or discrimination against [[bisexuality]] or [[LGBT]] people who are bisexual or perceived to be bisexual. It can also mean hatred, hostility, disapproval of, or prejudice towards LGBT people, sexual behavior, or cultures. '''Biphobic''' is the adjective form of this term used to describe the qualities of these characteristics while the less common '''biophobe''' is the noun form given as a title to individuals with "biphobic" characteristics. It need not include or exclude [[homophobia]], [[heterophobia]], or [[lesbophobia]], because there are [[stereotype]]s that are specific to bisexuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Eliason, MJ|title=The prevalence and nature of biphobia in heterosexual undergraduate students|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|volume=26|issue=3|year=1997|pages=317–26|pmid=9146816|doi=10.1023/A:1024527032040}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bisexual stereotypes=={{Discrimination sidebar}}
Bisexual stereotypes include, but are not limited to: [[promiscuity]], [[polygamy]], living the [[swinging]] lifestyle, and being "confused" or "greedy" or "slutty". &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glaad.org/programs/cim/birepresentations.php GLAAD: Cultural Interest Media&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, bisexuals are accused of bringing [[sexually transmitted disease]]s into the heterosexual community or into the LGBT community. A related stereotype is one in which a bisexual person is presumed to be willing to have sex with just about anyone. This stereotype leads to unwanted attention of a sexual nature directed at bisexual [[female]]s, while often stereotyping bisexual males as major [[AIDS]] risks.

Bisexuals are sometimes called "confused" by people, both heterosexuals and homosexuals, who believe that they are simply pretending to be bisexual in order to avoid homophobia. Similarly, bisexuals may be called "dabblers," as an insinuation that they are still experimenting sexually, or are simply perverted.

Often, however, heterosexuals will add more stereotypes based on homophobia. Homophobes often think that bisexuals are gender nonconformist. Homosexual people will sometimes see bisexuals as maintaining privilege and collaborating with the homophobes while simultaneously availing themselves of opportunities in LBGT communities. Some consider the belief that people are either heterosexual or homosexual, and thus that bisexuality does not truly exist, to be biphobic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dworkin, SH |title=Treating the bisexual client|journal=Journal of Clinical Psychology|volume=57|issue=5|year=2001|pages=671–80 | pmid=11304706 |doi=10.1002/jclp.1036}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2002 study said that a sample of men self-identifying as bisexual did not respond equally to pornographic material involving only men, and to pornography involving only women, but instead showed four times more arousal to one than the other. However, bisexuality does not imply equal attraction towards both genders. In addition, opponents state that genital arousal to homosexual pornographic material is not a good indicator of orientation. They also point out that the study showed a third of men had no arousal, and ask why this does not mean that one third of men are really [[asexual]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thetaskforce.org/media/NYTBiArt/LettersFromTheCommunity.cfm]{{Dead link|date=March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study, and ''[[The New York Times]]'' article which reported it in 2005,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/05/health/05sex.html Straight, Gay or Lying? Bisexuality Revisited] New York Times, July 5, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; were subsequently criticized as flawed and biphobic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://zzz.pridesource.com/article.shtml?article=15015 PrideSource: Bisexual study, New York Times article cause furor&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://main.bisexual.com/forum/showthread.php?t=3799 "Gay Straight or Lying? Bisexuality Revisited," Revisited - Part 1 by [[William Burleson]] June 26 2007&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lynn Conway]] criticized the author of the study, [[J. Michael Bailey]], citing his controversial history, and pointing out that the study has not been scientifically repeated and confirmed by any independent researchers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TS/Bailey/Bisexuality/Bisexuality-NYT%207-05-05.html "Straight, Gay or Lying? Bisexuality Revisted" J. Michael Bailey attacks the identities of bisexual men&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Conversely, there is a school of thought that says that "everyone is bisexual."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biresource.org/pamphlets/myths.pdf Myths About Bisexuality] (PDF pamphlet from Bisexual Resource Center)&lt;/ref&gt;
One common motive for negative attitudes toward bisexuality, for straight partners of bisexuals, is the fear that their bisexual parter will leave them for a member of the same sex. Similar fears exist among gay people as well. 

The heterosexual male is seen as having an unfair systemic advantage due to both [[sexism]] and homophobia.  Bisexual persons may also be the target of homophobia from those who consider only heterosexuality appropriate.  

Some [[radical feminism|radical]] [[Lesbian feminism|lesbian feminists]] think that bisexual women are giving in to [[patriarchy]].{{Fact|date=August 2008}} Others say that people against bisexuals are insecure about their sexuality themselves, similarly to homophobia. It is fair to note many anti-bisexuals are also [[homophobia|homophobic]], while maintaining there are only heterosexual and homosexual as sexual preferences, and a common stereotype is that female bisexuals are attention seeking heterosexuals, while male ones are just self-denying homosexuals too afraid to fully acknowledge their true orientation.

==See also==
{{Portal|LGBT|Portal LGBT.svg}}
*[[Bisexual erasure]]
*[[Duclod Man]]
*[[Heteronormativity]]
*[[Heterosexism]]
*[[Homophobia]]
*[[Monosexism]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* [[Marjorie Garber|Garber, Marjorie]] (1995). ''Bisexuality and the Eroticism of Everyday Life'', pp. 20-21, 28, 39.
* [[Mariam Fraser|Fraser, M.]], ''Identity Without Selfhood: Simone de Beauvoir and Bisexuality'', Cambridge and New York: Cambridge University Press 1999. p.124-140.

==External links==
* [http://www.bialogue.org/Pages/InfoPackets/MentalHealth.html Bialogue/GLAAD Bisexuality Packet for Mental Health Professionals]
* [http://www.advocate.com/exclusive_detail_ektid49066.asp Fairy Tales], by Job Brother in [[The Advocate]] September 21, 2007
* [http://marksimpson.com/pages/journalism/curiouser.html Curiouser and curiouser] by [[Mark Simpson (journalist)|Mark Simpson]]

{{Template group
|list =
{{LGBT}}
{{Discrimination}}
}}
{{Phobias}}

[[Category:Bisexuality]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:LGBT terms]]

[[da:Bifobi]]
[[es:Bifobia]]
[[fr:Biphobie]]
[[hr:Bifobija]]
[[he:ביפוביה]]
[[hu:Bifóbia]]
[[nl:Bifobie]]
[[pt:Bifobia]]
[[zh:雙性戀恐懼症]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>