<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051030212104|26912600" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="247171" pageid="247171" ns="0" title="Biphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-08T17:36:42Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Biphobia''' is the fear of, discrimination against, or hatred of [[bisexuality|bisexuals]]. It need not include [[homophobia]] or [[heterophobia]], because there are [[stereotype]]s that are specific to bisexuals.{{ref|biphobia}}

These include, but are not limited to: [[promiscuity]], [[polygamy]], living the [[swinging]] lifestyle, and being confused. In some cases, bisexuals are accused of bringing [[sexually transmitted disease]] into the heterosexual community or into the lesbian community. A related stereotype is one in which a bisexual is presumed to be willing to have sex with basically anyone. This stereotype leads to unwanted attention of a sexual nature directed at bisexual [[female]]s by swingers and heterosexual males while often stereotyping bisexual males as walking [[AIDS]] risks.

Often, however, heterosexuals and homosexuals will add more stereotypes based on homophobia or heterophobia. Homophobes may think that bisexuals are gender nonconformist. Heterophobes will often think of bisexuals as maintaining privilege and collaborating with the homophobes. Also, the belief that people are either heterosexual or homosexual (a somewhat common belief among both heterosexuals and homosexuals), and thus that bisexuality does not truly exist, is considered biphobic.{{ref|dichotomy}}

One common motive for negative attitudes toward bisexuality among [[lesbian]]s is the fear that a bisexual [[woman]] will leave a woman for a [[man]]; the heterosexual male is seen as having an unfair systemic advantage both due to [[sexism]] and due to homophobia.  Bisexual persons may also be the target of homophobia from those who consider only heterosexuality appropriate.  The reverse can also apply in that bisexual persons may be targets of heterophobia or descrimination by some gays/homosexuals - this is especially prevalent amongst bisexual men.

Some [[radical feminism|Radical]] [[lesbian]] [[feminism|feminists]] think that bisexual women are giving in to [[patriarchy]]. 

==See also==
* [[Sexual hierarchy]]

==References==
# {{note|biphobia}} {{Journal reference | Author=Eliason MJ | Title=The prevalence and nature of biphobia in heterosexual undergraduate students. | Journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior | Volume=26 | Issue=3 | Year=1997 | Pages=317-26}} PMID 9146816
# {{note|dichotomy}} {{Journal reference | Author=Dworkin SH | Title=Treating the bisexual client | Journal=Journal of Clinical Psychology | Volume=57 | Issue=5 | Year=2001 | Pages=671-80}} PMID 11304706

[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[nl:Bifobie]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>