<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151112211225|690356677" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="247171" pageid="247171" ns="0" title="Biphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-12T21:32:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Bi flag.svg|thumb|Bisexual Pride Flag]]
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Biphobia''' is aversion toward [[bisexuality]] and bisexual people as a [[social group]] or as individuals. People of any [[sexual orientation]] can experience or perpetuate such feelings of aversion. Biphobia is a source of [[discrimination]] against bisexual people, and may be based on negative bisexual [[stereotype]]s or irrational fear.

== Etymology and usage ==
''Biphobia'' is a [[portmanteau word]] patterned on the term ''[[homophobia]]''. It derives from the English [[English prefixes#Neo-classical|neo-classical prefix]] ''bi-'' (meaning "two") from ''bisexual'' and the root ''-phobia'' (from the {{lang-el|φόβος}}, ''phóbos'', "fear") found in ''homophobia''. Along with ''[[transphobia]]'', ''homophobia'' and ''biphobia'' are members of the family of terms used when [[Bigotry|intolerance]] and discrimination are directed toward [[LGBT]] people.

''Biphobia'' need not be a [[phobia]] as defined in [[clinical psychology]] (i.e., an [[anxiety disorder]]). Its meaning and use typically parallel those of ''[[xenophobia]]''.

The [[adjective|adjectival]] form ''biphobic'' describes things or qualities related to biphobia, whereas the noun ''biphobe'' is a label for people thought to harbor biphobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Eliason, MJ|title=The prevalence and nature of biphobia in heterosexual undergraduate students|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|volume=26|issue=3|year=1997|pages=317–26|pmid=9146816|doi=10.1023/A:1024527032040}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Negative stereotypes ==
While biphobia and homophobia are distinct phenomena, they do share some traits: with attraction to one's own gender being a part of bisexuality, the [[heterosexist]] view of heterosexuality being the only true attraction applies to bisexual people as well as to gay people. However, bisexuals are also stigmatized in other ways.

=== Denialism ===
The belief that bisexuality does not exist stems from [[Binary thinking|binary]] views of sexuality, that people are assumed to be exclusively homosexual ([[gay]]/[[lesbian]]) or heterosexual (straight), with bisexuals either [[The closet|closeted]] gay people wishing to appear heterosexual,&lt;ref&gt;Michael Musto, April 7, 2009. [http://blogs.villagevoice.com/dailymusto/archives/2009/04/ever_meet_a_rea.php Ever Meet a Real Bisexual?], ''The Village Voice''&lt;/ref&gt; or experimenting with their sexuality,&lt;ref name="bisexual erasure"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Yoshino |first=Kenji |authorlink=Kenji Yoshino |title=The Epistemic Contract of Bisexual Erasure |journal=[[Stanford Law Review]] |volume=52 |issue=2 |pages=353–461 |publisher=[[Stanford Law School]] |date=January 2000 |url=http://www.kenjiyoshino.com/articles/epistemiccontract.pdf |doi=10.2307/1229482 |jstor=1229482 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gold star"&gt;{{cite web|title=Why Do Lesbians Hate Bisexuals?|publisher=lesbilicious.co.uk|date=April 11, 2008|accessdate=March 26, 2011|url=http://www.lesbilicious.co.uk/community/why-do-lesbians-hate-bisexuals/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bisexual workers"&gt;{{cite web|first=Jessica|last=Geen|title=Bisexual workers 'excluded by lesbian and gay colleagues'|date=October 28, 2009|accessdate=March 26, 2011|url=http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2009/10/28/bisexual-workers-excluded-by-lesbian-and-gay-colleagues}}&lt;/ref&gt; and cannot be bisexual unless they are equally attracted towards men and women.&lt;ref name="Dworkin"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dworkin, SH |title=Treating the bisexual client|journal=Journal of Clinical Psychology|volume=57|issue=5|year=2001|pages=671–80 | pmid=11304706 |doi=10.1002/jclp.1036}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aphorism|Maxims]] such as "People are either gay, straight or lying" embody this [[dichotomous]] view of sexual orientations.&lt;ref name="Dworkin"/&gt; Bisexuals often face this type of discrimination from the heterosexual community, but are frequently eyed with suspicion by homosexuals as well, usually with the notion that bisexuals are able to escape oppression from heterosexuals because of their attraction towards the opposite gender. This leaves some that identify as bisexual to be perceived as "not enough of either" or "not real".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Compulsory Bisexuality?: The Challenges of Modern Sexual Fluidity|url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15299710903316661|journal = Journal of Bisexuality|date = 2009-11-13|issn = 1529-9716|pages = 431–449|volume = 9|issue = 3-4|doi = 10.1080/15299710903316661|first = Breanne|last = Fahs}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Resulting negative stereotypes represent bisexuals as confused, undecided, dabblers, insecure, experimenting or "just going through a phase".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bisexualindex.org.uk/index.php/Main/ItsJustAPhase "It's Just A Phase" Is Just A Phrase], The Bisexual Index&lt;/ref&gt;  Attractions toward both sexes are considered fashionable as in "[[bisexual chic]]" or [[gender bending]]. This fashionability effects bisexual males, as they are often invalidated more than females in terms of their sexuality not being viewed as "hot". Another discriminatory tendency that often effects exclusively males is the stereotype that women can be bisexual, but men cannot. Relations are dismissed as a substitute for sex with members of the "right" sex or as a more accessible source of [[sexual gratification]]. [[Situational homosexuality]] due to [[Sex segregation|sex-segregated]] environments or groups such as the armed forces, schools, sports teams, religious orders, and [[prison sexuality|prisons]] is another facet of explaining why someone is allegedly temporarily gay.

=== Promiscuity ===
The strict association of bisexuality with promiscuity stems from a variety of negative stereotypes targeting bisexuals as mentally or socially unstable people for whom sexual relations only with men, only with women or only with one person is not enough. These stereotypes may result from cultural assumptions that "men and women are so different that desire for one is an entirely different beast from desire for the other" ("a defining feature of [[heterosexism]]"), and that "verbalizing a sexual desire inevitably leads to attempts to satisfy that desire."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pepperminty.com/writing/bis-and-slut-myth.pdf "Bisexuals and the Slut Myth"], presented at the 9th [[International Conference on Bisexuality]]&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result, bisexuals bear a [[Stigma (sociological theory)|social stigma]] from accusations of cheating on or betraying their partners, leading a [[double life]], being "on the [[Down-low (sexual slang)|down-low]]", and spreading [[sexually transmitted disease]]s such as [[HIV]]/[[AIDS]]. They are characterized as being "slutty", insatiable, "easy", indiscriminate, and in the case of women, [[Hypersexuality|nymphomaniacs]]. Furthermore, they are strongly associated with [[polyamory]], [[Swinging (sexual practice)|swinging]], and [[polygamy]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glaad.org/programs/cim/birepresentations.php GLAAD: Cultural Interest Media] {{Wayback |url=http://www.glaad.org/programs/cim/birepresentations.php |date=20060419203924 |bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; the last being an established heterosexual tradition sanctioned by some religions and legal in several countries. People of any sexual orientation can change partners, practice [[serial monogamy]] or have multiple casual sex partners or multiple romantic relationships. The fact that bisexuals are potentially sexually attracted to both men and women does not mean that they must simultaneously engage in sexual relationships with both men and women to be satisfied, they can be happily married or in an exclusive relationship with one person of either gender.{{cn|date=November 2015}}

== Mental and sexual health effects ==
The mental and sexual health effects of biphobia on bisexuals are numerous. Studies show that bisexuals are often trapped in between the binaries of hetero vs homosexuality, creating a form of invalidation around their sexual identity. This often leads to recognized indicators of mental health issues such as low self-esteem and self-worth. These indicators and pressures to 'choose' a [[sexual identity]] can, in many cases, lead to [[depression (mood)|depression]] as they may feel they live in a culture that does not recognize their existence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Individual and Social Factors Related to Mental Health Concerns among Bisexual Men in the Midwestern United States|url = http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3383005/|journal = Journal of bisexuality|date = 2012-01-01|issn = 1529-9716|pmc = 3383005|pmid = 22745591|pages = 223–245|volume = 12|issue = 2|first = Brian|last = Dodge|first2 = Phillip W.|last2 = Schnarrs|first3 = Michael|last3 = Reece|first4 = Omar|last4 = Martinez|first5 = Gabriel|last5 = Goncalves|first6 = David|last6 = Malebranche|first7 = Barbara|last7 = Van Der Pol|first8 = Ryan|last8 = Nix|first9 = J. Dennis|last9 = Fortenberry}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While doing research on sexual tendencies of women who have sex with women, one study, from the Journal of Bisexuality, concluded that bisexual women are more likely to engage in various high risk behaviors and were more at risk of contracting HIV and other sexually transmitted diseases.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Sexual and drug-use risk factors for HIV and STDs: a comparison of women with and without bisexual experiences.|url = http://ajph.aphapublications.org/doi/pdf/10.2105/AJPH.89.12.1841|journal = American Journal of Public Health|pages = 1841–1846|volume = 89|issue = 12|doi = 10.2105/ajph.89.12.1841|first = V|last = Gonzales|first2 = K M|last2 = Washienko|first3 = M R|last3 = Krone|first4 = L I|last4 = Chapman|first5 = E M|last5 = Arredondo|first6 = H J|last6 = Huckeba|first7 = A|last7 = Downer}}&lt;/ref&gt; These behaviors have been attributed to the unlikeliness of bisexuals to discuss their sexuality and proper protection with health professionals for fear of judgement or discrimination, leaving them uneducated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://www.lgbthealtheducation.org/wp-content/uploads/12-054_LGBTHealtharticle_v3_07-09-12.pdf|title = IMPROVING THE HEALTH CARE OF LESBIAN, GAY, BISEXUAL AND TRANSGENDER PEOPLE: Understanding and Eliminating Health Disparities|last = Makadon MD|first = Harvey J|date = 7/9/2012|journal = Fenway Institute|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |last2 = Ard MD, MPH|first2 = Kevin L|publisher = U.S. Department of Health and Human Services}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bisexual erasure ==
[[Bisexual erasure]] or ''bisexual invisibility'' is the tendency to ignore, remove, falsify, or reexplain evidence of [[bisexuality]] in [[history]], [[academia]], the [[news media]], and other [[primary source]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://queersunited.blogspot.com/2008/05/word-of-gay-bisexual-erasure.html Word Of The Gay: BisexualErasure] May 16, 2008 "Queers United"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ronsuresha.com/?p=1018 The B Word] Suresha, Ron. "The B Word," Options (Rhode Island), November 2004&lt;/ref&gt; In its most extreme form, bisexual erasure can include denying that bisexuality exists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hutchins |first=Loraine |authorlink=Loraine Hutchins |title=Sexual Prejudice: The erasure of bisexuals in academia and the media |journal=[[American Sexuality magazine]] |volume=3 |issue=4 |publisher=[[National Sexuality Resource Center]] |year=2005 |url=http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0 | title = Sexual Prejudice - The erasure of bisexuals in academia and the media | accessdate = 2007-07-19 | last = Hutchins | first = Loraine | authorlink = Loraine Hutchins | work = American Sexuality Magazine | publisher = National Sexuality Resource Center, San Francisco State University | location = San Francisco, CA 94103, United States | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071216065035/http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=475&amp;PageID=0 | archivedate = 2007-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is often a manifestation of biphobia, although it does not necessarily involve overt antagonism. However, there is also increasing support, inclusion, and visibility in both bisexual and non-bisexual communities, especially in the [[LGBT]] community.&lt;ref name="Queers United"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://queersunited.blogspot.com/ |title=Queers United }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="the task force"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/issues/bisexuality |title=Task Force Report On Bisexuality }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="HRC"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hrc.org/issues/coming_out/bisexual/bisexual_articles.asp?listpage=2 |title=HRC article on bisexuality}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GLAAD"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://glaadbackup.com/2009/documents/GLAADNRI2009.pdf|title=GLAAD TV Report }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Maria, September 24, 2009. [http://bisocialnews.com/how-far-have-we-come How Far Have We Come?], ''BiSocial News''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Thirteen"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ausiellofiles.ew.com/2008/10/27/greys-anatomy-s-3/ |title=Thirteen On House }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another place that biphobia often manifests is within the LGBTQI movement itself. While the name specifically claims inclusivity making reference to lesbians, gays, bisexuals, transsexuals, queer identifying individuals, and intersex people, the needs of the BTQI community are often not prioritized in the same way that the needs of the LG community are. While the beginnings of the gay rights movement started in the late seventeen hundreds within groups of militant "sodomite-citizens" in Paris, it was not until 1997 that the UK’s first bisexual youth group was established.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Including the B-word: Reflections on the place of bisexuality
within lesbian and gay activism and psychology|last = Barker|first = Meg|date = 2004|journal = Lesbian and Gay Psychology Review|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

This marginalization also manifests regularly in terms of social acceptability of discrimination against bisexuals. For example, habits of letting biphobic comments and jokes that would not be acceptable were they about gays or lesbians go unchallenged. Another way this occurs is when people ask intrusive questions about a person’s bisexuality that would be considered offensive in relation to other’s monosexualities. While this primarily affects bisexuals on a social level this social discrimination also leads to institutional marginalization, which can result in exclusion from anti-discrimination policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = The Bisexuality Report: Bisexual inclusion in LGBT equality and diversity|last = Barker|first = Meg|date = February 2012|journal = Centre for Citizenship, Identities and Governance and Faculty of Health and Social Care|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Monosexism ==
Monosexism is a term used to refer to beliefs, structures, and actions that promote [[monosexuality]] (either exclusive heterosexuality or homosexuality) as the only legitimate or right sexual orientation, excluding bisexual or other non-monosexual orientations.&lt;ref name="Highleyman"&gt;Highleyman, Liz (1995). [http://www.black-rose.com/articles-liz/bipol.html "Identities and Ideas: Strategies for Bisexuals"], from the anthology ''Bisexual Politics: Theories, Queries, and Visions''. Haworth Press. ''Black Rose Web Pages''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="rust"&gt;[[Paula Rodriguez Rust|Rust, Paula C Rodriguez]] (2002). [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3778/is_200201/ai_n9069533/pg_18 "Bisexuality: The state of the union, Annual Review of Sex Research, 2002"], ''BNET''. {{dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term may be considered analogous to biphobia.&lt;ref name="rust"/&gt;

The term is primarily used in discussions of sexual orientation to denote aversion towards all non-monosexual people as a social group or as individuals. It was likely adopted in place of [[unisexual]], which is already used in biology and would produce confusion. It is sometimes considered derogatory by the people to whom it is applied.&lt;ref&gt;Hamilton, Alan (2000). ''{{waybackdate|site=http://www.biresource.org/pamphlets/glossary.html|date=20070805044122}} ''of "LesBiGay and Transgender Glossary", ''[http://www.biresource.net/ Bisexual Resource Center]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

The proportion of people who fit into the category depends on how one uses the word.  If the term is used to mean exclusively monosexual in behavior, then according to [[Alfred Kinsey]]'s [[Kinsey Reports|studies]], 63% of men and 87% of women are what may now be termed "monosexual" as determined by experiences leading to [[orgasm]].&lt;ref&gt;(1999). [http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/resources/bib-homoprev.html "Prevalence of Homosexuality"], ''The Kinsey Institute''. Note that Kinsey did not use the term "bisexual", but that he uses "exclusively homosexual" and "exclusively heterosexual".&lt;/ref&gt; Freud thought that no one was born monosexual and that it had to be taught by parents or society, though most people appear to believe that monosexuals are in fact the majority and identify as such.&lt;ref&gt;Rethinking Marxism: A Journal of Economics, Culture &amp; Society, Volume 8, Issue 3, 1995, Feminist Economies, DOI:10.1080/08935699508685453, Margaret Nash, pages 66-78.&lt;/ref&gt;

Monosexism could also be attributed to the belief in sexuality as a binary. The notion of sexuality as a binary is not new. Throughout the 1980s, modern research on sexuality was dominated by the idea that that heterosexuality and homosexuality were the only legitimate sexualities, dismissing bisexuality as "secondary homosexuality".&lt;ref name="ProQuest"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Managing Heterosexism and Biphobia: A Revealing Black Bisexual Male Perspective|url = https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=lang_en&amp;id=5iayOla-7qcC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR3&amp;dq=%2522Managing+Heterosexism+and+Biphobia:+A+Black+Bisexual+Male+Perspective&amp;ots=f6xf6Kx-0s&amp;sig=U0rv73VAXngWQt2HeAaQ-u9ZBK0#v=onepage&amp;q=%2522Managing%2520Heterosexism%2520and%2520Biphobia%253A%2520A%2520Black%2520Bisexual%2520Male%2520Perspective&amp;f=false|publisher = ProQuest|date = 2008-01-01|isbn = 9780549622482}}&lt;/ref&gt; These ideas persisted until the development of alternative models such as the Kinsey scale. The Kinsey scale was developed by Kinsey in 1953 and instituted a paradigm shift that completely changed the way that people looked at sexuality.&lt;ref name="ProQuest"/&gt; His was a seven point scale redefined sexuality as it allowed people to identify at various points throughout the scale with 0 being exclusively heterosexual and 7 being exclusively homosexual. The scale is now widely used and seeks to eliminate the dominance of the binary that is often the cause of biphobia.{{cn|date=November 2015}}

== Intersectional perspective ==

While the general bisexual population as a whole faces biphobia, this oppression is also aggravated by other factors, one of which is race. In his examination of the bisexual male perspective, entitled, ''Managing Heterosexism and Biphobia: A Revealing Black Bisexual Male Perspective'', Grady L Garner delves into the oppression that he faces as both a black and bisexual male. He explains that the internalization of negative sociocultural messages, reactions and attitudes can be incredibly distressing as bisexual black males attempted to translate or transform these negative experiences into positive bisexual identity sustaining ones.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Bisexuality in the United States: A Social Science Reader|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=EwcABAApgR8C|publisher = Columbia University Press|date = 2000-01-01|isbn = 9780231102278|first = Paula C.|last = Rust}}&lt;/ref&gt; The experience of bisexual black males is infinitely different from that of bisexual white males and acknowledgement of those differences is important. As the demands and tribulations of black bisexual males appear to be comparatively more distressing than those that black and white, homo- and heterosexual individual's encounter, this acknowledgement is important and vital to the understanding of biphobia from an intersectional perspective.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"/&gt;

== Case studies ==
Case studies allow researchers not only to gain further insight into the discrimination that bisexuals face but also to elevate the voices of bisexuals whose voices are generally ignored. A Scottish organization called LGBT Youth conducted a series of case studies interviewing various bisexual youths in the country about their experiences with biphobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Bi Visibility Case Study|url = https://www.lgbtyouth.org.uk/bi-vis-stories|website = www.lgbtyouth.org.uk|accessdate = 2015-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Aiden, an 18-year-old boy, claimed: "I feel like a lot of people don’t understand bisexuality and what it means to be bi. People often doubt it and because of that people doubt their own sexuality as well. Some people in society doubt that bisexuality is real and I believe this is a result of their lack of understanding of it. I sometimes feel like I have to prove my sexuality to other people. My friend is gay and his partner told me that it [my bisexuality] would pass and I’ll be gay in the end. Maybe that is his experience and could be that of some other people that they end up realising they’re gay, but that is not my experience. It is not right to assume that is the case with bisexuality as it often isn’t."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Case Study: Aidan|url = https://www.lgbtyouth.org.uk/bi-vis-story-aidan|website = www.lgbtyouth.org.uk|accessdate = 2015-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Brooke, a 15-year-old girl, stated: "It’s actually appalling to see the amount of bi phobia still circling around nowadays. For example, a few weeks back I was with a few friends at Pride Glasgow. Fantastic day, honestly amazing. We were planning it for months beforehand and something I noticed whilst planning was a slight stir in the LGBT community about bisexual people attending Pride. I saw a few opinions floating around, such as 'if you’re bisexual, why do you even attend pride? You have a choice whether you get to be normal and date the opposite sex, so you’re not really LGBT'. This shocked me because not only is this a totally false accusation of being able to ‘choose’, but the fact it was coming from fellow members of the LGBT community, that’s what was really a shock. The fact that people we are meant to feel most comfortable with and feel we could relate mostly to said something so hurtful and damaging to our community, was a really big step back. Me, along with a few of my bisexual friends were then sceptical about going to Pride, in case this was a common thought among LGBT people, but it turns out, it really isn’t. We went and there were hundreds of (proud I must say, and rightly so!) bisexual people, wearing flags and talking about their stories to us.”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Brooke's Story|url = https://www.lgbtyouth.org.uk/bi-vis-story-brooke|website = www.lgbtyouth.org.uk|accessdate = 2015-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bailey study ==
{{Further|Bisexuality#Perceptions and discrimination}}
A 2005 article in the ''[[The New York Times]]'' used the word ''biphobic'' when criticizing a study about male bisexuality. The study, which was by Gerulf Rieger, Meredith L. Chivers, and [[J. Michael Bailey]], and took place in 2002, said that a sample of men self-identifying as bisexual did not respond equally to pornographic material involving only men, and to pornography involving only women, but instead showed four times more arousal to one than the other. The article criticized the method of measurement of arousal as too crude to capture the richness (erotic sensations, affection, admiration) that constitutes sexual attraction.&lt;ref name="Carey"&gt;{{cite news |last=Carey |first=Benedict |title=Straight, Gay or Lying? Bisexuality Revisited |work=The New York Times |date=5 July 2005 |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F20714FB3B550C768CDDAE0894DD404482 |accessdate=24 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ngltf"&gt;[[National Gay and Lesbian Task Force]] (July 2005). [http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/reports/NYTBisexualityFactSheet.pdf The Problems with "Gay, Straight, or Lying?"] ([[PDF]]) Retrieved 24 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="FAIR"&gt;{{Cite web|title=New York Times Suggests Bisexuals Are 'Lying.' Paper fails to disclose study author's controversial history|publisher=[[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] |date=July 8, 2005|accessdate=June 22, 2013|url=http://fair.org/take-action/action-alerts/new-york-times-suggests-bisexuals-are-quotlyingquot/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Institute of Bisexuality]] stated that Bailey's study was misinterpreted and misreported by both ''The New York Times'' and its critics.&lt;ref name=bibrain.org&gt;{{cite web|title=Controversy over Professor J. Michael Bailey and the Existence of Bisexuality|publisher=[[American Institute of Bisexuality]]|year=2012|accessdate=15 March 2015|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131020184909/http://www.bibrain.org/ControversyOverBaileyV2.0.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|LGBT}}

* [[Bisexual American history]]
* [[Bisexual community]]
* [[Duclod Man]]
* [[Heteronormativity]]
* [[History of bisexuality]]
* [[International Day Against Homophobia, Transphobia and Biphobia]] (biphobia was added to the name of the day in 2015)
* [[List of media portrayals of bisexuality]]
* [[List of phobias]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|40em}}

== Further reading ==
* [[Marjorie Garber|Garber, Marjorie]] (1995). ''Bisexuality and the Eroticism of Everyday Life'', pp.&amp;nbsp;20–21, 28, 39.
* [[Mariam Fraser|Fraser, M.]], ''Identity Without Selfhood: Simone de Beauvoir and Bisexuality'', Cambridge and New York: Cambridge University Press 1999. p.&amp;nbsp;124–140.
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20110204071248/http://www.xtra.ca/public/viewstory.aspx?AFF_TYPE=3&amp;STORY_ID=1901&amp;PUB_TEMPLATE_ID=2 The fencesitters? Suspicions still haunt the bi/homo divide] - article in Xtra, Gay &amp; Lesbian news site, 2006]

== External links ==
* [http://www.bialogue.org/Pages/InfoPackets/MentalHealth.html Bialogue/GLAAD Bisexuality Packet for Mental Health Professionals]
* [http://www.advocate.com/exclusive_detail_ektid49066.asp Fairy Tales], by Job Brother in [[The Advocate]] September 21, 2007
* [http://marksimpson.com/pages/journalism/curiouser.html Curiouser and curiouser] by [[Mark Simpson (journalist)|Mark Simpson]]
* [http://out.ucr.edu/pdf/BiBasics.pdf Bisexuality Basics, UC Riverside LGBT Resource Center, Riverside, CA]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Bisexuality topics}}
{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Discrimination}}
}}

[[Category:Bisexuality]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Hatred]]
[[Category:LGBT terms]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>