<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131116010856|581848346" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="747210" pageid="747210" ns="0" title="Snob"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-20T20:21:32Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|original research=March 2008|refimprove=October 2013|pov=January 2011}}

A '''snob''' is a person who believes in the existence of an equation between [[Social status|status]] and human worth.&lt;ref name=debotton&gt;De Botton, A. (2004), ''Status Axiety''. London: Hamish Hamilton&lt;/ref&gt; The term also refers to a person who believes that some people are inherently inferior to him or her for any one of a variety of reasons, including real or supposed [[intellect]], [[wealth]], [[education]], [[ancestry]], [[Power (social and political)|power]], [[physical strength]], [[Social class|class]], [[taste (sociology)|taste]], [[beauty]], [[nationality]], [[celebrity|fame]], extreme success of a family member or friend, etc. Often this form of snobbery reflects the snob's personal attributes. For example, a common snobbery of the affluent is the belief that wealth is either the cause or result of superiority, or both.{{cn|date=June 2013}} Both definitions are used as a [[pejorative]].

==Etymology==
The word "snobbery" came into use the first time in England during the 1820s. It was said to have derived from the habit of many [[Oxford University|Oxford]] and [[Cambridge University|Cambridge]] colleges of writing ''sine nobilitate'' (without nobility) or ''s.nob.'' next to the names of ordinary students on examination lists in order to distinguish them from their aristocratic peers.&lt;ref name=debotton /&gt; These common, but typically wealthy students would then emulate symbols of aristocratic status (driver, maid etc.), and were then in turn mockingly identified as "snobs" by the aristocrats. After the later changing of the meaning of the term "snob", people with such emulation behaviour are now referred to as "snob victims".

==Snob victim==

The term "snob" is often misused when describing a "gold-tap owner",&lt;ref name=debotton/&gt; i.e. a person who insists on displaying (sometimes non-existing) wealth through [[conspicuous consumption]] of luxury goods (clothes, jewellery, cars etc.). Such person on the contrary craves the attention of snobs, trying to convince them with such consumption of his or her wealth and therefore status. Sophisticated snobs will then often assess that in such case there is no equation between (apparent) wealth and status, reducing the gold-tap owner to the object of their mockery. Such person is referred to as a ''snob victim''. The snob victim may be exploited economically by being deceived by a seller of [[Aspirational brand|aspirational goods]] (by means of e.g. [[advertising]]) into believing that status can indeed be acquired through consumption of such goods.

== Historic manifestations ==
Snobs can through time be found ingratiating themselves with a range of prominent groups – soldiers ([[Sparta]], 400 BC), bishops (Rome, 1500), poets (Weimar, 1815), farmers (China, 1967) - for the primary interests of snobs is power, and as the distribution of power changes, so, naturally and immediately, will the objects of the snob's admiration.&lt;ref  name=debotton /&gt;

Snobbery existed also in mediaeval feudal aristocratic Europe, when the clothing, manners, language and tastes of every class were strictly codified by customs or law. [[Chaucer]], a poet moving in the court circles, noted the provincial French spoken by the Prioress among the [[Canterbury Tales|Canterbury pilgrims]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;And French she spoke full fair and fetisly&lt;br&gt;
After the school of Stratford atte Bowe,&lt;br&gt;
For French of Paris was to her unknowe.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

William Rothwell notes "the simplistic contrast between the 'pure' French of Paris and her 'defective' French of Stratford atte Bowe that would invite disparagement."&lt;ref&gt;Rothwell, "Stratford Atte Bowe re-visited" ''The Chaucer Review'', 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; The disparagement is an element of the snobbery.

Snobbery surfaced more strongly as the structure of the society changed, and the [[bourgeoisie]] had the possibility to ''imitate'' [[aristocracy]]. Snobbery appears when elements of culture are perceived as belonging to an aristocracy or elite, and some people (the snobs) feel that the mere adoption of the fashion and tastes of the elite or aristocracy is sufficient to include someone in the elites, upper classes or aristocracy.

However, a form of snobbery can be adopted by someone not a part of that group; a [[pseudointellectual|pseudo-intellectual]], a celebrity worshipper, and a poor person idolizing money and the rich are types of snobs who do not base their snobbery on their personal attributes. Such a snob idolizes and imitates, if possible, the manners, worldview, and [[lifestyle (sociology)|lifestyle]] of a classification of people to which they aspire, but do not belong, and to which they may never belong (wealthy, famous, intellectual, beautiful, etc.).

== Analysis ==
[[William Hazlitt]] observed, in a culture where deference to class was accepted as a positive and unifying principle,&lt;ref&gt;The social historian [[G.M. Trevelyan]] referred to the deferential principle in British society as "beneficent snobbery", according to Ray 1955:24.&lt;/ref&gt; "Fashion is gentility running away from vulgarity, and afraid of being overtaken by it," adding subversively, "It is a sign the two things are not very far apart."&lt;ref&gt;Hazlitt, ''Conversations with Northcote'', quoted in Gordon N. Ray, "Thackeray's 'Book of Snobs'", ''Nineteenth-Century Fiction'' '''10'''.1 (June 1955:22-33) p. 25; Ray examines the context of snobbery in contemporaneous society.&lt;/ref&gt; The English novelist [[Edward Bulwer-Lytton, 1st Baron Lytton|Bulwer-Lytton]] remarked in passing, "Ideas travel upwards, ''manners'' downwards."&lt;!--italics in original--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bulwer-Lytton, ''England and the English'', noted in Ray 1955:24.&lt;/ref&gt; It was not the deeply ingrained and fundamentally accepted idea of "one's betters" that has marked snobbism in traditional European and American culture, but "aping one's betters".

Snobbery is a defensive expression of [[Emotional insecurity|social insecurity]], flourishing most where an [[The Establishment|Establishment]] has become less than secure in the exercise of its traditional prerogatives, and thus it was more an organizing principle for Thackeray's glimpses of British society in the threatening atmosphere of the 1840s than it was of Hazlitt, writing in the comparative social stability of the 1820s.&lt;ref&gt;See: Ray 1955:25f.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|3}}
* [[Boasting]]
* [[Chronological snobbery]]
* [[Class discrimination]]
* [[Egotism]]
* [[Elitism]]
* [[Emotional insecurity]]
* [[Four Yorkshiremen sketch]]
* [[Narcissism]]
* [[Pride]]
* [[Prima donna]]
* [[Queen bee (subculture)]]
* [[School diva]]
* [[Spoiled child]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/features/2001/0206.epstein.html Joseph Epstein, "In a snob-free zone"]: "Is there a place where one is outside all snobbish concerns&amp;mdash;neither wanting to get in anywhere, nor needing to keep anyone else out?"

===Etymologies===
*[http://www.askoxford.com/asktheexperts/faq/aboutwordorigins/snob Ask Oxford – Ask the Experts]
*[http://www.merriam-webster.com/cgi-bin/dictionary?snob Merriam Webster On-line Dictionary]
*[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=snob On-line Etymology Dictionary]

[[Category:Pejorative terms for people]]
[[Category:Personality traits]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>