<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091113203225|325680286" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="747210" pageid="747210" ns="0" title="Snob"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-14T18:35:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{ For2|the 1960s British Rock band|[[The Snobs]]}}
{{Article issues|article=y|OR=March 2008|citations missing=December 2007|date=April 2009}}

A '''snob''' is someone who adopts the [[worldview]] of '''snobbery''' — that some people are inherently inferior to him or her for any one of a variety of reasons, including real or supposed [[intellect]], [[wealth]], [[education]], [[ancestry]], etc. Often, the form of snobbery reflects the snob's personal attributes. For example, a common snobbery of the affluent is the belief that wealth is either the cause or result of superiority, or both, and a common snobbery of the physically attractive is that beauty is paramount.

Snobbery does not exist in mediaeval feudal aristocratic Europe, when the clothing, manners, language and tastes of every class were strictly codified by customs or law. 
Snobbery appeared when the structure of the society changed, (after 1789)and the bourgeoisie had the possibility to ''imitate'' aristocracy. Snobbery appears when elements of culture are perceived as belonging to an aristocracy or elite, and some people (the snobs) feel that the mere adoption of the fashion and tastes of the elite or aristocracy is sufficient to include someone in the elites, upper classes or aristocracy. 

However, a form of snobbery can be adopted by someone not a part of that group; a [[pseudointellectual|pseudo-intellectual]], a celebrity worshiper, and a poor person idolizing money and the rich are types of snobs who do not base their snobbery on their personal attributes. Such a snob idolizes and imitates, if possible, the manners, worldview, and [[lifestyle]] of a classification of people to which they aspire, but do not belong, and to which they may never belong (wealthy, famous, intellectual, beautiful, etc.). 

A snob is perceived by those being imitated as an ''arriviste'', perhaps ''[[nouveau riche]]'' or ''[[parvenu]]'', and the [[elite]] group closes ranks to exclude such outsiders, often by developing elaborate social codes, [[status symbol|symbolic status]] and recognizable marks of language. The snobs in response refine their behavior model.&lt;ref&gt;[[Norbert Elias]] (Edmund Jephcott, tr.), ''The Court Society'', 1983.&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Hazlitt]] observed, in a culture where deference to class was accepted as a positive and unifying principle,&lt;ref&gt;The social historian [[G.M. Trevelyan]] referred to the deferential principle in British society as "beneficent snobbery", according toRay 1955:24.&lt;/ref&gt; "Fashion is gentility running away from vulgarity, and afraid of being overtaken by it, [[William Hazlitt]] observed, adding subversively, "It is a sign the two things are not very far apart.""&lt;ref&gt;Hazlitt, ''Conversations with Northcote'', quoted in Gordon N. Ray, "Thackeray's 'Book of Snobs'", ''Nineteenth-Century Fiction'' '''10'''.1 (June 1955:22-33) p. 25; Ray examines the context of snobbery in contemporaneous society.&lt;/ref&gt; The English novelist[[Edward Bulwer-Lytton, 1st Baron Lytton|Bulwer-Lytton]] remarked in passing, "Ideas travel upwards, ''manners'' downwards."&lt;!--italics in original--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bulwer-Lytton, ''England and the English'', noted in Ray 1955:24.&lt;/ref&gt; It was not the deeply ingrained and fundamentally accepted idea of "one's betters" that has marked snobbism in traditional European and American culture, but "aping one's betters".

Snobbism is a defensive expression of [[Emotional insecurity|social insecurity]], flourishing most where an [[The Establishment|Establishment]] has become less than secure in the exercise of its traditional prerogatives, and thus it was an organizing principle for Thackeray's glimpses of British society in the threatening atmosphere of the 1840s than it was of Hazlitt, writing in the comparative social stability of the 1820s.&lt;ref&gt;This point is made by Ray 1955:25f.&lt;/ref&gt;

Snobbism is universally disdained wherever it is detected, inculcating a feeling of self-righteousness in those who identify themselves as free of the taint, which may bolster a sense of group solidarity, expressed as [[consensus]].  

==Historical origins==

Characteristically, snobs look down on people who have qualities which they regard as inferior, or flaunt their attributes which they regard as positive in order to make others seem inferior.{{Fact|date=March 2009}} Compare the points of view embodied in the informal and subjective categories of "[[highbrow]]" and its contrasted "[[lowbrow]]". 

The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' finds the word ''snab'' in a 1781 document with the meaning of ''[[shoemaker]]'' with a Scottish origin. The connection between "snab", also spelled "snob", and its more familiar meaning arising in [[England]] fifty years later is not direct.

Though the once popular etymology of ''snob'' as a contraction of the Latin phrase ''sine nobilitate'' ("without nobility") is now discredited,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = What is the origin of the word 'snob'? | url = http://www.askoxford.com/asktheexperts/faq/aboutwordorigins/snob | work = AskOxford (Oxford Dictionaries) | accessdate = 2008-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; a quote from the trade magazine ''The Tailor and Cutter'', 1878, admits no other interpretation: "it is the correct thing to vote a showily dressed man a snob."&lt;ref&gt;Quoted by Phillis Emily Cunnington, ''The History of Underclothes'' 1992:169.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Thackeray's "Snobs"==
It is agreed, however, that the word "snob" broke into broad public usage with [[William Makepeace Thackeray]]'s ''[[Book of Snobs]]'', a collection of satirical sketches that appeared serially in the magazine ''[[Punch magazine|Punch]]'', February 1846 to February 1847, and were collected and published in 1848.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon N. Ray, "Thackeray's 'Book of Snobs'", ''Nineteenth-Century Fiction'' '''10'''.1 (June 1955), pp. 22-33.&lt;/ref&gt;  Thackeray's definition of ''snob'' then was: "He who meanly admires mean things is a Snob". The "mean things", Thackeray was implying, were the showy things of this world, like a secretaryship in the Queen's Cabinet, where Prime Ministers invariably retired as [[earl]]s. 

:"Suppose in a game of life &amp;mdash; and it is but a twopenny game after all &amp;mdash; you are equally eager of winning. Shall you be ashamed of your ambition, or glory in it?"&lt;ref&gt;Thackeray, "Autour de mon Chapeau", 1863.&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
Thackeray had many opportunities to study snobs in action as he grew up. He was born in [[Kolkata|Calcutta]], [[India]], the only son of a Collector in the service of the [[British East India Company]], a sphere of opportunity for Englishmen of talent whose social standing was an impediment to a career at home, but who in India could lord it like a "[[Nawab|nabob]]". After his father died, Thackeray was sent home to England to be educated at the ancient and respectable though not quite stylish [[public school (England)|public school]] [[Charterhouse School|Charterhouse]], and at [[Trinity College, Cambridge]].

==Reverse snobbery==
{{main|Anti-elitism}} 
'''Reverse snobbery''' is the phenomenon of looking unfavorably on perceived social [[elites]] &amp;ndash; effectively the opposite of snobbery. For instance, poorer members of society may unfairly consider themselves to be friendlier, happier, more honest or moral than richer members of the society, and middle-income members of society may stress their poorer origins. This is common in British politics, in which MPs often say things such as "I grew up on a [[council estate]]" to try to prove their common roots.

The term ''[[bourgeois]]'' is frequently used in [[North America]] among those who self-identify as [[working class]], to describe individuals who borrow [[veneers]] of upper classes in order to affect a sophisticated, cultured image. In a related phenomenon, people who have worked to change their material lives may be accused of having "betrayed their roots".&lt;ref&gt;In the sense of their [[cultural heritage]].&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition somebody who has worked their way out of the lower classes and thus looks down upon both the lower classes for not working their way out and the upper classes for having an easy life but complain about the little things can also be refered to as a snob.

==See also==
*[[Chronological snobbery]]
*[[Classism]]
*[[Emotional insecurity]]
*[[Narcissism]]
*[[Pedant]]
*[[Pride]]
*[[Prima donna]]
*[[Queen bee (subculture)]]
*[[School diva]]
*[[Spoiled child]]
*[[Wannabe]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/features/2001/0206.epstein.html Joseph Epstein, "In a snob-free zone"]: "Is there a place where one is outside all snobbish concerns&amp;mdash;neither wanting to get in anywhere, nor needing to keep anyone else out?"

===Etymologies===
*[http://www.askoxford.com/asktheexperts/faq/aboutwordorigins/snob Ask Oxford - Ask the Experts]
*[http://www.merriam-webster.com/cgi-bin/dictionary?snob Merriam Webster On-line Dictionary]
*[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?l=s&amp;p=29 On-line Etymology Dictionary]

[[Category:Pejorative terms for people]]
[[Category:Personality traits]]

[[ca:Snob]]
[[da:Snob]]
[[de:Snob]]
[[es:Esnob]]
[[fa:فخرفروشی]]
[[fr:Snob]]
[[is:Snobb]]
[[it:Snob]]
[[he:סנוב]]
[[ka:სნობი]]
[[hu:Sznob]]
[[nl:Snob (persoon)]]
[[ja:スノッブ]]
[[pl:Snobizm]]
[[ro:Snob]]
[[ru:Сноб]]
[[sr:Сноб]]
[[sv:Snobb]]
[[uk:Сноб]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>