<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071113234012|171316640" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19168" pageid="19168" ns="0" title="Misogyny"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T00:50:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Original research|date=September 2007}} {{Discrimination}}
'''Misogyny''' ({{pronEng|m&lt;s&gt;ɪ&lt;/s&gt;ˈsɒʤ&lt;s&gt;ɪ&lt;/s&gt;ni}}) is hatred or strong prejudice against [[woman|women]]; an [[antonym]] of [[philogyny]]. Those holding misogynistic beliefs can be of either sex. Although misogyny is sometimes confused with [[misanthropy]], the terms are not interchangeable, for the latter refers more generally to the hatred of humanity. A concept related to misogyny is [[gynophobia]], the fear of women, but not necessarily hatred of them. The obsolete [[Latin language]] term '''horror feminae''' (literally "fear of women)&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=cB5UOSsIN74C&amp;pg=PA452&amp;lpg=PA452&amp;dq=%22horror+feminae%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=h67ydDeVux&amp;sig=yYp8tMCh1OwVbEDzaHqVP7rFnqc][http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=55059851][http://books.google.com/books?id=ffKmxdgKT5AC&amp;pg=PA91&amp;lpg=PA91&amp;dq=%22horror+feminae%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=FdQQbj3624&amp;sig=FJhdM1jWhzAvJ2bsSQSoR-BFNGI]&lt;/ref&gt;
may be seen used as a synonym both for misogyny and gynophobia.

Misogyny is considered by most [[feminist]] theories as an implicit motivation of political ideologies that justify and maintain the subordination of women to men. Such ideologies are typically called [[sexism]], by analogy with [[racism]] and [[antisemitism]]. Misogyny is, therefore, often associated with anti-woman [[sexism]], as [[misandry]] is associated with anti-man sexism.

== Forms of misogyny ==
There are many different forms of misogyny. In its most overt expression, a misogynist will openly hate all women simply because they are female.
Other forms of misogyny may be less overt. Some misogynists may simply be prejudiced against all women, or may hate women who do not fall into one or more acceptable categories. Entire cultures may be said to be misogynist if they treat women in ways that can be seen as harmful. Examples include forcing women to tend to all domestic responsibilities, demanding silence from a woman, or beating a woman. Subscribers to one model, the [[Madonna-whore complex|mother/whore dichotomy]], hold that women can only be "mothers" or "whores." Another variant is the virgin/whore dichotomy, in which women who do not adhere to a saintly standard of moral purity are considered "whores."  {{fact|date=October 2007}}

Frequently, the term ''misogynist'' is used in a looser sense as a term of derision to describe anyone who holds an unpopular or distasteful view about women as a group. A man who considers himself "a great lover of women," therefore, might somewhat paradoxically be termed a misogynist by those who consider his treatment of women sexist. Archetypes of this type of man might be [[Giacomo Casanova]] and [[Don Juan]], who were both reputed for their many libertine affairs with women.
Misogyny is a negative attitude towards women as a group, and so need not fully determine a misogynist's attitude towards each individual woman. The fact that someone holds misogynist views may not prevent them from having positive relationships with some women. Conversely, simply having negative relationships with some women does not necessarily mean someone holds misogynistic views. The term, like most negative descriptions of attitudes, is used as an epithet and applied to a wide variety of behaviors and attitudes. As with other terms, the more antipathetic one's position is in regards to misogyny, the larger the number of misogynists and the greater variety of attitudes and behaviors who fall into one's perception of "misogynist."{{Specify|date=January 2007}} This is, of course, the subject of much controversy and debate with opinions ranging widely as to the extent and breadth of misogyny in society.

[[Image:Maria laach eva teufel.jpg|thumb|left|[[Eve]] rides astride the Serpent on a capital in [[Maria Laach Abbey|Laach Abbey church]], 13th century]]

== Misogyny in religion ==
{{seealso|Feminist theology}}

Misogyny can be traced back to the origins of Modern civilization, such as in [[Greece]] and [[Judea]], in which stories and legends on the [[Fall of Man]] into a world of tragedy and death had been brought about by a woman. In both cultures, the creation of man is primary, and woman an afterthought. In [[Greek mythology]], the human race had already existed previous to the creation of women — a peaceful, autonomous existence as a companion to the gods. When [[Prometheus]] decides to steal the secret of fire from the gods, [[Zeus]] becomes infuriated and decides to punish humankind with an "evil thing for their delight" — [[Pandora]], the first woman, who carried a jar (usually described — incorrectly — as a box) she was told to never open. [[Epimetheus]] (the brother of Prometheus) is overwhelmed by her beauty, disregards Prometheus' warnings about her, and marries her. Pandora cannot resist peeking into the jar, and by opening it unveils all evil into the world — labour, sickness, old age, and death.&lt;ref&gt;Holland, J: "Misogyny: The World's Oldest Prejudice," pp. 12-13. Avalon Publishing Group, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; 
During the [[Great Jubilee]], [[Pope John Paul II]] issued an apology for all the past sins of the [[Roman Catholic Church]], dividing the sins into seven categories. Among general sins, sins in service of the truth, sins against Christian unity, sins against Jews, sins against respect of love, peace and culture, and sins against human rights, he also apologized for sins against the dignity of women and minorities.

The church has been criticized for being misogynistic. "The foundations of early Christian misogyny — its guilt about sex, its insistence on female subjection, its dread of female seduction — are all in [[Paul the Apostle|St. Paul's]] epistles. They provided a convenient supply of divinely inspired misogynistic texts for any Christian writer who chose to use them; his statements on female subjection were still being quoted in the twentieth century opponents of equality for women."&lt;ref&gt;[Rogers, Katherine M. ''The Troublesome Helpmate: A History of Misogyny in Literature,'' 1966.&lt;/ref&gt; Writers such as [[John Knox]] have been singled out for criticism.

However, given that [[Mary Magdalene]] became a [[saint]] and was one of the first witnesses to the [[Resurrection of Jesus]], many argue that [[Christianity]] has ultimately raised the status of women, despite the attitudes of some individuals. In the [[New Testament]], [[Jesus]] treats women with respect, even going so far as to save a [[Jesus and the woman taken in adultery|woman caught in adultery]] from stoning in [[Gospel of John|John]] 8. The apostle Paul in 1 Corinthians 5 states that
wives belong to their husbands, and equally husbands belong to their wives. See the article on [[Christian feminism]] for a fuller discussion.

== Misogyny in philosophy ==
[[Arthur Schopenhauer]] is famous for his essay "On Women" (Über die Weiber), in which he expressed his opposition to what he called "Teutonico-Christian stupidity" on female affairs. He claimed that "woman is by nature meant to obey." The essay does give two compliments however: that "women are decidedly more sober in their judgment than [[men]] are" and are more sympathetic to the suffering of others. However, the latter was discounted as weakness rather than humanitarian virtue.

[[Nietzsche]] is known for arguing that every higher form of civilization implied stricter controls on women (''[[Beyond Good and Evil (book)|Beyond Good and Evil]]'', 7:238); he frequently insulted women, but is best known for phrases such as "Women are less than shallow," and "Are you going to women? Do not forget the whip!"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Burgard |first=Peter J. |title=Nietzsche and the Feminine |origdate= |year=1994 |month=May |publisher=University of Virginia Press |location=Charlottesville, VA |isbn=0-8139-1495-7 |pages=p. 11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nietzsche's reputation as a misogynist is disputed by some, pointing out that he also made unflattering statements about men. Nietzsche can easily be interpreted as [[anti-feminist]], believing that women were primarily mothers and opposing the modern notion of [[women's liberation]] on the grounds that he considered it a form of [[slave morality]]. Whether or not this amounts to misogyny, whether his polemic statements against women are meant to be taken literally, and the exact nature of his opinions of women, are more controversial.&lt;ref name="Holub"&gt;Robert C. Holub, ''Nietzsche and The Women's Question''. [http://www-learning.berkeley.edu/robertholub/teaching/syllabi/Lecture_Nietzsche_Women.pdf Coursework for Berkley University]&lt;/ref&gt;

The philosopher [[Otto Weininger]], in his 1903 book ''Sex and Character'', characterized the "woman" part of each individual as being essentially "nothing," and having no real existence, having no effective consciousness or rationality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Izenberg | first = Gerald N. | year = 2001 | month = June | title = Review of Chandak Sengoopta's Otto Weininger: Sex, Science, and Self in Imperial Vienna | journal = The American Historical Review | volume = 106 | issue = 3 | pages = pp. 1074–1075 | url = http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0002-8762%28200106%29106%3A3%3C1074%3AOWSSAS%3E2.0.CO%3B2-5 | accessdate = 2007-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Weininger says, "No men who really think deeply about women retain a high opinion of them; men either despise women or they have never thought seriously about them." The author [[August Strindberg]] praised Weininger for probably having solved the hardest of all problems, the "woman problem."

== See also ==
* [[Domestic violence]]
* [[Ecole Polytechnique massacre]]
* [[Female genital cutting|Female circumcision]]
* [[Genital mutilation]]
* [[Hate Crime]]
* [[Male chauvinism]]
* [[Marriage strike]]
* [[Misandry]]
* [[Misanthropy]]
* [[Philogyny]]
* [[Prejudice]]
* [[Violence against women]]
* [[Women in Refrigerators]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Boteach, Shmuley. ''Hating Women: America's Hostile Campaign Against the Fairer Sex''. 2005.
* Clack, Beverley. ''Misogyny in the Western Philosophical Tradition''.
* Ellmann, Mary. ''Thinking About Women''. 1968.
* Forward, Susan, and Joan Torres. ''Men Who Hate Women and the Women Who Love Them: When Loving Hurts and You Don't Know Why''. Bantam Books, 1986. ISBN 0-553-28037-6
* Gilmore, David D. ''Misogyny: the Male Malady''. 2001.
* Haskell, Molly. ''From Reverence to Rape: The Treatment of Women in the Movies''. 1974. University of Chicago Press, 1987.
* Holland, Jack. ''Misogyny: The World's Oldest Prejudice''. 2006.
* Kipnis, Laura. ''The Female Thing: Dirt, Sex, Envy, Vulnerability''. 2006. ISBN 0-375-42417-2
* Patai, Daphne, and Noretta Koertge. ''Professing Feminism: Cautionary Tales from the Strange World of Women's Studies''. 1995. ISBN 0-465-09827-4
* Penelope, Julia. ''Speaking Freely: Unlearning the Lies of our Fathers' Tongues''. Toronto: Pergamon Press Canada, 1990.
* Morgan, Fidelis. ''A Misogynist's Source Book''.
* Rogers, Katharine M. ''The Troublesome Helpmate: A History of Misogyny in Literature''. 1966.
* Smith, Joan. ''Misogynies''. 1989. Revised 1993.
* ''World Health Organization Multi-country Study on Women's Health and Domestic Violence against Women''* 2005.

== External links ==
* [http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft809nb586/ Misogyny, Misandry, and Misanthropy]

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]

[[da:Misogyni]]
[[de:Misogynie]]
[[es:Misoginia]]
[[fr:Misogynie]]
[[gl:Misoxinia]]
[[it:Misoginia]]
[[he:מיזוגיניה]]
[[lt:Mizoginija]]
[[nl:Misogynie]]
[[ja:ミソジニー]]
[[pl:Mizoginia]]
[[pt:Misoginia]]
[[ro:Misoginie]]
[[simple:Misogyny]]
[[fi:Naisviha]]
[[sv:Misogyni]]
[[tr:Kadın düşmanlığı]]
[[zh:女性貶抑]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>