<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051110172943|27938855" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19168" pageid="19168" ns="0" title="Misogyny"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-12T08:49:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Misogyny''' is an exaggerated aversion toward [[woman|women]]. Compared with anti-woman [[sexism]] or [[misandry]] (aversion toward men), misogyny is usually regarded as directed against women by some men, though women can also harbor misogynistic views. In [[feminist]] theory, misogyny is recognised as a political ideology similar to [[racism]] or [[anti-Semitism]], existing to justify and reproduce the subordination of women by men. The etymology of misogyny comes from the [[Greek language|Greek]] and means to hate (''misein'') woman (''gyne'').

==Forms of misogyny==
There are many different forms of the idea of misogyny. In its most overt expression, a misogynist will openly hate all women simply because they are female. Some [[sexual predator]]s may fall into this category.

Other forms of misogyny may be more subtle. Some misogynists may simply hold all women under suspicion, or may hate women who don't fall into one or more acceptable categories. Entire cultures may be said to be misogynist if they treat women in ways that can be seen as hateful. Examples include forcing women to tend to all domestic responsibilites, demanding silence from a woman, or beating a woman consistently. Subscribers to one model, the mother/whore dichotomy, hold that women can only be "mothers" or "whores".

Frequently the term ''misogynist'' is used in a looser sense as a term of derision to describe anyone who holds an unpopular or distasteful view about women as a group.  A man who considers himself "a great lover of women," therefore, might somewhat paradoxically be termed a misogynist by those who consider his treatment of women sexist.

==Misogyny in philosophy and religion==
Many religions and philosophies contain what could be called misogyny.  [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]] insisted that women should not talk in church ("women should remain silent in the churches. They are not allowed to speak, but must be in submission, as the Law says." -1 Cor 14:34 NIV). In [[Hinduism]], the [[Code of Manu]] makes women incapable of ever being independent. At times in Indian history, it was customary for a woman to be pushed onto the funeral pyre of her husband (see [[Sati (practice)|sati]]). In [[Islam]], women are by [[Sharia|Sharia law]] forbidden to show any part of their body in public except their face, hands or the top of their feet. There is, however, wide disagreement from followers of these religions that these various teachings are misogynistic.

The [[16th century]] [[Protestant]] reformer [[John Knox]] wrote a book called ''[[The First Blast of the Trumpet Against the Monstrous Regiment of Women]]'' in which he argued against the ability of women to govern.

Some of the most famous philosophers exhibited misogyny at times. [[Arthur Schopenhauer]], in a very sophisticated epistemological discussion in his main work, included the sentence, "Reason is feminine in nature: it can only give after it has received".  [[Nietzsche]] is known for arguing that every higher form of civilisation implied stricter controls on women [''[[Beyond Good and Evil (book)|Beyond Good and Evil]]'', 7:238]; he frequently insulted women, but is best known for the phrases, "Women are less than shallow", "Woman was God's second blunder," and "Are you going to women?  Do not forget the whip!" [[Napoleon]], [[Niccolò Machiavelli|Machiavelli]],  [[Aristotle]], [[Leo Tolstoy|Tolstoy]] and even the progressive [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseau]] were also known for making cruel comments about women.  (It should also be noted, however, that philosophers such as [[John Stuart Mill]], [[Frederick Engels]] and [[Henry George]] supported [[feminism]].)

==Misogyny in culture== 
(n.b. Several entries that follow clearly employ misogyny for ironic or satirical purposes)

* In [[William Shakespeare]]'s [[Hamlet]], Hamlet chides his mother Gertrude for her decision to marry his uncle Claudius immediately after his father's death with the infamous line: "Frailty, thy name is woman!" (I, ii, 146)
* [[English people|British]] poet [[Robert Gould]] wrote a number of explicitly misogynistic satires in the 1680s.
* In the 19th century, [[Swedish people|Swedish]] [[playwright|dramatist]] and [[novelist]] [[August Strindberg]] had a powerful and overt misogynistic philosophy.
* Grumpy, in [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]]'s ''[[Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs]]'', says "All females is poison! They're full of wicked wiles!"
*[[Gaston (Beauty and the Beast)|Gaston]] from Disney's [[Beauty and the Beast (1991 film)|Beauty and the Beast]] first says that it's not right for a woman to read, then later calls Belle his "little wife" and says that Belle and he will have six or seven "strapping boys" like himself.
* [[Anal Cunt]], a [[noisecore]] shock band (in)famous for their intentionally offensive lyrics, often write songs with mysogynist themes such as "Women: Nature's Punching Bag", "You're Pregnant, So I Kicked You In the Stomach", and "I Became a Counselor So I Could Tell Rape Victims They Asked For It".
* [[R&amp;B]] group [[Bell Biv DeVoe]] famously sang, "Never trust a big butt and a smile" in their hit song "Poison".
* [[hip hop music|Rap]] artist [[Snoop Doggy Dogg]] has long been criticized for his mysogynist lyrics, especially in the 1990s.  As of late, he has been trying successfully to repair this image of himself.
* Comedian [[Andrew Dice Clay]] was famous for misogynist rants in his routines.
* [[Punk rock]] singer [[GG Allin]] was infamous for misogynist songs.
* Some feminists considered [[The Rolling Stones]]' "Stupid Girl", "Yesterday's Papers", and "Midnight Rambler" to be misogynistic. 
* The goth-metal group [[Type O Negative]] have often produced misogyny in their songs. One line claimed, "is there no difference between ''women'' and ''fire''? The one burns the spirit, the other the flesh!"  The first album, ''[[Slow Deep And Hard]]'', is particularly misogynist.
*[[Rush Limbaugh]] has been criticised by many feminists for popularizing the controversial term "[[Feminazi]]".
* Rapper [[Eminem]] has been labeled by some critics, including electronic musician [[Moby]], as a misogynist.
* In ancient times, Roman satirist [[Juvenal]], in particular his sixth satire.
* Travis Bickle in ''[[Taxi Driver]]'' quotes "I realize now how much she's just like the others, cold and distant, and many people are like that, women for sure, they're like a union."
*The comedy film ''[[How to Murder Your Wife]]'' has been criticised for misogyny.

==Further readings==
*Katharine M. Rogers, ''The Troublesome Helpmate: A History of Misogyny in Literature'' (1966)
*Mary Ellmann, ''Thinking About Women'' (1968) 
*Molly Haskell, ''From Reverence to Rape: The Treatment of Women in the Movies'', University of Chicago Press 1987 (First Edition 1974)
*Joan Smith, ''Misogynies'' (1989, revised 1993)

==See also==
*[[Male chauvinism]]
*[[Marriage strike]]
*[[Misandry]]
*[[Misanthropy]]
*[[Prejudice]]
*[[Rape culture]]
*[[Taliban treatment of women]]
*[[Testosterone poisoning]]

==External links==
*[http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft809nb586/ Misogyny, Misandry, and Misanthropy]

[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[de:Misogynie]]
[[fr:Misogynie]]
[[it:Misoginia]]
[[tr:Kadın Düşmanlığı]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>