<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041015020633|6737467" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19168" pageid="19168" ns="0" title="Misogyny"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-20T22:38:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Misogyny''' is an exaggerated pathological aversion towards women. Compare with anti-woman [[sexism]]. Misogyny is usually regarded as directed against women by some men, but women can also harbor misogynistic views. In [[feminist]] theory, misogyny is recognised as a political ideology similar to [[racism]] or [[anti-semitism]], existing to justify and reproduce the subordination of women by men.

==Forms of misogyny==

There are many different forms of misogyny. In its most overt expression, a misogynist will openly hate all women, and will hurt people simply because they are female. Some [[rape|rapists]] and [[sexual predator]]s fall into this category. 

Other forms of misogyny may be more subtle. Some misogynists may simply hold all women under suspicion, or may hate women who don't fall into one or more acceptable categories. Entire cultures may be said to be misogynistic if they treat women in ways that can be seen as hateful.

Frequently the term ''misogynist'' is used in a looser sense as a term of derision to describe anyone who holds an unpopular or distasteful view about women as a group.  A man who considers himself "a great lover of women," therefore, might somewhat paradoxically be termed a misogynist by those who consider his treatment of women sexist.

==Misogyny in philosophy and religion==

Many of the great religions and philosophies contain what could be called misogyny. [[St. Paul]] insisted that women cover their heads and should not talk in church. The [[Ten Commandments]] explicitly refer to wives as property. In [[Islam]], a woman receives half as much inheritance as a man, and her witness is worth half as much in court. In [[Hinduism]], the [[Code of Manu]] makes women incapable of ever being independent. At times in Indian history, it was customary for a woman to be pushed onto the funeral pyre of her husband (see [[Sati]]). There is, of course, wide disagreement as to whether these various teachings are misogynistic.

Some of the most famous philosophers exhibited misogyny at times. [[Arthur Schopenhauer]], in a very sophisticated epistemological discussion in his main work, included the sentence, "Reason is feminine in nature: it can only give after it has received". [[Napoleon]], [[Machiavelli]],  [[Aristotle]], [[Tolstoy]] and even the progressive [[Rousseau]] were also known for making cruel comments about women.  (It should also be noted, however, that philosophers such as [[John Stuart Mill]] and [[Henry George]] were supportive of [[feminism]].)

==Misogyny in popular culture==

* Grumpy, in [[Disney]]'s [[Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs]], says ''"All females is poison! They're full of wicked wiles!"''
* [[R&amp;B]] group [[Bel Biv Devoe]] famously sang "Never trust a big butt and a smile" in their hit song "Poison".
* [[Andrew Dice Clay]] was famous for misogynistic rants in his comedy routines.
* Rapper [[Snoop Dogg]] often says "I don't love hos" in his songs.
* The Goth group [[Type O Negative]] have often produced misogyny in their songs.  One line claimed, "'Liar' and 'woman' - the two words are the same".
* Rapper [[Eminem]] has been labled by some critics as misogynistic.

==See also==
*[[misandry]]
*[[misanthropy]]
*[[prejudice]]

==External link==
*[http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft809nb586/ Misogyny, Misandry, and Misanthropy]

[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Feminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>