<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112070717|87296600" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19168" pageid="19168" ns="0" title="Misogyny"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T14:42:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Misogyny'''  ({{IPA|/mɪ.ˈsɑ.ʤə.ni/}}) is hatred or strong prejudice against [[woman|women]]. The word comes from the [[Greek language|Greek]] words μίσος (misos, "hatred") + γυνη (gunê, "woman"). Compared with anti-woman [[sexism]] or [[misandry]] (hatred or fear of, or strong prejudice against men), misogyny is usually regarded as directed against women by some men, though women can also hold misogynistic views. In [[feminist]] theory, misogyny is recognized  as a political ideology - similar to [[racism]] or [[anti-Semitism]] - that justifies and maintains the subordination of women by men. 
==Forms of misogyny==

There are many different forms of misogyny. In its most overt expression, a misogynist will openly hate all women simply because they are female. Some [[sexual predator]]s may fall into this category.

Other forms of misogyny may be more subtle. Some misogynists may simply be prejudiced against all women, or may hate women who don't fall into one or more acceptable categories. Entire cultures may be said to be misogynist if they treat women in ways that can be seen as harmful. Examples include forcing women to tend to all domestic responsibilities, demanding silence from a woman, or beating a woman.{{fact}} Subscribers to one model, the mother/whore dichotomy, hold that women can only be "mothers" or "whores."{{fact}} Another variant is the virgin/whore dichotomy, in which women who do not adhere to a saintly standard of moral purity are considered "whores."{{fact}} Both of these viewpoints are widely regarded as archaic and uncommon in modern Western society.

Frequently the term ''misogynist'' is used in a looser sense as a term of derision to describe anyone who holds an unpopular or distasteful view about women as a group.  A man who considers himself "a great lover of women," therefore, might somewhat paradoxically be termed a misogynist by those who consider his treatment of women sexist, especially those who ascribe negative connotations to male sexuality. Archetypes of this type of man might be [[Giacomo Casanova]] (a historical figure) and [[Don Juan]] (fictional character), who were both reputed for their many libertine affairs with women. While a "seducer" like Casanova or Don Juan might appear outwardly charming and to enjoy the company of women, some may interpret these figures as being disrespectful of women, or as having no interest in them other than as sex objects or objects of romantic interest.

Misogyny is a negative attitude towards women as a group, and as such need not fully determine a misogynist's attitude towards each individual woman. The fact that someone holds misogynist views may not prevent them from having positive relationships with some women. Conversely, simply having negative relationships with some women does not necessarily mean someone holds misogynistic views. The term, like most negative descriptions of attitudes, is used as an epithet and applied to a wide variety of behaviors and attitudes. As with other terms, the more antipathetic one's position is in regards to misogyny, the larger the number of misogynysts and the greater variety of attitudes and behaviors that are "misogynist". This is, of course, the subject of much controversy and debate with opinions ranging widely as to the extent and breadth of misogyny in society.

==Misogyny in philosophy and religion==
Some religions and philosophies contain what could be called misogyny.

During the [[Great Jubilee]], Pope [[John Paul II]] issued an apology for all the past sins of the [[Roman Catholic Church]], dividing the sins into seven categories. Amongst general sins, sins in service of the truth, sins against Christian unity, sins against Jews, sins against respect of love, peace and culture, and sins against human rights, he also apologized for sins against the dignity of women and minorities.

In the [[16th century]] the [[Scotland|Scottish]] [[Protestant]] reformer [[John Knox]] wrote a book called ''[[The First Blast of the Trumpet Against the Monstrous Regiment of Women]]'' in which he argued against the ability of women to govern.

Some of the most famous philosophers exhibited misogyny at times. [[Arthur Schopenhauer]], in a very sophisticated epistemological discussion in his main work, included the sentence, "Reason is feminine in nature: it can only give after it has received".  [[Nietzsche]] is known for arguing that every higher form of civilisation implied stricter controls on women [''[[Beyond Good and Evil (book)|Beyond Good and Evil]]'', 7:238]; he frequently insulted women, but is best known for the phrases, "Women are less than shallow", "Woman was God's second blunder," and "Are you going to women?  Do not forget the whip!" [[Napoleon]], [[Niccolò Machiavelli|Machiavelli]],  [[Aristotle]], [[Leo Tolstoy|Tolstoy]] and even the progressive [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseau]] were also known for making such comments about women. It should also be noted, however, that philosophers such as [[John Stuart Mill]], [[Friedrich Engels]], [[Fyodor Dostoyevsky]], [[Heinrich Cornelius Agrippa]], and [[Henry George]] supported [[feminism]].

The philosopher [[Otto Weininger]] would have to be a contender for the greatest as well as one of the most influential of all misogynists. In his book ''Sex and Character'' (1903) he characterized the "woman" part of each individual as being essentially "nothing", and having no real existence, having no effective consciousness or rationality. Weininger says, "No men who really think deeply about women retain a high opinion of them; men either despise women or they have never thought seriously about them." The author [[August Strindberg]] praised Weininger for probably having solved the hardest of all problems, the "woman problem".

In more recent times [[Dave Sim]], acclaimed independent comic book creator, has produced a significant amount of misogynist literature, characterizing women as "The Merged Void"[http://theabsolute.net/misogyny/sim.html].

==Misogyny in Literature== 

"The foundations of early Christian misogyny- its guilt about sex, its insistence on female subjection, its dread of female seduction- are all in St. Paul's epistles. They provided a convenient supply of divinely inspired misogynistic texts for any Christian writer who chose to use them; his statements on female subjection were still being quoted in the twentieth century opponents of equality for women" 
The Troublesome Helpmate: A History of Misogyny in Literature Katherine M. Rogers  
 
"Regarding the passage of the women suffrage amendment in America, Rogers quoted from The Saturday Review, August 28, 1920: " "[It] is man's last stand against the subversion of his rights of virility by a tyranny which, unless we are much mistaken, will prove to be at once humiliating and dangerous. Humiliating, because it is the submission of the superior to the inferior sex. Dangerous, because, if it be pushed beyond a certain point, it will be overthrown by an appeal to physical force." But the hopeful possibility remains " that the men will resort to the weapons with which Nature has furnished them, and that the argument of the black eye, while it may disfigure temporarily the daughters of Eve, will be the only means of recovering the lost Rights of Man."  
The Troublesome Helpmate: A History of Misogyny in Literature Katherine M. Rogers  
 
No men who really think deeply about women retain a high opinion of them; men either despise women or they have never thought seriously about them. -- Otto Weininger 

As children, imbeciles and criminals would be justly prevented from taking any part in public affairs even if they were numerically equal or in the majority; woman must in the same way be kept from having a share in anything which concerns the public welfare. Sex and Character: Otto Weininger 
 
The sacred books should be burned rather than made available to women. -- Talmud, Sotah 3:4, Jewish Scripture 
  
Let the women learn in silence with all subjection. But I suffer not a woman to teach, nor to usurp authority over the man, but to be in silence. For Adam was first formed, then Eve. And Adam was not deceived, but the woman being deceived was in the transgression" (I Tim. 2: 11-14;). 
 
Ursala King in her 1987 article in Comparative Education: "World Religions, Women and Education" states very clearly that women "were always excluded from formal education once sacred knowledge became transmitted in an institutional manner".

==Misogyny in language==

{{POV-section}}
{{sources}}

Cultural beliefs, values, and concepts are reflected in language. The languages used by most people in the world developed in societies containing patriarchy, classism, and racism; therefore, these languages may contain implicit misogyny or other forms of oppression. Some linguists and philosophers argue that language does not only reflect, but also [shapes culture].

Gender-exclusive language implicitly casts the masculine as the dominant subject, using masculine or masculine based words as universals, thereby implcitly excluding the feminine. Terms such as "mankind", "man" (in reference to humanity), or "God" as assumed to be male, are some examples of gender-exclusive language. The word "man" appears in a number of words denoting female or gender-neutral concepts, for example, "woman" and "human." Some have argued that this etymological coincidence promotes a view of the female as derivative of the male, and so should be avoided in contemporary usage, for instance replacing "women" with "[[womyn]]".

Etymology is the branch of linguistics concerned with word origins. We can better understand the actual impact of oppressive language if we know its history. The word bitch comes from the Old English bicce, meaning female dog. The use of this word as a pejorative term for woman goes as far back as the fifteenth century. Today, when people use this word toward a woman, it is often when a woman has asserted herself in some way, not acted in a way considered womanly, or has exhibited some other quality of strength that makes others feel uncomfortable. In other cases, its use has no particular basis- in certain sub-cultures, the word bitch is used synonymously with the word woman. An example of this use is seen within the hip-hop and gansta rap sub cultures. "Bitches" are often strongly opinionated women who are not submissive. Within the last decade, there has been a trend to use the word toward men, comparing them in some way to a woman. "You're gonna be my bitch.", for example is used to mean that someone is being placed in the womanly role, which is a way of expressing that a woman's place is lower, submissive, weaker, and undesirable. Not only is the word bitch an expression of misogyny, it is also speciesist, comparing a woman to a dog, suggesting that being dog-like is inferior, making the woman "lower than human". The verb form of this word, "to bitch" originated sometime in the 1930's in American English, and means "to complain like a bitch" (dog-like woman). 

The word whore originates from the Old English word hore, meaning prostitute, and still means the same today. Slut came from the German schlutt, "slovenly woman", and the similar Swedish word slata, meaning "idle woman", and was first recorded in English around 1402. When either of these words are used to describe a male, again, the word male is inserted before the word, as in "male slut", since these words in their very origin refer to females, and there are no comparable words to describe men. Of course this is due to the sexual double standards we endure, where a promiscuous man is revered as a "stud", while a "slutty" woman gains a bad reputation, and is considered tainted. 

There is a whole litany of words used to denigrate a woman's genitalia. This is one of the most pervasive uses of oppressive misogynist language. The word snatch came about around 1903 as a pejorative term for vagina. The word pussy originated from the Low Germanic puse, meaning "vulva", to the Old Norse puss, meaning "pocket, or pouch", in 1726. The phrase "pussy-whipped" came about in 1956 in American English. A man who is "pussy-whipped" acquires a stigma which accuses him of being controlled by his female companion. Today the word pussy is used in several ways to suggest female weakness or inferiority. Female genitalia are objectified in the word pussy, as men throw the term around in a way that objectifies and degrades female sexuality, turning it into a product, or commodity to be possessed and consumed. "I'm gonna get some pussy tonight." is an example. In this way, women become separated from the genitalia, the product, no longer a whole person, but having been reduced to the body part that is there to supply pleasure to men when they demand it. Any other pejorative term for vagina can be inserted into this example. This word is also used toward men to suggest weakness. Men are essentially being compared to female genitalia, the inferior, objectified product, and therefore are being compared to a woman, the weakuse of the word is widespread and seems to be socially acceptable. Its use can be compared to ther, inferior, less courageous, and less capable gender, according to patriarchal definition. This at of a man being called a "faggot". Both are misogynist terms, as they attempt to degrade a man by accusing him of exhibiting feminine qualities. Another widely used example, is when a group of men is referred to as "ladies" to suggest feminine inferiority. Young boys learn to consider females the inferior gender at an early age as they begin to use female terms to degrade other boys. "You run like a girl." and "Don't be a pussy." are some examples. 

The word girl comes from the Middle English gyrle and originally had the meaning of "child" of either gender. It wasn't until around 1530 that the word girl took on a female connotation, when also acquiring the meaning of "unmarried woman". The word girl was used as a means of categorizing and subjugating certain types of women. Today, this is the most prolific and the most often denied use of misogynist language. Women are reduced to children as long as they appear to be under a certain age. Somehow, it is not until a woman reaches the maturity at which she shows the undesirable signs of aging does she finally acquire the respect of being referred to as an adult person- woman. Girls are commodities, girls are easier to exploit and control, and girls (children) have less power. It is no more acceptable to call a grown woman a girl than it is to call a black man a boy. Both of these are examples of verbal subjugation employed by our culture. Interestingly, although it is no longer socially acceptable to use the latter example, very few people object to this use of the word "girl". This is an example that very clearly illustrates that patriarchal verbal oppression is so insidious that people fail to acknowledge or object to women's being referred to as children. 

Some women find some of the [[slang]] terms that refer to women offensive. Such terms have existed throughout history, and change over time. Some of the terms are commonly used, while others are not. Furthermore, not all men use these terms, and some women do choose to use them. Many women also do not consider some of the terms to be offensive at all, and regard their usage as harmless and inoffensive, complementary, playful, or appreciative. Some of the terms common in contemporary usage are:

*''[[Babe]]'': a [[diminutive]] or complimentary way to address a woman (depending upon the context; notably, babe is one of several terms that often does not have negative or misogynistic connotations). More commonly said to a partner, in a similar way to "honey" or [[baby]]. Historically, [[baby]] is the diminutive of babe, but [[baby]] has taken its place in all but this and poetic contexts, where it is synonymous.
*''[[Bitch]]'': taken literally, bitch is the technical term for a female dog. In common parlance, it is often intended to be an insult describing a mean or petty woman. In some instances, such as some forms of hip-hop music, women in general may be referred to as "bitches;" however, this practice is uncommon outside of those arenas.  
*''[[Bimbo]]'': a demeaning way to address a woman, meant to imply a lack of intelligence, or occasionally used to describe an especially attractive woman who lacks intelligence. Bimbo is the [[Italian language|Italian]] word for [[child]], and it was originally used to refer to a prostitute working for an Italian [[organized crime]] organization. It's still used by some Italians much as the same way as [[Babe]] or [[Baby]] used by North Americans (though in its feminine form, Bimba), and so may not carry negative connotations in Italian culture.
*''[[Bird (disambiguation)|Bird]]'': a British English term referring to women in general. It is analogous to the term ''Chick'' in the United States. Some women may find the term "bird" somewhat demeaning; however, it is also commonly used in Ireland and Australia, where it carries no demeaning connotations.
*''Chick'': a term used primarily in the United States. Taken literally, it means a young bird, but often is a term used to refer to women (especially young, single, and attractive women) in general. Some women may find the term mildly offensive by interpreting it as infantilizing or objectifying, while other women take no offense at the term. It is sometimes claimed that the usage derives from the [[Spanish language|Spanish]] ''chica'' (girl), but neither the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' nor ''[[Merriam-Webster]]'' supports this derivation. The word ''chick'' was originally used in a gender-neutral sense to mean "human child" at least as early as the [[14th century]]. The popularity of the usage in [[North America]] may, nonetheless, be due in part to its similarity to the Spanish word chica.
*''[[Hag]]'': a term meant to imply an old woman, especially one who is disfigured or especially unattractive. Most men and women consider use of the term fairly offensive.
*''[[Skeezer]]'': used in some [[Hip hop music|hip-hop]] recordings. 
*''[[Wench]]'': Although this term once referred to a servant girl or peasant, it has now come to describe a promiscuous woman, especially a prostitute. [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/wench]
In some depictions of some cultural groups, terms considered extremely offensive to most women (e.g., ''[[bitch]]'', ''[[cunt]]'', ''[[toots]]'' or ''[[ho]]'') are used to refer to women in general.

Many terms that refer to women's physical appearance (e.g., ''hottie'', a sexually attractive woman) are widely used; some women believe that these terms may imply [[sexual objectification]], while many others find them inoffensive expressions of male appreciation. Many of the terms that some consider to be sexually objectifying are also used by some women about men, but the issue over whether or not this sexually objectifies men is far less often discussed (see [[misandry]]).

==Further reading==

*Katharine M. Rogers, The Troublesome Helpmate: A History of Misogyny in Literature (1966) 
*Mary Ellmann, Thinking About Women (1968) 
*Molly Haskell, From Reverence to Rape: The Treatment of Women in the Movies, University of Chicago Press 1987 (First Edition 1974) 
*Joan Smith, Misogynies (1989, revised 1993) 
*Gilmore, David D, Misogyny: the Male Malady (2001) 
*World Health Organisation Multi-country Study on Women's Health and Domestic Violence against Women* (2005) 
*Fidelis Morgan A Misogynist's Source Book 
*Jack Holland Misogyny: The World's Oldest Prejudice (2006) 
*Beverley Clack Misogyny in the Western Philosophical Tradition 
*Schmuley Boteach Hating Women: America's Hostile Campaign Against the Fairer Sex(2005) 
*Julia Penelope Speaking Freely: Unlearning the Lies of our Fathers' Tongues. Toronto: Pergamon Press Canada, (1990)


==See also==
*[[Domestic violence]]
*[[Ecole Polytechnique Massacre]]
*[[Female genital cutting|Female circumcision]]
*[[Genital mutilation]]
*[[Male chauvinism]]
*[[Marriage strike]]
*[[Misandry]]
*[[Misanthropy]]
*[[Prejudice]]
*[[Rape culture]]
*[[Taliban treatment of women]]
*[[Testosterone poisoning]]
*[[Violence against women]]
*[[Women in the Refrigerator]]

==External links==
*[http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft809nb586/ Misogyny, Misandry, and Misanthropy]
*[http://menarebetterthanwomen.com A misogynist website](contents may be offensive)

[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[de:Misogynie]]
[[es:Misoginia]]
[[fr:Misogynie]]
[[he:מיסוגניה]]
[[it:Misoginia]]
[[ja:ミソジニー]]
[[ka:მისოჯინია]]
[[nl:Misogynie]]
[[sv:Misogyni]]
[[pl:Mizogynia]]
[[pt:Misoginia]]
[[ro:Misoginism]]
[[fi:Naisviha]]
[[tr:Kadın düşmanlığı]]
[[zh:女性貶抑]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>