<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061029024558|84351097" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="523179" pageid="523179" ns="0" title="Enemy of the people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-29T03:52:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:''For the play by [[Henrik Ibsen]], see [[An Enemy of the People]].''
[[Image:Beria timemag 1101530720 400.jpg|thumb|July 20, 1953 [[Time (magazine)|TIME magazine]] [[irony|ironic]] cover: "[[Lavrenty Beria]]: Enemy of the people."]]
The term '''enemy of the people''' is a fluid designation referring to political or [[Social class|class]] opponents of the group using the term, sometimes including former allies. Its usage is derogatory, and meant to imply that the "enemies" have conspired against society as a whole.

The term "enemy of the people" has an extensive history.  Its earliest use may have been by the [[Roman Empire]], where the [[Roman Senate|senate]] used the term to apply to the [[Emperor]] [[Nero]] as a pretext for his arrest (he committed suicide).  Since that time, many groups have used the phrase, including the [[Jacobins]] during the radical phase of the French Revolution (the [[Reign of Terror]]), and most notably and famously by the [[Soviet Union]] and other Communist countries.

==Soviet Union==
The Soviet Union made extensive use of the term ([[Russian language]]: '''враг народа''', "vrag naroda"), as it fit in well with the idea that the people were in control.  Indeed, so great a number of people were labeled with the term that most modern connotations of the phrase associate it with communism.  It was in official use under the [[Bolshevik]]s' rule after the [[October Revolution]]. Soviet leaders abolished its use within the country near the end of the Soviet Union.

Other similar terms were in use as well:
*''enemy of the labourers'' (враг трудящихся, "vrag trudyashchikhsya")
*''enemy of the proletariat'' (враг пролетариата, "vrag proletariata")
*''class enemy'' (классовый враг, "klassovyi vrag"), etc.
In particular, the term "enemy of the workers" was formalized in the [[Article 58 (RSFSR Penal Code)]], and simillar articles in the codes of the other [[Republics of the Soviet Union|Soviet Republics]].

At various times these terms were applied, in particular, to the [[Royal House]], [[aristocrat]]s, the [[bourgeoisie]], [[cleric]]s, the [[intelligentsia]], business entrepreneurs, [[kulak]]s, [[monarchism|monarchists]], [[Menshevism|Mensheviks]], [[Socialist-Revolutionary Party|Esers]], [[Buddhism|Buddhists]], [[General Jewish Labor Union|Bundists]], [[Trotskyism|Trotskyists]], [[Bukharin|Bukharinists]], the "[[old Bolsheviks]]", the army and police, [[emigrant]]s, [[immigrant]]s, [[sabotage|saboteurs]], [[wrecking (Soviet crime)|wreckers]] (вредители, "vrediteli"), "[[parasitism (social offense)|social parasites]]" (тунеядцы, "tuneyadtsy"), ''Kavezhedists'' (people who administered and serviced the [[KVZhD]] ([[China Far East Railway]]), particularly the Russian population of [[Harbin]], [[China]]), those considered [[bourgeois nationalism|bourgeois nationalists]] (notably [[Ukraine|Ukrainian]], [[Lithuania|Lithuanian]], [[Latvia|Latvian]], [[Estonia|Estonian]] nationalists, [[Zionism|Zionists]], [[Basmachi]]), and members of certain ethnic groups (see [[Population transfer#Soviet Union|Population transfer: Soviet Union]]).

An ''enemy of the people'' could be imprisoned, expelled or executed, and his property could be confiscated. Close relatives of enemies of the people were branded "relatives of an enemy of the people", which effected restrictions of their rights. Any family members of the victim still enjoying their freedom were not allowed to hold positions of importance, and only in exceptional cases would they be tolerated as members of the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]], the key to advancement in the Soviet hierarchy. Being a friend of an ''enemy of the people'' automatically placed the person under suspicion.

A significant fraction of the ''enemies of the people'' were given this label not because of their hostile actions against the ''workers' and peasants' state'', but simply because of their social origin or actions before the revolution: those who used hired labor, high-ranking clergy, former policemen, merchants, etc. They were commonly known as ''[[lishenets|lishentsy]]'' (лишенцы, derived from Russian word ''лишение'', deprivation), because by the [[Soviet Constitution]] they were deprived of the right of [[voting]]. This automatically translated into a deprivation of various social benefits, some of them, e.g., [[rationing]], were at times critical for survival.

Since 1927, Article 20 of the Common Part of the penal code that listed possible "measures of social defence" had the following item 20a: "declaration to be an enemy of the workers with deprivation of the union republic citizenship and hence of the USSR citizenship, with obligatory expulsion from its territory". Nevertheless most "enemies of the people" suffered labor camps, rather than expulsion.

In [[1927]], the penal code of the Soviet Union was changed drastically. The update of the penal code turned the country into a police state, full of informants, who were derogatorily called ''stukach'' (стукач, literally "knocker"). According to [[Article 58 (RSFSR Penal Code)]], everyone was obligated to report all "anti-Soviet activity", including any expression of disagreement with the policy of the Party, even in casual jokes. This policy resulted in significant growth of [[Gulag]] camp populations as those who failed to report their relatives or friends were often themselves reported on. State-sponsored [[propaganda]] and mandatory (officially voluntary) participation in the [[Pioneer Movement]] helped to indoctrinate Soviet youth to follow the example of [[Pavlik Morozov]], a young boy who reported his own father, a [[kulak]].

One might wonder why there were so many enemies of workers left, seemingly contrary to the initial claims of [[Bolshevik]]s that the opponents of the [[proletariat]] were crushed as a class in the [[Soviet Union]]. This was handily explained by [[Stalinism|Stalinist]] doctrine, which included the "theory of the [[aggravation of class struggle under socialism]]". The theory postulated that class struggle grows more intense during the [[dictatorship of the proletariat]], thus requiring more extreme measures. Anti-Stalinist Marxists, particularly [[Trotskyism|Trotskyists]], reject this idea.

After [[1937]], the ranks of the "enemies of the people" were expanded to include those labeled as [[Traitor of Motherland Family Member]]s.  The extreme treatment of opponents is one of numerous reasons why the Soviet regime is often considered [[authoritarian]] or described as even [[totalitarian]].

==Further reading==
* Nicolas Werth, ''The Black Book of Communism: Crimes, Terror, Repression'', Harvard University Press, 1999, hardcover, 856 pages, ISBN 0-674-07608-7

==See also==
*[[Great Purge]]
*[[Dictatorship of the proletariat]]
*[[Troika (triumvirate)]]
*[[parasitism (social offense)|Parasitism]]
*[[Public enemy (term)|Public enemy]]

 &lt;!-- both --&gt;

[[Category:Political repression in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Political repression]]
[[Category:Soviet expressions]]
[[Category:Soviet phraseology]]

[[cs:Nepřítel lidu]]
[[ro:Inamic al poporului]]
[[ru:Враг народа]]
[[zh:阶级敌人]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>