<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20100806112259|377461968" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8727347" pageid="8727347" ns="0" title="Mortgage discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-11T06:42:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Mortgage discrimination''' or ''mortgage lending discrimination'' is the practice of banks, governments or other lending institutions denying [[loans]] to one or more groups of people primarily on the basis of race, ethnic origin, sex or religion. One of the most notable instances of widespread mortgage discrimination occurred in United States [[inner city]] neighborhoods from the 1930s up until the late 1970s. There is evidence that the practice still continues in the United States today.&lt;ref name="nytimes"&gt;''[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/15/nyregion/15subprime.html?ex=1350187200&amp;en=a9978e04a9864642&amp;ei=5088&amp;partner=rssnyt&amp;emc=rss Study Finds Disparities in Mortgages by Race]'' [[The New York Times]] By MANNY FERNANDEZ Published: October 15, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
[[African Americans]] and other minorities found it nearly impossible to secure mortgages for property located in [[redlining|redlined]] zones.&lt;ref&gt;"Loans To White Renegades Who Back Negroes Cut Off," Harlem Home News, April 7, 1911&lt;/ref&gt; The systematic denial of loans was a major contributor to the [[urban decay]] that plagued many American cities during this time period. Minorities who tried to buy homes continued to face direct discrimination from lending institutions into the late 1990s. The disparities are not simply due to differences in creditworthiness.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huduser.org/publications/fairhsg/lending.html What We Know About Mortgage Lending Discrimination in America (September 1999)]&lt;/ref&gt; With other factors held constant, rejection rates for Black and Hispanic applicants was about 1.6 times that for Whites in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3631/is_199507/ai_n8720778 Discrimination in mortgage lending Chicago Fed Letter,  Jul 1995  by Hunter, William C]&lt;/ref&gt; Fairness in lending was improved by the [[Home Mortgage Disclosure Act]], passed in 1975. It requires banks to disclose their lending practices in the communities they serve. In the 1970s, the private sector fight against mortgage discrimination began to be led by [[community development bank]]s, such as [[ShoreBank]] in [[Chicago]].&lt;ref name=""&gt;[http://www.spokesmanreview.com/business/story.asp?ID=194303 SR.com: 'Bank with a heart' thrives&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contemporary mortgage discrimination==
Several class action mortgage discrimination claims have been filed against lenders across the country, alleging that lenders disproportionately targeted minorities for high cost, high risk subprime lending, which has resulted in disproportionately higher rates of default and foreclosure for minority African American and Hispanic borrowers.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Aleo, Pablo Svirsky, Foreclosure Fallout: The Banking Industry's Attack on Disparate Impact Race Discrimination Claims Under the Fair Housing Act and Equal Credit Opportunity Act, Boston University Public Interest Law Journal 1 (Fall 2008).&lt;/ref&gt;

FHA loans, a Federal Mortgage program, went to the white majority and reached few minorities. In a study done in Syracuse, between 1996 and 2000, of the 2,169 FHA loans issued only 29 or 1.3 percent went to predominantly minority neighborhoods compared with 1,694 or 78.1 percent that went to white neighborhoods.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-86148585.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://syracusethenandnow.org/Redlining/NewRedlining/FHA_Goes_To_WellToDo.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Mortgage discrimination played a significant part in the real estate bubble that popped during the later part of 2008, it was found that minorities were disproportionately steered by lenders into subprime loans.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/10/01/minorities-more-likely-to_n_306870.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993 President [[Bill Clinton]] made changing the [[Community Reinvestment Act]] to make mortgages more obtainable for lower and lower-middle class families. The changes ushered in during the Clinton Presidency  encouraged banks to make mortgage loans to people who otherwise would not have qualified for them. In 1998 the Federal Bank of Boston issued a report entitled “Closing the Gap: A Guide to Equal Opportunity Lending." The 30 page document was intended to serve as a guide to loan officers to help curb discriminatory lending &lt;ref&gt;Closing the Gap, [http://www.bos.frb.org/commdev/commaff/closingt.pdf Closing the Gap: A Guide to Equal Opportunity Lending]&lt;/ref&gt; "Closing the Gap," instructs banks to hire based upon diversity needs, sweeten the compensation structure for working with lower income applicants, encourages shifting high risk, low income applications to the sub prime market, by saying "the secondary market [Subprime Market] is willing to consider ratios above the standard 28/36," and "Lack of credit history should not be seen as a negative factor."

While, "Closing the Gap" was not an industry-wide mandate, it illustrates the efforts banks took to meet public pressure to overcome perceived mortgage discrimination. Under the Clinton administration community organizers pressured banks to increase their loans to minorities even though many minority applicants could not qualify for traditional 30-year fix mortgages. Karen Wegmann, the head of Wells Fargo's community development group in 1993 told the New York Times, "The atmosphere now is one of saying yes." &lt;ref&gt;Shamed by Publicity, Banks Stress Minority Mortgages, [http://www.nytimes.com/1993/08/30/business/shamed-by-publicity-banks-stress-minority-mortgages.html?pagewanted=2] Shamed by Publicity, Banks Stress Minority Mortgages, accessed Dec. 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; The same New York Times article echoed "Closing the Gap," writing, "The banks have also modified some standards for credit approval. Many low-income people do not have credit-bureau files because they do not have credit cards. So lenders are accepting records of continuously paid utility bills as evidence of creditworthiness. Similarly, they will accept steady income from several employers instead of the length of time at one job."

Because of looser loan restrictions many people who could not find themselves qualifying for a mortgage before now could own a home. Under pressure from activist organizations such as ACORN, several of whom were allies of President Barack Obama &lt;ref&gt;O's Dangerous Pals: Barack's 'organizer' Buds Pushed for Bad Mortgages, [http://www.nypost.com/p/news/opinion/opedcolumnists/item_cvq7rDCHftKwJyLaecfPQK] Pals: Barack's 'organizer' Buds Pushed For Bad Mortgage, accessed Dec. 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;, then President Bill Clinton, and influential Democrats in Congress like Barny Frank,&lt;ref&gt;Frank Not Free From Blame In Mortgage Mess, [http://wbztv.com/local/barney.frank.bailout.2.829945.html] Frank Not Free from Blame in Mortgage Mess, accessed Dec. 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;, banks began loans to people who should not have qualified for loans. Because banks were pressured to loan to minorities and low income applicants, and because the applicants were low-income who had rented homes from generations the banks could reap profits by selling products loaded with fees because the applicants did not either know, or care to read the fine print that would eventually raise their mortgage payments &lt;ref&gt;Inside the Countrywide Lending Spree, [http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/26/business/yourmoney/26country.html?_r=2&amp;pagewanted=1] Inside the Countrywide Lending Spree, accessed Dec. 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Minorities willingly entered sub-prime mortgages in far great numbers than whites and represented a disproportional percentage of foreclosures,&lt;ref&gt;Minority families face wave of foreclosures
Consumer groups urge more 'teeth' in laws combating predators, [http://www.marketwatch.com/story/minority-families-face-wave-of-foreclosures], accessed Dec. 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Consumer groups urge more 'teeth' in laws combating predators, accessed Dec. 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting wave of minority foreclosures tipped a fading housing market into a dive and contributed to the economic fall of 2008/2009.

Recently, the [[NAACP]] has submitted a lawsuit concerning alleged injustices in the lending industry.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackenterprise.com/cms/exclusivesopen.aspx?id=3262 NAACP Fights Loan Discrimination]&lt;/ref&gt; An analysis, by N.Y.U.’s Furman Center for Real Estate and Urban Policy, illustrated stark racial differences between the [[New York City]] neighborhoods where subprime mortgages were common and those where they were rare. The 10 neighborhoods with the highest rates of mortgages from subprime lenders had black and Hispanic majorities, and the 10 areas with the lowest rates were mainly non-Hispanic white. The analysis showed that even when median income levels were comparable, home buyers in minority neighborhoods were more likely to get a loan from a subprime lender.&lt;ref name="nytimes"/&gt; Discrimination motivated by [[prejudice]] is contingent on the racial composition of neighborhoods where the loan is sought and the race of the applicant. Lending institutions have been shown to treat black and Latino mortgage applicants differently when buying homes in white neighborhoods than when buying homes in black neighborhoods.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen R Holloway (1998) ''Exploring the Neighborhood Contingency of Race Discrimination in Mortgage Lending in Columbus, Ohio'' Annals of the Association of American Geographers 88 (2), 252–276.&lt;/ref&gt; An example of this occurred in the 60's and 70's on the near northside of Chicago. Thousands of blacks, Latinos, and poor people were systematically dislocated and prevented from acquiring loans by realtors and lending institutions with the blessings of the city's urban renewal program.{{Citation needed|reason=washburnmav|date=July 2008}}

==Equal Credit Opportunity Act==
Under the Equal Credit Opportunity Act (“ECOA”), a creditor may not discriminate against an applicant based on the applicant’s race, color, or national origin “with respect to any aspect of a credit transaction,” 15 U.S.C.A. § 1691.

==Fair Housing Act==
Under the Fair Housing Act (“FHA”) (Title VIII of the Civil Rights Act of 1968), it is “unlawful for any person or other entity whose business includes engaging in residential real estate-related transactions to discriminate against any person in making available such a transaction, or in the terms or conditions of such a transaction, because of race, color, ... or national origin.”  42 U.S.C.A. § 3605. Section 3605, although not specifically naming foreclosures, discrimination in “the manner in which a lending institution forecloses a dlinquent or defaulted mortgage note” falls under the realm of the “terms or conditions of such loan.”  Harper v. Union Savings Association, 429 F.Supp. 1254, 1258-59 (N.D. Ohio 1977).

==FDIC==
Consistent with many jurisdictions throughout the country, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation (“FDIC”), based in part on a study conducted by the Federal Reserve Bank of Boston, issued a “Policy Statement On Discrimination In Lending” on April 29, 2004, emphasizing the breadth of prohibitions on discriminatory conduct in lending under the ECOA and the FHA.  The FDIC Policy Statement explained that “courts have recognized three methods of proof of lending discrimination under the ECOA and the FH Act,” including: “Overt evidence of discrimination,” when a lender blatantly discriminates on a prohibited basis; evidence of “disparate treatment,” when a lender treats applicants differently based on one of the prohibited factors; and evidence of "disparate impact," when a lender applies a practice uniformly to all applicants but the practice has a discriminatory effect on a prohibited basis and is not justified by business necessity.

FDIC Policy Statement, p.&amp;nbsp;5399 (April 29, 2004).

== Civil Rights Act of 1966 ==

In addition to ECOA and FHA, the Civil Rights Act of 1966, as amended, provides that “[a]ll citizens of the United States shall have the same right, in every State and Territory, as is enjoyed by white citizens thereof to inherit, purchase, lease, sell, hold, and convey real and personal property.”  42 U.S.C.A. § 1982.

== See also ==

*[[Computer-assisted reporting]]
*[[Redlining]]
*[[Racial steering]]
*[[Racial segregation|Segregation]]
*[[White flight]]
*[[Black flight]]
*[[Home Mortgage Disclosure Act]]

==Sources==

&lt;!--See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref&gt; and &lt;/ref&gt; tags and the tag below --&gt;

&lt;references/&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mortgage Discrimination}}
[[Category:Urban decay]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Mortgage industry of the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>