<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031028060750|1637406" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="765" pageid="765" ns="0" title="Abortion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-28T07:03:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[da:Abort]]
[[de:Abtreibung]]
[[nl:Abortus]]

"'''Abortion'''," in its most commonly used sense, refers to the deliberate early termination of [[pregnancy]], resulting in the death of the [[embryo]] or [[fetus]]. Medically, the term also refers to the early termination of a pregnancy by natural causes ("spontaneous abortion" or [[miscarriage]], which ends 1 in 5 of all pregnancies, usually within the first 13 weeks) or to the cessation of normal growth of a body part or organ. What follows is a discussion of the issues related to deliberate or "induced" abortion.

(Note: "morning after" or "emergency" contraceptive drugs that are taken within 72 hours of sex interfere with the release of eggs from the ovary or with fertilization, and so are not generally considered to be forms of abortion unless they interfere with implantation of a zygote when taken later).


== Methods of performing abortion ==

Depending on the stage of pregnancy an abortion is performed by a number of different methods. For the earliest terminations (before nine weeks or so) a [[chemical abortion]] is the usual method.  The procedure consists of giving either [[methotrexate]] or [[mifepristone]] ([[RU-486]]) followed by administration of [[misoprostol]].  Approximately 8% of these abortions require surgical followup.

Concurrent with chemical abortion and extending up until around the fifteenth week [[suction-aspiration abortion|suction-aspiration]] or vacuum abortion is the most common approach. replacing the more risky [[dilation and curettage]] (D &amp; C). ''[[Manual vacuum aspiration]]'' (MVE) consists of emptying the [[uterus]] by suction using a manual [[syringe]]. From the fifteenth week up until around the eighteenth week a surgical [[dilation and evacuation]] (D &amp; E) is used. D&amp;amp;E consists of opening the [[cervix]] of the [[uterus]] and emptying it using surgical instruments and suction.

''[[Dilation and suction curettage]]'' consists of emptying the [[uterus]] by suction using a special apparatus.  ''[[Curettage]]'' is cleaning the walls of [[uterus]] with a [[curette]].  ''[[Dilation and curettage]]'' (D&amp;amp;C) is a standard gynaecological procedure performed for a variety of reasons.

As the fetus size increases other techniques must be used to secure abortion in the third [[trimester]], premature expulsion of the fetus can be induced with [[prostaglandin]], this can be coupled with injecting the amniotic fluid with saline or urea solution. Very late abortions can be brought about by the controversial [[intact dilation and extraction]] (D &amp; X) or a [[hysterotomy abortion]], similar to a [[caesarian section]], and requiring the surgical decompression of the fetus's head before evacuation. This is also referred to as [[Intact dilation and extraction]]. 

See also: [[Sex selective abortion]], [[herbal contraception]], [[partial-birth abortion]]

==Possible side effects==

Some experts argue that abortion may increase women's risk of breast cancer and depression. However, the reason abortion 'increases' the risk of breast cancer is because if a woman does not have children near the beginning of childbearing age, that in itself increases their risk.

Depression, on the other hand, is a larger problem.  (&lt;i&gt;While the causes of depression vary, this article deals only with abortion-related depression&lt;/i&gt;). According to a study of 1884 women conducted by the National Longitudinal Survey of Youth, women who did not carry their first pregnancies to term are 65% more likely to have clinical depression around eight years later.

See also:

*[[Abortion in Canada]]
*[[Abortion in Ireland]] 
*[[Abortion in the United Kingdom]] 
*[[Abortion in the United States]] 
*[[Abortion, legal and moral issues]] 
*[[Religion and abortion]].</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>