<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113235000|87645159" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="765" pageid="765" ns="0" title="Abortion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T23:51:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Abortion}}

&lt;!--NOTE ABOUT INTRO: This is the product of extensive discussion between many Wikipedians. Please refer to Talk:Abortion/First paragraph and its archives before proposing — or making — any changes.--&gt;
An '''abortion''' is the removal or expulsion of an [[embryo]] or [[fetus]] from the [[uterus]], resulting in or caused by its [[death]]. This can occur spontaneously as a [[miscarriage]], or be artificially induced through [[chemistry|chemical]], [[surgery|surgical]] or other means. Commonly, "abortion" refers to an induced procedure at any point in the [[pregnancy]]; medically, it is defined as a miscarriage or induced termination before twenty weeks' [[gestation]], which is considered [[Viability|nonviable]].

Various methods of inducing abortion have been used throughout [[History of abortion|history]]. The [[Ethical aspects of abortion|moral]] and [[Abortion law|legal]] aspects of abortion are the subject of intense [[Abortion debate|debate]] in many parts of the world.
&lt;!--Note to editors: This article has a long and intense history of terminology debates. Please review the talk page before making changes to lines to see if there is a previous established consensus or compromise. Thank you.--&gt;

==Definitions==
The following medical terms are used to define an abortion:
* ''Spontaneous abortion ([[miscarriage]])'': An abortion due to accidental trauma or [[Death by natural causes|natural causes]], such as a chromosomal number discrepancy, early disease, or environmental factors.
*''Induced abortion'': An abortion deliberately caused. Induced abortions are further subcategorized into therapeutic abortions and elective abortions: 
**''Therapeutic abortion:'' &lt;ref&gt;Roche, Natalie E. (2004). [http://www.emedicine.com/med/topic3311.htm Therapeutic Abortion]. Retrieved [[2006-03-08]].&lt;/ref&gt;
*** To save the life of the pregnant woman.    
*** To preserve the woman's physical or mental health. 
*** To terminate a pregnancy that would result in a child born with a [[congenital disorder]] which would be [[fatal]] or associated with significant [[morbidity]]. 
*** To [[selective reduction|selectively reduce]] the number of [[fetus]]es to lessen health risks associated with  [[multiple birth|multiple pregnancy]].
**''Elective abortion'': An abortion performed for any other reason.

A pregnancy that ends earlier than 37 complete weeks of gestation, and where an [[infant]] is born and survives, is termed a [[premature birth]]. A pregnancy that ends with an infant dead upon birth at any gestational stage, due to causes including spontaneous abortion or complications during delivery, is termed a [[stillbirth]]. 

In common parlance, the term "abortion" is synonymous with induced abortion of a human fetus. However, in medical texts, the word 'abortion' can also refer to ''spontaneous abortion'' (miscarriage).

The distinctions between spontaneous abortion, therapeutic abortion and [[Induction (birth)|induced delivery]] may be blurred.  For example, in cases of [[pre-eclampsia]] spontaneous abortion may occur, but if it does not, doctors may opt for immediate delivery regardless of the potential viability of the fetus.

==Incidence==
The incidence of and reasons for induced abortion vary in regions in which abortion is generally permitted. It has been estimated approximately 46 million abortions are performed globally each year. Of these, 26 million are said to occur in [[abortion law|places where abortion is legal]]; the other 20 million happen where it is illegal. Some countries, such as [[Belgium]] (11.2 per 100 known pregnancies) and the [[Netherlands]] (10.6%), have a low rate of induced abortion, while others like [[Russia]] (62.6%) and [[Vietnam]] (43.7%) have a comparatively high rate. The world ratio is 26 induced abortions per 100 known pregnancies.&lt;ref&gt;Henshaw, Stanley K., Singh, Susheela, &amp; Haas, Taylor. (1999). [http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/journals/25s3099.html The Incidence of Abortion Worldwide]. ''International Family Planning Perspectives, 25 (Supplement)'', 30–8. Retrieved [[2006-01-18]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Image:UKAbortionbyGestationalAgeChart2004.png|thumb|right|220px|The percentage of abortions by [[gestational age]] in [[England and Wales]] during 2004.]]

Rates of abortion also vary depending upon the stage of [[pregnancy]] and the method practiced. In 2002, from data collected in those areas of the [[United States]] which sufficiently reported [[gestational age]], it was found that 86.7% of abortions were conducted at or prior to 12 weeks, 9.9% from 13 to 20 weeks, and 1.4% at or after 21 weeks. 91.3% percent of these were classified as having been done by "[[curettage]]" ([[Suction-aspiration abortion|suction-aspiration]], [[Dilation and curettage|D&amp;C]], [[Dilation and evacuation|D&amp;E]]), 5.2% by "[[chemical abortion|medical]]" means ([[mifepristone]]), 0.8% by "[[instillation abortion|intrauterine instillation]]" ([[saline (medicine)|saline]] or [[prostaglandin]]), and 1.5% by "other" ([[hysterotomy abortion|hysterotomy]] and [[hysterectomy]]). &lt;ref name="cdc2002"&gt;Strauss, Lilo T., Herndon, Joy, Chang, Jeani, Parker, Wilda Y., Bowens, Sonya V., Berg, Cynthia J. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. ([[2005-11-15]]). [http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/ss5407a1.htm Abortion Surveillance - United States, 2002]. ''Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report''. Retrieved [[2006-02-20]].&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Guttmacher Institute]] estimated that there were 2,200 [[intact dilation and extraction]] procedures in the U.S. during 2000 which would account for 0.17% of the total number of abortions performed that year.&lt;ref&gt;Finer, Lawrence B. &amp; Henshaw, Stanley K. (2003). [http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/journals/3500603.html Abortion Incidence and Services in the United States in 2000]. ''Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health, 35 (1).'' Retrieved [[2006-05-10]].&lt;/ref&gt;   Similarly, in [[England]] and [[Wales]] in 2004, 87.6% of terminations occurred at or under 12 weeks, 10.7% between 13 to 19 weeks, and 1.5% at or over 20 weeks. 76% of those reported were by vacuum aspiration, 4% by D&amp;E, 19% by a chemical agent, and 1% by [[feticide]].&lt;ref&gt;Government Statistical Service for the Department of Health. ([[2005-07-27]]). [http://www.dh.gov.uk/PublicationsAndStatistics/Publications/PublicationsStatistics/PublicationsStatisticsArticle/fs/en?CONTENT_ID=4116461&amp;chk=6T9UTA Abortion statistics, England and Wales: 2004]. Retrieved [[2006-05-10]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Image:AGIAbortionReasonsBarChart.png|thumb|left|320px|A [[bar chart]] depicting selected data from the 1998 [[Alan Guttmacher Institute|AGI]] [[meta-study]] on the reasons women stated for having an abortion.]]

A 1998 study aggregated data from studies in 27 countries on the reasons women seek to terminate their pregnancies. It concluded that common factors cited to have influenced the abortion decision were the desire to delay or end [[childbirth|childbearing]], concern over the interruption of [[employment|work]] or [[education]], issues of financial or relationship stability, and perceived immaturity. &lt;ref name="bankole98"&gt;Bankole, Akinrinola, Singh, Susheela, &amp; Haas, Taylor. (1998). [http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/journals/2411798.html Reasons Why Women Have Induced Abortions: Evidence from 27 Countries]. ''International Family Planning Perspectives, 24 (3)'', 117-127 &amp; 152. Retrieved [[2006-01-18]].&lt;/ref&gt; A 2004 study in which  [[United States|American]] women at [[abortion clinic|clinics]] answered a [[questionnaire]] yielded similar results. &lt;ref name="finer2005"&gt;Finer, Lawrence B., Frohwirth, Lori F., Dauphinee, Lindsay A., Singh, Shusheela, &amp; Moore, Ann M. (2005). [http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/journals/3711005.pdf Reasons U.S. women have abortions: quantative and qualitative perspectives]. ''Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health, 37 (3),'' 110-8. Retrieved [[2006-01-18]].&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Finland]] and the  [[United States]], concern for the health risks posed by pregnancy in individual cases was not a factor commonly given; however, in [[Bangladesh]], [[India]], and [[Kenya]] health concerns were cited by women more frequently as reasons for having an abortion. &lt;ref name="bankole98" /&gt; 1% of women in the 2004 survey-based U.S. study became pregnant as a result of [[rape]] and 0.5% as a result of [[incest]]. &lt;ref name="finer2005"/&gt; Another American study in 2002 concluded that 54% of women who had an abortion were using a form of [[birth control|contraception]] at the time of becoming pregnant while 46% were not. Inconsistent use was reported by 49% of those using [[condom]]s and 76% of those using [[oral contraception]]; 42% of those using condoms reported failure through slippage or breakage.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Rachel K., Darroch, Jacqueline E., Henshaw, Stanley K. (2002). [http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/journals/3429402.pdf Contraceptive Use Among U.S. Women Having Abortions in 2000-2001]. ''Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health, 34 (6).'' Retrieved [[June 15]], [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some abortions are undergone as the result of societal pressures.  These might include the stigmatization of [[disabled]] persons, preference for children of a specific [[sex]], disapproval of [[single parent|single motherhood]], insufficient economic support for [[family|families]], lack of access to or rejection of contraceptive methods, or efforts toward [[population control]] (such as [[People's Republic of China|China]]'s [[one-child policy]]). A combination of these factors can sometimes result in compulsory abortion or [[sex-selective abortion]]. In many areas, especially in [[developing country|developing nations]] or where abortion is illegal, women sometimes resort to "[[back-alley abortion|back-alley]]" or [[self-induced abortion|self-induced]] procedures. The [[World Health Organization]] suggests that there are 19 million terminations annually which fit its criteria for an [[Abortion#Unsafe abortion|unsafe abortion]]. &lt;ref name="whounsafe"&gt;World Health Organization. (2004). [http://www.who.int/reproductive-health/publications/unsafe_abortion_estimates_04/estimates.pdf Unsafe abortion: global and regional estimates of unsafe abortion and associated mortality in 2000]. Retrieved [[2006-01-12]].&lt;/ref&gt; See [[Abortion#Social issues|social issues]] for more information on these subjects.

==Forms of abortion==
===Spontaneous abortion===
{{main|Miscarriage}}

&lt;!--improve me!--&gt;
Spontaneous abortions, generally referred to as miscarriages, occur when an embryo or fetus is lost due to natural causes before the 20th week of development. Spontaneous abortions after the 20th week are generally considered to be preterm deliveries. Most miscarriages occur very early in a pregnancy. Between 10% and 50% of pregnancies end in miscarriage, depending upon the age and health of the pregnant woman.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://wuphysicians.wustl.edu/dept.asp?pageID=8&amp;ID=35 Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility: Recurrent Pregnancy Loss (Recurrent Miscarriage)]." (n.d.) Retrieved [[2006-01-18]] from Washington University School of Medicine, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology web site.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The risk for spontaneous abortion is greater in those with a history of more than three previous (known) spontaneous abortions, those who have had a previous induced abortion, those with systemic diseases, and in women over age 35.  

Other causes can be infection (of either the woman or the fetus), immune responses, or serious systemic diseases of the woman. 

A spontaneous abortion can also be caused by accidental [[Physical trauma|trauma]]; intentional trauma to cause miscarriage is considered an induced abortion.

===Induced abortion===
A pregnancy can be intentionally aborted in a number of ways. The manner selected depends chiefly upon the [[gestational age]] of the [[fetus]], in addition to the legality, regional availability, and/or doctor-patient preference for specific procedures.

====Surgical abortion====
[[Image:Abortionmethods.png|thumb|380px|right|[[Gestational age]] may determine which abortion methods are practiced.]]
In the first twelve weeks, [[suction-aspiration abortion|suction-aspiration]] or vacuum abortion is the most common method.&lt;ref&gt;Healthwise. [http://www.webmd.com/hw/womens_conditions/tw1078.asp#tw1112 Manual and vacuum aspiration for abortion]. (2004). ''WebMD.'' Retrieved [[2006-08-19]].&lt;/ref&gt;   ''[[Manual vacuum aspiration]]'', or MVA abortion, consists of removing the [[fetus]] or [[embryo]] by suction using a manual [[syringe]], while the ''[[Electric vacuum aspiration]]'' or EVA abortion method uses an electric [[pump]]. These techniques are comparable, differing in the mechanism used to apply suction, how early in pregnancy they can be used, and whether cervical dilation is necessary. MVA, also known as "mini-suction" and [[menstrual extraction]], can be used in very early pregnancy, and doesn't require cervical dilation.  Surgical techniques are sometimes referred to as ''STOP'': 'Suction (or surgical) Termination Of Pregnancy'. From the fifteenth week up until around the twenty-sixth week, a surgical [[dilation and evacuation]] (D &amp; E) is used. D &amp; E consists of opening the [[cervix]] of the [[uterus]] and emptying it using surgical instruments and suction.

''[[Dilation and curettage]]'' (D &amp; C) is a standard gynecological procedure performed for a variety of reasons, including examination of the uterine lining for possible malignancy, investigation of abnormal bleeding, and abortion.  ''[[Curettage]]'' refers to the cleaning of the walls of the [[uterus]] with a [[curette]]. The [[World Health Organization]] recommends this sort of procedure, also called Sharp Curettage, only when MVA is unavailable.&lt;ref&gt;World Health Organization. (2003). [http://www.who.int/reproductive-health/impac/Procedures/Dilatetion_P61_P63.html Managing complications in pregnancy and childbirth: a guide for midwives and doctors]. Retrieved [[2006-08-19]].&lt;/ref&gt;  Sharp curettage only accounted for 2.4% of abortion procedures in the US in 2002. &lt;ref name="cdc2002" /&gt; The term "D and C", or perhaps ''suction curette'', etc, is sometimes used as a euphemism to refer to the first trimester abortion procedure, irrespective of the method used to perform the procedure. 

Other techniques must be used to induce abortion in the third [[trimester]]. Premature delivery can be induced with [[prostaglandin]]; this can be coupled with injecting the [[amniotic sac|amniotic fluid]] with caustic solutions containing [[saline (medicine)|saline]] or [[urea]]. Very late abortions can be brought about by [[intact dilation and extraction]] (intact D &amp; X) (also called [[Intrauterine cranial decompression]]), which requires the surgical decompression of the fetus's head before evacuation, and is sometimes termed "[[partial-birth abortion]]."  A [[hysterotomy abortion]], similar to a [[caesarian section]] but resulting in a terminated fetus, can also be used at late stages of pregnancy. It can be performed vaginally, with an incision just above the [[cervix]], in the late mid-trimester.{{fact}}

From somewhere between the 20th to 23rd week of gestation, an [[medical injection|injection]] to stop the fetal heart can be used as the first phase of the surgical abortion procedure.&lt;ref&gt;Vause S, Sands J, Johnston TA, Russell S, Rimmer S. (2002). PMID 12521492 Could some fetocides be avoided by more prompt referral after diagnosis of fetal abnormality? J Obstet Gynaecol. 2002 May;22(3):243-5. Retrieved [[2006-03-17]].&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Dommergues M, Cahen F, Garel M, Mahieu-Caputo D, Dumez Y. (2003). PMID 12576743 Feticide during second- and third-trimester termination of pregnancy: opinions of health care professionals. Fetal Diagn Ther. 2003 Mar-Apr;18(2):91-7. Retrieved [[2006-03-17]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bhide A, Sairam S, Hollis B, Thilaganathan B. (2002). PMID 12230443 Comparison of feticide carried out by cordocentesis versus cardiac puncture. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2002 Sep;20(3):230-2. Retrieved [[2006-03-17]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Senat MV, Fischer C, Bernard JP, Ville Y. (2003). PMID 12628271 The use of lidocaine for fetocide in late termination of pregnancy. BJOG. 2003 Mar;110(3):296-300. Retrieved [[2006-03-17]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Senat MV, Fischer C, Ville Y. (2002). PMID 12001185 Funipuncture for fetocide in late termination of pregnancy. Prenat Diagn. 2002 May;22(5):354-6. Retrieved [[2006-03-17]].&lt;/ref&gt;

====Chemical abortion====
{{main|Chemical abortion}}

Effective in the first trimester of pregnancy, chemical (also referred to as a medical abortion), or non-surgical abortions comprise 10% of all abortions in the [[United States]] and [[Europe]]. Combined regimens include [[methotrexate]] or [[mifepristone]], followed by a [[prostaglandin]]--either [[misoprostol]] or [[gemeprost]]. Misoprostol is used in the U.S.; gemeprost is used in the UK and Sweden. When used within 49 days gestation, approximately 92% of women undergoing medical termination of pregnancy with a combined regimen experience completed abortion without surgical intervention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Spitz, I.M. et al|title=Early pregnancy termination with mifepristone and misoprostol in the United States|journal=New England Journal of Medicine|year=1998|volume=338|issue=18|id=PMID 9562577}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Misoprostol can be used alone, but has a lower efficacy rate than combined regimens.  In cases of failure of medical abortion, vacuum or manual aspiration is used to complete the abortion surgically.

====Other means of abortion====
[[Image:Angkordemon.jpg|thumb|right|240px|A visual representation of an abortion caused by pounding a woman with a mallet at [[Angkor Wat]].]]
Historically, a number of [[herb]]s reputed to possess [[abortifacient]] properties have been used in [[folk medicine]]: [[tansy]], [[pennyroyal]], [[black cohosh]], and the now-extinct [[silphium]] (see [[Abortion#History of abortion|history of abortion]]). The use of herbs in such a manner can cause serious — even lethal — side effects, such as [[multiple organ dysfunction syndrome|multiple organ failure]], and is not recommended by [[physician]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Ciganda, C., &amp; Laborde, A. (2003). [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=12807304&amp;query_hl=9 Herbal infusions used for induced abortion]. ''J Toxicol Clin Toxicol, 41(3),'' 235-9. Retrieved [[2006-01-25]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Abortion is sometimes attempted through means of trauma to the [[abdomen]]. The degree of force applied, if severe, can cause serious internal injuries without necessarily succeeding in inducing [[miscarriage]].&lt;ref&gt;Education for Choice. ([[2005-05-06]]). [http://www.efc.org.uk/Foryoungpeople/Factsaboutabortion/Unsafeabortion Unsafe abortion]. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt;  Both accidental and deliberate abortions of this kind can be subject to criminal liability in many countries. In [[Myanmar|Burma]], [[Indonesia]], [[Malaysia]], the [[Philippines]], and [[Thailand]], there is an ancient tradition of attempting abortion through forceful abdominal [[massage]].&lt;ref&gt;Potts, Malcolm, &amp; Campbell, Martha. (2002). [http://big.berkeley.edu/ifplp.history.pdf History of contraception]. ''Gynecology and Obstetrics'', vol. 6, chp. 8. Retrieved [[2005-01-25]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Reported methods of unsafe, [[self-induced abortion]] include the misuse of [[misoprostol]] (a drug for [[ulcer]]s), and the insertion of non-surgical implements such as [[knitting needle]]s and [[clothes hanger]]s into the [[uterus]].

==Health effects==
&lt;!--MAJOR REORG NEEDED. Entire section is argumentative, and biased: See Talk. --&gt;
Early-term surgical abortion is a simple procedure. When performed before the 16th week by competent [[Physician|doctor]]s — or, in some states, [[nurse practitioner]]s, [[nurse midwife|nurse midwives]], and [[physician assistant]]s — it is safer than [[childbirth]].&lt;ref&gt;Cates W., Jr, &amp; Tietze C. (1978). Standardized mortality rates associated with legal abortion: United States, 1972-1975 [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=639966&amp;dopt=Abstract Electronic version]. ''Family Planning Perspectives, 10 (2)'', 109-12. Retrieved [[2006-01-28]].&lt;/ref&gt;  &lt;!-- As I pointed out earlier, listing the negatives of this generally safe procedure first would be biased. --&gt;

As with most surgical procedures, the most common surgical abortion methods carry a small risk of potentially serious complications. These risks include: a perforated [[uterus]], perforated [[bowel]] or [[urinary bladder|bladder]], [[septic shock]], [[infertility|sterility]], and [[death]]. The risk of complications occurring can increase depending on how far the [[pregnancy]] has progressed, but remains less than [[Complications of pregnancy|complications]] that may occur from carrying the pregnancy to term.

Assessing the risks of induced abortion depend on a number of factors. First, there are relative health risks of induced abortion and pregnancy, which are both affected by wide variation in the quality of health services in different [[Society|societies]] and among different [[socio-economic]] groups, a lack of uniform [[definition]]s of terms, and difficulties in patient follow-up and after-care. The degree of risk is also dependent upon the skill and experience of the practitioner; maternal age, health, and [[Parity (medicine)|parity]]; [[gestational age]]; pre-existing conditions; methods and instruments used; [[medication]]s used; the skill and experience of those assisting the practitioner; and the quality of recovery and follow-up care. A highly-skilled practitioner of birth and abortion, operating under ideal conditions, will tend to have a low rate of complications; an inexperienced practitioner in an ill-equipped and ill-staffed facility, on the other hand, will often have a higher incidence of complications that could cause death during pregnancy, birth, or abortion.

In the [[United Kingdom]], the number of deaths due to legal abortion between the years of 1991 and 1993 was 5, as compared to the 9 deaths caused by [[ectopic pregnancy]] during the same time frame.&lt;ref&gt;Department of Health. (1998). ''[http://www.archive.official-documents.co.uk/document/doh/wmd/wmd-hm.htm Why Mothers Die: Report on Confidential Enquiries into Maternal Deaths in the United Kingdom 1994–1996].'' London: The Stationery Office. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt;  In the [[United States]], during the year 1999, there were 4 deaths due to legal abortion, 10 due to [[miscarriage]], and 525 due to pregnancy-related reasons.&lt;ref&gt;Elam-Evans, Laurie. D., Strauss, Lilo T., Herndon, Joy, Parker, Wilda Y., Bowens, Sonya V., Zane, Suzanne, ''et al.'' Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. ([[2003-11-23]]). ''[http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/ss5212a1.htm Abortion Surveillance - United States, 2000].'' Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt;  
&lt;ref&gt;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. ([[2003-02-20]]). [http://www.cdc.gov/od/oc/media/pressrel/fs030220.htm Fact Sheet: Pregnancy-Related Mortality Surveillance - United States, 1991-1999]. Retrieved [[2006-04-02]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Some practitioners advocate using minimal [[anaesthesia]] so that the patient can alert them to possible complications. Others recommend [[general anaesthesia]], in order to prevent patient movement, which might cause a perforation. General anaesthesia carries its own risks, including death, which is why public health officials recommend against its routine use.

[[Dilation]] of the [[cervix]] carries the risk of cervical tears or perforations, including small tears that might not be apparent and might cause [[cervical incompetence]] in future pregnancies. Most practitioners recommend using the smallest possible dilators, and using [[osmotic]] rather than [[Machine|mechanical]] dilators after the first [[trimester]] of pregnancy. 

Instruments are placed within the uterus to remove the fetus. These can, on rare occasions, cause [[perforation]] or [[laceration]] of the uterus, and damage to structures surrounding the uterus. Laceration or perforation of the uterus or cervix can, again on rare occasions, lead to even more serious complications.

Incomplete emptying of the uterus can cause [[hemorrhage]] and infection. Use of [[ultrasound]] verification of the location and duration of the pregnancy prior to abortion, with immediate follow-up of patients reporting continuing pregnancy symptoms after the procedure, will virtually eliminate this risk. The sooner a complication is noted and properly treated, the lower the risk of permanent injury or death. 

In rare cases, the abortion will be unsuccessful and the pregnancy will continue. An unsuccessful abortion can also result in the delivery of a live [[neonate]], or infant. This, termed a failed abortion, is very rare and can only occur late in the pregnancy. Some doctors faced with this situation have voiced concerns about the ethical and legal ramifications of then letting the neonate die. As a result, recent investigations have been launched in the [[United Kingdom]] by the Confidential Enquiry into Maternal and Child Health (CEMACH) and the Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, in order to determine how widespread the problem is and what an ethical response in the treatment of the infant might be.&lt;ref&gt;Rogers, Lois. ([[2005-11-27]]). "[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2087-1892696,00.html Fifty babies a year are alive after abortion]." ''The Sunday Times.'' Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[#unsafe abortion|Unsafe abortion]] methods (e.g. use of certain drugs, herbs, or insertion of non-surgical objects into the [[uterus]]) are potentially dangerous, carrying a significantly elevated risk for permanent injury or death, as compared to abortions done by [[physician]]s.

===Suggested effects===
There is controversy over a number of proposed risks and effects of abortion. Evidence, whether in support of or against such claims, might in part be influenced by the political and religious beliefs of the parties behind it.


====Breast cancer====
{{main|Abortion-breast cancer hypothesis|Breast cancer}}

The abortion-breast cancer (ABC) hypothesis (also known as ABC link) posits a [[causality|causal relationship]] between induced abortion and an increased risk of developing [[breast cancer]].  In early [[pregnancy]] the level of [[estrogen]]s increases, leading to [[breast]] [[cellular differentiation|growth]] in preparation for [[lactation]]. The abortion-breast cancer hypothesis proposes that if this process is interrupted with an abortion &amp;ndash; before full differentiation in the third [[trimester]] &amp;ndash; then more relatively vulnerable undifferentiated cells could be left than there were prior to the pregnancy, resulting in a greater potential risk of breast cancer.  The hypothesis, however, has not been scientifically verified, and abortion is not considered a breast cancer risk by any major cancer organization.

A large [[Epidemiology|epidemiological]] study by Dr. Mads Melbye et al. in 1997, with data from two national [[registry|registries]] in [[Denmark]], reported the correlation to be negligible to non-existent after [[statistical hypothesis testing|statistical adjustment]].&lt;ref&gt;Melbye M. et al. (1997) ''Induced abortion and the risk of breast cancer.'' [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=8988884 (abstract)] New England Journal of Medicine, 336, 81-5. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]] from PubMed.&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[National Cancer Institute]] conducted an official workshop with numerous experts on the issue in [[February 2003]], which concluded with its highest strength rating for the selected evidence it considered that "induced abortion is not associated with an increase in breast cancer risk."&lt;ref&gt;National Cancer Institute. ([[2003-03-04]]). [http://www.cancer.gov/cancerinfo/ere-workshop-report Summary Report: Early Reproductive Events and Breast Cancer Workshop]. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, Beral et al. published a collaborative reanalysis of 53 epidemiological studies and concluded that abortion does "not increase a woman's risk of developing breast cancer."&lt;ref&gt;Beral V. et al. (2004) ''Breast cancer and abortion: collaborative reanalysis of data from 53 epidemiological studies, including 83,000 women with breast cancer from 16 countries.'' [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15051280 (abstract)] ''The Lancet, 363,'' 1007-16. Retrieved [[2006-04-12]] from PubMed.&lt;/ref&gt;

Of over 100 experts at the National Cancer Institute workshop, [[Joel Brind|Dr. Joel Brind]], the primary advocate of an abortion-breast cancer link and an invitee to the workshop, filed the only dissenting opinion criticizing the NCI's and Melbye's conclusions.&lt;ref&gt;Brind, Joel. ([[2003-03-10]]). [http://www.bcpinstitute.org/nci_minority_rpt.htm Early Reproductive Events and Breast Cancer: A Minority Report]. Retrieved [[2006-03-24]].&lt;/ref&gt;  Brind argues that the majority of interview-based studies have indicated a link and some are [[statistically significant]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etters.net/cancerTP.htm#3 Etters.net] &amp;ndash; American abortion-breast cancer studies&lt;/ref&gt;  but there remains debate as to the reliability of these retrospective studies because of possible [[response bias]]. Most medical professionals agree with the recent prospective studies that conclude no abortion-breast cancer association,&lt;ref&gt;American Cancer Society. ([[2006-10-03]]) [http://www.cancer.org/docroot/CRI/content/CRI_2_4_2X_What_are_the_risk_factors_for_breast_cancer_5.asp  Cancer.org] – ''What Are the Risk Factors for Breast Cancer?'' Retrieved [[2006-03-30]].&lt;/ref&gt;  and the ABC issue is seen by some as merely a part of the current [[pro-life]] "women-centered" strategy against abortion.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur, Joyce. (2002) [http://www.prochoiceactionnetwork-canada.org/articles/abclink.shtml ProChoiceActionNetwork-Canada.org] – ''Abortion and Breast Cancer — A Forged Link''&lt;/ref&gt;  Nevertheless, the subject continues to be one of mostly political but some scientific contention.&lt;ref&gt;Jasen, P. (2005) [http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=1251638 Breast Cancer and the Politics of Abortion in the United States]. ''Medical History 2005 October 1; 49(4): 423–444.''&lt;/ref&gt;

====Fetal pain==== 
{{main|Fetal pain}} 

The existence or absence of fetal sensation during abortion is a matter of medical, ethical and public policy interest. Evidence is conflicting, with some authorities holding that the fetus is capable of feeling [[pain]] from the first [[trimester]],{{fact}} and others maintaining that the [[neuroanatomy|neuro-anatomical]] requirements for such experience do not exist until the second or third trimester.&lt;ref&gt; BBC News Article (2005). "[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/4180592.stm Foetuses 'no pain up to 29 weeks']." Retrieved [[2006-07-18]].&lt;/ref&gt;  

Pain receptors begin to appear in the seventh week of pregnancy. The [[thalamus]], the part of the brain which receives signals from the [[nervous system]] and then relays them to the [[cerebral cortex]], starts to form in the fifth week. However, other anatomical structures involved in the [[pain|nociceptic]] process are not present until much later in [[gestation]]. Links between the thalamus and cerebral cortex aren't forged until around the 23rd week.&lt;ref&gt;Parliamentary Office of Science and Technology. (1997). ''[http://www.parliament.uk/post/pn094.pdf Fetal Awareness].'' Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt;  There has been some suggestion that a fetus cannot feel pain at all, as it requires mental development that only occurs outside the womb.&lt;ref&gt;BBC News Article (2006). "[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/4905892.stm Foetuses 'cannot experience pain']." Retrieved [[2006-07-18]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Researchers have observed changes in the heart rates and [[hormones|hormonal levels]] of newborn [[infants]] after [[circumcision]], [[blood tests]], and surgery — effects which were alleviated with the administration of [[anesthesia]].&lt;ref&gt;Anand, K., Phil, D., &amp; Hickey, P.R. (1987). Pain and its effects on the human neonate and fetus. ''New England Journal of Medicine, 316 (21),'' 1321-9. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]] from [http://www.cirp.org/library/pain/anand/ The Circumcision Reference Library].&lt;/ref&gt;  Others suggest that the human experience of pain, being more than just [[physiology|physiological]], cannot be measured in such [[reflexive]] responses. &lt;ref&gt;Lee, Susan J., Ralston, Henry J. Peter, Drey, Eleanor A., Partridge, John Colin, &amp; Rosen, Mark A. (2005). [http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/short/294/8/947 Fetal Pain: A Systematic Multidisciplinary Review of the Evidence]. ''Journal of the American Medical Association, 294 (8)'', 947-954. Retrieved November 10, 2006. &lt;/ref&gt;

====Mental health====

[[Data]] on the incidence of disorders such as [[clinical depression]], [[substance abuse]], [[post-traumatic stress disorder]], [[anxiety]] and [[suicide]] in association with abortion remain inconclusive.

Some studies have shown abortion to have neutral or positive effects on the mental well-being of some patients.  A 1989 study of [[teenager]]s who sought [[pregnancy test]]s found that, counting from the beginning of pregnancy until two years later, the level of [[stress]] and [[anxiety]] of those who had an abortion did not differ from that of those who had not been pregnant at all or who had carried their pregnancy to term.&lt;ref&gt;Zabin, L.S., Hirsch, M.B., Emerson, M.R. (1989). [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=2620716&amp;dopt=Abstract When urban adolescents choose abortion: effects on education, psychological status and subsequent pregnancy]. ''Family Planning Perspectives, 21 (6),'' 248-55. Retrieved September 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Another study in 1992 suggested a link between elective abortion and later reports of positive [[self-esteem]]; it also noted that adverse emotional reactions to the procedure are most strongly influenced by pre-existing [[psychology|psychological]] conditions and other negative factors.&lt;ref name="russo"&gt;Russo, N. F., &amp; Zierk, K.L. (1992). [http://content.apa.org/journals/pro/23/4/269 Abortion, childbearing, and women]. ''Professional Psychology: Research and Practice, 23(4),'' 269-280. Retrieved September 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;Abortion, as compared to completion, of an undesired [[Gravidity|first pregnancy]] was not found to directly pose the risk of significant depression in a 2005 study.&lt;ref&gt;Schmiege, S. &amp; Russo, N.F. (2005). Depression and unwanted first pregnancy: longitudinal cohort study [http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/331/7528/1303 Electronic version] . ''British Medical Journal, 331 (7528),'' 1303. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Other studies have shown a correlation between abortion and negative psychological impact.  A 1996 study found that suicide is more common after a miscarriage and especially after an induced abortion than in the general population.&lt;ref&gt;Gissler, M., Hemminki, E., &amp; Lonnqvist, J. (1996). Suicides after pregnancy in Finland, 1987-94: register linkage study [http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/313/7070/1431 Electronic version]. ''British Medical Journal, 313,'' 1431-4. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt; 
Additional research in 2002 reported that the risk of clinical depression was higher for women who chose to have an abortion in comparison to those who opted to carry to term — even if the pregnancy was unwanted.&lt;ref&gt;Reardon, D.C. &amp; Cougle, J.R. (2002): Depression and unintended pregnancy in the National Longitudinal Survey of Youth: a cohort study. BMJ (British Medical Journal) 19.1.2002 324:151-2. [http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/324/7330/151?ijkey=6e69d766b00a6b5f6d244e90d4a8b9f9bcd165c5&amp;keytype2=tf_ipsecsha Electronic version.]&lt;/ref&gt; Another study in 2006, which used data gathered over a 25-year period, found an increased occurrence of depression, [[anxiety]], suicidal behavior, and [[substance abuse]] among women who had previously had an abortion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Fergusson D.M., Horwood L.J., &amp; Ridder E.M.|title=Abortion in young women and subsequent mental health|journal=Journal of Child Psychology &amp; Psychiatry|year=2006|volume=47|issue=1|page=16-24|id=PMID 16405636}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The existence of [[post-abortion syndrome]] (PAS), an independent set of mental symptoms associated with abortion that would warrant a general diagnosis or classification as an independent [[syndrome]], is currently considered a possibility by a tiny minority of the medical establishment. &lt;ref name="gomez"&gt; Gomez, Lavin C., &amp; Zapata, Garcia R. (2005).  
- [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=15999304&amp;dopt=Abstract "Diagnostic categorization of post-abortion syndrome"]. ''Actas Esp Psiquiatr, 33 (4),'' 267-72. Retrieved Setepmber 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Psychopathology|psychopathological]] symptoms attributed to [[post-abortion syndrome]] are similar to those of [[post-traumatic stress disorder]], but have also included, "repeated and persistent [[dream]]s and [[nightmare]]s related with the abortion, intense feelings of [[guilt]] and the 'need to repair'. &lt;ref name="gomez" /&gt; PAS is listed in neither the [[DSM-IV-TR]] nor the [[ICD|ICD-10]].

[[Miscarriage]], or spontaneous abortion, is known to present an increased risk of [[Clinical depression|depression]] in women.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.chmeds.ac.nz/research/chds/view1.pdf Depression Risk Increased After Miscarriage].'' ([[2002-04-01]]). Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Childbirth]] can also sometimes result in [[maternity blues]] or [[postpartum depression]].

==History of abortion==
[[Image:FrenchPeriodicalPills-January61845,BostonDailyTimes.jpg|thumb|right|140px|"French Periodical Pills." An example of a clandestine advertisement published in an 1845 edition of the ''Boston Daily Times''.]]
{{main|History of abortion}}
The practice of induced abortion, according to some [[anthropologists]], can be traced to ancient times. There is evidence to suggest that, historically, pregnancies were terminated through a number of methods, including the administration of [[abortifacient]] herbs, the use of sharpened implements, the application of abdominal pressure, and other techniques.

The [[Hippocratic Oath]], the chief statement of [[medical ethics]] in [[Ancient Greece]], expressly forbids all doctors from assisting in the procurement of an abortion by [[pessary]].  Nonetheless, [[Soranus]], a second-century Greek [[physician]], suggested in his work ''[[Gynecology]]'' that women wishing to abort their pregnancies should engage in violent exercise, energetic jumping, carrying heavy objects, and riding animals. He also prescribed a number of recipes for herbal baths, pessaries, and [[bloodletting]], but advised against the use of sharp instruments to induce miscarriage due to the risk of organ [[perforation]].&lt;ref&gt;Lefkowitz, Mary R. &amp; Fant, Maureen R. (1992). ''[http://www.stoa.org/diotima/anthology/wlgr/ Women's life in Greece &amp; Rome: a source book in translation].'' Baltimore, MD: John Hopkins University Press. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt;  It is also believed that, in addition to using it as a [[contraceptive]], the ancient Greeks relied upon [[silphium]] as an [[abortifacient]].  Such folk remedies, however, varied in effectiveness and were not without risk. [[Tansy]] and [[pennyroyal]], for example, are two [[poison|poisonous]] [[herbs]] with serious [[Adverse effect (medicine)|side effects]] that have at times been used to terminate pregnancy.

Abortion in the 19th century continued, despite bans in both the [[United Kingdom]] and the [[United States]], as the disguised, but nonetheless open, advertisement of services in the [[Victorian era]] suggests.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://users.telerama.com/~jdehullu/abortion/abhist.htm Histories of Abortion].'' (n.d.) Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social issues==

A number of complex issues exist in the debate over abortion. These, like the suggested effects upon health listed above, are a focus of research and a fixture of discussion among members on all sides of the controversy.

===Effect upon crime rate===
{{Main|Legalized abortion and crime effect}}

A controversial theory attempts to draw a [[correlation]] between the unprecedented nationwide decline of the overall [[crime rate]] witnessed in the [[United States]] during the 1990s and the decriminalization of abortion 20 years prior.

The suggestion was brought to widespread attention by a 1999 [[academic paper]], ''[[The Impact of Legalized Abortion on Crime]]'', authored by the [[economist]]s [[Steven Levitt|Steven D. Levitt]] and John Donohue. They attributed the drop in crime to a reduction in individuals said to have a higher statistical probability of committing crimes: unwanted children, especially those born to mothers who are [[African-American]], [[poverty|impoverished]], [[teenage pregnancy|adolescent]], [[education|uneducated]], and [[single parent|single]]. The change coincided with what would have been the adolescence, or peak years of potential criminality, of those who had not been born as a result of ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'' and similar cases. Donohue and Levitt's study also noted that states which legalized abortion before the rest of the nation experienced the lowering crime rate pattern earlier and that those with higher abortion rates had more pronounced reductions.&lt;ref&gt;Donohue, John J. and Levitt, Steven D. (2001). [http://ssrn.com/abstract=174508 The impact of legalized abortion on crime].''Quarterly Journal of Economics'' Retrieved [[2006-02-11]]. &lt;/ref&gt;  

Fellow economists Christopher Foote and Christopher Goetz criticized the [[methodology]] in the Donohue-Levitt study, noting a lack of accommodation for statewide yearly variations such as [[cocaine]] use, and recalculating based on incidence of crime [[per capita]]; they found no [[statistically significant]] results.&lt;ref&gt;Foote, Christopher L. and Goetz, Christopher F. (2005). [http://www.bos.frb.org/economic/wp/wp2005/wp0515.pdf Testing economic hypotheses with state-level data: a comment on Donohue and Levitt (2001)]. ''Working Papers, 05-15''. Retrieved [[2006-02-11]].&lt;/ref&gt;  Levitt and Donohue responded to this by presenting an adjusted [[data set]] which took into account these concerns and reported that the data maintained the statistical significance of their initial paper.&lt;ref&gt;Donohue, John J. and Levitt, Steven D. (2006). Measurement error, legalized abortion, and the decline in crime: a response to Foote and Goetz (2005). Retrieved [[2006-02-17]], from University of Chicago, Initiative on Chicago Price Theory web site: [http://pricetheory.uchicago.edu/levitt/Papers/ResponseToFooteGoetz2006.pdf http://pricetheory.uchicago.edu/levitt/Papers/ResponseToFooteGoetz2006.pdf].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Such research has been criticized by some as being [[utilitarian]], [[discrimination|discriminatory]] as to [[race]] and [[social class|socioeconomic class]], and as promoting [[eugenic]]s as a solution to [[crime]].&lt;ref&gt;"Crime-Abortion Study Continues to Draw Pro-life Backlash." ([[1999-08-11]]). ''The Pro-Life Infonet.'' Retrieved [[2006-02-17]] from [http://ohioroundtable.org/library/articles/life/crimeabortion.html Ohio Roundtable Online Library].&lt;/ref&gt;  &lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.americancatholic.org/Messenger/Jan2000/Editorial.asp Abortion and the Lower Crime Rate]." (2000, January). ''St. Anthony Messenger.'' Retrieved [[2006-02-17]].&lt;/ref&gt; Levitt states in his book, ''[[Freakonomics]]'', that they are neither promoting nor negating any course of action &amp;mdash; merely reporting data as economists.

===Sex-selective abortion===
{{Main|Sex-selective abortion and infanticide}}

The advent of both [[ultrasound]] and [[amniocentesis]] has allowed [[parent]]s to determine [[sex]] before [[childbirth|birth]]. This has led to the occurrence of [[sex-selective abortion and infanticide|sex-selective abortion]] or the targeted termination of a [[fetus]] based upon its sex.

It is suggested that sex-selective abortion might be partially responsible for the noticeable disparities between the [[birth rate]]s of [[male]] and [[female]] children in some places. The preference for male children is reported in many areas of [[Asia]], and the use of abortion to limit female births has been reported in [[Mainland China]], [[Republic of China|Taiwan]], [[South Korea]], and [[India]].&lt;ref&gt;Banister, Judith. ([[1999-03-16]]). [http://www.census.gov/ipc/www/ebspr96a.html Son Preference in Asia - Report of a Symposium]. Retrieved [[2006-01-12]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

In [[India]], the [[economic]] role of [[men]], the costs associated with [[dowry|dowries]], and a [[Hindu]] tradition which dictates that [[funeral|funeral rites]] must be performed by a male relative have led to a [[culture|cultural]] preference for [[son]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Mutharayappa, Rangamuthia, Kim Choe, Minja, Arnold, Fred, &amp; Roy, T.K. (1997). [http://www2.eastwestcenter.org/pop/misc/subj-3.pdf Son Preferences and Its Effect on Fertility in India]. ''National Family Health Survey Subject Reports, Number 3.'' Retrieved [[2006-01-12]].&lt;/ref&gt;   The widespread availability of diagnostic testing, during the 1970s and '80s, lead to advertisements for services which read, "Invest 500 [[rupee]]s [for a sex test] now, save 50,000 rupees [for a dowry] later." &lt;ref&gt;Patel, Rita. (1996). The practice of sex selective abortion in India: may you be the mother of a hundred sons. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]], from University of North Carolina, University Center for International Studies web site: [http://www.ucis.unc.edu/resources/pubs/carolina/abortion.pdf http://www.ucis.unc.edu/resources/pubs/carolina/abortion.pdf].&lt;/ref&gt; In 1991, the male-to-female [[sex ratio]] in India was skewed from its biological norm of 105 to 100, to an average of 108 to 100.&lt;ref&gt;Sudha, S., &amp; Irudaya Rajan, S. (1999). [http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/organizations/healthnet/gender/docs/sudha.html Female Demographic Disadvantage in India 1981-1991: Sex Selective Abortion, Female Infanticide and Excess Female Child Mortality]. Retrieved [[2006-01-12]] &lt;/ref&gt;  Researchers have asserted that between 1985 and 2005 as many as 10 million female fetuses may have been selectively aborted.&lt;ref&gt;Reaney, Patricia. ([[2006-01-09]]). "[http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L06779563.htm Selective abortion blamed for India's missing girls]." ''Reuters AlertNet.'' Retrieved [[2006-01-09]].&lt;/ref&gt;  The Indian government passed an official ban of pre-natal sex screening in 1994 and moved to pass a complete ban of sex-selective abortion in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;Mudur, Ganapati. (2002). "[http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/abridged/324/7334/385/b India plans new legislation to prevent sex selection]." ''British Medical Journal: News Roundup.'' Retrieved [[2006-01-12]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the [[People's Republic of China]], there is also a historic son preference. The implementation of the [[one-child policy]] in 1979, in response to population concerns, led to an increased disparity in the sex ratio as parents attempted to circumvent the law through sex-selective abortion or the abandonment of unwanted [[daughter]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Graham, Maureen J., Larsen, Ulla, &amp; Xu, Xiping. (1998). [http://www.agi-usa.org/pubs/journals/2407298.html Son Preference in Anhui Province, China]. ''International Family Planning Perspectives, 24 (2).'' Retrieved [[2006-01-12]].&lt;/ref&gt;  Sex-selective abortion might be a part of what is behind the shift from the baseline male-to-female birth rate to an elevated national rate of 117:100 reported in 2002.  The trend was more pronounced in rural regions: as high as 130:100 in [[Guangdong]] and 135:100 in [[Hainan]].&lt;ref&gt;Plafker, Ted. ([[2002-05-25]]). [http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/324/7348/1233/a?maxtoshow=&amp;HITS=10&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=&amp;fulltext Sex selection in China sees 117 boys born for every 100 girls]. ''British Medical Journal: News Roundup.'' Retrieved [[2006-01-12]].&lt;/ref&gt;  A ban upon the practice of sex-selective abortion was enacted in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.china.org.cn/english/2003/Mar/59194.htm China Bans Sex-selection Abortion]." ([[2002-03-22]]). ''Xinhua News Agency.'' Retrieved [[2006-01-12]].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Unsafe abortion===
[[Image:RussianAbortionPoster.jpg|thumb|240px|right|[[Soviet Union|Soviet]] [[Propaganda|poster]] circa 1925. Title translation: "Abortions performed by either trained or self-taught midwives not only maim the woman, they also often lead to death."]]
{{main|Unsafe abortion}}
Where and when access to safe abortion has been barred, due to explicit sanctions or general unavailability, women seeking to terminate their pregnancies have sometimes resorted to unsafe methods.

"[[Back-alley abortion]]" is a [[slang]] term for any abortion not practiced under generally accepted standards of [[sanitation]] and [[professional|professionalism]]. The [[World Health Organization]] defines an unsafe abortion as being, "a procedure...carried out by persons lacking the necessary skills or in an environment that does not conform to minimal medical standards, or both." &lt;ref name="whounsafe" /&gt; This can include a person without medical training, a professional health provider operating in sub-standard conditions, or the woman herself. 

Unsafe abortion remains a [[public health]] concern today due to the higher incidence and severity of its associated complications, such as incomplete abortion, [[sepsis]], [[hemorrhage]], and damage to internal organs. WHO estimates that 19 million unsafe abortions occur around the world annually and that 68,000 of these result in the death of the woman. &lt;ref name="whounsafe" /&gt; Complications of unsafe abortion are said to account, globally, for approximately 13% of all [[maternal death|maternal mortalities]], with regional estimates including 12% in [[Asia]], 25% in [[Latin America]], and 13% in [[sub-Saharan Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;Salter, C., Johnson, H.B., and Hengen, N. (1997). [http://www.infoforhealth.org/pr/l10edsum.shtml Care for postabortion complications: saving women's lives]. ''Population Reports, 25 (1).'' Retrieved [[2006-02-22]].&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Health education]], access to [[family planning]], and improvements in [[health care]] during and after abortion have been proposed to address this phenomenon.&lt;ref&gt;World Health Organization. (1998). [http://www.who.int/docstore/world-health-day/en/pages1998/whd98_10.html Address Unsafe Abortion]. Retrieved [[2006-03-01]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Abortion debate==
[[Image:March.jpg|thumb|right|240px||Pro-choice activists before the [[Washington Monument]] at the [[March for Women's Lives]].]]
[[Image:Pro-life protest.jpg|thumb|right|240px||Pro-life activists at the [[March for Life]] in 2002. The rally is held annually in [[Washington, DC]].]]
{{main|Abortion debate}}
Over the course of the [[history of abortion]], induced abortion has been the source of considerable [[debate]], [[controversy]], and [[activism]]. An [[opinion|individual's position]] on the complex [[ethical]], [[moral]], [[philosophical]], [[Biology|biological]], and [[legal]] issues is often related to his or her [[value system]]. Opinions of abortion may be best described as being a combination of beliefs on its morality, and beliefs on the responsibility, ethical scope, and proper extent of [[government]]al [[authority|authorities]] in [[public policy]].  [[religion|Religious ethics]] also has an influence upon both personal opinion and the greater debate over abortion (see [[religion and abortion]]).

Abortion debates, especially pertaining to [[abortion law]]s, are often spearheaded by [[advocacy|advocacy groups]] belonging to one of two camps. Most often those in favor of legal prohibition of abortion describe themselves as [[pro-life]] while those against legal restrictions on abortion describe themselves as [[pro-choice]].  Both are used to indicate the central principles in arguments for and against abortion:  "Is the fetus a human being with a fundamental right to ''life''?" for pro-life advocates, and, for those who are pro-choice, "Does a woman have the right to ''choose'' whether or not to have an abortion?"

In both public and private debate, arguments presented in favor of or against abortion focus on either the moral permissibility of an induced abortion, or justification of [[laws]] permitting or restricting abortion. Arguments on morality and legality tend to collide and combine, complicating the issue at hand.

Debate also focuses on whether the [[pregnancy|pregnant]] woman should have to notify and/or have the [[consent]] of others in distinct cases: a [[minor (law)|minor]] her parents; a [[marriage|legally-married]] or [[common-law marriage|common-law]] wife her husband; or a pregnant woman the biological father.  In a 2003 [[Gallup]] poll in the [[United States]], 72% of respondents were in favor of spousal notification, with 26% opposed; of those polled, 79% of males and 67% of females responded in favor.&lt;ref&gt;The Pew Research Center for the People and the Press. ([[2005-11-02]]). "[http://people-press.org/commentary/display.php3?AnalysisID=122 Public Opinion Supports Alito on Spousal Notification Even as It Favors Roe v. Wade]." ''Pew Research Center Pollwatch.'' Retrieved [[2006-03-01]].&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Public opinion===
Political sides have largely been divided into [[moral absolutism|absolutes]]. The abortion debate, as such, tends to center on individuals who hold strong positions. However, [[public opinion]] varies from poll to poll, country to country, and region to region:

*'''Australia''': In a February [[2005]] [[ACNielsen]] poll, as reported in [[The Age]], 56% thought the [[Abortion in Australia|current abortion laws]], which generally allow abortion for the sake of life or health, were "about right," 16% want changes in law to make abortion "more accessible," and 17% want changes to make it "less accessible." &lt;ref&gt;Grattan, Michelle. ([[2005-02-16]]). "[http://www.theage.com.au/news/National/Poll-backs-abortion-laws/2005/02/15/1108230007300.html Poll backs abortion laws]." ''The Age.'' Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt; A 1998 poll, conducted by Roy Morgan Research, asked, "Do you approve of the termination of unwanted pregnancies through surgical abortion?" 65% of the [[Australia|Australians]] polled stated that they approved of surgical abortion and 25% stated that they disapproved of it.&lt;ref&gt;Roy Morgan International. ([[1998-03-03]]). [http://www.roymorgan.com/news/polls/1998/3058 Almost Two-Thirds Of Australians Approve Of Abortion]. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt; 
* '''Canada''': A recent poll of [[Canada|Canadians]], conducted in April 2005 by [[Gallup poll|Gallup]], found that  52% of those polled want abortion laws to "remain the same," 20% want the laws to be "less strict," and 24% would prefer that the laws become "more strict." An earlier Gallup poll, from December 2001, asked, "Do you think abortions should be legal under any circumstances, legal only under certain circumstances or illegal in all circumstances and in what circumstances?" 32% of Canadians responded that they believe abortion should be legal in all circumstances, 52% that it should be legal in certain circumstances, and 14% that it should be legal in no circumstances. Canada currently has no laws restricting abortion. See [[Abortion in Canada]].
*'''Ireland''': A 1997 [[Irish Times]]/MRBI poll of the [[Republic of Ireland]]'s electorate found that 18% believe that abortion should never be permitted, 35% that one should be allowed in the event that the woman's life is threatened, 14% if her health is at risk, 28% that "an abortion should be provided to those who need it," and 5% were undecided.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, Geraldine. ([[1997-12-11]]). "[http://www.ireland.com/newspaper/front/1997/1211/archive.97121100003.html 77% say limited abortion right should be provided]." ''The Irish Times.'' Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt; 
* '''United Kingdom''': An online [[YouGov]]/[[Daily Telegraph]] poll in August 2005 found that 30% of [[United Kingdom|Britons]] would back a measure to reduce the legal limit for abortion to 20 weeks, 19% support a limit of 12 weeks, 9% support a limit of less than 12 weeks, and 25% support maintaining the current limit of 24 weeks. 6% responded that abortion should never be allowed while 2% said it should be permitted throughout the entirety of pregnancy.&lt;ref&gt;YouGov. ([[2005-07-30]]). [http://www.yougov.com/archives/pdf/TEL050101042_1.pdf YouGov/Daily Telegraph Survey Results]. Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt; 
* '''United States''': In a January 2006 [[CBS News]] poll, which asked, "What is your personal feeling about abortion?", 27% said that abortion should be "permitted in all cases," 15% that it should be "permitted, but subject to greater restrictions than it is now," 33% said that it should be "permitted only in cases such as rape, incest or to save the woman's life," 17% said that it should "only be permitted to save the woman's life," and 5% said that it should "never" be permitted.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.pollingreport.com/abortion.htm The Polling Report].'' (2006). Retrieved [[2006-01-11]].&lt;/ref&gt;  An April 2006 [[Harris Interactive|Harris]] poll on ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'', asked, "Do you favor or oppose the part of ''Roe v. Wade'' that made abortions up to three months of pregnancy legal?", to which 49% of respondents indicated favor while 47% indicated opposition.&lt;ref&gt; Harris Interactive. ([[2006-05-04]]). "[http://online.wsj.com/public/resources/documents/info-harris0503.html U.S. Attitudes Toward Roe v. Wade]." ''The Wall Street Journal.''  Retrieved [[2006-05-05]].&lt;/ref&gt;  One U.S. [[Gallup]]/[[CNN]]/[[USA Today]] poll conducted in 2003 yielded results very similar to an identical survey conducted in 1975.&lt;ref&gt; "[http://www.publicagenda.org/issues/pcc_detail.cfm?issue_type=abortion&amp;list=2 Views on abortion have not changed significantly since the 1970s]." (2006). ''Public Agenda Online.'' Retrieved [[2006-07-24]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Abortion law==
{{main|Abortion law}}
[[Image:AbortionLawsMap.png|thumb|240px|right|International status of abortion law ([[:Image:AbortionLawsMap.png|Detail]])]]
[[Image:Signing_the_Partial-Birth_Abortion_ban.jpg|thumb|240px|right|[[United States President]] [[George W. Bush]] signs the ''[[Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act]] of 2003'']]

Before the scientific discovery that human development began at fertilization, British common law allowed abortions to be performed before quickening, the earliest perception of fetal movement by a woman during the second trimester of pregnancy.  In 1861, the [[British Parliament]] passed the [[Offences Against The Person Act 1861|Offences Against the Person Act]], which put the [[common law]] offence of abortion into statute throughout the [[British Empire]]. The [[Soviet Union]], with legislation in 1920, and [[Iceland]] with legislation in 1935 were some of the first countries to generally allow abortion. The second half of the 20th century saw the liberalization of abortion laws in other countries. The [[Abortion Act 1967]] allowed abortion for limited reasons in the United Kingdom. In the 1973 case, ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'', the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] struck down state laws banning abortion in the first trimester, ruling that such laws violated an implied [[right to privacy]] in the [[United States Constitution]].  The [[Supreme Court of Canada]], similarly, in the case of ''[[R. v. Morgentaler]]'', discarded its criminal code regarding abortion in 1988, after ruling that such restrictions violated the security of person guaranteed to women under the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]].  Canada later struck down provincial regulations of abortion in the case of ''[[R. v. Morgentaler (1993)]].''  [[Abortion in Ireland]], on the other hand has been affected by the addition  of an [[Eighth Amendment of the Constitution of Ireland|amendment]] to its [[Constitution of Ireland|Constitution]] in 1983 by popular [[referendum]], recognizing "the right to life of the unborn".

Current laws pertaining to abortion are diverse. Religious, moral, and cultural sensibilities continue to influence abortion laws throughout the world. The [[right to life]], the right to [[liberty]], and the right to [[security of person]] are major issues of [[human rights]] that are sometimes used as justification for the existence or the absence of laws controlling abortion. Many countries in which abortion is legal require that certain criteria be met in order for an abortion to be obtained, often, but not always, using a [[trimester]]-based system to regulate the window in which abortion is still legal to perform:

* In the United States, some states impose a 24-hour waiting period before the procedure, prescribe the distribution of information on [[fetal development]], or require that parents be contacted if their [[Minor (law)|minor]] daughter requests an abortion.
* In the United Kingdom, as in some other countries, two doctors must first certify that an abortion is medically or socially necessary before it can be performed.
Other countries, in which abortion is normally illegal, will allow one to be performed in the case of [[rape]], [[incest]], or danger to the pregnant woman's life or health. A handful of nations ban abortion entirely: [[Abortion in Chile|Chile]], [[El Salvador]], [[Malta]], and [[Abortion in Nicaragua|Nicaragua]], although the [[Politics of Chile|Chilean government]] freely distributes the [[emergency contraception|"morning-after" pill]]. In [[Bangladesh]], abortion is illegal, but the government has long supported a network of "menstrual regulation clinics," where [[menstrual extraction]] ([[manual vacuum aspiration]]) can be performed as menstrual hygiene. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Surgical Abortion: History and Overview|publisher=National Abortion Federation|accessdate=2006-09-04|url=http://www.prochoice.org/education/resources/surg_history_overview.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{|width=100%
|-valign=top
|width=50%|
*[[:Category:Abortion by country|Abortion by country]]
*[[Abortion fund]]
*[[Contraception]]
*[[Fetal rights]]
*[[Ethical aspects of abortion]]
*[[Fertilisation]]
*[[Gynaecology]]
*[[Late-term abortion]]
*[[Libertarian perspectives on abortion]]
|width=50%|
*[[Obstetrics]]
*[[Paternal rights and abortion]]
*[[Pregnancy]]
*[[Religion and abortion]]
*[[Reproduction (disambiguation)|Reproduction]]
*[[Selective reduction]]
*[[Self-induced abortion]]
*[[Teenage pregnancy]]
*[[Violence in the abortion movement]]
|}

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
{{sisterlinks|abortion}}

*[http://annualreview.law.harvard.edu/population/abortion/abortionlaws.htm Abortion Laws of the World]
*[http://www.un.org/esa/population/publications/abortion Abortion Policies: A Global Review]
*"[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/twenty/watch/abortion.html Abortion Clinic]:" a 1983 PBS ''Frontline'' episode.
*[http://www.abortion.com/ Abortion.com]: online directory of U.S. abortion providers.
*[http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002912.htm#Definition U.S. National Library of Medicine and National Institutes of Health MedlinePlus encyclopedia]
*[http://www.religioustolerance.org/abortion.htm Abortion: All sides to the issue] from the [[Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance]]
*[http://www.publicagenda.org/issues/frontdoor.cfm?issue_type=abortion Issue Guide on Abortion] from Public Agenda Online
&lt;!-- HELP KEEP THIS ARTICLE SHORT AND SIMPLE: DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO EITHER "NON-NEUTRAL" SECTION. ADD THEM TO WHICHEVER SUB-ARTICLE WOULD BE APPROPRIATE INSTEAD. ALSO, PLEASE UNDERSTAND THAT SITES CONTAINING SHOCK MATERIAL SHALL, IN NO CASE, BE ACCEPTED. THANKS! !--&gt; 

'''The following information resources may be created by those with a non-neutral position in the abortion debate:'''
*[http://www.guttmacher.org/ The Guttmacher Institute]
*[http://justfacts.com/abortion.htm Just Facts: Abortion]
*[http://www.johnstonsarchive.net/policy/abortion Johnston's Archive: Abortion Statistics and Other Data]

'''The following links are to groups which advocate a specific position:'''

*[http://www.childrenbychoice.org.au Children by Choice] (Australia, pro-choice)
*[http://www.rtlaust.com Right to Life Australia] (pro-life)
*[http://www.caral.ca Canadians for Choice] (pro-choice)
*[http://www.lifecanada.org LifeCanada] (pro-life)
*[http://www.alranz.org Abortion Law Reform Association of New Zealand] (pro-choice)
*[http://www.voiceforlife.org.nz Voice for Life] (New Zealand, pro-life)
*[http://www.abortionrights.org.uk Abortion Rights] (United Kingdom, pro-choice)
*[http://www.lifeuk.org LifeUK] (United Kingdom, pro-life)
*[http://www.all.org American Life League] (pro-life)
*[http://www.naral.org NARAL Pro-choice America] (pro-choice)
*[http://www.care-net.org CareNet] (international, pro-life)
*[http://www.plannedparenthood.com Planned Parenthood] (international, pro-choice)

{{BirthControl}}

[[Category:Abortion| ]]
[[Category:Biological reproduction]]
[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]
[[Category:Gynecology]]
[[Category:Pregnancy]]
[[Category:Obstetrics]]
[[ar:إجهاض]]
[[bn:গর্ভপাত]]
[[bg:Аборт]]
[[ca:Avortament]]
[[cs:Interrupce]]
[[da:Provokeret abort]]
[[de:Schwangerschaftsabbruch]]
[[es:Aborto]]
[[eo:Aborto]]
[[fr:Avortement]]
[[id:Gugur kandungan]]
[[ia:Aborto]]
[[it:Interruzione volontaria di gravidanza]]
[[he:הפלה מלאכותית]]
[[lt:Abortas]]
[[hu:Terhességmegszakítás]]
[[mk:Абортус]]
[[nl:Abortus]]
[[ja:妊娠中絶]]
[[no:Abort]]
[[nn:Abort]]
[[pam:Abortion]]
[[pl:Aborcja]]
[[pt:Interrupção da gravidez]]
[[ro:Avort]]
[[ru:Аборт]]
[[simple:Abortion]]
[[sk:Potrat]]
[[sr:Абортус]]
[[sh:Abortus]]
[[fi:Abortti]]
[[sv:Abort]]
[[tl:Pagpapalaglag]]
[[th:การแท้ง]]
[[tr:Kürtaj]]
[[uk:Аборт]]
[[yi:אבארטאציע]]
[[zh:堕胎]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>