<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041110213217|7310643" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33183" pageid="33183" ns="0" title="Woman"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-10T21:34:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Human-woman.png|frame|right|&lt;small&gt;''Image of Woman on the [[Pioneer plaque]] sent to outer space&lt;/small&gt;'']]
A '''woman''' is an [[adult]] [[female]] [[human|human being]], as contrasted to an adult [[male]], which is a [[man]]. The term woman (irregular plural: women) is used to indicate biological sex distinctions, cultural gender role distinctions, or both. [[Womanhood]] is the period in a female's life after she has transitioned from a girl.

A '''girl''' is a [[female]] [[human]] [[child]], as contrasted to a male child, which is a [[boy]]. The term girl is used to indicate biological sex distinctions, cultural gender role distinctions, or both. After they mature, they become known as a woman with various colloquial exceptions, for example the word is also commonly used when discussing adult females in relationships, such as in the word [[girlfriend]].

== Sex ==
In terms of [[sex]], women have various sexual characteristics that differentiate them from [[man|men]]. In women, the [[sex organ]]s are involved in the reproductive system, whereas the [[secondary sex characteristics]] are involved in attracting a mate or nurturing children.

Although fewer females than males are born (the ratio is around 1:1.05), women make up the majority of the adult population. This is because males of all ages have a slightly higher death rate (even in the [[womb]]) and women live, on average, five years longer than men. This is thought to be a result of a combination of factors: [[genetics]] (redundant and varied [[gene]]s present on [[sex chromosome]]s in women); [[sociology]] (such as [[military service]]); [[health]]-impacting choices (such as use of [[cigarette]]s and [[alcohol]]); the presence of the female hormone [[estrogen]], which has a cardioprotective effect in premenopausal women, and the effect of high levels of [[androgen]]s in men.

After the onset of [[menarche]], most women are able to become [[pregnant]] and [[childbirth|bear children]]. The study of female reproduction and [[sex organ|reproductive organ]]s is called [[gynecology]]. Women generally reach [[menopause]] in their late 40s or early 50s, at which point they can no longer become pregnant.

In general, women suffer from the same illnesses as men; however there are some [[sex-related illness]]es that are found more commonly or exclusively in women.

Biological factors are usually not the sole determinants of whether a person is considered, or considers themselves a woman or not, some women can have an abnormal hormonal or chromosomal difference (such as [[congenital adrenal hyperplasia]]), or other [[intersex]] conditions; and some people born with standard male anatomies self-identify as women. (See the [[gender identity]] article.)

== Gender roles ==
''Main article: [[gender role]]''

Gender roles of women have changed greatly in history. Traditional gender roles for women would involve work tasks that are centered around home maintenance, a central role in caring for a family, and did not involve entering employment for an independent salary. Later, throughout the general [[feminism|feminist]] movement, these gender roles changed. These changes include many women were able to choose between this traditional, so called "[[homemaker]]" role in certain countries, or could enter into employment for an independent salary; labour related to home and family was divided amongst both adults in the home.

Study including the gender roles of women, and how they have changed over history, and the [[feminism]] movement is often termed  "[[women's studies]]".

== Terms for women ==

While the usual definition of the word ''girl'' is "female [[child]]", ''girl'' is also often used to refer to a young or unmarried woman. Since the early [[1970s]] such usage has been challenged by feminists. Today, using the word in the workplace (as in ''office girl'') is typically considered [[non-sexist language|inappropriate]] in the [[United States]] because it implies a view of woman as infantile but remains commonplace in several other English-speaking countries.

Conversely, in certain non-Western cultures, the word ''girl'' is still generally used to refer to a never-married woman in [[English language|English]]; in this sense it is used in a fashion roughly analogous to the obsolete English ''maid'' or ''maiden.''  Referring to an unmarried female as ''woman'' can, in such a culture, imply that she is sexually experienced, which would be considered insulting.

In more colloquial settings, the use of ''girl'' to refer to an adult female is also common practice in certain usage (such as ''girls' night out''). In this sense, ''girl'' may be considered to be the analogue to ''guy'' or ''bloke'' for a man (the latter being rare in U.S. English). Usages that are non-parallel, such as ''men and girls,'' are regarded by many as sexist.

In the popular culture of the [[20th century|20th]] and [[21st century]], several unofficial [[slang]] terms have appeared in the [[English language|English]] language to describe women. Some such terms are relatively neutral:

* ''chick'': coming from the [[Spanish]] word "chica/s" for a girl
* ''hottie'': a physically attractive woman
* ''[[sister]]'': a term which women, most often in the [[African American]] community, use when addressing each other. The same term is also used within some strands of [[feminism]], and also in the [[transsexual]] community in referring to other transsexual women.

Many people consider other terms to range from mildly to extremely offensive: ''[[bitch]]'', ''[[cunt]]'', and variations on [[prostitute]] (''ho'', ''hooker'', ''whore'', etc.).

== See also ==
* [[Famous women in history]]
* [[Female roles in the world wars]]
* [[Gender and sexuality studies]]
* [[Girl Scouts of the USA|Girl Scouts of America]]
* [[Heroines in literature]]
* [[List of women poets]]
* [[Matriarchy]]
* [[Misogyny]]
* [[New Woman]]
* [[Nü shu]], the women-only language
* [[Obstetrics]]
* [[Olympic medalists in athletics (women)]]
* [[Role of women in Judaism]]
* [[Taliban treatment of women]]
* [[White slavery|White slave trade]]
* [[Women in science fiction]]
* [[Women science fiction authors]]

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
*[http://www.fembio.org/default.shtml FemBio - Notable Women International]

[[Category:Human]]

[[ca:Dona]]
[[da:Kvinde]]
[[de:Frau]]
[[es:Mujer]]
[[fr:Femme]]
[[nl:Vrouw]]
[[ja:&amp;#22899;&amp;#24615;]]
[[nds:Fru]]
[[pl:Kobieta]]
[[ru:&amp;#1046;&amp;#1077;&amp;#1085;&amp;#1097;&amp;#1080;&amp;#1085;&amp;#1072;]]
[[fi:Nainen]]
[[sv:Kvinna]]
[[tokipona:meli]]
[[zh:&amp;#22899;&amp;#24615;]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>