<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051111215306|28060116" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33183" pageid="33183" ns="0" title="Woman"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T21:55:14Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Human-woman.png|frame|right|Image of a '''woman''' on the [[Pioneer plaque]] sent to outer space.]]
A '''woman''' is an [[adult]] [[female]] [[human|human being]], as contrasted with a [[man]] (an adult [[male]]), and a [[girl]], (a female child). The term ''woman'' (irregular plural: ''women'') is used to indicate [[biological sex]] distinctions, [[cultural]] [[gender role]] distinctions, or both.

==Etymology==
The [[English language|English]] term "man" (from [[Proto-Germanic]] ''[[mannaz]]'' "man, person") and words derived therefrom can designate any or even all of the human race regardless of their gender or age. This is indeed the oldest usage of "man". In [[Old English language|Old English]] the words [[wer]] and [[wyf]] (also [[wæpman]] and [[wifman]]) were what was used to refer to "a man" and "a woman" respectively, and "man" was gender neutral. In [[Middle English]] man displaced wer as term for "male human", whilst wyfman (which eventually evolved into woman) was retained for "female human". Man does continue to carry its original sense of "[[Human]]" however, resulting in an [[asymmetry]] sometimes criticized as sexist. [http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=man] (see also [[Womyn]]).

[[Image:Symbol_venus.png|thumb|110px|left|Symbol of the planet Venus]] The symbol for the planet [[Venus]] is the sign also known in biology for the female sex: a stylized representation of the goddess Venus's hand [[mirror]]: a circle with a small cross underneath ([[Unicode]]: &amp;#x2640;). The Venus symbol also represented [[femininity]], and in ancient alchemy stood for [[copper]]. Alchemists constructed the symbol from a circle (representing [[spirit]]) above a cross (representing [[matter]]).

== Biology and sex ==
Biological factors are not the sole determinants of whether persons are considered, or consider themselves, women. Some women can have abnormal hormonal or chromosomal differences (such as [[congenital adrenal hyperplasia]], complete or partial [[androgen insensitivity syndrome]] or other [[intersex]] conditions), and there are women who may be without, at least for an earlier part of their lives, typical female physiology (''trans'', [[transgender]]ed or [[transsexual]] women). (See [[gender identity]].)

In terms of [[biology]], the female [[sex organ]]s are involved in the reproductive system, whereas the [[secondary sex characteristics]] are involved in nurturing children or attracting a mate. Most non-transsexual women have the [[karyotype]] 46,XX, but around one in a thousand will be 47,XXX and one in 2500 will be [[Turner syndrome|45,X]].

[[Image:Bouguereau venus detail.jpg|thumb|right|Detail from [[Bouguereau]]'s [[The Birth of Venus]]]]
[[Image:Female anatomy frontal.png|left|frame|The human female [[reproductive system]]]]
Although fewer females than males are born (the ratio is around 1:1.05), women are more common in the adult population (about a 1.04:1 ratio). Women have a lower death rate than men, even in the [[uterus]], living on average five years longer due to a combination of factors: [[genetics]] (redundant and varied [[gene]]s present on [[sex chromosome]]s in women); [[sociology]] (such as not being expected in most countries to perform [[military service]]); [[health]]-impacting choices (such as [[suicide]] or the use of [[cigarette]]s and [[alcohol]]); the presence of the female hormone [[estrogen]], which has a cardioprotective effect in premenopausal women; and the effect of high levels of [[androgen]]s in men. Out of the total population there are 101.3 men for every 100 women (source: 2001 World Almanac). 

After the onset of [[menarche]], most women are able to become [[pregnant]] and [[childbirth|bear children]]. The study of female reproduction and [[sex organ|reproductive organ]]s is called [[gynaecology]]. Women generally reach [[menopause]] in their late 40s or early 50s, at which point their [[ovaries]] cease producing [[estrogen]] and they can no longer become pregnant.

In general, women suffer from the same illnesses as men; however there are some [[sex-related illness]]es that are found more commonly or exclusively in women.

==Legal rights of women historically==

See article [[Legal rights of women]].

Some early [[Law|legal]] systems that are the antecedents of modern systems formalized female dependency.

===Mosaic law===
In the [[Mosaic law]], [[divorce]] was a privilege of the husband only: the vow of a woman might be disallowed by her father or husband, and daughters could [[inherit]] only in the absence of sons (and then they were required to marry within their tribe). The guilt or innocence of a wife accused of adultery might be tried by the ordeal of the bitter water. Besides these instances, which illustrate the subordination of women (2 Deut. xxiv. 1. Numb. xxx. 3-Numb. xxvii., xxxvi. Numb. v. II.), there was much legislation dealing with, ''[[inter alia]]'', offences against [[chastity]], and marriage of a man with a captive heathen woman or with a purchased [[slave]]. Far from second marriages being restricted, as they were by [[Christian]] legislation, it was the duty of a childless widow to marry her deceased husband's brother.

== Culture and gender roles ==
[[Image:Weaving_profile.jpg|thumb|300px|left|A [[Bangladesh]]i woman weaving. [[Textile]] work has historically been considered a female occupation in some cultures.]]
''Main article: [[gender role]]''

From [[prehistory]], women, like men, have assumed a particular cultural role. In [[hunter-gatherer]] societies, women have almost always been the gatherers of plant foods, while men have hunted meat. Because of their intimate knowledge of plant life, most [[Anthropology|anthropologists]] argue that it was women who led the [[Neolithic Revolution]] and became history's first pioneers of [[agriculture]]. &lt;!--This needs to be sourced.--&gt; 

In more recent history, the gender roles of women have changed greatly. Traditional gender roles for [[middle class|middle-class]] women typically involved domestic tasks emphasizing child care, and did not involve entering employment for wages. For poorer women, especially among the [[working class]]es, this often remained an ideal, for economic necessity has long compelled them to seek employment outside the home, although the occupations traditionally open to working-class women were lower in prestige and pay than those open to men. Eventually, restricting women from wage labor came to be a mark of wealth and prestige in a family, while the presence of working women came to mark a household as being lower-class. 

The women's movement is in part a struggle for the recognition of [[equality of opportunity]] with men, and for [[equal rights]] irrespective of [[sex]], even if special relations and conditions are willingly incurred under the form of partnership involved in marriage. The difficulties of obtaining this recognition are due to historical factors combined with the habits and customs history has produced. Through a combination of [[economics|economic]] changes and the efforts of the [[feminism|feminist]] movement in recent decades, however, women in most societies now have access to careers beyond the traditional one of "[[homemaker]]".  

These changes are among the foci of the [[academic]] field of [[women's studies]].
&lt;br clear="all"&gt;

==Terms==
The [[English language]]'s original word for "woman" was [[Old English language|Old English]] ''w&amp;#299;f'', akin to German ''Weib''; it later became the modern word "wife." The modern word "woman" [[etymological]]ly derives from ''w&amp;#299;fmann'', with the addition of ''mann'', "person", from Germanic ''[[mannaz]]''. This formation is peculiar to English. The equivalents for "man" in Old English were ''wer'' (a cognate of Latin ''vir'', "man") and ''w&amp;#x1e3;pnedmann'', literally "weaponed person". As previously mentioned, the term ''man'' continues to carry its original sense of "[[Human]]", though this usage results in an asymmetry which is sometimes criticized as sexist.
&lt;!-- merge this with etymology? Or possible move Etymology into terms? 'Man' article needs to be changed for consistency --&gt;

The word ''girl'' originally meant "young person of either sex"; it was only around the beginning of the [[16th century]] that it came to mean specifically a ''female'' [[child]]. Nowadays ''girl'' is also often used colloquially to refer to a young or unmarried woman. Since the early [[1970s]], feminists have challenged such usage, and today, using the word in the workplace (as in ''office girl'') is typically considered [[Non-sexist language|inappropriate]] in the [[United States]] and [[United Kingdom]] because it implies a view of women as infantile. The use remains commonplace in several other [[English language|English-speaking]] countries. &lt;!--In which countries is "girl" not regarded as sexist when used is that way?--&gt;

Conversely, in certain non-Western cultures which link family [[honor]] with female [[virginity]], the word ''girl'' is still used to refer to a never-married woman; in this sense it is used in a fashion roughly analogous to the obsolete English ''maid'' or ''maiden''. Referring to an unmarried female as ''woman'' can, in such a culture, imply that she is sexually experienced, which would be an insult to her family.

In more informal settings, the use of ''girl'' to refer to an adult female is also common practice in certain usage (such as ''girls' night out''), even among elderly women. In this sense, ''girl'' may be considered to be the analogue to the British word ''bloke'' for a man. &lt;!--Removed guy, which can also be used to mean women.--&gt; Some regard non-parallel usages, such as ''men and girls,'' as  [[political correctness|offensive]].

There are various words used to refer to the quality of being a woman.  The term "womanhood" merely means the state of being a woman; "femininity" is used to refer to a set of supposedly typical female qualities associated with a certain attitude to [[gender role]]s; "womanliness" is like "femininity", but is usually associated with a different view of gender r&amp;ocirc;les; "femaleness" is a general term, but is often used as shorthand for "human femaleness"; "distaff" is an archaic adjective derived from women's conventional r&amp;ocirc;le as a spinner, now used only as a deliberate [[archaism]];  "[[muliebrity]]" is a neologism meant to provide a female counterpart of "[[virility]]", but used very loosely, sometimes to mean merely "womanhood", sometimes "femininity", and sometimes even as a collective term for women.

===Slang===
[[Image:Zanzibar woman.jpg|thumb|200px|right|[[Zanzibar]] woman, c. 1890]]
There are also many [[slang]] terms to refer to women; these have existed throughout history, and change over time.  Some of those common in contemporary usage are:

*''[[Babe]]'': A more [[appelative]]-like way to address a woman. More commonly said to a partner, in a similar way to "honey".
*''[[Bird (disambiguation)|Bird]]'': outdated British English, most women see it as demeaning. Also commonly used in modern Ireland where it is not considered very demeaning.
*''[[Bitch]]'': originally, and still widely used as, a pejorative term, this is used more casually in some communities in the U.K. (and in the U.S., in [[ebonics]] [McWhorter 2003], and even affectionately, especially between women [McWhorter 2005]).
*''Chick'': literally a young chicken or young bird of any kind, this term is mildly offensive to some women who interpret it to be infantilizing or objectifying; it is chiefly an Americanism. It is sometimes claimed that the usage derives from the [[Spanish language|Spanish]] ''chica'' (girl), but neither the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' nor ''[[Merriam-Webster]]'' supports this derivation. The word ''chick'' was used in a gender-neutral sense to mean "human child" at least as early as the [[14th century]]. The popularity of the usage in [[North America]] may, nonetheless, be due in part to its similarity to the Spanish word.
*''[[Hen]]'': [[Scotland|Scottish]] term used to address women.  It is also used in the term "[[hen party]]".
*''[[Sister]]'': a term which women rarely use when addressing each other; it is associated with, although by no means exclusive to, [[African American]] idiom. The same term is used within [[feminism]], and among [[transwomen]] communities.
*''[[Sheila]]'': used in Australia, becoming outdated in favour of more American terminologies.
Several older terms used by men, such as ''broad'' or ''skirt'', are now archaic, and rarely encountered.

Authors often create new euphemisms or other terms to refer to women, an example being the use of the word ''[[hamburger|burger]]'' on the [[United States|American]] [[television]] [[sitcom]] ''[[The Cosby Show]]'' to refer to an attractive female.

===Vulgar terms===
In some cultural groups, terms considered extremely offensive to most women (e.g., ''[[bitch]]'', ''[[cunt]]'', or ''[[ho]]'') are used to refer to women in general.  Many terms that refer to women's physical appearance (e.g., ''hottie'', a sexually attractive woman) see wide use, but many consider them to imply [[sexual objectification]], although many heterosexual women use ''hunk'' to describe an equivalent man.

== See also ==
* [[Famous women in history]]
* [[Female roles in the World Wars]]
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Gender and sexuality studies]]
* [[Gynaecology]]
* [[Heroines in literature]]
* [[Matriarchy]]
* [[Misogyny]]
* [[New Woman]]
* [[Obstetrics]]
* [[Women in science fiction]]
* [[Women's cinema]]

==References==
*''Roget&amp;#8217;s II: The New Thesaurus'', (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 2003 3rd edition) ISBN 0618254145 
*[http://www.powells.com/review/2002_01_31.html McWhorter, John. 'The Uses of Ugliness', ''The New Republic Online'', January 31, 2002] Retrieved [[May 11]] [[2005]] ["bitch" as an affectionate term]
*McWhorter, John. ''Authentically Black: Essays for the Black Silent Majority'' (New York: Gotham, 2003) ISBN 1592400019 [casual use of "bitch" in ebonics]

== External links ==
{{Commons|Woman}}
{{Commons2|Women}}
{{Wikiquote|Women}}
{{Wiktionary|woman}}
* [http://www.fembio.org/default.shtml FemBio - Notable Women International]
*[http://www.newsonwomen.com/ NewsOnWomen]

[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Women| ]]
[[Category: Gender]]

[[af:Vrou]]
[[zh-min-nan:Cha-bó·]]
[[bn:নারী]]
[[ca:Dona]]
[[cs:Žena]]
[[da:Kvinde]]
[[de:Frau]]
[[es:Mujer]]
[[eo:Virino]]
[[fr:Femme]]
[[ga:Bean]]
[[hi:औरत]]
[[it:Donna]]
[[he:אישה]]
[[ms:Perempuan]]
[[nl:Vrouw]]
[[nds:Fru]]
[[ja:女性]]
[[pl:Kobieta]]
[[pt:Mulher]]
[[ru:Женщина]]
[[scn:Fimmina]]
[[simple:Woman]]
[[sl:Ženska]]
[[sr:Жене]]
[[fi:Nainen]]
[[sv:Kvinna]]
[[zh:女性]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>