<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151008043313|684688231" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33183" pageid="33183" ns="0" title="Woman"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-10-08T04:35:32Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|adult human females}}
{{Redirect2|Womanhood|Women|the Tammy Wynette song|Womanhood (song)|other uses|Women (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Infobox
|title   = Woman
|image   = [[File:Woman Montage (1).jpg|300px]]
|caption = Left to right from top: {{flatlist|
* the&amp;nbsp;[[Queen of Sheba]]
* [[Venus (mythology)|Venus]]
* [[Joan of Arc]]
* [[Eva Perón]]
* [[Marie Curie]]
* [[Indira Gandhi]]
* [[Venus of Willendorf]]
* [[Wangari Maathai]]
* [[Mother Teresa]]
* [[Grace Hopper]]
* Mamechiho,&amp;nbsp;a&amp;nbsp;[[geisha]]
* a&amp;nbsp;[[Tibet]]an farmer
* [[Marilyn Monroe]]
* [[Oprah Winfrey]]
* [[Aung San Suu Kyi]]
* [[Josephine Baker]]
* [[Isis]]
* [[Laverne Cox]]
* [[Elizabeth I of England|Elizabeth I]]
* a&amp;nbsp;[[Quechua people|Quechua]] mother
}}}}
{{Women in society sidebar}}
{{Feminism sidebar}}
{{Feminist philosophy sidebar}}

A '''woman''' is a [[female]] [[human]].&lt;!--The word adult is not needed in this sentence; see the following sentence.--&gt; The term ''woman'' is usually reserved for an [[adult]], with the term [[girl]] being the usual term for a female [[child]] or [[Adolescence|adolescent]]. However, the term ''woman'' is also sometimes used to identify a female human, regardless of age, as in phrases such as "[[women's rights]]". "Woman" may also refer to a person's [[gender identity]] instead of their [[sex]]. {{Citation needed|date=September 2015}} Women are typically capable of giving [[birth]] from [[puberty]] until [[menopause]], although some sterile, [[intersex]] and/or [[transgender]] women cannot. Throughout history women have assumed or been assigned various social roles.

==Etymology==
The spelling of woman in English has progressed over the past millennium from ''wīfmann''&lt;ref&gt;"wīfmann": Bosworth &amp; Toller, ''Anglo-Saxon Dictionary'' (Oxford, 1898-1921) p. 1219. The spelling "wifman" also occurs: C. T. Onions, ''[[Oxford Dictionary of English Etymology]]'' (Oxford, 1966) p. 1011&lt;/ref&gt; to ''wīmmann'' to ''wumman'', and finally, the modern spelling ''woman''.&lt;ref&gt;''Webster's New World Dictionary, Second College Edition'', entry for "woman".&lt;/ref&gt;  In [[Old English]], ''wīfmann'' meant "female human", whereas ''wēr'' meant "male human". ''Mann'' or ''monn'' had a gender-neutral meaning of "human", corresponding to Modern English "person" or "someone"; however, subsequent to the [[Norman Conquest]], ''man'' began to be used more in reference to "male human", and by the late 13th century had begun to eclipse usage of the older term ''wēr''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=man man] - definition Dictionary.reference.com&lt;/ref&gt; The medial labial consonants f and m in ''wīfmann'' coalesced into the modern form "woman", while the initial element, which meant "female", underwent semantic narrowing to the sense of a married woman ("wife"). It is a popular misconception that the term "woman" is etymologically connected with "womb", which is from a separate Old English word, ''wambe'' meaning "stomach" (of male or female; modern German retains the colloquial term "Wampe" from Middle High German for "potbelly").&lt;ref&gt;[http://starling.rinet.ru/cgi-bin/response.cgi?single=1&amp;basename=/data/ie/germet&amp;text_number=%20562 Germanic Etymology]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dict.cc/?s=wampe dict.cc, DT-EN, entry: Wampe]&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, such a false derivation of "woman" has appeared in print.&lt;ref&gt;e.g. [http://www.sacred-texts.com/wmn/wb/wb04.htm ''The Woman's Bible'', By Elizabeth Cady Stanton and the Revising Committee, 1898]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Biological symbol===
The symbol for the planet [[Venus]] is the sign also used in biology for the female sex. It is a stylized representation of the goddess Venus's hand-[[mirror]] or an abstract symbol for the goddess: a circle with a small equilateral cross underneath. The Venus symbol also represented [[femininity]], and in ancient alchemy stood for [[copper]]. Alchemists constructed the symbol from a circle (representing [[spirit]]) above an equilateral cross (representing [[matter]]).

==Terminology==
{{Further|girl|virgin|mother|wife|goodwife|lady|maid|maiden|widow|}}
'''Womanhood''' is the period in a female's life after she has passed through childhood and adolescence, generally around the age 18.

The word ''woman'' can be used generally, to mean any female human or specifically, to mean an adult female human as contrasted with ''girl''. The word ''girl'' originally meant "young person of either sex" in English;&lt;ref&gt;Used in Middle English from c. 1300, meaning ‘a child of either sex, a young person’.  Its derivation is uncertain, perhaps from an Old English word which has not survived: another theory is that it developed from Old English ‘gyrela’, meaning ‘dress, apparel’: or was a diminutive form of a borrowing from another West Germanic Language. (Middle Low German has Gör, Göre, meaning ‘girl or small child’.)  "girl, n.". OED Online. September 2013. Oxford University Press. 13 September 2013&lt;/ref&gt; it was only around the beginning of the 16th century that it came to mean specifically a ''female'' [[child]].&lt;ref&gt;By late 14th century a distinction was arising between female children, often called  ‘gay girls’ – and male, or ‘knave girls’ -: a1375   William of Palerne  (1867) l. 816  ‘ Whan þe gaye gerles were in-to þe gardin come, Faire floures þei founde.’ (‘When the gay girls came into the garden, Fair flowers they found.’) By the 16th century the unsupported word had begun to mean specifically a female:  1546   J. Heywood Dialogue Prouerbes Eng. Tongue i. x. sig. D,   ‘The boy thy husbande, and thou the gyrle his wyfe.’  The usage meaning ‘child of either sex’ survived much longer in [[Hiberno-English|Irish English]]. "girl, n.". OED Online. September 2013. Oxford University Press. 13 September 2013&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''girl'' is sometimes  used colloquially to refer to a young or unmarried woman, however during the early 1970s feminists challenged such use because the use of the word to refer to a fully grown woman may cause offence. In particular, previously common terms such as ''office girl'' are no longer widely used. Conversely, in certain cultures which link family [[honor]] with female [[virginity]], the word ''girl'' is still used to refer to a never-married woman; in this sense it is used in a fashion roughly analogous to the obsolete English ''maid'' or ''maiden''. Referring to an unmarried female human as a ''woman'' may, in such a culture, imply that she is sexually experienced, which would be an insult to her family.{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

There are various words used to refer to the quality of being a woman. The term "womanhood" merely means the state of being a woman, having passed the [[menarche]]; "femininity" is used to refer to a set of typical female qualities associated with a certain attitude to [[gender role]]s; "womanliness" is like "femininity", but is usually associated with a different view of gender roles; "femaleness" is a general term, but is often used as shorthand for "human femaleness"; "distaff" is an archaic adjective derived from women's conventional role as a spinner, now used only as a deliberate [[archaism]]; "muliebrity" is a [[neologism]] (derived from the Latin) meant to provide a female counterpart of "[[virility]]", but used very loosely, sometimes to mean merely "womanhood", sometimes "femininity" and sometimes even as a collective term for women.{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

Menarche, the onset of [[menstruation]], occurs on average at age 12-13. Many cultures have [[rites of passage]] to symbolize a girl's [[coming of age]], such as confirmation in some branches of [[Christianity]],{{citation needed|date=April 2015}} [[bat mitzvah]] in [[Judaism]], or even just the custom of a special celebration for a certain [[birthday]] (generally between 12 and 21), like the [[Quinceañera]] of Latin America.

==History==
The earliest women whose names are known through archaeology include:
* [[Neithhotep]] (c. 3200 BCE), the wife of [[Narmer]] and the first queen of ancient Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;Aidan Dodson &amp; Dyan Hilton (2004). ''The Complete Royal Families of Ancient Egypt''. Thames &amp; Hudson. ISBN 0-500-05128-3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J. Tyldesley, ''Chronicle of the Queens of Egypt'', 2006, Thames &amp; Hudson.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Merneith]] (c. 3000 BCE), [[Queen consort|consort]] and regent of ancient Egypt during the [[First Dynasty of Egypt|first dynasty]]. She may have been ruler of Egypt in her own right.&lt;ref name="books.google.co.uk"&gt;{{Cite book |author=Wilkinson, Toby A.H. |authorlink=Toby Wilkinson |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AR1ZZO6niVIC&amp;pg=PA74&amp;dq=merneith+wife+daughter&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=merneith%20wife%20daughter&amp;f=false |title=Early dynastic Egypt |publisher=Routledge |edition=1 |year=2001 |isbn=978-0-415-26011-4 |page=74}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aidan Dodson &amp; Dyan Hilton (2004). ''The Complete Royal Families of Ancient Egypt''. p. 140. Thames &amp; Hudson. ISBN 0-500-05128-3.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Merit-Ptah]] (c. 2700 BCE), also lived in Egypt and is the earliest known female physician and [[Women in science|scientist]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.astr.ua.edu/4000WS/MERIT_PTAH.html Merit-Ptah] at the University of Alabama.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Peseshet]] (c. 2600 BCE), a [[physician]] in [[Ancient Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;Plinio Prioreschi, ''A History of Medicine'', Horatius Press 1996, p. 334.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lois N. Magner, ''A History of Medicine'', Marcel Dekker 1992, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Puabi]] (c. 2600 BCE), or Shubad – queen of [[Ur]] whose tomb was discovered with many expensive artifacts. Other known pre-Sargonic queens of Ur (royal wives) include Ashusikildigir, Ninbanda, and Gansamannu.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Women, Crime, and Punishment in Ancient Law and Society: The ancient Near East |author=Elisabeth Meier Tetlow |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ONkJ_Rj1SS8C&amp;pg=PA221|publisher=[[Continuum International Publishing Group]] |isbn=978-0-8264-1628-5 |year=2004 |accessdate=29 July 2011|page=221}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Kubaba|Kugbau]] (''circa'' 2,500 BCE), a taverness from [[Kish (Sumer)|Kish]] chosen by the [[Nippur]] priesthood to become hegemonic ruler of [[Sumer]], and in later ages deified as "Kubaba"
* [[Tashlultum]] (c. 2400 BCE), [[Akkadian Empire|Akkad]]ian queen, wife of [[Sargon of Akkad]] and mother of Enheduanna.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Women, Crime, and Punishment in Ancient Law and Society: The ancient Near East |author=Elisabeth Meier Tetlow |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ONkJ_Rj1SS8C&amp;pg=PA245&amp;dq=Tashlultum#v=onepage&amp;q=Tashlultum&amp;f=false |publisher=[[Continuum International Publishing Group]] |isbn=978-0-8264-1628-5 |year=2004 |accessdate=29 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Mesopotamia and the ancient Near East |author=Michael Roaf |authorlink=Michael Roaf |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SapVAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=Tashlultum&amp;dq=Tashlultum |publisher=Stonehenge Press |isbn=978-0-86706-681-4 |year=1992 |accessdate=29 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Baranamtarra]] (c. 2384 BCE), prominent and influential queen of [[Lugalanda]] of [[Lagash]]. Other known pre-Sargonic queens of the first Lagash dynasty include Menbara-abzu, Ashume'eren, Ninkhilisug, Dimtur, and Shagshag, and the names of several princesses are also known.
* [[Enheduanna]] (c. 2285 BCE),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Samuel Kurinsky |title=Jewish Women Through The Ages - The Proto-Jewess En Hedu'Anna, Priestess, Poet, Scientist |url=http://www.hebrewhistory.info/factpapers/fp036_women.htm |publisher=Hebrew History Federation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Jennifer Bergman |title=Windows to the Universe |url=http://www.windows2universe.org/people/ancient_epoch/enhedu.html |publisher=[http://www.nestanet.org/cms/content/welcome National Earth Science Teachers Association] |date=19 July 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Ordination of women#Sumeria and Akkadia|high priestess]] of the temple of the [[Sin (mythology)|Moon God]] in the [[Sumer]]ian city-state of [[Ur]] and possibly the first poet and first named author of either gender.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Adovasio, J. M., Olga Soffer, &amp; Jake Page |title=The Invisible Sex: Uncovering the True Roles of Women in Prehistory |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MBFNkKKypdMC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Invisible+Sex:+Uncovering+the+True+Roles+of+Women+in+Prehistory#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |publisher=Smithsonian Books &amp; Collins (Harper Collins Publishers) |edition=1st Smithsonian Books |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-06-117091-1 |pages=278–279}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biology and gender==
[[Image:Scheme female reproductive system-en.svg|thumb|right|The [[human female reproductive system]]]]
[[Image:Sky spectral karyotype.png|right|thumb|[[Spectral karyotype]] of a human female]]
[[Image:Anterior view of human female and male, with labels.png|left|thumb|Photograph of an adult female human, with an adult male for comparison.  Note that both models have partially shaved body hair, and that [[transgender]] females and males may appear different than the models.|alt=Photograph of an adult female human, with an adult male for comparison.  Note that both models have partially shaved body hair.]]
In terms of [[biology]], the female [[sex organ]]s are involved in the reproductive system, whereas the [[secondary sex characteristic]]s are involved in nurturing children or, in some cultures, attracting a mate. The [[ovaries]], in addition to their regulatory function producing hormones, produce female gametes called [[ovum|eggs]] which, when [[fertilization|fertilized]] by male gametes ([[spermatozoon|sperm]]), form new genetic individuals. The [[uterus]] is an organ with tissue to protect and nurture the developing fetus and muscle to expel it when giving birth. The [[vagina]] is used in copulation and birthing, although the term [[vagina]] is often colloquially and incorrectly used in the English language for the [[vulva]] or external female genitalia, which consists of (in addition to the vagina) the [[labia (genitalia)|labia]], the [[clitoris]], and the female [[urethra]]. The [[breast]] evolved from the sweat gland to produce milk, a nutritious secretion that is the most distinctive characteristic of mammals, along with live [[birth]]. In mature women, the breast is generally more prominent than in most other mammals; this prominence, not necessary for milk production, is probably at least partially the result of [[sexual selection]]. (For other ways in which men commonly differ physically from women, see [[Man#Biology and gender|man]].){{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

During early fetal development, embryos of both sexes appear gender-neutral. As in cases without two sexes, such as species that [[Asexual reproduction|reproduce asexually]], the gender-neutral appearance is closer to female than to male. A fetus usually develops into a male if it is exposed to a significant amount of [[testosterone]] (typically because the fetus has a Y chromosome from the father). Otherwise, the fetus usually develops into a female, typically when the fetus has an X chromosome from the father, but also when the father contributed neither an X nor Y chromosome. Later at puberty, estrogen feminizes a young woman, giving her adult sexual characteristics.{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

An imbalance of maternal hormonal levels and some chemicals (or drugs) may alter the secondary sexual characteristics of fetuses. Most women have the [[karyotype]] 46,XX, but around one in a thousand will be [[47,XXX]], and one in 2500 will be [[Turner syndrome|45,X]]. This contrasts with the typical male karotype of 46,XY; thus, the [[x chromosome|X]] and [[Y chromosome]]s are known as female and male, respectively. Because humans inherit mitochondrial DNA only from the mother's ovum, genetic studies of the female line tend to focus on [[Human mitochondrial genetics|mitochondrial DNA]].{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

Whether or not a child is considered female does not always determine whether or not the child later will identify themselves that way (see [[gender identity]]). For instance, [[intersex]] individuals, who have mixed physical and/or genetic features, may use other criteria in making a clear determination. At birth, babies may be assigned a gender based on their genitalia. In some cases, even if a child had XX chromosomes, if they were born with a penis, they were raised as a male.&lt;ref name="Fausto-Sterling2000"&gt;{{cite book|last=Fausto-Sterling|first=Anne|title=Sexing the Body: Gender Politics and the Construction of Sexuality|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=c3lhYfZzIXkC|accessdate=2 July 2015|year=2000|publisher=Basic Books|isbn=978-0-465-07714-4|pages=44–77}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are also [[transgender]] and [[transsexual]] women, who were assigned as male at birth, but identify as women; there are varying social, legal, and individual definitions with regard to these issues (see [[trans woman]]).{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

[[File:11-stages-womanhood-1840s.jpg|thumb|left|"The Life &amp; Age of Woman - Stages of Woman's Life from the Cradle to the Grave",1849]]
Although fewer females than males are born (the ratio is around 1:1.05), due to a longer life expectancy there are only 81 men aged 60 or over for every 100 women of the same age. Women typically have a longer life expectancy than men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=why-is-life-expectancy-lo |title=Why is life expectancy longer for women than it is for men? |publisher=Scientific American |date=2004-08-30 |accessdate=2009-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is due to a combination of factors: [[genetics]] (redundant and varied [[gene]]s present on [[sex chromosome]]s in women); [[sociology]] (such as the fact that women are not expected in most modern nations to perform [[conscription|military service]]); [[health]]-impacting choices (such as [[suicide]] or the use of [[cigarette]]s, and [[alcoholic beverage|alcohol]]); the presence of the female hormone [[estrogen]], which has a cardioprotective effect in premenopausal women; and the effect of high levels of [[androgen]]s in men. Out of the total human population, there are 101.3 men for every 100 women (source: 2001 World Almanac).{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}
[[File:Lactancia bebe aire libre.jpg|upright=0.8|thumb|Woman nursing her infant]]
Girls' bodies undergo gradual changes during [[puberty]], analogous  to but distinct from those experienced by boys. Puberty is the process of physical changes by which a [[child]]'s [[Human body|body]] matures into an [[adult]] body capable of [[sexual reproduction]] to enable [[fertilisation]]. It is initiated by [[hormone|hormonal]] signals from the [[brain]] to the [[gonad]]s-either the ovaries or the [[Testicle|testes]]. In response to the signals, the gonads produce hormones that stimulate [[libido]] and the growth, function, and transformation of the [[brain]], [[bone]]s, [[muscle]], [[blood]], [[skin]], [[human hair growth|hair]], [[breast]]s, and [[sex organ|sexual organs]]. [[Human development (biology)|Physical growth]]—height and weight—accelerates in the first half of puberty and is completed when the child has developed an adult body. Until the maturation of their reproductive capabilities, the pre-pubertal, physical differences between boys and girls are the [[Human genitals|genitalia]], the [[human penis|penis]] and the [[vagina]]. Puberty is a process that usually takes place between the ages 10–16, but these ages differ from girl to girl. The major landmark of girls' puberty is [[menarche]], the onset of [[menstruation]], which occurs on average between ages 12–13.&lt;ref name="Tanner"&gt;(Tanner, 1990).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="U.S. menarche"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Anderson SE, Dallal GE, Must A |title=Relative weight and race influence average age at menarche: results from two nationally representative surveys of US girls studied 25 years apart |journal=Pediatrics |volume=111 |issue=4 Pt 1 |pages=844–50 |date=April 2003 |pmid=12671122 |doi=10.1542/peds.111.4.844}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Canadian menarche"&gt;{{cite journal|title=Age at menarche in Canada: results from the National Longitudinal Survey of Children &amp; Youth|publisher=BMC Public Health |year= 2010 |pmid=21110899 |doi=10.1186/1471-2458-10-736 |pmc=3001737 |volume=10 |author=Al-Sahab B, Ardern CI, Hamadeh MJ, Tamim H |journal=BMC Public Health |page=736}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="UK menarche"&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://vstudentworld.yolasite.com/resources/final_yr/gynae_obs/Hamilton%20Fairley%20Obstetrics%20and%20Gynaecology%20Lecture%20Notes%202%20Ed.pdf |title=Obstetrics and Gynaecology |first=Diana |last=Hamilton-Fairley |edition=Second|publisher=Blackwell Publishing }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most girls go through [[menarche]] and are then able to become [[pregnant]] and [[childbirth|bear children]].&lt;ref&gt;Menarche and [[menstruation]] are absent in many of the intersex and transgender conditions mentioned above and also in [[primary amenorrhea]].&lt;/ref&gt; This generally requires internal fertilization of her eggs with the sperm of a man through [[sexual intercourse]], though [[artificial insemination]] or the surgical implantation of an existing embryo is also possible (see [[reproductive technology]]). The study of female reproduction and [[sex organ|reproductive organ]]s is called [[gynaecology]].{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

==Health==
{{further|Women's health|Maternal death}}
[[File:Pregnancy 26 weeks 1.jpg|upright|thumb|Pregnant woman]]
Women's health refers to health issues specific to human female anatomy. There are some diseases that primarily affect women, such as [[lupus erythematosus|lupus]]. Also, there are some [[sex-related illness|gender-related illnesses]] that are found more frequently or exclusively in women, e.g., [[breast cancer]], [[cervical cancer]], or [[ovarian cancer]]. Women and men may have different symptoms of an illness and may also respond to medical treatment differently. This area of medical research is studied by [[gender-based medicine]].{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

The issue of women's health has been taken up by many [[feminists]], especially where [[reproductive health]] is concerned. Women's health is positioned within a wider body of knowledge cited by, amongst others, the [[World Health Organisation]], which places importance on gender as a social determinant of health.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.who.int/social_determinants&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Maternal mortality]] or maternal death is defined by [[WHO]] as "the death of a woman while pregnant or within 42 days of termination of pregnancy, irrespective of the duration and site of the pregnancy, from any cause related to or aggravated by the pregnancy or its management but not from accidental or incidental causes."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/healthinfo/statistics/indmaternalmortality/en/ |title=WHO &amp;#124; Maternal mortality ratio (per 100 000 live births) |publisher=Who.int |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; About 99% of maternal deaths occur in developing countries. More than half of them occur in [[sub-Saharan Africa]] and almost one third in [[South Asia]]. The main causes of maternal mortality are severe bleeding (mostly bleeding after childbirth), infections (usually after childbirth), [[pre-eclampsia]] and [[eclampsia]], unsafe abortion, and pregnancy complications from [[malaria]] and [[HIV/AIDS]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs348/en/ |title=WHO &amp;#124; Maternal mortality |publisher=Who.int |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most European countries, Australia, as well as Japan and Singapore are very safe in regard to childbirth, while Sub-Saharan countries are the most dangerous.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/rankorder/2223rank.html |title=The World Factbook |publisher=Cia.gov |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reproductive rights and freedom==
[[File:Sterilization states.jpg|300px|thumb|right|A poster from a 1921 [[eugenics]] conference displays the U.S. states that had implemented sterilization legislation.]]
[[Reproductive rights]] are [[legal right]]s and freedoms relating to [[human reproduction|reproduction]] and [[reproductive health]]. The [[International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics]] has stated that:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.figo.org/projects/reproductive_and_sexual_health |title=Resolution on Reproductive and Sexual Health &amp;#124; International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics |publisher=Figo.org |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:(...) the human rights of women include their right to have control over and decide freely and responsibly on matters related to their sexuality, including sexual and reproductive health, free of coercion, discrimination and violence. Equal relationships between women and men in matters of sexual relations and reproduction, including full respect for the integrity of the person, require mutual respect, consent and shared responsibility for sexual behavior and its consequences.

Violations of reproductive rights include [[forced pregnancy]], [[forced sterilization]] and [[forced abortion]].

Forced sterilization was practiced during the first half of the 20th century by many Western countries. Forced sterilization and forced abortion are reported to be currently practiced in countries such as [[Uzbekistan]] and China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17612550 | work=BBC News | title=Uzbekistan's policy of secretly sterilising women | date=12 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b01fjx63 |title=BBC Radio 4 - Crossing Continents, Forced Sterilisation in Uzbekistan |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2012-04-16 |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalpost.com/dispatch/news/regions/asia-pacific/china/130409/china-mother-dies-after-forced-sterilization-one-child-policy |title=China 'one-child' policy: Mother of 2 dies after forced sterilization |publisher=GlobalPost |date=2013-04-09 |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/thousands-risk-forced-sterilization-china-2010-04-22 |title=Thousands at risk of forced sterilization in China &amp;#124; Amnesty International |publisher=Amnesty.org |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-18435126 | work=BBC News | title=China forced abortion photo sparks outrage | date=14 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrnk.org/uploads/pdfs/HRNK_HiddenGulag2_Web_5-18.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

The lack of adequate laws on sexual violence combined with the lack of access to [[contraception]] and/or [[abortion]] are a cause of enforced pregnancy (see [[pregnancy from rape]]).{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

==Culture and gender roles==
{{Main|Gender role}}
[[Image:Weaving profile.jpg|thumb|A woman weaving. [[Textile]] work is traditionally and historically a female occupation in many cultures.]]

In many [[prehistory|prehistoric]] cultures, women assumed a particular cultural role. In [[hunter-gatherer]] societies, women were generally the gatherers of plant foods, small animal foods and fish, while men hunted meat from large animals.{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

In more recent history, gender roles have changed greatly. Originally, starting at a young age, aspirations occupationally are typically veered towards specific directions according to gender.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Sharpe|first1=S.|title=Just like a Girl|date=1976|publisher=Penguin|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traditionally, [[middle class]] women were involved in domestic tasks emphasizing child care. For poorer women, especially [[working class]] women, although this often remained an ideal,{{Specify|date=February 2007}} economic necessity compelled them to seek employment outside the home. Many of the occupations that were available to them were lower in pay than those available to men.{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

As changes in the labor market for women came about, availability of employment changed from only "dirty", long hour factory jobs to "cleaner", more respectable office jobs where more education was demanded, women's participation in the U.S. labor force rose from 6% in 1900 to 23% in 1923. These shifts in the labor force led to changes in the attitudes of women at work, allowing for the revolution which resulted in women becoming career and education oriented.{{citation needed|date=August 2014}}

[[File:WomanFactory1940s.jpg|thumb|During [[World War II]], some women performed roles which would otherwise have been considered male jobs by the culture of the time]]

In the 1970s, many female academics, including scientists, avoided having children. However, throughout the 1980s, institutions tried to equalize conditions for men and women in the workplace. However, the inequalities at home stumped women's opportunities to succeed as far as men. Professional women are still responsible for domestic labor and child care. As people would say, they have a "double burden" which does not allow then the time and energy to succeed in their careers. Furthermore, though there has been an increase in the endorsement of egalitarian gender roles in the home by both women and men, a recent research study showed that women focused on issues of morality, fairness, and well-being, while men focused on social conventions.&lt;ref&gt;Gere, J., &amp; Helwig, C. C. (2012). Young adults' attitudes and reasoning about gender oles in the family context. "Psychology of Women Quarterly, 36", 301-313. doi: [http://pwq.sagepub.com/ 10.1177/0361684312444272]&lt;/ref&gt; Until the early 20th century, U.S. women's colleges required their women faculty members to remain single, on the grounds that a woman could not carry on two full-time professions at once. According to Schiebinger, "Being a scientist and a wife and a mother is a burden in society that expects women more often than men to put family ahead of career." (pg. 93).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Schiebinger|first=Londa|title=Has Feminism Changed Science? : Science and Private Life|year=1999|publisher=Harvard University Press|location=Cambridge|pages=92–103}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Movements advocate [[equality of opportunity]] for both sexes and [[civil rights|equal rights]] irrespective of gender. Through a combination of [[economics|economic]] changes and the efforts of the [[feminism|feminist]] movement,{{Specify|date=May 2007}}&lt;!-- Which one? The one that occupies university departments, the movements advocating specific rights, like the Suffragettes, first wave feminism, second wave, the collection of people who identify themselves as feminists? Be clear, please. --&gt; in recent decades women in many societies now have access to careers beyond the traditional [[homemaker]]. &lt;!-- Despite these advances, modern women in Western society still face challenges in the workplace as well as with the topics of education, violence, health care, politics, and motherhood, and others. -- Clear this sentence of its vagueness before returning it to the article.--&gt; &lt;!-- [[Sexism]] can be a main concern and barrier for woman almost anywhere, though its forms, perception, and gravity varies between societies and social classes. -- This sentence can be read in so many ways there is no point in keeping it. Either make it clearer, or move the subject from general, hence vague, to specific and comprehensible. --&gt;

Although a greater number of women are seeking higher education, salaries are often less than those of men. CBS News claimed in 2005 that in the United States women who are ages 30 to 44 and  hold a university degree make 62 percent of what similarly qualified men do, a lower rate than in all but three of the 19 countries for which numbers are available. Some Western nations with greater inequity in pay are Germany, New Zealand and Switzerland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2005/09/13/national/main838207_page2.shtml?tag=contentMain;contentBody | work=CBS News | title=U.S. Education Slips In Rankings | date=13 September 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Violence against women===
{{main|Violence against women}}
[[File:Campaign road sign against female genital mutilation (cropped).jpg|thumb|A campaign against [[female genital mutilation]] – a road sign near [[Kapchorwa]], [[Uganda]].]]
[[File:Torturing and execution of witches in medieval miniature.jpg|thumb|Burning witches, with others held in Stocks]]
[[File:Chinese girl from one of the Japanese Army's 'comfort battalions'.jpg|thumb|[[Rangoon]], [[Myanmar|Burma]]. August 8, 1945. A young [[Chinese diaspora|ethnic Chinese]] woman who was in one of the [[Imperial Japanese Army]]'s "comfort battalions"  is interviewed by an [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] officer.]]
The [[United Nations|UN]] [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women]] defines "violence against women" as:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/48/a48r104.htm |title=A/RES/48/104. Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|any act of gender-based violence that results in, or is likely to result in, physical, sexual or mental harm or suffering to women, including threats of such acts, coercion or arbitrary deprivation of liberty, whether occurring in public or in private life.}}

and identifies three forms of such violence: that which occurs ''in the family'', that which occurs ''within the general community'', and that which is perpetrated or condoned ''by the State''. It also states that "''violence against women is a manifestation of historically unequal power relations between men and women''".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=United Nations General Assembly |url=http://www.un-documents.net/a48r104.htm |title=A/RES/48/104 - Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women - UN Documents: Gathering a body of global agreements |publisher=UN Documents |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Violence against women remains a widespread problem, fueled, especially outside the West, by patriarchal social values, lack of adequate laws, and lack of enforcement of existing laws. Social norms that exist in many parts of the world hinder progress towards protecting women from violence. For example, according to surveys by [[UNICEF]],  the percentage of women aged 15–49 who think that a husband is justified in hitting or beating his wife under certain circumstances is as high as 90% in [[Afghanistan]] and [[Jordan]], 87% in [[Mali]], 86% in [[Guinea]] and [[Timor-Leste]], 81% in [[Laos]], and 80% in the [[Central African Republic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.childinfo.org/attitudes_data.php |title=Statistics by Area - Attitudes towards wife-beating - Statistical table |publisher=Childinfo.org |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A  2010 survey conducted by the [[Pew Research Center]] found that [[stoning]] as a punishment for [[adultery]] was supported by 82% of respondents in [[Egypt]] and [[Pakistan]], 70% in [[Jordan]], 56% [[Nigeria]], 42% in [[Indonesia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pewglobal.org/2010/12/02/muslims-around-the-world-divided-on-hamas-and-hezbollah/ |title=Muslim Publics Divided on Hamas and Hezbollah &amp;#124; Pew Research Center's Global Attitudes Project |publisher=Pewglobal.org |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Specific forms of violence that affect women include [[female genital mutilation]], [[sex trafficking]], [[forced prostitution]], [[forced marriage]], [[rape]], [[sexual harassment]], [[honor killings]], [[acid throwing]], and [[dowry death|dowry related violence]]. Governments can be complicit in violence against women, for instance through practices such as [[stoning]] (as punishment for [[adultery]]).

There have also been many forms of violence against women which have been prevalent historically, notably the [[Witch-hunt|burning of witches]], the sacrifice of [[widows]] (such as [[Sati (practice)|sati]]) and [[foot binding]]. The prosecution of women accused of [[witchcraft]] has a long tradition, for example [[witch trials in the early modern period]] (between the 15th and 18th centuries) were common in Europe and in the European colonies in North America. Today, there remain regions of the world (such as parts of Sub-Saharan Africa, rural North India, and Papua New Guinea) where belief in witchcraft is held by many people, and women accused of being witches are subjected to serious violence.&lt;ref&gt;http://scholarship.law.duke.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1129&amp;context=djcil#H2N1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mrc.ac.za/crime/witchhunts.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-21363894 | work=BBC News | title=Woman burned alive for 'sorcery' in Papua New Guinea | date=7 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, there are also countries which have criminal legislation against the practice of witchcraft. In [[Saudi Arabia]], witchcraft remains a crime [[punishable by death]], and in 2011 the country beheaded a woman for 'witchcraft and sorcery'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amnesty.org/en/news/saudi-arabia-beheading-sorcery-shocking-2011-12-12 |title=Saudi Arabia: Beheading for 'sorcery' shocking &amp;#124; Amnesty International |publisher=Amnesty.org |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/12/13/world/meast/saudi-arabia-beheading/ | work=CNN | title=Saudi woman beheaded for 'witchcraft and sorcery' - CNN.com | date=14 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is also the case that certain forms of violence against women have been recognized as criminal offenses only during recent decades, and are not universally prohibited, in that many countries continue to allow them. This is especially the case with [[marital rape]].&lt;ref&gt;In 2006, the UN Secretary-General's ''In-depth study on all forms of violence against women'' found that (pg 113): "Marital rape may be prosecuted in at least 104 States. Of these, 32 have made marital rape a specific criminal offence, while the remaining 74 do not exempt marital rape from general rape provisions. Marital rape is not a prosecutable offence in at least 53 States. Four States criminalize marital rape only when the spouses are judicially separated. Four States are considering legislation that would allow marital rape to be prosecuted."[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/vaw/publications/English%20Study.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In [[England and Wales]], marital rape was made illegal in 1991. The views of Sir Matthew Hale, a 17th-century jurist, published in ''The History of the Pleas of the Crown (1736)'', stated that a husband cannot be guilty of the rape of his wife because the wife "''hath given up herself in this kind to her husband, which she cannot retract''"; in England and Wales this would remain law for more than 250 years, until it was abolished by the [[Appellate Committee of the House of Lords]], in the case of ''R v R'' in 1991.[http://www.bailii.org/uk/cases/UKHL/1991/12.html]&lt;/ref&gt; In the Western World, there has been a trend towards ensuring [[gender equality]] within [[marriage]] and prosecuting [[domestic violence]], but in many parts of the world women still lose significant legal rights when entering a marriage.&lt;ref&gt;For example, in [[Yemen]], marriage regulations state that a wife must obey her husband and must not leave home without his permission.[http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrc/docs/ngos/Yemen%27s%20darkside-discrimination_Yemen_HRC101.pdf] In [[Iraq]] husbands have a legal right to "punish" their wives. The criminal code states at Paragraph 41 that there is no crime if an act is committed while exercising a legal right; examples of legal rights include: "The punishment of a wife by her husband, the disciplining by parents and teachers of children under their authority within certain limits prescribed by law or by custom".[http://law.case.edu/saddamtrial/documents/Iraqi_Penal_Code_1969.pdf] In the [[Democratic Republic of Congo]] the Family Code states that the husband is the head of the household; the wife owes her obedience to her husband; a wife has to live with her husband wherever he chooses to live; and wives must have their husbands' authorization to bring a case in court or to initiate other legal proceedings.[http://www.hrw.org/reports/2002/drc/Congo0602-09.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

Sexual violence against women greatly increases during times of [[war]] and [[armed conflict]], during [[military occupation]], or [[ethnic conflict]]s; most often in the form of [[war rape]] and [[sexual slavery]]. Contemporary examples of sexual violence during war include [[rape during the Bangladesh Liberation War]], [[rape in the Bosnian War]], [[rape during the Rwandan Genocide]], and [[War rape#Democratic Republic of the Congo|rape during Second Congo War]]. In Colombia, the [[Colombian conflict (1964–present)|armed conflict]] has also resulted in increased sexual violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amnesty.org/en/news/colombian-authorities-fail-stop-or-punish-sexual-violence-against-women-2012-10-04 |title=Colombian authorities fail to stop or punish sexual violence against women &amp;#124; Amnesty International |publisher=Amnesty.org |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Laws and policies on violence against women vary by jurisdiction. In the [[European Union]], sexual harassment and human trafficking are subject to [[Directive (European Union)|directive]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Directive 2002/73/EC - equal treatment of 23 September 2002 amending Council Directive 76/207/EEC on the implementation of the principle of equal treatment for men and women as regards access to employment, vocational training and promotion, and working conditions [http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CONSLEG:1976L0207:20021005:EN:PDF]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;DIRECTIVE 2011/36/EU OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL of 5 April 2011 on preventing and combating trafficking in human beings and protecting its victims, and replacing Council Framework Decision 2002/629/JH      http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:101:0001:0011:EN:PDF&lt;/ref&gt;

==Clothing, fashion and dress codes==
{{Further|Fashion|Modesty|Hijab by country}}
[[File:Group of Women Wearing Burkas.jpg|right|thumb|Afghan women wearing [[burqa]]s. Some Muslim women wear [[hijab]]s and other types of clothing as a symbol of modesty and privacy.]]
Women in different parts of the world dress in different ways, with their choices of clothing being influenced by local culture, religious tenets traditions, social norms, and fashion trends, amongst other factors. Different societies have different ideas about [[modesty]]. However, in many jurisdictions, women's choices in regard to dress are not always free, with laws limiting what they may or may not wear. This is especially the case in regard to [[Islam and clothing|Islamic dress]]. While certain jurisdictions legally mandate such clothing (the wearing of the headscarf), other countries forbid or restrict the wearing of certain [[hijab]] attire (such as [[burqa]]/covering the face) in public places (one such country is [[France]] - see [[French ban on face covering]]). These laws are highly controversial.&lt;ref&gt;https://doc.es.amnesty.org/cgi-bin/ai/BRSCGI/WOMENS%20RIGHT%20TO%20CHOOSE%20THEIR%20DRESS%20FREE%20OF%20COERCION?CMD=VEROBJ&amp;MLKOB=29309215959&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fertility and family life==
{{Further|Mother}}
[[File:Countriesbyfertilityrate.svg|thumb|300px|A world map showing countries by total fertility rate (TFR), according to the [[The World Factbook|CIA World Factbook]]'s 2015 data.
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
{{legend|#AE23AE|7–8 Children}}
{{legend|#FF00FF|6–7 Children}}
{{legend|#FF0000|5–6 Children}}
{{legend|#FF6600|4–5 Children}}
{{col-break}}
{{legend|#FFFF00|3–4 Children}}
{{legend|#00FF00|2–3 Children}}
{{legend|#35B0E3|1–2 Children}}
{{legend|#3555E3|0–1 Children}}
{{col-end}}]]
[[File:Non marital by countries.gif|300px|thumb|left|Percentage of births to unmarried women, selected countries, 1980 and 2007.&lt;ref name="non_mar1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/databriefs/db18.htm|title=Changing Patterns of Nonmarital Childbearing in the United States |work=CDC/National Center for Health Statistics|date=May 13, 2009|accessdate=September 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The [[total fertility rate]] (TFR) - the average number of children born to a woman over her lifetime - differs significantly between different regions of the world. In 2013, the highest estimated TFR was in [[Niger]] (7.03 children born per woman) and the lowest in [[Singapore]] (0.79 children/woman).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/rankorder/2127rank.html |title=The World Factbook |publisher=Cia.gov |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; While most Sub-Saharan African countries have a high TFR, which creates problems due to lack of resources and contributes to [[overpopulation]], most Western countries currently experience a [[sub replacement fertility rate]] which may lead to  [[population ageing]] and [[population decline]].

In many parts of the world, there has been a change in family structure over the past few decades. For instance, in the West, there has been a trend of moving away from living arrangements that include the [[extended family]] to those which only consist of the [[nuclear family]]. There has also been a trend to move from marital fertility to non-marital fertility. Children born outside marriage may be born to [[cohabitation|cohabiting couples]] or to [[single parent|single women]]. While births outside marriage are common and fully accepted in some parts of the world, in other places they are highly stigmatized, with unmarried mothers facing ostracism, including violence from family members, and in extreme cases even [[honor killings]].&lt;ref&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20130501013343/http://www.mrt-rrt.gov.au/CMSPages/GetFile.aspx?guid=91cf943a-3fa6-4fce-afec-4ab2c2a356fd&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3523123.stm | work=BBC News | title=Turkey condemns 'honour killings' | date=1 March 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, [[sex outside marriage]] remains illegal in many countries (such as Saudi Arabia, Pakistan,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eyeontheun.org/voices.asp?p=632 |title=Human Rights Voices – Pakistan, August 21, 2008 |publisher=Eyeontheun.org }}&lt;/ref&gt; Afghanistan,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aidsportal.org/news_details.aspx?ID=4236 |title=Home |publisher=AIDSPortal }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="travel.state.gov"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://travel.state.gov/travel/cis_pa_tw/cis/cis_1142.html |title=Iran |publisher=Travel.state.gov }}&lt;/ref&gt; Iran,&lt;ref name="travel.state.gov"/&gt; Kuwait,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/0/2f5665ae20b956cb8025675a0033cafb?Opendocument |title=United Nations Human Rights Website – Treaty Bodies Database – Document – Summary Record – Kuwait |publisher=Unhchr.ch }}&lt;/ref&gt; Maldives,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.everyculture.com/Ja-Ma/Maldives.html |title=Culture of Maldives – history, people, clothing, women, beliefs, food, customs, family, social |publisher=Everyculture.com }}&lt;/ref&gt; Morocco,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Fakim |first=Nora |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-19049000 |title=BBC News – Morocco: Should pre-marital sex be legal? |publisher=BBC |date=9 August 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Oman,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.interpol.com/Public/Children/SexualAbuse/NationalLaws/csaOman.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071215043802/http://www.interpol.com/Public/Children/SexualAbuse/NationalLaws/csaOman.pdf |archivedate=15 December 2007 |title=Legislation of Interpol member states on sexual offences against children – Oman |publisher=Interpol }}&lt;/ref&gt; Mauritania,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/j/drl/rls/hrrpt/2010/af/154358.htm |title=2010 Human Rights Report: Mauritania |publisher=State.gov |date=8 April 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; United Arab Emirates,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Dubai FAQs |url=http://www.dubaifaqs.com/education-dubai.php |title=Education in Dubai |publisher=Dubaifaqs.com }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Judd |first=Terri |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/briton-faces-jail-for-sex-on-dubai-beach-863918.html |title=Briton faces jail for sex on Dubai beach – Middle East – World |work=The Independent |date=10 July 2008 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sudan,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2007/06/28/idUSL28849488._CH_.2400 |title=Sudan must rewrite rape laws to protect victims |agency=Reuters |date=28 June 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Yemen,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees |url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/docid/47387b712f.html/ |title=Refworld &amp;#124; Women's Rights in the Middle East and North Africa – Yemen |publisher=UNHCR }}&lt;/ref&gt;).

The social role of the [[mother]] differs between cultures. In many parts of the world, women with dependent children are expected to stay at home and dedicate all their energy to child raising, while in other places (mostly in Western countries) mothers most often return to paid work (see [[Working parent|working mother]] and [[Housewife|stay at home mother]]).&lt;!-- dummy edit --&gt;

==Religion==
{{Further|Women in Christianity|Women in Judaism|Women in Islam|Women in Mormonism|Women in Hinduism|Women in Sikhism|Women in Buddhism}}
Particular religious doctrines have specific stipulations relating to [[gender roles]], social and private interaction between the sexes, appropriate dressing attire for women, and various other issues affecting women and their position in society. In many countries, these religious teachings influence the [[criminal law]], or the [[family law]] of those jurisdictions. (see for example [[Sharia law]]). The relation between religion, law and gender equality has been discussed by international organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp/html/http%3Cspan%20class=%27pullme%27%3EIt%20has%20become%20increasingly%20clear%20that%20disasters%20are%20setting%20back%20efforts%20in%20development%20%E2%80%93%20they%20can%20cripple%20the%20economy,%20destroy%20infrastructure,%20and%20plunge%20more%20people%20into%20poverty%3C/span%3E://www.unisdr.org/www.sealthedeal2009.org/petition/html/story.asp?NewsID=46370&amp;Cr=religion&amp;Cr1=#.Ustsg_tpCKE |title=United Nations News Centre - Harmful practices against women and girls can never be justified by religion – UN expert |publisher=Un.org |date=2013-10-29 |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
{{Main|Female education}}
[[File:Bolivia la paz literacy LOC.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.8|Women attending an adult literacy class in the [[El Alto]] section of [[La Paz]], [[Bolivia]].]]
[[File:Paula Khan.jpg|thumb|upright=0.8|A female [[biologist]] weighs a desert [[tortoise]] before release.]]

===Literacy===
{{main|Literacy}}
World literacy is lower for females than for males. The CIA World Factbook presents an estimate from 2010 which shows that 80% of women are literate, compared to 88.6% of men (aged 15 and over). Literacy rates are lowest in South and West Asia, and in parts of Sub-Saharan Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/xx.html |title=The World Factbook |publisher=Cia.gov |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===OECD countries===

====Education====
The educational [[Sex ratio|gender gap]] in [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]] (OECD) countries has been reduced over the last 30 years. Younger women today are far more likely to have completed a tertiary qualification: in 19 of the 30 OECD countries, more than twice as many women aged 25 to 34 have completed tertiary education than have women aged 55 to 64. In 21 of 27 OECD countries with comparable data, the number of women graduating from university-level programmes is equal to or exceeds that of men. 15-year-old girls tend to show much higher expectations for their careers than boys of the same age.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oecd.org/document/31/0,2340,en_2649_201185_33710751_1_1_1_1,00.html Education Levels Rising in OECD Countries but Low Attainment Still Hampers Some, [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]], Publication Date: 14 September 2004]. Retrieved December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
While women account for more than half of university graduates in several OECD countries, they receive only 30% of tertiary degrees granted in science and engineering fields, and women account for only 25% to 35% of researchers in most OECD countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oecd.org/document/13/0,2340,en_2649_33703_37682893_1_1_1_1,00.html Women in Scientific Careers: Unleashing the Potential, [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]], ISBN 92-64-02537-5, Publication Date: 20 November 2006]. Retrieved December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a common misconception that women have still not advanced in achieving academic degrees. According to Margaret Rossiter, a [[historian]] of science, women now earn 54 percent of all bachelor's degrees in the United States. However, although there are more women holding bachelor's degrees than men, as the level of education increases, the more men tend to fit the statistics{{clarify|reason="fit the statistics"? gibberish|date=August 2014}} instead of women. At the [[Postgraduate education|graduate level]], women fill 40 percent of the [[doctorate]] degrees (31 percent of them being in engineering).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Eisenhart, A. Margaret , Finkel, Elizabeth |title=Women (Still) Need Not Apply:The Gender and Science Reader|year=2001|publisher=Routledge|location=New York|pages=13–23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While to this day women are studying at prestigious universities at the same rate as men,{{clarify|reason=strongly suspect this is US-centric but cannot see the source|date=August 2014}} they are not being given the same chance to join faculty. Sociologist Harriet Zuckerman has observed that the more prestigious an institute is, the more difficult and time consuming it will be for women to obtain a faculty position there. In 1989, Harvard University tenured its first woman in chemistry, Cynthia Friend, and in 1992 its first woman in physics, Melissa Franklin. She also observed that women were more likely to hold their first [[professional]] positions as instructors and lecturers while men are more likely to work first in tenure positions. According to Smith and Tang, as of 1989, 65 percent of men and only 40 percent of women held tenured positions and only 29 percent of all scientists and engineers employed as assistant professors in four-year colleges and universities were women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Brainard, G. Susanne, Carlin, Linda |title=A six-year Longitudinal Study of Undergraduate Women in Engineering and Science:The Gender and Science Reader|year=2001|publisher=Routledge|location=New York|pages=24–37}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Jobs====
In 1992, women earned 9 percent of the Ph.D.'s awarded in [[engineering]] but only one percent of those women became a professor.{{Citation needed|date = June 2014|reason = Unsourced statistical claim}} In 1995, 11 percent of professors in [[science]] and engineering were women. In relation, only 311 deans of engineering schools were women, which is less than 1 percent of the total. Even in [[psychology]], a degree in which women earn the majority of Ph.D.'s, they hold a significant amount of fewer tenured positions, roughly 19 percent in 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Schiebinger|first=Londa|title=Has feminism changed science ?: Meters of Equity|year=1999|publisher=Cambridge: Harvard University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==Women in politics==
[[File:Map3.8Government Participation by Women compressed.jpg|left|thumb|251x251px|A world map showing female governmental participation by country, 2010.|alt=A world map showing female governmental participation by country, 2010.]]
[[File:Angela Merkel (2008).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Angela Merkel]] has earned the top spot on the FORBES list of Most Powerful Women In The World for eight of the past 10 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.forbes.com/profile/angela-merkel/|title=Angela Merkel|publisher=Forbes|accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Women are underrepresented in government in most countries. In October 2013, the global average of women in national assemblies was 22%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/world.htm |title=Women in Parliaments: World and Regional Averages |publisher=Ipu.org |date=2011-02-14 |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Suffrage]] is the civil right to [[vote]]. [[Women's suffrage in the United States]] was achieved gradually, first at state and local levels, starting in the late 19th century and early 20th century, and in 1920 women in the US received universal vote, with the passage of the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]]. Some Western countries were slow to allow women to vote; notably [[Switzerland]], where women gained the right to vote in federal elections in 1971, and in the canton of [[Appenzell Innerrhoden]] women were granted the right to vote on local issues only in 1991, when the canton was forced to do so by the [[Federal Supreme Court of Switzerland]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://history-switzerland.geschichte-schweiz.ch/chronology-womens-right-vote-switzerland.html |title=The Long Way to Women's Right to Vote in Switzerland: a Chronology |publisher=History-switzerland.geschichte-schweiz.ch |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2003/WOM1373.doc.htm |title=Experts In Women’S Anti-Discrimination Committee Raise Questions Concerning Reports Of Switzerland On Compliance With Convention |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2014-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Liechtenstein]], in 1984, through the [[Liechtenstein women's suffrage referendum, 1984]].

==Science, literature and art==
[[File:Bust Sappho Musei Capitolini MC1164.jpg|thumb|100px|right|Greek poet [[Sappho]]]]
Women have, throughout history, made contributions to [[science]], [[literature]] and [[art]]. One area where women have been permitted most access historically was that of [[obstetrics]] and [[gynecology]] (prior to the 18th century, caring for pregnant women in Europe was undertaken  by women; from the mid 18th century onwards medical monitoring of pregnant women started to require rigorous formal education, to which women did not generally have access, therefore the practice was largely transferred to men).&lt;ref name="Gelis"&gt;Gelis, Jacues. History of Childbirth. Boston: Northern University Press, 1991: 96-98&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bynum, W.F., &amp; Porter, Roy, eds. Companion Encyclopedia of the History of Medicine. London and New York: Routledge, 1993: 1051-1052.&lt;/ref&gt;

Writing was generally also considered acceptable for upper class women, although achieving success as a female writer in a male dominated world could be very difficult; as a result several women writers adopted a male pen-name (e.g. [[George Sand]], [[George Eliot]]).{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Gender studies|Feminism}}
* [[Lady]]
* [[Sex assignment]]
* [[Third gender]]
* [[Trans woman]]
* [[:Category:Lists of women]]

'''Medical:'''
* [[Childbirth]]
* [[Feminine psychology]]
* [[Gender differences]]
* [[Obstetrics]]

'''Dynamics:'''
* [[Femininity]]
* [[Feminization (sociology)]]
* [[Matriarchy]]
* [[Misogyny]]
* [[Mitochondrial Eve]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Women in science]]
* [[Women in religion]]

'''Political:'''
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Gender studies]]
* [[Womyn]]

'''Exploration:'''
* [[List of female explorers and travelers]]
* [[Mothers in space]]

{{Feminism}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*[http://www.aas.duke.edu/admin/deans/faculty/ Chafe, William H.], "The American Woman: Her Changing Social, Economic, And Political Roles, 1920–1970", Oxford University Press, 1972. ISBN 0-19-501785-4
* ''Routledge international encyclopedia of women'', 4 vls., ed. by Cheris Kramarae and Dale Spender, Routledge 2000
* ''[[Women in World History|Women in world history : a biographical encyclopedia]]'', 17 vls., ed. by [[Anne Commire]], Waterford, Conn. [etc.] : Yorkin Publ. [etc.], 1999–2002
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/32937/32937-h/32937-h.htm Woman In all ages and in all countries in 10 volumes]. Illustrated edition deluxe limited to 1,000 numbered copies with an index by Rénald Lévesque

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|woman|muliebrity}}
{{Wiktionary|Wikisaurus:woman}}
*{{Wikiquote-inline|Women}}
*{{Commons category-inline|Women}}
* [http://www.wic.org/misc/history.htm Women's History in America]
*[http://www.bium.univ-paris5.fr/histmed/medica/femmesmed_va.htm A History of Women’s Entrance into Medicine in France] studies and digitized texts by the [http://www.bium.parisdescartes.fr/ BIUM  (Bibliothèque interuniversitaire de médecine et d'odontologie, Paris)] see its digital library [http://www.bium.univ-paris5.fr/histmed/medica.htm Medic@].
* [http://www.helsinki.fi/science/xantippa/wee/wee26.html Women and Christianity: representations and practices]

{{Navboxes
|title = Articles related to Women
|list  =
{{Africa topic|Women in}}
{{Asia topic|Women in}}
{{North America topic|Women in}}
{{South America topic|Women in}}
{{Oceania topic|Women in}}
}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Females]]
[[Category:Women| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>