<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050710105104|18522643" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="167703" pageid="167703" ns="0" title="Empowerment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-07-12T13:53:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Empowerment''' refers to increasing the [[Politics|political]], [[social]] or [[Economics|economic]] strength of individuals or groups. It often involves the empowered developing  [[confidence]] in their own capacities.

==Sociology==
[[Sociology | Sociological]] empowerment often addresses members of groups that social discrimination processes have excluded from  decision-making processes through  - for example - discrimination based on [[race]], [[ethnicity]], [[religion]], [[gender]] etc. Note in particular the empowerment-technique often associated with [[feminism]]: [[consciousness-raising]].

==Management==
In the sphere of [[management]] and organizational theory, "empowerment" often refers loosely to processes for giving subordinates (or [[worker]]s generally) greater discretion and resources: distributing control in order to better serve both customers and the interests of employing organizations. (This use of the word appears somewhat at odds with other usage, which most often assumes the empowerment of groups and of individuals to better serve their '''own''' interests.)

One account of the history of workplace empowerment in the [[United States of America | United States]] recalls the clash of management styles in railroad construction in the [[American West]] in the mid-19th century, where "traditional" hierarchical East-Coast models of control encountered individualistic pioneer workers, strongly supplemented by methods of [[efficiency]]-oriented "worker [[responsibility]]" brought to the scene by [[Chinese American | Chinese]] [[coolie | laborer]]s. In this case, empowerment at the level of work [[team]]s or brigades achieved a notable (but short-lived) demonstrated superiority. See the [http://www.motivation-tools.com/workplace/history.htm views] of Robert L. Webb.

==Economics==
In [[economic development]], the empowerment approach focusses on mobilizing the [[self-help]] efforts of the poor, rather than providing them with [[social welfare]]. 

==Personal development==
In the arena of [[personal development]], empowerment forms an [[apogee]] of many a system of [[Self Realization | self-realisation]] or of [[identity]] (re-)formation. Realising the [[solipsism | solipsistic]] impracticality of everyone [[anarchy | anarchistically]] attempting to exercise [[power (sociology) | power]] over everyone else, empowerment [[guru | advocates]] have adopted the word "empowerment" to offer the attractions of such power, but they generally constrain its individual exercise to potentiality and to feel-good uses within the [[individual]] [[psyche]].

[[de:Empowerment]]

[[Category:Sociology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>