<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041105190848|7146659" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1119797" pageid="1119797" ns="0" title="Jewish quota"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-06T04:51:42Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Jewish quota''' was a percentage that limited the number of [[Jews]] in various establishments. In particular, in 19th and 20th centuries some countries had Jewish quotas for [[higher education]], a special case of '''[[Numerus clausus]]'''. These were an attempt to limit the influence of ethnic and/or religious Jews.

Jewish quotas for education could be state-wise law or adopted only in certain institutions, often unofficially.

The limitation took the form of total prohibition of Jewish students, or of limiting the number of Jewish students so that their share in the students' population would not be larger than their share in the general population. It was motivated by contemporary view of the balancing chances for education for ethnic groups.  In some establishments, the Jewish quota placed a limit on growth rather than set a fixed level of participation to be achieved.

The numerus clausus policies affected a limited number of people, since the number of university students before [[WWII]] was very small.

Jews who wanted education used various ways to handle this obstacle: bribing the authorities, changing their religion, or traveling to countries without such limitations. In Hungary, for example, 5,000 Jewish youngsters (including [[Edward Teller]]) left the country after the introduction of ''Numerus Clausus''.

== Countries legislating limitations on the admission of Jewish students==

*[[Imperial Russia]]: ''Numerus Clausus'' was enacted in [[1887]], stating that the share of Jewish students should be no more than 10% in cities where [[Jew]]s were allowed to live, 5% in other cities, and only 3% in [[Moscow]] and [[St. Petersburg]]. These limitations were deleted after the revolution of 1917.
*[[Hungary]]: a ''Numerus Clausus'' Act was introduced in [[1920]], as part of the rise of [[Anti-Semitism]] under the government of [[Pál Teleki]]. It was said that Jewish students would be no more than 6% of the student population (this was the share of Jews in the general population), compared to 30% before the war. Limitations were relaxed in [[1928]].
*[[Poland]]: see [[Numerus clausus#Numerus clausus in Poland|Numerus clausus in Poland]].
*[[Romania]] ''Numerus Clausus'' was introduced in [[1926]].
*[[United States]], limitations on the enrollment of Jewish students to the universities were practiced unofficially in the 1920s, especially in the northeastern universities.
*[[Nazi Germany]]: the Jewish quota, introduced on [[April 25]], [[1933]], permitted 1.5%  of high-school and university enrollment (5% in a single school).
*[[Canada]]: in 1920-1940s, some universities, such as [[McGill University]], had Jewish quotas.

[[Category:Jewish history]]
[[Category:Education]]
[[Category:Anti-Semitism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>