<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191020213210|922238184" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1119797" pageid="1119797" ns="0" title="Jewish quota"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-22T03:17:14Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Limits on Jewish immigration and education}}{{Use American English|date=January 2019}}{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2019}}{{Refimprove|date=May 2009}}
{{Antisemitism}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
A '''Jewish quota''' was a historical [[racial quota]] limiting the number of [[Jew]]s in various establishments to a certain percentage. In particular, in the 19th and 20th centuries, some countries had Jewish quotas in [[higher education]].

Jewish [[educational quotas]] could be statewide law or adopted only in certain institutions, often unofficially. The limitation took the form of total prohibition of Jewish students, or of limiting the number of Jewish students so that their share in the students' population would not be larger than their share in the general population.{{why|date=May 2018}} In some establishments, the Jewish quota placed a limit on growth rather than set a fixed level of participation to be achieved.

Jews who wanted an education used various ways to overcome this discrimination: bribing the authorities, changing their religion, or traveling to countries without such limitations. In Hungary, for example, 5,000 Jewish youngsters (including [[Edward Teller]]) left the country after the introduction of ''[[numerus clausus]]''.

==By countries==

===Canada===
Certain universities, notably [[McGill University]], [[Université de Montréal]] and the [[University of Toronto]], had longstanding quotas on the number of Jews admitted to the respective universities. [[McGill University]]'s strict quota was the longest, being officially adopted in 1920 up until the late 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;Gerald Tulchinsky, ''Canada's Jews: A People's Journey'', (Toronto: University of Toronto Press), 2008, p. 132-133, 319-321.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tulchinsky, ''Canada's Jews'', p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tulchinsky, ''Canada's Jews'', p. 410.&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Germany===
On 25 April 1933, the [[Nazi]] government introduced a 1.5 percent quota for new admissions of German Non-[[Aryan race|Aryans]]—i.e. essentially of German Jews—as core issue of a law claiming to generally limit the number of (Aryan and non-Aryan) students admitted to high-schools (''höhere Schulen'') and universities. In addition, high-schools and universities deemed to have more students than required for the professions for which they were training their students were required to reduce their student enrollment; doing so, they had to reach a maximum of 5 per cent of German non-Aryan students. The law was supposedly enacted to avoid overcrowding schools and universities,&lt;ref&gt;[http://alex.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno-plus?apm=0&amp;aid=dra&amp;datum=19330004&amp;zoom=2&amp;seite=00000225&amp;ues=0&amp;x=9&amp;y=13 Gesetz gegen die Überfüllung deutscher Schulen und Hochschulen (RGBl 1933 I, S. 225)] (original German text of the ''Law against the Overcrowding of German Schools and Universities'', introduced in 1933)
[http://alex.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno-plus?apm=0&amp;aid=dra&amp;datum=19330004&amp;seite=00000226&amp;zoom=2 Erste Verordnung zur Durchführung des Gesetzes gegen die Überfüllung deutscher Schulen und Hochschulen (RGBl 1933 I, S. 226)] (original German text of the ''First Regulation for the Implementation of the Law against the Overcrowding of German Schools and Universities'', introduced in 1933)&lt;/ref&gt; which referred to German concerns at the time that large numbers of students would decrease the quality of higher education. At the beginning of 1933, about 0.76 percent of the German population was Jewish, but more than 3.6 percent of German university students were Jewish, this number having steadily declined from over 9 percent in the 1880s.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.jstor.org/pss/40185665 Claudia Huerkamp (1993). Jüdische Akademikerinnen in Deutschland 1900–1938 (= Jewish academics in Germany 1900–1938). ''Geschichte und Gesellschaft, 19. Jg. (Heft 3),'' Rassenpolitik und Geschlechterpolitik im Nationalsozialismus, pp. 311–331.] Publisher: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht (GmbH &amp; Co. KG)&lt;/ref&gt; After 30 July 1939, Jews were no longer permitted to attend German public schools at all, and the prior quota law was eliminated by a non-public regulation in January 1940.&lt;ref name="Olenhusen"&gt;[https://www.jstor.org/pss/30196241 A. G. v. Olenhusen: Die "nichtarischen" Studenten an den deutschen Hochschulen (= The non-Aryan students at German universities). ''Vierteljahrshefte für Zeitgeschichte, 14(1966),'' pp. 175–206.] (German)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;p.&amp;nbsp;193&lt;/sup&gt;

Apart from their strong and predominant anti-Semitic agenda, the law and its subsequent regulations were temporarily indeed used to limit general university access, i.e. including "non-Aryans" (Jews), as the name of the law implied. Starting 1934, a regulation limited the overall numbers of students admitted to German universities, and a special quota was introduced reducing women's admissions to a maximum of 10 percent. Although the limits were not entirely enforced—women's quota stayed a bit above 10 percent mainly because a smaller percentage of men than women accepted their university admissions—they made it for women approximately twice as hard to enter a university career than for men with the same qualification.&lt;ref name="Bildungsbürgerinnen"&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=QVToe3288bEC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=%C3%BCberfremdung&amp;f=false Claudia Huerkamp (1996). ''Bildungsbürgerinnen. Frauen im Studium und in akademischen Berufen 1900-1945.'' (Reihe: ''Bürgertum, Band 10'')] {{ISBN|3-525-35675-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;S.&amp;nbsp;80ff.&lt;/sup&gt; After two semesters, the admission limits were revoked, however, leaving in place the non-Aryan regulations.&lt;ref name="Olenhusen"/&gt;&lt;sup&gt;p.&amp;nbsp;178&lt;/sup&gt;

:''For additional information in German, see the [[:de:Gesetz gegen die Überfüllung deutscher Schulen und Hochschulen|article at the German Wikipedia]]''

===Hungary===
''Numerus Clausus'' Act was introduced in 1920, under the government of [[Pál Teleki]]. It was said that the ethnic rate of students must meet the ethnic rate of population. Limitations were relaxed in 1928. Racial criteria in admitting new students were removed and replaced by social criteria. Five categories were set up: civil servants, war veterans and army officers, small landowners and artisans, industrialists, and the merchant classes.&lt;ref&gt;See: [https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/judaica/ejud_0002_0015_0_14969.html Numerus Clausus]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Latvia===
Jewish quotas were introduced in 1934, under [[Kārlis Ulmanis]]' authoritarian regime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://pdfs.jta.org/1935/1935-02-10_3070.pdf | location=New York |work=[[Jewish Daily Bulletin]] |date=February 10, 1935 |title=Minorities aided in new Polish edict}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Poland===
See [[Numerus clausus#Poland|Numerus clausus in Poland]] and [[Ghetto benches]].

===Romania===
''Numerus Clausus'' was not introduced by law,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hist-chron.com/judentum-aktenlage/numerus-clausus/EncJud_num-claus-d/EncJud_numerus-clausus-band12-kolonne-1267-1268.gif |title=Encyclopaedia Judaica: Numerus clausus, vol. 12, col. 1267-1268}}&lt;/ref&gt; but it was adopted by students in the universities Cluj, Bucharest, Iasi and Cernauti.

===Russia===
Discrimination against Jews in Russia has existed for centuries, including during [[Imperial Russia]] and the [[Soviet Union]].

''Numerus Clausus'' was enacted in 1887, stating that the share of Jewish students should be no more than 10 percent in cities where [[Jew]]s were [[Pale of Settlement|allowed to live]], 5 percent in other cities, and only 3 percent in [[Moscow]] and [[Saint Petersburg|St. Petersburg]]. These limitations were removed in the spring of 1917 after the tsar's abdication during the early phase of the Russian revolution of 1917-1918 (the so-called [[February Revolution]] of 1917); later, in the late 1940s during the initial phase of the [[Cold War]] and the tide of the anti-"[[rootless cosmopolitan]]" campaign a [[de facto]] gross discrimination of Jewish applicants was reintroduced in many institutions of higher education in the [[Soviet Union]] until [[Perestroika]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor=[[Mikhail Shifman]] |title=You Failed Your Math Test, Comrade Einstein: Adventures and Misadventures of Young Mathematicians Or Test Your Skills in Almost Recreational Mathematics |publisher=World Scientific |date=2005 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ho6fMF8ehogC}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=[[Edward Frenkel]] |title=The Fifth problem: math &amp; anti-Semitism in the Soviet Union |date=October 2012 |journal=The New Criterion |url=http://www.newcriterion.com/articles.cfm/The-Fifth-problem--math---anti-Semitism-in-the-Soviet-Union-7446}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/opinion/commentators/dominic-lawson/dominic-lawson-more-migrants-please-especially-the-clever-ones-2368622.html |location=London |work=[[The Independent]] |date=October 11, 2011 |title=More migrants please, especially the clever ones|author=[[Dominic Lawson]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=[[Andre Geim]] |title=Biographical |publisher=Nobelprize.org |date=2010 |url=https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/2010/geim-bio.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
Certain private universities, most notably [[Harvard]], introduced policies which effectively placed a quota on the number of Jews admitted to the university. According to historian [[David Oshinsky]], on writing about [[Jonas Salk]], "Most of the surrounding medical schools ([[Cornell University|Cornell]], [[Columbia University|Columbia]], [[University of Pennsylvania|Pennsylvania]], and [[Yale University|Yale]]) had rigid quotas in place. In 1935 Yale accepted 76 applicants from a pool of 501. About 200 of those applicants were Jewish and only five got in." He notes that Dean Milton Winternitz's instructions were remarkably precise: "Never admit more than five Jews, take only two Italian Catholics, and take no blacks at all."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Gerard N. Burrow|title=A History of Yale's School of Medicine: Passing Torches to Others|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XzYX_MduAG8C&amp;pg=PA107|year=2008|publisher=Yale University Press|page=107ff}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, Oshinsky added, "[[Jonas Salk]] and hundreds like him" enrolled in [[New York University]] instead.&lt;ref&gt;Oshinsky, David M. ''Polio: An American Story'', Oxford Univ. Press (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; Physicist and Nobel laureate [[Richard P. Feynman]] was turned away from [[Columbia College of Columbia University|Columbia College]] in the 1930s and went to [[MIT]] instead. See also [[Numerus clausus#United States|Numerus clausus in the United States]].

===Yugoslavia===
In 1940, the government of the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] enacted the Decree on the Enrollment of Persons of Jewish Descent at the University, Secondary School, Teacher Training College and Other Vocational Schools which limited the proportion of Jewish students to the proportion of Jews in the total population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://web.ceu.hu/jewishstudies/pdf/02_goldstein.pdf |title=The Jews in Yugoslavia 1918-1941: Antisemitism and the Struggle for Equality |last=Goldstein |first=Ivo |authorlink=Ivo Goldstein |pages=10–11 |format=PDF |accessdate=6 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Asian quota]]
* [[Disabilities (Jewish)]]
* [[Jewish intelligence]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Education scandals and controversies]]
[[Category:Education policy]]
[[Category:History of education]]
[[Category:Disabilities (Jewish)]]
[[Category:Race and education in the United States]]
[[Category:Quotas]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>