<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191114024653|926076191" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1099357" pageid="1099357" ns="0" title="Marxist feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-24T14:12:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism sidebar |Variants (general)}}
{{Marxism|Aspects}}

'''Marxist feminism''' is a philosophical variant of [[feminism]].  Marxist Feminism is focused on the ways in which women could be oppressed through systems of [[capitalism]] and the individual ownership of [[private property]].&lt;ref name="desaim2014"/&gt; According to Marxist feminists, [[women's liberation]] can only be achieved through a radical restructuring of capitalist economies, in which, they contend, much of women's labor is uncompensated.&lt;ref name="Ferguson"/&gt;

== Theoretical background in Marxism ==
Marxism follows the development of [[oppression]] and [[class division]] in the evolution of human society, revolving around the evolution and organisation of wealth and production, and concludes the evolution of oppressive societal structure to be relative to the evolution of oppressive family structures, i.e., the normalisation of oppressing the female sex marks or coincides to the birth of oppressive society in general.

In ''[[The Origin of the Family, Private Property, and the State]]'', published in 1884, inspired by and based on notes by [[Karl Marx]] to [[Lewis H. Morgan]]'s 1877 book ''[[Ancient Society]]'',&lt;ref name="Engels"/&gt; [[Friedrich Engels]] writes about the earliest origin of the family structure, social hierarchy, and the concept of male wealth, drawing from both ancient and contemporary study. He concludes that women originally had a higher social status, equal consideration in labor, and particularly, only females were sure to share a family name. A woman pursuing [[monogamy]], or even paired marriage, however, was socially unacceptable, so monogamy and paired marriage were a cultural desire of women. As the earliest males did not even share the family name, Engels says, they did not know for sure who their children were or benefit from [[inheritance]].&lt;ref name="engels pdf 11"/&gt;

When agriculture first became abundant and the abundance was considered male wealth, as it was sourced from the male work environment away from the home, a deeper wish for male [[Lineage (anthropology)|lineage]] and inheritance was founded. To achieve that wish, women were not only granted their long sought monogamy, but forced into it as part of domestic servitude, while males pursued a hushed culture of "[[hetaerism]]". Engels describes this situation as coincidental to the beginnings of forced servitude as a dominant feature of society, leading eventually to a European culture of [[class oppression]], where the children of the poor were expected to be servants of the rich.&lt;ref name="engels pdf 11"/&gt;

Engels rewrites a quote in this book, by himself and Marx from 1846, "The first division of labor is that between man and woman for the propagation of children", to say, "The first class opposition that appears in history coincides with the development of the antagonism between man and woman in monogamous marriage, and the first class oppression coincides with that of the female sex by the male."&lt;ref name="engels pdf 11"/&gt;

[[Gender oppression]] is [[Cultural reproduction|reproduced culturally]] and maintained through [[institutionalisation|institutionalised]] inequality. Portraying men as privileged at the expense of women, by refusing to acknowledge traditional domestic labor as equally valuable, the working class male is cultured into an oppressive structure which [[marginalisation|marginalises]] the female.&lt;ref name="Ferguson" /&gt;

== Productive and unproductive labor ==
Marx categorised the value of employment in two ways, [[Productive and unproductive labour|productive, and nonproductive]]. 

Loosely defined, 

*Productive labor: Production of materials, crafting of materials into products, roles which support production. 

*Unproductive labor: Circulation of commodities, financial exchange, [[marketing]], etc. 

Marxist feminist authors popular in 1970s USA, such as [[Margaret Benston]] and Peggy Morton, relied heavily on analysis of productive and unproductive labour to attempt to shift a perception of the time, that consumption was the purpose of a family, presenting arguments for a state paid wage to [[homemaking|homemakers]], and a cultural perception of the family as a productive entity. In capitalism, the work of maintaining a family has little material value, as it produces no marketable products. In Marxism, the maintenance of a family is productive, as it has a service value, and is used in the same sense as a commodity.&lt;ref name="Vogel"/&gt;

=== Wages for housework ===
Focusing on exclusion from productive labor as the most important source of female oppression, some Marxist feminists devoted their activism to fighting for the inclusion of domestic work within the waged capitalist economy. The idea of creating compensated reproductive labor was present in the writings of socialists such as [[Charlotte Perkins Gilman]] (1898) who argued that women's oppression stemmed from being forced into the private sphere.&lt;ref name="gilman4223"/&gt; Gilman proposed that conditions for women would improve when their work was located, recognized, and valued in the public sphere.&lt;ref name="Ferguson" /&gt;

Perhaps the most influential of effort to compensate reproductive labor was the [[Wages for housework|International Wages for Housework Campaign]], an organization launched in Italy in 1972 by members of the International Feminist Collective. Many of these women, including [[Selma James]],&lt;ref name="Gardiner"/&gt; Mariarosa Dalla Costa,&lt;ref name="Costa"/&gt;Brigitte Galtier, and [[Silvia Federici]]&lt;ref name="Cox"/&gt; published a range of sources to promote their message in academic and public domains. Despite beginning as a small group of women in Italy, The Wages for Housework Campaign was successful in mobilizing on an international level. A Wages for Housework group was founded in Brooklyn, New York with the help of Federici.&lt;ref name="Cox" /&gt; As [[Heidi Hartmann]] acknowledges (1981), the efforts of these movements, though ultimately unsuccessful, generated important discourse regarding the value of housework and its relation to the economy.&lt;ref name="Hartmann"/&gt;

=== Responsibility of reproductive labour ===
Another solution proposed by Marxist feminists is to liberate women from their forced connection to reproductive labour. In her critique of traditional Marxist feminist movements such as the Wages for Housework Campaign, [[Heidi Hartmann]] (1981) argues that these efforts "take as their question the relationship of women to the economic system, rather than that of women to men, apparently assuming the latter will be explained in their discussion of the former."&lt;ref name="Hartmann" /&gt; Hartmann (1981) believes that traditional discourse has ignored the importance of women's oppression as women, and instead focused on women's oppression as members of the capitalist system. Similarly, [[Gayle Rubin]], who has written on a range of subjects including sadomasochism, prostitution, pornography, and lesbian literature as well as anthropological studies and histories of sexual subcultures, first rose to prominence through her 1975 essay ''The Traffic in Women: Notes on the 'Political Economy' of Sex'',&lt;ref name="rubin1975"/&gt; in which she coins the phrase "sex/gender system" and criticizes Marxism for what she claims is its incomplete analysis of sexism under capitalism, without dismissing or dismantling Marxist fundamentals in the process.

More recently, many Marxist feminists have shifted their focus to the ways in which women are now potentially in worse conditions after gaining access to productive labour. [[Nancy Folbre]] proposes that feminist movements begin to focus on women's subordinate status to men both in the reproductive (private) sphere, as well as in the workplace (public sphere).&lt;ref name="folbre2133"/&gt; In an interview in 2013, Silvia Federici urges feminist movements to consider the fact that many women are now forced into productive ''and'' reproductive labour, resulting in a "[[Double burden|double day]]".&lt;ref name="Fed"/&gt; Federici argues that the emancipation of women still cannot occur until they are free from their burdens of unwaged labour, which she proposes will involve institutional changes such as closing the wage gap and implementing child care programs in the workplace.&lt;ref name="Fed" /&gt; Federici's suggestions are echoed in a similar interview with Selma James (2012) and these issues have been touched on in recent presidential elections.&lt;ref name="Gardiner" /&gt;

=== Affective labor ===

Feminist scholars and [[List of sociologists|sociologists]] such as [[Michael Hardt]],&lt;ref name=":2"/&gt; [[Antonio Negri]],&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; [[Arlie Russell Hochschild]]&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt;  and Shiloh Whitney&lt;ref name=":1"/&gt; discuss a new form of labor that transcends the traditional spheres of labor and which does not create product, or is byproductive.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Affective labor focuses on the blurred lines between personal life and economic life. Whitney states "The daily struggle of unemployed persons and the domestic toil of housewives no less than the waged worker are thus part of the production and reproduction of social life, and of the biopolitical growth of capital that valorizes information and subjectivities."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The concept of [[emotional labor]] is a focus of [[affective labor]], particularly the emotional labor that is present and required in traditionally pink collared jobs (jobs traditionally occupied by women). Arlie Russell Hochschild discusses the emotional labor of flight attendants in her book ''The Managed Heart: Commercialization of Human Feeling'' (1983)&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; in which she considers the affective labor of the profession as flight attendants smile, exchange pleasantries and banter with customers.

=== Sex Work ===
[[Alan Soble]]&lt;ref name=":3"/&gt; brings forth a challenging perspective on Marxism. Soble discusses in his book ''Pornography: Marxism, Feminism, and the Future of Sexuality'' (1986)&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; how pornography operates as sexual oppression in a capitalistic system. 

[[Anne Phillips]] and Barbara Taylor discuss in ''Sex and Skill: Notes towards a Feminist Economic''s (1980)&lt;ref name="phillips2432"/&gt; how [[sex work]] has become a new form of labor separate to reproductive and productive labor. Sex work is heavily criminalized and sex worker's are not socially recognized as a part of the labor force. There are multiple [[List of sex worker organizations|organizations]] including the [[Sex Workers Outreach Project USA|Sex Worker's Outreach Project]] working to normalise sex work within the capitalistic system and provide sex workers with rights, health care, decriminalization, and protection.

== Intersectionality and Marxist feminism ==
{{Main|Intersectionality and Marxist feminism}}
With the emergence of [[intersectionality]]&lt;ref name="crenshaw3312"/&gt; as a widely popular theory of current feminism, Marxist feminists include an analysis of other sources of oppression beyond class that increase exploitation in a capitalist system.  However, they also remain critical of intersectionality theory for relying on bourgeois [[identity politics]].&lt;ref name="mitchell2431"/&gt; Intersectionality operates within Marxist feminism as a lens to view the interaction of different aspects of identity as a result of structured, systematic [[oppression]]. The organization [[Radical Women]] provides an example of successfully incorporating Marxist feminist goals without overlooking those susceptible to exploitation. They contend the elimination of capitalist profit-driven economy will remove the motivation for sexism, racism, homophobia, and other forms of oppression.&lt;ref name="cornish2341"/&gt;

== Accomplishments and activism ==
The nature of Marxist feminists and their ability to mobilize to promote social change has enabled them to engage in important activism.&lt;ref name="marxist3124"/&gt; Though their controversial advocacy often receives criticism, Marxist feminists challenge capitalism in ways that facilitate new discourse and shed light on the status of women.&lt;ref name="Hartmann" /&gt; These women throughout history have used a range of approaches in fighting [[hegemonic]] capitalism, which reflect their different views on the optimal method of achieving liberation for women.&lt;ref name="Ferguson" /&gt;&lt;ref name="eisenstein"/&gt;

== Criticism of Marxist feminism ==
A common criticism of Marxist feminism is that women’s oppression within the family existed before capitalism. 

Another common criticism of Marxist feminism is that women's oppression also occurred in communist societies.  

== Marxist feminist critiques of other branches of feminism ==
[[Clara Zetkin]]&lt;ref name="zetkin2134"/&gt;&lt;ref name="zetlen"/&gt; and [[Alexandra Kollontai]]&lt;ref name="kol1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="kollontai1324"/&gt; were opposed to forms of feminism that reinforce class status. They did not see a true possibility to unite across economic inequality because they argue that it would be extremely difficult for an upper class woman to truly understand the struggles of the working class. For instance, Kollontai wrote in 1909: &lt;blockquote&gt;For what reason, then, should the woman worker seek a union with the bourgeois feminists? Who, in actual fact, would stand to gain in the event of such an alliance? Certainly not the woman worker.&lt;ref name="kol1"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Critics like Kollontai believed [[liberal feminism]] would undermine the efforts of Marxism to improve conditions for the working class. Marxists supported the more radical political program of liberating women through socialist revolution, with a special emphasis on work among women and in materially changing their conditions after the revolution. Additional liberation methods supported by Marxist feminists include radical "Utopian Demands", coined by [[Maria Mies]].&lt;ref name="mies3412"/&gt; This indication of the scope of revolution required to promote change states that demanding anything less than complete reform will produce inadequate solutions to long-term issues.&lt;br /&gt;

==Notable Marxist feminists==
* [[Angela Davis]]
* [[Raya Dunayevskaya]]
* [[Silvia Federici]]
* [[Shulamith Firestone]]
* [[Clara Fraser]]
* [[Alexandra Kollontai]]
* [[Sheila Rowbotham]]
* [[Evelyn Reed]]
* [[Chizuko Ueno]]
* [[Claudia Jones]]

== Marxist feminist organizations ==

* [[Radical Women]]

== See also ==
*[[Anarcha-feminism]]
*[[Feminist economics]]
*[[Feminist theory]]
*[[Material feminism]]
*[[Neo-Marxism]]
*''[[The Origin of the Family, Private Property, and the State]]''
*[[Radical feminism]]
*[[Socialist feminism]]
*[[Lucy R. Lippard]]
*[[Abortion under communism]]
*[[Intersectionality]]

== References ==
{{reflist|33em|refs=

&lt;ref name="desaim2014"&gt;Desai, Murli (2014), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=hUPhAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA119 Feminism and policy approaches for gender aware development]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Desai | editor-first = Murli | title = The paradigm of international social development: ideologies, development systems and policy approaches | page = 119 | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 2014 | isbn = 9781135010256 }}
:''Citing'': 
:* {{cite book | last = Poonacha | first = Veena | title = Gender within the human rights discourse | publisher = Research Centre for Women's Studies. S.N.D.T. Women's University | location = Bombay | series = RCWS Gender Series | year = 1995 | oclc = 474755917}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Ferguson"&gt;[[Ann Ferguson|Ferguson, Ann]]; [[Rosemary Hennessy|Hennessy, Rosemary]] (2010), "[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-class/ Feminist perspectives on class and work]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Stanford Uni | title = Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Engels"&gt;{{cite book | last = Engels | first = Frederick | author-link = Frederick Engels | title = The Origin of the Family, Private Property, and the State | publisher = Charles H. Kerr &amp; Co. | location = Chicago | origyear = 1884 | year = 1902 | oclc = 213734607| title-link = The Origin of the Family, Private Property, and the State }} [https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1884/origin-family/ View online.]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="engels pdf 11"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/download/pdf/origin_family.pdf|title=The Origin of the Family Private Property and the State|last=Engels}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Vogel"&gt;Vogel, Lise (2013), "[https://books.google.com/books?id=RKbdfZvS3_IC&amp;pg=PA17 A decade of debate]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Vogel | editor-first = Lise  | title = Marxism and the oppression of women: toward a unitary theory | page = 17 | publisher = Brill | location = Leiden, Holland | isbn = 9789004248953 | date = 2013-06-07  }}
:''Citing'':
:* {{cite journal | last = Benston | first = Margaret | author-link = Margaret Benston | title = The political economy of women's liberation | journal = [[Monthly Review]] | volume = 21 | issue = 4 | pages = 13&amp;ndash;27 | doi = 10.14452/MR-021-04-1969-08_2 | date = September 1969 | ref = harv }}
:* {{cite journal | last = Morton | first = Peggy| title = A woman's work is never done | trans-title = The production, maintenance and reproduction of labor power | journal = Leviathan | volume = 2 | date = May 1970 | oclc = 741468359 | ref = harv }}
::* ''Reproduced as'': {{citation | last = Morton | first = Peggy | contribution = Women's work is never done... or The production, maintenance and reproduction of labour power | editor-last = Various | title = Women unite! (Up from the kitchen. Up from the bedroom. Up from under.) An anthology of the Canadian Women's Movement | publisher = Canadian Women's Education Press | location = Toronto | year = 1972 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=CkbaAAAAMAAJ | oclc = 504303414 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="gilman4223"&gt;{{cite book | last = Gilman | first = C. P. | author-link = Charlotte Perkins Gilman | title = Women and economics: a study of the economic relation between men and women as a factor in social evolution | publisher = Small, Maynard, &amp; Co. | location = Boston | url = http://digital.library.upenn.edu/women/gilman/economics/economics.html | year = 1898 | oclc = 26987247 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Gardiner"&gt;{{cite news | last = Gardiner | first = Becky | title = A life in writing: Selma James | url = https://www.theguardian.com/books/2012/jun/08/life-in-writing-selma-james | work = [[The Guardian]] | date = 8 June 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Costa"&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Dalla Costa | first1 = Mariarosa | last2 = James | first2 = Selma | author-link1 = Mariarosa Dalla Costa | author-link2 = Selma James | title = The power of women and the subversion of the community | publisher = Falling Water Press | location = Bristol, England | url = http://libcom.org/library/power-women-subversion-community-della-costa-selma-james | year = 1972 | oclc = 67881986 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

&lt;ref name="Cox"&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Cox | first1 = Nicole | last2 = Federici | first2 = Silvia | author-link2 = Silvia Federici | title = Counter-planning from the kitchen: wages for housework: a perspective on capital and the left | publisher = New York Wages for Housework | location = New York | url = http://bcrw.barnard.edu/archive/workforce/Counter-Planning_from_the_Kitchen.pdf | year = 1976 | edition = 2nd | oclc = 478375855 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Hartmann"&gt;{{citation | last = Hartmann | first = Heidi | author-link = Heidi Hartmann | contribution = The unhappy marriage of Marxism and feminism: towards a more progressive union | editor-last = Sargent | editor-first = Lydia | editor-link = Lydia Sargent | title = Women and revolution: a discussion of the unhappy marriage of Marxism and Feminism | pages = 1&amp;ndash;42 | publisher = [[South End Press]] | location = Boston, Massachusetts | series = South End Press Political Controversies Series | year = 1981 | isbn = 9780896080621 | ref = harv | postscript = .}} 
* ''Reproduced as'': {{citation | last = Hartmann | first = Heidi | author-link = Heidi Hartmann | contribution = The unhappy marriage of Marxism and feminism: towards a more progressive union | editor-last1 = McCann | editor-first1 = Carole | editor-last2 = Kim | editor-first2 = Seung-kyung | title = Feminist theory reader: local and global perspectives | pages = 187&amp;ndash;199 | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 2013 | isbn = 9780415521024 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="rubin1975"&gt;[[Gayle Rubin|Rubin, Gayle]] (1975), "[https://genderstudiesgroupdu.files.wordpress.com/2014/08/the-rraffic-in-women.pdf The Traffic in Women: Notes on the 'Political Economy' of Sex]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Reiter | editor-first = Rayna | title = Toward an Anthropology of Women | publisher = Monthly Review Press | location = New York | isbn = 9780853453727 | year = 1975 }}
:''Reprinted in'': {{cite book | last = Nicholson | first = Linda | title = The second wave: a reader in feminist theory | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 1997 | isbn = 9780415917612 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="folbre2133"&gt;{{cite book | last = Folbre | first = Nancy | author-link = Nancy Folbre | title = Who pays for the kids?: gender and the structures of constraint | publisher = Routledge | location = London New York | year = 1994 | isbn = 9780415075657 | title-link = Nancy Folbre#Who Pays for the Kids? Gender and the Structures of Constraint (1994) }}
:''See also'': {{cite journal|last= Baker |first= Patricia |title=Reviewed work ''Who Pays for the Kids? Gender and the Structures of Constraint'' by Nancy Folbre |journal=[[Canadian Journal of Sociology]] |volume=21 |issue=4 |pages= 567–571 | doi = 10.2307/3341533 | jstor = 3341533 |date= Autumn 1996 |ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Fed"&gt;{{cite news | last = Vishmidt | first = Marina | title = Permanent reproductive crisis: an interview with Silvia Federici | url = http://www.metamute.org/editorial/articles/permanent-reproductive-crisis-interview-silvia-federici | work = [[Mute (magazine)|Mute]] | date = 7 March 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite book|title=Empire|last=Michael.|first=Hardt|date=2000|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=978-0674251212|oclc=1051694685}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Brown|first=J. V.|date=1985-09-01|title=The Managed Heart: Commercialization of Human Feeling. By Arlie Russell Hochschild. University of California Press, 1983. 307 pp. $14.95|journal=Social Forces|volume=64|issue=1|pages=223–224|doi=10.1093/sf/64.1.223|issn=0037-7732}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Whitney|first=Shiloh|date=2017-12-14|title=Byproductive labor|journal=Philosophy &amp; Social Criticism|volume=44|issue=6|pages=637–660|doi=10.1177/0191453717741934|issn=0191-4537}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/12552231|title=Pornography : Marxism, feminism, and the future of sexuality|last=Soble, Alan.|date=1986|publisher=Yale University Press|isbn=0300035241|location=New Haven|oclc=12552231}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="phillips2432"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Phillips|first=Anne|last2=Taylor|first2=Barbara|date=1980|title=Sex and Skill: Notes towards a Feminist Economics|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/1394973?origin=crossref|journal=Feminist Review|issue=6|pages=79|doi=10.2307/1394973}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="crenshaw3312"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Crenshaw|first=Kimberle|date=July 1991|title=Mapping the Margins: Intersectionality, Identity Politics, and Violence against Women of Color|journal=Stanford Law Review|volume=43|issue=6|pages=1241–1299|doi=10.2307/1229039|issn=0038-9765|jstor=1229039|citeseerx=10.1.1.695.5934}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="mitchell2431"&gt;{{cite book | last = Mitchell | first = Eve | title = I am a woman and a human: a Marxist feminist critique of intersectionality (''pamphlet'') | publisher = Unity and Struggle | location = Houston, NYC, and Atlanta | url = http://unityandstruggle.org/2013/09/12/i-am-a-woman-and-a-human-a-marxist-feminist-critique-of-intersectionality-theory/ | year = 2013 | url-status = bot: unknown | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170529010135/http://unityandstruggle.org/2013/09/12/i-am-a-woman-and-a-human-a-marxist-feminist-critique-of-intersectionality-theory/ | archivedate = 2017-05-29 }} [http://libcom.org//files/intersectionality-pamphlet.pdf Pdf of pamphlet.]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="cornish2341"&gt;Cornish, Megan (2001), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=06Hvq8Yobc0C&amp;pg=PA5 Introduction]", in Radical Women, {{cite book | editor-last = Radical Women | editor-link = Radical Women | title = The Radical Women manifesto: socialist feminist theory, program and organizational structure | pages = 5&amp;ndash;16 | publisher = Red Letter Press | location = Seattle, Washington | isbn = 9780932323118 | year = 2001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="zetkin2134"&gt;{{cite book | last = Zetkin | first = Clara | author-link = Clara Zetkin | title = On a bourgeois feminist petition | url = https://www.marxists.org/archive/draper/1976/women/3-zetkin.html | year = 1895 }}
:''Cited in'': {{cite journal | last1 = Draper | first1 = Hal | last2 = Lipow | first2 = Anne G. | title = Marxist women ''versus'' bourgeois feminism | journal = [[The Socialist Register]] | volume = 13 | pages = 179&amp;ndash;226 | publisher = Merlin Press Ltd. | date = 1976 | url = http://www.socialistregister.com/index.php/srv/article/view/5399 | ref = harv }} [http://www.socialistregister.com/index.php/srv/article/view/5399/2298 Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="zetlen"&gt;{{cite book | last = Zetkin | first = Clara | author-link = Clara Zetkin | title = Lenin on the ''women's question'' | publisher = International Publishers | location = New York, N.Y. | url = https://www.marxists.org/archive/zetkin/1920/lenin/zetkin1.htm | origyear = 1920 | year = 1966 | oclc = 943938450 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="kol1"&gt;{{cite book | last = Kollontai | first = Alexandra | author-link = Alexandra Kollontai | title = The social basis of the woman question | publisher = Allison &amp; Busby | url = https://www.marxists.org/archive/kollonta/1909/social-basis.htm | origyear = 1909 | year = 1977 | oclc = 642100577 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="kollontai1324"&gt;{{cite book | last = Kollontai | first = Alexandra | author-link = Alexandra Kollontai | title = Women workers struggle for their rights | publisher = Falling Wall Press | location = London | url = https://www.marxists.org/archive/kollonta/1919/women-workers/ch01.htm | origyear = 1919 | year = 1976 | oclc =258289277 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="mies3412"&gt;{{citation | author-last = Mies | author-first = Maria | author-link = Maria Mies | contribution = Utopian socialism and women's emancipation | editor-last1 = Mies | editor-first1 = Maria  | editor-last2 = Jayawardena | editor-first2 = Kumari | editor-link1 = Maria Mies | editor-link2 = Kumari Jayawardena | title = Feminism in Europe: liberal and socialist strategies 1789-1919 | pages = 33&amp;ndash;80 | publisher = Institute of Social Studies | location = The Hague | year = 1981 | series = History of the Women's Movement | url = https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=QpCIoAEACAAJ | oclc = 906505149 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="marxist3124"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.marxist.com/marxism-and-feminism-in-the-student-movement.htm|title=Marxism and Feminism in the student movement|last=Britain|first=Marxist Student Federation-|website=In Defence of Marxism|language=en-gb|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="eisenstein"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Eisenstein|first=Hester|date=2017-04-01|title=Hegemonic feminism, neoliberalism and womenomics: 'empowerment' instead of liberation?|url=http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/10.3898/NEWF:91.02.2017|journal=New Formations|language=en|volume=91|issue=91|pages=35–49|doi=10.3898/NEWF:91.02.2017|issn=0950-2378}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite journal | last = Poonacha | first = Veena | title = Hindutva's hidden agenda: why women fear religious fundamentalism | journal = [[Economic and Political Weekly]] | volume = 28 | issue = 11 | pages = 438&amp;ndash;439 | publisher = Sameeksha Trust (India) | date = 13 March 1993 | url = http://www.epw.in/journal/1993/11/commentary/hindutva-s-hidden-agenda-why-women-fear-religious-fundamentalism.html | ref = harv }}

::''Cited in'': 
:::Louis, Prakash (2005), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=ZdPipb-u21gC&amp;pg=PA171 Hindutva and weaker sections: conflict between dominance and resistance]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Puniyani | editor-first = Ram | title = Religion, power &amp; violence: expression of politics in contemporary times | page = 171 | publisher = Sage | location = New Delhi Thousand Oaks | isbn = 9780761933380 | date = 2005-07-21 }}
::* Federici, S. B. (2014). ''[http://libcom.org/files/Caliban%20and%20the%20Witch.pdf Caliban and the witch]'' (2., rev. ed). New York, NY: Autonomedia.
::* Eisenstein, H. (2017). Hegemonic Feminism, Neoliberalism and Womenomics: “Empowerment” Instead of Liberation? New Formations, (91), 35–49. &lt;nowiki&gt;https://doi.org/10.3898/NEWF:91.02.2017&lt;/nowiki&gt;
::* Marxist &amp; Materialist Feminism - The Feminist eZine. (n.d.). Retrieved October 3, 2019, from http://www.feministezine.com/feminist/philosophy/Marxist-Materialist-Feminism.html
::* Seneviratne, P. (2018). ''[https://vc.bridgew.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2011&amp;context=jiws Marxist Feminism Meets Postcolonial Feminism in Organizational Theorizing: Issues, Implications and Responses]''. ''19''(2), 12.
::* Hennessy, R., &amp; Ingraham, C. (1997). ''Materialist Feminism: A reader in Class, Difference, and Women’s lives.'' Routledge.
::* Andrade, J. E.-J., &amp; Andrade, J. E.-J. (2015). [http://www.scielo.br/pdf/rbcpol/n18/2178-4884-rbcpol-18-00265.pdf O feminismo marxista e a demanda pela socialização do trabalho doméstico e do cuidado com as crianças. ''Revista Brasileira de Ciência Política''], (18), 265–300. &lt;nowiki&gt;https://doi.org/10.1590/0103-335220151810&lt;/nowiki&gt;
::* Dalla Costa, M., &amp; James, S. (2017). [http://libcom.org/files/Dalla%20Costa%20and%20James%20-%20Women%20and%20the%20Subversion%20of%20the%20Community.pdf The Power of Women and the Subversion of the Community]. In S. Aronowitz &amp; M. J. Roberts (Eds.), ''Class'' (pp. 79–86). &lt;nowiki&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119395485.ch7&lt;/nowiki&gt;
::

== External links ==
*[https://books.google.com/books?id=GrjPEY6yQNgC Marxism, Liberalism, And Feminism (Leftist Legal Thought)] New Delhi, Serials (2010) by Dr.Jur. Eric Engle LL.M.
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20030207061336/http://www.maoism.org/misc/prolefem.htm Proletarian Feminism]
*[http://silviafederici.littlerednotebook.com/ Silvia Federici, recorded live at Fusion Arts, NYC. 11.30.04]
*[http://www.feministissues.com/marxist.html Marxist Feminism]
*[http://www.internationalviewpoint.org/spip.php?article1308 Feminism of the Anti-Capitalist Left] by Lidia Cirillo

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Marxist Feminism}}
[[Category:Marxist schools of thought|Feminism]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Marxist feminism| ]]
[[Category:Socialist feminism|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>