<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20080812012711|231353882" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1099357" pageid="1099357" ns="0" title="Marxist feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-08-18T11:36:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Marxism}}{{Feminism sidebar}}
'''Marxist feminism''' is a sub-type of [[feminist theory]]  which focuses on the dismantling of [[capitalism]] as a way to liberate women. Marxist feminism states that private property, which gives rise to economic inequality, dependence, political confusion and ultimately unhealthy social relations between men and women, is the root of women's oppression in the current social context. 

According to [[Marxist theory]], the individual is heavily influenced by the structure of society, which in all modern societies mean a class structure; that is, people's opportunities, wants and interests are seen to be shaped by the mode of production that characterizes the society they inhabit. Marxist feminists see contemporary gender inequality as determined ultimately by the capitalist mode of production. Gender oppression is class oppression and women's subordination is seen as a form of class oppression which is maintained (like [[racism]]) because it serves the interests of capital and the [[ruling class]]. Marxist feminists have extended traditional Marxist analysis by looking at domestic labour as well as wage work in order to support their position.

[[Radical Women]], a major Marxist-feminist organization, bases its theory on Marx' and Engels' analysis that the enslavement of women was the first building block of an economic system based on private property. They contend that elimination of the capitalist profit-driven economy will remove the motivation for sexism, racism, homophobia and other forms of oppression.&lt;ref&gt;''The Radical Women Manifesto: Socialist Feminist Theory, Program and Organizational Structure''[http://www.redletterpress.org/rwmanifesto.html], Red Letter Press, 2001, ISBN 0-932323-11-1, pages 21-26.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Critiques of Marxist Feminism==
[[Gayle Rubin]], who has written on a certain range of subjects including sadomasochism, prostitution, pornography and lesbian literature as well as anthropological studies and histories of sexual subcultures, first rose to prominence through her 1975 essay ''"The Traffic in Women: Notes on the 'Political Economy' of Sex"'', in which she coins the phrase "sex/gender system" and criticizes  Marxism for what she claims is its incomplete analysis of sexism under capitalism, without dismissing or dismantling Marxist fundamentals in the process.

[[Radical feminism]], which emerged in the 1970s, also took issue with Marxist feminism. Radical feminist theorists stated that modern society and its constructs (law, religion, politics, art, ''etc'') are the product of males and therefore have a [[patriarchal]] character. According to those who subscribe to this view, the best solution for women's oppression would be to treat patriarchy not as a subset of capitalism but as a problem in its own right (see [[identity politics]]). Thus eliminating women's oppression means eliminating male domination in all its forms. Like most feminists, however, radical feminists believe in replacing such domination with a culture and policy of [[sexual equality|equality]].{{Fact|date=July 2008}} 

Austrian economist [[Ludwig von Mises]] argued against the Marxist account of the experience of women.  He argued that the women's movement was an evolutionary, rather than revolutionary, step that furthered gains that capitalism had secured for women.  He claimed to show that women gained along with the rise of classical liberalism.  Under this analysis, the marriage contract was actually a first, albeit imperfect, step toward liberating women from the subservient position they had held since the age of violence{{Fact|date=July 2007}}.

Proponents of [[Socialist feminism]] have also criticized the Marxist interpretation for failing to find an inherent connection between [[patriarchy]] and classism{{Fact|date=July 2007}}.

==See also==
*[[Radical Women]]
*[[The Origin of the Family, Private Property, and the State]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://silviafederici.littlerednotebook.com/ Silvia Federici, recorded live at Fusion Arts, NYC. 11.30.04]
*[http://www.feministissues.com/marxist.html Marxist Feminism]

[[Category:Marxism|Feminism, Marxist]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Feminism and social class]]

[[cs:Marxistický feminismus]]
[[de:Marxistischer Feminismus]]
[[el:Μαρξιστικός φεμινισμός]]
[[fa:فمینیسم مارکسیستی]]
[[hr:Marksistički feminizam]]
[[he:פמיניזם מרקסיסטי]]
[[mk:Марксистички феминизам]]
[[sh:Marksistički feminizam]]
[[sv:Marxistisk feminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>