<?xml version="1.0"?><api batchcomplete=""><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1099357" pageid="1099357" ns="0" title="Marxist feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-24T19:37:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">Feminist theory emerged in the 1970’s stating that law is predominantly a product of males and therefore has a patriarchal character. The purpose of feminist theory is to identify and articulate the perspectives, needs and rights of women. Feminism is divided except for one premise: the general neglect by male-dominated jurisprudence of the values, fears, and harms experienced by women.
Feminism is  an intellectual commitment and a political movement that seeks justice for women and the end of sexism in all forms. However, there are many different kinds of feminism. Feminists disagree about what sexism consists in, and what exactly ought to be done about it; they disagree about what it means to be a woman or a man and what social and political implications gender has or should have.
Marxist-feminism focus on destruction of capitalism as way to liberate women and states that capitalism, which gives rise of economic dependence, is the root of women's oppression. 
 Marxism in capitalist societies the individual is shaped by class relations; that is, people's capacities, needs and interests are seen to be determined by the mode of production that characterises the society they inhabit. 
Marxist feminists see gender inequality as determined ultimately by the capitalist mode of production and the major social divisions as class related. Women's subordination is seen as a form of oppression (rather than an illiberal discrimination) which is maintained because it serves the interests of capital . Marxist feminists have extended traditional Marxist analysis by looking at domestic labour as well as waged work</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>