<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131118044056|582154657" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1943640" pageid="1943640" ns="0" title="Intersectionality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-18T05:17:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Intersectionality''' (or '''Intersectionalism''') is the study of intersections between different disenfranchised groups or groups of [[minorities]]; specifically, the study of the interactions of multiple systems of [[oppression]] or [[discrimination]].&lt;ref name=WikitionaryRef&gt;{{cite web|title=Wikitionary definition of Intersectionality (also see intersectionalism)|url=http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/intersectionality}}&lt;/ref&gt; This [[Feminist sociology|feminist sociological]] theory was first highlighted by [[Kimberlé Crenshaw]] in 1989. Intersectionality is a methodology of studying "the relationships among multiple dimensions and modalities of social relationships and subject formations" (McCall 2005). The theory suggests that—and seeks to examine how—various biological, social and cultural categories such as [[gender]], [[Race (classification of humans)|race]], [[social class|class]], ability, [[sexual orientation]], [[species]], and other axes of [[Identity (social science)|identity]] interact on multiple and often simultaneous levels, contributing to systematic [[injustice]] and [[social inequality]]. Intersectionality holds that the classical conceptualizations of [[oppression]] within [[society]], such as [[racism]], [[sexism]], [[homophobia]], and belief-based [[bigotry]] including [[nationalism]], do not act independently of one another; instead, these forms of oppression interrelate, creating a system of oppression that reflects the "intersection" of multiple forms of [[discrimination]].&lt;ref&gt;Knudsen, Susanne. "Intersectionality—A Theoretical Inspiration in the Analysis of Minority Cultures and Identities in Textbooks." Caught in the Web or Lost in the Textbook 2006 61–76. 26 Nov 2007 http://www.caen.iufm.fr/colloque_iartem/pdf/knudsen.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==Concept==
A standard textbook example of intersectionality theory might be "the view that women experience [[oppression]] in varying configurations and in varying degrees of intensity" (Ritzer, 2007, pg. 204). Cultural patterns of oppression are not only interrelated, but are bound together and influenced by the intersectional systems of society. Examples of this include [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[gender]], [[Social class|class]], ability, and [[ethnicity]] (Collins, 2000, pg. 42).

Intersectionality is an important paradigm for [[sociology]] and [[cultural studies]], but there have been many challenges in utilizing it to its fullest capacity. Difficulties arise due to the many complexities involved in making "multidimensional conceptualizations"&lt;ref name="arjournals.annualreviews.org"&gt;Irene Browne, Joya Misra. "The Intersection of Gender and Race in the Labor Market." Annual Review of Sociology 29Jun 2003 487–513. 29 Nov 2007 http://arjournals.annualreviews.org/doi/abs/10.1146/annurev.soc.29.010202.100016&lt;/ref&gt; that explain the way in which socially constructed categories of differentiation interact to create a social hierarchy. For example, intersectionality holds that knowing a woman lives in a sexist society is insufficient information to describe her experience; instead, it is also necessary to know her race/ethnicity, sexual orientation, class, etc., as well as society's attitude toward each of these in order to fully understand her position within society.

The theory of intersectionality also suggests that discrete forms and expressions of oppression actually shape, and are shaped by, one another. Thus, in order to fully understand the [[racialization]] of oppressed groups, one must investigate the ways in which racializing structures, social processes, and [[social representation]]s (or ideas purporting to represent groups and group members in society) are shaped by gender, class, sexuality, etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Meyer|first=Doug|title=An Intersectional Analysis of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender (LGBT) People's Evaluations of Anti-Queer Violence|journal=Gender &amp; Society|year=2012|month=December|volume=26|issue=6|pages=849–873|doi=10.1177/0891243212461299|url=http://gas.sagepub.com/content/26/6/849.abstract}}&lt;/ref&gt;  While the theory began as an exploration of the oppression of women within society, today sociologists strive to apply it to all people and to many different intersections of group membership.

==Historical background of intersectionality==
{{Further|Critical theory}}
A comprehensive historical study of the development of intersectionality theory has yet to be documented. From the little documentation that exists, it is understood that the concept of intersectionality came to the forefront of sociological circles in the late 1960s and early 1970s in conjunction with the multiracial feminist movement. It came as part of a critique of [[radical feminism]] that had developed in the late 1960s known as the "re-visionist feminist theory." This re-visionist feminist theory "challenged the notion that 'gender' was the primary factor determining a woman's fate".&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;hooks, bell. Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center. 2nd. Cambridge, Massachusetts: South End Press, 1984&lt;/ref&gt;

The movement led by women of color disputed the idea that women were a homogeneous category sharing essentially the same life experiences. This argument stemmed from the realization that white middle-class women did not serve as an accurate representation of the feminist movement as a whole. Recognizing that the forms of oppression experienced by white middle-class women were different from those experienced by black, poor, or disabled women, feminists sought to understand the ways in which gender, race, and class combined to "determine the female destiny."&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; Leslie McCall, a leading intersectionality theorist, argues that the introduction of the intersectionality theory was vital to [[sociology]], claiming that before its development, there was little research that addressed specifically the experiences of people who are subjected to multiple forms of subordination within society.&lt;ref name="journals.uchicago.edu"&gt;McCall, Leslie. "The Complexity of Intersectionality." Journal of Women in Culture and Society, Vol. 30, No. 3, Spring 2005, pp. 1771–1800. http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/pdf/10.1086/426800&lt;/ref&gt;

The term also has historical and theoretical links to the concept of "simultaneity" advanced during the 1970s by members of the [[Combahee River Collective]], in [[Boston, Massachusetts]]. Members of this group articulated an awareness that their lives—and their forms of resistance to oppression—were profoundly shaped by the simultaneous influences of race, class, gender, and sexuality. Thus, the women of the Combahee River Collective advanced an understanding of African American experiences that challenged analyses emerging from Black and male-centered social movements; as well as those from mainstream White, middle-class, heterosexual feminists. Theories of intersectionality increasingly also address the more than human. Examples of posthuman intersectionality include [[ecofeminism]] and are under development in the field of [[animal studies]].

==Intersectionality theory and feminist thought==

The term ''intersectionality theory'' was first coined by [[Kimberlé Crenshaw]] in 1989. Crenshaw mentioned that the intersectionality experience within black women is more powerful than the sum of their race and sex, that any observations that do not take intersectionality into consideration cannot accurately address the manner in which black women are ''subordinated''.&lt;ref&gt;DeFrancisco, Victoria, P., Palczewski, Catherine, H (2007). ''Communicating Gender Diversity: A Critical Approach''. Los Angeles: Sage Publications.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term gained prominence in the 1990s when sociologist [[Patricia Hill Collins]] reintroduced the idea as part of her discussion on [[black feminism]]. This term replaced her previously coined expression "black feminist thought", "and increased the general applicability of her theory from African American women to all women" (Mann and Huffman, 2005, pg. 61). Much like her predecessor Crenshaw, Collins argued that cultural patterns of oppression are not only interrelated, but are bound together and influenced by the intersectional systems of society, such as race, gender, class, and ethnicity (Collins, 2000, pg. 42).

According to feminists of color, and many white feminists' experiences of class, gender, sexuality, etc., cannot be adequately understood unless the influences of racialization are carefully considered. Feminists argue that an understanding of intersectionality is a vital element to gaining political and social equality and improving our democratic system. Collins' theory is one of particular interest because it represents the sociological crossroads between [[second-wave feminism|modern]] and [post-modern] [[feminist theory|feminist thought]].

	Marie-Claire Belleau argues for "strategic intersectionality" (2007, 51) in order to foster cooperation between feminisms of different ethnicities.&lt;ref&gt;Belleau, Marie-Claire.  ""L'intersectionalité": Feminisms in a Divided World; Québec-Canada" in Feminist Politics: Identity, Difference, and Agency (eds. Deborah Orr et al.) Lanham, Maryland: Rowman and Littlefield Publishers, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  She refers to different nat-cult (national-cultural) groups that produce unique types of feminisms.  Using Québécois nat-cult as an example, Belleau acknowledges that many nat-cult groups contain infinite sub-identities within themselves.  Due to this infinity, she argues that there are endless ways in which different feminisms can cooperate by using strategic intersectionality, and these partnerships can help bridge gaps between "dominant and marginal" groups (Belleau, 2007, 54).   Belleau argues that, through strategic intersectionality, differences between nat-cult feminisms are neither essentialist nor universal, but that they should be understood as results of socio-cultural contexts.  Furthermore, the performances of these nat-cult feminisms are also not essentialist.  Instead, they are strategies.

Although Belleau's idea of strategic intersectionality could help foster cooperation between feminisms that are isolated from each other, the notion of national-cultural identities as strategic may be problematic.  Her argument implies that strategy and essentialism are a dichotomy.  However, if identities are strategies, then their inherent value can be questioned and nat-cult identities cannot be defended and preserved for their own sake since they are simply tools to a greater end.  If we reject strategic intersectionality, then, identities must be essentialist according to Belleau's dichotomy.  Essentialist identities are also problematic, however, since they can foster stereotyping and discrimination.  It may be more useful, therefore, to view nat-cult feminist identities as identities in flux.  Using a dynamic understanding of identity allows nat-cult identities to retain their inherent values and also to avoid nat-cult caricatures.

==The complexities of intersectionality==

There are three different approaches to studying intersectionality. The three approaches are anticategorical complexity, intercategorical complexity, and intracategorical complexity, and they serve to represent the broad spectrum of current methodologies that are used to better understand and apply the intersectionality theory.&lt;ref name="journals.uchicago.edu"/&gt;

#'''Anticategorical complexity''': The anti-categorical approach is based on the deconstruction of categorical divisions. It argues that social categories are an arbitrary construction of history and language and that they contribute little to understanding the ways in which people experience society. Furthermore the anticategorical approach states that, "inequalities are rooted in relationships that are defined by race, class, sexuality, and gender,"&lt;ref name="journals.uchicago.edu"/&gt; therefore the only way to eliminate oppression in society is to eliminate the categories used to section people into differing groups. This analysis claims that society is too complex to be reduced down into finite categories and instead recognizes the need for a holistic approach in understanding intersectionality.
#'''Intercategorical (aka categorical) complexity''': The intercategorical approach to intersectionality begins by addressing the fact that inequality exists within society, and then uses this as the base of its discussion of intersectionality. According to intercategorical complexity, "the concern is with the nature of the relationships among social groups and, importantly, how they are changing."&lt;ref name="journals.uchicago.edu"/&gt; Proponents of this methodology use existing categorical distinctions to document inequality across multiple dimensions and measure its change over time.
#'''Intracategorical complexity''': The intracategorical approach can best be explained as the midpoint between the anticategorical and intercategorical approaches. It recognizes the apparent shortcomings of existing social categories and it questions the way in which they draw boundaries of distinction. Yet, this approach does not completely reject the importance of categories like the anticategorical approach; rather the intracategorical approach recognizes the relevance of social categories to the understanding of the modern social experience. Moreover it attempts to reconcile these contrasting views by focusing on people who cross the boundaries of constructed categories, in an effort to understand the ways in which the complexity and intersectionality of the human experience unfold.

==Key concepts==

===Interlocking matrix of oppression===
Collins refers to the various intersections of social inequality as the [[Matrix of Domination]]. This is also known as "vectors of oppression and privilege" (Ritzer, 2007, pg. 204). These terms refer to how differences among people (sexual orientation, class, race, age, etc.) serve as oppressive measures towards women, and ultimately change the experiences of living as a woman in society. Collins, [[Audre Lorde]] (in Sister Outsider), and [[bell hooks]] point towards either/or thinking as an influence on this oppression and as further intensifying these differences. Specifically, Collins refers to this as the construct of dichotomous oppositional difference. This construct is characterized by its focus on differences rather than similarities (Collins, 1986, pg. S20).

For example, society commonly uses dichotomies as descriptors such as black/white or male/female. Additionally, these dichotomies are directly opposed to each other and intrinsically unstable, meaning they rarely represent equal relationships. In a 1986 article, Collins further relates this to why Black women experience oppression.

===Standpoint epistemology and the outsider within===
Both Collins and [[Dorothy Smith]] have been instrumental in providing a sociological definition of [[standpoint theory]]. A standpoint is an individual's unique world perspective. The theoretical basis of this approach involves viewing societal knowledge as being located within an individual's specific geographic location. In turn, knowledge becomes distinctly unique and subjective—it varies depending upon the social conditions under which it was produced (Mann and Kelley, 1997, pg. 392).

The concept of the outsider within refers to a special standpoint encompassing the [[Self (sociology)|self]], family, and [[society]] (Collins, 1986, pg. S14). This relates to the specific experiences to which people are subjected as they move from a common cultural world (i.e. family) to that of the modern society (Ritzer, 2007, pg. 207). Therefore, even though a woman (especially a Black woman) may become influential in a particular field, she may feel as though she never quite belongs. Essentially, their personalities, behaviors, and cultural beings overshadow their true value as an individual; thus, they become the outsider within (Collins, 1986, pg. S14).

===Resisting oppression===
Speaking from a [[critical theory|critical]] standpoint, Collins points out that Brittan and Maynard claim "domination always involves the [[objectification]] of the dominated; all forms of oppression imply the devaluation of the subjectivity of the oppressed" (Collins, 1986, pg S18). She later notes that self-evaluation and self-definition are two ways of resisting oppression. Participating in [[self-awareness]] methods helps to preserve the self-esteem of the group that is being oppressed and help them avoid any dehumanizing outside influences.

Marginalized groups often gain a status of being an "other" (Collins, 1986, pg. S18). In essence, you are "an other" if you are different from what [[Audre Lorde]] calls the [[Normality (behavior)|mythical norm]]. "Others" are virtually anyone that differs from the societal [[Schema (psychology)|schema]] of an average white male. [[Gloria Anzaldúa]] theorizes that the sociological term for this is "[[othering]]", or specifically attempting to establish a person as unacceptable based on certain criterion that fails to be met (Ritzer, 2007, pg. 205).

Individual subjectivity is another concern for marginalized groups. Differences can be used as a weapon of self-devaluation by internalizing stereotypical societal views, thus leading to a form of psychological oppression. (In [[psychology]] this is known as a [[self-fulfilling prophecy]].) The point Collins effectively makes is that having a sense of self-value and a stable self-definition not obtained from outside influences helps to overcome these oppressive societal methods of domination.

===Applications of intersectionality===

SECTION I – Policies, practices, procedures and laws (PPPL) 
Intersectionality is “[a]n interdisciplinary approach that considers”(Hancock 2005) two or more intersections of race, class, gender, sexuality, and disability as “simultaneous processes” (Holvino 2010) that identify and rank members of society through systems of power and social relations (Jones 2003; McWhorter 2004) and  influences “political access, equality and the potential for any form of justice (Hancock 2005). 

In addition to the definition of social structure: "rules [policies, practices, procedures, and laws] regulating the allocation of power and resources along race/gender lines" (Nakano Glenn 2004). A few examples of how the application of social structure existed historically can be seen in [[Black codes]] and [[Jim Crow laws]], however, the most recent application is [[racial profiling]]. 
In order to understand how intersectionality applies in real world systems within PPPL one can draw attention to political and structural inequalities (Cho, Crenshaw &amp; McCall 2013). Two recent examples:

Voting Rights Act Section 5: On June 25, 2013 The United States Supreme Court invalidated the formula used to determine which states are covered by Section 5 of the Voting Rights Act. This decision no longer requires pre-approval by certain states to change voting rules. According to the Brennan Center for Justice, Section 5 blocked laws in 2012 that restricted voting rights for minority American citizens; communities of color, elderly, disabled, and college students, in Texas, South Carolina and Florida. In the aftermath the Department of Justice is seeking to block North Carolina restrictive voting laws. http://www.brennancenter.org/newsletter/voting-newsletter-doj-challenges-north-carolina-restrictions 

School-to-Prison-Pipeline: Zero tolerance policies in schools have led to a significant increase in disciplinary actions that involve the presence of law enforcement officers. In some states, such as Mississippi, one school district has police arrest students for minor classroom behaviors and a district in Alabama has a police officer onsite in their high schools (Elias 2013). There are disproportionate numbers of racial minorities and children with disabilities who are subjected to this institutional system of structural inequality. http://www.tolerance.org/magazine/number-43-spring-2013/school-to-prison

SECTION II – Applications of intersectionality
Some scholars have called for a wider net to be cast to include the practices in the political world (Hancock, 2007; Holvino, 2010), education (McCall, 2005; Jones 2003; Cooper 2009), healthcare (Kelly 2009) (Viruell-Fuentes, Miranda &amp; Abdulrahim 2012), employment, wealth, and property (Ladson-Billings &amp; Tate IV 1995).
Within the institution of education, Jones’ (2003) research on working class women in academia discusses the notion of meritocracy through the ranks of social strata but becomes further complicated by race and the additional external forces that oppress. In the systems of healthcare and people of color, researchers found that six months post 9/11 an increase in poor birth outcomes of children with parents with “Arab” or “Muslim” sounding names and how immigration policies also directly impact the fundamental causes of disease (Viruell-Fuentes, Miranda &amp; Abdulrahim 2012), Additionally applications with regard to property and wealth can be traced to the American historical narrative that is filled “with tensions and struggles over property-in its various forms. From the removal of Indians (and later Japanese Americans) from the land, to military conquest of the Mexicans, to the construction of Africans as property the ability to define, possess, and own property has been a central feature of power in America…[and  where] social benefits accrue largely to property owners” (Ladson-Billings &amp; Tate IV 1995) that is visible through generations to date.
One would apply the intersectionality framework analysis to various areas where race, class, gender, sexuality and ability are affected by policies, procedures, practices, and laws in “context-specific inquiries, including, for example, analyzing the multiple ways that race and gender interact with class in the labor market; interrogating the ways that states constitute regulatory regimes of identity, reproduction, and family formation..” (Cho, Crenshaw &amp; McCall 2013); examining the inequities in “the power relations [of the intersectionality] of whiteness.. [where] the denial of power and privilege .. of whiteness, and middle-classness..” thereby not addressing “the role of power it wields in social relations (Levine-Rasky, 2011).
[[User:CNoemiM|CNoemiM]] ([[User talk:CNoemiM|talk]]) 04:33, 18 November 2013 (UTC)
====Intersectionality and social work====
In the field of [[social work]], proponents of intersectionality hold that unless service providers take intersectionality into account, they will be of less use, and may in fact be detrimental, for various segments of the population. Thus, service providers have an obligation to be aware of the seemingly unrelated factors that can impact a person's life experience and response to the service and to adapt their methods accordingly. For instance, according to intersectionality, [[domestic violence]] counselors in the [[United States of America|United States]] that urged all women to report their abusers to police would be of little use to [[women of color]] due to the history of racially-motivated [[police brutality]] in that population, and those counselors should therefore develop a different approach appropriate for women of color.

Women with disabilities encounter more frequent domestic abuse, with a greater number of abusers. Health care workers and personal care attendants are also perpetrators in these circumstances and women with disabilities have fewer options for leaving the abusive situation. There is a "silence" principle concerning the intersectionality of women and disability, which maintains that there is an overall social denial of the prevalence of the abused and disabled and this abuse is frequently ignored when encountered. The paradox is the overprotection of people with disabilities combined with the expectations of promiscuous behavior of disabled women. This is met with limiting autonomy and isolating the individuals, which place women with disabilities in situations where further abuse, or more frequent abuse can occur. &lt;ref&gt;Lockhart, Lettie, Fran S. Danis. (2010). Domestic violence: intersectionality and culturally competent practice. Columbia University Press&lt;/ref&gt;

====Intersectionality and psychology====
Research in psychology has lagged behind other [[Social science|social]] and behavioral science fields in fully incorporating intersectionality into their theory or methods. Psychologists who study social processes and organization tend to think of intersecting identities as separable categories. That is, they assume that the research project can separate, for example, the effects of gender and socioeconomic status from one another. Some recent publications point to the development of a more sophisticated psychology of intersecting identities.&lt;ref&gt;"Gender: An Intersectionality Perspective" Sex Roles September 2008. http://www.springerlink.com/content/l81626817g48/?p=5cae742e006641daad50f3d29a7ae811&amp;pi=0&lt;/ref&gt;

====Intersectionality and the labor market====
The intersectionality of race and gender has been shown to have a visible impact on the labor market. "Sociological research clearly shows that accounting for education, experience, and skill does not fully explain significant differences in labor market outcomes." The three main domains on which we see the impact of intersectionality are wages, discrimination, and domestic labor. Most studies have shown that people who fall into the bottom of the social hierarchy in terms of race or gender are more likely to receive lower wages, to be subjected to [[stereotype]]s and discriminated against, or be hired for exploitive domestic positions. Through the study of the labor market and intersectionality we gain a better understanding of economic inequalities and the implications of the multidimensional impact of race and gender on social status within society.&lt;ref name="arjournals.annualreviews.org"/&gt;

====A Marxist-feminist critical theory====
Collins’ intersectionality theory and its relative principles have a wide range of applicability in the sociological realm, especially in topics such as [[politics]] and [[violence]] (see, for instance, Collins, 1998). A central tenet of interest is on the struggle faced by Black women in the economic sector. This provides a wonderful example of how the interrelated principles of Collins’ theory come together to add a new twist to a [[Marxian economics|Marxist economic theory]]. A brief historical perspective will allow for better understanding of how Collins used her insight and built a dynamic theory of political oppression as related to Black women in particular.

[[W. E. B. Du Bois]] theorized that the intersectional paradigms of race, class, and nation might explain certain aspects of Black political economy. Collins writes "Du Bois saw race, class, and nation not primarily as personal identity categories but as social hierarchies that shaped African American access to status, poverty, and power" (2000, pg. 42). Interestingly, Du Bois omitted gender from his theory, and considered it more of a personal identity category.

Cheryl Townsend Gilkes further expands upon this by pointing out the value of centering upon the experiences of Black Women. Joy James takes things one step further by "using paradigms of intersectionality in interpreting social phenomena" (Collins, 2000, pg. 44). Collins later integrated these three views by examining a Black political economy through both the centering of Black women's experiences and using a theoretical framework of intersectionality (Collins, 2000, pg. 44).

Collins uses a "[[Marxist feminist]]" approach and applies her intersectional principles to what she calls the "work/family nexus and black women's poverty". In her 2000 article "Black Political Economy" she describes how the intersections of [[consumer racism]], gender hierarchies, and disadvantages in the labor market can be centered on Black women's unique experiences (pg. 45–46). Considering this from a historical perspective examining interracial marriage laws and property inheritance laws creates what Collins terms a "distinctive work/family nexus that in turn influences the overall patterns of Black political economy" (pg. 46).

A historical example will clarify this and provide a more precise case of this application. Essentially, [[anti-miscegenation laws]] effectively suppressed the potential economic rising of black women. Many times, a marriage can be economically stabilizing for both husband and wife. However, since Black women were outlawed from marrying White men, Black women were denied access to sharing the prosperities of White male property. In essence, their biracial children were deprived of this as well. A perhaps [[latent function|latent consequence]] of this was the regulation of wealth for Black women.

==See also==
* [[Humanism]]
* [[Kyriarchy]]
* [[Womanism]]

==Citations==
{{reflist}}

==Selected bibliography==
* ''Race, Class and Gender: An Anthology'', ISBN 0-534-52879-1, co-edited by Patricia Hill Collins and Margaret Andersen, 1992, 1995, 1998, 2001, 2004, 2007
* ''[[Black Feminist Thought: Knowledge, Consciousness and the Politics of Empowerment]]'', ISBN 0-415-92484-7, by Patricia Hill Collins, 1990, 2000
* [[Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw|Crenshaw, Kimberlé W.]] (1991). ''Mapping the Margins: Intersectionality, Identity Politics, and Violence against Women of Color'', Stanford Law Review, Vol. 43, No. 6., pp.&amp;nbsp;1241–1299.
*Collins, P.H. (2000). Gender, Black Feminism, and Black Political Economy. Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 568. 41–53.
*Collins, P.H. (1986). Learning From the Outsider Within: The Sociological Significance of Black Feminist Thought. ''Social Problems'', 33 (6). S14–S32.
*Collins, P.H. (1998). The tie that binds: race, gender, and US violence. ''Ethnic and Racial Studies'', 21 (5).
*Mann, S.A. &amp; Kelley, L.R. (1997). Standing at the Crossroads of Modernist Thought: Collins, Smith, and the New Feminist Epistemologies. Gender and Society, 11(4). 391–408.
*Mann, S.A &amp; Huffman, D.J. (2005). The Decentering of Second Wave Feminism and the Rise of the Third Wave. Science and Society, 69 (1). 56–91.
*Lee, Butch &amp; Rover, Red (1993), Night-Vision: Illuminating War and Class on the Neo-Colonial Terrain. New York: Vagabond Press. ISBN 1-883780-00-4
*Ritzer, G. (2007). Contemporary Sociological Theory and Its Classical Roots: The Basics. Boston: McGraw-Hill.
*Siltanen, J. &amp; A. Doucet (2008) Gender Relations in Canada: Intersectionality and Beyond. Toronto: Oxford University Press
*Gutierrez y Muhs, G., Flores Niemann, Y., Gonzalez C.G. &amp; Harris, A.P. (2012). Presumed Incompetent: The Intersections of Race and Class for Women in Academia. Utah State University Press. ISBN 978-0-87421-922-7
*Lockhart, Lettie, Fran S. Danis. (2010). Domestic violence: intersectionality and culturally competent practice. Columbia University Press

==External links==
*[http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/45a/252.html Black Feminist Thought in the Matrix of Domination]
*[http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/Organizations/healthnet/WoC/feminisms/collins2.html Black Feminist Thought]
*[http://www.rpi.edu/~eglash/eglash.dir/SST/bft.htm A Brief History of Black Feminist Thought]
*[http://www.sagepub.co.uk/upm-data/13299_Chapter_16_Web_Byte_Patricia_Hill_Collins.pdf Intersectionality Theory]
*[http://girlwpen.com/?page_id=1724 The Intersectional Feminist Archives - GirlwPen.com]
* [http://www.intersectionality.org Transnational and transdisciplinary network on intersectionality for young scholars: www.intersectionality.org]
* [http://www.americanbar.org/content/dam/aba/publishing/perspectives_magazine/women_perspectives_Spring2004CrenshawPSP.authcheckdam.pdf "Intersectionality: The Double Bind of Race and Gender"], interview with Kimberlé Crenshaw, [[American Bar Association]], spring 2004

[[Category:Intersectional feminism| ]]
[[Category:Intersectionality| ]]
[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Critical theory]]

'''Annotated Bibliography'''Applications of Intersectionality Sections I and II
Appelbaum, B, &amp; Gebeloff, R.(2012, February 13). Who benefits from the safety net? The New York Times. Retrieved from http://economix.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/02/13/who-benefits-from-the-safety-net/. A news article that discusses the findings of the research study carried out by the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities in simplified terms for the general public.
Brah, A., &amp; Phoenix, A. (May 01, 2004). Ain't I a Woman? Revisiting Intersectionality.Journal of International Women's Studies, 5, 3, 75-86. The authors discuss the historical events, past and recent from anti-slavery and women’s suffrage to gulf war, and the relevance they continue to have on the intersections of race, class, gender and/or sexuality in present day by using primary sources and empirical research texts. The authors also review, at the time, recent theories and concepts to stimulate further discussions on intersectionality.
Brennan Center for Justice. (October 04, 2013) Voting Newsletter: DOJ Challenges North Carolina Restrictions. TheBrennan Center for Justice. Retrieved from http://www.brennancenter.org/newsletter/voting-newsletter-doj-challenges-north-carolina-restrictions. This website is based at the New York University School of Law that offers a legal challenge to policies, laws and practices that institutional structures construct. For my analysis on voting rights issues to show an example of political inequality.
Crenshaw, K. (1991). Mapping the margins: Intersectionality, identity politics, and violence against women of color. Stanford law review, 1241-129. As the scholar to introduce the theory of intersectionality Crenshaw follows up in this article a discussion on how identity politics of women of color is still being marginalized within groups of gender and race and to further explore the issues related to violence against women of color.
Elias, M. (June 06, 2013). The School-to-Prison Pipeline. Teaching Tolerance, 52, 43, 39-40. Article that discusses how the institutional racism of education impacts students of color in the United States.
Hancock, A.-M. (January 01, 2005). W.E.B. Du Bois: Intellectual Forefather of Intersectionality?. Souls, 7, 74-84. Hancock’s intersectionality analysis draws upon the perspective of W.E.B. Du Bois by using his work as her primary source that in its deep intellectual prose offers support to current day intersectionality theory and political world. 
Hancock, A.-M. (January 01, 2007). Intersectionality as a Normative and Empirical Paradigm. Politics &amp; Gender, 3, 2, 248-254. In this article Hancock appeals to the understanding that intersectionality is far more than the scholarly specialized work within women studies. Intersectionality requires a more broadened audience in the political world and the power wielded that is excludes intersections globally.
Holvino, E. (May 01, 2010). Intersections: The Simultaneity of Race, Gender and Class in Organization Studies. Gender, Work &amp; Organization, 17, 3, 248-277. In this article Holvino calls for a new concept to be drawn on practices related to identity, institutions, and society with regard to intersections of gender, race, ethnicity, sexuality, and class. The call is for organizations to include more people of color, more funded research and societal links to be connected and practiced by widening a better understanding of intersections.
Intersectionality. (June 01, 2007). Politics &amp; Gender, 3, 2, 229-232. In this brief editorial, a focus is made on how individual subjects of multiple identities known as intersectionality changes the political landscape when it is taken into consideration. It provides information on five scholarly articles on the topic of which I have also sourced.
Intersektionalitet Organization. (2011). http://www.intersektionalitet.org/en/what-is-intersectionality-3/. Website created in Sweden in association with Civis, an international peace organization, and supported by Ungdomsstyrelsen, National Board for Youth Affairs, a Swedish government agency, that focuses on providing information related to intersectionality such as literature, organizations, events, and discussion forum based on the topic. Although updates seem to be abandoned access to other sources are available.
Jones, S. J. (2003). Complex Subjectivities: Class, Ethnicity, and Race in Women's Narratives of Upward Mobility. Journal Of Social Issues, 59(4), 803. doi:10.1046/j.0022-4537.2003.00091.x. Jones raises issues of how intersections of working class professors require more attention by using personal narratives in her analysis and a call for research and activism to include social class understanding in academic and public education.
McCall, L. (March 01, 2005). The Complexity of Intersectionality. Signs, 30, 3, 1771-1800. McCall questions the limited teaching practices of intersectionality as part of the interdisciplinary section of women studies. The primary focus is to discuss, with supporting evidence, how to expand research on intersectionality by opening inhibiting concerns that create obstacles for a bigger scope on the topic.
Nakano-Glenn, Evelyn. Unequal Freedom: How Race and Gender Shaped American Citizenship and Labor. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 2004. Print. I have chosen specific pages and examples to assist me in defining intersectionality and relationality from Nakano-Glenn as additional supporting evidence. The literature covers an array of other subjects such as history, sociology, theory and concepts. I have chosen to use the simplest sections of the material to assist me in my project focus of intersectionality.
Phoenix, A. (August 01, 2006). Editorial: Intersectionality. European Journal of Women's Studies, 13, 3. Phoenix introduces the value and importance of intersectionality stimulated by the European Journal of Women’s Studies 10th anniversary and draws attention to the increasing number of conferences focused on intersectionality. The editorial directs reader to the key topics that will be discussed in the journal by various scholarly articles on intersectionality.
Sherman, A., Greenstein, R., &amp; Ruffing, K. (2012). Contrary to ‘Entitlement Society’Rhetoric, Over Nine-Tenths of Entitlement Benefits Go to Elderly, Disabled, or Working Households. Center on Budget and Policy Priorities. A research report detailing the demographics; age, race, employment and other factors, of benefit programs and costs. 
Velasquez, T.. Lecture at University of Washington: Women, Race, and Class. Theory, concepts, research, definition provided for topic of intersectionality project. The various class materials created an understanding of how  intersectionality and relationality impacts social structures in Western culture and deepens critical thinking of its influence in daily operations through raising the  awareness of how America’s social structures impact race, class, and gender.
Weber, L. (1998). A conceptual framework for understanding race, class, gender, and sexuality. Psychology of Women Quarterly, 22(1), 13-32. In this article Weber provides a basic six piece section of explanation in order to provide an understanding of the most common themes found in intersectionality. The intersectional themes discussed are context, social constructions, systems of power, macro (social structural) and micro (social psychological), simultaneous expression, and interdependence of knowledge and activism.
Viruell-Fuentes, E. A., Miranda, P. Y., &amp; Abdulrahim, S. (December 01, 2012). More than culture: Structural racism, intersectionality theory, and immigrant health. Social Science &amp;amp; Medicine, 75, 12, 2099-2106. Analysis through the lens of intersectionality on how structural racism impacts the health of immigrants and generations of people of color through access and disease.
[[User:CNoemiM|CNoemiM]] ([[User talk:CNoemiM|talk]]) 04:40, 18 November 2013 (UTC)</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>