<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20070922160537|159619381" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1943640" pageid="1943640" ns="0" title="Intersectionality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-09-22T16:22:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Merge|Intersectionality theory|date=August 2007}}
'''Intersectionality''' is a [[paradigm]]atic approach to [[sociology]], [[cultural studies]], and other social sciences, especially as applied to [[activism]] and [[social work]].  Intersectionality holds that the classical models of [[oppression]] within a society, such as those based on [[racism|race]]/[[ethnicity]]; [[sexism|gender]], [[religious discrimination|religion]], [[homophobia|sexuality]], [[classism|class]], [[ableism|disability]] and other markers of difference do not act independent of one another.  Instead, these forms of oppression interrelate, based on which markers apply to a given individual and/or oppressed social group and derives its name from this intersection of forms of oppression).  Intersectionality thus holds that knowing, for example, that a woman lives in a sexist society is insufficient information to describe her experience; instead, it is also necessary to know her race, her sexual orientation, her class, etc.  The theory of intersectionality also holds that discrete forms, or expressions, of oppression actually shape, and are shaped by, one another.  Thus, for an example, in order to fully understand the racialization of oppressed groups in the United States, one must investigate and examine the ways in which racializing structures, social processes, and social representations (or ideas purporting to represent groups and group members in society) are shaped by gender, class, sexuality, etc.  In turn, according to feminists of color--who have been the major contributors to intersectional theory during the past several decades--experiences of class, gender, sexuality, etc., cannot be adequately understood unless the influences of racialization are carefully considered.  Such an exacting approach to scholarly and activist investigations is often daunting, and thus rejected by many.  Yet feminists of color respond by pointing to the many flawed analyses and foundering interventions that have resulted from simplistic and distorting approaches that have assumed that discrete principles of social organization operate independently rather than interdependently in U.S. society.  Feminists also note the importance of intersectional understandings if organizational and political practice are to become more inclusive and democratic.

While scholars and some activists have rightly attributed the term "intersectionality" to
African American feminist and legal scholar, Kimberle Crenshaw; the term also has historical and theoretical links to the concept of "simultaneity" advanced during the 1970s by members of the Combahee River Collective, in Massachusetts.  Members of that group articulated their awareness that their lives--and their forms of resistance to oppression--were profoundly shaped by the simultaneous influences of race, class, gender, and sexuality.  Thus, the women of the Combahee River Collective advanced an understanding of African American experiences that challenged analyses emerging from Black and male-centered social movement circles; as well as from analyses of mainstream White, middle-class, heterosexual feminists.

In the field of social work, proponents of intersectionality hold that unless service providers take intersectionality into account, they will be of less use, and may in fact be detrimental, for various segments of the population.  Thus, service providers have an obligation to be aware of the seemingly unrelated factors that can impact a person's life experience and response to the service and to adapt their methods accordingly.  For instance, according to intersectionality, [[domestic violence]] counselors in the [[United States of America|United States]] that urged all women to report their abusers to police would be of little use to [[women of color]] due to the history of racially-motivated [[police brutality]] in that population, and those counselors should therefore develop a different approach appropriate for women of color.

==Selected bibliography==
*''[[Race, Class and Gender: An Anthology]]'', ISBN 0-534-52879-1, co-edited by Patricia Hill Collins and Margaret Andersen, [[1992]], [[1995]], [[1998]], [[2001]], [[2004]], [[2007]]
*''[[Black Feminist Thought: Knowledge, Consciousness and the Politics of Empowerment]]'', ISBN 0-415-92484-7, by Patricia Hill Collins, [[1990]], [[2000]]

[[Category:Activism]]

{{socio-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>