<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181119000453|869496362" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1943640" pageid="1943640" ns="0" title="Intersectionality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-22T14:22:52Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{merge from|Triple oppression|discuss=Talk:Intersectionality#Proposed merge with Triple oppression|date=October 2018}}
{{mi|
{{third-party|date=October 2018}}
{{Globalize|date=September 2018}}
{{context|date=October 2018}}
}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2018}}
{{Discrimination_sidebar}}
'''Intersectionality''' is an [[analytic framework]] that attempts to identify how interlocking systems of power impact those who are most marginalized in society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Intersectionality|volume = 1|last=Cooper|first=Brittney|date=1 February 2016|language=en|doi=10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199328581.013.20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Intersectionality considers that various forms of [[social stratification]], such as [[Social class|class]], [[race (human categorization)|race]], [[sexual orientation]], age, religion, creed, [[disability]] and [[gender]], do not exist separately from each other but are interwoven together. While the theory began as an exploration of the oppression of women of color within society, today the analysis is potentially applied to all social categories (including social identities usually seen as dominant when considered independently).

==Historical background==
{{external media|width=210px|align=right | topic = [[Women of the World Festival|Women of the World Festival 2016]] | video1 = [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-DW4HLgYPlA ''Kimberlé Crenshaw – On Intersectionality''] via [[Southbank Centre]] on [[YouTube]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite AV media | people= [[Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw|Kimberlé Crenshaw]] | date= 14 March 2016 |accessdate= 31 May 2016 | title= Kimberlé Crenshaw – On Intersectionality – keynote – WOW 2016 | medium= Video | publisher= [[Southbank Centre]] via YouTube| url = https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-DW4HLgYPlA }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The concept of intersectionality is intended to illuminate dynamics that have often been overlooked in feminist movements and theory.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Thompson | first = Becky | title = Multiracial feminism: recasting the chronology of Second Wave Feminism | journal = [[Feminist Studies]] | volume = 28 | issue = 2 | page = 337 | doi = 10.2307/3178747 | jstor = 3178747 | date = Summer 2002 | ref = harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; As articulated by [[bell hooks]], such an approach "challenged the notion that 'gender' was the primary factor determining a woman's fate".&lt;ref name="bell hooks 2014"&gt;{{cite book | last = hooks | first = bell | title = Feminist Theory: from margin to center | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 2014 | origyear = 1984 | edition = 3rd | isbn = 9781138821668 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This exploration stemmed from a historical exclusion of black women from the feminist movement that had been challenged since the 19th century by black feminists such as [[Anna J. Cooper|Anna Julia Cooper]]. 
The movement led by women of color disputed the idea, common to earlier feminist movements, that women were a homogeneous category who shared the same life experiences. This argument stemmed from the realization that white middle-class women did not serve as an accurate representation of the feminist movement as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Davis | first = Angela Y. | author-link = Angela Davis | title = Women, Race &amp; Class | publisher = Vintage Books | location = New York | year = 1983 | isbn = 9780394713519 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Recognizing that the forms of oppression experienced by white middle-class women were different from those experienced by black, poor, or disabled women, feminists sought to understand the ways in which gender, race, and class combined to "determine the female destiny".&lt;ref name="bell hooks 2014"/&gt;

First wave feminism focused on gaining political equality between men and women; however, racial inequality was a factor that was largely ignored by the movement. Consequently, early women's rights movements are often seen as exclusively pertaining to white women's membership, concerns, and struggles.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Gendered Lives: Communication, Gender, &amp; Culture|last=Fixmer-Oraiz,and Wood|first=Natalie, and Julia|publisher=Cengage Learning|year=2015|isbn=978-1-305-28027-4|location=Boston, MA|pages=59–60}}&lt;/ref&gt; Third wave feminism is noted for its efforts to understand the multiple layers of oppression present within injustice towards women. Third wave feminism notes the lack of attention to race, class, sexual orientation, and gender identity in early feminist movements, and tries to provide a channel to address political and social disparities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Gendered Lives: Communication, Gender, &amp; Culture|last=Fixmer-Oraiz, and Wood|first=Natalie, and Julia|publisher=Cengage Learning|year=2015|isbn=978-1-305-28027-4|location=Boston, MA|pages=72–73}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since these factors were not part of the main stream feminism movement, they were seen as struggles that were independent of each other. Intersectionality is a concept that recognizes these issues that were not a part of early social justice movements. 
Leslie McCall argues that the introduction of the intersectionality theory was vital to sociology, claiming that before its development there was little research that specifically addressed the experiences of people who are subjected to multiple forms of subordination within society.&lt;ref name="journals.uchicago.edu"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = McCall | first = Leslie | title = The complexity of intersectionality | journal = [[Signs (journal)|Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society]] | volume = 30 | issue = 3 | pages = 1771–1800 | doi = 10.1086/426800 | date = Spring 2005 | jstor = 10.1086/426800 | ref = harv }} [http://anthropology.msu.edu/anp270-us15/files/2015/05/The-Complexity-of-intersectionality-McCall-2005.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The term also has historical and theoretical links to the concept of "simultaneity" advanced during the 1970s by members of the [[Combahee River Collective]], in [[Boston, Massachusetts]].&lt;ref&gt;Wiegman, Robyn (2012), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=PAC_r_0nXFsC&amp;pg=PA244 Critical kinship (universal aspirations and intersectional judgements)]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Wiegman | editor-first = Robyn | title = Object lessons | page = 244 | publisher = Duke University Press | location = Durham, North Carolina | isbn = 9780822351603 | ref = harv | date = 2012-01-11 }}
:''Citing'':
:* {{cite book | last1 = Hull | first1 = Gloria T. | last2 = Bell-Scott | first2 = Patricia | last3 = Smith | first3 = Barbara | title = All the women are White, all the Blacks are men, but some of us are brave: Black women's studies | publisher = [[Feminist Press]] | location = Old Westbury, N.Y | year = 1982 | isbn = 9780912670928 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of this group articulated an awareness that their lives, and their forms of resistance to oppression, were profoundly shaped by the simultaneous influences of race, class, gender, and sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Einstein | first = Zillah | title = The Combahee River Collective Statement | publisher = [[Combahee River Collective]] | date = 1978 | url = http://circuitous.org/scraps/combahee.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, the women of the Combahee River Collective advanced an understanding of African-American experiences that challenged analyses emerging from Black and male-centered social movements, as well as those from mainstream white, middle-class, heterosexual feminists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Norman | first = Brian | title = 'We' in Redux: The Combahee River Collective's ''Black Feminist Statement'' | journal = [[Differences (journal)|differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies]] | volume = 18 | issue = 2 | page = 104 | doi = 10.1215/10407391-2007-004 | date = 2007 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other writers and theorists were using intersectional analysis in their work before the term was coined. For example, Chicana feminist theorist [[Gloria E. Anzaldúa|Gloria Anzaldúa]]'s work is described by [[Gloria Wekker]] as exemplifying how, "Existent categories for identity are strikingly not dealt with in separate or mutually exclusive terms, but are always referred to in relation to one another."&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Doing Gender in Media, Art and Culture: A Comprehensive Guide to Gender Studies|last=Buikema, Plate &amp; Thiele|first=R., L., K.|publisher=Routeledge|year=2009|isbn=978-0415493833|location=|pages=63–65}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wekker also points to the words and activism of [[Sojourner Truth|Sojourner Truth]] as an example of an intersectional approach to social justice.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

==Feminist thought==
{{Feminism sidebar}}
In 1989, [[Kimberlé Crenshaw]] became the first person to use the word "intersectionality" in the context of feminism.&lt;ref&gt;https://philpapers.org/archive/CREDTI.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/lifestyle/2014/04/kimberl-crenshaw-intersectionality-i-wanted-come-everyday-metaphor-anyone-could|title=Kimberlé Crenshaw on intersectionality: 'I wanted to come up with an everyday metaphor that anyone could use'|date=2 April 2014 |work=[[New Statesman]] |access-date=2016-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;The first use of the term was in a crucial 1989 paper written by Crenshaw for the University of Chicago Legal Forum, "Demarginalizing the Intersection of Race and Sex: A Black Feminist Critique of Antidiscrimination Doctrine, Feminist Theory and Antiracist Politics".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://archive.org/stream/DemarginalizingTheIntersectionOfRaceAndSexABlackFeminis/Demarginalizing+the+Intersection+of+Race+and+Sex_+A+Black+Feminis_djvu.txt|title=Full text of "Demarginalizing The Intersection Of Race And Sex A Black Feminis"|website=archive.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 1989"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Crenshaw | first = Kimberlé | author-link = Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw | title = Demarginalizing the intersection of race and sex: a Black feminist critique of antidiscrimination doctrine, feminist theory and antiracist politics | journal = [[University of Chicago Legal Forum]] | volume = 1989 | pages = 139–168 | date = 1989| url = http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?handle=hein.journals/uchclf1989&amp;div=10 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; In her work, Crenshaw discussed [[Black feminism]], which argues that the experience of being a black woman cannot be understood in terms of being black and of being a woman considered independently, but must include interactions between the two identities, which frequently reinforce each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last1 = Thomas | first1 = Sheila | last2 = Crenshaw | first2 = Kimberlé | author-link2 = Kimberlé Crenshaw | title = Intersectionality: the double bind of race and gender | work = Perspectives Magazine | date = Spring 2004 | page = 2 | publisher = [[American Bar Association]] | url =http://www.americanbar.org/content/dam/aba/publishing/perspectives_magazine/women_perspectives_Spring2004CrenshawPSP.authcheckdam.pdf |format=PDF }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to show that women of color have a vastly different experience from white women due to their race and/or class and that their experiences are not easily voiced or pinpointed, Crenshaw explores two types of male violence against women: [[domestic violence]] and [[rape]]. Through her analysis of these two forms of male violence against women, Crenshaw says that the experiences of women of color consist of a combination or intersection of both racism and sexism.&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 1991"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Crenshaw | first = Kimberlé | author-link = Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw |title=Mapping the margins: intersectionality, identity politics, and violence against women of color |journal=[[Stanford Law Review]] |volume=43 |issue=6 |pages=1241–1299 |jstor=1229039 |doi=10.2307/1229039 |date=July 1991 | ref = harv | citeseerx = 10.1.1.695.5934 }}&lt;/ref&gt; She says that because women of color are present within discourses that have been designed to address either race or sex, but not both at the same time, women of color are marginalized within both of these systems of oppression.&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 1991" /&gt;

In her work, Crenshaw identifies three aspects of intersectionality as affecting the visibility of women of color: structural intersectionality, political intersectionality, and representational intersectionality. Structural intersectionality deals with how women of color experience domestic violence and rape in a manner qualitatively different from the ways that white women experience them. Political intersectionality examines how [[Feminist legal theory|feminist]] and [[Anti-racism legislation|anti-racists]] laws and policies have paradoxically decreased the visibility of violence against women of color. Finally, representational intersectionality delves into how [[Popular culture|pop culture]] portrayals of women of color can obscure the actual, lived experiences of women of color.&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 1991" /&gt;

The term gained prominence in the 1990s, particularly in the wake of sociologist [[Patricia Hill Collins]]'s further development of Crenshaw's work in her writings on [[black feminism]]. Crenshaw's term replaced her previous coinage "black feminist thought," and "increased the general applicability of her theory from African American women to all women".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Mann | first1 = Susan A. | last2 = Huffman | first2 = Douglas J. | title = The decentering of second wave feminism and the rise of the third wave | journal = [[Science &amp; Society]] | volume = 69 | issue = 1 | pages = 56–91 | jstor = 40404229 | date = January 2005 | ref = harv | doi=10.1521/siso.69.1.56.56799}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|61}} Much like Crenshaw, Collins argued that cultural patterns of oppression are not only interrelated, but are bound together and influenced by the intersectional systems of society, such as race, gender, class, and ethnicity.&lt;ref name="Collins 2000"/&gt;{{rp|42}} Collins described this as "interlocking social institutions [that] have relied on multiple forms of segregation... to produce unjust results".&lt;ref&gt;Collins, Patricia Hill (2009) [1990], "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=icWTAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA277 Towards a politics of empowerment]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Collins | editor-first = Patricia Hill | editor-link = Patricia Hill Collins | title = Black feminist thought: knowledge, consciousness, and the politics of empowerment | page = 277 | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | edition = 2nd | isbn = 9780415964722 | title-link = Black Feminist Thought | year = 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Collins sought to create frameworks to think about intersectionality, rather than expanding on the theory itself. She identified three main branches of study within intersectionality. One branch deals with the background, ideas, issues, conflicts, and debates within intersectionality. Another branch seeks to apply intersectionality as an analytical strategy to various [[social institutions]] in order to examine how they might perpetuate social inequality. The final branch formulates intersectionality as a critical praxis to determine how [[social justice]] initiatives can use intersectionality to bring about social change.&lt;ref name="Collins 2015"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Collins|first=Patricia H. | author-link = Patricia Hill Collins | title = Intersectionality's definitional dilemmas | journal = [[Annual Review of Sociology]] | volume = 41 | pages = 1–20 | doi = 10.1146/annurev-soc-073014-112142 | date = 2015 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ideas behind intersectional feminism existed long before the term was coined. For example, in 1851 [[Sojourner Truth]] delivered her famous "[[Ain't I a Woman?]]" speech, in which she spoke from her racialized position as a former slave to critique essentialist notions of femininity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Brah |first1=Avtar |last2=Phoenix |first2=Ann |title=Ain't I A Woman? Revisiting intersectionality |journal=Journal of International Women's Studies | volume = 5 | issue = 3 | pages = 75–86 | date = 2004 | url = http://vc.bridgew.edu/jiws/vol5/iss3/8/| ref = harv }} [http://vc.bridgew.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1543&amp;context=jiws Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, in her 1892 essay, "The Colored Woman's Office", [[Anna J. Cooper|Anna Julia Cooper]] identifies black women as the most important actors in social change movements, because of their experience with multiple facets of oppression.&lt;ref name=Cooper2009&gt;Cooper, Anna Julia (2017) [1892], "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=ONFVDgAAQBAJ The colored woman's office]", in {{cite book |editor-last = Lemert|editor-first = Charles | title = Social theory: the multicultural, global, and classic readings | publisher = Westview Press | location = Boulder, Colorado | edition = 6th | isbn = 9780813350448 |date = 2016-07-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though intersectionality began with the exploration of the interplay between gender and race, over time other identities and oppressions were added to the theory. For example, in 1981 [[Cherríe Moraga]] and [[Gloria E. Anzaldúa|Gloria Anzaldúa]] published the first edition of ''[[This Bridge Called My Back]]''. This anthology explored how classifications of sexual orientation and class also mix with those of race and gender to create even more distinct political categories. Many black, Latina, and Asian writers featured in the collection stress how their sexuality interacts with their race and gender to inform their perspectives. Similarly, poor women of color detail how their socio-economic status adds a layer of nuance to their identities, ignored or misunderstood by middle-class white feminists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor-last1=Moraga|editor-first1=Cherríe|editor-last2=Anzaldúa|editor-first2=Gloria |editor-link1=Cherríe Moraga|editor-link2=Gloria E. Anzaldúa | title = This bridge called my back: writings by radical women of color | publisher = State University of New York (SUNY) Press | location = Albany | year = 2015 | edition = 4th | isbn = 9781438454382 |title-link=This Bridge Called My Back}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to black feminists and many white feminists, experiences of class, gender, and sexuality cannot be adequately understood unless the influence of racialization is carefully considered. This focus on racialization was highlighted many times by scholar and feminist [[bell hooks]], specifically in her 1981 book ''Ain't I A Woman: Black Women and Feminism''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = hooks | first = bell | author-link = bell hooks | title = Ain't I a Woman: black women and feminism | publisher = Pluto Press South End Press | location = London, Boston, Massachusetts | year = 1982 | isbn = 978-0-86104-379-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Feminists argue that an understanding of intersectionality is a vital element of gaining political and social equality and improving our democratic system.&lt;ref&gt;D'Agostino, Maria; Levine, Helisse (2011), "[https://books.google.com/books?id=dkOypf17LjgC&amp;pg=PA8 Feminist theories and their application to public administration]", in {{cite book| editor-last1 = D'Agostino | editor-first1 = Maria | editor-last2 = Levine | editor-first2 = Helisse | title = Women in Public Administration: theory and practice | page=8 | publisher = Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning | location = Sudbury, Massachusetts | year = 2011 | isbn = 9780763777258}}&lt;/ref&gt; Collins's theory represents the sociological crossroads between [[second-wave feminism|modern]] and [[Post-modern feminism|post-modern feminist thought]].&lt;ref name="Collins 2000"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Collins | first = Patricia Hill | author-link = Patricia Hill Collins | title = Gender, black feminism, and black political economy | journal = [[Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science]] | volume = 568 | issue = 1 | pages = 41–53 | doi = 10.1177/000271620056800105 | date = March 2000 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Marie-Claire Belleau argues for "strategic intersectionality" in order to foster cooperation between feminisms of different ethnicities.&lt;ref name="Belleau, Marie-Claire 2007"&gt;Belleau, Marie-Claire (2007), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=IuzvBBhq7-IC&amp;pg=PA51 'L'intersectionalité': Feminisms in a divided world; Québec-Canada]", in {{cite book | editor-last1 = Orr | editor-first1 = Deborah | title = Feminist Politics: identity, difference, and agency| pages = 51–62 | publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers | location = Lanham, Maryland | isbn = 978-0-7425-4778-0 | ref = harv |display-editors=etal| year = 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|51}} She refers to different ''nat-cult'' (national-cultural) groups that produce unique types of feminisms. Using [[Culture of Quebec|Québécois]] nat-cult as an example, Belleau says that many nat-cult groups contain infinite sub-identities within themselves, arguing that there are endless ways in which different feminisms can cooperate by using strategic intersectionality, and that these partnerships can help bridge gaps between "dominant and marginal" groups.&lt;ref name="Belleau, Marie-Claire 2007"/&gt;{{rp|54}} Belleau argues that, through strategic intersectionality, differences between nat-cult feminisms are neither essentialist nor universal, but should be understood as resulting from socio-cultural contexts. Furthermore, the performances of these nat-cult feminisms are also not essentialist. Instead, they are strategies.&lt;ref name="Belleau, Marie-Claire 2007"/&gt;

Similarly, Intersectional theorists like Vrushali Patil argue that intersectionality ought to recognize transborder constructions of racial and cultural hierarchies. About the effect of the state on identity formation, Patil says: "If we continue to neglect cross-border dynamics and fail to problematize the nation and its emergence via transnational processes, our analyses will remain tethered to the spatialities and temporalities of colonial modernity."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Patil|first=Vrushali|date=1 June 2013|title=From Patriarchy to Intersectionality: A Transnational Feminist Assessment of How Far We've Really Come|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|volume=38|issue=4|pages=847–867|doi=10.1086/669560|jstor=10.1086/669560|issn=0097-9740}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Marxist feminist critical theory ===
{{Marxism}}
[[W. E. B. Du Bois]] theorized that the intersectional paradigms of race, class, and nation might explain certain aspects of black political economy. Collins writes: "Du Bois saw race, class, and nation not primarily as personal identity categories but as social hierarchies that shaped African-American access to status, poverty, and power."&lt;ref name="Collins 2000"/&gt;{{rp|44}} Du Bois omitted gender from his theory and considered it more of a personal identity category.

Cheryl Townsend Gilkes expands on this by pointing out the value of centering on the experiences of black women. Joy James takes things one step further by "using paradigms of intersectionality in interpreting social phenomena". Collins later integrated these three views by examining a black political economy through the centering of black women's experiences and the use of a theoretical framework of intersectionality.&lt;ref name="Collins 2000"/&gt;{{rp|44}}

Collins uses a [[Marxist feminism|Marxist feminist]] approach and applies her intersectional principles to what she calls the "work/family nexus and black women's poverty". In her 2000 article "Black Political Economy" she describes how, in her view, the intersections of [[consumer racism]], gender hierarchies, and disadvantages in the labor market can be centered on black women's unique experiences. Considering this from a historical perspective and examining interracial marriage laws and property inheritance laws creates what Collins terms a "distinctive work/family nexus that in turn influences the overall patterns of black political economy".&lt;ref name="Collins 2000"/&gt;{{rp|45–46}} For example, [[anti-miscegenation laws]] effectively suppressed the upward economic mobility of black women.

The intersectionality of race and gender has been shown to have a visible impact on the labor market. "Sociological research clearly shows that accounting for education, experience, and skill does not fully explain significant differences in labor market outcomes."&lt;ref name="arjournals.annualreviews.org"&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Browne | first1 = Irene | last2 = Misra | first2 = Joya | title = The intersection of gender and race in the labor market | journal = [[Annual Review of Sociology]] | volume = 29 | pages = 487–513 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.soc.29.010202.100016 | date = August 2003 |jstor=30036977| ref = harv }} [https://www.researchgate.net/publication/249558187_The_Intersection_of_Gender_and_Race_in_the_Labor_Market Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|506}} The three main domains in which we see the impact of intersectionality are wages, discrimination, and domestic labor. Those who experience privilege within the social hierarchy in terms of race, gender and socio-economic status are less likely to receive lower wages, to be subjected to stereotypes and discriminated against, or to be hired for exploitative domestic positions. Studies of the labor market and intersectionality provide a better understanding of economic inequalities and the implications of the multidimensional impact of race and gender on social status within society.&lt;ref name="arjournals.annualreviews.org"/&gt;{{rp|506–507}}

==Key concepts==
===Interlocking matrix of oppression===
Collins refers to the various intersections of social inequality as the [[matrix of domination]]. This is also known as "vectors of oppression and privilege".&lt;ref name="Ritzer 2013"&gt;{{cite book |last1= Ritzer|first1= George|author1-link = George Ritzer |last2=Stepinisky |first2=Jeffrey|title = Contemporary sociological theory and its classical roots: the basics|pages = 204–207|publisher = McGraw-Hill|location = New York|edition = 4th|year = 2013|isbn = 9780078026782 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|204}} These terms refer to how differences among people (sexual orientation, class, race, age, etc.) serve as oppressive measures towards women and change the experience of living as a woman in society. Collins, [[Audre Lorde]] (in ''[[Sister Outsider]]''), and [[bell hooks]] point towards either/or thinking as an influence on this oppression and as further intensifying these differences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Dudley | first = Rachel A. | title = Confronting the concept of intersectionality: the legacy of Audre Lorde and contemporary feminist organizations | journal = McNair Scholars Journal | volume = 10 | issue = 1 | page = 5 | date = 2006 | url = https://scholarworks.gvsu.edu/mcnair/vol10/iss1/5/ | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, Collins refers to this as the construct of dichotomous oppositional difference. This construct is characterized by its focus on differences rather than similarities.&lt;ref name="Collins 1986"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Collins | first = Patricia Hill | author-link = Patricia Hill Collins | title = Learning from the outsider within: the sociological significance of black feminist thought | journal = [[Social Problems]] | volume = 33 | issue = 6 | pages = s14–s32 | doi = 10.2307/800672 | jstor = 800672 | date = December 1986 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|S20}}

===Standpoint epistemology and the outsider within===
Both Collins and [[Dorothy E. Smith|Dorothy Smith]] have been instrumental in providing a sociological definition of [[standpoint theory]]. A standpoint is an individual's unique world perspective. The theoretical basis of this approach views societal knowledge as being located within an individual's specific geographic location. In turn, knowledge becomes distinctly unique and subjective; it varies depending on the social conditions under which it was produced.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Mann | first1 = Susan A. | last2 = Kelley | first2 = Lori R. | title = Standing at the crossroads of modernist thought: Collins, Smith, and the new feminist epistemologies | journal = [[Gender &amp; Society]] | volume = 11 | issue = 4 | pages = 391–408 | doi = 10.1177/089124397011004002 | date = August 1997 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|392}}

The concept of the outsider within refers to a unique standpoint encompassing the [[Self (sociology)|self]], family, and society.&lt;ref name="Collins 1986"/&gt;{{rp|S14}} This relates to the specific experiences to which people are subjected as they move from a common cultural world (i.e., family) to that of modern society.&lt;ref name="Ritzer 2013" /&gt;{{rp|207}} Therefore, even though a woman—especially a Black woman—may become influential in a particular field, she may feel as though she does not belong. Their personalities, behavior, and cultural being overshadow their value as an individual; thus, they become the outsider within.&lt;ref name="Collins 1986"/&gt;{{rp|S14}}

===Resisting oppression===
Speaking from a [[critical theory|critical]] standpoint, Collins points out that Brittan and Maynard say "domination always involves the [[objectification]] of the dominated; all forms of oppression imply the devaluation of the subjectivity of the oppressed."&lt;ref name="Collins 1986"/&gt;{{rp|S18}} She later notes that self-valuation and self-definition are two ways of resisting oppression. Practicing [[self-awareness]] helps to preserve the self-esteem of the group that is being oppressed and allow them to avoid any dehumanizing outside influences.

Marginalized groups often gain a status of being an "other".&lt;ref name="Collins 1986"/&gt;{{rp|S18}} In essence, you are "an other" if you are different from what [[Audre Lorde]] calls the [[Normality (behavior)|mythical norm]]. "Others" are virtually anyone that differs from the societal [[Schema (psychology)|schema]] of an average white male. [[Gloria Anzaldúa]] theorizes that the sociological term for this is "[[othering]]", or specifically attempting to establish a person as unacceptable based on a certain criterion that fails to be met.&lt;ref name="Ritzer 2013" /&gt;{{rp|205}}

==In practice==
{{Globalize/US|section|date=March 2017}}
Intersectionality can be applied to nearly all fields from politics,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Hancock | first = Ange-Marie | title = Intersectionality as a normative and empirical paradigm | journal = [[Politics &amp; Gender]] | volume = 3 | issue = 2 | pages = 248–254 | doi = 10.1017/S1743923X07000062 | date = June 2007 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Holvino | first = Evangelina | title = Intersections: The simultaneity of race, gender and class in organization studies | journal = [[Gender, Work &amp; Organization]] | volume = 17 | issue = 3 | pages = 248–277 | doi = 10.1111/j.1468-0432.2008.00400.x | date = May 2010 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; education&lt;ref name="journals.uchicago.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Cooper2009/&gt;&lt;ref name="Jones 2003"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Jones | first = Sandra J. | title = Complex subjectivities: class, ethnicity, and race in women's narratives of upward mobility | journal = [[Journal of Social Issues]] | volume = 59 | issue =  4 | pages = 803–820 | doi = 10.1046/j.0022-4537.2003.00091.x | date = December 2003 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; healthcare,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Kelly | first = Ursula A. | title = Integrating intersectionality and biomedicine in health disparities research | journal = Advances in Nursing Science | volume = 32 | issue =  2 | pages = E42–E56 | doi = 10.1097/ANS.0b013e3181a3b3fc | pmid = 19461221 | date = April–June 2009 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Viruell-Fuentes et al 2012" /&gt; and employment, to economics.&lt;ref name="Ladson-Billings Tate 1995" /&gt; For example, within the institution of education, Sandra Jones' research on working class women in academia takes into consideration meritocracy within all social strata, but argues that it is complicated by race and the external forces that oppress.&lt;ref name="Jones 2003" /&gt; Additionally, people of color often experience differential treatment in the healthcare system. For example, in the period immediately after [[9/11]] researchers noted [[low birth weight]]s and other poor birth outcomes among Muslim and Arab Americans, a result they connected to the increased racial and religious discrimination of the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Lauderdale | first = Diane S. | title = Birth outcomes for Arabic-named women in California before and after September 11 | journal = [[Demography (journal)|Demography]] | volume = 43 | issue = 1 | pages = 185–201 | doi = 10.1353/dem.2006.0008 | date = February 2006 | ref = harv }} [http://www.rwj.harvard.edu/papers/Lauderdale.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt; Some researchers have also argued that immigration policies can affect health outcomes through mechanisms such as [[Stress (biology)#Overview|stress]], restrictions on access to health care, and the [[social determinants of health]].&lt;ref name="Viruell-Fuentes et al 2012"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Viruell-Fuentes |first1=Edna A. |last2=Miranda |first2=Patricia Y. |last3=Abdulrahim |first3=Sawsan | title = More than culture: Structural racism, intersectionality theory, and immigrant health | journal = [[Social Science &amp; Medicine]] | volume = 75 | issue = 12 | pages = 2099–2106 | doi = 10.1016/j.socscimed.2011.12.037 | pmid = 22386617 | date = December 2012 | ref = harv }} [http://sph.umd.edu/sites/default/files/files/che/Viruell%20Fuentes%20et%20al%202012%20SSM%20More%20than%20Culture%20Structural%20Racism.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, applications with regard to property and wealth can be traced to the American historical narrative that is filled "with tensions and struggles over property—in its various forms. From the removal of Native Americans (and later [[Internment of Japanese Americans|Japanese Americans]]) from the land, to military conquest of the Mexicans, to the construction of Africans as property, the ability to define, possess, and own property has been a central feature of power in America&amp;nbsp;... [and where] social benefits accrue largely to property owners".&lt;ref name="Ladson-Billings Tate 1995"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Ladson-Billings | first1 = Gloria | last2 = Tate IV | first2 = William F. | title = Toward a critical race theory of education (''id: 1410'') | journal = [[Teachers College Record]] | volume = 97 | issue = 1 | pages = 47–68 | date = 1995 | url = https://www.tcrecord.org/content.asp?contentid=1410 | ref = harv }} [http://hs.iastate.edu/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Toward_a_Critical_Race_Theory_of_Education.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt; One could apply the intersectionality framework analysis to various areas where race, class, gender, sexuality and ability are affected by policies, procedures, practices, and laws in "context-specific inquiries, including, for example, analyzing the multiple ways that race and gender interact with class in the labor market; interrogating the ways that states constitute regulatory regimes of identity, reproduction, and family formation";&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Cho |first1=Sumi |last2=Crenshaw |first2=Kimberlé Williams |last3=McCall |first3=Leslie | title = Toward a field of intersectionality studies: theory, applications, and praxis | journal = [[Signs (journal)|Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society]] | volume = 38 | issue = 4 | pages = 785–810 | doi = 10.1086/669608 | jstor = 10.1086/669608 | date = Summer 2013 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; and examining the inequities in "the power relations [of the intersectionality] of whiteness&amp;nbsp;... [where] the denial of power and privilege&amp;nbsp;... of whiteness, and middle-classness", while not addressing "the role of power it wields in social relations".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Levine-Rasky | first = Cynthia | title = Intersectionality theory applied to whiteness and middle-classness | journal = Social Identities: Journal for the Study of Race, Nation and Culture | volume = 17 | issue = 2 | pages = 239–253 | doi = 10.1080/13504630.2011.558377 | date = 2011 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intersectionality in a global context===
Over the last couple decades in the European Union, there has been discussion regarding the intersections of social classifications and the need to acknowledge their functions. Before Crenshaw coined her definition of intersectionality, there was debate on what these societal categories were, and how they played a role in the lives of many minorities. What was once a more cut and dry categorization between gender, race, and class has turned into a multidimensional intersection of “race” including religion, sexuality, ethnicities, etc. In the EU and UK they refer to these intersections under the notion of multiple discrimination. The EU passed a non-discrimination law which addresses these multiple intersections; however, there is debate on whether the law is still proactively focusing on the proper inequalities.&lt;ref&gt;Lawson, Anna. European Union Non-Discrimination Law and Intersectionality : Investigating the Triangle of Racial, Gender and Disability Discrimination, edited by Dagmar Schiek, Routledge, 2011. ProQuest Ebook Central&lt;/ref&gt; The European Union is not the only organization that is acknowledging this concept. People around the world are taking a new approach when identifying others identities as well as their own; although, there are still places that follow the traditional process of categorization as stated in the following quote. “The impact of patriarchy and traditional assumptions about gender and families are evident in the lives of Chinese migrant workers (Chow, Tong), sex workers and their clients in South Korea (Shin), and Indian widows (Chauhan), but also Ukrainian migrants (Amelina) and Australian men of the new global middle class (Connell).”. &lt;ref&gt;Analyzing Gender, Intersectionality, and Multiple Inequalities : Global, Transnational and Local Contexts, edited by Esther Ngan-ling Chow, and Tan Lin, Emerald Publishing Limited, 2011. ProQuest Ebook Central&lt;/ref&gt; This text suggests that there are many more intersections of discrimination for people around the globe, than Crenshaw originally accounted for in her definition.

===Social work===
In the field of [[social work]], proponents of intersectionality hold that unless service providers take intersectionality into account, they will be of less use for various segments of the population, such as those reporting domestic violence or disabled victims of abuse. According to intersectional theory, the practice of [[domestic violence]] counselors in the [[United States]] urging all women to report their abusers to police is of little use to [[women of color]] due to the history of racially motivated [[police brutality]], and those counselors should adapt their counseling for women of color.&lt;ref&gt;Bent-Goodley, Tricia B.; Chase, Lorraine; Circo, Elizabeth A.; Antá Rodgers, Selena T. (2010), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=IiRKrWlceK0C&amp;pg=PA77 Our survival, our strengths: understanding the experiences of African American women in abusive relationships]", in {{cite book | editor-last1 = Lockhart | editor-first1 = Lettie | editor-last2 = Danis | editor-first2 = Fran S. | title = Domestic violence intersectionality and culturally competent practice | page = 77 | publisher = Columbia University Press | location = New York | isbn = 9780231140270 | year = 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Women with disabilities encounter more frequent domestic abuse with a greater number of abusers. Health care workers and personal care attendants perpetrate abuse in these circumstances, and women with disabilities have fewer options for escaping the abusive situation.&lt;ref name="Lochart_Danis_131"&gt;Cramer, Elizabeth P.; Plummer, Sara-Beth (2010), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=IiRKrWlceK0C&amp;pg=PA131 Social work practice with abused persons with disabilities]", in {{cite book | editor-last1 = Lockhart | editor-first1 = Lettie | editor-last2 = Danis | editor-first2 = Fran S. | title = Domestic violence intersectionality and culturally competent practice | pages = 131–134 | publisher = Columbia University Press | location = New York| isbn = 9780231140270 | year = 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There is a "silence" principle concerning the intersectionality of women and disability, which maintains an overall social denial of the prevalence of abuse among the disabled and leads to this abuse being frequently ignored when encountered.&lt;ref name="Chenoweth"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Chenoweth | first = Lesley | title = Violence and women with disabilities: silence and paradox | journal = [[Violence Against Women (journal)|Violence Against Women]] | volume = 2 | issue = 4 | pages = 391–411 | doi = 10.1177/1077801296002004004 | date = December 1996 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; A paradox is presented by the overprotection of people with disabilities combined with the expectations of promiscuous behavior of disabled women.&lt;ref name="Lochart_Danis_131" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Chenoweth" /&gt; This leads to limited autonomy and social isolation of disabled individuals, which place women with disabilities in situations where further or more frequent abuse can occur.&lt;ref name="Lochart_Danis_131" /&gt;

== Criticism ==
{{POV|Section|date=October 2018}}

=== Methods &amp; Ideology ===
According to [[political theorist]] Rebecca Reilly-Cooper intersectionality relies heavily on [[standpoint theory]], which has its own set of criticisms. Intersectionality posits that an oppressed person is often the best person to judge their experience of oppression; however, this can create paradoxes when people who are similarly oppressed have different interpretations of similar events. Such paradoxes make it very difficult to synthesize a common actionable cause based on subjective testimony alone.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | last = Reilly-Cooper | first = Rebecca |url=https://rebeccarc.com/2013/04/15/intersectionality-and-identity-politics/|title=Intersectionality and identity politics|date=15 April 2013|publisher=More Radical With Age|access-date=23 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other narratives, especially those based on multiple intersections of oppression, are more complex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Kofi Bright | first1 = Liam  | last2 = Malinsky | first2 = Daniel | last3 = Thompson | first3 = Morgan |title= Causally interpreting intersectionality theory | journal = [[Philosophy of Science (journal)|Philosophy of Science]] | volume = 18 | issue = 1 | pages = 60–81 | doi = 10.1086/684173 | date = January 2016 | ref = harv }} [http://www.liamkofibright.com/uploads/4/8/9/8/48985425/causally_interpreting_intersectionality_theory_final.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt; Davis (2008) asserts that intersectionality is ambiguous and open ended, and that its "lack of clear-cut definition or even specific parameters has enabled it to be drawn upon in nearly any context of inquiry".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Davis | first = Kathy | title = Intersectionality as buzzword: A sociology of science perspective on what makes a feminist theory successful | journal = [[Feminist Theory (journal)|Feminist Theory]] | volume = 9 | issue = 1 | pages = 67–85 | doi = 10.1177/1464700108086364 | date = April 2008 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rekia Jibrin and Sara Salem argue that intersectional theory creates a unified idea of anti-oppression politics that requires a lot out of its adherents, often more than can reasonably be expected, creating difficulties achieving [[Praxis (process)|praxis]]. They also say that intersectional philosophy encourages a focus on the issues inside the group instead of on society at large, and that intersectionality is "a call to complexity and to abandon over simplification... this has the parallel effect of emphasizing 'internal differences' over hegemonic structures."&lt;ref name="Rekia Jibrin 2015"&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Jibrin | first1 = Rekia | last2 = Salem | first2 = Sara |title=Revisiting intersectionality: reflections on theory and praxis | journal = Trans-Scripts: An Interdisciplinary Online Journal in the Humanities and Social Sciences | volume = 5 | date = 2015 | url = http://sites.uci.edu/transscripts/2015-archives-2/ }} [http://sites.uci.edu/transscripts/files/2014/10/2015_5_salem.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|''See ''[[hegemony]] and [[cultural hegemony]].}}

Writing in the ''[[New Statesman]]'', Helen Lewis adds that in emphasizing internal differences over hegemonic structures, and having complex and at times contradictory recommendations, it can create paralysis because it is not very accessible.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | last = Lewis | first = Helen |title=The uses and abuses of intersectionality |url=http://www.newstatesman.com/helen-lewis/2014/02/uses-and-abuses-intersectionality |work=[[New Statesman]] |date=20 February 2014|access-date=23 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[moral psychologist]] [[Jonathan Haidt]], in a speech at the [[American conservative]] think tank [[Manhattan Institute]], criticized the theory by saying:&lt;blockquote&gt;[In intersectionality] the binary dimensions of oppression are said to be interlocking and overlapping. America is said to be one giant matrix of oppression, and its victims cannot fight their battles separately. They must all come together to fight their common enemy, the group that sits at the top of the pyramid of oppression: the straight, white, cis-gendered, able-bodied Christian or Jewish or possibly atheist male. This is why a perceived slight against one victim group calls forth protest from all victim groups. This is why so many campus groups now align against Israel. Intersectionality is like NATO for social-justice activists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.city-journal.org/html/age-outrage-15608.html|title=The Age of Outrage|date=17 December 2017|work=City Journal|author=Jonathan Haidt|access-date=6 March 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Primary inline|date=September 2018}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Barbara Tomlinson, a PhD employed at the Department of Women's Studies at UC Santa Barbara, has been critical of the applications of intersectional theory, and identified several ways in which the conventional theory has been destructive to the movement. She asserts that the common practice of using intersectionality to attack other ways of feminist thinking and the tendency of academics to critique intersectionality instead of using intersectionality as a tool to critique other conventional ways of thinking has been a misuse of the ideas it stands for. Tomlinson argues that in order to use intersectional theory correctly, intersectional feminists must not only consider the arguments but the tradition and mediums through which these arguments are made, Conventional academics are likely to favor writings by authors or publications with prior established credibility instead of looking at the quality of each piece individually, contributing to negative stereotypes associated with both feminism and intersectionality by having weaker arguments in defense of feminism and intersectionality become prominent based on renown. She goes on to argue that this allows critics of intersectionality to attack these weaker arguments, “[reducing] intersectionality’s radical critique of power to desires for identity and inclusion, and offer a deradicalized intersectionality as an asset for dominant disciplinary discourses”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Tomlinson | first = Barbara | title = To Tell the Truth and Not Get Trapped: Desire, Distance, and Intersectionality at the Scene of Argument | journal = Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society | volume = 38 | issue = 4 | pages = 993-1017 | doi = 10.1086/669571 | date = Summer 2013 | ref = harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Psychology===

{{Main|Biases|Heuristics in judgment and decision-making}}
Researchers in psychology have incorporated intersection effects since the 1950s{{Example needed|date=September 2018}}, long before the work of Patricia Hill Collins. Psychology incorporates these effects via the lenses of biases, heuristics, stereotypes, and judgments. Psychological interaction effects span a range of variables, although person by situation effects are the most examined category. As a result, psychologists do not construe the interaction effect of demographics such as gender and race as either more noteworthy or less noteworthy than any other interaction effect. In addition, oppression can be regarded as a subjective construct when viewed as an absolute hierarchy; even if an objective definition of oppression were reached, person-by-situation effects would make it difficult to deem certain persons or categories of persons as uniformly oppressed. For instance, black men are stereotypically perceived as violent, which may be a disadvantage in police interactions, but also as physically attractive,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Lewis | first = Michael B. | title = A facial attractiveness account of gender asymmetries in interracial marriage | journal = [[PLOS ONE]] | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0031703  | date = 9 February 2012 | ref = harv | volume=7 | issue = 2 | pages=e31703 | pmid=22347504 | pmc=3276508}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Lewis | first = Michael B. | title = Who is the fairest of them all? Race, attractiveness and skin color sexual dimorphism | journal = [[Personality and Individual Differences]] | volume = 50 | issue = 2 | pages = 159–162 | doi = 10.1016/j.paid.2010.09.018 | date = January 2011 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; which may be advantageous in romantic situations.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Psychological studies have shown that the effect of multiplying "oppressed" identities is not necessarily additive, but rather interactive in complex ways. For instance, black gay men may be more positively evaluated than black heterosexual men, because the "feminine" aspects of gay stereotypes temper the hypermasculine and aggressive aspect of black stereotypes.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Pedulla | first = David S. | title = The positive consequences of negative stereotypes: race, sexual orientation, and the job application process | journal = [[Social Psychology Quarterly]] | volume = 77 | issue = 1 | pages = 75–94 | doi = 10.1177/0190272513506229 | date = March 2014 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Remedios | first1 = Jessica D. | last2 = Chasteen | first2 = Alison L. | last3 = Rule | first3 = Nicholas O. | last4 = Plaks | first4 = Jason E. | title = Impressions at the intersection of ambiguous and obvious social categories: Does gay + Black = likable? | journal = [[Journal of Experimental Social Psychology]] | volume = 47 | issue = 6 | pages = 1312–1315 | doi = 10.1016/j.jesp.2011.05.015 | date = November 2011 | ref = harv | hdl = 1807/33199 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Alan Dershowitz]], scholar of United States constitutional law and criminal law, answering a question on the [[criticism of Israel]] by intersectional movements he stated that the concept of intersectionality is an oversimplification of reality that makes LGBT activists stand in solidarity with advocates of [[Sharia]], even though Islamic law denies the rights of the former. He feels that identity politics does not evaluate ideas or individuals on the basis of the quality of their character. Dershowitz argues that in academia, intersectionality is taught with a large influence from antisemitism. He states that Jews are actually more liberal and supportive of equal rights than many other religious sects.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | last = Frommer | first = Rachel | title= Alan Dershowitz derides theory of intersectionality in Columbia lecture |url= http://freebeacon.com/culture/alan-dershowitz-derides-theory-intersectionality-columbia-lecture|date=28 September 2017|work = [[The Washington Free Beacon]] |access-date=6 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Writer and political pro-Israel activist [[Chloé Valdary]] considers intersectionality "a rigid system for determining who is virtuous and who is not, based on traits like skin color, gender, and financial status". Valdary also states:&lt;blockquote&gt;Intersectionality's greatest flaw is in reducing human beings to political abstractions, which is never a tendency that turns out well—in part because it so severely flattens our complex human experience, and therefore fails to adequately describe reality. As it turns out, one can be personally successful and still come from a historically oppressed community—or vice versa. The human experience is complex and multifaceted and deeper than the superficial ways in which intersectionalists describe it.&lt;ref&gt;Valdary, Chloé.  [http://www.tabletmag.com/jewish-news-and-politics/258364/what-farrakhan-shares-with-intersectional-left "What Farrakhan Shares With the Intersectional Left"] ''Tablet Magazine''.  26 March 2018.  28 March 0218.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Compared to abiding religious faiths===
Intersectionality's premises have been characterized by some [[right-libertarian]]-leaning skeptics as manifested similarly to religious faith. Notably, for example, conservative [[political commentator]] [[Andrew Sullivan]] has argued that intersectionality manifests itself "almost as a religion. It posits a classic orthodoxy through which all of human experience is explained—and through which all speech must be filtered. Its version of original sin is the power of some identity groups over others. To overcome this sin, you need first to confess, i.e., 'check your privilege,' and subsequently live your life and order your thoughts in a way that keeps this sin at bay."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date = 10 March 2017|title = Is Intersectionality a Religion?|author = [[Andrew Sullivan]]|publisher = [[New York magazine]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://hotair.com/archives/2018/03/04/portland-state-university-panel-discussion-intersectionality-religion/|title=Portland State University panel discussion: 'Is Intersectionality a Religion?'|date=4 March 2018|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[David A. French]], writer for the ''[[National Review]]'', also agrees with Sullivan's conclusion, equating intersectionality's proponents to extremist Christian fundamentalists.&lt;ref&gt;[[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] politician [[David A. French|David French]], [https://web.archive.org/web/20180307030606/https://www.nationalreview.com/2018/03/intersectionality-the-dangerous-faith/ "Intersectionality, the Dangerous Faith"] (6 March 2018), ''National Review Online''&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Black feminism]] 
* [[Caste]]
* [[Humanism]]
* [[Identitarianism]]
* [[Kyriarchy]]
* [[Privilege (social inequality)]]
* [[Standpoint theory]]
* [[Triple oppression]]
* [[Womanism]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite news | last = Bates | first = Laura | author-link = Laura Bates | title = Sexism, double discrimination and more than one kind of prejudice | url = https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/womens-blog/2014/mar/31/laura-bates-everyday-sexism-double-discrimination-intersectionality | work = [[The Guardian]] | date = 31 March 2014 }}
* {{cite journal |last1=Clarke |first1=Averil Y. |last2=McCall |first2=Leslie |title=Intersectionality and social explanation in social science research |journal=Du Bois Review: Social Science Research on Race |volume=10 |issue=2 |pages=349–363 |doi=10.1017/S1742058X13000325 |year=2013 | ref = harv}}
* {{Cite book | last1 = Collins | first1 = Patricia Hill | last2 = Andersen | first2 = Margaret L. | author-link1 = Patricia Hill Collins | title = Race, Class, &amp; Gender: an anthology | publisher = [[Cengage Learning]] | location = Boston, Massachusetts | year = 2015 | origyear = 1992 | isbn = 978-1-305-09361-4 }}
* {{Cite book | last = Collins | first = Patricia Hill | author-link =  | title = Black Feminist Thought: knowledge, consciousness, and the politics of empowerment | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 2009 | origyear = 1990 | isbn = 978-0-415-96472-2 | title-link = Black Feminist Thought }}
* {{Cite book | last1 = Collins | first1 = Patricia Hill | last2 = Bilge | first2 = Sirma | author-link1 =  | title = Intersectionality | publisher = [[Polity Press]] | location = Cambridge, UK | year = 2016 | isbn = 978-0-7456-8448-2 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Collins | first = Patricia Hill | author-link =  | title = The tie that binds: race, gender and US violence | journal = [[Ethnic and Racial Studies]] | volume = 21 | issue = 5 | pages = 917–938 | doi = 10.1080/014198798329720 | date = 1998 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last1 = Doucet | first1 = Andrea | last2 = Siltanen | first2 = Janet | author-link1 = Andrea Doucet | title = Gender Relations in Canada: intersectionality and beyond | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Don Mills, Ontario | year = 2008 | isbn = 978-0-19-542320-4 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Doná | first = Giorgia | title = Interconnected modernities, ethnic relations and violence | journal = [[Current Sociology]] | volume = 61 | issue = 2 | pages = 226–243 | doi = 10.1177/0011392112456507 | date = March 2013 | ref = harv}}
* {{Cite journal | last = Harnois | first = Catherine E. | title = Race, Gender, and the Black Women's Standpoint | journal = [[Sociological Forum]] | volume = 25 | issue = 1 | pages = 68–85 | doi = 10.1111/j.1573-7861.2009.01157.x| date = 2010 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Hancock |first=Ange-Marie |date=2016 |title=Intersectionality: an intellectual history |location=New York |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-937037-5 |oclc=941724695 }}
* {{cite book |last=Köllen |first=Thomas |date=2014 |contribution-url=http://epub.wu.ac.at/4315/1/K%C3%B6llen_-_Minority_Stress.pdf |contribution-format=PDF |contribution=A review of minority stress related to employees' demographics and the development of an intersectional framework for their coping strategies in the workplace |title= The Role of Demographics in Occupational Stress and Well Being |series=Research in Occupational Stress and Well Being |volume=12 |publisher=Emerald |isbn=978-1-78350-646-0 |doi=10.1108/S1479-355520140000012000 |pages=41–82 |url=http://epub.wu.ac.at/4315/1/K%C3%B6llen_%2D_Minority_Stress.pdf |type=Submitted manuscript }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Lee | first1 = Butch | last2 = Rover | first2 = Red | title = Night-vision: illuminating war &amp; class on the neo-colonial terrain | publisher = Vagabond | location = New York | year = 1993 | isbn = 978-1-883780-00-5 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Leung | first = Lai-ching | title = Intersectional challenges: marginalization of ethnic minority sexual assault survivors in Hong Kong | journal = [[Affilia]] | volume = 32 | issue = 2 | pages = 217–229 | doi = 10.1177/0886109916678026 | date = May 2017 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Mitchell | first = Eve | title = I am a woman and a human: a Marxist feminist critique of intersectionality (''pamphlet'') | publisher = Unity and Struggle | location = Houston, NYC, and Atlanta | url = http://unityandstruggle.org/2013/09/12/i-am-a-woman-and-a-human-a-marxist-feminist-critique-of-intersectionality-theory/ | year = 2013 | deadurl = bot: unknown | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170529010135/http://unityandstruggle.org/2013/09/12/i-am-a-woman-and-a-human-a-marxist-feminist-critique-of-intersectionality-theory/ | archivedate = 29 May 2017 | df = dmy-all }} [http://libcom.org//files/intersectionality-pamphlet.pdf Pdf of pamphlet.]
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Ní Aoláin | first1 = Fionnuala | last2 = Rooney | first2 = Eilish | title = Underenforcement and intersectionality: gendered aspects of transition for women | journal = [[International Journal of Transitional Justice]] | volume = 1 | issue = 3 | pages = 338–354 | doi = 10.1093/ijtj/ijm031 | date = December 2007 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite news | last = Robertson | first = Eleanor | title = In defence of intersectionality – one of feminism's most important tools | url = https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/dec/23/in-defence-of-intersectionality | work = The Guardian | publisher = [[Guardian Media Group]] | date = 23 December 2013 }}
* {{Cite journal| last = Schuster | first = Julia | title = Intersectional expectations: young feminists' perceived failure at dealing with differences and their retreat to individualism | journal = [[Women's Studies International Forum]] | volume = 58 | pages = 1–8 | doi = 10.1016/j.wsif.2016.04.007 | date = September–October 2016 | ref = harv}}
* {{Cite journal | last = Smooth | first = Wendy | title = Intersectionality in electoral politics: a mess worth making | journal = [[Politics &amp; Gender]] | volume = 2 | issue = 3 | pages = 400–414 | doi = 10.1017/S1743923X06261087 | date = September 2006 | ref = harv}}
* {{Cite journal | last = Sunderland | first = Jane | title = 'Brown Sugar': The textual construction of femininity in two 'tiny texts' | journal = [[Gender and Language]] | volume = 6 | issue = 1 | pages = 105–129 | doi = 10.1558/genl.v6i1.105 | date = April 2012 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite news | last = Vidal | first = Ava | author-link = Ava Vidal | title = 'Intersectional feminism'. What the hell is it? (And why you should care) | url = https://www.telegraph.co.uk/women/womens-life/10572435/Intersectional-feminism.-What-the-hell-is-it-And-why-you-should-care.html | work = [[The Telegraph (website)|The Telegraph]] | date = 15 January 2014 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Weldon | first = S. Laurel | title = The structure of intersectionality: a comparative politics of gender | journal = Politics &amp; Gender | volume = 2 | issue = 2 | pages = 235–248 | doi = 10.1017/S1743923X06231040 | date = June 2006 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | editor1-last =Gutiérrez y Muhs | editor1-first = Gabriella | editor2-last = Niemann | editor2-first = Yolanda Flores | editor3-last = González | editor3-first = Carmen G. | editor4-last = Harris | editor4-first = Angela P. | title = Presumed Incompetent: the intersections of race and class for women in academia | publisher = University Press of Colorado | location = Boulder, Colorado | year = 2012 | isbn = 978-0-87421-922-7 }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary|intersectionality}}
* [https://archive.org/stream/DemarginalizingTheIntersectionOfRaceAndSexABlackFeminis/Demarginalizing%20the%20Intersection%20of%20Race%20and%20Sex_%20A%20Black%20Feminis_djvu.txt "Demarginalizing the Intersection of Race and Sex: A Black Feminist Critique of Antidiscrimination Doctrine, Feminist Theory and Antiracist Politics"], by [[Kimberlé Crenshaw]], 1989
*[http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/45a/252.html Black Feminist Thought in the Matrix of Domination]
*{{cite web |first=Patricia Hill |last=Collins |authorlink=Patricia Hill Collins|url=http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/Organizations/healthnet/WoC/feminisms/collins2.html |dead-url=yes |archive-date=11 December 2006 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061211050851/http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/Organizations/healthnet/WoC/feminisms/collins2.html |title=Black Feminist Thought |publisher=Women of Color Web |year=1990 }}
*[http://www.rpi.edu/~eglash/eglash.dir/SST/bft.htm A Brief History of Black Feminist Thought]
*[http://www.sagepub.co.uk/upm-data/13299_Chapter_16_Web_Byte_Patricia_Hill_Collins.pdf Intersectionality Theory]
* {{cite web |first=Allison |last=McCarthy |editor-first=Deborah |editor-last=Siegel |url=http://girlwpen.com/?page_id=1724 |title=The Intersectional Feminist |publisher=Girl w/ Pen |dead-url=yes |archive-date=15 November 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121115121230/http://girlwpen.com/?page_id=1724 }}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20170423171506/https://www.sfu.ca/iirp/documents/resources/101_Final.pdf Intersectionality 101]

[[Category:Critical theory]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Intersectional feminism| ]]
[[Category:Intersectionality| ]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1980s]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>