<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20040927162750|6190527" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="844779" pageid="844779" ns="0" title="State atheism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-09-27T16:28:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''State atheism''' is the official rejection of [[religion]] in all forms by a government in favor of [[atheism]]. Although many governments throughout history have officially opposed religion (and sometimes persecuted religious leaders), the only country that has ever actually banned religion was [[Albania]] under [[Enver Hoxha]].

== Distinction between state atheism and secular government ==
State atheism is not to be confused with [[anti-clericalism]], the effort to reduce the economic and political power of clergy in politics. Neither is it to be confused with religious neutrality, in which a government recognizes the legal necessity of [[separation of church and state]]. A state-sponsored religion within a political system implies bias toward one tradition at the expense of others, thus the separation of church and State protects religious minorities. Finally, state atheism is not to be confused with selective [[persecution]] of some religious beliefs or their adherents in favor of some other, more dominant religion. State atheism is opposed to all religion equally.

In brief, state atheism implies that the government actively opposes all forms of religion, while secular government implies that the government in question takes a neutral view towards religious matters.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>