<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131117100607|582031612" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="844779" pageid="844779" ns="0" title="State atheism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-17T10:26:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{atheism2}}

'''State atheism''' is the official promotion of [[atheism]] by a [[government]], sometimes combined with active suppression of [[religious freedom]] and practice.  In contrast, a [[secular state]] purports to be officially neutral in matters of [[religion]], supporting neither religion nor [[irreligion]].  State atheism may refer to a government's [[anti-clericalism]], which opposes religious institutional power and influence in all aspects of public and political life, including the involvement of religion in the everyday life of the citizen.

State promotion of atheism as a public norm was first practiced during the [[Revolutionary France]]. Since then, such a policy was repeated in [[Mexican Revolution|Revolutionary Mexico]] and in [[Communist state|Marxist-Leninist states]].  The [[Soviet Union]] had a long history of state atheism, in which social success largely required individuals to profess atheism and stay away from [[houses of worship]]; this attitude was especially militant during the middle [[Stalinist era]] from 1929–1939. The Soviet Union attempted to suppress public religious expression over wide areas of its influence, including places such as [[central Asia]].

==French Revolution==

[[File:Cruikshank - The Radical's Arms.png|left|thumb|1819 [[Caricature]] by English [[caricaturist]] [[George Cruikshank]]. Titled "The Radical's Arms", it depicts the infamous guillotine. "No God! No Religion! No King! No Constitution!" is written in the republican banner.]]
During the [[French Revolution]] French society considered the prospect of an atheist state.&lt;ref name=McGrath2006p46&gt;[[#McGrath2006|McGrath (2006)]]:46.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dubious |reason= bad source and counterfactual |date=November 2013}} After the Revolution, [[Jacques Hébert]], a radical revolutionary journalist, and [[Anacharsis Cloots]], a politician, both [[anticlerical]] and atheist, had successfully campaigned for the proclamation of the atheistic&lt;ref name=Freemont-Barnes2007p329&gt;[[#Freemont-Barnes2007|Freemont-Barnes (2007)]]:[http://books.google.com/books?id=6_2wkP4j-EsC&amp;pg=PA376&lt;!--this navigates to page 329 (not 376) in the text--&gt; 329].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cult of Reason]], which was adopted by the French Republic on November 10, 1793{{Disputed-inline|Talk page section|date=November 2013}}, though abandoned May 7, 1794 in favor of its [[deism|deistic]] replacement as the state religion, the [[Cult of the Supreme Being]].&lt;ref name=McGrath2006&gt;[[#McGrath2006|McGrath (2006)]].&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|reason= source is unreliable, not serious at all|date=November 2013}}

Cloots maintained that "Reason" and "Truth" were "supremely intolerant" and that the daylight of atheism would make the lesser lights of religious night disappear.&lt;ref name=McGrath2006 /&gt;{{Better source|reason= idem|date=November 2013}}  The state then further pushed its [[Dechristianisation of France during the French Revolution|campaign of dechristianization]],&lt;ref name=McGrath2006p45&gt;[[#McGrath2006|McGrath (2006)]]:45.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|reason= idem|date=November 2013}} which included removal and destruction of religious objects from places of worship and the transformation of churches into "Temples of the Goddess of Reason",  culminating in a celebration of Reason in [[Notre Dame de Paris|Notre Dame]] Cathedral.&lt;ref&gt;Latreille, A. FRENCH REVOLUTION, New Catholic Encyclopedia v. 5, pp. 972–973 (Second Ed. 2002 Thompson/Gale) ISBN 0-7876-4004-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Spielvogel2005|Spielvogel (2005)]]:549.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tallet1991|Tallet (1991)]]:1&lt;/ref&gt;

Counterrevolution against the [[Persecution of Christians|persecution]] rooted in the anticlerical aspects of the Revolution led to a [[War in the Vendée|war in the Vendée region]] where republicans suppressed the  Catholic and royalist uprising in what some call "the first modern [[genocide]]",&lt;ref name=McGrath2006p46 /&gt;&lt;ref name=JonassohnBjeornson1998&gt;[[#JonassohnBjeornson1998|Jonassohn, Bjeornson]]:208.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|reason= idem|date=November 2013}} (a term historians reject&lt;ref name=PMc&gt;Peter McPhee, [http://www.h-france.net/vol4reviews/mcphee3.html a review] of Reynald Secher, ''A French Genocide'', published in  H-France Review Vol. 4 (March 2004), No. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last = Vovelle | first = Michel  | authorlink = Michel Vovelle | title = Bourgeoisies de province et Revolution| publisher = Presses Universitaires de Grenoble |year=1987 | page = quoted in Féhér}}&lt;/ref&gt;).

Unlike later establishments of anti-theism by communist regimes, the French Revolutionary experiment was short (7 months), incomplete and inconsistent.&lt;ref name="McGrath2006p45"/&gt; Although brief, the French experiment was particularly notable for the influence upon atheists [[Ludwig Feuerbach]] (who called religion an opiate before Marx&lt;ref&gt;Luo, Zhufeng  [http://books.google.com/books?id=cEfiZlUpI5oC&amp;dq Religion under socialism in China], p. 151, M.E. Sharpe 1991&lt;/ref&gt;), [[Sigmund Freud]] and [[Karl Marx]].&lt;ref name=McGrath2006p46 /&gt;  Using the ideas of Feuerbach, Marx and Freud, communist regimes later treated religious believers as subversives or abnormal, sometimes relegated to psychiatric hospitals and reeducation.&lt;ref name=McGrath2006p46 /&gt;

==Revolutionary Mexico==
{{See also|Plutarco Elías Calles|Calles Law|Cristero War}}

Articles 3, 5, 24, 27, and 130 of the Mexican Constitution of 1917 as originally enacted were anticlerical and enormously restricted religious freedoms.&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu"&gt;Soberanes Fernandez, Jose Luis, [http://lawreview.byu.edu/archives/2002/2/Sob12.pdf Mexico and the 1981 United Nations Declaration on the Elimination of All Forms of Intolerance and of Discrimination Based on Religion or Belief], pp. 437-438 nn. 7-8, BYU Law Review, June 2002&lt;/ref&gt; At first the anticlerical provisions were only sporadically enforced, but when President [[Plutarco Elías Calles]] took office, he enforced the provisions strictly.&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu"/&gt; Calles’ Mexico has been characterized as an atheist state&lt;ref&gt;Haas, Ernst B., [http://books.google.com/books?id=ldKJ_Re6p8AC&amp;pg Nationalism, Liberalism, and Progress: The dismal fate of new nations], Cornell Univ. Press 2000&lt;/ref&gt; and his program as being one to eradicate religion in Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;Cronon, E. David "American Catholics and Mexican Anticlericalism, 1933-1936," ,pp. 205-208, Mississippi Valley Historical Review, XLV, Sept. 1948&lt;/ref&gt;

All religions had their properties expropriated, and these became part of government wealth. There was a forced expulsion of foreign clergy and the seizure of Church properties.&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu"&gt;http://www.ilstu.edu/class/hist263/docs/1917const.html&lt;/ref&gt; Article 27 prohibited any future acquisition of such property by the churches, and prohibited religious corporations and ministers from 
establishing or directing primary schools.&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu" /&gt; This second prohibition was sometimes interpreted to mean that the Church could not give religious instruction to children within the churches on Sundays, seen as destroying the ability of Catholics to be educated in their own religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myheritage.es/FP/newsItem.php?s=114433561&amp;newsID=68&amp;sourceList=dir|title=THE DECLINE AND FALL OF THE MARTIN-DEL-CAMPOs Part II|publisher=[http://www.myheritage.es myheritage.es]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- see also http://toolserver.org/~dcoetzee/duplicationdetector/compare.php?url1=http%3A%2F%2Fen.wikipedia.org%2Fw%2Findex.php%3Ftitle%3DState_atheism&amp;url2=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.nairaland.com%2F723007%2Ftai-solarin-life-ideas-accomplishments%2F2&amp;minwords=2&amp;minchars=13 --&gt;

The Constitution of 1917 also closed and forbade the existence of monastic orders (article 5), forbade any religious activity outside of church buildings (now owned by the government), and mandated that such religious activity would be overseen by the government (article 24).&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu"/&gt;

On June 14, 1926, President Calles enacted an [[anticlerical]] legislation known formally as The Law Reforming the Penal Code and unofficially as the [[Calles Law]].&lt;ref name="Joes, Anthony James p. 70"&gt;Joes, Anthony James [http://books.google.com/books?id=buHXFDFdeoQC&amp;pg=PA70&amp;dq=plutarco+calles+anticatholic&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=fnPEry3_KKxtgC6IdVhGGh8lMG8#PPA70,M1 Resisting Rebellion: The History And Politics of Counterinsurgency] p. 70, (2006 University Press of Kentucky) ISBN 0-8131-9170-X&lt;/ref&gt;   His [[anti-Catholic]] actions included outlawing religious orders, depriving the Church of property rights and depriving the clergy of civil liberties, including their right to trial  by jury (in cases involving anti-clerical laws) and the right to vote.&lt;ref name="Joes, Anthony James p. 70"/&gt;&lt;ref name="THE CRISTERO REBELLION - PART 1"&gt;Tuck, Jim [http://www.mexconnect.com/mex_/history/jtuck/jtcristero1.html THE CRISTERO REBELLION – PART 1] Mexico Connect 1996&lt;/ref&gt; Catholic antipathy towards Calles was enhanced because of his vocal atheism.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"&gt;{{cite book
|title=Mexico's New Politics
|author=David A. Shirk
|year=2005
|publisher=[[Lynne Rienner Publishers]]
|isbn=1-58826-270-7
|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=WOBRb0wKpocC&amp;pg=PA58&amp;lpg=PA58&amp;dq
}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was also a [[Catholicism and Freemasonry|Freemason]].&lt;ref&gt;Denslow, William R. [http://books.google.com/books?id=dmPato81X9sC&amp;pg=PA171&amp;dq=plutarco+calles+freemason&amp;sig=NsSB9-6KQUn50HmpBT8eh9nx3No 10,000 Famous Freemasons] p. 171 (2004
Kessinger Publishing)ISBN 1-4179-7578-4&lt;/ref&gt;  Regarding this period, recent President [[Vicente Fox]] stated, "After 1917, Mexico was led by anti-Catholic Freemasons who tried to evoke the anticlerical spirit of popular indigenous President [[Benito Juárez]] of the 1880s. But the military dictators of the 1920s were a more savage lot than Juarez." &lt;ref&gt;Fox, Vicente and Rob Allyn [http://books.google.com/books?id=bLDDf9vi-esC&amp;dq Revolution of Hope] p. 17, Viking, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Cristeroscolgados.jpg|thumb|250px|Cristeros hanged in [[Jalisco]].]]
Due to the strict enforcement of anti-clerical laws, people in strongly [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] areas, especially the states of [[Jalisco]], [[Zacatecas]], [[Guanajuato]], [[Colima]] and [[Michoacán]], began to oppose him, and this opposition led to the [[Cristero War]] from 1926 to 1929, which was characterized by brutal atrocities by both sides. Some Cristeros applied terrorist tactics, while the Mexican government persecuted the clergy, killing suspected Cristeros and supporters and often retaliating against innocent individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/Plutarco_Elias_Calles.aspx Calles, Plutarco Elías] The Columbia Encyclopedia, Sixth Edition. 2001–05 Columbia University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; On May 28, 1926, Calles was awarded a medal of merit from the head of Mexico's Scottish rite of Freemasonry for his actions against the Catholics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.storialibera.it/epoca_contemporanea/messico_1926-1929/articolo.php?id=508 The Cristeros: 20th century Mexico's Catholic uprising, from The Angelus, January 2002 , Volume XXV, Number 1] by Olivier LELIBRE, [[The Angelus]]&lt;/ref&gt;

A truce was negotiated with the assistance of U.S. Ambassador [[Dwight Whitney Morrow]].&lt;ref name="Blood Drenched Altars"&gt;Van Hove, Brian [http://www.ewtn.com/library/HOMELIBR/FR94204.TXT Blood Drenched Altars] 1996 EWTN&lt;/ref&gt; Calles, however, did not abide by the terms of the truce – in violation of its terms, he had approximately 500 Cristero leaders and 5,000 other Cristeros shot, frequently in their homes in front of their spouses and children.&lt;ref name="Blood Drenched Altars"/&gt; Particularly offensive to Catholics after the supposed truce was Calles' insistence on a complete state monopoly on education, suppressing all Catholic education and introducing "socialist" education in its place: "We must enter and take possession of the mind of childhood, the mind of youth.".&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"&gt;Van Hove, Brian [http://www.ewtn.com/library/HOMELIBR/FR94204.TXT Blood-Drenched Altars] Faith &amp; Reason 1994&lt;/ref&gt; The persecution continued as Calles maintained control under his [[Maximato]] and did not relent until 1940, when President [[Manuel Ávila Camacho]], a believing Catholic, took office.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"/&gt; This attempt to indoctrinate the youth in atheism was begun in 1934 by amending Article 3 to the [[Mexican Constitution]] to eradicate religion by mandating "socialist education", which "in addition to removing all religious doctrine" would "combat fanaticism and prejudices", "build[ing] in the youth a rational and exact concept of the universe and of social life".&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu"/&gt; In 1946 this "socialist education" was removed from the constitution and the document returned to the less egregious generalized secular education.
The effects of the war on the Church were profound. Between 1926 and 1934 at least 40 priests were killed.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"/&gt; Where there were 4,500 priests operating within the country before the rebellion, in 1934 there were only 334 priests licensed by the government to serve fifteen million people, the rest having been eliminated by emigration, expulsion, and assassination.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, Robert L. [http://books.google.com/books?id=8aWQ_7oKJfkC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;lpg=PA33&amp;dq=cristero+war+priests+killed&amp;source=web&amp;ots=YNDpLM2ukb&amp;sig=YWccvtnJKnSpaI15bTHCOX3zoyc#PPA33,M1 Latin America's Wars: The Age of the Caudillo, 1791–1899] p. 33 (2003
Brassey's) ISBN 1-57488-452-2&lt;/ref&gt;  By 1935, 17 states had no priest at all.&lt;ref&gt;Ruiz, Ramón Eduardo [http://books.google.com/books?id=AfdjWl1xKpwC&amp;pg=PA392&amp;dq=Tom%C3%A1s+Garrido+Canabal&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=HkfPtdqMt3qrdcMuprgfjnfnq60 Triumphs and Tragedy: A History of the Mexican People] p.393 (1993 W. W. Norton &amp; Company) ISBN 0-393-31066-3&lt;/ref&gt;

==Spanish Civil War==


In the Republican section during the [[Spanish Civil War]] state atheism was mandatory, many priests and nuns were killed, churches demolished and the tombs of saints desecrated.

==Communist states==
{{Main|Marxism and religion}}

[[File:Lenin, Engels, Marx.png|left|thumb|300px|[[Vladimir Lenin]], [[Friedrich Engels]], and [[Karl Marx]], whose combined ideologies formed the [[Marxist-Leninist]] interpretation of [[communism]].]]
A [[communist state]], in popular usage, is a [[State (polity)|state]] with a [[form of government]] characterized by [[Single-party state|single-party rule]] or [[Dominant-party system|dominant-party rule]] of a [[communist party]] and a professed allegiance to a [[Leninist]] or [[Marxist–Leninist]] [[Communism|communist]] ideology as the guiding principle of the state.  The founder and primary theorist of [[Marxism]], the Nineteenth-century German sociologist [[Karl Marx]], had an ambivalent attitude to religion, viewing it primarily as "the [[opium of the people]]" that had been used by the ruling classes to give the [[working classes]] false hope for millennia, whilst at the same time recognizing it as a form of protest by the working classes against their poor economic conditions.&lt;ref&gt;Raines, John. 2002. "Introduction". ''Marx on Religion'' (Marx, Karl). Philadelphia: Temple University Press. Page 05-06.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the Marxist–Leninist interpretation of Marxist theory, developed primarily by Russian revolutionary [[Vladimir Lenin]], religion is seen as negative to human development, and communist states that follow a Marxist–Leninist variant are [[Atheism|atheistic]] and explicitly [[Antireligion|antireligious]].&lt;ref name=Lenin&gt;
{{cite web
 | url=http://www.psylib.ukrweb.net/books/maenl01/txt17
 | last = Lenin
 | first = V. I.
 | title = About the attitude of the working party toward the religion.
 | accessdate=2006-09-09
 | work = Collected works, v. 17, p.41
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;  Lenin states:

{{cquote|Religion is the opiate of the people: this saying of Marx is the cornerstone of the entire ideology of Marxism about religion. All modern religions and churches, all and of every kind of religious organizations are always considered by Marxism as the organs of bourgeois reaction, used for the protection of the exploitation and the stupefaction of the working class.&lt;ref name=Lenin /&gt;}}

Although Marx and Lenin were both atheists, several [[Religious communism|religious communist]] groups exist, and [[Christian communism]] was important in the early development of communism.{{citation needed|date=December 2012}}

===Albania===
{{Main|Religion in Albania#Communist Albania}}

State atheism in [[People's Socialist Republic of Albania|Albania]] was taken to an extreme during the totalitarian regime installed after World War II, when religions, identified as imports foreign to Albanian culture, were banned altogether.&lt;ref name="Hall1999"&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/stable/3060414 Representations of Place: Albania], Derek R. Hall, ''The Geographical Journal'', Vol. 165, No. 2, The Changing Meaning of Place in Post-Socialist Eastern Europe: Commodification, Perception and Environment (Jul., 1999), pp. 161–172, Blackwell Publishing on behalf of The Royal Geographical Society (with the Institute of British Geographers)&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Agrarian Reform Law (Albania)|Agrarian Reform Law]] of August 1945 nationalized most property of religious institutions, including the estates of monasteries, orders, and dioceses. Many clergy and believers were tried, tortured, and executed. All foreign Roman Catholic priests, monks, and nuns were expelled in 1946.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"&gt;[http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-186.html Albania - Hoxha's Antireligious Campaign]&lt;/ref&gt;

Religious communities or branches that had their headquarters outside the country, such as the [[Jesuit]] and [[Franciscan]] orders, were henceforth ordered to terminate their activities in Albania. Religious institutions were forbidden to have anything to do with the education of the young, because that had been made the exclusive province of the state. All religious communities were prohibited from owning real estate and from operating philanthropic and welfare institutions and hospitals.
Although there were tactical variations in [[Enver Hoxha]]'s approach to each of the major denominations, his overarching objective was the eventual destruction of all organized religion in Albania. Between 1945 and 1953, the number of priests was reduced drastically and the number of Roman Catholic churches was decreased from 253 to 100, and all Catholics were stigmatized as fascists.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt;

The campaign against religion peaked in the 1960s. Beginning in 1967 the Albanian authorities began a violent campaign to try to eliminate religious life in Albania. Despite complaints, even by [[Party of Labour of Albania|APL]] members, all churches, mosques, monasteries, and other religious institutions were either closed down or converted into warehouses, gymnasiums, or workshops by the end of 1967.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-170.html Albania - The Cultural and Ideological Revolution]&lt;/ref&gt; By May 1967, religious institutions had been forced to relinquish all 2,169 churches, mosques, cloisters, and shrines in Albania, many of which were converted into cultural centers for young people. As the literary monthly Nendori reported the event, the youth had thus "created the first atheist nation in the world."&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt;

The clergy were publicly vilified and humiliated, their vestments taken and desecrated. More than 200 clerics of various faiths were imprisoned, others were forced to seek work in either industry or agriculture, and some were executed or starved to death. The cloister of the Franciscan order in Shkodër was set on fire, which resulted in the death of four elderly monks.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt;

Article 37 of the Albanian Constitution of 1976 stipulated, "The state recognizes no religion, and supports atheistic propaganda in order to implant a scientific materialistic world outlook in people.",&lt;ref&gt;[http://bjoerna.dk/dokumentation/Albanian-Constitution-1976.htm#C.%20Education,%20Science,%20Culture C. Education, Science, Culture], The Albanian Constitution of 1976.&lt;/ref&gt; and the penal code of 1977 imposed prison sentences of three to ten years for "religious propaganda and the production, distribution, or storage of religious literature." A new decree that in effect targeted Albanians with Muslim and Christian names stipulated that citizens whose names did not conform to "the political, ideological, or moral standards of the state" were to change them. It was also decreed that towns and villages with religious names must be renamed. Hoxha's brutal antireligious campaign succeeded in eradicating formal worship, but some Albanians continued to practice their faith clandestinely, risking severe punishment. Individuals caught with Bibles, icons, or other religious objects faced long prison sentences. Religious weddings were prohibited.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-184.html Albania - Social Structure under Communist Rule]&lt;/ref&gt;

Parents were afraid to pass on their faith, for fear that their children would tell others. Officials tried to entrap practicing Christians and Muslims during religious fasts, such as Lent and Ramadan, by distributing dairy products and other forbidden foods in school and at work, and then publicly denouncing those who refused the food, and clergy who conducted secret services were incarcerated.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt; Catholic priest [[Kurti, Shtjefen|Shtjefen Kurti]] had been executed for secretly baptizing a child in [[Shkodër]] in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;Sinishta, G., 1976. The Fulfilled Promise: A Documentary Account of Religious Persecution in Albania. Albanian Catholic Information Center, Santa Clara.&lt;/ref&gt;

The article was interpreted by Danes as violating The [[United Nations Charter]] (chapter 9, article 55) which declares that [[religious freedom]] is an inalienable human right. The first time that the question came before the United Nations' [[Commission on Human Rights]] at Geneva was as late as 7 March 1983. A delegation from Denmark got its protest over Albania's violation of religious liberty placed on the agenda of the thirty-ninth meeting of the commission, item 25, reading, "Implementation of the Declaration on the Elimination of all Forms of Intolerance and of Discrimination based on Religion or Belief.", and on 20 July 1984 a member of the [[Danish Parliament]] inserted an article in one of Denmark's major newspapers protesting the violation of religious freedom in Albania.

These massive attempts by communists to create an [[atheist]] [[nation]], devastated both [[Islam]] and [[Orthodox Christianity]] and they suffered irreparable loss, while on the other hand [[Roman Catholicism]] rebounded and regained its previous share of the population at 10%.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.islamicpluralism.org/2000/communism-and-religion-in-albania-the-longest&lt;/ref&gt; Despite all of this, majority of [[Albania]]'s population is still affiliated with some form of [[Religion]]. 
According to 2011 census, 58.79% of Albania adheres to [[Islam]], making it the largest [[Religion]] in the country. Majority of Albanian Muslims are Secular Sunni with a significant [[Bektashi]] Shia minority. [[Christianity]] is practiced by 16.99% of the population, making it the 2nd largest religion in the country. Remaining population is either [[Irreligious]] or belongs to other Religious groups.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.instat.gov.al/media/177358/njoftim_per_media_-_fjala_e_drejtorit_te_instat_ines_nurja_per_rezultatet_finale_te_census_2011.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Before World War II, there was given a distribution of 70% Muslims, 20% Eastern Orthodox, and 10% Roman Catholics.&lt;ref name="cia"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/al.html |publisher=Central Intelligence Agency |title=The World Factbook: Albania |accessdate=21 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, Gallup Global Reports 2010 shows that religion plays a role in the lives of only 39% of Albanians, and ranks Albania the thirteenth least religious country in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/128210/Gallup-Global-Reports.aspx |title=Gallup Global Reports |publisher=Gallup.com |date= |accessdate=2013-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===China===
{{Further2|[[Religion in China]]}}

{{Pie chart
|thumb = right
|caption = Religion in China overall based on different surveys&lt;ref name="ECRAN2012"&gt;Yu Tao, University of Oxford. ''[http://www.euecran.eu/pdf/ECRAN%20Analysing%20the%20Recent%20Development%20of%20Religious%20Communities%20in%20Contemporary%20Rural%20China_Yu%20Tao.pdf A Solo, a Duet, or an Ensemble? Analysing the Recent Development of Religious Communities in Contemporary Rural China]''. ECRAN - Europe-China Research and Advice Network. University of Nottingham. '''p. 12'''. ''Retrieved 25-09-2012''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="chinatoday.com.cn"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chinatoday.com.cn/ctenglish/se/txt/2009-06/19/content_203310.htm |title=Buddhism in China. By staff reporter ZHANG XUEYING |publisher=Chinatoday.com.cn |accessdate=2011年10月17日}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pewforum.org"&gt;{{cite web|author=ANALYSIS 1 May 2008 |url=http://pewforum.org/Importance-of-Religion/Religion-in-China-on-the-Eve-of-the-2008-Beijing-Olympics.aspx |title=Religion in China on the Eve of the 2008 Beijing Olympics |publisher=Pew Forum |date=2008年05月01日 |accessdate=2011年10月17日}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="purdue.edu"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/newsroom/research/2010/100726T-YangChina.html |title=Prof: Christians remain a small minority in China today |publisher=Purdue.edu |date=2010年07月26日 |accessdate=2011年10月17日}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|label1 = [[Chinese folk religion|Folk religions]] and [[Taoism]]
|value1 = 30
|color1 = Crimson
|label2 = [[Buddhism]]
|value2 = 18
|color2 = Orange
|label3 = [[Christianity]]
|value3 = 4
|color3 = Turquoise
|label4 = [[Ethnic minorities in China|Ethnic minorities]] indigenous religions (including [[Vajrayana]] and [[Theravada]])
|value4 = 4
|color4 = HotPink
|label5 = [[Islam]]
|value5 = 2
|color5 = LimeGreen
|label6 = [[Agnosticism|Agnostic]] or [[atheism|atheist]]
|value6 = 42
|color6 = SlateGray
}}
Traditionally, a large segment of Chinese population occasionally resorted to Buddhist temples and Buddhism has had a significant role in the everyday life of ordinary people.&lt;ref&gt;The Practice of Chinese Buddhism, 1900–1950 – Page 393&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Chinese Revolution (1949)|1949 Chinese Revolution]], China began a period of rule by the [[Communist Party of China]].&lt;ref&gt;Xie, Zhibin, [http://books.google.com/books?id=peah4XTpqnkC&amp;dq Religious diversity and public religion in China], p.145, Ashgate Publishing 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tyler, Christian [http://books.google.com/books?id=bEzNwgtiVQ0C&amp;dq Wild West China], p. 259, Rutgers Univ. Press 2004&lt;/ref&gt; For much of its early history, that government maintained under [[Marxism|Marxist]] thought that religion would ultimately disappear, and characterized it as emblematic of [[feudalism]] and foreign [[colonialism]]. 

During the [[Cultural Revolution]], student vigilantes known as [[Red Guards (China)|Red Guards]] converted religious buildings for secular use or destroyed them. This attitude, however, relaxed considerably in the late 1970s, with the [[reform and opening up]] period. The [[1978 Constitution of the People's Republic of China]] guaranteed [[freedom of religion]] with a number of restrictions.  Since then, there has been a massive program to rebuild Buddhist and Taoist temples that were destroyed in the Cultural Revolution.

The Communist Party has said that religious belief and membership are incompatible.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deccanherald.com/content/212827/no-religion-chinese-communist-party.html "No Religion for Chinese Communist Party Cadres".  ''Deccan Herald''.  December 2011.]&lt;/ref&gt; However, the state is not allowed to force ordinary citizens to become atheists.&lt;ref name="Temperman"&gt;{{cite book|title=State-Religion Relationship and Human Rights Law: Towards a Right to Religiously Neutral Governance|first=Jeroen|last=Temperman|publisher=Brill|date=May 30, 2010|pages=141–145}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are five religions recognized by the state: Buddhism, Taoism, Islam, Catholic Christianity, and Protestant Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.china-embassy.org/eng/zt/zjxy/t36492.htm
|title= White Paper—Freedom of Religious Belief in China
|publisher=Embassy of the People's Republic of China in the United States of America
|month=October
|year=1997
|accessdate=2007-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; (However, Chinese state Catholicism is not allowed to be affiliated in any way with Rome, and state Protestantism is similarly not allowed to be affiliated with Protestant churches abroad.) The state even promotes "normal" religious activity (e.g., not using mosques as a platform to preach jihad against the state) as a force for the stability of China.&lt;ref name="Temperman"/&gt;

Most people report no organized religious affiliation; however, people with a belief in folk traditions and spiritual beliefs, such as [[ancestor veneration]] and [[feng shui]], along with informal ties to local temples and unofficial house churches number in the hundreds of millions. The [[United States Department of State]], in its annual report on International Religious Freedom,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/irf/rpt/
|title=Annual Report to Congress on International Religious Freedom
|publisher=U.S.Department of State
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; provides statistics about organized religions. In 2007 it reported the following (citing the  Government's 1997 report on Religious Freedom and 2005 White Paper on religion):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90133.htm
|title=International Religious Freedom Report 2007 — China (includes Tibet, Hong Kong, and Macau)
|year=2007
|publisher=U.S.Department of State
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:* Buddhists 8%.
:* Taoists, unknown as a percentage partly because it is fused along with Confucianism and Buddhism.
:* Muslims, 1%, with more than 20,000 [[Imams]]. Other estimates state at least 1%.
:* Christians, Protestants at least 3%. Catholics, about 1.5%.

Statistics relating to [[Buddhism]] and religious [[Taoism]] are to some degree incomparable with statistics for [[Islam]] and [[Christianity]]. This is due to the traditional [[China|Chinese]] belief system which blends [[Confucianism]], [[Buddhism]], and [[Taoism]], so that a person who follows a traditional belief system would not necessarily identify him- or herself as exclusively Buddhist or Taoist, despite attending Buddhist or Taoist places of worship. According to Peter Ng, Professor of the Department of Religion at the Chinese University of Hong Kong, as of 2002, 95% of Chinese were religious in some way if religion is considered to include traditional folk practices such as burning incense for gods or ancestors at life-cycle or seasonal festivals, fortune telling and related customary practices.&lt;ref name=madsen&gt;{{cite book|last=Madsen|first=Richard|title=Chinese society: change, conflict and resistance|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-56073-3|editor=Elizabeth J. Perry, Mark Selden|page=239|chapter=Chapter 10. Chinese Christianity: Indigenization and conflict}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Tze Ming Ng, “Religious Situations in China Today: Secularization Theory Revisited” Paper presented at the Association for the Sociology of Religion Meetings, Chicago, August 14–16, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cuba===

Originally more tolerant of religion, [[Cuba]] began arresting many believers and shutting down religious schools after the [[Bay of Pigs Invasion]], its prisons since the 1960s being filled with clergy.&lt;ref name=Hertzke2006p43&gt;[[#Hertzke2006|Hertzke (2006)]]:[http://books.google.com/books?id=EkIvbxefBNsC&amp;pg=PA43 43]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1961 The Cuban government confiscated Catholic schools, including the Jesuit school Fidel Castro had attended. In 1965 it exiled two hundred priests.&lt;ref name=buckley2005-11-21&gt;William F. Buckley Jr., [http://old.nationalreview.com/flashback/1998200511210830.asp Cuba libre?], November 21, 2005, National review.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Communist Party of Cuba]] defines one of its aims as "the gradual overcoming of religious beliefs by [[materialist]]ic scientific propaganda and the cultural advancement of the workers."&lt;ref name="Temperman"/&gt; From 1976 to 1992, the [[Constitution of Cuba]] contained  a clause stating that the "socialist state...bases its activity on, and educates the people in, the scientific materialist concept of the universe". In 1992, the Communist Party of Cuba has allowed religious believers to join.&lt;ref name="Temperman"/&gt; Since the fall of the Soviet Union, Cuba has amended its statutes to declare itself a "[[secular state]]" rather than atheistic.

===Soviet Union===
{{main|Atheism in the Soviet Union}}
[[File:1922 Bezbozhnik magazine cover.jpg|left|thumb|USSR. 1922 issue of the ''[[Bezbozhnik (magazine)|Bezbozhnik]]'' (The Godless) magazine. By 1934, 28% of Eastern Orthodox churches, 42% of Muslim mosques and 52% of Jewish synagogues were shut down in the USSR.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071023063308/http://www.friends-partners.org/partners/beyond-the-pale/english/43.html Religions attacked in the USSR] (Beyond the Pale)&lt;/ref&gt;]]
State atheism in the Soviet Union (''gosateizm'') attempted to stop the spread of religious beliefs as well as remove "prerevolutionary remnants".&lt;ref name="Kowalewski1980"&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/stable/128810 Protest for Religious Rights in the USSR: Characteristics and Consequences], David Kowalewski, ''Russian Review'', Vol. 39, No. 4 (Oct., 1980), pp. 426–441, Blackwell Publishing on behalf of The Editors and Board of Trustees of the Russian Review&lt;/ref&gt;  Although all religions were persecuted,&lt;ref name=RussianOrthodox /&gt; the regime's efforts to eradicate religion, however, varied over the years with respect to particular religions, and were affected by higher state interests. Official policies and practices not only varied with time, but also in their application from one nationality and one religion to another.  Nationality and religion were always closely linked, and the attitude toward religion varied from a total ban on some religions to official support of others.

From the late 1920s to the late 1930s, such organizations as the [[League of Militant Atheists|League of the Militant Godless]] ridiculed all religions and harassed believers.{{citation needed|date=December 2012}} Anti-religious and atheistic propaganda was implemented into every portion of soviet life: in schools, communist organizations such as the [[Young Pioneer organization of the Soviet Union|Young Pioneer Organization]], and the media. Though Lenin originally introduced the [[Gregorian calendar]] to the Soviets, subsequent efforts to reorganise the week to improve worker productivity saw the introduction of the [[Soviet calendar]], which had the side-effect that a "holiday will seldom fall on Sunday".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,930406,00.html
|title=Staggerers Unstaggered
|date=December 7, 1931
|publisher=Time magazine
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within about a year of the revolution, the state [[Eminent domain|expropriated]] all church property, including the churches themselves, and in the period from 1922 to 1926, 28 Russian Orthodox bishops and more than 1,200 priests were killed (a much greater number was subjected to persecution).&lt;ref name=RussianOrthodox&gt;[http://countrystudies.us/russia/38.htm Country Studies: Russia-The Russian Orthodox Church] U.S. Library of Congress, Accessed Apr. 3, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  Most seminaries were closed, and publication of religious writing was banned.&lt;ref name=RussianOrthodox /&gt;  The Russian Orthodox Church, which had 54,000 parishes before World War I, was reduced to 500 by 1940.&lt;ref name=RussianOrthodox /&gt;  A meeting of the Antireligious Commission of the Central Committee of the All-Union Communist Party ([[Bolsheviks]]) that occurred on 23 May 1929 estimated the portion of believers in the [[USSR]] at 80 percent, though this percentage may be understated to prove the successfulness of the struggle with religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Marjorie Mandelstam Balzer|title=Religion and Politics in Russia: A Reader|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=DEufvUyRcygC|year=2009|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|isbn=978-0-7656-2415-4|pages=[http://books.google.com/books?id=DEufvUyRcygC&amp;pg=PA6 6–7]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Today, approximately 100 million citizens consider themselves Russian Orthodox Christians, amounting to 70% of population, although the Church claims a membership of 80 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article551693.ece | work=The Times | location=London | title=The rise of Russian Muslims worries Orthodox Church | first=Jeremy | last=Page | date=2005-08-05 | accessdate=2010-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90196.htm Russia]&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[CIA Factbook]], however, only 17% to 22% of the population is now Christian.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, Ethan [http://www.christianpost.com/article/20080324/31660_Gorbachev_Dispels_'Closet_Christian'_Rumors;_Says_He_is_Atheist.htm Gorbachev Dispels 'Closet Christian' Rumors; Says He is Atheist] Christian Post Reporter, Mar. 24, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the Soviet Union's attempts to eliminate religion,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jstor.org/pss/128810&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sabrina Petra Ramet, Ed., Religious Policy in the Soviet Union. Cambridge University Press (1993). P 4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Anderson, Religion, State and Politics in the Soviet Union and Successor States, Cambridge University Press, 1994, pp 3&lt;/ref&gt; other former USSR and anti-religious nations, such as [[Armenia]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/?id=5211|title=The Armenian Apostolic Church (World Council of Churches)}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kazakhstan]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2009/127366.htm International Religious Freedom Report 2009 – Kazakhstan] U.S. Department of State. 2009-10-26. Retrieved on 2009-11-05.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Uzbekistan]],&lt;ref name="state1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2924.htm |title=Uzbekistan |publisher=State.gov |date=2009-10-16 |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Turkmenistan]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/tx.html CIA - The World Factbook]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kyrgyzstan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2001/5598.htm |title=Kyrgyzstan |publisher=State.gov |date= |accessdate=2010-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tajikistan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5775.htm |title=Background Note: Tajikistan |publisher=State.gov |date= |accessdate=2009-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Belarus]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmaster.com/country/bo-belarus/rel-religion NationMaster - Belarusian Religion statistics]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/bo.html CIA - The World Factbook]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Moldova]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmaster.com/country/md-moldova/rel-religion NationMaster - Moldovan Religion statistics]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Albania]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/al.html CIA World Factbvook : Albania], reporting Muslim 70%, Albanian Orthodox 20%, Roman Catholic 10%, but noting, "percentages are estimates; there are no available current statistics on religious affiliation; all mosques and churches were closed in 1967 and religious observances prohibited; in November 1990, Albania began allowing private religious practice"&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmaster.com/country/gg-georgia/rel-religion NationMaster - Georgian Religion statistics]&lt;/ref&gt; have high religious populations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | editor-last = Miller | editor-first = Tracy | month = October | year = 2009 | publisher = [[Pew Research Center]] | title = Mapping the Global Muslim Population: A Report on the Size and Distribution of the World’s Muslim Population | format = [[Portable Document Format|PDF]] | url = http://pewforum.org/newassets/images/reports/Muslimpopulation/Muslimpopulation.pdf | accessdate = 8 October 2009}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Author Niels Christian Nielsen has written that the post-Soviet population in areas which were formerly predominantly Orthodox are now "nearly illiterate regarding religion", almost completely lacking the intellectual or philosophical aspects of their faith and having almost no knowledge of other faiths.&lt;ref&gt;Nielsen, Niels Christian, Jr., [http://books.google.com/books?id=Ts6w8JumlQMC&amp;d Christianity After Communism], p. 77-78, Westview Press 1998&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, their knowledge of their faith and the faith of others notwithstanding, many post-Soviet populations have a large presence of religious followers.

Today in the [[Russian Federation]], approximately 100 million citizens consider themselves Russian Orthodox Christians, amounting to 70% of population, although the Church claims a membership of 80 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article551693.ece | work=The Times | location=London | title=The rise of Russian Muslims worries Orthodox Church | first=Jeremy | last=Page | date=2005-08-05 | accessdate=2010-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90196.htm Russia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90196.htm|accessdate=2008-04-08|title=Russia}}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to a poll by the [[VCIOM|Russian Public Opinion Research Center]], 63% of respondents considered themselves Russian Orthodox, 6% of respondents considered themselves [[Muslim]] and less than 1% considered themselves either Buddhist, Catholic, Protestant or Jewish. Another 12% said they believe in God, but did not practice any religion, and 16% said they are non-believers.&lt;ref name=religionsurvey&gt;{{cite web|title= Опубликована подробная сравнительная статистика религиозности в России и Польше|publisher=religare.ru|date=6 June 2007|url=http://www.religare.ru/article42432.htm|accessdate=2007-12-27}} {{ru icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Ukraine]], 96.1% of the [[Ukrainians|Ukrainian]] population is [[Christian]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmaster.com/country/up-ukraine/rel-religion NationMaster - Ukrainian Religion statistics]&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Lithuania]], the only Catholic country which was once a Soviet republic,{{Citation needed|date=June 2013}} a 2005 report stated that 79% of [[Lithuanians]] belonged to the [[Roman Catholic Church]].&lt;ref&gt;Department of Statistics to the Government of the Republic of Lithuania. ''{{cite web |url=http://www.std.lt/en/pages/view/?id=1734 |title=Population by Religious Confession, census  |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20061001185140/http://www.std.lt/en/pages/view/?id=1734 |archivedate=2006-10-01}}''. Updated in 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

==North Korea==

[[North Korea]]'s government exercises virtual total control over society and imposes the [[cult of personality]] of [[Kim Jung Il]] and [[Kim Il Sung]], described as a [[political religion]]. Their ideology has been described as [[irreligion|"state-sanctioned atheism"]].&lt;ref name=Hertzke2006p44&gt;[[#Hertzke2006|Hertzke (2006)]]:[http://books.google.com/books?id=EkIvbxefBNsC&amp;pg=PA44 44]&lt;/ref&gt; Although the North Korean constitution states that freedom of religion is permitted,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.korea-np.co.jp/pk/061st_issue/98091708.htm DPRK's Socialist Constitution (Full Text)]&lt;/ref&gt; free religious activities no longer exist in North Korea, as the government sponsors religious groups only to create an illusion of religious freedom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/english/docs/2004/07/08/nkorea9040.htm Essential Background: Overview of human rights issues in Human Rights in North Korea (DPRK: The Democratic People's Republic of Korea) (Human Rights Watch, 8-7-2004)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/kn.html CIA - The World Factbook]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinal]] [[Nicolas Cheong Jin-suk]] has said that, "There's no knowledge of priests surviving persecution that came in the late forties, when 166 priests and religious were killed or kidnapped." which includes the Roman Catholic [[bishop of Pyongyang]], [[Francis Hong Yong-ho]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.30giorni.it/us/articolo.asp?id=10278 30Giorni | Korea, for a reconciliation between North and South (Interview with Cardinal Nicholas Cheong Jinsuk by Gianni Cardinale)]&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Juche]]'' ideology, based on [[Korean nationalism|Korean ultranationalism]], calls on people to "avoid spiritual deference to outside influences", which was interpreted as including religion originating outside of Korea.&lt;ref name="Temperman" /&gt; On November 2013, the repression against religious people led to the public execution of 80 people who possessed a [[Bible]].&lt;ref&gt; [[Fox News]], November 11, 2013. "[http://www.foxnews.com/world/2013/11/11/north-korea-publicly-executes-80-for-crimes-like-watching-films-owning-bible/ North Korea publicly executes 80, some for videos or Bibles, report says]"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://koreajoongangdaily.joins.com/news/article/article.aspx?aid=2980240&amp;cloc=joongangdaily|home|newslist1 Public executions seen in 7 North Korea cities, [[JoongAng Ilbo|Korea JoongAng Daily]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-1-of-3}}
* [[Antireligion]]
* [[Atheist nationalism]]
* [[Civil religion]]
* [[Communism and religion]]

{{Col-2-of-3}}
* [[Reign of Terror]]
* [[Religion in China]]
* [[Religion in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Religious persecution]]

{{Col-3-of-3}}
{{Portal|Atheism}}
* [[Religion in Russia]]
* [[Society of the Godless]]
* [[Staatssekretär für Kirchenfragen]]
* [[Terrible Triangle]]
* [[War in the Vendée]]
{{Col-end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
* {{wikicite |ref={{harvid|Baggini|2003}} |reference=Julian Baggini. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=bHSW8Wng6oEC Atheism: A Very Short Introduction]''. Oxford University Press; 2003. ISBN 978-0-19-280424-2.}}
* {{wikicite |ref="Davies1996" |reference=Davies, Norman. 1996. ''Europe: a history.'' Oxford: Oxford University Press.}}
* {{wikicite |ref="Dawkins2006" |reference=[[Richard Dawkins|Dawkins, Richard]]. 2006. ''[[The God Delusion]]''. Houghton Mifflin. ISBN 978-0-618-68000-9.}}
* {{wikicite |ref="Elsie2000" |reference=Elsie, Robert. 2000. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=N_IXHrXIsYkC A Dictionary of Albanian Religion, Mythology, and Folk Culture]''. C. Hurst &amp; Co. ISBN 978-1-85065-570-1.}}
* {{wikicite |ref="Elsie2001" |reference=Elsie, Robert. 2001. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=aAtQZ0vjf5gC A Dictionary of Albanian Religion, Mythology, and Folk Culture]''. New York: NYU Press. ISBN 0-8147-2214-8.}}
* {{wikicite |ref=Freemont-Barnes2007 |reference=Fremont-Barnes, Gregory. 2007. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=6_2wkP4j-EsC&amp;dq Encyclopedia of the Age of Political Revolutions and New Ideologies, 1760–1815]''. Greenwood Publishing Group. ISBN 978-0-313-33445-0.}}
* {{wikicite |ref=Gach2002 |reference=Gach, Gary. 2002. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=TvxsxV9oLqcChttp://books.google.com/books?id=arEFgUw-4b8C The complete idiot's guide to understanding Buddhism]. Alpha Books. ISBN 978-0-02-864170-6.}}
* {{wikicite |ref="Greeley2003" |reference=Greeley, Andrew M. 2003. ''Religion in Europe at the end of the second millennium: a sociological profile''. New Brunswick, N.J.: Transaction Publishers.}}
* {{wikicite |ref=Hertzke2006 |reference=Hertzke, Allen. 2006. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=EkIvbxefBNsC&amp;dq Freeing God's Children]''. Rowman &amp; Littlefield}}
* {{wikicite |ref=Jacques1995 |reference=Jacques, Edwin E. 1995. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=IJ2s9sQ9bGkC The Albanians: an ethnic history from prehistoric times to the present]''. McFarland. ISBN 978-0-89950-932-7.}}
* {{wikicite |ref="Marx1844" |reference=[[Karl Marx|Marx, Karl]]. February, 1844. ''[http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1843/critique-hpr/intro.htm A Contribution to the Critique of Hegel's Philosophy of Right]''. Deutsch-Französische Jahrbücher.}}
* {{wikicite |ref=JonassohnBjeornson1998 |reference=Jonassohn, Kurt and Karin Solveig Bjeornson. 1998. ''Genocide and Gross Human Rights Violations''. [[Transaction Publishers]]. ISBN 0-7658-0417-4.}}
* {{wikicite |ref=McCann1997 |reference=McCann, David R. 1997. ''Korea briefing: toward reunification'', Volume 4 of Korea briefing, Asia Society Briefings Series, Asia Society Country Briefing, Briefings of the Asia Society. M.E. Sharpe. ISBN 978-1-56324-885-6}}
* {{wikicite |ref=McGrath2006 |reference=McGrath, Alister E.  2006. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=24Xk90Bsp4gC&amp;dq The Twilight of Atheism]'', Random House.}}
* {{wikicite |ref="Miner2003" |reference=Miner, Steven Merritt. 2003. ''Stalin's holy war religion, nationalism, and alliance politics, 1941–1945''. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press.}}
* {{wikicite |ref="Pipes1989" |reference=Pipes, Daniel. 1989. ''The long shadow: culture and politics in the Middle East''. New Brunswick, U.S.A.: Transaction Publishers.}}
* {{wikicite |ref="Pospielovsky1998" |reference=Pospielovsky, Dimitry. 1935.  ''The Orthodox Church in the History of Russia'' Published 1998. St Vladimir's Seminary Press, 413 pages, ISBN 0-88141-179-5.}}
* {{wikicite |ref=Spielvogel2005 |reference=Spielvogel, Jackson. 2005. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=ni4PSpOxb6MC&amp;dq Western Civilization: Combined Volume]''. Thomson Wadsworth.}}
* {{wikicite |ref=Tallet1991 |reference=Tallet, Frank. 1991. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=aL4lsWdd-rAC&amp;dq Religion, Society and Politics in France Since 1789]''. Continuum International Publishing}}
* {{wikicite |ref="Wolak2004" |reference=Wolak, Arthur J. 2004. ''Forced out: the fate of Polish Jewry in Communist Poland''. Tucson, Ariz: Fenestra Books.}}

{{Relpolnav}}
{{Religious persecution|right}}
{{Atheism}}
{{Belief systems}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:State Atheism}}
[[Category:Atheism]]
[[Category:Religious law]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Religious discrimination]]
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Church and state law]]
[[Category:Political theories]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>