<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071014220749|164584862" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="844779" pageid="844779" ns="0" title="State atheism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-10-14T22:13:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{atheism2}}
'''State atheism''' is the official rejection of [[religion]] in all forms by a [[government]] in favor of [[atheism]]. The only country to officially ban religion was [[Albania]] under [[Enver Hoxha]]; however, numerous governments such as [[People's Republic of China|China]] and [[Mongolia]] throughout history have actively (and, sometimes, violently) opposed religion, persecuting religious institutions, leaders and believers, to the same extent as Hoxha's Albania. The [[Soviet Union]] had a long history of state atheism,&lt;ref&gt;Greeley, Andrew M. 2003. ''Religion in Europe at the end of the second millennium: a sociological profile''. New Brunswick, N.J.: Transaction Publishers.
&lt;/ref&gt; in which social success largely required individuals to proclaim atheism and stay away from churches; this attitude was especially militant under Stalin.&lt;ref&gt;By Pospielovsky
, Dimitry, 1935-  ''The Orthodox Church in the History of Russia''
Published 1998. St Vladimir's Seminary Press, 413 pages, ISBN 0881411795 page 257.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Miner, Steven Merritt. 2003. Stalin's holy war religion, nationalism, and alliance politics, 1941-1945. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press. Page 70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Davies, Norman. 1996. ''Europe: a history.'' Oxford: Oxford University Press. Page 962.&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union imposed atheism over wide areas of its influence, including places like central Asia.&lt;ref&gt;Pipes, Daniel. 1989. ''The long shadow: culture and politics in the Middle East''. New Brunswick, U.S.A.: Transaction Publishers. Page 55.&lt;/ref&gt;

Poland under communist rule promoted state atheism and suppressed religion.&lt;ref&gt;Wolak, Arthur J. 2004. ''Forced out: the fate of Polish Jewry in Communist Poland''. Tucson, Ariz: Fenestra Books. [Page 104.&lt;/ref&gt;

State atheism should not be confused either with [[anti-clericalism]] – the effort to reduce the power of the [[clergy]], especially in [[politics]] – or with [[secular state|state secularism]] in which a state decides to refrain from having an established religion or to take a neutral view toward religious matters. A state established religion within a political system implies preferential treatment of one tradition at the expense of others. Finally, state atheism should not be confused with selective [[persecution]] of some religious beliefs or their adherents in favor of some other, more dominant religion.

==Persecution under Communist regimes==
Communist states have defined fealty to the state in such a way that religion can be proscribed or surpressed.&lt;ref name=Pargeter2005&gt;Pargeter, Mark [http://www.starlightsite.co.uk/keston/lectures/sound/belivers.html Persecution of Believers] Keston Institute: Resources for the Studies of Communist Countries and Religious Affairs February 16, 2005{{Verify credibility|date=September 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because the religious faithful typically give their loyalty to a power above their state, such states have commonly treated this as a basis for supression or prohibition of the faith.  For example, the state would claim Jews were considered beholden to the State of Israel, Catholics to the Vatican City, Buddhists in Tibet to the Dalai Lama, and thereby attach the charge of sedition to certain religions.&lt;ref name=Pargeter2005/&gt;

==Albania under Hoxha==
{{clear}}
{{Religious persecution|right}}
{{Main|Religion in Albania}}
The trend toward state atheism in [[Albania]] was taken to an extreme during the [[totalitarian]] regime, when religions, identified as imports foreign to Albanian culture, were banned altogether. This policy was mainly applied and felt within the borders of the present Albanian state, thus producing a [[nonreligious]] majority in the population. 

The [[Agrarian Reform Law]] of August [[1945]] nationalized most property of religious institutions, including the estates of monasteries, orders, and dioceses. By May [[1967]], religious institutions had relinquished all 2,169 churches, mosques, cloisters, and shrines, many of which were converted into [[cultural center]]s for young people. Many Muslim imams and Orthodox priests renounced their "parasitic" past. More than 200 clerics of various faiths were imprisoned, while others were forced to seek work in either [[industry]] or [[agriculture]]. As the literary monthly "Nëndori" reported the event, the youth had thus "''created the first [[Atheist]] nation in the world.''"   
From year [[1967]] to the end of the [[totalitarian regime]], religious practices were banned and the country was proclaimed officially [[Atheist]], marking an event that happened for the first time in world history. Albanians born during the regime were never taught religion, so they grew up to become either [[Atheists]] or [[Agnostics]]. 

Old non-institutional [[Pagan]] practices in rural areas, which were seen as identifying with the national culture, were left intact. As a result the current Albanian state has also brought pagan festivals to life, like the lunar [[Spring Day|Spring]] festival ([[Albanian language|Albanian]]: ''Dita e Verës'') held yearly on [[March 14th]] in the city of [[Elbasan]], which is a national holiday.

==Religion in the Soviet Union==
{{Main|Religion in the Soviet Union}}
[[Image:1922 Bezbozhnik magazine cover.jpg|thumb|USSR. 1922 issue of the ''Bezbozhnik'' (The Atheist) magazine. By 1934, 28% of Christian Orthodox churches, 42% of Muslim mosques and 52% of Jewish synagogues were shut down in the USSR.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.friends-partners.org/partners/beyond-the-pale/english/43.html Religions attacked in the USSR] (Beyond the Pale)&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Soviet policy toward religion was based on the ideology of [[Marxism-Leninism]], which made atheism the official doctrine of the Soviet Union. As the founder of the Soviet state V. I. [[Lenin]]  put it: &lt;blockquote&gt;Religion is the [[opium of the people]]: this saying of [[Marx]] is the cornerstone of the entire ideology of Marxism about religion. All modern religions and churches, all and of every kind of religious organizations are always considered by Marxism as the organs of bourgeois reaction, used for the protection of the exploitation and the stupefaction of the working class.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.psylib.ukrweb.net/books/maenl01/txt17
 | last = Lenin
 | first = V. I.
 | title = About the attitude of the working party toward the religion.
 | accessdate=2006-09-09
 | work = Collected works, v. 17, p.41
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Marxism-Leninism has consistently advocated the control, suppression, and, ultimately, the elimination of religious beliefs. In the 1920s and 1930s, such organizations as the [[League of the Militant Godless]] ridiculed all religions and harassed believers. Atheism was propagated through schools, communist organizations (such as the [[Young Pioneer organization of the Soviet Union|Young Pioneer Organization]]), and the media. Though Lenin originally introduced the [[Gregorian calendar]] to the Soviets subsequent efforts to re-organise the week for the purposes of improving worker productivity with the introduction of the [[Soviet revolutionary calendar]] had a side-effect that a "holiday will seldom fall on Sunday" &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,930406,00.html
|title=Staggerers Unstaggered
|date=[[December 7]], [[1931]]
|publisher=Time magazine
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The regime's efforts to eradicate religion in the Soviet Union, however, varied over the years with respect to particular religions, and were affected by higher state interests. Official policies and practices not only varied with time but also in their application from one nationality and one religion to another. Although all Soviet leaders had the same long-range goal of developing a cohesive Soviet people, they pursued different policies to achieve it. For the Soviet regime, the questions of nationality and religion were always closely linked. Not surprisingly, therefore, the attitude toward religion also varied from a total ban on some religions to official support of others.

==The People's Republic of China==
{{Main|Religion in the People's Republic of China}}
The [[People's Republic of China]] was established in [[1949]] and for much of its early history maintained a hostile attitude toward religion which was seen as emblematic of [[feudalism]] and foreign [[colonialism]]. Houses of worship, including temples, mosques, and churches, were converted into non-religious buildings for secular use. 

In the early years of the People's Republic, religious belief or practice was often discouraged because it was regarded by the government as backward and superstitious and because some [[Communist]] leaders, ranging from [[Vladimir Lenin]] to [[Mao Zedong]], had been critical of religious institutions. During the [[Cultural Revolution]], religion was condemned as [[feudalistic]] and thousands of religious buildings were looted and destroyed.

This attitude, however, relaxed considerably in the late [[1970s]], with the end of the Cultural Revolution. The [[1978 Constitution of the People's Republic of China]] guarantees "freedom of religion" with a number of restrictions.  Since the mid-1990s there has been a massive program to rebuild Buddhist and Taoist temples that were destroyed in the Cultural Revolution.

The Communist Party has said that religious belief and membership are incompatible. Party membership is a necessity for many high level careers and posts. That along with other official hostility makes statistical reporting on religious membership difficult.  There are five recognized religions by the state, Buddhism, Taoism, Islam, Catholic Christianity, and Protestant Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.china-embassy.org/eng/zt/zjxy/t36492.htm
|title= White Paper--Freedom of Religious Belief in China
|publisher=Embassy of the People's Republic of China in the United States of America
|month=October
|year=1997
|accessdate=2007-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most people report no organized religious affiliation; however, people with a belief in folk traditions and non-religious spiritual beliefs, such as [[ancestor veneration]] and [[feng shui]], along with informal ties to local temples and unofficial house churches number in the hundreds of millions. The [[United States Department of State]], in its annual report on International Religious Freedom,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/irf/rpt/
|title=Annual Report to Congress on International Religious Freedom
|publisher=U.S.Department of State
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; gives possibly the most reliable statistics about organized religions. In 2007 it reported the following (citing the  Government's 1997 report on Religious Freedom and 2005 White Paper on religion):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90133.htm
|title=International Religious Freedom Report 2007 &amp;mdash; China (includes Tibet, Hong Kong, and Macau)
|year=2007
|publisher=U.S.Department of State
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:*Buddhists 8%&lt;!--0.1B/1.3B=7.7%--&gt;, with more than 200,000 monks and nuns. This value is seen as extremely low because there are more than 16,000 Buddhist temples that do not maintain traditional congregations.
:*Taoists, unknown as a percentage, there are more than 25,000 Taoist monks and nuns at more than 1,500 temples. Taoist belief is often intertwined with both Buddhism and traditional folk religions.
:*Muslims, 1.5%&lt;!--0.02B/1.3B=1.5%--&gt;, with more than 45,000 [[Imams]]. Other estimates are much higher.
:*Protestant Christians, at least 1.5%&lt;!--0.02B/1.3B=1.5%--&gt; with official churches. It was estimated that the percentage of Christians had reached 10%&lt;!--0.13B/1.3B=10%--&gt; by the end of 2006, about 1.5%&lt;!--0.02B/1.3B=1.5%--&gt; being Catholics.

It should be noted, however, that statistics relating to [[Buddhism]] and religious [[Taoism]] are to some degree incomparable with statistics for [[Islam]] and [[Christianity]]. This is due to the traditional [[China|Chinese]] belief system which blends [[Confucianism]], [[Buddhism]], and [[Taoism]], so that a person who follows a traditional belief system would not necessarily identify him- or herself as either Buddhist or Taoist, despite attending Buddhist or Taoist places of worship.

==External Links==
*[http://www.starlightsite.co.uk/keston/frontier/frontierindex.aspx Keston Institute: Resources for the Studies of Communist Countries and Religious Affairs]

==See also==
*[[Antireligion]]
*[[Society of the Godless]]
*[[Religious persecution]]
*[[Religion in Albania]]
*[[Religion in China]]
*[[Religion in the Soviet Union]]
*[[Religion in Poland]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

{{Atheism}}
{{Belief systems}}

[[Category:Atheism]]
[[Category:Religious law]]
[[Category:Separation of church and state]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]

[[ko:국가 무신론주의]]
[[it:Ateismo di Stato]]
[[fi:Valtioateismi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>