<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20060704204638|62077295" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="844779" pageid="844779" ns="0" title="State atheism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-09-03T16:24:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''State atheism''' is the official rejection of [[religion]] in all forms by a [[government]] in favor of [[atheism]]. The only country to ''officially'' ban religion was [[Albania]] under [[Enver Hoxha]]; however, numerous governments throughout history have actively (and, sometimes, violently) opposed religion, persecuting religious institutions, leaders and believers, to the same extent with Hoxha's Albania.

State atheism should not be confused either with [[anti-clericalism]] – the effort to reduce the power of the [[clergy]], especially in [[politics]] – or with religious neutrality, in which a government recognizes the legal necessity of the [[separation of church and state]]. A state-sponsored religion within a political system implies preferential treatment of one tradition at the expense of others; thus the separation of church and state protects religious minorities. Finally, state atheism should not be confused with selective [[persecution]] of some religious beliefs or their adherents in favor of some other, more dominant religion. State atheism is opposed to all forms of religion equally.

State atheism implies that the government actively opposes all forms of religion, while secular government can simply involve a government taking a neutral view towards religious matters.

==See also==
*[[Antireligion]]
*[[Secular republic]]
*[[Society of the Godless]]

{{atheism}}

[[Category:Atheism]]
[[Category:Religious law]]

[[fi:Valtioateismi]]
[[it:Ateismo di stato]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>