<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111114221642|460682361" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="844779" pageid="844779" ns="0" title="State atheism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-14T22:22:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{POV|date=August 2011}}
{{Weasel|date=August 2011}}
{{atheism2}}
[[Image:Cruikshank - The Radical's Arms.png|thumb|right|1819 [[Caricature]] by English [[caricaturist]] [[George Cruikshank]]. Titled "The Radical's Arms", it depicts the infamous guillotine. "No God! No Religion! No King! No Constitution!" is written in the republican banner.]]
'''State atheism''' is the official "promotion of [[atheism]]" by a [[government]], sometimes combined with active suppression of [[religious freedom]] and practice.&lt;ref name="Kowalewski1980"&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/stable/128810 Protest for Religious Rights in the USSR: Characteristics and Consequences], David Kowalewski, ''Russian Review'', Vol. 39, No. 4 (Oct., 1980), pp. 426–441, Blackwell Publishing on behalf of The Editors and Board of Trustees of the Russian Review&lt;/ref&gt;  In contrast, a [[secular state]] purports to be officially neutral in matters of [[religion]], supporting neither religion nor [[irreligion]].&lt;ref&gt;Madeley, John T. S. and Zsolt Enyedi, [http://books.google.com/books?id=n5Brda6FmswC&amp;dq Church and state in contemporary Europe: the chimera of neutrality], p. , 2003 Routledge&lt;/ref&gt;

Atheism is the absence of belief that any deities exist&lt;ref&gt;[[Religioustolerance.org]]'s short article on [http://www.religioustolerance.org/atheist4.htm Definitions of the term "Atheism"] suggests that there is no consensus on the definition of the term. [[Simon Blackburn]] summarizes the situation in [[The Oxford Dictionary of Philosophy]]: "Atheism. Either the lack of belief in a god, or the belief that there is none". Most dictionaries (see the OneLook query for [http://www.onelook.com/?w=atheism&amp;ls=a "atheism"]) first list one of the more narrow definitions. * {{Cite book |url=http://www.ditext.com/runes/a.html |title=Dictionary of Philosophy |first=Dagobert D.(editor) |last=Runes |authorlink=Dagobert D. Runes |year=1942 edition |publisher=Littlefield, Adams &amp; Co. Philosophical Library |location=New Jersey |isbn=0-06-463461-2 |quote=(a) the belief that there is no God; (b) Some philosophers have been called "atheistic" because they have not held to a belief in a personal God. Atheism in this sense means "not theistic". The former meaning of the term is a literal rendering. The latter meaning is a less rigorous use of the term though widely current in the history of thought | accessdate=2011-04-09}} - entry by [[Vergilius Ferm]]&lt;/ref&gt; and forms a [[binary opposition|binary pair]] with [[theism]], which is the belief that at least one deity exists.&lt;ref name=OED-theism&gt;{{cite book |title=Oxford English Dictionary |edition=2nd |year=1989 |quote=Belief in a deity, or deities, as opposed to atheism}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/theism |title=Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary |quote=belief in the existence of a god or gods | accessdate=2011-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Atheists have offered various rationales for not believing in any deity, but there is no one ideology or set of behaviors to which all atheists adhere.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Baggini|2003|pp=3-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Furthermore, atheism figures in to certain religious and spiritual belief systems, such as Jainism, Buddhism, Hinduism, and Neopagan movements&lt;ref name="Neopaganism"&gt;{{cite book|author=Carol S. Matthews|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=RfGhUW8RdUIC&amp;pg=PA194&amp;dq=neopaganism+atheism&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=8lvZTdHwIYfV0QHK3on8Aw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwADgU#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=A New Vision A New Heart A Renewed Call - Volume Two|publisher=William Carey Library|quote=Although Neo-Pagans share common commitments to nature and spirit there is a diversity of beliefs and practices. Some are atheists, others are polytheists (several gods exists), some are pantheists (all is God) and others are panentheists (all is in God).|date=19 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as Wicca.&lt;ref name="Wicca"&gt;{{cite book|author=Carol S. Matthews|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=stQQJlV9FT8C&amp;pg=PA115&amp;dq=neopaganism+atheism&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=8lvZTdHwIYfV0QHK3on8Aw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAjgU#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=New Religions|publisher=Chelsea House Publishers|quote=There is no universal worldview that all Neo-Pagans/Wiccans hold. One online information source indicates that depending on how the term ''God'' is defined, Neo-Pagans might be classified as monotheists, duotheists (two gods), polytheists, pantheists, or atheists.|date=19 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  State atheism is thus a [[misnomer]] referring to a government's [[anti-clericalism]], which opposes religious institutional power and influence, real or alleged, in all aspects of public and political life, including the involvement of religion in the everyday life of the citizen.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopædia Britannica, ''Anticlericalism'' (2007 Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.)&lt;/ref&gt;

State promotion of atheism as a public norm was first practised during a brief period in [[Revolutionary France]]. Since then, such a policy was repeated only in [[Mexican Revolution|Revolutionary Mexico]] and some [[communist states]].  The Soviet Union had a long history of state atheism,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Greeley2003|Greeley (2003)]].&lt;/ref&gt; in which social success largely required individuals to profess atheism, stay away from churches and even vandalize them; this attitude was especially militant during the middle Stalinist era from 1929-1939.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Pospielovsky1998|Pospielovsky (1998)]]:257.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Miner2003|Miner (2003)]]:70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Davies1996|Davies (1996)]]:962.&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union attempted to suppress religion over wide areas of its influence, including places like central Asia.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Pipes1989|Pipes (1989)]]:55.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Socialist People's Republic of Albania]] under [[Enver Hoxha]] went so far as to officially ban the practice of every religion.&lt;ref name="Elsie 2000:18"&gt;[[#Elsie2000|Elsie (2000)]]:18.&lt;/ref&gt;

==French Revolution==
During the [[French Revolution]], for the first time in history, a society delved into the prospect of an atheist state.&lt;ref name=McGrath2006p46&gt;[[#McGrath2006|McGrath (2006)]]:46.&lt;/ref&gt; After the Revolution, [[Jacques Hébert]], a radical revolutionary journalist, and [[Anacharsis Cloots]], a politician, both [[anticlerical]] and atheist, had successfully campaigned for the proclamation of the atheistic &lt;ref name=Freemont-Barnes2007p329&gt;[[#Freemont-Barnes2007|Freemont-Barnes (2007)]]:[http://books.google.com/books?id=6_2wkP4j-EsC&amp;pg=PA376&lt;!--this navigates to page 329 (not 376) in the text--&gt; 329].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cult of Reason]], which was adopted by the French Republic on November 10, 1793, though abandoned May 7, 1794 in favor of its [[deism|deistic]] replacement as the state religion, the [[Cult of the Supreme Being]].&lt;ref name=McGrath2006&gt;[[#McGrath2006|McGrath (2006)]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Cloots maintained that "Reason" and "Truth" were "supremely intolerant" and that the daylight of atheism would make the lesser lights of religious night disappear.&lt;ref name=McGrath2006 /&gt;  The state then further pushed its [[Dechristianisation of France during the French Revolution|campaign of dechristianization]],&lt;ref name=McGrath2006p45&gt;[[#McGrath2006|McGrath (2006)]]:45.&lt;/ref&gt; which included removal and destruction of religious objects from places of worship and the transformation of churches into "Temples of the Goddess of Reason",  culminating in a celebration of Reason in [[Notre Dame de Paris|Notre Dame]] Cathedral.&lt;ref&gt;Latreille, A. FRENCH REVOLUTION, New Catholic Encyclopedia v. 5, pp. 972–973 (Second Ed. 2002 Thompson/Gale) ISBN 0-7876-4004-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Spielvogel2005|Spielvogel (2005)]]:549.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tallet1991|Tallet (1991)]]:1&lt;/ref&gt;

Counterrevolution against the [[Persecution of Christians|persecution]] rooted in the anticlerical aspects of the Revolution led to a [[War in the Vendée|war in the Vendée region]] where republicans suppressed the  Catholic and royalist uprising in what some call the first modern [[genocide]].&lt;ref name=McGrath2006p46 /&gt;&lt;ref name=JonassohnBjeornson1998&gt;[[#JonassohnBjeornson1998|Jonassohn, Bjeornson]]:208.&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike later establishments of anti-theism by "communist" regimes, the French Revolutionary experiment was short (7 months), incomplete and inconsistent.&lt;ref name="McGrath2006p45"/&gt; Although brief, the French experiment was particularly notable for the influence upon atheists [[Ludwig Feuerbach]] (who called religion an opiate before Marx&lt;ref&gt;Luo, Zhufeng  [http://books.google.com/books?id=cEfiZlUpI5oC&amp;dq Religion under socialism in China], p. 151, M.E. Sharpe 1991&lt;/ref&gt;), [[Sigmund Freud]] and [[Karl Marx]].&lt;ref name=McGrath2006p46 /&gt;  Using the ideas of Feuerbach, Marx and Freud, "communist" regimes later treated religious believers as subversives or abnormal, sometimes relegated to psychiatric hospitals and reeducation.&lt;ref name=McGrath2006p46 /&gt;

==Mexico under Plutarco Elías Calles==
{{See also|Plutarco Elías Calles|Calles Law|Cristero War}}
The [[Mexican Constitution of 1917]]'s Articles 3, 5, 24, 27, and 130 as originally enacted were anticlerical and "enormously" restricted religious freedoms.&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu"&gt;Soberanes Fernandez, Jose Luis, [http://lawreview.byu.edu/archives/2002/2/Sob12.pdf Mexico and the 1981 United Nations Declaration on the Elimination of All Forms of Intolerance and of Discrimination Based on Religion or Belief], pp. 437-438 nn. 7-8, BYU Law Review, June 2002&lt;/ref&gt; At first the anticlerical provisions were only sporadically enforced, but when President [[Plutarco Calles]] took office, he enforced the provisions strictly.&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu"/&gt; Calles’ Mexico has been characterized as an atheist state&lt;ref&gt;Haas, Ernst B., [http://books.google.com/books?id=ldKJ_Re6p8AC&amp;pg Nationalism, Liberalism, and Progress: The dismal fate of new nations], Cornell Univ. Press 2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chadwick, Owen, [http://books.google.com/books?id=qugouOh3KjMC&amp;pg A History of Christianity], p. 265, Macmillan, 1998&lt;/ref&gt; and his program as being one to eradicate religion in Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;Cronon,  E. David "American Catholics and Mexican Anticlericalism, 1933-1936," ,pp. 205-208, Mississippi Valley Historical Review, XLV, Sept. 1948&lt;/ref&gt;

All religions had their properties appropriated, and these became part of government wealth. There was a forced expulsion of foreign clergy and the seizure of Church properties.&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu"&gt;http://www.ilstu.edu/class/hist263/docs/1917const.html&lt;/ref&gt; Article 27 prohibited any future acquisition of such property by the churches, and ordered the closing of all church-run primary schools (article 4). This second prohibition was sometimes interpreted to mean that the Church could not even give religious instruction to children within the churches on Sundays, effectively destroying the ability of Catholics to be educated in their own religion.&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu" /&gt;

The Constitution of 1917 also closed and forbade the existence of monastic orders (article 5), forbade any religious activity outside of church buildings (now owned by the government), and mandated that such religious activity would be overseen by the government (article 24).&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu"/&gt;
[[File:Cristeroscolgados.jpg|thumb|250px|Cristeros hanged in [[Jalisco]].]]

On June 14, 1926, President Calles enacted an [[anticlerical]] legislation known formally as The Law Reforming the Penal Code and unofficially as the [[Calles Law]].&lt;ref name="Joes, Anthony James p. 70"&gt;Joes, Anthony James [http://books.google.com/books?id=buHXFDFdeoQC&amp;pg=PA70&amp;dq=plutarco+calles+anticatholic&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=fnPEry3_KKxtgC6IdVhGGh8lMG8#PPA70,M1 Resisting Rebellion: The History And Politics of Counterinsurgency] p. 70, (2006 University Press of Kentucky) ISBN 0-8131-9170-X&lt;/ref&gt;   His [[anti-Catholic]] actions included outlawing religious orders, depriving the Church of property rights and depriving the clergy of civil liberties, including their right to trial  by jury (in cases involving anti-clerical laws) and the right to vote.&lt;ref name="Joes, Anthony James p. 70"/&gt;&lt;ref name="THE CRISTERO REBELLION - PART 1"&gt;Tuck, Jim [http://www.mexconnect.com/mex_/history/jtuck/jtcristero1.html THE CRISTERO REBELLION – PART 1] Mexico Connect 1996&lt;/ref&gt;  Catholic antipathy towards Calles was enhanced because of his vocal atheism.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"&gt;{{cite book
|title=Mexico's New Politics
|author=David A. Shirk
|year=2005
|publisher=[[Lynne Rienner Publishers]]
|isbn=1588262707
|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=WOBRb0wKpocC&amp;pg=PA58&amp;lpg=PA58&amp;dq
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He was also a [[Catholicism and Freemasonry|Freemason]].&lt;ref&gt;Denslow, William R. [http://books.google.com/books?id=dmPato81X9sC&amp;pg=PA171&amp;dq=plutarco+calles+freemason&amp;sig=NsSB9-6KQUn50HmpBT8eh9nx3No 10,000 Famous Freemasons] p. 171 (2004
Kessinger Publishing)ISBN 1-4179-7578-4&lt;/ref&gt;  Regarding this period, recent President [[Vicente Fox]] stated, "After 1917, Mexico was led by anti-Catholic Freemasons who tried to evoke the anticlerical spirit of popular indigenous President [[Benito Juárez]] of the 1880s. But the military dictators of the 1920s were a more savage lot than Juarez." &lt;ref&gt;Fox, Vicente and Rob Allyn [http://books.google.com/books?id=bLDDf9vi-esC&amp;dq Revolution of Hope] p. 17, Viking, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to the strict enforcement of anti-clerical laws, people in strongly [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] areas, especially the states of [[Jalisco]], [[Zacatecas]], [[Guanajuato]], [[Colima]] and [[Michoacán]], began to oppose him, and this opposition led to the [[Cristero War]] from 1926 to 1929, which was characterized by brutal atrocities by both sides. Some Cristeros applied terrorist tactics, while the Mexican government persecuted the clergy, killing suspected Cristeros and supporters and often retaliating against innocent individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/Plutarco_Elias_Calles.aspx Calles, Plutarco Elías] The Columbia Encyclopedia, Sixth Edition. 2001–05 Columbia University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;  On May 28, 1926, Calles was awarded a medal of merit from the head of Mexico's Scottish rite of Freemasonry for his actions against the Catholics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.storialibera.it/epoca_contemporanea/messico_1926-1929/articolo.php?id=508 The Cristeros: 20th century Mexico's Catholic uprising, from The Angelus, January 2002 , Volume XXV, Number 1] by Olivier LELIBRE, [[The Angelus]]&lt;/ref&gt;

A truce was negotiated with the assistance of U.S. Ambassador [[Dwight Whitney Morrow]].&lt;ref name="Blood Drenched Altars"&gt;Van Hove, Brian [http://www.ewtn.com/library/HOMELIBR/FR94204.TXT Blood Drenched Altars] 1996 EWTN&lt;/ref&gt;  Calles, however, did not abide by the terms of the truce – in violation of its terms, he had approximately 500 Cristero leaders and 5,000 other Cristeros shot, frequently in their homes in front of their spouses and children.&lt;ref name="Blood Drenched Altars"/&gt;  Particularly offensive to Catholics after the supposed truce was Calles' insistence on a complete state monopoly on education, suppressing all Catholic education and introducing "socialist" education in its place: "We must enter and take possession of the mind of childhood, the mind of youth.".&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"&gt;Van Hove, Brian [http://www.ewtn.com/library/HOMELIBR/FR94204.TXT Blood-Drenched Altars] Faith &amp; Reason 1994&lt;/ref&gt;  The persecution continued as Calles maintained control under his [[Maximato]] and did not relent until 1940, when President [[Manuel Ávila Camacho]], a believing Catholic, took office.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"/&gt; This attempt to indoctrinate the youth in atheism was begun in 1934 by amending Article 3 to the [[Mexican Constitution]] to eradicate religion by mandating "socialist education", which "in addition to removing all religious doctrine" would "combat fanaticism and prejudices", "build[ing] in the youth a rational and exact concept of the universe and of social life".&lt;ref&gt;Soberanes Fernandez, Jose Luis, [http://lawreview.byu.edu/archives/2002/2/Sob12.pdf Mexico and the 1981 United Nations Declaration on the Elimination of All Forms of Intolerance and of Discrimination Based on Religion or Belief], pp. 437-438 nn. 7-8, BYU Law Review, June 2002&lt;/ref&gt; In 1946 this "socialist education" was removed from the constitution and the document returned to the less egregious generalized secular education.
The effects of the war on the Church were profound.  Between 1926 and 1934 at least 40 priests were killed.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"/&gt; Where there were 4,500 priests serving the people before the rebellion, in 1934 there were only 334 priests licensed by the government to serve fifteen million people, the rest having been eliminated by emigration, expulsion, and assassination.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, Robert L. [http://books.google.com/books?id=8aWQ_7oKJfkC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;lpg=PA33&amp;dq=cristero+war+priests+killed&amp;source=web&amp;ots=YNDpLM2ukb&amp;sig=YWccvtnJKnSpaI15bTHCOX3zoyc#PPA33,M1 Latin America's Wars: The Age of the Caudillo, 1791–1899] p. 33 (2003
Brassey's) ISBN 1-57488-452-2&lt;/ref&gt;  By 1935, 17 states had no priest at all.&lt;ref&gt;Ruiz, Ramón Eduardo [http://books.google.com/books?id=AfdjWl1xKpwC&amp;pg=PA392&amp;dq=Tom%C3%A1s+Garrido+Canabal&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=HkfPtdqMt3qrdcMuprgfjnfnq60 Triumphs and Tragedy: A History of the Mexican People] p.393 (1993 W. W. Norton &amp; Company) ISBN 0-393-31066-3&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religion in communist states==
{{Main|Marxism and religion}}
The founder and primary theorist of [[Marxism]], the nineteenth century German sociologist [[Karl Marx]], had an ambivalent attitude to religion, viewing it primarily as "the [[opiate of the masses]]" that had been used by the ruling classes to give the [[working classes]] false hope for millennia, whilst at the same time recognizing it as a form of protest by the working classes against their poor economic conditions.&lt;ref&gt;Raines, John. 2002. "Introduction". ''Marx on Religion'' (Marx, Karl). Philadelphia: Temple University Press. Page 05-06.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the [[Marxist-Leninist]] interpretation of Marxist theory, developed primarily by Russian revolutionary [[Vladimir Lenin]], religion is seen as negative to human development, and [[socialism|socialist]] states that follow a Marxist-Leninist variant are [[Atheism|atheistic]] and explicitly [[Antireligion|antireligious]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 | url=http://www.psylib.ukrweb.net/books/maenl01/txt17
 | last = Lenin
 | first = V. I.
 | title = About the attitude of the working party toward the religion.
 | accessdate=2006-09-09
 | work = Collected works, v. 17, p.41
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; However, several [[Religious communism|religious communist]] groups exist, and [[Christian communism]] was important in the early development of communism.

===Socialist People's Republic of Albania===
{{Further|[[Religion in Albania#Totalitarian regime|Religion in Albania]]}}

State atheism in [[Socialist People's Republic of Albania|Albania]] was taken to an extreme during the totalitarian regime installed after World War II, when religions, identified as imports foreign to Albanian culture, were banned altogether.&lt;ref name="Hall1999"&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/stable/3060414 Representations of Place: Albania], Derek R. Hall, ''The Geographical Journal'', Vol. 165, No. 2, The Changing Meaning of Place in Post-Socialist Eastern Europe: Commodification, Perception and Environment (Jul., 1999), pp. 161–172, Blackwell Publishing on behalf of The Royal Geographical Society (with the Institute of British Geographers)&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Agrarian Reform Law (Albania)|Agrarian Reform Law]] of August 1945 nationalized most property of religious institutions, including the estates of monasteries, orders, and dioceses. Many clergy and believers were tried, tortured, and executed. All foreign Roman Catholic priests, monks, and nuns were expelled in 1946.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"&gt;[http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-186.html Albania - Hoxha's Antireligious Campaign&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Religious communities or branches that had their headquarters outside the country, such as the [[Jesuit]] and [[Franciscan]] orders, were henceforth ordered to terminate their activities in Albania. Religious institutions were forbidden to have anything to do with the education of the young, because that had been made the exclusive province of the state. All religious communities were prohibited from owning real estate and from operating philanthropic and welfare institutions and hospitals.
Although there were tactical variations in Hoxha's approach to each of the major denominations, his overarching objective was the eventual destruction of all organized religion in Albania. Between 1945 and 1953, the number of priests was reduced drastically and the number of Roman Catholic churches was decreased from 253 to 100, and all Catholics were stigmatized as fascists.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt;

The campaign against religion peaked in the 1960s. Beginning in 1967 the Albanian authorities began a violent campaign to try to eliminate religious life in Albania. Despite complaints, even by [[Party of Labour of Albania|APL]] members, all churches, mosques, monasteries, and other religious institutions were either closed down or converted into warehouses, gymnasiums, or workshops by the end of 1967.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-170.html Albania - The Cultural and Ideological Revolution]&lt;/ref&gt; By May 1967, religious institutions had been forced to relinquish all 2,169 churches, mosques, cloisters, and shrines in Albania, many of which were converted into cultural centers for young people. As the literary monthly Nendori reported the event, the youth had thus "created the first atheist nation in the world."&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt;

The clergy were publicly vilified and humiliated, their vestments taken and desecrated. More than 200 clerics of various faiths were imprisoned, others were forced to seek work in either industry or agriculture, and some were executed or starved to death. The cloister of the Franciscan order in Shkodër was set on fire, which resulted in the death of four elderly monks.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt;

Article 37 of the Albanian Constitution of 1976 stipulated, "The State recognizes no religion, and supports atheistic propaganda in order to implant a scientific materialistic world outlook in people.",&lt;ref&gt;[http://bjoerna.dk/dokumentation/Albanian-Constitution-1976.htm#C.%20Education,%20Science,%20Culture C. Education, Science, Culture], The Albanian Constitution of 1976.&lt;/ref&gt; and the penal code of 1977 imposed prison sentences of three to ten years for "religious propaganda and the production, distribution, or storage of religious literature." A new decree that in effect targeted Albanians with Muslim and Christian names stipulated that citizens whose names did not conform to "the political, ideological, or moral standards of the state" were to change them. It was also decreed that towns and villages with religious names must be renamed. Hoxha's brutal antireligious campaign succeeded in eradicating formal worship, but some Albanians continued to practice their faith clandestinely, risking severe punishment. Individuals caught with Bibles, icons, or other religious objects faced long prison sentences. Religious weddings were prohibited.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-184.html Albania - Social Structure under Communist Rule&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Parents were afraid to pass on their faith, for fear that their children would tell others. Officials tried to entrap practicing Christians and Muslims during religious fasts, such as Lent and Ramadan, by distributing dairy products and other forbidden foods in school and at work, and then publicly denouncing those who refused the food, and clergy who conducted secret services were incarcerated.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt; Catholic priest [[Kurti, Shtjefen|Shtjefen Kurti]], had been executed for secretly baptizing a child in [[Shkodër]] in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;Sinishta, G., 1976. The Fulfilled Promise: A Documentary Account of Religious Persecution in Albania. Albanian Catholic Information Center, Santa Clara.&lt;/ref&gt;

The article was interpreted by Danes as violating The [[United Nations Charter]] (chapter 9, article 55) which declares that [[religious freedom]] is an inalienable human right. The first time that the question came before the United Nations' [[Commission on Human Rights]] at Geneva was as late as 7 March 1983. A delegation from Denmark got its protest over Albania's violation of religious liberty placed on the agenda of the thirty-ninth meeting of the commission, item 25, reading, "Implementation of the Declaration on the Elimination of all Forms of Intolerance and of Discrimination based on Religion or Belief.", and on 20 July 1984 a member of the [[Danish Parliament]] inserted an article in one of Denmark's major newspapers protesting the violation of religious freedom in Albania.

===Czechoslovakia===
{{See also|Religion in Czechoslovakia|Religion in Slovakia}}
When [[communists]] seized power in former [[Czechoslovakia]] in February 1948, part of their agenda was also a fight against “dangerous ideological enemy that holds enormous influence on the masses” what was a reference made to [[Christianity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=NMI|url= http://www.upn.gov.sk/obdobie-1945-1989/likvidacia-klastorov-v-komunistickom-ceskoslovensku-barbarska-noc|title= Likvidácia kláštorov v komunistickom Československu – Barbarská noc  (“Eradication of monasteries in communist Czechoslovakia – Barbaric night”)|publisher=[http://www.upn.gov.sk/v2/index.php?page=about-nations-memory-institute Nation's Memory Institute]|date=2011}}&lt;!--Destruction of monasteries in communist Czechoslovakia - barbaric night 
Already before 1948 the Czechoslovak Communists regarded religious Orders as an important entity that holds an inconvenient influence over population and that is capable of forming its further opinion. After seizing the power in February 1948 by the Communist Party their plans, aimed against religious Orders, gained the important room for being brought into real life. First actions against monasteries took place already in the summer of 1948 when they were closed under the pretext that they are centres of anti-state activities. Although they were not many closed at that time, these events indicated the direction the further development will take. The implementation of already worked-out plans against religious Orders was postponed by state power due to other actions of the regime (such as Schismatic Catholic Action in June 1949, the preparation of so-called Ecclesiastical laws in the autumn of 1949), thus it could take place only in the first half of 1950.
Immediate preparation for action "K" (Monasteries) was the trial of ten representatives of the Orders who were accused of treason and espionage. The role of the process was to prepare justification of the whole action against the religious Orders and manipulate the public opinion in favour of these plans. After a thorough "processing" of the State Security investigators the members of religious Orders were “admitting” their "anti-state activities", hatred for "the establishment of people’s democracy", having sympathy for the "imperialism", the illegal manufacturing of various leaflets, the concealment of "enemy agents", weapons and valuables. The final verdict sentenced one of the accused (coincidentally the only one from Slovakia – Redemptorist Ján Mastiliak) to life imprisonment whereas all other sentences were totalling 132 years.
The very implementation of the action was handed over to State security service [[StB]]. There was conducted reconnaissance of monasteries to find out the number of their inhabitants. The police corps, military and communist militias was supposed to join too. They should be armed with rifles, sub-machine guns, light machine guns, batons and gas candles. The action day was determined to take place on Thursday, 13 April 1950 at 24.00hrs.

At the appointed time, members of the armed forces began to conquer the monasteries. Where their summons was met with ignorance, violent methods of penetration into objects were applied. After entering into the monasteries members of Orders has been gathered together to be informed about the reason for intervention, which was alleged sedition and anti-state activities of the Orders. Afterwards, they were forced to get into the prepared buses and trucks and transported into so called concentrating monasteries all over the Slovakia. There were 881 monks from 11 religious orders displaced during single night.

After the action "K", the second action took place during the night from 3rd to 4thof May 1950, designated as "K2". This one targeted the remaining male monasteries that become subject of another occupation. The two interventions affected in total 1180 people from 15 Orders living in 76 monasteries. After these two events the relocated monks in Slovakia were concentrated in following monasteries: Monastery of the martyrs (now Močenok) Hronský Beňadik, Podolinec-Kostolná and Báč.
The strict regime in concentrating monasteries was governed virtually by prison rules. In addition to forced-labor (sticking bags, picking rose-hips, carpentry and tailoring, work in agriculture) there was reserved dedicated time for political re-education. Communication with the outside world was completely eliminated or limited to a very minimum. The most stringent regime was in the monastery in Podolínec where there was the greatest number of men put together. The building was guarded by armed guards with dogs, and guard duty members were narrowly selected from the Leopoldov (famous state prison) and other prisons. At the monastery building the barbed wires were gradually installed and windows got equipped with lattice bars. The watch tower was built in the courtyard and surrounding area of monastery was illuminated by night lights. Monks who violated the prescribed codes of behaviour got punished by being put to solitary confinement localized in the basement.
After the completion of actions 'K' the attention turned onto the women's religious orders. The action targeting the destruction of monasteries of nuns was given the name "R" (Rehoľníčky, nuns in Slovak). In their case, the procedure was supposed to be applied in more moderate way, with assuming their "voluntary" removal from monasteries and only if they would resist, the help of security services would be called to take action. The action "R" itself was initiated on the 29th of August in 1950 at 8.00 a.m. in the morning.  In the course of this action however there were about 15 locations in Slovakia where citizens who disagreed with the destruction of religious communities gathered together. In several places people occupied the monasteries and did not allow for displacement of nuns to take place, while there were also sharp confrontations and attacks on present governmental officials. In these monasteries the action had to be repeated at night with the assistance of the Police Corps, communist militias and state security service. In total, there was 1962 people displaced and 137 women religious objects occupied and acquired during the action "R" on 28–31 August in 1950. Nuns were brought together in 16 concentrating monasteries. Another more than 1,600 nuns, however, had to remain working in hospitals because the state system could not find an adequate substitute for them.
After the occupation of the monasteries there were many libraries destroyed due to rough treatment by state authorities; valuable manuscripts, prints, paintings and furniture was stolen as well. The buildings acquired were handed over to various regional and local state administrative offices, sport clubs, orphanages etc. Communist state power perceived the Orders as the dangerous ideological enemy, who has considerable influence over the masses. But the action was also about the properties, real estates and other assets managed by religious orders. The report addressed to the political secretariat of the Central Communist Committee, that evaluated obtained material assets, described the result of action as the largest property transfer from the time of confiscation of the properties of displaced Germans, seizure of private enterprises by state and land reform. In other words, it was the third largest extent of “legalized” theft since 1945. However, the most painful result of the intervention was the sorrowful fate of thousands of religious men and women, who became for decades the citizen group subject of persecution by state.
According to the study: Letz, Robert: Persecution of Christians in Slovakia in 1948–1989. In: Miklosko, F. – Smolíková, G. – Smolik, P.: Crimes of Communism in Slovakia 1948–1989 (1). Presov: Publishing Michael Vasek, 2001, p. 128–142
Further reading:

Dubovská, Milan J.: Action monasteries. Martin: Matica Slovak, 1998.
Dubovská, Milan J.: Action religious. Martin: Matica Slovak, 2001.
Grandson, Francis: and R K Shares: the response to the Order of the communist regime in 1950 – the 1956th Bratislava, 1995.
JUDÁK, William – DAŇKOVÁ, S.: Exodus. Celebrating Thee God. Nitra: St. seminary. Gorazd, 1997
Memorial literature:
Korec, John Chrysostom: The barbaric night. Bratislava: Luc, 1990.
Macák, Ernest: Notes from behind bars. Bratislava: Publishing Don Bosco, 1996.
Petrik, Vincent: Last villa. Cambridge, Canada: Good book, 1990.--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, the [[monasteries]] had been seized by state security service ([[StB]]) during three so called “barbaric nights” in 1950. In total, 3142 people were displaced by force into concentrating monasteries. These were in case of male members of [[religious order|orders]] virtually turned into [[Internment|prison camps]] or [[Labor camp#Labor camps in various countries#Czechoslovakia|labor camps]] secured with guards and strict regime aiming the “political re-education” of [[monk]]s. The 213 [[monastery]] buildings and facilities were [[Confiscation|confiscated]] by state and content of many ancient precious libraries that survived even Turko-Tatar attacks in the [[middle ages]] was scrapped and used for cardboard production.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=NMI|url=http://www.upn.gov.sk/obdobie-1945-1989/vypovede-pamatnikov-o-barbarskej-noci|title= Likvidácia kláštorov v komunistickom Československu – Barbarská noc, výpovede svedkov (“Eradication of monasteries in communist Czechoslovakia – Barbaric night, reports of witnesses”)|publisher=[http://www.upn.gov.sk/v2/index.php?page=about-nations-memory-institute Nation's Memory Institute]|date=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1957 [[ŠtB]] arrested university students in eastern Slovakia town [[Košice]] who held [[Bible study (Christian)|Bible study]] meetings. The consequent investigations lead to further arrests of [[Christians]] and [[lawsuit]] in 1959 with non-public hearing and coverage by state-controlled media. Newspapers brought up the case under titles ''„Poison in gold-foil“'', ''„Sects are eradicating the thinking of youth“''  and ''„Report on trial with blue [[crusaders]]“'' ([[Modrý kríž|Blue Cross]] was Christian [[abstinent]] association fighting [[alcoholism]]). The arrested members of the Blue Cross were found „guilty“ of „spreading hostile [[Christianity|Christian ideology]]“ that is „contradicting scientific [[Marxist ideology]]“. They were sentenced pursuant to paragraph on [[Inciting subversion of state power|subversion of republic]]. At the same time their personal correspondence, typing machines and Christian literature was [[Confiscation|confiscated]], mainly the one written by national author [[Kristína Royová]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= Naše korene|last=Slavka, M. et al.|publisher = Nádej| location=Bratislava|year=1994|pages=187|ISBN=80-7120-029-8|quote= In 1957 [[StB]] arrested Miloš Rataj, undergraduate student in Košice. He was a son of teacher and poet Ján Rataj. Miloš Rataj together with his fellow students held private Bible Study and prayer meetings at the hostel belonging to university campus. Somebody reported their activities to authorities what triggered investigations and later leaded to a lawsuit. In the newspaper „Východoslovenské Noviny“ there were consequently published articles „Poison in gold-foil“ (No.41 in 1959), „Sects are eradicating the thinking of youth“  and „Report on trial with blue crusaders“. It was just a preparation for more thorough trial at court in Bratislava, where prior to that trial further church members had been arrested, namely Ing. O. Lupták, Ing. Vl. Matej, J. Rosa and J. Hollý from Stará Turá. The hearings during the trial were behind the closed doors excluding the public (sep 1959). The main guilt of accused was that they as members of blue cross „spread hostile Christian ideology“ that is „contradicting scientific Marxist ideology“. They were sentenced pursuant to paragraph on subversion of republic. At the same time their personal correspondence, typing machines and Christian literature was confiscated, mainly the one written by national author Kristína Royová.}}&lt;/ref&gt;, regarded by some authors for "Slovak [[Kierkegaard]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last= Trúsik|first=Pavol |year=2/2011|title= Kristína Royová – slovenský Kierkegaard? (Kristína Royová – Slovak Kierkegaard?) |publisher=Ostium, Internet journal for humanitarian science|quote= We can conclude that (Kristína) Royová was sort of Slovak version of Kierkegaard.|accessdate=2011-08-19|url=http://www.ostium.sk/index.php?mod=magazine&amp;act=show&amp;aid=75}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Soviet Union===
{{See also|Religion in the Soviet Union|Soviet anti-religious legislation|Persecution of Christians in the Soviet Union|Persecution of Christians in Warsaw Pact countries|Persecution of Muslims#Persecution of Muslims in the former USSR|l5=Persecution of Muslims in the former USSR}}

A.L. Eliseev writes that a meeting of the antireligious commission of the Central Committee of the All-Union Communist Party (Bolsheviks) took place on 23 May, 1929 under the Chairmanship of E. Laroslavskii.  The commission estimated the portion of believers in the country at 80 percent, though it cannot be ruled out that this percentage was somewhat understated to prove the successfulness of the struggle with religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Marjorie Mandelstam Balzer|title=Religion and Politics in Russia: A Reader|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=DEufvUyRcygC|year=2009|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|isbn=978-0-7656-2415-4|pages=[http://books.google.com/books?id=DEufvUyRcygC&amp;pg=PA6 6–7]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:1922 Bezbozhnik magazine cover.jpg|thumb|USSR. 1922 issue of the ''[[Bezbozhnik]]'' (The Godless) magazine. By 1934, 28% of Christian Orthodox churches, 42% of Muslim mosques and 52% of Jewish synagogues were shut down in the USSR.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071023063308/http://www.friends-partners.org/partners/beyond-the-pale/english/43.html Religions attacked in the USSR] (Beyond the Pale)&lt;/ref&gt;]]
State atheism in the Soviet Union was known as "''gosateizm''",&lt;ref name="jstor.org"&gt;''[http://www.jstor.org/pss/128810 Protest for Religious Rights in the USSR: Characteristics and Consequences]', JSTOR.&lt;/ref&gt; and was based on the ideology of [[Marxism-Leninism]]. As the founder of the Soviet state V. I. [[Lenin]]  put it: &lt;blockquote&gt;Religion is the [[opium of the people]]: this saying of [[Marx]] is the cornerstone of the entire ideology of Marxism about religion. All modern religions and churches, all and of every kind of religious organizations are always considered by Marxism as the organs of bourgeois reaction, used for the protection of the exploitation and the stupefaction of the working class.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.psylib.ukrweb.net/books/maenl01/txt17
 | last = Lenin
 | first = V. I.
 | title = About the attitude of the working party toward the religion.
 | accessdate=2006-09-09
 | work = Collected works, v. 17, p.41
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Marxism-Leninism has consistently advocated the control, suppression,and, ultimately, the elimination of religion.  Within about a year of the revolution the state [[expropriated]] all church property, including the churches themselves, and in the period from 1922 to 1926, 28 Russian Orthodox bishops and more than 1,200 priests were killed (a much greater number was subjected to persecution).&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://countrystudies.us/russia/38.htm Country Studies: Russia-The Russian Orthodox Church] U.S. Library of Congress, Accessed Apr. 3, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

From the late 1920s to the late 1930s, such organizations as the [[League of the Militant Godless]] ridiculed all religions and harassed believers. Anti-religious and atheistic propaganda was implemented into every portion of soviet life, in schools, communist organizations (such as the [[Young Pioneer organization of the Soviet Union|Young Pioneer Organization]]), and the media. Though Lenin originally introduced the [[Gregorian calendar]] to the Soviets subsequent efforts to re-organise the week for the purposes of improving worker productivity with the introduction of the [[Soviet revolutionary calendar]] had a side-effect that a "holiday will seldom fall on Sunday" &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,930406,00.html
|title=Staggerers Unstaggered
|date=December 7, 1931
|publisher=Time magazine
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although all religions were persecuted,&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; the regime's efforts to eradicate religion, however, varied over the years with respect to particular religions, and were affected by higher state interests. Official policies and practices not only varied with time but also in their application from one nationality and one religion to another. Although all Soviet leaders had the same long-range goal of developing a cohesive Soviet people, they pursued different policies to achieve it. For the Soviet regime, the questions of nationality and religion were always closely linked. Not surprisingly, therefore, the attitude toward religion also varied from a total ban on some religions to official support of others.

Most seminaries were closed, publication of religious writing was banned.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;  The Russian Orthodox Church, which had 54,000 parishes before World War I, was reduced to 500 by 1940.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;  Today, approximately 100 million citizens consider themselves Russian Orthodox Christians, amounting to 70% of population, although the Church claims a membership of 80 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article551693.ece | work=The Times | location=London | title=The rise of Russian Muslims worries Orthodox Church | first=Jeremy | last=Page | date=2005-08-05 | accessdate=2010-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90196.htm Russia&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; although according to the CIA Factbook, only 17% to 22% of the population is now Christian.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, Ethan [http://www.christianpost.com/article/20080324/31660_Gorbachev_Dispels_'Closet_Christian'_Rumors;_Says_He_is_Atheist.htm Gorbachev Dispels 'Closet Christian' Rumors; Says He is Atheist] Christian Post Reporter, Mar. 24, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===The People's Republic of China===
{{Further|[[Religion in China]]}}
&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[Image:Destroy old world.jpg|right|thumb|Chinese poster saying: "Smash the old world / Establish a new world." Classical example of the Red art from the early Cultural Revolution. A worker (or possibly Red Guard) crushes the crucifix, Buddha and classical Chinese texts with his hammer; 1967]] --&gt;

Between 1900-1950, 90 percent of the population occasionally resorted to Buddhist rites or temples and 99 percent were affected by Buddhist contributions to Chinese thought and behavior&lt;ref&gt;The Practice of Chinese Buddhism, 1900-1950 - Page 393&lt;/ref&gt; The [[People's Republic of China]] was established in 1949 and since then the government has been officially atheist.&lt;ref&gt;Xie, Zhibin, [http://books.google.com/books?id=peah4XTpqnkC&amp;dq Religious diversity and public religion in China], p.145, Ashgate Publishing 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tyler, Christian [http://books.google.com/books?id=bEzNwgtiVQ0C&amp;dq Wild West China], p. 259, Rutgers Univ. Press 2004&lt;/ref&gt; For much of its early history maintained a hostile attitude toward religion which was seen as emblematic of [[feudalism]] and foreign [[colonialism]]. Houses of worship, including temples, mosques, and churches, were converted into non-religious buildings for secular use.

In the early years of the People's Republic, religious belief or practice was often discouraged because it was regarded by the government as backward and superstitious and because some [[Communist]] leaders, ranging from [[Vladimir Lenin]] to [[Mao Zedong]], had been critical of religious institutions. During the [[Cultural Revolution]], religion was condemned as [[feudalistic]] and thousands of religious buildings were looted and destroyed.

This attitude, however, relaxed considerably in the late 1970s, with the end of the Cultural Revolution. The [[1978 Constitution of the People's Republic of China]] guaranteed "freedom of religion" with a number of restrictions.  Since the mid-1990s there has been a massive program to rebuild Buddhist and Taoist temples that were destroyed in the Cultural Revolution.

The Communist Party has said that religious belief and membership are incompatible. Party membership is a necessity for many high level careers and posts. That along with other official hostility makes statistical reporting on religious membership difficult.  There are five recognized religions by the state: Buddhism, Taoism, Islam, Catholic Christianity, and Protestant Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.china-embassy.org/eng/zt/zjxy/t36492.htm
|title= White Paper—Freedom of Religious Belief in China
|publisher=Embassy of the People's Republic of China in the United States of America
|month=October
|year=1997
|accessdate=2007-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most people report no organized religious affiliation; however, people with a belief in folk traditions and spiritual beliefs, such as [[ancestor veneration]] and [[feng shui]], along with informal ties to local temples and unofficial house churches number in the hundreds of millions. The [[United States Department of State]], in its annual report on International Religious Freedom,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/irf/rpt/
|title=Annual Report to Congress on International Religious Freedom
|publisher=U.S.Department of State
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; provides statistics about organized religions. In 2007 it reported the following (citing the  Government's 1997 report on Religious Freedom and 2005 White Paper on religion):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90133.htm
|title=International Religious Freedom Report 2007 — China (includes Tibet, Hong Kong, and Macau)
|year=2007
|publisher=U.S.Department of State
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:*Buddhists 8%.
:*Taoists, unknown as a percentage partly because it is fused along with Confucianism and Buddhism.
:*Muslims, 1.5%, with more than 45,000 [[Imams]]. Other estimates state at least 2%.
:*Christians, Protestants at least 2%. Catholics, about 1.5%. Total Christians according to 2008 different polls: 4%.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

Statistics relating to [[Buddhism]] and religious [[Taoism]] are to some degree incomparable with statistics for [[Islam]] and [[Christianity]]. This is due to the traditional [[China|Chinese]] belief system which blends [[Confucianism]], [[Buddhism]], and [[Taoism]], so that a person who follows a traditional belief system would not necessarily identify him- or herself as exclusively Buddhist or Taoist, despite attending Buddhist or Taoist places of worship. According to Peter Ng, Professor of the Department of Religion at the Chinese University of Hong Kong, as of 2002, 95% of Chinese were religious in some way if religion is considered to include traditional folk practices such as burning incense for gods or ancestors at life-cycle or seasonal festivals, fortune telling and related customary practices.&lt;ref name=madsen&gt;{{cite book|last=Madsen|first=Richard|title=Chinese society: change, conflict and resistance|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0415560733|editor=Elizabeth J. Perry, Mark Selden|page=239|chapter=Chapter 10. Chinese Christianity: Indigenization and conflict}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Tze Ming Ng, “Religious Situations in China Today: Secularization Theory Revisited” Paper presented at the Association for the Sociology of Religion Meetings, Chicago, August 14-16, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cambodia under the Khmer Rouge===
{{Further|[[Khmer Rouge rule of Cambodia]]}}
Though the constitution of [[Democratic Kampuchea]] guaranteed the right to worship according to any religion and the right not to worship according to any religion, it also provided that "Reactionary religions which are detrimental to Democratic Kampuchea and Kampuchean people are absolutely forbidden."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dccam.org/Archives/Documents/DK_Policy/DK_Policy_DK_Constitution.htm Constitution of Democratic Kampuchea (1975–1979)], [http://www.dccam.org/ dccam.org]&lt;/ref&gt; Religious people were killed in [[the killing fields]], as the leader of the [[Khmer Rouge]], [[Pol Pot]], suppressed [[Cambodia]]'s [[Buddhism|Buddhists]]: monks were defrocked; temples and artifacts, including statues of Buddha, were destroyed; and people praying or expressing other religious sentiments were often killed. The Christian and Muslim communities were among the most persecuted, as well. The Roman Catholic cathedral of Phnom Penh was completely razed. The Khmer Rouge forced Muslims to eat pork, which they regard as an abomination. Many of those who refused were killed. Christian clergy and Muslim imams were executed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://countrystudies.us/cambodia/29.htm Cambodia – Society under the Angkar&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mongolian People's Republic===
In 1936, and especially after Japanese encroachments had given the Soviets enough reason to deploy Soviet troops in [[Mongolia]] in 1937, a whole-scale attack on the [[Lamaism|Buddhist faith]] began. At the same time, [[Stalinist purges in Mongolia|Soviet-style purges]] took place in the Communist Party and in the Mongolian army. Mongolia's leader at that time was [[Khorloogiin Choibalsan]], a follower of [[Joseph Stalin]] who emulated many of the policies Stalin had implemented in the Soviet Union. The [[Stalinist purges in Mongolia|purges]] led to the almost complete eradiction of [[Lamaism]] in the country, and cost an estimated 30,000–35,000 lives.

===Cuba===
Originally more tolerant of religion, after the [[Bay of Pigs Invasion]], [[Cuba]] began arresting many believers and shutting down religious schools, its prisons since the 1960s being filled with clergy.&lt;ref name=Hertzke2006p43&gt;[[#Hertzke2006|Hertzke (2006)]]:[http://books.google.com/books?id=EkIvbxefBNsC&amp;pg=PA43 43]&lt;/ref&gt;  Since the fall of the Soviet Union, Cuba has amended its statutes to declare itself a "[[secular state]]" rather than atheistic.

In 1961 The Cuban government confiscated the Catholic schools, including the Jesuit school Fidel Castro had attended. In 1965 it exiled two hundred priests.&lt;ref name=buckley2005-11-21&gt;William F. Buckley Jr., [http://old.nationalreview.com/flashback/1998200511210830.asp Cuba libre?], November 21, 2005, National review.&lt;/ref&gt;

Pope [[John Paul II]] visited Cuba January 21–25, 1998, the first time a pope had visited Cuba and the first time since the Communist Revolution of 1959 that a papal visit was welcome.&lt;ref name=ac-cuba&gt;[http://www.americancatholic.org/features/cuba/ Pope John Paul II Visits Cuba], January 25, 1998, americancatholic.org&lt;/ref&gt; The main reason for the visit was not to call the Communist government to task, but to carry out a pastoral visit to the Catholic community and to deliver a message of evangelization.&lt;ref&gt;Jack Wintz, [http://www.americancatholic.org/Messenger/Apr1998 The Pope in Cuba: A Call for Freedom], americancatholic.org&lt;/ref&gt; In his farewell statement to the pope at the airport Fidel Castro thanked the pope for visiting the "last bastion of Communism."&lt;ref name=buckley2005-11-21 /&gt;

In 2009, when welcoming Cuba's new ambassador to the Vatican, Pope [[Benedict XVI]] said that the Catholic Church had been trying to help suffering Cubans and, thanks to a new government willingness to cooperate, it was able to take part in emergency relief and reconstruction efforts after hurricanes struck the island in 2008. The pope went on to say, "I hope concrete signs of openness to the exercise of religious freedom continue to multiply as they have in recent years,". In particular, he asked for "the opportunity to celebrate Holy Mass in some prisons, to conduct religious processions, for the repair and return of some churches and the construction of houses for religious, (and) the possibility that priests and religious could receive social security. In this way, the Catholic community could more freely exercise its specific pastoral task."&lt;ref&gt;Cindy Wooden, [http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/0905435.htm Pope urges greater religious freedom in Cuba, criticizes U.S. embargo], December 10, 2009, Catholic News Service.&lt;/ref&gt;

===North Korea===
[[North Korea]]'s government exercises virtual total control over society and imposes state sanctioned atheism, the [[cult of personality]] of [[Kim Jung Il]] and [[Kim Il Sung]], described as a [[political religion]].&lt;ref name=Hertzke2006p44&gt;[[#Hertzke2006|Hertzke (2006)]]:[http://books.google.com/books?id=EkIvbxefBNsC&amp;pg=PA44 44]&lt;/ref&gt; Although the North Korean constitution states that freedom of religion is permitted,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.korea-np.co.jp/pk/061st_issue/98091708.htm DPRK's Socialist Constitution (Full Text)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; free religious activities no longer exist in North Korea as the government sponsors religious groups only to create an illusion of religious freedom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/english/docs/2004/07/08/nkorea9040.htm Essential Background: Overview of human rights issues in Human Rights in North Korea (DPRK: The Democratic People's Republic of Korea) (Human Rights Watch, 8-7-2004)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/kn.html CIA - The World Factbook&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinal]] [[Nicolas Cheong Jin-suk]] has said that, "There's no knowledge of priests surviving persecution that came in the late forties, when 166 priests and religious were killed or kidnapped." which includes the Roman Catholic [[bishop of Pyongyang]], [[Francis Hong Yong-ho]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.30giorni.it/us/articolo.asp?id=10278 30Giorni | Korea, for a reconciliation between North and South (Interview with Cardinal Nicholas Cheong Jinsuk by Gianni Cardinale)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Continuing state atheism==
While many countries no longer follow state atheism, China, Vietnam, Laos, North Korea and Cuba, despite some economic liberalization, continued to persecute the religious.&lt;ref name=Hertzke2006p43/&gt; In addition to overt persecution, these states also sought to control religion by forcing upon the people state-sanctioned churches, essentially attempting to make the churches tools of the state.&lt;ref name=Hertzke2006p43 /&gt;

==Religious legacy of state atheism==

Author Niels Christian Nielsen has written that the post-Soviet population in areas which were formerly predominantly Orthodox are now "nearly illiterate regarding religion", almost completely lacking the intellectual or philosophical aspects of their faith and having almost no knowledge of other faiths.&lt;ref&gt;Nielsen, Niels Christian, Jr., [http://books.google.com/books?id=Ts6w8JumlQMC&amp;d Christianity After Communism], p. 77-78, Westview Press 1998&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, their knowledge of their faith and the faith of others notwithstanding, many post-Soviet populations have a large presence of religious followers. In Russia, the 2007 International Religious Freedom Report published by the US Department of State said that approximately 100 million citizens consider themselves Russian Orthodox Christians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90196.htm|accessdate=2008-04-08|title=Russia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a poll by the [[VCIOM|Russian Public Opinion Research Center]], 63% of respondents considered themselves Russian Orthodox, 6% of respondents considered themselves [[Muslim]] and less than 1% considered themselves either Buddhist, Catholic, Protestant or Jewish. Another 12% said they believe in God, but did not practice any religion, and 16% said they are non-believers.&lt;ref name=religionsurvey&gt;{{cite web|title={{ru icon}} Опубликована подробная сравнительная статистика религиозности в России и Польше|publisher=religare.ru|date=6 June 2007|url=http://www.religare.ru/article42432.htm|accessdate=2007-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Ukraine]], 96.1% of the [[Ukrainians|Ukrainian]] population is [[Christian]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmaster.com/country/up-ukraine/rel-religion NationMaster - Ukrainian Religion statistics&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Lithuania]], a 2005 report stated that 79% of [[Lithuanians]] belonged to the [[Roman Catholic Church]].&lt;ref&gt;Department of Statistics to the Government of the Republic of Lithuania. ''{{cite web |url=http://www.std.lt/en/pages/view/?id=1734 |title=Population by Religious Confession, census  |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20061001185140/http://www.std.lt/en/pages/view/?id=1734 |archivedate=2006-10-01}}''. Updated in 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most [[Poles]]—approximately 88.4% in 2007, are members of the Roman Catholic Church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stat.gov.pl/cps/rde/xbcr/gus/PUBL_oz_maly_rocznik_statystyczny_2009.pdf |title=Maly Rocznik Statystyczny Polski 2009 |format=PDF |language={{pl icon}} |date= |accessdate=2009-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the CIA World Factbook and the [[U.S. Department of State]], 60% of Mongolia's population are religious.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/mg.html CIA Factbook – Mongolia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2779.htm |title=Bureau of East Asian and Pacific Affairs – Mongolia |publisher=State.gov |date=2010-02-28 |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, despite the Soviet Union's attempts to eliminate religion,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jstor.org/pss/128810&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sabrina Petra Ramet, Ed., Religious Policy in the Soviet Union. Cambridge University Press (1993). P 4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Anderson, Religion, State and Politics in the Soviet Union and Successor States, Cambridge University Press, 1994, pp 3&lt;/ref&gt; other former USSR and anti-religious nations, such as [[Armenia]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/?id=5211|title=The Armenian Apostolic Church (World Council of Churches)}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kazakhstan]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2009/127366.htm International Religious Freedom Report 2009 – Kazakhstan] U.S. Department of State. 2009-10-26. Retrieved on 2009-11-05.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Uzbekistan]],&lt;ref name="state1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2924.htm |title=Uzbekistan |publisher=State.gov |date=2009-10-16 |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Turkmenistan]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/tx.html CIA - The World Factbook&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kyrgyzstan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2001/5598.htm |title=Kyrgyzstan |publisher=State.gov |date= |accessdate=2010-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tajikistan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5775.htm |title=Background Note: Tajikistan |publisher=State.gov |date= |accessdate=2009-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Belarus]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmaster.com/country/bo-belarus/rel-religion NationMaster - Belarusian Religion statistics&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/bo.html CIA - The World Factbook&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Moldova]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmaster.com/country/md-moldova/rel-religion NationMaster - Moldovan Religion statistics&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Mexico,&lt;ref name="tabulados"&gt;{{cite web|title=Religión|work=Censo Nacional de Población y Vivienda 2000|year=2000|publisher=[[INEGI]]|url=http://www.inegi.gob.mx/prod_serv/contenidos/espanol/bvinegi/productos/censos/poblacion/2000/definitivos/Nal/tabulados/00re01.pdf|format=PDF|accessdate=2 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Albania]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/al.html CIA World Factbvook : Albania], reporting Muslim 70%, Albanian Orthodox 20%, Roman Catholic 10%, but noting, "percentages are estimates; there are no available current statistics on religious affiliation; all mosques and churches were closed in 1967 and religious observances prohibited; in November 1990, Albania began allowing private religious practice"&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmaster.com/country/gg-georgia/rel-religion NationMaster - Georgian Religion statistics&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; have high religious populations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | editor-last = Miller | editor-first = Tracy | month = October | year = 2009 | publisher = [[Pew Research Center]] | title = Mapping the Global Muslim Population: A Report on the Size and Distribution of the World’s Muslim Population | format = [[Portable Document Format|PDF]] | url = http://pewforum.org/newassets/images/reports/Muslimpopulation/Muslimpopulation.pdf | accessdate = 8 October 2009}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-1-of-3}}
*[[Antireligion]]
*[[Civil religion]]
*[[Communism and religion]]
*[[Reign of Terror]]

{{Col-2-of-3}}
*[[Religion in China]]
*[[Religion in the Soviet Union]]
*[[Religious persecution]]
*[[Religion in Russia]]

{{Col-3-of-3}}
{{Portal|Atheism}}
*[[Society of the Godless]]
*[[Terrible Triangle]]
*[[War in the Vendée]]
{{Col-end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{wikicite |ref="Davies1996" |reference=Davies, Norman. 1996. ''Europe: a history.'' Oxford: Oxford University Press.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Dawkins2006" |reference=[[Richard Dawkins|Dawkins, Richard]]. 2006. ''[[The God Delusion]]''. Houghton Mifflin. ISBN 978-0-618-68000-9.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Elsie2000" |reference=Elsie, Robert. 2000. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=N_IXHrXIsYkC A Dictionary of Albanian Religion, Mythology, and Folk Culture]''. C. Hurst &amp; Co. ISBN 978-1-85065-570-1.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Elsie2001" |reference=Elsie, Robert. 2001. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=aAtQZ0vjf5gC A Dictionary of Albanian Religion, Mythology, and Folk Culture]''. New York: NYU Press. ISBN 0-8147-2214-8.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=Freemont-Barnes2007 |reference=Fremont-Barnes, Gregory. 2007. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=6_2wkP4j-EsC&amp;dq Encyclopedia of the Age of Political Revolutions and New Ideologies, 1760–1815]''. Greenwood Publishing Group. ISBN 978-0-313-33445-0.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=Gach2002 |reference=Gach, Gary. 2002. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=TvxsxV9oLqcChttp://books.google.com/books?id=arEFgUw-4b8C The complete idiot's guide to understanding Buddhism]. Alpha Books. ISBN 978-0-02-864170-6.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Greeley2003" |reference=Greeley, Andrew M. 2003. ''Religion in Europe at the end of the second millennium: a sociological profile''. New Brunswick, N.J.: Transaction Publishers.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=Hertzke2006 |reference=Hertzke, Allen. 2006. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=EkIvbxefBNsC&amp;dq Freeing God's Children]''. Rowman &amp; Littlefield}}
*{{wikicite |ref=Jacques1995 |reference=Jacques, Edwin E. 1995. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=IJ2s9sQ9bGkC The Albanians: an ethnic history from prehistoric times to the present]''. McFarland. ISBN 978-0-89950-932-7.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Marx1844" |reference=[[Karl Marx|Marx, Karl]]. February, 1844. ''[http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1843/critique-hpr/intro.htm A Contribution to the Critique of Hegel's Philosophy of Right]''. Deutsch-Französische Jahrbücher.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=JonassohnBjeornson1998 |reference=Jonassohn, Kurt and Karin Solveig Bjeornson. 1998. ''Genocide and Gross Human Rights Violations''. [[Transaction Publishers]]. ISBN 0-7658-0417-4.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=McCann1997 |reference=McCann, David R. 1997. ''Korea briefing: toward reunification'', Volume 4 of Korea briefing, Asia Society Briefings Series, Asia Society Country Briefing, Briefings of the Asia Society. M.E. Sharpe. ISBN 978-1-56324-885-6}}
*{{wikicite |ref=McGrath2006 |reference=McGrath, Alister E.  2006. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=24Xk90Bsp4gC&amp;dq The Twilight of Atheism]'', Random House.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Miner2003" |reference=Miner, Steven Merritt. 2003. ''Stalin's holy war religion, nationalism, and alliance politics, 1941–1945''. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Pipes1989" |reference=Pipes, Daniel. 1989. ''The long shadow: culture and politics in the Middle East''. New Brunswick, U.S.A.: Transaction Publishers.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Pospielovsky1998" |reference=Pospielovsky, Dimitry. 1935.  ''The Orthodox Church in the History of Russia'' Published 1998. St Vladimir's Seminary Press, 413 pages, ISBN 0-88141-179-5.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=Spielvogel2005 |reference=Spielvogel, Jackson. 2005. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=ni4PSpOxb6MC&amp;dq Western Civilization: Combined Volume]''. Thomson Wadsworth.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=Tallet1991 |reference=Tallet, Frank. 1991. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=aL4lsWdd-rAC&amp;dq Religion, Society and Politics in France Since 1789]''. Continuum International Publishing}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Wolak2004" |reference=Wolak, Arthur J. 2004. ''Forced out: the fate of Polish Jewry in Communist Poland''. Tucson, Ariz: Fenestra Books.}}

==External links==
*[http://www.keston.org.uk/ Keston Institute: Resources for the Studies of Communist Countries and Religious Affairs]

{{Relpolnav}}
{{Religious persecution|right}}
{{Atheism}}
{{Belief systems}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:State Atheism}}
[[Category:Atheism]]
[[Category:Religious law]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Religious discrimination]]
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Church and state law]]
[[Category:Political theories]]

[[es:Ateísmo de Estado]]
[[fr:Athéisme d'État]]
[[ko:국가 무신론주의]]
[[hr:Službeni ateizam]]
[[id:Negara ateis]]
[[it:Ateismo di Stato]]
[[he:אתאיזם מדיני]]
[[no:Statsateisme]]
[[pl:Ateizm państwowy]]
[[pt:Estado ateu]]
[[ro:Stat ateu]]
[[ru:Атеистическое государство]]
[[sr:Државни атеизам]]
[[sh:Državni ateizam]]
[[fi:Valtioateismi]]
[[tr:Devlet ateizmi]]
[[zh:国家无神论]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>