<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181026102616|865815886" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="844779" pageid="844779" ns="0" title="State atheism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-22T11:10:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Map of state atheism.svg|thumb|right|400px|{{longitem|World map showing nations that formerly or currently practice state atheism. 
{{legend|#F08080|Countries that formerly practiced state atheism}}
{{legend|#DC143C|Countries that currently practice state atheism}} }}
]]
{{Atheism sidebar|concepts}}
{{Irreligion sidebar|atheism}}
{{Status of religious freedom|expanded=persecution}}
'''State atheism''' is the incorporation of [[positive atheism]] or [[non-theism]] into [[Forms of government|political regimes]], particularly associated with Soviet systems.&lt;ref name="oxford"&gt;{{cite book|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=XguDDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT74#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|last1=Bullivant|first1=Stephen|last2=Lee|first2=Lois|title=A Dictionary of Atheism|date=2016|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=9780191816819|quote=State Atheism is the name given to the incorporation of positive atheism or non-theism into political regimes, particularly associated with Soviet systems. State Atheisms have tended to be as much anti-clerical and anti-religious as they are anti-theist, and typically place heavy restrictions on acts of religious organization and the practice of religion.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, a [[secular state]] purports to be officially neutral in matters of [[religion]], supporting neither religion nor [[irreligion]].&lt;ref name="Jeroen 1"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Temperman|first1=Jeroen|title=State-Religion Relationships and Human Rights Law : Towards a Right to Religiously Neutral Governance|date=2010|publisher=Brill Academic/Martinus Nijhoff Publishers|isbn=9789004181489|page=140|quote=Although the historical underlying incentives that accompanied the establishment of a secular state may have been characterized by criticism of certain religious doctrines or practices, presently a state of secularity in itself does not necessarily reflect value judgements about religion. In other words, state secularism does not come down to an official rejection of religion. State secularism denotes an intention on the part of the state to not affiliate itself with religion, to not consider itself a priori bound by religious principles (unless they are reformulated into secular state laws) and to not seek to justify its actions by invoking religion. Such a state of secularity denotes official impartiality in matters of religion rather than official irreligiosity. By contrast, secularism as a philosophical notion can indeed be construed as an ideological defense of the secular cause, which might include criticism of or scepticism towards religion. Thus, states that are 'ideologically secular' and that declare secular world-views the official state doctrine give evidence, explicitly or by implication, of judgements about the value of religion within society. Most versions of state communism, for instance, embrace Marxist criticism of religion.}}&lt;/ref&gt; State atheism may refer to a government's [[anti-clericalism]], which opposes religious institutional power and influence in all aspects of public and political life, including the involvement of religion in the everyday life of the citizen.&lt;ref name="Jeroen 2"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Temperman|first1=Jeroen|title=State-Religion Relationships and Human Rights Law : Towards a Right to Religiously Neutral Governance|date=2010|publisher=Brill Academic/Martinus Nijhoff Publishers|isbn=9789004181489|pages=140–141|quote=Before the end of the Cold War, many Communist States did not shy away from being openly hostile to religion. In most instances, communist ideology translated unperturbedly into state atheism, which, in turn, triggered measures aimed at the eradication of religion. As much was acknowledged by some Communist Constitutions. The 1976 Constitution of the People's Socialist Republic of Albania, for instance, was firmly based on a Marxist dismissal of religion as the opiate of the masses. It provided: "The state recognizes no religion of any kind and supports and develops the atheist view so as to ingrain in to the people the scientific and materialistic world-view."}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="FrankenLoobuyck2011"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Franken|first1=Leni|last2=Loobuyck|first2=Patrick|title=Religious Education in a Plural, Secularised Society. A Paradigm Shift|year=2011|publisher=Waxmann Verlag|language=English|isbn=9783830975434|page=152|quote=In this model, atheism is a state doctrine. Instead, it is regarded as an official state policy, aiming to eradicate all sympathy for religious ideas, and the idea that God exists in particular. The adherents of political atheism make a plea for an atheist state that has to foster atheist convictions in its citizenry.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oxford" /&gt;

The majority of [[Communist state|Marxist–Leninist states]] followed similar policies from 1917.&lt;ref name="Jeroen 2" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Borowik|first1=Irena|last2=Ancic|first2=Branko|last3=Tyrala|first3=Radoslaw|editor1-last=Ruse|editor1-first=Michael|editor2-last=Bullivant|editor2-first=Stephen|title=Oxford Handbook of Atheism|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0198745079|page=626|chapter=39.Central And Eastern Europe|quote=There have been only a few comparative analyses of atheism carried out in the CEE region. One of the few attempts of this kind is that undertaken by Sinita Zrinkak (see 2004). Comparing different types of generational responses to atheism in several CEE countries, on the basis of studies carried out in these countries and based on data from the EVS, he distinguishes three groups of countries in the region. The first group comprises countries in which state atheism had the most severe consequences... This group includes such countries as Estonia, Latvia, Russia, Ukraine, Belarus, and Bulgaria.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Eller China" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Wessinger2000" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Cuba" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Hertzke2006p44" /&gt; The [[Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic]] (1917–1991), and the [[Soviet Union]] (1922–1991) more broadly, had a long history of state atheism, whereby those seeking social success generally had to profess atheism and to stay away from [[houses of worship]]; this trend became especially militant during the middle [[Stalinist era]] from 1929 to 1939. The Soviet Union attempted to suppress public religious expression over wide areas of its influence, including places such as [[central Asia]]. Currently, only [[China]], [[Cuba]], [[North Korea]] and [[Vietnam]] are officially atheist.

==Communist states==
{{Main|Marxism and religion}}

A [[communist state]], in popular usage, is a [[State (polity)|state]] with a [[form of government]] characterized by [[One-party state|one-party rule]] or [[Dominant-party system|dominant-party rule]] of a [[communist party]] and a professed allegiance to a [[Leninist]] or [[Marxist–Leninist]] [[Communism|communist]] ideology as the guiding principle of the state.  The founder and primary theorist of [[Marxism]], the nineteenth-century German thinker [[Karl Marx]], had an ambivalent attitude toward religion, viewing it primarily as "the [[opium of the people]]" that had been used by the ruling classes to give the [[working classes]] false hope for millennia, whilst at the same time recognizing it as a form of protest by the working classes against their poor economic conditions.&lt;ref&gt;Raines, John. 2002. "Introduction". ''Marx on Religion'' (Marx, Karl). Philadelphia: Temple University Press. Page 05-06.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the Marxist–Leninist interpretation of Marxist theory, developed primarily by Russian revolutionary [[Vladimir Lenin]], religion is seen as negative to human development, and communist states that follow a Marxist–Leninist variant are [[Atheism|atheistic]] and explicitly [[Antireligion|antireligious]].&lt;ref name=Lenin&gt;
{{cite web
 | url=http://www.psylib.ukrweb.net/books/maenl01/txt17
 | last = Lenin
 | first = V. I.
 | title = About the attitude of the working party toward the religion.
 | accessdate=2006-09-09
 | work = Collected works, v. 17, p.41
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;  Lenin states:

{{quote|Religion is the opiate of the people: this saying of Marx is the cornerstone of the entire ideology of Marxism about religion. All modern religions and churches, all and of every kind of religious organizations are always considered by Marxism as the organs of bourgeois reaction, used for the protection of the exploitation and the stupefaction of the working class.&lt;ref name=Lenin /&gt;}}

Although Marx&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nicolaievsky|Maenchen-Helfen|1976|pp=38–45}}{{cnf|date=April 2017}}; {{harvnb|Wheen|2001|p=34}}{{cnf|date=April 2017}}; {{harvnb|McLellan|2006|pp=32–33, 37}}{{cnf|date=April 2017}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and Lenin{{sfnm|1a1=Fischer|1y=1964|1p=552|2a1=Leggett|2y=1981|2p=308|3a1=Sandle|3y=1999|3p=126|4a1=Read|4y=2005|4pp=238–239|5a1=Ryan|5y=2012|5pp=176, 182}}{{cnf|date=April 2017}} were both atheists, several [[Religious communism|religious communist]] groups exist, including [[Christian communism|Christian communists]].

[[Julian Baggini]] devotes a chapter of his book ''Atheism A Very Short Introduction'' to discussion of 20th century political systems, including communism and political repression in the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name="Baggini2003"&gt;{{cite book|author=Julian Baggini|title=Atheism: A Very Short Introduction|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oF8AusdNTXsC|date=26 June 2003|publisher=OUP Oxford|isbn=978-0-19-280424-2|pages=82–90}}&lt;/ref&gt; Baggini argues that "Soviet communism, with its active oppression of religion, is a distortion of original Marxist communism, which did not advocate oppression of the religious." Baggini goes on to argue that "Fundamentalism is a danger in any belief system" and that "Atheism's most authentic political expression... takes the form of state secularism, not state atheism."

===Soviet Union===
{{main|Religion in the Soviet Union|Irreligion in Russia|Irreligion in Kazakhstan|Irreligion in Azerbaijan|Irreligion in Estonia|Secularism and Irreligion in Georgia}}
[[File:1922 Bezbozhnik magazine cover.jpg|thumb|USSR. 1922 issue of the ''[[Bezbozhnik (magazine)|Bezbozhnik]]'' (The Godless) magazine. By 1934, 28% of Eastern Orthodox churches, 42% of Muslim mosques and 52% of Jewish synagogues were shut down in the USSR.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.friends-partners.org/partners/beyond-the-pale/english/43.html |title=Religions attacked in the USSR |accessdate=2005-07-22 |deadurl=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071023063308/http://www.friends-partners.org/partners/beyond-the-pale/english/43.html |archivedate=October 23, 2007 |df= }} (Beyond the Pale)&lt;/ref&gt;]]

State atheism, (''gosateizm'', a [[Abbreviation#Syllabic abbreviation|syllabic abbreviation]] of "state" (''gosudarstvo'') and "atheism" (''ateizm'')), was a major goal of the official [[Soviet]] ideology.&lt;ref name="Kowalewski1980"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Kowalewski|first1=David|title=Protest for Religious Rights in the USSR: Characteristics and Consequences|journal=Russian Review|jstor=128810|publisher=Blackwell Publishing on behalf of The Editors and Board of Trustees of the Russian Review|volume=39|issue=4|year=1980|pages=426–441|issn=0036-0341|doi=10.2307/128810}}&lt;/ref&gt;  To that end, the regime expropriated church property, publication of information against religious beliefs and the official promotion of anti-religious materials in the education system.

After the [[Russian Civil War]], the state used its resources to stop the implanting of religious beliefs in nonbelievers and remove "prerevolutionary remnants" that still existed.&lt;ref name="Kowalewski1980"/&gt; The [[Bolsheviks]] were particularly hostile toward the [[Russian Orthodox Church]] (which supported the [[White Movement]] during the [[Russian Civil War]]) and saw it as a supporter of [[Tsarist autocracy]].&lt;ref name="Fitzpatrick1996"&gt;{{cite book|author=Sheila Fitzpatrick|title=Stalin's Peasants: Resistance and Survival in the Russian Village After Collectivization|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YlBvcNMlr4EC|year=1996|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-510459-2|page=33}}&lt;/ref&gt; During a process of [[Collectivization in the Soviet Union|collectivization]] of land, Orthodox priests distributed pamphlets declaring that the Soviet regime was the [[Antichrist]] coming to place "the Devil's mark" on the peasants, and encouraged them to resist the government.&lt;ref name="Fitzpatrick1996"/&gt; [[Political repression in the Soviet Union|Political repression]] was widespread in the Soviet Union, and while religious persecution was applied to most religions,&lt;ref name=RussianOrthodox /&gt; the regime's anti-religious campaigns were often directed against specific religions based on state interests, that varied over time. The attitude in the Soviet Union toward religion varied from a total ban on some religions to official support of others.

From the late 1920s to the late 1930s, such organizations as the [[League of Militant Atheists]] ridiculed all religions and harassed believers.&lt;ref&gt;[[Richard Overy]] (2006), ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany, Stalin's Russia'', p. 271 {{ISBN|0-393-02030-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-religious and atheistic propaganda was implemented into every portion of soviet life: in schools, communist organizations such as the [[Vladimir Lenin All-Union Pioneer Organization|Young Pioneer Organization]], and the media. Though Lenin originally introduced the [[Gregorian calendar]] to the Soviets, subsequent efforts to reorganise the week to improve worker productivity saw the introduction of the [[Soviet calendar]], which had the side-effect that a "holiday will seldom fall on Sunday".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,930406,00.html
|title=Staggerers Unstaggered 
|date=December 7, 1931
|publisher=Time magazine
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within about a year of the revolution, the state [[Eminent domain|expropriated]] all church property, including the churches themselves, and in the period from 1922 to 1926, 28 Russian Orthodox bishops and more than 1,200 priests were killed (a much greater number was subjected to persecution).&lt;ref name=RussianOrthodox&gt;[http://countrystudies.us/russia/38.htm Country Studies: Russia-The Russian Orthodox Church] U.S. Library of Congress, Accessed Apr. 3, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  Most seminaries were closed, and publication of religious writing was banned.&lt;ref name=RussianOrthodox /&gt;  The Russian Orthodox Church, which had 54,000 parishes before World War I, was reduced to 500 by 1940.&lt;ref name=RussianOrthodox /&gt;  A meeting of the Antireligious Commission of the Central Committee of the All-Union Communist Party ([[Bolsheviks]]) that occurred on 23 May 1929 estimated the portion of believers in the [[USSR]] at 80 percent, though this percentage may be understated to prove the successfulness of the struggle with religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Marjorie Mandelstam Balzer|title=Religion and Politics in Russia: A Reader|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DEufvUyRcygC|year=2009|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|isbn=978-0-7656-2415-4|pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=DEufvUyRcygC&amp;pg=PA6 6–7]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the Soviet Union's attempts to eliminate religion,&lt;ref name="Kowalewski1980"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sabrina Petra Ramet, Ed., Religious Policy in the Soviet Union. Cambridge University Press (1993). P 4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Anderson, Religion, State and Politics in the Soviet Union and Successor States, Cambridge University Press, 1994, pp 3&lt;/ref&gt; other former USSR and anti-religious nations, such as [[Armenia]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/?id=5211|title=The Armenian Apostolic Church (World Council of Churches)}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kazakhstan]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2009/127366.htm International Religious Freedom Report 2009 – Kazakhstan] U.S. Department of State. 2009-10-26. Retrieved on 2009-11-05.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Uzbekistan]],&lt;ref name="state1"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2924.htm |title=Uzbekistan |publisher=State.gov |date=2009-10-16 |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Turkmenistan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/tx.html|title=The World Factbook|work=cia.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kyrgyzstan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2001/5598.htm |title=Kyrgyzstan |publisher=State.gov |date= |accessdate=2010-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tajikistan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5775.htm |title=Background Note: Tajikistan |publisher=State.gov |date= |accessdate=2009-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Belarus]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationmaster.com/country/bo-belarus/rel-religion|title=Belarus Religion Stats: NationMaster.com|work=nationmaster.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/bo.html|title=The World Factbook|work=cia.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Moldova]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationmaster.com/country/md-moldova/rel-religion|title=Moldova Religion Stats|work=nationmaster.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationmaster.com/country/gg-georgia/rel-religion|title=Georgia Religion Stats|work=nationmaster.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; have high religious populations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|editor-last=Miller |editor-first=Tracy |date=October 2009 |publisher=[[Pew Research Center]] |title=Mapping the Global Muslim Population: A Report on the Size and Distribution of the World's Muslim Population |format=[[Portable Document Format|PDF]] |url=http://pewforum.org/newassets/images/reports/Muslimpopulation/Muslimpopulation.pdf |accessdate=8 October 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091010050756/http://pewforum.org/newassets/images/reports/Muslimpopulation/Muslimpopulation.pdf |archivedate=October 10, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Author Niels Christian Nielsen has written that the post-Soviet population in areas which were formerly predominantly Orthodox are now "nearly illiterate regarding religion", almost completely lacking the intellectual or philosophical aspects of their faith and having almost no knowledge of other faiths.&lt;ref&gt;Nielsen, Niels Christian, Jr., [https://books.google.com/books?id=Ts6w8JumlQMC&amp;d Christianity After Communism], p. 77-78, Westview Press 1998&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, their knowledge of their faith and the faith of others notwithstanding, many post-Soviet populations have a large presence of religious followers.

Today in the [[Russian Federation]], approximately 100 million citizens consider themselves Russian Orthodox Christians, amounting to 70% of the population, although the Church claims a membership of 80 million.&lt;ref name="Page"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article551693.ece | work=The Times | location=London | title=The rise of Russian Muslims worries Orthodox Church | first=Jeremy | last=Page | date=2005-08-05 | accessdate=2010-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Russia"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90196.htm|title=Russia|work=U.S. Department of State}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90196.htm|accessdate=2008-04-08|title=Russia}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[CIA Factbook]], however, only 17% to 22% of the population is now Christian.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, Ethan [https://www.christianpost.com/news/gorbachev-dispels-closet-christian-rumors-says-he-is-atheist-31660/ Gorbachev Dispels 'Closet Christian' Rumors; Says He is Atheist] Christian Post, Mar. 24, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  According to a poll by the [[VCIOM|Russian Public Opinion Research Center]], 63% of respondents considered themselves Russian Orthodox, 6% of respondents considered themselves [[Muslim]] and less than 1% considered themselves either Buddhist, Catholic, Protestant or Jewish. Another 12% said they believe in God, but did not practice any religion, and 16% said they are non-believers.&lt;ref name=religionsurvey&gt;{{cite web|script-title=ru:Опубликована подробная сравнительная статистика религиозности в России и Польше|publisher=religare.ru|date=6 June 2007|url=http://www.religare.ru/article42432.htm|accessdate=2007-12-27|language=ru}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Ukraine]], 96.1% of the [[Ukrainians|Ukrainian]] population is [[Christian]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationmaster.com/country/up-ukraine/rel-religion|title=Ukraine Religion Stats|work=nationmaster.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Lithuania]], the only Catholic country which was once a Soviet republic,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Olsen|first=Brad|title=Sacred Places Europe: 108 Destinations|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cdM3qHlNeb4C&amp;pg=PA148|year=2007|publisher=CCC Publishing|isbn=978-1-888729-12-2|page=148}}&lt;/ref&gt; a 2005 report stated that 79% of [[Lithuanians]] belonged to the [[Roman Catholic Church]].&lt;ref&gt;Department of Statistics to the Government of the Republic of Lithuania. ''{{cite web |url=http://www.std.lt/en/pages/view/?id=1734 |title=Population by Religious Confession, census  |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061001185140/http://www.std.lt/en/pages/view/?id=1734 |archivedate=2006-10-01}}''. Updated in 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Albania===
{{Main|Religion in Albania#Communist Albania|Freedom of religion in Albania|Irreligion in Albania}}
Religion in [[Albania]] was subordinated to the interests of nationalism during periods of national revival, when it was identified as foreign predation to Albanian culture. During the late nineteenth century, and also when Albania became a state, religions were suppressed in order to better unify Albanians. This nationalism was also used to justify the communist stance of state atheism from 1967 to 1991.&lt;ref name="Hall1999"&gt;[https://www.jstor.org/stable/3060414 Representations of Place: Albania], Derek R. Hall, ''The Geographical Journal'', Vol. 165, No. 2, The Changing Meaning of Place in Post-Socialist Eastern Europe: Commodification, Perception and Environment (Jul., 1999), pp. 161–172, Blackwell Publishing on behalf of The Royal Geographical Society (with the Institute of British Geographers) "the perception that religion symbolized foreign (Italian, Greek and Turkish) predation was used to justify the communists' stance of state atheism (1967-1991)."&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Agrarian Reform Law (Albania)|Agrarian Reform Law]] of August 1945 nationalized most property of religious institutions, including the estates of mosques, monasteries, orders, and dioceses. Many clergy and believers were tried and some were executed. All foreign Roman Catholic priests, monks, and nuns were expelled in 1946.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-186.html|title=Albania - Hoxha's Antireligious Campaign|work=country-data.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Religious communities or branches that had their headquarters outside the country, such as the [[Jesuit]] and [[Franciscan]] orders, were henceforth ordered to terminate their activities in Albania. Religious institutions were forbidden to have anything to do with the education of the young, because that had been made the exclusive province of the state. All religious communities were prohibited from owning real estate and from operating philanthropic and welfare institutions and hospitals.
Although there were tactical variations in [[Enver Hoxha]]'s approach to each of the major denominations, his overarching objective was the eventual destruction of all organized religion in Albania. Between 1945 and 1953, the number of priests was reduced drastically and the number of Roman Catholic churches was decreased from 253 to 100, and all Catholics were stigmatized as fascists.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt;

The campaign against religion peaked in the 1960s. Beginning in February 1967 the Albanian authorities launched a campaign to eliminate religious life in Albania. Despite complaints, even by [[Party of Labour of Albania|APL]] members, all churches, mosques, monasteries, and other religious institutions were either closed down or converted into warehouses, gymnasiums, or workshops by the end of 1967.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-170.html|title=Albania - The Cultural and Ideological Revolution|work=country-data.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; By May 1967, religious institutions had been forced to relinquish all 2,169 churches, mosques, cloisters, and shrines in Albania, many of which were converted into cultural centers for young people. As the literary monthly Nendori reported the event, the youth had thus "created the first atheist nation in the world."&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt;

Clerics were publicly vilified and humiliated, their vestments were taken and desecrated. More than 200 clerics of various faiths were imprisoned, others were forced to seek work in either industry or agriculture, and some were executed or starved to death. The cloister of the Franciscan order in Shkodër was set on fire, which resulted in the death of four elderly monks.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt;

Article 37 of the Albanian Constitution of 1976 stipulated, "The state recognizes no religion, and supports atheistic propaganda in order to implant a scientific materialistic world outlook in people.",&lt;ref&gt;[http://bjoerna.dk/dokumentation/Albanian-Constitution-1976.htm#C.%20Education,%20Science,%20Culture C. Education, Science, Culture], The Albanian Constitution of 1976.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Jeroen 2" /&gt; and the penal code of 1977 imposed prison sentences of three to ten years for "religious propaganda and the production, distribution, or storage of religious literature."{{citation needed|date=July 2014}} A new decree that in effect targeted Albanians with Muslim and Christian names, stipulating that citizens whose names did not conform to "the political, ideological, or moral standards of the state" were to change them.{{citation needed|date=July 2014}} It was also decreed that towns and villages with religious names must be renamed.{{citation needed|date=July 2014}} Hoxha's brutal antireligious campaign succeeded in eradicating formal worship, but some Albanians continued to practice their faith clandestinely, risking severe punishment.{{citation needed|date=July 2014}} Individuals caught with Bibles, Qurans, icons, or other religious objects faced long prison sentences. Religious weddings were prohibited.{{citation needed|date=July 2014}}

Parents were afraid to pass on their faith, for fear that their children would tell others. Officials tried to entrap practicing Christians and Muslims during religious fasts, such as [[Lent]] and [[Ramadan]], by distributing dairy products and other forbidden foods in school and at work, and then publicly denouncing those who refused the food. Those clergy who conducted secret services were incarcerated.&lt;ref name="country-data.com"/&gt; Catholic priest [[Kurti, Shtjefen|Shtjefen Kurti]] had been executed for secretly baptizing a child in [[Shkodër]] in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;Sinishta, G., 1976. The Fulfilled Promise: A Documentary Account of Religious Persecution in Albania. Albanian Catholic Information Center, Santa Clara.&lt;/ref&gt;

The article was interpreted by Danes as violating The [[United Nations Charter]] (chapter 9, article 55) which declares that [[religious freedom]] is an inalienable human right. The first time that the question came before the United Nations' [[Commission on Human Rights]] at Geneva was as late as 7 March 1983. A delegation from Denmark got its protest over Albania's violation of religious liberty placed on the agenda of the thirty-ninth meeting of the commission, item 25, reading, "Implementation of the Declaration on the Elimination of all Forms of Intolerance and of Discrimination based on Religion or Belief.", and on 20 July 1984 a member of the [[Danish Parliament]] inserted an article into one of Denmark's major newspapers protesting the violation of religious freedom in Albania.

The 1998 [[Constitution of Albania]] defined the country as a [[parliamentary republic]], and established personal and political rights and freedoms, including protection against coercion in matters of religious belief.&lt;ref name=uscirf-oic&gt;{{cite web|title=The Religion-State Relationship and the Right to Freedom of Religion or Belief: A Comparative Textual Analysis of the Constitutions of Majority Muslim Countries and Other OIC Members|url=http://www.uscirf.gov/sites/default/files/resources/USCIRF%20Constitution%20Study%202012%20(full%20Text(2)).pdf|publisher= U.S. COMMISSION ON INTERNATIONAL RELIGIOUS FREEDOM|year=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=2013statealbania/&gt; Albania is a member state of the [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation]],&lt;ref name=uscirf-oic/&gt; and the 2011 census found that 58.79% of Albanians adhere to [[Islam]], making it the largest [[religion]] in the country. The majority of Albanian Muslims are secular Sunnis along with a significant [[Bektashi]] Shia minority. [[Christianity]] is practiced by 16.99% of the population, making it the 2nd largest religion in the country. The remaining population is either [[irreligious]] or belongs to other religious groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.instat.gov.al/media/177358/njoftim_per_media_-_fjala_e_drejtorit_te_instat_ines_nurja_per_rezultatet_finale_te_census_2011.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2017-03-26 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170326091156/http://www.instat.gov.al/media/177358/njoftim_per_media_-_fjala_e_drejtorit_te_instat_ines_nurja_per_rezultatet_finale_te_census_2011.pdf |archivedate=2017-03-26 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Before World War II, there was given a distribution of 70% Muslims, 20% Eastern Orthodox, and 10% Roman Catholics.&lt;ref name="cia"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/al.html |publisher=Central Intelligence Agency |title=The World Factbook: Albania |accessdate=21 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, Gallup Global Reports 2010 shows that religion plays a role in the lives of 39% of Albanians, and ranks Albania the thirteenth least religious country in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/128210/Gallup-Global-Reports.aspx |title=Gallup Global Reports |publisher=Gallup.com |date= |accessdate=2013-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. state department reports that in 2013, "There were no reports of societal abuses or discrimination based on religious affiliation, belief, or practice."&lt;ref name=2013statealbania&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.state.gov/documents/organization/222395.pdf|title=ALBANIA 2013 INTERNATIONAL RELIGIOUS FREEDOM REPORT|publisher=U.S. Department of State}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cambodia under the Khmer Rouge===
[[File:Bullet holes at angkor wat.jpg|thumb|Khmer Rouge bullet holes left at Angkor Wat temple]]
The [[Khmer Rouge]] actively persecuted Buddhists during their reign from 1975 to 1979.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yale.edu/cgp/chron.html|title=Chronology, 1994-2004 - Cambodian Genocide Program - Yale University|publisher=|accessdate=8 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Buddhist institutions and temples were destroyed and Buddhist monks and teachers were killed in large numbers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sptimes.com/News/050300/NIE/Remembering_the_death.shtml |title=Nie: Remembering the deaths of 1.7-million Cambodians |publisher=Sptimes.com |date= |accessdate=2015-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; A third of the nation's [[monastery|monasteries]] were destroyed along with numerous holy texts and items of high artistic quality. 25,000 Buddhist monks were massacred by the regime,&lt;ref name="NYTi"&gt;[https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DE163CF931A35752C0A964958260 Philip Shenon, Phnom Penh Journal; Lord Buddha Returns, With Artists His Soldiers] ''[[New York Times]]'' - January 2, 1992&lt;/ref&gt; which was officially an atheist state.&lt;ref name="Wessinger2000"&gt;{{cite book|last=Wessinger|first=Catherine|title=Millennialism, Persecution, and Violence: Historical Cases|year=2000|publisher=[[Syracuse University Press]]|language=English |isbn=9780815628095|page=282|quote=Democratic Kampuchea was officially an atheist state, and the persecution of religion by the Khmer Rouge was matched in severity only by the persecution of religion in the communist states of Albania and North Korea, so there were not any direct historical continuities of Buddhism into the Democratic Kampuchea era.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The persecution was undertaken because [[Pol Pot]] believed that Buddhism was "a decadent affectation". He sought to eliminate Buddhism's 1,500-year-old mark on [[Cambodia]].&lt;ref name="NYTi" /&gt;

Religion was also banned, and the repression of adherents of [[Islam]], [[Christianity]], and [[Buddhism]] was extensive. And according to [[Ben Kiernan]], the "fiercest extermination campaign was directed against the ethnic [[Cham people|Cham Muslim]] minority".{{sfn|Kiernan|2003|p=30}}

===China===
{{main|Freedom of religion in China|Irreligion in China}}
China is an officially atheist state,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Wielander|first=Gerda|title=Christian Values in Communist China|year=2013|publisher=Routledge|language=English|isbn=9781317976042|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; which has promoted atheism throughout the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/monitoring/253345.stm|title=China announces "civilizing" atheism drive in Tibet|year=1999|publisher=BBC|language=English|accessdate=3 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Eller China"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Eller|first1=Jack David|title=Introducing Anthropology of Religion: Culture to the Ultimate.|date=2014|publisher=Routledge|isbn=1138024910|page=254|quote=After the communist revolution of 1949, the People's Republic of China adopted a policy of official state atheism. Based on Marxist thinking that religion is class exploitation and false consciousness, the communist regime suppressed religion, "re-educated" believers and religious leaders, and destroyed religious buildings or converted them to non-religious uses.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2016, the [[General Secretary of the Communist Party of China|General Secretary]], [[Xi Jinping]], stated that members of the [[Communist Party of China]] must be "unyielding Marxist atheists" while in the same month, government officials ran over Chinese Christians who protested the demolition of their church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://time.com/4306179/china-religion-freedom-xi-jinping-muslim-christian-xinjiang-buddhist-tibet/|title=China's Leader Xi Jinping Reminds Party Members to Be 'Unyielding Marxist Atheists'|last=Campbell|first=Charlie|date=25 April 2016|publisher=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|accessdate=3 September 2017|location=Beijing}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Traditionally, a large segment of the Chinese population took part in [[Chinese folk religion]]s&lt;ref&gt;Ping Xiong, Freedom of Religion in China Under the Current Legal Framework and Foreign Religious Bodies, 2013 BYU L. Rev. 605 (2014)
Available at: http://digitalcommons.law.byu.edu/lawreview/vol2013/iss3/9&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Confucianism]], [[Taoism]] and [[Buddhism]] had played a significant role in the everyday lives of ordinary people.&lt;ref name="Sharma2011"&gt;{{cite book|author=Arvind Sharma|title=Problematizing Religious Freedom|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JGjqk1AxCU4C|date=8 August 2011|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|isbn=978-90-481-8993-9|page=201}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Chen1965"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Chen|first1=Kenneth|title=Chinese Communist Attitudes Towards Buddhism in Chinese History|journal=The China Quarterly|volume=22|year=1965|pages=14|issn=0305-7410|doi=10.1017/S0305741000048682|quote=In the journal Hsien-tai Fo-hsueh (Modern Buddhism), September 1959, there appeared a long article entitled "Lun Tsung-chiao Hsin-yang Tzu-yu" ("A Discussion Concerning Freedom of Religious Belief"), by Ya Han-chang, which was originally published in the official Communist ideological journal Hung Ch'i (Red Flag), 1959, No. 14. Appearing as it did in Red Flag it is justifiable to conclude that the views expressed in it represented the accepted Communist attitude toward religion. In this article, Ya wrote that the basic policy of the Chinese Communist Party and the People's Republic of China is to "recognise that everyone has the freedom to believe in a religion, and also that everyone has the freedom not to believe in a religion."}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Practice of Chinese Buddhism, 1900–1950 – Page 393&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Chinese Revolution (1949)|1949 Chinese Revolution]], China began a period of rule by the [[Communist Party of China]].&lt;ref&gt;Xie, Zhibin, [https://books.google.com/books?id=peah4XTpqnkC&amp;dq Religious diversity and public religion in China], p.145, Ashgate Publishing 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tyler, Christian [https://books.google.com/books?id=bEzNwgtiVQ0C&amp;dq Wild West China], p. 259, Rutgers Univ. Press 2004&lt;/ref&gt; For much of its early history, that government maintained under [[Marxism|Marxist]] thought that religion would ultimately disappear, and characterized it as emblematic of [[feudalism]] and foreign [[colonialism]].

During the [[Cultural Revolution]], student vigilantes known as [[Red Guards (China)|Red Guards]] converted religious buildings for secular use or destroyed them. This attitude, however, relaxed considerably in the late 1970s, with the [[reform and opening up]] period. The [[1978 Constitution of the People's Republic of China]] guaranteed [[freedom of religion]] with a number of restrictions.  Since then, there has been a massive program to rebuild Buddhist and Taoist temples that were destroyed in the Cultural Revolution.

The Communist Party has said that religious belief and membership are incompatible.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deccanherald.com/content/212827/no-religion-chinese-communist-party.html "No Religion for Chinese Communist Party Cadres".  ''Deccan Herald''.  December 2011.]&lt;/ref&gt; However, the state is not allowed to force ordinary citizens to become atheists.&lt;ref name="Temperman"&gt;{{cite book|title=State-Religion Relationship and Human Rights Law: Towards a Right to Religiously Neutral Governance|first=Jeroen|last=Temperman|publisher=Brill|date=May 30, 2010|pages=141–145}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[China]]'s five officially sanctioned religious organizations are the [[Buddhist Association of China]], [[Chinese Taoist Association]], [[Islamic Association of China]], [[Three-Self Patriotic Movement]] and [[Chinese Patriotic Catholic Association]]. These groups are afforded a degree of protection, but are subject to restrictions and controls under the [[State Administration for Religious Affairs]]. Unregistered religious groups face varying degrees of harassment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.china-embassy.org/eng/zt/zjxy/t36492.htm
|title= White Paper—Freedom of Religious Belief in China
|publisher=Embassy of the People's Republic of China in the United States of America
|date=October 1997
|accessdate=2007-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The constitution permits what is called "normal religious activities," so long as they do not involve the use of religion to "engage in activities that disrupt social order, impair the health of citizens or interfere with the educational system of the state. Religious organizations and religious affairs are not subject to any foreign dominance."&lt;ref name="Temperman"/&gt;

Article 36 of the [[Constitution of the People's Republic of China]] of 1982 specifies that:

{{blockquote|Citizens of the People's Republic of China enjoy freedom of religious belief. No state organ, public organization or individual may compel citizens to believe in, or not to believe in, any religion; nor may they discriminate against citizens who believe in, or do not believe in, any religion. The state protects normal religious activities. No one may make use of religion to engage in activities that disrupt public order, impair the health of citizens or interfere with the educational system of the state. Religious bodies and religious affairs are not subject to any foreign domination.&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.people.cn/constitution/constitution.html English translation of the Constitution of the People's Republic of China of 1982] (page visited on 20 February 2015).&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Most people report no organized religious affiliation; however, people with a belief in folk traditions and spiritual beliefs, such as [[ancestor veneration]] and [[feng shui]], along with informal ties to local temples and unofficial house churches number in the hundreds of millions. The [[United States Department of State]], in its annual report on International Religious Freedom,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=https://www.state.gov/g/drl/irf/rpt/
|title=Annual Report to Congress on International Religious Freedom
|publisher=U.S. Department of State
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; provides statistics about organized religions. In 2007 it reported the following (citing the Government's 1997 report on Religious Freedom and 2005 White Paper on religion):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=https://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90133.htm
|title=International Religious Freedom Report 2007 — China (includes Tibet, Hong Kong, and Macau)
|year=2007
|publisher=U.S. Department of State
|accessdate=2007-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:*Buddhists 8%.
:*Taoists, unknown as a percentage partly because it is fused along with Confucianism and Buddhism.
:*Muslims, 1%, with more than 20,000 [[Imams]]. Other estimates state at least 1%.
:*Christians, Protestants at least 2%. Catholics, about 1%.

Statistics relating to [[Buddhism]] and religious [[Taoism]] are to some degree incomparable with statistics for [[Islam]] and [[Christianity]]. This is due to the traditional [[China|Chinese]] belief system which blends [[Confucianism]], [[Buddhism]], and [[Taoism]], so that a person who follows a traditional belief system would not necessarily identify him- or herself as exclusively Buddhist or Taoist, despite attending Buddhist or Taoist places of worship. According to Peter Ng, Professor of the Department of Religion at the Chinese University of Hong Kong, {{as of|2002|lc=y}}, 95% of Chinese were religious in some way if religion is considered to include traditional folk practices such as burning incense for gods or ancestors at life-cycle or seasonal festivals, fortune telling and related customary practices.&lt;ref name=madsen&gt;{{cite book|last=Madsen|first=Richard|title=Chinese society: change, conflict and resistance|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-56073-3|editor=Elizabeth J. Perry, Mark Selden|page=239|chapter=Chapter 10. Chinese Christianity: Indigenization and conflict}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Tze Ming Ng, "Religious Situations in China Today: Secularization Theory Revisited" Paper presented at the Association for the Sociology of Religion Meetings, Chicago, August 14–16, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. State Department has designated China as a "country of particular concern" since 1999,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uscirf.gov/sites/default/files/China%202015.pdf|title=China - USCIRF Annual Report 2015|publisher=United States Commission on International Religious Freedom}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|quote=The religious freedom situation in Russia is deteriorating and China remains one of the world's most egregious violators of this fundamental right|author=Katrina Swett|title=Remarks by USCIRF Chair Katrina Lantos Swett at Conference on Religious Freedom, Violent Religious Extremism, and Constitutional Reform in Muslim-Majority Countries|date=7 Dec 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; in part, due to the scenario of Uighur Muslims and Tibetan Buddhists. Freedom House classifies Tibet and Xinjiang as regions of particular repression of religion, due to concerns of separatist activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://freedomhouse.org/report/freedom-world/2013/china|title=China - Country report - Freedom in the World - 2013|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Minority Rights Group International, Religious Minorities and China, November 2001, available at: http://www.refworld.org/docid/469cbf8e0.html [accessed 5 October 2015]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;United States Department of State, 2013 Report on International Religious Freedom - China, 28 July 2014, available at: http://www.refworld.org/docid/53d907958e.html [accessed 5 October 2015]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;United States Department of State, 2013 Report on International Religious Freedom - China: Macau, 28 July 2014, available at: http://www.refworld.org/docid/53d907945.html [accessed 5 October 2015]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Canada: Immigration and Refugee Board of Canada, China: Freedom of religious practice and belief in Fujian province, 8 October 1999, CHN33002.EX, available at: http://www.refworld.org/docid/3ae6ad442c.html [accessed 5 October 2015]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Heiner Bielefeldt]], the [[United Nations Special Rapporteur on Freedom of Religion or Belief|UN Special Rapporteur on Freedom of Religion or Belief]] says that China's actions against the Uighurs are "a major problem".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2015/03/12/uk-china-un-xinjiang-idUKKBN0M723B20150312|title=U.N. official calls China's crackdown on Uighurs "disturbing"|first=Sui-Lee|last=Wee|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Chinese government has protested the report, saying the country has "ample" religious freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2015/05/04/us-china-usa-religion-idUSKBN0NP0N220150504|title=China lodges protest with U.S. after religious freedom report|date=4 May 2015|work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cuba===
{{main|Religion in Cuba}}
Until 1992,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://theconversation.com/religion-shapes-cuba-despite-castros-influence-69701|title=Religion shapes Cuba despite Castro's influence|last=Maldonado|first=Michelle Gonzalez|date=1 December 2016|publisher=[[The Conversation (website)|The Conversation]]|language=English|accessdate=5 September 2017|quote=Under Castro's rule, Cuba was for decades a self-declared atheist state where Christians were persecuted and marginalized. ... In 1992 the Cuban Constitution was amended to declare it a secular state. It was no longer an atheist Republic.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cuba was officially an atheist state.&lt;ref name="Cuba"&gt;{{cite book|title =Freeing God's Children: The Unlikely Alliance for Global Human Rights|publisher=[[Rowman &amp; Littlefield]]|quote=Cuba is the only country in the Americas that has attempted to impose state atheism, and since the 1960s onward its jails have been filled with pastors and other believers.|accessdate = 2011-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Atheist State"&gt;{{cite book|title =The State of Religion Atlas|publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]]|quote=Atheism continues to be the official position of the governments of China, North Korea and Cuba.|accessdate = 2011-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 1960, several bishops signed a joint pastoral letter condemning communism and declaring it incompatible with Catholicism, and calling on Catholics to reject it.&lt;ref name="Mallin1994"&gt;{{cite book|author=Jay Mallin|title=Covering Castro: Rise and Decline of Cuba's Communist Dictator|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TUGwuKQWXW8C|date=1 January 1994|publisher=Transaction Publishers|isbn=978-1-4128-2053-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fidel Castro]] gave a four-hour long speech the next day, condemning priests who serve "great wealth" and using fears of [[Falangism in Latin America|Falangist]] influence in order to attack Spanish born priests, declaring "There is no doubt that [[Francisco Franco|Franco]] has a sizeable group of fascist priests in Cuba."

Originally more tolerant of religion, the Cuban government began arresting many believers and shutting down religious schools after the [[Bay of Pigs invasion]]. Its prisons were being filled with clergy since the 1960s.&lt;ref name=Hertzke2006p43&gt;[[#Hertzke2006|Hertzke (2006)]]:[https://books.google.com/books?id=EkIvbxefBNsC&amp;pg=PA43 43]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1961 The Cuban government confiscated Catholic schools, including the Jesuit school that Fidel Castro had attended. In 1965 it exiled two hundred priests.&lt;ref name=buckley2005-11-21&gt;William F. Buckley Jr., [http://old.nationalreview.com/flashback/1998200511210830.asp Cuba libre?] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110616061456/http://old.nationalreview.com/flashback/1998200511210830.asp |date=2011-06-16 }}, November 21, 2005, National review.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1976 the [[Constitution of Cuba]] added a clause stating that the "socialist state...bases its activity on, and educates the people in, the scientific materialist concept of the universe". In
1992, the [[Dissolution of the Soviet Union]] led the country to declare itself a [[secular state]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.state.gov/documents/organization/193177.pdf|title=CUBA - Status of Government Respect for Religious Freedom|work=International Religious Freedom Report for 2011|publisher=United States Department of State - Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Constitution of Cuba, Article 8: Freedom of Religion and Separation of Church and State|url=http://berkleycenter.georgetown.edu/quotes/constitution-of-cuba-article-8-freedom-of-religion-and-separation-of-church-and-state|publisher=Berkley Center for Religion, Peace &amp; World Affairs}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Catholic groups have worked to advance the [[United States–Cuban Thaw|Cuban thaw]]. In January 1998, [[Pope John Paul II]] paid a historic visit to the island, invited by the Cuban government and the Catholic Church in Cuba. The pope criticized the [[United States embargo against Cuba|US embargo]] during his visit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/12/17/catholic-church-cuba-us_n_6344510.html|title=How Pope John Paul II Paved The Way For The U.S.-Cuba Thaw|work=The Huffington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope Benedict XVI]] visited Cuba in 2012 and [[Pope Francis]] visited Cuba in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/the_americas/with-clean-streets-and-a-bit-of-suspense-cuba-awaits-pope-francis/2015/09/19/ee4a5ba6-5bf5-11e5-8475-781cc9851652_story.html|title=Pope Francis arrives in Havana, praising U.S.-Cuba thaw|author=Nick Miroff|date=19 September 2015|work=Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/may/10/pope-meets-cuban-president-raul-castro|title=Castro thanks Pope Francis for brokering thaw between Cuba and US|author=Rosie Scammell|work=the Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/18/world/americas/breakthrough-on-cuba-highlights-popes-role-as-diplomatic-broker.html|title=Pope Francis Is Credited With a Crucial Role in U.S.-Cuba Agreement|date=18 December 2014|work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.latimes.com/world/europe/la-fg-pope-francis-us-cuba-talks-20141218-story.html|title=Pope Francis' role in Cuba stretches back years|author=Los Angeles Times|date=18 December 2014|work=latimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Cuban government continued hostile actions against religious groups; in 2015 alone, the Castro régime ordered the closure or demolition of over 100 [[Assemblies of God|Pentecostal]], [[Methodist]], and [[Baptist]] parishes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsweek.com/castros-continue-shut-churches-cuba-421785|title=The Castros Continue to Shut Churches in Cuba|last=Bandow|first=Doug|date=1 February 2016|publisher=[[Newsweek]]|language=English|accessdate=5 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===East Germany===
{{main|Christianity in East Germany|New states of Germany#Religion}}
[[East Germany]] was an atheist state.&lt;ref&gt;Compare: [http://national.deseretnews.com/article/2672/25-years-after-berlin-walls-fall-faith-still-fragile-in-former-east-germany.html Deseret News National] "During the decades of state-sponsored atheism in East Germany, more formally known as the German Democratic Republic, the great emphasis was on avoiding religion."&lt;/ref&gt;
{{As of | 2012}} the area of the former German Democratic Republic was the least religious region in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.focus.de/politik/videos/ostdeutschland-hochburg-der-atheisten-als-pfarrer-in-einer-der-gottlosesten-regionen-der-welt_vid_33747.html|title= Ostdeutschland: Wo der Atheist zu Hause ist|year= 2012|publisher= [[Focus (German magazine)|''Focus'']]|accessdate= 2017-11-11 | quote = 52 Prozent der Menschen in Ostdeutschland sind laut einer aktuellen Studie Atheisten. Das ist ein globaler Spitzenwert.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="godless2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldcrunch.com/why-eastern-germany-most-godless-place-planet/culture-society/why-eastern-germany-is-the-most-godless-place-on-earth/c3s5177/#.UHNiqk3Ex_0|title= WHY EASTERN GERMANY IS THE MOST GODLESS PLACE ON EARTH|year= 2012|publisher= ''[[Die Welt]]''|accessdate= 2009-05-24|deadurl= yes|archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20120826093254/http://www.worldcrunch.com/why-eastern-germany-most-godless-place-planet/culture-society/why-eastern-germany-is-the-most-godless-place-on-earth/c3s5177/#.UHNiqk3Ex_0|archivedate= 2012-08-26|df= }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="atheistic2"&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://www.dialoginternational.com/dialog_international/2012/05/east-germany-the-most-atheistic-of-any-region.html
|title= East Germany the "most atheistic" of any region|year= 2012
|publisher= Dialog International|accessdate = 2009-05-24
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===North Korea===
{{location map+|North Korea|caption = Reeducation camps in North Korea (10 out of around 15 – 20)|float=right|width=|places={{location map~|North Korea|label= [[Kaechon concentration camp|Kaechon]]|position=bottom| lat=39.708276  | long=125.923276|region=KP-02}}{{location map~|North Korea|label= [[Chongori concentration camp|Chongori]]|position=left| lat=42.209925  | long=129.753658|region=KP-09}}{{location map~|North Korea|label= [[Sinuiju concentration camp|Sinuiju]]| position=right | lat=40.06138  | long=124.410145|region=KP-03 }}{{location map~|North Korea|label= [[Kangdong concentration camp|Kangdong]] | position=right | lat=39.0087801  | long=126.1536884|region=KP-01 }}{{location map~|North Korea|label= [[Danchon concentration camp|Danchon]]| position=left | lat=40.9  | long=128.8|region=KP-08 }}{{location map~|North Korea|label= [[Oro concentration camp|Oro]] | position=top | lat=40.02  | long=127.46|region=KP-08 }}{{location map~|North Korea|label= [[Hoeryong reeducation camp|Hoeryong]] | position=left | lat=42.7  | long=129.8|region=KP-09 }}{{location map~|North Korea|label= [[Hamhung concentration camp|Hamhung]] | position=right | lat=39.9  | long=127.53|region=KP-08 }}{{location map~|North Korea|label= [[Chungsan concentration camp|Chungsan]] | position=bottom | lat=39.1  | long=125.37|region=KP-02 }}{{location map~|North Korea|label= [[Yongdam concentration camp|Yongdam]] | position=right | lat=39.36  | long=127.26|region=KP-07 }}}}
{{main|Religion in North Korea|Freedom of religion in North Korea|Irreligion in North Korea}}
Although the [[Constitution of North Korea|North Korean constitution]] states that freedom of religion is permitted,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.korea-np.co.jp/pk/061st_issue/98091708.htm DPRK's Socialist Constitution (Full Text)]&lt;/ref&gt; free religious activities no longer exist in North Korea, because the government sponsors religious groups only to create an illusion of religious freedom.&lt;ref name=USCIRF&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uscirf.gov/countries-and-issues/east-asia/countries-particular-concern-democratic-peoples-republic-korea|title=Countries of Particular Concern: Democratic People's Republic of Korea|publisher=[[United States Commission on International Religious Freedom]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/english/docs/2004/07/08/nkorea9040.htm|title=Human Rights in North Korea (DPRK: The Democratic People's Republic of Korea) |date=7 July 2004 |publisher=Human Rights Watch}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/kn.html|title=The World Factbook|work=cia.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt; The North Korean government's [[Juche]] [[ideology]] has been described as "state-sanctioned atheism".&lt;ref name=Hertzke2006p44&gt;[[#Hertzke2006|Hertzke (2006)]]:[https://books.google.com/books?id=EkIvbxefBNsC&amp;pg=PA44 44]&lt;/ref&gt; After 1,500 churches were destroyed during the rule of [[Kim Il Sung]] from 1948 to 1994, three churches were built in [[Pyongyang]] to deflect human rights criticism.&lt;ref name=USCIRF/&gt;

The North Korean government promotes the [[cult of personality]] of [[Kim Jong-il]] and [[Kim Il-sung]], described as a [[political religion]], as well as the ''[[Juche]]'' ideology, based on [[Korean nationalism|Korean ultranationalism]], which calls on people to "avoid spiritual deference to outside influences", which was interpreted as including religion originating outside of Korea.&lt;ref name=uscirf2005&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uscirf.gov/sites/default/files/Thank%20You%20Father%20Kim%20Il%20Sung%20-%20Nov2005.pdf|title=THANK YOU FATHER KIM IL SUNG|publisher=U.S. Commission on International Religious Freedom |date=Nov 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Temperman" /&gt;

North Korea has been designated a "country of particular concern" by the U.S. State Department since 2001 due to its religious freedom violations.&lt;ref name=uscirf2010&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uscirf.gov/sites/default/files/resources/ar2010/northkorea2010.pdf|title=The Democratic People's Republic of Korea - USCIRF Annual Report|year=2010|publisher=United States Commission on International Religious Freedom}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uscirf.gov/news-room/press-releases/north-korea-must-be-held-accountable-its-abysmal-human-rights-record|title=North Korea Must be Held Accountable for its Abysmal Human Rights Record|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinal]] [[Nicolas Cheong Jin-suk]] has said that, "There's no knowledge of priests surviving persecution that came in the late forties, when 166 priests and religious were killed or kidnapped," which includes the Roman Catholic [[bishop of Pyongyang]], [[Francis Hong Yong-ho]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.30giorni.it/us/articolo.asp?id=10278|title=30Giorni - Korea, for a reconciliation between North and South (Interview with Cardinal Nicholas Cheong Jinsuk by Gianni Cardinale)|work=30giorni.it|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071023151637/http://www.30giorni.it/us/articolo.asp?id=10278|archivedate=2007-10-23|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On November 2013, the repression against religious people led to the public execution of 80 people, some of them for possessing [[Bible]]s.&lt;ref name=uscirf2005/&gt;&lt;ref name=uscirf2010/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Fox News]], November 11, 2013. "[http://www.foxnews.com/world/2013/11/11/north-korea-publicly-executes-80-for-crimes-like-watching-films-owning-bible/ North Korea publicly executes 80, some for videos or Bibles, report says]"&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mongolia===
In the [[Mongolian People's Republic]], after the invasion by Japanese troops of 1936, the Soviet Union deployed its troops in 1937, undertaking an offensive against the Buddhist religion. In parallel, a Soviet-style purge campaign was launched in the Communist Party and the Mongolian army. The Mongol leader at that time was Khorloogiin Choibalsan, follower of Joseph Stalin, who emulated many of the policies that Stalin developed in the Soviet Union. The purges succeeded in virtually eliminating Lamaism and cost an estimated thirty to thirty-five thousand lives.{{citation needed|date=August 2017}}

===Vietnam===
Officially, the [[Socialist Republic of Vietnam]] is an atheist state as declared by its [[Communist Party of Vietnam|communist government]].&lt;ref name="Guides2015"&gt;{{cite book|author=Rough Guides|title=The Rough Guide to Vietnam|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IuDtBgAAQBAJ|year=2015|publisher=Rough Guides|isbn=978-0-241-21409-1|at=Religion and beliefs|quote=After 1975, the Marxist-Leninist government of reunified Vietnam declared the state atheist, ...}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Non-Marxist-Leninist states==
===Revolutionary Mexico===
{{See also|Plutarco Elías Calles|Calles Law|Cristero War}}

Articles 3, 5, 24, 27, and 130 of the Mexican Constitution of 1917 as originally enacted were anticlerical and restricted religious freedoms.&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu"&gt;Soberanes Fernandez, Jose Luis, [http://lawreview.byu.edu/archives/2002/2/Sob12.pdf Mexico and the 1981 United Nations Declaration on the Elimination of All Forms of Intolerance and of Discrimination Based on Religion or Belief], pp. 437-438 nn. 7-8, BYU Law Review, June 2002&lt;/ref&gt; At first the anticlerical provisions were seldom enforced, but when President [[Plutarco Elías Calles]] took office in 1924, he enforced the provisions strictly.&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu"/&gt; Calles' Mexico has been characterized as an atheist state&lt;ref&gt;Haas, Ernst B., [https://books.google.com/books?id=ldKJ_Re6p8AC&amp;pg Nationalism, Liberalism, and Progress: The dismal fate of new nations], Cornell Univ. Press 2000&lt;/ref&gt; and his program as being one to eradicate religion in Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;Cronon, E. David "American Catholics and Mexican Anticlericalism, 1933-1936,", pp. 205-208, Mississippi Valley Historical Review, XLV, Sept. 1948&lt;/ref&gt;

All religions had their properties expropriated, and these became part of government wealth. There was an expulsion of foreign clergy and the seizure of Church properties.&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ilstu.edu/class/hist263/docs/1917const.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2007-03-03 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070303014932/http://www.ilstu.edu/class/hist263/docs/1917const.html |archivedate=2007-03-03 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 27 prohibited any future acquisition of such property by the churches, and prohibited religious corporations and ministers from 
establishing or directing primary schools.&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu" /&gt; This second prohibition was sometimes interpreted to mean that the Church could not give religious instruction to children within the churches on Sundays, seen as destroying the ability of Catholics to be educated in their own religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myheritage.es/FP/newsItem.php?s=114433561&amp;newsID=68&amp;sourceList=dir|title=THE DECLINE AND FALL OF THE MARTIN-DEL-CAMPOs Part II|publisher=[http://www.myheritage.es myheritage.es]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- see also http://toolserver.org/~dcoetzee/duplicationdetector/compare.php?url1=http%3A%2F%2Fen.wikipedia.org%2Fw%2Findex.php%3Ftitle%3DState_atheism&amp;url2=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.nairaland.com%2F723007%2Ftai-solarin-life-ideas-accomplishments%2F2&amp;minwords=2&amp;minchars=13 --&gt;

The Constitution of 1917 also forbade the existence of monastic orders (article 5) and any religious activity outside of church buildings (now owned by the government), and mandated that such religious activity would be overseen by the government (article 24).&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu"/&gt;

On June 14, 1926, President Calles enacted [[anticlerical]] legislation known formally as The Law Reforming the Penal Code and unofficially as the [[Calles Law]].&lt;ref name="Joes, Anthony James p. 70"&gt;Joes, Anthony James [https://books.google.com/books?id=buHXFDFdeoQC&amp;pg=PA70&amp;dq=plutarco+calles+anticatholic&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=fnPEry3_KKxtgC6IdVhGGh8lMG8#PPA70,M1 Resisting Rebellion: The History And Politics of Counterinsurgency] p. 70, (2006 University Press of Kentucky) {{ISBN|0-8131-9170-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;   His [[anti-Catholic]] actions included outlawing religious orders, depriving the Church of property rights and depriving the clergy of civil liberties, including their right to a trial by jury (in cases involving anti-clerical laws) and the right to vote.&lt;ref name="Joes, Anthony James p. 70"/&gt;&lt;ref name="THE CRISTERO REBELLION - PART 1"&gt;Tuck, Jim [http://www.mexconnect.com/mex_/history/jtuck/jtcristero1.html THE CRISTERO REBELLION – PART 1] Mexico Connect 1996&lt;/ref&gt; Catholic antipathy towards Calles was enhanced because of his vocal atheism.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"&gt;{{cite book
|title=Mexico's New Politics
|author=David A. Shirk
|year=2005
|publisher=[[Lynne Rienner Publishers]]
|isbn=1-58826-270-7
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WOBRb0wKpocC&amp;pg=PA58&amp;lpg=PA58&amp;dq
}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was also a [[Catholicism and Freemasonry|Freemason]].&lt;ref&gt;Denslow, William R. [https://books.google.com/books?id=dmPato81X9sC&amp;pg=PA171&amp;dq=plutarco+calles+freemason&amp;sig=NsSB9-6KQUn50HmpBT8eh9nx3No 10,000 Famous Freemasons] p. 171 (2004
Kessinger Publishing){{ISBN|1-4179-7578-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Regarding this period, recent President [[Vicente Fox]] stated, "After 1917, Mexico was led by anti-Catholic Freemasons who tried to evoke the anticlerical spirit of popular indigenous President [[Benito Juárez]] of the 1880s. But the military dictators of the 1920s were a more savage lot than Juarez."&lt;ref&gt;Fox, Vicente and Rob Allyn [https://books.google.com/books?id=bLDDf9vi-esC&amp;dq Revolution of Hope] p. 17, Viking, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Cristeroscolgados.jpg|thumb|250px|Cristeros hanged in [[Jalisco]].]]
Due to the strict enforcement of anti-clerical laws, people in strongly [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] states, especially [[Jalisco]], [[Zacatecas]], [[Guanajuato]], [[Colima]] and [[Michoacán]], began to oppose him, and this opposition led to the [[Cristero War]] from 1926 to 1929, which was characterized by brutal atrocities on both sides. Some Cristeros applied terrorist tactics, while the Mexican government persecuted the clergy, killing suspected Cristeros and supporters and often retaliating against innocent individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/Plutarco_Elias_Calles.aspx Calles, Plutarco Elías] The Columbia Encyclopedia, Sixth Edition. 2001–05 Columbia University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; On May 28, 1926, Calles was awarded a medal of merit from the head of Mexico's Scottish rite of Freemasonry for his actions against the Catholics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.storialibera.it/epoca_contemporanea/messico_1926-1929/articolo.php?id=508 The Cristeros: 20th century Mexico's Catholic uprising, from The Angelus, January 2002, Volume XXV, Number 1] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090903020244/http://www.storialibera.it/epoca_contemporanea/messico_1926-1929/articolo.php?id=508 |date=2009-09-03 }} by Olivier LELIBRE, [[The Angelus (magazine)|The Angelus]]&lt;/ref&gt;

A truce was negotiated with the assistance of U.S. Ambassador [[Dwight Whitney Morrow]].&lt;ref name="Blood Drenched Altars"&gt;Van Hove, Brian [http://www.ewtn.com/library/HOMELIBR/FR94204.TXT Blood Drenched Altars] 1996 EWTN&lt;/ref&gt; Calles, however, did not abide by the terms of the truce – in violation of its terms, he had approximately 500 Cristero leaders and 5,000 other Cristeros shot, frequently in their homes in front of their spouses and children.&lt;ref name="Blood Drenched Altars"/&gt; Particularly offensive to Catholics after the supposed truce was Calles' insistence on a complete state monopoly on education, suppressing all Catholic education and introducing "socialist" education in its place: "We must enter and take possession of the mind of childhood, the mind of youth.".&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"&gt;Van Hove, Brian [http://www.ewtn.com/library/HOMELIBR/FR94204.TXT Blood-Drenched Altars] Faith &amp; Reason 1994&lt;/ref&gt; The persecution continued as Calles maintained control under his [[Maximato]] and did not relent until 1940, when President [[Manuel Ávila Camacho]], a believing Catholic, took office.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"/&gt; This attempt to indoctrinate the youth in atheism was begun in 1934 by amending Article 3 to the [[Mexican Constitution]] to eradicate religion by mandating "socialist education", which "in addition to removing all religious doctrine" would "combat fanaticism and prejudices", "build[ing] in the youth a rational and exact concept of the universe and of social life".&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu"/&gt; In 1946 this "socialist education" was removed from the constitution and the document returned to the less egregious generalized secular education.
The effects of the war on the Church were profound. Between 1926 and 1934 at least 40 priests were killed.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"/&gt; Where there were 4,500 priests operating within the country before the rebellion, in 1934 there were only 334 priests licensed by the government to serve fifteen million people, the rest having been eliminated by emigration, expulsion, and assassination.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, Robert L. [https://books.google.com/books?id=8aWQ_7oKJfkC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;lpg=PA33&amp;dq=cristero+war+priests+killed&amp;source=web&amp;ots=YNDpLM2ukb&amp;sig=YWccvtnJKnSpaI15bTHCOX3zoyc#PPA33,M1 Latin America's Wars: The Age of the Caudillo, 1791–1899] p. 33 (2003
Brassey's) {{ISBN|1-57488-452-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By 1935, 17 states had no priest at all.&lt;ref&gt;Ruiz, Ramón Eduardo [https://books.google.com/books?id=AfdjWl1xKpwC&amp;pg=PA392&amp;dq=Tom%C3%A1s+Garrido+Canabal&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=HkfPtdqMt3qrdcMuprgfjnfnq60 Triumphs and Tragedy: A History of the Mexican People] p.393 (1993 W. W. Norton &amp; Company) {{ISBN|0-393-31066-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Human rights==
{{main|History of human rights}}
Article 18 of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] is designed to protect the right to freedom of thought, conscience, and religion. In 1993, the UN's human rights committee declared that article 18 of the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] "protects theistic, non-theistic and atheistic beliefs, as well as the right not to profess any religion or belief."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.minorityrights.org/3273/normative-instruments/ccpr-general-comment-22-300793-on-iccpr-article-18.html|title=CCPR General Comment 22: 30/07/93 on ICCPR Article 18|work=Minorityrights.org|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150116043952/http://www.minorityrights.org/3273/normative-instruments/ccpr-general-comment-22-300793-on-iccpr-article-18.html|archivedate=2015-01-16|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The committee further stated that "the freedom to have or to adopt a religion or belief necessarily entails the freedom to choose a religion or belief, including the right to replace one's current religion or belief with another or to adopt atheistic views." Signatories to the convention are barred from "the use of threat of physical force or penal sanctions to compel believers or non-believers" to recant their beliefs or convert.&lt;ref name=uscirf2005/&gt; Despite this, {{as of|2009|lc=on}} minority religions were still being persecuted in many parts of the world.&lt;ref name="fdih1"&gt;{{cite web |date=1 August 2003|title=Discrimination against religious minorities in Iran|author=International Federation for Human Rights|publisher=fdih.org|accessdate=3 March 2009|url=http://www.fidh.org/IMG/pdf/ir0108a.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.law2.byu.edu/lawreview/archives/2002/2/dav2.pdf|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090327185340/http://www.law2.byu.edu/lawreview/archives/2002/2/dav2.pdf|archivedate=27 March 2009|title=The Evolution of Religious Liberty as a Universal Human Right|date=6 June 2002|accessdate=3 March 2009|last=Davis|first=Derek H.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Theodore Roosevelt]] condemned the [[Kishinev pogrom]] in 1903, establishing a history of U.S. presidents commenting on the internal religious liberty of foreign countries.&lt;ref name=berkley-oval&gt;{{cite web|url=http://berkleycenter.georgetown.edu/responses/promoting-religious-freedom-from-the-oval-office|title=Responding to Religious Freedom and Presidential Leadership: A Historical Approach|publisher=[[Berkley Center for Religion, Peace, and World Affairs]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]'s 1941 State of the Union address, he outlined [[Four Freedoms]], including Freedom of worship, that would be foundation for the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, and future U.S. diplomatic efforts.&lt;ref name=berkley-oval/&gt; [[Jimmy Carter]] asked [[Deng Xiaoping]] to improve religious freedom in China, and Ronald Reagan told US Embassy staff in Moscow to help Jews harassed by the Soviet authorities.&lt;ref name=berkley-oval/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/384507/jewish/Mission-to-Russia.htm|title=Mission to Russia - A Rabbi Eulogizes President Reagan|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bill Clinton]] established the [[United States Commission on International Religious Freedom]] with the [[International Religious Freedom Act of 1998]], in order to use diplomacy to promote religious liberty in repressive states.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://berkleycenter.georgetown.edu/cornerstone/religious-freedom-and-presidential-leadership-a-historical-approach/responses/the-clinton-presidency-and-the-pivotal-era-for-religious-freedom|title=Responding to Religious Freedom and Presidential Leadership: A Historical Approach|author=Allen Hertzke|date=17 Feb 2015|publisher=[[Berkley Center for Religion, Peace, and World Affairs]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Columns-list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Antireligion]]
*[[Civil religion]]
*[[Communism and religion]]
*[[Freedom of religion]]
*[[Reign of Terror]]
*[[Religion in China]]
*[[New states of Germany#Religion|Religion in East Germany]]
*[[Religion in the Soviet Union]]
*[[Religious persecution]]
*[[Religion of Humanity]]
*[[Religion in Russia]]
*[[Militant atheism]]
*[[Scientism]]
*[[Society of the Godless]]
*[[Staatssekretär für Kirchenfragen]]
*[[War in the Vendée]]
}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{wikicite |ref="Davies1996" |reference=Davies, Norman. 1996. ''Europe: a history.'' Oxford: Oxford University Press.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Elsie2000" |reference=Elsie, Robert. 2000. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=N_IXHrXIsYkC A Dictionary of Albanian Religion, Mythology, and Folk Culture]''. C. Hurst &amp; Co. {{ISBN|978-1-85065-570-1}}.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Elsie2001" |reference=Elsie, Robert. 2001. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=aAtQZ0vjf5gC A Dictionary of Albanian Religion, Mythology, and Folk Culture]''. New York: NYU Press. {{ISBN|0-8147-2214-8}}.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=Freemont-Barnes2007 |reference=Fremont-Barnes, Gregory. 2007. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=6_2wkP4j-EsC&amp;dq Encyclopedia of the Age of Political Revolutions and New Ideologies, 1760–1815]''. Greenwood Publishing Group. {{ISBN|978-0-313-33445-0}}.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Greeley2003" |reference=Greeley, Andrew M. 2003. ''Religion in Europe at the end of the second millennium: a sociological profile''. New Brunswick, N.J.: Transaction Publishers.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=Jacques1995 |reference=Jacques, Edwin E. 1995. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=IJ2s9sQ9bGkC The Albanians: an ethnic history from prehistoric times to the present]''. McFarland. {{ISBN|978-0-89950-932-7}}.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Marx1844" |reference=[[Karl Marx|Marx, Karl]]. February, 1844. ''[http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1843/critique-hpr/intro.htm A Contribution to the Critique of Hegel's Philosophy of Right]''. Deutsch-Französische Jahrbücher.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=JonassohnBjeornson1998 |reference=Jonassohn, Kurt and Karin Solveig Bjeornson. 1998. ''Genocide and Gross Human Rights Violations''. [[Transaction Publishers]]. {{ISBN|0-7658-0417-4}}.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=McCann1997 |reference=McCann, David R. 1997. ''Korea briefing: toward reunification'', Volume 4 of Korea briefing, Asia Society Briefings Series, Asia Society Country Briefing, Briefings of the Asia Society. M.E. Sharpe. {{ISBN|978-1-56324-885-6}}}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Miner2003" |reference=Miner, Steven Merritt. 2003. ''Stalin's holy war religion, nationalism, and alliance politics, 1941–1945''. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press.}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Pospielovsky1998" |reference=Pospielovsky, Dimitry. 1935.  ''The Orthodox Church in the History of Russia'' Published 1998. St Vladimir's Seminary Press, 413 pages, {{ISBN|0-88141-179-5}}.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=Spielvogel2005 |reference=Spielvogel, Jackson. 2005. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=ni4PSpOxb6MC&amp;dq Western Civilization: Combined Volume]''. Thomson Wadsworth.}}
*{{wikicite |ref=Tallet1991 |reference=Tallet, Frank. 1991. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=aL4lsWdd-rAC&amp;dq Religion, Society and Politics in France Since 1789]''. Continuum International Publishing}}
*{{wikicite |ref="Wolak2004" |reference=Wolak, Arthur J. 2004. ''Forced out: the fate of Polish Jewry in Communist Poland''. Tucson, Ariz: Fenestra Books.}}

{{Religion and politics}}
{{Religious persecution}}
{{Irreligion}}
{{Belief systems}}
{{Portal bar|Politics|Atheism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:State Atheism}}
[[Category:Atheism]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Religion and government]]
[[Category:Religious persecution by communists]]
[[Category:Persecution by atheist states]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>