<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20100113011642|337508518" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25020034" pageid="25020034" ns="0" title="Media portrayal of LGBTQ people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-09-22T13:30:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Article issues|refimprove=November 2009|tone=November 2009|copyedit=November 2009|date=January 2010}}

'''Media portrayal of LGBT people''' ranges from positive to very negative.  Coverage has become more positive in recent years, possibly in an attempt by marketers to appeal to LGBT people.  However, LGBT people are still often portrayed negatively in television, films, and other media. The [[gay community]] is constantly battling with this negative media and overcoming [[LGBT stereotypes|stereotypes]].  

LGBT identified people look just like any other person so the media puts an image on the gay community to make it as visible as a difference in skin color.  In some pop culture, gays are purposely portrayed as overly promiscuous, flashy, or having a bold personality for entertainment's sake.  

There is currently a widespread ban of references in child-related entertainment,{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}} and when references do occur, they almost invariably generate controversy. In 1997, when American comedian [[Ellen DeGeneres]] [[coming out|came out]] of the [[closeted|closet]] on her popular sitcom, many sponsors, such as the [[Wendy's]] fast food chain, pulled their advertising.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gomestic.com/Consumer-Information/10-Unique-Facts-Regarding-the-Fast-food-Franchise-with-the-Old-fashioned-Burgers-Wendys.427675|title=10 Unique Facts Regarding the Fast-food Franchise with the Old-fashioned Burgers: Wendy’s|year=2009|work=Gomestic|publisher=Stanza Ltd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also, the media has somewhat made the gay community included and publicly accepted with television shows such as ''[[Will and Grace]]'' or ''[[Queer Eye]]''.  This increased publicity reflects with the coming-out movement of the LGBT community.  As more celebrities came out, more shows developed, such as the 2004 show ''[[The L Word]]''.  With the popularity of gay television shows, music artists, and gay fashion, the Western culture has had to open their eyes to the gay community.  

In the United States, gay people are frequently used as a symbol of social decadence by celebrity evangelists and by organizations such as [[Focus on the Family]]. 

In [[Québec]], ''RG Magazine'' was a major defender of LGBT causes for some 30 years.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

==News coverage of LGBT events==
Much of the negative media that surrounds the gay community has to do with [[pride parades]] that turn into [[drag queen|drag shows]] or [[riots]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}  Opposition argues that such degrees of sexuality and nudity in public is not appropriate.  News stories have typically identified the opposition to these demonstrations as lead by [[Christian]] conservatives and not political figures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishnews.com/appnews/540/5860/2008/8/4/594333_353231713890GayPride.html Gay Pride parade attracts thousands.  The Irish News.  April 4, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Marketing to the LGBT community==
The community has been targeted by marketers who view LGBT people as an untapped source of [[Disposable income|discretionary income]], as many couples have a dual income with no children. 

As companies are advertising more and more to the gay community, LGBT activists are using ad slogans to promote gay community views.  [[Subaru]] marketed its Forester and Outback with the slogan "It's Not a Choice. It's the Way We're Built" which was later used in eight U.S. cities on streets or in gay rights events.&lt;ref&gt;Fetto, John.  In Broad Daylight - Marketing to the gay community - Brief Article.  BNet.  Feb. 2001.  [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m4021/is_ISSN_0163-4089/ai_75171025/]&lt;/ref&gt;

==LGBT media advocacy organizations==
Many LGBT organizations exist to represent and defend the gay community. For example, the [[Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation]] in the United States and [[Stonewall (UK)|Stonewall]] in the UK work with the media to help portray fair and accurate images of the gay community.

==See also==
* [[Media portrayal of lesbianism]]
* [[List of media portrayals of bisexuality]]
* [[List of transgender characters in film and television]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Media Portrayal Of Lgbt People}}
[[Category:LGBT portrayals in media| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>