<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20120807144724|506239152" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25020034" pageid="25020034" ns="0" title="Media portrayal of LGBTQ people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-09-29T14:55:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=May 2011}}

'''Media portrayal of LGBT people''' ranges from positive to very negative. The [[gay community]] is constantly battling with the negative image and trying to overcome [[LGBT stereotypes|stereotypes]] in television, films and other media.  However, coverage has become more positive in recent years, possibly in an attempt by marketers to appeal to [[LGBT]] people.

==Overview==
Because [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[Bisexuality|bisexual]] and [[transgender]] people look just like anyone else, the media often adds images to make the gay community as visible as a difference in skin color.  In many forms of popular entertainment, gays are portrayed as overly promiscuous, flashy and incredibly bold.  

There is currently a widespread view that reference to gays should be omitted from child-related entertainment. When such references do occur they almost invariably generate controversy. In 1997, when American comedian [[Ellen DeGeneres]] [[coming out|came out]] of the [[closeted|closet]] on her popular [[sitcom]], many sponsors, such as the [[Wendy's]] fast food chain, pulled their advertising.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gomestic.com/Consumer-Information/10-Unique-Facts-Regarding-the-Fast-food-Franchise-with-the-Old-fashioned-Burgers-Wendys.427675|title=10 Unique Facts Regarding the Fast-food Franchise with the Old-fashioned Burgers: Wendy’s|year=2009|work=Gomestic|publisher=Stanza Ltd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Media has hurt the LGBT community but also helped them.  Milestones to the gay community such as the book "Vice Versa" and [[Ellen DeGeneres]] [[coming out]] has helped other LGBT come out and feel better about being themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url=http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=2Kc46h0Nu6IC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR13&amp;dq=medias+protrayal+of+gays+and+lesbians&amp;ots=XBW8Ssx0PR&amp;sig=QFTvaOQIU2O52SPN7LdWU1IV95I#v=onepage&amp;q=medias%20protrayal%20of%20gays%20and%20lesbians&amp;f=false Up From Invisibility: Lesbians, Gay men, And The Media in America: Larry Gross|year=2001|publisher=Columbia University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the stereotypical depictions of gays, the media has at times promoted acceptance of gays with television shows such as ''[[Will and Grace]]'' and ''[[Queer Eye]]''.  This increased publicity reflects the coming-out movement of the LGBT community.  As more celebrities come out, more gay-friendly shows develop, such as the 2004 show ''[[The L Word]]''.  With the popularity of gay television shows, music artists and gay fashion, Western culture has had to open its eyes to the gay community.  

This new acceptance from the media can partially be explained by the [[contact hypothesis]], aka inter group contact theory.  With more shows promoting the acceptance of gays, people are able to view a more correct depiction of the LGBT community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book}}|url=http://digitalarchive.gsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1015&amp;context=univ_lib_ura&amp;sei-redir=1&amp;referer=http%3A%2F%2Fscholar.google.com%2Fscholar%3Fhl%3Den%26q%3Dmedia%2527s%2Bportrayal%2Bof%2Blgbt%26btnG%3DSearch%26as_sdt%3D0%252C18%26as_ylo%3D%26as_vis%3D1#search=%22medias%20portrayal%20lgbt%22 Media's Portrayal of Homosexuality as a Reflection of Cultural Acceptance: Austin Thomas Rowe|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, gay people are frequently used as a symbol of social decadence by celebrity evangelists and by organizations such as [[Focus on the Family]]. 

In [[Québec]], ''RG Magazine'' was a major defender of LGBT causes for some 30 years.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

==News coverage of LGBT events==
Much of the negative media that surrounds the gay community has to do with [[pride parade]]s that turn into [[drag queen|drag shows]] or [[riots]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}  Opposition argues that such degrees of sexuality and nudity in public is not appropriate.  News stories have typically identified the opposition to these demonstrations as led by [[Christian]] conservatives and not political figures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishnews.com/appnews/540/5860/2008/8/4/594333_353231713890GayPride.html Gay Pride parade attracts thousands.  The Irish News.  April 4, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these views against LGBT's is [[symbolic racism]].  People's arguments against their nudity in public because it violates their traditional values.

==Marketing to the LGBT community==
The gay community has been targeted by marketers who view LGBT people as an untapped source of [[Disposable and discretionary income|discretionary spending]], as many couples have two income streams and no children. As a result, companies are advertising more and more to the gay community, and LGBT activists use advertisement slogans to promote gay community views.  [[Subaru]] marketed its "Forester" and "Outback" models with the slogan "It's not a choice. It's the way we're built" which was later used in eight United States cities on streets or in gay rights events.&lt;ref&gt;Fetto, John. In Broad Daylight - Marketing to the gay community - Brief Article. BNet. Feb. 2001. [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m4021/is_ISSN_0163-4089/ai_75171025/]&lt;/ref&gt;

==LGBT media advocacy organizations==
Many LGBT organizations exist to represent and defend the gay community. For example, the [[Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation]] in the United States and [[Stonewall (UK)|Stonewall]] in the UK work with the media to help portray fair and accurate images of the gay community. There are many other LGBT advocacy organizations in the United States that are all working for the same cause, equality. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://queersunited.blogspot.com/2008/07/listing-of-lgbt-advocacy-organizations.html |title=Queers United: The activist blog uniting the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, Queer, Intersexual, Asexual community &amp; Allies in the fight for equality |deadurl=no |accessdate=4 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Media portrayal of lesbianism]]
* [[List of media portrayals of bisexuality]]
* [[List of transgender characters in film and television]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Media Portrayal Of Lgbt People}}
[[Category:LGBT portrayals in media| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>