<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20140929212146|627597928" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25020034" pageid="25020034" ns="0" title="Media portrayal of LGBTQ people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-21T04:24:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{refimprove|date=May 2011}}
{{Cleanup-rewrite|it is written in a highly informal and subjective manner|date=March 2014}}
}}

'''Media portrayal of LGBT people''' ranges from positive to very negative. The [[LGBT community]] is constantly battling with the negative image and trying to overcome [[LGBT stereotypes|stereotypes]] in television, films and other media.  However, coverage has become more positive in recent years, possibly in an attempt by marketers to appeal to [[LGBT]] people. Representation of transgender characters has increased in the last ten years, now including reoccurring transgender characters in popular shows such as ''[[Grey's Anatomy]]'', ''[[Degrassi]]'', ''[[Ugly Betty]]'', ''[[Orange is the New Black]]'' and ''[[Glee (TV series)|Glee]]''.

==Overview==
Because [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]] and [[transgender]] people look just like anyone else, the media often adds images to make the gay community as visible as a difference in skin color.  In many forms of popular entertainment, gay men are portrayed as overly promiscuous, flashy and incredibly bold.

Gay and lesbian families are commonly misunderstood because society equates sexual orientation with the ability to reproduce. Gay and lesbian, even in the movies, are usually not the main characters. They most of the time fall into the stereotyped supporting characters or portrayed as a victim or villain.&lt;ref&gt;{{Mazur, M. A., &amp; Emmers-Sommer, T. M. (2002). The Effect of Movie Portrayals on Audience Attitudes about Nontraditional Families and Sexual Orientation. Journal Of Homosexuality, 44(1), 157-179. doi:10.1300/J082v44n0109}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is currently a widespread view that reference to gay people should be omitted from child-related entertainment. When such references do occur they almost invariably generate controversy. In 1997, when American comedian [[Ellen DeGeneres]] [[coming out|came out]] of the [[closeted|closet]] on her popular [[sitcom]], many sponsors, such as the [[Wendy's]] fast food chain, pulled their advertising.{{Citation needed|date=March 2014}}

Media has hurt the LGBT community but also helped them.  Milestones to the gay community such as the book "Vice Versa" and [[Ellen DeGeneres]] [[coming out]] has helped other LGBT come out and feel better about being themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url=http://books.google.com/?id=2Kc46h0Nu6IC&amp;pg=PR13&amp;dq=medias+protrayal+of+gays+and+lesbians#v=onepage&amp;q=medias%20protrayal%20of%20gays%20and%20lesbians&amp;f=false|title=Up From Invisibility: Lesbians, Gay men, And The Media in America|author=Larry Gross|year=2001|publisher=Columbia University Press| isbn=9780231119535}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the stereotypical depictions of gay people, the media has at times promoted acceptance of them with television shows such as ''[[Will and Grace]]'' and ''[[Queer Eye]]''.  This increased publicity reflects the coming-out movement of the LGBT community.  As more celebrities come out, more gay-friendly shows develop, such as the 2004 show ''[[The L Word]]''.  With the popularity of gay television shows, music artists and gay fashion, Western culture has had to open its eyes to the gay community.

This new acceptance from the media can partially be explained by the [[contact hypothesis]], aka inter group contact theory.  With more shows promoting the acceptance of gays, people are able to view a more correct depiction of the LGBT community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://digitalarchive.gsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1015&amp;context=univ_lib_ura&amp;sei-redir=1&amp;referer=http%3A%2F%2Fscholar.google.com%2Fscholar%3Fhl%3Den%26q%3Dmedia%2527s%2Bportrayal%2Bof%2Blgbt%26btnG%3DSearch%26as_sdt%3D0%252C18%26as_ylo%3D%26as_vis%3D1#search=%22medias%20portrayal%20lgbt%22|title=Media's Portrayal of Homosexuality as a Reflection of Cultural Acceptance|author=Austin Thomas Rowe|year=2010|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, gay people are frequently used as a symbol of social decadence by celebrity evangelists and by organizations such as [[Focus on the Family]].

In [[Québec]], ''RG Magazine'' was a major defender of LGBT causes for some 30 years.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

==News coverage of LGBT events==
Much of the negative media that surrounds the gay community has to do with [[pride parade]]s that turn into [[drag queen|drag shows]] or [[riots]]. There is very little positive media coverage, however there is some. Some examples of positive coverage is marches for same-sex marriage and shows like ellen and ru'pauls drag race. Both shows express successful LGBT.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}  Opposition argues that such degrees of sexuality and nudity in public is not appropriate. Although, lately there has been more shows to show lesbian and gay sexuality. Generally, News stories have typically identified the opposition to these demonstrations as led by [[Christian]] conservatives or strong believers of the Islamic religion and not political figures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irishnews.com/appnews/540/5860/2008/8/4/594333_353231713890GayPride.html|title=Gay Pride parade attracts thousands|work=The Irish News|date=April 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these views against LGBT's is [[symbolic racism]].  People's arguments against their nudity in public because it violates their traditional values.

==Marketing to the LGBT community==
The gay community has been targeted by marketers who view LGBT people as an untapped source of [[Disposable and discretionary income|discretionary spending]], as many couples have two income streams and no children. As a result, companies are advertising more and more to the gay community, and LGBT activists use advertisement slogans to promote gay community views.  [[Subaru]] marketed its "Forester" and "Outback" models with the slogan "It's not a choice. It's the way we're built" which was later used in eight United States cities on streets or in gay rights events.&lt;ref&gt;Fetto, John. In Broad Daylight - Marketing to the gay community - Brief Article. BNet. Feb. 2001. [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m4021/is_ISSN_0163-4089/ai_75171025/]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Media Portrayal of LGBT People of Color==
Overwhelmingly, the portrayal of the LGBT community in the American media centers on white LGBTs and their experiences. LGBT persons of color are severely underrepresented in the media in comparison to their actual population within the community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theroot.com/articles/culture/2012/03/lgbt_people_of_color_representation_on_tv_and_in_movies_needs_to_improve.html |title=More Representation for LGBT People of Color |deadurl=no |accessdate=27 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Breakdown of LGBT Representation==
Over the past five years there has been an increase in the number of regular and recurring LGBT characters in mainstream American media. &lt;ref&gt;[http://issuu.com/glaad/docs/wwatv14_16_optimized/24]&lt;/ref&gt; Each population has experienced general growth in representation, some more than others. Gay characters are the most frequently depicted of the LGBT community by a wide margin, followed by lesbian, bisexual, and transgender characters. However, heading into the new season, this trend will change in cable television with the number of bisexual identifying characters surpassing the number of lesbian characters for the first time. Additionally, the transgender community is the only one of the four to lose representation in media, declining from 2013 to 2014 on cable networks while losing representation entirely on broadcast networks. &lt;ref&gt;[http://issuu.com/glaad/docs/wwatv14_16_optimized/26]&lt;/ref&gt; In terms of [[Gender identity|gender identity]], a majority of the LGBT characters in media are male, though female characters follow within a close margin. Only one percent of characters identified as FtM ([[Trans man|Female-to-Male transgender]]). &lt;ref&gt;[http://issuu.com/glaad/docs/wwatv14_16_optimized/14]&lt;/ref&gt;

==LGBT media advocacy organizations==
Many LGBT organizations exist to represent and defend the gay community. For example, the [[Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation]] in the United States and [[Stonewall (UK)|Stonewall]] in the UK work with the media to help portray fair and accurate images of the gay community. There are many other LGBT advocacy organizations in the United States that are all working for the same cause, equality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://queersunited.blogspot.com/2008/07/listing-of-lgbt-advocacy-organizations.html |title=Queers United: The activist blog uniting the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, Queer, Intersexual, Asexual community &amp; Allies in the fight for equality |deadurl=no |accessdate=4 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Media portrayal of lesbianism]]
* [[List of media portrayals of bisexuality]]
* [[List of transgender characters in film and television]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Media Portrayal Of Lgbt People}}
[[Category:LGBT portrayals in media| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>