<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181121035602|869905345" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="43097" pageid="43097" ns="0" title="Gender dysphoria"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-21T03:57:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp|small=yes}}
{{Infobox medical condition (new)
| name            = Gender dysphoria
| synonyms        = Gender identity disorder
| symptoms        = Distress related to one's assigned gender or sex&lt;ref name="DSM-5 fact sheet" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Standards of Care" /&gt;
| complications   = Eating disorders, suicide, depression, anxiety, social isolation&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;
| onset           = 
| duration        = 
| causes          = 
| risks           = 
| diagnosis       = 
| differential    = Variance in gender identity or expression that is not distressing&lt;ref name="DSM-5 fact sheet" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Standards of Care" /&gt;
| prevention      = 
| treatment       = [[Transitioning (transgender)|Transitioning]], [[psychotherapy]]&lt;ref name="Standards of Care" /&gt;
| medication      = [[Transgender hormone therapy|Hormones]] (e.g., [[anabolic steroid|androgens]], [[antiandrogen]]s, [[estrogen (medication)|estrogens]])
| prognosis       = 
| frequency       = 
| deaths          = 
}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}
'''Gender dysphoria''' ('''GD''') is the distress a person experiences as a result of the [[sex]] and [[gender]] they were [[Sex assignment|assigned at birth]]. In this case, the assigned sex and gender do not match the person's [[gender identity]], and the person is [[transgender]]. Evidence from twin studies suggest that people who identify with a gender different from their assigned sex may experience such distress not only due to psychological or behavioral causes, but also biological ones related to their genetics or exposure to hormones before birth.&lt;ref name="etiology"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Heylens G, De Cuypere G, Zucker KJ, Schelfaut C, Elaut E, Vanden Bossche H, De Baere E, T'Sjoen G | title = Gender identity disorder in twins: a review of the case report literature | journal = The Journal of Sexual Medicine | volume = 9 | issue = 3| pages = 751–7 | date = March 2012 | pmid = 22146048 | doi = 10.1111/j.1743-6109.2011.02567.x | author3-link = Kenneth Zucker }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The diagnostic label '''gender identity disorder''' ('''GID''')&lt;!--NOTE: Per WP:Alternative title, the term should be bolded somewhere in the lead.--&gt; was used by the [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders|DSM]] until its reclassification as ''gender dysphoria'' in 2013, with the release of the [[DSM-5]]. The diagnosis was reclassified to better align it with medical understanding of the condition and to remove the [[Stigmatization|stigma]] associated with the term ''disorder''.&lt;ref name="recommendations"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Fraser |first=L |last2=Karasic |first2=D |last3=Meyer |first3=W |last4=Wylie |first4=K |title=Recommendations for Revision of the DSM Diagnosis of Gender Identity Disorder in Adults |journal=International Journal of Transgenderism |year=2010 |volume=12 |pages=80–85 |doi=10.1080/15532739.2010.509202 |issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Karl Bryant"&gt;{{cite web|first=Karl|last=Bryant|title=Gender Dysphoria |publisher=[[Encyclopædia Britannica Online]] |date=2018|access-date=August 16, 2018|url=https://www.britannica.com/science/gender-dysphoria}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Psychiatric Association]], publisher of the DSM-5, stated that [[gender nonconformity]] is not the same thing as gender dysphoria,&lt;ref name="What Is"&gt;{{cite web |title=What Is Gender Dysphoria? |publisher=[[American Psychiatric Publishing]] | access-date=November 20, 2018|url=https://www.psychiatry.org/patients-families/gender-dysphoria/what-is-gender-dysphoria}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that "gender nonconformity is not in itself a mental disorder. The critical element of gender dysphoria is the presence of clinically significant distress associated with the condition."&lt;ref name="DSM-5 fact sheet"&gt;{{cite web |title=Gender Dysphoria |publisher=[[American Psychiatric Publishing]] | access-date=December 24, 2016|url=https://www.psychiatry.org/File%20Library/Psychiatrists/Practice/DSM/APA_DSM-5-Gender-Dysphoria.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some transgender people and researchers support declassification of the condition because they say the diagnosis pathologizes gender variance and reinforces the [[Gender binary|binary model of gender]].&lt;ref name="recommendations"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Newman |first=L |title=Sex, Gender and Culture: Issues in the Definition, Assessment and Treatment of Gender Identity Disorder |journal=Clinical Child Psychology and Psychiatry |date=July 1, 2002 |volume=7 |pages=352–359 |doi=10.1177/1359104502007003004 |issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The main [[psychiatric]] approaches to treatment for persons diagnosed with gender dysphoria are [[psychotherapy]] or supporting the individual's preferred gender through [[hormone therapy]], gender expression and role, or surgery.&lt;ref name="Standards of Care"&gt;{{cite journal |year=2011 |title=Standards of Care for the Health of Transsexual, Transgender, and Gender-Nonconforming People, Version 7 |url=http://www.wpath.org/uploaded_files/140/files/IJT%20SOC,%20V7.pdf |journal=International Journal of Transgenderism |publisher=Routledge Taylor &amp; Francis Group |volume=13 |issue=4 |pages=165–232 |doi=10.1080/15532739.2011.700873 |access-date=August 30, 2014 |deadurl=yes |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140802135807/http://www.wpath.org/uploaded_files/140/files/IJT%20SOC%2C%20V7.pdf |archive-date=August 2, 2014 |df= |author=Coleman E}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Signs and symptoms ==
Symptoms of GD in children may include any of the following: disgust at their own genitalia, [[social isolation]] from their peers, [[anxiety (mood)|anxiety]], loneliness and [[Depression (mood)|depression]].&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite book |title=A Nurse's Guide to Women's Mental Health |last=Davidson |first=Michelle R. |publisher=Springer Publishing Company |year=2012 |isbn=0-8261-7113-3 |page=114}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[American Psychological Association]], transgender children are more likely to experience harassment and violence in school, foster care, residential treatment centers, homeless centers and juvenile justice programs than other children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Ansara |first1=Y. Gavriel |last2=Hegarty |first2=Peter |title=Cisgenderism in psychology: pathologising and misgendering children from 1999 to 2008 |journal=Psychology and Sexuality |volume=3 |issue=2 |year=2012 |pages=137–60 |doi=10.1080/19419899.2011.576696}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Adults with GD are at increased risk for stress, isolation, anxiety, depression, poor self-esteem and suicide.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Studies indicate that transgender people have an extremely high rate of suicide attempts; one study of 6,450 transgender people in the United States found 41% had attempted [[suicide]], compared to a national average of 1.6%. It was also found that suicide attempts were less common among transgender people who said their family ties had remained strong after they came out, but even transgender people at comparatively low risk were still much more likely to have attempted suicide than the general population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Grant |last2=Jaime |first2=M. |last3=Mottet |first3=Lisa |last4=Tanis |first4=Justin |last5=Harrison |first5=Jack |last6=Herman |first6=Jody |last7=Keisling |first7=Mara |title=Injustice at Every Turn: A Report of the National Transgender  Discrimination Survey |date=2011 |publisher=National Center for Transgender Equality and National Gay and Lesbian Task Force |location=Washington |url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/static_html/downloads/reports/reports/ntds_full.pdf |access-date=May 10, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Reyes |first1=Emily |title=Transgender study looks at 'exceptionally high' suicide-attempt rate |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2014/jan/28/local/la-me-ln-suicide-attempts-alarming-transgender-20140127 |access-date=May 10, 2015 |work=Los Angeles Times |date=January 28, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people are also at heightened risk for certain [[mental disorder]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Mentoring sexual orientation and gender identity minorities in a university setting |last=O'Keefe |first=CarolynAnne |publisher=ProQuest Dissertations &amp; Theses (PQDT) |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-542-91311-2 |location=California |page=xvi}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as [[eating disorder]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Diemer EW, Grant JD, Munn-Chernoff MA, Patterson DA, Duncan AE | title = Gender Identity, Sexual Orientation, and Eating-Related Pathology in a National Sample of College Students | journal = The Journal of Adolescent Health | volume = 57 | issue = 2 | pages = 144–9 | date = August 2015 | pmid = 25937471 | pmc = 4545276 | doi = 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2015.03.003 }}&lt;!--|access-date=May 10, 2015--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Doyle |first1=Kathryn |title=Sexual orientation, gender identity tied to eating disorder risk |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2015/05/08/us-eating-disorder-gender-idUSKBN0NT2E020150508 |access-date=May 10, 2015 |agency=Reuters |date=May 8, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gender dysphoria in those assigned male at birth tends to follow one of two broad trajectories: early-onset or late-onset. Early-onset gender dysphoria is behaviorally visible in childhood. Sometimes, early-onset gender dysphorics identify as gay for a period of time. This group is usually attracted to men in adulthood. Late-onset gender dysphoria does not include visible signs in early childhood, but some report having wishes to be female in childhood that they did not report to others. Those who experience late-onset gender dysphoria will often be attracted to women and may identify as lesbians. In those assigned female at birth, early-onset gender dysphoria is the most common course.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders |last= |first= |publisher=American Psychiatric Publishing |year=2013 |isbn=978-0-89042-554-1 |edition=Fifth |location=Arlington, VA |pages=455–456}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Causes ==
{{Main|Causes of transsexuality}}
GID exists when a person suffers discontent due to gender identity, causing them emotional distress.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Researchers disagree about the nature of distress and impairment in people with GID. Some authors have suggested that people with GID suffer because they are stigmatized and victimized;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=The Politics of Pathology and the Making of Gender Identity Disorder |last=Bryant |first=Karl Edward |publisher=ProQuest Dissertations &amp; Theses (PQDT) |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-549-26816-1 |location=Ann Arbor, Michigan |page=222}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that, if society had less strict gender divisions, transsexual people would suffer less.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

A twin study (based on seven people in a 314 sample) suggested that GID may be 62% heritable, indicating the possibility of a genetic influence or prenatal development as its origin, in these cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Coolidge FL, Thede LL, Young SE | title = The heritability of gender identity disorder in a child and adolescent twin sample | journal = Behavior Genetics | volume = 32 | issue = 4 | pages = 251–7 | date = July 2002 | pmid = 12211624 | doi = 10.1023/A:1019724712983 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Diagnosis ==
The [[American Psychiatric Association]] permits a diagnosis of ''gender dysphoria'' if the criteria in the DSM-5 are met. The DSM-5 states that at least two of the following criteria for gender dysphoria must be experienced for at least six months' duration in adolescents or adults for diagnosis:&lt;ref name="DSM5"&gt;{{cite book |author1=American Psychiatry Association |title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5) |date=2013 |publisher=American Psychiatric Publishing |location=Washington, DC and London |isbn=0-89042-555-8 |pages=451–460 |edition=5th}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--Note that these are paraphrased from the original to avoid copyright violation.--&gt;
* A strong desire to be of a gender other than one's assigned gender
* A strong desire to be treated as a gender other than one's assigned gender
* A significant incongruence between one's experienced or expressed gender and one's [[sexual characteristics]]
* A strong desire for the sexual characteristics of a gender other than one's assigned gender
* A strong desire to be rid of one's sexual characteristics due to incongruence with one's experienced or expressed gender
* A strong conviction that one has the typical reactions and feelings of a gender other than one's assigned gender
In addition, the condition must be associated with clinically significant distress or impairment.&lt;ref name="DSM5" /&gt;

The DSM-5 moved this diagnosis out of the sexual disorders category and into a category of its own.&lt;ref name="DSM5" /&gt; The diagnosis was renamed from gender identity disorder to gender dysphoria, after criticisms that the former term was stigmatizing.&lt;ref name="DSMVChild"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dsm5.org/ProposedRevision/Pages/proposedrevision.aspx?rid=192# |title=Gender Dysphoria in Children |publisher=American Psychiatric Association |date=May 4, 2011 |access-date=July 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subtyping by sexual orientation was deleted. The diagnosis for children was separated from that for adults, as "[[gender dysphoria in children]]". The creation of a specific diagnosis for children reflects the lesser ability of children to have insight into what they are experiencing, or ability to express it in the event that they have insight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=P 00 Gender Dysphoria in Children |url=http://www.dsm5.org/ProposedRevision/Pages/proposedrevision.aspx?rid=192# |publisher=American Psychiatric Association |access-date=April 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Other specified gender dysphoria'' or ''unspecified gender dysphoria'' can be diagnosed if a person doesn't meet the criteria for gender dysphoria but still has clinically significant distress or impairment.&lt;ref name="DSM5" /&gt;

The [[International Classification of Diseases]] ([[ICD-10]]) list several disorders related to gender identity:&lt;ref Name="ICD-10"&gt;{{cite web |publisher=[[World Health Organization]] | url=http://apps.who.int/classifications/icd10/browse/2016/en#/F60-F69 |title=International Classification of Diseases (ICD) F64 Gender identity disorders |access-date=August 9, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Potts |first=S |last2=Bhugra |first2=D |title=Classification of sexual disorders |journal=[[International Review of Psychiatry]] | year=1995 |volume=7 |pages=167–174 |doi=10.3109/09540269509028323 |issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Transsexual]]ism (F64.0): Desire to live and be accepted as a member of the opposite sex, usually accompanied by a desire for surgery and hormonal treatment
* [[Gender dysphoria in children|Gender identity disorder of childhood]] (F64.2): Persistent and intense distress about one's assigned gender, manifested prior to puberty
* Other gender identity disorders (F64.8)
* Gender identity disorder, unspecified (F64.9)
* [[Sexual maturation disorder]] (F66.0): Uncertainty about one's gender identity or sexual orientation, causing anxiety or distress

Significant revision of the ICD's classification of gender identity-related conditions is expected in the forthcoming [[ICD-11]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=International Classification of Diseases |url=http://www.who.int/health-topics/international-classification-of-diseases |publisher=World Health Organization |access-date=August 11, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{as of|2018|08}}, the ICD-11 lists this condition as "gender incongruence", under "conditions related to sexual health", coded into three conditions:&lt;ref name="icd11-gc"&gt;{{cite web |title=Gender incongruence (ICD-11) |url=https://icd.who.int/browse11/l-m/en#/http://id.who.int/icd/entity/411470068 |website=icd.who.int |publisher=WHO |access-date=August 28, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Gender incongruence of adolescence or adulthood (HA60): replaces F64.0
* Gender incongruence of childhood (HA61): replaces F64.2
* Gender incongruence, unspecified (HA6Z): replaces F64.9

In addition, sexual maturation disorder has been removed, along with [[dual-role transvestism]].&lt;ref name=pmid27717275&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Reed GM, Drescher J, Krueger RB, Atalla E, Cochran SD, First MB, Cohen-Kettenis PT, Arango-de Montis I, Parish SJ, Cottler S, Briken P, Saxena S | title = Disorders related to sexuality and gender identity in the ICD-11: revising the ICD-10 classification based on current scientific evidence, best clinical practices, and human rights considerations | journal = World Psychiatry | volume = 15 | issue = 3 | pages = 205–221 | date = October 2016 | pmid = 27717275 | pmc = 5032510 | doi = 10.1002/wps.20354 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ICD-11 defines gender incongurence as "a marked and persistent incongruence between an individual’s experienced gender and the assigned sex", with presentations similar to the DSM-V definition, but does not require significant distress or impairment.

== Management ==
Treatment for a person diagnosed with GID may include psychotherapy or to support the individual's preferred gender through hormone therapy, gender expression and role, or surgery. This may include psychological counselling, resulting in lifestyle changes, or physical changes, resulting from medical interventions such as hormonal treatment, genital surgery, electrolysis or laser hair removal, chest/breast surgery, or other reconstructive surgeries. The goal of treatment may simply be to reduce problems resulting from the person's transgender status, for example, counseling the patient in order to reduce guilt associated with cross-dressing, or counseling a spouse to help them adjust to the patient's situation.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book |title=Principles and Practice of Sex Therapy, Fourth Edition |last=Leiblum |first=Sandra |year=2006 |publisher=The Guilford Press |isbn=978-1-59385-349-5 |pages=488–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hormone treatment or surgery for gender dysphoria is somewhat controversial because of the irreversibility of certain{{which|date=February 2018}} physical changes. Guidelines have been established to aid clinicians. The [[World Professional Association for Transgender Health]] (WPATH) [[Standards of Care for the Health of Transsexual, Transgender, and Gender Nonconforming People|Standards of Care]] are used by some clinicians as treatment guidelines. Others use guidelines outlined in Gianna Israel and Donald Tarver's ''Transgender Care''. Guidelines for treatment generally follow a "[[harm reduction]]" model.&lt;ref name="AAP"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors =  | title = Office-based care for lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and questioning youth | journal = Pediatrics | volume = 132 | issue = 1 | pages = 198–203 | date = July 2013 | pmid = 23796746 | doi = 10.1542/peds.2013-1282 | quote = However, adolescents with multiple or anonymous partners, having unprotected intercourse, or having substance abuse issues should be tested at shorter intervals. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GLMA"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.glma.org/_data/n_0001/resources/live/GLMA%20Compendium%20of%20Health%20Profession%20Association%20LGBT%20Policy%20and%20Position%20Statements.pdf |title=www.glma.org Compendium of Health Profession Association LGBT Policy &amp; Position Statements |publisher=GLMA |year=2013 |access-date=August 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="APA"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.apa.org/about/policy/booklet.pdf |title=APA Policy Statements on Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, &amp; Transgender Concerns |publisher=American Psychological Association |year=2011 |access-date=August 27, 2013 |quote="BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that APA recognizes the efficacy, benefit, and necessity of gender transition treatments for appropriately evaluated individuals and calls upon public and private insurers to cover these medically necessary treatments;"}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Prepubescent children ===
{{Main|Gender dysphoria in children}}

The question of whether to counsel young children to be happy with their assigned sex, or to encourage them to continue to exhibit behaviors that do not match their assigned sex—or to explore a transsexual transition—is controversial. Some clinicians report that a significant proportion of young children diagnosed with gender dysphoria later do not exhibit any dysphoria.&lt;ref name="NPR"&gt;{{cite web |last=Spiegel |first=Alix |title=Q&amp;A: Therapists on Gender Identity Issues in Kids |publisher=NPR |date=May 8, 2008 |url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=90229789 |access-date=September 16, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Professionals who treat gender identity disorder in children have begun to refer and prescribe hormones, known as [[puberty blocker]]s, to delay the onset of puberty until a child is believed to be old enough to make an informed decision on whether hormonal gender reassignment leading to surgical gender reassignment will be in that person's best interest.&lt;ref&gt;''The Transgendered Child: A Handbook for Families and Professionals'' (Brill and Pepper, 2008){{full citation needed|date=May 2016}}{{page needed|date=May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Psychological treatments ===
{{Main|Psychotherapy}}
Until the 1970s, psychotherapy was the primary treatment for gender dysphoria, and generally was directed to helping the person adjust to the gender of the physical characteristics present at birth. Psychotherapy is any therapeutic interaction that aims to treat a psychological problem. Though some clinicians still use only psychotherapy to treat gender dysphoria, it may now be used in addition to biological interventions.&lt;ref name="treatment review"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Gijs |first=L |last2=Brawaeys |first2=A |title=Surgical Treatment of Gender Dysphoria in Adults and Adolescents: Recent Developments, Effectiveness, and Challenges |journal=Annual Review of Sex Research |year=2007 |volume=18 |issue=178–224}}&lt;/ref&gt; Psychotherapeutic treatment of GID involves helping the patient to adapt. Attempts to cure GID by changing the patient's gender identity to reflect birth characteristics have been ineffective.&lt;ref name="merck manual" /&gt;{{rp|1741}}

=== Biological treatments ===
{{Main|Sex reassignment therapy}}
Biological treatments physically alter [[Primary sex characteristic|primary]] and [[Secondary sex characteristic|secondary]] sex characteristics to reduce the discrepancy between an individual's physical body and gender identity.&lt;ref name="care guidelines"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Bockting |first=W |last2=Knudson |first2=G |last3=Goldberg |first3=J |title=Counselling and Mental Health Care of Transgender Adults and Loved Ones |date=January 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biological treatments for GID without any form of psychotherapy is quite uncommon. Researchers have found that if individuals bypass psychotherapy in their GID treatment, they often feel lost and confused when their biological treatments are complete.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hakeem |first=Az |title=Changing Sex or Changing Minds: Specialist Psychotherapy and Transsexuality |journal=Group Analysis |year=2008 |volume=41 |issue=2 |pages=182–196 |doi=10.1177/0533316408089883}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Psychotherapy, hormone replacement therapy, and sex reassignment surgery together can be effective treating GID when the [[HBIGDA-SOC|WPATH standards of care]] are followed.&lt;ref name="merck manual"&gt;{{cite book |author=George R. Brown, MD |chapter=Chapter 165 Sexuality and Sexual Disorders |pages=1740–1747 |editor1=Robert S. Porter, MD |title=The [[Merck Manual of Diagnosis and Therapy]] | edition=19th |date=July 20, 2011 |publisher=[[Merck &amp; Co.]], Inc. |location=[[Whitehouse Station, NJ]], USA |isbn=978-0-911910-19-3 |display-editors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|1570}} The overall level of patient satisfaction with both psychological and biological treatments is very high.&lt;ref name="treatment review" /&gt;

== Epidemiology ==
Estimated rates of those with a transgender identity range from a lower bound of 1:2000 (or about 0.05%) in [[Low Countries|the Netherlands and Belgium]]&lt;ref name="conway"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Olyslager |first=Femke |last2=Conway |first2=Lynn |author2-link=Lynn Conway |title=Transseksualiteit komt vaker voor dan u denkt. Een nieuwe kijk op de prevalentie van transseksualiteit in Nederland en België |url=http://rjh.ub.rug.nl/genderstudies/article/view/1904/1897 |journal=Tijdschrift voor Genderstudies |volume=11 |issue=2 |pages=39–51 |publisher=[[Amsterdam University Press]] | location=Amsterdam |year=2008 |language=Dutch |quote=…it is safe to assume that the lower limit for the inherent prevalence of transsexualism in the Netherlands and Flanders is on order of 1:2000 to 1:1000 for transgender females and on the order of 1:4000 to 1:2000 for transgender males. |laysource=How Frequently Does Transsexualism Occur? |layurl=http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TS/TSprevalence.html |issn=1388-3186 |access-date=August 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 0.5% of [[Massachusetts]] adults.&lt;ref name=AJPH&gt;{{Citation |last=Conron |first=KJ |last2=Scott |first2=G |last3=Stowell |first3=GS |last4=Landers |first4=S |date=January 2012 |volume=102 |issue=1 |pages=118–222 |issn=1541-0048 |oclc=01642844 |doi=10.2105/AJPH.2011.300315 |title=Transgender Health in Massachusetts: Results from a Household Probability Sample of Adults |journal=[[American Journal of Public Health]] | publisher=[[American Public Health Association]] | url=http://ajph.aphapublications.org/doi/pdf/10.2105/AJPH.2011.300315 |access-date=August 28, 2013 |quote=Between 2007 and 2009, survey participants aged 18 to 64 years in the Massachusetts Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (MA-BRFSS; N = 28 662) were asked: "Some people describe themselves as transgender when they experience a different gender identity from their sex at birth. For example, a person born into a male body, but who feels female or lives as a woman. Do you consider yourself to be transgender?" […] We restricted the analytic sample to 28176 participants who answered yes or no to the transgender question (excluding n=364, 1.0% weighted who declined to respond. […] Transgender respondents (n=131; 0.5%; 95% confidence interval [CI]=0.3%, 0.6%) were somewhat younger and more likely to be Hispanic than were nontransgender respondents. |pmc=3490554 |pmid=22095354}}&lt;/ref&gt; From a national survey of high-school students in [[New Zealand]], 8,500 randomly selected secondary school students from 91 randomly selected high schools found 1.2% of students responded "yes" to the question "Do you think you are transgender?".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Clark TC, Lucassen MF, Bullen P, Denny SJ, Fleming TM, Robinson EM, Rossen FV | title = The health and well-being of transgender high school students: results from the New Zealand adolescent health survey (Youth'12) | journal = The Journal of Adolescent Health | volume = 55 | issue = 1 | pages = 93–9 | date = July 2014 | pmid = 24438852 | doi = 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2013.11.008 | quote = Whether a student was transgender was measured by the question, "Do you think you are transgender? This is a girl who feels like she should have been a boy, or a boy who feels like he should have been a girl (e.g., Trans, Queen, [[Fa'afafine|Fa’faffine]], Whakawahine, Tangata ira Tane, [[Genderqueer]])?" […] Over 8,000 students (n = 8,166) answered the question about whether they were transgender. Approximately 95% of students did not report being transgender (n=7,731; 94.7%), 96 students reported being transgender (1.2%), 202 reported not being sure (2.5%), and 137 did not understand the question (1.7%). }}&lt;/ref&gt; These numbers are based on those who identify as transgender. It is estimated that about 0.005% to 0.014% of people assigned male at birth and 0.002% to 0.003% of people assigned female at birth would be diagnosed with gender dysphoria,{{Disputed inline |Off by two orders of magnitude?|reason=Williams Institute data and this ref appear to contradict each other |date=December 2017}} based on 2013 diagnostic criteria, though this is considered a modest underestimate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 5 |isbn=978-0-89042-555-8 |publisher=[[American Psychiatric Association]] | year=2013 |page=454}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research indicates people who [[Transitioning (transgender)|transition]] in adulthood are up to three times more likely to be male assigned at birth, but that among people transitioning in childhood the sex ratio is close to 1:1.&lt;ref name="prevalence"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Landén M, Wålinder J, Lundström B | title = Prevalence, incidence and sex ratio of transsexualism | journal = Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica | volume = 93 | issue = 4 | pages = 221–3 | date = April 1996 | pmid = 8712018 | doi = 10.1111/j.1600-0447.1996.tb10638.x | quote = On average, the male [to female]:female [to male] ratio in prevalence studies is estimated to be 3:1. However […] the incidence studies have shown a considerably lower male [to female] predominance. In Sweden and England and Wales a sex ratio of 1:1 has been reported. In the most recent incidence data from Sweden there is a slight male [to female] predominance among the group consisting of all applicants for sex reassignment, while in the group of primary [early onset] transsexuals there is no difference in incidence between men and women. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The term ''gender identity disorder'' is an older term for the condition in the DSM. The [[American Psychiatric Association]] (APA) uses the term ''gender dysphoria''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dsm5.org/Documents/Gender%20Dysphoria%20Fact%20Sheet.pdf |title=Gender Dysphoria Fact Sheet |publisher=APA |access-date=September 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The APA's DSM first described the condition in the third publication ("DSM-III") in 1980.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Koh J | title = [The history of the concept of gender identity disorder] | journal = Seishin Shinkeigaku Zasshi = Psychiatria Et Neurologia Japonica | volume = 114 | issue = 6 | pages = 673–80 | year = 2012 | pmid = 22844818 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2011, the UK [[National Research Ethics Service]] approved prescribing monthly injection of puberty-blocking drugs to youngsters from 12 years old, in order to enable them to get older before deciding on formal sex change. The [[Tavistock and Portman NHS Foundation Trust]] (T&amp;P) in North London has treated such children.  Clinic director Dr. Polly Carmichael said, "Certainly, of the children between 12 and 14, there's a number who are keen to take part. I know what's been very hard for their families is knowing that there's something available but it's not available here." The clinic received 127 referrals for gender dysphoria in 2010.&lt;ref name=dt15&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/health/healthnews/8454002/Puberty-blocker-for-children-considering-sex-change.html  telegraph.co.uk: "Puberty blocker for children considering sex change"], ''The Daily Telegraph'' (Alleyne) April 15, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

The T&amp;P completed a three-year trial to assess the psychological, social and physical benefits and risks involved for 12- to 14-year-old patients.  The trial was deemed such a success that doctors have decided to make the drugs more widely available and to children as young as 9 years of age. As recently as 2009, national guidelines stated that treatment for gender dysphoria should not start until puberty had finished. [[Ferring Pharmaceuticals]] manufactures the drug Triptorelin, marketed under the name [[Gonapeptyl]], at £82 per monthly dose. The treatment is reversible, which means the body will resume its previous state upon discontinuation of drugs.

== Society and culture ==

=== Gender as a social construction ===
{{Main|Social construction of gender}}
Social gender characteristics are created and supported by the expectations of a culture, and are therefore only partially related to biological sex. For example, the association of particular colors with "girl" or "boy" babies begins extremely early in Western European-derived cultures. Other expectations relate to approved and allowable behaviors and emotional expression.&lt;ref name="Marecek, Crawford &amp; Popp"&gt;{{cite book |authors=Marecek, J., Crawford, M., &amp; Popp, D. |year=2004 |chapter=On the Construction of Gender, Sex, and Sexualities |editors=A.H. Eagly, A.E. Beall, &amp; R.J. Sternberg |title=The Psychology of Gender |pages=192–216 |location=New York |publisher=Guilford Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some cultures have [[Third gender|three defined genders]]: man, woman, and effeminate man. For example, in [[Samoa]], the ''[[fa'afafine]]'', a group of feminine males, are entirely socially accepted. The fa'afafine do not have any of the stigma or distress typically associated in most cultures with deviating from a male/female gender role. This suggests the distress so frequently associated with GID in a Western context is not ''caused'' by the disorder itself, but by difficulties encountered from social disapproval by one's culture.&lt;ref name="fa'afafine"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Vasey PL, Bartlett NH | title = What can the Samoan "Fa'afafine" teach us about the Western concept of gender identity disorder in childhood? | journal = Perspectives in Biology and Medicine | volume = 50 | issue = 4 | pages = 481–90 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17951883 | doi = 10.1353/pbm.2007.0056 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, research has found that the anxiety associated with gender dysphoria persists in cultures, Eastern or otherwise, which are more accepting of gender nonconformity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 5 |isbn=978-0-89042-555-8 |publisher=[[American Psychiatric Association]] | year=2013 |page=459}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Australia, a 2014 High Court of Australia judgment unanimously ruled in favor of a plaintiff named  [[Norrie May-Welby|Norrie]], who asked to be classified by a third gender category, 'non-specific', after a long court battle with the NSW Registrar of Births, Deaths and Marriages.&lt;ref name="Norrie"&gt;{{cite AustLII|HCA|11|2014 |litigants=NSW Registrar of Births, Deaths and Marriages v Norrie |courtname=auto |date=April 2, 2014}}.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Court did not accept that gender was a social construction: it found that sex reassignment "surgery did not resolve her sexual ambiguity".&lt;ref name="Norrie" /&gt;{{rp|para 11}}

=== Classification as a disorder ===
The [[mental disorder|psychiatric diagnoses]] of gender identity disorder (now gender dysphoria) was introduced in DSM-III in 1980. [[Arlene Istar Lev]] and [[Deborah Rudacille]] have characterized the addition as a political maneuver to re-stigmatize homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Lev |first=Arlene Istar |title=Transgender Emergence: Therapeutic Guidelines for Working with Gender-Variant People and Their Families |authorlink=Arlene Istar Lev |publisher=Haworth Press |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-7890-2117-5 |page=172 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=LwxvazLRmiEC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;dq=homosexuality+dsm-iii+transsexuality}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Rudacille |first=Deborah |authorlink=Deborah Rudacille |title=The Riddle of Gender: Science, Activism, and Transgender Rights |publisher=Pantheon |date=February 2005 |isbn=978-0-375-42162-4}}{{page needed|date=May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Homosexuality was removed from DSM-II in 1974.) By contrast, [[Kenneth Zucker]] and [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] argue that gender identity disorder was included in DSM-III because it "met the generally accepted criteria used by the framers of DSM-III for inclusion."&lt;ref name="Historical Note"&gt;{{citation |last=Zucker |first=KJ |author-link=Kenneth Zucker |last2=Spitzer |first2=RL |author2-link=Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist) |title=Was the gender identity disorder of childhood diagnosis introduced into DSM-III as a backdoor maneuver to replace homosexuality? A historical note. |journal=Journal of Sex and Marital Therapy |date=Jan–Feb 2005 |volume=31 |issue=1 |pages=31–42 |doi=10.1080/00926230590475251 |pmid=15841704}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some researchers, including [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] and Paul J. Fink, contend that the behaviors and experiences seen in transsexualism are abnormal and constitute a dysfunction.&lt;ref name="PsychNews" /&gt; The American Psychiatric Association stated that [[gender nonconformity]] is not the same thing as gender dysphoria,&lt;ref name="What Is"/&gt; and that "gender nonconformity is not in itself a mental disorder. The critical element of gender dysphoria is the presence of clinically significant distress associated with the condition."&lt;ref name="DSM-5 fact sheet"/&gt;

Individuals with gender dysphoria may or may not regard their own cross-gender feelings and behaviors as a disorder. Advantages and disadvantages exist to classifying gender dysphoria as a disorder.&lt;ref name="Standards of Care" /&gt; Because gender dysphoria had been classified as a disorder in medical texts (such as the previous DSM manual, the DSM-IV-TR, under the name "gender identity disorder"), many insurance companies are willing to cover some of the expenses of sex reassignment therapy. Without the classification of gender dysphoria as a medical disorder, sex reassignment therapy may be viewed as cosmetic treatment, rather than medically necessary treatment, and may not be covered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Ford |first=Zack |title=APA Revises Manual: Being Transgender is No Longer a Mental Disorder |url=http://thinkprogress.org/lgbt/2012/12/03/1271431/apa-revises-manual-being-transgender-is-no-longer-a-mental-disorder/?mobile=nc |access-date=April 7, 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130202082602/http://thinkprogress.org/lgbt/2012/12/03/1271431/apa-revises-manual-being-transgender-is-no-longer-a-mental-disorder/?mobile=nc |archive-date=February 2, 2013 |dead-url=yes |df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, transgender people are less likely than others to have health insurance, and often face hostility and insensitivity from healthcare providers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Social Work Practice with Transgender and Gender Variant Youth |last=Mallon |first=Gerald P. |publisher=Routledge |year=2009 |isbn=0-415-99482-9 |location=New Jersey}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The DSM-IV-TR diagnostic component of distress is not inherent in the cross-gender identity; rather, it is related to social rejection and discrimination suffered by the individual.&lt;ref name="fa'afafine" /&gt; Psychology professor Darryl Hill insists that gender dysphoria is not a mental disorder, but rather that the diagnostic criteria reflect psychological distress in children that occurs when parents and others have trouble relating to their child's gender variance.&lt;ref name="PsychNews"&gt;{{cite news |title=Controversy Continues to Grow Over DSM's GID Diagnosis |url=http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleid=106462 |publisher=Psychiatric News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people have often been harassed, socially excluded, and subjected to discrimination, abuse and violence, including murder.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book |title=Children with Gender Identity Disorder: A Clinical, Ethical, and Legal Analysis |last=Giordano |first=Simona |publisher=Routledge |year=2012 |isbn=0-415-50271-3 |location=New Jersey |page=147}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2002, the British Lord Chancellor's office published a ''Government Policy Concerning Transsexual People'' document that categorically states, "What transsexualism is not ... It is not a mental illness."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dca.gov.uk/constitution/transsex/policy.htm |title=Government Policy concerning Transsexual People |work=People's rights/Transsexual people |publisher=U.K. Department for Constitutional Affairs |year=2003 |deadurl=yes |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080511211217/http://www.dca.gov.uk/constitution/transsex/policy.htm |archive-date=May 11, 2008 |df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2009, the government of France declared that a transsexual gender identity will no longer be classified as a psychiatric condition,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=La transsexualité ne sera plus classée comme affectation psychiatrique |url=http://www.lemonde.fr/societe/article/2009/05/16/la-transsexualite-ne-sera-plus-classee-comme-affectation-psychiatrique_1193860_3224.html |date=May 16, 2009 |work=Le Monde}}&lt;/ref&gt; but according to French trans rights organizations, beyond the impact of the announcement itself, nothing changed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.liberation.fr/societe/2011/05/17/la-france-est-tres-en-retard-dans-la-prise-en-charge-des-transsexuels_736344 |title="La France est très en retard dans la prise en charge des transsexuels" |date=May 17, 2011 |work=Libération |language=fr |quote=En réalité, ce décret n'a été rien d'autre qu'un coup médiatique, un très bel effet d'annonce. Sur le terrain, rien n'a changé.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Denmark made a similar statement in 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/denmark-will-be-the-first-country-to-no-longer-define-being-transgender-as-a-mental-illness-a7029151.html |title=Denmark will become first country to no longer define being transgender as a mental illness |date=May 14, 2016 |work=The Independent }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ICD-11, GID is reclassified as "gender incongruence", a condition related to sexual health.&lt;ref name="icd11-gc" /&gt; The working group responsible for this recategorization recommends keeping such a diagnosis in ICD-11 to preserve access to health services.&lt;ref name=pmid27717275 /&gt;

=== Intimate relationships ===
{{Missing information|section|relationships of trans people with male partners|date=December 2015}}
Intimate relationships between lesbians and female-to-male people with GID will sometimes endure throughout the transition process, or shift to becoming supportive friendships. Intimate relationships between heterosexual women and male-to-female people with GID often suffer once the GID is known or revealed. Researchers say the fate of the relationship seems to depend mainly on the woman's adaptability. Problems often arise, with the cisgender partner becoming increasingly angry or dissatisfied, if her partner's time spent in a female role grows, if her partner's libido decreases, or if her partner is angry and emotionally cut-off when in the male role. Cisgender women sometimes also worry about social stigma and may be uncomfortable with the bodily feminization of their partner as the partner moves through transition. The cisgender women who are likeliest to accept and accommodate their partner's transition, researchers say, are those with a low sex drive or those who are equally sexually attracted to men and women.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite book |title=Transsexual and Other Disorders of Gender Identity: A Practical Guide to Management |last=Barrett |first=James |publisher=RADCLIFFE MEDICAL PRESS LTD |year=2007 |isbn=1-85775-719-X |page=83}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Legislation ===
{{Main|School Success and Opportunity Act}}
In California, Assembly Bill (AB) No. 1266, the [[School Success and Opportunity Act]], authored by Assemblyman [[Tom Ammiano]] (D-San Francisco), was passed in May 2013 by the State Assembly:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Existing law prohibits public schools from discriminating on the basis of specified characteristics, including gender, gender identity, and gender expression, and specifies various statements of legislative intent and the policies of the state in that regard. Existing law requires that participation in a particular physical education activity or sport, if required of pupils of one sex, be available to pupils of each sex. This bill would require that a pupil be permitted to participate in sex-segregated school programs, activities, including athletic teams and competitions, and use facilities consistent with his or her gender identity, irrespective of the gender listed on the pupil's records.&lt;ref name="latimes"&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/local/political/la-me-pc-gender-identity-school-bathrooms-20130509,0,3700818.story ''Los Angeles Times'', "Assembly approves bill on gender identity in schools"] by Chris Megerian, May 9, 2013. Retrieved April 11, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; The California Catholic Conference opposed the bill as unnecessary, as laws already exist to fight discrimination against transgender students. A spokeswoman for the conference said that the issue should be handled by school officials.&lt;ref name="latimes" /&gt;

== See also ==
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite web |url=http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TSsuccesses/TransMen.html |title=Successful TransMen: Links and Photos |first=Lynn |last=Conway |authorlink=Lynn Conway |work=ai.eecs.umich.edu |date=June 26, 2014 |access-date=December 2, 2014}}
* {{cite web |url=http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TSsuccesses/TSsuccesses.html |title=Transsexual Women's Successes: Links and Photos |first=Lynn |last=Conway |work=ai.eecs.umich.edu |date=February 5, 2011 |access-date=December 2, 2014}}
* {{cite news |first=Juliet |last=Jacques |url=https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/series/transgender-journey |title=A Transgender Journey |work=[[The Guardian]] | access-date=December 2, 2014}}
* {{cite book |url=http://admin.associationsonline.com/uploaded_files/140/files/Standards%20of%20Care,%20V7%20Full%20Book.pdf |title=Standards of Care for Gender Identity Disorders |author=World Professional Association for Transgender Health |publisher=Harry Benjamin International Gender Dysphoria Association |year=2012 |deadurl=yes |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140924061804/http://admin.associationsonline.com/uploaded_files/140/files/Standards%20of%20Care%2C%20V7%20Full%20Book.pdf |archive-date=September 24, 2014 |df=}} Includes a description of ICD-10 criteria.

== External links ==
{{Medical resources
|  ICD10          = {{ICD10|F|64.9 || f|60}}, {{ICD10|F|64.8 || f|60}}
|  ICD9           = {{ICD9|302.85}}
|  ICDO           = 
|  OMIM           = 
|  MedlinePlus    = 001527
|  eMedicineSubj  = 
|  eMedicineTopic = 
|  MeshID         = D000068116
}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060604060835/http://www.transgendercare.com/guidance/resources/ictlep_soc.htm Health Law Standards of Care for Transsexualism] – An alternative to the Benjamin Standards of Care proposed by the International Conference on Transgender Law and Employment Policy.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20030812130936/http://www.lcd.gov.uk/constitution/transsex/policy.htm The Lord Chancellor's Department Government Policy concerning Transsexual People]

{{Transgender topics}}
{{Sexual identities}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gender Identity Disorder}}
[[Category:Gender identity]]
[[Category:Identity disorders]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender identity disorders| ]]
[[Category:Transgender and medicine]]
[[Category:Psychiatric diagnosis]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>