<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211121235836|1056465570" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="43097" pageid="43097" ns="0" title="Gender dysphoria"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-21T23:59:17Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Long term mental distress due to a mismatch between gender identity and sex assigned at birth}}
{{Infobox medical condition (new)
| name          = Gender dysphoria
| synonyms      = Gender identity disorder
| symptoms      = Distress related to one's assigned gender or sex&lt;ref name="DSM-5 fact sheet" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Maddux"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Standards of Care" /&gt;
| complications = Eating disorders, suicide, depression, anxiety, social isolation&lt;ref name="Davidson-2012" /&gt;
| onset         = 
| duration      = 
| causes        = 
| risks         = 
| diagnosis     = 
| differential  = Variance in gender identity or expression that is not distressing&lt;ref name="DSM-5 fact sheet" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Standards of Care" /&gt;
| prevention    = 
| treatment     = [[Transitioning (transgender)|Transitioning]], [[psychotherapy]]&lt;ref name="Maddux"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Standards of Care" /&gt;
| medication    = [[Transgender hormone therapy|Hormones]] (e.g., [[anabolic steroid|androgens]], [[antiandrogen]]s, [[estrogen (medication)|estrogens]])
| prognosis     = 
| frequency     = 
| deaths        = 
}}
{{Transgender sidebar|medicine}}
'''Gender dysphoria''' ('''GD''') is the distress a person feels due to a mismatch between their [[gender identity]]{{emdash}}their personal sense of their own [[gender]]{{emdash}}and their [[sex assignment|sex assigned at birth]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Campaign|first=Human Rights|title=Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity Definitions|url=http://www.hrc.org/resources/sexual-orientation-and-gender-identity-terminology-and-definitions}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MorrowMessinger"&gt;''Sexual Orientation and Gender Expression in Social Work Practice'', edited by Deana F. Morrow and Lori Messinger (2006, {{ISBN|0231501862}}), p. 8: "Gender identity refers to an individual's personal sense of identity as masculine or feminine, or some combination thereof."&lt;/ref&gt; The diagnostic label '''gender identity disorder''' ('''GID''')&lt;!--NOTE: Per WP:Alternative title, the term should be bolded somewhere in the lead.--&gt; was used until 2013 with the release of the [[DSM-5]]. The condition was renamed to remove the [[Stigmatization|stigma]] associated with the term ''disorder''.&lt;ref&gt;American Psychiatric Association, [https://www.psychiatry.org/File%20Library/Psychiatrists/Practice/DSM/APA_DSM-5-Gender-Dysphoria.pdf DSM-5 Fact Sheets, Updated Disorders: Gender Dysphoria] (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Association, 2013): 2 ("DSM-5 aims to avoid stigma and ensure clinical care for individuals who see and feel themselves to be a different gender than their assigned gender. It replaces the diagnostic name 'gender identity disorder' with 'gender dysphoria', as well as makes other important clarifications in the criteria.").&lt;/ref&gt;

People with gender dysphoria commonly identify as [[transgender]].&lt;ref name="Russo"&gt;{{cite book |vauthors=Russo J, Coker JK, King JH|title=DSM-5® and Family Systems|year=2017|page=352|publisher=[[Springer Publishing Company]]|isbn=978-0826183996|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0JfvDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA352|quote=People meeting criteria for Gender Dysphoria most often identify themselves as trans or transgender. ''Trans'' or ''transgender'' can be used as umbrella terms to include the broad spectrum of persons whose gender identity differs from the assigned gender (APA, 2013).}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gender nonconformity]] is not the same thing as gender dysphoria&lt;ref name="What Is"&gt;{{cite web|author=Ranna Parekh|title=What Is Gender Dysphoria?|url=https://www.psychiatry.org/patients-families/gender-dysphoria/what-is-gender-dysphoria|access-date=November 20, 2018|publisher=[[American Psychiatric Publishing]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and does not always lead to dysphoria or distress.&lt;ref&gt;World Professional Association for Transgender Health (WPATH), ''[https://www.wpath.org/publications/soc Standards of Care for the Health of Transsexual, Transgender, and Gender Nonconforming People]'', ver. 7 (2011), 5 ("only ''some'' gender nonconforming people experience gender dysphoria at ''some'' point in their lives.")&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[American Psychiatric Association]], the critical element of gender dysphoria is "clinically significant distress".&lt;ref name="DSM-5 fact sheet"&gt;{{cite web|title=Gender Dysphoria|url=https://www.psychiatry.org/File%20Library/Psychiatrists/Practice/DSM/APA_DSM-5-Gender-Dysphoria.pdf|access-date=December 24, 2016|publisher=[[American Psychiatric Publishing]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The causes of gender dysphoria are unknown but a gender identity likely reflects genetic and biological, environmental, and cultural factors.&lt;ref name="heylens et al"/&gt;&lt;ref name="diamond-2013"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Rosenthal-2014" /&gt; Treatment for gender dysphoria may include supporting the individual's [[gender expression]] or their desire for [[Sex reassignment therapy|hormone therapy or surgery]].&lt;ref name="Maddux"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eOlzCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA464|title=Psychopathology: Foundations for a Contemporary Understanding|vauthors=Maddux JE, Winstead BA|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=2015|isbn=978-1317697992|pages=464–465}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Standards of Care"&gt;{{cite journal|author=Coleman E|year=2011|title=Standards of Care for the Health of Transsexual, Transgender, and Gender-Nonconforming People, Version 7|url=http://www.wpath.org/uploaded_files/140/files/IJT%20SOC,%20V7.pdf|url-status=dead|journal=International Journal of Transgenderism|publisher=Routledge Taylor &amp; Francis Group|volume=13|issue=4|pages=165–232|doi=10.1080/15532739.2011.700873|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140802135807/http://www.wpath.org/uploaded_files/140/files/IJT%20SOC%2C%20V7.pdf|archive-date=August 2, 2014|access-date=August 30, 2014|s2cid=39664779}}&lt;/ref&gt; Treatment may also include counseling or [[psychotherapy]].&lt;ref name="Standards of Care" /&gt;

Some researchers and transgender people support declassification of the condition because they say the diagnosis [[pathologizes]] gender variance and reinforces the [[Gender binary|binary model of gender]].&lt;ref name="Karl Bryant"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|first=Karl|last=Bryant|title=Gender Dysphoria|encyclopedia=[[Encyclopædia Britannica Online]]|date=2018|access-date=August 16, 2018|url=https://www.britannica.com/science/gender-dysphoria}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Signs and symptoms ==
Distress arising from an incongruence between a person's felt gender and assigned sex/gender (usually at birth) is the cardinal symptom of gender dysphoria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Zucker|first1=Kenneth J.|last2=Lawrence|first2=Anne A.|last3=Kreukels|first3=Baudewijntje P.C.|year=2016|title=Gender Dysphoria in Adults|journal=Annual Review of Clinical Psychology|volume=12|pages=217–247|doi=10.1146/annurev-clinpsy-021815-093034|pmid=26788901|quote=[For DSM-5] a reconceptualization was articulated in which 'identity' per se was not considered a sign of a mental disorder. Rather, it was the incongruence between one’s felt gender and assigned sex/gender (usually at birth) leading to distress and/or impairment that was the core feature of the diagnosis.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Lev|first1=Arlene Istar|year=2013|title=Gender Dysphoria: Two Steps Forward, One Step Back|journal=Clinical Social Work Journal|volume=41|issue=3|pages=288–296|doi=10.1007/s10615-013-0447-0|quote=[Despite some misgivings], I think that the change in nomenclature from the DSM-IV to the DSM-5 is a step forward, that is, removing the concept of gender as the site of the disorder and placing the focus on issues of distress and dysphoria.|s2cid=144556484}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gender dysphoria in those [[assigned male at birth]] tends to follow one of two broad trajectories: early-onset or late-onset. Early-onset gender dysphoria is behaviorally visible in childhood. Sometimes gender dysphoria will stop for a while in this group and they will identify as gay or homosexual for a period of time, followed by recurrence of gender dysphoria. This group is usually sexually attracted to members of their natal sex in adulthood. Late-onset gender dysphoria does not include visible signs in early childhood, but some report having had wishes to be the opposite sex in childhood that they did not report to others. Trans women who experience late-onset gender dysphoria will usually be sexually attracted to women and may identify as lesbians or bisexual. It is common for people assigned male at birth who have late-onset gender dysphoria to [[Transvestic fetishism|cross-dress with sexual excitement]].&lt;!--NOTE: entire paragraph is sourced to refs at end of paragraph--&gt; In those [[assigned female at birth]], early-onset gender dysphoria is the most common course. This group is usually sexually attracted to women. Trans men who experience late-onset gender dysphoria will usually be sexually attracted to men and may identify as gay.&lt;ref name="dsm5"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/diagnosticstatis0005unse/page/451|title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders|publisher=American Psychiatric Publishing|year=2013|isbn=978-0-89042-554-1|edition=Fifth|location=Arlington, VA|pages=[https://archive.org/details/diagnosticstatis0005unse/page/451 451–460]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Guillamon"&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Guillamon A, Junque C, Gómez-Gil E|date=October 2016|title=A Review of the Status of Brain Structure Research in Transsexualism|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|volume=45|issue=7|pages=1615–48|doi=10.1007/s10508-016-0768-5|pmc=4987404|pmid=27255307}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Symptoms of GD in children include preferences for opposite sex-typical toys, games, or activities; great dislike of their own genitalia; and a strong preference for playmates of the opposite sex.&lt;ref name="DSM5"&gt;{{cite book|author1=American Psychiatry Association|url=https://archive.org/details/diagnosticstatis0005unse/page/451|title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5)|date=2013|publisher=American Psychiatric Publishing|isbn=978-0-89042-555-8|edition=5th|location=Washington, DC and London|pages=[https://archive.org/details/diagnosticstatis0005unse/page/451 451–460]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some children may also experience [[social isolation]] from their peers, [[anxiety (mood)|anxiety]], loneliness, and [[Depression (mood)|depression]].&lt;ref name="Davidson-2012"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Davidson|first=Michelle R.|title=A Nurse's Guide to Women's Mental Health|publisher=Springer Publishing Company|year=2012|isbn=978-0-8261-7113-9|page=114}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In adolescents and adults, symptoms include the desire to be and to be treated as the other sex.&lt;ref name = DSM5/&gt; Adults with GD are at increased risk for stress, isolation, anxiety, depression, [[low self-esteem|poor self-esteem]], and suicide.&lt;ref name="Davidson-2012" /&gt;  Transgender people are also at heightened risk for [[eating disorder]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Diemer EW, Grant JD, Munn-Chernoff MA, Patterson DA, Duncan AE|date=August 2015|title=Gender Identity, Sexual Orientation, and Eating-Related Pathology in a National Sample of College Students|journal=The Journal of Adolescent Health|volume=57|issue=2|pages=144–9|doi=10.1016/j.jadohealth.2015.03.003|pmc=4545276|pmid=25937471}}&lt;!--|access-date=May 10, 2015--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; and [[substance abuse]].&lt;ref&gt;Harmon, A., &amp; Oberleitner, M. G. (2016). Gender dysphoria. In Gale (Ed.), Gale encyclopedia of children's health: Infancy through adolescence (3rd ed.). Farmington, MI: Gale.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Causes ==
{{Main|Causes of transsexuality}}

The specific causes of gender dysphoria remain unknown, and treatments targeting the [[etiology]] or [[pathogenesis]] of gender dysphoria do not exist.&lt;ref name="treatment review"/&gt; Evidence from [[Twin studies|studies of twins]] suggests that genetic factors play a role in the development of gender dysphoria&lt;ref name="heylens et al"&gt;{{cite journal|author3-link=Kenneth Zucker|vauthors=Heylens G, De Cuypere G, Zucker KJ, Schelfaut C, Elaut E, Vanden Bossche H, De Baere E, T'Sjoen G|date=March 2012 |title=Gender identity disorder in twins: a review of the case report literature|journal=The Journal of Sexual Medicine|volume=9|issue=3|pages=751–7|doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2011.02567.x|pmid=22146048|quote=Of 23 [[Twin#Monozygotic (identical) twins|monozygotic]] female and male twins, nine (39.1%) were concordant for GID; in contrast, none of the 21 same‐sex dizygotic female and male twins were concordant for GID, a statistically significant difference (P = 0.005)... These findings suggest a role for genetic factors in the development of GID.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="diamond-2013"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Diamond|first=Milton|author-link=Milton Diamond|year=2013|title=Transsexuality Among Twins: Identity Concordance, Transition, Rearing, and Orientation|journal=International Journal of Transgenderism|volume=14|issue=1|pages=24–38|doi=10.1080/15532739.2013.750222|quote=Combining data from the present survey with those from past-published reports, 20% of all male and female monozygotic twin pairs were found concordant for transsexual identity... The responses of our twins relative to their rearing, along with our findings regarding some of their experiences during childhood and adolescence show their identity was much more influenced by their genetics than their rearing.|s2cid=144330783}}&lt;/ref&gt; and gender identity is thought to likely reflect a complex interplay of biological, environmental, and cultural factors.&lt;ref name="Rosenthal-2014"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Rosenthal|first=Stephen M.|date=2014-12-01|title=Approach to the Patient: Transgender Youth: Endocrine Considerations|journal=The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism|language=en|volume=99|issue=12|pages=4379–4389|doi=10.1210/jc.2014-1919|pmid=25140398|issn=0021-972X|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Diagnosis ==
The [[American Psychiatric Association]] permits a diagnosis of ''gender dysphoria'' in adolescents or adults if two or more of the following criteria are experienced for at least six months' duration:&lt;ref name="DSM5" /&gt;
&lt;!--Note that these are paraphrased from the original to avoid copyright violation.--&gt;
* A strong desire to be of a gender other than one's assigned gender
* A strong desire to be treated as a gender other than one's assigned gender
* A significant incongruence between one's experienced or expressed gender and one's [[sexual characteristics]]
* A strong desire for the sexual characteristics of a gender other than one's assigned gender
* A strong desire to be rid of one's sexual characteristics due to incongruence with one's experienced or expressed gender
* A strong conviction that one has the typical reactions and feelings of a gender other than one's assigned gender
In addition, the condition must be associated with clinically significant distress or impairment.&lt;ref name="DSM5" /&gt;

The DSM-5 moved this diagnosis out of the sexual disorders category and into a category of its own.&lt;ref name="DSM5" /&gt; The diagnosis was renamed from gender identity disorder to gender dysphoria, after criticisms that the former term was stigmatizing.&lt;ref name="DSMVChild"&gt;{{cite web|date=May 4, 2011|title=Gender Dysphoria in Children|url=http://www.dsm5.org/ProposedRevision/Pages/proposedrevision.aspx?rid=192#|access-date=July 3, 2011|publisher=American Psychiatric Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subtyping by sexual orientation was deleted. The diagnosis for children was separated from that for adults, as "[[gender dysphoria in children]]". The creation of a specific diagnosis for children reflects the lesser ability of children to have insight into what they are experiencing, or ability to express it if they have insight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=P 00 Gender Dysphoria in Children|url=http://www.dsm5.org/ProposedRevision/Pages/proposedrevision.aspx?rid=192#|access-date=April 2, 2012|publisher=American Psychiatric Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Other specified gender dysphoria'' or ''unspecified gender dysphoria'' can be diagnosed if a person does not meet the criteria for gender dysphoria but still has clinically significant distress or impairment.&lt;ref name="DSM5" /&gt; Intersex people are now included in the diagnosis of GD.&lt;ref name="Davy"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Davy|first1=Zowie|last2=Toze|first2=Michael|year=2018|title=What Is Gender Dysphoria? A Critical Systematic Narrative Review|journal=Transgender Health|publisher=Mary Ann Liebert, Inc. Publishers|volume=3|issue=1|pages=159–169|doi=10.1089/trgh.2018.0014|pmc=6225591|pmid=30426079}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[International Classification of Diseases]] ([[ICD-10]]) lists several disorders related to gender identity:&lt;ref name="ICD-10"&gt;{{cite web|title=International Classification of Diseases (ICD) F64 Gender identity disorders|url=http://apps.who.int/classifications/icd10/browse/2016/en#/F60-F69|access-date=August 9, 2018|publisher=[[World Health Organization]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Potts|first1=S|last2=Bhugra|first2=D|year=1995|title=Classification of sexual disorders|journal=[[International Review of Psychiatry]]|volume=7|issue=2|pages=167–174|doi=10.3109/09540269509028323}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Transsexual]]ism (F64.0): Desire to live and be accepted as a member of the opposite sex, usually accompanied by a desire for surgery and hormonal treatment
* [[Gender dysphoria in children|Gender identity disorder of childhood]] (F64.2): Persistent and intense distress about one's assigned gender, manifested prior to puberty
* Other gender identity disorders (F64.8)
* Gender identity disorder, unspecified (F64.9)
* [[Sexual maturation disorder]] (F66.0): Uncertainty about one's gender identity or sexual orientation, causing anxiety or distress

The [[ICD-11]], which will come into effect on 1 January 2022, significantly revises classification of gender identity-related conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=International Classification of Diseases|url=https://www.who.int/health-topics/international-classification-of-diseases|access-date=August 11, 2018|publisher=World Health Organization}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under "conditions related to sexual health", the ICD-11 lists "gender incongruence", which is coded into three conditions:&lt;ref name="icd11-gc"&gt;{{cite web|title=Gender incongruence (ICD-11)|url=https://icd.who.int/browse11/l-m/en#/http://id.who.int/icd/entity/411470068|access-date=August 28, 2018|website=icd.who.int|publisher=WHO}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Gender incongruence of adolescence or adulthood (HA60): replaces F64.0
* Gender incongruence of childhood (HA61): replaces F64.2
* Gender incongruence, unspecified (HA6Z): replaces F64.9

In addition, sexual maturation disorder has been removed, along with [[dual-role transvestism]].&lt;ref name="pmid27717275"&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Reed GM, Drescher J, Krueger RB, Atalla E, Cochran SD, First MB, Cohen-Kettenis PT, Arango-de Montis I, Parish SJ, Cottler S, Briken P, Saxena S|date=October 2016|title=Disorders related to sexuality and gender identity in the ICD-11: revising the ICD-10 classification based on current scientific evidence, best clinical practices, and human rights considerations|journal=World Psychiatry|volume=15|issue=3|pages=205–221|doi=10.1002/wps.20354|pmc=5032510|pmid=27717275}}&lt;/ref&gt; ICD-11 defines gender incongruence as "a marked and persistent incongruence between an individual’s experienced gender and the assigned sex", with no requirement for significant distress or impairment.

== Treatment ==
Treatment for a person diagnosed with GD may include psychological counseling, supporting the individual's [[gender expression]], or [[Sex reassignment therapy|hormone therapy or surgery]]. This may involve physical transition resulting from medical interventions such as hormonal treatment, genital surgery, electrolysis or laser hair removal, chest/breast surgery, or other reconstructive surgeries.&lt;ref name="NHS"&gt;{{cite web|year=2016|title=NHS - Treatment - Gender dysphoria|url=https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/gender-dysphoria/treatment/|access-date=January 10, 2019|publisher=NHS}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The goal of treatment may simply be to reduce problems resulting from the person's transgender status, for example, counseling the patient in order to reduce guilt associated with cross-dressing.&lt;ref name="Leiblum-2006"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Leiblum|first=Sandra|title=Principles and Practice of Sex Therapy, Fourth Edition|publisher=The Guilford Press|year=2006|isbn=978-1-59385-349-5|pages=488–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Guidelines have been established to aid clinicians. The [[World Professional Association for Transgender Health]] (WPATH) [[Standards of Care for the Health of Transsexual, Transgender, and Gender Nonconforming People|Standards of Care]] are used by some clinicians as treatment guidelines. Others use guidelines outlined in Gianna Israel and Donald Tarver's ''Transgender Care''.&lt;ref&gt;Heyes, C. J., &amp; Latham, J. R. (2018). Trans surgeries and cosmetic surgeries: The politics of analogy. ''Transgender Studies Quarterly'', ''5''(2), 174-189.&lt;/ref&gt; Guidelines for treatment generally follow a "[[harm reduction]]" model.&lt;ref name="AAP"&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Committee On Adolescence|date=July 2013|title=Office-based care for lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and questioning youth|journal=Pediatrics|volume=132|issue=1|pages=198–203|doi=10.1542/peds.2013-1282|pmid=23796746|quote=However, adolescents with multiple or anonymous partners, having unprotected intercourse, or having substance abuse issues should be tested at shorter intervals.|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GLMA"&gt;{{cite web|year=2013|title=www.glma.org Compendium of Health Profession Association LGBT Policy &amp; Position Statements|url=http://www.glma.org/_data/n_0001/resources/live/GLMA%20Compendium%20of%20Health%20Profession%20Association%20LGBT%20Policy%20and%20Position%20Statements.pdf|access-date=August 27, 2013|publisher=GLMA}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="APA"&gt;{{cite web|year=2011|title=APA Policy Statements on Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, &amp; Transgender Concerns|url=http://www.apa.org/about/policy/booklet.pdf|access-date=August 27, 2013|publisher=American Psychological Association|quote=BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that APA recognizes the efficacy, benefit, and necessity of gender transition treatments for appropriately evaluated individuals and calls upon public and private insurers to cover these medically necessary treatments;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Children ===
{{Main|Gender dysphoria in children}}

The question of whether to counsel young children to be happy with their assigned sex, or to allow them to continue to exhibit behaviors that do not match their assigned sex—or to explore a gender transition—is controversial. Follow-up studies of children with gender dysphoria until 2013 consistently show that the majority of them will not remain gender dysphoric after puberty and will instead identify as gay or lesbian.&lt;ref&gt;Wallien, M. S. C., &amp; Cohen-Kettenis, P. T. (2008). Psychosexual outcome of gender-dysphoric children. ''Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry'', 47, 1413–1423.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Drummond, K. D., Bradley, S. J., Badali-Peterson, M., &amp; Zucker, K. J. (2008). A follow-up study of girls with gender identity disorder. ''Developmental Psychology, 44,'' 34–45.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Steensma, T. D., McGuire, J. K., Kreukels, B. P. C., Beekman, A. J., &amp; Cohen-Kettenis, P. T. (2013). Factors associated with desistence and persistence of childhood gender dysphoria: A quantitative follow-up study. ''Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, 52,'' 582–590.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Update inline|date=June 2021|reason=Last paper published in 2013}} People are more likely to keep having gender dysphoria the more intense their gender dysphoria, cross-gendered behavior, and verbal identification with the desired/experienced gender are (i.e. stating that they ''are'' a different gender rather than ''wish to be'' a different gender).&lt;ref name="Ristori"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Ristori |first1=Jiska |last2=Steensma |first2=Thomas D. |title=Gender dysphoria in childhood |journal=International Review of Psychiatry |date=2 January 2016 |volume=28 |issue=1 |pages=13–20 |doi=10.3109/09540261.2015.1115754|pmid=26754056 |s2cid=5461482 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Professionals who treat gender dysphoria in children sometimes prescribe [[puberty blocker]]s to delay the onset of puberty until a child is believed to be old enough to make an informed decision on whether hormonal or surgical gender reassignment is in their best interest.&lt;ref&gt;''The Transgendered Child: A Handbook for Families and Professionals'' (Brill and Pepper, 2008){{full citation needed|date=May 2016}}{{page needed|date=May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Alleyne"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Alleyne |first1=Richard |title=Puberty blocker for children considering sex change |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/health/news/8454002/Puberty-blocker-for-children-considering-sex-change.html |access-date=1 December 2020 |work=The Telegraph |date=15 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Academy of Pediatrics]] state that "pubertal suppression in children who identify as TGD [transgender and gender diverse] generally leads to improved psychological functioning in adolescence and young adulthood."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Rafferty|first1=Jason|last2=Health|first2=Committee on Psychosocial Aspects of Child and Family|last3=Adolescence|first3=Committee On|last4=Section on Lesbian|first4=Gay|date=2018-10-01|title=Ensuring Comprehensive Care and Support for Transgender and Gender-Diverse Children and Adolescents|url=https://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/142/4/e20182162|journal=Pediatrics|language=en|volume=142|issue=4|pages=e20182162|doi=10.1542/peds.2018-2162|issn=0031-4005|pmid=30224363|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A review commissioned by the UK Department of Health found that there was very low certainty of quality of evidence about puberty blocker outcomes in terms of mental health, quality of life and impact on gender dysphoria.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Evidence review: Gonadotrophin releasing hormone analogues for children and adolescents with gender dysphoria|url=https://arms.nice.org.uk/resources/hub/1070905/attachment|url-status=live|access-date=2 April 2021|quote="The critical outcomes for decision making are the impact on gender dysphoria, mental health and quality of life. The quality of evidence for these outcomes was assessed as very low certainty using modified GRADE."}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Finnish government commissioned a review of the research evidence for treatment of minors and the [[Ministry of Social Affairs and Health|Finnish Ministry of Health]] concluded that there are no research-based health care methods for minors with gender dysphoria.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Finnish guidelines for treatment of child and adolescent gender dysphoria (published march 2021)|url=https://palveluvalikoima.fi/documents/1237350/22895008/Alaik%C3%A4iset_suositus.pdf/c987a74c-dfac-d82f-2142-684f8ddead64/Alaik%C3%A4iset_suositus.pdf|url-status=live|access-date=22 April 2021|website=Council for Choices in Health Care (COHERE)|quote=p. 6: ”Terveydenhuoltolain mukaan (8§) terveydenhuollon toiminnan on perustuttava näyttöön ja hyviin hoito- ja toimintakäytäntöihin. Alaikäisten osalta tutkimusnäyttöön perustuvia terveydenhuollon menetelmiä ei ole.”--- (Google translate:) “According to the Health Care Act (Section 8), health care activities must be based on evidence and good care and operating practices. There are no research-based health care methods for minors.”}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, they recommend the use of puberty blockers for minors on a case-by-case basis. In the [[United States]], several states have introduced or are considering legislation that would prohibit the use of puberty blockers in the treatment of transgender children.&lt;ref name="Safer"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Safer |first1=Joshua D. |title=Controversial pubertal blocker legislation may bring unintended consequences for children |url=https://www.healio.com/news/endocrinology/20200217/controversial-pubertal-blocker-legislation-may-bring-unintended-consequences-for-children# |access-date=15 December 2020 |work=Healio |date=17 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Medical Association]], the [[Endocrine Society]], the [[American Psychological Association]], the  [[American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry]] and the [[American Academy of Pediatrics]] oppose bans on puberty blockers for transgender children.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.endocrine.org/news-and-advocacy/news-room/2019/transgender-custody-statement|title = Endocrine Society urges policymakers to follow science on transgender health}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ama-assn.org/print/pdf/node/66096|title =AMA fights to protect health care for transgender patients}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.apa.org/pi/lgbt/resources/policy/issues/gender-affirmative-care|title =Criminalizing Gender Affirmative Care with Minors}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.aacap.org/AACAP/Latest_News/AACAP_Statement_Responding_to_Efforts-to_ban_Evidence-Based_Care_for_Transgender_and_Gender_Diverse.aspx|title =AACAP Statement Responding to Efforts to ban Evidence-Based Care for Transgender and Gender Diverse Youth}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2021/04/22/transgender-child-sports-treatments/|title =FAQ: What you need to know about transgender children|last1=Schmidt |first1=Samantha|website=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the UK, in the case of ''[[Bell v Tavistock]]'', an appeal court ruled that children under 16 could give consent to receiving puberty blockers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Siddique |first1=Haroon |title=Appeal court overturns UK puberty blockers ruling for under-16s 17 September 2021 |url=https://www.theguardian.com/society/2021/sep/17/appeal-court-overturns-uk-puberty-blockers-ruling-for-under-16s-tavistock-keira-bell |website=Guardian |date=17 September 2021 |publisher=Guardian |access-date=17 September 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Psychological treatments ===
{{Main|Psychotherapy}}
Until the 1970s, psychotherapy was the primary treatment for gender dysphoria and generally was directed to helping the person adjust to their assigned sex. Psychotherapy is any therapeutic interaction that aims to treat a psychological problem. Psychotherapy may be used in addition to biological interventions, although some clinicians use only psychotherapy to treat gender dysphoria.&lt;ref name="treatment review"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Gijs|first1=L|last2=Brawaeys|first2=A|year=2007|title=Surgical Treatment of Gender Dysphoria in Adults and Adolescents: Recent Developments, Effectiveness, and Challenges|journal=Annual Review of Sex Research|volume=18|issue=178–224}}&lt;/ref&gt; Psychotherapeutic treatment of GD involves helping the patient to adapt to their gender incongruence or to explorative investigation of confounding co-occurring&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Kaltiala-Heino|first1=Riittakerttu|last2=Sumia|first2=Maria|last3=Työläjärvi|first3=Marja|last4=Lindberg|first4=Nina|date=2015|title=Two years of gender identity service for minors: overrepresentation of natal girls with severe problems in adolescent development|journal=Child and Adolescent Psychiatry and Mental Health|volume=9|pages=9|doi=10.1186/s13034-015-0042-y|issn=1753-2000|pmc=4396787|pmid=25873995|quote=" "for the majority of adolescent-onset cases, GD presented in the context of severe mental disorders and general identity confusion. In such situations, appropriate treatment for psychiatric comorbidities may be warranted before conclusions regarding gender identity can be drawn.","There is still no clear consensus regarding hormonal treatment for adolescents because long-term data are unavailable;","In a nationwide long-term follow-up study of adult cases, psychiatric morbidity, suicide attempts and suicide mortality persisted as elevated after juridical and medical SR."}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Swedish National Board of Health and Welfare|date=Feb 2020|title=Development of the diagnosis gender dysphoria (Swedish)|url=https://www.socialstyrelsen.se/globalassets/sharepoint-dokument/artikelkatalog/ovrigt/2020-2-6600.pdf|url-status=live|access-date=13 March 2021|website=socialstyrelsen.se}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Kozlowska|first1=Kasia|last2=Chudleigh|first2=Catherine|last3=McClure|first3=Georgia|last4=Maguire|first4=Ann M.|last5=Ambler|first5=Geoffrey R.|date=2021-01-12|title=Attachment Patterns in Children and Adolescents With Gender Dysphoria|journal=Frontiers in Psychology|volume=11|pages=582688|doi=10.3389/fpsyg.2020.582688|pmid=33510668|pmc=7835132|issn=1664-1078|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=D’Angelo|first1=Roberto|last2=Syrulnik|first2=Ema|last3=Ayad|first3=Sasha|last4=Marchiano|first4=Lisa|last5=Kenny|first5=Dianna Theadora|last6=Clarke|first6=Patrick|date=2021-01-01|title=One Size Does Not Fit All: In Support of Psychotherapy for Gender Dysphoria|url= |journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|language=en|volume=50|issue=1|pages=7–16|doi=10.1007/s10508-020-01844-2|issn=1573-2800|pmc=7878242|pmid=33089441}}&lt;/ref&gt; mental health issues. Attempts to alleviate GD by changing the patient's gender identity to reflect assigned sex have been ineffective.&lt;ref name="merck manual"&gt;{{cite book|author=George R. Brown, MD|title=The Merck Manual of Diagnosis and Therapy|title-link=Merck Manual of Diagnosis and Therapy|date=July 20, 2011|publisher=[[Merck &amp; Co.]], Inc.|isbn=978-0-911910-19-3|editor1=Robert S. Porter, MD|edition=19th|location=[[Whitehouse Station, NJ]], USA|pages=1740–1747|chapter=Chapter 165 Sexuality and Sexual Disorders|display-editors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|1741}}

=== Biological treatments ===
{{Main|Sex reassignment therapy}}
Biological treatments physically alter [[Primary sex characteristic|primary]] and [[Secondary sex characteristic|secondary]] sex characteristics to reduce the discrepancy between an individual's physical body and gender identity.&lt;ref name="care guidelines"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bockting|first1=W|last2=Knudson|first2=G|last3=Goldberg|first3=J|date=January 2006|title=Counselling and Mental Health Care of Transgender Adults and Loved Ones|journal=International Journal of Transgenderism|volume=9|issue=3–4|pages=35–82|doi=10.1300/J485v09n03_03|s2cid=71503744|quote="As per Figure 1, delusions about sex or gender, dissociative disorders, thought disorders,or obsessive or compulsive features should be evaluated and treated prior to proceeding with hormone therapy or surgery. Thought disorders, dissociative disorders, and obsessive-compulsive disorders can, rarely, cause a transient wish for sex reassignment which disappears or significantly lessens when the underlying mental health condition is treated. It is important to treat these disorders before proceeding with hormones or surgery to ensure that the desire for alteration of primary or secondary sex characteristics is not a temporary desire." See also [https://www.wpath.org/publications/soc WPATH Standards of Care, version 7], page 23:“The role of mental health professionals includes making reasonably sure that the gender dysphoria is not secondary to or better accounted for by other diagnoses.” And the paradigmatic [http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00918369.2012.653300 Dutch model] for consideration of comorbid conditions before proceeding with treatment for childhood onset.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biological treatments for GD are typically undertaken in conjunction with psychotherapy; however, the [[HBIGDA-SOC|WPATH Standards of Care]] state that psychotherapy should not be an absolute requirement for biological treatments.&lt;ref name="SOC28"&gt;{{cite web |title=Standards of Care for the Health of Transsexual, Transgender, and Gender Nonconforming People |url=https://www.wpath.org/media/cms/Documents/SOC%20v7/SOC%20V7_English.pdf |publisher=World Professional Association for Transgender Health |access-date=15 March 2021 |pages=28–29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is known that some mental disorders are important to evaluate and treat before proceeding with hormones or surgery, as treatment of these mental disorders can sometimes make the wish for altering one's body disappear or significantly lessen.&lt;ref name="care guidelines" /&gt; 

Psychotherapy, [[transgender hormone therapy|hormone therapy]], and [[sex reassignment surgery]] can be effective at treating GD when the WPATH Standards of Care 6 are followed.&lt;ref name="merck manual" /&gt;{{rp|1570}} Hormonal treatments have been shown to reduce a number of symptoms of psychiatric distress associated with gender dysphoria.&lt;ref name = Neuroimaging&gt;{{cite journal |title=Neuroimaging gender dysphoria: a novel psychobiological model |journal=Brain Imaging and Behavior |last1=Altinay |first1=Murat |last2=Anand |first2=Amit |year=2020 |volume=14 |issue=4 |pages=1281–1297 |doi=10.1007/s11682-019-00121-8 |pmid=31134582 |s2cid=167207854 |url=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11682-019-00121-8 |accessdate=2021-10-16 |quote=A recently published study (Colizzi et al. 2014), where 118 patients were followed before and 12 months after HRT revealed that 14% of the patients had comorbid Axis-I psychiatric diagnosis. Psychiatric distress and impairment were found to be higher in the beginning phase of the study but after HRT, there was a significant improvement in major depressive disorder, anxiety and functional impairment. Similarly, Fisher and colleagues’ (Fisher et al. 2013) 2013 paper suggests that the dysfunction and impairment in the transgender population is highly associated with lack of HRT, which may suggest that at least a fraction of the impairment that was documented as comorbid Axis-I psychiatric disorders could in fact be impairment from GD. Finally, a metanalysis done by Dhejne and colleagues (Dhejne et al. 2016) reviewed 38 longitudinal studies that investigated psychiatric comorbidities pre and post gender affirmation treatments in transgender people with GD. The results of this analysis indicate that depression and GAD do have higher prevalence in transgender population but this finding was isolated to baseline (pre-gender affirmation treatments) where after gender affirmation therapies, rate of psychiatric comorbidities decreased to cisgender population levels }}&lt;/ref&gt; A WPATH commissioned systematic review of the outcomes of hormone therapy "found evidence that gender-affirming hormone therapy may be associated with improvements in [quality of life] scores and decreases in depression and anxiety symptoms among transgender people." The strength of the evidence was low due to methodological limitations of the studies undertaken.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Hormone Therapy, Mental Health, and Quality of Life Among Transgender People: A Systematic Review|url=https://doi.org/10.1210/jendso/bvab011|journal=[[Journal of the Endocrine Society]]|year=2021|doi=10.1210/jendso/bvab011|quote=This systematic review of 20 studies found evidence that gender-affirming hormone therapy may be associated with improvements in QOL scores and decreases in depression and anxiety symptoms among transgender people. Associations were similar across gender identity and age. The strength of evidence for these conclusions is low due to methodological limitations.|last1=Baker|first1=Kellan E.|last2=Wilson|first2=Lisa M.|last3=Sharma|first3=Ritu|last4=Dukhanin|first4=Vadim|last5=McArthur|first5=Kristen|last6=Robinson|first6=Karen A.|volume=5|issue=4|pages=bvab011|pmid=33644622|pmc=7894249}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those who choose to undergo sex reassignment surgery report high satisfaction rates with the outcome, though these studies have limitations including risk of bias (lack of randomization, lack of controlled studies, self-reported outcomes) and high loss to follow up.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Murad|first1=Mohammad Hassan|last2=Elamin|first2=Mohamed B.|last3=Garcia|first3=Magaly Zumaeta|last4=Mullan|first4=Rebecca J.|last5=Murad|first5=Ayman|last6=Erwin|first6=Patricia J.|last7=Montori|first7=Victor M.|date=February 2010|title=Hormonal therapy and sex reassignment: a systematic review and meta-analysis of quality of life and psychosocial outcomes|url=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19473181/|journal=Clinical Endocrinology|volume=72|issue=2|pages=214–231|doi=10.1111/j.1365-2265.2009.03625.x|issn=1365-2265|pmid=19473181|s2cid=19590739|quote="The evidence in this review is of very low quality9, 10 due to the serious methodological limitations of included studies. Studies lacked bias protection measures such as randomization and control groups, and generally depended on self-report to ascertain the exposure (i.e. hormonal therapy was self-reported as opposed to being extracted from medical records). Our reliance on reported outcome measures may also indicate a higher risk of reporting bias within the studies. Statistical heterogeneity of the results was also significant."}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Sutcliffe|first1=P. A.|last2=Dixon|first2=S.|last3=Akehurst|first3=R. L.|last4=Wilkinson|first4=A.|last5=Shippam|first5=A.|last6=White|first6=S.|last7=Richards|first7=R.|last8=Caddy|first8=C. M.|date=March 2009|title=Evaluation of surgical procedures for sex reassignment: a systematic review|url=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18222742/|journal=Journal of Plastic, Reconstructive &amp; Aesthetic Surgery: JPRAS|volume=62|issue=3|pages=294–306; discussion 306–308|doi=10.1016/j.bjps.2007.12.009|issn=1878-0539|pmid=18222742|quote="The evidence concerning gender reassignment surgery in both MTF and FTM transsexism has several limitations in terms of: (a) lack of controlled studies, (b) evidence has not collected data prospectively, (c) high loss to follow up and (d) lack of validated assessment measures. Some satisfactory outcomes were reported, but the magnitude of benefit and harm for individual surgical procedures cannot be estimated accurately using the current available evidence."}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For adolescents, much is unknown, including persistence. Disagreement among practitioners regarding treatment of adolescents is in part due to the lack of long-term data.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Young people qualifying for biomedical treatment according to the Dutch model&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Cohen-Kettenis|first1=Peggy T.|last2=Delemarre-van de Waal|first2=Henriette A.|last3=Gooren|first3=Louis J. G.|date=2008|title=The treatment of adolescent transsexuals: changing insights|url=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18564158/|journal=The Journal of Sexual Medicine|volume=5|issue=8|pages=1892–1897|doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2008.00870.x|issn=1743-6109|pmid=18564158}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=de Vries|first1=Annelou L. C.|last2=McGuire|first2=Jenifer K.|last3=Steensma|first3=Thomas D.|last4=Wagenaar|first4=Eva C. F.|last5=Doreleijers|first5=Theo A. H.|last6=Cohen-Kettenis|first6=Peggy T.|date=2014|title=Young adult psychological outcome after puberty suppression and gender reassignment|url=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25201798/|journal=Pediatrics|volume=134|issue=4|pages=696–704|doi=10.1542/peds.2013-2958|issn=1098-4275|pmid=25201798|s2cid=18155489}}&lt;/ref&gt; (including having GD from early childhood on which intensifies at puberty and absence of psychiatric comorbidities that could challenge diagnosis or treatment) found reduction in gender dysphoria, although limitations to these outcome studies have been noted, such as lack of controls or considering alternatives like psychotherapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Zucker|first=Kenneth J.|date=2019-10-01|title=Adolescents with Gender Dysphoria: Reflections on Some Contemporary Clinical and Research Issues|url=https://doi.org/10.1007/s10508-019-01518-8|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|language=en|volume=48|issue=7|pages=1983–1992|doi=10.1007/s10508-019-01518-8|pmid=31321594|s2cid=197663705|issn=1573-2800|quote="In the Dutch model, several factors were identified in deeming adolescent eligibility for early biomedical treatment. According to Cohen-Kettenis, Delemarre-van de Waal, and Gooren (2008), these included the following: (1) the presence of gender dysphoria from early childhood on; (2) an exacerbation of the gender dysphoria after the first signs of puberty; (3) the absence of psychiatric comorbidity that would interfere with a diagnostic evaluation or treatment; (4) adequate psychological and social support during treatment; and (5) a demonstration of knowledge of the sex/gender reassignment process. Several studies have reported on the benefits of this therapeutic protocol in reducing gender dysphoria (e.g., de Vries et al., 2014, which is the best study to date). Of course, one should bear in mind some of the limitation to these outcome studies, including the fact that not all assessed adolescents were deemed eligible for the treatment protocol (and thus we know relatively little about the longer-term outcomes of these youth) and that study designs have not included alternative treatment options (such as psychosocial therapy) or even being assigned to a wait-list control condition;"}}&lt;/ref&gt;

More rigorous studies are needed to assess the effectiveness, safety, and long-term benefits and risks of hormonal and surgical treatments.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Hembree|first1=Wylie C|last2=Cohen-Kettenis|first2=Peggy T|last3=Gooren|first3=Louis|last4=Hannema|first4=Sabine E|last5=Meyer|first5=Walter J|last6=Murad|first6=M Hassan|last7=Rosenthal|first7=Stephen M|last8=Safer|first8=Joshua D|last9=Tangpricha|first9=Vin|last10=T’Sjoen|first10=Guy G|date=2017-11-01|title=Endocrine Treatment of Gender-Dysphoric/Gender-Incongruent Persons: An Endocrine Society Clinical Practice Guideline|journal=The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism|volume=102|issue=11|pages=3869–3903|doi=10.1210/jc.2017-01658|issn=0021-972X|pmid=28945902|quote="In the future, we need more rigorous evaluations of the effectiveness and safety of endocrine and surgical protocols.Specifically, endocrine treatment protocols for GD/gender incongruence should include the careful assessment of the following: (1) the effects of prolonged delay of puberty in adolescents on bone health, gonadal function, and the brain (including effects on cognitive, emotional, social, and sexual development); [...] and (4) the risks and benefits of gender-affirming hormone treatment in older transgender people.” “Future research is needed to ascertain the potential harm of hormonal therapies (176).” "The satisfaction rate with surgical reassignment of sex is now very high (187).“Owing to the lack of controlled studies, incomplete follow-up, and lack of valid assessment measures, evaluating various surgical approaches and techniques is difficult." "Several postoperative studies report significant long-term psychological and psychiatric pathology (259–261).” "We need more studies with appropriate controls that examine long-term quality of life, psychosocial outcomes, and psychiatric outcomes to determine the long-term benefits of surgical treatment.”|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, a 2020 Cochrane review found insufficient evidence&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Haupt|first1=Claudia|last2=Henke|first2=Miriam|last3=Kutschmar|first3=Alexia|last4=Hauser|first4=Birgit|last5=Baldinger|first5=Sandra|last6=Saenz|first6=Sarah Rafaela|last7=Schreiber|first7=Gerhard|date=2020-11-28|title=Antiandrogen or estradiol treatment or both during hormone therapy in transitioning transgender women|url=https://www.cochranelibrary.com/cdsr/doi/10.1002/14651858.CD013138.pub2|journal=Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews|volume=11|pages=CD013138|doi=10.1002/14651858.cd013138.pub2|pmid=33251587|pmc=8078580|issn=1465-1858|quote=We found insufficient evidence to determine the efficacy or safety of hormonal treatment approaches for transgender women in transition.|pmc-embargo-date=November 28, 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; to determine whether feminizing hormones were safe or effective. Several studies have found significant long-term psychological and psychiatric pathology after surgical treatments.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; The Swedish West Region commissioned Health Technology Assessment found in 2018 that the certainty of the evidence for sustained satisfaction with surgery was very low.&lt;ref&gt;Georgas K, Beckman U, Bryman I, Elander A, Jivegård L, Mattelin E, et al. Gender affirmation surgery for gender dysphoria - effects and risks. [Könskonfirmerande kirurgi vid könsdysfori - effekter och risker]. Göteborg: Västra Götalandsregionen, Sahlgrenska University Hospital, HTA-centrum: 2018. Regional activity based HTA 2018:102. https://alfresco-offentlig.vgregion.se/alfresco/service/vgr/storage/node/content/workspace/SpacesStore/441006af-62a7-4f19-be73-6d698bf635f5/2018_102%20Rapport%20K%c3%b6nsdysfori.pdf?a=false&amp;guest=true&lt;/ref&gt;

== Comorbidities ==
Among youth, around 20% to 30% of individuals heading to gender clinics meet the DSM criteria for a [[anxiety disorder]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Janssen|first1=Aron|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DLZcDwAAQBAJ&amp;q=ADHD+gender+dysphoria|title=Affirmative Mental Health Care for Transgender and Gender Diverse Youth: A Clinical Guide|last2=Leibowitz|first2=Scott|date=2018-05-22|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-3-319-78307-9|pages=8|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

A review in 2014 stated that gender dysphoria symptoms in people with [[schizophrenia]] may arise due to delusionally changed gender identity or appear regardless of psychotic process.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Stusiński|first1=Jarosław|last2=Lew-Starowicz|first2=Michał|date=2018-12-29|title=Gender dysphoria symptoms in schizophrenia|journal=Psychiatria Polska|volume=52|issue=6|pages=1053–1062|doi=10.12740/PP/80013|issn=2391-5854|pmid=30659566|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A widely held view among clinicians is that there is an over-representation of [[Neurodevelopmental disorder|neurodevelopmental conditions]] amongst individuals with GD, although this view has been questioned.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Thrower|first1=Emily|last2=Bretherton|first2=Ingrid|last3=Pang|first3=Ken C.|last4=Zajac|first4=Jeffrey D.|last5=Cheung|first5=Ada S.|date=2020-03-01|title=Prevalence of Autism Spectrum Disorder and Attention-Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder Amongst Individuals with Gender Dysphoria: A Systematic Review|url=https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-019-04298-1|journal=Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders|language=en|volume=50|issue=3|pages=695–706|doi=10.1007/s10803-019-04298-1|issn=1573-3432|pmid=31732891|s2cid=208061795}}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies on children and adolescents with gender dysphoria have found a high prevalence of [[Autism spectrum|autism spectrum disorder]] (ASD) traits or a confirmed diagnosis of ASD. Adults with gender dysphoria attending specialist gender clinics have also been shown to have high rates of ASD traits or an autism diagnosis as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Kyriakou|first1=Andreas|last2=Nicolaides|first2=Nicolas C.|last3=Skordis|first3=Nicos|date=2020|title=Current approach to the clinical care of adolescents with gender dysphoria|journal=Acta Bio Medica : Atenei Parmensis|volume=91|issue=1|pages=165–175|doi=10.23750/abm.v91i1.9244|issn=0392-4203|pmc=7569586|pmid=32191677}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been estimated that children with ASD were over four times as likely to be diagnosed with GD,&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; with ASD being reported from 6% to over 20% of teens referring to gender identity services.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Kaltiala-Heino|first1=Riittakerttu|last2=Bergman|first2=Hannah|last3=Työläjärvi|first3=Marja|last4=Frisén|first4=Louise|date=2018-03-02|title=Gender dysphoria in adolescence: current perspectives|journal=Adolescent Health, Medicine and Therapeutics|volume=9|pages=31–41|doi=10.2147/AHMT.S135432|issn=1179-318X|pmc=5841333|pmid=29535563}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Epidemiology ==
{{See also|Transgender#Population figures|Transsexual#Prevalence}}

The DSM-5 estimates that about 0.005% to 0.014% of people assigned male at birth and 0.002% to 0.003% of people assigned female at birth are diagnosable with gender dysphoria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/diagnosticstatis0005unse/page/454|title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 5|publisher=[[American Psychiatric Association]]|year=2013|isbn=978-0-89042-555-8|page=[https://archive.org/details/diagnosticstatis0005unse/page/454 454]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to ''[[Black's Medical Dictionary]]'', gender dysphoria “occurs in one in 30,000 male births and one in 100,000 female births.”&lt;ref&gt;Gender Identity Disorders.  [https://www.google.com/books/edition/Black_s_Medical_Dictionary/6asrDwAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;gbpv=1&amp;bsq=Gender%20identity%20disorders  in Harvey Marcovitch, ed. Black's Medical Dictionary, 43rd edition, New York: Bloomsbury, 2018]&lt;/ref&gt; Studies in European countries in the early 2000s found that about 1 in 12,000 natal male adults and 1 in 30,000 natal female adults seek out [[sex reassignment surgery]].&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Zucker|first=Kenneth J.|date=2017|title=Epidemiology of gender dysphoria and transgender identity|url=http://www.publish.csiro.au/?paper=SH17067|journal=Sexual Health|language=en|volume=14|issue=5|pages=404–411|doi=10.1071/SH17067|pmid=28838353|issn=1448-5028}}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies of hormonal treatment or legal name change find higher prevalence than sex reassignment, with, for example a 2010 Swedish study finding that 1 in 7,750 adult natal males and 1 in 13,120 adult natal females requested a legal name change to a name of the opposite gender.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; 

Studies that measure transgender status by self-identification find even higher rates of gender identity different from sex assigned at birth (although some of those who identify as transgender or gender nonconforming may not experience clinically significant distress and so do not have gender dysphoria). A study in [[New Zealand]] found that 1 in 3,630 natal males and 1 in 22,714 natal females have changed their legal gender markers.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;  A survey of [[Massachusetts]] adults found that 0.5% identify as transgender.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name="AJPH"&gt;{{Citation|last1=Conron|first1=KJ|title=Transgender Health in Massachusetts: Results from a Household Probability Sample of Adults|date=January 2012|journal=[[American Journal of Public Health]]|volume=102|issue=1|pages=118–222|publisher=[[American Public Health Association]]|doi=10.2105/AJPH.2011.300315|issn=1541-0048|oclc=01642844|pmc=3490554|pmid=22095354|quote=Between 2007 and 2009, survey participants aged 18 to 64 years in the Massachusetts Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (MA-BRFSS; N = 28 662) were asked: "Some people describe themselves as transgender when they experience a different gender identity from their sex at birth. For example, a person born into a male body, but who feels female or lives as a woman. Do you consider yourself to be transgender?" […] We restricted the analytic sample to 28176 participants who answered yes or no to the transgender question (excluding n=364, 1.0% weighted who declined to respond. […] Transgender respondents (n=131; 0.5%; 95% confidence interval [CI]=0.3%, 0.6%) were somewhat younger and more likely to be Hispanic than were nontransgender respondents.|last2=Scott|first2=G|last3=Stowell|first3=GS|last4=Landers|first4=S}}&lt;/ref&gt; A national survey in [[New Zealand]] of 8,500 randomly selected secondary school students from 91 randomly selected high schools found 1.2% of students responded "yes" to the question "Do you think you are transgender?".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Clark TC, Lucassen MF, Bullen P, Denny SJ, Fleming TM, Robinson EM, Rossen FV|date=July 2014|title=The health and well-being of transgender high school students: results from the New Zealand adolescent health survey (Youth'12)|journal=The Journal of Adolescent Health|volume=55|issue=1|pages=93–9|doi=10.1016/j.jadohealth.2013.11.008|pmid=24438852|quote=Whether a student was transgender was measured by the question, "Do you think you are transgender? This is a girl who feels like she should have been a boy, or a boy who feels like he should have been a girl (e.g., Trans, Queen, [[Fa'afafine|Fa’faffine]], Whakawahine, Tangata ira Tane, [[Genderqueer]])?" […] Over 8,000 students (n = 8,166) answered the question about whether they were transgender. Approximately 95% of students did not report being transgender (n=7,731; 94.7%), 96 students reported being transgender (1.2%), 202 reported not being sure (2.5%), and 137 did not understand the question (1.7%).|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Outside of a clinical setting, the stability of transgender or non-binary identities is unknown.&lt;ref name=:0/&gt; 

Research indicates people who [[Transitioning (transgender)|transition]] in adulthood are up to three times more likely to be male assigned at birth, but that among people transitioning in childhood the sex ratio is close to 1:1.&lt;ref name="prevalence"&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Landén M, Wålinder J, Lundström B|date=April 1996|title=Prevalence, incidence and sex ratio of transsexualism|journal=Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica|volume=93|issue=4|pages=221–3|doi=10.1111/j.1600-0447.1996.tb10638.x|pmid=8712018|quote=On average, the male [to female]:female [to male] ratio in prevalence studies is estimated to be 3:1. However […] the incidence studies have shown a considerably lower male [to female] predominance. In Sweden and England and Wales, a sex ratio of 1:1 has been reported. In the most recent incidence data from Sweden, there is a slight male [to female] predominance among the group consisting of all applicants for sex reassignment, while in the group of primary [early onset] transsexuals there is no difference in incidence between men and women.|s2cid=26661088}}&lt;/ref&gt; The prevalence of [[gender dysphoria in children]] is unknown due to the absence of formal prevalence studies.&lt;ref name="Ristori" /&gt;

== History ==
Neither the [[DSM-I]] (1952) nor the [[DSM-II]] (1968) contained a diagnosis analogous to gender dysphoria. Gender identity disorder first appeared as a diagnosis in the [[DSM-III]] (1980), where it appeared under "psychosexual disorders" but was used only for the childhood diagnosis. Adolescents and adults received a diagnosis of transsexualism (homosexual, heterosexual, or asexual type). The DSM-III-R (1987) added "Gender Identity Disorder of Adolescence and Adulthood, Non-Transsexual Type" (GIDAANT).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Koh J|year=2012|title=[The history of the concept of gender identity disorder]|journal=Seishin Shinkeigaku Zasshi = Psychiatria et Neurologia Japonica|volume=114|issue=6|pages=673–80|pmid=22844818}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Pauly|first1=Ira B.|year=1993|title=Terminology and Classification of Gender Identity Disorders|journal=Journal of Psychology &amp; Human Sexuality|volume=5|issue=4|pages=1–14|doi=10.1300/J056v05n04_01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Drescher, Jack, [[doi:10.1080/19359701003589637|Transsexualism, Gender Identity Disorder and the DSM]], ''Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Mental Health'' 14, no. 2 (2010): 112.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Society and culture ==
[[File:2013 Rally for Transgender Equality 21175.jpg|right|thumb|A sign at a trans rights rally: "Gender is like that old jumper from my cousin: It was given to me and it doesn't fit."]]
Researchers disagree about the nature of distress and impairment in people with GD. Some authors have suggested that people with GD suffer because they are [[social stigma|stigmatized]] and [[victimisation|victimized]];&lt;ref name="Karl Bryant"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Bryant|first=Karl Edward|title=The Politics of Pathology and the Making of Gender Identity Disorder|year=2007|isbn=978-0-549-26816-1|location=Ann Arbor, Michigan|page=222}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that, if society had less strict gender divisions, transgender people would suffer less.&lt;ref name="Giordano-2012"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Giordano|first=Simona|title=Children with Gender Identity Disorder: A Clinical, Ethical, and Legal Analysis|publisher=Routledge|year=2012|isbn=978-0-415-50271-9|location=New Jersey|page=147}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some controversy surrounds the creation of the GD diagnosis, with Davy et al. stating that although the creators of the diagnosis state that it has rigorous scientific support, "it is impossible to scrutinize such claims, since the discussions, methodological processes, and promised field trials of the diagnosis have not been published."&lt;ref name="Davy"/&gt;

Some cultures have [[Third gender|three defined genders]]: man, woman, and effeminate man. For example, in [[Samoa]], the ''[[fa'afafine]]'', a group of [[feminine males]], are entirely socially accepted. The fa'afafine do not have any of the stigma or distress typically associated in most cultures with deviating from a male/female gender role. This suggests the distress so frequently associated with GD in a Western context is not ''caused'' by the disorder itself, but by difficulties encountered from social disapproval by one's culture.&lt;ref name="fa'afafine"&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Vasey PL, Bartlett NH|year=2007|title=What can the Samoan "Fa'afafine" teach us about the Western concept of gender identity disorder in childhood?|journal=Perspectives in Biology and Medicine|volume=50|issue=4|pages=481–90|doi=10.1353/pbm.2007.0056|pmid=17951883|s2cid=37437172}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, research has found that the anxiety associated with gender dysphoria persists in cultures, Eastern or otherwise, which are more accepting of gender nonconformity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/diagnosticstatis0005unse/page/459|title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 5|publisher=[[American Psychiatric Association]]|year=2013|isbn=978-0-89042-555-8|page=[https://archive.org/details/diagnosticstatis0005unse/page/459 459]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Australia, a 2014 High Court of Australia judgment unanimously ruled in favor of a plaintiff named [[Norrie May-Welby|Norrie]], who asked to be classified by a third gender category, 'non-specific', after a long court battle with the NSW Registrar of Births, Deaths and Marriages.&lt;ref name="Norrie"&gt;{{cite AustLII|HCA|11|2014|litigants=NSW Registrar of Births, Deaths and Marriages v Norrie|courtname=auto|date=April 2, 2014}}.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Court did not accept that gender was a social construction: it found that sex reassignment "surgery did not resolve her sexual ambiguity".&lt;ref name="Norrie" /&gt;{{rp|para 11}}

=== Classification as a disorder ===
The [[mental disorder|psychiatric diagnosis]] of gender identity disorder (now gender dysphoria) was introduced in DSM-III in 1980. [[Arlene Istar Lev]] and [[Deborah Rudacille]] have characterized the addition as a political maneuver to re-stigmatize homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lev|first=Arlene Istar|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LwxvazLRmiEC&amp;q=homosexuality+dsm-iii+transsexuality&amp;pg=PA172|title=Transgender Emergence: Therapeutic Guidelines for Working with Gender-Variant People and Their Families|publisher=Haworth Press|year=2004|isbn=978-0-7890-2117-5|page=172|author-link=Arlene Istar Lev}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rudacille|first=Deborah|title=The Riddle of Gender: Science, Activism, and Transgender Rights|date=February 2005|publisher=Pantheon|isbn=978-0-375-42162-4|author-link=Deborah Rudacille}}{{page needed|date=May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Homosexuality was removed from DSM-II in 1974.) By contrast, [[Kenneth Zucker]] and [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] argue that gender identity disorder was included in DSM-III because it "met the generally accepted criteria used by the framers of DSM-III for inclusion."&lt;ref name="Historical Note"&gt;{{citation|last1=Zucker|first1=KJ|title=Was the gender identity disorder of childhood diagnosis introduced into DSM-III as a backdoor maneuver to replace homosexuality? A historical note.|date=Jan–Feb 2005|journal=Journal of Sex and Marital Therapy|volume=31|issue=1|pages=31–42|doi=10.1080/00926230590475251|pmid=15841704|last2=Spitzer|first2=RL|author-link=Kenneth Zucker|author2-link=Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|s2cid=22589255}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some researchers, including Spitzer and Paul J. Fink, contend that the behaviors and experiences seen in transsexualism are abnormal and constitute a dysfunction.&lt;ref name="PsychNews"&gt;{{cite news|title=Controversy Continues to Grow Over DSM's GID Diagnosis|publisher=Psychiatric News|url=http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleid=106462}}&lt;/ref&gt; The American Psychiatric Association stated that [[gender nonconformity]] is not the same thing as gender dysphoria,&lt;ref name="What Is"/&gt; and that "gender nonconformity is not in itself a mental disorder. The critical element of gender dysphoria is the presence of clinically significant distress associated with the condition."&lt;ref name="DSM-5 fact sheet"/&gt;

Individuals with gender dysphoria may or may not regard their own cross-gender feelings and behaviors as a disorder. Advantages and disadvantages exist to classifying gender dysphoria as a disorder.&lt;ref name="Standards of Care" /&gt; Because gender dysphoria had been classified as a disorder in medical texts (such as the previous DSM manual, the DSM-IV-TR, under the name "gender identity disorder"), many insurance companies are willing to cover some of the expenses of sex reassignment therapy. Without the classification of gender dysphoria as a medical disorder, sex reassignment therapy may be viewed as a cosmetic treatment, rather than medically necessary treatment, and may not be covered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ford|first=Zack|title=APA Revises Manual: Being Transgender is No Longer a Mental Disorder|website=[[ThinkProgress]]|url=http://thinkprogress.org/lgbt/2012/12/03/1271431/apa-revises-manual-being-transgender-is-no-longer-a-mental-disorder/?mobile=nc|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130202082602/http://thinkprogress.org/lgbt/2012/12/03/1271431/apa-revises-manual-being-transgender-is-no-longer-a-mental-disorder/?mobile=nc|archive-date=February 2, 2013|access-date=April 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, transgender people are less likely than others to have health insurance, and often face hostility and insensitivity from healthcare providers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Mallon|first=Gerald P.|title=Social Work Practice with Transgender and Gender Variant Youth|publisher=Routledge|year=2009|isbn=978-0-415-99482-8|location=New Jersey}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The DSM-IV-TR diagnostic component of distress is not inherent in the cross-gender identity; rather, it is related to social rejection and discrimination suffered by the individual.&lt;ref name="fa'afafine" /&gt; Psychology professor Darryl Hill insists that gender dysphoria is not a mental disorder, but rather that the diagnostic criteria reflect psychological distress in children that occurs when parents and others have trouble relating to their child's gender variance.&lt;ref name="PsychNews" /&gt; Transgender people have often been harassed, socially excluded, and subjected to discrimination, abuse and violence, including murder.&lt;ref name="Davidson-2012" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Giordano-2012" /&gt;

In December 2002, the British Lord Chancellor's office published a ''Government Policy Concerning Transsexual People'' document that categorically states, "What transsexualism is not ... It is not a mental illness."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year=2003|title=Government Policy concerning Transsexual People|url=http://www.dca.gov.uk/constitution/transsex/policy.htm|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080511211217/http://www.dca.gov.uk/constitution/transsex/policy.htm|archive-date=May 11, 2008|work=People's rights/Transsexual people|publisher=U.K. Department for Constitutional Affairs}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2009, the government of France declared that a transsexual gender identity will no longer be classified as a psychiatric condition,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=May 16, 2009|title=La transsexualité ne sera plus classée comme affectation psychiatrique|work=Le Monde|url=http://www.lemonde.fr/societe/article/2009/05/16/la-transsexualite-ne-sera-plus-classee-comme-affectation-psychiatrique_1193860_3224.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; but according to French trans rights organizations, beyond the impact of the announcement itself, nothing changed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=May 17, 2011|title=La France est très en retard dans la prise en charge des transsexuels|language=fr|work=Libération|url=http://www.liberation.fr/societe/2011/05/17/la-france-est-tres-en-retard-dans-la-prise-en-charge-des-transsexuels_736344|quote=En réalité, ce décret n'a été rien d'autre qu'un coup médiatique, un très bel effet d'annonce. Sur le terrain, rien n'a changé.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Denmark made a similar statement in 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=May 14, 2016|title=Denmark will become first country to no longer define being transgender as a mental illness|work=The Independent|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/denmark-will-be-the-first-country-to-no-longer-define-being-transgender-as-a-mental-illness-a7029151.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the ICD-11, GID is reclassified as "gender incongruence", a condition related to sexual health.&lt;ref name="icd11-gc" /&gt; The working group responsible for this recategorization recommended keeping such a diagnosis in ICD-11 to preserve access to health services.&lt;ref name=pmid27717275 /&gt;

===Gender euphoria===
Gender euphoria (GE) is a proposed term for the satisfaction or enjoyment felt by a person due to consistency between their [[gender identity]] and gendered features associated with a gender different to the sex they were [[Sex assignment|assigned at birth]]. It is meant to be the positive counterpart of gender dysphoria.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Benestad|first=E.E.P.|date=October 2010|title=From gender dysphoria to gender euphoria: An assisted journey|url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.sexol.2010.09.003|journal=Sexologies|volume=19|issue=4|pages=225–231|doi=10.1016/j.sexol.2010.09.003|issn=1158-1360}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Transmedicalism]]
* {{slink|ICD-11|Gender incongruence}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite web|url=http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TSsuccesses/TransMen.html|title=Successful TransMen: Links and Photos|first=Lynn|last=Conway|author-link=Lynn Conway|work=ai.eecs.umich.edu|date=June 26, 2014|access-date=December 2, 2014}}
* {{cite web|url=http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TSsuccesses/TSsuccesses.html|title=Transsexual Women's Successes: Links and Photos|first=Lynn|last=Conway|work=ai.eecs.umich.edu|date=February 5, 2011|access-date=December 2, 2014}}
* {{cite news|first=Juliet|last=Jacques|url=https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/series/transgender-journey|title=A Transgender Journey|work=[[The Guardian]]|access-date=December 2, 2014}}
* {{cite journal |last1=Sharp |first1=Victoria Madeleine |last2=Lewis |first2=Clive Buckland |last3=Lieven |first3=Natalie Marie Daniella |title=Bell v Tavistock |journal=In the High Court of Justice Administrative Court Divisional Court |issue=[2020] EWHC 3274 (Admin) |page=CO/60/2020 |url=https://www.judiciary.uk/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/Bell-v-Tavistock-Judgment.pdf}}
* {{cite book|url=http://admin.associationsonline.com/uploaded_files/140/files/Standards%20of%20Care,%20V7%20Full%20Book.pdf|title=Standards of Care for Gender Identity Disorders|author=World Professional Association for Transgender Health|publisher=Harry Benjamin International Gender Dysphoria Association|year=2012|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140924061804/http://admin.associationsonline.com/uploaded_files/140/files/Standards%20of%20Care%2C%20V7%20Full%20Book.pdf|archive-date=September 24, 2014}} Includes a description of ICD-10 criteria.

== External links ==
{{Medical resources
|  ICD10          = {{ICD10|F|64.9 || f|60}}, {{ICD10|F|64.8 || f|60}}
|  ICD9           = {{ICD9|302.85}}
|  ICDO           = 
|  OMIM           = 
|  MedlinePlus    = 001527
|  eMedicineSubj  = 
|  eMedicineTopic = 
|  MeshID         = D000068116
}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060604060835/http://www.transgendercare.com/guidance/resources/ictlep_soc.htm Health Law Standards of Care for Transsexualism] – An alternative to the Benjamin Standards of Care proposed by the International Conference on Transgender Law and Employment Policy.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20030812130936/http://www.lcd.gov.uk/constitution/transsex/policy.htm The Lord Chancellor's Department Government Policy concerning Transsexual People]

{{Transgender topics}}
{{Sexual identities}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Gender identity]]
[[Category:Transgender and medicine]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>