<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151108025637|689580853" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="43097" pageid="43097" ns="0" title="Gender dysphoria"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-08T09:18:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox disease
 | Name           = Gender dysphoria /&lt;br /&gt;Gender identity disorder
 | Width          = 200
 | ICD10          = {{ICD10|F|64.9||f|60}}, {{ICD10|F|64.8||f|60}}
 | ICD9           = {{ICD9|302.85}}
 | ICDO           =
 | OMIM           =
 | MedlinePlus    = 001527
 | eMedicineSubj  =
 | eMedicineTopic =
 | MeshID         = D005783}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}
'''Gender dysphoria''' or '''gender identity disorder''' ('''GID''')&lt;!--NOTE: While the DSM-5 uses the term "gender dysphoria," many other sources still use the term "gender identity disorder"; see past discussions about this on the article's talk page or via its latest archives. --&gt; is the formal [[diagnosis]] used by [[psychologist]]s and [[physician]]s to describe people who experience significant [[dysphoria]] (distress) with the [[sex]] and [[gender]] they were [[Sex assignment|assigned at birth]]. Evidence suggests that people who identify with a gender different from the one they were assigned at birth may do so not just due to psychological or behavioral causes, but also biological ones related to their genetics, the makeup of their brains, or prenatal exposure to hormones.&lt;ref name="etiology"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Heylens|first=G|last2=De Cuypere|first2=G|last3=Zucker|first3=K|author3-link=Kenneth Zucker|last4=Schelfaut|first4=C|last5=Elaut|first5=E|last6=Vanden Bossche|first6=H|last7=De Baere|first7=E|last8=T'Sjoen|first8=G|title= Gender Identity Disorder in Twins: A Review of the Case Report Literature |journal=The Journal of Sexual Medicine|year=2012|volume=8 |pages=751–757|doi=10.1111/j.1743-6109.2011.02567.x|issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Estimates of the prevalence of gender dysphoria or GID range from a lower bound of 1:2000 (or about 0.05%) in [[Low Countries|the Netherlands and Belgium]]&lt;ref name="conway"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Olyslager |first=Femke |last2=Conway|first2=Lynn|author2-link=Lynn Conway|title=Transseksualiteit komt vaker voor dan u denkt. Een nieuwe kijk op de prevalentie van transseksualiteit in Nederland en België|url=http://rjh.ub.rug.nl/genderstudies/article/view/1904/1897|journal=Tijdschrift voor Genderstudies|volume=11|issue=2|pages=39–51|publisher=[[Amsterdam University Press]]|location=Amsterdam|year=2008|language=Dutch|quote=…it is safe to assume that the lower limit for the inherent prevalence of transsexualism in the Netherlands and Flanders is on order of 1:2000 to 1:1000 for transgender females and on the order of 1:4000 to 1:2000 for transgender males.|laysource=How Frequently Does Transsexualism Occur?|layurl=http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TS/TSprevalence.html|issn=1388-3186|accessdate=August 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 0.5% in [[Massachusetts]]&lt;ref name=AJPH&gt;{{Citation|last=Conron|first=KJ|last2=Scott|first2=G|last3=Stowell|first3=GS|last4=Landers|first4=S|date=January 2012|volume=102|issue=1|pages=118–222|issn=1541-0048|oclc=01642844|doi=10.2105/AJPH.2011.300315|title=Transgender Health in Massachusetts: Results from a Household Probability Sample of Adults|journal=[[American Journal of Public Health]]|publisher=[[American Public Health Association]]|url=http://ajph.aphapublications.org/doi/pdf/10.2105/AJPH.2011.300315|accessdate=August 28, 2013|quote=Between 2007 and 2009, survey participants aged 18 to 64 years in the Massachusetts Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (MA-BRFSS; N = 28 662) were asked: "Some people describe themselves as transgender when they experience a different gender identity from their sex at birth. For example, a person born into a male body, but who feels female or lives as a woman. Do you consider yourself to be transgender?" […] We restricted the analytic sample to 28176 participants who answered yes or no to the transgender question (excluding n=364, 1.0% weighted who declined to respond. […] Transgender respondents (n=131; 0.5%; 95% confidence interval [CI]=0.3%, 0.6%) were somewhat younger and more likely to be Hispanic than were nontransgender respondents.}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 1.2% in [[New Zealand]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=The Health and Well-Being of Transgender High School Students: Results From the New Zealand Adolescent Health Survey (Youth'12)|url=http://www.jahonline.org/article/S1054-139X(13)00753-2|last=Clark|first=Terryann C.|last2=Lucassen|first2=Mathijs F.G.|last3=Bullen|first3=at|last4=Denny|first4=Simon J.|last5=Fleming|first5=Theresa M.|last6=Robinson|first6=Elizabeth M.|last7=Rossen|first7=Fiona V.|date=January 15, 2014|journal=[[Journal of Adolescent Health]]|publisher=Society for Adolescent Health and Medicine|volume=54|issue=1|doi=10.1016/j.jadohealth.2013.11.008|quote=Whether a student was transgender was measured by the question, "Do you think you are transgender? This is a girl who feels like she should have been a boy, or a boy who feels like he should have been a girl (e.g., Trans, Queen, [[Fa'afafine|Fa’faffine]], Whakawahine, Tangata ira Tane, [[Genderqueer]])?" […] Over 8,000 students (n = 8,166) answered the question about whether they were transgender. Approximately 95% of students did not report being transgender (n=7,731; 94.7%), 96 students reported being transgender (1.2%), 202 reported not being sure (2.5%), and 137 did not understand the question (1.7%).|accessdate=January 19, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; These numbers are based on those who identify as [[transgender]]. It is estimated that about 0.005% to 0.014% of males and 0.002% to 0.003% of females would be diagnosed with gender dysphoria, based on current diagnostic criteria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 5|isbn =978-0890425558|publisher=[[American Psychiatric Association]]|year=2013|page=454}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research indicates people who [[Transitioning_(transgender)|transition]] in adulthood are up to three times more likely to be male assigned at birth, but that among people transitioning in childhood the sex ratio is close to 1:1.&lt;ref name="prevalence"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Landen|first=M|last2=Walinder|first2=J|last3=Lundstrom|first3=B|title=Prevalence, incidence and sex ratio of transsexualism|journal=Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica|year=1996|volume=93|pages=221–223|doi=10.1111/j.1600-0447.1996.tb10638.x|pmid=8712018|issue=4|quote=On average, the male [to female]:female [to male] ratio in prevalence studies is estimated to be 3:1. However […] the incidence studies have shown a considerably lower male [to female] predominance. In Sweden and England and Wales a sex ratio of 1:1 has been reported. In the most recent incidence data from Sweden there is a slight male [to female] predominance among the group consisting of all applicants for sex reassignment, while in the group of primary [early onset] transsexuals there is no difference in incidence between men and women.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

GID is classified as a medical disorder by the [[International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems|ICD-10 CM]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Gender identity disorder in adolescence and adulthood|publisher=ICD10Data.com|url=http://www.icd10data.com/ICD10CM/Codes/F01-F99/F60-F69/F64-/F64.1|accessdate=July 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[DSM-5]] (called ''gender dysphoria'').&lt;ref name="recommendations"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Fraser|first=L|last2=Karasic|first2=D |last3=Meyer|first3=W |last4=Wylie|first4=K|title=Recommendations for Revision of the DSM Diagnosis of Gender Identity Disorder in Adults|journal=International Journal of Transgenderism|year=2010|volume=12|pages=80–85|doi=10.1080/15532739.2010.509202|issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many transgender people and researchers support declassification of GID because they say the diagnosis pathologizes [[gender variance]], reinforces the [[Gender binary|binary model of gender]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Newman|first=L|title=Sex, Gender and Culture: Issues in the Definition, Assessment and Treatment of Gender Identity Disorder|journal=Clinical Child Psychology and Psychiatry|date=1 July 2002|volume=7|pages=352–359|doi=10.1177/1359104502007003004|issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; and can result in stigmatization of transgender individuals.&lt;ref name="recommendations"/&gt; The official classification of gender dysphoria as a disorder in the DSM-5 may help resolve some of these issues, because the term ''gender dysphoria'' applies only to the discontent experienced by some persons resulting from [[gender identity]] issues.&lt;ref name="recommendations"/&gt;

The current main psychiatric approaches to treatment for persons diagnosed with GID are psychotherapy or to support the individual's preferred gender through hormone therapy, gender expression and role, or surgery.&lt;ref name="Standards of Care"&gt;{{cite journal
|date=2011
|title=Standards of Care for the Health of Transsexual, Transgender, and Gender-Nonconforming People, Version 7
|url=http://www.wpath.org/uploaded_files/140/files/IJT%20SOC,%20V7.pdf
|journal=International Journal of Transgenderism
|publisher=Routledge Taylor &amp; Francis Group
|volume=
|issue=13
|pages=165–232
|doi=10.1080/15532739.2011.700873
|accessdate=August 30, 2014
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
==Signs and symptoms==
Symptoms of GID in children include disgust at their own genitalia, social isolation from their peers, anxiety, loneliness and [[Depression (mood)|depression]].&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite book|title=A Nurse's Guide to Women's Mental Health|last=Davidson|first=Michelle R.|publisher=Springer Publishing Company|year=2012|isbn=0826171133|page=114}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[American Psychological Association]], transgender children are more likely to experience harassment and violence in school, foster care, residential treatment centers, homeless centers and juvenile justice programs than other children.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Cisgenderism in psychology: pathologising and misgendering children from  1999 to 2008|year=2011|url=http://epubs.surrey.ac.uk/72252/2/YGA%20%26%20PH%202011%20Cisgenderism.pdf|last=Ansara and Peter Hegarty|first=Y. Gavriel|journal=Psychology &amp; Sexuality|publisher=Routledge University Press|accessdate=September 20, 2013|doi=10.1080/19419899.2011.576696}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Adults with GID are at increased risk for stress, isolation, anxiety, depression, poor self-esteem and suicide.&lt;ref name=":2"/&gt; Studies indicate that transgender people have an extremely high rate of suicide attempts; one study of 6,450 transgender people in the United States found 41% had attempted [[suicide]], compared to a national average of 1.6%. It also found that suicide attempts were less common among transgender people who said their family ties had remained strong after they came out, but even transgender people at comparatively low risk were still much more likely to have attempted suicide than the general population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Grant|last2=Jaime|first2=M.|last3=Mottet|first3=Lisa|last4=Tanis|first4=Justin|last5=Harrison|first5=Jack|last6=Herman|first6=Jody|last7=Keisling|first7=Mara|title=Injustice at Every Turn: A Report of the National Transgender  Discrimination Survey|date=2011|publisher=National Center for Transgender Equality and National Gay and Lesbian Task Force|location=Washington|url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/static_html/downloads/reports/reports/ntds_full.pdf|accessdate=10 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Reyes|first1=Emily|title=Transgender study looks at 'exceptionally high' suicide-attempt rate|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2014/jan/28/local/la-me-ln-suicide-attempts-alarming-transgender-20140127|accessdate=10 May 2015|work=Los Angeles Times|date=January 28, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people are also at heightened risk for certain [[mental disorder]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Mentoring sexual orientation and gender identity minorities in a university setting|last=O'Keefe|first=CarolynAnne|publisher=ProQuest Dissertations &amp; Theses (PQDT)|year=2007|isbn=9780542913112|location=California|page=xvi}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as [[eating disorder]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Diemer|first1=Elizabeth|last2=Grant|first2=Julia|last3=Munn-Chernoff|first3=Melissa|last4=Patterson|first4=David|last5=Duncan|first5=Alexis|title=Gender Identity, Sexual Orientation, and Eating-Related Pathology in a National Sample of College Students|journal=Journal of Adolescent Health|date=April 28, 2015|doi=10.1016/j.jadohealth.2015.03.003|accessdate=10 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Doyle|first1=Kathryn|title=Sexual orientation, gender identity tied to eating disorder risk|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2015/05/08/us-eating-disorder-gender-idUSKBN0NT2E020150508|accessdate=10 May 2015|work=reuters|date=8 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, a researcher found that the brains of adolescents with gender dysphoria react to the sex hormone [[androstadienone]] in a measurable way similar to the brain of the gender with which the person identifies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nu.nl/wetenschap/3802699/brein-jongere-in-verkeerd-lichaam-lijkt-van-andere-geslacht.html Brein jongere in verkeerd lichaam lijkt op dat van andere geslacht]. Nu.nl, 15 June 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

==Causes==
{{Undue-section|date=September 2013}}
{{Main|Causes of transsexualism}}
GID exists when a person suffers discontent due to gender identity, causing them emotional distress.&lt;ref name=":2"/&gt; Researchers disagree about the nature of distress and impairment in people with GID. Some authors have suggested that people with GID suffer because they are stigmatized and victimized;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Politics of Pathology and the Making of Gender Identity Disorder|last=Bryant|first=Karl Edward|publisher=ProQuest Dissertations &amp; Theses (PQDT)|year=2007|isbn=9780549268161|location=Ann Arbor, Michigan|page=222}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that, if the society had less-strict gender divisions, transsexual people would suffer less.&lt;ref name=":3"/&gt;

===Biological causes===
Genetic variation, hormones, and differences in brain functioning and brain structures provide evidence for the biological etiology of the symptoms associated with GID. Twin studies indicate that GID is 62% heritable, evidencing the genetic influence or prenatal development as its origin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Coolidge|first=F|last2=Thede|first2=L|last3=Young|first3=S|title=The Heritability of Gender Identity Disorder in a Child and Adolescent Twin Sample|journal=Behavior Genetics|date=4 April 2002|volume=32|issue=4|pages=251–257|doi=10.1023/A:1019724712983|pmid=12211624}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In male-to-female transsexuals, GID is associated with variations in an individual's genes that make the individual less sensitive to androgens.&lt;ref name=etiology /&gt; Zhou et al. (1995) found that in one area of the brain, male-to-female transsexuals have a typically female structure, and female-to-male transsexuals have a typically male structure.&lt;ref name="Zhou/Gooren"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Zhou|first1=Jiang-Ning|last2=Hofman|first2=Michel A.|last3=Gooren|first3=Louis J.G.|last4=Swaab|first4=Dick F.|title=A sex difference in the human brain and its relation to transsexuality|journal=Nature|volume=378|issue=6552|pages=68–70|year=1995|pmid=7477289|doi=10.1038/378068a0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Zhou et al. (1995) had a sample size of only six male-to-female transgender individuals. There may, for example, be some [[cisgender]] (non-transgender) heterosexual men with some brain structures that would be expected in a female, as the sample size in Zhou et al. (1995) is too small to exclude such possibilities. In addition, some aspects of [[trans women]]'s hypothalamus functioning resemble that typical of cisgender women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Berglund|first1=H.|last2=Lindström|first2=P.|last3=Dhejne-Helmy |first3=C.|last4=Savic |first4=I.|title=Male-to-Female Transsexuals Show Sex-Atypical Hypothalamus Activation When Smelling Odorous Steroids|journal=Cerebral Cortex|volume=18|issue=8|pages=1900–1908|year=2007|pmid=18056697|doi=10.1093/cercor/bhm216}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The presence of typically female patterns of white matter and neuron patterns has also been observed in the brains of male-to-female transsexuals&lt;ref name="newscientist.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn20032-transsexual-differences-caught-on-brain-scan.html|title=Transsexual differences caught on brain scan - life|date=January 26, 2011|publisher=New Scientist|accessdate=2011-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="endojournals.org"&gt;(2000). "Male-to-female transsexuals have female neuron numbers in the limbic nucleus", ''The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism,'' 85(5); retrieved from http://jcem.endojournals.org/cgi/content/full/85/5/2034&lt;/ref&gt; and overall longer instances of the androgen receptor gene.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Hare|first1=L|last2=Bernard|first2=P|last3=Sánchez|first3=F|last4=Baird|first4=P|last5=Vilain|first5=E|last6=Kennedy|first6=T|last7=Harley|first7=V|title=Androgen Receptor Repeat Length PolymorphismAssociated with Male-to-Female Transsexualism|journal=Biological Psychiatry|volume=65|issue=1|pages=93–96|year=2009|pmid=18962445|doi=10.1016/j.biopsych.2008.08.033|pmc=3402034}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Also see [[Causes of transsexualism]].) However, these markers do not identify every individual who undergoes transition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Allen|first=Mercedes|title=Transgender in the Genes?|magazine=GayCalgary and Edmonton|issue=61|date=November 2008|page=50|url=http://www.gaycalgary.com/a617}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar [[Biology and sexual orientation#Studies of brain structure|brain structure differences]] have, however, been noted between gay and heterosexual men, and between lesbian and heterosexual women.&lt;ref name="LeVay 1991"&gt;{{Cite journal|author=LeVay S |title=A difference in hypothalamic structure between heterosexual and homosexual men |journal=Science |volume=253 |issue=5023 |pages=1034–7 |date=August 1991 |pmid=1887219 |doi=10.1126/science.1887219 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Byne 2001"&gt;{{Cite journal |vauthors=Byne W, Tobet S, Mattiace LA, etal |title=The interstitial nuclei of the human anterior hypothalamus: an investigation of variation with sex, sexual orientation, and HIV status |journal=Horm Behav |volume=40 |issue=2 |pages=86–92 |date=September 2001 |pmid=11534967 |doi=10.1006/hbeh.2001.1680 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; More recent studies have found that circumstance and repeated activities such as [[Research on meditation|meditation]] modify brain structures in a process called brain plasticity or [[neuroplasticity]]. In May 2014, the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences reported that for fathers, parenting "rewires the male brain".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Eyal Abraham, Talma Hendler, Irit Shapira-Lichter, Yaniv Kanat-Maymon, Orna Zagoory-Sharon, and Ruth Feldman|title= Father's brain is sensitive to childcare experiences |journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences |volume=111 |issue=27 |pages=9792–9797 |date=May 2014 |pmid= |doi= 10.1073/pnas.1402569111|url=http://www.pnas.org/content/111/27/9792.abstract}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Diagnosis==
The [[American Psychiatric Association]] permits a diagnosis of ''gender dysphoria'' if the criteria in the ''Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (5th Edition)'', or DSM-5, are met. The DSM-5 moved this diagnosis out of the sexual disorders category and into a category of its own.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=P 01 Gender Dysphoria in Adolescents or Adults|url=http://www.dsm5.org/ProposedRevision/Pages/GenderDysphoria.aspx|publisher=American Psychiatric Association|accessdate=April 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The DSM-5 states that at least two of the criteria for gender dysphoria must be experienced for at least six months' duration in adolescents or adults for diagnosis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Gender Dysphoria|url=http://dsm.psychiatryonline.org/content.aspx?bookid=556&amp;sectionid=41101780|work=DSM-5|publisher=American Psychiatric Association|accessdate=20 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The diagnosis was renamed from "Gender Identity Disorder" to "Gender Dysphoria", after criticisms that the former term was stigmatizing.&lt;ref name="DSMVChild"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dsm5.org/ProposedRevision/Pages/proposedrevision.aspx?rid=192#|title=Gender Dysphoria in Children|publisher=American Psychiatric Association|date=May 4, 2011|accessdate=July 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subtyping by sexual orientation was deleted. The diagnosis for children was separated from that for adults. The creation of a specific diagnosis for children reflects the lesser ability of children to have insight into what they are experiencing, or ability to express it in the event that they have insight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=P 00 Gender Dysphoria in Children|url=http://www.dsm5.org/ProposedRevision/Pages/proposedrevision.aspx?rid=192#|publisher=American Psychiatric Association|accessdate=April 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[International Classification of Diseases]] ([[ICD-10]]) list three diagnostic criteria for "transsexualism" (F64.0):&lt;ref name="Standards of Care"/&gt; Uncertainty about gender identity which causes anxiety or stress is diagnosed as [[sexual maturation disorder]], according to the ICD-10.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Potts|first=S|last2=Bhugra|first2=D|title=Classification of sexual disorders|journal=International Review of Psychiatry|year=1995|volume=7|pages=167–174|doi=10.3109/09540269509028323|issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Management==
Treatment for a person diagnosed with GID may include psychotherapy or to support the individual's preferred gender through hormone therapy, gender expression and role, or surgery. This may include psychological counseling, resulting in lifestyle changes, or physical changes, resulting from medical interventions such as hormonal treatment, genital surgery, electrolysis or laser hair removal, chest/breast surgery, or other reconstructive surgeries. The goal of treatment may simply be to reduce problems resulting from the person's transgender status, for example, counseling the patient in order to reduce guilt associated with cross-dressing, or counseling a spouse to help them adjust to the patient's situation.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Principles and Practice of Sex Therapy, Fourth Edition|last=Leiblum|first=Sandra|url=http://www.amazon.com/Principles-Practice-Therapy-Fourth-Edition/dp/1593853491|accessdate=August 23, 2013|year=2006|publisher=The Guilford Press|isbn=1593853491|pages=488–489}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hormone treatment or surgery for GID is somewhat controversial because of the irreversibility of physical changes. Guidelines have been established to aid clinicians. The [[World Professional Association for Transgender Health]] (WPATH) [[Standards of Care for the Health of Transsexual, Transgender, and Gender Nonconforming People|Standards of Care]] are used by some clinicians as treatment guidelines. Others use guidelines outlined in Gianna Israel and Donald Tarver's ''Transgender Care''. Guidelines for treatment generally follow a "[[harm reduction]]" model.&lt;ref name="AAP"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/132/1/198.full#sec-7|title=Office-Based Care for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Questioning Youth: STI/HIV Testing and Prevention|publisher=American Academy of Pediatrics|date=June 24, 2013|accessdate=August 27, 2013|author=COMMITTEE ON ADOLESCENCE|quote="However, adolescents with multiple or anonymous partners, having unprotected intercourse, or having substance abuse issues should be tested at shorter intervals."}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GLMA"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glma.org/_data/n_0001/resources/live/GLMA%20Compendium%20of%20Health%20Profession%20Association%20LGBT%20Policy%20and%20Position%20Statements.pdf|title=www.glma.org Compendium of Health Prof ession Association LGBT Policy &amp; Position Statements|publisher=GLMA|year=2013|accessdate=August 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="APA"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apa.org/about/policy/booklet.pdf|title=APA Policy Statements on Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, &amp; Transgender Concerns|publisher=American Psychological Association|year=2011|accessdate=August 27, 2013|quote="BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that APA recognizes the efficacy,benefit, and necessity of gender transition treatments for appropriately evaluated individuals and calls upon public and private insurers to cover these medically necessary treatments;"}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prepubescent children===
{{Main|Gender identity disorder in children}}
The question of whether to counsel young children to be happy with their assigned sex or to encourage them to continue to exhibit behaviors that do not match their assigned sex—or to explore a transsexual transition—is controversial. Some clinicians report that a significant proportion of young children diagnosed with gender identity disorder later do not exhibit the dysphoria.&lt;ref name="NPR"&gt;{{cite web|last=Spiegel|first=Alix|title=Q&amp;A: Therapists on Gender Identity Issues in Kids|publisher=NPR|date=2008-05-08 |url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=90229789|accessdate=2008-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Professionals who treat gender identity disorder in children have begun to refer and prescribe hormones, known as a [[puberty blocker]], to delay the onset of puberty until a child is believed to be old enough to make an informed decision on whether hormonal gender reassignment leading to surgical gender reassignment will be in that person's best interest.&lt;ref&gt;''The Transgendered Child: A Handbook for Families and Professionals'' (Brill and Pepper, 2008)&lt;!-- ISBN, pages needed --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Psychological treatments===
{{Main|Psychotherapy}}
Until the 1970s, psychotherapy was the primary treatment for GID, and generally was directed to helping the person adjust to the gender of the physical characteristics present at birth. Psychotherapy is any therapeutic interaction that aims to treat a psychological problem. Though some clinicians still use only psychotherapy to treat GID, it may now be used in addition to biological interventions as treatment for GID.&lt;ref name="treatment review"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Gijs|first=L|last2=Brawaeys|first2=A|title=Surgical Treatment of Gender Dysphoria in Adults and Adolescents: Recent Developments, Effectiveness, and Challenges|journal=Annual Review of Sex Research|year=2007|volume=18|issue=178–224}}&lt;/ref&gt; Psychotherapeutic treatment of GID involves helping the patient to adapt. Attempts to "cure" GID by changing the patient's gender identity to reflect birth characteristics have been ineffective.&lt;ref name="merck manual"/&gt;{{rp|1568}}

===Biological treatments===
{{Main|Sex reassignment therapy}}
Biological treatments physically alter [[Primary sex characteristic|primary]] and [[Secondary sex characteristic|secondary]] sex characteristics to reduce the discrepancy between an individual's physical body and gender identity.&lt;ref name="care guidelines"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bockting|first=W|last2=Knudson|first2=G|last3=Goldberg|first3=J|title=Counselling and Mental Health Care of Transgender Adults and Loved Ones|date=January 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biological treatments for GID without any form of psychotherapy is quite uncommon. Researchers have found that if individuals bypass psychotherapy in their GID treatment, they often feel lost and confused when their biological treatments are complete.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hakeem|first=Az|title=Changing Sex or Changing Minds: Specialist Psychotherapy and Transsexuality|journal=Group Analysis|year=2008|volume=41|issue=2|pages=182–196 |doi=10.1177/0533316408089883}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Psychotherapy, hormone replacement therapy, and sex reassignment surgery together can be effective treating GID when the [[HBIGDA-SOC|WPATH standards of care]] are followed.&lt;ref name="merck manual"&gt;{{cite book|author=George R. Brown, MD|chapter=Chapter 165 Sexuality and Sexual Disorders|pages=1567–1573|editor1=Robert S. Porter, MD|title=The [[Merck Manual of Diagnosis and Therapy]]|edition=19th|date=20 July 2011|publisher=[[Merck &amp; Co.]], Inc.|location=[[Whitehouse Station, NJ]], USA|isbn=978-0-911910-19-3|display-editors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|1570}} The overall level of patient satisfaction with both psychological and biological treatments is very high.&lt;ref name="treatment review"/&gt;

==History==
The term ''gender identity disorder'' is an older term for the condition. Some groups, including the [[American Psychiatric Association]] (APA), use the term ''gender dysphoria''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dsm5.org/Documents/Gender%20Dysphoria%20Fact%20Sheet.pdf|title=Gender Dysphoria Fact Sheet|publisher=APA|accessdate=2 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The APA's [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual]] first described the condition in the third publication ("DSM-III") in 1980.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Koh|first=J|title=The history of the concept of gender identity disorder|journal=Seishin Shinkeigaku Zasshi|year=2012|pmid=22844818|volume=114|issue=6|pages=673–80}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2011, the UK [[National Research Ethics Service]] approved prescribing monthly injection of puberty-blocking drugs to youngsters from 12 years old, in order to enable them to get older before deciding on formal sex change. The [[Tavistock and Portman NHS Foundation Trust]] (T&amp;P) in North London has treated such children.  Clinic director Dr. [[Polly Carmichael]] said, "Certainly, of the children between 12 and 14, there's a number who are keen to take part. I know what's been very hard for their families is knowing that there's something available but it's not available here." The clinic received 127 GID referrals in 2010.&lt;ref name=dt15&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/health/healthnews/8454002/Puberty-blocker-for-children-considering-sex-change.html  telegraph.co.uk: "Puberty blocker for children considering sex change"], ''Telegraph'' (Alleyne) 15 Apr 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

The T&amp;P completed a three-year trial to assess the psychological, social and physical benefits and risks involved for 12- to 14-year-old patients.  The trial was deemed such a success that doctors have decided to make the drugs more widely available and to children as young as 9 years of age. As recently as 2009, national guidelines stated that treatment for GID should not start until puberty had finished. [[Ferring Pharmaceuticals]] manufactures the drug Triptorelin, marketed under the name [[Gonapeptyl]], at £82 per monthly dose. The treatment is reversible, which means the body will resume its previous state upon discontinuation of drugs.  MP (Member of Parliament) [[Andrew Percy]] said "I think many people will be horrified at the thought of a nine-year-old being provided with a drug that effectively stops them developing and maturing naturally."&lt;ref name=dt14&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/health/children/10839063/Sex-change-drugs-to-be-offered-to-nine-year-olds.html telegraph.co.uk: "Sex change drugs 'to be offered to nine-year-olds'"], 18 May 2014&lt;/ref&gt;  MP (Member of Parliament) [[Mark Pritchard (politician)|Mark Pritchard]] said, "With competing NHS resources, especially for life-saving cancer drugs, there needs to be an immediate investigation into why these drugs are being prescribed to those so young."&lt;ref name=dm17/&gt;

In May 2014, Carmichael said,
&lt;blockquote&gt;Now we’ve done the study--and the results thus far have been positive--we’ve decided to continue with it. So we’ve decided to do “stage not age” (as the criterion) because it’s obviously fairer. Twelve is an arbitrary age.  If they started puberty aged nine or ten instead of 12, as long as they’re monitored and the bone density doesn’t suffer, then it is right that the aim is to stop the development of secondary sex characteristics.&lt;ref name=dm17&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2631472/NHS-sex-change-drugs-nine-year-olds-Clinic-accused-playing-God-treatment-stops-puberty.html|title=NHS to give sex change drugs to nine-year-olds: Clinic accused of 'playing God' with treatment that stops puberty (Manning and Adams) 18 May 2014|work=Mail Online|accessdate=1 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Society and culture==

===Gender as a social construction===
Some cultures have [[Third gender|three defined genders]]: man, woman, and effeminate man. For example, in [[Samoa]], the ''[[fa'afafine]]'', a group of feminine males, are entirely socially accepted. The fa'afafine do not have any of the stigma or distress typically associated in Western cultures with deviating from a male/female gender role. This suggests the distress so frequently associated with GID in a Western context is not ''caused'' by the disorder itself, but by difficulties encountered from social disapproval by one's culture.&lt;ref name="fa'afafine"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Vasey|first=P|last2=Bartlett|first2=N|title=What Can the Samoan "Fa'afafine" Teach Us about the Western Concept of Gender Identity Disorder in Childhood?|journal=Perspectives in Biology and Medicine|year=2007|volume=50|issue=4|pages=481–490|doi=10.1353/pbm.2007.0056|pmid=17951883}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, research has found that the anxiety associated with the disorder persists in cultures, Eastern or otherwise, which are more accepting of gender nonconformity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 5|isbn =978-0890425558|publisher=[[American Psychiatric Association]]|year=2013|page=459}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Australia, a 2014 High Court of Australia judgment unanimously ruled in favor of a plaintiff named  [[Norrie May-Welby|Norrie]], who asked to be classified by a third gender category, 'non-specific', after a long court battle with the NSW Registrar of Births, Deaths and Marriages.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.austlii.edu.au/cgi-bin/sinodisp/au/cases/cth/HCA/2014/11.html?query= NSW Registrar of Births, Deaths and Marriages v Norrie [2014&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; HCA 11]&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Court did not accept that gender was a social construction: it found that sex affirmation "surgery did not resolve her[sic] sexual ambiguity".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=NSW Registrar of Births, Deaths and Marriages v Norrie |vol=2014 |reporter=High Court of Australia |opinion=11 |pinpoint=11 |court=High Court of Australia |date=2 April 2014 |url=http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/HCA/2014/11.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Classification as a disorder===
The [[mental disorder|psychiatric diagnoses]] of gender identity disorder (now gender dysphoria) was introduced in the DSM-III in 1980. Some sources have characterized the addition as a political maneuver to re-stigmatize homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Transgender Emergence: Therapeutic Guidelines for Working with Gender-Variant People and Their Families|author=Arlene Istar Lev|publisher=Haworth Press|year=2004|isbn=978-0-7890-2117-5|page=172|url=https://books.google.com/?id=LwxvazLRmiEC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;dq=homosexuality+dsm-iii+transsexuality}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Riddle"&gt;{{cite book|last=Rudacille|first=Deborah|authorlink=Deborah Rudacille|title=The Riddle of Gender: Science, Activism, and Transgender Rights|publisher=Pantheon|date=February 2005|isbn=978-0-375-42162-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Homosexuality was removed from the DSM-II in 1974.) By contrast, [[Kenneth Zucker]] and [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] argue that gender identity disorder was included in the DSM-III because it "met the generally accepted criteria used by the framers of DSM-III for inclusion."&lt;ref name="Historical Note"&gt;{{citation|last=Zucker|first=KJ|author-link=Kenneth Zucker|last2=Spitzer|first2=RL|author2-link=Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|title=Was the gender identity disorder of childhood diagnosis introduced into DSM-III as a backdoor maneuver to replace homosexuality? A historical note.|journal=Journal of Sex and Marital Therapy|date=Jan–Feb 2005|volume=31|issue=1|pages=31–42|doi=10.1080/00926230590475251|pmid=15841704}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some researchers, including [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] and Paul J. Fink, contend that the behaviors and experiences seen in transsexualism are abnormal and constitute a dysfunction.&lt;ref name="PsychNews"/&gt;

Individuals with gender dysphoria may or may not regard their own cross-gender feelings and behaviors as a disorder. Advantages and disadvantages exist to classifying gender dysphoria as a disorder.&lt;ref name="Standards of Care"/&gt; Because gender dysphoria is classified as a disorder in medical texts (such as the previous DSM manual, the DSM-IV-TR, under the name "gender identity disorder"), many insurance companies are willing to cover some of the expenses of sex reassignment therapy. Without the classification of gender dysphoria as a medical disorder, sex reassignment therapy may be viewed as cosmetic treatment, rather than medically necessary treatment, and may not be covered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ford|first=Zack|title=APA Revises Manual: Being Transgender is No Longer a Mental Disorder|url=http://thinkprogress.org/lgbt/2012/12/03/1271431/apa-revises-manual-being-transgender-is-no-longer-a-mental-disorder/?mobile=nc|accessdate=April 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, transgender people are less likely than others to have health insurance, and often face hostility and insensitivity from healthcare providers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Social Work Practice with Transgender and Gender Variant Youth|last=Mallon|first=Gerald P.|publisher=Routledge|year=2009|isbn=0415994829|location=New Jersey}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The DSM-IV-TR diagnostic component of distress is not inherent in the cross-gender identity; rather, it is related to social rejection and discrimination suffered by the individual.&lt;ref name="fa'afafine"/&gt; Psychology professor Darryl Hill insists that gender dysphoria is not a mental disorder, but rather that the diagnostic criteria reflect psychological distress in children that occurs when parents and others have trouble relating to their child's gender variance.&lt;ref name="PsychNews"&gt;{{cite news|title=Controversy Continues to Grow Over DSM's GID Diagnosis|url=http://psychnews.psychiatryonline.org/newsarticle.aspx?articleid=106462|publisher=Psychiatric News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people have often been harassed, socially excluded, and subjected to discrimination, abuse and violence, including murder.&lt;ref name=":2"/&gt;&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Children with Gender Identity Disorder: A Clinical, Ethical, and Legal Analysis|last=Giordano|first=Simona|publisher=Routledge|year=2012|isbn=0415502713|location=New Jersey|page=147}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2002, the British Lord Chancellor's office published a ''Government Policy Concerning Transsexual People'' document that categorically states, "What transsexualism is not ... It is not a mental illness."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dca.gov.uk/constitution/transsex/policy.htm|title=Government Policy concerning Transsexual People|work=People's rights/Transsexual people|publisher=U.K. Department for Constitutional Affairs|year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2009, the government of France declared that a transsexual gender identity will no longer be classified as a psychiatric condition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=La transsexualité ne sera plus classée comme affectation psychiatrique|url=http://www.lemonde.fr/societe/article/2009/05/16/la-transsexualite-ne-sera-plus-classee-comme-affectation-psychiatrique_1193860_3224.html|date=May 16, 2009|publisher=Le Monde}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 31, 2010, [[Thomas Hammarberg]], [[Commissioner for Human Rights]] within the Strasbourg-based Council of Europe, an independent institution, opposed the mental disorder classification and the sterilization of transgender persons as a requirement for legal sex change.&lt;ref&gt;[http://commissioner.cws.coe.int/tiki-view_blog_post.php?postId=74 Forced divorce and sterilisation - a reality for many transgender persons], commissioner.cws.coe.int; accessed April 11, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; The Principle 3 of [[The Yogyakarta Principles]] on The Application of International Human Rights Law In Relation to Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity states, "Persons of diverse sexual orientation and gender identities shall enjoy legal capacity in all aspects of life. Each person's self-defined sexual orientation and gender identity is integral to their personality and is one of the most basic aspects of self-determination, dignity and freedom," and the Principle 18 states, "Notwithstanding any classifications to the contrary, a person's sexual orientation and gender identity are not, in and of themselves, medical condition and are not to be treated, cured or suppressed." {{citation needed|date=April 2014}}

===Intimate relationships===
Intimate relationships between lesbians and female-to-male people with GID will sometimes endure throughout the transition process, or shift into becoming supportive friendships. Intimate relationships between heterosexual women and male-to-female people with GID often suffer once the GID is known or revealed. Researchers say the fate of the relationship seems to depend mainly on the woman's adaptability. Problems often arise, with the cisgender partner becoming increasingly angry or dissatisfied, if her partner's time spent in a female role grows, if her partner's libido decreases, or if her partner is angry and emotionally cut-off when in the male role. Cisgender women sometimes also worry about social stigma and may be uncomfortable with the bodily feminization of their partner as the partner moves through transition. The cisgender women who are likeliest to accept and accommodate their partner's transition, researchers say, are those with a low sex drive or those who are equally sexually attracted to men and women.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Transexual and Other Disorders of Gender Identity: A Practical Guide to Management|last=Barrett|first=James|publisher = RADCLIFFE MEDICAL PRESS LTD|year=2007|isbn=185775719X|page=83}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legislation===
In California, Assembly Bill (AB) No. 1266, authored by Assemblyman [[Tom Ammiano]] (D-San Francisco), was passed in May 2013 by the State Assembly:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Existing law prohibits public schools from discriminating on the basis of specified characteristics, including gender, gender identity, and gender expression, and specifies various statements of legislative intent and the policies of the state in that regard. Existing law requires that participation in a particular physical education activity or sport, if required of pupils of one sex, be available to pupils of each sex. This bill would require that a pupil be permitted to participate in sex-segregated school programs, activities, including athletic teams and competitions, and use facilities consistent with his or her gender identity, irrespective of the gender listed on the pupil's records.&lt;ref name="latimes"&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/local/political/la-me-pc-gender-identity-school-bathrooms-20130509,0,3700818.story#axzz2ycjKFR1a ''Los Angeles Times'', "Assembly approves bill on gender identity in schools"] by Chris Megerian, May 9, 2013; accessed April 11, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; The California Catholic Conference opposed the bill as unnecessary, as laws exist already to fight discrimination against transgender students. A spokeswoman for the conference said that the issue should be handled by school officials.&lt;ref name="latimes"/&gt;

Petitions were collected to require a referendum on the legislation in question, but the Secretary of State of California, [[Debra Bowen]], issued a decision determining that, due to disqualified signatures, the threshold of votes had not been reached to force the referendum in question.&lt;ref name="wfd"/&gt; Pacific Justice and Capitol Resource institutes, representing opponents of AB 1266, dispute this, filing a lawsuit, opposed by the State of California, to have the disqualified signatures validated and petitioners' names made public, which the State argues are confidential. Pro-referendum forces claim votes were mishandled due to malfeasance and incompetence in [[Tulare County, California|Tulare]] and [[Mono County, California|Mono]] counties, respectively.&lt;ref name="wfd"&gt;[http://www.wnd.com/2014/04/california-hides-id-of-petition-signers-in-coed-bathroom-dispute/#comment-1332913222 Suit against State of California over AB 1266], wnd.com, April 2014; accessed April 12, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite web |url=http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TSsuccesses/TransMen.html |title=Successful TransMen: Links and Photos |first=Lynn |last=Conway |authorlink=Lynn Conway |work=ai.eecs.umich.edu |date=June 26, 2014 |accessdate=December 2, 2014}}
* {{cite web |url=http://ai.eecs.umich.edu/people/conway/TSsuccesses/TSsuccesses.html |title=Transsexual Women's Successes: Links and Photos |first=Lynn |last=Conway |work=ai.eecs.umich.edu |date=February 5, 2011 |accessdate=December 2, 2014}}
* {{cite news |first=Juliet |last=Jacques|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/lifeandstyle/series/transgender-journey |title=A Transgender Journey |work=[[The Guardian]] |accessdate=December 2, 2014}}
* {{cite book |url=http://admin.associationsonline.com/uploaded_files/140/files/Standards%20of%20Care,%20V7%20Full%20Book.pdf |title=Standards of Care for Gender Identity Disorders |author=World Professional Association for Transgender Health |publisher=Harry Benjamin International Gender Dysphoria Association |year=2012}} Includes a description of ICD-10 criteria.

==External links==
* [http://www.transgendercare.com/guidance/resources/ictlep_soc.htm Health Law Standards of Care for Transsexualism] - An alternative to the Benjamin Standards of Care proposed by the International Conference on Transgender Law and Employment Policy.
* [http://www.lcd.gov.uk/constitution/transsex/policy.htm The Lord Chancellor's Department Government Policy concerning Transsexual People]

{{Sexual identities}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gender Identity Disorder}}
[[Category:Gender identity]]
[[Category:Identity disorders]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender identity disorders| ]]
[[Category:Transgender and medicine]]
[[Category:Psychiatric diagnosis]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>