<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20180523163913|842625493" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="315938" pageid="315938" ns="0" title="Numerus clausus"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-08-12T13:57:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{italic title}}
{{for|the property law concept|Numerus clausus (law)}}

'''''Numerus clausus''''' ("closed number" in [[Latin]]) is one of many methods used to limit the number of [[student]]s who may study at a [[university]]. In many cases, the goal of the ''numerus clausus'' is simply to limit the number of students to the maximum feasible in some particularly sought-after areas of studies.  In historical terms however, in some countries, ''numerus clausus'' policies were religious or [[racial quota]]s, both in intent and function.
{{TOC right}}

==Modern use==
{{hatnote|For historical use, see [[Numerus clausus#Historical use|section below]]|selfref=yes}}

The ''numerus clausus'' is used in countries and universities where the number of applicants greatly exceeds the number of available places for students. This is the case in many countries of [[continental Europe]]. Students in much of Europe choose their field of specialization when they begin university study, unlike students in North America, who specialize later. Fields such as medicine, law, biology, dentistry, pharmacology, psychology and business administration are particularly popular and therefore harder to gain admittance to study.

===Selected examples===
====Brazil====
{{main|Vestibular exam#Racial quotas}}
In November 2002 the Brazilian government passed Federal Law 10.558/2002, known as the "Quota Law". The law allowed for the establishment of racial quotas at public universities. In 2012 the [[Supreme Federal Court]] of Brazil unanimously upheld the law.&lt;ref&gt;Brazil's Supreme Court upholds affirmative action in universities, KAREN JUANITA CARRILLO Special to the AmNews | 5/16/2012, 6:04 p.m., Amsterdam News, http://amsterdamnews.com/news/2012/may/16/brazils-supreme-court-upholds-affirmative-action/&lt;/ref&gt;

====Germany====
{{Further information|Education in Germany#Admission}}
The ''numerus clausus'' is used in Germany to address overcrowding at universities. There are local admission restrictions, which are set up for a particular degree program (''{{Lang|de|Studiengang}}'') at the university's discretion, and nationwide admission restrictions in medicine, dentistry, veterinary medicine, and pharmacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hochschulkompass.de/en/degree-programmes/application-admission/admissions-procedure/local-admission-restrictions.html|title=Local admission restrictions|last=|first=|date=|website=hochschulkompass.de|publisher=German Rectors' Conference|access-date=2016-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hochschulkompass.de/en/degree-programmes/application-admission/admissions-procedure/national-admission-restrictions.html|title=National admission restrictions|last=|first=|date=|website=hochschulkompass.de|publisher=German Rectors' Conference|access-date=2016-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Not all degree programs restrict admissions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hochschulkompass.de/en/degree-programmes/application-admission/admissions-procedure/no-admission-restrictions.html|title=No admission restrictions|last=|first=|date=|website=hochschulkompass.de|publisher=German Rectors' Conference|access-date=2016-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most common admission criterion is the final grade of the university entrance qualification, that is the high school completion certificate formally allowing the applicant to study at a German university. Typically, this is the ''[[Abitur]]''. The final grade takes into account the grades of the final exams as well as the course grades. In colloquial usage, ''numerus clausus'' may also refer to the lowest admitted grade in this process. Other criteria, e.g. interviews, are increasingly common as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.wiwo.de/karriere/studenten-in-der-testmuehle-390632/|title=Auswahlverfahren der Universitäten: Studenten in der Testmühle|last=|first=|date=13 March 2009|website=|publisher=Wirtschaftswoche|language=German|access-date=2016-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Finland====
The Finnish system of implementing the ''numerus clausus'' provides a comparison to the German model. In Germany, the main weight of the student selection lies on the ''Abitur'' grades (i.e. high school diploma). In Finland, which has a similar nationwide final exam, the [[Abitur#Finland|matriculation examination]] (Finnish ''ylioppilastutkinto''), the majority of student selections are based on entrance exams. Most degree programs consist of a single major subject and have their own entrance procedures. Nearly all programs have a quota in which the score is calculated solely on the basis of the entrance exam. The written exams usually consist of open-ended questions requiring the applicant to write an essay or solve problems. Multiple choice tests are uncommon.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abo.fi/ansok/en/results Numerus Clausus. A system of Numerus Clausus (restricted entry) is in use at all institutions of higher education in Finland.]&lt;/ref&gt;

In fields where the competition for study places is less fierce. This is especially the case with the [[engineering]] and [[natural science]] programs. It is relatively easy to be accepted in these fields—about one-third of the study places in technology are awarded on the basis of the matriculation exam. The rest of the students are admitted on the basis of an entrance exam. After receiving a study place, the student must accept it in writing on the pain of forfeiting the place. In case the students receive more than one study place, they must select one. During the year, one person may accept only a single study place in an institution of higher education. The system is enforced through a national database on student admissions.

In the Finnish system, the ''numerus clausus'' is the most important factor limiting student numbers. After gaining entrance, traditionally a student cannot be expelled, pays no [[tuition]], and enjoys a state [[student benefit]]. The new legislation, introduced in the summer of 2005, limits the study period to seven years, but it is anticipated that it will be relatively easy to receive a permission for a longer study time. No changes to the financial position of the student are currently being considered (as of the summer of 2005).

====France====
In France, admission to the ''[[grande école|grandes écoles]]'' is obtained by competitive exams with a fixed, limited number of positions each year. Also, at the end of the first year of medical studies in universities, there is a competitive exam with a ''numerus clausus'' for determining which students are allowed to proceed to the second year; in later years of medical studies there is a competitive exam (''concours de l'internat'') for choosing medical specialties.&lt;ref&gt;M. Huguier, P. Romestaing (October 2014),  [https://www.researchgate.net/publication/303576208_Numerus_clausus_and_medical_demographics_in_France  Numerus clausus and medical demographics in France.]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ireland====
''Numerus clausus'' is also used in Ireland. [[University College Dublin]] uses the system in its admission for Medicine and Veterinary Medicine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://myucd.ucd.ie/admissions/alevel.ezc|title=A Level/GCE Applicant|author=EDge Interactive Publishing, Inc.|publisher=|accessdate=17 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Switzerland====
The introduction of the ''numerus clausus'' in Switzerland has limited the access to the medical studies at the universities. At all universities of the German-speaking part of Switzerland, the students need to have a high score on an aptitude test that comprises logical and spatial thinking and text understanding skills.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lyceum-alpinum.ch/en/academic/college-counselling/switzerland-germany/ Eignungstest für das Medizinstudium (Switzerland).] Numerus Clausus for Medical Studies in Switzerland and Germany.&lt;/ref&gt;

The universities in the western, French-speaking part of Switzerland did not decide to introduce a ''numerus clausus''. Instead, these universities provide unrestricted access to the first-year curriculum in medicine; and the best first-year students are allowed to further their medical studies at the same or at another university. In other popular faculties like psychology or journalism, there are also aptitude tests—but they concern only a single university.

====United States====
Starting in the 1980s, and ongoing {{as of|2017|lc=y}}, there have been allegations of an [[Asian quota]] in college admissions, analogous to the earlier [[Jewish quota]].&lt;ref name=lemann&gt;{{cite journal |title=Jews in Second Place |date=June 25, 1996 |first=Nicholas |last=Lemann |url=http://www.slate.com/articles/briefing/articles/1996/06/jews_in_second_place.html |journal=[[Slate (magazine)|Slate]] |quote=Just at the moment when Harvard, Yale, and Princeton have presidents named Rudenstine, Levin, and Shapiro, those institutions are widely suspected of having informal ceilings on Asian admissions, of the kind that were imposed on Jews two generations ago. |accessdate=2017-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=unz2012&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.theamericanconservative.com/articles/the-myth-of-american-meritocracy/ |title=The Myth of American Meritocracy |journal=[[The American Conservative]] |first=Ron |last=Unz |authorlink=Ron Unz |date=November 28, 2012 |accessdate=2017-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historical use==
{{further|Jewish quota}}
Before [[World War II]], the limitations in the number of students of [[Jew]]ish origin in many countries were usually resulting from their disproportionate numbers in the national universities. This limitation took the form of quotas restricting the number of Jewish students so that their share in the student population would correspond with their share in the general population. The limitations in enrolment were introduced in over a dozen countries, allowing access to higher education to a greater proportion of non-Jewish students.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.jhi.pl/publikacje/65 |title=Sytuacja prawna Żydów w Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej 1918–1939 - Żydowski Instytut Historyczny |website=www.jhi.pl |access-date=2016-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Countries legislating limitations on the admission of Jewish students, at various times, have included: [[Austria]], [[Canada]], [[Hungary]], [[Imperial Russia]], [[Iraq]], [[Latvia]] (from 1934 under [[Kārlis Ulmanis]] regime), [[Netherlands]], [[Poland]], [[Romania]], [[United States]], [[Vichy France]], and [[Yugoslavia]] among others.&lt;ref&gt;Freidenreich, Harriet Pass (1979) The Jews of Yugoslavia: A Quest for Community. Philadelphia:  Jewish Publication Society of America. "On Oct 5, 1940 the Royal Government in [[Serbia]] issued Two anti-Jewish decrees restricting them from producing or distributing food; and the other a numerous clausus law restricting enrollment in universities and high schools."&lt;/ref&gt;

===Selected examples===
====Canada====
Certain Canadian universities had longstanding quotas on the number of Jews admitted to the respective universities. [[McGill University]]'s strict quota was the longest, being officially adopted in 1920 up until the late 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;Gerald Tulchinsky, ''Canada's Jews: A People's Journey'', Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2008, pp. 132-133, 319-321, 410.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Germany====
A whole series of ''numerus clausus'' resolutions were adopted in 1929 on the grounds of race and place of origin, not religion.&lt;ref&gt;JTA Bulletin (1931-3-17), [http://pdfs.jta.org/1931/1931-03-17_064.pdf Berlin: The growing ''numerus clausus'' peril in Germany.] Page 4.&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 April 1933, the [[Nazi]] government introduced a 1.5 percent quota for new admissions of German non-Aryans, essentially of German Jews enrolling to German high-schools and universities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://alex.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno-plus?apm=0&amp;aid=dra&amp;datum=19330004&amp;zoom=2&amp;seite=00000225&amp;ues=0&amp;x=9&amp;y=13 Gesetz gegen die Überfüllung deutscher Schulen und Hochschulen (RGBl 1933 I, S. 225)] (original German text of the ''Law against the Overcrowding of German Schools and Universities'', introduced in 1933).
[http://alex.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno-plus?apm=0&amp;aid=dra&amp;datum=19330004&amp;seite=00000226&amp;zoom=2 Erste Verordnung zur Durchführung des Gesetzes gegen die Überfüllung deutscher Schulen und Hochschulen (RGBl 1933 I, S. 226)] (original German text of the ''First Regulation for the Implementation of the Law against the Overcrowding of German Schools and Universities'', introduced in 1933).&lt;/ref&gt;

====Hungary====
The Hungarian ''numerus clausus'' was introduced in 1920. The law formally placed limits on the number of minority students at university, and legalized corporal punishment. Though the text did not use the term ''Jew'', it was nearly the only group overrepresented in higher education. The policy is often seen as the first Anti-Jewish Act of twentieth century Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Péter Tibor Nagy, [http://mek.oszk.hu/03700/03797/03797.htm#7 The "numerus clausus" policy of antisemitism or policy of higher education], in ''The social and political history of Hungarian education''&lt;/ref&gt;

Its aim was to restrict the number of Jews to 6 percent, which was their proportion in Hungary at that time; the rate of Jewish students was approximately 15% in the 1910s.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;Miklos Molnar, ''A Concise History of Hungary'', CUP, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; In 1928 &amp;ndash; also because of the pressure of liberal capital and League of Nations &amp;ndash; the act was modified and the passage of the ethnicity quota had been eliminated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://regi.sofar.hu/hu/node/13270 |title=A Numerus Clausus módosítása - The modification of the Numerus Clausus law |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |website="http://regi.sofar.hu"}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the period of 1938–1945 the anti-Jewish acts were revitalised and eventually much worsened, partly due to [[German Nazi]] pressure, and in hope of revising the [[Treaty of Trianon]] with the help of Germany.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;

====Poland====
{{see also|Ghetto benches}}
''Numerus clausus'' in interwar Poland was unofficially introduced in 1937 by some universities. It was a result of highly disproportionate number of Jewish students in key disciplines including 62.9 percent in [[stomatology]], 34 percent in medical sciences, 29.2 percent in philosophy, 24.9 percent in chemistry and 22.1 percent in law (26 percent by 1929). Such numbers were the cause of a backlash at most Polish universities, with notable protest organized by the non-Jewish political parties.&lt;ref name="AJ"&gt;{{cite journal |title=Sytuacja prawna mniejszosci żydowskiej w Drugiej Rzeczypospolitej |trans-title=The legal status of the Jewish minority in the Second Republic |at=pp. 65–66 (20/38 in PDF) |author=Anna Jaskóła, [[University of Wrocław]] |publisher=Wydział Prawa, Administracji i Ekonomii. Instytut Historii Państwa i Prawa (Faculty of Law, Administration and Economy) |location=Wrocław |year=2010 |url=http://www.bibliotekacyfrowa.pl/Content/35560/004.pdf |work=Chapter 3: Szkolnictwo żydowskie |via=direct download from BibliotekaCyfrowa.pl}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[partitions of Poland]] by the neighbouring empires, Poles were denied education, and the severely limited number of schools were poorly funded. Following Poland's return to independence, the advocates of the ''numerus clausus'' policy pointed out that the limit would balance the chance to enter university of all nationalities in Poland (Polish, Lithuanian, Belorussian, Ukrainian, German etc.). The other reason given by the supporters of the idea was that it was an attempt to equal the chance of children from countryside families who had very limited access to education to the chance of the children of Jewish families living in the towns and cities. After World War II similar policies were introduced by the pro-Soviet communists, based on preferential treatment of peasant and working-class children. The students from working-class families were intended to form the new socialist intelligentsia.

====United States====
Between 1918 and the 1950s a number of private universities and medical schools in the United States introduced ''numerus clausus'' policies limiting admissions of students based on their religion or race to certain percentages within the college population. Many minority groups were negatively impacted by these policies; one of the groups affected was [[Jewish]] applicants, whose admission to some New England- and New York City-area [[liberal arts college]]s fell significantly between the late 1910s and the mid-1930s.&lt;ref name=Gladwell&gt;[http://www.newyorker.com/archive/2005/10/10/051010crat_atlarge Getting In: the social logic of Ivy League admissions] by [[Malcolm Gladwell]], [[The New Yorker]], 10 October 2005&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, the admission to [[Harvard University]] during that period fell from 27.6% to 17.1% and in [[Columbia University]] from 32.7% to 14.6%. Corresponding quotas were introduced in the medical and dental schools resulting during the 1930s in the decline of Jewish students: e.g. in [[Cornell University]] School of Medicine from 40% in 1918–22 to 3.57% in 1940–41, in [[Boston University]] Medical School from 48.4% in 1929–30 to 12.5% in 1934–35. At [[Yale University]], Dean Milton Winternitz's instructions to the admissions office regarding ethnic quotas were very specific: "Never admit more than five Jews, take only two [[Italian-American|Italian]] [[Catholic]]s, and take no [[African-American|blacks]] at all."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Gerard N. Burrow|title=A History of Yale's School of Medicine: Passing Torches to Others|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XzYX_MduAG8C&amp;pg=PA107|year=2008|publisher=Yale University Press|page=107ff}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, a notable exception among U. S. medical schools was the medical school of [[Middlesex University (Massachusetts)|Middlesex University]], which had no quotas and many Jewish faculty members and students; school officials believed that antisemitism played a role in the school's failure to secure [[American Medical Association|AMA]] accreditation.&lt;ref name=reisfounding&gt;{{cite web |author = Reis, Arthur H., Jr| title=The Founding | work=Brandeis Review, fiftieth Anniversary Edition | url=http://www.brandeis.edu/publications/review/50threview/founding.pdf | accessdate=2006-05-17}}, pp. 42–3: founder's son C. Ruggles Smith quoted: "From its inception, Middlesex was ruthlessly attacked by the American Medical Association, which at that time was dedicated to restricting the production of physicians, and to maintaining an inflexible policy of discrimination in the admission of medical students. Middlesex, alone among medical schools, selected its students on the basis of merit, and refused to establish any racial quotas"&lt;/ref&gt;

The most common method, employed by 90% of American universities and colleges at the time to identify the "desirable" (native-born, white, Protestant) applicants, was the application form questions about their religious preference, race, and nationality. Other more subtle methods included restrictions on scholarships, rejection of transfer students, and preferences for alumni sons and daughters.{{citation needed|date=March 2016}}

'''[[Legacy preference]]''' for university admissions was devised in 1925 at [[Yale University]], where the proportional number of Jews in the student body was growing at a rate that became alarming to the school's administrators.&lt;ref name=Gladwell/&gt; Prior to that year, Yale had begun to incorporate such amorphous criteria as 'character' and 'solidity', as well as 'physical characteristics', into its admissions process as an excuse for screening out Jewish students;&lt;ref name=Gladwell/&gt; but nothing was as effective as legacy preference, which allowed the admissions board to summarily pass over Jews in favor of 'Yale sons of good character and reasonably good record', as a 1929 memo phrased it. Other schools, including [[Harvard]], soon began to pursue similar policies for similar reasons, and Jewish students in the [[Ivy League]] schools were maintained at a steady 10% through the 1950s. Such policies were gradually discarded during the early 1960s, with Yale being one of the last of the major schools to eliminate the last vestige with the class of 1970 (entering in 1966).&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.yalealumnimagazine.com/issues/99_12/admissions.html The Birth of a New Institution] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100314164351/http://www.yalealumnimagazine.com/issues/99_12/admissions.html |date=2010-03-14 }}'' Geoffrey Kabaservice, ''Yale Alumni Magazine'', December 1999&lt;/ref&gt; While legacy admissions as a way of screening out Jewish students may have ceased, the practice of giving preference to legacies has continued to the present day. In the 1998 book ''The Shape of the River: Long-Term Consequences of Considering Race in College and University Admissions'', authors William G. Bowen, former Princeton University president, and [[Derek Bok]], former Harvard University president, found "the overall admission rate for legacies was almost twice that for all other candidates".

The religion preference question was eventually dropped from the admission application forms and noticeable evidence of informal ''numerus clausus'' policies in the American private universities and medical schools decreased by the 1950s.{{citation needed|date=March 2016}}

==As related to matters other than education==
''Numerus clausus'' is also a rule that regulates the number of practitioners of a public service in many areas. In the U.S., for instance, it can limit the number of liquor stores to be found in a given geographic area.

In France, it limits the distribution of [[civil law notary|public notaries]] geographically and, in effect, limits competition for their services (since their fees are fixed by the state). Notaries handle, for instance, title transactions, which is not allowed to lawyers in France. Similar limitations apply to [[pharmacist]]s, and to licensed premises for the consumption of strong alcoholic beverages.

In India the system of [[Mandal Commission|caste quotas for job placement]] is enforced,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url = http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2003-08-16/news/27551045_1_upper-caste-quota-obc-leaders-mandal-commission | title = Fear of OBC backlash may derail upper caste quota plan | website = timesofindia-economictimes | access-date = 2016-02-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and vigorously defended by strikes and riots.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | url = https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/feb/22/india-caste-protesters-accept-offer-to-end-riots-and-water-crisis | title = Delhi faces water crisis after canal sabotaged in deadly protests | last = France-Presse | first = Agence | date = 2016-02-22 | newspaper = The Guardian | language = en-GB | issn = 0261-3077 | access-date = 2016-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Often, the rule is administered by the corporation or professional body to which the public servant must adhere, but it is also employed by state entities that have the responsibility for assuring the uniformity of a public service across a national geography.

===Law===
{{main article|Numerus clausus (law)}}
''Numerus clausus'' is also used in law, [[property]] law in particular, as the principle that the [[Real estate|system of estates]]&lt;ref&gt;A Kellner "[http://www.grin.com/e-book/25439/a-description-of-the-system-of-estates-in-england-and-germany-in-the-18th A Description of the System of Estates in England and Germany in the 18th Century on the Basis of German Travel Reports]" {{ISBN|978-3-638-28068-6}};&lt;br /&gt;J.M. Moringiello "[http://inderscience.metapress.com/index/133U12211148683G.pdf Towards a system of estates in virtual property]" International Journal of Private Law, vol. 1, nr. 1–2 / 2008 pp. 3–13&lt;/ref&gt; allows only a [[Bundle of rights|limited number of property rights]] available in a legal system.&lt;ref&gt;TW Merrill, HE Smith "[http://www.yalelawjournal.org/pdf/110-1/NEW%20MERRILL.pdf Optimal standardization in the law of property: the ''numerus clausus'' principle]" Yale Law Journal, 10/2000; &lt;br /&gt;H Hansmann, R Kraakman "[http://lsr.nellco.org/harvard/olin/papers/388/ Property, contract, and verification: the ''Numerus Clausus'' problem and the divisibility of rights]" The Journal of Legal Studies, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; The ''numerus clausus'' principle has its roots in [[Roman law]].&lt;ref&gt;F Parisi "[http://www.law.gmu.edu/assets/files/publications/working_papers/05-38.pdf THE FALL AND RISE OF FUNCTIONAL PROPERTY]" George Mason Law &amp; Economics Research Paper No. 05-38 2005&lt;/ref&gt; In German law the ''numerus clausus'' principle has a constitutional foundation&lt;ref&gt;A Peukert "Güterzuordnung als Rechtsprinzip" (Mohr Siebeck, 2008) {{ISBN|978-3-16-149724-7}}; &lt;br /&gt;V. Jänich "Geistiges Eigentum – Eine Komplementärerscheinung zum Sacheigentum?" (Mohr Siebeck, 2002) {{ISBN|978-3-16-147647-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and limits property rights in their number (Typenzwang) and content (Typenfixierung). Other European states show equal doctrines.&lt;ref&gt;B. Akkermans, "The Principle of ''Numerus Clausus'' in European Property Law" (Antwerpen/Oxford/Portland: Intersentia, 2008) {{ISBN|978-90-5095-824-0}}; &lt;br /&gt;T.H.D. Struycken, "De ''Numerus Clausus'' in het Goederenrecht" (Deventer: Kluwer, 2007) {{ISBN|978-90-13-04105-7}}; &lt;br /&gt;L David "[http://wwp.biz/publications/338.pdf Ist der ''Numerus clausus'' der Immaterialgüterrechte noch zeitgemäss?]" Aktuelle Juristische Praxis (AJP), 1995&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Ghetto benches]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
;Books
* J Karabel, ''The Chosen: The Hidden History of Admission and Exclusion at Harvard, Yale, and Princeton'' (Houghton Mifflin, 2005)
* MG Synnot, 'Anti-Semitism and American Universities: Did Quotas Follow the Jews?', in [[Jeffrey S. Gurock]] (ed), ''Anti-Semitism in America'' (Routledge 1998) vol. VI, part 2

;Articles
* T Merrill and H Smith, ‘Optimal Standardization in the Law of Property: The Numerus Clausus Principle’ (2000) 110 Yale Law Journal 1
* H Hansmann and R Kraakman, ‘Property, Contract and Verification: The Numerus Clausus Problem and the Divisibility of Rights’ (2002) 31 Journal of Legal Studies 373

{{DEFAULTSORT:Numerus Clausus}}
[[Category:Education issues]]
[[Category:Education policy]]
[[Category:History of education]]
[[Category:Latin words and phrases]]
[[Category:Religious discrimination]]
[[Category:University and college admissions]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>