<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20030923031529|1470134" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="315938" pageid="315938" ns="0" title="Numerus clausus"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-09-23T07:27:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[he:&amp;#1504;&amp;#1493;&amp;#1502;&amp;#1512;&amp;#1493;&amp;#1505; &amp;#1511;&amp;#1500;&amp;#1488;&amp;#1493;&amp;#1494;&amp;#1493;&amp;#1505;]]
'''Numerus Clausus''' (''"closed number"'' in [[Latin language|latin]]) means 
limiting the number of students in universities and colleges according to a discriminatory rule.

Before the [[Second World War]] the limitations were usually based, in eastern [[Europe]], on the [[religion]] of the student, as the number of students of [[Jewish]] origin was limited.

The limitation was in form of total prohibition of acceptance of Jewish students, or limiting the number of Jewish students so that their share in the students' population will be not larger than their share in the general population.

== Countries installing limitations on admission of Jewish students==

* In [[Russia]] '''Numerus Clausus''' was introduced in [[1887]], saying that the share of Jewish students will be no more than 10% in cities where [[Jews]] were allowed to live, 5% in other cities, and only 3% in [[Moscow]] and [[St. Petersburg]]. These limitations were deleted after the revolution of 1917.
* In [[Hungary]] '''Numerus Clausus''' Act was enacted in [[1920]], as part of the raise of [[Anti-Semitism]] under the government of [[Miklos Horthy]]. It said that Jewish students will be no more than 6% of students population (this was the share of Jews in the general population), compared to 30% before the war. Limitaions were relaxed in [[1928]].
* [[Poland]] tried to introduce formal '''Numerus Clausus''' in 1923, but faced objection by the [[League of Nations]]. '''Numerus Clausus''' was intruduced unofficially by the universities. The share of Jewish students was limited to 10%, much less than the share of Jews in the population of Poland. In 1937, with the raise of Anti-Semitism, acceptance of Jewish students was totally prohibited.
* In [[Romania]] '''Numerus Clausus''' was introduced in [[1926]].
* In the [[United States]], limitations on the enrollment of Jewish students to the universities were practiced unofficialy in the 1920's, especially in the northeastern universities.

Jews who wanted education used various ways to handle this obstacle: bribing the authorities, changing their religion, or traveling to countries without such limitations. In Hungary, for example, 5,000 Jewish youngsters (including [[Edward Teller]]) left the country after the introduction of '''Numerus Clausus'''.

== External links ==

* [http://rwa.bibks.uu.se/link33.html?Numerus_Clausus?Effects_of?Attitued_towards?Methods_of_Circumvent The Raoul Wallenberg archive] index on Numerus clausus (english)
* [http://www.remember.org/jean/Chap1/timeline_HUNGARY3.htm (timeline, english)]
* [http://www.rubicon.hu/assign.php3?ID=1997010105 article (hungarian)]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>