<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101012171749|390322326" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="14698138" pageid="14698138" ns="0" title="Kill Haole Day"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-16T23:38:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In [[Hawaii|Hawai{{okina}}i]]'s schools, the last day of school before summer is reputedly known as '''Kill Haole Day'''. On Kill Haole Day, school children harass and sometimes assault white children. The origins of the day are unknown, but the tradition dates back to the 1950s.  

In the [[Hawaiian language]], ''[[haole]]'' means "foreign" or "foreigner".&lt;ref&gt;{{Hawaiian Dictionaries |Haole |accessdate= September 22, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The word predates the [[1778]] arrival of Captain [[James Cook]] (which is the generally accepted date of first contact with westerners), as recorded in several chants stemming from antiquity. Haole, in its current definition, first became associated with the children of [[Caucasoid|Caucasian]] immigrants in the early 1820s. It unified the self-identity of these Hawai{{okina}}i-born children whose parents were as culturally different as the children were similar.  For Haole children whose first language was Hawaiian, their parents were generally either [[missionary|religious missionaries]] or secular businessmen, and hailed from both [[Europe]] and [[North America]], not necessarily speaking a common [[dialect]] or even language. Over the years, "Haole" became an expression of contempt. Though its first usage described members of a socioeconomic class, it added a racial component, erroneously replacing "malihini" (newcomer) in addressing first generation Hawaiians originally from the continental U.S. Today it is applied to any Caucasian, or to those who think or behave in a "foreign" manner. In current application, Haole can be used either descriptively or as a racial slur (often, if not generally, preceded by an obscene invective).

In his 2009 book, lawyer and former Hawai{{okina}}i governor Ben Cayetano wrote that "Kill Haole Day" began as a news story headline about an incident between haole and local (not just Hawaiian) students. After that, "whenever there was a fight or an incident between haole and local students, the news media, particularly the newspapers with their haole-dominated editorial boards, repeatedly reprised 'Kill Haole Day' in their news stories -- as if it were a Hawaiian tradition."&lt;ref&gt;Cayetano, Ben. ''Ben: A Memoir, From Street Kid to Governor'' (Watermark, 2009), p. 531&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1999, School Superintendent Paul LeMahieu said he is aware of "kill haole day" but is not aware of any recent incidents. Also, in 1999, it became an issue for [[hate crimes]] legislation.&lt;ref name="starbulletin"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://starbulletin.com/1999/03/24/news/story7.html|title=‘Kill haole day’ linked to hate-crime bill}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Hate crime laws in the United States]]
* [[Local Law Enforcement Hate Crimes Prevention Act of 2007]]
* [[Beat Up a White Kid Day]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{Racism topics}}



[[Category:Hate crime]]
[[Category:Racism]]


{{Crime-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>