<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141026033138|631138750" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="14698138" pageid="14698138" ns="0" title="Kill Haole Day"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-06T05:49:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2012}}
'''Kill Haole Day''' is an annual event that some believe has occurred in some of [[Hawaii|Hawai{{okina}}i]]'s schools. On the last day of school before summer vacation, non-white students are said to harass and sometimes attack [[White people|white]] students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|location=Great Britain|author=Community Relations Commission|journal=New community|volume=7–8|page=267|issn=0047-9586|oclc=615546790|quote=My students talked of the High Schools' 'Kill Haole Day' when a day in the school year was dedicated to roughing up the whites.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his 2009 book, lawyer and former Hawai{{okina}}i governor [[Ben Cayetano]] wrote that "Kill Haole Day" began as a news story headline about an incident between [[haole]] and local (not just Hawaiian) students. After that, "whenever there was a fight or an incident between haole and non-haole students, the news media, particularly the newspapers with their haole-dominated editorial boards, repeatedly reprised 'Kill Haole Day' in their news stories – as if it were a Hawaiian tradition."&lt;ref&gt;Cayetano, Ben. ''Ben: A Memoir, From Street Kid to Governor'' (Watermark, 2009), p. 531&lt;/ref&gt;
 	
In 1999, School Superintendent Paul LeMahieu said he is aware of "kill haole day" but is not aware of any recent incidents. Also, in 1999, it became an issue for [[hate crimes]] legislation.&lt;ref name="starbulletin"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://starbulletin.com/1999/03/24/news/story7.html|title=‘Kill haole day’ linked to hate-crime bill}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  		  	
Newspaper columnist Lee Cataluna wrote in 2010, "In terms of actual, first-person, eyewitness accounts of Kill Haole Day, no one had any [incidents] that happened in the last three decades. Not one teacher, not one police officer, not one victim or perpetrator."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Catalune, Lee|title=Responses refute existence of any recent 'Kill Haole Day'|work=Honolulu Advertiser|date=November 23, 2010|url=http://www.staradvertiser.com/news/20101123_responses_refute_existence_of_any_recent_kill_haole_day.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Hawaii|Discrimination}}
* [[Hate crime laws in the United States]]
* [[Local Law Enforcement Hate Crimes Prevention Act of 2007]]
* [[Beat Up a White Kid Day]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Racism topics}}

[[Category:Hate crime]]
[[Category:History of racism in Hawaii]]
[[Category:Racism in the United States]]
[[Category:Xenophobia]]
[[Category:Racially motivated violence against European Americans]]

{{Crime-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>