<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151030022228|688168504" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="67084" pageid="67084" ns="0" title="Transphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-10-31T21:54:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!---
PLEASE NOTE:
When the article Transprejudice was merged into this article, consensus was reached that that term must remain in this article. Thus, please do not remove references to the term "transprejudice" from this article. Thank you.
--&gt;
{{Globalize |date=October 2015 |discuss=Talk:Transphobia#Globalize}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}

'''Transphobia''' (or much less commonly '''transprejudice''') is a range of antagonistic attitudes and feelings against [[transsexuality]] and transsexual or [[transgender]] people. Researchers describe transphobia as emotional disgust, fear, anger or discomfort felt or expressed towards people who do not conform to society's gender expectations,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Hate Crime: Impact, Causes and Responses|last = Chakraborti|first = Neil and Jon Garland|publisher = SAGE Publications, Ltd.|year = 2009|isbn = 1412945682|location = |pages = 77}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Handbook of Gender Research in Psychology, Volume 2|last = Chrisler, Donald R. McCreary|first = Joan C.|publisher = Springer|year = 2010|isbn = 1441913556|location = |pages = 366}}&lt;/ref&gt; and say that although it is an aspect of [[homophobia]],&lt;ref name="Adams"&gt;{{cite book|authors=Maurianne Adams, Lee Anne Bell, Pat Griffin|title=Teaching for Diversity and Social Justice|isbn =1135928509|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=2007|pages=198–199|accessdate=December 27, 2014|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zgGUAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA198|quote=Because of the complicated interplay among gender identity, gender roles, and sexual identity, transgender people are often assumed to be lesbian or gay (See ''Overview: Sexism, Heterosexism, and Transgender Oppression''). ... Because transgender identity challenges a binary conception of sexuality and gender, educators must clarify their own understanding of these concepts. ... Facilitators must be able to help participants understand the connections among sexism, heterosexism, and transgender oppression and the ways in which gender roles are maintained, in part, through homophobia.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Schuiling"&gt;{{cite book|authors=Kerri Durnell Schuiling, Frances E. Likis|title=Women's Gynecologic Health|isbn =0763756377|publisher=[[Jones &amp; Bartlett Publishers]]|year=2011|pages=187–188|accessdate=December 27, 2014|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pj_ourS3PBMC&amp;pg=PA186|quote=Homophobia is an individual's irrational fear or hate of homosexual people. This may include bisexual or transgender persons, but sometimes the more distinct terms of biphobia or transphobia, respectively, are used.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is similar to [[racism]] and [[sexism]], those attitudes are becoming generally unacceptable in modern society, whereas significantly more individuals still maintain transphobic views without fear of censure.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Microaggressions and Marginality: Manifestation, Dynamics, and Impact|last = Wing Sue|first = Derald|publisher = Wiley|year = 2010|isbn = 0470491396|location = |pages = 224}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The related term [[cissexism]] (or cissexual assumption, which is occasionally used synonymously with ''transphobia'' or, more rarely, '''''cisgenderism''''') is the appeal to norms that enforce the gender binary and gender essentialism, resulting in the oppression of gender variant, non-binary, and trans identities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://everydayfeminism.com/2014/03/everyday-cissexism/|title=3 Examples of Everyday Cissexism|author=Sian Ferguson|work=Everyday Feminism|accessdate=7 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cisgenderism refers to the assumption that, due to human [[sexual differentiation]], one's [[gender]] is determined solely by a [[biological sex]] of male or female (based on the assumption that all people must have either an [[XY sex-determination system|XX or XY]] sex-[[chromosome]] pair, or, in the case of cisgenderism, a bivalent male or female expression), and that trans people are inferior to [[cisgender]] people due to being in "defiance of nature".&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{cite journal|last= Lennon|first= Erica|last2= Mistler|first2= Brian|date= 2014|title= Cisgenderism|url= |journal=Transgender Studies Quarterly |publisher= |volume=1 |issue=1 |pages=63–64 |doi= 10.1215/23289252-2399623|accessdate=November 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Whether intentional or not, transphobia and cissexism have severe consequences for the target of the negative attitude. As homophobia and transphobia are correlated, many trans people experience homophobia and [[heterosexism]]; this is due to people who associate trans people's gender identity with [[homosexuality]], or because trans people also have a [[sexual orientation]] that is [[non-heterosexual]].&lt;ref name="Adams"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lives" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Spijkerboer"&gt;{{cite book|author=Thomas Spijkerboer|title=Fleeing Homophobia: Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity and Asylum|isbn =1134098359|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=2013|page=122|accessdate=December 27, 2014|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oOxBtViD0KcC&amp;pg=PA122|quote=Transgender people subjected to violence, in a range of cultural contexts, frequently report that transphobic violence is expressed in homophobic terms. The tendency to translate violence against a trans person to homophobia reflects the role of gender in attribution of homosexuality as well as the fact that hostility connected to homosexuality is often associated with the perpetrators' prejudices about particular gender practices and their visibility.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Attacking someone on the basis of a perception of their gender identity rather than a perception of their sexual orientation is known as "[[trans bashing]]", analogous to "[[gay bashing]]".

== Etymology and use ==
The word ''transphobia'' is a [[classical compound]] patterned on the term ''[[homophobia]]'', sharing its second component ''-phobia'' from the {{lang-el|φόβος}}, ''phóbos'', "fear".  The first component is the [[English prefixes#Neo-classical|neo-classical prefix]] ''trans-'' from ''transgender'' (originally meaning "across, on the far side, beyond"). Along with ''[[biphobia]]'', ''homophobia'' and ''transphobia'' are members of the family of terms used when [[Bigotry|intolerance]] and discrimination is directed toward [[LGBT]] people.

''Transphobia'' need not be a [[phobia]] as defined in [[clinical psychology]] (i.e., an [[anxiety disorder]]). Its meaning and use typically parallel those of ''[[xenophobia]]''.

The [[Adjective|adjectival]] form ''transphobic'' describes things or qualities related to transphobia, whereas the noun ''transphobe'' is a label for people thought to harbor transphobia.

==Origins==
The [[Transfeminism|transfeminist]] theorist and author [[Julia Serano]] argues in her book ''[[Whipping Girl]]'' that transphobia is rooted in [[sexism]]. She locates the origins of both transphobia and homophobia in what she calls "oppositional sexism", the belief that male and female are "rigid, mutually exclusive categories, each possessing a unique and nonoverlapping set of attributes, aptitudes, abilities, and desires". Serano contrasts oppositional sexism with "traditional sexism", the belief that males and [[masculinity]] are superior to females and [[femininity]]. Furthermore, she writes that transphobia is fueled by insecurities people have about gender and gender norms.&lt;ref name=serano&gt;Julia Serano. ''Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Sexism and the Scapegoating of Femininity'', Seal Press, 2007. ISBN 978-1-58005-154-5, ISBN 1-58005-154-5&lt;/ref&gt;

The transgender author and critic Jody Norton believes that transphobia is an extension of homophobia and [[misogyny]]. She argues that transgender people, like gays and lesbians, are hated and feared for challenging and undermining [[Gender role|gender norms]] and the [[gender binary]]. Norton writes that the "male-to-female transgender incites transphobia through her implicit challenge to the binary division of gender upon which male cultural and political hegemony depends".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Norton|first=Jody|title="Brain Says You're a Girl, But I Think You're a Sissy Boy": Cultural Origins of Transphobia|journal=International Journal of Sexuality and Gender Studies|year=1997|volume=2, Number 2|pages=139–164|doi=10.1023/A:1026320611878|issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Manifestations ==

===Harassment and violence===
{{see also|Violence against LGBT people}}
Harassment and violence directed against transgender people is often called [[trans bashing]], and can be physical, sexual or verbal. Whereas [[gay bashing]] is directed against a target's real or perceived [[sexual orientation]], trans bashing is directed against the target's real or perceived expressed [[gender identity]]. The term has also been applied to [[hate speech]] directed at transgender people&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonblade.com/2007/4-27/view/columns/10484.cfm Demagogues of defamation Gay: Where is the outrage when cable TV’s talking heads trash trans people?]&lt;/ref&gt; and to depictions of transgender people in the media that reinforce negative stereotypes about them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Mary|last=McNamara|title=Transgender Artists, Work Gaining Acceptance|publisher=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=2001-02-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Notable victims of violent crimes motivated by transphobia include [[Brandon Teena]], [[Gwen Araujo]], [[Angie Zapata]], [[Nizah Morris]], and [[Lauren Harries]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/4218250.stm|title=Transsexual to move to 'safer' LA|publisher=[[BBC News]]|date=6 September 2005}}]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[American Psychological Association]], transgender children are more likely than other children to experience harassment and violence in school, foster care, residential treatment centers, homeless centers and juvenile justice programs.&lt;ref name="Cisgenderism"&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Cisgenderism in psychology: pathologising and misgendering children from 1999 to 2008|year = 2011|url = http://epubs.surrey.ac.uk/72252/2/YGA%20%26%20PH%202011%20Cisgenderism.pdf|last = Ansara and Peter Hegarty|first = Y. Gavriel|journal = Psychology &amp; Sexuality|publisher = Routledge University Press|accessdate = 20 September 2013|doi = 10.1080/19419899.2011.576696}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers say trans youth routinely experience taunting, teasing and bullying at school, and that nearly all trans youth say they were verbally or physically harassed in school, particularly during gym class, at school events, or when using single-sex restrooms. Three-quarters report having felt unsafe.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

As adults, transgender people are frequently subjected to ridicule, stares, taunting and threats of violence, even when just walking down the street or walking into a store.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Transgender Voices: Beyond Women and Men|last = Girshick|first = Lori B.|publisher = University Press of New England|year = 2008|isbn = 158465838X|location = Hanover and London|pages = 133–144}}&lt;/ref&gt; A U.S. survey of 402 older, employed, high-income transgender people found that 60% reported violence or harassment because of their gender identity. 56% had been harassed or verbally abused, 30% had been assaulted, 17% had had objects thrown at them, 14% had been robbed and 8% had experienced what they characterized as an unjustified arrest.&lt;ref name="Lives"&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Lives of Transgender People|last = Beemyn|first = Genny|publisher = Columbia University Press|year = 2011|isbn = 0231143079|location = New York|pages = 91}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A study of 81 transgender people in [[Philadelphia]] found 30% reported feeling unsafe in public because they were transgender, with 19% feeling uncomfortable for the same reason. When asked if they had ever been forced to have sex, experienced violence in their home, or been physically abused, the majority answered yes to each question.&lt;ref name=":9"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Transgender Health and HIV Prevention: Needs Assessment Studies from Transgender Communities Across the United States|last = Bockting|first = Walter O.|publisher = CRC Press|year = 2006|isbn = 0789030152|location = |pages = 41–53}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A review of American studies on sexual violence towards transgender people found that around 50% of transgender people have been sexually assaulted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Stotzer|first=Rebecca|title=Violence against transgender people: A review of United States data|journal=Aggression and Violent Behavior|volume=14|issue=3|pages=170–179|url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1359178909000202|accessdate=9 April 2014|doi=10.1016/j.avb.2009.01.006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When transgender people are murdered, they are often shot or stabbed repeatedly, riddled with bullets or bludgeoned beyond recognition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Encyclopedia of Educational Psychology|last = Salkind|first = Neil|publisher = SAGE|year = 2008|isbn = 1412916887|location = |pages = 432}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Misgendering and exclusion===
{{anchor|deadnaming}}

Misgendering is a word coined by transgender American writer and biologist [[Julia Serano]] to refer to the experience of being labeled by someone as having a gender other than the one you identify with.&lt;ref name="Serano2009"&gt;{{cite book|author=Julia Serano|title=Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Sexism and the Scapegoating of Femininity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fR5ji5h5g1MC|date=20 May 2009|publisher=Seal Press|isbn=0-7867-4791-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Misgendering can be deliberate or accidental. It ordinarily takes the form of a person using pronouns (including "it") to describe someone that are not the ones that person prefers,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Queer Youth Cultures|last = Driver|first = Susan|publisher = State University of New York Press|year = 2008|isbn = 0791473384|location = |pages = 88}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Transgender Explained For Those Who Are Not|last = Herman|first = Joanne|publisher = AuthorHouse|year = 2009|isbn = 1449029574|pages = 50–51}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":11"&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Riddle of Gender: Science, Activism, and Transgender Rights|last = Rudacille|first = Deborah|publisher = Pantheon|year = 2005|isbn = 0375421629|location = |pages = 164–180}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Transgender Rights|last = Currah|first = Paisley|publisher = University of Minnesota Press|year = 2006|isbn = 0816643121|pages = 194}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":24"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Transgender Employment Experiences: Gendered Perceptions and the Law|last = Bender-Baird|first = Kyla|publisher = SUNY Press|year = 2011|isbn = 1438436742|pages = 5–24}}&lt;/ref&gt; calling a person "ma'am" or "sir" in contradiction to the person's gender identity,&lt;ref name=":11" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Q &amp; A: Queer in Asian America|last = Eng|first = David L.|publisher = Temple University Press|year = 1998|isbn = 1566396409|location = |pages = 232–233}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Looking Queer: Body Image and Identity in Lesbian, Bisexual, Gay, and Transgender Communities (Haworth Gay &amp; Lesbian Studies)|last = DeCecco|first = John|publisher = Routledge|year = 2012|isbn = 0789004631|location = New Jersey|pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt; using a pre-transition name for someone instead of a post-transition one&lt;ref name=":24" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Transgender Phenomenon|last = Ekins|first = Richard|publisher = |year = |isbn = 1847877265|location = |pages = 199}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Just One of the Guys?: Transgender Men and the Persistence of Gender Inequality|last = Schilt|first = Kristen|publisher = University Of Chicago Press|year = 2011|isbn = 1847877265|location = |pages = 167}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title = Media willfully misgender Chelsea Manning|date = 22 August 2013|url = http://www.salon.com/2013/08/22/media_willfully_misgender_chelsea_manning/|last = McDonough|first = Katie|publisher = Salon Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; (called "[[wikt:deadname|deadnaming]]"),&lt;ref&gt;
*{{cite news |first=Meredith Ramirez |last=Talusan |title=What 'deadnaming' means, and why you shouldn’t do it to Caitlyn Jenner |work=Fusion |date=June 4, 2015 |url=http://fusion.net/story/144324/what-deadnaming-means-and-why-you-shouldnt-do-it-to-caitlyn-jenner/ |accessdate=2015-06-08}}
*{{cite news|last1=Selby|first1=Jenn|title=Sarah Vine criticises lesbian mother Jack Monroe: 'If she was unsure about her sexuality, she should have taken greater precautions'|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/sarah-vine-on-jack-monroe-being-a-lesbian-mother-if-she-was-unsure-about-her-sexuality-she-should-have-taken-greater-precautions-9882054.html|accessdate=8 July 2015|work=The Independent|date=25 November 2014}}
*{{cite web|last1=Fae|first1=Jane|title=Changing your name should be a joyous moment, but for many it's a nightmare|url=http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/may/19/changing-your-name-nightmare-trans|website=Comment is Free|accessdate=8 July 2015|date=19 May 2015}}
*{{cite web|last1=Strapagiel|first1=Lauren|title=A Bar's Instagram Account Targeted Caitlyn Jenner With An Anti-Trans Post|url=http://www.buzzfeed.com/laurenstrapagiel/this-canadian-bar-posted-a-transphobic-image-about-caitlyn-j|website=BuzzFeed LGBT News|accessdate=8 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; or insisting that a person behave consistently with their assigned rather than self-identified gender, for example by using a bathroom designated for males even though the person identifies as female. The experience of being misgendered is common for all transgender people before they transition, and for many afterwards as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Sexual Deceit: The Ethics of Passing|last = Harrison|first = Kelby|publisher = Lexington Books|year = 2013|isbn = 0739177052|location = |pages = 12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people are regularly misgendered by doctors,&lt;ref name="Cisgenderism" /&gt; police, media and peers, experiences that they have described as mortifying,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Cisgenderism in Medical Settings: Challenging Structural Violence Through Collaborative Partnerships|date = |url = http://ansaraonline.com/yahoo_site_admin/assets/docs/Chapter_Seven_Ansara_with_Reference.19690148.pdf|last = Ansara|first = Y. Gavriel|accessdate = 20 September 2013|doi = |publisher = |page = 95}}&lt;/ref&gt; hurtful, especially to transgender youth,&lt;ref name=":16"&gt;{{Cite news|title = Shouting Disrupts Vigil For Murdered Transgender Woman Islan Nettles|date = 28 August 2013|url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/08/28/islan-nettles_n_3832004.html|last = Shapiro|first = Lila|publisher = Huffington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; cruel,&lt;ref name=":17"&gt;{{Cite news|title = Gender Block: Media misgendering and Chelsea Manning|date = 16 September 2013|url = http://this.org/blog/2013/09/16/gender-block-media-misgendering-and-chelsea-manning/|last = Di Menna|first = Hillary|publisher = This Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; and "only making our lives harder".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title = The happy story of my transgender coming-out|date = 23 August 2013|url = http://www.salon.com/2013/08/23/the_happy_story_of_my_transgender_coming_out/|last = Molloy|first = Parker Marie|publisher = Salon magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; Knowingly and deliberately misgendering a transgender person is considered extremely offensive by transgender individuals.&lt;ref name=":16" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":17" /&gt;
In 2008, Allen Andrade beat to death Colorado transgender teenager Angie Zapata, whom he later described to police as "it."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Homofiles: Theory, Sexuality, and Graduate Studies|last = Battis|first = Jess|publisher = Lexington Books|year = 2011|isbn = 0739131915|location = |pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2013, after murdered 21-year-old New York trans woman Islan Nettles was referred to as "he" by a speaker at her memorial service, transgender actress [[Laverne Cox]] characterized misgendering as "part of the violence that led to Islan's death."&lt;ref name=":16" /&gt;

In 2014, a Connecticut trans girl known only as Jane Doe (due to her status as a minor) has several times been placed in facilities for men and boys during her continuing imprisonment without charges. She has also been misgendered by the writers of some letters to the editor of the ''[[Hartford Courant]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.courant.com/keyword/jane-doe|title=Articles about Jane Doe - tribunedigital-thecourant|publisher=|accessdate=7 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Transgender people are often excluded from entitlements or privileges reserved for people whose gender identity they share, but whose assigned gender they do not. It is very common, for example, for transgender women to be stopped or questioned when they use public bathrooms designated for women.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":24" /&gt;

Homeless shelters, hospitals and prisons have denied trans women admission to women's areas and forced them to sleep and bathe in the presence of men.&lt;ref name="transparent"&gt;{{cite book |last= Beam|first= Cris |title= Transparent |publisher= Harvest Books |date=January 2008|isbn= 978-0-15-603377-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This situation has been changing in some areas, however. For example, on February 8, 2006, New York City's Department of Homeless Services announced an overhaul of its housing policy with the goal of specifically ending discrimination against transgender people in its shelters.&lt;ref name="housing"&gt;{{cite web
 |title=NYC's Department of Homeless Services Issues a Trans-Affirmative Housing Policy
 |publisher=The Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Center
 |date=5 February 2006
 |url=http://www.gaycenter.org/news/press/News.2006-02-07.3578982442/news_view
 |accessdate=6 September 2006 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060615050747/http://www.gaycenter.org/news/press/News.2006-02-07.3578982442/news_view &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 15 June 2006}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===As users of healthcare===
{{See also|Healthcare and the LGBT community}}
A study of 81 transgender people in [[Philadelphia]] found 14% said they had been refused routine medical care because they were transgender. 18% answered yes when asked if, when they went in for a check-up, "being transgendered create[d] a problem" for them.&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt;

Transgender people depend largely on the medical profession to receive not only [[Hormone replacement therapy (trans)|hormone replacement therapy]], but also vital care. In one case, [[Robert Eads]] died of ovarian cancer after being refused treatment by more than two dozen doctors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ftminfo.net/sundance.html|title=FTM Informational Network&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;|accessdate=2009-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In the US-based National Center For Transgender Equality's 2011 survey, 19% had been [[refused medical care]] due to their transgender or gender non-conforming status,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Injustice at Every Turn A Report of the National Transgender Discrimination Survey|url=http://transequality.org/PDFs/Executive_Summary.pdf|publisher=transequality.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; showing that refusal of treatment due to transphobia is not uncommon.
Another example of this is the case of [[Tyra Hunter]]. Hunter was involved in an automobile accident, and when [[Emergency medical services|rescue workers]] discovered she was transgender, they backed away and stopped administering treatment. She later died in a hospital.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.glaa.org/archive/1998/margiehunter1211.shtml|title=Victory in Tyra Hunter case&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;|accessdate=2009-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In many European countries, any transgender person who wishes to change their legal gender must first be sterilized. Several countries are reviewing this law; Sweden repealed it in December 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pazulka|first=Nicole|title=17 European Countries Force Transgender Sterilization|url=http://www.motherjones.com/mojo/2012/02/most-european-countries-force-sterilization-transgender-people-map|accessdate=August 24, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== In the workplace ===
Transphobia also manifests itself in the workplace. Some transgender people lose their [[employment|jobs]] when they begin to transition. A study from [[Willamette University]] stated that a transsexual person fired for following the recommended course of treatment rarely wins it back through federal or state statutes.&lt;ref name="TransEmploy"&gt;{{cite web |author=JoAnna McNamara
|title=Employment discrimination and the Transsexual|publisher=[[Willamette University]]|date=30 August 1996|url=http://www.willamette.edu/~rrunkel/gwr/mcnamara|accessdate=10 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

News stories from the ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'' and [[Associated Press]] cite a 1999 study by the [[San Francisco Department of Public Health]] finding a 70 percent [[unemployment]] rate amongst the city's transgender population. On February 18, 1999, the San Francisco Department of Public Health issued the results of a 1997 survey of 392 trans women and 123 trans men, which found that 40 percent of those trans women surveyed had earned money from full or part-time employment over the preceding six months. For trans men, the equivalent statistic was 81 percent. The survey also found that 46 percent of trans women and 57 percent of trans men reported [[employment discrimination]].&lt;ref name="transhealth"&gt;{{cite web |author=The Transgender Community Health Project |title=Sociodemographics|work=Descriptive Results|publisher=[http://hivinsite.ucsf.edu HIVInSite]|date=18 February 1999|url=http://hivinsite.ucsf.edu/InSite?page=cftg-02-02#S5.1X|accessdate=7 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2002 American study found that among educators, trans educators are 10-20% more likely to experience workplace harassment than their gay and lesbian colleagues.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

In the hiring process, discrimination may be either open or covert, with employers finding other ostensible reasons not to hire a candidate or just not informing prospective employees at all as to why they are not being hired. Additionally, when an employer fires or otherwise discriminates against a transgender employee, it may be a "mixed motive" case, with the employer openly citing obvious wrongdoing, job performance issues or the like (such as excessive tardiness, for example) while keeping silent in regards to transphobia.{{citation needed|date=September 2011}}

[[Workplace discrimination|Employment discrimination]] on the basis of gender identity and expression is [[Legal aspects of transsexualism in the United States#Discrimination|illegal in some U.S. cities, towns and states]]. Such discrimination is outlawed by specific legislation in the State of New Jersey and might be in other states (as it is in the states of California, Illinois, Maine, Minnesota, New Mexico and Washington) or city ordinances; additionally, it is covered by case law in some other states. (For example, Massachusetts is covered by cases such as Lie vs. Sky Publishing Co. and Jette vs. Honey Farms.) Several other states and cities prohibit such discrimination in public employment. Sweden and the United Kingdom has also legislated against employment discrimination on the grounds of gender identity. Sometimes, however, employers discriminate against transgender employees in spite of such legal protections.&lt;ref name="TransEmploy2"&gt;{{cite web |author=barbara findlay, Q.C. |title=Transgendered people and Employment: An equality analysis |publisher=[http://www.barbarafindlay.com/ barbara findlay Law Office]|date=June 1999|url=http://www.barbarafindlay.com/articles/43.pdf|accessdate=10 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is at least one high-profile employment-related court case unfavorable to transgender people. In 2000, the southern U.S. grocery chain [[Winn-Dixie (supermarket)|Winn-Dixie]] fired longtime employee Peter Oiler, despite a history of repeatedly earning raises and promotions, after management learned that the married, heterosexual truck driver occasionally [[crossdressing|cross-dressed]] off the job. Management argued that this hurt Winn-Dixie's corporate image. The [[American Civil Liberties Union]] filed a lawsuit against Winn-Dixie on behalf of Oiler but a judge dismissed it.&lt;ref name="ACLUWinnDixie"&gt;{{cite web |author=Ronald L. Wilson |title=Oliver v. Winn-Dixie Complaint |date=23 October 2000 |url=http://www.aclufl.org/legislature_courts/legal_department/briefs_complaints/oiler_complaint.cfm |accessdate=15 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sometimes transgender people facing employment discrimination turn to [[sex industry|sex work]] to survive,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Jacques|first=Juliet|title='No wonder many transsexual people end up in sex work'|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/lifeandstyle/2010/aug/25/transsexual-people-sex-work|accessdate=30 March 2012|newspaper=The Guardian|date=25 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; placing them at additional risk of such things as encountering troubles with the law, including arrest and criminal prosecution; enduring workplace violence; and possibly contracting [[sexually transmitted disease]]s such as [[HIV]].&lt;ref name="transhealth" /&gt;

=== From government ===
Transgender people also face the denial of [[right of asylum]] or inhuman treatment in process of asylum-seeking. For example, Fernada Milan, a transsexual woman from [[Guatemala]] was placed in an asylum center for males in [[Denmark]] and while there, was raped by several men. She was in danger of deportation into Guatemala where transgender people have no rights and face possible execution, but has since been granted entry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uncommon-scents.blogspot.co.uk/2012/08/what-im-most-afraid-of-when-i-go-back.html|title=UnCommon Sense|author=Natacha|publisher=|accessdate=7 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Transgender disenfranchisement is the practice of creating or upholding barriers that keep transgender individuals from [[voting]] and therefore restrict the principles of [[universal suffrage]].
{{See also|Transgender disenfranchisement in the United States}}

===In social conservatism===
The [[Christian Right]], including organizations such as the [[American Family Association]], [[Family Research Council]], [[Focus on the Family]], [[National Association for Research and Therapy of Homosexuality]], and [[Roman Catholic Church]], believe that transgenderism is unnatural and that transgender people are and remain their birth sex, and they oppose laws and policies intended to accommodate transgender people, such as allowing them to change their legal sex, use the washroom corresponding to the gender with which they identify, or become ordained Christian ministers. They say that God created people's bodies as they are meant to be, that accepting transgender people would violate scripture and natural law, and that the bible refers to male and female.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/transsexu9a.htm|title=Beliefs among religious conservatives about the causes &amp; cures of transsexuality (Cont'd)|publisher=|accessdate=7 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Ontario Consultants for Religious Tolerance website, under Pope [[John Paul II]], the [[Holy See|Vatican]] first stated its opposition to reassignment surgery in 2000, although it was not made public until 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/transsexu15.htm|title=Catholic beliefs about the causes &amp; cures of transsexuality|publisher=|accessdate=7 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In feminism===
{{See also|Feminist views on transgenderism and transsexualism}}
[[Radical feminist]] [[Janice Raymond]]'s 1979 book, ''The Transsexual Empire'', was and still is controversial due to its unequivocal condemnation of transsexual surgeries. In the book Raymond says, "All transsexuals rape women's bodies by reducing the real female form to an artifact, appropriating this body for themselves .... Transsexuals merely cut off the most obvious means of invading women, so that they seem non-invasive."&lt;ref name="Raymond 1994"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Raymond|first=J.|year=1994|title=The Transsexual Empire|publisher=Teachers College Press|edition=2nd|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to "." for the cite to end in a ".", as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Perhaps the most visible site of conflict between feminists and [[trans women]] has been the [[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]]. The festival ejected a transsexual woman, Nancy Burkholder, in the early 1990s.&lt;ref name="vangelder"&gt;
Van Gelder, Lindsy; and Pamela Robin Brandt. "The Girls Next Door: Into the Heart of Lesbian America", p. 73. Simon and Schuster, ISBN 978-0-684-83957-8&lt;/ref&gt; Since then, the festival has maintained an intention that it is for "[[womyn-born-womyn]]" only.&lt;ref&gt;http://michfest.com/festival_community_statements.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The activist group [[Camp Trans]] formed to protest the "womyn-born-womyn" intention and to advocate for greater acceptance of trans women within the feminist community. A number of prominent transgender activists and [[Transfeminism|transfeminists]] were involved in Camp Trans including [[Riki Wilchins]], Jessica Xavier, and [[Leslie Feinberg]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}} The festival considered allowing only post-operative trans women to attend, however this was criticized as [[Class discrimination|classist]], as many trans women cannot afford [[sex reassignment surgery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| last                  = Sreedhar
| first                 = Susanne
| authorlink            =
| editor-last           = Scott-Dixon
| editor-first          = Krista
| editor-link           =
| others                =
| title                 = Trans/Forming Feminisms: Trans/Feminist Voices Speak Out
| trans_title           =
| url                   = https://www.worldcat.org/title/transforming-feminisms-transfeminist-voices-speak-out/oclc/70839321
| archiveurl            =
| archivedate           =
| format                =
| accessdate            = September 30, 2013
| type                  =
| edition               =
| series                =
| volume                =
| year                  = 2006
| origyear              =
| month                 =
| publisher             = Sumach Press
| location              = Toronto
| isbn                  = 1-894-54961-9
| oclc                  = 70839321
| lccn                  =
| doi                   =
| bibcode               =
| id                    =
| page                  =
| pages                 = 164–65
| nopp                  =
| at                    =
| chapter               = The Ethics of Exclusion: Gender and Politics at the Michigan Womyn's Music Festival
| trans_chapter         =
| chapterurl            =
| quote                 =
| ref                   =
| laysummary            =
| laydate               =
| author-mask           =
| author-name-separator =
| author-separator      =
| display-authors       =
| separator             =
| postscript            =
| lastauthoramp            =
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Kimberly Nixon is a trans woman who volunteered for training as a rape crisis counselor at [[Vancouver Rape Relief &amp; Women's Shelter]] in Vancouver, British Columbia in 1995. When Nixon's transsexual status was determined, she was expelled. The staff decided that Nixon's status made it impossible for her to understand the experiences of their clients, and also required their clients to be genetically female. Nixon disagreed, disclosing her own history of partner abuse and sued for discrimination. Nixon's attorneys argued that there was no basis for the dismissal, citing Diana Courvant's experiences as the first publicly transsexual woman to work in a [[Women only space|women-only]] domestic violence shelter. In 2007 the Canadian Supreme Court refused to hear Nixon's appeal, ending the case.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.egale.ca/index.asp?lang=E&amp;menu=34&amp;item=1147&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rapereliefshelter.bc.ca/issues/nixon/jan082001_lakeman.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="perelle"&gt;
Perelle, Robin (February 14, 2007). Rape Relief wins: Supreme Court refuses to hear trans woman's appeal.'' [[Xtra!|Xtra]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Outside Canada, not all rape survivors organisations refuse to support transsexual rape survivors. Wellington Independent Rape Crisis featured former [[sex worker]], [[New Zealand Labour Party]] MP and the world's first transsexual elected national representative [[Georgina Beyer]] on one of its "Take Back the Night" marches as a rape survivor herself, and Beyer has also assisted the Auckland-based HELP Foundation for sexual abuse counselling, prevention and support, appearing in a poster campaign to call for higher levels of government funding.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}}

Transsexual women such as [[Sandy Stone (artist)|Sandy Stone]] challenged the feminist conception of "biological woman". Stone worked as a sound engineer for [[Olivia Records]] from about 1974 to 1978, resigning as the controversy over a trans woman working for a lesbian-identified enterprise increased.&lt;ref name="sayer"&gt;{{cite web|last=Sayer|first=Susan|title=From Lesbian Nation to Queer Nation|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_hb6655/is_n2_v21/ai_n28666686/|publisher=Hecate|date=1995-10-01|accessdate=2012-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The debate continued in Raymond's book,&lt;ref name="Raymond 1994"/&gt; which devoted a chapter to criticism of "the transsexually constructed lesbian-feminist." Groups like [[Lesbian Organization of Toronto]] then voted to exclude trans lesbians.&lt;ref name="ross1995"&gt;
Ross, Becki (1995). ''The House that Jill Built: A Lesbian Nation in Formation.'' University of Toronto Press, ISBN 978-0-8020-7479-9&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sheila Jeffreys]] labeled transgenderism "deeply problematic from a feminist perspective and [stated] that transsexualism should be seen as a violation of human rights."&lt;ref name="jeffreys1997"&gt;
Jeffreys, Sheila (1997). Transgender Activism: A Lesbian Feminist Perspective. "Journal of Lesbian Studies", Vol. 1(3/4) 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

However, [[Andrea Dworkin]], a noted [[anti-pornography feminist]] supported the right of trans women to be considered authentic women in her book ''Women-Hating'' (1978). Other cisgender feminist support came from the work of [[poststructuralist]] feminist [[Judith Butler]], particularly her books ''Gender Trouble'' (1990) and ''Bodies That Matter'' (1993), which argue that the violent "inscription" of gender as a social construct on human bodies leads to violence against those that violate such binaristic gender dichotomies.&lt;ref&gt;Judith Butler (1990). ''Gender Trouble''. New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Judith Butler (1993). ''Bodies That Matter''. New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt; Butler is lesbian. Most younger lesbian and other cisgender feminists strongly dissent from feminist transphobia. The latter is now generally regarded as archaic, rooted in feminists' historical distrust of patriarchal medical definitions of and interventions into women's physicality.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}}

===In the gay, lesbian, and bisexual communities===
Transphobia is documented in the [[lesbian]], [[gay]] and [[bisexual]] ([[LGBT|LGB]]) communities, despite historic cooperation between these communities in campaigns for equality, such as in the [[Stonewall Riots]].&lt;ref name=TransAdvocate1&gt;{{cite web|last1=Williams|first1=Christian|title=Interview With an Actual Stonewall Riot Veteran: The Ciswashing of Stonewall Must End!|url=http://www.transadvocate.com/interview-with-an-actual-stonewall-riot-veteran-the-ciswashing-of-stonewall-must-end_n_8750.htm|website=transadvocate.com|accessdate=27 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Prospect1&gt;{{cite web|last1=Talusan|first1=Meridith|title=45 Years After Stonewall, the LGBT Movement Has a Transphobia Problem|url=http://prospect.org/article/45-years-after-stonewall-lgbt-movement-has-transphobia-problem|website=prospect.org|publisher=Prospect|accessdate=27 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TheFrisky&gt;{{cite web|last1=Brink|first1=Rebecca Vipond|title=The Soapbox: On The Stonewall Rebellion's Trans History|url=http://www.thefrisky.com/2014-06-06/the-soapbox-on-the-stonewall-rebellions-trans-history/|website=thefrisky.com|publisher=Spin Entertainment|accessdate=27 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AutoStraddle&gt;{{cite web|author=Cara|title=Yet Another News Outlet Fails Queer History 101 by Erasing Trans* People from Stonewall|url=http://www.autostraddle.com/yet-another-news-outlet-fails-queer-history-101-by-erasing-trans-people-from-stonewall-154998/|website=autostraddle.com|accessdate=27 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Authors and observers, such as transgender author Jillian Todd Weiss, have written that "there are social and political forces that have created a split between gay/lesbian communities and bisexual/transgender communities, and these forces have consequences for civil rights and community inclusion. 'Biphobia' and 'transphobia' are a result of these social and political forces, not psychological forces causing irrational fears in aberrant individuals."&lt;ref name="weiss2004"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Weiss | first1 = JT | year = 2004 | title = GL vs BT The archaeology of biphobia and transphobia within U.S. gay and lesbian community | url = | journal = [[Journal of Bisexuality]] | volume = 3 | issue = | pages = 25–55 | doi=10.1300/j159v03n03_02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sears"&gt;Sears, J.T., and Williams, W.L. (1997). Overcoming Heterosexism and Homophobia. New York: Columbia University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":fone"&gt;Fone, B.R.S. (1998). ''The Columbia Anthology of Gay Literature: Readings from Western Antiquity to the Present Day.'' Columbia University Press, ISBN 9780231096706.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Gay and lesbian communities ====
[[File:Ticked Off Trannies protesters Shankbone 2010.jpg|thumb|Protesters outside the 2010 premiere of ''[[Ticked-Off Trannies With Knives]]'', written and directed by gay filmmaker [[Israel Luna]], objecting to what they considered to be transphobic portrayals in the film and its trailer, which referred to several notable real-life murders of transgender people before being taken down.&lt;ref name=Tribeca&gt;[http://blogs.reuters.com/fanfare/2010/04/25/ticked-off-trannies-and-detractors-take-on-tribeca/ "Ticked-Off Trannies," and detractors, take on Tribeca], Edith Honan, Reuters, April 25, 2010; accessed October 5, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Historian [[Joanne Meyerowitz]] documented transphobia within the [[gay rights movement]] in the mid 20th century in response to publicity surrounding the transition of [[Christine Jorgensen]]. Jorgensen, who made frequent [[Homophobia|homophobic]] remarks and insisted she was not connected to or identified with gay men, was a polarizing figure among activists:

&lt;blockquote&gt;In 1953, for example, ''ONE'' magazine published a debate among its readers as to whether gay men should denounce Jorgensen. In the opening salvo, the author Jeff Winters accused Jorgensen of a "sweeping disservice" to gay men. "As far as the public knows," Winters wrote, "you were merely another unhappy homosexual who decided to get drastic about it." For Winters, Jorgensen's story simply confirmed the false belief that all men attracted to other men must be basically feminine," which, he said, "they are not." Jorgensen's precedent, he thought, encouraged the "reasoning" that led "to legal limitations upon the homosexual, mandatory injections, psychiatric treatment – and worse." In the not-so-distant past, scientists had experimented with castrating gay men.&lt;ref name="mayerowitz2002"&gt;Meyerowitz, Joanne (2002). ''How Sex Changed: A History of Transsexuality in the United States.'' Harvard University Press ISBN 9780674009257.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Several prominent figures in [[second wave feminism]] have also been accused of transphobic attitudes, culminating in 1979 with the publication of ''[[The Transsexual Empire]]'' by [[Radical feminism|radical lesbian feminist]] [[Janice Raymond]], who popularized the term ''[[shemale]]'' as derogatory slur referring to [[trans women]] in 1994,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Raymond|first=J.|year=1994|title=The Transsexual Empire|publisher=Teachers College Press|edition=2nd}}&lt;/ref&gt; and her statements on transsexuality and transsexuals have been criticized by many in the [[LGBT]] and [[feminism|feminist]] communities as extremely [[transphobic]] and as constituting [[hate speech]].&lt;ref name="rose2004"&gt;Rose, Katrina C. (2004) "The Man Who Would be Janice Raymond." ''Transgender Tapestry'' 104, Winter 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="serano2007"&gt;[[Julia Serano]] (2007) ''Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Sexism and the Scapegoating of Femininity'', pp. 233-234&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="namaste2000"&gt;Namaste, Viviane K. (2000) ''Invisible Lives: The Erasure of Transsexual and Transgendered People'', pp. 33-34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hayes2003"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Hayes | first1 = Cressida J | year = 2003 | title = Feminist Solidarity after Queer Theory: The Case of Transgender | url = | journal = Signs | volume = 28 | issue = 4| pages = 1093–1120 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kay Brown of transhistory.net (website no longer online) compiled a long chronology of trans people being ejected from gay organizations since the 1970s. Her work was cited by Jillian Todd Weiss, who also wrote that "[t]here was a vigorous debate in the U.S. [[homophile]] movement of the 1950s [...] Some gay men and lesbians denounced those who felt themselves to be of the opposite sex, criticizing them for acting like "freaks," bringing disrepute to those gays and lesbians trying to live quietly within heterosexual society. Such attitudes were prevalent within the gay and lesbian community at the time."&lt;ref name="GLBTphobia"&gt;{{cite web |last=Weiss|first=Jillian Todd|title=GL vs. BT: The Archaeology of Biphobia and Transphobia Within the U.S. Gay and Lesbian Community|url=http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/glvsbt.htm|accessdate=7 July 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[trans men]] face rejection from lesbian communities they had been part of prior to transition. Journalist Louise Rafkin writes, "[t]here are those who are feeling curiously uncomfortable standing by as friends morph into men. Sometimes there is a generational flavor to this discomfort; many in the over-40 crowd feel particular unease", stating that this was "shaking the foundation of the lesbian-feminist world".&lt;ref name="rafkin"&gt;Rafkin, Louise (June 22, 2003) [http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2003/06/22/CM254728.DTL Straddling Sexes: Young lesbians transitioning into men are shaking the foundation of the lesbian-feminist world.] ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Trans men were part of the protest at the 2000 [[Michigan Womyn's Music Festival]], the first time the '[[womyn-born womyn]] only' policy has been used against trans males, women supporting the transsexual community and young gender-variant women.&lt;ref name="mantilla2000"&gt;Mantilla, Karla (October 1, 2000). Michigan: transgender controversy. ''[[Off Our Backs]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1970s, conflicts began to emerge due to different syntheses of lesbian, [[feminist]] and transgender political movements, particularly in the United States. San Francisco trans activist and entertainer Beth Elliott became the focus of debate over whether to include transgender lesbians in the movement, and she was eventually blacklisted by her own movement.&lt;ref name="rubin2003"&gt;Henry Rubin (2003). ''Self-made Men: Identity and Embodiment Among Transsexual Men.'' Vanderbilt 
University Press, ISBN 978-0-8265-1435-6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="nettick"&gt;Geri Nettick, Beth Elliot (1996). "Mirrors: Portrait of a Lesbian Transexual." Badboy Books ISBN 978-1-56333-435-1.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Bisexual communities and binarism====
One view is that the word ''bisexual'' is transphobic, as "bi" means "two" (thus implying a belief in the [[gender binary|binary view of gender]]). Some people, such as scholar Shiri Eisner, say that some make the claim that the term "erases nonbinary genders and sexes out of existence",&lt;ref name=Eisner1&gt;{{cite book|last1=Eisner|first1=Shiri|title=Bi: Notes for a Bisexual Revolution|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=CbJaZIosLwQC&amp;pg=PT27|date=2 July 2013|publisher=Seal Press, 2013|isbn=9781580054751|accessdate=28 December 2014|quote=Yet another way in which bisexuality has been recently imagined is as inherently binary. and therefore intrinsically transphobic. [...] As the argument classically goes, since he word bisexuality has bi (literally: two) in it, it inherently refers to a two-gender structure. This means it erases nonbinary genders and sexes out of existence.|pages=27}}&lt;/ref&gt; as many dictionaries define bisexuality as "[o]f, relating to, or having a sexual orientation to persons of either sex",&lt;ref name=Freedict1&gt;{{cite web|title=bisexual - definition of Bisexual by the Free Dictionary|url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/bisexual|website=thefreedictionary.com|publisher=The Free Dictionary|accessdate=28 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; "[s]exually attracted to both men and women"&lt;ref name=OxfordDicts&gt;{{cite web|title=bisexual: definition of bisexual in Oxford dictionary (British &amp; World English)|url=http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/bisexual|website=oxforddictionaries.com|publisher=Oxford Dictionaies|accessdate=28 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and other similar definitions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Merriam-Webster - Biseual Define|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/bisexual|website=merriam-webster.com|publisher=Merriam-Webster Online|accessdate=28 December 2014|quote=sexually attracted to both men and women}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Google&gt;{{cite web|title=Google Search: Bisexual definition|url=https://www.google.co.uk/webhp?complete=0&amp;gws_rd=cr&amp;ei=EUGgVLC5G4nsUvyfgKAL#complete=0&amp;q=bisexual+define|website=google.co.uk|quote=sexually attracted to both men and women.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, some bisexual individuals and scholars object to the notion that bisexuality means sexual attraction to only two genders, arguing that since ''bisexual'' is not simply about attraction to two sexes and encompasses gender as well, it can include attraction to more than one&lt;ref name="biresource.net"&gt;{{cite web |title =BRC Brochure 2010 |year =2010 |publisher =Bisexual Resource Council/[[Bisexual Resource Center]] |work =http://www.biresource.net/ |accessdate =July 8, 2013|url =http://www.biresource.net/BRC_Brochure_2010.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; or more than two genders&lt;ref name="bisexual.org"&gt;{{cite web|title=Doesn't identifying as bisexual reinforce a false gender binary?|publisher=[[American Institute of Bisexuality]]|date=2014|accessdate=May 27, 2014|url=http://bisexual.org/qna/doesnt-identifying-as-bisexual-reinforce-a-false-gender-binary/}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is occasionally defined as such.&lt;ref name="Eisner1"/&gt;  Others, such as the [[American Institute of Bisexuality]], say that the term "is an open and inclusive term for many kinds of people with same-sex and different-sex attractions"&lt;ref name="bisexual.org2"&gt;{{cite web|title=What is the difference between bisexual and terms like pansexual, polysexual, omnisexual, ambisexual, and fluid?|publisher=[[American Institute of Bisexuality]]|date=2014|accessdate=May 27, 2014|url=http://bisexual.org/qna/what-is-the-difference-between-bisexual-and-terms-like-pansexual-polysexual-omnisexual-ambisexual-and-fluid/}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that "the scientific classification ''bisexual'' only addresses the physical, biological sex of the people involved, not the gender-presentation."&lt;ref name="bisexual.org"/&gt;

In order to deal with issues related to transphobia and the gender binary, many individuals have taken on terms such as ''[[pansexual]]'', ''omnisexual'' (an alternative word for pansexual) or ''[[polysexual]]'' in place of the term ''bisexual''. The American Institute of Bisexuality argues that these terms "describe a person with homosexual and heterosexual attractions, and therefore people with these labels are also bisexual"&lt;ref name="bisexual.org2"/&gt; and that the notion that bisexuality is a reinforcement of a gender binary is a concept that is founded upon "anti-science, anti-Enlightenment philosophy that has ironically found a home within many Queer Studies departments at universities across the Anglophone world".&lt;ref name="bisexual.org"/&gt; Eisner agrees with this view, stating that "allegations of [[binarism]] have little to do with bisexuality's actual attributes or bisexual people's behavior in real life" and that the allegations are an attempt to separate the bisexual and transgender communities politically.&lt;ref name="Eisner1"/&gt;

==Consequences==
Transphobia creates significant stresses for transgender people which can lead them to feel shame, low [[self-esteem]], [[social alienation|alienation]] and inadequacy. Transgender youth often try to cope with the stress by running away from home, dropping out of school, using drugs or [[Self-mutilation|cutting]].&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Disparities in Psychiatric Care: Clinical and Cross-Cultural Perspectives|last = Ruiz MD|first = Pedro|publisher = Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins|year = 2009|isbn = 0781796393|location = |pages = 111}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although it is difficult to obtain accurate statistics, [[suicide]] rates among transgender people are thought to be especially high, because of how they are treated by their families and by society.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Suicide attempts reported by transgender and gender non-conforming adults vastly exceed the rate of the general U.S. population, 41 percent versus 4.6 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite techreport |first=Ann H. |last=Haas |author2=Philip Rodgers |title=Suicide Attempts Among Transgender and Gender Non-Conforming Adults |number= |institution=American Foundation for Suicide Prevention and Williams Institute, UCLA School of Law |year=2014 | url = http://williamsinstitute.law.ucla.edu/wp-content/uploads/AFSP-Williams-Suicide-Report-Final.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Transgender}}
{{div col|colwidth=20}}
* [[Cissexism]]
* [[Genderism]]
* [[Global Action for Trans Equality]]
* [[Hate crime]]
* [[Corrective rape]]
* [[Legal aspects of transsexualism]]
* [[LGBT people in prison]]
* [[LGBT rights opposition]]
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[List of unlawfully killed transgender people]]
* [[Non-binary discrimination]]
* [[Press for Change]] - UK law organisation for transgender people
* [[Transgender Day of Remembrance]]
* [[Transgender Europe]]
* [[Transgender Law Center]]
* [[Transgender youth]]
* [[Transmisogyny]]
* [[Yogyakarta Principles]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Citations broken|section|date=January 2013}}
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* [http://ec.europa.eu/justice/discrimination/files/trans_and_intersex_people_web3_en.pdf Thematic report on Discrimination against trans and intersex people on the grounds of sex, gender identity and gender expression], [[The European Commission]], 2012.

==External links==
* [http://www.gender.org/remember/ Remembering our Dead]
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/rcip//sbh.html Survivor bashing – bias motivated hate crimes]
* [http://new.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=2111&amp;Itemid=1837&amp;lang=en Translatina documentary (2010)]

{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Transgender|sidebar}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination against LGBT people]]
[[Category:Transphobia| ]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>