<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041001054043|6267879" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="67084" pageid="67084" ns="0" title="Transphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-01T05:55:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Category:Transgender-related topics]]
'''Transphobia''' (by analogy with [[homophobia]]) can entail any of an irrational fear, hatred of, discrimination against, or disapproval and refusal to accept [[transsexual]] and [[transgender]] people.

Transphobia can have consequences as severe as homophobia for the targeted person; also, many transpeople experience homophobia as well, from people who erroneously associate [[gender identity disorder]] as a form of [[homosexuality]] (see [[Homosexuality and Transgender]]).

Like other forms of behaviour such as homophobia, the discriminatory or intolerant behaviour can be direct and can take on the form of  [[harassment]], [[assault]], or [[murder]], or can be indirect, including refusing to take steps to ensure that transgendered people are treated in the same way a non-transgendered person would.&lt;!--horrible, can fix that later--&gt;

However, direct forms of transphobia can manifest itself in ways that are not related to violence - for example, there is the case of [[Tyra Hunter]] where she was involved in an automobile accident, and [[rescue worker]]s who were dispatched to the accident, on discovering her birth [[sex]], backed away and stopped the administering of treatment. 

&lt;!--something needs to come before here--&gt;
Transwomen are sometimes denied entry to women's spaces, and their reasons and policies for doing so are often felt as being transphobic, most notably the example of the [[Michigan Women's Music Festival]]. 

Transgender people depend largely on the medical profession to receive not only [[Hormone replacement therapy (trans)|hormone replacement therapy]] and [[sex reassignment surgery]], but also other vital care. Often it can be difficult for gender patients to receive proper health care and treatment, because medical [[gatekeeper]]s who are transphobic (or who misunderstand the nature of gender identity disorder) will refuse to administer necessary treatment; in at least one case that included the refusal to treat a transman for ovarian cancer, of which he subsequently died. 

Although the word transphobia is widely used, the phenomenon can be thought of, in some instances, as a [[paranoia]] more than a [[phobia]].

Two well-noted victims of transphobia were [[Brandon Teena]] and [[Gwen Araujo]].

==See also==
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Persecution of gays, lesbians, bisexuals, and the transgendered]]
* [[gay-bashing]]

==External links==
* [http://www.gender.org/remember/ Remembering our Dead]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>