<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131119181034|582403911" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12719721" pageid="12719721" ns="0" title="Native American mascot controversy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-20T01:44:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Vizquel96.jpg|thumb|right|180px|Former Cleveland Indians player [[Omar Vizquel]] wearing a baseball cap showing the image of the Cleveland Indians mascot, [[Chief Wahoo]]]]
The propriety of using '''Native American''' names and images in sports has been a topic of debate in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]] since the 1960s.
Numerous civil rights, religious, educational, athletic, and academic organizations consider the use of native names or symbols by non-native teams to be a harmful form of [[ethnic stereotyping]] which should be eliminated.&lt;ref name=APA2010&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apa.org/pi/oema/resources/communique/2010/08/native-themed-mascots.aspx|title=Legislative efforts to eliminate native-themed mascots, nicknames, and logos: Slow but steady progress post-APA resolution|publisher=American Psychological Association|date=August 2010|accessdate=01/23/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many individuals admire the heroism and romanticism evoked by the classic [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] image, but others view the use of [[mascot]]s as offensive, demeaning, or racist. Further complicating this issue is the varying levels of offensiveness with team names and mascots. For example, while the [[Washington Redskins]] use the slang term "[[Redskin (slang)|redskin]]" which is currently defined in dictionaries as derogatory,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/redskin|title=Definition of REDSKIN|publisher=Merriam-Webster}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Florida State Seminoles]]' use of the [[Seminole]] name is officially sanctioned by the [[Seminole Tribe of Florida]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wieberg|first=Steve|title=NCAA allowing Florida State to use its Seminole mascot|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/2005-08-23-fsu-mascot-approved_x.htm|publisher=USAToday|accessdate=July 14, 2013|date=August 23, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; The controversy has resulted in many institutions changing the names and images associated with their sports teams. Native American images and nicknames nevertheless remain fairly common in American sports, and may be seen in use by teams at all levels from elementary school to professional.

==History==
Americans have had a history of drawing inspiration from native peoples and "playing Indian" that dates back at least to the 18th century.&lt;ref name="Calloway"&gt;[[Colin G. Calloway|Calloway, Colin G.]] (2004) ''First Peoples'', 2nd Ed.&lt;/ref&gt; This practice led directly to the origins of many nicknames and mascots. Like the Boy Scouts (in particular, the [[Order of the Arrow]]) and many summer camps, university students in the late 19th and early 20th centuries adopted Indian names and symbols for their group identities, not from authentic sources but rather as Native American life was imagined by Euro-Americans.&lt;ref name="Spindel"&gt;{{cite book|last=Spindel|first=Carol|year=2002|title=Dancing at Halftime: Sports and the Controversy Over American Indian Mascots|location=New York|publisher=New York University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Professional team nicknames had similar origins. Founded as the Boston Red Stockings, the team became the [[History of the Boston Braves|Braves]] for the first time in 1912. Their owner, [[James Gaffney]], was a member of New York City's political machine, Tammany Hall, one of the societies originally formed to honor [[Tamanend]], a chief of the Delaware. The success of the Braves in the [[1914 World Series]] may have been the reason for the Cleveland team, which was looking for a new nickname, to become the [[Cleveland Indians#1894.E2.80.931935: Beginning to middle|Indians]] in 1915. The story that the team is named to honor [[Louis Sockalexis]], the first Native American to play major league baseball, cannot be verified from historical documents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=An Act of Honor or Exploitation? The Cleveland Indians' Use of the Louis Francis Sockalexis Story|first=Ellen|last=Staurowsky|journal=Sociology of Sports Journal|date=December 1998|volume=15(4)|page=299}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Redskins in Washington, DC was originally also the Boston Braves when formed in 1932, since it was the custom at the time to have the same team names when baseball and football shared the same stadium. Moving to the home of the Boston Red Sox, the name was changed to the Boston Redskins in 1933 before moving again to Washington. Thus the use of Native American names and imagery by this team began before the hiring of [[William Henry Dietz|Lone Star Dietz]] as coach in 1933.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sportsecyclopedia.com/nfl/wasbos/bosskins.html|title=The Boston Redskins|accessdate=04/24/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1940s the [[National Congress of American Indians]] (NCAI) created a campaign to eliminate negative stereotyping of Native American people in the media. Over time, the campaign began to focus on Indian names and mascots in sports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hylton|first=J Gordon|title=BEFORE THE REDSKINS WERE THE REDSKINS: THE USE OF NATIVE AMERICAN TEAM NAMES IN THE FORMATIVE ERA OF AMERICAN SPORTS, 1857-1933|publisher=North Dakota law review|date=01/01/2010|volume=86|page=879}}&lt;/ref&gt; The NCAI maintains that teams with mascots such as the [[Braves]] and the [[Redskins]] perpetuate negative stereotypes of Native American people, and demean their native traditions and rituals.&lt;ref name="NCAI"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncai.org/policy-issues/community-and-culture/anti-defamation-mascots|title=Anti-Defamation and Mascots|publisher=National Congress of American Indians|accessdate=12 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents of Native American mascots, however, believe that Native American mascots pay respect to these people and promote a better understanding of their cultures. Despite this issue gaining prominence during the [[civil rights movement]], it still continues today as many teams continue to possess mascots with controversial names and images.

The stereotyping of Native Americans must be understood in the context of history which includes conquest, forced relocation, and organized efforts to eradicate native cultures, such as the [[Native American boarding schools|boarding schools]] of the late 19th and early 20th centuries, which separated young Native Americans from their families in order to educate them as Euro-Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apa.org/pi/oema/resources/policy/mascots-justif.pdf|title=APA Resolution Justifications|year=2005|publisher=American Psychological Association|accessdate=01/21/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
As stated in an editorial by Carter Meland (Anishinaabe heritage) and David E. Wilkins (Lumbee) both professors of American Indian Studies at the University of Minnesota: "Since the first Europeans made landfall in North America, native peoples have suffered under a weltering array of stereotypes, misconceptions and caricatures. Whether portrayed as ''noble savages'', ''ignoble savages'', ''teary-eyed environmentalists'' or, most recently, simply as ''casino-rich'', native peoples find their efforts to be treated with a measure of respect and integrity undermined by images that flatten complex tribal, historical and personal experience into one-dimensional representations that tells us more about the depicters than about the depicted." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Star Tribune|title=Stereotypes in sports, chaos in federal policy|author=Carter Meland and David E. Wilkins|date=November 22, 2012|url=http://www.startribune.com/opinion/commentaries/180435801.html?refer=y|accessdate=01/30/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Arguments opposing the use of Native American mascots==
Opponents of Native American mascots assert that the mascots breed insensitivity and misunderstanding about native people. Opponents also highlight the seeming double standard for human beings as mascots where there are no mascots based on African Americans, or Asian Americans depicted in sports.&lt;ref name="AICS"&gt;[http://www.aics.org/mascot/mascot.html Mascots - Racism in Schools by State], American Indian Cultural Support&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of Notre Dame]] [[Notre Dame Fighting Irish|Fighting Irish]] and the [[University of Louisiana at Lafayette]]'s "[[Louisiana–Lafayette Ragin' Cajuns|Ragin' Cajuns]]" are sometimes cited as counterpoints to this argument.&lt;ref name=morgan&gt;{{cite news|last=Morgan|first=Ron|title=Red Scare: McCarthy had nothing on the PC police|url=http://corsicanadailysun.com/sports/x319982963/Morgan-Red-scare|accessdate=4 June 2013|newspaper=Corsicana Daily Sun|date=11 May 2013|quote=If the name Redskins is banned because it defames a particular group, then who’s next?  Doesn’t the term 'Fighting Irish' place a label on a particular nationality?  Those of French/Acadian extraction from South Louisiana should be insulted by the University of Louisiana Lafayette mascot, the 'Ragin’ Cajun.'}}&lt;/ref&gt;  These team names are exceptions in that they represent ethnic groups with an active stake in the organization, and the teams employ symbols that Euro-American cultures have historically used to represent themselves. The [[University of Notre Dame]] mascot, the [[Notre Dame Leprechaun|UND leprechaun]]&lt;ref name="ND"&gt;[http://und.cstv.com/trads/nd-m-fb-mas.html Notre Dame Fighting Irish - Traditions: The Leprechaun], University of Notre Dame Athletics&lt;/ref&gt; is a mythical being that represents the Irish, which is both an ethnic and a national group.&lt;ref name="fearson"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Fearon|first=James|title=Ethnic and Cultural Diversity by Country|journal=Journal of Economic Growth|year=2003|volume=8|issue=2|pages=195–222|url=http://telematica.politicas.unam.mx/biblioteca/archivos/040107017.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Ibid''., Ireland has an ethnic fractionalization score of 0.171, meaning that there is only a 17.1% chance that two randomly selected people in Ireland will be from different ethnic groups.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Cayenne (mascot)|University of Louisiana at Lafayette mascot]] is an anthropomorphic [[Cayenne (mascot)|cayenne pepper]], an ingredient frequently found in [[Cajun cuisine]]. Opponents also see this argument as a false equivalency because it ignores systemic inequality and serves to discount the Native American voice by saying that if one group isn't hurt by a particular portrayal, then no group has the right to be hurt, regardless of vastly different backgrounds, treatment, and social positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thesocietypages.org/socimages/2008/10/05/notre-dames-fighting-irish-mascot|title=Sociological Images by Gwen Sharp}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]] has called for an end to the use of Native American mascots, but only by non-native schools.&lt;ref name=USCCR&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.usccr.gov/press/archives/2001/041601st.htm |title=Statement of the United States Commission on Civil Rights on the use of Native American images and nicknames as sports symbols |accessdate=2007-10-21 |year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In cases where universities were founded to educate Native Americans, such mascots may not be examples of [[cultural appropriation]]. Examples include the [[Haskell Indian Nations Fighting Indians|Fighting Indians]] of the [[Haskell Indian Nations University]] and the [[University of North Carolina at Pembroke]], which continues to have a substantial number of native students, and close ties to the [[Lumbee]] tribe. Their nickname is the Braves, but the mascot is a [[red-tailed hawk]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uncp.edu/news/2005/braves_nickname.htm|title=NCAA: UNCP will keep the xBraves|date=August 9, 2005|accessdate=02/01/2013|publisher=University of North Carolina at Pembroke}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haskell.edu/athletics/quick_facts.php Haskell Indian Nations University Athletics] quick facts&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mcac-naia.org/members.php Midlands Collegiate Athletic Conference] Members&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civil rights===
The [[NAACP]] passed a resolution calling for the end of the use of Native American names, images, and mascots in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aistm.org/naacp_1999_resolution.htm|title=NAACP 1999 Resolution|accessdate=01/29/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, the [[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]] released an advisory opinion calling ''for an end to the use of Native American images and team names by non-Native schools.'' The opinion made the following points:
* The use of Native American images and nicknames in school is insensitive and should be avoided, and may violate anti-discrimination laws. 
*These references.. are particularly inappropriate and insensitive in light of the long history of forced assimilation that American Indian people have endured in this country.
*It is particularly disturbing that Native American references are still to be found in educational institutions ... where diverse groups of people come together to learn not only the "Three Rs," but also how to interact respectfully with people from different cultures.
*The use of stereotypical images may create a hostile  environment that may be intimidating to Indian students. American Indians have the lowest high school graduation rates in the nation and even lower college attendance and graduation rates. The perpetuation of harmful stereotypes may exacerbate these problems. 
*Schools that continue [these practices] claim that their use stimulates interest in Native American culture and honors Native Americans but have simply failed to listen to the Native groups, religious leaders, and civil rights organizations that oppose this behavior.
*Mascots, symbols and team names are not accurate representations of Native Americans. Even those that purport to be positive are romantic stereotypes that give a distorted view of the past. These false portrayals prevent non-Native Americans from understanding the true historical and cultural experiences of American Indians. Sadly, they also encourage biases and prejudices that have a negative effect on contemporary Indian people. These references may encourage interest in mythical "Indians" created by the dominant culture, but they block genuine understanding of contemporary Native people as fellow Americans.''&lt;ref name="usccr"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aistm.org/fr.usccr.htm |title=Statement of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights on the Use of Native American Images and Nicknames as Sports Symbols |publisher=The United States Commission on Civil Rights |date=April 13, 2001 |accessdate=2012-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2013 the State of Michigan Department of Civil Rights (MDCR) filed a complaint with the US Department of Education's Office of Civil Rights (OCR). MDCR's complaint asserts that new research clearly establishes that use of American Indian imagery negatively impacts student learning, creating an unequal learning environment in violation of Article VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964.&lt;ref name=MDCR&gt;{{cite web|title=Michigan Department of Civil Rights: Continued Use of American Indian Mascots Hurts Student Achievement|url=http://www.michigan.gov/mdcr/0,4613,7-138--294605--,00.html|publisher=State of Michigan|accessdate=23 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2013 the OCR dismissed the case on the basis that the legal standard required not only harm, but the intent to do harm, which was not established.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.freep.com/article/20130603/NEWS06/306030121/indian-mascot-ban-tossed-michigan|title=Feds toss Michigan complaint to ban Indian mascots for sports teams|date=June 3, 2013|newspaper=The Detroit Free Press|author=Lori Higgins|accessdate=06/05/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religious organizations===
In 1992, the [[Central Conference of American Rabbis]] issued a resolution calling for the end of sports teams names that promote racism, in particular the Atlanta Braves and the Washington Redskins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ccarnet.org/rabbis-speak/resolutions/1992/racism-1992/|title=Resolution Adopted by the CCAR: Racism|year=1992|accessdate=09/01/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, the [[United Methodist Church]] also passed a resolution condemning the use of Native American team names and sports mascots, which was highlighted in a meeting of the Black caucus of that organization in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.umc.org/site/apps/nlnet/content3.aspx?c=lwL4KnN1LtH&amp;b=5765541&amp;ct=3722449|title=Black caucus joins Native American mascot fight|date=April 4, 2007|accessdate=09/01/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;''A child once asked me why Indians were "mean." Where did he get that idea? By schools such as the University of Illinois "honoring" my ancestors?'' -- Rev. Alvin Deer (Kiowa/Creek), United Methodist Church &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archives.umc.org/umns/news_archive2001.asp?ptid=&amp;story={B523D699-F44C-4D4E-818E-1BC26CC53821}&amp;mid=3365|title=Mascot issue raises specters of racism, idolatry|date=3/9/2001|accessdate=10/19/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Education===
In a report on the status of Native American students, the [[National Education Association]] included the elimination of Indian mascots and sports team names as one of its recommendations.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=A Report on the Status of American Indians and Alaska Natives in Education|first=|author=Trujillo,Octaviana (Ph.D.)|author2=Alston, Denise (Ph.D.)|year=2005|publisher=National Education Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010 a law was passed in [[Wisconsin]] to eliminate race-based nicknames, logos and mascots in schools; but allowing retention if they have the permission of local Native American tribes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2010-10-06-kewaunee-school-mascot_N.htm | work=USA Today | first=Judy | last=Keen | title=Wis. law lets residents challenge race-based mascots | date=Oct. 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2013 a bill passed the Wisconsin assembly that would make it more difficult to remove Indian mascots by requiring the complainant to collect signatures of 10% of the school district's population and prove discrimination. Under the current law only one petitioner is needed, and the burden of proof is on the school.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.twincities.com/politics/ci_24316907/wisconsin-assembly-approves-bill-protecting-indian-mascots?source=rss|title=Wisconsin Assembly approves bill protecting Indian mascots|author=Todd Richmond|publisher=Associated Press|date=10/15/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of November, 2013, the bill has passed the state senate, and is likely to be signed by republican Gov. Scott Walker, over the objection of democrats and representative of Wisconsin’s Chippewa tribes’.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://wislawjournal.com/2013/11/17/opponents-urge-walker-to-veto-mascots-bill/|title=Opponents urge Walker to veto mascots bill|date=November 17, 2013|author=Associated Press|publisher=Wisconsin Law Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 17, 2012, the Oregon State Board of Education voted 5-1 to adopt a rule prohibiting Oregon public schools from using Native American names, symbols, or images as school mascots. Schools have until July 1, 2017 to comply. Fifteen schools using the nicknames Indians, Warriors, Braves and Chieftains were affected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ode.state.or.us/search/page/?id=3575|title=State Board of Education Bans Use of Native American Mascots|publisher=Oregon State Department of Education|accessdate=02/10/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However Native American response was not unanimous; out of nine tribes, two voiced opposition to the statewide ban on the basis of tribal sovereignty. Leaders said that there might have been an opportunity for developing an educational program for all students to learn about true native culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/politics/index.ssf/2012/05/two_tribes_call_state_board_of.html|newspaper=The Oregonian|title=Two tribes call state's Native American mascot ban disappointing|date=May 22, 2012|first=Ryan|last=Kost|accessdate=02/24/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of March, 2013, the Oregon legislature is considering bills that would modify the Board of Education's decision. One would allow for retention of a mascot or nickname with tribal approval, the other would remove the financial penalty for non-compliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.katu.com/politics/Lawmakers-could-change-Native-American-mascot-ban-200745601.html|title=Lawmakers could change Native American mascot ban|publisher=Associated Press|date=Mar 30, 2013|accessdate=04/19/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 26, 2012 the Washington State Board of Education (WSBE) passed a resolution calling for the end of Native American mascots in state schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/headlines/2012/09/washington-state-wants-schools-to-ban-native-american-mascots/|title=Washington State Wants Schools to Ban Native American Mascots|author=Abby Ellin|date=Sep 29, 2012|publisher=ABC News|accessdate=09/17/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sbe.wa.gov/documents/2012.09.26%20Native%20American%20Mascots%20Resolution.pdf|title=2012 Native American Mascot Resolution|accessdate=09/17/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Seattle Human Rights Commission passed a resolution supporting the WSBE in November, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattle.gov/HumanRights/Documents/SHRC_Resolution12-04NativeMascots.pdf|title=Resolution #12-4: Elimination of Native American Mascots|accessdate=09/17/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{see also|Issaquah_High_School}}

There has been backlash, however. In response to the Tennessee Commission of Indian affairs seeking a similar ban though the Tennessee Human Rights Commission, the legislature passed a law allowing only elected officials (themselves) to take any action banning school teams using American Indian names and symbols.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesnews.net/article/3758873/tennessee-senate-approves-measure-that-would-protect-indian-mascots|title=Tennessee Senate approves measure that would protect Indian mascots|date=May 10, 2007|author=Hank Hayes}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social sciences===
The harm done by the use of Native American mascots particularly in an academic context was stated by the Society of Indian Psychologists in 1999:
&lt;blockquote&gt;''Stereotypical and historically inaccurate images of Indians in general interfere with learning about them by creating, supporting and maintaining oversimplified and inaccurate views of indigenous peoples and their cultures. When stereotypical representations are taken as factual information, they contribute to the development of cultural biases and prejudices, (clearly a contradiction to the educational mission of the University.) In the same vein, we believe that continuation of the use of Indians as symbols and mascots is incongruous with the philosophy espoused by many Americans as promoting inclusivity and diversity.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aiansip.org/uploads/SIP_Indian_Mascot_Position_Statement.pdf|title=Society of Indian Psychologists|date=January 27, 1999|accessdate=08/19/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In 2005, the [[American Psychological Association]] issued a resolution "Recommending the Immediate Retirement of American Indian Mascots, Symbols, Images, and Personalities by Schools, Colleges, Universities, Athletic Teams, and Organizations" due to the harm done by creating a hostile environment, the negative impact on the self-esteem of American Indian children, and is discrimination that may violate civil rights. It also impacts non-natives by reinforcing mainstream stereotypes, preventing learning about Native American culture. Stereotyping is disrespectful of the beliefs, traditions and values of Native Americans.&lt;ref name=APA&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apa.org/pi/oema/resources/indian-mascots.aspx|title=Summary of the Resolution Recommending Retirement of American Indian Mascots|publisher=American Psychological Association|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar resolutions have been adopted by the [[American Sociological Association]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asanet.org/about/Council_Statements/use_of_native_american_nicknames_logos_and_mascots.cfm|title=Statement by the Council of the American Sociological Association on Discontinuing the Use of Native American Nicknames, Logos and Mascots in Sport|publisher=American Sociological Association|date=March 6, 2007|accessdate=01/23/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[American Counseling Association]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.counseling.org/docs/resolutions/resolutions-2001-present.pdf?sfvrsn=2|publisher=American Counseling Association|title=Opposition to Use of Stereotypical Native American Images as Sports Symbols and Mascots|year=2001|accessdate=01/23/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Social science research gives weight to the perceptions of those directly affected. In particular studies support the view that sports mascots and images are not trivial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Fryberg |first=Stephanie A.|title=Of Warrior Chiefs and Indian Princesses: The Psychological Consequences of American Indian Mascots|work=Basic and applied social psychology|date=09/2008|volume=30(3)|page=208}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stereotyping directly effects academic performance and self-esteem, which contribute to all of the other issues faced by Native Americans, including suicide, unemployment, and poverty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/07/opinion/sunday/intelligence-and-the-stereotype-threat.html|title=It’s Not Me, It’s You|first=ANNIE|last=MURPHY PAUL|date=October 6, 2012|newspaper=The New York Times|accessdate=02/11/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Euro-Americans exposed to mascots are more likely to believe not only that stereotypes are true, but that Native Americans have no identity beyond these stereotypes.&lt;ref name="bias"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Chaney|first=John| title=Do American Indian Mascots = American Indian People? Examining Implicit Bias towards American Indian People and American Indian Mascots|work=American Indian and Alaska native mental health research |date=01/01/2011|volume=18(1)|page=42}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research also demonstrates the harm done to society by stereotyping of any kind. Two studies examined the effect of exposure to an American Indian sports mascot on the tendency to endorse stereotypes of a different minority group. A study was first done at the University of Illinois, and then replicated at The College of New Jersey with the same results. Students were given a paragraph to read about Chief Illiniwek adapted from the University of Illinois' official website; while the control group was given a description of an arts center. In both studies the students exposed to the sports mascot were more likely to express stereotypical views of Asian-Americans. Although Chief Illiniwek was described only in terms of positive characteristics (as a respectful symbol, not a mascot), the stereotyping of Asian-Americans included negative characteristics, such as being "socially inept". This was indicative of a spreading effect; exposure to any stereotypes increased the likelihood of stereotypical thinking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kim-Prieto|first=Chu|title=Effect of Exposure to an American Indian Mascot on the Tendency to Stereotype a Different Minority Group|journal=Journal of Applied Social Psychology|date=03/2010|volume=40|number=3|page=534}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/the-hidden-brain/201003/native-american-imagery-sports-mascots-new-problem|work=Psychology Today|title=Native American imagery as sports mascots: A new problem|date=March 25, 2010|first=Shankar|last=Vedantam|accessdate=02/05/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{further|Stereotype|Stereotypes of Native Americans in North America}}

==Trend toward the elimination of mascots==

===Colleges and universities===
[[Image:Ticket Washington vs Stanford 1930 side1.jpg|right|thumb|250px|1930 Football ticket stub depicting the former Stanford Indian mascot]]
Some college teams voluntarily changed their names and mascots. [[Stanford University]] had "The Stanford Indian" as its mascot from 1930 to 1972. Today "[[Stanford Cardinal]]" honors the university athletic team color. The mascot of the [[Stanford Band]] is the "[[Stanford Tree]]." Another early change was the "[[Saltine Warrior#Mascot|Saltine Warrior]]" that represented [[Syracuse University]] from 1931 until 1978. After a brief attempt to use a Roman warrior, the mascot became Otto the Orange for the school color.

[[Marquette University]] changed their team name from the Warriors to the Golden Eagles in 1994.  The school’s president stated:"We live in a different era than when the Warriors nickname was selected in 1954. The perspective of time has shown us that our actions, intended or not, can offend others. We must not knowingly act in a way that others will believe, based on their experience, to be an attack on their dignity as fellow human beings."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gomarquette.com/genrel/051105aaa.html|title=Trustees announce new nickname selection process|date=May 11, 2005|publisher=Marquette University|accessdate=01/20/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 1994, [[St. John's University (New York)]] changed the name of its athletic teams from the Redmen to the Red Storm after the university was pressured by American Indian groups who considered Redmen a slur.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1998/07/09/nyregion/use-of-indians-as-mascots-to-be-subject-of-an-inquiry.html|title=Use of Indians As Mascots To Be Subject Of an Inquiry|newspaper=The New York Times|date=July 9, 1998|accessdate=02/08/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Miami University]] began discussion regarding the propriety of the Redskins name and images in 1972,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.miami.muohio.edu/about-miami/history-and-traditions/miami-tribe-relations/mascot-controversy/index.html|title=Mascot Controversy|accessdate=02/05/2013|publisher=Miami University}}&lt;/ref&gt; and changed its team nickname to [[Miami Redhawks|Redhawks]] in 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.miami.muohio.edu/about-miami/diversity/miami-tribe-relations/mascot-story/index.html|title=Mascot Story|accessdate=02/05/2013|publisher=Miami University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 2002, The Strategic Planning Committee of [[Stonehill College]] determined that the then-current mascot, the chieftain, was disrespectful to American Indians and decided that it would be changed. After discussion, the mascot was changed to the Skyhawk in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stonehill.edu/x12523.xml|title=Why a Skyhawk?|accessdate=02/05/2013|publisher=Stonehill College}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Jim Seavey, associate director of athletics stated: ''Twelve years ago, the college discarded the logo that depicted the Indian with the headdress and feathers and stuff. We really did not have anything to represent our identity that we were comfortable with. We felt . . . that it wasn't appropriate to have a physical representation of a Native American as our mascot," &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2005/02/27/digging_for_new_name_sends_stonehill_to_web/|title=Digging for new name sends Stonehill to Web|first=Emily|last=Sweeney|date=February 27, 2005|newspaper=The Boston Globe|accessdate=01/20/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, teams that are not directly affected by this controversy have issued their opinions. The [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lssaa.wisc.edu/aisas/policy07.html|title=University Of Wisconsin Athletic Department Policy On Native American Logos And Names|accessdate=02/05/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[University of Iowa]] have both refused to schedule non-conference games against schools with Native American mascots. The University of Iowa's own nickname, "Hawkeyes", has Native American origins (Iowa is the "[[Hawkeye State]]"), although the team uses a [[hawk]] as its symbol rather than an Indian. The [[University of Oregon]], following the example set by ''[[The Oregonian]]'' newspaper, declined to refer to the [[University of Illinois]] team as the "Illini" in a basketball game in 2005. The [[Central Michigan University]] nickname, the [[Central Michigan Chippewas|Chippewas]], was originally placed on the “hostile or abusive” list but was removed when the [[Saginaw Chippewa Tribal Nation]] of Michigan gave its support to the nickname.

[[Seattle University]] changed the nickname of their mascot from Chieftains to [[Seattle Redhawks|Redhawks]] in 2000.

In 2012, the [[University of California, Berkeley]] called for the student-run [[University of California Marching Band]] to discontinue performances of "[[California Indian Song]]" after complaints from alumni.  Currently, the Cal Band is attempting to rename the song and rewrite its lyrics.

====National Collegiate Athletic Association====
The [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] (NCAA), the ruling authority on college athletics, distributed a “self evaluation” to 31 colleges in 2005, for teams to examine the use of potentially offensive imagery with their mascot choice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fs.ncaa.org/Docs/NCAANewsArchive/2005/Association-wide/mascot%2Bmatter%2Bfits%2Binto%2Bproper-environment%2Bdiscussion%2B-%2B3-14-05%2Bncaa%2Bnews.html|title=Mascot matter fits into proper-environment discussion|date=Mar 14, 2005|first=Michelle|last=Brutlag Hosick|publisher=The NCAA News|accessdate=02/05/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently 19 teams were cited as having potentially "hostile or abusive" names, mascots, or images, that would be banned from displaying them during post-season play, and prohibited from hosting tournaments.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://fs.ncaa.org/Docs/NCAANewsArchive/2005/Editorial/ncaa%2Bcorrectly%2Bpositioned%2Bas%2Ba%2Bcatalyst%2Bfor%2Bsocial%2Bchange%2B-%2B10-24-05%2Bncaa%2Bnews.html
| title=NCAA correctly positioned as a catalyst for social change
| date=Oct 24, 2005
| first=Myles
| last=Brand 
| publisher=National Collegiate Athletic Association
| accessdate=01/16/2013
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Since then, all of the colleges previously using the nickname ''Indians'' changed them; [[Arkansas State University]] to [[Red Wolves]], [[Indiana University of Pennsylvania]] to Crimson Hawks, [[McMurry University]] to [[War Hawks]], [[Midwestern State University]] to Mustangs, [[Newberry College]] to Wolves, [[University of Louisiana at Monroe]] to Warhawks, and [[Catawba College]] to Catawba Indians with approval of that tribe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=2463164|title=NCAA says Catawba College can use Indians nickname|date=May 30, 2006|accessdate=02/01/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[College of William and Mary]] (W&amp;M) had previously changed from "Indians" to The Tribe, but was cited due to two feathers in its logo, which were removed. After a brief period of having the frog-like character [[Colonel Ebirt]] as its unofficial mascot, W&amp;M selected the [[Griffin (mascot)|Griffin]] in 2010. Both [[Alcorn State University]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://meacswacsports.blogspot.com/2011/04/bravehawk-chosen-as-new-mascot-at.html|date=April 25, 2011|title=Bravehawk chosen as new mascot at Alcorn State|accessdate=02/01/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Bradley University]] kept the nickname Braves but change their mascots, while the [[Chowan University]] Braves became the Hawks. The [[Carthage College]] Redmen became the Red Men, and the [[Southeastern Oklahoma State University]] Savages changed to Savage Storm. The [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]] Fighting Illini kept the nickname as referring to the state, not Native Americans, but officially stopped using the [[Chief Illiniwek]] image and mascot in 2007, although an attachment remains among many students and alumni;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.news-gazette.com/news/business/entrepreneurs/2012-04-21/former-chiefs-create-new-logo.html|title=Former Chiefs create new logo|date=04/21/2012|first=Julie|last=Wurth|newspaper=News-Gazette|accessdate=02/10/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://councilofchiefs.org/|title=The Tradition Continues|accessdate=03/15/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.news-gazette.com/news/local/2013-03-13/ui-student-vote-favors-chief-illiniwek.html|title=UI student vote favors Chief Illiniwek|date=03/13/2013|author=Christine Des Garennes|newspaper=News-Gazette|accessdate=04/30/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://chicago.cbslocal.com/2013/05/07/wisch-return-of-chief-illiniwek-proposed-and-ignored/|title=Wisch: Return Of Chief Illiniwek Proposed – And Ignored?|date=May 7, 2013|author=Dave Wischnowsky|accessdate=10/18/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; but not all.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ucimc.org/content/students-confront-chancellorkick-new-mascot-now-weekend|title=Students Confront Chancellor/Kick Off New Mascot Now! Weekend|publisher=Urbana-Champaign Independent Media Center|author=Brian Dolinar|date=October 22, 2010|accessdate=11/18/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The "Honor the Chief Society" filed an application with the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office in 2009 to register the Chief Illiniwek symbol, which the university opposed. In October, 2013 an agreement was reached that will allow limited private use of the name as long as accompanied by a disclaimer stating that the university is not involved in such use. A new chief cannot be named, and the university retains control of the name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2013-10-23/news/chi-u-of-i-works-out-deal-on-use-of-chief-illiniwek-20131023_1_chief-society-roger-huddleston-the-news-gazette|title=U. of I. works out deal on use of Chief Illiniwek|date=October 23, 2013|author=Jodi S. Cohen|newspaper=The Chicago Tribune|accessdate=11/17/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of North Dakota]] initially challenged the NCAA policy in court, but settled in 2007 when it was given three years to obtain consent from the Sioux tribes in the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ag.state.nd.us/ncaa/ncaa.htm|title=UND v. NCAA Lawsuit|publisher=North Dakota Attorney General|accessdate=02/24/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; When one tribe refused permission,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.grandforksherald.com/event/article/id/199066/|date=April 4, 2011|title=Plains tribes still oppose nicknames, logos|first=Chuck|last=Haga|newspaper=Grand Forks Herald|accessdate=02/24/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; the state Board of Higher Education proceeded with plans to eliminate the Fighting Sioux name and logo. In 2011 the State Legislature voted that the university should retain the name but in a 2012 referendum the voters decided to proceed with the change, which has been completed but no alternative nickname or logo has been selected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncaa.com/news/ncaa/2011-03-12/und-nickname-still-point-discussion|publisher=NCAA|title=UND nickname still point of discussion|author=The Associated Press|date=March 12, 2011|accessdate=02/03/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/college-sports/story/_/id/8045554/north-dakota-residents-vote-let-school-scrap-fighting-sioux-nickname|publisher=ESPN|title=UND OK to drop Fighting Sioux name|date=June 14, 2012|author=Associated Press|accessdate=02/03/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The NCAA has agreed to allow some of the logos to remain in the sports stadiums, while removing the larger and more obvious ones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/sports/2012/09/26/ncaa-agreement-permits-some-und-fighting-sioux-logos-to-remain/|title=Fighting Sioux Remains|date=09/26/2012|accessdate=10/18/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Four additional colleges originally on the "hostile and abusive" list: [[Central Michigan University]] (Chippewas),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2005/09/06/mascot|title=
Two More Universities Off NCAA's Mascot List|date=September 6, 2005|author=Doug Lederman|publisher=Inside Higher Ed|accessdate=11/04/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Florida State University]] (Seminoles), [[Mississippi College]] (Choctaws)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://diverseeducation.com/article/5547/#|title=NCAA: Mississippi College Can Keep Choctaws Nickname|date=February 23, 2006|author=Associated Press|accessdate=11/04/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[University of Utah]] ([[Utah Utes|Utes]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=2149907|title=NCAA takes Utah off banned mascots list|date=September 3, 2005|author=Associated Press|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=11/04/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; were granted waivers to retain their nicknames after gaining support from those respective tribes.

===High schools===
Many [[Secondary education in the United States|high schools]] across the country have encountered the same scenario, some making voluntary changes while others resisting. Twenty-eight high schools in 18 states have dropped the redskins name during the past 25 years as a result of a combination of state legal action, protests from Native American groups, or voluntarily. However, there remain 62 high schools in the United States that continue to use the redskins name, three of which have a majority of Native American students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://cnsmaryland.org/interactives/other-redskins/#aboutproject|title=The Other Redskins|publisher=Capitol News Service|accessdate=06/16/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Frontier Regional School]], in [[Deerfield, Massachusetts|Deerfield]], [[Massachusetts|MA]] removed its [[Redskin (slang)|Redskin]] mascot in 2000. The school now goes by the moniker of the [[Red-tailed hawk|Redhawks]].  Mountain Empire High School in [[Pine Valley, CA]] changed their mascot from the Redskins to the Red Hawks in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Vargas |first=Nicole |url=http://www.utsandiego.com/uniontrib/20050927/news_1s27p-preptu.html |title=Tradition meets political correctness |newspaper=The San Diego Union-Tribune |date=2005-09-27 |accessdate=2012-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Turners Falls High School of Turners Falls, MA changed its fight song, known as the tomahawk chop, but did not change its mascot. [[Blacksburg High School]] in Blacksburg, VA changed their mascot from the Indians to the Bruins, and the corresponding middle school mascot of the Braves was changed to the Titans. On the other hand, [[Union Public Schools|Union High School]] in [[Tulsa, Oklahoma]], a high-profile high school athletic program,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tulsaworld.com/sports/article.aspx?subjectid=227&amp;articleid=20090706_298_0_Unionf830726 "Sports Illustrated names Tulsa's Union on list of top athletic programs"], ''[[Tulsa World]]'', July 6, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; has consistently opposed protests and proposed legislation intended to change its "Redskins" nickname.&lt;ref&gt;Randy Krehbiel, [http://www.tulsaworld.com/news/article.aspx?subjectid=11&amp;articleid=20090131_16_A4_TheTul294912&amp;archive=yes "Indian Coalition Backs Nickname Bill: The Bill Would Bar Public Schools From Using the Names 'Redskins' or 'Savages.' "], ''[[Tulsa World]]'', January 31, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Savannah High School (Missouri)]] has been criticized for their mascot, Savannah Savages.

The Cooperstown Central School Board of Education (NY) voted 6-1 on March 6, 2013 to remove the Redskins mascot from its interscholastic athletic, extracurricular and academic programs. The move was prompted by a vote by the student body, asking that the mascot be changed. The Oneida Indian Nation was so moved by the actions of the Cooperstown students, that a letter by Oneida Nation Representative Ray Halbritter was written to the students, commending their decision and offering to make a contribution to help offset the cost of changing mascots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oneidaindiannation.com/pressroom/latestnews/Oneida-Indian-Nation-Congratulates-Cooperstown-Central-School-Board-for-Voting-to-Remove-Redskins-Mascot-196067191.html|title=Oneida Indian Nation Congratulates Cooperstown Central School Board for Voting to Remove Redskins Mascot|date=March 7, 2013|accessdate=03/14/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2013 administrators of a high school in Driggs, Idaho announced that it will drop its longtime "Redskins" nickname, logo and mascot to show respect for Native Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.adn.com/2013/06/12/2936829/idaho-high-school-drops-redskins.html|title=Idaho high school drops Redskins logo, mascot|date=June 12, 2013|newspaper=The Anchorage Daily News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 24, 2013 school board members of the Port Townsend High School in Port Townsend, Washington announced that it will drop its longtime "Redskins" since 1926 of the nickname, logo and mascot to show respect for the Native Americans.

===Professional teams===
The [[Golden State Warriors]] retain the name but eliminated Native American imagery in 1971.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nba.com/history/uniforms_warriors.html|title=Going Retro: Golden State Warriors|publisher=NBA|accessdate=02/12/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since that time, their logos have emphasized the state of California, with their current primary logo depicting the [[Eastern span replacement of the San Francisco–Oakland Bay Bridge|new eastern span]] of the [[San Francisco–Oakland Bay Bridge]]. The warrior depicted on secondary logos of the team is a generic, lightning-wielding figure. The [[Edmonton Eskimos]] are also exceptional, given that their only stereotypical element appears to be the name of one of their mascots, Nanook, a polar bear.
 
Some teams have made limited changes in recent years. In 1989 the Kansas City Chiefs switched from [[Warpaint (mascot)|Warpaint]], a Pinto horse ridden by a man in a feathered headdress, to their current mascot [[K. C. Wolf]]. In 2009 the horse returned, but ridden by a cheerleader. The NHL's [[Chicago Blackhawks]] use an [[NHL mascots#Tommyhawk|anthropomorphic hawk]] as their mascot character although a Native American's profile appears on their jerseys and the team was named in honor of the [[Frederic McLaughlin|team's founder]]'s [[U.S. 86th Infantry Division|military unit]], which was named the "Blackhawk Division" after [[Black Hawk (chief)|Black Hawk]], a Native American chief.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://chicago.cbslocal.com/2013/06/17/baffoe-should-the-blackhawks-ditch-their-indian-head-logo/|title=Should The Blackhawks Ditch Their Indian Head Logo?|author=Tim Baffoe|date=06/17/2013|publisher=CBS Chicago}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However the other professional teams continue to use Native American names and mascots as they always have.

The [[Atlanta Braves]] remain the home of the tomahawk chop (although it began at FSU).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://atlanta.braves.mlb.com/atl/fan_forum/1000chops_landing.jsp|title=Fan of 1,000 Chops|accessdate=02/12/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the mascot [[Chief Noc-A-Homa]] has been replaced.

The [[Cleveland Indians#Nickname and logo controversy|Cleveland Indians]] have replaced [[Chief Wahoo]] with a block letter "C" or script "I" in many situations, most recently with their caps and batting helmets for the 2013 season. But Chief Wahoo remains on the left sleeves of their jerseys.&lt;ref name="wahoo"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/blog/sweetspot/post/_/id/10856/cap-week-time-to-retire-chief-wahoo|title=Time to retire Chief Wahoo|date=May 13, 2011|first=Stephanie|last=Liscio|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=02/11/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Perhaps this is a limited response to protests by Native Americans and others, which have gone on for more than twenty years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cleveland.com/metro/index.ssf/2012/04/native_americans_to_mark_cleve.html|title=Native Americans to mark Cleveland Indians 1st games with annual protest of Chief Wahoo logo|first=Michael|last=Sangiacomo|newspaper=The Plain Dealer|date=April 1, 2012|accessdate=02/11/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1973, an Indians fan, [[John Adams (drummer)|John Adams]], has played a bass drum during games, usually doing a Hollywood tom-tom beat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20110909&amp;content_id=24436870&amp;vkey=news_cle&amp;c_id=cle|title=Adams continues to beat drum for Tribe: Indians superfan has missed just 38 games in past 38 years|author=Zack Meisel|publisher=MLB.com|date=09/09/2011|accessdate=07/09/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The appropriateness of the [[Washington Redskins]] name and logo, which is a picture of a Native American, has been debated since it was officially registered in 1967. With "redskin" considered by many Native Americans to be a racial slur as offensive to them as "the n-word" is to [[African Americans]], there have been a few instances of the media refusing to use the name in sports reporting. ''Kansas City Star'' policy on Washington's NFL team's name as stated by the editor: "I see no compelling reason for any publisher to reprint an egregiously offensive term as a casual matter of course."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Kansas City Star|title=Star policy on Washington NFL team's name|first=Derek|last=Donovan|date=September 24, 2012|url=http://adastrum.kansascity.com/?q=node/1534#storylink=cpy|accessdate=01/30/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Journal Star'' in Lincoln, Nebraska and the ''Portland Press Herald'' in Maine took the same position.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nebraska newspaper will no longer call D.C. football team 'Redskins'|first=Kathleen|last=Rutledge|newspaper=Lincoln Journal Star|date=01/28/03|url=http://www.freedomforum.org/templates/document.asp?documentID=17506|accessdate=01/23/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team's unofficial mascot is Zema Williams ([[Chief Zee]]), an African-American man who began attending games in 1978 wearing an Indian costume including feathered headdress and rubber tomahawk. Other fans attend in costume, and are also celebrated by the team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/dc-sports-bog/wp/2012/12/11/redskins-fan-gives-himself-an-indian-name-gets-deangelo-halls-helmet/|title=Redskins fan gives himself an Indian name, gets DeAngelo Hall’s helmet|first=Sarah|last=Kogod|date=December 11, 2012|newspaper=The Wasington Post|accessdate=01/23/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The name debate heated up in 1992, when Washington [[Super Bowl XXVI|made it to the Super Bowl]] against the [[Buffalo Bills]]. The game was held in Minnesota, which has the nation’s largest Native American population. Prior to the game, more than 2,000 Native Americans stood outside the stadium and protested with signs that read “we are not mascots” and “promote sports not racism.” The American Indian Movement along with the National Congress of American Indians sponsored the protest. Shortly afterwards, the court case to cancel the trademarks used by the team began.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=NFL's Washington needs to rethink offensive mascot name|date=6 November 2012|first=Sean|last=Corrado|url=http://pittnews.com/index.php/sports/70309-corrado-nfl-s-washington-needs-to-rethink-offensive-mascot-name|newspaper=The Pitt News|publisher=University of Pittsburg}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team continues to receive attention as the more egregious example.&lt;ref name="symposium"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesdispatch.com/sports/redskins-takes-a-beating-at-symposium-on-mascots/article_c83684e2-716c-11e2-9b8f-0019bb30f31a.html|title='Redskins' takes a beating at symposium on mascots|date=02/07/2013|newspaper=The Richmond Times-Dispatch|accessdate=02/08/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; A bill was introduced in the US House of Representatives on March 20, 2013 by [[Eni Faleomavaega|Eni F.H. Faleomavaega]], Delegate from [[American Samoa]], and co-sponsoed by 19 others to amend the Trademark Act of 1946 to void any trademarks that disparage Native American Persons or Peoples, such as ''redskins''. Ten members of congress also sent a letter to the NFL commissioner, all of the team owners including Dan Snyder, and [[Frederick W. Smith|Fred Smith]], CEO of FedEx, a primary sponsor of the team; requesting that the name be changed due to the many Native American organizations that oppose the continued use of the name, and in order to fulfill the NFL's own policy regarding diversity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.house.gov/list/press/as00_faleomavaega/eniredskins.html|title=MEMBERS OF CONGRESS URGE SNYDER AND THE NATIONAL FOOTBALL LEAGUE TO CHANGE THE WASHINGTON TEAM’S NAME|accessdate=10/30/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A co-sponsor, Delegate Eleanor Holmes Norton (D - DC), stated she supports the local team but not the name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nationalreview.com/corner/343602/house-dems-introduce-bill-ban-redskins-trademark-andrew-johnson|newspaper=The National Review|title=House Dems Introduce Bill to Ban ‘Redskins’ Trademark|first=Andrew|last=Johnson|date=March 21, 2013|accessdate=March 21, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Council of the District of Columbia]] passed a resolution November 5, 2013 stating its position that the name should be changed. Since the team plays in Maryland and practices in Virginia, it has no legal force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/dc-politics/dc-council-calls-on-washington-redskins-to-ditch-racist-and-derogatory-name/2013/11/05/17cbbd66-4646-11e3-bf0c-cebf37c6f484_story.html|title=D.C. Council calls on Washington Redskins to ditch ‘racist and derogatory’ name|author1=Mike DeBonis|author2=Aaron C. Davis|date=November 5, 2013|newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Varying degrees of offensiveness===
To further complicate this issue, many feel that there are varying levels of offensiveness with team names and mascots. The nature and degree of stereotyping varies depending upon the name of the team, the logo, the mascot, and the behavior of fans. The greatest offense is taken when the logo and mascot are caricatures viewed as insulting, such as the [[Cleveland Indians]]' [[Chief Wahoo]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catholicculture.org/news/features/index.cfm?recnum=5437|title=Coalition Of Religious Investors Fight Baseball Team Logo|date=July 10, 1997|accessdate=01/18/2013|publisher=Catholic Culture}}&lt;/ref&gt; the name of the team is often regarded as a racial slur, such as [[redskin (slang)|redskins]]; or the behavior of the mascot or fans is based upon popular images of Indians which trivialize authentic native cultures; such as the tomahawk chop.

==Argument supporting the use of Native American mascots==
[[Image:FedExField - Redskins Jaguars pregame field.jpg|thumb|right|210px|The Washington Redskins logo at FedEx Field, in Maryland]]
Some individuals who support the use of Native American mascots state that they are meant to be respectful, and to pay homage to Native American people.  Many have made the argument that Native American mascots focus on bravery, courage and fighting skills rather than anything derogatory. Karl Swanson, vice-president of the Washington Redskins professional football team, declared in the magazine ''[[Sports Illustrated]]'' that his team's name "symbolizes courage, dignity, and leadership," and that the "Redskins symbolize the greatness and strength of a grand people."&lt;ref name="bar"&gt;Emert, Phyllis Raybin (2003). "[http://www.njsbf.org/images/content/1/1/11134/Respect%20Winter%202003.pdf Native American Mascots: Racial Slur or Cherished Tradition?]" ''Respect'' (newsletter), New Jersey State Bar Foundation, 2:2 (Winter 2003).&lt;/ref&gt;

Anil Adyanthaya, an attorney, wrote on June 5, 2005, "The use of Aztec or Seminole as a nickname by itself would not appear to be racist, as such names refer to a particular civilization rather than an entire race of people. In this way, they are no different from other school nicknames such as Trojans and Spartans (like Aztecs, ancient peoples) or [[Notre Dame Fighting Irish|Fighting Irish]] and [[Lebanon Valley College|Flying Dutchmen]] (like Seminoles, nationalities). Similarly, Warriors and Braves are no different from the fighting men of other cultures, like Vikings, Minutemen, or Musketeers (all current [[NCAA]] mascots, the first of which is also an [[NFL]] mascot) so it seems hard to argue that their use is uniquely demeaning in some way."&lt;ref name="globe"&gt;{{cite news|last=Adyanthaya|first=Anil|title=Sports, mascots, and Native Americans|url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/oped/articles/2005/06/05/sports_mascots_and_native_americans/|newspaper=The Boston Globe|date=June 5, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is not the names by themselves that are uniquely insulting to Native Americans. [[Richard Lapchick|Dr. Richard Lapchick]], director emeritus of Northeastern University's Center for the Study of Sport in Society, in an article: "Could you imagine people mocking African Americans in black face at a game? Yet go to a game where there is a team with an Indian name and you will see fans with war paint on their faces. Is this not the equivalent to black face?''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/page2/story?page=lapchick/050825&amp;num=0|title=Mascots are a matter of respect|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=02/06/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Supporters of the use of native imagery reject the term racism because they associate that word with the experience of African-Americans rather than Native Americans; however, [[Racism and ethnic discrimination in the United States#Racism against Native Americans|racism]] is a broader term for any discriminatory practice based upon ethnicity. Slavery was a more personal assault and continued after emancipation in the form of discrimination that insured a continued source of cheap labor. What Euro-Americans wanted from Native Americans was not labor but land, and most were willing to have native people themselves assimilate. Continued discrimination came to those who refused to do so, but asserted their separate identity and rights of sovereignty. The [[Cultural appropriation|appropriation]] of native cultures is therefore a discriminatory practice that is not understood as such by those that think of assimilation as a positive process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|volume=56|journal=UCLA Law Review|page=591|title=Red: Racism and the American Indian|last=Berger|first=Bethany R.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Others claim Native American mascots help promote the culture to those who might be unaware of its significance. [[Chief Illiniwek]], the former athletic symbol for the [[University of Illinois]], became the subject of protest in 1988.&lt;ref name="Spindel"/&gt; However, in 1990 the Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois called the mascot a dignified symbol: "His ceremonial dance is done with grace and beauty. The Chief keeps the memory of the people of a great Native American tribe alive for thousands of Illinoisans who otherwise would know little or nothing of them. However, the tribal costume was not of the [[Illiniwek|Illini confederacy]], but that of the [[Lakota people|Lakota tribe]]. The [[Peoria (tribe)|Peoria Tribe of Indians of Oklahoma]] is the closest living descendants of the Illiniwek Confederacy; and in 2005, John P. Froman, the new Chief when asked his position by the NCAA, indicated that "Chief (Illiniwek) was not representative of our tribe and culture, mainly because the costume is Sioux."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Daily Illini|first=Courtney|last=Linehan|url=http://www.dailyillini.com/home/index.cfm?event=displayArticlePrinterFriendly&amp;uStory_id=7d161c2c-6bd4-466a-bffa-92e7825e264e |title=Illiniwek appeal denied|date=November 14, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, in response to a widely published column by journalist [[George Will]] in support of the symbol's use, he wrote a letter reiterating the Peoria Tribe's opposition to the symbol and decrying that the "University of Illinois has ignored the tribe’s request for nearly five years."&lt;ref&gt;John P. Froman. [http://www.nah.uiuc.edu/faculty/tyeeme/documents/froman2006.pdf Letter to George Will of The Washington Post]. January 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; On March 13, 2007, the University of Illinois board of trustees voted to retire Illiniwek's name, image and regalia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=2796923|publisher= ESPN|title=Illinois trustees vote to retire Chief Illiniwek - College Sports}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Steven Denson, director of diversity for [[Southern Methodist University]] and member of the [[Chickasaw]] nation, while not issuing a blanket endorsement, has nevertheless stated that there are acceptable ways to use Native American mascots if it is done in a respectful and tasteful manner. He states: "I believe it is acceptable if used in a way that fosters understanding and increased positive awareness of the Native-American culture. And it must also be done with the support of the Native-American community. There is a way to achieve a partnership that works together to achieve mutually beneficial goals."&lt;ref name="SMU"&gt;[http://www.redorbit.com/news/science/153383/nativeamerican_nicknamesmascots/index.html Native-American Nicknames/Mascots], Red Orbit (June 2, 2005).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Public opinion surveys===
In 2001, ''[[Indian Country Today Media Network|Indian Country Today]]'' conducted a poll of an undisclosed number of readers reporting that "81 percent of respondents indicated use of American Indian names, symbols and mascots are predominantly offensive and deeply disparaging to Native Americans." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://indiancountrytodaymedianetwork.com/ictarchives/2001/08/07/american-indian-opinion-leaders-american-indian-mascots-84807|title=AMERICAN INDIAN OPINION LEADERS: American Indian Mascots|date=August 7, 2001|newspaper=Indian Country Today|accessdate=01/23/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A survey conducted in 2002 by Sports Illustrated (SI) found that 81 percent of Native Americans who live outside traditional Indian reservations and 53 percent of Indians on reservations did not find the images discriminatory. The authors of the article concluded that "Although most Native American activists and tribal leaders consider Indian team names and mascots offensive, neither Native Americans in general nor a cross section of U.S. sports fans agree. According to the article, There is a near total disconnect between Indian activists and the Native American population on this issue." An Indian activist commented on the results saying "that Native Americans' self-esteem has fallen so low that they don't even know when they're being insulted."&lt;ref name=PriceWoo&gt;
{{cite news
 | url = http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1025046/index.htm
 | author = S.L. Price
 | title = The Indian Wars
 | work = Sports Illustrated
 | date = March 4, 2002 |pages=66–71}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after the SI article, a group of five researchers published an article in an academic journal, arguing against the validity of this survey and its conclusions. First they state that "The confidence with which the magazine asserts that a 'disconnect' between Native American activists and Native Americans exists on this issue belies the serious errors in logic and accuracy made in the simplistic
labeling of Native Americans who oppose mascots as 'activists.'" &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://jss.sagepub.com/content/26/4/381|title=Of Polls and Race Predudice|DOI=10.1177/0193732502238255|journal=Journal of Sport and Social Issues|date=November 2002|volume=26|issue=4|page=381|author1=C. Richard King|author2=Ellen J. Staurowsky|author3=Lawrence Baca|author4=Laurel R. Davis|author5=Cornel Pewewardy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;King, C. Richard. ''The Native American Mascot Controvery: A Handbook'' p.268. Peter Harris Research Group. (2002) Methodology for ''Sports Illustrated'' survey on the use of Indian nicknames, mascots, etc. Document produced by The Peter Harris Research Group and shared with Ellen Staurowsky in January 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, a poll  by the Annenberg Public Policy Center at the University of Pennsylvania had a similar result to the Sports Illustrated poll's findings, concluding that 91% of the 768 American Indians surveyed in the 48 states on the mainland USA found the name "[[Washington Redskins|Redskins]]" acceptable.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=|first=|author-link= |title=Most Indians Say Name of Washington "Redskins" Is Acceptable While 9 Percent Call It Offensive, Annenberg Data Show|journal=National Annenberg Election Survey|volume=|issue=|pages=|date=September 24, 2004|year=|url=http://www.annenbergpublicpolicycenter.org/Downloads/Political_Communication/naes/2004_03_redskins_09-24_pr.pdf|doi= |accessdate=2008-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Associated Press reported a telephone survey conducted by GfK Roper Public Affairs &amp; Corporate Communications in April, 2013 that 4 out of 5 Americans would keep the Redskins name while only 11% would change it. However, only 2 of the 1,004 persons interviewed identified themselves as Native American.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://ap-gfkpoll.com/featured/our-latest-story-2|title=AP-GfK poll: 4 in 5 Americans say don’t change Redskins nickname; 11 percent say change it|author=BEN NUCKOLS|publisher=Associated Press|date=May 2, 2013|accessdate=06/03/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The possible flaw in random and anonymous polls of Native American's opinion is that they must rely upon self-identification to select the target group. In an editorial in the Bloomington Herald Times, Steve Russell (an enrolled Cherokee citizen and associate professor of criminal justice at Indiana University), states that both SI and Annenberg's samples of "self-identified Native Americans... includes plenty of people who have nothing to do with Indians".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iupui.edu/~mstd/e320/amerind/flap.html|title=Some collected materials about the NCAA's decision to ban Indian sports mascots from the Indianapolis area|accessdate=01/27/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The problem of individuals claiming to be Native American when they are not is well known in academic research, and is a particular problem when non-natives claim Indian identity specifically to gain authority in the debate over sports mascots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Springwood|first=Charles|title="I’m Indian Too!": Claiming Native American Identity, Crafting Authority in Mascot Debates|publisher=Journal of sport and social issues|date=02/2004|volume=28|page=56}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2013 The Washington Post conducted a phone survey of people living in the DC Metro Area. No questions about ethnicity were asked, only whether they supported the continued use of the Redskins name and if they were sports fans in general and fans of the team in particular. Not surprisingly, fans support the retention of the name, but they also said that if it did change, they would continue to support the team. What was surprising is that a small majority (56%) of those that would keep the name also thought that the word "redskin" was not an appropriate way to describe a Native American Indian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/page/2010-2019/WashingtonPost/2013/06/25/National-Politics/Polling/release_246.xml?44|title=Should the Washington Redskins change their name?|date=July 30, 2013|accessdate=10/16/2013|newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Financial impact of change===
Many supporters of Native American mascots feel that the financial cost of changing mascots would far outweigh the benefits.  Sales of merchandise with team mascots and nicknames ranging from t-shirts to beer cozies generate millions of dollars in sales each year, and teams contend that a change in team mascots would render this merchandise useless.&lt;ref name="bar"/&gt; The cost of removing images from uniforms and all other items, which must be paid out of local school funds, is a greater factor for secondary schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.mailtribune.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20120518/NEWS/205180322|title=State bans Native American mascots|date=May 18, 2012|first=Sanne|last=Specht|newspaper=Mail Tribune|accessdate=02/11/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Opponents, however, are unconcerned with the cost of changing, and view mascots as caricatures of real Indians that do not honor them, but rather trivialize and demean important Indian dances and traditions.  Opponents feel that despite the cost of a change in team mascots, it should be done to prevent what they believe is racial stereotyping. [[Clyde Bellecourt]], director of the [[American Indian Movement]] stated: "It's the behavior that accompanies all of this that's offensive.  The rubber tomahawks, the chicken feather headdresses, people wearing war paint and making these ridiculous war whoops with a tomahawk in one hand and a beer in the other; all of these have significant meaning for us. And the psychological impact it has, especially on our youth, is devastating."&lt;ref name="bar"/&gt;

One attempt to affect the use of mascots financially began in 1992 when five Native Americans filed a petition to remove the [[trademark]] status of the [[Washington Redskins]] team name, which would have allowed sales of branded merchandise without payment of [[royalties]]. The [[Trademark Trial and Appeal Board]] in 1999 ruled in favor of the petition and cancelled the trademarks. Following appeals, in 2005 the [[United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit|D.C. Court of Appeals]] in ''[[Pro-Football, Inc. v. Harjo]]'' reversed the cancellation, ruling that there had been insufficient [[Evidence (law)|evidence]] to support the finding of [[disparagement]] and holding that the majority of the petitioners were barred by [[Laches (equity)|laches]] from maintaining the suit.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Pro-Football, Inc. v. Harjo]]'', 415 F.3d 44 (2005)&lt;/ref&gt; On 16 November 2009, the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]], refused to hear an appeal from Harjo;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2009/CRIME/11/16/scotus.redskins/ | publisher=CNN | title=Court rejects appeal over Redskins trademark | accessdate=May 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; however a second case Blackhorse v. Pro-Football, Inc. with younger plaintiffs whose standing is not hindered by laches is now proceeding.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/nfl/redskins/2013/05/09/native-americans-washington-mascot-fight/2148877/?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+UsatodaycomSports-TopStories+%28Sports+-+Top+Stories%29|title=New generation of American Indians challenges Redskins|newspaper=USA Today|author=Erik Brady|date=May 10, 2013|accessdate=05/10/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Support for certain teams by individual tribes==
The NCAA has granted waivers from their mascot policy to five university teams that have obtained official support from individual tribes for the use of their names and images, which is based upon the principle of [[Tribal sovereignty in the United States|Tribal Sovereignty]], as stated by the NCAI: "In general, NCAI strongly opposes the use of derogatory Native sports mascots. However, in the case where mascots refer to a particular Native nation or nations, NCAI respects the right of individual tribal nations to work with universities and athletic programs to decide how to protect and celebrate their respective tribal heritage.".&lt;ref name="NCAI"/&gt;

===Florida State Seminoles===
[[Image:Chief Osceola on Renegade FSU.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Osceola rides his horse Renegade at a [[Florida State University|Florida State]] home game.]]
The [[Florida State University]]'s use of [[Seminole]] imagery for its [[Florida State Seminoles]] athletic teams represents a case of an evolution of its relationship with the [[Seminole Tribe of Florida]]. The university has worn the nickname "Seminoles" since 1947 and annually crowns a Chief and Princess at Homecoming with Seminole tribe leaders participating as celebrants. Since 1978 home football games have been opened with the entrance of [[Osceola and Renegade]]. Florida State University officials disapprove of referring to human figures as 'mascots' and have asked sports writers to cease doing so. Official university statements speak only of using 'symbols', 'nicknames', and 'images' inspired by Seminole tradition.

The question of a nickname for athletic teams arose in 1947 as the Florida State College for Women became [[Florida State University]]. The name Seminoles was selected by student vote, and for the first two decades the athletic teams mostly used images based on stereotypes such as in [[Hollywood]] [[Westerns]]. Leaders of the [[Seminole Tribe of Florida]] who attended a basketball game on the campus in 1972 expressed their concerns to university officials regarding the antics of such mascots. Seminole leaders and university officials agreed on the need for something dignified and more representative of authentic Seminole traditions. Both ''Sammy Seminole'' and ''Chief Fullabull'' were retired that year.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite news|last=DeSlatte |first=Aaron |url=http://groups.yahoo.com/group/NatNews/message/39441 |title=FSU worked to cultivate better image of Seminole |newspaper=Florida Today |date=August 17, 2005 |accessdate=2012-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

1978 marked the first appearance of [[Osceola and Renegade]], in which a student portrays the 19th-century Seminole leader [[Osceola]], riding Renegade, an [[Appaloosa]] horse. The student, chosen for his horsemanship, wears clothing provided by the Seminole tribe but is not necessarily of native American descent himself. The Seminole Tribe of Florida officially sanctions the use of the Seminole as Florida State University’s nickname and of Osceola as FSU's symbol. Max Osceola, the chief and general council president of the Seminole Tribe of Florida, has stated that he regards it as an “honor” to be associated with the university.&lt;ref name="seminole" /&gt; However, the Seminole Tribe of Florida is only one of the tribal authorities representing Seminoles. Some members of the much larger [[Seminole Nation of Oklahoma]] objected to the use of the name and imagery, leading to the NCAA originally placed FSU on the list of colleges using imagery “hostile or abusive” towards Native Americans.&lt;ref name="mess"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2005/08/08/mascot|title=The Mascot Mess|date=August 8, 2005|first=Doug|last=Lederman|newspaper=Inside Higher Ed|accessdate=02/08/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However in July 2005, the Seminole Nation General Council, the legislative body for the Seminole Nation of Oklahoma, voted 18-2 not to oppose the use of Native American names and mascots by college sports teams.&lt;ref name="McBee"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nbcsports.msnbc.com/id/8940521/|title=Seminole Nation OK with use of mascot|publisher=NBC Sports|accessdate=02/06/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
Too detailed, not sourced:  
At the beginning of each home game Osceola plants a flaming spear at midfield. The image and actions of this figure were worked out in coordination with Florida Seminole leaders. Osceola never speaks or appears walking on foot. When the US national anthem is sung, Osceola simply waits with his spear across his lap. For the first three years of the tradition the figure actually went nameless; he was referred to as 'the Seminole warrior' because tribal leaders at the time preferred that the name of the actual historical figure not be used. The Florida State portrayal of Osceola romanticizes tradition in some aspects. The historical Osceola, a war leader, did not actually live long enough to attain the rank of Seminole "chief". Florida State does not sanction the use of that term, and refers to the symbols simply as "Osceola and Renegade". Historians debate how much inclination or opportunity Osceola had to ride horses in [[Seminole Wars|wartime]].

This detailed back and forth does not belong in this general article
Activists Michael Haney and [[David Narcomey]], general council member of the [[Seminole Nation of Oklahoma]], objected to FSU's use of the Seminole symbol and name, and acting independently of the Seminole Nation of Oklahoma, filed a complaint with the NCAA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/tim-giago/the-powerful-medicine-of-_b_80444.html?view=print | work=Huffington Post | first=Tim | last=Giago | title=The Powerful Medicine of Michael Haney | date=Nov. 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; David Narcomey, speaking on his own behalf, stated "I am deeply appalled, incredulously disappointed ... I am nauseated that the NCAA is allowing this 'minstrel show' to carry on this form of racism in the 21st century."

In response, Jennifer McBee, the Oklahoma Seminole tribe's attorney general, stated that while David Narcomey was a member of the Oklahoma Seminoles' General Council, he did not speak for the 14,000-member Seminole Nation of Oklahoma when he protested to NCAA officials about FSU's use of the Seminole name and image. McBee added that the NCAA never even asked the General Council for its opinion.&lt;ref name="McBee"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nbcsports.msnbc.com/id/8940521/|title=Seminole Nation OK with use of mascot|publisher=NBC Sports|accessdate=02/06/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Attorney General McBee stated that, as of June 2005, the council had taken no official position on the FSU issue.&lt;ref name="seminole" /&gt; Despite the opinions expressed by Haney and Narcomey, Ken Chambers, principal chief of the Seminole Nation of Oklahoma told ''The Palm Beach'' (Florida) ''Post'' in August 2005 that he had no objection to Florida State University using the Seminoles as a nickname and symbol, reversing the earlier public position of the Oklahoma tribe's spokesperson.&lt;ref name="usatoday_seminoles"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/2005-08-11-fsu-mascot-support_x.htm|title=Oklahoma Seminoles OK Name|newspaper=USA Today}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
--&gt;

In August 2005 the NCAA granted a waiver to the Florida State University which removed it from the “hostile or abusive” list.  According to Bernard Franklin, senior vice president of the NCAA: "The staff review committee noted the unique relationship between the university and the Seminole Tribe of Florida as a significant factor.  The decision of a namesake sovereign tribe, regarding when and how its name and imagery can be used, must be respected even when others may not agree."&lt;ref name="seminole"&gt;Wieberg, Steve (Aug. 23, 2005), "[http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/2005-08-23-fsu-mascot-approved_x.htm NCAA allowing Florida State to use its Seminole mascot]," ''USA Today''.&lt;/ref&gt; The relationship between the tribe and the university has been maintained to the present, with few voices in opposition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/10/24/sports/ncaafootball/amid-rising-discord-over-indian-images-florida-state-has-harmony.html?_r=0|title=Amid Rising Discord Over Indian Images, F.S.U. Has Harmony|date=October 23, 2013|accessdate=11/04/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other exceptions: granted or denied ===
Other Indian tribes have also supported the use of their tribal names as a tribute to their heritage.

The [[Ute tribe]] approved the use of the name "Utes" for the [[University of Utah]] and the NCAA granted a waiver to allow the name to remain. For many decades, the school did not have an official Western Athletic Conference mascot.  As early as the 1950s, the University of Utah created a Ute Indian boy, named "Hoyo", as its mascot.  The University of Utah club organizations, such as the Associated Students of the University of Utah, the University of Utah Alumni Association, the Daily Chronicle, and many other social organizations highly celebrated "Hoyo" at homecoming events, before and after football games events, and at other social events for many years.&lt;ref&gt;1951 ''Utonian'', p. 153, University of Utah&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to 1972, teams used both "Utes" and "Redskins" as nicknames, but dropped the latter in response to tribal concerns. In 1996 Swoop, a red tailed hawk, became the official mascot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://utahutes.cstv.com/trads/swoop.html|title=Mascot/Nickname History|accessdate=11/18/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Even though Swoop is now the University of Utah's official mascot, Utah fans and its clubs alike still use "Utes" as their nickname at sporting events. This is done with permission from the Ute Tribal Council.&lt;ref&gt;[http://utahutes.cstv.com/trads/ute-trads-general.html Utah Traditions], University of Utah Athletics website&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Central Michigan University]] nickname, the [[Central Michigan Chippewas|Chippewas]], was originally placed on the “hostile or abusive” list but was removed when the [[Saginaw Chippewa Tribal Nation]] of Michigan gave its support to the nickname.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=2149907 "NCAA takes Utah off banned mascots list"] - ESPN&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of North Dakota]]'s former athletic logo, a [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] figure, was recently dropped. Due to the [[NCAA]]'s perception that the term "Fighting Sioux" and the accompanying logo are offensive to native Americans, the NCAA pressured the university to discontinue use of the logo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/sports/2012/02/29/ncaa-dont-bring-fighting-sioux-name-to-playoffs/ |title=NCAA: Don't bring Fighting Sioux name to playoffs. |publisher=FoxNews.com |date=February 29, 2012 |accessdate=March 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When UND moved in the fall of 2009 to change its nickname, one of the two Sioux tribal councils in the state sued to have the name retained.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/09/us/09nickname.html | work=The New York Times | title=In Twist, Tribe Fights for College Nickname | first=Monica | last=Davey | date=December 9, 2009 | accessdate=May 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]], however, is permitted to use the name "Illini" owing to the NCAA ruling that the name "is closely related to the name of the state and not directly associated with Native Americans."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncaa.org/wps/wcm/connect/ncaa/ncaa/media+and+events/press+room/news+release+archive/2007/official+statements/statement+by+bernard+franklin+ncaa+senior+vice-president+for+governance+membership+education+and+research+services+on+university+of+illinois+mascot+decision?pageDesign=old+news+releases+template Statement by NCAA Senior Vice-President] (retrieved 11 Sept 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; The term [[Fighting Illini]] is in fact a reference to veterans from Illinois who fought during World War I.  The symbol [[Chief Illiniwek]] was ruled "hostile and abusive" and was retired in 2007 to comply with the NCAA's ruling, and the following year, in compliance with a related NCAA ruling, both U of I and [[Northwestern University]] retired their then-current rivalry trophy, the [[Sweet Sioux Tomahawk]].

[[The College of William &amp; Mary]], founded in 1693 with a charter to, among other things, educate and evangelize the native population, voluntarily changed its sports nickname from "Indians" to the [[William &amp; Mary Tribe|"Tribe"]] in the late 1970s. However, the NCAA forced the school to remove the two tribal feathers stemming from [[Gene Nichol#Athletic logo and the NCAA|their logo]] in 2006 due to "insensitivity" towards Native Americans.  The fact that the local Pamunkey and Mattaponi tribes supported the College's use of the feathers was not enough for the NCAA.

The [[Arkansas State University]] officially removed its mascot, the "Indians," in 2008, replacing it with the "[[Arkansas State Red Wolves|Red Wolves]]," at the request of the [[Osage Nation|Osage]] tribe.
{{see also|Arapahoe_High_School_(Centennial,_Colorado)}}

==Current status==
After decades of decline from over 3,000,&lt;ref name="AICS"/&gt; there remain less than 1,000 high school, university and professional teams that continue to have Native American mascots.&lt;ref name="NCAI"/&gt; Though changes have been made at the high school and college levels, at the professional level there has been virtually no change. The topic remains an issue on a national level, with a hearing before the US Senate Committee on Indian Affairs in 2011,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indian.senate.gov/hearings/hearing.cfm?hearingID=e655f9e2809e5476862f735da16ba74a|title=OVERSIGHT HEARING on Stolen Identities: The Impact of Racist Stereotypes on Indigenous People|date=May 5, 2011|accessdate=02/10/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a symposium at the Smithsonian [[National Museum of the American Indian]] in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsdesk.si.edu/releases/native-american-mascot-controversy-takes-center-stage-national-museum-american-indian|title=Native American Mascot Controversy Takes Center Stage at the National Museum of the American Indian|work=Sports Illustrated|date=02/07/2013|accessdate=02/10/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of sports team names and mascots derived from Indigenous peoples]]
*[[List of ethnic sports team and mascot names]] (all ethnicities)
*[[Religious symbolism in U.S. sports team names and mascots]]
*[[Vernon Bellecourt]]
*[[Charlene Teters]]
*[[Russell Means]]
*[[Chief Zee]]
*[[Fighting Whites]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* King, C. Richard, guest editor.  "Re/claiming Indianness: Critical Perspectives on Native American Mascots." Journal of Sport and Social Issues 28, no. 1 (February 2004). www.sagepub.com/ejournals
* King, C. Richard, and Charles Fruehling Springwood (2001). ''Beyond the Cheers: Race as Spectacle in College Sport''. SUNY Series on Sport, Culture, and Social Relations. State University of New York Press. ISBN 0-7914-5005-8.
* King, C. Richard, and Charles Fruehling Springwood, eds. (2001). ''Team Spirits: The Native American Mascots Controversy''. Foreword by Vine Deloria Jr. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press.
* Remillard, Arthur. "Holy War on the Football Field: Religion and the Florida State University Mascot Controversy." ''Horsehide, Pigskin, Oval Tracks, and Apple Pie: Essays on Sports and American Culture''. Edited by James Vlasich. McFarland, 2005.
{{refend}}

==External links==
'''Organizations'''
* [http://www.aistm.org/1indexpage.htm American Indian Sports Team Mascots]
* [http://www.aimovement.org/ncrsm/ National Coalition on Racism in Sports and Media]
* [http://www.racismagainstindians.org/UnderstandingMascots.htm STAR]
* [http://honorindians.com Honor Indians Institute]

'''Films'''
* ''[http://www.inwhosehonor.com/ In Whose Honor?]'' (1997). Written and produced by Jay Rosenstein. [[Ho-Ho-Kus, New Jersey]]: New Day Films.

&lt;!-- ;Websites
* [http://www.nativeculturelinks.com/mascots.html The Mascot Issue]. Lisa Mitten. February 17, 1999 (last updated May 20, 2008)
'''Articles'''
* [http://www.dickshovel.com/crimes.html "Crimes Against Humanity"] by [[Ward Churchill]]
* Keen, Judy. [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/USAToday/offers.html?url=%2FUSAToday%2Faccess%2F2156557021.html%3FFMT%3DFT%26FMTS%3DABS%3AFT%26date%3DOct%2B7%252C%2B2010%26author%3DJudy%2BKeen%26pub%3DUSA%2BTODAY%26edition%3D%26startpage%3DA.3%26desc%3DControversial%2Bmascot%2Bejected "Controversial mascot ejected: Wis. community to choose name after dropping 'Indians' name used since 1936"] (Kewaunee High School). [[USA Today]], October 7, 2010, page 3A.
 --&gt;
{{Atlanta Braves}}
 {{Chicago Blackhawks |state=collapsed}}
{{Cleveland Indians}}
{{Golden State Warriors}}
{{Kansas City Chiefs}}
{{Washington Redskins}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Native American Mascot Controversy}}
[[Category:American mascots]]
[[Category:College mascots in the United States| ]]
[[Category:Cultural appropriation]]
[[Category:Ethnic and racial stereotypes]]
[[Category:Native American topics]]
[[Category:Sports controversies]]
[[Category:Sports mascots]]
[[Category:Atlanta Braves]]
[[Category:Chicago Blackhawks]]
[[Category:Cleveland Indians]]
[[Category:Florida State Seminoles]]
[[Category:Golden State Warriors]]
[[Category:Kansas City Chiefs]]
[[Category:Washington Redskins]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>