<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081106050531|249980996" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12719721" pageid="12719721" ns="0" title="Native American mascot controversy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-06T05:10:56Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Kansas City Chiefs logo.svg|thumb|right|250px||The Kansas City Chiefs Logo]]
The use of '''Native American mascots''' in sports has become a contentious issue in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]]. Americans have had a history of "playing Indian" that dates back to at least the 1700s.&lt;ref name="Calloway"&gt;First Peoples, Colin G. Calloway, 2nd Edition, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Many individuals admire the heroism and romanticism evoked by the classic [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] image, but many too view the use of [[mascot]]s as both offensive and demeaning (especially amongst Native Americans).
Despite the concerns that have been raised, many Native American mascots are still used in American sports from the elementary to the professional level.

==History==
During the 1960s, the [[National Congress of American Indians]] created a campaign to eliminate negative stereotyping of Native American people in the media.  They focused mainly on cartoons and movies; however their protests of sports organizations garnered the most attention.&lt;ref name="tolerance"&gt;Fight Hate and Promote Tolerance http://www.tolerance.org/news/article_tol.jsp?id=165  www.tolerance.org&lt;/ref&gt; The National Congress of American Indians has long been opposed to mascots that portray Indians in a negative light.  They feel that teams with mascots such as the Braves and the Redskins perpetuate negative stereotypes of Indian people, and demean their native traditions and rituals.&lt;ref name="NCAI"&gt;National Congress of American Indians http://www.ncai.org/ncai/resource/documents/governance/ncainews4.2.99.htm National Congress of American Indians
Applauds "Redskins" Trademark Cancellation&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents of Native American mascots, however, believe that Native American mascots pay homage to these people and promote a better understanding of their cultures.&lt;ref name="tolerance" /&gt; Despite this issue emanating during the [[civil rights movement]], it still continues today as many teams continues to possess mascots with controversial names and images.&lt;ref name="tolerance" /&gt;

==Varying degrees of offensiveness?==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Redskins logo.gif|thumb|right|190px||The Washington Redskins Mascot]] --&gt;
[[Image:Vizquel96.jpg|thumb|right|180px|Cleveland Indians player [[Omar Vizquel]] wearing a baseball cap bearing the image of the Cleveland Indians mascot, [[Chief Wahoo]]]]
To further complicate this issue, many feel that there are varying levels of offensiveness with team names and mascots.  Anil Adyanthaya from the ''Boston Globe'' writes on June 5, 2005, "The use of Aztec or Seminole as a nickname by itself would not appear to be racist, as such names refer to a particular civilization rather than an entire race of people. In this way, they are no different from other school nicknames such as Trojans and Spartans (like Aztecs, ancient peoples) or [[Notre Dame Fighting Irish|Fighting Irish]] and [[Lebanon Valley College|Flying Dutchmen]] (like Seminoles, nationalities). Similarly, Warriors and Braves are no different from the fighting men of other cultures, like Vikings, Minutemen, or Musketeers (all current [[NCAA]] mascots, the first of which is also an [[NFL]] mascot) so it seems hard to argue that their use is uniquely demeaning in some way."&lt;ref name="globe"&gt; Boston Globe http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/oped/articles/2005/06/05/sports_mascots_and_native_americans/ Sports, mascots, and Native Americans&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|''Could you imagine people mocking African Americans in black face at a game?” he said. 'Yet go to a game where there is a team with an Indian name and you will see fans with war paint on their faces. Is this not the equivalent to black face?' ''|20px|20px|- Teaching Tolerance, May 9, 2001, ''Native American Mascots Big Issue in College Sports''&lt;ref name=teachingTolerance&gt;
{{cite web
 | url        = http://www.tolerance.org/news/article_tol.jsp?id=165
 | title      = Native American Mascots Big Issue in College Sports
 | accessdate = 2008-08-26
 | author     = Teaching Tolerance
 | format     = HTML 
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; }}

According to polling results published in [[Sports Illustrated]] in February 2002, "Although most Native American activists and tribal leaders consider Indian team names and mascots offensive, neither Native Americans in general nor a cross section of U.S. sports fans agree."&lt;ref name=PriceWoo&gt;  S.L. Price &amp; Andrea Woo, "The Indian Wars", Sports Illustrated, March 4, 2002, pp 66-71&lt;/ref&gt;. According to the article, "There is a near total disconnect between Indian activists and the Native American population on this issue."&lt;ref name=PriceWoo/&gt;

However, despite this varying degree of degradation, the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] (NCAA), the ruling authority on college athletics, distributed a “self evaluation” in June 2005, for teams to examine the use of potentially offensive imagery with their mascot choice.&lt;ref name="globe" /&gt; 

Some college teams, however, are changing their names and mascots without instruction of the NCAA.  For example, [[Marquette University]] changed their team name from the Warriors to the Golden Eagles in 1994.  The school’s president stated “we live in a different era than when the Warriors nickname was selected in 1954. The perspective of time has shown us that our actions, intended or not, can offend others. We must not knowingly act in a way that others will believe, based on their experience, to be an attack on their dignity as fellow human beings.” [[Stonehill College]] also changed their mascot from the Chieftain to the Skyhawk “out of respect to Native American culture.”&lt;ref name="globe" /&gt; 

Additionally, teams that are not directly affected by this controversy have issued their opinions. The [[University of Wisconsin]] and the [[University of Iowa]] have both refused to schedule non-conference games against schools with Native American mascots.&lt;ref name="globe" /&gt; Ironically, the University of Iowa's own nickname, "Hawkeyes", has Native American origins (Iowa is the "[[Hawkeye State]]"), although the team uses a [[hawk]] as its symbol rather than an Indian.

The [[University of Oregon]], following suit by the ''[[Oregonian]]'' newspaper, declined to refer to the [[University of Illinois]] team as the "Illini" in a basketball game in 2005. Illinois won the game 79-61.

==Argument supporting the use of Native American mascots==
[[Image:FedExField - Redskins Jaguars pregame field.jpg|thumb|right|210px|The Washington Redskins logo at FedEx Field, in Maryland]]
Some individuals who support the use of Native American mascots state that they are meant to be respectful, and to pay homage to Native American people.  The argument is made that Native American mascots focus on bravery, courage and fighting skills rather than anything derogatory. Karl Swanson, vice-president of the Washington Redskins professional football team, declared in the magazine ''[[Sports Illustrated]]'' that his team's name "symbolizes courage, dignity, and leadership," and that the "Redskins symbolize the greatness and strength of a grand people."&lt;ref name="bar"&gt;New Jersey State Bar Foundation http://www.njsbf.org/njsbf/student/respect/winter03-1.cfm Native American Mascots: Racial Slur or Cherished Tradition?&lt;/ref&gt;

Others claim Native American mascots help promote the culture to those who might be unaware of its significance. [[Chief Illiniwek]], the mascot for the [[University of Illinois]], has been another figure who has come under scrutiny. However, in 1990 the Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois called the mascot a “dignified” symbol: “His ceremonial dance is done with grace and beauty. The Chief keeps the memory of the people of a great Native American tribe alive for thousands of Illinoisans who otherwise would know little or nothing of them.”&lt;ref name="tolerance" /&gt;  However, the tribal dance and costume was not of the [[Illiniwek|Illini confederacy]], but that of the [[Lakota people|Lakota tribe]]. {{Fact|date=May 2008}}

Steven Denson, director of diversity for [[Southern Methodist University]] and member of the [[Chickasaw]] nation, while not issuing a blanket endorsement, has nevertheless stated that there are acceptable ways to use Native American mascots if it is done in a respectful and tasteful manner. He states, “I believe it is acceptable if used in a way that fosters understanding and increased positive awareness of the Native-American culture. And it must also be done with the support of the Native-American community. There is a way to achieve a partnership that works together to achieve mutually beneficial goals.”&lt;ref name="SMU"&gt;Red Orbit http://www.redorbit.com/news/science/153383/nativeamerican_nicknamesmascots/index.html Native-American Nicknames/Mascots&lt;/ref&gt;

==Argument opposing the use of Native American mascots==
Opponents of Native American mascots feel that the mascots breed insensitivity and misunderstanding about native people.  Opponents also highlight the seeming double standard for racial mascots where there are no mascots based on African Americans, Mexican Americans, or Asian Americans depicted in sports.&lt;ref name="AICS"&gt;American Indian Cultural Support http://www.aics.org/mascot/mascot.html Mascots - Racism in Schools by State&lt;/ref&gt; The [[University of Notre Dame]]’s “[[Notre Dame Fighting Irish|Fighting Irish]]."&lt;ref name="ND"&gt;University of Notre Dame http://und.cstv.com/trads/nd-m-fb-mas.html Notre Dame Fighting Irish - Traditions&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[University of Louisiana at Lafayette|University of Louisiana Lafayette]]'s "[[Louisiana Ragin' Cajuns|Ragin' Cajuns]]" are notable exceptions to the debate, as those schools selected symbols that represent ''themselves'' historically.

{{cquote|''(Trudie Lamb Richmond doesn't) know what to say when kids argue, 'I don't care what you say, we are honoring you. We are keeping our Indian.' ... What if it were 'our black' or 'our Hispanic'?''|20px|20px|- Amy D'orio quoting Trudie Lamb Richmond, March 1996, ''Indian Chief Is Mascot No More''&lt;ref name=amy_d&gt;
{{cite web
 | url        = http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E4DF1239F932A05750C0A960958260&amp;n=Top%2FReference%2FTimes%20Topics%2FSubjects%2FM%2FMascots
 | title      = Indian Chief Is Mascot No More
 | accessdate = 2008-08-26
 | author     = Amy D'orio
 | format     = HTML 
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; }}

A big issue in the Native American mascot debate is the use of Indian mascots by elementary, middle and high school sports teams.  Opponents of Native American mascots feel that children should be exposed to realistic and positive portrayals of American Indians during their educational years.  Kathy Morning Star, director of the American Indian Cultural Support, states that "It is the responsibility of educators to set the example and teach the youth of today to respect other ethnic or minority peoples - NOT to exploit or disrespect them by using them as 'mascots' or stereotypical 'images' which perpetuates racism."&lt;ref name="AICS" /&gt;

Many opponents also take offense to proponents of Native American mascots that claim they are simply paying tribute to native people.  Considering many Native Americans’ stance on this issue, opponents of Native American mascots feel that the mascots should be deemed offensive by the people being imitated, not by those who are imitating.  Barbara Munson of the [[Oneida tribe|Oneida nation]] states "When someone says you are hurting them by your action, if you persist - then the harm becomes intentional."&lt;ref name="AICS" /&gt;

Opponents also deem it insensitive when unconscious phrases like “Kill the Indians” or “Murder the Redskins” are yelled during sporting events (the latter of which is particularly yelled by [[Dallas Cowboys|Cowboys]], [[Philadelphia Eagles|Eagles]], and [[New York Giants|Giants]] fans, due to [[Significant rivalries in the NFL#NFC East|long-standing NFL rivalries]]), referring to the team playing, but also creating a negative view of Native Americans.&lt;ref name="AICS" /&gt;

==Florida State Seminoles==
[[Image:Chief Osceola on Renegade FSU.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Chief Osceola, the Florida State University mascot, riding his horse Renegade]]
The debate over the mascot and symbol of [[Florida State University]]'s [[Florida State Seminoles]] athletic teams is an interesting case study because of the university's close ties to the Seminole Tribe of Florida.

The university's first mascots were [[Sammy Seminole]]&lt;sup&gt;[http://fpc.dos.state.fl.us/reference/rc01465.jpg photo]&lt;/sup&gt; (1958-1972) and Chief Fullabull.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://unirel.fsu.edu/seminoles/pages/timeline.html Florida State Seminoles: A Tradition of Tribute :: Timeline&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[http://groups.yahoo.com/group/NatNews/message/39441 Yahoo! Groups&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Both were portrayed by [[White people|white]] undergraduate students who dressed in faux [[Native Americans in the United States|American Indian]] garb,&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; and the latter mascot would engage in antics such as stabbing a fake pig representing the mascot of an opposing team on the basketball court.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;

After leaders of the [[Seminole]] Tribe of Florida learned of these mascots, they attended a basketball game on the campus in 1972 and subsequently expressed their concern to the university regarding the Chief Fullabull mascot.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; Both mascots were retired that year,&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; and were replaced in 1978 with [[Chief Osceola and Renegade]], with a white student this time portraying the 19th century Seminole war chief [[Osceola]], Renegade  being his [[appaloosa]] horse.

In August 2005, the NCAA granted Florida State University a waiver, which removed FSU from the NCAA’s list of colleges whose sports teams, it said, used “hostile or abusive” imagery towards Native Americans.  According to Bernard Franklin, senior vice president of the NCAA, "The staff review committee noted the unique relationship between the university and the Seminole Tribe of Florida as a significant factor.  The decision of a namesake sovereign tribe, regarding when and how its name and imagery can be used, must be respected even when others may not agree."&lt;ref name="seminole"&gt;USA Today http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/2005-08-23-fsu-mascot-approved_x.htm NCAA allowing Florida State to use its Seminole mascot&lt;/ref&gt;

The Seminole Tribe of Florida officially sanctions the use of the Seminole as Florida State University’s nickname and of Chief Osceola as FSU's mascot. Max Osceola, the chief and general council president of the Seminole Tribe of Florida, feels that it is an “honor” to be associated with the university.&lt;ref name="seminole" /&gt;

Some members of the Seminole Tribe of Oklahoma, among them activists [[David Narcomey]] and Michael Haney,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/tim-giago/the-powerful-medicine-of-_b_80444.html?view=print Tim Giago: The Powerful Medicine of Michael Haney - Living on The Huffington Post&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; opposed FSU's use of the Seminoles mascot and name.   In addition, general council member of the Seminole nation of Oklahoma [[David Narcomey]] stated, speaking on his own behalf, "I am deeply appalled, incredulously disappointed ... I am nauseated that the NCAA is allowing this 'minstrel show' to carry on this form of racism in the 21st century." In 2005, Jennifer McBee, the Oklahoma Seminole tribe's attorney general, stated that the council had taken no official position on the FSU issue.&lt;ref name="seminole" /&gt;  Despite the individual comments of some members of the Oklahoma Seminoles, Ken Chambers, principal chief of the Seminole Nation of Oklahoma told ''The Palm Beach'' (Florida) ''Post'' in August 2005 that he had no objection to Florida State University using the Seminoles as a nickname and symbol, reversing the earlier public position of the Oklahoma tribe's spokesperson.&lt;ref name="usatoday_seminoles"&gt;http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/2005-08-11-fsu-mascot-support_x.htm Oklahoma Seminoles OK Name&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2005, the Seminole Nation General Council, the legislative body for the Seminole Nation of Oklahoma, voted 18-2 to not oppose the use of Native American names and mascots by college sports teams.

==Other==
Other Indian tribes have also supported the use of their tribal names as a tribute to their heritage. The [[Ute tribe]] approved the use of the name "Utes" for the [[University of Utah]] and the NCAA granted a waiver to allow the name to remain. 

The [[Sioux]] tribe, however, refused to approve the use of the name "[[North Dakota Fighting Sioux|Fighting Sioux]]" in the name of the [[University of North Dakota]]. UND has appealed several times to the NCAA and is currently under a championship host ban for not removing the moniker. 

The [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]], however, is permitted to use the name "Illini" owing to the NCAA ruling that the name "is closely related to the name of the state and not directly associated with Native Americans."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncaa.org/wps/portal/legacysiteviewer?CONTENT_URL=http://www2.ncaa.org/portal/media_and_events/press_room/2005/november/20051111_illinois_mascot_stmnt.html
 Statement by NCAA Senior Vice-President] (retrieved 19 April 2008)&lt;/ref&gt; The mascot [[Chief Illiniwek]] was ruled "hostile and abusive" and was retired in 2007 to comply with the NCAA's ruling.

The [[College of William &amp; Mary]], nicknamed the "Tribe," was forced to remove the two tribal feathers stemming from [[Gene R. Nichol#Athletic logo and the NCAA|their logo]] in 2006 due to insensitivity towards Native Americans.

==Financial impact of change==
Many supporters of Native American mascots feel that the financial cost of changing mascots would far outweigh the benefits.  Sales of merchandise with team mascots and nicknames ranging from t-shirts to beer coozies generate millions of dollars in sales each year, and teams contend that a change in team mascots would render this merchandise useless.&lt;ref name="bar" /&gt; However, the large amounts of revenue generated by the sales of new merchandise by professional sport teams whenever they change their logo, colors or mascot would seem to disprove this.{{Fact|date=September 2008}}

Opponents, however, are unconcerned with the cost of changing and view mascots as caricatures of real Indians that do not honor them, but rather trivialize and demean important Indian dances and traditions.  Opponents feel that despite the cost of a change in team mascots, it should be done to prevent what they believe is racial stereotyping. [[Clyde Bellecourt]], the director of the [[American Indian Movement]], stated "It's the behavior that accompanies all of this that's offensive.  The rubber tomahawks, the chicken feather headdresses, people wearing war paint and making these ridiculous war whoops with a tomahawk in one hand and a beer in the other-all of these have significant meaning for us. And the psychological impact it has, especially on our youth, is devastating."&lt;ref name="bar"/&gt;

One attempt to affect the use of mascots financially began in 1992 when five Native Americans filed a petition to remove the [[trademark]] status of the [[Washington Redskins]] team name, which would have disallowed sales of branded merchandise without payment of [[royalties]]. The [[Trademark Trial and Appeal Board]] in 1999 ruled in favor of the petition and cancelled the trademarks. Following appeals, in 2005 the [[United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit|D.C. Court of Appeals]] in ''[[Pro-Football, Inc. v. Harjo]]'' reversed the cancellation, ruling that there had been insufficient [[Evidence (law)|evidence]] to support the finding of [[disparagement]] and holding that the majority of the petitioners were barred by [[Laches (equity)|laches]] from maintaining the suit.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Pro-Football, Inc. v. Harjo]]'', 415 F.3d 44 (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current status==
The Native American mascot issue remains fiercely contested because of the many Native American mascots still currently used in sports. According to the American Indian Cultural Support, as of 2006, at least 2,498 kindergarten, elementary, middle and high schools use Native American Indian mascots throughout the country.&lt;ref name="AICS" /&gt;

Though change has been made on the public school and college level, the professional arena has seen virtually none and still utilizes mascots such as the [[Chicago Blackhawks]], [[Washington Redskins]], [[Cleveland Indians]], [[Atlanta Braves]], [[Kansas City Chiefs]], and many others.&lt;ref name="AICS" /&gt; During the 2007 post-season, for example, [[Chief Wahoo]] was very visible, including being displayed in the stats line on the bottom of network television screens for both [[TBS]] and [[Fox Sports]].

==Bibliography==
*King, C. Richard, and Charles Fruehling Springwood (2001). ''Beyond the Cheers: Race as Spectacle in College Sport''. SUNY Series on Sport, Culture, and Social Relations. State University of New York Press. ISBN 0791450058.
* King, C. Richard, and Charles Fruehling Springwood, eds. (2001). ''Team Spirits: The Native American Mascots Controversy''. Foreword by Vine Deloria Jr. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press.
* Spindel, Carol (2002). ''Dancing at Halftime: Sports and the Controversy Over American Indian Mascots''. Updated edition, with a new afterword. New York: New York University Press.

==Films==
* ''[http://www.inwhosehonor.com/ In Whose Honor?]'' (1997). Written and produced by Jay Rosenstein. [[Ho-Ho-Kus, New Jersey]]: New Day Films.

==See also==
*[[Charlene Teters]]
*[[Chief Illiniwek]]
*[[Chief Wahoo]]
*[[List of sports team names and mascots derived from Indigenous peoples]]
*[[List of ethnic sports team and mascot names]] (all ethnicities)
*[[Mascot]]
*[[National Congress of American Indians]]
*[[Seminole]]
*[[Vernon Bellecourt]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikinews|American Indian Movement spokesperson dies, age 75}}
'''Organizations'''
*[http://www.allarm.org/ ALLARM]
*[http://www.aimovement.org/ncrsm/ National Coalition on Racism in Sports and Media]
*[http://www.racismagainstindians.org/UnderstandingMascots.htm STAR]
*[http://honorindians.com Honor Indians Institute]

'''Articles'''
*[http://www.dickshovel.com/crimes.html "Crimes Against Humanity"] by [[Ward Churchill]]

'''Parody'''
*[http://www.shelflifeclothing.com/shirtpages/caucasians.html Turning the Tables on Racist Mascots]
*[http://honorindians.com/alternative-indian-mascots Alternative Indian Mascots]

[[Category:Native American topics]]
[[Category:Sports mascots]]
[[Category:Team sports]]
[[Category:College mascots| ]]
[[Category:Illinois Fighting Illini football]]
[[Category:Fictional Native Americans]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Stereotypes]]

[[simple:Native American mascot controversy]]
[[zh:美洲原住民吉祥物爭議]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>