<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141116205059|634124872" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12719721" pageid="12719721" ns="0" title="Native American mascot controversy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-18T15:28:59Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Vizquel96.jpg|thumb|right|180px|Former Cleveland Indians player [[Omar Vizquel]] wearing a baseball cap showing the image of the Cleveland Indians mascot, [[Chief Wahoo]]]]
&lt;!-- NOTE: This lead section is a summary of the sections below, so references are minimal 
(See WP:Manual_of_Style/Lead_section)--&gt;
The propriety of using Native American names and images in sports has been a topic of public controversy in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]] since the 1960s, as part of the movement for [[Native American civil rights]]. There have been protests and other actions targeting the more visible professional teams such as the [[Cleveland Indians]] (in particular their "Chief Wahoo" logo), and the Washington NFL team due to the name "Redskins" being defined in most American English dictionaries as derogatory slang.&lt;ref name="handbook"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books/about/The_Native_American_Mascot_Controversy.html?id=GApQrXWeGLwC|editor=C. Richard King|title=The Native American Mascot Controversy: A Handbook|chapter=4|author=Laurel R. Davis|publisher=Scarecrow Press|location=Lanham, Maryland|year=2010|isbn=978-0-8108-6731-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over 115 professional organizations representing civil rights, educational, athletic, and scientific experts have published resolutions or policies that state that the use of [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] names and/or symbols by non-native sports teams is a harmful form of [[ethnic stereotyping]] that promote misunderstanding and prejudice which contributes to other problems faced by Native Americans.&lt;ref name="APA2010"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apa.org/pi/oema/resources/communique/2010/08/native-themed-mascots.aspx|title=Legislative efforts to eliminate native-themed mascots, nicknames, and logos: Slow but steady progress post-APA resolution|publisher=American Psychological Association|date=August 2010|accessdate=January 23, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Coalition"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.coalitionagainstracism.org/|title=National Coalition Against Racism in Sports and Media|accessdate=October 3, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Defenders of the current usage often state their intention to honor [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]]s by referring to positive traits such as fighting spirit and being aggressive, brave, stoic, dedicated, and proud.&lt;ref name="handbook" /&gt; Supporters also state that the issue is not important being only about sports, and that the opposition is nothing more than "[[political correctness]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books/about/The_Native_American_Mascot_Controversy.html?id=GApQrXWeGLwC|editor=C. Richard King|title=The Native American Mascot Controversy: A Handbook|chapter=2|author=Barbara E. Munson|publisher=Scarecrow Press|location=Lanham, Maryland|year=2010|isbn=978-0-8108-6731-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Opinion poll|Surveys of public opinion]] consistently find that the majority of people in the United States support retaining the names and images in current use, however there has been a steady decline in the number of teams doing so. Native American images and nicknames nevertheless remain fairly common in American sports, and may be seen in use by teams at all levels from elementary school to professional.

==History==
Americans have had a history of drawing inspiration from native peoples and "playing Indian" that dates back at least to the 18th century.&lt;ref name="Calloway"&gt;[[Colin G. Calloway|Calloway, Colin G.]] (2004) ''First Peoples'', 2nd Ed.&lt;/ref&gt; This practice led directly to the origins of many nicknames and mascots. Like the Boy Scouts (in particular, the [[Order of the Arrow]]) and many summer camps, university students in the late 19th and early 20th centuries adopted Indian names and symbols for their group identities, not from authentic sources but rather as Native American life was imagined by Euro-Americans.&lt;ref name="Spindel"&gt;{{cite book|last=Spindel|first=Carol|year=2002|title=Dancing at Halftime: Sports and the Controversy Over American Indian Mascots|location=New York|publisher=New York University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Professional team nicknames had similar origins. Founded as the Boston Red Stockings, the team became the [[History of the Boston Braves|Braves]] for the first time in 1912. Their owner, [[James E. Gaffney|James Gaffney]], was a member of New York City's political machine, Tammany Hall, one of the societies originally formed to honor [[Tamanend]], a chief of the Delaware. The success of the Braves in the [[1914 World Series]] may have been the reason for the Cleveland team, which was looking for a new nickname, to become the [[Cleveland Indians#1894.E2.80.931935: Beginning to middle|Indians]] in 1915. The story that the team is named to honor [[Louis Sockalexis]], the first Native American to play major league baseball, cannot be verified from historical documents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=An Act of Honor or Exploitation? The Cleveland Indians' Use of the Louis Francis Sockalexis Story|first=Ellen|last=Staurowsky|journal=Sociology of Sports Journal|date=December 1998|volume=15(4)|page=299}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Redskins in Washington, DC was originally also the Boston Braves when formed in 1932, since it was the custom at the time to have the same team names when baseball and football shared the same stadium. Moving to the home of the Boston Red Sox, the name was changed to the Boston Redskins in 1933 before moving again to Washington. Thus the use of Native American names and imagery by this team began before the hiring of [[William Henry Dietz|Lone Star Dietz]] as coach in 1933.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sportsecyclopedia.com/nfl/wasbos/bosskins.html|title=The Boston Redskins|accessdate=2013-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1940s the [[National Congress of American Indians]] (NCAI) created a campaign to eliminate negative stereotyping of Native American people in the media. Over time, the campaign began to focus on Indian names and mascots in sports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hylton|first=J Gordon|title=BEFORE THE REDSKINS WERE THE REDSKINS: THE USE OF NATIVE AMERICAN TEAM NAMES IN THE FORMATIVE ERA OF AMERICAN SPORTS, 1857-1933|publisher=North Dakota law review|date=2010-01-01|volume=86|page=879}}&lt;/ref&gt; The NCAI maintains that teams with mascots such as the [[Braves]] and the [[Redskins]] perpetuate negative stereotypes of Native American people, and demean their native traditions and rituals.&lt;ref name="NCAI"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncai.org/policy-issues/community-and-culture/anti-defamation-mascots|title=Anti-Defamation and Mascots|publisher=National Congress of American Indians|accessdate=12 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents of Native American mascots, however, believe that Native American mascots pay respect to these people and promote a better understanding of their cultures. Despite this issue gaining prominence during the [[civil rights movement]], it still continues today as many teams continue to possess mascots with controversial names and images.

The stereotyping of Native Americans must be understood in the context of history which includes conquest, forced relocation, and organized efforts to eradicate native cultures, such as the [[Native American boarding schools|boarding schools]] of the late 19th and early 20th centuries, which separated young Native Americans from their families in order to educate them as Euro-Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apa.org/pi/oema/resources/policy/mascots-justif.pdf|title=APA Resolution Justifications|year=2005|publisher=American Psychological Association|accessdate=2013-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
As stated in an editorial by Carter Meland (Anishinaabe heritage) and David E. Wilkins (Lumbee) both professors of American Indian Studies at the University of Minnesota: "Since the first Europeans made landfall in North America, native peoples have suffered under a weltering array of stereotypes, misconceptions and caricatures. Whether portrayed as ''noble savages'', ''ignoble savages'', ''teary-eyed environmentalists'' or, most recently, simply as ''casino-rich'', native peoples find their efforts to be treated with a measure of respect and integrity undermined by images that flatten complex tribal, historical and personal experience into one-dimensional representations that tells us more about the depicters than about the depicted." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Star Tribune|title=Stereotypes in sports, chaos in federal policy|author=Carter Meland and David E. Wilkins|date=November 22, 2012|url=http://www.startribune.com/opinion/commentaries/180435801.html?refer=y|accessdate=2013-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opposition to the use of Native American mascots==
Opponents of Native American names, images, and mascots assert that they breed insensitivity and misunderstanding about native people which does harm to both individuals and society as a whole. Social science research demonstrating this harm has been the basis for civil rights, educational, athletic, and religious organizations calling for the end of these practices.

===Social sciences===
The harm done by the use of Native American mascots particularly in an academic context was stated by the Society of Indian Psychologists in 1999:
&lt;blockquote&gt;''Stereotypical and historically inaccurate images of Indians in general interfere with learning about them by creating, supporting and maintaining oversimplified and inaccurate views of indigenous peoples and their cultures. When stereotypical representations are taken as factual information, they contribute to the development of cultural biases and prejudices, (clearly a contradiction to the educational mission of the University.) In the same vein, we believe that continuation of the use of Indians as symbols and mascots is incongruous with the philosophy espoused by many Americans as promoting inclusivity and diversity.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aiansip.org/uploads/SIP_Indian_Mascot_Position_Statement.pdf|title=Society of Indian Psychologists|date=January 27, 1999|accessdate=2013-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In 2005, the [[American Psychological Association]] issued a resolution "Recommending the Immediate Retirement of American Indian Mascots, Symbols, Images, and Personalities by Schools, Colleges, Universities, Athletic Teams, and Organizations" due to the harm done by creating a hostile environment, the negative impact on the self-esteem of American Indian children, and is discrimination that may violate civil rights. It also impacts non-natives by reinforcing mainstream stereotypes, preventing learning about Native American culture. The APA states that stereotyping is disrespectful of the beliefs, traditions and values of Native Americans.&lt;ref name=APA&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apa.org/pi/oema/resources/indian-mascots.aspx|title=Summary of the Resolution Recommending Retirement of American Indian Mascots|publisher=American Psychological Association|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar resolutions have been adopted by the [[American Sociological Association]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asanet.org/about/Council_Statements/use_of_native_american_nicknames_logos_and_mascots.cfm|title=Statement by the Council of the American Sociological Association on Discontinuing the Use of Native American Nicknames, Logos and Mascots in Sport|publisher=American Sociological Association|date=March 6, 2007|accessdate=2013-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[American Counseling Association]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.counseling.org/docs/resolutions/resolutions-2001-present.pdf?sfvrsn=2|publisher=American Counseling Association|title=Opposition to Use of Stereotypical Native American Images as Sports Symbols and Mascots|year=2001|accessdate=2013-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Social science research gives weight to the perceptions of those directly affected. In particular studies support the view that sports mascots and images are not trivial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Fryberg |first=Stephanie A.|title=Of Warrior Chiefs and Indian Princesses: The Psychological Consequences of American Indian Mascots|work=Basic and applied social psychology|date=September 2008|volume=30(3)|page=208}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stereotyping directly affects academic performance and self-esteem, which contribute to all of the other issues faced by Native Americans, including suicide, unemployment, and poverty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/07/opinion/sunday/intelligence-and-the-stereotype-threat.html|title=It’s Not Me, It’s You|first=ANNIE|last=MURPHY PAUL|date=October 6, 2012|newspaper=The New York Times|accessdate=2013-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Euro-Americans exposed to mascots are more likely to believe not only that stereotypes are true, but that Native Americans have no identity beyond these stereotypes.&lt;ref name="bias"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Chaney|first=John| title=Do American Indian Mascots = American Indian People? Examining Implicit Bias towards American Indian People and American Indian Mascots|work=American Indian and Alaska native mental health research |date=2011-01-01|volume=18(1)|page=42}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research also demonstrates the harm done to society by stereotyping of any kind. Two studies examined the effect of exposure to an American Indian sports mascot on the tendency to endorse stereotypes of a different minority group. A study was first done at the University of Illinois, and then replicated at The College of New Jersey with the same results. Students were given a paragraph to read about Chief Illiniwek adapted from the University of Illinois' official website; while the control group was given a description of an arts center. In both studies the students exposed to the sports mascot were more likely to express stereotypical views of Asian-Americans. Although Chief Illiniwek was described only in terms of positive characteristics (as a respectful symbol, not a mascot), the stereotyping of Asian-Americans included negative characteristics, such as being "socially inept". This was indicative of a spreading effect; exposure to any stereotypes increased the likelihood of stereotypical thinking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kim-Prieto|first=Chu|title=Effect of Exposure to an American Indian Mascot on the Tendency to Stereotype a Different Minority Group|journal=Journal of Applied Social Psychology|date=March 2010|volume=40|number=3|page=534|doi=10.1111/j.1559-1816.2010.00586.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/the-hidden-brain/201003/native-american-imagery-sports-mascots-new-problem|work=Psychology Today|title=Native American imagery as sports mascots: A new problem|date=March 25, 2010|first=Shankar|last=Vedantam|accessdate=February 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civil rights===
The [[NAACP]] passed a resolution calling for the end of the use of Native American names, images, and mascots in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aistm.org/naacp_1999_resolution.htm|title=NAACP 1999 Resolution|accessdate=2013-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, the [[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]] released an advisory opinion calling ''for an end to the use of Native American images and team names by non-Native schools.'' The opinion made the following points:
* The use of Native American images and nicknames in school is insensitive and should be avoided, and may violate anti-discrimination laws. 
*These references.. are particularly inappropriate and insensitive in light of the long history of forced assimilation that American Indian people have endured in this country.
*It is particularly disturbing that Native American references are still to be found in educational institutions ... where diverse groups of people come together to learn not only the "Three Rs," but also how to interact respectfully with people from different cultures.
*The use of stereotypical images may create a hostile  environment that may be intimidating to Indian students. American Indians have the lowest high school graduation rates in the nation and even lower college attendance and graduation rates. The perpetuation of harmful stereotypes may exacerbate these problems. 
*Schools that continue [these practices] claim that their use stimulates interest in Native American culture and honors Native Americans but have simply failed to listen to the Native groups, religious leaders, and civil rights organizations that oppose this behavior.
*Mascots, symbols and team names are not accurate representations of Native Americans. Even those that purport to be positive are romantic stereotypes that give a distorted view of the past. These false portrayals prevent non-Native Americans from understanding the true historical and cultural experiences of American Indians. Sadly, they also encourage biases and prejudices that have a negative effect on contemporary Indian people. These references may encourage interest in mythical "Indians" created by the dominant culture, but they block genuine understanding of contemporary Native people as fellow Americans.''&lt;ref name="usccr"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aistm.org/fr.usccr.htm |title=Statement of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights on the Use of Native American Images and Nicknames as Sports Symbols |publisher=The United States Commission on Civil Rights |date=April 13, 2001 |accessdate=2012-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2013 the State of Michigan Department of Civil Rights (MDCR) filed a complaint with the US Department of Education's Office of Civil Rights (OCR). MDCR's complaint asserts that new research clearly establishes that use of American Indian imagery negatively impacts student learning, creating an unequal learning environment in violation of Article VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964.&lt;ref name=MDCR&gt;{{cite web|title=Michigan Department of Civil Rights: Continued Use of American Indian Mascots Hurts Student Achievement|url=http://www.michigan.gov/mdcr/0,4613,7-138--294605--,00.html|publisher=State of Michigan|accessdate=23 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2013 the OCR dismissed the case on the basis that the legal standard required not only harm, but the intent to do harm, which was not established.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.freep.com/article/20130603/NEWS06/306030121/indian-mascot-ban-tossed-michigan|title=Feds toss Michigan complaint to ban Indian mascots for sports teams|date=June 3, 2013|newspaper=The Detroit Free Press|author=Lori Higgins|accessdate=June 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the schools named in the MDCR complaint, [[Saranac, Michigan|Saranac Community Schools]] in [[Ionia County]], MI plans to retain the name Redskins but has replaced the logo on its uniforms with a "[[Dreamcatcher]]" and the band will no longer play the "Tomahawk Song" at games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://woodtv.com/2014/09/18/saranac-schools-make-changes-to-mascot/|title=Saranac Schools Make Changes to Mascot|publisher=WoodTV.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a report issued in 2012, a [[United Nations]] expert on Human Rights of Indigenous Peoples cited the continued use of Native American references by sports team as a part of the stereotyping that "obscures understanding of the reality of Native Americans today and instead help to keep alive racially discriminatory attitudes.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=14497&amp;LangID=E|title=USA: ‘Redskins’ Team mascot hurtful reminder of past suffering of Native Americans – UN rights expert|publisher=United Nations Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Education and school board action===
In a 2005 report on the status of Native American students, the [[National Education Association]] included the elimination of Indian mascots and sports team names as one of its recommendations.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=A Report on the Status of American Indians and Alaska Natives in Education|first=|author=Trujillo,Octaviana (Ph.D.)|author2=Alston, Denise (Ph.D.)|year=2005|publisher=National Education Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Seattle-area Issaquah School District adopted a policy banning symbols based on racial stereotypes; resulting in a change of the [[Issaquah High School]] team from the "Indians" to the "Eagles" in 2003 over the protest of some students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.seattlepi.com/news/article/Issaquah-High-School-changes-mascot-1118097.php|title=Issaquah High School changes mascot|author=THE ASSOCIATED PRESS|date=June 26, 2003|accessdate=2014-01-06|publisher=Hearst Seattle Media, LLC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010 a law was passed in [[Wisconsin]] to eliminate race-based nicknames, logos and mascots in schools; but allowing retention if they have the permission of local Native American tribes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2010-10-06-kewaunee-school-mascot_N.htm | work=USA Today | first=Judy | last=Keen | title=Wis. law lets residents challenge race-based mascots | date=Oct 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2013 a bill passed the Wisconsin assembly that would make it more difficult to remove Indian mascots by requiring the complainant to collect signatures of 10% of the school district's population and prove discrimination. Under the 2010 law only one petitioner is needed, and the burden of proof is on the school to disprove racism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.twincities.com/politics/ci_24316907/wisconsin-assembly-approves-bill-protecting-indian-mascots?source=rss|title=Wisconsin Assembly approves bill protecting Indian mascots|author=Todd Richmond|publisher=Associated Press|date=2013-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wisconsin’s Chippewa tribes have urged the Governor to veto the bill,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://wislawjournal.com/2013/11/17/opponents-urge-walker-to-veto-mascots-bill/|title=Opponents urge Walker to veto mascots bill|date=November 17, 2013|author=Associated Press|publisher=Wisconsin Law Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although initially stating that he had no interest in the issue,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2013/11/29/scott-walker-has-nothing-to-do-with-native-american-mascot-fight.html|title=Scott Walker Has ‘Nothing to Do With’ Native American Mascot Fight|author=David Freedlander|date=November 29, 2013|publisher=The Daily Beast}}&lt;/ref&gt; Governor [[Scott Walker (politician)|Scott Walker]] signed the bill into law on December 19, 2013; also sending a letter to tribal leaders in the state citing free speech as a justification for allowing use of names and mascots many find offensive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://host.madison.com/news/local/writers/jessica_vanegeren/scott-walker-signs-indian-mascot-bill-informs-tribes-of-reasoning/article_fc764c8c-68e3-11e3-a8ec-0019bb2963f4.html|title=Scott Walker signs Indian mascot bill, informs tribes of reasoning in letter|date=December 19, 2013|author=JESSICA VANEGEREN|newspaper=The Capital Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Professors of Law and Journalism contest this interpretation of free speech, since citizens have the right to free speech but not schools which are government entities. The Wisconsin Interscholastic Athletic Association, which runs state sporting tournaments, already has a policy against spectator behavior or displays that are offensive, including ones based on race and national origin, bans that are similar to but less restrictive than NCAA rules.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://host.madison.com/wsj/print_only/columnist/article_6601209b-420d-5a69-adc5-885281d9e5f3.html|title=For opponents of race-based mascots, WIAA a tempting target|date=January 5, 2014|author=Chris Rickert|newspaper=Wisconsin State Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although now allowed to do so, some schools that have already made a change have decided not to restore their prior mascots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.northjersey.com/news/education/wis-high-school-won-t-bring-back-indian-mascot-1.669912l|title=Wisconsin high school won't bring back Mukwonago Indian mascot after fighting to keep it|author=DINESH RAMDE, Associated Press|date=February 1, 2014|publisher=NewJersey.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Addressing the Wisconsin legislature, Laurie Boivin, the [[Menominee]] Nation's new chairwoman criticized the new mascot law, saying the changes will damage native children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://cdcgamingreports.com/menominee-leader-criticizes-wis-school-mascot-law/|title=Menominee leader criticizes Wis. school mascot law|author=TODD RICHMOND|publisher=Associated Press|date=February 13, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 17, 2012, the Oregon State Board of Education voted 5-1 to adopt a rule prohibiting Oregon public schools from using Native American names, symbols, or images as school mascots. Schools have until July 1, 2017 to comply. Fifteen schools using the nicknames Indians, Warriors, Braves and Chieftains were affected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ode.state.or.us/search/page/?id=3575|title=State Board of Education Bans Use of Native American Mascots|publisher=Oregon State Department of Education|accessdate=February 10, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However Native American response was not unanimous; out of nine tribes, two voiced opposition to the statewide ban on the basis of tribal sovereignty. Leaders said that there might have been an opportunity for developing an educational program for all students to learn about true native culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/politics/index.ssf/2012/05/two_tribes_call_state_board_of.html|newspaper=The Oregonian|title=Two tribes call state's Native American mascot ban disappointing|date=May 22, 2012|first=Ryan|last=Kost|accessdate=2013-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of March, 2013, the Oregon legislature was considering bills that would modify the Board of Education's decision. One would allow for retention of a mascot or nickname with tribal approval, the other would remove the financial penalty for non-compliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.katu.com/politics/Lawmakers-could-change-Native-American-mascot-ban-200745601.html|title=Lawmakers could change Native American mascot ban|publisher=Associated Press|date=Mar 30, 2013|accessdate=2013-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bill that was passed was vetoed by Governor [[John Kitzhaber]] as being too broad, allowing most schools to retain their names and mascots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/politics/index.ssf/2013/08/kitzhaber_vetoes_native_americ.html|title=Kitzhaber vetoes Native American mascot bill, says he'll look for consensus bill in 2014|author=Christian Gaston|newspaper=The Oregonian|date=August 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014 a revised bill is expected to become law that would allow schools to keep Native American mascots under certain conditions, including the approval of an appropriate tribe and the Board of Education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://theworldlink.com/reedsport/news/gov-kitzhaber-changes-direction-on-school-mascots/article_a07c2f7e-98e4-11e3-8c68-0019bb2963f4.html|title=Gov. Kitzhaber changes direction on school mascots|date=February 19, 2014|author=Chad Garland, The Associated Press|newspaper=The Umpqua Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 26, 2012 the Washington State Board of Education (WSBE) passed a resolution calling for the end of Native American mascots in state schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/headlines/2012/09/washington-state-wants-schools-to-ban-native-american-mascots/|title=Washington State Wants Schools to Ban Native American Mascots|author=Abby Ellin|date=Sep 29, 2012|publisher=ABC News|accessdate=2013-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sbe.wa.gov/documents/2012.09.26%20Native%20American%20Mascots%20Resolution.pdf|title=2012 Native American Mascot Resolution|accessdate=2013-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Seattle Human Rights Commission passed a resolution supporting the WSBE in November, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattle.gov/HumanRights/Documents/SHRC_Resolution12-04NativeMascots.pdf|title=Resolution #12-4: Elimination of Native American Mascots|accessdate=2013-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December, 2013 the [[Houston Independent School District]] by unanimous vote passed a preliminary plan to eliminate all ethnically sensitive names and mascots, one of which is the [[Lamar High School (Houston, Texas)|Lamar High School]] Redskins. The Washington NFL team issued a statement repeating its position that such names are not offensive to many Native Americans, but rather are a source of pride.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://m.click2houston.com/news/houston-isd-votes-to-change-school-mascots/-/16714936/23463546/-/n5jf59z/-/index.html|title=Houston ISD votes to change school mascots|author=Troy Blevins|publisher=KPRC}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2014 the new team names were announced, including Lamar High School which will become the Texans, the Hamilton Middle School Indians will be the Huskies and Welch Middle School Warriors will be the Wolf Pack.&lt;ref name="Ericka Mellon"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chron.com/news/houston-texas/houston/article/New-HISD-mascots-Huskies-Wolf-Pack-Texans-5403772.php|title=New HISD mascots: Huskies, Wolf Pack, Texans|author=Ericka Mellon|date=April 15, 2014|newspaper=The Houston Chronicle}}&lt;/ref&gt; "The moral cost to our reputation as a diverse district -- where we care about the sensitivities of every single individual -- would be incalculable if we were not to do this," HISD superintendent Terry Grier said.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://msn.foxsports.com/southwest/story/houston-schools-change-historically-insensitive-mascots-041614?ocid=twmsn|title=Houston schools change 'historically insensitive' mascots|author=Louis Ojeda Jr.|publisher=FOX Sports Southwest|date=April 16, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There has been backlash, however. In response to the Tennessee Commission of Indian affairs seeking a similar ban though the Tennessee Human Rights Commission, the legislature passed a law allowing only elected officials (themselves) to take any action banning school teams using American Indian names and symbols.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesnews.net/article/3758873/tennessee-senate-approves-measure-that-would-protect-indian-mascots|title=Tennessee Senate approves measure that would protect Indian mascots|date=May 10, 2007|author=Hank Hayes}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religious organizations===
In 1992, the [[Central Conference of American Rabbis]] issued a resolution calling for the end of sports teams names that promote racism, in particular the Atlanta Braves and the Washington Redskins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ccarnet.org/rabbis-speak/resolutions/1992/racism-1992/|title=Resolution Adopted by the CCAR: Racism|year=1992|accessdate=September 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, the [[United Methodist Church]] also passed a resolution condemning the use of Native American team names and sports mascots, which was highlighted in a meeting of the Black caucus of that organization in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.umc.org/site/apps/nlnet/content3.aspx?c=lwL4KnN1LtH&amp;b=5765541&amp;ct=3722449|title=Black caucus joins Native American mascot fight|date=April 4, 2007|accessdate=September 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://umc-gbcs.org/faith-in-action/native-american-mascots-must-go|title= Native American mascots must go: Time to remove them is long passed|author=Rev. Chebon Kernell|date=April 5, 2011|accessdate=January 21, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;''A child once asked me why Indians were "mean." Where did he get that idea? By schools such as the [[Chief Illiniwek|University of Illinois]] "honoring" my ancestors?'' -- Rev. Alvin Deer (Kiowa/Creek), United Methodist Church &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://archives.umc.org/umns/news_archive2001.asp?ptid=&amp;story={B523D699-F44C-4D4E-818E-1BC26CC53821}&amp;mid=3365| title=Mascot issue raises specters of racism, idolatry| date=March 9, 2001| accessdate=October 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A group of sixty-one religious leaders in Washington, D.C. sent a letter to NFL Commissioner Roger Goodell and team owner Dan Snyder stating their moral obligation to join the Change the Mascot movement due to the offensive and inappropriate nature of the name which causes pain whether or not that is intended.&lt;ref name="faith"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://apps.washingtonpost.com/g/documents/local/letter-to-goodell-and-snyder/695/|title=Letter to Goodell and Snyder|newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/faith-leaders-urge-redskins-owner-dan-snyder-and-nfl-to-change-teams-name/2013/12/05/e1dad2be-5dd3-11e3-be07-006c776266ed_story.html|title=Faith leaders urge Redskins owner Dan Snyder and NFL to change team’s name|author=Theresa Vargas|date=December 5, 2013|newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a meeting March 1, 2014, the Board of Directors of the Central Atlantic Conference of the [[United Church of Christ]] (UCC) unanimously passed a resolution proposing that its members boycott Washington Redskins games and shun products bearing the team’s logo until the team changes its name and mascot. Team spokesman Tony Wyllie offered a response, saying, “We respect those who disagree with our team’s name, but we wish the United Church of Christ would listen to the voice of the overwhelming majority of Americans, including Native Americans, who support our name and understand it honors the heritage and tradition of the Native American community.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/churches-propose-a-boycott-of-redskins-unless-the-team-change-its-name/2014/03/01/488669bc-a189-11e3-b8d8-94577ff66b28_story.html|title=Churches propose a boycott of Redskins unless the team changes its name|author=Carol Morello|date=March 1, 2014|newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; At its annual meeting in June 2014, the membership of the UCC also passed a resolution supporting the boycott.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://nativenewsonline.net/currents/united-church-christ-central-atlantic-conference-passes-resolution-calling-washington-nfl-team-name-change-calls-member-boycott/|title=UCC Central Atlantic Conference Passes Resolution Calling for Washington NFL Team Name Change &amp; Calls for Member Boycott|date=June 15, 2014|publisher=Native News Online}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/nfl/redskins/2014/06/14/church-of-christ-boycott-washington-redskins-name/10524269/|title=Church group latest to boycott Redskins over name|author=Erik Brady|date=June 14, 2014|newspaper=USA Today}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{further|Stereotype|Stereotypes of Native Americans in North America}}

==Other issues regarding team names and ethnic groups==

Opponents also highlight the double standard of Native American being the only racial group depicted in sports.&lt;ref name="AICS"&gt;[http://www.aics.org/mascot/mascot.html Mascots - Racism in Schools by State], American Indian Cultural Support&lt;/ref&gt; The only current exception may be the [[Coachella Valley High School]] "Arabs"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2013/11/07/arab-team-mascot-ethnic-slur/3461059/|title=California high school's Arab mascot draws ire|date=November 7, 2013|accessdate=September 17, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; which has also been the subject of controversy, resulting in the retirement of its more cartoonish representations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.desertsun.com/story/news/education/2014/09/09/mighty-arab-coachella-valley-high/15368751/|title='Mighty Arab' takes its place at Coachella Valley High|author=Brett Kelman|newspaper=The Desert Sun|date=September 10, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of Notre Dame]] [[Notre Dame Fighting Irish|Fighting Irish]] and the [[University of Louisiana at Lafayette]]'s "[[Louisiana–Lafayette Ragin' Cajuns|Ragin' Cajuns]]" are sometimes cited as counterpoints to this argument.&lt;ref name=morgan&gt;{{cite news|last=Morgan|first=Ron|title=Red Scare: McCarthy had nothing on the PC police|url=http://www.corsicanadailysun.com/sports/article_b76efcf1-9d5b-5a45-92f4-d4e4e17cbbf5.html|accessdate=October 20, 2014|newspaper=Corsicana Daily Sun|date=11 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; These team names are exceptions in that they represent ethnic groups with an active stake in the organization, and the teams employ symbols that Euro-American cultures have historically used to represent themselves. The [[University of Notre Dame]] mascot, the [[Notre Dame Leprechaun|UND leprechaun]]&lt;ref name="ND"&gt;[http://und.cstv.com/trads/nd-m-fb-mas.html Notre Dame Fighting Irish - Traditions: The Leprechaun], University of Notre Dame Athletics&lt;/ref&gt; is a mythical being that represents the Irish, which is both an ethnic and a national group.&lt;ref name="fearson"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Fearon|first=James|title=Ethnic and Cultural Diversity by Country|journal=Journal of Economic Growth|year=2003|volume=8|issue=2|pages=195–222|url=https://web.stanford.edu/group/fearon-research/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Ethnic-and-Cultural-Diversity-by-Country.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Ibid''., Ireland has an ethnic fractionalization score of 0.171, meaning that there is only a 17.1% chance that two randomly selected people in Ireland will be from different ethnic groups.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Cayenne (mascot)|University of Louisiana at Lafayette mascot]] is an anthropomorphic [[Cayenne (mascot)|cayenne pepper]], an ingredient frequently found in [[Cajun cuisine]]. Opponents also see this argument as a false equivalency because it ignores systemic inequality and serves to discount the Native American voice by saying that if one group isn't hurt by a particular portrayal, then no group has the right to be hurt, regardless of vastly different backgrounds, treatment, and social positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thesocietypages.org/socimages/2008/10/05/notre-dames-fighting-irish-mascot|title=Sociological Images by Gwen Sharp}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]] has called for an end to the use of Native American mascots, but only by non-native schools.&lt;ref name=USCCR&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usccr.gov/press/archives/2001/041601st.htm |title=Statement of the United States Commission on Civil Rights on the use of Native American images and nicknames as sports symbols |accessdate=2007-10-21 |year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In cases where universities were founded to educate Native Americans, such mascots may not be examples of [[cultural appropriation]]. Examples include the [[Haskell Indian Nations Fighting Indians|Fighting Indians]] of the [[Haskell Indian Nations University]] and the [[University of North Carolina at Pembroke]], which continues to have a substantial number of native students, and close ties to the [[Lumbee]] tribe. Their nickname is the Braves, but the mascot is a [[red-tailed hawk]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uncp.edu/news/2005/braves_nickname.htm|title=NCAA: UNCP will keep the xBraves|date=August 9, 2005|accessdate=February 1, 2013|publisher=University of North Carolina at Pembroke}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mcac-naia.org/members.php Midlands Collegiate Athletic Conference] Members&lt;/ref&gt;  Pembroke Middle School, the former Pembroke Senior High School, team nickname is the Warriors.

==Trend toward the elimination of mascots==

===Colleges and universities===
[[Image:Ticket Washington vs Stanford 1930 side1.jpg|right|thumb|250px|1930 Football ticket stub depicting the former Stanford Indian mascot]]
Some college teams voluntarily changed their names and mascots. [[Stanford University]] had "The Stanford Indian" as its mascot from 1930 to 1972. Today "[[Stanford Cardinal]]" honors the university athletic team color. The mascot of the [[Stanford Band]] is the "[[Stanford Tree]]." Another early change was the "[[Saltine Warrior#Mascot|Saltine Warrior]]" that represented [[Syracuse University]] from 1931 until 1978. After a brief attempt to use a Roman warrior, the mascot became Otto the Orange for the school color.

[[Marquette University]] changed their team name from the Warriors to the Golden Eagles in 1994.  The school’s president stated:"We live in a different era than when the Warriors nickname was selected in 1954. The perspective of time has shown us that our actions, intended or not, can offend others. We must not knowingly act in a way that others will believe, based on their experience, to be an attack on their dignity as fellow human beings."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gomarquette.com/genrel/051105aaa.html|title=Trustees announce new nickname selection process|date=May 11, 2005|publisher=Marquette University|accessdate=January 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 1994, [[St. John's University (New York)]] changed the name of its athletic teams from the Redmen to the Red Storm after the university was pressured by American Indian groups who considered Redmen a slur.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1998/07/09/nyregion/use-of-indians-as-mascots-to-be-subject-of-an-inquiry.html|title=Use of Indians As Mascots To Be Subject Of an Inquiry|newspaper=The New York Times|date=July 9, 1998|accessdate=February 8, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Miami University]] began discussion regarding the propriety of the Redskins name and images in 1972, and changed its team nickname to [[Miami RedHawks|RedHawks]] in 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.miami.muohio.edu/about-miami/diversity/miami-tribe-relations/mascot-story/index.html|title=Mascot Story|accessdate=February 5, 2013|publisher=Miami University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 2002, The Strategic Planning Committee of [[Stonehill College]] determined that the then-current mascot, the chieftain, was disrespectful to American Indians and decided that it would be changed. After discussion, the mascot was changed to the Skyhawk in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stonehillskyhawks.com/Why_A_Skyhawk|title=Why a Skyhawk?|accessdate=October 20, 2014|publisher=Stonehill College}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Jim Seavey, associate director of athletics stated: ''Twelve years ago, the college discarded the logo that depicted the Indian with the headdress and feathers and stuff. We really did not have anything to represent our identity that we were comfortable with. We felt . . . that it wasn't appropriate to have a physical representation of a Native American as our mascot," &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2005/02/27/digging_for_new_name_sends_stonehill_to_web/|title=Digging for new name sends Stonehill to Web|first=Emily|last=Sweeney|date=February 27, 2005|newspaper=The Boston Globe|accessdate=January 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, teams that are not directly affected by this controversy have issued their opinions. The [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lssaa.wisc.edu/aisas/policy07.html|title=University Of Wisconsin Athletic Department Policy On Native American Logos And Names|accessdate=February 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[University of Iowa]] have both refused to schedule non-conference games against schools with Native American mascots. The University of Iowa's own nickname, "Hawkeyes", has Native American origins (Iowa is the "[[Hawkeye State]]"), although the team uses a [[hawk]] as its symbol rather than an Indian. The [[University of Oregon]], following the example set by ''[[The Oregonian]]'' newspaper, declined to refer to the [[University of Illinois]] team as the "Illini" in a basketball game in 2005.

[[Seattle University]] changed the nickname of their mascot from Chieftains to [[Seattle Redhawks|Redhawks]] in 2000.

In 2012, the [[University of California, Berkeley]] called for the student-run [[University of California Marching Band]] to discontinue performances of "[[California Indian Song]]" after complaints from alumni.  Currently, the Cal Band is attempting to rename the song and rewrite its lyrics.

====National Collegiate Athletic Association====
The [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] (NCAA), the ruling authority on college athletics, distributed a “self evaluation” to 31 colleges in 2005, for teams to examine the use of potentially offensive imagery with their mascot choice.&lt;ref name="Hosick.20050314"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fs.ncaa.org/Docs/NCAANewsArchive/2005/Association-wide/mascot%2Bmatter%2Bfits%2Binto%2Bproper-environment%2Bdiscussion%2B-%2B3-14-05%2Bncaa%2Bnews.html|title=Mascot matter fits into proper-environment discussion|date=March 14, 2005|first=Michelle|last=Brutlag Hosick|publisher=The NCAA News|accessdate=February 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently 19 teams were cited as having potentially "hostile or abusive" names, mascots, or images, that would be banned from displaying them during post-season play, and prohibited from hosting tournaments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://fs.ncaa.org/Docs/NCAANewsArchive/2005/Editorial/ncaa%2Bcorrectly%2Bpositioned%2Bas%2Ba%2Bcatalyst%2Bfor%2Bsocial%2Bchange%2B-%2B10-24-05%2Bncaa%2Bnews.html| title=NCAA correctly positioned as a catalyst for social change| date=October 24, 2005| first=Myles| last=Brand| publisher=National Collegiate Athletic Association| accessdate=January 16, 2013}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Since then, all of the colleges previously using the nickname ''Indians'' changed them; [[Arkansas State University]] to [[Red Wolves]], [[Indiana University of Pennsylvania]] to Crimson Hawks, [[McMurry University]] to [[War Hawks]], [[Midwestern State University]] to Mustangs, [[Newberry College]] to Wolves, [[University of Louisiana at Monroe]] to Warhawks, and [[Catawba College]] to Catawba Indians with approval of that tribe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=2463164|title=NCAA says Catawba College can use Indians nickname|date=May 30, 2006|accessdate=February 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[California State University, Stanislaus]] eliminated Native American references to their Warrior nickname, initially using a Warrior Hawk mascot which never caught on;&lt;ref name="Hosick.20050314" /&gt; it has been replaced by a Roman Warrior, Titus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.warriorathletics.com/|title=The Official Site of Cal State Stanislaus Athletics}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[College of William and Mary]] (W&amp;M) had previously changed from "Indians" to The Tribe, but was cited due to two feathers in its logo, which were removed. After a brief period of having the frog-like character [[Colonel Ebirt]] as its unofficial mascot, W&amp;M selected the [[Griffin (mascot)|Griffin]] in 2010. Both [[Alcorn State University]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://meacswacsports.blogspot.com/2011/04/bravehawk-chosen-as-new-mascot-at.html|date=April 25, 2011|title=Bravehawk chosen as new mascot at Alcorn State|accessdate=February 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Bradley University]] kept the nickname Braves but change their mascots, while the [[Chowan University]] Braves became the Hawks. The [[Carthage College]] Redmen became the Red Men, and the [[Southeastern Oklahoma State University]] Savages changed to Savage Storm.

The [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]] Fighting Illini kept the nickname as referring to the state, not Native Americans, but officially stopped using the [[Chief Illiniwek]] image and mascot in 2007, although an attachment remains among many students and alumni;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.news-gazette.com/news/business/entrepreneurs/2012-04-21/former-chiefs-create-new-logo.html|title=Former Chiefs create new logo|date=April 21, 2012| first=Julie|last=Wurth|newspaper=News-Gazette|accessdate=February 10, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://councilofchiefs.org/|title=The Tradition Continues|accessdate=March 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.news-gazette.com/news/local/2013-03-13/ui-student-vote-favors-chief-illiniwek.html| title=UI student vote favors Chief Illiniwek| date=March 13, 2013| author=Christine Des Garennes|newspaper=News-Gazette| accessdate=April 30, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://chicago.cbslocal.com/2013/05/07/wisch-return-of-chief-illiniwek-proposed-and-ignored/| title=Wisch: Return Of Chief Illiniwek Proposed – And Ignored?| date=May 7, 2013| author=Dave Wischnowsky| accessdate=October 18, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; but not all.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Illinois Students Say: It's Time To Let Chief Illiniwek Go| publisher=Urbana Champaign Independent Media Center| accessdate = 2014-10-21| url = http://www.ucimc.org/content/illinois-students-say-its-time-let-chief-illiniwek-go| author=Carol Scott}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The "Honor the Chief Society" filed an application with the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office in 2009 to register the Chief Illiniwek symbol, which the university opposed. In October, 2013 an agreement was reached that will allow limited private use of the name as long as accompanied by a disclaimer stating that the university is not involved in such use. A new chief cannot be named, and the university retains control of the name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2013-10-23/news/chi-u-of-i-works-out-deal-on-use-of-chief-illiniwek-20131023_1_chief-society-roger-huddleston-the-news-gazette| title=U. of I. works out deal on use of Chief Illiniwek| date=October 23, 2013| author=Jodi S. Cohen| newspaper=The Chicago Tribune| accessdate=November 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of North Dakota]] initially challenged the NCAA policy in court, but settled in 2007 when it was given three years to obtain consent from the Sioux tribes in the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ag.state.nd.us/ncaa/ncaa.htm|title=UND v. NCAA Lawsuit|publisher=North Dakota Attorney General|accessdate=February 24, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; When one tribe refused permission,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.grandforksherald.com/event/article/id/199066/|date=April 4, 2011|title=Plains tribes still oppose nicknames, logos|first=Chuck|last=Haga|newspaper=Grand Forks Herald|accessdate=February 24, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; the state Board of Higher Education proceeded with plans to eliminate the Fighting Sioux name and logo. In 2011 the State Legislature voted that the university should retain the name but in a 2012 referendum the voters decided to proceed with the change, which has been completed but no alternative nickname or logo has been selected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncaa.com/news/ncaa/2011-03-12/und-nickname-still-point-discussion|publisher=NCAA|title=UND nickname still point of discussion|author=The Associated Press|date=March 12, 2011|accessdate=February 3, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/college-sports/story/_/id/8045554/north-dakota-residents-vote-let-school-scrap-fighting-sioux-nickname|publisher=ESPN|title=UND OK to drop Fighting Sioux name|date=June 14, 2012|author=Associated Press|accessdate=February 3, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The NCAA has agreed to allow some of the logos to remain in the sports stadiums, while removing the larger and more obvious ones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/sports/2012/09/26/ncaa-agreement-permits-some-und-fighting-sioux-logos-to-remain/|title=Fighting Sioux Remains|date=September 26, 2012|accessdate=October 18, 2013|work=Fox News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additional legal cases have run their course, leaving the Fighting Sioux name and logo officially retired.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://blogs.mprnews.org/statewide/2013/05/is_the_fighting_sioux_nickname_battle_over/|title=Is the Fighting Sioux nickname battle over?|author=Dan Gunderson|date=May 30, 2013|publisher=Minnesota Public Radio}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Four additional colleges originally on the "hostile and abusive" list: [[Central Michigan University]] (Chippewas),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2005/09/06/mascot|title=
Two More Universities Off NCAA's Mascot List|date=September 6, 2005|author=Doug Lederman|publisher=Inside Higher Ed|accessdate=November 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Florida State University]] (Seminoles), [[Mississippi College]] (Choctaws)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://diverseeducation.com/article/5547/#|title=NCAA: Mississippi College Can Keep Choctaws Nickname|date=February 23, 2006|author=Associated Press|accessdate=November 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[University of Utah]] ([[Utah Utes|Utes]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=2149907|title=NCAA takes Utah off banned mascots list|date=September 3, 2005|author=Associated Press|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=November 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; were granted waivers to retain their nicknames after gaining support from those respective tribes.

''See: [[Native_American_mascot_controversy#Colleges_and_universities_2|College Name/Mascots Changes]] for a full listing.''

===High schools===
High schools in both the US and Canada have had histories similar to colleges, some making voluntary changes while others resisting.

The Department of Educational Foundations at the [[University of Saskatchewan]] passed a resolution calling for the retirement of all school mascots and logos that depict First Nations people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ctvnews.ca/canada/staff-at-saskatchewan-university-calls-for-end-of-first-nations-logos-mascots-1.1546812|title=Staff at Saskatchewan university calls for end of First Nations logos, mascots|publisher=CTVNews.ca|date=November 16, 2013|accessdate=January 14, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2014 the [[Nez Perce people|Nez Perce Tribal Executive Committee]] sent a letter to two northern Idaho school districts with American Indian mascots asking that they be changed. The mascots are the Sacajawea Junior High Braves in [[Lewiston School District|Lewiston]] and the [[Nezperce, Idaho|Nezperce]] High School Indians. The school officials state that they will have meetings and gather public opinions before making a decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sltrib.com/sltrib/world/57451183-68/board-district-lewiston-mascot.html.csp|title= At request of American Indians, Idaho schools eye mascot name change|author=The Associated Press|date=January 26, 2014|publisher=The Salt Lake Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The students of [[Belmont High School (New Hampshire)]] have begun to question the use of Native American imagery in connection to their name, the Red Raiders, saying that while it was never intended to be offensive it is time for a change. At a meeting on the subject there were equal, but respectful comments of both sides.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.unionleader.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20140416/SPORTS21/140419211/1006/NEWS03|date=April 16, 2014|title=Students say they want to change the face of Belmont mascot|author=Dan Seufert|newspaper=New Hampshire Union Leader}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Turners Falls High School of Turners Falls, MA changed its fight song, known as the tomahawk chop, but did not change its name, the Indians. [[Blacksburg High School]] in Blacksburg, VA changed their mascot from the Indians to the Bruins, and the corresponding middle school mascot of the Braves was changed to the Titans.

[[Savannah High School (Missouri)]] has been criticized for their mascot, Savannah Savages.

[[The Dalles High School]] in The Dalles, Oregon will become the Riverhawks for Fall 2014 after being the "Indian Eagles" since 2000 after the merger of two schools. Although the Oregon legislature has allowed high schools to retain native mascots with the approval of a local tribe, the North Wasco County School District Superintendent Candy Armstrong states that, with 48 tribes in the area, “We thought [working with one] might not cause harmony but create more issues.”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://highschoolsports.oregonlive.com/news/article/-3668039736778055308/the-dalles-becomes-latest-oregon-school-to-drop-native-american-mascot/|title=The Dalles becomes latest Oregon school to drop Native American mascot|author=Jerry Ulmer|date=August 29, 2014|publisher=The Oregonian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

State lawmakers in Colorado are considering a bill that would deny state funding to schools on a case by case basis, depending upon the name, logo, and local Native American support. Names such as "Savages" and cartoon caricature logos would likely be targeted while more respectful usage might not.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://denver.cbslocal.com/2014/09/11/state-funding-center-school-mascot-controversy/|title=State Funding At Center Of School Mascot Controversy|date=September 11, 2014|publisher=CBS Denver}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December, 2013 the Houston, TX school district approved, in a preliminary vote, a new policy against any ethic mascots which would require a change for several schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.houstonchronicle.com/news/houston-texas/houston/article/Sensitivity-concerns-nudge-HISD-toward-new-mascots-5042804.php?t=31d9bb704e&amp;t=31d9bb704e33885cdd|title=Sensitivity concerns nudge HISD toward new mascots| author=Dug Begley| date=December 7, 2013| newspaper=The Houston Chronicle}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/sns-rt-us-usa-texas-redskins-20131212,0,4176024.story|title=Houston school board votes to stop using Native American mascot names|author=Andrea Lorenz|date=December 12, 2013|newspaper=The Chicago Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April, 2014 the schools effected by the policy announced new names: the [[Lamar High School (Houston, Texas)|Lamar High School]] Redskins will become the Texans, both the Hamilton Middle School Indians and [[Westbury High School (Houston, Texas)|Westbury High School]] Rebels will be the Huskies and the Welch Middle School Warriors will be the Wolf Pack. The initial cost of the change was $50,000 for new fall uniforms, and there will be additional costs such as changing names and logos on facilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://america.aljazeera.com/articles/2014/4/16/new-mascots-revealedforfourhoustonisdschools.html|title=Houston school district abandons mascots offensive to Native Americans|author=Dexter Mullins|date=April 16, 2014|publisher=Aljazeera America}}&lt;/ref&gt; The total cost is estimated to be $250,000.&lt;ref name="Ericka Mellon"/&gt; However it was noted that team uniforms are periodically replaced anyway, so the cost is not due only to the name changes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://offthekuff.com/wp/?p=60032|title=HISD unveils new mascots|date=April 17, 2014|author=Charles Kuffner}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A member of the [[Council of the District of Columbia]] has introduced a bill that would amend the city's Human Rights Act to prohibit any "race-based nickname, logo, mascot or team name" in DC schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/mike-debonis/wp/2014/09/23/d-c-council-bill-could-force-city-schools-to-drop-indians-or-warriors-mascots/|title=D.C. Council bill could force city schools to drop ‘Indians’ or ‘Warriors’ mascots|author=Mike DeBonis|date=September 23, 2014|newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Redskins/Redmen====
High Schools with the name Redskins have received particular attention due to the media coverage of the Washington NFL team, in particular three which have a majority of Native American students. As of early 2013 the Capitol News Service in Maryland listed twenty-eight high schools in 18 states that had dropped the "redskins" name during the prior 25 years as a result of a combination of state legal action, protests from Native American groups, or voluntarily; while 62 continue to use the redskins name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://cnsmaryland.org/interactives/other-redskins/#aboutproject|title=The Other Redskins|publisher=Capitol News Service|accessdate=June 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since that list was compiled, an additional four high school teams have changed their name. In addition of the Lamar HS in Houston, Texas cited above, there were:

The Cooperstown Central School Board of Education (NY) voted 6-1 on March 6, 2013 to remove the Redskins mascot from its interscholastic athletic, extracurricular and academic programs. The move was prompted by a vote by the student body, asking that the mascot be changed. The Oneida Indian Nation was so moved by the actions of the Cooperstown students, that a letter by Oneida Nation Representative Ray Halbritter was written to the students, commending their decision and offering to make a contribution to help offset the cost of changing mascots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oneidaindiannation.com/pressroom/latestnews/Oneida-Indian-Nation-Congratulates-Cooperstown-Central-School-Board-for-Voting-to-Remove-Redskins-Mascot-196067191.html|title=Oneida Indian Nation Congratulates Cooperstown Central School Board for Voting to Remove Redskins Mascot|date=March 7, 2013|accessdate=March 14, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2013 administrators of a high school in Driggs, Idaho announced that it will drop its longtime "Redskins" nickname, logo and mascot to show respect for Native Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| title = Idaho High School Drops Redskins Logo, Mascot| work = Huffington Post| accessdate = 2014-10-21| date = 2013-06-12| url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/06/12/teton-redskins-logo_n_3430496.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 24, 2013 school board members of the [[Port Townsend High School]] in Port Townsend, Washington voted to replace its "Redskins" nickname, logo, and mascot (used since 1926) due to its divisive nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.peninsuladailynews.com/article/20130625/NEWS/130629988/redskins-dropped-as-team-name-and-mascot-for-port-townsend-high|title='Redskins' dropped as team name and mascot for Port Townsend High School|author=Charlie Bermant|newspaper=Peninsula Daily News|date=June 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2014 the students selected Red Hawks as their new team name. The next step will be to select new graphics to replace the old.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.peninsuladailynews.com/article/20140410/news/304109981/port-townsend-students-pick-red-hawks-as-high-school-8217-s-new|title=Port Townsend students pick Red Hawks as high school’s new mascot|author=Charlie Bermant|date=April 10, 2014|newspaper=Peninsula Daily News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior changes include:
*[[Naperville Central High School]] in Illinois became the Redhawks in 1992 after being the Redskins since 1939. Twenty years later alumni retained an attachment to the old name, but most think the change was a good one.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://posttrib.suntimes.com/search/13987383-418/20-years-later-redskins-still-special-for-many-central-grads.html#.VDWq3OcUp8a| title=20 years later, Redskins still special for many Central grads|author=Bob Chiarito| date=July 26, 2012| newspaper=Post-Tribune|accessdate=October 8, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*[[Frontier Regional School]], in [[Deerfield, Massachusetts|Deerfield]], [[Massachusetts|MA]] removed its [[Redskin (slang)|Redskin]] mascot in 2000. The school now goes by the moniker of the [[Red-tailed hawk|Redhawks]].  
*Mountain Empire High School in [[Pine Valley, CA]] changed their mascot from the Redskins to the Red Hawks in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Vargas |first=Nicole |url=http://www.utsandiego.com/uniontrib/20050927/news_1s27p-preptu.html |title=Tradition meets political correctness |newspaper=The San Diego Union-Tribune |date=2005-09-27 |accessdate=December 18, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Brebeuf College School]] in [[North York]] changed its nickname to "Bulls" in 2004 after being called "Redmen" since 1963.
*[[David and Mary Thomson Collegiate Institute]] in [[Scarborough, Ontario]] had been the "Redmen" since 1959, which was changed to the  "Titans" in 2005. 
*The Regional School Unit 12 board of directors voted in 2011 that Wiscasset High School in Maine would no longer be the "Redskins", later becoming the Wolverines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://bangordailynews.com/2011/03/19/news/divided-rsu-12-board-allows-wiscasset-high-to-use-%E2%80%98redskins%E2%80%99-mascot-through-end-of-school-year/?ref=search|title=Wiscasset High to keep ‘Redskins’ mascot through end of school year|author=Seth Koenig|date=March 19, 2011|newspaper=Bangor Daily News}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August, 2014 selectmen of the town of Wiscasset voted to name a private road "Redskins Drive" as an indication of their continued attachment to the name of the school.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://bangordailynews.com/2014/08/26/opinion/editorials/wiscasset-moving-backward-redskins-name-not-appropriate/?ref=moreInopinion|title=Wiscasset moving backward; Redskin’s name not appropriate|date=August 26, 2014|newspaper=Bangor Daily News}}&lt;/ref&gt; However following weeks of criticism by members of Maine’s Indian tribes and others, the Wiscasset Board of Selectmen changed the name again, to Micmac Drive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://bangordailynews.com/2014/10/08/news/midcoast/wiscasset-selectmen-approve-request-to-change-offensive-road-name/?ref=moreInmidcoast|title=Wiscasset selectmen approve request to change offensive road name| author=Beth Brogan| newspaper= Bangor Daily News| date=October 8, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the other hand, [[Union Public Schools|Union High School]] in [[Tulsa, Oklahoma]], a high-profile high school athletic program,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.tulsaworld.com/sports/article.aspx?subjectid=227&amp;articleid=20090706_298_0_Unionf830726| title=Sports Illustrated names Tulsa's Union on list of top athletic programs"| newspaper=[[Tulsa World]]| date=July 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; has consistently opposed protests and proposed legislation intended to change its "Redskins" nickname.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| author=Randy Krehbiel| url=http://www.tulsaworld.com/sportsextra/union-redskins-have-no-plans-to-change-name/article_62594bd2-64cc-5ed9-828a-e9d5faa8c18b.html| title=Union Redskins have no plans to change name| newspaper=[[Tulsa World]]| date=October 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Controversy over the name and logo of the [[Bedford Road Collegiate]] "Redmen" in [[Saskatoon]], Saskatchewan began in the 1990s, with a vote by students in 1996 choosing to keep things as they are. One alumni of the school is using social media to advocate for a change.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/saskatchewan/redmen-team-name-irks-saskatoon-high-school-graduate-1.1041412|title=Redmen team name irks Saskatoon high school graduate |publisher=[[CBC News]] |date=September 22, 2011 |accessdate=October 14, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, a group of protestors of the name and logo where blocked from entering a high school basketball tournament at Bedford Road, the school and police citing safety concerns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/saskatchewan/protest-about-redmen-thwarted-at-saskatoon-high-school-1.1395601 |title=Protest about 'Redmen' thwarted at Saskatoon high school |publisher=[[CBC News]] |date=January 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2014, the Saskatoon public school board passed a motion to have the school drop the name "Redmen" and use a new name by the beginning of the new school year in September.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/saskatoon/change-bedford-road-redmen-name-school-board-says-1.2560182 |title = Change Bedford Road Redmen name, school board says |publisher = [[CBC News]] |date = March 4, 2014 |accessdate = March 5, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Ontario, there is debate over the [[Thorold Blackhawks]] junior hockey team and the [[Denis Morris Catholic High School]] "Redmen".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.niagarafallsreview.ca/2013/12/16/sensitivity-needed-in-thorold-team-logo-flap|title=Mascot debate should inspire change of thinking|date=December 17, 2013|author=Andrew Conte|publisher=Niagara Falls Review}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Natick High School]] in [[Natick, Massachusetts]] was also the Redmen. An initial vote by the school committee to change the name was in 2007, prompting the formation of a "Redmen Forever" committee by alumni of the school.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://redmenforever.org/index.html|title=Redmen Forever|accessdate=March 9, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of their activity, including a nonbinding town referendum in which 65% of the voters supported asking the school committee to reconsider the change, the name was dropped in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/bostonglobe/regional_editions/globe_west/west/2008/06/natick_dumps_re.html|title=Natick dumps Redmen nickname|author=David Dahl|date=June 17, 2008|newspaper=The Boston Glob|accessdate=March 9, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The school team is now the Redhawks,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.natickps.org/NatickHigh/Athletics/Main.cfm|title=Natick Public Schools|accessdate=March 9, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; however some continue to favor returning to the previous name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.facebook.com/pages/Natick-Redmen-Fan-Page/181380115242363|title=Natick Redmen Fan Page|accessdate=March 9, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, the [[Western Canada High School]] in [[Calgary, Canada]] has decided to change its "Redmen" nickname and logo with strong support from the school's administration, students and parents for the decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/calgary/calgary-high-school-to-change-redmen-team-name-1.2562922|title=Calgary high school to change 'Redmen' team name|publisher=CBC News Posted|date=March 6, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.calgaryherald.com/sports/Western+Canada+High+School+searches+name+logo/9588899/story.html|title=Western Canada High School searches for new name and logo: Redmen deemed inappropriate|author=Annalise Klingbeil|newspaper=Calgary Herald|date=March 6, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After failing in her appeals directly to [[Neshaminy High School]], a parent filed a complaint with the Pennsylvania Human Relations Commission alleging the "Redskins" name is a form of harassment offensive to Native Americans and her 13-year-old son who attends the school. The school board unanimously voted to ask the commission to dismiss the complaint,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.myfoxphilly.com/story/23785675/parent-asks-school-to-change-mascot-name|title=Parent Asks School To Change Mascot Name|date=October 25, 2013|author=Omari Fleming|publisher=Fox News}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the editors of the student newspaper, the Playwickian, voted to stop using the name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.mcall.com/2013-10-25/news/mc-pa-neshaminy-school-redskin-controversy-20131025_1_student-newspaper-native-americans-editorial|title=Student newspaper to stop using school's 'Redskin' nickname|date=October 25, 2013|author=Christian Menno|newspaper=The Morning Call}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the principal and the school board president have decided that the student newspaper's editorial board does not have the right to refuse to use the name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://indiancountrytodaymedianetwork.com/2013/11/15/neshaminy-high-school-152276|title=Neshaminy High School’s Editorial Board Challenged on Nixing ‘Redskins’|date=November 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The school board reached a compromise policy in which the name would not be entirely banned, but allowed in editorials and letters to the editor; however the editors of the paper and their attorney maintain that this policy is contrary to state law and the US Constitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.buckscountycouriertimes.com/news/local/neshaminy-board-passes-controversial-playwickian-policy/article_0f94aa14-3749-586c-930a-7d2e8c91ff78.html|title=Neshaminy board passes controversial Playwickian policy|date=June 26, 2014|author=MICHAEL MACAGNONE|newspaper=The Bucks County Courier Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both the student editor and the faculty adviser for the paper were suspended for two days by the school district supervisor for not printing the name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.splc.org/article/2014/09/playwickian-adviser-student-editor-suspended-for-redskins-ban|title=Playwickian adviser, student editor suspended for defying administrative orders with Redskins ban|author=Anna Schiffbauer|date=September 17, 2014|publisher=Student Press Law Center}}&lt;/ref&gt; The faculty adviser, Tara Huber was recently named Journalism Teacher of the Year by the Pennsylvania School Press Association. The Playwickian journalists will be honored by the ACLU on October 8, 2014, receiving be one of four Civil Libertarian Awards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.philly.com/philly/news/local/20140910_Neshaminy_journalists_to_be_honored_by_ACLU.html|title=Neshaminy journalists to be honored by ACLU|date=September 10, 2014|publisher=Philly.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Youth leagues===
In addition to schools, there are many teams for young players using Native American names that participate in [[Little league baseball]] and [[Pop Warner Little Scholars]] football as well as other youth leagues.

Ian Champeau, an [[Ojibway]] man in Ottawa, Ontario filed a human rights complaint against the Nepean Redskins Football Club on behalf of his five-year-old daughter in an effort to get the team to change its name. “How are they going to differentiate the playing field from the school yard? What’s going to stop them from calling my daughter a redskin in the school yard? That’s as offensive as using the n-word.” [[Assembly of First Nations]] National Chief Shawn A-in-chut Atleo said he supports the move because the word Redskin is “offensive and hurtful and completely inappropriate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.ca/2013/09/04/redskins-human-rights-complaint-a-tribe-called-red_n_3866220.html|title=Nepean Redskins Human Rights Complaint: A Tribe Called Red Member Takes Football To Tribunal| publisher=HuffPost Canada Music| author=Jason MacNeil| date=September 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Niigaan Sinclair ([[Anishinaabe]]), a writer and assistant professor at the [[University of Manitoba]] applauds the decision and contrasts it to the decision of Dan Snyder, the Washington team owner. Citing the combination of the stereotype of the Indian with sports in the early twentieth century: "The marriage of the Sioux-like warrior name and image to sports was complete, celebrating and re-telling American violence against indigenous communities every time one appears on sports highlights. It's tough to change abusive relationships."  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.winnipegfreepress.com/breakingnews/no-honour-in-native-names-238687531.html|title=No 'honour' in native names|author=Niigaan Sinclair|date=January 4, 2014|newspaper=Winnipeg Free Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team was changed to the "Nepean Eagles", chosen from 70 suggestions submitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sunnewsnetwork.ca/sunnews/sports/archives/2014/01/20140114-112929.html|title=Nepean Redskins says changing its 'controversial' name to cost about $100Gs|date=January 14, 2014|publisher=Sun News}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

A name of a team in a youth football league in Brooklyn, New York was changed from the Redskins to the Bears after some parents made complaints.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/sports/football/brooklyn-youth-football-team-drops-redskins-article-1.1911532|title=Brooklyn youth football team drops 'Redskins' name in response to parents' complaints| author=Bill Hutchinson| newspaper=NEW YORK DAILY NEWS| date=August 21, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other youth leagues contacted by the media to comment about the use of the Redskins name did not respond officially, however one parent of a player on a team in Leesburg, Virginia stated "...the name is a part of football history and tradition. I don't believe it is meant to be derogatory."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.si.com/nfl/2014/10/02/washington-redskins-nickname-change|title=Youth leagues also wrestling with controversial Redskins nickname|author=Sarah Barshop| publisher=Sports Illustrated| date=October 2, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Professional teams===
None of the [[National Basketball Association]] (NBA) teams that previously used Native American mascots continue to do so. The [[Atlanta Hawks]] were originally the Buffalo Bison, then the Tri-City Blackhawks (using an "Indian" logo)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.sportsecyclopedia.com/nba/tri/tricities.html| title=Tri-Cities Blackhawks (1946-1951)| accessdate=November 14, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; before becoming the Hawks in Milwaukee and St. Louis. The former [[Buffalo Braves]] relocated to San Diego, and are now the [[Los Angeles Clippers]]. 

The [[Golden State Warriors]], originally Philadelphia Warriors, then San Francisco Warriors, eliminated Native American imagery in 1971.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nba.com/history/uniforms_warriors.html|title=Going Retro: Golden State Warriors|publisher=NBA|accessdate=February 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since that time, their logos have emphasized the state of California, with their current primary logo depicting the [[Eastern span replacement of the San Francisco–Oakland Bay Bridge|new eastern span]] of the [[San Francisco–Oakland Bay Bridge]]. The warrior depicted on secondary logos of the team is a generic, lightning-wielding figure.
====Atlanta Braves====
The [[Atlanta Braves]] remain the home of the tomahawk chop (although it began at FSU).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://m.mlb.com/atl/video/v21042257/this-is-why-we-chop-the-history-of-the-tomahawk-chop|title=The history of the tomahawk chop| accessdate=October 21, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the mascot [[Chief Noc-A-Homa]] has been replaced in 1986.

====Chicago Blackhawks====
The NHL's [[Chicago Blackhawks]] use an [[NHL mascots#Tommyhawk|anthropomorphic hawk]] as their mascot character; although, a Native American's profile appears on their jerseys and the team was named in honor of the [[Frederic McLaughlin|team's founder]]'s [[U.S. 86th Infantry Division|military unit]], which was named the "Blackhawk Division" after [[Black Hawk (chief)|Black Hawk]], a Native American chief.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://chicago.cbslocal.com/2013/06/17/baffoe-should-the-blackhawks-ditch-their-indian-head-logo/|title=Should The Blackhawks Ditch Their Indian Head Logo?|author=Tim Baffoe|date=2013-06-17|publisher=CBS Chicago}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Cleveland Indians====
The [[Chief Wahoo]] logo of the [[Cleveland Indians#Nickname and logo controversy|Cleveland Indians]] was replaced with a block letter "C" or script "I" in many situations, such as on their caps and batting helmets.&lt;ref name="wahoo"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/blog/sweetspot/post/_/id/10856/cap-week-time-to-retire-chief-wahoo|title=Time to retire Chief Wahoo|date=May 13, 2011|first=Stephanie|last=Liscio|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=February 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of 2014, a decision was made to make the block "C" the team's primary logo—although Chief Wahoo will not disappear entirely—and some see this as a first step toward inevitable elimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.yahoo.com/blogs/mlb-big-league-stew/cleveland-indians-marginalize-chief-wahoo-logo-081024357--mlb.html|title=Cleveland Indians demote Chief Wahoo logo|author=David Brown|publisher=Yahoo Sports|date=January 9, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; A variety of responses to the issue has emerged from the Cleveland fanbase. Some fans have removed Chief Wahoo logos from purchased apparel, an outcome that is being termed "de-chiefing".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://espn.go.com/mlb/story/_/id/10715887/uni-watch-some-fans-removing-chief-wahoo-logos-protest|title=Hail To De-Chiefing|date=April 2, 2014|author=Paul Lukas|publisher=ESPN.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Blogger Peter Pattakos captured a photograph on April 4, 2014 outside a Cleveland Indians game which depicts a discussion between activist [[Robert Roche]] of the American Indian Movement and a sports fan costumed as the team mascot Chief Wahoo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://m.nbcsports.com/content/story-behind-awkward-chief-wahoo-confrontation-progressive-field-opening-day| last1=Calcaterra|first1=Craig|title=The story behind that awkward Chief Wahoo confrontation at Progressive Field on Opening Day|accessdate=5 August 2014|work=Hardball Talk|publisher=NBC Sports|date=April 7, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.clevelandfrowns.com/2014/04/redface-has-another-big-day-at-the-ballpark-in-cleveland/|title=Redface has another big day at the ballpark in Cleveland|author=Peter Pattakos|publisher=Cleveland Frowns|date=April 6, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; One reader's comments on press reports of the event led to a comparison with an "But I'm honoring you, dude!" editorial cartoon from 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://thelede.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/04/08/an-editorial-cartoon-on-native-american-mascots-comes-to-life-in-cleveland/?_php=true&amp;_type=blogs&amp;ref=robertmackey&amp;_r=0|title=An Editorial Cartoon on Native American Mascots Comes to Life in Cleveland|author=Robert Mackey|date=April 8, 2014|work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; An advocate for replacing Chief Wahoo makes the connection between the logo and fans wearing redface, beating a tom-tom, and other stereotypical "Indian" behavior that would not be acceptable toward any other ethnic group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hudsonhubtimes.com/opinion/2014/01/19/smoke-signals-should-cleveland-indians-mascot-chief-wahoo-get-the-ax|title=Smoke Signals: Should Cleveland Indians mascot 'Chief Wahoo' get the ax?|author=Tim Troglen|date=January 19, 2014|publisher=Hudson Hub-Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;
	 
One Native American group asked [[Nike, Inc.]] to cease production of any items displaying the Chief Wahoo logo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2014/apr/29/native-americans-pressing-nike-to-ax-chief-wahoo/?page=all|title=Native Americans pressing Nike to ax Chief Wahoo|author=Gosia Wozniacka|publisher=Associated Press|date=April 29, 2014|newspaper=The Washington Times| accessdate=October 21, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nike responded to the request by issuing a statement that it is bound by a contractual agreement with Major League Baseball (MLB) to manufacture apparel, and each MLB team is responsible for the logos they choose.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bizjournals.com/portland/blog/threads_and_laces/2014/05/nike-responds-to-chief-wahoo-protest.html?page=all|date=May 2, 2014|title=Nike responds to Chief Wahoo protest|author=Matthew Kish|publisher=Portland Business Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt; MLB Commissioner [[Bud Selig]] says that he has never received a complaint about the logo. He has heard that there are some protesting mascots, but individual teams such as the Indians and Braves should make their own decisions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://ftw.usatoday.com/2014/07/bud-selig-chief-wahoo|title=Selig claims he's received no complaints over Cleveland Indians' logo|author=Erik Brady|date=July 15, 2014|newspaper=USA Today}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Edmonton Eskimos====
The [[Edmonton Eskimos]] is an exceptional case, given that the only stereotypical element appears to be the name of one of their mascots, Nanook, a polar bear. The name Eskimo originated as a word used by the Cree to refer to the Inuit, who are few in the Edmonton area, and are ambivalent or supportive of the team name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ottawacitizen.com/sports/Time+rethink+name+Edmonton+Eskimos/8967574/story.html|title=Time to rethink the name "Edmonton Eskimos"|author=Tim Querengesser|newspaper=Ottawa Citizen|date=September 27, 2013}}{{dead|date=October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; A notable Inuk who openly supported the team name was former Edmonton Eskimo player Dave Ward.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/business/washington-redskins-fight-could-put-pressure-on-edmonton-eskimos-1.2680161|title=Washington Redskins fight could put pressure on Edmonton Eskimos|author=Matt Kwong|newspaper=cbc.ca|date=June 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Kansas City Chiefs====
In 1963 the [[Kansas City Chiefs]] became the last professional team to adopt a name referring to Native Americans, when the Dallas Texans (AFL) relocated.

In 1989 the Kansas City Chiefs switched from [[Warpaint (mascot)|Warpaint]], a Pinto horse ridden by a man in a feathered headdress, to their current mascot [[K. C. Wolf]]. Warpaint returned in 2009, but is ridden by a cheerleader.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kcchiefs.com/cheerleaders/warpaint.html|title=Warpaint|publisher=Kansas City Chiefs|accessdate=November 13, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the appearance of photographs of fans attending an October 2013 game wearing feathers and warpaint—and doing the tomahawk chop—in the ''[[Kansas City Star]]'', numerous Native Americans submitted complaints to the publication. One caller, who was especially upset that the photographs were published on [[Columbus Day]], described the images as a "mockery" and "racist". Writing for the ''Star'''s "Public Editor" column, Derek Donovan explained that he found the complaints "reasonable" and suggested that the newspaper depict "other colorful, interesting people in the crowds."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.kansascity.com/2013/10/27/4577055/fans-indian-dress-is-problematic.html|title=Chiefs fans’ ‘Indian’ dress is problematic|date=October 27, 2013|author=DEREK DONOVAN|newspaper=The Kansas City Star}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Kansas City Star'' reported in early August 2014 that the team's management is planning discussions with some Native American groups to find a non-confrontational way to eliminate, or at least reduce, offensive behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.kansascity.com/sports/spt-columns-blogs/sam-mellinger/article1161612.html|title= To avoid a cultural free-for-all, Chiefs form alliance with American Indian groups|author=SAM MELLINGER|newspaper=The Kansas City Star|date=August 6, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amanda Blackhorse, the lead plaintiff in the trademark case against the Washington Redskins, thinks the real solution is a name change for the Chiefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.kansascity.com/sports/spt-columns-blogs/sam-mellinger/article618354.html|title= Woman behind fight against Washington’s NFL nickname says Chiefs should be on guard|author=SAM MELLINGER|newspaper=The Kansas City Star|date=June 25, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Washington Redskins====
{{main|Washington Redskins name controversy}}
{{further|Redskin (slang)}}
The name and logo of the Washington Redskins is part of the larger controversy but receives the most public attention due to the prominence of the team being located in the [[Washington, D.C.|nation's capital]] and the name itself being defined in current dictionaries of American English as "usually offensive",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/redskin|title=Definition of REDSKIN|publisher=Merriam-Webster| quote=Definition of REDSKIN (usually offensive):  american indian| accessdate=November 7, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; "disparaging",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://ahdictionary.com/word/search.html?q=redskin| title=The American Heritage® Dictionary of the English Language, Fifth Edition| year=2011| publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt Publishing Company| quote=n. ''Offensive Slang'' Used as a disparaging term for a Native American.| accessdate=November 7, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/redskin|title=Redskin|publisher=Dictionary.com| quote=noun, ''Slang: Often Disparaging and Offensive.'' 1. a North American Indian.| accessdate=November 7, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; "insulting",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kdictionaries-online.com/DictionaryPage.aspx?ApplicationCode=18#&amp;&amp;DictionaryEntry=redskin&amp;SearchMode=Entry|title=definition of redskin|publisher=RANDOM HOUSE KERNERMAN WEBSTER'S College Dictionary| accessdate=November 7, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and "taboo".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/redskin?|title=Definition of redskin|publisher=Collins English Dictionary}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those officially censuring and/or demanding the name be changed include more than 80 organizations that represent various groups of Native Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.changethemascot.org/supporters-of-change/| title=Supporters of Change| accessdate=November 13, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The team's unofficial mascot is Zema Williams ([[Chief Zee]]), an African-American man who began attending games in 1978, wearing an Indian costume consisting of a feathered headdress and rubber tomahawk. Other fans also attend games in costume and are celebrated by the team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/dc-sports-bog/wp/2012/12/11/redskins-fan-gives-himself-an-indian-name-gets-deangelo-halls-helmet/|title=Redskins fan gives himself an Indian name, gets DeAngelo Hall’s helmet|first=Sarah|last=Kogod|date=December 11, 2012|newspaper=The Washington Post|accessdate=January 23, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:ChiefZee1.jpg|thumb|right|[[Chief Zee]] with fans]]

Native American opposition to the name began in the early 1970s with letters to the owner of the team&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/fred-hiatt-moving-beyond-the-imaginary-indians-perception/2014/09/21/ea1ee614-3f3b-11e4-9587-5dafd96295f0_story.html| title=Moving beyond the ‘imaginary Indians’ perception| author=Fred Hiatt| date=September 21, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the editors of the Washington Post.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/dc-sports-bog/wp/2014/06/03/the-great-redskins-name-debate-of-1972/|title=The Great Redskins Name Debate of … 1972?|author=Dan Steinberg|date=June 3, 2014|newspaper=The Washington Post.}}&lt;/ref&gt; National protests began in 1988, after the team's [[Super Bowl XXII]] victory, and again when [[Super Bowl XXVI|1992 Super Bowl]] between the Redskins and the [[Buffalo Bills]] was held in [[Minnesota]]. Before and during the game over 2,000 [[Chippewa]], [[Sioux]], [[Winnebago (tribe)|Winnebago]], [[Choctaw]], other Native Americans and members of the local population, protested.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1665&amp;dat=19920127&amp;id=iTMaAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=ACYEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5240,6002498|title=2,000 at Metrodome protest Indian mascots|newspaper=The New York times|date=January 27, 1992}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1992, a group of American Indians led by [[Suzan Shown Harjo|Suzan Harjo]] filed ''[[Harjo et al v. Pro Football, Inc.]]'' to have the United States trademarks associated with the Redskins name canceled under statutes which prevent registration of [[Term of disparagement|disparaging term]]s. The [[Trademark Trial and Appeal Board]] (TTAB) in 1999 ruled in favor of the petition and canceled the trademarks. Following appeals, in 2005, the [[United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit|D.C. Court of Appeals]] in ''[[Pro-Football, Inc. v. Harjo]]'' reversed the cancellation, ruling that there was insufficient [[Evidence (law)|evidence]] to support the finding of [[disparagement]] and holding that the majority of the petitioners were barred by [[Laches (equity)|laches]] from maintaining the suit.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Pro-Football, Inc. v. Harjo]]'', 415 F.3d 44 (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;  A second case was filed, ''Blackhorse v. Pro-Football, Inc.'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ttabvue.uspto.gov/ttabvue/v?qt=adv&amp;pno=92046185|title=United States Patent and Trademark Office|accessdate=October 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; with younger plaintiffs whose standing might not be hindered by laches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/nfl/redskins/2013/05/09/native-americans-washington-mascot-fight/2148877/?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+UsatodaycomSports-TopStories+%28Sports+-+Top+Stories%29|title=New generation of Native Americans challenges Redskins|newspaper=USA Today|author=Erik Brady|date=May 10, 2013|accessdate=May 10, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 18, 2014, the TTAB again voted to cancel the six trademarks held by the team in a two to one decision that held that the term "redskins" is disparaging to a "substantial composite of Native Americans", and this is demonstrated "by the near complete drop-off in usage of 'redskins' as a reference to Native Americans beginning in the 1960s." &lt;ref name="ttabvue.uspto.gov"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://ttabvue.uspto.gov/ttabvue/v?pno=92046185&amp;pty=CAN&amp;eno=199|title=USPTO TTABVUE. Proceeding Number 92046185|publisher=''United States Patent and Trademark Office''|date=June 18, 2014|accessdate=June 18, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2014/06/19/sports/football/us-patent-office-cancels-redskins-trademark-registration.html?_r=0|title=U.S. Patent Office Cancels Redskins Trademark Registration|author1=Ken Belson|author2=Edward Wyatt|date=June 18, 2014|newspaper=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; The TTAB majority held that the NCAI represented about 30 percent of Native Americans during the time in question, which the Board found satisfied the substantial composite test.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sbnation.com/nfl/2014/6/19/5825046/redskins-trademark-situation-explained-appeal-process|title=12 questions (and answers) that explain the 'Redskins' trademark case|author=Ryan Van Bibber|date=June 19, 2014|publisher=SBNation}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a press release the trademark attorney for the team stated that they were confident that they would once again prevail on appeal, and that today's decision will make no difference in the continued use of the Redskins name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://files.redskins.com/pdf/Statement-by-Bob-Raskopf-Trademark-Attorney-for-the-Washington-Redskins.pdf|format=PDF|title=Statement By Bob Raskopf, Trademark Attorney For The Washington Redskins|date=June 18, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Plaintiff [[Amanda Blackhorse]], a social worker and member of the Navajo Nation, said in an interview, "We’ve been through this process for eight years now. We will continue to fight. And, you know, this is not the end for us."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Meet the Navajo Activist Who Got the Washington Redskins’ Trademark Revoked: Amanda Blackhorse| work = Democracy Now! accessdate=June 19, 2014| date=June 19, 2014| url = http://www.democracynow.org/2014/6/19/meet_the_navajo_activist_who_got}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Washington Redskins filed its appeal of the case on August 14, 2014; stating their belief "that the Trademark Trial and Appeal Board (TTAB) ignored both federal case law and the weight of the evidence". They also cite infringement of their First Amendment right to free expression.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/nfl/redskins/2014/08/14/washington-redskins-appeal-federal-trademark-registrations/14066527/|title=Washington Redskins appeal decision to cancel trademark|author1=Erik Brady|author2=Megan Finnerty|publisher=USA TODAY Sports|date=August 14, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Evidence of disparagement submitted by the petitioners in the TTAB case include the frequent references to "scalping" made by sportswriters for sixty years when reporting the Redskins loss of a game,&lt;ref name="words"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.buzzfeed.com/lindseyadler/redskins-puns-in-sports-headlines|title=60 Years Of Shocking Redskins Headlines:A sampling of violent wordplay.|date=June 18, 2014|author=Lindsey Adler|publisher=BuzzFeed}}&lt;/ref&gt; and passages from movies made from the 1940s to the 1960s using "redskin" to refer to Native Americans as a savage enemy.&lt;ref name="movies"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/dc-sports-bog/wp/2014/06/18/here-are-some-of-the-movie-clips-cited-in-the-redskins-trademark-case/|title=Here are some of the movie clips cited in the Redskins trademark case|author=Dan Steinberg|date=June 18, 2014|newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; A linguistics expert for the team unsuccessfully argued that the name is merely a descriptive term no different than other uses of color to differentiate people by race.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/newsdesk/2014/06/dan-snyder-and-the-redskins-take-a-loss.html|date=June 18, 2014|title=Dan Snyder and the Redskins Take a Loss|author=Jay Caspian Kang|publisher=The New Yorker}}&lt;/ref&gt; The linguistic expert for the petitioners, Dr. [[Geoffrey Nunberg]], argued that whatever its origins, "redskins" was a slur at the time of the trademark registrations, based upon the passages from books and newspapers and the movie clips in which the word is inevitably associated with contempt, derision, condescension, or sentimental paeans to the noble savage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2014/06/a-linguist-on-why-redskin-is-racist-patent-overturned/373198/|title=When Slang Becomes a Slur|author=Geoffrey Nunberg|date=June 23, 2014|publisher=The Atlantic Monthly}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A symposium in February 2013 at the [[Smithsonian Institution|Smithsonian's]] [[National Museum of the American Indian]] in Washington, D.C.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsdesk.si.edu/releases/native-american-mascot-controversy-takes-center-stage-national-museum-american-indian|title=Native American Mascot Controversy Takes Center Stage at the National Museum of the American Indian|publisher=Smithsonian Institution|date=December 24, 2012|accessdate=December 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
, followed by a media campaign sponsored by the [[Oneida Indian Nation]] of New York&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/nfl/redskins/2013/09/05/oneida-indian-tribe-launches-radio-ads-against-redskins-name-roger-goodell-bigotry/2770179/|title=Indian tribe launches radio ads against Redskins' name|author=Erik Brady|publisher=USA TODAY Sports|date=September 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; led to a broader range of persons speaking out in favor of change or open discussion, including 50 U.S. Senators&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/sports/senate-democrats-urge-nfl-to-endorse-name-change-for-redskins/2014/05/22/f87e1a4c-e1f1-11e3-810f-764fe508b82d_story.html|title=Senate Democrats urge NFL to endorse name change for Redskins|author=Mark Maske|date=May 22, 2014|newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[President of the United States|President]] [[Barack Obama]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/obama-id-think-about-changing-washington-redskins-team-name/2013/10/05/e8d5cb4a-2dcd-11e3-b139-029811dbb57f_story.html?hpid=z2|title=Obama: ‘I’d think about changing’ Washington Redskins team name|author=David Nakamura|date=October 5, 2013|newspaper=The Washington Post|accessdate=October 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Statements in support of a name change have been made religious leaders in Washington, D.C.;&lt;ref name="faith"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://apps.washingtonpost.com/g/documents/local/letter-to-goodell-and-snyder/695/|title=Letter to Goodell and Snyder|newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; and The [[Leadership Conference on Civil and Human Rights]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/full-text-resolution-on-the-changing-of-the-washington-redskins-name/2013/12/12/b002f130-6342-11e3-91b3-f2bb96304e34_story.html|title=Full text: Resolution on the changing of the Washington Redskins name|date=December 12, 2013|newspaper=The Washington Post|author=Michelle Boorstein}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In response to the continued controversy, the team owner Dan Snyder sent an open letter to fans that was published in ''The Washington Post'' on October 9, 2013. In the letter Snyder states that the most important meaning of the name Redskins is the association that fans have to memories of their personal history with the team. Snyder also states that the name was chosen in 1933 to honor Native Americans in general and the coach and four players at that time who were Native American; and that in 1971 the then coach George Allen consulted with the Red Cloud Indian Fund on the Pine Ridge reservation when designing the logo.&lt;ref name="snyder"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/letter-from-washington-redskins-owner-dan-snyder-to-fans/2013/10/09/e7670ba0-30fe-11e3-8627-c5d7de0a046b_story.html|title=Letter from Washington Redskins owner Dan Snyder to fans|work=The Washington Post|date=October 9, 2013|author=Michelle Boorstein}}&lt;/ref&gt; Supporters also assert that a majority of Native Americans themselves are not offended, based upon a public opinion poll in 2004 in which 90% of those who identified as American Indians answered that they were "not bothered" by the name "Redskins" being used for the Washington football team.&lt;ref name="Annenberg.20140927"&gt;{{cite web |author=Kathleen Hall Jamieson Ph.D. |title=Most Indians Say Name of Washington "Redskins" Is Acceptable While 9 Percent Call It Offensive |url=http://www.annenbergpublicpolicycenter.org/most-indians-say-name-of-washington-redskins-is-acceptable-while-9-percent-call-it-offensive/ |website=The Annenberg Public Policy Center |accessdate=September 27, 2014 |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20131014154005/http://www.annenbergpublicpolicycenter.org/most-indians-say-name-of-washington-redskins-is-acceptable-while-9-percent-call-it-offensive/ |archivedate=October 14, 2013 |deadurl=no |date=September 24, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; However in a commentary published soon after that poll, fifteen Native American scholars collaborated on a critique that stated that there were so many flaws in the Annenberg study that rather than being a measure of Native American opinion, it was an expression of white privilege and colonialism.&lt;ref name="ClarkD.2005"&gt;{{cite journal|title=Indigenous Voice and Vision as Commodity in a Mass-Consumption Society: The Colonial Politics of Public Opinion Polling|author=D. Anthony Tyeeme Clark|journal=American Indian Quarterly|volume=29|issue=1/2 (Winter - Spring)| year=2005| pages=228–238| publisher=University of Nebraska Press| url=http://www.jstor.org/stable/4138809}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The team continues to cite current polls showing general public opinion in opposition to changing the name. One poll was part the 2014 poll of issues regarding the NFL, which included one question indicating 71% of the general public are in favor of keeping the name, with 18% in favor of a change.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.publicpolicypolling.com/main/2014/01/3rd-annual-nfl-poll.html|date=January 2, 2014|title=3rd Annual NFL Poll|publisher=Public Policy Polling}}&lt;/ref&gt; On their website the team states: “This poll, along with the poll taken among Native Americans by the Annenberg Institute, demonstrates continued, widespread and deep opposition to the Redskins changing our name. The results of this poll are solidly in line with the message we have heard from fans and Native Americans for months – our name represents a tradition, passion and heritage that honors Native Americans. We respect the point of view of the small number of people who seek a name change, but it is important to recognize very few people agree with the case they are making.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.redskins.com/news-and-events/article-1/Poll-Americans-Dont-Want-Name-Change/4fffb95f-c1af-4745-ae87-c57c448ff908|title=Poll: Americans Don't Want Name Change|date=January 2, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Onieda Indian Nation "believes more Americans would favor changing the team name of the Washington NFL club if they understood the full context of what the Oneidas and others consider a racial slur."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/nfl/2014/01/03/washington-redskins-oneida-indians-poll-name-change/4305713/|title=Oneida Indian Nation disputes phrasing in Redskins poll|author=Erik Brady|publisher=USA TODAY Sports|date=January 3, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A large protest march and rally with thousands of Native American participants was held before the game between Washington and the Minnesota Vikings on November 2, 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://espn.go.com/nfl/story/_/id/11809345/thousands-protest-washington-redskins-name-minnesota-vikings-game| title=
Thousands stage Redskins protest| date=November 2, 2014| author=Associated Press| publisher=ESPN}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police estimates of the number of protestors was between 3,500 and 4,000, while organizers put the number at 5,000. Fans were confronted by the protestors at the stadium with some tension and verbal exchanges, but no violence. Some fans hid or covered Redskins attire as they entered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/in-minnesota-native-americans-march-rally-to-protest-redskins-name/2014/11/02/fc38b8d0-6299-11e4-836c-83bc4f26eb67_story.html |title=In Minnesota, thousands of Native Americans protest Redskins’ name| author= John Woodrow Cox| date=November 2, 2014| newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other issues==

===Stereotyping by rival fans===
In addition to the behavior of the teams that have Native American names or mascots, their rivals often invoke racist stereotypes. In Alabama, at a game between the [[Pinson Valley High School]] "Indians" and [[McAdory High School]], the latter team displayed a banner using a disparaging reference to the ''Trail of Tears'' for which the principal of the school apologized to Native Americans, stated that the cheerleader squad responsible would be disciplined, and that all students would be given a lesson on the actual history of the Trail of Tears. Native Americans responded that it was an example of the continuing insensitivity and stereotyping of Indians in America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://usnews.nbcnews.com/_news/2013/11/18/21523300-alabama-principal-apologizes-for-trail-of-tears-banner-at-high-school-football-game|title=Alabama principal apologizes for 'Trail of Tears' banner at high school football game|author=Simon Moya-Smith|publisher=NBC News|date=November 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.upi.com/Odd_News/Blog/2013/11/19/McAdory-High-School-in-Alabama-apologizes-for-Trail-of-Tears-sign/5471384871891/|title=McAdory High School in Alabama apologizes for 'Trail of Tears' sign|author=Evan Bleier|date=November 19, 2013|publisher=UPI}}&lt;/ref&gt; A similar sign was displayed in Tennessee by the [[Dyersburg, Tennessee|Dyersburg]] Trojans when they played the [[North Side High School (Jackson, Tennessee)|Jackson Northside Indians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.motherjones.com/mojo/2013/11/heres-another-high-school-football-team-promoting-trail-tears|title=Here's Another High School Football Team Promoting the "Trail of Tears"|author=Tim Murphy|date=November 21, 2013|publisher=Mother Jones}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2013 when the Washington NFL team played the [[Kansas City Chiefs]] an employee of a [[Sonic Drive-In]] in Missouri placed a message outside that used scalping, reservations and whiskey to disparage the "Redskins". It was quickly removed with the owner's apologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2520773/Sonic-Drive-restaurant-upsets-racist-sign-scalp-Washington-Redskins.html|title=Fast food restaurant upsets customers with racist sign promising that the Kansas City Chiefs would 'scalp' the Washington Redskins|publisher=Daily Mail|author=Sara Malm|date=9 December 2013|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; A rubber severed "Indian" head impaled on a knife is used by a sports fan in Philadelphia to taunt rival teams with Native American mascots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.racialicious.com/2013/09/10/thanks-for-the-severed-head-you-proved-my-point/|title=Thanks for the severed head. You proved my point|accessdate=August 10, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another "Trail of Tears" sign was displayed by Oklahoma State University fans at their game with the Florida State Seminoles (shown on ESPN's College GameDay), which was quickly condemned by OSU officials who asked for its removal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsok.com/osu-football-trail-of-tears-college-gameday-sign-condemned-by-university/article/5337476?custom_click=rss&amp;utm_source=twitterfeed&amp;utm_medium=twitter|title=OSU football: 'Trail of Tears' College GameDay sign condemned by university|author=Erik Horne|date=August 30, 2014|publisher=NewsOK}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Varying degrees of offensiveness===
To further complicate this controversy, many feel that there are varying levels of offensiveness with team names and mascots. The nature and degree of stereotyping varies depending upon the name of the team, the logo, the mascot, and the behavior of fans. The greatest offense is taken when the logo and mascot are caricatures viewed as insulting, such as the [[Cleveland Indians]]' [[Chief Wahoo]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catholicculture.org/news/features/index.cfm?recnum=5437|title=Coalition Of Religious Investors Fight Baseball Team Logo|date=July 10, 1997|accessdate=January 18, 2013|publisher=Catholic Culture}}&lt;/ref&gt; the name of the team is often regarded as a racial slur, such as [[redskin (slang)|redskins]]; or the behavior of the mascot or fans is based upon popular images of Indians which trivialize authentic native cultures; such as the tomahawk chop.

==Support for the use of Native American mascots==
[[Image:FedExField - Redskins Jaguars pregame field.jpg|thumb|right|210px|The Washington Redskins logo at FedEx Field, in Maryland]]
Some individuals who support the use of Native American mascots state that they are meant to be respectful, and to pay homage to Native American people.  Many have made the argument that Native American mascots focus on bravery, courage and fighting skills rather than anything derogatory. Karl Swanson, vice-president of the Washington Redskins professional football team, declared in the magazine ''[[Sports Illustrated]]'' that his team's name "symbolizes courage, dignity, and leadership," and that the "Redskins symbolize the greatness and strength of a grand people."&lt;ref name="bar"&gt;{{cite journal| last=Emert| first=Phyllis Raybin|year=2003| url=http://www.njsbf.org/images/content/1/1/11134/Respect%20Winter%202003.pdf| title=Native American Mascots: Racial Slur or Cherished Tradition?| journal=Respect (newsletter)| publisher=New Jersey State Bar Foundation|volume=2| issue=2 (Winter 2003)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anil Adyanthaya, an attorney, wrote on June 5, 2005, "The use of Aztec or Seminole as a nickname by itself would not appear to be racist, as such names refer to a particular civilization rather than an entire race of people. In this way, they are no different from other school nicknames such as Trojans and Spartans (like Aztecs, ancient peoples) or [[Notre Dame Fighting Irish|Fighting Irish]] and [[Lebanon Valley College|Flying Dutchmen]] (like Seminoles, nationalities). Similarly, Warriors and Braves are no different from the fighting men of other cultures, like Vikings, Minutemen, or Musketeers (all current [[NCAA]] mascots, the first of which is also an [[NFL]] mascot) so it seems hard to argue that their use is uniquely demeaning in some way."&lt;ref name="globe"&gt;{{cite news|last=Adyanthaya|first=Anil|title=Sports, mascots, and Native Americans|url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/oped/articles/2005/06/05/sports_mascots_and_native_americans/|newspaper=The Boston Globe|date=June 5, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is not the names by themselves that are uniquely insulting to Native Americans. [[Richard Lapchick|Dr. Richard Lapchick]], director emeritus of Northeastern University's Center for the Study of Sport in Society, in an article: "Could you imagine people mocking African Americans in black face at a game? Yet go to a game where there is a team with an Indian name and you will see fans with war paint on their faces. Is this not the equivalent to black face?"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/page2/story?page=lapchick/050825&amp;num=0|title=Mascots are a matter of respect|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=February 6, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Supporters of the use of native imagery reject the term racism because they associate that word with the experience of African-Americans rather than Native Americans; however, [[Racism and ethnic discrimination in the United States#Racism against Native Americans|racism]] is a broader term for any discriminatory practice based upon ethnicity. Slavery was a more personal assault and continued after emancipation in the form of discrimination that insured a continued source of cheap labor. What Euro-Americans wanted from Native Americans was not labor but land, and many were willing to have native people themselves assimilate. Continued discrimination came to those who refused to do so, but asserted their separate identity and rights of sovereignty. The [[Cultural appropriation|appropriation]] of native cultures is therefore a discriminatory practice that is not understood as such by those that think of assimilation as a positive process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|volume=56|journal=UCLA Law Review|page=591|title=Red: Racism and the American Indian|last=Berger|first=Bethany R.|year=2009|url=http://www.uclalawreview.org/pdf/56-3-2.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Others claim Native American mascots help promote the culture to those who might be unaware of its significance. [[Chief Illiniwek]], the former athletic symbol for the [[University of Illinois]], became the subject of protest in 1988.&lt;ref name="Spindel"/&gt; However, in 1990 the Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois called the mascot a dignified symbol: "His ceremonial dance is done with grace and beauty. The Chief keeps the memory of the people of a great Native American tribe alive for thousands of Illinoisans who otherwise would know little or nothing of them. However, the tribal costume was not of the [[Illiniwek|Illini confederacy]], but that of the [[Lakota people|Lakota tribe]]. The [[Peoria (tribe)|Peoria Tribe of Indians of Oklahoma]] is the closest living descendants of the Illiniwek Confederacy; and in 2005, John P. Froman, the new Chief when asked his position by the NCAA, indicated that "Chief (Illiniwek) was not representative of our tribe and culture, mainly because the costume is Sioux."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Daily Illini|first=Courtney|last=Linehan|url=http://www.dailyillini.com/home/index.cfm?event=displayArticlePrinterFriendly&amp;uStory_id=7d161c2c-6bd4-466a-bffa-92e7825e264e |title=Illiniwek appeal denied|date=November 14, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, in response to a widely published column by journalist [[George Will]] in support of the symbol's use, he wrote a letter reiterating the Peoria Tribe's opposition to the symbol and decrying that the "University of Illinois has ignored the tribe’s request for nearly five years."&lt;ref&gt;John P. Froman. [http://www.nah.uiuc.edu/faculty/tyeeme/documents/froman2006.pdf Letter to George Will of The Washington Post]. January 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; On March 13, 2007, the University of Illinois board of trustees voted to retire Illiniwek's name, image and regalia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=2796923|publisher= ESPN|title=Illinois trustees vote to retire Chief Illiniwek - College Sports}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Steven Denson, director of diversity for [[Southern Methodist University]] and member of the [[Chickasaw]] nation, while not issuing a blanket endorsement, has nevertheless stated that there are acceptable ways to use Native American mascots if it is done in a respectful and tasteful manner. He states: "I believe it is acceptable if used in a way that fosters understanding and increased positive awareness of the Native-American culture. And it must also be done with the support of the Native-American community. There is a way to achieve a partnership that works together to achieve mutually beneficial goals."&lt;ref name="SMU"&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.redorbit.com/news/science/153383/nativeamerican_nicknamesmascots/index.html| title=Native-American Nicknames/Mascots|publisher=Red Orbit| date=June 2, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public opinion surveys==
In 2001, ''[[Indian Country Today Media Network|Indian Country Today]]'' conducted a poll of an undisclosed number of readers reporting that "81 percent of respondents indicated use of American Indian names, symbols and mascots are predominantly offensive and deeply disparaging to Native Americans." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://indiancountrytodaymedianetwork.com/ictarchives/2001/08/07/american-indian-opinion-leaders-american-indian-mascots-84807|title=AMERICAN INDIAN OPINION LEADERS: American Indian Mascots|date=August 7, 2001|newspaper=Indian Country Today|accessdate=January 23, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A survey conducted in 2002 by Sports Illustrated (SI) found that 81 percent of Native Americans who live outside traditional Indian reservations and 53 percent of Indians on reservations did not find the images discriminatory. The authors of the article concluded that "Although most Native American activists and tribal leaders consider Indian team names and mascots offensive, neither Native Americans in general nor a cross section of U.S. sports fans agree. According to the article, There is a near total disconnect between Indian activists and the Native American population on this issue." An Indian activist commented on the results saying "that Native Americans' self-esteem has fallen so low that they don't even know when they're being insulted."&lt;ref name=PriceWoo&gt;
{{cite news| url = http://www.si.com/vault/2002/03/04/319584/the-indian-wars-the-campaign-against-indian-nicknames-and-mascots-presumes-that-they-offend-native-americans--but-do-they-we-took-a-poll-and-you-wont-believe-the-results| author = S.L. Price| title = The Indian Wars| work = Sports Illustrated| date = March 4, 2002| pages=66–71}}&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after the SI article, a group of five researchers published an article in an academic journal, arguing against the validity of this survey and its conclusions. First they state that "The confidence with which the magazine asserts that a 'disconnect' between Native American activists and Native Americans exists on this issue belies the serious errors in logic and accuracy made in the simplistic labeling of Native Americans who oppose mascots as 'activists.'" &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://jss.sagepub.com/content/26/4/381|title=Of Polls and Race Predudice|DOI=10.1177/0193732502238255|journal=Journal of Sport and Social Issues|date=November 2002|volume=26|issue=4|page=381|author1=C. Richard King|author2=Ellen J. Staurowsky|author3=Lawrence Baca|author4=Laurel R. Davis|author5=Cornel Pewewardy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;King, C. Richard. ''The Native American Mascot Controversy: A Handbook'' p.268. (ISBN 9780810867321). Peter Harris Research Group. (2002) Methodology for ''Sports Illustrated'' survey on the use of Indian nicknames, mascots, etc. Document produced by The Peter Harris Research Group and shared with Ellen Staurowsky in January 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

More recent surveys, rather than addressing the larger issue, have targeted the controversy over the name of the Washington Redskins, asking if the word is offensive or if it should be changed. By a large majority (71-89 percent), public opinion has maintained that the name should not change, but when additional questions were asked also have found that the same respondents said "redskin" is not an appropriate term for Native Americans. See: [[Washington_Redskins_name_controversy#Public_opinion_polls|Redskins Public Opinion Polls]].  

At the Center for Indigenous Peoples Studies at [[California State University]], San Bernardino a survey has conducted of 400 individuals whose identity as Native American was verified, finding that 67% agreed with the statement that "Redskins" is offensive and racist. The response from non-natives was almost the opposite, with 68% responding that the name is not offensive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.buzzfeed.com/lindseyadler/native-americans-offended-by-racial-slur|title=New Study Finds 67% Of Native Americans Find Redskins Name Offensive|publisher=Buzzfeed.com|date=June 4, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cips.csusb.edu/docs/PressRelease.pdf|title=Survey on Redskins team name found most American Indians believe it to be offensive and racist.|accessdate=June 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are basic issues with the reliability of public opinion polls that overshadow their value in many cases. There has been a decline in the willingness of people to participate, now down to about 10%, so there is no way of knowing whether there is any systematic bias in the results. Survey methods also influence the results, with those done by traditional mail over-sampling the elderly, and those done using land-lines under-sampling the young, who only have cell phones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2012/05/survey_bias_how_can_we_trust_opinion_polls_when_so_few_people_respond_.single.html|title=Minority Opinions:Hardly anyone responds to public opinion surveys anymore. Can we still trust them?|author=Will Oremus|date=2012-05-17|accessdate=2013-11-21|publisher=Slate}}&lt;/ref&gt; The flaw in random and anonymous polls of Native American's opinion is that they must rely upon self-identification to select the target group. In an editorial in the Bloomington Herald Times, Steve Russell (an enrolled Cherokee citizen and associate professor of criminal justice at Indiana University), states that both SI and Annenberg's samples of "self-identified Native Americans... includes plenty of people who have nothing to do with Indians".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iupui.edu/~mstd/e320/amerind/flap.html|title=Some collected materials about the NCAA's decision to ban Indian sports mascots from the Indianapolis area|accessdate=January 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The problem of individuals claiming to be Native American when they are not is well known in academic research, and is a particular problem when non-natives claim Indian identity specifically to gain authority in the debate over sports mascots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Springwood|first=Charles|title="I’m Indian Too!": Claiming Native American Identity, Crafting Authority in Mascot Debates|publisher=Journal of sport and social issues|date=February 2004|volume=28|page=56}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Financial impact of change==
Many supporters of Native American mascots feel that the financial cost of changing mascots would far outweigh the benefits.  Sales of merchandise with team mascots and nicknames ranging from t-shirts to beer cozies generate millions of dollars in sales each year, and teams contend that a change in team mascots would render this merchandise useless.&lt;ref name="bar"/&gt; The cost of removing images from uniforms and all other items, which must be paid out of local school funds, is a greater factor for secondary schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.mailtribune.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20120518/NEWS/205180322|title=State bans Native American mascots|date=May 18, 2012|first=Sanne|last=Specht|newspaper=Mail Tribune|accessdate=February 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Opponents, however, are unconcerned with the cost of changing, and view mascots as caricatures of real Indians that do not honor them, but rather trivialize and demean important Indian dances and traditions.  Opponents feel that despite the cost of a change in team mascots, it should be done to prevent what they believe is racial stereotyping. [[Clyde Bellecourt]], director of the [[American Indian Movement]] stated: "It's the behavior that accompanies all of this that's offensive.  The rubber tomahawks, the chicken feather headdresses, people wearing war paint and making these ridiculous war whoops with a tomahawk in one hand and a beer in the other; all of these have significant meaning for us. And the psychological impact it has, especially on our youth, is devastating."&lt;ref name="bar"/&gt;

One attempt to affect the use of mascots financially is the case brought against the Washington Redskins to revoke their trademarks. (See: ''[[Native American mascot controversy#Washington Redskins|Washington Redskins]]'' above.)

A study done by the [[Emory University]] [[Goizueta Business School]] indicates that the growing unpopularity of Native American mascots is a financial drain for professional teams, losing money compared to more popular animal mascots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://blogs.emory.edu/sportsmarketing/2013/12/19/the-financial-impact-of-mascots-on-sports-brands/?_ga=1.256951951.500422532.1397069844b|title=The Financial Impact of Mascots on Sports Brands|publisher=Emory University|date=December 19, 2013|accessdate=April 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Support for certain teams by individual tribes==
The NCAA has granted waivers from their mascot policy to five university teams that have obtained official support from individual tribes for the use of their names and images, which is based upon the principle of [[Tribal sovereignty in the United States|Tribal Sovereignty]], as stated by the NCAI: "In general, NCAI strongly opposes the use of derogatory Native sports mascots. However, in the case where mascots refer to a particular Native nation or nations, NCAI respects the right of individual tribal nations to work with universities and athletic programs to decide how to protect and celebrate their respective tribal heritage."&lt;ref name="NCAI"/&gt;

===Florida State Seminoles===
[[Image:Chief Osceola on Renegade FSU.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Osceola rides his horse Renegade at a [[Florida State University|Florida State]] home game.]]
The [[Florida State University]]'s use of [[Seminole]] imagery for its [[Florida State Seminoles]] athletic teams represents a case of an evolution of its relationship with the [[Seminole Tribe of Florida]]. The university has worn the nickname "Seminoles" since 1947 and annually crowns a Chief and Princess at Homecoming with Seminole tribe leaders participating as celebrants. Since 1978 home football games have been opened with the entrance of [[Osceola and Renegade]]. Florida State University officials disapprove of referring to human figures as 'mascots' and have asked sports writers to cease doing so. Official university statements speak only of using 'symbols', 'nicknames', and 'images' inspired by Seminole tradition.

The question of a nickname for athletic teams arose in 1947 as the Florida State College for Women became [[Florida State University]]. The name Seminoles was selected by student vote, and for the first two decades the athletic teams mostly used images based on stereotypes such as in [[Hollywood]] [[Westerns]]. Leaders of the [[Seminole Tribe of Florida]] who attended a basketball game on the campus in 1972 expressed their concerns to university officials regarding the antics of such mascots. Seminole leaders and university officials agreed on the need for something dignified and more representative of authentic Seminole traditions. Both ''[[Sammy Seminole]]'' and ''Chief Fullabull'' were retired that year.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite news|last=DeSlatte |first=Aaron |url=http://groups.yahoo.com/group/NatNews/message/39441 |title=FSU worked to cultivate better image of Seminole |newspaper=Florida Today |date=August 17, 2005 |accessdate=June 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

1978 marked the first appearance of [[Osceola and Renegade]], in which a student portrays the 19th-century Seminole leader [[Osceola]], riding Renegade, an [[Appaloosa]] horse. The student, chosen for his horsemanship, wears clothing provided by the Seminole tribe but is not necessarily of native American descent himself. The Seminole Tribe of Florida officially sanctions the use of the Seminole as Florida State University’s nickname and of Osceola as FSU's symbol. Max Osceola, the chief and general council president of the Seminole Tribe of Florida, has stated that he regards it as an “honor” to be associated with the university.&lt;ref name="seminole" /&gt; However, the Seminole Tribe of Florida is only one of the tribal authorities representing Seminoles. Some members of the much larger [[Seminole Nation of Oklahoma]] objected to the use of the name and imagery, leading to the NCAA originally placed FSU on the list of colleges using imagery “hostile or abusive” towards Native Americans.&lt;ref name="mess"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2005/08/08/mascot|title=The Mascot Mess|date=August 8, 2005|first=Doug|last=Lederman|newspaper=Inside Higher Ed|accessdate=February 8, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However in July 2005, the Seminole Nation General Council, the legislative body for the Seminole Nation of Oklahoma, voted 18-2 not to oppose the use of Native American names and mascots by college sports teams.&lt;ref name="McBee"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nbcsports.msnbc.com/id/8940521/|title=Seminole Nation OK with use of mascot|publisher=NBC Sports|accessdate=February 6, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to Osceola, there are the FSU traditions of the "tomahawk chop" and "war chant", which have more controversial associations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seminoles.com/trads/fsu-trads-chant.html|title=Traditions: War Chant|publisher=FSU Athletics|accessdate=February 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://indiancountrytodaymedianetwork.com/mobile/article/war-chant-and-tomahawk-chop%3A-from-seminoles-to-republicans-%28via-braves,-diddy,-and-a-40-foot-cow%29-136321|title=War Chant and Tomahawk Chop: From Seminoles to Republicans (via Braves, Diddy, and a 40-Foot Cow)|date=September 28, 2012|publisher=Indian Country Today|accessdate=February 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
Too detailed, not sourced:  
At the beginning of each home game Osceola plants a flaming spear at midfield. The image and actions of this figure were worked out in coordination with Florida Seminole leaders. Osceola never speaks or appears walking on foot. When the US national anthem is sung, Osceola simply waits with his spear across his lap. For the first three years of the tradition the figure actually went nameless; he was referred to as 'the Seminole warrior' because tribal leaders at the time preferred that the name of the actual historical figure not be used. The Florida State portrayal of Osceola romanticizes tradition in some aspects. The historical Osceola, a war leader, did not actually live long enough to attain the rank of Seminole "chief". Florida State does not sanction the use of that term, and refers to the symbols simply as "Osceola and Renegade". Historians debate how much inclination or opportunity Osceola had to ride horses in [[Seminole Wars|wartime]].

This detailed back and forth does not belong in this general article
Activists Michael Haney and [[David Narcomey]], general council member of the [[Seminole Nation of Oklahoma]], objected to FSU's use of the Seminole symbol and name, and acting independently of the Seminole Nation of Oklahoma, filed a complaint with the NCAA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/tim-giago/the-powerful-medicine-of-_b_80444.html?view=print | work=Huffington Post | first=Tim | last=Giago | title=The Powerful Medicine of Michael Haney | date=Nov 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; David Narcomey, speaking on his own behalf, stated "I am deeply appalled, incredulously disappointed ... I am nauseated that the NCAA is allowing this 'minstrel show' to carry on this form of racism in the 21st century."

In response, Jennifer McBee, the Oklahoma Seminole tribe's attorney general, stated that while David Narcomey was a member of the Oklahoma Seminoles' General Council, he did not speak for the 14,000-member Seminole Nation of Oklahoma when he protested to NCAA officials about FSU's use of the Seminole name and image. McBee added that the NCAA never even asked the General Council for its opinion.&lt;ref name="McBee"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nbcsports.msnbc.com/id/8940521/|title=Seminole Nation OK with use of mascot|publisher=NBC Sports|accessdate=02/06/2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Attorney General McBee stated that, as of June 2005, the council had taken no official position on the FSU issue.&lt;ref name="seminole" /&gt; Despite the opinions expressed by Haney and Narcomey, Ken Chambers, principal chief of the Seminole Nation of Oklahoma told ''The Palm Beach'' (Florida) ''Post'' in August 2005 that he had no objection to Florida State University using the Seminoles as a nickname and symbol, reversing the earlier public position of the Oklahoma tribe's spokesperson.&lt;ref name="usatoday_seminoles"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/2005-08-11-fsu-mascot-support_x.htm|title=Oklahoma Seminoles OK Name|newspaper=USA Today | first1=Steve|last1=Wieberg|date=August 12, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
--&gt;
In August 2005 the NCAA granted a waiver to the Florida State University which removed it from the “hostile or abusive” list.  According to Bernard Franklin, senior vice president of the NCAA: "The staff review committee noted the unique relationship between the university and the Seminole Tribe of Florida as a significant factor.  The decision of a namesake sovereign tribe, regarding when and how its name and imagery can be used, must be respected even when others may not agree."&lt;ref name="seminole"&gt;Wieberg, Steve (Aug. 23, 2005), "[http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/2005-08-23-fsu-mascot-approved_x.htm NCAA allowing Florida State to use its Seminole mascot]," ''USA Today''.&lt;/ref&gt; The relationship between the tribe and the university has been maintained to the present, with few voices in opposition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/29/sports/ncaafootball/29seminoles.html?pagewanted=all|title=Bonding Over a Mascot|first=JOE|last=LAPOINTE|date=December 29, 2006|accessdate=February 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/10/24/sports/ncaafootball/amid-rising-discord-over-indian-images-florida-state-has-harmony.html?_r=0|title=Amid Rising Discord Over Indian Images, F.S.U. Has Harmony|date=October 23, 2013|accessdate=November 4, 2013|work=The New York Times|first=Mike|last=Tierney}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other exceptions: granted or denied ===
Other Indian tribes have also supported the use of their tribal names as a tribute to their heritage.

The [[Ute tribe]] approved the use of the name "Utes" for the [[University of Utah]] and the NCAA granted a waiver to allow the name to remain. For many decades, the school did not have an official Western Athletic Conference mascot.  As early as the 1950s, the University of Utah created a Ute Indian boy, named "Hoyo", as its mascot.  The University of Utah club organizations, such as the Associated Students of the University of Utah, the University of Utah Alumni Association, the Daily Chronicle, and many other social organizations highly celebrated "Hoyo" at homecoming events, before and after football games events, and at other social events for many years.&lt;ref&gt;1951 ''Utonian'', p. 153, University of Utah&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to 1972, teams used both "Utes" and "Redskins" as nicknames, but dropped the latter in response to tribal concerns. In 1996 Swoop, a red tailed hawk, became the official mascot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://utahutes.cstv.com/trads/swoop.html|title=Mascot/Nickname History|accessdate=November 18, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Even though Swoop is now the University of Utah's official mascot, Utah fans and its clubs alike still use "Utes" as their nickname at sporting events. This is done with permission from the Ute Tribal Council.&lt;ref&gt;[http://utahutes.cstv.com/trads/ute-trads-general.html Utah Traditions], University of Utah Athletics website&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Central Michigan University]] nickname, the [[Central Michigan Chippewas|Chippewas]], was originally placed on the “hostile or abusive” list but was removed when the [[Saginaw Chippewa Tribal Nation]] of Michigan gave its support to the nickname.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=2149907 "NCAA takes Utah off banned mascots list"] - ESPN&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of North Dakota]]'s former athletic logo, a [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] figure, was recently dropped. Due to the [[NCAA]]'s perception that the term "Fighting Sioux" and the accompanying logo are offensive to native Americans, the NCAA pressured the university to discontinue use of the logo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/sports/2012/02/29/ncaa-dont-bring-fighting-sioux-name-to-playoffs/ |title=NCAA: Don't bring Fighting Sioux name to playoffs. |publisher=FoxNews.com |date=February 29, 2012 |accessdate=March 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When UND moved in the fall of 2009 to change its nickname, one of the three Sioux tribal councils in the state sued to have the name retained.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/09/us/09nickname.html | work=The New York Times | title=In Twist, Tribe Fights for College Nickname | first=Monica | last=Davey | date=December 9, 2009 | accessdate=May 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]], however, is permitted to use the name "Illini" owing to the NCAA ruling that the name "is closely related to the name of the state and not directly associated with Native Americans."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fs.ncaa.org/Docs/PressArchive/2007/Official%2BStatements/Statement%2Bby%2BBernard%2BFranklin%2BNCAA%2BSenior%2BVice-President%2Bfor%2BGovernance%2BMembership%2BEducation%2Band%2BResearch%2BServices%2Bon%2BU.html|title=Statement By Bernard Franklin, NCAA Senior Vice-President For Governance, Membership, Education And Research Services, On University Of Illinois Mascot Decision|date=February 16, 2007|publisher=NCAA|accessdate=December 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term [[Fighting Illini]] is in fact a reference to veterans from Illinois who fought during World War I.  The symbol [[Chief Illiniwek]] was ruled "hostile and abusive" and was retired in 2007 to comply with the NCAA's ruling, and the following year, in compliance with a related NCAA ruling, both U of I and [[Northwestern University]] retired their then-current rivalry trophy, the [[Sweet Sioux Tomahawk]].

[[The College of William &amp; Mary]], founded in 1693 with a charter to, among other things, educate and evangelize the native population, voluntarily changed its sports nickname from "Indians" to the [[William &amp; Mary Tribe|"Tribe"]] in the late 1970s. However, the NCAA forced the school to remove the two tribal feathers stemming from [[Gene Nichol#Athletic logo and the NCAA|their logo]] in 2006 due to "insensitivity" towards Native Americans.  The fact that the local Pamunkey and Mattaponi tribes supported the College's use of the feathers was not enough for the NCAA.

The [[Arkansas State University]] officially removed its mascot, the "Indians," in 2008, replacing it with the "[[Arkansas State Red Wolves|Red Wolves]]," at the request of the [[Osage Nation|Osage]] tribe.

Relationships have also been established at the high school level. [[Arapahoe High School (Centennial, Colorado)]] now uses a logo provided by the Arapaho Tribe of Wyoming, which initially included an agreement that the image would not be placed on the gym floor or any article of clothing. The latter provision has not always been observed, but the logo does not appear on the team uniforms. The agreement also includes tribal participation in school events.

==Current status==
After decades of decline from over 3,000,&lt;ref name="AICS"/&gt; there remain fewer than 1,000 high school, university and professional teams that continue to have Native American mascots.&lt;ref name="NCAI"/&gt; Though changes have been made at the high school and college levels, at the professional level there has been virtually no change. The topic remains an issue on a national level, with a hearing before the US Senate Committee on Indian Affairs in 2011,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indian.senate.gov/hearings/hearing.cfm?hearingID=e655f9e2809e5476862f735da16ba74a|title=OVERSIGHT HEARING on Stolen Identities: The Impact of Racist Stereotypes on Indigenous People|date=May 5, 2011|accessdate=February 10, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a symposium at the Smithsonian [[National Museum of the American Indian]] in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsdesk.si.edu/releases/native-american-mascot-controversy-takes-center-stage-national-museum-american-indian|title=Native American Mascot Controversy Takes Center Stage at the National Museum of the American Indian|publisher=Smithsonian Institution|date=December 24, 2012|accessdate=December 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==Name/Mascot changes==
===Colleges and universities===
'''Note''': Leagues and conferences are current, not necessarily those applicable at the time of the nickname change.

{| class="wikitable sortable"
|- valign=baseline
! School
! Nickname
! Former Nickname
! Year Changed
! State
! League
! Division
! Conference
|-align="center"
|[[Arkansas State University]]
|[[Arkansas State Red Wolves|Red Wolves]]
|Indians
|2008
|[[Arkansas]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Football Bowl Subdivision|FBS]])
|[[Sun Belt Conference|Sun Belt]]
|-align="center"
|[[Carthage College]]
|[[Carthage Red Men|Red Men]]
|Redmen
|2006
|[[Wisconsin]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division III (NCAA)|III]]
|[[College Conference of Illinois and Wisconsin|CCIW]]
|-align="center"
|[[Chowan University]]
|[[Chowan Hawks|Hawks]]
|Braves
|2006
|[[North Carolina]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division II (NCAA)|II]]
|[[Central Intercollegiate Athletic Association|CIAA]]
|-align="center"
|[[Dartmouth College]]
|[[Dartmouth Big Green|Big Green]]
|Indians
|1969
|[[New Hampshire]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Football Championship Subdivision|FCS]])
|[[Ivy League|Ivy]]
|-align="center"
|[[Eastern Michigan University]]
|[[Eastern Michigan Eagles|Eagles]]
|Hurons
|1991
|[[Michigan]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Football Bowl Subdivision|FBS]])
|[[Mid-American Conference|MAC]]
|-align="center"
|[[Eastern Washington University]]
|[[Eastern Washington Eagles|Eagles]]
|Savages
|1973
|[[Washington (state)|Washington]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Football Championship Subdivision|FCS]])
|[[Big Sky Conference|Big Sky]]
|-align="center"
|[[Indiana University of Pennsylvania]]
|[[IUP Crimson Hawks|Crimson Hawks]]
|Indians
|2007
|[[Pennsylvania]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division II (NCAA)|II]]
|[[Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference|PSAC]]
|-align="center"
|[[University of Louisiana at Monroe]]
|[[Louisiana–Monroe Warhawks|Warhawks]]
|Indians
|2006
|[[Louisiana]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Football Bowl Subdivision|FBS]])
|[[Sun Belt Conference|Sun Belt]]
|-align="center"
|[[Marquette University]]
|[[Marquette Golden Eagles|Golden Eagles]]
|Warriors
|1994
|[[Wisconsin]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]]
|[[Big East Conference|Big East]]
|-align="center"
|[[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]
|[[UMass Minutemen and Minutewomen|Minutemen &amp; Minutewomen]]
|Redmen
|1972
|[[Massachusetts]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Football Bowl Subdivision|FBS]])
|[[Atlantic 10 Conference|A-10]]
|-align="center"
|[[McMurry University]]
|[[McMurry War Hawks|War Hawks]]
|Indians
|2006
|[[Texas]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division II (NCAA)|II]]
|[[Heartland Conference|Heartland]]
|-align="center"
|[[Miami University]]
|[[Miami RedHawks|RedHawks]]
|Redskins
|1997
|[[Ohio]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Football Bowl Subdivision|FBS]])
|[[Mid-American Conference|MAC]]
|-align="center"
|[[Newberry College]]
|[[Newberry Wolves|Wolves]]
|Indians
|2008
|[[South Carolina]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division II (NCAA)|II]]
|[[South Atlantic Conference|SAC]]
|-align="center"
|[[University of North Dakota]]
|[[University of North Dakota athletics|None]]
|Fighting Sioux
|2012
|[[North Dakota]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Football Championship Subdivision|FCS]])
|[[Big Sky Conference|Big Sky]]
|-align="center"
| [[Oklahoma City University]]
| [[Oklahoma City Stars|Stars]]
| Chiefs
| 1999
| [[Oklahoma]]
| [[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA]]
| I
| [[Sooner Athletic Conference|SAC]]
|-align="center"
|[[Quinnipiac University]]
|[[Quinnipiac Bobcats|Bobcats]]
|Braves
|2002
|[[Connecticut]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]]
|[[Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference|MAAC]]
|-align="center"
| {{sort|Rio Grande|[[University of Rio Grande]]}}
| [[University of Rio Grande#Athletics|RedStorm]]
| Redmen &amp; Redwomen
| 2008
| [[Ohio]]
| [[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA]]
| I
| [[Kentucky Intercollegiate Athletic Conference|KIAC]]
|-align="center"
| {{sort|Saint Bonaventure|[[St. Bonaventure University]]}}
|[[St. Bonaventure Bonnies|Bonnies]]
|Brown Indians
|1992
|[[New York]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]]
|[[Atlantic 10 Conference|A-10]]
|-align="center"
| {{sort|Saint Johns|[[St. John's University (New York City)|St. John's University]]}}
|[[St. John's Red Storm|Red Storm]]
|Redmen
|1994
|[[New York]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]]
|[[Big East Conference|Big East]]
|-align="center"
|[[Seattle University]]
|[[Seattle Redhawks|Redhawks]]
|Chieftains
|2000
|[[Washington (state)|Washington]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]]
|[[Western Athletic Conference|WAC]]
|-align="center"
|[[Siena College]]
|[[Siena Saints|Saints]]
|Indians
|1988
|[[New York]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]]
|[[Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference|MAAC]]
|-align="center"
| [[Southeast Missouri State University]]
| [[Southeast Missouri State Redhawks|Redhawks]]
| Indians &amp; Otahkians
| 2004
| [[Missouri]]
| [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
| [[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Division I (NCAA)#Football Championship Subdivision|FCS]])
| [[Ohio Valley Conference|OVC]]
|-align="center"
| [[Southeastern Oklahoma State University]]
| [[Southeastern Oklahoma State Savage Storm|Savage Storm]]
| Savages
| 2006
| [[Oklahoma]]
| [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
| [[Division II (NCAA)|II]]
| [[Great American Conference|GAC]]
|-align="center"
| [[Southern Nazarene University]]
| [[Southern Nazarene Crimson Storm|Crimson Storm]]
| Redskins
| 1999
| [[Oklahoma]]
| [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
| [[Division II (NCAA)|II]]
| [[Great American Conference|GAC]]
|-align="center"
|[[Stanford University]]
|[[Stanford Cardinal|Cardinal]]
|Indians
|1972
|[[California]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Football Bowl Subdivision|FBS]])
|[[Pacific-12 Conference|Pac-12]]
|-align="center"
|[[Stonehill College]]
|[[Stonehill Skyhawks|Skyhawks]]
|Chieftains
|2005
|[[Massachusetts]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division II (NCAA)|II]]
|[[Northeast-10 Conference|Northeast-10]]
|-align="center"
|[[College of William &amp; Mary]]
|[[William &amp; Mary Tribe|Tribe]]
|Indians
|1978
|[[Virginia]]
|[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|[[Division I (NCAA)|I]] ([[Football Championship Subdivision|FCS]])
|[[Colonial Athletic Association|CAA]]
|}

==See also==
*[[List of sports team names and mascots derived from Indigenous peoples]]
*[[List of ethnic sports team and mascot names]] (all ethnicities)
*[[Religious symbolism in U.S. sports team names and mascots]]
*[[Vernon Bellecourt]]
*[[Charlene Teters]]
*[[Russell Means]]
*[[Chief Zee]]
*[[Robert Roche (activist)|Robert Roche]]
*[[Sundance (activist)|Sundance]]
*[[Fighting Whites]]
*[[Pekin, Illinois#High school|Pekin High School Chinks]]
*[[United States national rugby league team]], aka Tomahawks.

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* King, C. Richard, guest editor.  "Re/claiming Indianness: Critical Perspectives on Native American Mascots." Journal of Sport and Social Issues 28, no. 1 (February 2004). www.sagepub.com/ejournals
* King, C. Richard, and Charles Fruehling Springwood (2001). ''Beyond the Cheers: Race as Spectacle in College Sport''. SUNY Series on Sport, Culture, and Social Relations. State University of New York Press. ISBN 0-7914-5005-8.
* King, C. Richard, and Charles Fruehling Springwood, eds. (2001). ''Team Spirits: The Native American Mascots Controversy''. Foreword by Vine Deloria Jr. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press.
* Remillard, Arthur. "Holy War on the Football Field: Religion and the Florida State University Mascot Controversy." ''Horsehide, Pigskin, Oval Tracks, and Apple Pie: Essays on Sports and American Culture''. Edited by James Vlasich. McFarland, 2005.
* Schaumann-Beltan, Karen, "Representing Native Americans in Sports" in Ross, Jeffrey Ian, ''American Indians at Risk'' ABC-CLIO (2013) [http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=8erXAQAAQBAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA219&amp;dq=From+Stereotyping+to+Invisibility:+The+Psychological+Consequences+of+Using+American+Indian+Mascots&amp;ots=-lF1mRXRnb&amp;sig=W1ZV-FM-db0Jrx_TEZtyPrMqpX4#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Google eBook]
{{refend}}

==External links==
'''Organizations'''
* [http://www.aistm.org/1indexpage.htm American Indian Sports Team Mascots]
* [http://www.racismagainstindians.org/UnderstandingMascots.htm Students and Teachers Against Racism on Understanding The American Indian Mascot Issue]
* [http://eonm.org/ Eradicating Offensive Native Mascotry]
'''Films'''
* ''[http://www.inwhosehonor.com/ In Whose Honor?]'' (1997). Written and produced by Jay Rosenstein. [[Ho-Ho-Kus, New Jersey]]: New Day Films.

&lt;!-- ;
'''Websites'''
* [http://nativeappropriations.com/ Native Appropriations]
'''Articles'''
* [http://www.nativeculturelinks.com/mascots.html The Mascot Issue]. Lisa Mitten. February 17, 1999 (last updated May 20, 2008)
* [http://www.dickshovel.com/crimes.html "Crimes Against Humanity"] by [[Ward Churchill]]
* Keen, Judy. [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/USAToday/offers.html?url=%2FUSAToday%2Faccess%2F2156557021.html%3FFMT%3DFT%26FMTS%3DABS%3AFT%26date%3DOct%2B7%252C%2B2010%26author%3DJudy%2BKeen%26pub%3DUSA%2BTODAY%26edition%3D%26startpage%3DA.3%26desc%3DControversial%2Bmascot%2Bejected "Controversial mascot ejected: Wis. community to choose name after dropping 'Indians' name used since 1936"] (Kewaunee High School). [[USA Today]], October 7, 2010, page 3A.
 --&gt;
{{Atlanta Braves}}
{{Chicago Blackhawks |state=collapsed}}
{{Cleveland Indians}}
{{Golden State Warriors}}
{{Kansas City Chiefs}}
{{Washington Redskins}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Native American Mascot Controversy}}
[[Category:Native American topics]]
[[Category:Race-related controversies in the United States]]
[[Category:Ethnic and racial stereotypes]]
[[Category:American mascots]]
[[Category:Sports mascots]]
[[Category:College mascots in the United States| ]]
[[Category:Cultural appropriation]]
[[Category:Sports controversies]]
[[Category:American football controversies]]
[[Category:Baseball controversies]]
[[Category:Basketball controversies]]
[[Category:Atlanta Braves]]
[[Category:Chicago Blackhawks]]
[[Category:Cleveland Indians]]
[[Category:Florida State Seminoles]]
[[Category:Golden State Warriors]]
[[Category:Kansas City Chiefs]]
[[Category:Washington Redskins]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>