<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211123130601|1056772826" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="50402549" pageid="50402549" ns="0" title="Capital punishment for homosexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-23T23:05:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Death penalty for sexual activity between persons of the same sex}}
{{LGBT rights sidebar}}
'''Capital punishment for homosexuality''' has been implemented by a number of countries in their history. It currently remains a legal punishment in several countries and regions, many of which  have ''[[sharia]]''-based criminal laws. Gay people also face extrajudicial killings by state and non-state actors, as in [[Chechnya]] in Russia [[Anti-gay purges in Chechnya|in 2019]], though it is denied by the Chechen authorities and Russia.

Imposition of the [[death penalty]] for homosexuality may be classified as [[judicial murder]] of gay people, which has been analyzed as a form of [[genocide]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=DeJong |first1=Christina |last2=Long |first2=Eric |title=Handbook of LGBT Communities, Crime, and Justice |publisher=Springer |isbn=978-1-4614-9188-0 |pages=339–362 |language=en |chapter=The Death Penalty as Genocide: The Persecution of “Homosexuals” in Uganda|date=4 December 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In current state laws==
[[File:World laws pertaining to homosexual relationships and expression.svg|thumb|{{legend|#8c210f|Death penalty for homosexuality}}{{legend|#cc6633|Death penalty, unenforced}}]]
{{Further|LGBT rights by country or territory|LGBT in Islam|Capital punishment for adultery|Sharia#Islamization}}

As of July 2020, the following jurisdictions prescribe the death penalty for homosexuality:

* {{flagicon|Afghanistan}} [[LGBT rights in Afghanistan|Afghanistan]]. A new Penal Code enacted in February 2018 explicitly criminalises same-sex sexual conduct.{{citation needed|date=July 2020}} Sources cited by the [[International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association]] (ILGBTIA) indicate that there is a "broad consensus amongst scholars that execution was the appropriate punishment if homosexual acts could be proven”.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|location=Geneva|pages=429}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sharia category of ''[[zina]]'' (illicit sexual intercourse), which according to some traditional Islamic [[Madhhab|legal schools]] may entail the ''[[Hudud|hadd]]'' (sharia-prescribed) punishment of stoning, when strict evidential requirements are met. The [[Hanafi]] school, prevalent in Afghanistan, does not regard homosexual acts as a ''hadd'' crime, although Afghan judges may potentially apply the death penalty for a number of reasons. No known death sentences for homosexuality have been passed since the end of Taliban rule in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/ |title=Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death |work=The Washington Post |date=16 June 2016 |access-date=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.deathpenaltyworldwide.org/country-search-post.cfm?country=Afghanistan |title=The Death Penalty in Afghanistan |publisher=Death Penalty Worldwide |access-date=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, following the [[2021 Taliban offensive]], fears of reprisal including death for those suspected of homosexuality were renewed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://thehill.com/policy/international/569741-they-will-kill-us-if-they-find-us-lgbt-afghans-fear-new-taliban-regime |title='They will kill us if they find us': LGBT Afghans fear new Taliban regime |publisher=The Hill |access-date=6 September 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Brunei}} [[LGBT rights in Brunei|Brunei]]'s ''Sharia Penal Code'', implemented in stages since 2014, prescribes death by stoning as punishment for same-sex relations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/mar/28/brunei-brings-in-death-by-stoning-as-punishment-for-gay-sex|title=Brunei introduces death by stoning as punishment for gay sex|last=correspondent|first=Hannah Ellis-Petersen South-east Asia|date=28 March 2019|work=The Guardian|access-date=28 March 2019|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt; After international backlash, in May 2019, the Sultan of Brunei explained that a "de facto" moratorium on the execution of the death penalty has been in force in the country for the last two decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Brunei says it won't enforce gay death penalty after backlash |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-brunei-lgbt-sultan/brunei-says-it-wont-enforce-gay-death-penalty-after-backlash-idUSKCN1SB0FS |website=Reuters |access-date=19 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* {{flagicon|Iran}} [[LGBT rights in Iran|Iran]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015"&gt;{{cite web|author1=Aengus Carroll|author2=Lucas Paoli Itaborahy|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia: A World Survey of Laws: criminalisation, protection and recognition of same-sex love|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/2017/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2017_WEB.pdf|website=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex association|access-date=5 April 2019|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Male-male anal intercourse is declared a capital offense in Iran's ''Islamic Penal Code'', enacted in 1991. Articles 233 through 241 criminalise both female and male same-sex activity; for a first offence, the death penalty only applies to some cases of male-male penile-anal intercourse, with female-female activity and other cases of male-male activity being punished by flogging instead of execution. Under the combination of articles 136 and 238, a woman convicted for the fourth time of the crime of ''musaheqeh'' ([[tribadism]]) is to be executed; there is no death penalty for non-genital-genital female-female sexual conduct.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Refugees|first=United Nations High Commissioner for|title=Refworld {{!}} Iran: Islamic Penal Code|url=https://www.refworld.org/docid/518a19404.html|access-date=20 July 2020|website=Refworld|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though the grounds for execution in Iran are difficult to track, there is evidence that several gay men were executed in 2005-2006 and in 2016, mostly on alleged charges of rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Asal, V.|author2=Sommer, U.|title= Legal Path Dependence and the Long Arm of the Religious State: Sodomy Provisions and Gay Rights Across Nations and Over Time|publisher=State University of New York Press|page=64}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=economist&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Economist|title=How homosexuality became a crime in the Middle East|date=6 June 2018|url=https://www.economist.com/open-future/2018/06/06/how-homosexuality-became-a-crime-in-the-middle-east}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|Iraq}} [[LGBT rights in Iraq|Iraq]]. Although homosexuality itself is legal since 2003&lt;ref name="Utah"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gjpi.org/2009/05/21/homosexuality-and-the-criminal-law-in-iraq/|title=Global Justice Project: Iraq » Archive » Homosexuality and the Criminal Law in Iraq: UPDATED|first=The University of|last=Utah|access-date=4 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ILGA 2009"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ilga.org/statehomophobia/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2009.pdf |title=State-sponsored Homophobia: A world survey of laws prohibiting same sex activity between consenting adults |last=Ottosson |first=Daniel |date=May 2009 |publisher=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association (ILGA) |pages=23 |access-date=2009-05-19 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091029181019/http://www.ilga.org/statehomophobia/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2009.pdf |archive-date=2009-10-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; LGBT can be charged under public indecency law 401.&lt;ref name="Utah"/&gt; People may face execution by vigilantes and Sharia courts set up by insurgents.&lt;ref name="bbc.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/av/world-middle-east-19525133/baghdad-s-persecuted-gays-have-nowhere-to-hide|title=Baghdad's persecuted gays have nowhere to hide|access-date=2021-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Mauritania}} [[LGBT rights in Mauritania|Mauritania]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt; According to a 1984 law, Muslim men can be stoned for engaging in homosexual sex, though no executions have occurred so far.&lt;ref name="WP"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/|title=Analysis - Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death|first1=Max|last1=Bearak|first2=Darla|last2=Cameron|date=16 June 2016|work=The Washington Post|quote=Lawyers in the country and other experts disagree on whether federal law prescribes the death penalty for consensual homosexual sex or only for rape. In a recent Amnesty International report, the organization said it was not aware of any death sentences for homosexual acts.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The country has observed a moratorium on the execution of the death penalty since 1987.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|location=Geneva|pages=347}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Nigeria}} [[LGBT rights in Nigeria|Nigeria]], where several northern [[States of Nigeria|states]] have adopted [[sharia]]-based criminal laws, though no executions are known.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|location=Geneva|pages=359}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Saudi Arabia}} [[LGBT rights in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Arabia]], which does not have codified criminal laws.&lt;ref name=" ILGA 2015" /&gt; According to the country's interpretation of sharia, a married man who commits sodomy, or a non-Muslim who engages in sodomy with a Muslim, can be stoned to death.&lt;ref name=" WP"/&gt; There are unconfirmed reports that two cross-dressing Pakistani nationals were killed by Saudi authorities in 2017, which Saudi officials have denied.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt; No other executions are known.{{cn|date=August 2021}} Homosexuality in Saudi Arabia is proven by 4 eye witnesses who have seen the penetration or a self confession if these conditions are not met they can't be stoned but can be given discretionary punishments like lashing and jails.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=iranian.com: Keyan Keihani, A Brief History of Male Homosexuality in the Qur'an, Saudi Arabia, Iran, and Arab-Islamic Culture|url=http://www.iranian.com/Opinion/2005/December/Homosexuality/index.html|access-date=2021-09-27|website=www.iranian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* {{flagicon|Somalia}} [[LGBT rights in Somalia|Somalia]] ({{flag|Jubaland}}), where insurgents and Somali officials have imposed sharia-based law in some regions.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt;
* {{flagicon|United Arab Emirates}} [[LGBT rights in the United Arab Emirates|United Arab Emirates]] Article 354 of the Federal Penal Code states: "shall be sentenced to the death penalty, whoever used coercion in having sexual intercourse with a female or sodomy with a male."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=UAE Penal Code |url=https://www.adjd.gov.ae/sites/Authoring/AR/ELibrary%20Books/E-Library/PDFs/Penal%20Code.pdf |website=ADJD.gov.ae |access-date=1 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, same-sex relations fall under the traditional Sharia category of [[Zina]], which encompasses any sexual intercourse outside of marriage, all of which are banned in the UAE. Some courts have gone beyond codified laws and passed sentences of stoning or flogging, thus making same-sex relationships liable to the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Lucas Ramón Mendos|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|website=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex association|access-date=7 February 2020|edition=13th|year=2019|page=479|quote=However, through the Sharia code the death penalty applies to same-sex sexual relations through the offense of Zina, which applies to sexual relations outside of the marriage of any sort. Courts have gone beyond codified laws and imposed harsher sentences of stoning and flogging for Zina crimes.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Foundation|first=Thomson Reuters|title=Stoning- where is it legal?|url=https://news.news.trust.org/item/20130927160132-qt52c/|url-status=live|website=news.trust.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Yemen}} [[LGBT rights in Yemen|Yemen]] Punishment for [[homosexuality]] in Yemen can originate from the codified [[penal code]], or from people seeking to enforce traditional [[Islamic morality]]. Article 264 of the national penal code prohibits private consensual [[homosexual acts]] between adult men. The stipulated punishment in the law for unmarried men is 100 lashes and up to a year in prison. The law stipulates that married men convicted of homosexuality are to be [[Capital punishment in Yemen|put to death]] by stoning.&lt;ref name="gaylawnet.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gaylawnet.com/laws/ye.htm|title=GayLawNet - Laws - Yemen|website=Gaylawnet.com|accessdate=17 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 268 of the national penal code prohibits private consensual homosexual acts between adult women. The law stipulates that premeditated acts of [[lesbianism]] are punished with up to three years in prison.&lt;ref name="gaylawnet.com"/&gt; In addition to the penal code, punishment for homosexuality can originate from people seeking to enforce traditional morality within their own family or for the broader society. In vigilante cases such as this, the punishment for homosexuality is oftentimes death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipsnews.net/2013/08/no-place-for-gays-in-yemen|title=No Place for Gays in Yemen - Inter Press Service|website=Ipsnews.net|accessdate=17 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Extrajudicial killings==
{{further|Social cleansing|Honor killing|Significant acts of violence against LGBT people|Persecution of gay and bisexual men by ISIL}}
In some regions, gay people have been murdered by [[Islamist]] militias, such as [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]] in parts of Iraq, Libya, and Syria and the [[Houthi movement]] in Yemen.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Under ISIS: Where Being Gay Is Punished by Death |url=https://abcnews.go.com/International/isis-gay-punished-death/story?id=39826182 |work=ABC News |date=13 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anti-gay purges in Chechnya|Anti-gay purges in the Chechen Republic]], a predominantly [[Islam in Russia|Muslim region]] of Russia, have included [[forced disappearance]]s — secret abductions, imprisonment, and [[torture]] — by local Chechen authorities targeting persons based on their perceived [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=A Victim of the Anti-Gay Purge in Chechnya Speaks Out: 'The Truth Exists' |url=https://time.com/5633588/anti-gay-purge-chechnya-victim/ |work=Time |date=26 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of 100 men, who authorities detained on suspicion of being gay or bisexual, three have reportedly died after being held in what [[human rights]] groups and eyewitnesses have called [[concentration camp]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Smith |first1=Lydia |title=Chechnya detains 100 gay men in first concentration camps since the Holocaust |url=http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/chechnya-detains-100-gay-men-first-concentration-camps-since-holocaust-1616363|access-date=16 April 2017 |work=International Business Times UK |date=10 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Advocate"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Reynolds |first1=Daniel |title=Report: Chechnya Is Torturing Gay Men in Concentration Camps |url=http://www.advocate.com/world/2017/4/10/report-chechyna-torturing-gay-men-concentration-camps |access-date=16 April 2017 |work=The Advocate |date=10 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Report of vigilante executions, beatings, and torture&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/27/ugandan-gay-rights-activist-murdered|title=Ugandan gay rights activist David Kato found murdered|last=Rice|first=Xan|date=27 January 2011|work=The Guardian|access-date=1 August 2019|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="tbinternet.ohchr.org"&gt;https://tbinternet.ohchr.org/Treaties/CCPR/Shared%20Documents/GHA/INT_CCPR_ICO_GHA_21415_E.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/204346.pdf|title=LIBERIA 2012 HUMAN RIGHTS REPORT|last=United States Department of State|first=Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor|date=2012|website=state.gov|access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://archive.globalgayz.com/africa/senegal/senegal-gay-couple-brutally-assaulted-by-parents/|title=Senegal: Gay Couple Brutally Assaulted by Parents|website=archive.globalgayz.com|access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; have been reported in heavily Christian and Muslim regions of Africa, in countries such as [[Uganda]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Amid 'Kill the Gays' bill uproar, Ugandan LGBTQ activist is killed |url=https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/amid-kill-gays-bill-uproar-ugandan-lgbtq-activist-killed-n1067336 |work=NBC News |date=16 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[South Africa]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Born free, killed by hate - the price of being gay in South Africa |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-35967725 |work=BBC News |date=7 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kenya]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Gay men hacked with machetes and murdered in wave of hate crimes in Kenya |url=https://www.gaystarnews.com/article/whats-behind-series-recent-violent-hate-crimes-against-gays-kenya170713/ |work=Gay News |date=17 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Liberia]], [[Ghana]], [[Cameroon]], and [[Senegal]]. In these countries, police turn a blind eye&lt;ref name="tbinternet.ohchr.org"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.glaad.org/blog/cameroonian-lgbti-activist-found-tortured-death-home|title=Cameroonian LGBTI activist found tortured to death in home|date=17 July 2013|website=GLAAD|language=en|access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; or even are complicit in the anti-gay violence.&lt;ref&gt;http://blogs.cuit.columbia.edu/rightsviews/files/2015/03/The-Being-LGBT-in-West-Africa-Project-Final-Report.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{see also|List of people executed for homosexuality in Europe}}

=== Australia ===
Australian states and territories first passed laws against homosexuality during the [[History of Australia|colonial era]], and nineteenth-century colonial parliaments retained provisions which made homosexual activity a capital offence until 1861.&lt;ref name=carbery&gt;{{cite web |last=Carbery |first=Graham |title=Towards Homosexual Equality in Australian Criminal Law: A Brief History |year=2010 |edition=2nd |url=http://www.alga.org.au/files/towardsequality2ed.pdf |publisher=Australian Lesbian and Gay Archives Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most jurisdictions removed capital punishment as a sentence for homosexual activity, although in [[Victoria, Australia|Victoria]] it remained as such when committed while also inflicting [[bodily harm]] or to a person younger than the age of fourteen until 1949.&lt;ref name=carbery /&gt; The last person arrested for homosexual sex in Australia was a man in 1984 in Tasmania.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://hrlibrary.umn.edu/undocs/html/vws488.htm|title=Toonen v. Australia, Communication No. 488/1992, U.N. Doc CCPR/C/50/D/488/1992 (1994).|website=hrlibrary.umn.edu|access-date=8 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last part of Australia to legalise consensual homosexual sex between adults was [[Tasmania]] in 1997. In 2017, same-sex marriage was legalised by the [[Government of Australia|Australian government]].{{fact|date=February 2021}}

Seven men are known in Australian history to have been executed for sodomy; however, six of those seven cases involved the sexual abuse of minors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.utas.edu.au/library/companion_to_tasmanian_history/H/Homosexuality.htm|title=Homosexuality|website=www.utas.edu.au|access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Those six cases being:
# John Mead, hanged at Sydney on 29 November 1836 for the forcible sodomy of a ten year old boy
# William Gibson, hanged at Launceston on 31 January 1859 for sodomy of a ten year old boy
# Hendrick Whitnalder, hanged at Hobart on 20 February 1863 for sodomy of a fourteen year old boy
# John Kelly, hanged at Beechworth on 4 May 1867 for sodomy of an eighteen month old boy
# Thomas Ross, hanged at Launceston on 30 January 1861 for an "unnatural crime" against a "little boy" of unknown age
# Dennis Collins, hanged at Launceston on 11 August 1863 for an "unnatural crime" against a seven year old boy&lt;/ref&gt; In the remaining case, Alexander Browne was hanged at Sydney on 22 December 1828 for sodomy with his shipmate William Lyster on the whaler ''Royal Sovereign''; Lyster was also convicted and sentenced to death, but his sentence was commuted before execution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Unfit for Publication press cuttings list|url=http://www.alga.org.au/files/ufpnewssources.pdf|website=Australian Lesbian &amp; Gay Archives}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, Joseph Fogg was hanged at Hobart on 26 February 1830 for an "unnatural crime", but the nature of the crime is unclear.&lt;ref name=26feb1830&gt;{{cite news|title=Executions|url=http://trove.nla.gov.au/newspaper/article/8644929|access-date=9 March 2017|work=Colonial Times|date=26 February 1830|location=Hobart|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Germany ===
During the period of [[Nazi Germany]] from 1933 to 1945, homosexual men were persecuted with thousands being imprisoned in [[Nazi concentration camps|concentration camps]] (and eventually [[extermination camp]]s) by the Nazi regime. Roughly 5,000–15,000 were sent to the concentration camps, with the death rate being estimated to be as high as 60%. Homosexuals in the camps suffered an unusual degree of cruelty by their captors, including being used as target practice on shooting ranges.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite book|title=The Racial State: Germany, 1933-1945|last=Burleigh|first=Michael|date=1991|publisher=Cambridge University Press|others=Wippermann, Wolfgang, Mazal Holocaust Collection.|isbn=0521391148|location=Cambridge [England]|oclc=22597244|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/racialstate00mich}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Giles|first=Geoffrey J|title=Social Outsiders in Nazi Germany|date=2001|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton, New Jersey|page=240}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Pink Triangle: The Nazi War Against Homosexuals|last=Plant|first=Richard|date=2013|publisher=Henry Holt and Company|isbn=9781429936934|location=New York|oclc=872608428}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sudan ===
In July 2020, the sodomy law that previously punished gay men with up to 100 lashes for the first offence, five years in jail for the second and the death penalty the third time around was abolished, with new legislation reducing the penalty to prison terms ranging from five years to life. Sudanese LGBT+ activists hailed the reform as a 'great first step', but said it was not enough yet, and the end goal should be the decriminalisation of gay sexual activity altogether.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-sudan-lgbt-rights-trfn/great-first-step-as-sudan-lifts-death-penalty-and-flogging-for-gay-sex-idUSKCN24H30J |title='Great first step' as Sudan lifts death penalty and flogging for gay sex |author=Ban Barkawi, Rachel Savage |publisher=Reuters |date=16 July 2020 |access-date=17 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United Kingdom ===
From 1533, under the [[Buggery Act 1533]], capital felony for any person to "commit the detestable and abominable vice of buggery with mankind or beast", was enacted, repealed and re-enacted several times by [[the Crown]], until it was reinstated permanently in 1563. Homosexual activity remained a capital offence until 1861.&lt;ref name="Colonial"&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1061&amp;context=englishfacpubs|journal=Journal of Homosexuality|volume=1|issue=3|date=1976|title=Homosexuals and the Death Penalty in Colonial America|author=Louis Crompton|access-date=20 May 2016|doi=10.1300/j082v01n03_03|pages=277–293|pmid=798008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last execution took place on 27 November 1835 when [[James Pratt and John Smith]] were hanged outside [[Newgate Prison]] in London.

=== United States ===
{{See also|Sodomy laws in the United States}}
During the [[Colonial history of the United States|colonial era]] of [[History of the United States|American history]], the various European nations which [[European colonization of the Americas|established colonies]] in the Americas brought their pre-existing laws against homosexuality (which included capital punishment) with them. The establishment of the [[United States]] after their victory in the [[American Revolutionary War|Revolutionary War]] did not bring about any changes in the status of capital punishment as a sentence for being convicted of homosexual behavior. Beginning in the 19th century, the various state legislatures passed legislation which ended the status of capital punishment being used for those who were convicted of homosexual behavior. [[South Carolina]] was the last state, in 1873, to repeal the death penalty for homosexual behaviour from its statute books. The number of times the penalty was carried out is unknown. Records show there were at least two executions, and a number of more convictions with vague labels, such as "crimes against nature".&lt;ref name="Colonial" /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{criminalization of homosexuality}}
[[Category:Capital punishment]]
[[Category:Criminalization of homosexuality]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>