<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241122003000|1258854401" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="50402549" pageid="50402549" ns="0" title="Capital punishment for homosexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-22T13:50:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|none}}
{{use dmy dates|date=July 2024}}
{{LGBT rights sidebar}}{{Discrimination sidebar}}[[File:Death Penalty for Consensual Homosexual Activity.png|thumb|300px|{{legend|#841B2D|Law explicitly provides for death penalty for sex between consenting adults of the same sex}}{{legend|#FF8C00|Law is unclear if death penalty is a legally possible punishment for same-sex acts, although such acts are criminalized&lt;ref name="ilga frameworks"&gt;{{Citation |title=Legal Frameworks: Criminalisation of consensual same-sex sexual acts |url=https://database.ilga.org/criminalisation-consensual-same-sex-sexual-acts |at=Methodology – Section 9. Death Penalty: Issues of legal certainty |access-date=16 October 2023|work=ILGA World Database |publisher=[[International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association]] |postscript=.}} {{blockquote|text="...{{nbsp}}'full legal certainty' is understood as the absence of disputes about whether the death penalty can be legally imposed for consensual same-sex sexual conduct. This legal certainty may be derived from the existence of written, codified laws unequivocally prescribing the death penalty for same-sex conduct{{nbsp}}... Conversely, the lack of clear provisions mandating the death penalty for consensual same-sex sexual acts, the existence of disputes between scholars and experts with regard to the interpretation of ambiguous provisions, and the need for judicial interpretation of certain 'generic' crimes to encompass consensual same-sex sexual acts has led ILGA World to classify the remaining five UN Member States{{nbsp}}... as jurisdictions where there is no full legal certainty.{{pb}} "It bears mentioning that in all five states{{nbsp}}... there is full certainty that the alternative in default of the death penalty is always a provision of law criminalising consensual same-sex sexual acts with corporal punishment, imprisonment and/or a fine. Therefore, this uncertainty does not hinge on 'criminalisation vs non-criminalisation', but rather on the severity of the penalties imposed."}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|name="legal uncertainty"}}}}]]
[[Capital punishment]] as [[criminalization of homosexuality|a criminal punishment]] for [[homosexuality]] has been implemented by a number of countries in their history. It is a legal punishment in several countries and regions, all of which have [[sharia]]-based criminal laws, except for [[LGBT rights in Uganda|Uganda]].

Gay people also face [[extrajudicial killings]] by state and non-state actors in some states and regions of the world. Locations where this is known to occur include [[LGBT rights in Iraq|Iraq]], [[LGBT rights in Libya|Libya]], [[LGBT rights in Syria|Syria]], the [[Anti-gay purges in Chechnya|Chechnya]] region of [[LGBT rights in Russia|Russia]], and the [[Gay panic defense#United States|United States]]. Imposition of the death penalty for homosexuality may be classified as [[judicial murder]] of gay people.

==In current state laws==
{{Further|LGBT rights by country or territory|LGBT in Islam|Capital punishment in Islam|Sodomy law|Sharia#Islamization}}
The [[International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association]] (ILGA) reported in 2020 that in at least six UN member states—Brunei, Iran, Mauritania, Nigeria ([[Sharia in Nigeria|some states in northern Nigeria]]), Saudi Arabia, and Yemen—homosexual activity is punishable by death.&lt;ref name="ilga frameworks"/&gt; These six were joined in 2023 by Uganda, which became the only Christian-majority country with capital punishment for some consensual same-sex acts.&lt;ref&gt;{{multiref2|1={{cite news |last1=Assheton |first1=Richard |title=Uganda anti-homosexuality bill sets death penalty as punishment |url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/uganda-anti-homosexuality-bill-death-penalty-nsbm3m7k0 |newspaper=The Times |date=23 March 2023 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20230531032804/https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/uganda-anti-homosexuality-bill-death-penalty-nsbm3m7k0 |archive-date=31 May 2023}}|2={{cite web |title=Uganda: LGBTQ+ rights in Uganda |url=https://www.rainbowfund.org/uganda-lgbtq |website=Rainbow World Fund |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20230817052743/https://www.rainbowfund.org/uganda-lgbtq |archive-date=17 August 2023}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; Excepting Uganda, all countries currently having capital punishment as a potential penalty for homosexual activity base those laws on interpretations of [[Islam]]ic teachings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |date=March 2021 |archive-date=29 June 2023 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20230629141336/https://www.uscirf.gov/sites/default/files/2021-03/2021%20Factsheet%20-%20Sharia%20and%20LGBTI.pdf |author=((USCIRF)) |title=Shari'a and LGBTI Persons: The Use of Shari'a as Religious Justification for Capital Punishment Against LGBTI Persons |url=https://www.uscirf.gov/sites/default/files/2021-03/2021%20Factsheet%20-%20Sharia%20and%20LGBTI.pdf |url-status=live |publisher=[[United States Commission on International Religious Freedom]] |place=Washington D.C. |page=2 |id=Factsheet}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ilga 2020"/&gt;{{rp|25, 31}} One source states that in 2007 alone, five countries had carried out executions for homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Asal |first1=Victor |last2=Sommer |first2=Udi |title=Legal Path Dependence and the Long Arm of the Religious State: Sodomy Provisions and Gay Rights across Nations and over Time |date=2016 |publisher=[[SUNY Press]] |isbn=978-1-4384-6325-4 |page=65 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zOdNDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA65 |via=[[Google Books]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2020, the ILGA stated that Iran and Saudi Arabia were the only countries in which government-sanctioned executions for consensual same-sex sexual activity had taken place since 2000.&lt;ref name="ilga 2020"/&gt;{{rp|38,49,74}}

===Complete legal certainty===
For the countries listed below, no dispute or uncertainty regarding the legal status of capital punishment as a possible penalty for same-sex sexual conduct exists. While clearly allowable, the application or enforcement of the legally-sanctioned death penalty varies across the jurisdictions, with some not having imposed or enacted the penalty for many years or decades, and some never having done so, while others have carried out executions recently and some do so regularly.&lt;ref name="ilga frameworks"/&gt;

As of March 2023, the following jurisdictions allow the death penalty to be imposed for homosexual conduct:
* {{flagicon|Brunei}} [[LGBT rights in Brunei|Brunei]]. The {{not a typo|{{lang|kxd|Syariah|italic=no}}}} Penal Code Order ({{langx|kxd|Syariah|lit=sharia}}), prescribes death by stoning for sex acts between men (in abeyance under a [[moratorium (law)|moratorium]], which may be lifted without warning at any time),&lt;ref name="April2019"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-47769964|title=Brunei implements stoning to death under anti-LGBT laws|work=BBC News |date=April 3, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="CNN-20190505"&gt;{{cite news |url=https://edition.cnn.com/2019/05/05/asia/brunei-lgbt-death-penalty-intl/index.html|title=Brunei backs down on gay sex death penalty after international backlash|date=6 May 2019 |access-date=6 May 2019|work=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="May2019"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.abc.net.au/news/2019-05-08/brunei-moratorium-death-penalty-gay-sex-remains-illegal/11087848|title=Why has Brunei suddenly backflipped on death penalty for gay sex?|work=ABC News |date=8 May 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{multiref2|1={{cite report |author1=Office of International Religious Freedom|author2=United States Department of State |title=2021 Report on International Religious Freedom: Brunei |url=https://www.state.gov/reports/2021-report-on-international-religious-freedom/brunei/ |publisher=United States Department of State |date=June 2, 2022 |quote=A 2019 de facto moratorium on the death penalty remained in place.}}|2={{cite news |last1=Kelleher |first1=Patrick |title=11 countries where LGBTQ+ people still face death penalty urged to abolish it |url=https://www.pinknews.co.uk/2022/05/17/lgbtq-death-penalty-idahobit/ |work=PinkNews |date=17 May 2022 |quote=According to Human Dignity Trust, the death penalty is implemented in Iran, Northern Nigeria, Saudi Arabia, Somalia and Yemen, and remains a "legal possibility" in Afghanistan, Brunei, Mauritania, Pakistan, Qatar and UAE.}}|3={{cite news |last1=Yee |first1=Claudia |title=What explains Brunei's expansion of the death penalty in 2019? |url=https://www.monash.edu/law/research/eleos/blog/eleos-justice-blog-posts/what-explains-bruneis-expansion-of-the-death-penalty-in-2019 |work=ELEOS |publisher=Monash University |language=en |date=31 August 2021}}|4={{cite news |last1=Patto |first1=Kasthuri |title=ASEAN Summit Should Draw Attention to Brunei's Appalling Human Rights Record |url=https://thediplomat.com/2021/10/asean-summit-should-draw-attention-to-bruneis-appalling-human-rights-record/ |work=The Diplomat: Know the Asia-Pacific |date=29 October 2021 |quote=The moratorium is still in place, but the human rights situation in Brunei remains appalling.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; De facto penalty: Seven years in prison and 30 lashes for married men.
* {{flagicon|Iran}} [[LGBT rights in Iran|Iran]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015–17"&gt;{{multiref2|1={{cite report| author3=ILGA World |first1=Aengus |last1=Carroll |last2=Itaborahy |first2=Lucas Paoli|title=''State-Sponsored Homophobia'': A World Survey of Laws: Criminalisation, protection and recognition of same-sex love |publisher=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association |location=Geneva |edition = 12th |url=https://ilga.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2017_WEB.pdf |access-date=15 July 2024 |date=May 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190422204557/https://ilga.org/downloads/2017/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2017_WEB.pdf |archive-date=22 April 2019}}|2={{cite report |last1=Carroll |first1=Aengus |last2=Itaborahy |first2=Lucas Paoli |title=''State Sponsored Homophobia 2015'': A world survey of laws: Criminalisation, protection and recognition of same-sex love |date=May 2015 |publisher=ILGA |location=Geneva |url=https://ilga.org/resources/state-sponsored-homophobia-report-2015-ilga/ |edition=10th}} {{webarchive|date=18 June 2024 |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20240618220829/https://ilga.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2015.pdf}} }}&lt;/ref&gt; Male-male anal intercourse is declared a capital offense in Iran's ''Islamic Penal Code'', enacted in 1991. Articles 233 through 241 criminalise both female and male same-sex activity; for a first offence, the death penalty only applies to some cases of male-male penile-anal intercourse, with female-female activity and other cases of male-male activity being punished by flogging instead of execution. Under the combination of articles 136 and 238, a woman convicted for the fourth time of the crime of ''musaheqeh'' ([[tribadism]]) is to be executed; there is no death penalty for non-genital-genital female-female sexual conduct.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Refugees|first=United Nations High Commissioner for|title=Refworld {{!}} Iran: Islamic Penal Code|url=https://www.refworld.org/docid/518a19404.html|access-date=20 July 2020|website=Refworld|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though the grounds for execution in Iran are difficult to track, there is evidence that several gay men were executed in 2005–2006 and 2016 mostly on alleged charges of rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Asal |first1=Victor |title=Legal Path Dependence and the Long Arm of the Religious State: Sodomy Provisions and Gay Rights Across Nations and Over Time |last2=Sommer |first2=Udi |date=December 2016 |publisher=State University of New York Press |isbn=9781438463230 |page=64}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=economist&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Economist|title=How homosexuality became a crime in the Middle East|date=6 June 2018|url=https://www.economist.com/open-future/2018/06/06/how-homosexuality-became-a-crime-in-the-middle-east}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Mauritania}} [[LGBT rights in Mauritania|Mauritania]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015–17" /&gt; According to a 1984 law, Muslim men can be stoned for engaging in homosexual sex, though no executions have occurred so far.&lt;ref name="WP"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/|title=Analysis – Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death|first1=Max|last1=Bearak|first2=Darla|last2=Cameron|date=16 June 2016|newspaper=The Washington Post|quote=Lawyers in the country and other experts disagree on whether federal law prescribes the death penalty for consensual homosexual sex or only for rape. In a recent Amnesty International report, the organization said it was not aware of any death sentences for homosexual acts.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The country has observed a moratorium on the execution of the death penalty since 1987.&lt;ref name="ilga 2019"/&gt;{{rp|347}}
* {{flagicon|Nigeria}} [[LGBT rights in Nigeria|Nigeria]]. Several northern [[States of Nigeria|states]] have adopted [[sharia]]-based criminal laws, though no executions are known.&lt;ref name="ilga 2019"/&gt;{{rp|359}}
* {{flagicon|Saudi Arabia}} [[LGBT rights in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Arabia]]. The kingdom does not have codified criminal laws.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015–17"/&gt; According to the country's interpretation of sharia, a married man who commits sodomy, or a non-Muslim who engages in sodomy with a Muslim, can be stoned to death.&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt; There are unconfirmed reports that two cross-dressing Pakistani nationals were killed by Saudi authorities in 2017, which Saudi officials have denied.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015–17" /&gt; Verified executions occurred in 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://metro.co.uk/2019/04/27/five-men-beheaded-saudi-arabia-gay-according-confessions-extracted-torture-9328194/ | title=Five men beheaded by Saudi Arabia were gay in claims from 'tortured confession' | date=27 April 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.pinknews.co.uk/2019/04/29/man-executed-saudi-arabia-gay/ | title=Man executed in Saudi Arabia admitted to gay sex in "invented" confession | date=29 April 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexuality in Saudi Arabia is proven by four eyewitnesses who have seen the penetration, or a self confession; if these conditions are not met they can not be stoned but can be given discretionary punishments like lashing and imprisonment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=iranian.com: Keyan Keihani, A Brief History of Male Homosexuality in the Qur'an, Saudi Arabia, Iran, and Arab-Islamic Culture|url=http://www.iranian.com/Opinion/2005/December/Homosexuality/index.html|access-date=2021-09-27|website=www.iranian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* {{flagicon|Uganda}} [[LGBT rights in Uganda|Uganda]]. In May 2023, the [[Anti-Homosexuality Act, 2023]] was signed into law, prescribing the death penalty for certain acts of "aggravated homosexuality". These are defined as: those who have homosexual sex with minors, with persons aged over 75 years, persons with disabilities, without or unable to consent, or with a person who is mentally ill. Anyone convicted of homosexuality more than once, or having infected others with a serious infectious disease such as HIV/AIDS, are also liable to be convicted as perpetrators of "aggravated homosexuality".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Okiror |first=Samuel |date=2023-05-29 |title=Ugandan president signs anti-LGBTQ+ law with death penalty for same-sex acts |language=en-GB |work=The Guardian |url=https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2023/may/29/ugandan-president-yoweri-museveni-anti-lgbtq-bill-death-penalty |access-date=2023-08-28 |issn=0261-3077}}
* Before the Act was promulgated, there was a draft version, the ''Anti-Homosexuality Bill'' (Bill no. 3 of 2023), that generated international news coverage. Had it passed intact it would have criminalised merely identifying as gay or non-binary, stipulating that "hold[ing] out as a lesbian, gay, transgender, a queer or any other sexual or gender identity that is contrary to the binary categories of male and female" was committing "an offence of homosexuality" and thus liable to the penalty of ten years in prison. This provision, 2(1)(d), was excluded from the Act that was passed and signed into law.
** {{citation |title=Bill No. 3 – The Anti-Homosexuality Bill 2023 |work=The Uganda Gazette: Bills Supplement |date=3 March 2023 |volume=CXVI |issue=16 |page=5 |url=https://www.jurist.org/news/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2023/03/Anti-Homosexuality-Bill-2023.pdf |publisher=Government of Uganda}}
** {{Cite news |first1=Larry |last1=Madowo |last2=Nicholls |first2=Catherine |date=2023-03-21 |title=Uganda parliament passes bill criminalizing identifying as LGBTQ, imposes death penalty for some offenses |url=https://www.cnn.com/2023/03/21/africa/uganda-lgbtq-law-passes-intl/index.html |access-date=2023-03-22 |work=CNN |language=en}}
** {{Cite news |last=Atuhaire |first=Patience |date=2023-03-21 |title=Uganda Anti-Homosexuality bill: Life in prison for saying you're gay |language=en-GB |work=BBC News |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-65034343 |access-date=2023-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Yemen}} [[LGBT rights in Yemen|Yemen]]. Punishment for [[homosexuality]] in Yemen can originate from the codified [[penal code]], or from people seeking to enforce traditional [[Islamic morality]]. Article 264 of the national penal code prohibits private consensual [[homosexual acts]] between adult men. The stipulated punishment in the law for unmarried men is 100 lashes and up to a year in prison. The law stipulates that married men convicted of homosexuality are to be [[Capital punishment in Yemen|put to death]] by stoning.&lt;ref name="gaylawnet.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gaylawnet.com/laws/ye.htm|title=GayLawNet – Laws – Yemen|website=Gaylawnet.com|access-date=17 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 268 of the national penal code prohibits private consensual homosexual acts between adult women. The law stipulates that premeditated acts of [[lesbianism]] are punished with up to three years in prison.&lt;ref name="gaylawnet.com"/&gt; In addition to the penal code, punishment for homosexuality can originate from people seeking to enforce traditional morality within their own family or for the broader society. In vigilante cases such as this, the punishment for homosexuality is oftentimes death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipsnews.net/2013/08/no-place-for-gays-in-yemen|title=No Place for Gays in Yemen – Inter Press Service|website=Ipsnews.net|date=16 August 2013 |access-date=17 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legality unclear===
According to the ILGA, there are five UN-member countries where the status of the death penalty as a punishment for same-sex sexual conduct is uncertain. This may be because experts or legal scholars dispute the effect of legal provisions, or because the laws relied upon to potentially sanction the death penalty are the {{transl|ar|zina}} provisions which relate to all sexual behaviours outside marriage, with applicability to homosexual relations uncertain, and so far, only theoretical.&lt;ref name="ilga 2020" /&gt;{{rp|25}}

{{As of|2020}}, these jurisdictions are:
* {{flagicon|Afghanistan}} [[LGBT rights in Afghanistan|Afghanistan]]. The [[Islamic Republic of Afghanistan]] enacted a Penal Code in February 2018 explicitly criminalising same-sex sexual conduct, stipulating prison sentences as the punishment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last=Human Rights Watch |title=Afghanistan: Events of 2020 |date=2020-11-23 |url=https://www.hrw.org/world-report/2021/country-chapters/afghanistan |work=English |language=en |access-date=2022-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the [[ILGA]] noted that a "high-profile Islamic scholar" has claimed there was a "broad consensus amongst scholars that execution was the appropriate punishment if homosexual acts could be proven", this could only be achieved, in theory, under {{transl|ar|[[zina]]}} provisions, applicable to all sexual contact outside marriage.&lt;ref name="ilga 2019"/&gt;{{rp|429}} The sharia category of {{transl|ar|zina}} (illicit sexual intercourse) according to some traditional Islamic [[Madhhab|legal schools]] may entail the ''[[Hudud|hadd]]'' (sharia-prescribed) punishment of stoning, when strict evidential requirements are met. The [[Hanafi]] school, prevalent in Afghanistan, does not regard homosexual acts as a ''hadd'' crime, although Afghan judges may have potentially applied the death penalty for a number of reasons. No known death sentences for homosexuality occurred after the end of Taliban rule in 2001.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost.com"&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/ |title=Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death |newspaper=The Washington Post |date=16 June 2016 |access-date=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.deathpenaltyworldwide.org/country-search-post.cfm?country=Afghanistan |title=The Death Penalty in Afghanistan |publisher=Death Penalty Worldwide |access-date=25 August 2017 |archive-date=14 September 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170914020231/http://www.deathpenaltyworldwide.org/country-search-post.cfm?country=Afghanistan |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, following the [[2021 Taliban offensive|Taliban takeover of Afghanistan]] in 2021, fears of reprisal including death for those suspected of homosexuality were renewed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://thehill.com/policy/international/569741-they-will-kill-us-if-they-find-us-lgbt-afghans-fear-new-taliban-regime |title='They will kill us if they find us': LGBT Afghans fear new Taliban regime |newspaper=The Hill |date=29 August 2021 |access-date=6 September 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Taliban spokesman told ''[[Reuters]]'' in 2021: "LGBT{{nbsp}}... That's against our Sharia law".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=OPENLY |title=Taliban say gay rights will not be respected under Islamic law |url=https://www.openlynews.com/i/?id=074ee892-e6ea-497b-85d5-206b794bd1aa |access-date=2022-12-03 |website=OPENLY}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Taliban judge said that "For homosexuals, there can only be two punishments: either stoning, or he must stand behind a wall that will fall down on him".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=This Taliban judge orders stoning, hanging, hands chopped of |url=https://www.bild.de/politik/international/bild-international/this-taliban-judge-orders-stoning-hanging-hands-chopped-of-77067554.bild.html |access-date=2022-12-03 |website=bild.de |language=de}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |date=2022-01-26 |title=LGBT People in Afghanistan After the Taliban Takeover |url=https://www.hrw.org/report/2022/01/26/even-if-you-go-skies-well-find-you/lgbt-people-afghanistan-after-taliban-takeover |journal=Human Rights Watch |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Pakistan}} [[LGBT rights in Pakistan|Pakistan]]. [[Hudood]] punishments for homosexuality include execution. However, the Hudood Ordinances have not been enforced "since the 1985 lifting of martial law", according to the U.S. State Department, and there are no known cases of Hudood being applied to same-sex sexual conduct. No known executions for homosexual activity have ever occurred in Pakistan.&lt;ref name="ilga 2020"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Pakistan 2021 State"&gt;{{cite report |author1=((Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor))|quote= The penalty for conviction of same-sex relations is a fine, two years to life imprisonment, or both{{nbsp}}... the Hudood Ordinance of 1979 criminalizes sexual intercourse outside of marriage in accordance with sharia, with penalties of whipping or, potentially, death. There have been disputes as to whether the Hudood Ordinance notionally applies to both opposite-sex and same-sex conduct, but there were no known cases of the government applying the ordinance to same-sex conduct, and there have been no known cases of executions for homosexuality.|title=2021 Country Reports on Human Rights Practices: Pakistan |chapter-url=https://www.state.gov/reports/2021-country-reports-on-human-rights-practices/pakistan/|date=2021 |publisher=United States Department of State |chapter=Section 6. Discrimination and Societal Abuses}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Qatar}} [[LGBT rights in Qatar|Qatar]]. Same-sex sexual activity is prohibited under the Penal Code 2004, which criminalises acts of "sodomy" and "sexual intercourse" between people of the same sex. These provisions carry a maximum penalty of seven years' imprisonment. Both men and women are criminalised under this law. The death penalty may be applicable to Muslims, for certain types of extramarital sex regardless of the gender of the participants. However, there is no evidence that the death penalty has been applied for consensual same-sex relations in private taking place between adults.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost.com"/&gt;
* {{flagicon|Somalia}} [[LGBT rights in Somalia|Somalia]]. Insurgents and Somali officials have imposed sharia-based law in several southern states. In territories controlled by [[al-Shabaab (militant group)|al-Shabaab]] homosexuality is [[Capital punishment in Somalia|punishable by death]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015–17" /&gt;&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt;
* {{flagicon|United Arab Emirates}} [[LGBT rights in the United Arab Emirates|United Arab Emirates]]. Same-sex sexual acts and expressions of sexual- and gender-identity are dealt with under the Federal Penal Code Articles 356 ("Voluntary debasement") and 358–359 ("Flagrant indecent acts"), prescribing prison sentences of between one and 15 years.{{efn|name="article 354"}} On occasion, Sharia courts have gone beyond codified laws and imposed sentences of stoning or flogging for {{transl|ar|[[zina]]}} crimes, thus theoretically making same-sex sexual activity liable to the death penalty, as occurring outside marriage. All cases of these rare sentences have involved heterosexual activity; all have, so far, been overturned.&lt;ref name="ilga 2019"&gt;{{cite report |author=Lucas Ramón Mendos |title=State-Sponsored Homophobia |url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf |publisher=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association |access-date=7 February 2020 |edition=13th |date=2019 |pages=138–141, 429, 479–481}} "Criminalisation - United Arab Emirates: Provisions in force", p. 479: {{blockquote|"However, it is through the Sharia code that the death penalty theoretically can apply to same-sex sexual relations through the offence of {{transl|ar|Zina}}, which applies to sexual relations outside of marriage of any sort. However, it appears that the law is used in rape cases only although in some cases courts have gone beyond codified laws and imposed harsher sentences of stoning and flogging for {{transl|ar|Zina}} crimes."}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ilga 2020"&gt;{{cite report|author1=((ILGA World))|author2=Lucas Ramón Mendos |author3=Kellyn Botha|author4=Rafael Carrano Lelis|author5=Enrique López de la Peña|author6=Ilia Savelev|author7=Daron Tan |title=State-Sponsored Homophobia report: 2020 global legislation overview update |url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_World_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_report_global_legislation_overview_update_December_2020.pdf |edition=14th revised |publisher=ILGA |location=Geneva |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20201215114401/https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_World_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_report_global_legislation_overview_update_December_2020.pdf|archive-date=15 December 2020 |language=en |date=14 December 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; While adherence of the country's legal system to [[sharia]] allows [[Capital punishment in the United Arab Emirates|for capital punishment for same-sex]] sexual activity— as with other sex acts by married persons outside marriage under {{transliteration|ar|[[zina]]}} provisions —there are no known instances of imposition of the death penalty {{as of|2020|lc=yes}}, according to the British non-profit, [[Human Dignity Trust]],{{efn|name="trust since 2015"}}&lt;ref name="hdt"&gt;{{cite web |title=United Arab Emirates: Criminalisation - Enforcement 2020 |url=https://www.humandignitytrust.org/country-profile/united-arab-emirates/ |website=Human Dignity Trust |date=2020 |access-date=7 August 2022 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amnesty International, the {{abbr|ILGA|International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association}}, and the U.S. Department of State.&lt;ref name="uae 2021 US State"&gt;{{cite report |author1=((Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor)) |title=2021 Country Reports on Human Rights Practices: United Arab Emirates|chapter-url=https://www.state.gov/reports/2021-country-reports-on-human-rights-practices/united-arab-emirates/|date=2021 |publisher=United States Department of State |chapter=Section 6. Discrimination and Societal Abuses}} {{blockquote|"Both civil law and sharia criminalize consensual same-sex sexual conduct between adults. Under sharia individuals{{nbsp}}... could be subject to the death penalty. Dubai's penal code allows for up to a 10-year prison sentence for conviction of such activity, while Abu Dhabi's penal code allows for up to a 14-year prison sentence. There were no known reports of arrests or prosecutions for consensual same-sex conduct" [in 2021].}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ilga 2020"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Batha|first=Emma|publisher=Thomson Reuters Foundation |title=Stoning - where does it happen?|date=29 September 2013 |work=TRF News |url=https://news.trust.org/item/20130927165059-w9g0i/|quote=...{{nbsp}}sentences were later reduced to one year and deportation.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{multiref2|1={{cite web |title=UAE Penal Code |url=https://www.adjd.gov.ae/sites/Authoring/AR/ELibrary%20Books/E-Library/PDFs/Penal%20Code.pdf |website=ADJD.gov.ae |access-date=1 February 2020}}|2={{cite act |article=354 (Prohibition of Sexual Violence)|title=Federal Law 3 of the Penal Code |date=1987 |url=https://evaw-global-database.unwomen.org/pt/countries/asia/united-arab-emirates/1987/article-354-of-federal-law-3-of-the-penal-code-prohibition-of-sexual-violence|access-date=2020-11-24|via=Global Database on Violence against Women: UN Women}}|3={{citation|title=Official Gazette of the United Arab Emirates|date=8 December 1987 |url=https://elaws.moj.gov.ae/UAE-MOJ_LC-En/00_PENALTIES%20AND%20CRIMINAL%20MEASURES/UAE-LC-En_1987-12-08_00003_Kait.html?val=EL1 |page=7 |issue=182|publisher=Ministry of Justice, UAE|language=en}} [https://www.moj.gov.ae/en/laws-and-legislation.aspx UAE Ministry of Justice] {{blockquote|Without prejudice to the provisions of the Law on juvenile delinquents and displaced, death penalty shall be imposed on whoever used coercion in having sexual intercourse with a female or sodomy with a male. |Ministry of Justice, UAE (English version as provided)|''Official Gazette of UAE'', issue 182 (1987)}}|4=The [[International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association]] (ILGA) report that there are differing opinions on the effect of this provision, saying:	
{{blockquote|1=...{{nbsp}}some scholars{{nbsp}}... interpret{{nbsp}}... [this provision] as applicable to consensual same-sex sexual activity, while others hold that 'it takes a stretch to read [it] as a criminalisation of consensual sex with the Arabic word for ''coercive'' syntactically placed as it is'.|2=ILGA World|3=''State-Sponsored Homophobia'' (2020), p. 82}}|5=This may relate solely to cases of sexual violence, but there is no certainty about its interpretation.|6={{cite web |title=United Arab Emirates LGBTI Resources |url=https://www.amerainternational.org/united-arab-emirates-lgbti-resources/ |website=AMERA International}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Extrajudicial executions ==

{{further|Social cleansing|Honor killing|Significant acts of violence against LGBT people|Persecution of gay and bisexual men by ISIL}}
In some regions, gay people have been murdered by [[Islamist]] militias and terrorist groups, such as [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]] in parts of Iraq, Libya, and Syria, the [[Houthi movement]] in Yemen, [[Hamas]] in the [[Gaza Strip]] as well as in [[Malaysia]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015–17" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Under ISIS: Where Being Gay Is Punished by Death |url=https://abcnews.go.com/International/isis-gay-punished-death/story?id=39826182 |work=ABC News |date=13 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="advocate2016"&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Broverman|first=Neal|date=2 March 2016|title=Hamas Leader Accused of Gay Sex, Killed|url=https://www.advocate.com/world/2016/3/01/hamas-leader-accused-gay-sex-killed|magazine=[[The Advocate (LGBT magazine)|The Advocate]]|access-date=2016-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Persecution by Islamic State ===
{{see also| Persecution of gay and bisexual men by ISIL }} &lt;!-- this is in the intro but not covered clearly: ... Persecution of MSM by the so-called Islamic State --&gt;

=== Chechnya ===
{{Further| Anti-gay purges in Chechnya }}

Anti-gay purges in [[Chechnya]], a predominantly [[Islam in Russia|Muslim region of Russia]], have included [[forced disappearance]]s—secret abductions, imprisonment, and [[torture]]—by local Chechen authorities targeting persons based on their perceived [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |title=A Victim of the Anti-Gay Purge in Chechnya Speaks Out: 'The Truth Exists' |url=https://time.com/5633588/anti-gay-purge-chechnya-victim/ |magazine=Time |date=26 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of one hundred men, whom authorities detained on suspicion of being gay or bisexual, three have reportedly died after being held in what [[human rights]] groups and eyewitnesses have called [[concentration camp]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Smith |first1=Lydia |title=Chechnya detains 100 gay men in first concentration camps since the Holocaust |url=http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/chechnya-detains-100-gay-men-first-concentration-camps-since-holocaust-1616363|access-date=16 April 2017 |work=International Business Times UK |date=10 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Advocate"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Reynolds |first1=Daniel |title=Report: Chechnya Is Torturing Gay Men in Concentration Camps |url=http://www.advocate.com/world/2017/4/10/report-chechyna-torturing-gay-men-concentration-camps |access-date=16 April 2017 |work=The Advocate |date=10 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Iraq ===
{{Broader| Extrajudicial killings in Iraq }}

Extrajudicial killings have occurred in [[Iraq]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2022/03/23/iraq-impunity-violence-against-lgbt-people|title=Impunity for Violence Against LGBT People|website=Human Rights Watch|date=23 March 2022 |language=en|access-date=2022-06-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cases include abductions, torture, rape and murder by vigilante mobs, militia and other perpetrators. LGBT people living in fear of their lives, campaigners [[Human Rights Watch]] (HRW) and IraQueer found. HRW's LGBT rights researcher Rasha Younes said: "LGBT Iraqis live in constant fear of being hunted down and killed by armed groups with impunity, as well as arrest and violence by Iraqi police, making their lives unliveable."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-60859049 | title=LGBT people in Iraq live in fear of lives - HRW | work=BBC News | date=17 May 2022 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Malaysia ===
{{broader| LGBT rights in Malaysia }}

In [[Malaysia]], extrajudicial murders of LGBT people have also occurred.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Lang |first1=Nico |title=Rape and Murder of Teen Shows Lack of Justice for LGBT Malaysians |url=https://www.advocate.com/world/2017/7/06/rape-and-murder-teen-shows-lack-justice-lgbt-malaysians |website=www.advocate.com |access-date=12 December 2022 |language=en |date=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Ghoshal |first1=Neela |title='The Deceased Can't Speak for Herself': Violence Against LGBT People in Malaysia |url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2019/06/25/deceased-cant-speak-herself-violence-against-lgbt-people-malaysia |website=Human Rights Watch |access-date=12 December 2022 |language=en |date=25 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MHC"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Yi Lih |first1=Beh |title=Death of transgender woman in Malaysia sparks fears of rising hate crime |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/malaysia-lgbt-crime-idUSL8N1YM12C |website=Reuters |access-date=12 December 2022 |language=en |date=17 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are no Malaysian laws that protect the LGBT persons from discrimination and [[hate crimes]].&lt;ref name="MHC"/&gt;

=== Sub-Saharan Africa ===

Reports of killings by mobs and vigilantes, family violence, and other abuse from the community towards LGBT persons&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/27/ugandan-gay-rights-activist-murdered|title=Ugandan gay rights activist David Kato found murdered|last=Rice|first=Xan|date=27 January 2011|work=The Guardian|access-date=1 August 2019|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ghana shadow"&gt;{{cite report |author1=Solace Brothers Foundation |author2=The Initiative for Equal Rights |author3=Center for International Human Rights of Northwestern University School of Law |author4=Heartland Alliance for Human Needs &amp; Human Rights Global Initiative for Sexuality and Human Rights |title=Human Rights Violations Against Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender (LGBT) People in Ghana: A Shadow Report |date=August 2015 |url=https://tbinternet.ohchr.org/Treaties/CCPR/Shared%20Documents/GHA/INT_CCPR_ICO_GHA_21415_E.pdf |id=Submitted for consideration at the 115th Session of the Human Rights Committee}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite report|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/204346.pdf|title=LIBERIA 2012 HUMAN RIGHTS REPORT|publisher=United States Department of State|author=((Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor))|date=2012|access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://archive.globalgayz.com/africa/senegal/senegal-gay-couple-brutally-assaulted-by-parents/|title=Senegal: Gay Couple Brutally Assaulted by Parents|website=archive.globalgayz.com|access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; have been reported in regions of Africa heavily influenced by conservative Christianity and Islam. Such incidents have occurred in: [[Algeria]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title='He is Gay' Written on a Wall in Blood, as Algerian Student is Murdered on Campus | url=https://www.albawaba.com/loop/he-gay-written-wall-blood-algerian-student-murdered-campus-1252164 |work= Albawa |date= February 13, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Uganda]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Amid 'Kill the Gays' bill uproar, Ugandan LGBTQ activist is killed |url=https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/amid-kill-gays-bill-uproar-ugandan-lgbtq-activist-killed-n1067336 |work=NBC News |date=16 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[South Africa]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Born free, killed by hate – the price of being gay in South Africa |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-35967725 |work=BBC News |date=7 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kenya]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Gay men hacked with machetes and murdered in wave of hate crimes in Kenya |url=https://www.gaystarnews.com/article/whats-behind-series-recent-violent-hate-crimes-against-gays-kenya170713/ |work=Gay News |date=17 July 2013 |access-date=20 July 2020 |archive-date=9 October 2021 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20211009214636/https://www.gaystarnews.com/article/whats-behind-series-recent-violent-hate-crimes-against-gays-kenya170713/ |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Liberia]], [[Ghana]], [[Cameroon]], and [[Senegal]]. In some locations, police may be unlikely to intervene in incidents or take action on reported abuse;&lt;ref name="ghana shadow"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.glaad.org/blog/cameroonian-lgbti-activist-found-tortured-death-home|title=Cameroonian LGBTI activist found tortured to death in home|date=17 July 2013|website=GLAAD|language=en|access-date=1 August 2019|archive-date=17 May 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190517025423/https://www.glaad.org/blog/cameroonian-lgbti-activist-found-tortured-death-home|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; they are at times complicit in the anti-gay violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author1=Philip P. Rodenbough |title=Being LGBT in West Africa |date=July 2014 |publisher=Virtual Student Foreign Service (VSFS) program, US Department of State; USAID |url=https://blogs.cuit.columbia.edu/rightsviews/files/2015/03/The-Being-LGBT-in-West-Africa-Project-Final-Report.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Palestine ===
{{anchor|Palestine}}{{Broader| LGBT rights in the State of Palestine #violence | label 1 = Violence against LGBT people in Palestine | Capital punishment in the Gaza Strip | label 2 = Executions in the Gaza Strip | Pinkwashing (LGBT) }}

Homosexuality is not a [[Capital punishment|capital offence]] in the [[Capital punishment in the Gaza Strip|Gaza Strip]] or elsewhere in Palestine.{{r|HDT 2023}}&lt;ref name="Haaretz Kassim"&gt;{{cite news | last1=Abusalim | first1=Dorgham | title= The Real Oppressors of Gaza's Gay Community: Hamas or Israel? | url= https://www.haaretz.com/opinion/2018-03-07/ty-article-opinion/.premium/who-are-the-real-oppressors-of-gazas-gay-community-hamas-or-israel/0000017f-f034-df98-a5ff-f3bd1d870000 | access-date= 26 June 2024 | date= 7 March 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The laws against homosexual behavior in Palestine{{efn|Some interpretations of these laws say that it does not outlaw consensual gay sex between adults at all. Anis. F. Kassim{{snd}}editor-in-chief of the Palestinian Yearbook of International Law{{snd}}said that the law in question "could be interpreted as allowing homosexuality".&lt;ref name="Haaretz Kassim"/&gt;}} are a relic of the British and Ottoman rule in [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]]; they specify prison sentences of 10 to 14 years.{{r|HDT 2023}}&lt;ref name="Haaretz Kassim"/&gt; There is no evidence that these British colonial-era laws are actually enforced in Gaza.{{r|HDT 2023}}

Reports of extra-judicial killings of LGBT people in Palestine have circulated, without being confirmed. Sources such as the news agency [[Reuters]], the news outlet ''[[The New Arab]]'', and the NGO [[Human Rights Watch]], characterise many of these reports as misinformation: the stories are exaggerated, oversimplified, or misattributions of events that occurred elsewhere.{{r|Reuters video}} Examples of this include: 
* Two members of [[Palestinian nationalist]] [[Palestinian political violence|militant groups]] were accused of espionage and killed by their comrades in situations that included rumours about homosexuality or bisexuality.{{r|New Arab-Spy}}{{r|HRW en}}
* During the [[Israel–Hamas war]], a video described as "Hamas executes people by throwing them off a roof of a building!" circulated on social media. Some derivatives of the meme claimed the men were executed for being gay.{{r|Reuters video}} The video, however, was from 2015 and not from Palestine.{{r|Reuters video}} A July 2015 report from [[Al Arabiya]], included identical images and states that they were originally shared by the so-called Islamic State, and showed the execution of four gay men in [[Fallujah]], Iraq.{{r|Reuters video}}

==== Mahmoud Ishtiwi ====

In February 2016, the [[Al-Qassam Brigades]] (the militant wing of the [[Hamas]] movement) executed [[Mahmoud Ishtiwi]], the commander of Al-Qassam's [[Zeitoun, Gaza|Zeitoun]] Battalion.&lt;ref name="Times - MRE" &gt;{{cite news|last=Pfeffer|first=Anshel|url=https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/hamas-leader-files-found-israel-idf-tunnels-gaza-lkmfwpcjm |date=10 March 2024 |title=Hamas leader's torture tactics revealed in IDF tunnel raid|work=The Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; The alleged offences were described evasively, the stated reason was {{langx|ar|تجاوزاته السلوكية والأخلاقية التي أقر بها | translation = for behavioral and moral violations, to which he confessed}},&lt;ref name="HRW en" &gt;{{cite news |title=Palestine: Torture, Death of Hamas Detainee - Human Rights Watch |url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2016/02/15/palestine-torture-death-hamas-detainee |access-date=19 May 2024 |work=Human Rights Watch |date=15 February 2016 |language=en |quote=His family said they discovered that Qassam operatives held him in secret locations until February 7, when the group's Military Information Department issued a statement saying it had executed Eshtewi after sentencing him to death 'for behavioral and moral violations to which he confessed.'}}&lt;/ref&gt; which some western news media interpreted as a [[euphemism]] for homosexual activity.&lt;ref name="NYT - MRE" &gt;{{cite news|last1=Hadid|first1=Diaa|last2=Waheidi|first2=Majd Al|date=2016-03-01|title=Hamas Commander, Accused of Theft and Gay Sex, Is Killed by His Own|work=The New York Times | url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/02/world/middleeast/hamas-commander-mahmoud-ishtiwi-killed-palestine.html|access-date=21 May 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="newsweek2016"&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Moore|first=Jack|date=2 March 2016|title=Hamas executed a prominent commander after accusations of gay sex|url=http://www.newsweek.com/prominent-hamas-commander-was-executed-after-accusations-gay-sex-432343|magazine=[[Newsweek]]|access-date=2016-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Local sources clarified that Shteiwi was convicted of spying for Israel.&lt;ref name="DW - local sources" &gt;{{cite web | url=https://p.dw.com/p/1HrRm | title="رايتس ووتش" تدين إعدام أحد عناصر كتائب القسام – Dw – 2016/2/8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Qassam Brigades alleged that Ishtiwi had been executed by firing squad,&lt;ref name="MRE (Arabic)"&gt;{{cite news| title = تعذيب وموت محتجز لدى حماس في غزة |url=https://www.hrw.org/ar/news/2016/02/16/286896 |work=Human Rights Watch |access-date=19 May 2024 |date=16 February 2016 |language=ar | quote = لتجاوزاته السلوكية والأخلاقية التي أقر بها - For his behavioral and moral transgressions that he acknowledged. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="HRW en"/&gt; but people who saw his body before burial alleged that he might have died in custody and been shot after death.&lt;ref name="מחמוד א-שתיווי" &gt;{{cite news |title=פלסטין: עציר עונה ומת בידי חמאס - Human Rights Watch |url=https://www.hrw.org/he/news/2016/02/15/286896 |access-date=15 April 2024 |date=15 February 2016 |language=he}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="HRW en"/&gt;

==== Lions' Den in Nablus ====

The Zuhair Relit ([[Lions' Den militant group]]) in [[Nablus]] in the [[West Bank]] executed one of their members for sharing information with the Israeli security services that led to the assassination of several leaders of the group. The young man had been bribed and blackmailed by [[Shin Bet]] allegedly using a video of him having sex with a male partner.{{r|toi blackmail}}{{r|New Arab-Spy}}{{r|Haaretz Amun 2023}}{{r|i24 targeted}} But it is unclear how this video became public, it may not have been released by the group themselves.{{r|Quds video}}

== Hate crimes ==
{{broader|Hate crime}}
Extrajudicial killings of perceived homosexuals occur in the [[Western world]], with varying levels of condoning, inaction, or condemnation from the social environments in which they occur. Levels of anti-LGBT crime vary by location; where they have lesser implicit or explicit societal support{{snd}}from government, influential people or bodies, for example{{snd}}attacks on LGBT people, including murders, are often classified as hate or bias crimes, rather than extrajudicial killings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |first1=Silvia |last1=Blanco |first2=Andrea |last2=García Baroja |first3=Silvia |last3=Ayuso|first4=Iker |last4=Seisdedos |first5=Almudena |last5=Barragán |first6=Juan |last6=Esteban Lewin|first7=Naiara |last7=Galarraga Gortázar |first8=José |last8=Naranjo |first9=Trinidad |last9=Deiros |first10=Antonio |last10=Pita |first11=Guillermo |last11=Abril |date=2023-06-28 |title=The worldwide offensive against the rights of LGBTQ+ people |url=https://english.elpais.com/international/2023-06-28/the-worldwide-offensive-against-the-rights-of-lgbtq-people.html |access-date=2024-06-04 |website=EL PAÍS English |language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Homophobic crime in Australia ===
{{see also| Gay gang murders | label1 = Homophobic killings in Sydney }} 
An [[Australia]]n study, published in 2000 by the [[Australian Institute of Criminology]], found that of the 454 male homicides between 1989 and 1999 in the state of [[New South Wales]], at least 37 were verifiably fuelled by [[homophobia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Mouzos |first1=Jenny |last2=Thompson |first2=Sue |date=June 1, 2000 |title=Gay-hate related homicides: an overview of major findings in NSW |url=https://www.aic.gov.au/publications/tandi/tandi155 |journal=Trends &amp; Issues in Crime and Criminal Justice |issue=155 |isbn=064224166X |issn=0817-8542}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{further|List of people executed for homosexuality in Europe}}

=== Australia ===
Australian states and territories first passed laws against homosexuality during the [[History of Australia|colonial era]], and nineteenth-century colonial parliaments retained provisions which made homosexual activity a capital offence until 1861.&lt;ref name=carbery&gt;{{cite web |last=Carbery |first=Graham |title=Towards Homosexual Equality in Australian Criminal Law: A Brief History |year=2010 |edition=2nd |url=http://www.alga.org.au/files/towardsequality2ed.pdf |publisher=Australian Lesbian and Gay Archives Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most jurisdictions removed capital punishment as a sentence for homosexual activity, although in [[Victoria, Australia|Victoria]] it remained as such when committed while also inflicting [[bodily harm]] or to a person younger than the age of fourteen until 1949.&lt;ref name=carbery /&gt; The last person arrested for homosexual sex in Australia was a man in 1984 in Tasmania.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://hrlibrary.umn.edu/undocs/html/vws488.htm|title=Toonen v. Australia, Communication No. 488/1992, U.N. Doc CCPR/C/50/D/488/1992 (1994).|website=hrlibrary.umn.edu|access-date=8 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last part of Australia to legalise consensual homosexual sex between adults was [[Tasmania]] in 1997. In 2017, same-sex marriage was legalised by the [[Government of Australia|Australian government]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Karp |first1=Paul |title=Same-sex marriage bill passes in Australian Senate |url=https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2017/nov/29/same-sex-marriage-bill-passes-in-australian-senate |access-date=19 May 2022 |work=The Guardian |date=29 November 2017 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Yaxley |first1=Louise |title=Same-sex marriage signed into law by Governor-General |url=https://www.abc.net.au/news/2017-12-08/same-sex-marriage-legal-after-gg-approval/9239334 |access-date=19 May 2022 |work=ABC News |date=7 December 2017 |language=en-AU}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the seven men in Australian history known to have been executed for sodomy, six cases involved the sexual abuse of minors; only one of the seven cases was for consensual acts between adults.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Croome |first=Rodney |date=2006 |publisher=Centre for Tasmanian Historical Studies |title=Companion to Tasmanian History: Homosexuality |website=University of Tasmania Library {{!}} utas.edu.au |url=https://www.utas.edu.au/library/companion_to_tasmanian_history/H/Homosexuality.htm |access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In that sole case, Alexander Browne was hanged at Sydney on 22 December 1828 for sodomy with his shipmate William Lyster on the whaler ''Royal Sovereign''; Lyster was also convicted and sentenced to death, but his sentence was commuted before execution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Unfit for Publication press cuttings list|url=http://www.alga.org.au/files/ufpnewssources.pdf|website=Australian Lesbian &amp; Gay Archives}}&lt;/ref&gt; Joseph Fogg was hanged at Hobart on 24 February 1830 for an "unnamed crime", also described in one source as an "abominable crime".&lt;ref name=26feb1830&gt;{{cite news|title=Executions|url=http://trove.nla.gov.au/newspaper/article/8644929|access-date=9 March 2017|work=Colonial Times|date=26 February 1830|location=Hobart|page=3|quote=This morning, the awful sentence of the law was carried into execution upon four other persons, viz.-John Jones and Samuel Killen, for sheep-stealing; Joseph Fogg, for a nameless offence, and Thomas Goodwin, for cutting and maiming with intent the kill.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Convict Records: Joseph Fogg |url=https://convictrecords.com.au/convicts/fogg/joseph/83346 |website=convictrecords.com.au |access-date=31 July 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; The exact nature of his crime is unclear; while likely a same-sex sexual offence given the labels applied ('unnamed', 'abominable'), it is uncertain whether it was for an adult consensual act, same-sex rape, or abuse of a minor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Coad |first1=David |title=Gender trouble down under: Australian masculinities |date=2002 |publisher=Presses universitaires de Valenciennes |location=Valenciennes |isbn=9782905725301 |page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Nazi Germany ===
{{main|Persecution of homosexuals in Nazi Germany#Death penalty}}
During the period of [[Nazi Germany]] from 1933 to 1945, homosexual men were persecuted with thousands being imprisoned in [[Nazi concentration camps|concentration camps]] (and eventually [[extermination camp]]s) by the Nazi regime. Roughly 5,000–15,000 were sent to the concentration camps, with the death rate being estimated to be as high as 60%. Homosexuals in the camps suffered an unusual degree of cruelty by their captors, including being used as target practice on shooting ranges.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite book|title=The Racial State: Germany, 1933–1945|last=Burleigh|first=Michael|date=1991|publisher=Cambridge University Press|others=Wippermann, Wolfgang, Mazal Holocaust Collection |isbn=0521391148 |location=Cambridge |oclc=22597244|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/racialstate00mich}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Giles|first=Geoffrey J|title=Social Outsiders in Nazi Germany|date=2001|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton, New Jersey|page=240}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Pink Triangle: The Nazi War Against Homosexuals|last=Plant|first=Richard|date=2013|publisher=Henry Holt and Company|isbn=9781429936934|location=New York|oclc=872608428}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1937 speech, Himmler argued that SS men who had served sentences for homosexuality should be transferred to a concentration camp and [[Postenpflicht|shot when trying to escape]]. This policy was never implemented, and some SS men were acquitted on homosexuality charges despite evidence against them.{{sfn|Giles|2010|p=393}} A few death sentences against SS men for homosexual acts were pronounced between 1937 and 1940.{{sfn|Lorenz|2018|p=15}} In a speech on 18 August 1941, Hitler argued that homosexuality should be combatted throughout Nazi organizations and the military. In particular, homosexuality in the [[Hitler Youth]] must be punished by death in order to protect youth from being turned into homosexuals, however the Hitler Youth never implemented this policy.{{sfn|Giles|2010|pp=393–394}}

After learning of Hitler's remark, Himmler decided that the SS must be at least as tough on homosexuality and drafted a decree mandating the death penalty to any member of the SS and police found guilty of engaging in a homosexual act. Hitler signed the decree on 15 November 1941 on the condition that there be absolutely no publicity, worried that such a harsh decree might lend fuel to left-wing propaganda that homosexuality was especially prevalent in Germany. Since it could not be published in the SS newspaper, the decree was communicated to SS men one-on-one by their superiors. However, this was not done consistently and many arrested men asserted that they had no knowledge of the decree.{{sfn|Giles|2010|pp=393–394}}

Even after the decree, only a few death sentences were pronounced.{{sfn|Giles|2010|p=394}}{{sfn|Longerich|2011|p=239}} Himmler often commuted the sentence especially if he thought that the accused was not a committed homosexual, but had suffered a one-time mistake (particularly while drunk). Many of those whose sentence was commuted were sent to serve in the [[Dirlewanger Brigade]], a penal unit on the Eastern Front, where most were killed.{{sfn|Giles|2010|p=394}} After late 1943, because of military losses, it was the policy to recycle SS men convicted of homosexuality into the Wehrmacht.{{sfn|Schlagdenhauffen|2018|p=33}}

The 1933 law on habitual criminals also allowed for execution after the third conviction.{{sfn|Lorenz|2018|pp=12–13}} On 4 September 1941 a new law allowed the execution of dangerous sex offenders or habitual criminals when "the protection of the ''Volksgemeinschaft'' or the need for just atonement require it". This law enabled authorities to pronounce death sentences against homosexuals, and is known to have been employed in four cases in Austria.{{sfn|Scheck|2020|p=422}}{{sfn|Lorenz|2018|p=13}} In 1943, [[Wilhelm Keitel]], head of the {{Lang|de|[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]|italic=no}}, authorized the death penalty for soldiers convicted of homosexuality in "particularly serious cases".{{sfn|Storkmann|2021|p=28}}{{sfn|Lorenz|2018|pp=14, 16}} Only a few executions of homosexual Wehrmacht soldiers are known, mostly in conjunction with other charges, especially [[desertion]].{{sfn|Storkmann|2021|p=28}} Some homosexuals were executed at Nazi euthanasia centers, such as [[Bernburg Euthanasia Centre|Bernburg]] or Meseritz-Obrawalde. It is difficult to estimate the number of homosexuals directly killed during the Nazi era.{{sfn|Lorenz|2018|p=11}}

=== United Kingdom ===
From 1533, under the [[Buggery Act 1533]], capital felony for any person to "commit the detestable and abominable vice of buggery with mankind or beast", was enacted, repealed and re-enacted several times by [[the Crown]], until it was reinstated permanently in 1563. Homosexual activity remained a capital offence until 1861.&lt;ref name="Colonial"&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1061&amp;context=englishfacpubs|journal=Journal of Homosexuality|volume=1|issue=3|date=1976|title=Homosexuals and the Death Penalty in Colonial America|first=Louis|last=Crompton|access-date=20 May 2016|doi=10.1300/j082v01n03_03|pages=277–293|pmid=798008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last execution took place on 27 November 1835 when [[James Pratt and John Smith]] were hanged outside [[Newgate Prison]] in London.

=== United States ===
{{See also|Sodomy laws in the United States}}
During the [[Colonial history of the United States|colonial era]] of [[History of the United States|American history]], the various European nations which [[European colonization of the Americas|established colonies]] in the Americas brought their pre-existing laws against homosexuality (which included capital punishment) with them. The establishment of the United States after their victory in the [[American Revolutionary War|Revolutionary War]] did not bring about any changes in the status of capital punishment as a sentence for being convicted of homosexual behavior. Beginning in the 19th century, the various state legislatures passed legislation which ended the status of capital punishment being used for those who were convicted of homosexual behavior. [[South Carolina]] was the last state, in 1873, to repeal the death penalty for homosexual behaviour from its statute books. The number of times the penalty was carried out is unknown. Records show there were at least two executions, and a number of more convictions with vague labels, such as "crimes against nature".&lt;ref name="Colonial" /&gt;

=== Sudan ===
In July 2020, the sodomy law that previously punished gay men with up to 100 lashes for the first offence, five years in jail for the second and the death penalty the third time around was abolished, with new legislation reducing the penalty to prison terms ranging from five years to life. Sudanese LGBT+ activists hailed the reform as a 'great first step', but said it was not enough yet, and the end goal should be the decriminalisation of same-sex sexual activity altogether.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-sudan-lgbt-rights-trfn/great-first-step-as-sudan-lifts-death-penalty-and-flogging-for-gay-sex-idUSKCN24H30J |title='Great first step' as Sudan lifts death penalty and flogging for gay sex |author1=Ban Barkawi|author2=Rachel Savage |work=[[Reuters]] |date=16 July 2020 |access-date=17 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{notelist|refs=
{{efn|name="article 354"|text=A separate provision of the penal code, Article 354 of the Federal Penal Code of the United Arab Emirates the death sentence is prescribed for certain sexual acts; it states: "shall be sentenced to the death penalty, whoever used coercion in having sexual intercourse with a female or sodomy with a male." There is no certain legal interpretation of this provision,&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt; but, according to [[Amnesty International]] it relates solely to rape ("Amnesty International{{nbsp}}... considers this article to address rape"),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report |editor=((Amnesty International)) |title=Love, hate and the law: decriminalizing homosexuality |chapter=Appendix 1: The Application of the Death Penalty for Consensual Same-sex Sexual Relations |pages=46–49 |date=4 July 2008|id=Index Number: POL 30/003/2008|chapter-url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/pol30/003/2008/en/}}&lt;/ref&gt; or is at least only applied to sexual violence, according to the ILGA ("...{{nbsp}}it appears that the law is used in rape cases"), not consensual same-sex sexual activity.&lt;ref name="ilga 2020"/&gt;}}
{{efn|name="trust since 2015"|1=The Human Dignity Trust noted in 2020 that all annual human rights reports from the U.S. Department of State on UAE after 2015 stated no prosecutions for same-sex sexual acts had been reported.}}
{{efn|name="legal uncertainty"|text=The ILGA, in its 2020 report and its 2023 database, note that there five UN-member countries where the status of the death penalty as a punishment for same-sex sexual conduct is uncertain. This may be because legal experts or scholars dispute the effect of legal provisions, or because the laws relied upon to potentially sanction the death penalty relate to sexual behaviours outside marriage, with applicability to homosexual relations so far only theoretical. The jurisdictions in this category are: Afghanistan, Pakistan, Qatar, Somalia (including Somaliland) and the United Arab Emirates.|2=&lt;ref name="ilga 2020" /&gt;{{rp|25}}}}
}}

==References==
{{reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name="HDT 2023" &gt;{{cite news |title=Palestine |url=https://www.humandignitytrust.org/country-profile/palestine/ |access-date=26 June 2024 |work=Human Dignity Trust |date=14 November 2023 |language=en|quote=Same-sex sexual activity is prohibited in Gaza under the British Mandate Criminal Code Ordinance 1936. The relevant provision carries a maximum penalty of ten years imprisonment. Only men are criminalised under this law.{{pb}} "The law was inherited from the British. It continues to be in operation in Gaza today, though it is not in force elsewhere in Palestine.{{pb}} "There is little evidence of the law being enforced, and it appears to be largely obsolete in practice.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Reuters video"&gt;{{cite news |title=Video of people thrown from roof shows punishment by IS, not Hamas |url=https://www.reuters.com/fact-check/video-people-thrown-roof-shows-punishment-by-is-not-hamas-2023-12-14/ |work=Reuters Fact Check |agency=Reuters |date=15 December 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="i24 targeted"&gt;{{cite news |title=Fearing Israeli retaliation, Lions' Den chief turns himself in to PA |url=https://www.i24news.tv/en/news/middle-east/palestinian-territories/1682662151-fearing-israeli-retaliation-lions-den-chief-turns-himself-in-to-pa |access-date=3 June 2024 |work=I24news |date=28 April 2023 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Quds video"&gt;{{cite news | title= A young man was killed as a result of being shot in Nablus | url= https://qudsnet.com/post/550656/%D9%85%D9%82%D8%AA%D9%84-%D8%B4%D8%A7%D8%A8-%D8%AC%D8%B1%D8%A7%D8%A1-%D8%AA%D8%B9%D8%B1%D8%B6%D9%87-%D9%84%D8%A5%D8%B7%D9%84%D8%A7%D9%82-%D9%86%D8%A7%D8%B1-%D9%81%D9%8A-%D9%86%D8%A7%D8%A8%D9%84%D8%B3 | access-date= 5 July 2024 | work= Quds Net News Agency | date= 9 April 2023 | language=ar}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="toi blackmail"&gt;{{cite news| title=Palestinian terror group Lion's Den claims it executed an Israeli spy in Nablus |url=https://www.timesofisrael.com/palestinian-terror-group-lions-den-claims-it-executed-an-israeli-spy-in-nablus/ | access-date=3 June 2024 | date=9 April 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="New Arab-Spy" &gt;{{cite news| title=Lions' Den execute man accused of informing for Israel |url=https://www.newarab.com/news/lions-den-execute-man-accused-informing-israel |access-date=3 June 2024 |work=[[The New Arab]] |location=London |date=10 April 2023 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="HRW en" &gt;{{cite news |title=Palestine: Torture, Death of Hamas Detainee - Human Rights Watch |url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2016/02/15/palestine-torture-death-hamas-detainee |access-date=19 May 2024 |work=Human Rights Watch |date=15 February 2016 |language=en |quote=His family said they discovered that Qassam operatives held him in secret locations until February 7, when the group's Military Information Department issued a statement saying it had executed Eshtewi after sentencing him to death 'for behavioral and moral violations to which he confessed.'}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="Haaretz Amun 2023" &gt;{{cite news| last1=Amun |first1=Fadi |title=Militant group Lion's Den announces execution of Palestinian for collaborating with Israel |url=https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/2023-04-09/ty-article/.premium/lions-den-announces-execution-of-palestinian-for-collaborating-with-israel/00000187-665c-dde0-afb7-7e5fd87e0000 |access-date=3 June 2024 |work=Haaretz |date=9 April 2023 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===Works cited===
*{{cite book |last1=Giles |first1=Geoffrey J. |title=The Routledge History of the Holocaust |date=2010 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=978-0-203-83744-3 |chapter=The Persecution of Gay Men and Lesbians During the Third Reich|pages=385–396}}
*{{cite book |last1=Longerich |first1=Peter |author1-link=Peter Longerich |title=Heinrich Himmler: A Life |date=2011 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |isbn=978-0-19-161705-8 |language=en}}
*{{cite book |last1=Lorenz |first1=Gottfried |title=Todesurteile und Hinrichtungen wegen homosexueller Handlungen während der NS-Zeit: Mann-männliche Internetprostitution. Und andere Texte zur Geschichte und zur Situation der Homosexuellen in Deutschland|trans-title=Death sentences and executions for homosexual acts during the Nazi era, male-male internet prostitution, and other texts on the history and situation of homosexuals in Germany |date=2018 |publisher=[[LIT Verlag]] |isbn=978-3-643-13992-4 |language=de}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Scheck |first1=Raffael |title=The Danger of 'Moral Sabotage': Western Prisoners of War on Trial for Homosexual Relations in Nazi Germany |journal=Journal of the History of Sexuality |date=2020 |volume=29 |issue=3 |pages=418–446 |doi=10.7560/JHS29305|s2cid=&lt;!-- --&gt; }}
*{{cite book|last=Schlagdenhauffen|first= Régis|chapter=Queer life in Europe during the Second World War" and "Punishing homosexual men and women under the Third Reich|title= Queer in Europe during the Second World War|publisher= Council of Europe|date= 2018| isbn =978-92-871-8464-1|url=https://rm.coe.int/079317-queer-in-europe-during-the-second-world-war-web-web/16808e4a53|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20220217041539/https://rm.coe.int/079317-queer-in-europe-during-the-second-world-war-web-web/16808e4a53|archive-date= 17 February 2022|pages=7–20, 21–38}}
*{{cite book |last1=Storkmann |first1=Klaus |title=Tabu und Toleranz: Der Umgang mit Homosexualität in der Bundeswehr 1955 bis 2000|trans-title=Taboo and Tolerance: Homosexuality and the Bundeswehr 1955 to 2000 |date=2021 |publisher=[[De Gruyter]] |isbn=978-3-11-073290-0 |language=de}}

{{Criminalization of homosexuality}}
{{Capital punishment}} 
{{World topic| prefix= Extrajudicial killings in | title= [[Extrajudicial killings |Extrajudicial killings in the world]] |noredlinks=yes}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Capital punishment|Homosexuality]]
[[Category:Criminalization of homosexuality]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>