<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191116102046|926433834" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="50402549" pageid="50402549" ns="0" title="Capital punishment for homosexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-16T11:42:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{LGBT rights sidebar}}
'''Capital punishment for homosexuality''' was historically implemented by a number of countries worldwide. It currently remains a legal punishment in several countries and regions, all of which have ''[[sharia]]''-based criminal laws. Being prescribed by the law does not necessarily mean that the penalty is carried out in practice. Gay people have also fallen victim to extrajudicial killings by state and non-state actors.

==In current state laws==
[[File:World laws pertaining to homosexual relationships and expression.svg|thumb|{{legend|#8c210f|Death penalty for homosexuality}}{{legend|#cc6633|Death penalty on books but not applied}}]]
{{Further|LGBT rights by country or territory|LGBT in Islam|Sharia#Islamization}}

As of 2019, the following jurisdictions prescribe the death penalty for homosexuality:

* {{flag|Afghanistan}}. A new Penal Code enacted in February 2018 explicitly criminalises same-sex sexual conduct. Sources cited by ILGA indicate that there is a "broad consensus amongst scholars that execution was the appropriate punishment if homosexual acts could be proven”.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|isbn=|location=Geneva|pages=429|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sharia category of ''[[zina]]'' (illicit sexual intercourse), which according to some traditional Islamic [[Madhhab|legal schools]] may entail the ''[[Hudud|hadd]]'' (sharia-prescribed) punishment of stoning, when strict evidential requirements are met. The [[Hanafi]] school, prevalent in Afghanistan, does not regard homosexual acts as a ''hadd'' crime, although Afghan judges may potentially apply the death penalty for a number of reasons. No known death sentences for homosexuality have been passed since the end of Taliban rule in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/ |title=Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death |work=The Washington Post |date=16 June 2016 |accessdate=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.deathpenaltyworldwide.org/country-search-post.cfm?country=Afghanistan |title=The Death Penalty in Afghanistan |publisher=Death Penalty Worldwide |accessdate=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Brunei}}'s ''Sharia Penal Code'', implemented in stages since 2014, prescribes death by stoning as punishment for same-sex relations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/mar/28/brunei-brings-in-death-by-stoning-as-punishment-for-gay-sex|title=Brunei introduces death by stoning as punishment for gay sex|last=correspondent|first=Hannah Ellis-Petersen South-east Asia|date=2019-03-28|work=The Guardian|access-date=2019-03-28|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt; After international backlash, in May 2019, the Sultan of Brunei explained that a "de facto" moratorium on the execution of the death penalty has been in force in the country for the last two decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Brunei says it won't enforce gay death penalty after backlash |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-brunei-lgbt-sultan/brunei-says-it-wont-enforce-gay-death-penalty-after-backlash-idUSKCN1SB0FS |website=Reuters |accessdate=August 19, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; This moratorium could be lifted at any time.
* {{flag|Iran}}.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt; Homosexual intercourse is declared a capital offense in Iran's ''Islamic Penal Code'', enacted in 1991. Though the grounds for execution in Iran are difficult to track, there is evidence that several people were hanged for homosexual behavior in 2005-2006 and in 2016, in some cases on dubious charges of rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Asal, V.|author2=Sommer, U.|title= Legal Path Dependence and the Long Arm of the Religious State: Sodomy Provisions and Gay Rights Across Nations and Over Time|publisher=State University of New York Press|page=64}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=economist&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Economist|title=How homosexuality became a crime in the Middle East|date=June 6, 2018|url=https://www.economist.com/open-future/2018/06/06/how-homosexuality-became-a-crime-in-the-middle-east|}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Mauritania}}.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt; According to a 1984 law, Muslim men can be stoned for engaging in homosexual sex, though no executions have occurred so far.&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt; The country observes a moratorium on the execution of the death penalty since 1987.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|isbn=|location=Geneva|pages=347|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Nigeria}}, where several northern [[States of Nigeria|states]] have adopted [[sharia]]-based criminal laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|isbn=|location=Geneva|pages=359|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Pakistan}}, where the death penalty for homosexual acts is technically permitted by the law, but not applied in practice.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;
* {{flag|Qatar}}, applicable only to Muslims, for extramarital sex regardless of the gender of the participants. There is no evidence that the death penalty has been applied for consensual same-sex relations taking place between adults and in private.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|isbn=|location=Geneva|pages=465|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Saudi Arabia}}, which does not have codified criminal laws.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt; According to the country's interpretation of sharia, a married man who commits sodomy, or a non-Muslim who engages in sodomy with a Muslim, can be stoned to death.&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt; There were unconfirmed reports that two cross-dressing Pakistani nationals were killed by Saudi authorities in 2017, which Saudi officials have denied.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;
* {{flag|Somalia}} ({{flag|Jubaland}}), where Islamic courts have imposed sharia-based death penalties in some southern regions.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt;
* {{flag|Sudan}}, for a third conviction.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015"&gt;{{cite web|author1=Aengus Carroll|author2=Lucas Paoli Itaborahy|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia: A World Survey of Laws: criminalisation, protection and recognition of same-sex love|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/2017/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2017_WEB.pdf|website=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex association|accessdate=April 5, 2019|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|United Arab Emirates}}: Legal experts disagree on whether the federal law of the [[LGBT rights in United Arab Emirates|United Arab Emirates]] prescribes the death penalty for consensual gay sex or only for rape.&lt;ref name="WP"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/|title=Analysis - Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death|first1=Max|last1=Bearak|first2=Darla|last2=Cameron|date=16 June 2016|work=The Washington Post|quote=Lawyers in the country and other experts disagree on whether federal law prescribes the death penalty for consensual homosexual sex or only for rape. In a recent Amnesty International report, the organization said it was not aware of any death sentences for homosexual acts. }}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 354 of the Federal Penal Code states: "whoever resorts to coercion in sexual intercourse with a female or homosexuality with a male, shall be punished by the death penalty."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|website=Legal Advice Middle East|title=UAE Federal law of 1987|url=https://legaladviceme.com/legislation/117/uae-federal-law-3-of-1987-promulgating-penal-code#volume-two-crimes-and-penalties|access-date=July 11, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; A recent [[Amnesty International]] report claims that there are no instances of death sentences for homosexual acts.&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt;
* {{flag|Yemen}}: If the same-sex activity occurs outside of marriage, the death penalty can be enforced.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.gaylawnet.com/laws/ye.htm|title=GayLawNet®™ &amp;#124; Laws &amp;#124; Yemen &amp;#124; YE|website=www.gaylawnet.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oftentimes, death is the resulting penalty due to honor killings and vigilante executions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ipsnews.net/2013/08/no-place-for-gays-in-yemen/|title=No Place for Gays in Yemen &amp;#124; Inter Press Service|website=www.ipsnews.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Extrajudicial killings==

In some regions, gay people have been murdered by [[Islamist]] militias, such as [[ISIS]] in parts of Iraq and Syria and the [[Houthi movement]] in Yemen.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;

[[Anti-gay purges in Chechnya|Anti-gay purges in the Chechen Republic]], a part of the [[Russian Federation]], have included [[forced disappearance]]s — secret abductions, imprisonment, and [[torture]] — by authorities targeting persons based on their perceived [[sexual orientation]]. An unknown number of men, who authorities detained on suspicion of being gay or bisexual, have reportedly died after being held in what [[human rights]] groups and eyewitnesses have called [[concentration camp]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Smith |first1=Lydia |title=Chechnya detains 100 gay men in first concentration camps since the Holocaust |url=http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/chechnya-detains-100-gay-men-first-concentration-camps-since-holocaust-1616363|accessdate=16 April 2017 |work=International Business Times UK |date=10 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Advocate"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Reynolds |first1=Daniel |title=Report: Chechnya Is Torturing Gay Men in Concentration Camps |url=http://www.advocate.com/world/2017/4/10/report-chechyna-torturing-gay-men-concentration-camps |accessdate=16 April 2017 |work=The Advocate |date=10 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Regions of Africa with Christian beliefs have had a common occurrence of vigilante executions and very widespread anti-gay sentiment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/27/ugandan-gay-rights-activist-murdered|title=Ugandan gay rights activist David Kato found murdered|last=Rice|first=Xan|date=2011-01-27|work=The Guardian|access-date=2019-08-01|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://tbinternet.ohchr.org/Treaties/CCPR/Shared%20Documents/GHA/INT_CCPR_ICO_GHA_21415_E.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://archive.globalgayz.com/africa/senegal/senegal-gay-couple-brutally-assaulted-by-parents/|title=Senegal: Gay Couple Brutally Assaulted by Parents|website=archive.globalgayz.com|access-date=2019-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; In these countries, police tend to turn a blind eye and be unsympathetic, often being complicit in the killings and refusing to investigate.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/204346.pdf|title=LIBERIA 2012 HUMAN RIGHTS REPORT|last=United States Department of State|first=Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor|date=2012|website=state.gov|access-date=2019-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.glaad.org/blog/cameroonian-lgbti-activist-found-tortured-death-home|title=Cameroonian LGBTI activist found tortured to death in home|date=2013-07-17|website=GLAAD|language=en|access-date=2019-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Australia===
Australian states and territories inherited British laws relating to homosexuality, and laws passed in nineteenth century colonial parliaments retained the provisions which made homosexual activity a capital crime.&lt;ref name=carbery&gt;{{cite journal |last=Carbery |first=Graham |title=Towards Homosexual Equality in Australian Criminal Law: A Brief History |year=2010 |edition=2nd |issue= |pages= |url=http://www.alga.org.au/files/towardsequality2ed.pdf |publisher=Australian Lesbian and Gay Archives Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, various jurisdictions began to reduce the death penalty for sodomy to life imprisonment, with Victoria being the last to remove the death penalty for this crime, in 1949.&lt;ref name=carbery /&gt; The last person arrested for homosexual sex in Australia was a man in 1984 in Tasmania.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://hrlibrary.umn.edu/undocs/html/vws488.htm|title=Toonen v. Australia, Communication No. 488/1992, U.N. Doc CCPR/C/50/D/488/1992 (1994).|website=hrlibrary.umn.edu|access-date=2019-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last part of Australia to legalise consensual homosexual sex between adults was [[Tasmania]] in 1997. In 2017, homosexual marriage was legalised.

===Nazi Germany===

While many of the Christian majority countries in Europe, the Americas and Asia had begun to [[Timeline of LGBT history|decriminalise homosexuality by the mid 20th century]], [[Adolf Hitler]] and the [[National Socialist German Workers Party]], with intense far-right nationalist support, outlawed homosexual groups and included homosexuals as one of the minority groups sent to concentration camps. An estimated 3000-9000 homosexuals died in concentration camps between 1933 and 1945, with another 2000-6000 survivors made to serve the rest of their sentence in prison under [[Paragraph 175]].

===United Kingdom===
From 1533 the capital felony for any person to "commit the detestable and abominable vice of buggery with mankind or beast", was repealed and re-enacted several times, until it was reinstated in 1563 remaining unchanged until 1861.&lt;ref name="Colonial"&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1061&amp;context=englishfacpubs|work=Journal of Homosexuality|volume=1|issue=3|date=1976|title=Homosexuals and the Death Penalty in Colonial America|author=Louis Crompton|accessdate=20 May 2016|doi=10.1300/j082v01n03_03|pages=277–293}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last execution took place on 27 November 1835 when [[James Pratt and John Smith]] were hanged at Newgate.

One source claims the last execution for sodomy in the [[British Empire]] happened in the [[Colony of Tasmania]] (now part of [[Australia]]) in 1867.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.utas.edu.au/library/companion_to_tasmanian_history/H/Homosexuality.htm|title=Homosexuality|website=www.utas.edu.au|access-date=2019-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States and colonial America===
{{See also|Sodomy laws in the United States}}
Colonial America had the laws of the United Kingdom, and the revolutionary states took many of those laws as the basis of their own, in some cases verbatim.&lt;ref name="Colonial" /&gt;  The last law where the death penalty was on the statute books was South Carolina, the old British law was not repealed until 1873, twelve years after the mother country.&lt;ref name="Colonial" /&gt;

The number of times the penalty was carried out is unknown. Records support two executions, and a number of more uncertain convictions, such as "crimes against nature".&lt;ref name="Colonial" /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Capital punishment]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:LGBT-related legislation]]
[[Category:Sex laws]]
[[Category:Persecution of LGBT people]]
[[Category:Same-sex sexuality]]
[[Category:LGBT rights by issue]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>