<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221117195523|1122476138" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="50402549" pageid="50402549" ns="0" title="Capital punishment for homosexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-20T08:28:42Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Death penalty for same-sex sexual activity}}
{{LGBT rights sidebar}}
Capital punishment as a [[criminalization of homosexuality|criminal punishment for homosexuality]] has been implemented by a number of countries in their history. It currently remains a legal punishment in several countries and regions, all of which  have [[sharia]]-based criminal laws. Gay people also face extrajudicial killings by state and non-state actors, as [[Anti-gay purges in Chechnya|in Chechnya in 2019]], though it is denied by the Chechen authorities and Russia.

Imposition of the [[death penalty]] for homosexuality may be classified as [[judicial murder]] of gay people, which has been analyzed as a form of [[genocide]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=DeJong |first1=Christina |last2=Long |first2=Eric |title=Handbook of LGBT Communities, Crime, and Justice |publisher=Springer |isbn=978-1-4614-9188-0 |pages=339–362 |language=en |chapter=The Death Penalty as Genocide: The Persecution of "Homosexuals" in Uganda|date=4 December 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In current state laws==
[[File:World laws pertaining to homosexual relationships and expression.svg|thumb|400px|{{legend|#8c210f|Death penalty for homosexuality}}{{legend|#cc6633|Death penalty, unenforced}}]]
{{Further|LGBT rights by country or territory|LGBT in Islam|Capital punishment for adultery|Sharia#Islamization}}

As of July 2020, the following jurisdictions prescribe the death penalty for homosexuality:

* {{flagicon|Afghanistan}} [[LGBT rights in Afghanistan|Afghanistan]]. A new Penal Code enacted in February 2018 explicitly criminalises same-sex sexual conduct.{{citation needed|date=July 2020}} Sources cited by the [[International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association]] (ILGBTIA) indicate that there is a "broad consensus amongst scholars that execution was the appropriate punishment if homosexual acts could be proven".&lt;ref name="ilga 2019"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|location=Geneva}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|429}} The sharia category of ''[[zina]]'' (illicit sexual intercourse), which according to some traditional Islamic [[Madhhab|legal schools]] may entail the ''[[Hudud|hadd]]'' (sharia-prescribed) punishment of stoning, when strict evidential requirements are met. The [[Hanafi]] school, prevalent in Afghanistan, does not regard homosexual acts as a ''hadd'' crime, although Afghan judges may potentially apply the death penalty for a number of reasons. No known death sentences for homosexuality have been enforced since the end of Taliban rule in 2001.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost.com"&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/ |title=Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death |newspaper=The Washington Post |date=16 June 2016 |access-date=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.deathpenaltyworldwide.org/country-search-post.cfm?country=Afghanistan |title=The Death Penalty in Afghanistan |publisher=Death Penalty Worldwide |access-date=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, following the [[2021 Taliban offensive]], fears of reprisal including death for those suspected of homosexuality were renewed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://thehill.com/policy/international/569741-they-will-kill-us-if-they-find-us-lgbt-afghans-fear-new-taliban-regime |title='They will kill us if they find us': LGBT Afghans fear new Taliban regime |newspaper=The Hill |date=29 August 2021 |access-date=6 September 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Brunei}} [[LGBT rights in Brunei|Brunei]]. ''Sharia Penal Code'', Prescribes death by stoning for gay men (temporarily in abeyance),&lt;ref name="April2019"&gt;[https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-47769964 Brunei implements stoning to death under new anti-LGBT laws]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="CNN-20190505"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://edition.cnn.com/2019/05/05/asia/brunei-lgbt-death-penalty-intl/index.html|title=Brunei backs down on gay sex death penalty after international backlash|date=6 May 2019 |access-date=6 May 2019|publisher=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="May2019"&gt;[https://www.abc.net.au/news/2019-05-08/brunei-moratorium-death-penalty-gay-sex-remains-illegal/11087848 Brunei won't impose death penalty for gay sex – but it's still illegal]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{multiref2|1={{cite report |author1=Office of International Religious Freedom|author2=United States Department of State |title=2021 Report on International Religious Freedom: Brunei |url=https://www.state.gov/reports/2021-report-on-international-religious-freedom/brunei/ |publisher=United States Department of State |date=June 2, 2022 |quote=A 2019 de facto moratorium on the death penalty remained in place.}}|2={{cite news |last1=Kelleher |first1=Patrick |title=11 countries where LGBTQ+ people still face death penalty urged to abolish it |url=https://www.pinknews.co.uk/2022/05/17/lgbtq-death-penalty-idahobit/ |work=PinkNews |date=17 May 2022 |quote=According to Human Dignity Trust, the death penalty is implemented in Iran, Northern Nigeria, Saudi Arabia, Somalia and Yemen, and remains a "legal possibility" in Afghanistan, Brunei, Mauritania, Pakistan, Qatar and UAE.}}|3={{cite news |last1=Yee |first1=Claudia |title=What explains Brunei's expansion of the death penalty in 2019? |url=https://www.monash.edu/law/research/eleos/blog/eleos-justice-blog-posts/what-explains-bruneis-expansion-of-the-death-penalty-in-2019 |work=ELEOS |publisher=Monash University |language=en |date=31 August 2021}}|4={{cite news |last1=Patto |first1=Kasthuri |title=ASEAN Summit Should Draw Attention to Brunei's Appalling Human Rights Record |url=https://thediplomat.com/2021/10/asean-summit-should-draw-attention-to-bruneis-appalling-human-rights-record/ |work=The Diplomat: Know the Asia-Pacific |date=29 October 2021 |quote=The moratorium is still in place, but the human rights situation in Brunei remains appalling.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; up to 10 years in prison, [[whipping]]s, and fines.
* {{flagicon|Iran}} [[LGBT rights in Iran|Iran]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015"&gt;{{cite web|first1=Aengus|last1=Carroll|author2=Lucas Paoli Itaborahy|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia: A World Survey of Laws: criminalisation, protection and recognition of same-sex love|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/2017/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2017_WEB.pdf|website=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex association|access-date=5 April 2019|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Male-male anal intercourse is declared a capital offense in Iran's ''Islamic Penal Code'', enacted in 1991. Articles 233 through 241 criminalise both female and male same-sex activity; for a first offence, the death penalty only applies to some cases of male-male penile-anal intercourse, with female-female activity and other cases of male-male activity being punished by flogging instead of execution. Under the combination of articles 136 and 238, a woman convicted for the fourth time of the crime of ''musaheqeh'' ([[tribadism]]) is to be executed; there is no death penalty for non-genital-genital female-female sexual conduct.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Refugees|first=United Nations High Commissioner for|title=Refworld {{!}} Iran: Islamic Penal Code|url=https://www.refworld.org/docid/518a19404.html|access-date=20 July 2020|website=Refworld|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though the grounds for execution in Iran are difficult to track, there is evidence that several gay men were executed in 2005–2006, 2016 and in 2022 mostly on alleged charges of rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Asal, V.|author2=Sommer, U.|title= Legal Path Dependence and the Long Arm of the Religious State: Sodomy Provisions and Gay Rights Across Nations and Over Time|publisher=State University of New York Press|page=64}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=economist&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Economist|title=How homosexuality became a crime in the Middle East|date=6 June 2018|url=https://www.economist.com/open-future/2018/06/06/how-homosexuality-became-a-crime-in-the-middle-east}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Mauritania}} [[LGBT rights in Mauritania|Mauritania]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt; According to a 1984 law, Muslim men can be stoned for engaging in homosexual sex, though no executions have occurred so far.&lt;ref name="WP"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/|title=Analysis – Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death|first1=Max|last1=Bearak|first2=Darla|last2=Cameron|date=16 June 2016|newspaper=The Washington Post|quote=Lawyers in the country and other experts disagree on whether federal law prescribes the death penalty for consensual homosexual sex or only for rape. In a recent Amnesty International report, the organization said it was not aware of any death sentences for homosexual acts.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The country has observed a moratorium on the execution of the death penalty since 1987.&lt;ref name="ilga 2019"/&gt;{{rp|347}}
* {{flagicon|Nigeria}} [[LGBT rights in Nigeria|Nigeria]]. Several northern [[States of Nigeria|states]] have adopted [[sharia]]-based criminal laws, though no executions are known.&lt;ref name="ilga 2019"/&gt;{{rp|359}}
* {{flagicon|Qatar}} [[LGBT rights in Qatar|Qatar]]. Same-sex sexual activity is prohibited under the Penal Code 2004, which criminalises acts of "sodomy" and "sexual intercourse" between people of the same sex. These provisions carry a maximum penalty of seven years' imprisonment. Both men and women are criminalised under this law. Also, [[the death penalty]] is applicable only to Muslims, for certain types of extramarital sex regardless of the gender of the participants. However, there is no evidence that the death penalty has been applied for consensual same-sex relations in private taking place between adults.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost.com"/&gt;
* {{flagicon|Saudi Arabia}} [[LGBT rights in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Arabia]]. Does not have codified criminal laws.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015"/&gt; According to the country's interpretation of sharia, a married man who commits sodomy, or a non-Muslim who engages in sodomy with a Muslim, can be stoned to death.&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt; There are unconfirmed reports that two cross-dressing Pakistani nationals were killed by Saudi authorities in 2017, which Saudi officials have denied.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt; Verified executions occurred in 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://metro.co.uk/2019/04/27/five-men-beheaded-saudi-arabia-gay-according-confessions-extracted-torture-9328194/ | title=Five men beheaded by Saudi Arabia were gay in claims from 'tortured confession' | date=27 April 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.pinknews.co.uk/2019/04/29/man-executed-saudi-arabia-gay/ | title=Man executed in Saudi Arabia admitted to gay sex in "invented" confession | date=29 April 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexuality in Saudi Arabia is proven by four eyewitnesses who have seen the penetration, or a self confession; if these conditions are not met they can't be stoned but can be given discretionary punishments like lashing and jails.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=iranian.com: Keyan Keihani, A Brief History of Male Homosexuality in the Qur'an, Saudi Arabia, Iran, and Arab-Islamic Culture|url=http://www.iranian.com/Opinion/2005/December/Homosexuality/index.html|access-date=2021-09-27|website=www.iranian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* {{flagicon|Somalia}} [[LGBT rights in Somalia|Somalia]].({{flag|Somalia}}), where insurgents and Somali officials have imposed sharia-based law.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt;
* {{flagicon|United Arab Emirates}} [[LGBT rights in the United Arab Emirates|United Arab Emirates]]. Article 354 of the Federal Penal Code states: "shall be sentenced to the death penalty, whoever used coercion in having sexual intercourse with a female or sodomy with a male."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=UAE Penal Code |url=https://www.adjd.gov.ae/sites/Authoring/AR/ELibrary%20Books/E-Library/PDFs/Penal%20Code.pdf |website=ADJD.gov.ae |access-date=1 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, same-sex relations fall under the traditional Sharia category of [[Zina]]. Some courts have gone beyond codified laws and passed sentences of stoning or flogging, thus making same-sex relationships liable to the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Lucas Ramón Mendos|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|website=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex association|access-date=7 February 2020|edition=13th|year=2019|page=479|quote=However, through the Sharia code the death penalty applies to same-sex sexual relations through the offense of Zina, which applies to sexual relations outside of the marriage of any sort. Courts have gone beyond codified laws and imposed harsher sentences of stoning and flogging for Zina crimes.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Foundation|first=Thomson Reuters|title=Stoning- where is it legal?|url=https://news.news.trust.org/item/20130927160132-qt52c/|url-status=live|website=news.trust.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Yemen}} [[LGBT rights in Yemen|Yemen]]. Punishment for [[homosexuality]] in Yemen can originate from the codified [[penal code]], or from people seeking to enforce traditional [[Islamic morality]]. Article 264 of the national penal code prohibits private consensual [[homosexual acts]] between adult men. The stipulated punishment in the law for unmarried men is 100 lashes and up to a year in prison. The law stipulates that married men convicted of homosexuality are to be [[Capital punishment in Yemen|put to death]] by stoning.&lt;ref name="gaylawnet.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gaylawnet.com/laws/ye.htm|title=GayLawNet – Laws – Yemen|website=Gaylawnet.com|access-date=17 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 268 of the national penal code prohibits private consensual homosexual acts between adult women. The law stipulates that premeditated acts of [[lesbianism]] are punished with up to three years in prison.&lt;ref name="gaylawnet.com"/&gt; In addition to the penal code, punishment for homosexuality can originate from people seeking to enforce traditional morality within their own family or for the broader society. In vigilante cases such as this, the punishment for homosexuality is oftentimes death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipsnews.net/2013/08/no-place-for-gays-in-yemen|title=No Place for Gays in Yemen – Inter Press Service|website=Ipsnews.net|date=16 August 2013 |access-date=17 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Extrajudicial killings==
{{further|Social cleansing|Honor killing|Significant acts of violence against LGBT people|Persecution of gay and bisexual men by ISIL}}
In some regions, gay people have been murdered by [[Islamist]] militias and terrorist groups, such as [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]] in parts of Iraq, Libya, and Syria, the [[Houthi movement]] in Yemen and [[Hamas]] in the [[Gaza Strip]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Under ISIS: Where Being Gay Is Punished by Death |url=https://abcnews.go.com/International/isis-gay-punished-death/story?id=39826182 |work=ABC News |date=13 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="advocate2016"&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Broverman|first=Neal|date=2 March 2016|title=Hamas Leader Accused of Gay Sex, Killed|url=https://www.advocate.com/world/2016/3/01/hamas-leader-accused-gay-sex-killed|magazine=[[The Advocate (LGBT magazine)|The Advocate]]|access-date=2016-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2016 [[Hamas]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=EU terrorist list|url=https://www.consilium.europa.eu/en/policies/fight-against-terrorism/terrorist-list/|access-date=2021-05-14|website=www.consilium.europa.eu|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Foreign Terrorist Organizations|url=https://www.state.gov/foreign-terrorist-organizations/|access-date=2021-05-14|website=United States Department of State|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; which controls the [[Palestinian National Authority]] and rules [[Gaza Strip|Gaza]], executed by firing squad Mahmoud Ishtiwi—one of the group's leading commanders—for homosexual activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Hadid|first1=Diaa|last2=Waheidi|first2=Majd Al|date=2016-03-01|title=Hamas Commander, Accused of Theft and Gay Sex, Is Killed by His Own|work=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/02/world/middleeast/hamas-commander-mahmoud-ishtiwi-killed-palestine.html|access-date=21 May 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="newsweek2016"&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Moore|first=Jack|date=2 March 2016|title=Hamas executed a prominent commander after accusations of gay sex|url=http://www.newsweek.com/prominent-hamas-commander-was-executed-after-accusations-gay-sex-432343|magazine=[[Newsweek]]|access-date=2016-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anti-gay purges in Chechnya|Anti-gay purges in the Chechen Republic]], a predominantly [[Islam in Russia|Muslim region]] of Russia, have included [[forced disappearance]]s—secret abductions, imprisonment, and [[torture]]—by local Chechen authorities targeting persons based on their perceived [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |title=A Victim of the Anti-Gay Purge in Chechnya Speaks Out: 'The Truth Exists' |url=https://time.com/5633588/anti-gay-purge-chechnya-victim/ |magazine=Time |date=26 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of 100 men, who authorities detained on suspicion of being gay or bisexual, three have reportedly died after being held in what [[human rights]] groups and eyewitnesses have called [[concentration camp]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Smith |first1=Lydia |title=Chechnya detains 100 gay men in first concentration camps since the Holocaust |url=http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/chechnya-detains-100-gay-men-first-concentration-camps-since-holocaust-1616363|access-date=16 April 2017 |work=International Business Times UK |date=10 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Advocate"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Reynolds |first1=Daniel |title=Report: Chechnya Is Torturing Gay Men in Concentration Camps |url=http://www.advocate.com/world/2017/4/10/report-chechyna-torturing-gay-men-concentration-camps |access-date=16 April 2017 |work=The Advocate |date=10 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Extrajudicial killings have occurred in [[Iraq]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2022/03/23/iraq-impunity-violence-against-lgbt-people|title=Impunity for Violence Against LGBT People|website=Human Rights Watch|date=23 March 2022 |language=en|access-date=2022-06-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cases include abductions, torture, rape and murder by vigilante mobs, millitia and perpetrators. LGBT people living in fear of their lives, campaigners [[Human Rights Watch|Human Rights Watch (HRW)]] and IraQueer found. HRW's LGBT rights researcher Rasha Younes said: "LGBT Iraqis live in constant fear of being hunted down and killed by armed groups with impunity, as well as arrest and violence by Iraqi police, making their lives unliveable."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-60859049 | title=LGBT people in Iraq live in fear of lives - HRW | work=BBC News | date=17 May 2022 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Report of vigilante executions, attacks, beatings, and torture&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/27/ugandan-gay-rights-activist-murdered|title=Ugandan gay rights activist David Kato found murdered|last=Rice|first=Xan|date=27 January 2011|work=The Guardian|access-date=1 August 2019|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ghana shadow"&gt;{{cite report |author1=Solace Brothers Foundation |author2=The Initiative for Equal Rights |author3=Center for International Human Rights of Northwestern University School of Law |author4=Heartland Alliance for Human Needs &amp; Human Rights Global Initiative for Sexuality and Human Rights |title=Human Rights Violations Against Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender (LGBT) People in Ghana: A Shadow Report |date=August 2015 |url=https://tbinternet.ohchr.org/Treaties/CCPR/Shared%20Documents/GHA/INT_CCPR_ICO_GHA_21415_E.pdf |id=Submitted for consideration at the 115th Session of the Human Rights Committee}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/204346.pdf|title=LIBERIA 2012 HUMAN RIGHTS REPORT|last=United States Department of State|first=Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor|date=2012|website=state.gov|access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://archive.globalgayz.com/africa/senegal/senegal-gay-couple-brutally-assaulted-by-parents/|title=Senegal: Gay Couple Brutally Assaulted by Parents|website=archive.globalgayz.com|access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; have been reported in heavily Christian and Muslim regions of Africa, in countries such as [[Algeria]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title='He is Gay' Written on a Wall in Blood, as Algerian Student is Murdered on Campus | url=https://www.albawaba.com/loop/he-gay-written-wall-blood-algerian-student-murdered-campus-1252164 |work= Albawa |date= February 13, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Uganda]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Amid 'Kill the Gays' bill uproar, Ugandan LGBTQ activist is killed |url=https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/amid-kill-gays-bill-uproar-ugandan-lgbtq-activist-killed-n1067336 |work=NBC News |date=16 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[South Africa]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Born free, killed by hate – the price of being gay in South Africa |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-35967725 |work=BBC News |date=7 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kenya]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Gay men hacked with machetes and murdered in wave of hate crimes in Kenya |url=https://www.gaystarnews.com/article/whats-behind-series-recent-violent-hate-crimes-against-gays-kenya170713/ |work=Gay News |date=17 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Liberia]], [[Ghana]], [[Cameroon]], and [[Senegal]]. In these countries, police turn a blind eye&lt;ref name="ghana shadow"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.glaad.org/blog/cameroonian-lgbti-activist-found-tortured-death-home|title=Cameroonian LGBTI activist found tortured to death in home|date=17 July 2013|website=GLAAD|language=en|access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; or even are complicit in the anti-gay violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author1=Philip P. Rodenbough |title=Being LGBT in West Africa |date=July 2014 |publisher=Virtual Student Foreign Service (VSFS) program, US Department of State; USAID |url=https://blogs.cuit.columbia.edu/rightsviews/files/2015/03/The-Being-LGBT-in-West-Africa-Project-Final-Report.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{see also|List of people executed for homosexuality in Europe}}

=== Australia ===
Australian states and territories first passed laws against homosexuality during the [[History of Australia|colonial era]], and nineteenth-century colonial parliaments retained provisions which made homosexual activity a capital offence until 1861.&lt;ref name=carbery&gt;{{cite web |last=Carbery |first=Graham |title=Towards Homosexual Equality in Australian Criminal Law: A Brief History |year=2010 |edition=2nd |url=http://www.alga.org.au/files/towardsequality2ed.pdf |publisher=Australian Lesbian and Gay Archives Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most jurisdictions removed capital punishment as a sentence for homosexual activity, although in [[Victoria, Australia|Victoria]] it remained as such when committed while also inflicting [[bodily harm]] or to a person younger than the age of fourteen until 1949.&lt;ref name=carbery /&gt; The last person arrested for homosexual sex in Australia was a man in 1984 in Tasmania.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://hrlibrary.umn.edu/undocs/html/vws488.htm|title=Toonen v. Australia, Communication No. 488/1992, U.N. Doc CCPR/C/50/D/488/1992 (1994).|website=hrlibrary.umn.edu|access-date=8 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last part of Australia to legalise consensual homosexual sex between adults was [[Tasmania]] in 1997. In 2017, same-sex marriage was legalised by the [[Government of Australia|Australian government]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Karp |first1=Paul |title=Same-sex marriage bill passes in Australian Senate |url=https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2017/nov/29/same-sex-marriage-bill-passes-in-australian-senate |access-date=19 May 2022 |work=The Guardian |date=29 November 2017 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Yaxley |first1=Louise |title=Same-sex marriage signed into law by Governor-General |url=https://www.abc.net.au/news/2017-12-08/same-sex-marriage-legal-after-gg-approval/9239334 |access-date=19 May 2022 |work=ABC News |date=7 December 2017 |language=en-AU}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the seven men in Australian history known to have been executed for sodomy, six cases involved the sexual abuse of minors; only one of the seven cases was for consensual acts between adults.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.utas.edu.au/library/companion_to_tasmanian_history/H/Homosexuality.htm|title=Homosexuality|website=www.utas.edu.au|access-date=1 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Those six cases being:
# John Mead, hanged at Sydney on 29 November 1836 for the forcible sodomy of a ten year old boy
# William Gibson, hanged at Launceston on 31 January 1859 for sodomy of a ten year old boy
# Hendrick Whitnalder, hanged at Hobart on 20 February 1863 for sodomy of a fourteen year old boy
# John Kelly, hanged at Beechworth on 4 May 1867 for sodomy of an eighteen-month-old boy
# Thomas Ross, hanged at Launceston on 30 January 1861 for an "unnatural crime" against a "little boy" of unknown age
# Dennis Collins, hanged at Launceston on 11 August 1863 for an "unnatural crime" against a seven year old boy&lt;/ref&gt; In that sole case, Alexander Browne was hanged at Sydney on 22 December 1828 for sodomy with his shipmate William Lyster on the whaler ''Royal Sovereign''; Lyster was also convicted and sentenced to death, but his sentence was commuted before execution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Unfit for Publication press cuttings list|url=http://www.alga.org.au/files/ufpnewssources.pdf|website=Australian Lesbian &amp; Gay Archives}}&lt;/ref&gt; Joseph Fogg was hanged at Hobart on 24 February 1830 for an "unnamed crime",  also described in one source as an "abominable crime".&lt;ref name=26feb1830&gt;{{cite news|title=Executions|url=http://trove.nla.gov.au/newspaper/article/8644929|access-date=9 March 2017|work=Colonial Times|date=26 February 1830|location=Hobart|page=3|quote=This morning, the awful sentence of the law was carried into execution upon four other persons, viz.-John Jones and Samuel Killen, for sheep-stealing; Joseph Fogg, for a nameless offence, and Thomas Goodwin, for cutting and maiming with intent the kill.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Convict Records: Joseph Fogg |url=https://convictrecords.com.au/convicts/fogg/joseph/83346 |website=convictrecords.com.au |access-date=31 July 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; The exact nature of his crime is unclear; while likely a same-sex sexual offence given the labels applied ('unnamed', 'abominable'), it too may not have been for consensual acts, but for same-sex rape, or abuse of a minor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Coad |first1=David |title=Gender trouble down under: Australian masculinities |date=2002 |publisher=Presses universitaires de Valenciennes |location=Valenciennes |isbn=9782905725301 |page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Germany ===
{{main|Persecution of homosexuals in Nazi Germany#Death penalty}}
During the period of [[Nazi Germany]] from 1933 to 1945, homosexual men were persecuted with thousands being imprisoned in [[Nazi concentration camps|concentration camps]] (and eventually [[extermination camp]]s) by the Nazi regime. Roughly 5,000–15,000 were sent to the concentration camps, with the death rate being estimated to be as high as 60%. Homosexuals in the camps suffered an unusual degree of cruelty by their captors, including being used as target practice on shooting ranges.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite book|title=The Racial State: Germany, 1933–1945|last=Burleigh|first=Michael|date=1991|publisher=Cambridge University Press|others=Wippermann, Wolfgang, Mazal Holocaust Collection.|isbn=0521391148|location=Cambridge [England]|oclc=22597244|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/racialstate00mich}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Giles|first=Geoffrey J|title=Social Outsiders in Nazi Germany|date=2001|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton, New Jersey|page=240}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Pink Triangle: The Nazi War Against Homosexuals|last=Plant|first=Richard|date=2013|publisher=Henry Holt and Company|isbn=9781429936934|location=New York|oclc=872608428}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1937 speech, Himmler argued that SS men who had served sentences for homosexuality should be transferred to a concentration camp and [[Postenpflicht|shot when trying to escape]]. This policy was never implemented, and some SS men were acquitted on homosexuality charges despite evidence against them.{{sfn|Giles|2010|p=393}}  A few death sentences against SS men for homosexual acts were pronounced between 1937 and 1940.{{sfn|Lorenz|2018|p=15}} In a speech on 18 August 1941, Hitler argued that homosexuality should be combatted throughout Nazi organizations and the military. In particular, homosexuality in the [[Hitler Youth]] must be punished by death in order to protect youth from being turned into homosexuals, however the Hitler Youth never implemented this policy.{{sfn|Giles|2010|pp=393–394}}

After learning of Hitler's remark, Himmler decided that the SS must be at least as tough on homosexuality and drafted a decree mandating the death penalty to any member of the SS and police found guilty of engaging in a homosexual act. Hitler signed the decree on 15 November 1941 on the condition that there be absolutely no publicity, worried that such a harsh decree might lend fuel to left-wing propaganda that homosexuality was especially prevalent in Germany. Since it could not be published in the SS newspaper, the decree was communicated to SS men one-on-one by their superiors. However, this was not done consistently and many arrested men asserted that they had no knowledge of the decree.{{sfn|Giles|2010|pp=393–394}} 

Even after the decree, only a few death sentences were pronounced.{{sfn|Giles|2010|p=394}}{{sfn|Longerich|2011|p=239}} Himmler often commuted the sentence especially if he thought that the accused was not a committed homosexual, but had suffered a one-time mistake (particularly while drunk). Many of those whose sentence was commuted were sent to serve in the [[Dirlewanger Brigade]], a penal unit on the Eastern Front, where most were killed.{{sfn|Giles|2010|p=394}} After late 1943, because of military losses, it was the policy to recycle SS men convicted of homosexuality into the Wehrmacht.{{sfn|Schlagdenhauffen|2018|p=33}}

The 1933 law on habitual criminals also allowed for execution after the third conviction.{{sfn|Lorenz|2018|pp=12–13}} On 4 September 1941 a new law allowed the execution of dangerous sex offenders or habitual criminals when "the protection of the ''Volksgemeinschaft'' or the need for just atonement require it". This law enabled authorities to pronounce death sentences against homosexuals, and is known to have been employed in four cases in Austria.{{sfn|Scheck|2020|p=422}}{{sfn|Lorenz|2018|p=13}}  In 1943, [[Wilhelm Keitel]], head of the [[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]], authorized the death penalty for soldiers convicted of homosexuality in "particularly serious cases".{{sfn|Storkmann|2021|p=28}}{{sfn|Lorenz|2018|pp=14, 16}} Only a few executions of homosexual Wehrmacht soldiers are known, mostly in conjunction with other charges especially [[desertion]].{{sfn|Storkmann|2021|p=28}} Some homosexuals were executed at Nazi euthanasia centers, such as [[Bernburg Euthanasia Centre|Bernburg]] or Meseritz-Obrawalde. It is difficult to estimate the number of homosexuals directly killed during the Nazi era.{{sfn|Lorenz|2018|p=11}}

=== United Kingdom ===
From 1533, under the [[Buggery Act 1533]], capital felony for any person to "commit the detestable and abominable vice of buggery with mankind or beast", was enacted, repealed and re-enacted several times by [[the Crown]], until it was reinstated permanently in 1563. Homosexual activity remained a capital offence until 1861.&lt;ref name="Colonial"&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1061&amp;context=englishfacpubs|journal=Journal of Homosexuality|volume=1|issue=3|date=1976|title=Homosexuals and the Death Penalty in Colonial America|first=Louis|last=Crompton|access-date=20 May 2016|doi=10.1300/j082v01n03_03|pages=277–293|pmid=798008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last execution took place on 27 November 1835 when [[James Pratt and John Smith]] were hanged outside [[Newgate Prison]] in London.

=== United States ===
{{See also|Sodomy laws in the United States}}
During the [[Colonial history of the United States|colonial era]] of [[History of the United States|American history]], the various European nations which [[European colonization of the Americas|established colonies]] in the Americas brought their pre-existing laws against homosexuality (which included capital punishment) with them. The establishment of the United States after their victory in the [[American Revolutionary War|Revolutionary War]] did not bring about any changes in the status of capital punishment as a sentence for being convicted of homosexual behavior. Beginning in the 19th century, the various state legislatures passed legislation which ended the status of capital punishment being used for those who were convicted of homosexual behavior. [[South Carolina]] was the last state, in 1873, to repeal the death penalty for homosexual behaviour from its statute books. The number of times the penalty was carried out is unknown. Records show there were at least two executions, and a number of more convictions with vague labels, such as "crimes against nature".&lt;ref name="Colonial" /&gt;

=== Sudan ===
In July 2020, the sodomy law that previously punished gay men with up to 100 lashes for the first offence, five years in jail for the second and the death penalty the third time around was abolished, with new legislation reducing the penalty to prison terms ranging from five years to life. Sudanese LGBT+ activists hailed the reform as a 'great first step', but said it was not enough yet, and the end goal should be the decriminalisation of same-sex sexual activity altogether.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-sudan-lgbt-rights-trfn/great-first-step-as-sudan-lifts-death-penalty-and-flogging-for-gay-sex-idUSKCN24H30J |title='Great first step' as Sudan lifts death penalty and flogging for gay sex |author1=Ban Barkawi|author2=Rachel Savage |work=[[Reuters]] |date=16 July 2020 |access-date=17 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

===Bibliography===
*{{cite book |last1=Giles |first1=Geoffrey J. |title=The Routledge History of the Holocaust |date=2010 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=978-0-203-83744-3 |chapter=The Persecution of Gay Men and Lesbians During the Third Reich|pages=385–396}}
*{{cite book |last1=Longerich |first1=Peter |author1-link=Peter Longerich |title=Heinrich Himmler: A Life |date=2011 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |isbn=978-0-19-161705-8 |language=en}}
*{{cite book |last1=Lorenz |first1=Gottfried |title=Todesurteile und Hinrichtungen wegen homosexueller Handlungen während der NS-Zeit: Mann-männliche Internetprostitution. Und andere Texte zur Geschichte und zur Situation der Homosexuellen in Deutschland|trans-title=Death sentences and executions for homosexual acts during the Nazi era, male-male internet prostitution, and other texts on the history and situation of homosexuals in Germany |date=2018 |publisher=[[LIT Verlag]] |isbn=978-3-643-13992-4 |language=de}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Scheck |first1=Raffael |title=The Danger of "Moral Sabotage": Western Prisoners of War on Trial for Homosexual Relations in Nazi Germany |journal=Journal of the History of Sexuality |date=2020 |volume=29 |issue=3 |pages=418–446 |doi=10.7560/JHS29305|s2cid=&lt;!--  --&gt; }}
*{{cite book|last=Schlagdenhauffen|first= Régis|chapter=Queer life in Europe during the Second World War" and "Punishing homosexual men and women under the Third Reich|title= Queer in Europe during the Second World War|publisher= Council of Europe|date= 2018| isbn =978-92-871-8464-1|url=https://rm.coe.int/079317-queer-in-europe-during-the-second-world-war-web-web/16808e4a53|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20220217041539/https://rm.coe.int/079317-queer-in-europe-during-the-second-world-war-web-web/16808e4a53|archive-date= 17 February 2022|pages=7–20, 21–38}}
*{{cite book |last1=Storkmann |first1=Klaus |title=Tabu und Toleranz: Der Umgang mit Homosexualität in der Bundeswehr 1955 bis 2000|trans-title=Taboo and Tolerance: Homosexuality and the Bundeswehr 1955 to 2000 |date=2021 |publisher=[[De Gruyter]] |isbn=978-3-11-073290-0 |language=de}}

{{Criminalization of homosexuality}}
{{Capital punishment}}
[[Category:Capital punishment|Homosexuality]]
[[Category:Criminalization of homosexuality]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>