<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171108203143|809391601" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="50402549" pageid="50402549" ns="0" title="Capital punishment for homosexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-18T17:13:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''death penalty for homosexuality''' has historically been implemented by a number of nations worldwide.  It is currently still extant in a fairly small number of countries or parts of countries, all due to [[sharia law]].   Even though the law may allow the death penalty it does not mean that it is carried out.  Conversely ''de facto'' death penalties may apply, for example the ''[[The Washington Post|Washington Post]]'' said that in Iraq "The penal code does not expressly prohibit homosexual acts, but people have been killed by militias and sentenced to death by judges citing sharia law."

==Current regimes with the death penalty==
* [[Afghanistan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/ |title=Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death |publisher=The Washington Post |date=16 June 2016 |accessdate=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.deathpenaltyworldwide.org/country-search-post.cfm?country=Afghanistan |title=The Death Penalty in Afghanistan |publisher=Death Penalty Worldwide |accessdate=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Brunei]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/04/15/brunei-gay-sex-law_n_5154960.html)|title=Brunei Law To Allow Death By Stoning For Gay Sex|work=The Huffington Post|accessdate=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Mauritania]], only applies to Muslim men&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;
* [[Sudan]] for a third conviction&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015"&gt;{{cite web|author1=Aengus Carroll|author2=Lucas Paoli Itaborahy|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia: A World Survey of Laws: criminalisation, protection and recognition of same-sex love|url=http://old.ilga.org/Statehomophobia/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2015.pdf|website=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex association|accessdate=6 May 2016|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Northern Nigeria]] where several states have adopted [[sharia law]]&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;
* [[Yemen]]&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="WP"&gt;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2014/02/24/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death/&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Saudi Arabia]]&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;
* [[Qatar]] applies only to Muslims, for extramarital-sex regardless of the gender of the participants&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;
* [[Somalia]] where several southern states have adopted sharia law&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;
* [[Iran]]&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;
* [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Solomon|first1=Andrew|title=Far and Away: Reporting from the Brink of Change|date=2016|page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is legal dispute whether the law of the [[United Arab Emirates]] allows for the death penalty for homosexuality, however [[Amnesty International]] could find no instances of the death penalty.&lt;ref name="WP" /&gt;

==Historical==

===Australia===
Australian states and territories inherited British laws relating to homosexuality, and laws passed in nineteenth century colonial parliaments retained the provisions which made homosexual activity a capital crime.&lt;ref name=carbery&gt;{{cite journal |last=Carbery |first=Graham |title=Towards Homosexual Equality in Australian Criminal Law: A Brief History |year=2010 |edition=2nd |issue= |pages= |url=http://www.alga.org.au/files/towardsequality2ed.pdf |publisher=Australian Lesbian and Gay Archives Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, various jurisdictions began to reduce the death penalty for sodomy to life imprisonment, with Victoria being the last to remove the death penalty for this crime, in 1949.&lt;ref name=carbery /&gt;

===United Kingdom===
From 1533 it was a capital felony for any person to "commit the detestable and abominable vice of buggery with mankind or beast," was repealed and re-enacted several times, until it was reinstated in 1563 remaining unchanged until 1861.&lt;ref name="Colonial"&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1061&amp;context=englishfacpubs|work=Journal of Homosexuality|volume=1|issue=3|date=1976|title=Homosexuals and the Death Penalty in Colonial America|author=Louis Crompton|accessdate=20 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States and colonial America===
{{See also|Sodomy laws in the United States}}
Colonial America had the laws of the United Kingdom, and the revolutionary states took many of those laws as the basis of their own, in some cases verbatim.&lt;ref name="Colonial" /&gt;  The last law where the death penalty was on the statute books was South Carolina, the old British law was repealed until 1873, twelve years after the mother country.&lt;ref name="Colonial" /&gt;

The number of times the penalty was carried out is unknown, records support two executions, and a number of more uncertain convections, such as "crimes against nature".&lt;ref name="Colonial" /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*

[[Category:LGBT rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>