<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201122040057|989987672" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="50402549" pageid="50402549" ns="0" title="Capital punishment for homosexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-22T04:01:59Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{LGBT rights sidebar}}
[[Capital punishment]] for [[homosexuality]] was implemented by a number of countries worldwide. It currently remains a legal punishment in several countries and regions, all of which have ''[[sharia]]''-based criminal laws. Being prescribed by the law does not necessarily mean that the penalty is carried out in practice. Gay people also face extrajudicial killings by state and non-state actors, as in [[Anti-gay purges in Chechnya|Chechnya in 2019]].

Imposition of the death penalty for homosexuality may be classified as [[judicial murder]] of gay people, which can be analyzed as a form of [[genocide]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=DeJong |first1=Christina |last2=Long |first2=Eric |title=Handbook of LGBT Communities, Crime, and Justice |publisher=Springer |isbn=978-1-4614-9188-0 |pages=339–362 |language=en |chapter=The Death Penalty as Genocide: The Persecution of “Homosexuals” in Uganda}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In current state laws==
[[File:World laws pertaining to homosexual relationships and expression.svg|thumb|{{legend|#8c210f|Death penalty for homosexuality}}{{legend|#cc6633|Death penalty on books but not applied}}]]
{{Further|LGBT rights by country or territory|LGBT in Islam|Capital punishment for adultery|Sharia#Islamization}}

As of July 2020, the following jurisdictions prescribe the death penalty for homosexuality:

* {{flagicon|Afghanistan}} [[LGBT rights in Afghanistan|Afghanistan]]. A new Penal Code enacted in February 2018 explicitly criminalises same-sex sexual conduct.{{citation needed|date=July 2020}} Sources cited by ILGA indicate that there is a "broad consensus amongst scholars that execution was the appropriate punishment if homosexual acts could be proven”.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|isbn=|location=Geneva|pages=429|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sharia category of ''[[zina]]'' (illicit sexual intercourse), which according to some traditional Islamic [[Madhhab|legal schools]] may entail the ''[[Hudud|hadd]]'' (sharia-prescribed) punishment of stoning, when strict evidential requirements are met. The [[Hanafi]] school, prevalent in Afghanistan, does not regard homosexual acts as a ''hadd'' crime, although Afghan judges may potentially apply the death penalty for a number of reasons. No known death sentences for homosexuality have been passed since the end of Taliban rule in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/ |title=Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death |work=The Washington Post |date=16 June 2016 |accessdate=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.deathpenaltyworldwide.org/country-search-post.cfm?country=Afghanistan |title=The Death Penalty in Afghanistan |publisher=Death Penalty Worldwide |accessdate=25 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Brunei}} [[LGBT rights in Brunei|Brunei]]'s ''Sharia Penal Code'', implemented in stages since 2014, prescribes death by stoning as punishment for same-sex relations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/mar/28/brunei-brings-in-death-by-stoning-as-punishment-for-gay-sex|title=Brunei introduces death by stoning as punishment for gay sex|last=correspondent|first=Hannah Ellis-Petersen South-east Asia|date=2019-03-28|work=The Guardian|access-date=2019-03-28|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt; After international backlash, in May 2019, the Sultan of Brunei explained that a "de facto" moratorium on the execution of the death penalty has been in force in the country for the last two decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Brunei says it won't enforce gay death penalty after backlash |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-brunei-lgbt-sultan/brunei-says-it-wont-enforce-gay-death-penalty-after-backlash-idUSKCN1SB0FS |website=Reuters |accessdate=August 19, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* {{flagicon|Iran}} [[LGBT rights in Iran|Iran]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015"&gt;{{cite web|author1=Aengus Carroll|author2=Lucas Paoli Itaborahy|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia: A World Survey of Laws: criminalisation, protection and recognition of same-sex love|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/2017/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2017_WEB.pdf|website=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex association|accessdate=April 5, 2019|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexual intercourse is declared a capital offense in Iran's ''Islamic Penal Code'', enacted in 1991. Articles 233 through 241 criminalise both female and male same-sex activity; the death penalty only applies to some cases of male-male penile-anal intercourse, with female-female activity and other cases of male-male activity being punished by flogging instead of execution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Refugees|first=United Nations High Commissioner for|title=Refworld {{!}} Iran: Islamic Penal Code|url=https://www.refworld.org/docid/518a19404.html|access-date=2020-07-20|website=Refworld|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though the grounds for execution in Iran are difficult to track, there is evidence that several people were hanged for homosexual behaviour in 2005-2006 and in 2016, in some cases on dubious charges of rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Asal, V.|author2=Sommer, U.|title= Legal Path Dependence and the Long Arm of the Religious State: Sodomy Provisions and Gay Rights Across Nations and Over Time|publisher=State University of New York Press|page=64}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=economist&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Economist|title=How homosexuality became a crime in the Middle East|date=June 6, 2018|url=https://www.economist.com/open-future/2018/06/06/how-homosexuality-became-a-crime-in-the-middle-east}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Mauritania}} [[LGBT rights in Mauritania|Mauritania]].&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt; According to a 1984 law, Muslim men can be stoned for engaging in homosexual sex, though no executions have occurred so far.&lt;ref name="WP"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/13/here-are-the-10-countries-where-homosexuality-may-be-punished-by-death-2/|title=Analysis - Here are the 10 countries where homosexuality may be punished by death|first1=Max|last1=Bearak|first2=Darla|last2=Cameron|date=16 June 2016|work=The Washington Post|quote=Lawyers in the country and other experts disagree on whether federal law prescribes the death penalty for consensual homosexual sex or only for rape. In a recent Amnesty International report, the organization said it was not aware of any death sentences for homosexual acts.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The country has observed a moratorium on the execution of the death penalty since 1987.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|isbn=|location=Geneva|pages=347|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Nigeria}} [[LGBT rights in Nigeria|Nigeria]], where several northern [[States of Nigeria|states]] have adopted [[sharia]]-based criminal laws, though no executions are known.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia 2019|last=Mendos|first=Lucas Ramón|publisher=ILGA|year=2019|isbn=|location=Geneva|pages=359|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Saudi Arabia}} [[LGBT rights in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Arabia]], which does not have codified criminal laws.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt; According to the country's interpretation of sharia, a married man who commits sodomy, or a non-Muslim who engages in sodomy with a Muslim, can be stoned to death.&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt; There are unconfirmed reports that two cross-dressing Pakistani nationals were killed by Saudi authorities in 2017, which Saudi officials have denied.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;
* {{flagicon|Somalia}} [[LGBT rights in Somalia|Somalia]] ({{flag|Jubaland}}), where Islamic courts have imposed sharia-based death penalties in some southern regions.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt;
* {{flag|United Arab Emirates}}: Legal experts disagree on whether the federal law of the [[LGBT rights in United Arab Emirates|United Arab Emirates]] prescribes the death penalty for consensual gay sex or only for rape.&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt; Article 354 of the Federal Penal Code states: "shall be sentenced to death penalty, whoever used coercion in having sexual intercourse with a female or sodomy with a male."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=UAE Penal Code |url=https://www.adjd.gov.ae/sites/Authoring/AR/ELibrary%20Books/E-Library/PDFs/Penal%20Code.pdf |website=ADJD.gov.ae |accessdate=1 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, same-sex relations fall under the traditional Sharia category of [[Zina]], which encompasses any sexual intercourse outside of marriage, all of which are banned in the UAE. Although application of Zina provisions in the UAE appears to be limited to prosecution of rape, some courts have gone beyond codified laws and passed sentences of stoning or flogging, thus theoretically making same-sex relationship liable to death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Lucas Ramón Mendos|title=State-Sponsored Homophobia|url=https://ilga.org/downloads/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2019.pdf|website=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex association|accessdate=February 7, 2020|edition=13th|year=2019|page=479|quote=However, it is through the Sharia code that the death penalty theoretically can apply to same-sex sexual relations through the offence of Zina, which applies to sexual relations outside of marriage of any sort. However, it appears that the law is used in rape cases only although in some cases courts have gone beyond codified laws and imposed harsher sentences of stoning and flogging for Zina crimes.}}&lt;/ref&gt; A recent [[Amnesty International]] report states that they are not aware of any death sentences for homosexual acts.&lt;ref name="WP"/&gt;

==Extrajudicial killings==
{{further|Social cleansing|Honor killing|Significant acts of violence against LGBT people|Persecution of gay and bisexual men by ISIL}}
In some regions, gay people have been murdered by [[Islamist]] militias, such as [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]] in parts of Iraq and Syria and the [[Houthi movement]] in Yemen.&lt;ref name="ILGA 2015" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Under ISIS: Where Being Gay Is Punished by Death |url=https://abcnews.go.com/International/isis-gay-punished-death/story?id=39826182 |work=ABC News |date=13 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anti-gay purges in Chechnya|Anti-gay purges in the Chechen Republic]], a predominantly [[Islam in Russia|Muslim region]] of Russia, have included [[forced disappearance]]s — secret abductions, imprisonment, and [[torture]] — by local Chechen authorities targeting persons based on their perceived [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=A Victim of the Anti-Gay Purge in Chechnya Speaks Out: 'The Truth Exists' |url=https://time.com/5633588/anti-gay-purge-chechnya-victim/ |work=Time |date=26 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; An unknown number of men, who authorities detained on suspicion of being gay or bisexual, have reportedly died after being held in what [[human rights]] groups and eyewitnesses have called [[concentration camp]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Smith |first1=Lydia |title=Chechnya detains 100 gay men in first concentration camps since the Holocaust |url=http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/chechnya-detains-100-gay-men-first-concentration-camps-since-holocaust-1616363|accessdate=16 April 2017 |work=International Business Times UK |date=10 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Advocate"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Reynolds |first1=Daniel |title=Report: Chechnya Is Torturing Gay Men in Concentration Camps |url=http://www.advocate.com/world/2017/4/10/report-chechyna-torturing-gay-men-concentration-camps |accessdate=16 April 2017 |work=The Advocate |date=10 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Report of vigilante executions, beatings, and torture&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/jan/27/ugandan-gay-rights-activist-murdered|title=Ugandan gay rights activist David Kato found murdered|last=Rice|first=Xan|date=2011-01-27|work=The Guardian|access-date=2019-08-01|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="tbinternet.ohchr.org"&gt;https://tbinternet.ohchr.org/Treaties/CCPR/Shared%20Documents/GHA/INT_CCPR_ICO_GHA_21415_E.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/204346.pdf|title=LIBERIA 2012 HUMAN RIGHTS REPORT|last=United States Department of State|first=Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor|date=2012|website=state.gov|access-date=2019-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://archive.globalgayz.com/africa/senegal/senegal-gay-couple-brutally-assaulted-by-parents/|title=Senegal: Gay Couple Brutally Assaulted by Parents|website=archive.globalgayz.com|access-date=2019-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; have been reported in highly religious regions of Africa, in countries such as [[Uganda]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Amid 'Kill the Gays' bill uproar, Ugandan LGBTQ activist is killed |url=https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/amid-kill-gays-bill-uproar-ugandan-lgbtq-activist-killed-n1067336 |work=NBC News |date=16 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[South Africa]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Born free, killed by hate - the price of being gay in South Africa |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-35967725 |publisher=BBC News |date=7 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kenya]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Gay men hacked with machetes and murdered in wave of hate crimes in Kenya |url=https://www.gaystarnews.com/article/whats-behind-series-recent-violent-hate-crimes-against-gays-kenya170713/ |work=Gay News |date=17 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Liberia]], [[Ghana]], [[Cameroon]], and [[Senegal]]. In these countries, police turn a blind eye&lt;ref name="tbinternet.ohchr.org"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.glaad.org/blog/cameroonian-lgbti-activist-found-tortured-death-home|title=Cameroonian LGBTI activist found tortured to death in home|date=2013-07-17|website=GLAAD|language=en|access-date=2019-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; or even are complicit in the anti-gay violence.&lt;ref&gt;http://blogs.cuit.columbia.edu/rightsviews/files/2015/03/The-Being-LGBT-in-West-Africa-Project-Final-Report.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{see also|List of people executed for homosexuality in Europe}}

===Australia===
Australian states and territories inherited British laws relating to homosexuality, and laws passed in nineteenth century colonial parliaments retained the provisions which made homosexual activity a capital crime until 1861.&lt;ref name=carbery&gt;{{cite web |last=Carbery |first=Graham |title=Towards Homosexual Equality in Australian Criminal Law: A Brief History |year=2010 |edition=2nd |issue= |pages= |url=http://www.alga.org.au/files/towardsequality2ed.pdf |publisher=Australian Lesbian and Gay Archives Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most jurisdictions removed capital punishment, although in Victoria it remained a capital crime when committed with violence or to a person younger than the age of fourteen until 1949.&lt;ref name=carbery /&gt; The last person arrested for homosexual sex in Australia was a man in 1984 in Tasmania.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://hrlibrary.umn.edu/undocs/html/vws488.htm|title=Toonen v. Australia, Communication No. 488/1992, U.N. Doc CCPR/C/50/D/488/1992 (1994).|website=hrlibrary.umn.edu|access-date=2019-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last part of Australia to legalise consensual homosexual sex between adults was [[Tasmania]] in 1997. In 2017, homosexual marriage was legalised.

Seven men are known in Australian history to have been executed for sodomy; however, six of those seven cases involved the sexual abuse of minors.&lt;ref&gt;Those six cases being:
# John Mead, hanged at Sydney on 29 November 1836 for the forcible sodomy of a ten year old boy
# William Gibson, hanged at Launceston on 31 January 1859 for sodomy of a ten year old boy
# Hendrick Whitnalder, hanged at Hobart on 20 February 1863 for sodomy of a fourteen year old boy
# John Kelly, hanged at Beechworth on 4 May 1867 for sodomy of an eighteen month old boy
# Thomas Ross, hanged at Launceston on 30 January 1861 for an "unnatural crime" against a "little boy" of unknown age
# Dennis Collins, hanged at Launceston on 11 August 1863 for an "unnatural crime" against a seven year old boy&lt;/ref&gt; In the remaining case, Alexander Browne was hanged at Sydney on 22 December 1828 for sodomy with his shipmate William Lyster on the whaler ''Royal Sovereign''; Lyster was also convicted and sentenced to death, but his sentence was commuted before execution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=|title=Unfit for Publication press cuttings list|url=http://www.alga.org.au/files/ufpnewssources.pdf|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=|website=Australian Lesbian &amp; Gay Archives}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, Joseph Fogg was hanged at Hobart on 26 February 1830 for an "unnatural crime", but the nature of the crime is unclear (the term could refer to consensual sex between adult males, same-sex rape, sexual abuse of minors, or bestiality).

===Nazi Germany===
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2020}}
{{Original research section|date=March 2020}}
Despite numerous countries in Europe, the Americas and Asia beginning to [[Timeline of LGBT history|decriminalise homosexuality by the mid 20th century]], [[Adolf Hitler]] and his [[Nazi Party]], with intense far-right nationalist support, outlawed homosexual groups and included homosexuals as one of the minority groups sent to [[Nazi death camp|death camp]]s. An estimated 3000-9000 homosexuals died in concentration camps between 1933 and 1945, with another 2000-6000 survivors made to serve the rest of their sentence in prison under [[Paragraph 175]].

=== Sudan ===
In July 2020, the sodomy law that previously punished gay men with up to 100 lashes for the first offence, five years in jail for the second and the death penalty the third time around was abolished, with new legislation reducing the penalty to prison terms ranging from five years to life. Sudanese LGBT+ activists hailed the reform as a 'great first step', but said it was not enough yet, and the end goal should be the decriminalisation of gay sexual activity altogether.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-sudan-lgbt-rights-trfn/great-first-step-as-sudan-lifts-death-penalty-and-flogging-for-gay-sex-idUSKCN24H30J |title='Great first step' as Sudan lifts death penalty and flogging for gay sex |author=Ban Barkawi, Rachel Savage |publisher=Reuters |date=16 July 2020 |accessdate=17 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
From 1533 the capital felony for any person to "commit the detestable and abominable vice of buggery with mankind or beast", was repealed and re-enacted several times, until it was reinstated in 1563, remaining unchanged until 1861.&lt;ref name="Colonial"&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1061&amp;context=englishfacpubs|work=Journal of Homosexuality|volume=1|issue=3|date=1976|title=Homosexuals and the Death Penalty in Colonial America|author=Louis Crompton|accessdate=20 May 2016|doi=10.1300/j082v01n03_03|pages=277–293}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last execution took place on 27 November 1835 when [[James Pratt and John Smith]] were hanged at [[Newgate Prison]] in London.

One source claims the last execution for sodomy in the [[British Empire]] happened in the [[Colony of Tasmania]] (now part of [[Australia]]) in 1867.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.utas.edu.au/library/companion_to_tasmanian_history/H/Homosexuality.htm|title=Homosexuality|website=www.utas.edu.au|access-date=2019-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States and colonial America===
{{See also|Sodomy laws in the United States}}
Colonial America variously inherited the laws of the [[Kingdom of Spain]] ([[Spanish Florida]] and the [[New Spain]]); the [[Kingdom of England]] to 1707, and from 1707 to independence, the [[Kingdom of Great Britain]]; the [[Kingdom of France]] ([[Louisiana (New France)|Louisiana]] and [[New France]]); and the [[Russian Empire]] ([[Russian America|Alaska]]). The independence of the Thirteen Colonies did not prompt changes to pre-existing legal systems but the subsequent westward expansion of the United States was accompanied by English legal traditions replacing those introduced by the French, Spanish and Russians (except in the future State of Louisiana).

South Carolina was the last state, in 1873, to repeal the death penalty for homosexual behaviour from its statute books. The number of times the penalty was carried out is unknown. Records show there were at least two executions, and a number of more convictions with vague labels, such as "crimes against nature".&lt;ref name="Colonial" /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{criminalization of homosexuality}}

[[Category:Capital punishment]]
[[Category:Criminalization of homosexuality]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>