<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061002204313|79110802" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="55084" pageid="55084" ns="0" title="Cultural genocide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-28T18:41:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Cultural genocide''' is a term used to describe the deliberate destruction of the cultural heritage of a people or nation for political or military reasons. 

==United Nations==

Article 7 of the "United Nations draft declaration on the rights of indigenous peoples" ([[26 August]] [[1994]]) defines "Cultural genocide" (emphasis added)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/E.CN.4.SUB.2.RES.1994.45.En?OpenDocument Draft United Nations declaration on the rights of indigenous peoples] drafted by The Sub-Commission on Prevention of Discrimination and Protection of Minorities Recalling  resolutions 1985/22 of 29 August 1985, 1991/30 of [[29 August]] [[1991]], 1992/33 of [[27 August]] [[1992]], 1993/46 of [[26 August]] [[1993]], presented to the Commission on Human Rights and the Economic and Social Council at 36th meeting [[26 August]] [[1994]] and adopted without a vote.&lt;/ref&gt;:
:Indigenous peoples have the collective and individual right not to be subjected to ethnocide and '''cultural genocide''', including prevention of and redress for:
::(a) Any action which has the aim or effect of depriving them of their integrity as distinct peoples, or of their cultural values or ethnic identities;
::(b) Any action which has the aim or effect of dispossessing them of their lands, territories or resources;
::(c) Any form of population transfer which has the aim or effect of violating or undermining any of their rights;
::(d) Any form of assimilation or integration by other cultures or ways of life imposed on them by legislative, administrative or other measures;
::(e) Any form of propaganda directed against them.

==Examples==

{{POV}}

The [[Government of Tibet in Exile]] and its supporters use the term to describe the activities of the [[People's Republic of China]] in Tibet which it claims is destroying ancient Tibetan culture and religion.  The activities which the Government in Exile accuses the Chinese government of performing include closing Tibetan Buddhist temples and encouraging outside immigration into Tibet.

Supporters of the People's Republic of China argue that while wishing to stop secessionist activity in Tibet it does not actively desire to see Tibetan culture eradicated.  They also claim that it is improper to use such a highly charged word as [[genocide]] to describe any cultural change, especially since Chinese policies in Tibet have allegedly been far less [[cultural assimilation|assimilationist]] than the policies of many nations which are making the criticism.

Other examples of alleged cultural genocide also include: the [[dissolution of the monasteries]] in medieval England, the flooding of the ancient city of [[Hasankeyf]] by the construction of the [[Ilısu Dam]], destruction of Armenian churches and the destruction of Greek/Byzantine monuments in [[Turkey]][http://www.chiesa.espressonline.it/dettaglio.jsp?id=46544&amp;eng=y]; the burning of national archives in [[Sarajevo]]; [[Indian Removal]] in the [[United States]] (and similar polices carried out by [[Australia]], [[Canada]] and [[New Zealand]] aimed at relocating and assimilating indigenous peoples); the deliberate destruction of the Irish Public Records Office and its thousand years of records by the [[Irish Republican Army]] in [[1922]]; the destruction of [[Armenia|Armenian]] stone crosses, cemeteries, and katchkars by [[Azerbaijan]] in the region of [[Nakhichevan]][http://www.armenica.org/history/old-jougha/index.html]; and the destruction of [[Cambodia]]n monuments and records by the [[Khmer Rouge]] (some of which might be described as being closer to ''cultural suicide''). Various critics of the Allied bombing of [[Dresden]] also describe the destruction of the militarily insignificant but architecturally priceless city by carpet bombing as cultural genocide or ''bomb holocaust''.

[[Racist]]s claim this practice is being inflicted on western countries due to alleged mass immigration
&lt;ref name=bnp&gt;[http://www.bnp.org.uk/news_detail.php?newsId=357 ''The Era of Defamation and Multi-Cultural Genocide''] [[British National Party]] claims "multi-cultural genocide" in progess against Britain&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=kkk&gt;[http://www.davidduke.com/?p=179 ''John Tyndall Arrested ''] [[Ku-Klux Klan]] leader claims cultural genocide against Whites&lt;/ref&gt;.

==See also==

* [[Endangered language]]
* [[Language policy]]
* [[Linguicide]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Stolen Generation]] of Australia
* [[Residential school]]s in Canada
* [[Native Schools]] in New Zealand
* [[Carlisle Indian Industrial School]] in the United States
* [[Ilısu Dam Campaign]]
* [[Southeastern Anatolia Project]]
* [[Welsh Not]]
* [[Prayer Book Rebellion]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;
==External links==

*[http://www.cceia.org/viewMedia.php/prmTemplateID/8/prmID/5139 Rethinking Cultural Genocide Under International Law] 
*[http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/ Raphael Lemkin] 
*[http://www.savetibet.org/news/newsitem.php?id=983 Tibetan cultural genocide] 
*[http://www.regnum.ru/english/560850.html Cultural genocide of Armenian monuments continues] 
*[http://www.australian-news.com.au/Aboriginal.htm Aboriginal cultural genocide] 
*[http://www.nemasys.com/ghostwolf/Native/genocide.shtml Spiritual and cultural genocide of the Native Americans] 
*[http://groups.yahoo.com/group/celtic_league/message/1772 Breton TV boss condemns the French government’s cultural genocide of the Breton people] 
*[http://www.kernowtgg.co.uk/ Cornish cultural genocide/Cornish paradox] 
*[http://www.pitcairners.org/bloodless_genocide2.html Bloodless Genocide of the Pitcairn People in Norfolk Island] 
*[http://www.cornwall24.co.uk/PNphpBB2-viewtopic-t-749-highlight-genocide.htm Cornish cultural genocide]

==Notes==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;&lt;references /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:Genocide]]

[[fr:Génocide culturel]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>