<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20110703185658|437590013" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="55084" pageid="55084" ns="0" title="Cultural genocide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-09-05T23:32:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
'''Cultural genocide''' is a term that lawyer [[Raphael Lemkin]] proposed in 1933 as a component to [[genocide]]. The term was considered in the 1948 [[United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples]] juxtaposed next to the term [[ethnocide]], but it was removed in the final document, replaced with simply "genocide". The precise definition of "cultural genocide" remains unclear.

==Usage==
As early as 1933, lawyer Raphael Lemkin proposed a cultural component to genocide, which he called "[[vandalism]]".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/madrid1933-english.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Acts Constituting a General (Transnational) Danger Considered as Offences Against the Law of Nations'' (J. Fussell trans., 2000) (1933)]; [http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/AxisRule1944-3.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Axis Rule in Occupied Europe'', p. 91 (1944)].&lt;/ref&gt; The term has since acquired rhetorical value as a phrase that is used to protest against the destruction of cultural heritage. It is also often misused as a catchphrase to condemn any destruction the user of the phrase disapproves of, without regard for the criterion of intent to destroy an affected group as such.

===Proposed usage===
The drafters of the 1948 [[Genocide Convention]] considered the use of the term, but dropped it from their consideration.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.un.org/icty/krstic/TrialC1/judgement/krs-tj010802e-3.htm#IIIG2bi Prosecutor v. Krstic, Case No. IT-98-33-T (Int'l Crim. Trib. Yugo. Trial Chamber 2001), at para. 576].
&lt;/ref&gt; The legal definition of [[genocide]] is left unspecific about the exact nature in which genocide is done only that it is destruction with intent to destroy a racial, religious, ethnic or national group as such.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm Convention on Prevention and Punishment of Genocide, art. 2, Dec. 9, 1948, 78 U.N.T.S. 277.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Article 7 of a 1994 draft of the [[United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples]] uses the phrase "cultural genocide" but does not define what it means.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/E.CN.4.SUB.2.RES.1994.45.En?OpenDocument Draft United Nations declaration on the rights of indigenous peoples] drafted by The Sub-Commission on Prevention of Discrimination and Protection of Minorities Recalling  resolutions 1985/22 of 29 August 1985, 1991/30 of 29 August 1991, 1992/33 of 27 August 1992, 1993/46 of 26 August 1993, presented to the Commission on Human Rights and the Economic and Social Council at 36th meeting 26 August 1994 and adopted without a vote.&lt;/ref&gt; The complete article reads as follows:
:Indigenous peoples have the collective and individual right not to be subjected to [[ethnocide]] and cultural genocide, including prevention of and redress for:
::(a) Any action which has the aim or effect of depriving them of their integrity as distinct peoples, or of their cultural values or ethnic identities;
::(b) Any action which has the aim or effect of dispossessing them of their lands, territories or resources;
::(c) Any form of [[population transfer]] which has the aim or effect of violating or undermining any of their rights;
::(d) Any form of [[acculturation|assimilation or integration]] by other cultures or ways of life imposed on them by legislative, administrative or other measures;
::(e) Any form of propaganda directed against them.

This declaration only appeared in a draft. The [[United Nations]] Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples was adopted by the [[United Nations General Assembly]] during its 62nd session at [[UN Headquarters]] in [[New York City]] on 13 September 2007, but only mentions "genocide", not "cultural genocide", although the article is otherwise unchanged.

==Examples of the term's usage==
The term was used for describing destruction of [[cultural heritage]] in connection with various events:

* In reference to the [[Axis powers]] (primarily, [[Nazi Germany]]) policies towards some nations in World War II (ex. [[Polish culture during World War II|destruction of Polish culture]])&lt;ref&gt;William Schabas, ''Genocide in international law: the crimes of crimes'', Cambridge University Press, 2000, ISBN 0521787904, [http://books.google.com/books?id=pYptuRHDQPgC&amp;pg=PA179&amp;dq=%22Cultural+genocide%22+Poand Google Print, p.179]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In 2007, a Canadian Member of Parliament criticized the Ministry of Indian Affairs' destruction of documents regarding the treatment of First Nations members as "cultural genocide."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.edmontonsun.com/News/Canada/2007/04/25/4127962-sun.html Jorge Barrera , ''‘Genocide’ target of fed coverup: MP'', Edmonton Sun, April 25, 2007.]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The [[Khachkar destruction in Nakhchivan|destruction by Azerbaijan]] of thousands of medieval Armenian gravestones at a cemetery in [[Julfa, Azerbaijan (city)|Julfa]], and Azerbaijan's subsequent denial that the site had ever existed, has been widely written about as being an example of cultural genocide.&lt;ref&gt;History Today, November 2007, "Sacred Stones Silenced in Azerbaijan"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Switzerland-Armenia Parliamentary Group, "The Destruction of Jugha", Bern, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

* Japan's suppression of the [[Korean language]], traditions, and names, and the teaching of [[Korean history]] during the [[Korea under Japanese rule|Japanese occupation of Korea]] from 1910 to 1945 has been mentioned as a case in point of cultural genocide, although some Japanese scholars have discussed more narrowly ascribing the term.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cgs.c.u-tokyo.ac.jp/workshops_e/w_2004_02_23_e.html CGS 1st Workshop: “Cultural Genocide” and the Japanese Occupation of Korea&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In 1989, [[Robert Badinter]], a French criminal lawyer known for his stance against the [[death penalty]], used the term "cultural genocide" on a television show to describe what he said was the disappearance of [[Tibetan culture]] in the presence of the [[14th Dalai Lama]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ina.fr/archivespourtous/index.php?vue=notice&amp;from=fulltext&amp;full=Salonique&amp;num_notice=5&amp;total_notices=8 Les droits de l'homme Apostrophes, A2 - 21 April 1989 - 01h25m56s], Web site of the [[Institut national de l'audiovisuel|INA]]&lt;/ref&gt; The Dalai Lama would later use the term himself in 1993&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dalailama.com/page.104.htm 10th March Archive]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[2008 Tibetan unrest|in 2008]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/7299212.stm BBC NEWS | World | Asia-Pacific | 'Eighty killed' in Tibetan unrest&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Genocide}}
* [[Cultural imperialism]]
* [[Linguicide]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Indigenous rights footer}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cultural Genocide}}
[[Category:Genocide]]
[[Category:Human rights by issue]]

[[ar:إبادة ثقافية]]
[[ca:Genocidi cultural]]
[[el:Πολιτισμική Γενοκτονία]]
[[fr:Génocide culturel]]
[[it:Genocidio culturale]]
[[pt:Genocídio cultural]]
[[ro:Genocid cultural]]
[[ru:Культурный геноцид]]
[[sv:Kulturellt folkmord]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>