<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241122070427|1258899644" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="55084" pageid="55084" ns="0" title="Cultural genocide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-27T16:09:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Type of genocide}}
{{Use British English|date=June 2023}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2023}}
[[File:Warsaw 1944 by Bałuk - 26320.jpg|thumb|[[Looting of Poland in World War II|Looting of Polish artwork]] at the [[Zachęta National Gallery of Art|Zachęta building]] by German forces during the [[Occupation of Poland (1939–1945)|Occupation of Poland]], [[1944]]]]
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
{{Genocide}}
'''Cultural genocide''' or '''culturicide''' is a concept described by Polish lawyer [[Raphael Lemkin]] in 1944, in the same book that coined the term ''[[genocide]]''.&lt;ref name="Bilsky2018"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Bilsky |first1=Leora |last2=Klagsbrun |first2=Rachel |title=The Return of Cultural Genocide? |journal=[[European Journal of International Law]] |date=23 July 2018 |volume=29 |issue=2 |pages=373–396 |doi=10.1093/ejil/chy025 |url=https://academic.oup.com/ejil/article/29/2/373/5057075 |access-date=2 May 2020 |language=en |issn=0938-5428 |doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; The destruction of culture was a central component in Lemkin's formulation of genocide.&lt;ref name="Bilsky2018"/&gt; Though the precise definition of ''cultural genocide'' remains contested, the [[United Nations]] does not include it in the definition of ''genocide'' used in the 1948 [[Genocide Convention]].&lt;ref name="UN2021"&gt;{{Cite web |last=United Nations Office on Genocide Prevention and the Responsibility to Protect |title=The Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide (1948) |url=https://www.un.org/en/genocideprevention/documents/Genocide%20Convention-FactSheet-ENG.pdf |website=[[United Nations]] |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210618180113/https://www.un.org/en/genocideprevention/documents/Genocide%20Convention-FactSheet-ENG.pdf |archive-date=18 June 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Tsitsernakaberd|Armenian Genocide Museum]] defines culturicide as "acts and measures undertaken to destroy [[nation]]s' or [[Ethnicity|ethnic group]]s' [[culture]] through spiritual, national, and cultural destruction",&lt;ref name="genocide-museum.am"&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.genocide-museum.am/eng/cultural_genocide.php |title=Cultural genocide |website=The Armenian genocide Museum-institute |access-date=10 October 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20240822220550/http://www.genocide-museum.am/eng/cultural_genocide.php |archive-date=22 August 2024}}&lt;/ref&gt; which appears to be essentially the same as [[ethnocide]]. Some [[Ethnology|ethnologists]], such as [[Robert Jaulin]], use the term ''[[ethnocide]]'' as a substitute for ''cultural genocide'',&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite book |title=La paix blanche: introduction à l'ethnocide |trans-title=White Peace: An Introduction to Ethnocide |first=Robert |last=Jaulin |author-link=Robert Jaulin |publisher=Éditions du Seuil |year=1970 |language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; although this usage has been criticized as risking the confusion between [[ethnicity]] and culture.&lt;ref name="DelantyKumar2006" /&gt; Cultural genocide and ethnocide have in the past been utilized in distinct contexts.&lt;ref name="BloxhamMoses2010"&gt;{{cite book |first1=Donald |last1=Bloxham |author1-link=Donald Bloxham |first2=A. Dirk |last2=Moses |author2-link=A. Dirk Moses |title=The Oxford Handbook of Genocide Studies |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xCHMFHQRNtYC&amp;pg=PR2-IA92 |access-date=28 February 2013 |date=15 April 2010 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |isbn=978-0-19-161361-6 |pages=2– |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140630192728/http://books.google.com/books?id=xCHMFHQRNtYC&amp;pg=PR2-IA92 |archive-date=30 June 2014 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cultural genocide without ethnocide is conceivable when a distinct ethnic identity is kept, but distinct cultural elements are eliminated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=https://jwsr.pitt.edu/ojs/jwsr/article/view/307/319 |last1=Hall |first1=Thomas D. |last2=Fenelon |first2=James V. |title=The futures of indigenous peoples: 9-11 and the trajectory of indigenous survival and resistance |journal=Journal of World-systems Research |date=2004 |pages=153–197 |doi=10.5195/jwsr.2004.307 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Culturicide involves the eradication and destruction of [[cultural artifact]]s, such as books, artworks, and structures.&lt;ref name="FH2019"&gt;{{cite web |title=Cultural Genocide, Stolen Lives: The Indigenous Peoples of Canada and the Indian Residential Schools |url=https://www.facinghistory.org/stolen-lives-indigenous-peoples-canada-and-indian-residential-schools/chapter-7/cultural-genocide |website=Facing History and Ourselves |date=16 October 2019 |access-date=3 December 2019 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The issue is addressed in multiple international treaties, including the [[Geneva Conventions]] and the [[Rome Statute]], which define [[war crime]]s associated with the destruction of culture. Cultural genocide may also involve [[forced assimilation]], as well as the suppression of a language or cultural activities that do not conform to the destroyer's notion of what is appropriate.&lt;ref name="FH2019"/&gt; Among many other potential reasons, cultural genocide may be committed for religious motives (e.g., [[iconoclasm]] which is based on [[aniconism]]); as part of a campaign of [[ethnic cleansing]] in an attempt to remove the evidence of a people from a specific locale or history; as part of an effort to implement a [[Year Zero (political notion)|Year Zero]], in which the past and its associated culture is deleted and history is "reset". The drafters of the 1948 [[Genocide Convention]] initially considered using the term, but later dropped it from inclusion.&lt;ref name="AbtahiWebb2008"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Davidson2012"/&gt;&lt;ref name="AutoCK-2"/&gt; The term "cultural genocide" has been considered in various draft United Nations declarations, but it is not used by the UN Genocide Convention.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== History ==

=== Etymology ===
The notion of 'cultural genocide' was acknowledged as early as 1944, when lawyer [[Raphael Lemkin]] distinguished a cultural component of genocide.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-1"/&gt; In 1989, [[Robert Badinter]], a French criminal lawyer known for his stance against the death penalty, used the term "cultural genocide" on a television show to describe what he said was the disappearance of [[Tibetan culture]] in the presence of the [[14th Dalai Lama]].&lt;ref name="AutoCK-10"/&gt; The Dalai Lama would later use the term in 1993&lt;ref name="AutoCK-11"/&gt; and again [[2008 Tibetan unrest|in 2008]].&lt;ref name="AutoCK-12"/&gt;

===United Nations proposals===
{{see also | United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples }}

The concept of cultural genocide was originally included in drafts of the 1948 [[Genocide Convention]].&lt;ref name="AbtahiWebb2008" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Davidson2012" /&gt;&lt;ref name="AutoCK-2" /&gt; Genocide was defined as the destruction of a group's language, religion, or culture through one of several methods. This definition of genocide was rejected by the drafting committee by a vote of 25 to 16, with 4 abstentions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Flores |first=Marcello |chapter=Introduction |date=2023-12-05 |title=Monuments and Identities in the Caucasus |pages=1–11 |url=https://brill.com/display/book/9789004677388/BP000001.xml |access-date=19 March 2024 |publisher=[[Brill Publishers|Brill]] |language=en |doi=10.1163/9789004677388_002 |isbn=978-90-04-67738-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Article 7 of a 1994 draft of the [[United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples]] (DRIP) uses the phrase "cultural genocide" but does not define what it means.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-4"/&gt; The complete article in the draft read as follows:
:Indigenous peoples have the collective and individual right not to be subjected to [[ethnocide]] and cultural genocide, including prevention of and redress for:
::(a) Any action which has the aim or effect of depriving them of their integrity as distinct peoples, or of their cultural values or ethnic identities;
::(b) Any action which has the aim or effect of dispossessing them of their lands, territories or resources;
::(c) Any form of [[population transfer]] which has the aim or effect of violating or undermining any of their rights;
::(d) Any form of [[acculturation|assimilation or integration]] by other cultures or ways of life imposed on them by legislative, administrative or other measures;
::(e) Any form of propaganda directed against them.

This wording only ever appeared in a draft. The DRIP—which was adopted by the [[United Nations General Assembly]] during its 62nd session at [[UN Headquarters]] in New York City on 13 September 2007—only makes reference to genocide once, when it mentions "genocide, or any other act of violence" in Article 7. Though the concept of "ethnocide" and "cultural genocide" was removed in the version adopted by the General Assembly, the sub-points from the draft noted above were retained (with slightly expanded wording) in Article 8 that speaks to "the right not to be subject to forced assimilation."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.un.org/development/desa/indigenouspeoples/wp-content/uploads/sites/19/2018/11/UNDRIP_E_web.pdf |title=United Nations Declaration on Rights of Indigenous Peoples |publisher=[[United Nations]] |page=10 |date=13 September 2007 |access-date=9 June 2015 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Relation to genocide ==

The [[United Nations]] does not include cultural genocide in the definition of ''genocide'' used in the 1948 [[Genocide Convention]]:
{{blockquote| The definition contained in Article II of the Convention describes genocide as a crime committed with the intent to destroy a national, ethnic, racial or religious group, in whole or in part. It does not include political groups or so called "cultural genocide". This definition was the result of a negotiating process and reflects the compromise reached among United Nations Member States while drafting the Convention in 1948...To constitute genocide, there must be a proven intent on the part of perpetrators to physically destroy [the] group. Cultural destruction does not suffice, nor does an intention to simply disperse a group, though this may constitute a [[crime against humanity]] as set out in the Rome Statute. It is this special intent, or ''dolus specialis'', that makes the crime of genocide so unique.&lt;ref name="UN2021"/&gt;}}

While not qualifying as genocide under the Convention, the issue is addressed in multiple international treaties, including the [[Geneva Conventions]] and the [[Rome Statute]], which define [[war crime]]s associated with the destruction of culture.

== List of cultural genocides ==
The term has been used to describe the destruction of [[cultural heritage]] in connection with various events which mostly occurred during the 20th century:

=== Europe ===
* Historian Stephen Wheatcroft states that the Soviet peasantry was subject to cultural destruction during the creation of the "[[New Soviet man]]",&lt;ref name=wheatcroft&gt;The Complexity of the Kazakh Famine: Food Problems and Faulty Perceptions Stephen G. Wheatcroft&lt;/ref&gt; Lynne Viola makes a similar characterization of [[Collectivization in the Soviet Union]] adding a noted colonial character to the project in their observation of the event.&lt;ref name="collectivizationstruggle"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Viola |first1=Lynne |title=The Collectivization of Agriculture in Communist Eastern Europe:Comparison and Entanglements |date=2014 |publisher=[[Central European University Press]] |isbn=978-963-386-048-9 |chapter=Collectivization in the Soviet Union: Specificities and Modalities |pages=49–69}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* During the [[Deportation of the Chechens and Ingush|genocide of the Chechens and Ingush]] in 1944, Soviet forces destroyed almost every piece of Chechen and Ingush language literature in existence, and damaged or destroyed many Chechen and Ingush cultural sites and artifacts, including [[Ingush towers|towers in the highlands]] that had been built to resist [[Mongol invasions of Durdzuketi|Mongol invasions in the 13th century]]. Chechens and Ingush gravestones were destroyed, and when the Chechens and Ingush were allowed to return to their homes a decade later, they were forbidden from settling in their ancestral mountain lands.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=29 April 2019 |title=The Massive Deportation of the Chechen People: How and why Chechens were Deported {{!}} Sciences Po Violence de masse et Résistance - Réseau de recherche |url=https://www.sciencespo.fr/mass-violence-war-massacre-resistance/fr/document/massive-deportation-chechen-people-how-and-why-chechens-were-deported.html |access-date=22 August 2024 |website=[[SciencesPo]] |language=fr |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=WAOP |date=14 April 2023 |title=Deportation of Chechens and Ingush in 1944. |url=https://deportation.org.ua/deportation-of-chechens-and-ingush-in-1944/ |access-date=22 August 2024 |website=WAOP? |language=en-US |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last1=Sultanov |first1=Akhmed |last2=Yelkhoyev |first2=Lecha |last3=Bigg |first3=Claire |date=22 February 2014 |title='There Was No Water, No Food' -- Chechens Remember Horror Of 1944 Deportations |url=https://www.rferl.org/a/chechen-deportation-1944-survivors/25273614.html |access-date=22 August 2024 |work=[[Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty]] |language=en |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* In reference to the [[Axis powers]] (primarily, [[Nazi Germany]])'s policies towards some nations during [[World War II]] (ex. the [[History of Poland (1939–1945)|German occupation of Poland]] &amp; [[Polish culture during World War II|the destruction of Polish culture]]).&lt;ref name="AutoCK-5"/&gt;&lt;ref name="AutoCK-9"/&gt;
* In the [[Bosnian War]] during the [[Siege of Sarajevo]], cultural genocide was committed by Bosnian Serb forces. The [[National and University Library of Bosnia and Herzegovina]] was specifically targeted and besieged by cannons positioned all around the city. The National Library was completely destroyed in the fire, along with 80 per cent of its contents. Some 3 million books were destroyed, along with hundreds of original documents from the [[Ottoman Empire]] and the [[Austria-Hungary|Austro-Hungarian monarchy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |work=[[Deutsche Welle]] |title=Burned library symbolizes multiethnic Sarajevo |date=25 August 2012 |url=https://www.dw.com/en/burned-library-symbolizes-multiethnic-sarajevo/a-16192965 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[2004 unrest in Kosovo#Destroyed churches|2004 unrest in Kosovo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=J̌овић |first=Саво Б. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=q6YRAQAAIAAJ|title=Етничко чишћење и културни геноцид на Косову и Метохији: Сведочанства о страдању Српске православне цркве и српског народа од 1945. до 2005. год |date=2007 |publisher=Информативно-издавачка установа Српске православне цркве |isbn=978-86-7758-016-2 |language=sr}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an urgent appeal,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://spc.rs/eng/appeal_extraordinary_session_expanded_convocation_holy_synod_bishops |title=Appeal from the extraordinary session of the Expanded Convocation of the Holy Synod of Serbian Orthodox Church |access-date=20 May 2020 |archive-date=19 February 2022 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220219163501/http://spc.rs/eng/appeal_extraordinary_session_expanded_convocation_holy_synod_bishops}}&lt;/ref&gt; issued on 18 March by the extraordinary session of the Expanded Convocation of the [[Holy Synod of the Serbian Orthodox Church|Holy Synod of Serbian Orthodox Church]] ({{abbr|SPC|Serbian Orthodox Church}}), it was reported that a number of Serbian churches and shrines in Kosovo had been damaged or destroyed by Albanian rioters. At least 30 sites were completely destroyed, more or less destroyed, or further destroyed (sites that had been previously damaged).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=ERP KiM Info |title=Dopunjeni i ispravljeni spisak uništenih i oštećenih pravoslavnih crkava i manastira na Kosovu u toku martovskog nasilja |language=bs |trans-title=Completed and corrected list of destroyed and damaged Orthodox churches and monasteries in Kosovo during the March violence |work=B92 Specijal |date=26 April 2004 |publisher=B92 |url=http://www.b92.net/specijal/kosovo2004/unistenecrkve.php |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*After the [[Greek Civil War]], Greek authorities had conducted a cultural genocide upon [[Macedonians (ethnic group)|Slavic Macedonians]] in Northern Greece through prohibition of communication in [[Slavic languages]], renaming of cities, towns and villages ([[Lerin]]/Лерин to [[Florina]] etc.), deportation of Slavic Macedonians, particularly women and children, as well as many other actions intended to marginalize and oppress the Slavic Macedonians residing in Northern Greece. While some of these actions had been motivated by political ideology, as many of the Slavic Macedonians had sided with the defeated communists, the majority of actions were committed to wipe out any traces of Slavic Macedonians or their culture in Northern Greece.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |date=1 May 1994 |title=Denying Ethnic Identity |url=https://www.hrw.org/report/1994/05/01/macedonians-greece |access-date=10 May 2021 |website=[[Human Rights Watch]] |language=en |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |date=24 February 2019 |title=Greece's invisible minority – the Macedonian Slavs |language=en-GB |work=[[BBC News]] |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/stories-47258809 |access-date=10 May 2021 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Turkey: Especially in the island of [[Imbros]]. The island was primarily inhabited by ethnic Greeks from antiquity until approximately the 1960s, when many were forced to flee due to a campaign of cultural genocide and discrimination enacted by the Turkish government.&lt;ref name="Alexandris"&gt;Alexis Alexandris, "The Identity Issue of The Minorities in Greece And Turkey", in Hirschon, Renée (ed.), ''Crossing the Aegean: An Appraisal of the 1923 Compulsory Population Exchange Between Greece and Turkey'', Berghahn Books, 2003, [https://books.google.com/books?id=8jJTge-_444C&amp;pg=PA120 p. 120]&lt;/ref&gt; Massive scale persecution against the local Greeks started in 1961, as part of the ''Eritme Programmi'' operation that aimed at the elimination of Greek education and the enforcement of economic, psychological pressure and violence. Under these conditions, the Turkish government approved the appropriation of &gt;90% of the cultivated areas of the island and the settlement of additional 6,000 ethnic Turks from mainland Turkey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Limpitsioúni |first=Anthí G. |script-title=el:Το πλέγμα των ελληνοτουρκικών σχέσεων και η ελληνική μειονότητα στην Τουρκία, οι Έλληνες της Κωνσταντινούπολης της Ίμβρου και της Τενέδου |language=el |title=To plégma ton ellinotourkikón schéseon kai i ellinikí meionótita stin Tourkía, oi Éllines tis Konstantinoúpolis tis Ímvrou kai tis Tenédou |trans-title=The nexus of Greek-Turkish relations and the Greek minority in Turkey, the Greeks of Constantinople, Imbros and Tenedos |publisher=Αριστοτέλειο Πανεπιστήμιο Θεσσαλονίκης |pages=98–99}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ashgate Studies in Pilgrimage"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Eade |first1=John |last2=Katic |first2=Mario |title=Ashgate Studies in Pilgrimage |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gBqrBAAAQBAJ&amp;q=imvros%2Bdiscrimination&amp;pg=PA37 |publisher=[[Ashgate Publishing]] |date=28 June 2014 |page=38 |isbn=978-1-4724-1592-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, the island was also officially renamed by Turkey in 1970 to ''Gökçeada'' to finalize the removal of any remaining Greek influence. 
*[[Francoist Spain]]: the alleged prohibition of the use of minority languages such as Catalan or [[Galician language|Galician]] in the public space, from schools to shops, public transport, or even in the streets, the banning of the use of Catalan or Galician birth names for children, the renaming of cities, streets and all toponyms from Catalan, Basque or Galician to [[Castilian Spanish|Castilian]]-Spanish, and the abolition of government and all cultural institutions in [[Catalonia]] as well as in [[Basque Country (greater region)|Basque Country]] and [[Galicia (Spain)|Galicia]] with the goal of total cultural suppression and [[Cultural assimilation|assimilation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Catalunya sota el règim franquista |language=ca |trans-title=Catalonia under the Franco regime |last=Benet |first=Josep |date=1978 |publisher=Blume |isbn=84-7031-064-X |edition=1. reedició |location=Barcelona |oclc=4777662}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
** [[John D. Hargreaves]] writes that "A policy of cultural genocide was implemented: the Catalan language and key symbols of Catalan independent identity and nationhood, such as the flag (the [[senyera]]), the national hymn ('[[Els Segadors]]') and the national dance (the [[sardana]]), were proscribed. Any sign of independence or opposition, in fact, was brutally suppressed. Catalan identity and consequently the Catalan nation were threatened with extinction."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Freedom for Catalonia?: Catalan nationalism, Spanish identity, and the Barcelona Olympic Games |last=Hargreaves |first=John E. |author-link=John D. Hargreaves |date=2000 |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-58615-3|location=Cambridge |oclc=51028883}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
** Although [[Josep Pla]] and other Catalan authors published books in Catalan in the 1950s, and even there were prizes of Catalan Literature during Francoism like the [[Premi Sant Jordi de novel·la]], editorial production in Catalan never recovered the peak levels it had reached before Spanish Civil War&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Benet |first=Josep |title=Cataluña bajo el régimen franquista |language=ca |trans-title=Catalonia under the Franco regime |date=1979 |publisher=Blume |isbn=84-7031-144-1 |edition=1. |location=Barcelona |oclc=7188603}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.gremieditors.cat/historia-de-ledicio-a-catalunya/ |title=Història de l'edició a Catalunya |date=27 September 2017 |language=ca |trans-title=History of publishing in Catalonia |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A prominent case of popularization of Catalan was [[Serrat|Joan Manuel Serrat]]: although he could compose Catalan songs and gained certain notoriety, he was not allowed to sing in Catalan in the Eurovision contest its [[La La La (Massiel song)|La, la, la]]. theme, and was replaced by Spanish singer [[Massiel]], who won the [[Eurovision Song Contest|Eurovision]] contest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Vatmanidis |first1=Theo |title=Catalonia crisis in Eurovision – how Spain blocked Catalan from victory |url=https://eurovisionary.com/catalonia-crisis-eurovision-spain-blocked-catalan-victory/ |website=EuroVisionary |access-date=8 December 2023 |date=8 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Overall, despite some tolerance as Franco's regime relaxed in the late 60s and early 70s, Catalan and the rest of minority languages of Spain were strictly banned from higher education, administration and all official endeavors, thus being in practice confined to the private sphere and domestic uses (see [[Language policies of Francoist Spain]]).
* During the 19th and early 20th centuries, some [[Education in Wales|schools in Wales]] adopted the [[Welsh Not]] policy to discourage students from speaking [[Welsh language|Welsh]] instead of English. Under this [[Language immersion#Types of learners|total immersion]] policy, students caught speaking Welsh were punished, most typically by having a lump of wood with the letters "WN" placed around their neck. Though the policy enjoyed widespread support among parents and the general public in Wales, some [[Welsh nationalism|Welsh nationalists]] have described it as an example of cultural genocide. Academic Martin Johnes noted that despite the Welsh Not not being an official state policy, instead coming down to actions taken by individual teachers, it nonetheless remains "a powerful symbol of the oppression of Welsh culture."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first1=Martin|last1=Johnes|title=History and the Making and Remaking of Wales|url=https://cronfa.swansea.ac.uk/Record/cronfa21049/Download/0021049-11052017134425.pdf|journal=History|date=2015|issn=1468-229X|pages=667–684|volume=100|issue=343|doi=10.1111/1468-229X.12141|access-date=5 November 2024|archive-date=26 March 2022|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220326202256/https://cronfa.swansea.ac.uk/Record/cronfa21049/Download/0021049-11052017134425.pdf|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[File:Irishin1871.jpg|thumb|Map showing the distribution of the Irish language in [[1871]]]] Numerous academics have argued [[Ireland]] was subject to cultural genocide under [[British rule in Ireland|British rule]], specifically focusing on attempts to suppress the [[Irish language]], the [[culture of Ireland]] and the [[Catholic Church in Ireland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.irishtimes.com/culture/books/cultural-genocide-the-broken-harp-identity-and-language-in-modern-ireland-by-tom%C3%A1s-mac-s%C3%ADom%C3%B3in-1.2299891 |title=Cultural genocide: The Broken Harp, Identity and Language in Modern Ireland, by Tomás Mac Síomóin |newspaper=[[The Irish Times]] |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.opendemocracy.net/en/opendemocracyuk/guardian-view-on-cultural-genocide/ |title=The Guardian view on{{nbsp}}... cultural genocide |website=[[openDemocracy]] |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Academics [[Paul Bartrop]], [[Tomás Mac Síomóin]] and Christopher Murray claimed that attempts to suppress the [[Irish language]] by the [[Dublin Castle administration]] amounted to a cultural genocide, and scholar [[Hilary Carey]] argued that the [[penal transportation]] of [[Convicts in Australia|Irish convicts to Australia]] was also a cultural genocide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JGUUpRAP4CoC&amp;pg=PA42 |title=Twentieth-Century Irish Drama: Mirror Up to Nation |first=Christopher |last=Murray |date=6 June 2019 |publisher=[[Syracuse University Press]] |via=Google Books|isbn=978-0-8156-0643-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WUJaBAAAQBAJ&amp;q=%22Cultural+genocide%22+ireland&amp;pg=PT29 |title=Believing in Australia: A cultural history of religions |first=Hilary M. |last=Carey |date=1 July 1996 |publisher=[[Allen &amp; Unwin]] |via=Google Books |isbn=978-1-74269-657-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Totten |first1=Samuel |author1-link=Samuel Totten |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rgGA91skoP4C&amp;pg=PA91 |title=Dictionary of Genocide |last2=Bartrop |first2=Paul Robert |author2-link=Paul Bartrop |last3=Jacobs |first3=Steven L. |date=6 June 2019 |publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]] |isbn=978-0-313-34642-2 |via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*France's [[Language policy in France|policies]] (also known as ''[[Vergonha]]'', "shame," in [[Occitan language|Occitan]]) towards its various [[Languages of France|regional and minority languages]], referring to non-standard French as [[patois]], have been described as genocide by professor of Catalan [[philology]] at the [[University of the Balearic Islands]] [[:ca:Jaume Corbera i Pou|Jaume Corbera i Pou]] who argues,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Corbera |first1=Jaume |title=Le patois des vieux |url=https://www.dbalears.cat/opinio/opinio/2001/09/23/63269/le-patois-des-vieux.html |access-date=14 December 2021 |agency=Diari de Balears |date=23 September 2001 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
When at the mid-19th century, primary school is made compulsory all across the State, it is also made clear that only French will be taught, and the teachers will severely punish any pupil speaking in ''patois''. The aim of the French educational system will consequently not be to dignify the pupils' natural humanity, developing their culture and teaching them to write their language, but rather to humiliate them and morally degrade them for the simple fact of being what tradition and their nature made them. The self-proclaimed country of the "human rights" will then ignore one of man's most fundamental rights, the right to be himself and speak the language of his nation. And with that attitude France, the "grande France" that calls itself the champion of liberty, will pass the 20th century, indifferent to the timid protest movements of the various linguistic communities it submitted and the literary prestige they may have given birth to.

[...]

France, that under [[Francisco Franco|Franco]]'s reign was seen here [in [[Catalonia]]] as the safe haven of freedom, has the miserable honour of being the [only] State of Europe—and probably the world – that succeeded best in the diabolical task of destroying its own ethnic and linguistic patrimony and moreover, of destroying human family bonds: many parents and children, or grandparents and grandchildren, have different languages, and the latter feel ashamed of the first because they speak a despicable ''patois'', and no element of the grandparents' culture has been transmitted to the younger generation, as if they were born out of a completely new world. This is the French State that has just entered the 21st century, a country where stone monuments and natural landscapes are preserved and respected, but where many centuries of popular creation expressed in different tongues are on the brink of extinction. The "gloire" and the "grandeur" built on a genocide. [[liberté, égalité, fraternité|No liberty, no equality, no fraternity]]: just cultural extermination, this is the real motto of the French Republic.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

* [[Ukraine]]. As of February 29, 2024, according to the published data of the [[Prime Minister of Ukraine]], Denys Shmyhal, about 900 objects of national heritage were damaged or destroyed in the occupied zones of Ukraine, and more than 20 thousand [[cultural monuments]] are under occupation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2024-02-29 |title=Шмигаль: Понад 20 тисяч пам'яток культури перебуває під російською окупацією |url=https://www.ukrinform.ua/rubric-culture/3833912-smigal-ponad-20-tisac-pamatok-kulturi-perebuvae-pid-rosijskou-okupacieu.html |access-date=2024-03-28 |website=www.ukrinform.ua |language=uk}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Cultural Genocide Against Ukraine: How is Russia Looting Ukrainian Museums? |url=https://ukraineworld.org/en/videos/cultural-genocide |access-date=2024-03-28 |website=ukraineworld.org |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=5 March 2024 |title="United for Justice. United for Heritage": Preserving Ukrainian Cultural Identity — EUAM Ukraine |url=https://www.euam-ukraine.eu/news/united-for-justice-united-for-heritage-preserving-ukrainian-cultural-identity/ |access-date=28 March 2024 |language=en-GB |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Asia===
* The [[persecution of Baháʼís]] in Iran as a case of [[religious persecution]] has been called a cultural genocide.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-13" /&gt;&lt;ref name="AutoCK-14" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Frelick |first=Bill |title=Iranian Baha'is and Genocide Early Warning |journal=Social Science Record |volume=24 |issue=2 |pages=35–37 |date=Fall 1987 |url=http://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ362917 |access-date=3 March 2013 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Azerbaijan's destruction, appropriation, and [[Falsification of history in Azerbaijan|denial of Armenian heritage]] sites in [[Nakhchivan Autonomous Republic|Nakhchivan]] and [[Nagorno-Karabakh]] have been characterized as ethnocide&lt;ref&gt;Petrosyan 2010 – Petrosyan H., Cultural ethnocide in Artsakh (mechanism of extortion of cultural heritage), state terrorism of Azerbaijan and the policy of ethnic cleansing against Nagorno Karabakh, Shushi, pp. 137-148 (in Arm.). Petrosyan 2020 – Ethnocide in Artsakh: The Mechanisms of Azerbaijan’s Usurpation of Indigenous Armenian Cultural Heritage, Cultural Heritage. Experiences &amp; Perspectives in International Context, Proceedings of the ROCHEMP center international conference, 23rd- 24th of January 2020, Yerevan, pp. 79-90.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Roberts |first=Kasey |date=6 June 2022 |title=Present-Day Ethnocide: The Destruction of Armenian Cultural Heritage in Azerbaijan |url=https://tuljournals.temple.edu/index.php/mundi/article/view/586 |journal=MUNDI |language=en |volume=2 |issue=1 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; or potential cultural genocide&lt;ref&gt;Kellogg, Ethan. [https://scholar.google.com/scholar_url?url=https://journals.library.cornell.edu/index.php/tcd/article/download/724/681&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=T&amp;oi=gsb-gga&amp;ct=res&amp;cd=0&amp;d=2144530705259449779&amp;ei=88qyZYHqDOSo6rQPktWn0Ao&amp;scisig=AFWwaeYLWt8sD_H-nTQ1Yhwu_3uu "Cultural Erasure in the Modern Day: The Destruction of Armenian Heritage Sites in Azerbaijan."] ''The Cornell Diplomat'' 9 (2023). This wide-spread destruction has taken place since at least the late 1990s, primarily in Nagorno-Karabakh and the Azerbaijani exclave of Nakhchivan, eliminating millennia of artifacts and altering the ethnic and cultural makeup of the region in a manner that may constitute cultural genocide.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Der Matossian |first=Bedross |date=2023-08-01 |title=Impunity, Lack of Humanitarian Intervention, and International Apathy: The Blockade of the Lachin Corridor in Historical Perspective |url=https://utpjournals.press/doi/10.3138/GSI-2023-0008 |journal=[[Genocide Studies International]] |language=en |volume=15 |issue=1 |pages=7–20 |doi=10.3138/GSI-2023-0008 |issn=2291-1847 |quote=There is no doubt that a cultural genocide is taking place in Artsakh where the vandalism or destruction of Armenian monuments has become the norm. |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Falcone |first=Daniel |date=6 January 2024 |title=Armenians Suffering in Nagorno-Karabakh Are Going Largely Ignored in US Media |url=https://truthout.org/articles/armenians-suffering-in-nagorno-karabakh-are-going-largely-ignored-in-us-media/ |access-date=20 February 2024 |website=[[Truthout]] |language=en-US |quote=In this under-reported case of cultural genocide involving political persecution, strains on due process rights, torture, lack of healthcare and food supplies, tens of thousands of ethnic Armenians have fled from Nagorno-Karabakh region after surrendering to Azerbaijan on September 20. |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and condemned by the [[International Court of Justice]] and [[European Parliament]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Texts adopted - Destruction of cultural heritage in Nagorno-Karabakh - Thursday, 10 March 2022 |url=https://www.europarl.europa.eu/doceo/document/TA-9-2022-0080_EN.html |access-date=29 January 2024 |website=www.europarl.europa.eu |language=en |quote=The European Parliament{{nbsp}}... calls on Azerbaijan to fully implement the provisional decision of the ICJ, in particular by 'refraining from suppressing the Armenian language, destroying Armenian cultural heritage or otherwise eliminating the existence of the historical Armenian cultural presence or inhibiting Armenians’ access and enjoyment thereof' and by 'restoring or returning any Armenian cultural and religious buildings and sites, artefacts or objects'; |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The destruction of thousands of medieval Armenian Churches, [[khachkars]] and gravestones at [[Armenian cemetery in Julfa|the Armenian cemetery]] in [[Julfa, Azerbaijan (city)|Julfa]] is a prominent example.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-7"/&gt;&lt;ref name="AutoCK-8" /&gt;&lt;ref name="LA Times"&gt;{{cite news |last=Womack |first=Catherine |date=7 November 2019 |title=Historic Armenian monuments were obliterated. Some call it 'cultural genocide' |url=https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2019-11-07/armenian-monuments-azerbaijan |newspaper=[[LA Times]] |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Turkey's destruction of [[Armenian cultural heritage in Turkey]] both during as well as in the decades after the [[Armenian genocide]].&lt;ref name="genocide-museum.am" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine |date=12 October 2023 |title=The Cultural Genocide Against Armenians |url=https://time.com/6322574/cultural-genocide-armenia-nagorno-karabakh-essay/ |access-date=6 February 2024 |magazine=[[Time (magazine)|TIME]] |language=en |quote=This is how cultural genocide plays out. A little more than 100 years ago was the Armenian Genocide waged by the Ottoman Empire, followed by largescale looting, vandalization, and destruction of Armenian sites across what is now modern-day Turkey. The prospect of a second cultural genocide is now on the table. Except now, Armenians will watch the spectacle unfold online, enduring the trauma site by site and monument by monument. |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Historian Sarah Cameron believes that while the [[Kazakh famine of 1931–1933]] combined with a campaign against nomads was not genocide in the sense of the Genocide Convention's definition, it complies with Raphael Lemkin's original concept of genocide, which considered destruction of culture to be as genocidal as physical annihilation.&lt;ref name="wheatcroft" /&gt; 
* [[Korea under Japanese rule|Japanese occupation of Korea]]. Japan's extensive policy of cultural genocide included [[Sōshi-kaimei|forcibly changing Korean names to Japanese names]], the exclusive use of the Japanese language, school instruction in the Japanese "ethical system", and [[Shinto]] worship.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-9" /&gt;
* The [[Sinicization of Tibet]] from the 1950s onwards. Following the [[1959 Tibetan uprising]], 97% of Tibet's monasteries were destroyed, while 2 million Tibetans, including 500,000 nomadic farmers, were relocated to newly created urban centers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Sandhar |first=Jaspreet |title=Cultural Genocide in Tibet: The Failure of Article 8 of the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples in Protecting the Cultural Rights of Tibetans |journal=Santander Art and Cultural Law Review |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=175–198 |date=2005 |url=https://www.ejournals.eu/SAACLR/2015/2(2015)/art/6788/ |access-date=3 March 2013 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Japanese [[Dialect card|ban and discrimination]] which the [[Ainu people|Ainu]] and [[Ryukyuan people|Ryukyuan]] cultures have been subjected to as well as other regional cultures.
* The [[Four Olds|"Destruction of the Four Olds"]] in the People's Republic of China during the [[Cultural Revolution]], in which [[Red Guards]] destroyed various religious, cultural, and historical sites throughout the country, especially in Beijing as well as in the [[Temple of Confucius, Qufu|Temple of Confucius]] in Shandong.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=MacFarquhar |first1=Roderick |last2=Schoenhals |first2=Michael |title=Mao's Last Revolution |publisher=[[Harvard University Press]] |year=2006 |isbn=978-0-674-02332-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Democratic Kampuchea]] (1975–1979), particularly its policies towards both the [[Kingdom of Cambodia (1953–1970)]] and the [[Khmer Republic|Khmer Republic (1970–1975)]].
*The newly-reunified [[Vietnam]] after the [[Fall of Saigon|end]] of the [[Vietnam War]], particularly its policies towards [[South Vietnam]].
*The persecution of [[Sri Lankan Tamils]] during the [[Sri Lankan civil war|Sri Lankan Civil War]] was a campaign of [[ethnic cleansing]] which was sponsored by the government and it has continued until the present day as a part of the Sinhalaisation of the northern and eastern parts of the island.
*The [[Islamic State|Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]]'s [[Forced conversion|forcible conversions]] in its territory as well as its destruction of ancient [[Assyria]]n, [[Rome|Roman]], [[Yazidi]] and Christian heritage sites and museums.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Cultural Genocide Funds ISIS Art-for-Weapons Trade |url=https://chargedaffairs.org/cultural-genocide-funds-isis-art-for-weapons-trade/ |website=Charged Affairs |date=7 March 2017 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}{{Dead link|date=December 2023 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[persecution of Uyghurs in China]]. Some one million members of [[Islam in China|China's Muslim]] [[Uyghurs|Uyghur]] minority have been detained in massive [[Xinjiang re-education camps|detention camps]], termed "[[Re-education through labor|reeducation camps]]", which exist for the purpose of changing the political thinking, identities and religious beliefs of the detainees, under the guise of "[[anti-terrorism]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Cronin-Furman |first=Kate |title=China Has Chosen Cultural Genocide in Xinjiang—For Now |url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2018/09/19/china-has-chosen-cultural-genocide-in-xinjiang-for-now/ |access-date=20 September 2018 |work=[[Foreign Policy]] |date=19 September 2018 |language=en |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Satellite evidence suggests that China has also razed more than two dozen Uyghur Muslim religious sites to the ground.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Kuo |first=Lily |date=7 May 2019 |title=Revealed: new evidence of China's mission to raze the mosques of Xinjiang |url=https://theguardian.com/world/2019/may/07/revealed-new-evidence-of-chinas-mission-to-raze-the-mosques-of-xinjiang |access-date=7 May 2019 |newspaper=[[The Guardian]] |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Oceania===
* The [[Stolen Generations]] in Australia where [[half-caste]] children were removed from their families.&lt;ref name="Wilkie1997" /&gt;

===North America===
{{See also|Cultural genocide in the United States|Trail of Tears}}
*Indigenous peoples in the United States. 
**In the mid-1800s to early 1900s, the United States established [[American Indian boarding schools]] to assimilate Native American children and youth into Euro-American culture.
*[[Canadian genocide of Indigenous peoples]]. 
**The [[Indian Residential Schools Truth and Reconciliation Commission]] of Canada concluded that the [[Canadian Indian residential school system]] "can best be described as 'cultural genocide.{{' "}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=2 June 2015 |title=Canada's Forced Schooling of Aboriginal Children Was 'Cultural Genocide,' Report Finds |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/03/world/americas/canadas-forced-schooling-of-aboriginal-children-was-cultural-genocide-report-finds.html |access-date=2 June 2015 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
**In 2015, Chief Justice [[Beverley McLachlin|Beverly McLachlin]], of the Supreme Court of Canada, stated in a speech to the [[Global Centre for Pluralism]] that Canada's historical treatment of Indigenous peoples was an attempt at cultural genocide, and "the worst stain on Canada's human-rights record."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/chief-justice-says-canada-attempted-cultural-genocide-on-aboriginals/article24688854/ |title=Chief Justice says Canada attempted 'cultural genocide' on aboriginals |last=Fine |first=Sean |date=28 May 2015 |work=[[The Globe and Mail]] |access-date=30 December 2018 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Main|Outline of genocide studies}}
{{Portal|Genocide}}
* [[Cultural assimilation]]
* [[Cultural imperialism]]
* [[Cultural racism]]
* [[Ethnic cleansing]]
* [[Ethnic conflict]]
* [[Ethnocentrism]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Forced assimilation]]
* [[Language death]]
* [[Linguistic discrimination]]
* [[Policide]]
* [[Population transfer]]
* [[Religious discrimination]]
* [[Religious persecution]]

==References==
{{Reflist|refs =

&lt;ref name="AbtahiWebb2008"&gt;{{cite book |first1=Hirad |last1=Abtahi |first2=Philippa |last2=Webb |title=The Genocide Convention |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sB_807GbDRgC&amp;pg=PA731 |access-date=22 February 2013 |year=2008 |publisher=[[Brill Publishers|BRILL]] |isbn=978-90-04-17399-6 |page=731}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Davidson2012"&gt;{{cite book |first=Lawrence |last=Davidson |title=Cultural Genocide |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2w9Ez6wT6icC |access-date=22 February 2013 |date=8 March 2012 |publisher=[[Rutgers University Press]] |isbn=978-0-8135-5344-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="DelantyKumar2006"&gt;{{cite book |first1=Gerard |last1=Delanty |first2=Krishan |last2=Kumar |title=The SAGE Handbook of Nations and Nationalism |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3Y3zK_jyagQC&amp;pg=PA326 |access-date=28 February 2013 |date=29 June 2006 |publisher=[[SAGE Publications]] |isbn=978-1-4129-0101-7 |page=326 |quote=The term 'ethnocide' has in the past been used as a replacement for cultural genocide (Palmer 1992; Smith 1991:30-3), with the obvious risk of confusing ethnicity and culture.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Wilkie1997"&gt;{{cite web |last=Wilkie |first=Meredith |title=Bringing them Home: report of the national inquiry into the separation of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander children from their families – Chapter 13 |url=https://humanrights.gov.au/our-work/bringing-them-home-chapter-13 |website=[[Australian Human Rights Commission]] |date=April 1997 |quote="The Australian practice of Indigenous child removal involved both systematic racial discrimination and genocide as defined by international law" |access-date=29 April 2021 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-1"&gt;[http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/madrid1933-english.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Acts Constituting a General (Transnational) Danger Considered as Offences Against the Law of Nations'' (J. Fussell trans., 2000) (1933)]; [http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/AxisRule1944-3.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Axis Rule in Occupied Europe'', p. 91 (1944)].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-2"&gt;See [https://web.archive.org/web/20010828104653/http://www.un.org/icty/krstic/TrialC1/judgement/krs-tj010802e-3.htm Prosecutor v. Krstic, Case No. IT-98-33-T (Int'l Crim. Trib. Yugo. Trial Chamber 2001), at para. 576].
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;ref name="AutoCK-3"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20000408162107/http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm |archive-date=8 April 2000 |title=Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide, Article 2, 78 U.N.T.S. 277. |date=9 December 1948}}&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-4"&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/E.CN.4.SUB.2.RES.1994.45.En?OpenDocument Draft United Nations declaration on the rights of indigenous peoples] drafted by The Sub-Commission on Prevention of Discrimination and Protection of Minorities Recalling resolutions 1985/22 of 29 August 1985, 1991/30 of 29 August 1991, 1992/33 of 27 August 1992, 1993/46 of 26 August 1993, presented to the Commission on Human Rights and the Economic and Social Council at 36th meeting 26 August 1994 and adopted without a vote.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-5"&gt;{{cite book |first=William |last=Schabas |author-link=William Schabas |title=Genocide in international law: the crimes of crimes |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |date=2000 |isbn=0-521-78790-4 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pYptuRHDQPgC&amp;dq=%22Cultural+genocide%22+Poand&amp;pg=PA179 |page=179}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-7"&gt;{{cite magazine |last1=Maghakyan |first1=Simon |title=Sacred Stones Silenced in Azerbaijan |magazine=[[History Today]] |date=November 2007 |volume=57 |issue=11 |url=https://www.historytoday.com/archive/sacred-stones-silenced-azerbaijan |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-8"&gt;Switzerland-Armenia Parliamentary Group, "The Destruction of Jugha", Bern, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-9"&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070307095928/http://www.cgs.c.u-tokyo.ac.jp/workshops_e/w_2004_02_23_e.html CGS 1st Workshop: "Cultural Genocide" and the Japanese Occupation of Korea] ([https://web.archive.org/web/20070307095928/http://www.cgs.c.u-tokyo.ac.jp/workshops_e/w_2004_02_23_e.html archive]) "During Germany's occupation of Poland (1939–1945) and Japan's occupation of Korea (1910–1945), the prohibition of use of the native tongue, the renaming of people and places, the removal of indigenous people from institutions of higher education, the destruction of cultural facilities, the denial of freedom of religious faith, and the changing of cultural education all took place. The instances of German cultural genocide, which Lemkin took as his basis, cannot be ignored when conducting comparative research." "One of the most striking features of Japan's occupation of Korea is the absence of an awareness of Korea as a "colony", and the absence of an awareness of Koreans as a "separate ethnicity". As a result, it is difficult to prove whether or not the leaders of Japan aimed for the eradication of the Korean race."&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-10"&gt;{{cite AV media |url=http://www.ina.fr/video/CPB89005126/les-droits-de-l-homme-video.html |work=Apostrophes |publisher=Ina.fr |author=Institut National de l'Audiovisuel |date=21 April 1989 |language=fr |title=Les droits de l'homme |trans-title=Human rights |medium=Videotape |access-date=2 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-11"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dalailama.com/messages/tibet/10th-march-archive |title=10th March Statements Archive |access-date=4 January 2015 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-12"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/7299212.stm |work=[[BBC News]] |title='Eighty killed' in Tibetan unrest |date=16 March 2008 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-13"&gt;{{cite journal| last=Ghanea-Hercock |first=Nazila |title=Review of secondary literature in English on recent persecutions of Bahá'ís in Iran |journal=Baháʼí Studies Review |volume=7 |publisher=Association for Baha'i Studies English-Speaking Europe |year=1997 |url=http://bahai-library.com/ghanea-hercock_literature_persecutions_bahai |access-date=3 March 2013 |archive-url= |archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-14"&gt;{{cite book |first=Nader |last=Saiedi |title=Gate of the Heart: Understanding the Writings of the Báb |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=L22SqPOZWnUC&amp;pg=PA377 |access-date=3 March 2013 |date=1 May 2008 |publisher=[[Wilfrid Laurier University Press]] |isbn=978-1-55458-035-4|page=377}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Further reading==
* [[Bibliography of genocide studies]]

== External links ==
* [http://ambassadors.net/archives/issue19/opinions2.htm From Paris to Cairo: Resistance of the Unacculturated] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101209073701/http://ambassadors.net/archives/issue19/opinions2.htm |date=9 December 2010 }} on identity and the nation state.
* [[:ca:Cronologia de la repressió del català|Chronology of the repression of the Catalan language]] in catalan language
{{Indigenous rights footer}}
{{Culture}}
{{Genocide topics}}{{Ethnicity}}{{DEFAULTSORT:Cultural Genocide}}
[[Category:Cultural genocide| ]]
[[Category:1940s neologisms]]
[[Category:Genocide]]
[[Category:Human rights by issue]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]
[[Category:Political and cultural purges]]
{{Discrimination}}




[[pt:Genocídio cultural]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>