<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211123172528|1056805953" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="55084" pageid="55084" ns="0" title="Cultural genocide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-23T17:30:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Type of genocide}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2020}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
{{Genocide}}
'''Cultural genocide''' or '''cultural cleansing''' is a concept which was proposed by lawyer [[Raphael Lemkin]] in 1944 as a component of [[genocide]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Bilsky |first1=Leora |last2=Klagsbrun |first2=Rachel |title=The Return of Cultural Genocide? |journal=European Journal of International Law |date=23 July 2018 |volume=29 |issue=2 |pages=373–396 |doi=10.1093/ejil/chy025 |url=https://academic.oup.com/ejil/article/29/2/373/5057075 |access-date=2 May 2020 |language=en |issn=0938-5428|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Though the precise definition of ''cultural genocide'' remains contested, the [[Tsitsernakaberd|Armenian Genocide Museum]] defines it as "acts and measures undertaken to destroy nations' or ethnic groups' culture through spiritual, national, and cultural destruction."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.genocide-museum.am/eng/cultural_genocide.php|title=Genocide Museum {{!}} The Armenian Genocide Museum-institute|website=www.genocide-museum.am|access-date=10 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[Ethnology|ethnologists]], such as [[Robert Jaulin]], use the term ''[[ethnocide]]'' as a substitute for ''cultural genocide'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=La paix blanche : introduction à l'ethnocide |author=Robert Jaulin |author-link=Robert Jaulin |publisher=Éditions du Seuil |year=1970 |language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; although this usage has been criticized as risking the confusion between [[ethnicity]] and [[culture]].&lt;ref name="DelantyKumar2006" /&gt; Juxtaposed next to ''ethnocide'', ''cultural genocide'' was considered in the 2007 [[United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples]]; however, it was removed in the final document and simply replaced with "genocide."

== Definition ==

The legal definition of ''[[genocide]]'' is unspecific about the exact way in which genocide is committed, only stating that it is destruction with the [[genocidal intent|intent to destroy]] a racial, religious, ethnic or national group.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-3" /&gt;

As such, cultural genocide involves the eradication and destruction of [[cultural artifact]]s, such as books, artworks, and structures, as well as the suppression of cultural activities that do not conform to the destroyer's notion of what is appropriate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Cultural Genocide, Stolen Lives: The Indigenous Peoples of Canada and the Indian Residential Schools |url=https://www.facinghistory.org/stolen-lives-indigenous-peoples-canada-and-indian-residential-schools/chapter-7/cultural-genocide |website=Facing History and Ourselves |publisher=Facing History and Ourselves |access-date=3 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among many other potential reasons, cultural genocide may be committed for religious motives (e.g., [[iconoclasm]]); as part of a campaign of [[ethnic cleansing]] in order to remove the evidence of a people from a specific locale or history; as part of an effort to implement a [[Year Zero (political notion)|Year Zero]], in which the past and its associated culture is deleted and history is "reset".

== History ==

=== Etymology ===
The notion of 'cultural genocide' has been acknowledged as early as 1944, when lawyer [[Raphael Lemkin]] distinguished a cultural component of genocide. The term itself would not emerge until later.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-1"/&gt; In 1989, [[Robert Badinter]], a French criminal lawyer known for his stance against the [[death penalty]], used the term "cultural genocide" on a television show to describe what he said was the disappearance of [[Tibetan culture]] in the presence of the [[14th Dalai Lama]].&lt;ref name="AutoCK-10"/&gt; The Dalai Lama would later use the term in 1993&lt;ref name="AutoCK-11"/&gt; and he would use it again [[2008 Tibetan unrest|in 2008]].&lt;ref name="AutoCK-12"/&gt;

===Proposed inclusion in the UN's DRIP===
{{see also | United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples }}

Those who drafted the 1948 [[Genocide Convention]] initially considered using of the term, but later dropped it from inclusion.&lt;ref name="AbtahiWebb2008"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Davidson2012"/&gt;&lt;ref name="AutoCK-2"/&gt;

Article 7 of a 1994 draft of the [[United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples]] (DRIP) uses the phrase "cultural genocide" but does not define what it means.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-4"/&gt; The complete article in the draft read as follows:
:Indigenous peoples have the collective and individual right not to be subjected to [[ethnocide]] and cultural genocide, including prevention of and redress for:
::(a) Any action which has the aim or effect of depriving them of their integrity as distinct peoples, or of their cultural values or ethnic identities;
::(b) Any action which has the aim or effect of dispossessing them of their lands, territories or resources;
::(c) Any form of [[population transfer]] which has the aim or effect of violating or undermining any of their rights;
::(d) Any form of [[acculturation|assimilation or integration]] by other cultures or ways of life imposed on them by legislative, administrative or other measures;
::(e) Any form of propaganda directed against them.

This wording only ever appeared in a draft. The DRIP—which was adopted by the [[United Nations General Assembly]] during its 62nd session at [[UN Headquarters]] in [[New York City]] on 13 September 2007—only makes reference to genocide once, when it mentions "genocide, or any other act of violence" in Article 7. Though the concept of "ethnocide" and "cultural genocide" was removed in the version adopted by the General Assembly, the sub-points from the draft noted above were retained (with slightly expanded wording) in Article 8 that speaks to "the right not to be subject to forced assimilation."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/development/desa/indigenouspeoples/wp-content/uploads/sites/19/2018/11/UNDRIP_E_web.pdf|title=United Nations Declaration on Rights of Indigenous Peoples|publisher=United Nations|page=10|date=13 September 2007|access-date=9 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== List of cultural genocides ==
The term has been used to describe the destruction of [[cultural heritage]] in connection with various events listed mainly from the 20th century:

===Europe===
* Historian Stephen Wheatcroft states that Soviet peasantry were subject to cultural destruction in the creation of the "[[New Soviet man]]".&lt;ref name=wheatcroft&gt;The Complexity of the Kazakh Famine: Food Problems and Faulty Perceptions Stephen G. Wheatcroft &lt;/ref&gt;
* In reference to the [[Axis powers]] (primarily, [[Nazi Germany]])'s policies towards some nations during [[World War II]] (ex. the [[History of Poland (1939–1945)|German occupation of Poland]] &amp; [[Polish culture during World War II|the destruction of Polish culture]]).&lt;ref name="AutoCK-5"/&gt; &lt;ref name="AutoCK-9"/&gt;
* In the [[Bosnian War]] during the [[Siege of Sarajevo]], cultural genocide was committed by Bosnian Serb forces. The [[National and University Library of Bosnia and Herzegovina]] was specifically targeted and besieged by cannons positioned all around the city. The National Library was completely destroyed in the fire, along with 80 percent of its contents. Some 3 million books were destroyed, along with hundreds of original documents from the [[Ottoman Empire]] and the [[Austria-Hungary|Austro-Hungarian monarchy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Welle (www.dw.com) |first1=Deutsche |title=Burned library symbolizes multiethnic Sarajevo {{!}} DW {{!}} 25 August 2012 |url=https://www.dw.com/en/burned-library-symbolizes-multiethnic-sarajevo/a-16192965 |publisher=Deutsche Welle}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[2004 unrest in Kosovo#Destroyed churches|2004 unrest in Kosovo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=J̌овић|first=Саво Б.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=q6YRAQAAIAAJ|title=Етничко чишћење и културни геноцид на Косову и Метохији: Сведочанства о страдању Српске православне цркве и српског народа од 1945. до 2005. год|date=2007|publisher=Информативно-издавачка установа Српске православне цркве|isbn=978-86-7758-016-2|language=sr}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an urgent appeal,&lt;ref&gt;[http://spc.rs/eng/appeal_extraordinary_session_expanded_convocation_holy_synod_bishops Appeal from the extraordinary session of the Expanded Convocation of the Holy Synod of Serbian Orthodox Church]&lt;/ref&gt; issued on 18 March by the extraordinary session of the Expanded Convocation of the [[Holy Synod of the Serbian Orthodox Church|Holy Synod of Serbian Orthodox Church]] ({{abbr|SPC|Serbian Orthodox Church}}), it was reported that a number of Serbian churches and shrines in Kosovo had been damaged or destroyed by rioters. At least 30 sites were completely destroyed, more or less destroyed, or further destroyed (sites that had been previously damaged).{{sfn|ERP KiM Info|2004}}
*After the [[Greek Civil War]], Greek authorities had conducted a cultural genocide upon [[Macedonians (ethnic group)|Slavic Macedonians]] in Northern Greece through prohibition of communication in [[Slavic languages]], renaming of cities, towns and villages ([[Lerin]]/Лерин to [[Florina]] etc.), deportation of Slavic Macedonians, particularly women and children, as well as many other actions intended to marginalize and oppress the Slavic Macedonians residing in Northern Greece. While some of these actions had been motivated by political ideology, as many of the Slavic Macedonians had sided with the defeated communists, the majority of actions were committed in order to wipe out any traces of Slavic Macedonians or their culture in Northern Greece.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=1994-05-01|title=Denying Ethnic Identity|url=https://www.hrw.org/report/1994/05/01/macedonians-greece|access-date=2021-05-10|website=Human Rights Watch|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=2019-02-24|title=Greece's invisible minority - the Macedonian Slavs|language=en-GB|work=BBC News|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/stories-47258809|access-date=2021-05-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=wmca2017|date=2017-06-21|title=Macedonian Genocide by Greeks {{!}} World Macedonian Congress -Australia|url=https://wmc-a.com/world-refugee-day/|access-date=2021-05-10|website=World Macedonian Congress - Australia|language=en-AU}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Francoist Spain]]: the alleged prohibition of the use of minority languages such as Catalan in the public space, from schools to shops, public transport, or even in the streets, the banning of the use of Catalan birth names for children, the persecution and destruction of books in [[Catalan language]],{{citation needed|date=November 2019}} renaming of cities, streets and all toponyms from Catalan to Spanish, and the abolition of government and all cultural institutions in [[Catalonia]], with the goal of total cultural suppression and [[Cultural assimilation|assimilation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Catalunya sota el règim franquista|last=1920-2008.|first=Benet, Josep|date=1978|publisher=Blume|isbn=847031064X|edition=1. reedició|location=Barcelona|oclc=4777662}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
** [[John D. Hargreaves]] writes that "A policy of cultural genocide was implemented: the Catalan language and key symbols of Catalan independent identity and nationhood, such as the flag (the [[senyera]]), the national hymn ('[[Els Segadors]]') and the national dance (the [[sardana]]), were proscribed. Any sign of independence or opposition, in fact, was brutally suppressed. Catalan identity and consequently the Catalan nation were threatened with extinction."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Freedom for Catalonia? : Catalan nationalism, Spanish identity, and the Barcelona Olympic Games|last=R.)|first=Hargreaves, John (John E.|date=2000|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9780521586153|location=Cambridge|oclc=51028883}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
** Although [[Josep Pla]] and other Catalan authors published books in Catalan in the 1950s, and even there were prizes of Catalan Literature during Francoism like the [[Premi Sant Jordi de novel·la]], editorial production in Catalan never recovered the peak levels it had reached before Spanish Civil War  &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Benet|first=Josep|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/7188603|title=Cataluña bajo el régimen franquista|date=1979|publisher=Blume|isbn=84-7031-144-1|edition=1.|location=Barcelona|oclc=7188603}}&lt;/ref&gt; [https://www.gremieditors.cat/historia-de-ledicio-a-catalunya/]. A prominent case of popularization of Catalan was [[Serrat|Joan Manuel Serrat]]: although he could compose Catalan songs and gained certain notoriety, he was not allowed to sing in Catalan in the Eurovision contest its [[La, la, la]]. theme, and was replaced by Spanish singer [[Massiel]], who won the [[Eurovision Song Contest|Eurovision]] contest [https://eurovisionary.com/catalonia-crisis-eurovision-spain-blocked-catalan-victory/]. Overall, despite some tolerance as Franco's regime relaxed in the late 60s and early 70s, Catalan and the rest of minority languages of Spain were strictly banned from higher education, administration and all official endeavors, thus being in practice confined to the private sphere and domestic uses (see [[Language policies of Francoist Spain]]).
*[[Ireland]] has been described as enduring cultural genocide under British rule, which aimed to eradicate the [[Irish language]], [[Irish culture]], and the [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.irishtimes.com/culture/books/cultural-genocide-the-broken-harp-identity-and-language-in-modern-ireland-by-tom%C3%A1s-mac-s%C3%ADom%C3%B3in-1.2299891|title=Cultural genocide: The Broken Harp, Identity and Language in Modern Ireland, by Tomás Mac Síomóin|website=The Irish Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.opendemocracy.net/en/opendemocracyuk/guardian-view-on-cultural-genocide/|title=The Guardian view on... cultural genocide|website=openDemocracy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://randompublicjournal.com/2018/02/20/bad-language-gaelic-and-britains-cultural-genocide/|title=Bad Language: Gaelic and Britain's Cultural Genocide|last=Jeggit|date=20 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ireland's cultural genocide is discussed in the ''Dictionary of Genocide'' (2007), as well as by Christopher Murray (1997) in reference to the suppression of the [[Irish language]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JGUUpRAP4CoC&amp;pg=PA42|title=Twentieth-Century Irish Drama: Mirror Up to Nation|first=Christopher|last=Murray|date=6 June 2019|publisher=Syracuse University Press|via=Google Books|isbn=9780815606437}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hilary Carey|Hilary M. Carey]] (1997) in reference to the [[Penal transportation|transportation of Irish convicts to Australia]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WUJaBAAAQBAJ&amp;q=%22Cultural+genocide%22+ireland&amp;pg=PT29|title=Believing in Australia: A cultural history of religions|first=Hilary M.|last=Carey|date=1 July 1996|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|via=Google Books|isbn=9781742696577}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by [[Tomás Mac Síomóin]] (2018).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Totten|first1=Samuel|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rgGA91skoP4C&amp;pg=PA91|title=Dictionary of Genocide|last2=Bartrop|first2=Paul Robert|last3=Jacobs|first3=Steven L.|date=6 June 2019|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=9780313346422|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Asia===
* The [[persecution of Baháʼís]] in [[Iran]] as a case of [[religious persecution]] has been called a cultural genocide.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-13"/&gt;&lt;ref name="AutoCK-14"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last =Frelick | first = Bill | title =Iranian Baha'is and Genocide Early Warning| journal =Social Science Record | volume =24| issue =2| pages =35–37| date =Fall 1987 | url =http://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ362917 | access-date = 3 March 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Khachkar destruction in Nakhchivan|destruction by Azerbaijan]] of thousands of medieval Armenian gravestones at a cemetery in [[Julfa, Azerbaijan (city)|Julfa]], and Azerbaijan's subsequent denial that the site had ever existed, has been cited as an example of cultural genocide.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-7"/&gt;&lt;ref name="AutoCK-8"/&gt;
* Historian Sarah Cameron believes that while the [[Kazakh famine of 1931–1933]] combined with a campaign against nomads was not genocide in the sense of the Genocide Convention definition, it complies with Raphael Lemkin's original concept of genocide, which considered destruction of culture to be as genocidal as physical annihilation.&lt;ref name=wheatcroft&gt;The Complexity of the Kazakh Famine: Food Problems and Faulty Perceptions Stephen G. Wheatcroft &lt;/ref&gt;
* Branch of the [[Japan Society for the Promotion of Science]] and the [[Korea under Japanese rule|Japanese occupation of Korea]].&lt;ref name="AutoCK-9"/&gt;
* The [[Sinicization of Tibet]] from the 1950's onwards.
*The destruction of [[Armenian cultural heritage in Turkey]] during, and in the decades after, the [[Armenian genocide]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.genocide-museum.am/eng/cultural_genocide.php|title=Genocide Museum {{!}} The Armenian Genocide Museum-institute|website=www.genocide-museum.am|access-date=10 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|ISIL]] [[forced conversion]]s in its territory and destroyed ancient [[Assyria]]n, [[Rome|Roman]], [[Yazidi]] and [[Christianity|Christian]] heritage sites and museums.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Cultural Genocide Funds ISIS Art-for-Weapons Trade |url=https://chargedaffairs.org/cultural-genocide-funds-isis-art-for-weapons-trade/ |website=Charged Affairs |date=7 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Uyghur genocide|Uyghur genocide in China]]. Some one million members of [[Islam in China|China's Muslim]] [[Uyghurs|Uyghur]] minority have been detained in mass [[Xinjiang re-education camps|detention camps]], termed "[[Re-education through labor|reeducation camps]]," which are aimed at changing the political thinking of detainees, their identities, and their religious beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Cronin-Furman|first=Kate|title=China Has Chosen Cultural Genocide in Xinjiang—For Now|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2018/09/19/china-has-chosen-cultural-genocide-in-xinjiang-for-now/|access-date=20 September 2018|website=Foreign Policy|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Satellite evidence suggests that China has also razed more than two dozen Uyghur Muslim religious sites to the ground.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kuo|first=Lily|date=7 May 2019|title=Revealed: new evidence of China's mission to raze the mosques of Xinjiang|url=https://theguardian.com/world/2019/may/07/revealed-new-evidence-of-chinas-mission-to-raze-the-mosques-of-xinjiang|access-date=7 May 2019|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Oceania===
* The [[Stolen Generations]] in Australia where [[half-caste]] children were removed from their families.&lt;ref name="Wilkie1997" /&gt;

===North America===
*[[Indigenous peoples in Canada]]. 
**In 2007, a Canadian Member of Parliament criticized the [[Minister of Indian Affairs|Ministry of Indian Affairs]]' destruction of documents that were evidence to the "cultural genocide" imposed on Indigenous peoples within Canada.&lt;ref name="AutoCK-6" /&gt;
**The [[Indian Residential Schools Truth and Reconciliation Commission]] of Canada concluded that the [[Canadian Indian residential school system]] "can best be described as 'cultural genocide.{{' "}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=2 June 2015|title=Canada's Forced Schooling of Aboriginal Children Was 'Cultural Genocide,' Report Finds|newspaper=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/03/world/americas/canadas-forced-schooling-of-aboriginal-children-was-cultural-genocide-report-finds.html|access-date=2 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
**In 2015, Chief Justice [[Beverley McLachlin|Beverly McLachlin]], of the Supreme Court of Canada, stated in a speech to the [[Global Centre for Pluralism]] that Canada's historical treatment of Indigenous peoples was an attempt at cultural genocide, and "the worst stain on Canada's human-rights record."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/chief-justice-says-canada-attempted-cultural-genocide-on-aboriginals/article24688854/|title=Chief Justice says Canada attempted 'cultural genocide' on aboriginals|last=Fine|first=Sean|date=28 May 2015|work=The Globe and Mail|access-date=30 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Genocide}}
{{div col|colwidth=23em}}
* [[American Indian boarding schools]]
* [[Canadian Indian residential school system]]
* [[Cultural conflict]]
* [[Cultural imperialism]]
* [[Culture war]]
* [[Ethnic cleansing]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Forced assimilation]]
* [[Institutional racism]]
* [[Language death]]
* [[Linguistic discrimination]] (includes Linguicide)
* [[List of destroyed heritage]]
* [[Native schools|Native schools in New Zealand]]
* [[Policide]]
* [[Religious cleansing]]
* [[Stolen Generations]] (Australia)
* [[Uyghur genocide]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|refs =

&lt;ref name="AbtahiWebb2008"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Hirad Abtahi|author2=Philippa Webb|title=The Genocide Convention|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sB_807GbDRgC&amp;pg=PA731|access-date=22 February 2013|year=2008|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-17399-6|page=731}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Davidson2012"&gt;{{cite book|author=Lawrence Davidson|title=Cultural Genocide|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2w9Ez6wT6icC|access-date=22 February 2013|date=8 March 2012|publisher=Rutgers University Press|isbn=978-0-8135-5344-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="DelantyKumar2006"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Gerard Delanty|author2=Krishan Kumar|title=The SAGE Handbook of Nations and Nationalism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3Y3zK_jyagQC&amp;pg=PA326|access-date=28 February 2013|date=29 June 2006|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-1-4129-0101-7|page=326|quote=The term 'ethnocide' has in the past been used as a replacement for cultural genocide (Palmer 1992; Smith 1991:30-3), with the obvious risk of confusing ethnicity and culture.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Wilkie1997"&gt;{{cite web|author=Wilkie, Meredith|title=Bringing them Home: report of the national inquiry into the separation of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander children from their families - Chapter 13|url=https://humanrights.gov.au/our-work/bringing-them-home-chapter-13|website=Australian Human Rights Commission|date=April 1997|quote="The Australian practice of Indigenous child removal involved both systematic racial discrimination and genocide as defined by international law"|access-date=29 April 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-1"&gt;[http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/madrid1933-english.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Acts Constituting a General (Transnational) Danger Considered as Offences Against the Law of Nations'' (J. Fussell trans., 2000) (1933)]; [http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/AxisRule1944-3.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Axis Rule in Occupied Europe'', p. 91 (1944)].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-2"&gt;See [https://web.archive.org/web/20010828104653/http://www.un.org/icty/krstic/TrialC1/judgement/krs-tj010802e-3.htm Prosecutor v. Krstic, Case No. IT-98-33-T (Int'l Crim. Trib. Yugo. Trial Chamber 2001), at para. 576].
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-3"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20000408162107/http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm|archive-date=8 April 2000|title=Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide, Article 2, 78 U.N.T.S. 277.|date=9 December 1948}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-4"&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/E.CN.4.SUB.2.RES.1994.45.En?OpenDocument Draft United Nations declaration on the rights of indigenous peoples] drafted by The Sub-Commission on Prevention of Discrimination and Protection of Minorities Recalling resolutions 1985/22 of 29 August 1985, 1991/30 of 29 August 1991, 1992/33 of 27 August 1992, 1993/46 of 26 August 1993, presented to the Commission on Human Rights and the Economic and Social Council at 36th meeting 26 August 1994 and adopted without a vote.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-5"&gt;William Schabas, ''Genocide in international law: the crimes of crimes'', Cambridge University Press, 2000, {{ISBN|0-521-78790-4}}, [https://books.google.com/books?id=pYptuRHDQPgC&amp;pg=PA179&amp;dq=%22Cultural+genocide%22+Poand Google Print, p.179]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-6"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.torontosun.com/News/Canada/2007/04/25/4128038-sun.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150503003253/http://rabble.ca/babble/aboriginal-issues-and-culture/genocide-target-federal-coverup-mp|archive-date=3 May 2015|author=Jorge Barrera|title='Genocide' target of fed coverup: MP|newspaper=Toronto Sun|date=25 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-7"&gt;History Today, November 2007, "Sacred Stones Silenced in Azerbaijan"&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-8"&gt;Switzerland-Armenia Parliamentary Group, "The Destruction of Jugha", Bern, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-9"&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070307095928/http://www.cgs.c.u-tokyo.ac.jp/workshops_e/w_2004_02_23_e.html CGS 1st Workshop: "Cultural Genocide" and the Japanese Occupation of Korea] ([https://web.archive.org/web/20070307095928/http://www.cgs.c.u-tokyo.ac.jp/workshops_e/w_2004_02_23_e.html archive]) "During Germany's occupation of Poland (1939-1945) and Japan's occupation of Korea (1910-1945), the prohibition of use of the native tongue, the renaming of people and places, the removal of indigenous people from institutions of higher education, the destruction of cultural facilities, the denial of freedom of religious faith, and the changing of cultural education all took place. The instances of German cultural genocide, which Lemkin took as his basis, cannot be ignored when conducting comparative research.""One of the most striking features of Japan's occupation of Korea is the absence of an awareness of Korea as a "colony", and the absence of an awareness of Koreans as a "separate ethnicity". As a result, it is difficult to prove whether or not the leaders of Japan aimed for the eradication of the Korean race."&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-10"&gt;{{cite AV media|url=http://www.ina.fr/video/CPB89005126/les-droits-de-l-homme-video.html|work=Apostrophes|publisher=Ina.fr|author=Institut National de l'Audiovisuel|date=21 April 1989|language=fr|title=Les droits de l'homme|trans-title=Human rights|medium=Videotape|access-date=2 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-11"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dalailama.com/messages/tibet/10th-march-archive|title=10th March Statements Archive|access-date=4 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-12"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/7299212.stm|work=BBC News|title='Eighty killed' in Tibetan unrest|date=16 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-13"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ghanea-Hercock|first=Nazila|title=Review of secondary literature in English on recent persecutions of Bahá'ís in Iran|journal=Bahá'í Studies Review|volume=7|publisher=Association for Baha'i Studies English-Speaking Europe|year=1997|url=http://bahai-library.com/ghanea-hercock_literature_persecutions_bahai|access-date=3 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="AutoCK-14"&gt;{{cite book|author=Nader Saiedi|title=Gate of the Heart: Understanding the Writings of the Báb|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=L22SqPOZWnUC&amp;pg=PA377|access-date=3 March 2013|date=1 May 2008|publisher=Wilfrid Laurier Univ. Press|isbn=978-1-55458-035-4|page=377}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

{{Indigenous rights footer}}
{{Culture}}
{{Ethnicity}}
{{Genocide topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cultural Genocide}}
[[Category:Cultural genocide| ]]
[[Category:1940s neologisms]]
[[Category:Genocide]]
[[Category:Human rights by issue]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]

[[pt:Genocídio cultural]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>