<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20070907191440|156328861" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="55084" pageid="55084" ns="0" title="Cultural genocide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-06T23:48:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Mergeto|Ethnocide|date=August 2007}}
{{Portal|Genocide|GenocidePortalLogo(ESR)2.JPG}}

'''Cultural genocide''' is a political and rhetorical term used to describe the deliberate destruction of the cultural heritage of a people or nation for political, military, religious, ideological, ethnical, or racial reasons. 

==Relevance to International Law==

As early as [[1933]], [[Raphael Lemkin]] proposed a cultural component to genocide, which he called "[[vandalism]]".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/madrid1933-english.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Acts Constituting a General (Transnational) Danger Considered as Offences Against the Law of Nations'' (J. Fussell trans., 2000) (1933)]; [http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/AxisRule1944-3.htm Raphael Lemkin, ''Axis Rule in Occupied Europe'', p. 91 (1944)].&lt;/ref&gt; However, the drafters of the 1948 [[Genocide Convention]] dropped that concept from their consideration.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.un.org/icty/krstic/TrialC1/judgement/krs-tj010802e-3.htm#IIIG2bi Prosecutor v. Krstic, Case No. IT-98-33-T (Int'l Crim. Trib. Yugo. Trial Chamber 2001), at para. 576] ("Although the Convention does not specifically speak to the point, the preparatory work points out that the ‘cultural’ destruction of a group was expressly rejected after having been seriously contemplated.  The notion of cultural genocide was considered too vague and too removed from the physical or biological destruction that motivated the Convention.").&lt;/ref&gt; The legal definition of [[genocide]] was confined to acts of physical or biological destruction with intent to destroy a racial, religious, ethnic or national group as such.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm Convention on Prevention and Punishment of Genocide, art. 2, Dec. 9, 1948, 78 U.N.T.S. 277.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Article 7 of the [[United Nations Draft Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples]] ([[26 August]] [[1994]]) &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/E.CN.4.SUB.2.RES.1994.45.En?OpenDocument Draft United Nations declaration on the rights of indigenous peoples] drafted by The Sub-Commission on Prevention of Discrimination and Protection of Minorities Recalling  resolutions 1985/22 of 29 August 1985, 1991/30 of [[29 August]] [[1991]], 1992/33 of [[27 August]] [[1992]], 1993/46 of [[26 August]] [[1993]], presented to the Commission on Human Rights and the Economic and Social Council at 36th meeting [[26 August]] [[1994]] and adopted without a vote.&lt;/ref&gt; uses the phrase "cultural genocide" but does not define what it means. The complete article reads as follows:
:Indigenous peoples have the collective and individual right not to be subjected to [[ethnocide]] and cultural genocide, including prevention of and redress for:
::(a) Any action which has the aim or effect of depriving them of their integrity as distinct peoples, or of their cultural values or ethnic identities;
::(b) Any action which has the aim or effect of dispossessing them of their lands, territories or resources;
::(c) Any form of [[population transfer]] which has the aim or effect of violating or undermining any of their rights;
::(d) Any form of [[acculturation|assimilation or integration]] by other cultures or ways of life imposed on them by legislative, administrative or other measures;
::(e) Any form of propaganda directed against them.

It should be noted that this declaration is only a draft. Were it to pass, it would be a "[[soft law]]" instrument and would not present binding legal obligations on UN parties.

Despite its lack of legal currency, the term has acquired rhetorical value as a phrase that is used to protest against the destruction of cultural heritage. It is also often misused as a catchphrase to condemn any destruction the user of the phrase disaproves of, without regard for the criterion of intent to destroy an affected group as such.

==Examples of the Term's Rhetorical Usage==

Cultural advocates have leveled charges of "cultural genocide" in connection with various events: 

* In 2007, a Canadian Member of Parliament criticized the Ministry of Indian Affairs' destruction of documents regarding the treatment of First Nations members as "cultural genocide."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.edmontonsun.com/News/Canada/2007/04/25/4127962-sun.html Jorge Barrera , ''‘Genocide’ target of fed coverup: MP'', Edmonton Sun, April 25, 2007.]&lt;/ref&gt;

* When Turkey's Minister of Cultural Affairs opened the Ahtamar Church in eastern Anatolia as a museum, critics objected to the choice of a Turkish name as a denial of the region's Armenian heritage and as a sort of "cultural genocide".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.turkishdailynews.com.tr/article.php?enewsid=69531 Cengiz Çandar, ''The So-Called ‘Akdamar museum’'', Turkish Daily News, March 30, 2007.]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Some scholars have discussed whether "cultural genocide" properly describes Japan's suppression of [[Korean language]], traditions, and names, and the teaching of [[Korean history]] during the [[Korea under Japanese rule|Japanese occupation of Korea]] from [[1910]] to [[1945]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cgs.c.u-tokyo.ac.jp/workshops_e/w_2004_02_23_e.html&lt;/ref&gt;

* Some right-wing activists have applied the term to what they see as a downfall of Western civilization due to liberal immigration policies, diversity, and multiculturism.&lt;ref name=bnp&gt;[http://www.bnp.org.uk/news_detail.php?newsId=357 ''The Era of Defamation and Multi-Cultural Genocide''] The [[British National Party]] claims "multi-cultural genocide" in progress against Britain.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name=kkk&gt;[http://www.davidduke.com/?p=179 ''John Tyndall Arrested ''] Former [[Ku-Klux Klan]] leader [[David Duke]] claims cultural genocide against Whites&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[Endangered language]]
* [[Language policy]]
* [[Linguicide]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Korea under Japanese rule]]
* [[Stolen Generation]] of Australia
* [[Residential school]]s in Canada
* [[Native Schools]] in New Zealand
* [[Carlisle Indian Industrial School]] in the United States
* [[Welsh Not]]
* [[Political Correctness]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==

*[http://www.cceia.org/resources/publications/dialogue/2_12/section_1/5139.html Rethinking Cultural Genocide Under International Law] 
*[http://www.preventgenocide.org/lemkin/ Raphael Lemkin] 
*[http://www.savetibet.org/news/newsitem.php?id=983 Tibetan cultural genocide] 
*[http://www.regnum.ru/english/560850.html Cultural genocide of Armenian monuments continues] 
*[http://www.australian-news.com.au/Aboriginal.htm Aboriginal cultural genocide] 
*[http://www.nemasys.com/ghostwolf/Native/genocide.shtml Spiritual and cultural genocide of the Native Americans] 
*[http://www.pitcairners.org/bloodless_genocide2.html Bloodless Genocide of the Pitcairn People in Norfolk Island] 
*[http://www.cornwall24.co.uk/PNphpBB2-viewtopic-t-749-highlight-genocide.htm Cornish cultural genocide]
*[http://socialissues.wiseto.com/Articles/EJ3010078215/ Canada Cultural Genocide: Forced Removal of Native Children]

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}} 

[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:Genocide]]

[[ca:Genocidi cultural]]
[[fr:Génocide culturel]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>