<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101021041519|391969485" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="264989" pageid="264989" ns="0" title="Non-binary gender"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-10-31T08:34:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2007}}
{{Original research|date=September 2008}}
{{Clear}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}
'''Genderqueer''' ('''GQ''') and '''intergender''' are catch-all terms for [[Gender identity|gender identities]] other than man and woman.  People who identify as genderqueer may think of themselves as being both man and woman, as being neither man nor woman, or as falling completely outside the [[gender binary]]. They may express a combination of masculinity and femininity, one or the other, or neither. [[Androgyne]] is also used commonly to describe this same category.  Since there is still relatively little agreed upon terminology, the distinction between the two categories is difficult to pull apart.  Genderqueers may have any sexuality/sexual identity, any physical sex, and may or may not identify as trans ([[Trans woman|trans women]] and [[Trans man|trans men]]).

Some genderqueer people see their identity as one of many possible genders other than man or woman, while others see "genderqueer" as an umbrella term that encompasses all of those possible genders. Still others see "genderqueer" as a [[third gender]] to complement the traditional two, while others identify as genderless or agender. Genderqueers, by definition, are united by their rejection of the notion that there are only two genders.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} The term "genderqueer" can also be used as an adjective to refer to any people who transgress gender, regardless of their self-defined gender identity.

==Gender and pronouns==

Some genderqueers prefer to go by the conventional binary pronouns "he" or "she", while others prefer [[gender-neutral pronoun]]s such as "ze", "sie", and "hir" or [[singular they|singular "they"]] instead of [[gender-specific pronoun|her/his]]. Some genderqueers prefer to be referred to alternately as he and she (and/or gender neutral pronouns), and some prefer to use only their name and not use pronouns at all.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Feinberg |first=L. |title=Transgender warriors: Making history from Joan of Arc to Dennis Rodman |publisher=Beacon |year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal box|LGBT|Transgender}}
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Bash Back]]
* [[Butch and femme]]
* [[Drag king]]
* [[Drag queen]]
* [[Girlfags and guydykes]]
* [[Queer]]
* [[Transcending Boundaries Conference]]
* [[Two-spirit]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

== References ==
* ''Gender Queer. Voices From Beyond the Sexual Binary'', Joan Nestle, Clare Howell, Riki Wilchins (2002) Alyson Books, New York.
* ''The Transgender Studies Reader'', Susan Stryker, Stephen Whittle (2006) Routledge, New York.

==External links==
* [http://unitedgenders.org United Genders of the Universe] a genderqueer organisation
* [http://androgyne.0catch.com Androgyne Online]: non-binary gender variants/variance
* [http://t-vox.org/ T-Vox] – International resource and information wiki.
* [http://qvox.org Qvox.org] – Web resource on queer gender and sexuality.
* [http://www.polygender.co.uk Polygender.co.uk] – Includes 'A Queergendered FAQ'.
* [http://www.genderfork.com Genderfork] – Photos and anonymous thoughts from the genderqueer community
* [http://www.whatisgender.net What is Gender?] – "A support forum for transgendered, non_binary, and significant others."

{{Template group
|list =
{{Sexual identities}}
{{LGBT|state=collapsed|main=expanded}}
}}

[[Category:Genderqueer| ]]
[[Category:Transgender identities]]

[[cy:Rhyngrywedd]]
[[da:Genderqueer]]
[[es:Genderqueer]]
[[it:Genderqueer]]
[[he:ג'נדרקוויר]]
[[ru:Гендерквир]]
[[sh:Interrodnost]]
[[fi:Genderqueer]]
[[sv:Intergender]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>