<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050911061803|23023155" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="264989" pageid="264989" ns="0" title="Non-binary gender"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-04T05:29:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''genderqueer''' person is part of a group of people who do not fit into the traditional two-[[gender]] or gender-binary system. As with any other groups that may be aligned with [[transgender]] identities, the reasons for identifying as genderqueer vary.  

There are different modes of being genderqueer, and it is an evolving concept.  It has been proposed by many scholars that all queer-identified people have trans issues--some more than others. Historically, queer communities have provided spaces where gender expression can come in many and varied forms. Ironically, queer communities, just as susceptible to trends and fashions as anyone else, are sometimes criticized for enforcing certain gender expressions and behaviors. The queer women's controversy over the "death of femme" is an example of this, as is the long-standing controversy among queer men regarding the phrase "straight-acting".

Some believe they are a little of both of the traditional genders or think they have no gender at all. Others view gender as a continuum, with the two traditional genders at the two poles and their place as somewhere within the continuum, while others believe there are as many genders as there are people. Still others believe that gender is a [[social construct]], and choose not to adhere to that construct.  Some genderqueers do fit into the stereotypical [[gender role]]s expected of their [[sex]], but still reject gender as a social construct. Still other people identify as genderqueer since, though they are [[cisgender]]ed, they do not fit many of society's expectations for the gender in which they identify. Some genderqueers believe their gender flows from day to day.  Many traditional societies, traditional religions, and political ideologies have strict gender identities, roles, and/or positions, and disapprove of such mixing or consider it unnatural.

Some people use "genderqueer" as a politicized version of the term [[androgyne]], which describes persons who have the gender identity of both a man and a woman or neither. This understanding of the term coincides with the term "multi-gendered", which is used more frequently as a term of distinction rather than a phrase for self-identification by individuals.

The term genderqueer can (but does not necessarily) include any transgender person. These individuals challenge the social norms of gender definition, in much the same way as [[homosexuality|homosexual]] and [[bisexuality|bisexual]] individuals challenge the social norms of [[sexuality]].

The term [[pansexual]] exists specifically in reference to the genderqueer understanding of gender, as it reflects a non-binary understanding of gender and its interplay with sexuality.

Some genderqueers identify sufficiently with one gender to use conventional pronouns, others prefer that [[gender-neutral pronoun]]s should be used to refer to them, such as "ze" and "per", [[sie and hir|"sie" and "hir"]], "zhe" and "hir", or [[singular they|singular "they"]] instead of [[gender-specific pronoun|her/his]], some alternate between different pronouns, and some prefer the use only of their name and no pronouns at all.  Many people of various political stripes, view such attempts as [[political correctness]].

==See also== 
*[[butch and femme]] 
*[[queer]] 
*[[genderfuck]]
*[[third gender]]
*[[list of transgender-related topics]]

==External links==
*[http://androgyne.0catch.com Androgyne Online]

[[Category:Transgender people and behavior]]
[[Category:Genderqueer|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>