<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20040809141958|6798826" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="264989" pageid="264989" ns="0" title="Non-binary gender"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-23T15:44:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Category:Transgender people and behavior]]
A '''genderqueer''' person is part of a group of people who do not feel that they fit into the traditional two-[[gender_role|gender]] system. As with any other groups that may be aligned with ''[[transgender]]'' identities, the reasons for identifying as genderqueer vary.  

There are different modes of being genderqueer, and it is an evolving concept. Some believe they are a little of both or feel they have no gender at all. Others believe that gender is a social construct, and choose not to adhere to that construct. Some genderqueers do fit into the stereotypical [[gender role]]s expected of their [[sex]], but still reject gender as a social construct. Still other people identify as genderqueer since, though they are [[cisgender]]ed, they do not fit many of society's expectations for the gender in which they identify. 

Some people use "genderqueer" as a politicized version of the term [[androgyne]], which describes persons who have the gender identity of both a man and a woman or neither.

The term genderqueer can (but does not necessarily) include any ''[[transgender]]'' person.  These individuals challenge the social norms of gender definition, in much the same way as [[homosexual]] and [[bisexual]] individuals challenge the social norms of [[sexuality]].

Some genderqueers identify sufficiently with one gender to use conventional pronouns, others prefer that one use [[gender-neutral pronoun]]s to refer to them, such as [[sie and hir|"sie" and "hir"]] or [[singular they|singular "they"]] instead of [[gender-specific pronoun|her/his]], some alternate between different pronouns, and some prefer the use only of their name and no pronouns at all.



==See also== 
*[[androgyne]]
*[[butch]] 
*[[femme]] 
*[[Queer]] 
*[[genderfuck]]
*[[List of transgender-related topics]]

==External links==
*[http://androgyne.0catch.com Androgyne Online]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>