<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131107140556|580601184" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="36283978" pageid="36283978" ns="0" title="Lookism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-19T18:32:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{Globalize/US|date=December 2012}}
{{Weasel|date=November 2013}}
{{unbalanced|date=November 2013}}
{{metricate|date=November 2013}}
{{Notability|Neologisms|date=November 2013}}
}}
'''Lookism''' is a term used to refer to the positive [[stereotype]]s, [[prejudice]], and preferential treatment given to physically attractive people, or more generally to people whose appearance matches cultural preferences. The pejorative term '''body fascism''' is also used as a synonym&lt;ref name="Jodi"&gt;O'Brien, Jodi (2008). ''Encyclopedia of Gender and Society, Volume 1.'' SAGE, ISBN 9781412909167&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Warren Farrell]] has proposed the term '''genetic celebrity''' to describe adoration of the attractive.&lt;ref&gt;Farrell, Warren (2005). ''Why Men Earn More: The Startling Truth About the Pay Gap -- And What Women Can Do About It''. AMACOM, ISBN 0814472109 p. 193&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Physical attractiveness]] is associated with good things, such as beautiful princesses; in contrast, physical unattractiveness is associated with negative things, such as wicked witches. Many people make automatic judgments of others based on their physical appearance that influence how they respond to those people. Research on the "What is beautiful is good" stereotype shows that, overall, those who are physically attractive benefit from their good looks: physically attractive individuals are perceived more positively and physical attractiveness has a strong influence on judgement of a person’s competence.&lt;ref name="Eagly et al., 1991)."&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Eagly | first1 = Alice| last2 = Ashmore | first2 = Richard | year = 1991 | title = What is beautiful is good, but... | journal = Psychological Bulletin| volume = 110 | pages = 109–128}}&lt;/ref&gt; In return, physically attractive people benefit from these stereotypical beliefs. Research shows that on average, physically attractive individuals have more friends, better social skills, and more active sex lives. However, attractiveness does not have any effect on the level of happiness experienced by the individual.&lt;ref name="Rhodes, Simmons, &amp; Peters, 2005)."&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Rhodes | first1 =  Gillian last2 = Simmons | first2 = Leigh | last3= Peters | first3= Marianne | year = 2005 | title = Attractiveness and Sexual Behavior: Does Attractiveness Enhance Mating Success?| journal = Evolution and Human Behavior| volume = 26 | pages = 186–201}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Who is considered physically attractive?==
In [[United States culture]], many cannot define what attractiveness is, but they know it when they see it.{{citation needed|date=April 2013}} A 2001 study suggested that infants seem to have high agreement about which shapes are more attractive than others.&lt;ref name="Game, Carchon, &amp; Vital-Durand,(2003)."&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Game | first1 = Florence| last2 = Carchon | first2 = Isabelle | last3 = Vital-Durand | first3 = Francois | year = 2003 | title = The effect of stimulus attractiveness on visual tracking in 2- to 6-month-old infants. | journal = Infant Behavior and Development | volume = 26 | pages = 135–150}}&lt;/ref&gt; This shows that judgements on attractiveness are not entirely influenced by culture. On average, smooth-skinned, [[Neoteny|youthful]], [[symmetrical]] faces are seen as more attractive. Those with [[muscular]] body types are seen as more attractive, healthy, and adventuresome. [[Overweight]] individuals are often stereotypically categorized as unattractive. Although there has been little research on the topic, taller people seem to benefit more from their stature and are more likely to get dates, be hired, and be seen as competent and powerful. A study by Timothy Judge and Daniel Cable (2004) showed that an individual who is 72 inches tall is predicted to earn almost $166,000 more across a 30 year career than an individual who is 65 inches tall.

==History==
Though the term "lookism" is of recent coinage, cultures and traditions worldwide have often warned against placing undue value on physical appearance:

:To judge by appearances is to get entangled in the Veil of Maya [in Buddhist thought] [...] From ancient times until relatively recently, there was widespread worry about lookism, because the appearance of others may deceive, especially in romance, or it may be personally or politically imprudent to judge or act on appearances. Judging by appearances was prohibited by monotheistic religions (“no graven images”) and criticized in ancient and medieval philosophies. [[Philosophical skepticism|Skeptics]], [[Stoics]], [[Cynicism (philosophy)|Cynics]], [[Epicureans]] and [[Scholastics]] elaborated various reasons to avoid or subordinate the role of appearances.&lt;ref&gt;Louis Tietje and Steven Cresap (2005). "[http://mises.org/journals/jls/19_2/19_2_2.pdf Is Lookism Unjust? The History and Ethics of Aesthetics and Public Policy Implications]." ''Journal of Libertarian Studies'', Vol 19 No 2, Spring 2005, pp. 31–50&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the term "Lookism" was first coined in the 1970s within the [[fat acceptance movement]]. It was used in the ''[[The Washington Post]]'' Magazine in 1978, which asserted that the term was coined by "fat people" who created the word to refer to "discrimination based on looks."&lt;ref&gt;John Ayto, ''20th Century Words'', Oxford: [[Oxford University Press]], 1999. ISBN 978-0-19-860230-9&lt;/ref&gt; The word appears in several major English language dictionaries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com Bartleby.com] — "[http://www.bartleby.com/61/64/L0246450.html Lookism]". ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition.'' 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lookism has received scholarly attention both from a [[cultural studies]] and an [[economics]] perspective. In the former context, lookism relates to preconceived notions of [[beauty]] and cultural [[stereotyping]] based on appearance as well as [[gender role]]s and expectations. Important economic considerations include the question of income gaps based on looks, as well as increased or decreased productivity from workers considered beautiful or ugly by their co-workers.

Some writers have examined body fascism among [[gay men]]. Author [[Michelangelo Signorile]] described it as "the setting of a rigid set of standards of physical beauty that pressures everyone within a particular group to conform to them. Any person who doesn't meet those very specific standards is deemed physically unattractive and sexually undesirable. In a culture in which the physical body is held in such high esteem and given such power, body fascism then not only deems those who don't or can't conform to be sexually less desirable, but in extreme sometimes dubbed lookism also deems a person completely worthless ''as a person'', based solely on his exterior. In this sense it is not unlike racism or sexism, or homophobia itself."&lt;ref name="Morrison"&gt;Morrison, Todd Eclectic Views on Gay Male Pornography: Pornucopia, Volume 47, Psychology Press,  ISBN 9781560232919&lt;/ref&gt;

==Empirical support==
According to [[Nancy Etcoff]], a psychologist at [[Massachusetts General Hospital]], "we face a world where lookism is one of the most pervasive but denied prejudices."&lt;ref&gt;[[William Safire]]. [http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/27/magazine/the-way-we-live-now-8-27-00-on-language-lookism.html "The Way We Live Now: 8-27-00: On Language; Lookism"], ''[[New York Times Magazine]]'', August 27, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Referring to several studies, Angela Stalcup writes that "The evidence clearly indicates that not only is there a premium for prettiness in Western culture, there is also penalty for plainness."&lt;ref&gt;Angela Stalcup. [http://angelastalcup.com/sample_article.pdf ''The Plainness Penalty: Lookism in Western Culture''.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Research by [[Dan Ariely]] found that American women exhibit a marked preference for dating taller men, and that for shorter men to be judged attractive by women, they must earn substantially more money than taller men.&lt;ref&gt;"Ariely found that a 5'4" man would need to make $229,000 more than a 6' man to have equal appeal; a 5'6" man would need $183,000 more; a 5'10" man would need $32,000 more." Lori Gottlieb (2010). ''Marry Him: The Case for Settling for Mr. Good Enough''. Penguin, ISBN 9781101185209 p. 239&lt;/ref&gt;

In the article "Is Lookism Unjust", Louis Tietje and Steven Cresap discuss when discrimination based on looks can legitimately be described as unjust.&lt;ref name = "xxx"&gt;Louis Tietje and Steven Cresap. (2005). "[http://www.mises.org/journals/jls/19_2/19_2_2.pdf Is Lookism Unjust?: The Ethics of Aesthetics and Public Policy Implications]". ''[[Journal of Libertarian Studies]]'' 19 (2): 31-50.&lt;/ref&gt;  Tietje and Cresap quote evidence that suggests there exists "a 7–to–9 percent 'penalty' for being in the lowest 9 percent of looks among all workers, and a 5 percent 'premium' for being in the top 33 percent". While accepting that the evidence indicates that such discrimination does occur, the authors argue that it has been pervasive throughout history. Therefore there can be no clear model of injustice in such discrimination, nor would legislation to address it be practicable. The authors conclude: "We do not see how any policy interventions to redress beauty discrimination can be justified."&lt;ref name = "xxx"/&gt;

==Political lookism==
Lookism has been an issue in politics for centuries, with a long tradition in the United Kingdom of "mercilessly exaggerat[ing]" the physical flaws of politicians in newspaper cartoons.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Johnathan (2012). "[http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2012/jan/10/too-ugly-for-politics-ed-miliband Can you be too ugly for politics?]", ''The Guardian'' 10 January 2012; accessed 19 October 2013&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[United_States_presidential_election,_1960#Debates|1960 Presidential race between John F. Kennedy and Richard Nixon]], it was often believed that Kennedy's more conventionally handsome appearance contributed to his winning more approval in their first televised debate,&lt;ref name="museum.tv"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.museum.tv/eotvsection.php?entrycode=kennedy-nixon |title=THE KENNEDY-NIXON PRESIDENTIAL DEBATES, 1960 – The Museum of Broadcast Communications |publisher=The Museum of Broadcast Communications (MBC) |date= |accessdate=2010-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; but some researchers have challenged this widespread idea and argued that Kennedy's appearance had little or no influence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/10510978709368226 |title=The myth of viewer‐listener disagreement in the first Kennedy‐Nixon debate|publisher=The Central States Speech Journal  |year= 1987 |accessdate=August 7, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

There are several variables that might contribute to the objectification of masculinity and femininity in politics. Scholar Charlotte Hooper argued that “gender intersects with other social divisions such as class, race and sexuality to produce complex hierarchies of (gendered) identities[.]”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hooper|first=Charlotte|title=Masculinities, IR and the ‘gender variable’: a cost-benefit analysis for (sympathetic) gender sceptics|journal=Review Of International Studies|year=1999|volume=25|pages=475–480|accessdate=September 23, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Hooper argues that institutional practices, such as military combat in war, have greatly defined what it means to be a man. Furthermore, the symbolic dimension, which includes sports, media, current affairs, etc. has “disseminate[d] a wealth of popular iconography which links Western masculinities to the wider world beyond the boarders of the state.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hooper|first=Charlotte|title=Masculinities, IR and the ‘gender variable’: a cost-benefit analysis for (sympathetic) gender sceptics|journal=Review of International Studies|year=1999|volume=25|pages=475–580|accessdate=September 23, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is where the ideology of lookism is firmly entrenched. according to Hooper. Similarly, Laura Shepherd suggests that men are required to fit into the “matrix of intelligibility”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Shepherd|first=Laura J.|title=Sex or Gender? Bodies in World Politics and Why Gender Matters|year=2010|publisher=Routledge|location=New York|chapter=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; by acting a certain way, dressing a certain way, and have a mentality that is devoid of emotion or anything effeminate; if they are successful in becoming the ultimate “man’s man” then they are virtually untouchable. However, others have suggested that there is only an explicit interest in the analysis of masculinity within this political sphere, it will be impossible to develop a reliable analysis of femininity within this same sphere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Enloe|first=Cynthia|title=‘Gender’ is not enough: the need for a feminist consciousness|journal=International Affiars|page=97|accessdate=September 23, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some{{who?|date=October 2013}} argue lookism affects women in an even more detrimental way than men. Drawing examples from [[Madeline Albright]]’s TED talk in 2010, “On Being a Woman and Diplomat”, Albright expressed her frustrations with how her male colleagues and media commentators would pick apart her appearance. Being the first female Secretary of State for the United States, Albright was in the spotlight on the domestic and international stage; everything from her age, weight, hairstyle and choice of dress were scrutinize;, yet ironically, the policy positions she believed to be her most important accomplishments (initiation of the G7, attempts to promote gender equality, etc.) were hardly taken into account.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Albright|first=Madeleine|title=On Being a Woman and a Diplomat|url=http://www.ted.com/talks/madeleine_albright_on_being_a_woman_and_a_diplomat.html|work=TED Talk|publisher=TEDwomen}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fact that Albright’s general appearance didn't fit into the narrow category of “attractive” made it even more difficult for her to navigate the space between being a woman and a diplomat. Albright is not the only woman in a position of power, or otherwise, that has been discriminated against because of her appearance. An article published in ''The Washington Pos''t in 2005 labeled Secretary of State, [[Condoleezza Rice]], as a “[[dominatrix]]” when she stepped out in thigh-high black-heeled boots during a visit to Wiesbaden Military Base in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Givhan|first=Robin|title=Condoleezza Rice's Commanding Clothes|accessdate=September 23, 2013|newspaper=The Washington Post|date=February 25, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the article was meant to give credit to Rice for “challeng[ing] expectations and assumptions”,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gavhin|first=Robin|title=Condoleezza Rice's Commanding Clothes|accessdate=September 23, 2013|newspaper=The Washington Post|date=February 25, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; some{{who?|date=October 2013}} argue that the article gave her a hyper-sexualized image, and further removed the audience from focusing on the purpose of her visit to the military place. Similarly, media commentators have often chosen to report on Hillary Clinton’s “man suits” and Julia Gillard’s short hairstyle, instead of focusing on these women’s professional accomplishments.{{cn|date=October 2013}} Sarah Palin, former governor of Alaska and 2008 Republican Vice-Presidential candidate, was the subject of much media attention due to her conventionally attractive appearance,&lt;ref&gt;Frick, Ali (2008). [http://thinkprogress.org/politics/2008/09/05/28702/cnbc-host-praises-palin-for-putting-a-skirt-on-i-want-her-laying-next-to-me-in-bed/ CNBC host praises Palin for ‘putting a skirt on’: ‘I want her laying next to me in bed.’], accessed 19 October 2013&lt;/ref&gt; with Palin suggesting that the focus on her appearance ignored her professional and policy accomplishments.&lt;ref&gt;Orr, Jimmy (2009). [http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/Politics/The-Vote/2009/1117/is-sarah-palin-newsweek-cover-sexist-palin-says-yesIs Sarah Palin Newsweek cover sexist? Palin says yes], accessed 19 October 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

==Law==
===United States===
Until the 1970s, lookism in the [[United States]] was sometimes codified into law. In many jurisdictions, so-called "[[ugly law]]s" barred people from appearing in public if they had diseases or disfigurements that were considered unsightly.&lt;ref name="brown"&gt;Brown, Patricia Leigh. "Viewing Ahab and Barbie Through the Lens of Disability." New York Times (August 20, 2000) as quoted by http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-29736932_ITM&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-29736932_ITM Begging the question: disability, mendicancy, speech and the law.(Viewpoint essay), 01-JAN-07, Schweik, Susan, Ohio State University Press]&lt;/ref&gt; Today, the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] considers extreme [[obesity]] to be a [[disability]] protected by the [[Americans with Disabilities Act]], and a few cities protect against discrimination based on appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gomez|first=Evangeline|url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/evangelinegomez/2012/01/31/should-businesses-worry-about-appearance-based-discrimination-in-the-workplace/|title=Should Businesses Worry About Appearance-Based Discrimination in the Workplace?|accessdate=27 February 2013|date=31 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Otherwise, there is no federal law protecting against discrimination based on physical appearance.

==See also==
[[File:Het leelijke jonge eendje.jpg|thumb|right|200px|''[[The Ugly Duckling]]'', book illustration by [[Theo van Hoytema]]]]
{{columns-list|2|
* [[Attributional ambiguity]]
* [[Colorism]]
* [[Egalitarianism]]
* [[Erotic capital]]
* [[Fat acceptance movement]]
* [[Halo effect]]
* [[Human physical appearance]]
* [[Physical attractiveness]]
* [[Sexual field]]
* [[Sexual objectification]]
* [[Sexual selection]]
* [[Social stigma]]
* [[Stigma (sociological theory)]]
* [[Ugliness]]
* [[Ugly law]]
}}

==References==
{{reflist}}
Albright, Madeleine. "On being a woman and a diplomat." TEDWomen Recorded December 2010. TED Talk February 2011. Web, http://www.ted.com/talks/madeleine_albright_on_being_a_woman_and_a_diplomat.html

Enloe, Cynthia. "‘Gender’ is not enough: the need for a feminist consciousness." International Affairs.: 97.

Givhan, Robin. "Condoleezza Rice's Commanding Clothes." The Washington Post, sec. Fashion and Beauty, February 25, 2005. http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A51640-2005Feb24.html (accessed September 23, 2013).

Hooper, Charlotte. "Masculinities, IR and the ‘gender variable’: a cost-benefit analysis for (sympathetic) gender sceptics." Review of International Studies. (1999): 475-480.

Shepherd, Laura J. Sex or Gender? Bodies in World Politics and Why Gender Matters. New York: Routlege, 2010.

==External links==
* [http://www.lookism.info lookism.info] — [[German language|German]] site on lookism, with English translations
* [http://abcnews.go.com/2020/story?id=123853&amp;page=4 abcnews.go.com], "The Ugly Truth About Beauty" - article on lookism

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]
[[Category:Human appearance]]
[[Category:Aesthetics]]
[[Category:Postmodern theory]]
[[Category:Political correctness]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>