<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20120923184246|514199859" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="36283978" pageid="36283978" ns="0" title="Lookism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-09-23T18:43:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Lookism''' is a term used to refer to the positive [[stereotype]]s, [[prejudice]], and preferential treatment given to physically attractive people, or more generally to people whose appearance matches cultural preferences. The pejorative term '''body fascism''' is also used as a synonym.&lt;ref name=Jodi"&gt;O'Brien, Jodi (2008). ''Encyclopedia of Gender and Society, Volume 1.'' SAGE, ISBN 9781412909167&lt;/ref&gt; [[Physical attractiveness]] is associated with good things, such as beautiful princesses, and physically unattractiveness is associated with negative things, such as wicked witches. Based on physical appearance, many people make automatic judgments of others that influence how they respond to those people.

Research on the "What is beautiful is good" stereotype shows that, overall, those who are physically attractive benefit from their good looks. Researchers found that physically attractive individuals are perceived more positively and that physical attractiveness has a strong influence on judgements of a person’s competence.&lt;ref name="Eagly et al., 1991)."&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Eagly | first1 = Alice| last2 = Ashmore | first2 = Richard | year = 1991 | title = What is beautiful is good, but... | journal = Psychological Bulletin| volume = 110 | pages = 109–128}}&lt;/ref&gt; In return, physically attractive people benefit from these stereotypical beliefs. Research shows that on average, physically attractive individuals have more friends, better social skills, and more active sex lives. However, attractiveness does not have any effect on the level of happiness experienced by the individual.&lt;ref name="Rhodes, Simmons, &amp; Peters, 2005)."&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Rhodes | first1 =  Gillian last2 = Simmons | first2 = Leigh | last3= Peters | first3= Marianne | year = 2005 | title = Attractiveness and Sexual Behavior: Does Attractiveness Enhance Mating Success?| journal = Evolution and Human Behavior| volume = 26 | pages = 186–201}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Who is considered physically attractive?==
In [[United States culture]], many cannot define what attractiveness is, but they know it when they see it.{{cite}} A 2001 study suggested that infants seem to have high agreement about which shapes are more attractive than others.&lt;ref name="Game, Carchon, &amp; Vital-Durand,(2003)."&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Game | first1 = Florence| last2 = Carchon | first2 = Isabelle | last3 = Vital-Durand | first3 = Francois | year = 2003 | title = The effect of stimulus attractiveness on visual tracking in 2- to 6-month-old infants. | journal = Infant Behavior and Development | volume = 26 | pages = 135–150}}&lt;/ref&gt; This shows that judgements on attractiveness are not entirely influenced by culture. On average, smooth-skinned, [[Neoteny|youthful]], [[symmetrical]] faces are seen as more attractive. Those with [[muscular]] body types are seen as more attractive, healthy, and adventuresome. [[Overweight]] individuals are often stereotypically categorized as unattractive. Although there has been little research on the topic, taller people seem to benefit more from their stature and are more likely to get dates, be hired, and be seen as competent and powerful. A study by Timothy Judge and Daniel Cable (2004) showed that individuals who are 72 in. tall are predicted to earn almost $166,000 more across a 30 year career than an individual who is 65 in. tall.{{cite}}

==History==
The term was first coined within the [[Fat acceptance movement]]. It was used in the ''[[The Washington Post]]'' Magazine in 1978, which asserted that the term was coined by "fat people" who created the word to refer to "discrimination based on looks."&lt;ref&gt;John Ayto, ''20th Century Words'', Oxford: [[Oxford University Press]], 1999. ISBN 978-0-19-860230-9&lt;/ref&gt; The word appears in several major English language dictionaries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com Bartleby.com] — "[http://www.bartleby.com/61/64/L0246450.html Lookism]". ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition.'' 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Lookism has received scholarly attention both from a [[cultural studies]] and an [[economics]] perspective. In the former context, lookism relates to preconceived notions of [[beauty]] and cultural [[stereotyping]] based on appearance as well as [[gender role]]s and expectations. Important economic considerations include the question of income gaps based on looks, as well as increased or decreased productivity from workers considered beautiful or ugly by their co-workers.

Some writers have examined body fascism among [[gay men]]. Author [[Michelangelo Signorile]] described it as "the setting of a rigid set of standards of physical beauty that pressures everyone within a particular group to conform to them. Any person who doesn't meet those very specific standards is deemed physically unattractive and sexually undesirable. In a culture in which the physical body is held in such high esteem and given such power, body fascism then not only deems those who don't or can't conform to be be sexually less desirable, but in extreme sometimes dubbed lookism also deems a person completely worthless ''as a person'', based solely on his exterior. In this sense it is not unlike racism or sexism, or homophobia itself."&lt;ref name="Morrison"&gt;Morrison, Todd Eclectic Views on Gay Male Pornography: Pornucopia, Volume 47, Psychology Press,  ISBN 9781560232919&lt;/ref&gt;

==Empirical support==
According to [[Nancy Etcoff]], a psychologist at [[Massachusetts General Hospital]], "we face a world where lookism is one of the most pervasive but denied prejudices."&lt;ref&gt;[[William Safire]]. [http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/27/magazine/the-way-we-live-now-8-27-00-on-language-lookism.html "The Way We Live Now: 8-27-00: On Language; Lookism"], ''[[New York Times Magazine]]'', August 27, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Referring to several studies, Angela Stalcup writes that "The evidence clearly indicates that not only is there a premium for prettiness in Western culture, there is also penalty for plainness."&lt;ref&gt;Angela Stalcup. [http://angelastalcup.com/sample_article.pdf ''The Plainness Penalty: Lookism in Western Culture''.]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the article "Is Lookism Unjust", Louis Tietje and Steven Cresap discuss when discrimination based on looks can legitimately be described as unjust.&lt;ref name = "xxx"&gt;Louis Tietje and Steven Cresap. (2005). "[http://www.mises.org/journals/jls/19_2/19_2_2.pdf Is Lookism Unjust?: The Ethics of Aesthetics and Public Policy Implications]". ''[[Journal of Libertarian Studies]]'' 19 (2): 31-50.&lt;/ref&gt;  Tietje and Cresap quote evidence that suggests there exists "a 7–to–9 percent 'penalty' for being in the lowest 9 percent of looks among all workers, and a 5 percent 'premium' for being in the top 33 percent". While accepting that the evidence indicates that such discrimination does occur, the authors argue that it has been pervasive throughout history. Therefore there can be no clear model of injustice in such discrimination, nor would legislation to address it be practicable. The authors conclude: "We do not see how any policy interventions to redress beauty discrimination can be justified."&lt;ref name = "xxx"/&gt;

==See also==
[[File:Het leelijke jonge eendje.jpg|thumb|right|200px|''[[The Ugly Duckling]]'', book illustration by [[Theo van Hoytema]].]]
*[[Attributional ambiguity]]
* [[Egalitarianism]]
* [[Erotic capital]]
* [[Fat acceptance movement]]
* [[Halo effect]]
* [[Human physical appearance]]
* [[Physical attractiveness]]
* [[Sexual field]]
* [[Sexual objectification]]
* [[Sexual selection]]
* [[Social stigma]]
* [[Stigma (sociological theory)]]
* [[Ugliness]]
* [[Ugly law]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.lookism.info lookism.info] — [[German language|German]] site on lookism, with English translations
* [http://abcnews.go.com/2020/story?id=123853&amp;page=4 abcnews.go.com], "The Ugly Truth About Beauty" - article on lookism

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]
[[Category:Human appearance]]
[[Category:Aesthetics]]

[[da:Lookism]]
[[de:Lookism]]
[[lt:Atrakcionizmas]]
[[pl:Atrakcjonizm]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>