<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111104231502|459053877" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="36283978" pageid="36283978" ns="0" title="Lookism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-10T05:51:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}} 
'''Lookism''' is a term used to refer to [[discrimination]] against or prejudice towards others based on their appearance. The term was first coined within the [[Fat acceptance movement]]. It was used in the ''[[The Washington Post]]'' Magazine in 1978, which asserted that the term was coined by "fat people" who created the word to refer to "discrimination based on looks."&lt;ref&gt;John Ayto, ''20th Century Words'', Oxford: [[Oxford University Press]], 1999. ISBN 978-0198602309&lt;/ref&gt; The word appears in several major English language dictionaries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com Bartleby.com] — "[http://www.bartleby.com/61/64/L0246450.html Lookism]". ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition.'' 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Lookism has received scholarly attention both from a [[cultural studies]] and an [[economics]] perspective. In the former context, lookism relates to preconceived notions of [[beauty]] and cultural [[stereotyping]] based on appearance as well as [[gender role]]s and expectations. Important economic considerations include the question of income gaps based on looks, as well as increased or decreased productivity from workers considered beautiful or ugly by their co-workers.

According to [[Nancy Etcoff]], a psychologist at [[Massachusetts General Hospital]], "we face a world where lookism is one of the most pervasive but denied prejudices."&lt;ref&gt;[[William Safire]]. [http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/27/magazine/the-way-we-live-now-8-27-00-on-language-lookism.html "The Way We Live Now: 8-27-00: On Language; Lookism"], ''[[New York Times Magazine]]'', August 27, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Referring to several studies, Angela Stalcup writes that "The evidence clearly indicates that not only is there a premium for prettiness in Western culture, there is also penalty for plainness."&lt;ref&gt;Angela Stalcup. [http://angelastalcup.com/sample_article.pdf ''The Plainness Penalty: Lookism in Western Culture''.]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the article "Is Lookism Unjust", Louis Tietje and Steven Cresap discuss when discrimination based on looks can legitimately be described as unjust.&lt;ref name = "xxx"&gt;Louis Tietje and Steven Cresap. (2005). "[http://www.mises.org/journals/jls/19_2/19_2_2.pdf Is Lookism Unjust?: The Ethics of Aesthetics and Public Policy Implications]". ''[[Journal of Libertarian Studies]]'' 19 (2): 31-50.&lt;/ref&gt;  Tietje and Cresap quote evidence that suggests there exists "a 7–to–9 percent 'penalty' for being in the lowest 9 percent of looks among all workers, and a 5 percent 'premium' for being in the top 33 percent". While accepting that the evidence indicates that such discrimination does occur, the authors argue that it has been pervasive throughout history. Therefore there can be no clear model of injustice in such discrimination, nor would legislation to address it be practicable. The authors conclude: "We do not see how any policy interventions to redress beauty discrimination can be justified."&lt;ref name = "xxx"/&gt;

==See also==
[[File:Het leelijke jonge eendje.jpg|thumb|right|200px|''[[The Ugly Duckling]]'', book illustration by [[Theo van Hoytema]].]]
*[[Egalitarianism]]
*[[Erotic capital]]
*[[Fat acceptance movement]]
*[[Human physical appearance]]
*[[Physical attractiveness]]
*[[Sexual field]]
*[[Sexual objectification]]
*[[Sexual selection]]
*[[Social stigma]]
*[[Stigma (sociological theory)]]
*[[Ugliness]]
*[[Ugly law]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.lookism.info lookism.info] — [[German language|German]] site on lookism, with English translations
*[http://abcnews.go.com/2020/story?id=123853&amp;page=4 abcnews.go.com], "The Ugly Truth About Beauty" - article on lookism

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]
[[Category:Human appearance]]
[[Category:Aesthetics]]

{{socio-stub}}

[[da:Lookism]]
[[de:Lookism]]
[[lt:Atrakcionizmas]]
[[pl:Atrakcjonizm]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>