<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20060904115314|73742327" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="39426115" pageid="39426115" ns="0" title="Gender pay gap"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-24T22:13:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''[[Income]] disparity''' or '''wage gap''' is a term used to describe inequities in average pay or salary between [[socio-economic]] groups within society, or the inequities in pay between individuals who produce the same work.  Income disparity generally occurs when certain groups within society suffer from [[social inequality]] within a society.

Common examples include: 
*lower average income for females than males (see [[#Gender gap|Gender gap]] below)
*Income discrepancy between minority ethnic groups and the majority.
*The income gap between the wealthy and the poor.

==Gender gap==
In the context of economic inequality, gender gap generally refers to the systemic differences in the [[social]] and [[economic]] roles of [[men]] and [[women]], or [[boys]] and [[girls]]. There is a debate to what extent this is the result of [[gender differences]], lifestyle choices, or because of [[discrimination]].

The widespread mechanization of industry has been accompanied by a shift in gender differentials in highly industrialized countries. However, this closing of the gender gap has not necessarily been followed in less industrialized countries, where women may earn less than two thirds that of men.&lt;ref name="Sethuraman"&gt;[http://www.wiego.org/papers/sethexec.html Gender, Informality and Poverty: A Global Review] S.V. Sethuraman, WIEGO, October 1998&lt;/ref&gt;

A United Nations report found that women working in manufacturing earned the following percentages in relation to men in 2003:.&lt;ref name="unstats"&gt;[http://unstats.un.org/unsd/demographic/products/indwm/ww2005/tab5g.htm Statistics and indicators on women and men: Table 5g Women's wages relative to men's]  United Nations Statistics Division, 22 April 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

* Botswana: 53%
* Columbia: 65%
* Paraguay: 53%
* Japan: 60%
* Singapore: 61%
* Sri Lanka: 81%
* Denmark: 87%
* France: 78%
* Germany: 74%
* Hungary: 74%
* Ireland: 69%
* Latvia: 82%
* Lithuania: 77%
* Malta: 92%
* Sweden: 91%
* Ukraine: 69%
* United Kingdom: 79%
* New Zealand: 80%

In 2004, women's wages in the USA were 76.5% of men's wages. [http://www.iwpr.org/pdf/WageRatioPress_release8-27-04.pdf This number compares the income off all men and women who work 35 hours or more each week.] However, some studies, such as those done by the [[Independent Women's Forum]], conclude that when taking into account variables when comparing male and female employment within the United States - type of job, hours worked in a week, tenure, benefits (for example maternity leave) - women make 98% of men's income. For further information, see [[Male-female income disparity in the USA ]].

According to the Centre for Economic Performance (CEP) at the [[London School of Economics]], it would take 150 years for the income gap between the two genders to close up due to discrimination and ineffective government policies.&lt;ref name="150 years"&gt; {{cite web |url=http://www.expressindia.com/fullstory.php?newsid=71698|title="Women have to wait 150 yrs for equal pay: Study"|publisher=[[The Indian Express]]|accessdate=2006-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Income disparity in Malaysia==
[[Image:IDMchart0001.jpg|thumb|220px|Chart of Malaysia's Income disparity.]]
According to the UNDP 1997 Human Development Report,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aseanfocus.com/asiananalysis/article.cfm?articleID=35 Asian Analysis 1998 by Asean Focus Group], Professor Michael Leigh
Director Institute of East Asian Studies University Malaysia, Sarawak.&lt;/ref&gt; and the 2004 [[United Nations]] [[Human Development]] (UNHDP) report,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dapmalaysia.org/english/2005/july05/lge/lge149.htm Speech at the Meeting between DAPSY National and Perak State Leaders In Teluk Intan by Lim Guan Eng], If the 2004 [[Petronas]] profits of RM 35.6 billion (US$9.89 billion) were distributed to the poor, Malaysia would not have wealth distribution problems.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Malaysia]] has the highest income disparity between the rich and poor in [[Southeast Asia]], greater than that of [[Philippines]], [[Thailand]], [[Singapore]], [[Vietnam]] and [[Indonesia]]. The UNHDP Report shows that the richest 10% in Malaysia control 38.4% of the economic income as compared to the poorest 10% who control only 1.7%. [[Kuala Lumpur]] as the capital of Malaysia has an increasing number of [[squatters]], [[shanty towns]] and [[slums]], and is also seeing an increase in criminal acts such as [[snatch theft]], [[robberies]], and [[rape]].

==See also==
*[[Economic inequality]]
*[[Income inequality metrics]]
*[[International inequality]]
*[[Male-female income disparity in the USA ]]

==Notes==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
*[http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=wage+gap&amp;search_crit=title&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form Read Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding Gender Wage Gaps]


[[Category:Labor]]
[[Category:Income distribution]]
[[Category:Employment compensation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>