<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171103004927|808463774" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="39426115" pageid="39426115" ns="0" title="Gender pay gap"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-20T11:26:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expanded=Policies}}
The '''gender pay gap''' is the average difference between a man's and a woman's [[remuneration]]. 

There are two distinct numbers regarding the pay gap: ''unadjusted'' versus ''adjusted'' pay gap which takes into account differences in hours worked, occupations chosen, education and job experience. 
For example, someone who takes time off (e.g. [[maternity leave]]) will likely not earn as much as someone who does not take time off from work. Factors like this contribute to lower yearly earnings for women, but even with all external factors have been adjusted for, a gender pay gap generally still exists.&lt;ref name="Blau"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Pew"/&gt;&lt;ref name="EC stats"/&gt;  ''Unadjusted'' pay gaps are much higher. In the United States, for example the unadjusted ''average'' female's  annual salary has commonly been cited as being 78% of the ''average'' male salary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://money.cnn.com/2015/04/13/news/economy/equal-pay-day-2015/ | title=78 cents on the dollar: The facts about the gender wage gap | work=CNN Money | date=April 14, 2015 | accessdate=May 28, 2015 | author=O'Brien, Sara Ashley | location=New York | quote=7% wage gap between male and female college grads a year after graduation even controlling for college major, occupation, age, geographical region and hours worked. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[World Economic Forum]] provides recent data from 2015 that evaluates the gender pay gap in 145 countries. Their evaluations take into account economic participation and opportunity, [[educational attainment]], health and survival, and [[political empowerment]] scores.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Schwab, Klaus|displayauthors=etal|title=The Global Gender Gap Report 2015|publisher=World Economic Forum|year=2015|pp=8–9|url=http://www3.weforum.org/docs/GGGR2015/cover.pdf|accessdate=29 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Over time==
A wide-ranging [[meta-analysis]] by Doris Weichselbaumer and [[Rudolf Winter-Ebmer]] (2005) of more than 260 published adjusted pay gap studies for over 60 countries has found that, from the 1960s to the 1990s, raw wage differentials worldwide have fallen substantially from around 65 to 30%. The bulk of this decline, however, was due to better labor market endowments of women. The 260 published estimates show that the unexplained component of the gap has not declined over time. Using their own specifications, Weichselbaumer and Winter-Ebmer found that the yearly overall decline of the gender pay gap would amount to a slow 0.17 log points, implying a slow level of convergence between the wages of men and women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Weichselbaumer | first1 = Doris | last2 = Winter-Ebmer | first2 = Rudolf | year = 2005 | title = A Meta-Analysis on the International Gender Wage Gap | url = http://www.econ.jku.at/papers/2003/wp0311.pdf | format = PDF | journal = Journal of Economic Surveys | volume = 19 | issue = 3| pages = 479–511 | doi = 10.1111/j.0950-0804.2005.00256.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another meta-analysis of 41 empirical studies on the wage gap performed in 1998 found a similar time trend in estimated pay gaps, a decrease of roughly 1% per year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Stanley|first1=T. D.|last2=Jarrell|first2=Stephen B.|title=Gender Wage Discrimination Bias? A Meta-Regression Analysis|journal=The Journal of Human Resources|date=1998|volume=33|issue=4|page=962|doi=10.2307/146404|jstor=146404}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to economist [[Alan Manning]] of the [[London School of Economics]], the process of closing the gender pay gap has slowed substantially and women could earn less than men for the next 150 years because of discrimination and ineffective government policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Manning | first1 = Alan | year = 2006 | title = The gender pay gap | url = http://cep.lse.ac.uk/pubs/download/CP200.pdf| journal = CentrePiece | publisher = Centre for Economic Performance | volume = 11 | issue = 1| pages = 13–16 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Woolcock, Nicola. [http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article693783.ece ''Women will earn the same as men – if they wait 150 years''.] [[The Sunday Times]], July 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; A 2011 study by the British [[Chartered Management Institute|CMI]] revealed that if pay growth continues for female executives at current rates, the gap between the earnings of female and male executives would not be closed until 2109.&lt;ref name="guardian equal pay cmi report"&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.theguardian.com/society/2011/aug/31/cmi-equal-pay-report | title=Women executives could wait 98 years for equal pay, says report | work=[[The Guardian]] | date=2011-08-31 | accessdate=August 31, 2011 | author=Goodley, Simon | location=London | quote=While the salaries of female executives are increasing faster than those of their male counterparts, it will take until 2109 to close the gap if pay grows at current rates, the Chartered Management Institute reveals.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women [[Chief Financial Officers]] (CFOs) are paid 16% lower on average as compared to their male counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Chase |first=Max |url=http://www.cfo-insight.com/corporate-strategy/corporate-strategy/female-cfos-may-be-best-remedy-against-discrimination/ |title=Female CFOs May Be Best Remedy Against Discrimination - CFO Insight |publisher=Cfo-insight.com |accessdate=2014-03-12 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130209181502/http://www.cfo-insight.com/corporate-strategy/corporate-strategy/female-cfos-may-be-best-remedy-against-discrimination/ |archivedate=2013-02-09 |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==By country==
===List by OECD 2015===
[[File:OECD gender wage gap.svg|thumb|400px|The gender gap in median earnings of full-time employees according to the [[OECD]] 2015.&lt;ref&gt;[[OECD]]. [http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/54/57/40846335.pdf ''OECD Employment Outlook 2008 – Statistical Annex''] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081206000000/http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/54/57/40846335.pdf |date=December 6, 2008 }}. OECD, Paris, 2008, p. 358.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

{| class="wikitable sortable"
! Country !! Gender gap !! Year
|-
| Australia || 15.38 || 2014
|-
| Austria || 17.73 || 2014
|-
| Belgium || 5.91 || 2013
|-
| Canada || 18.63 || 2015
|-
| Chile || 16.67 || 2013
|-
| Czech Republic || 16.46 || 2013
|-
| Denmark || 6.77 || 2013
|-
| Estonia || 26.60 || 2010
|-
| Finland || 19.61 || 2014
|-
| France || 13.67 || 2012
|-
| Germany || 17.08 || 2014
|-
| Greece || 9.09 || 2014
|-
| Hungary || 9.52 || 2015
|-
| Iceland || 13.59 || 2014
|-
| Ireland || 15.17 || 2014
|-
| Israel || 21.83 || 2011
|-
| Italy || 5.56 || 2014
|-
| Japan || 25.87 || 2014
|-
| Korea || 36.65 || 2014
|-
| Latvia || 13.33 || 2010
|-
| Lithuania || 6.96 || 2010
|-
| Luxembourg || 4.97 || 2010
|-
| Mexico || 16.67 || 2015
|-
| Netherlands || 18.60 || 2010
|-
| New Zealand || 6.08 || 2014
|-
| Norway || 7.12 || 2015
|-
| Poland || 11.07 || 2014
|-
| Portugal || 18.88 || 2014
|-
| Slovakia || 13.38 || 2015
|-
| Slovenia || 11.63 || 2010
|-
| Spain || 8.65 || 2012
|-
| Sweden || 13.42 || 2013
|-
| Switzerland || 14.50 || 2014
|-
| Turkey || 20.06 || 2010
|-
| United Kingdom || 16.93 || 2015
|-
| United States || 18.88 || 2015
|}

=== Australia ===
{{main article|Gender pay gap in Australia}}
In Australia, the gender pay gap is calculated on the average weekly ordinary time earnings for full-time employees published by the [[Australian Bureau of Statistics]]. The gender pay gap excludes part-time, casual earnings and overtime payments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=[[Department of Commerce (Western Australia)|Department of Commerce]]|url=http://www.commerce.wa.gov.au/labourrelations/Content/Work%20Life%20Balance/Pay%20Equity/FAQ_Pay_equity.html|title=Frequently asked questions about pay equity|accessdate=May 6, 2011|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110422155711/http://www.commerce.wa.gov.au/LabourRelations/Content/Work%20Life%20Balance/Pay%20Equity/FAQ_Pay_equity.html|archivedate=April 22, 2011|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia has a persistent gender pay gap. Between 1990 and 2009, the gender pay gap remained within a narrow range of between 15 and 17%.&lt;ref name="natsem"&gt;{{citation|author=National Centre for Social and Economic Modelling|url=http://www.actu.org.au/Images/Dynamic/attachments/6895/NATSEM_report.pdf|title=The impact of a sustained gender wage gap on the economy|journal=Report to the Office for Women, Department of Families, Community Services, Housing and Indigenous Affairs|year=2009|pages=v–vi|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101201110158/http://www.actu.org.au/Images/Dynamic/attachments/6895/NATSEM_report.pdf|archivedate=December 1, 2010|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2010, the Australian gender pay gap was 16.9%.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|author=Equal Opportunity for Women in the Workplace Agency|url=http://www.eowa.gov.au/Pay_Equity/Files/PE_STATS.pdf|title=Pay Equity Statistics|publisher=Australian Government|year=2010|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110217234222/http://www.eowa.gov.au/Pay_Equity/Files/PE_STATS.pdf|archivedate=February 17, 2011|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ian Watson of [[Macquarie University]] examined the gender pay gap among full-time managers in Australia over the period 2001–2008, and found that between 65 and 90% of this earnings differential could not be explained by a large range of demographic and labor market variables. In fact, a "major part of the earnings gap is simply due to women managers being female". Watson also notes that despite the "characteristics of male and female managers being remarkably similar, their earnings are very different, suggesting that discrimination plays an important role in this outcome".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Ian|last=Watson|year=2010|url=http://www.business.curtin.edu.au/files/295watson1.pdf|title=Decomposing the Gender Pay Gap in the Australian Managerial Labour Market|publisher=Macquarie University|journal=Australian Journal of Labour Economics|volume=13|number=1|pages=49–79|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110306114914/http://www.business.curtin.edu.au/files/295watson1.pdf|archivedate=March 6, 2011|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2009 report to the [[Department of Families, Housing, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs]] also found that "simply being a woman is the major contributing factor to the gap in Australia, accounting for 60 per cent of the difference between women's and men's earnings, a finding which reflects other Australian research in this area". The second most important factor in explaining the pay gap was industrial segregation.&lt;ref name="natsem" /&gt; A report by the World Bank also found that women in Australia who worked part-time jobs and were married came from households which had a gendered distribution of labor, possessed high job satisfaction, and hence were not motivated to increase their working hours.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://elibrary.worldbank.org/doi/abs/10.1596/9780821388105_ch5|title=Gender Differences in Employment and Why They Matter|date=2011-09-12|publisher=The World Bank|isbn=9780821388105|series=World Development Report|pages=198–253|doi=10.1596/9780821388105_ch5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
A study of wages among Canadian [[Supply chain management|supply chain managers]] found that men make an average of $14,296 a year more than women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Larson|first1=Paul D.|last2=Morris|first2=Matthew|title=Sex and salary: Does size matter? (A survey of supply chain managers)|journal=Supply Chain Management: an International Journal|date=2014|volume=19|issue=4|pages=385–394|doi=10.1108/SCM-08-2013-0268}}&lt;/ref&gt; The research suggests that as supply chain managers move up the corporate ladder, they are less likely to be female.

Each [[Provinces and territories of Canada|province and territory]] in Canada has a [[quasi-constitutional]] human rights code which prohibits discrimination based on sex. Several also have laws specifically prohibiting [[public sector]] and [[private sector]] employers from paying men and women differing amounts for substantially similar work. Verbatim, the Alberta Human Rights Act states in regards to equal pay, "Where employees of both sexes perform the same or substantially similar work for an employer in an establishment the employer shall pay the employees at the same rate of pay."&lt;ref&gt;For example, ''Alberta Human Rights Act'', RSA 2000, c A-25.5 at §6 in [[Alberta]] and ''Pay Equity Act'', RSO 1990, c P.7 in [[Ontario]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===China===
Using the gaps between men and women in economic participation and opportunity, educational attainment, health and survival, and political empowerment, ''The Global Gender Gap Report 2015'' ranks China's gender gap at 91 out of 145 countries (the lower the ranking, the narrower the gender gap), which is four rankings below 2014's global index. China's 2015 gender gap score was 0.681 (1.00 being equality). As an upper middle income country, as classified by the World Bank, China is the "third-least improved country in the world" on the gender gap. The health and survival subindex is the lowest within the countries listed; this subindex takes into account the gender differences of life expectancy and sex ratio at birth (the ratio of male to female children to depict the preferences of sons in accordance with China's [[One Child Policy]]).&lt;ref name="Schwab2015"/&gt;{{rp|4,26}} In particular, Jayoung Yoon claims the women's employment rate is decreasing. However, several of the contributing factors might be expected to increase women's participation. Yoon's contributing factors include: the traditional gender roles; the lack of childcare services provided by the state; the obstacle of childrearing; and the highly educated, unmarried women termed "leftover women" by the state. The term "leftover women" produces anxieties for women to rush marriage, delaying employment. In alignment with the traditional gender roles, the "Women Return to the Home" movement by the government encouraged women to leave their jobs to alleviate the men's unemployment rate.&lt;ref name=Yoon2015&gt;Yoon, Jayoung. "Labor Market Outcomes for Women in East Asia." ''Asian Journal of Women's Studies'', vol. 21, no. 4, 2015, pp. 384-408.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dominican Republic===
Dominican women, who are 52.2% of the [[labor force]], earns an average of 20,479 [[Dominican peso]]s, 2.6% more than Dominican men's average income of 19,961 pesos.&lt;ref name="ForbesMX"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Jorge Mateo |first1=Manauri |title=La banca aprovecha que en Dominicana hay más mujeres que hombres |url=https://www.forbes.com.mx/la-banca-aprovecha-que-en-dominicana-hay-mas-mujeres-que-hombres/ |website=Forbes México |accessdate=9 July 2016 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160709043200/http://www.forbes.com.mx/la-banca-aprovecha-que-en-dominicana-hay-mas-mujeres-que-hombres/ |archivedate=9 July 2016 |language=Spanish |date=6 July 2016 |deadurl=yes |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Global Gender Gap ranking, found by compiling economic participation and opportunity, educational attainment, health and survival, and political empowerment scores, in 2009 was 67th out of 134 countries representing 90% of the globe, and its ranking has dropped to 86th out of 145 countries in 2015. More women are in ministerial offices, improving the political empowerment score, but women aren't receiving equal pay for similar jobs, preserving the low economic participation and opportunity scores.&lt;ref name="Hausmann2009"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=Gk1oecRaQc8C&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PP8&amp;dq=gender+pay+gap+dominican+republic&amp;ots=sHWzOwp6kz&amp;sig=iuIlDU-ZUMWvcly8yUcgIfyl72c#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=The Global Gender Gap Report 2009|date=2009-01-01|publisher=World Economic Forum|isbn=9789295044289|author1=Hausmann, Ricardo|author2= Lauren D. Tyson|author3=Saadia Zahidi}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Schwab2015"&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www3.weforum.org/docs/GGGR2015/cover.pdf|title=The Global Gender Gap Report 2015|last=Schwab|first=Klaus|last2=Samans|first2=Richard|last3=Zahidi|first3=Saadia|last4=Bekhouche|first4=Yasmina|last5=Ugarte|first5=Paulina Padilla|last6=Ratcheva|first6=Vesselina|last7=Hausmann|first7=Ricardo|last8=Tyson|first8=Laura D'Andrea|publisher=World Economic Forum|year=2015|isbn=|location=|pages=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|15–17, 23}}

===European Union===
[[File:EU 27 Gender Pay Gap 2014.png|thumb|Gender gap in average gross hourly earnings according to [[Eurostat]] 2014.&lt;ref name="EC stats" /&gt;]]

At [[European Union|EU]] level, the gender pay gap is defined as the relative difference in the average gross hourly earnings of women and men within the economy as a whole. [[Eurostat]] found a persisting gender pay gap of 17.5% on average in the 27 [[Member state of the European Union|EU Member States]] in 2008.{{citation needed|date=September 2017}} There were considerable differences between the Member States, with the unadjusted pay gap ranging from less than 10% in Italy, Slovenia, Malta, Romania, Belgium, Portugal, and Poland to more than 20% in Slovakia, the Netherlands, Czech Republic, Cyprus, Germany, United Kingdom, and Greece and more than 25% in Estonia and Austria.&lt;ref name="EC stats"&gt;[[European Commission]]. [http://ec.europa.eu/justice/gender-equality/gender-pay-gap/situation-europe/index_en.htm ''The situation in the EU''.] Retrieved on July 12, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; However, taking into account the hours worked in Finland, men there only earned 0.4% more in net income than women.&lt;ref name="Nupponen"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Nupponen|first1=Sakari|title=Miehet painavat töitä niska limassa – naiset eivät|url=http://www.taloussanomat.fi/tyo-ja-koulutus/2010/04/07/miehet-painavat-toita-niska-limassa-naiset-eivat/20104864/139|website=taloussanomat.fi|publisher=Taloussanomat|accessdate=28 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Tilastokeskus"&gt;{{cite web|title=Tehtyjen työtuntien määrä on laskenut tasaisesti vuosina 1995-2005|url=http://tilastokeskus.fi/til/atutyo/2005/atutyo_2005_2007-09-21_tie_001.html|website=tilastokeskus.fi|publisher=Tilastokeskus|accessdate=28 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A recent survey of international employment law firms showed that gender pay gap reporting is not a common policy internationally. Despite such laws on a national level being few and far between, there are calls for regulation on an EU level. A recent (as of December 2015) resolution of the European Parliament urged the Commission to table legislation closing the pay gap. A proposal that is substantively the same as the UK plan was passed by 344 votes to 156 in the European Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/news-room/20151002IPR95366/pay-gap-between-men-and-women-meps-call-for-binding-measures-to-close-it|title=Pay gap between men and women: MEPs call for binding measures to close it {{!}} News {{!}} European Parliament|website=News {{!}} European Parliament|language=en|access-date=2017-02-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The European Commission has stated that the undervaluation of female work is one of the main contributors to the persisting gender pay gap.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Wo liegen die Ursachen? - Europäische Kommission|url = http://ec.europa.eu/justice/gender-equality/gender-pay-gap/causes/index_de.htm|website = ec.europa.eu|access-date = 2012-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Germany ====
Women earned 22–23% less than men, according to the [[Federal Statistical Office of Germany]]. The revised gender pay gap was 6–8% in the years 2006–2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Pressemitteilungen - Gender Pay Gap 2013 bei Vollzeitbeschäftigten besonders hoch - Statistisches Bundesamt (Destatis)|url = https://www.destatis.de/DE/PresseService/Presse/Pressemitteilungen/2014/03/PD14_104_621.html|website = Federal Statistical Office of German|access-date = 2016-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Institut der deutschen Wirtschaft|Cologne Institute for Economic Research]] adjusted the wage gap to less than 2%. They reduced the gender pay gap from 25% to 11% by taking in account the work hours, education and the period of employment. The difference in revenue was reduced furthermore if women hadn't paused their job for more than 18 months due to motherhood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Beschäftigungsperspektiven von Frauen - Nur 2 Prozent Gehaltsunterschied|url = http://www.iwkoeln.de/presse/pressemitteilungen/beitrag/beschaeftigungsperspektiven-von-frauen-nur-2-prozent-gehaltsunterschied-102500|website = German Institute for Economic Research|access-date = 2016-02-18|language = de}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title = Gender Pay Gap: Wie groß ist der Unterschied wirklich?|url = http://www.zeit.de/karriere/beruf/2013-03/lohnunterschied-geschlechter-statistik|newspaper = Die Zeit|access-date = 2016-02-18|issn = 0044-2070}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The most significant factors associated with the remaining gender pay gap are part-time work, education and occupational segregation (less women in leading positions and in fields like [[STEM]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title = Studie: Geschlecht senkt Gehalt um sieben Prozent|url = http://www.zeit.de/karriere/2013-03/gehalt-studie-frauen-maenner|newspaper = Die Zeit|access-date = 2016-02-18|issn = 0044-2070}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Netherlands ====
In the Netherlands, recent numbers from the CBS (Centraal Bureau voor statistieken; ''English: Central Bureau of Statistics'') claim that the pay gap is getting smaller. Adjusted for occupation level, education level, experience level and 17 other variables the difference in earnings in businesses has fallen from 9% (2008) to 7% (2014) and in government from 7% (2008) to 5% (2014). Without adjustments the gap is for businesses 20% (2014) and government 10% (2014). Young women actually earn more than men up until the age of 30, this is mostly due to a higher level of education. Women in the Netherlands, up until the age of 30, have a higher educational level on average than men; after this age men have on average a higher educational degree. The chance can also be caused by women getting pregnant and start taking part-time jobs so they can care for the children.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cbs.nl/nl-nl/nieuws/2016/47/krijgen-mannen-en-vrouwen-gelijk-loon-voor-gelijk-werk-|title=Krijgen mannen en vrouwen gelijk loon voor gelijk werk?|last=CBS|website=www.cbs.nl|language=nl-NL|access-date=2016-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== United Kingdom ====
In the United Kingdom, the aggregate gender pay gap has been on the decline, and even reversed for certain age groups. According to data from the Office for National Statistics, women aged 22–29 earned ₤1,111 more per year than men of the same age (between 2006 and 2013).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/money/2015/aug/29/women-in-20s-earn-more-men-same-age-study-finds|title=Women in their 20s earn more than men of same age, study finds|date=28 August 2015|work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2012, the gap officially dropped below 10% for full-time workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/money/2012/nov/22/gender-pay-gap-falls-full-time-workers|title=Gender pay gap falls for full-time workers|date=November 22, 2012|work=The Guardian|author=King, Mark|accessdate=December 19, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/rel/ashe/annual-survey-of-hours-and-earnings/2012-provisional-results/stb-ashe-statistical-bulletin-2012.html|title=Annual Survey of Hours and Earnings, 2012 Provisional Results|date=22 November 2012|work=Office for National Statistics}}&lt;/ref&gt; The aggregate gender pay gap can also be viewed as a generational sliding scale. Females between the ages of 55–65 have the largest disparity (18%), while females between the ages of 25–35 have the smallest disparity (6%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bls.gov/opub/reports/cps/highlights-of-womens-earnings-in-2013.pdf#8|title=Highlights of women's earnings in 2013|date=December 2014|publisher=U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics|format=PDF|work=BLS Reports}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the UK, the most significant factors associated with the remaining gender pay gap are part-time work, education, the size of the firm a person is employed in, and occupational segregation (women are under-represented in managerial and high-paying professional occupations).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Thomson|first=Victoria|date=October 2006|title=How Much of the Remaining Gender Pay Gap is the Result of Discrimination, and How Much is Due to Individual Choices?|url=http://www.ijull.co.uk/vol7/2/thomson.pdf|journal=International Journal of Urban Labour and Leisure|volume=7|issue=2|accessdate=September 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; When comparing full-time roles, men in the UK tend to work longer hours than women in full-time employment. Depending on the age bracket and percentile of hours worked men in full-time employment work between 1.35% and 17.94% more hours than women in full-time employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/publications/re-reference-tables.html?edition=tcm%3A77-328216|title=Annual Survey of Hours and Earnings, 2013 Provisional Results|publisher=Ons.gov.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt; When comparing part-time roles women out-earn men by 6.5% in 2015 (up from 5.5% in 2014).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Annual Survey of Hours and Earnings: 2015 Provisional Results|url=http://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/earningsandworkinghours/bulletins/annualsurveyofhoursandearnings/2015provisionalresults#gender-pay-differences|publisher=Office of National Statistics}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2014, the [[Equality Act 2010]] was augmented with regulations which require [[Employment Tribunal]]s to order an employer (except an existing [[Micro-enterprise|micro-business]] or a new business) to carry out an equal pay audit where the employer is found to have breached equal pay law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2014/2559/contents/made|title=The Equality Act 2010 (Equal Pay Audits) Regulations 2014|website=www.legislation.gov.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2015 study compiled by the Press Association based on data from the Office for National Statistics revealed that women in their 20s were out-earning men in their 20s by an average of £1,111, suggesting a reversal of trends. However, the same study showed that men in their 30s out-earned women in their 30s by an average of £8775. The study did not attempt to explain the causes of the gender gap.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/money/2015/aug/29/women-in-20s-earn-more-men-same-age-study-finds|title=Women in their 20s earn more than men of same age, study finds|date=29 August 2015|work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Update inline|date=April 2016}}

In April 2018 employers with over 250 employees will be required to publish data relating to pay inequalities. Data published is to include the pay and bonus figures between men and women, and will include data from April 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.paydata.co.uk/knowledge-hub/paynotes-gender-pay-reporting-%E2%80%93-what-employers-need-know|title=PAYnotes on Gender Pay Reporting – What employers need to know|date=February 26, 2016|work=Paydata Ltd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== India ===
{{main article|Gender pay gap in India}}
For the year 2013, the gender pay gap in [[India]] was estimated to be 24.81%.&lt;ref name="wageindicator"&gt;{{cite web|title=Gender Pay Gap in the Formal Sector: 2006 - 2013(September, 2013)|url=http://www.wageindicator.org/documents/publicationslist/publications-2013/gender-pay-gap-in-formal-sector-in-india-2006-2013|publisher=Wage Indicator Data Report}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further, while analyzing the level of female participation in the economy, a report slots India as one of the bottom 10 countries on its list. Thus, in addition to unequal pay, there is also unequal representation, because while women constitute almost half the Indian population (about 48% of the total), their representation in the work force amounts to only about one-fourth of the total.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Eleventh Five Year Plan (2007-2012) Planning Commission, Government of India|url=http://planningcommission.nic.in/plans/planrel/11thf.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===
Jayoung Yoon analyzes Japan's culture of the traditional male breadwinner model, where the husband works outside of the house while the wife is the caretaker. Despite these traditional gender roles for women, Japan's government aims to enhance the economy by improving the labor policies for mothers with Abenomix (2013), an economy revitalization strategy. Yoon believes Abenomix represents a desire to remedy the effects of an aging population rather than a desire to promote gender equality. Evidence for the conclusion is the finding that women are entering the workforce in contingent positions for a secondary income and a company need of part-time workers based on mechanizing, outsourcing and subcontracting. Therefore, Yoon states that women's participation rates do not seem to be influenced by government policies but by companies' necessities.&lt;ref name=Yoon2015 /&gt; ''The Global Gender Gap Report 2015'' established that Japan's economic participation and opportunity ranking (106th), 145th being the broadest gender gap, dropped from 2014 "due to lower wage equality for similar work and fewer female legislators, senior officials and managers".&lt;ref name="Schwab2015"/&gt;{{rp|25–27}}

===Jordan===
From a total of 145 states, the World Economic Forum calculates Jordan's gender gap ranking for 2015 as 140th through economic participation and opportunity, educational attainment, health and survival, and political empowerment evaluations. Jordan is the "world's second-least improved country" for the overall gender gap.&lt;ref name="Schwab2015"/&gt;{{rp|25–27}} The ranking dropped from 93rd in 2006.&lt;ref name="Hausmann2009"/&gt;{{rp|9}} In contradiction to Jordan's provisions within its constitution and being signatory to multiple conventions for improving the gender pay gap, there is no legislation aimed at gender equality in the workforce.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Alfarhan, Usamah F.|title=Gender Earnings Discrimination in Jordan: Good Intentions Are Not Enough|journal=International Labour Review|volume=154|issue=4|year=2015|pp= 563–580|doi=10.1111/j.1564-913X.2015.00252.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''The Global Gender Gap Report 2015'', Jordan had a score of 0.61, 1.00 being equality, on pay equality for like jobs.&lt;ref name="Schwab2015"/&gt;{{rp|25, 222}}

===Korea===
As stated by Jayoung Yoon, [[South Korea]]'s female employment rate has increased since the 1997 Asian Financial Crisis as a result of women 25 to 34 years old leaving the workforce later to become pregnant and women 45 to 49 years old returning to the workforce. Mothers are more likely to continue working after child rearing on account of the availability of affordable childcare services provided for mothers previously in the workforce or the difficulty to be rehired after taking time off to raise their children.&lt;ref name=Yoon2015 /&gt; The World Economic Forum found that, in 2015, South Korea had a score of 0.55, 1.00 being equality, for pay equality for like jobs. From a total of 145 countries, South Korea had a gender gap ranking of 115th (the lower the ranking, the narrower the gender gap). On the other hand, political empowerment dropped to half of the percentage of women in the government in 2014.&lt;ref name="Schwab2015"/&gt;{{rp|26, 228}}

[[North Korea]], on the other hand, is one of few countries where women earn more than men. The disparity is due to women's greater participation in the [[shadow economy of North Korea]].&lt;ref name="theg_Life"&gt;{{Cite web | title = Life in North Korea - the adult years | author = Fyodor Tertitskiy | work = the Guardian | date = 23 December 2015 | accessdate = 2017-04-13 | url = https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/dec/23/life-in-north-korea-the-adult-years }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== New Zealand ===
{{main article|Gender pay gap in New Zealand}}
{{Empty section|date=June 2016}}

=== Russia ===
{{main article|Gender pay gap in Russia}}
A wage gap exists in [[Russia]] (after 1991, but also before) and [[Statistics|statistical analysis]] shows that most of it cannot be explained by lower qualifications of women compared to men. On the other hand, [[occupational segregation]] by gender and [[Sexism|labor market discrimination]] seem to account for a large share of it.&lt;ref name=Newell2001&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1016/S0939-3625(01)00028-0| title = The Gender Pay Gap in the Transition from Communism: Some Empirical Evidence| journal = Economic Systems| volume = 25| issue = 4| pages = 287–304| year = 2001| last1 = Newell | first1 = A. | last2 = Reilly | first2 = B. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=globulin&gt;Ogloblin, C. G. (1999) "The Gender Earnings Differential in the Russian Transition Economy. ''Industrial and Labor Relations'' 52(4): 602-634.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Katz&gt;Katz, K. (2001) ''Gender, Work and Wages in the Soviet Union. A Legacy of Discrimination''. Palgrave. {{ISBN|978-0-333-73414-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=GerryLiKim268&gt;Gerry, C. J., Kim, B. and C. A. Li (2004) "The gender wage gap and wage arrears in Russia Evidence from RLMS". Journal of Population Economics 17:267-288. (p. 268).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hansbery&gt;{{cite paper |last=Hansberry |first=R. |year=2004 |title=An Analysis of Gender Wage Differentials in Russia from 1996–2002 |work=William Davidson Institute. Working Paper Number 720 |ssrn=615801 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kazakova&gt;Kazakova, E. "Wages in a Growing Russia. When is a 10 percent rise in the gender wage gap good news?". ''Economics of Transition'', Vol. 15 (2):365-592.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[October Revolution]] (1917) and the [[dissolution of the Soviet Union]] in 1991 have shaped the developments in the gender wage gap. These two main turning points in the [[History of Russia|Russian history]] frame the analysis of Russia's gender pay gap found in the economic literature. Consequently, the pay gap study can be examined for two periods: the wage gap in [[Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic|Soviet Russia]] (1917–1991), and the wage gap in the transition and post-transition (after 1991).

===Singapore===
According to Jayoung Yoon, Singapore's aging population and low fertility rates are resulting in more women joining the labor force in response to the government's desire to improve the economy. The government provides tax relief to mothers in the workforce to encourage them to continue working. Yoon states that "as female employment increases, the gender gap in employment rates…narrows down" in Singapore.&lt;ref name=Yoon2015 /&gt; As a matter of fact, ''The Global Gender Gap Report 2015'' ranks Singapore's gender gap at 54th out of 145 states globally based on the economic participation and opportunity, the educational attainment, the health and survival, and the political empowerment subindexes (a lower rank means a smaller gender gap). The gender gap narrowed from 2014's ranking of 59. In the Asia and Pacific region, Singapore has evolved the most in the economic participation and opportunity subindex, yet it is lower than the region's means in educational attainment and political empowerment.&lt;ref name="Schwab2015"/&gt;{{rp|25–27}}


===United States===
{{Refimprove science|section|date=May 2017}}
{{main article|Gender pay gap in the United States}}
{{See also|United States women|Equal Pay Act of 1963}}

[[File:US womens earnings as a percentage of mens 1979-2005.svg|thumb|right|Women's weekly earnings as a percent of men's by age, annual averages, 1979-2005&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Women’s earnings as a percentage of men’s, 1979-2005 : The Economics Daily : U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics|url=https://www.bls.gov/opub/ted/2006/oct/wk1/art02.htm|publisher=U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics|accessdate=22 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Looking at the gender pay gap over time, the [[United States Congress Joint Economic Committee]] showed that, as explained inequities decrease, the unexplained pay gap remains unchanged.&lt;ref&gt;[[United States Congress Joint Economic Committee]]. [http://jec.senate.gov/public/index.cfm?p=Earnings&amp;ContentRecord_id=db19df76-9299-4b46-a98c-ef33c21dab3d&amp;ContentType_id=2206321f-9e59-4f98-b972-d78c64abf642&amp;Group_id=51e071bd-07e9-46f2-bb70-cfc28baec8be ''Graph: Federal Workforce – Gender Pay Gap Unchanged''.] Retrieved on March 31, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, according to economists [[Francine D. Blau|Francine Blau]] and [[Lawrence Kahn]] and their research into the gender pay gap in the United States, a steady convergence between the wages of women and men is not automatic. They argue that after a considerable rise in women's wages during the 1980s, the gain decreased in the 1990s, which was due mainly to a much faster decline in the "unexplained" part of the gap during the 1980s than in the 1990s. They also contend that the slowing of this decline may have been caused by multiple factors, including "changes in labor force selectivity, changes in gender differences in unmeasured characteristics and in labor market discrimination, and changes in the favorableness of demand shifts".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Blau|first1=F. D.|last2=Kahn|first2=L. M.|title=The U.S. Gender Pay Gap in the 1990S: Slowing Convergence|journal=ILR Review|date=1 October 2006|volume=60|issue=1|pages=45–66|doi=10.1177/001979390606000103}}&lt;/ref&gt; A mixed picture of increase and decline characterizes the 2000s. Thus Blau and Kahn assume: &lt;blockquote&gt; With the evidence suggesting that convergence has slowed in recent years, the possibility arises that the narrowing of the gender pay gap will not continue into the future. Moreover, there is evidence that although discrimination against women in the labor market has declined, some discrimination does still continue to exist.&lt;ref name="Blau"&gt;{{cite journal|title=The Gender Pay Gap – Have Women Gone as Far as They Can?|url=https://web.stanford.edu/group/scspi/_media/pdf/key_issues/gender_research.pdf|format=PDF|journal=Academy of Management Perspectives|publisher=Stanford University|volume=21|pages=7–23|doi=10.5465/AMP.2007.24286161|author1=Francine D. Blau|author2=Lawrence M. Kahn|number=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the United States, the gender pay gap is measured as the ratio of female to male median yearly earnings among full-time, year-round (FTYR) workers. The female-to-male earnings ratio was 0.77 in 2012, meaning that, in 2012, female FTYR workers earned 77% as much as male FTYR workers.&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Census Bureau. ''[http://www.census.gov/prod/2013pubs/p60-245.pdf Income, Poverty, and Health Insurance Coverage in the United States: 2012.]'' Current Population Reports, P60–245, U.S. Government Printing Office, Washington, DC, 2013, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; Women's median yearly earnings relative to men's rose rapidly from 1980 to 1990 (from 60.2% to 71.6%), and less rapidly from 1990 to 2000 (from 71.6% to 73.7%) and from 2000 to 2009 (from 73.7% to 77.0%).&lt;ref name="census 2009"&gt;U.S. Census Bureau. [http://www.census.gov/prod/2010pubs/p60-238.pdf ''Income, Poverty, and Health Insurance Coverage in the United States: 2009.''] Current Population Reports, P60–238, U.S. Government Printing Office, Washington, DC, 2010, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Institute for Women's Policy Research. [http://www.iwpr.org/publications/pubs/the-gender-wage-gap-2009 ''The Gender Wage Gap: 2009''.] Retrieved March 31, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  More recent statistics show in 2014 that women's median pay has increased to 79 cents, according to the Institute for Women's Policy Research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iwpr.org/initiatives/pay-equity-and-discrimination|title=Pay Equity &amp; Discrimination|publisher=Institute for Women's Policy Research }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The raw wage gap data shows that a woman would earn roughly 73.7% to 77% of what a man would earn over their lifetime.  More precisely, data from the Bureau of Labor Statistics indicates the median earnings of female workers working full-time to be roughly 77% of the median earnings of their male counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/karinagness/2016/04/12/dont-buy-into-the-gender-pay-gap-myth/#5e089d2b4766|title=Don't Buy Into The Gender Pay Gap Myth|last=Agness|first=Karin|newspaper=Forbes|access-date=2017-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, when controllable variables are accounted for, such as job position, total hours worked, number of children, and the frequency at which unpaid leave is taken, in addition to other factors, a United States Department of Labor study, conducted by the CONSAD Research Group, found in 2008 that the gap can be brought down from 23% to between 4.8% and 7.1%.  Noting that the raw wage gap is the result of a number of factors, the report said that the raw gap should not be used to justify corrective action, adding that "Indeed, there may be nothing to correct. The differences in raw wages may be almost entirely the result of the individual choices being made by both male and female workers."&lt;ref name="consad.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.consad.com/content/reports/Gender%20Wage%20Gap%20Final%20Report.pdf |title=An Analysis of Reasons for the Disparity in Wages Between Men and Women |publisher=Consad.com |accessdate=2014-03-12 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131008051216/http://www.consad.com/content/reports/Gender%20Wage%20Gap%20Final%20Report.pdf |archivedate=October 8, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The gender pay gap has been attributed to differences in personal and workplace characteristics between women and men (education, hours worked, occupation, etc.) as well as direct and indirect discrimination in the labor market (gender stereotypes, customer and employer bias etc.).&lt;ref name="Kanter2008"&gt;{{cite book|last=Kanter|first=Rosabeth Moss |title=Men and Women of the Corporation|date=4 August 2008|publisher=PublicAffairs|isbn=978-0-7867-2384-3|authorlink=Rosabeth Moss Kanter}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="clinton4.nara.gov"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://clinton4.nara.gov/WH/EOP/CEA/html/gendergap.html#disc|title=Gender Wage Gap|website=clinton4.nara.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="policyalmanac.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.policyalmanac.org/economic/archive/pay_equity.pdf|title=Levine, Report for Congress, "The Gender Gap and Pay Equity: Is Comparable Worth the Next Step?", Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress, 2003|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The estimates for the discriminatory component of the gender pay gap include 5%&lt;ref name="justicetalking"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.justicetalking.org/ShowPage.aspx?ShowID=604|date=2007-05-28|accessdate=2012-03-13|title=Justice Talking: The Women's Equality Amendment / What Does It Mean and Is It Necessary?}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|2}} and 7%&lt;ref name="jec"&gt;[[United States Congress Joint Economic Committee]]. [http://jec.senate.gov/public/?a=Files.Serve&amp;File_id=9118a9ef-0771-4777-9c1f-8232fe70a45c ''Invest in Women, Invest in America: A Comprehensive Review of Women in the U.S. Economy.''] Washington, DC, December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|9}} for federal jobs, and a study showed that these grow as men and women's careers progress.&lt;ref name="jec" /&gt;{{rp|93}}  One economist testified to Congress that hundreds of studies have consistently found unexplained pay differences which potentially include discrimination.&lt;ref name="jec" /&gt;{{rp|80}}  Another criticized these studies as insufficiently controlled, and said that men and women would have equal pay if they made the same choices and had the same experience, education, etc.&lt;ref name="justicetalking" /&gt;{{rp||3}}

Other studies have found direct evidence of discrimination in recruitment.&lt;ref name="Correll" /&gt;
A 2007 study showed a substantial bias against women with children.&lt;ref name="Correll"&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Getting a Job: Is There a Motherhood Penalty?|author1=Shelley J. Correll |author2=Stephen Benard |author3=In Paik |work= American Journal of Sociology|volume=112|issue=5date=March 2007|pages=1297–1339|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|jstor=10.1086/511799}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Another study showed more jobs for women when orchestras moved to blind auditions.&lt;ref name="Goldin"&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://scholar.harvard.edu/files/goldin/files/orchestrating_impartiality_the_effect_of_blind_auditions_on_female_musicians.pdf|first=Goldin C|last=Rouse|date=2000|title=Orchestrating impartiality: The impact of blind auditions on female musicians.|work=The American Economic Review 90(4)|pages=715-41.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One study found that female applicants were favored; however, its results have been met with skepticism from other researchers, since it contradicts most other studies on the issue. Joan C. Williams, a distinguished professor at the University of California's Hastings College of Law, raised issues with its methodology, pointing out that the fictional female candidates it used were unusually well-qualified. Studies using more moderately-qualified graduate students have found that male students are much more likely to be hired, offered better salaries, and offered mentorship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.pnas.org/content/112/17/5360.abstract|title=National hiring experiments reveal 2:1 faculty preference for women on STEM tenure track|author=Wendy M. Williams|accessdate=14 June 2015|doi=10.1073/pnas.1418878112|volume=112|journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences|pages=5360–5365}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/morning-mix/wp/2015/04/14/study-finds-surprisingly-that-women-are-favored-for-jobs-in-stem/|title=Study finds, surprisingly, that women are favored for jobs in STEM|author=Sarah Kaplan|date=14 April 2015|work=Washington Post|accessdate=14 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact==

===Pensions===
The [[European Commission]] argues that the gender pay gap has far-reaching effects, especially in regard to pensions. Since women's earnings over a lifetime are on average 17.5% (as of 2008) lower than men's, these lower earnings result in lower pensions. As a result, elderly women are more likely to face poverty: 22% of women aged 65 and over are at risk of poverty compared to 16% of men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=European Commission|author-link=European Commission|url=http://ec.europa.eu/news/employment/110304_en.htm |title=Closing the gender pay gap|date=March 4, 2011|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110306180420/http://ec.europa.eu/news/employment/110304_en.htm|archivedate=March 6, 2011 |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Economy===
A 2009 report for the Australian [[Department of Families, Housing, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs]] argued that in addition to fairness and equity there are also strong economic imperatives for addressing the gender wage gap.  The researchers estimated that a decrease in the gender wage gap from 17% to 16% would increase GDP per capita by approximately $260, mostly from an increase in the hours females would work. Ignoring opposing factors as hours females work increase, eliminating the whole gender wage gap from 17% could be worth around $93 billion or 8.5% of GDP. The researchers estimated the causes of the wage gap as follows, lack of work experience was 7%, lack of formal training was 5%, [[occupational segregation]] was 25%, working at smaller firms was 3%, and being female represented the remaining 60%.&lt;ref name="natsem"/&gt;

An October 2012 study by the [[American Association of University Women]] found that over the course of 47 years, an American woman with a college degree will make about $1.2 million less than a man with the same education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aauw.org/what-we-do/public-policy/aauw-issues/gender-pay-gap/|title=Women in their 20s earn more than men of same age, study finds|work=American Association of University Women}}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, closing the pay gap by raising women's wages would have a stimulus effect that would grow the United States economy by at least 3% to 4%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Christianne Corbett|author2=Catherine Hill|date=October 2012|url=http://www.aauw.org/files/2013/02/graduating-to-a-pay-gap-the-earnings-of-women-and-men-one-year-after-college-graduation.pdf|title=Graduating to a Pay Gap: The Earnings of Women and Men One Year after College Graduation|location=Washington, DC|publisher=American Association of University Women}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=April 2016}}  By increasing women's workplace participation from its present rate of 76% to 84%, as it is in Sweden, the US could add 5.1 million women to the workforce, again, 3% to 4% of the size of the United States economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|first=Laura|last=Bassett|date=October 24, 2012|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/10/24/gender-wage-gap-economic-stimulus_n_2007588.html|title=Closing The Gender Wage Gap Would Create 'Huge' Economic Stimulus, Economists Say|work=Huffington Post}}, citing [https://web.archive.org/web/20121114190344/http://www.aauw.org/GraduatetoaPayGap/upload/AAUWGraduatingtoaPayGapReport.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economic theories==

===Neoclassical models===
In certain [[neoclassical economics|neoclassical]] models, discrimination by employers can be inefficient; excluding or limiting employment of a specific group will raise the wages of groups not facing discrimination. Other firms could then gain a competitive advantage by hiring more workers from the group facing discrimination. As a result, in [[Long run and short run|the long run]] discrimination would not occur. However, this view depends heavily on strong assumptions about the labor market and the [[production function]]s of the firms attempting to discriminate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Becker|first1=Gary|title=Nobel Lecture: The Economic Way of Looking at Behavior|journal=[[Journal of Political Economy]]|date=1993|volume=101|issue=3|pages=387–389|jstor=2138769|doi=10.1086/261880}}&lt;/ref&gt; Firms which discriminate on the basis of real or perceived customer or employee preferences would also not necessarily see discrimination disappear in the long run even under stylized models.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Cain|first1=Glen G.|editor1-last=Ashenfelter|editor1-first=Orley|editor2-last=Laynard|editor2-first=R.|title=Handbook of Labor Economics: Volume I|date=1986|isbn=9780444534521|pages=710–712|chapter=The Economic Analysis of Labor Market Discrimination: A Survey}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Monopsony explanation===
In [[monopsony]] theory, [[Monopsony#Wage discrimination|wage discrimination]] can be explained by variations in labor mobility constraints between workers. Ransom and Oaxaca (2005) show that women appear to be less pay sensitive than men, and therefore employers take advantage of this and discriminate in their pay for women workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://ftp.iza.org/dp704.pdf|title = Intrafirm Mobility and Sex Differences in Pay|last = Ransom|first = Michael|date = January 2005|journal = [[Industrial and Labor Relations Review]]|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |jstor = 30038574|last2 = Oaxaca|first2 = Ronald L.|author-link2 = Ronald Oaxaca|volume = 58|issue = 2|publisher = [[Sage Publications]]|issn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effect of discrimination==
Claims that women are "less willing" and having "less ability" to negotiate salaries and battle&amp;nbsp;[[sexual discrimination]]&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=An Analysis of Reasons for the Disparity in Wages Between Men and Women|url=http://www.consad.com/content/reports/Gender%20Wage%20Gap%20Final%20Report.pdf|author=CONSAD Research Corporation|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131008051216/http://www.consad.com/content/reports/Gender%20Wage%20Gap%20Final%20Report.pdf|deadurl=yes|format=PDF|archivedate=October 8, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Pew"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2015/04/14/on-equal-pay-day-everything-you-need-to-know-about-the-gender-pay-gap/|title=On Equal Pay Day, key facts about the gender pay gap|date=April 14, 2015|author=Patten, Eileen|work=Pew Research Center}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Blau"/&gt; are often attributed to being the cause of 25% to 40% of the wage gap.

The [[European Commission]] divides discrimination, as it impacts the EU wage gap, into several categories.  While ''direct discrimination'', when a woman is paid less than a man for the same job, is relatively rare due to strong EU laws against it, a more persistent problem is the undervaluing of women's work, with women being paid less for a job of equal value due to careers dominated by women being undervalued as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Tackling the gender pay gap in the European Union|url=http://ec.europa.eu/justice/gender-equality/files/gender_pay_gap/140319_gpg_en.pdf|journal=Justice|isbn=978-92-79-36068-8|author=European Commission}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ec.europa.eu/justice/gender-equality/gender-pay-gap/causes/index_en.htm|title=What are the causes? - European Commission|website=ec.europa.eu|access-date=2016-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Indeed, studies have consistently shown that the more an occupation's workforce comes to be dominated by women, the lower its wages become, regardless of the value or importance of the work in question.&lt;ref name=Reskin&gt;{{cite journal|last=Reskin|first=Barbara F. |year=1988 |title=Bringing the men back in: Sex differentiation and the devaluation of women's work. |journal=Gender &amp; Society 2.1 |pp=58-81|url=http://www.unc.edu/~kleinman/handouts/Bringing%20the%20Men%20Back%20In.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effect of job choices==
In Canada, it is shown that women are more likely to seek employment opportunities which greatly contrast the ones of men. About 20 percent of women, between the ages of 25 and 54, will make just under $12 an hour in Canada. The demographic of women who take jobs paying less than $12 an hour is also a proportion that is twice as large as the proportion of men taking on the same type of [[McJob|low-wage work]]. There still remains the question of why such a trend seems to resonate throughout the developed world. One identified societal factor that has been identified is the influx of women of color and immigrants into the work force. These groups both tend to be subject to lower paying jobs from a statistical perspective.&lt;ref&gt;Congress, C. L. (n.d.). [http://classes.uleth.ca/200801/mgt3390a/womensequalityreportEn.pdf Women in the Workforce: Still a Long Way from Equality]. Retrieved November 23, 2012, from Canadian Labour Congress.&lt;/ref&gt; Men are more likely to be in relatively high-paying, dangerous industries such as mining, construction, or manufacturing and to be represented by a union. Women, in contrast, are more likely to be in clerical jobs and to work in the service industry. These factors explain 53% of the wage gap.&lt;ref name="Blau"/&gt; A 2017 study in the ''[[American Economic Journal|American Economic Journal: Macroeconomics]]'' found that the growing importance of the services sector has played a role in reducing the gender gap in pay and hours.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Rachel|first=Ngai, L.|last2=Barbara|first2=Petrongolo,|date=2017|title=Gender Gaps and the Rise of the Service Economy|url=https://www.aeaweb.org/atypon.php?return_path=/doi/pdfplus/10.1257/mac.20150253&amp;etoc=1|journal=American Economic Journal: Macroeconomics|language=en|volume=9|issue=4|pages=|doi=10.1257/mac.20150253&amp;etoc=1|issn=1945-7707|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1998, adjusting for both differences in human capital and in industry, occupation, and unionism increases the size of American women's average earnings from 80% of American men's to 91%.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia |year=2015 |title=Gender, Economics of |encyclopedia=International Encyclopedia of the Social &amp; Behavioral Sciences (Second Edition) |publisher=Elsevier |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/B9780080970868710518 |last=Blau |first=Francine}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effect of socialization==

Another social factor, which is related to the aforementioned one, is the socialization of individuals to adopt specific [[gender role]]s.&lt;ref name=Mooney&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Mooney Marin|first1=Margaret|last2=Fan|first2=Pi-Ling|title=The Gender Gap in Earnings at Career Entry|journal=American Sociological Review|date=1997|volume=62|issue=4|pages=589–591|jstor=2657428|doi=10.2307/2657428}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jacobs|first1=Jerry|title=Revolving Doors: Sex Segregation and Women's Careers|date=1989|publisher=[[Stanford University Press]]|isbn=9780804714891}}&lt;/ref&gt; Job choices influenced by socialization are often slotted in to "demand-side" decisions in frameworks of wage discrimination,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Reskin|first1=Barbara|title=Sex Segregation in the Workplace|journal=Annual Review of Sociology|date=1993|volume=19|page=248|jstor=2083388|doi=10.1146/annurev.soc.19.1.241}}&lt;/ref&gt; rather than a result of extant labor market discrimination influencing job choice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Macpherson|first1=David A.|last2=Hirsch|first2=Barry T.|title=Wages and Gender Composition: Why do Women's Jobs Pay Less?|journal=Journal of Labor Economics|date=1995|volume=13|issue=3|page=460|jstor=2535151|doi=10.1086/298381}}&lt;/ref&gt; Men that are in non-traditional job roles or jobs that are primarily seen as a women-focused jobs, such as nursing, have high enough job satisfaction that motivates the men to continue in these job fields despite criticism they may receive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.426.5021&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf|title=Men in non-traditional occupations: Career entry, career orientation and experience of role strain |via=citeseerx.ist.psu.edu|doi=10.1108/hrmid.2006.04414cad.007|citeseerx=10.1.1.426.5021|author=Ruth Simpson|journal=Human Resource Management International Digest|volume=14|issue=3|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, in the eyes of employees, women in middle management are perceived to lack the courage, leadership, and drive that male managers appear to have, despite female middle managers achieving results on par with their male counterparts in terms of successful projects and achieving results for their employing companies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Martell, Richard F.|displayauthors=etal|title=Sex Stereotyping In The Executive Suite: 'Much Ado About Something'|journal=Journal of Social Behavior &amp; Personality|volume=13|issue=1|year=1998|pp=127–138|}}&lt;/ref&gt; These perceptions, along with the factors previously described in the article, contribute to the difficulty of women to ascend to the executive ranks when compared to men in similar positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Frankforter, Steven A.|title=The Progression Of Women Beyond The Glass Ceiling|journal=Journal of Social Behavior &amp; Personality|volume=11|issue=5|year=1996|pp=121–132}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Effect of pop culture ==
Gender roles are a key factor in the allocation of work to female and male employees, and societal ideas of gender roles stem somewhat from media influences.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Tharenou|first=Phyllis|date=2012-10-07|title=The Work of Feminists is Not Yet Done: The Gender Pay Gap—a Stubborn Anachronism|url=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11199-012-0221-8|journal=Sex Roles|language=en|volume=68|issue=3-4|pages=198–206|doi=10.1007/s11199-012-0221-8|issn=0360-0025}}&lt;/ref&gt; Media portrays ideals of gender-specific roles off of which gender stereotypes are built.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://lib.dr.iastate.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1009&amp;context=uhuru|title=Gender Pay Gap|last=Bryant|first=Molly|date=2012|website=|publisher=Iowa State University Digital Repository|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; These stereotypes then translate to what types of work men and women can or should do.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Some common stereotypes include the ideas that managers should be males, or that pregnant women are a loss for the company after giving birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Castagnetti|first=C.|last2=Rosti|first2=L.|date=2013-09-19|title=Unfair Tournaments: Gender Stereotyping and Wage Discrimination among Italian Graduates|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/47760193_Unfair_Tournaments_Gender_Stereotyping_and_Wage_Discrimination_among_Italian_Graduates|journal=Gender &amp; Society|volume=27|issue=5|pages=630–658|doi=10.1177/0891243213490231|issn=0891-2432}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this way, gender plays a mediating role in work discrimination, and women find themselves in positions that do not allow for the same advancements as males.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

==Anti-discrimination legislation==
According to the 2008 edition of the ''Employment Outlook'' report by the [[OECD]], almost all OECD countries have established laws to combat discrimination on grounds of gender. Examples of this are the Equal Pay Act of 1963 and Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964.&lt;ref&gt;Tharenou, Phyllis (2013). The Work of Feminists is Not Yet Done: The Gender Pay Gap—a Stubborn Anachronism&lt;/ref&gt; Legal prohibition of discriminatory behavior, however, can only be effective if it is enforced. The OECD points out that: &lt;blockquote&gt;"herein lies a major problem: in all OECD countries, enforcement essentially relies on the victims' willingness to assert their claims. But many people are not even aware of their legal rights regarding discrimination in the workplace. And even if they are, proving a discrimination claim is intrinsically difficult for the claimant and legal action in courts is a costly process, whose benefits down the road are often small and uncertain. All this discourages victims from lodging complaints."&lt;ref name="oecd1"&gt;[[OECD]]. [http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/8/19/40937574.pdf ''OECD Employment Outlook – 2008 Edition Summary in English''.] OECD, Paris, 2008, p. 3–4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Moreover, although many OECD countries have put in place specialized anti-discrimination agencies, only in a few of them are these agencies effectively empowered, in the absence of individual complaints, to investigate companies, take actions against employers suspected of operating discriminatory practices, and sanction them when they find evidence of discrimination.&lt;ref name="oecd1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="oecd2"&gt;[[OECD]]. [http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/36/17/43244511.pdf ''OECD Employment Outlook. Chapter 3: The Price of Prejudice: Labour Market Discrimination on the Grounds of Gender and Ethnicity''.] OECD, Paris, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, the [[Government Accountability Office|U.S. Government Accountability Office]] (GAO) found that women in the United States, on average, earned 80% of what men earned in 2000 and workplace discrimination may be one contributing factor. In light of these findings, GAO examined the enforcement of anti-discrimination laws in the private and public sectors. In a 2008 report, GAO focused on the enforcement and outreach efforts of the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] (EEOC) and the [[United States Department of Labor|Department of Labor]] (Labor). GAO found that EEOC does not fully monitor gender pay enforcement efforts and that Labor does not monitor enforcement trends and performance outcomes regarding gender pay or other specific areas of discrimination. GAO came to the conclusion that "federal agencies should better monitor their performance in enforcing anti-discrimination laws."&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Government Accountability Office. [http://www.gao.gov/products/GAO-08-799 ''Women's Earnings: Federal Agencies Should Better Monitor Their Performance in Enforcing Anti-Discrimination Laws''.] Retrieved on April 1, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Government Accountability Office. [http://www.gao.gov/new.items/d08799.pdf Report ''Women's Earnings: Federal Agencies Should Better Monitor Their Performance in Enforcing Anti-Discrimination Laws''.]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, the EEOC proposed a rule to submit more information on employee wages by gender to better monitor and combat gender discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;"Written Testimony of Jocelyn C. Frye Senior Fellow, Center for American Progress." 2016, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Economic inequality]]
* [[Equal Pay Day]]
* [[Equal pay for equal work]]
* [[Feminization of poverty]]
* [[Gender inequality]]
* [[Glass ceiling]]
* [[Global Gender Gap Report]]
* [[Income inequality metrics]]
* [[International inequality]]
* [[Lowell Mill Girls]]
* [[Material feminism]]
* [[Motherhood penalty]]

;For other wage gaps
* [[Racial wage gap in the United States]]
* [[Gay wage gap]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php/Gender_pay_gap_statistics ''Gender pay gap statistics''] by [[Eurostat]] of the [[European Commission]]
* [https://www.ofgel.com/index.html UK Gender Salary Comparisons for Graduates 6 months after leaving University. (Based on over 650,000 students)]
* [https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Rebecca_Blank/publication/223877364_Race_and_Gender_in_the_Labor_Market/links/5735f06e08ae9ace840ae9f9.pdf Race and gender in the labor market] Joseph G. Altonji and Rebecca M. Blank. Handbook of labor economics 3 (1999): 3143-3259.

{{Gender equality}}
{{Employment}}

[[Category:Income distribution]]
[[Category:Equal pay for equal work]]
[[Category:Economic inequality]]
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Feminist economics]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Misogyny]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>