<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20210915023026|1044405756" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="39264181" pageid="39264181" ns="0" title="Discrimination based on hair texture"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-09T03:28:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Discrimination based on hair texture''' is a form of [[Social justice|social injustice]], found worldwide. Afro-textured hair has frequently been seen as being unprofessional, unattractive, and unclean. {{Citation needed|date=February 2021|reason=Unsupported inflammatory statement}}

==History==
In the [[Western world]], afro-textured hair has historically been treated with disdain, by members of all ethnicities. In the 15th and 16th centuries, the [[Atlantic slave trade]] saw Black Africans forcibly transported from [[Sub-Saharan Africa]] to [[North America]] and, upon their arrival in the [[New World]], their heads would be shaved in effort to erase their culture, as many Africans used hairstyles to signify their tribal identity, marital status, age, and other personal characteristics.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://blackthen.com/you-cant-take-our-crowns-the-impact-of-slavery-on-black-womens-hair/|title=You Can't Take Our Crowns: The Impact Of Slavery On Black Women's Hair {{!}} Black Then|website=blackthen.com|language=en-US|access-date=2018-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Early on, both men and women would wear [[Headscarf|headscarves]] in order to protect their scalps from [[sunburn]] and [[Louse|lice]] but, as time progressed, these hair wraps became more associated with women, who began to wear them in various fashions, based on their region and personal style. In the 19th century, when slaves were no longer being imported from Africa, quality of life increased for them somewhat as they became more valuable in their owners' eyes. Now enjoying Sundays off, Black women would take the day to style their hair, uncovering it for church services but keeping it wrapped Monday through Saturday. As traditional styling tools weren't available to them, Black women began to use butter, kerosene, and bacon grease and combs meant for livestock to style their hair.

The concept of [[good hair]] arose in the time leading up to the [[Abolition of slavery in the USA|abolition of slavery in the United States]]. Slaves who worked in the home did not wear headscarves as field laborers did and, as they were often children of a white man in the family that owned them, they were more likely to have straight hair than kinky or curly.{{citation needed |date=August 2021}} To straighten their hair, Black women would often use a mixture of [[lye]], which could burn their skin. In [[New Orleans|New Orleans, Louisiana]], in the 18th century, Black and [[Louisiana Creole people|Louisiana Creole]] women were required by law to wear a [[tignon]], to cover their hair, and, in an act of resistance, did so but adorned their wraps with fine fabrics and jewelry.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://broadly.vice.com/en_us/article/j5abvx/black-womens-hair-illegal-tignon-laws-new-orleans-louisiana|title=When black Women Were Required By Law to Cover Their Hair|date=2018-04-10|work=Broadly|access-date=2018-11-29|language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Madam C. J. Walker]], an African American businesswoman, achieved great fortune and recognition for widening the teeth of the hot comb, which would straighten afro-textured hair.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.womenshistory.org/education-resources/biographies/madam-cj-walker|title=Madam C.J. Walker|website=DEV: National Women's History Museum|language=en|access-date=2018-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= https://www.naturalhair-products.com/black-hair-media.html |title= History Of Natural Hair }} Monday, July 20, 2020 &lt;/ref&gt;

==Discrimination by country==
===Dominican Republic===
In the [[Dominican Republic]] hair is seen as an important attribute of physical beauty. Many view straight hair as beautiful and appropriate for a professional setting while also seeing [[afro-textured hair]] as inappropriate and distracting. This mindset had stemmed from [[racial discrimination]]. This has changed over the years in the United States and abroad as the American [[Natural hair movement|Natural Hair Movement]] gains popularity.

In the Dominican Republic [[hair straightening]] is done for the same reasons it is done in the United States and the diaspora for convenience and of course influence from western beauty standards. As Rooks (1996) affirms, "Hair in 1976 spoke to racial identity politics as well as bonding between African American women. Its style could lead to acceptance or rejection from certain groups and social classes, and its styling could provide the possibility of a career" (p.&amp;nbsp;5-6).&lt;ref name="miamiherald1"&gt;{{cite web|url = http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?cc=mfsfront;c=mfs;c=mfsfront;idno=ark5583.0022.105;rgn=main;view=text;xc=1;g=mfsg|title = Black Women and Identity: What’s hair got to do with it?|publisher = Michigan State University|date = 2008–2009 |last = Thompson|first = Cheryl|author-link=Cheryl Thompson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Straightened and more conservative styles are still the standard in the workplace, as it is in the United States and other countries with African descendants of the diaspora. The views expressed aren't exclusive to the Dominican Republic. Contrary to popular misconception many Dominican women do wear natural hair and it is becoming increasingly accepted in society.

=== Jamaica ===
In 2018, a five-year-old girl was banned from attending classes at her primary school in [[Kingston, Jamaica]], for having dreadlocks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2018/aug/28/kingston-jamaica-girl-banned-from-school-for-dreadlocks-will-return-to-class-court-rules|title=Jamaican schoolgirl banned for her dreadlocks can go to class, court rules|last=Kingston|first=Kate Chappell in|date=2018-08-28|website=the Guardian|language=en|access-date=2018-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United States ===
{{Excerpt|Discrimination based on hair texture in the United States}}

=== Canada ===
Similar to many countries around the world, Black and [[First Nations]] Canadians have experienced discrimination in educational and professional environments. One type of discrimination has been based on their hair textures and styles.  The cause of this type of discrimination is based on long standing [[Eurocentrism|Eurocentric]] views of beauty that were established during early [[colonization]]. Setting this standard was used as a tool to suppress both African&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=View of Altered Beauty: African-Caribbean Women Decolonizing Racialized Aesthetics in Toronto, Canada {{!}} Revue YOUR Review (York Online Undergraduate Research)|url=https://yourreview.journals.yorku.ca/index.php/yourreview/article/view/40352/36553|access-date=2020-10-21|website=yourreview.journals.yorku.ca}}&lt;/ref&gt; and First nations culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=‘Assault’ on residential school students' identities began the moment they stepped inside|url=https://nationalpost.com/news/canada/assault-on-residential-school-students-identities-began-the-moment-they-stepped-inside|access-date=2020-10-21|website=National Post|language=en-CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though, Canada has made a commitment to support anti-racism and reconciliation&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Office|first=Privy Council|date=2020-09-23|title=2020 Speech from the Throne|url=https://www.canada.ca/en/privy-council/campaigns/speech-throne/2020/speech-from-the-throne.html|access-date=2020-10-21|website=gcnws}}&lt;/ref&gt; there has been no specific protections put in place (such as the United States [[CROWN Act (California)|CROWN Act]]) to protect against this form of discrimination.  

In [[Canada]], there has been notable cases of discrimination that made national news sites about Black Canadian women being discriminated against at their work place, due to their hair being deemed unprofessional. In 2016, a Bi-racial woman in Scarborough, Ontario, who was working at the retail chain [[Zara (retailer)|ZARA]], was asked to remove her [[box braids]] because her hair style was unprofessional.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Zara employee humiliated after managers try to 'fix' her hair {{!}} CBC News|language=en-US|work=CBC|url=https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/toronto/ballah-zara-discrimination-hairstyle-1.3527977|access-date=2020-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In another case, an African-American woman living in [[Montreal]], Quebec, was sent home from a restaurant and denied shifts, because her hair was in [[cornrows]]. The woman gained representation through the [[Center for Research-Action on Race Relations|Centre for Research Action on Race Relations]] (CRARR), and filed a case with the [[Quebec Human Rights Commission]] based racial and gender discrimination. She won her case and was rewarded $14,500 in damages.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Young black Montrealer claims she’s losing work over her hair|url=https://globalnews.ca/news/1888024/young-black-montrealer-claims-shes-losing-work-over-her-hair/|access-date=2020-10-21|website=Global News|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Montreal woman wins case after losing job at Madisons because of her hair|url=https://globalnews.ca/news/4732671/montreal-woman-wins-case-after-losing-job-at-madisons-because-of-her-hair/|access-date=2020-10-21|website=Global News|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

First Nations people in Canada have also experienced discrimination and harm due to wearing hair styles that do not conform to [[Eurocentrism|Eurocentric]] view. During the time of [[Canadian Indian residential school system|residential schools]], First Nations children braids were cut from their heads to force assimilation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=‘Assault’ on residential school students' identities began the moment they stepped inside|url=https://nationalpost.com/news/canada/assault-on-residential-school-students-identities-began-the-moment-they-stepped-inside|access-date=2020-10-21|website=National Post|language=en-CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar incidents of racism have happened recently in Canada. In 2009, in Thunder Bay, Ontario, a First Nations boy’s hair was cut by a teachers aide.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Thunder Bay mom wants answers after teacher's aide chops off son's hair {{!}} CBC News|language=en-US|work=CBC|url=https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/thunder-bay-mom-wants-answers-after-teacher-s-aide-chops-off-son-s-hair-1.853718|access-date=2020-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2018, a boy in Calgary, Alberta came from school with his hair cut after another student bullied him and then cut out his braid.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Son's braid cut at Calgary school: Indigenous mother hopes for teaching moment {{!}} CBC News|language=en-US|work=CBC|url=https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/calgary/sons-braid-cut-at-calgary-school-1.4689811|access-date=2020-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Braids hold significant ties to the past before colonization and have important culture meaning.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=View of Altered Beauty: African-Caribbean Women Decolonizing Racialized Aesthetics in Toronto, Canada {{!}} Revue YOUR Review (York Online Undergraduate Research)|url=https://yourreview.journals.yorku.ca/index.php/yourreview/article/view/40352/36553|access-date=2020-10-21|website=yourreview.journals.yorku.ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=‘Assault’ on residential school students' identities began the moment they stepped inside|url=https://nationalpost.com/news/canada/assault-on-residential-school-students-identities-began-the-moment-they-stepped-inside|access-date=2020-10-21|website=National Post|language=en-CA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Beard and haircut laws by country]]
* [[Black is Beautiful]]
* [[Blonde stereotype]]
* [[Blonde versus brunette rivalry]]
* [[Colorism]]
* [[Emo killings in Iraq]]
* [[Good hair (phrase)]]
*''[[Hair Love]]''
* [[Internalized racism]]
* [[Paper bag party]]
* [[Red_hair#Prejudice and discrimination against redheads|Prejudice and discrimination against redheads]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*"Black Women and Identity: What's Hair Got To Do With It?" vol. 22, no. 1, fall 2008–2009
*"Dreadlock Discrimination: Is There Such A Thing?" AOL Jobs. N.p., n.d. Web. 29 Apr. 2013.
*""Dreadlock Discrimination" Triggers Lawsuit." Racial Discrimination Based On A Hairstyle? N.p., n.d. Web. 30 Apr. 2013.
*"For African-American Women, a Hairstyle Can Be a Tricky Decision." SaportaReport. N.p., n.d. Web. 29 Apr. 2013.
*"Good Hair (film)." Wikipedia. Wikimedia Foundation, 28 Apr. 2013. Web. 30 Apr. 2013.
*"Willis Mason. History of the American People. Boston: Allyn and Bacon, 1922. Print.

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Anti-black racism]]
[[Category:Anti-indigenous racism]]
[[Category:Discrimination by type|Hair]]
[[Category:Human hair]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>