<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041030132035|7046300" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1117658" pageid="1117658" ns="0" title="Social model of disability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-02T02:28:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''social model of disability''' recognises that some people have impairments which affect how they function physically or mentally.  But those people are disabled by the barriers that exist in a society that does not take account of their needs.  These barriers may be in the physical, organisational or personal aspects of society - for instance, stairs without lifts, information not available in large print, or people’s negative attitudes.  The social model sees disabled people as having similar wants, needs and aspirations to non-disabled people, and seeking equal treatment.  Disability is not seen as something invoking pity or in need of a cure.  Indeed it may be viewed as a positive asset.  Equality for disabled people is seen in the same light as equality for other under-represented groups.

In the [[United Kingdom]], the [[Disability Discrimination Act]] definition of disability uses the medical model - disabled people are defined as people with certain conditions, or certain limitations on their ability to carry out ‘normal day-to-day activities’.  But the requirement on employers and service providers to make ‘reasonable adjustments’ to their policies or practices, or physical aspects of their premises, follows the social model.  By making adjustments, employers and service providers are removing the barriers that disable - they are effectively removing the disability.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>