<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201014124049|983474233" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1117658" pageid="1117658" ns="0" title="Social model of disability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-27T09:26:14Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Merge from|Social construction of disability|discuss=Talk:Social model of disability#Proposed merge of Social construction of disability into Social model of disability|date=October 2020}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2020}}
{{Disability}}

The '''social model of disability''' identifies systemic barriers, derogatory attitudes, and social exclusion (intentional or inadvertent), which make it difficult or impossible for individuals with impairments to attain their valued [[Capability approach#Key terms|functionings]]. The social model of disability diverges from the dominant [[medical model of disability]], which is a functional analysis of the body as a machine to be fixed in order to conform with normative values.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Paley|first=John|title=The Cartesian melodrama in nursing|journal=Nursing Philosophy|date=1 October 2002|volume=3|issue=3|pages=189–192|doi=10.1046/j.1466-769X.2002.00113.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; While [[Physiology|physical]], sensory, intellectual, or [[psychological]] variations may cause individual functional limitation or impairments, these do not necessarily have to lead to [[disability]] unless society fails to take account of and include people regardless of their individual differences.

The social model of disability is based on a distinction between the terms ''impairment'' and ''disability''. In this model, the word ''impairment'' is used to refer to the actual attributes (or lack of attributes) that affect a person, such as the inability to walk or breathe independently. The word ''disability'' is used to refer to the restrictions caused by society when it does not give equivalent attention and accommodation to the needs of individuals with impairments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leeds.ac.uk/disability-studies/archiveuk/thomas%20pam/Defining%20Impairment%20within%20the%20Social%20Model%20of%20Disability.pdf|title=Defining Impairment within the Social Model of Disability|author1=Pam Thomas|author2=Lorraine Gradwell|work=leeds.ac.uk|accessdate=2012-11-10|author3=Natalie Markham}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a simple example, if a person is unable to climb stairs, the medical model focuses on making the individual physically able to climb stairs.  The social model tries to make stair-climbing unnecessary, such as by replacing the stairs with a wheelchair-accessible ramp.  According to the social model, the person remains impaired with respect to climbing stairs, but the impairment should no longer be considered disabling in that scenario, because the person can get to the same locations without climbing any stairs.

The origins of the approach can be traced to the 1960s, and the specific term emerged from the [[United Kingdom]] in the 1980s.  According to [[Mike Oliver (disability advocate)|Mike Oliver]], the social model of disability was never meant to be an all-encompassing explanation of everything that a disabled person experiences.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Oliver |first1=Mike |title=The social model of disability: thirty years on |journal=Disability &amp; Society |date=October 2013 |volume=28 |issue=7 |pages=1024–1026 |doi=10.1080/09687599.2013.818773 |s2cid=145557887 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

=== UPIAS ===
The history of the social model of disability begins with the history of the [[disability rights movement]].  In 1975, the UK organization [[Union of the Physically Impaired Against Segregation]] (UPIAS, 1972-1990)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Baldwinson |first=Tony |title=UPIAS - The Union of the Physically Impaired Against Segregation (1972-1990) : a public record from private files |date=2019 |publisher=TBR Imprint |isbn=978-1-913148-01-0 |oclc=1099943533 }}{{page needed|date=October 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; claimed: "In our view it is society which disables physically impaired people. Disability is something imposed on top of our impairments by the way we are unnecessarily isolated and excluded from full participation in society."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leeds.ac.uk/disability-studies/archiveuk/UPIAS/fundamental%20principles.pdf |title=THE UNION OF THE PHYSICALLY IMPAIRED AGAINST SEGREGATION and THE DISABILITY ALLIANCE discuss Fundamental Principles of Disability |publisher=[[UPIAS]] |accessdate=2010-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leeds.ac.uk/disability-studies/archiveuk/finkelstein/UPIAS%20Principles%202.pdf |title=Fundamental Principles of Disability - Comments on the discussion held between the Union and the Disability Alliance on 22nd November, 1975 |publisher=[[UPIAS]] |accessdate=2010-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; This became known as the social interpretation, or social definition, of disability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hunt |first=Judy |title=No limits : the disabled people's movement : a radical history |publisher=TBR Imprint |year=2019 |isbn=978-1-913148-02-7 |location=Manchester |page=107 |oclc=1108503896 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Alf Morris ===
However, there is a hint from before the 1970s that the interaction between impairment and society was beginning to be considered. [[Alf Morris]] wrote that in 1969:

* "When the title of my Bill was announced, I was frequently asked what kind of improvements for the chronically sick and disabled I had in mind. It always seemed best to begin with the problems of access. I explained that I wanted to remove the severe and gratuitous '''social handicaps''' inflicted on disabled people, and often on their families and friends, not just by their exclusion from town and county halls, art galleries, libraries and many of the universities, but even from pubs, restaurants, theatres, cinemas and other places of entertainment ... I explained that I and my friends were concerned to stop '''society''' from treating disabled people as if they were a separate species." (emphasis added)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |first1=Alfred |last1=Morris |first2=Arthur |last2=Butler |title=No Feet to Drag - Report on the Disabled |publisher=Sidgwick &amp; Jackson |year=1972 |isbn=978-0-283-97867-8 |location=London |pages=9–10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Mike Oliver ===
Following the UPIAS "social definition of disability", in 1983 the disabled academic [[Mike Oliver (disability advocate)|Mike Oliver]] coined the phrase ''social model of disability'' in reference to these ideological developments.&lt;ref name="OliverSapey2006"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Michael Oliver|author2=Bob Sapey|title=Social work with disabled people|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qqiUQgAACAAJ|year=2006|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=978-1-4039-1838-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oliver focused on the idea of an individual model (of which the medical was a part) versus a social model, derived from the distinction originally made between impairment and disability by the UPIAS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.leeds.ac.uk/disability-studies/archiveuk/Oliver/in%20soc%20dis.pdf |author=MIKE OLIVER |title=THE INDIVIDUAL AND SOCIAL MODELS OF DISABILITY |publisher=leeds.ac.uk |date=23 July 1990 |accessdate=2012-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oliver's seminal 1990 book is widely cited as a major moment in the adoption of this model.  The book included just three pages about the social model of disability.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

=== Developments ===
The "social model" was extended and developed by academics and activists in Australia, the UK, the US and other countries, and extended to include all disabled people, including those who have [[learning disabilities|learning difficulties]] / [[learning disabilities]] / or who are [[intellectually disabled]], or people with emotional, mental health or behavioural problems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://old.bfi.org.uk/education/teaching/disability/thinking/medical.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120803101331/http://old.bfi.org.uk/education/teaching/disability/thinking/medical.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=2012-08-03 |title=Disabling Imagery? &amp;#124; Ways of thinking about disability: 'Medical Model' vs 'Social Model' &amp;#124; Learning resources&amp;#124; BFI |website=Old.bfi.org.uk |date=2010-03-22 |accessdate=2016-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Goodley|first=Dan|title='Learning Difficulties', the Social Model of Disability and Impairment: Challenging epistemologies|journal=Disability &amp; Society|date=1 March 2001|volume=16|issue=2|pages=207–231|doi=10.1080/09687590120035816|s2cid=143447725}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Tool for cultural analysis ==
The "social model" has become a key tool in the analysis of the cultural representation of disability; from literature, to radio, to charity-imagery to cinema.  The "social model" has become the key conceptual analysis in challenging, for examples, stereotypes and archetypes of disabled people by revealing how &lt;nowiki&gt;''&lt;/nowiki&gt;conventional imagery' reinforces the oppression of disabled people.  Key theorists include [[Paul Darke]] (cinema), Lois Keith&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Gardner|first=Lyn|date=3 February 2001|title=Cured by submission|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2001/feb/03/society|url-status=live|website=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; (literature), [[Lennard J. Davis|Leonard Davis]] (deaf culture), Jenny Sealey&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Theatre Company|first=Graeae|date=2020|title=Who We Are|url=https://graeae.org/about/who-we-are/|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; (theatre) and Mary-Pat O'Malley&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=O’Malley |first1=Mary-Pat |title=Falling between frames: Institutional discourse and disability in radio |journal=Journal of Pragmatics |date=1 February 2009 |volume=41 |issue=2 |pages=346–356 |doi=10.1016/j.pragma.2008.07.008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (radio).

==Components and usage==

A fundamental aspect of the social model concerns equality. The struggle for equality is often compared to the struggles of other socially marginalized groups.  Equal rights are said to [[Empowerment|empower]] people with the "ability" to make decisions and the opportunity to live life to the fullest. A related phrase often used by disability rights campaigners, as with other [[social activism]], is "[[Nothing About Us Without Us]]."&lt;ref name="Charlton2000"&gt;{{cite book|author=James I. Charlton|title=Nothing about us without us: disability oppression and empowerment|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ohqff8DBt9gC|year=2000|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-22481-0|page=3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The social model of disability focuses on changes required in society. These might be in terms of:

*Attitudes, for example a more positive attitude toward certain mental traits or behaviors, or not underestimating the potential quality of life of those with impairments,
*Social support, for example help dealing with barriers; resources, aids or [[positive discrimination]] to overcome them, for example providing a buddy to explain work culture for an autistic employee,
*Information, for example using suitable formats (e.g. [[braille]]) or levels (e.g. simplicity of language) or coverage (e.g. explaining issues others may take for granted),
*Physical structures, for example buildings with sloped access and elevators, or
*Flexible work hours for people with [[circadian rhythm sleep disorders]] or, for example, for people who experience [[anxiety]]/[[panic attacks]] in rush hour traffic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.equalityhumanrights.com/advice-and-guidance/your-rights/disability/disability-in-employment/examples-of-reasonable-adjustments-in-the-workplace/ |title=EHRC - Examples of reasonable adjustments in the workplace |publisher=Equalityhumanrights.com |date=2010-10-01 |accessdate=2012-11-10 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121023033858/http://www.equalityhumanrights.com/advice-and-guidance/your-rights/disability/disability-in-employment/examples-of-reasonable-adjustments-in-the-workplace/ |archivedate=23 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Limitations ===
Oliver did not intend the social model of disability to be an all-encompassing theory of disability, but rather a starting point in reframing how society views disability.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; This model was conceived of as a tool that could be used to improve the lives of disabled people, rather than a complete explanation for every experience and circumstance.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

It has been criticized for underplaying the role of impairments.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; It has also been criticized for not promoting the normal differences between disabled people, who can have any age, gender, race, and sexual orientation, and instead presenting them as a monolithic, [[Individuation|insufficiently individuated]] block of people.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== As an identity ==
In the late 20th century and early 21st century, the social model of disability became a dominant [[Identity (social science)|identity]] for disabled people in the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Shakespeare |first1=Tom |last2=Watson |first2=Nicholas |title=Defending the Social Model |journal=Disability &amp; Society |date=April 1997 |volume=12 |issue=2 |pages=293–300 |doi=10.1080/09687599727380 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The social model of disability implies that attempts to change, "fix" or "cure" individuals, especially when used against the wishes of the patient, can be discriminatory and prejudiced. This attitude, which may be seen as stemming from a medical model and a subjective value system, can harm the self-esteem and social inclusion of those constantly subjected to it (e.g. being told they are not as good or valuable, in an overall and core sense, as others). Some communities have actively resisted "treatments", while, for example, defending a unique culture or set of abilities. In the deaf community, sign language is valued even if most people do not know it and some parents argue against cochlear implants for deaf infants who cannot consent to them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=NASEO |url=http://www.beyonddiscovery.org/content/view.asp?I=261 |title=Sound from Silence - Sidebar - Cochlear Implan |work=Beyonddiscovery.org |accessdate=2012-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; People diagnosed as being on the [[autism spectrum]] may argue against efforts to change them to be more like others. They argue instead for acceptance of [[neurodiversity]] and accommodation to different needs and goals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Seidel |first=Kathleen |url=http://www.neurodiversity.com/autistic_distinction.html |title=the autistic distinction |work=neurodiversity.com |date=2004-08-20 |accessdate=2012-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some people diagnosed with a [[mental disorder]] argue that they are just different and don't necessarily conform.  The [[biopsychosocial model]] of disease/disability is a holistic attempt by practitioners to address this.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Engel |first1=G. |title=The need for a new medical model: a challenge for biomedicine |journal=Science |date=8 April 1977 |volume=196 |issue=4286 |pages=129–136 |doi=10.1126/science.847460 |pmid=847460 |bibcode=1977Sci...196..129E }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The social model implies that practices such as [[eugenics]] are founded on social values and a prejudiced understanding of the potential and value of those labeled disabled. "Over 200,000 disabled people were the first victims of the [[Holocaust]]."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eastrenfrewshire.gov.uk/holocaust/holocaust_remembrance_2004_-_other_victims/holocaust_remembrance_2004_-_disabled___the_holocaust.htm ] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090417064037/http://www.eastrenfrewshire.gov.uk/holocaust/holocaust_remembrance_2004_-_other_victims/holocaust_remembrance_2004_-_disabled___the_holocaust.htm |date=17 April 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 1986 article stated:  "It is important that we do not allow ourselves to be dismissed as if we all come under this one great metaphysical category 'the disabled'. The effect of this is a depersonalization, a sweeping dismissal of our individuality, and a denial of our right to be seen as people with our own uniqueness, rather than as the anonymous constituents of a category or group. These words that lump us all together – 'the disabled', 'spina bifida', 'tetraplegic', 'muscular dystrophy', – are nothing more than terminological rubbish bins into which all the important things about us as people get thrown away."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Brisenden|first=Simon|title=Independent Living and the Medical Model of Disability|journal=Disability, Handicap &amp; Society|date=1 January 1986|volume=1|issue=2|pages=173–178|doi=10.1080/02674648666780171}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Economic aspects ==
The social model also relates to economics. It proposes that people can be disabled by a lack of resources to meet their needs.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; For example, a person with impairments may need some kinds of support services to be able to participate fully in society, and can become disabled if society cuts the funding for those support services, perhaps in the name of [[Austerity|government austerity]] measures.

It addresses issues such as the under-estimation of the potential of people to contribute to society and add economic value to society, if given equal rights and equally suitable facilities and opportunities as others. Economic research on companies that attempt to accommodate disability in their workforce suggest they [[Return on Disability Index|outperform competitors]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.economist.com/node/21562229 |date=8 September 2012|title=Disability and business: The new green |newspaper=The Economist |access-date=26 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Autumn 2001, the UK Office for National Statistics identified that approximately one fifth of the working-age population was disabled – 7.1 million disabled people as opposed to 29.8 million able people – and in this analysis also provided insight into some of the reasons why disabled people were unwilling to enter the labour market, such as that the reduction in disability benefits in entering the labour market would not make it worthwhile to enter into employment. A three-pronged approach was suggested: "incentives to work via the tax and benefit system, for example through the Disabled Person’s Tax Credit; helping people back into work, for example via the New Deal for Disabled People; and tackling discrimination in the workplace via anti-discrimination policy. Underpinning this are the Disability Discrimination Act (DDA) 1995 and the Disability Rights Commission."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Smith |first1=Allan |last2=Twomey |first2=Breda |title=Labour market experiences of people with disabilities |journal=Labour Market Trends |volume=110 |issue=8 |date=August 2002 |pages=415–427 |url=https://s3.amazonaws.com/escoe-website/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/12151642/Labour-Market-Trends-Aug-2002.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Law and public policy==
In the [[United Kingdom]], the [[Disability Discrimination Act 1995|Disability Discrimination Act]] defines disability using the medical model - disabled people are defined as people with certain conditions, or certain limitations on their ability to carry out "normal day-to-day activities."  But the requirement of employers and service providers to make "reasonable adjustments" to their policies or practices, or physical aspects of their premises, follows the social model.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/DisabledPeople/RightsAndObligations/DisabilityRights/DG_4001068 |title=Definition of disability under the Equality Act 2010 - GOV.UK |publisher=Direct.gov.uk |date=2012-10-22 |accessdate=2012-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; By making adjustments, employers and service providers are removing the barriers that disable - according to the social model, they are effectively removing the person's disability. In 2006, amendments to the act called for local authorities and others to actively promote disability equality. This enforcement came in the shape of the Disability Equality Duty in December 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dotheduty.org/ |title=コアサーバーdotheduty.org |website=Dotheduty.org |accessdate=2016-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, The Disability Discrimination Act (1995) was amalgamated into the [[Equality Act 2010]] along with other pertinent discrimination legislation. It extends the law on discrimination to indirect discrimination. For example, if a carer of a person with a disability is discriminated against, this is now also unlawful.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.equalities.gov.uk/equality_act_2010.aspx |title=Home Office |publisher=Equalities |accessdate=2012-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since October 2010, when it came into effect, employers may not legally ask questions about illness or disability at interview for a job or for a referee to comment on such in a reference, except where there is a need to make reasonable adjustments for an interview to proceed. Following an offer of a job, an employer can lawfully ask such questions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thebottomlineonline.co.uk/pages/fullarticle.asp?id=222 |title=Previous Issues of The Bottom Line Online |publisher=Thebottomlineonline.co.uk |accessdate=2012-11-10 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120320201637/http://www.thebottomlineonline.co.uk/pages/fullarticle.asp?id=222 |archivedate=20 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[United States]], the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]] (ADA), revision of 2008 effective in January 2009, is a wide-ranging [[civil rights]] law that prohibits discrimination based on disability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ada.gov/pubs/adastatute08.pdf |title=AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OF 1990, AS AMENDED |website=Ada.gov |accessdate=2016-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; It affords similar protections against discrimination to Americans with disabilities as the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], which made discrimination based on [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[religion]], [[sex]], national origin, and other characteristics illegal. Certain specific conditions are excluded, such as [[alcoholism]] and [[transsexualism]].

In 2007, the [[European Court of Justice]] in the [[Chacon Navas v Eurest Colectividades SA]] court case, defined disability narrowly according to a [[medical model of disability|medical definition]] that excluded temporary illness, when considering the [[Directive establishing a general framework for equal treatment in employment and occupation]] (Council Directive 2000/78/EC). The directive did not provide for any definition of disability, despite discourse in policy documents previously in the EU about endorsing the social model of disability.  This allowed the Court of Justice to take a narrow medical definition.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}

==See also==
* [[Ableism]]
* [[Capability approach]]
* [[Models of deafness]]
* [[Equality Act (disambiguation)|Equality Act]]
* [[Inclusion (disability rights)]]
* [[Inspiration porn]]
* [[Survivorship bias]]

==Further reading==

* {{Cite book|title=The new politics of disablement|last=Oliver, Michael, 1945-2019.|date=2012|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|others=Barnes, Colin, 1946-, Oliver, Michael, 1945-2019.|isbn=9780230392441|location=Houndmills, Basingstoke|oclc=963741473}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* UK [[Disability Rights Commission]]: [https://web.archive.org/web/20090127034752/http://83.137.212.42/sitearchive/DRC/citizenship/howtouse/socialmodel/index.html The Social Model of Disability]. Accessed 2009-10-15.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070322010354/http://www.hrsdc.gc.ca/asp/gateway.asp?hr=%2Fen%2Fhip%2Fodi%2Fdocuments%2FDefinitions%2FDefinitions003.shtml&amp;hs= Article on Disability Perspectives and Data Sources] from Government of Canada.
*{{cite journal |author=Chapireau F, Colvez A |title=Social disadvantage in the international classification of impairments, disabilities, and handicap |journal=Soc Sci Med |volume=47 |issue=1 |pages=59–66 |date=July 1998 |pmid=9683379 |doi=10.1016/S0277-9536(98)00033-1|last2=Colvez }}
*{{cite journal |last1=Kearney |first1=PM |last2=Pryor |first2=J |title=The International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF) and nursing |journal=J Adv Nurs |volume=46 |issue=2 |pages=162–70 |date=April 2004 |pmid=15056329 |doi=10.1111/j.1365-2648.2003.02976.x}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Social Model Of Disability}}
[[Category:Disability]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]
[[Category:Disability studies]]
[[Category:Accessibility]]
[[Category:Medical sociology]]
[[Category:Medical models]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Sociological theories]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Social constructionism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>