<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081008013517|243793578" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1117658" pageid="1117658" ns="0" title="Social model of disability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-10-08T03:25:49Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{dablink|For specific activity related to implementation of certain aspects of this model, see the article '''[[Inclusion (disability rights)]]''' and the other articles and links there.}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
The '''social model of disability''' proposes that barriers and prejudice and exclusion by society (purposely or inadvertently) are the ultimate factors defining who is disabled and who is not in a particular society. It recognizes that while some people have [[physiology|physical]], intellectual,  or [[psychology|psychological]] differences from a statistical [[Arithmetic mean|mean]], which may sometimes be [[impairment]]s, these do not have to lead to [[disability]] unless society fails to accommodate and include them in the way it would those who are 'normal.' The phrase 'differently abled' is sometimes used to convey an aspect of the social model of disability, although the model is not generally taken as denying that some attributes (or loss of) can be seen (when unaided) as impairments. The origins of the approach can be traced to the 1960s and the [[Civil Rights Movement]]/[[human rights]] movements; the specific term itself emerged from the [[United Kingdom]] in the 1980s.

==History==
The approach behind the model is traced to the 1960s. In 1976, the UK organization [[Union of the Physically Impaired Against Segregation]] (UPIAS) claimed that disability was: ‘the disadvantage or restriction of activity caused by a contemporary social organization which takes little or no account of people who have physical impairments and thus excludes them from participation in the mainstream of social activities.’ In 1983 

The disabled academic [[Mike Oliver (disability advocate)|Mike Oliver]] coined the phrase ‘social model of disability’ in reference to these ideological developments. Oliver focused on the idea of an individual model (of which the medical was a part) versus a social model, derived from the distinction originally made between impairment and disability by the UPIAS. 

The 'social model' was extended and developed by academics and activists in the UK, US and other countries, and extended to include all disabled people, including those seen as having mental impairments or disabilities.

==Components and usage==

A fundamental aspect of the social model concerns equality. The struggle for equality is often compared to the struggles of other socially marginalized groups.  Equal rights are said to give empowerment and the 'ability' to make decisions and the opportunity to live life to the fullest. A related phrase often used by disability rights campaigners, as with other [[social activism]], is "[[Nothing About Us Without Us]]."

The social model of disability often focuses on changes required in society. These might be in terms of:

*Attitudes, for example a more positive attitude toward certain mental traits or behaviors, or not underestimating the potential quality of life of those with potential impairments
*Social support, for example help dealing with the above barriers, resources, aids or [[positive discrimination]] to overcome them.
*Information, for example using suitable formats (e.g. [[braille]]) or levels (e.g simplicity of language) or coverage (e.g. explaining issues others may take for granted)
*Physical structures, for example buildings with sloped access and elevators.

The social model of disability implies that attempts to change, 'fix' or 'cure' individuals, especially when against the wishes of the patient, can be discriminatory and prejudiced. It is often contended that this attitude, often seen as stemming from a medical model and a subjective value system, can harm the self-esteem and social inclusion of those constantly subjected to it (e.g. being told they are not as good or valuable, in some overall and core sense, as others). 

Some communities have actively resisted 'treatments', often alongside defending a unique culture or set of abilities. Some examples include: deaf parents arguing against cochlear implants for deaf infants who cannot consent to them, and valuing sign language even if most do not 'speak' it; people diagnosed with an [[autism spectrum disorder]] arguing against efforts to change them to be more like others.

They argue instead for acceptance of [[neurodiversity]] and accommodation to different needs and goals; people diagnosed with a [[mental disorder]] arguing that they are just different, don't necessarily conform, or have a [[psychosocial disability]] ultimately caused by discrimination or exclusion by society.

The social model implies that practices such as [[eugenics]] are founded on social values and a prejudiced understanding of the potential and value of those labeled disabled.

The social model of disability is often based on a distinction between the terms 'impairment' and 'disability.' Impairment is used to refer to the actual attributes (or loss of attributes) of a person, whether in terms of limbs, organs or mechanisms, including psychological. Disability is used to refer to the restrictions caused by society when it does not give equivalent attention and accommodation to the needs of individuals with impairments.

The social model also relates to economics. It proposes that people can be disabled by a lack of resources to meet their needs. It addresses issues such as the under-estimation of the potential of people to contribute to society and add economic value to society, if given equal rights and equally suitable facilities and opportunities as others.

==Policy==
In the [[United Kingdom]], the [[Disability Discrimination Act 1995|Disability Discrimination Act]] defines disability using the medical model - disabled people are defined as people with certain conditions, or certain limitations on their ability to carry out ‘normal day-to-day activities.’  But the requirement of employers and service providers to make ‘reasonable adjustments’ to their policies or practices, or physical aspects of their premises, follows the social model.  

By making adjustments, employers and service providers are removing the barriers that disable - according to the social model, they are effectively removing the person's disability. However, in 2006, amendments to the act called for local authorities and others to actively promote disability equality. We are yet to see if this means the social model of disability will be more rigorously observed. 

In the [[United States]], the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]] is a wide-ranging [[civil rights]] law that prohibits discrimination based on disability. It affords similar protections against discrimination to Americans with disabilities as the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], which made discrimination based on [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[religion]], [[sex]], national origin, and other characteristics illegal. Certain specific conditions are excluded, including [[alcoholism]] and [[transsexualism]].

== See also ==
* [[Inclusion (disability rights)]]
* [[Ableism]]
* [[Medical model of disability]]

==External links==
*[http://www.leeds.ac.uk/disability-studies/archiveuk/Oliver/in%20soc%20dis.pdf Paper on The Individual and Social Models of Disability], 1990, by Dr M Oliver who coined the term.
*[http://www.drc.org.uk/citizenship/howtouse/socialmodel/index.asp UK [[Disability Rights Commission]] website] section on the social model.
*[http://www.hrsdc.gc.ca/asp/gateway.asp?hr=/en/hip/odi/documents/Definitions/Definitions003.shtml&amp;hs= Article on Disability Perspectives and Data Sources] from Government of Canada.
*[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?db=pubmed&amp;cmd=Retrieve&amp;dopt=AbstractPlus&amp;list_uids=9683379&amp;query_hl=2&amp;itool=pubmed_DocSum Chapireau F. and Colvez A. (1998)] Social disadvantage in the [[International Classification of Impairments, Disabilities and Handicap]]. Soc Sci Med. 47(1):59-66.
*[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15056329 Kearney PM &amp; Pryor J. (2004)] [[International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health]] (ICF) and nursing. Journal of Advanced Nursing, Apr;46(2):162-70.

[[Category:Disability]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]
[[Category:Medical sociology]]
[[Category:Accessibility]]

[[fi:Vammaisuuden sosiaalinen malli]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>