<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081115104113|251940071" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="23213" pageid="23213" ns="0" title="Political correctness"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T10:55:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Political correctness''' (adjectivally, '''politically correct'''; both forms commonly abbreviated to '''PC''') is a term applied to [[language]], ideas, policies, or behavior seen as seeking to minimize offense to gender, racial, cultural, disabled, aged or other identity groups.   Conversely, the term "politically incorrect" is used to refer to language or ideas that may cause offense or that are unconstrained by [[orthodoxy]].

[[Ruth Perry]] traces the term back to [[Mao]]'s ''[[Little Red Book]]''. According to Perry, the term was later adopted by the radical left in the 1960s, initially seriously and later ironically, as a self-criticism of [[dogma]]tic attitudes. In the 1990s, because of the term's association with radical politics and [[communist]] [[political censorship|censorship]], it was used by the political right in the [[United States]] to try to discredit the Old and New Left.&lt;ref name="Perry-1992a"/&gt;

The term itself and its usage are controversial. The term "political correctness" is used almost exclusively in a [[pejorative]] sense,&lt;ref name="Schultz-1993a"&gt;Schultz, Debra L. (1993). To Reclaim a Legacy of Diversity: Analyzing the “Political Correctness” Debates in Higher Education. New York: National Council for Research on Women. [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICDocs/data/ericdocs2sql/content_storage_01/0000019b/80/13/34/5d.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Perry-1992a"&gt;Ruth Perry, (1992), "A short history of the term 'politically correct' " in ''Beyond PC: Toward a Politics of Understanding '' by Aufderheide, Patricia 1992&lt;/ref&gt; while "politically incorrect" is commonly used as an implicitly positive self-description, as in the series of "[[The Politically Incorrect Guide|Politically Incorrect Guides]]", produced by [[conservative]] publisher [[Regnery]]&lt;ref name="title"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.regnery.com/pig.html |title=Regnery |accessdate=2007-12-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the talk show [[Politically Incorrect]].

Some commentators have argued that the term "political correctness" is a [[straw man]] used by conservatives in the 1990s in order to challenge leftist [[social change]], especially with respect to issues of [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[religion]] and [[gender]].&lt;ref name="Schultz-1993a"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ellen Messer-Davidow. 1993. "Manufacturing the Attack on Liberalized Higher Education." ''Social Text'', Fall, pp. 40–80.&lt;br&gt;
Ellen Messer-Davidow. 1994. "Who (Ac)Counts and How." ''MMLA'' (The Journal of the Midwest Modern Language Association), vol. 27, no. 1, Spring, pp. 26–41.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;P. Lauter. 1995. "'Political correctness' and the attack on American colleges." In M. Bérubé &amp; C. Nelson, ''Higher education under fire: Politics, economics, and the crisis in the humanities''. New York, NY: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Scatamburlo, Valerie L. 1998. ''Soldiers of Misfortune: The New Right's Culture War and the Politics of Political Correctness.'' Counterpoints series, Vol. 25. New York: Peter Lang.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; * [[Barry Glassner]], ''The Culture of Fear'' New York: Basic Books, 1999, ISBN 0-465-01489-5 / ISBN 0-465-01490-9 &lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===In the United States===

The earliest citation is ''not politically correct'', in the [[U.S. Supreme Court]] decision ''[[Chisholm v. Georgia]]'' (1793), denoting the statement to which it refers is literally incorrect, owing to the U.S.'s political status as then understood.&lt;ref&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=2&amp;page=419 Chisholm v State of GA, 2 US 419 (1793)] ''Findlaw.com'' - Accessed February 6, 2007. "The states, rather than the People, for whose sakes the States exist, are frequently the objects which attract and arrest our principal attention[...]. Sentiments and expressions of this inaccurate kind prevail in our common, even in our convivial, language. Is a toast asked? 'The United States', instead of the 'People of the United States', is the toast given. This is not politically correct."&lt;/ref&gt;

===In Marxism-Leninism===

In [[Marxism-Leninism|Marxist-Leninist]] and [[Trotskyist]] vocabulary, the term "correct" was commonly used to describe the appropriate [[Party line (politics)|"party line"]], often called the "correct line".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thenation.com/doc/20051212/collini |title=Marxism and Form |accessdate=2007-08-26 |format= |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

A similar term was used in the [[People's Republic of China]], &lt;ref name="Perry-1992a"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chang-tu Hu, International Review of Education / Internationale Zeitschrift für Erziehungswissenschaft / Revue Internationale de l'Education, Vol. 10, No. 1. (1964), pp. 12-21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Susan Biele Alitto, Comparative Education Review, Vol. 13, No. 1. (Feb., 1969), pp. 43-59.&lt;/ref&gt; notably as part of [[Mao Zedong]]'s declarations on handling "nonantagonistic contradictions."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/428696/On-the-Correct-Handling-of-Contradictions-Among-the-People On the Correct Handling of Contradictions Among the People - Britannica Online Encyclopedia&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===In the U.S. New Left===

Even before the use of the term, the concept of the Left mocking its own use of language is evident in the 1956 pamphlet, "Lifeitselfmanship or How to Become a Precisely-Because Man" by the well-born communist [[Jessica Mitford]]. In response to ''Noblesse Oblige'', the book her sister [[Nancy Mitford|Nancy]] co-wrote and edited on the class distinctions in [[British English]], popularising the phrases "[[U and non-U English]]" (upper class and non-upper class), Jessica described L and non-L (Left and non-Left) English, mocking the clichés used by her comrades in the all-out [[class struggle]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Severo |first=Richard |date=July 23, 1996 |title=Jessica Mitford, Mordant Critic of American Ways, and a British Upbringing, Dies at 78 |work=The New York Times |publisher=Jessica Mitford Memorial Site |url=http://www.mitford.org/nytimes.htm |accessdate=2007-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Cohen |first=Nick |authorlink=Nick Cohen |date=20 August 2001 |title=Do you speak New Labour? |work=[[The New Statesman]] |url=http://www.newstatesman.com/200108200009 |accessdate=2007-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; (The title alludes to [[Stephen Potter]]'s series of books that included Lifemanship.)

Some U.S. [[New Left]] proponents adopted the usage of the phrase "political correctness". One 1970 example &lt;ref name="Perry-1992a"/&gt; is in [[Toni Cade Bambara]]'s essay ''The Black Woman'': "a man cannot be politically correct and a [male] [[chauvinist]] too", illustrating its usage in [[gender politics|gender]] and [[identity politics]], rather than solely about general political [[orthodoxy]].

Yet, soon afterwards, the New Left re-appropriated the term '''political correctness''' as [[satirical]] self-criticism; per Debra Shultz: "Throughout the 1970s and 1980s, the New Left, feminists, and progressives ... used their term ''politically correct'' ironically, as a guard against their own orthodoxy in social change efforts".&lt;ref&gt;Schultz citing Perry, 1992, P. 16&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Schultz-1993a"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Perry-1992a"/&gt; Hence the phrase's popular usage in English &lt;ref name="Perry-1992a" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.inthesetimes.com/article/3027/a_politically_correct_lexicon/ |title=A Politically Correct Lexicon |journal=In These Times |author=Joel Bleifuss |month=February | year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Bobby London]]'s usage in the underground comic book ''Merton of the Movement'', while the alternative term, ''ideologically sound'', followed a like lexical path, appearing in [[Bart Dickon]]'s satirical comic strips.

In typical left-wing usage, [[Ellen Willis]] says: "in the early '80s, when [[feminism|feminists]] used the term ''political correctness'' it was used to refer sarcastically to the [[anti-pornography movement]]'s efforts to define a '[[feminist sexuality]]' ".&lt;ref&gt;[[Ellen Willis]], "Toward a Feminist Revolution", in ''No More Nice Girls: Countercultural Essays'', Wesleyan University Press, 1992, ISBN 0-8195-5250-X, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

===In conservative rhetoric===

In the 1990s, after the [[Cold War]], this obscure term became part of conservative social and political challenges to curriculum expansion and "progressive" teaching methods in American universities and high schools (D'Souza 1991; Berman 1992; Schultz 1993; Messer Davidow 1993, 1994; Scatamburlo 1998). In 1991, in a commencement address at the [[University of Michigan]], U.S. President [[George H. W. Bush]] spoke against a "movement" that would "declare certain topics off-limits, certain expressions off-limits, even certain gestures off-limits".&lt;ref&gt;[http://bushlibrary.tamu.edu/research/papers/1991/91050401.html Remarks at the University of Michigan Commencement Ceremony in Ann Arbor], [[May 4]] [[1991]]. George Bush Presidential Library.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Use world wide===
The phrase "politically correct" is popular in other countries, including [[Scandinavia]]n countries (''politiskt korrekt''=pk), [[Portugal]], [[Spain]], and [[Latin America]] (''políticamente correcto''), [[New Zealand]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=mapp |title=Political Correctness - Next Steps  |date= 9 December 2005 |url=http://www.scoop.co.nz/stories/PA0512/S00144.htm |accessdate=2007-04-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;, [[France]] (''politiquement correct''), [[Germany]] (''politisch korrekt''), [[Poland]] (''poprawność polityczna'', ''poprawny politycznie''),  [[The Netherlands]] and [[Flanders]] (''politiek correct=poco''), [[Italy]] (''politicamente corretto'') and [[Russia]] (''политкорректность'', ''политкорректный''). Although the dominant usage is pejorative, a few writers use ''political correctness'' to describe [[inclusive language]] or [[civility]], and thus praise language that they see as politically correct.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |last=
  |first=
  |authorlink=
  |coauthors=
  |title=Teaching Politically Correct Language
  |work=
  |publisher=
  |date=
  |url=http://exchanges.state.gov/forum/vols/vol44/no1/p20.htm
  |format=
  |doi=
  |accessdate=
  |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Explanations==
===As a linguistic concept===

According to Andrews,&lt;ref name="cs"&gt;Cultural Sensitivity and Political Correctness: The Linguistic Problem of Naming, Edna Andrews, ''American Speech'', Vol. 71, No. 4 (Winter, 1996), pp. 389-404.&lt;/ref&gt; using "inclusive" and "neutral" language is based upon the idea that "language represents thought, and may even control thought"; per the [[Sapir–Whorf hypothesis]], a language's grammatical categories shape the speaker's ideas and actions,&lt;ref&gt;Development and Validation of an Instrument to Measure Attitudes Toward Sexist/Nonsexist Language Sex Roles: A Journal of Research,  March, 2000  by Janet B. Parks,  Mary Ann Roberton [http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m2294/is_2000_March/ai_63993943/pg_1]&lt;/ref&gt; although Andrews says that moderate conceptions of the relation between language and thought are sufficient to support the "reasonable deduction" of "cultural change via linguistic change".

Other cognitive psychology and cognitive linguistics works indicate that word-choices have significant "framing effects" on the perceptions, memories, and attitudes of speakers and listeners.&lt;ref&gt;Loftus, E. and Palmer, J. 1974. Reconstruction of Automobile Destruction: An example of the interaction between language and memory. Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior 13, pp.585-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kahneman, D. and Amos Tversky. 1981. The Framing of Decisions and the Psychology of Choice. Science, 211, pp.453-458&lt;/ref&gt; The relevant empirical question is whether or not [[Gender-neutral language|sexist language]] promotes sexism, i.e. sexist thought and action.

In some cases, what critics call ''political correctness'', its advocates defend as the usage of inoffensive language whose goal is multi-fold:

# The rights, opportunities, and freedoms of certain people are restricted because they are reduced to a [[stereotype]].
# Stereotyping largely is implicit, unconscious, and facilitated by the availability of pejorative labels and terms.
# Rendering the labels and terms socially unacceptable, people then must consciously think about ''how'' they describe someone unlike themselves.
# When labelling is a conscious activity, the described person's ''individual'' merits become apparent, rather than his or her stereotype.

A further complication is that terms chosen by an identity group, as acceptable descriptors of themselves, then pass into common usage, including usage by the very people whose racism and sexism, et cetera, the new terms mean to supersede. The new terms are thus devalued, and another set of words must be coined, giving rise to lengthy progressions such as ''Negro'', ''Coloured'', ''Black'', ''African-American'' and so on. (See [[Euphemism treadmill]].)

===As engineered term===

Some commentators, primarily on the Left, claim that the term "political correctness" was re-engineered by [[American conservatives]] after 1980 as a way to reframe political arguments in the United States. According to Hutton:

:"Political correctness is one of the brilliant tools that the American Right developed in the mid-1980s as part of its demolition of American liberalism....What the sharpest thinkers on the American Right saw quickly was that by declaring war on the cultural manifestations of liberalism - by levelling the charge of political correctness against its exponents - they could discredit the whole political project."&lt;ref&gt;Hutton W, [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,,619644,00.html "Words really are important, Mr Blunkett"] ''The Observer'', Sunday December 16, 2001 - Accessed February 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Such commentators say that there never was a "Political Correctness movement" in the United States, and that many who use the term are attempting to distract attention from substantive debates over discrimination and unequal treatment based on race, class, and gender (Messer-Davidow 1993, 1994; Schultz 1993; Lauter 1995; Scatamburlo 1998; Glassner 1999). Similarly, [[Polly Toynbee]] has argued that "the phrase is an empty rightwing smear designed only to elevate its user".&lt;ref&gt;Toynbee P, [http://society.guardian.co.uk/regeneration/comment/0,7941,617436,00.html "Religion must be removed from all functions of state"], ''The Guardian'', Sunday December 12, 2001 - Accessed February 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===As "Cultural Marxism"===

Some critics, primarily on the Right, claim that political correctness is a Marxist-inspired effort  aimed at undermining Western values.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.freecongress.org/PC_Essays/B_Intro_and_chapter_one.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; [[Peter Hitchens]] wrote in his book ''The Abolition of Britain'', "What Americans describe with the casual phrase ... political correctness is the most intolerant system of thought to dominate the British Isles since the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]]."  Lind and [[Patrick Buchanan|Buchanan]] have characterized PC as a technique originated by the [[Frankfurt School]]. According to Lind and Buchanan, the work of the Frankfurt School aimed at undermining Western values by influencing [[popular culture]] through [[Cultural Marxism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.academia.org/lectures/lind1.html William S. Lind states Political Correctness is a form of cultural marxism]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,157952,00.html Buchanan interview on Fox News]&lt;/ref&gt; Buchanan says in his book ''The Death of the West'': "Political Correctness is Cultural Marxism, a regime to punish dissent and to stigmatize social heresy as the [[Inquisition]] punished religious heresy. Its trademark is intolerance."(p. 89).

==Criticism==
===General===

Critics argue that political correctness is [[censorship]] and endangers [[free speech]] by limiting what is considered acceptable public discourse, especially in university and the political forums. [[University of Pennsylvania]] [[professor]] [[Alan Charles Kors]] and lawyer Harvey A. Silverglate, connect political correctness to Marxist philosopher [[Herbert Marcuse]], particularly his claim that liberal ideas of free speech were, in fact, repressive, viewing this "Marcusean logic" as the base  of [[speech codes]] formulated in American universities.&lt;ref&gt;Kors AC and Silvergate H, [http://reason.com/9811/fe.kors.shtml "Codes of silence - who's silencing free speech on campus -- and why"] ''Reason Magazine (online)'', November 1998 - Accessed February 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Kors and Silverglate went on to create the [[Foundation for Individual Rights in Education]], which campaigns against such speech codes.

Other critics say that politically correct terms are awkward [[euphemism]]s for truer, original, stark language, comparing them to [[George Orwell]]'s [[Newspeak]].&lt;ref&gt;Schmidt M. [http://www.ntu.org/main/press_papers.php?PressID=604&amp;org_name=NTUF "The Orwellian Language of Big Government"] ''NTUF Policy Paper 152'' Accessed February 3, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Camille Paglia]], a self-described "libertarian Democrat," argues that political correctness gives more power to the Left's enemies and alienates the masses against feminism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dim.com/~randl/camille.htm Camille Paglia says it best--] Accessed February 2, 2007. "My message to the media is: Wake up! The silencing of authentic debate among feminists just helps the rise of the far right. When the media get locked in their Northeastern ghetto and become slaves of the feminist establishment and fanatical special interests, the American audience ends up looking to conservative voices for common sense. As a libertarian Democrat, I protest against this self-defeating tyranny of political correctness."&lt;/ref&gt;

Some critics of political correctness claim that it [[marginalize]]s certain words, phrases, actions or attitudes through the instrumentation of public disesteem.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hprsite.squarespace.com/beyond-political-correctness/ "Beyond political correctness."] ''HPR online (the online site of the Harvard political review)'', Posted March 6, 2006 - Accessed February 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Young C. [http://www.reason.com/news/show/29189.html "Under the radar - political correctness never died."] ''Reason Online'' July 2004 - Accessed February 6, 2007. "On campuses across America, the censorship of speech and ideas in the name of sensitivity continues unabated."&lt;/ref&gt;

Some critics of ''political correctness'' argue that it is a form of [[coercion]] rooted in the assumption that in a political context, ''power'' refers to the dominion of some men over others, or the human control of human life; by this argument, ultimately, it means force or compulsion.&lt;ref&gt;Bailyn B. ''The Ideological Origins of the American Revolution''. p. 55-56. Cambridge: The Harvard University Press, 1967,1992. ISBN 0-674-44302-0. "The essence of what they meant by power was perhaps best revealed inadvertently by John Adams as he groped for words in drafting his ''Dissertation on the Canon and Feudal Law''. Twice choosing and then rejecting the word "power," he finally selected as the specification of the thought he had in mind "dominion," and in this association of words the whole generation concurred. "Power" to them meant the dominion of some men over others, the human control of human life: ultimately force, compulsion."&lt;/ref&gt; This argument holds that ''correctness'' in this context is subjective, and corresponds to the sponsored view of the government, minority, or special interest group that these conservative critics oppose. They claim that by silencing contradiction, their opponents entrench their views as orthodox, and eventually cause it to be accepted as true, as freedom of thought requires the ability to choose between more than one viewpoint.&lt;ref name=PAW_23&gt;Strauss L. ''Persecution and the Art of Writing''. p. 23. Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 1952. ISBN 0-226-77711-1. "They have not been convinced by compulsion, for compulsion does not produce conviction. It merely paves the way for conviction by silencing contradiction. What is called freedom of thought in a large number of cases amounts to — and even for all practical purposes consists of — the ability to choose between two or more different views presented by the small minority of people who are public speakers or writers. If this choice is prevented, the only kind of intellectual independence of which many people are capable is destroyed, and that is the only freedom of thought which is of political importance."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mansfield HC [http://www.weeklystandard.com/Utilities/printer_preview.asp?idArticle=6123&amp;R=EC642E5 "The cost of free speech."] ''The Weekly Standard.'' October 3, 2005 - Accessed February 6, 2007. "For lively exchange you need balance, as it is easy for a dominant majority to be unruffled by dissent when it is only from a token few."&lt;/ref&gt; Some conservatives refer to political correctness as "The Scourge of Our Times."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsmax.com/archives/articles/2002/4/4/121115.shtml Political Correctness: The Scourge of Our Times] - [[Agustin Blazquez]] with the collaboration of [[Jaums Sutton]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of political correctness have been accused of showing the same sensitivity to choice of words they claim to be opposing, and of perceiving a political agenda where none exists.&lt;ref name = "BaaBaa-Bollocks"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.septicisle.info/2006/03/baa-baa-rainbow-bollocks.html |title=Obsolete: Baa Baa Rainbow Bollocks. |accessdate=2007-10-06 |format= |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  For example, a number of news outlets claimed that a school altered the nursery rhyme "Baa Baa Black Sheep" to read "Baa Baa Rainbow Sheep."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
  |last=Blair
  |first=Alexandra
  |title=Why black sheep are barred and Humpty can't be cracked
  |publisher=The Times
  |date=2006-03-07
  |url=http://women.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/women/families/article738220.ece
  |accessdate=2007-10-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, the nursery, run by Parents and Children Together (Pact), simply had the kids "turn the song into an action rhyme. ... They sing happy, sad, bouncing, hopping, pink, blue, black and white sheep etc."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/4782856.stm |title=BBC NEWS | UK | Education | Nursery opts for 'rainbow' sheep |accessdate=2007-10-06 |format= |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The spurious claim about the nursery rhyme was widely circulated and later amplified into a suggestion that similar bans applied to the terms "black coffee" and "blackboard."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://teenink.com/talk/showthread.php?s=cb96eb0a024fd73bbc9080f5184fd151&amp;postid=322528 |title=Teen Ink - Bah, Bah, Rainbow Sheep |accessdate=2007-10-06 |format= |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Private Eye (magazine)|Private Eye]] magazine, similar stories, all without factual basis, have run in the British press since first appearing in ''[[The Sun]]'' in [[1986]].&lt;ref name = "BaaBaa-Bollocks"/&gt;

In a different example, [[NRK]], the largest broadcasting company in Norway, decided to alter the children's story of [[Pippi Longstocking]] to be "less excluding"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nrk.no/nyheter/kultur/1.1439383 Fjerner støtende ord] NRK Kulturnytt&lt;/ref&gt;. In the original stories, the main characters father is nigh permanently absent, this is explained as being due to his being a ''negerkonge'' - negro king - on a tropical island. The NRK version has him being a ''sydhavskonge'', roughly translated "southern sea king", instead&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dagbladet.no/kultur/2006/12/06/485141.html Pippis pappa ikke negerkonge lenger] - Dagbladet, 12-2006&lt;/ref&gt;. A second NRK-production was also altered to remove the word ''neger'' &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nrk.no/nyheter/kultur/1.1445964 -Et overgrep mot litteraturen] NRK Kulturnytt&lt;/ref&gt;, which is one of several hotly debated&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nrk.no/nyheter/kultur/1.3781150 -Greit å si neger] NRK Nyheter&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://pub.tv2.no/nettavisen/side2/kultur/article827886.ece Raser etter fjerning av negerkonge] TV2 Nettavisen&lt;/ref&gt; episodes in Norway&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aftenposten.no/meninger/kommentarer/article1520971.ece Negeren og nordmannen] Aftenposten nett&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vg.no/nyheter/meninger/artikkel.php?artid=148517 Ikke gjør som mora di sier] VG Nett&lt;/ref&gt; where the use of certain words has been deemed inappropriate or racist, and subsequently reduced, criticized, or even outlawed&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adressa.no/nyheter/sortrondelag/article976268.ece Forbudt å si neger] Adresseavisa&lt;/ref&gt;.

Another criticism is that enforcers rarely consult the minorities they claim to be protecting, and controversies are therefore based on [[assumption|assumptions]] that the minorities want this, when this is often not the case, as with the [[Speedy Gonzales#Controversy|Speedy Gonzales Mexican stereotypes case]], and with the [[Mr. T]] allegedly homophobic Snickers ads, which most gay men did not find homophobic.  Some people have accused the enforcers of supporting the stereotypes themselves.{{fact}}  The [[Campaign Against Political Correctness|CAPC]] website has branded political correctness completely [[intolerance|intolerant]] of any person who does not act in a politically correct fashion, and considers it to be more divisive than harmonious. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.capc.co.uk/faqs.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  Some critics nickname enforcers the "PC brigade" or the "diversity [[dictatorship|dictators]]".{{fact}}

===Political correctness and science===

Opponents of mainstream scientific views on [[evolution]], [[global warming]], [[passive smoking]], [[AIDS denialism|AIDS]], [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], and other issues have argued that political correctness is responsible for the failure of their views to get a fair hearing.  Thus [[Edward J. Steele|Ted Steele]], an associate university professor of biology, says, in his book, ''Lamarck's Signature'': "We now stand on the threshold of what could be an exciting new era of genetic research. [...] However, the 'politically correct' thought agendas of the neo-Darwinists of the 1990s are ideologically opposed to the idea of [[Lamarckism|'Lamarckian feedback']] just as the church was opposed to the idea of evolution based on natural selection in the 1850s! &lt;ref name="isbn0-7382-0171-5"&gt;{{cite book |author=Robert V. Blanden; Steele, Edward David; Lindley, Robyn A. |title=Lamarck's signature: how retrogenes are changing Darwin's natural selection paradigm |publisher=Perseus Books |location=Reading, Mass |year=1999 |pages= |isbn=0-7382-0171-5 |oclc= |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Tom Bethell]]'s ''[[The Politically Incorrect Guide to Science]]'' is a comprehensive presentation of the viewpoint that mainstream science is dominated by politically correct thinking. Bethell rejects mainstream views on evolution and global warming and supports [[AIDS denialism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Bethell, Tom |title=The Politically Incorrect Guide to Science |publisher=Regnery Publishing |location=Washington, D.C |year= |pages= |isbn=0-89526-031-X |oclc= |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Right wing political correctness==

Allegations of political correctness, in the sense of an enforced orthodoxy, have been directed against the political right.

During the run-up to the [[invasion of Iraq]], several weeks after their [[Grammy]] success, the country band the [[Dixie Chicks]] performed in [[London]] at the [[Shepherd's Bush Empire]] theatre. During this 10 March 2003 concert, the band introduced their song "Travelin' Soldier", during which [[Natalie Maines]], a Texas native, was quoted by ''[[The Guardian]]'' as saying, "Just so you know, [...] we're ashamed that the [[President of the United States]] &lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[George W. Bush]]&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; is from [[Texas]]." Though this is the official circulation of the comment, the full text of the statement Maines made was as follows:
“Just so you know, we’re on the good side with y’all. We do not want this war, this violence, and we’re ashamed that the President of the United States is from Texas.” [http://www.democracynow.org/2007/2/15/shut_up_and_sing_dixie_chicks]

The [[Dixie_Chicks#Political_controversy|resulting backlash]] against the band was described by columnist Don Williams as an example of exacting a price for expressing views the right considered politically incorrect. Williams wrote "the ugliest form of political correctness occurs whenever there's a war on. Then you'd better watch what you say." Williams noted that [[Ann Coulter]] and [[Bill O'Reilly (commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]] called it treason. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mach2.com/williams/index.php?t=1&amp;c=20060602120901 |title=Don Williams Insights - Dixie Chicks Were Right |accessdate=2007-11-09 |format= |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2004, then [[Australia]]n Labor leader [[Mark Latham]] described conservative calls for "civility" as "The New Political Correctness" [http://www.australianpolitics.com/news/2002/08/02-08-26.shtml].

Other examples include attempts to rename [[French fries]] as [[Freedom fries]], and the name [[Liberty cabbage]] used for [[sauerkraut]] during World War I.

==Satirical use==
Political correctness has frequently been a target of satire. Two early and famous examples are 1992's ''[http://www.fiction.net/tidbits/politics/pc.html Politically Correct Manifesto]'' by Saul Jerushalmy and Rens Zbignieuw X and 1994's ''[[Politically Correct Bedtime Stories]]'' by [[James Finn Garner]], in which traditional [[fairy tale]]s are rewritten from an exaggerated PC viewpoint. Other examples include [[Bill Maher]]'s former television program, which was entitled ''[[Politically Incorrect]]'' and [[George Carlin]]'s "Euphemisms" routine. ''[http://www.capc.co.uk/PC%20_Scrapbook_Main.htm The Politically Correct Scrapbook]'' also further satirizes political correctness. [[Comedy Central]]'s controversial animated show ''[[South Park]]'' regularly satirizes political correctness.

In response to the "Freedom Fries" incident, it was suggested that the [[Eugene Fama|Fama-French]] model used in [[corporate finance]] might be renamed the "Fama-Freedom" model.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.www.chibus.com/media/storage/paper408/news/2005/04/01/GsbNews/famaFrench.Model.Renamed.famaFreedom.Model-909279.shtml |title="Fama-French" Model Renamed "Fama-Freedom" Model - GSB News, Chicago Business |accessdate=2007-11-09 |format= |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Censorship]]   
* [[Christmas controversy]]   
* [[Hate speech]]   
* [[Identity Politics]]
* [[Kotobagari]] (a similar concept in the [[Japanese language]])   
* [[Newspeak]]   
* [[Non-sexist language]]; see [[Alternative political spelling#.22.40.22 replacing .22A.22 and.2For .22O.22|Alternative political spelling]] for a Spanish-language example.   
* [[Pensée unique]]   
* [[People-first language]]   
* [[Political consciousness]]   
* [[Race-baiting]]  
* [[Red-baiting]]   
* [[Speech code]]   
* [[Spin (public relations)|Spin]]   
* [[New World Order (conspiracy)]]   
* [[University of Pennsylvania controversies]]

==References==
&lt;!-- to cite a web resource, use this template
 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title= |work= |publisher= |date= |url= |format= |doi= |accessdate= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==

* Aufderheide, Patricia. (ed.). 1992. Beyond P.C.: Toward a Politics of Understanding. Saint Paul, Minnesota: Graywolf Press.
* Berman, Paul. (ed.). 1992. Debating P.C.: The Controversy Over Political Correctness on College Campuses. New York, New York: Dell Publishing.
* Gottfried, Paul E., ''After Liberalism: Mass Democracy in the Managerial State'', 1999. ISBN 0-691-05983-7
* Jay, Martin., ''The Dialectical Imagination: A History of the Frankfurt School and the Institute of Social Research, 1923-1950'', University of California Press,   New Ed edition (March 5, 1996). [http://catalog.loc.gov/cgi-bin/Pwebrecon.cgi?v3=1&amp;ti=1,1&amp;SEQ=20070214173109&amp;CNT=25%20records%20per%20page&amp;CMD=isbn%200520204239&amp;PID=2899&amp;SID=1 ISBN 0-520-20423-9]
* Switzer, Jacqueline Vaughn. ''Disabled Rights: American Disability Policy and the Fight for Equality''. Washington DC: Georgetown University Press, 2003.

===Against===

* Buchanan, Patrick J.2002. ''The Death of the West'', St Martin's Press.''
* [[Dinesh D'Souza]], ''Illiberal Education: The Politics of Race and Sex on Campus'' New York: Macmillan, Inc./The Free Press, 1991, ISBN 0-684-86384-7
* [[Henry Beard]] and [[Christopher Cerf]], ''The Official Politically Correct Dictionary and Handbook'', Villard Books, 1992, paperback 176 pages, ISBN 0-586-21726-6
* [[David E. Bernstein]], [http://mason.gmu.edu/~dbernste/book/ "You Can't Say That! The Growing Threat to Civil Liberties from Antidiscrimination Laws,"] Cato Institute 2003, 180 pages ISBN 1-930865-53-8 
* Daniel Brandt, "An Incorrect Political Memoir.", ''Lobster'' Issue 24: December 1992.
* [[William S. Lind]], [http://www.academia.org/lectures/lind1.html "The Origins of Political Correctness"],    Accuracy in Academia, 2000.
* [[Nat Hentoff]], ''Free Speech for Me - But Not for Thee'', HarperCollins, 1992, ISBN 0-06-019006-X
* [[Diane Ravitch]], ''The Language Police: How Pressure Groups Restrict What Students Learn'', Knopf, 2003, hardcover, 255 page.
* Nigel Rees, ''The Politically Correct Phrasebook: what they say you can and cannot say in the 1990s'', Bloomsbury, 1993, 192 pages, ISBN 0-7475-1426-7
* {{cite book
 |author=Kors, Alan C.
|coauthors=Silverglate, Harvey A.
 |year=1998
 |title=The Shadow University: The Betrayal of Liberty on America’s Campuses
 |publisher=Free Press 
 |location=New York
 |id=ISBN 0-684-85321-3
 }}
* [[Arthur Schlesinger Jr.]], ''The Disuniting of America: Reflections on a Multicultural Society'', W.W. Norton, 1998 revised edition, ISBN 0-393-31854-0
* Howard S. Schwartz, ''Revolt of the Primitive: An Inquiry into the Roots of Political Correctness'', Piscataway, NJ: Transaction Publishers, 2003 Revised Paperback Edition ISBN  0-765-80537-5
*[http://www.sba.oakland.edu/faculty/schwartz/PCJABS.htm ''Psychodynamics of Political Correctness'' - Published in Journal of Applied Behavioural Science]
* The [[Campaign Against Political Correctness]]

===Skeptical===
* Debra L. Schultz. 1993. ''To Reclaim a Legacy of Diversity: Analyzing the "Political Correctness" Debates in Higher Education.'' New York: National Council for Research on Women.
* Wilson, John. 1995. ''The Myth of Political Correctness: The Conservative Attack on High Education.'' Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press.

==External links==
*[http://politics.guardian.co.uk/columnist/story/0,9321,1293144,00.html Politically correct and proud of it Observer Special Report by Will Hutton]
*[http://www.linguistlist.org/issues/7/7-879.html Possible origins of the term at www.linguist.org]
*[http://www.languagemonitor.com/politically_correct/ Global Language Monitor list of the Top Ten Politically (In)Correct Terms from 2007 back to 2005]
*[http://www.lrb.co.uk/v27/n23/print/jone01_.html "Shortcuts"] by Thomas Jones, discusses the term "political correctness" in British discourse, ''[[London Review of Books]]'', December 1, 2005
*[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=420729&amp;in_page_id=1770 A list of examples cited by the Daily Mail of political correctness in the UK]

[[Category:Etiquette]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]
[[Category:Satire]]
[[Category:Sociolinguistics]]

[[br:Dereadegezh politikel]]
[[bg:Политическа коректност]]
[[cs:Politická korektnost]]
[[da:Politisk korrekthed]]
[[de:Politische Korrektheit]]
[[et:Poliitiline korrektsus]]
[[es:Corrección política]]
[[fr:Politiquement correct]]
[[ko:정치적 올바름]]
[[it:Politicamente corretto]]
[[he:תקינות פוליטית]]
[[lb:Politesch Korrektheet]]
[[hu:Politikai korrektség]]
[[nl:Politieke correctheid]]
[[ja:ポリティカル・コレクトネス]]
[[no:Politisk korrekthet]]
[[pl:Poprawność polityczna]]
[[pt:Politicamente correcto]]
[[ro:Corectitudine politică]]
[[ru:Политическая корректность]]
[[simple:Political correctness]]
[[fi:Poliittinen korrektius]]
[[sv:Politisk korrekthet]]
[[tr:Siyaseten doğruluk]]
[[uk:Політична коректність]]
[[zh:政治正確]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>