<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091112094208|325410960" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="23213" pageid="23213" ns="0" title="Political correctness"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-12T15:25:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Political correctness''' (adjectivally, '''politically correct'''; both forms commonly abbreviated to '''PC''') is a term denoting [[language]], ideas, policies, and behavior seen as seeking to minimize social offense in gender, racial, cultural, sexual orientation, handicap, and age-related contexts. In current usage, the terms are almost exclusively [[pejorative]], connoting “intolerant” and “intolerance” &lt;ref name="Perry-1992a"&gt;Ruth Perry, (1992), “A short history of the term ‘politically correct’ ”, in ''Beyond PC: Toward a Politics of Understanding '', by Patricia Aufderheide, 1992&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Schultz-1993a"&gt;Schultz, Debra L. (1993). To Reclaim a Legacy of Diversity: Analyzing the “Political Correctness” Debates in Higher Education. New York: National Council for Research on Women. [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICDocs/data/ericdocs2sql/content_storage_01/0000019b/80/13/34/5d.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; whilst the usage '''politically incorrect''', denotes an implicitly positive self-description. Examples include the [[conservative]] [[The Politically Incorrect Guide|Politically Incorrect Guides]] published by the [[Regnery]] editorial house, &lt;ref name="title"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.regnery.com/pig.html |title=Regnery |accessdate=2007-12-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the television talk show ''[[Politically Incorrect]]''. Thus, “politically incorrect” denotes language, ideas, and behavior, unconstrained by [[orthodoxy]] and the fear of giving offense.

==History==
===Early usages===
====In the USA====
The earliest citation is '''''not politically correct''''', found in the [[U.S. Supreme Court]] decision ''[[Chisholm v. Georgia]]'' (1793), denoting that the statement under judgment is literally incorrect, as understood in the eighteenth-century US: “The states, rather than the People, for whose sakes the States exist, are frequently the objects which attract and arrest our principal attention. . . . Sentiments and expressions of this inaccurate kind prevail in our common, even in our convivial, language. Is a toast asked? [To] ‘The United States’, instead of [to] the ‘People of the United States’, is the toast given. This is not politically correct.” &lt;ref&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=2&amp;page=419 Chisholm v State of GA, 2 US 419 (1793)] ''Findlaw.com'' - Accessed 6 February 2007. “The states, rather than the People, for whose sakes the States exist, are frequently the objects which attract and arrest our principal attention. . . . Sentiments and expressions of this inaccurate kind prevail in our common, even in our convivial, language. Is a toast asked? ‘The United States’, instead of the ‘People of the United States’, is the toast given. This is not politically correct.”&lt;/ref&gt;

==== In the UK ====
During the First World War, British [[Ministry of Information (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Information]] official [[Arnold Bennett]] used the expression '''''politically correct''''' in vetting language for “appropriateness”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Flower|first=Newmas|title=The Journals of Arnold Bennett|publisher=READ BOOKS, |date=2006|isbn=9781406710472|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=kRJblj1e4zsC&amp;pg=PA108&amp;lpg=PA108&amp;dq=%22Political+correctness%22+%22arnold+bennett%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=uHz1-mU8OI&amp;sig=SiegIW8PpdthjysBksX9m9yL5sw&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=7nEqSt2hBtmZjAe4vpHhCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===In Marxism–Leninism===
In [[Marxism-Leninism|Marxist–Leninist]] and [[Trotskyist]] vocabulary, ''correct'' was the common term denoting the “appropriate [[Party line (politics)|party line]]” and the ideologic/ “correct line”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thenation.com/doc/20051212/collini |title=Marxism and Form |accessdate=2007-08-26 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise in the [[People's Republic of China]], as part of Mao’s declarations on the ''correct'' handling of “non-antagonistic contradictions”.&lt;ref name="Perry-1992a"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Chang-tu Hu, International Review of Education / Internationale Zeitschrift für Erziehungswissenschaft / Revue Internationale de l'Education, Vol. 10, No. 1. (1964), pp.12–21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Susan Biele Alitto, Comparative Education Review, Vol. 13, No. 1. (Feb. 1969), pp.43–59.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/428696/On-the-Correct-Handling-of-Contradictions-Among-the-People |title=On the Correct Handling of Contradictions Among the People - Britannica Online Encyclopedia |publisher=Britannica.com |date=1957-02-27 |accessdate=2009-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; MIT professor of literature Ruth Perry traces the term from [[Mao Zedong]]’s ''[[Little Red Book]]'' (1964).

===In left-wing rhetoric===
Even before the term PC appeared, the Left mocked its own language usage in the pamphlet ''Lifeitselfmanship or How to Become a Precisely-Because Man'' (1956), by [[Jessica Mitford]], about “L and non-L” (Left and non-Left) English, mocking the Communist clichés used by her comrades when talking about fighting the [[class struggle]]. The pamphlet’s title refers to the [[Stephen Potter]] book series including the title ''Lifemanship'', and replies to ''Noblesse Oblige'', by [[Nancy Mitford]], about the perceptible class distinctions in [[British English]] usage, that popularised the phrases “[[U and non-U English]]” (Upper class and non-Upper class).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Severo |first=Richard |date=23 July 1996 |title=Jessica Mitford, Mordant Critic of American Ways, and a British Upbringing, Dies at 78 |work=The New York Times |publisher=Jessica Mitford Memorial Site |url=http://www.mitford.org/nytimes.htm |accessdate=2007-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Cohen |first=Nick |authorlink=Nick Cohen |date=20 August 2001 |title=Do you speak New Labour? |work=[[The New Statesman]] |url=http://www.newstatesman.com/200108200009 |accessdate=2007-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

In the 1960s, the radical [[left-wing politics|Left]] adopted the term, initially seriously, then ironically, in self-criticism of [[dogma]]tic attitudes. In the 1990s, because of the term’s association with radical left-wing politics and [[Communist]] [[political censorship|censorship]], the US [[right-wing politics|Right]] applied it to discredit the [[Old Left]] and the [[New Left]].&lt;ref name="Perry-1992a"/&gt; By 1970, [[New Left]] proponents had adopted the term ''political correctness''.&lt;ref name="Perry-1992a"/&gt; In the essay ''The Black Woman'', [[Toni Cade Bambara]] says: “. . . a man cannot be politically correct and a [male] [[chauvinist]] too” — a usage that widened the definition’s scope to include the politics of [[gender politics|gender]] and [[identity politics|identity]] to the politics of ideological [[orthodoxy]] in governing. The New Left thus re-appropriated the term ''political correctness'' as [[satirical]] self-criticism; per Debra Shultz: “Throughout the 1970s and 1980s, the New Left, feminists, and progressives . . . used their term ''politically correct'' ironically, as a guard against their own orthodoxy in social change efforts”.&lt;ref name="Perry-1992a"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Schultz-1993a"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schultz citing Perry (1992) p.16&lt;/ref&gt; Hence, it is a popular English usage in the underground comic book ''Merton of the Movement'', by [[Bobby London]], while ''ideologically sound'' an alternative term, followed a like lexical path, appearing in [[Bart Dickon]]’s satirical comic strips.&lt;ref name="Perry-1992a" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.inthesetimes.com/article/3027/a_politically_correct_lexicon/ |title=A Politically Correct Lexicon |journal=In These Times |author=Joel Bleifuss |month=February | year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, [[Ellen Willis]] says: “ . . . in the early ’80s, when [[feminism|feminists]] used the term ''political correctness'', it was used to refer sarcastically to the [[anti-pornography movement]]’s efforts to define a ‘feminist sexuality’ ”.&lt;ref&gt; Ellen Willis, “Toward a Feminist Revolution”, in ''No More Nice Girls: Countercultural Essays'' (1992) Wesleyan University Press, ISBN 0-8195-5250-X, p.19.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current usage==
Widespread use of the term "politically correct" and its derivatives began when it was adopted as a pejorative term by the political right in the 1990s, in the context of the [[Culture Wars]]. Writing in the [[New York Times]] in 1990,&lt;ref name="urlIDEAS &amp; TRENDS; The Rising Hegemony of the Politically Correct - The New York Times"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1990/10/28/weekinreview/ideas-trends-the-rising-hegemony-of-the-politically-correct.html?pagewanted=all |title=IDEAS &amp; TRENDS; The Rising Hegemony of the Politically Correct - The New York Times |format= |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard Bernstein]] noted "The term "politically correct," with its suggestion of Stalinist orthodoxy, is spoken more with irony and disapproval than with reverence. But across the country the term p.c., as it is commonly abbreviated, is being heard more and more in debates over what should be taught at the universities." Bernstein referred to a meeting of the [[Western Humanities Conference]] in [[Berkeley, California]], on " 'Political Correctness' and Cultural Studies," which examined "what effect the pressure to conform to currently fashionable ideas is having on scholarship". Bernstein also referred to "p.c.p" for "politically correct people", a term which did not take root in popular discussion.

Within a few years, this previously obscure term featured regularly in the lexicon of the conservative social and political challenges against [[curriculum]] expansion and [[progressive]] [[teaching]] methods in US high schools and universities.&lt;ref&gt;D’Souza 1991; Berman 1992; Schultz 1993; Messer Davidow 1993, 1994; Scatamburlo 1998&lt;/ref&gt; In 1991, addressing a graduating class of the [[University of Michigan]], U.S. President [[George H. W. Bush]] spoke against “ . . . a movement [that would] declare certain topics ‘off-limits’, certain expressions ‘off-limits’, even certain gestures ‘off-limits’ ” in allusion to liberal Political Correctness.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bushlibrary.tamu.edu/research/papers/1991/91050401.html Remarks at the University of Michigan Commencement Ceremony in Ann Arbor], May 4, 1991. George Bush Presidential Library.&lt;/ref&gt;  The most common usage here is as a pejorative term to refer to excessive deference to particular sensibilities at the expense of other considerations. The converse term "politically incorrect" came into use as an implicit term of self-praise, indicating that the user was not afraid to give offense.

The central uses of the term relate to issues of race and gender, and encompass both the language in which issues are discussed and the viewpoints that are expressed. Proponents of the view that black people are less intelligent, on average, than white people, or that women are less intelligent than men, state that criticism of these views is based on political correctness.&lt;ref name="urlThe Bell Curve Wars"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.galtoninstitute.org.uk/Newsletters/GINL9606/bell_curve_wars.htm |title=The Bell Curve Wars |format= |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples of language commonly criticised as "politically correct" include: &lt;ref name="urlwww.amazon.com"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.amazon.com/Official-Politically-Correct-Dictionary-Handbook/dp/078710146X |title=www.amazon.com |format= |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* "African-American" in place of "Black", "Negro" and other terms
* "Native American" in place of "Indian"
* “Gender-neutral” terms such as "firefighter" in place of "fireman" 
* Terms relating to disability, such as "visually challenged" in place of "blind"

More generally, any policy or factual claim opposed by the political right, such as the claim that [[global warming]] is a serious problem requiring a policy response may be criticized as "politically correct".&lt;ref name="urlwww.amazon.com"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.amazon.com/Global-Warming-Politically-Correct-Climate/dp/0595140661 |title=www.amazon.com |format= |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===World-wide===
The term '''''politically correct''''' is popular in [[Scandinavia]] (''politiskt korrekt''=pk), in [[Portugal]], [[Spain]], and [[Latin America]] (Sp., ''políticamente correcto'' | Port., ''politicamente correcto''), [[France]] (''politiquement correct''), [[Germany]] (''politisch korrekt''), [[Poland]] (''poprawność polityczna'', ''poprawny politycznie''), [[Slovenia]] (''politično korekten''), [[The Netherlands]] and [[Flanders]] (''politiek correct''), [[Italy]] (''politicamente corretto''), [[Russia]] (''политкорректность'', ''политкорректный''), and  [[New Zealand]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=mapp |title=Political Correctness - Next Steps  |date= 9 December 2005 |url=http://www.scoop.co.nz/stories/PA0512/S00144.htm |accessdate=2007-04-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; .

==Explanations==
=== As Cultural Marxism ===
Right-wing and conservative critics claim that ''political correctness'' is a Marxist undermining of Western values.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freecongress.org/PC_Essays/B_Intro_and_chapter_one.pdf ]{{Dead link|date=June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''The Abolition of Britain'', [[Peter Hitchens]] says: “What Americans describe with the casual phrase . . . ‘political correctness’ is the most intolerant system of thought to dominate the British Isles since the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]].” William S. Lind and [[Patrick Buchanan]] have characterized PC as a technique originated by the [[Frankfurt School]], whose work aimed at undermining Western values, by influencing [[popular culture]] through [[Cultural Marxism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.academia.org/lectures/lind1.html |title=William S. Lind says Political Correctness is a form of cultural marxism |publisher=Academia.org |date= |accessdate=2009-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,157952,00.html |title=Buchanan interview on Fox News |publisher=Foxnews.com |date=2005-05-27 |accessdate=2009-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[The Death of the West]]'', Buchanan says: “Political Correctness is Cultural Marxism, a regime to punish dissent and to stigmatize social heresy as the [[Inquisition]] punished religious heresy. Its trademark is intolerance.” &lt;ref&gt;Buchanan, Patrick ''The Death of the West'', p.89&lt;/ref&gt;

===As a linguistic concept===
In addressing the linguistic problem of naming, Edna Andrews says that using “inclusive” and “neutral” language is based upon the concept that “language represents thought, and may even control thought”.&lt;ref name="cs"&gt;Cultural Sensitivity and Political Correctness: The Linguistic Problem of Naming, Edna Andrews, ''American Speech'', Vol. 71, No. 4 (Winter, 1996), pp.389-404.&lt;/ref&gt;
This claim has been derived from the [[Sapir–Whorf hypothesis]], which states that a language’s grammatical categories shape the speaker’s ideas and actions; although Andrews says that moderate conceptions of the relation between language and thought are sufficient to support the “reasonable deduction . . . [of] cultural change via linguistic change”.&lt;ref&gt;Development and Validation of an Instrument to Measure Attitudes Toward Sexist/Nonsexist Language Sex Roles: A Journal of Research,  March 2000,  by Janet B. Parks,  Mary Ann Roberton [http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m2294/is_2000_March/ai_63993943/pg_1]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Other cognitive psychology and cognitive linguistics works indicate that word-choice has significant “[[Framing (social sciences)|framing effects]]” on the perceptions, memories, and attitudes of speakers and listeners.&lt;ref&gt;Loftus, E. and Palmer, J. 1974. “Reconstruction of Automobile Destruction: An example of the interaction between language and memory”. ''Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior'' 13, pp.585-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kahneman, D. and Amos Tversky. 1981. “The Framing of Decisions and the Psychology of Choice”. ''Science'', 211, pp.453-8&lt;/ref&gt; The relevant empirical question is whether or not [[Gender-neutral language|sexist language]] promotes sexism, i.e. sexist thought and action.

Advocates of [[inclusive language]] defend it as inoffensive-language usage whose goal is multi-fold:

# The rights, opportunities, and freedoms of certain people are restricted because they are reduced to [[stereotype]]s.
# Stereotyping is mostly implicit, unconscious, and facilitated by the availability of pejorative labels and terms.
# Rendering the labels and terms socially unacceptable, people then must consciously think about ''how'' they describe someone unlike themselves.
# When labelling is a conscious activity, the described person's ''individual'' merits become apparent, rather than his or her stereotype.

Critics of such arguments, and of inclusive language in general, commonly use the terminology of "political correctness" [http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/library/view.cfm?id=2623&amp;CFID=16394192&amp;CFTOKEN=66016122].

A common criticism is that terms chosen by an identity group, as acceptable descriptors of themselves, then pass into common usage, including usage by the racists and sexists whose racism and sexism, et cetera, the new terms mean to supersede. The new terms are thus devalued, and another set of words must be coined, giving rise to lengthy progressions such as ''Negro'', ''Coloured'', ''Black'', ''African-American'', and so on, (cf. [[Euphemism treadmill]]).

===As an engineered political term===
Some left-wing commentators claimed that after 1980, right-wing [[American conservatives]] re-engineered the term '''''political correctness''''' to ideologically re-frame US politics as a [[culture war]]. Hutton reports:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
"Political correctness is one of the brilliant tools that the American Right developed in the mid-1980s, as part of its demolition of American liberalism. . . . What the sharpest thinkers on the American Right saw quickly was that by declaring war on the cultural manifestations of liberalism — by levelling the charge of “political correctness” against its exponents — they could discredit the whole political project." &lt;ref&gt;Hutton W, [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,,619644,00.html “Words really are important, Mr Blunkett”] ''The Observer'', Sunday 16 December 2001 - Accessed 6 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Moreover, the commentators claimed there never was a “Political Correctness movement” in the US, and that many who use the term do so to distract attention from substantive debate about racial, class and gender discrimination and unequal legal treatment.&lt;ref&gt; Messer–Davidow 1993, 1994; Schultz 1993; Lauter 1995; Scatamburlo 1998; and Glassner 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[Polly Toynbee]] argued that “the phrase is an empty right-wing smear designed only to elevate its user.” &lt;ref&gt;Toynbee P, [http://society.guardian.co.uk/regeneration/comment/0,7941,617436,00.html “Religion must be removed from all functions of state”], ''The Guardian'', Sunday 12 December 2001 - Accessed 6 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Commenting on the UK's 2009 [[Harriet Harman#Equality Bill|Equality Bill]], Toynbee wrote that:

&lt;blockquote&gt;"The phrase "political correctness" was born as a coded cover for all who still want to say Paki, spastic or queer, all those who still want to pick on anyone not like them, playground bullies who never grew up. The politically correct society is the civilised society, however much some may squirm at the more inelegant official circumlocutions designed to avoid offence."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2009/apr/28/toynbee-equality-bill-welfare&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Criticism==
===General===
University of Pennsylvania professor [[Alan Charles Kors]] and lawyer Harvey A. Silverglate, connect ''political correctness'' to Marxist philosopher [[Herbert Marcuse]]’s claim that liberal ideas of free speech were repressive, arguing that such “Marcusean logic” is the base of [[speech codes]] in US universities, and later established the [[Foundation for Individual Rights in Education]], which campaigns against PC speech codes.&lt;ref&gt; Kors, A.C. and Silvergate, H, [http://reason.com/9811/fe.kors.shtml "Codes of silence - who's silencing free speech on campus -- and why"] ''Reason Magazine (online)'', November 1998 - Accessed 6 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The academic [[Camille Paglia]] said that PC empowers the enemies of the Left, and alienates the masses against [[feminism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://dim.com/~randl/camille.htm Camille Paglia says it best--] Accessed 2 February 2007. “My message to the media is: ‘Wake up!’ The silencing of authentic debate among feminists just helps the rise of the far right. When the media get locked in their Northeastern ghetto and become slaves of the feminist establishment and fanatical special interests, the American audience ends up looking to conservative voices for common sense. As a libertarian Democrat, I protest against this self-defeating tyranny of political correctness.”&lt;/ref&gt; 

{{further|[[Loony Left#Baa Baa White Sheep]]}}
Critics of PC have been accused of displaying the same sensitivity to word choice that they claim to oppose, and of perceiving non-existent political agenda.&lt;ref name = "BaaBaa-Bollocks"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.septicisle.info/2006/03/baa-baa-rainbow-bollocks.html |title=Obsolete: Baa Baa Rainbow Bollocks. |accessdate=2007-10-06 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, some newspapers reported that a school had altered the nursery rhyme “Baa Baa Black Sheep” to read “Baa Baa Rainbow Sheep”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Blair
  |first=Alexandra
  |title=Why black sheep are barred and Humpty can't be cracked
  |publisher=The Times
  |date=2006-03-07
  |url=http://women.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/women/families/article738220.ece
  |accessdate=2007-10-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt; But it is also reported that a better description is that the Parents and Children Together (PACT) nursery had the children “turn the song into an action rhyme. . . . They sing happy, sad, bouncing, hopping, pink, blue, black and white sheep etc.” &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/4782856.stm |title=BBC NEWS | UK | Education | Nursery opts for 'rainbow' sheep |accessdate=2007-10-06 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; That nursery rhyme story was circulated and later extended to suggest that like language bans applied to the terms “black coffee” and “blackboard”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://teenink.com/talk/showthread.php?s=cb96eb0a024fd73bbc9080f5184fd151&amp;postid=322528 |title=Teen Ink - Bah, Bah, Rainbow Sheep |accessdate=2007-10-06 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Private Eye (magazine)|Private Eye]] magazine reported that like stories, all baseless, ran in the British press since ''[[The Sun]]'' first published them in 1986.&lt;ref name = "BaaBaa-Bollocks"/&gt;

===Political correctness and science===
''See also: [[Politicization of science]]''

Groups opposing mainstream scientific views on [[evolution]], [[global warming]], [[passive smoking]], [[AIDS denialism|AIDS]], [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], and other contentious scientific matters argue that PC is responsible for the failure of their perspectives to receive a fair public hearing; thus, in ''Lamarck’s Signature: How Retrogenes are Changing Darwin’s Natural Selection Paradigm'', Assoc. Prof. [[Edward J. Steele]] says: “We now stand on the threshold of what could be an exciting new era of genetic research. . . . However, the ‘politically correct’ thought agendas of the neo–Darwinists of the 1990s are ideologically opposed to the idea of [[Lamarckism|‘Lamarckian Feedback’]], just as the Church was opposed to the idea of evolution based on natural selection in the 1850s!” &lt;ref name="isbn0-7382-0171-5"&gt;{{cite book |author=Robert V. Blanden; Steele, Edward David; Lindley, Robyn A. |title=Lamarck's signature: how retrogenes are changing Darwin's natural selection paradigm |publisher=Perseus Books |location=Reading, Mass |year=1999 |pages= |isbn=0-7382-0171-5 |oclc= |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The Politically Incorrect Guide to Science]]'', by [[Tom Bethell]], is a comprehensive presentation argument that mainstream science is dominated by politically correct thinking. Bethell rejects mainstream views about evolution and global warming, and supports [[AIDS denialism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Bethell, Tom |title=The Politically Incorrect Guide to Science |publisher=Regnery Publishing |location=Washington, D.C |year= 2005|pages= |isbn=0-89526-031-X |oclc= |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Right wing political correctness==
Accusations of political correctness, in the sense of enforced orthodoxy, have also been directed against the political right. Before the US [[invasion of Iraq]], the [[Dixie Chicks]] country band played in London. During the 10 March 2003 concert, they introduced the song “Travelin’ Soldier”; ''[[The Guardian]]'' quoted Texan [[Natalie Maines]]: “Just so you know, we’re on the good side with y’all. We do not want this war, this violence, and we’re ashamed that the President of the United States is from Texas.” &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.democracynow.org/2007/2/15/shut_up_and_sing_dixie_chicks |title="Shut Up and Sing": Dixie Chicks' Big Grammy Win Caps Comeback From Backlash Over Anti-War Stance |publisher=Democracynow.org |date= |accessdate=2009-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Newspaper columnist Don Williams described the [[Dixie Chicks#Political controversy|resulting backlash]] against the band as the price for freely speaking political views disapproved by the Right Wing — “the ugliest form of political correctness occurs whenever there’s a war on. Then you’d better watch what you say.” He noted that [[Ann Coulter]] and [[Bill O'Reilly (commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]] called the musicians’ comment treasonous.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mach2.com/williams/index.php?t=1&amp;c=20060602120901 |title=Don Williams Insights - Dixie Chicks Were Right |accessdate=2007-11-09 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Linguistic examples of right-wing adjustments to language, criticised as examples of political correctness include renaming [[French fries]] as “[[Freedom fries]]”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.parisvoice.com/voicearchives/03/apr/html/tips/tips1.html | title = Freedom fries and French toast}}&lt;/ref&gt; on the model of US manufacturers renaming [[sauerkraut]] as “[[Liberty cabbage]]” during the First World War as a marketing tool to avoid potential public disapproval of a product with a German name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.digitalhistory.uh.edu/database/article_display.cfm?HHID=531 | title = Over Here: World War I on the Home Front | work = Digital History | accessdate = 2006-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, then [[Australia]]n Labor leader [[Mark Latham]] described conservative calls for "civility" as "The New Political Correctness".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.australianpolitics.com/news/2002/08/02-08-26.shtml |title=The New Political Correctness: Speech By Mark Latham [August 26, 2002&amp;#93; |publisher=Australianpolitics.com |date= |accessdate=2009-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Satirical use==
Political correctness often is satirised, for example in the ''Politically Correct Manifesto'' (1992), by Saul Jerushalmy and Rens Zbignieuw X,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fiction.net/tidbits/politics/pc.html |title=TidBits: The PC Manifesto |publisher=Fiction.net |date= |accessdate=2009-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Politically Correct Bedtime Stories]]'' (1994), by [[James Finn Garner]], presenting [[fairy tale]]s re-written from an exaggerated PC perspective. 

Other examples include the television program ''[[Politically Incorrect]]'', [[George Carlin]]’s "Euphemisms" routine, and ''The Politically Correct Scrapbook''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.capc.co.uk/PC%20_Scrapbook_Main.htm |title=Book - Buy Now |publisher=Capc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2009-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The popularity of the [[libertarian]] ''[[South Park]]'' cartoon program on the Right led to the creation of the term ''[[South Park Republican]]'' by [[Andrew Sullivan]], and later the book ''[[South Park Conservatives]]'' by [[Brian C. Anderson]].&lt;ref name = "anderson"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Anderson | first = Brian C. | title = We're Not Losing the Culture Wars Anymore | url = http://www.city-journal.org/html/13_4_were_not_losing.html | date = Autumn 2003 | accessdate = 2007-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Replying to the “Freedom Fries” matter, wits suggested that the [[Eugene Fama|Fama-French]] model used in [[corporate finance]] be renamed the “Fama-Freedom” model.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.www.chibus.com/media/storage/paper408/news/2005/04/01/GsbNews/famaFrench.Model.Renamed.famaFreedom.Model-909279.shtml |title="Fama-French" Model Renamed "Fama-Freedom" Model - GSB News, Chicago Business |accessdate=2007-11-09 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Anti-racist mathematics]] 
* [[Christmas controversy]]
* [[Euphemism#The_.22euphemism_treadmill.22|Euphemism Treadmill]]   
* [[Hate speech]]   
* [[Identity Politics]]
* [[Kotobagari]] (a similar concept in the [[Japanese language]])    
* [[Logocracy]]
* [[Newspeak]]
* [[Non-sexist language]]; see [[Satiric misspelling]] ([[Alternative political spelling#.22.40.22 replacing .22A.22 and.2For .22O.22|Alternative political spelling]]) for a Spanish-language example.   
* [[Pensée unique]]   
* [[People-first language]]   
* [[Political consciousness]]   
* [[Race-baiting]]  
* [[Red-baiting]]   
* [[Speech code]]   
* [[Spin (public relations)|Spin]]   
* [[University of Pennsylvania controversies]]
* [[Xenocentrism]]

==References==
&lt;!-- to cite a web resource, use this template
 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title= |work= |publisher= |date= |url= |format= |doi= |accessdate= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
===For===
* Aufderheide, Patricia. (ed.). 1992. Beyond P.C.: Toward a Politics of Understanding. Saint Paul, Minnesota: Graywolf Press.
* Berman, Paul. (ed.). 1992. Debating P.C.: The Controversy Over Political Correctness on College Campuses. New York, New York: Dell Publishing.
* Gottfried, Paul E., ''After Liberalism: Mass Democracy in the Managerial State'', 1999. ISBN 0-691-05983-7
* Jay, Martin., ''The Dialectical Imagination: A History of the Frankfurt School and the Institute of Social Research, 1923-1950'', University of California Press,   New Ed edition (March 5, 1996). [http://catalog.loc.gov/cgi-bin/Pwebrecon.cgi?v3=1&amp;ti=1,1&amp;SEQ=20070214173109&amp;CNT=25%20records%20per%20page&amp;CMD=isbn%200520204239&amp;PID=2899&amp;SID=1 ISBN 0-520-20423-9]
* Switzer, Jacqueline Vaughn. ''Disabled Rights: American Disability Policy and the Fight for Equality''. Washington DC: Georgetown University Press, 2003.

===Against===
* Buchanan, Patrick J.2002. ''The Death of the West'', St Martin's Press.''
* [[Dinesh D'Souza]], ''Illiberal Education: The Politics of Race and Sex on Campus'' New York: Macmillan, Inc./The Free Press, 1991, ISBN 0-684-86384-7
* [[Henry Beard]] and [[Christopher Cerf]], ''The Official Politically Correct Dictionary and Handbook'', Villard Books, 1992, paperback 176 pages, ISBN 0-586-21726-6
* [[David E. Bernstein]], [http://mason.gmu.edu/~dbernste/book/ "You Can't Say That! The Growing Threat to Civil Liberties from Antidiscrimination Laws,"] Cato Institute 2003, 180 pages ISBN 1-930865-53-8 
* Daniel Brandt, "An Incorrect Political Memoir.", ''Lobster'' Issue 24: December 1992.
* [[William S. Lind]], [http://www.academia.org/lectures/lind1.html "The Origins of Political Correctness"],    Accuracy in Academia, 2000.
* [[Nat Hentoff]], ''Free Speech for Me - But Not for Thee'', HarperCollins, 1992, ISBN 0-06-019006-X
* [[Diane Ravitch]], ''The Language Police: How Pressure Groups Restrict What Students Learn'', Knopf, 2003, hardcover, 255 page.
* Nigel Rees, ''The Politically Correct Phrasebook: what they say you can and cannot say in the 1990s'', Bloomsbury, 1993, 192 pages, ISBN 0-7475-1426-7
* {{cite book |author=Kors, Alan C.|coauthors=Silverglate, Harvey A. |year=1998 |title=The Shadow University: The Betrayal of Liberty on America’s Campuses |publisher=Free Press |location=New York |isbn=0-684-85321-3 }}
* [[Arthur Schlesinger Jr.]], ''The Disuniting of America: Reflections on a Multicultural Society'', W.W. Norton, 1998 revised edition, ISBN 0-393-31854-0
* Howard S. Schwartz, ''Revolt of the Primitive: An Inquiry into the Roots of Political Correctness'', Piscataway, NJ: Transaction Publishers, 2003 Revised Paperback Edition ISBN  0-765-80537-5
*[http://www.sba.oakland.edu/faculty/schwartz/PCJABS.htm ''Psychodynamics of Political Correctness'' - Published in Journal of Applied Behavioural Science]
* The [[Campaign Against Political Correctness]]

===Skeptical===
* Debra L. Schultz. 1993. ''To Reclaim a Legacy of Diversity: Analyzing the "Political Correctness" Debates in Higher Education.'' New York: National Council for Research on Women.
* Wilson, John. 1995. ''The Myth of Political Correctness: The Conservative Attack on High Education.'' Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press.

==External links==
*[http://politics.guardian.co.uk/columnist/story/0,9321,1293144,00.html Politically correct and proud of it Observer Special Report by Will Hutton]
*[http://www.linguistlist.org/issues/7/7-879.html Possible origins of the term at www.linguist.org]
*[http://www.lrb.co.uk/v27/n23/print/jone01_.html "Shortcuts"] by Thomas Jones, discusses the term "political correctness" in British discourse, ''[[London Review of Books]]'', December 1, 2005
*[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=420729&amp;in_page_id=1770 A list of examples cited by the Daily Mail of political correctness in the UK]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Political Correctness}}
[[Category:Etiquette]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]
[[Category:Satire]]
[[Category:Sociolinguistics]]
[[Category:Censorship]]
[[Category:Freedom of expression]]
[[Category:Postmodernism]]
[[Category:1990s]]
[[Category:2000s]]
[[Category:Political correctness]]

[[be:Палітычная карэктнасць]]
[[br:Dereadegezh politikel]]
[[bg:Политическа коректност]]
[[cs:Politická korektnost]]
[[da:Politisk korrekthed]]
[[de:Politische Korrektheit]]
[[et:Poliitiline korrektsus]]
[[es:Corrección política]]
[[fr:Politiquement correct]]
[[ko:정치적 올바름]]
[[it:Politicamente corretto]]
[[he:תקינות פוליטית]]
[[lb:Politesch Korrektheet]]
[[hu:Politikai korrektség]]
[[nl:Politieke correctheid]]
[[ja:ポリティカル・コレクトネス]]
[[no:Politisk korrekthet]]
[[pl:Poprawność polityczna]]
[[pt:Politicamente correto]]
[[ro:Corectitudine politică]]
[[ru:Политическая корректность]]
[[simple:Political correctness]]
[[fi:Poliittinen korrektius]]
[[sv:Politisk korrekthet]]
[[tr:Siyaseten doğruluk]]
[[uk:Політична коректність]]
[[zh:政治正確]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>