<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081104042919|249578103" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="10874135" pageid="10874135" ns="0" title="Racism in China"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-13T03:34:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{ChineseText}}
'''[[Racism]] in the [[People's Republic of China]]''' is a complex issue influenced by [[History of China|Chinese history]], [[Chinese nationalism]], and many other factors.

==Causes==
===History===

*[[Opium Wars]]
*[[Boxer Rebellion]]
*[[Second Sino-Japanese War]]
*[[Nanjing anti-African protests]]

===Racial composition===

China's racial composition is overwhelmingly homogeneous with 91.9% of the population being [[Han Chinese]], which by itself is a convergence of people from diverse origins and races, and the remaining minorities largely composed of other mainland Asia ethnicities such as [[Tibetan people|Tibetan]]s, [[Uyghur people|Uygur]]s, [[Mongols]], and [[Koreans]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ch.html#People|title= China|accessdate= 2007-04-24|publisher= [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Perceptions of Persons of African/Black Descent==
In 2007, police anti-drug crackdowns in Beijing's [[Sanlitun]] district were reported to target persons from Africa as suspected criminals, though police officials denied targeting any group &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beijingnewspeak.com/2007/09/28/sanlitun-saga-update-anti-drug-operation-uncovers-no-drugs Beijing Newspeak :: Sanlitun saga update: anti-drug operation uncovers no drugs&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;. A well-documented incident in 1988 featured Chinese students and the general in widespread against African students studying in [[Nanjing]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED8153CF933A05751C1A96E948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all ''New York Times'' article by Nicholas Kristof]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-Japanese sentiment==
{{main|Anti-Japanese sentiment in China}}

Much anti-Japanese sentiment exists in China, most of it stemming from [[Japanese war crimes]] committed in the country during the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]]. [[Japanese history textbook controversies|History textbook revisionism]] in Japan and the denial or whitewashing of events such as the [[Nanking Massacre]] by right-wing Japanese groups has continued to inflame anti-Japanese feelings in China. Additionally, anti-Japanese sentiment in China is partially the result of political manipulation by the [[Communist Party of China]].&lt;ref name="fragile"&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.cceia.org/resources/transcripts/5425.html|title= China: Fragile Superpower: How China's Internal Politics Could Derail its Peaceful Rise |accessdate=2007-07-29 |date= 2007-04-05|author= Shirk, Susan}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[2005 anti-Japanese demonstrations]] were tolerated, if not approved by the Chinese government,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/4429809.stm|title= China's anti-Japan rallies spread|date= 2005-04-10|publisher= [[BBC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; unlike other demonstrations or "[[mass incident]]s" critical of the Chinese government itself.

==Ethnic slurs==

===Mandarin===

====Against westerners====
*'''yáng guǐzi''' ([[Chinese language|Chinese]]: 洋鬼子) "Foreign devil", a slur for [[White people]]
*'''guǐlǎo''' ([[Chinese language|Chinese]]: 鬼佬) Borrowed from Cantonese "[[Gweilo]]", "ghost" or "ghost guy", a slur for white people
lao wai (老外）is sometimes used in a derogatory way, while other times it is used in a polite way.  It depends on the tone and contexts.

====Against Japanese====
*'''xiǎo Rìběn''' (小日本) — Literally "little Japan"(ese). This term is so common that it has very little impact left (Google Search returns 21,000,000 results as of August 2007). The term can be used to refer to either Japan or individual Japanese. "小", or the word "little", is usually construed as "puny", "lowly" or "small country", but not "spunky".
*日本鬼子 (Rìběn guǐzi) — Literally "Japanese devils". This is used mostly in the context of the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]], when Japan invaded and occupied large areas of China. This is the title of [[Japanese Devils|a Japanese documentary on Japanese war crimes druring WWII]].
*倭 (Wō) — This was an ancient [[Chinese language|Chinese]] name for Japan, but was also adopted by the Japanese. Today, its usage in Chinese is usually intended to give a negative connotation (see Wōkòu below). The character is said to also mean "''dwarf''", although that meaning was not apparent when the name was first used. See [[Wa (Japan)]].
*倭寇 (Wōkòu) — Originally referred to Japanese pirates and armed sea merchants who raided the Chinese coastline during the [[Ming Dynasty]] (see [[Wokou]]). The term was adopted during the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]] to refer to invading Japanese forces, (similarly to [[Nazi Germany|Germans]] being called [[Hun]]s). The word is today sometimes used to refer to all Japanese people in extremely negative contexts.
*日本狗 (Rìběn gǒu, Cantonese: Yat Boon Gau) — Literally "Japanese dogs". The word is used to refer to all Japanese people in extremely negative contexts.
*大腳盆族 (dà jiǎo pén zú) - Ethnic slur towards Japanese used prodominantly by Northern Chinese, mainly those from the city of [[Tianjin]]. Literally "Big Feet Bowl Race".
*黃軍 (huáng jūn) - Literally "Yellow Soldier(s)", used during World War II to represent [[Imperial Japanese Army|Imperial Japanese soldiers]] due to the colour of the uniform. Today, it is used negatively against all Japanese. Since the stereotype of Japanese soldiers are commonly portrayed in war-related TV series in China as short men, with a toothbrush moustache (and sometimes round glasses, in the case of higher ranks), 黃軍 is also often used to pull jokes on Chinese people with these characteristics, and thus "appear like" Japanese soldiers.
*自慰队 (zì wèi duì) - A pun on the homophone "自卫队" (zì wèi duì, literally "Self-Defence Forces", see [[Japan Self-Defense Forces]]), the definition of 慰 (wèi) used is "to comfort". This phrase is used to refer to Japanese (whose military force is known as "自卫队") being [[Stereotypes of East Asians#Predators of white women|stereotypically hypersexual]], as "自慰队" means "Self-comforting Forces", referring to [[masturbation]].

====Against Koreans====
*高丽棒子 (Gāolì bàng zǐ) - Derogatory term used against all ethnic Koreans. 高丽 ([[Traditional Chinese character|Traditional]]: 高麗) refers to Ancient Korea ([[Koryo]]), while 棒子 means ''"club"'' or ''"corncob"'', referring to how Koreans would fit into trousers of the Ancient Koryo design. Sometimes 韓棒子 (hán bàng zǐ, "韓" referring to [[South Korea]]) is also used. Additionally, 死棒子 (sǐ bàng zǐ), Literally "dead corncob", is used.
*二鬼子 (èr guǐ zǐ) - A disparaging designation of puppet armies and traitors during the Anti-Japanese War of China.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.nciku.com/search/zh/detail/%E4%BA%8C%E9%AC%BC%E5%AD%90/99788?query=during&amp;internal=true Comprehensive Chinese-English Dictionary] &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://us.mdbg.net/chindict/chindict.php?page=worddict&amp;wdqchi=%E4%BA%8C%E9%AC%BC%E5%AD%90&amp;wdrst=0&amp;wdqchim=3&amp;wddmtm=1 mdbg Chinese English Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt;Japanese were known as "鬼子" (devils), and the 二鬼子 literally means "second devils". During World War II, some [[Korean people|Koreans]] were involved in Imperial Japanese Army, and so 二鬼子 refers to [[hanjian]] and ethnic Koreans. The definition of 二鬼子 has changed throughout time{{Or|date=September 2008}}, with modern slang usage entirely different from its original meaning during World War II and the subsequent [[Chinese civil war]].{{Fact|date=September 2008}}

====Other====
*印度阿三 (yìn dù ā sān) - Ethnic slur against [[Indian people|Indians]].
*台巴子 (tái bā zǐ) - Slur originating from the city of [[Shanghai]], 台巴子 refers to Taiwanese, especially advocates of [[Taiwan independence]].
*黑鬼子 (hēi guǐ zǐ) - "Literally "Black devil", Anti-African slur similar to [[nigger]].

===Cantonese===
*''[[Gweilo]]'' ({{zh-ts|t=鬼佬|s=鬼佬}}; [[Jyutping]]: gwai2 lou2; [[Cantonese (linguistics)|Cantonese]] {{IPA2|kwɐ̌ɪlə̌ʊ}}) "ghost" or "ghost guy", a slur for White people
*日本仔 (yut boon jai) - this is the most common term in used by Cantonese Speaking Chinese having similar meaning as the English word "Jap".  The term literally translates to "Japan kid".  This term has became too common that it has not much impact and does not seem to be too derogatory compared to other words below.
*架仔/架妹 (Cantonese: Ga Jai/Ga Mui) - Used only by Cantonese speakers to call Japanese men/young girls. "架(Ga)" came from the frequent use of simple vowels(-a in this case) in Japanese language. "仔(Jai)" means little boys, with relations to the stereotype of short Japanese men. "妹(Mui)" means young girls(the speaker usually uses a lustful tone), with relations to the stereotype of disrespect to female in Japanese society. Sometimes, "Ga" is used as an adjective to avoid using the proper word "Japanese".
*蘿蔔頭 (Cantonese: Law Baak Tau) - Literally "[[Daikon]] head". Commonly used by the older people in the Cantonese-speaking world to call Japanese men. The word probably came from the design of the head-gears of Japanese soldiers during the War.

==See also==

* [[Anti-Manchuism]]
* [[Fenqing]]
* [[Han chauvinism]]
* [[Hui pan-nationalism]]
* [[Sinocentrism]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Racism by country or region]]
[[Category:Culture of the People's Republic of China]]

{{china-stub}}

[[ta:சீனாவில் இனப் பாகுபாடு]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>