<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131107093940|580574166" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="10874135" pageid="10874135" ns="0" title="Racism in China"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-07T09:46:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Ethnic issues in China''' are complex and arise from the influences of [[History of China|Chinese history]], [[Chinese nationalism]], and many other factors. Ethnic issues have driven multiple Chinese historical movements, including [[Red Turban Rebellion]] — which targeted [[Mongol]] leaderships of the [[Yuan Dynasty]] — as well as in the [[Xinhai Revolution]] which overthrew the Manchus, [[Qing Dynasty]]. An ethnic dynamic is sometimes seen in modern unrest, such as the [[July 2009 Ürümqi riots]].

==Racism and ethnic tensions in pre-modern China==


[[File:1900 killing of foreigners.jpg|thumb|350px|right|Westerners shown as pig and goat and being executed by Chinese officials, image from the [[Boxer Rebellion]]]]

Pejorative statements about non-Han Chinese can be found in some ancient Chinese texts. For example, a 7&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century commentary to the [[Hanshu]] by [[Yan Shigu]] on the [[Wusun]] people likens "barbarians who have green eyes and red hair" to [[macaque]] monkeys.&lt;ref name="yanshigu"&gt;''[[Book of Han]]'', [http://www.guoxue123.com/shibu/0101/01hsyz/111.htm with commentary by Yan Shigu] '''Original text''':　烏孫於西域諸戎其形最異。今之胡人青眼、赤須，狀類彌猴者，本其種也。&lt;/ref&gt;

Some conflicts between different races and ethnicities resulted in genocide.  [[Ran Min]], a Han chinese leader, during the [[Wei–Jie war]], massacred non-Chinese [[Wu Hu]] peoples around 350 A.D. with the [[Jie people]] particularly affected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Ch04UBWfplQC&amp;pg=PA76&amp;dq=ran+min+non+chinese&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=_zNOTInoEIK88gbInd2-Ag&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=ran%20min%20non%20chinese&amp;f=false|title=China between empires: the northern and southern dynasties|author=Mark Edward Lewis|year=2009|publisher=Harvard University Press|location=|isbn=0-674-02605-5|page=76|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rebels slaughtered many  Arabs and Persian merchants in the [[Yangzhou massacre (760)]]. The Arab historian Abu Zayd Hasan of Siraf reports when the rebel [[Huang Chao]] captured Guang Prefecture, his army killed a large number of foreign merchants resident there: Muslims, Jews, Christians, and Parsees, in the [[Guangzhou massacre]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | editor=Gabriel Ferrand |year=1922 | title=Voyage du marchand arabe Sulaymân en Inde et en Chine, rédigé en 851, suivi de remarques par Abû Zayd Hasan (vers 916)| pages=76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 20th century, the social and cultural critic [[Lu Xun]] commented that, "throughout the ages, Chinese have had only two ways of looking at foreigners, up to them as superior beings or down on them as wild animals." &lt;ref&gt;Simon Leys, ''Chinese Shadows'' (New York: The Viking Press, 1977), 1. Leys has noted that Lu Xun's polemical utterance can be applied to the Maoist bureaucracy at the time Leys wrote his book. However, Leys also pointed out that it would be unfair to apply Lu Xun's statement to the Chinese people in general. As according to Leys, the Chinese people themselves are friendly and hospitable to foreigners.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Major ethnic conflicts in China==

*[[Opium Wars]]
*[[Boxer Rebellion]]
*[[Second Sino-Japanese War]]
*[[Nanjing anti-African protests]]

==Racism and ethnic prejudice among minorities==

The [[Mongols]] divided different races into a four-class [[caste|caste system]] during the [[Yuan dynasty]].

The [[List of emperors of the Yuan Dynasty|Mongol Emperor]] [[Kublai Khan]] had introduced a hierarchy of reliability by dividing the population of the Yuan Dynasty into the following classes:

*Mongols
*[[Semu]]ren, immigrants from the west and some clans of [[Central Asia]] (Muslims, Christians, Jews, Buddhists)
*North Chinese, [[Kitans]], [[Jurchens]] and [[Koreans]]
*Southerners, or all subjects of the former Song Dynasty

Partner merchants and non-Mongol overseers were usually either immigrants or local ethnic groups. Thus, in China they were [[Turkestani]] and [[Persian people|Persian]] Muslims, and [[Christian]]s. Foreigners from outside the Mongol Empire entirely, such as the [[Marco Polo|Polo family]], were welcomed everywhere.

Despite the high position given to Muslims, the Yuan Mongols discriminated against them severely, restricting Halal slaughter and other Islamic practices like Circumcision, as well as [[Kosher]] butchering for Jews, forcing them to eat food the Mongol way. Genghis Khan directly called Muslims "slaves".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hUEswLE4SWUC&amp;pg=PA24&amp;dq=yuan+dynasty+halal&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=QyhCTMOnLoL_8AbNt5DADw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=yuan%20dynasty%20halal&amp;f=false|title=China's Muslim Hui community: migration, settlement and sects|author=Michael Dillon|year=1999|publisher=Curzon Press|location=Richmond|page=24|isbn=0-7007-1026-4|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=N7_4Gr9Q438C&amp;pg=PA230&amp;dq=yuan+dynasty+halal&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=QyhCTMOnLoL_8AbNt5DADw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=yuan%20dynasty%20halal&amp;f=false|title=Buddhism and Islam on the Silk Road|author=Johan Elverskog|year=2010|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|location=|pages=229, 230|isbn=0-8122-4237-8|pages=340|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Toward the end, corruption and persecution became so severe that Muslim Generals joined the [[Han chinese]] in rebelling against the Mongols. The Ming founder Zhu Yuanzhang had Muslim Generals including [[Lan Yu (general)|Lan Yu]] who rebelled against the Mongols and defeated them in combat. Some Muslim communities had the name which in chinese means "baracks" or "thanks". Many Hui Muslims claim it is because they played an important role in overthrowing the Mongols and in thanks by the Han chinese.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=_hJ9aht6nZQC&amp;pg=PA234&amp;dq=barracks+hui+mongol&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=lSlCTPvjFMT48AbY9djrAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwAA#v=snippet&amp;q=%22barracks%22%20and%20%22thanks%20mongols&amp;f=false|title=Muslim Chinese: ethnic nationalism in the People's Republic|author=Dru C. Gladney|year=1996|publisher=Harvard Univ Asia Center|location=Cambridge Massachusetts|page=234|isbn=0-674-59497-5|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Muslims in the semu class also revolted against the Yuan dynasty in the [[Ispah Rebellion]] but the rebellion was crushed and the Muslims were massacred by the Yuan loyalist commander Chen Youding.

Uyghurs have also exhibited racism as well. The Uyghur leader [[Sabit Damulla Abdulbaki]] made the following proclamation on Han chinese and Tungans ([[Hui people|Hui Muslims]]):

"The Tungans, more than the Han, are the enemy of our people. Today our people are already free from the oppression of the Han, but still continue under Tungan subjugation. We must still fear the Han, but cannot fear the Tungans also. The reason we must be careful to guard against the Tungans, we must intensely oppose, cannot afford to be polite. Since the Tungans have compelled us, we must be this way. Yellow Han people have not the slightest thing to do with Eastern Turkestan. Black Tungans also do not have this connection. Eastern Turkestan belongs to the people of Eastern Turkestan. There is no need for foreigners to come be our fathers and mothers...From now on we do not need to use foreigners language, or their names, their customs, habits, attitudes, written language, etc. We must also overthrow and drive foreigners from our boundaries forever. The colors yellow and black are foul. They have dirtied our land for too long. So now it is absolutely necessary to clean out this filth. Take down the yellow and black barbarians! Long live Eastern Turkestan!"&lt;ref&gt;Zhang, ''Xinjiang Fengbao Qishinian [Xinjiang in Tumult for Seventy Years]'', 3393-4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Islamic Republic of Eastern Turkestan and the Formation of Modern Uyghur Identity in Xinjiang'', by JOY R. LEE [http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?Location=U2&amp;doc=GetTRDoc.pdf&amp;AD=ADA455923]&lt;/ref&gt;

American telegrams reported that certain Uyghur mobs in parts of Xinjiang were calling for White Russians to be expelled from Xinjiang during the [[Ili Rebellion]], along with Han Chinese. They were reported to say, "We freed ourselves from the yellow men, now we must destroy the white". The telegram also reported that "Serious native attacks on people of other races frequent.  White Russians in terror of uprising."&lt;ref&gt;[http://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1947v07/reference/frus.frus1947v07.i0008.pdf UNSUCCESSFUL ATTEMPTS TO RESEOLVE POLITICAL PROBLEMS IN SINKIANG; EXTENT OF SOVIET AID AND ENCOURAGEMENT TO REBEL GROUPS IN SINKIANG; BORDER INCIDENT AT PEITASHAN]&lt;/ref&gt;

During the late 19th century around [[Qinghai]] tensions exploded between different Muslim sects, between different ethnic groups, with emminty and division rising between Hui Muslims and Salar Muslims, and all tensions rising between Muslims, Tibetans and Han.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=xGvECiS-uEgC&amp;pg=PA82&amp;dq=share+at+least+some+measure+of+power+with+ma+warlords+sectarian&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=SDWOTZLgOqG00QGd1-CnCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=share%20at%20least%20some%20measure%20of%20power%20with%20ma%20warlords%20sectarian&amp;f=false|title=Labrang: a Tibetan Buddhist monastery at the crossroads of four civilizations|author=Paul Kocot Nietupski|year=1999|publisher=Snow Lion Publications|location=|isbn=1-55939-090-5|page=82|accessdate=2010-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The "Encyclopædia of religion and ethics, Volume 8" stated that the Dungan and Panthay revolts by the Muslims was set off by racial antagonism and class warfare, rather than the mistaken assumption that it was all due to Islam and religion that the rebellions broke out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=eEwTAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA894&amp;dq=The+most+notable+and+most+serious+of+such+outbreaks+have+been+those+of+the+north+(Kan-su+and+Shen-si)+in+1861-74,+and+of+the+south+(Yiin-nan)+in+1858-72.+It+would+be+a+mistake,+however,+to+attribute+these+ruinous+insurrections+to+religious+motives+alone,+for+racial+antagonisms+and+the+conflicting+interests+of+different+social+classes+were+certainly+no+less+potent+factors.&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=-_AITvyjB8zogQfJnuWsDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20most%20notable%20and%20most%20serious%20of%20such%20outbreaks%20have%20been%20those%20of%20the%20north%20(Kan-su%20and%20Shen-si)%20in%201861-74%2C%20and%20of%20the%20south%20(Yiin-nan)%20in%201858-72.%20It%20would%20be%20a%20mistake%2C%20however%2C%20to%20attribute%20these%20ruinous%20insurrections%20to%20religious%20motives%20alone%2C%20for%20racial%20antagonisms%20and%20the%20conflicting%20interests%20of%20different%20social%20classes%20were%20certainly%20no%20less%20potent%20factors.&amp;f=false|title=Encyclopædia of religion and ethics, Volume 8|author=James Hastings, John Alexander Selbie, Louis Herbert Gray|year=1916|publisher=T. &amp; T. Clark|location=|page=893|isbn=|accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racial and ethnic segregation==

Several laws enforcing [[racial segregation]] of foreigners were passed by the [[Han chinese]] during the [[Tang Dynasty]]. In 779 AD, Tang dynasty issued an [[edict]] which forced [[Uyghur people|Uighurs]] to wear their ethnic dress, and restricted them from marrying Chinese. Chinese disliked Uighurs because they practiced [[usury]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2013}}

In 836 AD Lu Chun was appointed as governor of [[Guangzhou|Canton]], he was disgusted to find Chinese living with foreigners and [[intermarriage]]. Lu enforced separation, banning [[interracial marriage]]s, and restricting foreigners to own properties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jqAGIL02BWQC&amp;pg=PA22&amp;dq=chinese+uighurs+779+edict+lure+canton+836+foreigners+and+chinese+lu+governor+forbade+marriages+forced+separate&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=SOTQTPwQgYGUB5OXibUM&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=chinese%20uighurs%20779%20edict%20lure%20canton%20836%20foreigners%20and%20chinese%20lu%20governor%20forbade%20marriages%20forced%20separate&amp;f=false|title=The golden peaches of Samarkand: a study of Tʻang exotics|author=Edward H. Schafer|year=1963|publisher=University of California Press|location=|isbn=0-520-05462-8|page=22|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 836 law specifically banned Chinese from forming relationships with "Dark peoples" or "People of colour", terms referring to foreigners, such as "Iranians, Sogdians, Arabs, Indians, Malays, Sumatrans", etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=vpgVvAh2_EsC&amp;pg=PA170&amp;dq=836+law+tang+dynasty&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ArT1TPbCK4K8lQezxoDhBQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=836%20private%20intercourse%20dark%20peoples&amp;f=false|title=China's cosmopolitan empire: the Tang dynasty|author=Mark Edward Lewis|year=2009|publisher=Harvard University Press|location=|isbn=0-674-03306-X|page=170|accessdate=2010-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jqb7L-pKCV8C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=a+history+of+chinese&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=MrT1TLPnJ8KclgeQ4PjfBQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAQ#v=snippet&amp;q=836%20decree%20chinese%20people%20of%20colour&amp;f=false|title=A history of Chinese civilization|author=Jacques Gernet|year=1996|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=|isbn=0-521-49781-7|page=294|accessdate=2010-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racial and ethnic composition==


China's [[List of ethnic groups in China|ethnic composition]] is largely homogeneous with 91.9% of the population being [[Han Chinese]], other ethnicities are [[Mongols]], [[Zhuang people|Zhuang]], [[Miao people|Miao]], [[Hui people|Hui]], [[Tibetans]], [[Uyghurs]] and [[Koreans]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ch.html#People|title= China|accessdate= 2007-04-24|publisher= [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some ethnic groups are more distinguishable due to [[physical appearance]]s and relatively low [[intermarriage]] rates. Many others have intermarried with Han Chinese, and have similar appearances. They are therefore less distinguishable from Han Chinese people, especially because a growing number of ethnic minorities are fluent at a native level in Mandarin Chinese. In addition, children often adopts "ethnic minority status" at birth if one of their parents is an [[ethnic minority]], even though their ancestry is overwhelmingly Han Chinese. There is a growing number of [[White people|Caucasians]], [[South Asian]]s, and [[African]]s living in large Chinese cities. Although relatively few acquire Chinese citizenship, the number of immigrants belonging to different racial groups has markedly increased recently due to China's economic success{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}. There are concentrated pockets of immigrants and foreign residents in some cities.

In May 2012, a 100-day crackdown on illegal foreigners in Beijing began, with many Beijing locals wary of foreign nationals as a result of recent crime events.&lt;ref name=steinfeld&gt;Jemimah Steinfeld, 25 May 2012, [http://edition.cnn.com/2012/05/24/world/asia/china-foreigners/index.html?hpt=ias_t2 Mood darkens in Beijing amid crackdown on 'illegal foreigners'], CNN&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;15 May 2012, [http://blogs.wsj.com/chinarealtime/2012/05/15/beijing-pledges-to-clean-out-illegal-foreigners/ Beijing Pledges to ‘Clean Out’ Illegal Foreigners], China Real Time Report, Wall Street Journal&lt;/ref&gt; [[China Central Television]] host Yang Rui made a controversial statement that "foreign trash" should be cleaned out of Beijing.&lt;ref name=steinfeld/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;22 May 2012, [http://www.chinasmack.com/2012/stories/cctv-yang-ruis-anti-foreigner-rant-chinese-netizen-reactions.html CCTV Yang Rui’s Anti-Foreigner Rant, Chinese Netizen Reactions], Chinasmack&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-Japanese sentiment==
{{Main|Anti-Japanese sentiment in China}}

Anti-Japanese sentiment exists in China, most of it stemming from [[Japanese war crimes]] committed in the country during the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]]. [[Japanese history textbook controversies|History textbook revisionism]] in Japan and the denial or whitewashing of events such as the [[Nanking Massacre]] by right-wing Japanese groups has continued to inflame anti-Japanese feelings in China. It has been alleged that anti-Japanese sentiment in China is partially the result of political manipulation by the [[Communist Party of China]].&lt;ref name="fragile"&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.cceia.org/resources/transcripts/5425.html|title= China: Fragile Superpower: How China's Internal Politics Could Derail its Peaceful Rise |accessdate=2007-07-29 |date= 2007-04-05|author= Shirk, Susan}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a [[BBC]] report, anti-Japanese demonstrations are said to have received tacit approval from Chinese authorities, although the Chinese ambassador to Japan, Wang Yi, stated that the Chinese government does not condone such protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/4429809.stm|title= China's anti-Japan rallies spread|date= 2005-04-10|publisher= [[BBC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tensions with Uyghurs==
A [[Uyghur people|Uyghur]] proverb says "Protect religion, Kill the Han and destroy the Hui".(baohu zongjiao, sha Han mie Hui  保護宗教，殺漢滅回).&lt;ref&gt;.''The Islamic Republic of Eastern Turkestan and the Formation of Modern Uyghur Identity in Xinjiang'', by JOY R. LEE [http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?Location=U2&amp;doc=GetTRDoc.pdf&amp;AD=ADA455923]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=_bPdlQITuOsC&amp;pg=PA170&amp;dq=uyghur+hui&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=0tOOTObPLYa8lQeh7PXMAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CE4Q6AEwBzgK#v=onepage&amp;q=uyghur%20hui&amp;f=false|title=China's minorities on the move: selected case studies|author=Robyn R. Iredale, Naran Bilik, Fei Guo|year=2003|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|isbn=0-7656-1023-X|page=170|accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anti Hui poetry was written by Uyghurs.&lt;ref name="Ildikó Bellér-Hann 2008 75"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=cF4lMj8skvoC&amp;pg=PA74&amp;dq=celebrates+heroic+deeds+beg+victories+chinese+tungans&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=haifTNarNYKC8ga1t7n-DA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=bayanday%20brick%20chinese%20muslims%20tungans&amp;f=false|title=Community matters in Xinjiang, 1880-1949: towards a historical anthropology of the Uyghur|author=Ildikó Bellér-Hann|year=2008|publisher=BRILL|location=|page=75|isbn=90-04-16675-0|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
In Bayanday there is a brick factory,&lt;br&gt;
it had been built by the Chinese.&lt;br&gt;
If the Chinese are killed by soldiers,&lt;br&gt;
the Tungans take over the plundering.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

It was also alleged that a Uyghur would not enter the mosque of [[Hui people]], and Hui and Han households were built closer together in the same area while Uyghurs would live farther away from the town.&lt;ref name="Ildikó Bellér-Hann 2008 75"/&gt;

Sometimes Uyghurs regard Hui Muslims from other provinces of China as fakes and refuse to eat food prepared by them.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=roiuY7bnb80C&amp;pg=PA130&amp;dq=uyghur+hui&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=F9OOTKP1LsOblgelvNHmAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=uyghur%20hui&amp;f=false|title=Muslim Uyghur students in a Chinese boarding school: social recapitalization as a response to ethnic integration|author=Yangbin Chen|year=2008|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=0-7391-2112-X|page=130|accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Uyghurs view food prepared by Hui as unpure and will not buy meat from Hui, and protests by Uyghur teachers in 1989 at [[Turpan]] erupted because Uyghurs refused to eat food prepared by Hui.&lt;ref name="David Westerlund, Ingvar Svanberg 1999 204"&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=weYQMv2RqCgC&amp;pg=PA204&amp;dq=uighurs+eat+hui+restaurants+never+but+meat+butcher+dining+hall+training&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Z6ifTMSCFcP48Ab16Mg3&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=uighurs%20eat%20hui%20restaurants%20never%20but%20meat%20butcher%20dining%20hall%20training&amp;f=false|title=Islam outside the Arab world|author=David Westerlund, Ingvar Svanberg|year=1999|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=0-312-22691-8|page=204|accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Children who are of mixed Han and Uyghur ethnicities are known as ''erzhuanzi'' (二转子) and Uyghurs call them ''piryotki''.&lt;ref name="David Westerlund, Ingvar Svanberg 1999 204"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Ildikó Bellér-Hann 2007 223"&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NKCU3BdeBbEC&amp;pg=PA223&amp;dq=erzhuanzi+uyghur&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=MbOfTL_5BcKB8ga9nNF1&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=erzhuanzi%20uyghur&amp;f=false|title=Situating the Uyghurs between China and Central Asia|author=Ildikó Bellér-Hann|year=2007|publisher=Ashgate Publishing, Ltd|isbn=0-7546-7041-4|page=223|accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are shunned by Uyghurs at social gatherings and events.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=MT2D_0_eBPQC&amp;pg=PA86&amp;dq=uyghur+han+children+of+mixed+han+uyghur+erzhuanzi&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=QKifTPj3LIH58Aa9tOinDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=uyghur%20han%20children%20of%20mixed%20han%20uyghur%20erzhuanzi&amp;f=false|title=Oasis identities: Uyghur nationalism along China's Silk Road|author=Justin Ben-Adam Rudelson, Justin Jon Rudelson|year=1997|publisher=Columbia University Press|isbn=0-231-10786-2|page=86|accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have accused the Chinese government as well as certain Han Chinese citizens of alleged discrimination against the [[Turkic Muslim]] [[Uyghur people|Uyghur]] minority.&lt;ref name="neednotapply"&gt;{{cite web |title= No Uighurs Need Apply|url= http://jamesfallows.theatlantic.com/archives/2009/07/no_uighurs_need_apply.php|date= 10 Jul 2009|work= |publisher= ''The Atlantic''|accessdate=12 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Uighurs blame 'ethnic hatred' |url= http://english.aljazeera.net/focus/2009/07/20097761931298561.html|date= July 7, 2009|work= |publisher= Al Jazeera|accessdate=12 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was used as a partial explanation for the [[July 2009 Ürümqi riots]] which pitted residents of the city against each other along largely racial lines. An essay in the ''[[People's Daily]]'' described the events as "so-called racial conflict"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://chinanewswrap.com/2009/07/10/peoples-daily-criticizes-double-standards-in-western-media-attitudes-to-75-incident/#more-2398 |title=People’s Daily criticizes double standards in Western media attitudes to 7.5 incident |work=China News Wrap |author=Global Times |date=10 July 2009}} [http://world.people.com.cn/GB/9628529.html original article in Chinese]&lt;/ref&gt; while several Western media sources labeled them as "[[race riots]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Race Riots Continue in China's Far West|url= http://www.time.com/time/photogallery/0,29307,1908981,00.html|date= 2009-07-07|work= |publisher= ''Time'' magazine|accessdate=13 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Deadly race riots put spotlight on China|url= http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/07/08/ED3H18KD53.DTL|date= July 8, 2009|work= |publisher= ''The San Francisco Chronicle''|accessdate=13 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Three killed in race riots in western China|url= http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/world/2009/0706/1224250105483.html|date= July 6, 2009|work= |publisher= ''The Irish Times''|accessdate=13 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2009, a report in the ''The Atlantic'' highlighted a help wanted sign in the traditionally Uyghur city of [[Kashgar]] which explicitly stated that "this offer is for Han Chinese only."&lt;ref name="neednotapply"/&gt;

It has also been reported that unofficial Chinese policy is to deny passports to Uyghurs until they reach retirement age, especially if they intend to leave the country for the [[Hajj|pilgrimage to Mecca]].&lt;ref name="neednotapply"/&gt;

Tensions between [[Hui people|Hui]] and Uyghurs arose because Qing and Republican Chinese authorities used Hui troops and officials to dominate the Uyghurs and crush Uyghur revolts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tfWq65DlGxkC&amp;pg=PA311&amp;lpg=PA311&amp;dq=uighurs+hui+tension&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=8TPi-3G9wM&amp;sig=X0MXs0jP0QDNsGBtcOEKDMtkYUM&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=nHc_TK2IJIH58AaHpfSUCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=hui%20troops%20to%20dominate%20the%20uyghurs&amp;f=false|title=Xinjiang: China's Muslim borderland|author=S. Frederick Starr|year=2004|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|location=|isbn=0-7656-1318-2|page=311|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hui population of Xinjiang increased by 520 percent from 1940–1982, average annual growth of 4.4 percent, the Uyghur population grew at 1.7 percent.  This increase in Hui population led to tensions between the Hui Muslim and Uyghur Muslim populations. Some old Uyghurs in [[Kashgar]] remember that the Hui army at the [[Battle of Kashgar (1934)]] massacred 2,000 to 8,000 Uyghurs, which caused tension as more Hui moved into Kashgar from other parts of China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GXj4a3gss8wC&amp;pg=PA113&amp;lpg=PA113&amp;dq=THis+dramatic+increase+in+the+hui+population+led+inevitably+to+significant+tensions+between+the+hui+and&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Uo0-lvm3LC&amp;sig=nSX6__Yia6RTdRn19YTIWt8cou4&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=gUpGTJm2EMSclgf0_oDoBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CBIQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=This%20dramatic%20increase%20in%20the%20hui%20population%20led%20inevitably%20to%20significant%20tensions%20between%20the%20hui%20and&amp;f=false|title=Xinjiang: China's Muslim borderland|author=S. Frederick Starr|year=2004|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|location=|isbn=0-7656-1318-2|page=113|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tibetan racism and ethnic prejudice==
In the frontier districts of [[Sichuan]], and other ethnic Tibetan areas in China, many people are of mixed Chinese-Tibetans ethnicity. These half-Chinese, half-Tibetans were despised by pure Tibetans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=I44XAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA355&amp;dq=tibetan+women+are+glad+to+marry&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=h8tVTPPsC4L78Ab10-nvBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=tibetan%20women%20are%20glad%20to%20marry&amp;f=false|title=The history of mankind, Volume 3|author=Friedrich Ratzel|year=1898|publisher=Macmillan and co., ltd.|location=|page=355|isbn=|accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ethnic [[Tibetan Muslims]] (called Kache in Tibetan) have lived peacefully alongside [[Tibetan Buddhist]]s for over a thousand years, because Buddhist Tibetans are prohibited by their religion from killing animals, yet require meat to survive in their mountain climate. However, Tibetans have severe problems with [[Hui Chinese|Chinese Muslim]]s (called Kyangsha in Tibetan).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=QVSVux0wIW0C&amp;pg=PA77&amp;dq=fischer+tibetans+hui&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=7CepTJqwNYG0lQeJ-LmZDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=like%20the%20old%20khache%20pork%20head%20hui%20&amp;f=false|title=The other global city|author=Shail Mayaram|year=2009|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis US|location=|page=76|isbn=0-415-99194-3|accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In history, Tibetans and [[Mongols]] refused to allow other ethnic groups such as [[Kazakhs]] to participate in the Kokonur ceremony in [[Qinghai]], until the Muslim General [[Ma Bufang]] urged to stop the practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=g3C2B9oXVbQC&amp;pg=PA54&amp;lpg=PA54&amp;dq=ma+bufang+genocidal+golog&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=5y4cjM9Y1_&amp;sig=hNOuP0tY5081BGCQBo88uA_asEo&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=AgAYTLadL4KclgecgYnuCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CBIQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=allowed%20the%20kazakhs%20to%20join&amp;f=false|title=Dilemmas The Mongols at China's edge: history and the politics of national unity |author=Uradyn Erden Bulag|year=2002|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|location=|page=54|isbn=0-7425-1144-8|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-African sentiment==
{{See also|Nanjing anti-African protests}}
Several clashes between [[African]] and Chinese students have occurred since the arrival of Africans to Chinese universities in the 1960s. Many African students come to China on a scholarship through the government to study at a university.  The African students were often perceived as threatening and not punctual.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1988/12/30/world/black-africa-leaves-china-in-quandary.html ''New York Times'']&lt;/ref&gt;  A well-documented [[Nanjing anti-African protests|incident in 1988]] featured Chinese students rioting against African students studying in [[Nanjing]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED8153CF933A05751C1A96E948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all ''New York Times'' article by Nicholas Kristof]&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2007, police anti-drug crackdowns in Beijing's [[Sanlitun]] district were reported to target people from [[Africa]] as suspected criminals, though police officials denied targeting any group.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beijingnewspeak.com/2007/09/28/sanlitun-saga-update-anti-drug-operation-uncovers-no-drugs Beijing Newspeak :: Sanlitun saga update: anti-drug operation uncovers no drugs&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Similar sentiment has emerged in [[Guangzhou]], where a very [[Africans in Guangzhou|large group of Africans]] have settled.

==Other racism and ethnic prejudice==
Hatred of foreigners from high ranking Chinese Muslim officers stemmed from the arrogant way foreigners handled Chinese affairs, rather than for religious reasons, the same reason other non Muslim Chinese hated foreigners. Promotion and wealth were other motives among Chinese Muslim military officers for anti foreignism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=eEwTAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA893&amp;dq=the+hatred+of+foreigners+sometimes+shown+by+muslim+officers+of+high+rank,+like+that+displayed+by+the+chinese+themselves,+is+to+be+referred,+not+to+religious&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=PsMITu3gG8Te0QGfmJHBCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=the%20hatred%20of%20foreigners%20sometimes%20shown%20by%20muslim%20officers%20of%20high%20rank%2C%20like%20that%20displayed%20by%20the%20chinese%20themselves%2C%20is%20to%20be%20referred%2C%20not%20to%20religious&amp;f=false|title=Encyclopædia of religion and ethics, Volume 8|author=James Hastings, John Alexander Selbie, Louis Herbert Gray|year=1916|publisher=T. &amp; T. Clark|location=|page=893|isbn=|accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Hui people|Hui]] soldier of the 36th division called [[Sven Hedin]] a "foreign devil", which is a now antiquated Chinese slur referring to foreigners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?ei=xSoqTP2HJ4H6lwfb862jBA&amp;ct=result&amp;id=83ZCAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=sven+hedin+teach+this+foreign+devil&amp;q=foreign+devils|title=History of the expedition in Asia, 1927-1935, Part 3|first=Sven Hedin|coauthors=Folke Bergman, Gerhard Bexell, Birger Bohlin, Gösta Montell|year=1945|publisher=Göteborg, Elanders boktryckeri aktiebolag|location=|isbn=|page=78|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?ei=xSoqTP2HJ4H6lwfb862jBA&amp;ct=result&amp;id=rCtwAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=sven+hedin+teach+this+foreign+devil&amp;q=foreign+devils|title=The flight of "Big Horse": the trail of war in Central Asia|first=Sven Hedin|coauthors=Francis Hamilton Lyon|year=1936|publisher=E. P. Dutton and co., inc|location=|isbn=|page=92|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Tungans]] (Chinese Muslims) were reported to be "strongly anti-Japanese".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=IAs9AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA134&amp;lpg=PA134&amp;dq=ma+hushan&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=KzhNeXbjkT&amp;sig=raCQibpp88Cf8Unpi8k-7jcQM-k&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=xCcqTPnrCoGBlAfV5rzmAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CCIQ6AEwBQ#v=snippet&amp;q=anti%20japanese%20slogans&amp;f=false|title=Warlords and Muslims in Chinese Central Asia: a political history of Republican Sinkiang 1911-1949|author=Andrew D. W. Forbes|year=1986|publisher=CUP Archive|location=Cambridge, England|isbn=978-0-521-25514-1|page=130|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1930s, a [[Belarus|White Russian]] driver accompanying the Nazi agent [[Georg Vasel]] in [[Xinjiang]] was afraid to meet the [[Hui people|Hui]] General [[Ma Zhongying]], saying "You know how the Tungans hate the Russians." Tungan is another name for Chinese Muslim. Georg passed the Russian driver off as German to get through.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?ei=F543TPm9NoL48AaT6LWmBg&amp;ct=result&amp;id=WAEbAAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=my+russian+jailers&amp;q=tungans+hate+russians|title=My Russian jailers in China|author=Georg Vasel, Gerald Griffin|year=1937|publisher=Hurst &amp; Blackett|location=|page=143|isbn=|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the Chinese Muslim generals encountered by [[Peter Fleming (writer)|Peter Fleming]] was concerned that his visitor was a foreign "barbarian" and was only impressed when he found out his outlook was Chinese in nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6C2aaB3f9P4C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=news+from+tartary&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=0ygqTJyDI8L7lwfx2ZjgAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA#v=snippet&amp;q=general%20barbarian%20chinese%20outlook&amp;f=false|title=News from Tartary: A Journey from Peking to Kashmir|author=Peter Fleming|year=1999|publisher=Northwestern University Press|location=Evanston Illinois|isbn=0-8101-6071-4|page=308|accessdate=2010-06-28|authorlink=Peter Fleming (writer)}}&lt;/ref&gt; The racist atmosphere made a [[Uighur]] feel inclined to grovel at the General's feet when asking for help. Other Uighur notables were forced to pay respect to the General, while his soldiers showed contempt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6C2aaB3f9P4C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=news+from+tartary&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=0ygqTJyDI8L7lwfx2ZjgAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=turki%20grovelled%20general's%20feet&amp;f=false|title=News from Tartary: A Journey from Peking to Kashmir|author=Peter Fleming|year=1999|publisher=Northwestern University Press|location=Evanston Illinois|isbn=0-8101-6071-4|page=308|accessdate=2010-06-28|authorlink=Peter Fleming (writer)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=bEzNwgtiVQ0C&amp;pg=PA265&amp;dq=muslim+chinese+can+just+be+as+contemptuous+of+the+turkis&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=LqifTK6FIsKB8ga4nNF1&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=muslim%20chinese%20can%20just%20be%20as%20contemptuous%20of%20the%20turkis&amp;f=false|title=Wild West China: the taming of Xinjiang|author=Christian Tyler|year=2004|publisher=Rutgers University Press|location=New Brunswick, New Jersey|isbn=0-8135-3533-6|page=265|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racial slurs were allegedly used by the Chinese Muslim troops against Uighurs.&lt;ref name="Andrew D. W. Forbes 1986 307"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=IAs9AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA134&amp;lpg=PA134&amp;dq=ma+hushan&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=KzhNeXbjkT&amp;sig=raCQibpp88Cf8Unpi8k-7jcQM-k&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=xCcqTPnrCoGBlAfV5rzmAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CCIQ6AEwBQ#v=snippet&amp;q=turban%20heads%20simple%20minded&amp;f=false|title=Warlords and Muslims in Chinese Central Asia: a political history of Republican Sinkiang 1911-1949|author=Andrew D. W. Forbes|year=1986|publisher=CUP Archive|location=Cambridge, England|isbn=0-521-25514-7|page=307|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hui General [[Ma Qi]] launched a [[racial war]] against the Tibetan [[Ngolok]]s, in 1928, inflicting a defeat upon them and seizing the Labrang Buddhist monastery.{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}} The Hui had a feud against the Ngoloks for a long time.{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}} Ma Qi's Muslim forces also machine-gunned Tibetan monks and ravaged the monastery several times, leaving thousands dead in bloody battles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5OHPw6t0BhcC&amp;pg=PA123&amp;dq=ma+qi+muslim&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=pX-qTOXTFMP88AbioMSODQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwADgK#v=onepage&amp;q=ma%20qi%20muslim&amp;f=false|title=Chinese awakenings: life stories from the unofficial China|author=James Tyson, Ann Tyson|year=1995|publisher=Westview Press|location=|isbn=0-8133-2473-4|page=123|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=xGvECiS-uEgC&amp;pg=PA90&amp;dq=ma+qi+muslim&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=S3-qTP3bBoKC8gbpgKXhBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEoQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=ma%20qi%20muslim&amp;f=false|title=Labrang: a Tibetan Buddhist monastery at the crossroads of four civilizations|author=Paul Kocot Nietupski|year=1999|publisher=Snow Lion Publications|location=|isbn=1-55939-090-5|page=90|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1936, after [[Sheng Shicai]] expelled 20,000 Kazakhs from Xinjiang to Qinghai, [[Hui people|Hui]] led by General [[Ma Bufang]] massacred their fellow Muslim Kazakhs, until there were 135 of them left.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=m98sAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=A+group+of+Kazakhs,+originally+numbering+over+20000+people+when+expelled+from+Sinkiang+by+Sheng+Shih-ts'ai+in+1936,+was+reduced,+after+repeated+massacres+by+their+Chinese+coreligionists+under+Ma+Pu-fang,+to+a+scattered+135+people&amp;dq=A+group+of+Kazakhs,+originally+numbering+over+20000+people+when+expelled+from+Sinkiang+by+Sheng+Shih-ts'ai+in+1936,+was+reduced,+after+repeated+massacres+by+their+Chinese+coreligionists+under+Ma+Pu-fang,+to+a+scattered+135+people&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=B4OnTKDwKMKqlAfJgYmtDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAA|title=The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, Volume 277|author=American Academy of Political and Social Science|year=1951|publisher=American Academy of Political and Social Science|location=|page=152|isbn=|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NnY5AAAAMAAJ&amp;q=kazakhs+ma+pu-fang&amp;dq=kazakhs+ma+pu-fang&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=qcq0TJbgNMH-8Ab_ts3jCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwBw|title=Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, Volumes 276-278|author=American Academy of Political and Social Science|year=1951|publisher=American Academy of Political and Social Science|location=|page=152|isbn=|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Empress Dowager [[Empress Dowager Cixi|Cixi]] was known for her [[xenophobia]] against non-Chinese peoples despite being a non-Han Chinese herself, also using the term foreign devils to describe them. [[Lao She]], a Manchu writer, also called Europeans foreign devils.

==Ethnic slurs==

===Against Europeans and Westerners===
{{Main|Anti-Western sentiment in China}}

*[[Yang guizi|洋鬼子]] (yáng guǐzi) - "Western devil", a slur for [[White people]] or [[Caucasian race|Caucasians]] popularized during the [[Opium War]], when the British empire waged and won a war so that their merchants could legally sell opium. This term is not really used these days.
*鬼佬 (guǐlǎo) - Borrowed from Cantonese "[[Gweilo]]", literally "ghost guy", a slur for White people. 
*红毛 ([[Ang mo]]) - "Red Hair" or "Red Fur", a slur used by [[Hokkien]] ([[Min-nan]]) people in Taiwan and Singapore to primarily refer to Dutch colonists who settled in [[Taiwan]] and British colonists who settled in Singapore during the 17th century and early 19th century respectively.
*毛子 (máo zi) - literally “body hair”, it is a derogatory term against Caucasian peoples. However, because most white people in contact with China were Russians before the 19th century, 毛子 became a derogatory term specifically against Russians.&lt;ref&gt;2012-05-02, [http://www.focustt.com/2012/0502/12751.shtml 中俄军演刚结束:毛子这举动让北京狼狈不堪!] (China-Russia military exercises conclude, the actions of ''Mao zi'' make Beijing stuck in a dilemma), 环球视线&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;2012-08-26, [http://www.cankaoa.com/bbs/201208/thread_52633_1.html 毛子告诉中国：美国佬不敢惹俄罗斯只是因为这] (''Mao zi'' tell China: Yankees won't mess with Russia because of this), 参考啊&lt;/ref&gt;

The historian [[Frank Dikötter]] explains.
&lt;blockquote&gt;A common historical response to serious threats directed towards a symbolic universe is 'nihilation', or the conceptual liquidation of everything inconsistent with official doctrine. Foreigners were labelled 'barbarians' or 'devils' to be conceptually eliminated. The official rhetoric reduced the Westerner to a devil, a ghost, an evil and unreal goblin hovering on the border of humanity. Many texts of the first half of the nineteenth century referred to the English as 'foreign devils' (''yangguizi''), 'devil slaves' (''guinu''), 'barbarian devils' (''fangui''), 'island barbarians' (''daoyi''), 'blue-eyed barbarian slaves' (''biyan yinu''), or 'red-haired barbarians' (''hongmaofan'').&lt;ref&gt;Dikötter, Frank (1992). The Discourse of Race in Modern China. Stanford University Press, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Against Arabs===
*阿人(ā rén) - a slur used in reference to [[Arabs]], used by Chinese people in [[Europe]], especially [[France]]. "阿人" is short for "阿拉伯人(ā lā bó rén)", which is a phonetic translation of "Arab". This abbreviation was used to make sure Arabs don't recognize the pronunciation when eavesdropping on conversations. However, it's unclear if this term is meant to be derogatory or not.

===Against indigenous peoples===
*番鬼 (Fan Guai) -  a slur that is used by some Southern Chinese from the Guangdong area to refer to foreigners, where 番 (Fan) means "Tribal people". In the past, The [[Minnan]] and [[Chaozhou]] people used 山番 (mountain tribal people) and 生番 (raw tribal people) to describe the [[Taiwanese aborigines|natives and aboriginals of Taiwan]].

===Against Japanese===
[[File:2012 Anti-Japan demonstrations7.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Demonstrators in Taiwan host signs telling "Japanese devils" to "get out" of the [[Senkaku Islands]] following an escalation in disputes in 2012.]]
*[[Xiao riben|小日本]] (xiǎo Rìběn) — Literally "little Japan"(ese). This term is so common that it has very little impact left (Google Search returns 21,000,000 results as of August 2007). The term can be used to refer to either Japan or individual Japanese. "小", or the word "little", is usually construed as "puny", "lowly" or "small country", but not "spunky".
*[[Riben guizi|日本鬼子]] (Rìběn guǐzi) — Literally "Japanese devil". This is used mostly in the context of the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]], when Japan invaded and occupied large areas of China. This is the title of [[Japanese Devils|a Japanese documentary on Japanese war crimes during WWII]].
*倭 (Wō) — An ancient [[Chinese language|Chinese]] name for Japan, but it was also adopted by the Japanese, pronounced [[Wa (Japan)|Wa]]. In current Chinese usage, Wō is usually intended to give a negative connotation (see Wōkòu below). Two commonly proposed etymologies for this word are "submissive; obedient" or "dwarf; short person".&lt;ref&gt;Carr, Michael (1992). "Wa 倭 Wa 和 Lexicography." ''International Journal of Lexicography'' 5.1, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 7th century, Japanese scribes replaced 倭 (Wō/Wa) with 和  (Hé/Wa) meaning "harmony."
*倭寇 (Wōkòu) — Originally referred to Japanese pirates and armed sea merchants who raided the Chinese coastline during the [[Ming Dynasty]] (see [[Wokou]]). The term was adopted during the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]] to refer to invading Japanese forces, (similarly to Germans being called [[Hun]]s). 
*自慰队 (zì wèi duì) - A pun on the homophone "自卫队" (zì wèi duì, literally "Self-Defence Forces", see [[Japan Self-Defense Forces]]), the definition of 慰 (wèi) used is "to comfort". This phrase is used to refer to Japanese (whose military force is known as "自卫队") being stereotypically hypersexual, as "自慰队" means "Self-comforting Forces", referring to [[masturbation]].
*架佬 (Ga Lou)-A neutral term for Japanese used by Cantonese (especially Hong Kong Cantonese), because Japanese use a lot of "Ga" at the end of a sentence. 架妹 (Ga Mui) is used for female Japanese.
* 蘿蔔頭 (Lo Baat Tau) — Literally meaning "Radish Head," used by the Cantonese to refer to the Japanese during World War II. This term was a reference to the popular Japanese hair style at the time which was regarded as making their heads look like a [[Daikon|white radish]].

===Against Koreans===
*[[:zh:高麗棒子|高丽棒子]] (Gāolì bàng zǐ) - Derogatory term used against all ethnic Koreans. 高丽 ([[Traditional Chinese character|Traditional]]: 高麗) refers to Ancient Korea ([[Goryeo|Koryo]]), while 棒子 means ''"club"'' or ''"corncob"'', referring to the weapon used by the puppet Korean police during the Anti-Japanese War of China.
*[[Er guizi|二鬼子]] (èr guǐ zǐ)&lt;ref name=people20111216&gt;[http://dangshi.people.com.cn/BIG5/16632423.html 第一滴血──從日方史料還原平型關之戰日軍損失 (6)] News of the Communist Party of China December 16, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; - A disparaging designation of puppet armies and traitors during the Anti-Japanese War of China.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nciku.com/search/zh/detail/%E4%BA%8C%E9%AC%BC%E5%AD%90/99788?query=during&amp;internal=true Comprehensive Chinese-English Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://us.mdbg.net/chindict/chindict.php?page=worddict&amp;wdqchi=%E4%BA%8C%E9%AC%BC%E5%AD%90&amp;wdrst=0&amp;wdqchim=3&amp;wddmtm=1 mdbg Chinese English Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese were known as "鬼子" (devil), and the 二鬼子 literally means "second devils". During World War II, some [[Korean people|Koreans]] were involved in Imperial Japanese Army, and so 二鬼子 refers to [[hanjian]] and ethnic Koreans. The definition of 二鬼子 has changed throughout time{{Or|date=September 2008}}, with modern slang usage entirely different from its original meaning during World War II and the subsequent [[Chinese civil war]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}}

===Against Africans and Blacks===
*黑鬼 (hei guǐ) - "Black devil"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/opinion/2009-07/31/content_8496740.htm|title= The disunited colors of prejudice|author= Hooi, Alexis|date= 2009-07-31|work= |publisher= China Daily|accessdate=2009-11-24|quote= Even now, some Guangzhou residents might admit using the generic and derogatory term "hei gui" or "ghost" to refer to Africans in the community.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Against Indians===
*阿差 (Ah Cha)-Ah Cha means "Good" in some Indian languages, is a derogatory Cantonese term used against Indians. During the 1950s-1970s, there were many Indians working in Hong Kong as laborers, or doormen, especially doormen for hotels.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}
*阿三 (A Sae) or 红头阿三 (Ghondeu Asae) - Originally a Shanghainese term used against South Asians. This term is now used in Mandarin as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.edubridge.com/erxiantang/l2/asan.htm|title=上海滩的"红头阿三"|author= |date= |work= |publisher=|accessdate=2010-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Against Uyghurs===
*Ch'an-t'ou (纏頭; turban heads) (used during the Republican period)&lt;ref name="Andrew D. W. Forbes 1986 307"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Garnaut"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ouigour.fr/recherches_et_analyses/Garnautpage_93.pdf|title=From Yunnan to Xinjiang:Governor Yang Zengxin and his Dungan Generals|last=Garnaut|first=Anthony|publisher=Pacific and Asian History, Australian National University)|accessdate=2010-07-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*nao-tzu-chien-tan (脑子简单; simple-minded) (used during the Republican period)&lt;ref name="Andrew D. W. Forbes 1986 307"/&gt;

===Against mixed races===
*erzhuanzi (二转子) children who are mixed Uyghur and Han.&lt;ref name="David Westerlund, Ingvar Svanberg 1999 204"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Ildikó Bellér-Hann 2007 223"/&gt; This term "Erh-hun-tze", was said by European explorers in the 19th century to refer to a people who were descended from a mixture of Chinese, Taghliks, and Mongols living in the area from Ku-ch'eng-tze to Barköl in Xinjiang.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=yBO3pmzzhWkC&amp;pg=PA526&amp;dq=erh-hun-tze+a+mongols+chinese+inhabit&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=81-GTazoJYHQgAfrnfDYCA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=erh-hun-tze%20a%20mongols%20chinese%20inhabit&amp;f=false|title=Journal Of Urusvati Himalayan Research Institute, Volumes 1-3|author=Roerich Museum, George Roerich|year=2003|publisher=Vedams eBooks (P) Ltd|location=|page=526|isbn=81-7936-011-3|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Orthographic pejoratives==
{{main|Graphic pejoratives in written Chinese}}

Some [[Chinese characters]] used to [[transcription into Chinese characters|transcribe]] non-Chinese peoples were graphically pejorative [[ethnic slurs]], where the insult derived not from the Chinese word but from the character used to write it. Take for instance, the [[Written Chinese]] transcription of ''Yao'' "the [[Yao people]]", who primarily live in the mountains of southwest China and Vietnam. When 11th-century [[Song Dynasty]] authors first transcribed the [[exonym]] ''Yao'', they insultingly chose ''yao'' 猺 "jackal" from a lexical selection of over 100 characters pronounced ''yao'' (e.g., 腰 "waist", 遙 "distant", 搖 "shake"). During a series of 20th-century Chinese [[language reform]]s, this graphic pejorative [[wikt:猺|猺]] (written with the 犭"[[Radical 94|dog/beast radical]]") "jackal; the Yao" was replaced twice; first with the invented character ''yao'' [[wikt:傜|傜]] (亻"[[Radical 9|human radical]]") "the Yao", then with ''yao'' [[wikt:瑤|瑤]] (玉 "[[Radical 96|jade radical]]") "precious jade; the Yao." Chinese [[orthography]] (symbols used to write a language) can provide unique opportunities to write ethnic insults [[Logograph|logographically]] that do not exist alphabetically. For the Yao ethnic group, there is a difference between the transcriptions ''Yao'' 猺 "jackal" and ''Yao'' 瑤 "jade" but none between the [[Chinese romanization|romanizations]] ''Yao'' and ''Yau''.

==See also==

* [[Anti-Manchuism]]
* [[Fenqing]]
* [[Hua-Yi distinction]]
* [[Hui pan-nationalism]]
* [[Sinocentrism]]
* [[2011 Chaozhou riot]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{ChineseText}}

==Additional source==
*{{zh icon}}[http://ncn.org/view.php?id=77002 程映虹︰80年代的校園反黑人運動 漫談中國的種族主義]

{{Racism topics}}
{{Asia topic|Racism in}}
{{Ethnic issues}}

[[Category:Racism by country|China]]
[[Category:People's Republic of China culture]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>