<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091002225457|317547391" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1435066" pageid="1435066" ns="0" title="Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-10-04T11:17:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- UN-related article; UN spelling/stylistic conventions--&gt;

{{Infobox Treaty
| name                = Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination against Women
| long_name           =
| image               = Weaving profile.jpg
| image_width         = 225px
| caption             =
| type                =
| date_drafted        =
| date_signed         = [[18 December]] [[1979]]
| location_signed     = [[New York City]]
| date_sealed         =
| date_effective      = [[3 September]] [[1981]]
| condition_effective = 20 ratifications
| date_expiration     =
| signatories         =
| parties             = 186 ([[List of parties to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women|Complete List]])
| depositor           =
| language            =
| languages           =
| website             =
| wikisource          = Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women
}}
[[Image:CEDAW Participation.svg|right|400px|thumb| Participation in the CEDAW {{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
{{legend|#00aa00|Signed and ratified}}
{{legend|#008000|Acceded or succeeded}}
{{legend|#008080|Unrecognized state, abiding by treaty}}
{{Col-2}}
{{legend|#eeee00|Only signed}}
{{legend|#ff1111|Non-signatory}}
{{Col-end}}
]]

The '''Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination against Women''' ('''CEDAW''') is an international convention adopted in [[1979]] by the [[United Nations]] [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]]. 
Described as an international [[bill of rights]] for [[woman|women]], it came into force on [[3 September]] [[1981]]. The [[United States]] is the only developed nation that has not ratified the CEDAW. Several countries have ratified the Convention subject to certain declarations, reservations and objections.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/reservations-country.htm Declarations, Reservations and Objections to CEDAW]&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Convention==
The Convention defines discrimination against women in the following terms:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Any distinction, exclusion or restriction made on the basis of sex which has the effect or purpose of impairing or nullifying the recognition, enjoyment or exercise by women, irrespective of their marital status, on a basis of equality of men and women, of human rights and fundamental freedoms in the political, economic, social, cultural, civil or any other field.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

It also establishes an agenda of action for putting an end to sex-based discrimination: 
States ratifying the Convention are required to enshrine [[gender equality]] into their domestic legislation, repeal all discriminatory provisions in their laws, and enact new provisions to guard against discrimination against women. They must also establish tribunals and public institutions to guarantee women effective protection against discrimination, and take steps to eliminate all forms of discrimination practiced against women by individuals, organizations, and enterprises.

==Members and ratification==
{{Main|List of parties to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women}}

The six UN member states that have not signed the convention are [[Iran]], [[Nauru]], [[Palau]], [[Somalia]], [[Sudan]], and [[Tonga]]. These are either Islamic states (Iran, Somalia, Sudan) or small Pacific Island nations (Nauru, Palau, Tonga). [[Niue]] and the [[Vatican City]] have also not signed it. The [[United States]] has signed, but not yet ratified.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/protocol/CEDAW%20Ratification%20Table%20IV-8.en.pdf Member states]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, after much pressure from women's organizations such as the [[National Alliance of Taiwan Women's Associations]], Taiwan's [[Legislative Yuan]] ratified the stipulations of CEDAW into its own domestic policy. It is still awaiting CEDAW's approval of its ratification.&lt;ref&gt;Government Information Office, Republic of China (Taiwan). "Taiwan Aims to Sign Up Against Discrimination." September 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women==
Convention oversight is the task of the '''Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women''', which is made up of 23 experts on women's issues from different UN member states. The Committee meets twice a year to review reports on compliance with the Convention's provisions that the signatory nations are required to submit every four years.

The Committee is one of the eight [[Human rights#Other UN Treaty Bodies|UN-related human rights treaty bodies]].

The Committee's members, described as "experts of high moral standing and competence in the field covered by the Convention", are elected to serve four-year terms in staggered elections held every two years. Its officers are a chairperson, three vice-chairpersons, and a rapporteur.  Efforts are made to ensure balanced geographical representation and the inclusion of the world's different forms of civilization and legal systems.

As of January 2007, the members are:

{| class="wikitable"
|- bgcolor="#ebf5ff"
!No.
!Country
!Name
!Position
|- bgcolor="#ebf5ff"
|-
| 1. || {{flagicon|Croatia}} [[Croatia]] || Dubravka Šimonović  || Chairperson
|-
| 2. || {{flagicon|Egypt}} [[Egypt]] || Naela Mohamed Gabr || 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Vice-Chairperson
|-
| 3. || {{flagicon|France}} [[France]] || Françoise Gaspard || 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; Vice-Chairperson
|-
| 4. || {{flagicon|Jamaica}} [[Jamaica]]  || Glenda P. Simms || 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; Vice-Chairperson
|-
| 5. || {{flagicon|Bangladesh}} [[Bangladesh]]  || Ferdous Ara Begum || Member
|-
| 6. || {{flagicon|Cuba}} [[Cuba]]  || Magalys Arocha Dominguez || Member
|-
| 7. || {{flagicon|Thailand}} [[Thailand]]  || Saisuree Chutikul || Member
|-
| 8. || {{flagicon|Algeria}} [[Algeria]]  || Meriem Belmihoub-Zerdani || Member
|-
| 9. || {{flagicon|Ghana}} [[Ghana]] || Dorcas Coker-Appiah|| Member
|-
| 10. || {{flagicon|Netherlands}} [[The Netherlands]] || Cornelis Flinterman  || Member
|-
| 11. || {{flagicon|Israel}} [[Israel]]  || Ruth Halperin-Kaddari || Member
|-
| 12. || {{flagicon|Italy}} [[Italy]]   || Tiziana Maiolo || Member
|-
| 13. || {{flagicon|Slovenia}} [[Slovenia]]  || Violeta Neubauer  || Member
|-
| 14. ||  {{flagicon|Mauritius}} [[Mauritius]]  || Pramila Patten || Member
|-
| 15. || {{flagicon|Brazil}} [[Brazil]] || Silvia Pimente || Member
|-
| 16. || {{flagicon|Japan}} [[Japan]] || Fumiko Saiga || Member
|-
| 17. || {{flagicon|Germany}} [[Germany]] || Hanna Beate Schöpp-Schilling || Member
|-
| 18. || {{flagicon|South Korea}} [[South Korea]] || Heisoo Shin || Member
|-
| 19. || {{flagicon|Singapore}} [[Singapore]]  || Anamah Tan || Member
|-
| 20. || {{flagicon|Portugal}} [[Portugal]] || Maria Regina Tavares da Silva || Member
|-
| 21. || {{flagicon|China}} [[China]] || Zou Xiaoqiao || Member
|-
| 22. || {{flagicon|Malaysia}} [[Malaysia]]  || Mary Shanthi Dairiam || Member and Rapporteur
|-
|}

==Optional Protocol==

The '''[[Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]]''' is a side-agreement to the Convention which allows its parties to recognise the competence of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women to consider complaints from individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/instree/cedawopprot-2000.html Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women], Article 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Optional Protocol was adopted by the UN General Assembly on [[6 October]] [[1999]] and entered into force on [[22 December]] [[2000]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/protocol/wom1242.htm |title=Optional Protocol to Women's Convention Comes into Force |date=2000-12-21 |accessdate=2008-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently it has 79 signatories and 98 parties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8-b&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en |title= Parties to the Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women |publisher=UN OHCHR |accessdate=2009-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
The CEDAW has been controversial for statements seen by [[Concerned Women for America]] as promoting [[radical feminism]].  Particularly referenced is a 2000 report which said that in [[Belarus]], "the Committee is concerned by the continuing prevalence of sex-role stereotypes and by the reintroduction of such symbols as a [[Mothers' Day]] and a Mothers' Award, which it sees as encouraging women's traditional roles."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/reports/a5538.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  Other controversial positions of CEDAW include supporting the decriminalization of prostitution in specific countries, criticizing Slovenia because only 30% of children are in daycare, demanding equal treatment for work of "equal value", and a treaty requirement that nations "embody the principle of the equality of men and women in their national constitution or other appropriate legislation." These requests are seen by Concerned Women for America and other [[antifeminist]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Marshall, Susan E.|title=Splintered sisterhood: gender and class in the campaign against woman suffrage|page=231|publisher=University of Wisconsin Press|date=1997}}&lt;!-- source only identifies CWA as an "antifemnist" organization--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Christian Right]] groups as a backdoor to an [[Equal Rights Amendment]] or comparable national legislation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cwfa.org/articledisplay.asp?id=1971 Concerned Women for America - Exposing CEDAW&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Australian and (defunct) New Zealand anti-feminist groups{{Weasel-inline|date=March 2009}} voiced similar concerns in the early eighties.

More recently, the controversy concerning CEDAW has centered around the question of easy access to abortion and contraception.  According to C-FAM (the [[Catholic Family and Human Rights Institute]]), at UN meetings officials pressed the delegation from Colombia to liberalize its abortion laws and to inaugurate campaigns encouraging contraceptive use and "reproductive health awareness".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.c-fam.org/publications/id.664/pub_detail.asp |title=UN Committee Pressures Slovakia over its Concordat with the Catholic Church}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many [[Islamic]] countries view the CEDAW as culturally biased towards the Western nations and have consequently placed reservations on the elements that they see as in fundamental contradiction with Islamic [[Sharia]] law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/reservations-country.htm |title=Declarations, Reservations and Objections to CEDAW  |publisher=UN Division for the Advancement of Women |accessdate=2008-01-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[Equal Rights Amendment]]
* [[Parental leave]]
* [[Declaration on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/index.htm CEDAW site]
* [http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/cedaw.htm Convention text]
* [http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en List of parties]
* [http://www.unifem-eseasia.org/projects/Cedaw/cedawseap.html/ CEDAW Southeast Asia Programme (CEDAW SEAP) funded by [[Canadian International Development Agency]]]
* [http://www.bayefsky.com Bayefsky Website has hard-to-find reports for UN Human Rights Treaties, including CEDAW reports, in accessible formats such as pdf and word documents]
* [http://www.imow.org/wpp/stories/viewStory?storyId=1849 An article about CEDAW in San Francisco, California, USA] by the [[International Museum of Women]].

{{International human rights legal instruments}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Convention On The Elimination Of All Forms Of Discrimination Against Women}}
[[Category:1979 in law]]
[[Category:Discrimination law]]
[[Category:United Nations conventions and covenants]]
[[Category:Reproductive rights]]
[[Category:Human rights instruments]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]
[[Category:20th-century treaties]]

[[de:Übereinkommen zur Beseitigung jeder Form von Diskriminierung der Frau]]
[[et:Konventsioon naiste diskrimineerimise kõigi vormide likvideerimise kohta]]
[[es:Convención sobre la Eliminación de todas las Formas de Discriminación contra la Mujer]]
[[fa:کنوانسیون امحای کلیه اشکال تبعیض علیه زنان]]
[[fr:Convention sur l'élimination de toutes les formes de discrimination à l'égard des femmes]]
[[gl:Convención sobre a eliminación de todas as formas de discriminación contra a muller]]
[[nl:Verdrag inzake de Uitbanning van alle Vormen van Discriminatie van Vrouwen]]
[[ja:女子に対するあらゆる形態の差別の撤廃に関する条約]]
[[ru:Конвенция о ликвидации всех форм дискриминации в отношении женщин]]
[[sv:FN:s kvinnokonvention]]
[[th:อนุสัญญาว่าด้วยการขจัดการเลือกปฏิบัติต่อสตรีในทุกรูปแบบ]]
[[tr:Kadına Karşı Her Türlü Ayrımcılığın Yok Edilmesi Sözleşmesi]]
[[war:CEDAW]]
[[zh:消除對婦女一切形式歧視公約]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>