<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071105111010|169356047" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1435066" pageid="1435066" ns="0" title="Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-06T21:05:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- UN-related article; UN spelling/stylistic conventions--&gt;
{{Treatybox|
treaty_name=Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women
|colour_scheme=background:pink
|image=[[Image:Weaving profile.jpg|center|225px]]
|caption=|place_signed=[[New York City]]
|date_signed=[[18 December]] [[1979]]
|date_entered_into_force=[[3 September]] [[1981]]
|conditions_for_entry_into_force=20 ratifications
|parties=185&lt;ref&gt;http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/states.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
|}}
&lt;!--Needs to be updated [[Image:CEDAW-members.PNG|thumb|right|400px|Parties to the CEDAW: members in dark green, countries which have signed but not ratified in light green, non-members in grey]]--&gt;

The '''Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women''' ('''CEDAW''') is an international convention adopted in [[1979]] by the [[United Nations]] [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]]. 
Described as an international [[bill of rights]] for [[woman|women]], it came into force on [[3 September]] [[1981]]. The [[United States]] is the only developed nation that has not ratified the CEDAW. 

==The Convention==
The Convention defines discrimination against women in the following terms:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Any distinction, exclusion or restriction made on the basis of sex which has the effect or purpose of impairing or nullifying the recognition, enjoyment or exercise by women, irrespective of their marital status, on a basis of equality of men and women, of human rights and fundamental freedoms in the political, economic, social, cultural, civil or any other field.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

It also establishes an agenda of action for putting an end to sex-based discrimination: 
States ratifying the Convention are required to enshrine male/female equality into their domestic legislation, repeal all discriminatory provisions in their laws, and enact new provisions to guard against discrimination against women. They must also establish tribunals and public institutions to guarantee women effective protection against discrimination, and take steps to eliminate all forms of discrimination practised against women by individuals, organizations, and enterprises.

==Ratification==
===Taiwan===
In 2007,after much pressure from women's organizations such as the [[National Alliance of Taiwan Women's Associations]], Taiwan's [[Legislative Yuan]] ratified the stipulations of CEDAW into its own domestic policy. It is still awaiting CEDAW's approval of its ratification.&lt;ref&gt;Government Information Office, Republic of China (Taiwan). "Taiwan Aims to Sign Up Against Discrimination." September 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Committee==
Convention oversight is the task of the [[Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women]], which is made up of 23 experts on women's issues from different UN member states. The Committee meets twice a year to review reports on compliance with the Convention's provisions that the signatory nations are required to submit every four years.

The committee is one of the seven UN-linked [[human rights treaty bodies]].

The Committee's members, described as "experts of high moral standing and competence in the field covered by the Convention", are elected to serve four-year terms in staggered elections held every two years. Its officers are a chairperson, three vice-chairpersons, and a rapporteur.  Efforts are made to ensure balanced geographical representation and the inclusion of the world's different forms of civilization and legal systems.

As of January 2007, the members are:

* {{flagicon|Croatia}} [[Dubravka Šimonović]], Chair 
* {{flagicon|Egypt}} [[Naela Mohamed Gabr]], Vice-Chair 
* {{flagicon|France}} [[Françoise Gaspard]], Vice-Chair 
* {{flagicon|Jamaica}} [[Glenda P. Simms]], Vice-Chair 
* {{flagicon|Malaysia}} [[Mary Shanthi Dairiam]], Rapporteur 
* {{flagicon|Bangladesh}} [[Ferdous Ara Begum]] 
* {{flagicon|Cuba}} [[Magalys Arocha Dominguez]] 
* {{flagicon|Thailand}} [[Saisuree Chutikul]] 
* {{flagicon|Algeria}} [[Meriem Belmihoub-Zerdani]] 
* {{flagicon|Ghana}} [[Dorcas Coker-Appiah]] 
* {{flagicon|Netherlands}} [[Cornelis Flinterman]] 
* {{flagicon|Israel}} [[Ruth Halperin-Kaddari]] 
* {{flagicon|Italy}} [[Tiziana Maiolo]] 
* {{flagicon|Slovenia}} [[Violeta Neubauer]] 
* {{flagicon|Mauritius}} [[Pramila Patten]] 
* {{flagicon|Brazil}} [[Silvia Pimentel]] 
* {{flagicon|Japan}} [[Fumiko Saiga]] 
* {{flagicon|Germany}} [[Hanna Beate Schöpp-Schilling]] 
* {{flagicon|South Korea}} [[Heisoo Shin]] 
* {{flagicon|Singapore}} [[Anamah Tan]] 
* {{flagicon|Portugal}} [[Maria Regina Tavares da Silva]] 
* {{flagicon|China}} [[Zou Xiaoqiao]]

==Optional Protocol==
In 1999, the General Assembly of the United Nations adopted the Optional Protocol of CEDAW.  The Protocol includes a procedure through which individual women or groups can denounce national violations of CEDAW directly to CEDAW’s committee of experts.  As of July 2007, 88 states had ratified the Protocol.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/protocol/sigop.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
The CEDAW has been controversial for statements seen by some as promoting [[radical feminism]].  Particularly referenced is a 2000 report which said that in [[Belarus]], "the Committee is concerned by the continuing prevalence of sex-role stereotypes and by the reintroduction of such symbols as a [[Mothers' Day]] and a Mothers' Award, which it sees as encouraging women's traditional roles."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/reports/a5538.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  Also in 2000, a report on [[Austria]] linked [[privatization]] with "[[Far right|right-wing extremism]]" &lt;ref&gt;http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/23sess.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and suggested that the government use "federal funding for political parties as an incentive for the increased representation of women in Parliament" and "integrate gender studies and feminist research in university curricula and research programmes" &lt;ref&gt;http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/cedaw23/Austria%20as%20adopted.html&lt;/ref&gt;. Other controversial positions of CEDAW include supporting the decriminalization of prostitution, criticizing Slovenia because only 30% of children are in daycare, demanding equal treatment for work of "equal value", and a treaty requirement that nations "embody the principle of the equality of men and women in their national constitution or other appropriate legislation." These requests are seen by [[Concerned Women for America]] and other [[anti-feminist]] and [[Christian Right]] groups as a backdoor to an [[Equal Rights Amendment]] or comparable national legislation.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cwfa.org/articledisplay.asp?id=1971&lt;/ref&gt; Australian and (defunct) New Zealand anti-feminist groups voiced similar concerns in the early eighties.

More recently, the controversy concerning CEDAW has centered around the question of easy access to abortion and contraception.  According to C-FAM (the Catholic Family and Human Rights Institute), at UN meetings officials pressed the delegation from Colombia to liberalize its abortion laws and to inaugurate campaigns encouraging contraceptive use and "reproductive health awareness".

==Cultural bias==
Many [[Islamic]] countries view the CEDAW as culturally biased towards the Western nations and have consequently placed reservations on the elements that they see as in fundamental contradiction with Islamic [[Sharia]] law.

The seven UN member states that have not signed the convention are [[Iran]], [[Nauru]], [[Palau]], [[Qatar]], [[Somalia]], [[Sudan]], and [[Tonga]]. These are either Islamic states (Iran, Qatar, Somalia, Sudan) or small Pacific Island nations (Nauru, Palau, Tonga). [[Niue]] and the [[Vatican City]] have also not signed it. The [[United States]] has signed, but not yet ratified.

==See also==

* [[Equal Rights Amendment]]
* [[Parental leave]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikisource}}
* [http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/ CEDAW site with links to full text of document, country reports, lists of reservations stated by particular countries, etc.]
* [http://www.unifem-eseasia.org/projects/Cedaw/cedawseap.html/ CEDAW Southeast Asia Programme (CEDAW SEAP) funded by [[Canadian International Development Agency]]]

[[Category:1979 in law]]
[[Category:United Nations conventions and covenants]]
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Human rights instruments]]

[[de:Übereinkommen zur Beseitigung jeder Form von Diskriminierung der Frau]]
[[et:Konventsioon naiste diskrimineerimise kõigi vormide likvideerimise kohta]]
[[es:Convención sobre la eliminación de todas las formas de discriminación contra la mujer]]
[[nl:Verdrag inzake de Uitbanning van alle Vormen van Discriminatie van Vrouwen]]
[[ja:女子に対するあらゆる形態の差別の撤廃に関する条約]]
[[sv:FN:s kvinnokonvention]]
[[tr:Kadına Karşı Her Türlü Ayrımcılığın Yok Edilmesi Sözleşmesi]]
[[war:CEDAW]]
[[zh:消除對婦女一切形式歧視公約]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>