<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20190925064203|917737657" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1435066" pageid="1435066" ns="0" title="Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-13T01:05:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{use dmy dates|date=May 2013}}
&lt;!-- UN-related article; UN spelling/stylistic conventions--&gt;
{{Infobox treaty
| name                = CEDAW
| long_name           = Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination Against Women
| image               = CEDAW Participation.svg
| image_width         = 250 px
| caption             = {{legend|#00aa00|Party through Signature and ratification}}
{{legend|#008000|Party through accession or succession}}
{{legend|#008080|Unrecognized state, abiding by treaty}}
{{legend|#eeee00|Only signed}}
{{legend|#ff1111|Non-signatory}}
| type                = 
| date_drafted        = 
| date_signed         = 18 December 1979
| location_signed     = New York City
|behen      = 
| date_effective      = 3 September 1981
| condition_effective = 20 ratifications
| date_expiration     = 
| signatories         = 99
| parties             = 189 ([[List of parties to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women|Complete List]])
| depositor           = Secretary-General of the United Nations
| language            = 
| languages           = Arabic, Chinese, English, French, Russian and Spanish
| website             = 
| wikisource          = Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women
}}

The '''Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination Against Women''' ('''CEDAW''') is an international treaty adopted in 1979 by the [[United Nations General Assembly]].
Described as an international [[bill of rights]] for women, it was instituted on 3 September 1981 and has been ratified by 189 states.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en|title=United Nations Treaty Collection|website=un.org|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150906035454/https://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en|archivedate=6 September 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over fifty countries that have ratified the Convention have done so subject to certain declarations, reservations, and objections, including 38 countries who rejected the enforcement article 29, which addresses means of settlement for disputes concerning the interpretation or application of the Convention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/reservations-country.htm |title=Declarations, Reservations and Objections to CEDAW |publisher=Un.org |accessdate=2011-09-27 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111222104936/http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/reservations-country.htm |archivedate=22 December 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Australia's declaration noted the limitations on central government power resulting from its federal constitutional system. The [[United States]] and [[Palau]] have signed, but not ratified the treaty. The [[Holy See]], [[Iran]], [[Somalia]], [[Sudan]], and [[Tonga]] are not signatories to CEDAW.

The CEDAW Chairperson position is currently held by [[Hilary Gbedemah]].&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ohchr.org/EN/HRBodies/CEDAW/Pages/Membership.aspx|title=OHCHR {{!}} Membership|website=www.ohchr.org|access-date=2019-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Convention==

=== Summary ===
The Convention has a similar format to the [[International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination|Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]], "both with regard to the scope of its substantive obligations and its international monitoring mechanisms".&lt;ref name=":2"/&gt; The Convention is structured in six parts with 30 articles total.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web |title=Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women |url=http://www.ohchr.org/EN/ProfessionalInterest/Pages/CEDAW.aspx |website=www.ohchr.org |accessdate=2015-05-08 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150507222247/http://www.ohchr.org/EN/ProfessionalInterest/Pages/CEDAW.aspx |archivedate=7 May 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Part I''' (Articles 1-6) focuses on non-discrimination, sex stereotypes, and sex trafficking.
* '''Part II''' (Articles 7-9) outlines women's rights in the public sphere with an emphasis on political life, representation, and rights to nationality.
* '''Part III''' (Articles 10-14) describes the economic and social rights of women, particularly focusing on education, employment, and health. Part III also includes special protections for rural women and the problems they face.
* '''Part IV''' (Article 15 and 16) outlines women's right to equality in marriage and family life along with the right to equality before the law.
* '''Part V''' (Articles 17-22) establishes the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women as well as the states parties' reporting procedure.
* '''Part VI''' (Articles 23-30) describes the effects of the Convention on other treaties, the commitment of the states parties and the administration of the Convention.

=== Core Provisions ===
'''Article 1''' defines [[Sexism|discrimination against women]] in the following terms:&lt;blockquote&gt;Any distinction, exclusion or restriction made on the basis of sex which has the effect or purpose of impairing or nullifying the recognition, enjoyment or exercise by women, irrespective of their marital status, on a basis of equality of men and [[Women's rights|women]], of human rights and fundamental freedoms in the political, economic, social, cultural, civil or any other field.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;'''Article 2''' mandates that states parties ratifying the Convention declare intent to enshrine [[gender equality]] into their domestic legislation, repeal all discriminatory provisions in their laws, and enact new provisions to guard against discrimination against women.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; States ratifying the Convention must also establish tribunals and public institutions to guarantee women effective protection against discrimination, and take steps to eliminate all forms of discrimination practiced against women by individuals, organizations, and enterprises.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 3''' requires states parties to guarantee basic human rights and fundamental freedoms to women "on a basis of equality with men" through the "political, social, economic, and cultural fields."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 4''' notes that "[a]doption...of special measures aimed at accelerating [[de facto]] equality between men and women shall not be considered discrimination." It adds that special protection for [[maternity]] is not regarded as gender discrimination.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 5''' requires states parties to take measures to seek to eliminate prejudices and customs based on the idea of the inferiority or the superiority of one sex or on [[stereotype]]d [[gender role|role for men and women]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; It also mandates the states parties "[t]o ensure...the recognition of the common responsibility of men and women in the upbringing and development of their children."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 6''' obliges states parties to "take all appropriate measures, including legislation, to suppress all forms of [[trafficking in women]] and [[Forced prostitution|exploitation of prostitution]] of women."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 7''' guarantees women equality in political and public life with a focus on equality in [[Suffrage|voting]], participation in government, and participation in "non-governmental organizations and associations concerned with the public and political life of the country."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 8''' provides that states parties will guarantee women's equal "opportunity to represent their Government at the international level and to participate in the work of [[international organizations]]."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 9''' mandates state parties to "grant women equal rights with men to acquire, change or retain their [[nationality]]" and equal rights "with respect to the nationality of their children."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 10''' necessitates equal opportunity in education for female students and encourages [[mixed-sex education|coeducation]]. It also provides equal access to athletics, scholarships and grants as well as requires "reduction in female students' drop out rates."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 11''' outlines the [[right to work]] for women as "an [[unalienable rights|unalienable right]] of all human beings." It requires [[equal pay for equal work]], the [[right to social security]], [[paid leave]] and [[maternity leave]] "with pay or with comparable [[social benefits]] without loss of former employment, seniority or social allowances." Dismissal on the grounds of maternity, [[pregnancy]] or status of marriage shall be prohibited with sanction.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 12''' creates the obligation of states parties to "take all appropriate measures to eliminate discrimination against women in the field of healthcare in order to ensure...access to health care services, including those related to [[family planning]]."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 13''' guarantees equality to women "in economic and social life," especially with respect to "the right to family benefits, the right to bank loans, mortgages and other forms of financial credit, and the right to participate in recreational activities, sports and all aspects of cultural life."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 14''' provides protections for rural women and their special problems, ensuring the right of women to participate in development programs, "to have access to adequate health care facilities," "to participate in all community activities," "to have access to agricultural credit" and "to enjoy adequate living conditions."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 15''' obliges states parties to guarantee "women equality with men before the law," including "a [[Capacity (law)|legal capacity]] identical to that of men." It also accords "to men and women the same rights with regard to the law relating to the [[freedom of movement|movement of persons]] and the freedom to choose their residence and domicile."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Article 16''' prohibits "discrimination against women in all matters relating to marriage and family relations." In particular, it provides men and women with "the same right to enter into marriage, the same right freely to choose a spouse," "the same [[Marriage law|rights and responsibilities during marriage]] and at its dissolution," "the same rights and responsibilities as parents," "the same rights to decide freely and responsibly on the number and spacing of their children," "the same personal rights as husband and wife, including the right to choose a family name, a profession and an occupation" "the same rights for both spouses in respect of the ownership, acquisition, management, administration, enjoyment and disposition of property, whether free of charge or for a valuable consideration."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

'''Articles 17 - 24''' These articles describe the composition and procedures of the CEDAW Committee,like the hierarchical structure and rules and regulations of systematic procedure of the relationship between CEDAW and national and international legislation and the obligation of States to take all steps necessary to implement CEDAW in full form.&lt;ref name="gov.uk"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/convention-on-the-elimination-of-all-forms-of-discrimination-against-women-cedaw-articles|title=Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women (CEDAW) Articles - GOV.UK|website=www.gov.uk|access-date=2017-10-16|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171016175827/https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/convention-on-the-elimination-of-all-forms-of-discrimination-against-women-cedaw-articles|archivedate=16 October 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Articles 25 - 30'''  (Administration of CEDAW)

These articles describe the general administrative procedures concerning enforcement of CEDAW, ratification and entering reservations of concerned states.&lt;ref name="gov.uk"/&gt;

==CEDAW with UNSCR 1325 and 1820==
[[File:Map5.1Discrepant Behavior compressed.jpg|right|400px|thumb| A world map showing countries by CEDAW enforcement, 2010.]]
'''Resolutions 1325 10th anniversary events highlight use of CEDAW mechanisms&lt;ref name="gnwp"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnwp.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/Cedaw-1325-1820-synergy2.pdf |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120501140626/http://www.gnwp.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/Cedaw-1325-1820-synergy2.pdf |url-status=dead |archive-date=2012-05-01 |title=Ensuring Accountability to UNSCR 1325 and 1820 using CEDAW reporting mechanisms |date=November 2010 |website=gnwp.org |publisher=Global Network of Women Peacebuilders |accessdate=5 July 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;'''

The 10th anniversary of Resolution 1325 in October 2010 highlighted the increasing demand for accountability to UN Security Council Resolution 1325 on Women, Peace and Security. Many expressed concern about the fact that only 22 Member States out of 192 have adopted national action plans. Women are still underrepresented, if not totally absent, in most official peace negotiations and sexual violence in peacetime and in conflict continue to increase.

These realities emphasized the need to use external legal mechanisms to strengthen the implementation of SCR 1325, particularly CEDAW. The well-established mechanisms of CEDAW – the Member States compliance report and the civil society shadow reporting process were cited as possible instruments to ensure accountability.

Several regional and international meetings including the High Level Seminar "1325 in 2020: Looking Forward…Looking Back," organized by the African Center for the Constructive Resolution of Disputes, and the "Stockholm International Conference 10 years with 1325 – What now?" called for the use of CEDAW to improve 1325 implementation.

'''Intersection between SCR 1325 and CEDAW
'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnwp.org/written-statement-submitted-to-cedaw-on-the-occasion-of-the-general-discussion-on-women-in-conflict-and-post-conflict-situations |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110723130833/http://www.gnwp.org/written-statement-submitted-to-cedaw-on-the-occasion-of-the-general-discussion-on-women-in-conflict-and-post-conflict-situations |url-status=dead |archive-date=23 July 2011 |title=Written Statement submitted to CEDAW on the occasion of the General Discussion on Women in Conflict and Post-conflict Situations |author=GNWP-ICAN |date=18 July 2011 |website=gnwp.org |publisher=Global Network of Women Peacebuilders (GNWP) – International Civil society Action Network (ICAN) |accessdate=25 August 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

While CEDAW and UN Security Council Resolutions 1325 and 1820 on Women, Peace and Security are important international instruments on their own, there is also an intersection among the three standards that can be used to enhance their implementation and impact.

Resolutions 1325 and 1820 broaden the scope of CEDAW application by clarifying its relevance to all parties in conflict, whereas CEDAW provides concrete strategic guidance for actions to be taken on the broad commitments outlined in the two Resolutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=UNIFEM |title=CEDAW and Security Council Resolution 1325: A Quick Guide |url=http://www.unrol.org/files/CEDAWandUNSCR1325_eng.pdf |journal=Women, Peace &amp; Security |date=2006 |accessdate=25 August 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140826120303/http://www.unrol.org/files/CEDAWandUNSCR1325_eng.pdf |archivedate=26 August 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

CEDAW is a global human rights treaty that should be incorporated into national law as the highest standard for women's rights. It requires the UN Member States that have ratified it (185 to date) to set in place mechanisms to fully realize [[women's rights]].

Resolution 1325 is an international law unanimously adopted by the Security Council that mandates the UN Member States to engage women in all aspects of peacebuilding including ensuring women's participation on all levels of decision–making on peace and security issues.

Resolution 1820 links sexual violence as a tactic of war with the maintenance of international peace and security. It also demands a comprehensive report from the UN Secretary-General on implementation and strategies for improving information flow to the Security Council; and the adoption of concrete protection and prevention measures to end sexual violence.

Resolutions 1325 and 1820, and CEDAW share the following agenda on women's human rights and [[gender equality]]:&lt;ref name="gnwp" /&gt;

# Demand women’s participation in [[decision-making]] at all levels
# Rejection of violence against women as it impedes the advancement of women and maintains their subordinate status
# Equality of women and men under the law; protection of women and girls through the [[rule of law]]
# Demand security forces and systems to protect women and girls from [[gender-based violence]]
# Recognition of the fact that distinct experiences and burdens of women and girls come from systemic discrimination
# Ensure that women’s experiences, needs and perspectives are incorporated into the political, legal and social decisions that determine the achievement of just and lasting peace

A General Comment from the CEDAW committee could strengthen women’s advocacy for the full implementation of Resolutions 1325 and 1820 at the country and community levels. Conversely, CEDAW’s relevance to conflict-affected areas will be underscored further by the two Resolutions.  In other words, all three international instruments will reinforce each other and be much more effective if used together in leveraging women’s human rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnwp.org/what-we-do/local-legislative-advocacy/cedaw-with-unscr-1325-and-1820 CEDAW with UNSCR 1325 and 1820 « Global Network of Women Peacebuilders&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://archive.is/20130414214651/http://www.gnwp.org/what-we-do/local-legislative-advocacy/cedaw-with-unscr-1325-and-1820 |date=14 April 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Members and ratification==
{{Main|List of parties to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women}}
The six UN member states that have not ratified or acceded to the convention are [[Iran]], [[Palau]], [[Somalia]], [[Sudan]], [[Tonga]], and the [[United States]].&lt;ref name="Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en |title=Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women |publisher=Treaties.un.org |accessdate=2011-09-27 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120823144158/http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en |archivedate=23 August 2012 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The one [[United Nations General Assembly observers#Non-member states|UN non-member state]] that had not acceded to the convention is the [[Holy See]]/[[Vatican City]].&lt;ref name="Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Note:'' See New Zealand No 47 Declarations and Reservations New Zealand has signed this treaty on behalf of Niue.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Taiwan|Republic of China (Taiwan)]] in 2007 has also ratified the treaty in its legislature, but is unrecognized by the United Nations and is a party to the treaty only unofficially.&lt;ref&gt;Government Information Office, Republic of China (Taiwan). "Taiwan Aims to Sign Up Against Discrimination." 8 September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The latest state to have acceded the convention was [[South Sudan]] on 30 April 2015.&lt;ref name="Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women" /&gt;

Within the United States, over 40 cities and local governments have adopted CEDAW ordinances or resolutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://citiesforcedaw.org/background/|title=Background, Cities for CEDAW|work=Cities for CEDAW|access-date=2018-11-15|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reservations ==
Many [[Reservation (law)|reservations]] have been entered against certain articles of the Convention.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Reservations to CEDAW: An Analysis for UNICEF |url=http://www.unicef.org/gender/files/Reservations_to_CEDAW-an_Analysis_for_UNICEF.pdf |website=www.unicef.org |accessdate=2015-05-08 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151004104944/http://www.unicef.org/gender/files/Reservations_to_CEDAW-an_Analysis_for_UNICEF.pdf |archivedate=4 October 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are also some reservations that are not specific to an article within the Convention but rather a general reservation to all aspects of the Convention that would violate a stated principle. For example, [[Mauritania]] made a reservation stating it approved the Convention "in each and every one of its parts which are not contrary to [[Sharia|Islamic Sharia]]."&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; A number these reservations, especially those entered by Islamic states parties, are subject to much debate.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite book |title=Human Rights |last=Henkin |first=Louis |publisher=Foundation Press |year=2009 |isbn= |location= |pages=221}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Article 28 of the Convention states that "a [[Reservation (law)|reservation]] incompatible with the object and purpose of the present Convention shall not be permitted."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; As a result, many states parties have entered objections to the reservations of other states parties.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Human rights |last=Henkin |first=Louis |publisher=Foundation Press |year=2009 |isbn= |location= |pages=822}}&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, many Nordic states parties were concerned that some of the reservations were "undermining the integrity of the text."&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite journal |url= |title=The Vienna Convention Reservations Regime and the Convention on the Discrimination Against Women |last=Clark |first=Belinda |date=1991 |journal=The American Journal of International Law |doi= |pmid= |access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over the years, some states parties have withdrawn their reservations.

As of May 2015, sixty-two states parties have entered reservations against some part of the Convention.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en |title=Declarations and Reservations |date=2015 |website=United Nations Treaty Collection |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150906035454/https://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en |archivedate=6 September 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Twenty-four states parties have entered objections to at least one of these reservations.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; The most reserved article is Article 29, concerning dispute resolution and interpretation of the Convention, with thirty-nine reservations.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; Because reservations to Article 29 are expressly allowed by the Convention itself, these reservations were not very controversial.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; Article 16, concerning the equality of women in marriage and family life is subject to twenty-three reservations.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; The Committee, in General Recommendation No. 28, specifically stated that reservations to Article 2, concerning general non-discrimination, are impermissible.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; However, Article 2 has seventeen reservations.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

==Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women==
The Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women is the United Nations (U.N.) treaty body that oversees the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women (CEDAW). The formation of this committee was outlined in [https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/text/econvention.htm#article17 Article 17] of the CEDAW, which also established the rules, purpose, and operating procedures of the committee.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet"&gt;{{cite web |last=U.N. Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights |title=Fact Sheet No. 22, Discrimination Against Women: The Convention and the Committee |url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/docid/47947740d.html |publisher=United Nations |accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout its years of operation the committee has held multiple sessions to ensure the rules outlined in the CEDAW are being followed. Over time the practices of the committee have evolved due to an increased focus on [[women's rights]] issues.

===History of the committee===
The Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women was formed on 3 September 1981 after the CEDAW received the 20 [[ratification]]s required for it to enter into force. Article 17 of the CEDAW established the committee in order to ensure that the provisions of the CEDAW were followed by the countries that had signed and agreed to be bound by it.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt; The first regular session of the committee was held from 18–22 October 1982. In this session the first officers of the committee were elected by simple majority, with Ms. L. Ider of [[Mongolia]] becoming chairperson.&lt;ref name="The Work Of CEDAW"&gt;{{cite book |last=United Nations Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women |title=The Work of CEDAW: Reports of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |year=1989 |publisher=United Nations |location=New York |isbn=9211301327 |pages=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other officers elected were three vice-chairpersons: M.&amp;nbsp;Caron of Canada, Z.&amp;nbsp;Ilic of [[Yugoslavia]] and L.&amp;nbsp;Mukayiranga of [[Rwanda]]. The final officer elected was D.&amp;nbsp;P. Bernard of [[Guyana]] as [[rapporteur]] of the committee. During this session, the committee also unanimously approved to adopt its [[rules of procedure]].&lt;ref name="The Work Of CEDAW" /&gt;

===Sessions===
[[File:Palais des nations.jpg|left|thumb|[[Palais des Nations]]]]
The rules regarding where and when the committee can hold sessions are laid out in their rules of procedure.&lt;ref name=Rules&gt;{{cite web |last=U.N. Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights |title=Rules of Procedure of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women |url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/docs/CEDAW_Rules_en.pdf |publisher=United Nations |accessdate=18 October 2012 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120707073126/http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/docs/CEDAW_Rules_en.pdf |archivedate=7 July 2012 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:UN Headquarters.jpg|thumb|[[UN Headquarters]]]]
The committee is allowed to hold as many meetings as are required to perform their duties effectively, with the [[State (polity)|states]] party to the CEDAW and the [[Secretary-General of the United Nations]] authorizing the number of regular sessions held.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; In addition, special sessions can be held at the request of either a state party to the convention or the majority of the members serving on the committee.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; Seventy-two sessions have been held to date, with the most recent taking place from 18 February to 9 March 2019.&lt;ref name=Sessions&gt;{{cite web |last=U.N. Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights |title=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women – Sessions |url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/sessions.htm |publisher=United Nations |accessdate=6 November 2012 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121105070602/http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/sessions.htm |archivedate=5 November 2012 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The first thirty-nine sessions were held at the [[United Nations headquarters]] building in New York City, with the fortieth and subsequent sessions held at the [[Palais des Nations]] in Geneva.&lt;ref name=Sessions /&gt; At its regular sessions, the Committee hears reports from states party to the CEDAW on their progress in adhering to CEDAW and implementing its ideas in their countries.&lt;ref name=Report&gt;{{cite web |last=United Nations Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women |title=Report of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women |url=https://undocs.org/A/67/38 |publisher=United Nations |accessdate=21 March 2017 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170322015440/http://undocs.org/A/67/38 |archivedate=22 March 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The committee also holds pre-sessional work groups to discuss the issues and questions that the committee should deal with during the following session.

===Reports===
Under [https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/text/econvention.htm#article18 article 18] of the CEDAW states must report to the committee on the progress they have made in implementing the CEDAW within their state.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; As most of the information the committee works with comes from these reports, guidelines have been developed to help states prepare accurate and useful reports.&lt;ref name=Methods&gt;{{cite web |last=United Nations Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women |title=Overview of the current working methods of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/wk-methods/Overview-English.pdf |publisher=United Nations |accessdate=18 October 2012 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131022084310/http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/wk-methods/Overview-English.pdf |archivedate=22 October 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Initial reports discussing the current picture of discrimination against women in the reporting states are required to specifically deal with each article of the CEDAW, and consist of no more than one-hundred pages.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; States are required to prepare and present these initial reports within one year of ratifying the CEDAW.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt; Periodic reports detailing the state's progress in adhering to the articles of the CEDAW should be no more than seventy-five pages in length and should focus on the specific period of time since the state's last report.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; States party to the CEDAW are typically required to provide periodic reports every four years, but if the committee is concerned about the situation in that state they can request a report at any time.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt;

The committee chooses which reports addressing by considering factors such as the amount of time the report has been pending, whether the report is initial or periodic (with more priority given to initial reports), and from which region the report originates.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; Eight states are invited to give their reports during each session and it is required a representative from the state is in attendance when the report is presented.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; The committee focuses on constructive dialogue when a report is presented and appreciates careful time management on the part of the state presenting its report.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; Due to the high backlog of overdue reports the committee has encouraged states to combine all of their outstanding reports into one document and sends reminders to states who have reports that are five years overdue.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; The CEDAW also requires that the committee provide an annual report that includes its activities, comments relating to the reports provided by states, information relating to the Optional Protocol of the CEDAW, and any other general suggestions or recommendations the committee has made.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; This report is given to the [[United Nations General Assembly]] through the [[United Nations Economic and Social Council|Economic and Social Council]].&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; All reports, agendas and other official documents pertaining to the committee, including the reports provided by the states, are provided to the public unless otherwise decided by the committee.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt;

===General Recommendations===

Along with issuing its annual report and offering advice to reporting states, the committee has the ability to issue general recommendations that elaborate on its views of the obligations imposed by CEDAW.&lt;ref name=Methods /&gt; To date, the committee has issued thirty-two general recommendations, the latest dealing with the gender related dimensions of refugee status, asylum, nationality and statelessness of women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |title=General recommendation No. 32 on the gender-related dimensions of refugee status, asylum, nationality and statelessness of women |url=https://undocs.org/CEDAW/C/GC/32 |website=undocs.org |publisher=United Nations |accessdate=21 March 2017 |date=14 November 2014 |id=CEDAW/C/GC/32 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170322014914/http://undocs.org/CEDAW/C/GC/32 |archivedate=22 March 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The recommendations issued by the committee in its first decade were short and dealt mainly with the content of states’ reports and reservations to the convention.&lt;ref name=Methods /&gt; Since 1991, however, recommendations have been focused on guiding states’ application of the CEDAW in specific situations.&lt;ref name=Methods /&gt; The formulation of a general recommendation begins with dialogue between the committee on the topic in the recommendation with various non-governmental organizations and other U.N. bodies.&lt;ref name=Methods /&gt; The recommendation is then drafted by a member of the committee and discussed and revised in the next session, and finally adopted in the following session.&lt;ref name=Methods /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 1''' (1986) discusses "reporting guidelines."&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite web |title=General recommendations made by the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/recommendations/recomm.htm#recom1 |website=www.un.org |accessdate=2015-05-08 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150510132556/http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/recommendations/recomm.htm#recom1 |archivedate=10 May 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 2''' (1987) discusses "reporting guidelines."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 3''' (1987) discusses "education and public information programs."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 4''' (1987) discusses "reservations."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 5''' (1988) discusses "temporary social measures."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 6''' (1988) discusses "effective national machinery and publicity."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 7''' (1988) discusses "resources."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 8''' (1988) discusses "Article 8."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 9''' (1989) discusses "statistical data."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 10''' (1989) discusses "the tenth anniversary of the adoption of CEDAW."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 11''' (1989) discusses "technical advisory services for reporting."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 12''' (1989) discusses "violence against women."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 13''' (1989) discusses "equal remuneration for work of equal value."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 14''' (1990) discusses "female circumcision."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 15''' (1990) discusses "women and AIDS."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 16''' (1991) discusses "unpaid women workers in rural and urban family enterprises."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 17''' (1991) discusses "measurement and qualification of the unremenerated domestic activities of women and their recognition in the GNP."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 18''' (1991) discusses "disabled women."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 19''' (1992) discusses "violence against women."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Specifically, it states that "[t]he definition of discrimination includes gender-based violence, that is, violence that is directed against a woman because she is a woman or that affects women disproportionately."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 20''' (1992) discusses "reservations."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 21''' (1994) discusses "equality in marriage and family relations."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 22''' (1995) discusses "Article 20 of the Convention."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 23''' (1997) discusses "women in political and public life."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 24''' (1999) discusses "women and health."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 25''' (2004) discusses "temporary special measures."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/recommendations/General%20recommendation%2025%20(English).pdf |title=General Recommendation No. 25 |date=2004 |author=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |publisher=United Nations |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170829012817/http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/recommendations/General%20recommendation%2025%20(English).pdf |archivedate=29 August 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 26''' (2008) discusses "women migrant workers."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://tbinternet.ohchr.org/Treaties/CEDAW/Shared%20Documents/1_Global/CEDAW_C_2009_WP-1_R_7138_E.pdf |title=General Recommendation No. 26 |date=Dec 5, 2008 |author=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |publisher=United Nations |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150518072534/http://tbinternet.ohchr.org/Treaties/CEDAW/Shared%20Documents/1_Global/CEDAW_C_2009_WP-1_R_7138_E.pdf |archivedate=18 May 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 27''' (2010) discusses "older women and protection of their human rights."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://undocs.org/CEDAW/C/GC/27 |title=General recommendation No. 27 on older women and protection of their human rights |date=16 December 2010 |accessdate=21 March 2017 |author=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |publisher=United Nations |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170322020032/http://undocs.org/CEDAW/C/GC/27 |archivedate=22 March 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 28''' (2010) discusses "the core obligations of states parties under Article 2."&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://undocs.org/CEDAW/C/GC/28 |title=General recommendation No. 28 on the core obligations of States parties under article 2 of the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women |date=16 December 2010 |author=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |publisher=United Nations |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170322015928/http://undocs.org/CEDAW/C/GC/28 |archivedate=22 March 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Here, the Committee states that reservations to Article 2 are incompatible with the object and purpose of the Convention and therefore impermissible under Article 28.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; The Committee encouraged states parties to withdraw any reservations to Article 2 as soon as possible.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 29''' (2013) discusses "economic consequences of marriage, family relations and their dissolution."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://docstore.ohchr.org/SelfServices/FilesHandler.ashx?enc=6QkG1d%2fPPRiCAqhKb7yhsldCrOlUTvLRFDjh6%2fx1pWDn3WHqqJ3IVTSBdup3cNv3DQC%2fGcQdgTzvPZJiBl3Uvy2%2fdGCrYDfjaxHtk2Xa0GOPds69ZKD4rX0xgLCmpw%2fA |title=General Recommendation No. 29 |date=2013 |author=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |publisher=United Nations |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170102001315/http://docstore.ohchr.org/SelfServices/FilesHandler.ashx?enc=6QkG1d%2fPPRiCAqhKb7yhsldCrOlUTvLRFDjh6%2fx1pWDn3WHqqJ3IVTSBdup3cNv3DQC%2fGcQdgTzvPZJiBl3Uvy2%2fdGCrYDfjaxHtk2Xa0GOPds69ZKD4rX0xgLCmpw%2fA |archivedate=2 January 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 30''' (2013) discusses "women in conflict prevention, conflict and post-conflict situations."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://docstore.ohchr.org/SelfServices/FilesHandler.ashx?enc=6QkG1d%2fPPRiCAqhKb7yhsldCrOlUTvLRFDjh6%2fx1pWCVoI%2bcjImPBg0gA%2fHq5Tl4bPxuafUJENxKkQQHQgPbs6rD6D03eyw2VKMujRg4KnRgN8SfU%2fTqRnQcf6ValVto |title=General Recommendation No. 30 |date=2013 |author=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |publisher=United Nations |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150518072536/http://docstore.ohchr.org/SelfServices/FilesHandler.ashx?enc=6QkG1d%2fPPRiCAqhKb7yhsldCrOlUTvLRFDjh6%2fx1pWCVoI%2bcjImPBg0gA%2fHq5Tl4bPxuafUJENxKkQQHQgPbs6rD6D03eyw2VKMujRg4KnRgN8SfU%2fTqRnQcf6ValVto |archivedate=18 May 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Here, the Committee said states parties are obliged to uphold women’s rights before, during, and after conflict when they are directly involved in fighting, and/or are providing peacekeeping troops or donor assistance for conflict prevention, humanitarian aid or post-conflict reconstruction.&lt;ref name="ohchr.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=13885&amp;LangID=E|title=OHCHR -|website=www.ohchr.org|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131213103356/http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=13885&amp;LangID=E|archivedate=13 December 2013|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Committee also stated that ratifying states should exercise due diligence in ensuring that non-state actors, such as armed groups and private security contractors, be held accountable for crimes against women.&lt;ref name="ohchr.org" /&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 31''' (2014) is a joint recommendation with the Committee on the Rights of the Child discussing "harmful practices."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://docstore.ohchr.org/SelfServices/FilesHandler.ashx?enc=6QkG1d%2fPPRiCAqhKb7yhsldCrOlUTvLRFDjh6%2fx1pWB%2fCwaXyGnWUrr9tw8Oba%2bivtzAFOVaSi92u9iEkn866XJ4Yg0q7L3%2f8dxqFZFqORPs%2f54YHqmVTyrLKxGPLY82qE9XNQDpE4IXxwy45IJCAQ%3d%3d |title=General Recommendation No. 31 |date=2014 |author=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |publisher=United Nations |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150906075441/http://docstore.ohchr.org/SelfServices/FilesHandler.ashx?enc=6QkG1d%2fPPRiCAqhKb7yhsldCrOlUTvLRFDjh6%2fx1pWB%2fCwaXyGnWUrr9tw8Oba%2bivtzAFOVaSi92u9iEkn866XJ4Yg0q7L3%2f8dxqFZFqORPs%2f54YHqmVTyrLKxGPLY82qE9XNQDpE4IXxwy45IJCAQ%3d%3d |archivedate=6 September 2015 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; For the first time, the Committee joined with the [[Committee on the Rights of the Child]] to release a comprehensive interpretation of the obligations of States to prevent and eliminate harmful practices done to women and girls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=15250&amp;LangID=E |title=UN human rights experts set out countries' obligations to tackle harmful practices such as FGM and forced marriage |date=November 5, 2014 |publisher=United Nations Human Rights, Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights |accessdate=November 15, 2014 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141129014305/http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=15250&amp;LangID=E |archivedate=29 November 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''General Recommendation No. 32''' (2014) discusses "gender-related dimensions of refugee status, asylum, nationality and statelessness of women."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://undocs.org/CEDAW/C/GC/32 |title=General recommendation No. 32 on the gender-related dimensions of refugee status, asylum, nationality and statelessness of women |date=14 November 2014 |author=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |publisher=United Nations |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170322014914/http://undocs.org/CEDAW/C/GC/32 |archivedate=22 March 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently the Committee is working on the '''General Recommendation''' Trafficking in women and girls in the context of global migration.

===Changes in the committee===

For the first ten years the committee operated significantly differently from now. The only form of [[censure]] given to the committee by the CEDAW was their general recommendations and concluding comments following a report.&lt;ref name=Reilly&gt;{{cite book |last=Reilly |first=Niamh |title=Women's human rights : seeking gender justice in a globalizing age |url=https://archive.org/details/womenshumanright0000reil |url-access=registration |year=2009 |publisher=[[Polity Press]] |location=Cambridge |isbn=9780745637006 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/womenshumanright0000reil/page/62 62] |edition=Reprinted.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the emergence of the Global Campaign for Women's Human Rights in 1991 more attention was given to the CEDAW, reviving the committee.&lt;ref name=Reilly /&gt; The committee made changes to the CEDAW that allowed it to meet more than once a year, and have taken advantage of this by meeting at least twice a year since 1997.&lt;ref name=Reilly /&gt; The committee originally only met for two weeks in its annual sessions, but that has now been changed to meeting multiple times a year in eighteen-day sessions.&lt;ref name=Report /&gt; CEDAW also gained new complaint and inquiry proceedings allowing the committee to initiate inquiry proceedings if it believes a state is in severe violation of the articles of the CEDAW.&lt;ref name=Reilly /&gt;

===Recommendations for improvement===
Despite evolving since the committee was first formed, members believe there are ways in which the committee can better meet the goals outlined in the CEDAW.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt; One of the committee's main goals moving forward is expanding its information base, allowing it to more effectively deal with issues that arise concerning the CEDAW.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt; The committee is authorized in [https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/text/econvention.htm#article22 Article 22] of the CEDAW to invite specialized U.N. agencies such as the [[United Nations Development Programme]] to deliver reports discussing women's rights issues in the state under discussion.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt; Another method for gathering information is requesting reports from non-governmental organizations dealing with discrimination against women that are operating in the country under discussion.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt; This is recommended to insure that the committee is receiving the full, unbiased picture of affairs within the reporting state.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt;

Another recommendation for improvement involves interpreting and clarifying the language used in the CEDAW in order to make the document as useful as it can be.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt; A third improvement that has been suggested is improving the efficiency of the committee.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt; Due to the backlog in reports faced by the committee it has been suggested that the government officials who prepare reports presented to the committee should be trained, in order to make all reports uniform and more easily processed.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt; A final suggestion for improvement is the implementation of a right of petition in the CEDAW, allowing the committee to hear complaints from citizens of a state against the state, increasing the committee's strength and direct impact on the problem of discrimination against women.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt;

===Languages===
The official languages of the committee are [[English language|English]], [[Arabic]], [[French language|French]], [[Russian language|Russian]], and [[Spanish language|Spanish]], with any statement made in one of the official languages translated into the other four.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; A speaker who does not speak one of the official languages provides a translator.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; All formal decisions and documents issued by the committee are provided in each of the official languages.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; The original rules of procedure adopted by the committee did not include Arabic as an official language, but the rule was amended in the committees second session to include Arabic.&lt;ref name="The Work Of CEDAW" /&gt;

===Members and Officers of the Committee===
Twenty-three members serve on the committee, described as experts for their experience and expertise in women's issues.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite book |last=Merry |first=Sally Engle |title=Human rights and gender violence : translating international law into local justice |year=2006 |publisher=[[Univ. of Chicago Press]] |location=Chicago [u.a.] |isbn=0226520730 |pages=82 |edition=[Nachdr.].}}&lt;/ref&gt; The members are nominated by their national governments and elected through a secret ballot by states party to the convention.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Upon winning the election and taking up their responsibilities the members of the committee recite the following statement, known as the solemn declaration, "I solemnly declare that I shall perform my duties and exercise powers as a member of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women honourably, faithfully, impartially and conscientiously".&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; The members come from a wide range of occupations including doctors, lawyers, diplomats and educators, providing various viewpoints to the committee due to their diversity.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Many members continue to hold full-time jobs outside the committee and receive little monetary payment for their work on the committee.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

To insure that the nationality of members encompasses all the diverse states who have signed the CEDAW, members are elected according to regions divided into [[Latin America]] and the [[Caribbean]], [[Africa]], [[Asia]], [[Western Europe]], and [[Eastern Europe]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; The members of the committee differ from those of other treaty bodies of the United Nations in that they have all been women with only one exception.&lt;ref name="Fact Sheet" /&gt; In the event a member of the committee is unable to continue serving on the committee before her term is up the state that had nominated the resigning member shall nominate another expert from their country to fill in her seat.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; Committee members and experts also attend an annual luncheon, hosted by the [[NGO Committee on the Status of Women, New York|NGO Committee on the Status of Women, NY]] (NGO CSW/NY), where key issues are discusses and the efforts of the committee are honored.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ngocsw.org/about/how-we-work |title=NGO CSW, NY / About / How We Work |publisher=Ngocsw.org |date=26 July 2011 |accessdate=2011-09-27 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111011010921/http://www.ngocsw.org/about/how-we-work |archivedate=11 October 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Officers of the Committee'''

The officers of the committee are composed of a chairperson, three vice-chairpersons and a rapporteur.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=U.N. Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights |title=Membership of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |url=http://www.ohchr.org/EN/HRBodies/CEDAW/Pages/Membership.aspx |publisher=[[OHCHR]] |accessdate=18 October 2012 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130903040414/http://www.ohchr.org/EN/HRBodies/CEDAW/Pages/Membership.aspx |archivedate=3 September 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Officers of the committee are nominated by another member of the committee, as opposed to a government which nominates members for the committee.&lt;ref name="The Work Of CEDAW" /&gt; All officers are elected by majority vote to a two-year term of office, and remain eligible for re-election after their term expires.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; The chairperson's duties include declaring a meeting to be open or closed, directing the discussion in a session, announcing decisions made by the committee, preparing agendas in consultation with the secretary-general, designating the members of pre-sessional working groups and representing the committee at United Nations meetings which the committee is invited to participate in.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; In the case the chairperson is unable to perform any her duties she designates one of the three vice-chairpersons to take over her role. If the chairperson fails to designate a vice-chairperson prior to her absence then the vice-chairperson with the first name in English alphabetical order takes over.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt; In the event an officer is unable to continue serving on the committee before her term expires a new officer from the same region as the original officer shall be nominated, elected and will take over the vacated office.&lt;ref name=Rules /&gt;
As of June 2019, the 23 members are:

{| class="wikitable" style="width:450px;"
|+ CEDAW Committee Membership&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Membership |url=http://www.ohchr.org/EN/HRBodies/CEDAW/Pages/Membership.aspx |website=www.ohchr.org |accessdate=2019-06-14 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! Name !! State !!  Term Expires
|-
| [[Gladys Acosta Vargas]] (Vice-Chairperson) || {{flag|Peru}} ||  2022
|-
| Hiroko Akizuki || {{flag|Japan}} || 2022
|-
| Tamader Al-Rammah || {{flag|Saudi Arabia}} || 2022
|-
| [[Nicole Ameline]] (Vice-Chairperson) || {{flag|France}} ||  2020
|-
| [[Gunnar Bergby]] || {{flag|Norway}} || 2020
|-
| [[Marion Bethel]] || {{flag|Bahamas}} || 2020
|-
| Louiza Chalal || {{flag|Algeria}} ||  2022
|-
| Esther Eghobamien-Mshelia || {{flag|Nigeria}} || 2020
|-
| Naela Gabr || {{flag|Egypt}} ||  2022
|-
| [[Hilary Gbedemah]] (Chairperson)&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; || {{flag|Ghana}} ||  2020
|-
| Nahla Haidar || {{flag|Lebanon}} ||  2020
|-
|[[Dalia Leinarte]] || {{flag|Lithuania}} ||2020
|-
| [[Rosario Manalo]] || {{flag|Philippines}} || 2020
|-
| [[Lia Nadaraia]] (Rapporteur) || {{flag|Georgia}} ||  2022
|-
| Aruna Devi Narain || {{flag|Mauritius}} || 2022
|-
| Ana Pelaez Narvaez || {{flag|Spain}} || 2022
|-
| [[Bandana Rana]] (Vice-Chairperson) || {{flag|Nepal}} || 2020
|-
| [[Rhoda Reddock]] || {{flag|Trinidad and Tobago}} || 2022
|-
| Elgun Safarov || {{flag|Azerbaijan}} || 2022
|-
| Wenyan Song || {{flag|China}} || 2020
|-
| Genoveva Tisheva || {{flag|Bulgaria}} || 2022
|-
| Franceline Toe Bouda || {{flag|Burkina Faso}} || 2022
|-
| Aicha Vall Verges || {{flag|Mauritania}} || 2020
|}

==Optional Protocol==
The [[Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]] is a side-agreement to the Convention which allows its parties to recognise the competence of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women to consider complaints from individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/instree/cedawopprot-2000.html Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080509170959/http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/instree/cedawopprot-2000.html |date=9 May 2008 }}, Article 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Optional Protocol was adopted by the UN General Assembly on 6 October 1999 and entered into force on 22 December 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/protocol/wom1242.htm |title=Optional Protocol to Women's Convention Comes into Force |date=21 December 2000 |accessdate=2008-07-15 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080907212930/http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/protocol/wom1242.htm |archivedate=7 September 2008 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently it has 80 signatories and 109 parties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8-b&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en |title=Parties to the Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women |publisher=UN OHCHR |accessdate=2009-10-03 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110520040105/http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8-b&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en |archivedate=20 May 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
Controversy around CEDAW comes from two opposite directions: social and religious [[conservative]]s which claim that CEDAW is seeking to impose a [[Liberalism|liberal]], [[Progressivism|progressive]], [[Feminism|feminist]] standard on countries, in detriment of [[traditional values]]; and [[radical feminists]], who are skeptical of the power, or even desire, of CEDAW to radically transform societies and truly liberate women, and claim that CEDAW adheres to a form of weak [[liberal feminism]] similar to other mainstream organizations. They also claim that UN members cannot create goals which represent values of the poor, conservative, religious, or weak, because few, if any, UN officials/staff are actually from this group for which they claim to represent. &lt;ref&gt;https://academic.oup.com/icon/article/10/2/512/666068/Gender-and-democratic-citizenship-the-impact-of&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://digitalcommons.law.umaryland.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1006&amp;context=iclc_papers |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2017-08-09 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180511154106/http://digitalcommons.law.umaryland.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1006&amp;context=iclc_papers |archivedate=11 May 2018 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://femequality.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/How-Does-the-CEDAW-Address-the-Problem-of-Culture-and-Tradition.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2017-08-09 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170810015119/http://femequality.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/How-Does-the-CEDAW-Address-the-Problem-of-Culture-and-Tradition.pdf |archivedate=10 August 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Special Measures for Gender Equality in The United Nations(UN)]]
* [[Equal Rights Amendment]]
* [[Parental leave]]
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Mixed-sex education]]
* [[Declaration on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women]]
* [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]]
* [[EGM: prevention of violence against women and girls]]
* [[Global Implementation Plan to End Violence against Women and Girls]]
* [[Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence]]
* [[Convention on the Political Rights of Women]]
* [[Maternity Protection Convention, 2000]]
* [[United Nations Development Fund for Women]]
* [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1325]]
* [[UN Women]]
* [[Women's rights]]
* [[Equality Now]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* [http://www.ipu.org/PDF/publications/cedaw_en.pdf The Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women and its Optional Protocol: Handbook for Parliamentarians], [[Inter-Parliamentary Union]] 2003
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20140107233916/http://www.unifem.org/gender_issues/women_war_peace/ UN WOMEN "Women, War &amp; Peace"]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120925101535/http://unwomen-nc.org.sg/gender_issues_datasheet_4.shtml UN WOMEN Singapore Committee – Governance, Peace &amp; Security]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20140302103750/http://www.unifem.org/gender_issues/violence_against_women/ UN WOMEN "Violence Against Women"]

==External links==
* [http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/index.htm CEDAW site]
* [http://www.ohchr.org/EN/ProfessionalInterest/Pages/CEDAW.aspx Convention text]
* [http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en List of parties]
* [http://www.cedaw2010.org/ CEDAW 2010], the website of the CEDAW Task Force of The Leadership Conference on Civil and Human Rights.
* [http://legal.un.org/avl/ha/cedaw/cedaw.html Introductory note by Dubravka Šimonović, procedural history note and audiovisual material] on the ''Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women'' in the [http://legal.un.org/avl/historicarchives.html Historic Archives of the United Nations Audiovisual Library of International Law]

{{United Nations}}
{{International human rights legal instruments}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Women Dicrimination Against Convention}}
[[Category:Treaties concluded in 1979]]
[[Category:Treaties entered into force in 1981]]
[[Category:Anti-discrimination treaties|Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]]
[[Category:United Nations treaties]]
[[Category:Reproductive rights|Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]]
[[Category:Women's rights instruments]]
[[Category:Feminism and society|Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]]
[[Category:Women in society|Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]]
[[Category:Sexism|Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Afghan Transitional Administration]]
[[Category:Treaties of Albania]]
[[Category:Treaties of Algeria]]
[[Category:Treaties of Andorra]]
[[Category:Treaties of the People's Republic of Angola]]
[[Category:Treaties of Antigua and Barbuda]]
[[Category:Treaties of Argentina]]
[[Category:Treaties of Armenia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Australia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Austria]]
[[Category:Treaties of Azerbaijan]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Bahamas]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bahrain]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bangladesh]]
[[Category:Treaties of Barbados]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Byelorussian Soviet Socialist Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of Belgium]]
[[Category:Treaties of Belize]]
[[Category:Treaties of Benin]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bhutan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bolivia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Bosnia and Herzegovina]]
[[Category:Treaties of Botswana]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Brazilian military government]]
[[Category:Treaties of Brunei]]
[[Category:Treaties of the People's Republic of Bulgaria]]
[[Category:Treaties of Burkina Faso]]
[[Category:Treaties of Myanmar]]
[[Category:Treaties of Burundi]]
[[Category:Treaties of the State of Cambodia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Cameroon]]
[[Category:Treaties of Canada]]
[[Category:Treaties of Cape Verde]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Central African Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of Chad]]
[[Category:Treaties of Chile]]
[[Category:Treaties of Taiwan]]
[[Category:Treaties of the People's Republic of China]]
[[Category:Treaties of Colombia]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Comoros]]
[[Category:Treaties of Zaire]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Republic of the Congo]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Cook Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties of Costa Rica]]
[[Category:Treaties of Ivory Coast]]
[[Category:Treaties of Croatia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Cuba]]
[[Category:Treaties of Cyprus]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Czech Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of Czechoslovakia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Denmark]]
[[Category:Treaties of Djibouti]]
[[Category:Treaties of Dominica]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Dominican Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of East Timor]]
[[Category:Treaties of Ecuador]]
[[Category:Treaties of Egypt]]
[[Category:Treaties of El Salvador]]
[[Category:Treaties of Equatorial Guinea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Eritrea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Estonia]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Derg]]
[[Category:Treaties of Fiji]]
[[Category:Treaties of Finland]]
[[Category:Treaties of France]]
[[Category:Treaties of Gabon]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Gambia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Georgia (country)]]
[[Category:Treaties of West Germany]]
[[Category:Treaties of East Germany]]
[[Category:Treaties of Ghana]]
[[Category:Treaties of Greece]]
[[Category:Treaties of Grenada]]
[[Category:Treaties of Guatemala]]
[[Category:Treaties of Guinea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Guinea-Bissau]]
[[Category:Treaties of Haiti]]
[[Category:Treaties of Honduras]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Hungarian People's Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of Iceland]]
[[Category:Treaties of India]]
[[Category:Treaties of Indonesia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Ba'athist Iraq]]
[[Category:Treaties of Ireland]]
[[Category:Treaties of Israel]]
[[Category:Treaties of Italy]]
[[Category:Treaties of Jamaica]]
[[Category:Treaties of Japan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Jordan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Kazakhstan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Kenya]]
[[Category:Treaties of Kiribati]]
[[Category:Treaties of North Korea]]
[[Category:Treaties of South Korea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Kuwait]]
[[Category:Treaties of Kyrgyzstan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Laos]]
[[Category:Treaties of Latvia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Lebanon]]
[[Category:Treaties of Lesotho]]
[[Category:Treaties of Liberia]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Libyan Arab Jamahiriya]]
[[Category:Treaties of Liechtenstein]]
[[Category:Treaties of Lithuania]]
[[Category:Treaties of Luxembourg]]
[[Category:Treaties of North Macedonia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Madagascar]]
[[Category:Treaties of Malawi]]
[[Category:Treaties of Malaysia]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Maldives]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mali]]
[[Category:Treaties of Malta]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Marshall Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mauritania]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mauritius]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mexico]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Federated States of Micronesia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Moldova]]
[[Category:Treaties of Monaco]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Mongolian People's Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of Montenegro]]
[[Category:Treaties of Morocco]]
[[Category:Treaties of Mozambique]]
[[Category:Treaties of Namibia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Nauru]]
[[Category:Treaties of Nepal]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Treaties of New Zealand]]
[[Category:Treaties of Nicaragua]]
[[Category:Treaties of Niger]]
[[Category:Treaties of Nigeria]]
[[Category:Treaties of Norway]]
[[Category:Treaties of Oman]]
[[Category:Treaties of Pakistan]]
[[Category:Treaties of the State of Palestine]]
[[Category:Treaties of Panama]]
[[Category:Treaties of Papua New Guinea]]
[[Category:Treaties of Paraguay]]
[[Category:Treaties of Peru]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Philippines]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Polish People's Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of Portugal]]
[[Category:Treaties of Qatar]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Socialist Republic of Romania]]
[[Category:Treaties of Rwanda]]
[[Category:Treaties of Saint Kitts and Nevis]]
[[Category:Treaties of Saint Lucia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Saint Vincent and the Grenadines]]
[[Category:Treaties of Samoa]]
[[Category:Treaties of San Marino]]
[[Category:Treaties of São Tomé and Príncipe]]
[[Category:Treaties of Saudi Arabia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Senegal]]
[[Category:Treaties of Seychelles]]
[[Category:Treaties of Sierra Leone]]
[[Category:Treaties of Singapore]]
[[Category:Treaties of Slovakia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Slovenia]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Solomon Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties of South Africa]]
[[Category:Treaties of South Sudan]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Treaties of Spain]]
[[Category:Treaties of Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Treaties of Suriname]]
[[Category:Treaties of Eswatini]]
[[Category:Treaties of Sweden]]
[[Category:Treaties of Switzerland]]
[[Category:Treaties of Syria]]
[[Category:Treaties of Tajikistan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Thailand]]
[[Category:Treaties of Togo]]
[[Category:Treaties of Trinidad and Tobago]]
[[Category:Treaties of Tunisia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Turkey]]
[[Category:Treaties of Turkmenistan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Tuvalu]]
[[Category:Treaties of Uganda]]
[[Category:Treaties of the Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic]]
[[Category:Treaties of the United Arab Emirates]]
[[Category:Treaties of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Treaties of Uruguay]]
[[Category:Treaties of Uzbekistan]]
[[Category:Treaties of Vanuatu]]
[[Category:Treaties of Venezuela]]
[[Category:Treaties of Vietnam]]
[[Category:Treaties of South Yemen]]
[[Category:Treaties of Yugoslavia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Zambia]]
[[Category:Treaties of Zimbabwe]]
[[Category:1979 in New York (state)]]
[[Category:Treaties adopted by United Nations General Assembly resolutions]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Isle of Man]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the British Virgin Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Falkland Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Turks and Caicos Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Greenland]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Faroe Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Aruba]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Netherlands Antilles]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to British Hong Kong]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to the Cook Islands]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Niue]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to Portuguese Macau]]
[[Category:Treaties extended to West Berlin]]
[[Category:1979 in women's history]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>