<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121106032251|521614336" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1435066" pageid="1435066" ns="0" title="Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-19T03:24:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- UN-related article; UN spelling/stylistic conventions--&gt;
{{Infobox Treaty
| name                = Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination against Women
| long_name           =
| image               = 
| image_width         =
| caption             =
| type                =
| date_drafted        =
| date_signed         = 18 December 1979
| location_signed     = [[New York City]]
| date_sealed         =
| date_effective      = 3 September 1981
| condition_effective = 20 ratifications
| date_expiration     =
| signatories         =
| parties             = 187 ([[List of parties to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women|Complete List]])
| depositor           =
| language            =
| languages           =
| website             =
| wikisource          = Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women
}}
[[Image:CEDAW Participation.svg|right|400px|thumb| Participation in the CEDAW {{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
{{legend|#00aa00|Signed and ratified}}
{{legend|#008000|Ratified by accession or succession}}
{{legend|#008080|Unrecognized state, abiding by treaty}}
{{Col-2}}
{{legend|#eeee00|Only signed}}
{{legend|#ff1111|Non-signatory}}
{{Col-end}}
]]

[[File:Map5.1Discrepant Behavior compressed.jpg|right|400px|thumb| A world map showing countries by CEDAW enforcement, 2010.]]

The '''Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination against Women''' ('''CEDAW''') is an [[international]] convention adopted in 1979 by the [[United Nations]] [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]].
Described as an international [[bill of rights]] for [[woman|women]], it came into force on 3 September 1981. Over fifty countries that have ratified the Convention have done so subject to certain declarations, reservations, and objections, including 38 countries who rejected the enforcement article (29).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/reservations-country.htm |title=Declarations, Reservations and Objections to CEDAW |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Australia's declaration noted the limitations on government power imposed by its Federal Constitutional System, though the [[United States]] is the only developed nation that has not ratified the CEDAW at all.

==The Convention==
The Convention defines discrimination against women in the following terms:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Any distinction, exclusion or restriction made on the basis of sex which has the effect or purpose of impairing or nullifying the recognition, enjoyment or exercise by women, irrespective of their marital status, on a basis of equality of men and [[Women's rights|women]], of human rights and fundamental freedoms in the political, economic, social, cultural, civil or any other field.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

It also establishes an agenda of action for putting an end to [[Sexism|sex-based discrimination]]:

States must take measures to seek to eliminate prejudices and customs based on the idea of the inferiority or the superiority of one sex or on [[stereotype]]d [[gender role|role for men and women]]. 

States ratifying the Convention are required to enshrine [[gender equality]] into their domestic legislation, repeal all discriminatory provisions in their laws, and enact new provisions to guard against discrimination against women. However, special protection for [[maternity]] is not regarded as gender discrimination (Article 4). Appropriate measures, including legislation, to suppress all forms of trafficking in women and forced prostitution are also not regarded as gender discrimination (Article 6). Equal opportunity in education for female students is required, and [[mixed-sex education|coeducation]] is encouraged. (Article 10). States ratifying the Convention must also establish tribunals and public institutions to guarantee women effective protection against discrimination, and take steps to eliminate all forms of discrimination practiced against women by individuals, organizations, and [[Business|enterprises]] (Article 2,(e)).

==CEDAW with UNSCR 1325 and 1820==
'''Resolutions 1325 10th anniversary events highlight use of CEDAW mechanisms&lt;ref name="gnwp"&gt;http://www.gnwp.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/Cedaw-1325-1820-synergy2.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
'''
* The 10th anniversary of Resolution 1325 in October 2010 highlighted the increasing demand for accountability to UN Security Council Resolution 1325 on Women, Peace and Security. Many expressed concern about the fact that only 22 Member States out of 192 have adopted national action plans. Women are still underrepresented if not totally absent in most official peace negotiations and sexual violence in conflict continue to increase.

These realities emphasized the need to use other legal mechanisms to strengthen the implementation of SCR 1325, particularly CEDAW. The well-established mechanisms of CEDAW – the Member States compliance report and the civil society shadow reporting process were cited as powerful instruments to ensure accountability.

Several regional and international meetings including the High Level Seminar “1325 in 2020: Looking Forward…Looking Back,” organized by the African Center for the Constructive Resolution of Disputes, and the “Stockholm International Conference 10 years with 1325 – What now?” called for the use of CEDAW to improve 1325 implementation.

'''Intersection between SCR 1325 and CEDAW
'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gnwp.org/written-statement-submitted-to-cedaw-on-the-occasion-of-the-general-discussion-on-women-in-conflict-and-post-conflict-situations&lt;/ref&gt;
* While CEDAW and UN Security Council Resolutions 1325 and 1820 on Women, Peace and Security are important international instruments on their own, there is also an intersection among the three standards that can be used to enhance their implementation and impact.

Resolutions 1325 and 1820 broaden the scope of CEDAW application by clarifying its relevance to all parties in conflict, whereas CEDAW provides concrete strategic guidance for actions to be taken on the broad commitments outlined in the two Resolutions (UNIFEM, 2006. CEDAW and SCR 1325: A Quick Guide).

CEDAW is a global human rights treaty that should be incorporated into national law as the highest standard for women’s rights. It requires UN Member States that have ratified it (185 to date) to set in place mechanisms to fully realize women’s rights.

Resolution 1325 is an international law unanimously adopted by the Security Council that mandates UN Member States to engage women in all aspects of peace building including ensuring women’s participation on all levels of decision–making on peace and security issues.

Resolution 1820 links sexual violence as a tactic of war with the maintenance of international peace and security. It also demands a comprehensive report from the UN Secretary General on implementation and strategies for improving information flow to the Security Council; and adoption of concrete protection and prevention measures to end sexual violence.

Resolutions 1325 and 1820, and CEDAW share the following agenda on women’s human rights and gender equality:&lt;ref name="gnwp"/&gt;

1.    Demand women’s participation in decision-making at all levels

2.    Rejection of violence against women as it impedes the advancement of women and maintains their subordinate status

3.    Equality of women and men under the law; protection of women and girls through the rule of law

4.    Demand security forces and systems to protect women and girls from gender-based violence

5.    Recognition of the fact that distinct experiences and burdens of women and girls come from systemic discrimination

6.    Ensure that women’s experiences, needs and perspectives are incorporated into the political, legal and social decisions that determine the achievement of just and lasting peace

A General Comment from the CEDAW committee could strengthen women’s advocacy for the full implementation of Resolutions 1325 and 1820 at the country and community levels. Conversely, CEDAW’s relevance to conflict-affected areas will be underscored further by the two Resolutions.  In other words, all three international instruments will reinforce each other and be much more effective if used together in leveraging women’s human rights.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gnwp.org/what-we-do/local-legislative-advocacy/cedaw-with-unscr-1325-and-1820&lt;/ref&gt;

==Members and ratification==
{{Main|List of parties to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women}}

The seven UN member states that have not ratified or acceded to the convention are [[Iran]], [[Palau]], [[Somalia]], [[Sudan]], [[South Sudan]], [[Tonga]], and the [[United States]]. The United States, South Sudan and Palau have signed it, but not yet ratified it.&lt;ref name="Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en |title='Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women' |publisher=Treaties.un.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The one [[United Nations General Assembly observers#Non-member states|UN non-member state]] that had not acceded to the convention is the [[Holy See]]/[[Vatican City]].&lt;ref name="Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Note:'' See New Zealand No 47 Declarations and Reservations New Zealand has signed this treaty on behalf on Niue.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Republic of China]] (Taiwan) in 2007 has also ratified the treaty in its legislature, but is unrecognized by the United Nations and is a party to the treaty only unofficially.&lt;ref&gt;Government Information Office, Republic of China (Taiwan). "Taiwan Aims to Sign Up Against Discrimination." September 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The latest state to have acceded the convention was [[Nauru]] on June 23, 2011.&lt;ref name="Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women" /&gt;

==Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women==
Convention oversight is the task of the '''Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women''', which is made up of 23 experts on women's issues from different UN member states. The Committee meets twice a year to review reports on compliance with the Convention's provisions that the signatory nations are required to submit every four years.

The Committee is one of the eight [[Human rights#Other UN Treaty Bodies|UN-related human rights treaty bodies]].

The Committee's members, described as "experts of high moral standing and competence in the field covered by the Convention", are elected to serve four-year terms in staggered elections held every two years. Its officers are a chairperson, three vice-chairpersons, and a rapporteur.  Efforts are made to ensure balanced geographical representation and the inclusion of the world's different forms of civilization and legal systems.

Committee members and experts also attend an annual luncheon, hosted by the NGO Committee on the Status of Women, NY ([[NGO CSW/NY]]), where key issues are discusses and the efforts of the committee are honored.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ngocsw.org/about/how-we-work |title=NGO CSW, NY / About / How We Work |publisher=Ngocsw.org |date=2011-07-26 |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of January 2011, the members are:

{| class="wikitable" style="width:450px;"
|-
! Name !! State !!  Term Expires
|-
|[[Silvia Pimentel]] (Chairperson) || {{flag|Brazil}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Victoria Popescu]] (Vice-Chairperson) || {{flag|Romania}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Zohra Rasekh]] (Vice-Chairperson) || {{flag|Afghanistan}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Nicole Ameline]] (Vice-Chairperson) || {{flag|France}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Violet Tsisiga Awori]] (Rapporteur) || {{flag|Kenya}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Magalys Arocha Dominguez]] || {{flag|Cuba}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Barbara Evelyn Bailey]] || {{flag|Jamaica}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Niklas Bruun]] || {{flag|Finland}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Indira Jaising]] || {{flag|India}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Soledad Murillo de la Vega]] || {{flag|Spain}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Zou Xiaoqiao]]  || {{flag|China}} ||  2012
|-
|[[Ayse Feride Acar]] || {{flag|Turkey}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Olinda Bareiro-Bobadilla]] || {{flag|Paraguay}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Meriem Belmihoub-Zerdani]] || {{flag|Algeria}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Naela Mohamed Gabr]] || {{flag|Egypt}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Ruth Halperin-Kaddari]] || {{flag|Israel}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Yoko Hayashi]] || {{flag|Japan}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Ismat Jahan]] || {{flag|Bangladesh}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Violeta Neubauer]] || {{flag|Slovenia}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Pramila Patten]] || {{flag|Mauritius}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Maria Helena Lopes de Jesus Pires]] || {{flag|Timor Leste}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Patricia Schulz]] || {{flag|Switzerland}} ||  2014
|-
|[[Dubravka Šimonović]] || {{flag|Croatia}} ||  2014
|}

==Optional Protocol==
The '''[[Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]]''' is a side-agreement to the Convention which allows its parties to recognise the competence of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women to consider complaints from individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/instree/cedawopprot-2000.html Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women], Article 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Optional Protocol was adopted by the UN General Assembly on 6 October 1999 and entered into force on 22 December 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/protocol/wom1242.htm |title=Optional Protocol to Women's Convention Comes into Force |date=2000-12-21 |accessdate=2008-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently it has 79 signatories and 104 parties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8-b&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en |title= Parties to the Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women |publisher=UN OHCHR |accessdate=2009-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
{{POV|date=September 2010}}
In an article in ''[[Moment (magazine)|Moment]]'' magazine in February 2011, Paula Kweskin, in discussing so-called “honor” killings taking place in the Palestinian Authority, writes that two-thirds of all murders in the Palestinian Authority and Gaza are [[honor killing|“honor” killings]].  These crimes go unpunished and laws grant impunity to those who kill based on “family honor.” In interviews and press releases on their websites, many NGOs, including Badil, the Palestinian Center for Human Rights, and the Women’s Center for Legal Aid and Counseling, have decried “honor” killings and the lack of legal protection for Palestinian women; yet these NGOs are silent when given a forum at CEDAW to address these problems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=by elisniv |url=http://momentmagazine.wordpress.com/2011/02/24/ngos-fail-palestinian-women-at-the-un/ |title=NGOs Fail Palestinian Women at the UN |publisher=Momentmagazine.wordpress.com |date=2011-02-24 |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The CEDAW has been controversial for statements that have been made by some of its members which were seen by a number of states and NGOs as promoting Western-style [[feminism]]. Often referenced is a 2000 report which said that in [[Belarus]], "the Committee is concerned by the continuing prevalence of sex-role stereotypes and by the reintroduction of such symbols as a [[Mothers' Day]] and a Mothers' Award, which it sees as encouraging women's traditional roles."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/reports/a5538.pdf |title=Womenwatch report |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other controversial positions of CEDAW include supporting the decriminalization of prostitution in specific countries, criticizing Slovenia because only 30% of children are in daycare, and pressuring numerous states to decriminalize abortion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fota.cdnetworks.net/pdfs/2009-02-b-80-Nations-Pressured-by-CEDAW-Comm-summ.pdf |title=Nations Pressured by CEDAW |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other requests are seen by groups as a backdoor to forcing states parties to adopt an [[Equal Rights Amendment]] or comparable national legislation, which is seen as a violation of the CEDAW treaty mandate and the sovereignty of states parties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cwfa.org/articledisplay.asp?id=1971 |title=Concerned Women for America - Exposing CEDAW |publisher=Cwfa.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

More recently, the controversy concerning CEDAW has centered around the question of easy access to abortion and contraception. According to C-FAM (the [[Catholic Family and Human Rights Institute]]), at UN meetings officials pressed the delegation from Slovakia to liberalize its abortion laws and to inaugurate campaigns encouraging contraceptive use and "reproductive health awareness".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.c-fam.org/publications/id.664/pub_detail.asp |title=UN Committee Pressures Slovakia over its Concordat with the Catholic Church}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Equal Rights Amendment]]
* [[Parental leave]]
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Mixed-sex education]]
* [[Declaration on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women]]
* [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]]
* [[United Nations Development Fund for Women]]
* [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1325]]
* [[UN Women]]
* [[Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence]]

==Further reading==
* [http://www.ipu.org/PDF/publications/cedaw_en.pdf The Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women and its Optional Protocol: Handbook for Parlamentarians], [[Inter-Parliamentary Union]] 2003
* [http://www.unifem.org/gender_issues/women_war_peace/%20 UN WOMEN "Women, War &amp; Peace"]
* [http://unwomen-nc.org.sg/gender_issues_datasheet_4.shtml UN WOMEN Singapore Committee - Governance, Peace &amp; Security]
* [http://www.unifem.org/gender_issues/violence_against_women/ UN WOMEN "Violence Against Women"]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/index.htm CEDAW site]
* [http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/cedaw.htm Convention text]
* [http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-8&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en List of parties]
* [http://www.cedaw2010.org/ CEDAW 2010], the website of the CEDAW Task Force of The Leadership Conference on Civil and Human Rights.
* [http://untreaty.un.org/cod/avl/ha/cedaw/cedaw.html Introductory note by Dubravka Šimonović, procedural history note and audiovisual material] on the ''Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women'' in the [http://untreaty.un.org/cod/avl/historicarchives.html Historic Archives of the United Nations Audiovisual Library of International Law]

{{International human rights legal instruments}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Convention On The Elimination Of All Forms Of Discrimination Against Women}}
[[Category:Treaties concluded in 1979]]
[[Category:Treaties entered into force in 1981]]
[[Category:Discrimination law]]
[[Category:United Nations conventions and covenants]]
[[Category:Reproductive rights]]
[[Category:Women's rights instruments]]

[[ar:اتفاقية القضاء على جميع أشكال التمييز ضد المرأة]]
[[da:FN's kvindekonvention]]
[[de:Übereinkommen zur Beseitigung jeder Form von Diskriminierung der Frau]]
[[et:Konventsioon naiste diskrimineerimise kõigi vormide likvideerimise kohta]]
[[el:Επιτροπή εξάλειψης διακρίσεων κατά γυναικών]]
[[es:Convención sobre la eliminación de todas las formas de discriminación contra la mujer]]
[[fa:کنوانسیون امحای کلیه اشکال تبعیض علیه زنان]]
[[fr:Convention sur l'élimination de toutes les formes de discrimination à l'égard des femmes]]
[[gl:Convención sobre a eliminación de todas as formas de discriminación contra a muller]]
[[ko:여성에 대한 모든 형태의 차별철폐에 관한 협약]]
[[it:Convenzione sull'eliminazione di ogni forma di discriminazione della donna]]
[[la:Conventio de Abrogatione in omni forma Discriminationis contra Mulieres]]
[[lv:Konvencija par jebkuras sieviešu diskriminācijas izskaušanu]]
[[nl:Verdrag inzake de uitbanning van alle vormen van discriminatie van vrouwen]]
[[ja:女子に対するあらゆる形態の差別の撤廃に関する条約]]
[[no:FNs kvinnekonvensjon]]
[[pl:Konwencja w sprawie Likwidacji Wszelkich Form Dyskryminacji Kobiet]]
[[ru:Конвенция о ликвидации всех форм дискриминации в отношении женщин]]
[[simple:Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]]
[[sv:FN:s kvinnokonvention]]
[[ta:பெண்களுக்கு எதிரான அனைத்து பாகுபாடுகளையும் ஒழிப்பதற்கான உடன்படிக்கை]]
[[th:อนุสัญญาว่าด้วยการขจัดการเลือกปฏิบัติต่อสตรีในทุกรูปแบบ]]
[[tr:Kadına Karşı Her Türlü Ayrımcılığın Yok Edilmesi Sözleşmesi]]
[[vi:Công ước loại bỏ mọi hình thức phân biệt đối xử với phụ nữ]]
[[war:CEDAW]]
[[zh:消除對婦女一切形式歧視公約]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>