<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141102213126|632193465" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="58849" pageid="58849" ns="0" title="Gender studies"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-15T05:31:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Gender studies''' is a [[Field of study|field]] of [[Interdisciplinarity|interdisciplinary]] study and [[List of academic disciplines|academic field]] devoted to [[gender identity]] and gendered [[Representation (politics)|representation]] as central categories of analysis. This field includes [[women's studies]] (concerning [[women]], [[feminism]], gender, and politics), [[men's studies]], and [[LGBT studies]].&lt;ref name="whitman"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.whitman.edu/content/genderstudies | title=Gender Studies | publisher=Whitman College | accessdate=May 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes, gender studies is offered together with study of [[Human sexuality|sexuality]]. These disciplines study [[gender]] and sexuality in the fields of literature, language, [[history]], [[political science]], [[sociology]], [[anthropology]], [[cinema studies|cinema]], [[media studies]], human development, law, and medicine.&lt;ref name="uchicago"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://gendersexuality.uchicago.edu/about/ | title=About - Center for the Study of Gender and Sexuality (CSGS) | publisher=[[The University of Chicago]] | accessdate=May 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also analyzes [[Race (human classification)|race]], [[ethnicity]], [[Location (geography)|location]], [[nationality]], and [[disability]].&lt;ref name="Race, Ethnicity, Gender &amp; Class"&gt;Healey, J. F. (2003). "Race, Ethnicity, Gender and Class: the Sociology of Group Conflict and Change".&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="indiana"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.indiana.edu/~gender/ | title=Department of Gender Studies | publisher=[[Indiana University]] (IU Bloomington) | accessdate=May 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gender study has many different forms. One view espoused by the philosopher [[Simone de Beauvoir]] said: "One is not born a woman, one becomes one".&lt;ref name="de Beauvoir"&gt;de Beauvoir, S. (1949, 1989). "The Second Sex".&lt;/ref&gt; This view proposes that in gender studies, the term "gender" should be used to refer to the [[social constructionism|social and cultural constructions]] of masculinities and femininities, not to the state of being male or female in its entirety.&lt;ref name="Stephanie Garrett"&gt;Garrett, S. (1992). "Gender", p. vii.&lt;/ref&gt; However, this view is not held by all gender theorists. Other areas {{which|date=January 2013}} of gender study closely examine the role that the biological states of being male or female (anatomical, physiological, and genetical explanations of male and female body parts, structure and nature of functions of body organs, genetic carriers etc.) have on social constructs of gender. Specifically, in what way gender roles are defined by biology and how they are defined by cultural trends. The field emerged from a number of different areas: the sociology of the 1950s and later (see [[Sociology of gender]]); the theories of the psychoanalyst [[Jacques Lacan#Lacan and his discontents|Jacques Lacan]]; and the work of feminists such as [[Judith Butler]].

Gender is an important area of study in many disciplines, such as [[literary theory]], drama studies, [[film theory]], performance theory, contemporary [[art history]], anthropology, sociology, [[sociolinguistics]] and [[psychology]]. These disciplines sometimes differ in their approaches to how and why they study gender. For instance in anthropology, sociology and psychology, gender is often studied as a practice, whereas in cultural studies representations of gender are more often examined.  In politics, gender can be viewed as a foundational discourse that political actors employ in order to position themselves on a variety of issues.&lt;ref&gt;Salime, Zakia. Between Feminism and Islam: Human Rights and Sharia Law in Morocco. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Gender studies is also a discipline in itself: an interdisciplinary area of study that incorporates methods and approaches from a wide range of disciplines.&lt;ref name=companion&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Essed | first1 = Philomena | authorlink1 = Philomena Essed | last2 = Goldberg | first2 = David Theo | authorlink2 = David Theo Goldberg | last3 = Kobayashi | first3 = Audrey | authorlink3 = Audrey Kobayashi | title = A Companion to Gender Studies | publisher = Wiley-Blackwell | year = 2009 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=ZPgYDTa9P84C&amp;dq=genders+studies | accessdate = 7 November 2011 | isbn = 978-1-4051-8808-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Each field came to regard "gender" as a practice, sometimes referred to as something that is [[Performative utterance|performative]].&lt;ref name = "performativity of gender"/&gt; [[Feminist theory]] of psychoanalysis, articulated mainly by [[Julia Kristeva]]&lt;ref&gt;Anne-Marie Smith, ''Julia Kristeva: Speaking the Unspeakable'' (Pluto Press, 1988)&lt;/ref&gt; (the "semiotic" and "abjection") and [[Bracha Ettinger]]&lt;ref&gt;Griselda Pollock, "Inscriptions in the Feminine" and "Introduction" to "The With-In-Visible Screen", in: ''Inside the Visible'' edited by Catherine de Zegher. MIT Press, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; (the feminine-prematernal-maternal matrixial Eros of borderlinking and com-passion,&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;Bracha L. Ettinger, "Diotima and the Matrixial Transference: Psychoanalytical Encounter-Event as Pregnancy in Beauty." In: Van der Merwe, Chris N., and Viljoen, Hein, eds. ''Across the Threshold''. NY: Peter Lang, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; "matrixial trans-subjectivity" and the "primal mother-phantasies"),&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mamsie.bbk.ac.uk/mother_respect.html&lt;/ref&gt; and informed both by [[Freud]], Lacan and the [[object relations theory]], is very influential in gender studies.

==Influences of gender studies==

===Gender studies and psychoanalytic theory===

====Sigmund Freud====
Some feminist ''critics'' {{who|date=July 2013}} have dismissed the work of [[Sigmund Freud]] as sexist, because of his view that women are 'mutilated and must learn to accept their lack of a penis' (in Freud's terms a "deformity").&lt;ref&gt;[[Karen Horney]] was one of the first to question the theory of penis envy. She argues that it is "the actual social subordination of women" that shapes their development: not the lack of the organ, but of the privilege that goes with it. Karen Horney (1922). "On the Genesis of the Castration Complex in Women" ''Psychoanalysis and Women''. Ed. J.B. Miller. New York: Bruner/Mazel, 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the other hand, feminist theorists such as [[Juliet Mitchell]], [[Nancy Chodorow]], [[Jessica Benjamin]], [[Jane Gallop]], [[Bracha Ettinger]], [[Shoshana Felman]], [[Griselda Pollock]],&lt;ref&gt;Griselda Pollock, ''Encounters in the Virtual Feminist Museum: Time, Space and the Archive''. Routledge. 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Luce Irigaray]] and Jane Flax have developed a Feminist psychoanalysis and argued that psychoanalytic theory is vital to the feminist project and must, like other theoretical traditions, be criticized by women as well as transformed to free it from vestiges of sexism (i.e. being [[censored]]). [[Shulamith Firestone]], in "The Dialectic of Sex" calls Freudianism the misguided feminism and discusses how Freudianism is ''almost'' completely accurate, with the exception of one crucial detail: everywhere that Freud writes "penis", the word should be replaced with "power".

====Jacques Lacan====
Lacan's theory of sexuation organizes femininity and masculinity according to different unconscious structures. Both male and female subjects participate in the "phallic" organization, and the feminine side of sexuation is "supplementary" and not opposite or complementary.&lt;ref&gt;Lacan, J. (1973). ''Encore''. Paris: Seuil, 1975.&lt;/ref&gt; Sexuation (sexual situation) — the development of gender-roles and role-play in childhood — breaks down concepts of gender identity as innate or biologically determined. (clarify-refutes?challenges?)&lt;ref name="Lacan &amp; Post-feminism"&gt;Wright, E. (2003). "Lacan and Postfeminism (Postmodern Encounters)"&lt;/ref&gt;
Critics like [[Elizabeth Grosz]] accuse [[Jacques Lacan]] of maintaining a sexist tradition in psychoanalysis.&lt;ref name ="Grosz"&gt;Grosz, E. (1990).  "Jacques Lacan: A Feminist Introduction", London: Routledge&lt;/ref&gt; Others, such as [[Judith Butler]], [[Bracha Ettinger]] and [[Jane Gallop]] have used Lacanian work, though in a critical way, to develop gender theory.&lt;ref name="Gender Trouble"&gt;Butler, J. (1999). "Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity".&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ettinger"&gt;Ettinger, B. (Collected Essays from 1994–1999). "The Matrixial Borderspace", [[University of Minnesota Press]], 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Gallop"&gt;Gallop, J. (1993). "The Daughter's Seduction: Feminism and Psychoanalysi", Cornell University Press&lt;/ref&gt;

====Julia Kristeva====
{{Main|Julia Kristeva}}
Julia Kristeva has significantly developed the field of semiotics. In her work on [[abjection]], she structures subjectivity upon the abjection of the mother and argues that the way in which an individual excludes (or abjects) their mother as means of forming an identity is similar to the way in which societies are constructed. She contends that patriarchal cultures, like individuals, have to exclude the maternal and the feminine so that they can come into being.&lt;ref name="Kristeva Abject"&gt;Kristeva, J. (1982). "Powers of Horror"&lt;/ref&gt;

====Bracha Ettinger====
{{Main|Bracha Ettinger}}
Bracha Ettinger transformed subjectivity in contemporary psychoanalysis since the early 1990s with the Matrixial&lt;ref&gt;Bracha L. Ettinger, "Matrix and Metramorphosis." In: ''Differences''. Vol. 4, nº 3: 176–208, 1992&lt;/ref&gt; feminine-maternal and prematernal Eros&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; of borderlinking (bordureliance), borderspacing (bordurespacement) and co-emergence. The matrixial feminine difference defines a particular gaze&lt;ref&gt;Bracha L. Ettinger, ''The Matrixial Borderspace''. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2006 (articles from 1994–1999). ISBN 0-8166-3587-0&lt;/ref&gt; and it is a source for trans-subjectivity and transjectivity&lt;ref&gt;Bracha L. Ettinger, "Matrixial Trans-subjectivity" in: ''Problematizing Global Knowledge''. Theory, Culture &amp; Society, Volume 23, Numbers 2–3, 2006. ISSN 0263-2764&lt;/ref&gt; in both males and females. Ettinger rethinks the human subject as informed by the archaic connectivity to the maternal and proposes the idea of a Demeter-Persephone Complexity.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|mdkbYsjlMA8|public lecture at EGS (2012)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Mark Blechner====
{{Main|Mark Blechner}}
Mark Blechner expanded psychoanalytic views of sex and gender, calling psychoanalysis "the once and future queer science".&lt;ref&gt;Blechner, M. J. (2009) 'Sex Changes: Transformations in Society and Psychoanalysis.' New York and London: Taylor &amp; Francis.&lt;/ref&gt;  He has argued that there is a "gender fetish" in western society, in which the gender of sexual partners is given enormously disproportionate attention over other factors involved in sexual attraction, such as age and social class. He proposes that the words "homosexuality" and "heterosexuality" be given prefixes, depending on the dimension that is the same or different between partners.&lt;ref&gt;Blechner, M. J. (1995) The shaping of psychoanalytic theory and practice by cultural and personal biases about sexuality. In T. Domenici and R. Lesser, (eds.) 'Disorienting Sexuality.' New York: Routledge, pp. 265–288.&lt;/ref&gt;  "Age heterosexuality" would indicate an attraction between people of different ages, for example. What is conventionally called "heterosexuality" (attraction between a man and a woman) would be called "gender heterosexuality".

Cultures can have very different norms of maleness and [[masculinity]]. Blechner identifies the terror, in Western males, of penetration. Yet in many societies, being gay is defined only by being a male who lets himself be penetrated. Males who penetrate other males are considered masculine and not gay and are not the targets of prejudice.&lt;ref&gt;Blechner, M. J. (1998) Maleness and masculinity. 'Contemporary Psychoanalysis,' 34:597–613.&lt;/ref&gt;  In other cultures, however, receptive [[fellatio]] is the norm for early adolescence and seen as a requirement for developing normal manliness.&lt;ref&gt;Herdt, G. (1981) 'Guardians of the Flute.' New York: McGraw-Hill.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Literary theory===
Psychoanalytically oriented French feminism focused on visual and literary theory all along. [[Virginia Woolf]]'s legacy as well as "[[Adrienne Rich]]'s call for women's revisions of literary texts, and history as well, has galvanized a generation of feminist authors to reply with texts of their own".&lt;ref&gt;Mica Howe &amp; Sarah A. Aguier (eds.). ''He said, She Says''. Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Griselda Pollock]] and other feminists have articulated Myth and Poetry&lt;ref name="Vanda Zajko 2006"&gt;Vanda Zajko &amp; Miriam Leonard (eds.). ''Laughing with Medusa''. Oxford University Press, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and literature,&lt;ref name="Vanda Zajko 2006"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Humm, Maggie, ''Modernist Women and Visual Cultures''. Rutgers University Press, 2003. ISBN 0-8135-3266-3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nina Cornietz, ''Dangerous Women, Deadly Words''. Stanford University Press, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; from the point of view of gender.

===Post-modern influence===
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}
The emergence of [[post-modernism]] theories affected gender studies,&lt;ref name="Lacan &amp; Post-feminism"/&gt; causing a movement in [[Gender identity|theories identity]] away from the concept of fixed or [[essentialism|essentialist]] gender identity, to [[Postmodernity#Distinctions in philosophy and critical theory|post-modern]]&lt;ref&gt;Grebowicz, M. (2007). ''Gender After Lyotard''. NY: SUNY Press, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; fluid&lt;ref&gt;Zohar, Ayelet (ed.), ''PostGender''. Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; or multiple identities.&lt;ref name=""Feminist Contentions"&gt;Benhabib, S.  (1995). "Feminist Contentions: A Philosophical Exchange" and Butler, J. (1995) "Feminist Contentions: A Philosophical Exchange".&lt;/ref&gt;

See [[Donna Haraway]], ''The Cyborg Manifesto,'' as an example of post-identity feminism.

More recently, the relation between post-modernism or post-structuralism and masculinity has been considered, whereby masculinity too can be taken as always in movement and never fixed or stable.&lt;ref&gt;Reeser,''Masculinities in Theory'', 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

==The development of gender theory==

===History of gender studies===

After the revolution of the universal suffrage of the 20 th Century and the women's liberation movement of the 1970s promoted a revision from the feminists to "actively interrogate" the usual and accepted versions of the History as it was known at the time. New way of looking at history came out of the analysis. This gave birth to the Gender History studies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Liddington|first=Jill|title=HISTORY, FEMINISM AND GENDER STUDIES|url=http://www.jliddington.org.uk/cig1.html|publisher=University of Leeds Centre for Interdisciplinary Gender Studies: Working Paper 1 Feminist Scholarship: within/across/between/beyond the disciplines}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women's studies===
{{Main|Women's studies}}
Women's studies is an [[interdisciplinary]] [[List of academic disciplines|academic field]] devoted to topics concerning [[women]], [[feminism]], [[gender identity|gender]], and [[politics]]. It often includes [[feminist theory]], [[women's history]] (e.g. a history of [[women's suffrage]]) and [[social history]], [[women's fiction]], [[women's health]], feminist psychoanalysis and the [[feminist]] and gender studies-influenced practice of most of the [[humanities]] and [[social sciences]].

===Men's studies===
{{Main|Men's studies}}
Men's studies is an [[interdisciplinary]] [[List of academic disciplines|academic field]] devoted to topics concerning [[men]], [[masculism]], [[gender identity|gender]], and [[politics]].  It often includes feminist theory, men's history and [[social history]], [[men's fiction]], [[men's health]], feminist psychoanalysis and the feminist and gender studies-influenced practice of most of the [[humanities]] and [[social sciences]].

===Judith Butler===
{{Main|Judith Butler}}

The concept of gender performativity is at the core of Butler's work, notably in ''[[Gender Trouble]]''. In Butler’s terms the performance of gender, sex, and sexuality is about power in society.&lt;ref name="performativity of gender"&gt;Butler, J. (1999). "Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity", 9.&lt;/ref&gt;  She locates the [[Social constructivism|construction]] of the "gendered, sexed, desiring subject" in "regulative discourses".
A part of Butler's argument concerns the role of sex in the construction of "natural" or coherent gender and sexuality. In her account, gender and heterosexuality are constructed as natural because the opposition of the male and female sexes is perceived as natural in the social imaginary.&lt;ref name="performativity of gender"&gt;Butler, J. (1999). "Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity", 163–71, 177–8.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Responses==
Historian and theorist Bryan Palmer argues that gender studies' current reliance on [[post-structuralism]] – with its reification of discourse and avoidance of the structures of oppression and struggles of resistance – obscures the origins, meanings, and consequences of historical events and processes, and he seeks to counter the current gender studies with an argument for the necessity to analyze lived experience and the structures of subordination and power.&lt;ref&gt;Bryan Palmer, "Descent into Discourse: The Reification of Language and the Writing of Social History", Trent University (Peterborough, Canada)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Rosi Braidotti]] has criticized gender studies as: "the take-over of the feminist agenda by studies on masculinity, which results in transferring funding from feminist faculty positions to other kinds of positions. There have been cases...of positions advertised as 'gender studies' being given away to the 'bright boys'. Some of the competitive take-over has to do with gay studies. Of special significance in this discussion is the role of the mainstream publisher Routledge who, in our opinion, is responsible for promoting gender as a way of deradicalizing the feminist agenda, re-marketing masculinity and gay male identity instead."{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}  Calvin Thomas countered that, "as Joseph Allen Boone points out, 'many of the men in the academy who are feminism's most supportive 'allies' ''are'' gay,'" and that it is "disingenuous" to ignore the ways in which mainstream publishers such as Routledge have promoted feminist theorists.{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}

==Other people whose work is associated with gender studies==
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-1-of-3}}
* [[Sara Ahmed]]
* [[Simone de Beauvoir]]
* [[Kate Bornstein]]
* [[Marie-George Buffet]]
* [[Judith Butler]]
* [[Micha Cárdenas]]
* [[Yves Durand (politician)|Yves Durand]]
* [[Bracha Ettinger]]
* [[Warren Farrell]]
* [[Michel Foucault]]
* [[Martine Faure]]
* [[Kristen R. Ghodsee]]
* [[Charlotte Perkins Gilman]]
* [[Madeleine Grumet]]
{{Col-2-of-3}}
* [[Judith Halberstam]]
* [[Donna Haraway]]
* [[bell hooks]]
* [[Karen Horney]]
* [[Luce Irigaray]]
* [[Evelyn Fox Keller]]
* [[Alfred Kinsey]]
* [[Julia Kristeva]]
* [[Audre Lorde]]
* [[Martine Martinel]]
* [[Angela McRobbie]]
* [[Laura Mulvey]]
* [[Vincent Peillon]]
{{Col-3-of-3}}
* [[Griselda Pollock]]
* [[Gayle Rubin]]
* [[Sarojini Sahoo]]
* [[Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick]]
* [[Kaja Silverman]]
* [[Dean Spade]]
* [[Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak]]
* [[Robert Stoller]]
* [[Sandy Stone (artist)]]
* [[Sylvia Walby]]
* [[Otto Weininger]]
* [[Monique Wittig]]
* [[Mary Wollstonecraft]]
{{Col-end}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Gender studies}}
{{Columns-list|2|
*[[Femininity]] and [[Masculinity]]
*[[Feminism]] and [[Masculism]]
*[[Feminist theory]]
*[[French feminism]]
*[[Gender]]
*[[Gender history]]
*[[Family economics]]
*[[Gender identity]]
*[[Gender identity disorder]]
*[[Gender role]]
*[[Genderqueer]]
*[[Gender sensitization]]
*[[Gynocentrism]] and [[Androcentrism]]
*[[Homophobia]], [[Heterophobia]], and [[Biphobia]]
*[[Intersexuality]]
*[[List of transgender-related topics]]
*[[Male Studies in the Caribbean]]
*[[Men and feminism]]
*[[Misogyny]] and [[Misandry]] ([[Sexism]])
*[[Postfeminism]]
*[[Postgenderism]]
*[[Queer theory]]
*[[Sex and gender distinction]]
*[[Sex differences in humans]]
*[[Sexual orientation hypothesis]]
*[[Sex and psychology]]
*[[Sexism]]
*[[Stereotyping]]
*[[Transgender]]
*[[Transphobia]]
*[[Women's liberation]] and [[Men's liberation]]
*[[Women's movement]] and [[Men's movement]]
*[[Women's rights]] and [[Men's rights]]
*[[Women's studies]] and [[Men's studies]]
}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|33em}}

== Bibliography ==
{{Hidden|Bibliography|
*Armstrong, Carol and de Zegher, Catherine (eds) (2006). ''Women Artists as the Millennium''. Cambridge Massachusetts: October Books, MIT Press. ISBN 978-0-262-01226-3 {{cite book|title= |oclc=62766150}}
*Boone, Joseph Allen and Michael Cadden, eds., 1990. ''Engendering Men'', New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-90255-X {{cite book|title= |oclc=20992567}}
*Butler, Judith, 1993.  "Bodies That Matter: On the Discursive Limits of 'Sex", New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-90366-1 {{cite book|title= |oclc=27897792}}
*Butler, Judith, "Feminism by Any Other Name", in ''differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies'' June, 1994. ISSN 1040-7391
*Butler, Judith, 1999.  ''Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity''. New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-92499-5 {{cite book|title= |oclc=41326734}}
*{{cite book |last=Cante |first=Richard C. |title=Gay Men and the Forms of Contemporary US Culture |publisher=Ashgate Publishing. ISBN 0-7546-7230-1 |date=March 2008 |location=London |oclc=173218594}}
*Cárdenas, Micha and Barbara Fornssler, 2010. ''Trans Desire/Affective Cyborgs''. New York: Atropos press. ISBN 0-9825309-9-4
*Cranny-Francis, Anne, Joan Kirkby, Pam Stavropoulos, Wendy Waring, eds., 2003. "Gender studies: terms and debates", Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan. ISBN 0-333-77612-7 {{cite book|title= |oclc=50645644}}
*De Beauvoir, Simone, 1989.  ''The Second Sex''. New York: random House Inc. ISBN 0-679-72451-6 {{cite book|title= |oclc=20905133}}
*Ettinger, Bracha L., 2001. "The Red Cow Effect", Reprinted in: Mica Howe &amp; Sarah A. Aguiar (eds.), ''He Said, She Says''. Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 2001. 57–88. ISBN 0-8386-3915-1 {{cite book|title= |oclc=46472137}}
*Farrell, W., 1994. ''The Myth of Male Power: Why Men are the Disposable Sex'', New York: Berkley Books.
*Ettinger, Bracha L., 2006 (Essays 1994–1999). ''The Matrixial Borderspace'', University of Minnesota Press. ISBN 0-8166-3587-0 {{cite book|title= |oclc=62177997}}
*Ettinger, Bracha L., 2006. "From Proto-ethical Compassion to Responsibility: Besidedness, and the three Primal Mother-Phantasies of Not-enoughness, Devouring and Abandonment". ''Athena: Philosophical Studies''. Vol. 2. {{ISSN|1822-5047}}.
*Foucault, Michel, 1988. "Care of the Self the History of Sexuality", Random House Inc. ISBN 0-394-74155-2 {{cite book|title= |oclc=20521501}}
*Foucault, Michel, 1990. "History of Sexuality: An Introduction", London: Random House Inc. ISBN 0-679-72469-9 {{cite book|title= |oclc=5102034}}
*Foucault, Michel, 1990. "Use of Pleasure: The History of Sexuality", London: Random House Inc. ISBN 0-394-75122-1 {{cite book|title= |oclc=5102034}}
*Foucault, Michel, 1995. "Discipline and Punish: The Birth of the Prison", translated by Allen Sheridan, London: Random House ISBN 0-679-75255-2 {{cite book|title= |oclc=32367111}}
*Fraser, Nancy, Judith Butler, Seyla Benhabib, and Drucilla Cornell, 1995. "Feminist Contentions: A Philosophical Exchange", New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-91086-2 {{cite book|title= |oclc=30623637}}
*Frug, Mary Joe. "A Postmodern Feminist Legal Manifesto (An Unfinished Draft)", in "''Harvard Law Review''", Vol. 105, No. 5, March, 1992, pp.&amp;nbsp;1045–1075. ISSN: 0017-811X
*Grebowicz, Margaret, (2007). ''Gender After Lyotard''. NY: Suny Press. ISBN 978-0-7914-6956-9 {{cite book|title= |oclc=63472631}}
*Healey, Joseph F., 2003. ''Race, Ethnicity, Gender and Class: the Sociology of Group Conflict and Change''. London: Pine Forge. ISBN 0-7619-8763-0 {{cite book|title= |oclc=50604843}}
*Kristeva, Julia, 1982.  "Powers of Horror. Trans. Leon Roudiez", New York: Columbia University Press. ISBN 0-231-05347-9 {{cite book|title= |oclc=8430152}}
*Farrell, W., Sterba, J. "Does Feminism Discriminate Against Men?  A Debate", New York: Oxford University Press.
* Kahlert, Heike / Schäfer, Sabine (eds.): Engendering Transformation. Post-socialist Experiences on Work, Politics and Culture. Opladen, Berlin, London, Toronto: Barbara Budrich Publishers 2012, ISBN 978-3-86649-422-0.
*Palmer, Bryan D., "Descent into Discourse: The Reification of Language and the Writing of Social History", Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 1999, ISBN 0-87722-720-9 {{cite book|title= |oclc=233030494}}
*Pinker, Susan, 2008. ''The Sexual Paradox: Extreme Men, Gifted Women and the Real Gender Gap''. Random. ISBN 0-679-31415-6 {{cite book|title= |oclc=181078409}}
*Pollock, Griselda, 2001. "Looking Back to the Future". G&amp;B Arts. ISBN 90-5701-132-8{{cite book|title= |oclc=42875273}}
*Pollock, Griselda, 2007. ''Encounters in the Virtual Feminist Museum: Time, Space and the Archive''. Routledge. ISBN 0-415-41374-5 {{cite book|title= |oclc=129952714}}
*Ridley-Duff, R. J., 2005. ''Interpersonal Dynamics: A Communitarian Perspective'', paper to MCA-ENROAC Conference, Antwerp. 7–9 April. [http://digitalcommons.shu.ac.uk/ciod_papers/1/]
*Ridley-Duff, R. J., 2007. ''Emotion, Seduction and Intimacy: Alternative Perspectives on Organisation Behaviour'', Bracknell: Men's Hour Books, ISBN 978-0-9754300-1-9, [http://www.scribd.com/doc/4912718/]
*Wright, Elizabeth, 2000.  ''Lacan and Postfeminism''. London: Icon Books Ltd. ISBN 1-84046-182-9 {{cite book|title= |oclc=44484099}}
*McElroy, Wendy, 2001. ''Sexual Correctness: The Gender-Feminist Attack on Women'', Jefferson: McFarland &amp; Company. ISBN 0-7864-0226-1 {{cite book|title= |oclc=34839792}}
*[[Oyèrónkẹ́ Oyěwùmí|Oyewumi, Oyeronke]], ed., 2005.  ''African Gender Studies: A Reader'', London: Palgrave MacMillan. {{cite book|title= |oclc=|isbn=1-4039-6283-9}}
*Reeser, Todd W. ''Masculinities in Theory'' (Malden: Wylie-Blackwell, 2010).
*Scott, Joan W. "Gender: A Useful Category of Historical Analysis", in ''Gender and the Politics of History'' (New York: Columbia University Press, 1988).
*Spector, Judith A, ed., 1986.  ''Gender Studies: New Directions in Feminist Criticism'', Madison: University of Wisconsin Press. {{cite book|title= |oclc=|isbn=0-87972-351-3}}
*Thomas, Calvin, ed., 2000. "Introduction: Identification, Appropriation, Proliferation", in ''Straight with a Twist: Queer Theory and the Subject of Heterosexuality''. Champaign: University of Illinois Press. {{cite book|title= |oclc=|isbn=0-252-06813-0 }}
*Zajko, Vanda and Leonard, Miriam, 2006. "Laughing with Medusa". Oxford University Press. {{cite book|title= |oclc=|isbn=0-19-927438-X}}
*de Zegher, Catherine (ed.) (1996). ''Inside the Visible''. MIT Press, Boston. {{cite book|title= |oclc=33863951|isbn=0-262-54081-9}}
}}

== External links ==
*[http://genport.uoc.edu/ GenPORT: Your gateway to gender and science resources]
*[http://www.xyonline.net/index.shtml xy: men, masculinities and gender politics]
*[http://namesorts.com/2014/03/14/onomastics-api-for-gender-studies/ Gendre, onomastics gender inference for Gender Studies]
*[http://moodle.ed.uiuc.edu/wiked/index.php/Gender_Inequities_in_the_Classroom WikEd – Gender Inequities in the Classroom]
*[http://www.intellinate.com/science/social-sciences/psychology/childrens-gender-beliefs.html Children’s Gender Beliefs]
*[http://www.gender.at.ua/ Gender Museum], a museum of women's history and women and gender movement.
*[http://genderstereotype.nomaki.jp/ Gender Stereotypes - Changes in People's Thoughts], a report based on a survey on roles of men and women.
*[http://urfak.petrsu.ru/gender_center.htm Karelian Center for Gender Studies (Regional NGO "KCGS")]
*[http://www.turtlebayandbeyond.org/2012/homosexuality/nordic-countries-defund-gender-ideology/ Nordic Countries Defund Gender Ideology]
*[http://vimeo.com/19707588 The Gender Equality Paradox]
*[http://www.hnkcnews.com/2014/04/09/obama-pushes-for-equal-pay-for-women/ Obama Pushes for Equal Pay for Women]
{{Feminism}}
{{LGBT |state=collapsed |academy=expanded}}
{{Sexual identities}}
{{Social sciences}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gender Studies}}
[[Category:Critical theory]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Branches of sociology (interdisciplinary)]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Gender studies| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>