<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020829150907|183621" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="59635" pageid="59635" ns="0" title="Equal Rights Amendment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-08-30T11:19:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The &lt;b&gt;Equal Rights Amendment&lt;/b&gt; (ERA) is a proposed, but as yet unratified, amendment to the [[United States Constitution]], that would guarantee equal rights under law for both sexes. It reads "Equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any state on account of sex." It was presented by the Congress to the states for ratification in [[1972]]. Initially the pace of ratifications was quick, but it then began to slow. Congress had set a seven year deadline for ratification, and by the end of the deadline in [[1979]] only 35 of the 38 required states had ratified. Congress then extended the ratification deadline until [[1982]], but no further states ratified.

The political climate changed in the early [[1980s]], and the [[Republican Party]] withdrew its earlier bipartisan support for the ERA.  Political opposition to the ERA was led by Phyllis Schlafly, a conservative Republican.

Supporters of the ERA have reintroduced it into Congress every year since 1982, but so far without success. Some opponents of the ERA argue that if reintroduced, it would need to regain the 35 ratifications all over again, plus the additional three still lacking. Supporters argue that the earlier 35 ratifications are still valid, and that only three more are necessary; some supporters go further and say that the remaining three ratifications could come after the deadline set by Congress, and then be recognized by Congress retroactively. They claim the passage of the [[United States Constitution/Amendment Twentyseven|27th Amendment]] over 200 years after it was first proposed supports this strategy, although unlike in the case of the ERA, the bill proposing the 27th Amendment did not set a deadline for ratification.

''See also:''  [[Legal aspects of transsexualism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>