<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171102100159|808348251" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="59635" pageid="59635" ns="0" title="Equal Rights Amendment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-08T12:33:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{US Constitution article series}}
The '''Equal Rights Amendment''' ('''ERA''') is a [[Article Five of the United States Constitution#Proposing amendments|proposed amendment]] to the [[United States Constitution]] designed to guarantee equal rights for all citizens regardless of sex; it seeks to end the legal distinctions between men and women in terms of [[divorce]], [[property]], [[Employment discrimination|employment]], and other matters.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SZK5BwAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PA425&amp;ots=yXHMyeKtF8&amp;dq=wladaver-morgan%20susan%20equal%20rights%20amendment&amp;pg=PA200#v=onepage&amp;q=wladaver-morgan%20susan%20equal%20rights%20amendment&amp;f=false|title=American Economic History: A Dictionary and Chronology: A Dictionary and Chronology|last=Olson|first=James S.|last2=Mendoza|first2=Abraham O.|date=2015-04-28|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=9781610696982|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ERA was originally written by [[Alice Paul]] and [[Crystal Eastman]]. The amendment was introduced in [[United States Congress|Congress]] for the first time in 1923 and has prompted conversations about the meaning of equality for women and men. In its early history, middle-class women were largely supportive, while those speaking for the working class were often opposed, arguing that employed women needed special protections regarding working conditions and employment hours. With the rise of the [[Women's Movement in the United States (1963-1982)|women's movement in the United States]] in the 1960s, the ERA garnered increasing support, and, after being reintroduced by Representative [[Martha Griffiths]] (D-MI), in 1971, it passed both houses of Congress in 1972 and was submitted to the state legislatures for ratification.

Congress had originally set a ratification deadline of March 22, 1979. Through 1977, the amendment received 35 of the necessary 38 state [[Article Five of the United States Constitution#Ratification of amendments|ratifications]]. With wide, bipartisan support (including that of both major political parties, both houses of Congress, and Presidents Ford and Carter)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Miller|first=Eric C.|date=2015-06-19|title=Phyllis Schlafly's "Positive" Freedom: Liberty, Liberation, and the Equal Rights Amendment|url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/584317|journal=Rhetoric &amp; Public Affairs|volume=18|issue=2|pages=277–300|issn=1534-5238}}&lt;/ref&gt; it seemed headed for ratification until [[Phyllis Schlafly]] mobilized conservative women in opposition, arguing that the ERA would disadvantage [[housewives]] and cause women to be drafted into the military.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/03/27/AR2007032702357_pf.html|title=  New Drive Afoot to Pass Equal Rights Amendment|website=www.washingtonpost.com|access-date=2017-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Four states rescinded their ratifications before the 1979 deadline; however, there is no precedent or mechanism within the US Constitution for rescinding, and, thus, it becomes a legal question. In 1978, a joint resolution of Congress extended the ratification deadline to June 30, 1982, but no further states ratified the amendment before that revised deadline.

On March 22, 2017, the 45th anniversary of Congress's submission of the amendment to the states, the [[Nevada Legislature]] was the first to ratify the ERA after the expiration of the original deadline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/03/21/520962541/nevada-on-cusp-of-ratifying-equal-rights-amendment-35-years-after-deadline|title=Nevada Ratifies The Equal Rights Amendment ... 35 Years After The Deadline|author1=Colin Dwyer|author2=Carrie Kaufman|date=March 21, 2017|publisher=[[NPR]]|accessdate=March 28, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Text ==
{{quote|'''Section 1.''' Equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of sex.

'''Section 2.''' The Congress shall have the power to enforce, by appropriate legislation, the provisions of this article.

'''Section 3.''' This amendment shall take effect two years after the date of ratification.&lt;ref&gt;86 Stat. [https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/STATUTE-86/pdf/STATUTE-86-Pg1523.pdf 1523]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/GPO-CONAN-1992/pdf/GPO-CONAN-1992-8.pdf|title=Proposed Amendments Not Ratified by States|accessdate=June 1, 2013|publisher=[[United States Government Printing Office]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Background==
[[File:Alice paul.jpg|thumb|[[Alice Paul]] toasting (with grape juice) the passage of the Nineteenth Amendment. August 26, 1920&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.alicepaul.org/who-was-alice-paul/|title=Who Was Alice Paul?|website=Alice Paul Institute|access-date=April 6, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
On the 75th anniversary of the [[Seneca Falls Convention]], July 1, 1923, feminist and advocate for women's rights Alice Paul announced that she planned on promoting and initiating an amendment to the United States Constitution that would give the same rights to men and women.&lt;ref&gt;Congressional Research Service. ''The Proposed Equal Rights Amendment: Contemporary Ratification Issues''
&lt;/ref&gt; She believed that the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Nineteenth Amendment]] would not be enough to ensure that men and women were treated equally regardless of sex. Paul wrote a draft and in honor of [[Lucretia Mott]], a female abolitionist who fought for women's rights and attended the First Women's Rights Convention, Paul named the amendment Mott's Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nps.gov/wori/learn/historyculture/lucretia-mott.htm.|title="Lucretia Mott" National Park Service|website=National Park Service|publisher=United States Government|access-date=March 21, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original amendment stated:

{{quote|Men and women shall have equal rights throughout the United States and every place subject to its jurisdiction. Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate legislation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Who was Alice Paul|url=http://www.alicepaul.org/who-was-alice-paul/|website=Alice Paul Institute|access-date=2016-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In 1943, Alice Paul further revised the amendment's wording; this text became Section 1 in the version passed by Congress in 1972.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://history.hanover.edu/courses/excerpts/336era.html|title=Equal Rights Amendments, 1923-1972|website=history.hanover.edu|access-date=2016-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

That wording was based on that of the [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fifteenth Amendment]] and [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Nineteenth Amendments]].

As a result, in the 1940s, ERA opponents proposed an alternative, which provided that “no distinctions on the basis of sex shall be made except such as are reasonably justified by differences in physical structure, biological differences, or social function.” It was quickly turned down by both pro and anti-ERA coalitions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ioM-8naFn60C&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s|title=Moving the Mountain: The Women's Movement in America Since 1960|last=Davis|first=Flora|date=1999-01-01|publisher=University of Illinois Press|isbn=9780252067822|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Feminists split===
Since the 1920s, the Equal Rights Amendment has caused a sharp debate among [[Feminism|feminists]] about the meaning of women's equality. It was "feminist against feminist", said historian [[Judith Sealander]].&lt;ref&gt;Judith Sealander, "Feminist Against Feminist: The First Phase of the Equal Rights Amendment Debate, 1923-1963", ''South Atlantic Quarterly'' (1982) 81#2 pp 147-161&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alice Paul]] and her [[National Woman's Party]] was the leading proponent, arguing that women should be on equal terms with men in all regards, even if that means sacrificing certain benefits given to women through protective legislation, such as shorter work hours and no night work or heavy lifting.&lt;ref&gt;Nancy Cott, "Feminist Politics in the 1920s: The National Woman's Party", ''Journal of American History'' (1984( 71#1 pp: 43-68. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/1899833 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; Opponents of the amendment, such as the [[Women's Joint Congressional Committee]], believed that these gender-based benefits protected women and that the loss of such protection would not be worth the supposed gain in equality. In general, middle-class elements supported the ERA, and working-class elements (and the labor movement) opposed it.&lt;ref&gt;Nancy Cott, "Historical Perspectives: The Equal Rights Amendment Conflict in the 1920s". in Marianne Hirsch and Evelyn Fox Keller eds., ''Conflicts in Feminism,'' (Routledge, 1990) ch 2.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1924, ''The Forum'' hosted a debate between [[Doris Stevens]] and [[Alice Hamilton]] concerning these two perspectives on the proposed amendment.&lt;ref&gt;Susan Ware, ed., "New Dilemmas for Modern Women", ''Modern American Women: A Documentary History'' (McGraw-Hill Higher Education, 1997)&lt;/ref&gt; Their debate reflected the wider tension in the developing feminist movement of the early 20th century between two approaches towards the equality of gender. One approach emphasized shared similarities between the sexes and demanded rights based on women's humanity. The other approach emphasized women's unique experiences and how they were different from men to obtain recognition for their specific needs.&lt;ref&gt;[[Nancy Cott]], ''The Grounding of Modern Feminism'' (Yale University Press, 1987)&lt;/ref&gt; The crusade against the ERA on behalf of working class women was led by [[Mary Anderson (labor leader)|Mary Anderson]] and the [[Women's Bureau]] beginning in 1923. These feminists argued that legislation including mandated minimum wages, safety regulations, restricted daily and weekly hours, lunch breaks, and maternity provisions would be more beneficial to the majority of women who were forced to work out of economic necessity, not personal fulfillment.&lt;ref&gt;Dorothy Sue Cobble, The Other Women's Movement: Workplace Justice and Social Rights in Modern America, (Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 2004), 51.&lt;/ref&gt; The debate over the ERA also drew from struggles between working class and professional women. Alice Hamilton said, in her speech “Protection for Women Workers,” that the ERA would strip working women of the small protections they had achieved, and leave them powerless to further improve their condition in the future, or attain necessary protections in the present.&lt;ref&gt;Genora Johnson Dollinger, “Women and Labor Militancy,” in Susan Ware, ed. Modern American Women: A Documentary History, (New York: McGraw-Hill, 1997), 125-126.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[National Woman's Party]] already had tested its approach in [[Wisconsin]], where it won passage of the Wisconsin Equal Rights Law in 1921.&lt;ref&gt;Genevieve G. McBride, {{"'}}Forward' Women: Winning the Wisconsin Campaign for the Country's First ERA, 1921" in Peter G. Watson Boone, ed., ''The Quest for Social Justice III: The Morris Fromkin Memorial Lectures, 1992–2002'' (Milwaukee: University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Keetley|editor1-first=Dawn|editor2-last=Pettegrew|editor2-first=John|title=Public Women, Public Words: A Documentary History of American Feminism, Volume II: 1900 to 1960|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=s3H087kqzlUC&amp;pg=PA284|year=2005|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|pages=284–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; It then took the ERA to Congress in the 1920s, where Senator [[Charles Curtis]], a future Vice President, and Representative [[Daniel Read Anthony, Jr.|Daniel R. Anthony, Jr.]]—[[Susan B. Anthony]]'s nephew, both Kansas Republicans, introduced it for the first time as Senate Joint Resolution No. 21 on December 10, 1923, and as House Joint Resolution No. 75 on December 13, 1923, respectively. Though the ERA was introduced in every congressional session between 1923 and 1970, it almost never reached the floor of either the Senate or the House for a vote—instead, it was usually blocked in committee; except in 1946, when it was defeated in the Senate by a vote of 38 to 35&amp;mdash;not receiving the required two-thirds vote.

===Hayden rider and protective labor legislation===
In 1950 and 1953, the ERA was passed by the Senate with a provision known as "the Hayden rider", introduced by [[Arizona]] Senator [[Carl Hayden]]. The Hayden rider added a sentence to the ERA to keep special protections for women: "The provisions of this article shall not be construed to impair any rights, benefits, or exemptions now or hereafter conferred by law upon persons of the female sex." By allowing women to keep their existing and future special protections, it was expected that the ERA would be more appealing to its opponents. Though opponents were marginally more in favor of the ERA with the Hayden rider, supporters of the original ERA believed it negated the amendment's original purpose -- causing the amendment not to be passed in the House.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content.cdlib.org/view?docId=kt6f59n89c&amp;brand=calisphere&amp;doc.view=entire_text|title=Conversations with Alice Paul: Woman Suffrage and the Equal Rights Amendment.|website=cdlib.org|publisher=Suffragists Oral History Project}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jofreeman.com/lawandpolicy/eraname.htm|title=What's in a Name? Does it matter how the Equal Rights Amendment is worded?|work=jofreeman.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Cynthia Ellen Harrison|title=On Account of Sex: The Politics of Women's Issues, 1945-1968|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AXlSB6-WpKUC&amp;pg=PA31|year=1989|publisher=University of California Press|pages=31–32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ERA supporters were hopeful that the second term of [[Dwight Eisenhower]] would advance their agenda. Eisenhower had publicly promised to "assure women everywhere in our land equality of rights," and in 1958, President Dwight Eisenhower asked a [[joint session of the United States Congress|joint session of Congress]] to pass the Equal Rights Amendment, the first president to show such a level of support for the amendment. However, the National Woman's Party found the amendment to be unacceptable and asked it to be withdrawn whenever the Hayden rider was added to the ERA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Cynthia Ellen Harrison|title=On Account of Sex: The Politics of Women's Issues, 1945-1968|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AXlSB6-WpKUC&amp;pg=PA31|year=1989|publisher=University of California Press|pages=31–32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Republican Party included support of the ERA in its platform beginning in [[1940 Republican National Convention|1940]], renewing the plank every four years until [[United States presidential election, 1980|1980]].&lt;ref name="'70s 245"&gt;{{cite book|title=How We Got Here: The '70s|last=Frum|first=David|authorlink=David Frum|year=2000|publisher=[[Basic Books]]|location=New York, New York|isbn=0-465-04195-7|pages=245–248}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ERA was strongly opposed by the [[American Federation of Labor]] and other labor unions, who feared the amendment would invalidate protective labor legislation for women. The Equal Rights Amendment was also opposed by [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] and most [[New Deal]]ers. They felt that ERA was designed for middle class women but that working class women needed government protection. They also feared that the ERA would undercut the male-dominated labor unions that were a core component of the [[New Deal coalition]]. Most northern Democrats, who aligned themselves with the anti-ERA labor unions, opposed the amendment.&lt;ref name="'70s 245" /&gt; The ERA was supported by southern Democrats and almost all Republicans.&lt;ref name="'70s 245"/&gt;

At the [[1944 Democratic National Convention]], the Democrats made the divisive step of including the ERA in their platform, but the Democratic Party did not become united in favor of the amendment until congressional passage in 1972.&lt;ref name="'70s 245"/&gt; The main support base for the ERA until the late 1960s was among middle class Republican women. The [[League of Women Voters]], formerly the [[National American Woman Suffrage Association]], opposed the Equal Rights Amendment until 1972, fearing the loss of protective labor legislation.

===1960s===
At the [[1960 Democratic National Convention|Democratic National Convention in 1960]], a proposal to endorse the ERA was rejected after it met explicit opposition from liberal groups including the [[American Civil Liberties Union]] (ACLU), the [[AFL–CIO]], labor unions such as the [[American Federation of Teachers]], [[Americans for Democratic Action]] (ADA), the [[American Nurses Association]], the Women's Division of the [[Methodist Church (USA)|Methodist Church]], and the National Councils of Jewish, Catholic, and Negro Women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jo Freeman|title=A Room at a Time: How Women Entered Party Politics|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LF8ov6Vc4YQC&amp;pg=PA209|year=2002|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=978-0-8476-9805-9|page=209}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The losing side then demanded that presidential candidate [[John F. Kennedy]] announce his support of the ERA; he did so in an October 21, 1960, letter to the chairman of the National Woman's Party.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=74146|author=Kennedy, John F|date=October 21, 1960|title=Letter to Mrs. Emma Guffey Miller, Chairman of the National Woman's Party|website=ucsb.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Kennedy was elected, he made [[Esther Peterson]] the highest-ranking woman in his administration as an Assistant Secretary of Labor. Peterson publicly opposed the Equal Rights Amendment based on her belief that it would weaken protective labor legislation.&lt;ref name="fofweb.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fofweb.com/History/MainPrintPage.asp?iPin=awhm0502&amp;DataType=Women&amp;WinType=Free|title=Peterson, Esther Eggertsen|work=Facts on File History Database|publisher=Infobase Learning}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peterson referred to the National Woman's Party members, most of them veteran suffragists and preferred the "specific bills for specific ills" approach to equal rights.&lt;ref name="fofweb.com"/&gt; Ultimately, Kennedy's ties to labor unions meant he and his administration did not support the ERA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Joseph M. Siracusa|title=Encyclopedia of the Kennedys: The People and Events That Shaped America|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PEojQDou7MIC&amp;pg=PA864|year=2012|publisher=ABC-CLIO|page=864}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a concession to feminists, Kennedy appointed a [[Blue-ribbon panel|blue-ribbon commission]] on women, the [[Presidential Commission on the Status of Women|President's Commission on the Status of Women]], to investigate the problem of sex discrimination in the United States. The commission was chaired by Eleanor Roosevelt who opposed the ERA but no longer spoke against it. In the early 1960s, Roosevelt announced that, due to unionization, she believed the ERA was no longer a threat to women as it once may have been and told supporters that they could have the amendment if they wanted it. However, she never endorsed the ERA. The commission she chaired reported (after her death) that no ERA was needed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Maurine Hoffman Beasley|title=Eleanor Roosevelt and the Media: A Public Quest for Self-fulfillment|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=55XG0oS3XyYC&amp;pg=PA184|year=1987|publisher=University of Illinois Press|page=184}}&lt;/ref&gt; The commission helped win passage of the [[Equal Pay Act of 1963]] which banned sex discrimination in wages in a number of professions (it would later be amended in the early 1970s to include the professions it initially excluded) and secured an [[executive order]] from Kennedy eliminating sex discrimination in the [[civil service]]. The commission, made largely of anti-ERA feminists with ties to labor, proposed remedies to the widespread sex discrimination it unearthed and in its 1963 final report held that on the issue of equality "a constitutional amendment need not now be sought".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Keetley|editor1-first=Dawn|editor2-last=Pettegrew|editor2-first=John|title=Public Women, Public Words: A Documentary History of American Feminism, Volume III: 1960 to the Present|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EDd2aNCoGlYC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|year=2005|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|page=251}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The commission established state and local commissions on the status of women and arranged for follow-up conferences in the years to come. The following year, the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] banned workplace discrimination not only on the basis of race, religion, and national origin, but also on the basis of sex, thanks to the lobbying of [[Alice Paul]] and [[Coretta Scott King]] and the skillful politicking of Representative [[Martha Griffiths]] of [[Michigan]].

A new women's movement gained ground in the later 1960s as a result of a variety of factors: [[Betty Friedan]]'s bestseller ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]''; the network of women's rights commissions formed by Kennedy's national commission; the frustration over women's social and economic status; and anger over the lack of government and [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] enforcement of the Equal Pay Act and Title VII of the Civil Rights Act. In June 1966, at the Third National Conference on the Status of Women in [[Washington, D.C.]], Betty Friedan and a group of activists frustrated with the lack of government action in enforcing Title VII of the Civil Rights Act formed the [[National Organization for Women]] to act as an "[[National Association for the Advancement of Colored People|NAACP]] for women", demanding full equality for American women and men. In 1967, at the urging of Alice Paul, NOW endorsed the Equal Rights Amendment. The decision caused some union Democrats and social conservatives to leave the organization and form the [[Women's Equity Action League]] (within a few years WEAL also endorsed the ERA), but the move to support the amendment benefited NOW, bolstering its membership. By the late 1960s NOW had made significant political and legislative victories and was gaining enough power to become a major lobbying force. In 1969, newly elected Representative [[Shirley Chisholm]] of [[New York (state)|New York]] gave her famous speech "Equal Rights for Women" on the floor of the U.S. House of Representatives.

==Congressional passage==
[[File:Martha Griffiths.jpg|thumb|upright|U.S. Representative [[Martha Griffiths]] championed the ERA]]
In February 1970, NOW picketed the United States Senate, a subcommittee of which was holding hearings on a constitutional amendment to lower the voting age to eighteen. NOW disrupted the hearings and demanded a hearing on the Equal Rights Amendment and won a meeting with Senators to discuss the ERA. That August, over 20,000 American women held a nationwide [[Women's Strike for Equality]] protest to demand full social, economic, and political equality.&lt;ref name=wommarch&gt;[http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,902696,00.html/ Nation, Women on] ''Time'' (New York), September 7, 1970 {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150406112028/http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,902696,00.html/|date=April 6, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Said Friedan of the strike, "All kinds of women's groups all over the country will be using this week on August 26 particularly, to point out those areas in women's life which are still not addressed. For example, a question of equality before the law; we are interested in the Equal Rights Amendment." Despite being centered in New York City—which was regarded as one of the biggest strongholds for NOW and other groups sympathetic to the [[women's liberation movement]] such as [[Redstockings]]&lt;ref name=femis209&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Rk966-N_rh0C&amp;pg=PA209&amp;lpg=PA209&amp;dq=women's+strike+for+equality+nation+second+wave+feminism&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=uHtNGnwy0U&amp;sig=0-Wy0f2zpE9LZtR9lsDA1WGYHqQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=GYsgU4GEL5SfqAGN2oDABg&amp;ved=0CHAQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=women's%20strike%20for%20equality%20nation%20second%20wave%20feminism&amp;f=false|title=Becoming The Feminist Subject. Conscious-Raising Groups in Second Wave Feminism|author=Voichita Nechescu|date=June 5, 2006|page=209|publisher=Proquest|isbn=0542771683|accessdate=April 1, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;—and having a small number of participants in contrast to the large-scale anti-war and civil rights protests that had occurred in the recent time prior to the event,&lt;ref name=wommarch /&gt; the strike was credited as one of the biggest turning points in the rise of [[second-wave feminism]].&lt;ref name=femis209 /&gt;

In Washington, D.C., protesters presented a sympathetic Senate leadership with a petition for the Equal Rights Amendment at the [[United States Capitol|U.S. Capitol]]. Influential news sources such as ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' also supported the cause of the protestors.&lt;ref name=wommarch /&gt; Soon after the strike took place, activists distributed literature across the country as well.&lt;ref name=femis209 /&gt; In 1970, congressional hearings began on the ERA.

On August 10, 1970, Michigan Democrat [[Martha Griffiths]] successfully brought [[Alice Paul#Equal Rights Amendment|Alice Paul's ERA]] to the House Floor, after fifteen years of bringing the bill to the House Judiciary Committee without success. The bill passed in the House and continued on to the Senate, which voted for the ERA with an added clause that women would be exempt from the military. The session of Congress ended before the bill could go any further.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://history.house.gov/People/Listing/G/GRIFFITHS,-Martha-Wright-(G000471)/|title=GRIFFITHS, Martha Wright {{!}} US House of Representatives: History, Art &amp; Archives|website=history.house.gov|language=en|access-date=2017-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Griffiths reintroduced the ERA, and achieved success on Capitol Hill with her House Joint Resolution No. 208, which was adopted by the House on October 12, 1971, with a vote of 354 yeas (For), 24 nays (Against) and 51 not voting.&lt;ref&gt;117 ''Congressional Record'' 35815&lt;/ref&gt; Griffiths's joint resolution was then adopted by the Senate on March 22, 1972, with a vote of 84 yeas, 8 nays and 7 not voting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://archive.org/stream/congressionalrec118funit#page/n93/mode/2up|title=Congressional record|work=archive.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Senate version, drafted by Senator [[Birch Bayh]] of Indiana,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Cruikshank|first=Kate|title=The Art of Leadership: A Companion to an Exhibition from the Senatorial Papers of Birch Bayh, United States Senator from Indiana, 1963–1980|url=http://www.libraries.iub.edu/index.php?pageId=8621|publisher=Indiana University|accessdate=10 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; passed after the defeat of an amendment proposed by Senator [[Sam Ervin]] of North Carolina that would have exempted women from the [[Conscription|draft]].&lt;ref name="'70s 245" /&gt; President [[Richard Nixon]] immediately endorsed the ERA's approval upon its passage by the [[92nd United States Congress|92nd Congress]].&lt;ref name="'70s 245" /&gt;

Contemporary movement on the ERA began in 2013, when Senators [[Ben Cardin]] of Maryland and [[Mark Kirk]] of Illinois, along with Congresswoman [[Jackie Speier]] of California, introduced identical bills in both the US Senate and House chambers to remove the ratification deadline altogether. Currently, the legislation continues to gain co-sponsors in both chambers in anticipation of completion of the amendment.

==Actions in the state legislatures==

===Ratifications===
In 1972, the ERA was sent to the states, with a seven-year deadline to get 38 states to ratify the amendment. Most states were eager to pass the legislation; in 1972, 22 states ratified the amendment and eight more joined in 1973. Between 1974 and 1977, only five states approved the ERA, and advocates became worried about the approaching March 22, 1979 deadline.&lt;ref name="ERA: History"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/history.htm|title=ERA: History|website=www.equalrightsamendment.org|access-date=2017-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the legislatures of four states which had ratified the ERA then adopted legislation purporting to rescind those ratifications. If, indeed, a state legislature has power to rescind, then the ERA actually had ratifications by only 31 states&amp;mdash;not 35&amp;mdash;when March 22, 1979 arrived.

The ERA has been ratified by the following states:&lt;ref&gt;Gladstone, Leslie W. ''CRS Report 85-154 GOV: The Proposed Equal Rights Amendment''. p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;
# Hawaii (March 22, 1972)
# New Hampshire (March 23, 1972)
# Delaware (March 23, 1972)
# Iowa (March 24, 1972)
# Idaho (March 24, 1972)
# Kansas (March 28, 1972)
# Nebraska (March 29, 1972)
# Texas (March 30, 1972)
# Tennessee (April 4, 1972)
# Alaska (April 5, 1972)
# Rhode Island (April 14, 1972)
# New Jersey (April 17, 1972)
# Colorado (April 21, 1972)
# West Virginia (April 22, 1972)
# Wisconsin (April 26, 1972)
# New York (May 18, 1972)
# Michigan (May 22, 1972)
# Maryland (May 26, 1972)
# Massachusetts (June 21, 1972)
# Kentucky (June 26, 1972)
# Pennsylvania (September 27, 1972)
# California (November 13, 1972)
# Wyoming (January 26, 1973)
# South Dakota (February 5, 1973)
# Oregon (February 8, 1973)&lt;ref&gt;Tara Watson and Melody Rose, "She Flies With Her Own Wings: Women in the 1973 Oregon Legislative Session", ''Oregon Historical Quarterly'' (2010) 111#1 pp 38-63.&lt;/ref&gt;
# Minnesota (February 8, 1973)
# New Mexico (February 28, 1973)
# Vermont (March 1, 1973)
# Connecticut (March 15, 1973)
# Washington (March 22, 1973)
# Maine (January 18, 1974)
# Montana (January 25, 1974)
# Ohio (February 7, 1974)
# North Dakota (March 19, 1975)
# Indiana (January 18, 1977)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/1977/01/19/indiana-ratifies-the-era-with-rosalynn-carters-aid/59d7c58b-9a19-41da-a528-f66f075933be/|title=Indiana Ratifies the ERA - With Rosalynn Carter's Aid|last=MacPherson|first=Myra|date=1977-01-19|work=The Washington Post|access-date=2017-03-22|last2=MacPherson|first2=Myra|language=en-US|issn=0190-8286}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Nevada (March 22, 2017), despite the ratification deadline expiring decades earlier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.lasvegasnow.com/news/nevada-ratifies-equal-rights-amendment-decades-past-deadline/678419418|title=Nevada ratifies Equal Rights Amendment decades past deadline|date=March 22, 2017|publisher=Las Vegas Now|accessdate=March 22, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ratifications rescinded===
Legislators in the following states voted to rescind their earlier ratification of the ERA:&lt;ref&gt;Hatch, Orrin G. (1983). "The Equal Rights Amendment: Myths and Realities".&lt;/ref&gt;
# Nebraska (March 15, 1973 – Legislative Resolution No. 9)
# Tennessee (April 23, 1974 – House Joint Resolution No. 371 and Senate Joint Resolution No. 29)
# Idaho (February 8, 1977 – Senate Joint Resolution No. 133 and House Concurrent Resolution No. 10)
# Kentucky (March 17, 1978 – House (Joint) Resolution No. 2 and House (Joint) Resolution No. 20)&lt;br&gt;The [[Lieutenant Governor of Kentucky]], [[Thelma Stovall]], who was acting as governor in the governor's absence, [[Veto#United States|vetoed]] the rescinding resolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1817&amp;dat=19780321&amp;id=FgkdAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=7J4EAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2808,5122388|title=ERA Supporter Vetoes Resolution|date=21 March 1978|via=Google News|work=The Tuscaloosa News|access-date=2016-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Constitution is silent regarding whether the governor of a state has any authority regarding whether that state ratifies an amendment to the Constitution. The Constitution is likewise silent regarding a state's authority to rescind its ratification of a proposed, but not yet adopted, constitutional amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://law.justia.com/constitution/us/article-5/02-proposing-a-constitutional-amendment.html|title=Authentication and Proclamation: Proposing a Constitutional Amendment|publisher=Justia|accessdate=July 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Refusal to recognize deadline extension to June 30, 1982===
On March 1, 1979, the [[South Dakota Legislature]] approved Senate Joint Resolution No. 2 which, while not going quite so far as to rescind South Dakota's 1973 ratification of ERA, stipulated that the ERA's opportunity for ratification—by ''any'' state of the Union—would expire on March 22, 1979. Furthermore, Senate Joint Resolution No. 2 made clear that South Dakota's own ratification of the ERA would no longer be valid after March 22, 1979, and that any ratification of the ERA after that date ''in any other state'' would be considered by South Dakota to be null and void.

===Non-ratifying states with one-house approval===
At various times, in 8 of the 14 non-ratifying states, one house of the legislature approved the ERA. It failed in those states because both houses of a state's legislature must approve during the same session for that state to ratify.
# Florida – whose House of Representatives voted to ratify the ERA on March 24, 1972, with a tally of 91 to 4; a second time on April 10, 1975, with a tally of 62 to 58; a third time on May 17, 1979, with a tally of 66 to 53; and a fourth time on June 21, 1982, with a tally of 60 to 58.&lt;ref&gt;Joan S. Carver, "The Equal Rights Amendment and the Florida Legislature", ''Florida Historical Quarterly'' (1982) 60#4 pp 455-481. 
&lt;/ref&gt;
# Illinois – whose Senate voted to ratify the ERA in May 1972 with a tally of 30 to 21, and again on May 22, 2014 (Senate Joint Resolution Constitutional Amendment No. 75)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ilga.gov/legislation/BillStatus.asp?DocTypeID=SJRCA&amp;DocNum=75&amp;GAID=12&amp;SessionID=85&amp;LegID=82279|title=Illinois General Assembly - Bill Status for SJRCA0075|website=www.ilga.gov|access-date=2016-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a tally of 39 to 11;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ilga.gov/legislation/votehistory/98/senate/09800SC0075_05222014_049000D.pdf|title=State of Illinois General Assembly Vote on Senate Joint Resolution Constitutional Amendment No. 75|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160811025826/http://www.ilga.gov/legislation/votehistory/98/senate/09800SC0075_05222014_049000D.pdf|archivedate=August 11, 2016|deadurl=yes|accessdate=May 25, 2017|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and whose House of Representatives voted to ratify the ERA on May 1, 1975 with a tally of 113 to 62, and again on May 21, 2003 with a tally of 76 to 41 (House Joint Resolution Constitutional Amendment No. 1). At various times, votes were conducted in both houses of the Illinois General Assembly on the question of ratifying the ERA and while most members voted ''in favor of'' ratification, the result was always less than the three-fifths supermajority vote in each house of the Illinois General Assembly for ratification as required by the internal parliamentary rules of both the Illinois Senate and the Illinois House of Representatives.  A provision of the Illinois State Constitution, which had required a supermajority of three-fifths in both legislative chambers, was found to be unconstitutional by the United States District Court for the Northern District of Illinois in the 1975 case of ''Dyer v. Blair''.&lt;ref&gt;Nancy Douglas Joyner, "Coalition politics: A case study of an organization's approach to a single issue". ''Women &amp; Politics'' (1982) 2#1-2 pp: 57-70. [http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/1554477X.1982.9970333 Abstract]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.i2i.org/files/2015/10/1975-Dyer-v-Blair-ND-Ill.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; Since then, the ERA has been voted on multiple times, but has only ever passed in one of the chambers. The most recent vote in favor of the ERA was in the state senate in May 2014 with a tally of 39 to 11, and 6 voting present.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ilga.gov/legislation/votehistory/98/senate/09800SC0075_05222014_049000D.pdf|title=State of Illinois General Assembly Vote on Senate Joint Resolution Constitutional Amendment No. 75|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160811025826/http://www.ilga.gov/legislation/votehistory/98/senate/09800SC0075_05222014_049000D.pdf|archivedate=August 11, 2016|deadurl=yes|accessdate=May 25, 2017|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Louisiana – whose Senate voted to ratify the ERA on June 7, 1972, with a tally of 25 to 13.
# Missouri – whose House of Representatives voted to ratify the ERA on February 7, 1975, with a tally of 82 to 75.&lt;ref&gt;Harriett Woods, ''Stepping Up to Power: The Political Journey of American Women'' (2000); memoir of ERA leader in Missouri legislature&lt;/ref&gt;
# North Carolina – whose House of Representatives voted to ratify the ERA on February 9, 1977, with a tally of 61 to 55.&lt;ref&gt;Donald G. Mathews and Jane S. De Hart, ''Sex, Gender, and the Politics of ERA: A State and the Nation'' (1992) focus on debate in North Carolina&lt;/ref&gt;
# Oklahoma – whose Senate voted to ratify the ERA on March 23, 1972, by a [[voice vote]].&lt;ref&gt;Wilbur J. Scott, "The equal rights amendment as status politics". ''Social Forces'' (1985) 64#2 pp: 499-506.&lt;/ref&gt;
# South Carolina – whose House of Representatives voted to ratify the ERA on March 22, 1972, with a tally of 83 to zero.
# Virginia – whose Senate voted to ratify the ERA on February 7, 2011, with a tally of 24 to 16 (Senate Joint Resolution No. 357); a second time on February 14, 2012, with a tally of 24 to 15 (Senate Joint Resolution No. 130); a third time on February 5, 2014, with a tally of 25 to 8 (Senate Joint Resolution No. 78); a fourth time on February 5, 2015, with a tally of 20 to 19 (Senate Joint Resolution No. 216);&lt;ref&gt;Patricia W. Goodman, "The ERA in Virginia: A Power Playground", ''Southern Exposure'' (1978) 6#3 pp 59-62.&lt;/ref&gt; and a fifth time on January 26, 2016, with a tally of 21 to 19 (Senate Joint Resolution No. 1).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?161+vot+SP0086|title=Archived copy|accessdate=2016-01-27|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160203010709/https://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?161+vot+SP0086|archivedate=2016-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the past twenty years, ratification resolutions have also been defeated in Arizona, Arkansas,&lt;ref&gt;Janine A. Parry, "What Women Wanted": Arkansas Women's Commissions and the ERA", ''Arkansas Historical Quarterly'' (2000) 59#3 pp: 265-298. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/40027988?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; and Mississippi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Martha H. Swain|title=Mississippi Women: Their Histories, Their Lives|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uH1SPgyl5e0C&amp;pg=PA289|year=2010|publisher=U of Georgia Press|page=289|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Will, George F.|url=http://www.nrlc.org/archive/Federal/ERA/GeorgeWillERALivingDead.pdf|format=PDF|title=Night of the Living Dead Amendment|publisher=Washington Post via National Right to Life Committee|date=February 13, 1994|accessdate=2014-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Francis, Roberta W.|title=Frequently Asked Questions|url=http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/faq.htm|publisher=Alice Paul Institute|accessdate=2009-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Congressional extension of ratification deadline==
In 1978—as the 1979 deadline approached—the [[95th United States Congress|95th Congress]] adopted House Joint Resolution No. 638 (H. J. Res. 638), by Representative [[Elizabeth Holtzman]] of [[New York (state)|New York]], which purported to extend the ERA's ratification deadline to June 30, 1982.&lt;ref&gt;Volume 92, ''United States Statutes At Large,'' page 3799&lt;/ref&gt; H. J. Res. 638 received less than two-thirds of the vote (a [[majority|simple majority]], not a [[supermajority]]) in both the House of Representatives and the Senate; for that reason, ERA supporters deemed it necessary that H. J. Res. 638 be transmitted to then President [[Jimmy Carter]] for signature as a safety precaution. Carter signed the joint resolution, though he questioned&amp;mdash;on procedural grounds&amp;mdash;the propriety of his doing so.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.experiencefestival.com/a/Equal_Rights_Amendment_-_Extension_of_ratification_deadline/id/1367020 Equal Rights Amendment - Extension of ratification deadline] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131019174107/http://www.experiencefestival.com/a/Equal_Rights_Amendment_-_Extension_of_ratification_deadline/id/1367020|date=October 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this disputed extension, no additional states ratified or [[Article Five of the United States Constitution#Rescinding a ratification|rescinded]].
[[File:Photograph of Jimmy Carter Signing Extension of Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) Ratification, 10-20-1978.jpg|thumb|upright=1.25|left|President Carter signing the extension]]
No additional states ratified the ERA during that extra period of slightly more than three years. On June 18, 1980, a resolution in the Illinois House of Representatives resulted in a vote of 102-71 in favor, but Illinois required a three-fifths majority on constitutional amendments and so the measure failed by five votes. In 1982, seven female ERA supporters went on a fast and seventeen chained themselves to the door of the Illinois senate chamber; none of this resulted in any state ratifications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=O'Dea, Suzanne|title=From Suffrage to the Senate: An Encyclopedia of American Women in Politics, Volume 1|date=1999|publisher=ABC-CLIO|page=244|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Si6ZVqdOqIgC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hungryheart"&gt;{{cite book|author=Nicholson, Zoe Ann|title=The Hungry Heart: A Woman's Fast for Justice|date=2004|publisher=Lune Soleil Press|ISBN=0972392831|url=http://www.lunesoleilpress.com/the-hungry-heart-a-womans-fast-for-justice.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="nytimes-era"&gt;{{cite news|last=Sheppard|first=Nathaniel|title=Women say they'll end fast but not rights fight|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1982/06/24/us/women-say-they-ll-end-fast-but-not-rights-fight.html|date=June 24, 1982|accessdate=September 18, 2016|publisher=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The closest the ERA came to gaining an additional ratification between the original deadline of March 22, 1979 and the revised June 30, 1982, expiration date was when it was approved by the [[Florida House of Representatives]] on June 21, 1982. In the final week before the deadline, that ratifying resolution was defeated in the [[Florida Senate]] by a vote of 16 yeas and 22 nays. Even if Florida had ratified the ERA, the proposed amendment would still have been two states short of the required 38 (seven states short if the rescissions were valid).

According to research by Professor Jules B. Gerard, professor of law at [[Washington University in St. Louis]], of the 35 legislatures that passed ratification resolutions, 24 explicitly referred to the 1979 deadline.&lt;ref&gt;Letter to House Judiciary Committee, June 14, 1978&lt;/ref&gt;

== In the courts ==
On December 23, 1981, in ''Idaho v. Freeman'', the [[United States District Court for the District of Idaho]] ruled that the rescissions—all of which occurred before the original 1979 ratification deadline—were valid and that the ERA's deadline extension was [[Constitutionality|unconstitutional]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court|litigants=State of Idaho v. Freeman|vol=529|reporter=F. Supp.|opinion=1107|court=D. Idaho|date=1982|url=http://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp/529/1107/2355452/|accessdate=2017-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[National Organization for Women]] appealed both rulings. On October 4, 1982, in ''NOW v. Idaho'', 459 U.S. 809 (1982), the U.S. Supreme Court vacated the ruling in ''Idaho v. Freeman'' and declared the entire matter [[Mootness|moot]] on the grounds that the ERA was dead for the reason given by the Administrator of General Services that the ERA had not received the required number of ratifications (38), so that "the Amendment has failed of adoption no matter what the resolution of the legal issues presented here."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eagleforum.org/era/now-v-idaho-memo.html Memorandum of Gerald P. Carmen, Administrator of General Services], July 1982.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eagleforum.org/era/now-v-idaho.html|title=Now v. Idaho|work=eagleforum.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Support for the ERA ==
Supporters of the ERA point to the lack of a specific guarantee in the Constitution for equal rights protections on the basis of sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/why.htm|title=ERA: Why|website=www.equalrightsamendment.org|access-date=2017-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1973, future Supreme Court Justice [[Ruth Bader Ginsburg]] summarized a supporting argument for the ERA in the [[American Bar Association Journal]]:&lt;blockquote&gt;The equal rights amendment, in sum, would dedicate the nation to a new view of the rights and responsibilities of men and women. It firmly rejects sharp legislative lines between the sexes as constitutionally tolerable. Instead, it looks toward a legal system in which each person will be judged on the basis of individual merit and not on the basis of an unalterable trait of birth that bears no necessary relationship to need or ability.&lt;ref&gt;Ginsburg, Ruth Bader. “The Need for the Equal Rights Amendment.” American Bar Association Journal, vol. 59, no. 9, 1973, pp. 1013–1019. JSTOR, www.jstor.org/stable/25726416.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In the early 1940s both the Democratic and Republican parties added support for the ERA to their platforms.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/history.htm|title=ERA: History|website=www.equalrightsamendment.org|access-date=2017-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[National Organization for Women]] (NOW) and ERAmerica, a coalition of almost 80 organizations, led the pro-ERA efforts. Between 1972 and 1982, ERA supporters held rallies, petitioned, picketed, went on hunger strikes, and performed acts of civil disobedience.&lt;ref name="ERA: History"/&gt; On July 9, 1978, NOW and other organizations hosted a national march in Washington D.C., which garnered over 100,000 supporters, and was followed by a Lobby Day on July 10.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://feminist.org/blog/index.php/2014/07/09/july-9-1978-feminists-make-history-with-biggest-ever-march-for-the-equal-rights-amendment/|title=July 9, 1978: Feminists Make History With Biggest-Ever March for the Equal Rights Amendment {{!}} Feminist Majority Foundation Blog|website=feminist.org|access-date=2017-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 6, 1982, NOW sponsored marches in states that had not passed the ERA including Florida, Illinois, North Carolina, and Oklahoma.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1982/06/07/us/thousands-march-for-equal-rights.html|title=THOUSANDS MARCH FOR EQUAL RIGHTS|last=Times|first=Winston Williams, Special To The New York|date=1982-06-07|work=The New York Times|access-date=2017-04-13|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; Key feminists of the time, such as [[Gloria Steinem]], spoke out in favor of the ERA, arguing that ERA opposition was based on gender myths that overemphasized difference and ignored evidence of unequal treatment between men and women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://historymatters.gmu.edu/d/7025/|title="All Our Problems Stem from the Same Sex Based Myths": Gloria Steinem Delineates American Gender Myths during ERA Hearings|website=historymatters.gmu.edu|access-date=2017-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Black Women and the ERA ===
Many black women supported the ERA since they felt impacted by both race and sex discrimination.&lt;ref name="SEDWICK 24–29"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=SEDWICK|first=CATHY|last2=WILLIAMS|first2=REBA|date=1976-01-01|title=BLACK WOMEN AND THE EQUAL RIGHTS AMENDMENT|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/41065957|journal=The Black Scholar|volume=7|issue=10|pages=24–29}}&lt;/ref&gt; One prominent black female supporter was black Congresswoman [[Shirley Chisholm]]. On August 10, 1970, she gave a speech on the ERA called “For the Equal Rights Amendment” in Washington D.C. In her speech, she talked about how widespread sex discrimination had become and how the ERA would address that. She also said that laws to protect women in the workforce from unsafe working conditions would also be needed by men, and thus the ERA would help all people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://archive.vod.umd.edu/civil/chisholm1970int.htm|title=Shirley Anita St. Hill Chisholm, "For the Equal Rights Amendment" (10 August 1970)|website=archive.vod.umd.edu|access-date=2017-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other black women at the time supported the ERA for similar reasons. By 1976, 60% of black women and 63% of black men were in favor of the ERA, and the legislation was supported by black organizations such as the [[National Association for the Advancement of Colored People|NAACP]], [[National Council of Negro Women]], [[Coalition of Black Trade Unionists]], National Association of Negro Business, and the [[National Black Feminist Organization]].&lt;ref name="SEDWICK 24–29"/&gt;

==Opposition to the ERA==
[[File:Anti-ERA women dnd0215.jpg|thumb|Anti-ERA women watching a committee meeting of the Florida Senate in 1979, where consideration of the ERA was postponed, thus effectively killing the resolution for the 1979 session]]
Opponents of the ERA focused on traditional gender roles, such as how men do the fighting in wartime. They argued that the amendment would eliminate the men-only draft requirement and guarantee the possibility that women would be subject to [[Conscription in the United States|conscription]] and be required to have military combat roles in future wars if it were passed. Defense of traditional [[gender role]]s proved to be a useful tactic. In Illinois, supporters of [[Phyllis Schlafly]], a [[Conservatism in the United States|conservative]] Republican activist from Illinois, used traditional symbols of the American [[housewife]]. They took homemade bread, jams, and apple pies to the state legislators, with the slogans, "Preserve us from a congressional jam; Vote against the ERA sham" and "I am for Mom and apple pie."&lt;ref name=Rosenberg225&gt;{{cite book|author=Rosenberg, Rosalind|title=Divided Lives: American Women in the Twentieth Century|date=2008|publisher=Hill &amp; Wang|page=225|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=h-GMcnUaLhEC&amp;pg=PA225}}&lt;/ref&gt; They appealed to married women by stressing that the amendment would repeal protective laws such as alimony and eliminate the tendency for mothers to obtain custody over their children in divorce cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Rhode, Deborah L.|title=Justice and Gender: Sex Discrimination and the Law|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=S1qosJPdqPkC&amp;pg=PA66|date=2009|publisher=Harvard University Press|pages=66–67}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was suggested that single-sex bathrooms would be eliminated and same-sex couples would be able to get married if the amendment were passed.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost.com"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/03/27/AR2007032702357_pf.html|title=New Drive Afoot to Pass Equal Rights Amendment|website=www.washingtonpost.com|access-date=2017-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traditional women started to oppose the ERA.&lt;ref name=kllap&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ushistory.org/us/57c.asp|title=The Equal Rights Amendment|website=ushistory.org|publisher=Independence Hall Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; Schlafly said the ERA was designed for the benefit of young career women and warned that if men and women had to be treated identically it would threaten the security of middle-aged housewives with no job skills. They could no longer count on alimony or Social Security.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost.com"/&gt;  Opponents also argued that men and women were already equal enough with the passage of the [[Equal Pay Act of 1963]] and the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.digitalhistory.uh.edu/disp_textbook.cfm?smtid=2&amp;psid=3345|title=Digital History|website=www.digitalhistory.uh.edu|access-date=2017-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that women's colleges would have to admit men. Her argument that protective laws would be lost resonated with working-class women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Rosenberg, Rosalind |title=Divided Lives: American Women in the Twentieth Century|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=h-GMcnUaLhEC&amp;pg=PA225|date=2008|pages=225–26|publisher=Hill &amp; Wang}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Phyllis Schlafly by Gage Skidmore.jpg|upright=0.85|thumb|left|[[Phyllis Schlafly]], a conservative activist, organized opposition to the ERA and argued that it "would lead to women being drafted by the military and to [[unisex public toilet|public unisex bathrooms]]"&lt;ref name=eilperin&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/03/27/AR2007032702357_pf.html|work=The Washington Post|title=New Drive Afoot to Pass Equal Rights Amendment|first=Juliet|last=Eilperin|accessdate=May 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
At the [[1980 Republican National Convention]], the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]] platform was amended to end its support for the ERA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Perlez|first=Jane|title=Plan to omit rights amendment from platform brings objections|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1984/05/17/us/plan-to-omit-rights-amendment-from-platform-brings-objections.html|work=New York Times|accessdate=July 24, 2013|date=May 17, 1984}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most prominent opponent of the ERA was Schlafly. Leading the Stop ERA campaign, Schlafly defended traditional gender roles and would often bait feminists by opening her speeches with lines like, "I'd like to thank my husband for letting me be here tonight—I always like to say that, because it makes the libs so mad."&lt;ref&gt;Critchlow, p. 247&lt;/ref&gt; When Schlafly began her campaign in 1972, public polls showed support for the amendment was widely popular and thirty states had ratified the amendment by 1973. After 1973, the number of ratifying states slowed to a trickle. Support in the states that had not ratified fell below 50%.&lt;ref&gt;Jane J. Mansbridge, ''Why we lost the ERA'' (University of Chicago Press, 1986) p 214.&lt;/ref&gt; Critchlow and Stachecki argue that public opinion in key states shifted against the ERA as opponents, operating on the local and state levels, won over the public. The state legislators in battleground states followed public opinion in rejecting the ERA.

Experts agree that Phyllis Schlafly was a key player in the defeat. Political scientist [[Jane Mansbridge]] in her history of the ERA argues that the draft issue was the single most powerful argument used by Schlafly and the other opponents to defeat ERA.&lt;ref&gt;Jane  Mansbridge, "Who's in Charge Here? Decision by Accretion and Gatekeeping in the Struggle for the ERA", ''Politics &amp; Society'' (1984) 13#4 pp 343-382.&lt;/ref&gt; She concludes, "Many people who followed the struggle over the ERA believed—rightly in my view—that the Amendment would have been ratified by 1975 or 1976 had it not been for Phyllis Schlafly's early and effective effort to organize potential opponents."&lt;ref&gt;Mansbridge, ''Why we lost the ERA'' (1986) p 110.&lt;/ref&gt; Legal scholar [[Joan C. Williams]] argues, "ERA was defeated when Schlafly turned it into a war among women over gender roles."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Williams|first=Joan|title=Unbending Gender: Why Family and Work Conflict and What To Do About It|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SxtNubyWAEMC&amp;pg=PA147|year=1999|publisher=Oxford UP|page=147}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historian Judith Glazer-Raymo argues:
&lt;blockquote&gt;As moderates, we thought we represented the forces of reason and goodwill but failed to take seriously the power of the family values argument and the single-mindedness of Schlafly and her followers. The ERA's defeat seriously damaged the women's movement, destroying its momentum and its potential to foment social change....Eventually, this resulted in feminist dissatisfaction with the Republican Party, giving the Democrats a new source of strength that when combined with overwhelming minority support, helped elect Bill Clinton to the presidency in 1992 and again in 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Glazer-Raymo|first=Judith|title=Shattering the Myths: Women in Academe|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pTWzBcW07RwC&amp;pg=PA19|year=2001|publisher=Johns Hopkins UP|page=19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Many ERA supporters blamed their defeat on [[Advocacy group|special interest]] forces, especially the insurance industry and conservative organizations, suggesting they funded an opposition that subverted the democratic process and the will of the pro-ERA majority.&lt;ref&gt;Critchlow and Stachecki (2008). ''The Equal Rights Amendment Reconsidered''. pp. 157-8&lt;/ref&gt; They argued that while the public face of the anti-ERA movement was Phyllis Schlafly and her STOP ERA organization, there were other important groups in the opposition as well, such as the powerful National Council of Catholic Women, [[Social feminism|labor feminists]], and (until 1973) the AFL–CIO. Opposition to the amendment was particularly high among religious conservatives, who argued that the amendment would guarantee universal abortion rights and the right for homosexual couples to marry.&lt;ref name="Francis ERA History"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/history.htm|author=Francis, Roberta W.|title=The History Behind the Equal Rights Amendment|website=equalrightsamendment.org|publisher=Alice Paul Institute|accessdate=2014-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;David W. Brady and Kent L. Tedin, "Ladies in Pink: Religion and Political Ideology in the Anti-ERA Movement", ''Social Science Quarterly'' (1976) 56#4 pp 564-75&lt;/ref&gt;  Critchlow and Stachecki say the anti-ERA movement was based on strong support among Southern whites, Evangelical Christians, Mormons, Orthodox Jews, and Roman Catholics, including both men and women.&lt;ref&gt;Critchlow and Stachecki (2008). ''The Equal Rights Amendment Reconsidered''. p. 160&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sonia Johnson]], a traditionally raised Mormon housewife whose eventual feminist advocacy for the ERA's passage led to her excommunication by the LDS church, subsequently wrote about her experiences in the memoir ''From Housewife to Heretic''. (Johnson and others led a hunger strike/fast at the Illinois state senate building in an effort to push Illinois toward ratification before the deadline of 1982.)

==Post-deadline ratifications==

Beginning in the mid 1990s, ERA proponents began an effort to win ratification of the ERA by the legislatures of states that did not ratify it between 1972 and 1982. These proponents claim that Congress can remove the ERA's ratification deadline despite the deadline having expired, allowing the states again to ratify it. They also claim that the ratifications ERA previously received remain valid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Three-State Strategy|url=http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/strategy.htm|publisher=Alice Paul Institute in collaboration with the ERA Task Force of the National Council of Women's Organizations|accessdate=April 25, 2014|author=Francis, Roberta W.|website=equalrightsamendment.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents of the three-state strategy have promoted ratification resolutions in the legislatures of most of the 15 states that never ratified the ERA before the time limit on its ratification expired.&lt;ref&gt;"Memorandum: Equal Rights Amendment: Ratification Issues", by David C. Huckabee. Specialist in American National Government, Government Division, The Library of Congress, Congressional Research Service. March 18, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 21, 2009, the [[National Organization for Women]] decided to support both efforts to obtain new ratifications and any strategy to submit a new ERA to the states for ratification.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2009 National NOW Conference Resolutions: Equal Rights Amendment|url=http://www.now.org/organization/conference/resolutions/2009.html|date=June 21, 2009|publisher=National Organization for Women|accessdate=2009-08-14|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090812221001/http://www.now.org/organization/conference/resolutions/2009.html|archivedate=2009-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, the [[Library of Congress]]'s [[Congressional Research Service]] issued a report saying that ratification deadlines are a [[political question]]:{{quote|ERA proponents claim that the Supreme Court's decision in ''Coleman v. Miller'' gives Congress wide discretion in setting conditions for the ratification process.}} It also says:{{quote|Revivification opponents caution ERA supporters against an overly broad interpretation of ''Coleman v. Miller'', which, they argue, may have been be {{sic}} a politically influenced decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=https://www.fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/R42979.pdf|format=PDF|author=Neale, Thomas H.|date=May 9, 2013|title=The Proposed Equal Rights Amendment: Contemporary Ratification Issues|publisher=Congressional Research Service}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

However, most recently, ERA Action has both led and brought renewed vigor to the movement by instituting what has become known as the "three state strategy".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Held, Herndon, and Stager|first=Allsion, Sheryl, and Danielle|date=1997|title=The Equal Rights Amendment: Why the ERA Remains Legally Viable And Properly Before the States|url=http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/misc/WM_law_article.pdf|journal=William &amp; Mary Journal of Women and the Law|volume=3:113|pages=113–136}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was in 2013 that ERA Action began to gain traction with this strategy through their coordination with Senate and House members not only to introduce legislation in both chambers to remove the ratification deadline, but also in gaining legislative sponsors. The Congressional Research Service then issued a report on the "three state strategy" on April 8, 2013 entitled "The Proposed Equal Rights Amendment: Contemporary Ratification Issues",&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/R42979.pdf|title=The Proposed Equal Rights Amendment: Contemporary Ratification Issues|last=Neale|first=Thomas|quote=Congressional Research Service|date=9 May 2013|accessdate=25 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; stating that the approach was viable.

In 2014, under the auspices of ERA Action and their coalition partners, both the Virginia and Illinois state senates voted to ratify the ERA; however, votes were blocked in both states' House chambers. In the meantime, the ERA ratification movement continued with the resolution being introduced in 10 state legislatures.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/index.htm|title=ERA: Home|website=www.equalrightsamendment.org|access-date=2017-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/03/21/520962541/nevada-on-cusp-of-ratifying-equal-rights-amendment-35-years-after-deadline|title=Nevada Ratifies The Equal Rights Amendment ... 35 Years After The Deadline|work=NPR.org|access-date=2017-04-06|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/maryland/politics/bal-cardin-equal-rights-amendment-20170121-story.html|title=As women march in D.C., Cardin co-sponsors new Equal Rights Amendment|last=Brown|first=Matthew Hay|work=baltimoresun.com|access-date=2017-04-06|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Then, on March 22 2017, the Nevada legislature became the first state in 40 years to ratify the ERA,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.aauw.org/2015/11/05/ratify-the-era/|title=Let's Ratify the ERA: A Look at Where We Are Now|last=says|first=Quora|website=AAUW: Empowering Women Since 1881|access-date=2017-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Illinois began to see movement again as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://chicago.suntimes.com/news/illinois-at-center-of-revived-equal-rights-amendment-fight/|title=Illinois at center of revived Equal Rights Amendment fight|work=Chicago Sun-Times|access-date=2017-04-06|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Subsequent congressional action==

The amendment has been reintroduced in every session of Congress since 1982. Senator [[Ted Kennedy]] (D-MA) championed it in the Senate from the [[99th United States Congress|99th Congress]] through the [[110th United States Congress|110th Congress]]. Senator [[Robert Menendez]] (D-NJ) introduced the amendment symbolically at the end of the [[111th United States Congress|111th Congress]] and has supported it in the [[112th United States Congress|112th Congress]]. In the House of Representatives, [[Carolyn B. Maloney]] (D-NY) has sponsored it since the [[105th United States Congress|105th Congress]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Equal Rights Amendment: 111th Congress|url=http://maloney.house.gov/sites/maloney.house.gov/files/documents/women/era/AUGUST%2012%20Facts%20About%20the%20ERA%20in%20the%20111th%20Congress.pdf|format=PDF|date=July 13, 2009|website=maloney.house.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt; most recently in August 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/bdquery/z?d113:h.j.res.56:|title=Bill Summary &amp; Status 113th Congress (2013 - 2014) H.J.RES.56 |website=loc.gov|publisher=Library of Congress}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1983, the ERA passed through House committees with the same text as in 1972; however, it failed by six votes to achieve the necessary two-thirds vote on the House floor. That was the last time that the ERA received a floor vote in the Congress.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RD3wqORd9jMC&amp;pg=PA308&amp;lpg=PA308&amp;dq=1983+%22equal+rights+amendment%22+%22six+votes%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Lz_WK1Sgkj&amp;sig=NPMx_gOnHO4VAM84GnBZ3dKtrb8&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=wahJTcuCKIWclge_7Lj6Dw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=1983%20%22equal%20rights%20amendment%22%20%22six%20votes%22&amp;f=false|author=Randall, Vicky|title=Women and Politics: An International Perspective|page=308|publisher=University of Chicago Press|date=1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the start of the 112th Congress on January 6, 2011, Senator Menendez, along with Representatives Maloney, [[Jerrold Nadler]] and [[Gwen Moore]], held a press conference advocating for the Equal Rights Amendment's adoption.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://maloney.house.gov/media-center/press-releases/constitution-read-aloud-maloney-menendez-nadler-moore-cite-need-equal-rights-amendment|title=As Constitution is read aloud, Maloney, Menendez, Nadler, Moore cite need for Equal Rights Amendment|date=January 6, 2011|website=maloney.house.gov|accessdate=April 22, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[113th United States Congress|113th Congress]] had a record number of women. On March 5, 2013, the ERA was reintroduced by Senator Menendez as S. J. RES. 10.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c113:S.J.+Res.+10:|title=Bill Text 113th Congress (2013-2014) S.J.RES.10.IS|website=loc.gov|publisher=Library of Congress}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailykos.com/story/2013/03/07/1192277/-Democrats-re-re-re-reintroduce-Equal-Rights-Amendment-but-shhhh-don-t-tell-anyone|author=Gray, Kaili Joy|date=March 7, 2013|title=Democrats re-re-re-reintroduce Equal Rights Amendment ... but shhhh, don't tell anyone|website=dailykos.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The "New ERA" introduced in 2013, sponsored by Representative Carolyn B. Maloney, adds an additional sentence to the original text: "Women shall have equal rights in the United States and every place subject to its jurisdiction."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Equal Means Equal|last=Neuwirth|first=Jessica|publisher=The New Press|year=2015|isbn=978-1-62097-039-3|location=New York|pages=102|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Proposed removal of ratification deadline===

On March 8, 2011, the 100th anniversary of [[International Women's Day]], Representative [[Tammy Baldwin]] (D-WI) introduced legislation (H.J.Res. 47) to remove the congressionally imposed deadline for ratification of the Equal Rights Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wispolitics.com/index.iml?Article=229427|title=U.S. Rep. Baldwin: Seeks to speed ratification of Equal Rights Amendment|website=wispolitics.com|accessdate=2011-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bill co-sponsors include Representatives [[Rob Andrews|Robert Andrews]] (D-NJ), [[Jackie Speier]] (D-CA), [[Luis Gutierrez]] (D-IL), [[Chellie Pingree]] (D-ME) and [[Debbie Wasserman Schultz]] (D-FL). On March 22, 2012, the 40th anniversary of the ERA's congressional approval, Senator [[Benjamin L. Cardin]] (D-MD) introduced (S.J. Res. 39)—which is worded with slight differences from Representative Baldwin's (H.J. Res. 47). Senator Cardin was joined by ten other Senators who added their names to the Senate Joint Resolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.congress.gov/bill/112th-congress/senate-joint-resolution/39/all-info|title=All Bill Information (Except Text) for S.J.Res.39 - A joint resolution removing the deadline for the ratification of the equal rights amendment|website=congress.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 24, 2013, the [[New Mexico House of Representatives]] passed a [[Resolution (law)|resolution]] asking that the congressionally imposed deadline for ERA ratification be removed.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.nmlegis.gov/Sessions/13%20Regular/memorials/house/HM007.pdf|format=PDF|title=House Memorial 7|author=51st Legislature, State of New Mexico, First Session, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lcsun-news.com/las_cruces-news/ci_22568975/roundhouse-roundup-feb-11-2013|title=Roundhouse roundup, Feb. 11, 2013|work=Las Cruces Sun-News|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140203021428/http://www.lcsun-news.com/las_cruces-news/ci_22568975/roundhouse-roundup-feb-11-2013|archivedate=2014-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The resolution was officially received by the U.S. House of Representatives on April 25, 2013, and was referred to the House's Committee on the Judiciary, as noted in the ''[[Congressional Record]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=https://www.congress.gov/crec/2013/04/25/CREC-2013-04-25-pt1-PgH2352.pdf|format=PDF|author=113th Congress, 1st Session
|title=Congressional Record|issue=Vol. 159, No. 58|page=H2352|website=congress.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==State Equal Rights Amendments==
{{Further information|State Equal Rights Amendments}}

Twenty-four states have adopted constitutions or constitutional amendments providing that equal rights under the law shall not be denied because of sex. Most of these provisions mirror the broad language of the ERA, while the wording in others resembles the [[Equal Protection Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metacrs7397/m1/1/high_res_d/RS20217_2004Aug23.pdf|title=Equal Rights Amendment: State Provisions|last=Gladstone|first=Leslie|date=August 23, 2004|publisher=[[Congressional Research Service]]|accessdate=June 19, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of course, the state actions do not change the federal draft laws that proved one of the stumbling blocks to passage of the national ERA. The 1879 [[Constitution of California]] contains the earliest state equal rights provision on record. Narrowly written, it limits the equal rights conferred to "entering or pursuing a business, profession, vocation, or employment". Near the end of the 19th century two more states, Wyoming (1890) and Utah (1896), included equal rights provisions in their constitutions. These provisions were broadly written to ensure political and civil equality between women and men.&lt;ref name="CRSReport"&gt;{{cite web|title=Equal Rights Amendments: State Provisions|url=https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metacrs7397/m1/1/high_res_d/RS20217_2004Aug23.pdf|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150515010101/http://digital.library.unt.edu/ark%3A/67531/metacrs7397/m1/1/high_res_d/RS20217_2004Aug23.pdf|work=CRS Report for Congress|publisher=Congressional Research Service - The Library of Congress|author=Leslie W. Gladstone|archivedate=May 15, 2015|dead-url=yes|date=August 23, 2004|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several states crafted and adopted their own equal rights amendments during the 1970s and 1980s, while the ERA was before the states, or afterward.
 
Some state Equal Rights Amendments and original constitutional equal rights provisions are:&lt;ref name="CRSReport"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.voteera.org/#!about1/c1xk3|title=VoteERA.org Equal Rights Amendment Women's Full Equality|work=VoteERA.org Equal Rights Amendment Women's Full Equality}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|'''Alaska''' – No person is to be denied the enjoyment of any civil or political right because of race, color, creed, sex or national origin. The legislature shall implement this section. ''Alaska Constitution, Article I, §3 (1972)''
 
'''California''' – A person may not be disqualified from entering or pursuing a business, profession, vocation, or employment because of sex, race, creed, color, or national or ethnic origin. ''California Constitution, Article I, §8 (1879)''

'''Colorado''' – Equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the state of Colorado or any of its political subdivisions because of sex. ''Colorado Constitution, Article II, §29 (1973)''

'''Connecticut''' - No person shall be denied the equal protection of the law nor be subjected to segregation or discrimination in the exercise or enjoyment of his or her civil or political rights because of religion, race, color, ancestry, national origin, sex or physical or mental disability. ''Connecticut Constitution, Article I, §20 (1984)''

'''Illinois''' - The equal protection of the laws shall not be denied or abridged on account of sex by the State or its units of local government and school districts. ''Illinois Constitution, Article I, §18 (1970)''

'''Iowa''' – All men and women are, by nature, free and equal and have certain inalienable rights—among which are those of enjoying and defending life and liberty,
acquiring, possessing and protecting property, and pursuing and obtaining safety and happiness. ''Iowa Constitution, Article I, §1 (1998)''

'''Maryland''' – Equality of rights under the law shall not be abridged or denied because of sex. ''Maryland Constitution, Declaration of Rights, Article 46 (1972)''

'''Massachusetts''' - All people are born free and equal, and have certain natural, essential, and unalienable rights; among which may be reckoned the right of enjoying and defending their lives and liberties; that of acquiring, possessing and protecting property; in fine, that of seeking and obtaining their safety and happiness. Equality under the law shall not be denied or abridged because of sex, race, color, creed or national origin. Massachusetts Constitution, Part 1, Article 1 as amended by Article CVI by vote of the People, (1976)

'''Montana''' – Individual dignity. The dignity of the human being is inviolable. No person shall be denied the equal protection of the laws. Neither the state nor any person, firm, corporation, or institution shall discriminate against any person in the exercise of his civil or political rights on account of race, color, sex, culture, social origin or condition, or political or religious ideas. ''Montana Constitution, Article II, §4 (1973)''

'''Oregon''' - Equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the state of Oregon or by any political subdivision in this state on account of sex. ''Oregon Constitution, Article I, §46 (2014)''

'''Utah''' – The rights of citizens of the State of Utah to vote and hold office shall not be denied or abridged on account of sex. Both male and female citizens of this State shall enjoy all civil, political and religious rights and privileges. ''Utah Constitution, Article IV, §1 (1896)''

'''Wyoming''' – In their inherent right to life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness, all members of the human race are equal. Since equality in the enjoyment of natural and civil rights is only made sure through political equality, the laws of this state affecting the political rights and privileges of its citizens shall be without distinction of race, color, sex, or any circumstance or condition whatsoever other than the individual incompetency or unworthiness duly ascertained by a court of competent jurisdiction. The rights of citizens of the state of Wyoming to vote and hold office shall not be denied or abridged on account of sex. Both male and female citizens of this state shall equally enjoy all civil, political and religious rights and privileges. ''Wyoming Constitution, Articles I and VI (1890)''}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Government of the United States|Law}}
* [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]]
* [[Equal pay for equal work]]
* [[Feminism in the United States]]
* [[First-wave feminism]]
* [[History of feminism]]
* [[History of women in the United States]]

==References==
{{Reflist|35em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite journal|last=Baldez|first=Lisa|author2=Epstein, Lee |author3=Martin, Andrew D. |year=2006|title=Does the U.S. Constitution Need an Equal Rights Amendment?|journal=[[Journal of Legal Studies]]|volume=35|issue=1|pages=243–283|doi=10.1086/498836|url=http://sites.lsa.umich.edu/admart/wp-content/uploads/sites/127/2014/08/jls06.pdf}}
*{{cite book|title=Pedestals and Podiums: Utah Women, Religious Authority, and Equal Rights|last=Bradley|first=Martha S.|year=2005|publisher=[[Signature Books]]|location=Salt Lake City, UT|isbn=1-56085-189-9}}
*{{cite book|title=Phyllis Schlafly and Grassroots Conservatism: A Woman's Crusade|last=Critchlow|first=Donald T.|year=2005|publisher=[[Princeton University Press]]|location=Princeton, NJ|isbn=0-691-07002-4}}
* Critchlow, Donald T., and Stachecki, Cynthia L. (2008). "The Equal Rights Amendment Reconsidered: Politics, Policy, and Social Mobilization in a Democracy", ''Journal of Policy History'' Volume 20, Number 1 [http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/journal_of_policy_history/v020/20.1.critchlow.html online]
* Dunlap, Mary C. (1976) "The Equal Rights Amendment and the Courts". ''Pepperdine Law Review'' Volume 3, Number 1 [http://digitalcommons.pepperdine.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2205&amp;context=plr online]
* Hatch, Orrin G. (1983). ''The Equal Rights Amendment: Myths and Realities'', Savant Press.
* Kempker, Erin M. (2013) "Coalition and Control: Hoosier Feminists and the Equal Rights Amendment". ''Frontiers: A Journal of Women Studies'' 34.2 (2013): 52-82. [https://web.archive.org/web/20140202155037/http://musejhuedu.kmvhr3.biz/login?auth=0&amp;type=summary&amp;url=%2Fjournals%2Ffrontiers%2Fv034%2F34.2.kempker.pdf online]
*{{cite book|title=A Lawyer Looks at the Equal Rights Amendment|last=Lee|first=Rex E.|authorlink=Rex E. Lee|year=1980|publisher=[[Brigham Young University Press]]|location=Provo, UT|isbn=0-8425-1883-5}}
*{{cite book|title=Why We Lost the ERA|last=Mansbridge|first=Jane J.|year=1986|publisher=[[University of Chicago Press]]|location=Chicago|isbn=0-226-50358-5}}
*{{cite book|chapter='Forward' Women: Winning the Wisconsin Campaign for the Country's First ERA, 1921.|title=The Quest for Social Justice III|last=McBride|first=Genevieve G.|editor=Peter Watson Boone (ed.)|year=2005|publisher=UW-Milwaukee|location=Milwaukee, WI|isbn=1-879281-26-0}}
* Neale, T. H. (2013). ''The proposed Equal Rights Amendment: Contemporary ratification issues'' (Washington, DC: Congressional Research Service) [http://digitalcommons.ilr.cornell.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2044&amp;context=key_workplace&amp;sei-redir=1&amp;referer=http%3A%2F%2Fscholar.google.com%2Fscholar%3Fstart%3D20%26q%3D%2522Equal%2BRights%2BAmendment%2522%26hl%3Den%26as_sdt%3D0%2C27%26as_ylo%3D2013#search=%22Equal%20Rights%20Amendment%22 online]
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Equal Rights Amendment}}
{{Wikisource}}
*[http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/ Alice Paul Institute]
*[http://www.united4equality.com/ United4Equality]
*[http://www.VoteERA.org VoteERA.org/] 
*[http://www.eagleforum.org/era/ Eagle Forum]
*[http://www.women-matter.org/ Women Matter]
*[http://www.eracoalition.org/ ERA Coalition]
*[http://www.katrinasdream.org/era/ Katrina's Dream]
*[https://www.eraaction.org/ ERA Action]
*[http://capitalnews.vcu.edu/2015/02/16/virginia-still-deciding-if-women-are-equal 2015 article on attempts to revive the amendment in Virginia]
* {{cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/volokh-conspiracy/wp-content/uploads/sites/14/2016/05/ginsburg.jpg |title=Opinion: The Fear of the Equal Rights Amendment |author=Ginsburg, Ruth Bader |author-link=Ruth Bader Ginsburg |date=7 April 1975 |newspaper=The Washington Post |accessdate=1 August 2017 |archivedate=3 May 2017 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170503130420/https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/volokh-conspiracy/wp-content/uploads/sites/14/2016/05/ginsburg.jpg |deadurl=no |quote=But opponents continue a campaign appealing to our insecurity. The campaign theme is fear, fear of unsettling familiar and, for many men and women, comfortable patterns; fear of change, engendering counsel that we should not deviate from current arrangements, because we cannot fully forecast what an equal opportunity society would be like.}}

{{Alice Paul}}
{{US Constitution|state=expanded}}

[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:History of women's rights in the United States]]
[[Category:Unratified amendments to the United States Constitution]]
[[Category:Second-wave feminism]]
[[Category:Counterculture of the 1960s]]
[[Category:Alice Paul]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>