<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051104001421|27299224" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="59635" pageid="59635" ns="0" title="Equal Rights Amendment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-07T01:13:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''Equal Rights Amendment''' ('''ERA''') was a proposed [[amendment]] to the [[United States Constitution]] which would have guaranteed [[equal rights]] under [[law]] for [[United States|Americans]] regardless of [[sex]].

The deadline for ratification of the ERA&amp;mdash;whether that deadline was [[March 22]], [[1979]], or [[June 30]], [[1982]]&amp;mdash;has come and gone and most observers are of the opinion that the ERA is no longer pending before America's [[state legislature|state lawmakers]] for consideration. Other persons, however, maintain that if the legislatures of just three more states ratify it, the ERA ''could'' become part of the Constitution. An article[http://www.4ERA.org/threestate.html] published in the William and Mary Law School Journal in [[1997]] provides the constitutional rationale for the "3-state strategy" and the [[Library of Congress]] has issued a [[report]] suggesting that this theory is at least worthy of serious consideration. Polls show that a majority of Americans continue to support the ERA, and efforts to introduce ERA ratification resolutions&amp;mdash;in the legislatures of those 15 states which never ratified the measure&amp;mdash;have increased in recent years. At the Federal level, supporters of the ERA have re-introduced the amendment in Congress[http://www.4ERA.org/legislation.html] every term since 1982 without success.  Regardless, the national debate on the ERA has largely subsided, in part because of expanded interpretations of existing statutes and constitutional provisions.

== Text ==
The ERA's text, as proposed in [[1972]] by the [[Ninety-second United States Congress|92nd Congress]], and as published in Volume 86, ''United States Statutes At Large'' (pages 1523&amp;ndash;1524), reads as follows:
&lt;blockquote&gt;''SECTION 1. Equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of sex.''&lt;br&gt;
''SEC. 2. The Congress shall have the power to enforce, by appropriate legislation, the provisions of this article.''&lt;br&gt;
''SEC. 3. This amendment shall take effect two years after the date of ratification.''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!-- Text of amendment from: Congressional Research Service. (1992). Proposed amendments not ratified by the states. In ''The Constitution of the United States of America: Analysis and Interpretation.'' (Senate Document No. 103–6). (Johnny H. Killian and George A. Costello, Eds.). Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office.--&gt;

== History in Congress ==
Although the [[1920]] [[ratification]] of the [[nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|19th Amendment]] had guaranteed American women's [[right to vote]], [[Alice Paul]], a [[suffragist]] leader, argued that this right alone would not end remaining vestiges of legal [[discrimination]] based upon [[gender]].  In [[1923]], Paul drafted the Equal Rights Amendment and presented it as the "[[Lucretia Mott]] Amendment" at the celebration of the 75th [[anniversary]] of the [[1848]] [[Seneca Falls Declaration of Sentiments]].

The [[National Women's Party]] took the ERA to Congress in the [[1920s]], where [[Charles Curtis|Senator Charles Curtis]] and [[Daniel Read Anthony, Jr.|Representative Daniel R. Anthony, Jr.]]&amp;mdash;both [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]s and both from [[Kansas]]&amp;mdash;introduced it for the first time as Senate Joint Resolution No. 21 on [[December 10]], [[1923]], and as House Joint Resolution No. 75 on [[December 13]], [[1923]], respectively.  Though the ERA was introduced in every session of Congress between 1923 and [[1970]], it never reached the floor of either the [[United States Senate|Senate]] or the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] for a vote&amp;mdash;instead, it was usually "bottled up" in [[U.S. Congressional committee|committee]].

[[Martha W. Griffiths|Representative Martha W. Griffiths]] of [[Michigan]], however, achieved success on Capitol Hill with her House Joint Resolution No. 208, which was adopted by the House of Representatives on [[October 12]], [[1971]], with a vote of 354 yeas, 24 nays and 51 not voting (117 ''Congressional Record'' 35815).  Griffiths' joint resolution was then adopted by the Senate on [[March 22]], [[1972]], with a vote of 84 yeas, 8 nays and 7 not voting (118 ''Congressional Record'' 9598).  And with that, the ERA was finally presented by the 92nd Congress to the state legislatures for ratification, as Article V of the Constitution prescribes.

== Opponents of the ERA in Congress ==
Opponents of the ERA, at the time of its proposal by the 92nd Congress, were a very interesting mix of politicians that included many conservatives and a few liberals.

In the House of Representatives:

* [[Thomas G. Abernethy]] (1903&amp;ndash;1998) (D-MS)
* [[John M. Ashbrook]] (1928&amp;ndash;1982) (R-OH)
* [[John W. Byrnes]] (1913&amp;ndash;1985) (R-WI)
* [[Glenn R. Davis]] (1914&amp;ndash;1988) (R-WI)
* [[W. J. Bryan Dorn]] (1916&amp;ndash;2005) (D-SC)
* [[Emanuel Celler]] (1888&amp;ndash;1981) (D-NY)
* [[William V. Chappell, Jr.]] (1922&amp;ndash;1989) (D-FL)
* [[William M. Colmer]] (1890&amp;ndash;1980) (D-MS)
* [[David W. Dennis]] (1912&amp;ndash;1999) (R-IN)
* [[John N. Erlenborn]] (1927&amp;ndash; ) (R-IL)
* [[John J. Flynt, Jr.]] (1914&amp;ndash; ) (D-GA)
* [[J. Edward Hutchinson]] (1914&amp;ndash;1985) (R-MI)
* [[Charles R. Jonas]] (1904&amp;ndash;1988) (R-NC)
* [[Earl F. Landgrebe]] (1916&amp;ndash;1986) (R-IN)
* [[William M. McCulloch]] (1901&amp;ndash;1980) (R-OH)
* [[Koln G. McKay]] (1925&amp;ndash;2000) (D-UT)
* [[Lucien N. Nedzi]] (1925&amp;ndash; ) (D-MI)
* [[William R. Poage]] (1899&amp;ndash;1987) (D-TX)
* [[John R. Rarick]] (1924&amp;ndash; ) (D-LA)
* [[John H. Rousselot]] (1927&amp;ndash;2003) (R-CA)
* [[Charles W. Sandman, Jr.]] (1921&amp;ndash;1985) (R-NJ)
* [[John P. Saylor]] (1908&amp;ndash;1973) (R-PA)
* [[John G. Schmitz]] (1930&amp;ndash;2001) (R-CA)
* [[Sam Steiger]] (1929&amp;ndash; ) (R-AZ)
* [[Leonor K. Sullivan]] (1902&amp;ndash;1988) (D-MO)
* [[Jamie L. Whitten]] (1910&amp;ndash;1995) (D-MS)
* [[Charles E. Wiggins]] (1927&amp;ndash;2000) (R-CA)

Note:  While Representatives Davis, Erlenborn and Landgrebe opposed the Amendment, they did not vote.

In the Senate:

* [[Wallace Bennett]] (1898&amp;ndash;1993) (R-UT)
* [[James L. Buckley]] (1923&amp;ndash; ) ("Conservative"-NY)
* [[Norris H. Cotton]] (1900&amp;ndash;1989) (R-NH)
* [[James O. Eastland]] (1904&amp;ndash;1986) (D-MS)
* [[Samuel J. Ervin, Jr.]] (1896&amp;ndash;1985) (D-NC)
* [[Paul J. Fannin]] (1907&amp;ndash;2002) (R-AZ)
* [[Barry M. Goldwater]] (1909&amp;ndash;1998) (R-AZ)
* [[Clifford P. Hansen]] (1912&amp;ndash; ) (R-WY)
* [[John C. Stennis]] (1901&amp;ndash;1995) (D-MS)

Note:  While Senator Eastland did not vote against it, he was opposed to the Amendment.

== Mixed reception in state legislatures ==
The initial pace of [[State legislature|state legislative]] ratifications was rapid during 1972 and [[1973]], but then slowed considerably with only three ratifications during [[1974]], just one in [[1975]], none at all in [[1976]], and only one in [[1977]].  The 92nd Congress, in proposing the ERA, had set a seven-year time limit for the Amendment's ratification, and by the end of that [[deadline]] on [[March 22]], [[1979]], a total of 35 of the required 38 states had ratified it.  Also, as of that date, four of those 35 states had subsequently adopted resolutions to ''rescind'' their earlier ratifications and a fifth state adopted a resolution declaring that its earlier approval of the ERA would not extend beyond March 22, 1979 (more on that below).

At various times, in eight of the 15 non-ratifying states, at least one chamber of the legislature approved the ERA, those eight states being:

*[[Florida]] whose House of Representatives voted to ratify the ERA on [[March 24]], [[1972]], with a tally of 91 to 4; a second time on [[April 10]], [[1975]], with a tally of 62 to 58; a third time on [[May 17]], [[1979]], with a tally of 66 to 53; and a fourth time on [[June 21]], [[1982]], with a tally of 60 to 58.
*[[Illinois]] whose Senate voted to ratify the ERA in [[May]] of 1972, with a tally of 30 to 21; and whose House of Representatives voted to ratify the ERA on [[May 1]], [[1975]], with a tally of 113 to 62; and again on [[May 21]], [[2003]], with a tally of 76 to 41.  It should be noted that, at various times, votes were conducted in both chambers of the Illinois General Assembly on the question of ratifying the ERA and while most members voted ''in favor of'' ratification, the result would often be less than the three-fifths supermajority vote&amp;mdash;a requirement that existed in Illinois when those votes were cast.
*[[Louisiana]] whose Senate voted to ratify the ERA on [[June 7]], [[1972]], with a tally of 25 to 13.
*[[Missouri]] whose House of Representatives voted to ratify the ERA on [[February 7]], [[1975]], with a tally of 82 to 75.
*[[Nevada]] whose Assembly voted to ratify the ERA on [[February 17]], [[1975]], with a tally of 27 to 13; and whose Senate voted to ratify the ERA on [[February 8]], [[1977]], with a tally of 11 to 10.
*[[North Carolina]] whose House of Representatives voted to ratify the ERA on [[February 9]], [[1977]], with a tally of 61 to 55.
*[[Oklahoma]] whose Senate voted to ratify the ERA on [[March 23]], [[1972]], by a Voice Vote.
*[[South Carolina]] whose House of Representatives voted to ratify the ERA on [[March 22]], [[1972]], with a tally of 83 to Zero.

On the other hand, and as previously noted, four of the 35 states which ''did'' fully approve the ERA early on later acted to ''rescind'' their ratifications and a fifth state announced that&amp;mdash;while not actually rescinding its previous assent to the ERA&amp;mdash;that assent would last only until March 22, 1979. The following are those actions:

*[[Idaho]] which ratified the ERA on [[March 24]], [[1972]], by approving Senate Joint Resolution No. 133, and which then adopted House Concurrent Resolution No. 10 on [[February 8]], [[1977]], to rescind that ratification.
*[[Kentucky]] which ratified the ERA on [[June 26]], [[1972]], by approving House (Joint) Resolution No. 2, and which then adopted House (Joint) Resolution No. 20 on [[March 17]], [[1978]], to rescind that ratification; there is some speculation about Kentucky's rescission in that the rescinding resolution was vetoed by the Lieutenant Governor who was acting as Governor in the Governor's absence.
*[[Nebraska]] which ratified the ERA on [[March 29]], [[1972]], by approving the erroneously-worded Legislative Resolution No. 83 and then approving the correctly-worded Legislative Resolution No. 86; Nebraska lawmakers then adopted Legislative Resolution No. 9 on [[March 15]], [[1973]], to rescind only the aforementioned Legislative Resolution No. 83.
*[[Tennessee]] which ratified the ERA on [[April 4]], [[1972]], by approving House Joint Resolution No. 371, and which then adopted Senate Joint Resolution No. 29 on [[April 23]], [[1974]], to rescind that ratification.

It is believed by some scholars that a state legislature ''cannot'' rescind its prior ratification of a proposed Federal constitutional amendment, a Congressional precedent&amp;mdash;not a judicial precedent&amp;mdash;established in [[1868]] with irregularities involving the ratification of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th Amendment]].  (See [[Article Five of the United States Constitution#Ratification|Article V of the United States Constitution]].)

In the specific case of [[South Dakota]], its lawmakers ratified the ERA on [[February 5]], [[1973]], by approving Senate Joint Resolution No. 1; then South Dakota legislators adopted Senate Joint Resolution No. 2 on [[March 1]], [[1979]], stipulating that the ERA's opportunity for ratification&amp;mdash;by any state of the Union&amp;mdash;would expire on March 22, 1979; furthermore, Senate Joint Resolution No. 2 made clear that South Dakota's own ratification would only be valid up until March 22, 1979, and that any activities transpiring after that date would be considered by South Dakota to be null and void.&lt;!--Information derived from "The Equal Rights Amendment: myths and realities" authored by Orrin G. Hatch, published 1983.--&gt;

== Shift in political attitudes ==
The political tide changed direction in the late [[1970s]] and throughout the [[1980s]].  The [[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]] withdrew its earlier support for the ERA.  The most prominent ERA opposition leader was [[Phyllis Schlafly]], a [[conservative]] Republican.  According to its [[critics]], the ERA would have granted more [[Political power|power]] to Congress and to the [[federal court|Federal courts]], a stance unpopular at a time when public opposition to expanded Federal government authority&amp;mdash;and Federal [[judicial activism]] in particular&amp;mdash;was growing.  Opponents, and even most supporters of the ERA, agree that if freshly re-proposed by Congress, the ERA would have to start from scratch and would need to gain state ratifications all over again&amp;mdash;the state approvals achieved during the [[1970s]] being non-transferable.

== "Sex Bias in the U.S. Code" ==
The report, entitled ''Sex Bias in the U.S. Code'', co-authored by [[Ruth Bader Ginsburg]] (and sixteen other individuals under the supervision of a government attorney), before Ginsburg became a federal judge, and published in 1977 by the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, sought to show how the proposed ERA (for which Ginsburg was an aggressive advocate) would change Federal laws to make them gender-neutral and to "eliminate sex-discriminatory provisions."

== Opposition issues ==
Opponents of the ERA argue that its passage would have far-reaching implications, obliterating traditional distinctions between the sexes. Women, ERA opponents claim, would be required to register for the [[Selective Service System]] (the draft) just as men currently do, and would have to serve in [[combat]] just as men must. Opponents go on to assert that the ERA would also remove [[laws]] that specially protect women, such as [[labor]] laws in heavy industry.  Some states, such as [[Connecticut]] and [[New Mexico]], have even ordered the use of tax monies in the case of "medically necessary" abortions, based upon state ERAs, under the theory that women must have health care every bit as comprehensive as that accorded to men.  Interestingly, Alice Paul&amp;mdash;author of the original ERA, as noted earlier&amp;mdash;was an opponent of abortion and described the procedure as "the ultimate exploitation of women."

Other critics have argued that the courts could rule that the ERA would mandate the recognition of [[gay marriage|same-sex marriage]]. Critics also maintain that the ERA would require the integration of single-sex [[school]]s, [[sports team]]s or even restrooms&amp;mdash;they point to a decision by a court in the State of [[Washington]] which ordered a [[fraternal]] [[civic]] [[organization]] to admit women, based upon the ERA within its state constitution.  Finally, some opponents of the ERA contend that the amendment simply is not necessary, and that other provisions of the Constitution&amp;mdash;and various rulings by the Supreme Court&amp;mdash;provide sufficient support for equal rights for both genders.

Supporters of the amendment characterize these implications as "scare tactics" designed to obscure the real advantages of a constitutional guarantee of equal rights for men and women.  Supporters assert that the [myths[http://www.4ERA.org/myths.htm]] which opponents perpetuate about the ERA are either without merit or concern separate issues which the ERA would not affect.

== Extension of ratification deadline ==
In 1978&amp;mdash;as the 1979 deadline approached&amp;mdash;the [[Ninety-fifth United States Congress|95th Congress]] adopted House Joint Resolution No. 638, by Representative [[Elizabeth Holtzman]] of [[New York]], which purported to extend the ERA's ratification deadline to [[June 30]], [[1982]] (Volume 92, ''United States Statutes At Large,'' page 3799).  

On [[December 23]], [[1981]], a United States District Court ruled, in the case of ''State of Idaho, et al. v. Freeman, et al.'' (529 F. Supp. 1107; judgment stayed [[January 25]], [[1982]]), that the ERA's deadline extension was [[unconstitutional]] and, further, that a state legislature may indeed rescind a prior ratification of a proposed amendment to the Federal Constitution. However, when the case was then appealed up to the [[United States Supreme Court]], the Justices dismissed it as "[[moot]]" on [[October 4]], [[1982]], (459 U.S. 809) on the technicality that the revised ratification deadline of [[June 30]], [[1982]], had already passed. Because the nation's highest Court did not issue an opinion on the direct substance of whether the deadline extension was&amp;mdash;or was not&amp;mdash;valid, the question of the extension's validity remains officially unanswered by the Federal judiciary.

No additional states ratified the ERA during that extra period of slightly more than three years.  In fact, the only occurrence favorable to the ERA between the original deadline of [[March 22]], [[1979]], and the revised [[June 30]], [[1982]], expiration date was&amp;mdash;as noted earlier&amp;mdash;its approval by the Florida House of Representatives on [[June 21]], [[1982]].  Not long afterward, that ratifying resolution was ''defeated'' in the Florida Senate by a vote of 16 yeas and 22 nays.

==  "Three-state strategy"==
Some ERA supporters argue that the earlier 35 ratifications are ''still'' valid, and that ''only three'' more ratifications are necessary ''without'' Congress having to even resubmit the ERA anew to the nation's state lawmakers.  According to this theory, three additional states could belatedly ratify the ERA, arguing that the history of the [[Twenty-seventh Amendment to the United States Constitution|27th Amendment]]&amp;mdash;which was ratified more than 200 years after it was first proposed&amp;mdash;supports the thinking behind this approach.  The theory postulates that, under the 1939 ruling by the U.S. Supreme Court in the case of ''[[Coleman v. Miller]]'', Congress would then&amp;mdash;in such a scenario&amp;mdash;be in a position to decide whether or not the ERA had been validly ratified under the Court's "political question" doctrine which reserves to Congress the power to pass judgment on the validity of a ratification.

In 1997, an article published in the William and Mary Journal of Women and the Law, entitled "Why the ERA Remains Legally Viable and Properly Before the States"[http://www.4ERA.org/threestate.html] presents the legal rationale for what has come to be known as the "Three State Strategy."  It argues, based on earlier precedents, that:

(1) the 35 ratifications from state legislatures during the 1970s remain valid;
(2) rescissions of prior ratifications are ''not'' constitutional;
(3) the 1978 extension of the ERA's deadline demonstrates that Congress can amend previously-established deadlines; and
(4) the 27th Amendment's abnormally long ratification period set a standard of "sufficiently contemporaneous"&amp;mdash;a term used during the Supreme Court's [[1921]] ruling in ''[[Dillon v. Gloss]]'', giving Congress the power to set time limits on constitutional amendments that it wishes to set such deadlines on.

The article in the William and Mary Journal of Women and the Law further reasons that because the Constitution gives Congress the power to amend the Constitution&amp;mdash;and indeed the power to alter aspects of the ratification process itself&amp;mdash;that if and when three additional states ratify the ERA, Congress has the power to deem the Amendment properly ratified and added to the Constitution.  The [[Library of Congress]]' Congressional Research Service [http://www.4ERA.org/threestate.html] has issued a report suggesting that this theory is at least worthy of serious consideration.

Pursuant to this legal rationale, ratification efforts have increased dramatically during the last few years. The Illinois House of Representatives as late as [[May 21]], [[2003]], adopted a resolution ratifying the ERA&amp;mdash;proposed in 1972&amp;mdash;but the Illinois Senate did not follow the House's lead and that particular resolution died in the General Assembly's upper chamber by the end of [[2004]]. On [[April 5]], [[2005]], the [[Arkansas]] Senate voted 16 yeas, 15 nays and 4 "not voting" on a resolution to approve the ERA, and while that number would ordinarily be sufficient for adoption in many state legislative bodies, under the parliamentary rules of the Arkansas Senate, a resolution of this type requires a majority vote of the total membership&amp;mdash;which would have been at least 18 yeas.  ERA ratification resolutions have likewise been introduced in Florida and Illinois during 2005.

To clarify, ''unlike'' the aforementioned House Joint Resolution No. 208 of the 92nd Congress and ''unlike'' the aforementioned House Joint Resolution No. 638 of the 95th Congress, the [[1789]] resolution of the [[First United States Congress|1st Congress]], proposing what is today the 27th Amendment did ''not'' set any deadline on that measure's ratification by the state legislatures.  Furthermore, neither the Supreme Court&amp;mdash;nor any lower Federal court&amp;mdash;has ruled on whether the 27th Amendment is actually a valid part of the Federal Constitution.

== Alternatives to the ERA ==
Despite the ERA's failure at ratification, many of its goals have otherwise been achieved through judicial interpretations of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] and of the [[Equal Protection Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th Amendment]].  The successes of feminism in altering both the culture and politics of the United States since the 1970s, together with the significant inclusion of women in many fields once traditionally dominated by men, have dampened much of the political momentum that once propelled the ERA.

== State ERAs ==
Since [[1879]], a total of 20 states have added equal rights amendments to their state constitutions. All of these state-level amendments, like the proposed Federal ERA, prohibit discrimination based on [[sex]]. Thirteen of the state-level amendments also prohibit discrimination based on [[race]], national origin, or [[creed]]&amp;mdash;and three of them even go so far as to prohibit discrimination on account of a physical handicap. Those 20 states are: [[Alaska]], [[California]], [[Colorado]], [[Connecticut]], [[Florida]], [[Hawaii]], [[Illinois]], [[Iowa]], [[Louisiana]], [[Maryland]], [[Massachusetts]], [[Montana]], [[New Hampshire]], [[New Mexico]], [[Pennsylvania]], [[Texas]], [[Utah]], [[Virginia]], [[Washington]], and [[Wyoming]].

== See also ==
* [[Article Five of the United States Constitution]]
* [[Section Twenty-eight of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]]
* Bradley, Martha S., ''[http://www.signaturebooks.com/excerpts/pedestals.htm Pedestals and Podiums: Utah Women, Religious Authority, and Equal Rights]'', Signature Books, Salt Lake City, UT, 2005, ISBN 1560851899 
&lt;!-- Categories and interwiki language links follow --&gt;

[[Category:U.S. history of women's rights]]
[[Category:U.S. Constitution unratified amendments]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>