<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091115122803|325969168" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18499" pageid="18499" ns="0" title="Left-wing politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-15T12:49:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Left-wing|the term used in sports|winger (sport)}}
{{Redirect|Leftism|the album of the band Leftfield|Leftism (album)}}
{{Redirect|Leftist|type of tree data structure in computer science|Leftist tree}}

{{Party politics}}
In [[politics]], '''''left-wing''''', '''''leftist''''' and '''''the Left''''' generally implies support for social change with a view to creating a more [[Egalitarianism|egalitarian]] society. The term ''Left'' was coined during the [[French Revolution]], referring to the seating arrangement in parliament; those who sat on the left supported the [[Radicalism (historical)|radical changes]] of the revolution, including the creation of a [[republic]] and [[secularization]].&lt;ref name="Knapp"/&gt; The concept of a distinct political Left originated with the [[June Days Uprising]] of [[1848]]. The organizers of the [[First International]] saw themselves as the successors of the left wing of the French Revolution. The term was applied to a number of revolutionary movements in Europe, especially [[socialism]], [[anarchism]]&lt;ref&gt; Brooks, Frank H. (1994). The Individualist Anarchists: An Anthology of Liberty (1881–1908). Transaction Publishers. p. xi. "Usually considered to be an extreme left-wing ideology, anarchism has always included a significant strain of radical individualism...&lt;/ref&gt;  and [[communism]]. The term is also used to describe [[social democracy]] and [[Social liberalism|social liberalism]].&lt;ref name="Van Gosse 2005"&gt;Van Gosse, ''The Movements of the New Left, 1950 - 1975: A Brief History with Documents'', Palgrave Macmillan, 2005, ISBN 9781403968043&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of the term==
{{See also|Left-Right politics|History of the Left in France}}
In politics the term ''left wing'' derives from the [[French Revolution]], when radical [[The Mountain|Montagnard]] and [[Jacobin (politics)|Jacobin]] deputies from the [[Third Estate]] generally sat to the left of the president's chair, a habit which began in the [[French States-General|Estates General]] of 1789. Throughout the [[France in the 19th century|19th century]], the main line dividing [[Politics of France|Left and Right in France]] was between supporters of the [[Republic]] and those of the [[Monarchy]].&lt;ref name="Knapp"&gt;{{cite book|author=Andrew Knapp and Vincent Wright|title=[http://books.google.com/books?id=67ttjXHhT3wC&amp;dq=the+government+and+politics+of+france&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=bn&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=tUFySqX7CYWIMqOg3LEM&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false The Government and Politics of France]|year=2006|publisher=Routledge}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Republic itself, or, as it was called by Radical Republicans, the Democratic and Social Republic (''la République démocratique et sociale''), was the objective of the French [[workers' movement]], and the [[lowest common denominator]] of the French Left. The [[June Days Uprising]] during the [[French Second Republic|Second Republic]] was the attempt by the left to assert itself after the [[1848 Revolution (France)|1848 Revolution]], but few of the (still predominantly rural) population supported them.

Following [[Napoleon III]]'s [[French coup of 1851|1851 coup]] and the subsequent establishment of the [[Second French Empire|Second Empire]], the Left was excluded from the political arena and focused on organising the workers. The growing French workers movement consisted of diverse strands; [[Marxism]] began to rival Radical Republicanism and the "[[Utopian socialism]]" of [[Auguste Comte]] and [[Charles Fourier]] with whom [[Karl Marx]] had become disillusioned. Socialism fused with the Jacobin ideals of Radical Republicanism leading to a political posture embracing nationalism, socialism, democracy, and [[anti-clericalism]] (opposition to the role of the church in controlling French social and cultural life) all of which remain distinctive features of the French Left. Most [[Catholicism in France|practicing Catholics]] continue to vote conservative while areas which were receptive to the revolution in 1789 continue to vote socialist.
In the United States and United Kingdom, many leftists, [[social liberal]]s, [[progressivism|progressive]]s and trade unionists were influenced by the works of [[Thomas Paine]], who introduced the concept of [[Asset-based egalitarianism]], which theorises that [[social equality]] is possible by a redistribution of resources, usually in the form of a [[Financial capital|capital]] grant provided at the [[age of majority]]. 

From mid-19th century, 'left' would increasingly refer to various forms of [[socialism]] and [[communism]]. Particularly influential was the publication of the [[Communist Manifesto]] by [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]] in 1848, which asserted that the history of all hitherto existing human society is the history of class struggle. It predicted that a [[proletarian]] revolution would eventually overthrow [[bourgeoisie|bourgeois]] society, and by abolishing private property create a [[classless]], [[Stateless communism|stateless]], and post-monetary society. The International Workingmen's Association (1864-76), sometimes called the [[First International]], brought together delegates from many different countries, and from many different left-wing groups and trade union organizations. Some of Marx's contemporaries espoused similar ideas, but differed in their views of how to reach to a classless and stateless society. Following the split between those associated with Marx and [[Mikhail Bakunin]] at the [[First International]], the anarchists formed the [[International Workers Association]].&lt;ref&gt;Marshall, Peter. "Demanding the Impossible&amp;nbsp; — A History of Anarchism" p. 9. Fontana Press, London, 1993 ISBN 978-0-00-686245-1&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Second International]] (1888-1916) was eventually divided by the question of supporting or opposing the [[First World War]]. Those who opposed the war, such as [[Lenin]] and [[Rosa Luxemburg]], saw themselves as further to the left (see [[Zimmerwald Left]]). Out of this conflict the socialist movement divided into [[Social Democracy|Social Democrats]] and Communists, the latter being seen as further to the Left. In the 1960s with the political upheavals of the [[Sino-Soviet split]] and [[May 1968 in France]], thinkers of the '[[New Left]]' viewed themselves as being more critical of Marxist and [[Marxism-Leninism|Marxist-Leninist]] discourse (labelled the '[[Old Left]]'). [[Left-libertarianism|Left-libertarian]] [[Roderick Long]] describes left-wing politics as including "concerns for worker empowerment, worry about plutocracy, concerns about feminism and various kinds of social equality.&lt;ref&gt;Long, Roderick. T. [http://en.liberalis.pl/2008/01/04/interview-with-roderick-long/ "An Interview With Roderick Long"]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States after [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]], the phrase "the Left" was used to describe [[labor unions]], [[civil rights movement]]s, and [[anti-war]] movements.&lt;ref name="Van Gosse 2005"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;JoAnne C. Reuss, ''American Folk Music and Left-Wing Politics'', The Scarecrow Press, 2000, ISBN 9780810836846&lt;/ref&gt;  In more recent times, in the United States, ''left-wing'' and ''right-wing'' have often been used as synonyms for [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrat]] and [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]], or as synonyms for  [[Modern liberalism in the United States|liberalism]] and [[Conservatism in the United States|conservatism]].&lt;ref&gt;http://thepage.time.com/2009/03/03/steele-to-gop-fight-for-coleman/?xid=rss-page&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theweek.com/article/index/96256/Is_it_Spains_place_to_investigate_Gitmo ABC news, reported in The Week, May 15, 2009, page 13]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;reported in Mother Jones, April 29, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.latimes.com/news/science/la-sci-politics10sep10,0,5982337.story&lt;/ref&gt;

==Varieties==
The spectrum of left-wing politics ranges from [[centre-left]] to [[far left]] (or [[Ultra-leftism|ultra-left]]). The term ''centre left'' describes a position close to the political mainstream. The terms ''far left'' and ''ultra-left'' refer to positions that are more [[Political radicalism|radical]]. The centre-left includes [[Social democracy|social democrat]]s, [[Progressivism|progressive]]s and also some [[Democratic socialism|democratic socialist]]s and [[Green politics|greens]] (in particular the [[Eco-socialism|eco-socialist]]s). Centre-left supporters accept market allocation of resources in a [[mixed economy]] with a significant [[public sector]] and a thriving [[private sector]]. Centre-left policies tend to favour limited [[Economic interventionism|state intervention]] in the [[Economics|economy]] in matters pertaining to the [[public interest]]. The centre-left also often favours moderate [[Environmentalism|environmentalist]] policies and generally, though not universally, supports individual freedom on moral issues.

In several countries, the terms ''far left'' and ''radical left'' have been associated with ideologies such as [[communism]], [[Maoism]], [[Autonomism]] and [[Collectivist anarchism]].  They have been used to describe groups that advocate [[anti-capitalist]], [[identity politics]] or [[eco-terrorism]]. In France, a distinction is made between the ''left'' ([[Socialist Party (France)|Socialist Party]] and [[French Communist Party|Communist Party]]) and the ''far left'' ([[Trotskyism|Trotskyists]], [[Maoism|Maoists]] and [[Anarchism|Anarchists]]).&lt;ref&gt;Cosseron, Serge (ed.). ''Le dictionnaire de l'extrême gauche''. Paris: [[Larousse]], 2007. p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; The US [[Department of Homeland Security]] defines left-wing extremism as groups who want "to bring about change through violent revolution rather than through established political processes."&lt;ref&gt;[http://theplumline.whorunsgov.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/hsa-leftwing-extremists-increase-in-cyber-attacks-dated-26-january-2009.pdf Left-wing extremists likely to increase use of cyber attacks over the next coming decade]&lt;/ref&gt;

In China, the term ''[[Chinese New Left]]'' denotes those who oppose the current [[Economic reform in the People's Republic of China|economic reforms]] and favour the restoration of more socialist policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{web cite|url=http://news.ft.com/cms/s/74029202-a389-11da-83cc-0000779e2340,s01=1.html|title=China launches ‘New Deal’ for farmers|publisher=[[Financial Times]]|date=2006-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Western world]], the term ''[[New Left]]'' refers to [[Culture|cultural]] politics. In the [[United Kingdom]] in the 1980s, the term ''[[hard left]]'' was applied to supporters of [[Tony Benn]], such as the [[Campaign Group]] and [[Labour Briefing]], as well as Trotskyist groups such as the [[Militant Tendency]] and [[Socialist Organiser]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/politics/1054337.stm]&lt;/ref&gt; In the same period, the term ''[[soft left]]'' was applied to supporters of the [[British Labour Party]] who were perceived to be more moderate.

The present day [[British Labour Party]] (also known as 'New Labour') are generally considered to be less left wing than they have been in the past. Politicalcompass.org places them to the right of centre, although more left wing than the [[Conservative Party]].

==Positions==
===Economics===
Most leftists favor some form of government intervention in the economy. Leftist economic beliefs range from [[Keynesian]] economics and the [[welfare state]] through [[industrial democracy]] and the [[social market]] to [[nationalization]] of the economy and [[Planned economy|central planning]].&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Glyn, ''Social Democracy in Neoliberal Times: The Left and Economic Policy since 1980'', Oxford University Press, 2001, ISBN 978-0199241385.&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[industrial revolution]], left-wingers supported [[trade union]]s. In the early twentieth century, the Left became associated with policies advocating extensive government intervention in the economy.&lt;ref&gt; Eric D. Beinhocker. ''The origin of wealth''. Harvard Business Press. 2006. ISBN 9781578517770 p. 416[http://www.google.com/books?id=eUoolrxSFy0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Beinhocker#PPA416,M1]&lt;/ref&gt; Leftists have criticized what they perceive as the exploitative nature of [[globalization]], such as [[sweatshops]], the ''[[race to the bottom]]'' and unjust lay-offs. The association of leftists with extensive government intervention lessened in the later part of the twentieth century.

Some leftists believe in [[Marxian economics]], which are based on the economic theories of [[Karl Marx]]. Some distinguish Marx's economic theories from his political philosophy, arguing that Marx's approach to understanding the economy is independent of his advocacy of revolutionary [[socialism]] or his belief in the inevitability of [[proletariat|proletarian]] revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = The Neo-Marxian Schools
  | publisher = The New School
  | url = http://cepa.newschool.edu/het/schools/neomarx.htm
  | accessdate = 2007-08-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Munro
  | first = John
  | title = Some Basic Principles of Marxian Economics
  | publisher = University of Toronto
  | url = http://www.chass.utoronto.ca/~munro5/MARXECON.htm
  | accessdate = 2007-08-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Marxian economics does not lean entirely upon the works of Marx, it draws from a range of Marxist and non-Marxist sources. The [[dictatorship of the proletariat]] or [[workers' state]] are terms used by Marxists to describe what they see as a temporary state between the [[Capitalism|capitalist]] and [[Communism|communist]] society. Marx defined the proletariat as salaried workers, in contrast to the [[lumpen proletariat]], who he defined as the poorest and outcasts of society, such as beggars, tricksters, entertainers, buskers, criminals and prostitutes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9049344/Lumpenproletariat Lumpen proletariat -- Britannica Online Encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt; The political relevance of farmers has divided the left. In ''[[Das Kapital]]'', Marx scarcely mentioned the subject.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,939251-2,00.html Marxism Fails on the Farm]&lt;/ref&gt; By contrast, [[Mao Zedong]] believed that the proletariat revolution would be run by rural peasants rather than urban workers after the [[Chinese civil war]].

[[Left-libertarian]]s, [[Libertarian socialist]]s and left-wing anarchists believe in a decentralized economy run by [[trade union]]s, [[workers' council]]s, [[cooperative]]s, [[Municipality|municipalities]] and [[Commune (socialism)|communes]], and oppose both government and [[Private property|private]] control of the economy.

===Nationalism===
{{See also|Left-wing nationalism}}
The question of [[nationality]] and [[nationalism]] has been a central feature of political debates on the Left.  During the French Revolution, nationalism was a policy of the Republicans, who were left-wing.&lt;ref&gt;William Doyle, ''The Oxford History of the French Revolution'', Oxford University Press, 2003, ISBN 9780199252985, "An exuberant, uncompromising nationalism lay behind France's revolutionary expansion in the 1790s...", "The message of the French Revolution was that the people are sovereign; and in the two centuries since it was first proclaimed it has conquered the world."&lt;/ref&gt; The Republican Left endorsed [[civic nationalism]]&lt;ref name="Knapp"/&gt;, which defined the nation as a "daily plebiscite" and as formed by the subjective "will to live together."  Related to "revanchism", the belligerent will to take revenge against Germany and retake control of [[Alsace-Lorraine]], nationalism could then be sometimes opposed to [[imperialism]].  In the 1880s, a debate thus pit those who opposed the "[[French colonial empire|colonial lobby]]", such as [[Georges Clemenceau]] (Radical), who declared that colonialism diverted France from the "blue line of the [[Vosges mountains|Vosges]]" (referring to Alsace-Lorraine), [[Jean Jaurès]] (Socialist) and [[Maurice Barrès]] (nationalist), against Jules Ferry (moderate republican), Léon Gambetta (republican) and [[Eugène Etienne]], the president of the parliamentary colonial group.  After the [[Dreyfus Affair]], nationalism became a main trait of the right-wing and, moreover, of the far right.&lt;ref&gt; [[Michel Winock|Winock, Michel]] (dir.), ''Histoire de l'extrême droite en France'' (1993)&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Marxism|Marxist]] [[social class]] theory of [[proletarian internationalism]] asserts that members of the [[working class]] should act in solidarity with working people in other countries due to common [[class interest]], rather than only focusing on their own countries. Proletarian internationalism is summed up in the slogan, "[[Workers of all countries, unite!]]", the last line of ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]''. Union members learned that more members meant more bargaining power, and taken to an international level, leftists argued that workers ought to act in solidarity to further increase the power of the working class. Proletarian internationalism saw itself as a deterrent against war, because people with a common interest are less likely to take up arms against one another, instead focusing on fighting the [[ruling class]]. According to Marxist theory, the [[antonym]] of proletarian internationalism is [[bourgeois nationalism]]. Marxists and others on the left see [[nationalism]],&lt;ref&gt;Szporluk, Roman. Communism and Nationalism. 2nd. Oxford University Press, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; [[racism]]&lt;ref&gt;Marxism, Racism, and Ethnicity
SOLOMOS and BACK American Behavioral Scientist.1995; 38: 407-420&lt;/ref&gt; (including [[anti-Semitism]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  |last=Lenin |first=Vladimir |title=Anti-Jewish Pogroms |work=Speeches On Gramophone Records |publisher= |year=1919 |url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1919/mar/x10.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;) and [[religion]] as [[Divide and rule|divide and conquer]] strategies used by the ruling classes to prevent the [[working class]] from uniting against them.  Left-wing movements therefore have often taken up [[anti-imperialism|anti-imperialist]] positions.

The failure of coups in [[German Revolution|Germany]] and [[Hungarian Soviet Republic|Hungary]], ended [[Bolshevik]] hopes for an imminent [[world revolution]] and led to promotion of "[[Socialism in One Country]]" by [[Joseph Stalin]]. In the first edition of the book ''Osnovy Leninizma'' (''Foundations of Leninism'', 1924), Stalin argued that revolution in one country is insufficient. But by the end of that year, in the second edition of the book, he argued that the "[[proletariat]] can and must build the socialist society in one country". In April 1925 [[Nikolai Bukharin]] elaborated the issue in his brochure ''Can We Build Socialism in One Country in the Absence of the Victory of the West-European Proletariat?'' The position was adopted as the state policy after Stalin's January 1926 article ''On the Issues of Leninism'' (К вопросам ленинизма). This idea was opposed by [[Leon Trotsky]] and his followers who still declared the need for an international "[[permanent revolution]]". Various Fourth Internationalist groups around the world continue to describe themselves as Trotskyist and see themselves as standing in this tradition while [[Maoist China]] supported Socialism in One Country.

Some link [[left-wing nationalism]] to the pressure generated by economic integration with other countries encouraged by [[free-trade]] agreements. This view is sometimes used to justify hostility towards [[Supranational union|supranational organizations]] such as the [[European Union]]. Left-wing nationalism can also refer to any nationalism which emphasises a working-class populist agenda which seeks to overcome perceived exploitation or oppression by other nations. Many [[Third World]] anti-colonial movements adopted left-wing and socialist ideas.

===Social progressivism and counterculture===
[[Social progressivism]] is another common feature of the modern Left, particularly in the United States, where social progressives played an important role in the [[abolition of slavery]]&lt;ref&gt;James Brewer Stewrt, ''Abolitionist Politics and the Coming of the Civil War'', University of Massachusetts Press, 2008, ISBN 9781558496354.  "...the progressive assumptions of 'uplift'." (page 40)&lt;/ref&gt;, [[women's suffrage]],&lt;ref&gt;http://lcweb2.loc.gov/learn/features/timeline/progress/suffrage/suffrage.html&lt;/ref&gt; [[civil rights]], and [[multiculturalism]]. Progressives have both advocated [[prohibition]] legislation and worked towards its repeal.  Current positions associated with social progressivism in [[Western world|the West]] include opposition to the death penalty, and support for legal recognition of [[same-sex marriage]], distribution of [[contraceptives]], public funding of embryonic [[stem-cell research]], and the right of women to choose [[abortion]].  Public education is a subject of great interest to social progressives, who support comprehensive [[sex education]], and making condoms available to high school students. 

Various [[counterculture]] movements in the 1960s and 1970s were associated with the "[[New Left]]". Unlike the earlier leftist focus on [[labour movement|union]] activism, the "New Left" instead adopted a broader definition of political activism commonly called [[social activism]]. U.S. "New Left" is associated with the [[Hippie|Hippie movement]], college campus mass protest movements and a broadening of focus from protesting [[social class|class]]-based oppression to include issues such as [[gender]], [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], and [[sexual orientation]]. The British "New Left" was an intellectually driven movement which attempted to correct the perceived errors of "[[Old Left]]". The New Left opposed the prevailing authority structures in society, which it termed "The Establishment", and those who rejected this authority became known as "anti-Establishment."  The New Left did not seek to recruit industrial workers, but rather concentrated on a [[social activist]] approach to organization. Many in the New Left were convinced that they could be the source for a better kind of [[social revolution]]. This view has been criticised by some [[Marxists]] (especially [[Trotskyites]]) who characterized this approach as 'substitutionism'- or what they saw as the misguided and apparently non-Marxist belief that other groups in society could 'substitute' for the revolutionary agency of the working class.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marxists.org/archive/cliff/works/1960/xx/trotsub.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.scribd.com/doc/4662049/Against-Substitutionism&lt;/ref&gt;

Many early [[Feminism|feminists]] and advocates of [[women's rights]] were considered politically [[Radicalization|radical]] left-wing by their contemporaries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gla.ac.uk/centres/tltphistory/training/advanced/custom/coredocs/coredoc2.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Feminist pioneers such as [[Mary Wollstonecraft]] were influenced by radical thinkers such as [[Thomas Paine]]. Many notable leftists have been claimed as influence in feminism, such as: Marxists [[Clara Zetkin]] and [[Alexandra Kollontai]], [[Helen Keller]], anarchist [[Emma Goldman]] and [[Annie Besant]], who was involved in various socialist groups.&lt;ref&gt;groups.http://www.feministsforlife.org/history/foremoth.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thomaspaine.org/Archives/occ.html&lt;/ref&gt; However, the classical Marxists such as Clara Zetkin&lt;ref&gt;Zetkin, Clara [http://www.marxists.org/archive/draper/1976/women/3-zetkin.html On a Bourgeois Feminist Petition] 1895&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zetkin, Clara [http://www.marxists.org/archive/zetkin/1920/lenin/zetkin1.htm Lenin on the Women’s Question]&lt;/ref&gt; and Alexandra Kollontai &lt;ref&gt;Kollontai, Alexandra [http://www.marxists.org/archive/kollonta/1909/social-basis.htm The Social Basis of the Woman Question] 1909&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kollontai, Alexandra [http://www.marxists.org/archive/kollonta/1919/women-workers/ch01.htm Women Workers Struggle For Their Rights] 1919&lt;/ref&gt;, though foremost supporters of radical social equality for women, were against feminism as a bourgeois ideology.

In more recent times the [[women's liberation movement]] is closely connected to the New Left and other [[new social movements]] that challenged the orthodoxies of the Old Left. [[Socialist feminism]] (e.g.[[Freedom Socialist Party]], [[Radical Women]]) and [[Marxist feminism]] (e.g. [[Selma James]]) saw themselves as a part of the left that challenged what they perceive to be male-dominated and [[sexist]] structures within the left. [[Liberal feminism]] is closely connected with [[Social liberalism|left-liberalism]], and the left-wing of mainstream American politics. (e.g. the [[National Organization for Women]]). [[Radical feminism]] (e.g. [[Mary Daly]]) is harder to place on a left-right spectrum; it has more in common with [[deep ecology]], which rejects this axis.

===Religion===
The Left has had a complex relationship with religion. The original French left-wing was [[anti-clerical]] and opposed the influence of the [[Roman Catholic Church]] while supporting [[separation of church and state]].&lt;ref name="Knapp"/&gt; [[Karl Marx]] was critical of institutionalized religion, saying "Religion is the sigh of the oppressed creature, the heart of a heartless world, and the soul of soulless conditions. It is the [[opium of the people]]."&lt;ref&gt;Marx, K. 1976. ''Introduction to A Contribution to the Critique of Hegel’s Philosophy of Right''. Collected Works, v. 3. New York.&lt;/ref&gt; In Soviet Russia the [[Bolshevik]]s originally embraced "an ideological creed which professed that all religion would atrophy" and "resolved to eradicate [[Christianity]] as such." In 1918 "ten [[Russian Orthodox|Orthodox]] hierarchs were summarily shot" and "children were deprived of any religious education outside the home."&lt;ref&gt;[[Michael Burleigh]] ''Sacred Causes'' HarperCollins (2006) p41-43&lt;/ref&gt; Later communist governments, such as the [[People's Republic of China]], have also been hostile to religion and have promoted [[atheism]].

However, religious beliefs have been associated with some left-wing movements, such as the American [[Abolitionism|abolitionist]] movement and the anti-[[capital punishment]] movement. [[Liberation theology]] is a mixing of left-wing politics and [[Christian theology]] and has Marxist origins. The terms [[religious socialism]] and [[religious communism]] refer to a number of egalitarian and [[utopia]]n religious societies practicing the voluntary dissolution of private property, so that society's benefits are distributed according to a person's needs, and every person performs labor according to their abilities.

Recently, the relationship between the Left and [[Islam]] has been a controversial issue.  Many on the Left support the [[Palestinian people|Palestinian]] liberation movement, but some [[liberal hawks]], including [[Christopher Hitchens]], see Islam as [[reactionary]], especially in its treatment of women.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.workersliberty.org/story/2008/09/08/political-islam-clerical-fascism&lt;/ref&gt;  There have been alliances between the Left and anti-war [[Muslim]]s, such as in [[Respect – The Unity Coalition]] and the [[Stop the War Coalition]] in Britain. In France, the Left has been divided over moves to ban the [[hijab]] from schools, with some supporting a ban based on separation of church and state, and others opposing the ban based on personal freedom.  This subject was the source of some debate within the [[Revolutionary Communist League (France)|Revolutionary Communist League]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.isj.org.uk/index.php4?id=45&lt;/ref&gt; There are some left-wing Islamic movements such as [[Islamic socialism]].

===The environment===
{{Main|Green politics}}

Environmental degradation can be seen as a class or equity issue as environmental destruction disproportionately affects poorer communities and countries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.blacksmithinstitute.org/articles/file/The+Argentimes.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Soviet Union and the People's Republic of China, in their drive to compete economically and militarily with the West, have caused significant environmental degradation; examples include the [[Chernobyl disaster]], and the drying of the [[Aral Sea]] and [[Lop Nor]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hc.ceu.hu/envsci/aleg/research/EnvDegradationEastEurope090903.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been alliances between left-wing trade unions and environmentalists over development issues, such as the [[Green Bans]] movement during the 1970s in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Meredith Burgman, Green Bans, Red Union: Environmental Activism and the New South Wales Builders Labourers' Federation (UNSW Press, Sydney,1998)&lt;/ref&gt; In Europe, some 'Green-Left' political parties exist which combine traditional social-democratic values such as greater economic equality with demands for environmental protection, such as the [[Nordic Green Left]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nordic-green-left-alliance.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 21st Century, questions about the environment have become increasingly politicized in the United States, with the Left generally accepting the findings of environmental scientists about [[global warming]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.usnews.com/blogs/barone/2009/03/16/the-left-pushes-secular-religions-global-warming-embryonic-stem-cell-research.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://dieoff.org/page8.htm&lt;/ref&gt; , and many on the Right disputing those findings.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/13/science/earth/13book.html, "Challenges to both Left and Right on Global Warming", by Andrew C. Revkin, Nov. 13, 2007, "The right says global warming is somewhere between a hoax and a minor irritant, and argues that liberals’ thirst for top-down regulations will drive American wealth to developing countries and turn off the fossil-fueled engine powering the economy."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/01/29/weather-channel-founder-blasts-gore-global-warming-campaign/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chris Mooney, ''The Republican War on Science'', "the modern Right has adopted a style of politics that puts its adherents in increasingly stark conflict with both scientific information and dispassionate, expert analysis in general.", p. 4-5, "...the Right's selective attack on Mann's work ultimately presents a huge diversion for policymakers trying to decide what to do about global warming." p. 89, Basic Books, 2006, ISBN 9780465046768&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-globalization and Third-worldism===
The [[Global Justice Movement]], also known as the [[anti-globalisation]] or [[alter-globalization]] movement, protests against global trade agreements and the negative consequences they perceive them to have for the poor and the environment. This movement is generally characterised as left-wing, though some activists within it reject association with the traditional left.  There are also those on the right, [[Pat Buchanan]] for example, who oppose globalization on nationalistic grounds.  The Global Justice Movement does not oppose globalisation per se, on the contrary, it supports some forms of [[Internationalism (politics)|internationalism]]. The main themes of the movement are the reforms (or abolition) of international institutions such as the [[World Bank]] and the [[International Monetary Fund]], and the creation of an international social and environmental justice movement. It rejects the leadership of any [[political party]], defining itself as a "movement of movements."

[[Third-worldism]] regards the inequality between developed, or [[First World]] countries, and the developing, or [[Third World]] countries as of key political importance.  It supports [[national liberation movements]] against what it takes to be [[imperialism]] by capitalist nations. Key figures associated with Third-worldism include [[Frantz Fanon]], [[Ahmed Ben Bella]], [[Andre Gunder Frank]], [[Samir Amin]] and [[Simon Malley]]. Among the [[New Left]] groups associated with Third Worldism were [[Monthly Review]] and the [[New Communist Movement]].

Third worldism is closely connected with [[Pan-Africanism]], [[Pan-Arabism]], [[Maoism]], [[African socialism]] and [[Socialism|Latin American socialist trends]]. The [[Palestine Liberation Organization]] and the [[Sandinistas]] are or have been particular ''causes célèbres''. Some left-wing groups in the developing world, such as the [[Zapatista Army of National Liberation]] in Mexico, the [[Abahlali baseMjondolo]] in [[South Africa]], and the [[Naxalites]] in India, argue that the First-World left takes a racist and paternalistic attitude towards liberation movements in the Third-World. There is particular criticism of the role played by [[NGOs]] and the assumption by the Western Anti-globalization movement that they should seek to influence the politics of the Third World.

===Post-modernism===
Left-wing [[postmodernism]] opposes attempts to supply universal explanatory theories, including Marxism, deriding them as [[Meta-narrative|grand narratives]]. It views culture as a battleground, and via [[deconstruction]] seeks to undermine all pretensions to knowledge. Left-wing critics of post-modernism assert that [[cultural studies]] inflates the importance of culture by denying the existence of an independent reality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.isj.org.uk/index.php4?id=59issue=105 Post-modernism, commodity fetishism and hegemony], Néstor Kohan, [[International Socialism (journal)|International Socialism]], Issue 105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://cscs.umich.edu/~crshalizi/chomsky-on-postmodernism.html Chomsky on Postmodernism], [[Noam Chomsky]], [[Z Communications|Z-Magazine's]] Left On-Line Bulletin Board.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996, [[physicist]] [[Alan Sokal]] wrote [[Sokal Affair|a nonsensical article]] entitled "Transgressing the Boundaries: Toward a Transformative Hermeneutics of Quantum Gravity".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.physics.nyu.edu/~as2/transgress_v2/transgress_v2_singlefile.html Transgressing the Boundaries: Towards a Transformative Hermeneutics of Quantum Gravity], [[Alan Sokal]], first published in; [[Social Text]], issue 46/47, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; The journal ''Social Text'' published the paper in its Spring/Summer 1996 issue, whereupon Sokal publicly revealed his hoax. While this action was interpreted as an attack upon leftism, Sokal intended it as a critique from within.
&lt;ref name="physics.nyu.edu"&gt;[http://www.physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/lingua_franca_v4/lingua_franca_v4.html A Physicist Experiments With Cultural Studies], [[Alan Sokal]]&lt;/ref&gt; He said he was concerned about what he saw as the increasing prevalence on the Left of "a particular kind of nonsense and sloppy thinking... that denies the existence of objective realities".&lt;ref name="physics.nyu.edu"/&gt;

Gary Jason, a philosophy professor, claims that "the failure of socialism, both empirically and theoretically...brought about a crisis of faith among socialists, and Post-modernism is their response."&lt;ref&gt;[http://libertyunbound.com/archive/2005_06/jason-pomo.html Socialism's Last Bastion], Gary Jason, Liberty&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Wiktionary|leftism}}
* [[Ideology]]
* [[List of left-wing internationals]]
* [[Post-left anarchy]]
* [[Right-wing politics]]
* [[Social criticism]]

==External links==
* [http://www.broadleft.org/index.htm Leftist Parties of the World]
* [http://www.governingdynamo.com/blog/2009/8/1/left-wing-and-right-wing-politics-where-are-you.html Brief article on left wing and right wing politics &amp; links to political orientation tests]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* ''Encyclopedia of the American Left'', ed. by Mari Jo Buhle, Paul Buhle, Dan Georgakas, Second Edition, Oxford University Press 1998, ISBN 0-19-512088-4
* Lin Chun, ''The British New Left'', Edinburgh : Edinburgh Univ. Press, 1993
* Geoff Eley, ''Forging Democracy: The History of the Left in Europe, 1850-2000'', Oxford University Press 2002, ISBN 0-19-504479-7
* "Leftism in India, 1917-1947", [[Satyabrata Rai Chowdhuri]], Palgrave Macmillan, UK, 2007, ISBN 9780230517165

{{DEFAULTSORT:Left-Wing Politics}}
[[Category:Left-wing politics| ]]
[[Category:Political spectrum]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]

[[ar:يسارية]]
[[zh-min-nan:Chó-phài]]
[[ca:Esquerra]]
[[cs:Levice]]
[[da:Venstreorienteret]]
[[de:Politische Linke]]
[[et:Vasakpoolsus]]
[[el:Αριστερά (πολιτική)]]
[[es:Izquierda política]]
[[eo:Politika maldekstro]]
[[fa:چپ (گرایش سیاسی)]]
[[fr:Gauche (politique)]]
[[gl:Esquerda política]]
[[ko:좌익]]
[[id:Sayap kiri]]
[[is:Vinstristefna]]
[[it:Sinistra (politica)]]
[[lv:Kreisa politika]]
[[lt:Kairė (politikoje)]]
[[hu:Baloldal]]
[[mk:Политичка левица]]
[[ms:Politik haluan kiri]]
[[nl:Links (politiek)]]
[[ja:左翼]]
[[no:Venstresiden]]
[[nn:Venstresida]]
[[pl:Lewica]]
[[pt:Esquerda política]]
[[ru:Левые (политика)]]
[[simple:Left-wing]]
[[sk:Ľavica (politika)]]
[[sr:Левица]]
[[fi:Vasemmisto]]
[[sv:Politisk vänster]]
[[tr:Solculuk]]
[[uk:Лівиця]]
[[ur:بایاں بازو]]
[[zh:左派]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>