<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041108162817|7223104" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18499" pageid="18499" ns="0" title="Left-wing politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-08T16:29:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In [[politics]], '''left-wing''', '''political left''', '''leftism''', or simply '''the left''', are terms which refer (with no particular precision) to the segment of the [[political spectrum]] typically associated with any of several strains of [[socialism]], [[social democrat|social democracy]], or [[liberalism]] (especially in the [[United States|American]] sense of the word), or with opposition to [[right-wing politics]]. [[Communism]] (as well as the [[Marxist]] philosophy that it relies on) and [[anarchism]] are considered to be radical forms of left-wing politics.
(See [[political spectrum]] and [[left-right politics]] for more on the merits/limitations of this kind of classification.) The terminology of left-right politics was originally based on the seating-arrangement of parliamentary partisans during the [[French Revolution]]. The more ardent proponents of radical revolutionary measures (including [[democracy]] and [[republicanism]]) were commonly referred to as leftists because they sat on the left side of successive legislative assemblies. As this original reference became obsolete, the meaning of the terms has changed as appropriate to the spectrum of ideas and stances being compared. 

The term is also often used to characterize the politics of the [[Soviet Union]] and other one-party "[[communist state]]s", although many (perhaps most) on the political left (including many Marxists) would not consider their own politics to have anything significant in common with any of these states.

==Left-wing issues==
[[Equality]], [[social justice]], labor rights and trade unionism, concern for the poor, working-class solidarity and [[internationalism]] are the values typically associated with the left wing of the political spectrum. The left is against hierarchy and authority, strict adherence to tradition, monoculturalism, privilege for the wealthy, and other values commonly associated with the political [[right-wing politics|right]]. Those on the left are sometimes called "[[Progressivism|progressive]]", a term that arose from their self-identification as the side of (social) "progress".

==History of the term==
The term "Left" was first used in the early days of French revolution. When the [[National Assembly]] first met, the reformers set on the left side of the meeting hall, while supporters of monarchy and nobility sat on the right. Originally, it wasn't meant to be a political statement, but as the factions within the National Assembly formed, the label stuck. 

Although it may seem ironic in terms of present-day usage, the original "leftists" during the [[French Revolution]] were the largely [[bourgeois]] supporters of [[laissez-faire capitalism]] and [[free market]]s. As the [[electorate]] expanded beyond property-holders, these relatively wealthy elites found themselves clearly victorious over the old [[aristocracy]] and the remnants of [[feudalism]], but newly opposed by the growing and increasingly organized and politicized workers and wage-earners. The "left" of [[1789]] would, in some ways be part of the present-day "right", [[liberal]] with regard to the rights of property and intellect, but not embracing notions of [[distributive justice]], rights for [[organized labor]], etc.

The European left has traditionally shown a smooth continuum between non-communist and communist parties (including such hybrids as [[eurocommunism]]), which have sometimes allied with more moderate leftists to present a [[united front]]. In the [[United States]], however, no avowedly socialist or communist party ever became a major player in national politics, although the [[Social Democratic Party (USA)|Social Democratic Party]] of [[Eugene V. Debs]] and its successor [[Socialist Party of America]] (in the late nineteenth and early twentieth century) and the [[Communist Party USA|Communist Party of the United States of America]] (in the [[1930s]]) made some inroads. While many American "liberals" would be "social democrats" in European terms, very few of them openly embrace the term "left"; in America, the term is mainly embraced by [[New Left]] activists, certain portions of the [[labor union|labor]] movement, and people who see their intellectual or political heritage as descending from 19th-century socialist movements.

The "[[New Left]]" has had varying degrees of unity since its rise in the 1960s, and can be seen as a [[coalition]] of numerous distinct movements, including (but not limited to) [[feminism|feminists]], [[greens]], some [[labor union]]s, some [[atheism|atheists]], some [[gay rights]] activists, and some minority ethnic and racially oriented [[civil rights]] groups. Many Greens deny that [[green politics]] is "on the left"; nonetheless, their economic policies can generally be considered left-wing, and when they have formed political coalitions (most notably in [[Germany]], but also in local governments elsewhere), it has almost always been with groups that would generally be classified as being on the left.

==Leftism and the Soviet Union==
Much as [[fascism]] is generally included in "the right", despite important differences from other rightists, Soviet-style [[communist state|state communism]] is generally included in "the left", despite important differences from other leftists. Some argue that (in spite of its use of socialist rhetoric), Soviet-style communism should be viewed independently of the conventional left-right spectrum: this case has, perhaps, been made most eloquently by [[Karl Popper]], through his development of the concept of [[totalitarianism]]. Critics of [[democratic socialism]] or of left-liberalism have often used the association of communism with Soviet-style politics to tar the political left with the perceived crimes of [[Stalinism]], but these accusations are usually little more than rhetorical devices (similar to the ones used by some critics of [[conservativism]] or other right-wing ideologies in associating the political right with fascism).

In the days of the Soviet Union, leftist movements worldwide had different relationships with Moscow-line communist parties, ranging from enthusiastic support to outright opposition. Even today, some parts of the radical left extol all or some aspects of Soviet-style communism or that of [[Maoism|Maoist]] [[China]], while others loath the perceived crimes of those regimes and denounce them at every turn. For example, most [[Trotskyism|Trotskyists]] adhere to some variant of [[Leon Trotsky]]'s view of the post-[[Lenin]] Soviet Union as a "[[degenerated workers' state]]" and denounce [[Stalin]] as a traitor, while the [[Revolutionary Communist Party, USA]] takes the opposite view and continues to praise the [[Chinese Cultural Revolution]].

Some critics of the left claim that leftist movements lost their moorings &amp;ndash; or their rationale &amp;ndash; after the collapse of the European communist states (beginning in [[1989]] and ending with the fall of the Soviet Union in [[1991]]). However, large segments of the left never took inspiration from the Soviet model and actually rejoiced to see the USSR's system collapse -- as [[Michael Albert]] of ''[[Z Magazine]]'' put it, "one down, one to go" (referring to [[Stalinism]] and [[capitalism]]).

==Leftism and postmodernism==
A few self-described leftists also subscribe to [[postmodernism]], including [[deconstructionism]], a philosophical point of view that claims that every text "contains the allegory of its own deconstruction" and thereby questions the possibility of rational discourse. (Most postmodernists see themselves as leftists, but most leftists are not postmodernists.) Critics on the right have generally seen this as an indication of the poorly thought-out, fashionable nature of academic leftism. However, there are many on the left who say that postmodernism makes no sense and offers no useful political lessons.

Some critics of the left also suggest that deconstructionism is not the only [[Friedrich Nietzsche|Nietzschean]] element in contemporary leftism, pointing to older, mistaken interpretations of Nietzsche as the font of [[moral relativism]] and the "[[God is dead]]" philosophy, both of which they see as characterizing the perceived [[nihilism]] of modern leftist politics. On the other hand, most leftists consider such accusations to be completely baseless and incorrect; this is especially true of religious leftists, many of whom hold the ideas of moral relativism and nihilism in less than low regard.

==Leftism and Neo-leftism in China==
The [[1949]] victory of the [[Chinese Revolution]] brought to power the then ultra-leftist [[Chinese Communist Party]] of [[Mao Zedong]], who, over the next quarter of a century attempted the radical transformation of society through the [[Great Leap Forward]] and the [[Chinese Cultural Revolution]]. After Mao's death, it became the conventional wisdom among China's leadership that these attempts had been a disaster. Although it has retained its name, the Chinese Communist Party today has abandoned Communism in its economic policies, pursuing instead an agenda of economic [[liberalization]], beginning in the 1980s with the [[Four Modernizations]] of [[Deng Xiaoping]]. The Chinese government, however, has remained rigidly [[authoritarian]]; socially and politically, it is still commonly viewed as repressive, though far less so than in Mao's time. Most leading Chinese dissidents are political and social liberals.
    
In contrast both to the government and the liberal dissidents, Chinese [[neo-leftism]], embracing [[postmodernism]] and [[Chinese nationalism]], and opposed both to democracy and to what they see as a return of China to the capitalist world, arose as a political idea during the mid-[[1990s]]. Neo-leftism is seen as being more appealing to students in China today than liberalism, as problems faced by China during its [[modernisation]] such as inequality and the widening gap between the rich and the poor are becoming more serious. 

==Leftism, Pacifism and "War on Terror"==
''See main article [[Post-September 11 anti-war movement]]''

After the [[September 11 terrorist attacks]], the immediate, worldwide reaction was widely described as "shock". [http://www.cnn.com/2001/WORLD/europe/09/11/trade.centre.reaction/], [http://www.tgorski.com/Terrorism/Psychological%20Shock%20Of%20September%2011%20-%20PEWS%20Research%20Report.htm] [http://www.guardian.co.uk/worldlatest/story/0,1280,-4339991,00.html] No national government claimed connection to the attacks and the governments most associated with [[Islamism]] sought to distance themselves from the attacks. [http://www.cnn.com/2001/WORLD/europe/09/11/trade.centre.reaction/] [http://groups.colgate.edu/aarislam/response.htm][http://www.september11news.com/InternationalReaction.htm] 
On the left, condemnation of the attacks was equally general, although often including (even in the days immediately after the attack) condemnation of ostensibly related aspects of U.S. policies [http://www.zmag.org/prashadcalam.htm] [http://www.guardian.co.uk/wtccrash/story/0,1300,550464,00.html] [http://www.zmag.org/chomnote.htm] U.S. elected officials generally identified as being on the left also joined in strongly condemning the attacks, without even choosing to point out a context. [http://kennedy.senate.gov/~kennedy/statements/01/09/2001913535.html] Three days after the attacks, Congress passed a resolution authorizing President Bush to use force against "those responsible". The Senate voted 98-0, the House 420-1, with only [[Barbara Lee]] (D-California) dissenting. [http://www.cnn.com/2001/US/09/14/congress.terrorism/], [http://www.daveyd.com/barbaraleevotepolitics.html]

===An anti-war movement forms===
''See main article [[Post-September_11_anti-war_movement#An_anti-war_movement_forms|Post-September 11 anti-war movement (section)]]''

Within days of the September 11 events, [[Responsibility for the September 11, 2001 attacks|it was widely (though not universally) agreed]] that [[Organizers of the September 11, 2001 attacks|the attacks were carried out by al-Qaida]]. [[September_11%2C_2001_attacks#Arab_and_Muslim_denials_of_Responsibility|Many Muslims]] though less so among Muslims in the U.S. [http://www.cnn.com/2002/US/02/26/gallup.muslims] [http://www.hamilton.edu/news/muslimamerica/summary.html], along with a small segment of the left [[9/11 domestic conspiracy theory|placed the blame elsewhere]]. A much larger minority of the left concurred with the clear majority of Muslims that a military attack on Afghanistan was not the correct answer to the September 11 events, a view even more widespread with respect to the [[2003 invasion of Iraq|later attack on Iraq]].

Within weeks, it became clear that Bush intended a set of changes to U.S. [[criminal law]] and [[immigration law]] and an [[History_of_Afghanistan_since_1992#U.S._invasion_of_Afghanistan| invasion of Afghanistan]]. The left was somewhat fragmented with respect to the invasion of Afghanistan. [http://csf.colorado.edu/mail/pfvs/2001III/msg01707.html] [http://website.lineone.net/~jon.simmons/roy/010929ij.htm]
[http://www.muhajabah.com/muslims4kucinich/archives/007435.php] Nonetheless, an international anti-war movement began to arise; in the U.S. and other countries whose governments enacted legislation analogous to the [[PATRIOT Act]], it was equally a movement in protest of what were perceived on the left to be assaults on civil liberties and immigrant rights. 

Most prominent in this loose coalition were leftists; [[pacifism|pacifists]] and others with longtime associations with global [[peace movement]]s; and Arabs and Muslims, including, but by no means limited to, Islamists. The predominant arguments against the Afghanistan invasion and the subsequent invasion of Iraq were on the grounds of [[pacifism]], [[international law]], opposition to perceived U.S. [[imperialism]]; disbelief in the sincerity of the U.S.'s stated war aims, belief that the wars were motivated by [[neocolonialism]] and [[oil imperialism theories|petroleum politics]]; that war would bring unnecessary suffering on the people of Afghanistan and that it was not the most effective way to dislodge or isolate al-Qaida; and, in a few cases, denial of al-Qaida's responsibility for the September 11 attacks. 

Many Islamists and Arabs, and a few leftists, saw the military campaigns as battles in a religious war -- a [[crusade]] -- against Islam. This was the obverse of the ideas expressed, for example, by [[Samuel P. Huntington]] in [[Clash of civilizations|''The Clash of Civilizations and the Remaking of World Order'']].

===Left and anti-war in the U.S. ===
''See main article [[Post-September 11 anti-war movement#Left and anti-war in the U.S.|Post-September 11 anti-war movement (section)]]''

The most prominent U.S.-based movement groups are [[ANSWER|Act Now to Stop War and End Violence (ANSWER)]] , [[Not in Our Name|Not in Our Name (NION)]], and [[United for Peace and Justice|United for Peace and Justice (UFPJ)]]. ANSWER and (to a lesser degree) NION have been targets of much criticism from within the left [http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?SectionID=15&amp;ItemID=2527] for their respective associations with the [[Workers World Party]] [http://www.why-war.com/encyclopedia/people/Ramsey_Clark/] [http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=3181] and the [[Revolutionary Communist Party (USA)|Revolutionary Communist Party]]. Right-wing critics have also siezed on these relationships, pointing at them to claim that these small parties "dominate" the anti-war movement.[http://www.worldnetdaily.com/news/article.asp?ARTICLE_ID=29524] Critics of ANSWER and NION from within the anti-war movement (such as [[Michael Albert]] and [[Stephen R. Shalom]] writing in ''[[Z magazine|Z]]'') generally urged support for these groups' rallies, depite their qualms, arguing that most people at a "...demonstration will in fact be unaware of exactly who said what and whether any particular speaker omitted this or that point. What they will experience will be a powerful antiwar protest. And most of the public will see it that way too." [http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?SectionID=15&amp;ItemID=2527]

The groups have collaborated at times on events, although collaboration has not always been easy. In perhaps [[ANSWER#The_Lerner_incident|the most infamous incident]], [[Michael Lerner (rabbi)|Rabbi Michael Lerner]] was banned from speaking at a [[February 16]], 2003 anti-war rally in [[San Francisco]], less than a month before the U.S. invaded Iraq. It was generally believed that this was done at ANSWER's behest, because Lerner had been critical of what he perceives as ANSWER's anti-[[Israel]] politics. Lerner, though irked that NION and UFPJ did not stand up for his inclusion as a speaker, continued to encourage people to attend the rally. 
[http://www.tikkun.org/magazine/index.cfm/action/tikkun/issue/tik0305/article/030512a.html], [http://www.commondreams.org/views03/0211-06.htm]

===Left and anti-war in Europe===
''See main article [[Post-September 11 anti-war movement#Left and anti-war in Europe|Post-September 11 anti-war movement (section)]]''

[[Popular opposition to war on Iraq]] in [[Europe]] climaxed in an international sychronized anti-war demonstration around the world on [[Global_protests_against_war_on_Iraq_%28pre-war%29#February_15.2C_2003_protests|February 15, 2003]]. Strong [[anti-American]] sentiments were expressed at most of these anti-war protests. 

Many European countries have large and growing [[Muslims in Europe|Muslim minorities]]. In some groups, such as the British [[Stop the War Coalition]], Muslims have taken leading positions. However, the presence of extremists and alleged [[Islamist]]s[http://www.geocities.com/emorseraf/the_london_streets.htm], as well as many anti-Israeli slogans, have caused that these anti-war rallies have been seen by some commentators to have been "hijacked" by them to become anti-Israeli, [[anti-Zionist]] and anti-Western events. In one case [http://www.jewishsf.com/bk030404/iwar20.shtml], the inflammatory atmosphere led to a serious case of violence against two [[Jewish]] teenagers. [[Aurélie Filipetti]], a spokeswoman of the [[Green Party]] in Paris, criticized some of her fellow French left-wingers for creating an anti-Israeli atmosphere which encourages [[antisemitism]].[http://www.nrg.co.il/online/archive/ART/466/162.html] (in [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]], partially translated at [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Left-wing_politics/Archive3]) Other Jewish leftists have also been critical that the European left is tolerant of antisemitism when it comes from the "oppressed world" of the [[Arab]]s. [http://www.nrg.co.il/online/1/ART/768/168.html]
These accusations have generated great controversy, particularly because they come from within the Left itself.

=== Islamist allies? ===
''See main article [[Post-September_11_anti-war_movement#Criticism_of_the_anti-war_movement|Post-September 11 anti-war movement (section)]]''

Exiled [[Iran]]ian writer [[Amir Taheri]], goes much further, viewing portions of the anti-war movement in Western Europe as "an alliance between the radical Left and hard-line Islamists... built around three themes: hatred of the United States, the dream of wiping Israel off the map, and the hoped-for collapse of the global economic system."  [http://www.benadorassociates.com/article/5163], [http://www.geocities.com/emorseraf/the_london_streets.htm] 
Taheri clearly views this alliance with Islamists as compromising traditional [[humanism|humanist]] values of the left and all "leftist" values in general; he clearly implies that this coalition could go on to embrace terrorism. 

While many leftists have happily worked with ''Arab'' or ''Muslim'' groups in opposition to perceived U.S. or Israeli imperialism, alliances between leftists and ''Islamists'' are relatively unusual. More typical examples of leftists working in anti-war coalitions with Muslims would be the membership of American Muslims for Jerusalem in UFPJ or of the Muslim Student Association, American Muslims for Global Peace, and Atlanta Masjid of Al-Islam in ANSWER. These are Muslim groups, but they are not Islamist groups.

==Political parties on the left== 
One might normally characterize the following parties as on the political left in their respective countries, though they might have relatively little in common with other left-wing groups beyond their opposition to the right.

Naturally, in all cases "left" and "right" are relative. For example, the [[Democratic Leadership Council]] (in which [[Bill Clinton]] was active) is generally considered to form the right wing of the U.S. [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic Party]], but in terms of the whole country he was generally perceived as being on the moderate left.

===Australia===
* [[Australian Greens]]
* [[Australian Labor Party]]
* [[Communist Party of Australia]]
* [[Socialist Alliance (Australia)]]
* [[Socialist Party (Australia)]]

===Belgium===
* [[Socialistische Partij - Anders|SP.A]]
* [[Socialist Party (francophone Belgium)|Parti Socialiste]]
* [[Groen!]]
* [[Ecolo|Ecolo]]
* [[Spirit|Spirit (political party)]]

===Canada=== 
* Canadian Federal Parties:
** Parties represented in the [[Canadian House of Commons]]:
*** [[Bloc Québécois]]
*** [[New Democratic Party]]
** Parties not represented in the [[Canadian House of Commons]], but registered with [[Elections Canada]]:
*** [[Canadian Action Party]]
*** [[Communist Party of Canada]]
*** [[Green Party of Canada]]
*** [[Marijuana Party of Canada]]
*** [[Marxist-Leninist Party of Canada]]
** Parties not represented in the [[Canadian House of Commons]], nor registered with [[Elections Canada]]:
*** [[Cosmopolitan Party of Canada]]
*** [[Socialist Alternative]]
*** [[Socialist Party of Canada (new)]]
* Albertan Provincial Parties:
**Parties represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Alberta New Democrats]]
**Parties not represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Alberta Greens]]
*** [[Communist Party of Canada|Communist Party of Alberta]]
* British Columbian Provincial Parties:
** Parties represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[New Democratic Party of British Columbia]]
** Parties not represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Green Party of British Columbia]]
*** [[Communist Party of BC]]
*** [[Marijuana Party of Canada|Marijuana Party of BC]]
*** [[People's Front]]
* Manitoban Provincial Parties:
** Parties represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[New Democratic Party of Manitoba]]
** Parties not represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Communist Party of Canada - Manitoba]]
*** [[Green Party of Canada|Green Party of Manitoba]]
* New Brunswick's Provincial Parties:
** Parties Represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[New Democratic Party (New Brunswick)]]
* Newfoundland and Labrador's Provincial Parties:
** Parties represented in the House of Assembly:
*** [[New Democratic Party of Newfoundland and Labrador]]
** Parties not represented in the House of Assembly:
*** [[Green Party of Canada|Newfoundland and Labrador Green Party]]
* Nova Scotian Political Parties:
** Parties represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Nova Scotia New Democratic Party]]
** Parties not represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Marijuana Party of Canada|Marijuana Party of BC]]
* Ontarian Political Parties:
** Parties represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Ontario New Democratic Party]]
** Parties not represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Communist Party of Ontario]]
*** [[Green Party of Ontario]]
* Prince Edward Island's Political Parties:
** Parties not represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Island New Democrats]]
* Quebec's Political Parties:
** Parties represented in the National Assembly:
*** [[Parti Québécois ]]
** Parties not represented in the National Assembly:
*** [[Bloc pot]]
*** [[Parti marxiste-léniniste du Québec]]
*** [[Parti vert du Québec]]
*** [[Union des Forces Progressistes]]
*** [[Gauche Socialiste]]
* Saskatchewan's Political Parties:
** Parties represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Saskatchewan New Democratic Party]]
** Parties not represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[New Green Alliance]]
* Yukon's Political Parties:
** Parties represented in the Legislative Assembly:
*** [[Yukon New Democratic Party]]

===Denmark=== 
* [[Socialistisk Folkeparti]]
* [[Enhedslisten]]
* [[Socialdemokraterne]]

===Estonia===
*[[Social Democratic Party (Estonia)]] (centre-left)
*[[Estonian Social Democratic Labour Party]] (eurocommunistic)
===Finland===
*[[Kansallinen Kokoomus|National Convention]]
*[[Suomen Sosialidemokraattinen Puolue|Finnish Social Democratic Party]]
*[[Vasemmistoliitto|Finnish Left Alliance]]
*[[Suomen Kommunistinen Puolue|Finnish Communist Party]]

===France===

*[[French Communist Party]]
*[[French Socialist Party]]
*[[Les Verts]] (French [[Green Party]])
*[[Parti Radical de Gauche]] (Left Radical party)

===Germany===
*[[German Green Party| B90/The Green]]
*[[Party of Democratic Socialism| PDS]]
*[[Social Democratic Party of Germany| SPD]]
*[[German Communist Party]]

===Greece===
*[[Panhellenic Socialist Movement| PASOK - Panhellenic Socialist Movement]] (Socialist)
*[[Communist Party of Greece| KKE - Communist Party of Greece]] (Communist)
*[[Synaspismos| SYN - Coalition of the left and progress]] (Radical Left)
*[[Democratic Social Movement| DI.K.KI - Democratic Social Movement]] (Democratic Socialist)

===Ireland===
''This section is about the [[Republic of Ireland]], for left-wing parties in [[Northern Ireland]] see the United Kingdom section below.''
* Parties represented in the [[Dáil Éireann]]:
** [[Irish Green Party]] (An Comhaontas Glas)
** [[Irish Labour Party]]
** [[Sinn Féin]]
** [[Socialist Party of Ireland]]
There are also a number of Independent TD's in Ireland's parliament who would describe themselves as socialist or "left-wing"

* Parties not represented in the [[Dáil Éireann]]:
** [[Socialist Workers Party]]
** [[The Workers Party (Ireland)]]

===Israel===
* Political parties
** [[Yachad]] (Dovish Social-Democrat Party)
** [[Hadash]] (Israeli-Arab Communist Party)
** [[Israeli Labor Party]] ''HaAvoda'' (Zionist center-left party)
* Non-parliamentary
** [[Peace movement]]s
*** [[Gush Shalom]] (extreme radical)
*** [[Peace Now]]
*** [[Taayush]]
** [[Marxism|Marxist movements]]
*** HaNoar HaOved VeHalomed ([[Zionist]] [[socialist]] youth movement)
*** [[Hashomer Hatzair|HaShomer HaTzair]] (Zionist socialist youth movement)
*** Maavak Socialisti ("Socialist Struggle")
*** Banki (Communist youth movement)

===Japan===
*[[Democratic Party of Japan]]
*[[Japanese Communist Party]]
*[[Social Democratic Party (Japan)]]

===Latvia===
* [[Par Cilveka Tiesibam Vienota Latvija|Par Cilv&amp;#275;ka Ties&amp;#299;b&amp;#257;m Vienot&amp;#257; Latvij&amp;#257;]]
* [[Tautas Saskanas Partija|Tautas Saska&amp;#326;as Partija]]
* [[Latvian Socialist Party|Latvijas Soci&amp;#257;listisk&amp;#257; Partija]]

===Latin America===
* [[Party of the Democratic Revolution]]
* [[Socialist Party of Chile]]
* [[Liberal Party of Colombia]]
* [[Democratic Revolutionary Party]]
* [[Puerto Rican Independence Party]]
* [[Institutional Revolutionary Party]]
* [[Radical Civic Union]]
* [[Cuban Liberal Union]]
* [[Communist Party of Cuba]]
* [[American Popular Revolutionary Alliance]]

===Netherlands===
*[[GroenLinks]] (Pro-European, multiculturalist Greens)
*[[Socialistische Partij]] (radical left}
*[[Partij van de Arbeid]] (social-democrats)

===New Zealand===
* [[Alliance (New Zealand political party)|Alliance]]
* [[Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand]]
* [[New Zealand Progressive Party|Progessive Party]]
* [[New Zealand Democratic Party]]

===Norway===
*[[Arbeidernes Kommunistparti|AKP]]
*[[Norsk kommunistisk Parti|NKP]]
*[[Rød Valgallianse|RV]]
*[[Sosialistisk Venstreparti| SV]]
*[[Det Norske Arbeiderparti| AP]]

===Portugal===
* [[Bloco de Esquerda]]
* [[Portuguese Communist Party|Partido Comunista Português]]
* [[Partido Socialista]] (center-left)

===Taiwan===
* [[Democratic Progressive Party]]
* [[Taiwan Solidarity Union]]

===United Kingdom===
* Parties represented in the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]]:
** [[The Labour Party (UK)|British Labour Party]] (although many would dispute that the modern Labour party belongs to this category)
** [[Liberal Democrats (UK)|Liberal Democrats]] (describe themselves as a centre-left party; since advent of [[New Labour]], usually seen as to the left of the Labour party in the [[Houses of Parliament]] and the [[Scottish Parliament]], and to the right of it in [[local government in the United Kingdom|local]] and regional government)
** [[Plaid Cymru]]
** [[Scottish National Party]]
** [[Sinn Féin]] (practices abstentionism)
** [[Social Democratic and Labour Party]]
* Parties represented in the [[Scottish Parliament]]:
** [[Scottish Green Party]]
** [[Scottish Labour Party]]
** [[Liberal Democrats (UK)|Scottish Liberal Democrats]]
** [[Scottish National Party]]
** [[Scottish Socialist Party]]
* Parties represented in the [[National Assembly for Wales]]:
** [[Forward Wales]] (Cymru Ymlaen)
** [[The Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]]
** [[Liberal Democrats (UK)|Liberal Democrats]]
** [[Plaid Cymru]]
* Parties represented in the [[Northern Ireland Assembly]]:
** [[Alliance Party of Northern Ireland]] (associated with the [[Liberal Democrats (UK)|Liberal Democrats]])
** [[Progressive Unionist Party]]
** [[Sinn Féin]]
** [[Social Democratic and Labour Party]] (associated with the [[Labour Party (UK)|British Labour Party]])
* Parties represented in the [[European Parliament]]
** [[The Labour Party (UK)|British Labour Party]]
* Parties not represented in any of the above legislatures:
** [[Alliance for Workers Liberty]]
** [[Clannasaor]]
** [[Communist Party of Britain]]
** [[Communist Party of Britain (Marxist-Leninist)]]
** [[Communist Party of Great Britain (PCC)]]
** [[Communist Party of Scotland]]
** [[Cornish Nationalist Party]]
** [[Cymru Annibynnol]]
** [[Cymru Goch]]
** [[Free Scotland Party]]
** [[Independent Working Class Association]]
** [[International Socialist Group]]
** [[Mebyon Kernow]]
** [[New Communist Party of Britain]]
** [[Northern Ireland Women's Coalition]]
** [[RESPECT Unity Coalition]]
** [[Revolutionary Communist Group]]
** [[Socialist Alliance]]
** [[Socialist Appeal]]
** [[Socialist Labour Party (UK)|Socialist Labour Party]]
** [[Socialist Party of England and Wales]]
** [[Socialist Party of Great Britain]]
** [[Socialist Workers Party (UK)|Socialist Workers Party]]
** [[International Communist League (Fourth Internationalist)|Spartacist League]]
** [[Welsh Socialist Alliance]]
** [[Wessex Regionalist Party]]
** [[The Workers Party (Ireland)|Workers Party of Ireland]]
** [[Workers Power]]

===United States===
* Parties represented in the [[United States Congress]]
** [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic Party ]] (center-left)
* Parties with local or state electoral success since 1950
** [[Green Party of the United States|Green Party]]
* Other contemporary left parties
** [[Communist Party USA|Communist Party]]
** [[Freedom Socialist Party]]
** [[New Party (USA)|New Party]]
** [[United States Peace and Freedom Party|Peace and Freedom Party]]
** [[Socialist Labor Party of America]]
** [[Socialist Workers Party (USA)|Socialist Workers Party]]
** [[Working Families Party]]
** [[Democratic Socialists of America]] (working within the Democratic Party)
** [[Social Democrats USA]]
** [[Socialist Party USA]]
** [[Workers World Party]]
** [[Liberal Party (New York State)|Liberal Party]] (center-left, only in New York State)
**[[Freedom Socialist Party]]
**[[Socialist Equality Party]]
**[[Socialist Action]]
**[[Solidarity (United States)|Solidarity]]
**[[Freedom Road Socialist Organization]]
* Defunct parties
** [[Social Democratic Party (USA)|Social Democratic Party]] (1897-1901)
** [[Minnesota Farmer-Labor Party]] (1918-1944)
** [[Socialist Party of America]] (1901-1973)

==See also==
*[[Anarchism]]
*[[Christian socialism]]
*[[Communism]]
*[[Democracy]]
*[[Democracy (varieties)]]
*[[Democratic socialism]]
*[[Egalitarianism]]
*[[Environmentalism]]
*[[Labor movement]]
*[[Left-Right politics]] discusses the range of various writers' meanings when they use the terms "left" and "right" in a political context. 
*[[Liberalism]]
*[[Libertarian socialism]]
*[[Marxism]]
*[[Political spectrum]] discusses various writers' views of the usefulness (or not) of the Left/Right dichotomy and of alternative spectra.
*[[Progressivism]]
*[[Radical centrist politics]]
*[[Right-wing politics]]
*[[Social democracy]]
*[[Socialism]]
*[[Syndicalism]]
*[[Trade unionism]]

==External links==
*[http://www.politicalcompass.org/ The Political Compass] an alternate view of the political spectrum
*[http://www.socialistinternational.org/ The official website of the Socialist International]
*[http://montages.blogspot.com/ Critical Montages]
*[http://www.civicactions.org/cgi-bin/wiki.pl?2004_Progressive_House_And_Senate_Races US Progressive Candidates of 2004] progressive candidates running for House and Senate races in 2004
*[http://s88303980.onlinehome.us/thecomintern/ TheComIntern] A Leftist Webzine
*[http://www.geocities.com/greenpartyvoter/ It's Time for a Change: A network of progressives]
*[http://www.moveon.org/ MoveOn.org] An influential U.S.-based center-left website
*[http://www.wsws.org/ The "World Socialist Website"]
*[http://www.marxists.org/ The Marxists Internet Archive] (a free online Marxist library)
----
==Other meanings==
'''Left wing''' can also refer to a player's position in [[sport]]s such as [[soccer]] and [[ice hockey]].
[[de:Linke Politik]]
[[fr:Gauche]]
[[nl:Links (politiek)]]
[[pl:Lewica]]
[[Category:Politics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>