<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114002532|171325252" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18499" pageid="18499" ns="0" title="Left-wing politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T11:06:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=October 2007}}
{{redirect|Left wing|the term used in sports|winger (sport)}}
{{redirect|Leftism|the album of the band [[Leftfield]]|Leftism (album)}}
{{political parties}}
In [[politics]], the concept of left-wing, refers to a segment of the political spectrum that considers a high priority the  achieving of social equality through collective rights (social), as opposed to purely individual interests (private) and a traditional view of society, represented on the right policy. In general, the left-wing tends to uphold a secular society, egalitarian and multicultural. Depending on the balance of all these factors, the political left is divided into many branches ideologically.The term has been associated, in varying degrees, with Classical [[Liberalism]], Social (as opposed to Classical) [[Social liberalism|Liberalism]], [[Modern liberalism in the United States|Modern American Liberalism]], [[Social Democracy]], [[Socialism]], [[Communism]], [[Marxism]], [[Syndicalism]], [[Communalism]], [[Communitarianism]], [[Libertarian Socialism]], [[Anarchism]], [[Left-Libertarianism]], [[Populism]], [[Anti-colonialism]], [[Green Politics]], [[Progressivism]], and the [[Religious Left]].

The left is generally [[secular]].{{Fact|date=September 2007}}  However, in some [[Roman Catholic]] countries there is a tradition of [[Liberation theology]] which focuses upon "social justice", and in some [[Protestant]] countries there is a tradition of [[Christian Socialism]].  Religious movements sometimes embrace left-wing politics (the [[U.S. civil rights movement]] is one such example), but these unions often revolve around specific political issues rather than a fundamental convergence.

In the first half of the twentieth century, the [[Old Left]] argued that differences in [[social class]] determined the nature of a society.  Between the 1950s and 1960s, this perspective, rooted in [[economic determinism]], was broadened by the [[New Left]] to include the broad spectrum of [[culture|cultural]] politics: [[anti-racism]]; [[affirmative action]]; [[feminism]]; [[environmentalism]]; and, ultimately, support for the [[LGBT]] civil rights movement.   

[[Center-left]], [[left of center]], and [[left liberal]] refer to the left side of [[mainstream]] politics in [[liberal democracy|liberal democracies]]. These support liberal democracy, [[representative democracy]], some degree of [[private property]] rights and [[free markets]], high spending on [[social welfare]], extensive [[regulation]] of the economy, and some [[public ownership]]. Examples of center-left political parties include the British [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], the New Zealand [[New Zealand Labour Party|Labour Party]], the American [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] and the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany]]. 

Whereas [[Soft left]] refers to [[reformist]], [[democratic]] or [[parliamentary]] forms of socialism (for example, [[Irving Howe]] or the [[Tribune (magazine)|Tribune]] group), [[Hard left]] refers to socialists who advocate more radical change in society, such as the British politician [[Tony Benn]] or the [[Militant Tendency]]. Organizations described as the [[far left]], for instance groups affiliated to the [[Fourth International]] adopt more radical versions of left-wing politics and are rooted in the politics of the "old left." [[Ultra-left]] organizations are those deemed to be on the most extreme left of the political spectrum, for example [[Italy|Italian]] [[autonomism]].
 
==Origins and history of the term==
:''See the [[Left-Right politics]] article for more detailed discussion of the history and development of the term''

The term originates from the [[French Revolution]], when [[liberalism|liberal]] deputies from the [[Third Estate]] generally sat to the left of the president's chair, a habit which began in the [[French States-General|Estates General]] of 1789. The nobility, members of the [[Second Estate]], generally sat to the right. It is still the tradition in the French [[Assemblée Nationale]] for the representatives to be seated left-to-right (relative to the Assemblée president) according to their political alignment.

As this original reference became obsolete, the meaning of the term has changed, and is now used to denote a broad variety of political philosophies and principles. In contemporary Western political discourse, the term is most often used to describe forms of [[socialism]], [[social democracy]], or, in the sense in which the term is understood in the United States, [[American liberalism|liberalism]].

In the United States, no avowedly Socialist or Communist party ever became a major player in national politics, although the [[Social Democratic Party (USA)|Social Democratic Party]] of [[Eugene V. Debs]] and its successor [[Socialist Party of America]] (in the late 19th and early 20th centuries) and the [[Communist Party USA|Communist Party of the United States of America]] (in the 1930s) made some inroads. While many American "liberals" might be "social democrats" in European terms, few openly embrace the term "left"{{Fact|date=November 2007}}; in the United States, the term is mainly embraced by [[New Left]] activists, certain portions of the [[trade union|labor]] movement, and people who see their intellectual or political heritage as descending from 19th century socialist movements.

Some Greens deny that [[green politics]] is "on the left" as several green proponents of capitalism have proposed what they considered more efficient means to achieve their objectives; nonetheless, green economic policies are generally considered to be left-wing, and when they have formed political coalitions (most notably in [[Germany]], but also in local governments elsewhere), it has almost always been with groups that classify themselves as on the left. {{Fact|date=February 2007}}

==Left-wing issues==

The left has traditionally been concerned with the [[lower classes]] and with combating [[oppression]]. Thus the [[industrial revolution]] saw left-wing politics become associated with the [[working conditions|conditions]] and [[worker's rights]] in the new industries. This led to movements advocating [[social democracy]], [[socialism]] and [[trade union]]ism. More recently, the left has criticized what it perceives as the exploitative nature of current forms of [[globalization]], e.g. the rise of [[sweatshops]] and the "[[race to the bottom]]", and either has sought to promote more just forms of globalization, such as [[fair trade]], or has sought to allow [[nation-states]] to "delink" or break free of the global economy.

Although specific means of achieving these ends are not agreed upon by different left-wing groups, almost all those on the left agree that some form of government or social intervention in economics is necessary,{{Fact|date=September 2007}} ranging from [[Keynesian]] economics and the [[welfare state]] through [[industrial democracy]] or the [[social market]] to [[nationalization]] of the economy and central [[planned economy|planning]].

As [[civil rights|civil]] and [[human rights]] gained more attention during the twentieth century, the left has allied itself with advocates of [[racial]] and [[gender]] equality and cultural [[tolerance]]. 

Advocacy of government or social intervention in the market puts some of those on the left at odds with advocates of the [[free market]].

==War and revolution==
{{main|The Left and war}}
Historically, the left have been opponents of [[imperialism|imperialist]] and [[colonialism|colonial]] wars, and have championed anti-colonial rebellions. Opponents argue however that from [[Napoleon]] onwards the left have generally supported military conquests by regimes of whom they approve e.g. the [[Soviet Union]].   

While some segments of the left are inspired by a strict adherence to [[pacifism]], much left-wing opposition to war arises from [[anti-capitalist]] sentiment; in other words, leftists reject warfare when they believe that [[capitalist]]s will benefit. Left-wing opposition to war is also often characterised by the [[Internationalism (politics)|internationalist]] belief that [[Workers of the world, unite!|world's workers]] share common interests with one another, rather than with the powers governing their respective countries.  

=== First and Second World Wars ===
The [[First World War]] triggered fierce debate among socialist groups as to the right response to take, with the leaderships of most socialist parties of the [[Second International]] supporting their governments, and a minority of socialists, such as [[Rosa Luxemburg]] and [[Lenin]] opposing the war as imperialist. Left-wing opponents to the war came together at the [[Zimmerwald Conference]]. The Bolshevik's responded to a revolt by soldiers against the First World War with promises of "bread, land and peace." These promises proved to be misleading however, because once the Bolsheviks seized power there was famine due to enforced collectivisation. This of course took place under economic blockade, and at a time when the Soviets put all their resources into efforts to defend their country from invasion, a period known as "War Communism."

As a result of the [[Nazi-Soviet pact]] supporters of the [[Soviet Union]] were instructed by [[Stalin]] to describe those who advocated military attacks upon [[Nazi]] [[Germany]] as capitalist warmongers, but when [[Hitler]] surprised Stalin by invading Communist occupied [[Poland]] overnight the majority of those on the left who had been opposed the war became supporters of military action against Germany and [[Japan]].

=== Spanish Civil War ===
The [[Spanish Civil War]] was seen by many on the left as an important fight against [[fascism]]. In response to the outbreak of war, some joined [[International Brigades]] or other left-wing [[militia]]s organized by trade unions or political parties. Others campaigned for arms embargoes and advocated intervention by the League of Nations.

=== Vietnam and Iraq anti-war movements ===
The biggest anti-war movement that involved the western left was that against the military support which the [[USA]] gave to [[South Vietnam]] when it was faced with an insurgency by the [[Vietcong]], who were supported militarily by [[North Vietnam]]. The protests were directed primarily against the American military intervention and eventually received considerable mainstream support. However, many of the most vocal critics of the war in Vietnam, including the leaders of organisations such as the [[Students for a Democratic Society]](SDS), were part of or sympathized with the [[counter culture]] and criticized American society as overly materalistic and government policy as repressive and imperialistic. Critics argue that the widespread support for these protests amongst those of military age was motivated largely by a desire to avoid military service, and once President [[Nixon]] abolished the draft and began to withdraw American troops from S-E Asia there were no widespread protests by young people about the subsequent suppression of liberty in [[Vietnam]] and [[Cambodia]] that occurred as a consequence of rule by [[Marxist]] governments. 

The American-led war in [[2003 Invasion of Iraq|Iraq]] led to new anti-war movements. The governments of some [[social democratic]] political parties (such as [[Tony Blair|Tony Blair's]] [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]]) sent their countries' troops to participate in this war. A Left justification for this policy is supplied by, for example, [[Oliver Kamm]] ''Anti-Totalitarianism: The Left-wing Case for a Neo-Conservative Foreign Policy''. &lt;ref&gt; [[Oliver Kamm]] ''Anti -Totalitarianism: The Left-wing Case for a Neo-Conservative Foreign Policy''2005, London: Social Affairs Unit ISBN 1-904863-06-X &lt;/ref&gt;  However, most of the left has opposed the war in Iraq.  Some claim that the war in Iraq is [[imperialist]], that [[petroleum|oil]] and control of the [[Middle East]] and not the removal of regime of [[Saddam Hussain]] were the actual goals.  Others seek to draw attention to the fact that some of the justification for the war turned out to be untrue, specifically the claim that Iraq had [[weapons of mass destruction]].&lt;ref&gt; Sheldon Rampton and John Stauber, ''Weapons of Mass Deception: The Uses of Propaganda in Bush's War on Iraq'', Tarcher, 2003, ISBN 1585422762, ISBN-13 978-1585422760. &lt;/ref&gt;  &lt;ref&gt; Ali A. Allawi, ''The Occupation of Iraq: Winning the War, Losing the Peace'', Yale University Press, 2007, ISBN 0300110154, ISBN-13 978-0300110159. &lt;/ref&gt; 

Some criticism has been levelled at some left-wing groups for forming anti-war coalitions with [[Conservatism|conservative]] organisations (such as the [[paleoconservative]] Antiwar.com) or with groups led by [[fundamentalist]] [[Islamists]] (such as the [[Muslim Association of Britain]]). Some on the French left (especially within [[ATTAC]]) argue that antiwar protests distract from the economic arguments advocated by the [[anti-globalisation]] movement. In the U.S., much left-wing activism was channelled into [[Anybody but Bush]] campaigns, which effectively meant supporting the [[centrist]] [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]]. In the U.K, anti-war feeling may have been a factor in a drop in support for the pro-war [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] government, and the cause of gains for the [[Liberal Democrats (UK)|Liberal Democrats]].

==The left and political violence==
{{disputed}}

The political term ''left'' arose during the French Revolution, i.e. during a period of [[political violence]]. The political left has a variety of positions on the issue of violence. This has ranged from the [[pacificism]] of the [[Independent Labour Party]] or social democrats' faith in [[reformism|legal, peaceful means of social change]] to the advocacy of violence by the [[revolutionary]] left. 

Among the advocates of violent revolution were the [[Narodniks]] in [[Russia]] in the late 19th and early 20th centuries. They sought to overthrow the oppressive authoritarianism of the [[Imperial Russia|Tsarist state]] by systematic attacks on the Tsar and his ministers, a strategy known as [[propaganda of the deed]]. Their strategy was hotly debated within the Russian left; for example, [[Leon Trotsky]] wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
'In our eyes, individual terror is inadmissible precisely because it belittles the role of the masses in their own consciousness, reconciles them to their own powerlessness, and turns their eyes and hopes toward a great avenger and liberator who someday will come and accomplish his mission.'&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/archive/trotsky/works/1920/dictatorvs/index.htm ''Terrorism and Communism''] by [[Leon Trotsky]]
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Similarly, most [[libertarian socialists]] turned against the Narodniks' terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://flag.blackened.net/noterror/ Anarchists Against Terrorism] for some classic anarchist critiques of terrorism. Notable libertarian socialist and anarchist opponents of propaganda of the deed include [[Peter Kropotkin]], [[Rudolf Rocker]] and [[Fernand Pelloutier]].&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1970s, various left-wing groups sprang up from the [[social movements]] of the time, such as [[Weatherman (organization)|Weathermen]] and the [[Symbionese Liberation Army]] in the U.S., the [[Angry Brigade]] in [[United Kingdom|the UK]], the [[Baader-Meinhof]] group in [[Germany]], the [[Red Brigades]] in [[Italy]] and so on. These groups turned to acts of terrorism in order to either hasten what they deemed progress or in order to shock the populace into dissatisfaction with the status quo. They also considered [[armed struggle]] to be necessary from an [[anti-imperialist]] view point, targeting in some cases [[NATO]] bases or [[United States military bases]] in an attempt to oppose the [[Vietnam War]]. Except in cases where they drew upon existing conflicts, for example the [[Provisional IRA]], they lacked political support, they were eventually dismantled by the state, which enacted [[anti-terrorism legislation]] to provide it with the "extraordinary means." [http://www.socialistreview.org.uk/article.php?articlenumber=8844]

==The Left and global justice/anti-corporate globalization==
The [[Global Justice Movement]] movement, also known as the [[anti-globalisation]] or [[alter-globalization]] movement, are protesters against global trade agreements and the negative consequences they perceive them to have for the poor and the environment. This movement is generally characterised as left-wing, though some activists within it reject association with the traditional left.  There are also those on the right, [[Pat Buchanan]] for example, who oppose globalization on nationalistic grounds.  The Global Justice Movement does not oppose globalisation per se, on the contrary, it supports some forms of [[internationalism]]). The main themes of the movement are the reforms of international institutions such as the [[World Bank]] and the [[International Monetary Fund]], and the creation of an international social justice movement.  It rejects the leadership of any [[political party]], defining itself as a "movement of movements." Free market critics claim that anti-globalization simply re-packages economic policies which have failed to decrease poverty in developing countries.

==The left and feminism==
:{{main|The left and feminism}}
Early [[feminism]] in the nineteenth century was often, although not always, connected to radical politics. Today, [[socialist feminist]]s, [[Marxist feminism|Marxist feminist]]s and [[liberal feminist]]s position themselves as on the left of the political spectrum.  [[Radical feminist]]s however reject the entire left/right distinction.

==The left and the Third World==

Left wing politics drove many of the anti-colonial movements in Africa, Asia and South America. After the collapse of the Soviet Union most Third World governments however sought funding from the [[World Bank]]. A contemporary exception is Venezuela, which relies on the income generated by its oil reserves.

Some left wing groups in the developing world, such as the [[Zapatista Army of National Liberation]] in [[Mexico]], argue that the [[Western]] left takes a racist and paternalistic attitude towards developing countries. There is particular criticism of the role played by [[NGOs]].

The [[anti-globalization]] movement around the world is one of the main generators of support for left-wing social causes of all types. There has however been a decline in support for Stalinist or Maoist politics (Note: there were many anti-Stalinist left-wing movements in developing countries during the Cold War but they were marginalized by the power of the pro-Stalinist movements funded by the Soviet Union.

==The left and postmodernism==

Left-wing Post-modernist theories reject attempts at universal explanatory theories such as Marxism, deriding them as [[Metanarrative|grand narratives]]. They argue for an embrace of culture as the battle grounds for change, rejecting traditional ways of organising such as political parties and [[trade unions]], focusing instead on critiquing or [[deconstruction]]. Left-wing critics of Post-modernism view it as a reaction to the economic failure of State Socialism (both in Europe and Latin America and the USA) and disillusionment with authoritarian [[Communist]] regimes. They assert that [[cultural studies]] courses inflate the importance of culture through denying the existence of an independent reality.&lt;ref name="Postmoden"&gt;p&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.isj.org.uk/index.php4?id=59issue=105 Postmodernism, commodity fetishism and hegemony], Néstor Kohan, [[International Socialism (journal)|International Socialism]], Issue 105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://cscs.umich.edu/~crshalizi/chomsky-on-postmodernism.html Chomsky on Postmodernism], [[Noam Chomsky]], [[Z Communications|Z-Magazine's]] Left On-Line Bulletin Board.&lt;/ref&gt;

The most famous critique of post-modernism from within the left came in the form of a 1996 prank by [[physicist]] and self-described leftist [[Alan Sokal]]. Concerned about what he saw as the increasing prevalence on the left of "a particular kind of nonsense and sloppy thinking… that denies the existence of objective realities, or…downplays their practical relevance…",&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/lingua_franca_v4/lingua_franca_v4.html A Physicist Experiments With Cultural Studies], [[Alan Sokal]]&lt;/ref&gt; Sokal composed [[Sokal Affair|a nonsensical article]] entitled "Transgressing the Boundaries: Toward a Transformative Hermeneutics of Quantum Gravity"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.physics.nyu.edu/~as2/transgress_v2/transgress_v2_singlefile.html Transgressing the Boundaries: Towards a Transformative Hermeneutics of Quantum Gravity],  [[Alan Sokal]], first published in; [[Social Text]], issule 46/47, [[1996]]&lt;/ref&gt;
, in which a mix of mis-stated and mis-used terms from [[physics]], [[postmodernism]], [[Literary criticism|literary analysis]], and [[Political philosophy|political theory]] are used to claim that physical [[reality]], and especially [[gravity|gravitation]], do not objectively exist, but are psychologically and politically constructed.

The journal ''Social Text'' published the paper in its Spring/Summer 1996 issue, whereupon Sokal publicly revealed his hoax. While some saw Sokal as attacking leftism in general, he was very clear that this was intended as a critique from within:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Politically, I'm angered because most (though not all) of this silliness is emanating from the self-proclaimed Left. We're witnessing here a profound historical ''volte-face''. For most of the past two centuries, the Left has been identified with science and against obscurantism… epistemic relativism betrays this worthy heritage and undermines the already fragile prospects for progressive social critique. Theorizing about “the social construction of reality” won't help us find an effective treatment for AIDS or devise strategies for preventing global warming. Nor can we combat false ideas in history, sociology, economics and politics if we reject the notions of truth and falsity.… The results of my little experiment demonstrate, at the very least, that some fashionable sectors of the American academic Left have been getting intellectually lazy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/lingua_franca_v4/lingua_franca_v4.html A Physicist Experiments With Cultural Studies], [[Alan Sokal]]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Right-wing critics view post-modernism as nihilistic. Gary Jason claims that "''The failure of socialism, both empirically and theoretically, ... brought about a crisis of faith among socialists, and Post-modernism is their response.''"&lt;ref&gt;[http://libertyunbound.com/archive/2005_06/jason-pomo.html Socialism's Last Bastion], Gary Jason, Liberty&lt;/ref&gt;

Some opponents, such as writer [[David Horowitz (conservative writer)|David Horowitz]], claim that post-modernists seek to deride the concept of truth, while at the same time engaging in politically motivated witch hunts of anybody deemed to deviate from [[politically correct]] views.

==The Left and Darwinism==
The [[left-wing politics|Left]]'s relationship with [[Darwinism]] has generally been congenial ([[Stalin]] typically excepting himself by supporting [[Trofim Lysenko]]'s [[Lamarckian]] views).  Around the turn of the 20th century, Socialists of the [[Progressive era]] explicitly opposed the [[Herbert Spencer|Spencer]]ian concept of the "[[survival of the fittest]]", and its extension to [[Social Darwinism]] (a cause which Darwin himself opposed).

In [[1875]] [[Friedrich Engels]] wrote a letter to Pyotr Lavrov saying

&lt;blockquote&gt;
"I accept the theory of evolution, but Darwin’s method of proof (struggle for life, natural selection) I consider only a first, provisional, imperfect expression of a newly discovered fact. ... The interaction of bodies in nature — inanimate as well as animate — includes both harmony and collision, struggle and cooperation. When therefore a self-styled natural scientist takes the liberty of reducing the whole of historical development with all its wealth and variety to the one-sided and meager phrase "struggle for existence", a phrase which even in the sphere of nature can be accepted only cum grano salis, such a procedure really contains its own condemnation."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1875/letters/75_11_17-ab.htm Engels to Pyotr Lavrov In London], Marx-Engels Correspondence 1875, Marx/Engels Internet Archive (2000)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In [[1902]] the [[anarchist]] philosopher and scientist [[Peter Kropotkin]] published the book ''[[Mutual Aid: A Factor of Evolution]]'', which discussed additional means for the natural selection and evolution of species, beyond "Survival of the Fittest". Written partly as a response to Social Darwinism and in particular to [[Thomas H. Huxley]]'s essay, "The Struggle for Existence", published in the magazine ''Nineteenth Century'', Kropotkin drew on his experiences in scientific expeditions during his time in [[Siberia]] to illustrate the phenomenon of cooperation in animal and human communities. After examining the evidence of cooperation among the animals, the "savages", the "barbarians", in the medieval city, and in modern times, he concluded that cooperation and mutual aid are as important in the evolution of the species as competition and mutual strife, if not more important.

==See also ==
===Left-wing ideologies===
*[[Communism]]
*[[Socialism]]
*[[Anarchism]]
*[[Marxism]]
*[[Marxist feminism]]
*[[Eco-socialism]]
*[[Green politics]]
*[[Democratic socialism]]
*[[Left communism]]
*[[Libertarian socialism]]
*[[Progressivism]]
*[[Social democracy]]
*[[Social Liberalism]]
*[[Syndicalism]]
*[[Religious Left]]

===Left-wing issues===
*[[Egalitarianism]]
*[[Environmentalism]]
*[[Labour movement]]
*[[Democracy]]
*[[Trade unionism]]
*[[Secularism]]
*[[New Left]]
*[[Liberal elite]]

===Related political topics===
*[[New social movements]]
*[[Political spectrum]] -- discusses various writers' views of the usefulness (or not) of the Left/Right dichotomy and of alternative spectra.
*[[Left-right politics]] -- discusses the range of various writers' meanings when they use the terms "left" and "right" in a political context. 
*[[Right-wing politics]]
*[[Post-left anarchy]] -- discusses anarchist critiques critical of leftism, which attempts to escape the confines of traditional leftist ideology.
*[[Social criticism]]

==Notes==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references/&gt;
&lt;!--See [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]] for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref(erences/)&gt; tags--&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==Bibliography==
*''Encyclopedia of the American Left'', ed. by Mari Jo Buhle, Paul Buhle, Dan Georgakas, Second Edition, Oxford University Press 1998, ISBN 0-19-512088-4
* Lin Chun, ''The British New Left'', Edinburgh : Edinburgh Univ. Press, 1993
* Geoff Eley, ''Forging Democracy: The History of the Left in Europe, 1850-2000'', Oxford University Press 2002, ISBN 0-19-504479-7
* [http://www.socialistreview.org.uk/article.php?articlenumber=8844 ''Marxism on Terrorism''] by [[John Molyneux (Trotskyist)|John Molyneux]]
* [http://www.marxists.org/archive/kautsky/1919/terrcomm/index.htm ''Terrorism and Communism''] by [[Karl Kautsky]]
* [http://www.palgrave.com/products/title.aspx?PID=278315] Leftism in India

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|leftism}}
'''Reference sites'''
*[http://www.marxists.org/ The Marxists Internet Archive] (a free online Marxist library)
*[http://www.politicalcompass.org/ The Political Compass] an alternate view of the political spectrum
*[http://www.broadleft.org/ Leftist Parties of the World] List of present-day leftist parties and organizations of the world, with links to their websites.
*[http://www.revleft.com Revolutionary Left - A forum dedicated to the Far-Left wing]

{{FA link|ar}}

[[Category:Left-wing politics| ]]
[[Category:Political terms]]
[[Category:Political spectrum]]

{{Link FA|ar}}
[[ar:يسارية]]
[[ca:Esquerra]]
[[cs:Levice (politika)]]
[[da:Venstreorienteret]]
[[de:Politische Linke]]
[[et:Vasakpoolsus]]
[[el:Αριστερά (πολιτική)]]
[[es:Izquierda política]]
[[eo:Politika maldekstro]]
[[fr:Gauche (politique)]]
[[gl:Esquerda política]]
[[ko:좌익]]
[[is:Vinstristefna]]
[[it:Sinistra (politica)]]
[[he:שמאל וימין בפוליטיקה]]
[[lt:Kairė (politikoje)]]
[[hu:Baloldal]]
[[mk:Левица]]
[[nl:Links (politiek)]]
[[ja:左翼]]
[[nn:Venstresida]]
[[pl:Lewica]]
[[pt:Esquerda política]]
[[ru:Левые (политика)]]
[[sr:Левица]]
[[fi:Vasemmisto]]
[[sv:Politisk vänster]]
[[tr:Solculuk]]
[[ur:بایاں بازو]]
[[zh:左派、右派]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>