<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081114112609|251748520" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18499" pageid="18499" ns="0" title="Left-wing politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T23:53:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Left-wing|the term used in sports|winger (sport)}}
{{redirect|Leftism|the album of the band [[Leftfield]]|Leftism (album)}}
{{Party politics}}
In [[politics]], '''''left-wing''''', '''''the political left''''' and '''''the Left''''' has had different meanings in different countries and time periods.The term was originally used in France during the [[French Revolution]] to indicate opposition to absolute [[monarchy]]. Since the publication of ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]'' and the rise of [[Marxism]], it has been associated with [[socialism]], [[communism]] and a wide range of related ideologies, including [[social liberalism]].  In the [[United States]], ''left-wing'' is often used as a synonym for the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]], which is more [[Social liberalism|socially liberal]] than the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]]&lt;ref&gt;For example, this quote from the on-line magazine [[Slate]]: ''Support for Obama among women—who began to move left in 1980—also reflects a shift toward liberalism.'' http://www.slate.com/id/2204109/&lt;/ref&gt;. 

==Origins and history of the term==
{{seealso|Left-Right politics}}
In relation to politics, the term ''left wing'' originates from the [[French Revolution]], when radical [[The Mountain|Montagnard]] deputies from the [[Third Estate]] generally sat to the left of the president's chair, a habit which began in the [[French States-General|Estates General]] of 1789. The moderate [[Feuillant (political group)|Feuillant]]s generally sat to the right. It is still the tradition in the French [[Assemblée Nationale]] for the representatives to be seated left-to-right (relative to the Assemblée president) according to their political alignment. In some European countries [[classical liberals]] were labeled as 'left' before [[Marxist]] ideas came to define the left. In the case of [[Denmark]] and [[Norway]] the historical liberal parties still carry the name ''[[Venstre]]'' (literally meaning 'Left') even though they are now considered to be right-wing. A similar phenomenon exists in France, where it is known as [[sinistrisme]].

From mid-19th century, 'left' would increasingly refer to various forms of [[socialism]] and [[communism]]. Particularly influential event was the publication of the [[Communist Manifesto]] by [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]] in 1848. It asserted that a [[proletarian]] revolution would overthrow [[bourgeoisie|bourgeois]] society, and by abolishing private property create a [[classless]] and [[Stateless communism|stateless]] society.

Socialist movements emerged across Europe and some countries outside of Europe. The [[Second International|International Workingmen's Association]] (commonly named the 'Second International') gathered labour parties with a combined membership of millions. During the [[First World War]], the Second International was divided on the question of supporting or opposing the war. The dissident tendency, which included the [[Russia]]n [[Bolshevik]]s of [[Lenin]], [[Rosa Luxemburg]] in [[Germany]] amongst others, considered themselves as further to the left that the other labour parties (see [[Zimmerwald Left]]). Out of this conflict the socialist movement divided into [[Social Democracy|Social Democrats]] and Communists, the former category either seen as left or center-left. In the 1960s with the political upheavals of the [[Sino-Soviet split]] and the May 1968 revolt in [[France]], thinkers of the '[[New Left]]' viewed themselves as being more critical of Marxist and [[Marxist-Leninist]] discourse (labelled the '[[Old Left]]').

==Definitions==
In terms of politics, the terms ''left'', ''right'' and ''centre'' are contextual terms, relative to the political situation of individual countries and regions. In contemporary [[Western world|Western]] political discourse, ''the Left'' is most often used to describe forms of [[socialism]], [[communism]] and [[social liberalism]]. [[Marxism|Marxist]] thinker [[Leszek Kolakowski]] has defined the concept of the left in abstract terms as being [[utopia]]n and [[Ideology|ideological]].&lt;ref&gt;The concept of the left, Marxism and Beyond.  L Kolakowski - On Historical Understanding and Individual Responsibility, 1971.&lt;/ref&gt;. ''[[Center left]]'' is a term used to describe a political position that is close to the center of the political mainstream in a particular country. In several European countries, it is a term used for alliances that encompass both leftist and centrist elements.

In France, differentiation is generally made between the ''left'' ([[Socialist Party (France)|Socialists]] and [[French Communist Party|Communists]]) on one side and the ''[[far left]]'' (Trotskyists, Maoists, Anarchists) on the other.&lt;ref&gt;Cosseron, Serge (ed.). ''Le dictionnaire de l'extrême gauche''. [[Paris]]: [[Larousse]], 2007. p. 20&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Chinese New Left]] denotes a tendency which opposes [[Economic reform in the People's Republic of China|economic reforms]] and in favours of the restoration of socialist policies along [[Maoist]] lines.&lt;ref&gt;{{web cite|url=http://news.ft.com/cms/s/74029202-a389-11da-83cc-0000779e2340,s01=1.html|title=China launches ‘New Deal’ for farmers|publisher=[[Financial Times]]|date=2006-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the western context, ''[[New Left]]'' refers to [[culture|cultural]] politics, sometimes referred to as [[identity politics]].

''[[Ultra-left]]'' refer to a various far left ideologies. The term ''[[hard left]]'' has been associated with politics of [[Tony Benn]] and the [[Campaign Group]] and [[Labour Briefing]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/politics/1054337.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;, as well as [[Trotskyism|Trotskyist]] groups such as the [[Militant Tendency]] and [[Socialist Organiser]]. The hard left is more strongly influenced by Marxism, while the [[soft left]] had a more [[gradualist]] approach to building [[socialism]].

==Positions==
===Economics and class===
Many on the left believe in [[Marxian economics]], which refers to a body of [[economics|economic]] thought stemming from the work of [[Karl Marx]]. Adherents of Marxian economics sometimes distinguish it from his political philosophy, arguing that Marx's approach to understanding the economy is intellectually valuable per se, independent of his advocacy of revolutionary [[socialism]] or the inevitability of [[proletariat|proletarian]] revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = The Neo-Marxian Schools
  | publisher = The New School
  | url = http://cepa.newschool.edu/het/schools/neomarx.htm
  | accessdate = 2007-08-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Munro
  | first = John
  | title = Some Basic Principles of Marxian Economics
  | publisher = University of Toronto
  | url = http://www.chass.utoronto.ca/~munro5/MARXECON.htm
  | accessdate = 2007-08-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It does not lean entirely upon the work of Marx and other widely known Marxists ([[Lenin]], [[Trotsky]], etc.), but may draw from a range of Marxist and non-Marxist sources.

The Left has traditionally identified itself with the [[lower classes]] and with combating oppression. Thus the [[industrial revolution]] saw left-wing politics become associated with the [[working conditions|conditions]] and [[worker's rights]] in the new industries. This led to build-up of [[trade union]] movements. More recently, the left has criticized what it perceives as the exploitative nature by current forms of [[globalization]], e.g. the rise of [[sweatshops]] and the "[[race to the bottom]]", and either has sought to promote more just forms of globalization, such as [[fair trade]], or has sought to allow [[nation-states]] to "delink" or break free of the global economy.

Although specific means of achieving these ends are not agreed upon by different left-wing groups, almost all those on the left agree that some form of government or social intervention in economics is necessary, ranging from [[Keynesian]] economics and the [[welfare state]] through [[industrial democracy]] or the [[social market]] to [[nationalization]] of the economy and central [[planned economy|planning]].&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Glyn, ''Social Democracy in Neoliberal Times: The Left and Economic Policy since 1980'', Oxford University Press, 2001, ISBN 978-0199241385.&lt;/ref&gt;

===National question===
The question of [[nationality]] and [[nationalism]] have been central features of political debates on the left. The [[Marxism|Marxist]] [[social class]] theory of [[proletarian internationalism]] asserts that members of the [[working class]] should act in solidarity with working people in other countries due to common [[class interest]], rather than only focusing on their own countries. Proletarian internationalism is summed up in the slogan, "[[Workers of all countries, unite!]]", the last line of ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]''. Union members learned that more members meant more bargaining power, and taken to an international level, leftists argued that workers ought to act in solidarity to further increase the power of the working class. Proletarian internationalism saw itself as a deterrent against war, because people with a common interest are less likely to take up arms against one another, instead focusing on fighting the [[ruling class]]. According to Marxist theory, the [[antonym]] of proletarian internationalism is [[bourgeois nationalism]]. Left-wing movements therefore have often taken up [[anti-imperialism|anti-imperialist]] positions.

On the other hand, there are strong elements of [[left-wing nationalism]], political tendencies which some link to the pressure generated by economic integration with other countries encouraged by [[free-trade]] agreements. This view is sometimes used to justify hostility towards [[Supranational union|supranational organizations]] such as the [[European Union]]. Left-wing nationalism can also refer to any nationalism emphasizing a working-class populist agenda attempting to overcome perceived exploitation or oppression by other nations. Many [[Third World]] anti-colonial movements adopted left-wing and socialist ideas.

===Anti-globalization===
The [[Global Justice Movement]] movement, also known as the [[anti-globalisation]] or [[alter-globalization]] movement, protests against global trade agreements and the negative consequences they perceive them to have for the poor and the environment. This movement is generally characterised as left-wing, though some activists within it reject association with the traditional left.  There are also those on the right, [[Pat Buchanan]] for example, who oppose globalization on nationalistic grounds.  The Global Justice Movement does not oppose globalisation per se, on the contrary, it supports some forms of [[internationalism]]). The main themes of the movement are the reforms of international institutions such as the [[World Bank]] and the [[International Monetary Fund]], and the creation of an international social justice movement. It rejects the leadership of any [[political party]], defining itself as a "movement of movements."

===Institutions===
{{see also|List of socialist countries|List of left-wing internationals}}
The [[Leninism|Leninist]] branch of Marxism argues that a proletarian revolution must be led by a [[Vanguard party|vanguard]] of [[professional revolutionaries]], men and women who are fully dedicated to the communist cause and who form the nucleus of the communist revolutionary movement. The [[dictatorship of the proletariat]] or [[workers' state]] are terms used by Marxists to describe what they see as a temporary state between the [[Capitalism|capitalist]] and [[Communism|communist]] society.

[[List of left-wing internationals|Left-wing internationals]] include dozens of historic and current organizations such as the [[International Workingmen's Association|First International]], the [[Second International]], or the [[Socialist International]], [[World Socialist Movement]], and the [[Revolutionary Internationalist Movement]], and the [[International Conference of Marxist-Leninist Parties and Organizations (Unity &amp; Struggle)]].

===Feminism===
{{main|The left and feminism}}
Early [[feminism]] in the nineteenth century was often, although not always, connected to radical politics. Today, [[socialist feminist]]s, [[Marxist feminism|Marxist feminist]]s and some [[liberal feminist]]s and [[radical feminist]]s position themselves as on the left of the political spectrum.

===Third-worldism===
[[Third-worldism]] is a tendency within left wing political thought to regard the division between developed, classically liberal nations and developing, or "[[third world]]" ones as of primary political importance.  Third-worldism tends to involve support for Third World nation states or [[national liberation movements]] against Western nations or their proxies in conflicts where the particular Third World state or movement.  The thought behind this view is often that contemporary [[capitalism]] can be characterised principally as [[imperialism]].  Hence, third-worldists say, resistance to capitalism must principally be resistance to the predations of advanced capitalist nations upon others.  

Key figures in the Third Worldist movement include [[Frantz Fanon]], [[Ahmed Ben Bella]], [[Andre Gunder Frank]], [[Samir Amin]] and [[Simon Malley]]. The [[New Left]] led to an explosion of support for Third Worldism, especially after the failure of revolutionary movements in the First World, such as [[Paris 1968]]. Among the New Left groups and movements associated with Third Worldism were [[Monthly Review]] and the [[New Communist Movement]]. 

Third worldism is also closely connected to movements such as [[Pan-Africanism]], [[Pan-Arabism]], [[Maoism]], [[African socialism]] and [[21st Century Socialism|Latin American socialist trends]]. National liberation movements such as the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]], [[Sandinistas]] and [[African National Congress]] have been ''causes célèbres'' of the movement. 

More recently, Third Worldism has become a powerful force in the [[World Social Forum]] (particularly since the Mumbai WSF in 2004){{Fact|date=October 2008}} and in the [[Cairo Anti-War Conference]]. 

Some left-wing groups in the developing world, such as the [[Zapatista Army of National Liberation]] in [[Mexico]], [[Abahlali baseMjondolo]] in [[South Africa]] and the [[Naxalites]] in [[India]], argue that the [[Western world|Western]] left usually takes a racist and paternalistic attitude towards popular movements in dominated countries. There is particular criticism of the role played by [[NGOs]] and the assumption by the [[Anti-globalization movement]] in Europe and North America that it is a global movement with an automatic right to lead movements in the South.

===Post-modernism===
Left-wing [[postmodernism]] reject attempts at universal explanatory theories such as Marxism, deriding them as [[Metanarrative|grand narratives]]. They argue for an embrace of culture as the battle grounds for change, rejecting traditional ways of organising such as political parties and [[trade unions]], focusing instead on critiquing or [[deconstruction]]. Left-wing critics of post-modernism view it as a reaction to the economic failure of state socialism (both in Europe, Latin America and the United States), and disillusionment with authoritarian [[Communist]] regimes. They assert that [[cultural studies]] courses inflate the importance of culture through denying the existence of an independent reality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.isj.org.uk/index.php4?id=59issue=105 Postmodernism, commodity fetishism and hegemony], Néstor Kohan, [[International Socialism (journal)|International Socialism]], Issue 105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://cscs.umich.edu/~crshalizi/chomsky-on-postmodernism.html Chomsky on Postmodernism], [[Noam Chomsky]], [[Z Communications|Z-Magazine's]] Left On-Line Bulletin Board.&lt;/ref&gt;

The most famous critique of post-modernism from within the left came in the form of a 1996 prank by [[physicist]] and self-described leftist [[Alan Sokal]]. Concerned about what he saw as the increasing prevalence on the left of "a particular kind of nonsense and sloppy thinking... that denies the existence of objective realities, or... downplays their practical relevance...", in which a mix of mis-stated and mis-used terms from physics, postmodernism, [[Literary criticism|literary analysis]], and [[Political philosophy|political theory]] are used to claim that physical [[reality]], and especially [[gravity|gravitation]], do not objectively exist, but are psychologically and politically constructed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/lingua_franca_v4/lingua_franca_v4.html A Physicist Experiments With Cultural Studies], [[Alan Sokal]]&lt;/ref&gt; Sokal composed [[Sokal Affair|a nonsensical article]] entitled "Transgressing the Boundaries: Toward a Transformative Hermeneutics of Quantum Gravity",&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.physics.nyu.edu/~as2/transgress_v2/transgress_v2_singlefile.html Transgressing the Boundaries: Towards a Transformative Hermeneutics of Quantum Gravity],  [[Alan Sokal]], first published in; [[Social Text]], issule 46/47, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; The journal ''Social Text'' published the paper in its Spring/Summer 1996 issue, whereupon Sokal publicly revealed his hoax. While some saw Sokal as attacking leftism in general, he was very clear that this was intended as a critique from within:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''Politically, I'm angered because most (though not all) of this silliness is emanating from the self-proclaimed Left. We're witnessing here a profound historical ''volte-face''. For most of the past two centuries, the Left has been identified with science and against obscurantism… epistemic relativism betrays this worthy heritage and undermines the already fragile prospects for progressive social critique. Theorizing about "the social construction of reality" won't help us find an effective treatment for AIDS or devise strategies for preventing global warming. Nor can we combat false ideas in history, sociology, economics and politics if we reject the notions of truth and falsity.… The results of my little experiment demonstrate, at the very least, that some fashionable sectors of the American academic Left have been getting intellectually lazy.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/lingua_franca_v4/lingua_franca_v4.html A Physicist Experiments With Cultural Studies], [[Alan Sokal]]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Gary Jason claims that "of socialism, both empirically and theoretically... brought about a crisis of faith among socialists, and Post-modernism is their response."&lt;ref&gt;[http://libertyunbound.com/archive/2005_06/jason-pomo.html Socialism's Last Bastion], Gary Jason, Liberty&lt;/ref&gt;

==Symbols==
[[Image:Flag of the Soviet Union.svg|thumb|300px|The flag of [[Soviet Union]] - the world's first [[socialist state]] - combined three left-wing symbols: [[red flag]]; [[red star]]; and [[hammer and sickle]].]]
The revolutionary or radical left usually uses the color [[red]] in its symbolism. The [[red flag]] became popular during the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Revolution]] of 1917.&lt;ref name="su flag"&gt;[http://www.crwflags.com/FOTW/flags/su.html|Flags of the World "Soviet"]&lt;/ref&gt; Red became the primary color of the flag of the [[Soviet Union]], and the [[red star]] became a Communist [[emblem]], leading to [[Cold War]] phrases such as ''Red Menace'' and ''[[People's Republic of China|Red China]]'' (distinguished from the right-wing [[Republic of China]], ''Free China'', or ''Taiwan''). China's de-facto anthem under [[Mao Zedong]] was ''[[The East is Red]]''.  [[Mao Zedong]] was sometimes referred to as a ''red sun''. The color was also associated with political groups such as the [[Red Guards (China)|Red Guard]] in China and the [[Red Guards (Russia)|Red Guard]]s during the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]], as well as with left-wing paramilitary terrorist groups such as the [[Red Army Faction]] in [[Germany]], and the [[Japanese Red Army]]. 

The [[hammer and sickle]] is a part of [[communist symbolism]]. The two tools are symbols of the industrial [[proletariat]] and the [[peasant]]ry.

==See also==
* [[Ideology]]
* [[Political spectrum]] 
* [[Post-left anarchy]] 
* [[Social criticism]]

==References and notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* ''Encyclopedia of the American Left'', ed. by Mari Jo Buhle, Paul Buhle, Dan Georgakas, Second Edition, Oxford University Press 1998, ISBN 0-19-512088-4
* Lin Chun, ''The British New Left'', Edinburgh : Edinburgh Univ. Press, 1993
* Geoff Eley, ''Forging Democracy: The History of the Left in Europe, 1850-2000'', Oxford University Press 2002, ISBN 0-19-504479-7
* [http://www.socialistreview.org.uk/article.php?articlenumber=8844 ''Marxism on Terrorism''] by [[John Molyneux (Trotskyist)|John Molyneux]]
* [http://www.marxists.org/archive/kautsky/1919/terrcomm/index.htm ''Terrorism and Communism''] by [[Karl Kautsky]]
* [http://www.palgrave.com/products/title.aspx?PID=278315 Leftism in India]

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|leftism}}
* [http://www.marxists.org/ The Marxists Internet Archive] (a free online Marxist library)
* [http://www.wsws.org/ World Socialist Web Site] News and analysis of current world developments in politics, economics and culture from a Marxist perspective.

{{FA link|ar}}

[[Category:Left-wing politics| ]]
[[Category:Political spectrum]]
[[Category:Political terms]]

{{Link FA|ar}}
[[ar:يسارية]]
[[ca:Esquerra]]
[[cs:Levice (politika)]]
[[da:Venstreorienteret]]
[[de:Politische Linke]]
[[et:Vasakpoolsus]]
[[el:Αριστερά (πολιτική)]]
[[es:Izquierda política]]
[[eo:Politika maldekstro]]
[[fr:Gauche (politique)]]
[[gl:Esquerda política]]
[[ko:좌익]]
[[id:Sayap kiri]]
[[is:Vinstristefna]]
[[it:Sinistra (politica)]]
[[lt:Kairė (politikoje)]]
[[hu:Baloldal]]
[[mk:Политичка левица]]
[[ms:Politik haluan kiri]]
[[nl:Links (politiek)]]
[[ja:左翼]]
[[no:Venstreorientert politikk]]
[[nn:Venstresida]]
[[pl:Lewica]]
[[pt:Esquerda política]]
[[ru:Левые (политика)]]
[[sk:Ľavica (politika)]]
[[sr:Левица]]
[[fi:Vasemmisto]]
[[sv:Politisk vänster]]
[[tr:Solculuk]]
[[uk:Лівиця]]
[[ur:بایاں بازو]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>