<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131112063555|581296266" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1271927" pageid="1271927" ns="0" title="Gender equality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-15T03:15:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{expert-subject|date=November 2012}}
{{refimprove|date=June 2013}}
{{copy edit|date=June 2013}}
{{lead too short|date=June 2013}}
}}

[[Image:Igualtat de sexes.svg|thumb|upright|One of generic symbols for gender equality]]

'''Gender equality''', also known as '''sex equality''', '''sexual equality''' or '''equality of the [[genders]],''' implies that men and women should receive equal treatment, unless there is a sound biological reason for different treatment.&lt;ref&gt;United Nations. Report of the Economic and Social Council for 1997. A/52/3.18 September 1997, at 28: "Mainstreaming a gender perspective is the process of assessing the implications for women and men of any planned action, including legislation, policies or programmes, in all areas and at all levels. It is a strategy for making women's as well as men's concerns and experiences an integral dimension of the design, implementation, monitoring and evaluation of policies and programmes in all political, economic and societal spheres so that women and men benefit equally and inequality is not perpetuated. The ultimate goal is to achieve gender equality."&lt;/ref&gt; This concept is key in the United Nations' [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], where the ultimate aim is to provide equality in law and equality in social situations, especially in democratic activities and securing [[equal pay for equal work]]. The [[Equal Rights Amendment]] in the United States also aims to ensure gender equality.

== History ==
{{cleanup-rewrite|section|date=June 2013}}

The [[Shakers]], a celibate evangelical group founded in America in 1774, practiced equality of the sexes soon after they began organizing into their own separatist enclaves. The head of the Shakers' central ministry in 1788, Joseph Meacham, had a revelation that the sexes should be equal, so he brought [[Lucy Wright]] into the ministry as his female counterpart, and together they restructured society to balance the rights of the sexes. Meacham and Wright established leadership teams where each elder, who dealt with the men's spiritual welfare, was partnered with an eldress, who did the same for women. Each deacon was partnered with a deaconess. Men had oversight of men; women had oversight of women. Women lived with women; men lived with men. In Shaker society, a woman did not have to be controlled or otherwise owned by any man. After Meacham's death in 1796, Wright was the head of the Shaker ministry until her own death in 1821. Going forward, Shakers maintained the same pattern of gender-balanced leadership for more than 200 years. They also promoted equality with women's rights advocates. In 1853, Shaker brother William Leonard wrote that Shakerism brought an end to the “degradation and oppression of WOMAN,” and suggested that the public discussion of woman’s rights, as well as other reforms, originated with Shakers and was due to their recognition of God as both male and female. In 1859, Shaker Elder Frederick Evans stated their beliefs forcefully, writing that Shakers were “the first to disenthrall woman from the condition of vassalage to which all other religious systems (more or less) consign her, and to secure to her those just and equal rights with man that, by her similarity to him in organization and faculties, both God and nature would seem to demand." Evans and his counterpart, Eldress Antoinette Doolittle, joined women's rights advocates on speakers' platforms throughout the northeastern U.S. in the 1870s. A visitor to the Shakers wrote in 1875, “Each sex works in its own appropriate sphere of action, there being a proper subordination, deference and respect of the female to the male in his order, '''and of the male to the female in her order''' [emphasis added], so that in any of these communities the zealous advocates of ‘women’s rights’ may here find a practical realization of their ideal.”&lt;ref&gt;Glendyne R. Wergland, ''Sisters in the Faith: Shaker Women and Equality of the Sexes'' (Amherst: University of Massachusetts Press, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; The Shakers were more than a radical religious sect on the fringes of American society; they put equality of the sexes into practice. They showed that equality could be achieved and how to do it.&lt;ref&gt;Wendy R. Benningfield, Appeal of the Sisterhood: The Shakers and the Woman’s Rights Movement (University of Kentucky Lexington doctoral dissertation, 2004), p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the wider society, the movement towards gender equality, especially in Western countries, began with the [[suffragette]] movement of the late-19th century, which sought to allow women to vote and hold elected office.

There have been substantial changes to [[women's property rights]], particularly in relation to their marital status. (See for example, [[Married Women's Property Act 1882]].)

In the 1960s, a more general movement for gender equality developed based on [[women's liberation]] and [[feminism]]. The central issue was that [[women's rights|the rights of women]] should be the same as [[men's rights|men]].  continued to focus on specific issues.

{{main|Convention against Discrimination in Education}}
Changes to attitudes to equality in education opportunities for boys and girls have also undergone a cultural shift.

{{main|Anti-discrimination laws}} 
Over time, there have been significant changes in attitudes which have resulted in more [[legislation]].

Some changes came about by adopting [[affirmative action]] policies. There was also a change in social views, including "[[equal pay for equal work]]" as well as most occupations  being equally available to men and women, in many countries. For example, many countries now permit women to serve in the [[armed forces]], the [[police|police forces]] and to be [[fire fighter]]s – occupations traditionally reserved for men. Although these continue to be male dominated occupations an increasing number of women are now  active, especially in directive fields such as politics and occupy high positions in business.

Similarly, men are increasingly working in occupations which in previous generations had been considered [[Women's work]], such as [[nursing]], [[Maid|cleaning]] and [[child care]]. In domestic situations, the [[Sex differences in humans|biological differences]] between men and women in relation to activities related to [[Pregnancy|child bearing]] are more commonly shared where possible, and the role of [[Parenting|child rearing]] is not as widely considered to be an exclusively female role, so that a wife may be free to pursue her [[career]] after marriage and following [[childbirth]].

Another manifestation of the change in social attitudes is the [[Married and maiden names#Feminism and preserving one's personal name|non-automatic taking by a woman of her husband's surname on marriage]] or combining names as in the [[Spanish naming customs]].

Many people consider that the objective of gender equality has not been fully achieved, especially in [[Non-western|non-Western]] countries. A highly contentious issue relating to gender equality is the role of women in [[religious law|religiously orientated societies]]. For example, [[Cairo_Declaration_on_Human_Rights_in_Islam#Contents|the Cairo Declaration on Human Rights in Islam]] declared that women have equal dignity, but not equal rights, and this was accepted by many predominantly Muslim countries.  In some [[Christianity|Christian churches]] the practice of [[churching of women]] may still have elements of [[Ritual purification]] and the [[Ordination of women]] to the priesthood may be restricted or forbidden. Some Christians or Muslims believe in [[Complementarianism]], a view that holds that men and women have different, but complementing roles. This view may be in opposition to the views and goals of gender equality.

In addition, there are also non-Western countries of low religiosity where the contention surrounding gender equality remains. In China, [[Sex-selective abortion and female infanticide#Cultural preference|cultural preference for a male child]] has resulted in a [[Missing women of Asia|shortfall of women]] in the population. [[Feminism in Japan]] has made many strides and resulted in in the [[Gender Equality Bureau]], but Japan remains low in gender equality compared to other industrialized nations.

Not all ideas for gender equality have been popularly adopted. For example: despite [[Topfreedom]] the right to be bare breasted in public frequently applies only to males and has remained a marginal issue. [[Breastfeeding in public]] is more commonly tolerated, especially in semi-private places such as restaurants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Jordan|first=Tim|title=Social Change (Sociology and society)|publisher=Blackwell|year=2002|isbn=0-631-23311-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, this picture of Western progress with regards to gender equality can be seen as severely oversimplified. Indeed, it is the contentious meaning of the term "equality" itself that makes measuring gender equality "progress" inherently problematic. Newman and White suggest that equality can be understood in three distinct ways: identical treatment, differential treatment, and fair treatment.&lt;ref name="Newman, Jacquetta A. 2012"&gt;Newman, Jacquetta A., and Linda A. White. Women, Politics, and Public Policy: The Political Struggles of Canadian Women. Don Mills, Ont.: Oxford UP, 2012. 14-15. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Identical treatment is the claim that equality means the deployment of generalizing, abstract, content-less reason, unaffected with regards to the gender it addresses.&lt;ref&gt;Ibid., 14.&lt;/ref&gt; This view assumes that gender differences are entirely socially constructed concepts, and that an underlying, gender-neutral human should be the target of equality. Next, the differential treatment notion of equality is the claim that biological ("sex") differences do, in fact, exist as tangible and real, and that structuring treatment around these differences is not unequal, so long as these biological differences are accurately defined (that is to say, so long as differential treatment is not random).&lt;ref&gt;Ibid., 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

The third view, that equality is fair treatment, is in a sense a reaction to both of the previous two claims. Equality as identical treatment assumes that the criteria we use to define human nature is itself objective, neutral, and fair for each human, and differential treatment assumes that there are inherent, empirical, tangible, biological differences that the binary categories of male-female derive from. Theorists like Judith Lorber, Michel Foucualt, Judith Butler, and many more attack both of these essentialist stances, articulating that any claim to an underlying human nature is absurd. In short, this is because what it is to be a human is at bottom a product of constructive discursive discourses. As Judith Lorber puts the point: "the paradox of 'human nature' is that it is always a manifestation of cultural meanings, social relationships, and power politics".&lt;ref&gt;Kimmel, Michael S., and Amy Aronson. The Gendered Society Reader. New York: Oxford UP, 2011. 18. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, theorists like Catharine MacKinnon claim that all circulating articulations of this fictitious "universal human" actually reflect socially male biases.&lt;ref&gt;Ibid., 17.&lt;/ref&gt; That is to say, unadulterated, objective, pure reason is merely a tacit disguise for patriarchal reinforcement. It is clear, then, how the identical treatment model fails on this view. Similarly, by this logic, the differential treatment is shown to merely use male rationality to define and construct the gender difference - as a result, true equality is precluded.

This tacit inequality in our sexual concept poses a particular problem, because Western Liberal Democracies are premised on descriptions of people that describe them as equal, yet this exists alongside a description of women and men that describes them in terms that makes them unequal. So the above claims of this article that "Non-Western" countries are less gender equal than Western countries must not be so quickly accepted. Since this acceptance of inequality in sexes is perceived as a natural difference between men and women, it thus permeates into society relatively undiagnosed. Disguised as objective, the subjective/biased nature of these claims for equal treatment become particularly difficult to address. This allows the state/laws to appear to be gender-neutral and universally applicable, while ignoring the backdrop of the underlying forces that have structured our legal system and personal cognition in such a way as to promote [[equal opportunity|equality of opportunity]] for social category male at the price of inequality for social category female. As Judith Lorber says: "it is the taken-for-grantedness of such everyday gendered behaviour that gives credence to the belief that the widespread differences in what women and men do must come from biology".&lt;ref&gt;Ibid., 16.&lt;/ref&gt; On such a view, then, addressing equality must take on more than formal equality, and become "fair treatment".&lt;ref name="Newman, Jacquetta A. 2012"/&gt; That is to say, the male paradigm cannot be seen as natural and objective, thus bias and preference and affirmative action to address past discriminations to women should be seen as furthering equality. Lorber describes the "bathroom problem" to articulate the inequality of overarching, gender-neutral laws.&lt;ref&gt;Ibid., 14.&lt;/ref&gt; She articulates how men's bathroom norms are used as the standard by which to determine how many and how large public bathrooms should be. For various reasons, however, women make more frequent use of the bathrooms than men, and as a result there are too few bathrooms for women, and sufficient amount for men. ). This tacit structural underpinning of male dominance is particularly dangerous for it creates the space for certain instances of female oppression to be viewed and experienced as the woman’s choice. For instance, a woman might choose not to pursue a job that isn’t compatible with her domestic obligations, while ignoring the structure of the patriarchal family in assigning those domestic roles to her, and furthermore the structuring of workplaces that tacitly stream out women that have this domestic duty in virtue of their strict required hours or inflexibility with days off, etc. As such, the fair treatment model of equality addresses the weaknesses of purely formal/de jure equality in addressing such tacit structural and systematic inequality for women.

==Efforts to fight inequality==
{{rewrite section|date=June 2013}}
{{see also|Gender inequality}}

World bodies have defined gender equality in terms of [[human rights]], especially [[women's rights]], and [[economic development]].&lt;ref name="Smart"&gt;{{cite journal |author=World Bank |title=Gender Equality as Smart Economics: A World Bank Group Gender Action Plan (Fiscal years 2007–10) |year=September, 2006 |url=http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTGENDER/Resources/GAPNov2.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MDG3"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.endpoverty2015.org/goals/gender-equity |title=Goal #3 Gender Equity |accessdate=2008-06-01 |publisher=United Nations Millennium Campaign |year=2008 |author=United Nations Millennium Campaign}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[UNICEF]] describes that gender equality  "means that women and men, and girls and boys, enjoy the same rights, resources, opportunities and protections. It does not require that girls and boys, or women and men, be the same, or that they be treated exactly alike."&lt;ref name="UNICEF"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unicef.org/gender/files/Overarching_2Pager_Web.pdf |title=Promoting Gender Equality: An Equity-based Approach to Programming |accessdate=2011-01-28 |publisher=UNICEF |date= |author=UNICEF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Nations Population Fund]] has declared that men and women have a right to [[Social equality|equality]].&lt;ref name="UNFPA"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unfpa.org/gender/ |title=Gender Equality: An End in Itself and a Cornerstone of Development |accessdate=2008-06-01 |publisher=United Nations Population Fund |year=February 2006 |author=UNFPA}}&lt;/ref&gt; "Gender equity" is one of the goals of the [[United Nations Millennium Project]], to end world [[poverty]] by 2015; the project claims, "Every single Goal is directly related to women's rights, and societies where women are not afforded equal rights as men can never achieve development in a [[Sustainability|sustainable]] manner."&lt;ref name="MDG3" /&gt;

Thus, promoting gender equality is seen as an encouragement to greater [[Prosperity|economic prosperity]].&lt;ref name="Smart" /&gt; For example, nations of the [[Arab world]] that deny equality of opportunity to women were warned in a 2008 [[United Nations]]-sponsored report that this disempowerment is a critical factor crippling these nations' return to the first rank of global leaders in commerce, [[Education|learning]] and [[culture]].&lt;ref name="ejoussour"&gt;[http://www.e-joussour.net/en/node/1511 Gender equality in Arab world critical for progress and prosperity, UN report warns], E-joussour (21 October 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, the [[European Union]] opened the [[European Institute for Gender Equality]] (EIGE) in [[Vilnius]], [[Lithuania]] to promote gender equality and to fight [[sex discrimination]].

It is also worthy to note that gender equality is part of the national curriculum in Great Britain and many other European countries.  [[Personal, Social and Health Education]], [[Religious education|religious studies]] and [[Language acquisition]] curricula tend to address gender equality issues as a very serious topic for discussion and analysis of its effect in society.

== See also ==
{{rewrite section|date=June 2013}}
{{portal|Gender studies}}

===General issues===
*[[Complementarianism]]
*[[Egalitarianism]]
*[[Feminism]]
*[[Gender inequality]]
*[[Gender mainstreaming]]
*[[Masculism]]
*[[Men's rights]]
*[[Right to equal protection]]
*[[Sex and gender distinction]]
*[[Sexism]]
*[[Women's rights]]

===Specific issues===
*[[Bahá'í Faith and gender equality]]
*[[Female economic activity]]
*[[Female education]]
*[[Gender Parity Index]] (in education)
*[[Gender sensitization]]
*[[Matriarchy]]
*[[Matriname]]
*[[Mixed-sex education]]
*[[Patriarchy]]
*Quaker [[Testimony of Equality]]
*[[Shared Earning/Shared Parenting Marriage]] (also known as [[Peer Marriage]])
*[[Women in Islam]]

===Laws===
*[[Anti-discrimination law]]
*[[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]] or CEDAW (United Nations, 1979)
*[[Danish Act of Succession referendum, 2009]]
*[[Equal Pay Act of 1963]] (United States)
*[[Equality Act 2006]] (UK)
*[[Equality Act 2010]] (UK)
*[[European charter for equality of women and men in local life]]
*[[Gender Equality Duty in Scotland]]
*[[Gender Equity Education Act (Taiwan)]]
*[[Lilly Ledbetter Fair Pay Act]] (United States, 2009)
*[[List of gender equality lawsuits]]
*[[Paycheck Fairness Act]] (in the US)
*[[Title IX]] of the [[Education Amendments of 1972]] (United States)
*[[Uniform civil code]] (India)
*[[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1325]]
*[[Women's Petition to the National Assembly]] (France, 1789)

===Organizations and ministries===
*[[Afghan Ministry of Women Affairs]] (Afghanistan)
*[[Centre for Development and Population Activities]]
*[[Christians for Biblical Equality]]
*[[Committee on Women's Rights and Gender Equality]] (European Parliament)
*[[Equal Opportunities Commission]] (UK)
*[[European Institute for Gender Equality]]
*[[Gender Empowerment Measure]], a metric used by the United Nations
*[[Gender-related Development Index]], a metric used by the United Nations
*[[Government Equalities Office]] (UK)
*[[International Center for Research on Women]]
*[http://www.societyforpeace.com/ International Society for Peace]
*[[Ministry of Integration and Gender Equality (Sweden)]]
*[[Ministry of Women, Family and Community Development (Malaysia)]]
*[[Philippine Commission on Women]] (Philippines)
*[[The Girl Effect]], an organization to help girls, worldwide, toward ending poverty

===Historical anecdotal reports===
* [[The_New_York_Times#Discrimination_in_employment|New York Times]]

===Other related topics===
*''[[Global Gender Gap Report]]''
*[[Shakers]]
*[[International Men's Day]]
*[[Potty parity]]
*[[Women's Equality Day]]
*[[Illustrators for Gender Equality]]
* [[Gender apartheid]]

== References ==
{{Ibid|date=June 2013}}
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{cleanup-rewrite|section|date=June 2013}}
* [http://www.unrol.org/article.aspx?article_id=28 United Nations Rule of Law: Gender Equality], on the relationship between gender equality, the [[rule of law]] and the [[United Nations]].
*[http://www.HillarysVillage.net HillarysVillage], Forum for women, minorities, members of the gay community and those who are otherwise marginalized.
*[http://uk.oneworld.net/guides/gender The OneWorld Guide to Gender Equality]
*[http://www.un.org/womenwatch WomenWatch], the United Nations Internet Gateway on Gender Equality and Empowerment of Women
*[http://www.undp.org/women/ Women's Empowerment], the United Nations Development Program's Gender Team
*[http://www.oecd.org/dac/gender GENDERNET], International forum of gender experts working in support of gender equality. Development Co-operation Directorate of the [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]]
*[http://www.oecd.org/dev/gender Gender at the OECD Development Centre], gender activities at the OECD Development Centre
*[http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/TOPICS/EXTGENDER/0,,menuPK:336874~pagePK:149018~piPK:149093~theSitePK:336868,00.html Gender Equality as Smart Economics] World Bank
*[http://www.vineetnayar.com/women-leadership-yes-she-can, Women Leadership: Yes she can!]
*[http://www.thelocal.se/guides/equality/Equality+in+Sweden/ The Local] Gender equality in Sweden (news collection)
*[http://www.womencandoit.no Women Can Do It!]
*[http://www.return2workmums.co.uk Return2WorkMums For women returners to the workplace]
*[http://www.ihatesexism.com/ Sexism Discussion Group]
*[http://ccr.sagepub.com/content/33/3/265.abstract Sexual Equality and Romantic Love]
*[http://www.mdgmonitor.org/map.cfm?goal=&amp;indicator=&amp;cd= Gender Equality Tracker]
*[http://www.genderwork.ca/ Gender and Work Database]
*[http://www.gendersite.org/ Gender and the Built Environment Database]
*[http://www.witec-eu.net/  WiTEC – The European Association for Women in Science, Engineering and Technology (SET)]
*[http://www.gell.it/  Gender Equality in Labour &amp; Life – Online Course focus on PA (SET)]
*[http://transequality.org  National Center for Transgender Equality]
*[http://www.annette-boeckler.de/liturgie/EgalitarianServices.html Egalitarian Jewish Services A Discussion Paper]

{{Library resources box 
|by=no 
|onlinebooks=no 
|others=no 
|about=yes 
|label=Gender equality}}

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Feminism}}
{{Masculism}}
{{Sexual identities}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gender Equality}}
[[Category:Gender equality| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>